<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21690994" ns="0" title="Florida Gators women&#039;s lacrosse"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college lacrosse team
|name             = Florida Gators women's lacrosse
|founded          = 2010
|image            = Florida Gators logo.svg
|image_size       = 175
|university       = [[University of Florida]]
|conference       = [[American Lacrosse Conference]]
|division         =
|location         = [[Gainesville, Florida]]
|coach            = [[Amanda O'Leary]]
|tenure           = since&amp;nbsp;2010
|stadium          = Donald R. Dizney Stadium
|capacity         = 1,500
|nickname         = [[Florida Gators]]
|colors           = Orange and Blue&lt;br&gt;{{colorbox|#FF4A00}} {{colorbox|#0021A5}}
|NCAA_champion    =
|NCAA_runner      =
|NCAA_semi        =
|NCAA_quarter     = 2011
|NCAA_tourney     = 2011
|conf_tourney     =
|conf_champion    = 2011
}}

The '''Florida Gators women's lacrosse''' team represents the [[University of Florida]] in the sport of college [[field lacrosse|lacrosse]].  The Gators compete in [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] of the [[National Collegiate Athletics Association]] (NCAA) and the [[American Lacrosse Conference]] (ALC).  They play their home games in Donald R. Dizney Stadium on the university's [[Gainesville, Florida]] campus, and are currently led by head coach [[Amanda O'Leary]].  In the two-season history of the Gators women's lacrosse program, the team has won one ALC championship and advanced to the quarterfinals of the 2011 NCAA national championship tournament.

== Background and overview ==

The [[University of Florida Athletic Association|University Athletic Association]] (UAA) quickly proceeded from new idea to reality in the creation of its newest sports program&amp;mdash;it decided to create a women's [[lacrosse]] program in 2005, publicly announced the new program in 2006, hired a head coach and joined a conference in 2007, and announced its first recruiting class and began construction of a dedicated lacrosse stadium in 2008.&lt;ref name=ufmediasupplement&gt;''[http://www.gatorzone.com/lacrosse/media/2011/supplement.pdf  Florida Lacrosse 2011 Media Supplement]'', University Athletic Association, Gainesville, Florida, pp. 8&amp;ndash;9, 43, 49 (2011).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  UAA officials selected women's lacrosse for its newest expansion sport because of the booming popularity of lacrosse at the high school level and the rapidly increasing competition available among Division I athletic programs.&lt;ref&gt;Adam West, &quot;[http://www.gainesville.com/article/20100219/articles/100219316?p=1&amp;tc=pg  Years in the making, Florida lacrosse debuts Saturday],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (February 19, 2010).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the University of Florida is a long-time member of the [[Southeastern Conference]] (SEC) for the other twenty NCAA sports in which it fields varsity teams,&lt;ref&gt;''See, generally'', [http://www.secsports.com/index.php SECSports.com].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; the Florida Gators women's lacrosse team competes in the American Lacrosse Conference (ALC).&lt;ref name=alcwebsite&gt;''See'' [http://www.americanlacrosseconference.org/  American Lacrosse Conference website].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Among the other eleven SEC member schools, only [[Vanderbilt University]] currently sponsors a varsity women's lacrosse team.&lt;ref&gt;VUCommodores.com, [http://vucommodores.cstv.com/sports/w-lacros/  Lacrosse Team].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The inaugural Florida Gators team played teams from fellow ALC member schools [[Johns Hopkins Blue Jays women's lacrosse|Johns Hopkins]], Ohio State, Penn State, Vanderbilt and defending NCAA champion [[Northwestern Wildcats women's lacrosse|Northwestern]], as well as non-conference opponents Cornell, [[Georgetown Hoyas women's lacrosse|Georgetown]], Navy and New Hampshire during the spring 2010 semester.&lt;ref name=ufmediasupplement/&gt;  The Gators played their first regular season game on February 20, 2010, posting a 16&amp;ndash;6 victory over the Jacksonville Dolphins.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://laxmagazine.com/college_women/DI/2009-10/news/022010_gators_pounce_on_jacksonville_in_rousing_debut  Gators Pounce on Dolphins in Rousing Debut],&quot; ''Lacrosse Magazine'' (February 20, 2010).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.  It was the second Division I lacrosse game played by a Florida-based team in the state of Florida, and the first between two in-state programs.  The Dolphins played the first Division I women's game in the state on February 6, 2010.  ''See'' Jacksonville Dolphins, [http://www.judolphins.com/wlacrosse/  Lacrosse].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The young Gators finished their inaugural season 10&amp;ndash;8, including ALC wins over Penn State and John Hopkins,&lt;ref name=ufmediasupplement/&gt; and were ranked eighteenth in the country in LaxPower's final power ratings.&lt;ref&gt;LaxPower.com, Women's College Lacrosse 2010, [http://www.laxpower.com/update10/binwom/rating01.php  Women's Division I Computer Ratings].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In only their second season of NCAA competition, the sixth-ranked Gators clinched their first ALC regular season championship by defeating the defending conference champion and second-ranked [[Northwestern Wildcats]] 13&amp;ndash;11 on April 14, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;Jeff Barlis, &quot;[http://www.gatorsports.com/article/20110414/ARTICLES/110419680/1136?Title=Lacrosse-tops-No-2-Northwestern  Lacrosse tops No. 2 Northwestern],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (April 14, 2011).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Gators completed a perfect 5&amp;ndash;0 ALC season three days later when they defeated the seventeenth-ranked [[Vanderbilt Commodores]] 8&amp;ndash;7.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gatorsports.com/article/20110418/ARTICLES/110419501/1136?Title=UF-lacrosse-team-makes-history  UF lacrosse team makes history],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (April 18, 2011).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Northwestern Wildcats edged the Gators 10&amp;ndash;9 in the ALC Tournament final, after the Gators defeated the Ohio State Buckeyes 16&amp;ndash;13 in the semifinal round.

The Gators received their first NCAA Tournament bid, seeded fourth in the sixteen-team field on May 9, 2011,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gatorsports.com/article/20110508/ARTICLES/110509523/1136?Title=UF-lacrosse-a-No-4-seed-in-NCAAs  UF lacrosse a No. 4 seed in NCAAs],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (May 8, 2011).  Retrieved May 10, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and defeated the Stanford Cardinal women's team 13&amp;ndash;11 in the first round of the NCAA tournament five days later.&lt;ref&gt;Kevin Brockway, &quot;[http://www.gatorsports.com/article/20110514/ARTICLES/110519706/1136?Title=UF-advances-in-NCAA-lacrosse-after-beating-Stanford  UF advances in NCAA after beating Stanford],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (May 14, 2011).  Retrieved May 15, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The young Gators eventually fell to the veteran [[Duke Blue Devils]] 13&amp;mdash;9 in the quarterfinals (&quot;Elite Eight&quot;) of the 2011 NCAA Tournament, finishing their second season with an overall win-loss record of 16&amp;ndash;4.&lt;ref&gt;Jeff Barlis, &quot;[http://www.gatorsports.com/article/20110521/ARTICLES/110529932/1136?Title=UF-lacrosse-season-ends-with-NCAA-loss-vs-Duke  UF lacrosse season ends with NCAA loss vs. Duke],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (May 21, 2011).  Retrieved May 21, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In advance of the spring 2012 season, ''[[Lacrosse Magazine]]'' ranked the Gators as the preseason No. 2 team in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.gatorzone.com/story.php?id=21246  Lacrosse Magazine Tabs Florida Gators Preseason No. 2],&quot; GatorZone.com (September 7, 2011).  Retrieved September 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Coaching staff ==

Florida named [[Amanda O'Leary]] as its inaugural head coach on June 22, 2007.&lt;ref name=ufolearybio&gt;GatorZone.com, Lacrosse, Coaching &amp; Support Staff, [http://gatorzone.com/lacrosse/staff/oleary  Amanda O'Leary].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Before she became Florida's first head coach, O'Leary served as the head coach at [[Yale University]] for fourteen seasons, and was previously an assistant coach at the [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]] and the [[University of Delaware]].&lt;ref name=ufolearybio/&gt;  As a collegiate player, O'Leary was honored as a two-time All-American [[Field lacrosse#Midfielders|midfielder]] at [[Temple University]], where she led her [[Temple Owls]] team to an NCAA Championship in 1988.&lt;ref name=ufolearybio/&gt;

Assistant coach Erica LaGrow is a second-year Gators assistant.&lt;ref name=uflagrowbio&gt;GatorZone.com, Lacrosse, Coaching &amp; Support Staff, [http://www.gatorzone.com/lacrosse/staff/lagrow  Erica LaGrow].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  She was a first-team All-[[Atlantic Coast Conference]] (ACC) midfielder for the [[North Carolina Tar Heels]], and graduated from the University of North Carolina in 2008.&lt;ref name=uflagrowbio/&gt;  LaGrow currently plays for the U.S. Women's Elite Lacrosse team, and was a key player on the U.S. national team that defeated Australia in the gold medal game of the 2009 [[Federation of International Lacrosse]] (FIL) Women's World Cup.&lt;ref name=uflagrowbio/&gt;

Assistant coach Caitlyn McFadden is a first-year Gators assistant.&lt;ref name=ufmcfaddenbio&gt;GatorZone.com, Lacrosse, Coaching &amp; Support Staff, [http://www.gatorzone.com/lacrosse/staff/mcfadden  Caitlyn McFadden].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  She played for the [[Maryland Terrapins]], and graduated from the University of Maryland in 2010 after leading the Terps to the 2010 NCAA Championship.&lt;ref name=ufmcfaddenbio/&gt;  McFadden was an IWLCA first-team All-American midfielder in her junior and senior seasons.&lt;ref name=ufmcfaddenbio/&gt;  As a senior, she was the recipient of the [[Tewaarton Award]] and [[Honda Sports Award]], and was named the ACC Player of the Year, the NCAA Tournament Most Valuable Player, and the IWLCA National Midfielder of the Year.&lt;ref name=ufmcfaddenbio/&gt;  The Maryland Terrapins sports program honored her with its Suzanne Tyler Award, given to the University of Maryland female athlete of the year.&lt;ref name=ufmcfaddenbio/&gt;

== Building the future ==

The first Gators recruiting class of twenty-four players&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Women's Lacrosse: University of Florida announces first lacrosse class,&quot; ''Inside Lacrosse'' (November 20, 2008).  Retrieved January 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gatorzone.com/story.php?id=14874  First Gator Lacrosse Signing Class Announced]&quot; GatorZone.com (November 19, 2008).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; included seven US Lacrosse first-team high school All-Americans&amp;mdash;Caroline Chesterman, Katie Ciaci, Brittany Dashiell, Samantha Farrell, Janine Hiller, Jamie Reeg and Julie Schindel, and US Lacrosse named another five as All-American Honorable Mentions—Ashley Bruns, Lelan Bailey, Jenna Hildebrand, Hayley Katzenberger and Mikey Meagher.&lt;ref&gt;LaxPower.com, [http://www.laxpower.com/all-amer/aa-list-hs.php?SelYear=2009&amp;SelGender=G&amp;SelList=AA  US Lacrosse 2009 High School All-Americans].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Dashiell, Bruns and Farrell, plus Kitty Cullen, Colby Rhea and Haydon Judge, were also named Under Armour All-Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Dave Yanovtiz, &quot;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/06/25/AR2009062503892.html  Florida Loads Up on Locals: Gatore' Inaugural Roster Full of Area Players],&quot; ''The Washington Post'' (June 26, 2009).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.  Aaron Wright, &quot;Before heading to Florida, six local girls team up at 'Classic': Gators will rely heavily on six Under Armour All-Americans in first season,&quot; ''Baltimore Sun'' (June 27, 2009).  Retrieved July 5, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Amanda Wedekind was previously named an Under Armour All-American as a rising sophomore in 2006.  The Gators' 2009&amp;ndash;2010 recruiting class was rated best in the nation.&lt;ref name=carney2252010&gt;Patrick Carney, &quot;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=4943749  Florida lacrosse starts strong],&quot; ESPN.com (February 25, 2010).  Retrieved March 1, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Donald R. Dizney Stadium ==

Completed during the summer of 2009, Donald R. Dizney Stadium hosts the Gators women's lacrosse team.&lt;ref name=radndreu3082009&gt;Robbi Andreu, &quot;[http://www.gainesville.com/article/20090308/ARTICLES/903080957?Title=Lacrosse-ready-to-get-dream-home  Lacrosse ready to get 'dream' home],&quot; ''The Gainesville Sun'' (March 8, 2009).  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  The facility includes a 1,500-seat stadium that runs the length of the game field.&lt;ref name=radndreu3082009/&gt;  The $15 million construction cost was funded entirely by private donors.&lt;ref name=radndreu3082009/&gt;  The facility also includes a second practice field, concessions stands, locker rooms, a training room, and other amenities.&lt;ref&gt;GatorZone.com, Lacrosse, Facilities, [http://gatorzone.com/facilities/?venue=lacrosse&amp;sport=lacro  Donald R. Dizney Stadium at Florida Lacrosse Facility].  Retrieved May 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  At the Gators' first home game, an overflow crowd of 2,214 was present in Dizney Stadium for the Gators' 16&amp;ndash;6 win over the Jacksonville Dolphins.

== See also ==

*[[Florida Gators]]
*[[History of the University of Florida]]
*[[List of University of Florida buildings]]
*[[University of Florida Athletic Association|University Athletic Association]]
*[[Women's lacrosse]]

== References ==

{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==

* [http://www.americanlacrosseconference.org/  American Lacrosse Conference] &amp;ndash; Official website of the American Lacrosse Conference.
* [http://www.gatorsports.com/section/gatorslacrosse  GatorSports.com] &amp;ndash; Florida Gators women's lacrosse news from ''The Gainesville Sun''.
* [http://web.gatorzone.com/lacrosse/  GatorZone.com] &amp;ndash; Official webpage of the Florida Gators women's lacrosse team.

{{Florida Gators athletic program navbox}}
{{Florida Gators women's lacrosse}}

[[Category:College lacrosse teams in the United States]]
[[Category:Florida Gators|Lacrosse]]
[[Category:Lacrosse teams in Florida]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 2010]]
[[Category:Women's lacrosse]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
