<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="217170" ns="0" title="Jackson State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
 |name              = Jackson State University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = 
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = &quot;Challenging Minds, Changing Lives&quot;
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = {{Start date|1877|10|23}}
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]], [[Historically black colleges and universities|HBCU]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = $12 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009. {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009|work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher =National Association of College and University Business Officers | url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf|format= PDF | accessdate = February 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = [[Carolyn Meyers]]
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 450
 |staff             = 1,200
 |students          = 8,687
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Jackson, Mississippi|Jackson]]
 |state             = [[Mississippi]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = &lt;br /&gt;[[United States]]
 |coor              = {{coord|32|17|46|N|090|12|28|W|display=inline,title}}
 |campus            = 
 |former_names      = Natchez Seminary&lt;br&gt;Jackson College&lt;br&gt;Jackson State College
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Royal blue|Royal Blue]] and [[White (color)|White]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#092183}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = [[Jackson State Tigers|Tigers]]
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = 
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = [http://www.jsums.edu www.jsums.edu] 
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}'''Jackson State University''' ('''Jackson State''' or '''JSU''') is a [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black university]] founded in 1877 in [[Natchez,_Mississippi|Natchez]], MS by the [[American Baptist Home Mission Society]] of New York. The Society moved the school to Jackson in 1882, renaming it '''Jackson College''', and developed its present campus in 1902. It became a state supported public institution in 1940. A member of the [[Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund]], JSU holds an important place in the history of US civil rights.

==History==
Jackson State University started as Natchez Seminary, a private school, under the auspices of the [[American Baptist Home Mission Society]] of New York, to educate Mississippi’s newly freed and underprivileged blacks. 

* 1877: Operated for 63 years as a private church school beginning with only twenty students. Inman Edward Page was the only black member of the original faculty.
* 1882: , the decision was made to purchase the fifty-two-acre J.A.P. Campbell estate in North Jackson, Mississippi. In 1883, the Society moved the school to Jackson, to the site where [[Millsaps College]] now stands. A part of this transition was the renaming of the school to Jackson College in recognition of the institution’s new, central location in the City of Jackson. Natchez Seminary soon relocated from its site in north Jackson to a tract of land in the southwest section of the city.

* In 1902, construction on the present campus' site began.

* In 1924, the first bachelor’s degree was awarded. During this period, the major educational activities were directed toward teacher education for in-service teachers.

* When the American Baptist Home Mission Society withdrew its support from the institution in 1934, A new board of trustees was organized that kept the school open. On May 30, 1938, control of the Board of Trustees was transferred to Jackson College, Incorporated.

* In 1940, the school was transferred from the private control of the church to the state education system and renamed Mississippi Negro Training School. Initially, the school had been specifically designated by the state to train rural and elementary teachers. In 1942, the Board of Trustees expanded the curriculum to a full four-year teacher education program, culminating in the Bachelor of Science Degree in Education. In May 1944, the first four-year graduating class under state support received their degrees.  In 1944, Mississippi Negro Training School was renamed Jackson College for Negro Teachers

* In 1953, the Division of Graduate Studies was organized during the Summer and the program of Liberal Arts started in the fall of that year. In 1956, Jackson College for Negro Teachers was renamed Jackson State College.

* During the late 1960s, the entire curriculum was reorganized and the following schools were established: the Schools of Liberal Studies, Education, Science and Technology, Business and Economics and the Graduate School.

* On 14 May 1970, two black students were shot and killed (and 12 wounded) by state police during [[Opposition to the Vietnam War|anti-Vietnam War protests]] in the [[Jackson State killings]]. Four hundred pieces of buckshot had struck the woman's dormatory. Howard Zinn reports a local grand jury found the attack justified. On March 15, 1974, Jackson State College was designated Jackson State University. Jackson State College gained university status in accordance with the expanded breadth and quality of its faculty and academic programs. From 1967-1977, the faculty tripled in size and the number of faculty members with graduate degrees increased eightfold. In 1979, the University was officially designated the state’s Urban University by the Board of Trustees, State Institutions of Higher Learning.

* In the late 1980s, the University and its surrounding community was enriched through the expansion of the Universities Center; the establishment of the West Jackson Community Development Corporation to improve blighted housing around the campus; the organization of a Staff Senate; and the creation of a Center for Professional Development and the Center for Technology Transfer.

* In the 1990s, a Campus Master Plan that projected the growth of the University into the 21st Century was developed. Fifteen new graduate and undergraduate programs evolved. These academic achievements were bolstered by the establishment of the School of Social Work, the formation of the School of Engineering, and the fall 1998 opening of the School of Allied Health Sciences, the School of Business received accreditation of the Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business (AACSB), a $13.5 million expansion of the H. T. Sampson Library, which doubled the capacity of the original structure, was completed, and the $17.2 million School of Liberal Arts building was occupied in 2001.

* In Fall 2000, the University received doctoral research intensive status with the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. This prestigious designation was based on the awarding of more than 20 doctoral degrees from the Division of Graduate Studies and the $40 million in federally funded research contracts secured through the Office of Research and Sponsored Programs.

* In 2002, the University celebrated its 125th anniversary. It developed and implemented its strategic plan–Beyond Survival: The Millennium Agenda for Jackson State University. The five-point strategic plan is moving Jackson State University to a new academic excellence. Thus, Vision 2020 was created to fulfill the first strategy–Remodel the Learning System at JSU. In 2002, the University was reorganized into six colleges: College of Business; College of Public Service; College of Liberal Arts; College of Science, Engineering and Technology; College of Lifelong Learning; and College of Education and Human Development.

* In 2004, a $20 million College of Business building was completed.

* In 2006, a new {{convert|91000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} student health wellness center opened. For the first time in the University’s history, private bond financing was secured to renovate some facilities on campus and to build new facilities, including a new Campus Union, a new president’s house, new student apartments, and dormitories which opened in 2006. The campus transformation and wide array of academic programs enhanced Jackson State’s presence.

Today, JSU provides traditional and non-traditional students of diverse backgrounds academic opportunities to develop knowledge and skills that will empower them to succeed in an increasingly complex and technologically advanced world. JSU has expanded online course offerings, and students are also afforded the opportunity to excel in areas beyond academic disciplines including art, culture, music and numerous intercollegiate sports and championship competitions. Jackson State’s long-term cooperative projects, corporate partnerships, its increasing presence among top universities for the amount of research dollars awarded to the University, and community initiatives strengthen the University’s commitment to its students, faculty, staff and alumni as well as to the West Jackson Community, the city, the state, the nation and several international countries.

==Campus==
Jackson State University is located in Jackson, the capital city and the cultural, political, geographic and business center of Mississippi. The campus is a {{convert|245|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus with 51 academic and administrative buildings. It is less than five minutes from downtown and less than twenty minutes from Jackson-Evers International Airport. The main campus is located on JR Lynch St between Prentiss and Dalton St. The United States Postal Service has assigned Jackson State ZIP code 39217 for P.O. box mail.

Ayer Hall was constructed in 1903 and is the oldest structure on campus. It was named in honor of the First President and was named to the National Register of Historic Places in 1977. Green-Gibb Pedestrian Walkway (Plaza) was named in honor of those who died in the [[Jackson State killings]]. The [[Walter Payton]] Health &amp; Wellness Center was constructed in 2006.

==Academics==
{{Infobox US university ranking
&lt;!-- U.S. rankings --&gt;
| ARWU_NU       = 
| Forbes        = 593
| USNWR_NU      = 
| Wamo_NU       =
&lt;!-- Global rankings --&gt;
| ARWU_W        = 
| QS_W          =
| THES_W        =
}}
JSU is to be a model urban learning community for highly motivated students from diverse backgrounds, where original research and experiential learning are integrated into rigorous and internationally prominent teaching, research and service learning programs. A historically black Doctoral/Research public university, Jackson State educates a diverse student population in a broad range of baccalaureate,  masters and doctoral programs. The learning process is enhanced through experiential learning.  Jackson State University is accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools (SACS) and is 1 of only 2 Historically Black Colleges and Universities to be classified as a research intensive university with high research activity by &lt;ref&gt;http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/lookup_listings/view_institution.php?unit_id=175856&amp;start_page=institution.php&amp;clq={%22ipug2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ipgrad2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22enrprofile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22ugprfile2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22sizeset2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22basic2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22eng2005_ids%22%3A%22%22%2C%22search_string%22%3A%22Jackson+State+University%22%2C%22first_letter%22%3A%22%22%2C%22level%22%3A%22%22%2C%22control%22%3A%22%22%2C%22accred%22%3A%22%22%2C%22state%22%3A%22%22%2C%22region%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urbanicity%22%3A%22%22%2C%22womens%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hbcu%22%3A%22%22%2C%22hsi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22tribal%22%3A%22%22%2C%22msi%22%3A%22%22%2C%22landgrant%22%3A%22%22%2C%22coplac%22%3A%22%22%2C%22urban%22%3A%22%22}&lt;/ref&gt;The Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education, along with Howard University.

JSU colleges include:
* College of Business
* College of Education and Human Development
* College of Liberal Arts
* College of Public Service
* College of Science, Engineering and Technology
* College of Lifelong Learning

==Student activities==
===Greeks===
Fraternities include [[Alpha Phi Alpha]], [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Omega Psi Phi]], [[Phi Beta Sigma]], and [[Iota Phi Theta]]. Sororities include [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]], [[Delta Sigma Theta]], [[Zeta Phi Beta]], [[Sigma Gamma Rho]], [[Kappa Kappa Psi]], and [[Tau Beta Sigma]].

===Athletics===
{{Main|Jackson State Tigers}}
Athletic teams are a member of the NCAA Division I-FCS (Football Championship Subdivision) [[Southwestern Athletic Conference]], commonly known as the SWAC. All SWAC sports are DI with Football being FCS. Currently, the university fields men's and women's basketball, football, baseball, softball, men's and women's golf, women's volleyball, men's and women's tennis, soccer, and men and women's bowling teams. The university's mascot is the Tiger, and the teams are sometimes referred to as the &quot;Blue Bengals.&quot; 

The Tiger football team has a heralded history, winning and sharing 16 SWAC titles, including 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clarionledger.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071215/SPORTS030101/712150356/1287/SPORTS|work=The ClarionLedger|title=Oliver leads Jackson State to SWAC title}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its most famous alumni includes NFL Hall of Famers [[Lem Barney]], [[Jackie Slater]] and [[Walter Payton]], and former [[Jacksonville Jaguars]] wide receiver Jimmy Smith. 

The men's golf team has gained notoriety as it has become a SWAC powerhouse and perennial NCAA tournament participant under head coach [[Eddie Payton]], older brother of [[Walter Payton]].{{fact|date=October 2009}}

JSU's well-known rivals include [[Southern University|Southern]], [[Alcorn State University|Alcorn State]], [[Mississippi Valley State University|Mississippi Valley State]], and [[Tennessee State University|Tennessee State]].

===Sonic Boom of the South===
The Jackson State University Marching Band, “The Sonic Boom of the South” is a very diverse, competent, and a flexible musical group.

The band was first organized in the early 1940s. As early as the mid-1920s, the University had a well-organized orchestra. The group was given the nickname, “The Sonic Boom of the South” by band director Harold J. Haughton, Sr. in 1971. In 1971, the majorettes abandoned their batons and became a dance team known as the Prancing J-Settes, also named by Haughton. In 1974, “Get Ready,” an old Motown favorite was selected as the band’s theme song. Also, during the mid 1970s, the “Tiger Run-On” was perfected. Created by Haughton, the “Tiger Run-On” is a fast, eye-catching shuffle step that blends an adagio step with an up-tempo shuffle (200 steps per minute), then back to adagio—a “Sonic Boom” trademark that brings fans to their feet during halftime performances. Oct 1990, Under the direction of Dowell Taylor and staff. The JSU Sonic Boom of the South performed in Los Angeles, California for Motown 30-What's Going on. This was the event that set the wheels in motion for the NATION attention of the Sonic Boom. In 2003 the marching band was in enshrined in the NCAA Hall of Champions. Also, the marching band was filmed by Electronic Art Sports (EA Sports) for inclusion in the 2005 vision of the video game &quot;EA Sports NCAA Football 2005.&quot;

The band has performed at halftime for the Atlanta Falcons, the Detroit Lions, the New Orleans Saints, the New York Jets, the Houston Oilers, the Philadelphia Eagles, the Cincinnati Bengals, and the Indianapolis Colts It also performed at the 1991 NBA All-Star game, Motown’s 30th Anniversary television special, the NAACP 34th Image Awards television special, and the Honda Battle of The Bands 2006, 2009, 2011.{{fact|date=November 2011}}

===The J-Settes===
The Prancing J-Settes is the official name of the Jackson State University dance line, an auxiliary group of the Jackson State University Marching Band that began in 1971.The thrill of a thousand eyes,” were the words spoken by Dr. Jimmie James, Jr. at the onset of the “Prancing Jaycettes” in 1971.  Shirley Middleton, a former majorette,  initiated the concept of the majorettes abandoning their batons and dancing to popular musical selections.  As the majorette sponsor, Shirley Middleton and the majorettes met with Dr. John A. Peoples, the University’s sixth president, and requested that they be permitted to “put down their batons.”Dr. Peoples agreed and thus legends were born.  In 1970, Middleton assembled 18 majorettes, and their notoriety immediately began to soar in rapid proportions.  Their beauty, grace, and poise were astounding and their dance routines to songs such as “Kool-Aid,” James Brown’s “Make it Funky,” and “Hot Pants,” were magnificent, unmatched by any other competing groups.

The group was initially named the “Prancing Jaycettes.”  The group’s name became official in 1971.  However, in 1982, the Prancing Jaycette organization officially changed its name to Prancing J-Settes, because of a name conflict with a local organization known as the Jackson Jaycees/Jaycettes.

Shirley Middleton served as sponsor of the J-Settes from 1970-1975.  In 1975, Narah Oatis was appointed the sponsor of the J-Settes.  Under her leadership, the Prancing J-Settes became nationally renowned.  During her reign, J-Sette marching technics such as the “Salt and Pepper,” “J-Sette Walk,” “Strut,” and “Tip Toe” were perfected.  The J-Settes consisted of lines of 12-16 young ladies who marched in rows affectionately named “Short and Sassy,” “Magnificent Middle,” or a “Tall and Tough.”  Mrs. Oatis tenure is best remembered by many for the J-Settes’s stellar performance at the 30th Anniversary of Motown in 1990,  the  “Coming to America routine,” “Proud Mary,” and the “Liturgical dance routine.”  (“Coming to America” and the “Proud Mary” routines were both originally performed in 1995.  The “Liturgical dance routine” was first performed in 1996.)  Narah Oatis served as director (sponsor) of the Prancing J-Settes for 21 years.   She resigned as sponsor of the J-Settes in February 1997.

In the Spring of 1997, a former J-Sette captain, Mrs. Kathy Pinkston-Worthy was appointed director (sponsor) of the Prancing J-Settes.  Under her direction, the J-Settes have become nationally known for their rapid fire highly technical dance routines to selections such as “I Go to Work” and “Swoop.”  Perhaps, the most celebrated marque performance by the Prancing J-Settes was rendered at the 34th NAACP Image Awards in Hollywood, California in 2003 where the J-Settes performed on National Television with “Cedric the Entertainer” and “Sugar Bear of E.U.”  Both routines were choreographed by Mrs. Worthy.

===Student media===
Jackson State is home to radio station [[WJSU-FM]] which plays jazz, gospel, news and public affairs programming. It also houses a low-powered television station, [[W23BC]]. Jackson State also publishes thejjhhh independent Blue and White Flash weekly student newspaper.

==Notable alumni==
{{AlumniStart}}
{{Alum|name=Shasta Averyhardt|year=2008|nota=Female [[LGPA]] golfer, 1st [[African-American]] woman to qualify for the [[LPGA]] tour since 2001, and its fourth African-American woman member in the 60-year history of the [[LPGA]].|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.blackamericaweb.com/?q=articles/news/the_state_of_black_america_news/24593|title=Former Jackson State golfer Shasta Averyhardt qualifies of LPGA tour}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Lem Barney]]|year=|nota=[[National Football League|NFL]] Hall of Fame cornerback with the [[Detroit Lions]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Marcus Benard]]|year=2009|nota=Current NFL linebacker|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Oil Can Boyd|Dennis &quot;Oil Can&quot; Boyd]]|year=|nota=former [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Corey Bradford]]|year=|nota=former [[National Football League]] player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Robert Brazile]]|year=|nota=former 7-time NFL [[Pro Bowl]] [[outside linebacker]] with the [[Houston Oilers]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Vivian Brown|year=|nota=[[Weather Channel]] meteorologist|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.weather.com/tv/personalities/Vivian-Brown.html|title=Vivian Brown|publisher=The Weather Channel Interactive, Inc.|accessdate=2009-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Emmett C. Burns, Jr.]]|year=|nota=Member of the Maryland House of Delegates
from the 10th district|ref=}}

{{Alum|name=[[Wes Chamberlain]]|year=|nota=former Major League outfielder|ref=}}
{{alum|name=[[Dave Clark (baseball)|Dave Clark]]|year=|nota=former Major League outfielder|ref=}}
{{alum|name=[[Robert G. Clark, Jr.]]|year=|nota=politician who was elected to the Mississippi House of Representatives in 1967. He was the first African American elected to the Mississippi State Legislature since the Reconstruction era.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Archie Cooley|Archie &quot;Gunslinger&quot; Cooley]]|year=1962|nota=former head football coach at [[Mississippi Valley State University]], [[University of Arkansas-Pine Bluff]], [[Norfolk State University]], and [[Paul Quinn College]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Speedy Duncan|Leslie &quot;Speedy&quot; Duncan]]|year=|nota=former 4-time NFL Pro-Bowl [[cornerback]] with the [[San Diego Chargers]] and [[Washington Redskins]].|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Marvin Freeman]]|year=|nota=former Major League pitcher|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Percy Greene]]|year=|nota=founded the [[Jackson Advocate]] newspaper, Mississippi's oldest black-owned newspaper|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Lindsey Hunter]]|year=|nota=Former NBA [[Point guard]]  of the [[Chicago Bulls]]. Won the [[2003-04 NBA season|2003-04]] championship with the Detroit Pistons and the [[2001–02 NBA season|2001-02]] championship with the [[Los Angeles Lakers]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Harold Jackson (football)|Harold Jackson]]|year=|nota=former NFL wide receiver; played majority career with the [[Los Angeles Rams]] and [[New England Patriots]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Malcolm D. Jackson|year=|nota=CIO at [[Environmental Protection Agency]] during  President Barack Obama administration. He is a Presidential Appointment.|ref=&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/oeiaa.html|title=Malcolm D. Jackson, Chief Information Officer and Assistant Administrator for the Office of Environmental Information}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Thadeus Jackson]]|year=|nota=NFL assistant coach|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Claudis James]]|year=|nota=former NFL player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jaymar Johnson]]|year=2008|nota=current NFL wide receiver|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Trey Johnson]]|year=|nota=current NBA/NBA Development League Player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Ed Manning]] |year=|nota=Drafted by the [[Washington Wizards|Baltimore Bullets]] in the 8th round (1st pick, 80th overall) of the 1967 [[NBA draft]], father of [[Danny Manning]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Audie Norris]]|year=|nota=former [[NBA]] [[Power forward (basketball)|Power Forward]] and superstar for [[Winterthur FC Barcelona]] in the late 80's|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Willie Norwood]]|year=|nota=American Gospel singer. He is the father and voice coach of R&amp;B singers [[Brandy]] and [[Ray J]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Eddie Payton]]|year=1973|nota=NFL kick returner; current Jackson state golf coach|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Walter Payton]]|year=1975|nota=NFL Hall of Fame running back; played entire career for the [[Chicago Bears]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Carlton W. Reeves]]|year=1986|nota=Judge of the [[United States District Court for the Southern District of Mississippi]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Purvis Short]]|year=|nota=former [[NBA]] [[Small forward]] scorer for the [[Golden State Warriors]] in the mid 80's|ref=}} 
{{Alum|name=[[Jackie Slater]]|year=|nota=NFL Hall of Fame offensive tackle; played entire career with the Los Angeles/[[St. Louis Rams]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jimmy Smith (wide receiver)|Jimmy Smith]]|year=|nota=Retired NFL wide receiver; played majority career with the [[Jacksonville Jaguars]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Tonea Stewart]]|year=|nota=Actress and Educator|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Cassandra Wilson]]|year=|nota=Jazz vocalist and musician|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Dr. Rod Paige]]|year=|nota=Secretary of Education during President George W. Bush administration from 2001-2005, and former head football coach from 1964-1968|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Bennie G. Thompson]]|year=|nota=Member [[U. S. House of Representatives]]. Serving from April 1993 to Current|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Demarco Morgan]]|year=|nota=News anchor for WNBC in New York City. |ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

==See also==
*[[Jackson State University Botanical Garden]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* {{official|http://www.jsums.edu}}
* [http://www.jsubound.ning.com www.jsubound.ning.com] -- Social network for prospective Jackson State University students to talk with recruiters and meet future classmates
* [http://www.jsutigers.com www.jsutigers.com] -- Official athletics web site
* [http://www.jsuflash.com  www.jsuflash.com] -- ''The Blue &amp; White Flash'' student newspaper
* [http://www.wjsu.org www.wjsu.org] WJSU-FM official site
* [http://tv23.jsums.edu/ tv23.jsums.edu] W23BC official site
* [http://sonicboomofthesouth.com sonicboomofthesouth.com] -- official Marching Band web site
* [http://www.aaregistry.org/historic_events/view/killings-jackson-state-university Jackson State University Riots May 14, 1970 in response to the Kent State shootings leaving 2 dead and many wounded]

{{Public Colleges and Universities in Mississippi}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}
{{Southwestern Athletic Conference}}

[[Category:Jackson State University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Mississippi]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1877]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Jackson metropolitan area]]
[[Category:Education in Jackson, Mississippi]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Jackson, Mississippi]]

[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی جکسون]]
[[it:Jackson State University]]
[[no:Jackson State University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
