<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2171906" ns="0" title="Slavery and religion"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{slavery}}
The issue of [[religion]] and [[slavery]] is an area of historical research into the relationship between the world's major religions and the practice of slavery.

==Judaeo-Christian Religion==
=== Slavery in the Bible ===
{{main|The Bible and slavery}}

The [[Book of Genesis|Genesis]] narrative about the [[Curse of Ham]] has often been held to be an [[aetiology|aetiological]] story, giving a reason for the enslavement of the [[Canaanites]]. The word ''ham'' is very similar to the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word for ''black''/''hot'', which is [[cognate]] with an [[Egyptian language|Egyptian]] word (''khem'', meaning ''[[black (hieroglyphic 'km')|black]]'') used to refer to [[Ancient Egypt|Egypt]] itself, in reference to the fertile black soil along the [[Nile valley]]. Although many scholars therefore view ''Ham'' as an eponym used to represent Egypt in the [[Table of Nations]],&lt;ref&gt;''Jewish Encyclopedia'' (1901), article on ''Ham''&lt;/ref&gt; a number of Christians throughout history, including [[Origen]]&lt;ref&gt;Origen, ''Homilies'', on Genesis 16:1&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Cave of Treasures]],&lt;ref&gt;(edited by Ciala Kourcikidzé), ''The cave of treasures: Georgian version'', translated by Jean-Pierre Mahé in ''The written corpus of eastern Christianity'' 526-27, part of ''Scriptores Iberici'' 23-24 (Louvain, 1992-93), 21:38-39&lt;/ref&gt; have argued for the alternate proposition that ''Ham'' represents all [[black people]], his name symbolising their dark skin colour;&lt;ref&gt;Goldenberg, D. M. (2003). The Curse of Ham. Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton University Press, page 141.&lt;/ref&gt; pro-slavery advocates, from [[Patriarch Eutychius of Alexandria|Eutychius of Alexandria]]&lt;ref&gt;(edited by J.P. Migne), ''Complete course in Patrology…Greek series'', (Paris, 1857-66), on ''Annals'' 111:917B:41-43&lt;/ref&gt; and [[John Philoponus]],&lt;ref&gt;A. Sanda, ''Opposcula Monophysitica Johannes Philoponi'' (Beirut, 1930), page 96&lt;/ref&gt; to American pro-slavery apologists,&lt;ref&gt;Haynes, S. R. (2002). Noah's Curse. New York: Oxford University Press, page 71.&lt;/ref&gt; have therefore occasionally interpreted the narrative as a condemnation of all black people to slavery.&lt;ref&gt;Felder, C. H. (2002). Race, Racism, and the Biblical Narratives. Minneapolis, Minnesota: Augsburg Fortress, page 8.&lt;/ref&gt; A few Christians, like [[Jerome]], even took up the [[racism|racist notion]] that black people inherently had ''a soul as black as [their] body''.&lt;ref&gt;Jerome, ''Homilies'', 1:3:28&lt;/ref&gt;

Slavery was customary in [[Ancient history|antiquity]], and it is condoned by the [[Torah]], which occasionally compels it.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|22:2-3|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|21:10-11|}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bible uses the [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] term ''ebed'' to refer to slavery; however, ''ebed'' has a much wider meaning than the English term ''slavery'', and in several circumstances it is more accurately translated into English as ''servant''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Jewish Encyclopedia]]'' (1901), article on ''Slaves and Slavery''&lt;/ref&gt; It was seen as legitimate to enslave captives obtained through warfare,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|20:10-16|}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not through kidnapping.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|24:7|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|20:10-16|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Children could also be sold into [[debt bondage]],&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:44|}}&lt;/ref&gt; which was sometimes ordered by a court of law.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Isaiah|22:2-3|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|2|Kings|4:1-7|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;&gt;''Jewish Encyclopedia'' (1901), article on ''Slaves and Slavery''&lt;/ref&gt; 

As with the [[Biblical Hittites|Hittite]] Laws and the [[Code of Hammurabi]],&lt;ref&gt;''Peake's commentary on the Bible'' (1962), on Exodus 21:18-27&lt;/ref&gt; the bible does set minimum rules for the conditions under which slaves were to be kept. Slaves were to be treated as part of an extended family;&lt;ref name=&quot;bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:14&quot;&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:14|}}&lt;/ref&gt; they were allowed to celebrate the [[Sukkot]] festival,&lt;ref name=&quot;bibleverse||Deuteronomy|16:14&quot;/&gt; and expected to honour [[Shabbat]].&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|20:10|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Israelite slaves could not be compelled to work ''with rigour'',&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:43|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:53|}}&lt;/ref&gt; and debtors who sold themselves as slaves to their creditors had to be treated the same as a hired servant.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:39|}}&lt;/ref&gt; If a master harmed a slave in one of the ways covered by the [[lex talionis]], the slave was to be compensated by [[manumission]];&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|21:26-27|}}&lt;/ref&gt; if the slave died within 24 to 48 hours, he or she was to be ''avenged''&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|21:20-21|}}&lt;/ref&gt; (whether this refers to the [[death penalty]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;&gt;Maimonides, ''Mishneh Torah''&lt;/ref&gt; or not&lt;ref&gt;''Jewish Encyclopedia'' (1901), article on ''Avenger of Blood''&lt;/ref&gt; is uncertain). 

Israelite slaves were automatically manumitted after six years of work, and/or at the next [[Jubilee (Biblical)|Jubilee]] (occurring either every 49 or every 50 years, depending on interpretation), although the latter would not apply if the slave was owned by an Israelite and wasn't in debt bondage.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:47-55|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Slaves released automatically in their 7th year of service, which did not include female slaves,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|21:7|}}&lt;/ref&gt; or&lt;ref&gt;''Jewish Encyclopedia'' (1901), article on ''Law, Codification of''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Peake's commentary on the Bible'' (1962), on Exodus 21:2-11&lt;/ref&gt; did,&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|15:12|}}&lt;/ref&gt; were to be given livestock, grain, and wine, as a parting gift&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|15:13-14|}}&lt;/ref&gt; (possibly hung round their necks&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;). This 7th-year manumission could be voluntarily renounced, which would be signified, as in other Ancient Near Eastern nations,&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Kelly Cheyne]] and John Sutherland Black, ''[[Encyclopaedia Biblica]]'' (1903), article on ''Slavery''&lt;/ref&gt; by the slave gaining a ritual [[ear piercing]];&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Exodus|21:5-6|}}&lt;/ref&gt; after such renunciation, the individual was enslaved ''forever'' (and not released at the Jubilee&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Kelly Cheyne and John Sutherland Black, ''Encyclopaedia Biblica'' (1903), article on ''Slavery''&lt;/ref&gt;). Non-Israelite slaves were always to be enslaved ''forever'', and treated as inheritable property.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Leviticus|25:44-46|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In several [[Pauline epistles]], and the [[First Epistle of Peter]], slaves are admonished to obey their masters, ''as to the Lord, and not to men'';&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Ephesians|6:5-8|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Colossians|3:22-25|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Timothy|6:1|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse||Titus|2:9-10|}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Peter|2:18}}&lt;/ref&gt; however these particular ''Pauline epistles'' are also [[authorship of the Pauline epistles|those whose Pauline authorship is doubted]] by many modern scholars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Ehrman |first=Bart D.|authorlink=Bart D. Ehrman |title=The New Testament: A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings |year=2004 |publisher=Oxford |location=New York |isbn=0-19-515462-2 }}, page 385&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Udo Schnelle]], ''Apostle Paul: His Life and Theology'' (2003), [english translation published 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Hermann Detering]], ''The Falsified Paul'' (1995)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen G. Wilson, ''Luke and the Pastoral Epistles'' (1979)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Norman Perrin]], ''The New Testament: An Introduction'' (1974)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;W. Bujard, ''Stilanalytische Untersuchungen zum Kolosserfrief als Beitrag zur Methodik von Sprachvergleichen'' (1973)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;E J Goodspeed, ''Key to Ephesians'' (1956),  page 6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mitton, ''The Epistle to the Ephesians'' (1951), pages 245-255&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Alfred Loisy]], ''The Origins of the New Testament'' (1936)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Percy Neale Harrison, ''The Problem of the Pastoral Epistles'' (1921)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Ferdinand Christian Baur]], ''Paul, the Apostle of Jesus Christ: His Life and Works'' (1845)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;also partially advocated by [[Desiderius Erasmus]]&lt;/ref&gt; By contrast, the [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]], one of the ''undisputed epistles'',&lt;ref&gt;Seven of the Pauline Epistles are regarded as genuine by most scholars; academics therefore use the term ''undisputed epistles'' to collectively refer to these seven&lt;/ref&gt; describes lawfully obtained manumission as the ideal for slaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{bibleverse|1|Corinthians|7:21-23|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another ''undisputed epistle'' is [[Epistle to Philemon|that to Philemon]], which has become an important text in regard to slavery, being used by pro-slavery advocates as well as by abolitionists;&lt;ref&gt;Religion and the Antebellum Debate Over Slavery, by John R. McKivigan, Mitchell Snay&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://medicolegal.tripod.com/cheevergvs.htm#p140 God Against Slavery, p. 140, by Rev. George B. Cheever, D.D]&lt;/ref&gt; in the epistle, [[Paul of Tarsus|Paul]] returns Onesimus, a fugitive slave, back to his master nature, which was opposed to the equality in which mankind was created.&lt;ref&gt;Philo, ''On the contemplative life''&lt;/ref&gt; However, more mainstream forms of first century [[Judaism]] didn't exhibit such qualms about slavery, and ever since the 2nd century expulsion of Jews from Judea, wealthy Jews have owned non-Jewish slaves, wherever it was legal to do so;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt; nevertheless, manumissions were approved by Jewish religious officials on the slightest of pretexts, and court cases concerning manumission were nearly always decided in favour of freedom, whenever there was uncertainty towards the facts&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[minor tractate|The Minor Tractates]]'', ''Abadim'' 9:6&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Talmud]], a document of great importance in Judaism, made many rulings which had the effect of making manumission easier and more likely:
*The costly and compulsory giving of gifts was restricted the 7th-year manumission only&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;
*The price of freedom was reduced to a proportion of the original purchase price rather than the total fee of a hired servant, and could be reduced further if the slave had become weak or sickly (and therefore less saleable).&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt;
*Voluntary manumission became officially possible, with the introduction of the manumission deed (the ''shetar shihrur''), which was counted as [[prima facie]] proof of manumission.
*Verbal declarations of manumission could no longer be revoked.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Gittin]]'' 1:6&lt;/ref&gt;
*Putting [[Tefillin|phylacteries]] on the slave, or making him publicly read three or more verses from the Torah, was counted as a declaration of the slave's manumission&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt;
*Extremely long term sickness, for up to 4 years in total, couldn't count against the slave's right to manumission after six years of enslavement&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt;

Jewish participation in the slave trade itself was also regulated by the Talmud. Fear of [[apostasy]] lead to the Talmudic discouragement of the sale of Jewish slaves to non-Jews,&lt;ref&gt;''Gittin'', 4:6&lt;/ref&gt; although loans were allowed;&lt;ref&gt;''Gittin'', 46b&lt;/ref&gt; similarly slave trade with [[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]] was only to be for the purpose of removing slaves from non-Jewish religion.&lt;ref&gt;''Jewish Encyclopedia'' (1901), article on ''Fairs''&lt;/ref&gt; Religious racism meant that the Talmudic writers completely forbade the sale or transfer of [[Canaan]]ite slaves out from [[Roman Palestine|Palestine]] to elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;''Gittin'' 4:6&lt;/ref&gt; Other types of trade were also discouraged: men selling themselves to women, and post-[[puberty|pubescent]] daughters being sold into slavery by their fathers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt; Pre-pubescent slave girls sold by their fathers had to be freed-then-married by their new owner, or his son, when she ''started'' [[puberty]];&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt; slaves could not be allowed to marry free Jews,&lt;ref&gt;''Gittin'' 4:5&lt;/ref&gt; although masters were often granted access to the ''services'' of the wives of any of their slaves&lt;ref&gt;''[[Kiddushin]]'' 22a&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Talmudic law, killing of a slave is punishable in the same way as killing of a freeman, even it was committed by the owner. While slaves are considered the owner's property, they may not work on Sabbath and holidays; they may acquire and hold property of the own.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia Judaica, 2007, vol. 18, p. 668&lt;/ref&gt; 

Several prominent Jewish writers of the Middle Ages took offense at the idea that Jews might be enslaved; [[Joseph Caro]] and [[Maimonides]] both argue that calling a Jew ''slave'' was so offensive that it should be punished by [[excommunication]].&lt;ref&gt;Maimonides, ''Mishneh Torah'', 6:14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Caro, ''[[Shulkhan Arukh]]'', ''Yoreah De'ah'' 334&lt;/ref&gt; However, they did not condemn enslavement of non-Jews. Indeed, they argued that the biblical rule, that slaves should be freed for certain injuries, should actually only apply to slaves who had converted to Judaism;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt; additionally, Maimonides argued that this manumission was really punishment of the owner, and therefore it could only be imposed by a court, and required evidence from witnesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt; Unlike the biblical law protecting fugitive slaves, Maimonides argued that such slaves should compelled to buy their freedom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jewish Encyclopedia 1901&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maimonides, Mishneh Torah&quot;/&gt; 

At the same time, Maimonides and other [[Halacha|halachic]] authorities forbade of strongly discouraged any unethical treatment of slaves. According to the traditional Jewish law, a slave is more like an indentured servant, who has rights and should be treated almost like a member of the owner's family. Maimonides wrote that, regardless whether a slave is Jewish or not, &quot;The way of the pious and the wise is to be compassionate and to pursue justice, not to overburden or oppress a slave, and to provide them from every dish and every drink. The early sages would give their slaves from every dish on their table. They would feed their servants before sitting to their own meals... Slaves may not be maltreated of offended - the law destined them for service, not for humiliation. Do not shout at them or be angry with them, but hear them out.&quot; In another context, Maimonides wrote that all the laws of slavery are &quot;mercy, compassion and forbearance&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Encyclopedia Judaica, 2007, vol. 18, p. 670&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/305549/jewish/Torah-Slavery-and-the-Jews.htm&lt;/ref&gt;&quot;

===Christianity===
{{main|Christianity and slavery}}

Slavery in different forms existed within [[Christianity]] for over 18 centuries. Although in the [[Early Christianity|early years of Christianity]], freeing slaves was regarded as an act of charity,&lt;ref name=&quot;Slavery in the Middle Ages&quot;&gt;[http://historymedren.about.com/library/weekly/aa012698.htm Slavery in the Middle Ages]&lt;/ref&gt; the actual ''institution'' of slavery was rarely criticised. Indeed, in 340, the [[Synod of Gangra]] condemned the [[Manicheanism|Manicheans]] for their urging that slaves should liberate themselves; the canons of the Synod instead declared that anyone preaching abolitionism should be anathematised, and that slaves had a ''Christian obligation'' to submit to their masters. [[Augustine of Hippo]], who renounced his former Manicheanism, argued that slavery was part of the mechanism to preserve the natural order of things;&lt;ref&gt;Augustine of Hippo, ''[[City of God (book)|City of God]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Elaine Pagels]], ''Adam, Eve, and the Serpent'' (1988), page 114&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Chrysostom]], regarded as a ''saint'' by [[Eastern Orthodoxy]] and [[Roman Catholicism]], argued that slaves should be resigned to their fate, as by ''obeying his master he is obeying God''&lt;ref&gt;[[Henri Daniel-Rops]], ''Cathedral and Crusade'' (1957), page 263&lt;/ref&gt; but also stated that ''Slavery is the fruit of covetousness, of extravagance, of insatiable greediness'' in his Epist. ad Ephes.&lt;ref&gt;http://medicolegal.tripod.com/catholicsvslavery.htm  Leroy J. Pletten, Roman Catholic Church
Opposition to Slavery (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 15th century, some of the Popes legitimized slavery, at least as a result of war.&lt;ref name=Catholic&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |last=Allard |first=Paul |title=Slavery and Christianity |encyclopedia=Catholic Encyclopedia |volume=XIV |publisher=Robert Appleton Company |location=New York |year=1912 |url=http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14036a.htm |accessdate=15 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1452 [[Pope Nicholas V]] issued the papal bull [[Dum Diversas]], which granted Afonso V of Portugal the right to reduce any &quot;Saracens, pagans and any other unbelievers&quot; to hereditary slavery. The approval of slavery under these conditions was reaffirmed and extended in his Romanus Pontifex bull of 1455.

In 1488 [[Pope Innocent VIII]] accepted the gift of 100 slaves from [[Ferdinand II of Aragon]] and distributed those slaves to his cardinals and the Roman nobility. Also, in 1639 [[Pope Urban VIII]] purchased slaves for himself from the [[Knights Hospitaller|Knights of Malta]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Bermejo, S.J. | first = Luis M. | title = Infallibity on Trial | publisher = Christian Classics, Inc. | location = London | year = 1992 | pages = 315–316 | isbn = 0870611909}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Popes in the 15th and 16th century denounced slavery as a ''great crime'', including [[Pope Pius II|Pius II]],&lt;ref name=Catholic /&gt; [[Pope Paul III|Paul III]],&lt;ref&gt;Alessandro Farnese, ''[[Sublimus Dei]]'' (1537) - [http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Paul03/p3subli.htm online copy]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Pope Eugene IV|Eugene IV]].&lt;ref&gt;Gabriele Condulmer, ''[[Sicut Dudum]]'' (1435) - [http://www.papalencyclicals.net/Eugene04/eugene04sicut.htm online copy]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the Dominican friars who arrived at the Spanish settlement at Santo Domingo in 1510 strongly denounced the enslavement of the local Indians. Along with other priests, they opposed their treatment as unjust and illegal in an audience with the Spanish king and in the subsequent royal commission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Thomas | first = Hugh | title = Rivers of Gold: The Rise of the Spanish Empire | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson | location = London | year = 2003| pages = 258–262 | isbn = 0297645633}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a response to this position, the Spanish monarchy's subsequent ''[[Requerimiento]]'' provided a religious justification for the enslavement of the local populations, on the pretext of refusing conversion to Roman Catholicism and therefore denying the authority of the Pope.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Thomas | first = Hugh | title = Rivers of Gold: The Rise of the Spanish Empire | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson | location = London | year = 2003| pages = 266 | isbn = 0297645633}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some other Christian organizations were slaveholders. The 18th century evangelical Protestant [[Society for the Propagation of the Gospel in Foreign Parts]] owned the Codrington Plantation, in [[Barbados]], containing several hundred slaves, branded on their chests with the word ''Society''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/4694896.stm BBC News story about a belated official apology for the Society's crimes]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Adam Hochschild, ''Bury the Chains, The British Struggle to Abolish Slavery'' (2005), page 61&lt;/ref&gt; [[George Whitefield]], famed for his sparking of the so-called ''[[Great Awakening]]'' of American evangelicalism, overturned a province-wide ban against slavery,&lt;ref&gt;Arnold Dallimore, ''George Whitefield: The Life and Times of the Great Evangelist of the Eighteenth Century'' (1980), Volume 2&lt;/ref&gt; and went on to own several hundred slaves himself.&lt;ref&gt;Edward J. Cashin, ''Beloved Bethesda : A History of George Whitefield's Home for Boys'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;

At other times, Christian groups worked against slavery. The seventh century [[Saint Eligius|Saint Eloi]] used his vast wealth to purchase British and Saxon slaves in groups of 50 and 100 in order to set them free.&lt;ref&gt;Life in Medieval Times by Marjorie Rowling&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Religious Society of Friends|Quakers]] in particular were early leaders in [[abolitionism]], attacking slavery since at least 1688. In 1787 the [[Society for Effecting the Abolition of the Slave Trade]] was formed, with 9 of the 12 founder members being Quakers; [[William Wilberforce]], an early supporter of the society, went on to push through the [[Slave Trade Act 1807|1807 Slave Trade Act]], striking a major blow against the transatlantic slave trade. Leaders of [[Methodism]] and [[Presbyterianism]] also vehemently denounced human bondage,&lt;ref&gt;Thoughts Upon Slavery, John Wesley, Published in the year 1774, John Wesley: Holiness of Heart and Life, 1996 Ruth A. Daugherty&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Charles G. Finney, Memoirs (New York: A.S. Barnes, 1876), 324&lt;/ref&gt; convincing their congregations to do likewise; Methodists subsequently made the repudiation of slavery a condition of membership.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ket.org/underground/history/westexpansion.htm &quot;Westward Expansion and Development of Abolitionist Thought&quot;, Kentucky underground railroad]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the southern United States, however, support for slavery was strong; anti-slavery literature was prevented from passing through the postal system, and even sermons, from the famed English preacher [[Charles Spurgeon]], were burned due to their censure of slavery.&lt;ref&gt;The Christian Cabinet, Dec. 14 1859&lt;/ref&gt; When [[civil war]] broke out, to settle the question of the limits of federal power, slavery became one of the issues which would be decided by the outcome; the southern defeat lead to a [[Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution|constitutional ban on slavery]]. Despite the general emancipation of slaves, members of fringe Christian groups like the [[Christian Identity]] movement, and the [[Ku Klux Klan]] (a white supremacist group) see the enslavement of Africans positive aspect of American history.

====Slave Christianity====
In the United States Christianity not only held views about Slavery but Slaves practiced their own form of Christianity. Prior to the work of [[Melville Herskovits]] in 1941 it was widely believed that all elements of African culture were destroyed by the horrific experiences of Africans forced to come to the United States of America. Since his groundbreaking work scholarship has found that Slave Christianity existed as an extraordinarily creative patchwork of African and Christian religious tradition.&lt;ref&gt;Charles H. Lippy, &quot;Slave Christianity&quot; in ''Modern Christianity to 1900: A People's History of Christianity'', ed. Amanda Porterfield (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 2007), 291-292.&lt;/ref&gt;  The slaves brought with them a wide variety of religious traditions including both tribal shamanism and [[Islam]]. Beyond that, tribal traditions could vary to a high degree across the African continent.

There were, however, some commonalities across the majority of tribal traditions. Perhaps the primary understanding of tribal traditions was that there was not a separation of the sacred and the secular.&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles H. Lippy 2007&quot;&gt;Charles H. Lippy, &quot;Slave Christianity&quot; in ''Modern Christianity to 1900: A People's History of Christianity'', ed. Amanda Porterfield (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 2007), 295.&lt;/ref&gt;   All life was sacred and the supernatural was present in every facet and focus of life. Most tribal traditions highlighted this experience of the supernatural in ecstatic experiences of the supernatural brought on by ritual song and dance. Repetitious music and dancing were often used to bring on these experiences through the use of drums and chanting. The realization of these experiences was in the &quot;possession&quot; of a worshipper in which one not only is taken over by the divine but actually becomes one with the divine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Charles H. Lippy 2007&quot;/&gt;

Echoes of African tribal traditions can be seen in the Christianity practiced by slaves in the Americas. The song, dance, and ecstatic experiences of traditional tribal religion were Christianized and practiced by slaves in what is called the &quot;Ring Shout.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Charles H. Lippy, &quot;Slave Christianity&quot; in ''Modern Christianity to 1900: A People's History of Christianity'', ed. Amanda Porterfield (Minneapolis: Fortress Press, 2007), 299-300.&lt;/ref&gt;  This practice was a major mark of African American Christianity during the slavery period.

==Islam==
{{main|Islam and slavery|Arab slave trade}} {{see also|Muhammad's slaves}}
In certain circumstances, [[Islam]] allows for slavery. Such slaves are to be able to purchase or acquire their freedom in various ways. The prophet [[Muhammad]] had several slaves himself. He himself said one of the best deeds is to free a slave. In total his household and friends freed 39,237 slaves. One of them bore him a son, who died as an infant.&lt;ref&gt;Montgomery Watt, ''Muhammad, Prophet and Statesman.'' Oxford University Press, 1961, page 226.&lt;/ref&gt; The slavery endorsed by the [[Qur'an]] limited the source of slaves to the children of two slave parents and non-Muslims captured in war. The [[Qur'an]] provides for [[manumission|emancipation]] of a slave as a means (or in one case, a requirement of) demonstrating remorse for the commission of certain sins. Proclamations of emancipation and repudiations of participation in slave trafficking did not occur in Muslim lands until after the Christian-European Colonial era - as late as 1962 in [[Saudi Arabia]], 1970 in [[Oman]] and [[Yemen]], and 1981 in [[Mauritania]].

==Hinduism==

{{main|History of the Indian caste system|Indian Caste System|Dalit|Hindu reform movements}}
The Caste system in India has often been compared to slavery or slave-like practices. In ancient and medieval times, lower caste Hindus (dubbed &quot;Untouchables&quot; or, more recently [[Dalit]]s) have had reduced social statuses similar to slaves.  Lower Caste Hindus' lives incorporated rigid segregation and bonded labor practices. Justification for such acts was often provided through the use of careful selection of scripture from the vast plethora of Hindu religious literature. However, mainstream Hinduism never condoned or accepted outright slavery.

The purported slavery-like status of the lower Castes, while distinct from others as in ownership - nonetheless permitted freedom for them. Hindus and scholars debate whether the caste system is an integral part of Hinduism sanctioned by the scriptures or an outdated social custom.&lt;ref&gt;Alex Michaels, ''Hinduism: Past and Present'' 188-97 (Princeton 2004) ISBN 0-691-08953-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=castesystem&gt;[http://www.atributetohinduism.com/Caste_System.htm Caste System] View of Scholars&lt;/ref&gt; The most ancient scriptures place little importance on caste and indicate social mobility (Rig Veda 9.112.3), while later scriptures such as the non sacred ''[[Manusmriti]]'' state that the four [[varna (Hinduism)|varna]]s are created by God, implying immutability. Manusmriti, (dated between 200 BCE and 100 CE), contains [[law]]s that [[Codification (law)|codified]] the [[caste]] system, reducing the flexibility of social mobility and excluding the untouchables from society, yet this system was originally non-heritable (Manu Smriti X:65). It is uncertain when the caste system become heritable and akin to slavery.

British colonialists, in the 19th century, exploited these divisions by mistranslating scriptures in Hinduism (such as the [[Manusmriti]]) and attaching undue weight to its importance over other more normative religious scripture in the religion in order to foster sectarian divisions among Hindus as part of the [[Divide and rule]] strategy employed by the crown. Nonetheless, a large number of [[Hindu reform movements]] in the 19th century metamorphosed the landscape of Hindu thought. Hindu reformers aggressively campaigned against any slavery of the lower castes and rendered the idea abhorrent to most mainstream Hindus.

In contemporary times, allegations of apartheid are often drawn against Hindus by partisan political activists. These charge are debunked by academics and scholars, given India's commitment to [[Reservation in India|affirmative action]]. Substantial improvements have taken place in the rights of [[Dalits]] (former &quot;Untouchables&quot;) enshrined in the [[Constitution of India]] (primarily written by a [[Dalit]], [[B. R. Ambedkar|Ambedkar]]), which is the principal object of article 17 in the Constitution as implemented by the Protection of Civil rights Act, 1955 &lt;ref&gt;The Constitution of India by P.M. Bakshi, Universal Law Publishing Co, ISBN 8175345004&lt;/ref&gt; and the fact that India has had a [[Dalit]], [[K.R. Narayanan]], for a [[President of India|president]], as well as the disappearance of the practice in urban public life.&lt;ref name =&quot;Mendelsohn&quot;&gt;Mendelsohn, Oliver &amp; Vicziany, Maria, &quot;The Untouchables, Subordination, Poverty and the State in Modern India&quot;, Cambridge University Press, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;Thus, mainstream sociologists such as Kevin Reilly, Stephen Kaufman, Angela Bodino, while being critical of Casteism, conclude that modern India does not practice any &quot;apartheid&quot; since there is no state sanctioned discrimination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reilley et al.&quot;&gt;Kevin Reilly, Stephen Kaufman, Angela Bodino, Racism: A Global Reader P21, M.E. Sharpe, 2003 ISBN 0765610604.&lt;/ref&gt; They write that [[Caste]]ism in India is presently &quot;not apartheid. In fact, untouchables, as well as tribal people and members of the lowest castes in India benefit from broad [[Reservation in India|affirmative action programs]] and are enjoying greater political power.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reilley et al.&quot;/&gt;

==Bahá'í Faith==
[[Bahá'u'lláh]], founder of the [[Bahá'í Faith]], commended [[Queen Victoria]] for abolishing the slave trade in a letter written to her majesty between 1868-1872.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www-personal.umich.edu/~jrcole/bhkings.htm &quot;Bahá'u'lláh's Tablets to the Rulers&quot; by Juan R.I. Cole, Department of History, University of Michigan]&lt;/ref&gt; Bahá'u'lláh also forbids slavery in the [[Kitáb-i-Aqdas]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/KA/ka-3.html &quot;A Description of the Kitáb-i-Aqdas&quot; page 14 by Shoghí Effendí Rabbání]&lt;/ref&gt; written around 1873 considered by Bahá'ís to be the holiest book revealed by Bahá'u'lláh in which he states, &quot;It is forbidden you to trade in slaves, be they men or women&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://reference.bahai.org/en/t/b/KA/ka-5.html &quot;The Kitáb-i-Aqdas&quot; Paragraph 72 by Bahá'u'lláh]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

[[Category:Slavery and religion| ]]

[[ar:العبودية والدين]]
[[fa:برده‌داری در ادیان]]
[[ta:அடிமைத்தனமும் சமயமும்]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
