<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21720190" ns="0" title="Box-sealing tape"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Box_Sealing_Tape_Large_Roll.jpg|right|thumb|250px|A large roll of box-sealing tape in the tape head of a case-sealing machine.]]

'''Box-sealing tape''', '''parcel tape''' or '''packing tape''' is a [[pressure-sensitive tape]] used for closing or sealing [[corrugated fiberboard]] boxes.  It consists of a [[pressure-sensitive adhesive]] coated onto a backing material which is usually a [[polypropylene]] or [[polyester]] film which is oriented to have strength in both the long (machine) direction and the cross direction.

Most often, the tape is 48 mm (approx 2 inches) wide but it is also used in 72 mm (approx 3-inch) widths.

A variety of backing strengths and calipers as well as adhesive formulations are available. It is often transparent or tan (beige, buff, brown).  Other colors and printing are sometimes available.

==Uses==
The tape is most often used as a closure for regular slotted containers (RSCs).  A &quot;single strip&quot; or &quot;center seam&quot; closure is applied over the center seams of a box extending 50–75 mm (2–3 inches) onto the end panels.

The tape can be used as a &quot;six-strip&quot; closure or &quot;H-seal&quot; by applying cross strips on the ends of the box.  This is used when a relatively weak tape is used or when extra box reinforcement is needed.  This method also seals the box to help keep contaminants out.

This tape has also been used by artists (Eg.[[Mark Jenkins]]) as a way to create molds of objects, as the strength of the tape allows for a strong shell for the mold when completed.

==Application==
[[Image:Box_Sealing_Tape_Magnum_3500.jpg|right|thumb|250px|An automatic box-sealing machine.]]

The tape can be applied manually with a stationary dispenser but is more often applied with a hand-held [[tape dispenser]]: this allows the user to more efficiently place the tape on the box, cut it off, and rub it down.

Automated machinery for application of tape to high-speed lines is also common.

==References==
*[[ASTM]] D5486 Standard Specification for Pressure Sensitive Tape for Packaging, Box Closure, and Sealing
*ASTM D1974 Standard Practice for Methods of Closing, Sealing and Reinforcing Fiberboard Boxes.
* Brody, A. L., and Marsh, K, S., &quot;Encyclopedia of Packaging Technology&quot;, John Wiley &amp; Sons, 1997, ISBN 0-471-06397-5

[[Category:Packaging]]
[[Category:Adhesive tape]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
