<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21776492" ns="0" title="Shanghai Disneyland Park"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox amusement park
|image=  
|name=Shanghai Disneyland Park
|opening_date=2016
|resort=[[Shanghai Disney Resort]]
|location=[[Shanghai]] 
|location2=[[China]]
|theme=Magic Kingdom
|homepage=[http://en.shanghaidisneyresort.com.cn/en/ Shanghai Disneyland Homepage]
|operator=[[The Walt Disney Company]] and Shanghai Shendi Group
}}

'''Shanghai Disneyland''' is an upcoming theme park which is to be built as part of the [[Shanghai Disney Resort]]. It is expected to open in 2016 and will be owned and operated through a joint venture between [[The Walt Disney Company]] and the Shanghai Shendi Group. Construction began on April 8, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;disney1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.shanghaidisneyresort.com.cn/en/press/entry1/ |title=DISNEY AND PARTNERS BREAK GROUND ON SHANGHAI DISNEY RESORT |publisher=Shanghai Disneyland Press Room |date=April 8, 2011 |accessdate=May 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===Construction===
Ground was broken for the new theme park on April 8, 2011, with the expectation that it will take 5 years to complete. An official opening date for the park has not yet been given.&lt;ref name=&quot;disney2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://corporate.disney.go.com/news/parks_resorts/news_release/WaltDisneyParksandResorts/2008/040711_twdc_shanghai.html/ |title=Disney and Partners Break Ground on Shanghai Disney Resort}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The park itself will contain classic Disney attractions that can be found with in other Disney Parks worldwide, along with new attractions built especially for the new park. The park will feature 4 lands, and will follow the traditional 'wheel/spoke' design that was designed by [[Walt Disney]] for [[Disneyland Park]] in 1955. At the center of the park, as per tradition, will lie a castle which will become the parks icon. It will be called Enchanted Storybook Castle and it will be the largest Disney castle to date and it will be the first castle to represent every [[Disney Princess]] instead of just one princess. This castle includes a walkthrough experience named Once Upon a Time Adventure and it will be part of a boat ride that cruises around Fantasyland.&lt;ref name=&quot;disney3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://disneyparks.disney.go.com/blog/2011/08/enchanted-storybook-castle-at-shanghai-disneyland/|title=Sneak Peek: Enchanted Storybook Castle at Shanghai Disneyland}}&lt;/ref&gt; As shown from early concept art, it appears that the [[Adventureland]] area (which traditionally has always been placed to the left of The Hub, has been moved to the traditional location of [[Tomorrowland]] (the right of the hub), which is an element taken from the orignial designs for Disneyland. Unique to Shanghai Disneyland will be an 11 acre 'green area' located in front of the castle.&lt;ref name=&quot;disney3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.shanghaidisneyresort.com.cn/en/press/entry1/|title=Shanghai Disneyland Press Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}
[http://en.shanghaidisneyresort.com.cn/en/ Shanghai Disneyland Website]
[http://disneyparks.disney.go.com Disney Parks Website]

{{Disney parks}}
{{coord missing|China}}

[[Category:Amusement parks in China]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
