<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21861066" ns="0" title="Phun"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=March 2009}}
[[File:Screenshot phun.PNG|right|thumb|Phun]]

'''Phun''' is a 2D [[physics engine]] created by Emil Ernerfeldt for his master thesis while he was studying at [[Umeå University]] in [[Sweden]]. It is based on the [[Constructionism (learning theory)|Constructionist learning]] paradigm, and free for non-commercial use. On May 15, 2008 Phun was taken over by [[Algoryx Simulation AB]], where Emil continues his work on the program.

==Overview==
Phun is a 2D physics sandbox written by Emil ErnerFeldt for his Master of Science thesis at the Umeå University in Sweden. It is based on the SPOOK&lt;ref name=&quot;Ghosts and Machines&quot;&gt;[http://urn.kb.se/resolve?urn=urn:nbn:se:umu:diva-1143 Claude Lacoursière's PhD Thesis 2009, Dept. Computing Science, Umeå University, Sweden]&lt;/ref&gt; linear constraint solver by Claude Lacoursière. It is written in [[C++]], and uses [[OpenGL Extension Wrangler Library|GLEW]], [[SDL]], and [[Boost C++ Libraries|Boost]] (including Boost.Filesystem). 

The name &quot;Phun&quot; is a combination of &quot;'''ph'''ysics&quot; and &quot;f'''un'''&quot;, and the built-in programming language is called thyme.

===History===
The first public beta of Phun was released on December 17, 2007, and received regular updates. The current official update as of now is beta 5.28. 

Phun Beta 5 was renamed to &quot;Algodoo: Phun Edition&quot; after Phun was taken over by [[Algoryx Simulation AB]]. Algodoo is now available to the public for a fee, and has already been made available for the Intel Classmate PCs &lt;ref name=&quot;algodoo&quot;&gt;[http://www.algodoo.com/ Algodoo homepage]&lt;/ref&gt; and demonstrated at the 2009 BETT event in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;Algodoo displayed on BETT&quot;&gt;[http://www.algoryx.se/algodoo_bett_press.html Algodoo displayed on BETT]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Coverage of Classmate PC and Algodoo at BETT&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/7826810.stm BBC Coverage on Intel Classmate PC and Algodoo at BETT]&lt;/ref&gt; Beta 5 work is now complete, and is available at phunland.com.

==Gameplay==
Phun is a sandbox physics program, which heavily concentrates on giving players just enough tools to envision their ideas. There is no set objective, and only basic tools. However, complicated devices can be built such as walkers, engines and transmissions.

===Thyme===
Thyme is a scripting language created by Emil. It can be used to load scenes and alter variables within the program ranging from the strength of gravity to the color of the background. Like a lot of games, phun features a console window (opened with ~) which allows users to enter thyme code. The console uses an auto-complete function and structure type organization system, where only the scope will be shown when auto-complete is called (using tab).

==User created content==
Phun has a wide range of community-built tools, including converters for [[BMP file format|BMP]], [[SVG]], [[.blend (file format)#File format|blend]] and [[AutoCAD]] formats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Available exporters for .phn format&quot;&gt;[http://www.phunland.com/wiki/Links#Converters.2Fexporters Available exporters for .phn format]&lt;/ref&gt;
Phun 4 had many user-made addons such as &quot;Phun Gears&quot;, which allowed users to add gears into their scenes,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phunland.com/forum/viewtopic.php?id=658 Phun external apps]&lt;/ref&gt; although this feature has now been implemented into Phun 5. The source code for Phun 5 has not been released yet due to phun commercializing, so no addons can be made for phun 5.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.phunland.com/forum/viewtopic.php?id=1075 Phun commercializing]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Phunbox===
The Phun community shares scenes under a creative commons 3 by-nc-sa license at [http://www.phunland.com/phunbox/ phunbox], a community-built filesharing website. Users allow others to use their work, abiding by the CC3 by-nc-sa license. The phunbox has now been replaced with the [http://www.algodoo.com/algobox/ algobox], where it includes content created in Phun and in Algodoo.

==Reception==
Phun has been discussed and shown extensively on the internet, as well as being demonstrated at the [[Intel Developer Forum]] 2008 in [[San Francisco]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Use of Phun in Intel developers keynote&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3dbD43tAXls Use of Phun in Intel developers keynote]&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been displayed on the 2009 BETT show in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;Algodoo displayed on BETT&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Coverage of Classmate PC and Algodoo at BETT&quot; /&gt;

An article about Algoryx and [[Algodoo]] has been published by TechWorld.&lt;ref name=&quot;TechWorld Algoryx and Algodoo&quot;&gt;[http://techworld.idg.se/2.2524/1.207124/har-ar-programmet-som-ska-forandra-fysiklektionen TechWorld article on Algoryx and Algodoo (Swedish)]&lt;/ref&gt; (Swedish).

Physicsworld.com reviewed Phun on Jun 2, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Web life: Phun&quot;&gt;[http://physicsworld.com/cws/article/print/39310 Physicsworld.com review]&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.phunland.com/wiki/Home Phun homepage]
*[http://www.phunbox.net/ Phun filesharing website]
*[http://www.algoryx.se/ Algoryx homepage]

[[Category:2007 software]]
[[Category:Computer physics engines]]

[[de:Phun]]
[[es:Phun]]
[[fr:Phun]]
[[it:Phun]]
[[ja:Phun]]
[[pl:Phun]]
[[ru:Phun]]
[[sv:Phun]]
[[uk:Phun]]
[[zh:Phun]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
