<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21863" ns="0" title="Netscape Navigator"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the original Netscape Navigator product (versions 1 to 4.08)|the final 2007 release|Netscape Navigator 9|a full list of Netscape software releases|Netscape (web browser)}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2007}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = Netscape Navigator
| logo                   =
| screenshot             = [[Image:Netscape Navigator.png|250px]]
| caption                = Netscape Navigator 4.08
| developer              = [[Netscape Communications Corporation]]
| released               = 15 December 1994 (Netscape Navigator 1.0)
| platform               = [[Cross-platform]]
| status                 = Unmaintained
| genre                  = [[Web browser]]
| website                = [http://archive.netscape.com/ archive.netscape.com]
}}
'''Netscape Navigator''' was a [[proprietary software|proprietary]] [[web browser]] that was popular in the 1990s. It was the [[flagship]] product of the [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] and the dominant web browser in terms of [[Usage share of web browsers|usage share]], although by 2002 its usage had almost disappeared. This was primarily due to the increased usage of Microsoft's [[Internet Explorer]] web browser software, and partly because the Netscape Corporation (later purchased by [[AOL]]) did not sustain Netscape Navigator's technical innovation after the late 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://browser.netscape.com/history  Netscape's Brief History] Retrieved on 02-16-2009&lt;/ref&gt;

The business demise of Netscape was a central premise of [[Microsoft antitrust trial|Microsoft's antitrust trial]], wherein the Court ruled that [[Microsoft Corporation]]'s bundling of Internet Explorer with the [[Windows operating system]] was a [[monopoly|monopolistic]] and illegal business practice.  The decision came too late for Netscape however, as Internet Explorer had by then become the dominant web browser in Windows.

The Netscape Navigator web browser was succeeded by [[Netscape Communicator]].  Netscape Communicator's 4.x source code was the base for the Netscape-developed [[Mozilla Application Suite]], which was later renamed [[SeaMonkey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Clark|first=Jim|title=Netscape Time|publisher=St. Martin's Press|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; Netscape's Mozilla Suite also served as the base for a browser-only spinoff called [[Mozilla Firefox]] and [[Netscape (web browser)|Netscape]] versions 6 through 9.

AOL formally stopped development of Netscape Navigator on December 28, 2007, but continued supporting the web browser with security updates until March 1, 2008, when AOL canceled technical support.  AOL allows downloading of archived versions of the Netscape Navigator web browser family. Moreover, AOL maintains the Netscape website as an [[Web portal|Internet portal]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://blog.netscape.com/2007/12/28/end-of-support-for-netscape-web-browsers/ |title=End of Support for Netscape web browsers |accessdate=2007-12-29 |author=Tom Drapeau |date=December 28, 2007 |work=The Netscape Blog }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History and development==
===The creation===
Netscape Navigator was based on the [[Mosaic (web browser)|Mosaic]] web browser, which was co-written by [[Marc Andreessen]], a part-time employee of the [[National Center for Supercomputing Applications]] and a student at the [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|University of Illinois]].  After Andreessen graduated in 1993, he moved to [[California]] and there met [[James H. Clark|Jim Clark]], the recently-departed founder of [[Silicon Graphics]].  Clark believed that the Mosaic browser had great commercial possibilities and provided the seed money.  Soon [[Mosaic Communications Corporation]] was in business in [[Mountain View, Santa Clara County, California|Mountain View]], [[California]], with Andreessen as a vice-president.  Since the University of Illinois was unhappy with the company's use of the Mosaic name, the company changed its name to Netscape Communications (thought up by sales representative Greg Sands) and named its flagship web browser Netscape Navigator.

[[Image:Mosaic Netscape 0.9 on Windows XP.png|thumb|225px|Mosaic Netscape 0.9, a pre-1.0 version. Note the image of the Mozilla mascot, and the Mosaic logo in the top-right corner.]]

Netscape announced in its first press release (October 13, 1994) that it would make Navigator available without charge to all non-commercial users, and Beta versions of version 1.0 and 1.1 were indeed freely downloadable in November 1994 and March 1995, with the full version 1.0 available in December 1994. Netscape's initial corporate policy regarding Navigator is interesting, as it claimed that it would make Navigator freely available for non-commercial use in accordance with the notion that Internet software should be distributed for free.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wp.netscape.com/newsref/pr/newsrelease1.html AOL.com - Netscape&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, within 2 months of that press release, Netscape apparently reversed its policy on who could freely obtain and use version 1.0 by only mentioning that educational and non-profit institutions could use version 1.0 at no charge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wp.netscape.com/newsref/pr/newsrelease8.html AOL.com - Netscape&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The reversal was complete with the availability of version 1.1 beta on March 6, 1995, in which a press release states that the final 1.1 release would be available at no cost only for academic and non-profit organizational use. Gone was the notion expressed in the first press release that Navigator would be freely available in the spirit of Internet software. Some security experts and cryptographer found out that all released Netscape versions had major security problems with crashing the browser with long [[URL]]s and 40 bits encryption keys.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Netscape (in)Security (problems)|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/19980129202401/http://hplyot.obspm.fr/~dl/netscapesec/|archivedate=29 January 1998|url=http://hplyot.obspm.fr/~dl/netscapesec/|date=22 July 1996|first=Laurent|last=Demailly|accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|publisher=The New York Times|date=26 September 1995|page=D19|title=Hackers Alert Netscape to Another Flaw|url=http://web.archive.org/web/19990116233126/http://hplyot.obspm.fr/~dl/netscapesec/nyt2.txt|accessdate=15 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first few releases of the product were made available in &quot;commercial&quot; and &quot;evaluation&quot; versions; for example, version &quot;1.0&quot; and version &quot;1.0N&quot;.  The &quot;N&quot; evaluation versions were completely identical to the commercial versions; the letter was there to remind people to pay for the browser once they felt they had tried it long enough and were satisfied with it.  This distinction was formally dropped within a year of the initial release, and the full version of the browser continued to be made available for free online, with boxed versions available on floppy disks (and later CDs) in stores along with a period of phone support. Email support was initially free, and remained so for a year or two until the volume of support requests grew too high.

During development, the Netscape browser was known by the code name [[Mozilla (mascot)|''Mozilla'']], which became the name of a [[Godzilla]]-like cartoon dragon [[mascot]] used prominently on the company's web site. The Mozilla name was also used as the [[user agent|User-Agent]] in [[HTTP]] requests by the browser. Other web browsers claimed to be compatible with Netscape's extensions to HTML, and therefore used the same name in their User-Agent identifiers so that web servers would send them the same pages as were sent to Netscape browsers. [[Mozilla]] is now a generic name for matters related to the [[open source]] successor to Netscape Communicator.

===The rise of Netscape===
[[Image:Navigator 1-22.png|thumb|225px|Netscape Navigator 1.22]]
When the consumer [[Internet]] revolution arrived in the mid-to-late 1990s, Netscape was well positioned to take advantage of it. With a good mix of features and an attractive [[software license|licensing]] scheme that allowed free use for non-commercial purposes, the Netscape browser soon became the [[de facto]] standard, particularly on the [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] platform. [[Internet service provider]]s and computer magazine publishers helped make Navigator readily available.

An important innovation that Netscape introduced in 1994 was the on-the-fly display of web pages, where text and graphics appeared on the screen as the web page downloaded. Earlier web browsers would not display a page until all graphics on it had been loaded over the network connection; this often made a user stare at a blank page for as long as several minutes. With Netscape, people using [[dial-up access|dial-up]] connections could begin reading the text of a web page within seconds of entering a web address, even before the rest of the text and graphics had finished downloading. This made the web much more tolerable to the average user.

[[Image:Netscape 2.02.png|thumb|225px|Netscape Navigator 2.02]]

Through the late 1990s, Netscape made sure that Navigator remained the technical leader among web browsers. Important new features included [[HTTP cookie|cookies]], [[HTML frame|frames]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071030083252/http://docs.rinet.ru/HTMLnya/ch13.htm|archivedate=30 October 2007|url=http://docs.rinet.ru/HTMLnya/ch13.htm|title=Using HTML 3.2, Java 1.1, and CGI; Ch. 13, Frames|first=Eric|last=Ladd}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[proxy auto-config]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wp.netscape.com/eng/mozilla/2.0/relnotes/demo/proxy-live.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20061218002753/wp.netscape.com/eng/mozilla/2.0/relnotes/demo/proxy-live.html|date=March 1996|archivedate=18 December 2006|title=Navigator Proxy Auto-Config File Format|accessdate=15 January 2011|work=Netscape Navigator Documentation}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[JavaScript]] (in version 2.0). Although those and other innovations eventually became open standards of the [[W3C]] and [[European Computer Manufacturers Association|ECMA]] and were emulated by other browsers, they were often viewed as controversial. Netscape, according to critics, was more interested in bending the [[World Wide Web|web]] to its own de facto &quot;standards&quot; (bypassing standards committees and thus marginalizing the commercial competition) than it was in fixing bugs in its products. Consumer rights advocates were particularly critical of cookies and of commercial web sites using them to invade individual privacy.

In the marketplace, however, these concerns made little difference. Netscape Navigator remained the market leader with more than 50% [[Usage share of web browsers|usage share]]. The browser software was available for a wide range of [[operating system]]s, including Windows ([[Windows 3.1x|3.1]], [[Windows 95|95]], [[Windows 98|98]], [[Windows NT|NT]]), [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]], [[Linux]], [[OS/2]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Watson|first=Dave|title=A Quick Look at Netscape|url=http://www.scoug.com/os24u/2001/netscape.html|publisher=The Southern California OS/2 User Group|accessdate=16 August 2010|date=21 July 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many versions of Unix including [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Sun Solaris]], [[Berkeley Software Design|BSDI]], [[IRIX]], [[IBM AIX (operating system)|AIX]], and [[HP-UX]], and looked and worked nearly identically on every one of them. Netscape began to experiment with prototypes of a web-based system, known internally as &quot;Constellation&quot;, which would allow a user to access and edit his or her files anywhere across a network no matter what computer or operating system he or she happened to be using.

Industry observers confidently forecast the dawn of a new era of connected computing. The underlying [[operating system]], it was believed, would become an unimportant consideration; future applications would run within a web browser. This was seen by Netscape as a clear opportunity to entrench Navigator at the heart of the next generation of computing, and thus gain the opportunity to expand into all manner of other software and service market.

===The fall of Netscape===
[[Image:Netscape-navigator-usage-data.svg|thumb|225px|Usage share of Netscape Navigator, 1994&amp;ndash;2007]]

With the success of Netscape showing the importance of the web (more and more people were using the Internet due in part to the ease of using Netscape) Microsoft then saw a new profitable market they could take over. Anti-Microsoft banter and talk of Netscape Constellation eliminating the operating system further forced Microsoft's hand. Following Netscape's lead, Microsoft started a campaign to enter the web browser software market. Like Netscape before them, Microsoft licensed the Mosaic source code from [[Spyglass, Inc.]] ([[University of Illinois]]). Using this basic code, Microsoft created [[Internet Explorer]] (IE).

The war between Microsoft and Netscape dominated the [[Browser Wars]]. Internet Explorer, [[Internet Explorer 1|Version 1.0]] (shipped in the Internet Jumpstart Kit in Microsoft Plus! For [[Windows 95]]&lt;ref name=&quot;History of Internet Explorer&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/windows/WinHistoryIE.mspx History of Internet Explorer]&lt;/ref&gt;) and IE, [[Internet Explorer 2|Version 2.0]] (the first cross platform web browser supporting Windows and [[Mac OS]] &lt;ref name=&quot;History of Internet Explorer&quot;/&gt;) were thought by many to be inferior and primitive when compared to contemporary versions of Netscape Navigator.  With the release of [[Internet Explorer 3|IE version 3.0]] (1996) Microsoft was able to catch up with Netscape competitively, with [[Internet Explorer 4|IE Version 4.0]] (1997) further improving in terms of market share.  [[Internet Explorer 5|IE 5.0]] (1999) improved stability and took significant market share from Netscape Navigator for the first time.

[[Image:Netscape 3 .png|thumb|225px|Netscape 3.04]]

There were two versions of Netscape Navigator 3.0; the Standard Edition and the Gold Edition. The latter consisted of the Navigator browser with e-mail, news readers, and a [[WYSIWYG]] web page compositor;  however these extra functions enlarged and slowed the software, rendering it prone to crashing.  

This Gold Edition was renamed [[Netscape Communicator]] starting with version 4.0; the name change diluted its name-recognition and confused users.  Netscape CEO [[Jim Barksdale]] insisted on the name change because Communicator was a general-purpose ''client'' application, which contained the Navigator ''browser.''  

The aging Netscape Communicator 4.x code was slower than [[Internet Explorer 5.0]]. Typical web pages had become heavily illustrated, often [[JavaScript]]-intensive, and encoded with HTML features designed for specific purposes but now employed as global layout tools (HTML tables, the most obvious example of this, were especially difficult for Communicator to render). The Netscape browser, once a solid product, became [[crash (computing)|crash-prone]] and [[computer bug|buggy]]; for example, some versions re-downloaded an entire web page to re-render it when the browser window was re-sized (a nuisance to dial-up users), and the browser would usually crash when the page contained simple [[Cascading Style Sheets]]. Moreover, Netscape Communicator's browser interface design appeared dated in comparison to Internet Explorer and interface changes in Microsoft and Apple's operating systems.

[[Image:Netscape Navigator.png|thumb|225px|Netscape 4.08]]

At decade's end, Netscape's web browser had lost dominance over the Windows platform. On other computer platforms, it was threatened by open-source browsers, and the August 1997 Microsoft financial agreement to invest one hundred and fifty million dollars in [[Apple Computer|Apple]], requiring that Apple make Internet Explorer the default web browser in new Mac OS distributions. The latest [[Internet Explorer for mac|IE Mac]] release at that time was  '''Internet Explorer version 3.0 for Macintosh''', but Internet Explorer 4 was released later that year.

Microsoft succeeded in having [[Internet service provider|ISPs]] and PC vendors distribute Internet Explorer to their customers instead of Netscape Navigator, mostly due to Microsoft using its leverage from Windows OEM licenses, and partly aided by Microsoft's investment in making IE [[brandable software|brandable]], such that a customized version of IE was offered. Also, web developers used [[proprietary software|proprietary]], browser-specific extensions in web pages.  Both Microsoft and Netscape were found guilty of supporting this, having added many proprietary HTML tags to their browsers, which forced users to choose between two competing and almost incompatible web browsers.

In March 1998, Netscape released most of the [[code base]] for Netscape Communicator under an [[open source license]]. The product, '''[[Netscape 5]]''', used open-source community contributions, and was known as ''[[Mozilla Application Suite|Mozilla]]'', Netscape Navigator's original [[Code name#Commercial code names in the computer industry|code name]]. Netscape programmers gave Mozilla a different GUI, releasing it as Netscape 6 and Netscape 7. After a long public beta test, Mozilla 1.0 was released on 5 June 2002. The same code-base, notably the [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]] [[layout engine]], became the basis of independent applications, including [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]] and [[Mozilla Thunderbird|Thunderbird]].

However, these web browsers took years to yield results. Meanwhile, [[America Online]] had bought Netscape, and released Netscape Navigator 6 from a pre-[[beta test|beta]]-quality form of the Mozilla codebase. This did nothing to win back users, who continued to migrate to Internet Explorer. On 28 December 2007, the Netscape developers announced that AOL had canceled development of Netscape Navigator, leaving it unsupported as of 1 March 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/7270583.stm BBC News Article] retrieved 29th February 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, archived and unsupported versions of the browser remain available for download.

===Release history===
* Mosaic Netscape 0.9 &amp;ndash; October 13, 1994 &lt;!--0.9, 0.94, 0.96 http://web.archive.org/web/19990423023723/browserwatch.internet.com/news/story/bw-news1.html --&gt;
* Netscape Navigator 1.0 &amp;ndash; December 15, 1994
* Netscape Navigator 1.1 &amp;ndash; March 1995
* Netscape Navigator 1.22 &amp;ndash; August 1995
* Netscape Navigator 2.0 &amp;ndash; March 1996&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.holgermetzger.de/Netscape_History.html holgermetzger.de&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Netscape Navigator 2.01 &amp;ndash; March 18, 1996
* Netscape Navigator 2.02
* Netscape Navigator 3.0 &amp;ndash; August 19, 1996
* Netscape Navigator 3.01
* Netscape Navigator 3.02
* Netscape Navigator 3.03
* Netscape Navigator 3.04 &amp;ndash; October 4, 1997&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sillydog.org/narchive/full123.php|title=Netscape Browser Archive Complete List - Early Netscape Section|accessdate=26 Mai 2011|date=2 May 2009|publisher=Sillydog.org|first=Antony|last=Shen}}&lt;/Ref&gt;
* Netscape Navigator 4.0 &amp;ndash; June 1997
* Netscape Navigator 4.01
* Netscape Navigator 4.02
* Netscape Navigator 4.03
* Netscape Navigator 4.04
* Netscape Navigator 4.05
* Netscape Navigator 4.06 &amp;ndash; August 17, 1998
* Netscape Navigator 4.07
* Netscape Navigator 4.08 &amp;ndash; November 9, 1998
* Netscape Navigator 4.78 &amp;ndash; 
* Netscape Navigator 4.79

From version 6 the name became &quot;Netscape&quot; dropping the &quot;Navigator&quot; portion from the title.

* Netscape 6.00
* Netscape 6.01 
* Netscape 6.1
* Netscape 6.2
* Netscape 6.2.1
* Netscape 6.2.2
* Netscape 6.2.3
* Netscape 7.00
* Netscape 7.01
* Netscape 7.02
* Netscape 7.1
* Netscape 7.2
* Netscape 8.0.2
* Netscape 8.0.3.3
* Netscape 8.0.4
* Netscape 8.1
* Netscape 8.1.2
* Netscape 8.1.3

Version 9 is available for Windows, Mac OS X and Linux.

* Netscape 9.0
* Netscape 9.0.0.1
* Netscape 9.0.0.2
* Netscape 9.0.0.3
* Netscape 9.0.0.4
* Netscape 9.0.0.5
* Netscape 9.0.0.6 &amp;ndash; Last Official Release.

As per official announcement: &quot;Official support ended on March 1st, 2008&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://browser.netscape.com/releases|title=Software Releases :: The Netscape Archive}}&lt;/Ref&gt;

==Criticism==
Netscape has been criticized for not meeting then-current web standards, often lagging behind or supporting them very poorly or even incorrectly. This criticism wasn't very loud during the days of its popularity as web designers then often simply developed for Netscape Navigator, but came to be an increasing annoyance to web designers who wish to provide [[backward compatibility]], most often with Netscape Navigator 4 and Netscape Communicator, to their web sites. Today, many web developers simply do not choose to support these old versions, due to their extremely small market share and lack of standardization as well as not being able to run on current machines. {{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

Netscape's own contributions to the web of this sort haven't always been of frustration to web developers. [[JavaScript]] (which has little to do with [[Java (programming language)|Java]]) was, for example, submitted as a new standard to [[Ecma International]], resulting in the [[ECMAScript]] specification. This move allowed it to be more easily supported by multiple web browsers and is today an established [[cross-browser]] scripting language, long after Netscape Navigator itself has dropped in popularity. Another example is the FRAME tag, that is also widely supported today, and even ended up becoming incorporated into official web standards such as the &quot;HTML 4.01 Frameset&quot; specification.

In a 2007 [[PC World (magazine)|PC World]] column, the original Netscape Navigator was considered the &quot;best tech product of all time&quot; due to its impact on the Internet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,130207-page,14-c,technology/article.html PC World - The 50 Best Tech Products of All Time&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Browser timeline]]
* [[Comparison of web browsers]]
* [[List of web browsers]]
* [[Netscape]]
* [[Mosaic (web browser)|Mosaic]]
* [[Mozilla]]
* [[Lou Montulli]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://ps.software.ibm.com/os2fixp/fixnews_a1.html#ns202 Notice for Netscape Navigator 2.02 for OS/2 and Netscape Communicator 4.04 for OS/2 Users]
* [http://www.rigaut.com/benoit/CERN/about/ The hidden features of Netscape Navigator 3.0]
* [http://sillydog.org/narchive/full123.php Netscape Browser Archive - Early Netscape], SillyDog701

{{sequence|
 prev=not available|
 list= Netscape Navigator (1-4.08)|
 next=[[Netscape Communicator]] (4)|
}}
{{gopher clients}}
{{Netscape}}
{{Early web browsers}}

[[Category:Netscape]]
[[Category:Windows web browsers]]
[[Category:Mac OS web browsers]]
[[Category:POSIX web browsers]]
[[Category:Gopher clients]]
[[Category:Discontinued web browsers]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:OS/2 web browsers]]
[[Category:History of web browsers]]

[[ar:نتسكيب نافيجاتور]]
[[ca:Netscape Navigator]]
[[cs:Netscape Navigator]]
[[de:Netscape Navigator]]
[[es:Netscape Navigator]]
[[fr:Netscape Navigator]]
[[gl:Netscape Navigator]]
[[ko:넷스케이프 내비게이터]]
[[id:Netscape Navigator]]
[[ia:Netscape Navigator]]
[[it:Netscape Navigator]]
[[kn:ನೆಟ್‌ಸ್ಕೇಪ್‌ ನ್ಯಾವಿಗೇಟರ್]]
[[lv:Netscape Navigator]]
[[mr:नेटस्केप नॅव्हिगेटर]]
[[nl:Netscape Navigator]]
[[ja:Netscape Navigator (ネットスケープコミュニケーションズ)]]
[[no:Netscape Navigator]]
[[pl:Netscape Navigator]]
[[pt:Netscape Navigator]]
[[ro:Netscape Navigator]]
[[ru:Netscape Navigator]]
[[simple:Netscape Navigator]]
[[sk:Netscape Navigator]]
[[sl:Netscape Navigator]]
[[sv:Netscape (datorprogram)]]
[[ta:நெட்சுகேப் நவிகேட்டர்]]
[[th:เน็ตสเคป แนวิเกเตอร์]]
[[uk:Netscape Navigator]]
[[vi:Netscape Navigator]]
[[zh-yue:Netscape Navigator]]
[[zh:网景导航者]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
