<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21861942" ns="0" title="Irving Brokaw"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox figure skater
|name= Irving Brokaw
|image= Irving Brokaw skater.jpg
|caption=skating
|fullname= Isaac Irving Brokaw
|altname= 
|country= [[United States of America|United States]]
|formercountry=
|birth_date= {{birth date|1870|3|29}}
|birth_place= [[New York, New York]]
|hometown=
|residence= 
|death_date= {{death date and age|1939|3|18|1870|3|29}}
|death_place= [[West Palm Beach, Florida]]
|height= 
|coach= 
|formercoach=
|choreographer=
|formerchoreographer=
|skating club= St. Nicholas Skating Club 
|retired= 
}}
'''Isaac Irving Brokaw''' (March 29, 1871 – March 18, 1939) was an [[United States|American]] [[figure skater]], [[artist]], [[lawyer]], and [[financier]]. He represented the [[United States at the 1908 Summer Olympics]] in [[figure skating at the 1908 Summer Olympics|the figure skating competition]], becoming the first American to compete in a sport included in the Winter Olympic program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |coauthors= |title=Champion Irving Brokaw Tells of Graceful and Skillful Movements on Blades |url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70C16F7385517738DDDA00994DB405B818DF1D3 |quote=Irving Brokaw, the American champion of 1908, predicts that skating in this ... swinging, curved figures, executed while the body assumes a graceful, ... |work=[[New York Times]] |date= March 19, 1911 |accessdate=2010-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After he won an international prize in [[Switzerland]], he brought the [[International style (architecture)|International Style]] of skating back to the United States.&lt;ref name=time/&gt; His book, &quot;Art of Skating&quot; was known as the figure skater's bible.&lt;ref name=time&gt;{{cite news |author= |coauthors= |title=100 Years on Ice |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,932555,00.html#ixzz12v3Z0bzY |quote=Thirty years later, Manhattan Socialite Irving Brokaw, after winning an international prize in Switzerland, brought the International Style of skating back to the U. S. It spread like wildfire after European stars, like the great Charlotte, staged spectacular exhibitions in Manhattan's Hippodrome. ... But nobody — not even the late Irving Brokaw, whose Art of Skating is the figure skater's bible — had ever known the date.

Read more: http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,932555,00.html#ixzz12v5BOulM|work=[[Time magazine]] |date= |accessdate=2010-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life and family==
He was born in [[New York City]] on March 29, 1871 as '''Isaac Irving Brokaw''' to Isaac Vail Brokaw and Elvira Tuttle Gould. He was a member of a wealthy New York City family, his father having founded the [[Brokaw Brothers]] men's clothing stores. His brothers were lawyer and sportsman [[George Tuttle Brokaw]] (whose first wife was Clare Booth, later Luce), Howard Crosby Brokaw, and Frederick Brokaw, who drowned at Elberon, New Jersey, while a student at Princeton. Noted cousins included sportsmen [[William Gould Brokaw]] and Clifford Vail Brokaw, their sisters Florence Brokaw, of Martin Hall, (Mrs. James E. Martin, later Mrs. Preston Pope Satterwhite) and Lilla Brokaw (Mrs. H. Bramhall Gilbert, later Mrs. Cyril Patrick William Francis Radclyffe Dugmore).

On February 4, 1903, Brokaw married Lucile Nave in St. Joseph. Her family co-owned the [[Nave &amp; McCord Mercantile Company]], a chain of wholesale stores in the Midwest. They had three daughters:
*Barbara (Mrs. Leonard Jarvis Cushing)
*Louise, aka Mimi (Mrs. Richard Derby Tucker)
*Lucile (Mrs. James Duane Pell Bishop and later Mrs Rombout van Riemsdyk). She became an artist.[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1070947/2/index.htm#ixzz18YzkY0Xj] Lucile Brokaw was the model for what is considered the first &quot;action&quot; fashion photograph, taken by [[Martin Munkacsi]] and published in [[Harper's Bazaar]] in 1933. In it she appears running down a beach.[http://store.metmuseum.org/posters+prints/martin-munkacsi-lucile-brokaw-piping-rock-beach-long-island-exhibition-poster/invt/80007346/?temp=enlarged&amp;layout=empty]

Irving Brokaw died March 19, 1939, in [[West Palm Beach, Florida]].

==Career==
As a figure skater, Brokaw competed in early national championships in the United States that predated the [[U.S. Figure Skating Championships]] and won the events in 1906 and 1908. He competed at the [[1908 Summer Olympics]] in figure skating, where he [[figure skating at the 1908 Summer Olympics|placed 6th]]. The 1908 Olympics were the first Games in which figure skating was contested. Brokaw became the first American to compete in skating, and by extension any Winter Olympic sport, at the Olympic Games.

He was later elected as an honorary president of the [[U.S. Figure Skating Association]], and made large contributions to skating techniques. 

Brokaw graduated from New York Law School and 1907, but never practiced law as a profession. He was also a well-known artist, and a member of The Salons of America, an art society, and also of the Huguenot Society. 

In the 1910, Brokaw wrote the book &quot;The Art of Skating&quot;, which was referred to as the &quot;figure skater's bible&quot; by [[Time Magazine]]. In 1976, he was posthumously inducted into the [[United States Figure Skating Hall of Fame]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9503EFDC143EE033A2575BC2A9679D946897D6CF Irving Brokaw, Former American Champion, Describes What Is True and &quot;Fake&quot; in This Art of Winter] – New York Times article
* [http://digitalgallery.nypl.org/nypldigital/dgkeysearchdetail.cfm?trg=1&amp;strucID=135925&amp;imageID=101182&amp;word=Ice&amp;s=3&amp;notword=&amp;d=&amp;c=&amp;f=2&amp;k=0&amp;lWord=&amp;lField=&amp;sScope=&amp;sLevel=&amp;sLabel=&amp;total=217&amp;num=0&amp;imgs=20&amp;pNum=&amp;pos=2 Irving Brokaw Skating in Central Park] – New York Public Library
* Collins, Arian, &quot;The Nave Family, Bordertown Publications, San Diego, CA, 2009

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Brokaw, Irving
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =Olympic figure skater, artist, lawyer
| DATE OF BIRTH     = March 29, 1870
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[New York, New York]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = March 18, 1939
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[West Palm Beach, Florida]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Brokaw, Irving}}
[[Category:Olympic figure skaters of the United States]]
[[Category:Figure skaters at the 1908 Summer Olympics]]
[[Category:American male single skaters]]
[[Category:1871 births]]
[[Category:1937 deaths]]
[[Category:People from New York City]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
