<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="William Marshal, first Earl of Pembroke" to="William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="70728" ns="0" title="William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=April 2011}}
[[File:William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke.jpg|thumb|200px|Effigy above the tomb of  '''William Marshal''' in [[Temple Church]], London]]
[[File:Temple church 905.jpg|thumb|200px|Effigy above the tomb of  '''William Marshal''' in [[Temple Church]], London]]

'''Sir William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke''' (1147 – 14 May 1219), also called '''William the Marshal''' (Guillaume le Maréchal), was an Anglo-Norman soldier and statesman. He was described as the &quot;greatest [[knight]] that ever lived&quot; by [[Stephen Langton]].  He served four kings — [[Henry II of England|Henry II]], [[Richard I of England|Richard the Lionheart]], [[John of England|John]] and [[Henry III of England|Henry III]] — and rose from obscurity to become a [[regent]] of England for the last of the four, and so one of the most powerful men in Europe.  Before him, the hereditary title of &quot;[[Marshal]]&quot; designated head of household security for the king of England; by the time he died, people throughout Europe (not just England) referred to him simply as &quot;the Marshal&quot;.

==Early life==
William's father, [[John Marshal (Earl Marshal)|John Marshal]], had been a supporter of [[Stephen of England|King Stephen]], who took the throne in 1135, but took the part of the [[Empress Matilda]] in the ensuing [[civil war]] of succession between her and Stephen that led to the collapse of England in 1139 into [[The Anarchy| &quot;the Anarchy&quot;]]. 

When King Stephen besieged [[Newbury Castle]] in 1152, according to William's biographer, he used the young William as a hostage to ensure that John kept his promise to surrender the castle. John, however, used the time allotted to reinforce the castle and alert Matilda's forces. When Stephen ordered John to surrender immediately or watch as he hanged William in front of the castle John replied that he should go ahead saying, &quot;I still have the hammer and the anvil with which to forge still more and better sons!&quot; Fortunately for the child, Stephen could not bring himself to hang young William.

==Knight-Errant==
[[Image:Matthew Paris - William Marshal.jpg|thumb|350px|William Marshal was the greatest jouster of his age.  From [[Matthew Paris]]'s ''Chronica Major'', Marshal unhorses Baldwin de Guisnes.]]
As a younger son of a minor nobleman, William had no lands or fortune to inherit, and had to make his own way in life.  Around the age of twelve, when his father's career was faltering, he was sent to Normandy to be brought up in the household of William de [[Tancarville]], a great magnate and cousin of young William's mother.  Here he began his training as a knight.  He was knighted in 1166 on campaign in Upper Normandy, then being invaded from Flanders.  His first experience of warfare was not a great success.  He failed to take advantage of the knights he had managed to overcome in the street skirmish at [[Neufchâtel-en-Bray]]. In 1167 he was taken by William de Tancarville to his first tournament where he found his true métier.  Quitting the Tancarville household he then served in the household of his mother's brother, [[Patrick of Salisbury, 1st Earl of Salisbury|Patrick]], [[Earl of Salisbury]].  In 1168 his uncle was killed in an ambush by [[Guy de Lusignan]].  William was injured and captured in the same skirmish. It is known that William received a wound to his thigh and that someone in his captor's household took pity on the young knight. He received a loaf of bread in which were concealed several lengths of clean linen bandages with which he could dress his wounds. This act of kindness by an unknown person perhaps saved Marshal's life as infection setting into the wound could surely have killed him. After a period of time, he was ransomed by [[Eleanor of Aquitaine]], who was apparently impressed by tales of his bravery.  Thereafter he found he could make a good living out of winning [[Tournament (medieval)|tournaments]].  At that time tournaments were dangerous, often deadly, staged battles, not the jousting contests that would come later, and money and valuable prizes could be won by capturing and ransoming opponents, their horses and armour.  His record is legendary: on his deathbed he recalled besting 500 knights during his tourneying career.

==William Marshal and the Young King Henry==
The Marshal's career entered a new phase in 1170 when he was appointed to the household of [[Henry the Young King]], eldest surviving son of Eleanor and her second husband [[Henry II of England]], crowned that year as associate king to his father.  William was intended to be the boy's tutor-in-arms, but became his mentor and idol.  He infected the boy with his passion for the tournament, and for the next twelve years he was the Young King's constant companion and tournament team manager.  He followed the Young King in his abortive rebellion against his father in 1173–74, and William makes his first appearance in the historical record in a list of rebels compiled by the clerks of Henry II.  William is alleged by his biographer to have knighted his young master during the course of the rebellion, but we know from other sources that Young Henry had in fact been knighted by his father before his coronation in 1170.

Between 1174, when Henry was reconciled to his father, and 1182, William led his master's Anglo-Norman team in all the major tournaments of the day, especially frequenting the huge international meetings in Picardy.  His job was to devise tactics and during the course of the tournament to act as minder to the Young King, to make sure he avoided the embarrassment of capture.  By the time of the French state tournament of 1179 at [[Lagny-sur-Marne]], held to celebrate the coronation of [[Philip II of France]], William Marshal was sufficiently wealthy to raise his own banner over his own company of knights.  He was also by then subject to the envy and conspiracy of rivals at the Young King's court.  In 1182 they engineered his downfall, by claiming that Marshal was more interested in profiting from tournaments than protecting his lord.  There were also accusations of disrespect to the king in his choice of warcry for his company ('God aids the Marshal') and the way his men trumpeted his fame above the king's.  His biographer attempts to deflect these serious charges by his enemies, by adding to them the preposterous charge that William Marshal had seduced the king's wife.  He was treated coldly by the king, until fed up by the insults, Marshal left to join the tournament team of the Young King's rival and cousin [[Philip of Flanders]].  He was however recalled to the Young King's household following the king's second rebellion against his father, and was at his side when Henry died of [[dysentery]] near [[Limoges]] on 11 June 1183.  The Marshal undertook to complete the crusade vow his dead master had made, and took his cloak stitched with the cross to Jerusalem, with the approval of the bereaved father, Henry II.

==Royal favour==
Upon his return during the course of 1185 William rejoined the court of King Henry II, and now served the father as a loyal captain through the many difficulties of his final years.  The returns of royal favour were almost immediate.  The king gave William the large royal estate of [[Cartmel]] in Cumbria, and the keeping of Heloise, the heiress of the northern barony of Lancaster.  It may be that the king expected him to take the opportunity to marry her and become a northern baron, but William seems to have had grander ambitions for his marriage.  In 1188 faced with an attempt by Philip II to seize the disputed region of Berry, Henry II summoned the Marshal to his side.  The letter by which he did this survives, and makes some sarcastic comments about William's complaints that he had not been properly rewarded to date for his service to the king.  Henry therefore promised him the marriage and lands of Dionisia, lady of [[Châteauroux]] in Berry.  In the resulting campaign, the king fell out with his heir [[Richard I of England|Richard]], count of Poitou, who consequently allied with Philip II against his father.  In 1189, while covering the flight of Henry II from [[Le Mans]] to [[Chinon]], William unhorsed the undutiful Richard in a skirmish. William could have killed the prince but killed his horse instead, to make that point clear. He is said to have been the only man ever to unhorse Richard. Nonetheless after Henry's death, Marshal was welcomed at court by his former adversary, now King Richard I, who was not foolish enough to exclude a man whose legendary loyalty and military accomplishments were too useful to ignore, especially in a king who was intending to go on Crusade.

During the old king's last days he had promised the Marshal the hand and estates of [[Isabel de Clare, 4th Countess of Pembroke|Isabel de Clare]] (c.1172–1220), but had not completed the arrangements.  King Richard however, confirmed the offer and so in August 1189, at the age of 43, the Marshal married the 17-year-old daughter of [[Richard de Clare, 2nd Earl of Pembroke|Richard de Clare]] (Strongbow). Her father had been [[Earl of Pembroke]], and Marshal acquired large estates and claims in England, Wales, [[Normandy]] and Ireland.  Some estates however were excluded from the deal.  Marshal did not obtain Pembroke and the title of earl, which his father-in-law had enjoyed, until 1199, as it had been taken into the king's hand in 1154.  However, the marriage transformed the landless knight from a minor family into one of the richest men in the kingdom, a sign of his power and prestige at court.  They had five sons and five daughters, and have numerous descendants (see below).  William made numerous improvements to his wife's lands, including extensive additions to [[Pembroke Castle]] and [[Chepstow Castle]].

William was included in the council of regency which the King appointed on his departure for the [[Third Crusade]] in 1190. He took the side of John, the king's brother, when the latter expelled the justiciar, [[William Longchamp]], from the kingdom, but he soon discovered that the interests of John were different from those of Richard. Hence in 1193 he joined with the loyalists in making war upon him. In spring 1194, during the course of the hostilities in England, before King Richard's return, William Marshal's elder brother John Marshal was killed defending Marlborough for John, whose seneschal he was.  Richard allowed Marshal to succeed his brother in the hereditary [[Earl Marshal|marshalship]], and his paternal honour of [[Hamstead Marshall]].  The Marshal served the king in his wars in Normandy against Philip II.  On Richard's death-bed the king designated Marshal as custodian of [[Rouen]] and of the royal treasure during the interregnum.

==King John and Magna Carta==
[[File:BitvaLincoln1217ortho.jpg|thumb|300px|A 13th-century depiction of the Second Battle of Lincoln, which occurred at Lincoln Castle on 20 May 1217 during the First Barons' War between the forces of the future Louis VIII of France and those of King Henry III of England. Louis' forces were attacked by a relief force under the command of William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke. Thomas du Perche, the Comte de la Perche, who was commanding the French troops, was killed; the illustration depicts his death. Perche had come to England to try and recover the honour of Perche which had been lost in 1204 by his mother (a niece of John, King of England) – this included Newbury and Shrivenham in Berkshire, Toddington in Buckinghamshire, and Haughley in Suffolk. This heavy defeat led to Louis being expelled from his base in the southeast of England.]]
William supported King John when he became king in 1199, arguing against those who maintained the claims of [[Arthur of Brittany]], the teenage son of John's elder brother [[Geoffrey II, Duke of Brittany|Geoffrey Plantagenet]].  William was heavily engaged with the defence of Normandy against the growing pressure of the Capetian armies between 1200 and 1203.  He sailed with King John when he abandoned the duchy in December 1203.  He and the king had a falling out in the aftermath of the loss of the duchy, when he was sent with the earl of Leicester as  ambassadors to negotiate a truce with King [[Philip II of France]] in 1204.  The Marshal took the opportunity to negotiate the continued possession of his Norman lands.  When William [[Commendation ceremony|paid homage]] to King Philip, John took offence and there was a major row at court which led to cool relations between the two men. This became outright hostility in 1207 when John began to move against several major Irish magnates, including William.  Though he left for [[Leinster]] in 1207 William was recalled and humiliated at court in the autumn of 1208, while John's [[justiciar]] in Ireland [[Meilyr fitz Henry]] invaded his lands, burning the town of [[New Ross]].  Meilyr's defeat by Countess Isabel led to her husband's return to Leinster.  He was once again in conflict with King John in his war with the Braose and Lacy families in 1210, but managed to survive.  He stayed in Ireland until 1213, during which time he had [[Carlow Castle]] erected&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Carlow Castle | work=Carlow Town.com | url=http://www.carlowtown.com/info_tosee.asp | accessdate=9 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; and restructured his honour of Leinster.  Taken back into favour in 1212, he was summoned in 1213 to return to the English court. Despite their differences, William remained loyal throughout the hostilities between John and his barons which culminated on 15 June 1215 at [[Runnymede]] with the sealing of [[Magna Carta]].  William was one of the few English earls to remain loyal to the king through the [[First Barons' War]].  It was William whom King John trusted on his deathbed to make sure John's nine-year-old son Henry would get the throne.  It was William who took responsibility for the king's funeral and burial at [[Worcester Cathedral]].

On 11 November 1216 at [[Gloucester]], upon the death of King John, William Marshal was named by the king's council (the chief barons who had remained loyal to King John in the [[First Barons' War]]) to serve as protector of the nine year old [[Henry III of England|King Henry III]], and regent of the kingdom. In spite of his advanced age (around 70) he prosecuted the war against [[Louis VIII of France|Prince Louis]] and the rebel barons with remarkable energy. In the [[Battle of Lincoln (1217)|battle of Lincoln]] he charged and fought at the head of the young King's army, leading them to victory.  He was preparing to besiege Louis in London when the war was terminated by [[Battle of Dover (1217)|the naval victory]] of [[Hubert de Burgh, 1st Earl of Kent|Hubert de Burgh]] in the straits of Dover. William was criticised for the generosity of the terms he accorded to Louis and the rebels in September 1217; but his desire for an expeditious settlement was dictated by sound statesmanship. Self-restraint and compromise were the keynote of Marshal's policy, hoping to secure peace and stability for his young liege. Both before and after the peace of 1217 he reissued Magna Carta, in which he is a signatory as one of the witnessing barons.  Without his prestige the Angevin dynasty might not have survived the disastrous reign of John; where the French and the rebels would not trust the English king's word, they would trust William.

==Death and legacy==
[[Image:Templechurch.jpg|thumb|300px|right|William Marshal was interred in [[Temple Church]], London]]
Marshal's health finally failed him early in 1219. In March 1219 he realised that he was dying, so he summoned his eldest son, also William, and his household knights, and left the [[Tower of London]] for his estate at [[Caversham, Berkshire|Caversham]] in Berkshire, near [[Reading, Berkshire|Reading]], where he called a meeting of the barons, Henry III, the papal legate [[Pandulf Masca]], the royal justiciar ([[Hubert de Burgh]]), and [[Peter des Roches]] (Bishop of Winchester and the young King's guardian).  William rejected the Bishop's claim to the regency and entrusted the regency to the care of the papal legate; he apparently did not trust the Bishop or any of the other magnates that he had gathered to this meeting.  Fulfilling the vow he had made while on crusade, he was invested into the order of the [[Knights Templar]] on his deathbed.  He died on 14 May 1219 at Caversham, and was buried in the [[Temple Church]] in London, where his effigy can still be seen.

After his death, his eldest son, also named William, commissioned a biography of his father to be written called ''[[L'Histoire de Guillaume le Marechal]]''.  This book, written so soon after his death, has preserved (and probably enhanced) the legend of William Marshal for posterity.  While his knightly achievements may be debatable, there is no doubt of his impact on the history and politics of England, from his stalwart defence of the realm to his support of the Magna Carta.

==Descendants of William Marshal &amp; Isabel de Clare==
#[[William Marshal, 2nd Earl of Pembroke]] (1190–6 April 1231), married (1) Alice de [[Béthune]], daughter of [[Duke of Albemarle|Earl of Albemarle]]; (2) 23 April 1224 [[Eleanor of Leicester|Eleanor Plantagenet]], daughter of King [[John of England]]. They had no children.
#[[Richard Marshal, 3rd Earl of Pembroke]]  (1191–16 April 1234), married Gervase le Dinant.  He died in captivity. They had no children.
#[[Maud Marshal]] (1194–27 March 1248), married (1) [[Hugh Bigod, 3rd Earl of Norfolk]], they had four children; (2) [[William de Warenne, 5th Earl of Surrey]], they had two children; (3) Walter de Dunstanville.
#[[Gilbert Marshal, 4th Earl of Pembroke]] (1197–27 June 1241), married (1) Marjorie of Scotland, youngest daughter of King [[William I of Scotland]]; by an unknown mistress he had one illegitimate daughter:
##Isabel Marshal, married to [[Rhys ap Maeldon Fychan]].
#[[Walter Marshal, 5th Earl of Pembroke]] (c. 1199–November 1245), married [[Margaret de Quincy, Countess of Lincoln]], granddaughter of [[Hugh de Kevelioc, 3rd Earl of Chester]]. No children.
#[[Isabel Marshal]] (9 October 1200–17 January 1240), married (1) [[Gilbert de Clare, 5th Earl of Hertford]], whose daughter [[Isabel de Clare]] married [[Robert Bruce, 5th Lord of Annandale]], the grandfather of [[Robert I of Scotland|Robert the Bruce]]; (2) [[Richard, Earl of Cornwall|Richard Plantagenet, Earl of Cornwall]]
#Sibyl Marshal (c. 1201–27 April 1245), married [[William de Ferrers, 5th Earl of Derby]]–they had seven daughters.
## Agnes Ferrers (died 11 May 1290), married William de Vesci.
## Isabel Ferrers (died before 26 November 1260)
## Maud Ferrers (died 12 March 1298)
## Sibyl Ferrers, married Sir Francis or Franco de Bohun.
## Joan Ferrers (died 1267)
## Agatha Ferrers (died May 1306), married Hugh Mortimer, of [[Chelmarsh]].
## Eleanor Ferrers (died 16 October 1274), married to:
#[[Eva Marshal]] (1203–1246), married [[William de Braose (died 1230)|William de Braose, Lord of Abergavenny]]
## [[Isabella de Braose]] (b.1222), married Prince [[Dafydd ap Llywelyn]]. She died childless.
##   [[Maud de Braose, Baroness Wigmore|Maud de Braose]] (1224–1301), in 1247, she married [[Roger Mortimer, 1st Baron Wigmore]] and they had descendants.
##   Eve de Braose (1227- 28 July 1255), married Sir William de Cantelou and had descendants.
##   [[Eleanor de Braose]] (c.1228- 1251). On an unknown date after August 1241, she married Sir Humphrey de Bohun and had descendants.
#[[Anselm Marshal, 6th Earl of Pembroke]] (c. 1208–22 December 1245), married Maud de Bohun, daughter of [[Humphrey de Bohun, 2nd Earl of Hereford]]. They had no children.
#Joan Marshal (1210–1234), married Warin de Munchensi (d. 1255), Lord of [[Swanscombe]]
##[[Joan de Munchensi]] (1230–20 September 1307) married [[William de Valence, 1st Earl of Pembroke|William of Valence]], the fourth son of [[John of England|King John]]'s widow, [[Isabella of Angoulême]], and her second husband, [[Hugh X of Lusignan]], [[Count of La Marche]]. de Valence was half-brother to [[Henry III of England|Henry III]] and [[Edward I of England|Edward I]]'s uncle.

===The Fate of the Marshal Family===
During the civil wars in Ireland, William had taken two manors that the [[Bishop of Ferns]] claimed but could not get back. Some years after William's death, that bishop is said{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} to have laid a curse on the family that William's sons would have no children, and the great Marshal estates would be scattered.  Each of William's sons did become earl of Pembroke and marshal of England, and each died without issue.  William's vast holdings were then divided among the husbands of his five daughters.  The title of &quot;Marshal&quot; went to the husband of the oldest daughter, [[Hugh Bigod, 3rd Earl of Norfolk]], and later passed to the Mowbray [[Duke of Norfolk|dukes of Norfolk]] and then to the Howard dukes of Norfolk, becoming &quot;Earl Marshal&quot; along the way.  The title of &quot;Earl of Pembroke&quot; passed to [[William de Valence, 1st Earl of Pembroke|William of Valence]], the husband of Joan Marshal's daughter, [[Joan de Munchensi]]; he became the first of the [[List of earls of Pembroke|de Valence line of earls of Pembroke]].

==William Marshal in fiction==
{{Cleanup|section|date=November 2010}}
* William is the central figure in the Anglo-Norman History of William Marshal.&lt;ref&gt;&lt;em&gt;History of William Marshal&lt;/em&gt;, ed. A.J. Holden, S. Gregory &amp; D. Crouch, 3 vols., ANTS Occasional Publications 4-6 (London: [[Anglo-Norman Text Society]], 2002-6)&lt;/ref&gt;
* William appears (named only as the [[Earl of Pembroke]]) in [[William Shakespeare]]'s historical play ''[[The Life and Death of King John|King John]]''.
* William Marshal is a central character in the traditional English ballad &quot;[[Queen Elanor's Confession]]&quot; ([[Child Ballads|Child]] 156), in which he is (fictitiously) revealed to have seduced [[Eleanor of Aquitaine]] while escorting her to England.
* Four generations of the Marshal family, from Isabel de Clare's parents through William fitzWilliam's fictitious bastard son, are the subjects of a series of four historical romances by [[Mary Pershall]].  ''Dawn of the White Rose'' (1985) is the one about William Marshal and Isabel de Clare.
* William Marshal also appears as a supporting character in [[Thomas B. Costain]]'s out of print novel ''Below the Salt'', and [[Sharon Kay Penman]]'s novels ''Time and Chance'' and ''Devil's Brood'', as well as a minor appearance in Penman's ''When Christ and His Saints Slept'', illustrating the story about young William's time as King Stephan's hostage and John Marshal's defiance.
* William Marshal makes appearance in [[James Blish]]'s historical novel, ''[[Doctor Mirabilis]]''. He appears at the Convocation at Westminster, and in absentia on his temporary break with Henry III. Blish himself acknowledges the historicity of Marshall, and further notes that in the company of [[Sir Miles Bonecor]] that they appear &quot;...as martial spear carriers in this account...&quot;. Ultimately, William is merely a figure present in the plot as opposed to a significant mover of events within this particular novel.
* William Marshal is the main character of the novel ''A Pride of Kings'' by Juliet Dymoke, published by the New English Library in 1978.
* William Marshal is a significant secondary character in the novel ''The Witch Hunter'' by [[Bernard Knight]], in the author's [[Crowner John Mysteries|John Crowner]] medieval mystery series, published in 2004.
* A new novel about William Marshal, ''The Greatest Knight'' by [[Elizabeth Chadwick]], based on primary sources and the main secondary source biographies of professors Painter, Duby and Crouch was published by Time Warner Books on 3 November 2005.  A sequel, ''The Scarlet Lion'' followed in 2006.  As one of the prominent historical figures of the period, Marshal also appears as a minor character in several of her other novels set around the same time.
* In film, Marshal makes a minor appearance in 1968's ''[[The Lion in Winter (1968 film)|The Lion in Winter]]'', portrayed by [[Nigel Stock (actor)|Nigel Stock]]. [[Clive Wood]] portrays Marshal in the [[The Lion in Winter (2003 film)|2003 remake]].
* Many events in William Marshal's life were incorporated into the 2001 film ''[[A Knight's Tale (film)|A Knight's Tale]]''.
* Another novel about William and his wife is ''Champion'' (in German &quot;Der Ritter der Könige) from Christian Balling of the year 1988.
* William Marshal is a major character in the novels ''The Devil is Loose'' and its sequel, ''Wolf at the Door'' by [[Graham Shelby]]. The books are about Richard Lionheart and King John, and are historical fictions about the events after the death of Henry II and the fall of the Angevin Empire.
* William Marshal also has 2 appearances in the historical romance novels &quot;The Falcon and the Flower&quot; and &quot;The Dragon and the Jewel&quot; by author [[Virginia Henley]].
* He is a major character in [[Sharon Penman]]'s 'Devil's Brood'.
* He is a major character in [[Mike Walker (radio dramatist)|Mike Walker]]'s [[BBC Radio 4]] series of plays ''[[Plantagenet]]'' and is played by [[Stephen Hogan]].
* William Marshal is a major character in [[Ridley Scott|Sir Ridley Scott's]] [[Robin Hood (2010 film)|Robin Hood]] epic who tries to convince King John to agree to the Magna Carta. He is played by [[William Hurt]].
* William Marshal is also a key character in Christopher Morley's new play ''The King's Disposition''.
* Peter Robert's radio play ''Holy Fool'' is about William Marshal (played by William Chubb) narrated by his squire (played by [[Michael Williams (actor)|Michael Williams]]).
* A character named &quot;Marshal&quot; (played by [[James Purefoy]]), based loosely on the historical William Marshal, is the central character in the 2011 film ''[[Ironclad (film)|Ironclad]]''.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*Paul Meyer, ''L'Histoire de Guillaume le Maréchal'' (Paris:  [[Société de l'histoire de France]], 1891–1901), with partial translation of the original sources into [[Modern French]].  Edition and English translation, ''History of William Marshal'', ed. A.J. Holden and D. Crouch, trans. S. Gregory (3 vols, Anglo-Norman Text Society, Occasional Publication Series, 4–6, 2002–2007).
*Sidney Painter, ''William Marshal,  Knight-Errant, Baron, and Regent of England'' (Baltimore:  Johns Hopkins Press, 1933; reprint  Toronto:  University of Toronto Press, 1982).
*Georges Duby, ''William Marshal, the Flower of Chivalry'' (New York:  Pantheon, 1985).
*[[David Crouch (historian)|David Crouch]], ''William Marshal: Knighthood, War and Chivalry, 1147–1219'' (2n edn, London: Longman, 2002). A healthy corrective to Duby's excessive reliance on the ''Histoire''.
*John Gillingham, 'War and Chivalry in the History of William the Marshal' in ''Thirteenth Century England'' II ed. P.R. Coss and S.D. Lloyd (Woodbridge, 1988) 1–13.
*Larry D. Benson, 'The Tournament in the romances of Chrétien de Troyes and L'Histoire de Guillaume le Maréchal' in ''Studies in Medieval Culture'' XIV 1980 1–24.
*David Crouch, &quot;Biography as Propaganda in the 'History of William Marshal&quot;, in'' Convaincre et persuader: Communication et propagande aux XII et XIIIe siècles''. Ed. par Martin Aurell. Poitiers: Université de Poitiers-centre d'études supérieures de civilisation médiévale, 2007.

==External links==
{{Commons|William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke|William Marshal, 1st Earl of Pembroke}}
*WilliamMarshal.com, [http://www.williammarshal.com the History of William Marshall]
*[http://www.castlewales.com/marshall.html William Marshall at Castlewales.com]
*Abels, Richard, [http://www.medievalgenealogy.org.uk/families/marshal/williammarshal.shtml William Marshal—Events in Life and Historical Context]


{{S-start}}
{{S-reg|en}}
{{Succession box| title=[[Earl of Pembroke]] | before=New Creation | after=[[William Marshal, 2nd Earl of Pembroke|William Marshal]] | years=1199–1219}}
{{S-hon}}
{{Succession box| title=[[Earl Marshal|Lord Marshal]] | before=[[John Marshal (Earl Marshal)|John Marshal]] | after=[[William Marshal, 2nd Earl of Pembroke|William Marshal]] | years=1199–1219}}
{{S-end}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
|NAME= Pembroke, William Marshal, 1st Earl Of
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=
|DATE OF BIRTH= 1146
|PLACE OF BIRTH=
|DATE OF DEATH= 14 May 1219
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pembroke, William Marshal, 1st Earl Of}}
[[Category:1146 births]]
[[Category:1219 deaths]]
[[Category:Earls Marshal]]
[[Category:Anglo-Normans]]
[[Category:Anglo-Normans in Wales]]
[[Category:Anglo-Normans in Ireland]]
[[Category:Earls in the Peerage of England]]
[[Category:Earls of Pembroke (1189)|William]]
[[Category:English soldiers]]
[[Category:Marshals of England]]
[[Category:People from Caversham]]
[[Category:People from Hamstead Marshall]]
[[Category:People from Marlborough]]
[[Category:People from Newbury, Berkshire]]
[[Category:Regents of England]]
[[Category:13th-century viceregal rulers]]
[[Category:Regents]]

{{Link FA|it}}

[[cs:Vilém Maréchal]]
[[cy:William Marshal, Iarll 1af Penfro]]
[[de:William Marshal, 1. Earl of Pembroke]]
[[et:William Marshal]]
[[es:William Marshal (1146-1219)]]
[[eo:Vilhelmo Marshal (1-a grafo de Pembroke)]]
[[fr:Guillaume le Maréchal]]
[[it:Guglielmo il Maresciallo]]
[[he:ויליאם מרשל]]
[[la:Guillelmus Marescallus]]
[[ms:William Marshal, Earl dari Pembroke Pertama]]
[[nl:Willem de Maarschalk]]
[[ja:ウィリアム・マーシャル (初代ペンブルック伯)]]
[[no:William Marshal, 1. jarl av Pembroke]]
[[pl:William Marshal]]
[[pt:Guilherme Marechal, 1.º Conde de Pembroke]]
[[ru:Уильям Маршал, 1-й граф Пембрук]]
[[sv:William Marshal, 1:e earl av Pembroke]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
