<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2191002" ns="0" title="Egyptian presidential election, 2005"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Update|date=March 2010}}
{{Infobox Election
|election_name      = Egyptian presidential election, 2005
|country            = Egypt
|type               = presidential
|ongoing            = no
|previous_election  = Egyptian_presidential_confirmation_referendum,_1999
|previous_year      = 1999
|next_election      = Egyptian presidential election, 2012
|next_year          = 2012
|election_date      = September 7, 2005
|colour1 = 3b9c9c
|image1 = [[Image:Hosni Mubarak ritratto.jpg|160px]] 
|nominee1 = [[Hosni Mubarak]]
|party1 = National Democratic Party (Egypt)
|popular_vote1 = 6,316,714 
|percentage1 = 88.6%
|colour2 = f88017
|image2 =[[File:Ayman Noor.jpg|200px]]
|nominee2 = [[Ayman Nour]]
|party2 = Tomorrow Party
|popular_vote2 = 540,405 
|percentage2 = 7.3%
|title = President
|before_election = [[Hosni Mubarak]]
|before_party = National Democratic Party (Egypt)
|after_election = [[Hosni Mubarak]]
|after_party = National Democratic Party (Egypt)
}}
{{Politics of Egypt}}

The '''Egyptian presidential election of 2005''', held on September 7, 2005, was the first allegedly contested presidential election in [[Egypt]]'s history. [[Hosni Mubarak]], the [[former]] [[Rulers and heads of state of Egypt|President of Egypt]], won a fifth consecutive six-year term in office, with official results showing he won 88.6% of the vote. Mubarak's opponent, [[Ayman Nour]], of the [[Tomorrow Party]], is estimated to have received 7.3% of the vote and [[Numan Gumaa]] received 2.8%, however, Nur claimed that prior polling results showed over 30%. Criticism of the election process has cenetred on the process of selecting the eligible candidates, and on alleged election-law violations during voting. Mubarak was sworn in for his new term on September 27.

__TOC__
The election was the first-ever [[Multi-party system|multi-party]] election in the history of Hosni Mubarak's authoritarian rule. Ten parties were set to take part; the leading candidates were:  
*[[Hosni Mubarak]] of the [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]]
*[[Numan Gumaa]] of the [[New Wafd Party]]
*[[Ayman Nour]] of the [[Tomorrow Party]]
Also contending are:
*[[Osama Shaltut]] of the [[Solidarity Party (Egypt)|Solidarity Party]]
*[[Ibrahim Turk]] of the [[Democratic Union Party (Egypt)|Democratic Union Party]]
*[[Ahmad al-Sabahi]] of the [[Umma Party (Egypt)|Umma Party]]
*[[Rifaat al-Agrudi]] of the [[National Conciliation Party (Egypt)|National Conciliation Party]]
*[[Fawzi Ghaza]] of the [[Egypt 2000 Party]]
*[[Mamduh Qinawi]] of the [[Free Social Constitutional Party|Constitutional Party]]
*[[Wahid al-Uqsuri]] of the [[Egyptian Arab Socialist Party]] (disqualified on September 3)

==Change from Referendum on Mubarak's Rule==

Until recently, [[Egyptians]] have only been able to approve or reject a candidate appointed by [[Parliament of Egypt|parliament]], which is dominated by [[Hosni Mubarak|Hosni Mubarak's]] [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|NDP]].  

Mubarak had been re-elected four times during his 24-year rule by such a [[referendum]].  Mubarak won the 1999 referendum with almost 94% of the vote, though turnout was probably around 10%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/work/feeds/afx/2005/09/08/afx2212162.html Opposition claims massive fraud in Egypt electoral poll - Forbes.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

A constitutional amendment approved in a referendum in May 2005 opened the way for multi-candidate presidential elections.

==2005 Presidential Election Process==

Under Egyptian [[election law]], all Egyptians over age eighteen are required to vote.  However, out of a population of approximately 77,500,000 (the largest in the Arab world), only about 32 million voters were registered (approximately 40% of the total population).

Under the election law, parties proposed candidates for the election, which were reviewed by the Presidential [[Election Commission (Egypt)|Election Commission]].  Of the 30 proposed candidates, only 10 were allowed to participate in the presidential election by the Presidential Election Commission.  One prominent candidate not allowed to run was [[Talaat Sadat]], the nephew of former President [[Anwar Sadat]], who appealed his disqualification unsuccessfully.

Egypt's largest [[Islam]]ic group, the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], was not permitted to field a candidate for the election because the organization is banned by the government, which prohibits political parties with a stated religious agenda. The Brotherhood has not backed any of the other candidates, but they encouraged Egyptians to go to the polls and vote for anyone other than Mubarak. 

The election campaign kicked off on August 17, 2005 and lasted until September 4, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4158232.stm BBC NEWS | Middle East | Egypt election campaigning begins&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; While many believed Hosni Mubarak's re-election a foregone conclusion, he campaigned seriously, trying to win votes across Egypt.

9,865 [[polling station|polling places]] were open until 10:00 p.m. Wednesday, September 7, so that voters could cast their ballots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofoman.com/newsdetails.asp?newsid=19559 Times of Oman&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Full results were not expected until at least Thursday September 8.

The election was overseen by Egyptian judges.  No international monitors were allowed to oversee the election.

According to a late August report by the [[Cairo Institute for Human Rights Studies]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cihrs.org/PDF/interim_report_EN.pdf Untitled Page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; media coverage was biased in favour of Hosni Mubarak.

If no candidate had received 50% of the vote, the top two candidates would have contested a second election scheduled for September 17.

==Criticisms of the 2005 Presidential Election Arrangements==

Some of the main legal opposition parties, including the leftist Tagammu Party and the Nasserist Party, [[election boycott|boycotted the election]], saying it is unlikely to be free or fair. Those opposing the election say the electoral reforms have not gone far enough because the election regulations severely restrict independent candidates and overwhelmingly favour the NDP.  

Secondly, the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], believed to be the most popular opposition group in Egypt, was excluded from running in the elections because Mubarak's government has made it officially illegal and barred from major political processes. Supporters of the Brotherhood and other opposition parties state that this undermines the credibility of the election.

In addition, there appeared to be official harassment of the leading opposition candidate Nour, who was stripped of his parliamentary immunity and arrested on January 2005, on what many observers regarded as trumped-up charges.  He was imprisoned for a short time that year before public and international outcry resulted in his release before trial.

The [[New Wafd Party]] and the [[Tomorrow Party|Tomorrow (Ghad) Party]] contested the election even though they had opposed the May 2005 constitutional referendum, and their respective candidates, [[Numan Gumaa]] and [[Ayman Nour]], drew significant support -- Nour won 12% and Gumaa won 5-7%.

==Results==

Media reports on September 8, based on anonymous statements from election commission officials, stated that preliminary results showed President [[Hosni Mubarak]] winning 78% - 80%&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/09/08/world/main828234.shtml Mubarak Wins Egypt Vote - CBS News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; of the vote and [[Ayman Nour]] winning 12%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20050908.wegypt0908/BNStory/International/ This page is available to GlobePlus subscribers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Gumaa was reported as receiving 5-7%.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.arabnews.com/?page=4&amp;section=0&amp;article=69756&amp;d=9&amp;m=9&amp;y=2005 Panel Rejects Nour’s Charge of Vote Fraud&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Late reports from September 8 placed Mubarak's numbers at approximately 72%, based once again on anonymous sources.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20050908/wl_nm/egypt_elections_dc] {{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The official result, that Mubarak won the election with 88.6% of the vote, was announced on September 9, 2005. Detailed results, with results and voting breakdowns by province for 15 of the 26 provinces (not including the largest provinces), were published in Al-Ahram, a state newspaper.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20050909/wl_nm/egypt_elections_dc] {{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same source states that Nour won 6.2% in the 15 provinces, 20% in the Nile delta province of Buheira, and 16% in Alexandria.

{{Egyptian presidential election, 2005}}

===Nour Demands Rerun of Election===

Following widespread reports of election law violations, Nour immediately demanded a rerun of the election.  However, the [[Election Commission (Egypt)|Presidential Election Commission]] rejected his request as baseless on September 8, 2005, a decision that cannot be appealed.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt; Nour's campaign manager, Wael Nawara, noted the Nour camp's surprise that the Presidential Election Commission would reject Nour's claims &quot;despite the coverage from the media and the repetitive nature of these complaints.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;

===Long-Term Impact of the Election===

While the result of the election appears to be a Mubarak victory, as many expected, another result many noted was a step toward democratization in Egypt, even if it had been marred by irregularities.

===International Reaction===
[[Saudi Arabia|Saudi]] Foreign Minister Prince [[Saud bin Faisal bin Abdul Aziz|Saud al-Faisal]] stated that the elections show that Mubarak has democratic intentions and that elections can take place there without harming stability: &quot;The poll that took place in Egypt refutes the case made by those who claim Egypt is unstable and question its march toward the future.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

[[United States]] [[United States Department of State|State Department]] spokesman Sean McCormack said that the United States saw this election as a &quot;historic departure&quot; and the debate during the election process would &quot;enrich the Egyptian political dialogue, certainly for years to come.&quot;  McCormack also stated that &quot;the Egyptian security services showed discipline in ensuring safety and security&quot; and praised the &quot;relative calm&quot; of Election Day.

However, McCormack criticized the lack of international monitors and the late decision to allow monitors, as well as the lack of media access that prevented opposition candidates from getting their message out. As for election day itself, he stated that &quot;there were reports of some irregularities at polling places in terms of campaign posters or t-shirts being seen at the actual polling place and a variety of other issues.&quot; The United States expressed its hope that &quot;the Egyptian Government and the Egyptian people can build upon this positive first step in holding this multi-candidate presidential election and build on the positive experiences, the positive actions in this election, as they look towards parliamentary elections in the fall time and look to addressing some of those issues that I mentioned that were less positive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/dpb/2005/52801.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==Election Day Events==

Though support for Mubarak is significant and he was expected to win by a wide margin, charges of widespread confusion, [[ballot stuffing]], vote-buying, intimidation, and other forms of [[voter fraud]] marred the election on September 7, 2005.

===Low Turnout===

The Mubarak government initially stated that turnout was high, though numbers varied.  Surprisingly, on September 9, the government released results and turnout figures that were low and may have been accurate, as low in some places as 19%.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

On September 8, however, an election official and Mubarak's campaign both stated that it was around 30%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/08/AR2005090800151_pf.html Controversy Swirls Over Egypt Vote&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Both on election day and afterwards, election monitoring groups stated that turnout was low, reportedly because ordinary Egyptians thought the outcome a foregone conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://about.upi.com/products/upi_scitech/UPI-20050907-055929-3140R] {{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 8, anonymous sources stated turnout in [[Alexandria]], the second-largest city in [[Egypt]], was 17%, and turnout in [[Ismaïlia]] (a city of about 750,000) was about 24%, with Mubarak taking more than 80% of the vote.  

Wael Namara, a spokesman for [[Ayman Nour]] of the [[Tomorrow Party]], estimated turnout to be between 10 and 15% in the countryside and from 3 to 5% in the cities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://today.reuters.co.uk/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=worldNews&amp;storyID=2005-09-07T210521Z_01_SCH718546_RTRUKOC_0_UK-EGYPT-ELECTIONS-OPEN.xml&amp;archived=False Breaking News, Business News, Financial and Investing News &amp; More | Reuters.co.uk&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In previous elections, voter turnout has run at less than 10 percent.&lt;ref&gt;http://in.today.reuters.com/news/newsArticle.aspx?type=worldNews&amp;storyID=2005-09-07T233301Z_01_NOOTR_RTRJONC_0_India-215318-4.xml&lt;/ref&gt; Voter turnout in the May 2005 referendum that allowed the presidential election was officially reported as 54%, but judges monitoring the elections said it was more like 3%.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.heraldtribune.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20050907/API/509070560&lt;/ref&gt;

===Alleged Irregularities===

Allegations of election law violations surfaced during the voting. News media reported that Mubarak's National Democratic Party transported voters to the polls by bus,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/world/20050907-0901-egypt-election.html SignOnSanDiego.com &gt; News &gt; World - Egyptians vote in first contested presidential election&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and allegedly did not allow voters to mark their choices behind a curtain, an essential requirement of a [[secret ballot]]. [[Polling station]]s in Cairo were plastered with Mubarak posters and members of the NDP hovered over voters, taking ballots from voters and handing them to polling station officials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/world/middle_east/article310985.ece Activists defy protest ban as Egypt votes in 'false' election - Middle East, World - The Independent&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ayman Nour]] of the [[Tomorrow Party]], one of the most prominent opposition candidates, along with others, has accused the government of not using truly [[election ink|indelible ink]] on the hands of voters, allowing voters favoring [[Hosni Mubarak]] to remove stamps indicating they had voted and return to vote again. Indelible ink was used only in major boxes, while non-permanent ink was used in many other boxes. There were rumors of certain voters that had no ink at all which would make voter fraud even less difficult.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metronews.ca/reuters_international.asp?id=93761 Metro News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Nour also alleged that there was widespread vote-buying, a charge supported by the Egyptian Organisation for Human Rights, though not otherwise corroborated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sudantribune.com/article.php3?id_article=11537 Egytians vote for president - Sudan Tribune: Plural news and views on Sudan&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Egyptian Organisation for Human Rights, while supporting Nour's claims, has stated that the irregularities were insufficient to require a rerun of the election.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;

===Protests by Kefaya Movement===

On September 7, 2005, men in plainclothes broke up a [[Cairo]] protest by the [[Kefaya]] movement calling for Egyptians to boycott the elections, beating some of the protesters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/nm/20050907/wl_nm/egypt_elections_beatings_dc] {{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Media sources state that as many as three thousand Kifaya protesters illegally marched on central Cairo, possibly the largest crowd ever drawn by that protest movement, while armed soldiers and police watched.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.scotsman.com/international.cfm?id=1906442005 Scotsman.com News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Election monitoring===

At 10:00 a.m. on September 7, two hours after the start of the election, Egypt's Presidential [[Election Commission (Egypt)|Election Commission]] unexpectedly stated that it would allow [[civil society]] groups to [[election monitor|monitor]] the election.  However, in many cases they were not allowed into polling places and were beaten and interrogated, especially in Southern Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=14479 Middle East Online&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

These citizen monitors were in addition to the Egyptian [[judge]]s who have been allowed to independently [[election monitor|monitor]] the elections.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kansascity.com/mld/kansascity/12577556.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Camilla Hall, a journalist at the [[Edinburgh Middle East Report]], showed, in an article in Winter 2006, how the Court of Cassation ruling, that revealed electoral fraud, displayed the weakness of [[Opposition (parliamentary)|parliamentary opposition]], compared to the relative strength of [[civil society]]. &lt;ref&gt; [http://emeronline.blogspot.com/search?q=election+monitoring Mubarak's Real Opposition | Election Monitoring Uncovered] by Camilla Hall. [[Edinburgh Middle East Report]] Online. Winter 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

===More Protests===

A larger protest of around 10,000 people was organized by Kifaya on September 10, 2005, to contest the election results and the mass rigging activities and cheating that occurred on the election day. It was reported by independent observers, reporters and candidate representatives that the NDP (Mubarak's Party) used government resources to change the election results. In some cases, citizens were beaten or forced to vote for Mubarak. In other cases, the boxes were already filled with marked ballots. However, the most explicit action that provoked the protest was allowing pro-Mubarak voters only to vote without being previously registered in the voter lists, giving Mubarak between 20 to 30 extra illegal points in the results.&lt;ref&gt;[http://optimusvoices.blogspot.com/2005/09/anti-mubarak-demostrations-september.html Voices&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Egyptian presidential election, 2011]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4192438.stm BBC: Guide to Egypt's election]
* [http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/BB73E07D-E423-4D2A-9DF8-12356F7DBA3D.htm Al-Jazeera: Egypt's Brotherhood urges all to vote]
* [http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/FDC81A50-8249-4F75-B951-C4B524208948.htm Al-Jazeera: Egyptian judges to supervise election]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/4221080.stm BBC: Egypt votes in landmark election]
* [http://english.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/E5693982-C205-4501-AF32-52283D3A3E43.htm Al-Jazeera: Opposition cries foul in Egyptian vote]
* [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/09/08/AR2005090800151.html Washington Post: Mubarak Wins Egypt's First Open Vote]
* [http://www.ifex.org/en/content/view/full/69027/ IFEX: Election coverage favours Mubarak]
*[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/1126350673259_238/?hub=TopStories CTV.ca Egyptian opposition denounces results of election]
* [http://emeronline.blogspot.com/search?q=election+monitoring Mubarak's Real Opposition | Electoral Monitoring Uncovered] by Camilla Hall. [[Edinburgh Middle East Report]] Online. Winter 2006

{{Egyptian elections}}

[[Category:2005 elections in Africa]]
[[Category:Elections in Egypt]]
[[Category:2005 in Egypt]]

[[ar:انتخابات الرئاسة المصرية 2005]]
[[es:Elección presidencial de Egipto (2005)]]
[[io:Prezidantala elektado di Egiptia, 2005]]
[[arz:انتخابات الرئاسه المصريه 2005]]
[[no:Presidentvalget i Egypt 2005]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
