<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2192486" ns="0" title="Lydden Hill Race Circuit"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Motorsport venue|
  Name          = Lydden Hill Race Circuit | 
  Location      = [[Wootton, Kent|Wootton]], [[Kent]], [[United Kingdom]] |
  Image         = [[File:Lydden Hill Race Circuit track map.svg|250px]] |
  Events        = European and British Rallycross Championship, club meetings |
  Length_km    = 1.609 or 1.400 [Rallycross only] |
  Length_mi    = 1.000 or 0.870 [Rallycross only] |
  Turns        = 4 |
  Record_time         = 38.3 |
  Record_class        =  |
  Record_driver       = [[Rob Cox]] |
  Record_team         = [[Lola Cars|Lola]] LC88 |
  Record_year         = 1989 |
}}

'''Lydden Hill Race Circuit''' (formerly known as ''Lydden Circuit'') is the UK's shortest road racing circuit (many shorter oval tracks exist) at exactly one mile (= 1.609 km), based at [[Wootton, Kent|Wootton]] about half-way between [[Canterbury]] and [[Dover]] in [[Kent]]. The track is mainly used for rallycross, drift, saloon and sports car racing as well as [[Motorcycle sport|motorcycle racing]]. It may be only a mile long, but Lydden is a testing circuit, with many undulation changes.

== History ==
The track was founded by the late [http://www.rallycross.de/history/history_pictures/history_billchesson.jpg Bill Chesson] († 1999) and the Astra Motor Club in 1955. They promoted stock-car racing and grass-track racing for motorcycles, and it wasn't until 1965 when asphalt was laid for the circuit, for hosting car racing up to [[Formula Three]].

On February 4, 1967 the sport of ''[[Rallycross]]'' was born at Lydden, thought up by TV producer Robert Reed (for [[ITV]]) and race organiser Bud Smith (750 Motor Club – Tunbridge Wells Centre) in cooperation with Chesson. Combining tarmac and non-tarmac elements, the inaugural race was won by [[Vic Elford]] in a [[Porsche 911]]. Between 1973 and 2009 Lydden Circuit saw a total of 24 rounds for the [[Embassy/ERA European Rallycross Championship]]s and [[FIA European Championships for Rallycross Drivers]], the first 23 (till 1996) all organised by the [[Thames Estuary Automobile Club]] (TEAC). To this day, Lydden, as the so-called &quot;Home of Rallycross&quot;, still holds British Rallycross Championship racing, especially with its popular [[Easter Monday]] meeting.

[[File:View of Chessons Drift on Lydden circuit race track.jpg|thumb|right|View of ''Dover Slope'' and ''Devils Elbow'' on Lydden Hill Race Circuit]]
In 1989, after disagreements between venue owner Chesson and the [[Royal Automobile Club|RAC]] [[Motor Sports Association|MSA]] about the safety precautions of the track, the circuit was bought by plant-hire entrepreneur and regular rallycross competitor Tom Bissett. 

In 1991, [[McLaren (racing)|McLaren]] bought the track and leased it to the [http://www.bemsee.net British Motorcycle Racing Club] (BMCRC) from 1993 on, thus allowing both cars and bikes to have full use of the track. BMCRC were based at Lydden until the end of 2007, and it formed their home track, playing host to the annual 'Lord of Lydden' and 'Sidecar burnup' races, together with a number of club motorcycle race meetings.

Another piece in the history of Lydden came in 2003, when McLaren had an application turned down for Lydden to become a private testing venue.

From 2008 on the new lease holder of the circuit will be, for at least five years, the Waste Recycling Consultant, MSA British Rallycross Champion (2002, 2005, 2009, 2010) and FIA European Rallycross Championship runner-up (1992) Pat Doran. Doran, an Englishman of Irish origin from [[Thorverton]] in [[Devon]], is planning several improvements for the venue as well as an extension of the racing programme (for cars and bikes alike) and his oldest daughter Amy Doran has been appointed as director for day-to-day running of the circuit.

== Rallycross Track Record ==
*[[Martin Schanche]] ([[Ford RS200|Ford RS200 E2]]) drove 3 ½ laps (1 lap = 1.400 km) in 2:28.8 Minutes during the 1990 [[FIA]] ERC round

* Sverre Isachsen (N), Ford Focus T16 4X4, drove 4 laps (1 lap = 1.300m) in 3.13.344 minutes during the 2009 [[FIA]] ERC Round

== Current events ==
=== Major events ===
*FIA European Rallycross Championship www.rallycross.de (in English and German)
*British Rallycross Championship www.lyddenhill.co.uk
*MSA British Rallycross Championship www.RallycrossUK.com
*BHP Performance Show www.bhpperformanceshow.com
*Lydden Hill Motorcycle Show www.lyddenhill.co.uk
*British Grasstrack Masters

=== Local meetings ===
*South East Motor Sport Enthusiasts Club (SEMSEC)
*Tunbridge Wells Motor Club (TWMC)
*Rochester Motor Club (RMC)
*British Racing Sports Car Club (BRSCC)
*British Automobile Racing Club (BARC)
*Vintage Motorcycle Racing Club (VMCC)
*Mitsubishi Lancer Register Sprint Series (MLR)
*Car &amp; Bike Trackdays

==External links==
* [http://www.lyddenhill.co.uk// Lydden Race Circuit home page]
* [http://www.rallycross.de/history/rx_history_ger.html Rallycross history with information on Lydden (in German)]
* [http://lyddenhill.com/lyddenguide.html  A spectators guide for the Lydden Hill Race Circuit]
{{coord|51|10|38.59|N|1|11|58.69|E|display=title}}

{{British motor racing circuits}}

[[Category:McLaren Group]]
[[Category:Sports venues in Kent]]
[[Category:Motorsport venues in England]]
[[Category:Canterbury]]

[[de:Lydden Hill Race Circuit]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
