<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="219619" ns="0" title="Bahawalpur"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox settlement
|name          = Bahawalpur
|other_name             = بہاولپور
|settlement_type        = City
|image_skyline          = Bahawalpur Montage.jpg
|imagesize              =
|image_caption          =
|pushpin_map            = Pakistan
|pushpin_label_position =
|pushpin_mapsize        =300
|pushpin_map_caption    =Location in Pakistan
|coordinates_display    = inline,title
|coordinates_region     = PK
|subdivision_type       = Country
|subdivision_name       = [[Pakistan]]
|subdivision_type1      = [[Subdivisions of Pakistan|Region]]
|subdivision_name1      = [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]]
|subdivision_type2      = [[Districts of Pakistan|District]]
|subdivision_name2      = [[Bahawalpur District]]
|subdivision_type3      = [[Tehsil]]
|subdivision_name3      = [[Bahawalpur Tehsil]]
|subdivision_type4      = Union councils
|subdivision_name4      = 36
|government_footnotes   =&lt;ref&gt;[http://203.215.180.58/portal/portal/media-type/html/group/320/page/default.psml/js_pane/P-103d7b410be-10000?nav=left]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://203.215.180.58/portal/portal/media-type/html/group/320/page/default.psml/js_pane/P-103d7b410be-10000?nav=left Area reference]&lt;br&gt;[http://www.statpak.gov.pk/depts/pco/index.html Density reference]&lt;/ref&gt;
|government_type        =
|leader_title           = Nazim
|leader_name            =----------------
|leader_title1          = Naib nazim
|leader_name1           =
|established_title      =
|established_date       =
|area_total_km2         = 2372
|area_metro_km2         =
|population_as_of       =2011
|population_footnotes   = &lt;ref name=&quot;estimate2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.world-gazetteer.com/wg.php?x=&amp;men=gpro&amp;lng=en&amp;dat=32&amp;geo=-172&amp;srt=pnan&amp;col=aohdq&amp;pt=c&amp;va=&amp;geo=413520701| title=Bahawlpur| first=World Gazetteer| last=Stefan Helders| accessdate=2006-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|population_note                =
|population_total               =855509
|population_density_km2         =838
|population_urban               =545103
|population_density_urban_km2   =
|latd=29 |latm=23 |lats=44 |latNS=N
|longd=71 |longm=41 |longs=1 |longEW=E
|elevation_footnotes    =
|elevation_m            =461
|elevation_ft           =1512
|timezone               =[[Pakistan Standard Time|PST]]
|utc_offset             = +5
|timezone_DST           =[[Pakistan Standard Time|PDT]]
|utc_offset_DST         = +6
|postal_code_type       =
|postal_code            =
|area_code              =
|blank_name             =
|blank_info             =
|website                = [http://www.bahawalpur.gov.pk/history.htm www.bahawalpur.gov.pk/]
|footnotes              = [http://pportal.punjab.gov.pk/portal/portal/media-type/html/group/304?page_name=Bahawalpur$d_home&amp;group_type=dist&amp;group_id=304&amp;group_name=Bahawalpur&amp;js_pane=P-1004ba76975-10000&amp;pview=true Bahawalpur Government Website]
}}

'''Bahawalpur''' (Urdu: بہاولپور), located in the [[Subdivisions of Pakistan|province]] of [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]], is the [[List of most populated metropolitan areas in Pakistan|twelfth largest]] city in [[Pakistan]]. The city was once the capital of the former [[princely state]] of [[Bahawalpur (princely state)|Bahawalpur]]. The city was home to various [[Nawab]]s (rulers) and counted as part of the [[Rajputana]] states (now [[Rajasthan]], [[India]]). The city is known for its famous palaces such as the [[Noor Mahal]], Sadiq Ghar Palace, and Darbar Mahal, as well as the ancient fort of [[Derawar Fort|Derawar]] in the [[Cholistan Desert]] bordering India. The city is located near the historical and ancient cities of [[Uch]] and [[Harappa]], which were once a stronghold of the [[Delhi Sultanate]] and [[Indus Valley Civilisation]]. The city is home to one of the few natural safari parks in Pakistan, [[Lal Suhanra National Park]].

In 2007, the city's population was recorded to have risen to 798,509 from 403,408 in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bahawalpur.gov.pk/area.htm Bahawalpur: Area &amp; Population] Official Bahawalpur Government Website, Accessed 2009-09-17&lt;/ref&gt; [[Punjabi &amp; Saraiki]] is one of the few local languages, while [[Urdu]] is well understood  and [[English language|English]] is the  official languages used in various educational and government institutions. Bahawalpur is located south of the [[Sutlej River]] and lies in the [[Cholistan]] region near the [[Thar Desert]]. It is situated 90&amp;nbsp;km from Multan, 420&amp;nbsp;km from Lahore, and 270&amp;nbsp;km from [[Faisalabad]].

The main crops for which Bahawalpur is recognised are [[cotton]], [[sugarcane]], [[wheat]], [[sunflower seed]]s, [[rapeseed|rape]]/[[mustard seed]] and [[rice]]. Bahawalpur [[mangoes]], citrus, [[Phoenix dactylifera|dates]] and [[guavas]] are some of the fruits exported out of the country. Vegetables include [[onion]]s, [[tomato]]es, [[cauliflower]], [[potato]]es and [[carrot]]s. Being an expanding industrial city, the government has revolutionised and libertised various markets, allowing the caustic soda, cotton ginning and pressing, flour mills, fruit juices, general engineering, iron and steel re-rolling mills, looms, oil mills, poultry feed, sugar, textile spinning, textile weaving, vegetable ghee and cooking oil industries to flourish.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pportal.punjab.gov.pk/portal/portal/media-type/html/group/304/page/default.psml/js_pane/P-11aeca7c599-100e5?nav=left Agricultural Assessment of Bahawalpur District]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{main|Bahawalpur (princely state)}}
The [[princely state]] of Bahawalpur was founded in 1802 by Nawab Mohammad Bahawal Khan II after the breakup of the [[Durrani Empire]]. The city is large at over 451 kilometres long. Nawab Mohammad Bahawal Khan III signed a treaty with the [[British India|British]] on 22 February 1833, guaranteeing the independence of the Nawab. The state acceded to Pakistan on 7 October 1947 when Nawab [[Sadeq Mohammad Khan V|Sadiq Muhammad Khan Abbasi V Bahadur]]&lt;ref name=&quot;royalark&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.4dw.net/royalark/Pakistan/bahawal5.htm| title=Bahawalpur: The Abbasi Dynasty| author=Christopher Buyers, Royal Ark website| accessdate=2007-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; decided to join Pakistan at the time of independence. Bahawalpur became a province of Pakistan in 1952 and was merged into the province of West Pakistan on 14 October 1955. When West Pakistan was divided into four provinces — Sindh, Balouchistan, NWFP, and Punjab — Bahawalpur became a part of Punjab.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}
And it is also the largest division of punjab area wise 45,588&amp;nbsp;km² [[Divisions of Pakistan]] and also largest district of punjab areawise Districts of Pakistan 24,830&amp;nbsp;km² [[Districts of Pakistan]].

== Geography and climate ==
The city, which lies just south of the [[Sutlej River]], is the site of the Adamwahan Empress Bridge, the only railway bridge over the Sutlej in Pakistan. It is situated 90&amp;nbsp;km from Multan, 420&amp;nbsp;km from Lahore, 122&amp;nbsp;km from [[Burewala]], 90&amp;nbsp;km from [[Vehari]], 270&amp;nbsp;km from [[Faisalabad]] and about 700&amp;nbsp;km from the national capital, [[Islamabad]]. The west region of the city is called the Sindh. It is a fertile alluvial tract in the Sutlej River valley that is irrigated by floodwaters, planted with groves of date palm trees, and thickly populated forests. The chief crops are [[wheat]], [[gram]], [[cotton]], [[sugarcane]], and [[Phoenix dactylifera|dates]].[[Mango]] [[Sheep]] and [[cattle]] are raised for export of [[wool]] and [[hides]]. East of Bahawalpur is the Pat, or Bar, a tract of land considerably higher than the adjoining valley. It is chiefly desert irrigated by the Sutlej inundation canals and yields crops of wheat, cotton, and [[sugarcane]]. Farther east, the [[Cholistan]], is a barren desert tract, bounded on the north and west by the Hakra depression with mound ruins of old settlements along its high banks; it is still inhabited by nomads.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The climate is mainly hot and dry. In the summer the temperature reaches the high forties (Celsius) during the day and the nights are slightly cooler. Since the city is located in a desert environment there is little rainfall. Weather conditions reach extremes in both summer and winter. The average temperature in summer is {{convert|33|C}} and {{convert|18|C}} in winter. The average rainfall is 20 to 25&amp;nbsp;cm annually.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

== Demographics ==

Bahawalpur is one of the largest districts of the Punjab, covering an area of 24,830&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;. It has peculiar demographic, topographic and geographical characteristics. The district is situated almost in the center of the country at an elevation of 152 meters from the sea levels. The population of Bahawalpur district increased from 1.453 million in 1981 to 2.411 million in 1998, showing a growth rate of 3.88% per year as compared with 3.3% for the entire Punjab. Population density has increased from 59 in 1981 to 97 in 1998, as compared with 353 for the Punjab. The majority of Bahawalpur's residents speak  [[Saraiki language|Saraiki]], while [[Urdu]],and [[English language|English]] are common languages used in various educational and government institutions. The principal inhabitants of the region surrounding Bahawalpur are Jat and Baluchi people.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

== Flora and fauna ==
{{Original research|date=June 2011}}
The most commonly seen animals in the city include the hog deer, ravine deer, black buck and blue bull. Fox, jackals, hares, wild boars, porcupines, mongoose, arks, owls and hawks are also found in large numbers.

The [[Bahawalpur Zoo]], is located in Bahawalpur. Spread over an area of several acres inside the city, it contains a variety of animal species, including Asiatic lions, Bengal tigers, hyenas, leopards, and peacocks. The zoo has a collection of 130 animals and 700 birds from tropical regions, particularly those found in the Cholistan region. The zoo occasionally breeds and supplies animals to other zoos in the country. It also has an aquarium and zoological museum with stuffed rare birds and animals.

Located 35 kilometres east of the city is the [[Lal Suhanra National Park]]housing large animals including lions and rhinoceros.

==Economy==
{{Original research|date=June 2011}}
[[File:Beautiful darbar m galleryfull.jpg|thumb|[[Darbar Mahal]], a former palace of the Nawabs of Bahawalpur]]
[[File:Hasilpur Bahawal Canal.jpg|thumb|Irrigation from canals such as this provides the city with fertile soil for crop production.]]
Bahawalpur lies at the junction of trade routes from the east, south-east, and south. It is a center for trade in wheat, cotton, millet, and rice grown in the surrounding region. Dates and mangoes are also grown here. Canals supply water for irrigation. The principal industries are cotton ginning, rice and flour milling, and the handweaving of textiles.

Soapmaking and cotton ginning are important enterprises; cotton, silk, embroidery, carpets, and extraordinarily delicate pottery are produced. Factories producing cottonseed oil and cottonseed cake were built in the 1970s. It is an important marketing center for the surrounding areas and is located on the crossroads between Peshawar, Lahore, Quetta and Karachi. Bahawalpur is also known for its distinctively embroidered slippers and shoes and filigree pottery.

Bahawalpur has only one railway bridge, the Adamwahan (Empress) Bridge, over the Sutlej River, and also has rail links with [[Peshawar]], the capital of [[North-West Frontier Province]] and [[Karachi]], the capital of [[Sindh]] (which is 899&amp;nbsp;km from Bahawalpur), making it an important rail centre. The surrounding area is mostly agricultural, which allows agricultural exports to many parts of the world. There is also a large market town for mangoes, dates, wheat, sugarcane, and cotton that brings in continuous demand all year round. It has soap making and cotton spinning factories, as well as enterprises producing silk and cotton textiles, carpets, and pottery. Bahwalpur has sugar mills that provide some of the export market out of the country.

[[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]] is Pakistan's most fertile province, rich in both agriculture and ancient history. It is also one of the more stable of the country's regions. The prosperous and hospitable town of Bahawalpur is a gentle introduction to the area, which makes the city an ideal tourist destination. From here one can journey into Cholistan - a sandy wasteland dotted with nomadic communities and windswept forts - or the [[Lal Suhanra National Park]], an important wildlife reserve. Further north is [[Harappa]], which is an important site of the [[Indus Valley Civilization]]. Bahawalpur is the most southerly town in the Punjab. There are daily flights from Islamabad about 555&amp;nbsp;km (344&amp;nbsp;mi) away. Most of the major destinations in the Punjab can be reached by car, bus, coach, and train.

== Culture ==
{{Original research|date=June 2011}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Palace bwp.jpg|left|thumb|[[Sadiq Ghar Palace]] is in urgent need of restoration; the palace has been closed to the public.]] --&gt;
[[File:Cholistan Jeep Rally Event.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Cholistan Jeep Rally]] is held in the city every year in the [[Cholistan desert]]]]
[[File:Derawar Fort 3 by gul791.jpg|left|thumb|[[Derawar Fort]] is on the outskirts of the city in the [[Cholistan Desert]]]]
The city of Bahawalpur has a rich heritage and is an important hot spot for historians as well as archeologists. Bahawalpur is known for its cotton, silk, embroidery, carpets, and extraordinarily delicate pottery. The Punjab Small Industries Corporation (PSIC) has established a Craft Development Center for Cholistan area, outside Farid Gate, Bahawalpur from where handicrafts manufactured in Cholistan can be purchased. Some of the souvenirs produced in the city include:

* Flassi - 4&amp;nbsp;ft by 7&amp;nbsp;ft, made of camel hair and cotton yarn; it is used for wall hanging, as a decoration piece and a carpet.
* Gindi or Rilli - Made of small pieces of many colors of cotton cloth and needlework; they can be used as wall hangings, bed covers, carpets and blankets.
* Changaries - Like big plaques, these are made of palm leaves in different bright colours with beautiful patterns and geometric designs. These are used for keeping the 'chapattis' and also as a wall decoration.
* Khalti - Like a purse embroidered on top with multicoloured threads.
* Artwork - An attractive type of embroidery done on dupatta, kurta and chaddar, etc.

The main shopping centers of Bahawalpur are Shahi Bazaar, Machli Bazaar, Farid Gate and the Mall. The commercial area in Satellite Town is a newly developed center that is gaining popularity. A few shopping malls, including Bobby Plaza, Takbeer Shopping Mall, Time, and Prince, cater for all kinds of needs. Shopping is a major attraction in the city; the city is bustling with traders and craftsmen selling all sorts of artwork for travellers and tourists.

[[File:NoorMahalbwp.JPG|thumb|[[Noor Mahal]] lit at night after being newly renovated]]

East of Bahawalpur is the [[Cholistan Desert]], which covers an area of about 15,000&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; and extends into the [[Thar Desert]] of [[India]]. The region was once watered by the [[Hakra River]], known as the Saravati in [[vedic]] times. At one time there were 400 forts in the area and archaeological finds around the [[Derawar Fort]], the only place with a perennial waterhole, indicate that it was contemporaneous with the [[Indus Valley Civilisation]]. The average annual rainfall is only 12&amp;nbsp;cm, and the area's scant cultivation is made possible by underground wells, drawn up by camels. The water is stored in troughs, built by the tribes, between sandhills and din waterholes called tobas. The people are racially similar to those in Rajasthan - tall, with sharp features. They live in large, round, mud and grass huts, usually built on the top of sandhills. On the whole, they are pastoral and nomadic. The main tribes are the Chachar, Mehr, Lar, Paryar, Channar, Chandani and Bohar. The forts here were built at 29&amp;nbsp;km intervals, which probably served as guard posts for the camel caravan routes. There were three rows of these forts. The first line of forts began from Phulra and ended in Lera, the second from Rukhanpur to Islamgarh, and the third from Bilcaner to Kapoo. Built with double walls of gypsum blocks and mud, they are all in ruins now. Some of them date back to 1000 BC, and were destroyed and rebuilt many times.

Even with all the markets and forts, one thing for which Bahawalpur is recognised above all others is the numerous palaces that still remain intact ever since the fall of the Nawabs. There are countless palaces in the city, locally known as Mahals. Some of the most famous include: [[Noor Mahal]], Gulzar Mahal, Darbar Mahal, Shimla Khoti Sadiq Ghar Palace and Darbar Mahal. The city also has a city gate called Farid Gate, which in its heyday provided the only entrance to the city for its rulers. The gate still remains and is now located in a busy market in the inner city. The [[Bahawalpur Museum]] and [[Bahawalpur National Library]] house various collections of coins, medals, postage stamps of the former state of Bahawalpur, manuscripts, documents, inscriptions, wood carvings, camel skin paintings, historical models and stone carvings from Islamic and pre-Islamic eras. There is a complete set of medals of all classes issued by the ex-state to its military officers, civilians, and other important citizens of the ex-state.

The city also has several mausoleums of prominent leaders who fought and defended the region over several thousands of years. Some of the most prolific include the tombs of Channen Peer Tomb Yazman and Mausoleums of Haugha Sahib. There is also an old fort of Munde Shahid, 50&amp;nbsp;km from Bahawalpur and [[Marot Fort]], which are considered to be antiquities. A place outside the Marot Fort is known as 'Baithak Maula Ali'. The tomb of Naugaza is located in the Munde Sharif Fort.

== Education ==
{{Original research|date=June 2011}}

[[Image:Front View of Campus Building.jpg|thumb| [[Quaid-e-Azam Medical College]], Bahawalpur designed by [[A. R. Hye]]]]

The city boasts a number of reputable educational establishments, most notably [[The Islamia University of Bahawalpur]], [[Quaid-e-Azam Medical College]], and [[Sadiq Public School]], which is one of the largest boarding schools in Pakistan. Other top schools include [[Beaconhouse School System (Pakistan)#Bahawalpur|Beaconhouse School Bahawalpur]],[[The City School (Pakistan)]], [[Bloomfield Hall Schools]], Askari Kids College, Umm al qura school, Progressive Schooling System, Dar e arqam School, Jinnah Public School, Rangers Public School and College, The Climber Public School, Army Public School, Salsaal Public School, and Dominican Convent School. Notable universities and colleges include: Government Sadiq Egertin College (Post Graduate College),Punjab College Bahawalpur, Arrshhouse College, Government Degree College, Government Sadiq Degree College for Girls, The Islamia University of Bahawalpur, [[Government College of Technology, Bahawalpur|Government College of Technology]], Government Sadiq College of Commerce, Government Polytechnic Institute, Government Polytechnic Institute For Women, Government Technical Training Institute,Government Technical High School Bahawalpur, Allama Iqbal College of Commerce and Government Para Medical School.

== Transport ==
{{Original research|date=June 2011}}
Bahawalpur is well connected with various cities in Pakistan. The city has its own airport built by the [[Department of Civil Aviation (Dubai)|Dubai Civil Aviation Department]] and the [[Civil Aviation Authority of Pakistan|CAA]]. [[Bahawalpur Airport]] links the city with various Pakistani cities such as Dera Ghazi Khan, Islamabad, Karachi and Lahore with the national flag carrier, [[Pakistan International Airlines]]. The airline has launched international flights to Dubai, and plans to introduce more international destinations. There are daily train and bus services from Multan, Lahore, Sukkur and Karachi to Bahawalpur.[[taxicabs]] and [[Auto rickshaw|rickshaws]] are plentiful in the city. Cars are also available for hire in the city.

== Gallery ==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:BahawalpurDaewoo.JPG|Daewoo Terminal, Bahawalpur
Image:Bahawalpurinsidefarid.JPG|Market Inside Farid Gate
Image:FaridGate.JPG|Farid Gate, Bahawalpur
Image:NoorMahal1.JPG|Noor Mahal
Image:SadiqDaneHighSchool.JPG|Sadiq Dane High School, Bahawalpur
Image:DringStadium.JPG|Entrance of Dring Stadium
Image:BahawalVictoriaHospital.JPG|Bahawal Victoria Hospital
File:Bahawalpur Airport.jpg|Sheikh Rashid Air Terminal, Bahawalpur Airport
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Bahawalpur Museum]]
* [[Bahawalpur Zoo]]
* [[Derawar Fort]]
* [[Noor Mahal]]
* [[Sadiq Public School Bahawalpur|Sadiq Public School]]
* [[Islamia University|The Islamia University of Bahawalpur]]
* [[Kakazai]]
* [[Quaid-e-Azam Medical College]]
* [[Saraiki language]]
* [[Saraikistan]]
* [[Saraiki nationalist movement]]
* [[Saraiki Wasaib]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|Bahawalpur}}
* [http://www.infobwp.com Bahawalpur]
* [http://www.tmabwpcity.com TMA Bahawalpur City]
* [http://www.tmabwpsadar.com TMA Bahawalpur Sadar]
* [http://www.mybahawalpur.com Bahawalpur City Information Portal]
* [http://www.bahawalpurpolice.gov.pk Bahawalpur Police website]
* [http://www.punjab.gov.pk Punjab Government website]
* [http://www.mybahawalpur.com/bahawalpur-pictures/gallery.html Bahawalpur Pictures]
* {{Wikitravel|Bahawalpur}}
* [http://www.itlinxpk.com Software House in Bahawalpur]
* {{dmoz|/Regional/Asia/Pakistan/Provinces/Punjab/Localities/Bahawalpur|Bahawalpur}}

{{PakistanCities}}
{{Pakistan topics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

[[Category:Populated places in Bahawalpur District]]
[[Category:Populated places established in 1748]]

[[ca:Bahawalpur (ciutat)]]
[[da:Bahawalpur]]
[[de:Bahawalpur]]
[[es:Bahawalpur]]
[[eo:Bahavalpur]]
[[fr:Bahawâlpur]]
[[gl:Bahawalpur]]
[[ko:바하왈푸르]]
[[hi:बहावलपुर]]
[[it:Bahawalpur]]
[[kl:Bahawalpur]]
[[lt:Bahavalpūras]]
[[mi:Bahawalpur]]
[[nl:Bahawalpur]]
[[ja:バハーワルプール]]
[[no:Bahawalpur]]
[[pnb:بہاولپور]]
[[pl:Bahawalpur]]
[[pt:Bahawalpur]]
[[ru:Бахавалпур]]
[[simple:Bahawalpur]]
[[sv:Bahawalpur]]
[[tr:Bahawalpur]]
[[ur:بہاولپور]]
[[vi:Bahawalpur]]
[[war:Bahawalpur]]
[[zh:巴哈瓦尔布尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
