<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="21979" ns="0" title="Netscape"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the web browser produced by this corporation|Netscape (web browser)}}
{{Infobox company
| company_name  = Netscape Communications
| company_logo  =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[Image:Netscape.svg|200px]] --&gt;
| type          = Subsidiary of AOL
| slogan        = ''We Only Use the Netscape
| fate          =
| successor     =
| foundation    = 1994
| location      = [[Mountain View, California]], United States (as an independent company)&lt;br&gt;[[Dulles, Virginia]], USA&lt;br/&gt;(after becoming a part of AOL)
| industry      = Internet, Software, &amp; Telecommunication
| key_people    = [[Marc Andreessen]] and [[James H. Clark|Jim Clark]] (founders)
| products      = [[Internet suite]]&lt;br/&gt;[[web browser]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Internet service provider]]&lt;br/&gt;[[web portal]]
| num_employees = 10,000
| parent        = [[AOL]]
| subsid        =
| website       = [http://netscape.aol.com/ netscape.aol.com/]
|
| homepage      = [http://netscape.aol.com/ netscape.aol.com/]
}}
'''Netscape Communications''' (formerly known as '''Netscape Communications Corporation''' and commonly known as '''Netscape''') is a US computer services company, best known for [[Netscape Navigator]], its [[web browser]]. When it was an independent company, its headquarters were in [[Mountain View, California]].&lt;ref&gt;Swartz, Jon. &quot;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/1997/10/02/BU33867.DTL Company takes browser war to Netscape's lawn].&quot; ''[[San Francisco Chronicle]]''. Thursday October 2, 1997. Retrieved on December 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The name Netscape was a trademark of [[Cisco Systems]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.networkworld.com/news/2010/063010-cisco-cius-tablet.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Netscape's web browser was once dominant in terms of [[Usage share of web browsers|usage share]], but lost most of that share to [[Internet Explorer]] during the [[browser wars|first browser war]]. By the end of 2006, the usage share of Netscape browsers had fallen, from over 90% in the mid 1990s, to less than 1%. Netscape developed the [[Transport Layer Security|Secure Sockets Layer Protocol]] (SSL) for securing online communication, which is still widely used,&lt;ref&gt;[http://publib.boulder.ibm.com/infocenter/iseries/v5r3/index.jsp?topic=/rzain/rzainhistory.htm History of SSL at IBM.com]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[JavaScript]], the most widely-used language for client-side scripting of web pages.

Netscape stock traded between 1995 and 2003, subsequently as a subsidiary of [[AOL]]. However, it became a [[holding company]] following AOL's purchase of Netscape in 1998. The Netscape brand is still extensively used by AOL. Some services currently offered under the Netscape brand, other than the web browser, include a discount [[Internet service provider]] and a popular [[social news]] website. In December 2007, AOL announced it would no longer be updating the Netscape browser. Tom Drapeau, director of AOL's Netscape Brand, announced that the company would stop supporting Netscape software products as of March 1, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://browser.netscape.com/| title=The Netscape Archive|accessdate=May 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The decision met mixed reactions from communities, with many arguing that the termination of product support is significantly belated. Internet security site ''Security Watch'' stated that a trend of infrequent security updates for AOL's Netscape caused the browser to become a &quot;security liability&quot;, specifically the 2005–2007 versions, [[Netscape Browser|Netscape Browser 8]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://securitywatch.eweek.com/browsers/netscape_death_is_long_overdue_good_for_security_1.html| title=Netscape Death is long overdue, Good for Security|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Asa Dotzler]], one of [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox's]] original bug testers, greeted the news with &quot;good riddance&quot; in his blog post, but praised the various members of the Netscape team over the years for enabling the creation of [[Mozilla]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://weblogs.mozillazine.org/asa/archives/2007/12/its_about_time.html| title=it's about time. r.i.p. netscape browser|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others protested and petitioned AOL to continue providing vital security fixes to unknowing or loyal users of its software, as well as protection of a well-known brand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.savenetscape.com| title=Save Netscape Petition|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=10422| title=Netscape Community – Online Petition for the Support of NN|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.savenetscape.tk| title=Save Netscape!|accessdate=January 2, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Early years===
{|class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: right; margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 2em; font-size: 85%; background:#c6dbf7; color:black; width:25em; max-width: 25%;&quot; cellspacing=&quot;5&quot;
|style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;|Netscape Communications wants you to forget all the highway metaphors you've ever heard about the Internet. Instead, think about an encyclopedia—one with unlimited, graphically rich pages, connections to E-mail and files, and access to Internet newsgroups and online shopping. 
|-
|style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;|—''Netscape Navigator'', [[Macworld]] (May 1995)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Hawn|first=Mathew|date=May 1995|title=Netscape Navigator. (Netscape Communications World Wide Web browser) (Software Review)(Evaluation) |journal=Macworld|accessdate=May 17, 2011|quote=Netscape Communications wants you to forget all the highway metaphors you've ever heard about the Internet. Instead, think about an encyclopedia—one with unlimited, graphically rich pages, connections to E-mail and files, and access to Internet newsgroups and online shopping. |url=http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-16739494.html {{subscription}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}
Netscape was the second company to attempt to capitalize on the (then) nascent [[World Wide Web]]. It was originally founded under the name, '''Mosaic Communications Corporation''', on April 4, 1994, the brainchild of [[James H. Clark|Jim Clark]] who had recruited [[Marc Andreessen]] as co-founder and [[Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers]] as investors. Clark recruited other early Netscape team members from [[Silicon Graphics|SGI]] and [[NCSA Mosaic]], including [[Rosanne Siino]] who became Vice President of Communications. The company's first product was the web browser, called ''Mosaic Netscape 0.9,'' released on October 13, 1994. This browser was subsequently renamed [[Netscape Navigator]], and the company took the 'Netscape' name on November 14, 1994&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| page = B3| title = Mosaic's Name Change| work=The San Francisco Chronicle| date = November 15, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; to avoid trademark ownership problems with [[National Center for Supercomputing Applications|NCSA]], where the initial Netscape employees had previously created the [[Mosaic (web browser)|NCSA Mosaic]] web browser. The Mosaic Netscape web browser used some NCSA Mosaic code with NCSA's permission, as noted in the application's &quot;About&quot; dialog box. Netscape made a very successful [[initial public offering|IPO]] on August 9, 1995. The stock was set to be offered at $14 per share. But, a last-minute decision doubled the initial offering to $28 per share. The stock's value soared to $75 on the first day of trading, nearly a record for first-day gain, the stock closed at $58.25 meaning a market value of $2.9&amp;nbsp;billion. The company's revenues doubled every quarter in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/8.08/loudcloud.html?pg=4| title=Going Public as Netscape Did, before making a dime in profits | publisher=Lycos | work=Wired 8.08 | author=David Sheff | accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Netscape's success (which is freezing &quot;Netscape's Moment&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/node/15464481 The description of Netscape's Moment in The Economist, Feb 4, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;) landed Andreessen, barefoot, on the cover of [[Time Magazine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Time&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url=http://www.time.com/time/covers/0,16641,1101960219,00.html
| title=Netscape's Marc Andreessen
| accessdate=February 3, 2007
| date=February 19, 1996
| work=Time Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Netscape advertised that &quot;the web is for everyone&quot; and stated one of its goals was to &quot;level the playing field&quot; among operating systems by providing a consistent web browsing experience across them. The Netscape web browser interface was identical on any computer. Netscape later experimented with prototypes of a web-based system which would enable users to access and edit their files anywhere across a network, no matter what computer or operating system they happened to be using. This did not escape the attention of [[Microsoft]], which viewed the [[commodification]] of operating systems as a direct threat to its bottom line, i.e. a move from Windows to another operating system would yield a similar browsing experience thus reducing barriers to change. It is alleged that several Microsoft executives visited the Netscape campus in June 1995 to propose dividing the market (although Microsoft denies this as it would have breached anti-trust laws), which would have allowed Microsoft to produce web browser software for [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] while leaving all other operating systems to Netscape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pub.umich.edu/daily/1998/oct/10-20-98/news/news14.html| title=Government alleges illegal campaign by [[Microsoft]]|accessdate=July 14, 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060708210502/http://www.pub.umich.edu/daily/1998/oct/10-20-98/news/news14.html |archivedate = July 8, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Netscape refused the proposition.

Microsoft released version 1.0 of [[Internet Explorer]] as a part of the [[Windows 95]] [[Microsoft Plus!|Plus Pack]] add-on. According to former [[Spyglass]] developer [[Eric Sink]], Internet Explorer was based not on NCSA Mosaic as commonly believed, but on a version of Mosaic developed at Spyglass&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://biztech.ericsink.com/Browser_Wars.html| title=Memoirs from the Browser Wars|accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; (which itself was based upon NCSA Mosaic). Microsoft quickly released several successive versions of Internet Explorer, bundling them with Windows, never charging for them, financing their development and marketing with revenues from other areas of the company. This period of time became known as the [[browser wars]], in which Netscape Communicator and Internet Explorer added many new features and went through many version numbers (not always in a logical fashion) in attempts to outdo each other. But Internet Explorer had the upper hand, as the amount of manpower and capital dedicated to it eventually surpassed the resources available in Netscape's entire business. By version 3.0, IE was roughly a feature-for-feature equivalent of Netscape Communicator, and by version 4.0, it was generally considered to be more stable on Windows than on the Macintosh platform. Microsoft also targeted other Netscape products with free workalikes, such as the [[Internet Information Server]] (IIS), a web server which was bundled with Windows NT.

Netscape could not compete with this strategy. In fact, it didn't attempt to. Netscape Navigator was not free to the general public until January 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.news.com/2100-1001-207681.html?legacy=cnet| title=Netscape cuts prices on retail products | publisher=C-Net | author=Alex Lash | accessdate=February 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; while Internet Explorer and IIS have always been free or came bundled with an operating system and/or other applications. Meanwhile, Netscape faced increasing criticism for the bugs in its products; critics claimed that the company suffered from '[[Creeping featurism|featuritis]]' – putting a higher priority on adding new features than on making them work properly. This was particularly true with Netscape Navigator 2, which was only on the market for 5 months in early 1996 before being replaced by Netscape Navigator 3. The tide of public opinion, having once lauded Netscape as the [[David]] to Microsoft's [[Goliath]], steadily turned negative, especially when Netscape experienced its first bad quarter at the end of 1997 and underwent a large round of lay-offs in January 1998. Netscape chief financial officer [[Peter Currie]] described the mid 1990s as &quot;hectic and crazy&quot; and that the company was undone by factors both internal and external.&lt;ref name=twsOctE23&gt;{{cite news
 |author=Alan T. Saracevic
 |title= Silicon Valley: It's where brains meet bucks
 |work=San Francisco Chronicle
 |quote= Some of the best stuff at the conference came during a session ... Peter Currie ... Both guys were real candid about how hectic and crazy things were back at Netscape, and Homer especially pointed out that the company was undone by a variety of factors, internal and external. 
 |date= October 23, 2005
 |url= http://articles.sfgate.com/2005-10-23/business/17397107_1_mike-homer-netscape-seed-money
 |accessdate=October 14, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Open sourcing===
January 1998 was also the month that Netscape started the [[open source]] [[Mozilla]] project. Netscape publicly released the [[source code]] of Netscape Communicator 4.0 in the hopes that it would become a popular open source project. It placed this code under the [[Netscape Public License]], which was similar to the [[GNU General Public License]] but allowed Netscape to continue to publish proprietary work containing the publicly released code. However, after having released the Communicator 4.0 code this way, Netscape proceeded to work on Communicator 4.5 which was focused on improving email and enterprise functionality. It eventually became clear that the Communicator 4.0 browser was too difficult to develop, and open source development was halted on this codebase. Instead, the open source development shifted to a next generation browser built from scratch. Using the newly built [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]] [[layout engine]], this browser had a much more modular architecture than Communicator 4.0 and was therefore easier to develop with a large number of programmers. It also included an XML user interface language named [[XUL]] that allowed single development of a user interface that ran on Windows, Macintosh, and Linux.

The [[United States Department of Justice]] filed an [[United States v. Microsoft|antitrust case]] against Microsoft in May 1998. Netscape was not a plaintiff in the case, though its executives were subpoenaed and it contributed much material to the case, including the entire contents of the 'Bad Attitude' internal discussion forum.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wired.com/news/politics/0,1283,14743,00.html| title=Microsoft Subpoenas Bad Attitude|accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1998, Netscape acquired web directory site NewHoo for the sum of $1&amp;nbsp;million, renamed it the [[Open Directory Project]], and released its database under an [[open content]] license.

===Acquisition by America Online===
{{Citations missing|section|date=October 2008}}
[[America Online]] (AOL) on November 24, 1998 announced it would acquire Netscape Communications in a tax-free stock-swap valued at US$4.2&amp;nbsp;billion at the time of the announcement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.cnet.com/2100-1023-218360.html| title=AOL buys Netscape for $4.2 billion}}&lt;/ref&gt; This merger was ridiculed by many who believed that the two corporate cultures could not possibly mesh; one of its most prominent critics was longtime Netscape developer [[Jamie Zawinski]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} The acquisition was seen as a way for AOL to gain a bargaining chip against Microsoft, to let it become less dependent on the Internet Explorer web browser. Others believed that AOL was interested in Netcenter, or Netscape's web properties, which drew some of the highest traffic worldwide. Eventually, Netscape's server products and its Professional Services group became part of iPlanet, a joint marketing and development alliance between AOL and Sun Microsystems. On November 14, 2000, AOL released Netscape 6, based on the Mozilla 0.6 source code. (Version 5 was skipped.) Unfortunately, Mozilla 0.6 was far from being stable yet, and so the effect of Netscape 6 was to further drive people away from the Netscape brand. It was not until August 2001 that Netscape 6.1 appeared, based on Mozilla 0.9.2 which was significantly more robust. A year later came Netscape 7.0, based on the Mozilla 1.0 core.

===Disbanding ===
After the Microsoft antitrust case found that Microsoft held and had abused monopoly power, AOL filed a suit against it for damages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.com.com/2100-1001-820227.html| title=AOL's Netscape Sues Microsoft|accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; This suit was settled in May 2003 when Microsoft paid US $750&amp;nbsp;million to AOL and agreed to share some technologies, including granting AOL a license to use and distribute Internet Explorer royalty-free for seven years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.com.com/2100-1032-1011296.html| title=Microsoft to pay AOL $750&amp;nbsp;million|accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.com.com/2100-1032_3-1011356.html| title=Is this the end of Netscape?|accessdate=July 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was considered to be the death knell for Netscape.

On July 15, 2003, [[Time Warner]] (formerly AOL Time Warner) disbanded Netscape. Most of the programmers were laid-off, and the Netscape logo was removed from the building. However, the Netscape 7.2 web browser (developed in-house rather than with Netscape staff) was released by [[AOL]] on August 18, 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pcpro.co.uk/news/news_story.php?id=62001| title=Netscape Internet Software Updated|accessdate=July 14, 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060623074531/http://www.pcpro.co.uk/news/news_story.php?id=62001 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = June 23, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Red Hat]] announced on September 30, 2004 that it had acquired large portions of the Netscape Enterprise Suite and was planning to convert them into an open source product to be bundled with [[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=04/09/30/169253 |title=Red Hat Acquires Netscape Server Products |publisher=Slashdot |date=September 30, 2004 |accessdate=May 23, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 1, 2005, Red Hat released [[Fedora Directory Server]].

On October 12, 2004, the popular developer website Netscape DevEdge was shut down by AOL. DevEdge was an important resource for Internet-related technologies, maintaining definitive documentation on the Netscape browser, documentation on associated technologies like HTML and JavaScript, and popular articles written by industry and technology leaders such as [[Danny Goodman]]. Some content from DevEdge has been republished at the [[Mozilla]] website.

===Final release of the browser===
[[Image:Netscape-logo.png|thumb|128px|Netscape logo 2005–2007, still used in some portals]]
The Netscape brand name continued to be used extensively. The company once again had its own programming staff devoted to the development and support for the series of [[Netscape (web browser)|web browsers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ufaq.org/modules.php?name=Forums&amp;file=viewtopic&amp;p=23612#23612 UFAQ. org – &quot;Announcing Netscape 9&quot; by Jay Garcia] Retrieved on February 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Netscape also maintained the [[Netscape#Propeller|Propeller]] web portal, which was a popular social-news site, similar to [[Digg]], which was given a new look in June 2006. AOL marketed a [[#Netscape Internet Service|discount ISP service]] under the Netscape brand name.

A new version of the Netscape browser, [[Netscape Navigator 9]], based on [[Firefox]] 2, was released in October 2007. It featured a sleek green and grey interface. In November 2007, IE had 77.4% of the browser market, Firefox 16.0% and Netscape 0.6%, according to Net Applications, an Internet metrics firm.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.informationweek.com/news/showArticle.jhtml?articleID=205204433 |title=AOL Kills Netscape's Future, Leaves Firefox to Battle IE |accessdate=December 29, 2007 |author=Gonsalves, Antone |date= December 28, 2007&lt;!-- 03:25&amp;nbsp;pm --&gt;|work=Informationweek.com |publisher=CMP Media LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On December 28, 2007, AOL announced that on February 1, 2008 it would drop support for the Netscape web browser and would no longer develop new releases. The date was later extended to March 1&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blog.netscape.com/2007/12/28/end-of-support-for-netscape-web-browsers/| title=End of Support for Netscape web browsers | publisher=Netscape Blog| author=Tom Drapeau | accessdate=December 28, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; to allow a major security update and to add a tool to assist users in migrating to other browsers. These additional features were included in the final version of [[Netscape Navigator 9]] (version 9.0.0.6), released on February 20, 2008.

==Software==
{{Main|Netscape (web browser)}}

===Classic releases===
====Netscape Navigator (versions 0.9–4.08)====
[[Image:Netscape2.02 Screenshot 800x924.jpg|thumb|Netscape Navigator 2.02]]
{{Main|Netscape Navigator}}

Netscape Navigator was Netscape's web browser from versions 1.0–4.8. The first [[beta version]]s were released in 1994 and were called Mosaic and later Mosaic Netscape. Then, a legal challenge from the [[National Center for Supercomputing Applications]] (makers of [[NCSA Mosaic]]), which many of Netscape's founders used to develop, led to the name Netscape Navigator. The company's name also changed from Mosaic Communications Corporation to Netscape Communications Corporation.

The browser was easily the most advanced available and so was an instant success, becoming market leader while still in beta. Netscape's feature-count and market share continued to grow rapidly after version 1.0 was released. Version 2.0 added a full email reader called Netscape Mail, thus transforming Netscape from a mere web browser to an [[Internet suite]]. The main distinguishing feature of the email client was its ability to display [[HTML]]. During this period, the suite was called Netscape Navigator.

Version 3.0 of Netscape (the first beta was codenamed &quot;Atlas&quot;) was the first to face any serious competition in the form of [[Microsoft]] [[Internet Explorer]] 3.0. But Netscape easily remained the number one browser for the time being.

Netscape also released a Gold version that incorporated [[JavaScript]], [[RSA (algorithm)|RSA]] security and an [[Apple Inc.]] [[QuickTime]] decoder.

====Netscape Communicator (versions 4.0–4.8)====
[[Image:OS2 Netscape Communicator 4.61.png|thumb|Netscape Communicator 4.61 for OS/2 Warp]]
{{Main|Netscape Communicator}}

Netscape 4 addressed the problem of Netscape Navigator being used as both the name of the suite and the browser contained within it by renaming the suite to Netscape Communicator. After five preview releases in 1996–1997, Netscape released the final version of Netscape Communicator in June 1997. This version, more or less based on Netscape Navigator 3 Code, updated and added new features. The new suite was successful, despite increasing competition from Internet Explorer (IE) 4.0 (which had a more advanced HTML engine) and problems with the outdated browser core. IE was slow and unstable on the Mac platform until version 4.5. Despite this, Apple entered into an agreement with Microsoft to make IE the default browser on new Mac OS installations, a further blow to Netscape's prestige. The Communicator suite was made up of Netscape Navigator, [[Netscape Mail &amp; Newsgroups]], Netscape Address Book and [[Netscape Composer]] (an HTML editor).

In January 1998, [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] announced that all future versions of its software would be available free of charge and developed by an [[open source]] community, [[Mozilla]]. [[Netscape 5|Netscape Communicator 5.0]] was announced (codenamed &quot;Gromit&quot;). However, its release was greatly delayed, and meanwhile there were newer versions of Internet Explorer, starting with [[Internet Explorer 4|version 4]]. These had more features than the old Netscape version, including better support of [[HTML]] 4, [[Cascading Style Sheets|CSS]], [[Document Object Model|DOM]], and [[ECMAScript]]. The more advanced [[Internet Explorer 5.0]] became the market leader.

In October 1998, Netscape Communicator 4.5 was released. It featured various functionality improvements, especially in the [[Netscape Mail &amp; Newsgroups|Mail and Newsgroups]] component, but did not update the browser core, whose functionality was essentially identical to that of version 4.08. One month later, [[Netscape Communications Corporation]] was bought by [[AOL]]. In November, work on Netscape 5.0 was canceled in favor of developing a [[Rewrite (programming)|completely new program from scratch]].

===Mozilla-based releases===
====Netscape 6 (versions 6.0–6.2.3)====
{{Main|Netscape 6}}

In 1998, an informal group called the [[Mozilla Organization]] was formed and largely funded by Netscape (the vast majority of programmers working on the code were paid by Netscape) to co-ordinate the development of Netscape 5 (codenamed &quot;Gromit&quot;), which would be based on the Communicator source code. However, the aging Communicator code proved difficult to work with and the decision was taken to scrap Netscape 5 and re-write the source code. The re-written source code was in the form of the [[Mozilla Application Suite|Mozilla]] web browser, which, with a few additions, Netscape 6 was based on.

This decision meant that Netscape's next major version was severely delayed. In the meantime, Netscape was taken over by AOL who, acting under pressure from the [[Web Standards Project]], forced its new division to release Netscape 6.0 in 2000. The suite again consisted of Netscape Navigator and the other Communicator components, with the addition of a built-in [[AOL Instant Messenger]] client, Netscape Instant Messenger. However, it was clear that Netscape 6 was not yet ready for release and it flopped badly. It was based on Mozilla 0.6, which was not ready to be used by the general public yet due to many serious bugs that would cause it to crash often or render web pages slowly. Later versions of Netscape 6 were much improved (especially 6.2.x was regarded as a good release), but the browser still struggled to make an impact on a disappointed community.

====Netscape 7 (versions 7.0–7.2)====
{{Main|Netscape (version 7)}}

Netscape 7.0 (based on Mozilla 1.0.1) was released in August 2002 was a direct continuation of Netscape 6 with very similar components. It picked up a few users, but was still very much a minority browser. It did, however, come with the popular [[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape]] Internet radio client. AOL had decided to deactivate Mozilla's popup-blocker functionality in Netscape 7.0, which created an outrage in the community. AOL learned the lesson for Netscape 7.01 and allowed Netscape to reinstate the popup-blocker. Netscape also introduced a new AOL-free-version (without the usual AOL addons) of the browser suite. Netscape 7.1 (codenamed &quot;Buffy&quot; and based on Mozilla 1.4) was released in June 2003.

In 2003, AOL closed down its Netscape division and laid-off or re-assigned all of Netscape's employees. Mozilla. org continued, however, as the independent [[Mozilla Foundation]], taking on many of Netscape's ex-employees. AOL continued to develop Netscape in-house, but, due to there being no staff committed to it, improvements were minimal. One year later, in August 2004, the last version based on Mozilla was released: Netscape 7.2, based on Mozilla 1.7.2.

After an official poll posted on Netscape's community support board in late 2006, speculation arose of the Netscape 7 series of suites being fully supported and updated by Netscape's in-house development team.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6590 Netscape Community Announcement – Netscape 7.2] Retrieved on February 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6303 Netscape Community poll – Should Netscape continue to update 7.2?] Retrieved on February 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mozillazine.org/talkback.html?article=20397 Mozillazine – Netscape 9 announced] Retrieved on February 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; This was not to be.

===Mozilla Firefox-based releases===
====Netscape Browser (version 8.0–8.1.3)====
{{Main|Netscape Browser}}

Between 2005 and 2007, Netscape's releases became known as ''Netscape Browser''. AOL chose to base Netscape Browser on the relatively successful [[Mozilla Firefox]], a re-written version of Mozilla produced by the Mozilla Foundation. This release is not a full Internet suite as before, but is solely a web browser. Other controversial decisions include the browser's being made only for [[Microsoft Windows]] and its featuring both the [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]] [[rendering engine]] of previous releases and the [[Trident (layout engine)|Trident]] engine used in Internet Explorer. AOL's acquisition of Netscape Communications in November 1998&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/8869/deal_is_done_aol_buys_netscape.html PC World Article Nov 24, 1998 12:00 am]&lt;/ref&gt; made it less of a surprise when the company laid off the Netscape team and outsourced development to [[Mercurial Communications]].{{When|date=August 2010}} Netscape Browser 8.1.3 was released on April 2, 2007, and included general bug fixes identified in versions 8.0–8.1.2&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6596 Netscape Community – Netscape 8.1.3] Retrieved on February 8, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=7647&amp;redirCnt=1 Netscape Community – Netscape 8.1.3 released] Retrieved on April 2, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

====Netscape Navigator (version 9.0)====
[[Image:NS9 screenshot.PNG|thumb|Netscape Navigator 9.0]]
{{Main|Netscape Navigator 9}}
[[Netscape Navigator 9]] was released on October 15, 2007. Its features were said to include [[newsfeed]] support and become more integrated with the Propeller Internet portal,&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6418 Netscape 9.0 confirmed on Netscape's community support board] Retrieved on January 24, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; alongside more enhanced methods of discussion, submission and voting on web pages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6926 Netscape 9 – February 20 Announcement] Retrieved on February 20, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; It also sees the browser return to multi-platform support across [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[Linux]] and [[Mac OS X]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6459 Netscape 9.0 30- January 7 announcement] Retrieved on January 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Like Netscape version 8.x, the new release was based upon the popular [[Mozilla Firefox]] (version 2.0), and supposedly had full support of all Firefox [[add-ons]] and [[plugins]], some of which Netscape was already providing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=6558 Netscape 9 – February 6, 2007 announcement] Retrieved on February 6, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Also for the first time since 2004, the browser was produced in-house with its own programming staff.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mozillazine.org/talkback.html?article=20397 Netscape announces cross-platform Netscape 9 to be developed in-house – Mozillazine] Retrieved on February 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; A beta of the program was first released on June 5, 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=8525 Netscape 9.0b1 released] Retrieved on June 5, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The final version was released on October 15, 2007.

===End of development and support===
AOL officially announced&lt;ref&gt;[http://blog.netscape.com/2008/02/20/netscape-9-users-time-to-flock-or-firefox/Netscape 9 Users: Time to Flock or Firefox – The Netscape Blog&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; that support for Netscape Navigator would end on March 1, 2008, and recommended that its users download either the [[Flock browser|Flock]] or [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]] browsers, both of which were based on the same technology.

===Mozilla Thunderbird-based releases===
====Netscape Messenger 9====
{{Main|Netscape Messenger 9}}
On June 11, 2007, Netscape announced Netscape Mercury, a stand-alone Email / News Client that was to accompany Navigator 9. Mercury was based on [[Mozilla Thunderbird]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=8688 Netscape Mercury in progress] Retrieved on June 11, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The product was later renamed Netscape Messenger 9, and an alpha version was released. In December 2007, AOL announced it was canceling Netscape's development of Messenger 9 as well as Navigator 9.

==Original product list==
Netscape's initial product line consisted of:

* [[Netscape Navigator]] web browser for [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]], [[OS/2]], [[Unix]], and [[Linux]]
* Netsite Communications web server, with a web-based configuration interface [http://web.archive.org/web/20080406122059/http://www.mcom.com/MCOM/products_docs/server.html]
* Netsite Commerce web server, simply the Communications server with SSL (https) added
* Netscape Proxy Server

Later Netscape products included:

* Netscape Personal Edition (the browser along with [[Point-to-Point Protocol|PPP]] software and an account creation wizard to sign up with an ISP)
* [[Netscape Communicator]] (a suite which included Navigator along with tools for mail, news, calendar, [[VoIP]], and composing web pages, and was bundled with [[AOL Instant Messenger]] and [[RealAudio]])
* Netscape FastTrack and Enterprise [[web server]]s
* Netscape Collabra Server, a [[Network News Transfer Protocol|NNTP]] news server acquired in a purchase of Collabra Software, Inc.
* Netscape Directory Server, an [[Lightweight Directory Access Protocol|LDAP]] server
* Netscape Messaging Server, an [[Internet Message Access Protocol|IMAP]] and [[Post Office Protocol|POP]] mail server
* Netscape Certificate Server, for issuing [[Transport Layer Security|SSL]] certificates
* Netscape Calendar Server, for group scheduling
* Netscape Compass Server, a [[Web search engine|search engine]] and [[web spider|spider]]
* [[Netscape Application Server]], for designing [[web application]]s
* Netscape Publishing System, for running a commercial site with news articles and charging users per access
* Netscape Xpert Servers
**ECxpert – a server for [[Electronic Data Interchange|EDI]] message exchange
**SellerXpert – [[Business-to-business electronic commerce|B to B]] Commerce Engine
**BuyerXpert – eProcurement Engine
**BillerXpert – Online Bill Paying Engine
**TradingXpert – HTML EDI transaction frontend
**CommerceXpert – Online Retail Store engine
*[[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape]] and [[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape Plus]]

Netscape created the [[JavaScript]] web page scripting language. It also pioneered the development of &quot;push technology,&quot; which effectively allowed web sites to send regular updates of information (weather, stock updates, package tracking, etc.) directly to a user's desktop (aka &quot;webtop&quot;); Netscape's implementation of this was named Netcaster.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catdancers.com/webmags/webrevu/1997/04_18/developers/04_18_97_2.html ]{{Dead link|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, businesses quickly recognized the use of push technology to deliver ads to users, and annoyed users turned off the feature, so Netcaster was short-lived.

Netscape was notable for its [[cross-platform]] efforts. Its client software continued to be made available for Windows ([[Windows 3.1x|3.1]], [[Windows 95|95]], [[Windows 98|98]], [[Windows NT|NT]]), Macintosh, Linux, [[OS/2]], [[BeOS]], and many versions of Unix including [[Digital Equipment Corporation|DEC]], [[Solaris (operating system)|Sun Solaris]], [[Berkeley Software Design|BSDI]], [[IRIX]], [[IBM AIX (operating system)|IBM AIX]], and [[HP-UX]]. Its server software generally was only available for Unix and Windows NT, though some of its servers were made available on Linux, and a version of Netscape FastTrack Server was made available for Windows 95/98. Today, most of Netscape's server offerings live on as the [[Sun Java System]], formerly under the [[Sun ONE]] branding. Although Netscape Browser 8 was Windows only, multi-platform support exists in the [[Netscape Navigator 9]] series of browsers.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot; /&gt;

==Current services==
{{Out of date|date=October 2009}}

===Netscape Internet Service===
Netscape ISP is a 56 kbit/s dial-up service offered at $9.95 per month&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.getnetscape.com/index.adp | title=GetNetscape Home Page | accessdate=March 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; ($6.95 with 12-month commitment). The company serves webpages in a compressed format to increase effective speeds up to 1300 kbit/s (average 500 kbit/s). The [[Internet service provider]] is run by [[AOL]] under the Netscape brand. The low-cost ISP was officially launched on January 8, 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.timewarner.com/corp/newsroom/pr/0,20812,670188,00.html | title=Netscape Launches Low-Cost Internet Access Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its main competitor is [[NetZero]]. Netscape ISP's advertising is generally aimed at a younger demographic, e.g., college students, and people just out of school, as an affordable way to gain access to the Internet.

====Web Accelerator====
The Web Accelerator precompresses text at the Server side to approximately 4% its original size, increasing effective throughput to 1300 kbit/s. The accelerator also precompresses Flash executables and images to approximately 30% and 10%, respectively. Netscape advertises this as &quot;DSL speeds over regular phone lines&quot;, although such speeds are limited to only web browsing, not downloads of files.

Another drawback of this approach is a loss in quality, where the graphics become heavily compacted and smeared, but the speed is dramatically improved such that web pages load in less than 5 seconds.

===Netscape.com===
Netscape always drove lots of traffic from various links included in the browser menus to its web properties. Some say it was very [http://news.cnet.com/Netscape-late-to-leverage-traffic/2100-1023_3-206685.html late to leverage this traffic] for what would become the start of the major [http://www.theregister.co.uk/1998/12/17/netscape_unveils_30m_netcenter_ad/ online portal wars]. When it did, Netcenter, the new name for its notorious http://home.netscape.com site entered the race with Yahoo!, [[Infoseek]], and MSN, which Google would only join years later.

The original Netscape.com was discontinued in June 2006, replaced by the site that would eventually become [[Propeller.com]]. Two continuations of the original Netscape.com portal are available; [http://www.compuserve.com/ Compuserve.com], the Web site of [[Compuserve]], and [http://isp.netscape.com/ ISP.Netscape.com], the Web site for Netscape's dial-up discount ISP service, continue to use the Netscape.com layout as it was before June 2006. Of the two, only the latter explicitly uses the Netscape branding.

Netscape.com is currently an AOL Netscape-branded mirror duplicate of the AOL.com portal with the [[URL]] http://netscape.aol.com/ [http://netscape.aol.com], replacing the former Social News website in September 2007. The social news site moved to the Propeller.com domain, where it stayed until ending operations in October 2010. It features facilities such as news, sports, horoscopes, dating, movies, music and more. The change has come to much criticism amongst many site users, because the site has effectively become an AOL clone, and simply re-directs to regional AOL portals in some areas across the globe. Netscape's exclusive features, such as the [http://blog.netscape.com Netscape Blog], [http://newsquake.netscape.com Netscape NewsQuake], [http://browser.netscape.com Netscape Navigator], [http://my.netscape.com My Netscape] and [http://community.netscape.com Netscape Community] pages, are less accessible from the AOL Netscape designed portal and in some countries not accessible at all without providing a full URL or completing an [[Internet search]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;nav=messages&amp;tid=9781&amp;tsn= Netscape Community responses]. Retrieved on September 20, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  The new AOL Netscape site was originally previewed in August 2007 before moving the existing site in September 2007.&lt;ref&gt;[http://community.netscape.com/n/pfx/forum.aspx?tsn=1&amp;nav=messages&amp;webtag=ws-nscpbrowser&amp;tid=9382 New Netscape Portal – Netscape Community] Retrieved on August 14, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Netscape.co.uk now redirects to AOL Search, with no Netscape branding at all.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.netscape.co.uk|title=Netscape.co.uk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propeller===
{{Main|Propeller.com}}
Netscape also operated the site [http://www.propeller.com Propeller], which is a [[social news]] aggregator, similar to [[Digg]], and formally known as Netscape.com between June 2006 and September 2007.

Revised in late 2007, propeller.com has been re-released and the use of the new social structure has spawned over 1,000,000 pages within a 2.5 month period. It shut down October 1, 2010.

===Open Directory Project===
{{Main|Open Directory Project}}
The '''Open Directory Project''' ('''ODP'''), also known as '''dmoz''' (from '''d'''irectory.'''moz'''illa.org, its original [[domain name]]), is a multilingual [[open content]] [[Web directory|directory]] of [[World Wide Web]] links owned by Netscape that is constructed and maintained by a [[virtual community|community]] of volunteer editors.

===Netscape Search===
Netscape operated a search engine, [http://search.netscape.com Netscape Search], which now redirects to [[AOL|AOL Search]] (which itself now merely serves [[Google]] search results). Another version of Netscape Search formerly found at [http://www.netscape.com/search netscape.com/search], was incorporated into Propeller, which has since closed.

===Netscape Forum Center===
Netscape also has a wide variety of community-based [[Internet forum|forums]] within [http://community.netscape.com Netscape Forum Center], including its [[Netscape (web browser)|browser]]'s community support board. To post on the forums, users must possess an [[User (computing)|AOL Screenname]] account in which to sign in, referred to within the site as the ''Netscape Network''. The same service is also available through [http://community.compuserve.com Compuserve Forum Center].

===Other sites===
Netscape also operates a number of country-specific Netscape portals, including [http://www.netscape.ca Netscape Canada] among others. The portal of [http://www.netscape.de Netscape Germany] was shut down in June 2008.

The [http://blog.netscape.com Netscape Blog] was written by Netscape employees discussing the latest on Netscape products and services. [http://newsquake.netscape.com Netscape NewsQuake] (formally ''Netscape Reports'') is Netscape's news and opinion blog, including video clips and discussions. As of October 2011, no new posts have been made on either of these blogs since August 2008.

==See also==
{{Portal box|San Francisco Bay Area|Companies|Internet}}
*[[Mozilla]]
*[[SeaMonkey]]
*[[The Book of Mozilla]]
*[[Code Rush]], a 1998 documentary about Netscape engineers.
*[[AOL Radio|Radio@Netscape]]
*[[Netscape (web browser)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Further reading ==
* [[James H. Clark|Clark, Jim]], ''Netscape Time: The Making of the Billion-Dollar Start-Up That Took On Microsoft'', New York : St. Martin's Press, 1999

==External links==
*[http://netscape.aol.com/ AOL.com – Netscape]
*[http://archive.netscape.com/releases The Netscape Archive]
*[http://blog.netscape.com/ The Netscape Blog]
*[http://www.ufaq.org/ The Netscape Unofficial FAQ]
*[http://sillydog.org/narchive/ Netscape Browser Archive], SillyDog701
*[http://www.holgermetzger.de/Netscape_History.html A Netscape Timeline], Holger Metzger
*[http://home.mcom.com/ Mosaic Communications Corporation]
*[http://www.getburn.com/netscape-navigator/1254.html/ Netscape navigator 9.0.06 ]
{{AOL Inc.}}
{{Netscape}}
{{Early web browsers}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}

[[Category:Netscape| ]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1994]]
[[Category:AOL]]
[[Category:Defunct computer companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies formerly listed on NASDAQ]]
[[Category:Companies based in Mountain View, California]]

[[ar:نتسكيب]]
[[ca:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[cv:Netscape]]
[[cs:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[de:Netscape Communications]]
[[es:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[fr:Netscape Communications]]
[[ko:넷스케이프]]
[[hi:नेटस्केप]]
[[id:Netscape]]
[[ia:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[it:Netscape Communications]]
[[he:נטסקייפ]]
[[ka:Netscape Navigator]]
[[mg:Netscape Communications]]
[[ml:നെറ്റ്‌സ്കേപ്]]
[[nl:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[ja:ネットスケープコミュニケーションズ]]
[[no:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[nn:Netscape Communications Corporation]]
[[pl:Netscape Communications]]
[[pt:Netscape]]
[[ru:Netscape Communications]]
[[sl:Netscape]]
[[fi:Netscape]]
[[sv:Netscape]]
[[tr:Netscape]]
[[vi:Netscape]]
[[zh:網景]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
