<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2202827" ns="0" title="Willem Oltmans"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox journalist
| name             = Willem Oltmans
| image            = Willem Oltmans.jpg
| caption          = 
| birthname        = Willem Leonard Oltmans
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|1925|06|10|mf=y}}
| birth_place      = [[Huizen]], [[Netherlands]]
| death_date       = {{Death date and age|2004|9|30|1925|06|10|mf=y}}
| death_place      = [[Amsterdam]], [[Netherlands]]
| education        = [[Nyenrode Business University]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Yale University]]
| occupation       = [[Investigative journalism|Investigative Journalist]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Author]]
| alias            = 
| title            = 
| family           = 
| spouse           = 
| domestic_partner =
| children         = 
| relatives        = 
| ethnicity        = 
| religion         = 
| years_active     = 1950-2004
| salary           = 
| networth         = 
| credits          = 
| agent            = 
| URL              =
}}

'''Willem Leonard Oltmans''' (June 10, 1925 - September 30, 2004) was a [[Netherlands|Dutch]] investigative journalist and author who did not hesitate to pro-actively intervene in international politics. 

Due to the highly critical and opposite stance he often took towards Dutch global politics, as of 1956 the Dutch government conspired to keep him out of work. During a lingering lawsuit (1991–2000), involving the Royal family, parties agreed to a binding arbitration in which the state had to pay him 8 million guilders in damages in 2000 (approx. 4 million in 2000 US dollars, 3.6 million euro's, over 5.6 million dollar these days). As an erudite orator Oltmans straightforward and uncompromising behaviour made him a striking media personality and unique phenomenon in Dutch society.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;&gt;[http://www.inghist.nl/Onderzoek/Projecten/BWN/lemmata/bwn6/oltmans Biography at the 'Netherlands Institute of History' (ING)]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
Oltmans was born into a wealthy family with roots in the [[Dutch East Indies]]. He studied at the prestigious [[Nyenrode Business University]] (1946) and [[Yale University]] (1948), without graduading. Originally intend on a career with the diplomatic corps of the foreign service, he ended up working in press offices in the Netherlands (1953–1955). He married in 1955 and worked as a free lance reporter in Rome in 1956. There he befriended Indonesian president [[Sukarno]], which started his remarkable career as a controversial journalist.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt;

Convinced that a well connected and informed individual could play a decisive role in the international political arena, he assumed a pro-active part in global political developments, becoming both a news reporter and news maker.

== Dutch state conspiracy ==
Against the will of the Dutch government, Oltmans interviewed [[Indonesia]]n president [[Sukarno]] in 1956. Once he became a confidant of Sukarno and part of his inner circle he took it upon himself to convince the broader public in the Netherlands of the legitimacy of Sukarno's viewpoints. In 1957 he pleaded for the transfer of [[Dutch New Guinea]] to Indonesia while in Indonesia. He claimed to have prevented a Dutch war against Indonesia over New Guinea by sending a memo to US president Kennedy. Since then [[Joseph Luns]], minister of foreign affairs covertly tried everything to sabotage Oltmans' career, with much success: for a long time, Oltmans was forced to live off welfare. Luns who now had become Oltmans' [[wikt:nemesis|nemesis]] called him a 'one engine mosquito'. In 1995 Oltmans published his book 'My friend Sukarno'.

He fought a long law suit (1991–2000) against the Dutch state, which he eventually won. In 2000 a commission awarded him eight million guilders (four million dollars) in damages, after taxes. Having paid two million guilders in lawyer's fees, Oltmans bought a penthouse on a canal in Amsterdam and a Steinway piano.

== Kennedy conspiracy ==
Oltmans was based in the USA in the 1960s, where he worked as a reporter for Dutch TV broadcaster [[Nederlandse Omroep Stichting|NOS]] and established ties to president Kennedy's closest circle of advisors.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt; After US president [[John F. Kennedy|John Kennedy]] was assassinated in [[Dallas]] in 1963, Oltmans interviewed the mother of accused assassin [[Lee Harvey Oswald]]: Marguerite Oswald. Further investigation led him to Oswald's babysitter baron de Mohrenschildt. According to Oltmans, baron [[George de Mohrenschildt]], who had ties to the [[CIA]], was the architect behind the killing. In 1977 de Mohrenschildt agreed to disclose information to Oltmans, but disappeared from their meeting place and was found dead in [[Florida]] a few weeks later.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boekenroute.nl/gasten/gtn1Auteur.aspx?AuteurID=6359 Oltmans, Willem ''&quot;Reportage over de Kennedy-moordenaars.&quot;'' (1977)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0kCCmkkYymU  CBS tv news report dd. 1977]&lt;/ref&gt;

Intent on irony, Oltmans played the role of de Mohrenschildt in [[Oliver Stone]]'s 1991 film about the assassination, ''[[JFK (film)|JFK]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jfk-online.com/jfkcameooltmans.html  Article about Oltmans cameo in the movie on the JFK website.]&lt;/ref&gt; b

== Oltmans in the Soviet Union ==
In the eighties Oltmans endeavoured to create a more balanced opinion in the West about the [[Soviet Union]]. Looking for a more poised perspective on the one sided bad image of the [[evil empire]]'s [[communist]] power he often traveled to [[Russia]]. Together with the Kremlin's foreign expert [[Georgi Arbatov]] he wrote the book 'The Soviet position' elaborating on [[Moscow]]'s perspective on the East-West issues in 1981. The book received much attention and was published in several languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt;

==Oltmans in Suriname==
In the eighthies Oltmans also actively interfered with the post-colonial Dutch-Suriname relationship. He recognised a bilateral relationship based in negative sentiments similar to the Dutch-Indonesian relationship. Intend on playing a mediating role Oltmans traveled to [[Suriname]] to interview military dictator [[Bouterse]]. He published a book that was banned in Suriname and misunderstood in the Netherlands.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt;

== Oltmans in South Africa==
Due to the ban imposed on him by Luns Oltmans was forced to help support himself through his family's inheritance. With the death of his parents (1966 and 1974) and after some bad financial investments he was to seek additional means of livelihood. In the late eighties he intended to use his large global network as a consultant to introduce entrepreneurs to Eastern European business opportunities. Through a string of quarrels with his stakeholders this initiative failed completely and Oltmans left for [[South Africa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt;

Both his brothers had settled in South Africa in 1948. He had visited the country regularly and in 1990 decided to settle there permanently. In South Africa he continued his tendency of actively intervening in local politics. His investgative reporting was not appreciated by the shaky South African regime of the time and in August 1992 he was deported on charges of [[espionage]]. Oltmans always insited the Dutch Security Service was involved in his deportation.&lt;ref name=&quot;inghist.nl&quot;/&gt;

==Publications (selection)==
* ''Persona Non Grata'' (Papieren Tijger, Breda, 1994) ISBN-13: 978-90-6728-081-5
* ''Mijn vriend Sukarno'' (Spectrum, Utrecht, 1995) ISBN 9027447624
* ''De staat van bedrog'' (Papieren Tijger, Breda, 1998) ISBN-13: 978-90-6728-095-2
* ''Cry for war'' (Papieren Tijger, Breda, 2003) ISBN-13: 978-90-6728-151-5
* ''Laatste wapenfeiten'' (Papieren Tijger, Breda, 2009) ISBN-13: 978-90-6728-239-0

== References ==
===Bibliography===
* Oltmans, Willem ''“Mijn vriend Sukarno”'' (Spectrum, Utrecht, 1995) ISBN 9027447624
* Oden, Edwin ''“De man van acht miljoen”'' (Balans, Amsterdam, 2010) ISBN 978 94 600 3283 7 [http://www.uitgeverijbalans.nl/web/Auteurs/Boek-5.htm?dbid=29121&amp;typeofpage=118930]

===External links===
* [http://www.inghist.nl/Onderzoek/Projecten/BWN/lemmata/bwn6/oltmans  Biography - Dutch Institute of Netherlands history]
* [http://www.kb.nl/index-en.html  National Library of the Netherlands Official website]
* [http://www.kb.nl/dossiers/oltmans/index.html  Online dossier - National library of Netherlands.]
* [http://www.antenna.nl/~fwillems/nl/oltmans/index.html  Online selection of essays.]
* [http://tvblik.nl/dossier/willem-oltmans  Online selection of TV interviews.]
* [http://www.vkblog.nl/bericht/349105/Willem_Oltmans  Online portrait by newspaper 'de Volkskrant'.]

===Notes &amp; citations ===
{{reflist|2}}

{{Persondata
| NAME              = Oltmans, Willem
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = June 10, 1925
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Huizen, Netherlands
| DATE OF DEATH     = September 30, 2004
| PLACE OF DEATH    = Amsterdam, Netherlands
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Oltmans, Willem}}
[[Category:1925 births]]
[[Category:2004 deaths]]
[[Category:Dutch journalists]]
[[Category:Dutch writers]]
[[Category:Dutch non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Dutch political writers]]
[[Category:Dutch television personalities]]
[[Category:Dutch people of Indonesian descent]]
[[Category:Dutch republicans]]
[[Category:Gay writers]]
[[Category:Gay actors]]
[[Category:LGBT people from the Netherlands]]
[[Category:LGBT journalists]]
[[Category:LGBT television personalities]]
[[Category:LGBT memoirists]]
[[Category:Investigative journalists]]
[[Category:Researchers of the John F. Kennedy assassination]]
[[Category:Conspiracy theories regarding the John F. Kennedy assassination]]
[[Category:Nyenrode Business University alumni]]
[[Category:Yale University alumni]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Deaths by euthanasia]]
[[Category:Euthanasia in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:People from Huizen]]

[[eo:Willem Oltmans]]
[[nl:Willem Oltmans]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
