<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2203170" ns="0" title="WCIX"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{unref|date=November 2011}}
{{Infobox_Broadcast
| call_letters             = WCIX
| station_logo             = [[File:WCIX Logo.png]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Image:WCIA.jpg]]
| station_slogan           =
| station_branding         = X 49&lt;br/&gt;WCIA 3 &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;
| analog                   =
| digital                  = 13 ([[very high frequency|VHF]]) &amp;&lt;br/&gt;[[WCIA]]-DT 48.2 ([[UHF]])&lt;br/&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 49 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| other_chs                =
| subchannels              = 49.1 [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br/&gt;49.2 [[CBS]]
| affiliations             =
| network                  =
| founded                  =
| airdate                  = 1967 (originally low-power W49AA 1967-1982)
| location                 = [[Springfield, Illinois|Springfield]] / [[Decatur, Illinois|Decatur]] /&lt;br/&gt;[[Champaign, Illinois|Champaign]] / [[Urbana, Illinois]]
| former_callsigns         = WCFN-TV (1985&amp;ndash;2011)
| callsign_meaning         = disambiguation from '''WCI'''A
| former_channel_numbers   = 49 (UHF analog, 1982&amp;ndash;2009)&lt;br/&gt;53 (UHF digital, 2002&amp;ndash;2009)
| owner                    = [[Nexstar Broadcasting Group]]
| licensee                 = Nexstar Broadcasting, Inc.
| sister_stations          = WCIA
| former_affiliations      = CBS (1985-2002, as satellite of WCIA)&lt;br/&gt;[[UPN]] (2002-2006)
| effective_radiated_power = 5 [[kilowatt|kW]]
| HAAT                     = 175.5 m
| class                    =
| facility_id              = 42116
| coordinates              = {{coord|39|47|27|N|89|30|53|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage                 =
}}

'''WCIX''' is the [[MyNetworkTV]]-affiliated [[television station]] for [[Central Illinois]] that is licensed to [[Springfield, Illinois|Springfield]]. It broadcasts a [[high-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[VHF]] channel 13 from a transmitter east of the city. Owned by the [[Nexstar Broadcasting Group]], the station is sister to [[CBS]] affiliate [[WCIA]] and the two share studios on South Neil Street (a.k.a. [[U.S. Route 45 in Illinois|U.S. 45]]) in downtown [[Champaign, Illinois|Champaign]]. They also operate a Springfield facility including a newsroom and sales office on East Edwards Street near the [[Illinois State Capitol]] along with a newsroom on North Water Street in Downtown [[Decatur, Illinois|Decatur]]. [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on WCIX includes: ''[[Family Guy]]'', ''[[Everybody Hates Chris]]'', ''[[America's Funniest Home Videos]]'', and ''[[The Insider (TV series)|The Insider]]''. They can also be seen on WCIA's second digital subchannel on [[UHF]] channel 48 from a transmitter in [[Seymour, Illinois|Seymour]].

==History==
Before WCIA signed on in 1953, it originally wanted to build its tower in [[White Heath, Illinois|White Heath]], near Decatur. The tower would have been placed on some of the highest ground in Central Illinois However, just after construction began, Prairie Television (owner of WTVP, now [[WAND]]) filed an objection. Even though it was obvious that Champaign / [[Urbana, Illinois|Urbana]] and Springfield / Decatur were going to be considered a single market, Prairie claimed WCIA was encroaching on its territory.  To avoid delays, that station moved its transmitter to its current location near Seymour.

WCIA quickly established itself as the dominant station in the region, despite its signal issues i the western half of the market.  Eventually, then-owner Midwest Television decided to open a low-powered relay of WCIA on UHF channel 49 to get better coverage in the state capital. That relay launched in 1967 under the calls '''W49AA'''. In 1982, it was upgraded to a full-power satellite under the calls '''WCFN'''.  In both cases, the station was a straight simulcast of WCIA, even airing WCIA's commercials.  However, it was mentioned in WCIA's legal IDs.

In 2002, WCFN broke off and became the area's [[UPN]] affiliate.  To make up for the shortfall in coverage, it was added to WCIA's digital subcarrier. WCIA carries WCFN's second digital subchannel for the same reason; the WCIA schedule is carried on WCFN-DT2 in [[1080i]] [[high definition television|HD]], while the main WCFN schedule is in [[480i]] standard definition.  After [[The WB]] and UPN closed down and merged to become [[The CW]], this station joined the other new network, MyNetworkTV, that is owned by [[News Corporation]] and sister to [[Fox Network|Fox]].

In early-2007, WCFN and the [[Illinois High School Association]] came to an agreement to carry coverage of IHSA tournaments that are televised throughout the state. Central Illinois had previously been without an over-the-air flagship station for these kind of events. Also, beginning with the [[2010-11 NBA season]], WCFN carried [[Chicago Bulls]], [[Chicago Cubs]], and [[Chicago White Sox]] games aired in the Chicagoland area by [[WCIU]]. Before 2011, WCFN would carry [[Labor Day]] coverage of the [[US Open (tennis)|US Open]] from [[CBS]] because of WCIA's commitment to air the [[MDA Telethon]]. In 2011, the tennis coverage shifted to WCIA since the telethon was limited to the night before Labor Day.

On August 29, 2011 the station's callsign was changed to [http://licensing.fcc.gov/cgi-bin/ws.exe/prod/cdbs/pubacc/prod/call_hist.pl?Facility_id=42116&amp;Callsign=WCFN WCIX], call letters formerly used by [[WFOR-TV]] in [[Miami, Florida|Miami]] for years until 1995, when that station changed from Channel 6 to Channel 4 and swapped with [[NBC]]'s [[WTVJ]]. The station's logo was changed to resemble that of sister station [[KARZ-TV]] in [[Little Rock, Arkansas]], which is also a MyNetworkTV affiliate associated with a Big Three-affiliated station (in that case, [[KARK-TV]]).

==Newscasts==
WCFN's ''Primetime News at 9'' was launched on April 7, 2005 using the news resources of WCIA. The broadcast originated from that station's Champaign headquarters and was targeted specifically at a Springfield audience. The name was altered to ''myCFN News at 9'' in 2006 to reflect the MyNetworkTV affiliation. In 2009, WCIA announced it would cancel the show and launch an hour long 7 o'clock newscast on weeknights beginning September 28. As a result, MyNetworkTV programming now airs out-of-pattern from 8 to 10. In 2006, WCIA began airing an hour-long extension of The Morning Show in WCFN. In 2007, another hour was added to the show. At the end of the 6:00 hour of the show, viewers are always reminded to flip the channel.

'''''The Morning Show'''''&lt;br/&gt;''(Weekday Mornings 7 to 9 a.m.)''
*Anchors:
**Rob Collins
*Weather:
**Robert Reese

'''''WCIA News at 7 on WCIX 49'''''&lt;br/&gt;''(Weeknights 7 to 7:30 p.m.)''&lt;br/&gt;
*Anchor:
**Dave Benton
*Weather:
**Derick Fabert
*Sports:
**Aaron Bennett

''WCIX features additional news personnel from WCIA. See that article for a complete listing.''

==External links==
*[http://illinoishomepage.net WCIX channel 49]
*[http://www.mynetworktv.com/ MyNetworkTV]
*{{TVQ|WCIX}}

{{CDSTV}}
{{NXST TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wcix}}
[[Category:MyNetworkTV affiliates]]
[[Category:Nexstar Broadcasting Group]]
[[Category:Channel 13 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1967]]
[[Category:Television stations in Illinois]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
