<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22042612" ns="0" title="Mikhail Morgulis"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=March 2009}}
{{BLP sources|date=November 2010}}

'''Mikhail Morgulis''' ({{lang-ru|Михаил Моргулис}}) (October 1, 1941– )&lt;ref&gt;Morgulis, Mikhail. Letter to Thomas Beyer, February, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[Russians|Russian]] writer, editor and evangelist. He has broadcast the word of God to millions primarily those living in Russia, Ukraine, Belarus and the former republics of the Soviet Union and to Russian speaking audiences in the United States and Canada.

Mikhail Morgulis was born in Kiev. His adoptive father, Zinovii Morgulis (Приёмный отец Зиновий Моргулис), was a journalist who published in Russian and Ukrainian newspapers and journals. His mother, Liubov Sadanovskaya (Любовь Садановская) was a physician.

Morgulis received his higher education at the Naval College and then Kiev University. He holds an M.A. from Norwich University (Vermont, USA) where he taught in their renown Russian School (Русская школа).   
 
In 1972 Morgulis won a coveted award sponsored by the Ukrainian Union of Soviet Writers and the [[Soviet Ministry of Culture]] for his collection of stories entitled ''It's Hope's Turn'' (''Очередь за надеждой''). In 1977 he emigrated from the Soviet Union going first to Vienna and then Rome before settling in New York City. There he wrote for The ''New Russian Word'' (''Новое Русское Слово'') and ''Russian Thought'' (''Русская Мысль'') in Paris. At the same time he worked in a relief organization for Russian immigrants. His articles and stories also appeared in the journals ''Continent'' (''Континент''), ''Time and Us'' (Время и Мы), ''The World'' (''Мир''), ''The New Journal'' (''Новый журнал'') and ''Panorama'' (''Панорама''),as well as in the literary almanacs ''Three Anniversaries for Andrei Sedykh'' (''Три юбилея Андрея Седых'') and ''Kaleidoscope'' (''Калейдоскоп''). 

In the 1980s he edited two literary journals, ''Literary Abroad'' (''Литературное зарубежье'') and ''Literary Courier'' (''Литературный курьер''), both intended to offer an opportunity for Russian writers and readers in exile primarily in the United States. 

In 1982 he moved to Chicago where he helped establish the Slavic Gospel Press which published over 100 works in Russian, including copies of the Bible and translations of text by C.S. Lewis, G.K. Chesterton, Dietrich Bonhoeffer and others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://barthsnotes.wordpress.com/2008/05/22/meet-mikhail-morgulis/ Richard Bartholomew “Meet Mikhail Morgulis&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Mikhail also began a series of spiritual radio broadcasts to the Soviet Union, beginning with his own literary novellas, ''Farewell, Cranes'' (''До свиданья, журавли''), and ''The Fate of the Clown'' (''Судьба клоуна'') that later appeared as audio-albums.  

In 1990 he was one of the first Russian evangelists to broadcast in the Russian language via Soviet television inside the Soviet Union. In 1991 he visited Russia with a delegation of American spiritual leaders and met with president of USSR Mikhail Gorbachev and other political figures. He prayed in the Kremlin and in the KGB headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.invictory.info/article223.html «А знаете, где вы молилсь? В кабинете Сталина….»]&lt;/ref&gt;

Mikhail Morgulis continues his work today&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.assistnews.net/Stories/2008/s08050111.htm “An Interview with … Russian Journalist Mikhail Morgulis.”]&lt;/ref&gt; through Christian Bridges International (Международный Христианский Мост)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.russianamericanbusiness.org/EN/web_CONTENT/articles/2005.01.20/group_04/1_articl/articl.shtml “What is Christian Bridge International.”]&lt;/ref&gt; and his Spiritual Diplomacy Foundation (Духовная Дипломатия)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christiantelegraph.com/issue510.html “Diplomat of the Year.”]&lt;/ref&gt; located in North Port, Florida. He continues to write and participate in an active ministry.

In 1971 Mkhail Morgulis married Tatiana Titov (Татьяна Николаевна Титова) (September 1, 1949 – ). They have three children, Valeria (1972), Zinovii (1977), and Nikolai (1986).

in 2010 Morgulis appeared on Belarus TV the night of the presidential elections, posing as an official international observer, and behaving like nothing was wrong with the elections.
Morgulis was there to help his friend Lukaschenko get reelected.

==Published books==
*1989 ''Return to the Red Planet: 22 Days in Gorbachev's Backyard'' (Scripture Pr Pubns) ISBN 089693764X.
*1991 ''Dreams of My Life'' (''Сны моей жизни'') (Zoloti vorota) ISBN 5884900031.
*1993 ''The Sermon of the Good Samaratin''  (''Притча о добром самаритянине'') (Moscow). 
*1994 ''What is the Most Terrifying Thing?'' (''Что самое страшное?'') (Moscow).  
*1995 ''The Cross and Love'' (''Крест и Любовь'') (Sacramento). 
*1996 ''Russia, between Sword and Cross''.  With Melissa Rose Marshall. 	
*2001 ''Spiritual Diplomacy: real-life stories'' (''Духовная Дипломатия: невыдуманные истории''). 
*2005 ''Yearning for Paradise'' (''Тоска по раю''). (Moscow).

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.spiritualdiplomacy.org/ Spiritual Diplomacy]
* [http://www.russianamericanbusiness.org/EN/web_CONTENT/articles/2005.01.20/group_04/1_articl/articl.shtml/ Article in Russian American Business]
*[http://www.morgulis.org/ Гостиная Михаила Моргулиса]
*[http://www.morgulis.tv/ Мorgulis TV]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Morgulis, Mikhail
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Morgulis, Mikhail}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Christian writers]]
[[Category:Russian writers]]
[[Category:Television evangelists]]

[[ru:Моргулис, Михаил Зиновьевич]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
