<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22042735" ns="0" title="R. K. Kamboj"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup-afd|date=March 2011}}
{{Orphan|date=January 2011}}
{{BLP refimprove|date=March 2011}}
'''Dr R. K [[Kamboj]]''' ('''''Rajender K Kamboj,  Rajender Kamboj, Raj Kamboj''''') is an  [[India]]n [[Pharmaceutical]] scientist in the area of [[drug discovery]] was born in 1955 to Sh.Karta Ram Kamboj at Village Fatehpur, Distt. [[Yamunanagar]], [[Haryana]]. He did his M.Sc in Biological Sciences in 1977. He joined the [[University of Adelaide]], [[Australia]] in 1981 and completed his Ph.D&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lupin appoints Dr Raj Kamboj as head NCE Research |author= |url=http://www.biospectrumasia.com/content/270608IND6411.asp |newspaper=BioSpectrum Asia Edition |date=27 June 2008 |accessdate=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in March 1986. During his doctoral studies at the University of Adelaide (1981–1986), Kamboj published his researches in ''[[Plant Physiology]]'', a highly cited  peer-reviewed scientific monthly journal published by American Society of Plant Biologists, which publishes articles on the [[physiology]], [[biochemistry]], cellular and molecular [[biology]], [[genetics]], [[biophysics]] and environmental biology of plants. Kamboj's doctoral thesis  was about ''Biochemical Studies on pollen and pollen-pistil interaction in `Petunia hybrida`''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hdl.handle.net/2440/21227 |title=Biochemical studies on pollen and pollen-pistil interaction in `Petunia hybrida` |author=Kamboj, Rajender Kumar |date=1986 |work=Ph.D. Thesis (Dept. of Agricultural Biochemistry) |publisher=[[University of Adelaide]] |accessdate=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

After completing his Ph.D, Dr Kamboj continued to work as research scientist in Australia till 1991. Thereafter, he moved to [[Canada]] to join Allelix Biopharmaceuticals Inc (''a part of NPS Pharmaceuticals, Inc, [[Toronto]]''), as its [[Vice President]] and [[Chief Scientific Officer]]. At Allelix, Kamboj was entrusted with the primary responsibility of managing its drug discovery programs. After working about 12 years with Allelix, Dr Kamboj joined ''Xenon Genetics Inc, [[Vancouver]]'' as its Vice President for [[Drug Discovery]]. In both the companies named above, Dr Kamboj was instrumental in taking the companies from the inception of the drug discovery group all the way to multiple [[license|licensing]] transactions and [[collaboration]]s. 

Dr Kamboj left Xenon Genetics Inc. in June 2008 to join [[Lupin Ltd]], a medium-sized, but aggressive transnational pharmaceutical company from India, where he was appointed President of  ''New Chemical Entity (NCE) Research'' of [[Lupin Ltd]]. In the same year, Kamboj was also appointed president of the ''Novel Drug Discovery and Development of [[Lupin Ltd]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Lupin goes all out to make up for lost chances |author=Satish John and C.H. Unnikrishnan |url=http://www.livemint.com/2010/02/08000106/Lupin-goes-all-out-to-make-up.html |newspaper=[[Mint (newspaper){{!}}Mint]] |date=8 February 2010 |accessdate=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Dr Kamboj has developed an extensive global network of contacts with pharmaceutical industry and academic scientific communities. His experience includes strong contribution to business development, licensing products and technologies, mergers and acquisitions and corporate development activities. He holds over forty (40) [[USA|U.S]] [[patent]] applications (filed and issued), covering the discovery and use of a number of human [[genes]]. He is the author/co-author of over 90 research articles/papers in the field of biomedical field. His career spans more than 29 years in [[research]], 16 years of which is in pharmaceutical industrial R&amp;D setting. 

Dr Kamboj is currently a member of the working group on ''New TB Drugs Team, India''. 

Dr Kamboj is also a member of the ''Market Advisory Groups (MAG)'' of the Asia Pacific Trade Council of [[British Columbia]], Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://apti.teamwork.gov.bc.ca/AboutUs/AsiaPacificTradeCouncil/Documents/india_report.pdf |title=Report of the India Market Advisory Group |author= |date=January 2007 |work= |publisher=Asia Pacific Trade Council |accessdate=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Kamboj, R K
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kamboj, R K}}
[[Category:Kamboj]]
[[Category:Indian educationists]]
[[Category:Indian scientists]]
[[Category:Pharmaceutical scientists]]
[[Category:Living people]]


{{India-med-bio-stub}}
{{India-scientist-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
