<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22053712" ns="0" title="601st Special Forces Group"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=March 2009}}
The '''601st Special Forces Group of general Moravec''' (601. skupina speciálních sil generála Moravce) is a [[special forces]] unit of the Czech Armed Forces. It was officially created in 2003, the product of reorganizations in the [[Military of the Czech Republic]] in this year. However, it has roots that go back as far as 1952 when it was a [[paratroop]] brigade.

==History ==

The 601st Special Forces finds its roots in a paratroop brigade created in 1952. This unit was based in [[Prešov]], [[Slovakia]], but in 1960 it was relocated to [[Prostějov]] and the unit joined the 22nd Paratroop Brigade, which was based in Prostějov. Until 1969 the members of the units were trained according to [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] doctrine, training mass parachute operations, defending points of military interest until the arrival of main ground forces. From 1970 to 1988, the unit began to focus on the training of small reconnaissance groups, which were to be inserted to the rear of an enemy to carry out diversionary and reconnaissance missions.

Members of the 601st Special Forces Group participate or participated in many foreign missions: 

*Saudi Arabia (1990)

*former Yugoslavia 
**[[UNPROFOR]] (1992—1995)
**[[IFOR]] (1996)
**[[SFOR]] (from 1996—2001)
**[[Kosovo Force|KFOR]] (from 1999—2006)

*Albania — [[AFOR]] (1999)

*Afghanistan 
**[[ISAF]] (2002)
**[[Operation Enduring Freedom]] (2004)

*[[Iraq]]
**1991
**[[Operation Enduring Freedom]] (2003)
**[[Multi-National Force – Iraq|MNF (I)]] (2004)
**IZ SFOR (2004)

*[[Kuwait]] — EF (2002, 2003)

6th Special Forces Company was the first Czech Army unit which operated in Kosovo in 1999. It laid foundations for activities of other Czech Army units in this territory. 

So far, the most important mission the Group has taken part in was Operation Enduring Freedom in Afghanistan in 2004. This mission was the first combat operation of the Czech Armed Forces since World War II. More than 100 people participated for six months and, without break, fulfilled their tasks in arduous climatic conditions. 
Participation in this mission was highly appraised by the highest state officials as well as the ACR and coalition partners. 601st SFG has taken a firm position within the world Special Forces elite group.

In the year 1999 this group became the honorary historical name of ''[[František Moravec|general Moravec]]'' from the [[president]] of the [[Czech Republic]].

==External links==
*[http://www.601skss.cz/english/index_en.html Official website]


[[Category:Military units and formations of the Czech Republic]]

[[de:601. skupina speciálních sil]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
