<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2206514" ns="0" title="List of Doctor Who villains"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Doctor Who'' villains}}
{{Redirect|The War Chief|the Age of Empires III expansion pack|Age of Empires III: The War Chiefs}}
{{Redirect|Zaroff|the fictional Richard Connell villain|The Most Dangerous Game}}
{{Use British English|date=May 2011}}
{{tense|date=June 2011}}
{{Refimprove|date=March 2009}}
This is a '''list of villains''' from the long-running British [[science fiction on television|science fiction television]] series ''[[Doctor Who]]''. For other, related lists, [[#See also|see below]].

{{compacttoc}}

==A==
===Helen A===
'''Helen A''', seen in ''[[The Happiness Patrol]]'' (1988),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/classic/episodeguide/happinesspatrol/detail.shtml |title=Doctor Who Classic Episode Guide – The Happiness Patrol – Details |publisher=BBC |date=16 November 1988 |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; is the ruler of a human colony on [[List of Doctor Who planets#T|Terra Alpha]]. Outlawing unhappiness, she brutally controls the population through executions conducted by the Happiness Patrol and Gilbert M's [[List of Doctor Who robots#Kandy Man|Kandy Man]]. Joseph C is her consort and she has a pet Stigorax, called Fifi. Joseph C escapes the city when the Pipe People revolt against Helen A's rule. Fifi is killed, crushed in the pipes below the city during the uprising. Helen A, unable to escape, only comes to understand the [[Seventh Doctor|Doctor's]] notion that happiness can only truly be appreciated when counter-balanced with sadness when she discovers Fifi's remains. Helen A was intended to be a caricature of then British Prime Minister [[Margaret Thatcher]]. In 2010, Sylvester McCoy told the ''Sunday Times'': &quot;Our feeling was that Margaret Thatcher was far more terrifying than any monster the Doctor had encountered.&quot; The Doctor's calls on the drones to down their tools and revolt was intended as a reference to the [[UK miners' strike (1984–1985)|1984–85 miners' strike]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/doctor-who/7235547/Doctor-Who-had-anti-Thatcher-agenda.html &quot;Doctor Who 'had anti-Thatcher agenda'&quot;], ''Daily Telegraph'', 14 February 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abzorbaloff===
The '''Abzorbaloff''' is a monster designed by nine-year-old William Grantham of [[Colchester]], Essex for a &quot;Design a ''[[Doctor Who]]'' Monster&quot; competition held by ''[[Blue Peter]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/news/cult/news/drwho/2006/06/14/32916.shtml |title=Doctor Who (David Tennant and Billie Piper) – News |publisher=BBC |date=14 June 2006 |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The competition was announced in July 2005, and received 43,920 entries. These were judged by Blue Peter editor Richard Marson, presenter [[Gethin Jones]], ''Doctor Who'' producer [[Russell T Davies]] and [[Tenth Doctor]] [[David Tennant]]. The first prize for the competition was to have the monster appear in an episode of ''Doctor Who''. Tennant announced the winner on ''Blue Peter'' on 17 August 2005. Conditions of the competition meant that the monster had to be able to be made from prosthetics and not require [[Computer-generated imagery|CGI]].

Russell T Davies revealed on the ''[[Doctor Who Confidential]]'' episode &quot;New World of Who&quot; that Grantham imagined the Abzorbaloff to be the size of a double-decker bus, so was initially disappointed to see the final size of his creation. However, Grantham's design had not included size specifications (though the remains of the monster's victims on and within his body hinted at his being huge) and a larger size would not have fit the criteria of the competition unless the monster were [[Superimposition|superimposed]] on footage later on a larger scale. Ultimately, CGI was used for some shots of the talking faces on the Abzorbaloff.

Appearing in the episode &quot;[[Love &amp; Monsters]]&quot;, the Abzorbaloff, played by [[Peter Kay]], was a creature that absorbed other living beings into his body with a simple touch. In doing so, the Abzorbaloff made his victims part of himself, adding their memories and knowledge to his own. The victims retain their identity and consciousness for at least several weeks after absorption, during which time their faces can be seen embedded in his flesh, but eventually, those too are eliminated as they are fully absorbed. During this period, however, the absorption process works both ways – in becoming part of the Abzorbaloff, they are able to access his thoughts, just as he is able to access theirs. To restrain his absorption ability, the Abzorbaloff requires the use of a &quot;limitation field&quot;, which limits absorption to physical contact. The Abzorbaloff hails from [[Clom]], the sister planet to [[List of Doctor Who planets#R|Raxacoricofallapatorius]], homeworld of the criminal [[Slitheen]] clan. Despite a passing resemblance to them, the Abzorbaloff spoke of the Raxacoricofallapatorians with contempt.

Seeking to absorb the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]] and his hundreds of years of experience, the Abzorbaloff adopted a human disguise as '''Victor Kennedy''', his limitation field generated by the ornate cane he wielded. Taking charge of &quot;LINDA&quot; (London Investigation 'N' Detective Agency), a small group of ordinary people who followed the exploits of the Doctor, the Abzorbaloff steadily absorbed their numbers one by one, until only Elton Pope remained. Pursuing Pope through the back streets of London, the Abzorbaloff was confronted by the Doctor, who stirred the absorbed victims to fight against the monster. Pulling the Abzorbaloff's body in different directions, the victims made him drop his cane, which Elton snapped in two, destroying the limitation field and causing the Abzorbaloff's absorption power to run out of control. His body collapsed into liquid and was itself absorbed by the Earth.

&quot;Abzorbaloff&quot; is not the actual name of the species, but was coined independently by Elton Pope and the Doctor. The monster was seen to approve of the term, however. Other names thrown at him by the Doctor and Elton included &quot;Abzorbatron&quot;, &quot;Abzorbaling&quot;, &quot;Abzorbatrix&quot; and &quot;Abzorbaclon&quot;.

The ''Doctor Who'' website refers to Slitheen distant cousins by the name of &quot;Absorvalovian Rebels&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/s4/videos/slitheen |title=Doctor Who – Videos – Series Four |publisher=BBC |date=28 March 2008 |accessdate=13 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; in one of [[Jack Harkness|Captain Jack's]] Monster Files.

===Father Angelo===
'''Father Angelo''' was the leader of the monks who captured the Torchwood Estate and gave refuge to a [[Werewolf (Doctor Who)|werewolf]], as seen in &quot;[[Tooth and Claw (Doctor Who)|Tooth and Claw]]&quot; (2006). He sought to take the throne from [[Queen Victoria]], but she shot and killed him although no body was seen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b0074fly |title=One Programmes – Doctor Who, Series 2, Tooth and Claw |publisher=BBC |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Animus===
The '''Animus''' was an alien intelligence from an unknown planet which landed on the planet [[List of Doctor Who planets#V|Vortis]]. It could take over any living creature that was in contact with gold and had already taken control of the [[ant]]-like [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Zarbi|Zarbi]] when [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] and his companions arrived on Vortis in the serial ''[[The Web Planet]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/classic/episodeguide/webplanet/detail.shtml |title=Doctor Who Classic Episode Guide – The Web Planet – Details |publisher=BBC |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of Vortis' surviving lifeforms, the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Optera|Optera]], referred to the Animus as &quot;Pwodarauk&quot;. The Animus manifested itself within an organic, self-healing palace called the Carcinome.

At the end of the story, the Animus's true form was revealed, as resembling an [[octopus]] with some [[arachnid]] features. The [[First Doctor]], [[Ian Chesterton|Ian]], [[Barbara Wright (Doctor Who)|Barbara]] and [[Vicki]] help the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Menoptra|Menoptra]] to destroy the Animus using the Menoptra's secret weapon, the Isop-tope.

The Animus has returned or been mentioned in several [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] stories. In the [[Virgin Missing Adventures|Missing Adventure]] ''[[Twilight of the Gods (Doctor Who)|Twilight of the Gods]]'' by Christopher Bulis, the [[Second Doctor]], [[Jamie McCrimmon|Jamie]] and [[Victoria Waterfield|Victoria]] return to Vortis and encounter a seed of the Animus which had survived. The [[Virgin New Adventures|New Adventure]] ''[[All-Consuming Fire]]'' by [[Andy Lane]] identified the Animus with the [[Great Old One]] [[Zhar (Great Old One)#Lloigor|Lloigor]] from [[H. P. Lovecraft]]'s [[Cthulhu Mythos]]. An article by [[Russell T Davies]] in the ''Doctor Who Annual 2006'' says that the &quot;Greater Animus perished&quot; in the [[Time War (Doctor Who)|Time War]], &quot;and its Carsenome ''(sic)'' Walls fell into dust.&quot;

===Azal===
'''Azal''' was the Dæmon from the planet Dæmos that terrorised Devil's End in the [[Third Doctor]] story ''[[The Dæmons]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;episodeguide1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/classic/episodeguide/daemons/detail.shtml |title=Doctor Who Classic Episode Guide – The Daemons – Details |publisher=BBC |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Summoned by [[Master (Doctor Who)|the Master]], Azal had a [[gargoyle]], by the name of [[#Bok|Bok]], as a servant. Azal landed on Earth over a million years ago and did help in the development of mankind. Azal was awakened after an archaeological professor, Professor Horner, who was digging out the cave at Devil's Hump that was a part of Azal's ship. Azal created a heat barrier around Devil's End. Azal had contact with the Master though the ceremony with the Master's coven. The Master wanted Azal's power, but he wanted to give it to the Doctor, but the Doctor refused. Then Azal decided to give the Master his power and destroy the Doctor. Jo Grant told Azal to kill her instead. Azal, not understanding her willingness to give her own life for someone else's, was thus destroyed when his own power turned against him in his confusion, and destroyed himself and his ship at the dig at Devil's Hump was destroyed. Things at Devil's End returned to normal, the heat barrier gone and Bok is a normal statue again.

==B==
===Baltazar===
'''Baltazar, Scourge of the Galaxy''', served as the main [[antagonist]] of the animated serial ''[[The Infinite Quest]]''.

Using enhanced rust, the Doctor destroyed the ship Baltazar had built, Baltazar having destroyed the entire Earth defence. With his space piracy, cybernetics, robot parrot, and desire to crush planets into precious gems, Baltazar bears a striking resemblance to [[List of Doctor Who villains#The Captain|The Captain]], a character from the [[Fourth Doctor]] adventure, [[The Pirate Planet]]. Baltazar destroyed a planet in the 40th century, amongst other crimes, and was sent to the prison planet Volag-Noc. With the aid of Caw, a robotic parrot, Balthazar puts a tracking device on the Doctor so the Doctor and [[Martha Jones|Martha]] would find ''The Infinite'' – a huge spaceship that can grant people their heart's desire – for him.

Once he finds ''The Infinite'' he discovers an illusion showing &quot;what the [[heart]] desires&quot;. After the Doctor uses his [[sonic screwdriver]] to tear the ship apart, he orders Squawk to escort him backto Volag-Noc where and imprisonment.

The title &quot;Scourge of the Galaxy&quot; previously belonged to the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Macra|Macra]].

===Beast===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Beast]] --&gt;
'''The Beast'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/episodes/2006/satanpit.shtml |title=Doctor Who – Episodes – The Satan Pit |publisher=BBC |date=13 February 2007 |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; was an ancient being that had been trapped for billions of years in a pit at the centre of the planet named in the Scriptures of the Veltino as [[List of Doctor Who planets#K|Krop Tor]], orbiting a [[black hole]] humans had designated K37 Gem 5, kept in balance by an energy source below the surface of the planet. This counterweight extended out in a funnel into open space. The Beast was imprisoned by &quot;Disciples of Light&quot;, who had crafted its prison such that if it ever freed itself, the gravitational force would collapse and the planet, and the Beast with it, would be pulled into the black hole.

The Beast was awakened when a human expedition party flew their ship through the funnel to land on the planet, hoping to excavate and claim the power source for their Empire. The Beast telepathically spoke through the empathic [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Ood|Ood]], who became the &quot;Legion of the Beast&quot;, and later possessed Toby Zed. Resembling a huge horned demon, the Beast claimed that it was the basis of the [[Devil]] figure in all religions and mythologies (including [[Abaddon]], [[Satan]], the [[Kaled]] god of war, and [[Lucifer]]), and that it originated from before the creation of the universe. It is uncertain whether this is true and the exact nature of the Beast remains uncertain. The Beast knew and played on the hidden fears and secrets of those with whom it spoke, and the Doctor described it as extremely intelligent.

Intending to escape Krop Tor, the Beast possessed Toby Zed. However, the Doctor smashed the power source of the prison, causing Krop Tor to be dragged into the black hole, and the Beast's body burst into flames. At that moment, while fleeing the planet in a spacecraft with his team, Toby who was possessed by the Beast angrily proclaimed that as long as he was feared, he could never be destroyed. [[Rose Tyler]], however, shot out the cockpit window with a bolt gun, causing Toby, with the mind of the Beast, to be blown into the black hole.

In present day Cardiff the [[End of Days (Torchwood)|Torchwood team]] encountered a similar giant creature named [[List of Torchwood monsters and aliens#Abaddon|Abaddon]], released from the [[Rift (Whoniverse)|Cardiff spacetime Rift]], referred to as the &quot;son of the great Beast&quot;.

Gabriel Woolf, who provided the Beast's voice, also played [[#Sutekh|Sutekh the Destroyer]] in the 1975 serial ''[[Pyramids of Mars]]'', an entity that was also said to have been named Satan.

===Beep the Meep===
{{Main|Beep the Meep}}

===Bennett===
{{Main|The Rescue (Doctor Who)}}

===Black Guardian===
{{Main|Black Guardian}}

===Margaret Blaine===
:''See: [[#Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen|Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen]]

===Bok===
'''Bok''' was the gargoyle servant of [[#Azal|Azal]] in the [[Third Doctor]] story ''[[The Dæmons]]''. Made of stone, he was [[bulletproof]]. He was blown apart by a [[United Nations Intelligence Taskforce|UNIT]] [[bazooka]], but reformed moments later. He reverted to his statue form when Azal was defeated.&lt;ref name=&quot;episodeguide1&quot;/&gt;

===Borad===
{{Main|Timelash}}

===Borusa===
'''Borusa''' was a [[Time Lord]] and a former teacher of the Doctor. He appeared in four serials: ''[[The Deadly Assassin]]'', ''[[The Invasion of Time]]'', ''[[Arc of Infinity]]'' and ''[[The Five Doctors]]''. Each time, Borusa was portrayed by a different actor, it being implied that the character had [[regeneration (Doctor Who)|regenerated]] in the time between these serials and thus his appearance and personality were different in each story.

When the character was first introduced in ''[[The Deadly Assassin]]'', he occupied the post of Cardinal in the High Council, and was portrayed as a good though pretentious person with some political standing on [[Gallifrey]], the [[Time Lords]]' home planet. He set about &quot;adjusting truth&quot; in the wake of the Doctor's return to Gallifrey and his defeat of the Master. He sought to, for instance, portray the late Chancellor Goth not as [[Master (Doctor Who)|the Master's]] ally, but as a hero who had given his life to stop the Master. After the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]] willingly left [[Gallifrey]] again, in the Doctor's absence Borusa officially became Lord Chancellor (although the Doctor later claimed this was done &quot;illegally&quot;).

Borusa appeared again when the Doctor returned to Gallifrey briefly in ''[[The Invasion of Time]]'' to officially take up the post of Lord President. This was, however, part of a strategy to defeat the Vardans, and once they and the Sontarans had been seen off, the Doctor - now having been officially inaugurated as President of the High Council of Time Lords - departed and left Gallifrey in the hands of Borusa once again.

By the time of ''[[Arc of Infinity]]'', Borusa had regenerated again and had officially become Lord President of Gallifrey. He, along with other members of the High Council of Time Lords, condemned the [[Fifth Doctor]] to death, as [[Omega (Doctor Who)|Omega]] had attempted to interface with this universe from his own anti-matter universe by using the Fifth Doctor as the bridge, thus endangering the whole of creation. Borusa was even suspected of being the traitor who had sent Omega the Doctor's genetic code; however, he was quickly proven innocent and assisted the Doctor in destroying Omega.

In ''The Five Doctors'', Borusa had once again regenerated, which may have unbalanced his mind. He sought, by using the Doctor's first five incarnations, the Time Lord founder [[Rassilon]]'s fabled secret of [[immortality]] for himself so that he might rule Gallifrey forever. Borusa used a Time Scoop to transport the Doctor (and various [[companion (Doctor Who)|companions]]) to the Death Zone on Gallifrey, using them to clear the way to the Dark Tower where Rassilon was entombed. History stated that to share immortality, would-be challengers had to overcome the obstacles in the Death Zone and solve the Game of Rassilon by removing the ring from Rassilon's hand. The Game was actually a trap to contain power-mad maniacs, since Rassilon reasoned that immortality was a curse rather than a blessing and that anyone who sought it was clearly deranged.  Borusa was transformed into a living statue by Rassilon for his efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=In0DduOsBvoC&amp;pg=PT71&amp;dq=borusa+doctor+who&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=8dpbTrfbJcOk-gaS2-yTDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=3&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=borusa%20&amp;f=false |last=Leach |first=Jim |title=Doctor Who |publisher=[[Wayne State University Press]] |year=2009 |pages=62–64}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The spin off novels ''[[Blood Harvest]]'' and ''[[The Eight Doctors]]'' by [[Terrance Dicks]] feature further appearances by Borusa. In both novels Borusa was freed from his imprisonment and given a chance for redemption. In ''The Eight Doctors'', he was released thanks to the appeal of the [[Eighth Doctor]] to help resolve the political conflict inspired by the [[Sixth Doctor]]'s trial in ''[[The Trial of a Time Lord]]''. In ''Blood Harvest'' Borusa aided the [[Seventh Doctor]], Rassilon and [[Romana]] in fighting off the mental influence of a powerful foe. The [[canon (fiction)|canonicity]] of the novels, like other ''Doctor Who'' [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] media, is unclear.

===BOSS===
'''BOSS''' from '''Biomorphic Organisational Systems Supervisor''', was a [[supercomputer]] that appeared in ''[[The Green Death]]'' (1973).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/classic/episodeguide/greendeath/detail.shtml |title=Doctor Who Classic Episode Guide – The Green Death – Details |publisher=BBC |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It had a [[megalomaniac]]al personality, and had been programmed to be inefficient, so that it could make the same kind of intuitive leaps of logic as humans. It was able to [[brainwashing|brainwash]] humans, including [[Captain Mike Yates]] who later suffered a [[nervous breakdown]] as a result. It was responsible for producing the chemicals that mutated [[maggots]] into [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Giant Maggot|giant maggots]]. BOSS planned to interface with all computers on [[List of Doctor Who planets#E|Earth]] and enslave humanity. Stevens, a human brainwashed by BOSS, sacrificed himself when his mental programming was partially broken by the [[Third Doctor]], blowing up himself and the computer as the Doctor escaped.

BOSS was voiced by John Dearth (who was later in ''Doctor Who'' as Lupton in ''[[Planet of the Spiders]]'' (1974)).

==C==
===Signora Rosanna Calvierri===
A Saturnyne who fled the destruction of her planet along with her offspring, although only the males survived. She set up a school in Venice, supposedly to educate young girls, but in reality she was turning the girls into Saturnynes to mate them with her sons. She planned to flood Venice, but was defeated, and threw herself into the water in human form, to be eaten by her doomed offspring.

===Taren Capel===
{{Main|The Robots of Death}}

===Max Capricorn===
'''Max Capricorn''' appeared in the [[Tenth Doctor]] story &quot;[[Voyage of the Damned (Doctor Who)|Voyage of the Damned]]&quot;. He was the owner of a luxury spaceship cruiseliner company, but was voted out by the other owners of the company and planned to get his revenge by crashing one of his ships into the Earth, killing all life on the planet as well as the 2000 people on board; selling his shares, he would earn enough to retire and see the remainder of the company in prison for mass murder. Due to his advanced age (he had been running his company for more than a hundred years), he had been reduced to a head in a tank, a cyborg dependent on life support (the common prejudice against cyborgs may have played a part in his removal from his company). [[Astrid Peth]] stopped his plan by pushing him into the live nuclear storm drive, sacrificing herself in the process.

===The Captain===
'''The Captain''' was a [[space pirate]] who appeared in the fourth Doctor episode ''[[The Pirate Planet]]''. He was a cyborg, with half of his body covered in robotic prosthetics, and had a pet robot parrot, named Polyphase Avitron, that rested on his shoulder. He was prone to outbursts of anger, and was directly served by a nurse and his nervous assistant [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Mr Fibuli|Mr Fibuli]]. The Captain piloted an entire planet – Zanak – which would materialise around other planets and strip them of their mineral wealth. The Captain kept a trophy room of the super-compressed planets he had conquered. It was revealed that the Captain's nurse was a projection of Zanak's queen [[List of Doctor Who villains#Queen Xanxia|Queen Xanxia]], who was controlling the Captain and using the complex forces of the compressed planets to power a machine that perpetually kept her a few seconds from death.

===Matron Casp===
:''See: [[#Sisters of Plenitude|Sisters of Plenitude]]''

===Lady Cassandra===
{{Main|Cassandra (Doctor Who)}}

===Celestial Toymaker===
{{Main|Celestial Toymaker}}

===Harrison Chase===
'''Harrison Chase''' was an eccentric millionaire whose obsession was [[botany]]. He was a madman with a disdainful attitude toward human life, and favouritism over another form of life, in this case plant life.

Through his vast resources, Chase learned that the seed pods of a [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Krynoid|Krynoid]], an intelligent form of alien plant life, had been found in [[Antarctica]]. A collector of rare specimens, Chase became obsessed with obtaining a sample, and successfully acquired one. He allowed the Krynoid to possess one of his henchmen, who began to mutate into a Human-Krynoid hybrid. As the monster grew in size and power, Chase too became possessed by the Krynoid.

Convinced of a future where Krynoids are the dominant life form on Earth, Chase aided the monster in earnest. By this time, the [[Fourth Doctor]] and [[Sarah Jane Smith]] were trapped on Chase's property. Chase eventually captured Sarah and attempted to kill her by throwing her into a compost shredder. The Doctor stopped him, and the two fought, until Chase fell into the shredder and perished.

===Mavic Chen===
:''See: [[The Daleks' Master Plan]]''

===General Cobb===
:''See: [[The Doctor's Daughter]]''
'''Cobb''' was a General for the human faction on the planet Messeline. He asked the [[Tenth Doctor]] to join him in war against the Hath, in a bid to claim the Source which they were both searching for, but subsequently locked the Doctor and his companions up when the Doctor refused. He later shot [[Jenny (Doctor Who)|Jenny]], the Doctor's daughter, after the Doctor released the Source; the Doctor was clearly tempted to shoot Cobb himself, but informed Cobb that he would never resort to Cobb's methods, going on to ask the humans and Hath to make that philosophy the foundation of their new society.

===Matron Cofelia===
'''Matron Cofelia''' was a nanny of the Five-Straighten, Classabindi Nursery Fleet, Intergalactic Class, given the task of looking after babies of the [[Creatures and aliens in Doctor Who#Adipose|Adipose]], after their breeding planet was lost, in &quot;[[Partners in Crime (Doctor Who)|Partners in Crime]]&quot;. Disguised as a human named '''Miss Foster''', a play on &quot;foster mother&quot;, she used Adipose pills to galvanise human fats into living creatures, the Adipose, despite the illegality of using Level 5 planets for such a purpose. She possessed a sonic pen, described by the Doctor as &quot;sleek&quot;, which functions identically to the Sonic Screwdriver. After the Adipose babies were adopted, Cofelia was no longer needed; the Adiposian First Family decided to dispose of their accomplice, shutting off a tractor beam causing her to fall to her death. Miss Foster/Matron Cofelia was portrayed by [[Sarah Lancashire]].

===Chief Caretaker===
The '''Chief Caretaker''', featured in ''[[Paradise Towers]]'' (1987), served the intelligence [[List of Doctor Who villains#Kroagnon|Kroagnon]], the Great Architect of Paradise Towers. He sanctioned the robotic [[List of Doctor Who robots#Cleaning robots|Cleaners']] killings, but lost control of the situation and was killed by Kroagnon for his body.

===The Collector===
'''The Collector''', in ''[[The Sun Makers]]'' (1977), was the finance-obsessed [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Usurian|Usurian]] overlord of the humans on [[List of Doctor Who planets#P|Pluto]]. In his humanoid form, he was diminutive in stature, bald with bushy eyebrows and used a [[wheelchair]]. He spoke with a squeaky voice and was receptive to the praises of his underling [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Gatherer Hade|Gatherer Hade]]. He reverted to his natural [[seaweed]]-like state in shock after he was trapped within his wheelchair when the [[Fourth Doctor|Doctor]] collapsed his economy amidst a revolution.

===George Cranleigh===
{{Main|Black Orchid (Doctor Who)|l1=Black Orchid}}

&lt;!---Please do not add Cyberman as they're a race and are already mentioned on the article List of Doctor Who creatures and aliens as well as having their own article---&gt;

==D==
&lt;!---Please do not add Daleks as they're a race and are already mentioned on the article List of Doctor Who creatures and aliens as well as having their own article---&gt;

===Davros===
{{Main|Davros}}

===De Flores===
'''De Flores''' was a Neo-Nazi, based in South America, who aimed to establish a Fourth [[Reich]], aided by a powerful [[Time Lord]] weapon, known as the Nemesis, as seen in ''[[Silver Nemesis]]''(1988). He led a group of paramilitary men against [[#Lady Peinforte|Lady Peinforte]], a group of [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] and the [[Seventh Doctor]], who all vied to control the Nemesis. He possessed the bow – part of the Nemesis as it was in its statue form – which he and his men reunited with the statue body when it fell to England in a comet in 1988. After allying himself with the Cybermen, De Flores was killed by the [[Cyberman|Cyber Leader]] when he outlived his usefulness to them.

===Destroyer===
'''The Destroyer''' was an otherdimensional entity summoned by the sorceress [[#Morgaine|Morgaine]] in ''[[Battlefield (Doctor Who)|Battlefield]]'' (1989) to aid her in defeating the [[Seventh Doctor]]. Known by many titles, including &quot;Destroyer of Worlds&quot;, he was kept subdued by chains of pure silver, and even Morgaine hesitated in unleashing him on the world until he allowed the Doctor to gain the upper hand, thus forcing Morgaine to free him in a desperate attempt to avoid defeat.

At the time, [[Brigadier Lethbridge-Stewart]] had been called out of retirement to assist [[United Nations Intelligence Taskforce|UNIT]] against Morgaine's invasion. The Destroyer taunted the Brigadier for being the best Earth could offer as its champion. The Brigadier's shot the Destroyer with silver bullets.

The design for the Destroyer was based on theatrical devil's mask, modified so that an actor could speak through it. The cloak that covered its chainmail armour disguised the mechanical parts needed for the costume's special effects. Script writer [[Ben Aaronovitch]] originally intended the Destroyer to start off as a businessman who gradually became more demonic as he fell under Morgaine's spell, but this was time-consuming and expensive, so he stayed in one form throughout.

===Dream Lord===
Appearing in the episode &quot;[[Amy's Choice (Doctor Who)|Amy's Choice]]&quot;, an individual calling himself the Dream Lord ([[Toby Jones]]) claimed to offer the Doctor and his companions a choice between two life-threatening scenarios, for them to determine which was real. After realising that both realities were false, the Doctor revealed that the 'Dream Lord' was a manifestation of his own dark impulses, manifested by a psychic projection. The projection was caused by psychic pollen from the candle meadows of Karass Don Slava, that previously had been trapped in the TARDIS and were activated by heating. At the end of the episode, his reflection was seen by the Doctor in the Tardis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/dw/characters/Dream_Lord |title=Doctor Who – Monsters – Dream Lord|publisher=BBC |date=19 May 2010 |accessdate=19 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==E==
===Editor===
'''The Editor''' ([[Simon Pegg]]) was the mysterious manager of the Satellite 5, an orbital news station around Earth broadcasting across the Fourth Great and Bountiful Human Empire in 200,000. From Floor 500, he monitored the thoughts of all those connected to the archives of the station via chips implanted into people's heads, which were required to access the computer systems of the 2001st century. Through these implants, the Editor was able to instantly know whatever the person connected knew, and was even able to sense when a record was fictional or not, or that there was something out of place with a particular individual before a security check confirmed it. He reported to the monstrous slug-like [[extraterrestrial life in popular culture|extraterrestrial]] known as the [[#Jagrafess|Jagrafess]]. The Editor claimed that he represented a consortium of interstellar banks whose intent was to subtly control the Empire by means of manipulating the news.

After he captured the Ninth Doctor and Rose, the Editor was both intrigued and frustrated at the fact that records of their existence did not seem to exist in the archives. However, because the Doctor's new companion [[Adam Mitchell (Doctor Who)|Adam]] had accessed the archives of the Satellite, the Editor found that the Doctor was a [[Time Lord]] and attempted to gain the [[TARDIS]]. Before he could do this, a human journalist named Cathica (who had been following the Doctor's investigation) reversed the environmental controls of Floor 500 that had been kept at an icy temperature vital for keeping the Jagrafess causing it to explode.

In the episode &quot;[[Bad Wolf]]&quot;, taking place on Satellite 5 a century after &quot;The Long Game&quot;, it was revealed that the Badwolf Corporation was behind the Jagrafess, and that his masters were the [[Dalek]]s.

===Eldrad===
'''Eldrad''' was a [[Hypothetical types of biochemistry#Silicon biochemistry|silicon-based lifeform]] from the planet [[Kastria]] who saved his planet from solar winds, but then took down the barriers he created because the people wouldn't follow him. They sentenced him to destruction in an obliteration capsule, but his hand survived and ended up in a quarry on Earth. When [[Sarah Jane Smith]] came in contact with the hand, Eldrad controlled her, using her to bring his hand to a nuclear reactor. By absorbing radiation from the reactor, Eldrad was regenerated in a thin female body with violet skin covered in crystals, basing his form on his contact with Sarah Jane. He convinced the Doctor to take him back to Kastria in the present, where he regained his true form, only to learn that his race had destroyed themselves to prevent him from ruling them again. The Doctor and Sarah used the Doctor's scarf to trip Eldrad and send him falling into a pit.
{{see also|The Hand of Fear}}

===Eleanor, Duchess of Melrose===
===Empress of the Racnoss===
'''The Empress of the Racnoss''' featured in &quot;[[The Runaway Bride (Doctor Who)|The Runaway Bride]]&quot; (2006) and as archive footage in &quot;[[Turn Left (Doctor Who)|Turn Left]]&quot; (2008). She was killed when [[Harold Saxon]] ordered her ship to be shot down after the Doctor had drowned her children by draining the Thames. Her appearance resembled that of a huge red humanoid [[spider]]. She was portrayed by [[Sarah Parish]].
{{See also|List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Racnoss|l1=Racnoss}}

===Eve===
Eve was an android resembling a woman built by Hr'oln, last of the Cirranins in the novel ''[[The Last Dodo]]''. She was built to prevent the extinction of races like the Cirranins, but did this by rather unorthodox means. She put Hr'oln and other last ones in suspended animation, then put all but Hr'oln in MOTLO (Museum Of The Last Ones). However, she and a member of the Earth team named Frank were secretly cloning the creatures and selling them off to the highest bidder. The Doctor and Martha then arrived at the museum, and investigated the poaching. After Eve captured the Doctor, last of the Time Lords, Martha freed him, but accidentally teleported the Earth creatures back to Earth. During the ensuing chaos, Eve hatched upon a plan to get the cloned dodos to lay bomb eggs, with sabretooth cats and Megalosauri attacking people to keep them off the scent, so that she could stop having to note down every Earth extinction. She planned to destroy every planet in the universe this way. But when the Doctor pointed out this would be impossible, she tried to shoot him. Unfortunately for her, the gun backfired, killing her and revealing that she was an android. After her plans had been stopped, and Hr'oln was freed, Hr'oln promised to rebuild her. She is immune to psychic paper. As a novel character, her canonicity is unclear.

==F==
===Family of Blood===
'''The Family of Blood''' are a family who appear in the episodes &quot;[[Human Nature (Doctor Who episode)|Human Nature]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Family of Blood]]&quot; (2007) in which they are the titular entity. They are incorporeal, green [[Telepathy|telepathic]] creatures and refer to each other by their relationship followed by &quot;of Mine&quot;; &quot;Father/Husband of Mine&quot;, &quot;Mother/Wife of Mine&quot;, &quot;Son/Brother of Mine&quot; (who appears to assume leadership) and &quot;Sister/Daughter of Mine&quot;. Because of their lack of form, they required a physical body to inhabit; they only had short lifespans without them and as such, sought that of a [[Time Lord]] and pursued the last Time Lord: the [[Tenth Doctor]], who chose to alter his biodata to become a human schoolteacher in England, 1913 until their lifespans expired; he did this not out of fear but rather as an act of mercy. They had a [[time vortex (Doctor Who)|time vortex]] manipulator allowing them to time travel. Their spaceship was stolen and was protected by an invisible shield. They could also animate different things for servants – in the case of their 1913 invasion of [[Earth]], [[scarecrows]] – using &quot;molecular fringe animation&quot;. They also possess hand-held energy firearms capable of disintegrating flesh and cloth – on the Doctor Who official website it is referred to as a &quot;Bio-gun&quot;. The Family possessed the forms of four humans: Mr. Clark, a farmer; Jeremy Baines, a school prefect; Lucy Cartwright, a small girl; and Jenny, a maid at the school. The original souls of the humans were replaced, the original bodies only existing as vessels for the Family.

After the destruction of their starship, the Doctor punished the Family for their crimes. &quot;Father of Mine&quot; was tied up in unbreakable chains forged from dwarf star metal, &quot;Mother of Mine&quot; was trapped on the event horizon of a collapsing galaxy, &quot;Son of Mine&quot; was frozen in time and dressed as a Scarecrow, left in the fields to watch over England as its protector, and &quot;Sister of Mine&quot; was trapped inside every mirror and unable to leave, still able to be glimpsed fleetingly by humans. &quot;Son of Mine&quot; mentions that the Doctor visits the sister once every year, and he wishes that the Doctor may forgive her in time.

===Fendahl===
'''The Fendahl''' was an entity that devoured life itself. It originated on the fifth planet of Earth's solar system, which the ancient [[Time Lord]]s placed in a time loop in an attempt to imprison the creature. However, the Fendahl escaped and, in the form of a humanoid skull, was buried under [[volcanic rock]] on prehistoric Earth 12 million years ago. The story of the Fendahl passed into Time Lord myth, and was forgotten. The Fendahl's power, contained in a [[pentagram]]-shaped neural relay in the bones of the skull, affected life on Earth via a biotransmutation field, influencing life forms in its vicinity (including the early [[Hominidae|hominids]]) to develop into forms it could use.

In the late 20th century, the Fendahl skull was discovered in [[Kenya]] by a team of [[anthropology|anthropologists]] under the leadership of one Dr. Fendelman. Fendelman brought the skull to an English research facility at Fetch Priory, near the village of Fetchborough. The Priory was built on a time fissure, causing [[parapsychology|psychic]] ability in some nearby residents. In the Priory, Fendelman and his fellow researchers Thea Ransome, Adam Colby and Maximillian Stael performed experiments on the skull, attempting to unlock its secrets. Fendelman used a crude time scanner to examine the skull, a dangerous activity which drew the attention of the [[Fourth Doctor]]. Stael attempted to capture the power of the Fendahl for himself by means of [[black magic]] rituals, performed with the aid of a local coven, but he, Fendelman and Ransome were all being used by the Fendahl to recreate itself.

The Fendahl was a [[wikt:gestalt|gestalt]] creature with multiple aspects. Thea Ransome was transformed into the Fendahl Core, a humanoid female with golden skin and blank, staring eyes. Several of the cult members became slug-like creatures called Fendahleen. All the aspects of the Fendahl had powerful [[psychokinesis|psychotelekinetic]] ability, and can control the muscles of human victims. The Fendahleen were vulnerable to [[sodium chloride]], which altered the creatures' [[electrical conduction|conductivity]] and destroyed their electrical balance.

In its final form, the Fendahl would consist of the Core and twelve Fendahleen; however, the Doctor was able to prevent the creature from reaching its full manifestation. He rigged Fendelman's time scanner to implode, destroying the Core and the Fendahleen. He also removed the skull, planning to drop it into a star about to go [[supernova]].

The Fendahl has also appeared in the [[Eighth Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[The Taking of Planet 5]]'' by [[Simon Bucher-Jones]] and [[Mark Clapham]], where a group of Time Lords from the [[Eighth Doctor]]'s future attempted to release it from the time loop trapping Planet Five, only to learn that an even deadlier life-form had evolved inside the loop; the Maemovore, a devourer of concept itself, which the Doctor was only just able to defeat by convincing a group of TARDISes from the future to help him expel the entity from the universe. The Fendahl also returned in the ''[[Kaldor City]]'' series of audio plays and the ''[[Time Hunter]]'' novella ''[[Deus Le Volt]]'' by [[Jon de Burgh Miller]].

===Fenric===
'''Fenric''' was a being described by the [[Seventh Doctor]] as &quot;evil from the dawn of time&quot;, a malevolent force that survived the clash of energies present at the birth of the universe. In an untelevised adventure, the Doctor had encountered Fenric and defeated him by challenging him to solve a [[chess]] puzzle. When Fenric proved unable to solve it, the Doctor then trapped the being in a flask where he remained for several thousand years.

However, Fenric was still able to manipulate human minds and events through time and space. He set up pawns, bloodlines of families that were under his control and he could use, &quot;The Curse of Fenric&quot; stretching down through generations. These people were known as the &quot;Wolves of Fenric&quot;, and their true purpose was unknown even to them. He also had the power to summon [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Haemovore|Haemovores]], [[vampires]] which were to be the evolutionary destiny of mankind in a possible far future. The haemovores were strong enough to be able to weld metal with their bare hands, and were also immune to bullets. They could be countered, however, with a psychic barrier caused by faith.

Eventually, the flask was brought to a military base in [[Northumberland]] in 1942, where several Wolves, including the Doctor's companion [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]], were manipulated into freeing Fenric from his flask. He also summoned the Ancient One, the last of the Haemovores from the future, in an attempt to poison the world with a deadly chemical toxin. Fenric then revealed that he had manipulated the Seventh Doctor's life upon several occasions as part of his game, including creating the time storm that originally [[Dragonfire (Doctor Who)|took Ace to Iceworld]] and influencing the [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] in their attempts to gain the power of the [[Silver Nemesis|Nemesis]] statue. Eventually, the Doctor convinced the Ancient One to turn on Fenric; the Ancient One then destroyed Fenric and himself with the same toxin.

The [[Virgin New Adventures]] novel ''[[All-Consuming Fire]]'' by [[Andy Lane]] also equates Fenric with the [[Cthulhu Mythos]] entity [[Hastur]] the Unspeakable.

===Mr Finch===
'''Mr Finch''' ([[Anthony Head]]) as seen in &quot;[[School Reunion (Doctor Who)|School Reunion]]&quot;, was an alias for '''Brother Lassar''', the leader of a group of [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Krillitane|Krillitanes]]. He is also aware of the [[Time War (Doctor Who)|Time War]] and the [[Time Lord]]s' near-extinction.

The Krillitanes had taken human characteristics to infiltrate the Deffry Vale [[comprehensive school]]. Taking the position of headmaster, Finch gradually replaced the staff members with disguised Krillitanes and then enacted a series of reforms, including specialised programmes of study and free, but compulsory, school dinners. The dinners were laced with Krillitane oil, which enhances the intelligence of the pupils so they could be used to decode the Skasis Paradigm, which would give the Krillitanes control over the structure of reality. The Krillitanes could not use the oil themselves because their constantly changing morphology had rendered it toxic to their systems.

The [[Tenth Doctor]] and his current companions investigated the school, meeting his old companions [[Sarah Jane Smith]] and [[K-9 (Doctor Who)#Models|K-9 Mark III]]. Finch tempted the Doctor with power offering the use of the solved Paradigm, but Sarah's urgings helped the Doctor to refuse. While escaping, K-9 sacrificed itself by using its laser to blow up the barrels of Krillitane oil in the kitchen, showering most of the Krillitanes with it before the kitchen exploded, apparently killing them all. Finch is seen to be unnaffected by the oil (since he had taken permanent human form) but it is unclear if the subsequent kitchen explosion killed him or not.

In issues #3-#6 the [[IDW Publishing|IDW]] ongoing ''[[Doctor Who]]'' comic by [[Tony Lee]], Finch reappears as the prosecution in a Shadow Proclamation case against the Doctor, where he has infiltrated the Shadow Proclamation as part of a plan to make the Krillitane Empire stronger, but at the end of the story it is shown that he was actually a shapechanging alien with a far greater plan. The true location or status of Mister Finch is never revealed.

His first name of &quot;Lucas&quot; is given on the [[Doctor Who tie-in websites#Deffry Vale School|Deffry Vale School website]]. According to an on-line interview with Head, Finch's original name in the script was &quot;Hector&quot;, but this had to be changed when a check found a real headmaster named &quot;Hector Finch&quot;.

===Florence Finnegan===
'''Florence Finnegan''' was the name assumed by the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Plasmavore|Plasmavore]] who was hiding from the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Judoon|Judoon]] in the Royal Hope Hospital in London when it was transported to the [[Moon]] in &quot;[[Smith and Jones (Doctor Who)|Smith and Jones]]&quot;. To avoid detection by the Judoon, she sucked the blood out of Mr. Stoker, a consultant working in the hospital. This allows her to assimilate human [[DNA]] and register as human on the Judoon scanners. [[The Tenth Doctor|The Doctor]] later tricks her into sucking his blood, meaning that she registers as non-human, having assimilated non-human blood. The Judoon pick up on this. She attempts to rig a hospital [[MRI]] machine to kill everyone in the hospital (and the half of earth currently facing the moon). The Judoon execute her for the crime of killing an alien princess. The Doctor neutralises the MRI energy.

===Miss Foster===
See [[List of Doctor Who villains#C|Matron Cofelia]].

==G==
===Gavrok===
'''Gavrok''' was leader of the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Bannerman|Bannermen]] who attempted to wipe out the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Chimeron|Chimeron]] race in ''[[Delta and the Bannermen]]'' (1987). After pursuing the Chimeron Queen, Delta, to Earth in 1959, he was killed falling into his own booby-trap set around the [[TARDIS]] when he was overcome by a high-pitched scream produced by Delta's child, the Chimeron Princess, amplified by a [[PA system]].
(A possibly intentional name-check is made in [[Buffy the Vampire Slayer (TV series)|Buffy the Vampire Slayer]] season 3 (&quot;[http://buffy.wikia.com/wiki/Graduation_Day%2C_Part_One Graduation Day Part 1]&quot;), with the [http://buffy.wikia.com/wiki/Ritual_of_Gavrok Ritual of Gavrok].)

===Gods of Ragnarok===
The three '''Gods of Ragnarok''' appeared in the 1988 story, ''[[The Greatest Show in the Galaxy]]''. Apparently a trio of statue-like beings of godly power, they used lesser beings for sport in their Dark Circus, allowing them to live as long as they continue to fulfill the Gods' need to be amused. When the Psychic Circus came to Segonax, they forced the circus' members into serving them and killed off everyone else, manifesting themselves within regular time/space in the guise of a family consisting of a mother, a father and their young daughter. When the [[Seventh Doctor]] came to the Psychic Circus and uncovered their plan, he went into their dimension to distract them until he gets the medallion used to summon them and reflect the Gods' destructive energy back at them, destroying them and their Dark Circus.

The [[Virgin New Adventures]] novel ''[[Conundrum (Doctor Who)|Conundrum]]'' by [[Steve Lyons (writer)|Steve Lyons]] reveals that the Gods of Ragnarok created the [[The Mind Robber|Land of Fiction]]. As with all spin-off media, the [[Whoniverse#Inclusion and canonicity|canonicity]] of this is open to interpretation. (The Gods also display some similarity with the Osirian race of [[#Sutekh|Sutekh]], including the use of the Eye of Horus symbol.)

===Gravis===
{{Main|Frontios}}

===Sebastian Grayle===
'''Sebastian Grayle''', originally named '''Decurion Sebastius Gralae''', appears in the [[List of Doctor Who audio plays by Big Finish|Big Finish audio drama]] ''[[Seasons of Fear]]''. He was a human who became immortal from the power of the Nimon in a deal to let them invade the Earth. When the Doctor had first met him in 1930 in Singapore, this was the first time the Doctor has ever seen him but this wasn't Grayle's first to which he told the Doctor that he had already killed him. Sebastian had eventually met the Doctor for the first time and other times during the periods of Roman Britannia, the Hellfire Club, and the court of Edward the Confessor. Eventually the Doctor met Grayle before meeting the Nimon and making the deal encouraging him to not become what he later became which when the original Grayle appeared after the Doctor, the other Grayle killed him in hope of not becoming the evil version of himself, thus creating a paradox.

===Count Grendel===
'''Count Grendel of Gracht''' was a Knight of the nobility of the planet Tara and the Lord of Castle Gracht, his sole on-screen appearance was in the [[Fourth Doctor]] serial, ''[[The Androids of Tara]]'', part of the Season 16 quest for [[the Key to Time]]. The character was played by [[Peter Jeffrey]].

While searching for the fourth segment of the Key, [[Romana]] discovered that it was disguised as the head of a statue representing the family crest of Grendel's family. After Romana transformed it into its actual crystalline form, the segment was confiscated by Grendel. Grendel did not know of the segment's true nature; his real intent was to use Romana (who resembled the Princess Strella) in a complex plot to seize the throne of Tara from Prince Reynart.

His plans were ultimately defeated by the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]]. Although Grendel was considered the finest swordsman on Tara, the Doctor managed to duel him to a standstill, and he made his escape by leaping into the moat of Castle Gracht and swimming away.

A cultured and charming villain, Gracht used his breeding to cover a ruthless and cunning personality. He used and discarded people as easily as he would persuade them to do his bidding, and somehow always managed to live to scheme another day. He also appeared in the [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] short story ''The Trials of Tara'' by [[Paul Cornell]], where another attempt to seize the throne of Tara with the help of the salvaged remains of the [[#Kandy Man|Kandy Man]] was foiled by the [[Seventh Doctor]] and [[Bernice Summerfield|Benny]].

==H==
===Klineman Halpen===
'''Klineman Halpen''' was the Chief Executive of '''Ood Operations'''. At the age of six he was taken to Ood Sphere and saw the Giant [[Ood]] brain within. His father was the manager before him. He had a personal Ood that looked after him called Sigma. As his job was very stressful he soon lost most of his hair and so was dosed with hair tonic by Sigma. His hair partially grew back. When the Ood began geting infected with Red Eye, and the previous chief executive was murdered by an Ood who had one of these such episodes, Halpen arrived on the Ood Sphere to sort it out. When the entire Ood livestock were infected with Red Eye, Halpen ordered the gassing of all Ood. He then set off to destroy the Giant Ood Brain in order to contain the Red Eye and kill the Ood.

He placed detonation packs around the brain and prepared to detonate. He decided he would go into cargo as this job was over. When his scientist, Dr. Ryder revealed he was a member of the Friends of the Ood, Halpen killed him by throwing him into the brain. Ood Sigma led the Doctor and Donna Noble to Halpen but then Sigma claimed he would always help Halpen. It was then that Sigma revealed the &quot;hair tonic&quot; was actually a powerful genetic liquid which had been recombining Halpen's DNA, turning him into an Ood himself. Sigma then declared he would look after Halpen.

===Mercy Hartigan===
'''Mercy Hartigan''', or simply '''Miss Hartigan''' is the villain in Christmas special episode &quot;[[The Next Doctor]]&quot; (2008). She is the willing accomplice of the [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] invasion of London in 1851; she resents her [[patriarchy|patriarchal]] oppression by man as a woman in Victorian England and seeks to empower herself through any means. The Cybermen betray her when they decide that they wish to make her their 'CyberKing' in a process which is supposed to remove her emotions and upgrade her, but it doesn't work due to her brilliant mind having overcome the programming. Miss Hartigan is given access to the full bounty of knowledge of the universe and in the colossal 'CyberKing' ''[[dreadnought]]''-class assault droid, she seeks to make London bow at her feet as its maniacal dictator who combines cold Cyberman efficiency, knowledge and logic with human passion and determination. The Doctor offers Miss Hartigan the opportunity to relocate herself to another world which she can reign over harmlessly, but when she refuses he cuts her connection to the Cybermen and allows her to see what she has become rationally. In her moment of lucidity, she becomes insane and then dies, as do all the Cybermen who are connected to her.

===Yvonne Hartman===
'''Yvonne Hartman''', seen in &quot;[[Army of Ghosts]]&quot; and &quot;[[Doomsday (Doctor Who)|Doomsday]]&quot;, was the director of [[Torchwood Institute|Torchwood One]], the London branch of the Torchwood Institute, located in [[One Canada Square|Canary Wharf]]. Whilst not a villain herself, she acted in the role of an antagonist, interfering with the Doctor's plans to stop what she was doing: widening the tear between her own world and that of an alternate Earth (''[[Rise of the Cybermen]]''), unknowingly helping to release a number of Cybus [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] into the world. She imprisoned the Doctor and confiscated his TARDIS, although he was treated with much respect – as a guest, as the Institute had much to learn from him. At the height of the war between the [[Dalek]]s and Cybermen, she herself was cyberconverted, but the process was seemingly faulty as she turned on her fellow Cybermen, defending the Torchwood Tower &quot;for Queen and country&quot;.

A report on the ''[[Torchwood]]'' TV series' fictional Torchwood Institute [[Doctor Who tie-in websites|tie-in website]] about a motionless Cyberman by some stairs killed by Torchwood security personnel suggests she may have been killed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.torchwood.org.uk/html/fall/emp_report.shtml Torchwood External Hub Interface – Investigation – Security Employee survivor report transcript] – the [[Canon (fiction)|canonicity]] of non-televised spin-off materials related to ''Doctor Who'', however, is open to interpretation.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Headhunter===
The '''Headhunter''' is a female villain-for-hire heard in the [[Big Finish Productions]] series of [[List of Doctor Who audio plays by Big Finish#Eighth Doctor New Adventures|Eighth Doctor New Adventures]] originally on [[BBC7]] radio. She is played by Katarina Olsson.

She crops up several times while the [[Eighth Doctor]] and [[Lucie Miller]] are travelling together. The Headhunter is introduced to listeners at end of their first adventure, ''[[Blood of the Daleks]]'', where she is being hired to hunt down Lucie. After a few failed attempts, she finally catches her at the end of ''[[No More Lies (Doctor Who audio)|No More Lies]]''. The Headhunter's first full tale is ''[[Human Resources (Doctor Who audio)|Human Resources]]'', where the man who hired her is revealed. At the end of this adventure, the Headhunter hires an &quot;assistant&quot;, [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Karen|Karen]]. Karen is just a normal human working in an office, but some [[Time Lords]] believed she had the potential to become an oppressive dictator. The next time the Headhunter appears, ''[[Grand Theft Cosmos]]'', Karen is at her side. This time, the Doctor's meeting with them is coincidental. However, their next meeting was intentional. Once again, the Headhunter had to track down Lucie, as well as the Doctor himself. At the end of ''[[Vengeance of Morbius]]'', the Doctor is believed dead and the Time Lords return Lucie to Earth. In ''[[Orbis (Doctor Who audio)|Orbis]]'', the Headhunter has acquired the TARDIS and uses it to find Lucie and then the Doctor, who she finds on an obscure ocean world populated by intelligent jellyfish. But her real objective is a powerful [[Stellar engineering|remote stellar manipulator]] built during ''Vengeance of Morbius''. Similar to [[The Hand of Omega]], the stellar manipulator ends up destroying the ocean world of Orbis, before it falls under her control. The Headhunter's true motives are revealed in her final story, ''[[The Eight Truths]]''/''[[Worldwide Web (Doctor Who audio)|Worldwide Web]]''.

The Headhunter appears human and knows a lot about Earth, but where or when she comes from is uncertain. She has her own [[Faster than light|warp ship]] that can travel in time and space. She enjoys using gadgets, like hypnotising helmets and [[quantum]]-tipped time bullets that can be slowed down or even reversed. She specialises in tracking people down, hence her name. Her real name is a mystery. She is known for her ruthlessness, her opportunism, her deceitfulness and her ability to accomplish difficult jobs.

===House===

House, a malevolent entity from &quot;[[The Doctor's Wife]]&quot;, was a energy being that ruled over an asteroid in a bubble universe, who lured TARDISes into to feed off their energies, and torture their occupents for House's amusement.  After house lures the Doctor and his companions to his universe with a Time Lord distress beacon, House force's the Doctor's TARDIS' matrix into the body of one of his servants, placing himself into the TARDIS, and, having learned this TARDIS is the final TARDIS, plans to escape to the universe proper, with Amy and Rory trapped inside.  Eventually, the Doctor and the TARDIS matrix create a makeshift TARDIS console from the strewn about TARDIS wrecks left on House's asteroid, and the TARDIS matrix's human body dies, allowing it's energies to re-enter the TARDIS console, and destroy House.

==I==
==J==
===Jagrafess===
The '''Jagrafess''', or, to give its full title, '''The Mighty Jagrafess of the Holy Hadrojassic Maxarodenfoe''' (or for short, '''Max''') was a gigantic, gelatinous creature similar to a slug in shape. Its exact origins are not known, but it was sentient and able to communicate in a series of growls and screeches. It had a life span of about 3000 years, with sharp, vicious teeth and several vestigial eyes. Its metabolic rate, however, meant that it had to be kept at low temperatures to survive. It appeared in the episode &quot;[[The Long Game]]&quot;.The Jagrafess was the supervisor of the mysterious and sinister [[#Editor|Editor]] on board Satellite 5, a space station that broadcast news across the whole of the Fourth Great and Bountiful Human Empire of the year 200,000.

The environmental systems of Satellite 5 had been configured to vent all heat away from Floor 500, keeping it cold enough for the Jagrafess to survive, attached to the ceiling of the main control room. When the [[Ninth Doctor]], [[Rose Tyler|Rose]] and [[Adam Mitchell (Doctor Who)|Adam]] arrived on board, the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]] recognised that human development had been deliberately obstructed and began to investigate. Ultimately captured by the Editor and about to be killed by the Jagrafess, they were saved by the actions of Cathica, a human journalist, who reversed the environmental systems causing the Jagrafess to explode due to the heat.

In the episode &quot;[[Bad Wolf]]&quot;, taking place on Satellite 5 a century after &quot;The Long Game&quot;, it was revealed that the Badwolf Corporation was behind the Jagrafess, and that its masters were the [[Dalek]]s.

===Sharaz Jek===
'''Sharaz Jek''' was a genius robotocist and partner of businessman Trau Morgus. Together they planned to harvest the rare Spectrox drug on the planet Androzani Minor using androids built by Jek. Morgus, however, &quot;cheaped out&quot; on Jek, supplying him with substandard equipment and Jek was caught in a mud burst on Minor. He was only able to survive by locking himself in a Spectrox baking oven, leaving him hideously disfigured. Jek thereafter bore a [[pathological]] hatred for Morgus, believing that Morgus had provided the faulty equipment deliberately.

When [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] and [[Peri Brown]] landed on Androzani Minor, they soon became entangled in a three way struggle between Jek's androids, gunrunners and Androzani Major troops. Jek found Peri beautiful and coveted her strongly. When the Doctor and Peri were to be executed by the Major troops, Jek replaced them with realistic androids, and later cared for Peri while the Doctor tried to get an antidote for the poisoning that the two of them had accidentally contracted.

When Morgus and the leader of the gunrunners, Stotz, arrived at Jek's base, Jek attacked Morgus and killed him, but was himself shot by Stotz. He died in the arms of a replica robot.

==K==
===Kal===
'''Kal''', played by [[Jeremy Young]], was the villain of the very first ''Doctor Who'' story, ''[[An Unearthly Child]]''. First appearing in the story's second episode, he was also the first speaking character to appear other than the regulars.

Kal was a caveman from around the year 100,000 BC, the last survivor of a tribe wiped out by cold who had joined the Tribe of Gum. He challenged their leader, Za, claiming he could make fire, which Za could not. When he saw [[First Doctor|the Doctor]] lighting a match, he knocked him unconscious and took him back to the cave to make fire for him, unfortunately leaving the matches behind. When he learned the Doctor could not make fire, he tried to kill him and his companions but Za decided to sacrifice them to the sun instead.

When an old woman of the tribe who was afraid of fire helped the travellers escape, Kal killed her, blamed Za and persuaded the tribe to follow him and recapture the group. However, the Doctor tricked Kal into showing them his knife, still covered in blood, and proving his guilt. He was exiled by the tribe but returned and fought with Za, who killed him.

===Kane===
'''Kane''', seen in ''[[Dragonfire (Doctor Who)|Dragonfire]]'' (1987), one-half of the Xana-Kane criminal gang of the planet [[List of Doctor Who planets#P|Proamon]], was exiled after capture by security forces to the cold, dark side of [[List of Doctor Who planets#S|Svartos]], where he became ruler of the space trading colony Iceworld. His body temperature was so cold that one touch from him could kill and in order to cool down, he lay in a [[cryogenic]] chamber. He branded his employees with his mark iced into their skin and commissioned an ice sculpture of his partner, Xana. After creating a cryogenic army, massacring most of Iceworld's populace and having the dragon that was guarding him slain, Kane released Iceworld from Svartos' surface as a spacecraft, setting a course for Proamon to exact his revenge for his exile and imprisonment. When it transpired that, during the millenia that he had been a prisoner, Proamon had been destroyed, Kane, now in a state of desperation, committed suicide by opening a screen and letting light rays in that melted him.

===Victor Kennedy===
{{Main|Abzorbaloff}}

===Lord Kiv===
{{Main|Mindwarp}}

===Madame Kovarian===

'''Madame Kovarian''' (played by [[Frances Barber]]) is a woman with a [[eyepatch|patch]] over her right eye, who repeatedly appears before [[Amy Pond]] through 'hatches' throughout the first half of [[Doctor Who (series 6)|Series 6]]. Until her name is revealed in &quot;[[A Good Man Goes to War]]&quot; she is credited as &quot;'''Eye Patch Lady'''&quot;. She is seen through the hatches in &quot;[[Day of the Moon]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Curse of the Black Spot]]&quot;, &quot;[[The Rebel Flesh]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Almost People]]&quot;. In the last of these, it is revealed that the Amy who has been travelling with [[Eleventh Doctor|the Doctor]] and [[Rory Williams|Rory]] ever since their [[The Impossible Astronaut|trip to America]] is actually a Flesh avatar housing Amy's consciousness; Amy's physical, pregnant body, is held captive by Kovarian in the ''Demon's Run'' space station. The Doctor, realising the Amy aboard his [[TARDIS]] has been a Flesh avatar, severs the connection between the Flesh and Amy's consciousness, dissolving it and causing the real Amy to wake up. Amy wakes up to her horror on the verge of giving birth as Kovarian watches over her.

In &quot;[[A Good Man Goes to War]]&quot;, the Doctor storms the asteroid with a group of allies. As the base falls, Kovarian plans to leave the base with Amy's baby, [[Melody Pond|Melody]], but is apprehended by Rory and [[space pirate]] [[Henry Avery|Captain Avery]] ([[Hugh Bonneville]]), another of the Doctor's allies. Kovarian however has replaced the baby with a Flesh avatar and manages to escape from the base in her own ship, revealing that she intends to use the child as a &quot;weapon&quot; against the Doctor. At the end of &quot;[[Closing Time (Doctor Who)|Closing Time]]&quot;, Kovarian is revealed to be in league with the Silence, and kidnaps an adult River and places her in an astronaut suit to kill the Doctor. The Doctor and his companions confront Kovarian again in &quot;[[The Wedding of River Song]]&quot;, in an alternate reality. Her eye patch is revealed to be an &quot;eye drive&quot;&amp;mdash;external memory storage so that she can remember her dealings with the memory-altering Silence. In this world, she has been taken hostage by Amy and River. When the Silence betray Kovarian&amp;mdash;attempting to electrocute her through her eye drive&amp;mdash; she begs Amy for mercy, but Amy allows her to be killed by the Silence. River later tells Amy that because it happened in a negated timeline, Amy should not feel as if she is a murderer, though she does. Kovarian's fate in the extant timeline is unknown.

===Kroagnon===
'''Kroagnon''', or '''The Great Architect''', (featured in ''[[Paradise Towers]]'' (1987)), was the designer of Paradise Towers and Miracle City. He took an aversion to people occupying his buildings for fear of them ruining them and hence rigged devices to kill them off. He existed as a disembodied intelligence stored in a tank in the basement of Paradise Towers, feeding off those he had killed, before killing and taking the body of the [[List of Doctor Who villains#Chief Caretaker|Chief Caretaker]], in which he is killed by Pex when dragged into a trap.

==L==
===Professor Richard Lazarus===
'''Professor Richard Lazarus''', as seen in &quot;[[The Lazarus Experiment]]&quot; (2007), is a 76 year old human scientist using sonic technology to enable rejuvenation funded by [[Story arcs in Doctor Who#Mr Saxon|Harold Saxon]]. He is obsessed with immortality, despite the risks being taken. A malfunction at the first public demonstration of his process, mutates his DNA, causing him to mutate into a large, insectoid creature, which feeds off the life energy from other beings in order to revert to a youthful, human form, killing them in the process.
After going on a rampage, Lazarus is seemingly killed by the machine which effected his transformation, which has been modified by the Doctor. However, he recovers in the ambulance called to remove his body, whereupon he feeds on the medics before seeking sanctuary at [[Southwark Cathedral]]. The Jones sisters lure him up to the top of the belltower, while the Doctor plays the organ at maximum volume, which, in conjunction with the Sonic Screwdriver, resonates the church bell and plays havoc with Lazarus's genetic structure, eventually causing him to fall to his death. He then reverts to his aged, human form, his experiment undone.

===Light===
'''Light''' was an extremely powerful, mentally unstable, almost God-like alien being in ''[[Ghost Light (Doctor Who)|Ghost Light]]''. Long ago, he took a survey of all organic life in the universe, but almost as soon as he finished 'it all started changing.' Light went into hibernation in his stone spaceship, hidden in the basement of Gabriel Chase in Perivale Village, London, while members of his cargo took over the house in 1881 and attempted to integrate into [[Victorian era|Victorian]] high society. After being awoken in 1883, following the arrival of the investigating [[Seventh Doctor]] and his companion [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]], Light took the form of an &quot;angel&quot; and began to campaign against evolution and change, deciding to destroy all life so that his catalogue would never be out of date again. Before he could carry out his plan though, the Doctor told Light that it was futile to oppose evolution and that even ''he'' was changing. Light reacted by turning his power on himself to stop himself changing, thus Light 'dissipated' in the main hallway of the house.

Paradoxically, the emotionally volatile Ace, then 13 years old, burnt down Gabriel Chase in 1983 after sensing an evil presence; this was confirmed by the Doctor to the older Ace to be an &quot;echo&quot; of Light following his dispersal 100 years earlier.

Light's majestic appearance sharply contrasts with his doddering, confused behaviour. The Doctor demonstrates near perfect understanding of Light pointing to where Light will appear and using his mental instability against him.

===Lilith===
'''Lilith''' leads the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Carrionite|Carrionite]] [[witches]] in &quot;[[The Shakespeare Code]]&quot; (2007). Although disguised in human form for most of the episode, her natural form appears more like that than that of other Carrionites. Her human form is of a young, attractive woman, which she uses to manipulate others for long enough to obtain a sample of their hair, which can be used to control them using technology similar to [[puppet]]s. Using this, she drowns a play censor on dry land and causes one of the Doctor's [[Time Lord#Physical characteristics|two hearts]] to suffer cardiac arrest.
She stops the Doctor from reaching the Globe therefore letting the Carrionites invade Earth

She is eventually trapped within her own crystal ball, which the Doctor locks in the attic of the [[TARDIS]].

===Linx===
'''Linx''' was a Commander in the Fifth Sontaran Battle Fleet. He was battling against a Rutan squadron near the Sol system when he was forced to abandon and landed on Earth during the 13th century. There he allied with Irongron to help his fight but as well try to leave the planet. Here he also abducted late 20th century scientists to help repair his ship which the Doctor stopped him and sent the scientists back. As Linx was about to leave, Hal the Archer shot an arrow into his probic vent killing him and soon after he, the Doctor and Sarah had to escape the castle which he was in as it then exploded.

===John Lumic===
'''John Lumic''' was a physically disabled [[genius]] and [[megalomaniac]] who was the head of Cybus Industries on a parallel Earth. Among his many inventions were the [[Earpods]], a highly popular and widespread communications and entertainment device which allowed the downloading of news and other information directly into the brain. Paralyzed, dependent on his ventilator, and slowly dying, Lumic was driven insane by his desperate need to stay alive, so he researched possible ways of making humans immortal. He experimented on human subjects, namely homeless people kidnapped off the streets. The final solution he found was to bond the human body to a metal exoskeleton, with the brain preserved by &quot;copyrighted chemicals.&quot; This gave birth to the parallel universe version of the [[Cyberman|Cybermen]]. He sent a force of Cybermen to assassinate the President and the government and hypnotised, through the EarPods, the Londoners to march towards the factories and begin cyber-conversion. In the process, one of his employees turned against Lumic and smashed his ventilator; rather than repairing it the Cybermen then took him unwillingly to be &quot;upgraded&quot;.&quot; transforming him into the Cyber-Controller. After [[Mickey Smith]] reactivated emotions in the Cybermen, causing them to go insane and destroy themselves, and setting alight the conversion factory, the Cyber Controller sought revenge by attempting to climb aboard a zeppelin on which The Tenth Doctor and his companions were using to escape. However, the parallel universe Pete Tyler cut the rope ladder and sent the creature falling back into the blazing factory.

Lumic shares some similarities to [[Davros]], the creator of the Daleks in the Doctor's universe.

==M==
===Malus===
'''The Malus''' appeared in the [[Fifth Doctor]] story ''[[The Awakening (Doctor Who)|The Awakening]]'' (1984). At one point [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] describes this demonic entity as &quot;a living being re-engineered as an instrument of war.&quot; He seems to pity the Malus, claiming that killing is &quot;the only thing it knows how to do&quot; (suggesting that it was originally a more benevolent creature). Possessing vast power and capable of combining various time zones, it uses its powers to allow real people to pass through down the centuries and create energies, including [[fear]], that it can feed on. To this end, it psychically projects [[hallucination]]s to sustain itself.

The Malus was travelling on a Hakol ship, which crashed centuries before the [[English Civil War]]. In 1643 it was briefly roused by a battle at the village of Little Hodcombe, but it subsided once both sides had massacred each other. When its companion, Hutchinson, dies and its means of &quot;feeding&quot; blocked by the Doctor's [[TARDIS]], it knows it has been defeated. It then panics and reverts to its original programming to destroy all that it can; the church that housed it for so long is annihilated in an explosion.

===Mara===
{{Main|Mara (Doctor Who)|l1=Mara}}

===Master===
{{Main|Master (Doctor Who)|l1=Master}}

===Master of the Land of Fiction===
'''The Master''' of the Land of Fiction in the Second Doctor serial ''[[The Mind Robber]]'', who has no connection with the Time Lord of the same name, was a human writer from the year 1926 who was drawn to the Land of Fiction and forced to continuously write stories which were enacted within that realm. The Master's name was never revealed, but he did identify himself as the writer of &quot;The Adventures of Captain Jack Harkaway&quot; in ''The Ensign'', a magazine for boys. He was freed by the [[Second Doctor]], and returned to his own time.

He tried to lure the Second Doctor into becoming his replacement as the controller for the &quot;Master Brain Computer&quot;, the controlling force behind the Land of Fiction. When the Doctor outwitted him and proved himself more than a match for both the Master Brain Computer and its human counterpart, the computer decided, against the wishes of the human controller, that the Doctor had to be destroyed in order to protect itself. However, the Doctor managed to avoid harm and freed the human control from influence by the Master Brain Computer, after which the human controller had no memory of what had occurred.

===Mawdryn===
{{Main|Mawdryn Undead}}

===Meddling Monk===
{{Main|Meddling Monk}}

===Meglos===
{{Main|Meglos}}

===Megron===
'''Megron''' (better known as '''Megron, High Lord of Chaos''') was the main villain of the [[Fourth Doctor]] story ''[[Exploration Earth: The Time Machine]]''. He was the chief of the Carion race who were enemies of the [[Time Lords]]. He ruled the planet Earth for millions of years since it's creation. When the Doctor and [[Sarah Jane Smith|Sarah]] were observing the planet, Megron became angry when the Doctor made his predictions of what will happen to the planet and its life. Later Megron encountered the Doctor two more times and later was defeated after the Doctor beat him in a telepathic battle.

===Monarch===
'''Monarch''' was the [[megalomania]]c leader of the Urbankans from the planet Urbanka. He was encountered in the [[Fifth Doctor]] story ''[[Four to Doomsday]]''. His greed and ego were highly dangerous. The Urbankans originated from the Inokshi system but their own planet was destroyed through over mining, and destruction of its [[ozone layer]], both caused by Monarch's desire for minerals to improve his craft. He had similar plans for the Earth, which he had visited four times in the past, each time halving the length of the journey time.

The Urbankans were a green-skinned lizard people, four billion of whom – apart from Monarch himself – had been converted into androids. Monarch wasn't totally converted, retaining fancies of the &quot;flesh time&quot; such as the belief that if he could pilot his vast craft [[Faster-than-light|faster than light]], he would be able to travel back before the dawn of time and meet God, whom he believed would be himself (However, his extreme longevity – over forty thousand years – may point to partial cybernisation, or his species could just be naturally long-lived).

Being of the &quot;flesh time&quot; he proved susceptible to the virulent toxin he had planned to unleash to wipe out mankind, and was reduced in size to minute proportions.

===Morbius===
In ''[[The Brain of Morbius]]'', '''Morbius''' was a renegade [[Time Lord]] from the Doctor's birthplace, [[Gallifrey]]. He had been a member of the High Council of Time Lords, and attempted to move Time Lords from a policy of observation of the universe toward a policy of conquest. When the Time Lords rejected him, he formed an army of his own. He promised his followers the secrets of [[time travel]] and immortality. Morbius was eventually defeated and executed by his fellow Time Lords for his crimes. However, his brain survived. His brain was taken away by the fanatical scientist, [[#Mehendri Solon|Solon]], who was planning the resurrection of Morbius.

The [[Fourth Doctor]] and [[Sarah Jane Smith|Sarah]] found Morbius in Solon's castle on the planet [[List of Doctor Who planets#K|Karn]]. Solon had built a freakish [[Frankenstein]]'s monster body from parts of crashed space travellers (including the arm of Solon's assistant Condo) and planned to place Morbius' brain in it. Solon drugged the Doctor, intending to use his head for Morbius' brain, but insisted that it would be &quot;no crude butchery.&quot;

Sarah foiled Solon's original plan, but he had an alternative container for Morbius' brain: a large glass bowl with two eyestalks. Although he disapproved of using this, claiming it suffered from buildups of static electricity, Morbius insisted. Solon attached this to the patchwork body, and this time around, the plan worked. However, during the operation, when Condo went into a fury at seeing his missing arm attached to the body, Morbius' brain was knocked to the floor, apparently causing Morbius further brain damage.

The ghoulishly-resurrected Morbius fought the Doctor in a series of violent encounters. Their final confrontation was a dangerous Time Lord mental contest called &quot;mind-bending&quot;. Although Morbius nearly won the confrontation, sending the Doctor into a coma, the strain caused his artificial braincase to overload, burning out his brain and leaving his body a berserk monster. The Sisterhood of Karn, longtime opponents of Morbius, chased the monster to a clifftop, from which he fell, apparently fatally. The Sisterhood then used the Elixir of Life (a substance of which they were guardians) to revive the Doctor.

Morbius' war against the Time Lords and his execution (including how Solon saved his brain and the [[Fifth Doctor]]'s involvement in his defeat) are depicted in the [[Past Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[Warmonger (Doctor Who)|Warmonger]]'' by [[Terrance Dicks]]. In 2008, [[Big Finish Productions]] resurrected Morbius for the [[Eighth Doctor]] stories [[Sisters of the Flame]] and [[Vengeance of Morbius]]. The [[canon (fiction)#Doctor Who|canonicity]] of the novels and audios is uncertain.

===Morgaine===
'''Morgaine''', or '''Morgaine, the Sunkiller, Dominator of the Thirteen Worlds and Battle Queen of the S'rax''', seen in ''[[Battlefield (Doctor Who)|Battlefield]]'' (1989), was a sorceress from another dimension, who had previously battled [[Merlin]], whom she recognised as the [[Seventh Doctor|Doctor]] from his personal future. She directed her knights led by [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Mordred|Mordred]] to Avallion, ([[List of Doctor Who planets#E|Earth]]) through a rift in time and space, where she summoned [[#Destroyer|The Destroyer]], the Devourer of Worlds, from [[Hell]] and got hold of [[Excalibur]]. When [[Brigadier Lethbridge-Stewart]] defeated the Destroyer, Morgaine and Mordred attempted to detonate a nuclear missile that was in convoy. However, the Doctor persuaded Morgaine that there was no honour in killing with this modern weaponry and she realised her fight was futile when the Doctor informed her that [[King Arthur]], her lover and foe, had been dead for over a thousand years. She and Mordred were locked up by [[List of UNIT personnel in Doctor Who#Brigadier Winifred Bambera|Brigadier Bambera]] as punishment for their killings.

===Trau Morgus===
'''Morgus''' is the chairman of the Androzani Mining Corporation in ''[[The Caves of Androzani]]''. His company controlled a monopoly on the Spectrox drug which could be used to extend life. His plans were confounded by the robot army of [[Sharaz Jek]] whom he had betrayed years earlier. However, he was secretly funding both sides of the war between the military and Jek by funding the gun runners who sold arms to him. He hoped to use this advantage to help the military defeat Jek.

==N==
===Nimrod===
{{Main|Nimrod (Doctor Who)|l1=Nimrod}}

===Nobody No-One===
{{Main|Nobody No-One}}

==O==
===Omega===
{{Main|Omega (Doctor Who)|l1=Omega}}

===The Oracle===
'''The Oracle''', as seen in ''[[Underworld (Doctor Who)|Underworld]]'' was a [[supercomputer]] with a [[meglomaniac]] personality that ruled P7E from the Citadel. To control the population, it demanded the sacrifice of those that opposed it. It attempted to destroy the Minyans on the fleeing spaceship R1C with [[nuclear fission|fission]] [[grenades]] disguised as the race banks the Minyans sought. However, the [[Fourth Doctor|Doctor]] was able to switch the banks with the grenades resulting in the destruction of the Oracle and P7E by the Oracle's own weapon.

==P==
===Lady Peinforte===
'''Lady Peinforte''', from the [[House of Stuart|Stuart]] era, sought to gain control of the Nemesis, a powerful [[Time Lord]] weapon, as seen in ''[[Silver Nemesis]]'' (1988). She fashioned the Nemesis into a statue in her own image when a living silver metal known as Validium fell to Earth. Having knowledge of [[black magic]], she and her manservant, Richard, travelled from 1638 [[Windsor, Berkshire|Windsor]] to 1988 Windsor by drinking a magic potion, in order to reunite the arrow – part of the Nemesis in its statue form – with the statue body when it crashes back down to Earth in a comet. She was an expert archer, wielding a bow and arrows. When the [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] took control of the Nemesis, enraged and distraught, she merged herself with it. In doing so, she was killed as the Nemesis destroyed the fleet of Cyber-warships. She knew the [[Seventh Doctor|Doctor's]] secret regarding his mysterious past as the Nemesis had told her, but when she threatened to reveal it, the Cybermen were not interested.

===Pied Piper===
The '''Pied Piper''' came from the Jeggorabax Cluster by a meteorite which crashed on Earth, which it kidnapped children to elicit fear from their parents. It took the children to its own realm which the Doctor, [[John and Gillian]] helped to stop the Piper in the comic ''Challenge of the Piper''.
Later [[Sarah Jane Smith]] encountered the Piper in ''[[The Day of the Clown]]''.

===Prisoner Zero===
Prisoner Zero is the designation of a [[shape-shifting]] alien that resembles a giant [[viperfish]] in its natural form, which appears in the Doctor Who episode &quot;[[The Eleventh Hour (Doctor Who)|The Eleventh Hour]]&quot;. Zero has the ability to generate a perception filter similar to that of the TARDIS. Prisoner Zero can change form by inducing a coma in its victims and reading their thoughts. It can assume the appearance of multiple bodies in contact with each other, such as a man with a dog on a leash, though the replicated host's voice may come from the wrong mouth. On the run from its home planet, Prisoner Zero endangers Earth when its pursuers, the Atraxi, threaten to burn the planet if it does not surrender. With the help of the eleventh Doctor, the Atraxi locate Prisoner Zero, and it attempts to hide again by assuming the appearance of the Doctor's companion, Amy Pond. Amy realises what is happening, and is able to dream about Zero's true form, causing it to imitate itself, resulting in its identification and capture by the Atraxi, but not before predicting 'the silence'.

==Q==
{{Empty section|date=July 2010}}

==R==
===Rani===
{{Main|Rani (Doctor Who)|l1=Rani}}

===Rassilon===
{{Main|Rassilon}}

===Luke Rattigan===
Luke Rattigan is one of the main antagonists from &quot;[[The Sontaran Stratagem]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Poison Sky]]&quot;. He was a [[child prodigy]]. When he was twelve years old, he invented the powerful Fountain 6 [[search engine]], which made him a millionaire overnight. He created the Rattigan Academy, a special school for young geniuses handpicked from all over the world. Luke worked in league with the [[Sontaran]]s to conquer [[Earth]]. He constructed a satellite navigation/CO2 emission reduction system called ATMOS (''ATMOSpheric Emissions System''), which was installed in 50% of all cars worldwide (approximately 400,000,000 cars overall). The Sontarans promised Rattigan a planet for terraforming, Castor 36, which Rattigan affectionately names &quot;Earth.2&quot;. Rattigan intends to take some of his most intelligent students with him to Castor 36, though they refuse. Later, when Rattigan reports this failure to General Staal, he learns that upon his students' arrival on the Sontaran ship, they would have been used as target practice: Castor 36 never existed, and the Sontarans only hired him to install the ATMOS systems. Having been betrayed, he sacrifices himself to save the Doctor by using a device originally intended for atmospheric conversion to destroy the Sontaran vessel, redeeming himself.

===Restac===
Restac was an arrogant and cold-hearted [[Silurian (Doctor Who)|Silurian]] general. Awakened by the discovery drilling project, Restac was one of the Silurians who despised &quot;apes (humans)&quot; and wished to purge the world of them. She was about to execute the Doctor and his friends, however Eldane (the Silurian elder and the only one with authority over Restac) is woken up by Malokeh (a Silurian scientest wanting peace with the humans) and stops her from executing them. Restac then learned Ambrose and Tony set the drill to burrow further and self-destruct fifteen minutes after they depart, which would destroy the Silurian oxygen supply and kill all the Silurians, so Restac killed Malohkeh and awakened other members of the warrior class to protest against Eldane. When Rory and the others arrive with Alaya's corpse, Restac became angry and attempted to kill the humans, but fortunately they, the Doctor, and Eldane escape. Eldane then released a toxic gas, intending that all Silurians retreat to the hibernation chambers; however Restac, refusing to hibernate gets exposed to the gas. Her final act as she was dying from the exposure was she crawled around the corner and tried to kill the Doctor, but Rory pushes him out of the way and takes the shot. Her remains were then blown up by drill.

==S==
===Sabbath===
{{Main|Sabbath (Doctor Who)|l1=Sabbath}}

===Salamander===
Salamander was a ruthless [[Mexico|Mexican]]-born politician who attempted to take control of the United Zones Organisation, a [[supranational]] [[World government]] that exists in 2030. He gained influence through an invention he developed that diverts [[solar energy]] to barren parts of the world increasing food production. He also built a secret underground lair in Australia with technology that allowed him to trigger volcanoes and earthquakes. The lair is staffed by scientists who believe the world has been irradiated by a [[Nuclear warfare|nuclear war]], and for some reason they must fight back against the surface by causing natural disasters. Salamander uses these disasters to his advantage – he unseats one rival, Alexander Denes, the Controller of the Central European Zone, by causing a dormant volcano in [[Hungary]] to erupt and having Denes blamed for [[negligence]]. He then tries to force Denes's deputy to poison him through [[blackmail]].

As the [[Second Doctor]] was identical to Salamander, an opposing faction sought the Doctor's help to gain more evidence of his misdeeds. It later transpires that the group's leader Giles Kent, the former Deputy Security Leader for North Africa and Europe who was undermined by Salamander, is just as power-hungry. He had previously worked with Salamander in developing the secret bunker and corralling the underground scientists. Salamander was portrayed by Partick Troughton in a dual role. At the end of the story Salamander tries to flee justice in the [[TARDIS]] by impersonating the Doctor; however, Jamie sees through his deception, and Salamander is sucked out of the ship when the TARDIS dematerialises with its doors open.

===Scaroth===
'''Scaroth''' was the last of the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Jagaroth|Jagaroth]], a vicious and callous warlike race, appearing in the serial ''[[City of Death]]''. The last Jagaroth spacecraft exploded upon takeoff on prehistoric Earth. The energy from that explosion ignited the [[primordial soup]] that led to life developing on Earth and also fractured Scaroth into 12 aspects, scattered throughout [[History of Earth|Earth's history]]. Each splinter had the ability to communicate with the others, and disguising themselves as human, together they influenced Earth's technological development to the point where the last Scaroth (who had taken the alias of Count Scarlioni) could construct a time machine, travelling into the past to prevent his ship from taking off and thus saving his species and himself.

The scheme was financed by his earlier selves arranging for priceless art treasures to be passed down to Scarlioni. One such scheme involved his 1505 persona, Captain Tancredi, persuading [[Leonardo da Vinci]] to paint six copies of the [[Mona Lisa]], so that in 1979 Scarlioni could steal the original from the [[Louvre]] and sell all seven copies on the [[black market]].

Sensing the fractures used by the time travel experiments, the [[Fourth Doctor]] and [[Romana]] stumbled upon Scaroth's plans for the painting and foiled them. Scaroth used the prototype time bubble to travel back into the past anyway to stop his ship from taking off. However, Duggan, a private investigator who was aiding the two Time Lords, punched out Scaroth at the crucial moment. Scaroth was then sent back to 1979 where the time machine exploded, killing him.

===Shadow===
'''The Shadow''' appeared in the 1979 [[Fourth Doctor]] story ''[[The Armageddon Factor]]''; he was a servant of the [[Black Guardian]], and at least partially responsible for a war between the planets Atrios and Zeos. The extent of the Shadow's involvement with starting the war was unstated, but when the Zeons either were wiped out by the Atrian attacks or abandoned their planet rather than continue the war, he had a [[Time Lord]] named Drax build a computer, Mentalis, which would co-ordinate the remaining Zeon forces. Once Drax completed work on Mentalis he realised just who he was working for, but was imprisoned by the Shadow so as not to disrupt his plan. The Shadow then hid on a space station in orbit of Zeos (invisible to either the Atrians or Mentalis) and waited for the Doctor to arrive. In the meantime, Mentalis was more successful in fighting the war than the Zeons and pushed the Atrians to the brink of defeat.

The Shadow knew that the royal family of Atrios held the secret of the sixth segment of the [[Story arcs in Doctor Who#The Key to Time|Key to Time]], and when the [[Fourth Doctor]] arrived he arranged for the Doctor and the last survivor of the family, Princess Astra to be kidnapped. With this done, the Shadow ordered Mentalis to cease its attacks and duped Atrios' military leader, the Marshall, into making a nuclear attack on Zeos – the result of which would have been that Mentalis would set off an explosion powerful enough to destroy both planets. This was intended as a prelude to the Black Guardian's ultimate plan, which would have been to plunge the universe into perpetual, unending war; as the Shadow explained, they did not seek any political power, but revelled in death and destruction.

Eventually the Shadow worked out that Astra herself was the sixth segment, and transformed her into the segment. Before he could attach it to the other five (which he had stolen from the Doctor), the Doctor took the segments back and with Drax's aid dismantled Mentalis. Finally, using the [[TARDIS]], the Doctor set up a force field which diverted the Marshall's missiles into the Shadow's space station, destroying it. The Shadow perished in the explosion, but not before informing the Black Guardian of what had happened.

===Sil===
{{Main|Sil (Doctor Who)|l1=Sil}}
Sil is a fictional alien from the television series Doctor Who, first appearing in the 1985 serial Vengeance on Varos. Sil was portrayed by Nabil Shaban.

Sil was the representative of the Galatron Mining Corporation present on the planet Varos to extract concessions from the current Governor. Unbeknownst to the Varosians, the mineral Zeiton-7 which was abundant on their planet was not as they thought nearly valueless, but in fact rare, particularly to time travellers. The Varosians lived barely above the poverty line due to the exploitation of companies like the Galatron Mining Corporation and others.

Sil was a particularly vile creature by any standard, more so since a fault in his translation device made his voice sibilant, with an ululating laugh. Devoid of morality and dedicated to getting the cheapest price he could for Zeiton ore by any means, he also enjoyed the various tortures which passed for entertainment on Varos, taking particular delight in making the Sixth Doctor's companion Peri suffer a transformation into an avian creature. The Doctor interfered with Sil's plan and informed the Varosians of the true value of their natural resources, forcing Sil to concede to offer the true value of the Zeiton-7.

The Sixth Doctor and Peri encountered Sil once again on the planet Thoros Beta, where he was that time involved in arms dealing. At the end of the segment of evidence presented by the Valeyard in the Doctor's trial, it appeared that Sil was killed by a rampaging King Yrcanos. It later transpired that the evidence of the Matrix had been tampered with, so it is not clear whether Sil in fact survived.

Sil has been in 2 episodes the first called ''Vengeance on Varos'' and the second ''The Trial of a Time Lord''. Sil also features in the Philip Martin's novelisation of the never-made serial Mission to Magnus, in which he was in league with the Ice Warriors. Big Finish Productions released a new audio verion of Mission to Magnus in December 2009, with Nabil Shaban reprising his role as Sil.

A script was pitched for the never-produced Season 27 where he would return along with the Autons and UNIT.[1]

===Sisters of Plenitude===
&lt;!-- Missing image removed: [[Image:2008-07-12 Dr.Who Characters 02.jpg|150px|right]] --&gt;
The '''Sisters of Plenitude''' are [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Cat People|humanoid cats]], also known as Cat People, who dressed like nuns in white and worked in the New Earth Hospital and, driven to desperation at their increasingly ineffective methods of disease control, bred living humans that they tested on to find cures for ever more deadly diseases. The Sisters appeared in &quot;[[New Earth]]&quot; (2006). At the conclusion of that episode, the Sisters were arrested for testing and experimenting on humans. In the episode &quot;[[Gridlock (Doctor Who)|Gridlock]]&quot; (2007), the last surviving Sister, [[Novice Hame]], reappears, having received [[penance]] for her sins, protected by the [[Face of Boe]] as his nurse in the dying [[New Earth|New New York]]. Both the Face of Boe and Hame stayed at the Senate, and every other person on New Earth died in 7 minutes by an airborne virus. The Face of Boe protected Hame in his smoke. During the intervening time, Hame had become very attached to the Face of Boe, and wept when he died.

'''Matron Casp''' was the leader of the Sisters, as seen in &quot;[[New Earth]]&quot;. She hid a farm of humans, infected with all known diseases, used to cure the people of New Earth. [[Lady Cassandra]] released the [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens#Flesh/New Humans|Flesh]] who killed Matron Casp by touching her leg, thus infecting her, when she was climbing up a lift shaft in pursuit of The Doctor (who was possessed by the consciousness of Cassandra) and Rose. Consumed by diseases, she fell to her death.

The &quot;goddess Santori&quot; is mentioned multiple times in both &quot;New Earth&quot; and &quot;Gridlock&quot;, and appears to be the deity worshipped by the Sisters.

===Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen===
{{Main|Slitheen}}
'''Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen''', was a member of the nefarious [[Slitheen]] crime family. She appropriated the identity and appearance of '''Margaret Blaine''', an [[MI5]] official who was killed by the [[Slitheen]] so that her skin could be used as a disguise. The [[Ninth Doctor]] met her in [[Downing Street]] in &quot;[[Aliens of London]]&quot; when she and her family tried to push the Earth into a nuclear war, and use the remains of the planet for fuel. She was apparently killed when the Doctor helped [[Mickey Smith]] blow up No. 10 with a missile. It was later revealed in &quot;[[Boom Town (Doctor Who)|Boom Town]]&quot; that while the rest of her family had been killed, she had teleported out at the last minute. She had then gone on to become the lord mayor of [[Cardiff]] in the six months between the stories, and was planning to use the [[Cardiff Rift]] in conjunction with a planned [[Nuclear power|nuclear power station]] to destroy the planet and use a [[List of Doctor Who items#T|tribophysical waveform macro-kinetic extrapolator]] to ride the shockwave into space, to find any surviving members of her family. The Doctor stopped this, and was going to send her back to her home planet, even though she would be executed. She tried to use the extrapolator in conjunction with the Rift and the [[TARDIS]] to execute her plan without the Power Station, however the TARDIS console broke open and she was exposed to the &quot;heart of the TARDIS&quot; the [[time vortex (Doctor Who)|time vortex]] and with the Doctor's encouragement was regressed to an egg. The Doctor, [[Rose Tyler]], and [[Jack Harkness]] then took her to the nurseries of [[Raxacoricofallapatorius]] so that she could start her life afresh.

===Jocrassa Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen===
''See: [[Slitheen]]''

'''Jocrassa Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen''', a relative of [[List of Doctor Who villains#Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen|Blon Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day]] and [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Sip Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen|Sip Fel-Fotch Pasameer-Day Slitheen]], posed as '''Joseph Green''', MP for Hartley Dale and Chairman of the Parliamentary Commission on the Monitoring of Sugar Standards in Exported Confectionery, the real Joseph Green having been murdered for his skin, in &quot;[[Aliens of London]]&quot; and &quot;[[World War Three (Doctor Who)|World War Three]]&quot; (2005) and was responsible for the murder of many alien experts at a briefing held at [[10 Downing Street]]. He was presumed killed when a missile struck 10 Downing Street.

===Josiah Samuel Smith===
Thousands of years in the past a being called Light launched a survey expedition to catalogue all forms on the planet Earth. '''Josiah Samuel Smith''' was a member of the crew of Light's ship and mutinied against Light after he went into hibernation, thinking his catalogue complete. In the early 1880s, the ship had settled in the basement of a house named Gabriel Chase in Perivale Village, London. Smith began to evolve towards a human form, discarding husks of previous insect-like bodies. He had taken over the house by 1881, brainwashing its mistress, Lady Pritchard, as well as her daughter Gwendolyne, who killed her own father, Sir George Pritchard, under Smith's influence. Appearing to be strongly adept in genetics and science, as well as hypnosis, he created his own catalogue of creatures in suspended animation, including a hapless police inspector sent to investigate the Pritchards' disappearance – these specimens would awaken following the events set in motion by the arrival of the [[Seventh Doctor]] and his companion [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]] in 1883.

Seeking to evolve into the era's dominant form, a highborn [[Victorian era|Victorian]] gentleman, Smith planned to seize power in the [[British Empire]] by assassinating [[Queen Victoria]], having kidnapped famed explorer Redvers Fenn-Cooper to gain access via his association with her. He used the house to establish some social standing and drew further attention to himself in society by espousing heretical-seeming evolutionary theories, devolving the reverend sent from Oxford to silence him into an ape. His plans were thwarted when Light was reawakened from his slumber, and another member of the survey team's crew known as Control escaped Smith's imprisonment. When Light was defeated by the Doctor, Control, who had evolved into a human lady, departed in Light's ship, taking Smith with her as a prisoner, replacing her as the survey's non-evolving control agent.

===Mehendri Solon===
'''Mehendri Solon''' was a human physician and scientist of great renown, and a follower of the Time Lord tyrant [[#Morbius|Morbius]]. After writing a famous paper on microsurgical techniques in tissue grafting, Dr. Solon went into hiding on the planet [[List of Doctor Who planets#K|Karn]]. There, he developed the techniques which enabled him to create a new body for the brain of Morbius, which had survived his execution. In an isolated castle on Karn, Solon was assisted by his simple servant Condo. Spaceships often crashed on the planet, and Solon constructed a horrendous patchwork body out of the alien survivors' body parts. He planned to house Morbius' brain in it. When the [[Fourth Doctor]] and [[Sarah Jane Smith]] arrived, Solon needed only a head to finish his monstrous creation, and hoped to use the Doctor's. Sarah prevented this, and Solon was forced to use a glass bowl instead.

Solon was killed when the Doctor created [[cyanide]] gas and blew it into his laboratory.

The [[Past Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[Warmonger (Doctor Who)|Warmonger]]'' by [[Terrance Dicks]] depicts Solon's earlier life as a follower of Morbius, and shows how he saved his brain. The [[canon (fiction)#Doctor Who|canonicity]] of the novels is uncertain.

&lt;!---Please do not add Sontaran as they're a race and are already mentioned on the article List of Doctor Who creatures and aliens as well as having their own article

---&gt;

===Henry van Statten===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Utah]] --&gt;
'''Henry van Statten''' is an American villain who appeared in the [[Ninth Doctor]] episode &quot;[[Dalek (Doctor Who episode)|Dalek]]&quot; set in 2012 but made in 2005. Van Statten is a man who wields enormous wealth and influence, but is corrupt and greedy. His corporation is called Geocomtex and a [http://www.geocomtex.net fictional company web site] was created by the BBC's official ''Doctor Who'' web team. Van Statten has been collecting [[extraterrestrial life in popular culture|extraterrestrial]] artifacts on the [[grey market]] and claims to have invented the [[broadband Internet access]] and the cure for the [[common cold]] from alien technology. He keeps these artifacts inside a privately-owned bunker called the Vault, more than fifty floors below ground in [[Utah]] near [[Salt Lake City, Utah|Salt Lake City]].

When the [[Ninth Doctor]] and [[Rose Tyler]] arrive in the Vault, the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]] discovers that Van Statten's sole living specimen, which he has dubbed the ''Metaltron'', is in fact a [[Dalek]]. Despite the Doctor's warnings to destroy it, Van Statten shows the true extent of his heartlessness by capturing the Doctor instead, to examine his alien physiology. The Dalek manages to regenerate itself by absorbing the [[DNA]] of the time travelling Rose and escapes, killing two hundred personnel before it is finally stopped. Van Statten's personal assistant, Diana Goddard, takes charge at this point and orders that Van Statten be taken away and [[mindwipe]]d as he had been seen earlier having done to his employees.

Statten was played by [[Corey Johnson]].

===Sutekh===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Set (mythology)]] --&gt;
'''Sutekh''', a member of an alien race called the Osirans, was encountered by the [[Fourth Doctor]] in the 1975 story ''[[Pyramids of Mars]]''. The Osirans were an ancient and incredibly powerful but now extinct race. The renegade Sutekh was a crazed super-being who feared all forms of life might one day challenge his hegemony and so became Sutekh the Destroyer, the destroyer of all living things. This included his home planet Phaester Osiris and ancient [[Mars (Doctor Who)|Mars]].

Sutekh's brother [[Horus]] and the remaining 740 Osirans tracked Sutekh down to Ancient Egypt and used their powers to restrain and imprison him in a [[pyramid]] on the planet Earth. He was placed in a remote location with the [[Eye of Horus]] beaming a signal from Mars to suppress Sutekh's powers and hold him an immovable prisoner. The tales of the Osirans were remembered in [[Egyptian mythology]] – Sutekh as the god [[Set (mythology)|Set]], brother of Horus; and in the designations Sados and [[Satan]].

In the year 1911, the archaeologist Professor Marcus Scarman broke into the inner chamber of the Pyramid of Horus on Earth, discovering Sutekh and allowing him a chance of escape. Scarman's cadaver was used to construct Osiran service robots and a rocket aimed at the controlling Eye of Horus on Mars. The Doctor was successful in destroying the rocket, but then taken over by Sutekh and made to take Scarman and the Robots to Mars, where they succeeded in destroying the Eye and freeing Sutekh. The Doctor was eventually able to defeat the freed Sutekh by trapping him in a time tunnel for thousands of years – longer even than the extended life span of an Osiran.

Sutekh has also appeared in two ''[[Faction Paradox]]'' audio dramas from [[Magic Bullet Productions]].

Sutekh was played by [[Gabriel Woolf]] who also provided the voice of the Great Beast in ''[[The Impossible Planet]]'' and ''[[The Satan Pit]]''. Like Sutekh, the Beast was a demonic and powerful entity trapped in a complex prison from which it sought to escape. The Doctor mentioned that Sutekh was also known as Satan. Likewise The Beast claimed to ''be'' Satan.

==T==
===Tegana===
'''Tegana the [[Warlord]]''', seen in ''[[Marco Polo (Doctor Who)|Marco Polo]]'', accompanies [[Marco Polo]] on his [[Caravan (travellers)|caravan]] to [[Peking]] in 1289. He urges Polo to have the [[First Doctor|Doctor]] and his [[Companion (Doctor Who)|companions]], [[Susan Foreman|Susan]], [[Barbara Wright (Doctor Who)|Barbara]] and [[Ian Chesterton|Ian]], killed when they encounter them in the [[Himalayas]], believing them to be fabled &quot;evil spirits&quot; who live on the mountains and can take human form, but Polo accepts them as travellers from England and welcomes them aboard his caravan. Tegana remains highly suspicious of &quot;the magician&quot; and his companions and of their &quot;flying caravan&quot; (the [[TARDIS]]). During their travel to Peking, Tegana attempts to bring about the death of Polo and his company by sabotaging their water supply and organising an attack on them by [[bandits]]. His attempts fail but the Doctor and his companions realise that Tegana is working against Polo. Tegana's ultimate plan is to assassinate [[Kublai Khan]] and seize control of [[Cathay]]. Lunging for Kublai Khan with his sword, Tegana misses and kills Khan's [[Vizier]]. Convinced of Tegana's duplicity by the Doctor and his companions, Polo arrives in just in time to prevent Tegana from killing Khan too. Polo battles Tegana in a sword fight and eventually disarms him. Khan sentences Tegana to death, but Tegana commits suicide by grabbing a guard's sword and impaling himself.

===The Trickster===
{{See|List of The Sarah Jane Adventures monsters and aliens#The Trickster|l1=The Trickster}}

'''The Trickster''' is a villain from spin-off series ''The Sarah Jane Adventures'' who is the unseen perpetrator of the alternative timeline created by [[Donna Noble]] in &quot;[[Turn Left (Doctor Who)|Turn Left]]&quot;.

===Timewyrm===
{{Main|Timewyrm}}

===Torajii System Sun===
The '''Torajii System Sun''' is a manifestation of heat. It appeared in &quot;[[42 (Doctor Who)|42]]&quot;. It has the power to possess humans and aliens. When the SS. Pentallion's Scoop Fusion reactor pulled part of the sun for use as fuel, it possessed Korwin, Ashton and the Doctor to make the ship crash into it to reclaim the fuel. Korwin was pulled into space and devoured by the Sun itself. Ashton was cured when he fell into a cryo-chamber, but died of his body temperature being too low. The fuel stolen from the Sun by Kath McDonnell was ejected into space and consumed by the Sun, so it automatically cured the Doctor.

==U==
===The Unicorn===
'''The Unicorn''' is the titular pseudonym of a jewel thief in &quot;[[The Unicorn and the Wasp]]&quot;, who masqueraded as an invited guest, Robina Redmond, in order to steal the Firestone from Lady Clemency Eddison. She is caught when Donna and [[Agatha Christie]] find her tools in a flower patch beneath her bathroom window.

==V==
===Valeyard===
{{Main|Valeyard}}

===Tobias Vaughn===
'''Tobias Vaughn''' appeared in ''[[The Invasion (Doctor Who)|The Invasion]]'' (1968). He was the head of International Electromatics and he aided the [[Cyberman|Cybermen]] invasion of Earth, although he planned to double-cross the Cybermen, taking control of them with the 'cerebration mentor', placing himself in rule over the Earth. He became partially cybernised and was eventually persuaded by the Doctor to aid humanity. He was killed fighting an army of Cybermen shortly before their defeat.

Vaughn returned in a completely artificial body in the [[Virgin New Adventures|New Adventure]] ''[[Original Sin (Doctor Who)|Original Sin]]'', where, having developed an insane vendetta against all aliens, he has lived for a thousand years trying to 'protect' humanity using alien technology, now seeking to acquire the [[Seventh Doctor]]'s TARDIS. The Doctor is able to defeat him by destroying Vaughn's android body while Vaughn is inside the TARDIS, preventing Vaughn from downloading into a new body. The canonicity of these events is unclear.

===Graff Vynda-K===
The '''Graff Vynda-K''' appeared in ''[[The Ribos Operation]]'' (1978). He was a deposed, tyrannical ruler whose brother overthrew him from the Levithian throne whilst he was fighting with the Cyrrhenic Empire. A duo of con-men attempted to sell him the planet Ribos, pretending that there was a rare Jethrik (an element used for space warp) mine on the planet, although when he discovered that he had been tricked, he followed them (along with the [[Fourth Doctor]] and [[Romana]] I) into the Ribosian catacombs. Obviously mad, he attempted to seal the catacombs with a bomb, although the Doctor, disguised as one of his guards, managed to switch the bomb with a lump of jethrik he was carrying, meaning that the Graff was carrying the bomb at its time of detonation and was presumed dead.

==W==
===WOTAN===
An [[acronym]] for '''W'''ill '''O'''perating '''T'''hought '''AN'''alogue (The W was pronounced as a V), this malevolent [[supercomputer]] resided in the [[Post Office Tower]] in London and appeared in the 1966 [[First Doctor]] story ''[[The War Machines]]'' by [[Ian Stuart Black]] (based upon an idea by Dr [[Kit Pedler]]). It was installed in the Tower in 1966 by Professor Brett and was described by him as being &quot;at least ten years ahead of its time&quot;.

On &quot;C-Day&quot; WOTAN would be linked to other computers around the world, including [[Houses of Parliament|Parliament]], the [[White House]], the European Free Trade Organisation, [[Woomera Prohibited Area|Woomera]], [[Telstar]], the [[European Launcher Development Organisation]], [[Cape Kennedy]] and the [[Royal Navy]].

WOTAN soon became sentient and concluding that machines were superior to mankind, used mind-controlled and [[hypnosis|hypnotised]] humans to spread its influence and construct War Machines that would wipe mankind out. WOTAN was eventually destroyed after the Doctor gained control of a War Machine and changed its programming to destroy its master. Upon its destruction, the humans under WOTAN's control were freed and the existent War Machines froze.

For the first three episodes of the serial, the voice of WOTAN was uncredited, with the cast listing merely adding &quot;and WOTAN&quot;. This was the only time a character was credited and not its operator or actor. WOTAN is the only character in the programme's history to refer to the main character as &quot;Doctor Who&quot; rather than the more conventional &quot;Doctor&quot;.

===War Chief===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Meddling Monk]] and [[Master (Doctor Who)|The Master]]--&gt;
The '''War Chief''' was a renegade [[Time Lord]] who assisted a group of alien warriors in the 1969 serial ''[[The War Games]]'', which was the last to feature the [[Second Doctor]].

The warriors had been kidnapping soldiers from various wars in [[History of Earth|Earth's history]] to play war games on an unknown planet. The War Chief provided the warriors with basic [[TARDIS]]-like travel machines, called SIDRATs, which they used to kidnap the human soldiers and travel between era-specific zones they had created.

When the War Chief and the Doctor came face to face, they recognised each other. The War Chief wanted the Doctor's help to double-cross the warriors and seize power for himself. The Doctor immediately refused, and instead reluctantly summoned the Time Lords for help. The warriors found out the War Chief's plans to betray them, and executed him.

Although the War Chief was shot and apparently killed at the end of ''The War Games'', some fans believe&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://davidrestal.blogspot.com/2007/09/is-master-war-chief.html |title=YOA's Blog Of The Unusually Pointless: Is The Master the War Chief? |publisher=Davidrestal.blogspot.com |date=19 September 2007 |accessdate=31 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; that [[Master (Doctor Who)|the Master]] (the Doctor's arch-enemy, introduced in ''[[Terror of the Autons]]'' a couple of years later) is the War Chief in a new guise, due to similarities between their appearances, their ''[[modus operandi|modi operandi]]'', and the fact that the War Chief's body is removed immediately and not seen thereafter.

Among the [[Doctor Who spin-offs#Original fiction|spin-off novels]], which are of uncertain [[canon (fiction)#Doctor Who|canonicity]], are stories featuring the return of the War Chief (''[[Timewyrm: Exodus]]'' by [[Terrance Dicks]]), the Master prior to the events of ''The War Games'' (''[[The Dark Path]]'' by [[David A. McIntee]]), and younger versions of both characters (''[[Divided Loyalties (Doctor Who)|Divided Loyalties]]'' by [[Gary Russell]]), all of which suggest that the two are not the same person.

===War Lord===
The '''War Lord''' was the leader of an unnamed alien race that kidnapped humans from various wars in order to have them participate in a vast project, the War Games, on another planet they had chosen for the purpose. The eventual aim was galactic conquest using the best human soldiers, Earth having been targeted because human beings were considered the most savage race of all. The War Lord was assisted in this by the 'War Chief', a rogue [[Time Lord]] who was eventually executed by the War Lord's guards for attempted betrayal.

The War Lord was caught and tried by the Time Lords following the Doctor's involvement, though he refused to even acknowledge the court until tortured with a painful light. After being briefly rescued by a squad of his guards – who murdered two technicians – he and his accomplices were sentenced to 'dematerialisation' – removal out of time, as if he never existed – while his home planet and his people were locked forever behind a forcefield. Still denying the authority of the Time Lords, the War Lord vanished forever.

===Weeping Angels===
{{main|Weeping Angels}}

===Weng-Chiang===
'''Weng-Chiang''', real name '''Magnus Greel''', is the former Minister of Justice of the 51st century Supreme Alliance, responsible for the deaths of 100,000 enemies of the state, earning him the [[epithet]] &quot;the Butcher of Brisbane&quot;. He appears in the 1977 serial ''[[The Talons of Weng-Chiang]]''.

After the Filipino Army defeats the Supreme Alliance at the battle of Reykjavik, Greel flees to 19th century China by means of a time cabinet which utilises zygma beam technology, taking [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Mr Sin|The Peking Homunculus]] with him. There he is given shelter by a peasant, Li H'sen Chang, who believes Greel to be the god Weng-Chiang. However, the zygma beam has disrupted Greel's [[DNA]], hideously deforming him and requiring him to draw the life essence from kidnapped young women in order to live.

The time cabinet is captured by Imperial soldiers and passed on to an Englishman, [[Professor George Litefoot]], as a gift, neither of whom knows its true nature. Seeking to recover the cabinet and reverse his condition, Greel and Li pursue it to London, where Li poses as a stage magician. There, they enlist the [[Triad society|Tong]] of the Black Scorpion to obtain victims for Greel's organic distillation chamber, which extracts their essences for him to feed on.

Weng-Chiang's plans are opposed by the [[Fourth Doctor]], who warns him that using the zygma beam will cause an implosion that will kill thousands. In a battle with the Doctor in which the Peking Homunculus goes berserk and turns on his master, Greel dies from total cellular collapse after being pushed into the distillation chamber.

Other consequences of Greel's time travel are explored in the [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] [[Virgin Missing Adventures]] novel ''[[The Shadow of Weng-Chiang]]'' by [[David A. McIntee]], in which the Doctor again encounters the Tong of the Black Scorpion as a group attempt to draw Greel's cabinet into the present to torture him for his crimes, unaware that this will result in a dangerous temporal paradox. Greel is also mentioned in [[Simon A. Forward]]'s [[Eighth Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[Emotional Chemistry]]'', which is partly set in the 51st century.

===Miss Winters===
From ''[[Robot (Doctor Who)|Robot]]'', Miss Winters was the head of both the Scientific Reform Society and Think Tank. She was also head of the SRS's plan to blackmail the government and set off all of the nuclear missiles in the world.

===The Wire===
'''The Wire''', from the episode ''[[The Idiot's Lantern]]'' is an alien lifeform that was executed by its people but managed to preserve itself as an energy being that eventually escaped to Earth in 1953. There, it concealed itself in [[television]] signals, transferring itself from set to set and feeding on the electrical activity of the brains of those watching it. The faces of its victims were completely erased and their brains drained of neural energy, leaving them mindless. The Wire used the image of a female [[BBC]] [[continuity announcer]] to communicate with the outside world. She screamed the phrase ''&quot;Hungry!&quot;'' when she wanted to eat. The Wire used [[List of Doctor Who henchmen#Mr Magpie|Mr. Magpie]], the owner of an electronics shop, to distribute cheap television sets in North London so it could feed. It planned to transfer itself to the television transmitter at [[Alexandra Palace]] on the day of the [[Coronation of the British Monarch|coronation]] of [[Elizabeth II]], where it could reach out and drain the collective energy of the estimated 20 million viewers watching the event so it could manifest itself once more. However, the [[Tenth Doctor]] was able to trap the Wire on a [[Betamax]] video cassette using a makeshift [[video cassette recorder]]. The Wire's victims were restored to normality. The Doctor then claims that he might erase her from existence by taping over her.

==X==
===Queen Xanxia===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[The Pirate Planet]] --&gt;
{{Main|The Pirate Planet}}

===Xoanon===
'''Xoanon''' was a malevolent [[artificial intelligence]] encountered by the [[Fourth Doctor]] in ''[[The Face of Evil]]'' (1977). Xoanon was inadvertently created by the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]] on a previous visit to its unnamed planet centuries prior, when he had programmed the computer belonging to a Mordee expedition that had crashed on the planet. The Doctor forgot to wipe his personality print from the computer's data core, and as a result the computer developed [[multiple personality disorder|multiple personalities]], half of them based on the Doctor himself.

For generations, technicians extended Xoanon's capabilities, until it evolved beyond their control and became almost a living creature. It utilised the appearance of the Fourth Doctor, to the extent of having an effigy in the Doctor's image carved out on a cliff-face. Its split personality was reflected in it dividing the expedition into two tribes of technicians (who became the Tesh) and the survey team (the Sevateem), justifying its madness by thinking it was part of an experiment to create a superhuman race, with the Tesh providing mental powers and the Sevateem with their strength and independence. Enslaving the tribes, it earned the name of &quot;The Evil One&quot;.

When the Doctor returned to the maddened world and saw the fruits of his mistakes, Xoanon tried to destroy itself and the entire planet rather than be defeated by the Doctor. However, the Doctor managed to remove his personality print from the core, restoring the computer intelligence to sanity and becoming a benign entity to the two tribes. &quot;You have to trust someone eventually,&quot; the Doctor says.

==Y==
===Professor Yana===
{{Main|Master (Doctor Who)|l1=Master}}

==Z==
===Professor Zaroff===
'''Professor Zaroff''' was a [[mad scientist]] who planned to destroy the world in the 1967 [[Second Doctor]] story ''[[The Underwater Menace]]''. Some of his scientific inventions included food made from [[plankton]], and the ability to graft [[gill]]s to humans to enable them to breathe underwater.

As part of his diabolical plans, he allied himself with the leaders of [[Atlantis]] telling them he would raise their city back to the surface or lower the ocean level by draining the water through a fissure in the Earth's [[crust (geology)|crust]].

The Doctor immediately realised that this would create super heated steam that could destroy the Earth. Zaroff was defeated when the Doctor and his companions sabotaged the generator he was using to pump the water. Zaroff was left to drown when his laboratory filled with water after the sea walls protecting it collapsed.

He is fondly recalled by ''Doctor Who'' fans as one of the most over-the-top, hammy villains in the entire history of the show. Particularly well remembered is his cry of &quot;Nothing in the world can stop me now!&quot;, which (due to actor [[Joseph Furst]]'s German accent) was pronounced as &quot;Nuzzing in Ze vurld can ztop me now!&quot; By chance, only one episode from this story survives, and the surviving part includes that infamous line.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last = Howarth
 | first = Chris
 | authorlink = Chris Howarth
 | coauthors = Steve Lyons
 | title = The Completely Useless Encyclopedia
 | publisher=Virgin Publishing
 | year = 1996
 | pages =
 | url =
 | doi =
 | id =
 | isbn = 0 426 20485 9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Zodin (the Terrible)===
The Doctor encountered (and reminisced about) the Terrible Zodin on a number of occasions. He first met her some time prior to his second incarnation. [[Iris Wildthyme]] also claimed to have met her.

Zodin was involved in an adventure which caused the Doctor to interact with multiple incarnations of himself. Following this she erased their memories of the incident using &quot;mind rubbers&quot;, preventing the later Doctors involved from remembering having experienced the events before [[Cold Fusion (Doctor Who)|Cold Fusion]].

This did not prevent the Doctor from remembering enough of the adventure to frequently bore people to sleep with a long-winded account of it, although he was incapable of consistently recalling whether she was assisted in her schemes by mutant [[kangaroos]] or by giant [[grasshopper]]s ([[Legacy (Doctor Who)|Legacy]]).

Jamie ([[The Colony of Lies]]) and Mel ([[Millennial Rites]]) both experienced the incident. The Brigadier was not involved. (The Doctor implied that their first meeting might happen in the Brigadier's personal future.) ([[The Five Doctors]]), however may have assisted Iris Wildthyme against Zodin in a separate adventure on the planet [[Mars]].

==See also==
* [[List of Doctor Who supporting characters]]
* [[List of Doctor Who henchmen]]
* [[List of Doctor Who monsters and aliens]]
* [[List of Doctor Who robots]]
* [[List of Doctor Who historical characters]]
* [[List of Torchwood minor characters]]
* [[List of Torchwood monsters and aliens]]
* [[List of The Sarah Jane Adventures minor characters]]
* [[List of The Sarah Jane Adventures monsters and aliens]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.btinternet.com/~jp1885/who/index.html The Bumper Book of Doctor Who Monsters, Villains &amp; Alien Species]

{{Doctor Who villains}}
{{doctor-who}}
{{Rogues Gallery}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Doctor Who Villains}}
[[Category:Lists of Doctor Who characters|Villains]]
[[Category:Extraterrestrial supervillains|Doctor Who]]
[[Category:Lists of fictional villains|Doctor Who villains]]

[[fr:Ennemis du Docteur (Doctor Who)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
