<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2209649" ns="0" title="Molloy College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced||date=May 2007}}
{{Infobox_University
|name            = Molloy College
|image           = 
|motto           = Veritas
|established     = 1955
|type            = Private, Catholic college
|endowment       = 
|faculty         = 
|full-time employees = 
|alumni          =
|president       = Drew Bogner, Ph.D.
|vice_president  = 
|principal       = 
|rector          =
|chancellor      =
|vice_chancellor = 
|dean            =
|head_label      =
|head            =
|students        = 4,400+
|doctoral        =
|profess         =
|city            =[[Rockville Centre, NY|Rockville Centre]]
|state           =[[New York]]
|country         =[[United States|USA]]
|campus          = 
|colours         = 
|nickname        = 
|mascot          = The Lion
|affiliations    = 
|footnotes       =
|website         = [http://www.molloy.edu/ www.molloy.edu]
|address         = 1000 Hempstead Ave., Rockville Centre, NY 11571-5002
|telephone       = 1-888-4-MOLLOY 
|coor            =
|logo            = 
}}

'''Molloy College''' is located in Rockville Centre, [[New York]], a [[Nassau County, New York|Nassau County]] community on [[Long Island]], in the [[United States]]. with a brand new, state-of-the art residential facility.  It also has a new 550 seat performing arts facility-- The Madison Theatre. The College was founded by the [[Dominican Sisters]] of the Congregation of the Holy Cross in 1955. 

A private Long Island college, Molloy provides a value-centered, multidimensional liberal arts education with more than 50 quality academic programs grounded in the Catholic faith, ideals of truth, and respect for the dignity and worth of every individual. Molloy's faculty is accomplished, yet approachable, leading small classes where students are encouraged to think critically and explore creatively. Combining the strengths of academic excellence and leadership with personal, compassionate mentoring, the College brings out the best in every student - while delivering the best value for their tuition dollar.

Nationally ranked, yet conveniently located, Molloy is one of the most affordable private colleges on Long Island. Many consider  Molloy &quot;an optimally-sized school&quot;: at approximately 4,400 undergraduate and graduate students, Molloy is large enough to offer students an academically-challenging, quality educational experience yet small enough to provide the personal attention that enhances every student's intellectual, ethical, spiritual and social development.

Molloy has a recently-expanded International Education Program, over 40 clubs and honor societies, ample service opportunities and NCAA Division II sports teams, students at Molloy have abundant opportunities to explore new interests, pursue athletics and enrich our community, here . . . and around the globe.

Molloy offers undergraduate and graduate programs in numerous areas. The College is proud to raise the standard for learning on Long Island. Steeped in a 50-year-tradition of quality education, it offers more than 50 academic programs. The wealth of opportunities the school presents you with will take you from your Associates degree to graduate studies. Allied health services, biology and computer science address the scientist in you. Criminal justice, social work and psychology give you a foundation on which you can make a difference in society. A degree in education, music or communication arts will develop your artistic, creative side. No matter which program you choose - be assured - it will launch you to a rewarding career.
 
Graduate students can study in the areas of business, education, nursing (includes a doctoral program), music therapy, speech-language  pathology or social work.  The social work graduate program is a joint venture with [[Fordham University]].  Molloy also offers a selection of continuing education courses each semester.

Its athletic teams compete as the Molloy Lions.  Sports include baseball, basketball, cross country, lacrosse, and soccer for men; basketball, cross country, dance team, lacrosse, soccer, softball, tennis, and volleyball for women, as well as an equestrian team for both men and women.  In 2010, the Molloy College outdoor track team was established.  

In addition to athletics, there are a number of clubs and organizations for Molloy College students. Including both Women's and Mens Rugby clubs.  

Molloy College has been ranked among the Best Regional Universities (Masters) in the U.S. News and World Report - America's Best Colleges rankings. The College also earned similar recognition from The Princeton Review. Both The Princeton Review and U.S. News and World Report provide annual rankings and reviews of colleges, based on a variety of criteria.

The Sustainability Institute at Molloy College focuses on its critical sustainability and &quot;green living&quot; challenges. Long Island's first-ever venture combining sustainability education and polic analysis within an academic institution, the Institute works to educate, foster meaningful debate and drive viable solutions to help ensure a sustainable future.

Molloy's Energeia Partnership brings together a diverse group of ethical leaders from this area's public, private and not-for-profit sectors to help address Long Island's most complex issues - education, institutional racism, poverty and the working poor, land use, energy, transportation, healthcare and media/social networking.




==Undergraduate Fields of Study==
*Division of Business
**Accounting B.S.
**Business Management B.S.
**Finance B.S.
*Division of Education
*Division of Humanities
*Division of Natural Sciences
*Division of Mathematics and Computer Science
*Division of Speech Language Pathology and Allied Health Sciences
*Division of Nursing 
*Division of Social Sciences

==Graduate Fields of Study==
*Division of Business
**Accounting M.B.A.
**Management M.B.A.
**Finance M.B.A.
**Personal Financial Planning M.B.A.
*Division of Education
*Division of Humanities
*Division of Nursing
*Division of Social Sciences
*Division of Speech Language Pathology


==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.molloy.edu  Molloy College webpage]

{{Dominican College and Universities}}

{{coord missing|New York}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in New York]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges on Long Island]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1955]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Dominican universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Nassau County, New York]]

{{NewYork-university-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
