<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2210615" ns="0" title="Gardner–Webb University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | POV=December 2009
 | refimprove=September 2010
 | cleanup=December 2009}}
{{Cleanup-university|date=April 2008}}
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Dcc2.jpg|right]] --&gt;
{{Infobox university
|name           = Gardner-Webb University
|image          = [[Image:gwwordmark.JPG|150px|Logo]]
|motto          = ''Pro Deo et Humanitate''
|mottoeng       = For God and Humanity
|established    = 1905
|endowment      = $39,985,841
|campus         = [[College town]]
|type           = Private/Liberal Arts
|president      = Dr. Frank Bonner
|city           = [[Boiling Springs, North Carolina|Boiling Springs]]
|state          = [[North Carolina]]
|country        = USA
|enrollment     = Approximately 4,300
|mascot         = Runnin’ Bulldogs
|colors         = Scarlet and Black&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#9C0606}}&amp;nbsp;{{color box|#000000}}
|athletics      = NCAA Division I &lt;br /&gt;Big South Conference
|affiliation    = Baptist State Convention of N.C.
|website        = [http://www.gardner-webb.edu www.gardner-webb.edu]
|}}

'''Gardner–Webb University''' is a private [[university]] located {{convert|40|mi|km}} west of Charlotte in [[Boiling Springs, North Carolina]], USA. The school has a total of 14 academic departments offering 45 major fields of study. Among the most popular of the school's 39 undergraduate majors are those in [[business]] (33%), [[education]] (29%), and the [[social science]]s (15%).  The main campus is situated on nearly {{convert|200|acre|km2}}, and there are an additional 16 satellite campuses located throughout North Carolina.  Associate's, bachelor's, master's and doctorate programs are offered through the university.

== Academics and accreditation ==

Gardner-Webb is a liberal arts college that focuses on teaching its students how to think logically about a wide range of subjects and how to communicate their ideas confidently and without confusion. Gardner-Webb has 16 departments and schools including the Godbold School of Business, Communication Studies Department, The School of Education, English Department, Music and Fine Arts Department, Mathematics Department, Natural Sciences Department, The School of Nursing, The School of Psychology, Physical Education-Wellness and Sports Studies Department, Religious Studies Department, Social Sciences Department, World Languages Department and the School of Divinity. Within these departments and schools the university offers 60 majors and 45 minors.

&lt;div style=&quot;float:right&quot;&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: smaller; margin-left: 1em;&quot;
|+'''Degrees Offered'''
|-
! rowspan=&quot;1&quot; | Department/Program
! rowspan=&quot;1&quot; | Degrees include&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
| The Broyhill School&lt;br /&gt;of Management
|
* Accounting
* Business Administration
* Computer Information&lt;br /&gt;Systems
* Economics/Finance
* Marketing
|-
| Department of Communication&lt;br /&gt;Studies
|
* Communication Studies
* Journalism
* Theater Arts
|-
| School of Education
|
* Elementary Education
* Middle Grades Education
|-
| Department of English&lt;br /&gt;Language and Literature
|
* English
* English with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure
|-
| Department of Fine Arts
|
* Art
* Fine Art
* Music
* Composition
* Elective Studies in&lt;br /&gt;Music Business
* Music Education
* Performance
* Sacred Music
|-
| Department of Mathematical&lt;br /&gt;Sciences
|
* Mathematics
* Mathematics with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure
|-
| Department of Natural&lt;br /&gt;Sciences
|
* Biology
* Chemistry
* Environmental Sciences
|-
| School of Nursing
|
* Associate Degree in Nursing (ASN)
* Bachelor of Science in Nursing (BSN)
* Master of Science in Nursing (MSN)
* Doctor of Nursing Practice (DNP)
|-
| Department of Physical&lt;br /&gt;Education, Wellness, and&lt;br /&gt;Sports Studies
|
* Athletic Training
* Health/Wellness
* Physical Education with&lt;br /&gt;Teacher Licensure
* Sport Management
|-
| School of Psychology&lt;br /&gt;and Counseling
|
* Psychology
|-
| Department of Religious&lt;br /&gt;Studies and Philosophy
|
* Biblical Languages and&lt;br /&gt;Literature
* Education Studies
* Mission Studies
* Religion
* Religious Thought and&lt;br /&gt;Philosophy
|-
| Department of Social&lt;br /&gt;Sciences
|
* History
* History with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure (Secondary)
* Political Science
* Social Sciences
* Social Sciences with&lt;br /&gt;Teacher Licensure&lt;br /&gt;(Secondary)
* Sociology
|-
| Department of World&lt;br /&gt;Languages, Literatures,&lt;br /&gt;and Cultures
|
* American Sign Language&lt;br /&gt;(ASL)
* English as a Second&lt;br /&gt;Language with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure
* French
* French with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure
* Spanish
* Spanish with Teacher&lt;br /&gt;Licensure
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
* &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gardner-webb.edu/academics/departments/index.html University departments]&lt;/ref&gt;
* &lt;ref&gt;(2007-2008) Undergraduate Catalog, 103-244.&lt;/ref&gt;
* This list does not contain Minors offered at Gardner-Webb&lt;br /&gt;University.
|}
&lt;/div&gt;

Gardner–Webb University is accredited by the [[Commission on Colleges of the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]] to award Associate, Baccalaureate, Master’s degrees and Doctorates.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Commission on Colleges: Member, Candidate, and Applicant List.&quot; Commission on Colleges Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. 9 Feb 2010. Web. [http://www.sacscoc.org/pdf/webmemlist.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition several departmental programs are accredited by the appropriate state or national agencies. The Education program is accredited by the [[North Carolina Department of Public Instruction]] and the [[National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education]] (NCATE). The Music and Nursing programs are accredited respectively by the [[National Association of Schools of Music]] and the [[National League for Nursing Accrediting Commission]]. The School of Divinity is accredited by the Association of Theological Schools of the United States and Canada. The Athletic Training Program is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Allied Health Education Programs (CAAHEP). The School of Business is accredited by the Association of Collegiate Business Schools and Programs (ACBSP). The University is authorized by the immigration authorities of the United States for the training of foreign students.

=== Guest-speaker series ===
Dimensions is the University's weekly guest-speaker series; Dimensions counts as a 1/2 credit course per semester. Full-time students are required to attend a minimum of ten sessions of Dimensions for six semesters. Part-time students are required to earn the 1/2 credit for Dimensions for every fifteen hours in which they are enrolled at the University until a minimum of three semesters worth of Dimensions credits have been earned. Failure to attend all ten sessions with result with no credit. During Dimensions time there are no classes that take session.

=== Special academic programs ===

Gardner-Webb offers several special academic programs; some of these include the NOEL program, the Program for the blind and visually impaired, deaf and hard of hearing, learning assistance, GOAL program, high school seniors, Honors program, ROTC, YMCA, and the study abroad programs.

The '''NOEL Program''' aids students with physical or mental disabilities. Students in the NOEL program are assigned to a disability specialist who works with the students while they attend Gardner-Webb.  These students are assisted through note takers, interpreters, lab assistants and tutors.  They are allowed extended testing time, and technology adapted to their disability. Their disability specialist helps them to achieve good study skills and helpful test-taking strategies.

The '''Program for the visually impaired''' gives orientation and mobility training to students to make the transition to Gardner-Webb.  The audiovisual department, located in the campus library, provides technology and special equipment for all students.

The '''Program for the deaf and hard of hearing''' provided qualified interpreters for classes, campus activities and theatrical productions.  Dorm buildings are equipped with specialized fire alarms and doorbell mechanism.  Video phones are available for deaf students or students with deaf relatives.

The '''Learning assistance programs''' are available to students who need help to make the transition to college-level work.  They may receive help through tutoring or other materials that help fit the student’s needs.  The program offers interdictory level classes in reading, writing, and mathematics.

The '''GOAL''' (greater opportunity for adult learners) program offers majors for adult students who wish to continue their baccalaureate degree.

The '''High school seniors program''' is for upcoming high school students interested in completing their senior year while attending college classes and earning college credits.  This program requires parental consent.

The '''Honors program''' is for academically gifted students.  The program provides challenging opportunities for students.

The '''Army ROTC''' program offers courses in military science and leadership opportunities. There is no charge for participating in this program.

The '''YMCA''' professional studies program is a culmination of the Cleveland County YMCA and the Gardner-Webb Student YMCA.  The program helps undergraduate students get ready for non-profit careers.

The '''Study abroad program''' highly advocates for undergraduates to explore new educational experiences in other countries. Gardner-Webb participates with schools in [[Costa Rica]], England, Switzerland, Sweden, South Korea, France, Spain, Hong Kong, [[Malta]] and Germany.

== Student life ==

Gardner–Webb University is home to many school-wide events.  At the beginning of the school year, returning students come back a week early and act as big brothers and big sisters for the upcoming freshmen.  During orientation week, students gather in their orientation groups and complete activities together.  Later, these orientation groups become the freshmen student's University 111 class, a class intended to introduce students to the University and how it works.

Homecoming is a time of celebration at GWU. Central to Homecoming Weekend is the parade down Main Street in Boiling Springs. The weekend is full of special meals for alumni and students.  One of the most popular traditions at Gardner-Webb is centered around the Friday night before the big Homecoming game. Students virtually &quot;destroy&quot; campus with rolls of toilet paper.  The activity that is now condoned by administration is a major part of Gardner-Webb tradition. Although some students believe that it is a waste of time and toilet paper, most enjoy and partake in this tried-and-true Homecoming event.  Others question the logic of toilet papering one's own campus.

Other popular activities include the spring formal, occasional movies on the quad (the grassy area in the center of campus), Earth Day activities, ski trips, Midterm Munchies, Beep Ball Baseball, Open-Mic Night at the coffee shop, participation in discount nights at Chick-fil-a, IHOP, Pizza Hut and Octoberfest (an event where the community and college students come together as an alternative for trick-or-treating).

=== Housing ===
The majority of full-time students at Gardner-Webb live in either the traditional residence halls or on-campus apartments. Costs for living on campus vary, depending on what a student choses: residence hall living, single-room residence hall living, suite living, or apartment living. Single accommodations for residence halls and group apartment living are subject to request of the Gardner-Webb Housing and Residence Education department based on room availability. Traditional residence hall living for the school year of 2009-2010 is $1,745 per student per semester.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Undergraduate 2009-2010 Tuition and Fees.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb 2010. [http://www.gardner-webb.edu/admissions/tuition-fees/undergraduate.html]&lt;/ref&gt; An additional $695 is for a single-occupancy room. Suite-style rooms and apartments are $2,260 and $2,780, respectively for the 2009-2010 school year per semester.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Undergraduate 2009-2010 Tuition and Fees.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb 2010.[http://www.gardner-webb.edu/admissions/tuition-fees/undergraduate.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Decker''' is a female-only residence hall. This building's construction was completed in 1949 and originally was slated to be for men.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Residence Halls: Decker Hall.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb 2010. [http://gardner-webb.edu/student-life/services/residence-education/Residence-Halls/decker/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Dover Memorial Library is across the small Decker parking lot in addition to the Suttle Wellness Center. Decker is rumored to be haunted by the ghost of a girl who committed suicide in 1955 and was the subject of the 2006 film, ''The Legacy: A Ghost Story'', which  won the Gold Award at the 2006 Aurora Film and Video Festival.

Decker Hall is a multilevel building, containing a ground floor, first, second and third &quot;loft-style&quot; floor. Located on the central &quot;Quad&quot; area, Decker Hall has single, double, and triple rooms. All floors in this building are equipped with community-style bathrooms.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Residence Halls: Decker Hall.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb 2010. [http://gardner-webb.edu/student-life/services/residence-education/Residence-Halls/decker/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Triple rooms are only available in the large loft attic in Decker.

'''H.A.P.Y.''', an acronym for the building's founders, '''H'''oey, '''A'''nthony, '''P'''adgett, and '''Y'''oung, was built in 1946. H.A.P.Y is located in the central location of campus. H.A.P.Y is the only residence hall that is coed. However, Males and females are opposite wings Divided by the lobby. The main building sports suite-style bathrooms (where four students share one bathroom), while the wing has one community bathroom.  H.A.P.Y. is a recently renovated building with nice carpet and furniture.

'''Honors House''' is a newer addition to the residence halls on Gardner-Webb's Campus.  The old white home served as overflow housing at one time but now houses students in single and double rooms with private and suite-style bathrooms.  It is farther from the campus and is the only coed residence hall. The house is split in two parts by sex.  The two sides are connected by a main lobby, kitchen, and laundry room.  Honors House was originally set up as a residence hall for honors students.

'''Royster''', formally a hospital in Boiling Springs, is a men's residence hall located across College Avenue and off the main campus.  The building is one story with a main hall and several wings.  Young men enjoy community style and private baths along with large rooms and high ceilings. As a former hospital, Royster has the singular distinction of being the only residence hall with an unused morgue in its basement.

'''Stroup''' (pronounced &quot;strap&quot;) is another residence hall for the female students. The building has community baths and in each room there are sinks. The building is in line for some well-needed renovations.

'''Mauney Hall''' is one of the largest places for on-campus students to live. Mauney has four floors with two-person rooms and a communal bathroom shared by the floor. Mauney residents may use the three washing and drying machines and snack and drink machines. The students who occupy Mauney Hall enjoy community style living that involves meeting your hall mates and learning the campus together. Flag Football at Garnder-Webb University offers a time for residence hall competitions which largely involve Mauney and Lutz-Yelton Halls. Mauney is one of the most-sought places to live on campus, third to the University Apartments and to Lutz-Yelton.

'''Myers-Spangler''' halls are mostly female residence halls with the exception of the first floor of Myers, which houses some of the overflow males. At the beginning of the 2009-2010 school year, Myers and Spangler will return to being all-female residence halls.  They are located further off the main quad area connected by an outdoor corridor.  The buildings have community style baths. Myers and Spangler were newly renovated this summer{{When|date=February 2011}} before the incoming freshman arrived.

'''Nanney''' is a two-story women's residence hall. (Over the last few years it has housed young men but was converted back to a women's residence hall in August 2008.)  The building has carpet and long rooms with built-in closets.  Bathtubs can still be found in the residence hall's bathrooms.

'''University Commons''' are student apartments and are considered on-campus housing.  There are seven complexes located off of the main quad area across from Lake Hollifield. They have four bedrooms, two bath units, a kitchen, living room, and free laundry.

=== Clubs ===
Gardner-Webb is home to numerous clubs, organizations, and honors societies.  One of the largest clubs is Campus Ministries United (CMU), which is composed of a large group of students who strive to learn more about God and help others through various Christ-centered programs such as prison fellowship, which is where a group of students go out to a local prison and spread the gospel to prisoners.  Focus is another club supported by campus ministries.  Students are placed with two leaders, usually placed on a team of ten or twelve.  Each team meets weekly and prays about their week or struggles they might be having and reads scripture.  The main purpose of Focus is for each team to go out at least once a semester to a church and lead a weekend or a particular service.  Games, food, praise and worship music, skits, and scripture passages and teachings are crucial to Focus.  Focus builds friendships among team members.

Alpha Chi is a special invitation academic organization that promotes and recognizes scholarship and elements of character which make scholarship effective.  Another popular club is The Dawg Pound — the students involved go to sporting events, sit in the student section, sport red and black club T-shirts and painted faces to support their Runnin' Bulldogs. It was founded in 2001 by Lutz-Yelton residents Matt Hudler and Nic Watson.

Other clubs include the Honors Student Association (HSA), which is another special invitation academic club that encourages an atmosphere of challenged learning through advanced classes, special trips, and special academic opportunities. Student Admissions Association (SAA) is a group of Gardner-Webb students wholove Gardner-Webb and are handpicked by their admissions counselors to share that love with prospective students through tours, Dawg Days, and overnight visits. Student YMCA (GWSY) is a branch of the Cleveland County YMCA that offers programs to help the Cleveland County and the Gardner-Webb community. Web Spinners is a theater club that promotes interest in theatrical productions, specifically those at Gardner-Webb. They also try to foster personal development in the various components of stage performance and theatre.

Deaf Club is a club for [[deaf]] students, the American Sign Language (ASL) majors, and other students interested in ASL or the deaf culture. Joyful Hands is a performing group that promotes understanding of [[sign language]] and the deaf culture. The group signs songs for the deaf and hearing communities. Residence Hall Association (RHA) provides activities or services necessary to promote the welfare and interest of all the residential students.

The Student Nurses Association provides connections to the outside world of nursing for future nurses. Its purpose is to 'aid in the development of professional nurses, provide educational programs of interest to students, and encourage involvement in nursing organizations.' This is a program only offered to those students who are pursuing a career in the nursing or possibly health care field. Along with being a part of the Student Nurses Association, one could be part of the National Student Nurses Association (NSNA). Gardner-Webb provides the students involved in SNA the opportunity to be involved at the national level.

All clubs are chartered by the Gardner–Webb University Student Government Association (SGA). The purpose of the SGA is to represent the rights and opinions of the undergraduate student body in a manner consistent with its mission and constitution.  SGA also works to promote positive relationships among the students, the faculty, and the administration.

=== The Verge ===
The Verge is a contemporary worship service, held in Dover Theatre, on every Tuesday night. It is one of the most popular extracurricular activities on Gardner-Webb's campus. The Verge features  musical groups that perform throughout the service. A special prayer time begins 45 minutes before each service; students pray for other students, the Verge service, the school, and the community. It is supported by Campus Ministries and run mainly by students.

== Athletics ==
{{Cleanup-rewrite|2=section|date=November 2009}}
{{Main|Gardner–Webb Runnin' Bulldogs}}
[[Image:GardnerWebbRunninBulldogs.png|thumb|left|GWU's athletic logo featuring 'Max the Bulldog']]
Gardner-Webb offers seventeen varsity sports at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] level. In football, the Runnin' Bulldogs compete in the [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|football championship subdivision (FCS)]]. The 2008-2009 academic year will see the Runnin' Bulldogs transition to the [[Big South Conference]] for all sports. The football team joined the Big South as an associate member in 2002. Since joining the Big South, the football team has had a record of 38-28. The first two years that they joined the Big South Gardner Webb won two conference titles in a row. Since then they have placed third every year. The Gardner Webb football team has played some difficult opponents including Georgia Tech, Appalachian State, Mississippi State, Wofford, and Ohio.The Gardner Webb football team has produced many All-Americans and athletes that have made it to the NFL the most recent was Brian Johnston, drafted by the Kansas City Chiefs in the 7th round.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=54093&amp;SPID=5748&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;ATCLID=723255&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=542438&amp;SPID=4160&amp;SPSID=46170&lt;/ref&gt;

Gardner-webb mens basketball has also been a growing program. Competing with the likes of #2 seeded Oklahoma, Virginia Tech and Kansas state this past 2008-2009 season. While in the 2007-2008 season pulling an upset win against The university of Kentucky. Behind Head coach Rick Scruggs the running bulldogs mens basketball team have posted a record of (356-295) over the last 14 seasons. They have reached every national tournament on every level except for the NCAA Division I Men’s National Tournament.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=46210&amp;SPID=4168&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;ATCLID=530262&amp;Q_SEASON=2008&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Gardner–Webb University's recently created men's swimming team (a group of 16 freshmen and 2 sophomores) placed third at the 2008 CCSA conference, setting several school records and finishing closely behind College of Charleston and Davidson.  The women also placed third at the conference championships.
Before joining the CCSA conference the women’s team was a part of the NEC.  As of 2007, the women’s team was four time NEC conference champions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=46236&amp;SPID=4172&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;ATCLID=801631&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to winning conference titles, both the men and women’s swim teams are academic all-stars.  The men and women’s team combined grade point average for the fall of 2008 gave them the highest GPA of the NCAA Division I schools that sponsor swimming programs.  The teams combined GPA was a 3.475.  The men’s team alone ranked first nationally with a 3.3 GPA, beating Georgetown University by 0.01.  The women’s team ranked second, just barely missing first by 0.02 to Marshall University.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?ATCLID=3663446&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&lt;/ref&gt;

In the fall of 2006, the Gardner-Webb soccer team won its conference and made it to the [[NCAA]] second round (a link to the roster of players that were involved in winning the 2006 [[Atlantic Sun Conference]] follows).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/SportSelect.dbml?SPSID=46183&amp;SPID=4164&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;Q_SEASON=2006&lt;/ref&gt;
The Women's soccer team is currently coached by Kevin Mounce and assisted by Sarah Currie. Coach Mounce has had four winning seasons in the past seven years. During his ten seasons coaching at Gardner-Webb, he holds the highest winning percentage (.514). In 2001 the Lady Bulldogs were the National Christian College Athletic Association Champions, following that tournament Mounce was named NCCAA National Women's Soccer Coach of the Year. In 2002, at the conclusion of their season, the team was ranked second in the nation for first-year division I programs by Soccer Buzz. In 2003 the Bulldogs had their first appearance in the Atlantic Sun Championship, finishing 5th in the league. For this accomplishment Kevin Mounce was named A-Sun coach of the year. In 2004 GWU had a forward, Leaana Woddorth who led the nation in scoring. She became A-Sun player of the year and broke many school records. In 2000 the Lady Bullogs became a Division I program participating in the Atlantic Sun Conference. In 2008 the team transferred to the Big South Conference. In their first year competing in the Big South they finished 4-12-2.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=46226&amp;SPID=4170&amp;DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;ATCLID=543366&amp;Q_SEASON=2008&lt;/ref&gt;

The Gardner-Webb Bulldog cheer-leading team has been around for many years. As of today,{{When|date=June 2011}} the cheerleading team has a coach by the name of Andrew Day. He has been coaching for a little over a few years at Gardner-Webb but is also an alumnus and alumni cheerleader of Gardner–Webb University. When Coach Drew first cheered here, chairs were the stunts to do. Now, toss ball up cupie, and heel stretch full down and many more have become standard. The history of the cheerleading program has changed so much in the past 11 years. It went from not being competitive at all, to being one of the forefront teams in college cheerleading. The past 11 years they have been competing with NCA. They started in Division II and now have changed to Small Co-ed (4 guys or less). That means they compete against any Division I, II, or III teams. Our school officially became a Division IAA in 2002. In their first appearance in the Small Coed Division they placed 5th in the Nation and 1st in the Southeast. The team is fortunate to have a lot of returns to place hopefully even higher this year.{{When|date=June 2011}} The talent here has continued to get stronger and stronger. We{{Who|date=June 2011}} are building a tradition of having great cheerleading.

Gardner-Webb sports requires dedication from not only the athletes and coaches, but also a committed strength staff. The athletics facilities for weight lifting and strength training are used on a daily basis to maximize athletes performance and to prevent injuries. The Gardner-Webb strength staff currently trains approximately 400 student-athletes. Teams are required to attend mandatory lifts and speed training while participating in a sport. The weight-training facilities are located in the GWU Football Center next to Spangler Stadium ([http://www.gardner-webb.edu/admissions/campusmap/index.html Campus map]). &quot;In order to keep the athlete from adapting to the same training stimulus, causing a plateau effect, the program is changed every 4-6 weeks&quot; ([http://www.gwusports.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=10300&amp;ATCLID=1148123 Bulldog Strength]). The importance of strength training to [prevent injuries]is also a major part for a strength training staff. This includes instructing athletes on how to properly perform correct lifting techniques, prevention methods: such as stretching, warming up correctly and altering programs for athletes who are recovering from an injury to ensure proper rehabilitation and a speedy recovery.&lt;ref&gt;Sibley, Tracy. Personal Interview. 15 Apr. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Basketball scandal ===
The Gardner-Webb community was rocked by scandal in the fall of 2002 when ordained minister and Gardner-Webb president of 16 years, Dr. Christopher White', admitted to writing a memo two years before ordering a star basketball player's grade-point average to be calculated without the &quot;F&quot; he received for cheating in his religion class; thereby allowing the athlete to play.  Without the change, Carlos Webb would have been ineligible in 2000–01, the season Gardner-Webb won the National Christian College Athletic Association championship. Carlos Webb was also named most valuable player that day. Two years later Gardner-Webb became NCAA Division I school. Under the university's honor code, a &quot;cheating F&quot; can never be removed from a student's transcript because it is a direct violation of the Gardner-Webb honor code. By removing the &quot;F&quot;, some{{Who|date=June 2011}} believed president White destroyed the power of the honor code and the integrity of Gardner–Webb University.

After eight days of students protesting, the school's trustees affirmed Christopher White's presidency after a 10-hour meeting on September 27, 2002 though they demoted a pair of administrators, one the vice president of academic affairs and the other his assistant, who had criticized White's actions.  Initially three faculty members also resigned as a result of the scandal.  In the end, eight faculty members and administrators (later called &quot;The Group of 8&quot;) suffered professional hardship due to demotion, resignation, or firing. The group of eight which led the faculty revolt against White included Blackburn, Williams, and Price.

Opponents said White's action and the trustees' failure to punish him violates the spirit of Gardner-Webb's honor code, while the president's backers, including the chairman of the board of trustees, said they were convinced White did not violate the letter of any school rules and that he acted in a spirit of fairness toward Carlos Webb, who had been incorrectly advised he could get the &quot;F&quot; removed from his GPA by retaking the class.  Trustees chairman Thomas Hardin said his board concluded that, while White's action was wrong, the president should not have been removed for a mistake made two years before. He said the demoted administrators were punished not for speaking out, but because in doing so they violated a student's right to privacy.

White states in ''The New York Times'' about why he made the decision to change Carlos Webb's grade. White said &quot;In trying to make a decision, there are two guiding principles: One is the university's word. When we tell a student this is what he needs to do, we need to stand by that. The Second thing is, I'm very concerned with student rights. They are our customers. They are our clients. We don't exist for ourselves. We exist for them. They deserve to be treated fairly.&quot; Webb was incorrectly advised that if he took the course again and passed it, his F would be replaced.

For nearly two weeks students picketed on the corner of College Avenue and Main Street with signs calling for the president's resignation and questioning his integrity.  Students were seen with copies of the Honor Code in their black frames taken from classrooms and the glass front busted and black tape over the poster.  The scandal tore the Gardner-Webb community apart.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In early October 2002, Dr. Christopher White resigned as Gardner–Webb University’s president and the grade remained on the student athlete’s transcript.  Gardner-Webb was put on NCAA probation for a five-year period that ended in early 2007.

== University Police ==
Gardner–Webb University has a police force on campus at all times. University Police makes hourly rounds of the campus. Parking is mandated by the University Police in addition to an array of other services provided to Gardner–Webb University. Services include assisting with common car problems such as flat tires, dead batteries, and car-entry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gardner-webb.edu/student-life/services/up/index.html &quot;University Police.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb. 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bulldog Escort program is also provided by University Police. The service is available from dusk to dawn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gardner-webb.edu/student-life/services/up/escort/index.html &quot;Bull Dog Escort Program.&quot; Gardner-Webb University. Web. 9 Feb 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; Should a student feel uncomfortable walking across campus, for any reason, the student can utilize this program to have a police officer from University Police escort them back to their dorm or car.

== Renovations and expansion ==
Every summer Gardner-Webb strives to make the campus and its facilities better for its students. Recent renovations include carpet and furniture in Lutz-Yelton and Mauney halls, suite style bathrooms in H.A.P.Y., and improvements to apartment complexes.

One major renovation occurred over the 2006-2007 Christmas break in which Gardner-Webb completely renovated the cafeteria, called &quot;The Caf&quot;, by students. The room is now home to a food court type serving area, numerous plasma screen televisions around the lower level seating area, and private TVs for each table in the upper level seating area.  During the summer of 2007 Gardner-Webb renovated the snack bar area in the downstairs of the Dover Campus Center. The new area looks like a sports bar and coffee shop restaurant. It is a place where students can use their meal plan or cash to purchase prepared foods and snack foods.  The new area was given the name &quot;The Kennel&quot; in reference to the Bulldog mascot.  The Kennel has television sets like the ones that are found in the &quot;Caf.&quot; In the summer of 2010 the &quot;Kennel&quot; was closed and renovations began to turn it into a Chick-fila express. Finally in the fall of 2010 the restaurant opened and now serves some Chick-fila items such as the classic chicken sandwich.

The fall of 2007 will boast the revealing of Gardner-Webb’s biggest capital campaign and expansion plan in history. The new plan is three phases and includes the building of a new Student Center (that will include a movie theater, food court, recreation area, prayer room, ballroom, and offices for major student clubs and organizations), a new science and math facility, and a new fine and performing arts building. The capital campaign will need to raise an initial $16 million for the first phase that will include the building of the new Student Center.

In the spring of 2010, Gardner–Webb University was honored with its largest financial gift to date. The University was awarded $5 million by the Tucker Family to assist in funding the construction of the Tucker Student Center. The new student center is slated to be built on Garnder-Webb's main campus, on the Lake Hollifield complex. In the fall of 2010, the University will officially break ground for this new facility.

== Rankings and ratings ==
Ranked, U.S. News America's best colleges, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2009 (Top Tier, Southern Region, Master's Level); Princeton review selectivity rating, 86 in 2006, 85 in 2007 (scores range from 60-99); Character-building college, Templeton foundation; Top 5, graduates with lightest debtload, 2006, 2007, U.S. News America's best colleges.
Recently Gardner-Webb was recognized as one of the top three Christian colleges in North Carolina by the Annual National College Survey.

== Historical timeline ==
1905-Chartered as Boiling Spring High School, a private boarding school established by the Kings Mountain and Sandy Run Baptist Associations.

1928-The institution was transformed into Boiling Spring Junior College.

1942-Renamed Gardner-Webb College, in honor of former governor of North Carolina [[O. Max Gardner]] (1929–33) and wife Fay Webb Gardner.

1947-[[O. Max Gardner]], appointed by Truman to be Ambassador to the United Kingdom, dies on the eve of his departure for England.

1971-Gardner-Webb receives full accreditation as a four-year school.

1970s-With talent-rich teams that included Artis Gilmore and John Drew, the Bulldogs ascend the junior-college rankings.  Their reputation for athletic ability and aggressive play earns them an adjective, as they become known as the ''Runnin''' Bulldogs, a nickname that has stuck.  (An apocryphal account.)

1980-Gardner-Webb offers its first Master of Arts Degree in education.

1992-The Gardner-Webb board of trustees votes to establish the Gardner-Webb School of Divinity.

1992-Gardner-Webb loses in the closing seconds of the NAIA Football National Championship Game to Central State Ohio. The GW team, led by Coach Woody Fish, features All-Americans and future professional players, including Gabe Wilkins.

1993-Gardner-Webb College becomes Gardner–Webb University.

1998-The Divinity school is renamed the Christopher White School of Divinity, in honor of the school's sitting president.

2000-Gardner-Webb Baseball Team advances to the NCAA College World Series.

2000-Gardner-Webb athletics moves to [[NCAA Division I]] status.

2002-President Christopher White is embroiled in a grade-changing scandal involving one of the school's basketball players.  The story makes national news and in the months that follow, White resigns as students, faculty, and alumni call for his removal. By 2004, the NCAA has placed Gardner-Webb on probation for &quot;lack of institutional control.&quot;  The probation expires in March 2007.

2004-Dr. Frank Campbell is named interim president of Gardner–Webb University.

2005-Gardner-Webb celebrates its 100-year anniversary as an educational institution.

2005-Dr. Frank Bonner (Ph.D., English, UNC Chapel Hill) is installed as Gardner-Webb's twelfth president.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aux.gardner-webb.edu/Facts/ Facts at official site]&lt;/ref&gt;

2006-The men's soccer team, led by long-time coach Tony Setzer, defeats Stetson in overtime to claim their first conference title in soccer as a Division I school. Gardner-Webb then defeats heavily-favored University of Alabama at Birmingham in the 1st round of the NCAA tournament. The season is brought to an end the following week as Gardner-Webb falls to the Clemson Tigers, 3-1.

2007-Gardner-Webb President Dr. Frank Bonner announces that as on August 6 the university will become North Carolina's first tobacco-free campus.

2007-Gardner-Webb athletics makes national news when the basketball team routs the University of Kentucky, 84-68, at Rupp Arena.

2010-Gardner-Webb opens the new John Henry Moss baseball stadium and Bill Masters field.

== Notable alumni ==
* Brook Collins: [[CEO]] Bizzy Bee Exterminators (President NPA 2007; National Pest Association), Atlanta Business Journal Man of the Year 2006. U.S News and World Report young business professional of the year 2006. Forbes 2007 list.
* [[W.J. Cash]]: Author of ''Mind of the South'' (1917-18 while Boiling Springs High School; Cash's sister Bertie attended 1928-30 as Junior College student)
* [[Ron Rash]]: Award-winning novelist and poet.
* [[Martha Mason (writer)|Martha Mason]], writer
* Joe DePriest: [[Journalist]] for the [[Charlotte Observer]].
* [[Artis Gilmore]]: [[American Basketball Association|ABA]] player, [[NBA]] [[All-Star]].
* Gilmer Blackburn: [[Provost (education)|Provost]] and [[Chancellor (education)|Vice-chancellor]], University of Virginia's College at Wise.
* Evans P. Whitaker, [[Ph.D.]], President of  [[Anderson University (South Carolina)|Anderson University]]
* Gerry Vaillancourt: [[Presenter|Broadcaster]], [[New Orleans Hornets]]
* [[John Drew (basketball)|John Drew]]: NBA player
* Woody Fish: College football coach
* [[Eddie Lee Wilkins]]: NBA player
* Jim Washburn: Defensive Line Coach of the Tennessee Titans [http://www.titansonline.com/team/coaches/staff.php?PRKey=7]
* Blake Lalli: Catcher [[Tennessee Smokies]] (Class AA affiliate of the [[Chicago Cubs]])
* Zach Ward: Pitcher [[New Britain Rock Cats]] (Class AA affiliate of the [[Minnesota Twins]])
* [[Jim Maxwell (American football)|Jim Maxwell]]: [[Linebacker]] in the [[NFL]] and [[Canadian Football League|CFL]]
* [[Gabe Wilkins]]: Former [[Defensive End]] [[Green Bay Packers, San Francisco 49ers]]
* [[Cara Saunders]]: Bahamas Olympic Track and Field Team member
* [[Dr. Linda Combs]]: [[Comptroller|Controller]] of the [[Office of Management and Budget]]
* Brian Johnston: Former [[Defensive End]] [[Kansas City Chiefs]], Currently picked up by the [[Miami Dolphins]] for the 2010-2011 Season.
* [[Orlando Early]]: Head men's basketball coach at the University of Louisiana at Monroe.
* [[Kelvin Wylie]]: Known as &quot;Hometown Kid&quot; on AND1 Mixtape Tour
* Dobson Collins: Wide Receiver with Philadelphia Eagles
* Tyler Kettering, MLS player, Chicago Fire
* Dennis Puckerin, Former member of the Trinidad &amp; Tobago National Men’s Soccer Team.
* [[Samantha Staton]]- Opera singer [Cincinnati Conservatory of Music, Master of Music] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.gardner-webb.edu/publications/press/2008/2008/october/opera-staton.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Johnny Hunt]], former president of the [[Southern Baptist Convention]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}
# {{cite web
|title = Gardner-Webb University Quick Facts web page
|url = http://www.gardner-webb.edu/about/quick_facts/index.html}}
# {{cite web
|title = Gardner-Webb University Police web page
|url = http://wwwebb.gardner-webb.edu/cp/}}
# {{cite web
|title = Gardner-Webb University History web page
|url = http://www.gardner-webb.edu/about/history/index.html}}
# {{cite web
|last = Washburn
|first = Jim
|title = Tennessee Titans Administration web page
|url = http://www.titansonline.com/team/coaches/staff.php?PRKey=7}}
# {{cite book
|title = Undergraduate Catalog
|location = Gardner-Webb University
|date = 2007-2008
|pages = 103–244}}
# Day, Andrew. &quot;About the Program.&quot; 17 Feb 2009 [http://gwucheer.g2gm.com/about.html].
# &quot;Clubs and Organizations.&quot; Student Life. Gardner–Webb University, 2008. Web. 17 Mar. 2009.
# French, Bethany. Personal interview. 3 Mar. 2009
# Olsen, Ted. &quot;Christianity Today&quot;,Oct.(web-only)2002. 17 Mar. 2009
# Bernstein, Viv. &quot;College Basketball; Christian Values Meet Athletic Scandal&quot;, 23, Oct. 2002 (Web) 20, March 2009.

== External links ==
{{Private colleges and universities in North Carolina}}
{{Big South Conference}}

{{Coord|35.2474562|-81.6706223|display=title}}

[[Category:Gardner–Webb University|*]]
[[Category:Education in Cleveland County, North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the Southern Baptist Convention|Gardner-Webb University]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the North Carolina Baptist Convention|Gardner-Webb]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1905]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Cleveland County, North Carolina]]

[[fr:Université Gardner–Webb]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
