<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22122598" ns="0" title="George Eid"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=February 2011}}

{{Infobox journalist
| name=          George Eid
| image= George Eid.jpg
| caption     =  November 2008
| order=         [[Journalist]]
| birth_place   =[[Beirut, Lebanon]]
| birth_name =   George Eid
| residence=     [[Mount Lebanon]]
| nationality =  [[Lebanese people|Lebanese]]{{Flag|Lebanon}}
| occupation    =[[News reporter, Anchor]]
| employer      =[[MTV,Lebanon]]
| birth_date    =June 25{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}.
| religion=      [[Maronite Christian]]
| spouse      =  Not Married
| notable_work=  Host of  Saadat Al Nakheb
| awards  =      Said Akl Award 2007
}}

'''George Eid''' ({{lang-ar|جورج عيد}}) (born June 25) is a [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] [[journalist]]–[[reporter]]-[[anchor]] who is known for his bold and liberal reports and articles. He is among the young journalists who appeared after the cedar revolution in Lebanon. At a young age he made a fast debut going through radio, television, e-media and written media in a period of seven years. Whereas he raised many controversial political and humanitarian issues.  He also served as a youth shadow Minister of Tourism and Industry (in Interim) in 2007–2008.

The 2nd Youth Shadow government after the bill was passed on December 12, 2005 by the Lebanese cabinet to establish and support such a structure, which was developed by the late MP and Editor in Chief of [[An-Nahar]] daily, [[Gebran Tueni]] who was assassinated during the Cedars revolution.

His reports and columns ranged between many Lebanese newspapers, most extensively [[An-Nahar]] and Al-Aamal between 2007-2009.

Prior to this Eid received the Said Akl award in 2007 for best poetic performance. He was also awarded the first prize from the international library of poets for his poem &quot;Life&quot;. 

In 2007 and after the July war, Eid participated in the UNDP conference (Malta) and helped to issue the overall report on the oil spill pollution in Lebanon whereas he had an active role in the treatment of many of the Lebanese shores from Jieh to Jbeil. 

He was also the Editor in Chief of the weekly magazine ''Al Raii el Aam'' (public opinion); in addition to that he occupied the seat of Political editor at the Webnewsagency iloubnan.info [http://www.iloubnan.info/tourism/article/id/27476/theme/118/lebanon/Tourism-in-Lebanon%E2%80%A6-and-Tripoli] in 2008. Eid also wrote for many magazines in Freelance such as ''Timeout-Beirut'', ''Naharashabab'' [http://www.Naharashabab.com], ''Elite'', El taswik el Arabi-Dubai, Haya-Dubai.

By the end of 2008, Lebanese Radio CEO Fouad Hamdan asked Eid to present a talk show on Radio Lebanon tackling the Lebanese elections in June 2009. Eid Proposed the name Saadat Al Nakheb [http://richlebanon.com/vote], which was swiftly approved and began airing on January 9, 2009. The show voiced out the youth's and independent politician's opinions. In a review by Annahar saadat al Nakheb was described as an &quot;innovative new show that is well in time and in need&quot;. The show aired till the end of June 2009, That is when he started the show &quot;Lana wa Lakum&quot; which tackled the daily issues of the society, the show ended by September 2009.

On April 7, 2009 Eid started his television career with the newly reborn Murr television, whereas he became a Reporter known for his special reports which covered a range variety of issues from social to political with an innovative style of reporting. 

On October 7, 2010, the MTV correspondent received threats [http://www.nowlebanon.com/NewsArchiveDetails.aspx?ID=207221] related to his reporting on the intriguing purchase of lands by [[Hezbollah]] in the eastern part of the Lebanese capital Beirut. A step which has been considered to cause demographic imbalance in the region [http://www.nowlebanon.com/NewsArticleDetails.aspx?ID=213948]. 

However despite the threats Eid prepared and aired a follow up report on the same issue on October 23, 2010 [http://www.nowlebanon.com/NewsArchiveDetails.aspx?ID=210785] and another on November 26, 2010.

On the 15th of January 2011 George Eid joined, Voice of Lebanon (VDL 100.5FM) radio station, as a news anchor and a show host. Whereas, on the 7th of February he aired the political show &quot; Al-mahkama&quot; which tackles all issues related to the Special tribunal of Lebanon. On the 17th of February Eid took in a live phone call from the witness in P.M hariri's assassination Zuhair el Sedik who launched a series of accusations live during the show. Following which Eid received a court summening by Ex-minister Karim Pacradoni who was accused by el Sedik. However the case was then dropped on the 25th of the February 2011.

The 22nd of April 2011 was another turning point, whereas Eid was shot at while reporting about outlaws in the Western Part of Beirut where Hezbollah militants dominate[http://nowlebanon.com/NewsArticleDetails.aspx?ID=264259]. However, Eid was not hurt or injured due to the protection of the Lebanese security forces and he was able to produce and publish the report on the same day.


==A selection of articles and editorials==
* [http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=691 عميدالحبر والدم]
* [http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=551 عذرا منك شارل شيخاني]
* [http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=459 نشيد الصحافي]
* [http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=654 الله اليوم في موسم الحصاد]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/en/article/id/25403 6 points balancing a handshake and a bullet]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/en/reportage/id/270 Downtown Beirut sit-in to a sudden end]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/politics/article/id/27583/theme/33/lebanon/The-General-who-knew-too-little-or-too-much? The General who knew too little or too much?]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/politics/article/id/26802/theme/32/lebanon/A-government-or-not-a-government? A government or not a government?]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/politics/article/id/26767/theme/32/lebanon/A-government...Pending-yesterday! A government...Pending yesterday!]
* [http://www.iloubnan.info/en/article/id/25703 On the threshold of a new presidential era?]

==Reports==
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KtJD-nLKfaQ] Broadband in Lebanon
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MiUmm5UWqFg] St Basil Church
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TjgHI9Dd6-E] Remembering Bachir Gemayel
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zpx8FOd5tBE] Ain el remaneh incident

==Media and interviews==
* [http://www.nna-leb.gov.lb/archive/07-12-2008/JOU41.html ورشة عمل شبابية في صور عن تنشيط وتنمية سياحية افضل]
* [http://www.nna-leb.gov.lb/archive/27-10-2008/JOU57.html الوزير ماروني التقى وزير السياحة في &quot;حكومة الظل]
* [http://www.nna-leb.gov.lb/archive/27-10-2008/JOU169.html عيد أطلع ديبلوماسية يونانية على نشاطات &quot;حكومة الظل الشبابية]
* [http://www.nna-leb.gov.lb/archive/14-04-2008/JOU102.html نادي &quot;نهارالشباب&quot; في جامعة سيدة اللويزة اطلق حملة &quot;لا للحرب]
* [http://www.nna-leb.gov.lb/archive/23-05-2007/JOU154.htm جامعة سيدة اللويزة كرمت 3 من طلابها نالوا &quot;جائزة سعيد عقل]

==Videography==
*[http://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=549975396&amp;ref=name#/group.php?gid=59555800922]
*[http://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=549975396&amp;ref=name#/group.php?gid=7713814762&amp;ref=ts]
*[http://www.facebook.com/video/video.php?v=104596240396&amp;oid=7713814762]
*[http://www.facebook.com/video/video.php?v=104573705396&amp;oid=7713814762]
*[http://www.facebook.com/video/?oid=7713814762#/video/video.php?v=97602930396&amp;oid=7713814762]

==See also==
* [[Gebran Tueni]]
* [[May Chidiac]]

==References==
* iloubnan.com-http://www.iloubnan.info/artsandculture/actualite/id/27272/theme/155/lebanon/Shadow%20Minister%20of%20Tourism%20announces%20the%20first%20international%20Aramaic%20festival here
* Naharashabab-http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-forum.php?ID=1005
* Naharashabab-[http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=2195]
* Naharashabab-[http://naharashabab.com/Headline-ar-highlights.php?ID=1760]
* richlebanon-[http://www.richlebanon.com/georgeeid]
{{Reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Eid, George
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =25-06
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Beirut, Lebanon]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Eid, George}}
[[Category:Lebanese Maronites]]
[[Category:People from Beirut]]
[[Category:Lebanese journalists]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
