<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Bryant and May Factory, Bow" to="Bow Quarter" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="2451401" ns="0" title="Bow Quarter"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Bow match factory 1.jpg|thumb|250px|Bryant &amp; May's match factory (now the Bow Quarter). (October 2006)]]
'''The Bow Quarter''' is a [[gated community]] in [[Bow, London]]. The building was originally the [[Bryant and May]] match factory, and was the site of the [[London matchgirls strike of 1888|Match Girls' strike]] in the 1880s. The factory was redeveloped in the 1980s, in one of [[east London]]'s first [[urban renewal]] projects.

==History==
From the mid-19th century to more than three-quarters of the way through the 20th century it was the location of the famous [[Bryant and May]] [[match]] factory. At one point at the turn of the two centuries it was London's largest factory.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}

The 3 acre (1.2 hectare) site, acquired by [[William Bryant (industrialist)|William Bryant]] and Francis May in 1861, contained a number of factories that had once been used for the manufacture of [[candle]]s, [[crinoline]] and [[rope]] but had fallen into disrepair.&lt;ref name=beaver-1/&gt; Assistance in adapting the site for match making was provided by [[John Edvard Lundström]], the [[Sweden|Swedish]] safety match maker.&lt;ref name=beaver-1/&gt;

Bryant and May were influential in fighting against the dreadful disease known as [[phossy jaw]], caused by the white [[phosphorus]] used in the manufacture of early matches. Some of the first welfare institutions in Britain for industrial workers began on this site, including the provision of a [[dentistry|dentist]].&lt;ref name=beaver-1/&gt;

The factory saw many famous historical events: the [[London matchgirls strike of 1888]] started there, culminating in the establishment of the first British [[trade union]] for women.&lt;ref name=beaver-1&gt;Beaver (1985). Part One: ''Building a Business''.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[blue plaque]] outside the entrance commemorates the role of social pioneer and [[feminism|feminist]] [[Annie Besant]] in leading the demands for better pay and conditions. It finally closed in 1979, when 275 people worked there, the work being transferred to Liverpool.&lt;ref name=beaver-3&gt;Beaver (1985). Part Three: ''The age of Technology''.&lt;/ref&gt; At full production, in 1911, the Bow site employed more than 2,000 women and girls.&lt;ref name=beaver-2&gt;Beaver (1985). Part Two: ''Years of Growth''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Present day==
The site fell into disrepair until 1988, when developers embarked upon one of east London's first [[urban renewal]] projects. Today Bow Quarter consists of 733 one- and two-bedroom apartments and penthouses, together with a handful of workers' cottages built around late 19th century. Set in {{convert|7|acre|m2}} of landscaped grounds, amenities include a residents' gym, a bar and restaurant and a convenience store.

The majority of the apartments today are housed in former factory and office buildings. Arlington for example was built as offices in 1874; Lexington and Manhattan date from the factory site redevelopment in 1911. The Victorian cottages near the entrance provided accommodation for the company directors whilst Staten was built as extra office accommodation in the late 1950s. The Park buildings (East, Central and West) were added in the mid 1990s.

In 2004 the TV series ''If...'' shot scenes in the fictional gated community ''Regent's Court'' inside Bow Quarter, some residents were also interviewed by the production team during the making of the programme.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/if/3489040.stm|title=BBC News - If... Things Don't Get Better | date=2004-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=bbcif2&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/programmes/if/3513980.stm|title=BBC News - Gates and ghettoes: A tale of two Britains | date=2004-03-18 | first=Anita| last=Rice}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Previous residents have included [[John Barrowman]] and [[Steve Strange]]{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}. Former resident [[Danny Wallace (humourist)|Danny Wallace]] declared his flat a [[micronation]] in the TV series [[How to Start Your Own Country (TV series)|How to Start Your Own Country]].

==References==
===Notes===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
* Beaver, Patrick (1985). ''The Match Makers''. London: Henry Melland. ISBN 0-907929-11-7.
* Emsley, John (2000). ''The Shocking History of Phosphorus: a biography of the Devil's element''. London: Macmillan. ISBN 0-333-76638-5.

==External links==
* [http://www.thebowquarter.co.uk/ Official Website]
* [http://www.bowquarter.com/ Residents' Association]
* [http://www.unionhistory.info/matchworkers/matchworkers.php Matchworker's strike]

{{Coord|51.5312|-0.0219|region:GB_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Tower Hamlets]]
[[Category:Housing in London]]
[[Category:Gated communities]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
