<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="222234" ns="0" title="Durango"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the state in Mexico|the capital city of that state|Durango, Durango}}
{{other uses}}
{{Infobox settlement
| name                    = Durango
| native_name             = &lt;small&gt;Estado Libre y Soberano de Durango&lt;/small&gt;
| native_name_lang        =
| settlement_type         = [[States of Mexico|State]]
| image_flag              = Flag of Durango.svg
| flag_size               = 160px
| flag_alt                =
| image_seal              = Escudo_de_Armas_de_Durango.svg
| seal_size               = 65px
| nickname                = &lt;!--NO--&gt;
| motto                   = &lt;!--NO--&gt;
| anthem                  = &lt;!--NO--&gt;
| image_map               = Durango en México.svg
| map_caption             = State of Durango within Mexico
| latd  =24  |latm  =56  |lats  =05 |latNS  =N
| longd = 104 |longm =54  |longs =43 |longEW =W
| coor_pinpoint           =
| coordinates_type        = region:MX-DUR_type:adm1st
| coordinates_display     = inline,title
| coordinates_footnotes   =
| subdivision_type        = [[Country]]
| subdivision_name        = [[Mexico]]
| subdivision_type1       = [[Capital City|Capital]]
| subdivision_name1       = [[Durango, Durango|Victoria de Durango]]
| subdivision_type2       = [[List of cities in Mexico|Largest&amp;nbsp;City]]
| subdivision_name2       = [[Durango, Durango|Victoria de Durango]]
| subdivision_type3       = [[Municipalities of Mexico|Municipalities]]
| subdivision_name3       = [[Municipalities of Durango|39]]
| established_title       = [[Sovereign state|Admission]]
| established_date        = May 22, 1824&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=La diputación provincial y el federalismo mexicano| url =http://books.google.com.mx/books?id=i_GK_-6deKIC&amp;pg=PA227&amp;lpg=PA227&amp;dq=22+De+Mayo+De+1824+durango&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=eyvDzsrMIz&amp;sig=zYxzmtG7gTQgGV-WNDfHgqcG_kU&amp;hl=es&amp;ei=FtAxS9joN56ltgf-_ojFDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CAgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=22%20De%20Mayo%20De%201824%20durango&amp;f=false| language =Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| established_title2     = [[Territorial evolution of Mexico|Order]]
| established_date2      = [[Territorial evolution of Mexico|17th]]
| founder                 =
| seat_type               =
| seat                    =
| government_footnotes    =
| leader_party            =
| leader_title            = [[List of Mexican state governors|Governor]]
| leader_name             = [[Jorge Herrera Caldera|Jorge Herrera]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|[[Institutional Revolutionary Party|PRI]]|23px]]
| leader_title1           = [[Senate of Mexico|Senators]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Senadores por Durango LXI Legislatura |url=http://www.senado.gob.mx/index.php?ver=int&amp;mn=4&amp;sm=4&amp;id=11 |publisher=Senado de la Republica |accessdate=November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| leader_name1            = [[Rodolfo Dorador Pérez Gavilán|Rodolfo Dorador]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Andrés Galván Rivas]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ricardo Pacheco]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
|leader_title2           = [[Chamber of Deputies of Mexico|Deputies]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Listado de Diputados por Grupo Parlamentario del Estado de Durango |url=http://sitl.diputados.gob.mx/LXI_leg/listado_diputados_gpnp.php?tipot=Edo&amp;edot=10 |publisher=Camara de Diputados |accessdate=November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|leader_name2            = {{Collapsible list
 |title       = [[Chamber of Deputies of Mexico|Federal Deputies]]
 |frame_style = border:none; padding: 0;
 |title_style = &lt;!-- (optional) --&gt;
 |list_style  = text-align:left;display:none;
 |1           = • [[Pedro Ávila Nevárez]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |2           = • [[Yolanda De la Torre]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |3           = • [[Óscar García Barrón]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |4           = • [[José Ricardo López Pescador|Ricardo López]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |5           = • [[Ricardo Rebollo]] [[File:PRI Party (Mexico).svg|PRI|23px]]
 |6           = • [[Laura Estrada]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]
 |7           = • [[Bonifacio Herrera]] [[File:PAN Party (Mexico).svg|PAN|23px]]
 |8           = • [[Carlos Cruz Martínez]] [[File:PRD Party (Mexico).svg|PRD|23px]]
 |9           = • [[Lorena Corona Valdés]]  
 |10          = • [[Alfonso Ríos Vázquez]] [[File:PT Party (Mexico).svg|PT|23px]]
}}
| unit_pref               = Metric&lt;!-- or US or UK --&gt;
| area_footnotes          = &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Resumen |url=http://cuentame.inegi.gob.mx/monografias/informacion/dur/default.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=10 |publisher=Cuentame INEGI |accessdate=November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| area_total_km2          = 123451
| area_land_km2           =
| area_water_km2          =
| area_water_percent      =
| area_note               = [[List of Mexican states by area|Ranked 4th]]
| elevation_m             =
| elevation_max_footnotes =&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Relieve |url=http://cuentame.inegi.gob.mx/monografias/informacion/dur/territorio/relieve.aspx?tema=me&amp;e=10 |publisher=Cuentame INEGI |accessdate=November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| elevation_max_m         = 3340
| elevation_max_ft        =
| elevation_min_m         =
| elevation_min_ft        =
| population_footnotes    = &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Proyecciones de la población de México 2005-2050 |url=http://www.conapo.gob.mx/00cifras/proyecta50/10.xls |publisher=Consejo Nacional de Población |accessdate=August 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| population_total        = 1,632,934
| population_as_of        = 2010
| population_density_km2  = auto
| population_density_rank = [[List of Mexican states by population density|30th]]
| population_demonym      = Duranguense
| population_note         =
| population_rank         = [[List of Mexican states by population|24th]]
| timezone1               = [[Central Standard Time|CST]]
| utc_offset1             = −6
| timezone1_DST           = [[Central Daylight Time|CDT]]
| utc_offset1_DST         = −5
| postal_code_type        = [[Postal codes in Mexico|Postal code]]
| postal_code             = 34-35
| area_code_type          = [[Area code]]
| area_code               = {{Collapsible list
|title       = Area codes [[Area codes in Mexico by code (600-699)|1]] and [[Area codes in Mexico by code (800-899)|2]]
|frame_style = border:none; padding: 0;
|title_style = &lt;!-- (optional) --&gt;
|list_style  = text-align:left;display:none;
 |1           = • 618
 |2           = • 629
 |3           = • 649
 |4           = • 671
 |5           = • 674
 |6           = • 675
 |7           = • 676
 |8           = • 677
 |9           = • 871
 |10          = • 872
}}
| iso_code                = MX-DUR
| blank_name_sec1         = [[Human Development Index|HDI]]
| blank_info_sec1         = {{increase}} 0.822 &lt;span style=&quot;color:#090&quot;&gt;High&lt;/span&gt; &lt;small&gt;[[List of Mexican states by HDI|Ranked 19th]]&lt;/small&gt;
| blank_name_sec2         = [[GDP]]
| blank_info_sec2         = US$ 8,158,602.5 [[Million|mil]]{{Ref label|engfactobox|a|}}
| website                 = {{URL|http://www.durango.gob.mx/|Official Web Site}}
| footnotes               =
{{note|engoffbox}}a. The state's GDP was 104,430,112 million of [[Mexican peso|pesos]] in 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Durango. |url=http://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/bise/mexicocifras/default.aspx?ent=10 |year=2010 |accessdate=November 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; amount corresponding to 8,158,602.5 millon of [[Dollar coin (United States)|dollars]], being a dollar worth 12.80 pesos (value of June 3, 2010).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Reporte: Jueves 3 de Junio del 2010. Cierre del peso mexicano. |url=http://www.pesomexicano.com.mx/archivo/2010/junio/03/reporte-jueves-3-de-junio-del-2010--cierre-del-peso-mexicano.htm#leermas |publisher=www.pesomexicano.com.mx |accessdate=August 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''Durango''' ({{IPA-es|duˈɾaŋɡo}}) officially ''Estado Libre y Soberano de Durango'' ({{lang-en|Free and Sovereign State of Durango}}) is one of the 31 states which, with the [[Mexico city|Federal District]], comprise the [[Political divisions of Mexico|32 Federal Entities]] of [[Mexico]]. The state is located in [[Northwest Mexico]].  With a population of 1,632,934, it has Mexico's second-lowest population density, after [[Baja California Sur]]. The city of [[Durango, Durango|Victoria de Durango]] is the state's capital.

==History==
===Pre-colonization===
Durango, along with the states of Chihuahua, Sonora and Sinaloa, formed the historical and geographical unity of Northern Mexico, for what was the majority of the last millennium; it wasn't until the territories were reorganized after the [[Independence of Mexico|independence]] struggle that they emerged as [[Federated state|independent entities]]. This broad area represents the natural corridor that the [[Sierra Madre Occidental]] offered to the [[Toltec]] and [[Nahuatlaca]] tribes, both whom took advantage of the large accidental stone conformations to survive in the wilderness of the territory. The new formations formed as the only security for the tribes that moved among Northern Mexico and the [[Valley of Anahuac]], eventually becoming a home-state for these tribes who then began to form small communities, united by language and region. The [[Huichol people|Huichol]], [[Cora people|Cora]], and [[Tarahumara]] [[Tepehuanos]] incorporated perfectly distinct nations, each with evident sedentary purposes, and a strong family structure, all whilst setting aside the bellicose attitude of the Chichimec tribe of the center of the then-current Republic. The exceptions were the [[Acaxee]], Humas, and Xiximes who were constantly at war but always on the look-out for final settlements in the region of the Quebradas. &lt;br&gt; On the east bank of the state a longitudinal zone can be found, that extends from the current state of [[Zacatecas]] to the [[Comarca Lagunera|la Laguna]] area between the entities of Durango and [[Coahuila]]. The &quot;Indios Laguneros&quot; (Laguna Indians) traveled interchangeably between this area, they were characterized by their rebellious attitude, instability, religious customs and for being hunters and gatherers. These Natives of which so little was recorded were the first inhabitants of the region long before they were exterminated by the [[Spanish Empire|Spanish]] colonists. Today, only a few remain of the Tepehuanos, Huicholes, Coras and Tarahumara tribes.

===Spanish colonization===
[[File:Francisco de Ibarra.jpg|thumb|left|Captain Francisco de Ibarra]]
Once the province of [[New Spain]] was established in the rest of the country, new explorers ventured out to conquer Northern Mexico, establishing the province of [[Nueva Vizcaya]], in honor of the [[Provinces of Spain|Spanish province]] of the same name.
[[Francisco de Ibarra]], the first to colonize Durango, settled this part of the vast northern province of [[Nueva Vizcaya, New Spain|Nueva Vizcaya]]. On July 8, 1563 he founded the capital city and named it Durango for the Basque town [[Durango, Biscay]], [[Spain]], [[Europe]].
Durango along with the three aforementioned states (Chihuahua,Sonora,and Sinaloa), formed part of the province of [[Nueva Vizcaya]], a name that was used during the [[Colonialism|Colonial Period]] to designate the territory discovered by Captain [[Francisco de Ibarra]] between 1554 and 1567. Several important factors contributed to the region being named Nueva Vizcaya, one was that the valley in which the &quot;Cerro de Mercado&quot; is located had a resemblance to the &quot;Valley of Guardiana&quot; that existed in the province of [[Biscay]]. The second reason was the fact that iron mines which were found in Durango also existed in the aforementioned Spanish province of Biscay; reasons of which gave more meaning to the assigned name of the region. Additionally, many of the soldiers who then came on the expedition of Captain Francisco de Ibarra and formalized the conquest of the region, were Basques.  &lt;br&gt; Equally important to note is that in 1552 [[Spanish people|Spanish]] Captain, Ginés Vázquez del Mercado, discovered one of the world’s richest iron-ore deposits (now an important part of Durango) which was named after him, present-day '''Cerro de Mercado'''.
Gradually, in the following decades, the [[Franciscans]] followed by the [[Jesuits]] began the evangelization of Nueva Vizcaya, laying the foundations of a large diocese. The towns, Nombre de Dios, Peñol (Peñón Blanco), San Juan Bautista del Río, Analco, Indé, Topia, La Sauceda, Cuencamé and Mezquital arose from the evangelical work of the Franciscan order; Mapimi, Santiago Papasquiaro, Tepehuanes , Guanacevi, Santa Maria del Oro, Tamazula, Cerro Gordo (Villa Ocampo), San Juan de Bocas (Villa Hidalgo) and two establishments that originally belonged to the Franciscans, La Sauceda (Canatlan) and Cuencame, were established by the religious members of the Society of Jesus at the invitation of the [[Basque Country (greater region)|Basque]] Governor Rodrigo del Río de Lossa.
The establishment of garrisons in Northern Mexico, provided security to the people immersed in isolation, a characteristic of the territory. The new routes enjoined the military camps and thus emerged the 'Courier of the Provinces', a government scheme adopted by the [[Spain|Spanish]] monarchs in 1767. The neo-Basque territory began to split in the [[colonial period]]. The first to emerge was the Sinaloa Province, which then included the areas known today as [[Sonora]] and [[Arizona]]. Later, the state of Coahuila separated, and with the Constitution of 1824, was divided into provinces creating the states of Durango and Chihuahua, and attaching some municipalities to the state of Zacatecas.
&lt;br&gt;
Durango did not escape the great national struggle between [[conservatives]] and [[liberals]] and the capital was taken several times by representatives of both sides, as was the case of siege imposed by Coronado and Patoni in 1858 for the liberal cause, as well as the [[France|French]] intervention that between 1864 and 1866 that occupied the state with the support of conservative forces. At the time that [[Porfirio Díaz]] was at the head of the Republic, Durango also experienced local dictatorships such as that of Governor Juan Manuel Flores, who held office between 1884 and 1897. Esteban Fernandez, who also became governor, was reelected in 1908 after his 4-year term only to leave in 1911.
&lt;br&gt;
During the [[Porfiriato]], Durango joined the network of railway and telegraph networks that he lay down on the country, resulting in the creation of new regions, as was the case of the Laguna region from which the cities of Lerdo and Gomez Palacio emerged, both now of paramount importance. The railroad also connects the state capital with [[Mexico City]] and the border towns, which allows the marketing of goods produced in the region, and the transportation of mineral resources for exportation.
&lt;br&gt;
[[File:Pancho Villa y Luz Corral de Villa.jpg|thumb|Photo of Gen. Francisco Villa and his wife, Sra. Maria Luz Corral de Villa (1914)]]
Durango played a very important role in the [[Mexican Revolution]]. Important revolutionary figures of extraordinary historical validity in important battles between 1910 and 1924 emerged, such as [[Francisco Villa]], Calixto Contreras and Severino Cenicero, in support of the &quot;Maderistas&quot;, supporters of the ideologies of President [[Francisco I. Madero]]. On November 21, 1910, Duranguense military personnel Jesús Agustín Castro and Oreste Pereyra, took up arms in the Laguna region commanding a small army that would join the forces of Francisco I. Madero, shortly after his assassination.
&lt;br&gt;
The splitting of the territories would continue with the government of Enrique R. Calderon, who implemented the provisions of President [[Lazaro Cardenas]] with the distribution of {{convert|100000|acre|km2}} in the Laguna region of Durango, and the formation of the Municipality of Tlahualilo, shedding Mapimí and Gomez Palacio.
At the half century the &quot;educational crusade&quot; began which bestowed upon Durango important colleges of upper education such as Instituto Tecnológico de Durango (Technological Institute of Durango) and Universidad Juarez del Estado de Durango (University of Juarez in Durango). The latter was based on the historical Instituto Juarez (Juarez Institute), which dates back to the eighteenth century.
At this time the town of Vicente Guerrero also emerged, separating itself from Suchil an action which resulted in completion of the geographical pattern which now is the state of Durango, with modern means of communication that in the form of paved roads connects most of the municipalities with the capital and connects the capital with the important cities across the country.
The last years are representative of the [[rural]] exodus to the main cities of the entity, requiring the implementation of numerous development services, that completely changed the traditional image of the [[Colony|Colonial]] and [[Porfirista]] Durango that seemed rooted in the style of life of most of its inhabitants.
This was a late colonization for the Spanish, due mostly to heavy resistance by the indigenous population. From first contact to modern times, the indigenous peoples have attempted to gain some autonomy, address grievances, and maintain traditional land ownership.
Spanish colonists became highly attracted to the Durango area for its mining and grazing prospects.
In 1823, shortly after victory over Spain in the [[Mexican War of Independence]], Durango earned the right to become a separate state.

==Geography==
[[File:Abies tamazula dgo.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Abies durangensis]] in Tamazula, Durango, Mexico]]
The state of Durango is bordered to the north by [[Chihuahua (state)|Chihuahua]], to the north-east by [[Coahuila]], to the south-east by [[Zacatecas]], to the south-west by [[Nayarit]], and to the west by [[Sinaloa]].
Most of the state is heavily mountainous and a good part forested; the [[Sierra Madre Occidental]] occupies the western and central part of the state.  This mountain range contains a good supply of minerals, including the silver that encouraged Spanish occupation of the territory after it was discovered.  These mines extend north into [[Chihuahua (state)|Chihuahua]] and south into the state of [[Zacatecas]]. Vast desert basins in the Laguna District are irrigated by the [[Nazas River]].

Major crops grown in the area include [[cotton]], [[wheat]], [[Maize|corn]], [[alfalfa]], [[beans]], [[sorghum]], and other vegetables.

Durango is famous for its [[scorpions]]. The scorpion is a common symbol representing the state. Mexicans generally refer to the people of Durango as ''Alacrán de Durango'' (''Scorpions from Durango''). The demonym for the natives of Durango is Duranguense(s).

The major occupations in Durango are farming, lumbering,mining, and [[ranch]]ing.

== Arts and culture ==
===The land of cinema===
Durango is known nationally and even internationally for two reasons: one being that it is &quot;the land of the scorpions&quot; due to the many species of scorpions in the state, especially in the colonial areas, and second as &quot;the land of cinema.&quot; Durango has among its credits over 120 film productions, both domestic and foreign, and as a result, during the decades of the 1950s, 60s, 70s and 80s, had earned that title. Durango has established itself as one of the favorite places of film producers and directors due to its picturesque views and scenic beauty.

Film had arrived in a train heading to Durango in 1889; when the [[Mexican Revolution]] began in 1910, film producer [[Raoul Walsh]] recorded the battles of General [[Francisco Villa]]. These scenes were included in the film ''[[The Life of General Villa]]'' produced by D. W. Griffith, and directed by [[Christy Cabanne]] in 1914. Hollywood had discovered Durango in the mid-century.

In 1954, the film industry officially entered the state; American film art director [[Jack Smith (film director)|Jack Smith]] had flown over Durango and was instantly seduced by the landscape. Subsequently, the first movie filmed in Durango was [[White Feather (1955 film)|''White Feather'']], directed by [[Robert D. Webb]]. Durango also had close ties with [[John Wayne]]. The close friendship between Durango and John Wayne, an American actor and icon of [[Western (genre)|Western]] movies, started in 1965, and resulted in the making of the films ''[[The Sons of Katie Elder]]'', ''[[The War Wagon]]'', and ''[[Chisum]]'', among many others. Such was the amount of time that Wayne spent filming in Durango, that he acquired a ranch in the state.

===Cuisine===
Basque conquerors who founded Durango and began the conquest of the northern territory brought their recipes and the first herds. Among the dishes from Durango, is &quot;caldillo&quot;, particularly noted for its antiquity. Along with beef it can be prepared with chile verde (green chile), chile Colorado (red chile), or chile pasado (dehydrated green chiles). The broth is the first culinary preparation in the long history of culture in Durango, and demonstrates the influence of cultures that have been in the genesis of Durango. Its origin goes back to the days of [[Basque people|Basque]] Captain Francisco de Ibarra; one of the first conceptions appears in an old manuscript that belonged to wealthy miner and landowner, Joseph del Campo Soberón and Larrea Soberon, the Count of Súchil Valley.

Durango is also known for its marmalades and preserves made from quince, figs, and peaches, as well as the native pitahaya.
'''Gallina Borracha''' or 'drunken chicken' is a dish unique to Durango, made mostly of Spanish ingredients, such as raisins, sherry and almonds. Traditional drinks include '''Licor de Membrillo''', a liquor made from [[quince]]. Durango is also known for its cheese, in particular [[queso chihuahua]], also called ''''queso menonita'''', a type of cheese made by the state's numerous [[Mennonite]] residents as well as the traditional &quot;&quot;Queso Ranchero&quot;&quot; usually made in the high Sierra's (mountains) of Durango which tourists as well as native's like to enjoy. Another plate unique to Durango (usually more to North Western Durango) is &quot;&quot;Venorio&quot;&quot; made with pork ribs cut into pieces, nopales (cactus) and a special chile sauce made with different ground seeds of pumpkin as well as chile seeds, and has a distinctive orange look to the sauce. Carne seca (beef jerky) is also another traditional food that can be used to make &quot;&quot;machaca con huevo&quot; (jerkey with eggs) and caldillo con papas (jerkey with potato soup). The people from Durango also enjoy traditional [[Mexican food|Mexican]] dishes, such as [[tamale]]s, [[taco]]s, [[cabrito]], and [[enchilada]]s as well as quesadillas made with the two cheese mentioned above.

===Eco-Tourism===
Durango consists of geographical diversity which allows sports enthusiasts to participate in [[extreme sports]] such as [[kayaking]], [[mountain biking]], [[abseiling]], [[free climbing]] and more; Durango is also home to a quantity of [[gorges]], and voluminous [[waterfalls]] that measure {{convert|80|ft|m}} one of which is '''Salto del Agua LLovida'''. The state also has numerous [[lakes]] that measure over 800 meters in diameter such as '''Lago de Puentecillas''' (Puentecillas Lake). Located in the desert patch known as [[Bolsón de Mapimí]], is the famous [[Mapimí Silent Zone]] known for its [[magnetic]] properties similar to the [[Bermuda Triangle]] and the unique [[fauna]] and [[flora]] found in the region.

==Demographics==
According to the last census that took place in 2005, Durango, with just over a million and a half inhabitants, occupies the 24th position within the 32 federal entities regarding population, and reports an average growth rate so low that it would take more than 250 years to double its number of inhabitants.

At least 2% of the population over 5 years of age speak an indigenous language, 80% of which belong to the [[Tepehuan]] ethnic group, which is indigenous to the state. Other smaller indigenous groups include the [[Huichol people|Huichol]] and the [[Mexicanero]]s, the latter of an unknown descent and who speak a variety of Nahuatl. Roughly 20,000 German-speaking [[Mennonites]] reside in secluded communities throughout the semi-desertic region of the state.

90% of the state population are baptized [[Catholics]] which are mostly concentrated in the rural areas; the urban areas of the state contain significant religious minorities consisting of [[Protestants]], [[Orthodox Christians]], [[Ashkenazim Jews]], [[Muslims]] and [[Buddhists]].

Despite the low demographic density it contains, only 12 inhabitants per km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;., 60% of the population is concentrated in only three of the 39 state municipalities: [[Durango, Durango|Durango]], [[Gómez Palacio (municipality)|Gómez Palacio]], and [[Lerdo]]. The rest live in small and disperse localities, for as much as 6,258 communities can be found in the state, 82% of which have fewer than 100 inhabitants.

Some 67% of the population lives in urban areas, below the 76% national average. Even so, the migration of people from the rural zones towards urban environments represents a serious issue for the government of Durango, because it implies satisfying a high demand for public services and utilities.

== Municipalities ==
{{Main|Municipalities of Durango}}
Durango is divided into ''([[Municipalities of Durango|39 municipalities]])''.

== Major communities==

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! City !! Municipality !! Population in 2000 !! Population in 2010
|-
| [[Durango, Durango|Victoria de Durango]] || [[Durango Municipality|Durango]] || 427,135 || 518,709
|-
| [[Gómez Palacio, Durango|Gómez Palacio]] || [[Gómez Palacio Municipality|Gómez Palacio]] || 210,113 || 257,352
|-
| [[Lerdo, Durango|Lerdo]] || [[Lerdo Municipality|Lerdo]] || 58,862 || 79,669
|-
| [[Santiago Papasquiaro]] || [[Santiago Papasquiaro Municipality|Santiago Papasquiaro]] || 22,571 || 26,121
|-
| [[El Salto, Durango|El Salto]] || [[Pueblo Nuevo Municipality, Durango|Pueblo Nuevo]] || 19,210 || 24,241
|-
| [[Ciudad Guadalupe Victoria|Guadalupe Victoria]] || [[Guadalupe Victoria Municipality|Guadalupe Victoria]] || 14,156 || 16,506
|-
| [[Vicente Guerrero Municipality|Vicente Guerrero]] || [[Vicente Guerrero, Durango|Vicente Guerrero]] || 14,444 || 15,982
|-
| [[Ciudad Canatlán|Canatlán]] || [[Canatlán Municipality|Canatlán]] || 10,260 || 11,495
|-
| [[Nuevo Ideal]] || [[Nuevo Ideal Municipality|Nuevo Ideal]] || 8,555 || 10,876
|-
| [[Villa Unión, Durango|Villa Unión]] || [[Poanas Municipality|Poanas]] || 10,168 || 10,753
|-
| [[Cuencamé, Durango|Cuencamé de Ceniceros]] || [[Cuencamé Municipality|Cuencamé]] || 8,806 || 9,848
|}

Source: INEGI&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 Census&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=INEGI|url=http://www.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/consulta_resultados/iter2010.aspx?c=27329&amp;s=est|work=Censo de Población y Vivienda 2010|publisher=INEGI|accessdate=18 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notable people ==
*[[Pancho Villa|Francisco &quot;Pancho&quot; Villa]]
*[[Dolores del Río]]
*[[Guadalupe Victoria]]
*[[Marlene Favela]]

== Popular culture ==

Bob Dylan's song, Romance in Durango, is on his &quot;Desire&quot; 1976 album.

==See also==
{{satop|Geography|North America|Northern America|Latin America|Mexico|Durango}}
{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Durango}}
{{Portal|Mexico}}
*{{es icon}} [http://www.durango.gob.mx/ Durango State Government]
*[http://www.filmcommissiondurango.com/ingles/cartagobernador.html Film Commission Durango]
*{{es icon}} [http://www.durangomexico.info/ Durango thousands of pictures of local rural communities]
*[http://www.houstonculture.org/mexico/durango.html John P. Schmal, &quot;The history of indigenous Durango&quot;] detailing the series of revolts
*{{es icon}} [http://www.congresodurango.gob.mx/Leyes/22.PDF Territorial Division (legal text)]

{{Durango}}
{{States of Mexico}}

[[Category:Durango| ]]
[[Category:States of Mexico]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1824]]

[[ar:ولاية دورانجو]]
[[an:Estato de Durango]]
[[be:Штат Дуранга]]
[[be-x-old:Дуранга (штат)]]
[[br:Durango (Mec'hiko)]]
[[bg:Дуранго]]
[[ca:Estat de Durango]]
[[cs:Durango (stát)]]
[[cy:Durango]]
[[da:Durango (stat)]]
[[de:Durango (Bundesstaat)]]
[[et:Durango osariik]]
[[es:Durango]]
[[eo:Durango (subŝtato)]]
[[eu:Durango (estatua)]]
[[fa:دورانگو]]
[[fr:État de Durango]]
[[gl:Estado de Durango]]
[[ko:두랑고 주]]
[[hr:Durango]]
[[id:Durango (negara bagian)]]
[[ia:Durango]]
[[it:Durango (stato)]]
[[he:דורנגו (מדינה)]]
[[ka:დურანგო (შტატი)]]
[[kw:Durango]]
[[sw:Durango (jimbo)]]
[[la:Durangum (Mexicum)]]
[[lv:Durango]]
[[lt:Durangas (valstija)]]
[[hu:Durango]]
[[mr:दुरांगो]]
[[ms:Durango (wilayah)]]
[[nah:Durango]]
[[nl:Durango (staat)]]
[[ja:ドゥランゴ州]]
[[no:Durango (delstat)]]
[[nn:Delstaten Durango]]
[[pnb:دورانگو]]
[[pms:Durango]]
[[pl:Durango (stan)]]
[[pt:Durango]]
[[ro:Durango (stat Mexic)]]
[[rm:Durango]]
[[ru:Дуранго (штат)]]
[[simple:Durango]]
[[sr:Држава Дуранго]]
[[sh:Durango]]
[[fi:Durango]]
[[sv:Durango (delstat)]]
[[tl:Durango]]
[[th:รัฐดูรังโก]]
[[tg:Иёлати Дуранго]]
[[tr:Durango]]
[[uk:Дуранго (штат)]]
[[vi:Durango]]
[[vo:Durango]]
[[war:Durango]]
[[zh:杜蘭戈州]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
