<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22351805" ns="0" title="Midsouth Emmy Awards"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox award
| name        = Midsouth Emmy Award
| image       =  
| imagesize   =  
| caption     = Midsouth Emmy Award
| description = Excellence in [[television]]
| presenter   = [[National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences|NATAS]]
| State     = [[Nashville, Tennessee]]
| year        = 1984
| website     = http://nashville.emmyonline.org/
}}

'''Midsouth Emmy Awards''' are a division of the [[National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences]]. The [[Nashville, Tennessee]] division was founded in 1984. In addition to granting the Midsouth [[Emmy Awards]], this division awards scholarships, honors industry veterans at the Silver Circle Celebration, conducts National Student Television Awards of Excellence, has a free research and a nationwide job bank. The chapter also participates in judging Emmy entries at the regional and national levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlnashville.emmyonline.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nashville.emmyonline.org/ |title=nashville.emmyonline.org |author= National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |format= |work= |publisher= [[NATAS]] |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= |accessdate=2009-04-10}}The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences&lt;/ref&gt;

==Boundaries==

The academy is divided into the following boundaries and encompasses the states of [[North Carolina]] (except Asheville) and [[Tennessee]] as well as the television market of [[Huntsville, Alabama]].&lt;ref name=&quot;urlnashville.emmyonline.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nashville.emmyonline.org/#89 |title=nashville.emmyonline.org |author= The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |format= |work= |publisher= [[NATAS]] |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= |accessdate=2009-04-10}} The National Academy of Television of Arts and Sciences boundaries&lt;/ref&gt; These boundaries are responsible for the submission of television broadcast materials presented for awards considerations. 

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| '''State''' || '''Qualifying Cities'''
|-
| ''Alabama'' || Decatur, Florence, Huntsville
|-
| ''North Carolina'' || Charlotte, Durham, Greensboro, Greenville, High Point, New Bern, Raleigh, Washington, Wilmington, Winston-Salem
|-
| ''Tennessee'' || Chattanooga, Jackson, Knoxville, Memphis, Nashville
|-
|}


==2008-2009 board of governors==

The chapter announces every year its Board of Governors. These individuals are respected community leaders and experts in their fields.&lt;ref name=&quot;urlnashville.emmyonline.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nashville.emmyonline.org/#111 |title=nashville.emmyonline.org |author= [[NATAS]] |authorlink= |coauthors= |date= |format= |work= |publisher= The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= |accessdate=2009-04-10}} The NAtional Academy of Television Arts and Sciences Board of Governors&lt;/ref&gt;


National Trustee - Phillip L. Bell, Executive Producer, Earnhardt &amp; Company

National Trustee – Gene Policinski, Vice President, The First Amendment Center

Alternate Trustee - Laura Faber, Anchor, WZTV Fox 17 News

President - Ellen Jones Pryor, Director of Communications, Frist Center for the Visual Arts

Vice President - Kenneth A. Smith, News Director, WZTV Fox 17 News

Regional Vice President - Steve Crump, Reporter, WSOC

Regional Vice President - Sharon Tinsley, President, Alabama Broadcasters Association

Treasurer - Jennifer Lane, Tax Director-Entertainment, Decosimo/Vaden

Secretary - Clifton Hunt, Promotions, NewsChannel 5 Network

Legal Counsel - Kenneth R. Jones, Jr., Jones Hawkins &amp; Farmer, PLC

Executive Director - Geneva M. Brignolo, NATAS Nashville

Advanced Media Chairman - Michael Schoenfeld, Vice President, Duke University

Development Chairman – Maureen Cleator, New Business Sales Manager, NewsChannel 5 Network

Education Chairman - Dr. Linda DeMarco Miller, Metro Nashville Public Schools

Emmy Awards Chairman - Beth Tucker Womack, Metro Nashville Public Schools

Program Chairman - Rich Stone, Stone Productions

Rising Star Chairman - Pete Weber, Voice of the Nashville Predators

Governor - David J. Bennett, President, Altura Productions

Governor - Dave Carter, VP/GM South Central, Comcast Spotlight

Governor – Jeff Davidson, Special Projects, WKRN

Governor - Nicholas Dugger, President, Tennessee Digital Video

Governor – Lisa Harless, Senior Vice President, Regions Morgan Keegan

Governor - Sandra M. Harris, Video Director, The Renaissance Center

Governor - Dr. David Hinton, Dean of Academic Affairs, Art Institute of Tennessee

Governor – Mason Hunter, Senior Director Media Licensing, BMI

Governor - Joe Pagetta, Media Relations Manager, NPT: Nashville Public Television

Governor - Emily Pearce, Assistant Director, Vanderbilt University News Service

Governor - Jacqueline Ann Pillers, Special Projects, NewsChannel 5 Network

Governor - Karen-Lee Ryan, Website Editor, TennesseeGreen.com and TennesseanTravel.com

Governor - Aaron Solomon, Anchor, WSMV

Governor - Sarah Trahern, Senior Vice President Programming, GAC: Great American Country

==22nd annual winners==
{{details|22nd Midsouth Emmy Awards}}

The winners of the 22nd Annual Midsouth Emmy Awards we announced in a live television broadcast on January 26, 2008. The live telecast was hosted by [[Mick Mixon]], who is the &quot;Voice&quot; of the [[Carolina Panthers]], and [[Pete Weber]], who is the &quot;Voice&quot; of the [[Nashville Predators]]. The awards were broadcasted live from the [[Schermerhorn Symphony Center]] in [[Nashville, TN]]

==23rd annual winners==
{{details|23rd Midsouth Emmy Awards}}

The winners of the 23rd Annual Midsouth Emmy Awards were announced in a live television broadcast on January 24, 2009. The show was hosted by Country music star, [[Hal Ketchum]].

==24th annual winners==
{{details|24th Midsouth Emmy Awards}}

The winners of the 24th Annual Midsouth Emmy Awards were announced in a live television broadcast on January 30, 2010. The show was hosted by three-time former [[NASCAR Championship|NASCAR Winston Cup]] champion, [[Darrell Waltrip]]. The awards were broadcast live from the [[Schermerhorn Symphony Center]] in [[Nashville, TN]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Emmy Awards}}
[[Category:Regional Emmy Awards|Midsouth *]]
[[Category:Awards established in 1984]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
