<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22368129" ns="0" title="Long Beach State 49ers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''{{main|California State University, Long Beach}}'''

[[Image:Csulb-tower2.jpg|thumb|right|The &quot;Go Beach!&quot; water tower.]]
An [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] member, Long Beach State has 18 sports teams and plays competitively in [[baseball]], [[cross country running|cross country]], [[softball]], [[track and field]], women's [[tennis]], and women's [[soccer]], as well as both men's and women's [[basketball]], [[volleyball]], [[water polo]] and [[golf]] teams.  The university is a founding member of the [[Big West Conference]], and also competes in the [[Mountain Pacific Sports Federation]] for sports not sponsored by the Big West.

In the realm of sports the school is referred to as &quot;Long Beach State.&quot; The official name of Long Beach State sports teams is &quot;The 49ers&quot; in honor of the year the university was founded and for the prospectors of the [[California Gold Rush]] one hundred years before then. Unofficially, &quot;The Beach&quot; is used to refer to Long Beach State and its sports teams as it is the only university on the West Coast with the word &quot;Beach&quot; in its name. One can see the cheer &quot;Go Beach!&quot; written on many CSULB products around campus and on the large [[water tower]] near the entrance to the campus.

The school colors have been black and gold since 2000, when they were changed by a student referendum (after [[George Allen (American football coach)|George Allen]] changed the football uniform colors) from the original brown and gold.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Traditions|url=http://www.longbeachstate.com/trads/traditions.html|work=Long Beach State website|accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Rivals==
The Beach has several rival schools when it comes to sports. In addition to being located in close proximity to each other, Long Beach State and [[California State University, Fullerton|Cal State Fullerton]] have competed heavily as conference rivals in baseball more than 20 years. More recently, specifically since 2006, Long Beach State and [[University of California, Irvine|UC Irvine]] have participated in the annual &quot;Black and Blue Rivalry Series.&quot; In this challenge, each school earns points for its collective conference championships and head-to-head victories against each other (across all NCAA sports in which both schools participate). The totals are added up at the end of the season and a winner is declared. Both schools are currently tied 2-2. Finally, Long Beach State also has a long-standing &quot;beach school&quot; rivalry with [[University of California, Santa Barbara|UC Santa Barbara]].

==Baseball==
{{seealso|Long Beach State 49ers baseball}}
Unlike all other Long Beach State sports teams, the baseball team unofficially goes under the moniker &quot;[[The Dirtbags]].&quot; After the hiring of Dave Snow as head coach in 1989, the LBSU baseball team has become one of the most successful teams in the school's athletic history. The Dirtbags are consistently ranked in the national top 30 and have appeared in 17 of the last 20 [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] tournaments. Along the way, the team has won 9 Big West conference championships, hosted 4 NCAA regionals (plus 1 super regional), and appeared in 4 College World Series.&lt;ref name=&quot;championships&quot;&gt;Mike Weathers became 'Dirtbag' head coach in 2001.
[http://www.longbeachstate.com/history/champteams.html Championship Teams]. ''49er Historical Archive.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The school has also produced a number of prominent professional players over the years, including former [[American League]] MVP [[Jason Giambi]], former American League Rookie of the Year [[Bobby Crosby]], and all-star and 2008 American League Rookie of the Year [[Evan Longoria]]. Many more ex-Dirtbags have participated in the prestigious [[Major League Baseball|MLB]] All-Star Futures game, such as rookie phenomenons [[Jered Weaver]] and [[Troy Tulowitzki]].&lt;ref name=&quot;proalums&quot;&gt;[http://www.longbeachstate.com/history/proalums.html Professional Alumni]. ''49er Historical Archive.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Volleyball==
{{see also|Long Beach State 49ers men's volleyball}}
Long Beach State is home to one of the top women's [[volleyball]] teams in the nation. CSULB alumnus [[Brian Gimmillaro]] has coached the team since 1985 and his tenure is the second-longest of any Long Beach State coach with one team. Long Beach State has appeared in the NCAA tournament 24 consecutive times under Gimmillaro, only missing the tournament once in 1986.

Long Beach State has won three national titles in women's volleyball, in 1989, 1993 and 1998. The 1998 women's team was the first team in NCAA Division I history to have an undefeated season. The team's most famous alumnus is [[Misty May-Treanor|Misty May]], who won two Olympic gold medals in Beach Volleyball in [[2004 Summer Olympics|2004]] and [[2008 Summer Olympics|2008]].

The men's volleyball competes in the [[Mountain Pacific Sports Federation]]. They won the MPSF regular season title in 2008. They won the 1991 [[NCAA Men's Volleyball Championship]] and have placed second five times.

==Tennis==
Long Beach State women's tennis team ('Beach Tennis') won the first of a conference record 8 Big West tennis titles in 2002 to reach their first NCAA tournament. From 2004–2009, Long Beach State won six consecutive Big West tennis titles and the automatic berth to the NCAA championships. The team has appeared in the conference title match every year since 2001.  The 2010 team went undefeated in league play to win the Big West Conference regular season championship.  The 2011 team captured another regular season title and then the program's eighth tournament championship by reaching a record eleventh consecutive conference final and then defeating rival UC Irvine for a sixth time in the championship match.  

'Beach Tennis' has qualified for eight NCAA Championships and advanced to the 'Round of 32' in 2006.  The 49ers have been a # 2 seed once, a # 3 seed five times and a # 4 seed twice in NCAA tournament play.

Head Coach Jenny Hilt-Costello has won a league record six Big West Conference Coach of the Year awards (2001, 2004, 2005, 2006, 2008, 2009) and was named the ITA West Region Coach of the Year and a finalist for the national award in 2004. 

Three 'Beach Tennis' players have earned Big West Conference Player of the Year honors, including Hannah Grady who became the first student-athlete in any Big West Conference sport to be named Player of the Year four consecutive years (06, 07, 08, 09).  In February 2010, court #1 at the Rhodes Tennis Center was named Hannah Grady Court in lieu of retiring her number, as tennis players do not wear numbers. Four players have been named Conference Freshman of the Year since the award started in 2005. 

Long Beach State has been nationally ranked continuously since March 2001. The 2006 team reached #18 in the ITA National Rankings; then peaking at #26 in 2007, #35 in 2008, #25 in 2009 and again #35 in 2010.  The 2011 team peaked and also finished at # 36 in the national rankings. 

The women's tennis team plays at the Terry L. Rhodes Tennis Center, which opened on campus Fall 2008. The tennis center is named after 49er alumnus Terry Rhodes following his $1.25 million gift to the women's tennis program. Mr. Rhodes' gift is the largest single sport donation in university history. The new facility also includes The Gloria and Bob Hendricks Family Scoreboard, a {{convert|40|ft|m|sing=on}} high electronic display of all matches donated by the family of the former 49er women's tennis head coach.  The facility is located on the northeast side of campus immediately next to the $70 million Student Recreation and Wellness Center that opened in Fall 2010.

==Basketball==
{{seealso|Long Beach State 49ers men's basketball}}
The CSULB men's basketball team has also enjoyed success in recent times. In the 2006-07 season, the 49ers finished with a 24-8 (12-2) record, the Big West conference championship, and the school's first trip to the NCAA tournament in 12 years. Star guard Aaron Nixon was named Big West player of the year, as well as being selected as an AP Honorable Mention All-American. On April 6, 2007, it was announced that [[Dan Monson]] (formerly of [[Gonzaga University]] and the [[University of Minnesota]]) would become Long Beach State's next head Men's Basketball Coach, succeeding Larry Reynolds.

The women's basketball team had its greatest success during the 1980s when coached by [[Joan Bonvicini]] for 12 years. During that time the team went 325-71. The 49ers won 10 Big West Conference titles, made 10 straight NCAA appearances, had 12 consecutive winning seasons, and never won fewer than 24 games in a season. Bonvicini guided the 49ers to Final Four appearances in 1987 and 1988.

==Water Polo==
The Long Beach State women's water polo team ranked as high as 10th in the nation during the 2011 season.  Finishing the regular season with a 12-16 record, the 49ers went into the [[Big West Conference]] Championship seeded 6th.  After knocking out two higher ranked teams, ([[UC Santa Barbara]] and [[CSU Northridge]]) Long Beach advanced to the championship game against [[UC Irvine]]. The 2011 squad also contributed five players to the All-Big West Team.

==Football==
{{seealso|Long Beach State 49ers football}}
Long Beach State competed in Division I football for a number of years (1969–91), producing a number of professional players, including [[Terrell Davis]] and [[Mike Horan (American football)|Mike Horan]], among others.  [[George Allen (football)|George Allen]], the famed [[Los Angeles Rams]] and [[Washington Redskins]] coach, had a short one-year tenure at Long Beach State. Long Beach State discontinued its football program after the 1991 season due to budget constraints. Prior to going Division I in 1969 the football team competed in the old &quot;College Division&quot; of the NCAA from 1955 through 1968.

==Olympics==
Long Beach State has had the honor of having at least one of its own athletes participate in every [[Summer Olympic Games]] since the first Olympiad after the school's founding.&lt;ref name=&quot;olympians&quot;&gt;[http://www.longbeachstate.com/history/olympians.html Olympians Associated with Long Beach State]. ''49er Historical Archive.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

==Coaches==
Long Beach has also had a number of nationally prominent coaches, including [[Tex Winter]], [[Jerry Tarkanian]] and [[Lute Olson]] in men's basketball, [[George Allen (football)|George Allen]] in football,  [[Frances Schaafsma]] in women's volleyball and basketball, [[Joan Bonvicini]] in women's basketball, and Jon Urbanchek and Don Gambril in swimming.

==Popular culture==
Alumnus [[J.P. Calderon|John &quot;J.P.&quot; Calderon]] competed in the 13th edition of the hit reality television show [[Survivor (US TV series)|Survivor]]. Calderon, who is now a professionally ranked [[Association of Volleyball Professionals|AVP]] player, graduated from Cal State Long Beach in 2000 after playing on the nationally ranked Division I Men's Volleyball Team.

==Club sports==
In addition to NCAA-sanctioned sports, Long Beach State also fields numerous competitive club sports teams, such as [[College rugby|rugby]], [[ice hockey]], [[ultimate (sport)|ultimate]], [[soccer]], [[sport rowing|crew]], and many others.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
 
==External links==
{{Portal box|Los Angeles|University}}
*[http://www.longbeachstate.com/index-main.html Official web site of Long Beach State Athletics]

[[Category:Long Beach State 49ers|*]]
[[Category:College sports teams in California]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
