<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="224278" ns="0" title="Epiphany (web browser)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox web browser
| name                   = Epiphany
| logo                   = [[File:Epiphany-web-browser.png|60px]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Epiphany3.0.png|300px]]
| caption                = Epiphany 3.0.0
| author                 = [[Marco Pesenti Gritti]]
| developer              = [[GNOME|The GNOME Web Browser Developers]]
| released               = {{start date|2003|9|11}}
| frequently updated     = yes
| programming language   = [[C (programming language)|C]] ([[GTK+]])
| operating system       = [[Linux]], [[BSD]], [[Mac OS X]]
| engine                 = [[WebKit]] (previously [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko]])
| platform               = [[GNOME]]
| language               = More than 60 languages
| genre                  = [[Web browser]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License|GPL]] v2+
| website                = [http://projects.gnome.org/epiphany/ projects.gnome.org/epiphany/]
}}
'''Epiphany''' is an [[open source]] [[web browser]] for the [[GNOME]] [[desktop environment]]. The browser is a [[Fork (software development)|descendant]] of [[Galeon]], and was created after developer disagreements about Galeon's growing complexity.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;galeon-history_website&quot; /&gt; Since then Epiphany is developed as part of GNOME project and reuses most of its technologies and settings when applicable.

==Development==
=== Galeon fork ===
Epiphany was originally developed as a [[Fork (software development)|fork]] of [[Galeon]] by [[Marco Pesenti Gritti]], who was also the initiator of Galeon. The fork occurred because of the different aims of Gritti and the rest of Galeon development team about new features. While Gritti regarded Galeon's monolithic design and the amount of user-configurable features as factors limiting Galeon's maintainability and user base expansion, the rest of Galeon developers believed that Galeon still wasn't feature complete. At the same time the GNOME project created the [[GNOME]] [[human interface guidelines]], which promoted simplification of user interfaces. As Galeon was considered a [[power user]]-oriented browser, the implementation of those guidelines was believed to be unacceptable by most developers. As a result, Gritti created a new browser based on Galeon's codebase with most non-mission-critical features stripped out. Epiphany was intended to be fully compliant with the GNOME human interface guidelines, with a very simple user interface. As such Epiphany does not have its own theme settings and uses GNOME’s settings, which are specified in the [[GNOME Control Center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;galeon-history_website&quot; /&gt;

Gritti explains his motivations:

{{quotation|While Mozilla has an excellent rendering engine, its default XUL-based interface is considered to be overcrowded and bloated. Furthermore, on slower processors even trivial tasks such as pulling down a menu is less than responsive.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Epiphany aims to utilize the simplest interface possible for a browser. Keep in mind that simple does not necessarily mean less powerful. We believe the commonly used browsers of today are too big, buggy, and bloated. Epiphany addresses simplicity with a small browser designed for the web—not mail, newsgroups, file management, instant messaging or coffee making. The UNIX philosophy is to design small tools that do one thing, and do it well.|Marco Pesenti Gritti&lt;ref name=&quot;mozdev-home&quot;/&gt;}}

Galeon continued after the fork, but lost its momentum due to the remaining developers' failure to keep up with new features and changes [[Mozilla]] introduced. Galeon development finally stalled and the developers decided to work on a set of extensions to bring Galeon's advanced features to Epiphany.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;

Epiphany's early philosophy included a commitment to creating a web browser specifically for GNOME:

{{quotation|Epiphany's main goal is to be integrated with the gnome desktop. We dont aim to make epiphany usable outside Gnome. If someone will like to use it anyway, it's just a plus. Ex: Making people happy that don't have control center installed is not a good reason to have mime configuration in epiphany itself.|Marco Pesenti Gritti&lt;ref name=&quot;mozdev-home&quot;/&gt;}}

Gritti is no longer involved with the Epiphany project and a GNOME team lead by Xan Lopez, Christian Persch and Jean-François Rameau now direct the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;

While some believe that Epiphany should be the default web browser in [[Linux distributions]] with GNOME as the default [[desktop environment]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_look_214&quot; /&gt; the common practice is to distribute [[Firefox]] instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_garden&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;canonical_default-browser&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora_default-browser&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;suse_default-broswer&quot; /&gt; In most minimalist distributions, Epiphany is installed with the GNOME meta-package or packages group.&lt;ref name=&quot;gentoo_default-browser&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;arch_default-browser&quot; /&gt;

=== Gecko-based ===
The first version of Epiphany was released on 24 December 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;epiphany-turns-7&quot; /&gt;

Epiphany initially used the [[Gecko (layout engine)|Gecko layout engine]] from the [[Mozilla]] project to display web pages. It provided a GNOME integrated [[front-end]] to Gecko, instead of the Mozilla [[XUL]] interface.&lt;ref name=&quot;dont-click_book&quot; /&gt;

The development process of Epiphany was mainly focused on numerous small usability improvements. The most notable of them was the new text entry widget, which first appeared in 1.8 stable version series. The new widget supported icons inside the text area, reducing amount of chrome needed to represent the information, and thus conforming GNOME HIG.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-text-entry_devblog&quot; /&gt;

The second major milestone (after version 1.0) in Epiphany development was the 2.14 release: this was the first Epiphany release which followed GNOME's version numbering. It also featured network awareness with [[NetworkManager]], [[smart bookmark]]s-related improvements and possibility to be compiled against [[XULRunner]]. The latter is specifically important: previously Epiphany could only use [[Firefox]] or [[Mozilla Application Suite|Mozilla]]/[[SeaMonkey]] as a [[layout engine]] provider, so it could only be installed alongside with one of those browsers. The XULRunner support gave the possibility to install Epiphany as the only web browser in the system.&lt;ref name=&quot;pi-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;198_devblog&quot; /&gt;

=== WebKit-based ===
The development process heavily suffered from multiple problems, related to the GECKO backend.&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-announcement&quot; /&gt; To address these issues in July 2007 the Epiphany team added support for [[WebKit]] as an alternative rendering engine for Epiphany.&lt;ref name=&quot;port-buddha&quot; /&gt; As the backend development advanced, on {{dts|2008|4|1}} the Epiphany team announced that it would stop using the Gecko rendering engine and proceed using only WebKit.&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-announcement&quot; /&gt;

The size of the development team and the complexity of porting the whole browser to a new backend caused Epiphany to re-release version 2.22 with bugfixes instead of the actual development code,&lt;ref name=&quot;epiphany-loves-webkit&quot; /&gt; so the browser remained stagnant until {{dts|2009|7|1}}, when the project team announced that Epiphany 2.26 would be the final Gecko-based version.&lt;ref name=&quot;gecko-eol&quot; /&gt; Eventually, in September 2009 the Webkit-powered Epiphany was released, as part of the release of GNOME 2.28.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_garden&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Epiphany 2.26.1 - 3.2.0.png|thumb|right|Epiphany 2.26.1 (left) showing its larger [[user interface chrome]] area than with current versions (right)]]
More recent versions of the browser have reduced the amount of [[user interface chrome]], including menus and control buttons, although the latter can be optionally added. Epiphany supports [[Tabbed Document Interface|tabbed browsing]], [[HTTP cookie|cookie]] management, [[Pop-up ad|popup]] blocking and an extensions system via the Epiphany-extensions package. The Java ([[IcedTea]]) plug-in is also available.

=== Release history ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Version
! Date
! Changes&lt;ref name=&quot;gnome-rn&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;git_news&quot; /&gt;
|-
! 0.5
| {{dts|2003|4|13}}&lt;ref name=&quot;footnotes_ephy-05&quot; /&gt;
|
* Ability to drag bookmarks, smart bookmarks and topics to the toolbar.
* Optional Go button for URL bar.
* Help support.
|-
! 0.6
| {{dts|2003|5|4}}&lt;ref name=&quot;freebsd_makefile&quot; /&gt;
|
* [[Drag and drop]] of links to [[Tab (GUI)|tab bar]].
* Security preferences added.
* The user primary language automatic detection.
* New history dialog.
* Default bookmarks toolbar.
|-
! 0.7
| {{dts|2003|6|12}}&lt;ref name=&quot;freebsd_makefile&quot; /&gt;
|
* Zoom control for the toolbar.
* Ability to reload page bypassing cache.
* Traditional bookmarks menu.
* ''Exit fullscreen'' button.
|-
! 0.8
| {{dts|2003|7|13}}&lt;ref name=&quot;mzine_ephy-08&quot; /&gt;
|
* Tooltips.
* Imroved GNOME integration.
* Fast search for bookmarks and history.
* Drag and drop of [[URL]]s in the bookmarks toolbar.
|-
! 0.9
| {{dts|2003|7|}}
| ''Bugfixes only.''
|-
! 1.0
| {{dts|2003|09|11}}&lt;br /&gt;''GNOME 2.04''
|
* Support for Mozilla 1.6.
|-
! 1.2
| {{dts|2004|03|31}}&lt;br/&gt;''GNOME 2.06''
|
* Support for Mozilla 1.7 and 1.8.
* Lockdown mode.
* Caret browsing.
|-
! 1.4
| {{dts|2004|09|15}}&lt;br/&gt;''GNOME 2.08''
|
* Offline mode.
* Per site [[popup|Pop-up ad]] blocking.
|-
! 1.6
| {{dts|2005|03|19}}&lt;br/&gt;''GNOME 2.10''
|
* Extensions manager.
|-
! 1.8
| {{dts|2005|9|5}}&lt;br /&gt;''GNOME 2.12''
|
* Python bindings.
* ''Find'' toolbar.
* [[Favicon]] and [[Secure Sockets Layer|SSL]] [[Computer icon|icons]] displayed in location bar.&lt;ref name=&quot;new-text-entry_devblog&quot; /&gt;
* Gecko 1.8 support.
* Error messages display in content area.
* Use of the standard GNOME printing system.
|-
! 2.14
| {{dts|2006|03|14}}
| 
* [[XULRunner]] backend supported.&lt;ref name=&quot;198_devblog&quot; /&gt;
* Topic suggestions in bookmarks manager.&lt;ref name=&quot;topics_devblog&quot; /&gt;
* Version numbering synced to [[GNOME]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pi-1&quot; /&gt;
* [[NetworkManager]] [[DBUS]] interface support.
|-
! 2.16
| {{dts|2006|09|25}}
|
* History preserved for links, opened in new tabs.&lt;ref name=&quot;ephy216_rn&quot; /&gt;
* Spell check support.
* Page security info dialogue from Certificates extension.
* New GTK+ Printing dialogs.
* Stability improvements.&lt;ref name=&quot;stabler-stable_devblog&quot; /&gt;
|-
! 2.18
| {{dts|2007|03|}}
|
* Bookmarks online storage.&lt;ref name=&quot;foresight_devblog&quot; /&gt;
* UI for Ad Blocker.
|-
! 2.20
| {{dts|2007|09|}}
| rowspan=4 |
* Migration from Gecko to WebKit.&lt;ref name=&quot;epiphany-loves-webkit&quot; /&gt;
* PDF printing.
* Migration from gnome-vfs to GIO.
|-
! 2.22
| {{dts|2008|03|12}}
|-
! 2.24
| {{dts|2008|09|}}
|-
! 2.26
| {{dts|2009|03|}}
|-
! 2.28
| {{dts|2009|09|}}
|
* Gecko backends removed.
* Support for the WebInspector.&lt;ref name=&quot;webinspector&quot; /&gt;
* Python support for extensions removed.
|-
! 2.30
| {{dts|2010|03|}}
|
* Broken SSL certificate warning.
* Custom page menus support.
|-
! 2.32
| {{dts|2010|09|}}
| ''Bugfixes only''.
|-
! 3.0
| {{dts|2011|03|}}
|
* Reduced the amount of [[user interface chrome]].
* Geolocation support.
* Switched from text zooming to full content zooming.
* New download manager.
* Migration to [[GTK+]] 3 and GNOME 3 technologies.
|-
! 3.2
| {{dts|2011|09|}}
|
* Separate font settings.
* WebKit's internal page source viewer made default.
* [[#Web Applications mode|Web Applications mode]].
|}

== Features ==
Epiphany is based on the [[WebKit]] web browser engine, which provides following features:
* Support for [[HTML]] 4 and [[XHTML]]&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-secsupport&quot; /&gt;
* Support for [[CSS]] 1 and 2&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-secsupport&quot; /&gt;
* Substantial degree of implementation of [[HTML5]] and CSS 3 features&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-secsupport&quot; /&gt;
* [[Web Inspector]] HTML and [[JavaScript]] debugging tool&lt;ref name=&quot;webinspector&quot; /&gt;
* [[Netscape Server Application Programming Interface|NSAPI]], including [[Adobe Flash]] and [[IcedTea|IcedTea (java)]] [[Plug-in (computing)|plug-ins]] support&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;

=== GNOME integration ===
Epiphany reuses GNOME frameworks and settings.&lt;ref name=&quot;linux-non-geeks_book&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora-10_book&quot; /&gt; Therefore its user interface theming is handled with GNOME default theme, the network settings with GNOME [[NetworkManager]] configuration, printing with GNOME printing system, settings with GSettings and GNOME default applications settings are used for [[internet media type]]s handling.

The built-in preference manager for Epiphany is designed to present user only basic browser-specific settings. All the advanced configuration is done with the stand-alone GSettings configurator tools such as GNOME's default '''dconf''' (command line) and '''dconf-editor''' (graphical).&lt;ref name=&quot;running-linux_book&quot; /&gt;

Epiphany follows the [[GNOME]] [[Human Interface Guidelines]].&lt;ref name=&quot;suse-unleashed_book&quot; /&gt;

=== Bookmarks ===
[[File:Epiphany bookmarks management.png|thumb|Bookmarks management and categorisation]]
While most browsers feature a hierarchical folder-based [[Internet bookmark|bookmark]] system, Epiphany uses categorized bookmarks, where a single bookmark (such as &quot;Epiphany&quot;) can exist in multiple categories (such as &quot;Web Browsers&quot;, &quot;GNOME&quot;, and &quot;Computer Software&quot;). Special categories include bookmarks that have been used frequently (&quot;Most Frequent&quot;) and bookmarks that have not yet been categorized. Another innovative concept supported by Epiphany (though originally from [[Galeon]]) is “[[smart bookmark]]s”. These take a single argument specified from the address bar or from a textbox in a toolbar.&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen01Jul10&quot; /&gt; Bookmarks along with browsing history are accessed from the address bar in find-as-you-type manner.

=== Web Applications mode ===
[[File:Wikipedia application launcher (Epiphany).png|thumb|left|Web application launcher]]
[[File:Wikipedia Web Application (Epiphany).png|thumb|right|Wikipedia as desktop application]]
Since GNOME 3.2&lt;ref name=&quot;gnome32_rn&quot;/&gt; Epiphany allows creating application launchers for [[web application]]s. The subsequent invocation of such launcher brings up an [[Site-specific browser|individual chromeless instance]] of Epiphany limited to the single domain, with the off-site links opening in a normal browser.&lt;ref name=&quot;web-application-mode_devblog&quot; /&gt; The launcher created this way is accessible from the desktop and is not limited to [[GNOME Shell]]. For instance it may be used with [[Unity (user interface)|Unity]], used on [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]].&lt;ref name=&quot;install-wam-ubuntu_3rd&quot; /&gt; This feature facilitates the integration of desktop and [[the Web]], which is a goal of the Epiphany developers.&lt;ref name=&quot;web-comes_devblog&quot; /&gt; Similar features can be found in the Windows version of [[Google Chrome]]. For the same purpose [[Mozilla Foundation]] previously developed a standalone application [[Mozilla Prism]], which was superseded by the project [[Chromeless]].&lt;ref name=&quot;mozilla-chromeless&quot; /&gt;

Currently the web applications are managed within Epiphany's main instance: the applications can be deleted from the page, accessible with a [[about URI scheme|special URI]] '''about:applications'''. This approach is considered a temporary solution until common GNOME-wide application management is implemented in GNOME 3.4.&lt;ref name=&quot;git_news&quot; /&gt;{{update after|2012|03|28|reason=GNOME 3.4 is supposed to have a generic solution for managing web applications}}

=== Modularity ===
Epiphany is extensible with a plugin system known as '''Epiphany extensions'''. The package of the same name is distributed by the developers of Epiphany, containing official extensions. Though it adds some useful features (see the table below), it is often criticized for being too limited, specifically compared to [[Add-on (Mozilla)|Firefox extensions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Train09Mar11&quot; /&gt;

Previously extensions could be written in either [[C (programming language)|C]] or [[Python (programming language)|Python]], but the Python support was dropped with WebKit adoption.&lt;ref name=&quot;gl-tp-ext&quot; /&gt;

Current list of Epiphany extensions include:&lt;ref name=&quot;git-ext&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gl-of-ext&quot; /&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Official Epiphany extensions
|-
! Actions
| Execute arbitrary commands from context menu
|-
! Ad Blocker
| [[Ad filtering]]
|-
! Auto Reload Tab
| Reload a tab periodically
|-
! Certificates
| View the page [[security certificate|certificate]] and manage the certificates
|-
! Gestures
| Perform actions with [[mouse gestures]]
|-
! Greasemonkey
| run [[Greasemonkey|user scripts]] to modify web pages' behavior
|-
! HTML5Tube
| View [[Youtube]] videos using [[HTML5 video|WebKit's HTML5 media player]]
|-
! News Feed Subscription
| Subscribe to a news feed offered by the webpage in your favorite news reader
|-
! Push Scroll
| Drag the page on middle mouse click
|-
! Soup Fly
| A tool to debug the SoupSession WebKit uses
|-
! Tab Key Tab Navigate
| Use the Tab key to navigate between tabs
|-
! Tab States
| Indicates new content in background tabs
|}

Several unofficial extensions exist, though most of them are not supported any more.&lt;ref name=&quot;gl-tp-ext&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;old-unofficial-ext&quot; /&gt;

== Reception ==

In reviewing the Webkit-powered Epiphany 2.28 in September 2009, [[Paul Ryan]] of [[Ars Technica]] said &quot;Epiphany is quite snappy in GNOME 2.28 and scores 100/100 on the [[Acid3]] test. Using WebKit will help differentiate Epiphany from Firefox, which is shipped as the default browser by most of the major Linux distributors.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_garden&quot; /&gt;

In reviewing Epiphany in July 2010 Jack Wallen described it as &quot;efficient, but different&quot; and noted its problem with crashes. &quot;When I first started working with Epiphany it crashed on most sites I visited. After doing a little research (and then a little debugging) I realized the issue was with javascript. Epiphany (in its current release), for some strange reason, doesn’t like javascript. The only way around this was to disable javascript. Yes this means a lot of features won’t work on a lot of sites – but this also means those same sites will load faster and won’t be so prone to having issues (like crashing my browser).&quot; Wallen concluded positively about the browser, &quot;Although Epiphany hasn’t fully replaced Chrome and Firefox as my one-stop-shop browser, I now use it much more than I would have previously. [It has a] small footprint, fast startup, and clean interface.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallen01Jul10&quot;&gt; {{Cite news|url = http://www.ghacks.net/2010/07/01/epiphany-an-efficient-but-different-web-browser/|title = Epiphany: An efficient, but different, web browser|accessdate = 24 March 2011|last = Wallen|first = Jack|authorlink = |year = 2010|month = July| work = Ghacks.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2011 Veronica Henry reviewed Epiphany, saying &quot;To be fair, this would be a hard sell as a primary desktop browser for most users. In fact, there isn’t even a setting to let you designate it as your default browser. But for those instance where you need to fire up a lighting-fast browser for quick surfing, Epiphany will do the trick.&quot; She further noted, &quot;Though I still use Firefox as my primary browser, lately it seems to run at a snail’s pace. So, one of the first things I noticed about Epiphany is how quickly it launches. And subsequent page loads on my system are equally as fast.&quot; Henry criticized Epiphany for its short list of extensions, singling out the lack of [[Firebug (web development)|Firebug]] as a deficiency.&lt;ref name=&quot;Train09Mar11&quot; /&gt; Epiphany does, however, support the Web Inspector offered by the Webkit engine, which has similar functionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Timothy |last=Hatcher |title=Introducing the Web Inspector|url=http://webkit.org/blog/41/introducing-the-web-inspector/|accessdate=2007-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Free software|Computer Science}}
* [[List of web browsers]]
* [[Comparison of web browsers]]
{{br}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;!-- Primary sources --&gt;

&lt;!--   Home sites --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;galeon-history_website&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://galeon.sourceforge.net/links/history.php
|title      = Galeon, A History or, why Galeon is the way it is
|last       = DeRosia
|first      = Chris
|date       = 2003-07-29
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;mozdev-home&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url         = http://epiphany.mozdev.org/
|title       = Epiphany's initial home page
|author      = Marco Pesenti Gritti
|date        = 2002-12-08
|archiveurl  = http://web.archive.org/web/20030424094846/http://epiphany.mozdev.org/
|archivedate = 2003-04-24
|accessdate  = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--   Release Process --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ephy216_rn&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url         = http://live.gnome.org/Epiphany/RelNotes216
|title       = Epiphany 2.16 Release Notes
|date        = 2008-03-02
|accessdate  = 2011-10-17
|publisher   = The GNOME Project
|archiveurl  = http://web.archive.org/web/20080908075132/http://live.gnome.org/Epiphany/RelNotes216
|archivedate = 2008-09-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gnome32_rn&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/3.2/#epiphany
|title      = GNOME 3.2 Release Notes
|first1     = Olav
|last1      = Vitters
|first2     = André
|last2      = Klapper
|first3     = Allan 
|last3      = Day
|publisher  = The GNOME Project
|date       = 2011-09-28
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gnome-rn&quot;&gt;{{citation
| url        = http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/
| title      = GNOME Release Notes
| publisher  = The GNOME Project
| accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;git_news&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://git.gnome.org/browse/epiphany/plain/NEWS
|title      = ''NEWS'' file
|publisher  = The GNOME Project's [[Git (software)|git repository]]
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gl-tp-ext&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = https://live.gnome.org/Epiphany/Extensions
|title      = Third Party Extensions for Epiphany 2.28 and later
|publisher  = The GNOME Project
|accessdate = 2011-11-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;git-ext&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://git.gnome.org/browse/epiphany-extensions/tree/extensions
|title      = Extensions tree
|publisher  = The GNOME Project's [[Git (software)|git repository]]
|accessdate = 2011-11-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gl-of-ext&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = https://live.gnome.org/Epiphany/Extensions
|title      = Official Epiphany Extensions
|publisher  = The GNOME Project
|accessdate = 2011-11-22
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;old-unofficial-ext&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.sstuhr.dk/epiphany-extensions/
|title      = Old Unofficial Epiphany Extensions (doesn't work with newer versions of Epiphany)
|first      = Stefan
|last       = Stuhr
|date       = 2008-05-10
|accessdate = 2011-11-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--   Development blogs --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;new-text-entry_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2005/08/03/new-text-entry-field-with-focus-indication-and-icons/
|title      = New text entry field with focus indication and icons
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2005-08-03
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;198_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2006/02/27/198-released-xulrunner/
|title      = 1.9.8 released; XULRunner
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2006-02-27
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;topics_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2006/01/22/topic-suggestions/
|title      = Topic suggestions
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2006-01-22
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pi-1&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2006/03/14/%cf%80-1/
|title      = π -1
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2006-03-14
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;stabler-stable_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2007/01/30/a-new-stabler-stable-release/
|title      = A new stabler stable release
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2007-01-30
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;foresight_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2007/03/04/foresight-and-epilicious/
|title      = Foresight and Epilicious
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2007-03-04
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;port-buddha&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/xan/2007/07/24/if-you-see-the-buddha-on-the-road-port-it-to-gtk/
|title      = If you see the Buddha on the road, port it to GTK+
|first      = Xan
|last       = Lopez
|date       = 2007-07-24
|accessdate = 2011-11-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-announcement&quot;&gt;{{cite mailing list
|url         = http://mail.gnome.org/archives/epiphany-list/2008-April/msg00000.html
|title       = ANNOUNCEMENT: The Future of Epiphany
|first       = Christian
|last        = Persch
|mailinglist = epiphany-list
|date        = 2008-04-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;epiphany-loves-webkit&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/xan/2008/04/06/epiphany-%e2%99%a5-webkit/
|title      = Epiphany ♥ WebKit
|first      = Xan
|last       = Lopez
|date       = 2008-04-06
|accessdate = 2011-11-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gecko-eol&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2009/07/01/gecko-end-of-life/
|title      = Gecko end-of-life
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2009-07-01
|accessdate = 2011-11-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;epiphany-turns-7&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/epiphany/2009/12/24/epiphany-turns-7/
|title      = Epiphany turns 7
|publisher  = The GNOME Web Browser Developers
|date       = 2009-12-24
|accessdate = 2011-06-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;web-comes_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/xan/2011/04/11/the-web-comes-to-gnome-ready-or-not/
|title      = The Web comes to GNOME, ready or not
|first      = Xan
|last       = Lopez
|date       = 2011-04-11
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;web-application-mode_devblog&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://blogs.gnome.org/xan/2011/08/31/web-application-mode-in-gnome-3-2/
|title      = Web application mode in GNOME 3.2
|first      = Xan
|last       = Lopez
|date       = 2011-08-31
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Third-party --&gt;

&lt;!--   Books --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dont-click_book&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url               = http://books.google.com/books?id=IGFPnJpa5cIC&amp;pg=PT216&amp;dq=epiphany+gnome&amp;cd=5#v=onepage&amp;q=epiphany%20gnome&amp;f=false
|first             = Scott
|last              = Granneman
|title             = Don't click on the blue e!: switching to Firefox
|publisher         = [[O'Reilly Media]]
|publication-date  = 2005
|publication-place = [[Sebastopol, CA]], [[USA]]
|isbn              = 0596009399
|page              = 201
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora-10_book&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url               = http://books.google.com/books?id=yZ7Z6Wq3EdcC&amp;pg=PA244&amp;dq=epiphany+gnome&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=epiphany%20gnome&amp;f=false
|first             = Richard
|last              = Peterson
|title             = Fedora 10 Linux Desktop
|publisher         = Surfing Turtle Press
|publication-date  = 2008
|publication-place = [[San Francisco]], [[USA]]
|isbn              = 0982099827
|page              = 224
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;linux-non-geeks_book&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url               = http://books.google.com/books?id=fTvN7BfU_WoC&amp;pg=PA116&amp;dq=epiphany+gnome&amp;lr=&amp;cd=23#v=onepage&amp;q=epiphany%20gnome&amp;f=false
|first             = Rickford
|last              = Grand
|title             = Linux for non-geeks: a hands-on, project-based, take-it-slow guidebook
|publisher         = [[No Starch Press]]
|publication-date  = 2004
|publication-place = [[San Francisco]], [[USA]]
|isbn              = 1593270348
|pages             = 116&amp;ndash;117
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;running-linux_book&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url               = http://books.google.com/books?id=9xrE5gokRQwC&amp;pg=PT112&amp;dq=epiphany+gnome&amp;lr=&amp;cd=22#v=onepage&amp;q=epiphany&amp;f=false
|first1            = Matthias Kalle
|last1             = Dalheimer
|first2            = Matt
|last2             = Welsh
|title             = Running Linux
|edition           = 5
|publisher         = [[O'Reilly Media]]
|publication-date  = 2006
|publication-place = [[Sebastopol, CA]], [[USA]]
|isbn              = 0596007604
|page              = 94
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;suse-unleashed_book&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url               = http://books.google.com/books?id=P_mbgQfn3ZAC&amp;pg=PA225&amp;dq=epiphany+gnome&amp;cd=8#v=onepage&amp;q=epiphany%20gnome&amp;f=false
|first             = Michael
|last              = McCallister
|title             = SUSE Linux 10 unleashed
|series            = Unleashed Series
|publisher         = [[Sams Publishing]]
|publication-date  = 2006
|publication-place = [[USA]]
|isbn              = 0672327260
|page              = 225
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;webkit-secsupport&quot;&gt;{{citation
|title      = SpecSupport
|url        = https://trac.webkit.org/wiki/SpecSupport
|publisher  = [[WebKit]] project
|accessdate = 2011-11-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--   Net news --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;footnotes_ephy-05&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://gnomedesktop.org/node/1047
|title      = Epiphany 0.5.0 released
|publisher  = [http://gnomedesktop.org/ FoorNotes]
|date       = 2003-04-13
|accessdate = 2011-10-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;mzine_ephy-08&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.mozillazine.org/talkback.html?article=3440
|title      = Epiphany 0.8.0 Released
|publisher  = [[mozillaZine]]
|date       = 2003-07-13
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;FSM&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/books/ubuntu_applications/epiphany
|title      = Epiphany, the ultimate Gnome browser|accessdate = 2008-11-07
|last       = Min
|first      = Andrew
|publisher  = [[Free Software Magazine]]
|work       = The Ubuntu Applications book (under construction)
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_look_214&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://arstechnica.com/open-source/news/2006/03/linux-20060328.ars/3
|title      = A look at GNOME 2.14
|authorlink = Paul Ryan
|first      = Paul
|last       = Ryan
|publisher  = [[Ars Technica]]
|date       = 2006-03-28
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ars_garden&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://arstechnica.com/open-source/news/2009/09/linux-garden-gets-a-new-gnome-with-version-228.ars
|title      = Linux garden gets a new GNOME with version 2.28
|authorlink = Paul Ryan
|first      = Paul
|last       = Ryan
|publisher  = [[Ars Technica]]
|date       = 2009-09-24
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--   Organisations --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;arch_default-browser&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.archlinux.org/groups/i686/gnome/
|title      = Group Details - gnome (i686)
|publisher  = [[Arch Linux]] website
|date       = dynamicly generated
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;canonical_default-browser&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.ubuntu.com/ubuntu/features/web-browsing
|title      = Web browsing
|publisher  = [[Canonical Ltd]]
|year       = 2011
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;fedora_default-browser&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/Fedora/15/html/Release_Notes/sect-Release_Notes-Changes_for_Desktop_Users.html#sect-RelNotes-Productivity
|title      = Release Notes for Fedora 15
|publisher  = The [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] Docs Team
|year       = 2011
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;freebsd_makefile&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.freebsd.org/cgi/cvsweb.cgi/ports/www/epiphany/Makefile
|title      = Epiphany Makefile in FreeBSD Ports
|publisher  = [[FreeBSD]]
|date       = dynamicly generated
|accessdate = 2011-10-21
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gentoo_default-browser&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://gentoo-portage.com/gnome-base/gnome/Dep#ptabs
|title      = Gentoo-Portage - gnome-base/gnome
|publisher  = [[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]]-Portage.com
|date       = dynamicly generated
|accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;suse_default-broswer&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://en.opensuse.org/Product_highlights
|title      = Product highlights
|publisher  = [[OpenSuSE]] project
|year       = 2011
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;webinspector&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.webkit.org/blog/197/web-inspector-redesign/
|title      = Web Inspector Redesign
|last       = Hatcher
|first      = Timothy
|publisher  = Webkit developers [[blog]]s
|date       = 2008-09-30
|accessdate = 2011-10-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;mozilla-chromeless&quot;&gt;{{citation
|title      = Prism is now Chromeless
|url        = https://mozillalabs.com/blog/2011/02/prism-is-now-chromeless/
|first      = Lloyd
|last       = Hilaiel
|publisher  = [[Mozilla Labs]]
|date       = 2011-02-11
|accessdate = 2011-11-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--   Blogs --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;install-wam-ubuntu_3rd&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.webupd8.org/2011/10/install-epiphany-320-with-web.html
|title      = Install Epiphany 3.2.0 with Web Application mode in Ubuntu 11.10 Oneiric Ocelot
|first      = Andrew
|date       = 2011-10-03
|accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Train09Mar11&quot;&gt;{{citation
|url        = http://www.trainsignaltraining.com/top-linux-browsers
|title      = Top 3 Alternative Linux Browsers
|accessdate = 24 March 2011
|last       = Henry
|first      = Veronica
|authorlink =
|year       = 2011
|month      = March
|work       = Train Signal Training
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Category:Epiphany (software)}}
*[http://projects.gnome.org/epiphany/ Epiphany Homepage]
*[http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gup/hig/ GNOME Human Interface Guidelines]

{{gopher clients}}
{{GNOME Software}}
{{Web browsers}}
{{Aggregators}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Epiphany (Web Browser)}}
[[Category:GNOME]]
[[Category:Gopher clients]]
[[Category:Mozilla]]
[[Category:POSIX web browsers]]
[[Category:Mac OS X web browsers]]
[[Category:Free web browsers]]
[[Category:Software based on Webkit]]
[[Category:2002 software]]
[[Category:Software forks]]

[[ar:إبفني]]
[[ast:Epiphany]]
[[ca:Epiphany]]
[[cs:Epiphany]]
[[de:Epiphany (Browser)]]
[[es:Epiphany]]
[[fa:اپیفانی (مرورگر وب)]]
[[fr:Epiphany]]
[[ko:에피파니]]
[[hi:एपिफेनी]]
[[it:Epiphany (browser)]]
[[he:Epiphany]]
[[csb:Epiphany]]
[[hu:Epiphany (böngésző)]]
[[nl:Epiphany (webbrowser)]]
[[ja:Epiphany]]
[[no:Epiphany]]
[[nn:Epiphany]]
[[pl:Epiphany]]
[[pt:Epiphany]]
[[ru:Epiphany]]
[[simple:Epiphany]]
[[sk:Epiphany]]
[[fi:Epiphany]]
[[sv:Epiphany (webbläsare)]]
[[th:Epiphany]]
[[uk:Epiphany]]
[[zh:Epiphany]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
