<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2243617" ns="0" title="Hot Coffee mod"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:''Hot Coffee'' mod}}
&lt;!-- {{Redirect6|Hot Coffee|the beverage|coffee|the lawsuit over a hot coffee burn|Liebeck v. McDonald's Restaurants}} --&gt;
{{Infobox VG
| title          = Hot Coffee mod
| italic title   = no
| image          = [[File:Hot coffee.png|220px]]
| caption        = A screenshot of the ''GTA: San Andreas'' with the Hot Coffee mod
| aspect ratio   =
| resolution     =
| developer      = [[Rockstar Games]]
| publisher      = Patrick Wildenborg
| distributor    =
| designer       = [[Rockstar Games]]
| license        =
| series         = ''[[Grand Theft Auto (series)|Grand Theft Auto]]''
| engine         =
| version        =
| released       = See [[Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas]]
| genre          =
| modes          =
| ratings        = [[ESRB]]: AO&lt;br/&gt;[[PEGI]] 18+&lt;br/&gt;[[OFLC]] RC
| platforms      = [[Microsoft Windows]]
| media          = Download
| requirements   =
| input          =
}}

The '''''Hot Coffee'' mod''' is a normally inaccessible [[minigame]] in the 2004 [[video game]] ''[[Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas]]'', developed by [[Rockstar North]]. Public awareness of the existence of the minigame arrived with the release of the ''Hot Coffee'' [[Mod (computer gaming)|mod]], created for the version released in 2005 for [[Microsoft Windows]]. This mod enables access to the minigame. 

The minigame portrays [[sexual intercourse]] between the main character, [[Carl &quot;CJ&quot; Johnson]], and his in-game [[girlfriend]]. The name of the mod is derived from the girlfriend's offer for the main character to come into her home for &quot;[[coffee]]&quot;—a [[euphemism]] for sex.

Although the &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; minigame was completely disabled and its existence was only highlighted after the mod's release for the PC version on June 9, 2005,&lt;ref name=ModRelease&gt;{{cite web | url = http://patrickw.gtagames.nl/mods.html | title = Hot Coffee mod developer's mod listing | work = PatrickW's modding website | accessdate = July 5, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; the assets for the minigame were also discovered in both the [[PlayStation 2]] and [[Xbox]] versions of the game, and people found ways to enable the minigame via console video game hacking tools. By the middle of July 2005, the minigame's discovery attracted considerable [[Video game controversy|controversy]] from lawmakers and politicians, prompting the game to be [[Video game content rating system|re-rated]] as an [[Adult video games|adult game]], and pulled from some shelves. An updated version of ''San Andreas'' has since been released with the minigame removed completely, allowing the game to regain its original rating. A [[Patch (computing)|patch]] for the original version of the game, which disables the minigame and crashes the game if one attempts to access it, has also been released.&lt;ref name=nomoarcoffee&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nomorehotcoffee.com/ | title = No More Hot Coffee | work = [[Rockstar Games]] | accessdate =  2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, a more advanced hack still gives access to this minigame, even on the updated version.

== Minigame overview and Hot Coffee mod ==
{{Inappropriate tone|date=November 2008}}
During the course of the main plot of the game, the player (as main character [[Carl &quot;CJ&quot; Johnson]]) may date up to six [[girlfriend]]s, carrying out various &quot;date missions&quot; in order to improve his relationship with a particular girl. Once Carl has become particularly close to a girlfriend, she may end a successful date by inviting him into her house for &quot;coffee,&quot; from which Carl may choose to accept or decline. Improving relationships with girlfriends through successful dates and other related activities will eventually reward CJ with new items (vehicles and special wardrobes), along with pre-existing gameplay benefits (e.g. dating a nurse grants the character free visits to the hospital, without losing his weapons, after dying).

In the unmodified version of ''San Andreas'', the player sees an exterior view of the girlfriend's house while hearing the muffled voices of Carl and his girlfriend as they engage in sexual intercourse. However, the ''Hot Coffee'' modification replaces this with a minigame which allows the player to actually enter the girlfriend's bedroom and control Carl's actions during sex. None of the six possible sex scenes involve any [[nudity]] (except when  using the unrelated &quot;Nude Girlfriends&quot; mod), and there are animation problems with the girlfriends' partly clothed [[texture mapping|textures]] and bedrooms.

[[Rockstar Games]], the publisher of the ''[[Grand Theft Auto (series)|Grand Theft Auto]]'' series, initially denied allegations that the minigame was &quot;hidden&quot; in the video game, stating that the ''Hot Coffee'' modification (which they claim violated the game's [[software license|End User Licence Agreement]]) is the result of &quot;[[Hacker (computer security)|hackers]]&quot; making &quot;significant technical modifications to and [[reverse engineering]]&quot; the game's code.&lt;ref name=baertlein&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.yahoo.com/news?tmpl=story&amp;u=/nm/20050714/us_nm/media_grandtheftauto_dc_2 | title = 'Grand Theft' maker blames hackers for sex scenes | work = [[Reuters]] | accessdate =  13 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, this claim was undermined when a hacker known as N.A.V.A.I.D G, on July 12, 2005, released an &quot;[[Action Replay]] Power Save&quot; for the Xbox console, and codes for the PlayStation 2 [[Action Replay]] game enhancer that allowed the scenes to be accessed in each of the console versions. These new methods of accessing &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; demonstrated that the controversial content was, indeed, built into the console versions as well.

The PC mod itself is actually just an edited copy of the game script files with a single [[bit]] changed. The mod was also made possible on the console versions, by changing the bit inside a user's saved game file or by using a third-party modding device. Take-Two has stated that the mod constitutes a violation of the End User License Agreement,&lt;ref&gt;[http://ir.take2games.com/ReleaseDetail.cfm?ReleaseID=169278 Take-Two Games - Investor Relations General Information&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; even though modification of the main.scm file is common within the mod community.

The oral sex animations are however clearly visible in the background of an early mission, &quot;Cleaning the Hood&quot;, even in the re-released game.&lt;ref name=&quot;Norway&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://pub.tv2.no/nettavisen/it/article432538.ece | title = Norwegian article proving the sex animations are used in the game | work = Nettavisen | accessdate =  14 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; This may explain why the mini-game was not simply removed when the decision was made to cut it from the game: its assets were in use elsewhere.&lt;ref name=&quot;romblog&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.romsteady.net/blog/2005/07/my-take-on-hot-coffee.html | title = My Take On &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; | work = Rom's Rants | accessdate =  14 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversy ==
The revelation of the minigame sparked a fair amount of controversy around ''GTA:SA'', with some politicians firing harsh words at both the game's developer and the [[Entertainment Software Rating Board]] (ESRB), the organization which establishes content ratings for video games in North America. It has also rekindled the debate over the influence of video games in general with new protests against several other games such as ''[[Killer7]]'', ''[[The Sims 2]]'', and ''[[Bully (video game)|Bully]]''.

[[Jack Thompson (attorney)|Jack Thompson]] was one of the first to criticize the game for its hidden content, believing violent media is one of the main causes of violent crime in America. Thompson lashed out against [[Rockstar Games]] on several occasions for previous games they have developed.

[[United States Senate|U.S. Senator]] [[Hillary Rodham Clinton|Hillary Clinton]] jumped into the fray by suggesting new regulations be put on video games sales.&lt;ref name=&quot;feldman&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamespot.com/news/2005/07/14/news_6129040.html | title = Clinton calls for federal game regulation | work = [[GameSpot]] | accessdate =  14 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ESRB is also conducting an investigation into whether the game's publisher lied about the game's content in an attempt to avoid the '''Adults Only 18+''' rating. Also, Congress passed a resolution to have the [[Federal Trade Commission]] investigate whether Rockstar intentionally undermined the ESRB by having the content in the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;feldman2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamespot.com/ps2/action/gta4/news_6129836.html | title = Take-Two sued, confirms FTC investigation | work = [[GameSpot]] | accessdate =  27 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In New York, a [[class action lawsuit]] was filed by Florence Cohen, an 85-year-old grandmother who purchased the game for her 14-year-old grandson (according to the old rating of M, the game is typically considered inappropriate for this age). Cohen's lawsuit claimed that Rockstar Games and [[Take-Two Interactive]], the publisher of the game, are guilty of [[deception]], [[false advertising]], [[fraud]] and [[abuse]].  The accusation of deception is based on the change from M-rated to AO, meaning according to the lawsuit that the original rating was a deceptive practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;berardini&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.teamxbox.com/xbox/8839/Grandma-Sues-Rockstar-Over-San-Andreas/ | title = Grandma Sues Rockstar Over San Andreas | work = [[TeamXbox]] | accessdate =  27 July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A protest group known as the Peaceholics organized a protest on August 4, 2005 at Rockstar's headquarters. The group demonstrated against ''San Andreas'' as well as the upcoming game ''[[Bully (video game)|Bully]]'', the latter due to fears that the content could inspire children to become bullies themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;ransom&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.joystiq.com/entry/1234000070053157/ | title = March against Bully | work = [[Joystiq]] | accessdate = 4 August 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;crecente&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://kotaku.com/gaming/rockstar/group-releases-rockstar-demands-115751.php | title = Group Releases Rockstar Demands | work = [[Joystiq]] | accessdate =  4 August 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Response ==
=== Product re-rating ===
On July 20, 2005, the [[ESRB]] announced that it was changing the rating of ''GTA:SA'' from '''Mature''' (M) to '''Adults Only 18+''' (AO).&lt;ref name=&quot;RerateToAORating&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamespot.com/news/6129500.html | title = San Andreas rated AO, Take-Two suspends production | work = [[GameSpot]] | accessdate = July 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rockstar stated that it would discontinue manufacturing the current version of the game, and produce a new version that would not include the content that is unlocked by the Hot Coffee mod. In the fourth quarter of 2005, Rockstar released this &quot;clean&quot; version with the &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; scenes removed (''Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas'' 1.01), allowing the game to be rerated to a '''Mature 17+''' rating.&lt;ref name=&quot;RevertToMRating&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamespot.com/news/6152490.html | title = FTC Hot Coffee ruling scalds, but doesn't burn Take-Two | work = [[GameSpot]] | accessdate = July 1, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 29, 2005, as a result of the newly-discovered scenes, the [[Office of Film and Literature Classification (Australia)|OFLC]] revoked the game's &quot;MA15+&quot; classification (the highest currently available for computer games in Australia), and changed the game's status to &quot;RC&quot; (Refused Classification) meaning that the original version could no longer be sold in Australia. The patched version was given an &quot;MA15+&quot; classification on September 12, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oflc.gov.au/special.html?n=46&amp;p=156&amp;sTitle=San+Andreas&amp;sMediaFilm=1&amp;sMediaPublications=1&amp;sMediaGames=1&amp;sDateFromM=1&amp;sDateFromY=1970&amp;sDateToM=7&amp;sDateToY=2006&amp;record=207350 The Classification Board and Classification Review Board&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 10, 2005, Rockstar Games officially released a patch for ''San Andreas''.&lt;ref name=&quot;coldcoffee&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.nomorehotcoffee.com/ | title = No More Hot Coffee | work = [[Rockstar Games]] patch website | accessdate = 14 June 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nicknamed the &quot;Cold Coffee Patch&quot; by some,{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} the patch fixed many performance issues and bugs. However, the patch also disabled the controversial &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; scenes, even if the &quot;Hot Coffee&quot; mod was reinstalled.

There was little reaction in [[Europe]]. The game was already classified as [[Pan European Game Information|PEGI 18+]] prior to the release of the mod. Furthermore, unlike the United States, many European nations operate the same regime for video games as they do to films, thus it is a criminal offense to sell adult-only games to minors. For example, the UK version of ''GTA:SA'' as with all previous incarnations of the series all the way back to the original [[Grand Theft Auto (video game)|GTA]], was rated as 18 by the [[BBFC]]. There may also be more general cultural factors in the differing responses to the incident.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Similarly, news of the mod did not make any impact at all in Japan, where the game was released by [[Capcom]].

=== Product withdrawal and recall ===
The day after the rating change, several [[North America]]n chain stores, and [[Interactive Entertainment Merchants Association|IEMA]] retailers, which accounted for every major retailer in the [[United States]] and approximately 85% of the game's market in the country, removed the PC and console versions of the game from their store shelves, either restickering the box with the new rating, or returning it to Take-Two Interactive. These included major chains such as [[GameStop]], [[Sears Holdings Corporation|Sears]], [[Hudson's Bay Company]], [[Zellers]], [[Hollywood Video]], [[Blockbuster (movie rental store)|Blockbuster]], [[Wal-Mart]], [[Target Corporation|Target]], [[Best Buy]], and [[Electronics Boutique]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} Rockstar gave some retailers ESRB &quot;Adults Only&quot; rating stickers to put on their copies of ''GTA:SA'', should they decide to keep selling the original product.

[[eBay]] removed copies of ''GTA:SA'' that had been reported by the eBay community. eBay claimed that ''GTA:SA'' violated the terms of the eBay seller policy and could not be sold unless it was located in the ''Everything Else &gt; Mature Audiences'' section. This section requires a credit card to validate the age of the eBay user. {{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

On August 24, 2005, Rockstar announced a mandatory [[Product recall|recall]] for all games still owned by the general public.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} Consumers who had already purchased the game were allowed to keep it in certain areas, but with the patch installed, although players cannot be forced to return (or destroy) existing copies. Given the higher value of the &quot;uncensored&quot; versions, it is doubtful that many gamers will return their copies voluntarily.  However, those who were over 18 (or 21 depending on region) have [[grandfather clause|grandfathered]] these copies of the game to their collection.

Version 2.0 of ''GTA:SA'', which omitted the sexual minigame content, was designed by Rockstar to crash if the game data files were modified. This made it necessary for players to use a previous version if they wished to install multiplayer game [[Mod (computer gaming)|modification]]s such as ''San Andreas Multiplayer'' or ''[[Multi Theft Auto]]'' and other game modifications that include new scripts or vehicles. Certain [[Copyright infringement of software|pirated or illegally distributed]] versions of the original game may also be made available on the Internet or from illegal retail outlets. Downgraders are also available to unpatch and revert the game version and support the Hot Coffee minigame again.

This limitation later was overcome &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = GTA modding |url=http://www.gtamodding.com/index.php?title=San_Andreas_v2.0_Modding |accessdate=2010-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; by two members of the unofficial ''Grand Theft Auto'' modding community, who discovered a method of creating modifications which would work with version 2.0. Users of version 2.0 might still need to use previous versions or use a downgrader in order to install a mod not created with the new method.

===Federal and legal action===
In December 2005, Senators [[Hillary Rodham Clinton|Hillary Clinton]], [[Joe Lieberman]] and [[Evan Bayh]] introduced the [[Family Entertainment Protection Act]], which called for a federal mandate enforcement of the ESRB ratings system in order to protect children from inappropriate content.

On January 26, 2006, the city of [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] filed a lawsuit against [[Take-Two Interactive]], the game's publisher, accusing the company of failing to disclose the game's sexual content.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

Rockstar has allegedly vowed legal action against any subsequent sources that reveal how to access this part of the game, mainly cheat device code sites.{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}}

On June 8, 2006, Rockstar, Take-Two and the [[Federal Trade Commission|FTC]] settled. They are required to &quot;clearly and prominently disclose on product packaging and in any promotion or advertisement for electronic games, content relevant to the rating, unless that content had been disclosed sufficiently in prior submissions to the rating authority.&quot; Should the companies violate the settlement they are liable for $11,000 in [[civil penalty|civil penalties]].&lt;ref name=&quot;settlement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Adams |first= David |authorlink= |coauthors= | date=2006-06-08 |month=June |url=http://ps2.ign.com/articles/711/711788p1.html |title=Rockstar, FTC Settle Over Hot Coffee |work= |pages= |publisher=[[IGN]] | language= |accessdate=2006-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Civil class actions ===
In 2006 attorneys brought several [[class action]]s alleging Take-Two committed consumer [[fraud]]. In December 2007, a settlement of the litigation was reached.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gtasettlement.com/|title=GTA Settlement|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071224175535/http://www.gtasettlement.com/|archivedate=Dec 24, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, [[Ted Frank]] filed an objection to the settlement on the grounds that the settlement sought $1 million for [[attorney's fee|attorneys' fees]], but the total payout to class members was less than $27,000.&lt;ref name=527GP&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamepolitics.com/2008/05/27/did-lawyers-inflate-fees-hot-coffee-class-action-suit|publisher=[[Gamepolitics.com]]|title=Did Lawyers Inflate Fees in Hot Coffee Class Action Suit?|date=2008-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Over&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://overlawyered.com/2008/05/grand-theft-auto-class-action-settlement-26505-for-the-unrepresented-class-1-million-fee-request/
|publisher=[[Overlawyered]]
|title=Grand Theft Auto: Class Action Settlement - $26,505 for the unrepresented class, $1 million fee request
|date=2008-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; A court hearing was already scheduled on June 25, 2008.  Frank previously told GamePolitics that the lawsuits were meritless and extortionate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.gamepolitics.com/2008/04/29/overlawyered-blog-doesnt-think-much-of-hot-coffee-class-action-settlement
|publisher=[[Gamepolitics.com]]
|title=Overlawyered Disses Hot Coffee Class Action Settlement
|date=2008-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As part of the settlement, Take-Two will pay a $873,000 [[Cy-près doctrine|cy-près]] award to the National [[Parent-Teacher Association]] and the ESRB.&lt;ref name=527GP/&gt;&lt;ref name=Over/&gt;

As of June 25, 2008, less than 2,700 claimants responded to the settlement, for which the plaintiff's attorneys expressed disappointment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gamesindustry.biz/articles/lawyers-shocked-at-lack-of-hot-coffee-claimants |title=Lawyers shocked at lack of Hot Coffee claimants |accessdate=2008-06-26 |author=Matt Martin |date=2008-06-25 |publisher=[[gamesindustry.biz]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frank expressed that this was further proof that the case had no merit.

As of September 1, 2009, Take Two agreed to settle a securities class action suit related to the controversy over the game and over backdating allegations for just over $20 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS220177+01-Sep-2009+BW20090901 |title=Take-Two Interactive Software, Inc. Announces Settlement of Securities Class Action |accessdate=2009-09-01 |date=2009-09-01 |publisher=Thomson Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{wikinews|Video game's secret sex scenes spark outrage}}
{{wikinews|Stores drop game &quot;Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas&quot; after given 'Adults Only' rating}}
{{wikinews|Grand Theft Auto under fire}}
* [http://patrickw.gtagames.nl/ PatrickW's Website (creator of original mod) ]
* [http://www.ps2savetools.com PS2 Save Tools (home to GTA:SA Censor Remover) ]
* [http://www.grandtheftwiki.com/Hot_Coffee_Modification Hot Coffee Modification] on [http://www.grandtheftwiki.com Grand Theft Wiki]
* [[StrategyWiki:Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas/Hot Coffee#Accessing the mod|''GTA: San Andreas'' Hot Coffee guide]] at [[StrategyWiki:Main Page|StrategyWiki]]
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/11/technology/11game.htm? New York Times article about Hot Coffee Mod controversy]
* [http://www.igniq.com/2005/07/gta-hot-coffee-also-confirmed-on-ps2.html Igniq.com article on the code's existence in the PS2 version]
* [http://pc.ign.com/articles/635/635277p1.html IGN: Rockstar Responds to GTA: SA's AO Rating]
* [http://www.nomorehotcoffee.com Rockstar's anti Hot Coffee game patch]

{{Video game controversy}}
{{Grand Theft Auto}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hot Coffee Minigame Controversy}}
[[Category:Sex scandals]]
[[Category:Video game mods]]
[[Category:Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas]]
[[Category:Obscenity controversies]]
[[Category:Self-censorship]]
[[Category:Criticisms of software and websites]]

[[fr:Hot Coffee]]
[[ia:Hot Coffee]]
[[ja:ホットコーヒー問題]]
[[pl:Hot Coffee]]
[[pt:Hot Coffee]]
[[fi:Hot Coffee]]
[[uk:Hot Coffee (мод)]]
[[zh:熱咖啡]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
