<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22506" ns="0" title="Oberlin College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|41.292929|N|82.218576|W|type:edu|display=title}}
{{Infobox university
|name=Oberlin College
|motto = Learning and Labor
|mascot=[[Yeomen|Yeomen (men's teams) &amp; Yeowomen (women's teams)]]
|established=September 2, 1833
|type=[[Private university|Private]]
|president=[[Marvin Krislov]]
|enrollment=2,800 &lt;ref&gt;url=http://new.oberlin.edu/about/fast-facts.dot | title=Fast Facts | accessdate = April 29, 2011 &lt;/ref&gt;
|staff=1,058
|endowment= $633 million USD&lt;ref&gt;As of March 31, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = March 15, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|city=[[Oberlin, Ohio|Oberlin]]
|state=[[Ohio]]
|country=United States
|campus=[[town|small town]]
|website=[http://new.oberlin.edu/ new.oberlin.edu]
|image=[[Image:Oberlin College Seal.png|Oberlin College seal]]
}}

'''Oberlin College''' is a  private [[liberal arts]] college in [[Oberlin, Ohio]], noteworthy for having been the first American institution of higher learning to regularly admit female and black students.  Connected to the college is the [[Oberlin Conservatory of Music]], the oldest continuously operating conservatory in the country.  The college's motto is &quot;Learning and Labor.&quot;  Oberlin is known for having more alumni who earn PhDs than any other liberal arts college in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;http://oberlin.edu/instres/irhome/assessment/phd.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Oberlin is a member of the [[Great Lakes Colleges Association]] and the [[Five Colleges of Ohio]] consortium.

==History==
[[Image:OberlinArchSmall.jpg|200px|right|thumb|The Oberlin campus in 1909]]
Both the college and the town of Oberlin were founded in 1833 by a pair of [[Presbyterian]] ministers, [[John Jay Shipherd]] and [[Philo P. Stewart]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cityofoberlin.com/Administration/community.html Cityofoberlin.com]&lt;/ref&gt; The ministers named their project after [[J. F. Oberlin|Jean-Frédéric Oberlin]], an [[Alsace|Alsatian]] minister whom they both admired. Oberlin attained prominence because of the influence of its second president, the evangelist [[Charles Finney]], after whom one of the College's chapels and performance spaces is named. [[Asa Mahan]] (1800–1889) served as Oberlin's first president from 1835–1850.

Oberlin Collegiate Institute (as it was originally called) was built on {{convert|500|acre|km2}} of land specifically donated by the previous owner, who lived in [[Connecticut]]. Shipherd and Stewart's vision was for both a religious community and school. For a more detailed history of the founding of the town and the college, see [[Oberlin, Ohio]].

Oberlin has long been associated with progressive causes. Its founders bragged that &quot;Oberlin is peculiar in that which is good.&quot; Oberlin was the first college in the United States to regularly admit African-American students (1835) after a casting vote by the Rev. [[John Keep]]. It is also the oldest continuously operating [[coeducation]]al institution, since having [[List of mixed-sex colleges and universities in the United States|admitted four women in 1837]]. These four women, who were the first to enter as full students, were [[Mary Kellogg]] (Fairchild), [[Mary Caroline Rudd]], [[Mary Hosford]], and [[Elizabeth Prall]]. All but Kellogg graduated. [[Mary Jane Patterson]] graduated in 1862 to become the first black woman to earn a B.A. degree. The college was listed as a [[National Historic Landmark]] on December 21, 1965, for its significance in admitting African-Americans and women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=450&amp;ResourceType=Site|title=National Historic Landmarks Program - Oberlin College|work=|accessdate=8 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college had some difficult beginnings, and Keep and [[William Dawes (abolitionist)|William Dawes]] were sent to England to raise funds for the college in 1839–40.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=SG-g_52iY6gC&amp;pg=PA192&amp;lpg=PA192&amp;dq=%22William+Dawes%22+slavery&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5a8Q7IO3TO&amp;sig=e043LSF-W5JKeENqAHuN6U-IbAU&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=G_vdSZbnNp-ZjAfzp9GNDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8#PPA192,M1 The culture of English antislavery, 1780-1860], David Turley, p192, 1991, ISBN 0-415-02008-5, accessed April 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

One historian called Oberlin &quot;the town that started the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]&quot; due to its reputation as a hotbed of [[abolitionism]].&lt;ref&gt;Brandt, Nat (1990). ''The town that started the Civil War''. Syracuse University Press. ISBN 0-8156-0243-X.&lt;/ref&gt; Oberlin was a key stop along the [[Underground Railroad]]. In 1858, both students and faculty were involved in the controversial [[Oberlin-Wellington Rescue]] of a fugitive slave, which received national press coverage. Two participants in this raid, [[Lewis Sheridan Leary]] and [[John Anthony Copeland]], along with another Oberlin resident, [[Shields Green]], also participated in [[John Brown's Raid on Harpers Ferry]].  This heritage was commemorated on campus by the 1977 installation of sculptor [[Cameron Armstrong]]'s &quot;Underground Railroad Monument&quot; (a railroad track rising from the ground toward the sky)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sculpturecenter.org/oosi/sculpture.asp?SID=44 Underground Railroad Monument]&lt;/ref&gt; and monuments to the Oberlin-Wellington Rescue&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/external/EOG/CivilWarTour/Stop5.html Oberlin-Wellington Rescue Monument]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Harper's Ferry Raid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/external/EOG/CivilWarTour/Stop4.html Harper's Ferry Memorial]&lt;/ref&gt;

Oberlin's school colors are cardinal red and [[mikado yellow]], often casually referred to as &quot;crimson and gold.&quot;  Those colors were formally designated for the college by a faculty committee in 1889 and were drawn from the family coat of arms of [[John Frederick Oberlin]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/giving/of_recognition.html Oberlin College]&lt;/ref&gt; They remain in the official registry of school colors maintained by the [[American Council on Education]].

===Presidents of Oberlin College===
* [[Asa Mahan]] 1835-1850
* [[Charles Grandison Finney]] 1851-1866
* [[James Harris Fairchild]] 1866-1889
* [[William Gay Ballantine]] 1891-1896
* [[John Barrows]] 1899-1902
* [[Henry Churchill King]] 1902-1927
* [[Ernest H. Wilkins]] 1927-1946
* [[William Edwards Stevenson]] 1946-1960
* [[Robert K. Carr]] 1960-1969
* [[Robert W. Fuller]] 1970-1974
* [[Emil Danenberg]] 1975-1982
* [[S. Frederick Starr]] 1983-1994
* [[Nancy Dye]] 1994-2007
* [[Marvin Krislov]] 2007–present

===Introduction of co-ed dormitories===
In 1970, Oberlin made the cover of ''[[Life (magazine)|Life]]'' as one of the first colleges in the country to have co-ed dormitories.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.oberlin.edu/175/didyouknow-coed.html College web site]&lt;/ref&gt;  The article featured two students who lived in South Hall. At first, the dorm was floor-by-floor co-ed, which was considered quite radical. Dean of Women Rose Montague and the two senior residents in the dorm at the time were guests on a Chicago TV station morning talk show soon after ''Life'''s article came out, to talk about the &quot;experiment&quot;. The program, &quot;Kennedy and Company,&quot; sought to reveal the &quot;darker&quot; side of co-ed dorm life from parents' perspective. The male senior resident (Lloyd Blanchard) was asked on live TV if he had &quot;ever had sex in the dorm,&quot; to which he replied, &quot;That's really none of your business.&quot; Starting in the 2010-11 school year, except for women-only halls, Baldwin Cottage for Women, and one safe space housing option for women and transgender students, Oberlin students were allowed to room with students of any gender in any room on campus. &lt;ref&gt;[http://new.oberlin.edu/office/housing/housing-options/gender-policies/]&lt;/ref&gt;

Historian [[Geoffrey Blodgett]], a professor and graduate of Oberlin, pointed out that campus dorms caused anger among students during the 1960s. Students reacted vocally against the new dorms of the 1950s and 1960s (Dascomb, East, North and South), calling them expedient &quot;slabs&quot; of &quot;sleeping and feeding space,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Geoffrey Blodgett|Blodgett, Geoffrey]] (May 11, 1995). &quot;The Grand March of Oberlin campus plans&quot;. ''Oberlin Observer''. Vol. 16 No. 17 Sec. Observations. (web archive: [http://www.oberlin.edu/observer/observer16.17/observations.html Oberlin.edu])&lt;/ref&gt; and this protest soon took on other controversies, including the [[Civil Rights Movement]] and the [[Vietnam War]]. Hebrew House, as it was known, was set up as winter term project to operate similar to an [[Israel]]i ''[[kibbutz]].'' The experiment was a success, and now all but one of Oberlin College's dormitories are coed. The Baldwin Cottage is open only to women and [[transgender]] students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://new.oberlin.edu/student-life/housing/housing-options/detail.dot?id=184702&amp;buildingId=175104 College web site]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
Of Oberlin's nearly 3,000 students, nearly 2,400 are enrolled in the College of Arts &amp; Sciences, a little over 400 in the [[Oberlin Conservatory of Music|Conservatory of Music]], and the remaining 180 or so in both College and Conservatory under the five-year Double Degree program. 

===College of Arts &amp; Sciences===
[[Image:Peters Hall Oberlin.JPG|thumb|right|300px|Peters Hall, home of the language departments.]]
The College of Arts &amp; Sciences offers over 45 majors, minors and concentrations. Based on students graduating with a given major, its most popular majors over the last ten years have been (in order) English, Biology, History, Politics and Environmental Studies. The College's science programs are considered strong for a smaller liberal arts college, especially [[Chemistry]] and [[Neuroscience]].

===Conservatory of Music===
[[Image:Oberlin music2.jpg|thumb|right|Conservatory of Music at Oberlin College]]
The [[Oberlin Conservatory of Music|Conservatory]] is located on the college campus. Conservatory admission is rigorous, with over 1400 applicants worldwide auditioning for 120 seats. Students benefit from over 500 performances yearly, most free of charge, with concerts and recitals almost daily. The Conservatory was one of the recipients of the 2009 [[National Medal of Arts]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nea.gov/news/news10/Medals/oberlin.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allen Memorial Art Museum===
The [[Allen Memorial Art Museum]], with over 12,000 holdings, was the first college art museum west of the Alleghenies and is held on par with those at Princeton, Harvard, and Yale.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/colrelat/welcome/octour/stourart.html Short Tour: Allen Art Museum&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===College Library===
[[Oberlin College Library]] system is one of the largest and finest undergraduate libraries in the nation.  In addition to the main library there are branch libraries for art, music, and science, and a central storage facility.  The libraries have strong collections of print and media materials and provide access to an extensive array of online databases and journals.  Beyond the 2.4 million-plus items available on campus, Oberlin students have rapid access to more than 46 million volumes from over 85 Ohio institutions in through the [[OhioLINK]] consortium.&lt;ref&gt;[http://new.oberlin.edu/arts-and-sciences/libraries/ Oberlin College Library&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;   In addition to the breadth of its holdings, the Oberlin College Library is recognized for its quality: it received the Association of College and Research Libraries Excellence in Academic Libraries Award in 2002,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/acrl/awards/excellenceacademic.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; and in 2006 Director of Libraries Ray English was named the [[Association of College and Research Libraries|ACRL]]'s Academic-Research Librarian of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ala.org/ala/mgrps/divs/acrl/awards/librarianoftheyear/englishspeech.cfm&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 2007 the main level of the main library was converted into an Academic Commons that provides integrated learning support and is a hub of both academic and social activity.

===OhioLINK consortium===
Oberlin students and faculty benefit by Oberlin's membership in the [[OhioLINK]] consortium, providing access to 12,000+ commercially licensed online journals, 130 databases, 18,000+ ebooks and is rapidly growing digital media collections. The OhioLINK Central Catalog represents the library holdings of 87 libraries in the state, including the State Library of Ohio, plus the Center for Research Libraries. The collection is nearing 10 million unique records representing 27.5 million holdings in the system, and undergraduates account for the larger percentage of OhioLINK online borrowing – the process by which any enrolled student can readily request the loan of books and other items from any other library in the system.

===Experimental College===
The college's &quot;Experimental College&quot; or ExCo program, a student-run department, allows any student or interested person to teach their own class for a limited amount of college credit. ExCo classes by definition focus on material not covered by existing departments or faculty.

Many courses supplement conventional disciplines, from [[languages]] and areas of [[Film|cinema]] or [[literature]], to musical ensembles, [[martial arts]] and forms of dancing.  Other ExCos cover an array of topics, in the past ranging from Aquariums&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/exco/students/oldcourses/fall02.htm Fall 2002 Exco course listing]&lt;/ref&gt; to Wilderness Skills&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/exco/students/oldcourses/spring03.htm Spring 2003 Exco course listing]&lt;/ref&gt; to Hacky Sack to philosophical discussions of Calvin and Hobbes.  Due to the nature of ExCo, while some staple courses are continued for years, the overall number and selection of classes offered varies dramatically from semester to semester.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/exco/about/history.htm EXCO Committee]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Winter Term===
Another aspect of Oberlin's academics is the Winter Term during the month of January. This term was created to allow students to do something outside the regular course offerings of the college. Students may work alone or in groups, either on or off campus, and may design their own project or pick from a list of projects and internships set up by the college each year. Students must complete a winter term project three years out of their four in the College of Arts and Sciences. Projects range from serious academic research with co-authorship in scientific journals, to humanitarian projects, to making avant-garde films about historic Chicago neighborhoods, to learning how to bartend. A full-credit project is suggested to involve five to six hours per weekday.&lt;ref&gt;[http://oberlin.edu/winterterm/ Office of Winter Term]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus culture==
=== Student Cooperative Association ===
The [[Oberlin Student Cooperative Association]], or OSCA, is a non-profit corporation that houses 175 students in four housing co-ops and feeds 620 students in nine dining co-ops. Its budget is more than $2 million, making it the third-largest of its kind in North America behind the Berkeley Student Cooperative and the Inter-Cooperative Council of Ann Arbor,{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} and by far the largest relative to the size of the institution whose students it serves.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

OSCA is entirely student-run, with all participating students working as cooks, buyers, administrators, and coordinators. Every member is required to do at least one hour per week of cleaning, ensuring that no one is valued above others. Most decisions within OSCA are made by modified [[Consensus decision-making|consensus]]. Oberlin bans all fraternities and sororities, making the co-ops the largest student-organized social system at the college.

===Political activism===
[[Image:DSCN4646 oberlincollegepetershall e2.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Students passing through the Memorial Arch in front of Peters Hall. The arch is dedicated to the memory of missionaries from Oberlin who were killed in the [[Boxer Rebellion]].]]

Oberlin students have a reputation for being notably liberal or progressive. The college was ranked among the ''[[Princeton Review]]'s''' list of ''&quot;Colleges with a Conscience&quot;'' in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/SchoolList.aspx?id=767 Colleges with a conscience]&lt;/ref&gt; Recent activism among the student body has resulted in a campus-wide ban on sales of [[Coca-Cola]] products.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, Samantha (November 19, 2004). &quot;College set to ban Coca-Cola&quot;. ''Oberlin Review'' (web link: [http://www.oberlin.edu/stupub/ocreview/2004/11/19/news/article1.html Oberlin.edu])&lt;/ref&gt;

Oberlin is also known for its liberal attitude toward sexuality and gender expression. Oberlin was ranked among the 20 friendliest campuses for LGBT students in ''[[The Advocate]]'s College Guide for LGBT Students''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.advocate.com/issue_story_ektid35308.asp The Advocate College Guide for LGBT Students is the best ever road map to gay-friendly campuses. Even if we do say so ourselves.]&lt;/ref&gt; Several different student groups exist to support the interests of LGBT students and their allies.

The school hosts a Sexual Information Center, where students may receive [[STI]] tests, free or heavily discounted condoms and lubricant, and counseling on sexual issues. The Sexual Information Center sponsors [[Safe sex|Safer Sex]] Night, originally started in the 1980s as a response to the AIDS crisis, as well as [[Drag (clothing)|Drag]] Ball, which marks Transgender Awareness week. Both these events are well-attended by students, although they have drawn criticism from conservatives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.frontpagemag.com/articles/Read.aspx?GUID=63F0BBAF-685D-49D8-811D-FA1BF266CB2B |title=Radical Activist U: Oberlin College |date=2003-11-05 |accessdate=2008-10-02 |author=Pearce, Jean |publisher=FrontPageMag}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Oberlin is a finalist in [[People for the Ethical Treatment of Animals|PETA]]'s &quot;Most Vegetarian-Friendly college&quot; contest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peta2.com/college/vegfriendlycollege-09/?c=923fs Peta2.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

A sampling of the school's past commencement speakers reflects its reputation for embracing diversity, ranging from Archbishop [[Desmond Tutu]], [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]] and [[Jesse L. Jackson]] to figures as varied as [[Pete Seeger]] and [[Robert Frost]]; even [[Adlai Stevenson II|Adlai Stevenson]] appeared, a month prior to his death.

===Music===
In addition to the Conservatory, Oberlin has myriad musical opportunities available for amateur musicians and students in the college. The Oberlin Gilbert and Sullivan Players (OGASP) perform one [[Gilbert and Sullivan]] operetta each semester. The entirely student-run Oberlin College Marching Band (OCMB), founded in 1998, performs at various sporting events including football games, women's rugby, and pep rallies throughout the year.  There are a number of [[a cappella]] groups, including the Obertones (all-male), the Acapelicans (all-female), Nothing But Treble (all-female), and 'Round Midnight (co-ed jazz). In addition, students in the college can form [[chamber music|chamber groups]] and receive coaching through the Conservatory. Student composers also provide a demand for musicians to perform their work.

The college radio station [[WOBC-FM]], and the party circuit (including the popular on-campus venue, The 'Sco) contribute to the campus music scene. Many alumni have pursued careers in popular and [[indie music]], including members of the bands [[The Mars Volta]], [[Rasputina]], [[Come (American band)|Come]], [[Deerhoof]], [[Liz Phair]], [[Josh Ritter]], [[Songs: Ohia]], [[The Sea and Cake]], [[Teengirl Fantasy]], [[Tortoise (band)|Tortoise]], [[Trans Am (band)|Trans Am]], [[Sleepytime Gorilla Museum]], [[Skeletons (band)|Skeletons]], and the [[Yeah Yeah Yeahs]]. Due in part to both this and the school's proximity to [[Cleveland, Ohio|Cleveland]], the college attracts touring artists with a frequency nearly unparalleled among institutions of its size.

===Art rental===
Oberlin's museum has a unique art rental program. At the beginning of every semester students camp out in front of the north gate of the college's [[Allen Memorial Art Museum]] to get first pick of original etchings, lithographs and paintings by artists including [[Pierre-Auguste Renoir|Renoir]], [[Warhol]], [[Dalí]], and [[Picasso]]. For five dollars per semester, students can hang these works on their dorm room walls. The program was started in the 1940s by Ellen Johnson, a professor of art at Oberlin, in order to &quot;develop the aesthetic sensibilities of students and encourage ordered thinking and discrimination in other areas of their lives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Angell, Sue (September 26, 2005). &quot;Art Rental Still Going Strong After 60 Years&quot;. ''Oberlin Online: News and Features''. (web link: [http://oberlin.edu/news-info/05sep/art.html Oberlin.edu])&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sustainability==
Oberlin College has demonstrated its commitment to the pursuit of [[sustainability]] on a  number of fronts. An estimated 50% of the school's electricity needs are met using [[renewable energy|sustainable energy]] sources. Oberlin's innovative [[Adam Joseph Lewis Center for Environmental Studies|Center For Environmental Studies]], a building the [[United States Department of Energy|Department of Energy]] labeled as one of the “milestone” buildings of the 20th century, incorporates a 4,600 square foot (425 square meter) [[photovoltaic array]], the biggest of its kind in Ohio. The school utilizes [[biodiesel]], [[hybrid vehicle|hybrid]], and [[electric vehicle]]s for various purposes, offers financial support to a local transit company providing [[public transportation]] to the school, and has been home to [http://www.oberlinbikecoop.org/ the Oberlin Bike Co-op], a cooperatively run bicycle center, since 1986. Each of the residence halls also monitors and displays real time and historic power and water use. Some dorms also have orbs which display a color depending on how real time energy use compares to the average historic energy use.   The school's Campus Committee on Shareholder responsibility provides students, faculty, and staff with the opportunity to make suggestions and decisions on [[proxy vote]]s.
In 2007, Oberlin received a grade of “B+” from the [[Sustainable Endowments Institute]]'s annual College Sustainability Report Card, and was featured among schools as a “Campus Sustainability Leader”.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.endowmentinstitute.org/ &quot;College Sustainability Report Card 2008&quot;] Sustainable Endowments Institute. Retrieved on July 20, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2008, Oberlin received an &quot;A-&quot; on the annual College Sustainability Report Card.&lt;ref&gt;[http://greenreportcard.org/report-card-2009/schools/oberlin-college &quot;College Sustainability Report Card 2009&quot;] Sustainable Endowments Institute. Retrieved on October 1, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It was also listed as the school with the greenest conscience by Plenty in their green campuses ratings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.plentymag.com/features/2008/09/green_campuses.php &quot;Green Campuses 3.0&quot;] Plenty. Retrieved on October 1, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, Oberlin's ranking has dropped &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sierraclub.org/sierra/201009/coolschools/top100.aspx &quot;Sierra Club Top 100&quot;] Sierra Club. Retrieved on February 9, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; in part because it continues to rely on coal to heat its buildings. Though the school is making efforts to change the decades old coal plant, it is likely going to be more difficult than similar schools in the east and west because of a lack of economically viable alternatives.

Additionally, according to a recently published article on ''[[The Oberlin Review]]'', renovated dorms may use more electricity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebecca Cable p. 1&quot;&gt;Rebecca Cable, ''Renovated Dorms May Use More Energy'', The Oberlin Review, ''April 2010'', p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; This is the case for Noah, Kade, Harvey and Price renovated during the summer of 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebecca Cable p. 1&quot;/&gt; The College architect, Steve Varelmann, has called the numbers &quot;erratic and possibly unreliable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebecca Cable p. 1&quot;/&gt; According to Varelmann, a possible explanation for this phenomenon is that previously non-functioning equipment started functioning again after the renovation.&lt;ref&gt;Rebecca Cable, ''Renovated Dorms May Use More Energy'', The Oberlin Review, ''April 2010'',
p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Students may also be at blame for their behavior: &quot;What electronic devices are they using? Are they voluntarily reducing light usage? Are spaces experiencing increased use due to the improvements achieved from the renovation?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebecca Cable p. 4&quot;&gt;Rebecca Cable, ''Renovated Dorms May Use More Energy'', The Oberlin Review, ''April 2010'', p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; John Scofield, professor of physics at Oberlin concluded that &quot;We are building more and more efficient buildings, yet we're using more energy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebecca Cable p. 4&quot;/&gt;

==Publications and media==
Oberlin students publish a wide variety of periodicals. The college's largest publications are ''[[The Oberlin Review]]'' and ''[[The Grape]].'' The Oberlin Review is a traditional weekly newspaper, focusing on current events, with a circulation of around 2,500. The Grape is Oberlin's student-run [[alternative newspaper]]. There is also a newspaper pertaining to the interests of students of color, called ''In Solidarity.''

Magazines on campus include ''[[Drivel Magazine]],'' a satire and humor publication,&lt;ref&gt;[http://drivel-magazine.com/ Drivel Magazine]&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Plum Creek Review]],'' a [[literary review]] containing student-written fiction, poetry, translations, and visual art.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/stupub/plmcreek/ Plum Creek Review]&lt;/ref&gt; ''Spiral'' is a magazine focused on [[genre fiction]]. The College also produces a quarterly alumni magazine,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/oam Oberlin.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; while the Conservatory publishes its own magazine once a year.

The WOBC News Corps, a news division of [[WOBC-FM]] created in February 2010, produces local news segments that air bi-hourly. WOBC, a large student organization with significant non-student membership, also maintains an online blog that focuses on music and local events.

==Athletics==
The school's varsity sports teams are the [[Yeomen]] and Yeowomen. The name Yeomen arose in the early 1900's as a result of blending the former team moniker with the schools official motto. Early on in the program, football players and other athletes were known simply as Oberlin Men or &quot;O&quot; Men. Eventually, as the athletic department became more cohesive, the Yeomen mascot was adopted, drawing on the phonetic sound of &quot;O&quot; Men and the schools official motto of &quot;Learning and Labor&quot;. As women's sports became more prevalent, &quot;Yeowomen&quot; was adopted to describe the mascot representing women's athletics. They participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s Division III and the [[North Coast Athletic Conference]]. Oberlin's [[American football|football]] team was the first team coached by legendary coach [[John Heisman]], who led the team to a 7&amp;ndash;0 record in 1892. Oberlin is the last college in Ohio to beat [[Ohio State]] (winning 7–6 in 1921). Though in modern times the football team was more famous for losing streaks of 40 games (1992&amp;ndash;1996) and 44 games (1997&amp;ndash;2001), the Yeomen have enjoyed limited success in recent years.

The college also hosts several club sports teams, including the Oberlin [[Ultimate (sport)|Ultimate]] team. Oberlin Ultimate was founded in 1976 and is often among the top 10 teams in its region. Recently, leaders of the Athletic Department and various club sports have spoken out in favor of increased institutional support for the teams, requesting that the College provide access to professional sports trainers and team transportation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Karlgaard, Joe, et al. |title=Club Sports Demand Equal Attention |url=http://www.oberlin.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/ocreview/20080516.php?a=l_club_sports&amp;sec=letters |work=The Oberlin Review |date=2007-10-05 |accessdate=2008-08-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Football===
{{Main|Oberlin Yeomen football}}
[[File:Oberlin quaterback.jpg|250px|thumb|left|An Oberlin quarterback attempts a pass]]
Oberlin football plays its home game at [[Savage Stadium]].

Oberlin played its first football game in 1891, going 2 and 2 that season. In 1892, they were coached by [[John Heisman]]; Oberlin went 7 and 0, beating [[Ohio State]] twice by scores of 40–0 and 50–0. They outscored opponents 262 to 30.

Oberlin was one of the founding members of the Ohio Athletic Conference in 1902, along with Case, [[Kenyon College]], [[Ohio State]], [[Ohio Wesleyan University]] and Western Reserve. The league commonly was known as the &quot;Big Six.&quot; [[Ohio State Buckeyes football|Ohio State]] joined the [[Big Ten]] in 1913. Ohio State's all-time highest margin of victory was a 128–0 thrashing of Oberlin in 1916. Oberlin is the last in-state school to defeat Ohio State. The Yeomen upset the Buckeyes 7–6 at [[Ohio Field]] in [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]] in [[1921 Ohio State Buckeyes football team|1921]].

The Oberlin teams of 1994 to 2000 have been rated the fifth worst college football team of all time by ESPN.com's Page 2. In 1994, Oberlin lost all nine games of its season scoring only ten points and giving up 358 points. In 1995, the Yeomen were outscored 469 to 72. In August 1996, ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' featured Oberlin in its annual College Football Preview as the worst team in Division III. After four winless seasons from 1993 to 1996, Oberlin opened its 1997 season with an 18–17 victory over [[Thiel College]], sparking post-game jubilation with fans rushing the field. The victory garnered national attention as ESPN featured it on ''SportsCenter''. Oberlin would not win again for years.  [[Swarthmore College]] and Oberlin scheduled a 1999 matchup, with both schools nursing long losing streaks, just so one of them could end their streak. Oberlin lost 42–6 and continued a 44-game losing streak, ending it with a 53–22 victory over [[Kenyon College]] at home in October 2001.&lt;ref&gt;Page2 Staff. &quot;Worst college football teams of all time&quot;. ESPN.com's ''[[Page2]]''. (web link: [http://espn.go.com/page2/s/list/colfootball/teams/worst.html go.com])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;2008 Oberlin College Football Media Guide (web link: [http://www.goyeo.com/documents/2008/8/4/2008_football_media_guide.pdf?id=357 Goyeo.com], pages 39–40)&lt;/ref&gt;

Since then the team has enjoyed modest success, staying competitive in most games and going 5–5 (with better than .500 records in conference) in 2003, 2006, and 2007.

In March 2008, Chris Schubert, a former wide receiver for Oberlin, was invited to a mini camp hosted by the [[Cleveland Browns]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Steve| last=King| coauthors=| title=Oberlin's Schubert vying for a shot| date=2008-05-03 | publisher=[[Cleveland Browns]]|url=http://www.clevelandbrowns.com/article.php?id=8426| work =www.clevelandbrowns.com | pages = | accessdate = 2009-05-08| language = }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; He did not make the roster but in November 2008, was signed by the [[Mahoning Valley Thunder]] of the [[AF2]]. He scored a touchdown in his first game for the Thunder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=| last=| coauthors=| title=Schubert Scores In Professional Debut with the Thunder| date=2009-03-28 | publisher=Oberlin College|url=http://www.goyeo.com/news/2009/3/28/FB_0328093047.aspx| work =goyeo.com | pages = | accessdate = 2009-05-08| language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, Schubert completed a season with the [[Richmond Raiders]] of the [[American Indoor Football Association]], leading the team in receptions, yards, and touchdowns.&lt;ref&gt;http://goyeo.com/news/2010/7/21/FB_0721104655.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cheerleading===
In 2011, Oberlin began its most recent attempt to feature a cheerleading squad. In 2006, a cheerleader fell from atop a pyramid at a football game, initiating the demise of Oberlin’s Cheerleading Club. That injury prompted the school to restrict the club’s activities, prohibiting stunting and tumbling, after which participation fizzled out. The club’s charter, however, remained intact and was used to bring the squad back in 2011. Tryouts were held in the spring of 2011 and the the cheerleading team went active at Oberlin's first home football game that Fall, a 42-0 win over [[Kenyon College]]. The squad also cheers for the [[basketball]] team and participates in spirit building and service events across campus and in the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Perry|first=Nick|title=Oberlin Cheerleading Club Revived|url=http://www.fearlessandloathing.com/2011/09/oberlin-cheerleading-club-revived/|publisher=Fearless and Loathing|accessdate=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rugby===
Oberlin has both women's and men's rugby teams, the Rhinos and the Gruffs, respectively. The Rhinos were formed in the early 1990s and have been competing continuously since then. The Rhinos have been one of the more successful Oberlin teams, defeating The Ohio State University 14–0 in Spring 2008, and winning the Teapot Dome Tournament. Rhino colors are green and black. 
The Oberlin College Men's Rugby team was founded in 1973 by Bruce Kostic Class of 1974. They won their first game defeating the Elyria Black River Rugby Club. Oberlin, formed as the Oberlin College Rugby Club (OCRC), was sponsored by the Oberlin College Rathskeller, then the campus pub. In its second season, 1974, the team complied a 3–2 record and carried a roster of 32 players, mainly football and lacrosse players.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/cgi-bin/cgiwrap/ocreview/20080509.php?a=s_rugby_rhinos&amp;sec=sports Oberlin.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; The Gruffs had their formal charter disbanded in the 1990s. It was re-formed in the fall of 2006 mainly under the supervision of Keith Yoder and David Sokoll. Since then, the Gruffs have continued to grow as a formal, chartered, club sports organization of Oberlin College.

===Ultimate===
Oberlin has both a men's and a women's [[Ultimate (sport)|Ultimate]] team, known as the Flying Horsecows and the Preying Manti&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberlin.edu/stuorg/obult/manti/index.html The Preying Manti]&lt;/ref&gt;  respectively. The Horsecows have made trips to College Nationals in 1992, 1995, 1997, and 1999. The Manti qualified for Nationals for the first time in 1997. Both teams qualified for DIII nationals in 2010. Both teams also maintain a tradition of emphasizing the [[Ultimate (sport)#Spirit of the Game|spirit of Ultimate]].  Recently, the Flying Horsecows, after having an unsuccessful 2006–2007 season, hired a coach to work them into shape, and succeeded in advancing to the Regional championship tournament.&lt;ref&gt;[http://upa.org/college/top25history/2008-top25-open.shtml UPA.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
{{main|List of Oberlin College alumni}}
&lt;!-- Please don't add names here, rather do it on the article named above --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.oberlin.edu/ Official website]
* [http://www.oberwiki.net/ Oberwiki, the Oberlin wiki]
* [http://www.oberlin.edu/archive/oberlins_namesake/ Oberlin's Namesake, a multimedia presentation]

{{ohio_five}}
{{GLCA}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Oberlin Group}}
{{CLAC}}
{{North Coast Athletic Conference}}

{{Registered Historic Places}}

[[Category:1833 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ohio]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Education in Lorain County, Ohio|Oberlin College]]
[[Category:Five Colleges of Ohio]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1833]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Posse schools]]
[[Category:Oberlin College]]
[[Category:National Historic Landmarks in Ohio]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:History of African-American civil rights]]
[[Category:History of women's rights in the United States]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Lorain County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Lorain County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]

[[cs:Oberlin College]]
[[de:Oberlin College]]
[[es:Oberlin College]]
[[fa:کالج ابرلین]]
[[fr:Oberlin College]]
[[it:Oberlin College]]
[[nl:Oberlin College]]
[[ja:オベリン大学]]
[[no:Oberlin College]]
[[zh:欧柏林大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
