<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="225577" ns="0" title="Portland State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=November 2009}}
{{Infobox university
 |name              = Portland State University
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = Portland State University Seal.svg
 |image_size        = 200px
 |caption           =
 |latin_name        =
 |motto             = &lt;i&gt;Doctrina urbi serviat&lt;i/&gt;
 |mottoeng          = Let Knowledge Serve the City
 |established       = 1946
 |closed            =
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]]
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         = [[United States Dollar|$]]28.2 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        =
 |president         = [[Wim Wiewel]]
 |vice-president    =
 |superintendent    =
 |provost           = [[Roy W. Koch]]
 |vice_chancellor   =
 |rector            =
 |principal         =
 |dean              =
 |director          =
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           =
 |staff             = 2,248 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ous.edu/irs/04_profiles/psu.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
 |students          = 29,818
 |undergrad         = 22,706 &lt;ref name=&quot;pdx.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.pdx.edu/profile/Snapshot-of-Portland-State&lt;/ref&gt;
 |postgrad          = 7,112 &lt;ref name=&quot;pdx.edu&quot;/&gt;
 |doctoral          =
 |other             =
 |city              = [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]]
 |state             = [[Oregon]]
 |province          =
 |country           = [[United States of America]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|45|30|46|N|122|41|07|W|display=inline,title}}
 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|49|acre|ha}}
 |former_names      = Vanport Extension Center (1946)&lt;br/&gt;Portland State College (1955)
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            = 16 varsity teams
 |colors            = Green &amp; White {{colorbox|#6A7F10}}{{colorbox|white}}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pdx.edu/faqs/what-colors-should-i-use-in-portland-state-university-print-and-online-publications&lt;/ref&gt;
 |colours           =
 |nickname          = [[Portland State Vikings|Vikings]]
 |mascot            = Victor E. Viking
 |athletics         = [[NCAA Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Big Sky Conference]]
 |affiliations      =
 |website           = [http://www.pdx.edu/ pdx.edu]
 |logo              = [[File:Portland State University Logo.svg|250px]]
 |footnotes         =
}}
'''Portland State University''' ('''PSU''') is a public state [[urban university]] located in [[Downtown Portland|downtown]] [[Portland, Oregon]], [[United States]]. Founded in 1946, it has the largest overall enrollment of any university in the state of [[Oregon]], including undergraduate and graduate students. It is also the only public university in the state that is located in a major metropolitan city. Portland State is part of the [[Oregon University System]].

The athletic teams are known as the [[Portland State Vikings]] with school colors of green and white. Teams compete at the NCAA Division I Level, primarily in the [[Big Sky Conference]]. Schools at PSU include the [[Portland State University School of Business Administration]], Graduate School of Education, School of Fine and Performing Arts, School of Social Work, College of Urban and Public Affairs, Maseeh College of Engineering and Computer Science, and the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences.

==History==
The University was established as the '''Vanport Extension Center''' in June 1946 to satisfy the demand for higher education in Portland for returning World War II veterans. Classes were held in the vacated-for-summer Vanport Junior High School. This first summer session had 221 students. Over 1410 students registered for the 1946 fall term, which was delayed until October 7 due to a lack of space. Since population in [[Vanport City, Oregon]] was decreasing after World War II, the extension center was able to use buildings created for other purposes: two childcare centers, a recreation building with three classrooms, and a shopping center, which required substantial modification to house a library, offices, and six classrooms. [[Lincoln High School (Portland, Oregon)|Lincoln]] and [[Jefferson High School (Portland, Oregon)|Jefferson]] high schools were used after school hours, as well as the [[University of Oregon]]'s dental and medical schools, located in Portland, and at Vanport Junior High School.&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Epler | first=Stephen E. | title=Portland State University: The First 25 Years: 1955-1980 | editor=John Eliot Allen | date=1980-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the [[Vanport City, Oregon|Vanport Flood of 1948]], the college became known as &quot;the college that wouldn't die&quot; for refusing to close after the flood.&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;die&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Dodds | first=Gordon B | title=The College That Would Not Die | year=2000 | isbn=0875952747}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term was coined by Lois Hennessey, a student who wrote about the college and the flood in the [[Christian Science Monitor]],&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot; /&gt; though students nicknamed the school &quot;The college without a future.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot; /&gt; (Hennessey, coincidentally, was the mother of poet [[Gary Snyder]].)  The school occupied [[Grant High School (Portland, Oregon)|Grant High School]] in the summer of 1948,&lt;ref name=&quot;thesis&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Polich | first=Edward L. | title=A history of Portland's secondary school system with emphasis on the superintendents and the curriculum (Thesis/dissertation) | publisher=[[University of Portland]] | year=1950 | page=161 | oclc=232551057}}&lt;/ref&gt; then to hastily converted buildings at the Oregon Shipyard,&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot; /&gt; known as the Oregon Ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;die&quot; /&gt; In 1953,&lt;ref name=&quot;first25&quot; /&gt; the school moved to downtown Portland and occupied the vacated buildings of Lincoln High School on SW Broadway street, including the &quot;scabby&quot; [[Lincoln Hall (Portland, Oregon)|Lincoln Hall]], then known as &quot;Old Main.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;youngpsu&quot; /&gt; The school changed its name to the '''Portland State Extension Center''' between December 1951 and February 1952,&lt;ref name=&quot;die&quot; /&gt; and in 1955, the Center changed its name to '''Portland State College''' to mark its maturation into a four-year degree-granting institution.&lt;ref name=&quot;die&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ous.edu/about/chanoff/files/history.pdf | title = Chronological History of the Institutions of the Oregon University System | format = pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; Students and faculty had begun calling the school &quot;Portland State College&quot; by 1952, however.&lt;ref name=&quot;die&quot; /&gt; It was also called &quot;The U by the Slough&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;youngpsu&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=PSU at 50: Young PSU perked with vitality of mind (1 of 8 parts) | last=Terry | first=John | date=1996-02-15 | work=The Oregonian | accessdate=2 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1956, the veterans had subsided, and baby food was no longer stocked in the bookstore.&lt;ref name=&quot;youngpsu&quot; /&gt;

Portland State University's growth for the next couple of decades was constricted under the Oregon University System's 1929 ruling that no public university or college in Oregon could duplicate the programs offered by another, with grandfathered exclusions for the [[University of Oregon]] and [[Oregon State University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;osb policies&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.ous.edu/sites/default/files/about/polipro/files/BoardPolicies11-05.pdf
 | title = Oregon State Board of Higher Education Policies
 | date = November 2005
 | publisher = Oregon University System
 | page = 45
 | format = PDF
 | accessdate = 2011-03-24
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Nevertheless, graduate programs were added in 1961 and doctoral programs were added in 1968. The institution was granted university status by the [[Oregon State Board of Higher Education]] in 1969, becoming Portland State University.

[[Image:Lincoln High School Portland Oregon 1920.jpg|thumb|Lincoln Hall circa 1920, then a high school]]
In 1994 PSU did away with the traditional undergraduate distribution system and adopted a new interdisciplinary general education program known as University Studies. This program has been controversial both on and off campus due to some evidence that University Studies does not produce students who are adept at writing at the college level, but it is one of the programs at Portland State that has garnered national attention for its successful retention of first-year students.  ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' has on multiple occasions listed University Studies as a &quot;Program to Look For&quot;. In 2003 Portland State was approved to award degrees in [[Black Studies]]. That same year the university opened a center housed in a new building to support Native American students.

In 2004 Dr. [[Fariborz Maseeh]] donated, through [[The Massiah Foundation]], $8 million to the College of Engineering and Computer Science. The college was renamed the Maseeh College of Engineering and Computer Science. This was the largest single donation to the University at the time and this gift along with others led to, in May 2006, the opening of a new engineering building, the &quot;Northwest Center for Engineering, Science and Technology&quot; which houses much of the College. The LEED gold-certified engineering building reflects the university's increased emphasis on engineering, science and technology. The {{convert|130000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} facility includes classrooms, offices and 41 research and teaching labs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.fap.pdx.edu/floorplans/detail.php?buildingID=11
 | title = FAP - Facilities &amp; Planning - Building Details: Engineering Building
 | accessdate = 2011-03-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2004, Portland State announced a joint offering with [[Oregon Health &amp; Science University]] (OHSU) to establish the nation's first [[biomedical informatics]] program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.cs.pdx.edu/CSdegrees/five_yearCSBioInformaics.html
 | archiveurl = http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20070607160821/http://www.cs.pdx.edu/CSdegrees/five_yearCSBioInformaics.html
 | archivedate = 2007-06-07
 | title = Biomedical Informatics: Portland State University and Oregon Health &amp; Science University—Five year, dual degree program
 | accessdate = 2010-03-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 2005, Representative [[Mitch Greenlick]] and others introduced legislation in the [[Oregon House of Representatives]] that would have merged Portland State and OHSU. The legislation was met with resistance as it was opposed by the presidents of both universities. Consequently, the bill died.  Again, in March 2007, Representative Greenlick introduced HB 3034,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leg.state.or.us/07reg/measures/hb3000.dir/hb3024.intro.html Relating to integration of Portland State University and Oregon Health and Science University; creating new provisions; amending ORS 97.170, 174.108, 181.871, 190.410, 192&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; a proposal which would remove Portland State from the [[Oregon University System]] and merge its governance with OHSU into a ''Portland Metropolitan Universities Board''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://media.www.dailyvanguard.com/media/storage/paper941/news/2007/04/13/News/A.WorldClass.University-2840199.shtml A world-class university? - News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; A legislative hearing was held on March 19 where representatives from PSU and OHSU opposed the proposal.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.lists.pdx.edu/pipermail/gov-relations/2007-March/000187.html Legislative Update&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 2008 the [http://www.millerfound.org/ James F. and Marion L. Miller Foundation] awarded Portland State University a $25 million challenge grant. The grant is the largest amount in the history of the Foundation and at Portland State. Both the $25 million Miller grant and the funds raised to match it must be used exclusively for sustainability programs. Today, Portland State’s sustainability research and education, led by Robert Constanza, director of the Portland State Institute for Sustainable Solutions, is focused on four primary areas of inquiry: creating sustainable urban communities, the integration of human societies and the natural environment, implementing sustainability and mechanisms of change and measuring sustainability. Since 1998, the Miller Foundation has also contributed more than $5.3 million to Portland State.

==Academics==
[[Image:IMG 2653-vi.jpg|thumb|265px|Portland State University]]
Portland State is the largest and fastest growing school in the [[Oregon University System]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.ous.edu/factreport/enroll/futcur
 | title = Future &amp; Historical Enrollment
 | date = 2010-12-10
 | accessdate = 2011-03-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
The university is ranked among ''The Best 376 Colleges'' in its 2012 edition, &quot;Best in the West&quot;, &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.princetonreview.com/schoollist.aspx?id=763
 | title = The Princeton Review Best Regional Colleges
 | accessdate = 2011-11-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
and as a &quot;College With a Conscience&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://ir.princetonreview.com/releasedetail.cfm?releaseid=168268
 | title = Princeton Review Colleges with a Conscience
 | accessdate = 2011-11-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

by the ''[[Princeton Review]]''. Portland State's MBA was ranked in the top 100 by the &quot;Princeton Review&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://ir.princetonreview.com/releasedetail.cfm?releaseid=168268
 | title = Princeton Review Top 100 MBA Rankings
 | accessdate = 2011=-11-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, Portland State has increasingly added more [[doctoral]] programs as it has grown from its original mission as a liberal arts undergraduate college into a more broad-based research university. Recently added doctorates are Mathematics, Biology, Chemistry, Applied Physics, Computer Science, Applied Psychology, Engineering &amp; Technology Management, Mechanical Engineering, and Sociology.

Portland State awarded a total of 5,206 degrees for the 2009-10 academic year, including 3,532 bachelor degrees, 1,625 master degrees and 50 doctoral degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = Portland State News
  | url = http://www.pdx.edu/news/20587/
  | accessdate = 2008-06-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

U.S. News &amp; World Report currently ranks Portland State University in the fourth tier in 2007 as a research university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = National universities: Tier 4
  | publisher = US News.com
  | url = http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/t4natudoc_brief.php
  | accessdate = 2007-03-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Portland State University School of Business Administration ranks 22nd on a list of the Global Top 100 Schools in the 2007–2008 edition of 'Beyond Grey Pinstripes,' a biennial ranking of business schools conducted by the Aspen Institute Center for Business Education.{{Expand section|date=November 2010}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.beyondgreypinstripes.org/index.cfm
| title = Beyond grey pinstripes
| work = The Aspen Institute Center for Business Education
| accessdate = October 11, 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Portland State University School of Business Administration is also ranked in other surveys, such as the Princeton Review's ''Best 294 Business Schools''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.princetonreview.com/SchoolList.aspx?id=786
 | title = Princeton Review's 2012 Best 294 Business Schools
 | accessdate = 2011-11-3
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Planetizen]] currently ranks Portland State University's graduate Urban &amp; Regional Planning Program, at the Nohad A. Toulan School of Urban Studies and Planning, within the top 25 best urban planning programs in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.planetizen.com/topschools
| title = The Top Schools For Urban Planners
| work = Planetizen
| accessdate = June 9, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges and schools===
[[File:Portland state university EB.jpg|thumb|Engineering Building, Maseeh College of Engineering and Computer Science]]
Portland State University's academic programs are organized into seven major academic units:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.pdx.edu/sites/www.pdx.edu.registration/files/media_assets/reg_bulletin_2008_2009.pdf
| title = Bulletin 2008-2009
| format=PDF
| work = Portland State University
| accessdate = June 22, 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
:*College of Liberal Arts and Sciences - An array of undergraduate, graduate, and certificate programs in over 20 majors, including Anthropology, Applied Linguistics, Biology, Black Studies, Chemistry, Chicano/Latino Studies, Communication, Conflict Resolution, Economics, English, Environmental Programs, Foreign Languages and Literatures, Geography, Geology, History, International Studies, Mathematics and Statistics, Native American Studies, Philosophy, Physics, Psychology, Science Education, Sociology, Speech and Hearing Sciences, and Women's Studies.
:*Portland State University School of Business Administration - Undergraduate and graduate majors include Business Administration, Financial Analysis, and International Management. Postgraduate and certificate programs include Accounting, International Business Studies, and Food Industry Management. The school also offers doctoral programs as part of the Systems Science doctoral program.
:*Graduate School of Education - Graduate programs in initial and continuing licensure, Education (Early Childhood, Elementary, Middle Level, and High School), Educational Leadership, and various specialization programs.
:*Maseeh College of Engineering and Computer Science - Undergraduate and graduate programs include Civil, Computer, Electrical, Environmental, and Mechanical Engineering, as well as Computer Science. Graduate programs also include Engineering Management, Manufacturing Engineering, Systems Engineering, Software Engineering, and Technology Management. The school also offers doctoral programs as part of the Systems Science and the Environmental Sciences and Resources doctoral programs.
:*School of Fine and Performing Arts - Undergraduate programs include Architecture, Art, Art History, Arts Studies, Film, Film Studies, Music, Theater Arts, and Dance. Graduate studies include Architecture, Art, Music, Theater Arts, and Secondary Art Education.
:*School of Social Work - The school offers programs in Social Work at the undergraduate and graduate levels, Undergraduate Child and Family Studies, and Doctoral social work programs.
:*College of Urban and Public Affairs - This college is organized in a series of subsidiary schools focusing on various aspects of Urban and Public Affairs:
:**School of Community Health - Undergraduate and graduate studies in Health Studies and Community Health. The school also offers a graduate certificate in Gerontology.
:**Mark O. Hatfield School of Government - Undergraduate and graduate studies in Criminology/Criminal Justice, Political Science, and Public Administration. Institutes include the Criminal Justice Research Policy Institute, Executive Leadership Institute, Institute for Nonprofit Management, National Policy Consensus Center, Institute for Tribal Administration, and the Center for Turkish Studies.
:**Nohad A. Toulan School of Urban Studies and Planning - Undergraduate programs include a major and minor in Community Development, and minors in Real Estate Development and Sustainable Urban Development. Graduate certificates include Real Estate Development, Transportation, and Urban Design. Graduate studies include Urban Studies, as well as Urban and Regional Planning. Institutes include the Center for Urban Studies, Institute of Portland Metropolitan Studies, Center for Population Research Census, Center for Real Estate, and the Center for Transportation Studies.

In addition, Portland State University, through the School of Extended Studies, offers continuing education and special learning activities, including credit courses, degree-completion programs, distance-learning courses, noncredit community programs, relicensure, certifications, high school courses, summer programs, and online study.

==Student life==
[[Image:PSU campus in spring 07.JPG‎|thumb|left|The South Park Blocks of [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]] are in PSU's central campus.]]
Portland State differs from the other universities in Oregon partially because as an urban institution it attracts a student body older than other rural universities. In the 2009-2010 school year, it was reported that the average age of an attending undergraduate student was 25 years. A significant percentage of Portland State's classes are offered at night and Saturdays. Indeed, some programs only offer night classes. PSU also delayed the development of its campus for decades after its founding. The institution sold land in a neighboring block soon after its move to downtown Portland, and delayed the construction of student housing until the early 1970s.

While the mean age of students is 27, increasing traditional enrollment is lowering the average student age.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.oirp.pdx.edu/source/port0910/all_all.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Mixed-use building projects (commercial, educational, residential) by the university preserve downtown shops and businesses while transforming the university from a &quot;commuter campus&quot; to a mix between a commuter and a traditional campus. Recently completed residences include the [[Stephen Epler Hall]] and [[The Broadway (Portland State)|The Broadway]]. Further steps toward increasing housing capacity &amp;mdash; and university control over its own housing &amp;mdash; are being taken with plans for further construction, and with PSU taking over management of the residence halls it currently owns. Optional residential and social opportunities exist with a small but active Greek system, which includes [[Alpha Chi Omega]], [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]], [[Alpha Phi Alpha]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Phi Delta Theta]], [[Phi Sigma Sigma]], [[Alpha Kappa Psi]] and [[Phi Gamma Nu]].&lt;ref&gt;http://web.pdx.edu/~salp/groups_display.php?group_type=3&amp;order_by=1&amp;order_type=1&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2007, Portland State University took over the managing of the on-campus housing at Portland State University. College Housing Northwest, which has previously managed the on-campus housing buildings (including The Broadway, Stephen Epler Hall, West Hall, King Albert, St. Helens, Montgomery Court, and Ondine) for over 30 years, will still maintain its off-campus housing (including Goose Hollow, The Palidian, The Cambrian, and Clay).

The [[students' union|student government]] is the Associated Students of Portland State University (ASPSU).  In addition to a student body President and Vice President, there is a Student Fee Committee, a 25-member Student Senate chaired by the Vice President, and a Judicial Board which rules on ASPSU constitutional questions. There are also a number of university committees that have student members appointed by the ASPSU President.&lt;ref&gt;http://aspsu.pdx.edu&lt;/ref&gt; Portland State also participates in the [[Oregon Student Association]], the statewide student lobbying non-profit.

The fully student-run [[student newspaper|newspaper]] at Portland State is the ''[[Daily Vanguard]]'', established in 1946. Student-run broadcasters run radio station [[KPSU (Portland)|KPSU]], and television station [[PSU TV]].  ''[[The Portland Review]]'' is a literary magazine of poetry, fiction, and art published by [[PSU's Student Publications Board]] since 1956.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://portlandreview.tumblr.com/aboutus
 | title = About Us
 | accessdate = 2011-03-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additional [[student newspaper]]s at PSU are ''The Rearguard'', an alternative-monthly newspaper, and ''The Spectator''.

The 1.3 million volume [[Branford Price Millar Library]] is located in the center of campus, and offers an open microcomputer lab. The Branford Price Millar Library is a repository for federal documents.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.pdx.edu/govinfoservice.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Portland State University has mass transit by [[MAX Green Line]], [[MAX Yellow Line]], [[Portland Streetcar]], [[Trimet]] buses, and by [[Oregon Health &amp; Science University]] and [[Portland Community College]] shuttles on SW Harrison Street at SW Broadway.

Among a number of student managed [http://www.pdx.edu/recreation/listofclubs.html/ club sports] on campus are the [http://www.pdxrugby.com/ PSU Rugby Club], the [http://www.psuvikingshockey.com/ PSU Ice Hockey Club] and the [http://psulax.com/ PSU Lacrosse Club].

==Athletics==
[[File:Portland State Vikings Logo.svg|thumb|Portland State Vikings]]
{{Main|Portland State Vikings}}
Portland State is a member of the [[Big Sky Conference]] since 1996, [[Pac-12 Conference]] in wrestling, and the [[Pacific Coast Softball Conference]]. PSU competes at the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I level in basketball, women's volleyball, golf, soccer, wrestling, tennis, softball, indoor and outdoor track and field, and cross country. Football competes at the [[Division I (NCAA)#Division I-Championship Subdivision|Division I AA]] (or Football Championship Subdivision) level.

Prior to joining Division I, the school won NCAA National Division II championships in women's volleyball and wrestling. The school has also placed second twice nationally in football and once in women's basketball at the Division II level.

Portland State's colors are green and white, and its mascot is the Viking personified as &quot;Victor E. Viking&quot;. 
Among the two more notable former Portland State athletes are [[Freeman Williams]] and [[Neil Lomax]]. Freeman Williams was the NCAA Division I national men's basketball individual scoring leader in 1977 and 1978. Neil Lomax was a record setting quarterback who went on to star for the St. Louis Cardinals in the NFL in the mid-1980s.   Football's &quot;[[Run &amp; Shoot]]&quot; offense was first implemented at the college level at PSU by coach [[Darryl &quot;Mouse&quot; Davis]]. An assistant coach at Portland State,
Davis took over as Head Coach in 1975 following the departure of Ron Stratten. Behind his revolutionary new “Run-and-Shoot” offense (developed in the late 1960s at Hillsboro (OR)HS) and a strong-armed quarterback named June Jones, Davis led the Viking program to new heights - an 8-3 record, including a perfect 5-0 home mark. Davis' quarterback protégés were Lomax and June Jones.

Home games for football are held off-campus at [[Jeld-Wen Field]], and home games for basketball are held on-campus at the [[Peter Stott Center]]. In 2008, the men's basketball team earned their first ever bid into the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship]].

==Notable faculty and staff==
&lt;!--notability must include already having a Wikipedia article (no redlinks). Please add in alphabetical order--&gt;
*[[Randy Hanson]] - secondary football coach and [[special teams]] coordinator&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blog.oregonlive.com/nfl/2009/10/oakland_raiders_assistant_coac.html|title=Fractured jaw leads to damaged reputation for Oakland Raiders assistant coach Randy Hanson following rift with head coach Tom Cable|last=Fentress|first=Aaron|date=2009-10-31|work=[[The Oregonian]]|accessdate=12 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[David Maier]] -- Maseeh Professor of Computer Science,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cs.pdx.edu/people/faculty|title=Portland State University Department of Computer Science Faculty|accessdate=16 Jan 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[ACM Fellow]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://fellows.acm.org/fellow_citation.cfm?id=1492347&amp;srt=alpha&amp;alpha=M|title=ACM&gt; Fellows Award / David Maier|accessdate=16 Jan 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Chet Orloff]] - professor of Urban Studies and Planning, director emeritus of [[Oregon Historical Society]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oregonlive.com/portland/index.ssf/2010/01/portland_state_prof_takes_on_a.html|title=Portland State prof takes on a new kind of museum: one on the Internet using a Wikipedia model |last=Saker|first=Anne|date=2010-01-11|work=[[The Oregonian]]|accessdate=2010-01-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Sergio Palleroni]] - architect and co-founder of BASIC Initiative &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.basicinitiative.org/About/Staff_Fellows.htm|title=BaSiC Inititive / Sergio Palleroni|accessdate=9 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ivan Sutherland]] -- Director, Asynchronous Research Center (ARC),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arc.cecs.pdx.edu/people|title=Asynchronous Research Center|accessdate=16 Jan 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Turing award]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://awards.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=3467412&amp;srt=all&amp;aw=140&amp;ao=AMTURING|title=ACM Award Citation / Ivan Sutherland|accessdate=16 Jan 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
&lt;!--notability must include already having a Wikipedia article (no redlinks). Please add in alphabetical order--&gt;
*[[Jean M. Auel]] - author of ''[[The Clan of the Cave Bear]]''
*[[Bree Schaaf Boyer]] - U.S. Olympic Bobsledder, [[2010 Winter Olympics|2010 Winter Olympics, Vancouver BC]]
*[[Ken Butler]] - artist and experimental musician
*[[Tony Curtis (American football)|Tony Curtis]] - backup tight end for the [[Dallas Cowboys]]
*[[Issa (Senegalese singer)|Issa]] - singer, songwriter and producer signed with [[Akon]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://localcut.wweek.com/2008/10/13/issas-global-conspiracy &quot;Issa's Global Conspiracy&quot;]. ''[[Willamette Week]]''&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dave Jansen]] - Wrestler and mixed martial artist&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wec.tv/DaveJansen|title=WEC | World Extreme Cagefighting: Dave Jansen|accessdate=26 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mark Dacascos]] - actor and martial artist
*[[Carolyn Davidson]] - creator of the [[Nike, Inc.|Nike]] [[swoosh]]
*[[D. Scott Davis]] - Chairman and CEO, [[United Parcel Service of America]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.equilar.com/CEO_Compensation/United_Parcel_Service_D._Scott_Davis.php 2008 CEO Compensation for D. Scott Davis], Equilar.com&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Paul De Muniz]] - [[Oregon Supreme Court]] Chief Justice
*[[Clint Didier]] -  former [[NFL]] tight end, [[Super Bowl XVII]] Champion&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/DidiCl00.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[David James Duncan]] - novelist, essayist
*[[Mike Erickson]] -  frequent candidate for elected office and entrepreneur&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afms.com/team.htm AFMS - Transportation Intelligence is our Business&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Dan Frantz]] - American football player for the [[Chicago Rush]]
*[[Katie Harman]] - 2002 [[Miss America]]
*[[Adam Hayward]] - linebacker for [[Tampa Bay Buccaneers]]
*[[Darick Holmes]] - a former [[NFL]] [[running back]]
*[[June Jones]] - head football coach, [[Southern Methodist University]]
*[[Terence Knox]] - Actor
*[[Jeff Lahti]] -  retired [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher and [[1982 World Series]] Champion
*[[Joseph LeBaron]] - current U.S. Ambassador to [[Qatar]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.state.gov/outofdate/bios/l/25087.htm State department bio of Joseph LeBaron]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://qatar.usembassy.gov/ambswear.html U.S. Envoy &quot;Thrilled to Return to Qatar&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Neil Lomax]] - [[National Football League]] quarterback, played for St. Louis/[[Arizona Cardinals]] (1981–89)
*[[Courtney Love]] - actress and frontwoman of alternative rock band [[Hole (band)|Hole]] (did not graduate)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moonwashedrose.com/media/entertainment94.html Entertainment Weekly, 1994: The Power of Love]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Holly Madison]] - ''[[Playboy]]'' model, Reality TV Star &quot;[[The Girls Next Door]]&quot;
*[[Fariborz Maseeh]] - Pioneer in the field of [[MEMS|micro-electro mechanical systems (MEMS)]] and philanthropist who founded IntelliSense in 1991
*[[Charles Moose]] - former police chief for [[Montgomery County, Maryland]], one of the sites of the [[Beltway Sniper attacks]]
*[[Jack Ohman]] - editorial cartoonist for ''[[The Oregonian]]''
*[[Steve Olin]] -  late [[Major League Baseball]] pitcher
*[[Pierre Ouellette]] - [[science fiction]] author
*[[Bill Plympton]] - animator
*[[Mike Richardson (publisher)|Mike Richardson]] - founder, [[Dark Horse Comics]]
*[[Gordon Riese]] - Portland State pitcher and Pac-10 Referee
*[[R. William Riggs]] - former Oregon Supreme Court justice
*[[Barbara Roberts]] - 34th Governor of Oregon
*[[Harry Anastasiou]] Pioneer in peace-building initiatives across the world and author of two books
*[[Betty Roberts]] - first woman to serve on the [[Oregon Supreme Court]] and [[Oregon Court of Appeals]]
*[[Deborah J. Ross]] - [[science fiction]] and fantasy author&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pdx.edu/magazine/news/fanfare-spring-2010|title=Portland State Portland State Magazine: News: Fanfare: Spring 2010|last=Kirkland|first=Kathryn|date=2010-06-10|accessdate=13 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Richard Sanders (wrestler)]] [[NCAA]], [[FILA]] abd [[Summer Olympics|Olympic]] wrestler{{cn|date=November 2011}}&lt;!-- cite attendance --&gt;
*[[Lawrence Leighton Smith]] - conductor and pianist
*[[Esperanza Spalding]] - jazz musician&lt;ref&gt;{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p514023/biography|pure_url=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/musicnightlife/2004125035_jazzinjan150.html | work=The Seattle Times | title=A hopeful outlook for jazz | date=2008-01-15 | first=Paul | last=de Barros}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Tom Trebelhorn]] - Major League Baseball manager
*[[Ime Udoka]] - current small forward for the [[Sacramento Kings]] in the [[National Basketball Association]]
*[[Freeman Williams]] - retired [[National Basketball Association]] guard
*[[Norm Winningstad]] - businessman and engineer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bizjournals.com/portland/news/2010/11/25/norm-winningstad-dies-at-age-85.html|title=Norm Winningstad dies at age 85|last=Smith|first=Rob|date=November 25, 2010|work=[[Portland Business Journal]]|accessdate=2 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jordan Senn]] - linebacker for [[Carolina Panthers]]

==Awards==
In 2006, Portland State was declared to be the nation's first Salmon Safe University by the nonprofit organization Salmon Safe. The award was given to recognize campus-wide efforts toward environmental sustainability by treating storm water runoff before it reaches the local watershed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | last = Krader
  | first = Sascha
  | title = PSU first 'salmon safe' university
  | work = Vanguard
  | date = 2006-08-09
  | url = http://media.www.dailyvanguard.com/media/storage/paper941/news/2006/08/09/News/Psu-First.salmon.Safe.University-2606893.shtml
  | accessdate = 2007-10-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 3, 2008, [[The Jimmy and Rosalynn Carter Partner Foundation]] announced Portland State as the recipient of The Jimmy and Rosalynn Carter Partnership Award for Campus-Community Collaboration for their Watershed Stewardship Program.  The program has led over 27,000 community volunteers donating a quarter million hours to install 80,000 plants and restore {{convert|50|acre|ha}} of watershed along {{Convert/spell|2|mi|km}} of river. Individual projects have been led and supported by 700 students working as part of class projects, resulting in two master's theses and three research articles.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pdx.edu/news/20547/ Portland State | News | Portland State Wins First U.S. National Carter Foundation Partnership Award&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==College Bowl==
Portland State's entry in the 1965 General Electric [[College Bowl]] Team won the nationally televised quiz show that pitted teams of college students from across the country against each other. The team knocked off its competitors for five consecutive weeks, retiring as champions, and setting a new record for total points scored.
The University's Smith Memorial Student Union building was named after team member Michael J. Smith, who competed in the tournament while suffering from [[cystic fibrosis]] and died in 1968.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aux.pdx.edu/auxiliary/message.php&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image: Portland State University Native American Center.jpg|Native American Student and Community Center
Image: PSUShattuck.jpg|Shattuck Hall, Newly Remodeled Home to the Department of Architecture, Fine Art, and Graphic Design
Image: Epler Hall.jpg|Stephen E. Epler Hall, Student Residences
Image:159-5937 IMG.JPG|College of Urban &amp; Public Affairs
Image:159-5943 IMG.JPG|[[Portland Streetcar]] at Urban Plaza Station
Image:Portland_state_university_broadway.jpg| The Broadway Housing Building
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Sister project links|Portland State University}}
{{commonscat-inline}}
*{{cite web
 | year = 2006
 | url = http://www.usnews.com/usnews/edu/college/directory/brief/drglance_3216_brief.php
 | title = Portland State University: At a Glance
 | work = [[America's Best Colleges]]
 | publisher = [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]
 | accessdate = 2006-04-07
}}
*{{cite web
 | year = 2006
 | url = http://www.princetonreview.com/college/research/profiles/generalinfo.asp?listing=1023397&amp;LTID=1
 | title = Portland State University
 | publisher = [[Princeton Review]]
 | accessdate = 2006-05-23
}}
*[http://www.pdx.edu Portland State University]
**[http://extended.pdx.edu/index.shtml School of Extended Studies]
**[http://www.oirp.pdx.edu/ Office of Institutional Research and Planning]
**[http://www.goviks.com/ Portland State University Sports]
**[http://www.pdx.edu/magazine/ PSU Magazine (Alumni Publication)]

{{Colleges and universities in Oregon}}
{{Oregon University System}}
{{Big Sky Conference}}

[[Category:Portland State University| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Urban 13 universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1946]]
[[Category:Coalition of Urban and Metropolitan Universities]]

[[de:Portland State University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی پورتلند]]
[[fr:Portland State University]]
[[ja:ポートランド州立大学]]
[[no:Portland State University]]
[[ro:Portland State University]]
[[simple:Portland State University]]
[[uk:Портлендський державний університет]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
