<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2255500" ns="0" title="Lone Star Series"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox MLB rivalry
|team1=Houston Astros
|team2=Texas Rangers
|team1abr=Astros
|team2abr=Rangers
|team1logo=[[Image:Houston Astros Cap Insignia.svg|125px|Houston Astros logo]]
|team2logo=[[Image:Texas Rangers Insignia.svg|120px|Texas Rangers logo]]
|first_meeting=June 8, 2001
|last_meeting=June 30, 2011
|next_meeting=May 18, 2012, [[Minute Maid Park]]
|meetings=66
|regularseason=37–29, Rangers
|largest_victory=18–3, Rangers (May 21, 2005)
|current_streak=1, Astros
|longeststreak_team1=4
|longeststreak_team2=5
}}
The '''Lone Star Series''' (also, '''Silver Boot Series''') is an annual [[Major League Baseball]] contest featuring Texas' two major league franchises, the [[Houston Astros]] of the [[National League]] and the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] of the [[American League]]. It is an outgrowth of the &quot;natural rivalry&quot; established by MLB as part of [[interleague play]].

The winner of the 6-game series is awarded the Silver Boot.  A {{convert|30|in|mm|adj=on}} tall display of a size-15 [[cowboy boot]] cast in silver, complete with a custom, hand-made [[spur]]. If the series is split (3-to-3), the winner is the club which scored the most [[run (baseball)|runs]] over the course of the series.

==History==
===19th century: The Beginning of Baseball in Texas===
The birth of baseball in Texas happened at the same time as the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] in 1861 with the formation of the '''Houston Base Ball Club''' to promote the game the same way [[Alexander Cartwright]] had during the 1840s with the '''Knickerbocker Base Ball Club''' in [[Manhattan]]. Baseball was played in Galveston and other Lone Star locations prior to the Civil War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lalire |first=Gregory |url=http://www.historynet.com/baseball-in-the-west.htm |title=Baseball in the West » HistoryNet – From the World's Largest History Magazine Publisher |publisher=HistoryNet |date=March 31, 2011 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The distribution of the game was interrupted by the Civil War but would pick up by the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tbhof.org/features/feature-20051028.htm |title=Texas Baseball Hall of Fame |publisher=Tbhof.org |date=April 11, 1928 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baseball was played during the Civil War mostly by [[Union (American Civil War)|Yankees]] but occasionally by Confederates. A humorous story by Texas-based Union soldier George A. Putnam told of a baseball game interrupted by [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] gunfire. 
Putnam stated: 
{{Cquote|Suddenly there was a scattering of fire, which three outfielders caught the brunt; the centerfield was hit and was captured, left and right field managed to get back to our lines. The attack...was repelled without serious difficulty, but we had lost not only our centerfield, but...the only baseball in Alexandria, Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/articles/aubrecht2004b.shtml |title=Civil War Baseball: Baseball and the Blue and the Gray |publisher=Baseball-almanac.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

On April 21, 1867, the first occurrence of a baseball game was taken into account by the [[Houston Post]]. At the [[Battle of San Jacinto|San Jacinto]] Battlegrounds near Houston, where General [[Sam Houston]] led Texas to triumph in the [[Texas War of Independence|War of Independence]] from Mexico in 1836, a baseball game took place on the anniversary now celebrated as [[Texas Independence Day]]. The [[Houston]] [[Stonewall Jackson|Stonewalls]] defeated the [[Galveston, Texas|Galveston]] [[Robert E. Lee]]s, 35–2, that rivaled the result of what originally happened on the same site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lsjunction.com/facts/tx_bball.htm |title=Early Texas Baseball |publisher=Lsjunction.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Baseball spread throughout the state in the next two decades as a popular amateur game. The influence of what Houston had done in the early 1860s, those who acquired the nuances of the game from Civil War travels, and experience of immigrants who moved to Texas during the [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction Era]] helped in organizing the sport and bringing more attention to the game in the state of Texas. Scarcely a generation after the state’s first recorded game in 1867, Texas fielded 100 minor league clubs—more than any other state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baseballasamerica.org/houston.htm Baseball As America&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The acceptance of baseball had expanded throughout Texas like a stampede of cattle by the end of the 19th century. Houston was the founding member of the  [[Texas League]] in 1888 and also won their first league pennant the next year. The Houston ballclub went by the nicknames of Babies, Red Stockings, Mud Cats, Magnolias, and Wanderers&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.astrosdaily.com/history/before/ |title=Before the Colt .45s |publisher=Astrosdaily.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; before Buffaloes became permanent around the turn of the 20th century.

===20th century: Growth and popularity of baseball in Texas===
The roots of the Lone Star Series started in the late 19th century and early 20th century in the [[Texas League]]. There were teams in [[Austin, TX|Austin]], [[Beaumont, TX|Beaumont]], [[Cleburne, TX|Cleburne]], [[Corsicana, TX|Corsicana]], [[Fort Worth, TX|Fort Worth]], [[Galveston, TX|Galveston]], [[Greenville, TX|Greenville]], [[Paris, TX|Paris]], [[San Antonio]], [[Sherman, TX|Sherman]], [[Temple, TX|Temple]], [[Texarkana, TX|Texarkana]], [[Waco, TX|Waco]] as well as [[Dallas]] and [[Houston]]. (Both the Rangers and Astros have teams in present-day Double A Texas League. The Rangers' affiliate is the [[Frisco Roughriders]] while the Astros' affiliate is the [[Corpus Christi Hooks]].) Along with the Texas League, there have been many baseball leagues that briefly existed in Texas or included at least one team from the Lone Star State such as: Lone Star Colored League of Texas,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.negroleaguebaseball.com/negro_league_blog/2006/08/negro_league_or.html |title=Negro League Baseball Blog |publisher=Blog.negroleaguebaseball.com |date=August 23, 2006 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Negro American League]], Colored Texas League, Texas Negro League, Texas-Oklahoma Negro League, South Texas Negro League,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sanangelocolts.com/news/?id=6121 |title=News |publisher=sanangelocolts.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  West Texas Negro League, Mexican National League, [[Central Baseball League]], [[American Association (20th century)|American Association]], [[All-American Association]], South Central League, Arkansas State League, [[Cotton States League]], Rio Grande Valley League, Rio Grande Association, Southwestern League, Panhandle-Pecos Valley League, Longhorn League, North Texas League, [[West Texas-New Mexico League]], [[Sooner State League]], [[Arizona-Texas League]], Lone Star League, Big State League, Gulf States League, East Texas League, Texas Association, Arkansas-Texas League, [[West Texas League]], South Texas League, Middle Texas League, Central Texas League, Texas-Southern League, [[Texas-Louisiana League]], Texas Valley League, Texas-Oklahoma League, Southwest Texas League, [[Evangeline Baseball League|Evangeline League]], West Dixie League, Gulf Coast League, [[Western Association]], and [[Sophomore League]] and also including present-day [[Pacific Coast League]], [[United League Baseball]], [[Texas Collegiate League]], [[Continental Baseball League]], [[Texas Winter League]], and [[American Association of Independent Professional Baseball]].

Long before professional baseball came to Texas, college baseball also has been a staple of [[Culture of Texas|Texas culture]]. Outside of the Lone Star Shootout, [[college baseball]] in Texas is overwhelmingly popular and has some intense in-state rivalries such as the [[Battle of the Brazos]] between [[Texas A&amp;M University|Texas A&amp;M]] and [[Baylor University]], [[Houston-Rice rivalry]], the Holy War between Baylor and [[TCU Horned Frogs baseball|TCU]], Battle of the Piney Woods between [[Sam Houston State University|Sam Houston State]] and [[Stephen F. Austin State University]], and the [[Lone Star Showdown]] between the [[Texas Longhorns baseball|Texas Longhorns]] and [[Texas A&amp;M Aggies]]. Other in-state rivalries include Texas-Rice, [[Texas State]]-Rice, [[Texas State]]-[[University of Texas at San Antonio]], [[Texas Tech Red Raiders|Texas Tech]]-Baylor, Texas-Texas Tech, Texas Tech-Texas A&amp;M, Texas-Baylor, Sam Houston State-Houston, [[Texas Southern University|Texas Southern]]-[[Prairie View A&amp;M]], [[St. Mary's University, Texas|St. Mary's]]-[[University of the Incarnate Word]], [[Dallas Baptist University|Dallas Baptist]]-[[Houston Baptist University|Houston Baptist]] as well as other esoteric rivalries. Tournaments, like the Southwest Diamond Classic in [[Frisco, TX]], Whataburger College Classic in [[Corpus Christi, TX]], and Houston College Classic played at Minute Maid Park, take place there in late February because of the more convenient, warmer weather. Texas collegiate baseball programs can be found throughout the different levels of the [[NCAA]]. 1-A conferences that include Texas collegiate baseball are the [[Big 12 Conference]], [[Conference USA]], and the [[Mountain West Conference]] as well as the [[Southland Conference]], [[Southwestern Athletic Conference]], and 1-A Independent teams, [[UTPA]] and [[Dallas Baptist]]. (TCU, Texas, Texas A&amp;M, Texas Tech, Rice, Houston, Baylor, and [[Southern Methodist University|SMU]] (ceased operations after 1980) baseball programs once belonged together to the [[Southwest Conference]] before 1996; [[Clark Field (Austin, Texas)|Clark Field]], [[Dan Law Field]], [[Olsen Field]], and [[TCU Diamond]] are just some of the ballparks that played host to Southwest Conference baseball over the course of the SWC.) Other conferences that include one or more Texas collegiate baseball programs are the [[Heartland Conference]], [[Lone Star Conference]], [[American Southwest Conference]], [[Southern Collegiate Athletic Conference]], [[Red River Athletic Conference]], [[Sooner Athletic Conference]], [[Southwest Junior College Conference.]], [[Texas Intercollegiate Athletic Association]], [[Western Junior College Athletic Conference]], and [[NAIA independent schools]] ([[University of Houston–Victoria]]).

The Lone Star Series was the consequence of many things that happened to Texas in the 1950s: population shift westward from metropolitan areas on the East Coast, the [[NASA|space program]], [[Texas#Modern era|more modernized higher education]], and the formation of the brief [[Continental League]] resulting in expansion in [[Major League Baseball]] shortly thereafter. 

Prior to 1962, there were no Major League Baseball teams in Texas until the [[Astros#Beginnings: The 1960s|Houston Colt .45's]] of the National League. They played in [[Colt Stadium]] for the first three years of existence, fighting against hot and humid weather and outrageously large mosquitoes, which also had an effect on the fans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ballparkwatch.com/stadiums/past/colt_stadium.htm |title=Colt Stadium / Houston Colt .45s / 1962–1964 |publisher=Ballparkwatch |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Unbelievably, they did not play a Sunday night baseball game at home until June 9, 1963, which was also the major leagues' first Sunday night game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseballlibrary.com/chronology/byyear.php?year=1963#June |title=The Chronology – 1963 |publisher=BaseballLibrary.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Astros, as they came to be with the new all-weathered [[Harris County Domed Stadium]], really did not have a strong rivalry with any team in the NL, except for the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] and later on the [[Atlanta Braves]]. 

During the planning of the second wave of expansion in the big leagues in 1968, the [[National League]] considered putting a new team in the [[Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex|Dallas-Fort Worth area]] by an overwhelming majority of its owners. However, Judge [[Roy Hofheinz]] did not want it to happen or allow it because he owned all the television and radio rights in Texas for Astros ballgames. The other owners were in favor, except Hofheinz, of having a rivalry approaching the intensity of the [[Dodgers–Giants rivalry]] in the Senior Circuit. San Diego and Montreal were selected instead.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-8331907_ITM | work=Fort Worth Star-Telegram | title=Rangers, Astros to meet at last | first=T.R. | last=Sullivan | date=June 3, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Dallas-Fort Worth area would have to wait four more years for a team to arrive when the Senators (see below) moved to [[Arlington, TX]]. It would be another 32 years before there was a meeting between the Rangers and Astros.

Before they were the Texas Rangers, the team belonged to the [[Beltway]] as the second version of the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Washington Senators]] where they played mediocre baseball most of the time for the first 11 years of existence. They replaced the old [[Minnesota Twins|Washington Senators]] who had moved to Minnesota to become the Twins in 1961. The new Senators changed into the Texas Rangers in time for the 1972 season and so a rivalry was born. (At one time, the [[History of the Oakland Athletics#Finley looks for a way out|Kansas City Athletics]] were interested in moving to the Dallas/Fort Worth area in the early 1960s but were voted down, 9–1, by the other American League owners.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseballlibrary.com/baseballlibrary/ballplayers/K/Kansas_City_Athletics.stm |title=Kansas City Athletics |publisher=BaseballLibrary.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sportsecyclopedia.com/al/kcityas/kca_s.html |title=Kansas City Athletics (1955–1967) |publisher=Sportsecyclopedia.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Astros have been in Texas ten years longer than the Rangers, but the Senators/Rangers franchise is one year older than the Astros. They met, starting in 1992, at the end of [[Spring Training]] with the Rangers winning 2–0 claiming the very first Silver Boot. On April 1, 1993, [[Nolan Ryan]] returned to the [[Astrodome]] as a member of the Texas Rangers in front of 53,657, the biggest crowd to see a big league game in Texas up to that point. The Rangers won the last two exhibition games, a 6–5 victory in Arlington in 1999 and a 9–3 victory at Houston in 2000, before the two teams met for the first time in regular season in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;T.R. Sullivan&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;MLB.com |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20080516&amp;content_id=2712533&amp;vkey=news_mlb&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=mlb |title=The Official Site of Major League Baseball: News: As series evolved, so did Silver Boot |publisher=Mlb.mlb.com |date=May 16, 2008 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1997 off-season, &quot;radical&quot; realignment plans were bandied around about possibly rearranging teams from one league to another, especially Houston and Texas. In order to cut down on traveling costs and align teams together based on geography, the MLB owners came up with many plans to put the Astros and Rangers in a more suitable placement together. However, the [[American League]] and [[National League]] would lose their respective identities in the process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://baseballforthought.blogspot.com/2006/05/proposal-for-mlb-realignment.html |title=Baseball For Thought: A Proposal for MLB Realignment |publisher=Baseballforthought.blogspot.com |date=May 11, 2006 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armchairgm.com/CPCP's_MLB_Realignment CPCP's MLB Realignment – ArmchairGM – Sports Wiki Database]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.andromedan.com/linda/realign.htm |title=Baseball diary, radical realignment, fans against realignment, major league baseball team addresses, NO radical realignment, Bud Selig, Plan A, realignment options |publisher=Andromedan.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (The only move was the Brewers from the AL Central to the [[NL Central]].) One of the plans in 2000 even featured the Texas Rangers in a six-team [[AL Central]] so that they would be with other teams in the [[Central Standard Time (North America)|Central Time Zone]] while the fledging [[Arizona Diamondbacks]] would have had to leave the [[NL West]] for the [[AL West]] to replace the Rangers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/comment/sgcol04.htm | work=USA Today | date=May 22, 2000 | accessdate=May 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 2005–06 off-season, the Florida Marlins were considering moving to [[San Antonio]] among other cities due to lack of funding for a new stadium. Another professional baseball team in Texas, whether by relocation or expansion, in either league would create greater rivalries, similar to the kind in the NBA with the [[San Antonio Spurs|Spurs]], [[Dallas Mavericks|Mavericks]], and [[Houston Rockets|Rockets]], and possible realignment issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Pinto |first=David |url=http://www.baseballmusings.com/archives/013259.php |title=Deep in the Heart of Texas |publisher=Baseball Musings |date=March 3, 2006 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Of course, the Lone Star Series wasn't conceived until {{By|2001}}, four years after [[Interleague Play]] began. It was only logical to have the Rangers and Astros matched together since they are the only MLB teams representing Texas. Since both play in two different &quot;divisions&quot; ([[AL West]] and [[NL Central]] respectively), [[Major League Baseball]] had to rectify the oversight even though Interleague Play wouldn't be rotated from division to division on a yearly basis until 2002.

On November 11, 2011, the Astros were sold to [[Jim Crane]], and also agreed to move to the [[American League West]] beginning with the 2013 season. Thus the Lone Star Series will now be considered an intradivisional rivalry instead of an Interleague series, and both the Astros and Rangers are expected to play each other more often instead of playing only six games a season.

==Lone Star Series results==
[[Image:Silver Boot.JPG|right|thumb|300px|Silver Boot 2011]]
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;
|-
!Year
!Series Winner
!Texas W
!Houston W
!Notes
|-
|[[2001 Major League Baseball season|2001]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2001 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|3
|3
|[[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Rangers]] win tiebreaker outscoring [[Astros]] 44–28 (4–5, 16–4, 5–6, 12–9, 1–2, 6–2)
|-
|[[2002 Major League Baseball season|2002]]
| style=&quot;background:#983222;&quot;|[[2002 Houston Astros season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Astros&lt;/span&gt;]]
|2
|4
|
|-
|[[2003 Major League Baseball season|2003]]
| style=&quot;background:#983222;&quot;|[[2003 Houston Astros season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Astros&lt;/span&gt;]]
|2
|4
|
|-
|[[2004 Major League Baseball season|2004]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2004 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|3
|3
|[[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Rangers]] win tiebreaker outscoring [[Astros]] 42–29 (3–1, 8–7, 0–1, 5–7, 8–10, 18–3)
|-
|[[2005 Major League Baseball season|2005]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2005 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|4
|2
|
|-
|[[2006 Major League Baseball season|2006]]
| style=&quot;background:#983222;&quot;|[[2006 Houston Astros season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Astros&lt;/span&gt;]]
|2
|4
|
|-
|[[2007 Major League Baseball season|2007]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2005 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|4
|2
|
|-
|[[2008 Major League Baseball season|2008]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2008 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|3
|3
|[[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Rangers]] win tiebreaker outscoring [[Astros]] 34–28 (16–8, 6–2, 4–5, 3–4, 3–2, 2–7)
|-
|[[2009 Major League Baseball season|2009]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2009 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|5
|1
|
|-
|[[2010 Major League Baseball season|2010]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2010 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|5
|1
|
|-
|[[2011 Major League Baseball season|2011]]
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|[[2011 Texas Rangers season|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Rangers&lt;/span&gt;]]
|4
|2
| 
|-
|'''Overall'''
| style=&quot;background:#003279;&quot;|&lt;span style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;'''Rangers (8–3)'''&lt;/span&gt;
|'''37'''
|'''29'''
|
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!
|}

==The Rivalry==
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = AstrosRet 34.PNG
|Name   = Nolan Ryan
|Number = 34
|Team   = Houston Astros
|Year   = 1996
|}}
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = RangersRet 34.PNG|95px
|Name   = Nolan Ryan
|Number = 34
|Team   = Texas Rangers (baseball){{!}}Texas Rangers
|Year   = 1996
|}}
*One year before their first official matchup in Interleague Play, both teams retired the number of Hall of Famer [[Nolan Ryan]] who had successful runs with both teams.

*According to [[Mike Lamb]] and [[Mark Teixeira]], the Rangers-Astros &quot;rivalry&quot; is more for the fans of Texas than like a bitter rivalry (e.g. [[White Sox–Cubs rivalry|Windy City Series]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;Alyson Footer&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;MLB.com |url=http://houston.astros.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20070517&amp;content_id=1971221&amp;vkey=news_hou&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=hou |title=The Official Site of The Houston Astros: News: Lone Star Series kicks off in Houston |publisher=Houston.astros.mlb.com |date=May 18, 2007 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;Todd Wills&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;Special to MLB.com |url=http://mlb.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20080516&amp;content_id=2712765&amp;vkey=news_tex&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=tex&amp;partnered=rss_tex |title=Ryan holds court on Lone Star Series &amp;#124; texasrangers.com: News |publisher=Mlb.mlb.com |date=May 16, 2008 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*On July 1, 2006, [[Gary Matthews Jr.]] made an unbelievable catch by taking away a home run from Houston Astros first baseman Mike Lamb in the top of the 8th inning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/recap?gameId=260701113 |title=ESPN – Astros vs. Rangers – Recap – July 01, 2006 |publisher=ESPN  |date=July 1, 2006 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/baseball/al/rangers/2006-07-12-matthews-jr-focus_x.htm | work=USA Today | title=Matthews Jr. a late bloomer | first=Jorge L. | last=Ortiz | date=July 13, 2006 | accessdate=May 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*While with the Astros for two years, [[Roger Clemens]] never pitched against the Rangers in twelve Lone Star Series matchups.

*Only four players have played for both the Rangers and Astros against their in-state opponent since 2001. Those players are: [[Doug Brocail]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/TEX/TEX200805160.shtml |title=May 16, 2008 Houston Astros at Texas Rangers Play by Play and Box Score |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=May 16, 2008 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/HOU/HOU200407030.shtml |title=July 3, 2004 Texas Rangers at Houston Astros Play by Play and Box Score |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=July 3, 2004 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Mike Lamb]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/HOU/HOU200106170.shtml |title=June 17, 2001 Texas Rangers at Houston Astros Box Score and Play by Play |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=June 17, 2001 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/HOU/HOU200506250.shtml |title=June 25, 2005 Texas Rangers at Houston Astros Box Score and Play by Play |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=June 25, 2005 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Richard Hidalgo]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/TEX/TEX200106080.shtml |title=June 8, 2001 Houston Astros at Texas Rangers Box Score and Play by Play |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=June 8, 2001 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/TEX/TEX200505200.shtml |title=May 20, 2005 Houston Astros at Texas Rangers Box Score and Play by Play |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=May 20, 2005 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[Ivan Rodriguez|Ivan &quot;Pudge&quot; Rodriguez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/HOU/HOU200905230.shtml |title=May 23, 2009 Texas Rangers at Houston Astros Box Score and Play by Play |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=May 23, 2009 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/TEX/TEX200206280.shtml |title=June 28, 2002 Houston Astros at Texas Rangers Play by Play and Box Score |publisher=Baseball-Reference.com |date=June 28, 2002 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

*[[Minute Maid Park]] and [[Rangers Ballpark in Arlington]] both had been using Sea Isle 1 turf through the 2008 season rather than natural grass because of the aggressive Texas summer heat. Before the 2009 season, the Astros chose to replace the previous surface in their respective ballpark with a more durable sod that requires less sunlight than other natural grass turf systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bizjournals.com/houston/stories/2008/12/08/daily14.html?f=et63&amp;ana=e_du | first=Greg | last=Barr | title=Astros find new field of dreams | date=December 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Beginning in 2008, the Lone Star Series saw for the first time two African-American managers go head-to-head against one another, the Astros' [[Cecil Cooper]] and the Rangers' [[Ron Washington]] which lasted for two years.

*There has only been one rainout in the history of the Lone Star Series. A game scheduled for Sunday June 30, 2002 at the Rangers Ballpark in Arlington was unceremoniously postponed due to rain and rescheduled for Monday September 2. The Rangers won the last matchup of the year against the Astros, 7–2, in front of a minuscule crowd of 24,468, but the Astros won the Silver Boot regardless of the outcome of the game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/recap?gameId=220902113 |title=Houston Astros vs. Texas Rangers – Recap – September 02, 2002 – ESPN |publisher=ESPN  |date=September 2, 2002 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*The contrast between the Rangers and Astros in their ballpark histories, playoff histories, and  uniform histories are very apparent. The Rangers, since 1972, have always played in open-air stadiums ([[Arlington Stadium]] and [[Rangers Ballpark in Arlington]]) while the Astros have mostly played in indoor stadiums ([[Astrodome]] and [[Minute Maid Park]]). The Rangers have had a lean postseason history with four appearances (1996, 1998, 1999, and recently 2010, winning the ALDS over the [[Tampa Bay Rays]] in five games to advance to their first ALCS against the [[New York Yankees]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/dallas/mlb/news/story?id=5679952&amp;campaign=rss&amp;source=MLBHeadlines |title=2010 ALDS: Texas Rangers celebrate with Josh Hamilton using ginger ale – ESPN Dallas |publisher=ESPN  |date=October 13, 2010 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Rangers won their first [[American League]] pennant in their 50th season on October 22, 2010 beating New York 4 games to 2,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://texas.rangers.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20101022&amp;content_id=15800740&amp;vkey=recap&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=tex |title=The Y'all Classic! Texas boots Yanks in ALCS &amp;#124; texasrangers.com: News |publisher=Texas.rangers.mlb.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  then lost to the [[San Francisco Giants]] in the World Series 4–1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2010/SPORT/11/02/baseball.series.giants.rangers/index.html |publisher=CNN | title=Giants beat Rangers to win World Series | date=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On the other side, the Astros have appeared in nine postseasons (1980, 1981, 1986, 1997, 1998, 1999, 2001, 2004, 2005) as well as one World Series in {{By|2005}}. While the Rangers have traditionally worn variations of red, white, and blue to represent the [[Flag of Texas|Lone Star flag]], the Astros have changed color schemes (e.g. Shooting Star of the late 1960s, [[Rainbow Guts]]) and logos many times throughout their history.

*Other differences, not related to baseball, include the weather during the summer, population, cultural, and allegiance preferences between the different regions of [[List of geographical regions in Texas|Texas]]. Both [[Houston, TX]] and [[Arlington, TX]] have humid subtropical climates; however, the [[Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex]] mostly has dry winds in the summer (and icy conditions in the winter, with some frost at night) compared to [[Greater Houston]]'s severe relative humidity and minimal wind except near the coast (and milder winter conditions). The Metroplex is inland located in [[North Texas]] while Houston is in the face of the [[Gulf of Mexico]] in [[Southeast Texas]].The [[Dallas, TX|city of Dallas]] has the 8th [[List of United States cities by population|largest population in the United States]] and 3rd [[Population of Texas cities in 2000|largest population in Texas]]; the city of Houston has the 4th largest population in the United States and largest population in Texas. 

*Since their inductions into Major League Baseball, there have been only 59 players to play for the Houston Astros and the Texas Rangers. Some notable names are [[Ken Caminiti]], [[Richard Hidalgo]], [[Mike Lamb]] and [[Carlos Lee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/friv/multifranchise.cgi?level=franch&amp;t1=HOU&amp;t2=TEX&amp;t3=&amp;t4=&amp;submit=Find+Players#Players |title=who played for Houston Astros and Texas Rangers |publisher=Baseball-reference.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; But out of those 59, only 3 have played their entire careers for both teams, [[Chuck Jackson (baseball)|Chuck Jackson]], [[Mike Richardt]] &amp; [[Mike Simms]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/friv/multifranchise.cgi?level=franch&amp;t1=HOU&amp;t2=TEX&amp;t3=&amp;t4=&amp;exclusively=1&amp;submit=Find+Players#Players |title=who played for Houston Astros and Texas Rangers exclusively |publisher=Baseball-reference.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*On February 6, 2008, [[Nolan Ryan]] became the Rangers' team president after being the special assistant to general manager, scouting players, and holding pitching camps with the Astros for the past three seasons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cbs11tv.com/sports/Nolan.Ryan.Rangers.2.647336.html cbs11tv.com – Nolan Ryan Named Rangers Team President]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (Nolan Ryan was also the only person to be named DHL Hometown Hero by two organizations, the Rangers and Astros, respectively.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;Kevin Yanik&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;MLB.com |url=http://twins.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20061001&amp;content_id=1694317&amp;vkey=news_hou&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=hou |title=The Official Site of The Houston Astros: News: Ryan elected Astros' Hometown Hero |publisher=Twins.mlb.com |date=September 26, 1981 |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;T.R. Sullivan&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;MLB.com |url=http://www.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20060927&amp;content_id=1686153&amp;vkey=news_tex&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=tex |title=The Official Site of The Texas Rangers: News: Ryan named Rangers Hometown Hero |publisher=Mlb.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*On August 18, 2009, the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Rangers]] acquired [[Ivan Rodriguez]] in a trade from the [[Houston Astros]] to help them down the stretch for the purpose of achieving their first playoff appearance in ten years. It will be Rodriguez's second stint with Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;T.R. Sullivan&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;MLB.com |url=http://texas.rangers.mlb.com/news/article.jsp?ymd=20090818&amp;content_id=6482172&amp;vkey=news_tex&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=tex |title=Pudge rejoins Rangers for chance to win &amp;#124; texasrangers.com: News |publisher=Texas.rangers.mlb.com |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*On September 14, 2010, the Houston Astros Triple-A affiliate, the [[Round Rock Express]], announced that they would become the Texas Rangers new minor league affiliate. This left the Houston Astros without a Triple-A team and the Texas Rangers old Triple-A team, the [[Oklahoma City RedHawks]] without a parent club. On September 20, 2010, the Houston Astros made the Oklahoma City RedHawks their own affiliate. These changes went in to effect immediately due to neither team making the play-offs but changes won't be seen until the 2011 Season.

*One David Meyer (of Dallas) and James Grubb (of Houston) have an annual wager on the Silver Boot, which began in 2006.  The conditions of the deal will auto renew for a term of 50 years.

*One Eliberto Quinonez (of Fort Worth) and Augustus &quot;Gus&quot; Presas (of Houston) ALSO have an annual wager on the Silver Boot, which began in 2005.  Their conditions of the deal will auto renew for a term of 51 years.  The conditions of this deal constitute that the loser deliver one beef taco to the winner via the back of a 1987 Ford pick-up truck.

==See also==
*[[Governor's Cup (Texas)]] (NFL)
*[[Texas Derby]] (MLS)

==Sources ==
*{{cite book|title=Texas Almanac 2008–2009|author=The Dallas Morning News|year=2008}}
*{{cite book|title=Southwest Conference's Greatest Hits|first=Neal|last=Farmer|year=1996}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{Houston Astros}}
{{Texas Rangers}}
{{MLB rivalries}}

[[Category:Sports in Houston, Texas]]
[[Category:Sports in the Dallas – Fort Worth Metroplex]]
[[Category:Houston Astros]]
[[Category:Texas Rangers (baseball)]]
[[Category:Baseball in Texas]]
[[Category:Interleague play]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball rivalries]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
