<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22556159" ns="0" title="Ateneo School of Science and Engineering"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University
|name             = Ateneo de Manila University&lt;br&gt;School of Science and Engineering
|native_name      = Pamantasang Ateneo de Manila&lt;br&gt;Paaralan ng Agham at Inhenyeriya
|image            = 
|established      = 2000
|type             = Roman Catholic
|dean             = Fabian M. Dayrit, M.A., Ph.D.
|location         = [[Ateneo de Manila University]], Loyola Heights, [[Quezon City]], [[Metro Manila]], {{PHL}}
|website= [http://sose.ateneo.edu sose.ateneo.edu]
}}

The '''Ateneo de Manila School of Science and Engineering''' is one of the four [[Loyola Schools]] of the [[Ateneo de Manila University]].

==History==
{| style=&quot;float:right; margin:1em 1em 1em 1em; width:24em; border: 1px solid #a0a0a0; padding: 2px; bg-color=yellow; text-align:right;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#0260A8&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|&lt;font color=&quot;FFFFFF&quot;&gt;'''Deans of the Ateneo School of Science and Engineering'''&lt;/font&gt;
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''[[Ma. Assunta Cuyegkeng|Dr. Ma. Assunta C. Cuyegkeng]]&lt;ref&gt;Acting Dean&lt;/ref&gt;'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''[[Fabian Dayrit|Dr. Fabian M. Dayrit]] present'''
|}

In 2000, the School of Arts and Sciences of the university, which comprises the College and the Graduate School, restructured into the four Loyola Schools of Humanities, Management, Science and Engineering, and Social Sciences. The School of Science and Engineering was officially headed by [[Ma. Assunta Cuyegkeng|Dr. Ma. Assunta C. Cuyegkeng]], a professor of [[chemistry]] and the former Vice President for the Loyola Schools, as the acting dean. [[Fabian Dayrit|Dr. Fabian M. Dayrit]], also a professor of chemistry, took over and currently serves as the dean of the school.

The dean's office, the Mathematics and Biology Departments, the Health Sciences Program Office, and many of the school's science laboratories are located in the Science Education Complex. The other departments are located at Schmitt Hall (Chemistry), the Manila Observatory (Environmental Science), and Faura Hall (DISCS, ECCE, and Physics).

==Academic Departments==
[[Image:ScienceEducationComplex.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The Science Education Complex]]
&lt;ref&gt;http://sose.ateneo.edu/module.php?LM=departments&amp;id=1204720424274&amp;pid=1204706943725&lt;/ref&gt;
===Biology===
*Bachelor of Science in Biology
*Bachelor of Science in Life Sciences
*Master of Biology
*Master in Biology Education (offered with the Department of Education, School of Social Sciences)
*Master of Science in Biology

===Chemistry===
*Bachelor of Science in Chemistry
*Bachelor of Science in Chemistry and Bachelor of Science in Applied Computer Systems (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Bachelor of Science in Chemistry and Bachelor of Science in Materials Science Engineering (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Bachelor of Science in Management of Applied Chemistry (offered with the John Gokongwei School of Management)
*Bachelor of Science and Master of Science in Chemistry (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Master of Chemistry
*Master of Science in Chemistry
*Master of Science in Chemistry Education (offered with the Department of Education, School of Social Sciences)
*Master of Science in Science Education (offered with the Department of Education, School of Social Sciences)
*Doctor of Philosophy in Chemistry

===Electronics, Communications, and Computer Engineering===
&lt;ref&gt;http://ohm.ecce.admu.edu.ph/wiki/bin/view/Main/DegreePrograms&lt;/ref&gt;
*Bachelor of Science in Electronics and Communications Engineering
*Bachelor of Science in Computer Engineering 
*Master of Science in Electronics Engineering

===Environmental Science===
*Bachelor of Science in Environmental Science
*Master in Environmental Management (offered with the [[University of San Francisco]])
*Master of Science in Environmental Science
*Master of Science in Atmospheric Science

===Information Systems and Computer Science===
*Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
*Bachelor of Science in Management Information Systems (offered with the John Gokongwei School of Management)
*Bachelor of Science in Management Information Systems and Master of Science in Computer Science (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Bachelor of Science and Master of Science in Computer Science (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Master of Science in Computer Science
*Master of Information Technology
*Doctor of Philosophy in Computer Science

===Mathematics===
*Bachelor of Science in Mathematics
*Bachelor of Science in Applied Mathematics Major in Mathematical Finance
*Bachelor of Science and Master of Applied Mathematics Major in Mathematical Finance (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Master of Mathematics
*Master of Science in Mathematics Education (offered with the Department of Education, School of Social Sciences)
*Master of Science in Mathematics
*Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics

===Physics===
*Bachelor of Science in Physics
*Bachelor of Science in Physics and Bachelor of Science in Applied Computer Systems (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Bachelor of Science in Physics and Bachelor of Science in Materials Science Engineering (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Bachelor of Science and Master of Science in Physics (dual-degree, five-year course)
*Master of Physics Education (offered with the Department of Education, School of Social Sciences)
*Master of Science in Physics
*Doctor of Philosophy in Physics

===Health Sciences Program===
*Bachelor of Science in Health Sciences (offered with the [[Ateneo School of Medicine and Public Health]])

==Notes and references==
{{Reflist}}

{{Ateneo de Manila University}}
[[Category:Ateneo de Manila University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
