<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22671551" ns="0" title="Translink Cup"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{ infobox football tournament
| caption              = Scott McDonald holding the Translink Cup in 2009 after captaining Celtic to the win
| current              = [[2010–11_Brisbane_Roar_season#Translink_Cup|2010 Translink Cup]]
| founded              = 2007
| region               = {{AUS}}
| current champions    = {{flagicon|England}} '''[[Everton F.C.|Everton]]''' (1st title)
| most successful club = [[File:QueenslandRoarColours.png|20px]] '''{{ALeague BR}}''' (2 titles)
}}

The '''Translink Cup''' also known as the '''Roar against Racism trophy''' is an [[Australia]]n [[football (soccer)|association football]] invitational trophy contested in an annual charity friendly match hosted by [[Brisbane Roar]] of the [[Hyundai A-League]] and is held at [[Suncorp Stadium]], often used as a pre-season match for both teams to warm them up for the regular season, the match is also the 'Roar Against Racism' match to promote the decline of racism on the football pitch. All proceeds from the match goes to the 'Let's kick racism out of football' charity and a donation is also made by [[TransLink (South East Queensland)|Translink]] who sponsors and has naming rights to the cup.

==Competition==
The competition was little known for the first 2 years of format with Queensland Roar booking under-rated overseas teams such as [[Supersport United]] with the game pulling only just over 12,000 fans into Suncorp Stadium. The competition got major media publicity in 2009 when talk of English [[Premier League]] clubs [[Fulham FC|Fulham]] or [[Everton FC|Everton]] would tour to Brisbane to play against Queensland Roar in the Translink Cup. But original plans for Queensland to play Fulham were scrapped after the team went into a financial crisis. The 2009 version was then locked in with [[Scottish Premier League]] club [[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]] for 12 July&lt;ref&gt;http://www.foxsports.com.au/story/0,8659,25407071-5000940,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;. The Game was a huge success after new Celtic Manager [[Tony Mowbray]] decided to use the game as a warm-up for [[UEFA Champions League]] qualifiers and bring many of his first team squad to Brisbane, this included Polish international goalkeeper [[Artur Boruc]], former Barcelona player [[Marc Crosas]], former Manchester City star and Greek international striker [[Georgios Samaras]], [[Andreas Hinkel]] who has been capped by Germany 19 times, Scottish international [[Shaun Maloney]] and the team was captained by Australian Star [[Scott McDonald]]. Brisbane were eventually overpowered by the Scottish giants 3-0 with New Zealand International [[Chris Killen]] picking up the Man of the Match award after scoring a double in quick succession. The match was also notable as 3 Brisbane Roar players ([[Craig Moore]], [[Charlie Miller]] and [[Bob Malcolm]]) had previously played for [[Rangers FC|Rangers]] for a combined total of 483 appearances. Over 31,000 people from around the globe turned up to the match, with many of the 31,000  Celtic supporters.

=== 2007 ===

The inaugural translink cup was fought between [[Queensland Roar]] and [[Supersport United]] at [[Suncorp Stadium]], the game started off at a high tempo with Simon Lynch creating a close-range shot only to be saved by the keeper, Reinaldo eventually opened the scoring in the 12th minute after a a low header from a corner, he doubled the home sides lead in the 37 minute after dazziling footwork to get past a back. Mashego gave Supersport an almost instant reply with a low and fast shot into the bottom corner of the net in the 39th minute. By Half-Time Queensland Roar were the better team. Queensland came back scoring 7 minutes into the second half through prolific striker [[Simon Lynch (footballer)|Simon Lynch]]. Mashego came close to scoring a double in the 63rd minuted after his shot hit the crossbar, Queensland Roar finished off the scoring in the 70th minuted through newly signed youth player [[Tahj Minniecon]]. Queensland Roar 4, Supersport United 1.

Facts:
* This was Tahj Minniecon's first game in Queensland Roar colours
* Queensland Roar won their first Translink Cup
* This was Queensland Roar first major or minor silverware
* Reinaldo was awarded the man of the match award

=== 2008 ===

Queensland Roars Against Racism clash started with both [[Matt McKay]] and [[Serginho van Dijk]] going close to scoring in the opening 20 minutes before Smits opened the scoring on 35 minutes. The youngster outjumped Fabio to meet Hyuk-Su Seo’s cross and drilled the football past the keeper.  Frank Farina's men responded with McKay doubling the lead just before the break. Palmeiras youngster Portela found the bottom corner of the roar’s goal through a free kick in the 57th minute. Palmeiras had a goal ruled out on 62 minutes with Valdivia ruled offside as he turned in a free kick from Portela. Farina made changes after the goal, bringing on Robbie Kruse and Scottish trialist Charlie Miller. Five minutes from the end Miller went close with a volley thudding against the crossbar. But the former Scottish international showed his ability as a provider, beating two defenders before teeing up Murdocca to thump home the third goal in injury time. Queensland Roar 3, Palmeiras B 1

Facts:
* This was Charlie Miller's and Serginho van Dijk's debut game for the Roar
* Queensland Roar win their second Translink Cup
* Portela from Palmeiras B was awarded the man of the match award

=== 2009 ===

Celtic Manager [[Tony Mowbray]] decided to use the game as a warm-up for [[European Champions League]] qualifiers and brought a near full-strength squad for the fixture, including [[Artur Boruc]], [[Lee Naylor (footballer)|Lee Naylor]], [[Stephen McManus]], [[Gary Caldwell]], [[Massimo Donati]], [[Marc Crosas]], [[Georgios Samaras]], [[Andreas Hinkel]], [[Shaun Maloney]] and [[Scott McDonald]].

The game started fast and furious and it looked as though Brisbane Roar could overcome the Glasgow giants with Brisbane youngster, [[Robbie Kruse]] having 3 shots in the opening 10 minutes that force Celtic goalkeeper [[Artur Boruc]] into making many acrobatic saves. Celtic also forced Brisbane Roar goalkeeper [[Liam Reddy]] also made two notacible saves in the first 30 minutes. The pace of the game eventually eased up after the half-hour mark and Celtic took advantage of this with [[New Zealand national football team|New Zealand]] international [[Chris Killen]] scoring from a header in the 39th minute. He managed to get his second only 2 minutes later with a low shot going under Liam Reddy. At half-time Scottish trialist [[Bob Malcolm]] came on to the pitch where he showed glimpses of his ability with the former [[Rangers FC|Rangers]] man making a few good tackles to break up play. [[Japan national football team|Japanese]] international [[Koki Mizuno]] came on at half time along with [[Georgios Samaras]]. Mizuno mad an almost instant impact scoring with a powerful header in the 50th minute to seal the win for Celtic. Another high point of the game for Celtic fans was when [[Marc-Antoine Fortune]] came onto the field in the 70th minute to make his debut for Celtic after recently signing for the club from [[FC Nancy]] for £3.5 million. Celtic controlled the game for majority of the second half limiting Brisbane Roar to only one shot on goal. The game ended after one minute of injury time and a minor injury to celtic youngster [[Milan Misun]]. Celtic FC 3, Brisbane Roar 0.

Facts:
* Bob Malcolm and Luke Brattan made their debuts for Brisbane Roar
* Celtic FC won their first Translink Cup
* Chris Killen won the man of the match award
* This was Tony Mowbray's first game as manager of Celtic
* Marc-Antoine Fortune made his debut for Celtic
* The match broke the record for highest attendance at a Translink Cup Match
* It is also notable as 3 Brisbane Roar players ([[Craig Moore]], [[Charlie Miller]] and Bob Malcolm) had previously played for Rangers - Celtic's [[Old Firm|arch rivals]] in Scotland - for a combined total of 483 appearances.

=== 2010 ===

[[Everton F.C.|Everton]]'s third game on tour in [[2010–11_Everton_F.C._season#Pre-season_friendlies|Australia]] included [[Jermaine Beckford|Jermaine Beckford's]] first start for the blues.
[[Jack Rodwell]] scored his second goal of the tour to give [[Everton F.C.|Everton]] the lead four minutes into the second half.
The Toffees appeared to be in cruise control until [[Brisbane Roar|Roar]] substitute [[Kosta Barbarouses]] equalised in the 66th minute.
But [[Magaye Gueye]] turned in [[Jose Baxter|Jose Baxter’s]] tantalising cross from close range seven minutes from time.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mirrorfootball.co.uk/news/Brisbane-Roar-1-2-Everton-Sunday-Mirror-match-report-Magaye-Gueye-on-target-as-Everton-complete-clean-sweep-of-Australian-tour-article529635.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2011 ===
It was announced by the Roar on July 5 that the club would not be playing an overseas team in a match for the Translink Cup.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.brisbaneroar.com.au/default.aspx?s=newsdisplay&amp;id=40238&lt;/ref&gt;

==Results==
===Match===
==== 2007 ====
----
{{footballbox
  | date = 1 July 2007&lt;br/&gt;20:00 [[UTC+10]]
  | team1 = {{ALeague QR}}
  | score =  4 – 1
  | team2 = {{flagicon|South Africa}}[[Supersport United]]
  | goals1 = [[Reinaldo]] {{goal|12', 37}}&lt;br/&gt; [[Simon Lynch (footballer)|Lynch]] {{goal|52}}&lt;br/&gt; [[Tahj Minniecon|Minniecon]] {{goal|70}}
  | goals2 = Mashego {{goal|39}}
  | stadium = [[Suncorp Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brisbane]], [[Queensland]]
  | attendance = 12,000+
  | referee = [[Matthew Breeze]]
}}

==== 2008 ====
----
{{footballbox
  | date = 12 July 2008&lt;br /&gt;19:00 [[UTC+10]]
  | team1 = {{ALeague QR}}
  | score = 3 &amp;ndash; 1
  | report = [http://www.qldroar.com.au/default.aspx?s=qldfc_news_item&amp;id=22786 (Report)]
  | team2 = {{flagicon|BRA}}  [[Sociedade Esportiva Palmeiras B|Palmeiras B]]
  | goals1 = [[Tim Smits|Smits]] {{Goal|35}} &lt;br/&gt; [[Matt McKay|McKay]] {{Goal|43}} &lt;br/&gt; [[Massimo Murdocca|Murdocca]] {{Goal|90+2}}
  | goals2 = Portela {{Goal|57}}
  | stadium = [[Suncorp Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brisbane]], [[Queensland]]
  | attendance = 12,841
  | referee = [[Peter Green (referee)|Peter Green]]
}}

==== 2009 ====
----
{{footballbox
  | date = 12 July 2009&lt;br /&gt;19:00 [[UTC+10]]
  | team1 = {{ALeague BR}}
  | score =  0 – 3 
  | report = [http://www.brisbaneroar.com.au/default.aspx?s=newsdisplay&amp;id=28156 (Report)]  
  | team2 = {{flagicon|Scotland}}  [[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]]
  | goals1 = 
  | goals2 = [[Chris Killen|Killen]] {{Goal|39', 41}} &lt;br/&gt;[[Koki Mizuno|Mizuno]], {{Goal|50}}
  | stadium = [[Suncorp Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brisbane]], [[Queensland]]
  | attendance = 31,340
  | referee = [[Peter Green (referee)|Peter Green]]
}}

==== 2010 ====
----
{{footballbox
  | date = 10 July 2010&lt;br /&gt;19:00 [[UTC+10]]
  | team1 = {{ALeague BR}}
  | score =  1 – 2  
  | report =   
  | team2 = {{flagicon|ENG}}  [[Everton F.C.|Everton]]
  | goals1 = [[Kosta Barbarouses|Barbarouses]] {{Goal|66}}
  | goals2 = [[Jack Rodwell|Rodwell]] {{Goal|49}} &lt;br/&gt;[[Magaye Gueye|Gueye]] {{Goal|83}}
  | stadium = [[Suncorp Stadium]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brisbane]], [[Queensland]]
  | attendance = 19,786
  | referee = 
}}

===Summaries===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%; text-align: center;&quot;
|-
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; width=&quot;5%&quot;|Year
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; width=&quot;3%&quot;|Crowd
!width=&quot;1%&quot; rowspan=&quot;10&quot;|
!colspan=&quot;3&quot;|Match
|-
!width=&quot;15%&quot;|Home Team
!width=&quot;10%&quot;|Score
!width=&quot;15%&quot;|Away Team
|-
|2007&lt;br /&gt;''[[Queensland_Roar_season_2007-08#Pre-season|Details]]''
|''12,000+''
|'''{{flagicon|Australia}}''' ''[[Brisbane Roar FC|Queensland Roar]]''
|'''4–1'''
|'''{{flagicon|South Africa}}''' ''[[Supersport United]]''
|-style=&quot;background: #D0E6FF;&quot;
|-
|2008&lt;br /&gt;''[[Queensland_Roar_season_2008-09#Translink_Cup|Details]]''
|''12,841''
|'''{{flagicon|Australia}}''' ''[[Brisbane Roar FC|Queensland Roar]]''
|'''3–1'''
|'''{{flagicon|Brazil}}''' ''[[Palmeiras B]]''
|-style=&quot;background: #D0E6FF;&quot;
|-
|2009&lt;br /&gt;''[[Brisbane_Roar_season_2009-10#Pre-Season|Details]]''
|''31,430 ''
|'''{{flagicon|Australia}}''' ''[[Brisbane Roar FC|Brisbane Roar]]''
|''' 0-3'''
|'''{{flagicon|Scotland}}''' ''[[Celtic F.C.|Celtic]]''
|-style=&quot;background: #D0E6FF;&quot;
|-
|2010&lt;br /&gt;''[[Brisbane Roar season 2010-11|Details]]''
|''19,786 ''
|'''{{flagicon|Australia}}''' ''[[Brisbane Roar FC|Brisbane Roar]]''
|''' 1-2 '''
|'''{{flagicon|ENG}}''' ''[[Everton F.C.|Everton]]''
|-style=&quot;background: #D0E6FF;&quot;
|}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Brisbane Roar]]
[[Category:International club soccer competitions hosted by Australia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
