<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22679" ns="0" title="Office of Strategic Services"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Government agency
|agency_name     = Office of Strategic Services
|nativename      = OSS
|nativename_a    =
|nativename_r    =
|logo            = OSSInsignia.gif
|logo_width      = 150px
|logo_caption    = OSS Shoulder Insignia
|seal            =
|seal_width      = 
|seal_caption    = 
|formed          = June 13, 1942
|preceding1      =
|preceding2      =
|dissolved       = September 20, 1945
|superseding     = [[Central Intelligence Agency]]
|jurisdiction    =
|headquarters    =
|employees       = 13,000 estimated&lt;ref&gt;Dawidoff, p. 240&lt;/ref&gt;
|budget          =
|minister1_name  =
|minister1_pfo   =
|minister2_name  =
|minister2_pfo   =
|chief1_name     = Major General [[William Joseph Donovan]]
|chief1_position = Co-ordinator of Information
|chief2_name     = Brigadier General John Magruder
|chief2_position = Director for Intelligence
|parent_agency   =
|child1_agency   =
|child2_agency   =
|website         =
|footnotes       =
}}

The '''Office of Strategic Services''' ('''OSS''') was a [[United States]] [[intelligence agency]] formed during [[World War II]]. It was the wartime intelligence agency, and it was a predecessor of the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA). The OSS was formed in order to coordinate [[espionage]] activities behind enemy lines for the branches of the [[United States Armed Forces]].

==Origins and activities==
Prior to the formation of the OSS (the American version of the British [[Secret Intelligence Service]] and [[Special Operations Executive]]), American intelligence had been conducted on an ad-hoc basis by the various departments of the executive branch, including the [[United States Department of State|State]], [[United States Department of the Treasury|Treasury]], [[United States Department of the Navy|Navy]], and [[United States Department of War|War]] Departments. They had no overall direction, coordination, or control. The [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] and [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] had separate code-breaking departments ([[Signals Intelligence Service]] and [[OP-20-G]]). Also, the original code-breaking operation of the State Department, [[Black Chamber|MI-8]], run by [[Herbert Yardley]], had been shut down in 1929 by [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[Henry Stimson]], deeming it an inappropriate function for the diplomatic arm, because &quot;gentlemen don't read each other's mail&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Stimson, Henry L. ''On Active Service in Peace and War'' (1948). ''per'' ''Bartlett's Familiar Quotations'', 16th ed.&lt;/ref&gt; 

President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] was concerned about American intelligence deficiencies. On the suggestion of Canadian/British spymaster [[William Stephenson]], the senior British intelligence officer in the western hemisphere, Roosevelt requested that [[William J. Donovan]] draft a plan for an intelligence service. Colonel Donovan was employed to evaluate the global military position in order to offer suggestions concerning American intelligence requirements because the U.S. did not have a central intelligence agency. After submitting his work, &quot;Memorandum of Establishment of Service of Strategic Information,&quot; Colonel Donovan was appointed as the &quot;Co-ordinator of Information&quot; in July 1941.

[[Image:Donovan reviews OGs.jpg|thumb|left|350px|General William J. Donovan reviews Operational Group members in [[Bethesda, Maryland]] prior to their departure for China in 1945]] 

The Office of Strategic Services was established by a Presidential military order issued by President Roosevelt on June 13, 1942, to collect and analyze strategic information required by the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]] and to conduct special operations not assigned to other agencies. During the War, the OSS supplied policy makers with facts and estimates, but the OSS never had jurisdiction over all foreign intelligence activities. The [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] was responsible for intelligence work in [[Latin America]], and the Army and Navy guarded their areas of responsibility.

From 1943–1945, the OSS played a major role in training [[Kuomintang]] troops in [[China]] and [[Burma]], and recruited [[Jingpo people|Kachin]], and other indigenous irregular forces for sabotage as well as guides for Allied forces in [[China Burma India Theater of World War II|Burma]] fighting the Japanese Army.  Among other activities, the OSS helped arm, train and supply [[resistance movement]]s, including [[Mao Zedong]]'s [[People's Liberation Army|Red Army]] in China and the [[Viet Minh]] in [[French Indochina]], in areas [[military occupation|occupied]] by the [[Axis powers]] during [[World War II]]. The OSS also recruited and ran one of the war's most important spies, the German diplomat [[Fritz Kolbe]]. Other functions of the OSS included the use of [[propaganda]], [[espionage]], [[subversion]], and post-war planning.

The OSS purchased Soviet code and cipher material (or Finnish information on them) from émigré [[Finnish army]] officers in late 1944. Secretary of State [[Edward Stettinius, Jr.]], protested that this violated an agreement President Roosevelt made with the Soviet Union not to interfere with Soviet cipher traffic from the United States. General Donovan might have copied the papers before returning them the following January, but there is no record of [[Arlington Hall]]'s receiving them, and CIA and NSA archives have no surviving copies. This codebook was in fact used as part of the [[Venona]] [[decryption]] effort, which helped uncover large-scale Soviet espionage in [[North America]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Christopher Andrew (historian)|Andrew, Christopher]] and [[Vasili Mitrokhin|Mitrokhin, Vasili]], ''The Mitrokhin Archive, Volume 1: The KGB in Europe and the West'', 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;

One of the greatest accomplishments of the OSS during World War II was its penetration of [[Nazi Germany]] by OSS operatives. The OSS was responsible for training German and Austrian individuals for missions inside Germany. Some of these agents included exiled communists and Socialist party members, labor activists, anti-Nazi prisoners-of-war, and German and Jewish refugees. At the height of its influence during World War II, the OSS employed almost 24,000 people.&lt;ref name=cnn&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2008/US/08/14/spies.revealed.ap/index.html &quot;Chef Julia Child, others part of WWII spy network&quot;], [[CNN]], 2008-08-14&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:George Musulin.jpg|thumb|225px|OSS 1st Lieutenant [[George Musulin]] behind enemy lines in German-occupied Serbia, as Chetnik, during his first mission on November 1943. His second misson was [[Operation Halyard|Halyard]]]]

In 1943, the Office of Strategic Services set up operations in Istanbul.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hassell, A page 158&quot;&gt;Hassell and McCrae, p.158&lt;/ref&gt; Turkey, as a neutral country during the Second World War, was a place where both the Axis and Allied powers sought to set up networks of spies. The railroads connecting [[central Asia]] with [[Europe]] as well as Turkey's close proximity to the Balkan states placed it at a crossroads of intelligence gathering. The goal of the OSS Istanbul operation called Project Net-1 was to infiltrate and extenuate subversive action in the old Ottoman and [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hassell, A page 158&quot;/&gt;

Head of operations at OSS Istanbul was a banker from Chicago named Lanning &quot;Packy&quot; Macfarland who maintained the cover story as a banker for the American [[lend-lease program]].&lt;ref&gt;Hassell and MacRae, p.159&lt;/ref&gt; Macfarland hired Alfred Schwarz, a Czechoslovakian engineer and businessman who came to be known as &quot;Dogwood&quot; and ended up establishing the notorious Dogwood information chain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hassell, A page 166&quot;&gt;Hassell and MacRae, p.166&lt;/ref&gt; Dogwood in turn hired a personal assistant named Walter Arndt and established himself as an employee of the Istanbul Western Electrik Kompani.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hassell, A page 166&quot;/&gt; Through Schwartz and Arndt the OSS was able to infiltrate [[anti-fascist]] groups in Austria, Hungary and Germany. Schwartz was able to convince Romanian, Bulgarian, Hungarian and Swiss diplomatic couriers to smuggle American intelligence information into these territories and establish contact with elements antagonistic to the Nazis and their collaborators.&lt;ref&gt;Hassell and MacRae, p.167&lt;/ref&gt; Couriers and agents memorized information and produced analytical reports; when they were not able to memorize effectively they recorded information on [[microfilm]] and hid it in their shoes or hollowed pencils.&lt;ref name=rubin&gt;Rubin, B: ''Istanbul Intrigues'', page 168. Pharos Books, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; Through this process information about the Nazi regime made its way to Macfarland and the OSS in Istanbul and eventually to Washington.

While the OSS &quot;Dogwood-chain&quot; produced a lot of information, its reliability was increasingly questioned by British intelligence. Eventually by May 1944 through collaboration between the OSS, British intelligence, Cairo and Washington the entire &quot;Dogwood-chain&quot; was found to be unreliable and dangerous.&lt;ref name=rubin /&gt; Planting phony information into the OSS was intended to misdirect the resources of the Allies. Schwartz's &quot;Dogwood – chain&quot; which was the largest American intelligence gathering tool in occupied territory, was shortly thereafter shut down.&lt;ref&gt;Hassell and MacRae, p.184&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1942, a young physician named Christian J. Lambertsen invented the first [[Scuba set|Self-contained Underwater Breathing Apparatus]] (SCUBA) and demonstrated it to OSS &amp;ndash; after already being rejected by the U.S. Navy &amp;ndash; in a pool at a hotel in Washington D.C.&lt;ref name=cjl&gt;Shapiro, T. Rees. [http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/02/18/AR2011021802873.html &quot;Christian J. Lambertsen, OSS officer who created early scuba device, dies at 93&quot;]. ''[[Washington Post]]'' (February 18, 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; The OSS not only bought into the concept, they hired Lambertsen to lead the program and build up the dive element of their maritime unit.&lt;ref name=cjl /&gt;

==Transformation into the CIA==
One month after the war was won in the [[Pacific Theater of Operations]], on September 20, 1945, the 33rd U.S. President [[Harry S Truman]] signed an [[Executive order (United States)|Executive Order]] which came into effect as of October 1, 1945. Thus in the following days from September 20, 1945 the functions of the OSS were split between the [[Department of State]] and the [[United States Department of War|Department of War]]. The State Department received the Research and Analysis Branch of OSS which was renamed the Interim Research and Intelligence Service or ([[IRIS]]) and headed by U.S. Army Colonel Alfred McCormack. This was later renamed the [[Bureau of Intelligence and Research]].

The War Department took over the [[Secret Intelligence Branch|Secret Intelligence]] (SI) and [[counter-espionage|Counter-Espionage]] (X-2) Branches, which were then housed in a new office created for just this purpose—the [[Strategic Services Unit]] (SSU). The Secretary of War appointed Brigadier General [[John Magruder (Brigadier General)|John Magruder]] (formerly Donovan's Deputy Director for Intelligence in OSS) as the director to oversee the liquidation of the OSS, and more importantly, the preservation of the clandestine intelligence capability of the OSS.

In January 1946, President Truman created the Central Intelligence Group (CIG) which was the direct precursor to the CIA. The assets of the SSU, which now constituted a streamlined &quot;nucleus&quot; of clandestine intelligence was transferred to the CIG in mid-1946 and reconstituted as the Office of Special Operations (OSO). Next, the [[National Security Act of 1947]] established the United States's first permanent peacetime intelligence agency, the [[Central Intelligence Agency]], which then took up the functions of the OSS.  The direct descendant of the paramilitary component of the OSS is the [[Special Activities Division]] of the CIA.&lt;ref&gt;Waller, Douglas &quot;CIA's Secret Army&quot;, ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Facilities==
[[Prince William Forest Park]] (then known as Chopawamsic Recreational Demonstration Area) was the site of an OSS training camp that operated from 1942 to 1945. Area &quot;C&quot;, consisting of approximately {{convert|6,000|acre|km2}}, was used extensively for communications training, whereas Area &quot;A&quot; was use for training some of the OGs.  [[Catoctin Mountain Park]], now the location of [[Camp David]], was the site of OSS training Area &quot;B.&quot; [[Congressional Country Club]] (Area F) in [[Bethesda, Maryland|Bethesda]], MD was the primary OSS training facility.

The [[London]] branch of the OSS, its first overseas facility, was at 70, Grosvenor Street, W1. 
 
The Facilities of the [[Catalina Island Marine Institute]] at Toyon Bay on Santa Catalina Island, Calif., are composed (in part) of a former OSS survival training camp.

The National Park Service commissioned a study of OSS National Park training facilities by Professor John Chambers of Rutgers University.

[[Camp X]], near [[Oshawa]], [[Ontario]], [[Canada]], where an &quot;assassination and elimination&quot; training program was operated by the OSS. It was dubbed &quot;the school of mayhem and murder&quot; by George Hunter White who trained at the facility in the 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;Albarelli, H.A. [http://aterriblemistake.com ''A Terrible Mistake:The Murder of Frank Olson and the CIA’s Secret Cold War Experiments''] 2009. p.67 ISBN 0977795373&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personnel==
The names of all OSS personnel and documents of their OSS service, previously a closely guarded secret, were released by the US [[National Archives and Records Administration|National Archives]] on August 14, 2008.  Among the 24,000 names were those of [[Julia Child]], [[Arthur Goldberg]], [[Saul K. Padover]], [[Arthur Schlesinger, Jr.]], [[Bruce Sundlun]], and [[John Ford]].&lt;ref name=cnn /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blackledge, Brett J. and Herschaft, Randy [http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080814/ap_on_go_ot/spies_revealed  , &quot;Documents: Julia Child part of WW II-era spy ring&quot;], [[Associated Press]]&lt;/ref&gt;  The 750,000 pages in the 35,000 personnel files include applications of people who were not recruited or hired, as well as the service records of those who were.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archives.gov/research/arc/topics/oss-personnel/ Office of Strategic Services Personnel Files from World War II] – overview page, search links, digital excerpts;
[http://research.archives.gov/description/1593270 ARC Identifier 1593270: Personnel Files, compiled 1942 - 1945, documenting the period 1941 - 1945], from Record Group 226: Records of the Office of Strategic Services, 1919 - 2002; [http://www.archives.gov/iwg/declassified-records/rg-226-oss/personnel-database.pdf Personnel database] – complete list&lt;/ref&gt;

===Moe Berg===
[[File:MoeBergGoudeycard.jpg|thumb|right|225px|[[Major league baseball]] player [[Moe Berg]] of the [[Boston Red Sox]] was an OSS agent]]
Major League Baseball player [[Moe Berg]], a graduate of [[Princeton University]] and [[Columbia Law School]], was recruited by [[Nelson Rockefeller]] (the coordinator of the U.S. [[Office of Inter-American Affairs]]) and then by the OSS in 1943 because of his language skills.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oSjrZv0rOMQC&amp;pg=PA47&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg+%22rockefeller%22&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg%20%22rockefeller%22&amp;f=false |title=The rock, the curse, and the hub: a random history of Boston sports |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=2005 |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1Jc9wBsImOIC&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg+%22rockefeller%22&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg%20%22rockefeller%22&amp;f=false |title=Encyclopedia of the Central Intelligence Agency  |publisher=Infobase Publishing|year=2003 |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hahn&gt;Hahn, Gilbert, Jr. [http://books.google.com/books?id=6mZWVFsxFg8C&amp;pg=PA86&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UxRbTfOPC4SclgebufHJDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''The Notebook of an Amateur Politician'']. Lanham, Maryland: Lexington Books, 2002. p. 86 ISBN 0-7391-0405-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Redmont, Robert. [http://books.google.com/books?id=IRs-CCUZhwAC&amp;pg=PA144&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UxRbTfOPC4SclgebufHJDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''The Red Sox Encyclopedia'']. Sports Publishing, 2002. p. 144. ISBN 1-58261-244-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=boxerman&gt;Boxerman, Burton Alan and Boxerman, Benita W. [http://books.google.com/books?id=qJEQTaE7JEAC&amp;pg=PA109&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UxRbTfOPC4SclgebufHJDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CE0Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Jews and Baseball: Entering the American mainstream, 1871–1948''] Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland, 2006. p. 109 ISBN 978-0-7864-2828-1&lt;/ref&gt;  He spoke unaccented German, as well as Italian, French, Spanish, Japanese, Greek, Russian, Hebrew, and Latin, in addition to English.&lt;ref name=stitch&gt;Elston, Gene [http://books.google.com/books?id=e2XTiZwdp0AC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=pxZbTd2fLIS8lQeD-rX7DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''A Stitch in Time: A Baseball Chronology'']. Houston, Texas: Halcyon, 2001. p.12. ISBN 1-931-823-33-2&lt;/ref&gt;  He was given the code name &quot;Remus&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ZG2P4hC8JBYC&amp;pg=PA253&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=From Hitler's doorstep: the wartime intelligence reports of Allen Dulles, 1942-1945|publisher= Penn State Press|date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; was assigned to the [[Secret Intelligence Branch|Secret Intelligence]] branch, and took part in missions in the Caribbean, South America, France, and England.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=8dKozfsRRH4C&amp;pg=PA19&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Baseball's Dead of World War II: A Roster of Professional Players Who Died in Service  |publisher=McFarland |year=2009 |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He was also involved in the [[Balkans Campaign (World War II)|Balkans Campaign]], parachuting into [[Yugoslavia#Yugoslavia during the Second World War|Yugoslavia]] to evaluate the various [[Yugoslav Front of World War II|resistance groups]] operating against the Nazis, and determining after meeting with him that [[Josip Broz Tito|Tito]]'s were the most effective.&lt;ref&gt;Dawidoff, pp.153–55&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=XOPZ2nA6OcEC&amp;pg=PA155&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Blessings of freedom: chapters in American Jewish history |publisher=|year= 2002|accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He next dropped behind German lines in occupied Norway, where he met with Free Norwegian guerrillas and gathered information leading to the destruction of a German plant being used to develop atomic weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;google1&quot;/&gt;

Later, he was briefed in [[nuclear physics]], provided a [[Beretta]] revolver and a [[cyanide pill]] (to kill himself if necessary), and sent to [[Zurich, Switzerland]] posing as a Swiss physics student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1Idyqj51P-MC&amp;pg=PA120&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Playing for their nation: baseball and the American military during World War II |publisher= |date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His instructions were to attend a December 1944 lecture at the [[Technische Hochschule]] there by Germany's top nuclear scientist who was heading their atomic bomb project, [[Werner Heisenberg]], to an audience filled with Nazi agents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=15gfIulH4D8C&amp;pg=PT160&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Spying: the secret history of history |publisher=Black Dog Publishing |year= 2004|accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Gmdthgi8_CkC&amp;pg=PA296&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Edwin Hubble: mariner of the nebulae  |publisher=|date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  His orders were to kill the scientist if he determined that the Germans were far along in their efforts to build an atomic weapon.&lt;ref name=hahn /&gt;&lt;ref name=boxerman /&gt;&lt;ref name=stitch /&gt;&lt;ref name=empire&gt;Elias, Robert.[http://books.google.com/books?id=C0IdjLNw88gC&amp;pg=PA152&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=pxZbTd2fLIS8lQeD-rX7DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwATgK#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''The Empire Strikes Out: How Baseball Sold U.S. Foreign Policy and Promoted the American Way Abroad''] New York: The New Press, 2009. p. 152 ISBN 978-1-59558-195-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chalou, George C. [http://books.google.com/books?id=P3OIFS_yzyUC&amp;pg=PA293&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=UxRbTfOPC4SclgebufHJDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''The Secret War: The Office of Strategic Services in World War II'']. Washington, D.C.: [[National Archives and Records Administration]], 1992. p. 293 ISBN 0-091333-91-6&lt;/ref&gt; He determined the scientist was not a threat.&lt;ref name=empire /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dl6kWs-T8osC&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=From nuclear military strategy to a world without war: a history and a proposal |publisher= |date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  President Roosevelt was pleased with the conclusions of his report.&lt;ref name=&quot;google2&quot;/&gt;

On another mission, he disguised himself as a Nazi German officer in order to enter a munitions plant in Italy, to determine if new weapons were being developed there.&lt;ref name=boxerman /&gt;&lt;ref name=stitch /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=e2XTiZwdp0AC&amp;pg=PA12&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=A stitch in time: a baseball chronology  |publisher= Halcyon Press|date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He also parachuted behind German lines a number of times, in order to gain intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3zrlkSxpxYoC&amp;pg=PA172&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;ct=result#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false |title=Teenager on first, geezer at bat, 4-F on deck: major league baseball in 1945
 |publisher=McFarland|date= |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Berg was awarded the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]], but declined to accept it as he was told that upon accepting it he would be forbidden from saying what he had done to deserve the award.&lt;ref&gt;Bloomfield, Gary L. [http://books.google.com/books?id=48-qDw9hvB8C&amp;pg=PT21&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=pxZbTd2fLIS8lQeD-rX7DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''Duty, Honor, Victory: America's Athletes in World War II''] Guilford, Connecticut: Lyons Press, 2003. p.65. ISBN 1-59228-067-6&lt;/ref&gt; He is also the only former Major League Baseball player whose baseball card is displayed at CIA headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, W. Thomas.[http://books.google.com/books?id=1Jc9wBsImOIC&amp;pg=PA23&amp;dq=of+strategic+services%22+moe+berg&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=fChbTfGKBoOKlwe8m_2SDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwATgU#v=onepage&amp;q=of%20strategic%20services%22%20moe%20berg&amp;f=false ''Encyclopedia of the Central Intelligence Agency''] New York: Facts on File, 2003. p.23. ISBN 0-8160-4-666-2&lt;/ref&gt;

==Branches==
{{Div col}}
* Censorship and Documents
* [[X-2 Counter Espionage Branch|X-2]] ([[counterespionage]]) {{nb10}}
* Research &amp; Analysis
* [[Morale Operations Branch]]
* Foreign Nationalities
* Operational Group Command
* Field Experimental Unit
* Special Projects
* Maritime Unit
* Special Operations
* Secret Intelligence&lt;ref&gt;For all branch information: {{cite web|last=Clancey|first=Patrick|title=Office of Strategic Services (OSS) Organization and Functions|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USG/JCS/OSS/OSS-Functions/index.html|publisher=HyperWar|accessdate=12 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 {{Div col end}}

==Detachments==
{{Div col}}
* [[OSS Detachment 101]]: Burma
* OSS Detachment 202: China
* OSS Detachment 303: New Delhi, India
* OSS Detachment 404: attached to British [[South East Asia Command]] in [[Kandy]], [[Sri Lanka|Ceylon]]
* OSS Detachment 505: [[Calcutta, India]]
{{Div col end}}

===US Army units attached to the OSS===
*[[2671st Special Reconnaissance Battalion (United States)|2671st Special Reconnaissance Battalion]]
*[[2677th Office of Strategic Services Regiment (United States)|2677th Office of Strategic Services Regiment]]

==In popular culture==
* The 1946 Paramount film ''[[O.S.S. (film)|O.S.S.]]'', starring [[Alan Ladd]] and [[Geraldine Fitzgerald]], showed agents training and on a dangerous mission. Commander John Shaheen acted as [[technical advisor]].
* The 1946 film ''[[13 Rue Madeleine]]'' stars [[James Cagney]] as an OSS agent who must find a mole in French partisan operations. [[Peter Ortiz]] acted as technical advisor.
* The 1946 film ''[[Cloak and Dagger (1946 film)|Cloak and Dagger]]'' stars [[Gary Cooper]] as a scientist recruited to OSS to exfiltrate a German scientist defecting to the allies with the help of a woman guerrilla and her partisans. [[E. Michael Burke]] acted as technical advisor.
* The 1957 book ''You're Stepping on My Cloak and Dagger'' by [[Roger Wolcott Hall]] is a witty look at Hall's experiences with the OSS.
* Author [[W.E.B. Griffin]]'s ''[[Honor Bound series|Honor Bound]]'' and ''[[Men at War (series)|Men At War]]'' series revolves around fictional OSS operations.
* The O.S.S. was a featured organization in [[DC Comics]], introduced in ''[[G.I. Combat]]'' #192 (July 1976). Led by the mysterious Control, they operated as an espionage unit, initially in Nazi-occupied France. The organization would later become [[List of government agencies in DC Comics#A|Argent]].
* In the ''[[Wolfenstein (series)|Wolfenstein]]'' series of video games, the main character is a member of a fictional organisation called the OSA (Office of Secret Actions),which is inspired by the OSS. 
* Most games in the ''[[Medal of Honor (series)|Medal of Honor]]'' video game franchise feature a fictional OSS agent as the main character.
* In the Season 6 ''[[X-Files]]'' episode &quot;Triangle&quot;, the woman from the 1939 scenes portrayed by [[Gillian Anderson]] as [[Dana Scully|Scully]] is a member of OSS.
* In the [[2006 in film|2006 film]] ''[[The Good Shepherd (film)|The Good Shepherd]]'' Matt Damon plays Edward Wilson, a [[Skull and Bones]] recruit who joins the OSS to help with a mission in London. He quickly gains rank as the head of the newly formed CIA's Counterintelligence service.
* The OSS is referenced in the 2007 film ''[[Smokin' Aces]]''.
* In the [[2008 in film|2008 film]] ''[[Indiana Jones and the Kingdom of the Crystal Skull]]'', it is indicated that Indiana Jones did work for the OSS, attaining the rank of Colonel.
* In the 2009 film ''[[Inglourious Basterds]]'' by [[Quentin Tarantino]], the &quot;basterds&quot; are members of OSS, although no such OSS unit existed.
* A French pulp fiction series ''[[OSS 117]]'', by author [[Jean Bruce]], follows the adventure of Hubert Bonisseur de la Bath, alias OSS 117, a French operative working for the OSS. The original series (four or five books a year) lasted from 1949 to 1963, until the death of Jean Bruce, and was continued by his wife and children until 1992. Numerous movies were made in the 1960s, and in 2006 a nostalgic comedy was made, celebrating the spy movie genre, ''Cairo, Nest of Spies'', with [[Jean Dujardin]] playing OSS 117. A sequel followed in 2009 called ''OSS 117: Lost in Rio'' (original title in French: ''OSS 117: Rio Ne Répond Plus'').
* The 2008 film ''Flash of Genius'' is about famed American inventor and OSS veteran, [[Robert Kearns]].

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Government of the United States}}
* [[Special Operations Executive]]
* [[X-2 Counter Espionage Branch]]
* [[OSS Detachment 101]] operated in the [[China Burma India Theater of World War II]].
* [[Special Forces (United States Army)]]
* [[Paramarines]]
* [[Operation Halyard]]
* [[Operation Paperclip]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist}}

;Select historical bibliography
* Albarelli, H.P. ''A Terrible Mistake: The Murder of Frank Olson and the CIA’s Secret Cold War Experiments'' (2009) ISBN 0977795373
* [[Richard Aldrich|Aldrich, Richard J.]] ''Intelligence and the War Against Japan: Britain, America and the Politics of Secret Service'' (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2000)
* [[Stewart Alsop|Alsop, Stewart]] and Braden, Thomas. ''Sub Rosa: The OSS and American Espionage'' (New York: Reynal &amp; Hitchcock, 1946)
* Bank, Aaron. ''From OSS to Green Berets: The Birth of Special Forces'' (Novato, CA: Presidio, 1986)
* Bartholomew-Feis, Dixee R. ''The OSS and Ho Chi Minh: Unexpected Allies in the War against Japan'' (Lawrence : University Press of Kansas, 2006)
* Bernstein, Barton J. &quot;Birth of the U.S. biological warfare program&quot; ''[[Scientific American]]'' 256: 116 – 121, 1987.
* Brown, Anthony Cave. ''The Last Hero: Wild Bill Donovan'' (New York: Times Books, 1982)
* [[William J. Casey|Casey, William J.]] ''The Secret War Against Hitler'' (Washington: Regnery Gateway, 1988)
* Chalou, George C. (ed.) ''The Secrets War: The Office of Strategic Services in World War II'' (Washington: National Archives and Records Administration, 1991)
* Dawidoff, Nicholas. ''The Catcher was a Spy: The Mysterious Life of Moe Berg'' ( New York: Vintage Books, 1994)
* [[Allen Dulles|Dulles, Allen]]. ''The Secret Surrender'' (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1966)
* Dunlop, Richard. ''Donovan: America’s Master Spy'' (Chicago: Rand McNally, 1982)
* Ford, Corey. ''Donovan of OSS'' (Boston: Little, Brown, 1970)
* Grose, Peter. ''Gentleman Spy: The Life of Allen Dulles'' (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1994)
* Hassell, A, and MacRae, S: ''Alliance of Enemies: The Untold Story of the Secret American and German Collaboration to End World War II'', Thomas Dunne Books, 2006
* Hunt, E. Howard. ''American Spy'', 2007
* Jakub, Jay. ''Spies and Saboteurs: Anglo-American Collaboration and Rivalry in Human Intelligence Collection and Special Operations, 1940–45'' (New York: St. Martin's, 1999)
* Jones, Ishmael. ''The Human Factor: Inside the CIA's Dysfunctional Intelligence Culture'' (New York: Encounter Books, 2008, rev 2010)
* Katz, Barry M. ''Foreign Intelligence: Research and Analysis in the Office of Strategic Services, 1942–1945'' (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1989)
* Kent, Sherman. ''Strategic Intelligence for American Foreign Policy'' (Hamden, CT: Archon, 1965 [1949])
* Lovell, Stanley P. ''Of Spies and Stratagems'' (Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey: Prentice-Hall, 1963)
* McIntosh, Elizabeth P. ''Sisterhood of Spies: The Women of the OSS'' (Annapolis, MD: Naval Institute Press, 1998)
* Melton, H. Keith. ''OSS Special Weapons and Equipment: Spy Devices of World War II'' (New York: Sterling Publishing, 1991)
* Moulin, Pierre.  ''U.S. Samurais in Bruyeres'' (CPL Editions: Luxembourg, 1993)
* Persico, Joseph E. ''Piercing the Reich: The Penetration of Nazi Germany by American Secret Agents During World War II'' (New York: Viking, 1979)
* Peterson, Neal H. (ed.) ''From Hitler’s Doorstep: The Wartime Intelligence Reports of Allen Dulles, 1942–1945'' (University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1996)
* Pinck, Daniel C. ''Journey to Peking: A Secret Agent in Wartime China'' (Naval Institute Press, 2003)
* Pinck, Daniel C., Jones, Geoffrey M.T. and Pinck, Charles T. (eds.) ''Stalking the History of the Office of Strategic Services: An OSS Bibliography'' (Boston: OSS/Donovan Press, 2000)
* [[Kermit Roosevelt|Roosevelt, Kermit]] (ed.) ''War Report of the OSS'', two volumes (New York: Walker, 1976)
* Rudgers, David F. ''Creating the Secret State: The Origins of the Central Intelligence Agency, 1943–1947'' (Lawrence, KS: University of Kansas Press, 2000)
* Smith, Bradley F. and Agarossi, Elena. ''Operation Sunrise: The Secret Surrender'' (New York: Basic Books, 1979)
* Smith, Bradley F. ''The Shadow Warriors: OSS and the Origins of the CIA'' (New York: Basic, 1983)
* Smith, Richard Harris. ''OSS: The Secret History of America’s First Central Intelligence Agency'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1972; Guilford, CT: Lyons Press, 2005)
* Steury, Donald P. ''The Intelligence War'' (New York: Metrobooks, 2000)
* Troy, Thomas F. ''Donovan and the CIA: A History of the Establishment of the Central Intelligence Agency'' (Frederick, MD: University Publications of America, 1981)
* Troy, Thomas F. ''Wild Bill &amp; Intrepid'' (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1996)
* Waller, John H. ''The Unseen War in Europe: Espionage and Conspiracy in the Second World War'' (New York: Random House, 1996)
* Warner, Michael. ''The Office of Strategic Services : America’s First Intelligence Agency'' (Washington, D.C.: Central Intelligence Agency, 2001)
* Yu, Maochun. ''OSS in China: Prelude to Cold War'' (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1996)

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/books-and-monographs/oss/index.htm &quot;The Office of Strategic Services: America's First Intelligence Agency&quot;]
* [http://www.nps.gov/history/history/online_books/oss/index.htm National Park Service Report on OSS Training Facilities]
*[http://docs.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box4/folo54.html Collection of Documents at the Franklin D. Roosevelt Presidential Museum and Library, Part 1] and [http://docs.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box4/folo55.html Part 2]
*[http://www.osssociety.org The OSS Society]
*[http://www.ossreborn.com OSS Reborn]

{{Intelligence agencies of USA}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Office Of Strategic Services}}
[[Category:1942 establishments]]
[[Category:1945 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Office of Strategic Services| ]]
[[Category:Defunct United States intelligence agencies]]
[[Category:Intelligence services of World War II]]
[[Category:World War II resistance movements]]

[[ca:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[cs:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[da:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[de:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[es:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[fr:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[ko:전략사무국]]
[[id:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[it:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[nl:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[ja:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[no:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[pms:Ufissi dij Servissi Stratégich]]
[[pl:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[pt:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[ru:Управление стратегических служб]]
[[sr:Уред за стратешке услуге]]
[[fi:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[sv:Office of Strategic Services]]
[[tr:Stratejik Servisler Ofisi]]
[[zh:战略情报局]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
