<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2278820" ns="0" title="Sister Ray"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the song}}
{{Song infobox
| Name           = Sister Ray
| Cover          =
| Artist         = [[The Velvet Underground]]
| Album          = [[White Light/White Heat]]
| Released       = January 30, 1968
| track_no       = 6
| Recorded       = September 1967, Scepter Studios, [[New York City]], [[New York]]
| Genre          = [[Protopunk]], [[experimental rock]], [[avant-garde music|avant-garde]]
| Length         = 17:29
| Writer         = [[Lou Reed]]
| Composer       = Lou Reed, [[John Cale]], [[Sterling Morrison]], [[Maureen Tucker]]
| Label          = [[Verve Records]]
| Producer       = [[Tom Wilson (producer)|Tom Wilson]]
| Tracks         = 
#&quot;[[White Light/White Heat (song)|White Light/White Heat]]&quot;
#&quot;[[The Gift (Velvet Underground song)|The Gift]]&quot;
#&quot;[[Lady Godiva's Operation]]&quot;
#&quot;[[Here She Comes Now]]&quot;
#&quot;[[I Heard Her Call My Name]]&quot;
#&quot;Sister Ray&quot;
}}
&quot;'''Sister Ray'''&quot; is a song by [[The Velvet Underground]] that closes side two of their 1968 [[avant-garde]] [[rock music|rock]] album ''[[White Light/White Heat]]''. The song's lyrics were written by [[Lou Reed]], with music composed by [[John Cale]], [[Sterling Morrison]], [[Maureen Tucker]] and Reed.

&quot;Sister Ray&quot; was a concert favorite of the band, who regularly closed their set with the song. The studio recording of the song was recorded in one single take that lasts over seventeen minutes, while live versions were known to last as much as half an hour or more. The triple live album ''[[Bootleg Series Volume 1: The Quine Tapes]]'', released in 2001, features three live performances of  &quot;Sister Ray&quot; from 1969, with approximate running times of 24, 38 and 29 minutes.
 
==Studio version==
===Recording===
The studio recording of &quot;Sister Ray&quot; was recorded in one take. The band agreed to accept whatever faults occurred during recording, resulting in over seventeen minutes of highly [[improvisation]]al material.

The song was recorded with Lou Reed providing [[singer|lead vocals]] and [[electric guitar|guitar]], Sterling Morrison on guitar and Maureen Tucker on [[drum kit|drums]] while John Cale plays an [[organ (music)|organ]] that was routed through a [[distortion (guitar)|distorted]] [[guitar amplifier]]. Secondary guitarist [[Sterling Morrison]] remarked that he was amazed at the volume of Cale's organ during the recording and had switched the guitar pickup on his [[Fender Stratocaster]] from the bridge position to the neck position to get &quot;more oomph&quot;. Also notable about the song is that it features no [[bass guitar]]&amp;mdash;[[John Cale]], who usually played bass or viola, was playing his organ on the take. The band had a sponsorship from [[Vox (musical equipment)|Vox]] amplifiers, resulting in use of top of the line amps and distortion pedals to create a very distorted and noisy sound.

After the opening sequence, which is a modally flavored I-bVII-IV G-F-C [[chord progression]], much of the song is led by Cale and Reed exchanging percussive [[chord (music)|chord]]s and noise for over ten minutes, similar to [[avant-jazz]]. The recording engineer is famously rumored to have walked out while recording the song. Lou Reed recalled: &quot;The engineer said, 'I don't have to ''listen to this''. I'll put it in Record, and then I'm ''leaving''. When you're done, come get me.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;American Masters: ''Lou Reed: Rock &amp; Roll Heart'' documentary&lt;/ref&gt;

Reed called the song &quot;Sister Ray&quot; in acknowledgment to [[Ray Davies]] of the British band, [[The Kinks]].&lt;ref&gt;Tom Robinson Radio Show, BBC 6 Music 22/5/07&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subject matter===
The song concerns drug use, violence, [[homosexuality]] and [[transvestism]]. Reed said of the [[lyrics]]: &quot;'Sister Ray' was done as a joke—no, not as a joke—but it has eight characters in it and this guy gets killed and nobody does anything. It was built around this story that I wrote about this scene of total debauchery and decay. I like to think of ‘Sister Ray' as a [[transvestite]] [[Heroin|smack]] dealer. The situation is a bunch of [[drag queen]]s taking some sailors home with them, shooting up on smack and having this [[orgy]] when the police appear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.thestranger.com/seattle/Content?oid=11801
| title = The Stranger interview with Lou Reed}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Performance lineup===
* [[Lou Reed]] - [[singer|vocals]], [[electric guitar|guitar]]
* [[John Cale]] - [[Vox Continental]] [[organ (music)|organ]]
* [[Sterling Morrison]] - [[Fender Stratocaster]] guitar
* [[Maureen Tucker]] - [[drum kit|drums]]

==Cover versions==
*[[Joy Division]], [[New Order]], and [[The Sisters of Mercy]] have done covers of the track. A Joy Division cover played live on April 3rd 1980 appears on the 1981 compilation ''[[Still (Joy Division album)|Still]]'', and a New Order cover played live at Glastonbury 1987 was released in 1992 on the album ''[[BBC Radio 1 Live in Concert (New Order album)|BBC Radio 1 Live in Concert]]''.
*[[Jonathan Richman]] plays a portion of &quot;Sister Ray&quot; on his song &quot;Velvet Underground.&quot; Indeed, it has been argued that Richman's &quot;[[Roadrunner (Jonathan Richman song)|Roadrunner]]&quot; is, considering its distorted organ solo (provided by producer [[John Cale]]) and chordal similarities, largely a reworking of &quot;Sister Ray&quot; in musical terms, although Richman's positive and life-affirming lyrics about the joys of driving around suburban Boston are in marked contrast to Reed's detached saga of &quot;debauchery and decay&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2007/jul/20/popandrock5   Laura Barton, The Guardian, 20 July 2007, &quot;The car, the radio, the night - and rock's most thrilling song&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.furious.com/perfect/modernlovers.html William Crain, '&quot;The Modern Lovers: Despite All the Amputations&quot;'', 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*British power-punk band [[Buzzcocks]] formed as a result of a classified ad placed by founding member [[Howard Devoto]] seeking musicians to collaborate on a version of &quot;Sister Ray&quot;.
*The Danish post-punk band, Before played this song live at Roskilde Festival 1982, looping these lines &quot;I'm searching for my mainer, I said I couldn't hit it sideways, I couldn't hit it sideways, Aw just like Sister Ray said, Lay it on him.&quot; in an upbeat tempo.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.vastlyrics.com/v/Velvet%20Underground/Sister%20Ray/ Song Lyrics]

{{White Light/White Heat}}
{{The Velvet Underground}}

[[Category:The Velvet Underground songs]]
[[Category:1968 songs]]
[[Category:Songs written by Lou Reed]]
[[Category:Songs about drugs]]
[[Category:Experimental rock songs]]

[[cs:Sister Ray]]
[[fr:Sister Ray]]
[[it:Sister Ray]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
