<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Ports system" to="Ports collection" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="3868958" ns="0" title="Ports collection"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Ports collections''' (or ''ports trees'', or just ''ports'') are the sets of [[makefile]]s and [[Patch_(computing)|patch]]es provided by the [[BSD]]-based [[operating system]]s, [[FreeBSD]], [[NetBSD]], and [[OpenBSD]], as a simple method of installing software or creating binary packages. They are usually the base of a [[package management system]], with ports handling package creation and additional tools managing package removal, upgrade, and other tasks.  In addition to the BSDs, a few [[Linux distribution]]s have implemented similar [[infrastructure]], including [[Gentoo_Linux|Gentoo]]'s [[Portage (software)|Portage]], [[Arch Linux|Arch]]'s [[Arch Build System|Arch Build System (ABS)]] and [[CRUX]]'s Ports.

== NetBSD's pkgsrc ==
{{main|Pkgsrc}}

NetBSD's ''pkgsrc'' ports collection is distinctive in that it aims to be portable and is usable on a number of operating systems aside from NetBSD itself, including the other BSDs, [[Linux]] and other [[Unix-like]]s.  ''pkgsrc'' was created in August 1997 based on the existing FreeBSD ports system. It follows a quarterly release schedule and as of July 2006 contains over 6000 packages. With their 1.4 release, [[DragonFly BSD]] announced that they would be adopting ''pkgsrc'' as their official package management system. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Matthew|last=Dillon|title=PKGSRC will be officially supported as of the next release|url=http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/users/2005-08/msg00347.html|accessdate=2008-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== OpenBSD ports ==
In contrast to [[FreeBSD Ports]], on which it was originally based, the OpenBSD ports system is intended as a source used to create the end product, [[Software package (installation)|packages]]: installing a port first creates a package and then installs it. Packages are made up of a makefile, [[text file]]s with descriptions and installation messages, any patches required to adjust the program to work on OpenBSD and a packing list listing the files to be included in the packages. The ports tree uses a set of standard makefiles, some of which are shared with the [[Source_code|source]] tree, to provide the bulk of its functionality; this shared infrastructure includes many utility functions for port developers and means that ports can often be made very simply. As a security precaution or an aid when developing new ports, port builds may be run using [[systrace]] and a default policy is provided. In late October 2007 OpenBSD developer Nikolay Sturm announced that -stable ports tree should be considered unmaintained due to the lack of resources. This effectively forces users to run -current ports/base tree in order to keep up with security updates. In 2009 it was decided to revive the -stable ports tree under supervision of Robert Nagy and Jasper Lievisse Adriaanse. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=William|last=Yodlowsky|title=4.6-stable ports|url=http://kerneltrap.org/mailarchive/openbsd-announce/2009/10/22/6515363|accessdate=2009-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Arch Build System|Arch ABS]]
*[[FreeBSD Ports]]
*[[Portage (software)|Gentoo Portage]]
*[[MacPorts]]
*[[pkgsrc|NetBSD pkgsrc]]
&lt;!-- XXX: someone should mention something about Fedora 7's ports-like thing they have if it's worth mentioning; I don't know enough about it to add to the discussion, however --&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://openbsd.org/porting.html OpenBSD ports]
* [http://www.openbsd.org/cgi-bin/man.cgi?query=ports The OpenBSD ports manpage]
* [http://www.freebsd.org/ports/ FreeBSD Ports]
* [http://www.netbsd.org/Documentation/software/packages.html pkgsrc: The NetBSD Packages Collection]
* [http://www.gobolinux.org/?page=doc/articles/compile The ideas behind Compile]

[[Category:BSD]]
[[Category:Free package management systems]]

[[ar:المنقولات]]
[[de:Port (Paketverwaltung)]]
[[es:Ports]]
[[eo:Portaĵa arbo]]
[[hu:Ports rendszer]]
[[pl:Kolekcja portów]]
[[pt:Coleção ports]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
