<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22824199" ns="0" title="2008–09 Connecticut Huskies women&#039;s basketball team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{NCAATeamSeason
  |Mode=Basketball
  |sex=women
  |Year=2008-09
  |Prev year=2007-08
  |Next year=2009-10
  |Team=Connecticut Huskies
  |Image=
  |Conference=Big East Conference
  |ShortConference=Big East
  |CoachRank=1&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/rankings&lt;/ref&gt;
  |APRank=
  |Record=39-0
  |ConfRecord=16-0
  |HeadCoach=Geno Auriemma
  |AsstCoach1= Chris Dailey
  |AsstCoach2= Jamelle Elliott
  |AsstCoach3= Shea Ralph
  |StadiumArena=[[Harry A. Gampel Pavilion]]
  |Champion=Big East Champions&lt;br&gt;Maggie Dixon Classic Champions&lt;br&gt;Caribbean Classic Champions
  |BowlTourney=[[2009 NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Women's Division I Tournament]]
  |BowlTourneyResult= [[2009 NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Tournament|Champions]]
}}
The '''2008–09 Connecticut Huskies women's basketball team''' represented the [[University of Connecticut]] in the 2008–2009 [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]] basketball season. Coached by [[Geno Auriemma]], the Huskies played their home games at the [[XL Center|Hartford Civic Center]] in [[Hartford, Connecticut]], and on campus at the [[Harry A. Gampel Pavilion]] in [[Storrs, Connecticut]], and are a member of the [[Big East Conference]].  They enjoyed an undefeated season and won their sixth NCAA championship by defeating the [[Louisville Cardinals]], 76&amp;ndash;54.

==Regular season==
===Pre-season===
[[File:UConn Team At White House 2009.jpg|thumb|450px|The players, coaches, and other staff of the 2008-2009 UConn Huskies, winners of the [[2009 NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Tournament|2009 national championship]], are honored at the [[White House]] by [[President of the United States|President]] [[Barack Obama]] on April 27, 2009.]]
Both major pre-season polls ranked the Huskies number 1, each just one vote shy of unanimous. The AP Top 25 poll included all but one vote for Connecticut, with a single vote for Stanford, and the ESPN/USA Today Poll had all but one vote for Connecticut, with a single vote for Tennessee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/rankings?seasonYear=2009&amp;weekNumber=1&amp;seasonType=2|title=2009 NCAA Women's Basketball Rankings|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team returned much of the previous year's team. Of the departing seniors, only Brittany Hunter started more than half the team's game, although Mel Thomas failed to reach that mark due to a career-ending injury.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/020708aaa.html|title=Mel Thomas Named To CoSIDA Women's Basketball Academic All-District I First Team |accessdate=2009-06-11|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5hYi0TTOJ|archivedate=2009-06-15|deadurl=no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Huskies started with a pair of triple digit scoring pre-season games. The first game was against Division II [[Stonehill College]] in nearby [[North Easton, Massachusetts]]. It was the first chance for fans to see freshman Caroline Doty, [[Tiffany Hayes]], and Heather Buck in action. Caroline and Tiffany both scored in double-digits, and Heather had three rebounds and a blocked shot. The final score was in favor of UConn, 100-49.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/recaps/110608aab.html|title=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/recaps/110608aab.html|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second pre-season game was even more lopsided, with UConn prevailing over Team SRP 103-37.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/recaps/111208aaa.html|title=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/recaps/111208aaa.html|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Non conference opener===
The regular season opening game was against [[Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets women's basketball|Georgia Tech]], a team unranked in the pre-season. The game would be tied at halftime, with Connecticut pulling ahead late to win by eleven points 82-71.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283210041|title=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283210041|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Connecticut would win their next three games easily, beating San Diego State and Rhode Island at home, and BYU in Utah, each win by at least 45 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/sched/conn-w-baskbl-sched.html|title=UConn Huskies Women's Basketball|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following game would bring #4 ranked Oklahoma to Connecticut. Characterized as a &quot;significant test&quot; by ESPN's Graham Hays, Connecticut would win easily by 32 points, 106-72.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283350041|title=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283350041|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; UConn would then play nearby [[College of the Holy Cross|Holy Cross]], winning easily 96-37. In this game Caroline Doty would hit her tenth consecutive three-point goal, a UConn school record, and four off the national record.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283380041|title=Doty extends school-record streak of made 3-pointers to 10 in UConn romp|accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 14, the Huskies competed in the Maggie Dixon Classic at Madison Square Garden and defeated Penn State by a score of 77-63. From December 18 to the 21, the Huskies competed in the Caribbean Classic held in Cancun, Mexico. The Huskies were undefeated at the tournament.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/sched/conn-w-baskbl-sched.html&lt;/ref&gt; After returning from Mexico, the Huskies traveled to South Carolina for their fifth consecutive road game. The team shot 57% form the field, and held their opponents to under 40%. [[Tina Charles (basketball)|Tina Charles]] has 21 points and 14 rebounds, helping lead the Huskies to their eleventh victory of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283632579|title=UConn improves to 11-0 for third straight year with win over South Carolina|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Connecticut hosted [[Hartford Hawks|Hartford]] on New year's Eve. The [[Hartford Hawks]], coached by former UConn star [[Jennifer Rizzotti|Jen Rizzotti]], were no match, falling behind by 33 at halftime. [[Renee Montgomery]] hit 9 of 11 in the first half, and did not return in the second half after taking an elbow to the mouth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=283660041|title=Montgomery scores 20 as UConn rolls|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; LSU came to Connecticut for the first game of the new year. Both teams had been to the prior Final Four, each losing in the semi-final round. However, LSU had graduated five seniors, so the Lady Tigers were not expected to be as strong as the previous year's team. The pollsters concurred, not giving LSU a single vote for a top 25 position in either of the two major polls. LSU played stronger than their ranking, losing by 13 for the third closest match of the season to that date. Renee Montgomery's six assists, brought her to 1500 points and 500 assists for her career, a mark reach by only two other UConn players, [[Diana Taurasi]] and [[Jennifer Rizzotti|Jen Rizzotti]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290030041|title=Montgomery's six assists lead her into exclusive company|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Beginning of  conference play===
The Big East opening game would be against [[University of South Florida|South Florida]] USF would go on to win the [[Women's National Invitation Tournament|WNIT]] this season, but UConn was far too strong on this day. USF was one of the nation's best scoring team, scoring over 100 on five occasions, including 126 against Grambling State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collegerpi.com/women/|title=CollegeRPI.com|accessdate=2009-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; UConn decided to work on defense, and held USF to just over 25% from the field. USF scored only 11 points in the second half.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290060058|title=Charles, Moore spark UConn rout of South Florida|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next game would be against West Virginia, in West Virginia, the home of UConn senior Renee Montgomery. In her first game in West Virginia, two years prior, she scored seven points. This time she would lead the team in points (28), assists(5), and steals(2) to lead UConn to a 30 point victory in front of her home town crowd.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290100277|title=Montgomery's 28 points help UConn improve to 20-1 vs. WVU|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three days later, UConn would play at home against DePaul. UConn built a 15 point lead by halftime against the unranked team, but despite falling another ten points behind, DePaul would play them even in the second half. The final score was 77-62, in favor of UConn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290130041|title=Moore just 29 points short of 1,000 as UConn tops DePaul|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maya Moore entered the game on 17 January 2009 against Syracuse 29 points shy of 1,000 for her career. She would score 40 to easily surpass that mark, reaching the plateau faster than any other female in UConn history. However, the game would also be notable for a season ending injury to starter Caroline Doty, reported at the time to be a knee injury. Doty would score 17 points before halftime, but just before halftime, she injured her knee during a fast break. It was the same knee she injured in 2007. Moore's forty points is only the second forty point performance in UConn women's history; the other is Nykesha Sales' 46 against Stamford in 1997. UConn would win the game 107-53.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290170041|title=Moore scores 40, including 1,000th point; Doty injures knee|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following game was a highly anticipated showdown between the #1 and # 2 ranked teams in the nation. Both Connecticut and North Carolina entered the game 17-0 on the season. Connecticut had the higher ranking, but would need to replace starter Carolyn Doty. Her knee injury in the prior game would turn out to be a season-ending ACL tear. The result would be anti-climatic, as UConn reached a double-digit lead early in the game, extended to a 46-30 halftime lead, and finished with a 30 point victory, 88-58. The five starters, including Lorin Dixon in a her first start of the season, would each score in double digits, led by Renee Montgomery with 21.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290190153|title=Montgomery, Moore lead the way in UConn's rout |accessdate=2009-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next game against Cincinnati would be even more lopsided. UConn outscored the Bearcats in the first half 39-7. The seven points allowed in the first half were only one point off the school record of six in a half. While Cincinnati would outscore the Huskies in the second half 27-26, the outcome was not in doubt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290242132|title=No. 1 Connecticut has no letdown after routing UNC, taking care of Cincinnati|accessdate=2009-07-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 26 January game against Louisville would pit UConn against the team they beat by only six in the previous year's Big East Tournament title game. Louisville was ranked 10th in the nation, and still had [[Angel McCoughtry]], winner of the [[Big East Conference Women's Basketball Player of the Year]] in 2007. Angle would live up to her reputation with 24 points and 14 rebounds, but it wasn't enough, as Maye Moore scored 27 to lead UConn to a 93-65 win.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290260041|title=Top-ranked UConn cruises to 20-0 record|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next game was against unranked Georgetown. UConn would win by 19, with five players scoring in double-digits, but the game was surprisingly close, given that the average margin of victory for UConn was 34 at that point.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290310046|title=No. 1 Huskies pull away to remain undefeated|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following game was against Rutgers, a team that has often given UConn a strong challenge, winning half of the last ten meetings. Rutgers would stay close in the first half, entering the half down only six 34-28, but UConn would pull away in the second half behind a double-double by Moore (24 points, 10 rebounds).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290340041|title=Dominant Connecticut blows out Rutgers|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marquette would endure another double-double by Moore(22 points, 10 rebounds), in their 83-49 loss to UConn on 7 February.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290380269|title=Moore has 22 points, 10 rebounds as Huskies rout Golden Eagles|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following game against unranked St. John's on 11 February, started as if it would be another rout. UConn led by 15 at halftime, and increased the lead to 20. The St. John's team responded and cut the lead to seven, before UConn regrouped and finished with a 13 point victory, 77-64. Maya would contribute another double-double (20 points, 10 rebounds), while Renee Montgomery and Tina Charles each scored 21 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290422599|title=UConn tops St. John's to stay unbeaten|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next game would be the last game of the season at Gampel Arena. The game itself would be anticlimactic, as UConn easily beat Pittsburgh 95-42. The highlight of the evening would be the induction into the Huskies of Honor for Renee Montgomery, kept a secret from her until the announcement. One of her first reactions, after the shock of the announcement, was the regret that her parents wouldn't see it, but seconds later, her parents would walk onto the floor. They had been in town, but shared the secret. Renee is the first active player at UConn to be so honored. She would go on to score a team high 20 points.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290460041|title=Montgomery helps UConn dismantle Pittsburgh after being honored|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 18th of February, Connecticut played Providence in Providence. The Huskies scored the first eleven points, and never trailed. The Huskies started the second half in even more impressive fashion, scoring the first 25 points of the half. UConn would win easily 75–39.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290492507|title=UConn never trails after opening with 11-0 run|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following game was against Notre Dame, ranked 24th at the time. The Notre Dame Irish would give Connecticut their toughest match of the year. The Irish lead most of the first half. Although UConn would go to the half with a three point lead, Notre Dame out scored UConn in the initial minutes of the second half, with a lead of 43–41 at one time. Prior to this game the Huskies had trailed for only a combined 27 minutes all season. Connecticut would retake the lead, and finished the game with a ten point margin, the closest game of the season to that date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290530041|title=Montgomery leads No. 1 UConn to another home triumph|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 24th of February, UConn hosted Villanova. Tina Charles had a double-double with 19 points and 10 rebounds to lead UConn to the win 74-47.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290550041|title=Charles scores 19 to lead UConn to rout of Villanova|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four days later, Seton Hall came to Hartford, for the last regular season game of the year. As a surprise for the departing seniors, Maya Moore and Kaili McLaren sang the national anthem. Moore then went on to score 18 points, to help lead UConn to an 81–50 win, and guarantee a share of the Big East regular-season title.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290590041|title=Huskies wrap up share of Big East regular-season title|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 March 2009, UConn played its last regular season game against rival Rutgers. UConn moved out to a 16 point halftime lead 36–20, but Rutgers out scored UConn the second half to make the final score ten points, tied for closest result of the season. The win leaves the Huskies still  undefeated on the season, now 30–0.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290610164|title=Montgomery leads way as No. 1 UConn undefeated for first time since '02-'03|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Big East Tournament===
Connecticut opened the Big East Tournament against South Florida, a team it had beaten by 46 points earlier in the season. This game would be closer, but not by much. Kalana Greene led the Huskies with a season high 20 points, scoring 18 points before halftime, and leading the Huskies to a 47–10 halftime lead. USF would match the UConn production in the second half, but the 37 point margin held. The final score was 79–42.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290670041|title=Greene, Moore have double-doubles as Huskies rout South Florida|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second tournament game was against Villanova, a team UConn had beaten by 27 points less than two weeks earlier. However, the game was tied at 25 apiece, with under six minutes to go in the first half. Maya Moore then helped lead the team on a 23–2 run to put the game out of reach. The Huskies won 72–42.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290680041|title=Moore's 17 points lead UConn to Big East finals|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The final game, on 10 March, for the Big East Tournament Championship, was against Louisville, ranked #7 in the country. The Cardinals who would go on to play in the Finals of the NCAA tournament, were no match for UConn on this day. Maya Moore left the game with eight minutes to go, having scored 28 points. St that time the Louisville team had scored 27.  UConn would win the game in convincing fashion, 75–36.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=290690041|title=Huskies rout Cardinals to win 15th Big East tourney championship|publisher=ESPN|accessdate=2009-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Roster==
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;  style=&quot;background:#002868;color:#FFFFFF;&quot;
| '''Number''' || '''Name''' || '''Height''' || '''Position''' || '''Class'''
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 21  ||  Heather Buck || 6-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;3 || Center/Forward  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;Freshman
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 31  || Tina Charles  || 6-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;4 || Center  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;Junior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 30  || Lorin Dixon  || 5-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;4 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; Sophomore
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 5  ||  Caroline Doty || 5-10 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;Freshman
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 13  || Jacquie Fernandes  || 5-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;9 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; Junior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 22  || Meghan Gardler  || 6-0 || Forward  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; Junior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 32  || Kalana Greene  || 5-10 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;Junior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 3 ||Tiffany Hayes   || 5-10 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;Freshman
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 51|| Cassie Kerns  || 6-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;3 || Center-Forward  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; Senior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 12 ||Jessica McCormack   || 6-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;5 || Center  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; Redshirt/Sophomore
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 41 || Kaili McLaren  || 6-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;2 || Forward  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; Junior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 20||Renee Montgomery   || 5-&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;7 || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt; Senior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 23 ||Maya Moore   ||  6-0|| Forward  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; Sophomore
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 2 ||Tahirah Williams   ||6-0  || Guard  ||&lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;Senior
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|}
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/mtt/conn-w-baskbl-mtt.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Schedule==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;90%&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;  style=&quot;background:#002868;color:#FFFFFF;&quot;
| '''Date''' || '''Location''' || '''Opponent''' || '''UConn Points''' || '''Opp. Points''' || '''Record'''
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 16 Nov 2008 ||Storrs, Conn.   ||Georgia Tech  || 82 ||71 ||1-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 20 Nov 2008 ||XL Center   ||San Diego State  ||99 ||55 ||2-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 22 Nov 2008 ||XL Center   ||Rhode Island  || 91 ||43 ||3-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  25 Nov 2008 ||Marriott Center (Provo, Utah)  ||Brigham Young||96||47||4-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  30 Nov 2008 || Gampel Pavilion  || Oklahoma|| 106|| 78||5-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  2 Dec 2008 || Gampel Pavilion  || Holy Cross||96 ||37 ||6-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  14 Dec 2008 || Madison Square Garden  ||Penn State || 77|| 63||7-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  18 Dec 2008 ||Moon Palace Resort, Cancun ||Washington || 109|| 51||8-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  19 Dec 2008 || Moon Palace Resort, Cancun || Northern Colorado|| 85||40 ||9-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  20 Dec 2008 || Moon Palace Resort, Cancun ||Florida State ||83 || 71||10-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  28 Dec 2008|| Colonial Life Arena  ||South Carolina ||77 || 48||11-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  31 Dec 2008 || XL Center  ||Hartford || 78|| 41||12-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  3 Jan 2009 || XL Center  || Louisiana State|| 76|| 63||13-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  6 Jan 2009 || USF Sun Dome  ||South Florida || 83||37 ||14-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  10 Jan 2009 || WVU Coliseum  ||West Virginia || 85|| 55||15-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  13 Jan 2009 ||  Gampel Pavilion || DePaul|| 77||62 ||16-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  17 Jan 2009 || XL Center  ||Syracuse ||107 ||53 ||17-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  19 Jan 2009 || Smith Center  ||North Carolina ||88 ||58 ||18-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  24 Jan 2009 || Fifth Third Arena  ||Cincinnati || 65|| 34||19-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  26 Jan 2009 || Gampel Pavilion  || Louisville|| 93|| 65||20-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  31 Jan 2009 ||Washington, DC   || Georgetown||80 ||61 ||21-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  3 Feb 2009 ||XL Center|| Rutgers|| 75|| 56||22-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  7 Feb 2009 || Al McGuire Center  ||Marquette || 83|| 49||23-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  11 Feb 2009 ||  Queens, NY ||St. Johns || 77|| 64||24-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  15 Feb 2009 || Gampel Pavilion  ||Pittsburgh || 95|| 42||25-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  18 Feb 2009 || Alumni Hall  || Providence||75 || 39||26-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  22 Feb 2009 || XL Center  ||Notre Dame || 76|| 66||27-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  24 Feb 2009 ||  Gampel Pavilion || Villanova|| 74|| 47||28-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|  28 Feb 2009 ||  XL Center || Seton Hall|| 81||50 ||29-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 2 Mar 2009 || Louis Brown Athletic Center  ||Rutgers || 69|| 59||30-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 8 Mar 2009 ||  XL Center ||South Florida ||79 || 42||31-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 9 Mar 2009 || XL Center   ||Villanova || 72||42 ||32-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 10 Mar 2009 || XL Center   ||Louisville|| 75||36 ||33-0
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/stats/2008-2009/teamstat.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Player stats==
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;  style=&quot;background:#002868;color:#FFFFFF;&quot;
| '''Player''' || '''Games Played''' || '''Minutes''' || '''Field Goals''' || '''Three Pointers''' || '''Free Throws'''|| '''Rebounds'''|| '''Assists'''|| '''Blocks'''|| '''Steals'''|| '''Points'''
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Moore&lt;/span&gt;Maya Moore ||39   ||1209  || 284 ||90 ||96 ||348 ||127 ||59||76||754
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Montgomery&lt;/span&gt;Renee Montgomery ||39    ||  1237 ||   226||  99|| 93 ||82  || 199 || 9|| 61||644
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Charles&lt;/span&gt;Tina Charles ||   39 || 982  || 259  || 0 || 124 || 348 || 41 ||62 || 35|| 642
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Greene&lt;/span&gt;Kalana Greene || 39   || 990  || 141  || 6 || 50 || 181 || 68 || 11|| 37||338
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Doty&lt;/span&gt;Caroline Doty || 17 ||406 || 52  || 30 ||13  || 57 || 33 ||4 ||16 ||147
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Hayes&lt;/span&gt;Tiffany Hayes ||  39  || 1002  || 109  || 46 || 63 || 156 || 102 ||15 || 44||327
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;McLaren&lt;/span&gt;Kaili McLaren ||   38 || 581  || 61  || 0 || 37 || 130 || 73 ||22 ||19 ||159
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Williams&lt;/span&gt;Tahirah Williams ||  33  || 245  || 33  || 0 || 22 ||  62|| 22 ||4 ||9 ||88
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Dixon&lt;/span&gt;Lorin Dixon ||   39 || 604  || 28  || 2 || 31 || 63 || 71 || 2|| 17||89
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Gardler&lt;/span&gt;Meghan Gardler || 32   || 335  || 19  || 5 || 15 || 62 || 21 || 3|| 12||58
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Fernandes&lt;/span&gt;Jacquie Fernandes || 30   || 141  || 8  || 3 || 4 || 17 || 2 ||0 ||3 ||23
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| &lt;span style=&quot;display:none&quot;&gt;Kerns&lt;/span&gt;Cassie Kerns ||  18  || 68  || 2  ||0  || 1 || 5 || 3 ||2 ||2 ||5
|}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/stats/2008-2009/teamcume.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==NCAA Basketball Tournament==
[[Image:Championship Trophy UConn wbb 2009.jpg|thumb |160px|alt=Championship Trophies|Championship Trophies]]
Connecticut won its sixth National Championship and completed its third perfect season. They won every game by double digits for the first time in NCAA history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first= |last= |coauthors= |title=Charles' 25 points, 19 boards push UConn to 39-0 record, sixth national title|work = [[Associated Press]] |publisher=[[ESPN]]|year=2009 |accessdate=10 May 2009 |url=http://scores.espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=294000063 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Trenton Regional
**Connecticut 104, Vermont 65
**Connecticut 87, Florida 59
**Connecticut 77, California 53
**Connecticut 83, Arizona State 64
*Final Four
**Connecticut 83, Stanford 64
**Connecticut 76, Louisville 54&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ncaamarchmadness2009.com/womens/&lt;/ref&gt;

*On April 27, the Huskies visited the White House and met President Barack Obama. The President took the University of Connecticut's women's basketball team over to the outdoor half-court at the White House to shoot hoops.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/042709aad.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and honors==
*Geno Auriemma, Winged Foot Award &lt;ref&gt;http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/050609aaa.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*Tina Charles, [[NCAA Basketball Tournament Most Outstanding Player|Tournament Most Outstanding Player]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.midwestsportsfans.com/2009/03/ncaa-tournament-mvp-most-outstanding-player-mop-men-women-march-madness/&lt;/ref&gt;
*Renee Montgomery, Wooden All-American selection &lt;ref name=&quot;woodenaward.cstv.com&quot;&gt;http://woodenaward.cstv.com/ot/09-w-baskbl-all-american.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore, AP All-America first team&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=ESPN |url =http://sports.espn.go.com/ncw/news/story?id=3324060 |accessdate =23 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore,  Big East Player of the Year
* Maya Moore, Big East Tournament Most Outstanding Performer&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Big East press release |url =http://www.bigeast.org/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=92557&amp;SPID=11229&amp;DB_OEM_ID=19400&amp;ATCLID=3690106 |accessdate =23 April 2009 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore,  CoSIDA/ESPN Academic All-America First Team&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=UConn Press release |url =http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/022409aaa.html |accessdate =23 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Maya Moore, Naismith Award &lt;ref&gt;http://www.naismithawards.com/History/NaismithTrophy/tabid/58/Default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore, National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) Division I State Farm Coaches’ All-America Basketball Team &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=WBCA Press Release |url =http://www.wbca.org/releases/2009SFAATPR.html |accessdate =10 April 2009 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore, State Farm Wade Trophy Player of the Year (2009 Division 1) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=WBCA Press Release |url =http://www.wbca.org/releases/2009SFWTPR.html |accessdate =10 April 2009 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore, USBWA National Player of the Year by the [[United States Basketball Writers Association]] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=USBWA Press release |url =http://www.sportswriters.net/usbwa/news/2009/women090401.html |accessdate =1 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Maya Moore, Women's NCAA Final Four All-Tournament Team&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=UConn Press Release|url =http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/spec-rel/040709aad.html |accessdate =23 April 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Maya Moore, Wooden All-American selection &lt;ref name=&quot;woodenaward.cstv.com&quot;/&gt;
*Maya Moore, Wooden Award &lt;ref&gt;http://woodenaward.cstv.com/ot/award-winners.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Team players drafted into the WNBA==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;  style=&quot;background:#002868;color:#FFFFFF;&quot;
| '''Round''' || '''Pick''' || '''Player''' || '''NBA Club'''
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
| 1  || 4|| Renee Montgomery ||   [[2009 Minnesota Lynx season|Minnesota Lynx]]
|- align=&quot;center&quot; bgcolor=&quot;&quot;
|}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wnba.com/draft2009/draft_board.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[UConn–Rutgers rivalry]]
*[[UConn–Tennessee rivalry]]
*[[2008–09 Connecticut Huskies men's basketball team]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.uconnhuskies.com/sports/w-baskbl/conn-w-baskbl-body.html Official Site]

{{2008-09 Connecticut Huskies basketball}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2008–09 Connecticut Huskies Women's Basketball Team}}
[[Category:Connecticut Huskies women's basketball seasons]]
[[Category:NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship seasons]]
[[Category:NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship Final Four seasons]]
[[Category:2008–09 NCAA Division I women's basketball season|Connecticut]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
