<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22899865" ns="0" title="Pasquale Scotti"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Scotti identikit.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Photofit of Pasquale Scotti on the basis of a mug-shot from the 1980s issued in October 2011 in relation to an international arrest warrant.&lt;ref name=polizia/&gt;]]
'''Pasquale Scotti''' ([[Casoria]], September 8, 1958), is an Italian criminal and boss of the [[Camorra]]—a Mafia-type organisation in [[Naples]] and [[Campania]]—involved in the [[Nuova Camorra Organizzata]] (NCO), headed by [[Raffaele Cutolo]].&lt;ref name=rep271284&gt;{{it icon}} [http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1984/12/27/evade-dall-ospedale-il-vice-di-cutolo.html Evade dall'ospedale il vice di Cutolo], La Repubblica, December 27, 1984&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Camorra boss==
He was described as a smooth and ruthless personality and one of the most able of the lieutenants of Cutolo together with [[Vincenzo Casillo]].&lt;ref name=rep271284/&gt;&lt;ref name=rep100185&gt;{{it icon}} [http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1985/01/10/torturato-assassinato-da-killer-camorristi.html Torturato e assassinato da killer camorristi], La Repubblica, January 10, 1985&lt;/ref&gt; Scotti and Casillo—who had close ties to the secret services—mediated between Cutolo and the regional leaders of the [[Christian Democracy (Italy)|Christian Democrat party]] ({{lang-it|Democrazia Cristiana}}, DC), the military secret service and the [[Red Brigades]] to obtain the release of the politician [[Cirillo kidnap|Ciro Cirillo]], who had been kidnapped in April 1981. Scotti also administered the assets of the NCO investing it in Italy and abroad.&lt;ref name=gio111011&gt;{{it icon}} [http://www.ilgiornale.it/interni/sfugge_poliziotti_e_regala_champagne/11-10-2011/articolo-id=551012-page=0-comments=1 Sfugge ai poliziotti e gli regala champagne], Il Giornale, October 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

Casillo was killed by a bomb in his car in January 1983, presumably to cover the secret negotiations by DC politicians to free Cirillo contravening to official policy of the Italian government to not negotiate with so-called terrorists. Scotti was behind the killing of Casillo’s mistress because she knew too much about the dealings of his erstwhile ally.&lt;ref name=rep271284/&gt;

==Arrest and escape==
After the transfer of Cutolo to the prison island [[Asinara]] and the wave of arrest against the NCO in June 1983, Scotti tried to rearrange the organisation.&lt;ref name=rep271284/&gt; He was arrested on December 17, 1983, in his fiefdom [[Caivano]] where he controlled the rackets and trafficking in drugs, smuggled cigarettes and arms. His arrest involved a shoot out with the police in which Scotti was injured. During detention, fearing a vendetta of rival Camorristi, he decided to become a [[pentito]] and collaborate with the authorities revealing different aspects of NCO. On Christmas Eve of 1984, he escaped from the hospital of Caserta where he had been hospitalized for a wound to the hand.&lt;ref name=rep271284/&gt;

==Fugitive or dead==
Since 1985, he has been on the &quot;[[List of most wanted fugitives in Italy|most wanted list]]&quot; of the Italian ministry of the Interior for murder and concealment of corpse and other crimes. On January 17, 1990, an international [[arrest warrant]] was issued against him, to be arrested for extradition.&lt;ref&gt;{{it icon}} [http://www.interno.it/mininterno/export/sites/default/it/sezioni/sala_stampa/notizie/polizia/app_notizia_17196.html Direzione Centrale della Polizia Criminale - &quot;Programma Speciale di Ricerca&quot; - Scotti Pasquale]&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2005, he received a life sentence for a series of 26 murders in 1982-83 during the Camorra war between the NCO and the [[Nuova Famiglia]].&lt;ref name=rep&gt;{{it icon}} [http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2005/01/23/altri-ergastoli-per-cutolo-vecchi-padrini-della.html Altri ergastoli per Cutolo e i vecchi padrini della Nco], La Repubblica, January 23, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2011, while Scotti had been on the run for nearly 27 years, the Italian police issued a new [[photofit]] on the basis of a mug-shot from the 1980s.&lt;ref name=gio111011/&gt;&lt;ref name=polizia&gt;{{it icon}} [http://www.poliziadistato.it/articolo/view/23950/ Latitanti: un cutoliano in fuga da 27 anni], Polizia di Stato, October 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Speculations that Scotti is not alive anymore have been made. He either might have been killed by rival factions in the Camorra, or because he had turned state witness, or because he knew too much about involvement of politicians and secret services in the release of the kidnapped Cirillo.&lt;ref name=gio111011/&gt; According to a [['Ndrangheta]] boss turned state witness, Franco Pino, Scotti died in 1984.&lt;ref name=rep211011&gt;{{it icon}} [http://napoli.repubblica.it/cronaca/2011/10/21/news/boss_calabrese_il_super_latitante_pasquale_scotti_stato_ucciso-23617791 Boss calabrese: &quot;Il super latitante Pasquale Scotti è stato ucciso&quot;], La Repubblica, October 21, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gds211011&gt;{{it icon}} [http://www.gazzettadelsud.it/NotiziaArchivio.aspx?art=145415&amp;Edizione=6&amp;A=20111021 Il pentito e il superlatitante della camorra], Gazzetta del Sud, October 21, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Scotti, Pasquale
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 8, 1958
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Scotti, Pasquale}}
[[Category:1958 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Naples]]
[[Category:Camorristi]]
[[Category:Nuova Camorra Organizzata]]
[[Category:Fugitives wanted by Italy]]
[[Category:Fugitives wanted on murder charges]]
[[Category:Fugitives wanted on organised crime charges]]

[[it:Pasquale Scotti]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
