<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2290517" ns="0" title="WPBN-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{referenced|date=September 2010}}
{{infobox_broadcast |
  call_letters             = WPBN-TV/WTOM-TV|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = [[Image:Tv7-4 logo.png|150px]] |
  station_slogan           = ''Fair. Accurate. Honest.''&lt;br&gt;''Inspiring. Informative. Entertaining.'' &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  station_branding         = TV 7&amp;4 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;7&amp;4 News&lt;br&gt;ABC 29&amp;8 &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  analog                   = |
  digital                  =&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT:''' 47 ([[UHF]])
&lt;br&gt;'''WGTU-DT2:''' 29 (UHF)
&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT:''' 35 (UHF)
'''WGTQ-DT2:''' 8 (VHF)|
  other_chs                =&lt;small&gt;50 (UHF) [[Harrietta, Michigan|Harrietta]]&lt;/small&gt;|
  subchannels              = 7.1/4.1 NBC-HD&lt;br&gt;29.2/8.2 NBC-SD &lt;br&gt;7.2/4.2 ABC-SD|
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = '''WPBN:''' September 13, 1954&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' May 16, 1959|
  location                 = '''WPBN:''' [[Traverse City, Michigan|Traverse City]]/[[Cadillac, Michigan]]&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' [[Cheboygan, Michigan|Cheboygan]]&lt;br&gt;WGTQ: Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan|
  callsign_meaning         = '''WPBN:''' '''P'''aul '''B'''unyan '''N'''etwork&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' '''T'''op '''O'''f '''M'''ichigan|
  former_callsigns         = |
  former_channel_numbers   = '''WPBN:'''&lt;br&gt;7 (VHF analog, 1954-2009)&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:'''&lt;br&gt;4 (VHF analog, 1959-2009)&lt;br&gt;35 (UHF digital)|
  owner                    = [[Barrington Broadcasting]]|
  licensee                 = Barrington Traverse City License, LLC|
  sister_stations          = WGTU/WGTQ, [[WBVC (The CW Plus)|&quot;WBVC&quot;]]|
  former_affiliations      = ABC (secondary, 1954-1971)&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT2:'''&lt;br&gt;[[The Tube (TV channel)|The Tube]] (2006-2007)&lt;br&gt;[[Retro Television Network|RTV]] (2007-2008)&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT3:'''&lt;br&gt;[[NBC Weather Plus|NBC WX+]]|
  effective_radiated_power = '''WPBN:''' 500 [[kilowatt|kW]]&lt;br&gt;'''WGTU-DT2:''' 68.4 kW&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' 78 kW&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ-DT2:''' 15 kW|
  HAAT                     = '''WPBN &amp; WGTU-DT2:'''&lt;br&gt;393 m&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' 168 m&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ-DT2:''' 288 m|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = '''WPBN:''' 21253&lt;br&gt;'''WGTU-DT2:''' 59280&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:''' 21254&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ-DT2:''' 59279|
  coordinates              = '''WPBN &amp; WGTU-DT2:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|44|44|53.0|N|85|4|8.0|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|45|39|0.6|N|84|20|36.9|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WTOM-TV}}&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ-DT2:''' {{coord|46|3|8.2|N|84|6|38.8|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WGTQ}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.upnorthlive.com upnorthlive.com]|
}}

'''WPBN-TV''' is the [[NBC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for the Northern [[Lower Peninsula of Michigan|Lower]] and Eastern [[Upper Peninsula of Michigan|Upper]] Peninsulas of [[Michigan]] that is licensed to [[Traverse City, Michigan|Traverse City]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 47 ([[PSIP|virtual channel]] 7) from a transmitter east of [[Kalkaska, Michigan|Kalkaska]]. There is also a low-powered digital fill-in translator on UHF channel 50 from a transmitter south of [[Harrietta, Michigan|Harrietta]] in the [[Manistee National Forest]]. Owned by [[Barrington Broadcasting]], the station operates [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate [[WGTU]] and its full-time satellite WGTQ (owned by Tucker Broadcasting of Traverse City) through a [[shared services|shared services agreement]] (SSA). The two share studios on [[M-72 (Michigan highway)|M-72]] just west of Traverse City.

==Overview==
Like other network affiliates in this vast and rural area, it operates a full-time satellite, '''WTOM-TV'''. Licensed to [[Cheboygan, Michigan|Cheboygan]], this station broadcasts a high definition digital signal on UHF channel 35 (virtual channel 4) from a transmitter on [[U.S. Route 23|U.S. 23]] east of the city. It reaches as far as [[Petoskey, Michigan|Petoskey]], [[Cedarville, Michigan|Cedarville]], [[Indian River, Michigan|Indian River]], and [[Brevort, Michigan|Brevort]]. Unlike the previous analog signal, it does not cover [[Sault Sainte Marie, Michigan|Sault Sainte Marie]] and the Eastern Upper Peninsula. To make up for this shortfall in coverage, WPBN is carried on the digital subcarriers of WGTU and Sault Sainte Marie satellite WGTQ.

Together, the two stations are known on-air as '''''TV 7&amp;4''''' and serve the largest television [[media market|market]] east of the [[Mississippi River]]: 23 counties in the Northern Lower Peninsula, three counties in the Eastern Upper Peninsula, and portions of [[Northern Ontario]] including [[Sault Ste. Marie, Ontario]]. However, WTOM has not been available in [[Canada]] on cable since the early-2000s when [[Shaw Communications]] replaced it with [[Detroit]]'s [[WDIV]]. WTOM also serves as the default NBC affiliate for [[Alpena, Michigan|Alpena]] as that area does not have an affiliate of its own.

==History==
WPBN-TV began broadcasting on February 13, 1954 airing an analog signal on VHF channel 7. It was owned by the Biederman family and their company, Midwest Broadcasting, along with [[WTCM (AM)|WTCM]]-AM 1400 (now 580).  Company president Les Biederman had signed on WTCM, [[Northern Michigan]]'s oldest radio station, in 1940. Over the next decade, he bought or signed-on several other [[amplitude modulation|AM]] stations throughout the area. These were known as the Paul Bunyan Network with WTCM as the flagship station. Since channel 7 covered much of the territory covered by the radio stations, Biederman decided not to call his new station WTCM-TV (for '''T'''raverse '''C'''ity, '''M'''ichigan) but rather WPBN-TV (for '''P'''aul '''B'''unyan '''N'''etwork). 

In the 1950s, the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) ruled that the eastern half of the Upper Peninsula was part of the Traverse City/Cadillac market. At the time, the only television station in that area had been private [[CBC Television]] affiliate [[CJIC-TV]]. Since WPBN was already operating at the maximum power allowed, Biederman signed-on '''WTOM-TV''' in Cheboygan on May 16, 1959 bringing [[United States|American]] television to the Eastern Upper Peninsula for the first time. Since then, the two stations have been known collectively as 7&amp;4. 

Until 1971, it shared [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] programming with [[CBS]] affiliates [[WWTV|WWTV/WWUP]]. WPBN aired ABC's sports programming on the weekends while WWTV aired some of the network's game shows and soap operas. In 1971, WGTU signed-on and took the ABC affiliation. In 1980, Midwest Broadcasting wanted to expand its broadcast operations in Northern Michigan. However, the FCC told the family that they could do so only if they sold some stations to stay under ownership limits. One of the stations sold off was WPBN/WTOM (which count as one station for ratings and regulatory purposes) to U.S. Tobacco. 

From 1999 to 2005, it was owned by [[Raycom Media]]. In late-2005, following that company's purchase of [[The Liberty Corporation]], Raycom announced that WPBN would be sold along with another NBC affiliate in the Upper Peninsula, [[WLUC-TV]] in [[Marquette, Michigan|Marquette]]. The sale was necessary to help meet FCC restrictions on station ownership. On March 27, 2006, Raycom announced that Barrington Broadcasting would acquire twelve Raycom stations including this channel. The FCC approved the deal in June 2006 and the finalization took place on August 12. At that point, the station joined WLUC, [[Saginaw, Michigan|Saginaw]]'s NBC affiliate [[WEYI-TV]] and (to a degree) [[Toledo, Ohio]]'s NBC affiliate [[WNWO-TV]] as part of Barrington's family of stations in and around Michigan. 

On September 19, 2007 an application was filed to the FCC by [[Max Media]] to sell WGTU, its full-time satellite WGTQ, and CW cable station to Tucker Broadcasting for $10 million. After approval, that company entered into a shared services agreement with Barrington . According to the FCC filing, WPBN would sell advertising time and provides other programming for Tucker's stations. After this station renovated its studios over the summer, the two stations consolidated operations into the expanded facilities. WPBN and WGTU began to share a website as well. For the digital transition on June 12, 2009, WPBN filed a petition with the FCC move its Traverse City digital signal on UHF channel 50 to the analog tower in Harrietta to maintain coverage in that area. It then signed-on a new digital signal on UHF channel 47 from WGTU's tower in Kalkaska. 

Unlike WPBN, WTOM-DT on UHF channel 35 did not initially offer NBC programming in full high definition. Instead, the signal was transmitted in an unconverted format. A true high definition signal for that station was included once WTOM shut down its analog signal on the transition date. Its new digital signal covers a fraction of the area once served by the VHF analog signal due to the rather low-powered 78 [[kilowatt|kW]] digital signal on UHF. To make up for this shortfall in coverage, standard definition feeds of WPBN and WTOM were added to the digital subcarriers of WGTU and WGTQ respectively.

==News operation==
[[File:Wpbn news2010.png|thumb|right|News open.]]

When WTOM first began broadcasting, it had a separate news department based at its studios on U.S. 23 east of Cheboygan. However, this operation was closed down and the channel eventually became a full-time satellite of WPBN. 

For most of the last half-century, WPBN has been second in the news ratings in the market behind WWTV according to [[Nielsen Media Research]]. Early on, the Biedermans devoted significant resources to WPBN's news operation utilizing the resources of the co-owned radio stations.   This continues today, resulting in a higher-quality product than conventional wisdom would suggest for a station in the 116th market. In terms of coverage, WPBN has traditionally had more of a Traverse City focus compared with WWTV who has facilities southeast of Cadillac. 

Station alumni include Christa Quinn and the immortal &quot;Deputy&quot; Don Melvoin who first hosted the ''Deputy Don'' kids show in the 1950s. After a stint in [[Hollywood]] that included roles on ''[[The Twilight Zone (1959 TV series)|The Twilight Zone]]'' and a movie filmed on [[Mackinac Island]] called ''Somewhere in Time'', Melvoin came back to WPBN to host ''Deputy Don Rides Again'' and the horror flick ''Count Zappula''. Don Melvoin died in 2002. In addition to its main studios, there is a bureau in [[Gaylord, Michigan|Gaylord]] on West Main Street. In the past, the station had also maintained newsrooms in Petoskey and Cadillac. The latter was closed in November 2008 after a reporter based there was laid-off. 

On September 10, 2007, it began airing a midday broadcast weekdays at 11 after ''[[Today (NBC program)|Today]]''  In January 2009, the station laid-off nine employees and canceled the weekday midday show. expanded to four hours. After WGTU consolidated its operations with WPBN, it became possible full newscasts would return to WGTU for the first time since 1984.  On September 13, 2010, WPBN began producing a weeknight newscast at 6:30 on WGTU, ''UpNorthLive Tonight''.  It originates from a secondary set at WPBN's studios, and features local news and weather but also goes into detail covering community events and various businesses. There is no sports report given in this broadcast.  The only other newscast on the station is a 10-minute weeknight update at 11.  Lori Puckett, WGTU's original only on-air personality who continues anchoring the weeknight update, appeared on WPBN in the local segments of the 2008 ''[[Jerry Lewis MDA Telethon]]''. 

As of October 17, 2011, this station airs its newscasts in [[Aspect ratio (image)|16x9]] [[standard definition]] widescreen.

===Newscast titles===
*''[[NewsWatch (branding)|Newswatch]] 7&amp;4'' (1980s-early 1990s) 
*''NewsChannel 7&amp;4'' (early 1990s-1999)
*''7&amp;4 News'' (1999-present)

===Station slogans===
*&quot;Your Only 24-Hour Local News and Weather Source&quot; (1990-1999)
*&quot;Coverage You Can Count On&quot; (1999-2008)
*&quot;Fair. Accurate. Honest.&quot; (2008-present)

==News team==
'''Anchors'''
*Melissa Smith - weekday mornings and &quot;Matters of the Heart&quot; segment producer
*Marc Schollett - weeknights at 5, 5:30, 6, and 11
*Diana Fairbanks - weeknights at 5, 5:30, 6, and 11
**&quot;Buddy Check&quot; segments producer
*Erika Erickson - weeknights at 6:30 (on WGTU)
*Brody O'Connell - weekends
'''''7&amp;4 News Storm Team Meteorologists'''''
*Mark Watkins ([[American Meteorological Society|AMS]] Seal of Approval) - Chief seen weeknights
*Joe Charlevoix - weekday mornings
*Christina Burkhart
 - weekends and news reporter

'''Sports''' (both seen on ''Hometown Highlights'')
*Giacomo Accardo - weeknights at 6 and 11
**sports reporter
*Harrison Beeby - sports reporter and news producer

'''Reporters'''
*Doug Luciani - &quot;Chamber Connection&quot; segment producer
*Doug Stanton - &quot;Writer's Minute&quot; segment producer
*Jamie Kramer - weeknights at 6:30 (on WGTU)
*Bob Rhodes - Chief Photojournalist
*Kate Fox - multimedia journalist
*Andrew Keller - Gaylord Bureau
*Brody O'Connell
*Lauren Amstutz

==External links==
*[http://www.upnorthlive.com/ WPBN-TV/WTOM-TV &quot;TV 7&amp;4&quot;]
*{{TVQ|WPBN-TV}}
*{{TVQ|WTOM-TV}}

{{Northern Michigan TV}}
{{Alpena TV}}
{{NBC Michigan}}
{{Barrington Broadcasting}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wpbn-Tv}}
[[Category:NBC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Barrington Broadcasting Company]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1954]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1959|WTOM-TV]]
[[Category:Television stations in Traverse City, Michigan]]
[[Category:Television stations in Michigan]]
[[Category:Channel 47 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 35 digital TV stations in the United States|WTOM-TV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
