<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="22943476" ns="0" title="American philosophy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Scene at the Signing of the Constitution of the United States.png|thumb||right|320px|Painting by [[Howard Chandler Christy]] of the scene at the [[Philadelphia Convention]] which led to the signing of the [[United States Constitution]], an important document in American political and legal philosophy.]]

'''American philosophy''' is the [[philosophical]] activity or output of Americans, both within the [[United States]] and abroad. The ''[[Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]'' notes that while American philosophy lacks a &quot;core of defining features, American Philosophy can nevertheless be seen as both reflecting and shaping collective American identity over the history of the nation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/a/american.htm &quot;American philosophy&quot; at the Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved on May 24, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==17th century==
{{See also|17th century philosophy}}

The American philosophical tradition began at the time of the [[European colonization of the Americas|European colonization]] of the [[New World]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt; The [[Puritan]] arrival in [[New York]] set the earliest American philosophy into the religious tradition, and there was also an emphasis on the relationship between the individual and the community. This is evident by the early colonial documents such as the [[Fundamental Orders of Connecticut]] (1639) and the [[Massachusetts Body of Liberties]] (1641).&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt; 

Thinkers such as [[John Winthrop]] emphasized the public life over the private, holding that the former takes precedence over the latter, while other writers, such as [[Roger Williams (theologian)|Roger Williams]] (co-founder of [[Rhode Island]]) held that [[religious tolerance]] was more integral than trying to achieve religious homogeneity in a community.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wnet/historyofus/web03/segment2.html &quot;Religious Tolerance&quot; - Freedom: A History of US: PBS.com] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==18th century==
{{See also|18th century philosophy}}

18th century American philosophy is often broken into two halves, the earlier half being marked by Puritan [[Calvinism]], and the latter characterized by the American incarnation of the [[European Enlightenment]] that is associated with the [[political thought]] of the Founding Fathers.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt;

===Calvinism===
[[Jonathan Edwards (theologian)|Jonathan Edwards]] is considered to be &quot;America's most important and original philosophical theologian.&quot;&lt;ref name = SEPJEdwards&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/edwards/ ''Standford Encyclopedia of Philosophy,'' &quot;Jonathan Edwards,&quot; First published Tue Jan 15, 2002; substantive revision Tue Nov 7, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; Noted for his energetic sermons, such as &quot;[[Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God]]&quot; (which is said to have begun the [[First Great Awakening]]), Edwards emphasized &quot;the absolute sovereignty of God and the beauty of God's holiness.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SEPJEdwards&quot;/&gt; Working to unite Christian [[Platonism]] with an [[empiricist]] [[epistemology]], with the aid of [[Newtonian physics]], Edwards was deeply influenced by [[George Berkeley]], himself an empiricist, and Edwards derived his importance of the immaterial for the creation human experience from Bishop Berkeley. 

The non-material mind consists of understanding and will, and it is understanding, interpreted in a Newtonian framework, that leads to Edwards' fundamental metaphysical category of Resistance. Whatever features an object may have, it has these properties because the object resists. Resistance itself is the exertion of God's power, and it can be seen in [[Newton's laws of motion]], where an object is &quot;unwilling&quot; to change its current state of motion; an object at rest will remain at rest and an object in motion will remain in motion.

[[File:Thomas Jefferson by Rembrandt Peale, 1800.jpg|thumb|upright|Portrait of Thomas Jefferson by [[Rembrandt Peale]], 1800.]]

As a Calvinist and [[Compatibilism and incompatibilism#Hard Determinism|hard determinist]], Jonathan Edwards also rejected the [[Free will|freedom of the will]], saying that &quot;we can do as we please, but we cannot please as we please.&quot; According to Edwards, neither good works nor self-originating faith lead to salvation, but rather it is the unconditional grace of God which stands as the sole arbiter of human fortune.

===The Age of Enlightenment===
While the early 18th century American philosophical tradition was decidedly marked by religious themes, the latter half saw a reliance on [[reason]] and [[science]], and, in step with the thought of the [[Age of Enlightenment]], a belief in the perfectibility of human beings, [[laissez-faire]] [[economics]], and a general focus on political matters.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt;

Four of the [[Founding Fathers of the United States|Founding Fathers]], [[John Adams]], [[Thomas Jefferson]], [[Benjamin Franklin]], and [[James Madison]], wrote extensively on political issues. In continuing with the chief concerns of the Puritans in the 17th century, the Founding Fathers debated the relationship between the individual and the state, as well as the nature of the state, importantly concerning the state's relationship to God and religion. It was at this time that the [[United States Declaration of Independence]] and [[United States Constitution]] were written, and they are the result of debate and compromise. 

The Constitution sets forth a [[federated]] [[republic]]an form of [[government]] that is marked by a [[balance of powers]] accompanied by a [[checks and balances]] system between the three branches of government: a [[judicial branch]], an [[executive branch]] led by the [[President of the United States|President]], and a [[legislative branch]] composed of a [[bicameral legislature]] where the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] is the [[lower house]] and the [[United States Senate|Senate]] is the [[upper house]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://supreme.justia.com/constitution/article-1/02-bicameralism.html &quot;Bicameralism and Enumerated, Implied, Resulting, and Inherent Powers&quot;] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

While the Declaration of Independence does contain within it references to the Creator, the Founding Fathers were decidedly not exclusively [[theism|theistic]], some openly professing personal concepts of [[deism]], as was characteristic of other European Enlightenment thinkers, such as [[Maximilien Robespierre]], [[François-Marie Arouet]] (better known by his [[pen name]], [[Voltaire]]), and [[Rousseau]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://atheism.about.com/od/churchstatemyths/a/doi.htm &quot;Declaration of Independence &amp; Christianity Myth&quot;] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The most notably and self-consciously Christian of the Founding Fathers was John Adams. However, the 1796 [[Treaty of Tripoli]], signed by John Adams, states that &quot;the government of the United States of America is not in any sense founded on the Christian Religion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/bar1796t.asp &quot;The Avalon Project&quot; at Yale Law School Library] Retrieved August 2, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Thomas Paine]], the [[intellectual]], [[pamphleteer]], and [[revolutionary]] who wrote [[Common Sense (pamphlet)|''Common Sense'']] and ''[[Rights of Man]]'' was an influential Enlightenment thinker and American Founding Father. ''Common Sense'', which has been described as “the most incendiary and popular pamphlet of the entire revolutionary era&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gordon Wood, ''The American Revolution: A History'' (New York: Modern Library, 2002), 55&lt;/ref&gt; provides justification for the American revolution and independence from the British Crown.

==19th century==
{{See also|19th century philosophy}}

The 19th century saw the rise of [[Romanticism]] in America. The American incarnation of Romanticism was [[transcendentalism]] and it stands as a major American innovation. The 19th century also saw the rise of the school of pragmatism, along with a smaller, [[Hegelian]] philosophical movement led by [[George Holmes Howison]] that was focused in [[St. Louis]], though the influence of American pragmatism far outstripped that of the small Hegelian movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt;  

Other reactions to materialism included the &quot;[[Objective idealism]]&quot; of [[Josiah Royce]], and the &quot;[[Personalism]],&quot; sometimes called &quot;Boston personalism,&quot; of [[Borden Parker Bowne]].  

===Transcendentalism===
[[Image:Henry David Thoreau.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Henry David Thoreau, 1856]]
[[Image:Ralph Waldo Emerson ca1857.jpg|thumb|upright|Ralph Waldo Emerson, ca. 1857]]
[[Transcendentalism]] in the United States was marked by an emphasis on subjective experience, and can be viewed as a reaction against [[modernism]] and [[intellectualism]] in general and the mechanistic, [[reductionism|reductionistic]] worldview in particular. Transcendentalism is marked by the [[holism|holistic]] belief in an ideal spiritual state that 'transcends' the physical and empirical, and this perfect state can only be attained by one's own intuition and personal reflection, as opposed to either industrial progress and scientific advancement or the principles and prescriptions of traditional, organized religion. The most notable transcendentalist writers include [[Ralph Waldo Emerson]], [[Henry David Thoreau]], and [[Margaret Fuller]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adherents.com/largecom/fam_transcendentalist.html &quot;Famous Transcendentalists&quot;] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

The transcendentalist writers all desired a deep return to [[nature]], and believed that real, true knowledge is intuitive and personal and arises out of personal immersion and reflection in nature, as opposed to scientific knowledge that is the result of empirical sense experience.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/transcendentalism/ &quot;Transcendentalism&quot; at the SEP] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

Things such as scientific tools, political institutions, and the conventional rules of morality as dictated by traditional religion need to be transcended. This is found in [[Henry David Thoreau]]'s ''[[Walden; or, Life in the Woods]]'' where transcendence is achieved through immersion in nature and the distancing of oneself from society.

===Darwinism in America===
The release of [[Charles Darwin]]'s [[evolutionary theory]] in his 1859 publication of ''[[On the Origin of Species]]'' had a strong impact on American philosophy. [[John Fiske (philosopher)|John Fiske]] and [[Chauncey Wright]] both wrote about and argued for the re-conceiving of philosophy through an evolutionary lens. They both wanted to understand [[morality]] and the [[mind]] in Darwinian terms, setting a precedent for [[evolutionary psychology]] and [[evolutionary ethics]].

Darwin's biological theory was also integrated into the social and political philosophies of [[English people|English]] thinker [[Herbert Spencer]] and American philosopher [[William Graham Sumner]]. Herbert Spencer, who coined the oft-misattributed term &quot;[[survival of the fittest]],&quot; believed that societies were in a struggle for survival, and that groups within society are where they are because of some level of fitness. This struggle is beneficial to human kind, as in the long run the weak will be weeded out and only the strong will survive. This position is often referred to as [[Social Darwinism]]. 

Sumner, much influenced by Spencer, believed along with the industrialist [[Andrew Carnegie]] that the social implication of the fact of the struggle for survival is that laissez-faire capitalism is the natural political-economic system and is the one that will lead to the greatest amount of well-being. William Sumner, in addition to his advocacy of free markets, also espoused [[anti-imperialism]] (having been credited with coining the term &quot;[[ethnocentrism]]&quot;), and advocated for the [[gold standard]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nndb.com/people/882/000165387/ &quot;William Graham Sumner&quot; - nndb.com] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pragmatism===
Perhaps the most influential school of thought that is uniquely American is [[pragmatism]]. It began in the late nineteenth century in the United States with [[Charles Sanders Peirce]], [[William James]], and [[John Dewey]]. Pragmatism begins with the idea that belief is that upon which one is willing to act. It holds that a proposition's meaning is the consequent form of conduct or practice that would be implied by accepting the proposition as true.&lt;ref name=&quot;IEPrag&quot;&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/p/pragmati.htm &quot;Pragmatism&quot; at IEP] Retrieved on July 30, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

====Charles Sanders Peirce====
[[Image:Charles Sanders Peirce theb3558.jpg|thumb|upright|Charles Sanders Peirce, an American pragmatist, logician, mathematician, philosopher, and scientist.]]

[[Polymath]], [[logician]], [[mathematician]], philosopher, and [[scientist]] [[Charles Sanders Peirce]] ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|p|ɜr|s}} like &quot;purse&quot;; 1839–1914) coined the term &quot;pragmatism&quot; in the 1870s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://science.jrank.org/pages/10825/Pragmatism-Charles-Sanders-Peirce.html &quot;Pragmatism - Charles Sanders Peirce&quot;] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He was a member of [[The Metaphysical Club]], which was a conversational club of intellectuals that also included [[Chauncey Wright]], future [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] [[List of Justices of the Supreme Court of the United States|Justice]] [[Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr.]], and another early figure of pragmatism, [[William James]].&lt;ref name=&quot;IEPrag&quot;/&gt; In addition to making profound contributions to [[semiotics]], logic, and mathematics, Peirce wrote what are considered to be the founding documents of pragmatism, &quot;[[s:The Fixation of Belief|The Fixation of Belief]]&quot; (1877) and [[s:How to Make Our Ideas Clear|&quot;How to Make Our Ideas Clear&quot;]] (1878).

In &quot;The Fixation of Belief&quot; Peirce argues for the superiority of the [[scientific method]] in settling belief on theoretical questions. In &quot;How to Make Our Ideas Clear&quot; Peirce argued for pragmatism as summed up in that which he later called the [[pragmatic maxim]]: &quot;Consider what effects, that might conceivably have practical bearings, we conceive the object of our conception to have. Then, our conception of these effects is the whole of our conception of the object&quot;. Peirce emphasized that a conception is general, such that its meaning is not a set of actual, definite effects themselves. Instead the conception of an object is equated to a conception of that object's effects to a general extent of their conceivable implications for informed practice. Those conceivable practical implications are the conception's meaning.

The maxim is intended to help fruitfully clarify confusions caused, for example, by distinctions that make formal but not practical differences. Traditionally one analyzes an idea into parts (his example: a definition of truth as a sign's correspondence to its object). To that needful but confined step, the maxim adds a further and practice-oriented step (his example: a definition of truth as sufficient investigation's destined end). 

It is the heart of his pragmatism as a method of experimentational mental [[Pragmatic maxim#6|reflection]]&lt;ref&gt;Peirce (1902), ''[[Charles Sanders Peirce bibliography#CP|Collected Papers]]'' v. 5, paragraph 13, note 1. See relevant quote at [[Pragmatic maxim#6]]&lt;/ref&gt; arriving at conceptions in terms of conceivable confirmatory and disconfirmatory circumstances — a method hospitable to the formation of explanatory hypotheses, and conducive to the use and improvement of verification.&lt;ref&gt;See ''[[Charles Sanders Peirce bibliography#CP|Collected Papers]]'', v. 1, paragraph 34, [http://www.textlog.de/4220.html Eprint] (in &quot;The Spirit of Scholasticism&quot;), where Peirce ascribes the success of modern science less to a novel interest in verification than to the improvement of verification.&lt;/ref&gt; Typical of Peirce is his concern with inference to explanatory hypotheses as outside the usual foundational alternative between deductivist rationalism and inductivist empiricism, though he himself was a [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Mathematics of logic|mathematician of logic]] and a [[Founders of statistics|founder of statistics]].

[[Charles Sanders Peirce#Philosophy|Peirce's philosophy]] includes a pervasive [[Categories (Peirce)|three-category system]], both [[fallibilism]] and [[Pragmatism#antiskep|anti-skeptical]] belief that truth is discoverable and immutable, [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Philosophy: logic, or semiotic|logic as formal semiotic]] (including [[Semiotic elements and classes of signs (Peirce)|semiotic elements and classes of signs]], [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Modes of inference|modes of inference]], and [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Pragmatism|methods of inquiry]] along with pragmatism and [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Critical_common-sensism|critical common-sensism]]), [[Philosophical realism|Scholastic realism]], [[Charles Sanders Peirce#Philosophy: metaphysics|theism]], [[objective idealism]], and belief in the reality [[Synechism|of continuity]] of space, time, and law, and in the reality [[Tychism|of chance]], mechanical necessity, and [[Agapism|creative love]] as principles operative in the cosmos and as modes of its evolution.

====William James====
[[Image:wm james.jpg|thumb|upright|left|William James, an American pragmatist and psychologist.]]

[[William James]] (1842–1910) was &quot;an original thinker in and between the disciplines of physiology, psychology and philosophy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/james/ &quot;William James&quot; at SEP] Retrieved on July 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He is famous as the author of ''[[The Varieties of Religious Experience]]'', his monumental tome ''[[Principles of Psychology]]'', and his lecture &quot;[[The Will to Believe]].&quot;

James, along with Peirce,&lt;ref&gt;See &quot;Pragmatism (Editor [3])&quot;, c. 1906, especially the portion published in ''[[Charles Sanders Peirce bibliography#CP|Collected Papers]]'' v. 5 (1934), paragraphs 11-12.&lt;/ref&gt; saw pragmatism as embodying familiar attitudes elaborated into a radical new philosophical method of thinking and resolving dilemmas. In his 1910 ''[[s:Pragmatism: A New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking|Pragmatism: A New Name for Some Old Ways of Thinking]]'' he wrote:
{{cquote|[T]he tangible fact at the root of all our thought-distinctions, however subtle, is that there is no one of them so fine as to consist in anything but a possible difference of practice. To attain perfect clearness in our thoughts of an object, then, we need only consider what conceivable effects of a practical kind the object may involve — what sensations we are to expect from it, and what reactions we must prepare.}}
James is also known for his [[radical empiricism]] which holds that relations between objects are as real as the objects themselves. James was also a pluralist in that he believed that there may actually be multiple correct accounts of truth. He rejected the [[correspondence theory of truth]] and instead held that truth involves a belief, facts about the world, other background beliefs, and future consequences of those beliefs. Later in his life James would also come to adopt [[neutral monism]], the view that the ultimate [[reality]] is of one kind, and is neither [[Mental substance|mental]] nor [[physical property|physical]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/neutral-monism/ &quot;Neutral Monism&quot; at the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

====John Dewey====

[[John Dewey]] (1859–1952), while still engaging in the lofty academic philosophical work of James and Peirce before him, also wrote extensively on political and social matters, and his presence in the public sphere was much greater than his pragmatist predecessors. In addition to being one of the founding members of pragmatism, John Dewey was one of the founders of [[functional psychology]] and was a leading figure of the [[Progressive education|progressive]] movement in U.S. schooling during the first half of the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Violas, Paul C.; Tozer, Steven; Senese, Guy B. |title=School and Society: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives |publisher=McGraw-Hill Humanities/Social Sciences/Languages |year= |page=121 |isbn=0-07-298556-9 |doi=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Dewey argued against the individualism of classical liberalism, asserting that social institutions are not &quot;means for obtaining something for individuals. They are means for creating individuals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/dewey-political/#2 &quot;Dewey's Political Philosophy&quot; at SEP] Retrieved on July 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He held that individuals are not things that should be accommodated by social institutions, instead, social institutions are prior to and shape the individuals. These social arrangements are a means of creating individuals and promoting individual freedom.

Dewey is well known for his work in the [[applied philosophy]] of the [[philosophy of education]]. Dewey's philosophy of education is one where children learn by doing. Dewey believed that schooling was unnecessarily long and formal, and that children would be better suited to learn by engaging in real-life activities. For example, in math, students could learn by figuring out proportions in cooking or seeing how long it would take to travel distances with certain modes of transportation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://wilderdom.com/experiential/JohnDeweyPhilosophyEducation.html John Dewey: Philosophy of Education&quot;] Retrieved on July 30, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==20th century==
[[Image:George Santayana.jpg|thumb|upright|George Santayana, the most famous Hispanic-American philosopher.]]
{{See also|20th century philosophy}}

Pragmatism, which began in the 19th century in America, by the beginning of the 20th century began to be accompanied by other philosophical schools of thought, and was eventually eclipsed by them, though only temporarily. The 20th century saw the emergence of process philosophy, itself influenced by the scientific world-view and [[Einstein]]'s [[theory of relativity]]. The middle of the 20th century was witness to the increase in popularity of the [[philosophy of language]] and analytic philosophy in America. [[Existentialism]] and [[Phenomenology (philosophy)|phenomenology]], while very popular in Europe in the 20th century, never achieved the level of popularity in America as they did in continental Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt;

===Rejection of idealism===
Pragmatism continued its influence into the 20th century, and Spanish-born philosopher [[George Santayana]] was one of the leading proponents of pragmatism in this period. He held that [[idealism]] was an outright contradiction and rejection of [[common sense]]. He held that, if something must be certain in order to be knowledge, then it seems no knowledge may be possible, and the result will be [[skepticism]]. According to Santayana, knowledge involved a sort of faith, which he termed &quot;animal faith.&quot; 

In his book ''[[Scepticism and Animal Faith]]'' he asserts that knowledge is not the result of reasoning. Instead, knowledge is what is required to order to act and successfully engage with the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/santayana/ &quot;George Santayana&quot; at the Stanford Encylclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 9, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; As a naturalist, Santayana was a harsh critic of [[Foundationalism|epistemological foundationalism]]. The explanation of events in the natural world is within the realm of science, while the meaning and value of this action should be studied by philosophers. Santayana was accompanied in the intellectual climate of 'common sense' philosophy by the thinkers of the [[New Realism]] movement, such as [[Ralph Barton Perry]].

===Process philosophy===
[[Process philosophy]] embraces the Einsteinian world-view, and its main proponents include [[Alfred North Whitehead]] and [[Charles Hartshorne]]. The core belief of process philosophy is the claim that events and processes are principle [[ontological]] categories.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/process-philosophy/ &quot;Process Philosophy&quot; at the SEP] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Whitehead asserted in his book ''The Concept of Nature'' that the things in nature, what he referred to as &quot;concresences&quot; are a conjunction of events that maintain a permanence of character. Process philosophy is [[Heraclitan]] in the sense that a fundamental ontological category is change.&lt;ref&gt;[http://websyte.com/alan/process.htm &quot;Process Philosophy and the New Thought Movement&quot;] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Charles Hartshorne was also responsible for developing the process philosophy of Whitehead into [[process theology]].

===Analytic philosophy===
[[Image:Wvq-passport-1975-400dpi-crop.jpg|thumb|upright|An image of Quine as seen on his [[passport]].]]
The middle of the 20th century was the beginning of the dominance of [[analytic philosophy]] in America. Analytic philosophy, prior to its arrival in America, had begun in Europe with the work of [[Gottlob Frege]], [[Bertrand Russell]], [[Ludwig Wittgenstein]], and the [[logical positivists]]. According to logical positivism, the truths of logic and mathematics are [[tautology (logic)|tautologies]], and those of science are empirically verifiable. Any other claim, including the claims of ethics, aesthetics, theology, metaphysics, and ontology, are meaningless (this theory is called [[verificationism]]). With the rise of [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[Nazi Party]], many positivists fled [[Germany]] to [[United Kingdom|Britain]] and America, and this helped reinforce the dominance of analytic philosophy in the United States in subsequent years.&lt;ref name=&quot;AmerIEP&quot;/&gt;

[[W.V.O. Quine]], while not a logical positivist, shared their view that philosophy should stand shoulder to shoulder with science in its pursuit of intellectual clarity and understanding of the world. He criticized the logical positivists and the [[Analytic-synthetic distinction|analytic/synthetic distinction of knowledge]] in his essay &quot;[[Two Dogmas of Empiricism]]&quot; and advocated for his &quot;web of belief,&quot; which is a [[coherentism|coherentist]] theory of justificiation. In Quine's epistemology, since no experiences occur in isolation, there is actually a holistic approach to knowledge where every belief or experience is intertwined with the whole. Quine is also famous for inventing the term &quot;gavagai&quot; as part of his theory of the [[indeterminacy of translation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nickbostrom.com/old/quine.html &quot;UNDERSTANDING QUINE'S THESES OF INDETERMINACY&quot; by Nick Bostrom] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Kripke.JPG|thumb|upright|left|Saul Kripke at [[Juquehy]] Beach]]  [[Saul Kripke]], a student of Quine at [[Harvard]], has profoundly influenced analytic philosophy. Kripke was ranked among the top ten most important philosophers of the past 200 years in a poll conducted by [[Brian Leiter]] (Leiter Reports: a Philosophy Blog; [[open access poll]])&lt;ref&gt;Brian Leiter, &quot;The last poll about philosophers for awhile--I promise!&quot; [http://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2009/03/the-last-poll-about-philosophers-for-awhilei-promise.html] (March 7, 2009) and &quot;So who *is* the most important philosopher of the past 200 years?&quot; [http://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2009/03/so-who-is-the-most-important-philosopher-of-the-past-200-years.html] (March 11, 2009), ''Leiter Reports: A Philosophy Blog''.&lt;/ref&gt; Kripke is best known for four contributions to philosophy: (1) [[Kripke semantics]] for [[modal logic|modal]] and related logics, published in several essays beginning while he was still in his teens. (2) His 1970 Princeton lectures [[Naming and Necessity]] (published in 1972 and 1980), that significantly restructured the [[philosophy of language]] and, as some have put it, &quot;made metaphysics respectable again&quot;. (3) His interpretation of the philosophy of [[Wittgenstein]].&lt;ref&gt;1982. Wittgenstein on Rules and Private Language: an Elementary Exposition. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press. ISBN 0-674-95401-7. Sets out his interpretation of Wittgenstein aka Kripkenstein.&lt;/ref&gt; (4) His theory of [[truth]]. He has also made important contributions to [[set theory]] (see [[admissible ordinal]] and [[Kripke-Platek set theory]])

[[David Kellogg Lewis]], another student of Quine at [[Harvard]], was ranked as one of the greatest philosophers of the 20th century in a poll conducted by [[Brian Leiter]] ([[open access poll]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://leiterreports.typepad.com/blog/2009/03/lets-settle-this-once-and-for-all-who-really-was-the-greatest-philosopher-of-the-20thcentury.html &quot;Let's Settle This Once and For All: Who Really Was the Greatest Philosopher of the 20th-Century?&quot;] Retrieved on July 29, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He is well known for his controversial advocacy of [[modal realism]], the position which holds that there is an infinite number of concrete and causally isolated [[Possible World|possible worlds]], of which ours is one.&lt;ref&gt;[http://philosophy.princeton.edu/david_lewis.html &quot;David K. Lewis&quot; - Princeton University Department of Philosophy] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; These possible worlds arise in the field of [[modal logic]].

[[Thomas Kuhn]] was an important philosopher and writer who worked extensively in the fields of the [[history of science]] and the [[philosophy of science]]. He is famous for writing ''[[The Structure of Scientific Revolutions]]'', one of the most cited academic works of all time. The book argues that science proceeds through different ''[[paradigms]]'' as scientists find new puzzles to solve. There follows a widespread struggle to find answers to questions, and a shift in world views occurs, which is referred to by Kuhn as a ''[[paradigm shift]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/thomas-kuhn/#3 &quot;Thomas Kuhn&quot; at the SEP] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The work is considered a milestone in the [[sociology of knowledge]].

===Return to political philosophy===
The analytic philosophers troubled themselves with the abstract and the conceptual, and American philosophy did not fully return to social and political concerns (that dominated American philosophy at the time of the founding of the United States) until the 1970s. The return to political and social concerns included the popularity of works of [[Ayn Rand]], who promoted [[Ethical egoism]] (which she called [[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)|Objectivism]]) in her novels, ''[[The Fountainhead]]'' in 1943 and ''[[Atlas Shrugged]]'' in 1957. 

These two novels gave birth to the [[Objectivist movement]], one which started as a small group of students called The Collective, one of whom was a young [[Alan Greenspan]], the well-known libertarian [[Chairman of the Federal Reserve]]. Objectivism holds that there is an objective external reality that can be known with reason, that human beings should [[ethical egoism|act in accordance with their own rational self-interest]], and that the proper form of economic organization is [[laissez-faire]] capitalism.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aynrand.org/site/PageServer?pagename=objectivism_intro &quot;INTRODUCING OBJECTIVISM&quot; by Ayn Rand] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Academic philosophers have been highly critical of the quality and intellectual rigor of Rand's work,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cato-unbound.org/2010/01/20/roderick-long/the-winnowing-of-ayn-rand/ &quot;The Winnowing of Ayn Rand&quot; by Roderick Long] Retrieved July 10, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.heraldscotland.com/the-philosophical-art-of-looking-out-number-one-1.835066 &quot;The philosophical art of looking out number one&quot; at heraldscotland] Retrieved July 10, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; but she remains a popular, albeit controversial, figure within the American libertarian movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/rand/ &quot;Ayn Rand&quot; at the Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved July 10, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cato.org/special/threewomen/rand.html &quot;Profile of Ayn Rand at the Cato Institute] Retrieved July 10, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1971 [[John Rawls]] published his book ''[[A Theory of Justice]]''. The book puts forth Rawls' view of ''[[justice as fairness]]'', one which is based on a form of [[social contract]] theory. Rawls employs the use of a conceptual mechanism called the [[veil of ignorance (philosophy)|veil of ignorance]] to outline his idea of the [[original position]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://jeffersonswall.blog-city.com/john_rawls_vs_robert_nozick.htm &quot;Philosophy: John Rawls vs. Robert Nozick&quot;] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

In Rawls' philosophy, the original position is the correlate to the [[Thomas Hobbes|Hobbesian]] [[state of nature]]. While in the original position, persons are said to be behind the veil of ignorance, which makes these persons unaware of their individual characteristics and their place in society, such as their race, religion, wealth, etc. The principles of justice are chosen by rational persons while in this original position. The two principles of justice are the equal liberty principle and the principle which governs the distribution of social and economic inequalities. From this, Rawls argues for a system of [[distributive justice]] in accordance with the Difference Principle, which says that all social and economic inequalities must be to the greatest benefit of the least advantaged.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/justice-distributive/ &quot;Distributive Justice&quot; at SEP] Retrieved December 18, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Viewing Rawls as promoting excessive government control and rights violations, [[Libertarianism|libertarian]] [[Robert Nozick]] published ''[[Anarchy, State, and Utopia]]'' in 1974. The book advocates for a minimal state and defends the liberty of the individual. He argues that the role of government should be limited to &quot;police protection, national defense, and the administration of courts of law, with all other tasks commonly performed by modern governments – education, social insurance, welfare, and so forth – taken over by religious bodies, charities, and other private institutions operating in a free market.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/nozick/ &quot;Robert Nozick (1938—2002)&quot; at the Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

Nozick asserts his view of the [[entitlement theory]] of justice, which says that if everyone in society has acquired their holdings in accordance with the principles of acquisition, transfer, and rectification, then any pattern of allocation, no matter how unequal the distribution may be, is just. The entitlement theory of justice holds that the &quot;justice of a distribution is indeed determined by certain historical circumstances (contrary to end-state theories), but it has nothing to do with fitting any pattern guaranteeing that those who worked the hardest or are most deserving have the most shares.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/nozick/ &quot;Robert Nozick&quot; at IEP] Retrieved January 5, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Alasdair MacIntyre]], while he was born and educated in the [[United Kingdom]], has spent around forty years living and working in the United States. He is responsible for the resurgence of interest in [[virtue ethics]], a [[Ethics|moral theory]] first propounded by the ancient [[Greek philosophy|Greek philosopher]] [[Aristotle]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/09/004-the-virtues-of-alasdair-macintyre-6 &quot;The Virtues of Alasdair MacIntyre&quot;] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/ &quot;Virtue Ethics&quot; at SEP] Retrieved on September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He is considered the preeminent [[Thomism|Thomist]] political philosopher. He holds that &quot;modern philosophy and modern life are characterized by the absence of any coherent moral code, and that the vast majority of individuals living in this world lack a meaningful sense of purpose in their lives and also lack any genuine community&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iep.utm.edu/p-macint/ &quot;Political Philosophy of Alasdair MacIntyre&quot; at IEP.com] Retrieved December 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; He recommends a return to genuine political communities where individuals can properly acquire their virtues.

Outside [[academic]] philosophy, political and social concerns took center stage with the [[Civil Rights Movement]] and the writings of [[Martin Luther King, Jr.]]

===Feminism===
[[Image:Betty Friedan 1960.jpg|thumb|upright|Betty Friedan]]{{See also| History of feminism}}
While there were earlier writers who would be considered feminist, such as [[Sarah Grimké]], [[Charlotte Perkins Gilman]], [[Elizabeth Cady Stanton]], and [[Anne Hutchinson]], the feminist movement of the 1960s and 1970s, also known as [[second-wave feminism]], is notable for its impact in philosophy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/feminism-topics/ &quot;Topics in Feminism&quot; at the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 7, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; 

The popular mind was taken with [[Betty Friedan]]'s ''[[The Feminine Mystique]]''. This was accompanied by other feminist philosophers, such as [[Adrienne Rich]]. These philosophers critiqued basic assumptions and values of philosophy, such as objectivity and what they believe to be masculine approaches to ethics, for example, rights-based political theories. They wrote that there is no such thing as a value-neutral inquiry and they sought to analyze the social dimensions of philosophical issues.

==Contemporary philosophy==
[[Image:Hilary Putnam.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Hilary Putnam]]  
Towards the end of the 20th century there was a resurgence of interest in pragmatism. Largely responsible for this are [[Hilary Putnam]] and [[Richard Rorty]]. Rorty is famous as the author of ''[[Philosophy and the Mirror of Nature]]'' and ''[[Philosophy and Social Hope]]''. Hilary Putnam is well known for his [[quasi-empiricism in mathematics]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Hilary Putnam|Putnam, Hilary]], 1975, ''Mind, Language, and Reality. Philosophical Papers, Volume 2''. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK. ISBN 88-459-0257-9&lt;/ref&gt; his challenge of the [[brain in a vat]] [[thought experiment]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/brain-vat/ &quot;Brains in a Vat&quot; at the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and his other work in [[philosophy of mind]], [[philosophy of language]], and [[philosophy of science]].

The debates that occur within the [[philosophy of mind]] have taken center stage. American philosophers such as Hilary Putnam, [[Donald Davidson (philosopher)|Donald Davidson]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.utm.edu/research/iep/d/davidson.htm &quot;Donald Davidson&quot; at the Internet Encylclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Dennett]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://philosophy.uwaterloo.ca/MindDict/dennett.html &quot;Daniel Dennett&quot; at the Dictionary of the Philosophy of Mind] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; [[Douglas Hofstadter]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indiana.edu/~alldrp/members/hofstadter.html Douglas Hofstadter's page at Indiana.edu] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Searle]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://philosophy.uwaterloo.ca/MindDict/searle.html &quot;John Searle&quot; at the Dictionary of the Philosophy of Mind] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[Patricia Churchland|Patricia]] and [[Paul Churchland]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/materialism-eliminative/#BriHis &quot;Eliminative Materialism&quot; at the Stanford Encylclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; continue the discussion of such issues as the nature of [[mind]] and the [[hard problem of consciousness]], a philosophical problem indicated by the Australian philosopher [[David Chalmers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://consc.net/papers/facing.html &quot;Facing Up to the Problem of Consciousness&quot; - David Chalmers] Retrieved September 10, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

Noted American legal philosophers [[Ronald Dworkin]] and [[Richard Posner]] work in the fields of political philosophy and [[jurisprudence]]. Posner is famous for his [[economic analysis of law]], a theory which uses microeconomics to understand legal rules and institutions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/legal-econanalysis/ &quot;The Economic Analysis of Law&quot; by Lewis Kornhauser at the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 11, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; Dworkin is famous for his theory of [[law as integrity]] and [[Interpretivism (legal)|legal interpretivism]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/law-interpretivist/ &quot;Interpretivist Theories of Law&quot; by Nicos Stavropoulos at the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy] Retrieved September 11, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal
| doi = 10.1093/ojls/8.2.266
| issn = 01436503
| volume = 8
| issue = 2
| pages = 266–277
| last = Allan
| first = T. R. S.
| title = Review: Dworkin and Dicey: The Rule of Law as Integrity
| journal = Oxford Journal of Legal Studies
| accessdate = 2009-09-111
| year = 1988
| jstor = 764314
| publisher = Oxford University Press
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[African-American]] philosopher [[Cornel West]] is known for his analysis of American cultural life with regards to [[race (classification of human beings)|race]], [[gender]], and [[Social class|class]] issues, as well as his associations with [[pragmatism]] and [[transcendentalism]].

[[Alvin Plantinga]] is a [[Christian]] thinker known for his [[evolutionary argument against naturalism]], his assertion that one can know God as a properly [[basic belief]], and his [[modal logic|modal]] version of the [[ontological argument]] for the existence of God. [[Michael C. Rea]] has developed Plantinga's thought by claiming that both naturalism and supernaturalism are research programmes that have to be adopted as a basis for research.&lt;ref&gt;Michael C. Rea: World Without Design: Ontological Consequences of Naturalism. Oxford, Clarendon Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[History of philosophy]]

'''Lists:'''
* [[List of American philosophers]]
* [[List of African American philosophers]]
* [[List of Jewish American philosophers]]

'''Organizations:'''
* [[American Philosophical Association]]
* [[American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy]]
* [[American Philosophical Society]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.apaonline.org/ American Philosophical Association]
* [http://www.amphilsoc.org/ American Philosophical Society]
* [http://www.american-philosophy.org/ Society for the Advancement of American Philosophy]

{{Philosophy topics}}
{{United States topics}}

[[Category:Philosophy by region]]
[[Category:American literature]]

[[bg:Американска философия]]
[[es:Filosofía en Estados Unidos]]
[[et:Ameerika filosoofia]]
[[fr:Philosophie américaine]]
[[ja:アメリカ合衆国の哲学]]
[[ru:Американская философия]]
[[sk:Americká filozofia]]
[[sv:Amerikansk filosofi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
