<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2296056" ns="0" title="Sky High (2005 film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name = Sky High
| image = Sky_High_movie_poster.jpg
| caption = Theatrical release poster (L-R: [[Kelly Vitz]], Winstead, Angarano, Russell, Preston, Strait, Panabaker)
| director = [[Mike Mitchell (director)|Mike Mitchell]]
| producer = [[Andrew Gunn (producer)|Andrew Gunn]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Brian Grazer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ron Howard]]
| writer = Paul Hernandez&lt;br /&gt;[[Bob Schooley]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mark McCorkle]]
| starring = [[Michael Angarano]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Danielle Panabaker]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kurt Russell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kelly Preston]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mary Elizabeth Winstead]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Steven Strait]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Lynda Carter]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bruce Campbell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cloris Leachman]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dave Foley]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kevin McDonald]]
| music = [[Michael Giacchino]]
| cinematography = [[Shelly Johnson (cinematographer)|Shelly Johnson]]
| editing = Peter Amundson
| studio = [[Imagine Entertainment]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Gunn Films]]
| distributor = [[Walt Disney Pictures]]
| released = {{start date|2005|7|29}}
| runtime = 100 minutes
| country = United States
| language = English
| budget = $35 million
| gross = $86,369,815
| Followed by = [[Sky High 2]]
}}

'''''Sky High''''' is a 2005 American [[Comedy film|comedic]] [[superhero film|superhero]] [[Family film|family]] film about an airborne school for teenage superheroes. It was directed by [[Mike Mitchell (director)|Mike Mitchell]] and written by Paul Hernandez, Robert Schooley, and [[Mark McCorkle]].  The starring cast includes [[Michael Angarano]] as Will, an incoming freshman at the school; [[Danielle Panabaker]] as his best friend; [[Kurt Russell]] and [[Kelly Preston]] as his parents; [[Mary Elizabeth Winstead]] as a popular senior; [[Steven Strait]] as Will's rival; and [[Lynda Carter]] as the principal. [[Andrew Gunn (producer)|Andrew Gunn]], [[Brian Grazer]] and [[Ron Howard]] produced the film for [[Walt Disney Pictures]].

==Plot==
The story describes the beginning of the freshman year for Will Stronghold ([[Michael Angarano]]) at Sky High School, a school for young superheroes that floats in the sky. Will's parents pose as suburban real-estate agents Steve and Josie Stronghold, but they are really The Commander ([[Kurt Russell]]) and Jetstream ([[Kelly Preston]]), the two most famous and powerful superheroes. The Commander has superhuman strength, and Jetstream is able to fly. Will's best friend is Layla ([[Danielle Panabaker]]), a pretty supergirl who can manipulate plant life.

The students at Sky High include Speed (Will Harris), a bully who can run faster than the human eye can see; Lash ([[Jake Sandvig]]), a bully who can stretch his body; Penny ([[Malika Haqq|Malika]] and [[Khadijah Haqq]]), a cheerleader who can make copies of herself; and Warren Peace ([[Steven Strait]]), the brooding, fire-throwing son of a supervillain and a superhero, who are currently at war. Warren's father was sent to prison by the Commander, and will be released after his third life. As the school year begins, Will is the only student who has not yet developed any superpowers.  Students with great powers are taught to be heroes, while less capable youngsters are designated as &quot;hero support&quot; and derisively referred to as &quot;sidekicks&quot;.  The abilities of the sidekicks include melting, glowing, and turning into a [[guinea pig]]. Will is put into the sidekick program due to his lack of powers, and Layla is made a sidekick after she protests the two tiered schooling by refusing to demonstrate her powers.

At the end of Will's first day at Sky High, the Commander shows him the Stronghold family's underground control center, the Secret Sanctum, which holds souvenirs from past battles. One souvenir is a weapon called a &quot;Pacifier&quot;, which the Commander took from his arch-enemy, a supervillain named Royal Pain, fifteen years ago. Another is the eyeball of a robot the Commander recently defeated. As the Commander and Will chat, Royal Pain remotely spies on them through a camera hidden in the eyeball. 

Will initially makes friends with the sidekicks, but he is transferred to the Hero program after his latent super-strength emerges during a fight with Warren.  He also attracts the attention of Gwen Grayson ([[Mary Elizabeth Winstead]]), a beautiful &quot;technopath&quot; who controls machines with her mind.  Will makes a date with Layla to prove he still likes her, but he forgets about it and has dinner with Gwen and his parents, so Layla tries to make him jealous by getting Warren to go with her to the Sky High homecoming dance.

On the day before the dance, Gwen tricks Will into throwing a party at his house, and Speed steals the Pacifier when she seduces Will into showing her the Secret Sanctum. She also convinces Layla that Will no longer likes her, but Will rejects Gwen's snobbishness and refuses to go to the dance with her, even though his parents have promised to attend as honorary guests. After his parents leave for the dance, Will reads the Commander's school yearbook, which contains a photograph of a girl who looks just like Gwen. When he sees a picture of the girl holding a pacifier, he guesses that the girl is Royal Pain and Gwen is her daughter, sees that the Pacifier is missing, and concludes that Gwen must be avenging herself on the Commander for defeating her mother. Will contacts the Sky High bus driver ([[Kevin Heffernan (comedian)|Kevin Heffernan]]), who rushes him to the dance.

Meanwhile, Gwen reveals to the dance participants that she is Royal Pain herself, who was formally a brilliant schoolgirl who invented the pacifier, but despite that and her powers, she was underestimated by the school and therefore made a sidekick. Outraged, she hatched a plan to destroy Sky High and replace it with her own school for supervillains, with the intention of turning everyone into babies with the Pacifier and raising them into villains.  Only Warren and the sidekicks escape.

When Will arrives at school, he apologizes to Layla and teams up with Warren and the sidekicks to defeat Gwen, Speed, Lash, and Penny. He discovers he has also inherited his mother's flying ability when Gwen throws him off Sky High's floating platform, and he helps to hold the school in the air as the sidekicks reactivate its sabotaged antigravity device. The babies are returned to their original state, Will and Layla kiss, and the dance resumes while Royal Pain and her gang are held in the detention room. Afterward, the villains are sent to prison, Warren becomes Will's best friend, Layla becomes Will's girlfriend, and the bus driver becomes a superhero after falling into a vat of toxic waste.

==Cast==
* [[Michael Angarano]] as William Theodore &quot;Will&quot; Stronghold, a [[freshman]] at Sky High. His parents are the two most famous superheroes&amp;nbsp;— Commander and Jetstream&amp;nbsp;— as well as Maxville's top real estate agents in their secret identities. He has both [[super strength]] and [[flight]]. 
* [[Danielle Panabaker]] as Layla Williams. Will's best friend since childhood. She is a [[Pacifism|pacifist]], [[vegetarian]], and [[Feminism|feminist]], and is able to animate and control plant life. Her mother's abilities are said to allow her to talk to animals, and her father is a normal human. 
* [[Mary Elizabeth Winstead]] as Gwendolyn &quot;Gwen&quot; Grayson/Royal Pain/Sue Tenny, a senior at Sky High whom Will has a crush on. Her power is [[technopathy]]. Winstead said of her role, &quot;I bounced around. I was either the hero of the sidekicks or the sidekick to the heroes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire//index.php?category=0&amp;id=31721 Sky Kids Have Hero Issues],&quot; ''SciFi.com'' (22-JULY-05).&lt;/ref&gt; While in her Royal Pain suit, [[Patrick Warburton]] provides the vocal effects.
* [[Steven Strait]] as Warren Peace (a pun on the novel ''[[War and Peace]]''), the son of an unnamed superheroine and a supervillain known as Barron Battle, a [[homophone]] off [[Battle of Barren Hill|barren battle]] (who in jail with four life sentences). He is [[Pyrokinesis|pyrokinetic]], meaning he can control and manipulate fire
* [[Dee Jay Daniels]] as Ethan, a sidekick who is friends with Will, he can melt into a small orange puddle (which earned him the nickname &quot;Popsicle&quot;). His color code is mostly red, orange and yellow.
* [[Kelly Vitz]] as Magenta/Maj, Will's friend whose ability is to [[Shapeshifting|shapeshift]] into a [[guinea pig]] complete with purple highlights/streaks in her fur. 
* [[Nicholas Braun]] as Zachary &quot;Zach&quot; Braun/Zack Attack, Will's spacey childhood friend, who has the ability to glow in the dark.
* [[Malika Haqq|Malika]] and [[Khadijah Haqq]] as Penny Lent, Gwen's best friend, who can duplicate herself and is naturally athletic.
* [[Jake Sandvig]] and Will Harris as Lash and Speed, the resident bullies at Sky High; Lash is skinny, and has elasticity and can stretch his body parts far, while Speed is large yet can run at [[super speed]]. 
* [[Kurt Russell]] as Steve Stronghold/The Commander, Will's father. As the Commander, he is one of the world's strongest superheroes, displaying [[superhuman strength]] and [[invulnerability]], and is a successful businessman in his secret identity. 
* [[Kelly Preston]] as Josie DeMarco-Stronghold/Jetstream, Will's mother. She is a successful real estate agent. As Jetstream, she has the power of supersonic flight; she is also touted as being an expert in hand-to-hand combat. 
* [[Lynda Carter]] as Principal Powers, the principal of Sky High. She appears to have the power to transform into a comet and back at will. She mainly uses her power as a form of transportation. 
* [[Bruce Campbell]] as Tommy Boomowski/Coach Boomer/Sonic Boom, the gym teacher at Sky High, also known as Sonic Boom due to his ability to release sonic waves from his vocal cords. His power is known as [[sonic scream]]ing. His real name is Tommy Boomowski as seen in the Commander's Sky High Yearbook. 
* [[Kevin Heffernan (comedian)|Kevin Heffernan]] as Ron Wilson, the Sky High bus driver/pilot. Ron is the son of two superheroes but does not have any powers himself. He feels a great sense of pride in driving the &quot;superheroes of tomorrow&quot; to school. 
* [[Cloris Leachman]] as Nurse Spex, a kind and eccentric elderly lady that serves as Sky High's single known nurse, with the ability of [[X-ray vision]]. 
* [[Jim Rash]] as Mr. Grayson/Stitches, Royal Pain's bumbling sidekick. He raised her as his daughter after she was turned into a baby by the Pacifier.  
* [[Dave Foley]] as Jonathan Boy/All-American Boy, the Commander's old sidekick. He now works as Hero Support teacher at Sky High
* [[Kevin McDonald]] as Professor Medulla, the Mad Science teacher, with a hyper-advanced (and oversized) brain, which grants him advanced intelligence, creativity and a multitude of genius-level skills – so much that even as a baby, he still possesses an intellect greater than the average adult. 
* [[Kim Rhodes]] as Elastic Girl/Professor Jeannie Elast, who has the talent to twist her body into anything she wants. 
* [[Tom Kenny]] and [[Jill Talley]] as Mr. and Mrs. Chester Timmerman, who make a small cameo in the movie.

==Production==
[[Image:Oviatt-library-small.jpg|frame|Oviatt Library at CSU Northridge]]
Exterior shots of the Sky High school were filmed at the [[Oviatt Library]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.csun.edu Oviatt Library]&lt;/ref&gt; at [[California State University]] in Northridge.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csun.edu/licensing/filming.php CSUN Licensing - Facilities Use&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to scifi.com, Disney was attracted by the &quot;original concept&quot; of &quot;children of superheroes going to high school&quot;, originally conceived by screenwriter Paul Hernandez in the 1990s.&lt;ref name=scifi&gt;[http://www.scifi.com/sfw/advance/25_interview.html Kurt Russell and company go back to high school to learn what it means to be super in Sky High]&lt;/ref&gt; After recruiting comedy writers [[Mark McCorkle]] and [[Bob Schooley]] for polishing Hernandez's script, Disney hired several comedians like [[Kevin McDonald]], [[Dave Foley]], and [[Kevin Heffernan (comedian)|Kevin Heffernan]] for supporting roles.&lt;ref name=scifi/&gt; For the main roles, the casting was a mix of established and new teenager actors: while [[Michael Angarano]] and [[Mary Elizabeth Winstead]] were already successful, [[Danielle Panabaker]] was little-known and [[Steven Strait]] (a former model) was hired after his first audition ever.&lt;ref name=scifi/&gt;

Producer [[Mike Mitchell (director)|Mike Mitchell]] said that ''Sky High'' functions on two premises: &quot;the adults are all insane&quot; and &quot;the girls are smarter than the boys&quot;:&lt;ref name=dvd&gt;''Sky High'' DVD extras&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, all the adults portrayed in the film tend to be caricatured, while the teenage girls are written as more assertive and powerful than the boys. For the treatment of the teenage actors, Mitchell also stated that the actors all had their own trailer and were generally kept separated, because &quot;we did not want them to date after the second week and break up after the fourth&quot;, which would have made filming difficult.&lt;ref name=dvd/&gt;

Mitchell, a science fiction fan, admitted that this project &quot;was a dream&quot;, because it brought him together with four of his favorite SF cult heroes: namely [[Wonder Woman]] (popularized in the eponymous 1970s series by actress [[Lynda Carter]]), [[Snake Plissken]] (portrayed by [[Kurt Russell]]), [[Ash Williams]] (from ''[[Evil Dead]]'', played by [[Bruce Campbell]]) and [[Cloris Leachman]], who earned fame as Frau Blücher in ''[[Young Frankenstein]]''.&lt;ref name=scifi/&gt;

==Notes about the movie==
*It is one of the first theatrical film movies (along with ''[[The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy (film)|The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy]]'') to be only released on DVD and never released on VHS.
*It was released in summer 2005, a year before ''[[Zoom (film)|Zoom]]'', a [[Tim Allen]] film that explores similar territory.

==Reception and box office figures==
''Sky High'' received generally favorable reviews. Based on review aggregrator [[Rotten Tomatoes]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://rottentomatoes.com rottentomatoes.com]&lt;/ref&gt; the film earned a &quot;fresh&quot; rating of 72% positive reviews (85 positive, 33 negative). Critics on this website were generally favorable on the firmly tongue-in-cheek nature of the film, which knowingly spoofed comic clichés, but others found it too cheesy. Commercially it was a success: on an estimated budget of [[United States dollar|US$]]35 million, it earned just under $64 million in the US alone,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0405325/business Sky High (2005) - Box office / business&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and another $22 million internationally, bringing the total to just over $86 million.

==Soundtrack==
{{Infobox album
| Name        =  Sky High (Original Soundtrack)
| Type        = Soundtrack
| Artist      = Various Artists
| Cover       = Skyhighalbum.jpg
| Cover size  =
| Released    = July 26, 2005
| Recorded    =
| Genre       = [[Soundtrack]]
| Length      =
| Label       = [[Hollywood Records]]
| Misc          = {{Singles
| Name          = Sky High (Original Soundtrack)
| Type          = Soundtrack
| single 1      = [[I Melt with You#Notable covers|I Melt with You]]
| single 1 date = 2005
}}
}}

{{Album ratings
| rev1 = [[Allmusic]]
| rev1score = {{rating|2.5|5}} &lt;ref&gt;{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r783768}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The ''Sky High Original Soundtrack'' was released by [[Hollywood Records]] on July 26, 2005, and is composed of [[Cover version|covers]] of songs from the 1980s.

===Track listing===
#&quot;[[I Melt with You]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Bowling for Soup]] (''Originally by: [[Modern English (band)|Modern English]]'')
#&quot;Through Being Cool&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[They Might Be Giants]] (''Originally by: [[Devo]]'')
#&quot;Save It for Later&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Flashlight Brown]] (''Originally by: [[The Beat (band)|The Beat]]'')
#&quot;[[Everybody Wants to Rule the World]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Christian Burns]] (''Originally by: [[Tears for Fears]]'')
#&quot;[[One Thing Leads to Another]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Steven Strait]] (''Originally by: [[The Fixx]]'')
#&quot;[[Lies (Thompson Twins song)|Lies]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[The Click Five]] (''Originally by: [[Thompson Twins]]'')
#&quot;[[Voices Carry]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Vitamin C (artist)|Vitamin C]] (''Originally by: [['Til Tuesday]]'')
#&quot;[[Please, Please, Please Let Me Get What I Want]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Elefant (band)|Elefant]] (''Originally by: [[The Smiths]]'')
#&quot;[[True (Spandau Ballet song)|True]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Cary Brothers]] (''Originally by: [[Spandau Ballet]]'')
#&quot;[[Just What I Needed]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Caleigh Peters]] (''Originally by: [[The Cars]]'')
#&quot;Can't Stop the World&quot;&amp;nbsp;– Ginger Sling (''Originally by: [[The Go-Go's]]'')
#&quot;[[And She Was]]&quot;&amp;nbsp;– Keaton Simons (''Originally by: [[Talking Heads]]'')
#&quot;Twist and Crawl&quot;&amp;nbsp;– [[Skindred]] (''Originally by: [[The Beat (band)|The Beat]]'')

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
*[[PS 238]]

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{official|http://disney.go.com/disneyvideos/liveaction/skyhigh/}}
* {{imdb title|id=0405325|title=Sky High}}
* {{amg title|id=313197|title=Sky High}}

{{Mike Mitchell}}

[[Category:2005 films]]
[[Category:American action comedy films]]
[[Category:American children's films]]
[[Category:American coming-of-age films]]
[[Category:American fantasy-comedy films]]
[[Category:American teen films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Disney films]]
[[Category:Superhero films]]
[[Category:Superhero comedy films]]

[[ar:سكاي هاي (فيلم 2005)]]
[[de:Sky High – Diese Highschool hebt ab!]]
[[es:Sky High]]
[[fr:L'École fantastique]]
[[id:Sky High]]
[[it:Sky High - Scuola di superpoteri]]
[[nl:Sky High (2005)]]
[[pl:Sky High]]
[[pt:Sky High]]
[[ru:Высший пилотаж (фильм, 2005)]]
[[simple:Sky High (2005 movie)]]
[[fi:Sky High]]
[[sv:Höjdarskolan: Sky High]]
[[th:รวมพันธุ์โจ๋ พลังเหนือโลก]]
[[vi:Sky High (phim 2005)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
