<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2301918" ns="0" title="Huang Zunxian"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Huang Zunxian''' ({{zh|c=黃遵憲|p=Huáng Zūnxiàn|w='''Huang Tsun-hsien'''}}, 1848—28 March 1905), [[courtesy name]] '''Gongdu''' (公度), was a [[Chinese people|Chinese]] [[writer]] and [[poet]], active during the late [[Qing Dynasty]]. He was born in Chia-ying, now [[Mei County, Guangdong]], and died 57 years later in the same place.

==Biography==
Huang was a government official who worked as a diplomat but is remembered today for his poetry. His diplomatic duties took him to [[Japan]], the [[United States]], [[England]] and [[Singapore]] wherein he collected materials for his poems. He created a literary breakthrough by studying speech  and folk songs of the common people in his home town of Chia-ying, and incorporating them into his poetry.

While Huang was a councilor to He Ruzhang, the Qing dynasty's first envoy to Japan in September 1880, he was ordered to compile a policy paper for the visiting Korean reformist [[Kim Hongjip]] with recommendations for Korea's foreign policy.  This important document, known as the Chaoxian Celue (J: Chōsen Sakuryaku K:Choseon Chekryak) advised Korea to strengthen itself through reform and, &quot;Keeping close to China, Creating ties with Japan, and allying with the United States.&quot;  The document was presented to the Korean government upon Kim Hongjip's return and may have been one of the key inspirations for reforms in Korea from 1881 onwards.

==References==
*Kamachi, Noriko. ''Reform in China: Huang Tsun-Hsien and the Japanese Model.'' Cambridge, MA: Council on East Asian Studies, 1981.

*[[Encyclopædia Britannica 2005 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]], article- &quot;Huang Tsun-hsien&quot;

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Huang, Zunxian
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1848
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1905
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Huang, Zunxian}}
[[Category:Qing Dynasty poets]]
[[Category:Hakka people]]
[[Category:People from Meixian]]
[[Category:Chinese folklorists]]
[[Category:1848 births]]
[[Category:1905 deaths]]


{{China-poet-stub}}

[[es:Huang Zunxian]]
[[fr:Huang Zunxian]]
[[ko:황준헌]]
[[nl:Huang Zunxian]]
[[ja:黄遵憲]]
[[zh:黃遵憲]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
