<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2302374" ns="0" title="Liu E"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|This article is about the [[Qing Dynasty]] official and writer.  For the [[Han Zhao]] empress, see [[Empress Liu E]].}}

'''Liu E''' ({{zh|t={{linktext|劉|鶚}}|s={{linktext|刘|鹗}}|p=Liú È}}, 18 October [[1857 in literature|1857]] — 23 August [[1909 in literature|1909]]), [[Chinese style name|courtesy name]]/&quot;zì&quot;: &quot;'''Tieyun'''&quot; ('''T'ieh-yün''') (鐵雲), was a [[China|Chinese]] scholar, entrepreneur, and writer.

==Government and politics==
Liu was a native of Dantu (modern day [[Zhenjiang]]). In the government he worked with flood control, famine relief, and railroads. He became disillusioned with official ideas of reform and became a proponent of private economic development modeled after western systems. During the [[Boxer Uprising]] he speculated in government rice, distributing it to the poor. He was [[Cashiering|cashiered]] for these efforts, but shrewd investments had left him wealthy enough to follow his pioneering archaeological studies and to write fiction.

==Oracle bone archeology and scholarship==
He collected five thousand [[oracle bone]] fragments, published the first volume of examples and rubbings in 1903, and correctly identified thirty-four [[Oracle bone script|oracle bone script characters]].

==''The Travels of Lao Can''==
It was his economic ideas that inspired his literary work ''The Travels of Lao Can'' ({{zh|c={{linktext|老|残|游|记}}|p={{linktext|Lǎo| Cán| Yóu|jì}}}}, or using the [[Wade-Giles]] romanization: &quot;The Travels of Lao Ts'an&quot;) written in 1903-04&lt;ref name=masterworks&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=cUcHvd-KYUUC&amp;pg=PA299 Barbara Stoler Miller, Masterworks of Asian Literature in Comparative Perspective: A Guide for Teaching, published by M.E. Sharpe, 1994]&lt;/ref&gt; and published in [[1907 in literature|1907]]. Thinly disguising his own views in those of the physician hero, Liu satirically describes (inaccurately){{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} the rise of the Boxers in the countryside , the decay of the Yellow River control system, and the hypocritical incompetence of the bureaucracy. The novel, a social satire that showed the limits of the old elite and officialdom, was an immediate success. The 1983 translation by [[Yang Xianyi]] and [[Gladys Yang]] omits major sections on the grounds that Liu could not have written them because they were superstitious.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

==Exile and death==
Liu was framed for malfeasance related to his work during the Boxer Rebellion and was exiled in 1908, dying within the next year in [[Ürümqi|Urumqi, Xinjiang]].

==References==
{{reflist}}
*Shen, Tianyou, ''[[Encyclopedia of China]]'', 1st ed.
* ''The Travels of Lao Ts'an'', Liu T'ieh-yün (Liu E), translated by Harold Shadick, professor of Chinese literature in Cornell University. Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1952. Reissued: New York; London: Columbia University Press, 1990. 277p. (A Morningside Book).
* ''The travels of Lao Can'', translated by Yang Xianyi, Gladys Yang (Beijing: Panda Books, 1983; 176p.)

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Liu, E
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1857
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1909
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Liu, E}}
[[Category:Qing Dynasty politicians]]
[[Category:Qing Dynasty poets]]
[[Category:Chinese novelists]]
[[Category:Chinese archaeologists]]
[[Category:Chinese people of the Boxer Rebellion]]
[[Category:1857 births]]
[[Category:1909 deaths]]


{{China-politician-stub}}
{{China-writer-stub}}
{{China-academic-bio-stub}}

[[cs:Liu O]]
[[es:Liu E]]
[[fr:Liu E]]
[[ja:劉鶚]]
[[fi:Liu E]]
[[zh:刘鹗]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
