<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23037" ns="0" title="Punk rock"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the music genre|the play of the same name|Punk Rock (play)}}
{{Infobox Music genre
| name              = Punk rock
| color             = white
| bgcolor           = crimson
| stylistic_origins = [[Rock and roll]]{{•wrap}} [[folk music|folk]]{{•wrap}} [[rockabilly]]{{•wrap}} [[ska]]{{•wrap}} [[surf music|surf rock]]{{•wrap}} [[garage rock]]{{•wrap}} [[glam rock]]{{•wrap}} [[Pub rock (UK)|pub rock]]{{•wrap}} [[protopunk]]
| cultural_origins  = Mid-[[1970s in music|1970s]], United States, United Kingdom, and Australia 
| instruments       = {{nowrap begin}}[[singer|Vocals]]{{•wrap}} [[electric guitar]]{{•wrap}} [[Bass guitar|bass]]{{•wrap}} [[Drum kit|drums]]{{nowrap end}}
| popularity        = Topped charts in UK during late 1970s. International commercial success for [[pop punk]] and [[ska punk]], mid-1990s–2000s.
| derivatives       = {{nowrap begin}}[[New Wave music|New Wave]]{{•wrap}} [[post-punk]]{{•wrap}} [[gothic rock]]{{•wrap}} [[alternative rock]]{{•wrap}} [[grunge]]{{•wrap}} [[emo]]{{nowrap end}}
| subgenrelist      = Punk rock subgenres
| subgenres         = {{nowrap begin}}[[Anarcho-punk]]{{•wrap}} [[art punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Christian punk]]{{•wrap}} [[crust punk]]{{•wrap}} [[garage punk]]{{•wrap}} [[glam punk]]{{•wrap}} [[hardcore punk]]{{•wrap}}  [[oi!]]{{•wrap}} [[Riot Grrrl]]{{•wrap}} [[skate punk]]{{nowrap end}}
| fusiongenres      = {{nowrap begin}}[[2 Tone]]{{•wrap}} [[anti-folk]]{{•wrap}} [[avant-punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Celtic punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Chicano punk]]{{•wrap}} [[cowpunk]]{{•wrap}} [[deathrock]]{{•wrap}} [[folk punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Scottish Gaelic punk|Gaelic punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Gypsy punk]]{{•wrap}} [[pop punk]]{{•wrap}} [[psychobilly]]{{•wrap}} [[punk blues]]{{•wrap}} [[punk jazz]]{{•wrap}} [[ska punk]]{{nowrap end}}
| regional_scenes   = {{nowrap begin}}[[Argentine punk|Argentina]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk rock in Australia|Australia]]{{•wrap}} [[Basque Radical Rock|Basque Country]] {{•wrap}} [[List of topics related to Belgian punk|Belgium]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk in Brazil|Brazil]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk rock in California|California]]{{•wrap}} [[French punk|France]]{{•wrap}} [[German punk|Germany]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk rock in Spain|Spain]]{{•wrap}} [[Uruguayan punk|Uruguay]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk in Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]]{{nowrap end}}
| local_scenes      = {{nowrap begin}}[[Brisbane punk rock|Brisbane]]{{•wrap}} [[Toronto punk rock|Toronto]]{{nowrap end}}
| other_topics      = {{nowrap begin}}[[Protopunk]]{{•wrap}} [[DIY ethic]]{{•wrap}} [[List of musicians in the first wave of punk music|First wave punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Queercore]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk fashion]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk ideologies]]{{•wrap}} [[list of punk movies|Punk movies]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk zine|Punk fanzines]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk subculture]]{{•wrap}} [[Timeline of punk rock|Punk timeline]]{{•wrap}} [[List of musicians in the second wave of punk music|Second wave punk]]{{•wrap}} [[Straight Edge]]{{•wrap}} [[List of punk bands, 0–K|List of punk bands]]{{•wrap}} [[Punk rock subgenres]]{{nowrap end}}
'''
'''
}}
'''Punk rock''' is a [[rock music]] genre that developed between 1974 and 1976 in the United States, the United Kingdom, and Australia. Rooted in [[garage rock]] and other forms of what is now known as [[protopunk]] music, punk rock bands eschewed perceived excesses of mainstream 1970s rock. Punk bands created fast, hard-edged  music, typically with short songs, stripped-down instrumentation, and often political, [[anti-establishment]] lyrics. Punk embraces a [[DIY ethic]]; many bands self-produced recordings and distributed them through informal channels.

By late 1976, bands such as the [[Ramones]], in New York City, and the [[Sex Pistols]] and [[The Clash]], in London, were recognized as the vanguard of a new musical movement. The following year saw punk rock spreading around the world, and it became a major cultural phenomenon in the United Kingdom. For the most part, punk took root in local scenes that tended to reject association with the mainstream. An associated [[punk subculture]] emerged, expressing youthful rebellion and characterized by distinctive [[Punk fashion|styles of clothing and adornment]] and a variety of [[Punk ideologies|anti-authoritarian ideologies]].

By the beginning of the 1980s, faster, more aggressive styles such as [[hardcore punk|hardcore]] and [[Oi!]] had become the predominant mode of punk rock. Musicians identifying with or inspired by punk also pursued a broad range of other variations, giving rise to [[post-punk]] and the [[alternative rock]] movement. By the turn of the century, [[pop punk]] had been adopted by the mainstream, as bands such as [[Green Day]] and [[The Offspring]] brought the genre widespread popularity.

==Characteristics==
===Philosophy===
[[File:Ramones - Ramones cover.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Ramones]]' 1976 [[Ramones (album)|debut album]] laid down the musical &quot;blueprint for punk&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Erlewine, Stephen Thomas, [{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p5223|pure_url=yes}} &quot;The Ramones: Biography&quot;], ''Allmusic''. Retrieved on October 11, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; while its cover image had a similarly formative influence on punk visual style.&lt;ref name=RamonesCover&gt;Bessman (1993), pp. 48, 50; Miles, Scott, and Morgan (2005), p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The first wave of punk rock aimed to be aggressively modern, distancing itself from the bombast and sentimentality of early 1970s rock.&lt;ref name=&quot;RMB&quot;&gt;Robb (2006), foreword by Michael Bracewell.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[Ramones]] drummer [[Tommy Ramone]], &quot;In its initial form, a lot of [1960s] stuff was innovative and exciting. Unfortunately, what happens is that people who could not hold a candle to the likes of [[Jimi Hendrix|Hendrix]] started noodling away. Soon you had endless solos that went nowhere. By 1973, I knew that what was needed was some pure, stripped down, no bullshit rock 'n' roll.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ramone, Tommy, &quot;Fight Club&quot;, ''[[UNCUT (magazine)|Uncut]]'', January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Holmstrom]], founding editor of ''[[Punk (magazine)|Punk]]'' magazine, recalls feeling &quot;punk rock had to come along because the rock scene had become so tame that [acts] like [[Billy Joel]] and [[Simon and Garfunkel]] were being called rock and roll, when to me and other fans, rock and roll meant this wild and rebellious music.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MM&quot;&gt;McLaren, Malcolm, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/5263364.stm &quot;Punk Celebrates 30 Years of Subversion&quot;], BBC News, August 18, 2006. Retrieved on January 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In critic [[Robert Christgau]]'s description, &quot;It was also a subculture that scornfully rejected the political idealism and Californian flower-power silliness of hippie myth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Christgau, Robert, [http://www.robertchristgau.com/xg/bkrev/mcneil-nyt.php &quot;''Please Kill Me: The Uncensored Oral History of Punk'', by Legs McNeil and Gillian McCain&quot; (review)], ''New York Times Book Review'', 1996. Retrieved on January 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Patti Smith]], in contrast, suggests in the documentary ''25 Years of Punk'' that the hippies and the punk rockers were linked by a common anti-establishment mentality.

Throughout punk rock history, technical accessibility and a [[Do it yourself|DIY]] spirit have been prized. In the early days of punk rock, this ethic stood in marked contrast to what those in the scene regarded as the ostentatious musical effects and technological demands of many mainstream rock bands.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., Rodel (2004), p. 237; Bennett (2001), pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt; Musical virtuosity was often looked on with suspicion. According to Holmstrom, punk rock was &quot;rock and roll by people who didn't have very much skills as musicians but still felt the need to express themselves through music&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MM&quot;/&gt; In December 1976, the English [[fanzine]] ''Sideburns'' published a now-famous illustration of three chords, captioned &quot;This is a chord, this is another, this is a third. Now form a band.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 280–281, including reproduction of the original image. Several sources incorrectly ascribe the illustration to the leading fanzine of the London punk scene, ''[[Sniffin' Glue]]'' (e.g., Wells [2004], p. 5; Sabin [1999], p. 111). Robb (2006) ascribes it to [[The Stranglers]]' in-house fanzine, ''Strangled'' (p. 311). In fact, ''Strangled'', which only began appearing in 1977, evolved out of ''Sideburns'' (see, e.g., {{cite web|url=http://www.xulucomics.com/strangled.html|title=''Strangled'' |publisher=Xulu Brand Comics|accessdate=2009-03-19}})&lt;/ref&gt; The title of a 1980 single by the New York punk band Stimulators, &quot;Loud Fast Rules!&quot;, inscribed a catchphrase for punk's basic musical approach.&lt;ref&gt;Blush (2001), pp. 173, 175. See also [http://www.kbdrecords.com/2006/09/21/the-stimulators-loud-fast-rules-7/ The Stimulators—Loud Fast Rules 7″] Killed By Death Records (September 21, 2006).&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of British punk rock's leading figures made a show of rejecting not only contemporary mainstream rock and the broader culture it was associated with, but their own most celebrated predecessors: &quot;No [[Elvis Presley|Elvis]], [[The Beatles|Beatles]] or the [[The Rolling Stones|Rolling Stones]] in 1977&quot;, declared [[The Clash]] song &quot;1977&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Harris (2004), p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt; The previous year, when the punk rock revolution began in Great Britain, was to be both a musical and a cultural &quot;Year Zero&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;Reynolds p4&quot;&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Even as nostalgia was discarded, many in the scene adopted a [[nihilism|nihilistic]] attitude summed up by the [[Sex Pistols]] slogan &quot;No Future&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;RMB&quot;/&gt; in the later words of one observer, amid the unemployment and social unrest in 1977, &quot;punk's nihilistic swagger was the most thrilling thing in England.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jeffries, Stuart. &quot;A Right Royal Knees-Up&quot;. ''The Guardian''. July 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; While &quot;self-imposed [[social alienation|alienation]]&quot; was common among &quot;drunk punks&quot; and &quot;gutter punks&quot;, there was always a tension between their nihilistic outlook and the &quot;radical leftist utopianism&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Washburne, Christopher, and Maiken Derno. ''Bad Music''. Routledge, 2004. Page 247.&lt;/ref&gt; of bands such as [[Crass]], who found positive, liberating meaning in the movement. As a Clash associate describes singer [[Joe Strummer]]'s outlook, &quot;Punk rock is meant to be our freedom. We're meant to be able to do what we want to do.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kosmo Vinyl, ''The Last Testament: The Making of London Calling'' (Sony Music, 2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

The issue of authenticity is important in the punk subculture—the pejorative term &quot;[[poseur]]&quot; is applied to those who associate with punk and adopt its stylistic attributes but are deemed not to share or understand the underlying values and philosophy. Scholar Daniel S. Traber argues that &quot;attaining authenticity in the punk identity can be difficult&quot;; as the punk scene matured, he observes, eventually &quot;[e]veryone got called a poseur&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pages=30–64 |doi=10.1353/cul.2001.0040 |title=L.A.'s 'White Minority': Punk and the Contradictions of Self-Marginalization |year=2001 |last1=Traber |first1=Daniel S. |journal=Cultural Critique |volume=48}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Musical and lyrical elements===
Punk rock bands often emulate the bare musical structures and arrangements of 1960s [[garage rock]].&lt;ref&gt;Murphy, Peter, &quot;Shine On, The Lights Of The Bowery: The Blank Generation Revisited&quot;, ''Hot Press'', July 12, 2002; [[Barney Hoskyns|Hoskyns, Barney]], &quot;Richard Hell: King Punk Remembers the [ ] Generation&quot;, ''[[Rock's Backpages]]'', March 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; Typical punk rock instrumentation includes one or two electric guitars, an electric bass, and a drum kit, along with vocals. Punk rock songs tend to be shorter than those of other popular genres—on the Ramones' [[Ramones (album)|debut album]], for instance, half of the fourteen tracks are under two minutes long. Most early punk rock songs retained a traditional rock 'n' roll [[verse-chorus form]] and 4/4 [[time signature]]. However, punk rock bands in the movement's second wave and afterward have often broken from this format. In critic Steven Blush's description, &quot;The Sex Pistols were still rock'n'roll...like the craziest version of [[Chuck Berry]]. [[Hardcore punk|Hardcore]] was a radical departure from that. It wasn't verse-chorus rock. It dispelled any notion of what songwriting is supposed to be. It's its own form.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;blush&quot;&gt;Blush, Steven, &quot;Move Over My Chemical Romance: The Dynamic Beginnings of US Punk&quot;, ''[[UNCUT (magazine)|Uncut]]'', January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Punk rock vocals sometimes sound nasal,&lt;ref&gt;Wells (2004), p. 41; Reed (2005), p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; and lyrics are often shouted instead of sung in a conventional sense, particularly in hardcore styles.&lt;ref name=&quot;S159&quot;&gt;Shuker (2002), p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; The vocal approach is characterized by a lack of variety; shifts in pitch, volume, or intonational style are relatively infrequent.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 58; Reynolds (2005), p. ix.&lt;/ref&gt; Complicated guitar solos are considered self-indulgent and unnecessary, although basic guitar breaks are common.&lt;ref&gt;Chong, Kevin, [http://www.cbc.ca/arts/music/guitarsolos.html &quot;The Thrill Is Gone&quot;], Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, August 2006. Retrieved on December 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Guitar parts tend to include highly distorted [[power chords]] or [[barre chords]], creating a characteristic sound described by Christgau as a &quot;buzzsaw drone&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Laing (1985), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Some punk rock bands take a [[surf rock]] approach with a lighter, twangier guitar tone. Others, such as [[Robert Quine]], lead guitarist of [[The Voidoids]], have employed a wild, &quot;[[Gonzo journalism|gonzo]]&quot; attack, a style that stretches back through [[The Velvet Underground]] to the 1950s recordings of [[Ike Turner]].&lt;ref&gt;Palmer (1992), p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Bass guitar lines are often uncomplicated; the quintessential approach is a relentless, repetitive &quot;forced rhythm&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; although some punk rock bass players—such as [[Mike Watt]] of [[The Minutemen (band)|The Minutemen]] and [[Firehose (band)|Firehose]]—emphasize more technical bass lines. Bassists often use a [[Plectrum|pick]] due to the rapid succession of notes, which makes [[fingerpicking]] impractical. Drums typically sound heavy and dry, and often have a minimal set-up. Compared to other forms of rock, [[syncopation]] is much less the rule.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 61–63.&lt;/ref&gt; Hardcore drumming tends to be especially fast.&lt;ref name=&quot;S159&quot;/&gt; Production tends to be minimalistic, with tracks sometimes laid down on home tape recorders&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 118–119.&lt;/ref&gt; or simple four-track portastudios. The typical objective is to have the recording sound unmanipulated and &quot;real&quot;, reflecting the commitment and &quot;authenticity&quot; of a live performance.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Punk recordings thus often have a [[lo-fi]] quality, with the sound left relatively unpolished in the [[audio mastering|mastering]] process; recordings may contain dialogue between band members, false starts, and background noise.

[[Image:Clash 21051980 12 800.jpg|left|thumb|[[The Clash]], performing in 1980]]
Punk rock lyrics are typically frank and confrontational; compared to the lyrics of other popular music genres, they frequently comment on social and political issues.&lt;ref&gt;Sabin (1999), pp. 4, 226; Dalton, Stephen, &quot;Revolution Rock&quot;, ''Vox'', June 1993. See also Laing (1985), pp. 27–32, for a statistical comparison of lyrical themes.&lt;/ref&gt; Trend-setting songs such as The Clash's &quot;[[Career Opportunities (song)|Career Opportunities]]&quot; and [[Chelsea (band)|Chelsea's]] &quot;Right to Work&quot; deal with unemployment and the grim realities of urban life.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Especially in early British punk, a central goal was to outrage and shock the mainstream.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 81, 125.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sex Pistols classics &quot;[[Anarchy in the U.K.]]&quot; and &quot;[[God Save the Queen (Sex Pistols song)|God Save the Queen]]&quot; openly disparage the British political system and social mores. There is also a characteristic strain of anti-sentimental depictions of relationships and sex, exemplified by &quot;Love Comes in Spurts&quot;, written by [[Richard Hell]] and recorded by him with The Voidoids. [[Anomie]], variously expressed in the poetic terms of Hell's &quot;[[Blank Generation (song)|Blank Generation]]&quot; and the bluntness of the Ramones' &quot;Now I Wanna Sniff Some Glue&quot;, is a common theme. Identifying punk with such topics aligns with the view expressed by [[V. Vale]], founder of San Francisco fanzine ''[[RE/Search|Search and Destroy]]'': &quot;Punk was a total cultural revolt. It was a hardcore confrontation with the black side of history and culture, right-wing imagery, sexual taboos, a delving into it that had never been done before by any generation in such a thorough way.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Savage (1991), p. 440. See also Laing (1985), pp. 27–32.&lt;/ref&gt; However, many punk rock lyrics deal in more traditional rock 'n' roll themes of courtship, heartbreak, and hanging out; the approach ranges from the deadpan, aggressive simplicity of Ramones standards such as &quot;I Wanna Be Your Boyfriend&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Segal, David|title=Punk's Pioneer|work=Washington Post|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn?pagename=article&amp;node=digest&amp;contentId=A25121-2001Apr16|date=2001-04-17|accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; to the more unambiguously sincere style of many later pop punk groups.

===Visual and other elements===
The classic punk rock look among male U.S. musicians harkens back to the T-shirt, motorcycle jacket, and jeans ensemble favored by American [[Greaser (subculture)|greasers]] of the 1950s associated with the [[rockabilly]] scene and by British [[Rocker (subculture)|rockers]] of the 1960s. The cover of the Ramones' 1976 debut album, featuring a shot of the band by ''Punk'' photographer Roberta Bayley, set forth the basic elements of a style that was soon widely emulated by rock musicians both punk and nonpunk.&lt;ref name=RamonesCover/&gt; Richard Hell's more androgynous, ragamuffin look—and reputed invention of the [[safety pin#Culture|safety-pin aesthetic]]—was a major influence on Sex Pistols impresario [[Malcolm McLaren]] and, in turn, British punk style.&lt;ref name=&quot;RHV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Isler, Scott; Robbins, Ira |title=Richard Hell &amp; the Voidoids |work=[[Trouser Press]]|url=http://www.trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=richard_hell_and_the_voidoids|accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), pp. 58, 63, 64; Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt; (John Morton of Cleveland's [[The Electric Eels|Electric Eels]] may have been the first rock musician to wear a safety-pin-covered jacket.)&lt;ref&gt;See {{cite web|author=Weldon, Michael|title=Electric Eels: Attendance Required |url=http://www.cleveland.com/music/index_story.ssf?/music/more/local/cle/2/index.html|publisher=Cleveland.com|accessdate=19 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; McLaren's partner, fashion designer [[Vivienne Westwood]], credits Johnny Rotten as the first British punk to rip his shirt, and Sex Pistols bassist [[Sid Vicious]] as the first to use safety pins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Young, Charles M.| date= October 20, 1977| title=Rock Is Sick and Living in London| work=Rolling Stone| url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/thebeatles/articles/story/9437647/sex_pistols_rock_is_sick_and_living_in_london?source=thebeatles_rssfeed | accessdate=10 October 2006|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060914225550/http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/thebeatles/articles/story/9437647/sex_pistols_rock_is_sick_and_living_in_london?source=thebeatles_rssfeed |archivedate = September 14, 2006|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early female punk musicians displayed styles ranging from [[Siouxsie Sioux]]'s bondage gear to Patti Smith's &quot;straight-from-the-gutter androgyny&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strohm&quot;&gt;Strohm (2004), p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt; The former proved much more influential on female fan styles.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., Laing (1985), &quot;Picture Section&quot;, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, tattoos, [[Body piercing|piercings]], and metal-studded and -spiked accessories became increasingly common elements of [[punk fashion]] among both musicians and fans, a &quot;style of adornment calculated to disturb and outrage&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wojcik (1997), p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; The typical male punk haircut was originally short and choppy; the [[Mohawk hairstyle|Mohawk]] later emerged as a characteristic style.&lt;ref&gt;Wojcik (1995), pp. 16–19; Laing (1985), p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; Those in hardcore scenes often adopt a [[skinhead]] look.

[[Image:punks.jpg|left|thumb|UK punks, circa 1986]]
The characteristic stage performance style of male punk musicians does not deviate significantly from the macho postures classically associated with rock music.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 89, 97–98, 125.&lt;/ref&gt; Female punk musicians broke more clearly from earlier styles. Scholar John Strohm suggests that they did so by creating personas of a type conventionally seen as masculine: &quot;They adopted a tough, unladylike pose that borrowed more from the macho swagger of sixties garage bands than from the calculated bad-girl image of bands like [[The Runaways]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Strohm&quot;/&gt; Scholar Dave Laing describes how bassist [[Gaye Advert]] adopted fashion elements associated with male musicians only to generate a stage persona readily consumed as &quot;sexy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 92, 88.&lt;/ref&gt; Laing focuses on more innovative and challenging performance styles, seen in the various erotically destabilizing approaches of Siouxsie Sioux, [[The Slits]]' [[Ari Up]], and [[X-Ray Spex]]' [[Poly Styrene]].&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 89, 92–93.&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of emphatic syncopation led punk dance to &quot;deviant&quot; forms. The characteristic style was originally the [[Pogo (dance)|pogo]].&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 34, 61, 63, 89–91.&lt;/ref&gt; Sid Vicious, before he became the Sex Pistols' bassist, is credited with initiating the pogo in Britain as an attendee at one of their concerts.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 90; Robb (2006), pp. 159–160.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Moshing]] is typical at hardcore shows. The lack of conventional dance rhythms was a central factor in limiting punk's mainstream commercial impact.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt;

Breaking down the distance between performer and audience is central to the punk ethic.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; Fan participation at concerts is thus important; during the movement's first heyday, it was often provoked in an adversarial manner—apparently perverse, but appropriately &quot;punk&quot;. First-wave British punk bands such as the Sex Pistols and [[The Damned (band)|The Damned]] insulted and otherwise goaded the audience into intense reactions. Laing has identified three primary forms of audience physical response to goading: can throwing, stage invasion, and spitting or &quot;gobbing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 84–85.&lt;/ref&gt; In the hardcore realm, stage invasion is often a prelude to [[stage diving]]. In addition to the numerous fans who have started or joined punk bands, audience members also become important participants via the scene's many amateur periodicals—in England, according to Laing, punk &quot;was the first musical genre to spawn fanzines in any significant numbers&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pre-history== &lt;!-- this section is a redirect from [[Punk Rock History]] --&gt;

===Garage rock and mod===
{{Details3|[[Garage rock]] and [[Mod (subculture)]]}}
In the early and mid-1960s, garage rock bands that came to be recognized as punk rock's progenitors began springing up in many different locations around North America. [[The Kingsmen]], a garage band from Portland, Oregon, had a breakout hit with their 1963 cover of &quot;[[Louie, Louie]]&quot;, cited as &quot;punk rock's defining [[Urtext|ur-text]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Sabin (1999), p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt; The minimalist sound of many garage rock bands was influenced by the harder-edged wing of the [[British Invasion]]. [[The Kinks]]' hit singles of 1964, &quot;[[You Really Got Me]]&quot; and &quot;[[All Day and All of the Night]]&quot;, have been described as &quot;predecessors of the whole three-chord genre—the Ramones' 1978 'I Don't Want You,' for instance, was pure Kinks-by-proxy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Harrington (2002), p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1965, [[The Who]] quickly progressed from their debut single, &quot;[[I Can't Explain]]&quot;, a virtual Kinks clone, to &quot;[[My Generation (The Who song)|My Generation]]&quot;. Though it had little impact on the American charts, The Who's mod anthem presaged a more cerebral mix of musical ferocity and rebellious posture that characterized much early British punk rock: John Reed describes The Clash's emergence as a &quot;tight ball of energy with both an image and rhetoric reminiscent of a young [[Pete Townshend]]—speed obsession, pop-art clothing, art school ambition&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Reed (2005), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; The Who and fellow mods [[The Small Faces]] were among the few rock elders acknowledged by the Sex Pistols.&lt;ref&gt;Fletcher (2000), p. 497.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1966, mod was already in decline. U.S. garage rock began to lose steam within a couple of years, but the raw sound and outsider attitude of &quot;garage [[psychedelic rock|psych]]&quot; bands like [[The Seeds]] presaged the style of bands that would become known as the archetypal figures of protopunk.&lt;ref&gt;See Sabin (1999), p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protopunk===
{{Details|Protopunk}}
In 1969, debut albums by two [[Michigan]]-based bands appeared that are commonly regarded as the central protopunk records. In January, Detroit's [[MC5]] released ''[[Kick Out the Jams]]''. &quot;Musically the group is intentionally crude and aggressively raw&quot;, wrote critic [[Lester Bangs]] in ''[[Rolling Stone]]'':
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Most of the songs are barely distinguishable from each other in their primitive two-chord structures. You've heard all this before from such notables as the Seeds, [[Blue Cheer]], [[? &amp; the Mysterians|Question Mark and the Mysterians]], and the Kingsmen. The difference here&amp;nbsp;... is in the hype, the thick overlay of teenage-revolution and total-energy-thing which conceals these scrapyard vistas of clichés and ugly noise.&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;&quot;I Want You Right Now&quot; sounds exactly (down to the lyrics) like a song called &quot;I Want You&quot; by [[the Troggs]], a British group who came on with a similar sex-and-raw-sound image a couple of years ago (remember &quot;[[Wild Thing (The Troggs song)|Wild Thing]]&quot;?)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/mc5/albums/album/105316/review/5941601/kick_out_the_jams MC5: ''Kick Out the Jams''] review by Lester Bangs, ''[[Rolling Stone]]'', April 5, 1969. Retrieved on January 16, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/mc5/albums/album/105316/review/5941601/kick_out_the_jams|date =20070205080821|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;[[File:Iggy-Pop 1977.jpg|thumb|right|[[Iggy Pop]], the &quot;godfather of punk&quot;]]
That August, [[The Stooges]], from [[Ann Arbor, Michigan|Ann Arbor]], premiered with a [[The Stooges (album)|self-titled album]]. According to critic [[Greil Marcus]], the band, led by singer [[Iggy Pop]], created &quot;the sound of [[Chuck Berry]]'s [[You Can't Catch Me|Airmobile]]—after thieves stripped it for parts&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Marcus (1979), p. 294.&lt;/ref&gt; The album was produced by [[John Cale]], a former member of New York's experimental rock group [[The Velvet Underground]]. Having earned a &quot;reputation as the first underground rock band&quot;, The Velvet Underground inspired, directly or indirectly, many of those involved in the creation of punk rock.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early 1970s, the [[New York Dolls]] updated the original wildness of 1950s rock 'n' roll in a fashion that later became known as [[glam punk]].&lt;ref&gt;Harrington (2002), p. 538.&lt;/ref&gt; The New York duo [[Suicide (band)|Suicide]] played spare, experimental music with a confrontational stage act inspired by that of The Stooges. At the Coventry club in the New York City borough of [[Queens]], [[The Dictators]] used rock as a vehicle for wise-ass attitude and humor.&lt;ref&gt;Bessman (1993), pp. 9–10.&lt;/ref&gt; In Boston, [[The Modern Lovers]], led by Velvet Underground devotee [[Jonathan Richman]], gained attention with a minimalistic style. In 1974, an updated garage rock scene began to coalesce around the newly opened [[The Rathskeller|Rathskeller]] club in [[Kenmore Square]]. Among the leading acts were the [[Real Kids]], founded by former Modern Lover [[John Felice]]; [[Willie Alexander|Willie Alexander and the Boom Boom Band]], whose frontman had been a member of the Velvet Underground for a few months in 1971; and Mickey Clean and the Mezz.&lt;ref&gt;Andersen and Jenkins (2001), p. 12. {{cite web | last =Vaughan| first = Robin| title = Reality Bites| work = Boston Phoenix| url = http://bostonphoenix.com/boston/music/cellars/documents/02927794.htm|date = June 6–12, 2003| accessdate =}} {{cite web | last =Harvard| first = Joe| title = Mickey Clean and the Mezz| work = Boston Rock Storybook | url = http://www.rockinboston.com/themezz.htm| accessdate =}} {{cite web | last =Robbins | first = Ira| title = Wille Alexander| work = Trouser Press Guide | url = http://trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=willie_alexander_and_the_boom_boom_band| accessdate = 2007-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1974, as well, the Detroit band [[Death (punk band)|Death]]—made up of three African-American brothers—recorded &quot;scorching blasts of feral ur-punk&quot;, but couldn't arrange a release deal.&lt;ref name=Rubin&gt;{{cite news | author =Rubin, Mike | title = This Band Was Punk Before Punk Was Punk| work = New York Times | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/03/15/arts/music/15rubi.html|date=2009-03-12| accessdate = 2009-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Ohio, a small but influential underground rock scene emerged, led by [[Devo]] in [[Akron, Ohio|Akron]] and [[Kent, Ohio|Kent]] and by Cleveland's [[Electric Eels (band)|The Electric Eels]], Mirrors and [[Rocket from the Tombs]]. In 1975, Rocket from the Tombs split into [[Pere Ubu]] and [[The Dead Boys|Frankenstein]]. The Electric Eels and Mirrors both broke up, and [[The Styrenes]] emerged from the fallout.&lt;ref&gt;Klimek, Jamie, [http://www.jilmar.com/mirrors/story.html &quot;Mirrors&quot;], ''Jilmar Music''; Jäger, Rolf, [http://www.rent-a-dog.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=16%3Athe-styrenes-city-of-women&amp;catid=2%3Akatalogarchiv&amp;Itemid=4&amp;lang=en &quot;Styrenes—A Brief History&quot;], ''Rent a Dog''. Both retrieved on November 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Britain's [[The Deviants (band)|Deviants]], in the late 1960s, played in a range of psychedelic styles with a satiric, anarchic edge and a penchant for [[Situationist International|situationist]]-style spectacle presaging the Sex Pistols by almost a decade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thanatosoft.freeserve.co.uk/supermarketfiles/strangedays.htm|title=Interview with Mick Farren|publisher = ''Strange Days'' (Japan)|first=Toshikazu|last=Ohtaka|coauthor=Akagawa, Yukiko |accessdate=2008-01-10|quote=Soundwise, we wanted to be incredibly loud and violent! That says it all. The hippies wanted to be nice and gentle, but our style was the opposite of that peaceful, natural attitude.|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080508000420/http://www.thanatosoft.freeserve.co.uk/supermarketfiles/strangedays.htm |archivedate = May 8, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1970, the act evolved into the [[Pink Fairies]], which carried on in a similar vein.&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (1998), pp. 86–91.&lt;/ref&gt; With his [[The Rise and Fall of Ziggy Stardust and the Spiders from Mars|Ziggy Stardust]] persona, [[David Bowie]] made artifice and exaggeration central—elements, again, that were picked up by the Sex Pistols and certain other punk acts.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 24–26.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Doctors of Madness]] built on Bowie's presentation concepts, while moving musically in the direction that would become identified with punk. Bands in London's [[Pub rock (UK)|pub rock]] scene stripped the music back to its basics, playing hard, R&amp;B-influenced rock 'n' roll. By 1974, the scene's top act, [[Dr. Feelgood]], was paving the way for others such as [[The Stranglers]] and [[Cock Sparrer]] that would play a role in the punk explosion. Among the pub rock bands that formed that year was [[The 101ers|The 101'ers]], whose lead singer would soon adopt the name Joe Strummer.&lt;ref&gt;Robb (2006), p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bands anticipating the forthcoming movement were appearing as far afield as [[Düsseldorf]], West Germany, where &quot;punk before punk&quot; band [[Neu!|NEU!]] formed in 1971, building on the [[Krautrock]] tradition of groups such as [[Can (band)|Can]].&lt;ref name=&quot;trouser2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last =Neate| first = Wilson| title = NEU! | work = Trouser Press | url = http://www.trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=neu | accessdate = 2007-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Japan, the anti-establishment Zunō Keisatsu (Brain Police) mixed garage psych and folk. The combo regularly faced censorship challenges, their live act at least once including onstage masturbation.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson (2002), p. 588.&lt;/ref&gt; A new generation of Australian garage rock bands, inspired mainly by The Stooges and MC5, was coming even closer to the sound that would soon be called &quot;punk&quot;: In [[Brisbane]], [[The Saints (band)|The Saints]] also recalled the raw live sound of the British [[Pretty Things]], who had made a notorious tour of Australia and New Zealand in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (2000), p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Radio Birdman]], cofounded by Detroit expatriate [[Deniz Tek]] in 1974, was playing gigs to a small but fanatical following in [[Sydney]].

===Etymology===
From the late 16th through the 18th century, ''[[wikt:punk|punk]]'' was a common, coarse synonym for ''prostitute''; William Shakespeare used it with that meaning in ''The Merry Wives of Windsor'' (1602) and ''Measure for Measure'' (1623).&lt;ref&gt;Dickson (1982), p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt; The term eventually came to describe &quot;a young male hustler, a gangster, a hoodlum, or a ruffian&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leblanc (1999), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; As [[Legs McNeil]] explains, &quot;On TV, if you watched cop shows, ''[[Kojak]]'', ''[[Baretta]]'', when the cops finally catch the mass murderer, they'd say, 'you dirty Punk.' It was what your teachers would call you. It meant that you were the lowest.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Leblanc (1999), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; The first known use of the phrase ''punk rock'' appeared in the ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' on March 22, 1970, attributed to [[Ed Sanders]], cofounder of New York's anarcho-prankster band [[The Fugs]]. Sanders was quoted describing a solo album of his as &quot;punk rock—redneck sentimentality&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Shapiro (2006), p. 492.&lt;/ref&gt; In the December 1970 issue of ''[[Creem]]'', Lester Bangs, mocking more mainstream rock musicians, ironically referred to Iggy Pop as &quot;that Stooge punk&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bangs, Lester, [http://www.creemmagazine.com/_site/BeatGoesOn/IggyPop/OfPopAndPiesPt001.html &quot;Of Pop and Pies and Fun&quot;], ''Creem'', December 1970. Retrieved on November 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Suicide's [[Alan Vega]] credits this usage with inspiring his duo to bill its gigs as a &quot;punk mass&quot; for the next couple of years.&lt;ref&gt;Nobahkt (2004), p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Patti Smith Copenhagen 1976.jpg|thumb|right|[[Patti Smith]], performing in 1976]]
[[Dave Marsh]] was the first music critic to employ the term ''punk rock'': In the May 1971 issue of ''Creem'', he described [[? and the Mysterians]], one of the most popular 1960s garage rock acts, as giving a &quot;landmark exposition of punk rock&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Shapiro (2006), p. 492. Note that Taylor (2003) misidentifies the year of publication as 1970 (p. 16).&lt;/ref&gt; Later in 1971, in his fanzine ''[[Bomp!|Who Put the Bomp]]'', [[Greg Shaw]] wrote about &quot;what I have chosen to call 'punk rock' bands—white teenage hard rock of '64-66 ([[Standells]], Kingsmen, [[Shadows of Knight]], etc.)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gendron (2002), p. 348 n. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lenny Kaye]] used the term &quot;classic garage-punk,&quot; in reference to a song recorded in 1966 by The Shadows of Knight, in the liner notes of the anthology album ''[[Nuggets: Original Artyfacts from the First Psychedelic Era, 1965-1968|Nuggets]]'', released in 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;letitrock&quot;&gt;Houghton, Mick, &quot;White Punks on Coke&quot;, ''Let It Rock''. December 1975.&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1972, the fanzine ''Flash'' included a &quot;Punk Top Ten&quot; of 1960s albums.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; By that December, the term was in circulation to the extent that ''[[The New Yorker]]''{{'}}s [[Ellen Willis]], contrasting her own tastes with those of ''Flash'' and fellow critic [[Nick Tosches]], wrote, &quot;''Punk-rock'' has become the favored term of endearment.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Willis, Ellen, &quot;Into the Seventies, for Real&quot;, ''The New Yorker'', December 1972; reprinted in Willis's ''Out of the Vinyl Deeps'' (2001, University of Minneapolis Press), pp. 114–16. Italics in original.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1973, Terry Atkinson of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'', reviewing the debut album by a hard rock band, [[Aerosmith]], declared that it &quot;achieves all that punk-rock bands strive for but most miss.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson, Terry, &quot;Hits and Misses&quot;, ''Los Angeles Times'', February 17, 1973, p. B6.&lt;/ref&gt; Three months later, Billy Altman launched the short-lived ''punk magazine''.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 13; [http://www.punkmagazine.com/stuff/morestuff/listening_party7.html &quot;Punk Magazine Listening Party # 7&quot;], ''Punk Magazine'', July 20, 2001. Retrieved on March 4, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1974, ''Los Angeles Times'' critic Robert Hilburn reviewed the second New York Dolls album, [[Too Much Too Soon (album)|''Too Much Too Soon'']]. &quot;I told ya the New York Dolls were the real thing&quot;, he wrote, describing the album as &quot;perhaps the best example of raw, thumb-your-nose-at-the-world, punk rock since [[the Rolling Stones]]' ''[[Exile on Main Street]]''.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hilburn, Robert, &quot;Touch of Stones in Dolls' Album&quot;, ''Los Angeles Times'', May 7, 1974, p. C12.&lt;/ref&gt; Bassist Jeff Jensen of Boston's Real Kids reports of a show that year, &quot;A reviewer for one of the free entertainment magazines of the time caught the act and gave us a great review, calling us a 'punk band.'&amp;nbsp;... [W]e all sort of looked at each other and said, 'What's punk?'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Harvard, Joe, [http://www.rockinboston.com/realkids.htm &quot;Real Kids&quot;], ''Boston Rock Storybook''. Retrieved on November 27, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.rockinboston.com/realkids.htm|date =20071226183408|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1975, ''punk'' was being used to describe acts as diverse as the [[Patti Smith|Patti Smith Group]], the [[Bay City Rollers]], and [[Bruce Springsteen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sav131&quot;&gt;Savage (1991), p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; As the scene at New York's [[CBGB]] club attracted notice, a name was sought for the developing sound. Club owner [[Hilly Kristal]] called the movement &quot;street rock&quot;; John Holmstrom credits ''[[The Aquarian Weekly|Aquarian]]'' magazine with using ''punk'' &quot;to describe what was going on at CBGBs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), pp. 130–131.&lt;/ref&gt; Holmstrom, McNeil, and Ged Dunn's magazine ''[[Punk (magazine)|Punk]]'', which debuted at the end of 1975, was crucial in codifying the term.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;It was pretty obvious that the word was getting very popular&quot;, Holmstrom later remarked. &quot;We figured we'd take the name before anyone else claimed it. We wanted to get rid of the bullshit, strip it down to rock 'n' roll. We wanted the fun and liveliness back.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sav131&quot;/&gt;

==Early history==
===North America===
====New York City====
{{Listen
|filename=Television-Blank Gen (Live).ogg
|title=&quot;Blank Generation&quot;
|description=The original anthem of the punk scene, performed live by [[Television (band)|Television]] in 1974 or 1975, with [[Richard Hell]] on lead vocals. The verse, described by [[Gary Valentine Lachman]] as defying melody, yields to the chorus, &quot;set to a descending pattern reminiscent of [[Peggy Lee]]'s &quot;[[Fever (Little Willie John song)|Fever]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Valentine (2006), p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Tom Verlaine]]'s virtuosic guitar style would lead the band away from what became the typical punk approach.&lt;ref&gt;Valentine (2006), pp. 52–55.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The origins of New York's punk rock scene can be traced back to such sources as late 1960s [[trash culture]] and an early 1970s [[underground rock]] movement centered on the [[Mercer Arts Center]] in [[Greenwich Village]], where the [[New York Dolls]] performed.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), pp. 86–90, 59–60.&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1974, a new scene began to develop around the [[CBGB]] club, also in [[lower Manhattan]]. At its core was [[Television (band)|Television]], described by critic John Walker as &quot;the ultimate garage band with pretensions&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;W&quot;&gt;Walker (1991), p. 662.&lt;/ref&gt; Their influences ranged from the Velvet Underground to the staccato guitar work of [[Dr. Feelgood]]'s [[Wilko Johnson]].&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), pp. 53, 54, 56.&lt;/ref&gt; The band's bassist/singer, [[Richard Hell]], created a look with cropped, ragged hair, ripped T-shirts, and black leather jackets credited as the basis for punk rock visual style.&lt;ref name=&quot;S89&quot;&gt;Savage (1992), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1974, [[Patti Smith]], a member of the Mercer Arts Center crowd and a friend of Hell's, came to CBGB for the first time to see the band perform.&lt;ref&gt;Bockris and Bayley (1999), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; A veteran of independent theater and performance poetry, Smith was developing an intellectual, feminist take on rock 'n' roll. On June 5, she recorded the single &quot;[[Hey Joe]]&quot;/&quot;[[Piss Factory]]&quot;, featuring Television guitarist [[Tom Verlaine]]; released on her own Mer Records label, it heralded the scene's [[do it yourself]] (DIY) ethic and has often been cited as the first punk rock record.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Patti Smith—Biography|publisher=Arista Records|url=http://www.arista.com/psmith/smithbio.html|accessdate=2007-10-23|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071103053048/http://www.arista.com/psmith/smithbio.html |archivedate = November 3, 2007|deadurl=yes}} Strongman (2008), p. 57; Savage (1991), p. 91; Pareles and Romanowski (1983), p. 511; Bockris and Bayley (1999), p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt; By August, Smith and Television were gigging together at another downtown New York club, [[Max's Kansas City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;S89&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:CBGB club facade.jpg|thumb|left|Facade of legendary music club [[CBGB]], New York]]
Out in [[Forest Hills, Queens]], several miles from lower Manhattan, the members of a newly formed band adopted a common surname. Drawing on sources ranging from the Stooges to [[The Beatles]] and [[The Beach Boys]] to [[Herman's Hermits]] and 1960s [[girl group]]s, the [[Ramones]] condensed rock 'n' roll to its primal level: &quot;'1-2-3-4!' bass-player [[Dee Dee Ramone]] shouted at the start of every song, as if the group could barely master the rudiments of rhythm.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), pp. 90–91.&lt;/ref&gt; The band played its first gig at CBGB on August 16, 1974, on the same bill as another new act, Angel and the Snake, soon to be renamed [[Blondie (band)|Blondie]].&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the year, the Ramones had performed seventy-four shows, each about seventeen minutes long.&lt;ref&gt;Bessman (1993), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;When I first saw the Ramones&quot;, critic [[Mary Harron]] later remembered, &quot;I couldn't believe people were doing this. The dumb brattiness.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), pp. 132–133.&lt;/ref&gt; The Dictators, with a similar &quot;playing dumb&quot; concept, were recording their debut album. ''[[The Dictators Go Girl Crazy!]]'' came out in March 1975, mixing absurdist originals such as &quot;Master Race Rock&quot; and loud, straight-faced covers of cheese pop like [[Sonny &amp; Cher]]'s &quot;[[I Got You Babe]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Deming, Mark|title=&quot;''The Dictators Go Girl Crazy!''&quot; (review)|publisher=Allmusic|url={{Allmusic|class=album|id=r61283|pure_url=yes}}|accessdate=2007-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

That spring, Smith and Television shared a two-month-long weekend residency at CBGB that significantly raised the club's profile.&lt;ref&gt;Bockris and Bayley (1999), p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt; The Television sets included Richard Hell's &quot;Blank Generation&quot;, which became the scene's emblematic anthem.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992) claims that &quot;Blank Generation&quot; was written around this time (p. 90). However, the Richard Hell anthology album ''Spurts'' includes a live Television recording of the song that he dates &quot;spring 1974.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, Hell left Television and founded a band featuring a more stripped-down sound, [[The Heartbreakers]], with former New York Dolls [[Johnny Thunders]] and [[Jerry Nolan]]. The pairing of Hell and Thunders, in one critical assessment, &quot;inject[ed] a poetic intelligence into mindless self-destruction&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;RHV&quot;/&gt; A July festival at CBGB featuring over thirty new groups brought the scene its first substantial media coverage.&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), p. 96; Savage (1992), p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Television—with Fred Smith, former Blondie bassist, replacing Hell—recorded a single, &quot;Little Johnny Jewel&quot;, for the tiny Ork label. In the words of John Walker, the record was &quot;a turning point for the whole New York scene&quot; if not quite for the punk rock sound itself—Hell's departure had left the band &quot;significantly reduced in fringe aggression&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;W&quot;/&gt;
{{Listen
|filename=Ramones-Blitzkrieg Bop.ogg
|title=&quot;Blitzkrieg Bop&quot;
|description=The chorus of the [[Ramones]]' first single &quot;is a primer on the punk take on rock rhythm...everyone pumps out the rock rhythmic layer—on a drum, on a single note, on a single chord&quot;, according to scholar Michael Campbell. &quot;This is as pure, and as energetic, as rock rhythm gets.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (2008), p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Other bands were becoming regulars at CBGB, such as [[Mink DeVille]] and [[Talking Heads]], which moved down from Rhode Island. More closely associated with Max's Kansas City were Suicide and the band led by drag queen [[Jayne County|Wayne County]], another Mercer Arts Center alumna. The first album to come out of this downtown scene was released in November 1975: Smith's debut, ''[[Horses (album)|Horses]]'', produced by John Cale for the major [[Arista Records|Arista]] label.&lt;ref&gt;Walsh (2006), p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The inaugural issue of ''Punk'' appeared in December.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt; The new magazine tied together earlier artists such as Velvet Underground lead singer [[Lou Reed]], the Stooges, and the New York Dolls with the editors' favorite band, The Dictators, and the array of new acts centered around CBGB and Max's.&lt;ref&gt;Walsh (2006), pp. 15, 24; for ''Punk'', Wayne County, and punk homosexuality, see McNeil and McCain (2006), pp. 272–275; Savage (1992), p. 139; for CBGB's closing in 2006, see, e.g., Damian Fowler, [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/6054042.stm &quot;Legendary punk club CBGB closes&quot;], [[BBC News]], October 16, 2006. Retrieved on December 11, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; That winter, Pere Ubu came in from Cleveland and played at both spots.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early in 1976, Hell left The Heartbreakers; he soon formed a new group that would become known as [[The Voidoids]], &quot;one of the most harshly uncompromising bands&quot; on the scene.&lt;ref&gt;Pareles and Romanowski (1983), p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt; That April, the Ramones' debut album was released by [[Sire Records]]; the first single was &quot;[[Blitzkrieg Bop]]&quot;, opening with the rally cry &quot;Hey! Ho! Let's go!&quot; According to a later description, &quot;Like all cultural watersheds, ''[[Ramones (album)|Ramones]]'' was embraced by a discerning few and slagged off as a bad joke by the uncomprehending majority.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;trouser3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Ramones|author=Isler, Scott; Robbins, Ira|work=Trouser Press|url=http://trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=ramones|accessdate=2007-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the instigation of Ramones lead singer [[Joey Ramone]], the members of Cleveland's Frankenstein moved east to join the New York scene. Reconstituted as the [[Dead Boys]], they played their first CBGB gig in late July.&lt;ref&gt;Adams (2002), p. 369; McNeil and McCain (2006), pp. 233–234.&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Ork put out an [[Extended play#The 7&quot; EP in punk rock|EP]] recorded by Hell with his new band that included the first released version of &quot;Blank Generation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Richard Hell—Another World/Blank Generation/You Gotta Lose|publisher=Discogs|url=http://www.discogs.com/release/984363|accessdate=2007-10-23}} Buckley (2003), p. 485.&lt;/ref&gt;

The term ''punk'' initially referred to the scene in general, than the sound itself—the early New York punk bands represented a broad variety of influences. Among them, the Ramones, The Heartbreakers, Richard Hell and The Voidoids, and the Dead Boys were establishing a distinct musical style. Even where they diverged most clearly, in lyrical approach—the Ramones' apparent guilelessness at one extreme, Hell's conscious craft at the other—there was an abrasive attitude in common. Their shared attributes of minimalism and speed, however, had not yet come to define punk rock.&lt;ref&gt;Walsh (2006), p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other U.S. cities====
{{Listen
|filename=Crime-Hot Wire My Heart.ogg
|title=&quot;Hot Wire My Heart&quot;
|description=With what music historian [[Clinton Heylin]] described as the &quot;most brutal guitar sound this side of [[The Stooges]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (2007), p. 380. Heylin dates the &quot;Hot Wire My Heart&quot; single to 1976.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Crime (band)|Crime]] self-released the first single by a West Coast punk band, two songs (the B-side was &quot;Baby, You're So Repulsive&quot;) in a style likened to &quot;revved up, distorted [[Chuck Berry]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hannon (2009), p. 18. Hannon suggests &quot;Hot Wire My Heart&quot; came out in January 1977 or shortly thereafter.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In 1975, [[the Suicide Commandos]] formed in Minneapolis. They were one of the first U.S. bands outside of New York to play in the Ramones-style harder-louder-faster mode that would define punk rock.&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (1999), p. 319.&lt;/ref&gt; Detroit's Death self-released one of their 1974 recordings, &quot;Politicians in My Eyes&quot;, in 1976.&lt;ref name=Rubin/&gt; As the punk movement expanded rapidly in the United Kingdom that year, a few bands with similar tastes and attitude appeared around the United States. The first West Coast punk scenes emerged in San Francisco, with the bands [[Crime (band)|Crime]] and [[The Nuns]],&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (1999), p. 426.&lt;/ref&gt; and Seattle, where the Telepaths, Meyce, and [[The Screamers#History|The Tupperwares]] played a groundbreaking show on May 1.&lt;ref&gt;Humphrey, Clark. [http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=2374 &quot;Rock Music—Seattle&quot;]. HistoryLink.org, May 4, 2000. Retrieved on November 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Rock critic [[Richard Meltzer]] cofounded [[VOM (punk rock band)|VOM]] (short for &quot;vomit&quot;) in Los Angeles. In Washington, D.C., raucous roots-rockers The Razz helped along a nascent punk scene featuring Overkill, the [[Slickee Boys]], and The Look. Around the turn of the year, White Boy began giving notoriously crazed performances.&lt;ref&gt;Andersen and Jenkins (2001), pp. 2–13.&lt;/ref&gt; In Boston, the scene at the Rathskeller—affectionately known as the Rat—was also turning toward punk, though the defining sound retained a distinct [[garage rock]] orientation. Among the city's first new acts to be identified with punk rock was [[DMZ (band)|DMZ]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Robbins| first = Ira| title = DMZ | work = Trouser Press | url = http://www.trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=dmz| accessdate =2007-12-01}} {{cite web | last =Donnelly| first = Ben| title = DMZ | work = Dusted | url = http://www.dustedmagazine.com/reviews/143| accessdate =2007-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Bloomington, Indiana, [[The Gizmos]] played in a jokey, raunchy, Dictators-inspired style later referred to as &quot;frat punk&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Lovell| first = Paul| title = Interview with Kenne Gizmo | work = Boston Groupie News | url =http://www.bostongroupienews.com/BGNGizmoInterview.htm|year =1978| accessdate =2007-12-28}} {{cite web | last =Eddy| first = Chuck| title = Eddytor's Dozen | work = Village Voice | url =http://www.killerskiss.com/press/EddytorsDozen.htm|date =2005-07-15| accessdate =2007-12-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like their garage rock predecessors, these local scenes were facilitated by enthusiastic impresarios who operated nightclubs or organized concerts in venues such as schools, garages, or warehouses, advertised via inexpensively printed flyers and fanzines. In some cases, punk's do it yourself ethic reflected an aversion to commercial success, as well as a desire to maintain creative and financial autonomy.&lt;ref&gt;Ross, Alex. &quot;Generation Exit&quot;, ''The New Yorker'', April 25, 1994, pp. 102–104.&lt;/ref&gt; As Joe Harvard, a participant in the Boston scene, describes, it was often a simple necessity—the absence of a local recording industry and well-distributed music magazines left little recourse but DIY.&lt;ref&gt;Harvard, Joe, [http://www.rockinboston.com/boomboom.htm &quot;Willie &quot;Loco&quot; Alexander and the Boom Boom Band&quot;], ''Boston Rock Storybook''. Retrieved November 27, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.rockinboston.com/boomboom.htm|date =20071024024237|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australia===
{{Listen
|filename=Saints-(I'm) Stranded.ogg|title=&quot;(I'm) Stranded&quot; | description=''[[Sounds (magazine)|Sounds]]'' magazine in Britain found &quot;[[(I'm) Stranded (song)|(I'm) Stranded]]&quot; &quot;so bloody incredible&quot; it provided readers the Australian address from which they could mail order it.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jonh Ingham]], quoted in Stafford (2006), p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ed Kuepper]]'s &quot;sheet-metal guitar sets the breakneck tempo&quot;, while lead singer [[Chris Bailey (musician)|Chris Bailey]] &quot;howl[s] into the gale.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stafford (2006), p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Its DIY sound was later described as &quot;crud-encrusted&quot;, praise in the punk milieu.&lt;ref&gt;Raftery, Brian. &quot;The 30 Essential Punk Albums of 1977&quot;. ''Spin''. October 2007, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
At the same time, a similar music-based subculture was beginning to take shape in various parts of Australia. A scene was developing around Radio Birdman and its main performance venue, the Oxford Tavern (later the Oxford Funhouse), located in Sydney's [[Darlinghurst]] suburb. In December 1975, the group won the ''RAM (Rock Australia Magazine)''/Levi's Punk Band Thriller competition.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2003), p. 3; McFarlane (1999), p. 507.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1976, The Saints were hiring Brisbane [[Hall (concept)#Public halls|local halls]] to use as venues, or playing in &quot;Club 76&quot;, their shared house in the inner suburb of [[Brisbane central business district|Petrie Terrace]]. The band soon discovered that musicians were exploring similar paths in other parts of the world. [[Ed Kuepper]], coleader of The Saints, later recalled:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
One thing I remember having had a really depressing effect on me was the first Ramones album. When I heard it [in 1976], I mean it was a great record&amp;nbsp;... but I hated it because I knew we’d been doing this sort of stuff for years. There was even a [[chord progression]] on that album that we used&amp;nbsp;... and I thought, &quot;Fuck. We’re going to be labeled as influenced by the Ramones&quot;, when nothing could have been further from the truth.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABC&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author= Australian Broadcasting Corporation | date= October 2, 2003| title=Misfits and Malcontents | work=abc.net.au| url=http://www.abc.net.au/arts/music/stories/s780315.htm | accessdate= November 1, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On the other side of Australia, in [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]], germinal punk rock act the [[The Manikins|Cheap Nasties]], featuring singer-guitarist [[Kim Salmon]], formed in August.&lt;ref&gt;McFarlane (1999), p. 548.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1976, The Saints became the first punk rock band outside the U.S. to release a recording, the single &quot;[[(I'm) Stranded (song)|(I'm) Stranded]]&quot;. As with Patti Smith's debut, the band self-financed, packaged, and distributed the single.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Beaumont, Lucy | date=2007-08-17 | title=&lt;nowiki&gt;&quot;Great Australian Albums&amp;nbsp;[TV review]&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/nowiki&gt; | work= The Age | url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/tv-reviews/great-australian-albums/2007/08/17/1186857752215.html | accessdate=2007-09-22}} {{cite web | author= Gook, Ben | date=2007-08-16 | title=&lt;nowiki&gt;&quot;Great Australian Albums The Saints – (I'm) Stranded&amp;nbsp;[DVD review]&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/nowiki&gt; | work=Mess+Noise | url=http://www.messandnoise.com/releases/5734 | accessdate=2007-09-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;(I'm) Stranded&quot; had limited impact at home, but the British music press recognized it as a groundbreaking record.&lt;ref&gt;Stafford (2006), pp. 57–76.&lt;/ref&gt; At the insistence of their superiors in the UK, [[EMI]] Australia signed The Saints. Meanwhile, Radio Birdman came out with a self-financed EP, ''[[Burn My Eye]]'', in October.&lt;ref name=&quot;M507&quot;&gt;McFarlane (1999), p. 507.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Trouser Press]]'' critic Ian McCaleb later described the record as the &quot;archetype for the musical explosion that was about to occur&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;McCaleb (1991), p. 529.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
{{Listen
|filename=Anarchy in the UK.ogg
|title=&quot;Anarchy in the U.K.&quot;
|description=With its &quot;inflammatory, venomous lyrics [and] crude energy&quot;, the [[Sex Pistols]]' debut single &quot;established punk's modus operandi&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (2002), p. 1337.&lt;/ref&gt; Producer [[Chris Thomas (record producer)|Chris Thomas]] layered multiple tracks of [[Steve Jones (musician)|Steve Jones]]'s guitar to create a &quot;searing wall of sound&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; while [[John Lydon|Johnny Rotten]] spewed the vocals &quot;as if his teeth had been ground down to points.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Marcus (1989), p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
After a brief period unofficially managing the New York Dolls, Englishman [[Malcolm McLaren]] returned to London in May 1975, inspired by the new scene he had witnessed at CBGB. The [[Kings Road]] clothing store he co-owned, recently renamed [[SEX (boutique)|Sex]], was building a reputation with its outrageous &quot;anti-fashion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rollingstone.com/artists/thesexpistols/biography &quot;The Sex Pistols&quot;], ''Rolling Stone Encyclopedia of Rock 'n' Roll'' (2001). Retrieved on September 11, 2006; Robb (2006), pp. 83–87; Savage (1992), pp. 99–103.&lt;/ref&gt; Among those who frequented the shop were members of a band called The Strand, which McLaren had also been managing. In August, the group was seeking a new lead singer. Another Sex habitué, [[Johnny Rotten]], auditioned for and won the job. Adopting a new name, the group played its first gig as the [[Sex Pistols]] on November 6, 1975, at [[Central Saint Martins College of Art and Design|St. Martin's School of Art]]&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 22; Robb (2006), p. 114; Savage (1992), p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; and soon attracted a small but ardent following.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.punk77.co.uk/groups/bromley.htm The Bromley Contingent]&quot;, punk77.co.uk. Retrieved on December 3, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1976, the band received its first significant press coverage; guitarist [[Steve Jones (musician)|Steve Jones]] declared that the Sex Pistols were not so much into music as they were &quot;chaos&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 151–152. The quote has been incorrectly ascribed to McLaren (e.g., Laing [1985], pp. 97, 127) and Rotten (e.g., [http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A791336 &quot;Punk Music in Britain&quot;], BBC, October 7, 2002), but Savage directly cites the ''[[NME|New Musical Express]]'' issue in which the quote originally appeared. Robb (2006), p. 148, also describes the ''NME'' article in some detail and ascribes the quote to Jones.&lt;/ref&gt; The band often provoked its crowds into near-riots. Rotten announced to one audience, &quot;Bet you don't hate us as much as we hate you!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Friedlander and Miller (2006), p. 252.&lt;/ref&gt; McLaren envisioned the Sex Pistols as central players in a new youth movement, &quot;hard and tough&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Savage (1992), p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt; As described by critic Jon Savage, the band members &quot;embodied an attitude into which McLaren fed a new set of references: late-sixties radical politics, sexual fetish material, pop history,...youth sociology&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bernard Rhodes]], a sometime associate of McLaren's and friend of the Sex Pistols', was similarly aiming to make stars of the band [[London SS]]. Early in 1976, London SS broke up before ever performing publicly, spinning off two new bands: [[The Damned (band)|The Damned]] and [[The Clash]], which was joined by [[Joe Strummer]], former lead singer of The 101'ers.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 124, 171, 172.&lt;/ref&gt; On June 4, 1976, the Sex Pistols played Manchester's [[Free Trade Hall|Lesser Free Trade Hall]] in what came to be regarded as one of the most influential rock shows ever. Among the approximately forty audience members were the two locals who organized the gig—they had formed the [[Buzzcocks]] after seeing the Sex Pistols in February. Others in the small crowd went on to form [[Joy Division]], [[The Fall (band)|The Fall]], and—in the 1980s—[[The Smiths]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | date=2006-06-27| title=Sex Pistols Gig: The Truth | publisher= BBC | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/manchester/content/articles/2006/05/11/110506_sex_pistols_gig_feature.shtml | accessdate=2007-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July, the Ramones crossed the Atlantic for two London shows that helped spark the nascent UK punk scene and affected its musical style—&quot;instantly nearly every band speeded up&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 56; McNeil and McCain (2006), pp. 230–233; Robb (2006), pp. 198, 201. Quote: Robb (2006), p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt; On July 4, they played with the [[The Flamin Groovies|Flamin' Groovies]] and [[The Stranglers]] before a crowd of 2,000 at the [[Roundhouse (venue)|Roundhouse]].&lt;ref&gt;Robb (2006), p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt; That same night, The Clash debuted, opening for the Sex Pistols in [[Sheffield]]. On July 5, members of both bands attended a Ramones club gig.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2003), p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; The following night, The Damned played their first show, as a Pistols opening act in London. In critic [[Kurt Loder]]'s description, the Sex Pistols purveyed a &quot;calculated, arty nihilism, [while] the Clash were unabashed idealists, proponents of a radical left-wing social critique of a sort that reached back at least to&amp;nbsp;... [[Woody Guthrie]] in the 1940s&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=Loder, Kurt | date=2003-03-10| title=The Clash: Ducking Bottles, Asking Questions | publisher= MTV.com | url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1470448/20030310/clash.jhtml | accessdate=2007-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Damned built a reputation as &quot;punk's party boys&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor (2004), p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; This London scene's first [[fanzine]] appeared a week later. Its title, ''[[Sniffin' Glue]]'', derived from a Ramones song. Its subtitle affirmed the connection with what was happening in New York: &quot;+ Other Rock 'n' Roll Habits for Punks!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another Sex Pistols gig in Manchester on July 20, with a reorganized version of the Buzzcocks debuting in support, gave further impetus to the scene there.&lt;ref&gt;Cummins, Kevin, &quot;Closer to the Birth of a Music Legend&quot;, ''The Observer'', August 8, 2007, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; In August, the self-described &quot;First European Punk Rock Festival&quot; was held in Mont de Marsan in the southwest of France. [[Eddie and the Hot Rods]], a London pub rock group, headlined. The Sex Pistols, originally scheduled to play, were dropped by the organizers who said the band had gone &quot;too far&quot; in demanding top billing and certain amenities; The Clash backed out in solidarity. The only band from the new punk movement to appear was The Damned.&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), pp. 131–132; Savage (1992), p. 216. Strongman describes one of the Sex Pistols' objectionable requests as &quot;some entourage accommodation&quot;. Savage says they were dropped from the festival following a violent altercation between [[Sid Vicious]], then part of the Sex Pistols' &quot;entourage&quot;, and journalist [[Nick Kent]] at a Pistols gig. It is possible that the organizers were specifically afraid of Vicious's attendance.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the next several months, many new punk rock bands formed, often directly inspired by the Sex Pistols.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., Marcus (1989), pp. 37, 67.&lt;/ref&gt; In London, women were near the center of the scene—among the initial wave of bands were the female-fronted [[Siouxsie and the Banshees]] and [[X-Ray Spex]] and the all-female [[The Slits]]. There were female bassists [[Gaye Advert]] in [[The Adverts]] and [[Shanne Bradley]] in [[The Nipple Erectors]]. Other groups included [[Subway Sect]], [[Eater]], [[UK Subs|The Subversives]], the aptly named [[London (band)|London]], and [[Chelsea (band)|Chelsea]], which soon spun off [[Generation X (band)|Generation X]]. Farther afield, [[Sham 69]] began practicing in the southeastern town of [[Hersham]]. In [[Durham]], there was [[Penetration (band)|Penetration]], with lead singer [[Pauline Murray]]. On September 20–21, the [[100 Club Punk Festival]] in London featured the four primary British groups (London's big three and the Buzzcocks), as well as Paris's female-fronted [[Stinky Toys]], arguably the first punk rock band from a non-[[Anglosphere|Anglophone]] country. Siouxsie and the Banshees and Subway Sect debuted on the festival's first night; that same evening, Eater debuted in Manchester.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Eater | publisher= Detour Records| url=http://www.detour-records.co.uk/EATER.htm | accessdate=2007-12-29|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071015050705/http://www.detour-records.co.uk/EATER.htm |archivedate = October 15, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the festival's second night, audience member [[Sid Vicious]] was arrested, charged with throwing a glass at The Damned that shattered and destroyed a girl's eye. Press coverage of the incident fueled punk's reputation as a social menace.&lt;ref&gt;Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 111; Gimarc (2005), p. 39; Robb (2006), pp. 217, 224–225.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:AnarchyInTheUKPoster.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Sex Pistols]]' &quot;[[Anarchy in the U.K.]]&quot; poster—a ripped and safety-pinned [[Union Flag]].&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jamie Reid]]'s work had a major influence on punk style and contemporary graphic design in general.&lt;ref name=P245&gt;Pardo (2004), p. 245.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Some new bands, such as London's [[Alternative TV]] and Edinburgh's [[Rezillos]], identified with the scene even as they pursued more experimental music. Others of a comparatively traditional rock 'n' roll bent were also swept up by the movement: [[The Vibrators]], formed as a pub rock–style act in February 1976, soon adopted a punk look and sound.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 221, 247.&lt;/ref&gt; A few even longer-active bands including [[Surrey]] neo-mods [[The Jam]] and pub rockers The Stranglers and [[Cock Sparrer]] also became associated with the punk rock scene. Alongside the musical roots shared with their American counterparts and the calculated confrontationalism of the early Who, the British punks also reflected the influence of [[glam rock]] and related bands such as [[Slade]], [[T. Rex (band)|T.Rex]], and [[Roxy Music]].&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (1993), p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the groups openly acknowledging that influence were [[The Undertones]], from Derry in Northern Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;trouser5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Undertones|author=Robbins, Ira|work=Trouser Press|url=http://trouserpress.com/entry.php?a=undertones|accessdate=2007-10-23|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071103154929/http://theundertones.net/r_200103.htm |archivedate = November 3, 2007|deadurl=yes}} {{cite web|title=Alive and Kicking|author=Reid, Pat|publisher=Undertones.net|work=Rhythm Magazine|month=May | year=2001|url=http://theundertones.net/r_200103.htm|accessdate=2007-10-23|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071103154929/http://theundertones.net/r_200103.htm |archivedate = November 3, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another punk band formed to the south, Dublin's [[The Radiators From Space]].

In October, The Damned became the first UK punk rock band to release a single, the romance-themed &quot;[[New Rose]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Griffin, Jeff, &quot;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/johnpeel/artists/t/thedamned/ The Damned]&quot;, BBC.co.uk. Retrieved on November 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; The Vibrators followed the next month with &quot;We Vibrate&quot; and, backing long-time rocker [[Chris Spedding]], &quot;Pogo Dancing&quot;. The latter was hardly a punk song by any stretch, but it was perhaps the first song ''about'' punk rock. On 26 November, the Sex Pistols' &quot;[[Anarchy in the U.K.]]&quot; came out—with its debut single the band succeeded in its goal of becoming a &quot;national scandal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Anarchy in the U.K. | work= Rolling Stone| url=http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/6595898/anarchy_in_the_uk| date=2004-12-09| accessdate= 2007-10-22|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071012084358/http://www.rollingstone.com/news/story/6595898/anarchy_in_the_uk |archivedate = October 12, 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jamie Reid]]'s &quot;anarchy flag&quot; poster and his other design work for the Sex Pistols helped establish a distinctive [[Punk visual art|punk visual aesthetic]].&lt;ref name=P245/&gt; On December 1, an incident took place that sealed punk rock's notorious reputation: On ''Thames Today'', an early evening London TV show, Sex Pistols guitarist Steve Jones was goaded into a verbal altercation by the host, [[Bill Grundy]]. Jones called Grundy a &quot;dirty fucker&quot; on live television, triggering a media controversy.&lt;ref&gt;Lydon (1995), p. 127; Savage (1992), pp. 257–260; Barkham, Patrick, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,3604,1427563,00.html &quot;Ex-Sex Pistol Wants No Future for Swearing&quot;], ''The Guardian'' (UK), March 1, 2005. Retrieved on December 17, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, the Sex Pistols, The Clash, The Damned, and The Heartbreakers set out on the Anarchy Tour, a series of gigs throughout the UK. Many of the shows were cancelled by venue owners in response to the media outrage following the Grundy confrontation.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 267–275; Lydon (1995), pp. 139–140.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second wave==
By 1977, a second wave of the punk rock movement was breaking in the three countries where it had emerged, as well as in many other places. Bands from the same scenes often sounded very different from each other, reflecting the eclectic state of punk music during the era.&lt;ref name=&quot;R211&quot;&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. 211.&lt;/ref&gt; While punk rock remained largely an underground phenomenon in North America, Australia, and the new spots where it was emerging, in the UK it briefly became a major sensation.&lt;ref&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=explore|id=style/d204|pure_url=yes}} &quot;Punk Rock&quot;], [[Allmusic]]. Retrieved on January 7, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===North America===
{{Listen
|filename=Germs Forming.ogg
|title=&quot;Forming&quot;
|description=As inchoate as its name suggests, [[Germs (band)|The Germs]]' &quot;[[Forming (song)|Forming]]&quot; was the first [[Punk rock in California|L.A. punk]] record&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 437; Mullen, Brendan, and Marc Spitz (May 2001). &quot;Sit on My Face, Stevie Nicks! The Germs, Darby Crash, and the Birth of SoCal Punk&quot;, ''Spin'', p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; and pointed directly toward the [[Hardcore punk|hardcore]] sound that would soon emerge.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2000), p. 391.&lt;/ref&gt; The teenagers' performance has been described both as a signal example of punk incompetence&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (2007), p. 376.&lt;/ref&gt; and as &quot;bringing monotony to new heights&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Claude Bessy (singer)|Claude Bessy]], quoted in Mullen et al. (2002), p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The [[Punk rock in California|California punk scene]] was in full swing by early 1977. In Los Angeles, there were [[The Weirdos]], [[The Zeros (American band)|The Zeros]], [[Black Randy and the Metrosquad]], [[The Germs]], [[X (U.S. band)|X]], [[The Dickies]], [[The Bags]], and the relocated Tupperwares, now dubbed [[The Screamers]].&lt;ref&gt;Spitz and Mullen (2001), passim.&lt;/ref&gt; San Francisco's second wave included [[The Avengers (band)|The Avengers]], [[Negative Trend]], [[The Mutants (San Francisco)|The Mutants]], and The Sleepers.&lt;ref&gt;Stark (2006), passim.&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Dils]], from [[Carlsbad, California|Carlsbad]], moved between the two major cities.&lt;ref&gt;Unterberger (1999), p. 398. For examples of early California punk recordings, see [http://www.breakmyface.com/bands/dangerhouse1.html Dangerhouse Records—Part 1] BreakMyFace.com.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Wipers]] formed in Portland, Oregon. In Seattle, there was The Lewd.&lt;ref name=&quot;KE&quot;&gt;Keithley (2004), pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt; Often sharing gigs with the Seattle punks were bands from across the Canadian border. A major scene developed in Vancouver, spearheaded by the Furies and Victoria's all-female Dee Dee and the Dishrags.&lt;ref name=&quot;KE&quot;/&gt; [[The Skulls (Canadian band)|The Skulls]] spun off into [[D.O.A. (band)|D.O.A.]] and [[Subhumans (Canadian band)|The Subhumans]]. The K-Tels (later known as the [[Young Canadians]]) and [[Pointed Sticks]] were among the area's other leading punk acts.&lt;ref&gt;Keithley (2004), pp. 24, 35, 29–43, 45 et seq.&lt;/ref&gt;

In eastern Canada, the Toronto protopunk band Dishes had laid the groundwork for another sizable scene,&lt;ref&gt;Miller, Earl. [http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-17544041_ITM &quot;File Under Anarchy: A Brief History of Punk Rock's 30-Year Relationship with Toronto's Art Press&quot;]. ''International Contemporary Art'', December 22, 2005. Retrieved on November 25, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; and a September 1976 concert by the touring Ramones had catalyzed the movement. Early Ontario punk bands included [[The Diodes]], [[The Viletones]], [[The Battered Wives]], [[The Demics]], [[Forgotten Rebels]], [[Teenage Head (band)|Teenage Head]], The Poles, and The Ugly. Along with the Dishrags, Toronto's The Curse and B Girls were North America's first all-female punk acts.&lt;ref&gt;Worth, Liz. [http://www.exclaim.ca/articles/research.aspx?csid1=111 &quot;A Canadian Punk Revival&quot;]. ''Exclaim'', June 2007. Retrieved on November 27, 2007; Keithley (2004), pp. 40–41, 87, 89.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1977, the Viletones, Diodes, Curse, and Teenage Head headed down to New York City to play &quot;Canada night&quot; at CBGB.&lt;ref&gt;O'Connor, Alan (2002), &quot;Local Scenes and Dangerous Crossroads: Punk and Theories of Cultural Hybridity&quot;, ''Popular Music'' 21/2, p. 229; Wagner, Vit (October 15, 2006), [http://www.thestar.com/article/97082 &quot;Nazi Dog Set to Snarl Again&quot;], ''Toronto Star''. Retrieved on November 11, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

By mid-1977 in downtown New York, punk rock was already ceding its cutting-edge status to the anarchic sound of [[Teenage Jesus and the Jerks]] and [[Mars (band)|Mars]], spearheads of what became known as [[No Wave]],&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (2007), pp. 491-494.&lt;/ref&gt; although several original punk bands continued to perform and new ones emerged on the scene. [[The Cramps]], whose core members were from Sacramento by way of Akron, had debuted at CBGB in November 1976, opening for the Dead Boys. They were soon playing regularly at Max's Kansas City.&lt;ref&gt;Porter (2007), pp. 48–49; Nobahkt (2004), pp. 77–78.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Misfits (band)|Misfits]] formed in nearby New Jersey. Still developing what would become their signature [[B movie]]–inspired style, later dubbed [[horror punk]], they made their first appearance at CBGB in April 1977.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (2008), pp. 120, 238–239.&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Leave Home]]'', the Ramones' second album, had come out in January.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; The Dead Boys' debut LP, ''[[Young, Loud and Snotty]]'', was released at the end of August.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; October saw two more debut albums from the scene: Richard Hell and The Voidoids' first full-length, ''[[Blank Generation (album)|Blank Generation]]'', and the Heartbreakers' ''[[L.A.M.F.]]''&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; One track on the latter exemplified both the scene's close-knit character and the popularity of heroin within it: &quot;[[Chinese Rocks]]&quot;—the title refers to a strong form of the drug—was written by Dee Dee Ramone and Hell, both users, as were the Heartbreakers' Thunders and Nolan.&lt;ref&gt;McNeil and McCain (2006), pp. 213–14.&lt;/ref&gt; (During the Heartbreakers' 1976 and 1977 tours of Britain, Thunders played a central role in popularizing heroin among the punk crowd there, as well.)&lt;ref&gt;Boot and Salewicz (1997), p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; The Ramones' third album, ''[[Rocket to Russia]]'', appeared in November 1977.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ohio protopunk bands were joined by Cleveland's [[The Pagans]],&lt;ref&gt;Adams (2002), pp. 377–380.&lt;/ref&gt; Akron's Bizarros and [[Rubber City Rebels]], and Kent's [[Human Switchboard]]. Bloomington, Indiana, had MX-80 Sound and Detroit had [[The Sillies]]. [[The Suburbs]] came together in the Twin Cities scene sparked by the Suicide Commandos. [[The Feederz]] formed in Arizona. Atlanta had The Fans. In North Carolina, there was Chapel Hill's H-Bombs and Raleigh's Th' Cigaretz.&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;&gt;Aaron, Charles, [http://www.spin.com/features/magazine/2007/09/0710_spiritof77/ &quot;The Spirit of '77&quot;], ''Spin'', September 20, 2007. Retrieved on November 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The Chicago scene began not with a band but with a group of DJs transforming a gay bar, La Mere Vipere, into what became known as America's first punk dance club. Tutu and the Pirates and Silver Abuse were among the city's first punk bands.&lt;ref&gt;Raymer, Miles, [http://www.chicagoreader.com/features/stories/sharpdarts/071122/ &quot;Chicago Punk, Vol. 1&quot;], ''Chicago Reader'', November 22, 2007; Austen, Jake, [http://www.timeout.com/chicago/articles/music/24456/savage-operation &quot;Savage Operation&quot;], ''Time Out Chicago'', November 22, 2007. Both retrieved December 18, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In Boston, the scene at the Rat was joined by the [[Nervous Eaters]], Thrills, and [[Human Sexual Response (band)|Human Sexual Response]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author=| title = 1977 Club Listings—Boston Punk Scene | publisher=Boston Groupie News | url = http://www.bostongroupienews.com/GigList1977.htm| accessdate =2010-11-15}} {{cite web | author=| title = 1978 Club Listings—Boston Punk Scene | publisher=Boston Groupie News | url =http://www.bostongroupienews.com/GigList.htm| accessdate =2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Washington, D.C., the Controls played their first gig in spring 1977, but the city's second wave really broke the following year with acts such as Urban Verbs, [[Half Japanese]], D'Chumps, Rudements and Shirkers.&lt;ref&gt;Andersen and Jenkins (2001), pp. 11–15, 23–26, 32, 35, 39, 41, 49, 59, 60, 68, 84, 91, 93 et seq.&lt;/ref&gt; By early 1978, the D.C. jazz-fusion group Mind Power had transformed into [[Bad Brains]], one of the first bands to be identified with [[hardcore punk]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Simmons, Todd, [http://www.thevillager.com/villager_181/thewednesdaythemusic.html &quot;The Wednesday the Music Died&quot;], ''The Villager'', October 18–24, 2006. Retrieved on November 27, 2007; Wells (2004), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

===United Kingdom===
{{Listen
|filename=Oh Bondage Up Yours.ogg
|title=&quot;Oh Bondage Up Yours!&quot;
|description=[[X-Ray Spex]]' debut single, an antimaterialistic anthem considered &quot;one of punk rock's defining moments.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dougan (2002), p. 1250.&lt;/ref&gt; As [[Lora Logic]]'s saxophone &quot;serrate[s] right through the ubiquitous guitar-buzzsaw&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (2007), p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; [[Poly Styrene]] sings &quot;in a voice somewhere between that of a wailing baby and that of a banshee&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Leblanc (1999), p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The Sex Pistols' live TV skirmish with Bill Grundy was the signal moment in British punk's transformation into a major media phenomenon, even as some stores refused to stock the records and radio airplay was hard to come by.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 260, 263–267, 277–279; Laing (1985), pp. 35, 37, 38.&lt;/ref&gt; Press coverage of punk misbehavior grew intense: On January 4, 1977, the ''[[Evening News (London)|Evening News]]'' of London ran a front-page story on how the Sex Pistols &quot;vomited and spat their way to an Amsterdam flight&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1977, the first album by a British punk band appeared: ''[[Damned Damned Damned]]'' (by the Damned) reached number thirty-six on the UK chart. The EP ''[[Spiral Scratch (EP)|Spiral Scratch]]'', self-released by Manchester's Buzzcocks, was a benchmark for both the DIY ethic and regionalism in the country's punk movement.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), pp. 296–298; Reynolds (2005), pp. 26–27.&lt;/ref&gt; The Clash's [[The Clash (album)|self-titled debut album]] came out two months later and rose to number twelve; the single &quot;[[White Riot]]&quot; entered the top forty. In May, the Sex Pistols achieved new heights of controversy (and number two on the singles chart) with &quot;[[God Save the Queen (Sex Pistols song)|God Save the Queen]]&quot;. The band had recently acquired a new bassist, Sid Vicious, who was seen as exemplifying the punk persona.&lt;ref&gt;Colegrave and Sullivan (2005), p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt;

Scores of new punk groups formed around the United Kingdom, as far from London as [[Belfast]]'s [[Stiff Little Fingers]] and [[Dunfermline]], Scotland's [[The Skids]]. Though most survived only briefly, perhaps recording a small-label single or two, others set off new trends. [[Crass]], from [[Essex]], merged a vehement, straight-ahead punk rock style with a committed anarchist mission. Sham 69, London's Menace, and the [[Angelic Upstarts]] from [[South Shields]] in the Northeast combined a similarly stripped-down sound with populist lyrics, a style that became known as [[streetpunk]]. These expressly working-class bands contrasted with others in the second wave that presaged the [[post-punk]] phenomenon. Liverpool's first punk group, [[Big in Japan (band)|Big in Japan]], moved in a glam, theatrical direction.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), pp. 365, 378.&lt;/ref&gt; The band didn't survive long, but it spun off several well-known post-punk acts.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1991), p. 298.&lt;/ref&gt; The songs of London's [[Wire (band)|Wire]] were characterized by sophisticated lyrics, minimalist arrangements, and extreme brevity.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), pp. 170–172.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 1977, according to music historian [[Clinton Heylin]], they were &quot;England's arch-exponents of New Musick, and the true heralds of what came next.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heylin (2007), p. 304.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Wirepinkflagcover.jpg|right|thumb|The stark cover design of [[Wire (band)|Wire]]'s debut LP, ''[[Pink Flag]]'', symbolized the evolution of punk style.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), pp. 171–172; Buckley (2003), p. 1179; Strongman (2008), p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Alongside thirteen original songs that would define classic punk rock, The Clash's debut had included a cover of the recent Jamaican [[reggae]] hit &quot;[[Police and Thieves]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Shuker (2002), p. 228; Wells (2004), p. 113; Myers (2006), p. 205; {{cite web | title=Reggae 1977: When The Two 7's Clash | work=Punk77.co.uk | url=http://www.punk77.co.uk/punkhistory/reggae.htm | accessdate= December 3, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Other first wave bands such as The Slits and new entrants to the scene like [[The Ruts]] and [[The Police]] interacted with the reggae and [[ska]] subcultures, incorporating their rhythms and production styles. The punk rock phenomenon helped spark a full-fledged ska revival movement known as [[2 Tone]], centered around bands such as [[The Specials]], [[The Beat (band)|The Beat]], [[Madness (band)|Madness]], and [[The Selecter]].&lt;ref&gt;Hebdige (1987), p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

June 1977 saw the release of another charting punk album: The Vibrators' ''Pure Mania''. In July, the Sex Pistols' third single, &quot;[[Pretty Vacant]]&quot;, reached number six and The Saints had a top-forty hit with &quot;[[This Perfect Day (song)|This Perfect Day]]&quot;. Recently arrived from Australia, the band was now considered insufficiently &quot;cool&quot; to qualify as punk by much of the British media, though they had been playing a similar brand of music for years.&lt;ref&gt;Wells (2004), p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; In August, The Adverts entered the top twenty with &quot;Gary Gilmore's Eyes&quot;. As punk became a broad-based national phenomenon in the summer of 1977, punk musicians and fans were increasingly subject to violent assaults by [[Teddy boy]]s, football [[yobbo]]s, and others. A Ted-aligned band recorded &quot;The Punk Bashing Boogie&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), pp. 182–184.&lt;/ref&gt;

In September, Generation X and The Clash reached the top forty with, respectively, &quot;Your Generation&quot; and &quot;[[Complete Control]]&quot;. X-Ray Spex' &quot;[[Oh Bondage Up Yours!]]&quot; didn't chart, but it became a requisite item for punk fans.&lt;ref&gt;Gaar (2002), p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; In October, the Sex Pistols hit number eight with &quot;[[Holidays in the Sun]]&quot;, followed by the release of their first and only &quot;official&quot; album, ''[[Never Mind the Bollocks, Here's the Sex Pistols]]''. Inspiring yet another round of controversy, it topped the British charts. In December, one of the first books about punk rock was published: ''The Boy Looked at Johnny'', by [[Julie Burchill]] and [[Tony Parsons (British journalist)|Tony Parsons]].&lt;ref&gt;The title echoes a lyric from the title track of Patti Smith's 1975 album ''Horses''&lt;/ref&gt; Declaring the punk rock movement to be already over, it was subtitled ''The Obituary of Rock and Roll''. In January 1978, the Sex Pistols broke up while on American tour.

===Australia===
In February 1977, EMI released The Saints' debut album, ''[[(I'm) Stranded]]'', which the band recorded in two days.&lt;ref&gt;McFaarlane, p. 547.&lt;/ref&gt; The Saints had relocated to Sydney; in April, they and Radio Birdman united for a major gig at [[Paddington, New South Wales#Paddington Town Hall|Paddington Town Hall]].&lt;ref&gt;Cameron, Keith. [http://arts.guardian.co.uk/filmandmusic/story/0,,2129910,00.html &quot;Come the Revolution&quot;]. ''Guardian'', July 20, 2007. Retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Last Words (band)|Last Words]] had also formed in the city. The following month, The Saints relocated again, to Great Britain. In June, Radio Birdman released the album ''[[Radios Appear]]'' on its own Trafalgar label.&lt;ref name=&quot;M507&quot;/&gt;

[[The Victims (Perth band)|The Victims]] became a short-lived leader of the Perth scene, self-releasing the classic &quot;[[Television Addict]]&quot;. They were joined by [[The Scientists]], [[Kim Salmon]]'s successor band to the Cheap Nasties. Among the other bands constituting Australia's second wave were [[Johnny Dole &amp; The Scabs]], the Hellcats, and Psychosurgeons (later known as the Lipstick Killers) in Sydney;&lt;ref&gt;Gardner, Steve. [http://www.divinerites.com/nk_radio.htm &quot;Radio Birdman&quot;]. ''Noise for Heroes'', summer 1990. Retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Leftovers (Australian band)|The Leftovers]], [[The Survivors (Australian band)|The Survivors]], and Razar in Brisbane;&lt;ref&gt;Nichols (2003), pp. 44, 54.&lt;/ref&gt; and La Femme, The Negatives, and The Babeez (later known as The News) in [[Melbourne]].&lt;ref&gt;Strahan, Lucinda. [http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/09/02/1030953434428.html &quot;The Star Who Nicked Australia's Punk Legacy&quot;]. ''The Age'', September 3, 2002. Retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Melbourne's [[art rock]]–influenced [[The Birthday Party (band)|Boys Next Door]] featured singer [[Nick Cave]], who would become one of the world's best-known [[post-punk]] artists.&lt;ref&gt;Erlewine (2002), p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rest of the world===
{{Listen
|filename=Metal Urbain-Panik.ogg
|title=&quot;Panik&quot;
|description=With its &quot;near [[motorik]] beat&amp;nbsp;... gruff guitar riffs, shouted lyrics, and the occasionally swooping synth line&quot;, [[Métal Urbain]]'s debut single is one of the earliest examples anywhere of a style that would become identified with post-punk.&lt;ref&gt;Crumsho, Michael. [http://www.dustedmagazine.com/reviews/1257 &quot;Dusted Reviews: Metal Urbain—''Anarchy in Paris!''&quot;]. ''Dusted Magazine'', February 5, 2004. Retrieved on May 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Meanwhile, punk rock scenes were emerging around the globe. In France, ''les punks'', a Parisian subculture of Lou Reed fans, had already been around for years.&lt;ref&gt;Sabin (1999), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the lead of [[Stinky Toys]], [[Métal Urbain]] played its first concert in December 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Metal Urbain| publisher=Metalorgie | url=http://www.metalorgie.com/punk/groupes.php?id=2513 | accessdate= December 5, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1977, Asphalt Jungle played at the second Mont de Marsan punk festival.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; Stinky Toys' debut single, &quot;Boozy Creed&quot;, came out in September. It was perhaps the first non-English-language punk rock record, though as music historian [[George Gimarc]] notes, the punk enunciation made that distinction somewhat moot.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; The following month, Métal Urbain's first 45, &quot;Panik&quot;, appeared.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (2005), p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; After the release of their minimalist punk debut, &quot;Rien à dire&quot;, [[Marie et les Garçons]] became involved in New York's [[Dance-punk|mutant disco]] scene.&lt;ref&gt;James (2003), pp. 91–93.&lt;/ref&gt; Asphalt Jungle's &quot;Deconnection&quot; and Gasoline's &quot;Killer Man&quot; also came out before the end of the year, and other French punk acts such as [[Oberkampf (band)|Oberkampf]] and Starshooter soon formed.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson (2000), p. 445; OM. [http://www.francomix.com/article-French_Punk_New_Wave_1975_1985-39.html &quot;French Punk New Wave 1975–1985&quot;] ''Francomix'', January 20, 2005. Retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nineteen seventy-seven also saw the debut album from Hamburg's [[Big Balls and the Great White Idiot]], arguably West Germany's first punk band.&lt;ref&gt;Robbins, Ira (October 2007). &quot;The Spirit of '77&quot;, ''Spin'', p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Other early German punk acts included the Fred Banana Combo and Pack. Bands primarily inspired by British punk sparked what became known as the [[Neue Deutsche Welle]] (NDW) movement. Vanguard NDW acts such as the [[Nina Hagen Band]] and S.Y.P.H. featured strident vocals and an emphasis on provocation.&lt;ref name=&quot;B3&quot;&gt;Burns and Van Der Will (1995), p. 313.&lt;/ref&gt; Before turning in a mainstream direction in the 1980s, NDW attracted a politically conscious and diverse audience, including both participants of the left-wing alternative scene and [[White power skinhead|neo-Nazi skinheads]]. These opposing factions were mutually attracted by a view of punk rock as &quot;politically as well as musically...'against the system'.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;B3&quot;/&gt;

[[Andy McCoy|Briard]] jump-started Finnish punk with its 1977 single &quot;I Really Hate Ya&quot;/&quot;I Want Ya Back&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.btinternet.com/~thisispunkrock/ps/fin/1/briardback.htm Briard: &quot;I Really Hate Ya&quot;/&quot;I Want Ya Back&quot; 7&quot; (1977)] &quot;Punk Rock from Finland&quot;/''This Is Punk Rock''.&lt;/ref&gt; other early Finnish punk acts included [[Eppu Normaali]] and singer [[Pelle Miljoona]]. In Yugoslavia, punk rock acts emerged in Croatia ([[Paraf]]), Slovenia ([[Pankrti]]), and Serbia ([[Pekinška patka]]). In Japan, a punk movement developed around bands playing in an art/noise style such as [[Friction (band)|Friction]], and &quot;psych punk&quot; acts like Gaseneta and Kadotani Michio.&lt;ref&gt;Palmer, Robert. [http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D61130F930A1575AC0A961948260&amp;sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=print &quot;The Pop Life&quot;]. ''The New York Times'', September 23, 1987; [http://noise.as/jpsyc &quot;Psychedelia in Japan&quot;]. ''Noise: NZ/Japan''. Both retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In New Zealand, Auckland's Scavengers and [[Suburban Reptiles]] were followed by [[The Enemy (New Zealand band)|The Enemy]] of Dunedin.&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;/&gt; In Brazil, punk first came to prominence in Brasília, the capital, with the bands [[Aborto Elétrico]] and Dado e o Reino Animal.&lt;ref&gt;McGowan and Pessanha (1998), p. 197.&lt;/ref&gt; Punk rock scenes also grew in other countries such as Belgium ([[The Kids (Belgian band)|The Kids]], [[Chainsaw (rock band)|Chainsaw]]),&lt;ref&gt;Killings, Todd. [http://www.victimoftime.com/articles/kids-headline-chaos-tejas-fest/ &quot;The Kids Headline Chaos In Tejas Fest&quot;]. ''Victim of Time'', May 16, 2007. Retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; the Netherlands (The Suzannes, [[The Ex (band)|The Ex]]),&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 581.&lt;/ref&gt; Spain (La Banda Trapera Del Río, Kaka De Luxe),&lt;ref&gt;Schrader, Stuart. [http://www.shit-fi.com/Articles/Spain1978/Spain1978.htm &quot;Drogas, Sexo, Y Un Dictador Muerto: 1978 on Vinyl in Spain&quot;], ''Shit-Fi'', June 4, 2008. Retrieved on July 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Sweden ([[Ebba Grön]], [[KSMB (band)|KSMB]]),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.music.com/person/ebba_gron/1/ &quot;Ebba Grön&quot;] Music.com; [http://www.music.com/group/ksmb/1/ &quot;KSMB&quot;] Music.com. Both retrieved on November 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and Switzerland (Nasal Boys, [[Kleenex (band)|Kleenex]]).&lt;ref&gt;Mumenthaler, Samuel [http://swissmusic.swissinfo.org/eng/swissmusic.html?siteSect=135&amp;sid=1540228&amp;cKey=1041252660000 &quot;Swiss Pop &amp; Rock Anthology from the Beginnings till 1985: WAVE (3)&quot;], ''SwissMusic''; Debored, Guy. [http://www.trakmarx.com/2006_05/13_kleenex.htm &quot;Kleenex&quot;] ''TrakMarx'', October 2006. Both retrieved on November 27, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://swissmusic.swissinfo.org/eng/swissmusic.html?siteSect=135&amp;sid=1540228&amp;cKey=1041252660000|date =20071206073314|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Schism and diversification==
[[File:Flipper 930club.jpg|thumb|right|[[Flipper (band)|Flipper]], performing in 1984]]
By 1979, the [[hardcore punk]] movement was emerging in [[Southern California]]. A rivalry developed between adherents of the new sound and the older punk rock crowd. Hardcore, appealing to a younger, more suburban audience, was perceived by some as anti-intellectual, overly violent, and musically limited. In Los Angeles, the opposing factions were often described as &quot;Hollywood punks&quot; and &quot;beach punks&quot;, referring to Hollywood's central position in the original L.A. punk rock scene and to hardcore's popularity in the shoreline communities of [[South Bay, Los Angeles|South Bay]] and [[Orange County, California|Orange County]].&lt;ref&gt;Blush (2001), p. 18; Reynolds (2006), p. 211; Spitz and Mullen (2001), pp. 217–232; Stark (2006), &quot;Dissolution&quot; (pp. 91–93); see also, [http://flipsidefanzine.com/PortalHome.html &quot;Round-Table Discussion: Hollywood Vanguard vs. Beach Punks!&quot;] (Flipsidezine.com article archive).&lt;/ref&gt;

As hardcore became the dominant punk rock style, many bands of the older California punk rock movement split up, although X went on to mainstream success and [[The Go-Go's]], part of the Hollywood punk scene when they formed in 1978, adopted a pop sound and became major stars.&lt;ref&gt;Spitz and Mullen (2001), pp. 274–279.&lt;/ref&gt; Across North America, many other first and second wave punk bands also dissolved, while younger musicians inspired by the movement explored new variations on punk. Some early punk bands transformed into hardcore acts. A few, most notably the Ramones, Richard Hell and The Voidoids, and Johnny Thunders and The Heartbreakers, continued to pursue the style they had helped create. Crossing the lines between &quot;classic&quot; punk, [[post-punk]], and hardcore, San Francisco's [[Flipper (band)|Flipper]] was founded in 1979 by former members of Negative Trend and The Sleepers.&lt;ref&gt;See also Reynolds (2005), pp. 208–211.&lt;/ref&gt; They became &quot;the reigning kings of American underground rock, for a few years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Dougan, John. [{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p4278|pure_url=yes}} Flipper—Biography]. Allmusic. Retrieved on November 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Radio Birdman broke up in June 1978 while touring the UK,&lt;ref name=&quot;M507&quot;/&gt; where the early unity between [[Bohemianism|bohemian]], middle-class punks (many with art school backgrounds) and [[working class|working-class]] punks had disintegrated.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), pp. 1–2, 17; Laing (1985), p. 109; Savage (1991), p. 396.&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast to North America, more of the bands from the original British punk movement remained active, sustaining extended careers even as their styles evolved and diverged. Meanwhile, the [[Oi!]] and [[anarcho-punk]] movements were emerging. Musically in the same aggressive vein as American hardcore, they addressed different constituencies with overlapping but distinct anti-establishment messages. As described by Dave Laing, &quot;The model for self-proclaimed punk after 1978 derived from the Ramones via the eight-to-the-bar rhythms most characteristic of The Vibrators and Clash.&amp;nbsp;... It became essential to sound one particular way to be recognized as a 'punk band' now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1979, former Sex Pistols bassist Sid Vicious died of a heroin overdose in New York. If the Sex Pistols' breakup the previous year had marked the end of the original UK punk scene and its promise of cultural transformation, for many the death of Vicious signified that it had been doomed from the start.&lt;ref&gt;Savage (1992), p. 530.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Listen
| filename = The Clash - London Calling.ogg
| title = &quot;London Calling&quot;
| description = The [[London Calling (song)|title track]] of [[The Clash]]'s [[London Calling|1979 double album]] was the band's biggest UK hit on first release.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;London Calling&quot; hit number eleven. In 1991, after the band had broken up, a rerelease of &quot;[[Should I Stay or Should I Go]]&quot; reached number one.&lt;/ref&gt; The atmospheric production gives it a &quot;grandeur rarely heard on punk records.&quot;&lt;ref name=R94&gt;Rooksby (2001), p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joe Strummer]] wanted it mixed to &quot;sound like a foggy morning on the River Thames.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gray (2005), p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt; The guitar chords on the second and fourth beats in the verse nod toward [[reggae]].&lt;ref name=R94/&gt;}}
By the turn of the decade, the punk rock movement had split deeply along cultural and musical lines, leaving a variety of derivative scenes and forms. On one side were [[New Wave music|New Wave]] and post-punk artists; some adopted more accessible musical styles and gained broad popularity, while some turned in more experimental, less commercial directions. On the other side, hardcore punk, Oi!, and anarcho-punk bands became closely linked with underground cultures and spun off an array of [[Hybrid genre|subgenres]].&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. xvii.&lt;/ref&gt; Somewhere in between, [[pop punk]] groups created blends like that of the ideal record, as defined by [[Mekons]] cofounder Kevin Lycett: &quot;a cross between [[ABBA|Abba]] and the Sex Pistols&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Wells (2004), p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; A range of other styles emerged, many of them [[Fusion (music)|fusions]] with long-established genres. The Clash album ''[[London Calling]]'', released in December 1979, exemplified the breadth of classic punk's legacy. Combining punk rock with reggae, ska, R&amp;B, and rockabilly, it went on to be acclaimed as one of the best rock records ever.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., Spencer, Neil, and James Brown, [http://music.guardian.co.uk/rock/story/0,,1934098,00.html &quot;Why the Clash Are Still Rock Titans&quot;], ''The Observer'' (UK), October 29, 2006. Retrieved February 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, as observed by Flipper singer Bruce Loose, the relatively restrictive hardcore scenes diminished the variety of music that could once be heard at many punk gigs.&lt;ref name=&quot;R211&quot;/&gt; If early punk, like most rock scenes, was ultimately male-oriented, the hardcore and Oi! scenes were significantly more so, marked in part by the slam dancing and [[moshing]] with which they became identified.&lt;ref&gt;Namaste (2000), p. 87; Laing (1985), pp. 90–91.&lt;/ref&gt;

===New Wave===
{{Details|New Wave music}}
In 1976—first in London, then in the United States—&quot;New Wave&quot; was introduced as a complementary label for the formative scenes and groups also known as &quot;punk&quot;; the two terms were essentially interchangeable.&lt;ref&gt;Gendron (2002), pp. 269–274.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[NME]]'' journalist [[Roy Carr]] is credited with proposing the term's use (adopted from the cinematic [[French New Wave]] of the 1960s) in this context.&lt;ref&gt;Strongman (2008), p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; Over time, &quot;New Wave&quot; acquired a distinct meaning: Bands such as Blondie and Talking Heads from the CBGB scene; [[The Cars]], who emerged from the Rat in Boston; The Go-Go's in Los Angeles; and The Police in London that were broadening their instrumental palette, incorporating dance-oriented rhythms, and working with more polished production were specifically designated &quot;New Wave&quot; and no longer called &quot;punk&quot;. Dave Laing suggests that some punk-identified British acts pursued the New Wave label in order to avoid radio censorship and make themselves more palatable to concert bookers.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;

Bringing elements of punk rock music and fashion into more pop-oriented, less &quot;dangerous&quot; styles, New Wave artists became very popular on both sides of the Atlantic.&lt;ref&gt;Wojcik (1995), p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; New Wave became a catch-all term,&lt;ref&gt;Schild, Matt, [http://www.aversion.com/bands/interviews.cfm?f_id=292 &quot;Stuck in the Future&quot;], Aversion.com, July 11, 2005. Retrieved on January 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; encompassing disparate styles such as [[2 Tone]] ska, the [[mod revival]] inspired by [[The Jam]], the sophisticated pop-rock of [[Elvis Costello]] and [[XTC]], the [[New Romantic]] phenomenon typified by [[Ultravox]], [[synthpop]] groups like [[Tubeway Army]] (which had started out as a straight-ahead punk band) and [[Human League]], and the sui generis subversions of Devo, who had gone &quot;beyond punk before punk even properly existed&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; New Wave became a pop culture sensation with the debut of the cable television network [[MTV]] in 1981, which put many New Wave videos into regular rotation. However, the music was often derided at the time as being silly and disposable.&lt;ref&gt;[{{Allmusic|class=explore|id=essay/|pure_url=yes}} &quot;New Wave&quot;], Allmusic. Retrieved on January 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-punk===
{{Details|Post-punk}}
{{Listen
|filename=The Fall Totally Wired.ogg
|title=&quot;Totally Wired&quot;
|description=[[The Fall (band)|The Fall]]'s 1980 ode to [[amphetamine]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt; With its &quot;taut, twitchy, dissonant music and [[Mark E. Smith]] tunelessly screaming&quot;, writes [[Toby Creswell]], it &quot;mostly resembles the [[Legendary Stardust Cowboy]]'s '[[Legendary Stardust Cowboy#&quot;Paralyzed&quot;|Paralysed]]' for its live feel and sense of abandon...like a New Wave record played badly rather than a punk record played well.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Creswell (2006), p. 395.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
During 1976–77, in the midst of the original UK punk movement, bands emerged such as Manchester's [[Joy Division]], [[The Fall (band)|The Fall]], and [[Magazine (band)|Magazine]], Leeds' [[Gang of Four (band)|Gang of Four]], and London's [[The Raincoats]] that became central post-punk figures. Some bands classified as post-punk, such as [[Throbbing Gristle]] and [[Cabaret Voltaire (band)|Cabaret Voltaire]], had been active well before the punk scene coalesced;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. xxi.&lt;/ref&gt; others, such as The Slits and [[Siouxsie and the Banshees]], transitioned from punk rock into post-punk. A few months after the Sex Pistols' breakup, [[John Lydon]] (no longer &quot;Rotten&quot;) cofounded [[Public Image Ltd]]. [[Lora Logic]], formerly of X-Ray Spex, founded [[Essential Logic]]. [[Killing Joke]] formed in 1979. These bands were often musically experimental, like certain New Wave acts; defining them as &quot;post-punk&quot; was a sound that tended to be less pop and more dark and abrasive—sometimes verging on the [[atonality|atonal]], as with Subway Sect and Wire—and an anti-establishment posture directly related to punk's. Post-punk reflected a range of [[art rock]] influences from [[Captain Beefheart]] to [[David Bowie]] and [[Roxy Music]] to [[Krautrock]] and, once again, the Velvet Underground.&lt;ref name = &quot;Reynolds p4&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Sioux-edinburgh80.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Siouxsie Sioux]], lead singer of [[Siouxsie and the Banshees]], performing in 1980]]
Post-punk brought together a new fraternity of musicians, journalists, managers, and entrepreneurs; the latter, notably [[Geoff Travis]] of [[Rough Trade Records|Rough Trade]] and [[Tony Wilson]] of [[Factory Records|Factory]], helped to develop the production and distribution infrastructure of the [[Indie (music)|indie music]] scene that blossomed in the mid-1980s.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), pp. xxvii, xxix.&lt;/ref&gt; Smoothing the edges of their style in the direction of New Wave, several post-punk bands such as [[New Order]] (descended from Joy Division), [[The Cure]], and [[U2]] crossed over to a mainstream U.S. audience. [[Bauhaus (band)|Bauhaus]] was one of the formative [[gothic rock]] bands. Others, like Gang of Four, The Raincoats and Throbbing Gristle, who had little more than cult followings at the time, are seen in retrospect as significant influences on modern popular culture.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. xxix.&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of U.S. artists were retrospectively defined as post-punk; Television's debut album ''[[Marquee Moon]]'', released in 1977, is frequently cited as a seminal album in the field.&lt;ref&gt;See, e.g., [http://www.rhapsody.com/television/more.html Television] overview by Mike McGuirk, [[Rhapsody (online music service)|Rhapsody]]; [{{Allmusic|class=album|id=r19770|pure_url=yes}} ''Marquee Moon''] review by Stephen Thomas Erlewine, Allmusic; [http://www.popmatters.com/music/reviews/t/television-marquee2003.shtml Television: ''Marquee Moon'' (remastered edition)] review by Hunter Felt, [[PopMatters]]. All retrieved January 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[No Wave]] movement that developed in New York in the late 1970s, with artists such as [[Lydia Lunch]] and [[James Chance]], is often treated as the phenomenon's U.S. parallel.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2003), p. 13; Reynolds (2005), pp. 1–2.&lt;/ref&gt; The later work of Ohio protopunk pioneers Pere Ubu is also commonly described as post-punk.&lt;ref&gt;See. e.g., Reynolds (1999), p. 336; Savage (2002), p. 487.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the most influential American post-punk bands was Boston's [[Mission of Burma]], who brought abrupt rhythmic shifts derived from hardcore into a highly experimental musical context.&lt;ref&gt;Harrington (2002), p. 388.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, Australia's Boys Next Door moved to London and changed their name to [[The Birthday Party (band)|The Birthday Party]], which evolved into [[Nick Cave and the Bad Seeds]]. Led by the [[Primitive Calculators]], Melbourne's [[Little band scene|Little Band scene]] would further explore the possibilities of post-punk.&lt;ref&gt;Potts, Adrian (May 2008), [http://www.viceland.com/int/v15n5/htdocs/big-and-ugly-109.php &quot;Big and Ugly&quot;], ''Vice''. Retrieved on December 11, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Later [[alternative rock]] musicians found diverse inspiration among these post-punk predecessors, as they did among their New Wave contemporaries.&lt;ref&gt;See Thompson (2000), p. viii.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

===Hardcore===
{{Details|Hardcore punk}}
A distinctive style of punk, characterized by superfast, aggressive beats, [[screaming (music)|screaming vocals]], and often politically aware lyrics, began to emerge in 1978 among bands scattered around the United States and Canada. The first major scene of what came to be known as hardcore punk developed in Southern California in 1978–79,&lt;ref&gt;Sabin (1999), p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; initially around such punk bands as The Germs and [[Fear (band)|Fear]].&lt;ref&gt;Blush (2001), pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; The movement soon spread around North America and internationally.&lt;ref name=&quot;andersen&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;hardcore&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vandorston&quot;/&gt; According to author Steven Blush, &quot;Hardcore comes from the bleak suburbs of America. Parents moved their kids out of the cities to these horrible suburbs to save them from the 'reality' of the cities and what they ended up with was this new breed of monster&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;blush&quot;/&gt;
{{Listen
|filename= Pay to Cum.ogg
|title=&quot;Pay to Cum&quot;
|description= [[Bad Brains]]' debut single, &quot;[[Pay to Cum]]&quot; (1980), typifying the band's &quot;high-speed playing, rapid-fire lyrics, dramatic pauses, and performance intensity,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Mahon (2008), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; was pivotal in hardcore's emergence as the American punk standard.&lt;ref&gt;Frere-Jones (2004), p. 34; Parker, Chris, &quot;''Bad Brains''&quot;, ''CMJ New Music Report'', April 3, 2000, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Among the earliest hardcore bands, regarded as having made the first recordings in the style, were Southern California's [[Middle Class (band)|Middle Class]] and [[Black Flag (band)|Black Flag]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hardcore&quot;&gt;Blush (2001), p. 17; Coker, Matt, &quot;Suddenly In Vogue: The Middle Class May Have Been the Most Influential Band You’ve Never Heard Of&quot;, ''OC Weekly'', December 5, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vandorston&quot;&gt;Van Dorston, A.S., [http://www.fastnbulbous.com/punk.htm &quot;A History of Punk&quot;], fastnbulbous.com, January 1990. Retrieved on December 30, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bad Brains]]—all of whom were black, a rarity in punk of any era—launched the [[Washington, D.C. hardcore|D.C. scene]].&lt;ref name=&quot;andersen&quot;&gt;Andersen and Jenkins (2001).&lt;/ref&gt; [[Austin, Texas]]'s [[Big Boys (band)|Big Boys]], San Francisco's [[Dead Kennedys]], and [[Vancouver]]'s [[D.O.A. (band)|D.O.A.]] were among the other initial hardcore groups. They were soon joined by bands such as the [[Minutemen (band)|Minutemen]], [[Descendents]], [[Circle Jerks]], [[Adolescents (band)|Adolescents]], and [[TSOL]] in Southern California; D.C.'s [[Teen Idles]], [[Minor Threat]], and [[State of Alert]]; and Austin's [[MDC (band)|MDC]] and [[The Dicks]]. By 1981, hardcore was the dominant punk rock style not only in California, but much of the rest of North America as well.&lt;ref&gt;Blush (2001), pp. 12–21.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[New York hardcore]] scene grew, including the relocated Bad Brains, New Jersey's [[Misfits (band)|Misfits]] and [[Adrenalin O.D.]], and local acts such as the Nihilistics, [[The Mob (New York band)|The Mob]], [[Reagan Youth]], and [[Agnostic Front]]. [[Beastie Boys]], who would become famous as a hip-hop group, debuted that year as a hardcore band. They were followed by [[The Cro-Mags]], [[Murphy's Law (band)|Murphy's Law]], and [[Leeway (band)|Leeway]].&lt;ref&gt;Andersen and Jenkins (2001), p. 89; Blush (2001), p. 173; {{cite web|author=Diamond, Mike|title=Beastie Boys Biography|publisher=Sing365.com|url=http://www.sing365.com/music/lyric.nsf/Beastie-Boys-Biography/0B982363068317484825682C0009A5AE|accessdate=2008-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 1983, [[Minneapolis hardcore|St. Paul]]'s [[Hüsker Dü]], Willful Neglect and Chicago's [[Naked Raygun]] were taking the hardcore sound in experimental and ultimately more melodic directions. Hardcore would constitute the American punk rock standard throughout the decade.&lt;ref&gt;Leblanc (1999), p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;

The lyrical content of hardcore songs is often critical of commercial culture and middle-class values, as in Dead Kennedys' celebrated &quot;[[Holiday in Cambodia]]&quot; (1980).&lt;ref name=&quot;vandorston&quot; /&gt; [[Straight edge]] bands like Minor Threat, [[Boston hardcore|Boston]]'s [[SS Decontrol]], and [[Reno, Nevada]]'s [[7 Seconds (band)|7 Seconds]] rejected the self-destructive lifestyles of many of their peers, and built a movement based on positivity and abstinence from cigarettes, alcohol, drugs, and casual sex.&lt;ref&gt;Lamacq, Steve, [http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio1/documentaries/060829_straightedge.shtml &quot;x True Til Death x&quot;], BBC Radio 1, 2003. Retrieved on January 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1980s, bands from the American southwest and California such as [[JFA (band)|JFA]], [[Agent Orange (band)|Agent Orange]], and [[The Faction]] helped create a rhythmically distinctive style of hardcore known as [[skate punk]]. Skate punk innovators also pointed in other directions: Big Boys helped establish funkcore, while [[Venice, California]]'s [[Suicidal Tendencies]] had a formative effect on the [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]]–influenced [[crossover thrash]] style. Toward the end of the decade, crossover thrash spawned the [[metalcore]] fusion style and the superfast [[thrashcore]] subgenre developed in multiple locations.&lt;ref&gt;Weinstein (2000), p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Oi!===
{{Details|Oi!}}
{{Listen
|filename=The Exploited Punks not dead.ogg
|title=&quot;Punks Not Dead&quot;
|description=The title track of [[The Exploited]]'s debut, ''[[Punk's Not Dead (The Exploited album)|Punks Not Dead]]'', the top independent UK album of 1981.&lt;ref&gt;Hess (2007), p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt; Defying punk's disappearance from the British mainstream, the song exemplifies the band's sound and that of Oi! groups in general: &quot;harsher, darker, and cruder than their '77 forefathers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lamey and Robbins (1991), p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[Image:StrengthThruOi.jpg|thumb|right|''[[Strength Thru Oi!]]'', with its notorious image of [[British Movement]] activist and felon [[Nicky Crane]]&lt;ref name=Bushell&gt;{{cite web|author= Bushell, Garry|url=http://www.garry-bushell.co.uk/oi/index.asp |title=Oi!—The Truth|publisher=garry-bushell.co.uk|date= |accessdate=2010-12-23 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080731120915/http://www.garry-bushell.co.uk/oi/index.asp |archivedate = 2008-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Following the lead of first-wave British punk bands [[Cock Sparrer]] and [[Sham 69]], in the late 1970s second-wave units like [[Cockney Rejects]], [[Angelic Upstarts]], [[The Exploited]], and [[The 4-Skins]] sought to realign punk rock with a working class, street-level following.&lt;ref&gt;Sabin (1999), p. 216 n. 17; Dalton, Stephen, &quot;Revolution Rock&quot;, Vox, June 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; For that purpose, they believed, the music needed to stay &quot;accessible and unpretentious&quot;, in the words of music historian [[Simon Reynolds]].&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2005), p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; Their style was originally called &quot;real punk&quot; or [[streetpunk]]; [[Sounds (magazine)|''Sounds'']] journalist [[Garry Bushell]] is credited with labelling the genre ''Oi!'' in 1980. The name is partly derived from the Cockney Rejects' habit of shouting &quot;Oi! Oi! Oi!&quot; before each song, instead of the time-honored &quot;1,2,3,4!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Robb (2006), p. 469.&lt;/ref&gt; Oi! bands' lyrics sought to reflect the harsh realities of living in [[Margaret Thatcher]]'s Britain in the late 1970s and early 1980s.&lt;ref name = Robb511&gt;Robb (2006), p. 511.&lt;/ref&gt; A subgroup of Oi! bands dubbed &quot;[[punk pathetique]]&quot;—including [[Splodgenessabounds]], [[Peter and the Test Tube Babies]], and [[Toy Dolls]]—had a more humorous and absurdist bent.

The Oi! movement was fueled by a sense that many participants in the early punk rock scene were, in the words of [[The Business (band)|The Business]] guitarist Steve Kent, &quot;trendy university people using long words, trying to be artistic&amp;nbsp;... and losing touch&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in Robb (2006), pp. 469–470.&lt;/ref&gt; According to Bushell, &quot;Punk was meant to be of the voice of [[the dole]] queue, and in reality most of them were not. But Oi was the reality of the punk mythology. In the places where [these bands] came from, it was harder and more aggressive and it produced just as much quality music.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Robb (2006), p. 470.&lt;/ref&gt; Lester Bangs described Oi! as &quot;politicized football chants for unemployed louts&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bangs, Lester. &quot;If Oi Were a Carpenter&quot;. ''Village Voice''. April 27, 1982.&lt;/ref&gt; One song in particular, The Exploited's &quot;Punks Not Dead&quot;, spoke to an international constituency. It was adopted as an anthem by the groups of disaffected Mexican urban youth known in the 1980s as ''bandas''; one ''banda'' named itself PND, after the song's initials.&lt;ref&gt;Berthier (2004), p. 246.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although most Oi! bands in the initial wave were apolitical or [[left wing]], many of them began to attract a [[white power skinhead]] following. Racist skinheads sometimes disrupted Oi! concerts by shouting fascist slogans and starting fights, but some Oi! bands were reluctant to endorse criticism of their fans from what they perceived as the &quot;middle-class establishment&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;tzvi&quot;&gt;Fleischer, Tzvi. [http://www.aijac.org.au/review/2000/258/sounds.html &quot;Sounds of Hate&quot;]. Australia/Israel &amp; Jewish Affairs Council (AIJAC), August 2000. Retrieved on January 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In the popular imagination, the movement thus became linked to the [[far right]].&lt;ref&gt;Robb (2006), pp. 469, 512.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Strength Thru Oi!]]'', an album compiled by Bushell and released in May 1981, stirred controversy, especially when it was revealed that the belligerent figure on the cover was a [[Neo-Nazism|neo-Nazi]] jailed for racist violence (Bushell claimed ignorance).&lt;ref name=Bushell/&gt; On July 3, a concert at Hamborough Tavern in [[Southall]] featuring The Business, The 4-Skins, and The Last Resort was firebombed by local Asian youths who believed that the event was a neo-Nazi gathering.&lt;ref&gt;Gimarc (1997), p. 175; Laing (1985), p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the Southall riot, press coverage increasingly associated Oi! with the extreme right, and the movement soon began to lose momentum.&lt;ref name = Robb511/&gt;
{{clear}}

===Anarcho-punk===
{{Details|Anarcho-punk}}
[[Image:Crass3.jpg|thumb|left|[[Crass]] were the originators of anarcho-punk.&lt;ref name=&quot;W35&quot;&gt;Wells (2004), p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; Their all-black militaristic dress became a staple of the genre.]]
Anarcho-punk developed alongside the Oi! and American hardcore movements. With a primitive, stripped-down musical style and ranting, shouted vocals, British bands such as [[Crass]]—the scene's &quot;moral leaders&quot;—[[Subhumans (U.K. band)|Subhumans]], [[Flux of Pink Indians]], [[Conflict (band)|Conflict]], [[Poison Girls]], and [[The Apostles]] attempted to transform the punk rock scene into a full-blown anarchist movement. Revolution and military action were primary lyrical topics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Scaruffi, Piero | year=2005| title=Anarchists | work=The History of Rock Music: 1976–1989| url=http://www.scaruffi.com/history/cpt42.html | accessdate=2009-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
As with straight edge, anarcho-punk is based on a set of principles, including prohibitions on wearing leather and the promotion of a vegetarian or vegan diet.&lt;ref name=&quot;W35&quot;/&gt;

The movement spun off several subgenres of a similar political bent. [[Discharge (band)|Discharge]], founded back in 1977, established [[D-beat]] in the early 1980s. Other groups in the movement, led by [[Amebix]] and [[Antisect]], developed the extreme style known as [[crust punk]]. Several of these bands rooted in anarcho-punk such as [[The Varukers]], Discharge, and Amebix, along with former Oi! groups such as [[The Exploited]] and bands from father afield like Birmingham's [[Charged GBH]], became the leading figures in the [[UK 82]] hardcore movement. The anarcho-punk scene also spawned bands such as [[Napalm Death]], [[Carcass (band)|Carcass]], and [[Extreme Noise Terror]] that in the mid-1980s defined [[grindcore]], incorporating extremely fast tempos and [[death metal]]–style guitarwork.&lt;ref&gt;Purcell (2003), pp. 56–57.&lt;/ref&gt; Led by Dead Kennedys, a U.S. anarcho-punk scene developed around such bands as Austin's [[MDC (band)|MDC]] and Southern California's Another Destructive System.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sosrecords.us/label/taxonomy/term/1 News Items]. SOS Records, March 12, 2007; [http://www.animamundi.org/links.html Links] Anima Mundi. Both retrieved on November 25, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://sosrecords.us/label/taxonomy/term/1|date =20071218223342|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

===Pop punk===
{{Details|Pop punk}}
With their love of the [[Beach Boys]] and late 1960s [[bubblegum pop]], the Ramones paved the way to what became known as pop punk.&lt;ref&gt;Besssman (1993), p. 16; Carson (1979), p. 114; Simpson (2003), p. 72; McNeil (1997), p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1970s, UK bands such as [[Buzzcocks]] and [[The Undertones]] combined [[Pop music|pop]]-style tunes and lyrical themes with punk's speed and chaotic edge.&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, Ryan. [http://punkmusic.about.com/od/artistprofiles/p/buzzcocksfinal.htm &quot;The Buzzcocks, Founders of Pop Punk&quot;]. About.com. Retrieved on December 16, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1980s, some of the leading bands in Southern California's hardcore punk rock scene emphasized a more melodic approach than was typical of their peers. According to music journalist [[Ben Myers]], [[Bad Religion]] &quot;layered their pissed off, politicized sound with the smoothest of harmonies&quot;; [[Descendents (band)|Descendents]] &quot;wrote almost surfy, Beach Boys–inspired songs about girls and food and being young(ish)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Myers (2006), p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Epitaph Records]], founded by [[Brett Gurewitz]] of Bad Religion, was the base for many future pop punk bands, including [[NOFX]], with their [[third wave ska]]–influenced [[skate punk]] rhythms. Bands that fused punk with light-hearted pop melodies, such as [[The Queers]] and [[Screeching Weasel]], began appearing around the country, in turn influencing bands like [[Green Day]] and [[The Offspring]], who brought pop punk wide popularity and major record sales. Bands such as [[The Vandals]] and [[Guttermouth]] developed a style blending pop melodies with humorous and offensive lyrics. The mainstream pop punk of latter-day bands such as [[Blink-182]] is criticized by many punk rock devotees; in critic Christine Di Bella's words, &quot;It's punk taken to its most accessible point, a point where it barely reflects its lineage at all, except in the three-chord song structures.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Di Bella, Christine. [http://www.popmatters.com/music/concerts/b/blink-182-020611.shtml &quot;Blink 182 + Green Day&quot;]. PopMatters.com. June 11, 2002. Retrieved on February 4, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other fusions and directions===
From 1977 on, punk rock crossed lines with many other popular music genres. Los Angeles punk rock bands laid the groundwork for a wide variety of styles: [[The Flesh Eaters (band)|The Flesh Eaters]] with [[deathrock]]; [[The Plugz]] with [[Chicano punk]]; and [[Gun Club]] with [[punk blues]]. [[The Meteors]], from [[South London]], and [[The Cramps]], who moved from New York to Los Angeles in 1980, were innovators in the [[psychobilly]] fusion style.&lt;ref&gt;Porter (2007), p. 86.&lt;/ref&gt; Milwaukee's [[Violent Femmes]] jumpstarted the American [[folk punk]] scene, while [[The Pogues]] did the same on the other side of the Atlantic, influencing many [[Celtic punk]] bands.&lt;ref&gt;Hendrickson, Tad. [http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=101915358 &quot;Irish Pub-Rock: Boozy Punk Energy, Celtic Style&quot;]. NPR Music, March 16, 2009. Retrieved on November 12, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The Mekons, from [[Leeds]], combined their punk rock ethos with country music, greatly influencing the later [[alternative country]] movement. In the United States, varieties of [[cowpunk]] played by bands such as [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]]'s [[Jason &amp; the Scorchers]], Arizona's [[Meat Puppets]], and Southern California's [[Social Distortion]] had a similar effect.

Other bands pointed punk rock toward future rock styles or its own foundations. New York's [[Suicide (band)|Suicide]], L.A.'s [[The Screamers]] and [[Nervous Gender]], Australia's [[JAB]], and Germany's [[Deutsch-Amerikanische Freundschaft|DAF]] were pioneers of [[synthpunk]]. [[The Ex (band)|The Ex]], from the Netherlands, were in the [[art punk]] vanguard.&lt;ref&gt;Hopper, Justin. [http://www.pittsburghcitypaper.ws/gyrobase/Content?oid=oid%3A20305 &quot;The Ex: 27 Years of Dutch Art-punk&quot;]. ''Pittsburgh City Paper'', December 7, 2006. Retrieved on November 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Chicago's [[Big Black]] was a major influence on [[noise rock]], [[math rock]], and [[industrial rock]]. [[Garage punk]] bands from all over—such as [[Medway]]'s [[Thee Mighty Caesars]], Chicago's [[Dwarves (band)|Dwarves]], and [[Adelaide]]'s [[Exploding White Mice]]—pursued a version of punk rock that was close to its roots in 1960s garage rock. Seattle's [[Mudhoney (band)|Mudhoney]], one of the central bands in the development of [[grunge]], has been described as &quot;garage punk&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Simpson (2003), p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and later developments==
===Alternative rock===
{{main|Alternative rock}}
The underground punk rock movement inspired countless bands that either evolved from a punk rock sound or brought its outsider spirit to very different kinds of music. The original punk explosion also had a long-term effect on the music industry, spurring the growth of the independent sector.&lt;ref&gt;Laing (1985), pp. 118, 128.&lt;/ref&gt; During the early 1980s, British bands like New Order and The Cure that straddled the lines of post-punk and New Wave developed both new musical styles and a distinctive industrial niche. Though commercially successful over an extended period, they maintained an underground-style, [[subculture|subcultural]] identity.&lt;ref&gt;Goodlad and Bibby (2007), p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States, bands such as Hüsker Dü and their Minneapolis protégés [[The Replacements (band)|The Replacements]] bridged the gap between punk rock genres like hardcore and the more melodic, explorative realm of what was then called &quot;[[college rock]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Azerrad (2001), passim; for relationship of Hüsker Dü and The Replacements, see pp. 205–206.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Sonic1991b.jpg|thumb|right|[[Sonic Youth]]'s [[Kim Gordon]] in 1991, walking on her bass guitar]]
A 1985 ''[[Rolling Stone]]'' feature on the Minneapolis scene and innovative California hardcore acts such as Black Flag and Minutemen declared, &quot;Primal punk is passé. The best of the American punk rockers have moved on. They have learned how to play their instruments. They have discovered melody, guitar solos and lyrics that are more than shouted political slogans. Some of them have even discovered the [[Grateful Dead]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thirdav.com/zinestuff/rs452.html Goldberg, Michael, &quot;Punk Lives&quot;], ''Rolling Stone'', July 18 – August 1, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the 1980s, these bands, who had largely eclipsed their punk rock forebears in popularity, were classified broadly as [[alternative rock]]. Alternative rock encompasses a diverse set of styles—including [[gothic rock]] and [[grunge]], among others—unified by their debt to punk rock and their origins outside of the musical mainstream.&lt;ref name=Erlewine&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/23/showbiz/music/nirvana-nevermind/index.html |title=American Alternative Rock/Post-Punk|author=Erlewine, Stephen Thomas|publisher=Allmusic |date=|accessdate=2011-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As American alternative bands like [[Sonic Youth]], which had grown out of the No Wave scene, and Boston's [[Pixies]] started to gain larger audiences, major labels sought to capitalize on the underground market that had been sustained by hardcore punk for years.&lt;ref&gt;Friedlander and Miller (2006), pp. 256, 278.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1991, [[Nirvana (band)|Nirvana]] emerged from Washington State's grunge scene, achieving huge commercial success with its second album, ''[[Nevermind]]''. The band's members cited punk rock as a key influence on their style.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thebiographychannel.co.uk/biography_story/691:1872/1/Kurt_Donald_Cobain.htm &quot;Kurt Donald Cobain&quot;], Biography Channel. Retrieved on November 19, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Punk is musical freedom&quot;, wrote singer [[Kurt Cobain]]. &quot;It’s saying, doing, and playing what you want.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in St. Thomas (2004), p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt; Nirvana's success opened the door to mainstream popularity for a wide range of other &quot;left-of-the-dial&quot; acts, such as [[Pearl Jam]] and [[Red Hot Chili Peppers]], and fueled the alternative rock boom of the early and mid-1990s.&lt;ref name=Erlewine/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/23/showbiz/music/nirvana-nevermind/index.html |title='Nevermind,' Never Again?|author=Morgenstein, Mark |publisher=CNN |date= 2011-09-23|accessdate=2011-10-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Emo===
[[File:JimmyEatWorldnewcastle.jpg|thumb|left|[[Jimmy Eat World]], performing in 2008]]
{{Details|Emo}}
In its original, mid-1980s incarnation, emo was a less musically restrictive style of punk developed by participants in the Washington, D.C. area hardcore scene. It was originally referred to as &quot;emocore&quot;, an abbreviation of &quot;emotive hardcore&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Greenwald (2003), pp. 9–12.&lt;/ref&gt; Notable early emo bands included [[Rites of Spring]], [[Embrace (American band)|Embrace]], [[The Hated]], and [[One Last Wish]]. The term derived from the tendency of some of these bands' members to become strongly emotional during performances. [[Fugazi]], formed out of the dissolution of Embrace, inspired a second, much broader based wave of emo bands beginning in the mid-1990s. Groups like San Diego's [[Antioch Arrow]] generated new, more intense subgenres like [[screamo]], while others developed a more melodic style closer to indie rock. Bands such as Seattle's [[Sunny Day Real Estate]] and [[Mesa, Arizona]]'s [[Jimmy Eat World]] broke out of the underground, attracting national attention.
{{clear}}

===Queercore and riot grrrl===
[[Image:Carrie Brownstein.jpg|thumb|upright|right|[[Carrie Brownstein]], performing with [[Sleater-Kinney]] in 2005]]
{{Details3|[[Queercore]] and [[Riot Grrrl]]}}
In the 1990s, the queercore movement developed around a number of punk bands with gay, lesbian, or bisexual members such as [[God Is My Co-Pilot (band)|God Is My Co-Pilot]], [[Pansy Division]], [[Team Dresch]], and [[Sister George]]. Inspired by openly gay punk musicians of an earlier generation such as [[Jayne County]], [[Phranc]], [[Darby Crash]] and [[Randy Turner]], and bands like [[Nervous Gender]], [[The Screamers]], and [[Coil (band)|Coil]], queercore embraces a variety of punk and other alternative music styles. Queercore lyrics often treat the themes of prejudice, [[sexual identity]], [[gender identity]], and individual rights. The movement has continued into the 21st century, supported by festivals such as [[Queeruption]].&lt;ref&gt;Spencer (2005), pp. 279–289.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1991, a concert of female-led bands at the International Pop Underground Convention in [[Olympia, Washington]], heralded the emerging riot grrrl phenomenon. Billed as &quot;Love Rock Revolution Girl Style Now&quot;, the concert's lineup included [[Bikini Kill]], [[Bratmobile]], [[Heavens to Betsy]], [[L7 (band)|L7]], and [[Mecca Normal]].&lt;ref&gt;Raha (2005), p. 154.&lt;/ref&gt; The riot grrrl movement foregrounded feminist concerns and progressive politics in general; the DIY ethic and fanzines were also central elements of the scene.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson (2005), pp. 261–62.&lt;/ref&gt; Singer-guitarists [[Corin Tucker]] of Heavens to Betsy and [[Carrie Brownstein]] of [[Excuse 17]], bands active in both the queercore and riot grrrl scenes, cofounded the celebrated indie/punk band [[Sleater-Kinney]] in 1994. Bikini Kill's lead singer, [[Kathleen Hanna]], the iconic figure of riot grrrl, moved on to form the [[art punk]] group [[Le Tigre]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;McGowen, Brice. [http://www.unc.edu/glbtsa/lambda/articles/28/3/letigre.htm &quot;Eye of the Tiger&quot;]. ''Lamda'', February/March 2005. Retrieved on November 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Revival==
{{Listen
|filename=Longview.ogg
|title=&quot;Longview&quot;
|description=The [[Green Day]] single that led the way in pop punk's rise to mainstream success.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis (2008), p. 269; Diehl (2007), p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt; Playing with the quiet-loud dynamic associated with grunge,&lt;ref&gt;Catucci (2004b), p. 347.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[Longview (song)|Longview]]&quot; features a conversational-sounding vocal from [[Billie Joe Armstrong]] in the verse and a [[Lounge music|lounge jazz]]–style bass line &quot;wired to detonate.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Spitz (2006), p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Normal_180914_1994-XX-XX_-_Green_Day_Live_.jpg|thumb|upright|right|[[Billie Joe Armstrong]] of [[Green Day]], performing in 1994]]
By the 1990s, punk rock was sufficiently ingrained in Western culture that punk trappings were often used to market highly commercial bands as &quot;rebels&quot;. Marketers capitalized on the style and hipness of punk rock to such an extent that a 1993 ad campaign for an automobile, the [[Subaru Impreza]], claimed that the car was &quot;like punk rock&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Klein (2000), p. 300.&lt;/ref&gt; Along with Nirvana, many of the leading alternative rock artists of the early 1990s acknowledged the influence of earlier punk rock acts. With Nirvana's success, the major record companies once again saw punk bands as potentially profitable.&lt;ref&gt;Zuel, Bernard (April 2, 2004), [http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/04/01/1080544618404.html &quot;Searching for Nirvana&quot;], ''Sydney Morning Herald''. Retrieved on September 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, California's [[Green Day]] and [[Bad Religion]] were both signed to major labels. The next year, Green Day put out ''[[Dookie]],'' which became a huge hit, selling nine million albums in the United States in just over two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;RIAAD&quot;&gt;See, e.g., [http://www.riaa.com/goldandplatinumdata.php?table=SEARCH Searchable Database—Gold and Platinum], RIAA. Retrieved on December 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Bad Religion's ''[[Stranger Than Fiction (Bad Religion album)|Stranger Than Fiction]]'' was certified [[RIAA certification|gold]].&lt;ref&gt;Fucoco, Christina (November 1, 2000), [http://www.livedaily.com/news/2098.html &quot;Punk Rock Politics Keep Trailing Bad Religion&quot;], liveDaily. Retrieved on September 1, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Other California punk bands on the independent label [[Epitaph Records|Epitaph]], run by Bad Religion guitarist [[Brett Gurewitz]], also began achieving mainstream popularity. In 1994, Epitaph released ''[[Let's Go (Rancid album)|Let's Go]]'' by [[Rancid (band)|Rancid]], ''[[Punk in Drublic]]'' by [[NOFX]], and ''[[Smash (The Offspring album)|Smash]]'' by [[The Offspring]], each eventually certified gold or better. That June, Green Day's &quot;[[Longview (song)|Longview]]&quot; reached number one on ''Billboard''{{'}}s [[Alternative Songs|Modern Rock Tracks]] chart and became a top forty airplay hit, arguably the first ever American punk song to do so; just one month later, The Offspring's &quot;[[Come Out and Play (song)|Come Out and Play]]&quot; followed suit. [[MTV]] and radio stations such as Los Angeles' [[KROQ-FM]] played a major role in these bands' crossover success, though NOFX refused to let MTV air its videos.&lt;ref name=&quot;punkbroke&quot;&gt;Gold, Jonathan. &quot;The Year Punk Broke.” ''SPIN''. November 1994.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Smash'' went on to sell over twelve million copies worldwide, becoming the best-selling independent-label album of all time.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Sound Sampler&quot;, ''Billboard'', January 27, 2007, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the lead of Boston's [[The Mighty Mighty Bosstones|Mighty Mighty Bosstones]] and two California bands, [[Berkeley, California|Berkeley]]'s [[Operation Ivy (band)|Operation Ivy]] and [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]]'s [[Sublime (band)|Sublime]], [[ska punk]] and ska-core became widely popular in the mid-1990s. By 1996, genre acts such as [[Reel Big Fish]] and [[Less Than Jake]] were being signed to major labels. The original [[2 Tone]] bands had emerged amid punk rock's second wave, but their music was much closer to its Jamaican roots—&quot;ska at [[78 rpm record|78 rpm]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hebdige (1987), p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; Ska punk bands in the [[third wave of ska]] created a true musical fusion between the genres. ''[[...And Out Come the Wolves]]'', the 1995 album by Rancid—which had evolved out of Operation Ivy—became the first record in this ska revival to be certified gold;&lt;ref&gt;''...And Out Come the Wolves'' was certified gold in January 1996. ''Let's Go'', Rancid's previous album, received gold certification in July 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; Sublime's [[Sublime (album)|self-titled 1996 album]] was certified platinum early in 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;RIAAD&quot;/&gt;

In Australia, two popular groups, skatecore band [[Frenzal Rhomb]] and pop punk act [[Bodyjar]], also established followings in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Eliezer, Christie. &quot;Trying to Take Over the World&quot;. ''Billboard''. September 28, 1996, p. 58; Eliezer, Christie. &quot;The Year in Australia: Parallel Worlds and Artistic Angles&quot;. ''Billboard''. December 27, 1997–January 3, 1998, p. YE-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Green Day and ''Dookie'''s enormous sales paved the way for a host of bankable North American pop punk bands in the following decade.&lt;ref&gt;D'Angelo, Joe, [http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1491001/20040915/green_day.jhtml &quot;How Green Day's ''Dookie'' Fertilized A Punk-Rock Revival&quot;], MTV.com, September 15, 2004. Retrieved on December 3, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; With punk rock's renewed visibility came concerns among some in the punk community that the music was being co-opted by the mainstream.&lt;ref name=&quot;punkbroke&quot; /&gt; They argued that by signing to major labels and appearing on MTV, punk bands like Green Day were buying into a system that punk was created to challenge.&lt;ref&gt;Myers (2006), p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt; Such controversies have been part of the punk culture since 1977, when The Clash was widely accused of &quot;selling out&quot; for signing with [[Columbia Records|CBS Records]].&lt;ref&gt;Knowles (2003), p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt; The Vans [[Warped Tour]] and the mall chain store [[Hot Topic]] brought punk even further into the U.S. mainstream.&lt;ref&gt;Diehl (2007), pp. 2, 145, 227.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In the mainstream==
{{Listen
|filename=All The Small Things.ogg
|title=&quot;All the Small Things&quot;
|description=The first U.S. punk-identified single to reach the top ten, built on a &quot;schoolyard-chant verse and na-na-na chorus&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Catucci (2004a), p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;[[All the Small Things]]&quot; exemplifies [[Blink-182]]'s &quot;formulaic hits&quot;, in [[Marc Spitz]]'s description: &quot;adenoidal verse, minimally pulsing bass, explosive three-chord guitar riffs tempered by sweet harmony&quot;.&lt;ref name=Spitz144&gt;Spitz (2006), p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;}}
By early 1998, the punk revival had commercially stalled,&lt;ref&gt;Gross (2004), p. 677.&lt;/ref&gt; but not for long. That November, The Offspring's ''[[Americana (The Offspring album)|Americana]]'' on the major [[Columbia Records|Columbia]] label debuted at number two on the album chart. A bootleg MP3 of its first single, &quot;[[Pretty Fly (For a White Guy)]]&quot;, made it on to the Internet and was downloaded a record 22 million times—illegally.&lt;ref&gt;Diehl (2003), p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, ''[[Enema of the State]]'', the first major-label release by pop punk band [[Blink-182]], reached the top ten and sold four million copies in under twelve months.&lt;ref name=&quot;RIAAD&quot;/&gt; In January 2000, the album's second single, &quot;[[All the Small Things]]&quot;, hit the sixth spot on the [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard'' Hot 100]]. While they were viewed as Green Day &quot;acolytes&quot;,&lt;ref name=Spitz144/&gt; critics also found [[teen pop]] acts like [[Britney Spears]], the [[Backstreet Boys]], and [['N Sync]] suitable points of comparison for Blink-182's sound and market niche.&lt;ref&gt;Blasengame, Bart. &quot;Live: Blink-182&quot;. ''Spin''. September 2000, p. 80; Pappademas, Alex. &quot;Blink-182: ''The Mark, Tom and Travis Show: The Enema Strikes Back''&quot;. ''Spin''. December 2000, p. 222.&lt;/ref&gt; The band's ''[[Take Off Your Pants and Jacket]]'' (2001) and ''[[Blink-182 (album)|Blink-182]]'' (2003) respectively rose to numbers one and three on the album chart. In November 2003, ''[[The New Yorker]]'' described how the &quot;giddily puerile&quot; act had &quot;become massively popular with the mainstream audience, a demographic formerly considered untouchable by punk-rock purists.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Goings On About Town: Nightlife&quot;. ''The New Yorker''. November 10, 2003, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Other new North American pop punk bands, though often critically dismissed, also achieved major sales in the first decade of the 2000s. Ontario's [[Sum 41]] reached the Canadian top ten with its 2001 debut album, ''[[All Killer No Filler]]'', which eventually went platinum in the United States. The record included the number one U.S. Alternative hit &quot;[[Fat Lip]]&quot;, which incorporated verses of what one critic called &quot;brat rap.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sinagra (2004), p. 791.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Good Charlotte]], from Maryland, had three successive top ten albums beginning with ''[[The Young and the Hopeless]]'' in 2002. Florida's [[Yellowcard]], which had been together since 1997, had its first hit in 2003 with its major-label debut, ''[[Ocean Avenue (song)|Ocean Avenue]]''. [[Simple Plan]], from Montréal, climbed to number three in the United States with ''[[Still Not Getting Any...]]'' in 2004. 
[[File:Antiflag1 cropped.jpg|thumb|right|[[Justin Sane]] and [[Chris Barker (bassist)|Chris#2]] of [[Anti-Flag]], performing in 2006]]
That same year, Green Day, which had gone through a relatively fallow period commercially, took ''[[American Idiot]]'' to number one on both the U.S. and UK charts; the band matched the feat five years later with ''[[21st Century Breakdown]]''. [[Jimmy Eat World]], taking emo in a radio-ready pop punk direction,&lt;ref&gt;Pierce, Carrie, [http://media.www.thebatt.com/media/storage/paper657/news/2004/11/24/Aggielife/Jimmy.Eat.World-814898.shtml &quot;Jimmy Eat World: ''Futures''—Interscope Records&quot;], ''The Battalion'', November 24, 2004. Retrieved on December 2, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; had top ten albums in 2004 and 2007. In a similar style, [[Fall Out Boy]] hit number one with 2007's ''[[Infinity on High]]''. The wave of commercial success was broad-based: [[AFI (band)|AFI]], with roots in hardcore and skate punk, had great success with 2003's ''[[Sing the Sorrow]]'' and topped the U.S. chart with ''[[Decemberunderground]]'' in 2006. Two years later, The Offspring had its fifth top ten album with ''[[Rise and Fall, Rage and Grace]]'' and its third [[Alternative Songs|Modern Rock/Alternative Songs]] chart-topper with &quot;[[You're Gonna Go Far, Kid]]&quot;. Starting in 2003, [[Alkaline Trio]] had four consecutive top twenty-five albums, peaking at number eleven with 2010's ''[[This Addiction]]''.

The effect of commercialization on the music became an increasingly contentious issue. As observed by scholar Ross Haenfler, many punk fans &quot;'despise corporate punk rock', typified by bands such as Sum&amp;nbsp;41 and Blink&amp;nbsp;182&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Haenfler (2006), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, politicized and independent-label punk continued to thrive in the United States. Since 1993, [[Anti-Flag]] had been putting progressive politics at the center of its music. The administration of [[George W. Bush]] provided them and similarly minded acts eight years of conservative government to excoriate. [[Rise Against]] was the most successful of these groups, registering top ten records in 2006 with ''[[The Sufferer &amp; the Witness]]'' and two years later with ''[[Appeal to Reason]]''. Leftist folk punk band [[Against Me!]]'s ''[[New Wave (Against Me! album)|New Wave]]'' was named best album of 2007 by ''[[Spin (magazine)|Spin]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Kandell, Steve| date= January 1, 2008| title=Album of the Year: Against Me!| work=Spin| url=http://www.spin.com/articles/album-year-against-me | accessdate=January 31, 2011}} {{cite web | author= Wood, Mikael| date= August 1, 2007| title=Against Me!: 'New Wave'| work=Spin| url=http://www.spin.com/reviews/against-me-new-wave-sire| accessdate=January 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the realm of the U.S. independents, Celtic punk attracted a substantial audience. [[Flogging Molly]] and [[Dropkick Murphys]] each had top twenty albums on small labels, with the former's ''[[Float (Flogging Molly album)|Float]]'' landing at number four in 2008. 

Elsewhere around the world, &quot;[[psychobilly|punkabilly]]&quot; band [[The Living End]] became major stars in Australia with their [[The Living End (The Living End album)|self-titled 1998 debut]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author= Aiese, Eric| date= February 27, 2001 | title=Living End 'Rolls On' with Aussie Punkabilly Sound| work=Billboard|publisher=AllBusiness.com| url=http://www.allbusiness.com/retail-trade/miscellaneous-retail-retail-stores-not/4614949-1.html| accessdate=February 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group topped the national album chart again with ''[[State of Emergency (The Living End album)|State of Emergency]]'' in 2006 and ''[[White Noise (The Living End album)|White Noise]]'' in 2008.

==See also==
{{wikinews|Vivien Goldman: An interview with the Punk Professor}}
* [[List of punk rock bands, 0–K|List of punk bands]]
* [[Punk rock subgenres]]
* [[Timeline of punk rock]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=25em}}

==Sources==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* Adams, Deanna R. (2002). ''Rock 'n' Roll and the Cleveland Connection'' (Kent, Ohio: Kent State University Press). ISBN 0-87358-691-4
* Andersen, Mark, and Mark Jenkins (2001). ''Dance of Days: Two Decades of Punk in the Nation's Capital'' (New York: Soft Skull Press). ISBN 1-887128-49-2
* Anderson, Mark (2002). &quot;Zunō keisatsu&quot;, in ''Encyclopedia of Contemporary Japanese Culture'', ed. Sandra Buckley (London and New York: Routledge), p.&amp;nbsp;588. ISBN 0-415-14344-6
* [[Michael Azerrad|Azerrad, Michael]] (2001). ''[[Our Band Could Be Your Life]]'' (New York: Little, Brown). ISBN 0-316-78753-1
* Bennett, Andy (2001). &quot;'Plug in and Play!': UK Indie Guitar Culture&quot;, in ''Guitar Cultures'', ed. Andy Bennett and Kevin Dawe (Oxford and New York: Berg), pp.&amp;nbsp;45–62. ISBN 1-85973-434-0
* Berthier, Héctor Castillo (2001). &quot;My Generation: Rock and ''la Banda{{'}}''s Forced Survival Opposite the Mexican State&quot;, in ''Rockin' las Américas: The Global Politics of Rock in Latin/o America'', ed. Deborah Pacini Hernandez (Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press), pp.&amp;nbsp;241–60. ISBN 0-8229-4226-7
* Bessman, Jim (1993). ''Ramones: An American Band'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN 0-312-09369-1
* Blush, Steven (2001). ''American Hardcore: A Tribal History'' (Los Angeles: Feral House). ISBN 0-92291-571-7
* Bockris, Victor, and Roberta Bayley (1999). ''Patti Smith: An Unauthorized Biography'' (New York: Simon &amp; Schuster). ISBN 0-684-82363-2
* Boot, Adrian, and Chris Salewicz (1997). ''Punk: The Illustrated History of a Music Revolution'' (New York: Penguin). ISBN 0-1402-6098-6
* Buckley, Peter, ed. (2003). ''The Rough Guide to Rock'' (London: Rough Guides). ISBN 1-84353-105-4
* [[Julie Burchill|Burchill, Julie]], and [[Tony Parsons (British journalist)|Tony Parsons]] (1978). ''The Boy Looked at Johnny: The Obituary of Rock and Roll'' (London: Pluto Press). ISBN 0-86104-030-9
* Burns, Rob, and Wilfried Van Der Will (1995). &quot;The Federal Republic 1968 to 1990: From the Industrial Society to the Culture Society&quot;, in ''German Cultural Studies: An Introduction'', ed. Burns (Oxford and New York: Oxford University Press), pp. 257–324. ISBN 0-19-871503-X
* Campbell, Michael, with James Brody (2008). ''Rock and Roll: An Introduction'', 2d ed. (Belmont, Calif.: Thomson Schirmer). ISBN 0-534-64295-0
* Carson, Tom (1979). &quot;''Rocket to Russia''&quot;, in ''Stranded: Rock and Roll for a Desert Island'', ed. Greil Marcus (New York: Knopf). ISBN 0-394-73827-6
* Catucci, Nick (2004a). &quot;Blink-182&quot;, in ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Nathan Brackett (New York: Fireside/Simon &amp; Schuster), p.&amp;nbsp;85. ISBN 0-7432-0169-8
* Catucci, Nick (2004b). &quot;Green Day&quot;, in ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Nathan Brackett (New York: Fireside/Simon &amp; Schuster), pp.&amp;nbsp;347–48. ISBN 0-7432-0169-8
* Colegrave, Stephen, and Chris Sullivan (2005). ''Punk: The Definitive Record of a Revolution'' (New York: Thunder's Mouth). ISBN 1-56025-769-5
* Creswell, Toby (2006). ''1001 Songs: The Great Songs of All Time and the Artists, Stories and Secrets Behind Them'' (New York: Thunder's Mouth). ISBN 1-56025-915-9
* Dickson, Paul (1982). ''Words: A Connoisseur's Collection of Old and New, Weird and Wonderful, Useful and Outlandish Words'' (New York: Delacorte). ISBN 0-4400-9606-5
* Diehl, Matt (2007). ''My So-Called Punk: Green Day, Fall Out Boy, the Distillers, Bad Religion—How Neo-Punk Stage-Dived into the Mainstream'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN 0-312-33781-7
* Dougan, John (2002). &quot;X-Ray Spex&quot;, in ''All Music Guide to Rock: The Definitive Guide to Rock, Pop, and Soul'', 3d ed., ed. Vladimir Bogdanov, Chris Woodstra, and Stephen Thomas Erlewine (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-879-30653-X
* Ellis, Iain (2008). ''Rebels Wit Attitude: Subversive Rock Humorists'' (Berkeley, Calif: Soft Skull/Counterpoint). ISBN 1-59376-206-2.
* Erlewine, Stephen Thomas (2002). &quot;The Birthday Party&quot;, in ''All Music Guide to Rock: The Definitive Guide to Rock, Pop, and Soul'', 3d ed., ed. Vladimir Bogdanov, Chris Woodstra, and Stephen Thomas Erlewine (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-879-30653-X
* Fletcher, Tony (2000). ''Moon: The Life and Death of a Rock Legend'' (New York: HarperCollins). ISBN 0-380-78827-6
* [[Sasha Frere-Jones|Frere-Jones, Sasha]] (2004). &quot;Bad Brains&quot;, in ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Nathan Brackett (New York: Fireside/Simon &amp; Schuster), pp.&amp;nbsp;34–35. ISBN 0-7432-0169-8
* Friedlander, Paul, with Peter Miller (2006). ''Rock and Roll: A Social History'', 2d ed. (Boulder, Co.: Westview). ISBN 0-8133-4306-2
* Friskics-Warren, Bill (2005). ''I'll Take You There: Pop Music And the Urge for Transcendence'' (New York and London: Continuum International). ISBN 0-8264-1700-0
* Gaar, Gillian G. (2002). ''She's a Rebel: The History of Women in Rock &amp; Roll'', 2d ed. (New York: Seal). ISBN 1-58005-078-6
* Gendron, Bernard (2002). ''Between Montmartre and the Mudd Club: Popular Music and the Avant-Garde'' (Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press). ISBN 0-226-28735-1
* Gimarc, George (1997). ''Post Punk Diary, 1980–1982'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN 0-312-16968-X
* Gimarc, George (2005). ''Punk Diary: The Ultimate Trainspotter's Guide to Underground Rock, 1970–1982'' (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-87930-848-6
* Glasper, Ian (2004). ''Burning Britain—The History of UK Punk 1980–1984'' (London: Cherry Red Books). ISBN 1-901447-24-3
* Goodlad, Lauren M. E., and Michael Bibby (2007). &quot;Introduction&quot;, in ''Goth: Undead Subculture'', ed. Goodlad and Bibby (Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press). ISBN 0-8223-3921-8
* Gray, Marcus (2005 [1995]). ''The Clash: Return of the Last Gang in Town'', 5th rev. ed. (London: Helter Skelter). ISBN 1-905-13910-1
* [[Andy Greenwald|Greenwald, Andy]] (2003). ''[[Nothing Feels Good: Punk Rock, Teenagers, and Emo]]'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN=0-312-30863-9
* Gross, Joe (2004). &quot;Rancid&quot;, in ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Nathan Brackett (New York: Fireside/Simon &amp; Schuster), p.&amp;nbsp;677. ISBN 0-7432-0169-8
* Haenfler, Ross (2006). ''Straight Edge: Hardcore Punk, Clean-Living Youth, and Social Change'' (New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press). ISBN 0-8135-3852-1
* Hannon, Sharon M. (2009). ''Punks: A Guide to an American Subculture'' (Santa Barbara, Calif.: Greenwood). ISBN 978-0-313-36456-3
* Harrington, Joe S. (2002). ''Sonic Cool: The Life &amp; Death of Rock 'n' Roll'' (Milwaukee: Hal Leonard). ISBN 0-634-02861-8
* Harris, John (2004). ''Britpop!: Cool Britannia and the Spectacular Demise of English Rock'' (Cambridge, Mass.: Da Capo) ISBN 0-306-81367-X
* [[Dick Hebdige|Hebdige, Dick]] (1987). ''Cut 'n' Mix: Culture, Identity and Caribbean Music'' (London: Routledge). ISBN 0-415-05875-9
* Hess, Mickey (2007). ''Is Hip Hop Dead?: The Past, Present, and Future of America's Most Wanted Music'' (Westport, Conn.: Praeger). ISBN 0-275-99461-9
* Heylin, Clinton (1993). ''From the Velvets to the Voidoids: The Birth of American Punk Rock'' (Chicago: A Cappella Books). ISBN 1-55652-573-3
* Heylin, Clinton (2007). ''Babylon's Burning: From Punk to Grunge'' (New York: Canongate). ISBN 1-84195-879-4
* Home, Stewart (1996). ''Cranked Up Really High: Genre Theory and Punk Rock'' (Hove, UK: Codex). ISBN 1-899598-01-4
* Jackson, Buzzy (2005). ''A Bad Woman Feeling Good: Blues and the Women Who Sing Them'' (New York: W. W. Norton). ISBN 0-393-05936-7
* James, Martin (2003). ''French Connections: From Discothèque to Discovery'' (London: Sanctuary). ISBN 1-86074-449-4
* [[Joey Keithley|Keithley, Joe]] (2004). ''I, Shithead: A Life in Punk'' (Vancouver: Arsenal Pulp Press). ISBN 1-55152-148-2
* [[Naomi Klein|Klein, Naomi]] (2000). ''[[No Logo|No LOGO: Taking Aim at the Brand Bullies]]'' (New York: Picador). ISBN 0-312-20343-8
* Knowles, Chris (2003). ''Clash City Showdown'' (Otsego, Mich.: PageFree). ISBN 1-58961-138-1
* Laing, Dave (1985). ''One Chord Wonders: Power and Meaning in Punk Rock'' (Milton Keynes and Philadelphia: Open University Press). ISBN 0-335-15065-9
* Lamey, Charles P., and Ira Robbins (1991). &quot;Exploited&quot;, in ''The Trouser Press Record Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Ira Robbins (New York: Collier), pp.&amp;nbsp;230–31. ISBN 0-02-036361-3
* Leblanc, Lauraine (1999). ''Pretty in Punk: Girls' Gender Resistance in a Boys' Subculture'' (New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press). ISBN 0-8135-2651-5
* [[John Lydon|Lydon, John]] (1995). ''Rotten: No Irish, No Blacks, No Dogs'' (New York: Picador). ISBN 0-312-11883-X
* Mahon, Maureen (2008). &quot;African Americans and Rock 'n' Roll&quot;, in ''African Americans and Popular Culture, Volume 3: Music and Popular Art'', ed. Todd Boyd (Westport, Conn.: Praeger), pp.&amp;nbsp;31–60. ISBN 978-0-275-98925-5
* [[Greil Marcus|Marcus, Greil]], ed. (1979). ''Stranded: Rock and Roll for a Desert Island'' (New York: Knopf). ISBN 0-394-73827-6
* Marcus, Greil (1989). ''Lipstick Traces: A Secret History of the Twentieth Century'' (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press). ISBN 0-674-53581-2
* McCaleb, Ian (1991). &quot;Radio Birdman&quot;, in ''The Trouser Press Record Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Ira Robbins (New York: Collier), pp.&amp;nbsp;529–30. ISBN 0-02-036361-3
* McFarlane, Ian (1999). ''The Encyclopedia of Australian Rock and Pop'' (St Leonards, Aus.: Allen &amp; Unwin). ISBN 1-86508-072-1
* McGowan, Chris, and Ricardo Pessanha (1998). ''The Brazilian Sound: Samba, Bossa Nova, and the Popular Music of Brazil'' (Philadelphia: Temple University Press). ISBN 1-56639-545-3
* [[Legs McNeil|McNeil, Legs]], and Gillian McCain (2006 [1997]). ''Please Kill Me: The Uncensored Oral History of Punk'' (New York: Grove). ISBN 0-8021-4264-8
* Miles, Barry, Grant Scott, and Johnny Morgan (2005). ''The Greatest Album Covers of All Time'' (London: Collins &amp; Brown). ISBN 1-84340-301-3
* [[Ben Myers|Myers, Ben]] (2006). ''Green Day: American Idiots &amp; the New Punk Explosion'' (New York: Disinformation). ISBN 1-932857-32-X
* [[Brendan Mullen|Mullen, Brendan]], with Don Bolles and [[Adam Parfrey]] (2002). ''Lexicon Devil: The Fast Times and Short Life of Darby Crash and the Germs'' (Los Angeles: Feral House). ISBN 0-922915-70-9
* Nichols, David (2003). ''The Go-Betweens'' (Portland, Ore.: Verse Chorus Press). ISBN 1-891241-16-8
* Nobahkt, David (2004). ''Suicide: No Compromise'' (London: SAF). ISBN 0-946719-71-3
* O'Hara, Craig (1999). ''The Philosophy of Punk: More Than Noise'' (San Francisco and Edinburgh: AK Press). ISBN 1-873176-16-3
* Palmer, Robert (1992). &quot;The Church of the Sonic Guitar&quot;, in ''Present Tense: Rock &amp; Roll and Culture'', ed. Anthony DeCurtis (Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press), pp.&amp;nbsp;13–38. ISBN 0-8223-1265-4
* Pardo, Alona (2004). &quot;Jamie Reid&quot;, in ''Communicate: Independent British Graphic Design Since the Sixties'', ed. Rick Poyner (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press), p.&amp;nbsp;245. ISBN 0-300-10684-X
* Pareles, Jon, and Patricia Romanowski (eds.) (1983). ''The Rolling Stone Encyclopedia of Rock &amp; Roll'' (New York: Rolling Stone Press/Summit Books). ISBN 0-671-44071-3
* Porter, Dick (2007). ''The Cramps: A Short History of Rock 'n' Roll Psychosis'' (London: Plexus). ISBN 0-85965-398-6
* Purcell, Natalie J. (2003). ''Death Metal Music: The Passion and Politics of a Subculture'' (Jefferson, N.C., and London: McFarland). ISBN 0-7864-1585-1
* Raha, Maria (2005). ''Cinderella's Big Score: Women of the Punk and Indie Underground'' (Emeryville, Calif.: Seal). ISBN 1-58005-116-2
* Reed, John (2005). ''Paul Weller: My Ever Changing Moods'' (London et al.: Omnibus Press). ISBN 1-84449-491-8
* Reynolds, Simon (1999). ''Generation Ecstasy: Into the World of Techno and Rave Culture'' (London: Routledge). ISBN 0-415-92373-5
* Reynolds, Simon (2005). ''Rip It Up and Start Again: Post Punk 1978–1984'' (London and New York: Faber and Faber). ISBN 0-571-21569-6
* [[John Robb (musician)|Robb, John]] (2006). ''Punk Rock: An Oral History'' (London: Elbury Press). ISBN 0-09-190511-7
* Rodel, Angela (2004). &quot;Extreme Noise Terror: Punk Rock and the Aesthetics of Badness&quot;, in ''Bad Music: The Music We Love to Hate'', ed. Christopher Washburne and Maiken Derno (New York: Routledge), pp.&amp;nbsp;235–56. ISBN 0-415-94365-5
* Rooksby, Rikky (2001). ''Inside Classic Rock Tracks'' (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-87930-654-8
* Sabin, Roger (1999). ''Punk Rock, So What? The Cultural Legacy of Punk'' (London: Routledge). ISBN 0-415-17030-3.
* [[Jon Savage|Savage, Jon]] (1991). ''England's Dreaming: The Sex Pistols and Punk Rock'' (London: Faber and Faber). ISBN 0-312-28822-0
* Savage, Jon (1992). ''England's Dreaming: Anarchy, Sex Pistols, Punk Rock, and Beyond'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN 0-312-08774-8
* Shapiro, Fred R. (2006). ''Yale Book of Quotations'' (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press). ISBN 0-300-10798-6
* Schmidt, Axel, and Klaus Neumann-Braun (2004). ''Die Welt der Gothics: Spielräume düster konnotierter Tranzendenz'' (Wiesbaden: VS Verlag). ISBN 3-531-14353-0
* Shuker, Roy (2002). ''Popular Music: The Key Concepts'' (London: Routledge). ISBN 0-415-28425-2
* Simpson, Paul (2003). ''The Rough Guide to Cult Pop: The Songs, the Artists, the Genres, the Dubious Fashions'' (London: Rough Guides). ISBN 1-84353-229-8
* Sinagra, Laura (2004). &quot;Sum 41&quot;, in ''The New Rolling Stone Album Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Nathan Brackett (New York: Fireside/Simon &amp; Schuster), pp.&amp;nbsp;791–92. ISBN 0-7432-0169-8
* Smith, Kerry L. (2008). ''Encyclopedia of Indie Rock'' (Westport, Conn.: Greenwood). ISBN 978-0-313-34119-9
* Spencer, Amy (2005). ''DIY: The Rise of Lo-Fi Culture'' (London: Marion Boyars). ISBN 0-7145-3105-7
* Spitz, Marc (2006). ''Nobody Likes You: Inside the Turbulent Life, Times, and Music of Green Day'' (New York: Hyperion). ISBN 1-4013-0274-2
* Spitz, Marc, and Brendan Mullen (2001). ''We Got the Neutron Bomb: The Untold Story of L.A. Punk'' (New York: Three Rivers Press). ISBN 0-609-80774-9
* Stafford, Andrew (2006). ''Pig City: From the Saints to Savage Garden'', 2d rev. ed. (Brisbane: University of Queensland Press). ISBN 0-7022-3561-X
* Stark, James (2006). ''Punk '77: An Inside Look at the San Francisco Rock N' Roll Scene'', 3d ed. (San Francisco: RE/Search Publications). ISBN 1-889307-14-9
* Strohm, John (2004). &quot;Women Guitarists: Gender Issues in Alternative Rock&quot;, in ''The Electric Guitar: A History of an American Icon'', ed. A. J. Millard (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press), pp.&amp;nbsp;181–200. ISBN 0-8018-7862-4
* Strongman, Phil (2008). ''Pretty Vacant: A History of UK Punk'' (Chicago: Chicago Review Press). ISBN 1-55652-752-7
* St. Thomas, Kurt, with Troy Smith (2002). ''Nirvana: The Chosen Rejects'' (New York: St. Martin's). ISBN 0-312-20663-1
* Taylor, Steven (2003). ''False Prophet: Field Notes from the Punk Underground'' (Middletown, Conn.: Wesleyan University Press). ISBN 0-8195-6668-3
* Taylor, Steve (2004). ''The A to X of Alternative Music'' (London and New York: Continuum). ISBN 0-8264-8217-1
* Thompson, Dave (2000). ''Alternative Rock'' (San Francisco: Miller Freeman). ISBN 0-87930-607-6
* Unterberger, Richie (1998). ''Unknown Legends of Rock 'n' Roll: Psychedelic Unknowns, Mad Geniuses, Punk Pioneers, Lo-Fi Mavericks &amp; More'' (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-87930-534-7
* Unterberger, Richie (1999). ''Music USA: The Rough Guide'' (London: Rough Guides). ISBN 1-85828-421-X
* Unterberger, Richie (2002). &quot;British Punk&quot;, in ''All Music Guide to Rock: The Definitive Guide to Rock, Pop, and Soul'', 3d ed., ed. Vladimir Bogdanov, Chris Woodstra, and Stephen Thomas Erlewine (San Francisco: Backbeat). ISBN 0-879-30653-X
* [[Gary Valentine Lachman|Valentine, Gary]] (2006). ''New York Rocker: My Life in the Blank Generation with Blondie, Iggy Pop, and Others, 1974–1981'' (New York: Thunder's Mouth). ISBN 1-56025-944-2
* Walker, John (1991). &quot;Television&quot;, in ''The Trouser Press Record Guide'', 4th ed., ed. Ira Robbins (New York: Collier), p.&amp;nbsp;662. ISBN 0-02-036361-3
* Walsh, Gavin (2006). ''Punk on 45; Revolutions on Vinyl, 1976–79'' (London: Plexus). ISBN 0-85965-370-6
* Weinstein, Deena (2000). ''Heavy Metal: The Music and Its Culture'' (New York: Da Capo). ISBN 0-306-80970-2
* [[Steven Wells|Wells, Steven]] (2004). ''Punk: Loud, Young &amp; Snotty: The Story Behind the Songs'' (New York and London: Thunder's Mouth). ISBN 1-56025-573-0
* Wilkerson, Mark Ian (2006). ''Amazing Journey: The Life of Pete Townshend'' (Louisville: Bad News Press). ISBN 1-4116-7700-5
* Wojcik, Daniel (1995). ''Punk and Neo-Tribal Body Art'' (Jackson: University Press of Mississippi). ISBN 0-87805-735-8
* Wojcik, Daniel (1997). ''The End of the World as We Know It: Faith, Fatalism, and Apocalypse in America'' (New York: New York University Press). ISBN 0-8147-9283-9
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Punk|Punk rock}}
* [http://www.nyu.edu/library/bobst/research/fales/downtown.html Fales Library of NYU Downtown Collection] archival collection with the personal papers of NYC punk figures.
* [http://www.fastnbulbous.com/punk.htm A History of Punk] 1990 essay by rock critic A.S. Van Dorston
* [http://www.punk77.co.uk/ Punk 77] history of early UK punk
* [http://www.villagevoice.com/2005-10-18/specials/we-have-to-deal-with-it-punk-england-report/ &quot;We Have to Deal With It: Punk England Report&quot;], by [[Robert Christgau]], ''[[Village Voice]]'', January 9, 1978
{{punk}}
{{rock}}

{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Punk Rock}}
[[Category:Culture of New York City]]
[[Category:Punk rock| ]]
[[Category:Rock music genres]]
[[Category:Underground culture]]
[[Category:Youth culture in the United Kingdom]]

{{Link FA|fr}}
{{Link FA|th}}

[[ar:بانك]]
[[be-x-old:Панк-рок]]
[[bar:Punk]]
[[br:Punk rock]]
[[ca:Punk rock]]
[[cs:Punk rock]]
[[da:Punk-rock]]
[[de:Punk (Musik)]]
[[et:Punk rock]]
[[el:Πανκ]]
[[es:Punk]]
[[eu:Punk]]
[[fa:پانک راک]]
[[fr:Punk rock]]
[[fy:Punk rock]]
[[gd:Punc]]
[[ko:펑크 록]]
[[hr:Punk rock]]
[[id:Punk rock]]
[[it:Punk rock]]
[[he:פאנק רוק]]
[[ka:პანკ როკი]]
[[la:Musica punk]]
[[lv:Pankroks]]
[[lt:Pankrokas]]
[[lmo:Punk rock]]
[[mk:Панк рок]]
[[nl:Punk (muziek)]]
[[ja:パンク・ロック]]
[[no:Pønkrock]]
[[nn:Pønkrock]]
[[uz:Punk rock]]
[[pl:Punk]]
[[pt:Punk rock]]
[[ro:Muzică punk]]
[[ru:Панк-рок]]
[[scn:Punk rock]]
[[simple:Punk rock]]
[[sk:Punk rock]]
[[sl:Punk]]
[[sr:Панк рок]]
[[sv:Punkrock]]
[[ta:பங்க்]]
[[th:พังก์ร็อก]]
[[tr:Punk rock]]
[[uk:Панк-рок]]
[[zh:朋克搖滾]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
