<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2322553" ns="0" title="WCTX"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WCTX|
  station_logo             = [[Image:Wctx 2008.png|140px]]|
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = MyTV9 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;News 8 &lt;small&gt;(newscasts)&lt;/small&gt;|
  digital                  = 39 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])|
  affiliations             = 59.1 [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br&gt;59.2 [[TheCoolTV]]|
  founded                  = 1980|
  location                 = [[New Haven, Connecticut|New Haven]]/[[Hartford, Connecticut]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''CT''' ([[United States Postal Service|USPS]] [[Connecticut|state]] abbreviation) and&lt;br&gt;The '''X''' (past branding)|
  former_callsigns         = WTVU (1994-1996)&lt;br&gt;WBNE (1996-2000)|
  owner                    = [[LIN TV Corporation]]|
  licensee                 = WTNH Broadcasting, Inc.|
  sister_stations          = [[WTNH]], [[WWLP]]/[[WFXQ-CD]], [[WPRI-TV]], [[WNAC-TV]]|
  former_channel_numbers   = 59 (UHF analog, 1994-2009)|
  former_affiliations      = [[NBC]] (1980-1994, as repeater of [[WVIT]])&lt;br&gt;[[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1994-1995)&lt;br&gt;[[The WB Television Network|The WB]] (1995-2000)&lt;br&gt;[[UPN]] (2001-2006)&lt;br&gt;[[weather radar]] (on DT2)|
  effective_radiated_power = 170 [[kilowatt|kW]]|
  HAAT                     = 301 [[meter|m]]|
  facility_id              = 33081|
  coordinates              = {{coord|41|25|22.7|N|72|57|4.1|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.myzone.tv/ myzone.tv]|
}}

'''WCTX''' is the [[MyNetworkTV]]-affiliated [[television station]] for the state of [[Connecticut]] that is licensed to [[New Haven]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 39 from a transmitter in [[Hamden, Connecticut|Hamden]]. Owned by the [[LIN TV Corporation]], the station is sister to [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate [[WTNH]] and the two share studios on Elm Street in Downtown New Haven. However, master control and some internal operations originate from hub facilities at [[NBC]] affiliate [[WWLP]] in [[Chicopee, Massachusetts]]. [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on WCTX includes: ''[[30 Rock]]'', ''[[Judge Judy]]'', ''[[Dr Phil (TV series)|Dr. Phil]]'', ''[[TMZ on TV]]'', and ''[[The Insider (TV series)|The Insider]]''. 

Like sister station WTNH that has a large [[Fairfield County, Connecticut|Fairfield County]] audience as well. This area is part of the [[New York City]] DMA which is where MyNetworkTV flagship [[WWOR-TV]] is based. WCTX is available on channel 9 on almost all of Connecticut's cable systems and this is reflected in its on-air branding '''''MyTV9'''''.

==Digital television==

On WCTX-DT2, [[Comcast]] digital channel 240, and [[Charter Communications|Charter]] digital channel 260 is [[TheCoolTV]].	

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! [[Video resolution|Video]]
! [[Aspect ratio|Aspect]]
! Programming
|-
| 59.1 || [[1080i]] || [[16:9]] || Main WCTX programming / MyNetworkTV
|-
| 59.2 || [[480i]] || [[4:3]] || TheCoolTV
|}

==History==
As early as 1953, a [[Construction permit#Broadcasting|construction permit]] for the analog UHF channel 59 allotment was issued by the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) and was originally owned by the Connecticut Radio Foundation. However, the group was never able to get the station on-the-air and sold the permit to Impart Systems in 1967. In 1980, [[Viacom (1971–2005)|Viacom]], then-owner of [[NBC]] affiliate [[WVIT]], built a [[low-power television|low-power]] translator on UHF channel 59 in New Haven. Although WVIT had boosted its power to cover New Haven a few months earlier, some areas in Southern Connecticut still could not get a good signal from the station.

On November 5, 1994, this station finally began broadcasting as a stand-alone [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] with the calls '''WTVU'''. It initially operated at low-power running [[Shop at Home]] programming for most of the day and later adding coverage of the [[O.J. Simpson]] murder trial. In April 1995, WTVU upgraded to full power operations. In June of that year, LIN TV took over control of the station through a [[local marketing agreement]] (LMA) with WTNH. With the LMA came an affiliation with [[WB Television Network|The WB]], which until that point, had been airing its prime time programming on WTNH following its late newscast on Saturday nights. 

The LMA also allowed WTVU to significantly upgrade its programming.  It acquired stronger syndicated programs, mostly barter shows and second runs from WTNH. It also began running classic sitcoms such as: ''[[Perry Mason]]'', ''[[I Love Lucy]]'', ''[[Happy Days]]'', ''[[The Honeymooners]]'', ''[[The Andy Griffith Show]]'', ''[[The Beverly Hillbillies]]'', ''[[I Dream of Jeannie]]'', ''[[Bewitched]]'', and ''[[Gilligan's Island]]'' among others that fell off the schedules of [[WCCT-TV|WTXX]] and [[WHPX-TV|WTWS]] some years back. It also picked up [[Hartford Whalers]] hockey, which aired on the station until the team became the [[Carolina Hurricanes]] in 1997. 

On April 1, 1996, the station changed its call letters to '''WBNE''' (for &quot;'''WB''' '''N'''ew '''E'''ngland&quot;). After [[Tribune Broadcasting]] (a minority owner of The WB) purchased then-UPN affiliate WTXX, WBNE and that station swapped network affiliations on January 1, 2001. With the new network relationship came the current '''WCTX''' calls and use of the on-air identity &quot;The X&quot;. That identity was used in lieu of the conventional &quot;UPN (channel number)&quot; branding. LIN TV purchased WCTX outright in 2002. On September 19, 2005, WCTX became known as &quot;UPN 9,&quot; highlighting its cable channel position in some areas. This branding was the same as WWOR in New York City, a station that is available over-the-air and on cable in [[Southwestern Connecticut]]. 

On January 24, 2006, The WB and UPN announced that the networks would cease broadcasting and merge to create a new network called [[CW Television Network|The CW]]. It was to be jointly owned by [[CBS]] and the [[Warner Bros.]] unit of [[Time Warner]]. WTXX was chosen as Connecticut's CW affiliate after its owner Tribune announced a ten year deal with the upcoming network leaving WCTX to tentatively become an Independent once again. However on April 26, WCTX announced it would join MyNetworkTV (a second new network launched by [[News Corporation]]). 

This began broadcasting on September 5, and as a result, the station did not carry the final two weeks of programming from UPN. With its new network affiliation, the station changed its branding to the current &quot;My TV 9&quot;. As of the 2007/2008 season, [[University of Connecticut]] men's college basketball games now air primarily on WCTX while a handful of games air on sister station WTNH. It recently signed a multi-year television deal with the [[WNBA]]'s [[Connecticut Sun]] to broadcast select regular season games as well. 

Until March 31, 2008, WCTX served as the default MyNetworkTV affiliate on Comcast and Charter cable systems for the [[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield]]/[[Holyoke, Massachusetts]] market as that area did not have an affiliate of its own. On that date, [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate [[WGGB-TV]] added the network as a secondary affiliation on its new [[Fox Network|Fox]] [[WGGB-DT2|second]] [[digital subchannel]]. Although WCTX was dropped from Comcast, it is still seen on Charter. This station was also repeated on W11BJ (now [[WFXQ-CD]]) from a transmitter on [[Rattlesnake Mountain (Connecticut)|Rattlesnake Mountain]] in [[Farmington, Connecticut|Farmington]] from 2004 until 2006 while LIN TV built a new transmitter for that channel and moved its city of license to Springfield. 

On June 12, 2009, WCTX left channel 59 and moved to channel 39 when the analog to digital conversion was completed. It is considered an alternate ABC affiliate airing that network's programs when WTNH is unable to do so such as during a breaking news emergency or local special. Until TheCoolTV was added on WCTX-DT2, this aired a 24-hour live feed of WTNH's regional [[weather radar]] known as the &quot;SkyMax Doppler Network&quot;.

==Newscasts==
Since the start of the local marketing agreement with WCTX in 2000, WTNH has been producing a nightly prime time newscast at 10 on this channel. It has competed right from the start with [[WTIC-TV]]'s 10 o'clock broadcast which established itself as a viewer favorite since going on-the-air in 1989. As of the February 2008 ratings period, that channel's weeknight newscast is actually the most watched 10 or 11 p.m. broadcast in the market even gathering more viewership that the [[Big Three television networks|big three stations]] in Connecticut. 

In 2005, WCTX began simulcasting the second hour of WTNH's weekday morning show (at 6) followed by a third hour from 7 until 8 seen exclusively on WCTX except for simulcasted ''[[Good Morning America]]'' cut-ins on WTNH. The second hour was eventually dropped for an unknown reason. The 7 a.m. hour received competition on March 3, 2008 when WTIC made its initial weekday morning show launch. On April 26, 2010; WTNH re-branded from ''News Channel 8'' to ''News 8''. In addition, WTNH began broadcasting newscasts in [[16:9]] [[widescreen]] [[enhanced definition]], with WCTX's newscasts being included in the upgrade. On October 4, 2010; WTNH began broadcasting newscasts in high definition, becoming the third station in the market to do so. WCTX's newscasts also made the transition.

'''Anchors'''
*Kristen Cusato - weekday mornings
*Chris Velardi - weekday mornings
*Darren Kramer - weeknights
*Ann Nyberg - weeknights
*Sara Welch - weekends and reporter 
*Ted Koppy - Sundays and reporter 

'''''Storm Team 8 Meteorologists'''''
*[[Gil Simmons]] ([[Certified Broadcast Meteorologist]]) - weekday mornings

'''Sports'''
*Noah Finz - Director seen weeknights
*John Pierson - weekends
*Marc Robbins - reporter

'''Reporters'''
*Mark Davis - Chief Political Correspondent based at Hartford Bureau
*Jocelyn Maminta - health and medical correspondent 
*Erin Cox - investigative and general assignment
*Teresa LaBarbera - weekday morning traffic
*Tina Detelj - New London Bureau
*Crystal Haynes
*Keith Kountz 
*Annie Rourke
*Jamie Muro
*Bob Wilson
*Kent Pierce

==External links==
*[http://www.myzone.tv/ WCTX &quot;My TV 9&quot;]
*[http://www.wtnh.com/ WTNH &quot;News 8&quot;]
*{{TVQ|WCTX}}

{{Hartford/New Haven TV}}
{{Springfield MA TV}}
{{MNTV New England}}
{{LIN TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wctx}}
[[Category:MyNetworkTV affiliates]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1980]]
[[Category:Channel 39 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television stations in New Haven, Connecticut]]
[[Category:Television stations in Connecticut]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
