<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2327057" ns="0" title="Christian Academy of Louisville"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
|name = Christian Academy of Louisville|
image = [[File:Christian Academy of Louisville.jpg|300px|English Station]]|
motto = Heart for God. Mind for Truth. Friends for Life. Service for Eternity.|
established = 1975|
type = [[Private school|Private]]| 
religion = [[Protestant]]|
head_name = Superintendent|
head = Tim Greener| 
head_name2 = Executive Director|
head2 = Maurice &quot;Moe&quot; Lundrigan|
campus = English Station (main), Rock Creek (original), Southwest, Southern Indiana|
class = 20|
SAT = 1718.2|
ACT = 25.2|
city = [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]]|
state = [[Kentucky|KY]]|
country = [[United States|USA]]|
enrollment = 3069|
faculty = 269|
ratio = 15:1| 
year = 2009|
athletics =  [[Baseball]], [[Basketball]], [[Cheerleading]], [[Cross country running|Cross Country]], [[Field Hockey]], [[American Football|Football]], [[Golf]], [[Lacrosse]], [[Soccer]], [[Softball]], [[swimming (sport)|Swimming]], [[Tennis]], [[Track and Field]], [[Volleyball]], [[Marching Band]]|
colors = [[Red]], [[White]], [[Blue]]| 
mascot = [[Centurion]]| 
homepage = [http://www.christianacademyschools.org/ Official site]| 
}}
'''Christian Academy of Louisville''', is a member of the Christian Academy School System which holds a distinctive place among educational institutions in the [[Louisville, Kentucky|Kentuckiana]] area by providing a high-quality, Christian education.  The school seeks to provide a &quot;traditional education in a Christ-centered environment&quot;, and families seeking admission must have a reference from a [[minister of religion|minister]] certifying that they attend a [[church (building)|church]] regularly. The school holds accreditation from the [[Association of Christian Schools International]] (ACSI), the [[Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]], the Kentucky Non-Public School Commission, the National Council of Private School Accreditation, the State of [[Kentucky]], and the State of [[Indiana]].

==History==
Christian Academy of Louisville was founded in 1975 by South Louisville Christian Church with 120 students in grades one through six. In 1978, Christian Academy purchased the Rock Creek Campus in St. Matthews with 336 students. In 1982, the first senior class graduated with 19 students. Today there are more than 1,800 alumni from Christian Academy of Louisville.

Continued growth led to the building of the English Station Campus, located on {{convert|65|acre|m2}}, which opened in the Fall of 1998. Currently, more than 1,800 students (Preschool-12) attend the English Station Campus with an additional 335 students attending Preschool-5th grade at the Rock Creek Campus.

In the Fall of 2000, the Christian Academy School System was created with the addition of Christian Academy of Louisville Southwest and Northside Christian School. The Southwest Campus, located in Shively, opened with 76 students in grades K-2. The Northside Campus, located in New Albany, Indiana, joined with 190 students in Preschool through 5th grade. In the Fall of 2003, Graceland Christian School, located in New Albany, Indiana, joined the school system with over 450 students in grades K-12

The {{convert|60|acre|m2|sing=on}} Christian Academy of Indiana campus, which combined the Graceland and Northside campuses into a single school, opened in the Fall of 2005 with more than 700 students.

A new{{convert|25|acre|m2|sing=on}} Southwest Campus was dedicated in 2006 and now serves over 350 students in grades preschool - 8th.

Today, the Christian Academy School System serves more than three thousand students located on four campuses in Louisville and Southern [[Indiana]].

Starting in [[2011 PDL season|2011]], the school's Centurion Soccer Fields, on the English Station Campus, are serving as the home to the city's [[USL Premier Development League]] team, the [[River City Rovers]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.roverssoccer.com/home/roverNews/491766.html |title=Centurion Soccer Fields at Christian Academy of Louisville (English Station) will be the 2011 home field for the Rovers! |publisher=River City Rovers |accessdate=April 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics and achievement==
The school regularly produces [[National Merit Scholar|National Merit Finalists]] and Governor's Scholars from its large population of academically dominant students. The class of 2009 had four National Merit Finalists, three National Merit Commended Students, five Governor's Scholars, two Governor's School for the Arts and one Commonwealth Diploma recipient. 

The class of 2009 received more than $5.6 Million in scholarships and provided more than 16,291 service hours to the local community.  Typically, about ninety-nine percent of Christian Academy graduates go on to [[college]].

==Missions==
'''From Appalachia to Africa: Building and Empowering Globally'''

Christian Academy seeks to train the next generation of leaders to share the gospel message with others in the community, nation and around the world. Since 1998, Christian Academy has sponsored at least one mission trip abroad to share Christ's love and a message of salvation to others.

In 2001, Christian Academy developed the Christian Academy Missions Program to provide consistent school-sponsored opportunities for the students to serve Christ nationally and internationally.  Since the beginning of the program, more than 500 students have participated in school-sponsored mission trips from Appalachia to Africa.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{coord missing|Kentucky}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Christian Academy Of Louisville}}
[[Category:Schools in Louisville, Kentucky]]
[[Category:Private high schools in Kentucky]]
[[Category:Private middle schools in Kentucky]]
[[Category:Private elementary schools in Kentucky]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1975]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
