<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2328647" ns="0" title="3e"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|3E (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox TV channel
| name             = 3e
| logofile         = 3e.jpg
| logosize         = 140px
| launch           = 30 March 2006 
| closed date      = 
| share            = 1.1% {{profit}}
| share as of      = 31/12/2010
| share source     = &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medialive2.com/television/channel-share-of-viewing/channel-share-of-viewing.html |title=Media Live |publisher=Medialive2.com |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| owner            = TV3 Group  
| slogan           = '''The Home Of Entertainment'''
| country          = [[Republic of Ireland]] 
| broadcast area   = Republic of Ireland
| former names     = 
| replaced names   = Channel 6 &lt;small&gt;(2006-2009)&lt;/small&gt;
| sister names     = [[TV3 Ireland|TV3]]
| picture format   = 16:9 SDTV (has 4:3 flag set)
| terr serv 1      = [[Saorview]]
| terr chan 1      = Channel 6
| sat serv 1       = SCTV Digital
| sat chan 1       = Channel 106 
| sat serv 2       = [[Sky (UK &amp; Ireland)|Sky Ireland]] |
| sat chan 2       = Channel 105
| cable serv 1     = [[UPC Ireland]]
| cable chan 1     = Channel 106
| sat radio serv 1 = 
| sat radio chan 1 = 
| adsl serv 1      = [[Magnet Entertainment]]
| adsl chan 1      = Channel 106
| online serv 1    = 
| online chan 1    = 
}}

'''3e''' (''3 entertainment'') is a [[Commercial broadcasting|commercial]] [[television network]] in the [[Republic of Ireland]]. Launched on [[5 January]] [[2009]] (replacing Channel 6 which previously launched in March 2006).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Steven |last=Carroll |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Channel 6 rebranded by owner TV3 as 3e |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2009/0105/1230936655682.html |work=[[The Irish Times]] |publisher= |date=5 January 2009 |accessdate=5 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The channel is operated by Kish Media a subsidiary of [[TV3 Ireland|TV3 Group]] owned by  [[Doughty Hanson &amp; Co]].

==The TV3 Group==
The TV3 Group was established in [[January 2009]]. The network operates TV3 and its sister channel 3e and its online service '''tv3.ie'''. The networks studios is located at [[Ballymount]], [[Dublin]]. TV3 was initially the first channel from the network launched in [[1998]]. The network expanded in [[2008]] when TV3 purchased rival channel Channel 6 and rebranded the channel in January 2009 as 3e. In [[November 2008]], '''tv3.ie''' website was rebranded, with the intention to develop it into an entertainment portal. Catch up facilities, as well as exclusive content is available for TV3 programming as are news, weather, sport and entertainment updates.

==Broadcasting policy==
3e broadcasts a wide range of programming which is made up largely of [[US]], [[Australian]] and [[UK]] television acquisitions, while also airing some Irish content. 3e utilizes the existing staff at TV3 (200 employees) to operate the channel. The channel airs mainly dramas, comedy, sports and movies. The channel provides a diverse mix of programming both local and international, targeting a demographic ranging between 16 to 35 year olds.

==Availability==

The channel is currently available to 90% of homes within the Republic of Ireland through the national [[digital terrestrial television]] service [[Saorview]] since November 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boards.ie/vbulletin/showthread.php?threadid=2056092641&lt;/ref&gt;
It is available to 80% of homes through digital cable and satellite service such as [[UPC Ireland]], [[Magnet Networks]], [[Smart Telecom|Smartvision]] and [[Sky Ireland]].

==History==
===Concept===

The channel was originally operated by Kish Media's subsidiary ''Channel 6 Broadcasting Ltd''. This was initially owned by a consortium made up of Tullamore Beta, Barry family of Barry's Tea and Gowan Group. In its infant stages, the channels consortium invested €14 million to fund the project. The idea behind the channel was to compete with [[RTÉ]]'s second general entertainment channel [[RTÉ Two]] which targets a similar demographic and [[TV3 Ireland]]. It was anticipated that Channel 6 would launch further channels including a Channel 6+1 service and a music channel.

The station's first [[managing director]] was Martin Drake, who left the company after just eight months, and after a period under interim CEO Mark Kellett, the channel's top job was taken by Managing Director Michael Murphy, who later left the channel when it was fully transferred over to TV3 and integrated into the TV3 Group. In June 2008, it was reported that Kish Media were in discussions to sell Channel 6. It was later reported in [[July 2008]] that its rival [[TV3 Ireland|TV3]], would purchase the channel for around €10 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent.ie&quot;&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/business/media/tv3-to-buy-channel-6-for-836410m-1441338.html ''Irish Independent'', 26 July 2008: ''TV3 to buy Channel 6 for €10m'']. Retrieved 2008-08-03.&lt;/ref&gt; The deal was given the approval of the [[Broadcasting Commission of Ireland]], and was approved by the Irish Competition Authority thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/business/irish/tv3s-836410m-takeover-move-for-channel-6-clears-first-hurdle-1445268.html ''Irish independent'', 2 August 2008: ''TV3's €10m takeover move for Channel 6 clears first hurdle'']. Retrieved 2008-08-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2008, TV3 confirmed they were to rebrand Channel 6 to '''3e''' on 5 January 2009. The channel would utilize existing TV3 programming and provide TV3 audiences with a wider range of programming. 3e provides viewers with a broad mix of US and Australian acquisitions and is often used as a TV3 replay service featuring repeats of previously broadcasted programs on TV3 such as [[Ireland AM]], [[Expose (TV3 series)|Expose]] and [[Midday]]. In November 2010, the TV3 Group confirmed 3e made financial losses, but expect revenue to increase in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/finance/2010/1106/1224282791429.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ireland-channel-6.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Channel 6 Logo]]

== Restructuring ==
* With the announcement that TV3 Group would operate the channel. It was confirmed in December 2008 that TV3 would axe the majority of Channel 6's homegrown programming which included ''[[Night Shift (Irish TV series)|Night Shift]]'' which had a cult following. The controversial move to cancel the series was reported in the media with major criticism from music journalists and music fans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.state.ie/channel-6s-night-shift-to-be-taken-off-air/|title=Channel 6’s NightShift to be taken off air|date=2008-12-08|accessdate=2008-12-25|publisher=''[[State (magazine)|State]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other shows which were cancelled with TV3's acquisition of Channel 6 included music shows ''Day Shift'' and ''Pop Scene'', and ''Take 6'', a weekly movie review show.

* From 2009, TV3 began to use the channel as a replay service. In late 2010, 3e began producing its own programming which includes ''FYI'' (previously [[3e#News and sport|3e News]]) and ''Uploaded''.

* 3e was made available on [[Sky Ireland]] in late 2009. Previously, under the Channel 6 branding the channel was not available on this service due to a dispute between Kish Media and Sky.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/satellite/a28568/no-sky-launch-for-irelands-channel-6.html ''Digital Spy'', 29 January 2006: ''No Sky launch for Ireland's Channel 6'']. Retrieved 2008-08-03.&lt;/ref&gt; This situation was rectified on 29 September 2009 when TV3 Group and [[Sky Ireland]] confirmed that that 3e would be made available on its service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tv3.ie/pr_sub.php?type=1&amp;view_pr=75 ''TV3 Press Release'', 29 September 2009: ''TV3 ANNOUNCES NEW HOME ON SKY FOR 3e '']. Retrieved 2009-10-01.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://freetexthost.com/csbuf2vuwf
|title=Free Text Host - Email from TV3 regarding move of 3e 
|publisher=''Keith Feeney/Free Text Host''
|date=2009-10-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* It was reported on 24 July 2009; [[TV3 Ireland|TV3 Group]] sought to change 3e's licensing from the [[Broadcasting Commission of Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.independent.ie/business/media/broadcasting-watchdog-to-rule-on-crossmedia-obrien-probe-1838223.html|title=Broadcasting watchdog to rule on cross-media O'Brien probe|date=2008-07-26|accessdate=2008-07-29|publisher=[[Irish Independent]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 July 2009, the [[Broadcasting Commission of Ireland]] announced that the 3e licence would be licensed under Section 34, rather than Sections 36 and 41, of the Broadcasting Act 2001.  This means that 3e is no longer a separate cable and satellite service rather it will be covered by the main terms and conditions of the existing TV3 contract.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iftn.ie/?act1=record&amp;only=1&amp;aid=73&amp;rid=4282379&amp;tpl=archnewshome&amp;force=1|title=BCI Approves Changes to Setanta Ireland &amp; Awards New Contracts|date=2008-07-29|accessdate=2008-07-29|publisher=''[[Irish Film and Television Network|IFTN]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Viewing figures ===
* TV3 Group reported on 12 November 2009 that 3e's viewing figures had increased since moving to Sky 105. Its audience share increased by 25% from 0.9% to 1.1% - this brought the channel back to the audience figures received by Channel 6 at the end of 2008.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.independent.ie/business/media/3e-to-launch-own-news--after-reporting-25pc-surge-in-new-sky-slot-1940290.html&lt;/ref&gt;

* As of 2010, 3e has increased its viewing figures through an increase in Irish programming and live sports.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tv3.ie/pr_sub.php?type=2&amp;view_pr=86&lt;/ref&gt;

===Budget===
In [[2008]], TV3 received €3 million in funding from the licence fee for independent productions on the channel. In [[2009]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/finance/2009/1024/1224257392869.html&lt;/ref&gt; TV3 had revenues of €54,300,000. In the previous year (2008), TV3 received €62 million in advertising revenue. Increases in programme cost during 2008 included new sporting contracts with the [[Gaelic Athletic Association|GAA]] and [[UEFA]], the first renewal of their contract with the British broadcaster [[ITV]] for shows such as ''[[The X Factor (UK)|The X-Factor]]'' and ''[[Coronation Street]]'', a small but significant increase in programmes commissioned from independent producers and their takeover of Channel 6 (now 3e). They also increased their investment in online technology, with their online service earning a profit for the first time. In [[2009]], two rounds of redundancies reduced TV3 staff to 213 people. Staff savings have been augmented by agreed reductions in wages. The 200 staff working in TV3 now provide seven hours of live television five days a week, an increase of two hours and a staff reduction of 50 since 2007.

In [[2010]], 3e's parent company recorded losses at the station during 2009. A pre-tax loss of €5million was reported to the Irish Company Registrars Office (CRO). Kish Media will not look to recoup their €14.5million investment until such time as the channel begins to make profits and when all liabilities at the station are paid as they fall due. It is expected that the channel will move into profit in 2010, however the downturn in the Irish market and falling advertising rates did cause the channel problems during 2009. Revenue was down in 2008 from 2007, while expenses during 2008 had be reduced slightly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=McCaughren |first=Samantha |url=http://www.thepost.ie/news/ireland/3e-records-losses-but-profit-expected-this-year-47536.html |title=3e records losses, but profit expected this year |publisher=The Post |date=2010-02-21 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Programming==
In [[2009]], several rearrangements of the 3e schedule occurred - as it re-branded from Channel 6 - including showing repeats of ''[[Xpose]]'' and ''[[Emmerdale]]'' straight after [[TV3 (Ireland)|TV3]], followed by putting ''Xpose'' on at 17:30 instead of 18:30 and removing repeat showings of ''Emmerdale'' and replacing them with repeat showings of ''[[Coronation Street]]''. Each of the changes failed to ignite 3e audience share, at first a small drop was seen.  As you can see Xpose was returned to 18:30, while a ''Coronation Street'' omnibus was on a Sunday afternoon, however ultimately both ITV soaps were dropped from the schedule.

===Homegrown===
* As Channel 6 the channel produced several shows to compete with both [[RTÉ Two]]'s and [[TV3 (Ireland)|TV3]]'s youth orientated programming, such as, ''[[Cois Farraige]]'' an Irish surfing and surf culture show hosted by Jenny Buckley , ''[[Access Hollywood]]'' also hosted by Jenny Buckley, ''[[Day Shift]]'' a weekend morning music show, ''Game On'' a video games show, ''[[Night Shift (Irish TV series)|Night Shift]]'' a late night interactive music show hosted by [[Michelle Doherty]], ''[[Quiz 6]]'' a phone-in quiz show, where viewers could answer on screen puzzles to win cash and ''[[Take Six]]'' a movie show hosted by Elsa Jones, Sean Musanje and Serena Bellissimo. Channel 6 had cancelled all but ''Day Shift'', ''Night Shift'', ''Pop Scene'' and ''Take 6'' by the time TV3 had bought the station. TV3 cancelled all of the remaining Channel 6 programmes as they relaunch the channel as 3e.
* With the relaunch of the channel to 3e the Channel 6 programming was replaced by repeats of TV3's ''[[Xposé]]'', ''[[Xposé]]XTRA'' and ''[[The Holiday Show]]''. Towards the end of 2009 TV3 began to produce more programming ''Xccelerate'' a weekly motoring show for 3e, produced by City Productions for TV3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.tv3.ie/pr_sub.php?type=1&amp;view_pr=83 |title=IRELAND’S ONLY MOTORING SHOW REVS UP ON 3e |publisher=TV3 |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* In [[2010]], TV3 will bring their mix of homegrown morning shows to the channel as repeats. ''[[Ireland AM]]'' will be repeated on 3e each morning at 10:15, ''The Morning Show'' will be repeated the following morning on 3e at 09:25 and ''Midday'' will be repeated the following morning on 3e at 08:35.

===News and sport===
* Although designed as an entertainment channel, 3e started broadcasting news updates shortly after the station rebranded to 3e. ''3e News Update'' is a minute long news broadcast from [[TV3 News]]. ''3e News Update'' broadcasts Monday to Friday at 18:59, 19:59, 20:59, and 21:59. The News Updates were presented by TV3 News presenters.
* Since September 2009 TV3 Sport has provided live coverage of the [[UEFA Europa League]] (formerly the [[UEFA Cup]]) on 3e, the Irish rights for which TV3 shares with [[Setanta Ireland]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uefa.com/multimediafiles/download/competitions/uefacup_/67/58/75/675875_download.pdf |title=MEDIA content rights sales: UEFA Europa League |publisher=UEFA |date=2009-12-21 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* CEO of the TV3 Group [[David McRedmond]] revealed in an interview with [[Hot Press]] on Thursday 8 October 2009 that '''3e''' would produce a new news programme targeting a demographic between 15 to 34 years of age. The show will air every evening and it is expected to start broadcasting at the end of October 2009,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hotpress.com/David%20McRedmond/news/TV3%20boss%20compares%20Irish%20media%20control%20to%20Soviet%20State%20system/5889866.html |title=TV3 boss compares Irish media control to Soviet State system |publisher=Hot Press |date=2009-10-08 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; however the show's launch was put back until the end of November 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=O2 Ideas Room |url=http://www.independent.ie/business/media/3e-to-launch-own-news--after-reporting-25pc-surge-in-new-sky-slot-1940290.html |title=3e to launch own news after reporting 25pc surge in new Sky slot - Media, Business |publisher=Independent.ie |date=2009-11-12 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''[[TV3 News#3e News|3e News]]'' began broadcasting 23 November 2009 at 18:00. It broadcasts Monday to Friday each week. The main news anchor is Caroline Twohig, The sports anchor is Paul Walsh and the cyber reporter is Cassie Stokes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.tv3.ie/pr_sub.php?type=1&amp;view_pr=84 |title=3e News presenters confirmed! |publisher=TV3 |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; 3e News is to be renamed as ''[[TV3 News#3e News|FYI]]''(Fresh Young Independent) from 10 March 2010. The show's presenters remain on in their current roles and the format of an Interactive news aimed at the 15 to 35 year old age group remains.   ''3e News Update'' has been replaced with ''FYI. Update'' at 7:58, ''FYI. Online'' at 8:58 and ''FYI. Download'' at 9:58.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|url=http://www.tv3.ie/pr_sub.php?type=1&amp;view_pr=120 |title=fyi. – A FRESH APPROACH TO NEWS |publisher=YV3 |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Imports===
As Channel 6 the channel launched several new high profiled US series including ''[[Heroes (TV series)|Heroes]]'', ''[[House (TV series)|House]]'', ''[[Rachel Ray]]'', ''[[My Name is Earl]]'', ''[[American Dad]]'', ''[[Dexter (TV series)|Dexter]]'', ''[[Family Guy]]'' and ''[[The Closer]]'' however due to the channels lack of coverage it was unable to launch these series to Irish Audiences. Other high profiled well known series were bought in the hope that they would help launch the channel to viewers used to shows like ''[[CSI (franchise)|CSI]]'', ''[[Fraiser]]'', ''[[Friends]]'', ''[[Sex and the City]]'', ''[[Scrubs (TV series)|Scrubs]]'', ''[[The Sopranos]]'', ''[[Swingtown]]'' and ''[[The Wire]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/article660945.ece | work=The Times | location=London | title=Comment Stephen Price | date=8 October 2006 | accessdate=23 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the take over of the channel by TV3 and its relaunch to 3e they have been able to add some of TV3's imports to their service including the ITV package of shows used by TV3 and other late night shows such as ''[[Jimmy Kimmel Live!]]'' and the first series of ''[[In Treatment]]''. TV3 have since moved most of their American shows to the channel tending to show ITV programming or imported documentaries on TV3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iftn.ie/news/?act1=record&amp;aid=73&amp;rid=4281923&amp;tpl=archnews&amp;only=1 |title='In Treatment' Comes to 3e |publisher=The Irish Film &amp; Television Network |date=2009-03-02 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

The latest US import to be broadcast on ''3e'' is the comedy-musical ''[[Glee (TV series)|Glee]]'', which has its first showing every Friday night at 21:00 on ''3e'' before ''TV3'' on Wednesday night. ''[[The Cleveland Show]]'' now broadcasts along side ''[[Family Guy]]'' and ''[[American Dad]]''. [[The Middle (TV Series)|The Middle]] is also shown on 3e. The second series of ''In Treatment'' has yet to be aired on the channel.

Documentaries from ITV such as ''Britain's Youngest Boozers'' and ''Addicted to Boob Jobs'' are now broadcast on the channel, as well as repeats of ''[[I'm a Celebrity...Get Me Out of Here!]]'', ''[[Dancing on Ice]]'', ''[[The X Factor (UK)|The X Factor]]'', ''[[The X Factor (UK)|The Xtra Factor]]'' and ''[[Britain's Got Talent]]'' as they air on [[ITV]] and [[TV3 (Ireland)|TV3]]. 3e also simulcast [[Five (channel)|Five]]'s reality TV series ''[[Don't Stop Believing]]'' in Summer 2010. American talent shows such as [[America's Got Talent]] and [[American Idol]] both broadcast on the channel, with the forthcoming US version of [[The X Factor (UK)|The X-Factor]] set to be repeated on the channel from TV3.  

In mid-2009 ''Jimmy Kimmel Live'' stopped broadcasting on the channel. ''[[Conan (TV series)|Conan]]'' airs Monday to Friday Late night on 3e, one week after US airing, it began broadcasting on the channel on 15 November 2010.

3e also broadcast the Australian fly on the wall documentaries [[Bondi Rescue]] and [[Border Security: Australia's Front Line|Nothing to Declare]]. UK programmes include [[The Graham Norton Show]], [[Fonejacker]] and [[The Only Way is Essex]], which broadcast late night Friday and Saturday.

The critically acclaimed American comedies [[30 Rock]], [[Community]], [[Hung (TV series)|Hung]] and [[The Office (U.S. TV series)|The Office US]] all air on the channel. The [[Seth Green]] Animated comedies [[American Dad]], [[Family Guy]] and [[The Cleveland Show]] all air from 22:00 Monday to Friday. Weekend sitcoms include [[Accidentally on Purpose (TV series)|Accidentally on Purpose]] (which replaced repeats of ''Xposé'' in August 2011 Monday to Friday at 18:30) [[Better with You]] and [[The King of Queens]] air early evening at the weekend.Family comedies [[Everybody Hates Chris]] and [[Malcolm in the Middle]] broadcast during the daytime with alternating stripped schedules as one ends the other takes over. Classic US family comedy  [[Full House]] and [[Growing Pains]] are currently air at the weekend.

American detective franchises [[CSI: Crime Scene Investigation]], [[CSI: Miami]], [[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]], [[NCIS: Los Angeles]] and [[JAG (TV series)|JAG]] are broadcast on the channel. Other US detective serials on the channel include [[Dexter (TV series)|Dexter]], [[The Closer]], [[Chuck (TV series)|Chuck]] and [[House (TV series)|House]].

American Sci-Fi and fantasy serials include [[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]], [[V (2009 TV series)|V]] and [[Supernatural (TV series)|Supernatural]]. Teen drama [[Degrassi: The Next Generation]] and [[Friday Night Lights (TV series)|Friday Night Lights]] are shown weekend mornings.

Daytime chat shows include [[The Steve Wilkos Show]] and [[The Jeremy Kyle Show]]. Other shows include [[3rd Rock from the Sun]], [[King of Queens (TV series)|King of Queens]] and [[That '70s Show]].

== On air identifiers ==
March 2006—present: Channel 6 launched it first set of identifiers (idents) in March 2006 and they remained on the channel up to December 2008 with the re-brand of the channel. The presentation package was produced by Cleverality. There were several indents during this period. The 'blue dot' in the centre of the six would be transformed from a symbol representing entertainment into the 'blue dot'. Examples of those symbols include, the masks for drama and comedy, film reels, a television set etc..

January 2009—present: Channel 6 was rebranded 3e in January 2009. The new idents were made by Dublin based Image Now. The 3e idents consists of the 'e' bouncing around the screen next to the '3',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=67ZJwGUqWjQ&amp;feature=related |title=Broadcast Yourself |publisher=YouTube |date=2010-04-01 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}{{Failed verification#doc_editlinks|date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; one is generic while the other one has the 'e' in flames trying to put them out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5gJuIxr4CNE&amp;feature=related |title=3e ident January 2009 to Present - Fire |publisher=YouTube |date=2009-11-09 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A third ident was added in October 2009 for use before soccer matches, it shows the 'e' kicking a football against the '3'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lBcMuV60Uy8 |title=3e ident January 2009 to Present - football |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fourth ident was added in October 2010, which features the 'e' slipping on a banana skin as a pie and rake hits it.

Christmas idents: During the Channel 6 era the 'blue dot' would turn from a Christmas figure - such as snowmen, mistletoe and holly - into the 'blue dot'. 3e's Christmas idents were made in-house at TV3. Three idents were introduced 'Missletoe', 'Snowballs' and 'Lights' The new idents were first show on Saturday 19 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5gR_gqJGM_E&amp;feature=PlayList&amp;p=890E939DB63C4BDE&amp;index=0&amp;playnext=1 |title=3e Christmas ident 2009 - Misseltoe |publisher=YouTube |date=2009-12-19 |accessdate=2010-05-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[TV3 (Ireland)|TV3]]
* [[Media in Ireland]]
* [[List of Irish television channels]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.tv3.ie/3e/index.php 3e website]

{{Channel 6}}
{{Irish Television Channels}}

[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2006]]
[[Category:Television stations in Ireland]]
[[Category:TV3 (Ireland)]]

[[ga:3e]]
[[fi:3e]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
