<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23290782" ns="0" title="List of True Blood characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
| in-universe = August 2010
| update = July 2010
}}

''[[True Blood]]'' is an American television drama series created and produced by [[Alan Ball (screenwriter)|Alan Ball]]. It is based on ''[[The Southern Vampire Mysteries]]'' by [[Charlaine Harris]].

This article includes main characters (i.e. characters played by a main cast member), as well as every recurring vampire, and every other character to appear in at least four episodes.&lt;ref&gt;http://tviv.org/True_Blood/Characters TVIV.com—True Blood characters&lt;/ref&gt;

==Main characters==
===Principal characters===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:auto; background: #FFFFFF;&quot;
|- style=&quot;color:white&quot;
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:20%&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:60%&quot;| Actor/actress
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Starring seasons
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Recurring seasons
|-
| [[Sookie Stackhouse]] || [[Anna Paquin]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Sookie Stackhouse is a telepathic waitress in a small-town restaurant and the main protagonist of the series. Because of her ability, she has difficulty forming lasting human relationships. She becomes involved in a romantic relationship with a vampire, Bill, upon discovering that she can't read his mind. This relationship with a supernatural being causes a lot of controversy in her small town. Through Bill, she finds herself entering into a world of creatures and supernatural conflict that surpasses her worst nightmares. She has lived with her grandmother, Adele Stackhouse, since childhood, after the death of her parents. After Adele's death Sookie inherits the home. It is revealed in season 3 that Sookie is part faerie, another race of supernaturals that are widely believed to have been driven to extinction by vampires who drained them of their blood to obtain the ability to walk in the sun and not burn. The faeries commonly refer to this as &quot;stealing their light&quot; and hence have a distinct fear and hatred of vampires. It is from the faeries that Sookie inherited her telepathic powers, magical light and apparently delicious tasting blood. Sookie comes into contact with a community of faeries living in a hidden world in Bon Temps and after learning of Bill's betrayal at the end of season 3, goes to join them in their magical world only to learn it was a trick by the fae in order to keep all the humans with faery DNA in the faery world. Sookie returns to Bon Temps to learn a year passed when for her it was only several minutes. 
|-
| [[Bill Compton (The Southern Vampire Mysteries)|Bill Compton]] || [[Stephen Moyer]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Bill Compton is a vampire romantically involved with Sookie. Turned during the American Civil War against his will, Bill shows more compassion for human life than many other vampires. He is outwardly expressive of his emotions and holds onto memories of his past human life, behaviors that are unique amongst his vampire peers. While not an extremely old vampire, Bill is quite powerful and was referred to by Russell Edgington as one of the most promising vampires in the Americas. Bill risks his life and standing in vampire society to protect Sookie from those who wish to take advantage of her faery ancestry. It is revealed in season 3 and hinted at in season 2 that Bill's original purpose for returning to Bon Temps was to discover if Sookie was a faerie and if so deliver her to Queen Sophie Anne to whom he was loyal at the time, so that she could drain Sookie's blood and gain the ability to walk in the sun and not burn. She may have realized Sookie's faerie ancestry from Hadley, Sookie's cousin who is a favorite human companion of the queen, who may have inadvertently revealed information about Sookie's powers. Once Sookie discovers what she believes to be the true reason for Bill's interest in her, she banishes him from her life. Shortly after the queen arrives at Bill's house in Bon Temps expecting him to hand Sookie over to her; when he refuses the two begin a duel to the death. By making a deal with Nan Flanngan, Bill has the queen killed by human snipers and becomes the new king of Louisiana. 

In early episodes it is revealed that Bill had a human wife and two children (Tom and Sarah) before he became a vampire. A short time after being turned Bill returns to his family in his desperation to see them one last time. He discovers that his son has recently died of an illness (pox). Upon seeing his tears of blood at the death of his son his wife becomes hysterical at which point Lorena, the vampire who turned Bill, steps in and glamors her. Bill too glamors her and with Lorena leaves his human family forever. The fates of Bill's wife and young daughter, who was not present during his return home, are unclear though Adele Stackhouse makes reference to the recently deceased previous owner of Bill's family home as the last Compton in Bon Temps, who may have been a descendent of Bill's daughter. Though, in episode 4 of the fourth season, Bill involves into sexual relationship with Portia Bellefleur (sister of Sheriff Bellefleur) and upon meeting her grandmother, he finds out that she is a decendent of his daughter Sarah and consequently breaks up with Portia.
|-
| [[Sam Merlotte]] || [[Sam Trammell]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Sam Merlotte is the owner of Merlotte's, where Sookie works. During the first season, Sam is characterized by his adoration and loyalty towards Sookie Stackhouse. When Bill Compton becomes involved with Sookie, he openly disapproves of their relationship and, despite initial support of vampire rights, feels as though vampires and humans should be separate whether they're equals or not. Sam is a shape shifter and is often seen watching over Sookie in the form of a dog, and the first supernatural introduced to the series that isn't a vampire. It is presumable that Bill is aware that Sam is a shifter, suggesting in one episode that Sam is the only one who can protect Sookie while he is away and displaying a coldness to Sam in his dog form. Due to his nature, Sam is targeted by a [[maenad]] in the second season. As Sam was adopted as a baby, in the third season he explores his family background and meets his somewhat backward birth family which consists of his alcoholic father, his manipulative mother and crude younger brother. Sam's mother and brother both have the ability to shape shift though his father does not. Sam's adopted parents abandoned him when he was a teenager after witnessing his first transformation into a beagle. He returned home to find they had moved, leaving behind all his possessions. It is from his adopted father, on his death bed, that he learns the identities of his birth parents though he is warned by his adopted mother that they are bad people and he is better off not knowing them. Sam suffers from anger issues and has a darker hidden past. 
|-
| [[Jason Stackhouse]] || [[Ryan Kwanten]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Jason Stackhouse is Sookie's not-too-bright, self-involved brother, who is vigilant in defending and protecting Sookie. He supervises a road crew during the day, and is known for bedding the women of Bon Temps at night. During the first season, he is the prime suspect in the murders of four women, all of whom have a connection to him. After the death of his V-addict girlfriend Amy, he comes to believe that he is responsible for the murders. He is then recruited by the Fellowship of the Sun, an anti-vampire church, who approve of what they believe to be his crime of killing fangbangers. During the second season, Jason briefly becomes an active member of the Fellowship, but later leaves it. In the third season, he develops a relationship with a supernatural creature, Crystal Norris, and thinks of joining the police. Crystal is forced to leave town with her fiance but Jason pledges to find her. Like his sister Jason is also part faerie though he does not appear to have inherited any of the special abilities that Sookie possesses. However, some speculate that his potential faerie &quot;ability&quot; is the sexual magnetism that many faeries possess. In season 4 he is a deputy on the Bon Temps police force and caretaker of the werepanthers of Hotshot.
|-
| [[Tara Thornton]] || [[Rutina Wesley]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Tara Thornton has been Sookie Stackhouse's best friend since they were children. Tara grew up in a very abusive home with an alcoholic mother, and consequently finds it difficult to fit in with normal society or to trust people. She is very adept at reading people and constantly distances herself from others by speaking her observations candidly and plainly. As a result, she has difficulty holding down a job until she becomes a bartender at Merlotte's. In the first season, Tara deals with her alcoholic mother and ultimately pays for her mother to have a faux exorcism from &quot;Miss Janette&quot; who turns out to be a cashier at a pharmacy in a nearby town who was scamming them. Before discovering the scam, Tara returns to Miss Janette for her own exorcism which she believes will put her life on track. During the exorcism ritual Tara sees herself as a child with black eyes, though this is later revealed to have been Marianne's consciousness attracted by the spiritual power of ritual. In the second season, she is under the influence of the [[maenad]] Marianne Forrester, who manipulates her intense relationship with a man named Eggs (Benedict). Eggs is shot dead by Jason while admitting forcefully to Andy Bellefleur his guilt to the murders Marianne forced him to do while under her influence. Having lost the only man she ever loved Tara attempts suicide in the third season by taking pills though the attempt is thwarted by Lafayette. 

Tara is later abducted by a delusional vampire who believes she loves him. He holds her captive for many days, even taking her to the mansion of Russell Edginton, for whom he works, where he plans to turn her into a vampire. She eventually escapes the vampire by tricking him into letting her drink his blood so she would have the power to smash his skull with one of the weapons that adorned the wall of their room. However this does not kill him and he comes after her, eventually being killed by Jason at Merlotte's. Tara ends up traumatized by her experience and after discovering that Jason had been the one who killed Eggs, cuts off her hair and leaves Bon Temps. In season 4, Tara has moved to New Orleans and working as a cage fighter, and is in a relationship with another fighter, Naomi. In the season 4 finale, Tara is shot in the side of her head while trying to save Sookie from Debbie. Sookie picks her up from a pool of her own blood, cradling her and screaming for help. It is currently unknown whether she is alive or not.
|-
| Lafayette Reynolds || [[Nelsan Ellis]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Lafayette Reynolds, Tara's cousin, is a short order cook at Merlotte's, a drug dealer, a member of Jason Stackhouse's road crew, and a gay prostitute. During the first season, he is seen selling vampire blood. Due to this, Eric captures and tortures him in the second season, only to instruct him on selling vampire blood once again in the third season, at the queen's orders. In the third season, Lafayette is introduced to a male witch, Jesus, who becomes his romantic interest. Jesus works as a nurse for Lafayette's mother, Ruby ([[Alfre Woodard]]), who is aggressively Christian and mentally ill, though she often has moments of unexpected clarity. In season 4 Lafayette begins to explore wicca with his fellow lover/witch Jesus. Lafayette is killed at the end of the first novel in the series. In ''True Blood'', he is saved due to the popularity of his character and to help expand Tara Thornton's role in the series. 

In casting, Alan Ball had concerns that the character's sexuality would be a dominating trait, &quot;because you don't want to bring in someone who's going to play that in a phony way&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lafayette Philly&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Hiltbrand |first=David|title=Actor brings extended life to 'True Blood' character |url=http://www.philly.com/inquirer/entertainment/20100704_Actor_brings_extended_life_to__True_Blood__character.html|work=Philadelphia Enquirer|accessdate=August 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nelsan Ellis says that it took him a few episodes to find the character.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ellis Vibe&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Rhett|first=Starrene |title=Nelsan Ellis (Lafayette) Talks 'True Blood,' Gay Marriage, Tyler Perry |url=http://www.vibe.com/content/nelsan-ellis-lafayette-talks-true-blood-gay-marriage-tyler-perry|work=Vibe Magazine|accessdate=2010-08-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ellis says that he based many of Lafayette's mannerisms on his mother and his sister,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lafayette Philly&quot; /&gt; and that the costuming also helps him get into character.

{{quote|I have more makeup on than any of the females in the cast. Once they get me with the fake eyelashes and the eye makeup, I listen to some Rihanna and I'm there.|[[Nelsan Ellis]]|''[[The Philadelphia Enquirer]]''}}
|-
| [[Eric Northman]] || [[Alexander Skarsgård]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Eric Northman is the Sheriff of Area 5, a vampire district in Louisiana. A Swedish Viking warrior in life, he is over 1,000 years old and is a powerful member of the vampire community. He runs the vampire bar, Fangtasia, in Shreveport, and develops an interest in Sookie Stackhouse after discovering her unique ability to read minds during the first season. He requests Sookie's services in finding a thief in the first season, then enlists her aid again in the second, seeking to retrieve his maker Godric, an ancient vampire gone missing in [[Dallas]]. His attraction to Sookie becomes more apparent as he tricks her into consuming his blood. In the third season, however, he protects Sookie from werewolf attacks and becomes intent on revenge on vampire king Russell Edgington, after discovering that Russell was the vampire who killed his human relatives before Eric became a vampire. Eric's father is shown to have worn a crown which was taken by Russell Edgington to add to his collection which suggests that Eric's family may have been early Swedish nobles or royalty. In season 4 he buys Sookie's house while she is away in Fae and is cursed by Marnie while trying to shut down her coven. He is left without memory of who he is and is taken in by Sookie. Eric demonstrates more sensitivity with Sookie and the two fall in love. He is confronted by Marnie again who possesses him to kill Bill. Sookie uses her powers to stop Eric from killing Bill, releasing him from Marnie's control and restoring his memories from before and during his amnesia. While his old personality has returned, he is still in love with Sookie. Eric and Bill then team up to stop Marnie. After stopping her, Eric and Bill are both rejected by Sookie, who loves them both. When Nan visits, she reveals that both Eric and Bill have been sentenced to the True Death. However, she reveals she is starting a rebellion against the Authority after having been sentenced herself and asks them to join. When she threatens Sookie, Eric decapitates her guards to distract her so Bill can stake her.
|-
| [[Pamela Swynford De Beaufort|Pam]] || [[Kristin Bauer]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Pamela Swynford De Beaufort, commonly referred to as simply Pam, made into a vampire by Eric about a century before the events of the series, is introduced during the first season as his loyal (albeit lazy) assistant and the bouncer at Fangtasia. Though Pam's background has largely not been explored within True Blood, she and Eric occasionally speak to one another in Swedish. She also has claimed that she used to be a prostitute &quot;a long, long time ago&quot;. Cynical and apparently devoid of feelings for anyone except Eric, she is often by his side though she does not accompany him to Dallas in the second season, presumably she was told to run Fangtasia in Eric's absence. After Lafayette is healed by Eric's blood, Pam enlists him to sell V for Eric. Throughout the series, Pam often displays lesbian tendencies and is even seen performing a sexual act on the new female dancer at Fangtasia who later becomes jealous of Pam for her close relationship with Eric. In season three Pam was briefly held captive and tortured by the Magister, who was trying to find out who was selling V though she revealed nothing, further proving for fierce loyalty to Eric. She wept tears of blood when Eric attempted to burn Russell Edgington in the sun and himself in the process. This was the first time she had been seen to show deep emotions. In season four, after she finds out about the incident with Eric and the witches, she goes after them and demands that Marnie removes the spell she cast on Eric. Marnie tries to cooperate at first, but is once again possessed by the witch Antonia's spirit, and casts a spell on Pam to make her face rot, which leaves Pam horrified.
|-
| [[Jessica Hamby]] || [[Deborah Ann Woll]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Jessica Hamby is a young vampire &quot;made&quot; by Bill as a part of his punishment for murdering a fellow vampire at the end of the first season. Having been raised in an overly strict Christian family, she relishes the freedom that comes with being a vampire, but her petulant attitude often tries Bill's patience. At Bill's request, for most of her part in season 1 she lives at Fangtasia with Pam and Eric who apparently let her feed on a man with tattoos and body piercings, though they quickly become frustrated and annoyed by her and return her to Bill not long after. During season two, Jessica finds a love interest in Hoyt Fortenberry, but he ends their involvement after she attacks his obnoxious mother. During the third season, Jessica makes several young-vampire mistakes, such as accidentally draining a person to death. She eventually rekindles her romance with Hoyt and moves in with him. Jessica is a character exclusive to the series; she does not appear in the ''Southern Vampire Mysteries''. Jessica is increasingly frustrated by the constant regrowth of her hymen after sex, remarking angrily that she will be a virgin forever. 
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#791422&quot;|
|-
|}

===Other main characters===
====Bon Temps residents====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:auto; background: #FFFFFF;&quot;
|- style=&quot;color:white&quot;
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:20%&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:60%&quot;| Actor/actress
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Starring seasons
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Recurring seasons
|-
| Bud Dearborne || [[William Sanderson]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Bud Dearborne is the sheriff of Renard Parish and an old friend of Sookie and Jason's deceased parents. While he is well respected in the town of Bon Temps, he goes out of his way to show his distaste for vampires and vocally objects to Sookie's relationship with Bill. He doesn't believe Jason is the murderer in the first season. Despite the blatant prejudice he shows Bill, he regularly scolds Andy for being unfair and biased in his dealings with suspects. In the second season, he investigates the murders of Miss Jeanette and Daphne. His attempts at identifying and locating their killer is complicated by the outrageous behavior of Bon Temps' residents while under Maryann's influence. In the third season, Bud resigns after yet another murder takes place and leaves Andy Bellefleur in charge.
|-
| Andy Bellefleur || [[Chris Bauer]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Andy Bellefleur is a police detective in Bon Temps who is somewhat incompetent at his job and is regularly disrespected by the town's citizens. He is a recovering alcoholic. He is assigned to investigate the series of murders that occur during the first season. Throughout the season, Jason Stackhouse is Andy's primary suspect even when evidence doesn't point toward him being responsible. He is suspended from his duties in the second season, but makes a comeback as he claims to have shot Eggs, whom the town believes responsible for murders committed by Maryann. In the third season, he takes over from Sheriff Dearborne and reluctantly trains Jason in being a police officer. For most of Maryann's reign of terror he manages to keep from falling under her influence until the night she is killed by Sam. Andy is one of the few Bon Temps residents who remembers what Maryann had done, although his knowledge of who and what she was appears limited as he was heavily intoxicated a lot of the time. In season 4 he is shown to have an addiction to V &quot;vampire blood&quot;. It is also revealed in season 4 that his sister Portia is a direct descendant of Bill Compton, this would also mean that Andy too is a direct descendant of Bill's.
|-
| Hoyt Fortenberry || [[Jim Parrack]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Hoyt Fortenberry is Jason's best friend, who works on the road crew. Sweet and good-hearted, he is the only person whose thoughts are consistently kind when Sookie eavesdrops and is unprejudiced against vampires. He is extremely shy around women, and takes the prospect of forming a relationship seriously. For the majority of the first season he is bossed around by his mother, but eventually stands up to her. In the second season, he begins a relationship with Jessica, a newly turned vampire and Bill Compton's vampire-ward. He breaks up with her after she attacks his mother, but they rekindle their romance during the third season and are shown to be living together in the fourth season. Hoyt breaks up with Jessica due to her difficulties having a normal relationship and her growing feelings for Jason, though he is unaware of the latter.
|-
| Arlene Fowler || [[Carrie Preston]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Arlene Fowler is a waitress at Merlotte's. A four-time divorcee, she is a single mother of two. While she has a good heart, she is often apt to resort to bigotry (directed at vampires) and openly disapproves of Sookie's relationship with Bill. Arlene often makes remarks that have distinctly racist undertones though this often appears to be unintentional. Toward the end of the first season, she becomes engaged to her boyfriend Rene, who later turns out to be a murderer and is later killed in self defense by Sookie when he attacks her. During the second season, she develops a relationship with Terry Bellefleur but soon discovers she is pregnant with what she believes to be Rene's baby in season three. She soon becomes depressed and afraid that her baby will grow up to be a serial killer and then, with the aid of the new waitress at Merlotte's, she secretly attempts to have a miscarriage using a mysterious brew, to no avail. While initially Terry believed the baby was his, when Arlene informs him that it is Rene's Terry tells her the baby's paternity is no issue to him and her fear of her unborn child's future seems to slacken, knowing that there will be a good man in its life though it is unknown if her intention to miscarry still lingers. After the birth of her baby she remains adamant that her baby is evil due to Rene's genetics
|- 
| Terry Bellefleur || [[Todd Lowe]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Terry Bellefleur, a cousin of Detective Andy Bellefleur, is an Iraq war veteran who works as one of the cooks at Merlotte's. He shows clear signs of [[post-traumatic stress disorder]] but despite his unusual behavior, is a gentle soul. He is one of the few who are kind to Bill and he finds him to be a kindred soul as Bill is a veteran like him. While working at Merlotte's, he begins to show interest in Arlene, and the two become romantically involved during the second season. Due to Maryann's influence, their relationship appears to progress more quickly than Terry wants. In the third season, Arlene reveals she's pregnant with Rene's baby, but Terry still wants to be the child's parent.
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#791422&quot;|
|-
|}

====Supernaturals====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:auto; background: #FFFFFF;&quot;
|- style=&quot;color:white&quot;
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:20%&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:60%&quot;| Actor/actress
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Starring seasons
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Recurring seasons
|-
| Tommy Mickens || [[Marshall Allman]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Tommy, Sam's younger brother, is an illiterate teenage shapeshifter. He has tried to kill Sam, and has stolen from him. He is shocked by the news of having a brother he never knew about and hated him at first, but after spending time with him he begins to enjoy having Sam for a brother to the point where he asks Sam to let him stay with him after a fight with his father. He moves in with Sam after Sam discovers his parents use him in dog fighting. He starts working in Sam's bar, but is fired after picking a fight. While working in the bar he seems to have an attraction to Jessica, even attacking Hoyt in his dog form. He then attempts to steal Sam's money, but Sam angrily shoots him - an injury he is healed of in Season 4. At some point during the year separating seasons 3 and 4, Tommy, left with no place to stay, is aided by Maxine Fortenberry who welcomes him to stay at her house. After a while Tommy is contacted by his mother, and is tricked into being abducted by Joe Lee who intends to have him enter dogs fights like he did before. Tommy manages to retaliate immediatey, and murders Joe Lee and his mother while trying to escape. He then goes to Sam for help, and they both dispose of the bodies in the swamp, to be eaten by the alligators. Bearing out the legend relayed to Sam early in season four, Tommy, having killed his shifter mother, becomes a Skinwalker, complicating Sam's life significantly. In the form of Sam, he fires Sookie and has sex with Luna before kicking her out, prompting Sam to kick him out for good. He then takes the form of Maxine to sell her natural gas rights. He then writes an apology note for Sam on his way out before being confronted by Marcus who is looking for Sam. Tommy shows up to Marcus' shop in the form of Sam and Marcus warns him to stay away from Luna, his ex-wife. Tommy as Sam claims he never touched her, but that his brother did, prompting Marcus and his wolves to beat up Tommy to the point where he reverts back to his original form. Alcide then takes Tommy to Merlotte's where Sam meets them. Tommy is about to die due to the beating and shifting into Sam. Sam tries to call for some vampire blood to heal Tommy, but Tommy doesn't want it and makes amends with Sam before dying.
|-
| Jesus Velasquez || [[Kevin Alejandro]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Jesus Velasquez is introduced in the third season as a potential love interest to Lafayette. He was born in [[Catemaco]], Veracruz, México, a famous place, full of &quot;brujos&quot;. He works as a nurse at the mental institution where Lafayette's mother is a patient. On their first meeting, he seems to take an immediate interest in Lafayette, followed by a personal visit to Merlotte's to spend time with Lafayette while he is at work. Although they like each other he leaves once he finds out Lafayette is a drug dealer. When Lafayette calls Jesus to help with his mother, their attraction is once again ignited and they spend the night together. Jesus reveals himself to be a &quot;[[Brujería|brujo]]&quot; (or &quot;witch&quot;) to Lafayette and encourages him to develop his own wiccan talents. In season 4, he is revealed to be a Wiccan student of Marnie Stonebrook. The character is exclusive to the series, and was developed to help extend Lafayette's storyline. In the season 4 finale, Marnie kills Jesus to gain his power. His ghost later visits Lafayette to comfort him.
|-
| Crystal Norris || [[Lindsay Pulsipher]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]] || [[True Blood (season 4)|4]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| A werepanther living in the inbred commune of Hotshot, she becomes involved with Jason after he sees her during a drug raid on Hotshot. She seems to be heavily attracted to him, but also informs him she has been promised to her half-brother and thus fiancé, Felton. Jason attempts to lure her away from Hotshot, unaware of her supernatural background, but Felton and her father get her to return every time. Eventually, Crystal escapes Hotshot and hides in Jason's house, who is content with her choice and continues his relationship with her. She then reveals she is a werepanther, but he isn't fazed. Eventually she is forced to leave town with Felton, just after Felton kills her father. Jason pledges to track her down. She reappears as a kidnapper of Jason with the intent to turn him into a werepanther in order to breed with him and continue the werepanther bloodline.
|-
| [[Alcide Herveaux]] || [[Joe Manganiello]] || [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Alcide Herveaux is a werewolf who helps Sookie in finding Bill while Bill is held captive by Russell Edgington. He does this to relieve the debt his family owed towards Eric Northman. Alcide is one of the few good werewolves introduced thus far. He is handsome and has an ongoing attraction with Sookie. He admits to Sookie early on that he used to be in love with his ex Debbie who is a shifter and now a werewolf groupie. She led people to believe she left him because he didn't want a baby. She also says he wasn't man enough and left him for Coot. At the end of season three, Eric borrows Alcide's truck to help kill Edgington, finally relieving him of his debt to Eric. In Season 4 it is revealed that he is back together with Debbie, who is in a recovery program, and living in Shreveport. He is confronted by the Shreveport pack master Marcus Bozeman about not joining the pack. He prefers not to be part of a pack, but when Debbie insists on joining, Alcide relents. He even tells Marcus he's open to moving up in the pack to please Debbie. His relationship with Debbie becomes strained when she senses Alcide might have feelings for Sookie after he saves her life. In addition, Alcide doesn't want the same things that Debbie does, such as a family and being more involved with the pack. Alcide also loses faith in Marcus after Marcus beats Tommy to death. He and Sam eventually team up to exact vengeance on Marcus. Seeing Marcus in his bedroom with Debbie becomes the last straw for Alcide and after Sam beats up Marcus, Alcide breaks his windpipe to protect Sam and formally breaks it off with Debbie.
|-
| Lorena Krasiki|| [[Mariana Klaveno]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Lorena is the vampire who &quot;made&quot; Bill. She is first introduced briefly in season 1 when Bill, fresh from the field of battle in the 1860s, came to her small house in the woods seeking assistance. Pretending to be a lone widow at the time to seduce men and then feed on them she let him in and proceeded to seduce him, when he refused her advances she attacked him and after becoming intrigued by him eventually turned him into a vampire. A lonely yet malevolent being, Lorena quickly becomes emotionally dependent on Bill. Through her influence he becomes a crazed killer and together they revel in the torture of humans before draining them of their blood, often having sex as their victims bleed to death watching. When Bill realizes the monster he has become he forces Lorena to release him and leaves her. 

The two do not meet again for over 70 years when in season 2 she is summoned to the vampire hotel in Texas by Eric who, in his desperation to find Godric, schemes with her to hold Bill captive while Sookie infiltrates the Fellowship of the Sun so that he cannot interfere. Lorena is coerced into Eric's plan. Her love and longing for Bill has intensified over the years and as she holds him captive the two share memories of their twisted past together. Bill eventually escapes after hitting her over the head with a plasma television. Lorena makes an appearance at the party after Godric is freed from the Fellowship of the Sun and challenges Sookie who aggressively defends her relationship with Bill and warns Lorena off him. When she tries to attack Sookie she is stopped by Godric who again comments on her old age and how she has not bettered herself in all that time he then orders her to leave his area which she begrudgingly does but not before an emotional departing with Bill outside. 

Lorena returns in season 3 when Bill is captured by Russell Edgington. At the time she appears to have been living as a guest in Russell's mansion. Upon seeing Lorena Bill becomes enraged and hurls a lamp at her, bursting her into flames. Lorena of course survives this. Russell leaves Bill to Lorena and though at first Bill resists her advances, the two end up having very violent sex in which he twists her neck 180 degrees. After this he calls Sookie and ends their relationship though he did so only to protect her and delude Lorena who believes he has returned to her. Eventually Bill's deception becomes apparent and she resolves to kill him due her instruction from Russell. She spends a lengthy and very emotional time torturing him in the servants house in the mansion grounds before allowing werewolves to feed on his blood. When Sookie escaped from Russell and bursts into the room to save Bill, Lorena attacks her but Sookie gets the upper hand and plunges a piece of wood into Lorena's chest, thus killing her. 
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#791422&quot;|
|-
|}

====Seasonal antagonists====
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:auto; background: #FFFFFF;&quot;
|- style=&quot;color:white&quot;
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:20%&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:60%&quot;| Actor/actress
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Starring seasons
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Recurring seasons
|-
|{{anchor|Rene Lenier|Drew Marshall}}Rene Lenier/Drew Marshall || [[Michael Raymond-James]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Rene Lenier was the main antagonist of Season 1. Rene Lenier is introduced as a [[Cajun]] resident of Bon Temps, a co-worker and friend of Jason; although it is not revealed until the season finale. Initially, he is portrayed as a protagonist that approves of Sookie dating a vampire. He becomes engaged to Arlene and is widely respected in Bon Temps. However, Sookie eventually comes to suspect that he is the perpetrator behind a series of murders involving women associated with vampires. She finds out Rene, whose real name was Drew Marshall, had previously lived in [[Bunkie, Louisiana]], but fled the town after killing his sister Cindy, a &quot;fangbanger&quot;. Now speaking with a trained Cajun accent and living under a fake identity, he used Jason as an unwitting source for knowledge about women who've slept with vampires. Towards the end of the season, some characters beside Sookie realize Rene is the murderer, hence when he ultimately comes after Sookie, both Sam and Bill jump to her rescue. Sookie kills Rene in self-defense, but Arlene later learns she is pregnant with his child and becomes greatly concerned over carrying an &quot;evil child&quot;. 

Rene appears before Arlene in the season 4 finale and warns her about &quot;him&quot;. Whether he's sincere and whether it was Terry he meant is left ambiguous. 
|-
|{{anchor|Maryann Forrester}}Maryann Forrester || [[Michelle Forbes]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Maryann Forrester was the main antagonist of Season 2. Maryann Forrester is a wealthy [[maenad]], who initially presents herself as a social worker. Drawn to Bon Temps due to the potent energy she attributes to a ritual performed by a faux [[Louisiana Voodoo|voodoo doctor]], she takes an interest in Tara and has Tara move in with her. She introduces Tara to Benedict Talley, a troubled man she had previously taken in to take care of and used to kill several of her victims. Throughout the second season, Maryann's true nature becomes apparent: she is devoted to [[Dionysus]] and intends to find a suitable supernatural creature to kill in his honor, hoping to bring him to earth once again. She finds pleasure in hosting giant orgies, creating mayhem and chaos and witnessing pure lust. She controls the actions of the inhabitants of Bon Temps by putting a bizarre spell on them, which turns their eyes completely black and has them do her bidding. Sookie, however, is unaffected by Maryann's spell. Maryann turns into a full-blown antagonist when she settles into Sookie's house and orders the Bon Temps residents to capture Sam Merlotte, whom she intends to sacrifice in her tribute to Dionysus. She ultimately succeeds in capturing Sam and has Eggs slide a knife in his heart, but Bill saves Sam. Sam, shifting into a white bull, has Maryann believe Dionysus has returned to earth. Hence Maryann drops her supernatural shields and Sam, still in the guise of a white bull, is able to kill Maryann for good. After she is killed the town returns to their senses and have no memory of what they had done under Maryann's influence and remember her simply as the elegant woman who threw wild parties.
|-
|{{anchor|Russell Edgington}}Russell Edgington || [[Denis O'Hare]] || [[True Blood (season 3)|3]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Russell Edgington was the main antagonist of Season 3. A 2800-year-old vampire, Russell is the vampire king of Mississippi. He was born a Celt, though he speaks in German when angered. It is implied that he allied himself with Hitler during WWII, telling Eric Northman, &quot;Adolf was right; there is a Master Race...it's just not the '''human''' race.&quot; Though often gentle and polite, he is also shown to be wrathful, manipulative, and somewhat mentally unstable (particularly after the death of his consort Talbot) not recognizing the power that &quot;the Authority&quot; suposedly have over vampires in general, and secretly defying them (as shown when he kills the Magister). His great age means he is much stronger and faster than Eric or Bill, who he effortlessly defeats in single combat. He can also fly.

He abducts Bill in season three in hopes of gathering intel on the queen of Louisiana, with whom he hopes to enter into a [[lavender marriage]], not to conceal his orientation, but instead, to merge their respective kingdoms. After discovering that Sookie has unusual abilities, Russell takes an interest in her. When Bill is no longer of use to him, he orders for his execution, but Sookie thwarts his plans. After Eric kills Russell's consort Talbot in retaliation for Russell murdering Eric's human family centuries ago, Russell becomes hysterical and kills an anchorman on live television to address a statement to the world, in which he announces his view that vampires and humans aren't equals and vampires will rule over them. This has widespread fallout as shown in season 4 with the vampires focusing hard on improving their image. Eric, Sookie and Bill manage to dispose of Russell at the end of the third season by tricking him and burying him underneath concrete. 

In the season 4 finale it is implied that Russell has escaped the concrete, when Alcide finds a mysterious hole in a parking garage floor with silver chains discarded near it.
|-
|{{anchor|Marnie Stonebrook}}Marnie Stonebrook || [[Fiona Shaw]] || [[True Blood (season 4)|4]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Marnie Stonebrook was the main antagonist of Season 4. Marnie Stonebrook is a local shop-owner and palm-reader, and leader of the Wiccan coven to which Holly Cleary and Jesus Velasquez belong. A timid character, she comes under the influence of the spirit of Antonia, whose great power allows her to raise a bird from the dead. Seeing an apparent necromancer as a threat to vampires, Bill Compton sends Eric Northman to break up the meetings, but Antonia possesses Marnie to cast a spell on him wiping Eric's memories. Marnie is unsure how the spell worked, but attempts to reverse it under pressure from Pam. When Pam, impatient, becomes menacing, Antonia again inhabits Marnie, and casts a spell on Pam, disfiguring her. Marnie's students quickly abandon her as a result. Bill has Marnie captured and imprisoned in his mansion, but she admits while glamored that she has no idea how to reverse either spell. She is then fully taken over by Antonia, who plans to kill all vampires. Tara runs into her walking down a road while waiting for Pam to attack her, and they band together to get revenge on vampires. Antonia gathers the coven of Wiccans to fight against the vampire race. When the battle becomes to extreme, the others want out but she forces them to stay. After the massacre of the Tolerance Festival, Antonia is disheartened by seeing innocent casualties and leaves Marnie's body, but Marnie convinces her to rejoin her as collateral damage is to be expected, revealing a shift in her attitudes. After Marnie cold bloodedly kills a member of the coven Antonia wants out, but Marnie puts a binding spell on her drawing her back in. Jesus performs a ritual to free Antonia's spirit from Marnie. Bill shoots Marnie, killing her. However, Marnie's spirit appears before Lafayette and enters his body. She kills Jesus to steal his power and then tries to burn Eric and Bill at the stake. With the help of Holly, Sookie and Tara, the spirits of Antonia and Adele appear and convince Marnie it is time to leave the realm of the living, which she does.

|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#791422&quot;|
|-
|}

==Past main characters==
{{small|In order of first appearances}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; margin-right:auto; background: #FFFFFF;&quot;
|- style=&quot;color:white&quot;
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:20%&quot;| Name
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:60%&quot;| Actor/actress
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Starring seasons
!style=&quot;background-color:#791422; width:10%&quot;| Recurring seasons
|-
| Adele Stackhouse || [[Lois Smith]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || [[True Blood (season 4)|4]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Adele Stackhouse (née Hale), commonly referred to as &quot;Gran&quot;, is Jason and Sookie's paternal grandmother. Her husband is missing, pressumed dead. A widow living on her own, she raised Jason and Sookie following their parents' death. Sookie keeps living with her after becoming an adult and later inherits Gran's house. She is portrayed as a very kind-hearted, motherly figure, with even Tara Thornton's mother crediting her for raising Tara when she couldn't. She is one of the few characters who supports Sookie's relationship with Bill, and is greatly interested in Bill's historic knowledge of Bon Temps, as she is head of the &quot;Descendants of the Glorious Dead&quot;, an organization devoted to honoring the memory of the Civil War. Mid-season, Adele is brutally killed by Rene Lenier, who originally came to her house to murder Sookie. Adele had a brother, Bartlett Hale ([[Cheyenne Wilbur]]), whose pedophilic affinity for Sookie when she was a child prompted Bill to kill him. At the time he had been disowned by Adele after she too discovered his desires for her granddaughter and the two had apparently not spoken for many years. In the season 4 finale, Adele's spirit appears to take Marnie's spirit out of Lafayette.
|-
| Dawn Green || [[Lynn Collins]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Dawn is Sookie's co-worker, previously in a relationship with Jason. She briefly attempts to rekindle her relationship with him, but after he criticizes her after finding out she slept with a vampire, she forces him out of her house at gunpoint. Shortly thereafter, Sookie discovers her strangled body. It is later confirmed she was murdered by Rene Lenier, who targeted &quot;fangbangers&quot;, women who slept with vampires.
|-
| Lettie Mae Thornton || [[Adina Porter]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Lettie Mae Thornton is Tara's abusive, alcoholic mother. During the first season, she convinces Tara to fund an exorcism to expel a demon that she is convinced lives inside her. She blames the demon for her actions, claiming he targeted her for her closeness with Jesus. Tara reluctantly agrees to pay for Lettie Mae's exorcism, after which Lettie Mae visually and mentally improves and develops into a faithful member of the local Christian community. The woman that performed the exorcism, Miss Jeanette, is exposed as a fraud and later killed by Maryann, but Lettie Mae refuses to believe her exorcism was unreal. In the second season, she assists her gay nephew Lafayette in taking Tara away from Maryann's detrimental influence but is later manipulated by Tara, who wants to go and save Eggs from Maryann, and holds a gun on Lafayette and Sookie while Tara runs to help him. This dissolved the short truce she had with Lafayette who was visibly scared during the experience due to the shock of his torture at the hands of Eric the vampire. In the third season, Lettie Mae is oblivious to a suicide attempt of her daughter as she happily &quot;converses&quot; with the reverend who had come by to speak religiously with Tara. When Tara pays her mother a visit on her way to leave Bon Temps for good, she discovers Lettie Mae is having an affair with her church's married reverend who had previous appeared apprehensive of her subtle advances. In an episode of the fourth season, it's discovered that she's now the reverend's wife. Lettie Mae's sister is Lafayette's mother. She comments to Tara that she pities her for having to raise a sexual deviant, which is the only reference she makes to her sister in the series.
|-
| Steve Newlin || [[Michael McMillian]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]], [[True Blood (season 3)|3]], [[True Blood (season 4)|4]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Reverend Steve Newlin is head of the Fellowship of the Sun, a prominent anti-vampire church that makes regular TV appearances in the True Blood universe, intent on spreading fear and hatred of vampires. He is featured mainly in the second season, as Jason decides to join his church. In the second season, his church holds Eric's maker Godric, who came to them voluntarily, in custody with the intention of burning him to death publicly. When Sookie and Bill start investigating Godric's disappearance, Newlin orders Sookie's abduction, but it fails. Later, when Sookie visits his church in disguise, he recognizes her and locks her in his basement. Godric and the Texas vampires, however, thwart his plans of burning everyone associated with Godric, lecturing him on vampires showing more humanity than Newlin and his humans. In the third season, he makes recurring appearances on television, especially after Russell Edgington slaughters an anchorman on live television and Newlin sees his chance to call for the death of all vampires once again. An earlier interview with Nan Flanagan reveals Newlin was being investigated by the IRS and apparently going through a divorce seen in the postmortem of the episode &quot;I Got a Right to Sing the Blues&quot;. In the fourth season episode &quot;If You Love Me, Why Am I Dyin'?&quot;, it is said that Steve Newlin has been missing for six months. In the final episode of Season 4, it is revealed he has been turned into a vampire.
|-
| Amy Burley || [[Lizzy Caplan]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Amy Burley is Jason's bohemian, V-addicted love interest. Hailing from [[Connecticut]], she meets Jason in vampire bar Fangtasia. After learning he is looking for more V to use, she comes to his house and uses V together with him. She starts a relationship with Jason, who thinks that she might be &quot;the one&quot;, and becomes a waitress at Merlotte's. When she and Jason run out of V, she orchestrates the abduction of one of Lafayette's vampire clients, Eddie Gauthier. It becomes apparent she has experience in kidnapping vampires, implying she is a drainer. She and Jason lock Eddie in their basement, but soon Eddie warns Jason that Amy is a psychopath. Jason disapproves of Amy's cruel treatment of Eddie and attempts to free him, but Amy stakes Eddie in reaction, straining her relationship with Jason. Amy promises she and Jason will do only one last trip of V, but while doing so, she is strangled to death by Rene Lenier.
|-
| Eddie Gauthier || [[Stephen Root]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Eddie Gauthier is the vampire that supplies Lafayette with V during the first season. A middle-aged, overweight gay man, he became a vampire shortly after his marriage with his wife fell apart and he became dire for male attention. He believed becoming a vampire would spark the interest of gay males in him, but seems to spend most of his days at home watching television. He is under the illusion Lafayette is genuinely attracted to him, while Lafayette pretends to want Eddie in order to collect his blood. Jason and his V-addicted girlfriend Amy abduct him so as to use him as a V-reservoir, but as Jason tries to free Eddie, he is staked by Amy. Eddie briefly reappears in the second season, as Jason has a nightmare involving his mixed feelings about vampires. In season four, Lafayette goes to a witch's coven, and their leader, Marnie, contacts Eddie from the dead who then tells Marnie that he has a rose to give to Lafayette. Stunned, Lafayette abruptly leaves.
|-
| &quot;Eggs&quot; Benedict Talley || [[Mehcad Brooks]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]] || [[True Blood (season 1)|1]]
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| &quot;Eggs&quot; Benedict Talley is a guest of Maryann Forrester's who has a less than reputable past; he gradually begins a romantic relationship with Tara Thornton during the second season, but their relationship is constantly manipulated by Maryann. It becomes apparent that Maryann regularly puts Eggs under her influence and then has him perform horrible actions, such as murder and cutting out human hearts. After Maryann's death, he comes to Sookie requesting her aid in regaining his memories of the moments in which Maryann controlled him. Sookie does so, and he remembers murdering several people at Maryann's command. Shocked, he turns himself in to Andy Bellefleur and presents him with the knife the murders were committed with. Jason mistakes this as an attempt to murder Andy and shoots Eggs. His death causes great grief to Tara, but the police force are able to blame him for the murders committed by Maryann.
|-
| Sarah Newlin || [[Anna Camp]] || [[True Blood (season 2)|2]] || -
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot;| Sarah Newlin is the wife of Rev. Steve Newlin. She claims to have originally supported vampire rights, but that she had an epiphany after her fangbanger sister disappeared. She argues with her husband frequently because he will not give her more of a leadership role in the Fellowship of the Sun. She has a strong attraction to Jason Stackhouse, and moves him from the Fellowship camp into her home so that she can be close to him. The two characters have an affair, though their relationship dissolves when her husband realizes that Sookie is his sister, and believes (incorrectly) that Jason is a spy. She disagrees with Steve's methods with regard to starting a vampire war and can be seen openly arguing with him on live television during an interview with Nan Flanagan after the Godric fiasco. 
|-
|colspan=&quot;5&quot; bgcolor=&quot;#791422&quot;|
|-
|}

== Additional characters ==
===Supporting vampire characters===
{{small|In order of first appearances}}

==== Nan Flanagan ====
'''Nan Flanagan''' is the spokesperson for the [[American Vampire League]] and has intermittently been shown being interviewed on televised news programs within the series. She presents a beautiful, unthreatening view of vampires to the human community at large. She denounces acts of violence committed against vampires (especially those perpetrated by the Fellowship of the Sun during the second season) and denies allegations of vampire attacks on humans based on a lack of evidence. Off the air, she is revealed to be much more aggressive and not possessed of particularly lofty ideals. In &quot;I Will Rise Up&quot;, it is implied that she is a high-level bureaucrat within the vampire community, a position that gives her the authority to fire [[#Godric|Godric]]. Although she has power over sheriffs, Sophie-Anne, in &quot;I Got A Right To Sing The Blues&quot;, says that Flanagan and the League have no authority over vampire monarchs. A &quot;documentary&quot; on the fifth disc of the season one DVDs shows pictures of Nan Flanagan with both President Roosevelts (Teddy and Franklin) and possibly appearing in a painting by George Seurat. The season three episode &quot;Everything is Broken&quot;, she conducts an interview with Eric on behalf of the Authority regarding Russell, King of Mississippi. She later issues Eric the Authority's order to go after Russell and kill him. Nan is shown to deal out harsh words and punishments with ease in her mission to make vampires equals with humans. Despite this, she is secretly a hypocrite; after stating out loud that she only drinks True Blood, Nan Flanagan is shown to have a woman in her limousine that she feeds upon. She has a more prominent role in Season 4 as she has elected Bill Compton the Vampire King of Louisiana and the two work together rigorously to restore a positive image of vampires into the minds of humans after Russell created an extremely negative one. During the vampire war against witches, she and Bill become at odds with each other when she appears to be more concerned with their image instead of their survival. She would prefer not to kill any humans to ruin their image while Bill believes that killing the necromancer Marnie/Antonia would better ensure their survival. In the season 4 finale, Nan reveals she knows about Sookie's blood. She also reveals to Bill and Eric that she quit both the AVL and the Authority and is making plans to overthrow the latter. She tries to recruit Bill and Eric and they refuse. When she threatens Sookie, revealing that she's knows what Sookie is, Eric kills her guards while Bill kills Nan herself.

Nan—first appearing in episode 1.01: [[Strange Love (True Blood)|Strange Love]]—is portrayed by [[Jessica Tuck]], and appears as a supporting character during the first three seasons, and as a series regular in season four, of ''True Blood''.

==== Liam, Malcolm, and Diane ====
'''Liam''', '''Malcolm''', and '''Diane''' are vampire acquaintances of Bill Compton who live together in a &quot;nest&quot; (a small coterie of vampires; living together in this way often makes the members more brutal and callous about human life) and come to live in Bon Temps during the first season. They all despise mainstreaming and have no regard for human life. Malcolm is the oldest of the three; indeed, he is older than Bill, and assumes a leadership role in the nest. He likes to party and has a human lover named Jerry. Sookie discovers, telepathically, that Jerry has [[hepatitis D]] and is trying to infect the nest. Liam pays Maudette Pickens a large sum of money to have sex with her, and is videotaped in the act. Diane slept with Bill shortly after she was turned in the 1930s, and has been trying to seduce him ever since. All three vampires are killed in a fire set by Royce Williams and his associates, Chuck and Wayne. Sookie initially thinks Bill was caught in the fire as well. 

Liam, Malcolm and Diane—first appearing in episodes 1.01: [[Strange Love (True Blood)|Strange Love]] (Liam) and 1.02: The First Taste (Malcolm and Diane)—are portrayed by [[Graham Shiels]], [[Andrew Rothenberg]], and [[Aunjanue Ellis]], respectively. They appear as supporting characters during the first season of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Longshadow ====
'''Longshadow''' is the bartender at Fangtasia. In season one, Sookie discovers that he's been stealing money from the bar when she reads the mind of a waitress working there named Ginger. Longshadow glamors Ginger when she discovers what he's been doing. Bill stakes Longshadow in order to save Sookie's life when he attacks her for revealing his treachery, and this murder means that Bill now must be punished by the local vampires. 

Longshadow—first appearing in episode 1.04: Escape from Dragon House—is portrayed by [[Raoul Trujillo]], and appears as a supporting character during the first season of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Chow ====
'''Chow''' is the bartender at the Shreveport Vampire Bar, Fangtasia. Chow is introduced in the series as the new bartender after Longshadow is staked by Bill. When they first meet in season one, Bill admits that he prefers Longshadow after Chow boasts of having a lower [[Par (score)|par]] in a golf video game for [[Wii]]. 

Chow—first appearing in episode 1.09: Plaisir d'Amour—is portrayed by [[Patrick Gallagher (actor)|Patrick Gallagher]], and appears as a supporting character during the first two seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== The Magister ====
'''The Magister''', was a vampire judge who presided over all the vampires of North America. He was from the [[Iberian peninsula]] and was turned during the late ninth century. He was feared because of his political power and advanced age. During the first season, he tried and sentenced Bill for murdering Longshadow, a fellow vampire. As punishment for the crime, he forced Bill to sire Jessica in order to replace the vampire he had killed during a time when their numbers are so important. In season three, he tasked Sophie-Anne and Eric with finding out who was selling vampire blood and their source. Although he was suspicious that they were the actual culprits he nonetheless took their innocence at face value. In episode 7, he was forced by King Russell to officiate the marriage between him and Queen Sophie-Anne. After the deed was done, Russell used The Magister's cane to decapitate him. 

The Magister-first appearing in episode 1.10: I Don't Wanna Know—is portrayed by [[Zeljko Ivanek]], and appears as a supporting character during season one and three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Godric ====
'''Godric ''' was the vampire sheriff of Area 9, a designation for an area that includes Dallas, Texas. Despite being 2,100 years old, he still has the human body of a teenager. He is also covered in tattoos. He is depicted as being friendly toward humans, interested in their well-being, and supportive of a peaceful co-existence between vampires and human beings. Eric Northman claims &quot;there are none above him in the [[New World]]&quot;, referring (erroneously&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Denis O’Hare: Russell’s Older Than Godric |author=Aemac |date=March 22, 2010 |url=http://www.trueblood-news.com/denis-ohare-russells-older-then-godric |accessdate=August 10, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;) to the physical power he has accumulated as one of the oldest vampires in the Americas. He and Eric investigated Nazi Germany's use of werewolves in [[World War II]].

When he goes missing, Eric sends [[Sookie Stackhouse]] and [[#Hugo Ayers|Hugo]] to the Dallas area to look for him. It is discovered that he is being held prisoner by the Fellowship of the Sun for a ritual execution. While infiltrating the Fellowship, Sookie is captured and attacked by one of their members, Gabe. As Gabe is attempting to rape Sookie, Godric appears and rescues her by breaking Gabe's neck. Conflict at the Fellowship comes to a head with a standoff between the Fellowship members and a vampire force led by Stan (one of Godric's lieutenants). Godric is able to defuse the incident without bloodshed. However, the Fellowship retaliates by sending a suicide bomber to his home, destroying three vampires and killing two human companions.

When asked how a vampire as powerful as he is could have been captured by humans, Godric reveals that he was taken into their custody willingly, believing that allowing himself to be killed by anti-vampire fanatics will bring about some sort of reconciliation, and atonement for his many crimes against humans during his long life. He takes the blame for what [[#Nan Flanagan|Nan Flanagan]] describes as a &quot;PR disaster&quot;, as well as for the deaths from the bombing. He resigns as sheriff at her recommendation. After such a long life, Godric finds himself weary of his existence and saddened that humans and vampires refuse to work together and coexist, so decides he has been alive long enough. As his maker, Godric is greatly loved and revered by Eric, who begs him not to kill himself&amp;mdash;to no avail. He &quot;meets the sun&quot; at dawn on the roof of the Hotel Carmilla, surprised and inspired by the fact that a &quot;human&quot;, [[Sookie Stackhouse]], would accompany him and shed tears at his end.

In the season three finale, Godric's spirit apparently appears to Eric and tries to get him to embrace peace and forgiveness during his battle with Russell. He expresses his sadness at Eric's actions when he and Bill bury Russell alive, rather than allow Russell the peace that true death would bring.

When he was in Scandinavia, he watched [[Eric Northman]] fight in battle skillfully. After the battle he killed Eric's two surviving comrades and offered the mortally wounded Viking a chance to become a vampire.

Godric—first appearing in episode 2.05: Never Let Me Go—is portrayed by [[Allan Hyde]], and appears as a supporting character during seasons two, three, and four&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tvline.com/2011/02/true-blood-exclusive-look-whos-returning/|title=''True Blood'' Exclusive: Look Who's Returning!|work=TV Line|last=Ausiello|first=Michael|date=February 24, 2011|accessdate=February 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Isabel ====
'''Isabel Beaumont''' is a lieutenant of Godric's introduced during the second season. She and Stan bicker constantly throughout the investigation in Dallas, much to Eric's frustration. At one point, Stan mentions that she has been working for Godric for forty years. She has a human boyfriend, Hugo, who accompanies Sookie when she infiltrates the Fellowship of the Sun, but is revealed to be a traitor to the vampires. In a conversation with Eric, she describes her interest in Hugo as being like &quot;a science experiment&quot;, however even after the discovery of Hugo's treachery she admits to still loving him (prompting Godric to reduce his punishment from execution to banishment). During a meeting with Nan Flanagan that results in Godric's resignation, he recommends that Isabel take his position as the sheriff of Area Nine. Whether or not she becomes Godric's replacement after his suicide is unclear. Her appearance in &quot;I Will Rise Up&quot; suggests that she does not follow Hugo into exile.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hbo.com/#/true-blood/episodes/2/21-i-will-rise-up/synopsis.html|title=True Blood Episode 2.09: I Will Rise Up—Synopsis|work=HBO|accessdate=April 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sookie phones her while she is looking for Bill, suggesting that she is still in Dallas. 

Isabel—first appearing in episode 2.05: Never Let Me Go—is portrayed by [[Valerie Cruz]], and appears as a supporting character during season two of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Stan Baker ====
'''Stan Baker''' is Godric's lieutenant in Texas. He is opposed to vampires &quot;coming out of the coffin&quot;, and wants to kill the members of the Fellowship of the Sun. Despite his high position under Godric's rule of Area 9, his brash, unrepentant attitude and his opinion that humans are no more than food made him untrustworthy in the eyes of most other vampires. His age is unknown but it's implied that he was turned during the Middle Ages. According to Isabel, he was killed in the explosion caused by Luke in Godric's nest. 

Stan—first appearing in episode 2.05: Never Let Me Go—is portrayed by [[Ed Quinn]], and appears as a supporting character during season two of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

====Sophie-Anne Leclerq====
'''Sophie-Anne Leclerq''' was the Vampire Queen of Louisiana, a 500 year old vampire. She commands Eric to make Lafayette sell V in order to keep her fortune from running out, despite vampire taboos against humans drinking their blood, and against the V trade in general. Her human lover, Hadley, is Sookie's cousin. She is seen as very cold and unforgiving and also having the personality of a spoiled child. But she is very powerful and full of useful information about supernatural creatures. Sophie-Anne is forced in to a marriage of convenience with Russell Edgington who wishes to possess her territory. Hadley informs Sophie-Anne of Sookie's ability at some point before the series and she subsequently sent Bill Compton to Bon Temps to seduce her and procure her for Sophie-Anne. In doing this, Bill allowed the Rattrays to beat Sookie within an inch of her life so Bill can feed her his blood. When Sookie angrily throws Bill out after discovering this, he blames Sophie-Anne. He lures the Queen to his home and tells her only one of them will leave alive. The pair fight briefly, only for Bill to reveal armed forces who were hiding inside the house the entire time. After calling him a traitor, Sophie-Anne is violently gunned down and killed with wooden bullets by the armed forces who are revealed to be Nan Flanagan's. Flanagan thanks Bill for his cooperation, and it is shown that Sophie-Anne's death was a part of a deal made between Nan and Bill, whom she makes the Vampire King of Louisiana.

Sophie-Anne—first appearing in episode 2.11: Frenzy—is portrayed by [[Evan Rachel Wood]], and appears as a supporting character from the end of season two until her true death in early season four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Talbot ====
'''Talbot''' is Russell Edgington's consort, turned by him some 700 years ago in his native [[Greece]]. He is seen to be very sensitive, taking interruptions to his carefully planned dinners and damage to his mansion very personally. During the episodes we can hear Talbot speaking Greek. Talbot has a liking for Eric Northman and seems to be totally uninterested in Russell's political plans. Eventually, his anger over Russell's antics reaches a boiling point and he breaks several of the artifacts Russell has collected over the centuries. Eric agrees to spend time with him while Russell is out of town to calm him down. However, once they are alone Eric seduces him and stakes Talbot from behind, killing him. Russell, unhinged by Talbot's death, had his remains placed in a glass jar which he took with him wherever he went. In the season 3 finale, Sookie takes Talbot's remains and pours them down the sink, torturing Russell by turning on the garbage disposal as she does.

Talbot—first appearing in episode 3.02: Beautifully Broken—is portrayed by [[Theo Alexander]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Franklin Mott ====
'''Franklin Mott''' was a British vampire who worked for Russell Edgington as an investigator. He was first seen entering Merlotte's and having a one-night stand with Tara. He then revealed his true colors when he blackmailed Jessica into telling him all she knew about Bill. He then bit and tied up Tara and took her to Russell's mansion. He was emotionally unstable and wanted Tara to become his vampire bride. In order for Tara to escape and find Sookie, she mercilessly bludgeoned him using a medieval [[morning star (weapon)|morning star]]. Despite his injuries, which included a crushed skull, he survived. In the episode &quot;Everything is Broken&quot;, Franklin found Tara in the parking lot of Merlotte's. While he was choking her, Jason shot him in the heart with a wooden bullet, granting him the true death at last.

Franklin—first appeared in episode 3.02: Beautifully Broken — was portrayed by [[James Frain]], and appeared as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

===Additional characters, introduced in season 1===
{{small|In order of first appearances}}

==== Mike Spencer ====
'''Mike Spencer''' is both the town coroner and the director of the local funeral home; he presided over the burial of Sookie's parents when she was a child. During the second season he becomes a frequent participant in Maryann's orgies. 

Mike—first appearing in episode 1.02: The First Taste—is portrayed by [[John Billingsley]], and appears as a supporting character during the first three seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Jane Bodehouse ====
'''Jane Bodehouse''' is a middle-aged alcoholic woman with a grown son who is a regular at Merlotte's and a frequently featured minor character, first introduced in the first season. In one of her earliest appearances, Tara Thornton explains that her [[modus operandi]] is to arrive at Merlotte's, become intoxicated, wait for someone to approach her, and then hit on them when they offer to drive her home. She is one of the many Bon Temps residents that fall under Maryann's influence in season two. The staff at Merlotte's frequently must call her son to take her home. While under Maryann's influence she becomes even more giddy and excitable than usual, engaging in frequent sexual acts and she cut off her own finger to place on the meat tree offering to Dionysus. She later found her finger and it was surgically reattached.
Jane—first appearing in episode 1.02: The First Taste—is portrayed by [[Patricia Bethune]], and appears as a supporting character during the first two seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== David Finch ====
'''David Finch''' (alias &quot;Duke Smith&quot;) is a leading right-wing politician. In the third season he returned, having been elected a congressman, as a TV debate opponent of Nan Flanagan. In spite of his anti-vampire and anti-gay politics, he is both [[Closeted|secretly homosexual]] and a user of V, which he buys from Lafayette.

David—first appearing in episode 1.03: Mine—is portrayed by [[John Prosky]], and appears as a supporting character during season one and three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Maxine Fortenberry ====
'''Maxine Fortenberry''' is a resident of Bon Temps and the mother of Hoyt Fortenberry. She's characterized by her over-protective and possessive relationship with her son and (despite his age) treats him as though he's a child. She is threatened by any other women in his life, and he still lives at home with her despite being in his late 20s. In the first season, she appears to be open-minded toward vampires: she is concerned that Bill Compton will be injured in the presence of a cross and wants to have her picture taken with him. In the second season, when Hoyt introduces her to Jessica Hamby, she becomes vociferously resentful of vampires. When she first meets Jessica, she blatantly tells her that she disapproves of her son having a relationship with a vampire. Maxine is among the many residents of Bon Temps that fall under Maryann's influence. While possessed, she reveals to Hoyt that his father's death was actually a suicide and she fraudulently claimed he was killed fighting a robber in order to collect the insurance. She is also said to be racist towards [[African-Americans]], though she wants this kept secret. In the third season episode 'Fresh Blood&quot;, its is revealed that Maxine pushed the girl Summer to date Hoyt to make him forget Jessica. Despite Hoyt's reunion with Jessica, Maxine is determined to get Hoyt and Summer together. Maxine and Summer try in vain to change Hoyt's mind. Maxine is later seen at a gun store buying a rifle. It is revealed in season 4 that Maxine had attempted to kill Jessica; however she failed due to her poor aim.

Maxine—first appearing in episode 1.04: Escape From Dragon House—is portrayed by [[Dale Raoul]], and appears as a supporting character during the first four seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Kevin Ellis ====
'''Kevin Ellis''' is a deputy sheriff in Bon Temps and a minor character that first appears during the investigation of Dawn Green's murder in the first season. He also appears during the second season as one of the many residents of Bon Temp under Maryann's influence. In season three, Kevin is attacked when responding to a distress call in the middle of the night and almost killed. Jason and Crystal know that the person who attacked Kevin is Crystal's fiance from Hot Shot. 

Kevin—first appearing in episode 1.04: Escape From Dragon House—is portrayed by [[John Resig]], and appears as a supporting character during the first three seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Lisa &amp; Coby Fowler ====
'''Lisa''' and '''Coby''' are Arlene's preteen children, from before meeting René. Appearing recurrently during the first two seasons, they are notably only referred to during season three, with Terry now acting as the children's father. 

Lisa and Coby—first appearing in episode 1.05: Sparks Fly Out—are portrayed by [[Laurel Weber]] and [[Alec Gray (actor)|Alec Gray]], respectively. They appear as supporting characters during season one, two and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Royce Williams ====
'''Royce Williams''' is a Bon Temps local who, along with two friends, burns down the house where Diane, Malcolm, and Liam live, also killing their human guest, Neil Jones, in the process. Royce and his friends, Chuck and Wayne, not only have an open distaste for vampires but send back food prepared by Lafayette Reynolds at Merlotte's (implying that they'll catch [[AIDS]] if they eat it because he's gay). He is captured by Eric Northman for killing the three vampires. While being held captive at Fangtasia, he confesses to Lafayette that he's been a screw-up most of his life. The sordid escapades he details include a sexual adventure with one of his cousins' girlfriends and a homosexual encounter in camp. During an escape attempt, he is torn apart and partially devoured by Eric as retaliation for attacking him with silver. After death, he provides important assistance to Lafayette, who uses the metal implant in Royce's femur to break his chains. 

Royce is portrayed by [[Caleb Moody]]- first appearing in episode 1.05: Sparks Fly Out—and appears as a supporting character during the first two seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Miss Jeanette ====
'''Nancy LeVoir''' is first introduced in season one as '''Miss Jeanette'''; she works as a drugstore clerk but also performs fake exorcisms on the side to support her family. Her body is discovered at the end of the last episode of season one in Andy Bellefleur's car. In the first episode of season two, it's revealed her heart has been cut out (something that becomes a trademark of Maryann's throughout the season). In a later episode, it's explained that (as a maenad) Maryann attacks supernatural beings to offer their heart to [[Dionysus]]. Thinking that Miss Jeanette is genuinely supernatural in nature, Maryann removes the woman's heart in the hopes that it will lure the god to her. When her body is examined, she's shown to have the same scratches on her back as Sookie and Daphne; another signature of Maryann's. 

Miss Jeanette—first appearing in episode 1.07: Burning House of Love—is portrayed by [[Aisha Hinds]], and appears as a supporting character during the first two seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Ginger ====
'''Ginger''' is one of the human employees working at Fangtasia and first appears in the final episodes of season one. She is known for her shrill, and frequent, screaming. During Sookie's telepathic investigation at Fangtasia, when Eric enlists her to help identify who is stealing money from the bar, Ginger is introduced as the last human employee (though her exact job title is never provided). By reading Ginger's repeatedly glamored mind, Sookie is able to learn that a vampire is responsible, prompting Longshadow to attack. Bill kills Longshadow to prevent him from harming Sookie, and Ginger is traumatized from having to watch. Pam reluctantly glamors her again to solve the problem, deciding that further deterioration of her mind is preferable to transforming her into a vampire to ensure her silence. Ginger continues to work at Fangtasia in season two, but her vapid, emotional nature makes her unreliable. She tells Sookie the location of Lafayette when held at gunpoint by her in Episode 3 and lets Sam Merlotte, Lisa and Colby Fowler into Fangtasia before dark after Sam bribes her in Episode 11. In season four, she is showing a large measure of loyalty and caring towards Pam as she holds Pam in her coffin during Antonia's spell, and later she comforts Pam during a bout of jealous despair, even when told not to. 

Ginger—first appearing in episode 1.08: The Fourth Man in the Fire—is portrayed by [[Tara Buck]], and appears as a supporting character in all four seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Kenya Jones ====
'''Kenya Jones''' is introduced during the first season; she works as a sheriff's deputy on the Bon Temps Police Department. The character first appears when she is called to the scene of Tara's car accident and arrests her for [[driving under the influence]]. She appears to be familiar with both Lettie Mae Thornton and Maryann, as well as Tara. Kenya appears to show a dislike towards Andy Bellefleur and begins working more closely with Sheriff Dearborne when Andy is removed from the force. In Season 3 she is shown to be frustrated when Andy is made sheriff and disapproves when he allows Jason Stackhouse to work in the police department. 

Kenya—first appearing in episode 1.11: To Love Is to Bury—is portrayed by [[Tanya Wright]], and appears as a supporting character during the first three seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Rosie ====
'''Rosie''' is the somewhat whimsical receptionist of the Bon Temps Police Station. After Deputy Kevin Ellis is nearly killed in duty in season three, Rosie admits to Andy and Jason to be deeply in love with him. 

Rosie—first appearing in episode 1.11: To Love Is to Bury—is portrayed by [[Tess Alexandra Parker]], and appears as a supporting character during the first three seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Karl ====
'''Karl''' is Maryann's assistant and serves her as an all-purpose [[domestic worker]]. Making his first appearance in the last episode of season one, he functions as a cook, chauffeur, house keeper, and masseur at various points during season two. Karl serves Maryann and her guests without complaint, speaking infrequently in general. He seems to knowingly help in the coordination of Maryann's bacchanalia, but he neither participates nor shows visible signs of possession. At the end of the second season, Lafayette Reynolds tries to shoot Maryann, but she deflects the bullet and it goes into Karl's head. Maryann only shows the most momentary pause at the death of her companion and her role in it, remarking that he &quot;never made it far in this lifetime&quot;. 

Karl—first appearing in episode 1.12: You'll Be the Death of Me—is portrayed by [[Adam Leadbeater]], and appears as a supporting character during the first two seasons of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

===Additional characters, introduced in season 2===
{{small|In order of first appearances}}

==== Daphne Landry ====
'''Daphne Landry''' is a waitress hired at Merlotte's when Sookie Stackhouse leaves for Dallas in season two. She claims to have some experience working at the [[Cracker Barrel]] in [[Alexandria, Louisiana]] during her interview, though (despite an obvious effort) she proves to be consistently inept in accomplishing what's expected of her as a waitress. She is shown to have strange claw marks on her back that are eventually revealed to be a trademark of Maryann Forrester's; the marks are also found on Miss Jeanette's corpse and inflicted on Sookie early in season two. After tentatively flirting with Sam Merlotte, she reveals that not only does she know that he's a shapeshifter, but that she's a shapeshifter as well. The two begin a romance soon after, but when Daphne lures Sam to one of Maryann's [[bacchanalia]], it becomes clear that their relationship was all a plan to trap Sam for her mistress. As Daphne is unable to secure Sam as a sacrifice, a possessed &quot;Eggs&quot; Talley carves out her heart at Maryann's command instead. 

Daphne—first appearing in episode 2.01: Nothing But the Blood—is portrayed by [[Ashley Jones]], and appears as a supporting character during season two of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Luke McDonald ====
'''Luke McDonald''' is a member of the Fellowship of the Sun depicted as a friend, enemy, and rival of Jason Stackhouse at different points of the second season. Growing up in Odessa, Texas, he signs up to join a training camp for the Fellowship of the Sun (an anti-vampire church) when a knee injury prevents him from joining the military or maintaining a college football scholarship. On the bus ride there, he bonds with Jason Stackhouse, though he later becomes jealous of the amount of attention Jason receives. At camp, Luke tells Jason that the only reason that Sarah likes him is because she wants to sleep with him, making his resentment clear to everyone. Luke is eventually selected to join the Soldiers of the Sun, though his initial performance is poor due to his attempts at out-pacing Jason. Though a bitter animosity grows between the two characters, they make amends when Jason helps Luke climb over a fence he is too exhausted to scale.

After the confrontation between Stan's vampires and the Fellowship, it initially appears that Luke has left his position with the Soldiers of the Sun. Later, at Godric's gathering, he arrives with a silver bomb strapped to his chest. After detonating the bomb, he's killed in the explosion along with (according to Isabel) three vampires and two human companions. The character was part of various interactive internet campaigns related to the show; including a fictional [http://fellowshipofthesun.org/sos/ blog] and [http://www.youtube.com/user/TheLukenatorTX YouTube channel]. 

Luke—first appearing in episode 2.02: Keep This Party Going—is portrayed by actor Wes Brown (not to be confused with English footballer, [[Wes Brown]]), and appears as a supporting character during season two of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Barry Horowitz ====
'''Barry Horowitz''' is a bellboy at the Dallas vampire hotel, the Hotel Carmilla, in the second season. Sookie discovers that he is also a telepath. He is terrified of anyone learning that he is a telepath, and refuses to communicate with her. Nevertheless, when Sookie calls for his help telepathically when the Fellowship of the Sun captures her, he does help her. Lorena briefly feeds from Barry, stopping when she realizes that his blood tastes different from other humans. This distracts Lorena long enough for Bill to attack her and knock her unconscious with a plasma television. Bill then helps Barry escape. Barry briefly appears in Episode 1 of Season 4 in Fae, the magical world of the faeries, with his faery god-father, eating a magical glowing fruit. 

Barry—first appearing in episode 2.04: Shake and Fingerpop—is portrayed by [[Chris Coy]], and appears as a supporting character during season two and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Gabe ====
'''Gabe''' is a mercenary who helps train and lead the Soldiers of the Sun, Rev. Steve Newlin's secret, paramilitary unit of the Fellowship of the Sun. Appearing in the second season of ''True Blood'', he is characterized by the typical abhorrence of vampires common amongst Fellowship members. After Hugo informs Rev. Newlin that he and Sookie Stackhouse are being sent to infiltrate the Fellowship, Gabe helps Rev. Newlin kidnap and imprison the two of them in the church basement, where they are also keeping vampires and a vampire-fighting arsenal. Once Rev. Newlin learns that Jason (a Fellowship member at the time) and Sookie are siblings, he and Gabe apprehend Jason. Gabe is left to execute Jason for his betrayal, but Jason overpowers him and escapes. Enraged, Gabe returns to the church, and tries to rape Sookie. Before he succeeds, Godric appears and breaks his neck. 

Gabe—first appearing in episode 2.05: Never Let Me Go—is portrayed by [[Greg Collins (actor)|Greg Collins]], and appears as a supporting character during season two of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Hadley Hale ====
'''Hadley Hale''' is the cousin of Sookie and Jason Stackhouse and one of Queen Sophie-Anne's human lovers. Hadley is first mentioned during &quot;Cold Ground&quot; in season one, when the residents of Bon Temps are visiting Sookie's home to offer their condolences for the recently murdered Adele &quot;Gran&quot; Stackhouse. Tara Thornton asks Sookie whether she should contact Hadley, and Sookie responds that after leaving a [[Drug rehabilitation|rehabilitation clinic]] that Gran paid for, no one has heard from Hadley or knows where she is. She makes her debut in the series during the second season episode &quot;Frenzy&quot;, when Bill Compton visits Sophie-Anne, the vampire queen of Louisiana. Hadley is a member of Sophie-Anne's retinue of human companions, and is often in her mistress' company. When Sophie-Anne leaves Bill momentarily, Hadley asks him how Sookie and Gran are doing. Though she is still interested in her past amongst human beings, she's aware that there is no way she can return from the vampire world she is now a part of. In the third season Sophie-Anne is shown to be very concerned for Hadley's safety when King Russell Edgington and Eric Northman break into her house. The Queen worriedly yells Hadley's name and asks to be reunited with her in her imprisonment, thus revealing that Hadley is the human lover and companion of Sophie-Anne. She was the one who revealed Sookie's gift to Sophie-Anne, sparking the queen's interest in her. Eric later uses Hadley to get information about Sookie from Sophie-Anne. After Sophie-Anne stays silent, a scared and injured Hadley tells Eric what he wants to know and by doing so, saves her own life. Eric uses her again when he catches her leaving Sophie-Anne's bedroom and orders her to deliver a message to Sookie. In episode 9 of season three, it’s revealed that Hadley has a young son (about 8 years old) named Hunter. Hunter, like his mother's cousin Sookie, is telepathic. 

Hadley—first appearing in episode 2.11: Frenzy—is portrayed by [[Lindsey Haun]], and appears as a supporting character during season two and three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

===Additional characters, introduced in season 3===
{{small|In order of first appearances}}

==== Yvetta ====
'''Yvetta''' is the new exotic dancer of Fangtasia in season three. Initially enjoying the attention of Eric, as much that she eventually gets to think he actually cares for her, she is eventually hit with the realization that she is of no interest at all to him. In retaliation for his callous attitude, she saves Sookie from captivity, and cleans out the bar's safe. Though thought of as an uneducated immigrant by Pam, Yvetta reveals that in her native country, [[Estonia]], she was a cardiologist.

Yvetta—first appearing in episode 3.01: Bad Blood—is portrayed by [[Natasha Alam]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''. Her very first appearance was in the first of the 2010 ''True Blood'' minisodes.
{{-}}

==== Coot ====
'''Coot''' is the leader of his werewolf pack that were responsible for kidnapping Bill Compton at Russell Edgington's request. He is engaged to Debbie, Alcide's ex-girlfriend. He is seen as immature, wild, and crazy. In episode 7, he is shot twice by Alcide, and dies. 

Coot—first appearing in episode 3.01: Bad Blood—is portrayed by [[Grant Bowler]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Gus ====
Werewolf '''Gus''' is a member of Coot's pack, until killed by Jessica whilst leading an attack on her and Bill, on orders from Russell. 

Gus—first appearing in episode 3.01: Bad Blood—is portrayed by [[Don Swayze]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Melinda Mickens ====
'''Melinda Mickens''' is Sam's biological mother, who gave him up for adoption. She is also the mother of Tommy, and the wife of Joe Lee. She is seen as a poor mother, who tries to use Sam to get things from him. She is a shifter, like her sons. It is revealed that she is scared to leave Joe Lee, since it is him that had previously pushed her into dogfighting for money and now she expects Tommy to do the same because she is too old. She apparently dies at Tommy's hand while trying to come between Tommy and Joe Lee as they fight

Melinda—first appearing in episode 3.02: Beautifully Broken—is portrayed by [[J. Smith-Cameron]], and appears as a supporting character during season three and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Joe Lee Mickens ====
'''Joe Lee Mickens''' is Sam's biological father, who was serving time in jail when Sam was born. He is also the father of Tommy, and husband to Melinda. He tries to use Sam for money while pretending to be a caring father. He tries to hide from Sam the fact that he forces Tommy in to dogfights in order to make money. He dies at Tommy's hand after Joe Lee tries to recapture Tommy and make him fight again in the 4th season.

Joe Lee—first appearing in episode 3.02: Beautifully Broken—is portrayed by [[Cooper Huckabee]], and appears as a supporting character during season three and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Calvin Norris ====
'''Calvin Norris''' is the head of the inbred Norris clan, managing the family's drug business. He strongly opposes the budding relationship between his daughter, Crystal, and Jason Stackhouse, demanding that Crystal marry her brother/cousin Felton. He is shot dead by Felton, moments prior to the DEA's attack on their home. 

Calvin — first appearing in episode 3.02: Beautifully Broken — is portrayed by [[Gregory Sporleder]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

==== Debbie Pelt ====
'''Debbie Pelt''' is a werewolf and Alcide's ex-girlfriend. After breaking up with Alcide, she becomes engaged to Coot. While Sookie becomes convinced it is possible to reunite Alcide and Debbie, Debbie becomes a member of Coot's pack in a bizarre initiation ceremony. At this ceremony, Sookie and Alcide discover Russell Edgington, a vampire who employs werewolves to carry out missions for him, supplies this pack with V. Later on, in episode 6, Debbie and Coot feed on Bill Compton's blood after Bill is tortured by Lorena. After Sookie, Tara and Alcide free Bill in episode 7, Debbie reappears and threatens to kill Sookie, but is stopped by Tara. When Coot enters the scene, Alcide fatally shoots him , causing Debbie to vow vengeance upon Alcide. 
After burning down a hair salon operated by Alcide's sister, Debbie leads a werewolf attack on Sookie's house at Russell's orders. While Bill and Jessica fight off the werewolves, Debbie personally confronts Sookie and the two become entangled in a brutal fight. After Sookie scars Debbie with a pair of scissors, she forces Debbie out of her house with a shotgun. In season 4 she has rekindled her relationship with Alcide and living with him, sober and reformed. However, their renewed relationship hits a few bumps as Debbie has different desires from Alcide and also suspects him of having feelings for Sookie. She almost leaves Alcide for her new pack master Marcus, but Alcide arrives and kills him before breaking up with Debbie.
In the last episode of season 4 Debbie, having being Abjured by Alcide, turns up in Sookies house with a shotgun and attempts to shoot Sookie. She shoots Tara in the side of the head after Tara pushed Sookie out of the way, and in retaliation Sookie kills Debbie while Debbie begs for her life on the floor. It is currently unknown if Tara survived.

Debbie—first appearing in episode 3.04: 9 Crimes—is portrayed by [[Brit Morgan]], and appears as a supporting character during season three and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

====Felton Norris====
'''Felton Norris''' is Crystal's brutal brother/cousin/fiancée, and a front-man in the Norris family drug business. He is violent and frequently beats Crystal when she strays from him. Just before the DEA raid the town Felton reveals he is addicted to V. In the season three finale, he forces Crystal to leave town with him, after shooting their father. He is seen again in Episode 2 of Season 4 when it is revealed he and Crystal have kidnapped Jason in order to turn him into a were-panther. He is ambushed and killed by Jason while trying to recapture Jason after Jason escapes the bed that the Hotshot were-panthers tied him to in an effort to add new bloodlines to the in-bred Hotshot community.

Felton—first appearing in episode 3.04: 9 Crimes—is portrayed by [[James Harvey Ward]], and appears as a supporting character during season three and four of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

====Summer====
'''Summer''' is the sweet girl-next-door who has had a crush on Hoyt for a long time. After his breakup with Jessica, she, with help from Maxine, becomes his new girlfriend. She is shown to be opposed to vampires, hence attaining Maxine's approval. Eventually she has her heart crushed when Hoyt returns to Jessica. She has a very upbeat talkative personality, loving dolls and show tunes and talking constantly. Hoyt finds it hard to stand her but admits that it is better than being alone. It is something of a visual gag that Summer at 5&quot;0&quot; is nearly a foot and half shorter than the 6&quot;5&quot; Hoyt.

Summer—first appearing in episode 3.05: Troubles—is portrayed by [[Melissa Rauch]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood''.
{{-}}

====Holly Cleary====
'''Holly Cleary''' is hired as a waitress at Merlotte's in the third season. She is very friendly and helps Tara and Arlene throughout Season 3. She reveals herself as a victim of a brutal rape from years before and a single mother of two. She is also a devoted [[Wicca]]n. When Arlene decides that she doesn't want her baby, but cannot morally abort it, Holly performs a Wiccan ceremony which, if carried out correctly, should lead to Arlene miscarrying. In season 4, it is revealed that she is one of Marnie's students and a member of her coven. After the incident with Eric, while she still is a waitress at Merlotte's, Sookie reads her mind and finds out that she has abandoned Marnie's witch coven for her and her sons' safety. She then begins to date Andy Bellefleur in episode 6 of Season 4. 

Holly—first appearing in episode 3.08: Night on the Sun—is portrayed by [[Lauren Bowles]], and appears as a supporting character during season three of ''True Blood'' and a main character during season 4. 
{{-}}

====Russell Edgington====
Possibly the oldest vampire in existence, Russell is 2800 years old. He was born into a Celtic tribe. He is almost 3 times older than Eric Northman, and 700 years older than Eric's maker, Godric. He was far stronger and faster than Erik, Bill or the Magister. Like Erik, Russell was capable of flying. It is implied that during WWII he allied himself with the Nazis; he tells Erik that, &quot;Adolf was right about one thing: there is a Master Race. It's just not the '''human''' race.&quot; He was King of Mississippi. Last seen at the end of Season 3, he was bound in silver and entombed alive in cement at the hands of Bill Compton and Eric Northman. Russell Edgington killed Eric Northman's father, mother, and baby sister with the help of werewolves. Eric exacted revenge by staking Russell's royal consort, Talbot. Russell went mad and killed a news anchor on live television by removing part of his spine, sparking an anti-vampire movement which can be seen throughout Season 4. In the Season 4 finale it is discovered that the parking garage under which Russell was buried has been dug up and the remains of a silver chain is found, implying that he has escaped.

====Claudine====
Claudine was a fairy first introduced in &quot;Hitting the Ground&quot;. She had stated that she, and others like her, had protected and, on occasion, saved Sookie from danger. 
When Sookie is comatose after being drained by Bill, she meets Claudine in a dream. Claudine gives her glowing water to drink and asks her if she wants to come to her &quot;home&quot;. As the portal to her is a pond, Sookie is afraid to enter as she does not know how to swim. Sookie hears in Claudine's thoughts that &quot;the water did not kill them&quot;. This implies that Claudine knows how Sookie's and Jason's parents died. When Bill comes to Sookie's hospital bed, night comes to the dream realm. The other Fairies in the dream enter the pond and Claudine warns Sookie to not let 'him' take her &quot;light&quot;. (&quot;Hitting the Ground&quot;) 
A few days later, Bill enters the dream realm Sookie had visited. There he is met by Claudine, who first thinks that he has killed Sookie. After a short chase Bill pins Claudine down, but seems unable to control himself. Before he can feed on her, Claudine uses the same light power Sookie is capable of, and throws him a few meters away. Bill convinces Claudine that Sookie is alive and he would never harm her, and also pleads to Claudine to reveal the true nature of what Sookie and Claudine are, so that Sookie can protect herself. (&quot;Everything Is Broken&quot;)

The next night when Sookie visits her grandmother's grave, Claudine and other faes appear to her. Claudine tells Sookie she is not alone and she should come with them. Sookie holds out a glowing hand to Claudine and the two women disappears along with the other fairies. (&quot;Evil is Going On&quot;)

Claudine magically transports Sookie to her home dimension, known as Faery. Sookie inquires if Claudine is head of the fairies. Claudine laughs this off and tells Sookie she is actually her fairy godmother. Sookie snipes that she didn't do a very good job to which Claudine replies &quot;You're still alive aren't you?&quot; Claudine then leaves Sookie so she can go and mingle with the other fairies and recently transported part fairies such as old acquaintance Barry and her grandfather Earl.

When Sookie realizes that Faery is a trap for the part humans, she is confronted by queen of the fairies, Mab. As Mab tries to force feed Sookie a Lumiere fruit in order to magically manipulate Sookie into seeing Faery as a bright, peaceful place, Claudine looks on guiltily. When Sookie accidentally uses her powers to uncover the true barren world of Faery and the true, grotesque face of the fairies to all those around; Sookie and Earl try to find a way of escaping Faery and its malevolent inhabitants. As Sookie runs off, a distressed Claudine calls out for her until she is ordered by Mab to go after them. (&quot;She's Not There&quot;)

Claudine arrives at Sookie's front porch and demands that Sookie come with her back to Fairy Land. She tells Sookie about the times she helped save her life, however Sookie replies with a no. In a flash, Eric Northman captures Claudine and begins to feed from her. With amnesia, Eric doesn't know how to stop drinking her blood. He kills her, making her true form appear and to lose her light, thus disappearing in thin dust. (&quot;If You Love Me, Why Am I Dyin'?&quot;)

===Additional characters, introduced in season 4===
====Antonia Gavilán de Logroño====
Antonia was a powerful witch that originally lived in northern Spain (specifically, in the city of [[Logroño]]) during the latter portion of the sixteenth century. In 1610, at the height of the [[Spanish Inquisition]].  She became a necromancer in order to save her village from fever, not only as healer she as well served as a midwife. Later Antonia was fed on by vampires hiding out as priests within the local Catholic church, raped by the vampire Luis (now one of Bill's sheriffs in Louisiana) at his maker's behest, burned at stake and killed. As she was being burned, she and her fellow witches cast a spell that brought all vampires within 20 miles of Logroño out of ground and into the sun, destroying them, an act that she replicates in Bontemps four centuries later, after inhabiting Marnie's body inside Bill's compound. She eventually becomes disheartened over the collateral damage done in her war against the vampires and leaves Marnie's body. Marnie, however, convinces Antonia to re-bond with Marnie, as the latter wishes to continue the war, with Antonia as her source of power. After Marnie kills a member of their coven, Antonia sees that Marnie has become evil and leaves her body, but Marnie puts a binding spell on her and draws her back in. Antonia is finally freed from Marnie by Jesus, and all the spells she has performed have been broken. She is portrayed by [[Paola Turbay]] and Fiona Shaw (when possessing Marnie).
In the last episode of season 4 Antonia returns once more to Marnie to ease her passage to the afterlife and comfort and forgive her.

====Portia Bellefleur====
'''Portia Bellefleur''' is Andy Bellefleur's sister, and a successful attorney. She has business dealings with Bill Compton, which develop into a sexual relationship. Bill breaks the relationship off when he discovers that Portia is one of his descendants, which he considers incestuous. Portia was far more reluctant to end the relationship, so Bill glamours her into being afraid of him. 

Portia first appeared in episode 4.1: She's Not There-and is portrayed by [[Courtney Ford]].

====Don Bartolo====
Don Bartolo is the grandfather to Jesus, and a brujo or shaman, who lives in Mexico. Don Bartolo attempted to teach Jesus the ways of being a brujo, but Jesus' mother would not allow it, and Jesus was never allowed to see his grandfather again. Don Bartolo is first shown in flashback, when Jesus was a young boy. Seen later in current times, he is older, grayer, yet still a mysterious force to be dealt with. 

Don Bartolo first appears in episode 4.5: Me and the Devil, then appears in episode 4.6: I Wish I Was the Moon &amp; episode 4.7: Cold Grey Light of Dawn. Don Bartolo is portrayed by veteran actor [[Del Zamora]].

====Luna Garza====
Luna Garza is a shapeshifter in whom Sam takes a romantic interest. A member of one of Sam's evening shapeshifter gatherings, Luna reveals that she is a Skinwalker and can take the form of another human being. She is initially reluctant to start a relationship with Sam because her ex-husband, and father of her daughter, is a jealous werewolf, but finally decides she wants to be with him. She is turned off from him after the first night they supposedly have sex when he is extremely rude toward her. She and Sam soon learn that it was actually Tommy, in the form of Sam, that had sex with her. She and Sam finally consummate their relationship on a camping trip with her daughter.

Luna Garza is portrayed by [[Janina Gavankar]].

====Marcus Bozeman====
Marcus Bozeman is the werewolf pack leader of Shreveport. He shows up at Alcide's house urging him to join his pack now that he's moved to Shreveport, but Alcide refuses. Marcus then visits Debbie to get her to convince Alcide to join, which he eventually does. Marcus sees potential in Alcide to rise up the ranks in the pack and urges the pack to stay out of the war between vampires and witches. Marcus is then revealed to be Luna's ex and warns Sam to stay away from her. Marcus then goes to Merlotte's to find Sam only to find Tommy, and tells Tommy to tell Sam to meet him at his bike repair shop. At his shop, Marcus tells Sam to stay away from Luna. Sam claims that he never touched her but that his brother did, prompting Marcus and his wolves to beat him up. He is shocked to see that Sam changed into Tommy. When Tommy dies, Sam vows vengeance against Marcus. Marcus then visits Debbie when he questions Alcide's allegiance. When Debbie questions it, too, along with a lack of desire to have children, Marcus offers to help her with that. Marcus is killed by Alcide during a confrontation at Alcide and Debbie's house.

Marcus Bozeman first appears in episode 4.5: Me and the Devil and is portrayed by [[Dan Buran]].

====Naomi====
Naomi is Tara's girlfriend from New Orleans. She met Toni, the name Tara was using, cage-fighting. After receiving mail addressed to Tara Thornton she travels to Bon Temps to confront Toni/Tara. After making up with Tara, Pam tries to kill them out of anger, and Tara tells her that she will not have her blood on her hands, and tells her to leave.

Naomi is portrayed by [[Vedette Lim]].

====Mavis====
Mavis was an African-American, Creole woman during the early 20th century. In flashbacks the story of her death is told: she was having an affair with a married white man. When she carried his child, he killed the baby and then her. 

Bent on seeing her baby one last time, she doesn't find rest and wanders as a spirit, showing herself to Mikey Bellefleur and Lafayette. After posessing Lafayette the matter is resolved, and with the help of Jesus she leaves in peace with the spirit of her baby.

Mavis is portrayed by [[Nondumiso Tembe]].

== See also ==
{{wikiquote|True Blood (TV series)|True Blood}}
* [[Characters of The Southern Vampire Mysteries]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.hbo.com/trueblood/ True Blood] Official site
* {{imdb title|id=0844441|title=True Blood}}
* {{tv.com|74645|True Blood}}

{{True Blood}}
{{The Southern Vampire Mysteries}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Characters Of True Blood}}
[[Category:Lists of television characters|True Blood]]
[[Category:Fictional vampires]]
[[Category:True Blood]]

[[da:Fiktive personer i True Blood]]
[[es:Anexo:Personajes de True Blood]]
[[it:Personaggi di True Blood]]
[[he:דם אמיתי - דמויות]]
[[sh:Spisak likova serije True Blood]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
