<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="233154" ns="0" title="Sclera"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|White of the eye|the film|White of the Eye (film)}}
{{Infobox Anatomy |
  Name         = Sclera |
  Latin        = |
  GraySubject  = 225 |
  GrayPage     = 1006 |
  Image        = Schematic diagram of the human eye en.svg |
  Caption      = Schematic diagram of the [[human eye]]. |
  Image2       = |
  Caption2     = |
  Width        = 305 |
  Precursor    = |
  System       = |
  Artery       = [[anterior ciliary arteries]], [[long posterior ciliary arteries]], [[short posterior ciliary arteries]] |
  Vein         = |
  Nerve        = |
  Lymph        = |
  MeshName     = Sclera |
  MeshNumber   = A09.371.784 |
  DorlandsPre  = |
  DorlandsSuf  = |
}}
The '''sclera''' (from the Greek ''skleros'', meaning hard&lt;ref&gt;Mosby’s Medical, Nursing and Allied Health Dictionary, Fourth Edition, Mosby-Year Book Inc., 1994, p. 1402&lt;/ref&gt;), also known as the '''white''' or '''white of the eye''', is the opaque (usually white, though certain animals, such as horses and lizards, can have black sclera), fibrous, protective, outer layer of the [[human eye|eye]] containing [[collagen]] and [[elastic fiber]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassin&quot;&gt;Cassin, B. and Solomon, S. ''Dictionary of Eye Terminology''. Gainesville, Florida: Triad Publishing Company, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;  In the development of the [[embryo]], the sclera is derived from the [[neural crest]].&lt;ref&gt;Hermann D. Schubert. ''Anatomy of the Orbit'' http://www.nyee.edu/pdf/schubert.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In children, it is thinner and shows some of the underlying pigment, appearing slightly blue. In the elderly, fatty deposits on the sclera can make it appear slightly yellow.

Human eyes are somewhat distinctive in the [[animal]] kingdom in that the sclera is very plainly visible whenever the eye is open. This is not just due to the white color of the human sclera, which many other species share, but also to the fact that the human [[Iris (anatomy)|iris]] is relatively small and comprises a significantly smaller portion of the exposed eye surface compared to other animals. It is theorized that this adaptation evolved because of our [[social animal|social]] nature as the eye became a useful [[animal communication|communication]] tool in addition to a [[sensory organ]]. It is believed that the conspicuous sclera of the human eye makes it easier for one individual to infer where another individual is looking, increasing the efficacy of this particular form of [[nonverbal communication]].&lt;ref&gt;Michael Tomasello, Brian Hare, Hagen Lehmann, Josep Call. &quot;Reliance on head versus eyes in the gaze following of great apes and human infants: the cooperative eye hypothesis&quot; http://www.chrisknight.co.uk/wp-content/uploads/2008/06/eyes-cooperation.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Animal researchers have also found that, in the course of their domestication, dogs have also developed the ability to pick up visual cues from the eyes of humans, making them one of only two species known to seek visual cues from another individual's eyes. Dogs do not seem to use this form of communication with one another and only look for visual information from the eyes of humans.&lt;ref name=&quot;secretlife&quot;&gt;{{cite episode|title=The Secret Life of the Dog|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00pssgh|serieslink=Horizon (BBC TV series)|series=Horizon|credits=Director and Producer: Dan Child, Executive Producer: Andrew Kohen|network=[[BBC]]|station=[[BBC2]]|airdate=2010-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Structure==
The sclera forms the posterior five-sixths of the [[connective tissue]] coat of the [[globe (human eye)|globe]]. It is continuous with the [[dura mater]] and the [[cornea]], and maintains the shape of the globe, offering resistance to internal and external forces, and provides an attachment for the [[extraocular muscle]] insertions.  The sclera is perforated by many nerves and vessels passing through the posterior scleral foramen, the hole that is formed by the [[optic nerve]].  At the [[optic disc]] the outer two-thirds of the sclera continues with the dura mater (outer coat of the brain) via the dural sheath of the optic nerve. The inner third joins with some [[choroid]]al tissue to form a plate ([[Lamina cribrosa sclerae|lamina cribrosa]]) across the optic nerve with perforations through which the optic fibers ([[Nerve fascicle|fasciculi]]) pass.  The thickness of the sclera varies from 1mm at the posterior pole to 0.3&amp;nbsp;mm just behind the rectus muscle insertions.  The sclera's blood vessels are mainly on the surface.  Along with the vessels of the [[conjunctiva]] (which is a thin layer covering the sclera), those in the [[episclera]] render the inflamed eye bright red.&lt;ref name=eb&gt;&quot;eye, human.&quot;Encyclopædia Britannica from [[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]] 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

In many [[vertebrate]]s, the sclera is reinforced with plates of [[cartilage]] or [[bone]], together forming a circular structure called the '''[[scleral ring]]'''. In primitive fish, this ring consists of four plates, but the number is lower in many living [[ray-finned fish]]es, and much higher in [[lobe-finned fish]]es, various [[reptile]]s, and [[bird]]s. The ring has disappeared in many groups, including living [[amphibian]]s, some reptiles and fish, and all [[mammal]]s.&lt;ref name=VB&gt;{{cite book |author=Romer, Alfred Sherwood|author2=Parsons, Thomas S.|year=1977 |title=The Vertebrate Body |publisher=Holt-Saunders International |location= Philadelphia, PA|page= 461|isbn= 0-03-910284-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The eyes of all non-human [[primate]]s are dark with small, barely visible sclera.  See [[Cooperative eye hypothesis]]

==Histology==
The [[collagen]] of the sclera is continuous with the [[cornea]].  From outer to innermost, the four layers of the sclera are:
* [[episclera]]
* [[Stroma of iris|stroma]]
* [[Suprachoroid lamina|lamina fusca]]
* [[Corneal endothelium|endothelium]]

The sclera is opaque due to the irregularity of the collagen fibers, as opposed to the near-uniform thickness and parallel arrangement of the corneal collagen. Moreover, the cornea bears more [[Glycosaminoglycan|mucopolysaccharide]] (a carbohydrate that has among its repeating units a nitrogenous sugar, hexosamine) to embed the fibrils.  

The cornea, unlike the sclera, has 5 layers.  The middle, thickest layer is also called the stroma. The sclera, like the cornea, contains a basal endothelium, above which there is the lamina fusca, containing a high count of pigment cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;eb&quot;/&gt;

Sometimes, very small gray-blue spots can appear on the sclera, a harmless condition called [[scleral melanocytosis]].

==Additional images==

[[Image:Limbus.png|thumb|right|180px|Limbus is the border between cornea and sclera]]
&lt;gallery&gt;
 Image:Gray875.png|Interior of anterior half of bulb of eye.
 Image:Gray880.png|The terminal portion of the optic nerve and its entrance into the eyeball, in horizontal section.
 Image:Gray1206.png|The interior of the posterior half of the left eyeball.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{BUHistology|08008loa}}
* {{UMichAtlas|eye_1}} - &quot;Sagittal Section Through the Eyeball&quot;

{{Eye}}
{{Visual_system}}
{{Muscles of orbit}}

[[Category:Eye anatomy]]

[[bn:স্‌ক্লেরা]]
[[ca:Escleròtica]]
[[cs:Bělima]]
[[de:Sclera]]
[[dv:ލޮލުގެ ހުދުކަޅި]]
[[el:Σκληρός χιτώνας]]
[[es:Esclerótica]]
[[eu:Esklerotika]]
[[fa:صلبیه]]
[[fr:Sclère]]
[[ko:공막]]
[[hr:Bjeloočnica]]
[[it:Sclera]]
[[kk:Ақ қабық]]
[[lt:Odena]]
[[nl:Sclera]]
[[no:Sclera]]
[[pl:Twardówka (oko)]]
[[pt:Esclera]]
[[ru:Склера]]
[[sk:Očné bielko]]
[[sl:Beločnica]]
[[sr:Beonjača]]
[[sh:Bjeloočnica]]
[[fi:Kovakalvo (silmä)]]
[[sv:Ögonvita]]
[[uk:Білкова оболонка ока]]
[[ur:صُلبہ]]
[[zh:巩膜]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
