<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2348457" ns="0" title="Joe Pepitone"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Joe Pepitone
|position=[[First baseman]] / [[Center fielder]]
|bats=Left
|throws=Left
|birth_date={{birth date and age|1940|10|9}}
|birth_place=[[Brooklyn, New York]]
|debutdate=April 10
|debutyear=1962
|debutteam=New York Yankees
|finaldate=May 25
|finalyear=1973
|finalteam=Atlanta Braves
|stat1label=[[Batting average]]
|stat1value=.258
|stat2label=[[Home run]]s
|stat2value=219
|stat3label=[[Runs batted in]]
|stat3value=721
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[New York Yankees]] ({{by|1962}}–{{by|1969}})
* [[Houston Astros]] ({{by|1970}})
* [[Chicago Cubs]] ({{by|1970}}–{{by|1973}})
* [[Atlanta Braves]] ({{by|1973}})
* [[Tokyo Yakult Swallows|Yakult Atoms]] ({{by|1973}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 3× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1963 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1963]], [[1964 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1964]], [[1965 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1965]])
* 3× [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1965, 1966, 1969)
}}
'''Joseph &quot;Joe&quot; Anthony Pepitone''' (born October 9, 1940 in [[Brooklyn]], [[New York]]) is a former [[Major League Baseball]] [[first baseman]] and [[outfielder]] who played the bulk of his career for the [[New York Yankees]].  He also played several seasons with the [[Chicago Cubs]] and had short stints with the [[Houston Astros]] and [[Atlanta Braves]].  During his time with the Yankees, Pepitone was thrice-named to play in the [[All-Star Game]] and also won three [[Golden Glove]] awards.  His fame was adequate for him to become something of a cultural icon.

==Baseball career==
===Yankees===
In 1958, Pepitone was signed by the New York Yankees as an amateur [[free agent]]. After playing four seasons in the [[minor leagues]], he broke in with the Yankees in 1962, playing behind [[Moose Skowron]] at [[first base]]. A much-discussed [[legend]] was that while on his way to 1962 [[spring training]] in [[Florida]], Pepitone spent his entire $25,000 (${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|25000|1958|r=0}}}} today) signing bonus. He bought a [[Ford Thunderbird]], a boat which he towed with the Thunderbird, and a [[dog]]. He arrived at Yankees [[spring training]] in [[Fort Lauderdale|Fort Lauderdale, Florida]], with a new car, a new boat, a new dog, and was wearing a new [[shark]]-skin suit.

Yankee management believed he could handle the first base job, and before the 1963 season traded Skowron to the [[Los Angeles Dodgers|Dodgers]]. Pepitone responded, hitting .271 with 27 HR and 89 RBI. He went on to win three [[Gold Gloves]], but in the [[1963 World Series]] he made an infamous [[error]]. With the score tied 1-1 in the seventh inning of Game Four, he lost a routine [[Clete Boyer]] throw in the white shirtsleeves of the Los Angeles crowd, and the batter, [[Jim Gilliam]], went all the way to [[third base]] and scored the Series-winning run on a sacrifice fly. He redeemed himself somewhat in the [[1964 World Series|1964 Series]] against the [[St. Louis Cardinals|Cardinals]] with a Game 6 [[grand slam (baseball)|grand slam]].

The ever-popular Pepitone remained a fixture throughout the decade, even playing [[center field]] after bad [[knees]] reduced [[Mickey Mantle]]'s mobility. 

===Astros, Cubs, and Braves===
After the 1969 season, despite having won his third [[Golden Glove Award]], Pepitone was traded to the [[Houston Astros|Astros]] for [[Curt Blefary]]. However, he played only about half the 1970 season before being traded to the [[Chicago Cubs|Cubs]].

In Chicago, Pepitone replaced [[Ernie Banks]] at first place.  He stayed with the Cubs through the 1971 and 1972 seasons, and was traded to the [[Atlanta Braves]] in May, 1973.  In Atlanta, Pepitone only played three games, which marked the end of his major-league career in the United States.

===Japan===
In June 1973, Pepitone accepted an offer of $70,000 (${{formatnum:{{Inflation|US|70000|1973|r=0}}}} today) a year to play for the [[Tokyo Yakult Swallows|Yakult Atoms]], a professional [[baseball]] team in [[Japan]]'s [[Central League]]. While in Japan, he hit .163 with one [[home run]] and two [[RBI]]s in 14 [[games played]]. According to an edition of ''Total Baseball'', Pepitone spent his days in Japan skipping games for claimed injuries only to be at night in [[disco]]s, behavior which led the Japanese to adopt his name into their [[vernacular]]--as a word meaning &quot;goof off&quot;.{{fact|date=November 2011}}

==Life after baseball==
===Memoirs===
[[Jim Bouton]] talks extensively about Pepitone in his book ''[[Ball Four]]''. Pepitone is described as being extremely vain. Bouton said that Pepitone went nowhere without a bag containing hair products for his rapidly balding head. Pepitone even had two [[hair piece|toupees]], one for general wear and one for under his baseball cap, which he called his &quot;game piece.&quot; Bouton told a humorous story about how the game piece came loose one day when Pepitone took off his cap for the national anthem.

In January 1975, Pepitone published his own tell-all baseball memoir, titled ''Joe, You Coulda Made Us Proud.'' The book received substantial attention for its many revelations. Later that year, he posed nude for Foxy Lady magazine, featuring full frontal nudity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/29878446/page/2/ Where Have Baseball's Characters Gone?- Article at NBC Sports]&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Other work===
In the late 70's, Pepitone played for the New Jersey Statesmen in the American Professional Slow Pitch League (APSPL), one of three [[professional softball leagues]] active during this period. Pepitone would also serve the front office  of the North American Softball League (NASL) for their only season in 1980.

In June 1982, Pepitone was hired as a batting coach with the Yankees, but was replaced by [[Lou Piniella]] later in the season.&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70C12F7355C0C758CDDAF0894DA484D81 New York Times Article - June 6, 1982]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1990s, Pepitone was given a job in the Yankees' front office. He currently spends his time signing autographs and baseball memorabilia at autograph shows, and working in a public relations capacity for the Yankees.

===Criminal history===
*Pepitone spent four months at [[Rikers Island]] jail in 1988 for two [[misdemeanor]] drug convictions after he and two other men were arrested on March 18, 1985, in [[Brooklyn]] after being stopped by the police for running a red light in a car containing nine ounces of [[cocaine]], 344 [[quaaludes]], a [[Freebase (chemistry)|free-basing]] kit, a pistol and about $6,300 in cash.&lt;ref&gt;[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50915F83D5C0C738EDDAA0894DD484D81 New York Times Article - March 20, 1985]&lt;/ref&gt; Coverage of the story by WOR-TV (Channel 9) in the New York area featured clips of an incredulous Pepitone declaring, &quot;I didn't know cocaine was illegal&quot;, and his brother Vinnie, a New York City detective, staunchly defending his character.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}} He was released from jail on a work-release program when Yankee owner [[George Steinbrenner]] offered him a job in minor-league player development for the team.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D7103EF936A25754C0A96E948260 New York Times Article - July 15, 1988]&lt;/ref&gt;
*In January 1992, Pepitone was charged with misdemeanor assault in [[Catskills|Kiamesha Lake, New York]], after a scuffle police said was triggered when Pepitone was called a &quot;has-been.&quot; He was arraigned in town court and released after he posted $75 bail.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA123AF933A25752C0A964958260 New York Times Article - January 10, 1992]&lt;/ref&gt;
*In October 1995, the 55-year-old Pepitone was arrested and charged with driving while intoxicated after losing control of his car in [[New York City]]'s [[Queens-Midtown Tunnel]]. Police found Pepitone bloodied, disoriented and mumbling as he walked through the tunnel. Authorities charged Pepitone with drunken driving after he refused to take a sobriety test.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=You Can Call Me Joe Pepitone|publisher=Long Beach (CA) Press-Telegram|date=October 26, 1995|accessdate=2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Pepitone pled guilty. When asked if he was staying away from alcohol, Pepitone responded: &quot;I don't drink that much.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Joe Pepitone In Auto Plea|author=Karen Freifeld |publisher=Newsday (Melville, NY)|date=February 23, 1996|accessdate=2006-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Three times divorced, Pepitone currently resides in [[Amityville, New York]].

==Pop Culture references==

===Larry David productions===
Pepitone has been mentioned in at least five episodes of shows written by or produced by [[Larry David]].
*Joe Pepitone was mentioned in the 1993 ''[[Seinfeld]]'' episode titled ''[[The Visa]]''. In the episode, [[Cosmo Kramer]] reluctantly describes his experience at a recent baseball fantasy camp, wherein Pepitone was crowding home plate while Kramer was pitching, leading to Kramer's [[beanball]] that resulted in a subsequent camp-ending brawl, in which Kramer punched [[Mickey Mantle]].
*Pepitone was mentioned in the 1994 ''[[Seinfeld]]'' episode titled ''[[The Mom and Pop Store]]''. In the episode, [[George Costanza]] buys John Voight's car, thinking it belonged to [[Jon Voight]] the actor. George tells Mr. Morgan, &quot;Well, I think we need more special days at the stadium, you know? Like, uh...Joe Pepitone Day. Or, uh...Jon Voight Day.&quot;
*In the 1996 ''Seinfeld'' episode titled ''[[The Rye]]'', [[Cosmo Kramer|Kramer]] (while driving a [[hansom cab]] through Central Park) refers to Joe Pepitone as the designer of New York City's [[Central Park]].
*Pepitone is mentioned in the sixth season of the [[HBO]] series ''[[Curb Your Enthusiasm]]'' episode titled &quot;The Anonymous Donor&quot;, in which Larry David's Pepitone jersey gets lost at the dry cleaners. Larry and Leon Black then go out trying to find who is wearing it.
*In the episode, &quot;Mister Softee&quot; in the eighth season of [[Curb Your Enthusiasm]], Larry and Leon attend a baseball autograph signing where Leon says, &quot;I'm gonna go check out Joe Pepitone up in here,&quot; though Pepitone does not actually appear.

===Other TV references===
Joe Pepitone was first mentioned in the 1987 ''[[Golden Girls]]'' episode titled ''Whose Face is this, Anyway''.  In this episode, Blanche tells Dorothy that she cannot possibly begin to comprehend the trauma a gorgeous woman goes through when she realizes her beauty is about to fade.  Dorothy yells out, &quot;And who do you see when you look at me Blanche, Joe Pepitone?!&quot;.

In the 1994 [[Mystery Science Theater 3000]] episode &quot;Zombie Nightmare&quot;, Mike Nelson refers to Joe Pepitone.

Pepitone is mentioned in the first season of [[The Sopranos]] episode entitled &quot;[[Down Neck]]&quot;. [[Tony Soprano|Tony]] is having a flashback to his childhood during a therapy session with [[Jennifer Melfi|Dr. Melfi]] when he recalls walking out of his house when he was around 8 or 9 years old and his [[Junior Soprano|Uncle Junior]] shouts from his car &quot;Anthony, you watch the game last night?&quot;, Tony replies &quot;No, my mom made me go to bed&quot;, and then Uncle Junior says &quot;Joey Pepitone, three RBIs!&quot;.

===Literature===
In 2010, the novella ''Soul of a Yankee: The Iron Horse, The Babe and the Battle for Joe Pepitone,'' written by Pepitone's nephews William A. &amp; Joseph V. Pepitone, was released. In it, the ghost of Lou Gehrig takes Joe through his life to show him the error of his ways, while the ghost of Babe Ruth tries to tempt Joe back into the wild life.

==Accolades==
Pepitone was a member of the [[1963 in baseball|1963]], [[1964 in baseball|1964]] and [[1965 in baseball|1965]] [[American League]] [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All Star Team]]. He won the [[Gold Glove]] award for [[first baseman|first basemen]] in 1965, [[1966 in baseball|1966]] and [[1969 in baseball|1969]].

==See also==
* [[List of top 300 Major League Baseball home run hitters]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Books===
*Bouton, Jim, and Leonard Shecter. ''Ball Four; My Life and Hard Times Throwing the Knuckleball in the Big Leagues''. New York: World Pub. Co., 1970. 400 pages. (ISBN 0-9709117-0-X)
*Pepitone, Joe, and Berry Stainback. ''Joe, You Coulda Made Us Proud''. Chicago: Playboy Press, 1975. 246 pages. (ISBN 0-87223-428-2)
*Pepitone, William A., and Joseph V. ''Soul of a Yankee: The Iron Horse, the Babe and the Battle for Joe Pepitone''. Morrisville, NC: Self-Published through lulu.com, 2011. 130 pages. (ISBN 0-55774-941-7)

===Newspapers===
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0F17F6385B127A93C1A9178AD85F468685F9 Yanks Harvest Bumper Farm Crop; Well-Balanced Array of Minor Leaguers Aids Champions All-Star Rookie Cast Includes Sons of Keller, Tresh - Mike Tresh's Son on List - New York Times article, January 3, 1962]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10B13FF3D5E147B93CAA91789D85F468685F9 BROOKLYN TALENT AT YANKEE CAMP; Pepitone Stands Out - New York Times article, February 8, 1962]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0E17FE3F5910728DDDAC0A94DA405B828AF1D3 YANKEE ROOKIES RATED BEST EVER; Houk Praises Tresh, Gibbs, Linz, Pepitone and Keller - New York Times article, February 25, 1962]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70C1FFD395C137A93C3A81788D85F468685F9 Mantle, Boyer Hit Homers As Yanks Top Orioles, 4-1; Yanks Turn Back Orioles, 4 to 1, On Homers by Mantle and Boyer - New York Times article, March 11, 1962]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70B13FD3D5A157B93C3A8178FD85F468685F9 Sports of The Times; Overheard at the Stadium - Time Marches On - Nuisance Hitter - The Hollywood Touch - New York Times article, April 11, 1962]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10A13FC355A107B93C7A91789D95F4D8685F9 Yanks Trade Pepitone to Astros for Blefary;; INTERLEAGUE DEAL INVOLVES NO CASH Houk Plans to Use Blefary in Outfield -- Walker Sees Change Helping Pepitone - New York Times article, December 5, 1969]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0A11F83D5E16738DDDAB0A94DF405B808BF1D3 Astros' Pepitone Threatens to Retire - New York Times article, July 22, 1970]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10A15FE355A157493C2AA178CD85F448785F9 Cubs Acquire Pepitone on Waivers - New York Times article, July 30, 1970]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F5071EFC3F5F117B93C1A9178ED85F468785F9 Pepitone Quits Baseball; 'No Longer Interested' - New York Times article, May 3, 1972]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60B17FF345A137B93C3A9178DD85F468785F9 Pepitone to Return to Cubs 'to Help Win the Pennant' - New York Times article, June 1, 1972]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60F17FE3959137A93C2AB178ED85F478785F9 Pepitone Is Traded By Cubs to the Braves - New York Times article, May 20, 1973]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F60C10FC3959137A93C5AB178ED85F478785F9 Pepitone Quits Again - New York Times article, May 27, 1973]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FA0F14F638551A7493CAAB178ED85F478785F9 Pepitone Hoping to Do His Swinging in Japan - New York Times article, May 28, 1973]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F10613FD3959147A93C6AB178DD85F478785F9 Pepitone's a Hero in His Tokyo Debut Before 40,000 - New York Times article, June 24, 1973]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0712FB385C1A7A93CBA9178CD85F478785F9 Pepitone Returns to U.S. - New York Times article, July 9, 1973]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F20A17F93E5814728DDDA00994DD405B848BF1D3 The Joe Pepitone Prayer: Don't Let Me Die in Japan; For 12 years--from 1962 -- Joe Pepitone played first and outfield for the New York Yankees, Houston Astros and Chicago Cubs - New York Times article, May 19, 1974]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F0071EFC3A5F107A93C4AB178ED85F408785F9 Sports Editor's mailbox: No Tears for Joe Pepitone - New York Times article, May 26, 1974]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F70C12F7355C0C758CDDAF0894DA484D81 PEPITONE IS GRATEFUL TO REJOIN YANKEES - New York Times article, June 6, 1982]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50915F83D5C0C738EDDAA0894DD484D81 PEPITONE ARRESTED ON DRUG CHARGES - New York Times article, March 20, 1985]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DA173BF937A35756C0A963948260 Pepitone Is Indicted - New York Times article, May 4, 1985]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DE1E3EF934A1575BC0A960948260 SPORTS PEOPLE; Pepitone Trial Starts - New York Times article, August 27, 1986]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50717FE385D0C7B8DDDA00894DE484D81 PEPITONE IS GUILTY OF LESSER CHARGES - New York Times article, September 18, 1986]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50715FF3D5F0C708EDDA90994DE484D81 PEPITONE SENTENCED TO SIX MONTHS IN JAIL - New York Times article, October 23, 1986]
*[http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=FB0717F83D550C748DDDAC0894D0484D81 Pepitone to Begin 6-Month Jail Term - New York Times article, May 17, 1988]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D7103EF936A25754C0A96E948260 Pepitone Hired by Yanks - New York Times article, July 15, 1988]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DC133AF936A2575AC0A96E948260 Pepitone Is Released - New York Times article, September 15, 1988]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA123AF933A25752C0A964958260 SPORTS PEOPLE: BASEBALL; Pepitone in Scuffle at Hotel Lounge - New York Times article, January 10, 1992]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D71639F935A15753C1A963958260 SPORTS PEOPLE: BASEBALL; Pepitone Is Arrested - New York Times article, October 26, 1995]
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/newsday/search.html Joe Pepitone In Auto Plea - Newsday article, February 23, 1996]

== External links ==
*{{baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=p/pepitjo01 |fangraphs=1010167 |cube=joe-pepitone}}
*[http://www.baseballlibrary.com/baseballlibrary/ballplayers/P/Pepitone_Joe.stm Joe Pepitone's entry in BaseballLibrary.com]

{{AL First Baseman Gold Glove Award}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Pepitone, Joe
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = October 9, 1940
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Brooklyn, New York
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pepitone, Joe}}
[[Category:New York Yankees players]]
[[Category:American League All-Stars]]
[[Category:American memoirists]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:Chicago Cubs players]]
[[Category:Houston Astros players]]
[[Category:Atlanta Braves players]]
[[Category:Yakult Atoms players]]
[[Category:American expatriate baseball players in Japan]]
[[Category:Baseball coaches]]
[[Category:New York Yankees coaches]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball first basemen]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball outfielders]]
[[Category:People from New York City]]
[[Category:People from Brooklyn]]
[[Category:People from Long Island]]
[[Category:Hawaii Islanders players]]
[[Category:Baseball players from New York]]
[[Category:American people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:1940 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[ja:ジョー・ペピトーン]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
