<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2349779" ns="0" title="Championnat de France amateur"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox football league
| logo       =  
| pixels     = 140
| country    = {{Flag|France}}
| confed     = [[UEFA]]
| founded    = 1993
| teams      = 69 ([[2010–11 Championnat de France amateur|2010–11 season]])
| promotion  = [[Championnat National]]
| relegation = [[Championnat de France amateur 2]]
| levels     = 4
| domest_cup = [[Coupe de France]]
| confed_cup = [[UEFA Europa League|Europa League]] (via domestic cup)
| champions  = [[Gazélec Ajaccio]]
| most successful club = 
| season     = [[2010–11 Championnat de France amateur|2010–11]]
| tv         = 
| website    = [http://www.fff.fr/cfa Official site]
| current    = [[2011–12 Championnat de France amateur]]
}}

The '''Championnat de France amateur''', commonly referred to as simply '''CFA''' and formerly known as '''National 2''', is a [[Association football|football]] league competition. The league serves as the fourth division of the [[French football league system]] behind [[Ligue 1]], [[Ligue 2]], and the [[Championnat National]]. Contested by 72 clubs, the Championnat de France amateur operates on a system of [[promotion and relegation]] with the Championnat National and the [[Championnat de France amateur 2]], the fifth division of [[French football]]. Seasons run from August to May, with teams in four groups playing 34 games each totalling 1360 games in the season. Most games are played on Saturdays and Sundays, with a few games played during weekday evenings. Play is regularly suspended the last weekend before Christmas for two weeks before returning in the second week of January.

The Championnat de France amateur was initially founded by the [[French Football Federation]] in 1927 and was composed of the regional amateur league champions. The league served as the first division of French football until 1929 before the league was converted to the professional league that exists today in 1932.&lt;ref name=&quot;gauthey&quot;&gt;Gilles Gauthey, ''Le football professionnel français'', Paris, 1961, p.18&lt;/ref&gt; The current incarnation of the CFA was founded in 1993 as National 2 and lasted for five years before being converted to the current format used today. Most clubs that participate in the league are amateur clubs, hence the league name, but a small amount of clubs are [[semi-professional]]. The matches in the league attract on average between 800 and 1,000 spectators per match. However, this average is dragged down by the minuscule turnouts for the pros' home reserve matches. The current champions are [[SR Colmar|Colmar]] who accumulated 103 points in Groupe A to earn promotion to the third division.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Colmar en National? Point sur les quatre Groupes |url=http://www.foot-national.com/articles-2524.html |work=Foot National |publisher=Foot National |date=22 May 2010|accessdate=22 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The winners of the Groupe B, Groupe C, and Groupe D were [[Gap FC|Gap]], [[Chamois Niortais F.C.|Niort]], and [[US Orléans|Orléans]], respectively. All three clubs, alongside the champions, earned promotion to the Championnat National.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Niort en National, le point sur tous les groupes|url=http://www.foot-national.com/articles-2492.html |work=Foot National |publisher=Foot National |date=8 May 2010|accessdate=8 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Orléans est en National |url=http://www.foot-national.com/flashes-14446.html |work=Foot National |publisher=Foot National |date=15 May 2010|accessdate=15 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gap en National, incertitude entre Colmar et l'UJA Alfortville |url=http://www.foot-national.com/articles-2534.html |work=Foot National |publisher=Foot National |date=29 May 2010|accessdate=29 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The amateur championship of France was created in 1993 under the name ''National 2'' as an heir to the now-defunct [[Division 3]]. The league's debut coincided with the creation of the [[Championnat National]], the third division of French football, which is commonly known as ''National''. For the first three years of the competition, an amateur champion was crowned in France regardless of whether the club was amateur or a reserve team. In 1998, the [[French Football Federation]] changed the competition's format creating two separate tables; one for the amateur clubs and another for the reserve teams of professional clubs. The dual tables allowed the league to declare a champion for the amateurs and the reserves with four team tournaments being held following the conclusion of league play to determine the champions. In 2001, the federation ended this style and reverted to the original format allowing both the amateur clubs and reserve teams to be grouped together based on their regional location. The winner of each group would then earn promotion to the Championnat National, unless the club is a reserve team. Meanwhile, the reserve teams continued to use the previous format with the best reserve teams of each group being inserted into a tournament to decide the reserves' champion.

==Competition format==
There are 72 clubs that participate in the Championnat de France amateur annually. The clubs are split into four parallel groups of 18 with their group affiliation being based on the [[Regions of France|regional location]]. The league is open to the best reserve teams in France and amateur clubs in France, although only the amateur clubs are eligible for promotion to the Championnat National. During the course of a season, usually from August to May, each club plays the others in their respective group twice, once at their home stadium and once at that of their opponents, for a total of 34 games. Since the league it is considered amateur, teams receive four points for a win and two points for a draw. One point is awarded for a loss. A club gets no points from a game for certain disciplinary reasons or if they forfeit. Teams are ranked by total points, then [[goal difference]], and then goals scored. At the end of each season, the club with the most points, regardless of the group, is crowned champion and promoted to the Championnat National. If points are equal, head-to-head match results, followed by the goal difference, and then goals scored determine the winner. If still equal, teams are deemed to occupy the same position. If there is a tie for the championship or for relegation, a play-off match at a neutral venue decides rank. The three other highest-placed amateur teams in the other groups are also promoted, while the 4 lowest-placed teams from each group are relegated to the [[Championnat de France amateur 2]] and the eight winners of the eight groups and the top four second-place finishers from the Championnat de France amateur 2 are promoted in their place.

==Teams==
The following teams are competing in the Championnat de France amateur for the [[2009–10 Championnat de France amateur|2009–10 season]].

{{col-begin}}
{{col-4}}

===Groupe A===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  
|-
!Club Name
|-
|[[UJA Alfortville]]
|-
|[[CSO Amnéville]]
|-
|[[Besançon RC]]
|-
|[[SR Colmar]]
|-
|[[AFC Compiègne]]
|-
|[[JA Drancy]]
|-
|[[USL Dunkerque]]
|-
|[[SAS Épinal]]
|-
|[[RC Lens]] Reserves
|-
|[[Lille OSC]] Reserves
|-
|[[AS Marck]]
|-
|[[FC Mulhouse]]
|-
|[[AS Nancy]] Reserves
|-
|[[Olympique Noisy-le-Sec]]
|-
|[[US Raon-l'Étape]]
|-
|[[L'Entente SSG]]
|-
|[[RC Strasbourg]] Reserves
|-
|[[Vesoul Haute-Saône]]
|-
|[[Villemomble Sports]] 
|}
{{col-4}}

===Groupe B===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  
|-
!Club Name
|-
|[[RCO Agde]]
|-
|[[Gazélec Ajaccio]]
|-
|[[ASF Andrézieux]]
|-
|[[CA Bastia]]
|-
|[[FC Bourg-Péronnas]]
|-
|[[Gap FC]]
|-
|[[Grenoble Foot 38|Grenoble]] Reserves
|-
|[[Jura Sud Foot]]
|-
|[[US Le Pontet]]
|-
|[[AS Lyon-Duchère]] 
|-
|[[Olympique Lyonnais|Lyon]] Reserves
|-
|[[US Marignane]]
|-
|[[FC Martigues]]
|-
|[[FC Montceau Bourgogne]]
|-
|[[Montpellier HSC]] Reserves
|-
|[[FC Sochaux-Montbéliard|Sochaux]] Reserves
|-
|[[Sporting Toulon Var]]
|-
|[[FC Villefranche]]
|}
{{col-4}}

===Groupe C===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  
|-
!Club Name
|-
|[[US Albi]]
|-
|[[Genêts Anglet]]
|-
|[[Aurillac FCA]]
|-
|[[Balma SC]]
|-
|[[FC Girondins de Bordeaux|Bordeaux]] Reserves
|-
|[[US Colomiers (football)|US Colomiers]]
|-
|[[Vendée Fontenay Foot]]
|-
|[[Le Mans Union Club 72|Le Mans]] Reserves
|-
|[[Les Herbiers VF]]
|-
|[[FC Libourne-Saint-Seurin]] 
|-
|[[Vendée Luçon Football]]
|-
|[[EDS Montluçon]]
|-
|[[Chamois Niortais FC]]
|-
|[[Paris Saint-Germain F.C.|Paris SG]] Reserves
|-
|[[Pau FC]]
|-
|[[Red Star Saint-Ouen|Red Star FC]]
|-
|[[Toulouse Fontaines Club]]
|-
|[[AS Yzeure]]
|}
{{col-4}}

===Groupe D===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;  
|-
!Club Name
|-
|[[AJ Auxerre]] Reserves
|-
|[[US Avranches]]
|-
|[[SM Caen]] Reserves
|-
|[[USJA Carquefou]]
|-
|[[AS Cherbourg Football|AS Cherbourg]]
|-
|[[US Ivry]]
|-
|[[Le Havre AC]] Reserves
|-
|[[FC Mantes]]
|-
|[[US Sénart-Moissy]]
|-
|[[US Orléans]]
|-
|[[GSI Pontivy]]
|-
|[[US Quevilly]]
|-
|[[Quimper Cornouaille FC]]
|-
|[[Racing Club de France]]
|-
|[[Stade Rennais F.C.|Rennes]] Reserves
|-
|[[SO Romorantin]]
|-
|[[ES Viry-Châtillon]]
|-
|[[La Vitréenne FC]] 
|}
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.fff.fr Official Site of the Fédération française de football]
*[http://www.soccerway.com/national/france/cfa/ Championnat de France amateur Fixtures] {{en icon}}

{{Championnat de France Amateurs seasons}}
{{Championnat de France Amateurs Groupe A}}
{{Championnat de France Amateurs Groupe B}}
{{Championnat de France Amateurs Groupe C}}
{{Championnat de France Amateurs Groupe D}}
{{Football in France}}
{{UEFA fourth leagues}} 
{{Use British English|date=August 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Championnat De France Amateur}}
[[Category:Championnat de France amateur| ]]
[[Category:Football leagues in France|4]]

[[de:Championnat de France Amateur]]
[[es:Championnat de France Amateurs]]
[[fr:Championnat de France amateur de football]]
[[ko:샹피오나 드 프랑스 아마퇴르]]
[[it:Championnat de France amateur]]
[[nl:Championnat de France amateur]]
[[ja:フランスアマチュア選手権]]
[[pl:Championnat de France amateur]]
[[pt:Championnat de France Amateur]]
[[ru:Любительский чемпионат Франции по футболу]]
[[fi:Championnat de France amateur]]
[[tr:Championnat de France amateur]]
[[uk:Аматорський чемпіонат Франції з футболу]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
