<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Microsoft antivirus" to="MSAV" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="1626435" ns="0" title="MSAV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Microsoft Anti-Virus
| screenshot             = [[File:MSAV.png|300px]]
| caption                = Microsoft Anti-Virus
| author                 = [[Microsoft Corporation]]
| developer              = [[Central Point Software]]
| released               = March 30, 1993
| latest release version = 
| latest release date    = {{Start date and age|1996|06|01|df=no}}
| operating system       = [[DOS]], [[Windows 3.1x]]
| platform               = [[IA-32]]
| size                   = '''MSAV.EXE:''' {{Nowrap|236 KB}}&lt;br /&gt; '''VSAFE.COM:''' {{Nowrap|62 KB}}&lt;br /&gt; '''Virus Definitions:''' {{Nowrap|60 KB}}
| language               = [[English language|English]]
| status                 = Discontinued
| genre                  = [[Antivirus software]]
| license                = [[Proprietary_software|Proprietary]]
}}

{{Redirect|Microsoft antivirus|the later Microsoft anti-virus product|Microsoft Security Essentials|a malware masquerading as an antivirus|MS Antivirus (malware)}}

'''Microsoft Anti-Virus''' ('''MSAV''') was an [[antivirus software|antivirus]] program introduced by [[Microsoft]] for its [[MS-DOS]] [[operating system]]. The program first appeared in MS-DOS version 6.0
(1993 &lt;ref&gt;[http://oldfiles.org.uk/powerload/timeline.htm A History of Microsoft MS-DOS and Windows (and its main competitors) on the 8086 Processor family]&lt;/ref&gt;)
and last appeared in MS-DOS 6.22. The first version of the antivirus program was basic, had no update facility (updates had to be obtained from a BBS), and could scan for 1,234 different viruses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ia700202.us.archive.org/7/items/MsavVirusList/virus.html List of viruses detectable by MSAV]&lt;/ref&gt; '''Microsoft Anti-Virus for Windows''' ('''MWAV'''), included as part of the package, could be run under [[Windows 3.1x]].

== History ==
Microsoft Anti-Virus was supplied by [[Central Point Software]] Inc. (later acquired by [[Symantec]] in 1994 and integrated into Symantec's [[Norton AntiVirus]] product) and was essentially a stripped down version of the [[Central Point Anti-Virus]] (CPAV) product which, in turn, Central Point Software Inc., had licensed from [[Carmel Software Engineering]] in Haifa, Israel. Carmel Software sold the product as [[Turbo Anti-Virus]] both domestically and abroad.

Microsoft Anti-Virus for Windows was also provided by Central Point Software. This product became noted as determining that the upgrade program of [[Windows 95]] was detected as a [[computer virus]], something which was embarrassing to Microsoft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.computerhope.com/msavhlp.htm MS-DOS MSAV command help]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Features ==
Both the MS-DOS and Windows versions of the latest product had common features; the &quot;Detect and Clean&quot; strategy, and the detection of [[Boot sector virus|boot sector]] and [[Trojan horse]]-type viruses (which were the typical virus problems at the time).

The program also had an anti-stealth and [[check sum]] feature that could be used to detect any changes in normal files. This technology was intended to make up for the unavailability of regular update packages. The final update of MSAV was released on June 1996 by Symantec&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/127807]&lt;/ref&gt;, it added the ability to detect polymorphic viruses and the virus definitions were updated to scan for a total of 2,371 viruses.
=== VSafe TSR ===
[[File:VSafe.png|300px|right]]
VSafe was a [[terminate and stay resident]] component of MSAV that provided real-time virus protection.

By default, VSafe does the following:
* Checks executable files for viruses (on execution).
* Checks all disks (hard drive and floppy) for boot sector viruses.
* Warns of attempts to write to the boot sector or partition table of the hard disk
* Warns of formatting that could erase the hard disk.
There are more features that can be enabled, VSafe can:
* Warn of attempts of executable files to terminate and stay resident (by normal methods).
* Prevent programs from writing to disk.
* Warn of attempts to write to the boot sector of a floppy disk.
* Warn of attempts to modify executable files.

VSafe had a number of virus definitions embedded within its executable, but was capable of loading additional (updated) signatures from an external definition file.

== References ==
{{wikinews|Microsoft develops anti-virus product}}
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Microsoft Security Products}}
[[Category:Discontinued Microsoft software|Anti-Virus]]
[[Category:Antivirus software]]

[[cs:Microsoft Anti-Virus]]
[[de:Central Point Anti-Virus#Microsoft Anti-Virus]]
[[es:Microsoft Anti-Virus]]
[[fa:ام‌اس‌ای‌وی]]
[[it:Microsoft Anti-Virus]]
[[sv:Microsoft Anti-Virus for Windows]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
