<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23563407" ns="0" title="List of EastEnders characters (1995)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''EastEnders'' characters (1995)}}
The following is a list of characters that first appeared in the [[BBC]] [[soap opera]] ''[[EastEnders]]'' in 1995, by order of first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}

==Tiffany Mitchell==
{{Main|Tiffany Mitchell}}
'''Tiffany Dawn Mitchell''' ([[née]] '''Raymond''') was played by [[Martine McCutcheon]] from 1995 until 1998. The character was created by the writer, [[Tony Jordan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;echo&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a82988/martine-had-doubts-over-echo-beach-part.html Martine had doubts over 'Echo Beach' part]&quot;, Digital Spy. URL last accessed on 2008-08-01.&lt;/ref&gt; She was introduced as a school friend of [[Bianca Jackson]] and became a prominent and popular character during her tenure due to a combustible relationship with the soap's landlord, [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant Mitchell]]. McCutcheon quit the role in 1998 in order to pursue a musical career. Producers made the controversial decision to kill the character off, an act that McCutcheon publicly criticised as she had hoped to return at some stage. A book released in 1998, documenting Tiffany's time in the soap, was a number one bestseller.

==Lydia==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Lydia
|portrayer=[[Marlaine Gordon]]
|years=1995–96
|first=21 March 1995
|last=12 February 1996
|born=
|occupation= Market trader
|family=
}}
'''Lydia''' is a recurring character played by [[Marlaine Gordon]] between 1995 and 1996.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://archive.thisislancashire.co.uk/2001/4/26/681547.html Ex-Rover died in Army booze binge tragedy]&quot;, [[Lancashire Evening Telegraph]]. URL last accessed on 2007-05-06.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.discogs.com/artist/E'voke?anv=Evoke Evoke]&quot;, Discogs. URL last accessed on 2007-05-06.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Lydia was first seen in [[Walford]] in March 1995, when she was hired as an apprentice [[hairdresser]] by [[Della Alexander]]. She was a bit obnoxious and liked to gossip, and she often ended up infuriating her employer, particularly as she was often the topic of the gossip. Lydia ended up losing her job in May that year when Della decided to move away from Walford. Audacious Lydia spent the last few days of her employment badmouthing Della to anyone who would listen and boasting about a new job she was applying for in an upper class salon. She then gave Della her reference to sign, which described her as popular, bubbly and humorous. Della had the last laugh however, when she re-wrote the reference depicting her as obnoxious and useless. A furious Lydia then left, uttering a tirade of homophobic abuse at her [[lesbian]] employer as she went.  

Later in the year Lydia came back to Walford to apply for a job at [[Ian Beale]]'s chip shop. She was rejected after a disastrous interview, but managed to get herself a job working on [[Sanjay Kapoor (EastEnders)|Sanjay]] and [[Gita Kapoor]]'s market stall instead. She soon started dating the philandering chef [[Steve Elliot]]. Steve, who had always run a mile from commitment in the past, seemed quite taken with Lydia, and in 1996, the two moved into a flat together.

In February 1996, Steve promised to give testimony at [[Arthur Fowler]]'s trial. A criminal firm had persuaded Steve to host a late-night game of [[poker]] in his night café, which Arthur's son [[Mark Fowler|Mark]] attended. He won a sizeable sum and gave the winnings to his father. Arthur was later falsely accused of [[embezzlement]] and he was assumed guilty, which was due, in part, to the suspicious and unaccountable sum of money he had been given by Mark. The firm refused to allow Steve to testify at Arthur's trial, as they feared it would place them under a police investigation. After several threats Steve decided not to testify, but this earned the scorn of Lydia and she managed to persuade him to go through with it.

In order to change his mind the firm kidnapped Lydia. Steve was frantic, but he eventually found a distraught Lydia, who informed him that the mobsters had attempted to drown her and threatened to kill her if he didn't back out of testifying. Fearful for his girlfriend's life, Steve packed his things and both he and Lydia left Walford later that night. Their last appearance was in February 1996.

==Ted Hills==
{{Main|Ted Hills}}
'''Ted Hills''' was played by [[Brian Croucher]]. He was introduced in 1995 as the patriarch of the Hills family, who were the extended family of established character [[Kathy Beale]]. Ted was axed in 1997.

==Tony Hills==
{{Main|Tony Hills}}
'''Tony Hills''' was played by [[Mark Homer]]. He was first shown on screen on 7 September 1995 after arriving from [[Norfolk]] with his sister, [[Sarah Hills]], played by [[Daniella Denby-Ashe]]. At first, he was painted as an unsympathetic character; at one point he sold [[methylenedioxymethamphetamine|ecstasy]] with a friend, Dan Zappieri. Eventually, he quit dealing after Dan gave Sarah ecstasy without her knowledge.

==Sarah Hills==
{{main|Sarah Hills}}
'''Sarah Hills''' was played by [[Daniela Denby-Ashe]]. She was troublesome when she arrived on [[Albert Square]], [[shoplifting]] from various market stalls. This was noticed by [[Alistair Matthews]], a shop manager and religious cult leader who made Sarah turn to religion to avoid being turned in to the police.

==Guppy Sharma==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image=
|name=Guppy Sharma
|portrayer=[[Lyndam Gregory]]
|years=1995–96
|first=17 October 1995
|last=5 March 1996
|occupation= Clothes dealer
}}
'''Gopal &quot;Guppy&quot; Sharma'''  was a clothes dealer, played by Lyndam Gregory.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.uk.castingcallpro.com/view.php?uid=60997 Lyndam Gregory]&quot;, .castingcallpro.com.URL last accessed on 2009-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt;  Guppy is first seen in October 1995, approaching market trader [[Gita Kapoor]] about a business proposition whereby he would supply her with mock designer clothing for her stall at cut price. While Gita's husband [[Sanjay Kapoor (EastEnders)|Sanjay]] is out of the country tending to a dying relative, Gita grows close to Guppy; a flirtatious relationship begins. 

Gita grows suspicious of Guppy when he is beaten up by his former employer - an owner of a [[sweatshop]] - who is angry that Guppy has set up business alone. He refuses to tell Gita who his current business partner is. He pursues Gita, buying her flowers and attempting to kiss her, until he is followed and confronted by his business partner, Gita's sister, [[Meena McKenzie]]. Gita had disowned her sister 2 years prior for having an affair with her husband, and in an attempt to reconcile with Gita, Meena had persuaded Guppy to offer her cheap business on her behalf. It transpires that Guppy is Meena's fiancé, and Meena grows angry when she discovers that Guppy has been wooing Gita. Arguments between the sisters resurface with Meena refusing to believe that Guppy feels anything for Gita other than pity; she opts to go ahead with her plan to marry Guppy.

The Kapoors decide to end their business arrangement with Guppy just as they are noticed selling counterfeit goods by the market inspector, Lesley. Guppy bribes Lesley, but they are witnessed by police and both are arrested. When Guppy reappears, he informs Sanjay that his wedding to Meena never took place. He persuades Sanjay to invest £2,000 in a business venture and then steals his money, leaving Sanjay in debt with a loan shark.
{{-}}

==Felix Kawalski==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = EastEnders
|image= 
|name=Felix Kawalski
|portrayer=[[Harry Landis]]
|years=1995–97
|born=1929
|death=2005
|first=9 November 1995
|last=29 May 1997
|occupation=[[Barber]]
|sisters=Julia Kawalski
}}
'''Felix Kawalski''', played by [[Harry Landis]], is a [[Jewish]]-[[Poles|Polish]] [[immigration|immigrant]] who sets up a [[barber]]shop in [[Walford]]. A survivor of the [[Holocaust]], Felix has spent his life searching for his family to no avail. He assumes they had all perished in the [[Nazi concentration camps]], so he is thrilled when he finally makes contact with his surviving sister.

Felix is first seen in November 1995 when he moves to Walford to open a barber shop. He is interested in [[brass band]] music, and when he notices [[Sonia Fowler|Sonia Jackson]] attempting to play the [[trumpet]] he tries to offer her the benefit of his wisdom. However, Sonia takes his kind gesture the wrong way and tells her stepfather [[Alan Jackson (EastEnders)|Alan]]. Thinking that Felix is a [[paedophile]], Alan immediately warns him to stay away from Sonia. Intimidated, Felix agrees.

Rumours about Felix begin to spread around Walford, leading Sonia and her friend [[Clare Bates|Clare Tyler]] to think that he had murdered his wife, cut her to pieces and buried her in the basement of his shop. They are terrified of him, even more so when Clare enters the shop on a dare and notices that he has a [[razor|cut throat razor]]. Clare runs away when Felix refuses to tell her what is in his basement, and she immediately assumes his dead wife must have been down there. She, Sonia and [[Janine Butcher]] steal Felix's keys and sneak into the dark basement where Clare trips and knocks herself out. Panicking, Sonia and Janine run to [[The Queen Victoria]] [[public house]] and tell Clare's stepfather [[Nigel Bates]] that she has been [[kidnapping|kidnapped]]. Nigel and the Mitchell brothers, [[Grant Mitchell (EastEnders)|Grant]] and [[Phil Mitchell|Phil]], find Felix unbuttoning Clare's clothing and immediately suspect the worst. Grant attacks Felix and only stops when Clare tells that him Felix is merely taking care of her, following her fall. As she looks around the cellar, she discovers that all Felix has to hide is a vast collection of [[butterfly|butterflies]].

The residents all apologise to Felix the next day, and they learn the story behind Felix's collection of butterflies. They learn that Felix is a Polish [[Jew]] who had been living in [[Kraków]] during World War II when [[Germany]] invaded and most Jewish residents were placed in [[Nazism|Nazi]] concentration camps. Felix's father refused to flee Poland, as he would not leave his precious collection of butterflies behind. When the Nazis came to arrest his family, he and his sister hid, but he sneezed, revealing their hiding place. His sister was found but Felix escaped with a small box of butterflies. He travelled from Poland to [[England]], where he was taken in by his uncle. He believed that the rest of his family had perished, and blamed himself for his sister's death. He continued to collect butterflies in his father's honour ever since.

Felix befriends the other senior residents of Walford, [[Jules Tavernier (EastEnders)|Jules Tavernier]], [[Ethel Skinner]], [[Blossom Jackson]] and [[Nellie Ellis]]. He and Jules often play [[chess]] together in The Queen Victoria pub. Felix is left furious during a chess tournament when Jules keels over while asleep, scattering the chess pieces in the process.

Even though Felix does not know where his family are or even if they are still alive, he has spent his life trying to find them. He eventually discovers that his sister has survived and she is living in [[Israel]]. After making contact with her, he decides to leave Walford to live there with her. He later returns for a brief visit in May 1997 to tie up some loose ends. On his return, he asks Blossom Jackson to go on holiday to Israel with him, and they depart that month. 

The hint of romance between Felix and Blossom remains just that, and Blossom returns to England. When Blossom returns for her great grandson [[Billie Jackson|Billie]]'s funeral in October 2010, she reveals she and Felix had reconciled but he had died of an illness five years previously.
{{-}}

==April Branning==
{{Main|April Branning}}
'''April Branning''' was played by [[actress]], [[Debbie Arnold]]. April is the eldest child of [[Jim Branning|Jim]] and [[Reenie Branning]], and sister of [[Carol Jackson]], [[Derek Branning|Derek]], [[Suzy Branning|Suzy]], [[Max Branning|Max]] and [[Jack Branning]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{EastEnders}}
{{EastEnders characters|year}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Eastenders Characters (1995)}}
[[Category:Lists of EastEnders characters|1995]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1995|*, EastEnders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
