<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2357049" ns="0" title="Richard Trumka"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-protected|small=yes}}
{{Infobox person
|name        = Richard Trumka
|image      = Richard Trumka.jpg
|imagesize   =
|caption     =
|birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|1949|07|24}}
|birth_place = [[Nemacolin, Pennsylvania|Nemacolin]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[United States|U.S.]]
|death_date  =
|death_place =
|other_names =
|known_for   = President, United Mine Workers of America; Secretary-Treasurer, AFL-CIO; President, AFL-CIO
|occupation  = Miner; Labor leader; Attorney/Litigator
|nationality = American
}}
'''Richard Louis Trumka''' (born July 24, 1949)&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot;&gt;''Who's Who in America.'' 62nd ed. New Providence, N.J.: Marquis Who's Who, 2007. ISBN 0083797011&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[organized labor]] leader in the [[United States]]. He was elected President of the [[AFL-CIO]] on September 16, 2009, at the [[National trade union center|labor federation]]'s convention in [[Pittsburgh]], [[Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;SweeneyRetire&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/16/business/16labor.html Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Promising a New Day, Again.&quot;] ''New York Times.'' September 15, 2009; [http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/13/us/13labor.html Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Labor Leader Is Stepping Down Both Proud and Frustrated.&quot;] ''New York Times.'' September 12, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; He served as the Secretary-Treasurer of the AFL-CIO, from 1995 to 2009, and prior to that was President of the [[United Mine Workers]] from 1982 to December 22, 1995.  Mr. Trumka was named in Esquire Magazine's 2011 Americans of the Year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esquire.com/features/americans-2011/richard-trumka-1211 Esquire's 2011 Americans of the Year, November 21, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life and career==
Trumka, born in [[Nemacolin, Pennsylvania]] near Pittsburgh, is an [[Italian American]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.osia.org/public/foundation/about-gala.asp Richard Trumka Awarded 2003 Sons of Italy Foundation Humanitarian Award]&lt;/ref&gt; third-generation  [[Polish American]], [[Roman Catholic]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholicnews.com/data/stories/cns/1001332.htm Pattison, Mark. &quot;Catholic Upbringing Gave AFL-CIO Leader Sense of Fairness, Justice.&quot; ''Catholic News Service.'' March 30, 2010.]&lt;/ref&gt; [[coal mining|coal miner]] son of Frank Richard and Eola Elizabeth (Bertugli) Trumka.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Combative&quot; /&gt; He went to work in the [[Mining|mine]]s in 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;Combative&quot; /&gt; He received a [[bachelor of science]] degree from [[Pennsylvania State University]] in 1971 and a [[law degree]] from [[Villanova University]] in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jim McKay, &quot;From Mines to Summit of Unionism,&quot; ''Pittsburgh Post-Gazette,'' October 23, 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; He married Barbara Vidovich in 1982.  They have one son.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1982/11/28/us/around-the-nation-umw-chief-married-threat-upsets-schedule.html &quot;U.M.W. Chief Married; Threat Upsets Schedule.&quot;] ''Associated Press.'' November 28, 1982.&lt;/ref&gt;

===National labor career===
From 1974 to 1979, Trumka was a staff attorney with the United Mine Workers at their headquarters in [[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot; /&gt; He was elected to the board of directors of UMWA District 4 in 1981 and became President of the United Mine Workers in 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot; /&gt;

While President of the UMWA, Trumka led a successful nine-month [[labor strike|strike]] against the [[Pittston Coal strike|Pittston Coal Company]] in 1989, which became a symbol of resistance against employer cutbacks and retrenchment for the entire labor movement.&lt;ref&gt;Frank Swoboda, &quot;Coal Miner Strike Was Symbol for Labor Movement,&quot; ''Washington Post,'' January 2, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;  A major issue in the dispute was Pittston's refusal to pay into the industrywide health and retirement fund created in 1950. Trumka encouraged non-violent [[civil disobedience]] to confront the company and relied on a [[comprehensive campaign|corporate campaign]] involving [[Wall Street]] investors.

The United Mine Workers conducted a nationwide strike against Peabody Coal in 1993. Trumka was asked to respond to the possibility that some coal companies might hire permanent replacement workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;RegisterGuard&quot;&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Y24VAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=duoDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4062,549653&amp;dq=im+saying+if+you+strike+a+match+and+you+put+your+finger+in+it+you-re+likely+to+get+burned&amp;hl=en McClain, John D. &quot;Coal Miners' President Says Violence Possible.&quot; ''Eugene Register-Guard.'' September 3, 1993.]&lt;/ref&gt; He told the ''[[Associated Press]]'' in September 1993, &quot;I'm saying if you strike a match and you put your finger in it, you're likely to get burned.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McClain, John D. &quot;Violence Possible, UMW Chief Says.&quot; ''Virginian-Pilot.'' September 3, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; He also said, &quot;That doesn't mean I'm threatening to burn you. That just means if you strike the match, and you put your finger in it, common sense will tell you it'll burn your finger. Common sense will tell you that in these strikes, that when you inject [[Strikebreaker|scabs]], a number of things happen. And a confrontation is one of the potentials that can happen. Do I want it to happen? Absolutely not. Do I think it can happen? Yes, I think it can happen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RegisterGuard&quot; /&gt; The ''Associated Press'' reported that he was not threatening violence, and noted that UMWA staff had spent &quot;thousands of man hours trying to prevent anything from happening ... to our members or by our members.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Y24VAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=duoDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4062,549653&amp;dq=im+saying+if+you+strike+a+match+and+you+put+your+finger+in+it+you-re+likely+to+get+burned&amp;hl=en McClain, John D. &quot;Coal Miners' President Says Violence Possible.&quot;  ''Eugene Register-Guard.'' September 3, 1993.] Ellipsis in original.&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides his domestic labor activities, Trumka established an office that raised U.S. mineworker solidarity with the miners in [[South Africa]] while they were fighting [[apartheid]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anc.org.za/show.php?doc=ancdocs/history/aam/conference/shill.html Hill, Sylvia. &quot;Presentation: The Free South African Movement.&quot; African National Congress. October 10-13, 2004.]&lt;/ref&gt; He further served as the U.S. [[Shell Oil|Shell]] [[boycott]] chairman, which challenged the multinational Royal Dutch/Shell Group for its continued business dealings in South Africa. For these steps, Trumka received the 1990 [[Letelier-Moffitt Human Rights Award]].

During his tenure as Secretary-Treasurer of the AFL-CIO, Trumka focused on creating investment programs for the [[pension]] and [[fringe benefits|benefit]] funds of the labor movement, capital market strategies,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mcclatchydc.com/homepage/story/76439.html Stephen F. Diamond. &quot;Commentary: Trumka may give AFL-CIO the vitality it sorely needs.&quot;  McClatchy-Tribune News Service. October 2, 2009.]&lt;/ref&gt; and demanding corporate accountability to America's communities. He chaired the AFL-CIO Industrial Union Council, a consortium of manufacturing unions focusing on key issues in trade, health care and labor law reform.  He co-chairs the [[China Currency Coalition]], an alliance of industry, agriculture, services, and worker organizations whose stated mission is to support U.S. manufacturing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/pressRelease/idUS173377+02-May-2008+PRN20080502 &quot;China Currency Coalition Applauds Senator Obama's Support of S. 796, The Fair Currency Act of 2007.&quot;] Press release.  China Currency Commission. May 2, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

But Trumka's tenure as Secretary-Treasurer was not without controversy. In 1996, [[Teamsters]] president [[Ron Carey (labor leader)|Ron Carey]] was locked in a tight reelection battle with [[James P. Hoffa]], son of disappeared Teamsters president [[Jimmy Hoffa]] and a long-time Teamsters union attorney. Hoffa was also out-raising Carey in funds by more than 4-to-1, but the Carey campaign was convinced it could win if the campaign could bypass the local leadership (which supported Hoffa) and get his message directly to Teamsters members.&lt;ref name=&quot;RushforCash&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DC173BF932A1575AC0A961958260&amp;scp=52&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Behind Turmoil For Teamsters, Rush for Cash.&quot; ''New York Times.'' September 21, 1997.]&lt;/ref&gt; Martin Davis, a Carey campaign consultant who owned The November Group (a direct-marketing company), allegedly contacted Trumka in the summer of 1996 and concocted a scheme whereby the Teamsters would donate $150,000 to the AFL-CIO for spurious [[getting out the vote|get-out-the-vote]] efforts and the AFL-CIO would pay the same amount to [[Citizen Action]] (a liberal grassroots lobbying and organizing group).&lt;ref name=&quot;RushforCash&quot; /&gt; Citizen Action would then pay $100,000 to The November Group, which would use the cash to finance Carey's direct marketing effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;BarsTeamsterLeader&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E2D91E38F93BA25752C1A961958260&amp;scp=88&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;An Overseer Bars Teamster Leader From Re-Election.&quot; ''New York Times.'' November 18, 1997].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7D91E38F93AA2575AC0A961958260&amp;scp=49&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;3 Teamster Aides Make Guilty Pleas and Hint At Plot.&quot; ''New York Times.'' September 19, 1997.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ProposedDeal&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2DB1038F93BA2575AC0A961958260&amp;scp=45&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven and Van Natta, Don, Jr. &quot;Proposed Deal With Democrats Draws Focus of Investigators in Teamsters Election.&quot; ''New York Times.'' September 18, 1997].&lt;/ref&gt; The alleged scheme was revealed on August 22, 1997, by a federal government official overseeing the Teamsters' election.&lt;ref name=&quot;ProposedDeal&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MoneyScheme&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE3DD103EF930A1575BC0A961958260&amp;scp=29&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Labaton, Stephen. &quot;Federal Report Describes Teamster Money Scheme.&quot; ''New York Times.'' August 23, 1997.]&lt;/ref&gt; The federal government overturned Carey's successful reelection, and ordered a new election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2DF103EF930A1575BC0A961958260&amp;scp=30&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Teamster Voting That Chose Carey Declared Invalid.&quot; ''New York Times.'' August 23, 1997.]&lt;/ref&gt; On November 17, 1997, a federal official disqualified Carey from seeking elective office in the union.&lt;ref name=&quot;BarsTeamsterLeader&quot; /&gt; Carey was indicted on federal perjury charges in January 2001,&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DC143FF935A15752C0A9679C8B63&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Ex-President of Teamsters Is Charged With Lying.&quot; ''New York Times.'' January 26, 2001.]&lt;/ref&gt; pled not guilty,&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3D9153EF931A35751C0A9679C8B63&amp;scp=4&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Ramirez, Anthony. &quot;Metro Briefing.&quot; ''New York Times.'' February 2, 2001.]&lt;/ref&gt; and was found not guilty on all charges on October 12, 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cleared&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2D9123FF930A25753C1A9679C8B63&amp;scp=12&amp;sq=%22Ron+Carey%22&amp;st=nyt Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Former Teamsters President Is Cleared of Lying Charges.&quot; ''New York Times.''October 13, 2001.]&lt;/ref&gt; Trumka invoked his [[Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution|Fifth Amendment right against self-incrimination]] during the government's [[grand jury]] investigation and a congressional panel, but was never charged with any crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;TrumkaFifth&quot;&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=aXDR8281bQlw Rosenkrantz, Holly. &quot;Trumka Has Detractors, Not Opponents, in AFL-CIO Bid.&quot; ''Bloomberg Business News.'' June 8, 2009.] Accessed 2011-03-23.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TellsFaith&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/01/us/afl-cio-chief-tells-panel-of-faith-in-deputy.html Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;A.F.L.-C.I.O. Chief Tells Panel of Faith in Deputy.&quot; ''New York Times.'' May 1, 1998].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Teamster Aide's Conviction May Lead to Fraud.&quot; ''Detroit News.'' November 21, 1999.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the AFL-CIO had a policy (enacted in the wake of several Teamsters' scandals in the late 1950s) appearing to require anyone who asserted their Fifth Amendment rights to be removed from office, AFL-CIO President [[John Sweeney (labor leader)|John Sweeney]] wrote in a letter sent to AFL-CIO member unions in November 1997 that the AFL-CIO policy regarding assertion of Fifth Amendment rights had &quot;never been applied by the federation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CancelsTestimony&quot;&gt;Sammon, Bill. &quot;House Subcommittee Cancels AFL-CIO Officials' Testimony.&quot; ''Washington Times.'' April 30, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; The letter went on to say that &quot;The policy calls for removal only when the union determines that the Fifth Amendment is being invoked to conceal discovery of corruption. The AFL-CIO, as you know, has for some time been conducting its own internal inquiry and has no basis to conclude that there was any unlawful conduct by Secretary-Treasurer Trumka. ... It is clear that the policy does not apply.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;CancelsTestimony&quot; /&gt; During testimony before a congressional subcommittee on April 30, 1998, Sweeney said that a December 1957 resolution adopted by the AFL-CIO amended the policy so that it would not be automatically invoked but rather applied only if the invocation of Fifth Amendment rights were used &quot;as a shield to avoid discovery of corruption&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;TellsFaith&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sweeney's testimony was paraphrased by the ''[[Associated Press]]'' to the same effect. See: Galvin, Kevin. &quot;AFL-CIO Head Defends Aide.&quot; ''Associated Press.'' April 30, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; The labor federation appeared satisfied that Trumka should not step down. After Trumka spoke to an executive session of the AFL-CIO Executive Board in January 1998, board members said their concerns about Trumka's involvement in the scandal had been alleviated.&lt;ref&gt;Galvin, Kevin. &quot;Labor Sets 1998 Agenda.&quot; ''Associated Press.'' January 31, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; On April 30, 1998, Sweeney said no evidence had yet come to light indicating any wrongdoing by Trumka.&lt;ref name=&quot;TellsFaith&quot; /&gt;

On July 1, 2008, Trumka delivered a speech attacking [[racism]] in the [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 presidential election]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Combative&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.madison.com/tct/opinion/294460 John Nichols, &quot;AFL's Trumka: Labor Must Battle Racism to Elect Obama,&quot; ''Capital Times,'' July 3, 2008.]&lt;/ref&gt;  A video &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7QIGJTHdH50 AFL-CIO's Richard Trumka on Racism and Obama]&lt;/ref&gt; with an excerpt of the speech attracted more than 535,000 hits on [[YouTube]] as of July 1, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Combative&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/03/business/03labor.html Greenhouse, Steven. &quot;Combative Union Leader Steps From the Shadows.&quot;] ''New York Times.'' July 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;  Trumka's video was &quot;surely the first YouTube moment in the history&quot; of the labor movement.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/09/06/AR2009090602292.html Alec MacGillis, &quot;No Getting Around This Guy AFL-CIO's Richard Trumka Aims to Hold That Line on Health Care,&quot;] ''Washington Post,'' September 7, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Trumka was elected president of the AFL-CIO after the retirement of [[John Sweeney (labor leader)|John Sweeney]] in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;SweeneyRetire&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Organized labour}}
{{Commonscat-inline}}
*[http://www.aflcio.org AFL-CIO]
*[http://www.umwa.org United Mine Workers of America]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7QIGJTHdH50 Richard Trumka speech attacking racism in the 2008 presidential election]
*[http://www.ips-dc.org/about/letelier-moffitt The Letelier-Moffitt Human Rights Award]

{{Start box}}
{{Succession box|
  before= [[John Sweeney (labor leader)|John Sweeney]] |
  title= President, [[AFL-CIO]] |
  years= 2009 - |
  after= Incumbent
}}
{{Start box}}
{{Succession box|
  before= [[Sam Church]] |
  title= President, [[United Mine Workers of America]] |
  years= [[1982]] - [[1995]] |
  after= [[Cecil Roberts (unionist)|Cecil Roberts]]
}}
{{End box}}
{{AFL-CIO}}

{{Persondata         &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              =Trumka, Richard
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =July 24, 1949
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Nemacolin, Pennsylvania|Nemacolin]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[United States|U.S.]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Trumka, Richard}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:AFL–CIO people]]
[[Category:American labor leaders]]
[[Category:American lawyers]]
[[Category:American Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania State University alumni]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania political activists]]
[[Category:People from Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:American people of Polish descent]]
[[Category:United Mine Workers of America]]
[[Category:Villanova University School of Law alumni]]

[[fr:Richard Trumka]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
