<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23616636" ns="0" title="Hassan al-Banna"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox officeholder
| name        = Hasan al-Banna&lt;br /&gt;{{lang|ar|حسن البنا}}
|image       =
|office      = 1st General Guide of the Egyptian [[Muslim Brotherhood]]
|president   = 
|term_start  = 1928
|term_end    = 1949
|predecessor = 
|successor   = [[Hassan al-Hudaybi]]
|birth_date  = {{Birth date|1906|10|14}}
|birth_place = [[Mahmoudiyah, Egypt|Mahmoudiyah]], [[Beheira Governorate|Beheira]], [[Egypt]]
|death_date  = {{Death date and age|1949|02|12|1906|10|14}}
|death_place = [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]]
|religion      = [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] [[Islam]]
|otherparty  = 
|alma_mater  = [[Dar al-Ulum]]
}}
'''Sheikh Hasan Ahmed Abdel Rahman Muhammed al-Banna''' ({{lang-ar|حسن أحمد عبد الرحمن محمد البنا}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈħæsæn ˈæħmæd ʕæbdeɾɾˤɑħˈmɑːn mæˈħæmmæd elˈbænnæ|IPA}}) known as '''Hasan al-Banna''' (born on October 14, 1906 – February 12, 1949) was a schoolteacher and imam, best known for founding the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], one of the largest and most influential 20th century [[Islamic revival|Muslim revivalist]] organizations.

==Biography==
===Early life===
Banna was born in 1906 in [[Mahmoudiyah, Egypt]] (north-west of [[Cairo]] in the Nile delta).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mitchell|1993|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; His father, Sheikh Ahmad 'Abd al-Rahman al-Banna al-Sa'ati, was a local [[imam]] (prayer leader) and [[masjid]] teacher of the [[Hanbali]] rite. He was educated at Dar Al-Uloum school in Cairo [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdcd.j0s2yt0jfme6y.html [Islam times&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;]. He wrote and collaborated on books on [[Muslim]] traditions, and also had a shop where he repaired watches and sold gramophones.  Though Sheikh Ahmad al-Banna and his wife owned some property, they were not wealthy and struggled to make ends meet, particularly after they moved to Cairo in 1924. Like many others, they found that Islamic learning and piety were no longer as highly valued in the capital, and that craftsmanship could not compete with large-scale industry.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, 1.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lia, 22-24.&lt;/ref&gt;

When Hasan al-Banna was twelve years old, he became involved in a [[Sufism|Sufi]] order, and became a fully initiated member in 1922.&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, 2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lia, 25-26.&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of thirteen, he participated in [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]] during the [[revolution]] of 1919 against [[History of Modern Egypt|British rule]].&lt;ref&gt;Mitchell, 3.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lia, 26-27.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Establishment of the Muslim Brothers===
It was to spread this message that Al-Banna launched the society of the [[Muslim Brothers]] in March 1928. At first, the society was only one of the numerous small Islamic associations that existed at the time. Similar to those that Al-Banna himself had joined since he was 12, these associations aimed to promote personal piety and engaged in charitable activities. By the late 1930s, it had established branches in every Egyptian province. 

A decade later, it had 500,000 active members and as many sympathizers in Egypt alone, while its appeal was now felt in several other countries as well. The society's growth was particularly pronounced after Al-Banna relocated its headquarters to [[Cairo]] in 1932. The single most important factor that made this dramatic expansion possible was the organizational and ideological leadership provided by Al-Banna.

In [[Ismaïlia]], he preached in the mosque, and even in coffee-houses, which were then a novelty and were generally viewed as morally suspect. At first, some of his views on relatively minor points of Islamic practice led to strong disagreements with the local religious élite, and he adopted the policy of avoiding religious controversies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell 7&quot;&gt;Mitchell, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lia, 32-35.&lt;/ref&gt;

He was appalled by the many conspicuous signs of foreign military and economic domination in Isma'iliyya: the [[United Kingdom|British]] military camps, the public utilities owned by foreign interests, and the luxurious residences of the foreign employees of the [[Suez Canal Company]], next to the squalid dwellings of the Egyptian workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell 7&quot;/&gt;

===Political Activity===
He endeavored to bring about the changes he hoped for through institution-building, relentless activism at the grassroots level, and a reliance on mass communication. He proceeded to build a complex mass movement that featured sophisticated governance structures; sections in charge of furthering the society's values among peasants, workers, and professionals; units entrusted with key functions, including propagation of the message, liaison with the Islamic world, and press and translation; and specialized committees for finances and legal affairs.

In anchoring this organization into Egyptian society, Al-Banna relied on pre-existing social networks, in particular those built around mosques, Islamic welfare associations, and neighborhood groups. This weaving of traditional ties into a distinctively modern structure was at the root of his success. Directly attached to the brotherhood, and feeding its expansion, were numerous businesses, clinics, and schools. In addition, members were affiliated to the movement through a series of cells, revealingly called ''usar'' (families. singular: ''[[usrah]]''). 

The material, social and psychological support thus provided were instrumental to the movement's ability to generate enormous loyalty among its members and to attract new recruits. The services and organizational structure around which the society was built were intended to enable individuals to reintegrate into a distinctly Islamic setting, shaped by the society's own principles.

Rooted in [[Islam]], Al-Banna's message tackled issues including [[colonialism]], [[public health]], [[educational]] policy, [[natural resources]] management, [[Marxism]], [[social inequalities]], [[Arab nationalism]], the weakness of the Islamic world on the international scene, and the growing conflict in [[Mandate Palestine|Palestine]]. By emphasizing concerns that appealed to a variety of constituencies, Al-Banna was able to recruit from among a cross-section of Egyptian society — though modern-educated civil servants, office employees, and professionals remained dominant among the organization's activists and decisionmakers. Al-Banna was also active in resisting British rule in [[Egypt]].


===Last Days and Assassination===
Between 1948 and 1949, shortly after the society sent volunteers to fight in the [[1948 Israeli-Arab War|war in Palestine]], the conflict between the [[Kingdom of Egypt|monarchy]] and the society reached its climax. Concerned with the increasing assertiveness and popularity of the brotherhood, as well as with rumors that it was plotting a [[coup]], [[Prime Minister of Egypt|Prime Minister]] [[Mahmoud an-Nukrashi Pasha]] disbanded it in December 1948. The organization's assets were impounded and scores of its members sent to jail. Following Pasha's assassination, Al-Banna promptly released a statement condemning the assassination, stating that terror is not an acceptable way in Islam.{{cn|date=November 2011}}

This in turn prompted the assassination of Al-Banna. On February 12, 1949 in [[Cairo]], Al-Banna was at the Jamiyyah al-Shubban al-Muslimeen headquarters with his brother in-law [[Abdul Karim Mansur]] to negotiate with Minister [[Zaki Ali Basha]] who represented the government side.  Minister [[Zaki Ali Basha]] never arrived.  By 5 o'clock in the evening Al-Banna and his brother-in-law decided to leave. The assassination happened when Al-Banna and his brother in-law called a taxi. As they stood waiting for the taxi, they were shot by two men. He was still alive for several hours after the shooting and saving him would have been possible if it was not for orders by the government at the time to not allow any doctors or medical help from reaching him. As a result, he eventually died of his wounds and lack of medical attention.

In honor of his death in 1949, he was often referred to as '''&quot;As-Syahid Imam Hassan Al-Banna&quot;''',or '''The Martyr Imam Hassan Al-Banna'''.

==Legacy==

Hasan al-Banna is known to have great impact in the modern Islamic thought.&lt;ref&gt;Wright, 19&lt;/ref&gt;

He is the grandfather of [[Tariq Ramadan]] and older brother of [[Gamal al-Banna]].

==See also==
* [[History of the Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{Wikiquote}}
*{{cite book |last=Gensicke |first=Klaus |year=2007 |title=Der Mufti von Jerusalem und die Nationalsozialisten: Eine politische Biographie Amin el-Husseinis |location=Darmstadt |publisher=Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft |isbn=9783534208081 }} {{de icon}}
*{{cite book |last=Lia |first=Brynjar |year=1998 |title=The Society of the Muslim Brothers in Egypt: The Rise of an Islamic Mass Movement |location=Reading, UK |publisher=Garnet |isbn=0863722202 }}
*{{cite book |last=Mallmann |first=Klaus-Michael |lastauthoramp=yes |first2=Martin |last2=Cüppers |year=2006 |title=Halbmond und Hakenkreuz: Das Dritte Reich, die Araber und Palästina |location=Darmstadt |publisher=Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft |isbn=3534197291 }}
*{{citation|last=Mitchell|first=Richard P.|year=1993|title=The Society of the Muslim Brothers|location=London |publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-508437-5|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=ltVtj3Kh7IIC&amp;printsec=frontcover}}
*{{cite journal |last=Soage |first=Ana B. |year=2008 |title=Hasan al-Banna or the politicisation of Islam |journal=Totalitarian Movements and Political Religions |volume=9 |issue=1 |pages=21–42 |doi= }}
*{{Cite book
| publisher = Knopf
| isbn = 037541486X
| last = Wright
| first = Lawrence
| authorlink = Lawrence Wright
| title = [[The Looming Tower]]: Al-Qaeda and the Road to 9/11
| date = 2006-08-08
| page = 480
}}
* [http://www.youngmuslims.ca/biographies/display.asp?ID=8 Hasan Al-Banna&lt;!-- bot-generated title --&gt;] at www.youngmuslims.ca

==External links==
* [http://www.hassanalbanna.org www.hassanalbanna.org]
* [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdcd.j0s2yt0jfme6y.html biography]
* [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdcg.79wrak97tj54a.html Founder of the Muslim Brotherhood, Al-Banna was one of the century's most original thinkers]
* [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdcc.iq0a2bqisy-82.html The Ten Principles of Hasan al-Banna]
* [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdcd.x0o2yt0xxme6y.html Letter to a Muslim Student]
* [http://www.islamtimes.org/vdca.unyk49nuogt14.html Hasan al-Banna]
* [http://www.makingsenseofjihad.com/albannas_on_jihad/ &quot;''On Jihad''&quot; from ''Five Tracts of Hasan al-Banna'']

{{start box}}
{{s-rel}}
{{succession box|title=General Guide of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]]|before=''New position''|after=[[Hassan al-Hudaybi]]|years=1928&amp;ndash;1949}}
{{end box}}

{{IslamismNorthAfrica}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Banna, Hasan Al
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =October 14, 1906
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Mahmoudiyah, Egypt|Mahmoudiyah]], [[Beheira Governorate|Beheira]], [[Egypt]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =February 12, 1949
| PLACE OF DEATH    =[[Cairo]] [[Egypt]]
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Banna, Hasan Al}}
[[Category:1906 births]]
[[Category:1949 deaths]]
[[Category:Al-Azhar University alumni]]
[[Category:Assassinated Egyptian politicians]]
[[Category:Assassinated people]]
[[Category:Assassinated politicians]]
[[Category:Egyptian Islamists]]
[[Category:Egyptian religious leaders]]
[[Category:Murder in 1949]]
[[Category:Muslim activists]]
[[Category:Muslim Brotherhood]]
[[Category:Muslim Brotherhood leaders]]
[[Category:Muslim philosophers]]
[[Category:People murdered in Egypt]]

[[ar:حسن البنا]]
[[az:Həsən Bənna]]
[[bn:হাসান আল বান্না]]
[[br:Hasan Al-Banna]]
[[ca:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[cs:Hasan al-Banná]]
[[de:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[es:Hasan al-Banna]]
[[fa:حسن‌البنا]]
[[fr:Hassan el-Banna]]
[[id:Hasan al-Banna]]
[[it:Hasan al-Banna]]
[[he:חסן אל-בנא]]
[[jv:Hasan al-Banna]]
[[hu:Haszan al-Banna]]
[[ml:ഹസനുൽ ബന്ന]]
[[arz:حسن البنا]]
[[ms:Hassan al Banna]]
[[nl:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[ja:ハサン・アル＝バンナー]]
[[no:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[pnb:حسن البنا]]
[[ps:حسن البنا]]
[[pl:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[pt:Hassan al Banna]]
[[ru:Аль-Банна, Хасан]]
[[sq:Hasan El-Bena]]
[[so:Sheekh Xasan Albanaa]]
[[fi:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[sv:Hassan al-Banna]]
[[th:ฮาซัน อัลบันนา]]
[[tr:Hasan el-Benna]]
[[uk:Гасан аль-Банна]]
[[ur:حسن البنا]]
[[zh:哈桑·班納]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
