<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="236486" ns="0" title="Coat of arms of the Philippines"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{infobox coat of arms
|name             = Coat of Arms of the Philippines
|image            = Coat of Arms of the Philippines.svg
|image_caption    = 
|image_width      = 200
|year_adopted     = July 3, 1946
|middle           = Coat of arms of the Philippines (per 1998 Law).svg
|middle_width     = 150
|middle_caption   = Version passed by the Congress in 1998. It must be approved by a referendum before becoming official
|armiger          = [[Philippines]]
|shield           = Paleways of two (2) pieces, azure and gules; a chief argent studded with three (3) mullets equidistant from each other; and, in point of honor, ovoid argent over all the sun rayonnant with eight minor and lesser rays. 
|crest            = 
|supporters       = 
|motto            = [[Republic of the Philippines]]&lt;br /&gt;''Republika ng Pilipinas''
|other_elements   = Bald Eagle of the United States&lt;br /&gt;and Lion-Rampant of Spain (the charge of [[Kingdom of León]])&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;These elements were not included in Republic Act No. 8491 in 1998, and therefore considered removed, but the change has not been implemented pending ratification by national referendum.&lt;/small&gt;
|earlier_versions = With motto: ''&quot;Isang Bansa, Isang Diwa&quot;''&lt;br /&gt;With scroll reading: &quot;Republic of the Philippines&quot;
|use              = Various [[Government of the Philippines|Philippine Government]] departments
}}

The '''Coat of Arms of the Philippines''' features the eight-rayed sun of the [[Philippines]] with each ray representing the eight provinces ([[Batangas]], [[Bulacan]], [[Cavite]], [[Manila]], [[Laguna (province)|Laguna]], [[Nueva Ecija]], [[Pampanga]] and [[Tarlac]]) which were placed under martial law by [[Governor-General of the Philippines|Governor-General]] [[Ramón Blanco]] during the [[Philippine Revolution]], and the three five-pointed stars representing the three primary geographic regions of [[Luzon]], [[Visayas]], and [[Mindanao]]. In the blue field on the left side is the Eagle of the [[United States]], and in the red field on the right is the Lion-Rampant of [[Spain]], both representing colonial history. It is also used by the [[Philippine National Bank]]. The [[blazon]] of the coat of arms from Flag and Heraldic Code of the Philippines (Republic Act 8491) is as follows: 

{{quote|''...Paleways of two (2) pieces, azure and gules; a chief argent studded with three (3) mullets equidistant from each other; and, in point of honor, ovoid argent over all the sun rayonnant with eight minor and lesser rays. Beneath shall be the scroll with the words &quot;REPUBLIKA NG PILIPINAS,&quot; inscribed thereon.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Chan Robles Virtual Law Library - Republic Act No. 8491 |accessdate=2010-11-10 |url=http://www.chanrobles.com/republicacts/republicactno8491.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==History==
[[File:Escudo de Manila.svg|thumb|90px|left|Coat of arms of Manila, created by Royal Decree]]
The Philippine heraldic symbol begin when [[King Philip II of Spain]] authorize the first coat of arms to [[City of Manila]] through the royal decree issued on March 20, 1596 is as follows:

{{quote|''...a shield will have in the center of its upper part a golden castle on the red field, closed by a blue door and windows, and shall be surmounted by a crown; and in the lower half on the blue field a half lion and a half dolphin of silver, armed and languid gules - that is to say, with red nails and tongue, the said lion shall hold in his paw sword with guard and hilt''}}

[[File:Escudo del rey de España abreviado antes de 1868 con toisón.svg|thumb|90px|left|Coat of arms of the [[Spanish East Indies]] (1565–1899).]]
Eventually the seal evolved and changes some details and features, but the principal devices remained unaltered. The new design was patterned after the national standard of Spain, the seal consist of [[fleur-de-lis]]  surrounded by quartered flag of Castille and Aragon represented by thwo golden castles located on the red field and two red lions on a white field. The seal was later adopted by Spanish colonial government.
  
During [[Philippine Revolution]] in 1896, the Filipino leaders had no permanent political symbol, however two different coat of arms was easily adopted by the Filipinos, both arms consist of an equilateral triangle, but differs on symbols found inside the triangle. many documents of [[Katipunan]] bore a letter K which stand for Kalayaan (Liberty), while  some had the rising mythological sun in the center. General [[Emilio Aguinaldo]] adopted the mythological sun and five  pointed stars in each angle of the equilateral triangle as their coat of arms.

During American occupation, a law was enacted prescribing the new coat of arms for the Philippines
. At this time, the Manila coat of arms adopted by Spanish colonial government was still in use until 1905 when [[Philippine Commission]] adopted the &quot;new arms and great seal of the Philippine Islands&quot; designed by Gaillard Hunt of the US State Department. It consist of 13 alternating red and white stripes representing 13 original colonies of America; a chief blue above, the honor color, and over them  in an oval the arms of Manila with the castle of Spain and the sea lion prominently displayed it also consist of a American eagle, the symbol of United States. beneath the shieldwas the scroll with the words ''Philippine Islands''. It remained unaltered until the inauguration of [[Commonwealth of the Philippines]] in 1935.

During [[Commonwealth of the Philippines|Commonwealth Era]], extensive reform was mad to the government in preparation for Philippine independence. One of major changes is changing symbol for Filipinos. &quot;The Arms and Great seal of the Commonwealth Government of the Philippines&quot; was approved in 1935, the number of stripes reduce from thirteen to two and three five-pointed stars were added. The eagle was slightly enlarge and place closer to the arm. the word ''Commonwealth of the Philippines'' replaced ''Philippine Islands'' in the scroll below, it also incorporated the modified seal of City of Manila.

On December 15, 1938, President [[Manuel Quezon]] created the Special Committee of Arms of the Philippines. After almost two years of studying, The committee recommend certain modifications to the coat of arms of the Commonwealth of the Philippines. They recommend that the eight ray Philippine sun must be the point of honor. It was revised in 1940, It featured two stripes, blue on the right side while red on the left side of the shield; a chief white field above, studded  with tree five-pointed stars equidistant from each other, over them, the eight-ray sun in rayonant with each ray flanked on the both sides of minor rays inside an oval. On the crest is the American eagle, her talon grasping an olive branch with eight leaves and eight fruits, and the left talon grasping three spears, beneath the shield is the scroll with inscription ''Philippines''

Following the providing appropriate symbols to various branches of the government. President Quezon  created the Philippine Heraldic Committee in 1940. The committee was assigned the studying and recommending the designs and symbolism for official seals of Philippines' political subdivision, cities and government institutions. The heraldic work of the committee was suspended during [[Pacific War]].

during the [[Second Philippine Republic]], a more nationalistic policy were adopted, the seal was revised, Foreign components of the Filipino heraldic symbol which previously representing its  colonial links to [[Spain]] and [[United States]] were removed, Instead salient features of the falg and seal of short-lived [[First Philippine Republic|Philippine Republic]] were incorporated, which consist of the eight-ray mythological sun and three stars located beneath the  equilateral triangle. Written within three sets of two marginal lines of the tree sides of the triangle were ''Kalayaan, Kapayapaan, Katarungan'' (Liberty, Peace, Justice). Around the seal was a double marginal circle within which was written ''Republika ng Pilipinas'' (Republic of the Philippines)

[[File:Coat of arms of the Commonwealth of the Philippines.png|thumb|90px|Arms of the [[Commonwealth of the Philippines]] (1939-1946).]]
After the [[World War II]], President [[Sergio Osmena]] reactivate the Philippine Heraldic Committee. the new design pursuant to Commonwealth Act No. 731 was approved by the [[Congress of the Philippines]] on July 3, 1946, It was designed by Captain Galo B. Ocampo, secretary of the [[National Historical Institute (Philippines)|Philippine Heraldry Committee]]it consist of the Philippine Sun with eight rays, occupies the point of honor in the center, while three five-pointed stars, representing [[Luzon]], [[Visayas]] and [[Mindanao]], occupy the upper portion of the field. On the right side, on the blue field is the bald-headed American eagle and on the left side, on the red field, the lion rampant of Spain, beneath the arms is scroll inscribed with the words ''Republic of the Philippines''

During [[Ferdinand Marcos|Marcos administration]], The ''Isang Bansa, Isang Diwa'' (One Nation, One Spirit) become the national motto of the Philippines. It was immediately incorporated in to the national seal replacing the words ''Republic of the Philippines'' which were originally inscribed in a scroll beneath the arms, it was approved by the Office of the President on July 31, 1978. The revision of the national seal is due to belief of President Marcos that under his government New Society Program, the ultimate unity of the Filipinos could be achieved through the active participation of every citizen motivated by one guiding spirit. When President [[Corazon Aquino]] took over the government. She obliterate any Marcos contribution to the Philippine History. The Philippine coat of arms was reverted, removing the national motto pursuant to Republic Act No. 8491 approved on February 12, 1998. The original design has been followed until now.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=vqKsKUUSNNQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Footnotes to Philippine History]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.antiqbook.com/boox/witt/08-0342.shtml Coat of arms under American administration]

{{Symbols of the Philippines}}
{{Coats of arms of Asia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Coat Of Arms Of The Philippines}}
[[Category:National symbols of the Philippines]]
[[Category:National coats of arms|Philippines]]

[[ar:شعار الفلبين]]
[[bs:Grb Filipina]]
[[ca:Escut de les Filipines]]
[[cs:Státní znak Filipín]]
[[de:Wappen der Philippinen]]
[[el:Εθνόσημο των Φιλιππίνων]]
[[es:Escudo de Filipinas]]
[[fr:Armoiries des Philippines]]
[[ko:필리핀의 국장]]
[[hr:Grb Filipina]]
[[bpy:ফিলিপাইনর চিনত্হান]]
[[id:Lambang Filipina]]
[[he:סמל הפיליפינים]]
[[lt:Filipinų herbas]]
[[hu:A Fülöp-szigetek címere]]
[[mk:Грб на Филипини]]
[[nl:Wapen van de Filipijnen]]
[[ja:フィリピンの国章]]
[[no:Filippinenes riksvåpen]]
[[pl:Herb Filipin]]
[[pt:Brasão de armas das Filipinas]]
[[ru:Герб Филиппин]]
[[sco:Coat o airms o the Philippines]]
[[sh:Grb Filipina]]
[[fi:Filippiinien vaakuna]]
[[sv:Filippinernas statsvapen]]
[[tl:Sagisag ng Pilipinas]]
[[th:ตราแผ่นดินของฟิลิปปินส์]]
[[uk:Герб Філіппін]]
[[yo:Coat of arms of the Philippines]]
[[zh:菲律賓國徽]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
