<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23757" ns="0" title="Purdue University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Redirect6|Purdue|other members of this university system|Purdue University system|all other uses}}
{{Infobox university
|name           = Purdue University
|image_name     = Purdue University Seal.svg
|image_size     = 150px
|motto          = &lt;!-- please see talk page before changing --&gt;
|established    = May 6, 1869
|type           = [[public university|Public]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Flagship campus|Flagship]]&lt;br/&gt;[[land-grant university|Land-Grant]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Sea grant colleges|Sea-Grant]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Space grant colleges|Space-Grant]]
|calendar       = Semester
|endowment      = US$1.630 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]] (systemwide)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = nacubo.org/Research/NACUBO_Endowment_Study Public_NCSE_Tables| date = May 31, 2011 | url =http://nacubo.org/id/43224690 | accessdate =2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president      = [[France A. Córdova]]
|provost        = [[Timothy D. Sands]]
|city           = [[West Lafayette, Indiana|West Lafayette]]
|state          = [[Indiana]]
|country        = U.S.
|students       = 39,697 (Fall 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue5&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/DataDigest/pages/fastfacts/fast2.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2009–10 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad      = 31,145 (Fall 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue5&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad       = 8,552 (Fall 2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue5&quot;/&gt;
|faculty        = 6,614
|Rank           = 66th
|campus         = Large town: {{convert|2474|acre|km2}}&lt;br /&gt;plus {{convert|15108|acre|km2}} for agricultural and industrial research&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Data Digest West Lafayette 2006–2007 &gt; Facilities &gt; Land and Facilities | publisher=Purdue University | accessdate=2007-09-22 | url=http://www.purdue.edu/DataDigest/pages/facilities/fa_land.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors = Old Gold and Black &lt;span style=&quot;background:#B1946C; width:50px; border:1px solid #000;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span style=&quot;background:black; width:50px; border:1px solid #000;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;
| Color1           = Old Gold
| Color1Hex        = B1946C
| Color2           = Black
| Color2Hex        = 000000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Purdue Identity Graphics Standards | publisher=Purdue University | accessdate=2008-11-28 | url=http://www.extension.purdue.edu/ktgmarketing/StandardsManual_screen.pdf|format=PDF}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|free_label     = [[College athletics|Athletics]]
|free           = 18 Division I / IA [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] teams
|mascot         = [[Boilermaker Special]]
|nickname       = [[Purdue Boilermakers|Boilermakers]]
|affiliations   = [[Purdue University system]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Association of American Universities]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Committee on Institutional Cooperation]]
|website        = [http://www.purdue.edu www.purdue.edu]
|logo           = [[File:Purdue University Wordmark.svg|center|200px]]
|footnotes      =
}}

'''Purdue University''', located in [[West Lafayette, Indiana|West Lafayette]], Indiana, U.S., is the [[flagship university]] of the six-campus [[Purdue University system]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Purdue Points of Pride | publisher=Purdue University | accessdate=2009-11-02 | url=http://www.purdue.edu/UNS/pridepoints/970321.Points.pride.html |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20040508100503/http://www.purdue.edu/UNS/pridepoints/970321.Points.pride.html |archivedate = May 8, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue was founded on May 6, 1869, as a [[land-grant university]] when the [[Indiana General Assembly]], taking advantage of the [[Morrill Land-Grant Colleges Act|Morrill Act]], accepted a donation of land and money from [[Lafayette, Indiana|Lafayette]] businessman [[John Purdue]] to establish a college of science, technology, and agriculture in his name.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=About Purdue &gt; Purdue History | publisher=Purdue University | accessdate=2009-11-02 | url=http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/about/history.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first classes were held on September 16, 1874, with six instructors and 39 students.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue.edu&quot;/&gt; Today, Purdue enrolls the second largest student body of any university in Indiana as well as the second largest [[international student]] population of any public university in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2009a/08CordovaInternational.html | accessdate = 2010-08-02 | title = Purdue's international student population 2nd largest among U.S. public universities  |year= 2008 | last = Sen | first = Soumitro | publisher=Purdue University }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Purdue offers both [[undergraduate education|undergraduate]] and [[graduate school|graduate]] programs in over 210 [[academic major|major]] areas of study. The university has also been highly influential in America's [[aviation history|history of aviation]], having established the first [[credit (education)|college credit]] offered in [[flight training]], the first four-year bachelor's degree in aviation, and the first university airport ([[Purdue University Airport]]). In the mid-20th century, Purdue's aviation program expanded to encompass advanced [[spaceflight]] technology giving rise to Purdue's nickname, ''Cradle of Astronauts''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.purdue.edu/UNS/astro/astromain.html |title = Purdue Astronauts |publisher=Purdue University News Service |accessdate = 2006-06-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20041216032631/http://www.purdue.edu/UNS/astro/astromain.html |archivedate = December 16, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-two Purdue graduates have gone on to become astronauts, including [[Gus Grissom]] (one of the original [[Mercury Seven]] astronauts), [[Neil Armstrong]] (the first person to walk on the moon), and [[Eugene Cernan]] (the most recent person to walk on the moon).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | title =History of the Purdue School of Aeronautics and Astronautics  | work=College of Engineering web site | publisher=Purdue University | url =https://engineering.purdue.edu/AAE/AboutUs/History }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:JohnPurdue.jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[John Purdue]], the university's namesake]]
In 1865, the [[Indiana General Assembly]] voted to take advantage of the [[Morrill Land-Grant Acts|Morrill Land-Grant Colleges Act of 1862]], and began plans to establish an institution with a focus on agriculture and engineering. Communities throughout the state offered their facilities and money to bid for the location of the new college. Popular proposals included the addition of an agriculture department at [[Indiana University]] or at what is now [[Butler University]]. By 1869, [[Tippecanoe County]]’s offer included $150,000 from Lafayette business leader and philanthropist [[John Purdue]], $50,000 from the county, and 100 acres (40 ha) of land from local residents. On May 6, 1869, the General Assembly  established the institution in Tippecanoe County as Purdue University, in the name of the principal benefactor. Classes began at Purdue on September 16, 1874, with six instructors and 39 students.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue.edu&quot;/&gt;  A campus of five buildings was completed by the end of the year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/?page=purduefaq |title=Frequently Asked Questions about Purdue History |at=What were the first buildings on campus? |publisher=Purdue Libraries, Archives and Special Collections |accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue issued its first degree, a Bachelor of Science in chemistry, in 1875 and admitted its first women students that fall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/content/John%20Bradford%20Harper.pdf |title=John Bradford Harper: the first graduate of Purdue University |first=David M. |last=Hovde |year=2009 |publisher=Purdue Libraries, Archives and Special Collections |format=PDF |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Topping, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Emerson E. White]], the university’s president from 1876 to 1883, followed a strict interpretation of the Morrill Act. Rather than emulate the classical universities, White believed that Purdue should be an &quot;industrial college&quot; and devote its resources toward providing a [[liberal education|liberal]] (or broad) education with an emphasis on science, technology, and agriculture. He intended not only to prepare students for industrial work, but also to prepare them to be good citizens and family members.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, pp. 89–94, 97–100.&lt;/ref&gt; Part of White’s plan to distinguish Purdue from classical universities included a controversial attempt to ban fraternities. This ban was ultimately overturned by the [[Indiana Supreme Court]] and led to White’s resignation.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, pp. 107–111.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image: LOC 6a04356u 1904 Panorama of campus, Purdue Univ.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.5|A view of Purdue University in 1904]]
In the late 1890s former U.S. President [[Benjamin Harrison]] served on the board of trustees and delivered lectures about world affairs.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, pp. 130–131.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the end of the nineteenth century, the university was organized into schools of agriculture, engineering (mechanical, civil, and electrical), and pharmacy. Purdue had a number of engineering laboratories, including testing facilities for a locomotive and a [[Corliss steam engine]], one of the most efficient engines of the time. The School of Agriculture was sharing its research with farmers throughout the state with its cooperative extension services and would undergo a period of growth over the following two decades. Programs in education and home economics were soon established, as well as a short-lived school of medicine.

President [[Edward C. Elliott]] oversaw a campus building program between the world wars. Inventor, alumnus, and trustee David E. Ross coordinated several fundraisers, donated lands to the university, and was instrumental in establishing the Purdue Research Foundation. Ross’s gifts and fundraisers supported such projects as [[Ross–Ade Stadium]], the [[Purdue Memorial Union|Memorial Union]], a civil engineering surveying camp, and the [[Purdue University Airport]]. The Purdue Airport was the country’s first university-owned airport and the site of the country’s first college-credit flight training courses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aiaa.org/Participate/Uploads/05-0443westlafayette.pdf |title=Historic Aerospace Site: Purdue University Airport, West Lafayette, Indiana |author=American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics |year=2005 |pages=2–3 |format=PDF |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Amelia Earhart]] joined the Purdue faculty in 1935 as a consultant for these flight courses and as a counselor on women’s careers. In 1937, the Purdue Research Foundation provided the funds for the [[Lockheed Model 10 Electra|Lockheed Electra 10-E]] that Earhart flew on her attempted round-the-world flight. 

Every school and department at the university was involved in some type of military research or training during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; During a project on radar receivers, Purdue physicists discovered properties of [[germanium]] that led to the making of the first [[transistor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.computerhistory.org/semiconductor/timeline/1941-semiconductor.html |title=1941 - Semiconductor diode rectifiers serve in WW II |year=2007 |work=The Silicon Engine: A Timeline of Semiconductors in Computers |publisher=[[Computer History Museum]] |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pbs.org/transistor/science/info/germanium.html |title=Germanium Comes of Age |year=1999 |work=Transistorized! The History of the Invention of the Transistor |publisher=PBS.org |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Army and the Navy conducted training programs at Purdue and more than 17,500 students, staff, and alumni served in the armed forces.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue also set up about a hundred centers throughout Indiana to train skilled workers for defense industries.&lt;ref&gt;Topping. p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt; As veterans returned to the university under the [[G.I. Bill]], first-year classes were taught at some of these sites to alleviate the demand for campus space. Four of these sites are now degree-granting regional campuses of the [[Purdue University system]]. Purdue’s on-campus housing became racially desegregated in 1947, following pressure from Purdue President [[Frederick L. Hovde]] and Indiana Governor [[Ralph F. Gates]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/orthefirenexttime |title=Or the Fire Next Time: A Timeline of African American History at Purdue |year=2010 |author=Purdue Libraries, Archives and Special Collections |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Topping, p. 355.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, Hovde worked to expand the academic opportunities at the university. The 1950s saw a decade-long construction program with an emphasis on science and research. The university established programs in veterinary medicine, industrial management, and nursing, as well as the first computer science department in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cs.purdue.edu/history/history.html |title=History of the Department of Computer Sciences at Purdue University |first1=John R. |last1=Rice |first2=Saul |last2=Rosen |date=1994 |publisher=Purdue University |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Undergraduate humanities courses were strengthened, although Hovde only reluctantly approved of graduate-level study in these areas. Purdue awarded its first Bachelor of Arts degrees in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;Topping, p. 321.&lt;/ref&gt; The programs in liberal arts and education, formerly administered by the School of Science, were soon split into their own school.

In recent years, Purdue’s leaders have continued to support high-tech research and international programs. In 1987, U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]] visited the West Lafayette campus to give a speech about the influence of technological progress on job creation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Reagan Hails U.S. Technology's Role |first=Gerald M. |last=Boyd |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1987/04/10/us/reagan-hails-us-technology-s-role.html |newspaper=The New York Times |date=April 10, 1987 |page=A12 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1990s, the university expanded its course offerings in foreign languages and world cultures and added more opportunities to study abroad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Campus Life: Purdue; The Race Is On To Ready Students For Globalization |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/03/25/style/campus-life-purdue-the-race-is-on-to-ready-students-for-globalization.html |newspaper=The New York Times |date=March 25, 1990 |page=47 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The first buildings of the Discovery Park interdisciplinary research center were dedicated in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.insideindianabusiness.com/newsitem.asp?id=12097 |title=Purdue Dedicates Center For Entrepreneurship |date=October 21, 2004 |work=Inside Indiana Business |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue launched a Global Policy Research Institute in 2010 to explore the potential impact of technical knowledge on public policy decisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=NSF director to lead new Purdue research institute |url=http://www.newsday.com/news/nation/nsf-director-to-lead-new-purdue-research-institute-1.1743660 |agency=Associated Press |newspaper=Newsday |date=February 5, 2010 |accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[File:Engineeringmallentrance.jpg|thumb|left|View of the entrance to the Engineering Mall]]
Purdue's campus is situated in the small city of [[West Lafayette, Indiana|West Lafayette]], near the western bank of the [[Wabash River]]. State Street, which is concurrent with [[Indiana State Road 26|State Road 26]], divides the northern and southern portions of campus. Academic buildings are mostly concentrated on the eastern and southern parts of campus, with residence halls to the west, and athletic facilities to the north. The [[Greater Lafayette Public Transportation Corporation]] (CityBus) operates eight campus loop bus routes on which students, faculty, and staff can ride free of charge.

===Purdue Mall===
[[File:Purdue Engineering Fountain.JPG|thumb|right|Engineering Fountain]]
The Purdue Mall is the central quad of Purdue University. It is also known as the Engineering Mall, due to its proximity to several engineering buildings. The most prominent feature of the Purdue Mall is the {{convert|38|ft|m|adj=on}}-tall concrete [[Engineering Fountain]], and also features the [[Frederick L. Hovde]] Hall of Administration, which houses the office of the university president, [[France A. Córdova]]. The [[Purdue Bell Tower]] is located between the Purdue and Memorial Malls. The Bell Tower is considered an icon of the university and can be found on many Purdue logos and those of the cities of [[Lafayette, Indiana|Lafayette]] and [[West Lafayette, Indiana|West Lafayette]].

&lt;!-- [[File:Hall of Music, Purdue.JPG|thumb|Edward C. Elliott Hall of Music]] --&gt;
Southwest of the Purdue Mall is the [[Edward C. Elliott Hall of Music]], one of the largest [[proscenium|proscenium theaters]] in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.housing.purdue.edu/HTML/HallOfMusic/venues/elliott/elliott.html |title=Hall of Music Productions – Venues – Purdue University |publisher=Housing.purdue.edu |date=1990-09-30 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue's Student Concert Committee often invites famous entertainers to perform there for an audience of students, faculty, and the general public. Also near the Purdue Mall is Felix Haas Hall, which was constructed in 1909 as Memorial Gymnasium in memory of the 17 Purdue University football players, coaches, alumni, and fans who perished in the [[Purdue Wreck]] railroad accident on October 31, 1903. The structure was renovated in 1985 to house the Computer Science department. In 2006, it was renamed in honor of retired Provost Felix Haas and began to also house the Statistics department.

===Memorial Mall===
[[File:Purdue Student Union.JPG|thumb|right|Purdue Memorial Union]]
The Purdue Memorial Mall, located south of the Purdue Mall, is the original section of campus. A popular meeting place for students, the grassy, open Memorial Mall is surrounded by the Stewart Student Center, Stanley Coulter Hall, the Class of 1950 Lecture Hall, Recitation Building, Beverly Stone Hall, and University Hall. The Memorial Mall also features the Hello Walk. East of the Memorial Mall is the [[Purdue Memorial Union]], Purdue's [[student activity center|student union]] building, and the adjacent Union Club Hotel.

University Hall is the only building remaining from the original six-building campus. Construction began in 1871, when the building was known as &quot;The Main Building&quot;. The building was dedicated in 1877 and the project cost $35,000 to complete. University Hall originally housed the office of the president, a chapel, and classrooms, but was remodeled in 1961 to house only the department of history and classrooms used by the School of Liberal Arts. At the request of [[John Purdue]], he was buried in the Memorial Mall, directly across from the main entrance of University Hall.&lt;ref&gt;Purdue Libraries, Archives and Special Collections. (2009). [http://www.lib.purdue.edu/spcol/johnpurdue/death.php &quot;Themes: Death and funeral&quot;]. ''Portrait of a founder: John Purdue and Purdue University'' online exhibit. Retrieved April 30, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===South campus===
The area south of State Street is home to Purdue's agricultural, fine arts and veterinary buildings. This area also includes the [[Purdue University Horticulture Gardens|Horticulture Gardens]], [[Discovery Park (Purdue)|Discovery Park]], and the [[Purdue University Airport|Purdue Airport]].

[[File:Greenhouses @ Purdue.jpg|thumb|Greenhouses on South Campus]]

===West campus===
The western portion of campus consists of student housing, dining, and recreation facilities. Students can play club and [[intramural sports]] at the Recreational Sports Center, the Boilermaker Aquatic Center, and the intramural playing fields in this area. Purdue's Recreational Sports Center, built in 1957, is the first building in the nation created solely to serve university student recreational needs. From January 2011 until August 2012, the building will undergo a [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]]-certified expansion and renovation project to become the Student Wellness and Fitness Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Purdue trustees advance recreational and grounds facilities |author=Schenke, Jim |agency=Purdue University News Service |date=December 4, 2009 |url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2009b/091204BOTFacilities.html |accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Stadium area===
Much of the northern part of campus sits on land purchased for the university by industrialist [[David E. Ross]] and author &amp; humorist [[George Ade]]. David Ross is one of two people buried on Purdue's campus (the other being John Purdue).  Many of Purdue's athletic facilities are located there, including [[Ross–Ade Stadium]] ([[American football]]), [[Mackey Arena]] (basketball), and [[Lambert Fieldhouse]] (indoor [[track &amp; field]]). This area also includes the [[Slayter Center of Performing Arts]] and Cary Quadrangle, one of the largest all-male housing units in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;housing.purdue.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.housing.purdue.edu/HTML/Housing/Cary_Quadrangle | accessdate=2009-08-25 | publisher=Purdue University Housing and Food Services | title=Cary Quadrangle }}&lt;/ref&gt;  David Ross's grave site is in a garden atop the hill just to west of the Slayter band shell.

==Academics==
===Organization and administration===
&lt;!-- Colleges/schools according to Purdue listing at http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/about/colleges_schools.html --&gt;
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin-left:1em; font-size:90%; line-height:1.4em; width:300px;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; | '''College/school founding'''
|-
| '''College/school''' || '''Year founded'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |&lt;hr&gt;
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Agriculture|College of Agriculture]] || 1869
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Education|College of Education]] || 1908
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]] || 1876
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Health and Human Sciences|College of Health and Human Sciences]] || 1905
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Liberal Arts|College of Liberal Arts]] || 1953
|-
| [[Krannert School of Management]] || 1962
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Pharmacy|College of Pharmacy]]|| 1884
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Science|College of Science]] || 1907
|-
| [[Purdue University College of Technology|College of Technology]] || 1964
|-
| [[Purdue University School of Veterinary Medicine|School of Veterinary Medicine]] || 1877
|}
Purdue offers more than 200 options for major areas of study at the West Lafayette campus alone, and a variety of options for minors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/academics/index.html |title=Purdue University – Academics |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue is organized into eight colleges and schools contained within larger colleges; the two exceptions are the [[Krannert School of Management]] and the [[Purdue University School of Veterinary Medicine|School of Veterinary Medicine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/about/colleges_schools.html |title=Purdue University – Colleges/Schools |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; These two academic units retained their &quot;school&quot; status during a university-wide renaming policy in 2004 and 2005 in deference to national [[professional school]] naming conventions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/uns/html3month/2004/041119.BOT.facilities.html |title=Purdue trustees name academic units, 4 buildings, 1 department |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=November 19, 2004 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 1, 2010 the College of Health and Human Sciences was formed. The new college was created by combining existing academic units. These units include the School of Nursing, the School of Health Sciences, the College of Consumer and Family Sciences, and non-humanities majors from the College of Liberal Arts; namely psychology and hearing and speech pathology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.hhs.purdue.edu/about/about.html |title=Purdue College of Health and Human Sciences |publisher=Hhs.purdue.edu |date=July 1, 2010 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[University President]], appointed by the [[Board of Trustees]], is the [[chief administrative officer]] of the university. The office of the president oversees admission and registration, student conduct and counseling, the administration and scheduling of classes and space, the administration of student athletics and organized extracurricular activities, the libraries, the appointment of the faculty and conditions of their employment, the appointment of all non-faculty employees and the conditions of employment, the general organization of the university, and the planning and administration of the university budget.

The Board of Trustees directly appoints other major officers of the university including a [[provost (education)|provost]], who serves as the chief academic officer for the university, a number of vice presidents with oversight over specific university operations, and the satellite campus chancellors.

===Research===
The University expended $472.7 million in support of research system-wide in 2006–07, using funds received from the state and federal governments, industry, foundations, and individual donors. The faculty and more than 400 research laboratories put Purdue University among the leading research institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Purdue University – Facts Online – Research| url = http://www.purdue.edu/facts/research.html| accessdate =March 9, 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue University is considered by the [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education]] to have &quot;very high research activity&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=16817&amp;start=782 |title=Carnegie Classifications |publisher=Carnegiefoundation.org |date=2007-05-10 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue also was rated the nation's fourth best place to work in academia, according to rankings released in November 2007 by ''[[The Scientist]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gawrylewski |first=Andrea |url=http://www.the-scientist.com/article/display/53733/ |title=Purdue pushes forward :The Scientist [2007-11-01&amp;#93; |publisher=The-scientist.com |date=2007-11-01 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue's researchers provide insight, knowledge, assistance, and solutions in many crucial areas. These include, but are not limited to Agriculture; Business and Economy; Education; Engineering; Environment; Healthcare; Individuals, Society, Culture; Manufacturing; Science; Technology; Veterinary Medicine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/research/research_areas.html |title=Purdue University – Research Areas |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:MSEE.jpg|thumb|Materials Science and Electrical Engineering Building]]
Purdue University generated a record $333.4 million in sponsored research funding during the 2007–08 fiscal year with participation from [[National Science Foundation]], [[National Aeronautics and Space Administration]], and the U.S. departments of [[United States Department of Agriculture|Agriculture]], [[United States Department of Defense|Defense]], [[United States Department of Energy|Energy]], and [[United States Department of Health and Human Services|Health and Human Services]].&lt;ref name=&quot;news.uns.purdue.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2008b/080804RebarResearchFunding.html |title=Purdue generates record $333.4 million in research funding |publisher=News.uns.purdue.edu |date=2008-08-04 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Purdue University established the [[Discovery Park (Purdue)|Discovery Park]] to bring innovation through multidisciplinary action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/dp/index.php |title=Discovery Park at Purdue University |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In all of the eleven centers of Discovery Park, ranging from entrepreneurship to energy and advanced manufacturing, research projects reflect a large economic impact and address global challenges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.nanohub.org/resources/5025/ |title= Discovery Park at Purdue University: Engine for Academic and Commercial Growth |author=Buck, Charles; Sharma, Pankaj (2008) |accessdate= 2008-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue University's nanotechnology research program, built around the new Birck Nanotechnology Center in Discovery Park, ranks among the best in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/x/2007a/070612SandsSmalltimes.html |title=Purdue's nanotechnology research facilities rank 8th in U.S. survey |publisher=News.uns.purdue.edu |date=2007-06-12 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Purdue Research Park]] which opened in 1961&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/html3month/020110.B.Research.park.html |title=Purdue Research Park |publisher=News.uns.purdue.edu |date=2002-01-10 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; was developed by Purdue Research Foundation&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prf.org/index.asp |title=Purdue Research Foundation |publisher=Prf.org |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is a private, nonprofit foundation created to assist Purdue. The park is focused on companies operating in the arenas of life sciences, homeland security, engineering, advanced manufacturing and information technology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdueresearchpark.com/about/index.asp |title=Purdue Research Parks [ About the Parks &amp;#93; |publisher=Purdueresearchpark.com |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; It provides an interactive environment for experienced Purdue researchers and private business and high-tech industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceC&quot;/&gt; It currently employs more than 3,000 people in 155 companies, including 90 technology-based firms.&lt;ref name=&quot;news.uns.purdue.edu&quot;/&gt; The Purdue Research Park was ranked first by the Association of University Research Parks in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;research_park_rank&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| year = 2004
| url = http://www.aurp.net/more/awards.cfm
| title = AURP Annual Award Recipients: Outstanding Research/Science Park Achievement Award
| publisher=Association of University Research Parks
| accessdate = 2008-08-11
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080112195707/http://www.aurp.net/more/awards.cfm |archivedate = January 12, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
&lt;!-- U.S. rankings --&gt;
| ARWU_NU       = 40
| Forbes        =
| USNWR_NU      = 62
| Wamo_NU       = 79
&lt;!-- Global rankings --&gt;
| ARWU_W        = 61
| QS_W          = 85
| THES_W        = 98
}}
In national rankings for 2011, Purdue was ranked #40 by ARWU, #62 by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'', and #79 by ''[[Washington Monthly]]''. In global rankings for 2011, the university was ranked #61 by ARWU, #85 by [[QS]], and #98 by ''[[Times Higher Education World University Rankings|Times]]''.

===Sustainability===
Purdue's Sustainability Council, composed of University administrators and professors, meets monthly to discuss environmental issues and sustainability initiatives at Purdue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainability Council&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Sustainability Council
| publisher=Purdue University
| url =http://www.purdue.edu/sustainability/council.htm#
| accessdate = 2009-06-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The University is currently constructing its first [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] Certified building in an addition to the Mechanical Engineering building, which is to be completed in Spring 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus Buildings &amp; Features&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Campus Buildings &amp; Features
| publisher=Purdue University
| url =http://www.purdue.edu/sustainability/pages/campus_buildings.html
| accessdate = 2009-06-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The school is also in the process of developing an arboretum on campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Purdue's Sustainability Initiatives&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =Purdue's Sustainability Initiatives
| publisher=Purdue University
| url =http://www.purdue.edu/sustainability/pages/sustainability_initi.html
| accessdate = 2009-06-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, a system has been set up to display live data detailing current energy production at the campus utility plant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Purdue's Sustainability Initiatives&quot;/&gt; The school holds an annual &quot;Green Week&quot; each fall, an effort to engage the Purdue community with issues relating to environmental sustainability.&lt;ref name=&quot;GreenWeek 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title =GreenWeek 2008
| publisher=Purdue University
| url =http://www.purdue.edu/sustainability/
| accessdate = 2009-06-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
===Student body===
[[Image:PU grad.jpg|thumb|right|Graduation Ceremony]]
The Purdue student body is composed primarily of students from [[Indiana]]. In 2006–07, 23,086 out of a total of 39,288 students enrolled were Indiana residents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_county.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2007, the racial diversity of the undergraduate student body was 86.9% [[white people|white]], 5.51% [[Asian people|Asian]], 3.53% [[Black people|African American]], and 2.75% [[Hispanic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_race.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Of these students, 41.2% are female.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_gender.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Domestic minorities constitute a total of 15.4% in the Graduate student body population&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue2006&quot;/&gt; of which 38.5% are female.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue1&quot;/&gt; The largest minority (six percent of the full-time student body)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_int.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; is international, representing 123 countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_int_country.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; In graduate student population, non-residents occupy an overwhelming majority, about 78%.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_res.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost all undergraduates&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/students/stu_full_part.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and about 70% of the graduate student population attend full-time.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue3&quot;/&gt; The school's selectivity for admissions is &quot;more selective&quot; by [[USNWR]]: approximately 70% of applicants are admitted.

===Housing===
[[File:Cary Quad and Spitzer Court, Purdue University.png|thumb|left|Cary Quad and Spitzer Court at Purdue University]]
Purdue University operates fifteen separate [[residence hall]]s for its undergraduate and graduate students, including: Cary Quadrangle, [[Amelia Earhart|Earhart]] Hall, First Street Towers, [[Benjamin Harrison|Harrison]] Hall, Hawkins Hall, Hillenbrand Hall, Hilltop Apartments, [[John T. McCutcheon|McCutcheon]] Hall, Meredith Hall, Owen Hall, Purdue Village, Shreve Hall, [[Booth Tarkington|Tarkington]] Hall, [[Harvey Washington Wiley|Wiley]] Hall, and Windsor Halls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.housing.purdue.edu/HTML/Housing | accessdate=2009-08-25 | publisher=Purdue University Housing and Food Services | title=Housing Choices }}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the residence halls, Cary and Tarkington are male-only while Windsor is female-only; the remainder are [[coed]]. The newest residence hall, First Street Towers, opened in July 2009 and is exclusively for upperclassmen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.housing.purdue.edu/HTML/Housing/First_Street_Towers | accessdate=2009-08-25 | publisher=Purdue University Housing and Food Services | title=First Street Towers }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are 12 [[cooperative]] houses at Purdue (5 men's houses and 7 women's houses). The men's houses include Circle Pines, Fairway, Marwood, Chauncey, and Gemini. The women's houses include Ann Tweedale, Glenwood, Twin Pines, Maclure, Stewart, Devonshire, and Shoemaker. All cooperative houses are governed under the Purdue Cooperative Council which is led by Purdue University students who live in these houses. The cooperative system allows for a much lower cost of living than other types of housing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.purduecooperatives.org/home | accessdate=2007-11-16 | publisher=Purdue Cooperatives | title=Housing Cost Comparison }}&lt;/ref&gt; as the members take an active role in sharing chores and cooking all meals themselves, as opposed to hiring out cleaning and cooking staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue4&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/datadigest/2006-07/pages/instruction/in_activities_organi.htm |title=Purdue University Data Digest 2006–07 |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Purdue University hosts the nation's third largest [[fraternities and sororities|Greek community]], with approximately 5,000 students participating in one of the 46 men's fraternities or 29 women's sororities.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite news | publisher=[[Purdue Exponent]] | url=http://archive.purdueexponent.org/interface/bebop/showstory.php?date=2003/06/16&amp;section=campus&amp;storyid=Greeksystem | date=2003-06-16 | accessdate=2007-11-16 | title=5,000 students call Greek system their home | last=Poston | first=Heather }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several of Purdue's most distinguished graduates are members of fraternities and sororities.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue4&quot;/&gt; Purdue's Greek system is very strong and works together in various aspects, including the Inter-Fraternity Council, Panhellenic, and many very successful philanthropies. For example, in 2010, Zeta Tau Alpha's philanthropy, Big Man On Campus (BMOC) raised over $125,000 with the help of the rest of the Greek community, all benefitting Breast Cancer awareness and research. Every Chapter has their own national philanthropy dedicated to a certain cause that many chapters also participate in. Besides philanthropy, Purdue Greeks are involved all over campus including College Mentors for Kids, Purdue University Dance Marathon, Boiler Gold Rush, Purdue Student Government and many other various activities.

===Media===
The ''[[Purdue Exponent]]'', an independent [[student newspaper]], has the largest circulation of any Indiana college newspaper, with a daily circulation of 17,500 copies during the spring and fall semesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://archive.purdueexponent.org/?module=leftside&amp;target=aboutUs |title=The Exponent – Purdue's Student Newspaper |publisher=Purdueexponent.org |date=2008-02-16 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[WBAA]] is a radio station owned by Purdue University. The station operates on the AM frequency of 920&amp;nbsp;kHz and FM frequency of 101.3&amp;nbsp;MHz. Its studios are in the [[Edward C. Elliott Hall of Music]] on the Purdue campus, and the transmitters are located in [[Lafayette, Indiana]]. WBAA is the longest continuously-operating radio station in Indiana, having been licensed on April 4, 1922. WBAA airs [[National Public Radio|NPR]] and local news/talk programming during the day. Overnight, the AM station airs [[jazz]] while the FM station airs [[European classical music|classical music]].

There are also a few [[campus radio]] stations on campus. Currently, three radio stations operate from [[residence halls]], broadcasting via internet only; WCCR from Cary Quadrangle (not to be confused with the current WCCR FM or WCCR-LP stations in other states), WILY from Wiley Hall, and WHHR from Harrison Hall. A fourth student station, the Purdue Student Radio club operates from the [[Purdue Memorial Union]] and broadcasts on low power AM in addition to internet streaming.&lt;ref name=WCCRwebsite&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/WCCR |title=&quot;WCCR Website&quot; |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=September 1, 2005 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WILYwebsite&gt;[http://web.ics.purdue.edu/~wily/index.php &quot;WILY Radio Website&quot;]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AM1610website&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/radio |title=&quot;Purdue Student Radio AM1610 Website&quot; |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WHHRwebsite&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.ics.purdue.edu/~whhr/index.html |title=&quot;Harrison Hall Radio Website |publisher=Web.ics.purdue.edu |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

W9YB is the [[callsign]] of the [[Amateur Radio Club]] at Purdue University. W9YB also holds the self declared title of having one of the largest and most active collegiate [[amateur radio]] stations in the country. W9YB actively participates in [[emergency management]] for the [[Tippecanoe County]] area and maintains ready status with its members in skills to assist.&lt;ref name=w9ybwebsite&gt;[http://www.purdue.edu/w9yb &quot;W9YB Website&quot;]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Athletics===
{{See also|Purdue Boilermakers}}
[[File:Joe Tiller.jpg|thumb|right|Former Purdue Football head coach, [[Joe Tiller]]]]
Purdue is home to 18 Division I/I-A [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] teams including football, basketball, cross country, tennis, wrestling, golf, volleyball and others. Purdue is a founding member of the [[Big Ten Conference]], and played a central role in its creation. Traditional rivals include Big Ten colleagues the [[Indiana University (Bloomington)|Indiana]] [[Indiana Hoosiers|Hoosiers]], the [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|Illinois]] [[Illinois Fighting Illini|Fighting Illini]], and the [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]] [[Fighting Irish]] from the [[Big East Conference]] (football program independent, however). 

Purdue is tied with Alabama in producing the most Super Bowl winning quarterbacks. [[Len Dawson]] (SB IV, MVP), [[Bob Griese]] (SB VII and VIII), and [[Drew Brees]] (SB XLIV, MVP).

The Boilermaker men's and women's basketball teams have won more Big Ten Championships than any other conference school, with 27 conference banners, including a league-leading 22 for the men’s team. Purdue men's basketball has an all-time winning record against all Big Ten schools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oldgoldfreepress.com/columnist/OGFP_Staff/columns/3.shtml Old Gold Free Press |title=All-Time Big Ten Series Records |publisher=OldGoldFreePress.com |accessdate=May 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Insignia and traditions==
===Boilermakers===
[[File:Purdue Pete.svg|thumb|200px|Purdue Pete – one of the most recognized symbols of Purdue University]]
{{Main|Purdue Boilermakers}}
The moniker for the University's athletics teams has become a popular reference for all things Purdue. A reporter first used the name in 1891 to describe the year's winning football team and quickly gained approval from students.

===Mascots, logos, and colors===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Boilermaker special.jpg|thumb|[[Boilermaker Special]] - the official mascot of Purdue University]] --&gt;
In the more than 130 years since the founding of the university, several mascots have emerged in support of the Boilermaker athletic teams, including: The [[Boilermaker Special]], [[Purdue Pete]], and more recently, Rowdy.

The [[Boilermaker Special]] has been the official mascot of Purdue University since 1940. Designed to look like a train locomotive, the Special was originally designed to demonstrate Purdue's engineering programs and is maintained by the members of the Purdue Reamer Club.

As the unofficial mascot of Purdue Athletics, [[Purdue Pete]] is one of the most recognized symbols of Purdue University.

An {{convert|18|ft|m|adj=on}} statue of &quot;[[The Boilermaker]]&quot; was erected in 2005 across from Ross Ade Stadium.

Purdue University adopted its school colors, [[Old Gold]] and Black, in the fall of 1887. Members of Purdue's first football team in 1887 felt that the squad should be distinguished by certain colors, and since Princeton was at the time the most successful gridiron unit, its colors were considered. Though actually orange and black, the Princeton colors were known by many as yellow and black. Purdue gridders opted for old gold over yellow, kept the black, and began flying the colors that endure today.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://purduesports.cstv.com/trads/old-gold-black.html |title=Purdue Official Athletic Site |publisher=Purduesports.cstv.com |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Seal===
The official seal of Purdue was officially inaugurated during the University's centennial in 1969. The seal, approved by the Board of Trustees, was designed by Prof. Al Gowan, formerly at Purdue. It replaced one that had been in use for 73 years, but was never officially accepted by the board.

In medieval heraldry, a griffin symbolized strength, and Abby P. Lytle used it in her 1895 design for a Purdue seal. When Professor Gowan redesigned the seal, he retained the griffin symbol to continue identification with the older, unofficial seal. As on the older seal, the words &quot;Purdue University&quot; are set in the typeface Uncial. The three-part shield indicates three stated aims of the University: education, research, and service, replacing the words Science, Technology, and Agriculture on the earlier version.

===Song===
The official [[fight song]] of Purdue University, &quot;[[Hail Purdue!]]&quot;, was composed in 1912 by alumni Edward Wotawa (music) and James Morrison (lyrics) as the &quot;Purdue War Song&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/purdue/about/traditions.html |title=Purdue University – Purdue Traditions |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=1943-03-06 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Hail Purdue&quot; was copyrighted in 1913 and dedicated to the [[The Purdue Varsity Glee Club|Varsity Glee Club]].

===Grand Prix===
{{Main|Purdue Grand Prix}}

This 50-mile, 160-lap go-kart race is &quot;The Greatest Spectacle in College Racing&quot; and wraps up Gala Week each year. All 33 participating karts are made from scratch by student teams. The event has been raising money for student scholarships since it began in 1958.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purduegrandprix.org/?page=history |title=Purdue Grand Prix |publisher=Purdue Grand Prix |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was created as a counter-part to Indiana University's more established and well known [[Little 500]].

===Old Oaken Bucket===
Found on a farm in southern [[Indiana]], the oaken bucket is one of the oldest football trophies in the nation. The winner of the annual Purdue vs. [[Indiana University]] [[American football]] game gets to add a bronze &quot;P&quot; or &quot;I&quot; chain link and keep the trophy until the next face-off. Ironically, the first competition in 1925 led to a 0–0 tie, resulting in the first link on the chain being an &quot;IP.&quot; Purdue currently leads the trophy series at 55-26-3.

===Boiler Gold Rush===
Boiler Gold Rush (BGR) is Purdue's new-student orientation program.  BGR, which takes place before each fall semester, was formed to ease the transition to college for incoming students and to help them get acquainted with successful college life. The Boiler Gold Rush program was formed by Roger Sharritt in 1993.  In the first year, Sharritt’s operation, then called Corn Camp, served just 100 new students with around 15 staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Student Access, Transition and Success|title=Boiler Gold Rush|url=http://www.purdue.edu/sats/bgr/|accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Since 1993, the program has gone from being called Corn Camp to Boiler Gold Rush, has moved from operations in the Cary Quadrangle living residence to the Student Access, Transition and Success (SATS) office, and has increased from 100 students to over 5,500 in 2011. A few other significant changes include that the program now takes place the week immediately before the beginning of the fall semester and that during BGR, students live in the rooms they will be living in for the rest of the year, as was not the case in the first few years of the program’s development.

Boiler Gold Rush activities include speaker presentations from various academic, cultural, safety and professional organizations on campus, campus tours lead by Team Leaders, academic 'meet the schools' picnic and interest sessions, late night events at the Purdue Memorial Union, Recreational Sports Center and local stores, and a sports pep rally.

===Breakfast Club===

Students dress up in costumes – from traditional Halloween garb to creative, hand-made costumes as they bar-hop before Boilermaker home football games.  The Breakfast Club plays a significant role during the football season, combining the two most common college hobbies – drinking and football. It can best be described as a mixture between a pep rally and a Halloween party. Many football fans are very dedicated, getting up at 6&amp;nbsp;am on Saturdays and lining up at the bars on Chauncey Hill by 7&amp;nbsp;am.

==People==
{{Main|List of Purdue University people}}
===Faculty===
The original faculty of six in 1874 has grown to 2,563 tenured and tenure-track faculty in the Purdue Statewide System by Fall 2007 totals. The number of faculty and staff members system-wide is 18,872.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/facts/pages/faculty_staff.html |title=Purdue University Facts Online : Faculty and Staff |publisher=Purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The current faculty includes scholars such as [[Shreeram Shankar Abhyankar]] – known for his contributions to [[singularity theory]], [[Arden L. Bement Jr.]] – Director of the [[National Science Foundation]], [[R. Graham Cooks]], [[Joseph Francisco]], [[Douglas Comer]], [[Louis de Branges de Bourcia]] who proved the [[Bieberbach conjecture]], [[Ei-ichi Negishi]], [[Victor Raskin]], [[Michael Rossmann]] who mapped human common [[cold virus]], [[Leah Jamieson]], and [[H. Jay Melosh]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.purdue.edu/provost/shtml/profs.shtml ]{{Dead link|date=January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Purdue's tenured faculty comprises sixty [[Dean (education)|Academic Deans]], Associate Deans, and Assistant Deans; 63 Academic Department Heads; 753 Professors; 547 Associate Professors and 447 Assistant Professors. Purdue employs 892 non-tenure-track faculty, Lecturers, and Postdoctorals at its West Lafayette campus. Purdue employs another 691 tenured and 1,021 Non-Tenure Track Faculty, Lecturers, and Postdoctorals at its Regional Campuses and Statewide Technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

[[List of Purdue University people|Two faculty members]] have been awarded Nobel Prizes while at Purdue, in addition to a third laureate, [[Herbert C. Brown]], who was a former Purdue faculty member. In all seven Nobel Prizes have been associated with Purdue including [[alumni]], researchers, current and previous faculty.

===Alumni===
[[Image:Neil Armstrong pose.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Neil Armstrong]]]]
Purdue alumni has achieved strong recognition in a wide range of areas, but particularly in science and industry. The university's alumni pool collectively holds over 15,000 United States patents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/newsroom/general/2010/100807FACCommence.html |title=Purdue Newsroom – President tells graduates they're joining a special group: Purdue alumni |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=August 7, 2010 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Purdue has produced 22 astronauts, including [[Gus Grissom]], the first vertically launched person to return to space, [[Neil Armstrong]], the first to walk on the moon, and [[Eugene Cernan]], the last astronaut to do so.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/astro/namelog.html |title=Purdue Astronaut Alumni |publisher=News.uns.purdue.edu |date=1967-01-26 |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Over one third of all of NASA's manned space missions have had at least one Purdue graduate as a crew member.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.uns.purdue.edu/UNS/astro/astromain.html |title=Purdue Astronauts |publisher=News.uns.purdue.edu |accessdate=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; These individuals have led significant advances in research and development of aerospace technology and established an amazing record for exploration of space.

In science, Purdue has also produced a trio of Nobel prize winning physicists in [[Edward Mills Purcell]], [[Ben Roy Mottelson]] and [[Julian Schwinger]]; as well as a trio of Nobel prize winning chemists in [[Akira Suzuki (chemist)|Akira Suzuki]], [[Herbert C. Brown]] and [[Ei-ichi Negishi]]. Other noted Purdue alumni in science include pioneer of robotics and remote control technology [[Thomas B. Sheridan]] and Chinese physicist [[Deng Jiaxian]]. 

In business and economics, Purdue alumni include [[Stephen Bechtel]], the billionaire owner of [[Bechtel]] Corporation, Nobel prize winning economist [[Vernon L. Smith]], Federal Reserve Bank president [[Jeffrey Lacker]], popcorn inventor popcorn specialist [[Orville Redenbacher]]. In 2010, Bloomberg also revealed that Purdue was one of the universities in America with the most undergraduate alumni serving as chief executive officers of Standard &amp; Poor's 500 firms. They are [[Gregory Wasson]], president/CEO of Walgreen Co, [[Mark Miller]], chairman/president/CEO of Stericycle Inc,  [[Charles Davidson]], chairman/CEO of Noble Energy Inc, [[Samuel Allen]], chairman /president/CEO of Deere &amp; Co., Donald Thompson, president/COO of McDonald's Corp., and [[John Martin]], chairman/CEO of Gilead Sciences Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purdue.edu/newsroom/general/2010/100601BloombergCEO.html |title=Purdue Newsroom – Purdue on Bloomberg list for undergrad alumni as CEOs |publisher=Purdue.edu |date=June 1, 2010 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In government and culture, Purdue alumni include former [[Egypt]]ian Prime Minister [[Essam Sharaf]], [[Pulitzer Prize]] winners [[Booth Tarkington]] and [[John T. McCutcheon]], theater and television director [[Tom Moore (director)|Tom Moore]], CEO of Rand Corporation [[James Thomson (executive)|James Thomson]], founder and CEO of [[C-SPAN]] [[Brian Lamb]], former Governor of Indiana [[Harry G. Leslie]], former Governor of Mississippi [[Kirk Fordice]], former Secretary of the United States Department of Agriculture [[Earl L. Butz]], former United States Senator [[Birch Bayh]], 2012 Presidential Candidate [[Herman Cain]], Chinese nationalist General [[Sun Liren]], [[Anthony W. Miller]], United States Deputy Secretary of Education, and University of Chicago president [[Hugo F. Sonnenschein]]. 

In sports, Purdue has produced [[NCAA]] record-breaking basketball coaching legend [[John Wooden]], basketball Hall of Famer [[Rick Mount]], and NBA All-Stars [[Glenn Robinson]], [[Brad Miller (basketball)|Brad Miller]], [[Terry Dischinger]] and [[Joe Barry Carroll]].  Purdue has produced many quarterbacks for the NFL and Purdue quarterbacks have thrown for more yards and touchdowns in the NFL than that of any school.&lt;ref&gt;http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pur/sports/m-footbl/auto_pdf/08-mediaguide-section1.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Purdue has the distinction of having three NFL [[Super Bowl MVP]]-winning quarterbacks in [[Drew Brees]], [[Bob Griese]] and [[Len Dawson]]. Daytona 500 winner [[Ryan Newman]] graduated from Purdue with a Bachelor's degree in vehicle structure engineering.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purduesports.com/genrel/021708aab.html |title=Ryan Newman Wins Daytona 500 |publisher=Purduesports.com |date=February 17, 2008 |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Dauch Alumni Center acts as a showcase for the university's alumni and alumnae. The {{convert|67000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} center houses the offices of the Purdue Alumni Association and University Development. It is a destination and gathering area for the Purdue Alumni Association’s 68,000 members and more than 410,000 living alumni/alumnae.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.purduealum.org/dauch/pages/about/index.html |title=Purdue University Dauch Alumni Center – About the Center |publisher=Purduealum.org |accessdate=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Indiana}}
{{Wikipedia-Books}}
*[[Purdue University system]]
{{clear}}

==References==
;References
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
;Bibliography
* {{cite book |last=Topping |first=Robert W. |title=A Century and Beyond: The History of Purdue University |year=1988 |publisher=Purdue University Press |location=West Lafayette, Indiana |isbn=0-911198-95-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{Official|http://www.purdue.edu}}
* [http://www.purduesports.com Official athletics website]

{{PU}}
{{Big Ten Conference}}
{{Committee on Institutional Cooperation}}
{{Public colleges and universities in Indiana}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}

{{Coord|40.424|N|86.929|W|display=title|source:dewiki}}

[[Category:Purdue University| ]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Air traffic controller schools]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1869]]
[[Category:Committee on Institutional Cooperation]]
[[Category:Education in Tippecanoe County, Indiana]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Tippecanoe County, Indiana]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Tippecanoe County, Indiana]]
[[Category:West Lafayette, Indiana]]
[[Category:Forestry education]]

[[ar:جامعة بوردو]]
[[ca:Purdue University]]
[[cs:Purdue University]]
[[da:Purdue University]]
[[de:Purdue University]]
[[es:Universidad Purdue]]
[[fa:دانشگاه پردیو]]
[[fr:Université Purdue]]
[[ko:퍼듀 대학교]]
[[id:Universitas Purdue]]
[[is:Purdue-háskóli í West Lafayette]]
[[it:Università Purdue]]
[[la:Universitas Purdue]]
[[mr:पर्ड्यू विद्यापीठ]]
[[arz:جامعة پورديو]]
[[nl:Purdue-universiteit]]
[[ja:パデュー大学]]
[[no:Purdue University]]
[[pnb:پرڈیو یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Purdue University]]
[[pt:Universidade de Purdue]]
[[ru:Университет Пердью]]
[[simple:Purdue University]]
[[sk:Purdueova univerzita]]
[[fi:Purduen yliopisto]]
[[sv:Purdue University]]
[[te:పర్డ్యూ విశ్వవిద్యాలయం]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยเพอร์ดู]]
[[vi:Đại học Purdue]]
[[zh:普渡大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
