<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2377011" ns="0" title="Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{coord|40.438948|N|79.947705|W|type:landmark|display=title}}
{{Infobox_nrhp | name = Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens
| nrhp_type =
| designated_other1_name = City of Pittsburgh Historic Structure
| designated_other1_date = December 26, 1972&lt;ref name=&quot;CPHD list&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.phlf.org/historic-plaque-program/local-historic-designations/ | title = Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation: Local Historic Designations| date =2002-05-01 | accessdate = 2009-07-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| designated_other1_abbr = CPHS
| designated_other1_link = List of City of Pittsburgh historic designations
| designated_other1_color = black
| designated_other1_textcolor=gold
| designated_other2_name = Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation Historic Landmark
| designated_other2_date = 1970&lt;ref name=&quot;PHLF list&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.phlf.org/plaques/locallist.html | title = Internet Archive: Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation: PHLF Plaques &amp; Registries| date=2007-01-27 | accessdate = 2009-07-11 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070127092030/http://www.phlf.org/plaques/locallist.html |archivedate=2007-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  | designated_other2_abbr = [[Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation|PHLF]]
  | designated_other2_link = List of Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation Historic Landmarks
  | designated_other2_color = gold
  | designated_other2_textcolor=black
| image = Phipps conservatory 0.JPG
| imagesize = 300px
| caption = Main entrance to Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens
| location= [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
| area =
| built =1893
| architect= [[Lord &amp; Burnham]]
| architecture= [[Victorian architecture|Victorian greenhouse]]
| added = November 13, 1976
| governing_body = Local government
| refnum=76001598&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|2006a}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''Phipps Conservatory and Botanical Gardens''' is a complex of buildings and grounds set in [[Schenley Park]], [[Pittsburgh]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[United States]] (near the [[Carnegie Museums]] in [[Central Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]]). It is a City of Pittsburgh historic landmark and is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.arch.state.pa.us/pdfs/H001763_01B.pdf | title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory - Nomination Form: Phipps Conservatory | date=1976 | accessdate=2010-06-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The gardens were founded in 1893 by steel and real-estate magnate [[Henry Phipps]] as a gift to the City of Pittsburgh. Its purpose is to educate and entertain the people of Pittsburgh with formal gardens (Roman, English, etc.) and various species of exotic plants ([[Arecaceae|palm trees]], [[Succulent plant|succulents]], [[bonsai]], [[Orchidaceae|orchids]], etc.). Currently the facilities house elaborate gardens within the thirteen room conservatory itself and on the adjoining grounds. In addition to its primary [[Flora (plants)|flora]] exhibits, the sophisticated glass and metalwork of the [[Lord &amp; Burnham]] conservatory offers an interesting example of [[Victorian architecture|Victorian]] greenhouse architecture.

The entrance pavilion of the Phipps Conservatory has silver-level [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] certification.

==Gardens==
{| class=&quot;infobox bordered&quot; cellpadding=&quot;4&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;float: left; font-size: 100%&quot;
|- style=&quot;white-space: nowrap; background: #ccccff;&quot;
! '''Indoor rooms'''
!
! '''Outdoor gardens'''
|- style=&quot;vertical-align: middle;&quot;
| style=&quot;white-space:&quot; |
*Palm Court
*Serpetine Room
*Fern Room
*Orchid Room
*Stove Room
*South Conservatory
*Tropical Fruit and Spice Room
*The Gallery
*Sunken Garden
*Desert Room
*Victoria Room
*Parterre de Boderie Room
*East Room
*Tropical Forest Conservatory
| style=&quot;white-space:&quot; |[[Image:Phipps pittsburgh winter show.jpg|center|175px]]
A swan display in the Sunken Garden&lt;br /&gt; during the 2005 Winter Flower Show.
| style=&quot;white-space:&quot; |
*Discovery Garden
*Japanese Courtyard Garden
*Aquatic Garden
*Outdoor Garden
*Medicinal Plant Garden
*Botany Hall Garden
|}
{{-}}

==Expansion==
[[Image:Phipps conservatory 3.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Side wing of Phipps]]
In October 2003 Phipps announced an expansion project. The first phase, a [[Green building|green]] engineered Welcome Center topped by a neo-Victorian dome, was designed by IKM Incorporated, and completed in 2005. The Production Greenhouses and a Tropical Forest Conservatory were completed in 2006.

The Tropical Forest conservatory will have a different theme every two years, beginning with the country of Thailand. In addition to a &quot;Research Forest Station&quot; and a &quot;Healer's Hut&quot; (designed to educate visitors about various cultural topics), there are two waterfalls, several bridges, a stream and a wide variety of plants, from Bamboo, Orchids and Frangipani to plants of economic, cultural and horticultural value to the people of Thailand. The second theme is &quot;Headwaters of the Amazon,&quot; which opened in early 2009. 
[[Image:Phipps2.jpg|right|thumb|250px|An example of a [[Dale Chihuly]] art glass installation at the Phipps Conservatory in 2007]]
The new Tropical Forest Conservatory has several interesting features, which make it extremely energy-efficient (for a glass house.) It has &quot;[[earth tubes]]&quot; running underground to help cool the tropical forest, and a Solid Oxide [[fuel cell]], which powers this newly constructed part of the building. In addition, there are computer-controlled shades that block excess sun light from entering the structure, and also help to insulate it at night.

In 2007, Phipps teamed with glass artist [[Dale Chihuly]] and his Seattle-based team of glass blowers. They worked together to create a marriage of hand-blown glass and living plants. Following the closing of the exhibit in February, the conservatory retained four prominent pieces (the Welcome Center [[chandelier]], the hanging gold star in the Desert Room, the [[celadon]] and purple gilded Fiori in the Tropical Fruit and Spice Room and the bronze, apricot and chartreuse Ikebana in the Palm Court) and subsequently purchased 26 smaller pieces for its permanent collection including six multi-colored Macchia (wavy, shell-like bowls), 13 amber Cattails and seven Paintbrushes, all of which are installed in the Palm Court. The total Chihuly collection is valued at $1.2 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/08192/895985-437.stm PG: Chihuly works will become permanent fixtures at Phipps, July 10, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, Phipps teamed with another glass artist [[Hans Godo Frabel]] to create another stunning exhibit titled &quot;Gardens and Glass.&quot; Unlike the Chihuly pieces, Frabel's work is more realistic, although still whimsical at times. Highlights of this exhibit include Longfellows, intricate glass orchid and lotus plants and various clowns (balancing on either glass playing cards or colored glass balls.) This collaboration will be on display until January 2010.

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Phipps conservatory.JPG|Main entrance of the Phipps Conservatory.
Image:Phipps6.jpg|Exterior view of a section of the conservatory.
Image:Phipps conservatory 1.JPG|Exterior view of a section of the conservatory.
Image:Phipps conservatory 5.JPG|The [[University of Pittsburgh|University of Pittsburgh's]] [[Cathedral of Learning]] can be seen over the top of a Phipps atrium.
Image:Phipps conservatory outdoor gardens 1.JPG|[[Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]] as viewed from across Phipps' outdoor gardens.
Image:Phipps conservatory outdoor gardens gate.JPG|Gate to the outdoor gardens.
Image:Acer griseum leafless.JPG|A leafless [[Acer griseum]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
[[File:IMG 3950 FB.jpg|thumb|IMG 3950 FB]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}&lt;!--added under references heading by script-assisted edit--&gt;
*{{cite book | author=Toker, Franklin | title=Pittsburgh: An Urban Portrait | location=Pittsburgh | publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]] | year=1986, 1994 | isbn=0-8229-5434-6}}

{{commons|Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.phipps.conservatory.org/ Phipps Conservatory Website]
*[http://www.ikminc.com/ IKM Incorporated Website]
*[http://www.gigapan.org/viewGigapan.php?id=248 Gigapan of Phipps display of Dale Chihuly: IIkebana, 2007]
*[http://www.gigapan.org/viewGigapan.php?id=203 Gigapan of Phipps display of Dale Chihuly: River of Glass, 2007]
*[http://www.gigapan.org/viewGigapan.php?id=211 Gigapan of Phipps display of Dale Chihuly: Blue Marlins, Cobalt Fiori, Cobalt Reeds and Niijima Floats, 2007]

Video&lt;br&gt;
*[http://www.growingagreenerworld.com/episode104/ Growing a Greener World: Phipps Conservatory-The Greenest in the World]
*[http://www.wqed.org/ondemand/onq.php?cat=19&amp;id=62 WQED onQ: Phipps Tropical Forest: Thailand]

{{Pittsburgh}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures on the National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Botanical gardens in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design basic silver certified buildings]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:City of Pittsburgh historic designations]]
[[Category:Pittsburgh History &amp; Landmarks Foundation Historic Landmarks]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Greenhouses]]

[[es:Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
