<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2377058" ns="0" title="Westminster College (Missouri)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University 
|image          = 
|name           = Westminster College
|established    = 1851 
|motto          = Religio et Scientia (Faith and Reason)
|type           = [[Private school|Private]]
|endowment      = $38.9 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 18, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president      = George B. &quot;Barney&quot; Forsythe
|city           = [[Fulton, Missouri|Fulton]]
|state          = [[Missouri]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|Academics      = 36 [[major]]s, 34 [[minor]]s, and 12 [[pre-professional]] programs 
|undergrad      = 1,064 degree seeking students from 24 states and 67 countries 
|faculty        = 61 full-time instructional faculty
|faculty - student ratio         = 14:1 
|campus         = [[Rural]] town, {{convert|86|acre|1}}
|free_label     = Athletics 
|free           = 8 varsity teams 
|website= [http://www.westminster-mo.edu/ westminster-mo.edu]
|mascot         = Winston Blue Jay
}}

'''Westminster College''' is a private, selective, [[liberal arts]] institution in [[Fulton, Missouri]], USA. It was founded by [[Presbyterians]] in 1849 as '''Fulton College''' and assumed the present name in 1851. The [http://www.churchillmemorial.org/Pages/default.aspx National Churchill Museum and Library] are located on the campus.  The National Churchill Museum (formally known as the Churchill Memorial) is a national historic site and includes the Church of [[St Mary Aldermanbury|St Mary the Virgin, Aldermanbury]].  The church, designed by [[Sir Christopher Wren]] in 1667, was rebuilt on the campus to commemorate [[Winston Churchill|Sir Winston Churchill]], who made his famous &quot;[[Iron Curtain]]&quot; speech at Westminster College in 1946.  As a bookend to history, [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] gave a speech in 1992, declaring the end of the [[Cold War]].

On November 9, 1990, the one year anniversary of the fall of the Berlin Wall, former President [[Ronald Reagan]] delivered a speech dedicating a major section of the [[Berlin Wall]], which now stands as a permanent monument on the College Quad, as a backdrop. The monument, named &quot;Breakthrough&quot; as designed by Winston Churchill's granddaughter, [[Edwina Sandys]]. See photo below for a visual of the Church, Library, and Berlin Wall monument.

==Academics==

Westminster College is classified as a selective institution.  Westminster College has produced four [[Rhodes Scholarship|Rhodes Scholars]], two [[Truman Scholars]], and a [[Marshall Scholarship|Marshall Scholar]] in its 155-year history.
[[Image:Churchwall.jpg|thumb|right|300px|[[Christopher Wren]] designed Church of [[St Mary Aldermanbury]], rebuilt at Westminster College, Missouri]]The college has been recognized for its academics by various national publications.  This includes being named one of America’s Best Colleges (U.S.News &amp; World Report), Best Midwestern College and one of America’s Best Value Colleges (The Princeton Review), one of the Most Interesting Colleges in America (Kaplan-Newsweek), and one of the 20 Hidden Gems among America’s colleges and universities (The Washington Post).  Westminster College was also named one of the 50 Best American Colleges for 2008 by Forbes magazine in August 2008.  The only Missouri college or university named to the Top Fifty, Westminster was ranked 39th. This is ahead of notable colleges such as [[Rice University]], [[University of Virginia]], [[University of California-Berkeley]], [[Cornell College]], and [[Wake Forest University]].  Historically, Westminster has graduated a significant number of students who go on to law school and medical school.  This is reflected in Westminster's concentrated law and medical academic tracks.

==Student body==
The states best represented in the student body are Missouri, Illinois, Oklahoma, Texas and Arkansas (students come from 24 states).  Over 16% of the student body is international students and over fifty nations are represented in the student body, and 18% of the students were ranked in the top tenth of their high school class.

== Traditions ==
Westminster College is characterized by many traditions developed since its founding in 1851.  For example, during the &quot;Columns Ceremony,&quot; incoming freshmen walk through the original columns of ruined Westminster Hall, which was destroyed by fire in 1909.  Upon graduation, departing seniors again walk through the columns, but in the opposite direction.  Tradition dictates that between these ceremonies, students must never walk through the columns.  The College maintains many ties to British history and culture as evidenced by the Church of St. Mary the Virgin, Aldermanbury, the Winston Churchill Memorial and Library, and the presence of bagpipes at numerous special events and observances.

Westminster students are required to adhere to the College's Honor Code and to honor its many traditions.  The Skulls of Seven, founded in 1898, is a secret society dedicated to upholding the honor code, traditions, and ideals of the College.  According to legend, the Skulls of Seven convene their initiations and meetings in the tunnels that run beneath campus.

Westminster has traditionally had a strong [[Fraternities and sororities|Greek]] system, including six fraternities, each with their own residences. The Alpha Delta chapter of [[Beta Theta Pi]], founded in 1868, is the oldest fraternity west of the [[Mississippi River]].  Other fraternities include [[Delta Tau Delta]], the [[Kappa Alpha Order]], [[Phi Delta Theta]], [[Sigma Chi]], and [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]].  The level of participation in the Greek system, however, has fallen in recent years. In 2005, Westminster lost its sorority chapter of [[Delta Delta Delta]]. Sororities, however, remain active on campus including [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]], [[Kappa Alpha Theta]], and [[Alpha Gamma Delta]].

== Athletics ==
[[File:Winstonbluejay.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]] 
Athletes (&quot;Blue Jays&quot;) play in the [[St. Louis Intercollegiate Athletic Conference]] of the NCAA Division III for most sports.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.westminster-mo.edu Westminster College Home Page]

{{Colleges and universities in Missouri}}
{{Saint Louis Intercollegiate Athletic Conference}}
{{Presbyterian Colleges}}
{{Upper Midwest Athletic Conference}}

{{coord|38.8483|-91.956|type:edu_region:US-MO|display=title}}

[[Category:Westminster College (Missouri)| ]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Missouri]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1851]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Former Mid-America Intercollegiate Athletic Association members]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Callaway  County, Missouri]]
[[Category:Education in Callaway County, Missouri]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Callaway County, Missouri]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
