<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23803629" ns="0" title="Lubna al-Hussein"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Lubna Ahmed al-Hussein''' is a [[Sudanese people|Sudanese]] Muslim, media worker and activist who came to international attention in July 2009 when she was prosecuted for wearing trousers. Her case has become a ''[[cause célèbre]]'', with organisations such as the [[Arabic Network for Human Rights Information]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sd0&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|last=Hassan | first = Amro
| date = 12 July 2009
| url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2009/07/sudanese-journalist-taken-to-court-for-sensational-clothing.html
| title= Sudan: Female journalist faces 40 lashes for choice of clothes|publisher= [[Los Angeles Times]] &quot;Babylon &amp; Beyond&quot; blog |accessdate=&lt;!-----2009-07-30-----&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Amnesty International]] issuing statements in support.

==Background==
Al-Hussein is a journalist who, at the time of her arrest, worked for the media department of the 
[[United Nations Mission in Sudan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/jul/31/inpraiseof-lubna-hussein-sudan
|work=The Guardian |location = London |date = 31 July 2009
|author= Editorial
| title= In praise of… Lubna Hussein|accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
She was known for her public criticism of the [[government of Sudan]]'s treatment of women.

==Trousers case==
===Background===
The [[Sudan#Legal system|legal system of the country]] is based on Islamic law ([[sharia]]), and it permits [[judicial corporal punishment]] such as [[flagellation]].  The [[criminal law]] prohibits dressing indecently in public, a charge which carries a punishment of 40 lashes and a fine. According to the director of police, in 2008 in [[Khartoum State]] alone, over 40&amp;nbsp;000 women were arrested for clothing offences; it is not known how many were convicted or flogged.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2009/sep/04/sudan-woman-trousers-trial ''The Guardian'' Comment is free column by Lubna Hussein]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Article 152====
The full text of Article 152 in the Memorandum to the 1991 Penal Code is:

:152 Obscene and Indecent Acts

:(1) Whoever does in a public place an indecent act or an act contrary to public morals or wears an obscene outfit or contrary to public morals or causing an annoyance to public feelings shall be punished with flogging which may not exceed forty lashes or with fine or with both.

:(2) The act shall be contrary to public morals if it is regarded as such according to the standard of the person's religion or the custom of the country where the act takes place.

===Arrest===
On 3 July 2009, the Public Order Police entered the Kawkab Elsharq Hall, looking for any women and girls wearing trousers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/sudan/5956721/Whip-me-if-you-dare-says-Lubna-Hussein-Sudans-defiant-trouser-woman.html
|title='Whip me if you dare' says Lubna Hussein, Sudan's defiant trouser woman
|last=Osman|first=Talal|coauthors=Meo, Nick  |date=1 August 2009
|work= The Daily Telegraph| location = London
|accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Al-Hussein — who had come to book a cousin's wedding party and was watching an Egyptian singer and sipped a coke while she waited — was arrested with twelve other women.&lt;ref name=&quot;sd3&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.msmagazine.com/news/uswirestory.asp?ID=11850
| title=Journalist Goes to Trial in Sudan Flogging Case |author=Feminist Wire
|work = MS. Magazine |date = 30 July 2009
|publisher= [[Feminist Majority Foundation]]
|accessdate=&lt;!-----2009-07-30-----&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Ten of them pled guilty immediately, were given ten lashes each, and released. Hussein and two other women refused this offer and insisted on a trial. 

Between the arrest and the trial, Hussein began to publicize the case by printing 500 invitation cards and sending emails with the subject line &quot;Sudanese journalist Lubna invites you again to her flogging tomorrow&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;obs20090802&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/aug/02/sudan-women-dress-code
|title=Lubna Hussein: &quot;I'm not afraid of being flogged. It doesn't hurt. But it is insulting&quot;
|last=Copnall |first=James |date= 2 August 2009 |work=The Observer | location = London
|accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Appearances in court===
When the case came to trial, the judge offered to dismiss it, pointing out that she enjoyed [[diplomatic immunity|immunity from prosecution]] thanks to her [[United Nations]] job. Al-Hussein stated that she wished to resign her job, and test the law. If she is found guilty, she intends to appeal her case to the upper court and even the constitutional court, in an effort to change the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;obs20090802&quot;/&gt;

In Al-Hussein's second appearance in court, on 4 August, the judge again postponed her case, this time for a month, saying he wanted to get advice about whether she was immune from prosecution or not. Outside the courtroom, police fired [[tear gas]] at protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/8182658.stm
|work=BBC News Online | location = London
|title=Protests at Sudan woman's trial 
|date=4 August 2009
|accessdate=&lt;!-----2009-08-07-----&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Ban Ki-moon]], the [[UN Secretary-General]], stated his concern about the punishment she faces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/africa/article6738355.ece
|title=Protests outside court as Lubna Hussein faces lashes over trousers
|last=McConnell|first=Tristan 
|work= The Times |location = London
|date=4 August 2009|accessdate=&lt;!-----2009-08-08-----&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 September she was found guilty and fined 500 [[Sudanese pound]]s, but not sentenced to flogging. She stated that she intended not to pay, and was prepared to face a month in jail instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt; BBC News [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/8241894.stm Sudanese 'trousers' woman fined] 7 Sept 2009&lt;/ref&gt; This third appearance again featured diplomats and human rights workers observing the case in court, and protesters outside. Journalists counted about 150 of the latter, who were heckled by a smaller number of counter-protesters and beaten by [[riot police]].&lt;ref&gt;The Guardian [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/sep/07/sudanese-woman-escapes-lash-trousers Sudanese woman found guilty of indecency for wearing trousers vows to fight ruling] 7 Sept 2009&lt;/ref&gt; At least 40 protesters were arrested and released on bail.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

===Further developments===
When Hussein tried to fly to [[Lebanon]] in early August for an interview about this case, the Sudanese authorities prevented her from leaving the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE57A38020090811
|title=Sudanese woman in trouser case banned from travel
|date=11 August 2009|work= Reuters
|accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside Sudan, support for her case developed slowly, despite her intimate knowledge of how the media works and her international contacts. The [[BBC]] radio programme ''[[Woman's Hour]]'' discussed the extent to which the case had been ignored by British feminists.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/womanshour/01/2009_35_fri.shtml Feminism and Lubna Hussein, 4 Sep 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposition to the law===
This has become a [[test case]] for women's rights in Sudan.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; Hussein, who considers herself to be a good Muslim and was wearing loose fitting pants covered by a long blouse,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/2346.htm Lubna Al-Hussein, Sudanese Journalist Sentenced to Lashing for Wearing Pants: There Were Dozens of Thousands of Women Like Me ] excerpts from an interview ... aired on Al-Mihwar TV on December 17, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; contends that the case &quot;is not about religion, it is about men treating women badly.&quot; She wants to change the law on behalf of all the women of Sudan.&lt;ref name=&quot;obs20090802&quot;/&gt; She argues that Article 152, which allows the flogging or fining of anyone who “violates public morality or wears indecent clothing” without defining &quot;indecent clothing&quot;, itself  violates both the [[Interim Constitution of Sudan]] and sharia. 

On the eve of Hussein's third appearance in court, [[Amnesty International]] released a statement asking the Sudanese government to repeal Article 152 and drop the charges against her. It states that the [[African Commission on Human and Peoples' Rights]] &quot;ordered Sudan to amend Article 152 on the grounds that flogging amounted to state-sanctioned torture&quot; in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amnesty.org.uk/news_details.asp?NewsID=18402 Sudan: Amnesty International calls on government to repeal law penalising women for wearing trousers]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an article in the American magazine ''[[Foreign Policy (magazine)|Foreign Policy]]'', this case has encouraged disparate activists, from NGOs to opposition politicians, to co-operate with one another in their efforts to change the law.&lt;ref&gt;''Foreign Policy'' [http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2009/08/05/pants_pants_revolution Pants Pants Revolution] 5 Sept 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Human rights in Sudan]]
*[[Sudanese teddy bear blasphemy case]]
*[[Liberal movements within Islam]]
*[[Islamic feminism]]
*[[We Wish to Inform You That Tomorrow We Will Be Killed with Our Families]]
*[[Hijab]]
*[[Islam and clothing]]
*[[Clothing laws by country]]
*[[Committee for the Propagation of Virtue and the Prevention of Vice]]
*[[Mutaween]], Islamic religious police

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Lubna Al-Hussein
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Lubna Al-Hussein}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Sudanese journalists]]
[[Category:Arab journalists]]
[[Category:Sudanese activists]]
[[Category:Islamic feminists]]

[[ar:لبنى أحمد الحسين]]
[[de:Lubna Ahmed el Hussein]]
[[arz:لبنى الحسين]]
[[no:Lubna Ahmad al-Hussein]]
[[sv:Lubna Ahmad al-Hussein]]
[[ta:லுப்னா அல்-ஹுசைன்]]
[[th:ลุบนา ฮุสเซน]]
[[vi:Lubna Ahmed el-Hussein]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
