<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2384535" ns="0" title="New York University School of Social Work"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University 
|name           = NYU Silver School of Social Work
|established    = 1960
|free_label     = Dean
|free           = [[Lynn Videka]]
|type           = [[Private university|Private]] 
|city           = [[New York City]] 
|state          = [[New York]] 
|country        = [[United States|USA]] 
|enrollment     = 1000+
|website        = [http://www.nyu.edu/socialwork/ www.nyu.edu/socialwork]
}}
The '''Silver School of Social Work''', is one of 15 schools within [[New York University]] and is one of the few schools in the country to provide a continuum of social work education from undergraduate through doctoral levels.
==About the School==
Founded in 1960 as the NYU School of Social Work, the NYU Silver School of Social Work is a leader in clinically inspired Social Work education.  The school was renamed the Silver School of Social Work in honor of NYU Alumni Constance and Martin Silver who, in 2007, pledged $50 million to the School of Social Work.  This is the largest known donation to a school of social work in the history of the United States.

The school offers a comprehensive education in professional social work and affords the opportunity to draw on the incomparable resources of [[New York City]].  It has developed unique educational partnerships with over 600 public and non-profit agencies throughout the tri-state area.  Students at the School of Social Work collectively provide more than one half-million hours of service each year through their field placements and volunteer work.
The school's faculty are involved in a wide range of scholarly research initiatives, work intensively with government and community-based agencies, and play key roles in major social work journals.  Recently the school launched a new initiative; the &quot;Zelda Foster Studies in Palliative and End-of-Life Care,&quot; a program named after the social worker most closely associated with the modern-day [[Palliative care|palliative care movement]] and a former teacher at the School of Social Work.

The School provides accredited programs at the undergraduate, masters, and doctoral levels, and serves as a major postgraduate training center for hundreds of practitioners in the New York region.  The School’s [[Master of Social Work]] (MSW) program is distinguished for its focus on clinical social work, and for the education of relationship-centered, reflective practitioners.
==Research Facilities==
The Silver School of Social Work benefits from its access to NYU's research resources.  [[Bobst Library]] at NYU is one of the largest open-stack research libraries in the nation, as it houses more than 3.3 million volumes, 20 thousand journals, and over 3.5 million microforms. The School itself is also home to [http://www.nyu.edu/socialwork/ip/ Information for Practice], a globally focused website providing the latest news and emerging scholarship in the Social Work profession.
==Main Campus==
The School's main facilities are located in the heart of NYU's Washington Square campus in [[Greenwich Village]].  The school's educational, extracurricular, and social hub is housed in three historic townhouses bordering [[Washington Square Park]] where students can meet with faculty, take classes, and access NYU's network of student services and administrative offices.  
[[Image:Black &amp; white townhouse.gif|thumb|alt=Historic Townhouses.|Historic NYUSilver Townhouses.]] 
==Satellite Campuses==
NYU Silver's MSW program is also available on the campuses of [[St. Thomas Aquinas College]] in [[Rockland County, New York]]; the [[College of Staten Island]]; and [[Sarah Lawrence College]] in [[Westchester County, New York]]. 
{|
| [[Image:StatenIslandCenterArts2.jpg‎|thumb|upright|alt=Staten Island|Staten Island Campus]]
| [[Image:Sarah Lawrence.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Sarah Lawrence|Sarah Lawrence, located in Westchester County, NY]]
| [[Image:St.ThAquinas.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=St. Thomas Aquinas|St. Thomas Aquinas College, located in Rockland County, NY]]
|}
==Student organizations==
The [[Graduate Student Council]], or GSA, is the largest elected student organization in the School of Social Work which acts as a liaison between the students and the administration and faculty of the Silver School of Social Work. GSA invites graduate students to bring feedback about the program, suggest events and come to them for direction and assistance.  Similarly, the school houses an [[Undergraduate Student Council]] (UGSA) and [[Doctoral Student Association]] (DSA) for undergraduate and PhD social work students.  Organizations such as the Student Committee on Licensing Issues, Sustainable Silver (an environmental group), Asian-Students Association, Pride and Practice, and U-And-Me are also among the larger student-run organizations within the school.
==External links==
*[http://www.nyu.edu/ New York University]
*[http://www.nyu.edu/socialwork New York University School of Social Work]

{{New York University}}
{{Social work}}

{{coord missing|New York}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:New York University School Of Social Work}}
[[Category:New York University schools|School of Social Work]]
[[Category:Schools of social work]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1960]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Rockland County, New York]]

[[fr:New York University School of Social Work]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
