<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23860094" ns="0" title="Broadway Shopping Centre, Bexleyheath"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox shopping mall
  | shopping_mall_name = Broadway Shopping Centre
  | image = BSCB-logo.png
  | image_width = 160px
  | location           = Broadway, [[Bexleyheath]]
  | opening_date       = 1984
  | owner              = [[Jones Lang LaSalle]] (2009-)
  | manager            = Peter Sedge
  | floors             = 1 (main retail level)&lt;br /&gt;4 (including parking levels)
  | number_of_stores   = 59
  | number_of_anchors  = 2
  | parking            = 1000 spaces
  | website            = http://www.broadwayshoppingcentre.com
}}
'''Broadway Shopping Centre''',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.completelyretail.co.uk/scheme/Bexleyheath-Shopping-Centre-Bexleyheath/index.html&lt;/ref&gt; (branded as '''The Mall Bexleyheath''' from circa 2004 until reverting to its original name in 2009), is the principal covered [[shopping centre]] in the town centre of [[Bexleyheath]] and is the largest single covered shopping facility in the [[London Borough of Bexley]]. 

The centre opened in its current form in [[1984]], underwent an extensive refurbishment in [[2007]], and had been due to form part of a wider regeneration of the surrounding area of Bexleyheath over the coming years, which would have seen additional retail amenity, [[Bexley Council|council]] offices, a [[library]] and residential development adjacent to the existing building.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bexley.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=6803 Bexley Council]&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 2010, following the sale of the centre, its new owners confirmed the major expansion plan would not be going ahead, though a small extension to the existing site remains a possibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;plansdump&quot;&gt;[http://www.newsshopper.co.uk/news/8410375.BEXLEYHEATH__Ambitious_civic_offices_redevelopment_shelved_for_a_supermarket/ News Shopper, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

There are 59 [[Retailing|retail shop]] units considered to be within the Mall building (including several premises where public access is from the Broadway itself)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themall.co.uk/my-mall/bexleyheath/floor-plans.aspx The Mall Bexleyheath floor plan from The Mall website] (note some changes have been made since this map was produced)&lt;/ref&gt; and additional smaller retailers in 'RMUs' (small, freestanding [[kiosk]]-like units).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themall.co.uk/business/commercial-opportunities/retail-units.aspx The Mall: RMUs]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early years of the centre's existence, the site was known as the Broadway Shopping Centre; its owners included [[Aviva|Norwich Union]]. In the early 21st century the building was acquired by [[the Mall Fund]], becoming one of their network of centres under the generic &quot;The Mall&quot; branding. The Mall Fund subsequently purchased the neighbouring Broadway Square, and ran it alongside The Mall. In 2009, The Mall Fund's parent company Capital &amp; Regional agreed a deal to sell the centre to [[Jones Lang LaSalle]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.propertyweek.com/story.asp?storycode=3153717 Property Week on JLL sale]&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of its departure from the network, use of the Mall corporate material declined, though some elements (such as signage and branding) remained under The Mall identity, being replaced over a period of time. Other centres which have been sold off by The Mall Fund (such as [[The Ashley Centre]]) have reverted to their former names following their sale. Some marketing materials for the centre, as of Spring 2010, began to appear bearing the names 'Broadway' or 'Broadway Shopping Centre'. In September 2010, new signage bearing the name &quot;Broadway Shopping Centre Bexleyheath&quot;, with the centre's new red-and-white logo, began replacing the Mall-branded elements.

Following the sale of the centre, it was removed from The Mall's corporate website,;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themall.co.uk/bexleyheath/default.aspx The Mall Bexleyheath website removal notice]&lt;/ref&gt; initially, it did not have a dedicated website of its own as a replacement; however, JLL subsequently established one at broadwayshoppingcentre.com - with signs promoting this URL appearing in the centre from September 2010.

== Information and location ==
The Mall is located in a rectangular building in the centre of [[Bexleyheath]]. The boundaries of the centre are the Broadway to the north, Townley Road to the west, Albion Road to the south and Norwich Place to the east.&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;q=the%20mall%20bexleyheath&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;sa=N&amp;tab=wl Google maps]&lt;/ref&gt; Norwich Place and the Broadway are now pedestrianised; the Broadway having been [[Pedestrian zone|pedestrianised]] in [[1993]], and Norwich Place - partly closed off in the 1993 changes - was fully paved as part of the Broadway Square changes of 2001. Access to the malls is via pedestrian entrances at three sides of the mall (Broadway, Townley Road and Norwich Place), and vehicle access to the centre (for parking and deliveries) is via ramping at Albion Road. 

The centre is a four-storey building; public access to the retail stores is on the ground level; the first floor contains primarily 'service' (delivery bays), office space including the centre management suite, and the customer [[Washroom|toilets]]; and the upper floors are [[car park]]ing. There are two levels of parking - Upper and Lower - and each is divided into three sectors (East, West and Central). [[Marks &amp; Spencer]], [[W H Smith]] and [[British Home Stores|BHS]] have since opening offered some of their retail activity on the first floor, accessed via lifts/stairs/escalators within the relevant store; the 2010 [[H&amp;M]] and [[New Look (clothing retailer)|New Look]] stores, and the 2011 [[River Island]] store, introduced retail space on the first floor as part of the remodelling process to develop their retail space. Additionally, some stores have suspended ceilings to create a 'false' upper level in their stores, including [[Next (clothing)|Next]] and [[HMV Group|HMV]]. 

The building encompasses three covered malls of shops which converge on a central square, and also includes a row of shops facing onto the Broadway itself (the shops between [[Marks &amp; Spencer]] and [[Thomson Holidays|Thomson]] (inclusive) are considered part of the Mall, though their postal addresses are given as being on the Broadway). The sloping nature of the land in the centre of Bexleyheath means that the Broadway entrance leads to a mall which is [[Inclined plane|inclined]] until it meets the central square, and the Townley Road entrance is the only entrance of the three to be connected to the street level by steps/ramping.

== History and design ==
The Mall opened in its current form in 1984. The interior [[Color scheme|colour scheme]] of the mall, until the 2007 revamp, was in hues of [[brown]], [[Gold (color)|gold]] and [[Cream (colour)|cream]], with [[marble]]d pillars, brown tiling in selected areas, cream and brown marble effect floor tiles and [[copper]]-coloured ceiling tiles and strips. The 2007 revamp altered this, most significantly in replacing the entire ceiling with a new [[white]] and [[grey]] one.

The exterior of the building is principally [[brick]], with dark brown [[roof tiles]]; a [[Ceramic glaze|glazed]] white frontage was added to the main entrance area as part of the 2007 alterations. 

In addition to the main retail units, small kiosks have featured within the centre to offer additional retail space within the malls; currently there are a number of kiosks in the 'RMU' format also used in a number of [[the Mall Fund]]'s other centres. The inaugural winner of the Mall Fund's 'Make Your Mark' competition for new retailers was 'Daisy's Dog Deli', a pet food RMU based at The Mall, Bexleyheath.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.makeyourmark.org.uk/inspiring_stories/success_for_first_winner_of_make_your_mark_in_the_mall Make Your Mark on Daisy's Dog Deli]&lt;/ref&gt; This firm has since relocated to trade from a kiosk at the [[Bluewater]] regional shopping mall.

== Developments and redevelopments ==
=== Broadway Square ===
In [[2001]], a new shopping development adjacent to the Mall was opened, having been under development for some time. Broadway Square uses a 'strip mall' format to offer a pub and six large retail units, with an associated two-level (basement and ground) car park. Broadway Square was recently acquired by [[The Mall Fund]] and is now run in conjunction with the neighbouring Mall, though is still not officially considered part of it. Retailers currently trading from Broadway Square (as at August 2010) are [[TK Maxx]], [[JD Sports]], [[Poundland]], [[Wilkinson (retailer)|Wilkinson]], [[Peacocks (clothing)|Peacocks]] and [[Sainsbury's]]. It was not initially clear whether the sale of the Mall to JLL also included Broadway Square, but new centre maps installed by JLL in September 2010 included the Square stores as well as the main centre, suggesting the whole site had indeed been sold.

=== 2007 revamp ===
In late 2006 work began on a major refurbishment of the Mall. The [[Washroom|lavatory facilities]] were [[Maintenance, repair and operations|revamped]], and as part of this the men's toilet was [[Moving (address)|relocated]], with the previous men's room becoming a baby changing and feeding area. The mall level was also revamped, with the copper [[ceiling]] strips and tiles, which had been in place since the centre's opening, removed, and replaced by a new white and grey ceiling. Several new [[Skylight (window)|skylight]]s were also cut into the roof of the centre to allow more [[Sunlight|natural light]] in - due to the design of the building, with the mall level at the bottom of a four-storey development, access to natural light had been limited prior to the changes. There were also new glazed entrances developed at two of the three pedestrian entrances. The revamp also allowed space for Mall TV displays (monitors broadcasting a loop of information and promotional material) and advertising hoardings. Some of The Mall branded elements introduced in the revamp remained in the centre briefly following the sale to JLL but have now begun to be replaced.

=== Previous developments of major stores ===
Due to the location and design of the building, it has not been possible to extend or materially alter the Mall. However, there have been a small number of changes to the [[Configuration (geometry)|configuration]] of units in the centre, which have made a limted number of new units available. 

Two of these changes involved the division of the centre's original [[Woolworths Group|Woolworths]] store. When the centre opened in [[1984]], a large Woolworths was located at the eastern side of the centre close to [[Marks &amp; Spencer]]. In 1990 this was cut in half, creating three new units - one which is currently occupied by [[HMV Group|HMV]], one for [[Superdrug]] and one for [[Argos (retailer)|Argos]]. The remainder continued as a smaller Woolworths. In 2000, Woolworths moved to the former [[Safeway (UK)|Safeway]] unit on the western side of the centre (near to [[W H Smith]]), with the smaller Woolworths divided again; this allowed Superdrug and Argos to extend to their current sizes, and also allowed the development of three new shop units, taken up by [[Game (retailer)|GAME]], [[Phones4U]] and Sussex Stationers. Former office space above Woolworths was let to [[Reed (company)|Reed]], with public access to this space created by converting a former Woolworths fire exit. Woolworths remained in the former Safeway store until their collapse at the end of 2008. 

Following the closure of Woolworths, its later premises were extensively remodelled and divided into two new retail units. Posters were subsequently applied to the hoardings which confirmed New Look would be taking up a portion of the redeveloped space, relocating from their current store in the centre; subsequently, a strap appeared on another section of the hoarding confirming an [[H&amp;M]] store would be occupying that section of the space from September: this will be H&amp;M's first presence in Bexleyheath.&lt;ref&gt;[source: corporate promotional messages placed on hoardings around the development site]&lt;/ref&gt; The New Look store opened in late August 2010, followed by the H&amp;M in early September.

The only other major store to have changed its configuration since the mall opened was [[Boots Group|Boots]], which expanded to its current size in [[2001]] by taking over a vacant single store (formerly occupied by [[Stylo|Instep Sports]]) neighbouring their original unit.

=== Forthcoming and proposed developments ===
[[The Mall Fund|The Mall Company]] backed a scheme as part of a proposed redevelopment of Bexleyheath town centre. The scheme would have seen Bexley [[Magistrates' Court]], which currently neighbours the Mall on its south-eastern side, moved to the current [[Library|Central Library]] site, and the Broadway Square car park replaced by a new parking facility on part of the current Civic Offices site. The existing Magistrates' Court, Broadway Square car park and the remainder of the Civic Offices site would then have been redeveloped with two levels of retail stores (linked into the existing Mall at ground level), with new council offices, a new library and a series of residential blocks located above this. This development was approved by Bexley Council in 2009 and was expected to be developed between 2010 and 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bexley.gov.uk/CHttpHandler.ashx?id=3827&amp;p=0 The Mall's redevelopment plans on Bexley Council's website (pdf)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thisislocallondon.co.uk/whereilive/southeast/bexley/4190442.BEXLEY__Plans_unveiled_for_multi_million_pound_redevelopment_of_Broadway_civic_offices/ Report on proposed revamp from This Is Local London]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The plans were submitted to the council by Capital &amp; Regional (as The Mall Fund) prior to the sale of The Mall to JLL; it was not immediately clear what effect the sale would have on the redevelopment plans, or if JLL would take over the project in its existing form. In 2010 it was confirmed that the large-scale redevelopment proposed by C&amp;R would not be going ahead: the library and magistrates' court would remain in their existing locations, with the council selling the civic offices site to a large food store (as had been proposed by construction firm John Laing in the rival bid for the original development plan). JLL may redevelop and extend their mall site in a smaller way,&lt;ref name=&quot;plansdump&quot; /&gt; most likely by extending the building onto the Broadway Square car park which neighbours the existing building.

== List of retailers ==
The following is a list of retailers trading in the Centre as of 9 November 2011, not including RMUs.

* [[Hutchison 3G|3 Store]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=3+Store+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=2658639138541440481 Google maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ann Summers]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Ann+Summers+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=6423893116071914293&amp;ei=3Rd4SpGBBJHQjAem9OGnBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=local_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 Google maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Argos (retailer)|Argos]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://wwp.greenwichmeantime.com/time-zone/europe/uk/england/london/greater-london/bexley/bexleyheath/argos-store/ GreenwichMeanTime.com - Argos]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Stylo|Barratts]]
* [[BHS]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thomsonlocal.com/Bhs-Ltd/0021445112402493000/map/companyinfo.html Thomson Local]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bijou Brigitte (opened December 2010)
* [[Boots Group|Boots]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Boots+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=202424431414127964&amp;dtab=2&amp;ei=_hd4Sv6jG9nKjAfYmuWnBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=local_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Boots Group|Boots Opticians]] (formerly [[Dollond &amp; Aitchison|D&amp;A]]) - prior to Boots-D&amp;A merger, Boots Opticians operated from a store on Broadway (now [[CeX]]) opposite the main Mall entrance
* [[Burger King]]
* [[Burton (clothing)|Burton]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocalweb.net/index/MCS/tlw_477443.htm The Local Web - Burton]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Buy The Book
* [[Card Factory]] - opened spring 2011 (former [[Krisp Clothing]] store) - the card firm's second Bexleyheath branch
* [[Carphone Warehouse]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theopeninghours.co.uk/Bexleyheath/The-Carphone-Warehouse-Unit-63a-Broadway-Shopping-Centre,370439.html The Opening Hours - Carphone Warehouse]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Claire's]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yell.com/listings/DoFindListings/2969211/Claire's/Fashion-Accessories Yell - Claire's]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[C&amp;J Clark|Clarks]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ikent.co.uk/profile/406667/Bexleyheath/The-Clarks-Shop/ iKent - Clarks]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Clinton Cards]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.brownbook.net/business/462196/clinton-cards-plc Brownbook - Clinton Cards]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dorothy Perkins]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Dorothy+Perkins+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=textlatlng=11320959274956686669 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Signet Jewelers|Ernest Jones]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ernestjones.co.uk/webstore/store.do?storeNumber=3217 Ernest Jones website]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Evans (clothing)|Evans]] - formerly a standalone store, now as concession within [[BHS]]&lt;ref name=&quot;wallisevans&quot;&gt;[http://www.themall.co.uk/my-mall/bexleyheath/whats-on/16-Jul-2009-6719.aspx Wallis &amp; Evans details]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Gallery Gifts&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Gallery+Gifts+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=16300880497385486961 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Game (retailer)|GAME]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yell.com/b/Game+Stores+Ltd-Computer+Games-Bexleyheath-DA67JJ-2917517/index.html Yell - Game]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Greggs]]
* [[H&amp;M]] (from September 2010)
* [[H. Samuel]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hsamuel.co.uk/webstore/store.do?storeNumber=4120 H Samuel]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Harris's (footwear store, opened December 2010)
* [[HMV Group|HMV]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yell.com/b/HMV+(U.K)+Ltd-Music+Shops+(CDs+and+DVDs)-Bexleyheath-DA67JJ-525883/index.html Yell - HMV]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Holland &amp; Barrett]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocalweb.net/index/HOF/tlw_534070.htm The Local Web - Holland &amp; Barrett]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Honeybee Boutique&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Honeybee+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=17173403908335882643 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jessops]] - opened August 2011
* [[Marks &amp; Spencer]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ukretailpark.com/south-east-england/bexleyheath-marks-spencer.htm UK Retailpark - M&amp;S]&lt;/ref&gt; split across two stores, facing one another
* [[McDonald's]]
* [[Monsoon Stores Ltd|Monsoon]] and [[Monsoon Stores Ltd|Accessorize]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monsoon.co.uk/stry/bexleyheathm Monsoon]&lt;/ref&gt; - formerly two separate stores, combined into one unit in 2009
* [[National Westminster Bank|NatWest]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yell.com/b/NatWest+Bank+plc-Banks-Bexleyheath-DA67JG-4680141/index.html Yell - NatWest]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[New Look (clothing retailer)|New Look]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bview.co.uk/listing/0533331/New-Look-in-DA6 BView - New Look]&lt;/ref&gt; (Relocated to the ex-Woolworths store as of 18 August 2010)
* [[Telefonica Europe|O2]]
* [[Optical Express]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.opticalexpress.com/stores/bexleyheath-the-mall-6.html Optical Express]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Past Times (opened Oct 2009)
* [[Phones4U]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;ei=Shh4SvzGNZjMjAfGitmnBg&amp;resnum=0&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Phones4u+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=1197480049879091294&amp;ei=TRh4SpKGC5CZjAfzgtinBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=local_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Pure Party &amp; [[Birthdays (retailer)|Birthdays]] - previous Birthdays standalone store moved to this new store in 2009
* [[Reed (company)|Reed]]
* Sblended Milkshakes
* [[River Island]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scoot.co.uk/England/Kent/Bexleyheath/River-Island-Clothing-Co-Ltd-CDPK495.html Scoot - River Island]&lt;/ref&gt; - relocated to larger former [[Mothercare]] store from November 2011
* [[Starbucks]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wozzon.com/url/venue/Starbucks+Coffee+The+Mall+Bexleyheath/5752205102 woZZOn - Starbucks]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Steads (shoe repair)
* [[Superdrug]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cylex-uk.co.uk/company/superdrug-stores-plc-16611742.html Cylex-UK - Superdrug]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Body Shop]]
* [[AS Watson|The Perfume Shop]]
* [[Thomas Cook Group|Thomas Cook]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.co.uk/maps?hl=en&amp;um=1&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;q=Thomas+Cook+Bexleyheath&amp;fb=1&amp;split=1&amp;gl=uk&amp;view=text&amp;latlng=15733765313346956821&amp;ei=KBl4SqOHMZnUjAeFjt2nBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=local_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4 Google Maps]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Thomson Holidays|Thomson]]
* [[T-Mobile]] and [[Orange (telecommunications)|Orange]] - (Previously a T-Mobile store; Orange moved in with its [[Everything Everywhere|sister company]] in 2011)
* [[Vision Express]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visionexpress.com/store-locator/opticians-in-london/south-east-london/london-bexleyheath/ Vision Express]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Vodafone United Kingdom|Vodafone]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelocalweb.net/index/MPH/tlw_641268.htm The Local Web - Vodafone]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wallis (retailer)|Wallis]] - returned as concession within BHS in 2009&lt;ref name=&quot;wallisevans&quot; /&gt; having been absent from Bexleyheath since 1994
* [[W H Smith]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ikent.co.uk/profile/36230/Bexleyheath/W-H-Smith-Ltd/ iKent - WH Smith]&lt;/ref&gt; - Bexleyheath Post Office has traded from this store since 2008, having previously been a standalone service further down the Broadway

===Forthcoming retailers and changes===

[[Heinrich Deichmann-Schuhe GmbH|Deichmann]] are to take up a new store (combining the former [[Next (clothing)|Next]] and Sussex Stationers sites) which is scheduled to open in late November 2011.

== Former retailers ==
Retailers which have formerly traded at the Broadway Shopping Centre but no longer do so include [[Currys.digital|Dixons]], [[Topshop]] and [[Topman]], [[Miss Selfridge]], [[Woolworths Group|Woolworths]], [[Safeway (UK)|Safeway]], [[Rosebys]], [[Radio Rentals]], [[Our Price]], [[Dolcis Shoes|Dolcis]], [[JJB Sports]], [[Waterstone's]], [[The Link (retailer)|The Link]], [[Rumbelows]], [[Krisp Clothing|Krisp]], [[Principles (retailer)|Principles]] and [[Next (clothing)|Next]]. Some of these firms are still trading elsewhere in the country, though others are now defunct or dormant: see the retailers' pages for more detailed information about each firm. 

[[JD Sports]] traded inside the mall for a time (in what is now T-Mobile) after their merger with First Sport, which previously occupied the unit, but subsequently closed this small store to focus on their larger and more recent Broadway Square site.

[[Mothercare]] and [[Early Learning Centre]] were located in separate stores inside the shopping centre for a number of years, but relocated in September 2010 to a former [[Aldi]] store on Market Place, outside the centre's boundaries.

The Greenwich &amp; Bexley Community Hospice (formerly Cottage Hospice) charity operated a retail store at various store locations within the mall building for a time, generally taking short-term lets of then-vacant units and relocating as and when required to release stores for new regular tenants. The hospice's most recent store location within the building closed in June 2011 and was not replaced; the hospice's other charity shops elsewhere continue to trade as normal.

== External links ==
* [http://www.broadwayshoppingcentre.com The centre's official website]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord|51.4561|0.1459|type:landmark_region:GB-BEX|display=title}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Bexley]]
[[Category:Shopping centres in London]]
[[Category:Shopping malls established in 1984]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
