<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2386044" ns="0" title="Adamson University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image_caption =
|native_name    = Pamantasang Adamson 
|image          = [[File:Seal of Adamson University.png|200px]]
|motto          = Thee Thy Will;&lt;br /&gt;Education with a Heart;&lt;br /&gt;''Veritas in Caritate''&lt;br /&gt;(&quot;Truth in Charity&quot;)
|established    = 30 June 1932
|type           = [[Private university|Private]], [[Roman Catholic Church|Roman Catholic]], [[Lazarists|Vincentian]]
|president      = Rev. Fr.Gregorio Bañaga, Jr ,CM
|city           = [[Manila]]
|country        = [[Philippines]]
|address        = 900 San Marcelino St. Ermita, Manila
|students = 15,881 (1st semester SY 2009-2010)
|campus         = [[Urban area|Urban]] 4.7&amp;nbsp;hectares
|colors = Navy Blue and White {{color box|navy}}{{color box|white}}
|mascot         = (Adam, Sonny, and Sonia)
|free_label     = Hymn
|free           = [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vf51ab3lJUI Adamson Hymn]
|nickname       = [[falcons, baby falcons]]
|affiliations = [[Association of Southeast Asian Institutions of Higher Learning|ASAIHL]], ACUP, CEAP, COCOPEA, FAAP, [[International Association of Universities|IAU]], IFCU, [[PAASCU]], PACU, PACUCOA, [[South Manila Inter-Institutional Consortium|SMIIC]], [[University Athletic Association of the Philippines|UAAP]]
|website = [http://www.adamson.edu.ph www.adamson.edu.ph]
|logo           =[[File:Header_AdU.JPG|150px]]
}}

'''Adamson University''' is a [[private university]] [[Catholic]] [[university]] in [[Manila]], [[Philippines]], founded on June 30, 1932 by [[Greeks|Greek]] immigrant George Lucas Adamson as the [[Adamson School of Industrial Chemistry]].&lt;ref name=MAdam&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hri.org/forum/life/adamson.html|title=Greeks in the Philippines
|publisher=www.hri.org|accessdate=2009-01-02|last=|first=}}&lt;/ref&gt; On February 5, 1941, the school was granted university status by the Department of Education,&lt;ref name=MAdam&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adamson.edu.ph/about/history.shtml|title= Adamson University History}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on December 4, 1964, the university was turned over to the Vincentian Fathers of the [[Congregation of the Mission]] (CM) and was incorporated into the Adamson-Ozanam Education Institutions, Inc.

Adamson University has programs in Graduate Education, [[Law]], the [[Arts]] and [[Sciences]], [[Engineering]], [[Nursing]], [[Pharmacy]], [[Architecture]], [[Business Administration]], [[Teacher Education]], as well as secondary, elementary, and preparatory education. Adamson has eight distinguished courses for Center of Development and Center of Excellence identified by the Philippines Commission on Higher Education&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ched.gov.ph/statistics/coecods.html|title=Statistics}} {{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has been granted Autonomous Status.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adamson.edu.ph/news/2010/06/news02.shtml|title= Adamson University Deregulated Status}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is a member of the [[University Athletic Association of the Philippines]]

==History==
George Lucas Adamson, a Greek chemist from [[Athens]], founded the Adamson School of Industrial Chemistry on June 20, 1932 to train young men and women in practical industrial chemistry. It started as a one-classroom school that evolved into the Adamson School of Industrial Chemistry and Engineering on February 19, 1936. Its application for university status was approved by the Secretary of Public Instruction on February 5, 1941 and thereafter it has been known as Adamson University.

Shortly after the opening, George Adamson invited his cousin Alexander Athos Adamson to work in the school. Alexander Adamson joined the administration on July 15, 1932, serving at various times as Vice-President, Treasurer and Registrar. In 1934, Alexander's brother, George Athos Adamson, came to work in the school, becoming Dean of the College of Engineering of the university.

Evdoxia Savaides Adamson, wife of Fabio Lucas Adamson, started working and teaching in the university in 1939, then served as Dean of the College of Education and of the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences. Sofia Adamson, George Athos Adamson's wife, taught in the College of Education after arriving in 1939 and briefly served as Directress of the Junior Normal College.

With the exception of George Athos and Sofia, who left after the [[Second World War]], all the members of the Adamson family remained working in the university until its turnover to the Vincentian Fathers and Brothers of the Congregation of the Mission in 1964. George Lucas Adamson served as President from the beginning until 1967, for a total of 35 years including a three-year holdover stint.

Before finally settling on its permanent home along San Marcelino Street in 1946 after the war, the school stayed in three different locations: Sta. Cruz (1932–1933), San Miguel (1933–1939) and Intramuros (1939–1941). In San Marcelino, the university expanded with the acquisition of the Meralco building in 1968 and the St. Theresa's College-Manila campus in 1977, both just across the street.


The transfer of ownership in 1964 incorporated the university into the Adamson-Ozanam Educational Institutions, Inc. It also led to its transition from a secular to a [[Roman Catholicism|Catholic]] institution, with the Vincentians holding top administrative posts and becoming majority members of the Board of Trustees. St. Vincent de Paul, founder of the C.M., was declared university patron saint and the motto &quot;Veritas in Caritate&quot; (Truth in Charity) was adopted.

Although Adamson University was founded as a secular school, when the [[Congregation of the Mission|Vincentian Fathers]] took over, they introduced religious programs to place it in line with the ideals of Catholic education.  A theology department was opened and campus ministry was strengthened, Masses were held daily, religious icons and celebrations were introduced on the University campus.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adamson.edu.ph/about/main.shtm|title=About|publisher=adamson.edu.ph}} {{dead link|date=February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prime minister Leandro I. Montañana, C.M., a Spanish Vincentian, was the second President, but the first under the Vincentian (C.M.) administration. He served in that capacity until 1985 when Fr. Rolando S. Dela Goza, C.M., the first Filipino President, took the office and held it until 1994. Next came Fr. Jimmy Belita, C.M., university President until 2003 who in turn was succeeded by the current President Fr. Gregorio L. Bañaga, Jr., C.M.

While remaining best known for its Chemistry and Engineering programs, Adamson University gradually added Architecture, Sciences, Pharmacy, Business, Education, Liberal Arts, Law, Graduate, Basic Education, and Theology courses. In the 1990s, it registered its highest enrollment figure ever: 21,994 students.

Adamson University celebrated its diamond jubilee on February 5–11, 2007 during which occasion it was also declared a Historic Site by the [[National Historical Institute]].

==Campus==
Adamson University is located in San Marcelino Street, [[Ermita, Manila|Ermita]] in Manila. The [[Technological University of the Philippines]], [[Santa Isabel College, Manila|Santa Isabel College]], [[Emilio Aguinaldo College]], and [[Philippine Normal University]] are its nearest neighbors. Adamson University has seven buildings occupying 4.7&amp;nbsp;hectares of land:
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Adamson University.jpg|Adamson University
Image:Adusv.jpg|Saint Vincent de Paul Building

Image:Francis Regit Clet Building.jpg|Francis Regis Clet Building
Image:Saint Vincent Hall.jpg|Saint Vincent Hall
Image:AdUsvgym.jpg|[[St. Vincent Gym]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Buildings===
* Saint Vincent de Paul Building
* Saint Therese Building
* Cardinal Santos Building
* Ozanam Building
* Fr. Leandro Montañana Building
* John Perboyre Building
* Francis Regis Clet Building
* Falcon Tower (Soon to Rise 12 Storey Building)
* Searching Bldg.

==Organization and structure==
===President and Vice Presidents===
* Rev. Fr. Gregorio Bañaga Jr., C.M. PhD President
* Rev. Fr. Francisco Nicolas P. Magnaye, Jr., C.M. Vice President for Academic Affairs
* Rev. Fr. Andrew S. Bayal, C.M. Vice President for Student Affairs
* Ana Liza M. Ragos Vice President for Administration
* Rev. Fr. Maximino D. Rendon, C.M. Vice President for Finance

===Accreditation===
Adamson University is an accredited member of various national and international educational organizations:
* Philippine Association of Colleges and Universities (PACU)
* Catholic Educational Association of the Philippines (CEAP)
* Association of Catholic Universities of the Philippines (ACUP)

===Grading System===
====Performance-Based Evaluation====
A “Fail” policy is strictly observed, except on output-based subjects (e.g. thesis or its equivalent, and internship), where “No grade” is given. A student would only earn credits for the subject if he passed both the lecture and laboratory components. The student is required to re-enroll both the lecture and laboratory if he/she failed either of the components. Due to inherent differences in the course requirements of different subjects in the various programs, the parameters used for the evaluation of students' performance and its corresponding weight are based on the course objectives as stipulated in the syllabus. The course requirements and its corresponding weight distribution are consensuses among the faculty handling the same subject or should be decided upon by an individual faculty who is the only one handling the subject. In either case the course requirements and its corresponding weight distribution is verified and confirmed by the dean/chair. Grades in the examinations, quizzes, and other requirements are computed as the percentage of raw scores and shall not be transmuted. The passing grade is 70%. The course requirements, its breakdown, and the computation of grade are provided for to the students by their respective professors at the start of the semester.

see [[Academic grading in the Philippines]] for the Grade Point Scale

=== Integrated Community Extension Service ===
Students are encouraged to participate in social action and in the community extension services of the University. They are invited to get involved actively in sharing their time, talents and treasures implementing community organization and development programs, activities and services for the marginalized. These programs are under the office of Integrated Community Extension Services (ICES) in coordination with the academic and co-academic offices.

==Student life==
[[File:Pak yoU - Adamson University.jpg|right|150px]]
You can join in Paranormal Experts Group of Adamson University. Ghost Hunters society
The Office for Student Affairs (OSA) assumes the responsibility for managing the growth and development of students.  The OSA works with the Vice-President for Student Affairs (VPSA) in the implementation of policies promoting students' welfare.

There are also international students who are currently enrolled at Adamson. These students are from [[South Korea]], [[China]], [[Taiwan]], [[Thailand]] and other [[Southeast Asia]]n countries, as well as from [[Bangladesh]], [[Iran]] and some [[Africa]]n countries.

===Student Government===
The Adamson University Student Government (AUSG) was established on October 11. 1981 after a three stage election that started the basic political unit in the university.

On March 18 and 19, 1983, the Constitution, drafted by the student parliament convened as a constituent body, was unanimously ratified in a University-wide plebiscite. Intended to serve as a laboratory for student leadership, the AUSG features a modified presidential system with parliamentary powers operating on the principle of diffusion of powers. It consists of three branches, namely: the Executive Council, the Student Parliament, and the Judiciary.

===Student organizations===
The Office for Student Affairs recognizes the existence of several student organizations. They include societies in many subject disciplines, such as Mathematics and areas of professional education, such as Accountancy, as well as religious organizations and leisure interest societies. Sputnik Gang and Tau Gama is also allowed here.

===[[AIESEC]]===
Present in over 110 countries and territories and with over 60,000 members, AIESEC is the world's largest student-run organisation. Focused on providing a platform for youth leadership development, AIESEC offers young people the opportunity to be global citizens, to change the world, and to get experience and skills that matter today. AIESEC Adamson is a new member of AIESEC Philippines. AIESEC Adamson offers Internships abroad and a global learning environment to all Adamsonians.

== Notable alumni ==
{{main|List of Adamson University alumni}}

===Politics and governance===
* [[Isidro Lebrilla Hemedes Jr.]] - Municipal Mayor [[Cabuyao, Laguna]]
* [[Ruthlane Uy Asmundson]] Mayor - [[Davis, California]], U.S.A.
* [[Angelito Gatlabayan]] Congressman - 2nd District of [[Antipolo City]]
* [[Mohammad Ali Lucman Pacasum]] Congressman - 1st District [[Lanao del Sur]]
* [[Recto Cantimbuhan]] - Vice Governor of [[Cavite]]
* [[Rolando Ampatuan]] - Municipal Mayor [[Maguindanao]]

===Sports===
* [[Marlou Aquino]] - 1996 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Rookie of the Year and [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Best Player of the Conference, currently plays for the [[Meralco Bolts]]
* [[Ken Bono]] - 2007 UAAP Most Valuable Player, former player of the [[Alaska Aces (PBA)|Alaska Aces]] (2007–2008) and the [[San Miguel Beermen]] (2008–2009), currently plays for the [[Coca Cola Tigers]]
* [[Hector Calma]] - 3-time [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Mythical First Team member, a member of the [[PBA's 25 Greatest Players]], a gold medalist of the 1986 [[FIBA Asia Championship]] and 1984 [[FIBA Asia Champions Cup]]
* [[Melvin Mamaclay]] - Currently plays for the [[Sta. Lucia Realtors]]
* [[Gherome Ejercito]] - Last played for the [[Rain or Shine Elasto Painters]]
* [[Eddie Laure]] - 1998 [[MBA]] Rookie of the Year, 2000 [[MBA]] Mythical Second Team, 2001 [[MBA]] Most Valuable Player, 2001 [[MBA]] Mythical First Team, 2001 [[MBA]] Scoring Champion
* [[Kenneth Duremdes]] - 1998 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Most Valuable Player, 1998 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Mythical First Team, 1998 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Governor's Cup Best Player of the Conference, 1998 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Commissioner's Cup Best Player of the Game, 1998 All-Filipino Cup Best Player of the Conference, 1997 PBA Most Improved Player, 1996 All-Star Game Most Valuable Player
* [[Edward Joseph Feihl]] - 1998 RP Centennial Team member, 1997 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Mythical Second Team, 1996 [[Philippine Basketball Association|PBA]] Mythical Second Team
* [[Richard Alonzo]] - Former player of [[Purefoods Tender Juicy Giants]] (2006–2008) and [[Burger King Whoopers]] (2008–2009), currently plays for the [[Barako Bull Energy Boosters (2000-2011)|Barako Bull Energy Boosters]]
* [[Mel Alas|Carmelo &quot;Mel&quot; Alas]] - [[Adamson Soaring Falcons]] coach for UAAP 68th season
* [[Louie Alas|Francisco Luis &quot;Louie&quot; Alas]] - Letran Knights (NCAA) coach


===Arts, religion, and culture===
* [[Guillermo Gómez Rivera]] - writer
* Fr. [[Fernando Suarez]], CC - Filipino Catholic priest
* Dr. [[Lizelle Eugenio - Villanueva]] - Bb. Pilipinas 1992 Semi-Finalist, Mrs. Philippines-International 2009

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.adamson.edu.ph Official website]
* [http://adamsonians.com Adamsonians Online Community]

{{Adamson University}}
{{UAAP}}
{{SMIIC}}
{{Vincentian Colleges and Universities}}
{{University Belt}}
{{Philippine Universities in QS Rankings}}
{{Coord|14|35|10|N|120|59|10|E|type:edu|display=title}}

[[Category:Adamson University|*]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1932]]
[[Category:Higher education in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the Philippines]]
[[Category:University Athletic Association of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Congregation of the Mission]]

[[bcl:Adamson na Unibersidad]]
[[pam:Adamson University]]
[[simple:Adamson University]]
[[tl:Pamantasang Adamson]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
