<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23929" ns="0" title="PHP-Nuke"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=December 2008}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = PHP-Nuke
| logo                   = [[Image:PHP-Nuke logo.png|200px|PHP-Nuke logo]]
| screenshot             = &lt;!--  Commented out because image was deleted: [[Image:PHPNukeWebsite.gif|250px|Screenshot]] --&gt;
| caption                =  The PHP-Nuke website runs by PHP-Nuke CMS.
| author                 = Francisco Burzi
| developer              =
| latest release version = 8.2
| latest release date    = {{release date|2009|5|22}}
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| programming language   = [[PHP]]
| genre                  = [[Content management system]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = http://www.phpnuke.org
}}
'''PHP-Nuke''' is a web-based automated news publishing and [[content management system]] based on [[PHP]] and [[MySQL]] originally authored by Franscisco Burzi. The system is controlled using a web-based user interface. PHP-Nuke was originally a [[fork (software)|fork]] of the Thatware news portal system.

PHP-Nuke was originally released under the [[GNU General Public License]] as [[free software]]. Versions after 7.5 require a license fee. This is permitted under the [[GNU GPL]] (providing the [[source code]] is included), and the purchaser of the software has the right to freely distribute the source code of the product. Burzi no longer owns the PHP-Nuke site.

As of version 5.6, the display of a [[copyright]] message on webpages is required in accordance with the GPL section 2(c).&lt;ref&gt;[http://phpnuke.org/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=6966]&lt;/ref&gt;

PHP-Nuke requires a [[web server]] which supports the [[PHP]] extension (such as the [[Apache HTTP Server]]), as well as an [[SQL]] database (such as [[MySQL]], [[mSQL]], [[PostgreSQL]], [[ODBC]], [[ADABAS]], [[Sybase]] or [[InterBase]]).

==Features of==
PHP-Nuke is a content management system allowing webmasters to create community-based portals (websites), allowing users and editors to post news items (user-submitted news items are selected by editors) or other types of articles. Registered users can then comment on these articles.

Modules can be added to the PHP-Nuke system allowing additional features such as an [[Internet forum]], Calendar, News Feed, [[FAQ]]'s , Private Messaging and others. The site is maintained through an administration interface.

PHP-Nuke includes the following standard modules:

* Advertising—Manages ads on the page layout (theme). Supports images/links, [[javascript]]/[[HTML]], and [[Adobe Flash|Flash]]
* Avantgo—Provides mobile versions of the last 10 news articles
* Content—Manages the main content &quot;pages&quot;
* Downloads—Manages file downloads. There are no uploads&amp;mdash;it stores links to files on other servers
* Encyclopedia—Manages phrases/words and definitions
* FAQ—Manages Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)
* Feedback—Communicate to the webmaster. It is an online form, but provides feedback via email.
* Forums—Manages discussion forums for the site. It is based on bb2nuke, which is a PHP-Nuke port of the popular open-source phpBB discussion board.
* Journal—Maintain public and/or private notes
* Members List—Displays site members
* News—Manages news stories, including future-dated news to be released at a specific date and time. Each article can be assigned to a single category.
* Private Messages—Allows members to send private messages to others on the site. Members can prevent messages from other members.
* Recommend Us—Send an email message recommending the site to others.
* Search—Allows users to search your site.
* Statistics—Displays summary and detailed site statistics, including page views.
* Stories (News) Archives—Provides access to older news articles.
* Submit News—Allow visitors to submit news. Email notification is sent, but the submission is stored in the administrator control panel. Administrator can delete, edit, and/or post the article without rekeying.
* Surveys (Polls)—Create visitor surveys
* Top—Displays the most-visited articles, downloads, etc.
* Topics—Displays news by topic. The administrator defines the topics and assigns topics to content.
* Web Links—Manages a hierarchical directory of links to selected websites
* Your Account—Manages members &quot;profile&quot; information, including their preferred theme, the number of news articles to display on their home page, etc.

PHP-Nuke supports many languages and its look and feel can be customized using the ''Themes'' system, but major changes requires knowledge of PHP, HTML and CSS.

==Issues==

Currently as it stands there are numerous vulnerabilities that affect all versions of PHP-Nuke,  including the latest release 8.1.35.  Until a new release is made it is '''strongly recommended''' to avoid this software.

* Several security holes have been discovered in PHP-Nuke, including [[SQL injection]] via unchecked PHP code.&lt;ref&gt;
Secunia Vulnerability Report for PHP-Nuke 7.x http://secunia.com/product/2385/?task=advisories&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;	
Secunia Vulnerability Report for PHP-Nuke 8.x http://secunia.com/product/13524/?task=advisories&lt;/ref&gt;

* PHP-Nuke may have issues with some search engine indexes.  PHP-Nuke does not use simple URLs or unique titles for pages.
...

==Forks==
Notable [[Fork (software development)|fork]]s include:
*[http://www.cpgnuke.com/ Dragonfly CMS] &amp;mdash; based on PHP-Nuke 6.5 with [[Coppermine Photo Gallery]] included
*[http://www.lgnuke.org/ LGNuke] &amp;mdash; 7.6 and web 2.0 with [[AJAX]] included.
*[http://www.nuke-evolution.com Nuke-Evolution] &amp;mdash; Many security fixes, custom modifications, and modifications pre-installed
*[http://www.matteoiammarrone.com/cleanuke Clean Nuke] based on PHP-Nuke 7.6/WL Nuke 1.1 is a special version for simple content website.
*[[Ravennuke|RavenNuke CMS]] &amp;mdash; 7.6, with many security fixes, custom modifications, add-ons, and XHTML 1.0 Transitional compliance
*[[phpWebSite]] &amp;mdash;
*[[Postnuke]] &amp;mdash; 5.0
* PragmaMx
*[[XOOPS]] &amp;mdash; PHP-Nuke and myPHPNuke
*[http://phpnuke-clan.net/ PNC] &amp;mdash; PHP-Nuke with vWar and SQuery included. Customized for gaming and clan community
*[http://mega-nuke.com Mega-Nuke] &amp;mdash; 7.4, with many security fixes, custom modifications and add-ons
*[[:fr:NPDS|NPDS]] One of the most advanced Community Management System - Actually REvolution 2011 release

==License==
PHP-Nuke is distributed for free and licensed under the GNU/GPL license, however current versions must be purchased and can then be distributed for free.

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* {{dmoz|Computers/Programming/Languages/PHP/Scripts/Content_Management/PHP-Nuke|PHP-Nuke}}
&lt;!-- Wikipedia is NOT a repository of links. Please feel free to submit your link to the DMoz.org/Google Directory category listed above. --&gt;

{{Application frameworks}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Php-Nuke}}
[[Category:Content management systems]]
[[Category:Open source content management systems]]
[[Category:PHP programming language]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[ar:بي إتش بي نيوك]]
[[ca:PHP-Nuke]]
[[de:PHP-Nuke]]
[[es:PHP-Nuke]]
[[fa:پی‌اچ‌پی-نیوک]]
[[fr:PHP-Nuke]]
[[he:PHP-Nuke]]
[[hy:ՓիԷյչՓի-Նուք]]
[[ku:PHP-Nuke]]
[[nl:PHP-Nuke]]
[[ja:PHP-Nuke]]
[[no:PHP-Nuke]]
[[pl:PHP-Nuke]]
[[pt:PHP-Nuke]]
[[ru:PHP-Nuke]]
[[th:PHP-Nuke]]
[[tr:PHP-Nuke]]
[[vi:PHP-Nuke]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
