<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="239274" ns="0" title="University of Nevada, Reno"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
 |name              = University of Nevada, Reno
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = University of Nevada (at) Reno seal.png
 |image_size        = 210px
 |caption           =
 |latin_name        =
 |motto             = Omnia Pro Patria ([[Latin]])
 |mottoeng          = All for our Country
 |established       = 1874
 |closed            =
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]] [[land-grant university|Land-Grant]]
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         = $186 Million [http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf]
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        =
 |president         = Marc Johnson (Interim)
  |vice-president    =
 |superintendent    =
 |provost           = Heather Hardy
 |vice_chancellor   =
 |rector            =
 |principal         =
 |dean              =
 |director          =
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           = 999
 |staff             =
 |students          = 17,679 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unr.edu/nevadanews/templates/details.aspx?articleid=5530&amp;zoneid=15 |title=Nevada News &amp;#124; University of Nevada, Reno |publisher=Unr.edu |date=2010-09-08 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |undergrad         = 14,431
 |postgrad          = 3,248
 |other             =
 |city              = [[Reno, Nevada|Reno]]
 |state             = [[Nevada]]
 |province          =
 |country           = [[United States]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|39|32|45|N|119|49|00|W|source:placeopedia|display=title}}
 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|290|acre|m2}}
 |former_names      =
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            =
 |colors            = {{color box|#003366}}{{color box|#999999}} Blue &amp; Silver&lt;ref name=fonts&gt;{{cite web|title=Fonts and Colors|url=http://www.unr.edu/im/policies/fonts-and-colors|work=University of Nevada, Reno|accessdate=16 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |colours           =
 |nickname          =  [[Nevada Wolf Pack|Wolf Pack]]
 |mascot            = Alphie and Wolfie Jr.
 |athletics         = [[NCAA Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Western Athletic Conference]]
 |affiliations      =
 |website           = http://www.unr.edu
 |logo              = [[File:UniversityofNevadaRenoSignature.png|210px]]
 |footnotes         =
}}

The '''University of Nevada, Reno''' (also referred to as '''University of Nevada''', '''UNR''', or simply '''Nevada'''), is a teaching and research university established in 1874 and located in [[Reno, Nevada]], USA.  It is the [[Land-grant university|land grant institution]] for the state of [[Nevada]].

The campus is home to the large-scale structures laboratory in the College of Engineering, which has put Nevada researchers at the forefront nationally in a wide range of seismological and large-scale structures testing and modeling. The Nevada Terawatt Facility, located on a satellite campus of the university, includes a terawatt-level [[Z-pinch]] machine and terawatt-class high-intensity laser system - one of the most powerful such lasers on any college campus in the country. It is home to the University of Nevada School of Medicine, with campuses in both of Nevada's major urban centers, Las Vegas and Reno, and a health network that extends to much of rural Nevada. The faculty are considered worldwide and national leaders in diverse areas such as environmental literature, journalism, Basque studies, and social sciences such as psychology.

The Carnegie Foundation ranks the University of Nevada, Reno in the Doctoral/Research University-Intensive category, which places it among the top 10 percent of all colleges and universities in the United States. This classification reflects the success in providing undergraduate students with opportunities to pursue degrees in more than 75 disciplines, and to pursue advanced degrees in a broad range of fields. Today, more than 100 graduate-degree programs are offered at the master's and doctoral level. Some of the degree programs offered by the university include journalism, biotechnology, mining, engineering, business administration, and natural sciences such as [[seismology]].

The university is home to the [[Donald W. Reynolds School of Journalism]], which has produced six [[Pulitzer Prize]] winners.&lt;ref&gt;http://journalism.unr.edu/about-us/&lt;/ref&gt; The school includes 16 clinical departments and five nationally recognized basic science departments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.medicine.nevada.edu/ |title=University of Nevada School of Medicine |publisher=Medicine.nevada.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The University of Nevada is also home to the National Judicial College, founded in 1963.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.judges.org/about.html |title=The NJC Experience |publisher=Judges.org |date=1978-01-01 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:UN RENO.jpg|thumb|left|Manzanita Lake in the southwestern part of the campus.]]
The University of Nevada was established by the Nevada State Constitution, and was founded in [[Elko, Nevada]] in 1874. In 1885, the University of Nevada was moved from Elko to its current home in Reno.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Discover Nevada: History, stats, and highlights|url=http://www.unr.edu/discover-nevada/university-history|work=University of Nevada, Reno|accessdate=2 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The University of Nevada remained the only four-year academic institution in the state of Nevada until 1965, when the Nevada Southern campus (now the [[University of Nevada, Las Vegas]]) was separated to become its own university.

The University of Nevada, Reno has been affected by the national economic crisis, which resulted in the vertical cutting of several programs rather than blanket across the board cuts. The Fall 2011 semester saw the largest incoming class in the history of the University.

===Precise name===
There is some debate over whether the university should be called UNR or Nevada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Demeritt |first=Clint |url=http://nevadasagebrush.com/blog/2007/09/25/the-coming-of-the-comma/ |title=The coming of the comma |publisher=The Nevada Sagebrush |date=2007-09-25 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, some claim that since it was the first university in the state, its historic name should be its official designation as it is in many other multi-campus public university systems such as the [[University of Michigan]] or similar to the way the University of California's flagship campus of UC Berkeley is referred to as &quot;Cal&quot;, but only for sporting purposes.   Several of the university's institutions retain the institution's traditional name, &quot;University of Nevada,&quot; including the alumni association, the student government, and the athletics department (which refers to the university's teams simply as &quot;Nevada,&quot; a practice held since the late 1800s). When the University plays in sports against in-state rival, the University of Nevada, Las Vegas, the school's name is decided by the home team. When the game is held in Reno, it reads UNLV vs Nevada, however, if held in Las Vegas it reads, UNLV vs UNR.

==Academics==
[[Image:Nevada-fountain.jpg|thumb|right|The fountain located in the University of Nevada Honor Court]]

University of Nevada, Reno is ranked 181 amongst national universities nationwide as a Tier 1 University.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/university-of-nevada-2568 |title=University of Nevada-Reno - Best College - Education - US News |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2011-09-13 |accessdate=2011-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  It also has the highly prestigious ranking of being one of the world's top 500 universities. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.unr.edu/nevada-today/news/2011/shanghai-rankings&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2011.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Bachelor's degree|Bachelor's]], [[master's degree|master's]], and [[doctorate|doctoral]] programs are offered through:

{|
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
===Colleges===
* [[College of Agriculture, Biotechnology, and Natural Resources at the University of Nevada|College of Agriculture, Biotechnology, and Natural Resources]]
* [[College of Business Administration at the University of Nevada|College of Business Administration]]
* [[College of Education at the University of Nevada|College of Education]]
* [[College of Engineering at the University of Nevada|College of Engineering]]
* [[College of Human and Community Sciences at the University of Nevada|College of Human and Community Sciences]]
* [[College of Liberal Arts at the University of Nevada|College of Liberal Arts]]
* [[College of Science at the University of Nevada|College of Science]]
* [[University of Nevada Cooperative Extension]]
* [[National Judicial College]]
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |

===Schools===
* [[Donald W. Reynolds School of Journalism]]
* [[Graduate School at the University of Nevada|Graduate School]]
* [[Mackay School of Earth Sciences and Engineering]]
* [[Orvis School of Nursing]]
* [[College of Liberal Arts at the University of Nevada| Nevada School of the Arts]]
* [[School of Medicine at the University of Nevada|School of Medicine]]
* [[School of Public Health]]
* [[School of Social Work]]
* [[School of Social Research and Justice Studies]]
|}

===Centers===
Nevada sponsors a center dedicated to [[Basque people|Basque]] studies (Including [[Basque language]]) due to the large Basque population in northern Nevada.

In addition, the university maintains and sponsors many [[Centers, institutes, and facilities related to the University of Nevada, Reno|centers, institutes &amp; facilities]].

===Libraries===
The university and surrounding community is served by several campus libraries. The libraries are:
* Mathewson-IGT Knowledge Center (main library). Opened on August 11, 2008 it was a $75.3 million project which began in September 2005. It replaced the Getchell library.
** Basque Library (housed in separate section of the Knowledge Center)
* DeLaMare Library (engineering, computer science, mining, and geology)
** Mary B. Ansari Map Library
* Savitt Medical Library
* Nell J. Redfield Learning and Resource Center (education library and resources)

===Rankings and reputation===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| Forbes = 221
| USNWR_NU = 181
| Wamo_NU = 235
| ARWU = 401-500
}}
Within the College of Business at the University of Nevada, the part-time MBA program is ranked 21st in the United States by BusinessWeek as of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.business.unr.edu/grad/part-time-program/index.html |title=Best Part-Time MBA &amp;#124; Graduate Programs &amp;#124; College of Business &amp;#124; University of Nevada, Reno |publisher=Business.unr.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[Image:Reno with mountains.gif|thumb|left|An older picture showing part of the campus in the foreground]]
The campus is located just north of downtown [[Reno, Nevada|Reno]] overlooking [[Truckee Meadows]] and the downtown casinos.

===Early construction===
The university's first building, Morrill Hall, was completed in 1887 and still stands on the historic quad at the campus' southern end. The hall is named after U.S. Senator Justin Morrill, author of the 1862 Land-Grant College Act.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Straka|first=Thomas|title=Ten things you didn't know about: Land-grant universities|url=http://www.unr.edu/silverandblue/archive/2009/fall/NSB_Fall_2009_WEB_36.pdf|accessdate=2 August 2011|newspaper=Nevada Silver &amp; Blue|date=2009 November}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Lincoln Hall (all-male residence) and Manzanita Hall (all-female residence) were both opened in 1896.

===The Quad===
The Quad is located in the southern part of the campus, surrounded by Morrill Hall and the Mackay School of Mines. This quadrangle is modeled after Thomas Jefferson’s at the University of Virginia. The northern end of the Quad contains a statue of [[John William Mackay]] (namesake of Nevada's Mackay School of Mines, later renamed the [[Mackay School of Earth Sciences and Engineering]]), created by [[Mount Rushmore]] designer [[Gutzon Borglum]]. The Quad and the original campus buildings surrounding it have a listing on the National Register of Historic Places.

[[Image:University of Nevada Quad, 2009-11-08.JPG|thumb|right|View of the Quad, looking north]]

===Arboretum===
Across the campus of the university exists the [[University of Nevada, Reno Arboretum]], which was established in 1985, contains a collection of trees, shrubs, flowers, ornamentals and native flora, including over 60 genera and about 200 species of trees, many with several cultivars present. Thirty-six mature elm trees line the Quad.

===Mackay Stadium===
{{Main|Mackay Stadium}}
The football team plays at Mackay Stadium, The modern Mackay Stadium was completed in 1965 with a seating capacity of 7,500. The facility has been expanded several times in the last 15 years and now seats 29,993.

===Residential Life===
The University Of Nevada, Reno offers a variety of options to students who are willing to stay on-campus. There are 8 different resident halls which comprise living learning communities and substance free halls. The living learning communities houses students of similar academic interests.
===Sustainability===
Since its creation in the Fall of 2008, the University of Nevada, Reno's Sustainability Committee has been gathering information on various aspects of campus sustainability and beginning the development of a plan for creating a more sustainable campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainability Committee and Campus Sustainability&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Sustainability Committee Information
  | publisher = University of Nevada-Reno
  | url = http://www.unr.edu/sustainability/committee/index.html
  | accessdate = 2009-06-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
A lot of efforts are made towards recycling and keeping the campus green. Many University buses run on bio-diesel fuels. The bicycle program has seen a significant increase in the number of bicycle users. The University's Food Services has made a commitment of 1% of the meal plan revenue to go towards funding sustainable initiatives on campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus Sustainability: Food&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Campus Sustainability: Food
  | publisher = University of  Nevada- Reno
  | url = http://environment.unr.edu/sustainability/campus-life/food.html
  | accessdate = 14 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to reduce energy use, UNR has installed solar panels on the Joe Crowley Student Union and built its first LEED accredited building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus Sustainability: Energy&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Campus Sustainability: Energy
  | publisher = University of  Nevada- Reno
  | url = http://environment.unr.edu/sustainability/energy/index.html
  | accessdate = 14 August 2011 }} &lt;/ref&gt;
The University of Nevada, Reno has been ranked among the nation's most sustainable colleges,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unr.edu/nevadanews/templates/details.aspx?articleid=5202&amp;zoneid=13 |title=Nevada News &amp;#124; University of Nevada, Reno |publisher=Unr.edu |date=2009-10-07 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; receiving an overall grade of &quot;B+&quot; on the Sustainable Endowment Institute's College Sustainability Report Card 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainable Endowments Institute Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title =College Sustainability Report Card 2010
  | publisher =Sustainable Endowments Institute
  | url =http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2010/schools/university-of-nevada-reno
  | accessdate = 2009-10-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student government==
===Associated Students of the University of Nevada===
The Associated Students of the University of Nevada (ASUN) is made up of every undergraduate student at the University of Nevada and provides a vehicle, through elected officials, to voice student concerns. The ASUN was founded as the Athletic Association in 1898 and is composed of an Executive Branch, Legislative Branch and Judicial Branch. The current ASUN President, Casey Stiteler, oversees all three branches and appoints the lead positions of the Executive Branch. The Executive Branch of ASUN consists of the following student body officers - President and Vice President - elected by the undergraduate student body. Appointed members include the Director of Programming, Director of Clubs and Organizations, Director of Traditions, Director of Campus Unity, Director of Legislative Affairs, Presidential Assistant on Public and Campus Relations, Attorney General, and Chief of Staff. The Senate of the Associated Students was established in 1933. The Senate is led by the Speaker of the Senate, and is the official voice of the undergraduate students on decisions regarding campus policies, programming, and money spent by the student government on student support services. The senate consists of 22 senators elected from each of the academic schools and colleges. [https://nevadaasun.com ASUN]

===Graduate Student Association===
The Graduate Student Association (GSA) represents the graduate student population at the University of Nevada. The GSA consists of 25 Council Members and a 3 member Executive Council. The Council Members are elected from all of the colleges and schools throughout the university with graduate programs. The Executive Council includes the GSA President, Vice President of Internal Affairs, and Vice President of External Affairs, which are elected by the GSA Council Members.

==Athletics==
{{Further|[[Nevada Wolf Pack]]}}
[[Image:NevadaWolfPack.png|thumb|right|Nevada Wolf Pack logo]]
Though often referred to as UNR within the state, the university is simply called ''Nevada'' for athletics purposes. Its sports teams are nicknamed the Wolf Pack (always two words). They participate in the NCAA's [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|FBS]] for [[American football|football]]) and in the [[Western Athletic Conference]].

===Men's basketball===
{{Further|[[Nevada Wolf Pack men's basketball]]}}

In March 2004, the Wolf Pack Men's basketball team qualified for the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA tournament]] and advanced to the Sweet Sixteen for the first time in school history. The team earned a repeat trip in 2005 and beat [[University of Texas at Austin|Texas]] in the first round before falling to eventual national runner-up [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign|Illinois]]. The team returned for 2006 as a #5 seed but was upset in the first round by former [[Big Sky Conference]] rival [[The University of Montana|Montana]]. They began the 2006-07 season ranked #24. The Pack's major star during this recent period of success was [[Nick Fazekas]]. In 2007, Nevada was ranked #9 in men's basketball, which is the highest ranking that Nevada has ever held. Coach [[Mark Fox (basketball)|Mark Fox]] took over after Trent Johnson left in 2004 to coach at [[Stanford University]]. On April 3, 2009 it was announced that David Carter would replace Fox who decided to leave Nevada for the same position at the [[University of Georgia]].

===Football===
{{Further|[[Nevada Wolf Pack football]]}}

The football team, currently coached by [[College Football Hall of Fame]]r [[Chris Ault]], plays at [[Mackay Stadium]]. The modern Mackay Stadium was completed in 1965 with a seating capacity of 7,500. The facility has been expanded several times in the last 15 years and now seats 29,993. In 2005, Nevada won a share of the WAC Title. The 2010 season saw Nevada at its best finishing the season ranked #11 in the AP and #13 in the BCS, stunning Boise State 34-31 and costing the Broncos a possible shot at the BCS title, to win another share of the WAC Title.

===Other===
{{Further|[[Nevada Wolf Pack]]}}
Other successes have come in boxing (four collegiate champion teams), [[rifle shooting]], baseball, women's soccer and softball, swimming and diving, rugby and lacrosse.

===Rivalries===
Annually, Nevada's football team plays its primary rival, [[University of Nevada, Las Vegas|UNLV]], for the [[Fremont Cannon]] in the [[Battle for Nevada]]. Nevada currently enjoys a 22-15 lead in the series, after beating UNLV in 2011, 37-0, in Reno, for the seventh straight year.  Nevada also plays UNLV once a year in basketball, with UNLV currently leading the series 51-19.  Nevada's two out-of-state rivals, particularly in [[American football|football]], are [[Boise State Broncos|Boise State]] and [[California State University, Fresno|Fresno State]]. Boise State is currently a member of the [[Mountain West Conference]], and Fresno State and Nevada will move there in 2012, which will intensify the Nevada-UNLV rivalry as UNLV is also in the MWC.

===Mascot===
The Wolf Pack's mascot is an [[anthropomorphized]] wolf named Alphie, who took over the duties of cheering from his uncle, Wolfie, in 1999. In 2007, Alphie was joined by his younger brother, Wolfie Jr.

===Conference affiliations===
Nevada has been a member of the [[Western Athletic Conference|WAC]] since 2000. Nevada will join the [[Mountain West Conference|Mountain West]] starting in 2012.[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncaa/news/story?id=5735144]

Previous conference memberships include:

* 1992-99 - [[Big West Conference|Big West]]
* 1979-92 - [[Big Sky Conference|Big Sky]] (swapped conference affiliations with [[Gonzaga University]], which has been without football since 1941)
* 1969-79 - [[West Coast Conference|West Coast Athletic]] - (independent for football)
*1954-1968 - [[Northern California Athletic Conference]]
[http://cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/div_ia/wac/nevada/index.php]

==Student media==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Ansari Business Bldg.JPG|thumb|left|Ansari Business Building]] --&gt;

Nevada's editorially independent, weekly student newspaper is called ''[[The Nevada Sagebrush]]''. It comes out every Tuesday afternoon, and employs more than 40 people, 25 full-time. Prior to 2004, the newspaper called itself simply the ''Sagebrush''.

The newspaper won the Associated Collegiate Press Pacemaker award in 2008 and 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nevada Sagebrush nominated for Pacemaker award|url=http://journalism.unr.edu/latestnews/app-news/0/185/nevada-sagebrush-nominated-for-pacemaker-award/|work=Reynolds School of Journalism|publisher=University of Nevada, Reno|accessdate=14 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was also a finalist for a Pacemaker at the 2006 and 2007 ACP student journalism awards. It has won the best of show award at the fall 2005, 2006 and 2007 ACP national conferences in its category (weekly broadsheet at a four-year university). It was also nominated for an online ACP Pacemaker in 2008. It's new web site, [www.nevadasagebrush.com], which launched in the fall of 2007, has also been recognized by the Center for Innovation in College Media for it breaking news packages, podcasts, videos and general innovation and Web presence. Many of The ''Nevada Sagebrush'''s former editors go on to work and take internships at newspapers and news organizations such as ''The Washington Post'', ''The Oregonian'', ''USA Today'', ''The Miami Herald'', ''The Arizona Republic'' and the Associated Press as well as dozens of local newspapers around the country.

[[UNR Insight Magazine|Insight Magazine]] is the only student-run magazine at the University of Nevada, Reno. Formerly Nevada's yearbook for nearly 100 years, ''Insight Magazine'', has evolved into the second major publication circulating at the university. The first edition of Insight Magazine was published in September 2008. It presents itself as a theme-based monthly magazine, providing photography, stories and graphics,  in contrast to the weekly, newspaper-style of ''The Sagebrush''. It is put out both in print and online. The online version, ''UNRINSIGHT.com'', provides both support for the published stories and independent content.

In its sophomore year, Insight Magazine has received national attention from major college media organizations, such as the Associated College Press and the College Media Advisers. Insight placed fifth for headline presentation in Best of Collegiate Design 2009 by the &quot;College Media Advisers&quot;. At the 2009 ACP Conference in Austin, Texas, Insight placed fifth in Best of Show for an audio podcast.

Nevada's literary arts journal ''Brushfire'' was created by a group of students in 1950.  It is released once a semester and publishes original poetry, literature, and art by students and some faculty and community members.

The university is also home to a student-run radio station, Wolf Pack Radio. The station broadcasts primarily through its website, although it comes through at 1700 AM.
Starting in the Fall 2010 semester, Nevada broadcast journalism students started &quot;Wolf Pack Week,&quot; a 30-minute television newscast that is shown around campus.  Future episodes will air on PBS in Reno and Las Vegas.

There are other independent student publications on campus (although they have stopped publishing regularly since 2006), including ''The Nevada Blue'' and the ''Pack Patriot''.

==Greek life==
{|
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
Interfraternity Council
*[[Alpha Epsilon Pi]], (ΑΕΠ)
*[[Alpha Tau Omega]], (ΑΤΩ)
*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]], (ΛΧΑ)
*[[Nu Alpha Kappa]], (ΝΑΚ)
*Nu Phi, (NΦ)
*[[Phi Delta Theta]], (ΦΔΘ)
*[[Pi Kappa Phi]], (ΠΚΦ)
*[[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], (ΣΑΕ)
*[[Sigma Nu]], (ΣΝ)
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], (ΣΦΕ)
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]], (ΤΚΕ)
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
Panhellenic Council
*[[Delta Delta Delta]], (ΔΔΔ)
*[[Delta Gamma]], (ΔΓ)
*[[Kappa Alpha Theta]] (ΚΑΘ)
*[[Pi Beta Phi]], (ΠΒΦ)
*[[Sigma Kappa]], (ΣΚ)
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
Multicultural Greek Council
*[[Alpha Kappa Psi]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.akpsi.org/news/25818/Psi-Phi-chapter-installs-at-University-of-Nevada---Reno.htm |title=Psi Phi chapter installs at University of Nevada - Reno - Alpha Kappa Psi |publisher=Akpsi.org |date= |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  (AKΨ)
*[[Alpha Phi Gamma (sorority)|Alpha Phi Gamma]] (colony)
*[[Delta Sigma Pi]], (ΔΣΠ)
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]], (ΔΣΘ)
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]]
*[[Lambda Phi Xi]], (ΛΦΞ)
*[[Lambda Psi Rho]], (ΛΨΡ)
*[[Nu Alpha Kappa]]
*[[Phi Beta Sigma]]
*Sigma Omega Nu
|}
===Former Fraternities &amp; Sororities===
*[[Alpha Tau Omega]], suspended for two years, until 2010, &quot;student conduct office found ATO guilty of hazing pledge members during recruitment last semester&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chase |first=Rebecca |url=http://nevadasagebrush.com/blog/2008/02/19/ato-found-guilty-of-hazing/ |title=ATO found guilty of hazing |publisher=The Nevada Sagebrush |date=2008-02-19 |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;
*[[Pi Kappa Alpha]], university charter revoked, new rushing member &quot;Albert Santos drowned in Manzanita Lake.&quot;

==Notable alumni &amp; faculty==
{{Main|List of people associated with the University of Nevada, Reno}}

==Film history==
The University of Nevada's classically-styled campus has served as the setting for many movies, including:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.delamare.unr.edu/CampusOnAHill/ |title=Campus on the Hill: A walking tour of the University of Nevada |publisher=Delamare.unr.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''[[Andy Hardy's Blonde Trouble]]'' (1944)
*''[[Margie (film)|Margie]]'' (1946)
*''[[Apartment for Peggy]]'' (1948)
*''[[Mother Is a Freshman]]'' (1949)
*''[[Mr. Belvedere Goes to College]]'' (1949)
*''[[Hilda Crane]]'' (1956)

==See also==
*[[Black Rock Press - University of Nevada, Reno]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.unr.edu/ Official website]
*[http://www.nevadawolfpack.com/ Official Athletics website]

{{NevadaUC}}
{{Western Athletic Conference}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nevada, Reno, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Nevada, Reno| ]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Nevada System of Higher Education]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Reno, Nevada]]
[[Category:Education in Washoe County, Nevada]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Washoe County, Nevada]]

[[de:University of Nevada, Reno]]
[[fa:دانشگاه نوادا در رینو]]
[[fr:Université du Nevada à Reno]]
[[ko:네바다 대학교 리노]]
[[ja:ネバダ大学リノ校]]
[[zh:內華達大學雷諾分校]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
