<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="239327" ns="0" title="Wake Forest University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name =Wake Forest University
|image_name = Wake Forest University Seal.svg
|image_size  =  200px
|motto =''Pro humanitate''
|mottoeng = For humanity
|established =February 3, 1834
|type =[[Private school|Private]]
|endowment =$935.2 million&lt;ref&gt;As of March 31, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = Wake Forest University Endowment Survey | work = The College Sustainable Report Card | publisher = Sustainable Endowments Institute | url = http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2011/schools/wake-forest-university/surveys/endowment-survey | accessdate = June 13, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
|staff =
|faculty =636 (non-med school)
|president =[[Nathan O. Hatch|Nathan Hatch]]
|undergrad =4,412
|postgrad =2,418
|former_names =Wake Forest Manual Labor Institute&lt;br&gt;(1834–1839)&lt;br&gt;Wake Forest College&lt;br&gt;(1839–1967)
|city =[[Winston-Salem, North Carolina|Winston-Salem]]
|state =[[North Carolina]]
|country =[[United States]]
|campus =[[Suburban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|340|acre|km²|1}}&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wikimapia.org/#y=36134816&amp;x=-80276595&amp;z=16&amp;l=0&amp;m=a&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors =[[Old Gold]] and [[black]]&lt;br/&gt;{{color box|#CFB53B}} {{color box|#000000}}
|mascot =[[Demon Deacon|The Demon Deacon]]
|athletics = [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] FBS&lt;br/&gt;26 varsity sports
|nickname =[[Wake Forest Demon Deacons|Demon Deacons]]  
|affiliations =[[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]]
|logo=[[File:Wake Forest University Logo.svg|200px]]
|website =[http://www.wfu.edu/ www.wfu.edu]
}}
'''Wake Forest University''' is a [[Private university|private]], coeducational [[university]] in the U.S. state of [[North Carolina]], founded in 1834. The university received its name from its original location in [[Wake Forest, North Carolina|Wake Forest]], north of [[Raleigh, North Carolina]], the state capital. The Reynolda Campus, the university's main campus, is located north of downtown [[Winston-Salem, North Carolina|Winston-Salem]], after the university moved there in 1956. The [[Wake Forest Baptist Medical Center]] campus is located nearby. The University also occupies lab space at the Bowman Gray Technical Center, at the downtown Piedmont Research Park, and at the Center for Nanotechnology and Molecular Materials. The University's [[Babcock Graduate School of Management]] maintains a presence on the main campus in Winston-Salem and in [[Charlotte, North Carolina]].

In the 2011 U.S. News America's Best Colleges report, Wake Forest ranked 25th overall among national universities, tied with the University of Virginia and the University of California, Los Angeles. Additionally, the same report ranked Wake Forest University 12th overall in terms of Best Undergraduate Teaching among national universities.

In the 2009 BusinessWeek Undergraduate Business Schools Rankings, the Calloway School of Business and Accountancy was ranked 14th overall, and first in terms of Academic Quality.

==History==
Wake Forest University was founded after the North Carolina [[Baptist]] State Convention purchased a {{convert|600|acre|km²|1|sing=on}} plantation from Dr. [[Calvin Jones (NC physician)|Calvin Jones]] in an area north of [[Raleigh, North Carolina|Raleigh]] ([[Wake County, North Carolina|Wake County]]) called the &quot;Forest of Wake.&quot; The new school, designed to teach both Baptist ministers and laymen, opened on February 3, 1834, as the Wake Forest Manual Labor Institute, named because students and staff were required to spend half of each day doing manual labor on the plantation. Dr. [[Samuel Wait]], a Baptist minister, was selected as the &quot;principal,&quot; later president, of the institute.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wfu.edu/history/HST_WFU/perry.html History of Wake Forest University&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:UpperQuad ACB.jpg|right|thumb|Wait Chapel located on the Hearn Plaza (or the 'Upper Quad').]]
In 1838, it was renamed Wake Forest College, and the manual labor system was abandoned. The town that grew up around the college came to be called the town of [[Wake Forest, North Carolina|Wake Forest]]. In 1862, during the [[American Civil War]], the school closed due to the loss of most students and some faculty to service in the [[Confederate States Army]].  The College re-opened in 1866 and prospered over the next four decades under the leadership of presidents [[Washington Manley Wingate]], [[Thomas H. Pritchard]], and [[Charles Taylor (university president)|Charles Taylor]]. In 1894, the School of Law was established, followed by the School of Medicine in 1902. The university held its first summer session in 1921.

The leading college figure in the early 20th century was Dr. [[William L. Poteat]], a gifted [[biology|biologist]] and the first layman to be elected president in the college’s history. “Dr. Billy” continued to promote growth, hired many outstanding professors, and expanded the [[science]] curriculum. He also stirred upheaval among North Carolina Baptists with his strong support of teaching the theory of [[evolution]] but eventually won formal support from the Baptist State Convention for academic freedom at the College.

[[File:BensonCenter ACB.jpg|thumb|left|The Benson University Center]]
The School of Medicine moved to [[Winston-Salem]] (then North Carolina's second-largest city) in 1941 under the supervision of Dean [[Coy Cornelius Carpenter]], who guided the school through the transition from a two-year to a four-year program. The school then became the [[Bowman Gray]] School of Medicine. The following year, 1942, Wake Forest admitted its first female undergraduate students, after [[World War II]] dramatically depleted the pool of male students.

In 1946, as a result of large gifts from the [[Z. Smith Reynolds Foundation]], the entire college agreed to move to Winston-Salem, a move that was completed for the beginning of the fall 1956 term, under the leadership of Dr. Harold W. Tribble. Charles and Mary Babcock (daughter of [[R. J. Reynolds]]) donated to the college about {{convert|350|acre|km²|1}} of fields and woods at &quot;Reynolda,&quot; their estate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.journalnow.com/servlet/Satellite|title=www.journalnow.com/servlet/Satellite&lt;!--INSERT TITLE--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1952 to 1956, fourteen new buildings were constructed on the new campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;The Undergraduate Schools: Bulletin of Wake Forest University 2007–2008&lt;/ref&gt; These buildings were constructed in [[Georgian (architecture)|Georgian]] style.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt; The old campus in Wake Forest was sold to the Baptist State Convention to establish the [[Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary]].

A graduate studies program was inaugurated in 1961, and in 1967 the school became the fully accredited Wake Forest University. The [[Babcock Graduate School of Management]] was established in 1969. The [[James R. Scales Fine Arts Center]] opened in 1979. In 1986, Wake Forest gained autonomy from the Baptist State Convention of North Carolina and established a fraternal relationship with it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://revgil.blogspot.com/2007/02/wake-forest-university-and-baptist.html|title= address given by Bill Leonard, dean of the Divinity School, at the spring 2007 convocation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1999/111799h.htm|title=Hearn says Wake Forest remains committed to its Baptist heritage}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The thirteenth president of Wake Forest is [[Nathan O. Hatch]], former provost at the [[University of Notre Dame]]. Hatch was officially installed as president on October 20, 2005. He assumed office on July 1,  2005, succeeding [[Thomas K. Hearn, Jr.]], who had retired after 22 years in office.

===Political, social===
On March 17, 1978, President [[Jimmy Carter]] made a major National Security address in [[Wait Chapel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=30516|title=Address at Wake Forest University}}&lt;/ref&gt; Twice the school has hosted [[United States presidential election debates|presidential debates]]. The first, between then-Vice President [[George H.W. Bush]] and Governor [[Michael Dukakis]] on September 25, 1988. The second matched then-Governor [[George W. Bush]] against Vice President [[Al Gore]] on October 11, 2000.  Both debates were hosted in [[Wait Chapel]].

In the predawn hours of April 18, 1978, students affixed a large Mickey Mouse to the {{convert|10|ft|m|adj=mid|-diameter}} clock face of Wait Chapel facing the Quad.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Criminal Charges Possible in WFU Mickey Mouse Prank&quot;, Winston-Salem Journal, April 19, 1978&lt;/ref&gt; On September 13, 2007 Wait Chapel was the venue for a broadcast of [[National Public Radio]] (NPR) show, [[Wait, Wait, Don't Tell Me]]. The show aired on September 15.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.npr.org/programs/waitwait/|title= Wait, Wait, Don't Tell Me}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
Since 1986, the university has produced 12 [[Rhodes Scholar]]s&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.wfu.edu/2011/11/20/turner-named-rhodes-scholar/ | title=Turner named Rhodes Scholar | accessdate = 2011-11-21 | author=WFU News Service | date=2011-11-20  | publisher=Wake Forest University | quote=He is the 12th Wake Forest student to be named a Rhodes Scholar in the past 25 years}}&lt;/ref&gt; and numerous [[Marshall Scholarship|Marshall]] and [[Fulbright]] recipients.

[[File:WakeInsideReynolda.jpg|left|thumb|A formal lounge area used for studying inside Reynolda Hall overlooking the Magnolia Quad (Manchester Plaza).]]

===Undergraduate===
Wake Forest's undergraduate component consists of Wake Forest College (School of Arts and Science) and the Wayne Calloway School of Business and Accountancy. The university offers 34 majors and many interdisciplinary minors across various fields of study. In order to attend the Wayne Calloway School, students must make a special application to its program. The Calloway School offers a five-year accountancy program whereby a student earns a BS and an MS in Accountancy and qualifies to sit for the [[Certified Public Accountant|CPA]] exam after 5 years of combined undergraduate and graduate study.

In order to graduate, a Wake Forest student must finish a basic set of classes and a set of divisional classes. The basic set of classes includes a first-year seminar, a writing seminar, health and PE classes, and foreign language literature. The latter usually requires students to take additional languages classes first. Languages available include Spanish, French, German, Latin, Greek, Japanese, Chinese, Arabic, and others.

About 89% of Wake Forest professors hold the terminal degree in their field. Wake Forest professors are expected to excel in both teaching and scholarship.

Wake Forest offers a number of [[study abroad]] programs for its undergraduates and, in the summers, for its [[law school]] students. About half of Wake Forest undergraduates spend at least one semester abroad.
[[File:WaitChapelAtNight.jpg|thumb|Wait Chapel at night.]]

The Wake Forest Department of Theatre and Dance has sixteen full-time faculty and provides academic instruction in acting, directing, dance, and related subjects, and runs the university theatre.

:{{Details|Wake Forest Department of Theatre and Dance|this}}

===Graduate===
====Wake Forest Graduate School of Arts and Sciences====
The Graduate School of Arts and Sciences offers 25 programs of graduate-level study and includes 13 areas of Ph.D. study as well as five joint degree programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://graduate.wfu.edu/ | title=Do Something Extraordinary | work=Wake Forest University Graduate School of Arts and Sciences | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://graduate.wfu.edu/admissions/programs.html | title=Programs of Study | work=Wake Forest University Graduate School of Arts and Sciences | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Professional schools====
In addition to the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, Wake Forest University has four professional schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;quick_wfu&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/visitors/quickfacts.html | title=Visitors' Center: Quick Facts | accessdate=2008-09-03 | publisher=Wake Forest University}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Wake Forest School of Law=====
{{Main|Wake Forest University School of Law}}

=====Wake Forest School of Medicine=====
{{Main|Wake Forest University School of Medicine}}

=====Babcock Graduate School of Management=====
{{Main|Babcock Graduate School of Management}}

=====Wake Forest School of Divinity=====
{{Main|Wake Forest University School of Divinity}}
The Wake Forest University School of Divinity offers a Master of Divinity degree as well two dual-degree programs in cooperation with other graduate programs at the university: a four-year Master of Divinity/Master of Arts in Counseling program and a five-year Master of Divinity and Juris Doctor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/mdiv.html | title=The Master of Divinity Program | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/counseling.html | title=Master of Divinity/Master of Arts in Counseling Dual Degree | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/law.html | title=Dual Degree in Master of Divinity and Juris Doctor  | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The school currently lists 12 faculty, 15 adjunct faculty, and 15 associated faculty from other university departments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/alphalist.html |title=Faculty | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/alphalist.html | title=Adjunct Faculty | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/alphalist.html | title=Associated University Faculty | work=Wake Forest University School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the idea had been around for many years, long-range planning for the university's divinity school began in April 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;div-about&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://divinity.wfu.edu/about.html | title=About the School of Divinity | accessdate=2008-09-03 | publisher=Wake Forest University}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In May 1996, Bill J. Leonard was appointed the school's first dean.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1996/052196l.htm | title=Leonard Named Dean of New Divinity School | author=Kevin Cox | date=1996-05-21 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Leonard soon began describing the school as students, faculty, and staff continue to describe it today, &quot;Christian by tradition, ecumenical in outlook, and Baptist in heritage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1999/101299s.htm | title=&quot;Not Instruction, but Provocation&quot;: Doing Theology at a New Divinity School | author=Bill J. Leonard | date=1999-10-12 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In March 1998, the school announced selections for its 14 member board of visitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1998/033198d.htm | title=WFU Names First Members to New Divinity School Board | author=Wayne Thompson | date=1998-03-31 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The first faculty members were named in April 1998, and additional faculty were hired that October.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1998/042898d.htm | title=WFU Announces First Faculty of Divinity School | author=Wayne Thompson | date=1998-04-28 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1998/101498w.htm | title=Wake Forest Divinity School Expands First Faculty | author=Kevin Cox | date=1998-10-14 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1999, 19 women and five men became the first 24 students to enroll in the program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/1999/081899d.htm | title=Divinity school's first students playing a part in university's history | author=Julie Leonard | date=1999-08-18 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university's first 20 Master of Divinity degrees were conferred May 20, 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wfu.edu/wfunews/2002/052002g.html | title=WFU comes full circle as Divinity School celebrates first graduates | author=Vanessa Urruela Willis | date=2002-05-20 | publisher=Wake Forest University News Service | accessdate=2008-09-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rankings===

In the 2011 ''[[US News and World Report|U.S. News]]'' America's Best Colleges report, Wake Forest ranked 25th (tied with [[University of Virginia]], [[University of Southern California]] and [[UCLA]]) overall among &quot;national universities.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/national-search/page+2 |title=National Universities Rankings |author=[[US News and World Report]] |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, the same report ranked Wake Forest University 12th overall in terms of &quot;Best Undergraduate Teaching&quot; among &quot;national universities.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-ut-rank Best Undergraduate Teaching | Rankings | Top National Universities | US News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In the 2009 ''[[BusinessWeek]]'' Undergraduate Business Schools Rankings, the Calloway School of Business and Accountancy was ranked 14th overall, and tied for #1 in terms of Academic Quality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bwnt.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/undergrad_bschool_2009/ The Top Undergraduate Business Programs - Businessweek&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Undergrad Rankings 2009 |url=http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/rankings// |year=2009 |accessdate=2009-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Institute of International Education 2008 Report on International Educational Exchange, Wake Forest was ranked second in undergraduate participation in study-abroad programs among doctoral/research universities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wfu.edu/news/release/2008.11.17.s.php/?p=89229 |title=Open Doors 2008 |year=2008 |accessdate=2009-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2010 US News Graduate School Rankings ranked Wake Forest's Law school 38th in the country, its Medical school 33rd in Primary Care and 44th in Research, and the Babcock School of Management 46th.

==Wake Forest University Press==
Wake Forest is the home of [http://www.wfu.edu/wfupress/ Wake Forest University Press]. Established in 1976 by Irish scholar Dillon Johnston, with the support of Provost Edwin Wilson and President James Ralph Scales, the press is the premier publisher of Irish poetry in North America. Among the poets published are Ciaran Carson, Thomas Kinsella, Michael Longley, Medbh McGuckian, John Montague, Eilean Ni Chuilleanain and Irish language poet Nuala Ni Dhomhnaill. 

==Student life==
===Fraternities and sororities===
Wake Forest's Greek life is unusual in that the Greeks do not have houses concentrated in a &quot;Greek Row.&quot; Instead Greeks occupy lounges adjoining halls of a greater building. These areas are spread out evenly across campus, with the exception of Delta Kappa Epsilon, which has its residence off campus.
Approximately 50% of the undergraduate student body is Greek.

Fraternities on campus: [[Alpha Kappa Psi]], [[Alpha Sigma Phi]], [[Alpha Phi Omega]], [[Chi Psi]], [[Delta Kappa Epsilon]], [[Kappa Alpha Order]],  [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Kappa Kappa Psi]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Lambda Chi Alpha]], [[Phi Beta Sigma]], [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], [[Sigma Chi]], [[Sigma Nu]], [[Sigma Pi]], [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], and [[Theta Chi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Wayback|url=http://www.wfu.edu/housing/greek/ifc/index.html|title=WFU | Residence Life &amp;amp; Housing|date=20060902000111}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sororities on campus: [[Alpha Delta Pi]], [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]], [[Chi Omega]], [[Delta Delta Delta]], [[Delta Zeta]], [[Kappa Delta]], [[Kappa Beta Gamma]], [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]], and [[Phi Mu]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.wfu.edu/panhellenic/ WFU | National Panhellenic Council&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Wake Forest is also home to the Sigma Delta chapter of [[Order of Omega]], an honor society for members of Greek organizations. Members are selected from the top 3% of Greeks on campus based high standards in the areas of scholarship, leadership, and involvement within their respective organization and within the Greek, campus and local communities.&lt;ref&gt;{{Wayback|url=http://www.wfu.edu/housing/greek/omega.html|title=Order of OMEGA: Sigma Delta Chapter|date=20060902000306}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Physical activity options===
Wake Forest offers a vast array of possibilities for physical activity, be it for recreation or health.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}} The university offers classes in [[Yoga]], Dance, Boot Camp, etc. In addition, some classes are offered for credit on sports theory and practice, as well as several dance courses. Intramural Sports are also extremely popular and take place for a variety of sports, depending on the season.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}  The university rec center, Reynolds Gym, is the oldest gym in the ACC.  The university is in the planning process for a new rec center to replace the aging Reynolds Gym and the now inadequate Miller Fitness Center.

===Dining facilities===
Every Wake Forest undergraduate student who lives on campus is required to sign up for some form of a meal plan in coordination with [[Aramark]]. The meals can be consumed in the main dining facility known as &quot;The Pit&quot; or the [[Magnolia]] Room, both of which are located at Reynolda Hall, in the center of the campus. At the neighboring Benson Center, students can buy food and snacks independent of their meal plan from Aramark or from [[Chick-fil-A]]. A [[Subway (restaurant)|Subway]] is also located on campus, off Hearn Plaza.

In the fall of 2005, Aramark, through its Fresh Foods Company, renovated &quot;The Pit&quot; in an attempt to improve the quality of the dining experience. The newly renovated area contains a variety a food stations with a &quot;cooked upon order&quot; service.  As of October 6, 2008, there has been a full-service [[Starbucks]] in the library.

===Student media===
*[[WFDD]] is the broadcast service of Wake Forest University, with a signal of 36,000 watts broadcasting to 32 counties in North Carolina and [[Virginia]].
*''WAKE Radio'' is a student-run [[internet]] radio station. Students regularly broadcast shows ranging from political talk to underground indie music hours.
*''The Student'' is a student-run website created and run by students to help integrate the student body to academic activities and social events around campus and the Winston-Salem area.
*Wake Forest University's school newspaper is the ''Old Gold &amp; Black'' (OGB), named for the school's colors. Published weekly from an office in Benson University Center, the ''[[Old Gold &amp; Black]]'' is produced by a group of student editors, reporters and photographers.
*The school television channel is [[Wake tv]]. Its feature television show is the weekly edition ''Wake-TV News''. ''Sportsline'' is another popular show among students, where callers can ask the hosts questions about sports.
*''The Howler'' is the annual yearbook.
*''Three to Four Ounces'' is the only official literary magazine on campus, publishing a collection of original student poetry, prose, and art each semester. It is also the longest-running media outlet on campus, as it began in 1882 as ''The Student'' when the school was still known as Wake Forest College.&lt;ref&gt;{{Wayback|url=http://wakestudent.com/about/|title=The Student at Wake Forest University|date=20070717214508}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Notice'' is a student-made magazine funded by ''Three to Four Ounces'' and designed to enlighten the students of Wake Forest about the creative people surrounding them. The project's intent is to celebrate and encourage creativity on campus in visual arts, music, writing, or any provocative form of expression.

===Undergraduate student housing===
Wake Forest undergraduate students are guaranteed on-campus housing for four years. For their first two years as a full time enrolled student, students are required to live on campus. Residence Life is divided into thirteen communities which are staffed by a graduate hall director and a staff of RAs (resident advisers) who facilitate community building and assume administrative responsibilities.  All student housing has air-conditioning, closets, wired/wireless internet access, cable television connections, and free unlimited washer/dryer usage. Every residence hall is equipped with at least one communal lounge area (with a big-screen television, sometimes a ping-pong table, pianos, etc.) and kitchen area. Student housing in Polo offers two-bedroom apartment-style living and four bedroom, two bathroom townhouse-style living, complete with furnished bedrooms, living room, and dining room furniture.

The thirteen community areas for the 2011–12 academic year are: Bostwick Hall, Johnson Hall, Babcock Hall, Luter Hall, Collins Hall, South Hall, Palmer/Piccolo Halls, Kitchin Hall, Davis Hall, Poteat/Huffman Halls, Taylor/Efird Halls, Polo/Martin/Roadhouses Area, and the Apartments Area.  Freshman housing is located in Collins, South, Babcock, Luter, Bostwick, and Johnson halls.

The office of Residence Life &amp; Housing boasts 105 undergraduate RAs, and 13 graduate hall directors.  Along with student staff, the RL&amp;H office supports two major residential student organizations: the Resident Student Association, and the National Residence Hall Honorary.

===Student union===
The event-planning arm of Wake Forest is undergraduate student led and run organization known as Student Union. Student union projects include such events as [[Homecoming]], Family Weekend, Special Lectures, Concert Events, and the Coffeehouse music series.

Their most celebrated and well-attended event is the annual &quot;Shag on the Mag&quot; that occurs on the Manchester Quad (formerly the Magnolia Quad) each spring and was begun in 2005 by then Springfest Chairman Joseph Bumgarner. A big tent covering the entire quad is laid out and students [[shag]] dance together to a live band.

===Student government===
Wake Forest Student Government (known as SG) works under a [[Semi-presidential system|semi-Presidential system]].

The core component is the General Assembly, which acts as a student legislature. The General Assembly is made up of legislators, represented and voted by each residence hall. The legislators are assigned within one of six committees to specialize in a particular area of student needs.

==Athletics==
{{main|Wake Forest Demon Deacons}}
[[File:WakeForestRolledQuad.jpg|thumb|&quot;Rolling the Quad&quot; is a WFU tradition that is done after major victories in athletic competition.]]
[[File:DemonDeaconACB.jpg|right|thumb|Wake Forest University Mascot Demon Deacon]]

Originally, Wake Forest's athletic teams were known as the Fighting Baptists, due to its association with the Baptist Convention (from which it later separated itself). However, in 1923, after a particularly impressive win against the [[Duke University|Duke]] [[Duke Blue Devils|Blue Devils]], a newspaper reporter wrote that the Deacons &quot;fought like Demons&quot;, giving rise to the current team name, the &quot;'''[[Demon Deacon]]s'''.&quot;

Wake Forest has won a total of eight national championships in four different sports; four of these championships have come in the past six years. Wake Forest is sometimes referred to as being a part of &quot;[[Tobacco Road]]&quot; or &quot;The Big Four,&quot; terms that refer to the four North Carolina schools that compete heatedly against each other within the ACC; these include [[Duke University|Duke]], [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill|North Carolina]], and [[North Carolina State]], as well as Wake Forest.

The Demon Deacons participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA's]] Division I (in the [[Football Bowl Subdivision|Bowl Subdivision]] for [[college football|football]]) and in the [[Atlantic Coast Conference]].

The [[Athletic director|Athletics Director]] is Ron Wellman.

===Football===
{{main|Wake Forest Demon Deacons football}}
{{seealso|2010 Wake Forest Demon Deacons football team}}
{{seealso|2011 Wake Forest Demon Deacons football team}}

====2006 Season====
{{main|2006 Wake Forest Demon Deacons football team}}
Wake Forest's football team was ranked in the Top 25 in the nation by the [[AP Poll]] during most of the 2006 season. They won the 2006 ACC Atlantic Division Title and went on to defeat the [[2006 Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets football team|Georgia Tech Yellow Jackets]] 9-6 on December 2 in the ACC Championship Game in Jacksonville, FL. The win sent Wake Forest to the [[Orange Bowl (game)|Orange Bowl]] to play the Big East champion [[Louisville Cardinals football|Louisville Cardinals]], where they lost 24–13. However, this made Wake Forest the smallest school to ever compete in the [[Bowl Championship Series]]. Of all schools that play Division I FBS football, only [[Rice University|Rice]] and [[University of Tulsa|Tulsa]] have smaller undergraduate enrollments, and Wake has the smallest undergraduate enrollment of any school in the [[BCS conference]]s.

For his part in the record-setting season, coach [[Jim Grobe]] was unanimously selected ACC Coach of the Year, and handily won the AP Coach of the Year award several weeks later. Coach Grobe signed a ten-year contract in 2003.

====2007 Season====
{{main|2007 Wake Forest Demon Deacons football team}}
Wake Forest followed its success in 2006 with another excellent year and finished the regular season with a record of 8 wins and 4 losses. During the season, the Demon Deacons were briefly ranked in the Top 25. Their success throughout the year earned Wake Forest an invitation to the Meineke Car Care Bowl in Charlotte, North Carolina. Played on December 29 in the Bank of America stadium (home of the Carolina Panthers) the Demon Deacons defeated the Connecticut Huskies 24-10.

Wake Forest's head coach, Jim Grobe, continues to garner national attention as an outstanding college football coach. Though he was offered coaching positions at other schools, Grobe chose to remain with the Deacons, citing a desire to remain at an institution that successfully balances high-level academics with a major athletic program.

Wake Forest plays its home football games at [[BB&amp;T Field]] (formerly Groves Stadium).

===Men's basketball===
{{main|Wake Forest Demon Deacons men's basketball}}
Wake Forest is generally regarded as a competitive program in men's [[basketball]], frequently qualifying for the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship]] (20 times in the school's history). They reached the [[Final Four]] once, in 1962. The school's famous basketball alumni include [[Billy Packer]], a guard on the 1962 Final Four team who became far more famous as a basketball broadcaster; Tyrone Curtis [[Muggsy Bogues|&quot;Muggsy&quot; Bogues]], the shortest player ever to play in the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]]; [[Randolph Childress]], for his MVP performance in the 1995 ACC Tournament; [[Washington Wizards]] star [[Josh Howard]]; [[Chris Paul]] of the [[New Orleans Hornets]] and the 2006 [[NBA Rookie of the Year Award]]; and two-time league MVP and three-time [[NBA Finals]] MVP [[Tim Duncan]]. [[Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum]] is the home venue for the Demon Deacons basketball team. [[Skip Prosser]], Wake Forest University's men's basketball coach since 2001, died in Winston-Salem on July 26, 2007. One of Prosser's assistant coaches, [[Dino Gaudio]], was named to replace him.  On April 13, 2010, [[Jeff Bzdelik]] was hired, taking the place of the recently fired Gaudio.

===Women's basketball===
Wake Forest is generally regarded as a competitive program in women's [[basketball]], frequently qualifying for the NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship. [[Lawrence Joel Veterans Memorial Coliseum]] is the home venue for the Demon Deacons basketball team. [[Mike Petersen]], Wake Forest University's women's basketball coach is in his 5th season and is excited about the upcoming season.  Candice Jackson joins Bob Clark as the team assistant coaches.

===Women's field hockey===
Recent athletic honors include three consecutive [[NCAA]] [[Field Hockey]] [[NCAA Women's Field Hockey Championship|national championships]] in 2002, 2003, and 2004 under Head Coach [[Jennifer Averill]]. In 2005, the Deacs were defeated in the semifinal round by [[Duke University]], and in the 2006 championship game by the [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]].

===Golf===
Wake Forest has had several successful [[golf]] teams, winning [[NCAA Division I Men's Golf Championships|national championships]] in 1974, 1975, and 1986. Several well-known players include [[Arnold Palmer]], [[Lanny Wadkins]], [[Darren Clarke]], [[Jay Haas]], [[Curtis Strange]], Billy Andrade, Gary Halberg, [[Robert Wrenn]], [[Scott Hoch]], [[Webb Simpson]], and [[Bill Haas]].

===Soccer===
{{main article|Wake Forest Demon Deacons soccer}} 
Wake Forest is a consistent [[NCAA Men's Soccer Championship|national title]] contender in men's [[soccer]]. In recent years several players from the program have played professionally in [[Major League Soccer]], including [[Brian Carroll]], [[Will Hesmer]], [[Justin Moose]], [[Michael Parkhurst]], [[Pat Phelan (soccer)|Pat Phelan]], [[James Riley (soccer)|James Riley]], [[Scott Sealy]], [[Matt Taylor (American soccer)|Matt Taylor]], and [[Wells Thompson]]. In 2006 the team advanced to the final four of the NCAA tournament where they were defeated in a penalty kick shootout by the [[University of California, Santa Barbara]]. They captured the [[2007 Division I Men's College Cup|2007 NCAA Men's Soccer Championship]] defeating Ohio State 2-1, with the winning goal scored by [[Zack Schilawski]].  The Demon Deacons returned to the final four of the [[2009 Division I Men's College Cup]], losing to the [[University of Virginia]] 2-1 in overtime in the semifinals.

===Baseball===
{{main|Wake Forest Demon Deacons baseball}}
Wake Forest won the [[1955 College World Series]] in [[NCAA baseball|baseball]].
In 2009, the team began playing on [[Ernie Shore Field]], in [[Winston-Salem]], NC, moving to this field from their former home at [[Gene Hooks Stadium]] on campus.  

===Screamin' Demons===
Student attendance of [[Wake Forest Football]] and [[Basketball]] games is high, in part due to the program known as &quot;Screamin' Demons.&quot; At the beginning of each respective athletic season students on the Reynolda Campus can sign up for the program whereby they pay $15 for each season; in addition to the best seats at the games, this gets students a football shirt in the fall and a tie-dye t-shirt in the spring along with a card that serves as an automatic pass to the sporting events. They lose this privilege if they miss two of the games. Through the planning of Sports Marketing and the Screamin' Demons program, basketball game seats in the students section are difficult to attain without participating in the Screamin' Demons program. The arena can seat only 2,250 of the 4,500 undergraduate students at Wake Forest. At least 150 seats are always set aside for non-Screamin Demons, who sit behind the 2,100 member group.

==Student organizations==
There are over 160 chartered student organizations of all sorts. Student sports organizations are highly visible on campus. Special interest organizations range from the academic, such the [[Model United Nations]] team, to the artistic, such as the [[handbell]] choir. In spring of 2006, the [[Mock Trial]] team was notable in qualifying for the national tournament while only in its 2nd year in operation. Religious organizations are also numerous. Both the [[College Republicans]] and [[College Democrats]] have active chapters at the University. Historic student organizations such as the Philomathesians, an artistic literary magazine, are also present. Students are entertained by numerous performing groups, including The Lilting Banshee Comedy Troupe.

The Office of Student Development, led by [[Michael Gerald Ford]], son of [[Gerald R. Ford]], oversees all student organizations. Student Development also organizes leadership oriented student activities such as LEAD, a semester long course in campus leadership.

===Volunteer Service Corps===
The Volunteer Service Corps (VSC) is one of the most popular student organizations. It coordinates volunteering in both the local and international/national setting via service projects and trips. The organization has annual service trips to Russia, Vietnam, and Latin America. In light of the disaster caused by [[Hurricane Katrina]], VSC sent 30 Wake Students on a Wake Alternative Spring Break in the Spring of 2006.

===A cappella groups===
Wake Forest has a number of vibrant [[a cappella]] groups that produce annual records and have popular performances on and off campus.
They include:
* [[Chi Rho Wake Forest Christian Male A Cappella Ensemble|Chi Rho]] – award winning all male Christian group
* Innuendo – mixed gender a cappella group
* Plead the Fifth [http://www.wfupleadthefifth.com]- all male group 
* [http://www.minorvariation.com Minor Variation]- all female Christian group
* Demon Divas – all female group

===Army ROTC===
Wake Forest University offers only Army ROTC. In 2006 the Army ROTC program was awarded the MacArthur Award by the [[United States Army]] for having the best medium sized ROTC battalion in the nation. There are about sixty cadets in the program, and about half of each military science class finishes Leadership Development Advanced Camp ([[LDAC]]) as a &quot;Distinguished Military Graduate,&quot; the top 20% of ROTC graduates.

The minimum service commitment of a contracted cadet who graduates from ROTC is four years active duty and four years of inactive reserve duty after that. Alternatively, a cadet can choose to forgo active duty service and serve eight straight years in the active Reserve or National Guard. Other alternative service plans are available for those who intend to be an Army doctor, lawyer, or chaplain with source of commissioning via ROTC.

At Wake Forest contracted ROTC cadets are given full scholarship, a monthly stipend, and book money by the US Army. The university extends the scholarship with free room and board.

The program also serves students from [[Winston-Salem State University]] and [[Salem College]].

==Technology==
Wake Forest has received praise for its efforts in the field of technology. In 2003, The Princeton Review listed it as the number two &quot;Most Connected Campus&quot; in the [[United States]]. The University's Information Systems (IS) department has a program that issues new [[ThinkPad|Lenovo ThinkPad]] laptop computers to all undergraduate and graduate students and faculty. High speed wireless and wired Internet access is now provided across campus.
For undergraduate students living on campus, the university provides Resident Technology Advisors (RTAs), undergraduate students who also live on campus, trained to aid students with technical help for their laptops.

Information Systems, in cooperation with high technology firms like [[IBM]], [[AT&amp;T]], and [[Hewlett Packard|HP]], also actively engage in technology testing with members of the student body. These selected students participate through either co-payment or leasing plans in experimental uses of technology in education and college life through [http://www.wfu.edu/is/research/index.html IS Research and Development]. A recent program of this type was called MobileU and provided students involved in the program with PDA/phone combos and software to support educational and personal activities.

The University is a founding member of WinstonNet, a non-profit organization of educational and municipal institutions in [[Winston-Salem, NC]] that among other things provides a gigabit ethernet based regional [[point of presence]] (or, rPOP) for the [[North Carolina Research and Education Network]].

Wake Forest University provides faculty with access to high performance computing efforts locally with the WFU DEAC cluster and statewide with its participation in the NC Grid Computing Initiative. The statewide efforts are coordinated through the non-profit organization.

==University campuses==
===Reynolda Campus===
[[File:ZSR ACB.jpg|thumb|300px|right| Z. Smith Reynolds Library]]
The Reynolda Campus is the main campus for Wake Forest University, housing the undergraduate colleges, three of the four graduate schools, and half the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. The core of Reynolda campus is the two interlinked quads, separated by the main administrative building/main dining facility, Reynolda Hall, into North and South Campus.

North Campus consists of the T.K. Hearn Plaza, better known as &quot;the quad,&quot; which holds the six upperclassmen residential buildings, the US Post Office, [[Subway (restaurant)|Subway]] restaurant, book/office supply store, clothing/athletic store, and [[Wait Chapel]]. Wait Chapel serves multiple functions. Its auditorium serves as an area for prayer, ceremonies, concerts, and certain guest speakers. The classrooms at Wait Chapel house the offices and classrooms for the Divinity School and the Religion Department.  

South Campus is the home of Manchester Quad (formerly known as the Magnolia Quad or Mag quad). It holds freshman housing, most of the classroom buildings, the Benson Center, and the Z. Smith Reynolds Library.

===Bowman Gray Campus===
Known as the Bowman Gray Campus, a large hospital and medical center are located away from the Reynolda Campus in the Ardmore neighborhood near downtown Winston-Salem. This combined facility is now known as the Wake Forest University Baptist Medical Center, and is currently the largest employer in [[Forsyth County, North Carolina|Forsyth County]]. The facility comprises the Wake Forest University School of Medicine, formerly known as the Bowman Gray School of Medicine, North Carolina Baptist Hospital, and Wake Forest University Physicians.

===Bowman Gray Technical Center===
In 2003, the Bowman Gray Technical Center (BGTC), a third, smaller, campus, opened near the main campus. This campus is the administrative base for the Wake Forest University Center for Structural Biology, and the physical location for seven of the 16 faculty members comprising the Center.

===Charlotte campus===
Wake Forest's Babcock Graduate School of Management operates a satellite campus in the Morrocroft office complex in the [[SouthPark (Charlotte neighborhood)|SouthPark]] neighborhood of Charlotte, North Carolina. The Charlotte campus opened in 1995. Since the campus' opening, the program has expanded to offering two [[MBA]] programs with over 170 students enrolled in the programs.

The campus was originally scheduled to relocate to the [[Duke Energy Center]] in Uptown Charlotte, but Wake Forest changed its plans about the relocation. Wake Forest is currently exploring options for relocation to another facility in Charlotte's core business district.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://charlotte.bizjournals.com/charlotte/stories/2009/05/25/daily5.html |title=Wake Forest nixes plans for uptown tower|publisher=Charlotte Business Journal |date=2009-05-22 |accessdate=2009-005-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mba.wfu.edu/newsDetail.aspx?id=336 |title=Wake Forest University plans for growth and increases commitment in Charlotte|publisher=Wake Forest University |date=2009-05-22 |accessdate=2009-005-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Overseas===
The University owns a number of properties in Europe where each fall and spring semester, a group of Wake Forest students and a resident professor live and study together&lt;ref&gt;[http://provost.wfu.edu/43.72.1/WFU_Abroad_Programs WFU Abroad Programs] Website of the Office of the Provost, Wake Forest University&lt;/ref&gt; 

====Casa Artom in Venice====
In 1974, the building that formerly housed the American Consulate in [[Venice]] was purchased by Wake Forest and named Casa Artom in honor of Dr. Camillo Artom, a professor at the Baptist Medical Center until 1969. 

====Flow House in Vienna====
In 1998, Wake Forest purchased a three-story villa in [[Vienna]]. The acquisition was made possible through the donation of Vic and Roddy Flow of Winston-Salem, and the house was named in their honor. Built in 1898, the house was formerly the office of the U.S. Consulate.

====Worrell House in London====
In 1977, Wake Forest acquired a large, brick home in [[Hampstead]] for its London program. The house, a gift from Eugene and Ann Worrell, was named in their honor. Formerly known as Morven House, the building served as the home and studio of landscape painter Charles Edward Johnson.

==Movies or documentaries filmed at the University==
*''[[A Union In Wait]]''
*''[[Junebug (film)|Junebug]]''
*''[[The 5th Quarter]]'' — based on the story of the 2006 Wake Forest football team and star linebacker [[Jon Abbate]]
*''[[Hellraiser III]]''

==See also==
* [[List of Wake Forest University people]]
* [[Reynolda Gardens]]
* [[Reynolda Village]]
* [[Reynolda House Museum of American Art]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commons}}
* [http://www.wfu.edu/ Official school website]

{{Wake Forest University}}
{{Atlantic Coast Conference}}
{{Private colleges and universities in North Carolina}}

{{coord|36.135|-80.277|display=title}}

[[Category:Wake Forest University| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1834]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in North Carolina]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Winston-Salem, North Carolina]]

[[de:Wake Forest University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ویک فارست]]
[[fr:Université de Wake Forest]]
[[it:Wake Forest University]]
[[ja:ウェイクフォレスト大学]]
[[no:Wake Forest University]]
[[simple:Wake Forest University]]
[[sv:Wake Forest University]]
[[ta:வேக் ஃபாரச்ட் பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[zh:维克弗斯特大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
