<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23932028" ns="0" title="Ohio State–Penn State football rivalry"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|Events|date=October 2010}}
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: right; clear: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; width: 26em;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; background-color: #B0C4DE;&quot;  | Ohio State Buckeyes–Penn State Nittany Lions
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot; |
|-
| '''First meeting''' || Penn State, 37–0 (1912)
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Last meeting''' || Penn State, 20-14 (2011)
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Next meeting''' || October 27, 2012
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Number of meetings''' || 27
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''All-time series''' || Series Tied, 13-13* {{nowrap|&lt;small&gt;*2010 vacated win not included&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Largest victory''' || Penn State, 63–14 (1994)
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Current streak''' || Penn State, 1 
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Longest PSU win streak''' || 4 (1912, 1956, 1963–1964)
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Longest OSU win streak''' || 3 (2002–2004)
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''At Ohio State''' || Ohio State leads, 8*–7 {{nowrap|&lt;small&gt;*2010 vacated win not included&lt;/small&gt;}}
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''At Penn State''' || Series tied, 5–5
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Bowl games''' || Penn State leads, 1–0
|}

The '''Ohio State&amp;ndash;Penn State football rivalry''' is an American [[college football]] [[college rivalry|rivalry]] game played annually by the [[Ohio State Buckeyes football|Buckeyes]] of [[The Ohio State University]] and the [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Nittany Lions]] of [[The Pennsylvania State University]].  Before Penn State joined the [[Big Ten Conference]] in 1990, Ohio State and Penn State only played eight times, the last of which was in the [[Fiesta Bowl|1980 Fiesta Bowl]].  After Penn State joined the Big Ten, the rivalry continued as an annual conference game.

==Series history==
===1912–1980: Pre-Big Ten era===
Penn State won the first four meetings in the series, however these meetings spread across 53 seasons, between 1912 and 1964.  The first ever match-up was held in [[Columbus, Ohio]] in November 1912.  Penn State had just come off a 8–0–1 season in 1911.  All of the experts had picked Ohio State to win this game in a blowout.{{fact|date=October 2011}}  However, it was the Nittany Lions shutting the Buckeyes out, 37–0.

It would not be until 1956 when Penn State made a return trip to Columbus, however when they did they won the second meeting between the schools, 7–6.  Penn State would win two more games at [[Ohio Stadium]] before Ohio State won a game in 1975.  The first ever match-up of the two held in [[State College, Pennsylvania]] was in 1976 where Ohio State beat Penn State 12–7.  Penn State won in 1978 back in Columbus.

In 1980, the two schools played in their first and only postseason bowl, the [[Fiesta Bowl|1980 Fiesta Bowl]].  The Ohio State Buckeyes were 9–3, while the Penn State Nittany Lions were 10–2.  The Penn State Nittany Lions won at [[Sun Devil Stadium]] in [[Tempe, Arizona]] 31–19.  As Ohio State and Penn State now play in the same conference, it is unlikely for the two schools to face off in another bowl game.{{fact|date=October 2011}}

===1993–2000: Penn State enters the Big Ten===
Following the 1980 Fiesta Bowl, Penn State and Ohio State did not meet again until Penn State joined the Big Ten in 1993.  This officially started the rivalry between these two teams.{{fact|date=October 2011}}  From 1993 to the present, the Buckeyes and Nittany Lions have played annually.  Ohio State won the first conference meeting, 24–6 after a close 7–6 first quarter.  Ohio State has won 11 of the matchups, while Penn State has won six.  The largest margin of victory for ether teams came in 1994 when Penn State beat Ohio State 63–14.  Interestingly following this defeat, an Ohio State sportswriter dropped Penn State from #1 to #2 in the AP Poll.  In 1995, the Nittany Lions were the losing team, losing 28–25 to Ohio State.  In 1996, the Buckeyes beat the Nittany Lions 38–7 in a game that some picked Penn State to win.{{fact|date=October 2011}} The Nittany Lions got revenge next year as Penn State, ranked No. 1 at the time and into November before losing to Michigan, came back from 27–17 to win 31–27. The two teams split the next two, and Ohio State won in 2000 45–6. That was the most lopsided Ohio State win over Penn State and the second biggest margin of victory for either team.

===2001–2010: Paterno vs. Tressel===
The decade of the 2000s saw several close games between the Buckeyes and the Nittany Lions, as they put long time Penn State head coach [[Joe Paterno]], against Ohio State head coach [[Jim Tressel]].  Ohio State went 6–3&lt;ref name=&quot;Vacation&quot;&gt; This does not include the 2010 season, in which all wins were vacated by Ohio State in July 2011&lt;/ref&gt; during this period.  What would have been the Buckeyes' seventh win in 2010, along with that entire season, was vacated as a result of players receiving improper benefits.  The two teams were perennially near the top of the Big Ten standings.{{fact|date=October 2011}}  Ohio State won six&lt;ref name=&quot;Vacation&quot;/&gt; Big Ten titles (2002, 2005–2009), while Penn State won two titles (2005 and 2008, both shared with Ohio State).

The 2001 game was significant because it gave Paterno his 324th career win. Penn State was suffering through a dismal season with a 1–4 start with Matt Senaca leading the way. Senaca was soon benched in this game where Ohio State climbed to a 27–9 lead and promising freshman{{fact|date=October 2011}} Zack Mills helped Penn State come back and nearly saved their season (Penn State finished 5–6). The following year, Penn State would very nearly beat Ohio State in the Horseshoe, only losing 13–7 to the eventual national champions. In 2003, Penn State had a dismal season but actually looked like the better team against the Buckeyes as they took a 17–7 lead at one point. Ohio State came back to win 21–20 with a last second field goal falling just short. Ohio State won the next game 21–10 despite being outscored 10–7 offensively. That game was only one of two times that the Nittany Lions scored double digits at Ohio Stadium since joining the Big Ten in 1993.

In 2005, Penn State was an underdog{{fact|date=October 2011}} despite trouncing then-No. 18 Minnesota 44–14 the week before and being undefeated. However, Penn State played defense and shut down the Buckeye ground game.{{fact|date=October 2011}}  The 2005 teams met for what became the deciding game for the Big Ten championship, Penn State upset the then-favored Buckeyes 17–10 in State College, with Penn State finishing No. 3 in both polls and Ohio State finishing No. 4 themselves. Penn State went on to lose to Michigan next week in a controversial{{fact|date=October 2011}} 27–25 game but went on to win out the rest of the way as Ohio State won out the remainder of the way, including a come-from-behind win over Michigan 25–21.  This resulted in the two teams sharing the Big Ten title. Penn State defeated ACC champion Florida State 26–23 in the Orange Bowl as Ohio State defeated Notre Dame 34–20 in the Fiesta Bowl.

The 2006 game has a deceptive final score, Penn State led 3–0 and was a fullback fumble away from leading 10–0, but missed a field goal early in the third that would have made it 6–0, Ohio State struck back and went up 7–3, early in the fourth quarter, Ohio State's Troy Smith avoided a sack and threw the ball downfield, it was nearly intercepted but Brian Robiskie caught it for a touchdown. Penn State drove down to the one yard line, but a false start penalty pushed them back, forcing them to kick a field goal. Still, with the score 14–6, the Nittany Lions drove down the field and nearly scored the game tying touchdown, but with two minutes left, Malcolm Jenkins intercepted an Anthony Morelli pass and ran it back for a touchdown to make it 21–6.  Penn State made the same mistake again with one minute left, making it 28–6.  In the 2007 game, Ohio State came back from an early 7–3 deficit to take a 17–7 halftime lead and eventually winning 37–17.

The 2008 meeting between the two teams saw the third ranked Nittany Lions won 13–6 against the 10th ranked Buckeyes at Ohio Stadium.  This game turned out to be the deciding factor in giving Penn State a berth in the [[Rose Bowl (game)|Rose Bowl]]; the teams shared the Big Ten title, but the Lions were chosen ahead of Ohio State due to their head-to-head win.  Before that victory, Penn State had a seven game road losing streak to the Buckeyes, and interestingly enough, Penn State has yet to score 14 or more points in Columbus since joining the Big Ten. Regardless, the Lions did not turn the ball over, while Ohio State did twice. The 2009 meeting also played a role in the Big Ten championship, with both teams tied for first in conference at the time since previously unbeaten Iowa lost to Northwestern. With the roles reversed, the visitors, Ohio State, won a stubborn defensive struggle over the home team 24–7,  In what Kirk Herbstriet called &quot;rope-a-dope&quot; offensive strategy for both teams.{{fact|date=October 2011}} This time, Penn State turned the ball over twice and Ohio State did not turn it over once.

In 2010, the Buckeyes were listed as huge favorites against a 6–3 Penn State team. Penn State had other ideas, however, rolling to a 14–3 lead at halftime, with Penn State QB Matt McGloin throwing the first touchdown passes against Ohio State since Joe Pateno became head coach. Ohio State rallied to retake the lead and win, with the aid of two Matt McGloin interceptions, won 38–14.

After the 2010 season, it was revealed that several Ohio State players, most notably QB [[Terrelle Pryor]] received improper benefits.  An investigation into the determined that Tressel had knowledge of the situation but failed to notify the University or the NCAA.  This resulted in Tressel resigning from the program.  As part of a self-imposed sanction, Ohio State vacated all of its wins from the season, including its win over Penn State, its Big Ten Title, and [[2011 Sugar Bowl|Sugar Bowl]] appearance.

===2011–present===
2011 begins a new era in the rivalry.  With the addition of [[Nebraska Cornhuskers football|Nebraska]] into the Big Ten, the conference split into two six-team divisions.  Both Ohio State and Penn State were placed in the &quot;Leaders&quot; Division and will continue to play each other annually.  The 2011 season also marks a new era for the Buckeyes and Nittany Lions, as [[Luke Fickell]] was named the interim head coach for the season after Tressel's resignation and [[Tom Bradley]] after longtime Penn State head coach [[Joe Paterno]] was fired 9 games into the season following the uncovering of the [[Penn State sex abuse scandal]]. 

Both schools will have new head coaches for the 2012 season.  On November 28, 2011, Ohio State hired former [[Utah Utes football|Utah]] and [[Florida Gators football|Florida]] head coach [[Urban Meyer]] as head coach, beginning a new era in the rivalry. Meyer had been considered by many{{who|date=November 2011}} as a possible replacement for Paterno at Penn State

==Game results==

''Ohio State victories are colored &lt;font color=&quot;990000&quot;&gt;█&lt;/font&gt; scarlet.  Penn State victories are colored &lt;font color=&quot;#1C3C6B&quot;&gt;█&lt;/font&gt; blue.  Vacated victories are shaded in &lt;font color=&quot;lightgray&quot;&gt;█&lt;/font&gt; gray''

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Date
! Site
! colspan=2 | Winning team
! colspan=2|Losing team
! Series
! Attendance
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|November 17, 1898||Columbus
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''37'''||align=left|Ohio State||0
|PSU 1–0
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 20, 1956||Columbus
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''7'''||align=left|Ohio State||6
|PSU 2–0
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|November 9, 1963||Columbus
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''10'''||align=left|Ohio State||7
|PSU 3–0
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|November 7, 1964||Columbus
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''27'''||align=left|Ohio State||0
|PSU 4–0
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|September 20, 1975||Columbus
|align=left|'''Ohio State'''||'''17'''||align=left|Penn State||9
|PSU 4–1
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|September 18, 1976||State College
|align=left|'''Ohio State'''||'''12'''||align=left|Penn State||7
|PSU 4–2
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|September 16, 1978||Columbus
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''19'''||align=left|Ohio State||0
|PSU 5–2
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|December 26, 1980||Tempe, AZ&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;sup&gt;
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''31'''||align=left|Ohio State||19
|PSU 6–2
|
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 30, 1993||Columbus
|align=left|'''Ohio State'''||'''24'''||align=left|Penn State||6
|PSU 6–3
|95,060
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 29, 1994||State College
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''63'''||align=left|Ohio State||14
|PSU 7–3
|97,079
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 7, 1995||State College
|align=left|'''Ohio State'''||'''28'''||align=left|Penn State||25
|PSU 7–4
|96,655
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 5, 1996||Columbus
|align=left|'''#3 Ohio State'''||'''38'''||align=left|#4 Penn State||7
|PSU 7–5
|94,241
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 11, 1997||State College
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''31'''||align=left|Ohio State||27
|PSU 8–5
|97,282
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 3, 1998||Columbus
|align=left|'''#1 Ohio State'''||'''28'''||align=left|#7 Penn State||9
|PSU 8–6
|93,479
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 16, 1999||State College
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''23'''||align=left|#17 Ohio State||10
|PSU 9–6
|97,007
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|September 23, 2000||Columbus
|align=left|'''#14 Ohio State'''||'''45'''||align=left|Penn State||6
|PSU 9–7
|98,144
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 27, 2001||State College
|align=left|'''Penn State'''||'''29'''||align=left|Ohio State||27
|PSU 10–7
|108,327
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 26, 2002||Columbus
|align=left|'''#4 Ohio State'''||'''13'''||align=left|#17 Penn State||7
|PSU 10–8
|105,103
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|November 1, 2003||State College
|align=left|'''#8 Ohio State'''||'''21'''||align=left|Penn State||20
|PSU 10–9
|108,276
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 30, 2004||Columbus
|align=left|'''Ohio State'''||'''21'''||align=left|Penn State||10
|Tie 10–10
|104,947
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 8, 2005||State College
|align=left|'''#18 Penn State'''||'''17'''||align=left|#6 Ohio State||10
|PSU 11–10
|109,839
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|September 23, 2006||Columbus
|align=left|'''#1 Ohio State'''||'''28'''||align=left|Penn State||6
|Tie 11–11
|105,266
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|October 27, 2007||State College
|align=left|'''#1 Ohio State'''||'''37'''||align=left|#25 Penn State||17
|OSU 12–11
|110,134
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|October 25, 2008||Columbus
|align=left|'''#3 Penn State'''||'''13'''||align=left|#10 Ohio State||6
|Tie 12–12
|105,711
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #990000;color:lightgray;&quot;
|November 7, 2009||State College
|align=left|'''#15 Ohio State'''||'''24'''||align=left|#11 Penn State||7
|OSU 13–12
|110,033
|-align=center style=&quot;background: lightgray;color:black;&quot;
|November 13, 2010&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;sup&gt;||Columbus
|align=left| #8 Ohio State || 38 ||align=left|#11 Penn State||14
|OSU 13–12
|105,466
|-align=center style=&quot;background: #1C3C6B;color:white;&quot;
|November 19, 2011||Columbus
|align=left|'''#21 Penn State'''||'''20'''||align=left|Ohio State||14
|Tie 13-13
|105,493
|}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; 1980 Fiesta Bowl&lt;br&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; Win vacated by Ohio State

===References===
{{Reflist}}

{{Ohio State Buckeyes football navbox}}
{{Penn State Nittany Lions football navbox}}
{{Big Ten Conference football rivalry navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ohio State–Penn State Rivalry}}
[[Category:College football rivalries in the United States]]
[[Category:Ohio State Buckeyes football]]
[[Category:Penn State Nittany Lions football]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
