<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23962352" ns="0" title="Missouri University of Science and Technology"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=January 2009}}
{{Infobox university
|name=  Missouri University of Science and Technology
|image=  [[Image:University of Missouri seal bw.svg|140px|University of Missouri seal]]
|tagline= Missouri's premier technological research university
|motto=''Salus Populi''&lt;br&gt;([[Latin]], The Welfare of the People)
|established=  1870
|type=  [[Public university|Public]]&lt;br&gt;[[space grant colleges|Space grant]]
|endowment= [[US$]] 101.2 million&lt;ref name = &quot;Endowment 2010&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf |format=PDF |title= 2010 NCSE Public Tables Endowment Market Values Final |publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers and Commonfund Institute |page=3 (#65) |date=August 31, 2010 |accessdate=February 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;2010 facts&quot; /&gt;
|chancellor=  Dr. John F. Carney III
|provost= Dr. Warren Kent Wray
|faculty=  497 (398 full-time, 99 part-time) (Fall 2010) &lt;ref name=&quot;2010 facts&quot;&gt;[http://www.umsystem.edu/ums/about/facts/#rolla &quot;Facts and Figures - Missouri University of Science and Technology&quot;] (Fall 2010)&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff=  851 (740 full-time, 111 part-time) (Fall 2010) &lt;ref name =&quot;2010 facts&quot; /&gt;
|students=  7,206&lt;ref name=&quot;news.mst.edu&quot;&gt;http://news.mst.edu/2010/09/record_number_of_female_and_in.html&lt;/ref&gt; (78% male, 22% female) &lt;ref name = &quot;Best College 2010-11&quot; /&gt;
|undergrad=  5,504 (Fall 2010)
|postgrad=  1,702 (Fall 2010)
|city=  [[Rolla, Missouri|Rolla]]
|state=  [[Missouri]]
|country=  [[USA]]
|address=  106 Parker Hall, 300 W. 13th St.&lt;br&gt;Rolla, Missouri 65409
|telephone=  (800) 522-0938
|campus=  [[Rural area|Rural]], {{convert|284|acre|ha|1}} &lt;ref name=&quot;Best College 2010-11&quot;&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/missouri-university-of-science-%26-technology-2517 Missouri University of Science &amp; Technology], ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 
|colors=  Dark Green, Gold, and Silver {{color box|#085706}} {{color box|#DFC463}} {{color box|#C0C0C0}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Careaga |first=Andrew |title=Some clarifications about the new word mark |url=http://namechange.mst.edu/logo/ |date=September 18, 2007 |work=namechange.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T |accessdate=19 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Standards |url=http://standards.mst.edu/stationery.html |work=standards.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T |accessdate=19 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|nickname=  [[Missouri S&amp;T Miners|Miners]]
|mascot=  [http://standards.mst.edu/images/FullJoe.jpg Joe Miner]
|website=  [http://www.mst.edu/ www.mst.edu]
|logo= [[Image:Missouri S&amp;T logo.svg|130px|Missouri S&amp;T logo]]
}}

'''Missouri University of Science and Technology''' (commonly '''Missouri S&amp;T''' and formerly known as the '''University of Missouri–Rolla''' and originally '''Missouri School of Mines and Metallurgy'''&lt;ref name=namechange&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://news.mst.edu/2007/04/curators_approve_umr_name_chan.html
| title=Curators approve UMR name change
| work=news.mst.edu
| publisher=Missouri S&amp;T Office of Public Relations
| date=2007-04-06
| accessdate=2009-01-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;) is an institution of higher learning located in [[Rolla, Missouri]], [[United States]], and part of the [[University of Missouri System]]. Most of its 7,206 students (Fall 2010 enrollment) study [[engineering]], [[computer|computing]], [[mathematics]] and the sciences. Although known primarily as an engineering school, Missouri S&amp;T has numerous majors in humanities, social sciences, arts, sciences and business.

The school is famous for its repeated success in national engineering design competitions and its century-long tradition of aggrandized celebrations surrounding [[Saint Patrick's Day]].

==History==
[[Image:Norwood Hall at Missouri S&amp;T.jpg|thumb|right|Norwood Hall, from the southwest]]
Missouri S&amp;T was originally a [[University of Missouri]] offspring called the ''Missouri School of Mines and [[Metallurgy]]'' (MSM), founded in 1870 as the first technological learning institution west of the [[Mississippi River]]. Early in its beginnings, the School of Mines was focused primarily on [[mining]] and metallurgy, but by the 1920s, had expanded into [[civil engineering|civil]], [[electrical engineering|electrical]], [[mechanical engineering|mechanical]] and [[chemical engineering]] as well as [[chemistry]], [[physics]], [[mathematics]] and [[geology]]. The school became home to Missouri's first operational [[nuclear reactor]] in 1961. 

In 1964, the School of Mines, although always a part of the University of Missouri system, changed its name to ''University of Missouri at Rolla''. The curriculum was expanded to include most of the science and engineering disciplines, as well as social sciences and [[liberal arts]] such as psychology and history. In 1968, the campus name was slightly altered to the ''University of Missouri–Rolla'', thus conforming to the naming scheme of the other three campuses.  Business and management programs were gradually added in the following years.  On January 1, 2008 UMR became known as ''Missouri University of Science and Technology'' or ''Missouri S&amp;T'' for short.&lt;ref name=namechange /&gt;

==Campus==
===Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge===
[[Image:umr stonehenge.jpg|right|frame|Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge, next to U.S. Highway 63.]]

[[Stonehenge replicas and derivatives|Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge is a partial reconstruction]] of the original [[Stonehenge]] monument located on [[Salisbury Plain]], west of [[London]]. Missouri S&amp;T's version of the ancient structure is located on the [[Ordinal directions|northwest]] corner of campus, and was dedicated on June 20, 1984 during the summer [[solstice]]. It features a 50 foot (15 m) diameter ring of 30 stones around a horseshoe of five [[trilithon]]s through which various sightings of [[sunrise]] and [[sunset]] can be made. About 160 tons of [[granite]] were used to construct the monument. The rock was cut by Missouri S&amp;T's [[water jet cutter]] equipment, which used two waterjets cutting at a pressure of 15,000 pounds of force per square inch (103 MPa), slicing across the surface just like a conventional saw. The cutter moved at a speed of about 10 feet per minute (50&amp;nbsp;mm/s) and cut between one-quarter and one-half inch (6 and 13&amp;nbsp;mm) on each pass.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rockmech.mst.edu/stonehenge/ Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge Website]&lt;/ref&gt;

After completion, Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge received an award from the National Society of Professional Engineers for being one of 1985's Ten Outstanding Engineering Achievements.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rockmech.mst.edu/stonehenge/answerspage4.html Missouri S&amp;T Stonehenge FAQ page]&lt;/ref&gt;

A few years after its construction, a new health center building was erected that blocked the sightings of the sun throughout much of the year.

===Millennium Arch===
[[Image:UMR Stonehenge night.jpg|right|thumb|200px|The Millennium Arch, in front of Castleman Hall.]]

The university worked with artist [[Edwina Sandys]] to develop a new way to make deep cuts in granite and used the method to create the Millennium Arch sculpture, across the campus from Stonehenge. The Arch is a single [[trilithon]] with a vague silhouette of a man and a woman on each of its supporting megaliths several meters from the arch (and can be seen in the distance between the two silhouettes in the image to the left). The monument is located on 10th Street, facing Castleman Hall, in Rolla. The project was developed in the High Pressure Waterjet Laboratory of the Rock Mechanics &amp; Explosive Research Center at Missouri S&amp;T.

There are two similar but smaller megaliths showing the same silhouette on each side of the sidewalk entrance to the Rock Mechanics &amp; Explosive Research Center.

===Curtis Laws Wilson Library===
The Curtis Laws Wilson Library is the main academic library on the campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.mst.edu Curtis Laws Wilson Library]. Missouri S&amp;T. ''URL retrieved April 4, 2007''.&lt;/ref&gt; The library is open from 8:00 A.M. to midnight each day.  The third floor of the library is strictly a quiet study area with multiple rooms circling around the main area. The IT Helpdesk Walk-In Center for campus is located in the library on the first floor. A snack bar is also located in the back left corner of the first floor and recently celebrated its two year anniversary.

==Academics==
Missouri S&amp;T was ranked 45th overall, and 12th among public universities, by U.S. high school counselors in 2008&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.mst.edu/about/
| title=About Missouri S&amp;T
| work=mst.edu
| publisher=Missouri S&amp;T
| accessdate=2010-05-24
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, [[Forbes]] ranked S&amp;T as number 1 in the Midwest and 12th among U.S. public universities for &quot;getting rich&quot;, having named it a top 25 &quot;most connected&quot; campus in 2006, and a top 25 entrepreneurial campus in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url=http://www.mst.edu/about/
| title=About Missouri S&amp;T
| work=mst.edu
| publisher=Missouri S&amp;T
| accessdate=2009-01-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2010, Missouri S&amp;T's Experimental Mine was named the United States' No. 1 &quot;awesome lab&quot; by ''[[Popular Science]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.mst.edu/2010/08/experimental_mine_tops_popular.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.popsci.com/science/gallery/2010-08/gallery-30-awesome-college-labs&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the average ACT score for entering freshmen was 27.7 (90th percentile), considerably&lt;ref name=&quot;news.mst.edu&quot;/&gt; higher than both the state (21.5) and national (20.9) averages.&lt;ref name=&quot;EnrollmentPressRelease&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = UMR enrollment surpasses 6,000 goal
  | work = news.mst.edu
  | publisher = Missouri S&amp;T Office of Public Relations
  | date = 2007-09-26
  | url = http://news.mst.edu/2007/09/umr_enrollment_surpasses_6000.html
  | accessdate = 2009-01-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Missouri S&amp;T's residence hall system is widely recognized; the university was voted &quot;School of the Year 2005&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://news.mst.edu/2005/11/umr_picked_as_school_of_the_ye_1.html&lt;/ref&gt; by the Midwest Affiliate of College and University Residence Halls, or MACURH (a regional subdivision of [[NACURH]]) and its honor organization, National Residence Hall Honorary (NRHH), was chosen as the 2008 National Chapter of the Year.

The school operates the 200&amp;nbsp;kW [[Missouri University of Science and Technology Nuclear Reactor|Missouri S&amp;T reactor]] on-campus for educational, training and research purposes.  The Missouri S&amp;T reactor is the first [[nuclear reactor]] to become operational in Missouri, and first achieved criticality in 1961.

=== Student Engineering Projects ===
The Student Design &amp; Experiential Learning Center (SDELC)&lt;ref name=SDELC&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://design.mst.edu/index.html |title=Student Design &amp; Experiential Learning Center |work=design.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri University of Science and Technology |accessdate=July 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; was established in 2000 to better support the various multi-disciplinary student design teams. In 2004, the Center's mission expanded to provide experiential learning in academic courses, identify and support student service learning projects within the curriculum, and support ad-hoc student teams in specialty academic events involving multi-disciplinary student research.

By 2006 the SDELC had expanded to ten student design teams. The center's expanded mission involved better funding and offering support and resources to multi-disciplinary project teams that had a research base to their activities. The SDELC provided academic credit opportunities in the form of three, one-hour classes on design, leadership and communication. The center also offers a half-credit course on experiential design through the Residential College (RC) program which has a per-semester enrollment of over 100 students engaged in hands-on learning projects. The SDELC's student design teams, research teams and projects, and academic courses are the foundation of experiential learning at Missouri S&amp;T.&lt;ref name=SDELC/&gt;

The [http://solarhouse.mst.edu/ Missouri S&amp;T Solar House Team], designs and builds a house that is completely sustained by energy collected directly from the sun. After the house is built on campus, it is disassembled and transported to [[Washington, D.C.]] for the [[Solar Decathlon]], a month long competition. The Solar House Team placed 11th overall in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=UMR's solar house is heading home |url=http://news.mst.edu/2007/10/umrs_solar_house_is_heading_ho.html |work=news.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T Office of Public Relations |date=2007-10-23 |accessdate=2009-01-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The team took first place in the Energy Balance category at the 2005 competition. At the 2002 competition the team took first place in Refrigeration, second place in Energy Balance and third in Hot Water. In 2002 and 2005, the Missouri S&amp;T team took 9th place and 7th overall place respectively.

This chapter of [http://ewb-mst.org/ Engineers Without Borders] currently has four ongoing international projects in Guatemala, Honduras, and Bolivia. Over one hundred students are part of the team that work to develop sustainable solutions to engineering problems, such as lack of access to drinking water, in developing countries.

The [http://aavg.mst.edu/ Advanced Aero-Vehicle Group] constructs a [[remote control]]led airplane for the annual Society of Automotive Engineers' Aero Design competition. This year's plane, which had an 8-foot [[wingspan]] and weighed only 9.4 pounds, competed in the Aero Design's open class designation at the east competition. The project is of interest mainly to aerospace engineering students, but students from other disciplines are also on the team. In 2005, the group placed third at the east competition and fifth at the west competition. The Advanced Aero Vehicle Group also constructs a rocket every year.  The rocket competes in the USLI competition hosted by NASA, in which the rocket must carry a payload one mile into the atmosphere. The AAVG group is also working on a research and development subgroup to compliment the existing plane and rocket groups.

The [http://humanpowered.mst.edu/ Missouri S&amp;T Human Powered Vehicle Team] demonstrates the engineering excellence of its members via a human-powered vehicle. The team promotes alternative energy technology while providing tomorrow’s engineers with hands-on experience in applying classroom knowledge. Through the spirit of intercollegiate competition, this project hopes to foster leadership, teamwork and the continuous advancement of technologies for the betterment of humanity. The Missouri S&amp;T Human Powered Vehicle Team competes annually at the American Society of Mechanical Engineers Human Powered Vehicle Challenge in both West and East Coast Competitions. The team has placed among the top two overall in 14 of 16 competitions, and holds the female sprint record of 41.8&amp;nbsp;mph and male sprint record of 48.6&amp;nbsp;mph.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asme.org/Events/Contests/HPV/HPV_Results_2.cfm/ |title=HPVC Results |work=asme.org |publisher=ASME |accessdate=February 5, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the team swept both the East and West Coast competitions and placed 1st in every event: Design, Male Drag Race, Female Drag Race and the Endurance Race, giving the team 1st Place Overall and National Speed Class Champions.

The [http://fsae.mst.edu/ Missouri S&amp;T Formula SAE] team constructs a small [[Formula One cars|formula-style]] race car every year, suitable for [[mass production]] and sale to weekend [[autocross]]ers. The team competes in [[Brooklyn, Michigan]] against more than 100 other teams from universities around the world. The vehicle's cost, sales presentation, engineering design, acceleration, braking and racing performance all factor in to its final score. The team has placed in the top ten in eight of the past twelve competitions, including first-, second- and fourth-place finishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=SAE Collegiate Design Series |url=http://students.sae.org/competitions/formulaseries/results/ |work=students.sae.org |publisher=SAE International |accessdate=October 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [http://design.mst.edu/concretecanoe/ Missouri S&amp;T Concrete Canoe Team] designs and constructs a [[concrete canoe]] and races it on a lake in regional and national competitions. The team has participated in concrete canoe competitions since the 1970s. The entire project, including fundraising and construction, is completed by the students. The team took third place in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://experiencethis.mst.edu/concrete_canoe/ |title=Concrete Canoe Archives |accessdate=2008-07-09 |work=Experience This |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T |date=2008-04-18 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Missouri S&amp;T's [[Solar car racing|solar car]] team has met with much success. Every two years, the team constructs a single-passenger car, its top covered with gallium arsenide [[solar cells]], that runs exclusively on solar power. The car's [[41xx steel|chromoly steel]] frame houses [[lithium ion battery|lithium ion batteries]], which are much lighter than conventional [[lead-acid batteries]]. Every time the car is rebuilt, changes make it lighter and more efficient. The team regularly enters [[Solar car racing|solar car races]] in the United States and occasionally enters international races. The car claimed first place in Sunrayce '99, first place in the 2000 Formula Sun Grand Prix, fourth place in the Australian World Solar Challenge in 2001, second place in the 2001 [[North American Solar Challenge|American Solar Challenge]], and first place in the 2003 American Solar Challenge.  The next car will be Solar Miner VII for the 2010 North American Solar Challenge.

The Missouri S&amp;T Satellite Project team started as an Aerospace enigineering course (AE301 Spacecraft Design) when NASA put out a contest for a 2 year development and build project (Nanosat Program), that must accomplish its goals in the harsh environment of space. After taking third place in Nanosat4, the Team is still perfecting this project and fixing minor errors in the first model. The team is still working hard to perfect their twin satellites for their flight in space and preparing for entry into the Nanosat 6 competition.

The [http://robot.mst.edu/ S&amp;T Robotics Team] participates annually in the Intelligent Ground Vehicle Competition ([http://www.igvc.org/ IGVC]). The team builds autonomous vehicles that traverse [[obstacle course]]s consisting of lane markers and obstacles. The current vehicles are designed to be omnidirectional so that they can easily drive around obstacles. Typically there are 30-50 students on the team and two faculty advisors. The students handle all design and management aspects of the team but occasionally receive help from technicians to fabricate parts.

Missouri S&amp;T is home to the only Mine Rescue Team made up entirely of college students. The team competes regularly against professionals in simulated [[mining accident|mine disasters]].  The team placed 12th and 14th in the competition among industry teams at the South Regional Mine Rescue Competition, sponsored by the U.S. Mine Safety and Health Administration. The Missouri S&amp;T team also had the highest scores on two written exams that were part of the competition.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

== Athletics ==
{{Main|Missouri S&amp;T Miners}}
Missouri S&amp;T athletic teams are known as the Miners; and the women's teams are referred to as the Lady Miners. The name comes from the university's history as a mining school. Missouri S&amp;T competes at the [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] level in thirteen sports and is a member of the [[Great Lakes Valley Conference]] (GLVC) for most sports, the [[Great Lakes Football Conference]] (GLFC) for football,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=[[NCAA]]|url=http://www.ncaa.org/wps/portal/ncaahome?WCM_GLOBAL_CONTEXT=/ncaa/NCAA/NCAA+News/NCAA+News+Online/2010/Division+II/GLVC+targets+2012+as+inaugural+football+season_01_21_10_NCAA_News|title=GLVC targets 2012 as inaugural football season 
|date=January 21, 2010|accessdate=April 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[New South Intercollegiate Swimming Conference]] (NSISC) for men's swimming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|work=Collegeswimming.com|url=http://www.collegeswimming.com/news/2011/feb/10/missouri-st-truman-state-lead-nsisc-championships/|title=Missouri S&amp;T, Truman State Lead NSISC Championships|date=February 10, 2011|accessdate=April 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Club and intramural sports===
Club sports associated with Missouri S&amp;T include [[Ultimate (sport)|Ultimate frisbee]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.minerthreat.com/ |title=Miner Threat Ultimate |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=Miner Threat }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lacrosse]], [[College rugby|Rugby Union]], [[Roller Hockey]], and [[Shooting_sports#Shotgun|Trap and Skeet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web.mst.edu/~trpskt/ |title= Missouri S&amp;T Trap and Skeet |accessdate=2009-09-03 |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T Trap and Skeet}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Intramural sports]] have a very large following at the Missouri S&amp;T.  With over 60 men's teams and over 10 women's teams, sports are arranged into divisions.  Nineteen different sports are contested each year: Golf, Softball, Swimming, [[Ultimate (sport)|Ultimate]], Cross Country, Football, Billiards, Badminton, Volleyball, Darts, Racquetball, Bowling, Basketball, Table Tennis, Tennis, Track, Washers (similar to Horseshoes), Weightlifting and Soccer.

==Student life==
The Missouri S&amp;T event calendar includes current campus events.&lt;ref name=&quot;mstcal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://calendar.mst.edu/|title=Calendar of Events|work=calendar.mst.edu|publisher=Missouri University of Science and Technology|accessdate=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The student government is designed to enhance the collegiate experience of every student at Missouri S&amp;T.

There are over 200 student organizations at Missouri S&amp;T ranging from professional societies to community service organizations and beyond. Missouri S&amp;T has many organizations independent of university funding with which students are very active. Independent houses include: Swimmer House, Green Phish, Rock House, The Annex, The Buffalo Barn, The Swamp, Room 7, Nice House, Mean Phish, Pike Street and Goal Phish.

=== Student media ===
The student-run newspaper at Missouri S&amp;T, ''The Missouri Miner'', is published every Thursday during the school year and can be read online.&lt;ref&gt;http://mominer.mst.edu/&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2007, the paper threatened to sue the school because the university cut funding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Student Newspaper at Missouri-Rolla Threatens to Sue Over Big Budget Cut |url=http://chronicle.com/news/article/1668/student-newspaper-at-missouri-rolla-threatens-to-sue-over-big-budget-cut |publisher=[[The Chronicle of Higher Education]] |date=2007-02-15 |accessdate=2008-01-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After a one school year break because of many reasons including having funding cut, ''The Missouri Miner'' starting republishing in the Fall 2009 semester.

There are two [[FM broadcasting|broadcast]] radio stations associated with Missouri S&amp;T: [[KMNR]], previously known as KMSM, is a student-run, [[Freeform (radio format)|freeform]] radio station whose music playlist varies with the mood and inclination of the [[disc jockey|DJ]], with some playing caller requests. Every year KMNR hosts two concerts&amp;nbsp;– Freakers Ball in the fall and MasqueRave (formerly Glitter Ball) in the spring. [[KMST (FM)|KMST]], previously known as KUMR, is a member-supported [[public radio station]], typically playing [[european classical music|classical]], [[bluegrass music|bluegrass]] and [[jazz]] and [[National Public Radio]] programs. On July 16, 2007, KUMR officially changed its call letters to KMST, in advance of the change of name from &quot;University of Missouri-Rolla&quot; to the &quot;Missouri University of Science and Technology&quot;.

There is also an [[amateur radio]] station, WØEEE, founded in 1931 and run by the Amateur Radio Club,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://w0eee.mst.edu/ |title=W0EEE Web Server |accessdate=2008-05-26 |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T Amateur Radio Club }}&lt;/ref&gt; the first campus club at MSM and one of the oldest student/college amateur stations in the US.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

=== Greek Life ===
Approximately 25% of the undergraduate student body belongs to a social Greek organization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://studentlife.mst.edu/documents/GRDSUMSP07.doc |title=Fraternity &amp; Sorority Life Academic Statistics by Living Group |accessdate=2008-04-19 |format=Microsoft Word |month=June |year=2007 |work=studentlife.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T }}&lt;/ref&gt;  There are five sororities and twenty-two fraternities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Governing Councils and Chapters | url=http://studentlife.mst.edu/greek/governing_chapters.html | accessdate=2007-06-12 |work=studentlife.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The various social, service and honorary Greek chapters perform substantial amounts of community service each year and raise thousands of dollars for local and national charities.  They also promote scholarship and leadership amongst their members.

Fraternities at Missouri S&amp;T include: [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]], [[Alpha Phi Alpha]], [[Beta Sigma Psi]], [[Delta Lambda Phi]], [[Delta Sigma Phi]] ([http://deltasig.mst.edu Delta Epsilon Chapter]), [[Delta Tau Delta]], [[Theta Xi]], [[Kappa Alpha Order]], [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Lambda Chi Alpha]], [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Sigma Nu]], [[Sigma Pi]], [[Sigma Tau Gamma]], [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], [[Sigma Chi]], [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]], [[Phi Kappa Theta]], [[Omega Psi Phi]], and [[Triangle Fraternity|Triangle]]. Sororities on campus include: [[Delta Sigma Theta]], [[Zeta Tau Alpha]], [[Kappa Delta]], [[Phi Sigma Rho]], [[Chi Omega]].

=== Traditions ===

[[St. Patrick's Day]] is the largest annual celebration and predominant cultural event at Missouri S&amp;T, with each year's observance touted as the &quot;Best Ever!&quot;. During St. Pat's, students wear green sweatshirts (which are sold as fund-raisers throughout the season), carry [[shillelagh (weapon)|shillelagh]]s and [[party]] (including drinking green beer). One tradition, observed primarily among fraternities, is the &quot;killing&quot; of rubber snakes in commemoration of [[St. Patrick]]'s mythical banishing of snakes from [[Ireland]]. Along with snake invasion comes the tradition of Follies. Students meet daily at &quot;the Puck&quot; (a short cylindrical stage bearing a large shamrock) to hear jokes and participate in short competitions. On the third day of Follies, students move to the town's band-shell to participate in the ceremonial arrival of St. Pat's Court. The day after Follies, students participate in &quot;Gonzo and Games&quot;. Gonzo and Games are two days of elaborate games in which different organizations compete. Friday of St. Pat's week is concluded with [[Coronation]], a ceremony where the Queen of Love and Beauty is announced. The final event of St. Pat's week is a Saturday morning parade on Pine Street, which is painted green by St. Pat's Board Alumni. This parade is known throughout the United States and boasts well over one hundred floats and participating groups. The rationale for the celebration is the notion that St. Patrick is the [[patron saint]] of engineers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = St. Patrick
  | last = Alfred University
  | date = 2007-04-03
  | url = http://www.herr.alfred.edu/special/archives/traditions/patrick.shtml
  | accessdate = 2007-04-03 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070208113916/http://www.herr.alfred.edu/special/archives/traditions/patrick.shtml &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = St. Patrick Was an Engineer
  | last = University of Missouri Archives
  | date = 2003-01-17
  | url = http://muarchives.missouri.edu/St.Pat'sDay.html
  | accessdate = 2007-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The recognition of St. Patrick as the &quot;Patron Saint of Engineers&quot; began in 1903 when the Engineering students of the University of Missouri in [[Columbia, Missouri|Columbia]] claimed St. Patrick's Day to be a holiday for engineers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://muarchives.missouri.edu/c-rg9-eng.html
|title = A History of the College of Engineering at MU
|accessdate = 2007-08-31
|last = Meade
|first = Mark C
|publisher = University of Missouri Archives
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The tradition has remained to this day and has been adopted by many other schools across the nation.
St. Patrick's Day 2008 marked the one hundredth consecutive year of St. Patrick's Day celebrations at Missouri S&amp;T.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url =  http://web.mst.edu/~stpats/history1.html
|title = History: St. Pat's Celebration Committee
|accessdate = 2007-08-31
|publisher = Missouri S&amp;T
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Religious Organizations ===

Missouri S&amp;T also has several religious organizations for students, including but not limited to the following:
Baptist Student Union (BSU), Campus Crusade for Christ (CRU), Catholic Newman Center, [http://web.mst.edu/~xa/ Chi Alpha], [http://web.mst.edu/~ccf/ccf/Welcome.html Christian Campus Fellowship] (CCF), Fellowship of Christian Athletes (FCA), Muslim Student Association, and Wesley Methodist.

==Notable alumni and former students==
*[[Greg Raymer|Greg &quot;Fossilman&quot; Raymer]], 2004 [[World Series of Poker]] champion, won $5 million.
*[[Bruce L. Edwards]], served as general editor for the recently published four volume reference set, ''C. S. Lewis: Life, Works, and Legacy'' (Praeger Perspectives, 2007).
*[[Glenn J. Lesniak]], [[U.S. Army]] Major General.

===Computer Sciences===
*Steve Sullivan, 2001 and 2006 [[Academy Scientific and Technical Award]] winner for visual effects; a principal engineer with [[George Lucas]]' [[Industrial Light &amp; Magic]] special effects company&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Academy Scientific and Technical Awards
  | url = http://www.ilmfan.com/main/index.php?module=webpage&amp;id=26
  | accessdate = 2009-01-14 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Jack Dorsey]], [[United States|American]] [[software architect]] and [[businessperson]] best known as the creator of [[Twitter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Co-founder of Twitter receives key to St. Louis with 140 character proclamation |url=http://www.ksdk.com/news/local/story.aspx?storyid=185395&amp;catid=3 |date=September 19, 2009 |work=ksdk.com |publisher=[[KSDK]] |accessdate=29 September 2009 |quote=After high school in St. Louis and some time at the University of Missouri-Rolla, Jack headed east to New York University. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Engineering===
*[[Joe N. Ballard]], retired Army General and former commander of the [[United States Army Corps of Engineers]]
*[[George Mueller]], an electrical engineering graduate instrumental in managing [[NASA]]'s fledgling [[Apollo program]] in the 1960s
*[[Joan Woodard|Dr. Joan Woodard]], Executive Vice President and Deputy Laboratories Director for the nuclear weapons program at [[Sandia National Laboratories]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Dr. Joan B. Woodard
  | url = http://www.sandia.gov/about/welcome/woodard-bio08-5260524.pdf
  | format = PDF
  | accessdate = 2009-01-14 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Richard R. Paul]], retired [[United States Air Force|Air Force]] [[General officer|General]] and commander of [[Air Force Research Laboratory]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Biographies : MAJOR GENERAL RICHARD  R. PAUL
  | url = http://www.af.mil/bios/bio.asp?bioID=6705
  | accessdate = 2007-06-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070511070038/http://www.af.mil/bios/bio.asp?bioID=6705 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Braden Lusk]], assistant professor of mining engineering at the [[University of Kentucky]], co-host of the [[Discovery Channel]] series ''The Detonators''; received bachelor's and [[Ph.D.]] in Mining Engineering from Missouri S&amp;T&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Braden Lusk : The Detonators : Discovery Channel
 | url = http://dsc.discovery.com/tv/detonators/bios/lusk.html
 | accessdate = 2009-03-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scientists===
* [[Clyde Cowan]], co-discoverer of the [[neutrino]]
*[[Farouk El-Baz]], Supervisor of Lunar Science Planning in [[NASA]]'s [[Project Apollo|Apollo Program]]

===Mining===
*[[Daniel C. Jackling]], discovered the [[porphyry copper deposit]] that created the [[Bingham Canyon Mine]] and later founded the [[Utah Copper Company]] (later bought by [[Kennecott Copper]]).

===Astronauts===
*[[Thomas Akers]], retired Air Force [[Colonel (United States)|Col.]], a veteran of four space flights, holds bachelor's and master's degrees in mathematics from UMR ('73 and '75), made a guest appearance on the TV show ''[[Home Improvement (TV series)|Home Improvement]]'' on season 3 episode 24 &quot;Reality Bytes&quot;, and is currently a professor at Missouri S&amp;T teaching mathematics.
*[[Janet L. Kavandi|Janet Kavandi]], whose debut space shuttle flight in June 1999 was the final Mir-shuttle docking, holds a master's degree in chemistry from Missouri S&amp;T ('82).
*[[Sandra Magnus]], who became a NASA astronaut in 1996, holds a bachelor's degree in physics ('86) and a master's degree in electrical engineering ('90) from Missouri S&amp;T.

===Business===
*[[Gary D. Forsee]], former [[Chief executive officer|CEO]] of [[Sprint Nextel Corporation|Sprint]]; he became the 22nd president of the University of Missouri System on February 18, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Gary D. Forsee appointed 22nd President of the University of Missouri | url=http://www.umsystem.edu/ums/news/releases/news07122001.shtml | accessdate=2007-12-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Forsee was an undergraduate member of the Beta-Chi Chapter of Kappa Sigma, and recently named Kappa Sigma's Man of the Year 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wilson|first=Mitchell|title=2009 Kappa Sigma Fraternity Man of the Year|url=http://www.kappasigma.org/content/2009-kappa-sigma-fraternity-man-year|accessdate=2011-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Ted Weise]], former president of [[FedEx Express (airline)|FedEx]], one of the first employees of FedEx (formerly Federal Express) when the company started in the early 1970s, and worked his way up to the position of president. He holds a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering from Missouri S&amp;T ('67).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=FedEx CEO Theodore L. Weise to Retire, COO David J. Bronczek to Succeed Weise | url=http://www.fedex.com/us/about/news/pressreleases/archives/pressrelease192842165.html?link=4 | accessdate=2007-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Joseph D. Rupp]], Chairman, President and Chief Executive Officer of [[Olin Corporation]]. He holds a bachelor's degree in [[metallurgical engineering]] from Missouri S&amp;T &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Joseph D. Rupp Profile | url=http://people.forbes.com/profile/joseph-d-rupp/59826 | work=forbes.com | accessdate=2009-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was a member of the Beta-Chi Chapter of Kappa Sigma.
*[[Michael M. Sears]], managed [[Super Hornet]] development at [[McDonnell Douglas]], senior executive at [[Boeing]], convicted in [[United States Air Force tanker contract controversy|Air Force tanker procurement scandal]].  [[Master of Science]] (1976).&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Michael M. Sears&quot; [[Marquis Who's Who]], 2004 [[Gale Cengage|Gale]] Biography in Context. Fee via [[Fairfax County Public Library]], accessed   2010-10-18. Document URL http://ic.galegroup.com/ic/bic1/ReferenceDetailsPage/ReferenceDetailsWindow?displayGroupName=K12-Reference&amp;prodId=BIC2&amp;action=e&amp;windowstate=normal&amp;catId=&amp;documentId=GALE%7CK2015466199&amp;mode=view&amp;userGroupName=fairfax_main&amp;jsid=01d98279cbc4b5f6ce67b3cbb97f9580 Gale Document Number: GALE|K2015466199&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable faculty==
===Mining===
* [[Paul Worsey]]

===Math and statistics===
* [[Thomas Akers]]

===Art===
* [[James Bogan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://news.mst.edu/2009/04/literary_magazine_celebrates_a.html |title=Literary magazine celebrates anniversary with Bogan's work on Brazil |date=April 21, 2009 |work=news.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri University of Science and Technology |accessdate=October 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://news.mst.edu/2005/05/umrs_james_bogan_receives_outs.html |title=UMR's James Bogan receives outstanding teaching honors |date=May 26, 2005 |work=news.mst.edu |publisher=Missouri S&amp;T |accessdate=October 21, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://web.mst.edu/~jbogan/ |title=James Bogan's Website |accessdate=May 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.mst.edu/ Official website]
*[http://sports.mst.edu/ Athletics]

{{Coord|37.955544|-91.773513|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{Colleges and universities in Missouri}}
{{GLVC}}
{{Great_Lakes_Football_Conference}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Missouri University Of Science And Technology}}
[[Category:Missouri University of Science and Technology]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Phelps County, Missouri]]
[[Category:University of Missouri System]]
[[Category:Schools of mines|Missouri-Rolla, University of]]
[[Category:Engineering universities and colleges in Missouri]]
[[Category:Rolla, Missouri|UMR]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Technical universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Glass science institutes]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Former Mid-America Intercollegiate Athletic Association members]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1870]]

[[fa:دانشگاه علم و فناوری میزوری]]
[[ja:ミズーリ工科大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
