<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23969509" ns="0" title="Pilot (The Cleveland Show)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Television episode
| Title        = Pilot
| Series       = The Cleveland Show
| Image        = [[File:Pilot - The Cleveland Show promo.png|220px]]
| Caption      = Cleveland and Cleveland, Jr. leaving Quahog.
| Season       = 1
| Episode      = 1
| Airdate      = September 27, 2009
| Production   = 1APS01
| Writer       = [[Seth MacFarlane]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mike Henry (voice actor)|Mike Henry]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Richard Appel]]
| Director     = Anthony Lioi
| Guests       = *[[Alex Borstein]] as [[Lois Griffin]]
*[[Fergie (singer)|Stacy Ferguson]] as Holt's mother
*[[Seth Green]] as [[Chris Griffin]]
*[[Mila Kunis]] as [[Meg Griffin]]
*[[Jennifer Tilly]] as [[List of characters in Family Guy#Bonnie Swanson|Bonnie Swanson]]
*[[Patrick Warburton]] as [[Joe Swanson]]
| Episode list = [[The Cleveland Show (season 1)|''The Cleveland Show'' (season 1)]]&lt;br/&gt;[[List of The Cleveland Show episodes|List of ''The Cleveland Show'' episodes]]
| Next         = [[Da Doggone Daddy-Daughter Dinner Dance]]
}}
&quot;'''Pilot'''&quot; is the first episode of the [[The Cleveland Show (season 1)|first season]] of the [[animated cartoon|animated]] [[television comedy|comedy series]] ''[[The Cleveland Show]]''. Directed by Anthony Lioi and written by series creators [[Seth MacFarlane]], [[Mike Henry (voice actor)|Mike Henry]] and [[Richard Appel]], the episode originally aired on [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] in the United States on September 27, 2009. The episode follows [[Cleveland Brown]], and his son, [[Cleveland Brown, Jr.|Cleveland, Jr.]], as they begin their journey across the country, with a final destination of California. The two give a final farewell to their friends in [[Family Guy#Setting|Quahog]], [[Rhode Island]], but along the way to their destination, they decide to stop in Cleveland's hometown of Stoolbend, Virginia. While there, Cleveland reconnects with an old crush he had in high school, named [[List of characters in The Cleveland Show|Donna Tubbs]], and immediately finds love, and eventually a new family. Cleveland and Donna ultimately decide to get married, and the two families begin to accept each other into their new lives.

The series is a [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] of the animated comedy series ''[[Family Guy]]'', which was created by executive producer Seth MacFarlane in 1999. Cleveland Brown, voiced by Mike Henry, was a recurring characters on ''Family Guy'', and served as a neighbor to the [[Griffin family]] in Quahog. Prior to the pilot of ''The Cleveland Show'', Cleveland last appeared in the [[Family Guy (season 7)|seventh season]] ''Family Guy'' episode &quot;[[Peter's Progress]]&quot;; he has since made infrequent guest appearances since the inception of his spin-off series.

Critical responses to the episode were mixed; critics praised its storyline and numerous cultural references. According to [[Nielsen ratings]], it was viewed in 9.42 million viewers in its original airing. The episode featured guest performances by [[Alex Borstein]], [[Fergie (singer)|Stacy Ferguson]], [[Seth Green]], [[Mila Kunis]], [[Jennifer Tilly]] and [[Patrick Warburton]], along with several recurring guest voice actors for the series. &quot;Pilot&quot; was released on [[DVD]] along with all twenty other episodes from the first season on September 28, 2010. The Pilot episode was leaked to the Internet the last week of June 2009.

==Plot==
At The Drunken Clam, [[Peter Griffin|Peter]], [[Joe Swanson|Joe]], [[Glen Quagmire|Quagmire]] and Cleveland sit at a table. Cleveland tells the guys that he has lost his house to [[Loretta Brown|Loretta]] due to their [[divorce]] settlement. He also tells the guys that he now has custody of [[Cleveland Brown, Jr.|Cleveland Jr.]] (it revealed that Cleveland Jr. is now 14 years old and has become incredibly overweight). After having his house damaged by Peter once again, Cleveland decides to leave Quahog and head to [[California]] to pursue his dream of being a [[minor league baseball|minor league]] [[Scout (sport)|scout]] for a professional [[baseball]] organization. Before he leaves, Cleveland asks if [[Lois Griffin|Lois]] and [[Bonnie Swanson|Bonnie]] will kiss each other. They do a simple one at first, but then start to [[make out]]. Peter, Joe, Quagmire and [[Brian Griffin|Brian]] all gaze in shock while Cleveland is happy, and he says it is the first time he has ever asked for something he really wanted. Later, after saying goodbye to all his friends, Cleveland and Cleveland, Jr, leave Quahog.

While passing through his old town of Stoolbend, [[Virginia]], he sees his old school and heads inside. There, he bumps into his old flame [[Donna Tubbs]]. She invites him to stay at her house for a couple of days, where Donna relays to Cleveland how she needs a father figure around for her kids after splitting with her husband, Robert. While at Donna's house, he is introduced to [[Rallo Tubbs|Rallo]] and [[Roberta Tubbs|Roberta]], Donna's kids, and the neighbors, including the local [[redneck]] and the family of bears, which include father [[Tim the Bear|Tim]], his wife, and son Raymond.

Donna experiences problems with her two kids, and Cleveland agrees to help; this results in him becoming the very person Donna needs around. The inevitable happens, and Cleveland sticks around – after a complication involving the return of her delinquent of an ex-husband, Robert. After a romantic montage, followed by the dismissal of Robert, Cleveland and Donna get married.

==''The Cleveland Show''/''Family Guy''==
The first act (with the exception of the theme song) is meant to look like the beginning of a ''Family Guy'' episode. This is achieved in two ways:
* The opening credits are designed very similarly to ''Family Guy'''s opening credits
* The interstitial music sounds like ''Family Guy'''s interstitial music
* The cutaways
* The main characters take on the same roles; [[Cleveland Brown]] is the naive, carefree breadwinner of the household ([[Peter Griffin|Peter]]), Cleveland Jr. can be compared to [[Chris Griffin|Chris]], and the same can be said for Donna to an earlier, saner [[Lois Griffin|Lois]]. There is the still the formulaic angry baby/toddler ([[Stewie Griffin|Stewie]]). The only slight difference is Roberta, who, unlike [[Meg Griffin|Meg]], is attractive, popular and not a living doormat.

==Trivia==
* Originally, in the theme song, Cleveland sang &quot;My happy black-guy face&quot;, but it was rewritten as &quot;My happy mustached face&quot; to be more racially sensitive. 

* In a flashback, Cleveland and Donna puke on each other after chugging two beers. This would become the first of many puking gags. 

* This is the first of four episodes during the first season to have a cold open before the theme song. The others being [[A Brown Thanksgiving]], [[Brown History Month]] and [[You're the Best Man, Cleveland Brown]]. 
* It first aired in the US on September 27, 2009, and aired in the UK on February 1, 2010, along with [[Da Doggone Daddy-Daughter Dinner Dance]].

==Pop-culture references==
Within this episode, many references to ''Family Guy'' can be found:

* Oscar® nominated American actress [[Kathleen Turner]] is featured in this episode as starring in the 1992 baseball film ''[[The Babe]]'' instead of [[John Goodman]].

* [[Peter Griffin|Peter]]: &quot;Man he aged faster than Kathleen Turner&quot; (Regarding Cleveland Jr.)

* Peter destroying Cleveland's home and subsequently ruining Cleveland's relaxing bath.

* [[Lois Griffin|Lois]] asking Cleveland jokingly, &quot;Who's gonna run that deli you never go to?,&quot; is a reference to &quot;Cleveland's Deli&quot;, which has not been seen since [[Hell Comes to Quahog]].

* During his explanation of why he is leaving, Cleveland references plots to different ''Family Guy'' episodes, including [[Brian Goes Back to College]] and [[One If By Clam, Two If By Sea]].

* While reminiscing, Cleveland also mentions recreating &quot;all the whole damned ''[[Star Wars]]'' movies&quot;. This is a reference to ''Family Guy'''s ''Star Wars'' parodies.

* [[Stewie Griffin|Stewie's]] line, &quot;What the hell?! ''He's'' getting his own show?!&quot; is a reference to Cleveland being an unlikely ''Family Guy'' character to get a spin-off series.

* Peter: “Light it Brian.” Brian: “Peter, I really don't think we should do this” Peter: “Do it Brian. It's the only way I'm going to catch that bird&quot;. Road Runner:&quot;Meep-Meep!&quot; Peter:&quot; Here he comes. LIGHT IT!” The bird in question is none other than the ''[[Looney Tunes]]'' character “Road Runner” and Peter, with the rocket strapped to his back, is imitating the other famous character “Wile E. Coyote”.

* Peter, Quagmire &amp; Joe are dressed as [[The Beatles]] as they appeared on the cover of their 1967 album “[[Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band]].” Peter is dressed as [[George Harrison]], Quagmire is dressed as [[John Lennon]] &amp; Joe is dressed as [[Paul McCartney]]. They wanted Cleveland to be dressed up like [[Ringo Starr]].

* Holt: “I gotta go get my dinner on. I'll come by later. Bring the new Dave. Live in Austin. Sick.” This more than likely is a reference to “Live from Austin, Texas”, the 2007 release from former “[[Talking Heads]]” front man, [[David Byrne]].

* Roberta's white boyfriend Federline Jones bears a striking resemblance to Kevin Federline, the ex-husband of Pop singer [[Britney Spears]].

* The hand in the box Cleveland calls “Thing” is a reference to [[Thing (The Addams Family)|the character]] from ''[[The Addams Family]]''.

* Holt's line &quot;Yippee ki yay mothe-&quot; before he is knocked off the ladder and cut off is a reference to John McClane's trademark line in the ''[[Die Hard (franchise)|Die Hard]]'' series.

* While Cleveland remembers his past moments with Donna, a cut of the song &quot;[[How Deep is Your Love]]&quot; by [[Bee Gees]] has been played.

==Reception==
Reaction to the pilot was mixed. According to Nielsen, the episode's premiere was watched by 9.42 million viewers and earned a 4.9/12 rating in the 18-49 demographics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvbythenumbers.com/2009/09/28/tv-ratings-nbc-sunday-night-football-wins-cleveland-show-opens-large-desperate-housewives-down/28617 |title=TV Ratings Sunday, September 27, 2009|publisher=TVbytheNumbers.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ahsan Haque from IGN gave the premiere 8.3/10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Haque |first=Ahsan |url=http://tv.ign.com/articles/102/1028583p1.html |title=IGN: Pilot Review |publisher=Tv.ign.com |date= |accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it currently has a rating of 57/100 on [[Metacritic]].&lt;ref name=metacritic&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.metacritic.com/tv/shows/clevelandshow?q=cleveland%20show |title=The Cleveland Show reviews at |publisher=Metacritic.com |date=2009-09-27 |accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[The A.V. Club]]'' graded the episode a C-, stating &quot;There are a lot of elements that make ''The Cleveland Show'' seem like it should work better than it does, but as a whole, it hasn’t quite managed to stand up and differentiate itself enough from its parent show to be taken as its own thing&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Todd|last=VanDerWerff|url=http://www.avclub.com/articles/the-cleveland-show,33383/|title=The Cleveland Show|work=The A.V. Club|date=2009-09-27|accessdate=2011-10-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Parents Television Council]], a frequent [[criticism of Family Guy|critic]] of ''The Cleveland Show'''s parent show, ''[[Family Guy]]'', named the series' premiere episode its &quot;Worst TV Show of the Week&quot; for the week ending October 2, 2009, due to sexually explicit humor. The authors cited a number of scenes, including the send-off scene where [[Lois Griffin]] and [[List of characters in Family Guy#The Swansons|Bonnie Swanson]] oblige Cleveland's request to passionately kiss; Cleveland's remarks to his son about the sexual desires of female students at his alma mater; his demanding to Roberta's date that he bring her home exactly on time (not for her safety, but for his own sexual gratification, the PTC stated); Cleveland — after attempting to reinstate Rallo at school after he was suspended for peeking up his teacher's skirt — encouraging Rallo to continue his behavior; and the episode-closing incest joke that made reference to ''[[The Brady Bunch]]''.  &quot;Last year, Britney Spear courted controversy with her song, “If You Seek Amy” – perhaps the clumsiest double entendre in pop culture history.  “All of the boys and all of the girls want to – If you seek Amy.”  Clearly, she wasn’t even trying to make sense. Cleveland Show (and American Dad, and Family Guy) creator Seth MacFarlane has basically made a career out of incorporating vulgar sexual references into his shows.  He seems to comb the Urban Dictionary for arcane sexual terms to inspire his comic bits.  For example, the episode also contained the acronym FUPA.  Roberta’s substitute teacher holds up the fat suit and admires its quality:

 

MS. ECK:  “Hollywood costume shop.  High quality.  Look at this FUPA” [&quot;Fat Upper P**** Area&quot;.  [flips the suit] “Look at this poopa.  FUPA, poopa.  FUPA, poopa.”   

 

&quot;By basing so much of his comedy on crass, disgusting sexual content, MacFarlane ensures that every middle-school viewer (the group at which the show is marketed) will repeat those terms on the playground the following day.  For continuing to pollute the airwaves with adult sexual content targeted at children, The Cleveland Show has one again been named Worst TV Show of the Week.&quot; the PTC review stated.&lt;ref name=&quot;PTC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=&quot;The Cleveland Show&quot; on Fox|url=http://www.parentstv.org/PTC/publications/bw/2009/1002worst.asp|work=Worst TV Show of the Week|date=2009-10-02|accessdate=2009-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{imdb episode|id=1415942}}
*{{Tv.com episode|1274599}}

{{Sequence |
 prev= — |
 list=[[The Cleveland Show (season 1)]] |
 next=[[Da Doggone Daddy-Daughter Dinner Dance]]
}}

{{The Cleveland Show episodes}}

[[Category:2009 television episodes]]
[[Category:The Cleveland Show episodes]]
[[Category:Television pilots|Cleveland Show, The]]

[[es:Pilot (The Cleveland Show)]]
[[it:Episodi di The Cleveland Show (prima stagione)#Ritorno a casa]]
[[ru:Pilot (Шоу Кливленда)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
