<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="23979549" ns="0" title="The Exchange, Ilford"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox shopping mall
  | shopping_mall_name = The Exchange
  | image =  
  | image_width = 80px
  | motto              =
  | location           = Main Road, [[Ilford]]
  | opening_date       = 
  | owner              = Meyer Bergman
  | manager            = 
  | floors             = 3
  | number_of_stores   = 90
  | number_of_anchors  = 4
  | Major_Tenants      = Debenhams, TK Maxx, New Look &amp; River Island
  | parking            = 1200 spaces
  | website            = [http://theexchangeilford.co.uk/]
}}

'''The Exchange''' is the main [[Retailing|retail shopping mall]] in the [[town centre]] of [[Ilford]], officially within the [[London Borough of Redbridge]] (though the postal county is historically given as Essex). It was owned by [[The Mall Fund]] for a period of time but has now been sold and reverted to its original name of ''The Exchange Mall''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yelp.co.uk/biz/the-mall-ilford-ilford Customer reviews]&lt;/ref&gt;. It trades from three levels of retail, though its architectural design layout has resulted in the lower floor of retail being separated into two parts, meaning customers wishing to access both parts of the lower level have to travel between the sections via the middle level. There is also an upper level of retail and [[food court]] facilities accessed from the middle level. Transit between levels is via a series of lifts, stairs and escalators within the Mall; in addition, some stores trade from two or more levels of the mall.

The Exchange's anchor stores are [[Debenhams]] (formerly [[Allders]]), [[Marks &amp; Spencer]], [[TK Maxx]] and [[Wilkinson (retailer)|Wilkinson's]]  (the latter of which occupies a former [[Woolworths Group|Woolworths]] store). A new Primark store has opened adjacent to the Exchange.

Other major stores within The Mall Ilford include [[WH Smith]], [[New Look (clothing retailer)|New Look]], [[Sports Direct]], [[Clinton Cards]], [[Burger King]], [[HMV Group|HMV]], [[Ryman]], [[Poundland]], [[Peacocks (clothing)|Peacocks]], [[99p Stores]], [[The Body Shop]] and [[Game (retailer)|GAME]].

The design and layout of some of the stores is notable: the [[Marks &amp; Spencer]] store is bisected by the Mall site: at ground level it is accessile from the High Road by its external doors either side of the Mall entrance, whilst on the middle level of the mall it is accessible from two entrances facing opposite each other (as in [[The Mall Bexleyheath]]). One of the two sides of M&amp;S is also publicly accessible from the Upper level of the Mall. [[TK Maxx]] was initially two separate stores facing each other on opposite sides of the Mall, but this has more recently been changed, with the extension of TK Maxx across the mall area to create a single unified store, in effect splitting the lower mall into three segments, with a third section around the Cranbrook Road entrance (by Wilkinson) which is now separated from the other main part of the lower mall by TK Maxx.&lt;ref name=&quot;floor&quot;&gt;[http://www.themall.co.uk/my-mall/ilford/floor-plans.aspx The Mall Ilford floorplans]&lt;/ref&gt;

Past architectural features of the mall were a, now defunct, granite floating sphere and a wishing fountain. 

[[Image:Ilford Exchange Shopping Centre.JPG|thumb|200px|The main pedestrian frontage of the mall, with 'Exchange' branding, on Ilford High Road; this entrance provides access to the smaller part of the first level and access to escalators leading to upper levels]]

The centre is accessible by car, with access to parking via Havelock Street and Ley Street. The centre is also served by the numerous [[Transport for London]] bus services which serve central Ilford.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://theexchangeilford.co.uk/]

{{coord|51.5596|0.0724|type:landmark_region:GB-RDB|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mall Ilford}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Redbridge]]
[[Category:Shopping centres in London]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
