<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="239870" ns="0" title="University of Pittsburgh"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Infobox university
|image=[[File:University of Pittsburgh Seal (official).svg|200px|University of Pittsburgh Seal]]
|name='''University of Pittsburgh'''
|motto=''Veritas et Virtus'' ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng=Truth and Virtue
|tagline=&quot;Leader in education, pioneer in research, partner in regional development&quot;
|established=February 28, 1787
|type=[[Commonwealth System of Higher Education|State-related]]&lt;ref name=&quot;state&quot;/&gt;
|endowment=US$2.54 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Endowment update&quot;/&gt;
|chancellor=[[Mark Nordenberg]]
|provost=Patricia E. Beeson
|city=[[Pittsburgh]]
|state=[[Pennsylvania]]
|country=United States
|students=28,823&lt;ref name=&quot;enrollfn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;/&gt;
|undergrad=18,371&lt;ref name=&quot;enrollfn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad=10,452&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;/&gt;
|faculty=4,807&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pittsburgh&quot;/&gt;
|campus=Urban, {{convert|132|acre|ha|0}}
|former_names=Pittsburgh Academy (1787–1819)&lt;br/&gt;Western University of Pennsylvania (1819–1908)
|colors=Blue &amp; Gold &amp;nbsp; {{color box|#002b5e}} {{color box|#cdb87c}}
|nickname=Pitt, [[Panthers of Pittsburgh|Panthers]]
|mascot=[[Panthers of Pittsburgh|Roc the Panther]]
|athletics=[[Pittsburgh Panthers|17 varsity teams]]&lt;br/&gt;[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Big East Conference|Big East]], [[Eastern Wrestling League|EWL]], [[East Atlantic Gymnastics League|EAGL]], [[Atlantic Coast Conference|ACC]] (pending)&lt;ref name=&quot;ACC&quot;/&gt;
|affiliations=[[Association of American Universities|AAU]], [[Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities|APLU]], [[EDUCAUSE]], [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools|MSA]], [[Oak Ridge Associated Universities|ORAU]], [[Universities Research Association|URA]]
|website=[http://www.pitt.edu/ pitt.edu]
|logo=[[Image:PittPanthers.png|100px|Pitt school logo]]
|}}
[[Image:CathedralfromFrick.jpg|thumb|upright|At {{convert|535|ft|m}}, Pitt's [[Cathedral of Learning]], here viewed from the [[Frick Fine Arts Building]], is the [[Western Hemisphere]]'s tallest educational structure.]]
The '''University of Pittsburgh''', commonly referred to as '''Pitt''', is a [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education|state-related]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987&quot;/&gt; research university located in [[Pittsburgh]], Pennsylvania, United States. Founded as Pittsburgh Academy in 1787 on what was then the American frontier, Pitt is one of the oldest continuously chartered institutions of higher education in the United States.  Pitt evolved into the Western University of Pennsylvania with an alteration to its charter in 1819, and upon relocating to its current campus in the [[Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]] neighborhood of Pittsburgh in 1908, the school received its current moniker, the University of Pittsburgh. For most of its history Pitt was a private institution, until it became part of the [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education]] in 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19871&quot;/&gt;

Pitt has consistently placed in the top cluster of U.S. public research universities and among the overall top 25 research universities according to the ''[[Center for Measuring University Performance]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;TheCenterRankings&quot;/&gt; is listed as one of ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'''s top  20 public universities,&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews2010public&quot;/&gt; and has been listed among the best colleges for the quality of life of its students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mucha&quot;/&gt;  Pitt has also been named as a &quot;best value&quot; by various publications,&lt;ref name=&quot;USNewsBV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KiplingerBV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PRbestvalue&quot;/&gt; and has appeared in multiple rankings of the world's top universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_W&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;THE&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GUR&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HEEACT&quot;/&gt;

Pitt is among the nation's and world's most active research institutions as evidenced by its $642&amp;nbsp;million in annual research expenditures, its standing among the top five schools in the amount of [[National Institutes of Health]] research allocations, and its election as one of the 61 North American members of the [[Association of American Universities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Chancellor&quot;/&gt; Pitt and its [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine|medical school]] are also closely affiliated with the [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center]], one of the nation's leading academic medical centers.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT UPMC HonorRoll&quot;/&gt;

Pitt is popularly recognized for its centerpiece building, the [[Cathedral of Learning]], for its central role in developing the first polio vaccine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19872&quot;/&gt; and for fielding nationally competitive [[NCAA Division I]] [[Pittsburgh Panthers|athletic programs]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ESPN.com&quot;/&gt;

==History of the University==
[[Image:brackenridge.jpg|thumb|upright|left|[[Hugh Henry Brackenridge]], founder of Pittsburgh Academy in 1787, was a fiery revolutionary, an early supporter of the [[U.S. Constitution]], and is considered America's first novelist.]]
{{Main|History of the University of Pittsburgh}}

===The founding===
Founded by [[Hugh Henry Brackenridge]] as '''Pittsburgh Academy''' in 1787, the University of Pittsburgh is one of the few universities and colleges established in the 18th century in the United States. It is the oldest continuously chartered institution of learning in the U.S. west of the [[Allegheny Mountains]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987&quot;/&gt; The school began its life as a preparatory school, presumably in a [[Log Cabin (University of Pittsburgh)|log cabin]], possibly as early as 1770&lt;ref name=&quot;Annual catalog of the Western University of Pennsylvania, Year Ending 1905&quot;/&gt; in Western Pennsylvania, then a frontier.&lt;ref name=&quot;Early Schools&quot;/&gt;  Hugh Henry Brackenridge sought and obtained a charter for the school from the state legislature of the [[Pennsylvania|Commonwealth of Pennsylvania]] that was passed by the assembly on February 28, 1787, just ten weeks before the opening of the [[Philadelphia Convention|Constitutional Convention]] in Philadelphia.&lt;ref name=&quot;The history of Pittsburgh: its rise and progress&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Through one hundred and fifty years: the University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt;  A brick building was erected in 1790 on the south side of Third Street and Cherry Alley for the Pittsburgh Academy.&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1909&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1910&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alberts&quot;/&gt; The small two-story brick building, with a gable facing the alley, contained three rooms: one below and two above.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rev. John Taylor: the first rector of Trinity Episcopal Church of Pittsburgh and his commonplace book&quot;/&gt;

===The Western University===
Within a short period, more advanced education in the area was needed, so in 1819 the [[Pennsylvania|Commonwealth of Pennsylvania]] amended the school's 1787 charter to confer university status. The school took the name the '''Western University of Pennsylvania''', or WUP, and was intended to be the western sister institution to the [[University of Pennsylvania]] in [[Philadelphia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Celebration of the One Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary: History of the University&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Through One Hundred and Fifty Years: The University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt; By 1830, WUP had moved into a new three-story, freestone-fronted building, with Ionic columns and a cupola, near its original buildings fronting the south side of Third Street, between Smithfield Street and Cherry Alley in downtown [[Pittsburgh]]. By the 1830s, the university faced severe financial pressure to abandon its traditional  liberal education in favor of the [[Pennsylvania General Assembly|state legislature's]] desire for it to provide more vocational training. The decision to  remain committed to liberal education nearly killed the university, but it persevered despite its abandonment by the city and state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alberts17&quot;/&gt; It was also during this era that founder of [[Mellon Bank]], [[Thomas Mellon]] (Class of 1837), graduated and later taught at WUP.&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1909&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1910&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alberts&quot;/&gt;

===Fires===
[[Image:Pitt1833.jpg|thumb|right|Western University of Pennsylvania, the previous name of Pitt, is depicted in this 1833 oil painting at its location on 3rd Avenue in downtown Pittsburgh.]]
The University's buildings, along with most of its records and files, were destroyed in the Great Fire of 1845 that wiped out 20 square blocks of Pittsburgh. Classes were temporarily held in Trinity Church until a new building was constructed on Duquesne Way (on what was the site of the former [[Horne's]] department store). Only four years later, in 1849, this building also was destroyed by fire. Due to the catastrophic nature of these fires, operations were suspended for a few years to allow the University time to regroup and rebuild. By 1854, WUP had erected a new building on the corner of Ross and Diamond (now Forbes Avenue) streets (site of the present day [[Pittsburgh City-County Building|City-County building]]) and classes resumed in 1855. It is during this era, in 1867, that [[Samuel Pierpoint Langley]], astronomer, inventor, aviation pioneer and future Secretary of the [[Smithsonian Institution]], was chosen as director of the [[Allegheny Observatory]] that was donated to WUP in 1865. Langley was professor of astronomy and physics and remained at WUP until 1891, when he was succeeded by another prominent astronomer, [[James Edward Keeler|James Keeler]]. Growing quickly during this period, WUP outgrew its downtown facilities and the university moved its campus to [[Allegheny, Pennsylvania|Allegheny City]] (present-day [[Northside (Pittsburgh)|North Side]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1909&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1910&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alberts&quot;/&gt;

===A move north===
[[Image:Pitt1890to1909.jpg|thumb|right|Western University of Pennsylvania's campus on Observatory Hill on Pittsburgh's North Side from 1890 to 1909]]
The University eventually found itself on a {{convert|10|acre|ha|sing=on}} site on the North Side's [[Observatory Hill (Pittsburgh)|Observatory Hill]] at the location of its [[Allegheny Observatory]]. There, it constructed two new buildings, Science Hall and Main Hall, that were occupied by 1889 and 1890 respectively. During this era, the first collegiate football team was formed at Pitt in 1889. In 1892, the Western Pennsylvania Medical College was amalgamated into the University. By 1893, the University had graduated its first African-American, William Dammond.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1893: William Hunter Dammond&quot;/&gt; In 1895, WUP established its School of Law and [[Andrew Carnegie]] and [[George Westinghouse]] were elected to the Board of Trustees, where they joined [[Andrew Mellon]] who was elected in 1894. The Pittsburgh College of Pharmacy and Pittsburgh Dental School also joined the University in 1896. In 1898, the first women, sisters Margaret and Stella Stein, graduated from the University.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1898: Margaret and Stella Stein&quot;/&gt;  During this period, University engineering professor [[Reginald Fessenden]] was conducting pioneering work in radio broadcasting. By 1904, playing at [[Exposition Park (Pittsburgh)|Exposition Park]], the University had its first undefeated football team.&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1909&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1910&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;alberts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1906: Reginald Fessenden&quot;/&gt;

===A new name and home===
[[File:Thaw1913.jpg|thumb|left|[[Thaw Hall]], circa 1910]]
Citing a need to avoid confusion, distinguish itself from the University of Pennsylvania, and return to its roots by identifying itself with the city, the Western University of Pennsylvania, by act of the state legislature, was renamed the '''University of Pittsburgh''' in the summer of 1908. During this time, the University had also outgrown its accommodations on what is now the North Side of Pittsburgh and its departments had been scattered throughout the city for years. To consolidate all of its components on one campus, WUP bought {{convert|43|acre|m2}} of land in December 1907 in what is now the Oakland neighborhood of Pittsburgh and began relocating departments there by 1909.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Owl&quot;/&gt; The initial campus plan for the University centered on the winning submission from a national architectural contest that incorporated a Greek Acropolis design by [[Henry Hornbostel]] for 30 buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: the story of the University of Pittsburgh, 1787–1987&quot;/&gt; However, due to financial and other constraints, only four of the buildings were constructed in this style, of which only [[Thaw Hall]] remains today. It was also during this period that the university, led by Chancellor [[Samuel McCormick]],  would again fend off pressures to abandon the school's commitment to liberal education in favor of more technical-based training. During his administration, McCormick would also lead the university into a new level of national recognition, expansion, and growth, as well as began institutional support of  athletics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19873&quot;/&gt;

===A national landmark===
[[File:1935CathedralofLearningOwl.jpg|thumb|150px|right|The [[Cathedral of Learning]] circa 1935]]
In the 1920s, new university chancellor [[John Gabbert Bowman]] declared that he had a vision for a centerpiece &quot;tall building&quot; for the university. The {{convert|14|acre}} Frick Acres property in Oakland was soon purchased and plans for the campus shifted focus from the hillside to a neo-[[Gothic Revival architecture|Gothic Revival]] plan that today comprises the [[Cathedral of Learning]], [[Heinz Memorial Chapel]], [[Stephen Foster Memorial]], and [[Clapp Hall]] buildings. By 1925, Bowman had settled on a design by [[Charles Klauder]] for the &quot;tall building&quot;: an attention-getting {{convert|535|ft|m|sing=on}} tower whose great height, with open spaces all around, would suggest the &quot;character that ought to be in an educated man.&quot;  The building's &quot;parallel lines going up and up...would express courage [and] fearlessness&quot; and it would &quot;unify Pittsburgh into a community conscious of its character.&quot;  The Cathedral is &quot;cut off&quot; flat at the top to suggest that its lines, like education, have no ending. The building was financed by donors as well as a campaign to collect dimes from local school children. Bowman was a persuasive leader and although the [[Great Depression]] intervened, the [[Cathedral of Learning]], on which construction was begun in 1926, started hosting classes in 1931 and was formally dedicated in 1937. Today, it remains the second tallest university building in the world and contains an equally-impressive interior highlighted by a half-acre (2,000 m²) Gothic hall Commons Room with {{convert|52|ft|m|sing=on}} tall arches currently surrounded by 27&amp;nbsp;[[Nationality Rooms]], however eight more Nationality Rooms are in the making.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Nationality Rooms - rooms in planning&quot;/&gt; 

===Development of the polio vaccine===
[[Image:SalkatPitt.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Jonas Salk]] developed the first polio vaccine at the University of Pittsburgh.]]
In the early 20th century, epidemics of [[poliomyelitis|polio]] began to hit the United States and other industrialized countries. As hospital wards filled with patients in [[iron lung]]s, and tens of thousands were left disabled, fear of contracting polio grew rampant and led to the closing of many public facilities. Meanwhile, [[Jonas Salk|Dr. Jonas Salk]] had set up the University of Pittsburgh's Virus Research Lab in the basement of what is now [[Salk Hall]]. By 1951, Salk and his team had begun immunization experiments in monkeys using dead polio virus. Soon, however, Salk began to test inoculations in paralyzed polio patients and by 1953 human trials among the general population were initiated. By the spring of the following year, the largest controlled field trials in medical history were underway, and by 1955 the [[polio vaccine|vaccine]] developed by [[Jonas Salk]] and his team of Pitt researchers was declared effective. By 1962, Salk's vaccine had reduced the incidence of polio in the United States by ''95 percent''. The breakthroughs in immunology and vaccine development at Pitt by Salk and his team are considered one of the most significant scientific and medical achievements in history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Remembering Polio: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Salk Polio Vaccine&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shot Heard 'Round the World&quot;/&gt;

===State relations===
In 1966, Pitt was designated by [[Pennsylvania]] as a [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education|state-related]] university. As such, Pitt receives public funds ($185.4&amp;nbsp;million in fiscal year 2011) covering about 9% of its operating budget and offers reduced tuition to Pennsylvania residents. Pitt remains under independent control, but is typically categorized as a public university. Upon affiliation with the state, subsidized tuition led to a massive influx of new students and rapid expansion of Pitt's size and scope. In the 1970s, Pitt's football team returned to greatness with a national championship season in 1976 led by [[Pro Football Hall of Fame|Hall of Fame]] running back [[Tony Dorsett]] and continued success in the 1980s with players such as [[Pro Football Hall of Fame|Hall of Fame]] quarterback [[Dan Marino]]. In the 1980s, significant medical research in the field of [[organ transplantation]] was conducted by [[Thomas Starzl]], establishing Pitt as the world leader in the field of organ transplantation. In 1991, long-time chancellor [[Wesley Posvar]] retired after 24 years in office. His administration is best known for elimination of the university's debt from its 1960s financial crisis and for increasing the school's prestige and endowment. Under Posvar, Pitt's operating budget grew sevenfold to $630&amp;nbsp;million and its endowment tripled to $257&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt&quot;/&gt;
[[Mark Nordenberg]] has been chancellor of the University since 1995 and is leading Pitt through a period of substantial progress, including a $2-billion capital-raising campaign that is over half-way toward achieving its goal&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Giving: Office of Institutional Advancement&quot;/&gt; and a $1-billion 12-year facilities plan.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Announces 12-Year Facilities Plan To Support Programmatic Direction&quot;/&gt; In 2010, Pitt's $2.033&amp;nbsp;billion endowment ranked 28th among all colleges and universities and 7th nationally among public universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endowment&quot;/&gt; Pitt's endowment now stands at $2.545&amp;nbsp;billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Endowment update&quot;/&gt;

==Location and campus==
[[Image:HeinzChapelSouth.jpg|thumb|left|[[Heinz Memorial Chapel]]]]
The University of Pittsburgh's main campus comprises approximately 132 urban acres (0.53&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) located in Pittsburgh's historic [[Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]] neighborhood. Much of the campus, including its centerpiece 42-story [[Cathedral of Learning]], falls within the [[Schenley Farms Historic District|Oakland Civic Center/Schenley Farms National Historic District]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NRHP-districts&quot;/&gt; The campus contains an eclectic mix of architecture that includes Greek revival, Neogothic, Italian Renaissance, and modern. It has been termed &quot;a theme park of replica buildings, representing the architecture of the past speaking to the present.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Weighing in on Pitt's eclectic architecture&quot;/&gt; The campus has won multiple Green Star Awards from the [[Professional Grounds Management Society]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Wins Grounds Services Award&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PGMS Green Star Awards: Urban University Grounds: University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PGMS News - PGMS Salutes Grounds Management Excellence; College and University Grounds Lead the Way&quot;/&gt;

The University of Pittsburgh's main campus can be thought to be made up of four contiguous sections: upper (sports complexes, [[Upper campus residence halls (University of Pittsburgh)|residence halls]]); mid ([[Benedum Hall|Benedum]], [[Chevron Science Center|Chevron]], [[Allen Hall (University of Pittsburgh)|Allen]] and [[Thaw Hall]]s); lower ([[Cathedral of Learning]], [[William Pitt Union|Union]], [[Wesley W. Posvar Hall|Posvar Hall]]); and on the west end of campus, the [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center|medical center complex]]. The campus is generally bordered by Darragh Street/McKee Place to the west and Bellefield Avenue/Dithridge Street to the east; Forbes and Fifth avenues traverse the campus from west to east. Although generally within walking distance, the university also runs a [[University of Pittsburgh Transportation System|bus and shuttle service]] between various campus locations and bordering neighborhoods.

The main campus abuts or is within a short walking distance of many recreational, cultural, and educational institutions that also populate the Oakland neighborhood.   The campus is directly adjacent to [[Schenley Plaza]], the main branch of the [[Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh|Carnegie Public Library]], the [[Carnegie Museums of Pittsburgh|Carnegie Museums of Natural History and Art]], and the Carnegie Music Hall. [[Carlow University]] is just west of campus, adjacent to the University's medical center complexes. [[Carnegie Mellon University]], [[Central Catholic High School (Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania)|Central Catholic High School]] and historic [[Schenley Park]], site of the [[Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens]], lie across [[Junction Hollow]] on the east end. Some Pitt professors also hold adjunct professorships at Carnegie Mellon and ''vice-versa''.
{{-}}

===Historic buildings===
[[Image:StephenFosterWinter.jpg|thumb|right|[[Stephen Foster Memorial]]]]
There are two University buildings listed separately on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]: [[Allegheny Observatory]] (in Pittsburgh's Riverview Park on the [[Northside (Pittsburgh)|Northside]]) and the [[Cathedral of Learning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PENNSYLVANIA – Allegheny County&quot;/&gt; Twenty-one of Pitt's buildings (including the 5 residence halls that make up [[Schenley Quadrangle]], see below) are [[contributing properties]] to the [[Schenley Farms Historic District|Schenley Farms-Oakland Civic Center Historic District]] that has been listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]] as a [[historic district (United States)|historic district]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NRHP-districts&quot;/&gt;

Due to the historical nature of various sites in or around Pitt's buildings, the Commonwealth of [[Pennsylvania]] has placed historical markers outside the
[[Allegheny Observatory]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Allegheny Observatory&quot;/&gt; [[Wesley W. Posvar Hall|Posvar Hall]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Forbes Field&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Barney Dreyfuss (1865-1932)&quot;/&gt; [[Salk Hall]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Salk Polio Vaccine – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;/&gt;
[[Stephen Foster Memorial]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen C. Foster Memorial – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;/&gt; and the [[William Pitt Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;V.F.W. – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;/&gt;
In addition, a Pennsylvania Historical Marker has been placed on campus near the Cathedral of Learning to mark the significance of the University of Pittsburgh itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt; Another state historical marker has been placed to highlight the significance of Pitt's involvement in the archaeological excavation at the [[Meadowcroft Rockshelter]] in [[Avella, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Meadowcroft Rockshelter&quot;/&gt;

In addition, the [[Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation]] has designated the following Pitt buildings as Pittsburgh Historic Landmarks: [[Allegheny Observatory]], [[Allen Hall (University of Pittsburgh)|Allen Hall]], [[Alumni Hall (University of Pittsburgh)|Alumni Hall]], [[Bellefield Hall]], [[Chancellor's Residence (University of Pittsburgh)|Chancellor's Residence]], [[Cathedral of Learning]], the [[Cathedral of Learning#Commons Room|Cathedral of Learning interior rooms]], [[Gardner Steel Conference Center]], [[Heinz Memorial Chapel]], [[Thaw Hall]], [[Salk Hall]], [[Schenley Quadrangle|Schenley Quadrangle residence halls]], [[Stephen Foster Memorial]], the [[University Child Development Center]], and the [[William Pitt Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation: PHLF Plaques &amp; Registries&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh History &amp; Landmarks Foundation announces Historic Building and Landscape Designations&quot;/&gt;

Other Pitt buildings not designated individually as landmarks, but listed among the 16 Pitt-owned contributing properties to the Schenley Farms Historic District, include [[Clapp Hall]], [[O'Hara Student Center]], [[Ruskin Hall]], [[Thackeray Hall]], [[Frick Fine Arts Building]], [[Music Building (University of Pittsburgh)|Music Building]], and the [[University Club (University of Pittsburgh)|University Club]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hearing set on historic landmark nomination for two Pitt buildings&quot;/&gt;

Historic structures within, adjacent to, or near Pitt's campus, but not belonging to the university, include the [[Carnegie Museums of Pittsburgh|Carnegie Museum buildings]], [[Pittsburgh Science and Technology Academy|Frick School]], [[Forbes Field]] wall remnant, [[Christopher Magee|Magee]] Estate iron fence, the [[Mary Schenley Memorial Fountain|Schenley Fountain]], [[Mellon Institute]], [[Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens]], the [[Pittsburgh Athletic Association]], [[Cathedral of Saint Paul in Pittsburgh|St. Paul's Cathedral]], St. Nicholas Greek Orthodox Church, [[Schenley High School]], [[Soldiers and Sailors Memorial Hall]], and the [[Stephen Foster (sculpture)|Stephen Foster sculpture]].  Many of these buildings and their facilities are integrated into the events and activities of the university.

===Other buildings===
{{Main|List of University of Pittsburgh buildings}}
[[Image:FrickFineArts.jpg|thumb|left|[[Frick Fine Arts Building]]]]

The majority of [[List of University of Pittsburgh buildings|Pitt-owned facilities]] are clustered in the [[Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]] neighborhood of Pittsburgh which includes the [[Schenley Farms Historic District]], however a few prominent facilities are scattered elsewhere throughout the city, including the adjacent [[Shadyside (Pittsburgh)|Shadyside]] neighborhood. Pitt also maintains regional Pennsylvania campuses in [[University of Pittsburgh at Bradford|Bradford]], [[University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg|Greensburg]], [[University of Pittsburgh at Johnstown|Johnstown]], and [[University of Pittsburgh at Titusville|Titusville]], as well as a Computer Center in RIDC Park in [[Blawnox, Pennsylvania|Blawnox]], the Plum Boro Science Center in [[Plum, Pennsylvania|Plum]], the [[University of Pittsburgh Applied Research Center]] (U-PARC) in [[Harmarville, Pennsylvania|Harmarville]], and the [[Pymatuning Laboratory of Ecology]] in [[Linesville, Pennsylvania|Linesville]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pymatuning Laboratory of Ecology&quot;/&gt; The university also has a major archeological research site, the [[Allen L. Cook Spring Creek Preserve]], in Spring Creek, [[Wyoming]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Receives 4,700 Acres of Wyoming Land Teeming With Dinosaur Fossils&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Go West&quot;/&gt;

Athletic facilities of the [[University of Pittsburgh Panthers]] that are located in Oakland in the upper campus and include the [[Cost Sports Center|Charles L Cost Sports Center]], [[Fitzgerald Field House]], the [[Petersen Events Center]], [[Trees Hall]] and [[:Image:TreesField3.jpg|Trees Field]]. An approximately $30&amp;nbsp;million upgrade of on-campus sports facilities, termed the [[Petersen Sports Complex]], is under construction and will include new soccer, baseball, softball facilities, as well as clear space for the future construction of a new track and field and band complex following its completion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Petersen Sports Complex&quot;/&gt; Athletic facilities in Pittsburgh that are located outside of the Oakland neighborhood include [[Heinz Field]] and the [[UPMC Sports Performance Complex]].

Major on-campus residence halls include the [[Litchfield Towers]], [[Schenley Quadrangle]], [[Bouquet Gardens]] and [[Ruskin Hall]] located on the lower campus, [[Lothrop Hall]] and [[Forbes Hall]] on the medical campus, and [[Pennsylvania Hall (Pittsburgh)|Pennsylvania]], [[Panther Hall|Panther]], and [[Sutherland Hall|Sutherland]] halls located on the upper campus.
{{-}}

===University of Pittsburgh Medical Center===
{{Main|University of Pittsburgh Medical Center}}
{{See also|List of University of Pittsburgh buildings#UPMC|l1=List of UPMC buildings in Pittsburgh}}
[[Image:WPUlawn.jpg|thumb|right|[[William Pitt Union]] and the [[Panthers of Pittsburgh#Millennium Panther|Millennium Panther]]]]

The [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center]] (UPMC), which is consistently ranked in U.S. News &amp; World Report's &quot;Honor Roll&quot; of America's top hospitals,&lt;ref name=&quot;UPMCrank&quot;/&gt; consists of the following hospitals and facilities in the [[Oakland (Pittsburgh)|Oakland]] area, many of which have shared use with various university departments: UPMC Presbyterian Hospital, UPMC Montefiore Hospital, Magee-Women's Hospital of UPMC, Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic in Thomas Detre Hall, Eye and Ear Institute, [[Forbes Tower]] (home to the [[University of Pittsburgh School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences|School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences]]), Iroquois Building, Kaufman Medical Building, Medical Arts Building, 230 McKee Place, and UPMC University Center. UPMC academic hospitals and facilities that are scattered elsewhere throughout the city include the [[Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC]] campus in the [[Lawrenceville (Pittsburgh)|Lawrencevville]] neighborhood, the [[UPMC Sports Performance Complex]] on the [[South Side (Pittsburgh)|South Side]], and UPMC Shadyside and the [[University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute]] in the Hillman Cancer Center both located in the [[Shadyside (Pittsburgh)|Shadyside]] neighborhood adjacent to Oakland.

===Panthers===
{{Main|Panthers of Pittsburgh}}

In the fall of 1909, the University of Pittsburgh was the first college or university to adopt the panther (''[[Cougar|Puma concolor]]'') as its mascot.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Panther&quot;/&gt; Popular as photo sites, there are ten representations of Panthers in and about Pitt's campus, and ten more painted fiberglass panthers placed around the campus by the Pitt Student Government. These fiberglass panther structures are given to a campus group for a year and painted by the group to reflect their interests. The oldest representations are four panthers that guard each corner of the Panther Hollow bridge. Other Oakland locations include both inside and in front of the William Pitt Union, outside the Petersen Events Center, &quot;Pitt the Panther&quot; on the carousel in Schenley Plaza, the Panther head fountain on the front of the Cathedral of Learning, and the Pitt Panther statue outside Heinz Field on Pittsburgh's North Side.

==Education==
[[File:Cathedral of Learning inside entrance.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Cathedral of Learning#Commons Room|Commons Room]] in the Cathedral of Learning]]
Throughout its history, Pitt has been committed to a liberal arts education with a well-rounded curriculum in the arts, sciences, and humanities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alberts17&quot;/&gt; Pitt has an increasing emphasis on undergraduate research experience and for providing real-world opportunities such as co-ops and internships.&lt;ref name=&quot;undergrad-research&quot;/&gt;  Undergraduate degrees can be earned as Bachelor's of Arts, Bachelor's of Science, and Bachelor's of Philosophy.  Along with providing certificate programs, graduate level masters, professional, and doctoral degrees are also awarded.  Pitt has also initiated a University-wide Outside the Classroom Curriculum (OCC) that includes a structured series of extracurricular programs and experiences designed to complement students' academic studies and help develop personal attributes and professional skills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Outside the Classroom Curriculum: Your Pitt Pathway&quot;/&gt; Students who complete the OCC requirements receive an OCC &quot;transcript&quot; and a green cord of distinction to wear at commencement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt to Offer Students Opportunity to Develop Professional Skills Through Extracurricular Experiences in a New Program: Outside the Classroom Curriculum to be implemented this fall&quot;/&gt;

===Schools===
Bachelor's, master's, doctoral and professional programs are offered through the following academic units:
{|style=&quot;border:0 solid #ddd; background:#fefefe; padding:3px; margin:0;&quot;
|
* [[Dietrich School of Arts and Sciences]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh College of Business Administration|College of Business Administration]]
* [[Joseph M. Katz School of Business|Joseph M. Katz Graduate School of Business]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Dental Medicine|School of Dental Medicine]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Education|School of Education]]
* [[Swanson School of Engineering]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh College of General Studies|College of General Studies]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences|School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh Honors College|University Honors College]]
|style=&quot;width:40px;&quot;|
|
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Information Sciences|School of Information Sciences]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Law|School of Law]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine|School of Medicine]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Nursing|School of Nursing]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Pharmacy|School of Pharmacy]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public and International Affairs|Graduate School of Public &amp; International Affairs (GSPIA)]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health|Graduate School of Public Health]]
* [[University of Pittsburgh School of Social Work|School of Social Work]]
|}

===International studies===
[[Image:Indianroom2.jpg|thumb|right|The Indian Classroom, one of 27 [[Nationality Rooms]] in the Cathedral of Learning]]
Pitt’s history of commitment to international education is illustrated by its unique collection of 27 [[Nationality Rooms]] on the first and third floors of the [[Cathedral of Learning]]. As a further demonstration of this commitment, Pitt is one of the country’s leading producers of both Fulbright scholars and Peace Corps volunteers&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;University Center for International Studies (UCIS)&quot;/&gt; and one of less than 20 American universities to claim five or more area studies programs that have been competitively designated as National Resource Centers by the [[United States Department of Education|U.S. Department of Education]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt-fall-07&quot;/&gt;

Pitt's National Resource Centers include Asian,  European, Latin American, Russian and East European, and Global studies,&lt;ref name=&quot;ritchie&quot;/&gt; as well as Pitt's International Business Center.&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt-fall-07&quot;/&gt; In addition, Pitt's Asian Studies Center has been awarded status as a [[Confucius Institute]] by the Chinese Ministry of Education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chinese Ministry of Education Awards University of Pittsburgh First Confucius Institute in Pennsylvania&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Confucius Institute at the University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt; Further, Pitt is home to one of just ten European Union Centers of Excellence in the U.S., funded by the [[European Commission]].

The [[University of Pittsburgh Center for International Studies|University Center for International Studies]] (UCIS) coordinates international education curricula, centers on topical specializations in international studies, and the centers for area studies, including the National Resource Centers, among existing faculty and departments throughout the university. It does not itself give degrees but awards certificates of attainment to degree candidates in the University's schools and also operates certificate programs in African Studies (undergraduate) and in Global Studies (undergraduate &amp; graduate).&lt;ref name=&quot;about-ucis&quot;/&gt; UCIS also operates the Study Abroad Office,&lt;ref name=&quot;Study Abroad Office&quot;/&gt; Nationality Rooms and Intercultural Exchange Programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;about nationality rooms&quot;/&gt;

Pitt's study abroad program, under the auspices of UCIS, helps to facilitate student study in over a hundred different countries, and oversees a variety of programs including the Panther Programs, which are course taught abroad that have been developed and are accompanied by faculty of the university; two-way exchange agreements with foreign institutions; and Pitt-recognized, third-party exchange programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Study Abroad Program Options&quot;/&gt; The university also offers several study abroad scholarships, including those through the Nationality Rooms program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scholarships for Study Abroad&quot;/&gt; In addition, following the decision to end a 24-year sponsorship of the [[Semester at Sea]] program due to academic, administrative and safety concerns,&lt;ref name=&quot;Provost explains decision to drop Semester at Sea&quot;/&gt;  Pitt has created a Multi-region Academic Program (PittMAP) that involves international travel, accompanied by university faculty, to three different continents for the comparative study of one of six rotating global study themes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Map Program&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;robinet&quot;/&gt;

===Rankings===
&lt;table class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width:23em; font-size:75%; text-align:left;&quot;&gt;
{|class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 23em; font-size: 75%;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 100%; text-align: center;&quot; |
&lt;big&gt;Pitt rankings&lt;/big&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; &lt;noinclude&gt;font-size:larger;&lt;/noinclude&gt;&quot;&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Academic Ranking of World Universities|ARWU]]'' World&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_W&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt; 56 &lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''ARWU'' United States&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_W&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt; 37&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;ARWU'' Life Sciences&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_LIFE&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;ARWU'' Clinical Medicine&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_MED&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt; 12&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;ARWU'' Social Sciences&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_SOC&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;47&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Center for Measuring University Performance|CMUP]]'' Research Universities&lt;ref name=&quot;TheCenterRankings&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index|FSPI]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;FSBI&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;31&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[HEEACT - Performance Ranking of Scientific Papers for World Universities|HEEACT]]'' World&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_HEEACT_W&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Global University Ranking|GUR]]'' Global&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_RatER_Global&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;42&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[SCImago Institutions Rankings|SCImago]]'' Worldwide&lt;ref name=&quot;SCImago&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[College and university rankings#The Times Higher Education - QS World University Rankings|THES]]'' World&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_THES_W&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;64&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''[[College and university rankings#U.S. News &amp; World Report College and University rankings|USNWR]]'' National University&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_NU&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;56&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''USNWR'' National Best Values&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_NBV&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''USNWR'' National Top Publics&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_TPS&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[Joseph M. Katz Graduate School of Business|Business]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Bus&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;79&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Education|Education]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Ed&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[Swanson School of Engineering|Engineering]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Eng&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;48&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Law|Law]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Law&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;71&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Information Sciences|Library &amp; Information]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_LibS&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine|Medical]] (research)&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Medr&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' Medical (primary care)&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Medc&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Nursing|Nursing]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Nurs&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Pharmacy|Pharmacy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Pharmacy&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences|Physical Therapy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PhysicalTherapy&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public and International Affairs|Public Affairs]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PublicAffairs&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health|Public Health]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PublicHealth&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;''&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;USNWR'' [[University of Pittsburgh School of Social Work|Social Work]]&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_SocialWork&quot;/&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[College and university rankings#Washington Monthly College rankings|Washington Monthly]]'' National&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Wamo_NU&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Global University Ranking by Wuhan University|Wuhan]]'' International ESI&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Wuhan&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt; ''[[Webometrics Ranking of World Universities|Webometrics]]'' World&lt;ref name=&quot;Webometrics&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/th&gt;&lt;td&gt;39&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
|}
[[Image:cathedralLawfromMellon2.jpg|thumb|left|The lawn of the [[Cathedral of Learning]].]]

The [[Center for Measuring University Performance]] has ranked Pitt, along with only six other schools, in the top tier of U.S. public research universities and in the 6th&amp;nbsp;tier (or top&amp;nbsp;25) among all universities according to its 2009 annual report.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheCenterRankings&quot;/&gt;

In 2009, ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranked Pitt 20th in comparison to other [[public university|public universities]] in the United States and 56th among all national universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews2010public&quot;/&gt; In addition, ''U.S. News'' ranked Pitt 39th on the dimension of &quot;best value&quot; among all national universities,&lt;ref name=&quot;USNewsBV&quot;/&gt; ''Princeton Review'' placed Pitt among its &quot;Best Value Public Colleges&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;PRbestvalue&quot;/&gt; while ''[[Kiplinger]]'' rated Pitt the best value in Pennsylvania and eighth best nationally for out-of-state students among public universities in their 2011 rankings.&lt;ref name=&quot;KiplingerBV&quot;/&gt;

In worldwide evaluations of universities, ''[[Newsweek]]'' ranked Pitt 37th in its &quot;The Top 100 Global Universities.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Complete List: The Top 100 Global Universities&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranked 50th worldwide (and 37th in the U.S.) in the [[Shanghai Jiao Tong University|Shanghai Jiao Tong University's]] [[Academic Ranking of World Universities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_W&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranked 116th in the 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]],&lt;ref name=&quot;QS World University Rankings 2010 Results&quot;/&gt; coming 39th in the United States, and attaining 99th for Arts &amp; Humanities.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranks 24th of all universities in the world for the impact and performance of its scientific public publications according to the Performance Ranking of Scientific Papers for World Universities produced by the [[Higher Education Evaluation and Accreditation Council of Taiwan]] (HEEACT).&lt;ref name=&quot;HEEACT&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranks as the 26th best higher education research institution worldwide according to [[SCImago]] Institutions Rankings' 2009 World Report.&lt;ref name=&quot;SCImago&quot;/&gt; Other world rankings include 29th in the world in the latest ranking by the Research Center for Chinese Science Evaluation at [[Wuhan University]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Wuhan&quot;/&gt; 37th in the world in the latest [[Webometrics Ranking of World Universities|Webometrics]] rankings,&lt;ref name=&quot;Webometrics&quot;/&gt; and 42nd in the world according to both the 2006 G-Factor International University Ranking&lt;ref name=&quot;G-Factor International University Ranking 2006: Top 300&quot;/&gt; as well as the [[Russia]]n-based 2009 Global University Ranking.&lt;ref name=&quot;GUR&quot;/&gt;

In addition to its academic rankings, Pitt has also been recognized for its positive campus atmosphere, with [[The Princeton Review]] rating Pitt as having the 8th happiest student body and the 11th best quality of life in the nation in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mucha&quot;/&gt;

Many of university's individual schools, departments, and programs are highly regarded in their particular field as evidenced by the number of Pitt programs that were ranked in the latest [[United States National Research Council rankings|National Research Council rankings]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NRC Rankings in Each of 41 Areas&quot;/&gt; Particularly well regarded programs include Pitt's Department of Philosophy, which has long been renowned in the U.S. and worldwide, and is especially strong in the areas of mathematical and philosophical logic, metaphysics, history and philosophy of science, philosophy of language, philosophy of mathematics, philosophy of mind and psychology, and semantics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Welcome to the 2006–2008 Philosophical Gourmet Report&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

The University of Pittsburgh Schools of the Health Sciences, including [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine|Medicine]], [[University of Pittsburgh School of Dental Medicine|Dental]], [[University of Pittsburgh School of Nursing|Nursing]], [[University of Pittsburgh School of Pharmacy|Pharmacy]], [[University of Pittsburgh Graduate School of Public Health|Public Health]], and [[University of Pittsburgh School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences|Rehabilition]] are also all highly ranked and regarded in their respective fields.&lt;ref name=&quot;U.S. News ranks graduate programs&quot;/&gt;  In addition, the [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center]], is consistently honored as one of America's top hospitals.&lt;ref name=&quot;UPMCrank&quot;/&gt;

The university's [[Joseph M. Katz School of Business]] MBA program is ranked first in the U.S. in &quot;Value for Money,&quot; 51st overall in the nation, and its faculty research is ranked 47th in the world by the 2007 [[Financial Times]] ranking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Katz School Ranks First in the Nation for MBA Value&quot;/&gt; The Joseph Katz Graduate School consistently ranks among the top ten public business schools in the U.S. according to ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]''.

Pitt's law school faculty has been ranked 21st in the nation based upon standard objective measures of scholarly impact.&lt;ref name=&quot;Top 35 Law Faculties Based on Scholarly Impact, 2007&quot;/&gt; Overall Pitt's [[University of Pittsburgh School of Law|Law School]] is ranked 63rd by The Law School 100,&lt;ref name=&quot;Law School 100 -- Ranking the Best Law Schools in the United States&quot;/&gt; is listed among the nation's top law schools by The Princeton Review,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Princeton Review: University of Pittsburgh School of Law&quot;/&gt; and was ranked 71st by  [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] in 2011,&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Law&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Law School Rankings&quot;/&gt; down from a peak ranking of 48th in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;PRELAW HANDBOOK - Law School Rankings: 2000-present&quot;/&gt;

Pitt is home to the Gertrude E. and John M. Petersen Institute of [[Nanotechnology|NanoScience]] and Engineering, which was ranked second in the nation in 2006 for microscale and nanoscale research by the leading global trade publication, ''[[Small Times]]''. Pitt also has a recognized program in [[Radio-frequency identification]] device (RFID) technology, with its research program rated among the top three in the world along with MIT and the University of Cambridge in England.&lt;ref name=&quot;RFID Lowdown&quot;/&gt;

===Scholars===
[[File:ClassonHeinzChapelsteps.jpg|thumb|right|upright|A class meets outside on the steps of [[Heinz Memorial Chapel|Heinz Chapel]]]]
Pitt students have regularly won national and international scholarships and fellowship awards, including four [[Rhodes Scholarship]]s since 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt4&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11325/1191508-298.stm | title=Pitt graduate named Rhodes Scholar | first=Molly | last=Born | newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | location=Pittsburgh, PA | date=2011-11-21 | accessdate=2011-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, in addition to the three national military academies, Pitt was one of only nine universities, and the only public university, to claim both Rhodes and Marshall Scholars. Since 1995, Pitt undergraduates have also won six [[Marshall Scholarship]]s, five [[Truman Scholarships]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt grad named 2010 Rhodes Scholar&quot;/&gt; five [[Morris K. Udall Foundation|Udall Scholarships]], a [[Churchill Scholarship]], a [[Gates Cambridge Scholarship]],&lt;ref name=&quot;white&quot;/&gt; 35&amp;nbsp;[[Barry M. Goldwater Scholarship|Goldwater Scholarships]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Neuroscience Student From Pennsylvania Awarded Goldwater Scholarship&quot;/&gt; 23 [[National Security Education Program|Boren Scholarships]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Four Pitt Honors College Students Receive 2010 David L. Boren Awards for International Study&quot;/&gt; and three Mellon Humanities Fellowships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt students win Truman, Goldwater scholarships&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt students win Goldwater, Udall scholarships&quot;/&gt;

Pitt is also a leading producer of [[Fulbright Program|Fulbright]] scholars, placing in the top 20 of all universities in the number of student scholars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=10006 | title= Pitt Is Again a Top Producer of Fulbright Grant Winners | first=John | last=Harvith | first2=Kelly | last2=Byrnes | newspaper=Pitt Chronicle | publisher=University of Pittsburgh | location=Pittsburgh, PA | volume=12 | number=32 | date=2011-11-21 | accessdate=2011-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pitt alumni have won awards such as the [[Nobel Peace Prize]], the Nobel Prize in medicine, the [[Pulitzer Prize]] for fiction, the [[Shaw Prize]] in medicine, the Albany Prize in medicine, the [[John Fritz Medal|Fritz Medal]] in engineering, the [[Templeton Prize]], and the Grainger Challenge Prize for sustainability.&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;armanlos&quot;/&gt;

===Research===
Pitt, one of 62 elected members of the [[Association of American Universities]], has a strong research presence with $642&amp;nbsp;million in annual research expenditures,&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Chancellor&quot;/&gt; ranking among the top 20 universities in the country in terms of total research and development expenditures in science and engineering,&lt;ref name=&quot;Universities report continued decline in real federal S&amp;E R&amp;D funding in FY 2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NSF funding: Where Pitt stands&quot;/&gt; 13th in the U.S. in total federal science and engineering research expenditures,&lt;ref name=&quot;Federal S&amp;E obligations to academic institutions reach new highs in FY 2006 but fail to keep up with inflation&quot;/&gt; and 10th in total federal obligations for science and engineering research and development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Is Ranked Among the Top 10 U.S. University Recipients of Federal Research and Development Obligations&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranked in the top 25 of all universities in the world for the impact and performance of its scientific public publications, including in the top ten for clinical medicine, according to the Performance Ranking of Scientific Papers for World Universities produced by the Higher Education Evaluation and Accreditation Council of Taiwan.&lt;ref name=&quot;HEEACT&quot;/&gt; Pitt is also ranked 29th in the world based on Essential Science Indicators according to the Research Center for Chinese Science Evaluation of [[Wuhan University]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wuhan&quot;/&gt; Pitt places much emphasis on undergraduate research and has integrated such research experience as a key component of its undergraduate experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;undergrad-research&quot;/&gt;

Pitt is a major center of biomedical research; in FY 2008, it ranked fifth in the nation in competitive peer-reviewed [[NIH]] funding allocations,&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Chancellor&quot;/&gt; and the [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center]] ranked 13th among hospitals nationwide by ''USNews'' in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;UT UPMC HonorRoll&quot;/&gt;

=== Collaboration with Carnegie Mellon University ===
Pitt neighbors the campus of [[Carnegie Mellon University]] (CMU), and in some cases, buildings of the two universities are intermingled. This helps to facilitate a myriad of academic and research collaborations between the two schools, including such projects as the [[Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center]], the [[Pittsburgh Life Sciences Greenhouse]], the Immune Modeling Center, the Center for the Neural Basis of Cognition, the [[University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute]], as well as the National Science Foundation-supported Pittsburgh Science of Learning Center.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pitt.edu/~oafa/community.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.learnlab.org/|title=Welcome|publisher=Pittsburgh Science of Learning Center|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, the universities also offer multiple dual and joint degree programs such as the [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine#MD/PhD Program|Medical Scientist Training Program]], the Molecular Biophysics and Structural Biology Graduate Program, and the Law and Business Administration program. Some professors hold joint professorships between the two schools, and students at each university may take classes at the other (with appropriate approvals).&lt;ref name=&quot;PCHE Cross Registration&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pchepa.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=14&amp;Itemid=29|title=Cross Registration |publisher=Pittsburgh Council on Higher Education|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pitt students and faculty also have access to the CMU library system, as well as the [[Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh]], through the Oakland Library Consortium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | url=http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1300/J121v07n01_06?journalCode=wrsi20#preview | title=Models of Access: The Oakland Library Consortium | first=Sylverna | last=Ford | year=1992 | publisher=The Haworth Press, Inc. | journal=Resource SHaring and Information Networks | volume=7 |number=1 | pages=67-80 | doi=10.1300/J121v07n01_06 | accessdate=2011-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two universities also co-host academic conferences, such as the 2012 Second Language Research Forum.&lt;ref name=&quot;SLRF 2012&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ml.hss.cmu.edu/slrf2012/|title=SLRF 2012 in Pittsburgh|publisher=SLRF 2012 Organizing Committee|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community==
[[Image:Eberlyhallside.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Eberly Hall]]]]
Pitt was ranked second overall, and the top public university in the nation, as a &quot;Best Neighbor&quot; for positive impact on its urban community, including both commercial and residential activities such as revitalization, cultural renewal, economics, and community service and development according to the 2009  &quot;Saviors of Our Cities&quot; ranking.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saviors of Our Cities: 2009 Survey of College &amp; University Civic Partnerships&quot;/&gt; Pitt was also listed as a &quot;best neighbor&quot; in the previous ranking released in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;CMU, Pitt rate as good neighbors&quot;/&gt; These rankings reflect the statistics that each year Pitt spends more than $1.7&amp;nbsp;billion in the community and supports nearly 33,800&amp;nbsp;jobs in [[Allegheny County]]. Pitt's research program alone imports more than $642&amp;nbsp;million into the region each year (more than $3.60 for each $1 of state appropriations), and supports some 23,100 local jobs.&lt;ref name=&quot;harvith&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg Issues a University Update on the Economy and Our Community&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The 2008 Report of Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg&quot;/&gt; Pitt students also spend more than $213&amp;nbsp;million on goods, services, and rental payments within the local economy.&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;/&gt; Pitt ranked sixth in the number of startups spawned by technologies developed by its researchers according to [[Association of University Technology Managers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AUTM U.S. Licensing Survey, FY 2004: A Survey Summary of Technology Licensing (and Related) Performance for U.S. Academic and Nonprofit Institutions, and Technology Investment firms&quot;/&gt;

Pitt and its [[University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine|medical school]] are closely affiliated with the [[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center]]. With over 50,000 employees and more than $7&amp;nbsp;billion in annual revenue, the Medical Center is the largest employer in Western Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;UPMC Community Benefits Report Fiscal Year 2008: Strengthening the Fabric of a Community&quot;/&gt;

Through the Pitt Volunteer Pool, faculty and staff members donate more than 10,000 hours annually to community service projects for agencies such as the Salvation Army, Pittsburgh AIDS Task Force, and Greater Pittsburgh Community Food Bank.

Pitt also is a leading producer of [[Peace Corps]] volunteers.&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;University ranks high in Peace Corps volunteers&quot;/&gt;  According to the Peace Corps' 2008 ranking of colleges and universities, only 14&amp;nbsp;schools in the nation produced more Peace Corp volunteers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peace Corps Top Colleges and Universities 2008&quot;/&gt;  Pitt's graduate school also ranked 10th for most alumni Peace Corps volunteers.&lt;ref name=&quot;webster&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

==Athletics==
{{Main|Pittsburgh Panthers}}
[[File:Heinz Field.jpg|thumb|[[Heinz Field]], home of [[Pittsburgh Panthers football|Pitt football]]]]

The University of Pittsburgh's sponsors 19 [[varsity team|varsity]] sports teams, called the &quot;[[Pittsburgh Panthers]]&quot; or &quot;Pitt Panthers,&quot; that participate at the highest level of competitive [[college athletics|collegiate athletics]] in the United States, [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division&amp;nbsp;I ([[Football Bowl Subdivision|Division I FBS]] for [[american football|football]]). The varsity teams compete as members of the [[Big East Conference]], [[Eastern Wrestling League]], [[East Atlantic Gymnastics League]], and [[Eastern College Athletic Conference]]. There are also approximate 30 additional athletic teams that compete at the non-varsity club sports level.

Pitt’s highest-profile athletic programs, [[Pittsburgh Panthers football|American football]] and [[Pittsburgh Panthers men's basketball|men’s basketball]], are consistently competitive. Pitt has been regularly ranked as having one of the best combinations of football and basketball programs by multiple sports media outlets,&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 Hoops &amp; Helmets Rankings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Best of both: BCS era combined standings&quot;/&gt; including [[CBSSports.com|CBS Sports]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Flourishing Five No. 5: Resurgent Pitt football doing its part&quot;/&gt; [[ESPN]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ESPN.com&quot;/&gt; and ''[[Sports Illustrated]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;All-Sport Rankings&quot;/&gt;

On September 18, 2011, it was announced that the [[Atlantic Coast Conference]] had officially extended an invitation to Pittsburgh to join the ACC after approving the university's application.  No specific date for the Panthers' official membership has been set at this time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACC&quot;/&gt;

===Scholar athletes===
During 2006–2007 school year, of approximately 450 Pitt student athletes, 311 had term grade point averages exceeding 3.0, 23 had a perfect average of 4.0, and 124 were named Big East Academic All-Stars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scholar Athletes&quot;/&gt;

===Football===
{{Main|Pittsburgh Panthers football}}

Traditionally the most popular sport at the University of Pittsburgh, [[Pittsburgh Panthers football|football]] has been played at the highest levels at the University since 1890. During the more than 100 years of competitive football at Pitt, the University has helped pioneer the sport by, among other things, instituting the use of numbers on jerseys&lt;ref name=&quot;Hail to Pitt: A Sports History of the University of Pittsburgh&quot;/&gt; and desegregating the [[Sugar Bowl]]. Some of college football's all-time greatest coaches and players have plied their trade at Pitt, including [[Glenn Scobey Warner|Pop Warner]], [[Jock Sutherland]], [[Marshall Goldberg]], [[Joe Schmidt]], [[Mike Ditka]], [[Tony Dorsett]], [[Hugh Green (American football)|Hugh Green]], [[Mark May]], [[Dan Marino]], [[Bill Fralic]], [[Curtis Martin]], [[Darrelle Revis]], [[Russ Grimm]] and [[Larry Fitzgerald]]. Among the top schools in terms of all-time wins, Pitt teams have claimed nine [[Pittsburgh Panthers football#National Championships|National Championships]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Athletics&quot;/&gt; and boast 86&amp;nbsp;players that have been chosen as first-team All-Americans.

===Basketball===
[[File:2009PittUConn2ndmin.jpg|thumb|left|[[Pittsburgh Panthers men's basketball|Pitt basketball]] in the [[Petersen Events Center]]]]
{{Main|Pittsburgh Panthers men's basketball|Pittsburgh Panthers women's basketball}}

Pitt first sponsored varsity [[Pittsburgh Panthers men's basketball|men's basketball]] in 1905 and became an early national power after winning two Helms Foundation National Championships in 1927–28 and 1929–30.  Those teams, coached by the innovative and legendary [[Naismith Basketball Hall of Fame|Naismith Hall of Fame]] inductee [[Clifford Carlson|&quot;Doc&quot; Carlson]], were led by National Player of the Year and Hall of Famer [[Chuck Hyatt|Charlie Hyatt]]. Following a [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|Final Four]] appearance in 1941, Pitt appeared in a handful of NCAA tournaments throughout the 50, 60s, and 70s, including an Elite Eight appearance in 1974 led by All-American [[Billy Knight]]. Pitt joined the Big East Conference in 1982, and by the end of the decade had secured a pair of Big East regular season championships led by All-Americans [[Charles D. Smith|Charles Smith]] and [[Jerome Lane]].  In the 2000s, led by coach [[Jamie Dixon]], an era of consistent national and conference competitiveness has been achieved, including reaching the number one ranking in various national polls.  Since 2002, Pitt has appeared in nine straight NCAA tournament appearances advancing to five Sweet Sixteens and an Elite Eight. During this time, Pitt and has won three Big East regular season championships, two Big East Tournament Championships, and has advanced to six Big East Tournament Championship games.

The [[Pittsburgh Panthers women's basketball|Pittsburgh Panthers women's varsity basketball program]] started during the 1914–1915 school year and lasted until 1927 before going on hiatus until 1970. Pitt's women's team has posted several NCAA, NWIT, and EAIAW tournament appearances. Led head coach [[Agnus Berenato]], Pitt has played in post-season tournaments each of the last five seasons, including three [[NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA Tournaments]] appearances where it advanced to the Sweet Sixteen in 2008 and 2009.

===Olympic sports===
[[File:Pittsburgh Panthers Alternate Logo.svg|thumb|150px|thumb|The current Panther logo is a stylized panther head introduced in 1997 designed to suggest that it was cut by a welding torch from steel.]]
{{See also|Pittsburgh Panthers baseball|Pittsburgh Panthers volleyball|Pittsburgh Panthers wrestling}}

Pitt has had a long history of success in other intercollegiate athletic events.  In [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Track and Field|Track and Field]], Pitt has produced several Olympic and NCAA champions such as 800 m Olympic gold medalist [[John Woodruff]], two-time 110&amp;nbsp;m hurdle Olympic gold medalist [[Roger Kingdom]], and seven-time NCAA champion and 2005 World Champion [[triple jump]]er [[Trecia Smith|Trecia-Kaye Smith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cstv&quot;/&gt; The [[Pittsburgh Panthers wrestling|wrestling program]] has a rich history and is among the leaders in producing individual national champions with 16.&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT Wrestling Media Guide 2006–2007&quot;/&gt; Pitt's [[Pittsburgh Panthers volleyball|women's volleyball]] team, one of the winningest program in the nation,&lt;ref name=&quot;Volleyball Releases 2007 Schedule&quot;/&gt; has won 11&amp;nbsp;[[Big East Conference|Big East]] championships, and appeared in 11&amp;nbsp;NCAA tournaments since the program began in 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;2006 Pitt Volleyball Media Guide&quot;/&gt; Pitt's [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Swimming and Diving|swimming and diving teams]] have produced several Olympians and won 19 men's and nine women's Big East Championships since joining the conference in 1983. Pitt [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Gymnastics|women's gymnastics]] is a regular qualifier for the NCAA Northeast Regional Championship.&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT Gymnastics Media Guide 2007&quot;/&gt; [[Pittsburgh Panthers baseball|Baseball]], Pitt's oldest varsity sport, has produced several major league players and has become a regular participant in the Big East post-season championship.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Baseball Media Guide 2006&quot;/&gt;  Other varsity sports have also found varying degrees of success and include [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Cross Country|cross country]], soccer, [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Softball|softball]], and [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Tennis|tennis]].

===Support groups===
The history-rich [[University of Pittsburgh Varsity Marching Band]] was founded in 1911 and performs at athletic and other events. The [[Pittsburgh Panthers#Pitt Cheerleaders and Dance Team|Pitt cheerleading squad]] has won multiple [[cheerleading]] national championships, including three straight from 1992–1994. The Pitt dance team also has been competitive in national competitions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spirit Groups&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cheer and Dance Finish in Top 20 in Respective Competitions&quot;/&gt;

==People==

===Heads of the University===
[[Image:HollandPitt.jpg|thumb|upright|[[William Jacob Holland]] served as Chancellor from 1891 to 1901, and was also a world renowned entomologist.]]
{{Main|University of Pittsburgh History#Heads of the University of Pittsburgh|l1=Heads of the University of Pittsburgh}}

The University of Pittsburgh has had many individuals lead it throughout its history. During the academy days, the title of Principal was worn by the head of the school. Due to fires, early records are incomplete. When Pittsburgh Academy transitioned into the Western University, the title was changed to Chancellor.  This title has lasted except for a brief change during Wesley Posvar's administration when it was transiently switched to President.  Samuel McCormick oversaw the name change from the Western University of Pennsylvania to the University of Pittsburgh in 1908 and is therefore listed with the chancellors of the University of Pittsburgh. Acting chancellors are also included in the list below. For more information on past heads of the University, and for photos, please see [[University of Pittsburgh History#Heads of the University of Pittsburgh|Pitt History: Heads of the University]].

===Notable alumni and faculty===
{{Main|List of notable University of Pittsburgh people}}
Alumni have won awards and prizes that include the [[Academy Award]], the [[Super Bowl]], the Nobel Prize, the [[Pulitzer Prize]], the [[National Medal of Arts]], the [[National Medal of Science]], the [[Perkin Medal]], the [[National Medal of Technology]], and the [[MacArthur Fellows Program|MacArthur &quot;Genius Award&quot;]].&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;armanlos&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Legacy Gallery&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Strictly Bill&quot;/&gt;  The faculty and alumni have been pioneers in such fields as [[John Brashear|astronomy]], [[Samuel Pierpont Langley|aviation]], [[Jonas Salk|virology]], [[John Wistar Simpson|nuclear energy]], [[Benjamin Spock|psychology]], [[Herbert Boyer|genetics]] in addition to being given  popular titles such as the [[Reginald Fessenden|Father of Radio Broadcasting]], the [[Vladimir Zworykin|Father of Television]], the [[Peter Safar|Father of CPR]], the [[Paul Lauterbur|Father of the MRI]], and the [[Thomas Starzl|Father of Organ Transplantation]].

{|style=&quot;margin: 1em auto 1em auto&quot;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Wangari Maathai portrait by Martin Rowe.jpg|&lt;center&gt;[[Wangari Maathai]]&lt;br&gt;2004 [[Nobel Peace Prize]]&lt;/center&gt;
File:Gene Kelly in Take Me Out to the Ball Game trailer.jpg|&lt;center&gt;[[Gene Kelly]]&lt;br&gt;[[Academy Award]] Winner&lt;/center&gt;
Image:Chabonsigning.jpg|&lt;center&gt;[[Michael Chabon]]&lt;br&gt;2001 [[Pulitzer Prize]] Winner&lt;/center&gt;
Image:Orrin Hatch, official 110th Congress photo.jpg|&lt;center&gt; [[Orrin Hatch]]&lt;br&gt;[[United States Senator|US Senator]]&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|}

==Student life==

===Traditions===
:''See also: [[Hail to Pitt]], [[Pitt Victory Song]], [[University of Pittsburgh Alma Mater]], [[Pittsburgh Panthers football#Traditions|Pitt football traditions]]''

'''Annual Bonfire and Pep Rally''' hosted by the Pitt Program Council is held prior to or during some football games. Held on the lawn of the [[Cathedral of Learning]], it often involves the band, cheerleaders, football team, visiting dignitaries, and giveaways.&lt;ref name=&quot;Turning up the heat&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt traditions&quot;/&gt;

[[File:PittProgramCouncilFallFest2008.jpg|thumb|A concert during Fall Fest 2008]]
'''Bigelow Bash''' is a spring festival held by the Pitt Program Council between the [[William Pitt Union]] and the [[Cathedral of Learning]], involving a range of activities, novelties, and bands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bigelow Bash features Queens of the Stone Age and a friendly monkey&quot;/&gt;

'''E-Week''' is a spring celebration organized by the Engineer Student Council for a week-long, fun-filled series of activities and competitions to demonstrate engineering skills and foster a spirit of camaraderie. Activities include games such as Monopoly, Ingenuity, Jeopardy, Assassins, and include a talent show, relay race, mini-Olympics, and blood drive. The festivities reach climax with a parade on Friday, a soapbox derby on Saturday, and the &quot;e-ball finale&quot; on Saturday evening. Each year, a unique theme is chosen. Each engineering department competes against the others, while some smaller departments join forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;E-Week's 50th Anniversary&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt's School of Engineering Holds 50th Annual E-Week March 18–26: Pittopoly, Duct Tape Challenge, and Soap Box Derby part of this year's festivities&quot;/&gt;

'''Fall Fest''' is an annual fall festival held by the Pitt Program Council between the [[William Pitt Union]] and the [[Cathedral of Learning]], also involving a range of activities, novelties, and bands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Students celebrate Fall Fest&quot;/&gt;

'''Football Tunnel''' is a tradition where student organizations, carrying [[heraldic flag|standards]], form a tunnel for the football players to run through as the enter the football field from the locker room.  Originally, this long standing tradition involved only Pitt [[fraternities and sororities]].  The tradition was briefly lost following the 1999 season when Pitt's football program transitioned from playing in [[Pitt Stadium]] to [[Three Rivers Stadium]] in 2000 followed by [[Heinz Field]] in 2001.  The tradition was resurrected beginning with the 2008 football season.&lt;ref name=&quot;cstv5&quot;/&gt;

'''Forbes Field Home Plate Slide''' is a tradition for good luck on midterm and finals in which students slide into or step on a former home plate from [[Forbes Field]], where the Pittsburgh Pirates played for many seasons. The plate is on display inside [[Wesley W. Posvar Hall|Posvar Hall]] near its original location.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus tour map&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;''University of Pittsburgh'' (''Off the Record'')&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh6&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wojcichowski&quot;/&gt;

'''Greek Week''' Greek Week is a year long initiative for the Greek organizations on campus to raise money for different charitable organizations through different events.  The two biggest events each year are the Pitt Dance Marathon and Greek Sing.  The Pitt Greeks have signed a contract with the [[University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute]] to raise $500,000 over the next five years. Yearlong fundraising activities are also held to support other charitable organizations such as the [[Ronald McDonald House]], [[Make a Wish Foundation]], and the Pittsburgh Food Bank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Greekweek&quot;/&gt;

'''Homecoming''', as in other universities, revolves around one home football game each year. Pitt's homecoming involves activities hosted by the Pitt Program Council highlighted by fireworks and a laser-light display between the [[William Pitt Union]] and the [[Cathedral of Learning]].&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube&quot;/&gt; This is followed by Casino Night in the union, the football game, and a homecoming cruise on a [[Gateway Clipper Fleet|Gateway Clipper Party Liner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming 2007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming events include fireworks, lasers&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt's homecoming history long, filled with memories&quot;/&gt;

'''Honors Convocation''' is a ceremony whose modern incarnation was begun in 1977, but whose roots date to the 1930s' Scholar's Day and Tap Day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Documenting Pitt: Honors Convocation Programs&quot;/&gt; The Honors Convocation is typically held in late winter to present awards and recognition for academic and service achievements of the students, faculty, alumni, and staff throughout the schools and departments of the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;Honors Convocation&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:HeinzChapelfromBalcony.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Interior of [[Heinz Memorial Chapel]]]]
'''Lantern Night''' is an annual ceremony, initiated in 1921 one of the University’s longest standing traditions. It is a formal induction for freshman women to university life and unites them as they begin their education at Pitt. Traditionally held on the evening before the first day of classes, the ceremony today takes place in [[Heinz Memorial Chapel|Heinz Chapel]]. Part of the Lantern Night tradition is for a distinguished alumna to give the freshman address, while other distinguished alumnae are flame bearers who light the lanterns given to each freshman woman as a keepsake.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rites of Passage&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lanternpanther&quot;/&gt;

'''Omicron Delta Kappa Walk''' is a stone walkway between the [[Cathedral of Learning]] and [[Heinz Memorial Chapel]] that contains the engraved names of Pitt's [[Omicron Delta Kappa]] Senior of the Year award winners. The walk is the only one of its kind in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Senior Greg Heller-LaBelle Named 2006 Omicron Delta Kappa Senior of the Year&quot;/&gt;

'''Panther Sendoff''' is an annual free reception typically held in [[Alumni Hall (University of Pittsburgh)|Alumni Hall]] to congratulate each year's graduating class and wish them well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Student Traditions&quot;/&gt;

'''Rubbing the Panther Nose''' is as another good luck tradition in which students rub the nose of the [[Panthers of Pittsburgh#Millennium Panther|Millennium Panther]] outside the [[William Pitt Union]] prior to exams.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Alumn Association: Traditions: When You Wish Upon a Panther&quot;/&gt; This tradition has further grown into one that is used by the wider university community when seeking general good fortune and was featured in a national television advertisement for the 2012 [[Hyundai Tucson]] automobile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xTzasfzgxqg&amp;feature=relmfu | title=2012 Hyundai Tuscon: &quot;Nose Rub&quot; | medium=Television commercial | publisher=HyundaiUSA | date=September 30, 2011 | accessdate=October 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''University of Pittsburgh Annual Jazz Seminar and Concert''' is a fall lecture and concert series founded by [[Nathan Davis (saxophonist)|Dr. Nathan Davis]], professor in the Music Department, and University officials in 1970. Renowned jazz musicians, critics, and historians lead seminar sessions for students and others in the local jazz community. These sessions are free and open to the public and deal with topics ranging from entering the music business to practice techniques, composing, arranging, and individual instrument mastery. Previous musicians who have attending include [[Dizzy Gillespie]], [[Kenny Clarke]], [[Sonny Rollins]], [[Dexter Gordon]], and [[Max Roach]].&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar &amp; Concert&quot;/&gt;

[[File:PittVarsityWalk.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Varsity Walk]]
'''Varsity Walk''' is a walkway between the [[Cathedral of Learning]] and [[Heinz Memorial Chapel]] on which is carved the names of former Pitt athletes (each year since 1950) who have promoted the University through their athletic (Panther Award) or academic (Blue-Gold Award) achievements.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Varsity Walk&quot;/&gt;

'''Victory Lights''' is a tradition where golden flood lights illuminate the top of the Cathedral of Learning after every football victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt traditions&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pittnews&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets of the Cathedral: Starting at the top&quot;/&gt;

===Pitt Arts===
'''Pitt Arts''' is a program founded by the University in 1997 to encourage students to explore and connect to the art and cultural opportunities of the City of Pittsburgh via three programs. ''Art Encounters'' provides trips to arts events for undergrads that include free tickets, transportation, a catered reception, and encounters with international artists and thinkers. ''Free Visits'' grants undergrad and grad students free admission using their Pitt IDs to the [[Carnegie Museums of Pittsburgh|Carnegie Museum of Art]], [[Carnegie Museums of Pittsburgh|Carnegie Museum of Natural History]], [[Heinz History Center|Senator John Heinz History Center]], [[Phipps Conservatory &amp; Botanical Gardens|Phipps Conservatory]], [[Mattress Factory]], and the [[Carnegie Museums of Pittsburgh|Andy Warhol Museum]]. ''Cheap Seats'' is a program that everyone at Pitt can use to take advantage of deeply-discounted tickets to the most sought-after arts events in the area, including the Pittsburgh [[Pittsburgh Ballet Theatre|ballet]], [[Pittsburgh Opera|opera]], [[Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra|symphony]], theater, concerts, and other [[Cultural District, Pittsburgh|cultural district]] activities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt arts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT ARTS Reaches More Than 32,000 Participants This Year&quot;/&gt;

===Student theater===
[[Image:StephenfosterDoors.jpg|thumb|left|Pitt's [[Stephen Foster Memorial]] contains two theaters.]]
* '''[[University of Pittsburgh Repertory Theatre]]''', or Pitt Rep, is the production company of the Department of Theatre Arts which puts public student performances of classic masterpieces, contemporary productions, and student-directed labs.  It also runs the Shakespeare-in-the-Schools which tours classic theater for K-12 students throughout the Pittsburgh area.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts&quot;/&gt;
* '''[[Friday Nite Improvs]]''', Pittsburgh's longest-running theatre show, was started in 1989 by graduate theatre students. It takes place weekly inside the [[Cathedral of Learning]]'s studio theatre.
* '''[[Kuntu Repertory Theatre]]''', founded in 1974, is the second-oldest African American performing arts organization affiliated with a major research university. It promotes and encourages participation in theater arts centered on the African heritage and experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuntu Repertory Theatre&quot;/&gt;
* The '''Redeye Theatre Project''' is a festival of one-act plays cast, written, and rehearsed in 24 hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redeye Theatre Project&quot;/&gt;
* '''Pitt Musical Theater Club''' provides undergraduates the opportunity to perform in student directed variety shows and musicals.  The club was founded in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Musical Theater Club&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

===Student music===
[[Image:MusicbuildPitt.jpg|thumb|upright|The [[Music Building (University of Pittsburgh)|Music Building]] once served as home to the original studio for ''[[Mr. Rogers' Neighborhood]]'']]
*'''Pitt Men's Glee Club''', founded in 1890, is the oldest extracurricular club on campus.  The internationally showcased&lt;ref name=&quot;PMGC in Bologna- Beatus Vir&quot;/&gt; club includes both undergraduate and graduate students from throughout the University. Traditionally, the Glee Club has sung for a variety of campus-wide and community functions, including graduations, receptions, alumni gatherings, sporting events, and chancellor's events. The Glee Club has also participated in national Collegiate Men's Choir festivals and international music festivals aside from seasonal concerts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Men's Glee Club&quot;/&gt;

*'''[[Heinz Chapel Choir]]''' is an accomplished and internationally-known&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinz Chapel choir program&quot;/&gt; ''a cappella'' choir consisting entirely of Pitt students that has been performing for over 70 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinz Chapel Choir&quot;/&gt;

*'''University of Pittsburgh Women's Choral Ensemble''', founded in 1927, is open to all women of the University including undergraduates, graduate students, and staff. The ensemble leads the traditional lamplighter processional each fall and performs repertory ranging from traditional sacred and secular classics to international folk songs, popular music, and show tunes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: Women's Choral Ensemble&quot;/&gt;

*'''University of Pittsburgh Orchestra''' performs several concerts and consists of music students, students from the University at large, faculty, staff, and members of the metropolitan community.  The orchestra performs not only works of the standard art music literature, but also new works of student composers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: The University Orchestra&quot;/&gt;

*'''Pitt Jazz Ensemble''', founded in 1969, has been recognized internationally{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} as one of the best collegiate jazz groups{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}. Under the direction of [[Nathan Davis (saxophonist)|Dr. Davis]], the ensemble has performed around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh Jazz Ensemble&quot;/&gt;

*'''Pitt African Music and Dance Ensemble''', founded in 1983 by a Ghanaian ethnomusicologist Dr. Willie O. Anku, specializes in music and dances from Africa. Under the direction of J. S. Kofi Gbolonyo, it presents a range of African artistic expressions including music, dance, drama and visual arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: African Music and dance&quot;/&gt;

*'''[[Pitt Band]]''', founded in 1911, is the varsity marching band of the University of Pittsburgh and performs at various athletic and other University events.

*'''Pitt Pendulums''', founded in 1996, is a co-ed a cappella group. The group performs at a variety of on- and off- campus events, including tours of the United States and Canada.  The Pendulums are annual competitors in the [[International Championship of Collegiate A Cappella]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pittsburgh Pendulums: History&quot;/&gt; and were most recently featured on [[WQED (TV)|WQED]]'s [http://www.wqed.org/ondemand/onq.php?cat=3&amp;id=488 OnQ].&lt;ref name=&quot;WQED OnQ OnDemand: The Pitt Pendulums&quot;/&gt;

*'''Sounds of Pleasure''', founded in 1997, is an all-female a cappella group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sounds of Pleasure&quot;/&gt;

*'''VoKols''', founded in 2006, is a co-ed a cappella group that sings a combination of American and Hebrew pop music.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillel JUC- VoKols: History of the VoKols&quot;/&gt;

*'''Carpathian Ensemble''', founded within the Department of music in 2008, the ensemble performs [[Romani music|Gypsy]], [[Klezmer]], [[Music of Armenia|Armenian]], [[Music of Moldova|Moldavian]], [[Music of Ukraine|Ukrainian]], and [[Music of the Republic of Macedonia|Macedonian]] music.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.music.pitt.edu/carpathian | title=Department of Music: Carpathian Ensemble | publisher=University of Pittsburgh | accessdate=2011-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

===Student media===
[[Image:Wesley Wentz Posvar Hall.JPG|thumb|left|upright|[[Wesley W. Posvar Hall]]]]
* '''[[WPTS-FM]]''' is a non-commercial radio station owned by the University of Pittsburgh, and offers a mix of student-run programming. The station operates at 92.1 [[Megahertz|MHz]] with an [[Effective radiated power|ERP]] of 16 watts, and is licensed to Pittsburgh.
* '''''[[JURIST]]''''' is the world's only law-school-based, comprehensive, legal news and research service staffed by a mostly-volunteer team of part-time law student reporters, editors and Web developers. It is led by law professor Bernard Hibbitts at the [[University of Pittsburgh School of Law]].
* '''''[[The Pitt News]]''''' is an independent, student-written, and student-managed newspaper for the University's Oakland (main) campus. Founded in 1908, it is now published Monday through Friday during the school year and Wednesdays during the summer. It circulates 14,000 copies for each issue published.
* '''[[UPTV (University of Pittsburgh Television)]]''' is a student-managed, student-produced, closed-circuit television station. As of June 2006, only students living in campus residence halls or university operated-housing can view programming.
* '''''[[Three Rivers Review]]''''' and '''''Collision''''' are two undergraduate, bi-annual, literary journals publishing both poetry and prose.
* '''''[[Pittsburgh Undergraduate Review|The Pittsburgh Undergraduate Review]]''''' is a multidisciplinary journal showcasing undergraduate research.
* '''''Pitt Political Review''''' is a student-created, student-written publication of the University Honors College. PPR, as it is called, provides a venue for serious discussion of politics and policy issues in a nonpartisan way.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Political Review&quot;/&gt;
* '''''[[The Original Magazine]]''''' is a nonprofit, semiannual arts and culture publication based at, and partially funded by, the University of Pittsburgh, that aims to both bring and publicize accessible art and creative writing to Pittsburgh.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Original&quot;/&gt;
{{-}}

===Student organizations===
[[Image:AlumniHallatPitt.jpg|thumb|right|[[Alumni Hall (University of Pittsburgh)|Alumni Hall]]]]
There are over 350 student clubs and organizations at the University of Pittsburgh all sizes and covering all manner of interests.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Freshman Prospectus&quot;/&gt; Some of the larger ones include the following, presented in alphabetical order.

'''Black Action Society''' is the recognized student organization for promoting the cultural, educational, political, and social needs of black students at the university. It comprises nine committees including the publication of the student-run publication ''BlackLine'' as well as community outreach, political action, and programing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Constitution&quot;/&gt; In the past the BAS has hosted lectures by such figures as [[Cornel West]], [[Spike Lee]], and [[Carol Mosley-Braun]].

'''Blue and Gold Society''', founded in 1991, is a group of undergraduate student leaders chosen as liaisons between the student community and the Pitt Alumni Association.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blue and Gold Society&quot;/&gt;

'''Graduate and Professional Student Assembly (GPSA)''' is the student government that represents the interests of all graduate and professional student at the University of Pittsburgh and serves as the umbrella organization for all of the graduate/professional school student governments. GPSA's mission is to ensure that the concerns of these students are heard and also provides services and programs such travel grants, legal and financial consulting, and social functions.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Graduate and Professional Student Association&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:TowersfromPosvar.jpg|thumb|left|upright|[[Litchfield Towers]] and [[David Lawrence Hall]] (right)]]
'''Student Government Board (SGB)''' is the governing body that provides undergraduate students with representation to the university administration, presenting their needs, interests, and concerns. Another important aspect of the SGB is allocation of the student activities fee, which provides money to over 350 student organizations at the University of Pittsburgh. The SGB also has ten standing committees who address various aspects of campus life, including diversity, freshman involvement, and governmental relations.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Student Government Board&quot;/&gt;

'''[[Oakland Zoo (cheering section)|Oakland Zoo]]''' is the student athletic cheering section, and is an officially recognized student club by the University of Pittsburgh.  At over 2,000 members, it is the largest such group at the University.  The group helps participate with the Athletic Department and Pitt Student Government Board in setting student ticket policy as well as organizing special student events.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oakland Zoo Club&quot;/&gt;

'''Pitt Pathfinders''' is a student-run organization that hosts campus tours, assists prospective students in making well-informed college-related decisions, and promotes Pitt pride.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Pathfinders&quot;/&gt;

'''Pitt Program Council''' is the all-campus programming organization at the university.  Comprising eight student committees, a variety of programs and festivities are planned and sponsored including Fall Fest, Bigelow Bash, Homecoming Laser and Fireworks
Show, as well as trips to New York City, Cedar Point, Spring break in Panama City Beach, FL. Other activities include art gallery exhibits, films, horseback riding, sports tournaments, lectures, fitness and dance classes, and Black and White Ball.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Program Council&quot;/&gt;

'''Quo Vadis''' is a student organization that conducts guided tours and interpretations of the [[Cathedral of Learning|Cathedral of Learning's]] 27 [[Nationality Rooms]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Quo Vadis&quot;/&gt;

'''Rainbow Alliance''' is a student advocacy group for Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender, Queer, and Allied students. Among other activities, Pitt Rainbow Alliance holds an Annual Drag Show to raise money for Pittsburgh AIDS Task Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rainbow Alliance&quot;/&gt;

'''Telefact''' is an informational telephone service run by students that researches and answers callers' questions. The service is free to use and can be reached at 412–624-FACT.

'''University of Pittsburgh Mock Trial''' is a year long extracurricular activity open to Pitt undergraduates that provides an opportunity to learn about the practice of litigation through a series of team-based [[mock trial]] competitions. Pitt Mock Trial has qualified for American Mock Trial Association post-season tournaments each of the last six years, finishing in the fifth overall place at the 2008 National Championship Tournament.&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Mock Trial&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Mock Trial Team Places Fifth in American Mock Trial Association National Competition&quot;/&gt;

'''[[William Pitt Debating Union]]''' is a co-curricular program and hub for a wide range of debating activities, including intercollegiate policy debate, public debate, and debate outreach. 1981 [[National Debate Tournament]] champions,&lt;ref name=&quot;Results from Previous National Debate Tournament, 1977-1986&quot;/&gt; it has qualified for the National Debate Tournament forty times&lt;ref name=&quot;National Debate Tournament Participating Schools, 1947–2006&quot;/&gt; and is one of the oldest organizations of its kind in the nation, growing from the University’s Division of Public Speaking in 1912.&lt;ref name=&quot;William Pitt Debating Union&quot;/&gt;

===Greek life===
As of 2008, the University of Pittsburgh [[Greek system]] raised $285,000 for the [[University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute]].  The effort is part of the Pittsburgh Greek system's five-year pledge to raise $500,000 for the cancer center.&lt;ref name=&quot;Greekweek&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!colspan=2|Fraternities
!colspan=2|Sororities
|-
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]]
* [[Delta Chi]]
* [[Delta Phi]]
* [[Delta Tau Delta]]
* [[Iota Nu Delta]]
* [[Kappa Sigma]]
* [[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
* [[Phi Delta Theta]]
* [[Pi Kappa Alpha]]
* [[Pi Kappa Phi]] Colony
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Phi Kappa Theta]]
* [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]]
* [[Sigma Alpha Mu]]
* [[Sigma Beta Rho]]
* [[Sigma Chi]]
* [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
* [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]
* [[Triangle]]
* [[Zeta Beta Tau]]

|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Alpha Delta Pi]]
* [[Alpha Epsilon Phi]]
* [[Chi Omega]]
* [[Delta Delta Delta]]
* [[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]]
* [[Delta Zeta]]
* [[Kappa Delta]]
|  style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:smaller;&quot;|
* [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]]
* [[Sigma Delta Tau]]
* [[Sigma Sigma Sigma]]
* [[Theta Phi Alpha]]
* [[Theta Nu Xi]]
* [[Zeta Sigma Chi]]
|}

==Regional campuses==
Regional campuses offer Master's, Bachelor's, and [[Associate's degree|Associate's]] degrees at four locations in [[Western Pennsylvania]]. They also allow students to take preliminary courses and relocate to other regional campuses or the Oakland campus to complete their degrees. They offer several degrees and certificates:
* [[University of Pittsburgh at Bradford]] – Master's, Bachelor's, Associate's and Certificate
* [[University of Pittsburgh (Greensburg)|University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg]] – Master's, Bachelor's and Certificate
* [[University of Pittsburgh at Johnstown]] – Bachelor's and Certificate
* [[University of Pittsburgh at Titusville]] – Bachelor's in Business Management and Arts in Human Relations, Associate's and Certificate

==References and notes==
[[File:Cathedral of Learning stitch 1.jpg||right|thumb|upright|[[Cathedral of Learning]]]]
[[File:Pitthomecoming2010CommonsR.jpg|right|thumb|upright|Cathedral [[Cathedral of Learning#Commons Room|Commons Room]] during Homecoming]]
[[Image:FrickFineArtsCourtyard.jpg|thumb|upright|View from the cloister in the [[Frick Fine Arts Building]]]]
[[File:HillmanLibUnivPitt.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Hillman Library]]]]
[[Image:AustrianRoom.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Nationality Rooms#Austrian|Austrian]] [[Nationality Rooms|Nationality Room]]]]
[[Image:ArmenianRoom.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Nationality Rooms#Armenian|Armenian]] [[Nationality Rooms|Nationality Room]]]]
[[File:UkrainRoom2.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Nationality Rooms#Ukrainian|Ukrainian]] [[Nationality Rooms|Nationality Room]]]]
[[File:HungarianRoom.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Nationality Rooms#Hungarian|Hungarian]] [[Nationality Rooms|Nationality Room]]]]
[[Image:FrickFineArtsLibrary.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Frick Fine Arts Building|Frick Fine Arts]] Library]]
[[Image:SchenleyQuadcolumn.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Schenley Quadrangle]]]]
[[File:Schenley Fountain.JPG|thumb|upright|[[Mary Schenley Memorial Fountain]] in front of the [[Frick Fine Arts Building]]]]
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;''University of Pittsburgh'' (''Off the Record'')&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=VLU2z9ic3n0C&amp;pg=PA6&amp;lpg=PA6&amp;dq=university+of+pittsburgh+forbes+home+plate+exams+good+luck|title=''University of Pittsburgh'' (''Off the Record'')|last=Cruttenden|first=Jamie|date=October 1, 2005|page=6|publisher=[[College Prowler]]|accessdate=April 29, 2008|isbn=9781596581746}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2006 Pitt Volleyball Media Guide&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pitt/sports/w-volley/auto_pdf/06-media-guide.pdf|title=2006 Pitt Volleyball Media Guide|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2009 Chancellor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chancellor.pitt.edu/publications/2009-Annual-Report.pdf|title=2009 Report of the Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg|year=2009|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|pages=4, 10|accessdate=April 29, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;2010 Hoops &amp; Helmets Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cfn.scout.com/2/954366.html|title=2010 Hoops &amp; Helmets Rankings|first=Richard|last=Cirminiello|publisher=CollegeFootballNews.com|date=March 16, 2010|accessdate=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ACC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theacc.com/genrel/091811aaa.html|title=ACC Extends Formal Invitations for Membership to Pittsburgh and Syracuse|date=September 18, 2011|publisher=[[Atlantic Coast Conference]]|accessdate=September 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AUTM U.S. Licensing Survey, FY 2004: A Survey Summary of Technology Licensing (and Related) Performance for U.S. Academic and Nonprofit Institutions, and Technology Investment firms&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|url=http://www.autm.net/Content/NavigationMenu/Surveys/LicensingSurveysAUTM/FY2004LicensingSurvey/04AUTMSurveySumUS.pdf|title=AUTM U.S. Licensing Survey, FY 2004: A Survey Summary of Technology Licensing (and Related) Performance for U.S. Academic and Nonprofit Institutions, and Technology Investment firms|publisher=The Association of University Technology Managers (AUTM)|year=2005|editor-last=Stevens|editor-first=Ashley J.|editor2-last=Toneguzzo|editor2-first=Frances|editor3-last=Bostrom|editor3-first=Dana|location=Northbrook, IL|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Alberts17&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00c50130m&amp;seq=37|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=17|year=1987|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;All-Sport Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2006/sioncampus/12/14/allsports.rankings/index.html|title=All-Sport Rankings|date=December 14, 2006|last=Bressman|first=Theodore B.|work=Sports Illustrated|accessdate=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Annual catalog of the Western University of Pennsylvania, Year Ending 1905&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittcatalogs;idno=1905a754541;view=image;seq=31|title=Annual catalog of the Western University of Pennsylvania, Year Ending 1905|page=27|year=1905|publisher=Western University of Pennsylvania|accessdate=December 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Best of both: BCS era combined standings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://collegefootball.rivals.com/content.asp?CID=1090378|title=Best of both: BCS era combined standings|publisher=Rivals.com|location=Brentwood, TN|first=Steve|last=Megargee|date=June 3, 2010|accessdate=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bigelow Bash features Queens of the Stone Age and a friendly monkey&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/8505|title=Bigelow Bash features Queens of the Stone Age and a friendly monkey|last=Anderson|first=Sam|date=April 7, 2003|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Blue and Gold Society&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~bluegold/|title=Blue and Gold Society|date=January 23, 2006|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;CMU, Pitt rate as good neighbors&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=5481|title=CMU, Pitt rate as good neighbors |date=August 31, 2006|newspaper=University Times|volume=39|number=1|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Campus tour map&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/commencement/visitors/campus_tour.pdf|title=Campus tour map|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg Issues a University Update on the Economy and Our Community&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|title=Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg Issues a University Update on the Economy and Our Community|publisher=News From Pitt, University of Pittsburgh|date=February 18, 2009|url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/news/chancellor-mark-nordenberg-issues-university-update-economy-and-our-community|accessdate=February 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Cheer and Dance Finish in Top 20 in Respective Competitions&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/genrel/042307aac.html|title=Cheer and Dance Finish in Top 20 in Respective Competitions|year=2007|work=Pitt Athletics|publisher=PittsburghPanthers.com|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Chinese Ministry of Education Awards University of Pittsburgh First Confucius Institute in Pennsylvania&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=2976&amp;-Find|title=Chinese Ministry of Education Awards University of Pittsburgh First Confucius Institute in Pennsylvania|date=August 1, 2007|work=News from Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Confucius Institute at the University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucis.pitt.edu/cipitt/|title=Confucius Institute at the University of Pittsburgh|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Constitution&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~basoc/home.htm|title=Constitution|publisher=Black Action Society|accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: African Music and dance&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/africanDrumming.html|title=Department of Music: African Music and dance|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=June 8, 2008 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080509042336/http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/africanDrumming.html|archivedate = May 9, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: The University Orchestra&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/orchestra.html|title=Department of Music: The University Orchestra|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=June 8, 2008 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080422063150/http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/orchestra.html|archivedate=April 22, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Department of Music: Women's Choral Ensemble&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/womensChoral.html|title=Department of Music: Women's Choral Ensemble|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=June 8, 2008 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080423220138/http://www.music.pitt.edu/performance/womensChoral.html|archivedate=April 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Documenting Pitt: Honors Convocation Programs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/d/documentingpitt/honors.html|title=Documenting Pitt: Honors Convocation Programs|year=2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=January 19, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;E-Week's 50th Anniversary&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/6185|title=E-Week's 50th Anniversary|last=Miller|first=Brenda|date=March 30, 2004|publisher=The Pitt News|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ESPN.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/espn/news/story?page=061221two-sportchart|title=Top two-sport schools over the last five years|publisher=ESPN |date=December 21, 2006|accessdate=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Early Schools&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pitttext;idno=22aep3676s;view=image;seq=0029|title=Early Schools|journal=Pittsburgh School Bulletin|date=1928-05|page=25|publisher=Pittsburgh Teachers Association, Inc.|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=December 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Endowment update&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Audited Financial Statements|date=2011|url=http://www.cfo.pitt.edu/documents/13324UPghAnnualReportwithOpinion_FINAL_09_14_11.pdf|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Endowment&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=2010 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments|year=2011|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf|format=PDF|publisher=National Association of College and University Business Officers|accessdate=2011-02-93}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;FSBI&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.academicanalytics.com/|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080822232018/http://www.academicanalytics.com/TopSchools/TopSchools.aspx|title=FSP Index Top Performing Schools|date=August 22, 2008|archivedate=August 22, 2008|publisher=Academic Analytics, LLC|accessdate=September 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Federal S&amp;E obligations to academic institutions reach new highs in FY 2006 but fail to keep up with inflation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nsf.gov/statistics/infbrief/nsf08316/nsf08316.pdf|title= Federal S&amp;E obligations to academic institutions reach new highs in FY 2006 but fail to keep up with inflation|last=Bennof|first=Richard|year=2008|month=October|format=PDF|work=InfoBrief Science Resource Statistics|publisher=[[National Science Foundation]]|page=3|accessdate=October 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Flourishing Five No. 5: Resurgent Pitt football doing its part&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbssports.com/collegefootball/story/13660952/top-footballbasketball-schools-resurgent-pitt-football-doing-its-part?tag=coverlist_active;coverlist_photo|title=Flourishing Five No. 5: Resurgent Pitt football doing its part|first=Dennis|last=Dodd|publisher=CBSSports.com|date=July 22, 2010|accessdate=July 22, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Four Pitt Honors College Students Receive 2010 David L. Boren Awards for International Study&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=5902|title=Four Pitt Honors College Students Receive 2010 David L. Boren Awards for International Study|first=Patricia Lomando|last=White|date=June 28, 2010|volume=11|number=19|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;G-Factor International University Ranking 2006: Top 300&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://universitymetrics.com/gfactor2006top300|title=G-Factor International University Ranking 2006: Top 300|publisher=Universitymetrics.com|year=2006|accessdate=August 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;GUR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globaluniversitiesranking.org/images/banners/top-100(eng).pdf|title=Global universities ranking: The 1st hundred|publisher=Global University Ranking|year=2009|accessdate=August 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Go West&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittmag.pitt.edu/fall2006/feature1.html|title=Go West|last=Collins|first=Mark|coauthors=Cara J. Hayden|work=Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Greekweek&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=1626|last=Moore|first=Anthony M.|title=Pitt’s Greek Community Emphasizes Community Service|date=August 19, 2008|work=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;HEEACT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.heeact.edu.tw/en-us/2009/TOP/100|title=HEEACT 2009 Ranking Top 100|publisher=Higher Education Evaluation &amp; Accreditation Council of Taiwan (HEEACT)|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hail to Pitt: A Sports History of the University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite book|editor-last=O'Brien|editor-first=Jim|title=Hail to Pitt: A Sports History of the University of Pittsburgh|page=62|year=1982|isbn=0-916114-08-2|publisher=Wolfson Publishing Co}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hearing set on historic landmark nomination for two Pitt buildings&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=5198|title=Hearing set on historic landmark nomination for two Pitt buildings|last=Sajna|first=Mike|date=January 23, 1997|newspaper=University Times|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=October 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinz Chapel Choir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~heinzcc/index.html|title=Heinz Chapel Choir|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinz Chapel choir program&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=YtM0AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=4m0DAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5969%2C11045420|title=Heinz Chapel choir program|newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|location=Pittsburgh, PA|date=November 28, 1986|accessdate=July 2, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillel JUC- VoKols: History of the VoKols&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hilleljuc.org/vokols/history.php|title=Hillel JUC- VoKols: History of the VoKols|publisher=Hillel Jewish University Center|accessdate=May 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pitt.edu/homecoming.html |title=Homecoming 2007|date=September 29, 2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=May 1, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming events include fireworks, lasers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/14604|title=Homecoming events include fireworks, lasers|last=Polantz|first=Katelyn|date=October 20, 2006|work=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Honors Convocation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/convocation/index.html|title=Honors Convocation|year=2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Katz School Ranks First in the Nation for MBA Value&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.katz.pitt.edu/news/013007.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070707101139/http://www.katz.pitt.edu/news/013007.html|archivedate=June 10, 2007| title=Katz School Ranks First in the Nation for MBA Value|date=January 29, 2007|accessdate=September 6, 2009|work=Joseph M. Katz Graduate School of Business Press Release}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;KiplingerBV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kiplinger.com//tools/colleges/index.php?table=none&amp;sortby=out_rank&amp;sortorder=ASC#colleges|title=Kiplinger's Best Values in Public Colleges|date=2011-01|publisher=Kiplinger.com|accessdate=January 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kuntu Repertory Theatre&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kuntu.org/|title=Kuntu Repertory Theatre|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Law School 100 -- Ranking the Best Law Schools in the United States&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lawschool100.com/|title=Law School 100 – Ranking the Best Law Schools in the United States|publisher=LawTV|year=2009|accessdate=April 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Law School Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uscollegeranking.org/law/the-best-law-schools-colleges-ranking-in-u-s.html|title=Law School Rankings|publisher=USNews|year=2010|accessdate=August 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Allegheny Observatory&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorepahistory.com/hmarker.php?markerId=1149|title=Marker Details: Allegheny Observatory|publisher=ExplorePAhistory.com|accessdate=September 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Barney Dreyfuss (1865-1932)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorepahistory.com/hmarker.php?markerId=1013|title=Marker Details: Barney Dreyfuss (1865–1932)|publisher=ExplorePAhistory.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Forbes Field&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorepahistory.com/hmarker.php?markerId=1015|title=Marker Details: Forbes Field|publisher=ExplorePAhistory.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: Meadowcroft Rockshelter&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorepahistory.com/hmarker.php?markerId=732|title=Marker Details: Meadowcroft Rockshelter|publisher=ExplorePAhistory.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marker Details: University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://explorepahistory.com/hmarker.php?markerId=1121|title=Marker Details: University of Pittsburgh|publisher=ExplorePAhistory.com|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mucha&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.philly.com/inquirer/breaking/news_breaking/99840589.html?cmpid=15585797|title=Survey: Penn State drinks, Main Line thinks|last=Mucha|first=Peter|date=August 3, 2010|work=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]]|accessdate=August 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NRC Rankings in Each of 41 Areas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stat.tamu.edu/~jnewton/nrc_rankings/nrc41.html|title=NRC Rankings in Each of 41 Areas|work=Research-Doctorate Programs in the United States: Continuity and Change|publisher=National Research Council|year=1995|accessdate=January 2, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NRHP-districts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalregisterofhistoricplaces.com/PA/Allegheny/districts.html|title=PENNSYLVANIA – Allegheny County – Historic Districts|publisher=[[National Register of Historic Places]]|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NSF funding: Where Pitt stands&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/u/FMPro?-db=ustory&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;storyid=8355&amp;-Find|title= NSF funding: Where Pitt stands|last=Hart|first=Peter|date=October 23, 2008|work=University Times|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=October 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;National Debate Tournament Participating Schools, 1947–2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://groups.wfu.edu/NDT/HistoricalLists/particip.html|title=National Debate Tournament Participating Schools, 1947–2006|publisher=Wake Forest University|accessdate=February 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Oakland Zoo Club&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Oakland Zoo Club|publisher=University of Pittsburgh |date=July 16, 2008|url=http://www.sorc.pitt.edu/orgSearch.asp?ID=715&amp;search=name&amp;nameSearch=Zoo|accessdate=October 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Outside the Classroom Curriculum: Your Pitt Pathway&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.occ.pitt.edu/index.html|title=Outside the Classroom Curriculum: Your Pitt Pathway|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=February 11, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PENNSYLVANIA – Allegheny County&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalregisterofhistoricplaces.com/pa/Allegheny/state.html|title=PENNSYLVANIA – Allegheny County|publisher=National Register of Historic Places|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PGMS Green Star Awards: Urban University Grounds: University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pgms.org/2007greenstar/category14a.htm|title=PGMS Green Star Awards: Urban University Grounds: University of Pittsburgh|year=2007|publisher=[[Professional Grounds Management Society]]|accessdate=August 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PGMS News - PGMS Salutes Grounds Management Excellence; College and University Grounds Lead the Way&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pgms.org/pgmsnews/2003pgmsgreenstars.htm|title=PGMS News – PGMS Salutes Grounds Management Excellence; College and University Grounds Lead the Way|year=2003|publisher=[[Professional Grounds Management Society]]|accessdate=August 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT ARTS Reaches More Than 32,000 Participants This Year&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=3327&amp;-Find|title=PITT ARTS Reaches More Than 32,000 Participants This Year|date=April 24, 2008|work=News From Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT Gymnastics Media Guide 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pitt/sports/w-gym/auto_pdf/0607-media-guide.pdf|title=PITT Gymnastics Media Guide 2007|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PITT Wrestling Media Guide 2006–2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pitt/sports/m-wrestl/auto_pdf/0607_media_guide.pdf|title=PITT Wrestling Media Guide 2006–2007|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PMGC in Bologna- Beatus Vir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=now to post a comment! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l8OiJPFF6Hw |title=PMGC in Bologna- Beatus Vir |publisher=YouTube |date=May 18, 2010 |accessdate=September 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PRELAW HANDBOOK - Law School Rankings: 2000-present&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prelawhandbook.com/law_school_rankings__2000_present|title=PRELAW HANDBOOK – Law School Rankings: 2000–present|publisher=Prelaw Handbook|year=2009 |accessdate=April 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PRbestvalue&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=7770| title=Pitt Named &quot;Best Value&quot; University by Princeton Review | first=John|last=Harvith | newspaper=Pitt Chronicle | publisher=University of Pittsburgh | location=Pittsburgh, PA|volume=12|number=8|date=February 28, 2011|accessdate=February 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Peace Corps Top Colleges and Universities 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.peacecorps.gov/multimedia/pdf/stats/schools2008.pdf|title=Peace Corps Top Colleges and Universities 2008|date=September 30, 2007|format=PDF|publisher=[[Peace Corps]]|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Petersen Sports Complex&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittsburghpanthers.com/facilities/pitt-facilities-olympic-sports-complex.html|title=Petersen Sports Complex|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=January 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Philosophy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stat.tamu.edu/~jnewton/nrc_rankings/nrc41.html#area9|title=Philosophy|last=Newton|first=H. J.|work=NRC Rankings in each of the 41 Areas|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Alumn Association: Traditions: When You Wish Upon a Panther&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alumni.pitt.edu/traditions/#wish|title=Pitt Alumn Association: Traditions: When You Wish Upon a Panther|date=June 30, 2008|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=August 15, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Athletics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cstv.com/auto_pdf/s_chools/pitt/datadump/sports/football/mediaguide/2005/panther_history|title=Pitt Athletics|publisher=PittsburghPanthers.com|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Baseball Media Guide 2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pitt/sports/m-basebl/auto_pdf/Pitt-Baseball-mguide.pdf|title=Pitt Baseball Media Guide 2006|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Giving: Office of Institutional Advancement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.giveto.pitt.edu/|title=Pitt Giving: Office of Institutional Advancement|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1893: William Hunter Dammond&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/history/1893.html|title=Pitt History – 1893: William Hunter Dammond|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1898: Margaret and Stella Stein&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/history/1898.html|title=Pitt History – 1898: Margaret and Stella Stein|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt History – 1906: Reginald Fessenden&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/history/1906.html|title=Pitt History – 1906: Reginald Fessenden|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Mock Trial Team Places Fifth in American Mock Trial Association National Competition&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=3323&amp;-Find|title=Pitt Honors College Mock Trial Team Places Fifth in American Mock Trial Association National Competition|date=April 23, 2008|work=News From Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Receives 4,700 Acres of Wyoming Land Teeming With Dinosaur Fossils&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/media/pcc060130/land_donation_main_2006JAN30.html|title=Pitt Honors College Receives 4,700 Acres of Wyoming Land Teeming With Dinosaur Fossils|work=Pitt Chronicle|date=January 30, 2006|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 30, 2008}} &lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Honors College Senior Greg Heller-LaBelle Named 2006 Omicron Delta Kappa Senior of the Year&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.honorscollege.pitt.edu/news-events/news-archive/odk.html|title=Pitt Honors College Senior Greg Heller-LaBelle Named 2006 Omicron Delta Kappa Senior of the Year|date=March 16, 2006|work=University Honors College|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Is Ranked Among the Top 10 U.S. University Recipients of Federal Research and Development Obligations&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=3479&amp;-Find|title=Pitt Is Ranked Among the Top 10 U.S. University Recipients of Federal Research and Development Obligations|date=October 20, 2008 |work=News From Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=October 20, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Map Program&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abroad.pitt.edu/pantherprograms/pittMAP.html|title=Pitt Map Program|publisher=Study Abroad Office, University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Men's Glee Club&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittmensgleeclub.org/|title=Pitt Men's Glee Club|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Musical Theater Club&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittnews.com/newsstory/musical-theatre-club-tries-to-fill-a-campus-void/|title=Pitt Musical Theater Club}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Neuroscience Student From Pennsylvania Awarded Goldwater Scholarship&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=8149 | title=Pitt Neuroscience Student From Pennsylvania Awarded Goldwater Scholarship|first=Patricia Lomando|last=White|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|date=April 4, 2011|accessdate=April 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Pathfinders&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pathfinders.pitt.edu/default.html|title=Pitt Pathfinders|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080317113135/http://www.pathfinders.pitt.edu/default.html|archivedate=March 17, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Political Review&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittpoliticalreview.org/|title=Pitt Political Review|accessdate=February 17, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Program Council&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittprogramcouncil.com|title=Pitt Program Council|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=January 12, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt Wins Grounds Services Award&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=7140 | title= Pitt Wins Grounds Services Award|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle |publisher=University of Pittsburgh | location=Pittsburgh, PA | date=December 6, 2010 | accessdate=December 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt arts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~pittarts/|title=Pitt arts|date=April 9, 2008|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt grad named 2010 Rhodes Scholar&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/09326/1015574-100.stm|title=Pitt grad named 2010 Rhodes Scholar|first=Karen|last=Kane|date=November 22, 2009|newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=November 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt students win Goldwater, Udall scholarships&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=12106|title=Pitt students win Goldwater, Udall scholarships|newspaper=University Times|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|date=April 15, 2010|volume=42|number=16|accessdate=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt students win Truman, Goldwater scholarships&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Barlow|first=Kimberly K |title=Pitt students win Truman, Goldwater scholarships |publisher=University Times|date=April 3, 2008|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/u/FMPro?-db=ustory&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;storyid=8045&amp;-Find|accessdate=April 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt to Offer Students Opportunity to Develop Professional Skills Through Extracurricular Experiences in a New Program: Outside the Classroom Curriculum to be implemented this fall&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=3393&amp;-Find|title=Pitt to Offer Students Opportunity to Develop Professional Skills Through Extracurricular Experiences in a New Program: Outside the Classroom Curriculum to be implemented this fall|publisher=University of Pittsburgh:News From Pitt|date=August 6, 2008|accessdate=August 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt traditions&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/AFShome/s/o/sorc/public/html/thepitt/traditions.htm|title=Internet Archive: The Panther Pitt: Pitt Traditions|date=August 20, 2006|accessdate=May 1, 2008 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060822113321/www.pitt.edu/AFShome/s/o/sorc/public/html/thepitt/traditions.htm |archivedate=August 22, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt's School of Engineering Holds 50th Annual E-Week March 18–26: Pittopoly, Duct Tape Challenge, and Soap Box Derby part of this year's festivities&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.engr.pitt.edu/news/article_view.php?id=1649|title=Pitt's School of Engineering Holds 50th Annual E-Week March 18–26: Pittopoly, Duct Tape Challenge, and Soap Box Derby part of this year's festivities|date=March 19, 2004|publisher=Swanson School of Engineering, University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt's homecoming history long, filled with memories&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/14608|title=Pitt's homecoming history long, filled with memories|last=Catalano|first=Emily|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|date=October 19, 2006|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987&quot;&gt;Upon joining the [[Commonwealth System of Higher Education]] in 1966, the University of Pittsburgh legally remained a private entity and in practice, retained the administrative and academic freedom of a private institution. It sets its own standards for student admission and retention, faculty, and teaching. Its assets remain in the hands of the corporation, its employees are employed by the corporation, and its affairs are governed by an independent Board of Trustees.&lt;sup&gt;''A''&lt;/sup&gt; In-state tuition is subsidized by the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania and the state provides approximately 11% of its operating budget.&lt;sup&gt;''B''&lt;/sup&gt; The University of Pittsburgh is categorized as a [[public university]] in the [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education|Carnegie Foundation Classifications]]&lt;sup&gt;''C''&lt;/sup&gt; and is typically listed as a public university in third party publications.&lt;sup&gt;''D''&lt;/sup&gt; For simplicity, Pitt sometimes refers to itself a &quot;public university&quot;. :&lt;sup&gt;''A''&lt;/sup&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00c50130m&amp;seq=363|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=343|year=1986|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]]}} :&lt;sup&gt;''B''&lt;/sup&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.news.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=3379&amp;-Find|title=University of Pittsburgh Trustees Approve 2008–09 Budget, Set Tuition Rates|date=08-07-11|publisher=University of Pittsburgh: News From Pitt|accessdate=July 15, 2008}} :&lt;sup&gt;''C''&lt;/sup&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=16063&amp;start=782|title=Classifications: University of Pittsburgh-Main Campus|publisher=The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|accessdate=July 15, 2008}} :&lt;sup&gt;''D''&lt;/sup&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/pittsburgh-pa/university-of-pittsburgh-3379|title=Best Colleges Overview: University of Pittsburgh|publisher=USNews.com|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19871&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs;idno=00c50130m;seq=0021|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=1|year=1986|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19872&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs;idno=00c50130m;seq=0230|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=210|year=1987|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–19873&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00c50130m&amp;seq=83|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=63|year=1987 |isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00c50130m&amp;seq=509|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|title=Pitt: The Story of the University of Pittsburgh 1787–1987|page=453|year=1986|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pitt: the story of the University of Pittsburgh, 1787–1987&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs;idno=00c50130m;seq=81|title=Pitt: the story of the University of Pittsburgh, 1787–1987|last=Alberts|first=Robert C|pages=60–61|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|isbn=0-8229-1150-7|year=1986}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh History &amp; Landmarks Foundation announces Historic Building and Landscape Designations&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phlf.org/2007/06/27/pittsburgh-history-landmarks-foundation-announces-historic-building-and-landscape-designations/|title=Pittsburgh History &amp; Landmarks Foundation announces Historic Building and Landscape Designations|date=June 27, 2007|accessdate=February 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation: PHLF Plaques &amp; Registries&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.phlf.org/plaques/locallist.html|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070127092030/http://www.phlf.org/plaques/locallist.html|archivedate=January 27, 2007|title=Pittsburgh History and Landmarks Foundation: PHLF Plaques &amp; Registries|date=January 27, 2007|accessdate=February 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh Jazz Ensemble&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~pittjazz/ensemble.html|title=Pittsburgh Jazz Ensemble|work=Jazz at Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Provost explains decision to drop Semester at Sea&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=1396|title=Provost explains decision to drop Semester at Sea|first=Peter|last=Hart|newspaper=University Times|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|volume=37|number=21|date=June 23, 2005|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;QS World University Rankings 2010 Results&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2010/results|title=QS World University Rankings 2010 Results}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Quo Vadis&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sorc.pitt.edu/orgSearch.asp?ID=183&amp;search=type&amp;orgTypePick=7|title=Quo Vadis|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RFID Lowdown&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rfidlowdown.com/2005/10/pitt_created_rf_3.html|title=RFID Lowdown, the on-line RFID new publication RFID Lowdown|year=2007|accessdate=July 1, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rainbow Alliance&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pitt.edu/~sorc/rainbow/index.html|title=Rainbow Alliance|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=May 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Redeye Theatre Project&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~sorc/rtp |title=Redeye Theatre Project|date=February 17, 2008|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Remembering Polio: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Salk Polio Vaccine&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.polio.pitt.edu/|title=Remembering Polio: Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of the Salk Polio Vaccine|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Results from Previous National Debate Tournament, 1977-1986&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://groups.wfu.edu/NDT/Results/NDT%20results%201977-1986%20(31-40).pdf|format=PDF|title=Results from Previous National Debate Tournament, 1977–1986|accessdate=February 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rev. John Taylor: the first rector of Trinity Episcopal Church of Pittsburgh and his commonplace book&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pitttext;idno=00hc14502m;seq=0012|title=Rev. John Taylor: the first rector of Trinity Episcopal Church of Pittsburgh and his commonplace book|last=Dahlinger|first=Charles W.|page=10|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rites of Passage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.provost.pitt.edu/whistory/passage/passage.html#|title=Rites of Passage|year=2003|work=The History of Women at Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SCImago&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scimagoir.com/pdf/sir_2009_world_report.pdf|title=SCImago Institutions Rankings (SIR): 2009 World Report|year=2009|publisher=SCImago Institutions Rankings|accessdate=November 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Salk Polio Vaccine – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.waymarking.com/waymarks/WM8E0_Salk_Polio_Vaccine|title=Salk Polio Vaccine – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com|publisher=Waymarking.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Saviors of Our Cities: 2009 Survey of College &amp; University Civic Partnerships&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|title=Saviors of Our Cities: 2009 Survey of College &amp; University Civic Partnerships|date=Fall 2009|url= http://www.evandobelle.com/SOOC%20Survey%20Overview.pdf |last=Dobelle|first=Evan S.|publisher=Westfield State College| location=Westfield, MA |page=4 |accessdate=December 19, 2010|postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Scholar Athletes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=158|title=Scholar Athletes|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|date=April 29, 2007|accessdate=July 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Scholarships for Study Abroad&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abroad.pitt.edu/finances/scholarships.html|title=Scholarships for Study Abroad|publisher=Study Abroad Office, University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets of the Cathedral: Starting at the top&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=27|title=Secrets of the Cathedral: Starting at the top|date=September 11, 2003|newspaper=University Times|volume=36|number=2|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Sounds of Pleasure&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~sorc/pleasure/index.html|title=Sounds of Pleasure|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Student Organization Resource Center|accessdate=May 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Spirit Groups&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/trads/pitt-trads-spirit.html|title=Spirit Groups|work=Traditions|publisher=PittsburghPanthers.com|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephen C. Foster Memorial – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.waymarking.com/waymarks/WM6ZB_Stephen_C_Foster_Memorial|title=Stephen C. Foster Memorial – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com|publisher=Waymarking.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Strictly Bill&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wqed.org/mag/features/0108/strickland.php|title=Strictly Bill|last=Curran|first=Ann|publisher=Pittsburgh Magazine|accessdate=April 29, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080125062407/http://www.wqed.org/mag/features/0108/strickland.php |archivedate = January 25, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Student Traditions&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alumni.pitt.edu/impact/trad-right.html|title=Student Traditions|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Students celebrate Fall Fest&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/14473|title=Students celebrate Fall Fest|last=Singer|first=Drew|date=September 6, 2008|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Study Abroad Office&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abroad.pitt.edu/|title=Study Abroad Office|date=May 3, 2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Study Abroad Program Options&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abroad.pitt.edu/programs.html|title=Study Abroad Program Options|publisher=Study Abroad Office, University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;THE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html|title=Top 200: The Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2010–2011|publisher=Times Higher Education|year=2011|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The 2008 Report of Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Mark|last=Nordenberg|authorlink=Mark Nordenberg|title=The 2008 Report of Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg|year=2008|page=20|location=Pittsburgh, PA|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|url=http://www.chancellor.pitt.edu/publications/2008-Annual-Report.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Celebration of the One Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary: History of the University&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.archive.org/stream/universityofpitt821univ#page/4/mode/2up|title=The Celebration of the One Hundred and Twenty-Fifth Anniversary: History of the University|volume=8|issue=21|journal=University of Pittsburgh Bulletin|date=November 1, 1912|pages=4–5|accessdate=January 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Complete List: The Top 100 Global Universities&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14321230/site/newsweek/print/1/displaymode/1098/|title=The Complete List: The Top 100 Global Universities|work=Newsweek|date=August 10, 2006|accessdate=June 18, 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070403020728/http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14321230/site/newsweek/print/1/displaymode/1098/ |archivedate = April 3, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Legacy Gallery&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umc.pitt.edu/gallery/|title=The Legacy Gallery|date=November 20, 2007|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080303163337/http://www.umc.pitt.edu/gallery/|archivedate=March 3, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Nationality Rooms - rooms in planning&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~natrooms/pages/rooms_in_planning.html |title=The Nationality Rooms – rooms in planning |publisher=Pitt.edu |accessdate=September 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Original&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.originalmag.com/|title=The Original|accessdate=February 27, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Owl&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittyearbooks;idno=1909e49702;seq=23|title=The Owl|page=10|publisher=Western University of Pennsylvania|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Panther&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/trads/pitt-trads-mascot.html|title=The Panther|publisher=Pittsburgh Panthers|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pittsburgh Pendulums: History&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~sorc/pendulums/|title=The Pittsburgh Pendulums: History|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Student Organization Resource Center|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Princeton Review: University of Pittsburgh School of Law&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.princetonreview.com/UniversityofPittsburghSchoolofLaw.aspx|title=The Princeton Review: University of Pittsburgh School of Law|publisher=The Princeton Review|year=2009|accessdate=April 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Pymatuning Laboratory of Ecology&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~biohome/Dept/Frame/pymatuninglabs.htm|title=The Pymatuning Laboratory of Ecology|date=February 20, 2008|publisher=University of Pittsburgh, The Department of Biological Sciences|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Shot Heard 'Round the World&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://museum.pharmacy.pitt.edu/salk/|title=The Shot Heard 'Round the World|publisher=University of Pittsburgh School of Pharmacy|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Varsity Walk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/trads/pitt-trads-walk.html|title=The Varsity Walk |work=Traditions|publisher=PittsburghPanthers.com|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The history of Pittsburgh: its rise and progress&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pitttext&amp;idno=00adc8925m&amp;view=image&amp;seq=353|last=Killikelly|first=Sarah H.|title=The history of Pittsburgh: its rise and progress|page=269|year=1906|publisher=B.C. &amp; Gordon Montgomery Co.|location=Pittsburgh, PA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;TheCenterRankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|editor-last=Capaldi|editor-first=Elizabeth D.|editor2-last=Lombardi|editor2-first=John V.|editor3-last=Abbey|editor3-first=Craig W.|editor4-last=Craig|editor4-first=Diane D.|title=The Top American Research Universities: 2009 Annual Report|year=2010|pages=8 &amp; 16|location=Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ|publisher=The Center for Measuring University Performance|url=http://mup.asu.edu/research2009.pdf|format=PDF|accessdate=May 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Through One Hundred and Fifty Years: The University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs;idno=00afj8718m;seq=0096|title=Through One Hundred and Fifty Years: The University of Pittsburgh|first=Agnes Lynch|last=Starrett|page=66|year=1937|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Press|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=November 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Through one hundred and fifty years: the University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00afj8718m&amp;seq=48|last=Starrett|first=Agnes Lynch|title=Through one hundred and fifty years: the University of Pittsburgh|page=26|year=1937|publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Top 35 Law Faculties Based on Scholarly Impact, 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leiterrankings.com/faculty/2007faculty_impact.shtml|title=Top 35 Law Faculties Based on Scholarly Impact, 2007|last=Leiter|first=Brian|date=September 1, 2007|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Turning up the heat&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/12168|title=Turning up the heat|last=Miller|first=Alexis|date=September 6, 2002|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;U.S. News ranks graduate programs&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|last=Hart|first=Peter|title=U.S. News ranks graduate programs|newspaper=University Times|date=April 30, 2009|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/u/FMPro?-db=ustory&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;storyid=8679&amp;-Find|accessdate=2009=05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;UPMC Community Benefits Report Fiscal Year 2008: Strengthening the Fabric of a Community&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://www.upmc.com/aboutupmc/CommunityCitizenship/Documents/community_benefits_08_report.pdf|title=UPMC Community Benefits Report Fiscal Year 2008: Strengthening the Fabric of a Community|publisher=UPMC|date=2009-05|pages=33|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;UPMCrank&quot;&gt;{{cite press release|title=UPMC Named to U.S. News &amp; World Report Honor Roll of America’s Best Hospitals for the Ninth Time|publisher=UMPC Media Relations|date=July 11, 2008|url=http://www.upmc.com/MediaRelations/NewsReleases/2008/Pages/US-News-08.aspx|accessdate=March 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USNewsBV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-best-values|title=America's Best Colleges 2010: Best Values: National Universities|publisher=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]|year=2009|accessdate=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_LIFE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/ARWUFIELD2009LIFE.jspm|title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Life and Agriculture Sciences – 2009|year=2009 |publisher=Center for World-Class Universities and the Institute of Higher Education of Shanghai Jiao Tong University|location=Shanghai, China|accessdate=November 22, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_MED&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/ARWUFIELD2009MED.jsp|title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Clinical Medicine and Pharmacy – 2009|year=2009 |publisher=Center for World-Class Universities and the Institute of Higher Education of Shanghai Jiao Tong University|location=Shanghai, China|accessdate=November 22, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_SOC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/ARWUFIELD2009SOC.jsp|title=Academic Ranking of World Universities in Social Sciences – 2009|year=2009 |publisher=Center for World-Class Universities and the Institute of Higher Education of Shanghai Jiao Tong University|location=Shanghai, China|accessdate=November 22, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_ARWU_W&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arwu.org/ARWU2009.jsp|title=Academic Ranking of World Universities|year=2009|publisher=Center for World-Class Universities and the Institute of Higher Education of Shanghai Jiao Tong University|location=Shanghai, China|accessdate=November 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_HEEACT_W&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.heeact.edu.tw/mp.asp?mp=4|title=HEEACT Ranking of Scientific Papers|year=2009|publisher=Higher Education Evaluation &amp; Accreditation Council|accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Pharmacy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-pharmacy-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Graduate Schools: Pharmacy|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2008|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PhysicalTherapy&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-physical-therapy-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Graduate Schools: Physical Therapy|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2008|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PublicAffairs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-public-affairs-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Public Affairs Schools|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2008|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_PublicHealth&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-public-health-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Graduate Schools: Public Health|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2007|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_RatER_Global&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globaluniversitiesranking.org/images/banners/top-100(eng).pdf|title=Global Universities Ranking|year=2009|publisher=RatER|accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_SocialWork&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-social-work-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Graduate Schools: Social Work|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2008|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_THES_W&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html|title=World University Rankings|year=2010|publisher=The Times Higher Educational Supplement|author=The Times|accessdate=October 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Bus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-business-schools/rankings/page+4|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Business Schools|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Ed&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-education-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Education Programs|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Eng&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-engineering-schools/rankings/page+2|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Engineering Schools|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Law&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/rankings/page+3|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Law Schools|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_LibS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-library-information-science-programs/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Library and Information Studies: Rankings|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2009|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Medc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools/primary-care-rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Medical Schools: Primary Care Rankings|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Medr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools/research-rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Medical Schools: Research Rankings|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_NBV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-best-values|work=America's Best Colleges 2009|title=Best Colleges: Top Public Schools: National Universities|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2009|accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_NU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/national-search|work=America's Best Colleges 2009|title=National Universities Rankings|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2009|accessdate=May 18, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_Nurs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-nursing-schools/rankings|work=America's Best Graduate Schools|title=Best Graduate Schools: Nursing|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2007|accessdate=April 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_USNWR_TPS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-top-public|work=America's Best Colleges 2009|title=Best Colleges: Best Values: National Universities|publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2009|accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Wamo_NU&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/college_guide/rankings/national_university_rank.php|title=The Washington Monthly 2009 National University Rankings|year=2009|work=The Washington Monthly|accessdate=December 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;USUnivRankings_Wuhan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rccse.whu.edu.cn/college/sjdxkyjzl.htm|title=世界大学科研竞争力排行榜2007|format=PDF|year=2007|publisher=''Research Center for Chinese Science Evaluation''|accessdate=September 28, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;UT UPMC HonorRoll&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=UPMC makes U.S. News honor roll|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=8801|newspaper=University Times|date=July 23, 2009|accessdate=November 30, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Universities report continued decline in real federal S&amp;E R&amp;D funding in FY 2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/infbrief/nsf08320/nsf08320.pdf|title= Universities report continued decline in real federal S&amp;E R&amp;D funding in FY 2007 |last=Britt|first=Ronda|year=2008|month=August|format=PDF|work=InfoBriefs: Science Resources Statistics|publisher=[[National Science Foundation]]|pages=3, TABLE&amp;nbsp;4|accessdate=October 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University Center for International Studies (UCIS)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucis.pitt.edu/main/|title=University Center for International Studies (UCIS)|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Announces 12-Year Facilities Plan To Support Programmatic Direction&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=2929&amp;-Find|title=University of Pittsburgh Announces 12-Year Facilities Plan To Support Programmatic Direction|date=May 17, 2007|accessdate=June 21, 2007|work=University of Pittsburgh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.play.pitt.edu/|title=University of Pittsburgh Department of Theatre Arts|accessdate=June 8, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Freshman Prospectus&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://www.pitt.edu/%7Eoafa/pdf/oafa_prospectus_web_09.pdf|title=University of Pittsburgh Freshman Prospectus|publisher=University of Pittsburgh Office of Admissions and Financial Aid|year=2009|pages=30|accessdate=February 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Graduate and Professional Student Association&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittgpsa.org|title=University of Pittsburgh Graduate and Professional Student Association|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar &amp; Concert&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~pittjazz/seminar.html|title=University of Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar &amp; Concert|work=Jazz at Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Mock Trial&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pittmocktrial.org/Site/Welcome.html|title=University of Pittsburgh Mock Trial|date=April 6, 2008|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh Student Government Board&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~sgb|title=University of Pittsburgh Student Government Board|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=July 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university/501/universitypittsburgh |title=University of Pittsburgh |publisher=Topuniversities |accessdate=September 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University of Pittsburgh6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.teenink.com/College/article.php?link=Past/2007/April/21186.xml|title=University of Pittsburgh|last=Copley|first=Chris M|publisher=Teen Ink|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;University ranks high in Peace Corps volunteers&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=5710|title=University ranks high in Peace Corps volunteers|date=January 25, 2007|work=University Times|volume=39|number=10|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;V.F.W. – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.waymarking.com/waymarks/WM9WW|title=V.F.W. – Pennsylvania Historical Markers on Waymarking.com|publisher=Waymarking.com|accessdate=September 7, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Volleyball Releases 2007 Schedule&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/sports/w-volley/spec-rel/062107aaa.html|title=Volleyball Releases 2007 Schedule|date=June 21, 2007|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;WQED OnQ OnDemand: The Pitt Pendulums&quot;&gt;{{cite video|url=http://www.wqed.org/ondemand/onq.php?cat=3&amp;id=488|airdate=April 15, 2009|medium=TV, multimedia video|editor-last=Ruggieri|editor-first=Paul|title=WQED OnQ OnDemand: The Pitt Pendulums|location=Pittsburgh, PA|publisher=WQED|accessdate=May 29, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Webometrics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webometrics.info/top12000.asp|title=Ranking Web of World universities: Top 12000 World Rankings|publisher=Cybermetrics Lab|location=Madrid, Spain |date=2011-01|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Webometrics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webometrics.info/top6000.asp|title=Webometrics Ranking of World Universities: Top 6000 Universities|publisher=Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Científicas (CSIC) Cybermetrics Lab|date=2009-07|accessdate=August 24, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Weighing in on Pitt's eclectic architecture&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.utimes.pitt.edu/?p=1016|title=Weighing in on Pitt's eclectic architecture|last=Steele|first=Bruce|date=October 24, 2002|work=University Times|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Welcome to the 2006–2008 Philosophical Gourmet Report&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.philosophicalgourmet.com/|title=Welcome to the 2006–2008 Philosophical Gourmet Report|last=Leiter|first=Brian|date=November 10, 2006|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;William Pitt Debating Union&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.comm.pitt.edu/debate/index.html|title=William Pitt Debating Union|date=April 2, 2008|publisher=Department of Communication, Univ. of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wuhan&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rccse.whu.edu.cn/college/sjdxkyjzl.htm|title= 世界大学科研竞争力排行榜2007 （前500名+中国大学）|publisher=[[Wuhan University]]|accessdate=August 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;about nationality rooms&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/%7enatrooms/pages/about_nr.html|title=about nationality rooms|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;about-ucis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucis.pitt.edu/main/about.html|title=About UCIS|date=August 31, 2006|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;alberts&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittmiscpubs&amp;idno=00c50130m&amp;seq=21|title=Pitt: the story of the University of Pittsburgh, 1787–1987|last=Alberts|first=Robert C.|year=1986|publisher=[[University of Pittsburgh Press]]|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;armanlos&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-format=d.html&amp;-lay=a&amp;-sortfield=date&amp;-sortorder=descend&amp;keywords=Rhodes&amp;-max=50&amp;-recid=36894&amp;-find=|title=For Second Year Straight, Pitt Student Named Rhodes Scholar|date=November 19, 2006|work=News from Pitt|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;chancellor-2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.umc.pitt.edu/chancellor/publications/2006ChancellorReport.pdf|title=The 2006 Report of Chancellor Mark A. Nordenberg|date=June 23, 2006|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080414064540/http://www.umc.pitt.edu/chancellor/publications/2006ChancellorReport.pdf|archivedate=April 14, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cstv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/pitt/sports/m-track/auto_pdf/06-07-mg-part1.pdf|title=Track &amp; Field/Cross Country|format=PDF|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cstv5&quot;&gt;[http://pittsburghpanthers.cstv.com/sports/m-footbl/spec-rel/GDC_Events.html Upcoming events: Pitt Students – Make Your Heinz Field Standard/Claim Your Grill Night (Aug 27), Pittsburghpanthers.com; accessdate August 24, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;enrollfn&quot;&gt;This enrollment figure reflects the total headcount of full-time and part-time undergraduate and graduate students attending classes at the University of Pittsburgh-Pittsburgh Campus in Fall 2010 only. An additional 6,911 full-time and part-time undergraduate students attend the university across the four regional campuses for a university-wide headcount of 35,734 total students, 25,282 of which are undergraduates.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;factbook&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=University of Pittsburgh Fact Book 2011|year=2011|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|url=http://www.ir.pitt.edu/factbook/documents/fb11.pdf|format=PDF|accessdate=June 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;harvith&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=3854|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|first=John|last=Harvith|date=October 12, 2009|accessdate=October 18, 2009|title=Pitt Is Nation’s Top-ranked Public School in 2009 Education-Civic Partnership Survey|volume=10|issue=26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;lanternpanther&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/media/pcc020822/lanternpanther.html|title=Lantern, Panther Ceremonies Set for Sunday|last=Fogel|first=Jessica |work=Pitt Campaign Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1909&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittyearbooks;idno=1909e49702;view=image;seq=22|title=The Owl|year=1909|page=9|publisher=Western University of Pennsylvania|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;owl1910&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=pittyearbooks;idno=1910e49702;seq=12|title=The Owl|year=1910|page=7|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 28, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mac10.umc.pitt.edu/m/FMPro?-db=ma&amp;-lay=a&amp;-format=d.html&amp;id=2788&amp;-Find|title=Pitt Ranked 4th Among Public Universities, 10th Among All U.S. Colleges and Universities With Endowments in Excess of $1&amp;nbsp;Billion in The FY 2006 Percentage Increase in Its Endowment|date=January 24, 2007|work=University of Pittsburgh}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt-fall-07&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://www.pittmag.pitt.edu/fall2007/feature1.html|title=The Company We Keep|last=Gill|first=Cindy|date=Fall 2007|journal=Pitt Magazine|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pitt4&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=5873|title=Chancellor’s Report: Pitt Striving to Attain Ever-Higher Levels of Educational Strength…and Beauty|date=June 28, 2010|volume=11|number=19|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=July 1, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pittnews&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/12269|title=&quot;Homecoming must be preserved&quot; (editorial)|date=September 18, 2002|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pittsburgh&quot;&gt;This figure reflects the total number of faculty at the Pittsburgh campus only. 403 additional faculty serve the four regional campuses for a university-wide total of 5,210 faculty members.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ritchie&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=6112|title=Pitt’s Global Studies Program Receives First-Time Designation as a National Resource Center by the United States Department of Education|first=Amanda Leff|last=Ritchie|date=August 24, 2010|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;robinet&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=6106|title=A New State of Mind: Journey Across Three Continents Shakes Up Students’ Visions, Notions About the World|newspaper=Pitt Chronicle|first=Jane-Ellen|last=Robinet|date=August 24, 2010 |publisher=University of Pittsburgh|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=August 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;state&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pdehighered.state.pa.us/higher/cwp/view.asp?A=6&amp;Q=41016|title=PA Higher/Adult Ed.: State-Related Universities|date=April 3, 2008|publisher=Pennsylvania Department of Education|accessdate=July 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;undergrad-research&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pitt.edu/~UGR/index.html|title=Undergraduate Research|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;usnews2010public&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-top-public|title=America's Best Colleges 2010: Top Public Schools: National Universities|publisher=[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]|year=2009|accessdate=August 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;webster&quot;&gt;{{cite newspaper|url=http://www.pittnews.com/node/18184|title=&quot;Pitt up in Peace Corps rankings&quot;|last=Webster|first=Henry Clay|date=January 16, 2008|newspaper=[[The Pitt News]]|location=Pittsburgh, PA|accessdate=September 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;white&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=White|first=Patricia Lomando|title=Pitt Honors College’s Katherine MacCord Wins Gates Cambridge Scholarship|publisher=Pitt Chronicle|date=February 16, 2009|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/?p=2147|accessdate=February 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wojcichowski&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chronicle.pitt.edu/media/pcc050221/BHMseries_EDEKE.html|title=Edeke Has It!|last=Wojcichowski|first=Leigh Ann|date=February 21, 2005|work=Pitt Chronicle|publisher=University of Pittsburgh|accessdate=April 29, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;{{cite video|title=Pitt Homecoming 2004 laser/fireworks............ part 4 of 4|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7n7TbrP1rfg|publisher=YouTube|location=Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|date=2004|accessdate=July 13, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|PITT|Pittsburgh}}
{{Commons|University of Pittsburgh}}
*[http://www.pitt.edu/ University of Pittsburgh] official website
*[http://www.pittsburghpanthers.com/ Pittsburgh Panthers intercollegiate athletics] official website
;Further reading
*[http://digital.library.pitt.edu/d/documentingpitt/ Documenting Pitt – digital University archive]
*[http://www.pitt.edu/publications.html List of University and student publications]

{{University of Pittsburgh}}
{{University of Pittsburgh Medical Center}}
{{Pittsburgh}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{Big East Conference}}
{{Eastern Wrestling League}}
{{East Atlantic Gymnastics League}}
{{Pittsburgh universities}}
{{Public universities in Pennsylvania}}
{{Public Ivy}}

{{Coord|40.444565|N|79.953274|W|format=dms|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pittsburgh, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Pittsburgh|University Of Pittsburgh A]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Big East Conference schools]]
[[Category:Commonwealth System of Higher Education]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Urban 13 universities]]
[[Category:Gothic Revival architecture in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in the 1780s]]
[[Category:1787 establishments in the United States]]


[[af:Universiteit van Pittsburgh]]
[[ar:جامعة بتسبرج]]
[[bg:Питсбъргски университет]]
[[cs:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[de:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[es:Universidad de Pittsburgh]]
[[fa:دانشگاه پیتسبورگ]]
[[fr:Université de Pittsburgh]]
[[ga:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[ko:피츠버그 대학교]]
[[hi:पिट्सबर्ग विश्वविद्यालय]]
[[hr:Sveučilište u Pittsburghu]]
[[is:Pittsburgh-háskóli]]
[[it:Università di Pittsburgh]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת פיטסבורג]]
[[hu:Pittsburghi Egyetem]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Pittsburgh]]
[[ja:ピッツバーグ大学]]
[[no:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[pnb:یونیورسٹی آف پٹسبرگ]]
[[pl:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[pt:Universidade de Pittsburgh]]
[[ro:Universitatea Pittsburgh]]
[[ru:Университет Питтсбурга]]
[[simple:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[fi:Pittsburghin yliopisto]]
[[sv:University of Pittsburgh]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยพิตส์เบิร์ก]]
[[uk:Університет Піттсбурга]]
[[vi:Đại học Pittsburgh]]
[[zh:匹茲堡大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
