<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2398349" ns="0" title="Edward James"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the poet and patron of the arts|other persons of the same name|Edward James (disambiguation)}}

'''Edward William Frank James''' (1907&amp;ndash;1984) was a British [[poet]] known for his [[patronage]] of the [[surrealism|surrealist]] art movement.

==Early life and marriage==
[[Image:West Dean House.JPG|thumb|West Dean House]]

Edward James was born on 16 August 1907, the only son of William James, an American railroad magnate who moved to England and married Evelyn Forbes, a Scots socialite, who was reputedly fathered by the [[Prince of Wales]] (later [[Edward VII]]).&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Hooks, [http://www.surrealeden.com &quot;Surreal Eden: Edward James &amp; Las Pozas&quot;], Princeton Architectural Press, New York, 2006, ISBN 978-1568986128,  p.14&lt;/ref&gt; He had four older sisters: Audrey, Millicent, Xandra, and Silvia. James was educated briefly at [[Eton college|Eton]], and then at [[Institut Le Rosey|Le Rosey]] in Switzerland, then at [[Christ Church, Oxford]], where he was a contemporary of [[Evelyn Waugh]] and [[Harold Acton]]. In 1912 he inherited the {{convert|8000|acre|km2|sing=on}} [[West Dean House]] in [[Sussex]], on the death of his father.

James' first sponsorship of note was in publishing [[John Betjeman]]'s first book of poems when at Oxford. He worked with [[Brian Howard (poet)|Brian Howard]] on the Glass Omnibus. After Oxford, James had a brief career as a trainee diplomat at the embassy in [[Rome]]. He was asked to send a coded message to London that the Italians had laid the keels for three destroyers, but got the code wrong; the message said &quot;300 destroyers&quot;. Shortly after this he was sent &quot;on indefinite leave&quot;. 

In the early 1930s, James married [[Tilly Losch]], an Austrian dancer, choreographer, actress and painter. He had several productions created expressly for her, the most notable of which was ''Les Ballets 1933'', which included [[Kurt Weill]], [[Lotte Lenya]] and [[George Balanchine]]. He and [[Boris Kochno]] commissioned that year [[Bertolt Brecht|Brecht]] and [[Kurt Weill|Weill's]] last collaboration, ''[[The Seven Deadly Sins (ballet chanté)|The Seven Deadly Sins]]'', which Balanchine produced, directed and choreographed. 

James divorced Losch in 1934, accusing her of adultery with [[Serge Obolensky|Prince Serge Obolensky]], an American hotel executive; her countersuit, in which she made it clear that James was homosexual, failed.&lt;ref&gt;Coleby, Nicola, &quot;A Surreal Life: Edward James, 1907-1984&quot;, Exhibition Catalogue, Royal Pavilion (Brighton, 1998).&lt;/ref&gt;  James was in fact bisexual.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2007/09/24/070924fa_fact_gray Francine du Plessix Gray, Onward and Upward with the Arts, “The Surrealists’ Muse”], ''The New Yorker'', September 24, 2007, p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; After the divorce, James joined a social set in England which included the [[Mitford sisters]] and the composer [[Lord Berners]].

==Surrealism==
[[Image:Portrait of Edward James.jpg|thumb|''[[Not to be Reproduced]]'' a Portrait of Edward James by [[René Magritte]]]]
James is best known as a passionate and early supporter of [[Surrealism]], a movement that was born from the political uncertainty and upheaval between the wars. Rejecting the bourgeois' dominating rationality, surrealists escaped into a world of fantasy and irrationality. He sponsored [[Salvador Dalí]] for the whole of 1938 and his collection of paintings and art objects that subsequently came to be accepted as the finest collection of surrealist work in private hands. He also provided practical help, supporting Dalí for about two years, and allowed [[René Magritte]] to stay in his London house to paint. 

James appeared in two famous surrealist paintings, both by Magritte:
*''[[Not to be Reproduced]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ac-amiens.fr/pedagogie/arts_plastiques/capes04/magritte2.jpg]&lt;/ref&gt;
*''The Pleasure Principle: Portrait of Edward James''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abcgallery.com/M/magritte/magritte59.html The Pleasure Principle (Portrait of Edward James)], by René Magritte. 1937. Oil on canvas. 79 x 63.5 cm. Edward James Foundation, Chichester, UK.&lt;/ref&gt;

Each suggests an alienated person. In the first, James looks away from the centre; in the second he looks into a mirror which shows the back of his head; in the third James's head is a fireball. 

As well as Dalí and Magritte, his art collection included works by [[Hieronymus Bosch]], [[Giorgio de Chirico]], [[Paul Klee]], [[Leonora Carrington]], [[Pavel Tchelitchew]], [[Pablo Picasso]], [[Giacometti]], [[Max Ernst]] and [[Paul Delvaux]], amongst others.&lt;ref&gt;Margaret Hooks, [http://www.surrealeden.com &quot;Surreal Eden: Edward James &amp; Las Pozas&quot;], Princeton Architectural Press, New York, 2006, ISBN 978-1568986128,  p.167&lt;/ref&gt; Most were sold at a well-publicized sale at [[Christies]] two years after his death. 

His intellectual interest in surrealism is demonstrated by his sponsorship of ''[[Minotaure]]'', a lavish Surrealist magazine published in Paris. His refurbishment of Monkton House, in a part of the [[West Dean House|West Dean Estate]], was a Surrealist dream. It was done in collaboration with the pioneering British decorator, [[Syrie Maugham]], and has some of the most iconic Surrealist works on display, including the large [[Mae West Lips Sofa|sofa]] to which [[Salvador Dalí|Dalí]] gave the form and colour of [[Mae West]]'s lips, and his [[Lobster Telephone]] in white. His most fantastic surrealist creation was realised in the Mexican rain forest, a surrealist Sculpture garden, &quot;Las Pozas&quot; (see [[#Las Pozas|below]]).

==New Mexico==
In 1940, James showed up in [[Taos, New Mexico]], [[United States]], as a guest of [[Mabel Dodge Luhan]], where he was known for his amusing, clever eccentricity and effeminate manner. In Taos, he met the Hon. [[Dorothy Brett]], an impoverished  British aristocrat and painter, who in 1941 sold him nine paintings for $580. He later invited the 70 year-old Brett (as she was known) to return to England and reside at West Dean, but she declined.&lt;ref&gt;Sean Hignett and Franklin Watts,''Brett: From Bloomsbury to New Mexico,'' New York, 1983, ISBN 978-0531097755&lt;/ref&gt;

== Las Pozas == &lt;!-- If you change this section heading, also change the redirect at the page &quot;Las Pozas&quot; --&gt;
[[Image:Xilitla Las Pozas 0407 036.jpg|thumb|The surrealist sculpture park ''Las Pozas'', Xilitla.]]
[[Image:Laspozas1.JPG|thumb|right|''Las Pozas'', Xilitla.]] 

Las Pozas (&quot;the Pools&quot;) was created by James, more than {{convert|2000|ft|m}} above sea level, in a subtropical rainforest in the mountains of [[Mexico]] just outside the town of Xilitla. It includes more than {{convert|80|acre|m2}} of natural waterfalls and pools interlaced with towering Surrealist sculptures in concrete.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-30Mar08&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/indexes/2008/03/30/style/t/index.html#pageName=30laspozas &quot;Dream Works: Can a Legendary Surrealist Garden in Mexico Bloom Again?&quot;], ''New York Times Style Magazine'', March 30, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Las Pozas is near the village of [[Xilitla, San Luis Potosí]], a seven-hour drive north of Mexico City. In the early 1940s, James went to [[Los Angeles]], and then decided that he &quot;wanted a Garden of Eden set up . . . and I saw that Mexico was far more romantic” and had &quot;far more room than there is in crowded Southern California” &lt;ref&gt;Margaret Hooks, [http://www.surrealeden.com &quot;Surreal Eden: Edward James &amp; Las Pozas&quot;], Princeton Architectural Press, New York, 2006, ISBN 978-1568986128&lt;/ref&gt;. In [[Hollywood]] in 1941, his lifetime friend and cousin, [[Magic Realism|Magic Realist]] painter [[Bridget Bate Tichenor]], encouraged him to search for a surreal location in Mexico to express his diverse esoteric interests.&lt;ref&gt;Bridget Bate Tichenor Biography http://BridgetBateTichenor.com/&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Cuernavaca, Mexico|Cuernavaca]], he hired Plutarco Gastelum as a guide. They discovered Xilitla in November 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-30Mar08&quot;/&gt; Eventually Plutarco married a local woman and had four children. James was &quot;Uncle Edward&quot;, to the children called James,and frequently stayed with them in a house Plutarco had built, a mock-Gothic cement castle, now a hotel - La Posada El Castillo.&lt;ref name=&quot;L&amp;T&quot;/&gt; 

Between 1949 and 1984, James built scores of surreal concrete structures with names like the House on Three Floors Which Will in Fact Have Five or Four or Six, the House with a Roof like a Whale, and the Staircase to Heaven.&lt;ref name=&quot;L&amp;T&quot;&gt;Gini Alhadeff, [http://www.travelandleisure.com/articles/concrete-jungle &quot;Concrete Jungle&quot;], ''Travel + Leisure&quot;, September 2003&lt;/ref&gt; There were also plantings and beds full of tropical plants, including orchids - there were, apparently, 29,000 at Las Pozas at one time &lt;ref name=&quot;TG-6Nov07&quot;&gt;Joanna Moorhead, [http://arts.guardian.co.uk/art/architecture/story/0,,2206530,00.html &quot;The Magic Kingdom (James' Las Pozas, Mexico)&quot;], ''The Guardian'', 6 November 2007&lt;/ref&gt;- and a variety of small casas (homes), niches, and pens that held exotic birds and wild animals from the world over -- James owned many exotic animals and once took his pet boa constrictors to the Hotel Francis in [[Mexico City]].&lt;ref name=&quot;L&amp;T&quot;/&gt;. 

Massive sculptures up to four stories tall punctuate the site. The many trails throughout the garden site are composed of steps, ramps, bridges and narrow, winding walkways that traverse the valley walls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stepsandfalls.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=14&amp;Itemid=28 &quot;Los Pozas - steps and falls&quot;], virtual tour of the grounds of Las Pozas, DVD, published 2007; retrieved March 30, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; Construction of Las Pozas cost more than $5 million. To pay for it, James sold his collection of Surrealist art at auction.&lt;ref name=&quot;L&amp;T&quot;/&gt; 

In the summer of 2007, the Fundación Pedro y Elena Hernández, the company [[Cemex]], and the government of [[San Luis Potosí]] paid about $2.2 million for Las Pozas and created [http://www.xilitla.org Fondo Xilitla], a foundation that will oversee the preservation and restoration of the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-30Mar08&quot;/&gt;

== West Dean ==
[[Image:The St Roches' Arboretum at West Dean.jpg|thumb|The St Roche's Arboretum at West Dean]]
In 1964, James gave his English estate which included [[West Dean House]] at [[West Dean, West Sussex|West Dean]] to a charitable trust. The Edward James Foundation comprises [[West Dean College]], a centre for the preservation of traditional arts and crafts, through short courses and full-time Diplomas and MAs. One of only two professional Tapestry Weaving studios in the UK, an Art Gallery are all housed on a {{convert|6400|acre|km2|sing=on}} estate which is open to the public through the West Dean Gardens.

[[West Dean College]] is part of the Edward James Foundation set up in 1971 in response to James' vision of establishing “an educational foundation where creative talents can be discovered and developed, and where one can spread culture through the teaching of crafts and the preservation of knowledge that might otherwise be destroyed or forgotten”. 

Edward James is buried in the St Roche's Arboretum at [[West Dean, West Sussex|West Dean]], with the simple inscription ''Edward James 1907 - 1984 Poet''. The stone was carved by [[John Skelton (sculptor)|John Skelton]].

== Writings ==
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;poem&gt;
I have seen such beauty as one man has seldom seen;
:therefore will I be grateful to die in this little room,
surrounded by the forests, the great green gloom
:of trees my only gloom - and the sound, the sound of green.
Here amid the warmth of the rain, what might have been
:is resolved into the tenderness of a tall doom
who says: 'You did your best, rest' - and after you the bloom
:of what you loved and planted still will whisper what you mean.
And the ghosts of the birds I loved, will attend me each a friend;
:like them shall I have flown beyond the realm of words.
You, through the trees, shall hear them, long after the end
:calling me beyond the river. For the cries of birds
continue, as - defended by the cortege of their wings -
:my soul among strange silences yet sings.

&amp;mdash;Edward James, Poet 1907 - 1984{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}&lt;/poem&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

* E. James, &quot;The Bones of my Hand&quot;, privately printed, London 1930. 
* E. James, ''The Glass Omnibus,'' privately printed, London 1934.
* E. James, ''The Gardener Who Saw God'', 1937
* Edward James wrote four poems &quot;Sécheresses&quot; and Francis Poulenc put them in music for choir 4 mixt voices and piano ro orchestra in 1937
* George Melly (ed), ''Swans Reflecting Elephants, My Early Years'', Autobiography of Edward James (Weidenfeld, London 1982).

==Portrait sculpture==
An early marble portrait sculpture of Edward James exists, by the sculptor [[Isamu Noguchi]]. 

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Ballet}}
* [http://www.junglegossip.com/index.htm ''Edward James, Builder of Dreams''], documentary film by Avery Danziger
* [http://www.surrealeden.com ''Surreal Eden: Edward James &amp; Las Pozas''], by Margaret Hooks
* [http://www.westdean.org.uk West Dean, the Edward James Foundation]

&lt;!----re: Las Pozas---&gt;

&lt;!----re: Las Pozas---&gt;

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = James, Edward
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1907
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1984
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:James, Edward}}
[[Category:Alumni of Christ Church, Oxford]]
[[Category:British architects]]
[[Category:British artists]]
[[Category:British gardeners]]
[[Category:English landscape and garden designers]]
[[Category:Landscape design history of England]]
[[Category:1907 births]]
[[Category:1984 deaths]]
[[Category:Gardens in Mexico]]&lt;!---re: Las Pozas---&gt;
[[Category:Landscape design history]]&lt;!---re: Las Pozas---&gt;
[[Category:Surrealism]]
[[Category:Visionary environments]]

[[de:Edward James]]
[[es:Edward James]]
[[pt:Edward James]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
