<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24025" ns="0" title="Polygyny"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | refimprove=March 2009
 | original research=April 2009
 | NPOV=November 2011
}}

[[File:Map3.4Polygyny compressed.jpg|thumb|A world map showing countries by polygyny prevalence, 2010.]]
{{Legal recognition of polygamy}}

'''Polygyny''' (from neo-[[Greek language|Greek]]: [[Wiktionary:πολύς|πολύ]] ''poly'' - &quot;many&quot;, and [[Wiktionary:γυνή|γυνή]] ''gyny'' - &quot;woman or wife&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;''Greek-English Lexicon'', Liddell &amp; Scott, s.v. γυνή&lt;/ref&gt; is a form of marriage in which a man has two or more wives at the same time.&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's Third New International Dictionary, Unabridged'', s.v. 'polygyny'.&lt;/ref&gt;  In countries where the practice is illegal, the man is referred to as a [[bigamist]] or a polygamist. It is distinguished from relationships where a man has a sexual partner outside marriage, such as a [[concubine]], casual sexual partner, [[paramour]], cohabits with a married woman or other culturally but not legally recognized secondary partner. Polygyny is the most common form of [[polygamy]]; the much rarer practice of [[polyandry]] is the form of marriage in which one woman has two or more husbands at the same time.&lt;ref&gt;''Webster's Third New International Dictionary, Unabridged'', s.v. ‘polyandry’.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Polygyny has been practiced in some cultures throughout history. It was partially accepted in ancient [[Hebrews|Hebrew]] society, in classical [[China]], and in sporadic traditional Native American, [[Africa]]n and [[Polynesia]]n cultures. In [[India]] it was known to have been practiced during ancient times. It was accepted in ancient [[Greece]], until the [[Roman Empire]] and the [[Roman Catholic Church]] when having one wife, but multiple lovers became the norm. It was accepted in Sub-Saharan Africa for most of the past two millennia.

In the Hebrew Bible, polygyny was a permitted practice (and required in the case of a [[levirate marriage]]) whilst polyandry (a woman having more than one husband) was seen as adultery.

In the [[United States]], polygyny or &quot;[[plural marriage]]&quot; was allowed in the early [[History of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints|history]] of [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS Church).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kristus.dk/jkk/text.php?id=90225 History of the Church, Volume 5, pages 501-507] from [[kristus.dk]]&lt;/ref&gt; It ended in 1890 under the president of the LDS Church at the time, [[Wilford Woodruff]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://lds.org/scriptures/dc-testament/od/1?lang=eng Doctrine and Covenants - Official Declaration 1], [[LDS Church]]&lt;/ref&gt; Officially since 1899, members of the LDS Church faced excommunication for being polygynous. There are several sects who separated themselves from LDS Church, and who have no ties nor relationship to the LDS Church that continue to practice polygyny despite polygynous [[marriage]] being illegal in the United States.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}

In historical China a child was considered to have more than one mother.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}} For example, a child might have up to four mothers, the first wife being the &quot;official mother&quot; (嫡母 dímǔ) – in spoken language called &quot;big mother&quot; (大媽 dàmā) – the others being regarded as unofficial mothers (庶母 shùmǔ), in spoken language called &quot;little mother&quot; (小媽 xiǎomā) or &quot;aunt&quot; (阿姨 āyí, 姨娘 yíniáng). However, this custom was primarily a result of the concubinage system, where only the first wife by marriage was considered the wife and the mistress of the household. A concubine did not marry her owner. Her main duty was to provide a son to her owner, and any children from the liaison were not regarded as officially hers. But she was also brought into the household to provide sexual pleasure to the man and servitude to his wife.

In polygynous marriages generally, usually one wife is the “queen wife” who is accorded a higher status than the other wives and has some authority over the other wives.&lt;ref&gt;[[Matt Ridley|Ridley, M.]] (1995) ''The [[Red Queen]]: Sex and the Evolution of Human Nature'', Penguin Books, ISBN 0-14-024548-0.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Motivations===

There is also some research that show that males living in polygynous marriages live longer; 12 percent longer on average. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn14564 Polygamy is the key to a long life - life - 19 August 2008 - New Scientist&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Women have been more likely than men to be left unmarried or widowed. One current viable reason is that throughout human history males have always had a higher mortality rate. Polygyny ensured that such women were cared for and also helped ensure the births of the large numbers of children required for the survival of pre-mechanized, largely agrarian cultures in which early mortality rates were high.{{Citation needed|date=June 2007}}

The required inheritance of widows requires men in some societies to marry the widow of a deceased brother. This [[levirate marriage]] helps provide support for her and increases his number of wives.

In some societies only well-to-do men could afford to have more than one wife, particularly if each wife required maintenance of a separate household. The current traditional form of Islam permits as many as four wives, but depending on the man's financial circumstances, fewer wives are more common; indeed, the vast majority of Muslim men are monogamous.

While few present-day states permit polygamous marriages, polygynous male behavior may be observed in the establishment of [[Mistress (lover)|mistresses]], who are openly or secretly supported. In this way, men may be technically monogamous but ''de facto'' polygynous.

Economically, polygyny tends to benefit all but the most desirable women, by giving them more opportunities to marry rich men, who are in short supply. Most men tend to be disadvantaged by polygyny, however, since when many women are able to marry a rich man, it leaves fewer women available for the less rich.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.psychologytoday.com/articles/200706/ten-politically-incorrect-truths-about-human-nature?page=2 Ten Politically Incorrect Truths About Human Nature | Psychology Today&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sociology==
[[File:POLYGYNY.JPG|thumb|300px|right|Figure 1. Frequency of Marriage Types Across Cultures from the Standard Cross-Cultural Sample of pre-industrial societies ([[Standard Cross-Cultural Sample|Murdock &amp; White]] 1969)]]
{{Close relationships}}
===Hebrew Bible===

The [[Hebrew Bible]] indicates that polygyny was practised in ancient [[Israelite]] societies. Though the institution was not extremely common, it was not particularly unusual and was certainly not prohibited but discouraged by the Bible (namely the Mosaic Law recommended that kings should not have many wives, and when Solomon took 1000 wives the Bible cites his polygamy as the reason of the fall of his faith). The Bible mentions approximately forty polygynists, including [[Abraham]], [[Jacob]], [[Esau]], [[David]] and [[King Solomon]], with little or no further remark on the institution.

The [[Torah]], the [[Five Books of Moses]], includes specific regulations on the practice of polygyny. {{Bibleverse||Exodus|21:10|NIV}} states that multiple marriages are not to diminish the status of the first wife, while {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|21:15-17|NIV}} states that a man must award the inheritance due to a [[first-born son]] to the son who was actually born first, even if he hates that son's mother and likes another wife more (implying that he had divorced the first-born son's mother); and {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|17:17|NIV}} states that the king shall not have too many wives.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chabad.org/library/article.asp?AID=9981&amp;showrashi=true Judaica Press Complete Tanach, Devarim - Chapter 17] from [[Chabad.org]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The king's behavior is condemned by Prophet Samuel in {{bibleverse|1|Samuel|8}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The biblical institution of a [[levirate marriage]] was a form of polygyny. {{bibleverse||Deuteronomy|25:5-10|NIV}} required a man to marry and support his deceased brother's [[widow]], if he died without her having given birth to a son. The practice has been justified in that it was important for the deceased brother to have an heir to inherit his lands, and to say the prayers for the dead for him. The practice was also a means to ensure that the widow was provided for. If the eldest brother refused to marry the widow then it was the responsibility of the next brother and so on down the family line.

===Judaism===
{{quote|Polygyny continued to be practiced well into the biblical period, and it is attested among Jews as late as the second century CE.&lt;ref name=coogan&gt;{{cite book|last=Coogan|first1=Michael|title=God and Sex. What the Bible Really Says|url=http://books.google.nl/books?id=2_gPKQEACAAJ&amp;dq=god+and+sex&amp;hl=nl&amp;ei=4fbCTaPKDpGXOrq88Z0I&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwAQ|accessdate=May 5, 2011|edition=1st|year=2010|month=October|publisher=Twelve. Hachette Book Group|location=New York, Boston|isbn=978-0-446-54525-9|page=78}}&lt;/ref&gt;|[[Michael Coogan]]|[[God and Sex|God and Sex. What the Bible Really Says.]]}}

Since the 11th century, [[Ashkenazi]] Jews have followed [[Rabbenu Gershom]]'s ban on polygyny (except in rare circumstances).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.faqs.org/faqs/judaism/FAQ/04-Observance/section-55.html Frequently asked questions, Judaism and Polygamy].&lt;/ref&gt;

Some [[Mizrahi]] Jewish communities (particularly [[Yemenite Jews]] and [[Persian Jews]]) discontinued polygyny much more recently, as they immigrated to countries where it was forbidden or illegal. Such is the case in the [[State of Israel]], which has made polygamy illegal.&lt;ref&gt;''Penal Law Amendment (Bigamy) Law'', 5719-1959.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/839776 The English Law of Bigamy in a Multi-Confessional Society: The Israel Experience] by P Shifman.&lt;/ref&gt; In practice, however, the law is only loosely enforced, primarily so as not to interfere with [[Bedouin]] culture, where polygyny is practiced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1027756.html Victims of polygamy].&lt;/ref&gt; Pre-existing polygynous unions among [[Arab Jews|Jews from Arab countries]] (or other countries where the practice was not prohibited by their tradition and was not illegal in the local law) are also not subject to this Israeli law, although a similar cultural concession to the Bedouin is not extended to Mizrahi Jews, and they are not permitted to enter into new polygamous marriages in Israel.

Among [[Karaite Jews]], who do not adhere to Rabbinic interpretations of the Torah, polygyny is non-existent today. Karaites interpret {{bibleverse||Leviticus|18:18|HE}} to mean that a man can only take a second wife if his first wife gives her consent&lt;ref&gt;Keter Torah on Leviticus, pp.96—97.&lt;/ref&gt; and Karaites interpret {{bibleverse||Exodus|21:10|HE}} to mean that a man can only take a second wife if he is capable of maintaining the same level of marital duties due to his first wife: namely, food, clothing, and sexual gratification.

Because of these two biblical limitations and because nearly all western countries outlaw it, polygyny is considered impractical, and there are no known cases of it among Karaite Jews.

===Christianity===
{{Main|Christian Plural Marriage}}
Polygyny was not practiced by Christians during the New Testament era. Plural marriage is currently rejected by most sects of [[Christianity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Polygamy:  A Cultural and Biblical Perspective |last= Gaskiyane |first= I |year= 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Catechism of the Catholic Church|last= Ratzinger |first= Joseph |page=411 |year= 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Documents of Vatican II|last= Abbott |first= Walter |page=249 |year= 1966}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.gotquestions.org/polygamy.html |title= Why did God allow polygamy / bigamy in the Bible?}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.gameo.org/encyclopedia/contents/M376ME.html/?searchterm=polygamy |title= Marriage|work = Global Anabaptist Mennonite Encyclopedia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://orthodoxeurope.org/page/10/1.aspx#47 |title= Marriage|work = An Online Orthodox Catechism}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Mormon Polygamy:  A History |last= Van Wagoner |first= Richard |authorlink = Richard S. Van Wagoner |year= 1992 | ISBN = 1560850574}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lds.org/ldsorg/v/index.jsp?locale=0&amp;sourceId=9887ec6f164b2110VgnVCM100000176f620a____&amp;vgnextoid=bbd508f54922d010VgnVCM1000004d82620aRCRD |title= Polygamy (Plural Marriage)|work = The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.sbc.net/aboutus/basicbeliefs.asp |title= Southern Baptist Basic Beliefs|work = SBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.mennolink.org/doc/cof/art.19.html|work = MennoLink|title=The Mennonite Confession of Faith:  Acticle 19.  Family, Singleness, Marriage}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.gameo.org/encyclopedia/contents/D674.html|work = GAMEO|title=Dordrecht Confession of Faith 1632}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lcms.org/graphics/assets/media/CTCR/human_sexuality1.pdf|work = Lutheran Church Missouri Synod|title=Human Sexuality:  A Theological Perspective | pages = 10–11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current predominant belief among Christians in the United States is that polygyny is wrong and claim there is New Testament Biblical evidence to support that stance, citing for example {{bibleverse||Matthew|19:4-6|KJV}} (KJV):

{{quote|And he answered and said unto them, Have ye not read, that he which made them at the beginning made them male and female,

And said, For this cause shall a man leave father and mother, and shall cleave to his wife: and they twain shall be one flesh?

Wherefore they are no more [[wikt:twain|twain]], but one flesh. What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder.}}

Some{{Who|date=August 2010}} suggest the New Testament Church did ban polygyny for bishops ([[First Epistle to Timothy|1 Timothy]] 3:2). However, the word for &quot;one&quot; is correctly translated as &quot;first&quot; and as an indefinite article as well, which opens other possible interpretations.&lt;ref&gt;http://home.sprynet.com/~jbwwhite/HEIS_MIA.html&lt;/ref&gt;{{Self-published inline|date=April 2010}}  The [[First Epistle to the Corinthians]] of [[Paul the Apostle]] concisely addresses each of the two gender forms of [[polygamy]] (in the sequence first [[polyandry]] and next polygyny) as follows: &quot;But because of cases of sexual immorality, each man should have his own wife and each woman her own husband.&quot; (1 Corinthians 7:2, NRSV)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblestudytools.com/nrs/1-corinthians/7-2.html &quot;1 Corinthians 7:2, New Revised Standard Version Bible, copyright 1989, Division of Christian Education of the National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Additional contrasts between 1 Timothy and 1 Corinthians on other specific topics are compiled within broader-scale discussions on [[authorship of the Pauline epistles]].

Interviewed by ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine about his book, [[Michael Coogan]] said that according to [[Sola Scriptura]], the [[Mormon]]s were right about [[polygamy]].&lt;ref name=silver&gt;Alexandra Silver [http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2027582,00.html What the Bible Has to Say About Sex] Time.com&lt;/ref&gt;  He was chief editor for the [[Oxford Annotated Bible]], 4th Edition&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford_4th&quot;&gt;Michael D. Coogan, ed. ''The New Oxford Annotated Bible with Apocrypha, New Revised Standard Version, Fourth Edition'' Copyright© Jan 2010 by Oxford University Press, Inc. [http://www.oup.com/us/collections/NOAB/?view=usa Publisher Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; (as well as the prececessor 3rd Edition).  As to why fundamentalist Mormons are &quot;right in a sense&quot; regarding polygyny, the reasoning he offers does include both &quot;There is no unequivocal statement in the Bible, especially the Hebrew Bible, that says that monogamy should be the norm&quot;, and also &quot;If you're going to be a strict literalist, there's nothing wrong with polygamy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;silver&quot;/&gt;  The ''Oxford Annotated Bible, 4th Edition''&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford_4th&quot;/&gt; in turn does, in comparison, annotate 1 Corinthians 7:2 as &quot;...Paul counsels monogamy...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;This quote is excerpted from the full sentence, &quot;Against the temptation to immorality, Paul counsels monogamy and fidelity in marriage; compare or confer with 1 Thess 4:3-5.&quot; Copyright© Jan 2010 by Oxford University Press, Inc.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;welborn&quot;&gt;Laurence L. Welborn &quot;The First Letter of Paul to the Corinthians&quot;, in Michael D. Coogan, ed. ''The New Oxford Annotated Bible with Apocrypha, New Revised Standard Version, Fourth Edition'' 2010:2008&lt;/ref&gt;

===East Asia===
Having offspring is very important in Chinese culture. China has practiced polygyny for thousands of years. Polygyny had been legal and was written in the law as recently as the end of the Qing/Ching dynasty of the imperial China (1911).

A part of the Confucian tradition indicates the importance of procreation, as it is considered to be part of [[filial piety]]. Therefore, it is possible that this type of thinking influenced the view towards polygyny.

In the past, Emperors could have hundreds to thousands of concubines. And subsequently rich officials and merchants could also have a number of concubines besides wives. The first wife is head or mother wife, other wives are under her headship if the husband is away, and others are concubines and have lower status than the full wives. Offspring from concubines did receive equal wealth/legacy from their father.

The original wife (or legal wife) is referred to as the 正室 zhèngshì /정실 (main room) both in China, Japan and Korea. 大婆 dàpó (big woman/big wife) is the slang term. Both terms indicate the orthodox nature and hierarchy. The official wife is either called &quot;big mother&quot; (大媽 dàmā), mother or auntie. The child of the concubine simply addresses the big mother as auntie.

The written word for the second woman is 側室 cèshì /측실 and literally means &quot;she who occupied the side room&quot;. This word is also used in both China and Japan. They are also called 妾 qiè/첩 in China and Korea.

The common terms referring to the second woman and the act of having the second woman respectively are 二奶 (èrnǎi / yi nai), literally &quot;the second wife&quot;. The terms have been widely used in the media.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com.hk/search?hl=en&amp;q=%E4%BA%8C%E5%A5%B6&amp;btnG=Google+Search&amp;meta= 二奶 - Google Search&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Though illegal, it is still practiced by many richer men who can afford to support a [[mistress (lover)|mistress]] and her subsequent children. The mass media often report polygyny cases of the rich and the famous.

====People's Republic of China====
In modern mainland China, polygamy (and by extension polygyny) is illegal under Marriage Law passed in 1951{{Dubious|date=March 2009}}, except for those members of an ethnic minority who traditionally practice polygamy (both polygyny and polyandry){{Dubious|date=May 2010}}. Polygyny was seen as a characteristic of the [[bourgeoisie]] and as such, many senior Communist leaders who had mistresses and concubines during the [[Long March]] were forced to disband them. Because of this, polygyny is virtually unheard of in China today{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}.&lt;!---I hate to use Dubious again, but these statements seem very unfounded. Source them when you can, please---&gt;

However, with the opening up of the country and the increased contact with Hong Kong and Taiwan, certain polygamous activities began appearing. Cross-border polygyny is ever increasing between PRC, Hong Kong and ROC.{{Dubious|date=March 2009}}&lt;!---Slanderous information---&gt;

====Taiwan====
Polygyny is illegal in the 1930 ROC civil law.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shs.edu.tw/works/essay/2008/03/2008032917040336.pdf SHS.edu.tw 民法－結婚要件之研析]&lt;/ref&gt; However, it is common for some richer Taiwanese to have secret second lovers who become concubines not living together with the wife.{{Citation needed|date=March 2007}} Taiwanese merchants, businessmen and workers are stationed in mainland China during work trips, and it is usual to keep secret lovers or even secret families there.

====Hong Kong and Macau====
Polygyny was banned in October 1971 but the practice is still evident. [[Chinese people|Chinese]] men in [[Hong Kong]] could still practice polygamy by virtue of the [[Qing Code]], which ended only with the passing of the Marriage Act of 1971. A famous example is Dr [[Stanley Ho]] who owns the [[Casino Lisboa, Macau|Casino Lisboa]] in [[Macau]]. He has four wives. His uncle has 12 wives.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}}

Kevin Murphy of the [[International Herald Tribune]] reported on the cross-border polygamy phenomenon in Hong Kong in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.iht.com/articles/1995/02/07/lunar.php .&lt;/ref&gt; The cost of maintaining a second family is lower in the PRC. Since work pressure in Hong Kong is extremely high and the birth rate is the lowest in the world, many local businessmen keep a secret concubine across the border in mainland China.{{Citation needed|date=September 2007}} Girls in mainland China are moreover more willing to be full-time mothers at a younger age.

In a research paper of Berlin Humboldt University on sexology, Doctor Man-Lun Ng estimated about 300,000 men to have mistresses in China. In 1995, 40% of extramarital affairs involved a stable partner&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.hu-berlin.de/sexology/IES/hongkong.html The International Encyclopedia of Sexuality: Hong Kong&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Period drama is performed to this day depicting the former culture of polygamy (usually polygyny). A famous example is the ''[[Wuxia]]'' novel ''[[The Deer and the Cauldron]]'' by Hong Kong writer [[Jin Yong|Louis Cha]], in which the protagonist [[Wei Xiaobao]] has seven wives. The novel and its film and TV series adaptations became immensely popular among Chinese-speaking communities around the world.

===Islam===
{{Main|Polygamy in Islam}}

Although it is permitted in most Islamic countries under certain circumstances,{{Clarify|date=July 2010}} polygamy is not widely practiced under Islam. In fact, it is claimed{{where?|date=November 2011}} that Islam was the first religion to have limited the number of wives a man is permitted to four, and that Islam alone has expressly banned polyandry. Men who marry more than one woman may do so with the constraints that they are responsible for treating all their wives with kindness and dignity as well as for providing for their material needs equally.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

Many majority [[Muslim]] countries retain the traditional [[Sharia]] which interprets teachings of the Quran to permit polygamy with up to four wives, as long as it is practiced under the specified conditions. Exceptions to this include [[Albania]], [[Tunisia]], [[Turkey]], and former [[USSR]] republics. Though about 70% of the population of Albania is [[Cultural Muslim|historically Muslim]], the majority is non-practicing. Turkey and Tunisia are countries with overwhelmingly Muslim populations that enforce [[Laïcité|secularist practices]] by law. In the former USSR republics, a prohibition against polygamy has been inherited from [[Law of the Soviet Union|Soviet Law]]. A current revival of polygamy in the [[Muslim World]] has fueled attempts to re-legalize and re-legitimize it in some countries and communities where it is illegal.

====Russia====
Polygamy is illegal throughout the [[Russian Federation]] but is tolerated in predominantly Muslim republics such as Chechnya, [[Ingushetia]], and [[Dagestan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/europe/article338474.ece War-ravaged Chechnya needs polygamy, says its leader - Europe, World - The Independent&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ramzan Kadyrov]], President of the [[Chechen Republic]], has been quoted on radio as saying that the depopulation of [[Chechnya]] by war justifies legalizing polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pilegesh.blogspot.com/2007/02/i-do-i-do-i-do-i-do-economic-case-for.html Pilegesh.org: I Do, I Do, I Do, I Do The Economic Case for Polygamy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Kadyrov has been supported by Nafigallah Ashirov, the Chairman of the Council of Grand [[Mufti]]s of Russia, with  the statement that polygamy is already widespread among Muslim communities of the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ipsnews.net/news.asp?idnews=32064 SOCIETY: 'Polygamy Could Supply More Russians' - IPS ipsnews.net&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although non-Muslim Russian populations are historically monogamous, Russian politician [[Vladimir Zhirinovsky]] offered to legalize polygyny in order to tackle the demographic crisis of [[Russian people|Russians]]. Zhirinovsky made his first proposal to legalize polygamy as early as 1993, after Kadyrov's declaration that he would introduce an amendment to legalize polygyny for all Russian citizens.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sptimes.ru/index.php?action_id=2&amp;story_id=14235 The St. Petersburg Times - Zhirinovsky: When One Wife Is Not Enough&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/4610396.stm BBC NEWS | Europe | Polygamy proposal for Chechen men&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Kyrgyzstan====
Although illegal, polygamy is a traditional practice that has been revived in [[Kyrgyzstan]]. A proposal to decriminalize polygamy came before the Kyrgyz parliament and on March 26, 2007, despite strong backing of the Justice Minister, the country's ombudsman and the Muslim Women's organization ''[[Mutakalim]]'' that gathered 40,000 signatures in favour of polygamy, the parliament rejected the bill. President [[Kurmanbek Bakiyev]] is known as a prominent opponent of legalizing polygyny.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2007/3/D46AEFBC-4179-4966-806C-E0D37A9C815C.html Kyrgyzstan: Debate On Legalized Polygamy Continues&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2007/03/3a857e81-77ec-42af-a249-e0ed943d85f4.html?napage=3 Features - Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tajikistan====
Due to a recent increase in the number of polygamous marriages, proposals were made in [[Tajikistan]] to re-legalize polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurasianet.org/departments/culture/articles/eav102002.shtml Central Asia: Increase In Polygamy Attributed To Economic Hardship, Return To Tradition | EurasiaNet.org&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Tajik women who want to be second wives are particularly supportive of decriminalizing polygyny. Mukhiddin Kabiri, the Deputy Chairman of the [[Islamic Renaissance Party of Tajikistan]] states that legislation is unlikely to stop the growth in polygyny and criticizes the ruling élite for speaking out against the practice while taking more than one wife themselves.&lt;ref&gt;[http://iwpr.net/?p=rca&amp;s=f&amp;o=162938&amp;apc_state=henirca2002 IWPR Institute for War &amp; Peace Reporting&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other former USSR republics====
There have also been recent arguments in favour of re-legalizing polygamy in other ex-Soviet Muslim republics like [[Kazakhstan]], [[Azerbaijan]] and [[Uzbekistan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rickross.com/reference/polygamy/polygamy298.html Saidazimova, Gulnoza.  ''Polygamy hurts - in the pocket.'' Reprinted from Asia Times Online, February 4, 2005  &lt;/ref&gt;

====Bosnia and Herzegovina====
The Muslim communities of [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]] have been traditionally known to practice polygamy at a very limited level. The custom last existed in [[Cazin|Cazinska Krajina]] in the early 1950s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.everyculture.com/multi/A-Br/Bosnian-Americans.html Bosnian Americans - History, Modern era, The first bosnians in america&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Although illegal in the country, polygamy is encouraged by certain religious circles and there is a current increase in the number of practitioners. This trend appears linked with the advent of [[Wahhabism]] in the [[Balkans]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.b92.net/eng/insight/opinions.php?nav_id=40280 B92 - Insight - Viewpoint - Emissaries of Militant Islam Make Headway in Bosnia&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Bosniaks|Bosniak]] population in neighbouring [[Sandžak]] has also been affected by this trend in Bosnia. There have been attempts to adopt an entire Islamic jurisdiction including polygamy but these moves have been rejected. However, this has not barred the top cleric, the Mufti of [[Novi Pazar]], Muamer Zukorlić from taking a second wife.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wluml.org/english/newsfulltxt.shtml?cmd%5B157%5D=x-157-546374 Bosnia and Herzegovina: The veil comes down, again | Women Reclaiming and Redefining Cultures&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Turkey====
In [[Turkey]], polygamy has been illegal since the adoption of the Turkish Civil Code in 1926, a milestone in [[Atatürk]]'s secularist reforms.

Polygamy is a common occurrence in [[Kurds|Kurdish]] villages.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/this_world/4165896.stm BBC NEWS | Programmes | This World | The hidden wives of Turkey&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, it is on the rise in Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opinionjournal.com/taste/?id=110007775 Opinion &amp; Commentary - Wall Street Journal - Wsj.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; An opinion poll in 2004 showed that 63% of Turks favored polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.parapundit.com/archives/002388.html#002388 ParaPundit: Most Turks In Favor Of Polygamy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; On April 6, 2007, the Municipal Assembly of Çıplaklı in [[Alanya]], composed of members of the ruling moderate Islamist [[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|AK Parti]] and conservative-liberal [[Motherland Party (Turkey)|ANAP]], unanimously adopted a resolution to support men who consider taking a second wife (''kuma''). The people of Çıplaklı are [[Yörük]], a [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] ethnicity who practice [[transhumance]]. &quot;When we go to the summer pastures and leave our wives behind, we feel very lonely,&quot; explained Ali İhsan Topal, a member of the Assembly from the AK Parti.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radikal.com.tr/haber.php?haberno=217712 Radikal-çevrimiçi / Politika / Belediye kuma alınmasına destek olacak!&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sororal polygyny====
'''Sororal polygyny''' is a [[Types of marriages|type of marriage]] in which two or more sisters share a husband. In [[Islam]], this type of polgyny is specifically prohibited.
Reference from [[Quran]] (Chapter 4, verse 23):
{{quote|Forbidden unto you are your mothers, and your daughters, and your sisters, and your father's sisters, and your mother's sisters, and your brother's daughters and your sister's daughters, and your foster-mothers, and your foster-sisters, and your mothers-in-law, and your step-daughters who are under your protection (born) of your women unto whom ye have gone in - but if ye have not gone in unto them, then it is no sin for you (to marry their daughters) - and the wives of your sons who (spring) from your own loins. And (it is forbidden unto you) that ye should have two sisters together, except what hath already happened (of that nature) in the past (before this revelation). Lo! Allah is ever Forgiving, Merciful.}}

===Hinduism===
Polygyny is legal according to the [[Hinduism|Hindu]] scriptures. Many mythological and epical characters are well known for practising polygyny. [[Krishna]], one of the incarnations of [[Vishnu]] had 16108 consorts at his kingdom of [[Dwarka]]. [[Pandu]], the father of the [[Pandava|Pandavas]] in [[Mahabharata]] had two wives Kunti and Madri.

===United States and Canada===

Polygyny is illegal in the United States and Canada, with some exceptions existing in Canada's provinces of [[Saskatchewan]] and [[British Columbia]]

[[Mormon fundamentalism]] is a belief in the validity of selected [[fundamentalism|fundamental]] aspects of [[Mormonism]] as taught and practiced in the nineteenth century. The principle most often associated with fundamental latter-day saint teachings is [[plural marriage]], a form of polygyny first taught by [[Joseph Smith, Jr.]], the founder of the [[Latter Day Saint movement]].

At times, sources have claimed there are as many as 60,000 Fundamentalist latter-day saints in the United States,&lt;ref&gt;Martha Sonntag Bradley, &quot;Polygamy-Practicing Mormons&quot; in [[J. Gordon Melton]] and Martin Baumann (eds.) (2002). ''Religions of the World: A Comprehensive Encyclopedia'' '''3''':1023–1024.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Dateline NBC]]'', 2001-01-02.&lt;/ref&gt; with fewer than half of them living in polygamous households.&lt;ref&gt;Ken Driggs, &quot;Twentieth-Century Polygamy and Fundamentalist Mormons in Southern Utah&quot;, ''[[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]]'', Winter 1991, pp. 46–47.&lt;/ref&gt; However, others have suggested that there may be as few as 20,000 Mormon fundamentalists&lt;ref&gt;Irwin Altman, &quot;Polygamous Family Life: The Case of Contemporary Mormon Fundamentalists&quot;, ''[[Utah Law Review]]'' (1996) p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = DMQ&gt;D. Michael Quinn, [http://content.lib.utah.edu/u?/dialogue,10141 &quot;Plural Marriage and Mormon Fundamentalism&quot;], [[Dialogue: A Journal of Mormon Thought]] '''31'''(2) (Summer 1998): 1–68, accessed 2009-03-27.&lt;/ref&gt; with only 8,000 to 15,000 practicing polygamy.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Eliot Smith, &quot;'The Mormon Question' Revisited: Anti-Polygamy Laws and the Free Exercise Clause&quot;, LL.M. thesis, [[Harvard Law School]], 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The largest Mormon fundamentalist groups are the [[Fundamentalist Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints]] (FLDS Church) and the [[Apostolic United Brethren]] (AUB).  The FLDS Church is estimated to have 10,000 members residing in the sister cities of [[Hildale, Utah|Hildale]], Utah and [[Colorado City, Arizona|Colorado City]], Arizona; [[Eldorado, Texas|Eldorado]], Texas; [[Westcliffe, Colorado|Westcliffe]], Colorado; [[Mancos, Colorado|Mancos]], Colorado; [[Creston, British Columbia|Creston]] and [[Bountiful, British Columbia|Bountiful]], British Columbia; and [[Pringle, South Dakota|Pringle]], South Dakota.&lt;ref&gt;[http://attorneygeneral.utah.gov/polygamy/The_Primer.pdf &quot;The Primer&quot;] - Helping Victims of Domestic Violence and Child Abuse in Polygamous Communities. A joint report from the offices of the Attorney Generals of Arizona and Utah.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Africa===

Polygyny is more widespread in Africa than in any other continent.&lt;ref&gt;Clignet, R., ''Many Wives, Many Powers'', Northwestern University Press, Evanston (1970), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; Generally in rural areas with growing populations, the higher the incidence of polygyny, the greater the delay of first marriage for young men, and this creates a surplus of marriageable girls. Widespread polygyny is thus a major source of tension between younger and older men, and also between older husbands and younger wives. The higher the average polygyny rate, the greater the element of gerontocracy. Quite apart from the actual rate of polygyny, the distribution of wives may be uneven, reflecting a source of competitiveness or inequality among married men. Where there is a more even spread of wives, this reflects a more egalitarian and conformist attitude. It follows that comparison between profiles of polygyny for various African societies provides an insight into their inner characteristics.&lt;ref&gt;Spencer, Paul, ''The Pastoral Continuum: the Marginalization of Tradition in East Africa'', Clarendon Press Oxford, 1998, (pp. 51-92. &quot;Polygyny and the Manifestations of Inequality&quot;)&lt;/ref&gt;

==In nature==
{{Expand section|date=December 2009}}
Several species such as the [[wood mouse]] ''Apodemus sylvaticus'' possess a polygamous social order in which males mate with multiple females. Such circumstances result in competition between males during reproductive periods. This competition can extend beyond the superficial scrambling for females and exists at a microscopic level as competition between spermatozoa in the reproductive tract of the female organism.

A variety of methods for practicing polygamy can be observed in the animal kingdom.&lt;ref&gt;[http://faculty.vassar.edu/suter/1websites/bejohns/mateselection/files/polygyny.htm Polygyny&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, female defense polygyny is seen in marine amphipods, where the male herds the females into a cluster. This allows them to be protected by the male, while the male has continuous access to the females. Resource defense polygyny is a strategy seen in [[African cichlid]] fish, where the male collects empty snail shells which the females use to lay eggs. A third type is scramble competition polygamy, where females are widely spaced or fertility is time-limited, as in [[orangutans]].

Elephant seals are known from long-term behavioral studies to be highly polygynous.&lt;ref&gt;[http://beheco.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/arh112v1 Extreme polygyny among southern elephant seals on Sea Lion Island, Falkland Islands&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Harem===
{{Main|Harem (zoology)}}
In [[zoology]], the term '''Harem''' is used for the social organization of certain species, such as those in the [[Hominidae]] and [[Equidae]] [[family (biology)|families]], in groups of females surrounding a single dominant male. Non-dominant males will organize themselves in [[bachelor group]]s.

===Bachelor band===&lt;!--article &quot;bachelor group&quot; and &quot;bachelor band&quot; redirect to this section title---&gt;
{{See also|Clique}}
Among members of certain species, such as [[Ape|apes (Superfamily Hominoidea)]], [[horse]]s (more broadly, [[Equidae|Family Equidae]]), [[dog]]s and [[whale]]s, young non-dominant males can spontaneously form &quot;bachelor groups&quot; or &quot;bachelor bands.&quot;

==See also==
{{div col|cols=3}}
* [[Cairo Declaration on Human Rights in Islam]]
* [[Mating system]]
* [[Monogamy]]
* [[Mormonism and polygamy]]
* [[Plaçage]]
* [[Polyamory]]
* [[Polyandry]]
* [[Polygamy]]
* [[Polygamy in Christianity]]
* [[Polygynandry]]
* [[Polygyny threshold model]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* Low, Bobbi S. (1990). Marriage systems and pathogen stress in human societies . ''American Zoologist 30:'' 325‑339. [http://sitemaker.umich.edu/snre-faculty-bobbilow/files/pathogenstressamzoo.pdf Full text] - (Paper reports [[positive correlation]] between pathogen stress &amp; polygyny.)
* [[Korotayev]] A., [[Dmitri Bondarenko|Bondarenko D.]] [http://www.scribd.com/doc/16411737/Korotayev-A-Bondarenko-D-Polygyny-and-Democracy-a-CrossCultural-Comparison-CrossCultural-Research-The-Journal-of-Comparative-Social-Science Polygyny and Democracy: a Cross-Cultural Comparison // Cross-Cultural Research. The Journal of Comparative Social Science. 34/2 (May2000). P. 190–208] (Paper reports [[negative]] [[correlation]] between polygyny &amp; democracy.)

==External links==
* [http://www.patriarchpublishinghouse.com/ Patriarch Publishing House]
* [http://www.cuhk.edu.hk/ant/research.htm The Chinese University Of Hong Kong: Anthropology Department: Research Topics]
* [http://www.cuhk.edu.hk/ant/others/past1999.htm Hong Kong Anthropological Society: speeches summary]
* [http://www.biblicalpolygamy.com/ BiblicalPolygamy.com]
* [http://www.righteouswarriors.com/ Righteouswarriors.com]
* [http://www.scribd.com/doc/17263693/Korotayev-Munck-Galtons-Asset-and-Flowers-Problem “Galton’s Asset” and “Flower’s Problem”: Cultural Networks and Cultural Units in Cross-Cultural Research (or, the Male Genital Mutilations and Polygyny in Cross-Cultural Perspective)]
{{Close plural relationships}}

[[Category:Anthropology]]
[[Category:Mating systems]]
[[Category:Polygamy]]

[[br:Lieswregiezh]]
[[ca:Poligínia]]
[[de:Polygynie]]
[[es:Poliginia]]
[[eo:Poliginio]]
[[eu:Poliginia]]
[[fa:چندزنی]]
[[fr:Polygynie]]
[[ko:일부다처제]]
[[is:Fjölkvæni]]
[[it:Poliginia]]
[[he:פוליגיניה]]
[[ka:პოლიგინია]]
[[lv:Poliginija]]
[[ml:ബഹുഭാര്യത്വം]]
[[nl:Polygynie]]
[[ja:一夫多妻制]]
[[pl:Wielożeństwo]]
[[pt:Poliginia]]
[[ru:Полигиния]]
[[sah:Полигиния]]
[[sq:Poligjinia]]
[[sr:Полигинија]]
[[fi:Polygynia]]
[[ta:பலமனைவி மணம்]]
[[tr:Polijini]]
[[uk:Полігінія]]
[[zh:一夫多妻制]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
