<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="241099" ns="0" title="Villanova University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image          = [[File:Villanova University Seal.svg|200px]]
|name           = Villanova University
|motto          = Veritas, Unitas, Caritas ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng       = [[Truth]], [[Cooperation|Unity]], [[Love]]''
|established    = 1842
|type           = [[Private school|Private]]
|affiliation    = [[Roman Catholic]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Order of Saint Augustine]]
|endowment      = $297 million&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;
|president      = [[Rev. Peter M. Donohue, O.S.A.]]
|city           = [[Villanova, Pennsylvania|Villanova]]
|state          = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country        = [[United States]]
|students       = 10,482&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.villanova.edu/villanova/media/fastfacts.html |title=Villanova University: Villanova at a Glance |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad      = 6,394
|postgrad       = 3,200
|faculty        = 545
|staff          = 2,000
|campus         = [[Suburban]], {{convert|254|acre|km2}}
|nickname       = [[Villanova Wildcats|Wildcats]]
|mascot         = Will D. Cat
|fightsong      = ''V for Vilanova''
|colors         = [[Blue]] and [[White]] {{Color box|#00337F}}&amp;nbsp;{{Color box|#FFFFFF}}
|website        = [http://www.villanova.edu/ www.villanova.edu]
|logo           = [[File:Villanova University Logo.svg|center|200px]]
|}}
'''Villanova University''' is a private university located in [[Radnor Township, Pennsylvania|Radnor Township]], a suburb northwest of [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]], in the [[United States]]. Named for [[Thomas of Villanova|Saint Thomas of Villanova]], the school is the oldest  [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] university in the [[Commonwealth (U.S. state)|Commonwealth]] of Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;largest catholic&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/enroll/admission/university/profile.htm |title=University Profile |work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2007-03-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070218115621/http://www.villanova.edu/enroll/admission/university/profile.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Founded in 1842 by the [[Order of Saint Augustine]], the university traces its roots to [[St. Augustine Church, Philadelphia|old Saint Augustine's Church]], Philadelphia, which the Augustinian friars founded in 1796, and to its parish school, Saint Augustine's Academy, which was established in 1811.

==History==
[[File:Oldnova.jpg|thumb|250|right|Villanova College in 1849]]
In October 1841, two [[Order of Saint Augustine|Augustinian friars]] from Saint Augustine's Church in Philadelphia purchased the {{convert|200|acre|km2|sing=on}} &quot;Belle Air&quot; estate in Radnor Township with the intention of starting a school. The school, which was called the &quot;Augustinian College of Vilanova,&quot; opened in 1842. However, the [[Philadelphia Nativist Riots]] of 1844 that burned Saint Augustine's Church in Philadelphia caused financial difficulties for the Augustinians, and the college was closed in February 1845. The college reopened in 1846 and graduated its first class in 1847. In March 1848, the governor of Pennsylvania incorporated the school and gave it the power to grant degrees.  In 1859, the first master's degree was conferred on a student.&lt;ref&gt;Address by Dean of the Graduate School Gerald Long to incoming graduate students. 24 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1857, the school closed again as the demand for priests in Philadelphia prevented adequate staffing, and the crisis of the [[Panic of 1857]] strained the school financially. The school remained closed throughout the Civil War and reopened in September 1865; since then it has operated continuously.&lt;ref name=&quot;vill-history1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heritage.villanova.edu/history.html |title=The Mission and Heritage of Vilanova University|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2007-08-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first great expansion of Vilanova began in the late 1890s. Desiring an institution that would &quot;rank among the best in the United States,&quot; the college built more classrooms, dormitories, and recreational facilities, and bought instructional equipment.

The School of Technology was established in 1905. In 1915, a two-year pre-medical program was established to help students meet medical schools' new requirements. This led to a four-year pre-medical program, the B.S. in biology, and the founding of the sciences division in 1926.[[Image:Corr Hall.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Corr Hall from The Grotto]]

Vilanova was all-male until 1918, when the college began evening classes to educate [[nun]]s to teach in [[parochial school]]s. In 1938, a laywoman received a Villanova degree for the first time. It was not until the nursing school opened in 1953 that women permanently began attending Villanova full-time. In 1958, the College of Engineering admitted its first female student; other colleges admitted women only as commuters. Vilanova University became fully coeducational in 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;vill-history1&quot;/&gt;

During [[World War II]], Villanova was one of 131 colleges and universities nationally that took part in the [[V-12 Navy College Training Program]] which offered students a path to a Navy commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanova-v-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://heritage.villanova.edu/vu/heritage/allthings/2002SPh.htm |title=Amidst the Depression and War, Progress Still Prevails |publisher=[[Villanova, Pennsylvania]]: Villanova University|last= |first= |accessdate=September 29, 2011 |date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[World War II]], Villanova expanded, returning [[veterans]] swelling enrollments and the faculty growing fourfold. Additional facilities were built and in 1953, the College of [[Nursing]] and the School of [[Law]] were established. Villanova achieved university status on November 18, 1953. Between 1954 and 1963, 10 new buildings were built or bought on land adjacent to the campus, including Bartley, Mendel, and Dougherty Halls.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan2405&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.villanovan.com/media/storage/paper581/news/2006/09/07/Features/The-Facts.About.The.History.Of.Villanova-2262405-page3.shtml |title=The Facts About the History of Vilanova|work=The Villanovan|accessdate=2007-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1970s and 1980s, Vilanova worked to become a nationally recognized university. The quality of faculty and students improved dramatically and international studies programs were introduced. Additional residential and recreational facilities were constructed, and efforts to increase the [[Financial endowment|endowment]] were undertaken.

In the 1980s, endowed chairs were established in [[theology]], [[philosophy]], [[engineering]], and [[business]]; scholarship funding was increased, and the curriculum expanded and improved. An extensive building campaign created facilities for the Colleges of Liberal Arts and Sciences, Engineering, Commerce and Finance, and student residences on the south and the west campuses.  In 1985, the school also won the Men's NCAA basketball tournament, giving the school increased national exposure.

Over the history of the university, it has also served as a headquarters of the [[Order of Saint Augustine]] in North America, and has provided staff to establish Catholic high schools throughout the United States, such as [[St. Augustine High School (San Diego, California)|St. Augustine High School]] in [[San Diego, California]], which was established in 1922 with teaching staff dispatched from Vilanova. {{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

==Campus==
[[Image:Villanova Church.jpg|thumb|upright|right|St. Thomas of Villanova Chapel, on the Villanova University campus.]]
Villanova University sits on {{convert|254|acre|km2}} just {{convert|12|mi|km}} from [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania|Philadelphia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;location&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/enroll/admission/university/location.htm|title=Campus location|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2007-10-09 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070523165433/http://www.villanova.edu/enroll/admission/university/location.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The campus was formerly known as [[Arboretum Villanova]] which includes roughly 1,500 trees across campus, including the only known instance of a naturally-growing [[Sequoia sempervirens|sequoia]] east of the Mississippi River.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}  Official Arboretum status has been revoked due to the university's lack of upkeep to Arboretum rules and standards such as the planting of new trees and the offering of tours.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan92508&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://media.www.villanovan.com/media/storage/paper581/news/2008/09/25/Features/Vu.Not.A.National.Arboretum-3450294.shtml|title=VU: Not a national arboretum|work=The Villanovan|accessdate=2009-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are three named areas on the campus, all within easy walking distance:
*Main Campus contains most of the educational buildings, administration buildings, Student Center, Library, Bookstore, the Villanova Chapel, the main cafeteria along with a variety of coffee shops and eateries, the newly built Athletic Center as well as the Pavilion and Villanova Stadium, and many freshmen, sophomore and junior student residences.
*West Campus contains the Law School, St. Mary's hall (a large building for single housing, a cafeteria, classrooms, indoor swimming pool, market, etc.) some administrative buildings, and housing for juniors as well as some seniors who are permitted to live on campus. Also included are basketball and tennis courts, soccer fields, volleyball courts and [[barbecue]] pits. The SEPTA Paoli/Thorndale station - Villanova is also located here. There is also the Law School parking garage in addition to apartment parking.
*South Campus contains 7 freshman and sophomore residence halls, Donohue Court (South Campus Cafeteria) and Donohue Market (South Campus Market). The [[SEPTA Route 100]] line has a stop right behind Stanford Hall.

===Main Campus===
[[Image:Villanova University A panoramic shot.jpg|thumb|300px|right|A panoramic view of the Main Campus in early spring]]
The most prominent feature of the Villanova campus is [[St. Thomas of Villanova Church]], whose dual spires are Villanova's tallest structure. The cornerstone for the church was laid in 1883, with construction continuing until 1887.  The church underwent major renovations in 1943 and 1992.  It is built in [[Gothic Revival architecture|Gothic Revival style]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;St. Thomas of Villanova Church&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/homepage/artofvillanova/stvchurch.htm|title=St. Thomas of Villanova church |accessdate=2008-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The church lies at the head of the path crossing [[U.S. Route 30|Lancaster Avenue]] into the parking lots and toward South Campus. As such, it is a popular meeting place for students, and hosts three student-oriented masses on Sunday nights at 6:00PM, 8:00PM, and 10:00PM.  The church is also home to St. Thomas of Villanova Parish, whose Masses take place Sunday morning.  The stained-glass windows of the church depict the life of [[Augustine of Hippo|St. Augustine of Hippo]].
[[File:VillanovaMonastery.jpg|thumb|left|St. Thomas of Villanova Monastery]]
Situated behind the Church is Mendel Field, around which sit six major campus buildings: Mendel Hall, Tolentine Hall, White Hall, Falvey Hall, John Barry Hall, and the Chemical Engineering Building.  Mendel Hall, named for pioneering [[genetics|geneticist]] and Augustinian monk [[Gregor Mendel]], holds science labs, lecture halls, and other facilities. Mendel Hall's two large buildings are connected underground and by a second-floor indoor bridge that forms the gateway between West and Main Campus. In 1998, the college commissioned a {{convert|7|ft|m|sing=on}} [[bronze sculpture]] of Mendel by Philadelphia [[sculpture|sculptor]] [[James Peniston]], and installed it outside the hall's entrance.&lt;ref name=&quot;sculpture&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jepsculpture.com/mendel.shtml |title=James Peniston Sculpture |accessdate=2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tolentine Hall, one of the oldest buildings on campus, houses classrooms, academic offices such as the Registrar's Office and the Office of the President, and computer labs, and is connected to Villanova's monastery, St. Thomas Hall.  White Hall, consisting mainly of classrooms and laboratories, is directly connected to the Chemical Engineering Building, which was built in 1947.  &quot;Old Falvey&quot; is the [[annex]] of the [[Falvey Memorial Library]], named for Rev. Daniel Falvey who served as librarian from 1940 until his death in 1962.  It is home to some classrooms in the Art History and Education departments as well as some offices, along with The Math Center, The Writing Center, and The Augustinian Heritage Institute, and the Matthew J. Ryan Center, a division of the Political Science Department.  John Barry Hall, named for naval officer [[John Barry (naval officer)|Commodore John Barry]], houses the Navy ROTC Program.  To the West of the Church, the Center for Engineering Education and Research (CEER), which opened in 1998, holds engineering labs, engineering classrooms, an engineering computer lab, and an auditorium hall for projections and slideshows.

Slightly east of Mendel Field sits The Grotto, a landscaped haven between Falvey Library and two residence halls: Alumni Hall, home to the Service Learning Community; and Corr Hall, the location of the Center for Peace and Justice Studies.  Often home to outdoor [[mass (liturgy)|mass]]es and other large gatherings, the Grotto is sometimes perfect for quiet contemplation.  The grotto includes a statue depicting [[Our Lady of Good Counsel]] and plaques dedicated to the veterans of [[World War II]] and the [[Vietnam War]].  Across from Alumni Hall and The Grotto are St. Rita's Hall and Austin Hall.  In addition to being two residence halls, these two buildings also house the Campus Ministry Office and University Admissions Office, respectively.  Falvey Library, the campus's main research library, houses over 1,000,000 books, thousands of periodicals, television production studios, and quiet places for solitary or group study.&lt;ref name=&quot;Falvey&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/enroll/admission/virtualtour.htm |title=Launch Villanova University Virtual Tour|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2007-10-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; Behind Falvey Library is the Saint Augustine Center for Liberal Arts, commonly called &quot;SAC&quot;, which is home to many departments in the College of Liberal Arts, numerous offices, several seminar-type classrooms, and is home to the Advising and Professional Development Program.

East of Corr Hall sits Kennedy Hall, which houses the University Shop, the campus bookstore. Across a small courtyard is Dougherty Hall, the campus's main dining hall, referred to as &quot;The Pit&quot; because of its underground location, one of three all-you-can-eat facilities on campus.  Dougherty also houses several smaller eateries and many Student Activity Offices. Next to Kennedy is Connelly Center with its radically different architecture resembling an alpine ski lodge, containing: the Belle Aire Terrace, which serves a variety of food; several meeting rooms; areas for group study; the Commuter Student Lounge on the upper level; another lounge on the lower level, the campus cinema (movie theater); a large conference room; a smoothie shop; and Holy Grounds, the name of Villanova's coffee shop.

Between the dining halls of Dougherty and the meeting halls of Connelly is &quot;The Oreo&quot;.  A large black-and-white sculpture by [[Jay Dugan]], some of the major campus celebrations have occurred in its circular shadow &amp;ndash; including celebratory vandalism in the wake of the 1985 NCAA Men's Basketball Championship. Sitting just west of The Quad, ''The Awakening'' (as it is officially known) has served as a meeting place in the heart of the campus for generations of Villanovans.

Still further east, there is &quot;The Quad&quot; where there lies a square formation between two dormitories, Sheehan Hall and Sullivan Hall.  Bartley Hall, home to the Villanova School of Business is the last building before Ithan Avenue, which is where main campus ends.  Bartley is adjacent to another entrance to Main Campus, at the intersection of Lancaster Avenue and Ithan Avenue.  Behind Bartley Hall are two new buildings: The Health Services Building, home to the Counseling and Medical Centers; and Driscoll Hall, home to the College of Nursing.

===West Campus===
Situated across the [[SEPTA]] tracks north and west of Mendel hall is West Campus: home to St. Mary's Hall, the West Campus Apartments, and the [[Villanova University School of Law|Law School]]. St. Mary's, a labyrinthine building of classrooms, residence rooms, a cafeteria, and large chapel, was originally built as a seminary, and was once home to the College of Nursing.  Behind St. Mary's sit the Apartments &amp;ndash; eight buildings that house junior and senior resident students.

One of three commuter train stops on campus, the [[Villanova (SEPTA Regional Rail station)|Villanova Rail Station]] on the [[Paoli/Thorndale Line]] provides access to the city of [[Philadelphia]], about 30 minutes away.

===South Campus===
Sitting diagonally across Lancaster Ave. and Ithan Ave. from Bartley Hall, South Campus is home to several residence halls &amp;ndash; usually reserved for underclassmen &amp;ndash; and Donahue Hall, home to &quot;The Spit&quot;, short for &quot;South Pit&quot;. Donahue hall also houses Donahue Market, commonly referred to by students as &quot;The Sparket&quot;.

The second and third of three on-campus train stops, the [[Villanova (SEPTA Route 100 station)|Villanova stop]] and the [[Stadium (SEPTA station)|Stadium stop]] on the [[SEPTA Route 100]] line provides access to the city of [[Philadelphia]], about 30 minutes away.

===Environmentalism===
In May 2007, the University’s president signed the American College &amp; University Presidents Climate Commitment, promising to support research and education to end [[global warming]]. The new College of Nursing and the new School of Law are being built according to [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] (LEED) specifications.

On November 16, 2007, the College of Engineering unveiled a Solar Electric System atop its Center for Engineering Education and Research (CEER) that will supply up to 4,000 watts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.villanova.edu/engineering/newsevents/newsarchives.htm?page=unveiling.htm|title= Father Donohue throws the Switch to Officially Unveil the New Solar Electric System|accessdate=2007-12-12 |work= villanova.edu }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%;width:100%;border:0px;text-align:center;line-height:120%;&quot;
!colspan=&quot;5&quot;|'''Academic Divisions of Villanova University'''
|-
|colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0px&quot;|''Undergraduate, Graduate &amp; Professional Studies''
|colspan=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0px&quot;|''Graduate &amp; Professional Studies''
|-
|College of Liberal Arts and Sciences&lt;br/&gt;1842
|College of Engineering&lt;br/&gt;1905
|[[Villanova School of Business]]&lt;br/&gt;1922
|College of Nursing&lt;br/&gt;1953
|[[Villanova University School of Law|School of Law]]&lt;br/&gt;1953
|}

===University rankings===
For more than a decade, Villanova University has been ranked #1 by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' in the Best Universities-Masters category in the northern region, a ranking for schools in the North which offer strong Masters, and undergraduate programs while having lesser doctorate programs. Villanova has several highly regarded academic programs, including an engineering school that is ranked #9 among undergraduate engineering programs whose highest degree is a masters. The [[Villanova School of Business]] was ranked #7 in the 2011 ''[[Business Week]]'' rankings of undergraduate business schools,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/business/newsmedia/rankings.htm |title=VSB In The Rankings |accessdate=2007-03-10|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; #69 in the 2012 ''U.S. News and World Report'' rankings of undergraduate business schools, and #29 in the [[Financial Times]]' ranking of top executive [[MBA]] programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/business/assets/documents/newsmedia/ft2006.pdf |title=Financial Times Ranks the Villanova School of Business Executive MBA Program Among the Top 30 in the Nation |accessdate=2007-03-10|work=villanova.edu|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Villanova University School of Law]] is ranked as a Top Law School by the 2009 edition of [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'s &quot;Best Graduate Schools,&quot; placing 61st overall.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/law/search/page+3|title=U.S. News and World Report Law School Rankings |accessdate=2007-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2006, ''[[PC Magazine]]'' and ''[[The Princeton Review]]'' ranked Villanova #1 in its review of top &quot;wired colleges&quot; in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcmag wired colleges&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,1895,2073411,00.asp |title=Top 10 Wired Colleges|accessdate=2006-12-20|work=The Princeton Review}}&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Nursing has been designated a Center of Excellence in Nursing Education by the National League for Nursing in 2004 and again in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/nursing/newsevents/news.htm?page=2007_9_29.htm|title=Villanova Nursing recognized again as Center of Excellence in Nursing Education|accessdate=2008-02-20 |work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Villanova’s Master’s program in Psychology was ranked among the top 10 Master’s-only departments (95th percentile) in the United States and Canada with regard to research productivity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/artsci/psychology/graduate/whyvillanova.htm|title=Villanova Psychology}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admissions and retention statistics===
&lt;!-- Please ensure that all statistics agree with the cited reference. If they do not agree, please do not change them, or provide an alternative reference that agrees with the statistic. --&gt;
Villanova University has an overall undergraduate acceptance rate of 39.1%, accepting just over 6,000 of the 15,398 applicants in 2011. Of the accepted students, 84% ranked in the top 10% of their high school class, and 99% ranked in the top 20%. The GPA range for a typical student is 3.81-4.21/4.00 on a weighted scale. The middle 50 percent range of SAT scores for the typical accepted applicant was 1340-1440/1600, and the middle 50 percent range of the composite ACT score for the typical accepted applicant was 30-33.
&lt;ref name=&quot;CBd&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.villanova.edu/villanova/admission/overview/undergrad/statistics.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
Villanova's student organizations include standard club sports, cultural organizations, Greek-letter fraternities and sororities, and more.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/studentdevelopment/organizations.htm |title=Campus organizations |accessdate=2007-10-09|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Villanova students participate in charitable and philanthropic activities and organizations, including the largest student-run [[Special Olympics]] in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;special olympics&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/specialolympics/ |title=Special Olympics |accessdate=2007-10-09|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Orientation===
Under the four-day New Student Orientation Program, about 25 new students are assigned to each Orientation Counselor, or &quot;O.C.,&quot; who guides them through various activities concerning diversity, academics, athletics, sexual awareness, the Philadelphia Area, and student concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/specprograms/orientation/about/ |title=Mission|accessdate=2008-02-20|work=villanova.edu/.../Orientation}}&lt;/ref&gt; The program is run by a staff director, a student chairperson, a student administrative coordinator, and a student steering committee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/specprograms/orientation/staff/ |title=Meet the Staff|accessdate=2008-02-20|work=villanova.edu/.../Orientation |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080110122130/http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/specprograms/orientation/staff/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Blue Key Society===
The Blue Key Society consists of around 200 volunteer campus tour guides who work with the Admissions Office to give three tours each weekday, various special tours as needed and selected weekend tours throughout the school year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://students.villanova.edu/bluekey/faqs.html Blue Key Society&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus ministry and service===
Reflecting traditions of Roman Catholic and Augustinian spirituality, Campus Ministry touches every aspect of University life through prayer, liturgy, community service, and pastoral care. Campus Ministry encourages all to integrate personal faith into the academic and social environment of the University. Campus Ministry promotes the Augustinian ideal of an intellectual community seeking both wisdom and a fuller spiritual life.

====Special Olympics====
The annual Special Olympics Fall Festival at Villanova University is the largest and most successful student-run Special Olympics in the world.&lt;ref&gt;NBC10 News, November 7, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; It draws more than 1,000 athletes and 400 coaches from 44 Pennsylvania counties.  Athletes may advance through the festival to regional and international competition.
Students apply to be a part of the 82-volunteer planning committee, which works for more than nine months alongside with Special Olympics Pennsylvania (SOPA), which oversees more than 300 events statewide.&lt;ref name=&quot;special olympics&quot;/&gt;
The event is put on with the aid of some 2,500 student volunteers and more than 1,000 other volunteers from the Villanova community.

====Habitat for Humanity====
Villanova students participate in [[charitable organization]]s and service trips in the U.S. and abroad. In 2004, Villanova had more participants in the [[Habitat for Humanity International|Habitat for Humanity]] Collegiate Challenge than any other U.S. university.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://publications.villanova.edu/blueprints/september2004/hhumanity.htm|title=Office of Communication and Public Affairs: Habitat for Humanity applauds Villanova participation|accessdate=2007-02-18|work=Blueprints}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pastoral Musicians====
The second-largest musical group at Villanova, the Pastoral Musicians have about 60 voices and 35 instrumentalists, primarily undergraduates, up from 30 musicians in 1995. Their musical selection shows the diversity of style within the Roman Catholic tradition: contemporary praise music from different cultures, Bach, Palestrina, Mozart, Lauridsen, and others.

====Engineers Without Borders====
Villanova EWB is a student chapter of [[Engineers Without Borders (USA)|Engineers Without Borders]], a non-profit organization that focuses on helping to improve the living conditions of communities worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ewb-usa.org/ Ewb-Usa&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Villanova EWB is one of the fasting growing student organizations on campus, expanding from a mere handful of engineering students in the spring of 2006 to a current membership of approximately 75 students in multi-disciplinary programs.

The chapter’s inaugural project was to design and build a playground for a grade school in [[New Orleans]] following the tragic events of [[Hurricane Katrina]]. Villanova EWB was the only student organization to win an award from the regional [[Project Management Institute]], receiving an Honorable Mention from PMI for project of the year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.villanova.edu/engineering/newsevents/newsarchives.htm?page=service.htm Villanova Engineering Students Learn through Service&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The most recent project involved designing and building a water treatment and distribution system which provided an orphanage and surrounding villages in northern [[Thailand]] with drinking water and irrigation for their crops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.students.villanova.edu/egrorgs/EWB/thailand.html Engineers Without Borders - Villanova Chapter&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; There are also plans for a variety of projects in the Philadelphia area, including K-12 outreach programs, as well as many more international projects.

===Rays of Sunshine===
Formerly known as Project Sunshine, The Office of Community Service, commonly called &quot;Rays of Sunshine&quot;, is a student-led community service organization dedicated to reaching out to all kinds of communities with kindness and compassion. Through tutoring, mentoring, or visiting the elderly, sick, and disabled, Rays of Sunshine works to &quot;bring some sunshine&quot; into the lives of others.&lt;ref name=&quot;sunshine&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/sunshine/|title=Rays of Sunshine|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greek life===
Roughly 15% of Villanova students identify with one of twelve [[Fraternities and sororities|fraternities]], eleven [[Sorority|sororities]], and one service fraternity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.www.villanovan.com/media/storage/paper581/news/2008/04/10/Features/Greek.Life.At.Villanova-3312745.shtml/|title=Greek Life at Villanova|work=www.villanovan.com|accessdate=2008-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no fraternity or sorority houses on-campus.

The first Greek organization at the school was established in 1902 as a social organization and circle of individuals interested in classical studies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/studentdevelopment/greeklife/about/|title=About Us|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2008-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
====Sororities====
[[National Panhellenic Conference]] Sororities
* [[Alpha Chi Omega]]
* [[Alpha Phi]]
* [[Delta Delta Delta]]
* [[Delta Gamma]]
* [[Kappa Delta]]
* [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]]
* [[Pi Beta Phi]]
* [[Chi Omega]]

[[National Pan-Hellenic Council]] Sorority
* [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]]

[[National Association of Latino Fraternal Organizations]] Sorority
* [[Lambda Theta Alpha]] 

[[National APIA Panhellenic Association]] Sorority
* [[Sigma Psi Zeta]]
{{col-break}}
====Fraternities====
[[North-American Interfraternity Conference]] Fraternities
&lt;!-- Please do not add Kappa Sigma to this list. It has no charter at Villanova, as confirmed by the Kappa Sigma website at http://www.kappasigma.org/chapters.php. (December 17, 2008) --&gt;
* [[Beta Theta Pi]]
* [[Delta Tau Delta]]
* [[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
* [[Phi Gamma Delta]]
* [[Phi Sigma Kappa]]
* [[Pi Kappa Phi]]
* [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]]
* [[Sigma Chi]]
* [[Sigma Nu]]
* [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]

National Pan-Hellenic Council Fraternity
* [[Kappa Alpha Psi]]

[[National Association of Latino Fraternal Organizations]] Fraternity
* [[Phi Iota Alpha]]
{{Col-end}}

====Service Fraternity====
The Sigma Eta chapter of [[Alpha Phi Omega]], whose motto is &quot;Leadership, Friendship, and Service,&quot; meets weekly on Villanova's campus to plan service projects on and off campus, including school cleanups through Philly Cares Day, working at soup kitchens and tutoring children in Math and Science at Philadelphia public schools.&lt;ref name=&quot;APO&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.greek.villanova.edu/alphaphiomega/about.html|title=Alpha Phi Omega|accessdate=2008-02-20 |work= villanova.edu |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080121114745/http://www.greek.villanova.edu/alphaphiomega/about.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Villanova Emergency Medical Service===
Villanova Emergency Medical Service (VEMS), is a student-run ambulance service licensed and dedicated to serving the campus community. VEMS membership consists of more than 40 undergraduate student volunteers; the majority of whom are certified as [[Emergency Medical Technicians]], volunteering more than 25,000 hours annually. Villanova is one of only a handful of colleges to provide EMS services to their campus, and one of only 52 who provide emergency response and transport to at least the Basic Life Support (BLS) Level.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncemsf.org/resources/database/search.ems|title=NCEMSF Database|accessdate=2007-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  VEMS has been recognized on a national level multiple times by the [[National Collegiate EMS Foundation|National Collegiate EMS Foundation (NCEMSF)]], specifically being named 2001 Campus Organization of the Year and receiving EMS website of the year in 2000, 2004, and 2006. Their skills competition team also placed in second at the 2011 Annual Physio-Control BLS Skills Competition. The team consisted of Capt. William Pandos, Lt. Christopher Cahill, Lt. John Skinner, Treasurer Philip Walker, EMT Erin Mack, and EMT Kyle Lewis. VEMS hosted the second annual NCEMSF Conference in 1995 as well as the twelfth annual conference in Philadelphia in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncemsf.org/about/hall-of-fame.ems|title=NCEMSF Awards|accessdate=2007-06-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus Publications and Media===
''[[The Villanovan]]'' has been the officially recognized and accredited student newspaper since its founding in 1916. The newspaper of record of Villanova University, the tabloid-sized weekly produces usually 12 issues per semester at a circulation of 6,500 copies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanovan.com/home/generalinformation/|accessdate=2008-02-20|title=General Information|work=villanovan.com |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080204172533/http://www.villanovan.com/home/generalinformation/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-02-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The paper's awards include 2nd Place for Tabloid Feature Cover from the Columbia Scholastic Press Association's Collegiate Circle (2007); Certificate of Merit for Editorial Writing from the Columbia Scholastic Press Association's Collegiate Circle (2007); Certificate of Merit for portfolio of work in the Feature Photograph category from the Columbia Scholastic Press Association's Collegiate Circle (2007); [[Pennsylvania Newspaper Association]]'s Keystone Award for Best Feature Story; and 1st Place with Special Merit and Outstanding Sports Coverage from the American Scholastic Press Association.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}}

''The Villanova Times'', the independent, free speech, bi-weekly student newspaper, won the [[Collegiate Network]] Award for Layout and Design in 2005–2006, 2007–2008 and 2008–2009.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}

[[WVTV (Villanova)]], the student-run campus [[television station]] broadcasts on channel 17. Starting in 1999 as the Villanova TV Production Club, the station produces news, events, films and other programming for the Villanova community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.villanova.edu/wvtv/history.htm|title=VTV|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[WXVU]], the student-operated [[FM broadcasting|FM]] [[radio station]], operates at 89.1 [[megahertz]]. With an output of 75 watts, WXVU can be heard in an {{convert|8|mi|km|sing=on}} radius around the campus. Since 1991, the station has supplied the Villanova community with a varied program of music, news, sports, public affairs, and specialty programming.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wxvufm.com/index.php?page=about|title=About the Station|work=wxvufm.com|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

POLIS Literary Magazine, a student publication printed once a semester by the Villanova University Honors Program, features writing and artwork by Villanova students and professors. Each issue features creative nonfiction, poetry, short fiction, and black-and-white photography focusing on a central theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/artsci/honors/newsevents/polis.htm|title=Polis Literary Magazine|work=villanova.edu|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Each issue also features articles on literature, entertainment, and dining.

===NROTC===
The Villanova [[Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps|Naval Reserve Officer Training Corps]] (NROTC) Program mission is to develop [[Midshipman|midshipmen]] mentally, morally and physically and to imbue them with the highest ideals of duty, and loyalty, and with the core values of honor, courage and commitment in order to commission college graduates as naval officers who possess a basic professional background, are motivated toward careers in the naval service, and have a potential for future development in mind and character so as to assume the highest responsibilities of command, citizenship and government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.nrotc.navy.mil/mission.aspx|title=Naval Reserve Officers Training Corp|accessdate=2010-05-26|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Villanova NROTC is part of the Philadelphia NROTC Consortium; consisting of Villanova University and [[University of Pennsylvania]] (including the cross town agreements with [[Drexel University|Drexel]] and [[Temple University]]). Located in [[John Barry (naval officer)|Commodore John Barry]] Hall, it is institution that has been a part of the University since World War Two. The battalion consists of more than 100 Navy and Marine Corps midshipmen under the advisement of a staff of highly trained and motivated Navy and Marine Corp Officers and Senior Enlisted. Known for its dedication to excellence, motivation, and pride, the NROTC unit has provided our nation with the finest Navy and Marine Corps Officers for over 50 years.

Midshipmen in the Villanova NROTC program are required to take specific Navy and Marine Corps classes, wear their service's uniform on Tuesdays, attend physical training events, participate in extra-curricular programs that range from sports teams to rifle-shooting, and adhere to the basic premise that “a midshipman does not lie, cheat, or steal”.  By the time their four years have come to a close, these values have been deeply ingrained into each midshipman, and they know what it means to be a [[commissioned officer]] and a Villanovan. Thousands of midshipmen have gone through this experience to join the ranks of what can be considered the “extended” Villanova community in the U.S. Navy and Marine Corps. Although times have changed as well as the specifics of training, the program remains largely unchanged from the program that has descended from World War Two.

Since its inception in the summer of 1946, the NROTC unit on campus has produced 22 Admirals and Generals in the United States Navy and Marine Corps.  At one point, there had only been two four-star generals in the U.S. Marine Corps, one of them the Commandant of the Marine Corps, and they had both been graduates of Villanova NROTC. In 2004, the commanders of both [[U.S. Atlantic Fleet|U.S. Naval Forces Atlantic]] ([[William J. Fallon|Admiral William J. Fallon]]) and [[U.S. Pacific Fleet|U.S. Naval Forces Pacific]] ([[Walter Doran|Admiral Walter F. Doran]]) were Villanova NROTC graduates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cffc.navy.mil/history.htm|title=Former Commanders U.S. Fleet Forces Command|accessdate=2010-05-26|work=villanova.edu}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cpf.navy.mil/commander/previous/|title=Former Commanders U.S. Pacific Fleet|accessdate=2010-05-26|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; Admiral Fallon was later assigned as Commander, U.S. Central Command from March 2007 to March 2008. ADM Fallon was the first Navy officer to hold that position.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sptimes.com/2007/03/17/Tampabay/With_passing_of_flag_.shtml|title=With passing of flag, CentCom gets new leader|accessdate=2010-05-26|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student Conduct and Disciplinary Procedures===
All rules regarding student behavior are outlined in the Student Handbook, colloquially known as the &quot;Blue Book.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.villanova.edu/generalcounsel/.../2010_2011_studenthandbook.pdf|title=Student Handbook|accessdate=2010-05-26|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; This handbook is amended yearly to ensure that it is up to date with any new fads or caprices of the student body. Because of the religious nature of the school, all policies in the Blue Book are founded in the &quot;Catholic intellectual and moral tradition.&quot; As a result, discipline is not taken lightly at Villanova. The Blue Book strictly forbids drug and alcohol consumption; indecency; sexual activity; dangerous, disruptive or illegal behavior; gambling; the possession of &quot;illegal video and recoring equipment&quot; or electrical appliances; the use of candles, open flames or incense; illegal elevator access; and other serious offenses. Any student found in violation of these policies is likely subject to substantial fines and probation, and oftentimes suspension, expulsion and loss of residency privileges.

===Music Activities===
Villanova University is without a formal music department; therefore, the Office of Music Activities is charged with the organization of the student [[performing arts]] groups on campus.  Musicians on campus are from every school in the University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/music/about.htm Villanova.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;  Located on the lower floor of St. Mary's Hall, the Office of Music Activities coordinates the activities of over 600 students — nearly 10% of the student body.&lt;ref&gt;Dunphy, John, Director of Music Activities.  ''Lecture.'' April 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Villanova Band====
The Villanova Band is the largest and oldest musical group at Villanova with over 100 members. The Villanova Band has five divisions: the Concert Band, the Scramble Band, the Pep Band, the Jazz Ensemble, and the Villanova Orchestra. Any student or faculty at Villanova can participate in any or all of these bands. The Concert Band plays two concerts; one at the end of each semester. It also performs throughout the Villanova community and on its annual &quot;Fall Tour&quot;. Past Fall Tour destinations include [[Florida]], [[Puerto Rico]], [[Montreal]], and [[South Carolina]]. The Scramble Band performs for Villanova Football games between plays and at halftime on the field. The Villanova Pep Band performs at Villanova Men's and Women's Basketball games, including post-season games such as the Big East Tournament. The Jazz Ensemble and Orchestra also has end-of-semester concerts but also performs around the Philadelphia area several times a year. The band is made up of students of every school within Villanova.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vuband.com/ Vuband.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Villanova Singers====
Villanova's [[men's chorus]], the Villanova Singers, was founded in 1953 by Dean Harold Gill Reuschlein, then Dean of the [[Villanova University School of Law|Law School]].  Established for the purpose of singing various types of music and enriching the cultural life of the University, Dean Reuschlein was known to say that he was &quot;as proud of the Villanova Singers as I am of what the Law School has become.&quot;&lt;ref name=vusinghist&gt;[http://vusingers.villanova.edu/Singers%20History.htm Vusingers.villanova.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

Since 1963, the Singers have toured extensively; recent highlights include 7-day tours of [[Italy]] in the Spring 2001, [[Austria]] and [[Germany]] in the Spring of 2003, [[Puerto Rico]] in the Spring of 2004,&lt;ref name=vusinghist/&gt; and [[Rio de Janeiro]] in Spring of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vusingers.villanova.edu/ Vusingers.villanova.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;  In concert with the Villanova Voices, the Singers perform two concerts each year: one for [[Christmas]], and one in the Spring.

Entirely student-run, the Singers are governed by an 9-member board of students and sing an eclectic repertoire, ranging from sacred to patriotic, gospel to contemporary, as well as several arrangements by their director, Brian Meneely. Within the Singers, there exists a smaller, student-directed ''[[a cappella]]'' group known as the Spires.  Alumni of the Spires include [[Jim Croce]], [[Tommy West]] and [[Tim Hauser]] from [[The Manhattan Transfer]].&lt;ref name=vusinghist/&gt;

====Villanova Voices====
The Villanova Voices, the University's [[women's chorus]], is the oldest women's organization at the University.  Originally called the Villanova Women's Glee Club, the group was founded by twenty women from the University's College of Nursing in 1960, shortly after Villanova became coeducational.  They sing at various Wildcat games, Special Olympics ceremonies, at local charity events, and &quot;spread holiday cheer&quot; to senior citizens at several nursing homes and to the people of Philadelphia at the [[King of Prussia Mall]].  Their attendant ''a cappella'' group, the Haveners, is student-directed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.villanova.edu/studentlife/music/groups/vocal.htm#voices Villanova.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{Main|Villanova Wildcats}}
[[File:VillanovaWildcats.png|right|thumb|175px|Villanova Wildcats logo]]

Villanova University's [[varsity team|varsity]] men's [[college athletics|athletics]] programs include [[college baseball|baseball]], [[college basketball|basketball]], [[cross country running]], [[college football|football]], [[golf]], [[college lacrosse|lacrosse]], [[college soccer|soccer]], [[swimming (sport)|swimming]] and [[diving]], [[tennis]], and [[track and field]]. Women's varsity athletics programs include basketball, cross country running, [[field hockey]], lacrosse, [[college rowing (United States)|rowing]], soccer, [[college softball|softball]], swimming and diving, tennis, track and field, [[volleyball]], and [[water polo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://villanova.cstv.com/ Villanova.com - Official Athletic site of the Villanova University Wildcats&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Sports teams participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s Division I and in the [[Big East Conference]], except for football and women's lacrosse. Football plays in the [[Colonial Athletic Association]]. Women's lacrosse plays in the [[Patriot League#History|Patriot League]]. The Wildcats are also part of the [[Philadelphia Big 5]], the traditional Philadelphia-area basketball rivalry. Their fiercest city rivalry, which is called the &quot;[[Holy War (Villanova vs. St. Joe's)|Holy War]]&quot;, is with [[St. Joseph's University]].

In the NCAA graduation report released on November 18, 2009, Villanova has a graduation-success rate of 96 percent for student-athletes who entered college in 2002-03. Villanova women's basketball team is among the athletic program's 14 teams with a 100 percent graduation rate for 2002-03. The Wildcats' nationally ranked men's basketball and football teams are both at 92 percent. The men's basketball team's graduation-success rate places it fifth nationally among Division I schools.

In 2009, Villanova's football team won the national title in the Football Championship Subdivision (formerly Division I-AA).&quot;Our number-one priority at Villanova has always been recruiting kids who want to get a good education,&quot; Wildcats football coach Andy Talley said. Talley added that no matter how many games or titles Villanova wins, the athletic department's goal is to prepare students for life after college.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.philly.com/inquirer/sports/20091119_Villanova_earns_high_marks_for_graduating_athletes.html Villanova earns high marks for graduating athletes]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite those comments, Villanova is currently evaluating whether or not the football program should accept a possible invitation to join the Big East Conference if so invited. Joining the Big East would allow Villanova to generate much more revenue from membership in a BCS conference. &quot;Our football evaluation is ongoing,&quot; Villanova AD Vince Nicastro told The Associated Press. &quot;We are moving forward as quickly as we can, but not at the expense of being absolutely thorough. We still don't have a specific decision date, but it is likely to be resolved some time during this academic year.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/news/story?id=5756898 Sports.espn.go.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Men's Basketball===
{{Main|Villanova Wildcats men's basketball}}
In 1985, under the direction of coach [[Rollie Massimino]], the men's basketball team won the [[1985 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]] in the first year of the 64-team field. The final game, against defending champion and ten-point-favorite [[Georgetown Hoyas|Georgetown]], is often cited among the greatest upsets in college basketball history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/page2/s/list/010523upset.html|title=ESPN.com: Page 2's List for top upset in sports history|accessdate=2006-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, under the direction of coach [[Jay Wright (coach)|Jay Wright]], Villanova's men's basketball team reached the [[2005 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|NCAA Tournament]] [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|Sweet 16]], losing to #1 seed and eventual champion [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill|North Carolina]] by one point on a traveling call on [[Allan Ray]]. {{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} In 2005-2006, the team began the year ranked #4 in the major polls from ''USA Today'' and the Associated Press. A 75-62 loss to eventual champion [[University of Florida|Florida]] ended the team's run for a second NCAA championship in the Regional Final. This team was led by a four guard set, a unique type of lineup designed by coach Jay Wright. In the 2006-2007 season, the Wildcats had a record of 22-11, and lost to [[Kentucky Wildcats|Kentucky]] in the first round of the [[2007 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|2007 tournament]]. In the [[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]], the [[2007-08 Villanova Wildcats men's basketball team|team]] was eliminated by the top-seeded, eventual champion [[Kansas Jayhawks]] in the Sweet 16, after upsetting the fifth seeded [[Clemson]] Tigers in the 1st round and defeating the thirteenth seeded [[Siena College|Siena]] Saints in the 2nd round. In the [[2009 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|2009 tournament]], the [[2008–09 Villanova Wildcats men's basketball team|Wildcats]] upset the #1 seed [[University of Pittsburgh|Pittsburgh Panthers]] on a last second shot by guard Scottie Reynolds to win the East Region and advance to the Final Four. The team was then defeated by the eventual champion [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill|North Carolina Tar Heels]] in the [[2009 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament|2009 Final Four]] game.

The home venues for the Wildcats include the on-campus 6,500 seat [[The Pavilion|Pavilion]] for smaller attendance games, as well as the larger, 21,600 seat [[Wells Fargo Center (Philadelphia)]] (formerly, [[Wachovia Center]]) at the Philadelphia sports complex. The February 13, 2006 meeting between Villanova and the [[University of Connecticut]] set the record for the highest attendance at a college basketball game in Pennsylvania, with 20,859 attendees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncb/boxscore?gameId=260440222 ESPN - Connecticut vs. Villanova - Box Score - February 13, 2006&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Men's Football===
{{Main|Villanova Wildcats football}}
The Villanova men's football team competes in NCAA Division I-AA as a member of the [[Football Championship Subdivision]] in the [[Colonial Athletic Association]]. On December 18, 2009 the team defeated the [[Montana Grizzlies football|Montana Grizzlies]] to be crowned the 2009 NCAA Division I-AA champions, and were co-conference champions with the [[Richmond Spiders football|Richmond Spiders]] in the same year. On September 10, 2010, ESPN reported that the [[Big East Conference]] had informally invited the program to compete in that BCS conference. The same report stated that the University was considering the invite.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/news/story?id=5553575 Sports.espn.go.com] ''[[ESPN.com]]'', September 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Men's Lacrosse===
{{Main|Villanova Wildcats men's lacrosse}}
The Villanova men's [[lacrosse]] team competes in NCAA Division I as a member of the [[Big East Conference]]. Through 2009, Villanova men's lacrosse was a member of the [[Colonial Athletic Association]] and in 2009, Villanova won the CAA tournament as the fourth seed (the lowest-seeded championship team in conference history)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncaa.com/sports/m-lacros/spec-rel/050309aab.html Villanova Secures First CAA Men's Lacrosse Title], National Collegiate Athletic Association, May 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; for its first title.&lt;ref&gt;[http://insidelacrosse.com/page.cfm?pagerid=2&amp;news=fdetail&amp;storyid=206996 Villanova claims first CAA title with 10-9 win over Towson], ''[[Inside Lacrosse]]'', May 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The team also made its first NCAA tournament appearance that year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.baltimoresun.com/sports/college/lacrosse/bal-sp.laxrup11may11,0,5700820.story Virginia crushes Villanova, 18–6, faces Hopkins in next round], ''[[The Baltimore Sun]]'', May 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Women's cross country===
In 2010 and 2009, the women's cross country team won the NCAA National Championships under Coach Gina Procaccio. The 2010 victory was led by individual national champion [[Sheila Reid]] of Villanova. The Wildcats also hold the NCAA record for the most Division 1 team and individual wins in women's cross country with 9 team victories ('89, '90, '91, '92, '93, '94, '98, '09, '10) and 8 individual champions, 7 of which coincided.

===Track and Field===
Villanova University's [[Track and Field]] team has a long history of athletic success that has spanned from [[Big East]] Conference Championships to NCAA Championships.&lt;ref name=&quot;trackandfield&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.runnova.com|title=Runnova|accessdate=2008-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Men's Team has produced 69 NCAA Championships, 36 Indoor and 33 Outdoor. The team has had 8 NCAA team Championships (4 Cross Country, 3 Indoor, 1 Outdoor). Villanova has produced 28 athletes who have made appearances in the Olympics, 10 of whom have medaled (7 Gold medals, 3 Silver medals). The men's team has also won 112 Penn Relay Championships, which stands as the most wins by any school. The men's current coaches include head coach [[Marcus O'Sullivan]] and assistant head coach Anthony Williams.&lt;ref name=&quot;trackandfield&quot;/&gt;

The Women's team has also had a multitude of success, producing 11 Big East team Championships and 9 NCAA team Championships, most recently winning the 2009 and 2010 NCAA Championships. They have also produced 7 Olympians including [[Vicki Huber]], [[Sonia O'Sullivan]], [[Kim Certain]], [[Kate Fonshell]], [[Jen Rhines]], [[Carmen Douma]], and [[Carrie Tollefson]]. The Women's team has won 28 Penn Relay Championships, which is the most wins by any women's team. The current women's coaches include head coach Gina Procaccio and assistant head coach Anthony Williams.&lt;ref name=&quot;trackandfield&quot;/&gt;

At least one Villanovan athlete has competed in every [[Summer Olympics]] since 1948, winning a total of 13 medals (9 gold, 4 silver).&lt;ref name=&quot;NovaMagSum2008&quot;&gt;''Villanova'' magazine, Summer 2008, &quot;Villanovans have won 13 Olympic Medals&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Traditions==
===The University Seal===

An adaptation of the seal of the Order of St. Augustine, the seal of Villanova University is one of the campus's most ubiquitous images, adorning everything from buildings to chairs to backpacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.images.villanova.edu/seallegend/|title=The University Seal|accessdate=2007-10-09|work=villanova.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; A ribbon carries the University motto: ''Veritas, Unitas, Caritas'' ([[Truth]], [[Cooperation|Unity]], and [[Charity (virtue)|Charity]]), [[virtue]]s to which every member of the Villanova community should aspire. A book symbolizes Augustine's dedication to education and the [[New Testament]] where he found Christianity. A [[cincture]] is part of the [[religious habit|habit]] worn by members of the Order of Saint Augustine. Hovering above is the flaming heart, symbol of Augustine's search for God and his love of neighbors. Behind the book is the [[crosier]] &amp;mdash; a staff traditionally held by a [[Bishop]] &amp;mdash; commemorating Augustine's service as Bishop of [[Hippo Regius|Hippo]]. Above and behind the book are two [[Christian cross|cross]]es, symbolic of Augustine's conversion and the University's commitment to Christianity. Framing the central portion of the seal is a [[laurel wreath]] exemplifying victory through the pursuit of knowledge, and 1842 is the year of the University's founding. Surrounding the seal is the incorporated fide of the University: ''Universitas Villanova In Statu Pennsylvaniae''.

===The Liberty Bell's &quot;Sister Bell&quot;===

[[Image:Villanova Old Falvey.JPG|thumb|left|The old wing of the [[Falvey Library]].]]

Villanova University is also home to the [[Liberty Bell]]'s &quot;Sister Bell,&quot; the replacement bell ordered from the Whitechapel Bell Foundry after the original bell cracked in 1753.&lt;ref name=&quot;sisterbell1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://publications.villanova.edu/vumagazine/fall2003/sister_bell.htm|title=Villanova Magazine Fall 2003 Edition|accessdate=2007-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; This new bell was installed at the Pennsylvania State House ([[Independence Hall (United States)|Independence Hall]]), and attached to the State House clock. The Sister Bell rang the hours until the late 1820s, when the bell was removed during a renovation and loaned to the [[Olde St. Augustine Church]] in Philadelphia. In 1829, the bell was hung in a new cupola and tower designed by architect [[William Strickland (architect)|William Strickland]]. There it remained until May 8, 1844, when it was destroyed, along with the Olde St. Augustine Church, during the [[Philadelphia Nativist Riots]]. The friars of the [[Order of Saint Augustine]] had the &quot;Sister Bell&quot; recast and transferred to Villanova University.&lt;ref name=&quot;sisterbell1&quot;/&gt;

At the university's centennial celebration, the bell was rung by [[Dennis Joseph Dougherty|Archbishop Dennis Joseph Dougherty]] to open the ceremonies. In 1954, the bell was displayed as part of an exhibit at [[Gimbels]] department store in Philadelphia that focused on the growth and development of the university.&lt;ref name=&quot;sisterbell2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.archives.villanova.edu/arch/case_01/005.htm|title=Villanova University Archives: The Liberty Bell's Sister|accessdate=2007-10-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070915175240/http://www.archives.villanova.edu/arch/case_01/005.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sister Bell is currently enshrined in the Heritage Room on the basement floor of the St. Augustine Monastery on Villanova's campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;sisterbell1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sisterbell2&quot;/&gt;

===Campus Myths===
[[Image:Villanova alumni hall.JPG|thumb|Right|Alumni Hall, one of the oldest buildings on campus.]]
A number of legends are spread around campus by students. Some of these include the existence of secret tunnels and catacombs under campus, the haunting of some of the older dormitories (sometimes linked to their use as hospitals during the [[American Civil War|Civil War]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan2405&quot; /&gt; and speculation over the existence of an entire wing of St. Mary's Hall which is completely blocked off.

The three buildings most commonly discussed as being haunted are Alumni Hall (located by St. Thomas of Villanova church on the main campus), St. Mary's Hall and Dundale (both located on the west campus).

Alumni Hall dates back to 1848 and stands as one of the oldest structures on campus. The school was closed in 1861 due to the Civil War and reopened in 1865. In that time this hall is believed to have been used as a military hospital and potential evidence of that use, such as a pulley located at the top of the main stairwell for moving bodies up and down, can still be seen. The building was used as a hospital again for influenza patients after World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan2405&quot; /&gt;  This history has led to rumors that the building is haunted.

St. Mary's Hall was built in 1962 and served as an Augustinian Seminary until 1972.{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} Laid out with long corridors and over a thousand rooms, there is a large chapel and many partial floors, basements and sub-basements to feed the legends of blocked off wings.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan2405&quot; /&gt;

The property on which Dundale Hall is located was originally purchased by an industrialist, Israel Morris II, in 1874, and was built as a mansion for his family. Purchased from his family in 1978, it has been used for a variety of meetings and is home to several offices. On more than a handful of occasions, the school's Public Safety officers have been called out late at night to investigate lights in the building coming on inexplicably.&lt;ref name=&quot;villanovan2405&quot; /&gt;

==Alumni==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}
[[Image:Governor Edward G. Rendell.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Ed Rendell]] JD '68, [[Governor]] of [[Pennsylvania]]]]
{{Main|List of alumni of Villanova University}}
Villanova University has produced several notable alumni.

[[Golden Globe]]-nominated actress [[Maria Bello]] got her first taste of the stage in a production at Vasey Hall. Actor and [[Coen Brothers]] favorite [[Jon Polito]] has garnered both stage and screen awards, and NFL Hall of Famer, longtime FOX commentator and feature film actor [[Howie Long]] graduated in 1982.  [[Tim Hauser]], founder of [[The Manhattan Transfer|Manhattan Transfer]], [[Jim Croce]], and [[Don McLean]] have all been prominent members of the musical tradition at Villanova.  [[Tony Award]]-winning playwright and screenwriter [[David Rabe]] premiered ''[[In the Boom Boom Room]]'' at Villanova's Vasey Hall. [[Brian Westbrook]] and [[Michael Bradley (basketball)|Michael Bradley]] both attended Villanova before launching their careers in professional sports.

In addition to former Pennsylvania Governor [[Ed Rendell]], Villanova has produced several military and governmental officials. Wife to the governor and [[federal judge]] for the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit]], [[Marjorie Rendell]], is also a graduate. Numerous Marine generals and Naval Admirals are products of Villanova's [[NROTC|Naval ROTC]] program, including [[William J. Fallon]], Admiral in the United States Navy and Commander of [[United States Central Command]]; [[George B. Crist]], Marine General and the first Marine to be designated Commander in Chief, Central Command; and [[Anthony Zinni]], retired four-star General in the United States Marine Corps.

The business world, too, has had several prominent businessmen who got their start at Villanova.  [[Robert J. Darretta, Jr.]] &amp;ndash; [[CFO|chief financial officer]] and vice chairman of [[Johnson &amp; Johnson]], [[John Drosdick]] &amp;ndash; former [[CEO]] of [[Sunoco]], [[Thomas G. Labrecque]] &amp;ndash; former Chairman and CEO of [[Chase Manhattan Bank]], [[Francis Saul]] &amp;ndash; president of [[Chevy Chase (Bank)]], and [[Martin McGuinn]] &amp;ndash; former CEO of [[Mellon Financial Corp.]] have all studied at Villanova at some point in their careers.

[[John Joseph O'Connor]], Cardinal Archbishop of the [[Archdiocese of New York]], obtained a Masters degree in Advanced Ethics at Villanova University.  [[John L. Hennessy]], president of [[Stanford University]] earned a Bachelor's in Electrical Engineering, and [[Deirdre Imus]], Head of the Diedre Imus Environmental Center for Pediatric Oncology (and wife to radio host [[Don Imus]]) is also a graduate.

==See also==
{{Portal|Philadelphia}}
*[[Education in Philadelphia]]
*[[Roman Catholicism in the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=35em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.villanova.edu/ Official website]
*[http://www.villanova.com/ Official Athletics website]
*''[http://www.vutimes.wordpress.com The Villanova Times]''

{{Coord|40.03771|-75.33755|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

{{Villanova University}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#FFFFFF;color:#00337F;border:1px solid #00337F;
|list =
{{Big East Conference}}
{{Patriot League}}
{{ECHA}}
{{Big 5}}
{{Philadelphia College Radio Collective}}
{{Colleges and universities in metropolitan Philadelphia}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Pennsylvania}}
|state =autocollapse
}}

[[Category:Villanova University|*]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Big East Conference schools]]
[[Category:Education in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Radnor Township, Delaware County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1842]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Delaware County, Pennsylvania]]

[[de:Villanova University]]
[[es:Universidad Villanova]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ویلانوا]]
[[fr:Université Villanova]]
[[it:Villanova University]]
[[nl:Villanova Universiteit]]
[[no:Villanova University]]
[[simple:Villanova University]]
[[ta:விலனோவா பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[vi:Đại học Villanova]]
[[zh:维拉诺瓦大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
