<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="241128" ns="0" title="Michigan State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Featured article}}
{{Infobox university
|name= Michigan State University
|image= [[File:MSU Seal 2010.svg|200px|Michigan State University Seal]]
|motto= Advancing Knowledge. Transforming Lives.
|endowment= [[United States dollar|US $]]1.449 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]]&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2010.{{cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2010 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2009 to FY 2010| work = 2010 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|president= Dr. [[Lou Anna Simon]]
|established= February 12, 1855
|type= [[Flagship campus|Flagship]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Public university|Public]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Land-grant university|Land grant]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Sea grant colleges|Sea grant]]
|calendar = Semester
|staff= 6,355&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt;
|faculty= 4,985&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/about/thisismsu/facts.html MSU Facts]&quot;. Michigan State University Newsroom. Retrieved July 1, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
|students= 47,800&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;&gt;{{cite web | publisher = WNEM | url =http://www.wnem.com/story/15432657/svsus-student-enrollment-up-this-year | accessdate = September 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad= 36,058&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt;
|non-degree= 2,025&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad= 11,073&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt;
|colors= [[Variations of Green#MSU Green|Green]] &amp; [[White]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www2.ur.msu.edu/toolkit/color-palette.html Official MSU Colors]&quot;. Michigan State University University Relations Graphic Standards&lt;/ref&gt;
{{color box|#18453b}}{{color box|#ffffff}}
|city= [[East Lansing, Michigan]]
|country= [[United States|USA]]
|mascot= [[Sparty]]
|campus= Suburban&lt;br /&gt;(21&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) campus&lt;br /&gt;10,000&amp;nbsp;acres (8&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;) in existing or planned development
|sports= [[Michigan State Spartans|Spartans]]
|website= [http://www.msu.edu/ msu.edu]
|logo= [[File:Michigan State University wordmark.svg|230px]]
}}

'''Michigan State University''' ('''MSU''') is a [[public university|public]] research university in [[East Lansing, Michigan]], USA. Founded in 1855, it was the pioneer [[land-grant institution]] and served as a model for future land-grant colleges in the United States under the 1862 [[Morrill Land-Grant Colleges Act|Morrill Act]].

MSU pioneered the studies of [[packaging]], [[Hospitality management studies|hospitality business]], [[telecommunication]] and [[music therapy]].{{Citation needed (lead)|date=February 2011}} Today its [[study abroad|study-abroad]] program is the largest of any single-campus university in the country, offering more than 200 programs in more than 60 countries on all continents including [[Antarctica]]. 

It is considered to be one of America's [[Public Ivy]] universities, which recognizes top public research universities in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;publicivy&quot;&gt;Greene, Howard and Greene, Matthew. ''The Public Ivies: America's Flagship Public Universities'' (New York: HarperCollins, 2001). ISBN 0-06-093459-X.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the introduction of the [[Morrill Act]], the college became [[coeducation]]al and expanded its curriculum beyond [[agriculture]]. Today, MSU is the [[List of largest United States university campuses by enrollment|ninth-largest university]] in the United States, with 47,800 students and 2,954 [[Faculty (teaching staff)|faculty]] members. The school's [[nuclear physics]], [[engineering]], [[political science]], [[business]], [[journalism]], [[education]], [[law]] and [[osteopathic medicine]] programs are among the nation's best.

MSU's [[NCAA Division I|Division I]] sports teams are called the [[Michigan State Spartans|Spartans]]. They compete in the [[Big Ten Conference]] in all sports except ice hockey, in which the team is part of the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]]. MSU's [[American football|football]] [[Michigan State Spartans football|team]] won the [[Rose Bowl Game|Rose Bowl]] in 1954, 1956 and 1988 and boasts six national championships.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/msu/sports/m-footbl/auto_pdf/133-170-spartan-history.pdf]&quot;. College Football Data Warehouse. Accessed December 28, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/div_ia/bigten/michigan_state/national_champs.php|date =20070320093240|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its men's basketball team won the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|NCAA National Championship]] in 1979 and 2000 and is currently enjoying a streak of six [[Final Four]] appearances over the last 13 seasons. MSU men's [[ice hockey]] won [[NCAA Men's Ice Hockey Championship|national titles]] in 1966, 1986 and 2007. Cross country has historically been Michigan State's most successful sport, especially during a four-decade period spanning roughly 1930–1970 during which the Spartans won eight NCAA championships and numerous other conference and national titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frimodig, L. 1971&quot;&gt;Frimodig, L., &amp; Stabley, F. (1971). Spartan Saga: A History of Michigan State Athletics. East Lansing: Michigan State University.&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{Main|History of Michigan State University}}

=== Agriculture school ===
[[Image:Beaumont Tower 10 2007 BR.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Beaumont Tower]] marks the site of [[College Hall (Michigan State University)|College Hall]].]]
The [[Michigan Constitution]] of 1850 called for the creation of an &quot;agricultural school&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[[s:Michigan Constitution of 1850|Michigan Constitution of 1850]]&quot;. Wikisource. Article 13, Section 11. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; though it was not until February 12, 1855, that Michigan [[List of Governors of Michigan|Governor]] [[Kinsley S. Bingham]] signed a bill establishing the United States' first agriculture college, the Agricultural College of the State of Michigan.&lt;ref name=&quot;sesquicentennial&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/msuarhc/articlepg1.htm Milestones of MSU's Sesquicentennial]&quot;. MSU University Archives and Historical Collection. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Classes began on May 13, 1857, with three buildings, five faculty members, and 63 male students. The first president, [[Joseph R. Williams]], designed a curriculum that required more scientific study than practically any undergraduate institution of the era. It balanced [[science]], [[liberal arts]], and practical training. The curriculum excluded [[Latin language|Latin]] and [[Greek language|Greek]] studies, since most applicants did not study any classical languages in their rural high schools. However, it did require three hours of daily [[manual labour|manual labor]], which kept costs down for both the students and the College.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Darling, Birt. | title=City in the Forest; The Story of Lansing | location=New York | publisher=Stratford House | year=1950|page=121 | lccn=50008202}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Williams' innovations and his defense of education for the masses, the State Board of Education saw Williams' curriculum as [[elitism|elitist]]. They forced him to resign in 1859 and reduced the curriculum to a two-year vocational program.

=== Land Grant pioneer ===
In 1860, [[Joseph R. Williams]] became acting [[lieutenant governor]]&lt;ref name=&quot;josephrwilliams&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/msuarhc/williams.htm Joseph R. Williams Biographical Information]&quot;. MSU University Archives and Historical Collection Accessed March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and helped pass the Reorganization Act of 1861. This gave the College a four-year curriculum and the power to grant [[master's degree]]s. Under the act, a newly created body, known as the State Board of Agriculture, took over from the State Board of Education in running the institution.&lt;ref name=&quot;sesquicentennial&quot;/&gt; The College changed its name to State Agricultural College, and its first class graduated in the same year. As the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] had just begun, there was no time for an elaborate graduation ceremony.  The first alumni enlisted to the [[Union Army]]. The following year, [[Abraham Lincoln]] signed the First [[Morrill Act]] of 1862 to support similar colleges, making the Michigan school a national model. Williams had died the previous year.

=== Co-ed college ===

[[Image:Cowles House 10 2007 BR.jpg|thumb|left|The Alice B Cowles House is the official home of the university president and is the oldest existing building on campus.]]
The college first admitted women in 1870, although at that time there were no female residence halls. The few women who enrolled either boarded with faculty families or made the arduous [[stagecoach]] trek from Lansing. From the early days, female students took the same rigorous scientific agriculture courses as male students. In 1896, the faculty created a &quot;Women Course&quot; that melded a [[Family and consumer science|home economics]] curriculum with [[liberal arts]] and sciences. That same year, the College turned the old Abbot Hall male dorm into a women's dormitory. It was not until 1899 that the State Agricultural College admitted its first [[African American]] student, William O. Thompson. After graduation, he taught at what is now [[Tuskegee University]]. President Jonathan L. Snyder invited its president [[Booker T. Washington]] to be the Class of 1900 commencement speaker. A few years later, Myrtle Craig became the first woman African-American student to enroll at the College. Along with the Class of 1907, she received her degree from U.S. President [[Theodore Roosevelt]], commencement speaker for the Semi-Centennial celebration. The City of East Lansing was incorporated in that same year,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Miller, Whitney. | title=East Lansing: Collegeville Revisited (Images of America) | location=Charleston, South Carolina | publisher=Arcadia Publishing | year=2002 | isbn=0-7385-2045-4 | page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and two years later the college officially changed its name to Michigan Agricultural College (M.A.C.).
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[Image:Hannah statue.jpg|thumb|left|As part of its sesquicentennial celebration, MSU erected this 7-foot (2.1 m) bronze statue of [[John A. Hannah]], sculpted by California artist Bruce Wolfe.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Kristin K. &quot;[http://www.msutoday.msu.edu/news/index.php3?article=17Sep2004-1 Ceremony pays tribute to 'pragmatic visionary']&quot;. ''MSU Today''. September 17, 2004. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; ]] --&gt;

=== Big Ten university ===

During the early 20th century, M.A.C. expanded its curriculum well beyond agriculture. By 1925 it had expanded enough that it changed its name to Michigan State College of Agriculture and Applied Science (M.S.C.). In 1941 the Secretary of the State Board of Agriculture, [[John A. Hannah]], became president of the College. He began the largest expansion in the institution's history, with the help of the 1945 [[G. I. Bill of Rights|G.I. Bill]], which helped World War II veterans to receive an education. One of Hannah's strategies was to build a new dormitory building, enroll enough students to fill it, and use the income to start construction on a new dormitory. Under his plan, enrollment increased from 15,000 in 1950 to 38,000 in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Heineman, Kenneth J. | title=Campus Wars: The Peace Movement at American State Universities in the Vietnam Era | location=New York | publisher=New York University Press | year=1993 | isbn=0-8147-3512-6|page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1957 Hannah continued MSU's expansion by co-founding Michigan State University–Oakland, now [[Oakland University]], with [[Matilda Dodge Wilson]]. Hannah also got the chance to improve the athletic reputation of M.S.C. when the [[University of Chicago]] resigned from the [[Big Ten Conference]] in 1946. Hannah lobbied hard to take its place, gaining admission in 1949.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=It's Big 10 Now – Spartans Admitted|accessdate=2010-06-12|newspaper=Wisconsin State Journal|date=1949-05-21, p. 13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Six years later, in its Centennial year of 1955, the State of Michigan renamed the College as Michigan State University of Agriculture and Applied Science.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Kuhn, Madison. | title=Michigan State: The First Hundred Years, 1855–1955 | location=East Lansing | publisher=Michigan State University Press | year=1955 | isbn=0-87013-222-9 | page=471}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nine years after that, the University governing body changed its name from the State Board of Agriculture to the MSU Board of Trustees. The State of Michigan&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.michigan.gov/ |title=Michigan.gov |publisher=Michigan.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; allowed the University to drop the words &quot;Agriculture and Applied Science&quot; from its name. Since 1964 the institution has gone by the name of Michigan State University.

=== Global leader by 2012 ===
[[Image:MSU Cyclotron.jpg|thumb|right|The [[National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory]] features one of the most powerful instruments of its type in the world.&lt;ref name=Bruns&gt;Bruns, Adam (January 2009).[http://www.siteselection.com/features/2009/jan/Michigan/ How Are You Helping Companies Grow?].''Site Selection Magazine''. Retrieved on December 27, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Since the end of the Hannah era, Michigan State has shifted its focus from increasing the size of its student body to advancing its national and global reputation. In September 2005, current president [[Lou Anna Simon]] called for MSU, one of the [[Public Ivy|public ivy institutions]], to become the global model leader for Land Grant institutions by the year 2012. Her plans include creating a new [[residential college]] and increasing grants awarded from the [[National Institutes of Health]] past the [[United States dollar|$]]100 million mark. While there are over 100 [[Land-grant universities]] in the United States, she has stated that she would like Michigan State University to be the leader.&lt;ref&gt;Darrow, Bob. [http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2005/09/simon_msu_to_be_model Simon: MSU to be model university]. ''The State News''. September 9, 2005. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Michigan State, the [[University of Michigan]] and [[Wayne State University]] created the [[University Research Corridor]] in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-university-research-corridor&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = MSU, U-M, Wayne State create University Research Corridor | publisher = MSU News | url =http://news.msu.edu/story/1317/ | accessdate = July 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This alliance was formed to transform and strength Michigan's economy by reaching out to businesses, policymakers, innovators, investors and the public to speed up technology transfer, make resources more accessible and help attract new jobs to the state.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-university-research-corridor&quot;/&gt;

== Campus ==
{{Main|Campus of Michigan State University}}
[[Image:MSU Campus Map small rev3.png|thumb|right|MSU's main campus lies north of the CN Railway and south of Michigan and Grand River Avenues.]]
MSU's sprawling campus is located in East Lansing, Michigan. The campus is perched on the banks of the [[Red Cedar River (Michigan)|Red Cedar River]]. Development of the campus started in 1856 with three buildings: a multipurpose building called [[College Hall (Michigan State University)|College Hall]], a dormitory later called &quot;[[Saints' Rest]]&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070613062800/http://www.s150.msu.edu/SaintsRest.php Saints' Rest: Early Campus Life at MSU.] Michigan State University. Retrieved on March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and a barn. Today, MSU's contiguous campus consists of {{convert|5200|acre|km2}}, {{convert|2000|acre|km2}} of which are developed. There are 556 buildings: 100 for academics, 131 for [[agriculture]], 166 for housing and [[food service]], and 42 for athletics. Overall, the university has {{convert|22,763,025|ft2|m2}} of total indoor space.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.eas.msu.edu/fit/reports/buildingdatasummary.cfr Building Data Summary]&quot;. ''MSU Physical Plant''. Retrieved February 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Connecting it all is {{convert|26|mi|km}} of roads and {{convert|100|mi|km}} of sidewalks.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.rcpd.msu.edu/FAQ Frequently Asked Questions]&quot;. MSU Resource Center for Persons with Disabilities (RCPD). Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; MSU also owns 44 non-campus properties, totaling {{convert|22000|acre|km2}} in 28 different counties.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.canr.msu.edu/lmo/index.htm Land Management Office]&quot;. Michigan State University Land Management Office. August 29, 2005. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:MSU Beaumont Tower 1.jpg|left|thumb|View of Beaumont Tower from the north.]]

=== North campus ===
The oldest part of campus lies on the north bank of the Red Cedar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Forsyth|first=Kevin S.|title=Michigan Agricultural College – Introduction|url=http://kevinforsyth.net/ELMI/campus.htm|work=A Brief History of East Lansing, Michigan|accessdate=25 February 2011|year=2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It includes [[Collegiate Gothic]] architecture, plentiful trees, and curving roads with few straight lines. It was in this area that the College built its first three buildings, of which none survive. Other historic buildings north of the river include [[Cowles House (East Lansing, Michigan)|Cowles House]], the president's official residence, and [[Beaumont Tower]], a [[carillon]] clock tower marking the site of [[College Hall (Michigan State University)|College Hall]], the original classroom building. To the east lies [[Eustace–Cole Hall]], America's first freestanding laboratory for [[horticulture]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Stanford, Linda O. | title=MSU Campus: Buildings, Places, Spaces | location=East Lansing | publisher=Michigan State University Press | year=2002 | isbn=0-87013-631-3|page=60}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other landmarks include the bronze statue of former president [[John A. Hannah]],&lt;ref&gt;Roeschke, Jaclyn. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2004/09/former_039u039_president Former 'U' president immortalized with bronze statue]&quot;. ''The State News''. September 20, 2004. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[W. J. Beal Botanical Garden]], and the painted boulder known as &quot;[[The Rock (Michigan State University)|The Rock]]&quot;, which is a popular spot for theatre, [[tailgate party|tailgating]], and candlelight vigils. On the northwest corner of campus lies the University's hotel, the Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center. The university also has a museum, initiated in 1857. MSU Museum is one of the oldest museums in the Midwest and is accredited by the American Association of Museums.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://museum.msu.edu/GeneralInformation/About/ MSU Museum – About the Museum]&quot;. Retrieved February 25, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== South campus ===

[[Image:MSU Wharton Center.jpg|right|thumb|The [[Wharton Center for Performing Arts]] hosts many productions throughout the year and was host to the final US Presidential Debate before the 1992 election.]] &lt;br&gt;
The campus south of the river consists mostly of post-World War II [[International Style (architecture)|International Style]] buildings with sparse foliage, relatively straight roadways, and numerous parking lots. The &quot;2020 Vision&quot; Master Plan proposes replacing these parking lots with [[multi-storey car park|parking ramps]] and green space,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://prod.gis.msu.edu/construction/update.jsp 2020 Vision Campus Master Plan]&quot;. MSU Campus Planning and Administration. 2006. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://www.2020vision.msu.edu/construction/|date =20080315235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; but these plans will take many years to reach fruition. As part of the master plan, the University erected a new bronze statue of ''[[Sparty|The Spartan]]'' in 2005. This replica replaced the original [[modernist]] [[terra cotta]] statue,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Stanford, Linda | title=MSU Campus: Buildings, Places, Spaces | location=East Lansing, Michigan| publisher=Michigan State University Press | year=2002|isbn=0-87013-631-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; which can still be seen inside [[Spartan Stadium, East Lansing|Spartan Stadium]]. Notable academic and research buildings on the South Campus include the [[National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory|Cyclotron]] and the [[Michigan State University College of Law|College of Law]].

This part of campus is home to the [[Michigan State University Horticulture Gardens|MSU Horticulture Gardens]] and the adjoining [[4-H]] Children's Garden. South of the gardens lie the [[Canadian National]] and [[CSX Transportation|CSX]] railroads, which divide the main campus from thousands of acres of university-owned farmland. The university's agricultural facilities include the Horse, Dairy Cattle, Beef Cattle, Sheep, and Poultry Teaching and Research Farms, as well as the Air Quality Control Lab and the Diagnostics Center for Population and Animal Health.
{{-}}

=== Dubai Education Center ===
In 2007, Michigan State University established an education center in [[Dubai]], [[United Arab Emirates]]. MSU Dubai was the first American university with a presence in [[Dubai International Academic City]], with classes beginning in August 2008. The University offered six undergraduate programs: Business Administration; Child and Youth Development; Construction Project Management; Early Childhood Education; Media Management and Research; Computer Engineering, which later was changed to Electrical and Computer Engineering; and a Master's Degree in Human Resources &amp; Labor Relations. The University attracted over 100 students from all over the Middle East and beyond.&lt;ref&gt;About Michigan State University Dubai – http://dubai.msu.edu/quick-facts/about-msu-dubai/news/msu-dubai-challenges-middle-east-students-dream-big-committing-new-&lt;/ref&gt; During the 2009-2010 academic year MSU Dubai intended to seek licensure through the Commission for Academic Accreditation of the U.A.E. with the goal of full program accreditation prior to the graduation of its first class in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://dubai.msu.edu/quick-facts/about-msu-dubai&lt;/ref&gt; After two years of activity, MSU shut down all undergraduate programs in Dubai due to financial reasons. The Dubai campus remains as a research site, a Study Abroad center, and for its dozen graduate students.

=== Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center ===
The Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center doubles as a 4-star hotel and a business friendly conference center. It is located on the northwest corner of Michigan State University’s campus, across from the [[Brody Complex]], on Harrison Road just south of Michigan Avenue. The hotel has 160 rooms and suites which can accommodate anyone staying in East Lansing for a business conference, sporting event or an on-campus visit, but it originally served as a dormitory for MSU students. Besides a lodging facility, the Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center serves as a “learning laboratory for the 300-400 students each year that are enrolled in The School of Hospitality Business and other majors.” The Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center strives to facilitate education by hosting conferences and seminars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kelloggcenter.com/about/history.html |title=Kellogg Hotel and Conference Center |accessdate=May 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Academics ==
{{Main|Michigan State University academics}}
{{See also|Michigan State University Libraries}}
[[Image:MSU Library 1.jpg|thumb|ㅣleft|[[Michigan State University Libraries|The MSU Library]] is located on the oldest part of campus between [[Beaumont Tower]] and the river.]]
MSU has the [[List of largest US universities by enrollment|ninth largest]] student body in the U.S. For the fiscal year of 2009–10, the Office of the Registrar conferred 11,140 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reg.msu.edu/ReportServer/Pages/ReportViewer.aspx?/ROReports/UFY-DegreesConf&amp;term_seq_id=1096 Degrees Conferred-Fiscal Year]''Office of the Registar'.' Retrieved June, 22,2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The student body is 55% female and 45% male. While 89% of students come from all 83 counties in the State of Michigan,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Michigan State University: Student Body&quot;. ''The Princeton Review''. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; also represented are all 50 states in the U.S. and about 130 other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt; In 2010-2011 5,351 international students enrolled at MSU. The top five countries represented: China, Korea, India, Taiwan and Canada. [http://oiss.isp.msu.edu/about_stats.php] MSU has about 4,500 faculty and 6,000 staff members, and a student/faculty ratio of 19:1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Davis, Amy. | title=Michigan State University Off the Record | publisher=College Prowler | year=2005 | isbn=1-59658-083-6 | page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Listed as a [[Public Ivy]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Greene, Howard R. &amp; Greene, Matthew W. | year=2001 | title=The Public Ivies: America’s Flagship Public Universities (1st ed.) | publisher=New York: Cliff Street Books | isbn=0-06-093459-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michigan State is a member of the [[Association of American Universities]]. Michigan State University [[Ombudsman]] is the longest continually operating ombudsman office at a college or university in the country.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://newsroom.msu.edu/site/indexer/3180/content.htm America’s longest-operating Office of the Ombudsman turns 40]&quot;. Michigan State University Newsroom. September 19, 2007. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Albert Fert]], an [[Adjunct professor]] at MSU, was awarded the 2007 [[Nobel Prize in Physics]] together with [[Peter Grünberg]].&lt;ref&gt;Thoel, Tara. &quot;[http://statenews.com/index.php/article/2007/10/adjunct_physics_professor_at_msu_wins_nobel_prize Adjunct physics professor at MSU wins Nobel Prize]&quot;. ''The State News''. October 9, 2007. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; MSU's [[study abroad]] program is the largest of any single-campus university in the United States with 2,461 students studying abroad in 2004–2005 in over 60 countries on all continents, including [[Antarctica]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://studyabroad.msu.edu/programs/antarcticscience.html Studies in Antarctic System Science—Antarctica]&quot;. MSU Office of Study Abroad. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; MSU has six faculty members elected to the National Academy of Sciences (NAS); Martin Bukovac (1983), James Dye (1989), Pamela Fraker (2007), Richard Lenski (2006), Michael Thomashow (2003), and James Tiedje (2003).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasonline.org/site/Dir/605305206?pg=rslts Search] ''National Academy of Sciences'.' Retrieved April 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Its admissions are moderately difficult; for 2009's entering class, the 25th/75th percentiles for the SAT were 1030 and 1240/1600, and its 25th/75th percentiles on the ACT were 23 and 27/36.&lt;ref&gt;[http://trustees.msu.edu/meetings/pdfs/bot_minutes_9_11_2009.pdf] ''MSU Board of Trustee Minutes'.' Retrieved October 24, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Rankings ===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| QS_W  = 164
| GUR = 36–39
| ARWU_W = 92
| ARWU_N = 50
| ARWU_SOC = 32
| ARWU_BUS = 34
| CMUP = 43
| USNWR_NU =71
| USNWR_Bus = 46
| USNWR_Medc = 7
| USNWR_Eng = 58
| USNWR_Ed = 17
| Wamo_NU = 33
| Forbes = 282
| THES_W = 96
| FSPI = 86
}}
Michigan State ranks {{ordinal|92}} in the world, according to a [[Shanghai Jiao Tong University]] study, which measures scientific research leading towards a [[Nobel Prize]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2011.html Top 500 World Universities]&quot;. ''Institute of Higher Education'', Shanghai Jiao Tong University. January 1, 2011. Retrieved September 5, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranks MSU 71st in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/rankings/national-universities/page+8]&quot;. ''U.S. News and World Report''. Retrieved November 03, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]] placed Michigan State University at 164th internationally.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011?page=3&lt;/ref&gt;

The university has over 200 academic programs. ''U.S. News'' has ranked MSU's graduate-level [[elementary education]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;elementaryed&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/edu/brief/edusp04_brief.php America's Best Graduate Schools 2008: Elementary Education].&quot; ''U.S. News and World Report''. Retrieved February 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[secondary education]],&lt;ref name=&quot;secondaryed&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/edu/brief/edusp05_brief.php America's Best Graduate Schools 2008: Secondary Education].&quot; ''U.S. News and World Report''. Retrieved February 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Industrial and Organizational Psychology]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/phdhum/brief/psysp5_brief.php America's Best Graduate Schools 2008: Psychology Specialties: Industrial/Organizational Psychology].&quot; ''U.S. News and World Report''. Retrieved February 22, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; programs No.1 for the last 14 years.
The National Communication Association (NCA) ranks MSU’s Ph.D. programs as No. 1 in educating researchers in the rapidly growing fields of health communication and communication technology.

MSU is also ranked number four in several other fields, including international/intercultural communication, mass communication, and interpersonal communication based on the November 2004 NCA report. &lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.natcom.org/Default.aspx?id=630&amp;libID=651 NCA Doctoral Reputational Study, 2004]''National Communication Association''. Retrieved November 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eli Broad College of Business was ranked No. 9 among public institutions and No. 20 nationally in 2010 by ''Business Week''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Best U.S. B-Schools of 2010|url=http://www.businessweek.com/interactive_reports/bs_2010_US_FTMBA_TAB_1111.html|work=Business Week|accessdate=3 December 2010|date=11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2008 ''U.S. News'' ranked Michigan State's [[Supply Chain Management]] program in the Eli Broad College of Business No.1 in the nation for the second year in a row.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/bizspec10_brief.php Supply Chain Management/Logistics]&quot;. ''USNews.com:America's Best Colleges 2008''. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the Eli Broad College of Business undergraduate accounting program is ranked 11th overall and 8th among public schools, the graduate accounting program is ranked 9th overall and 6th among public schools, and the doctoral program is ranked 8th overall and 5th among public schools according to the 2010 ''[[Public Accounting Report]]'''s Annual Survey of Accounting Professors. &lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-rankings-broad-accounting&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Annual PAR ranks all Broad accounting programs in top 10 among publics | publisher = Eli Broad College of Business | url =http://broad.msu.edu/information/news/item?oid=1923 | accessdate = July 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The College of Communication Arts and Sciences was established in 1955 and was the first of its kind in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-rankings-comarts&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Distinctions for College of Communication Arts and Sciences | publisher = Michigan State University | url =http://msu.edu/about/rankings-and-recognitions/distinctions/communication-arts-and-sciences.html | accessdate = July 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college's Media and Information Studies doctoral program was ranked No. 2 in 2007 by ''[[The Chronicle of Higher Education]]'' in the category of mass communication.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-rankings-comarts&quot;/&gt; The communication doctoral program was ranked No. 4 in a separate category of communication in ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'''s 2005 Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index, published in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-rankings-comarts&quot;/&gt; The college's faculty and alumni include eight [[Pulitzer Prize]] winners and a two-time [[Emmy Award]] winning recording mixer.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU-rankings-comarts&quot;/&gt;

MSU’s graduate program in [[nuclear physics]] is ranked No. 1 in the nation by U.S. News. In [[primary care|primary medical care]], ''U.S. News'' ranks MSU's College of Osteopathic Medicine at No.5, College of [[Veterinary Medicine]] at No.9, and the College of Human Medicine at No.18.&lt;ref name=&quot;gradrankings&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://newsroom.msu.edu/site/indexer/3044/content.htm MSU professional and grad programs maintain strong positions in rankings]&quot;. Michigan State University Newsroom. March 30, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other programs of note include [[criminal justice]],&lt;ref&gt;Rykert, Wilbur Lewis. &quot;The History of the School of Criminal Justice at Michigan State University 1935–1963&quot; (Masters Thesis). 1985.&lt;/ref&gt; [[music therapy]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.music.msu.edu/about/fastfacts.php About Us: Fast Facts]&quot;. MSU College of Music. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://www.music.msu.edu/about/fastfacts.php|date =20070815153555|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hospitality management studies|hospitality business]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bus.msu.edu/shb/documents/Historic%20Milestones.pdf MSU.edu], &quot;Historic Milestones&quot; (PDF). The School of Hospitality Business. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[packaging]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://packaging.msu.edu/history.php MSU.edu], &quot;history&quot;, MSU School of Packaging. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://packaging.msu.edu/history.php|date =20080315235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[political science]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070828123417/http://polisci.msu.edu/about/achievements.htm MSU.edu], &quot;Achievements&quot;. MSU Department of Political Science. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[dietetics]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://fshn.msu.edu/programs/dietetics.html MSU.edu], &quot;Dietetics&quot;. MSU Department of Food Science and Human Nutrtion. Retrieved April 27, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[communication]]s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsroom.msu.edu/site/indexer/2264/content.htm MSU.edu], &quot;MSU communication programs lead nation&quot;. Michigan State University newsroom. December 10, 2004. Retrieved January 30, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sustainable Endowments Institute awarded Michigan State with an overall grade of &quot;B&quot; on the 2009 Campus Sustainability Survey, including &quot;A&quot;s in the categories of Administration, Transportation, Endowment Transparency, and Investment Policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://greenreportcard.org/report-card-2009/schools/michigan-state-university |title=Greenreportcard.org |publisher=Greenreportcard.org |date=2008-06-30 |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Research ===
[[Image:MSU Computer Center.jpg|thumb|The Computer Center once housed the early research computer [[MISTIC]]]]
The university spent nearly [[United States dollar|$]]405 million in 2008–09 on research,&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt; capping a long history of academic research. In 1877, botany professor [[William J. Beal]] performed the first documented genetic crosses to produce hybrid [[maize|corn]], which led to increased yields. MSU dairy professor [[G. Malcolm Trout]] invented the process for the [[Homogenization (chemistry)|homogenization]] of milk in the 1930s. In the 1960s, MSU scientists developed [[cisplatin]], a leading cancer fighting drug.
&lt;br&gt;
Today Michigan State continues its research with facilities such as the [[United States Department of Energy|U.S. Department of Energy]]-sponsored MSU-DOE Plant Research Laboratory&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://prl.msu.edu/ |title=Michigan State University &amp;#124; College of Natural Science &amp;#124; Plant Research Laboratory |publisher=Prl.msu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a [[particle accelerator]] called the [[National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory]]. The U.S. Department of Energy Office of Science named Michigan State University as the site for the [[Facility for Rare Isotope Beams]] (FRIB). The $550 million facility will attract top researchers from around the world to conduct experiments in basic nuclear science, astrophysics, and applications of isotopes to other fields.
[[Image:MSU Vet Research Farm.jpg|thumb|right|The Veterinary Research Farm.]]

In 2004, scientists at the Cyclotron produced and observed a new isotope of the element [[germanium]], called Ge-60&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nscl.msu.edu/science/nuggets/60Ge First observation of Germanium-60 and Selenium-64]&quot;. ''NSCL Science Nuggets''. Retrieved April 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In that same year, Michigan State, in consortium with the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]] and the government of [[Brazil]], broke ground on the 4.1-meter [[SOAR Telescope|Southern Astrophysical Research Telescope]] (SOAR) in the [[Andes Mountains]] of [[Chile]]. The consortium telescope will allow the Physics &amp; Astronomy department to study galaxy formation and origins.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/thisismsu/points_pride.html Points of Pride]&quot;. ''MSU Today''. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://www.msu.edu/thisismsu/points_pride.html|date =20080315235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1999, MSU has been part of another consortium called the [[Michigan Life Sciences Corridor]], which aims to develop [[biotechnology]] research in the State of Michigan.&lt;ref&gt;Truscott, John. &quot;[http://www.state.mi.us/migov/gov/PressReleases/199907/LifeSciencesCorridorPR.htm Governor Signs Bill Creating 'Life Sciences Corridor' in Michigan]&quot;. Michigan Executive Office press release. July 19, 1999. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, the College of Communication Arts and Sciences' [[Quello Center for Telecommunication Management and Law|Quello Center]] researches current issues of information and communication management.

=== Endowment ===
MSU's (private, non-Morrill Act) [[financial endowment|endowment]] started in 1916 when the Engineering Building burned down. Automobile magnate [[R.E. Olds]] helped the program stay afloat with a gift of $100,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Rodriguez, Michael | title=R.E. Olds and Industrial Lansing | location=Charleston, South Carolina | publisher=Arcadia Publishing | year=2004 | isbn=0-7385-3272-X | page=117}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was a time when MSU lagged behind peer institutions in terms of endowments. As recently as the early 1990s, MSU was last among the eleven Big Ten schools, with barely over $100 million in endowment funds. That changed dramatically in the first decade of the 21st century, when the University started a campaign to increase the size of the endowment. At the close of [[fiscal year]] 2004–2005, the endowment had risen to $1.325 billion, raising the University to sixth of the 11 Big Ten schools in terms of endowment; within $2 million of the fifth-rated school.&lt;ref&gt;Seguin, Rick. &quot;[http://newsbulletin.msu.edu/jan2606/endowment.html Endowment surges in growth, rankings]&quot;. MSU News Bulletin. 2006. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The rapid increase in the size of the endowment will help to improve outdated facilities, such as the Music Building, which the College of Music hopes to soon replace with money from its alumni fundraising program.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.music.msu.edu/alumni/campaign.php Capital Campaign]&quot;. MSU School of Music. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://www.music.msu.edu/alumni/campaign.php|date =20080315235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Colleges ==
[[Image:MSU South Campus skyline.jpg|thumb|The South Campus skyline]]
MSU has over 200 academic programs offered by 17 degree granting colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt;

=== Residential colleges ===
MSU has several [[residential colleges]], based on the [[Oxbridge]] &quot;living-learning&quot; model. By putting classes in student dormitories, these colleges improve student access to faculty and facilities. MSU's first residential college, [[Justin Morrill]] College started in 1965 with an interdisciplinary curriculum.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.enolagaia.com/JMC.html Unofficial website]&quot;. Justin Morrill College. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; MSU closed Morrill College in 1979, but today the university has three residential colleges, including the recent opening of the [[Residential College in Arts &amp; Humanities]] (RCAH) located in Snyder and Phillips halls.

Established in 1967, [[James Madison College]] is a smaller component residential college in [[political science]] housed in Case Hall. Classes in the college are small, with an average of 25 students, and most instructors are [[tenure]] track faculty. James Madison College has about 1150 students total, with each [[freshman]] class containing about 320 students.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070627063337/http://www.jmc.msu.edu/quickfacts.asp &quot;Quick Madison Facts&quot;]. James Madison College @ Michigan State University. Retrieved June 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Each of Madison's four [[Academic major|majors]]—Social Relations and Policy, International Relations, Political Theory and Constitutional Democracy, and Comparative Cultures and Politics&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070814085350/http://www.jmc.msu.edu/ps/youandjmc.asp &quot;You and JMC&quot;]. James Madison College @ Michigan State University. Retrieved June 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;—requires two years of foreign language and one semester of &quot;field experience” in an [[intern]]ship or study abroad program. Although Madison students make up about 4% of MSU graduates, they represent around 35% of the MSU’s [[Phi Beta Kappa Society|Phi Beta Kappa]] members.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071020201533/http://jmc.msu.edu/quickfacts.asp Quick Madison Facts]&quot;. James Madison College @ Michigan State University. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:MSU Phillips Hall.jpg|thumb|right|Snyder-Phillips Hall was built in 1947. The building was recently expanded to make room for a new residential college.]]

Also established in 1967, [[Lyman Briggs College]] teaches math and science within social, historical and philosophical contexts.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lymanbriggs.msu.edu/future/educationalPhilosophy.cfm Educational Philosophy]&quot;. Lyman Briggs College. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Many Lyman Briggs students intend to pursue careers in medicine, but the school supports over 30 coordinate majors, from human biology to computer sciences.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lymanbriggs.msu.edu/current/majors.cfm Majors]&quot;. Lyman Briggs College. Retrieved June 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Lyman Briggs is one of the few colleges that lets undergraduates teach as &quot;Learning Assistants.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.lymanbriggs.msu.edu/academics/Forms/LAApplication2008-09.pdf Undergraduate Learning Assistant Application 2008–2009]&quot; (PDF). Lyman Briggs College. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://lymanbriggs.msu.edu/current/forms/LA_Application_2010-11.pdf|date =20080410055103|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

MSU's newest residential college is the [[Residential College in Arts &amp; Humanities]]. Founded October 21, 2005,&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Laura. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2005/10/trustees_approve_residential Trustees approve residential college]&quot;. ''The State News''. October 24, 2005. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the college provides around 600 [[undergraduates]] with an individualized [[curriculum]] in the [[liberal arts|liberal]], [[visual arts|visual]] and [[performing arts]]. Though all the students will graduate with the same [[academic degree|degree]], MSU encourages students in the college to get a [[Double degree|second degree]] or specialization.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://rcah.msu.edu/about/program.php How the Program Works]&quot;. Michigan State University Residential College in Arts &amp; Humanities. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The university houses the new college in a newly renovated Snyder-Phillips Hall, the location of MSU's first residential college, Justin Morrill College.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://rcah.msu.edu/living/ Living in the College]&quot;. Michigan State University Residential College in Arts &amp; Humanities. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:MSU Law School 1.jpg|thumb|The MSU Law School Building]]

=== Professional schools ===
The [[Michigan State University College of Law]] is an independent, non-profit corporation&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.msu.edu/faculty_staff/board.html MSU College of Law Board of Trustees]&lt;/ref&gt; affiliated&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.msu.edu/news/2005/ten-year-affiliation.html MSU Law News, &quot;Law College to Mark 10-Year Affiliation with MSU&quot;, October 17, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; with the [[public university|public]] institution. Founded in Detroit in 1891 as the Detroit College of Law, the law school moved to East Lansing in 1995 becoming an integral part of the university. Students attending MSU College of Law come from 42 states and 13 countries. The law school publishes the Michigan State Law Review,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msulr.law.msu.edu/ Main Page]&quot;. ''Michigan State Law Review''. Accessed March 5, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://msulr.law.msu.edu|date =20070702025546|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Michigan State Journal of International Law and the Journal of Medicine and Law. The College of Law is the home of the [[Geoffrey Fieger]] Trial Practice Institute,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.law.msu.edu/tpi/ The Geoffrey Fieger Trial Practice Institute]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Law. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; the first trial practice institute in the United States. The [[Intellectual Property]] and Communications Law program was ranked seventeenth nationally, in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;White, Russ. &quot;[http://newsroom.msu.edu/site/indexer/2726/content.htm Press Release]&quot;. Michigan State University Newsroom. April 4, 2006. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Eli Broad College of Business]] has programs in [[accounting]], [[information systems]], [[finance]], [[management]], [[marketing]] and [[supply chain management]], and [[The School of Hospitality Business|hospitality business]]. The school has 4,775 [[undergraduate]] students and 776 [[graduate students]]. The Eli Broad Graduate School of Management, which ''[[Business Week]]'' magazine ranks 11th among public institutions, offers three [[MBA]] programs, as well as [[double major|joint degrees]] with the [[Michigan State University College of Law|College of Law]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.bus.msu.edu/graduate Graduate Programs]&quot;. The Eli Broad College of Business and Eli Broad Graduate School of Management. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The opening of the [[Eugene C. Eppley Center for Graduate Studies in Hotel, Restaurant and Institutional Management]] brought the first program in the United States to offer a Master of Business Administration degree in Hotel, Restaurant and Institutional Management to MSU.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bus.msu.edu/shb/documents/Historic%20Milestones.pdf &quot;Historic milestones&quot;], MSU School of Hospitality and Business. p 2. Retrieved 6/10/08.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Michigan State University College of Nursing]] grants [[Bachelor of Science in Nursing|B.S.N.]], [[Master of Science in Nursing|M.S.N.]], and [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] degrees.

=== Medical schools ===
[[File:Msu-chm-secchia-center-evening.jpg|thumb|right|MSU Secchia Center]]
The [[MSU College of Osteopathic Medicine]] was the world's first publicly funded college of [[Osteopathic medicine in the United States|osteopathic medicine]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.com.msu.edu/osteomed/welcome.html A Message from the Dean]&quot;. MSU College of Osteopathic Medicine. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It has a long-standing tradition of retaining its alumni in Michigan to practice – more than two-thirds of the college’s graduates remain to practice in Michigan.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.com.msu.edu/osteomed/history.html Brief History of the Michigan State University College of Osteopathic Medicine]&quot;. MSU College of Osteopathic Medicine. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, the Michigan State University Board of Trustees approved a resolution endorsing the expansion of the College of Osteopathic Medicine to two sites in [[southeast Michigan]], a move board members and college officials say will not only improve medical education in the state, but also address a projected physician [[shortage]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.com.msu.edu/pub-rel/expansion_may2007.html MSU board endorses expansion of osteopathic college to southeast Michigan]&quot;. MSU College of Osteopathic Medicine. May 18, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;
According to U.S. News &amp; World Report, the College of Osteopathic Medicine (DO degree) ranked No.8 medical schools in the country for primary care and the College of Human Medicine (MD degree) has regularly ranked among the top thirty medical schools in the country for primary care.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/grad/rankings/med/brief/mdprank_brief.php America's Best Graduate Schools 2008].&quot; ''U.S. News &amp; World Report''. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Michigan State University College of Human Medicine|College of Human Medicine]] graduates students with medical doctor [[Doctor of Medicine|MD]] degrees and is split into seven distinct campuses located in [[Lansing]], [[Kalamazoo, Michigan|Kalamazoo]], [[Flint, Michigan|Flint]], [[Saginaw]], [[Marquette, Michigan|Marquette]], [[Traverse City, Michigan|Traverse City]] and [[Grand Rapids]]. Each campus is affiliated with local hospitals and other medical facilities professionals in the area.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://humanmedicine.msu.edu/future/meded.php/ Medical Education]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Human Medicine. Accessed Jun 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; For example, the Lansing campus includes [[Sparrow Hospital]] and [[Ingham Regional Medical Center]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://humanmedicine.msu.edu/future/meded_lansing.php Lansing Campus]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Human Medicine. Retrieved June, 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Human Medicine has recently gained attention for its expansion into the Grand Rapids area, with the new [http://www.secchiacenter.com/ Secchia Center] completed in the Fall of 2010, that is expected to fuel the growing medical industry in that region.&lt;ref&gt;Schneider, Keith. &quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/11/realestate/commercial/11hill.html?ex=1187496000&amp;en=07ec444174548dce&amp;ei=50700 Grand Rapids Lays Foundations for a Health Mecca]&quot;. ''The New York Times''. July 11, 2007. Retrieved December 10, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Though Michigan State has offered courses in veterinary science since its founding, the [[Michigan State University College of Veterinary Medicine|College of Veterinary Medicine]] was not formally established as a four-year, degree-granting program until 1910.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://cvm.msu.edu/about-the-college About the College]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Veterinary Medicine. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Ranked ninth in the nation,&lt;ref name=&quot;gradrankings&quot;/&gt; the college has over {{convert|170000|ft2|m2}} of office, teaching, and research space, as well as a veterinary [[teaching hospital]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://cvm.msu.edu/about-the-college/cvm-facilities Facilities]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Veterinary Medicine. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other academic units ===
In recent years, MSU's music program has grown substantially. Music major enrollment increased more than 97% between 1991 and 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;musicfacts&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.music.msu.edu/about/fastfacts.php Fast Facts]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Music. Accessed December 15, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.music.msu.edu/about/fastfacts.php|date =20070815153555|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2007, this growth led the university board of trustees to spin the music program off into its own college unit: The MSU College of Music.&lt;ref&gt;Harbison, Sarah. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2007/02/online_update_music_school Music school becomes MSU's 16th college]&quot;. ''The State News''. February 23, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The new college faces many new challenges, such as working with limited space&lt;ref&gt;Thoel, Tara. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2007/10/music_building_overcrowded Music Building overcrowded, students fight for practice time]&quot;. ''The State News''. October 16, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and funding.&lt;ref&gt;Thoel, Tara. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/index.php/article/2007/09/college_of_music_celebrates_new_status_with_concert New rhythm: College of Music celebrates new status with concert]&quot;. ''The State News''. September 26, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, MSU's music college plans on continued success, placing an annual average of 25 graduate students in tenure stream university positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;musicfacts&quot;/&gt;

MSU's [http://www.educ.msu.edu/ College of Education at Michigan State University] offers graduate and undergraduate degrees in several fields, including [[counseling]], [[educational psychology]], [[special education]], [[teacher education]] and [[kinesiology]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.educ.msu.edu/college/ About Our College]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Education. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The college has had high-ranked programs in elementary,&lt;ref name=&quot;elementaryed&quot;/&gt; educational technology, educational policy, and secondary education.&lt;ref name=&quot;secondaryed&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Henion, Andy. &quot;[http://msutoday.msu.edu/news/index.php3?article=27Mar2008-1 MSU education programs top national rankings for 14th consecutive year]&quot;. ''MSU Today''. March 28, 2008. Retrieved March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Michigan State ties the [[University of Wisconsin–Madison]] for the top spot in [[rehabilitation counseling]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.educ.msu.edu/college/coeawards/toprank.htm Graduate Programs Rankings 2008].&quot; Michigan State University College of Education. Retrieved March 28, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Education is currently housed in Erickson Hall. [[File:Erickson Hall.jpg|thumb|Erickson Hall]]

Founded in 1956, the [[Michigan State University Honors College|MSU Honors College]] provides individualized curricula to MSU's top undergraduate students. Though the college has no majors of its own, it has its own [[dean (education)|dean]] and academic advisers to help Honors students with their educational pursuits.
[[High school]] students starting at MSU may join the Honors College if they are in the top 5% of their high school graduating class and have either an [[ACT (examination)|ACT]] score of at least 30 or an [[SAT]] total score of at least 1360.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/honcoll/prospective.html Prospective Members]&quot;. Michigan State University Honors College. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Once admitted, students must maintain a 3.20 GPA and complete eight approved honors courses in order to graduate with Honors College designation on their degree.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/honcoll/requirements.html Honors Requirements].&quot; Michigan State University Honors College. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

After three years of planning, [[Michigan State University College of Engineering|The College of Engineering]] successfully launched the first stages of its Residential Experience for Spartan Engineering, formally known as the Residential Option for Scientists and Engineers (ROSES), the new program is located in Wilson Hall after being housed in Bailey Hall for a number of years. The Residential program essentially combines with a brand new academic component, Cornerstone Engineering, where freshman engineering students not only get an overview of the engineering field(s) but get a hands-on experience along with it.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.egr.msu.edu/future-engineer/life/residential MSU.edu] Michigan State University. College of Engineering. Residential Experience for Spartan Engineering.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Global Engineering Education|Global Engineering]] is a new subject that is of certain interest for not only the Cornerstone Engineering and Residential Experience programs but for the entire [[Michigan State University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]] at MSU. [[Engineering]] in today's society has shown to have a monumental impact on the global economy due to advancements in education, interdependence on economics with infrastructure, computers, transportation, technology and other [[manufactured goods]] as well as Michigan State University's [[study abroad|study-abroad]] program being ranked #1 in the nation, allowing for students to experience education and learn cultures in hundreds of countries.&lt;ref&gt;[http://studyabroad.msu.edu/contact/fact_sheet.pdf MSU.edu], MSU Study abroad. Accessed September 8th, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  Also of note is the innovative [http://vipp.isp.msu.edu/ Visiting International Professional Program], which connects professional education to the expertise of Michigan State University, a world leader in global research and leadership training. VIPP creates practical links between the world-class faculty at MSU and global industries, businesses, governments and societies. The newly established Cornerstone Engineering and Residential Experience programs for [[Michigan State University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]] have started programs abroad for more courses in engineering including [[Study abroad]] [[seminars]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.egr.msu.edu/undergraduate/news/2008/08/22/cornerstone-engineering-program MSU.edu], College of Engineering. Currents Magazine. Summer 2009. Volume 9 Number&lt;/ref&gt;

MSU currently offers a 30 credit graduate program for Masters in Educational Technology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://edutech.msu.edu/ |title=Educational Technology Programs at MSU|publisher=Edutech.msu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; in 3 different formats; completely online,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://edutech.msu.edu/online.html |title=Educational Technology Program at Michigan State University |publisher=Edutech.msu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; hybrid&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://edutech.msu.edu/hybrid.html |title=Educational Technology Program at Michigan State University |publisher=Edutech.msu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; in East Lansing, Michigan, or overseas. [http://edutech.msu.edu/overseas.html MSU.edu] The overseas program is offered at universities around the world. Past locations have included England, France, Switzerland and Thailand. The program lasts one month a summer for three summers, with each summer covering 9 credit hours. One online class is required between the second and third summer. The classes are focused on preparing teachers in integrating technology into their classrooms and helping them understand the affordances and constraints of using different programs. The courses are taught by MSU professors and are open to students around the world.

== Athletics ==

{{Main|Michigan State Spartans|List of Michigan State Spartans championships}}

Michigan State's [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[NCAA Division I-A|Division I-A]] program offers 12 [[Varsity team|varsity]] sports for men and 13 for women.&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt; Since their teams are called the Spartans, MSU's mascot is a Spartan warrior named [[Sparty]]. The university participates in the Big Ten Conference in all varsity sports except ice hockey, which competes in the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]]. The current athletic director is Mark Hollis, who was promoted to the position on January 1, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/2007-09-12-3746318224_x.htm | work=USA Today | title=Michigan State promotes Mark Hollis to athletic director | date=September 12, 2007 | accessdate=May 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hollis replaced [[Ron Mason]], who served as head hockey coach from 1979 to 2002, retiring with a record total of 924 wins, and a 635–270–69 record at MSU.&lt;ref name=&quot;ronmason&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-hockey/mtt/mason_ron00.html Player Bio: Ron Mason]. MSU Spartans.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Michigan State is among only sixteen Division 1A programs to win multiple national titles in football, and the only school to win multiple national titles in football, basketball, and hockey (MSU was the first athletic program to win multiple national titles in both football and basketball). MSU has won all of its football championships playing only division 1A opponents. The Spartans have participated in two events, in basketball and ice hockey, which have set world records for spectator attendances for both sports.

In 1888 Michigan State University (then as known as Michigan Agricultural College) along with Olivet, Albion and Hillsdale Colleges was a founding member of the nation's oldest athletic conference, the [[Michigan Intercollegiate Athletic Association]] (MIAA). MAC left the conference in 1907.

=== Football ===
{{Main|Michigan State Spartans football}}
[[Image:MSU Spartan Stadium Facade.jpg|thumb|right|[[Spartan Stadium, East Lansing|Spartan Stadium]] hosts varsity [[American football|football]] games and other events.]]
[[American football|Football]] has a long tradition at Michigan State. Starting as a club sport in 1884, football gained varsity status in 1896.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Grinczel, Steve. | title=They Are Spartans | location=Charleston, South Carolina | publisher=Arcadia Publishing | year=2003 | isbn=0-7385-3214-2 | page=9}}&lt;/ref&gt; MSU football teams won the [[Rose Bowl Game|Rose Bowl]] in 1954, 1956 and 1988. The Spartans accounted for four of the top eight selections in the [[1967 NFL Draft]], the only time a college football program has accomplished such a feat.

Today, the football team competes in [[Spartan Stadium, East Lansing|Spartan Stadium]], a renovated 75,005 seat football stadium near the center of campus. The current coach is [[Mark Dantonio]], who was hired on November 27, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/27/sports/ncaafootball/27coach.html?_r=2&amp;oref=slogin&amp;oref=slogin Michigan State Looks to Cincinnati for Coach]&quot;. ''The New York Times''. November 27, 2006. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Dantonio had an 18–17 record in his three year tenure at the [[University of Cincinnati]], including a 1–0 Bowl Game record.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://sports.espn.go.com/ncf/news/story?id=2677122 Michigan State hires former Cincy coach Dantonio]&quot;. ESPN.com. November 27, 2006. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; He led the team in its first season to a 7–6 record. The Spartans played in the Champs Sports Bowl against Boston College on December 28, 2007 and the Capital One Bowl against Georgia on January 1, 2009. MSU's traditional archrival is the [[University of Michigan]], against whom they compete annually for the [[Paul Bunyan Trophy]]. Their record against the Wolverines currently stands at 32-67-5. Michigan State is one of three Big Ten teams to have an annual non-conference football game against [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]]. MSU's record against the Fighting Irish is 25–44–1 but the Spartans have had much success against the Irish recently, becoming the first team ever to win six straight games at Notre Dame Stadium.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/div_ia/bigten/michigan_state/opponents_records.php?teamid=2349 Michigan State vs. Notre Dame]&quot;. College Football Data Warehouse. Accessed March 6, 2008. {{Wayback|url=http://www.cfbdatawarehouse.com/data/div_ia/bigten/michigan_state/opponents_records.php?teamid=2349|date =20070930011203|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, the Spartans finished 7-1 in conference play were Co-Big Ten Champions along with the [[University of Wisconsin]] and [[Ohio State University|Ohio State]].

[[Image:MSU Breslin Center.jpg|thumb|left|The Jack Breslin Student Events Center is home to the men and women's basketball teams.]]

=== Men's basketball ===

{{Main|Michigan State Spartans men's basketball}}
{{See also|Category:Michigan State Spartans men's basketball players|Category:Michigan State Spartans men's basketball coaches}}

MSU's men's basketball team has won the [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Championship|National Championship]] twice: in 1979 and again in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://static.espn.go.com/ncb/s/2000/1106/861084.html Spartans can relate to Izzo's winning ways]&quot;. ESPN.com. Retrieved March 10, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1979, [[Magic Johnson|Earvin &quot;Magic&quot; Johnson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;magicjohnson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/j/johnsma02.html Magic Johnson Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; along with [[Greg Kelser]],&lt;ref name=&quot;gregkelser&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/k/kelsegr01.html Greg Kelser Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jay Vincent]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jayvincent&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/v/vinceja01.html Jay Vincent Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and Mike Brkovich, led the MSU team to a 75–64 win against the [[Larry Bird]]-led [[Indiana State University|Indiana State]] Sycamores. In 2000, three players from [[Flint, Michigan|Flint]], [[Morris Peterson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;morrispeterson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/p/petermo01.html Morris Peterson Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charlie Bell (basketball)|Charlie Bell]]&lt;ref name=&quot;charliebell&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/b/bellch01.html Charlie Bell Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mateen Cleaves]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mateencleaves&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/c/cleavma01.html Mateen Cleaves Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; led the team to its second national title. Dubbed the &quot;Flintstones&quot;, they were the key to the Spartans' win against the [[University of Florida]]. On December 13, 2003, Michigan State and [[University of Kentucky|Kentucky]] played in the ''[[Basketbowl]]'', in which a record crowd of 78,129 watched the game in [[Detroit]]’s [[Ford Field]]. Kentucky won 79–74.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-baskbl/recaps/121303aaa.html Men's Basketball Falls To No. 8 Kentucky, 79–74]&quot;. MSU Spartans.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The basketball team currently plays at the [[Jack Breslin Student Events Center]] under head coach [[Tom Izzo]], who has a 336–137 record. The student spirit section at Breslin is called the [[Izzone]]. Izzo's coaching has helped the team make six [[Final Four]]s since 1999, winning the title in 2000, and thirteen consecutive NCAA tournament appearances (beginning in 1998). In 2009 the Spartans made it to the National Championship game and lost 89–72 to North Carolina. In 2010, the Spartans made it to the Final Four and lost 50-52 to Butler. The Spartans lost in the first round of the NCAA tournament in 2011 to UCLA 76-78.

=== Men's ice hockey ===
[[Image:MSU Munn Ice Arena.jpg|thumb|right|[[Munn Ice Arena]] was named for former [[American football|football]] coach Clarence L. &quot;Biggie&quot; Munn.]]
{{Main|Michigan State Spartans men's ice hockey}}
{{See also|Category:Michigan State Spartans ice hockey players|Category:Michigan State Spartans ice hockey coaches}}
The Michigan State University men's [[ice hockey]] team started in 1924, though it has only been a varsity sport since 1950. The team has since won national titles in 1966, 1986 and 2007. The Spartans came close to repeating the national title in 1987, but lost the championship game to the [[University of North Dakota]]. They play at MSU's [[Munn Ice Arena]]. Former head coach Ron Mason is college hockey's winningest coach with 924 wins total and 635 at MSU.&lt;ref name=&quot;ronmason&quot;/&gt; The current head [[Coach (ice hockey)|coach]] is [[Rick Comley]], who has a 181-133-39 record at MSU and will be retiring at the end of the 2010–11 season.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-hockey/mtt/comley_rick00.html Player Bio: Rick Comley]&quot;. MSU Spartans.com. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Since the Big Ten Conference does not include Division I men's [[ice hockey]], Michigan State competes in the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]]. Michigan State leads the CCHA in all-time wins, is second in CCHA Conference championships with 7, and is first in CCHA Tournament Championships with 11. Along with the [[University of Michigan]] (U-M) and the [[Ohio State University]], it is one of three Big Ten schools in the CCHA. As with other sports, the hockey rivalry between MSU and U-M is a fierce one, and on October 6, 2001, MSU faced U-M in the [[Cold War (ice hockey)|Cold War]], during which a world record crowd of 74,554 packed [[Spartan Stadium, East Lansing|Spartan Stadium]] to watch the game end in a 3–3 tie.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-hockey/recaps/100601aaa.html Spartan Hockey Ties Wolverines In Front Of Record Crowd]&quot;. MSU Spartans.com. October 6, 2001. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
In the 2006–2007 season, the Men's Ice Hockey team defeated [[Boston College]] for its third [[NCAA]] hockey championship.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-hockey/recaps/040707aaa.html Abdelkader's Last-Minute Tally Hands Spartans Third NCAA Title]&quot;. MSU Spartans.com. April 7, 2007. Retrieved March 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Men's cross country ===
{{See also|Michigan State Cross Country}}
Between World War I and World War II, Michigan State College competed in the [[Central Collegiate Conference]], winning titles in 1926–1929, 1932, 1933 and 1935. Michigan State also experienced success in the [[IC4A]], at New York’s [[Van Cortlandt Park]], winning 15 team titles (1933–1937, 1949, 1953, 1956–1960, 1962, 1963 and 1968). Since entering the Big Ten in 1950, Michigan State has won 14 men’s team titles (1951–1953, 1955–1960, 1962, 1963, 1968, 1970 and 1971). Michigan State hosted the inaugural [[NCAA Men's Cross Country Championship|NCAA cross country championships]] in 1938 and every year thereafter through 1964 (there was no championship in 1943). The Spartans won NCAA championships in 1939, 1948, 1949, 1952, 1955, 1956, 1958 and 1959.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frimodig, L. 1971&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Erickson, C. (2007). 2007–2008 Michigan State Cross Country and Track and Field Media Guide. East Lansing: MSU Sports Information Office.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ncaa.com/history/xc-d1.html|title=NCAA History|accessdate=2010-11-15|publisher=NCAA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Student life ==
[[Image:Hubbard Hall panoramic.jpg|thumb|right|Hubbard Hall is a twelve-story [[residence hall]] on the eastern edge of campus. It is MSU's second tallest building, surpassed by [[Spartan Stadium (East Lansing)|Spartan Stadium]]]]
East Lansing is very much a [[college town]], with 60.2% of the population between the ages of 15 and 24.&lt;ref&gt;[http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/QTTable?_bm=y&amp;-geo_id=16000US2624120&amp;-qr_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U_DP1&amp;-ds_name=DEC_2000_SF1_U&amp;-_lang=en&amp;-_sse=on East Lansing city, Michigan]&quot;. U.S. Census. 2000. Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; President John A. Hannah's push to expand in the 1950s and 1960s resulted in the largest [[residence hall]] system in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;Kiernan, Vincent. &quot;[http://chronicle.com/free/2003/01/2003010202t.htm Michigan State Asks Students to Turn Off Their Computers Over Winter Break]&quot;. ''The Chronicle of Higher Education''. January 2, 2003. Accessed April 13, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://chronicle.com/free/2003/01/2003010202t.htm|date =20070930190706|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 16,000 students live in MSU's 23 [[Michigan State University Housing|undergraduate halls]], one graduate hall, and three apartment villages. Each residence hall has its own hall government, with representatives in the [[Residence Halls Association]]. Yet despite the size and extent of on-campus housing, the residence halls are complemented by a variety of housing options. 58% of students live off-campus,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Michigan State University: Campus Life&quot;. ''The Princeton Review''. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; mostly in the areas closest to campus, in either apartment buildings, former single-family homes, fraternity and sorority houses, or in a [[Student Housing Cooperative at Michigan State University|co-op]].
[[Image:MSU Union.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Michigan State University Student Union|MSU Union]], designed by [[Pond and Pond]] is home to many events on campus.]]

=== Greek life ===
{{See also|List of Michigan State University fraternities and sororities}}
With over 3,000 members, Michigan State University's [[fraternity and sorority houses|Greek Community]] is one of the largest in the nation. Started in 1872&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.studentlife.msu.edu/current_students/greek.htm Greek Affairs]&quot;. Michigan State University Department of Student Life. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and re-established in 1922 by [[Lambda Chi Alpha]] Fraternity, [[Alpha Gamma Rho]] Fraternity, and [[Alpha Phi]] Sorority; the MSU Greek system now consists of 55 Greek lettered student societies.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.gogreek.msu.edu/flash.html Home]&quot;. Michigan State University Greek Societies. Accessed December 15, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.gogreek.msu.edu/flash.html|date =20071216235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; These chapters are in turn under the jurisdiction of one of MSU's four Greek governing councils: National Panhellenic Conference, North American Interfraternity Council, National Pan-Hellenic Council,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nphchq.org/&lt;/ref&gt; and Independent Greek Council. National Pan-Hellenic Council is made up of 9 organizations, 5 Fraternities and 4 Sororities, that were founded on Historically Black College and Universities (HBCU's).&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.ed.gov/about/inits/list/whhbcu/edlite-list.html&lt;/ref&gt; The [[North-American Interfraternity Conference|Interfraternity Council]] and the [[National Panhellenic Conference|Women's Panhellenic Council]] are each entirely responsible for their own budgets, giving them the freedom to hold large fundraising and recruitment events. MSU's fraternities and sororities hold many [[philanthropy]] events and community fundraisers. For example, in April 2011 the Greek Community held Greek Week to raise over $260,000 for the [[American Cancer Society]], and $5,000 for each of these charities: [[Big Brothers Big Sisters of America|Big Brothers Big Sisters]], [[The Listening Ear]] and previous charities include: the [[Make-A-Wish Foundation|Make-a-Wish]] Foundation (MSU Chapter), Share Laura's Hope, The Mary Beth Knox Scholarship, and the [[Special Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;Spurlock, Amanda. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/article.phtml?pk=35455 Cancer relay promotes unity, awareness]&quot;. ''The State News'', March 27, 2006. Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Student organizations ===
[[Image:Student Services Building.jpg|thumb|right|The Student Services Building houses the MSU Department of Student Life, as well as ASMSU and the Greek governing councils.]]
The Associated Students of Michigan State University (ASMSU) is the [[undergraduate]] [[students' union|student government]] of Michigan State University.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://asmsu.msu.edu/ Michigan State University – Student Government]&quot;. Associated Students of Michigan State University. Retrieved March 26, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; It is unusual amongst [[university]] [[Students' union|student governments]] for its [[decentralized]] bicameral structure,&lt;ref&gt;Associated Students of Michigan State University Website. &quot;[http://asmsu.msu.edu/documents/organization-wide%20flowchart.pdf Organizational Flowchart.]&quot; ([[PDF]] File). Accessed July 20, 2006. {{Wayback|url=http://asmsu.msu.edu/documents/organization-wide%20flowchart.pdf|date =20060901144553|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the relatively non-existent influence of the Greek system. ASMSU representatives are [[nonpartisan]] and many are elected in noncompetitive races. Their mission is to enhance the individual and collective student experience through education, empowerment, and advocacy by education to the needs and interest of students. Some services they offer include: free blue books, low cost copies and faxes, free yearbooks, interest free loans, funding for student organizations, free legal consultation, health insurance, and iClicker rentals. There are many ways of getting involved such as: Freshman Class Council, Senior Class Council, appointments to General Assembly, and employment. 

Students pay $16.75 per semester to fund the functions of the ASMSU, including stipends for the organization's officers and activities throughout the year.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, Kristi. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/article.phtml?pk=35500 ASMSU tax hike to fund new positions]&quot;. ''The State News''. March 29, 2006. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Some students have criticized ASMSU for not having enough electoral participation to gain a student mandate. [[Voter turnout|Turnout]] since 2001 has hovered between 3 and 17 percent, with the 2006 election bringing out 8% of the undergraduate student body.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, Kristi. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/article.phtml?pk=35452 Student vote count still low for ASMSU]&quot;. ''The State News''. March 27, 2006. Retrieved March 5, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

Student-run organizations beyond student government also have a large impact on the East Lansing/Michigan State University community. Student Organizations are registered through the Department of Student Life, which currently has a registry of over 550 student organizations. &lt;ref&gt;[http://studentlife.msu.edu/current_students/rso/orgs.htm] &quot;Department of Student Life&quot; &lt;/ref&gt; One example is the [[Tower Guard]] honor society. Tower Guard is the oldest and one of the most respected student organizations on campus,&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.msu.edu/~towergrd/aboutus.html About Tower Guard.] ''MSU Tower Guard''.&lt;/ref&gt; and works closely with the Resource Center for Persons with Disabilities (RCPD) in assisting students with disabilities.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}}

The Eli Broad College of Business includes 27 student organizations. The three largest organizations are the Finance Association (FA), the Accounting Student Association (ASA), and the Supply Chain Management Association (SCMA).&lt;ref&gt;Business Week. 2008. [http://www.businessweek.com/bschools/rankings/undergraduate_mba_profiles/michstate.html Undergraduate profile]. Retrieved July 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The SCMA is the host of the university's largest major specific career fair. The fair attracts over 100 companies and over 400 students each year.&lt;ref&gt;Michigan State University. 2008. Accessed July 9, 2008. http://www.bus.msu.edu/clubs/scma/careerfair/&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Activism ===

[[Activism|Activists]] have played a significant role in MSU history. During the height of the [[Vietnam War]], student protests helped create [[co-ed]] residence halls, and blocked the routing of [[Interstate 496]] through campus.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Sturm, {{cite web | url = http://www.lansingcitypulse.com/lansing/archives/040505/040505cover.html | title = Where is McPherson leading Moo U? Critics see comparisons to MSU’s Vietnam-era role | publisher = The Lansing City Pulse | date = 5 May 2004 | accessdate = 31 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1980s, Michigan State students convinced the University to [[divestment|divest]] the stocks of companies doing business in [[apartheid]] [[South Africa]] from its endowment portfolio, such as [[The Coca-Cola Company|Coca-Cola]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=U.S. Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs. | title=The Anti-Apartheid Act of 1985 | location=Washington | publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office | year=1985|page=213}}&lt;/ref&gt; MSU has many student groups focused on political change. Graduate campus groups include the Graduate Employees Union&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://geuatmsu.org/?page_id=2 About &amp; FAQs]&quot;. Graduate Employees Union at Michigan State University. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and the Council of Graduate Students.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://cogs.msu.edu/ Welcome]&quot;. MSU Council of Graduate Students. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Michigan State also has a variety of partisan groups ranging from [[liberalism|liberal]] to [[conservatism|conservative]], including the [[College Republicans]], the [[College Democrats]] and several [[Third party (politics)|third party]] organizations. Other partisan activist groups include [[Young Americans for Freedom]] and [[Young Americans for Liberty]] on the right; [[Young Democratic Socialists]], Students for Economic Justice, [[Young Communist League]] and ''[[Movimiento Estudiantil Chicano de Aztlan|MEChA]]'' on the left. Given MSU's proximity to the Michigan state capital of [[Lansing, Michigan|Lansing]], many politically inclined Spartans intern for state representatives.

=== Sustainability ===

The MSU Office of Sustainability works with the University Committee for a Sustainable Campus to &quot;foster a collaborative learning culture that leads the community to heightened awareness of its environmental impact.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;The Office of Campus Sustainability&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title =The Office of Campus Sustainability
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://www.ecofoot.msu.edu/index.htm
  | archiveurl =http://web.archive.org/web/20070812224921/http://www.ecofoot.msu.edu/index.htm
  | archivedate =2007-08-12
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The University is a member of the Chicago Climate Exchange, the world’s first greenhouse gas emission registry, and boasts the lowest electrical consumption per square foot among [[Big Ten]] universities. The University has set a goal of reducing energy use by 15%, reducing greenhouse gas emissions by 15%, reducing landfill waste by 30% by 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot; MSU honored by National Wildlife Federation for sustainability efforts&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = MSU honored by National Wildlife Federation for sustainability efforts
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://news.msu.edu/story/5634/
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university has also pledged to meet [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]]-certification standards for all new construction. In July 2009, the University completed construction of a $13.3 million recycling center, and hopes to double their 2008 recycling rate of 14% by 2010.
&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU Board of Trustees OKs $13.3M step to go 'green'&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = MSU Board of Trustees OKs $13.3M step to go ‘green’
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://statenews.com/index.php/article/2008/01/msu_board_of_trustees_oks_133m_step_to_go_green
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The construction of Brody Hall, a residence hall of Michigan State University Housing, was completed in August 2011 and qualified for LEED Silver certification because the facility includes a rain water collection tank used for restroom fixtures, a white PVC roof, meters that will monitor utilities to make sure they are used efficiently, and the use of recycled matter and local sources for building materials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://food-management.com/news_briefs/michigan_state_brody0105 |title=MSU Opens New Dining Hall |date=January 5, 2011 |accessdate=April 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Environmental Steward’s program support’s President Simon’s &quot;Boldness by Design&quot; strategic vision to transform environmental stewardship on campus within the seven year time frame.&lt;ref name=&quot;Environmental Stewardship Program&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Environmental Stewardship Program
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://www.bespartangreen.msu.edu/about.html
  | accessdate = 2010-11-29 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Environmental stewards promote environmental changes among co-workers and peers, be points of contact for their department for environment-related concerns, and be liaisons between the Be Spartan Green Team and buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Environmental Stewardship Program&quot;/&gt;

ECO is the leading student-run sustainability organization on campus. They are also affiliated with regional and national groups such as Campus Climate Challenge and the Michigan Student Sustainability Coalition.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU ECO Get Involved On Campus&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = MSU ECO Get Involved On Campus
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =https://www.msu.edu/~eco/campus.html
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}{{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Student Organic Farm is a student-run, four-season farm, which teaches the principals of organic farming and through a certificate program and [[community supported agriculture]] (CSA) on ten acres on the MSU campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;MSU Organic Farm&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = MSU Organic Farm
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://www.msuorganicfarm.org/home.php/
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
The certificate program consists of year round crop production, course work in organic farming, practical training and management, and an off-site internship requirement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Certificate Program Overview&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Certificate Program Overview
  | publisher =Michigan State University
  | url =http://www.msuorganicfarm.org/certificateprogram.htm
  | accessdate = 2008-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Media ===
[[Image:MSU Bronze Sparty 2.jpg|thumb|upright|A 2005 bronze replica of &quot;The Spartan&quot; (nicknamed &quot;[[Sparty]]&quot;) replaces Leonard D. Jungwirth's [[modernist]] original.&lt;ref&gt;Oswald, Tom. &quot;[http://www.msutoday.msu.edu/news/index.php3?article=26Aug2005-3 'Sparty' Unveiled]&quot;. ''MSU Today''. August 26, 2005. Retrieved April 14, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
MSU has a variety of campus media outlets. The student-run newspaper is called ''[[The State News]]'' and free copies of the paper are available online or at East Lansing newsstands. The paper prints 28,500 copies of the paper Monday through Friday during the fall and spring semesters, and 15,000 copies Monday through Friday during the summer.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.statenews.com/aboutus.phtml Masthead]&quot;. ''The State News'.' Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The paper is not published on weekends, holidays, or semester breaks, but is continually updated online at statenews.com. The campus [[yearbook]] is called the ''Red Cedar Log''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[https://www.msu.edu/~redcedar/about/about.html About RCL]&quot;. ''Red Cedar Log'' website. Accessed November 29, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; ''Red Cedar Review'', Michigan State University's premier literary digest for over forty years, is the longest running undergraduate-run literary journal in the United States.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070819194925/http://msupress.msu.edu/rcrorg/about.php About Red Cedar Review]&quot;. ''Red Cedar Review'' website. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; It is published annually by the [[Michigan State University Press]].

MSU also publishes a student-run magazine during the academic year called Ing Magazine.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://ingising.com/]&quot;. ingising.com Retrieved October 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Created in 2007 by MSU alumnus Adam Grant, the publication is released at the beginning of each month and currently publishes 7 issues each school year.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://ingising.com/about.php]&quot;. IngisIng.com Retrieved October 5, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Electronic media include three radio stations and one [[public television]] station, as well as [[MSU Telecasters|student-produced]] television shows. MSU's [[Public Broadcasting Service]] affiliate, [[WKAR-TV]], the station is the second-oldest educational television station in the United States, and the oldest east of the [[Mississippi River]]. Besides broadcasting PBS shows, WKAR-TV produces its own local programming, such as a high school [[quiz bowl]] show called &quot;QuizBusters&quot;. In addition, MSU has three radio stations; WKAR-AM plays [[National Public Radio]]'s talk radio programming, whereas WKAR-FM focuses mostly on classical music programming.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.wkar.org/ Main Page]&quot;. WKAR.org. Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Michigan State's student-run radio station, [[WDBM]], broadcasts mostly alternative music during weekdays, and electric music programming nights and weekends.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071224053200/http://www.impact89fm.org/shows.html Shows]&quot;. Impact 89FM. Retrieved December 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:MSU forest trail.jpg|thumb|left|upright|MSU's campus is heavily forested. This trail runs behind several residence halls, including Owen Hall, McDonel Hall and Holmes Hall.]]

== People ==
{{Main|List of Michigan State University people}}
The current president of the University is [[Lou Anna Simon]] who took over on January 1, 2005, after being appointed by MSU's governing board, the [[Board of Trustees]]. The Board receives its mandate from the Michigan Constitution since MSU is a state-owned school. The constitution allows for eight [[trustee]]s who are elected by statewide referendum every two years. Trustees have eight-year terms, with two of the eight elected every other year.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.legislature.mi.gov/(hgdxmueqsj45to45yyksoijr)/mileg.aspx?page=GetMCLDocument&amp;objectname=mcl-Article-VIII-5 Michigan Constitution of 1963]&quot;. Article VIII. Section 5. Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; As of 2007, the Board is made up of three [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]] and five [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]].&lt;ref&gt;Roeschke, Jaclyn. &quot;[http://www.statenews.com/article.phtml?pk=26745 Ferguson, Foster win MSU trustee seats]&quot;. ''The State News''. November 5, 2004. Retrieved April 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 19th century ===
[[Image:MSU Eustace-Cole Hall.jpg|thumb|right|[[Eustace-Cole Hall]] was the United States' first freestanding horticulture laboratory. It is the only MSU building on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]. Additionally, Eustace-Cole Hall houses the offices of the Michigan State University Honors College.]]
Important College leaders in the 19th century include [[John Clough Holmes|John C. Holmes]], who kept the Agriculture School from being a part of the [[University of Michigan]] and is widely credited with being the prime mover for the school's founding;&lt;ref name=&quot;sesquicentennial&quot;/&gt; [[Joseph R. Williams]], the first president;&lt;ref name=&quot;josephrwilliams&quot;/&gt; and [[Theophilus C. Abbot]], the third president who stabilized the College after the Civil War.&lt;ref name=&quot;tcabbot&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/msuarhc/abbot.htm Theophilus Capen Abbot]&quot;. Michigan State University Archives &amp; Historical Collections. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Also of importance was botany professor [[William J. Beal]], an early plant (hybrid corn) geneticist who championed the laboratory teaching method.&lt;ref name=&quot;williamjbeal&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.givingto.msu.edu/beal.html William James Beal Society]&quot;. Campaign for MSU University Development. Accessed April 18, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.givingto.msu.edu/beal.html|date =20070416115959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another distinguished faculty member of the era was the alumnus/professor [[Liberty Hyde Bailey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;libertyhydebailey&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://rmc.library.cornell.edu/bailey/biography/biography_7.html Liberty Hyde Bailey – A Man for All Seasons]&quot;. Cornell University Library. p. 7. Retrieved April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Bailey was the first to raise the study of horticulture to a science, paralleling botany, which earned him the title of &quot;Father of American Horticulture&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Hugo, Nancy | title=Earth Works: Readings for Backyard Gardeners | publisher=University of Virginia Press | year=1997 | isbn=0-8139-1831-6|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[William L. Carpenter (Michigan jurist)|William L. Carpenter]], a jurist who was elected to the Third Judicial Circuit of Michigan in 1894, and member of the [[Michigan Supreme Court]] from 1902 until 1904. Other famous 19th century graduates include [[Ray Stannard Baker]],&lt;ref name=&quot;raystannardbaker&quot;&gt;Bannister, Robert. &quot;[http://www.swarthmore.edu/SocSci/rbannis1/Baker/index.html Ray Stannard Baker]&quot;. Swathmore Department of History. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; a famed &quot;[[muckraker]]&quot; journalist and [[Pulitzer Prize]] winning biographer; [[Minakata Kumagusu]],&lt;ref name=&quot;minakatakumagusu&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.minakatakumagusu-kinenkan.jp/english/kannai/tenji_2/index.htm Going Abroad]&quot;. Minakata Kumugusu Museum. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; a renowned environmental scientist; and [[William Bagley (educator)|William Chandler Bagley]], a pioneering education reformer.&lt;ref name=&quot;williamcbagley&quot;&gt;Null, J. Wesley. [http://www3.baylor.edu/%7EWesley_Null/ADisciplinedProgressivesample.pdf A Disciplined Progressive Educator: The Life and Career of William Chandler Bagley]' (PDF). New York: Peter Lang. ISBN 0-8204-6909-2.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:MSU Human Ecology Building.jpg|left|thumb|The Human Ecology Building]]

=== 20th and 21st centuries ===
There are currently around 442,000 living MSU [[alumni]] worldwide giving the school one of the largest number of alumni of any institution of higher learning.&lt;ref name=&quot;msufacts&quot;/&gt; Famous MSU alumni include former Michigan governors [[James Blanchard]]&lt;ref name=&quot;jamesblanchard&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000538 Blanchard, James Johnston]&quot;. 208. &quot;[[Abdulaziz Mohammed Al-Failakawi]], Commercial Analyst and Relationship Manager at [[Kuwait International Bank]]. Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[John Engler]],&lt;ref name=&quot;johnengler&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.michigan.gov/formergovernors/0,1607,7-212-31303-2273--,00.html Governor John Engler Biography]&quot;. Michigan's Former Governors. Retrieved April 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. Senators [[Debbie Stabenow]]&lt;ref name=&quot;debbiestabenow&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://stabenow.senate.gov/biography.htm Biography]&quot;. United States Senator Debbie Stabenow. Retrieved April 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tim Johnson (U.S. Senator)|Tim Johnson]], U.S. ambassador to Brazil [[Donna Hrinak]], former Jordan Prime Minister [[Adnan Badran]], billionaire philanthropists [[Tom Gores]] and [[Eli Broad]],&lt;ref name=&quot;elibroad&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.forbes.com/lists/2006/54/biz_06rich400_Eli-Broad_599L.html 400 Richest Americans – 42 – Eli Broad]&quot;. ''Forbes''. September 21, 2006. Retrieved April 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Chief Justice of the Texas Supreme Court [[Wallace B. Jefferson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Wallace B. Jefferson&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.supreme.courts.state.tx.us/court/justice_wjefferson.asp |title=State.tx.us |publisher=Supreme.courts.state.tx.us |date= |accessdate=2010-11-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; trial lawyer [[Geoffrey Feiger]], former [[Food and Drug Administration]] official [[Peter Rheinstein]], former Detroit mayor [[Kwame Kilpatrick]], [[Pulitzer Prize]]-winning novelist [[Richard Ford]], [[Teamsters]] president [[James P. Hoffa]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jamesphoffa&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.teamster.org/about/hoffa/hoffabio.htm Biography of General President Hoffa]&quot;, teamster.org. International Brotherhood of Teamsters. Accessed April 26, 2006. {{Wayback|url=http://www.teamster.org/about/hoffa/hoffabio.htm|date =20060415235959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Quicken Loans]] founder and [[Cleveland Cavaliers]] owner and billionaire [[Dan Gilbert (businessman)|Dan Gilbert]],&lt;ref name=&quot;dangilbert&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.forbes.com/lists/2006/54/biz_06rich400_Daniel-Gilbert_LIVH.html 400 Richest Americans – 354 – Daniel Gilbert]&quot;. ''Forbes''. September 21, 2006. Retrieved April 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sergeant at Arms of the United States House of Representatives|Sergeant at Arms of the U.S. House of Representatives]] [[Wilson Livingood]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wilsonlivingood&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.msu.edu/unit/msuaa/magazine/s95/wilson.htm Wilson Livingood: Security for the U.S. Home]&quot;. Michigan State University Alumni Association Magazine. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; former Michigan U.S. Senator and [[United States Secretary of Energy|Secretary of Energy]] [[Spencer Abraham]],&lt;ref name=&quot;spencerabraham&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/government/abraham-bio.html Secretary of Energy Spencer Abraham]&quot;. The White House. Retrieved April 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; former Vice President of the Republic of [[Liberia]] [[Harry Moniba]], and former [[United States Ambassador to Italy|U.S. Ambassador to Italy]] [[Peter Secchia]]. Alumni in [[Hollywood]] include actors [[James Caan (actor)|James Caan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jamescaan&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001001/bio James Caan – Biography]&quot;. Internet Movie Database. Retrieved April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anthony Heald]],&lt;ref name=&quot;anthonyheald&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0372217/bio Anthony Heald – Biography]&quot;. Internet Movie Database. Retrieved April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Urich]]&lt;ref name=&quot;roberturich&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0001810/bio Robert Urich – Biography]&quot;. Internet Movie Database. Retrieved April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[William Fawcett (actor)|William Fawcett]];&lt;ref name=&quot;williamfawcett&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0269514/bio William Fawcet – Biography]&quot;. Internet Movie Database. Retrieved January 25, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; comedian [[Dick Martin (comedian)|Dick Martin]], film director [[Sam Raimi]], and [[Academy Award]] winning film editor of ''[[The Hurt Locker]]'' and the ''[[Spider-Man (film)|Spider-Man]]'' films, [[Bob Murawski]],&lt;ref name=&quot;bobmurawski&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0613657/bio Bob Murawski – Biography]&quot;. Internet Movie Database. Retrieved April 27, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as screenwriter [[David Magee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;davidmagee&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.cal.msu.edu/portals/stansell.htm 2006 Distinguished Alumni Award: David S. Magee, BA Theatre '84]&quot;. Michigan State University College of Arts and Letters. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Puerto Rican comedian [[Sunshine Logroño]] (who has played the occasional Hollywood movie) was a graduate student at MSU. Journalists include NBC reporter [[Chris Hansen]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3949042/ Chris Hansen]&quot;. &quot;Dateline NBC&quot;. Retrieved November 13, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; AP White House Correspondent [[Nedra Pickler]], and NPR Washington Correspondent [[Don Gonyea]]. Novelist [[Michael Kimball]] graduated in 1990. Author [[Erik Qualman]] graduated with honors in 1994 and was also Academic Big-Ten in basketball. [[Susan K. Avery]], the first woman president and director of the [[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]], received an MSU bachelor's degree in [[physics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = | title =WHOI names Dr. Susan K. Avery first woman president | publisher =Cape Cod Today | date =October 16, 2007 | url =http://www.capecodtoday.com/news716.htm | accessdate=2009-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, two of the [[Little Rock Nine]] attended Michigan State, including [[Ernest Green]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ernestgreen&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://newsroom.msu.edu/site/indexer/1069/content.htm MSU Announces Celebratory Plans in Honor of Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.]&quot;. MSU Newsroom. January 12, 2000. Retrieved April 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; the first black student to graduate from [[Little Rock Central High School]], and [[Carlotta Walls LaNier]].&lt;ref name=&quot;carlottawellslanier&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/entry-detail.aspx?entryID=729 Carlotta Wells Lanier]&quot;. Encyclopedia of Arkansas. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The University awarded an honorary degree to [[Robert Mugabe]] in 1990, but revoked it in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wilx.com/home/headlines/28302079.html | title = Mugabe Stripped Of MSU Degree | publisher = WILX.com | date = 2008-09-12 | accessdate = 2008-10-20 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Spartans formerly or currently in the [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] include [[Earvin &quot;Magic&quot; Johnson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;magicjohnson&quot;/&gt; [[Greg Kelser]],&lt;ref name=&quot;gregkelser&quot;/&gt; [[Jay Vincent]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jayvincent&quot;/&gt; [[Steve Smith (basketball)|Steve Smith]],&lt;ref name=&quot;stevesmith&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/s/smithst01.html Steve Smith Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved April 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Scott Skiles]],&lt;ref name=&quot;scottskiles&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/s/skilesc01.html Scott Skiles Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved April 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jason Richardson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jasonrichardson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/r/richaja01.html Jason Richardson Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved April 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mateen Cleaves]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mateencleaves&quot;/&gt; [[Alan Anderson (basketball)|Alan Anderson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;alanderson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/a/anderal01.html Alan Anderson Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Zach Randolph]],&lt;ref name=&quot;zachrandolph&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/r/randoza01.html Zach Randolph Statistics]&quot;. Basketball-Reference.com. Retrieved April 20, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Morris Peterson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;morrispeterson&quot;/&gt; [[Charlie Bell (basketball)|Charlie Bell]]&lt;ref name=&quot;charliebell&quot;/&gt; and [[Shannon Brown]].&lt;ref name=&quot;shannonbrown&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Shannon Brown|url=http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/b/brownsh01.html|work=Basketball-Reference.com|accessdate=April 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the [[American Football League]]'s [[American Football League All-Time Team|All-Time Team]] are tight-end [[Fred Arbanas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fredarbansas&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.kcchiefs.com/history/60s/ Chiefs History 1960s]&quot;. Kansas City Chiefs. Accessed April 28, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.kcchiefs.com/history/60s/|date =20070416115959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Safety (American football position)|safety]] [[George Saimes]].&lt;ref name=&quot;georgesaimes&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/S/SaimGe00.htm?redir George Saimes Statistics]&quot;. Pro-Football-Reference.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[National Football League]], MSU alumni include Carl Banks, who was a member of the Giants teams that won [[Super Bowl XXI|Super Bowls XXI]] and [[Super Bowl XXV|XXV]]. Banks was a standout in their Super Bowl XXI victory in which he recorded 14 total tackles, including ten solo tackles, as well as being part of the NFL's 1980's All-Decade Team
[[Morten Andersen]],&lt;ref name=&quot;mortenandersen&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=164 Morten Andersen]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Plaxico Burress]],&lt;ref name=&quot;plaxicoburress&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=28759 Plaxico Burress]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Andre Rison]],&lt;ref name=&quot;andrerison&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://andrerison.com/index.html Andre 'Bad Moon' Rison]&quot;. AndreRison.com. Accessed April 28, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://andrerison.com/index.html|date =20070416115959|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Derrick Mason]],&lt;ref name=&quot;derrickmason&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=25021 Derek Mason]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Muhsin Muhammad]],&lt;ref name=&quot;muhsinmuhammad&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=23866 Muhsin Muhammad]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[T. J. Duckett]],&lt;ref name=&quot;tjduckett&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=32994 T.J. Duckett]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Flozell Adams]],&lt;ref name=&quot;flozelladams&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=25961 Flozell Adams]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Julian Peterson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;julianpeterson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.nflplayers.com/players/player.aspx?id=28767 Julian Peterson]&quot;. NFLPlayers.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Charles Rogers (American football)|Charles Rogers]],&lt;ref name=&quot;charlesrogers&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/R/RogeCh01.htm Charles Rogers Statistics]&quot;. Pro-Football-Reference.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jim Miller (quarterback)|Jim Miller]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jimmiller&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-footbl/spec-rel/050806aaa.html MSU Announces Football Broadcast Team]&quot;. MSUSpartans.com. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Earl Morrall]],&lt;ref name=&quot;earlmorrall&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.mashf.com/1987_inductees.htm#Earl_Morrall Class of '87]&quot;. Muskegon Area Sports Hall of Fame. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wayne Fontes]],&lt;ref name=&quot;waynefontes&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/F/FontWa20.htm Wayne Fontes Statistics]&quot;. Pro-Football-Reference.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bubba Smith]]&lt;ref name=&quot;bubbasmith&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.collegefootball.org/famersearch.php?id=60009 George Webster].&quot; College Football Hall of Fame. Retrieved April 28, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Drew Stanton]].&lt;ref name=&quot;drewstanton&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.sportsline.com/nfl/players/playerpage/421487 Drew Stanton]&quot;. NFL Football at CBSSports.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Former MSU quarterback [[Jeff Smoker]] now plays in the [[Arena Football League (1987–2008)|Arena Football League]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jeffsmoker&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.azrattlers.com/team/roster/index.html?player_id=85 #15 Smoker, Jeff, QB]&quot;. azrattlers.com. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Former Michigan State players in the [[National Hockey League]] include All Star Defensemen [[Duncan Keith]], [[Rod Brind'Amour]],&lt;ref name=&quot;rodbrindamour&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=576 Rod Brind'Amour].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Anson Carter]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ansoncarter&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=847 Anson Carter].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Donald McSween]],&lt;ref name=&quot;donaldmcsween&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=576 Don McSween].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adam Hall]],&lt;ref name=&quot;adamhall&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=44996 Adam Hall].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[John-Michael Liles]], [[Justin Abdelkader]], brothers [[Kelly Miller (ice hockey)|Kelly Miller]]&lt;ref name=&quot;kellymiller&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid%5B%5D=3728 Kelly Miller].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kip Miller]],&lt;ref name=&quot;kipmiller&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=3730 Kip Miller].&quot; Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as their cousins, brothers [[Ryan Miller]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ryanmiller&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid%5B%5D=45065 Ryan Miller].&quot;Florida Panthers star forward David Booth also attended MSU. Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved April 21, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Drew Miller]].&lt;ref name=&quot;drewmiller&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid=69845 Drew Miller]&quot;. Internet Hockey Database. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Former Michigan State players in [[Major League Baseball]] include [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum|Hall of Fame]] inductee [[Robin Roberts (baseball player)|Robin Roberts]],&lt;ref name=&quot;robinroberts&quot;&gt;[http://www.baseballhalloffame.org/hofers_and_honorees/hofer_bios/roberts_robin.htm Robin Roberts]&quot;. National Baseball Hall of Fame. Accessed April 17, 2007. {{Wayback|url=http://www.baseballhalloffame.org/hofers_and_honorees/hofer_bios/roberts_robin.htm|date =20070405083946|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kirk Gibson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;kirkgibson&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.baseball-almanac.com/players/player.php?p=gibsoki01 Kirk Gibson Baseball Stats]&quot;. Baseball Almanac. Retrieved April 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Steve Garvey]]&lt;ref name=&quot;stevegarvey&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://spartanstars.home.comcast.net/msubaseball.htm Steve Garvey]&quot;. Michigan State Baseball Alumni. Retrieved April 29, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Mark Mulder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;markmulder&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://stlouis.cardinals.mlb.com/team/player.jsp?player_id=150426 Mark Mulder]&quot;. The Official Site of the St. Louis Cardinals. Retrieved April 17, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Olympics|Olympic]] [[gold medal]]ists include [[Savatheda Fynes]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sevathedafynes&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/genrel/msu-genreleases26.html Major Athletic Award Winners Announced at Michigan State]&quot;. msuspartans.cstv.com. June 12, 1997. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Fred Alderman]].&lt;ref name=&quot;frederickalderman&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDD1330F932A1575AC0A96E958260 Frederick Alderman, Oldest U.S. Olympic Gold Medalist, 93]&quot;. ''The New York Times''. September 21, 1998. Retrieved January 9, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Spartans are also contributing athletes to [[Major League Soccer]], as [[Kevin Reiman]], [[Doug Demartin]], [[Dave Hertel]], [[Greg Janicki]], [[Kenzo Webster]], [[Rauwshan McKenzie]], [[John Minagawa-Webster]] and [[Ryan McMahen]] have all played in [[Major League Soccer]].&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://msuspartans.cstv.com/sports/m-soccer/spec-rel/012808aaa.html Kevin Reiman Selected In MLS Supplemental Draft]&quot;. msuspartans.cstv.com. January 28, 2008 Accessed April 11, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, [[Alex Skotarek]], [[Steve Twellman]] and [[Buzz Demling]] played in the [[North American Soccer League]], with Demling playing in the [[1972 Summer Olympics]] and the [[United States Men's National Soccer Team]] in the 1970s.

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Michigan|University}}
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[List of land-grant universities]]
** [[Morrill Land-Grant Colleges Act]]
* [[List of colleges and universities in Michigan]]
* [[Michigan#Education|State of Michigan Education]]
{{div col end}}

== References ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Further reading ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | author=Kuhn, Madison. | title=Michigan State: The First Hundred Years, 1855–1955 | location=East Lansing | publisher=Michigan State University Press | year=1955 | isbn=0-87013-222-9}}
* {{cite book | author=Stanford, Linda O., and Dewhurst, C. Kurt. | title=MSU Campus: Buildings, Places, Spaces | location=East Lansing | publisher=Michigan State University Press| year=2002 | isbn=0-87013-631-3}}
{{refend}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|Michigan State University}}
* [http://www.msu.edu/ Official site]
* [http://www.msuspartans.com/ Official athletics site]
* [http://www.mac1855.com/ Michigan Agricultural College artifacts, a private collection]
{{Coord|42.723387|-84.481366|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}
{{Michigan State University}}
{{Lansing-East Lansing}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:white;color:#18453b;border:1px solid #18453b;
|state =autocollapse
|list =
{{Big Ten Conference}}
{{Committee on Institutional Cooperation}}
{{Central Collegiate Hockey Association}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{Public universities in Michigan}}
{{Public Ivy}}
{{Largest United States universities by undergraduate enrollment}}
}}

[[Category:Michigan State University]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:Committee on Institutional Cooperation]]
[[Category:East Lansing, Michigan]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1855]]
[[Category:Education in Lansing, Michigan]]
[[Category:Forestry education]]
[[Category:Grand River Avenue]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Michigan]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ingham County. Michigan]]

{{Link GA|zh}}

[[ar:جامعة ولاية ميشيغان]]
[[az:Miçiqan Universiteti]]
[[bg:Мичигански щатски университет]]
[[ca:Universitat de Michigan State]]
[[cs:Michigan State University]]
[[da:Michigan State University]]
[[de:Michigan State University]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de Míchigan]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی میشیگان]]
[[fr:Université d'État du Michigan]]
[[fy:Michigan State University]]
[[ko:미시간 주립 대학교]]
[[hi:मिशिगन विश्वविद्यालय]]
[[it:Università statale del Michigan]]
[[ms:Michigan State University]]
[[nl:Michigan State University]]
[[ja:ミシガン州立大学]]
[[no:Michigan State University]]
[[pnb:میشیگن سٹیٹ یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Michigan State University]]
[[pt:Michigan State University]]
[[ru:Университет штата Мичиган]]
[[simple:Michigan State University]]
[[fi:Michiganin osavaltionyliopisto]]
[[tl:Pamantasang Estado ng Misigan]]
[[ta:மிச்சிகன் மாநிலப் பல்கலைக்கழகம்]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยมิชิแกนสเตต]]
[[zh:密西根州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
