<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24133330" ns="0" title="Kidnapping of Jaycee Lee Dugard"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox civilian attack
| title        = Jaycee Dugard abduction case
| location     = Abduction: [[South Lake Tahoe, California|South Lake Tahoe]], [[El Dorado County, California]], [[United States]]&lt;br&gt;Confinement: 1554 Walnut Avenue (unincorporated [[Contra Costa County]] near) [[Antioch, California]]
| date         = {{Start date|1991|06|10}} – August 26, 2009
| time         =
| timezone     =
| type         = [[Kidnapping]], [[false imprisonment]], [[rape]]
| victim       = Jaycee Lee Dugard&lt;br&gt;missing for 18 years
| susperps     =
| perpetrators = Phillip Garrido and Nancy Garrido
}}
The '''kidnapping of Jaycee Lee Dugard''' occurred on June 10, 1991 in [[South Lake Tahoe, California]]. Dugard was 11 years old at the time and was [[child abduction|abducted]] from a street while she was walking from home to a school bus stop. Searches began immediately after the kidnapping, but no reliable leads were generated. She remained missing for more than 18 years.

On August 25, 2009, convicted sex offender Phillip Craig Garrido visited the campus of [[UC Berkeley]] accompanied by two young girls. Their unusual behavior there sparked an investigation that led to his bringing the two girls to a parole office on August 26, accompanied by a young woman who was then identified as Dugard.

Garrido, 58, and his wife Nancy Garrido, 54, of [[Antioch, California]], were arrested for kidnapping and other charges; they pleaded guilty on April 28, 2011 to Dugard's kidnapping and sexual assault. Law enforcement officers believe Dugard was kept in a concealed area behind Garrido's house in Antioch for 18 years. During this time Dugard bore two daughters who were aged 11 and 15 at the time of her reappearance.

On June 2, 2011, Phillip Garrido was sentenced to 431 years imprisonment; his wife received 36 years to life.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-13631641
 | title = Jaycee Dugard kidnap: Victim rues 'stolen life'
 | author =
 | publisher = [[BBC News]]
 | date = June 2, 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background of kidnappers==
{{Garridosinfo}}
Phillip Craig Garrido was born in [[Contra Costa County, California]], on April 5, 1951. He grew up in [[Brentwood, California|Brentwood]], where he graduated from [[Liberty High School (Brentwood, California)|Liberty High School]] in 1969. His father, Manuel Garrido, who continues to reside in Brentwood, said his son was a &quot;good boy&quot; as a child, but radically changed after a serious motorcycle accident as a teenager, and later turned to drug use (primarily [[methamphetamine|crystal meth]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bulwa|first=Demian|title=Dugard: I never tried to run from Garridos|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/06/02/BAFB1JP44B.DTL&amp;tsp=1|accessdate=3 June 2011|newspaper=SF Gate|date=June 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Sacramento Bee]]'' and the [[Associated Press]] have reported that the elder Garrido has begun demanding money in exchange for speaking with reporters; both organizations have refused.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/breakingnews/ci_13226119
 | title = Accident, drug use changed man accused in abduction, father says
 | author = Costa, Hilary, Lockett, Jonathan, and Burgarino, Paul
 | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News
 | date = 2009-08-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.contracostatimes.com/mytown/ci_13223532
 | author = Costa, Hilary
 | title = Father: Man accused of abducting Jaycee Lee Dugard changed after accident, drug use
 | publisher = Contra Costa Times
 | date = 2009-08-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | title = From the Editor: Why we won't stoop and pay for a scoop
 | author = Sill, Melanie
 | publisher = [[Sacramento Bee]]
 | date = 2009-09-13
 | accessdate = 2009-09-13
 | url = http://www.sacbee.com/fromtheeditor/story/2177006.html
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.meganslaw.ca.gov/cgi/prosoma.dll?searchby=offender&amp;id=14299162D0546
 | title = Garrido's entry on the California Sex Offender's Registry
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972, Garrido was arrested and charged with [[sexual assault|sexually assaulting]] a 14-year-old girl, but the case did not go to trial after the girl declined to testify.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/04/us/04rape.html
 | title = Suspect Faced ’72 Rape Case
 | publisher = The New York Times
 | date = 2009-09-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1973, Garrido married high-school classmate Christine Murphy, who said Garrido was [[domestic violence|abusive]]. Murphy alleges that Garrido kidnapped her when she tried to leave him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.cbsnews.com/blogs/2009/09/01/crimesider/entry5279298.shtml
 | author = Saltzman, Sammy Rose
 | title = Phillip Garrido &quot;Tried to Gouge My Eyes Out,&quot; Says First Wife
 | work = Crimesider
 | publisher = CBS News
 | date = 2009-09-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976, Garrido kidnapped Katherine Callaway in [[South Lake Tahoe, California]]. He took her to a [[Reno, Nevada]] warehouse, where he sexually assaulted her.&lt;ref name=callaway&gt;{{cite news
 | title = Rape victim describes Garrido's attack
 | publisher = [[Seattle Times]]
 | date = 2009-09-02
 | accessdate = 2009-09-13
 | author = Stanton, Sam
 | author2 = Minugh, Kim
 | author3 = Lillis, Ryan
 | url = http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/nationworld/2009788724_phil02.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt; When a police officer noticed a suspicious car parked outside at unusually late hours, he came up to investigate. Callaway then emerged and asked for help. Garrido was promptly arrested.&lt;ref name=callaway/&gt; He was charged and convicted of crimes in both federal and state courts.&lt;ref name=callaway/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ktvn-NDPS&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.ktvn.com/Global/story.asp?S=11010442
 | title = Nevada Department of Public Safety Media Release
 | publisher = KTVN-TV
 | date = 2009-08-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 1976 court-ordered psychiatric evaluation, Garrido was diagnosed as a &quot;sexual deviant and chronic drug abuser.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.latimes.com/media/acrobat/2009-09/49002128.pdf
 | title = Report of Lynn B. Gerow, Jr., M.D.
 | date = 1976-09-20
 | publisher = latimes.com
 | accessdate = 2009-11-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The psychiatrist recommended that a [[neurology|neurological]] examination be conducted because Garrido's chronic drug use could be &quot;responsible in part&quot; for his &quot;mixed&quot; or &quot;multiple&quot; sexual deviation. Garrido was then evaluated by a neurologist. The diagnostic impression was: &quot;normal neurological examination.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.latimes.com/media/acrobat/2009-09/49002152.pdf
 | title = Report of Albert F. Peterman, M.D.
 | date = 1977-01-06
 | publisher = latimes.com
 | accessdate = 2009-11-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In court, Garrido testified that he masturbated in his car by the side of grammar schools and high schools while watching young girls.&lt;ref name=nydailynews_01&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/2009/09/01/2009-09-01_phillip_garrido_charged_with_kidnapping_jaycee_lee_dugard_told_court_he_stalked_.html
 | author = Dillon, Nancy, and Siemaszko, Corky
 | title = Phillip Garrido, charged with kidnapping Jaycee Lee Dugard, told court he stalked girls at schools
 | publisher = New York Daily News
 | date = 2009-08-30
 | accessdate = 2009-10-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Garrido was convicted on March 9, 1977 and began serving a 50-year federal sentence on June 30, 1977, at [[United States Penitentiary, Leavenworth|Leavenworth Penitentiary]] in Kansas.

At Leavenworth, Garrido met Nancy Bocanegra, who was visiting another prisoner, her uncle. On October 5, 1981, Garrido and Bocanegra were married at Leavenworth. On January 22, 1988, Garrido was released from Leavenworth to Nevada State Prison, where he had served seven months of a five-years-to-life Nevada sentence. He was transferred to federal parole authorities in Antioch on August 26, 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;ktvn-NDPS&quot;/&gt; In Antioch, the Garridos lived in the home of his elderly mother, who suffered from [[dementia]]. As a parolee, he was monitored, later wore a [[GPS]]-enabled ankle bracelet, and was regularly visited by police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/us_and_americas/article6815569.ece
 | author = Harvey, Mike
 | title = Jaycee police question kidnapper over prostitute murders
 | publisher = The Times
 | date=2009-08-31
 | accessdate=2009-09-02
| location=London
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Abduction and search effort==
In September 1990, Jaycee Dugard and her family moved from the [[Orange County, California|Orange County]] city of [[Garden Grove, California|Garden Grove]] to South Lake Tahoe. At the time of the abduction, Dugard was in fifth grade attending Meyers Elementary School near South Lake Tahoe.{{fact|date=August 2011}}

On June 10, 1991 Dugard's stepfather, Carl Probyn, witnessed the abduction from within sight of their home. He saw two people in a gray sedan (possibly a [[Mercury Monarch]] or [[Mercury Zephyr]]) make a U-turn at the school bus stop where Dugard was waiting, and a woman forced Dugard into the car.  (In a ''[[Primetime (TV series)|Primetime]]'' interview on July 10, 2011, Dugard stated a stun-gun was used to incapacitate her). Probyn then gave chase on a bicycle, but he was unable to overtake the vehicle. Some of Dugard's classmates were also witnesses to the abduction. Initial suspects included Probyn and Ken Slayton, Dugard's biological father. Probyn took and passed several [[polygraph]] tests, and Slayton was also quickly cleared of suspicion.{{fact|date=August 2011}}

Within hours of Dugard's disappearance, local and national media converged upon South Lake Tahoe to cover the story. Within days, dozens of local volunteers assisted in the search effort, which involved nearly every resource within the community. Within weeks, tens of thousands of fliers and posters were mailed to businesses throughout the United States. Since Dugard's favorite color was pink, the entire town was blanketed in pink ribbons as a constant reminder of her disappearance and a demonstrated support for the family throughout the community.{{fact|date=August 2011}}

Dugard's mother, Terry Probyn, founded a group called Jaycee's Hope, which directed the volunteer and fundraising effort. Cassette tapes of the song ''Jaycee Lee'' along with T-shirts, sweatshirts and buttons were sold to raise money for poster materials, postage, printing and related expenses. Child Quest International and The National Center for Missing and Exploited Children were also involved in the effort. A reward was offered, which was displayed on the posters and fliers. The kidnapping case also attracted nationwide attention and was featured many times on the television show ''[[America's Most Wanted]]''.{{fact|date=August 2011}}

The ensuing months and years were a continuous effort of child safety awareness, fundraising events and candlelight vigils marking Dugard's disappearance and keeping her story before the public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,543640,00.html
|title = Police: California Girl Kidnapped 18 Years Ago Kept as Sex Slave in Couple's Backyard | publisher = FOX News | date = 2009-08-27
|accessdate=2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/12/opinion/12sat2.html | title = The Problem of Sex Offenders | publisher = The New York Times | date = 2009-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/6101545/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-walks-into-police-station-18-years-after-disappearance.html | title = Jaycee Lee Dugard walks into police station 18 years after disappearance | publisher = The Telegraph | date = 2009-08-27 | author = Moore, Matthew| location=London
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.kcra.com/news/20798097/detail.html | title = Dugard's Biological Dad Rips Garridos | date = 2009-09-08 | publisher = [[KCRA-TV]] | accessdate = 2009-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kidnapping site:{{Coord|38|53|08|N|119|59|12|W|type:landmark|display=inline}} Washoan Blvd near Nadowa Street, South Lake Tahoe, CA 96150&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Location of Garrido house: {{Coord|38|0|31|N|121|46|15|W|type:landmark|display=inline}} 1554 Walnut Avenue, Antioch, CA 94509-7223&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.charleyproject.org/cases/d/dugard_jaycee.html | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080116084746/http://www.charleyproject.org/cases/d/dugard_jaycee.html | archivedate = 2008-01-16 | title = Charley project website: Profiles the disappearance of Jaycee Lee Dugard, missing since June 10, 1991 from South Lake Tahoe, California}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Captivity ==
The Garridos' home on Walnut Avenue is in an [[unincorporated area]] in northeast [[Antioch, California|Antioch]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LAtimes2&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://articles.latimes.com/2009/aug/31/local/me-kidnapped31 | author = La Ganga, Maria L., Dolan, Maura, and Hennessy-Fiske, Molly
|title = Sex offenders move to Antioch area 'because they can' | publisher = Los Angeles Times | date = 2009-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; A neighbor of the Garridos said he recalls, as a child, meeting Dugard through a fence in the Garridos' yard soon after the kidnapping. He said that she had identified herself by the name &quot;Jaycee&quot; and that's when he asked her if she lived there or was just visiting, she answered that she lived there. At that point Phillip Garrido came out and took her back indoors. The Garridos later built a privacy fence around the property, which already had several large trees in the yard.&lt;ref name='CostaContraTimes'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.contracostatimes.com/jayceedugard/ci_13223494
|author = Costa, Hilary | title = Neighbor spoke to Jaycee Lee Dugard through fence | publisher = Contra Costa Times | date = 2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From April to August 1993, Phillip Garrido was returned to [[federal prison]] for parole violation.

Jaycee Lee Dugard bore two daughters by Phillip Garrido, born in August 1994 and in November 1997.&lt;ref name='kcra birth'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.kcra.com/news/22351413/detail.html | author = | title = Judge Issues Birth Certificates For Dugard's Kids | publisher = KCRA.com
 | date = 2010-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; During their time together as a family, Dugard presented herself to everyone as the daughter of the Garridos and described the younger girls as her little sisters. Her two daughters also told others she was their older sister.&lt;ref name='telegraph'&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/jaycee-lee-dugard/6127898/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-daughters-thought-she-was-their-sister.html
 | author = Allen, Nick | title = Jaycee Lee Dugard: daughters thought she was their sister | publisher = [[Daily Telegraph]] | date = 2009-09-02
| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most U.S. media sources have declined to name the children, although names have been given in foreign media coverage of the case.&lt;ref name='telegraph2'&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/jaycee-lee-dugard/6135477/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-new-photos-released.html | author = Allen, Nick | title = Jaycee Lee Dugard: new photos released | publisher = [[Daily Telegraph]] | date = 2009-09-03| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Garrido operated a print shop, where Dugard acted as the graphics artist. Ben Daughdrill, a customer of Garrido's printing business, claimed he met and spoke by telephone with Dugard and that she did excellent work. During this time, Dugard had access to the business phone and an email account. One customer of the printing business indicated she never hinted to him about her childhood abduction or true identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/29/us/29abduct.html | title = Kidnapping Victim Was Not Always Locked Away | publisher = The New York Times | date = 2009-08-28 | accessdate = 2009-09-01 | author = McKinley, Jessie}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While in Antioch, Garrido also kept a [[blog]] associated with what he called &quot;Gods Desire Church.&quot; In the blog Garrido said he had the power to control sound with his mind. Garrido asked several people, including customers, to sign testimonials confirming that they witnessed his ability to &quot;control sound with my mind&quot; and a device he developed &quot;for others to witness this phenomena.&quot;&lt;ref name=merc_28_1&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/ci_13231478 | author = Simerman, John | title = Accused abductor of Jaycee Dugard turned increasingly zealous, customers say | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News | date = 2009-08-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://voicesrevealed.blogspot.com/
 | title = Phillip Craig Garrido's blog}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Law enforcement officers believe that at the time they became involved in 2009, Dugard's living quarters were in a secondary backyard behind Phillip Garrido's house. The private area of the yard included sheds (one of which was [[soundproof]]ed and used as a recording studio in which Garrido recorded himself singing religious-themed and romantic country songs), two tents, and what has been described as a camping-style shower and toilet. The area was surrounded by tall trees and a {{Convert|6|ft|m|adj=on}} high fence. An entrance to the secondary backyard was covered by a [[tarpaulin]]. Privacy in the yard was enhanced by tents and outbuildings, as well as an old car similar to the one used in the abduction. Law enforcement officers visited the residence at least twice in recent years, but did not give the backyard more than a quick inspection. When police investigated, they found the backyard to be crowded with typical childhood possessions, including books and toys, among the tents and sheds. Electricity was supplied by extension cords. Jaycee Dugard was seen in the house and sometimes answered the front door. While the family kept to themselves, the girls were sometimes seen playing in the backyard or as passengers in Garrido's car. Garrido claims to have home-schooled the two girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/ci_13237170 | author = de Sá, Karen | title = Cops search two Antioch homes for evidence in the Jaycee Dugard case | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News | date = 2009-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dugard's aunt, Tina Dugard, and a former business associate of the Garridos, Cheyvonne Molino, have commented that Dugard's children looked healthy. Tina Dugard said that upon her meeting them after their reappearance, they &quot;always appeared and behaved like normal kids&quot;. Molino said of the times she met them while they were captive &quot;that in her presence the girls never acted robotically&quot; and didn't wear unusual clothing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.ocregister.com/news/jaycee-143194-dugard-tina.html |author=Hardesty, Greg | title = Exclusive video: Interview with Jaycee's aunt | publisher = Orange County Register | date = 2009-09-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cbsnews.com/blogs/2009/09/01/crimesider/entry5279423.shtml | author = Smith, Ryan | title = Controversy: Jaycee Dugard Daughter's Photos | work = Crimesider
 | publisher=CBS News | date = 2009-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Missed opportunities to rescue Dugard===

* Police failed to make the connection that Jaycee Lee Dugard was kidnapped in South Lake Tahoe, the same location as Garrido's 1976 kidnapping of Katherine Callaway Hall.

* On April 22, 1992, less than a year after her kidnapping, a male caller contacted the Contra Costa County Sheriff's Department from a gas station in [[Oakley, California]], less than two miles from the Garridos' home in Antioch.  The caller reported that he saw Dugard in the gas station staring intently at a missing child poster of herself. The caller then reported seeing her leave in a large yellow van, possibly a Dodge.  In 2009, after Dugard's release, an old yellow Dodge van was recovered from the Garrido property, one that matched the description of the van given in the call. The license plate was not reported in the 1992 call and the caller, the girl, and the van were gone by the time police arrived. The caller never identified himself, and the police did not pursue the matter any further.&lt;ref name='SFChronicle'&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/10/05/MNS11A1JEG.DTL | author = Bulwa, Demian | title = 92 tipster told of girl like Dugard in Oakley | publisher=San Francisco Chronicle | date=2009-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jaycee Dugard reported that she never left the Garrido property from the day she was kidnapped until shortly before her first child was born in August 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Dugard|first=Jaycee|title=A Stolen Life|pages=101–106|year=2011|publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster|isbn=978-1-4516-2918-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

* In June 2002, the fire department responded to a report of a juvenile with a shoulder injury that occurred in a swimming pool at Garrido's home. This information was not relayed to the parole office, which had no record of either a juvenile or a swimming pool at Garrido's address.&lt;ref name=&quot;report&quot; /&gt;

* In 2006, one of Garrido's neighbors called [[9-1-1]] to inform them there were tents in the backyard with children living there and that Garrido was &quot;[[psychosis|psychotic]]&quot; with [[sexual addiction]]s. A deputy sheriff spoke with Garrido at the front of the house for about 30 minutes and left after telling him there would be a code violation if people were living outside on the property. After Dugard was found in August 2009, the local police issued an apology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/missing-girl-could-have-been-found-in-2006-1778997.html | author = Adams, Guy | title = Missing girl could have been found in 2006 | publisher=The Independent | date=2009-08-29
| location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;abc_bringing&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=8431843 | author = Netter, Sarah and Ghebremedhin, Sabina | title = Cops Apologize for Muffing Chance to Rescue Jaycee Dugard in 2006 | publisher=ABC News | date = 2009-08-28
 | accessdate=2009-08-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* On November 4, 2009, the California Office of the Inspector General issued a report&lt;ref name=&quot;report&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.oig.ca.gov/media/reports/BAI/reports/Special%20Report%20on%20CDCR's%20Supervision%20of%20Parolee%20Phillip%20Garrido.pdf | title = Special Report: The California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation's Supervision of Parolee Phillip Garrido | publisher=California Office of the Inspector General | date = 2009-11-04 | accessdate = 2009-11-04}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; which enumerated various lapses by the [[California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation]] that contributed to Dugard's continued captivity. The central finding was that Garrido was incorrectly classified as needing only low-level supervision and all other lapses were derived from it. In his report, the inspector general detailed an instance in which a parole agent encountered a 12-year-old girl at the home of Phillip Garrido, but accepted Garrido's &quot;explanation that she was his brother's daughter and [the agent] did nothing to verify it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-jaycee-dugard5-2009nov05,0,1237255.story | title = State prison watchdog strongly criticizes procedures in Jaycee Dugard case
 | publisher = Los Angeles Times | date = 2009-11-04 | first = Michael | last = Rothfeld}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reappearance==
{{Infobox person|name        = &lt;div style=&quot;background-color:lightsteelblue&quot;&gt;&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Jaycee Dugard&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
|caption     = &lt;small&gt;A photograph of Dugard posted on the [[FBI]]'s website&lt;/small&gt;
|nationality = [[United States|American]]
|home_town   = [[South Lake Tahoe, California]]
|birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|1980|05|03}}
|birth_name  = Jaycee Lee Dugard
|birth_place = [[Anaheim, California]]
|children = Daughter, (b Aug 1994)&lt;br /&gt;Daughter, (b Nov 1997)
}}

On August 24, 2009, Garrido visited the [[San Francisco]] office of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] (FBI) and left a four-page essay containing his ideas about religion and sexuality, suggesting he had discovered a solution to problem behaviors like his own past crimes. The essay described how he had cured his own criminal sexual behaviors and how that information could be used to assist in curing other [[sexual predator]]s by &quot;controlling human impulses that drive humans to commit dysfunctional acts.&quot; On the same day, Phillip Garrido went to a [[University of California, Berkeley]] [[University of California Police Department|police office]] seeking permission to hold a special Christian event on campus as a part of his &quot;God's Desire&quot; program. He spoke with U.C. Berkeley special events manager Lisa Campbell. She perceived his behavior as odd and asked him to make an appointment for the next day, which he did, leaving his name in the process. The next morning, August 25, Campbell notified campus police officer Ally Jacobs about the meeting later that morning with Garrido, and her concerns. Jacobs ran a background check, learned that Garrido was on parole for [[rape]], and decided to sit in on the meeting. Garrido arrived with two girls, whom he introduced as his daughters. At the meeting, Jacobs felt that the girls' behavior was unusual, and phoned the parole office to relay her concerns. As no one was in, she left a report of the meeting on voicemail.&lt;ref name=&quot;report&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://abcnews.go.com/US/Weekend/story?id=8447788
 | author = Von Fremd, Mike, Snow, Kate, and Splane, Stephen
 | title = Dugard Kidnapping Suspect Told FBI He'd Cured Himself
 | publisher = ABC News
 | date = 2009-08-30
 | accessdate=2009-08-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nypostfiend&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.nypost.com/p/news/national/item_LQyPZo4M9gGGguABUawNDL
 | author = Alpert, Lukas I.
 | title = Fiend Gave the FBI his Perv-Cure Manifesto
 | publisher = New York Post
 | date = 2009-08-30
 |accessdate=2009-08-30
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After hearing Jacobs' recorded message, two parole agents drove to Garrido's house later that day. Upon arrival, they handcuffed him and searched the house, only finding his wife Nancy and his elderly mother at home. Then the parole agents drove Garrido back to the parole office.
En route, Garrido said that the two girls who had accompanied him to UC Berkeley &quot;were the daughters of a relative, and he had permission from their parents to take them to the university.&quot; Although the parole office had barred Garrido from being around minors a month before, the agents overlooked this violation. After reviewing his file with a supervisor, they drove him home and ordered him to report back to the office again the next day to further discuss his visit to UC Berkeley and follow up on their concerns about the two girls.&lt;ref name=&quot;report&quot; /&gt;

Garrido arrived at the parole office in [[Concord, California|Concord]] on August 26 with his wife, Nancy, the two girls and Jaycee Lee Dugard, who was introduced as &quot;Allissa&quot;. When they arrived, his parole officer was on the phone with Jacobs to obtain a more detailed description of her interaction with Garrido and the two girls. Jacobs informed the officer that the girls were calling Garrido &quot;Daddy,&quot; but the parole officer believed that Garrido had no children. The parole officer then decided to separate Garrido from the women and girls to obtain an identification.

Dugard, maintaining her false identity as &quot;Allissa&quot;, stated that she was the girls' mother. When the parole officer said that she looked too young to be the mother and asked her age, &quot;Alyssa (''sic'') said that she was 29 years old, laughingly explaining that she often gets that comment and that people believe she is the girls' sister,&quot; the report states. As the questioning continued, Dugard and Nancy Garrido became agitated and wanted to know why they were being questioned. When the parole officer explained that he was investigating Garrido's visit to the UC campus with the two girls, Dugard said that she knew Garrido had taken the girls to the campus and that she also knew he was a paroled sex offender who had kidnapped and raped a woman. &quot;She added that Garrido was a changed man and a great person who was good to her kids. Allissa subsequently stated that she didn't want to provide any additional information and that she might need a lawyer.&quot;

It was later suggested that Dugard was beginning to show signature signs of [[Stockholm syndrome]] during her questioning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/jaycee-lee-dugard/6509828/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-showed-signs-of-Stockholm-syndrome.html
 | author = Nick Allen
 | title = Jaycee Lee Dugard showed signs of Stockholm syndrome
 | publisher = The Telegraph
 | date = 2009-10-05
 | accessdate=2011-05-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The parole agent then asked Garrido in another room to explain the relationship between him and &quot;Allissa&quot; and the two girls. Garrido said that all three were his nieces, the daughters of his brother in [[Oakley, California|Oakley]]. &quot;Garrido stated that the parents were divorced, the girls were living with them and other people, and he did not know his brother's address or phone number,&quot; the report states. The parole officer returned to the women and insisted on seeing identification from &quot;Allissa,&quot; but Dugard replied that she &quot;had learned a long time ago not to carry or give any personal information to anyone.&quot; She also said she needed a lawyer. At this point, the parole officer called in [[Concord, California|Concord]] police.

The report continues: &quot;As they waited for the officer to arrive, Alyssa (''sic'') said she was sorry that she had lied. She explained that she was from Minnesota and had been hiding for five years from an abusive husband. She was terrified of being found, she said, and that was the reason she could not give the parole agent any information.&quot; Two Concord police officers continued the questioning of Dugard, who maintained her false identity and the story she had told to the parole agent. In the other room, a Concord police sergeant questioned Garrido, who finally admitted that he was the father of the two girls. When the parole agent resumed his questioning of Garrido, the latter admitted to kidnapping and raping &quot;Allissa&quot;. Under further questioning, Dugard revealed her true identity and confirmed that she had been kidnapped and raped by Garrido.

Garrido and his wife were then placed under arrest. An [[FBI]] [[Special agent]] put Dugard on the telephone with her mother, Terry Probyn. Dugard retained custody of her children and was soon reunited with her mother.&lt;ref name=&quot;cop&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.abcnews.go.com/Nightline/story?id=8437707
 | author = Ghadishah, Arash
 | title = EXCLUSIVE: Meet Cop Who Helped Nail Alleged Dugard Kidnapper
 | publisher = ABC News
 | date = 2009-08-28
 | accessdate = 2009-08-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AP_Girl_held&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://apnews.myway.com/article/20090828/D9AC06JO0.html
 | author = Williams, Juliet, and Young, Samantha
 | title = Stepdad: Girl held 18 years enjoys 'happy' reunion
 | publisher = Associated Press
 | date = 2009-08-28
 | accessdate = 2009-08-28
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/8228180.stm
 | title = Police 'sorry' for kidnap blunder
 | publisher = BBC News
 | date = 2009-08-29
 | accessdate = 2009-09-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
===Reunion and afterward===
[[File:A Stolen Life by Jaycee Dugard.jpg|150px|thumb|right|Dugard's memoir, ''A&amp;nbsp;Stolen&amp;nbsp;Life'']]
In the days following Dugard's return, Carl Probyn, her stepfather, confirmed that she and her daughters were in good health and intelligent, their reunion was going well, and they were proceeding slowly. He said his stepdaughter had developed a significant emotional bond with Phillip Garrido, and the girls cried when they learned of their father's arrest. According to Jaycee Dugard's aunt, Tina Dugard, about the two girls: &quot;They are clever, articulate, curious girls who have a bright future ahead of them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2009/08/31/earlyshow/main5276887.shtml
 | title = Jaycee's Stepdad: Her New Life &quot;Like Mars&quot;
 | publisher = CBS News
 | date = 2009-08-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/Jaycee-Dugard-And-Children-Cried-When-Phillip-Garrido-Was-Arrested-Says-Ms-Dugards-Stepfather/Article/200908415371513
 | author = Milam, Greg
 | title = Jaycee and Kids 'Cried At Kidnapper's Arrest'
 | publisher = Sky News
 | date=2009-09-01
 | accessdate = 2009-10-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/09/03/california.missing.girl/index.html
 | title = Jaycee Dugard's aunt: 'This is a joyful time'
 | publisher = CNN
 | date = 2009-09-03
 | accessdate = 2009-10-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ernie Allen, president of the [[National Center for Missing and Exploited Children]], said Dugard's reappearance is an important event for families of other long-term missing children, because it shows that there is hope even in long-term cases. [[Elizabeth Smart (activist)|Elizabeth Smart]] has stressed the importance of focusing on the future with a positive attitude as an effective approach to accepting what has happened. [[Shawn Hornbeck]] also commented on the case.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNGandossy&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/08/27/california.missing.girl/
 | title = Sheriff: Kidnap victim, children kept in backyard compound
 | author = Gandossy, Taylor, Watkins, Tom, and Wilson, Stan
 | date = 2009-08-28
 | publisher = CNN
 | accessdate = 2009-09-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/news/ci_13226665
 | author = Kaplan, Tracey
 | title = Challenges ahead for Jaycee Dugard's recovery from long ordeal
 | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News
 | date = 2009-08-28
 | accessdate = 2009-09-25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20301153,00.html
 | author = Oh, Eunice
 | title = Elizabeth Smart's Advice to Jaycee Dugard: Move Forward in Life
 | publisher = People
 | date= 2009-08-28
 | accessdate = 2009-11-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.people.com/people/article/0,,20302413,00.html
 | author = Dodd, Johnny
 | title = Shawn Hornbeck: Jaycee Dugard Brainwashed, in Shock
 | publisher = People
 | date = 2009-09-04
 | accessdate = 2009-10-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Three weeks after her release, Jaycee Dugard made a request to gain control of the pets that were raised in the home where she was held captive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/unleashed/2009/09/jaycee-dugard-animals-labrador-rottweiler-pigeon-mouse.html
 | date = 2009-09-18
 | title = Animal control officials hope to reunite kidnap victim Jaycee Lee Dugard with her 12 pets
 | publisher = Los Angeles Times
 | accessdate = 2009-09-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 14, 2009, ''[[People (magazine)|People]]'' published on its cover the first verified photo of Jaycee Dugard as an adult. Her mother, Terry Probyn, was reported in 2009 to have planned with [[Broadway Books]] to publish a book, originally set for release in 2010, detailing the girls' decades-long absence and return.&lt;ref&gt;''People''(October 26, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;  Dugard's memoir, ''A Stolen Life'', was published on July 12, 2011 by [[Simon &amp; Schuster]].

===Police investigations===
Following the arrest, police extensively searched the Garrido house for evidence of other crimes. Because Phillip Garrido had access to his neighbor's house, it was also searched for evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/jaycee-lee-dugard/6116417/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-Death-dogs-search-Philip-Garridos-home-for-missing-girls.html
 | author = Allen, Nick
 | title = Jaycee Lee Dugard: 'Death dogs' search Phillip Garrido's home for missing girls
 | publisher = The Telegraph
 | date = 2009-08-31
 | accessdate = 2009-09-01
| location=London
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://abcnews.go.com/US/story?id=8451296
 | author = Netter, Sarah, Von Fremd, Mike, Waldman, Ronna, and Nalty, Ariane
 | title = Garrido Investigators Unearth Bone Fragments
 | publisher = ABC News
 | date = 2009-08-31
 | accessdate = 2009-09-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police also searched the homes and business of one of Phillip Garrido's printing business clients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.cbsnews.com/blogs/2009/09/10/crimesider/entry5300871.shtml
 | author = Katz, Neil
 | title = Jaycee Dugard Investigation Turns to Phillip Garrido's Associates
 | work = Crimesider
 | publisher = CBS News
 | date = 2009-09-10
 | accessdate = 2009-09-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between September 15, 2009, and September 22, 2009, police agencies from [[Hayward, California]], and [[Dublin, California]], conducted searches of the Garridos' property investigating missing girls from those communities. The results of the search turned up no clues to the disappearances of the girls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/breaking-news/ci_13340993
 | author = Kurhi,Eric
 | title = Hayward, Dublin police searching Garrido property for clues this morning
 | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News
 | date = 2009-09-15
 | accessdate = 2009-09-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2011 Hayward police announced that Garrido has not been eliminated as a suspect and is still a person of interest in the case of [[Michaela Garecht]].&lt;ref name='FOX40'&gt;{{cite web 
| url = http://www.fox40.com/news/headlines/ktxl-phillip-garrido-may-have-more-victims-20110713,0,5828068.story
 | author = Cox, Terri 
 | title = Phillip Garrido May Have More Victims
 | publisher = Fox 40
 | date = 2011-07-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Garrido's statements ===
On August 27, 2009, [[KCRA|KCRA-TV]] in [[Sacramento, California]], interviewed Garrido in his jail cell by telephone. During the interview Garrido said, &quot;In the end, this is going to be a powerful, heartwarming story&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;kcra&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 | url = http://www.kcra.com/news/20591281/detail.html
 | title = Kidnap Suspect: 'Wait Until You Hear The Story'
 | publisher=KCRA-TV
 | date= 2009-08-27
 | accessdate = 2009-09-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; because, in his version of events:

{{cquote|My life has been straightened out. [...] Wait till you hear the story of what took place at this house. You're going to be absolutely impressed. It’s a disgusting thing that took place with me at the beginning, but I turned my life completely around.&lt;ref name=&quot;kcra&quot;&gt;
{{cite web|url= http://www.kcra.com/news/20591281/detail.html| title= Kidnap Suspect: 'Wait Until You Hear The Story'|publisher=KCRA-TV|date= 2009-08-27|accessdate= 2009-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:garritobackyard1.jpg|thumb|Investigators at the Antioch home]]
Garrido repeatedly told the reporter how he &quot;filed documents&quot; with the [[FBI]] on August 24, 2009, which, when they were published, would cause people to &quot;fall over backwards&quot; and that he could not reveal more because he &quot;had to protect law enforcement&quot; and &quot;what happened&quot; [...] was &quot;something that humans have not understood well.&quot; In the interview Garrido denied he had ever harmed Dugard's two daughters. He said their births changed his life and &quot;they slept in my arms every single night since birth. I never touched them.&quot; On August 28, 2009, FBI spokesman Joseph Schadler confirmed that Garrido had indeed left the documents with the agency, as he had claimed, but declined to discuss further details.&lt;ref name=&quot;kcra&quot; /&gt; The document, titled 'Origin of Schizophrenia Revealed', was eventually released by the FBI. The document is about stopping [[Schizophrenia|schizophrenics]] from turning violent and controlling sounds with the human mind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.scribd.com/doc/19208889/Garrido-Spiritual-Manifesto
 | title = Garrido Spiritual Manifesto
 | accessdate = 2011-05-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Legal proceedings===
On August 28, 2009, Garrido and his wife pleaded not guilty to charges including kidnapping, rape and [[false imprisonment]]. A bail review/pre-preliminary hearing was held September 14, 2009, at the El Dorado County Superior Court in [[Placerville, California]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://garrido.eldoradocourt.org/|title=People of the State of California v. Phillip Garrido and Nancy Garrido
 | publisher = Superior Court of California, County of El Dorado
 | date = 2009-09-08
 | accessdate = 2009-09-13
}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the hearing, Superior Court Judge Douglas Phimister set bail for Phillip Garrido at $30 million. However, there is a no-bail parole hold on Garrido. The judge kept Nancy Garrido in custody on a no-bail hold. Nancy Garrido could request bail at a later date.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2009/09/garrido-court-hearing.html
 | author = La Ganga, Maria L.
 | title = Phillip Garrido's bail set at $30 million, will undergo psychiatric testing
 | publisher = Los Angeles Times
 | date = 2009-09-14
 | accessdate = 2009-09-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://edition.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/09/14/garrido.court/
 | author=Simon, Dan
 | title = Suspects in Jaycee Dugard kidnapping appear in court
 | publisher = CNN
 | date = 2009-09-14
 | accessdate = 2009-09-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.mercurynews.com/topstories/ci_13333365
 | author = Simerman, John, and Salonga, Robert
 | title = Phillip Garrido bail set at $30 million
 | publisher = Silicon Valley Mercury News
 | date = 2009-09-14
 | accessdate = 2009-09-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/Jaycee-Lee-Dugard-Secret-Garden-Compound-Where-Kidnapped-Girl-Lived-With-Daughters/Article/200908415370911
 | title = Scemata of compound
 | publisher = SkyNews
 | date = 2009-09-05
 | accessdate = 2009-10-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://media.sacbee.com/smedia/2009/08/28/12/Dugard.source.prod_affiliate.4.pdf
 | title = Criminal complaints against Garridos
 | date = 2009-08-28
 | publisher = sacbee.com
 | accessdate = 2009-09-13}} Also available [http://www.rgj.com/assets/pdf/J7141529828.PDF here]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://garrido.eldoradocourt.org/documents.html
 | title = El Dorado County Superior Court documents
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.oig.ca.gov/media/reports/BAI/reports/Special%20Report%20on%20CDCR's%20Supervision%20of%20Parolee%20Phillip%20Garrido.pdf
 | title = Office of the Inspector General Special Report
 | publisher = oig.ca.gov
 | accessdate = 2009-11-01
}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the September 14 hearing, Phimister also granted a request from Phillip Garrido's attorney to have a psychologist or psychiatrist appointed to conduct a confidential evaluation of Garrido. This examination is to be used by the defense to assist in case preparation. Additional mental health examinations could be ordered at subsequent phases in the proceedings.&lt;ref name=&quot;everydaypsychology&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://everydaypsychology.com/2009/09/will-forensic-psychologists-be-involved.html
 | title = Will Forensic Psychologists be involved in the Phillip Garrido case?
 | publisher = everydaypsychology.com
 | date = 2009-09-05
 | accessdate = 2009-09-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 29, 2009, a short hearing was held to set a date for the next pre-preliminary hearing when issues such as [[discovery (law)|discovery]] were to be discussed. This hearing occurred on December 11, 2009. Katie Callaway Hall, whom Phillip Garrido raped in 1976, appeared in the courtroom in both the October and December hearings. She did not speak in either proceeding.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url = http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/10/29/california.kidnapping/
 | title = Garridos in court for hearing as 1976 rape victim watches
 | publisher = CNN
 | date = 2009-10-30
 | accessdate = 2009-10-31
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='KCRA_12_11_2009_Hearing'&gt;{{cite web |
url = http://www.kcra.com/news/21929319/detail.html |
title = Garridos Have Brief Court Appearance |
publisher = KCRA Sacramento |
date = 2009-12-11 |
accessdate = 2009-12-26
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 5, 2009, Phimister ordered Nancy Garrido's defense attorney, Gilbert Maines, to be removed from the case. According to a posting on the court's website,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://garrido.eldoradocourt.org/docs/nancy/20091105-MinOrd-ConfEvid.pdf
 | title = Minute Order
 | publisher = Superior Court of California, El Dorado County
 | date = 2009-11-09
 | accessdate = 2009-11-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the decision occurred in review of &quot;confidential evidence&quot; that has not been disclosed to the public, and details of the proceedings were kept sealed. The decision was immediately stayed until November 30, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.ktvu.com/news/21566929/detail.html
 | title = Nancy Garrido's Attorney Removed From Kidnap Case
 | publisher = KTVU
 | date = 2009-11-09
 | accessdate = 2009-11-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 12, 2009, Phimister appointed Stephen A. Tapson as interim counsel for Nancy Garrido.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://garrido.eldoradocourt.org/docs/nancy/20091112-ExParteMinOrd-IntCounselAppt.pdf
 | title = Ex Parte Minute Order
 | publisher = Superior Court of California, El Dorado County
 | date = 2009-11-12
 | accessdate = 2009-11-12
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Gilbert Maines appealed the decision and was given a favorable ruling by the California Third District Court of Appeal on December 15, 2009.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |
url = http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2009/12/15/BA6H1B4SIN.DTL&amp;tsp=1 |
title = Court: Nancy Garrido's lawyer wrongly bounced |
publisher = San Francisco Chronicler |
date = 2009-12-16 |
accessdate = 2009-12-24
| first=Bob
| last=Egelko
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On December 22, 2009, the same court gave the Eldorado Superior Court until January 2010 to respond to the ruling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.sacbee.com/eldorado/story/2416182.html | title = Clash over Nancy Garrido's attorney remains unsettled | publisher = Sacramento Bee | date = 2009-12-23 | accessdate = 2009-12-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Both Gilbert Maines and Stephen Tapson appeared at the discovery hearing on December 11, 2009.&lt;ref name='KCRA_12_11_2009_Hearing' /&gt; A hearing was held on January 21, 2010. At that hearing, Maines was removed from the case and Tapson was appointed defense counsel for Nancy Garrido. In addition, bail in the amount of $20 million was set for Nancy Garrido.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.sacbee.com/latest/story/2480112.html|title=Judge names new lawyer for Nancy Garrido, sets bail at $20 million|author=Stanton, Sam|publisher=Sacramento Bee|date=2010-01-21|accessdate=2010-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mr. and Mrs. Garrido both made a 'full confession' in the case, said Tapson at a press conference on February 28, 2011. The development came as lawyers for both sides have re-opened discussions on a possible plea deal that may obviate the need for a trial. Mrs. Garrido's attorney acknowledged that she was facing &quot;241 years, eight months to life&quot; and that he was working for a reduced sentence in the 30 year range. He stated that the prosecutor had acknowledged that Mr. Garrido was a master-manipulator and that Mrs. Garrido was under both his influence and that of substances during the period of Dugard's kidnapping so should receive some consideration while alluding to parallels with [[Patty Hearst]] and [[Stockholm Syndrome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ktvu.com/news/27029177/detail.html?cxntlid=cmg_cntnt_rss|title=Garridos Confess To Dugard Kidnapping|author=not stated|publisher=KTVU TV|date=2011-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On Thursday, April 7, 2011, Phillip and Nancy Garrido, instead of pleading guilty (as had been expected based on their previous statements) pleaded not guilty to charges of kidnapping and raping Dugard, as well as other charges, in an amended indictment. Phillip Garrido's attorney, public defender Susan Gellman, alleged that the grand jury might have been improperly selected and might have acted improperly. Gellman did not elaborate on her claim in the courtroom but said outside that she had questions about the racial and geographic makeup of the grand jury that originally indicted the Garridos in September 2010. Judge Phimister noted that there were issues about the process itself before the grand jury, and also stated that the court would consider whether the grand jury acted appropriately. The developments were largely unforeseen by attorney Stephen Tapson, who represents Nancy Garrido; Tapson had said earlier that week that Phillip Garrido had made a deal with prosecutors to plead guilty and spend the rest of his life in prison. Gellman was upset with Tapson for telling reporters that her client had planned to plead guilty, saying that Tapson should only speak about his own client, Nancy Garrido. Tapson said he only found out about Gellman's plans late on Wednesday. Neither attorney would elaborate further on the specific concerns about the grand jury. El Dorado County, California District Attorney Vern Pierson did not think the complaints about the grand jury would ultimately derail his case against the Garridos.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

On April 28, 2011, the Garridos pleaded guilty to kidnapping and rape.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gorman |first=Steve |title=The California couple charged with abducting 11-year-old Jaycee Lee Dugard in 1991 and holding her captive for 18 years pleaded guilty on Thursday to kidnapping and sexual assault charges that carry life prison sentences. |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/04/28/us-kidnap-california-plea-idUSTRE73R6P720110428 |accessdate=April 28, 2011 |newspaper=Reuters |date=April 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The District Attorney also stated Nancy Garrido seemed to feel genuinely guilty, while it was said that Dugard was relieved that she and her children would not have to testify.

On June 2, 2011, Phillip Garrido was sentenced to 431 years; his wife received 36 years to life.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC News&quot;/&gt; Phillip Garrido is serving his sentence at [[California State Prison, Corcoran]] while Nancy Garrido is incarcerated at [[Valley State Prison for Women]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Salonga|first=Robert|title=Jaycee Dugard kidnappers now official state prison inmates|url=http://www.contracostatimes.com/ci_18293681|accessdate=9 September 2011|newspaper=Contra Costa Times|date=June 16, 2011|comment=the article reports Nancy Garrido as being sent to Central California Women's Facility (CSP-CCWF). However, the CDCR inmate locator reports she's at Valley State Prison for Women (CSP-VSPW)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation (CDCR) Inmate Locator|url=http://inmatelocator.cdcr.ca.gov/default.aspx|publisher=[[California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation]]|accessdate=9 September 2011|quote=Phillip Garrido is CDCR# AH9000 and Nancy Garrido is WE1452}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Dugard, who did not attend the sentencing, had sent a written statement that was read aloud in court :
{{quote|&quot;I chose not to be here today because I refuse to waste another second of my life in your presence. I've chosen to have my mom read this for me. Phillip Garrido, you are wrong. I could never say that to you before, but I have the freedom now and I am saying you are a liar and all of your so-called theories are wrong. Everything you have ever done to me has been wrong and someday I hope you can see that. What you and Nancy did was reprehensible. You always justified everything to suit yourself but the reality is and always has been that to make someone else suffer for your inability to control yourself and for you, Nancy, to facilitate his behavior and trick young girls for his pleasure is evil. There is no God in the universe that would condone your actions. To you, Phillip, I say that I have always been a thing for your own amusement. I hated every second of every day of 18 years because of you and the sexual perversion you forced on me. To you, Nancy, I have nothing to say. Both of you can save your apologies and empty words. For all the crimes you have both committed I hope you have as many sleepless nights as I did. Yes, as I think of all of those years I am angry because you stole my life and that of my family. Thankfully I am doing well now and no longer live in a nightmare. I have wonderful friends and family around me. Something you can never take from me again. You do not matter any more.&quot;
|Jaycee Lee Dugard|June 2, 2011}}

===Settlement with the State of California===
In July 2010, the State of California approved a $20 million dollar settlement with Jaycee Dugard, to compensate her for &quot;various lapses by the Corrections Department [which contributed to] Dugard's continued captivity, ongoing sexual assault and mental and/or physical abuse.&quot; The settlement, part of AB1714, was approved by the [[California State Assembly]] by a 70 to 2 vote, and by the [[California State Senate]] by a 30 to 1 vote. [[San Francisco County Superior Court]] Judge Daniel Weinstein, who mediated the settlement, stated that the settlement was reached to avoid a lawsuit which would be a &quot;greater invasion of privacy and greater publicity for the state.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jul/02/local/la-me-0702-dugard-settlement-20100702|title=Jaycee Lee Dugard's family will receive $20 million from California|publisher=Los Angeles Times|date=July 2, 2010|accessdate=July 11, 2011|author=Maria L. La Ganga|author2=Shane Goldmacher}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bill was signed by California Governor [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] on July 9.&lt;ref name=cnn20100701&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/CRIME/07/01/california.dugard/?hpt=T1 |title=California lawmakers approve $20 million to settle Dugard claims |work=CNN |date=2010-07-01 |accessdate=2010-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=AB1714&gt;California A.B. 1714, [http://www.leginfo.ca.gov/pub/09-10/bill/asm/ab_1701-1750/ab_1714_bill_20100709_chaptered.html as chaptered, as of July 9, 2010].&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lawsuit against the United States===
On September 22, 2011, Dugard filed suit in [[United States District Court for the Northern District of California]] accusing the United States of failing to monitor Garrido when he was a federal parolee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/09/23/us-crime-dugard-lawsuit-idUSTRE78M03G20110923|author=Emmet Berg|title=Jaycee Dugard sues U.S. over monitoring of her captor|publisher=Reuters|date=2011-09-22|accessdate=2011-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television Shows===
* An American crime show titled &quot;Wicked Attraction&quot; aired an episode about Phillip Garrido and Nancy Garrido. The episode also went into details of the events leading up to Jaycee Dugard's kidnapping and recovery.

* A British channel 4 documentary titled &quot;Captive for 18 years: Jaycee Lee&quot; focused on the story of Jaycee Lee's kidnap, recovery and the beginnings of trial including interviews with Jaycee's step-father. (http://www.channel4.com/programmes/captive-for-18-years-jaycee-lee/4od)

== See also==
* [[:Category:Children kept in captivity|Cases of children kept in captivity]]
* [[:Category:Kidnapped American children|Cases of kidnapped American children]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Jaycee Lee Dugard kidnapping}}
{{kml}}
*[http://www.contracostatimes.com/jaycee-dugard Jaycee Dugard Case] ongoing coverage by the [[Contra Costa Times]]
*[http://extras.mercurynews.com/slideshows/news/2009/08/jaycee_dugard_0828/ Photo slide show of Dugard case]
*[http://www.thejaycfoundation.org The JAYC Foundation Inc.]
*[http://www.scribd.com/doc/19208889/Garrido-Spiritual-Manifesto &quot;The Origin of Schizophrenia Revealed&quot;], the &quot;manifesto&quot; that Phillip Garrido sent to the FBI. 
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dugard, Jaycee Lee}}
[[Category:1991 crimes in the United States]]
[[Category:2009 crimes in the United States]]
[[Category:Crime in California]]
[[Category:Kidnappings|Jaycee Lee Dugard]]

[[ar:جايسي دوغارد]]
[[de:Entführung von Jaycee Lee Dugard]]
[[eo:Kidnapo de Jaycee Lee Dugard]]
[[fa:آدم‌ربایی جیسی دوگارد]]
[[fr:Enlèvement de Jaycee Lee Dugard]]
[[he:חטיפת ג'ייסי לי דוגארד]]
[[ja:ジェイシー・リー・デュガード誘拐事件]]
[[no:Jaycee Lee Dugard]]
[[ru:Похищение Джейси Ли Дьюгард]]
[[fi:Jaycee Lee Dugardin sieppaus]]
[[sv:Jaycee Lee Dugard]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
