<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2414106" ns="0" title="Microsoft BackOffice Server"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Microsoft BackOffice Small Business Server 4 0 CD case.jpg|thumb|right|Small Business Server in Microsoft's BackOffice product line]]
'''Microsoft BackOffice Server''' was a [[computer software]] package featuring [[Windows NT Server]] and other Microsoft [[Server (computing)|server]] products that ran on NT server. It was marketed during the 1990s and early 2000s for use in branch operations and for small businesses to run their [[back office]] operations. 
The small business edition of BackOffice Server was released for versions 4.0 and 4.5. In 2000 it was spun off from the &quot;BackOffice&quot; brand, becoming a variant of [[Windows Server]] branded as '''[[Windows Small Business Server]]'''. BackOffice Server itself was discontinued on October 1, 2001.

==Software Included==
Besides Windows NT Server, versions of BackOffice Server suite also included [[Microsoft SQL Server]], [[Microsoft SNA Server]], [[Microsoft Systems Management Server]] (SMS), [[Microsoft Mail]] Server or [[Microsoft Exchange Server]], [[Microsoft Proxy Server]] or [[Microsoft Internet Security and Acceleration Server|Microsoft Internet Security and Acceleration (ISA) Server]], and [[Internet Information Services]] (IIS). The &quot;Small Business&quot; editions omitted SNA Server and SMS.

==Versions==

* late 1994 — '''BackOffice 1.0'''
: includes [[Windows NT 3.5|Windows NT Server 3.5]], SQL Server 4.21a, SNA Server 2.1, SMS 1.0, and Mail Server 3.2.
* late 1995 — '''BackOffice 1.5'''
: includes [[Windows NT 3.51|Windows NT Server 3.51]], SQL Server 6.0, SNA Server 2.11, SMS 1.1, and Mail Server 3.5.
* April 25, 1996 — '''BackOffice 2.0'''
:includes Windows NT Server 3.51, IIS 1.0, SQL Server 6.0 or 6.5, SNA Server 2.11, SMS 1.1, and Exchange Server 4.0.
* December 1996 — '''BackOffice 2.5'''
:includes [[Windows NT 4.0|Windows NT Server 4.0]], IIS 2.0, SQL Server 6.5, SNA Server 3.0, SMS 1.2, Exchange Server 4.0, Proxy Server 1.0, [[Microsoft Index Server|Index Server]] 1.1, [[Internet Explorer]] 3.01, and [[Microsoft FrontPage|FrontPage]] 1.1
* December 9, 1997 — '''BackOffice Server 4.0'''
:includes Windows NT Server 4.0, IIS 3.0, SQL Server 6.5, SNA Server 4.0, SMS 1.2, Exchange Server 5.0, Proxy Server 2.0, Index Server 2.0, [[Microsoft Transaction Server|Transaction Server]] 2.0, Site Server 3.0, FrontPage 98, and [[Visual InterDev]] 1.0.
* January 12, 1999 — '''BackOffice Server 4.5'''
:includes Windows NT Server 4.0 SP4, IIS 4.0, SQL Server 7.0, SNA Server 4.0, SMS 2.0, Exchange Server 5.5, Proxy Server 2.0, Index Server 2.0, Transaction Server 2.0, Internet Explorer 5.0, FrontPage 2000, and Visual InterDev 6.0.
* February 28, 2001 — '''BackOffice Server 2000'''
:includes [[Windows 2000 Server]], SQL Server 2000, SMS 2.0, Exchange Server 2000, ISA Server 2000, and [[Microsoft Host Integration Server|Host Integration Server]] 2000.

==Requirements==
Backoffice server 4.5 with 1 server license and 5 clients access licenses (CAL) marketed for $675US.  It required 2 Gigabytes minimum hard drive space, a minimum processor type of [[Pentium Pro]] 200&amp;nbsp;MHz, and a minimum RAM size of 128 megabytes.

==See also==
*[[Windows Small Business Server]]

==External links==
*[http://www.microsoft.com/technet/archive/bosi/default.mspx Microsoft BackOffice Server] Archived documentation on Microsoft Technet

{{DEFAULTSORT:Microsoft Backoffice Server}}
[[Category:Discontinued Microsoft software|BackOffice Server]]
[[Category:Windows Server System|BackOffice Server]]

[[fr:Back office (logiciel)]]
[[pl:BackOffice]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
