<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2415701" ns="0" title="WERE"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|other uses|Were (disambiguation)}}
{{dablink|For the Cleveland area radio station which carried the WERE call letters from 1949&amp;ndash;2007, see [[WJMO]].}}
{{Infobox radio station
|name               = WERE 
|image              = [[File:WERE logo (low res).png]] 
|city               = [[Cleveland Heights, Ohio|Cleveland Heights]], [[Ohio]] 
|area               = [[Greater Cleveland]]
|branding           = {{nowrap|'''NewsTalk 1490'''}}
|slogan             = The People's Station
|frequency          = '''1490'''&amp;nbsp;([[Hertz|kHz]]) 
|airdate            = June 4, 2007&lt;br&gt;(as '''WERE''')&lt;br&gt;July 1, 1947&lt;br&gt;(as '''WJMO''')
|format             = [[All-news radio|News]]/[[Talk radio|Talk]]
|power              = 1,000 [[watt]]s
|class              = C
|facility_id        = 74472
|coordinates        = {{coord|41|30|48.00|N|81|36|5.00|W}}
|callsign_meaning   = '''W'''-&quot;[[Lake Erie|Lake '''ER'''i'''E''']]&quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;{{nowrap|carried over from [[WJMO#WERE_.281300_AM.29|WERE (1300&amp;nbsp;AM)]]}}&lt;/small&gt;
|former_callsigns   = 1947-2007: '''WJMO'''
|former_frequencies = 1947-1958: '''1540'''&amp;nbsp;([[Hertz|kHz]])
|affiliations       = [[Radio One (company)|Syndication One]]&lt;br&gt;[[USA Radio Network]]
|owner              = [[Radio One (company)|Radio One]] 
|licensee           = {{nowrap|Blue Chip Broadcasting Licenses, Ltd.}}
|sister_stations    = [[WENZ]], [[WJMO]], [[WZAK]]
|webcast            = [http://newstalkcleveland.com/?get-streaming-audio-player=1 Listen Live]
|website            = [http://www.newstalkcleveland.com NewsTalkCleveland.com]
}}

'''WERE''' (1490 [[AM broadcasting|AM]]) — branded '''NewsTalk 1490''' — is a commercial [[radio station]] licensed to [[Cleveland Heights, Ohio]] broadcasting a [[talk radio|news/talk]] format. The station is owned by [[Radio One (company)|Radio One]], and has studios at 2510 St. Clair Avenue, while the transmitter is along Euclid Avenue near East 118th Street, adjacent to the [[Case Western Reserve University]] campus. It uses the on-air slogan &quot;The People's Station,&quot; and is the Cleveland AM affiliate for ''[[The Tom Joyner Morning Show]]'' (shared with sister station [[WZAK]] FM 93.1), the Cleveland affiliate for ''[[Redding News Review]]'', and airs syndicated programming from station owner Radio One and [[USA Radio Network]].

==History==
===WJMO (1490 AM)===
{{Distinguish2|[[WJMO]] (1300 AM)}}
WJMO went on the air on June 1, 1947 licensed to Cleveland as a daytime-only broadcaster at 1540&amp;nbsp;kHz with studios at 2157 Euclid Avenue and a power of 1000 watts. The owner was Wentworth J. Marshall, formerly head of the Marshall Drug Co. chain, and the general manager was David M. Baylor. When it debuted, WJMO was the only Cleveland radio station without a network affiliation. As a result, the station specialized in recorded music. Early staff included Gene Carroll (mornings), Howie Lund (afternoons), and Billy Evans on sports.&lt;ref name=encyclopedia&gt;
{{cite encyclopedia
  | last = Van Tassel
  | first = David D., ed.
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors = John J. Grabowski, ed.
  | encyclopedia = The Encyclopedia of Cleveland History
  | title = WJMO
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | date = 1996
  | edition = 2nd ed.
  | location = Bloomington
  | pages = 1058–59
  | url = http://ech.case.edu/ech-cgi/article.pl?id=W23
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01
  | doi =
  | id = ISBN 0-253-33056-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1948 WJMO carried the football games of [[Case Western Reserve University|Western Reserve College]] Red Cats, both at home from League Park and on the road. In the first broadcast on September 25 Gil Gibbons called the action as Western Reserve met [[Western Michigan University|Western Michigan]] in [[Kalamazoo, Michigan|Kalamazoo]].&lt;ref name=archives&gt;
{{Cite web
  | last =
  | first =
  | authorlink =
  | coauthors =
  | title = WJMO History
  | work = Cleveland Broadcast Radio Archives Project
  | publisher =
  | date =
  | url = http://www.cleve-radio.com/index2.htm#WJMO-AM%20&amp;%20FM
  | format =
  | doi =
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 5, 1952, in an attempt to emphaze music rather than DJs, Baylor issued an orders to play four songs every 15 minutes.&lt;ref name=archives/&gt; As a result a number of DJs chose to leave the station. Later than year, Wentworth sold the station on August 20 for $100,000 to Maryland-based United Broadcasting, headed by Richard Eaton. Ownership was later put in the name of Eaton's affiliated company Friendly Broadcasting of Ohio.&lt;ref name=encyclopedia/&gt; WJMO also had a license for an FM sister station at 106.5&amp;nbsp;MHz, which was to sign on in 1959 with the WJMO-FM call letters.

On February 1, 1958, Friendly Broadcasting of Columbus assumed control of WSRS 1490-AM and 95.3-FM from Sam R. Sague, and switched call letters, licenses, studios and facilities, selling off their former frequencies to Tuschman Broadcasting Company. WJMO took over the former WSRS offices at 2156 Lee Road in Cleveland Heights, and WSRS-FM became WJMO-FM, later [[WXRK|WCUY]]. The 1540-AM facility became [[WABQ]] with the switch (whose format and call letters currently reside at 1460-AM) and the 106.5 facility ultimately signed on as WABQ-FM, and became WXEN in 1960. The 1540-AM frequency is currently [[WWGK]], while the 106.5 facility is now home to [[WMVX]].

Shortly after the frequency change in the early 1960s, WJMO moved to a black-oriented [[R&amp;B]] format. In 1970 a dispute arose over working conditions and the lack of blacks in key positions. Key station personnel staged a &quot;sick out,&quot; which took the station off the air. The dispute attracted the involvement of a number of groups, including the Cleveland chapter of the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference]].&lt;ref name=encyclopedia/&gt;

The [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference|SCLC]] asked sponsors to withhold advertising from WJMO or face a boycott by black community groups. In retaliation, the personnel involved in the &quot;sick out&quot; were fired. In the efforts to resolve matters, the fired personnel were reinstated, and Kennard &quot;Ken&quot; Hawkins was appointed the station's general manager. Hawkins became the first African American to hold that position at a Cleveland radio station.&lt;ref name=archives/&gt;

United Broadcasting ran into problems with the FCC regarding the operation of its stations in Washington and Miami. It was also alleged that Eaton bribed the ABC network to gain favorable terms for three of its stations.

Meanwhile in Cleveland, United Broadcasting had other problems. On December 11, 1973, station vice president Van Lane (real name Morris Schecter) and engineer John Rees of Washington's [[WTEM|WRC radio]] pled guilty in federal court to charges of bugging Hawkins' office. It was later revealed that the lines were linked between Hawkins' office at the station and Lane's home in Shaker Heights. Lane and Rees were fined $500 each. Former United Broadcasting controller and VP Morton Silverman of Columbia, Maryland, was also charged with three felony counts of illegal wiretapping, but the Justice Department agreed to reduce the charges to a misdemeanor.&lt;ref name=archives/&gt;

A year later, on December 2, 1974, Washington-based attorney Roy F. Perkins, Jr., the former attorney for United Broadcasting, pled guilty in federal court to a misdemeanor charge of bugging Hawkins' office. He was fined $2,000. Perkins claimed that he authorized the bugging because of rumors of payola at the station.&lt;ref name=archives/&gt;

In January 1990, United Broadcasting re-acquired the 92.3&amp;nbsp;MHz facility, by now [[WXRK|WRQC]], and changed its callsign to WJMO-FM. United Broadcasting sold WJMO and WJMO-FM in 1992 to Zebra Communications, owned by Xenophon Zapis (owner of Zapis Communications and [[WZAK]]), Lynn Tolliver (WZAK program director) and Bobby (Otis) Rush (WZAK DJ). Although Tolliver and Rush were both African Americans, Zapis was a key party in the new ownership, and the sale was contested by the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference]].&lt;ref name=archives/&gt;

The sale was approved by the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] in 1993,&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Santiago
  | first = Roberto
  | coauthors =
  | title = WJMO sale approved by FCC, but SCLC appeal is likely
  | work =
  | pages = 1B
  | language =
  | publisher = The Plain Dealer
  | date = May 22, 1993
  | url =
http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CPDB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0F8074245A242118&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated4&amp;req_dat=0D1C2ED46ABD2E15
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
and WJMO became the first radio station with significant African American ownership in the Cleveland area. In 1994, as a result of the legal battles, the [[Southern Christian Leadership Conference|SCLC]] gained significant control of WJMO,&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Santiago
  | first = Roberto
  | title = SCLC gains control of WJMO-AM
  | pages = 1A
  | publisher = The Plain Dealer
  | date = December 10, 1993
  | url =
http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CPDB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=0F807969AD9C2B0D&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated4&amp;req_dat=0D1C2ED46ABD2E15
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
which was seen as less profitable than WJMO-FM and WZAK.

The SCLC appointed a local group (dubbed NewCo) that directly had an input in stations' programming, and produced talk and public affairs shows between the hours of 8 p.m. and 5 a.m. Meanwhile, due to the high legal fees incurred by Zapis, Zebra and the SCLC, all of the local deejays on the station were replaced with ABC Radio's &quot;Solid Gold Soul&quot; music service.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Santiago
  | first = Roberto
  | title = FCC Approves Transfer of Two Urban Stations
  | pages = 4B
  | publisher = The Plain Dealer
  | date = February 18, 1994
  | url =
http://infoweb.newsbank.com/iw-search/we/InfoWeb?p_action=doc&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_docnum=1&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;p_product=NewsBank&amp;p_text_direct-0=document_id=(%200F807C708F8D268B%20)&amp;p_docid=0F807C708F8D268B&amp;p_theme=aggregated4&amp;p_queryname=0F807C708F8D268B&amp;f_openurl=yes&amp;p_nbid=V6CU5CIWMTE3OTc5NTQzMC4xNzAwOTM6MTo2Om5jZGNwbA&amp;&amp;p_multi=CPDB
  | accessdate = 2007-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the call letters of the FM station were changed to [[WXRK|WZJM]]—a combination of W'''Z'''AK and W'''JM'''O. (The WJMO-FM calls did resurface on the 99.5&amp;nbsp;MHz facility in Washington, DC—then co-owned with WJMO—in 1999. Today it broadcasts as [[WIHT]].)

On August 12, 1998, Chancellor Media Corporation of Texas announced its purchase of WJMO and [[WXRK|WZJM]] from Zebra Communications, along with its purchase of four other Cleveland radio stations, [[WZAK]], [[WDOK]] 102.1-FM, [[WQAL]] 104.1-FM, and [[WKNR|WRMR]] 850-AM, for $275 million.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last =
  | first =
  | coauthors =
  | title =  Company News; Chancellor Media to Buy Six Cleveland Radio Stations
  | work =
  | pages =
  | language =
  | publisher = The New York Times
  | date = August 13, 1998
  | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E5D9123AF930A2575BC0A96E958260
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
It was, at the time, the largest radio deal in Cleveland broadcasting history.

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:WJMO1490logo.png|thumb|150px|WJMO logo, 1999-2005. A similar logo (with &quot;Solid Gold Soul&quot; in place of &quot;24-Hour Gospel&quot;) was used for many years prior.|{{deletable image-caption|1=Wednesday, 3 December 2008}}]] --&gt;On July 13, 1999, Chancellor Media merged with Capstar Broadcasting (which at the time owned [[WKNR]]) to form AMFM Inc., at that time the nation's largest radio station owner with 465 stations. AMFM sold WZAK and WJMO to Radio One on July 20, 2000 as part of a required divestiture when AMFM merged with [[Clear Channel Communications]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite press release
  | title = Justice Department Requires Clear Channel and AMFM to Divest 99 Radio Stations in 27 Markets. Required Sale is Largest Radio Divestiture Ever
  | publisher = U.S. Department of Justice
  | date = July 20, 2000
  | url = http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/pr/2000/July/415at.htm
  | accessdate = 2007-01-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:WJMO 1490.png|right|thumb|Logo before June 2007.]]
====Later years====
The station became a gospel music outlet on May 17, 1999 after nearly forty years with an [[rhythm &amp; blues]] format, which was reputed by many to have been the longest running such station in the country (though recently, AM 1490—now known as [[WERE (AM)|WERE]]--has been featuring classic soul/R&amp;B music on Friday and Saturday nights as a nod to its former format).&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
  | last = Feran
  | first = Tom
  | coauthors =
  | title = WJMO Gives up Soul for Gospel
  | work =
  | pages = 2E
  | language =
  | publisher = The Plain Dealer
  | date = May 19, 1999
  | url =
http://infoweb.newsbank.com/iw-search/we/InfoWeb?p_action=doc&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_docnum=1&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;p_product=NewsBank&amp;p_text_direct-0=document_id=(%200F80D3C45AEBAAFF%20)&amp;p_docid=0F80D3C45AEBAAFF&amp;p_theme=aggregated4&amp;p_queryname=0F80D3C45AEBAAFF&amp;f_openurl=yes&amp;p_nbid=O68J58XSMTE3OTc5MDk0My4zNDMxOToxOjY6bmNkY3Bs&amp;&amp;p_multi=CPDB
  | accessdate = 2007-05-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2007 frequency &quot;trade&quot;===
On June 4, 2007, Radio One radio stations WJMO (1490&amp;nbsp;AM) and [[WJMO|WERE (1300&amp;nbsp;AM)]] were involved in what was then reported as a frequency &quot;trade.&quot;  In reality, these two stations swapped [[Call sign|call letter]]s along with their respective [[Radio format|format]]s.  WJMO changed its call letters to '''WERE''', and changed its format to [[All-news radio|news]]/[[Talk radio|talk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Washington, Julie|date=May 19, 2007|title=WERE and WJMO trading AM frequencies|url = http://blog.cleveland.com/pdextra/2007/05/gospel_singer_and_morning_radi.html|newspaper=[[The Plain Dealer|Cleveland.com]]|publisher=Cleveland Live, Inc|accessdate=June 4, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==WERE==
===Current programming===
Weekday programming includes ''Daybreak USA'' (from USA Radio) with Scott West, Susan Hydcock, and Bobby Collins; ''[[The Tom Joyner Morning Show]]'' (from [[Citadel Media|ABC/Citadel]]) aired in simulcast with sister station [[WZAK]]; ''The [[Warren Ballentine]] Show'' and ''The [[Rev. Al Sharpton|Al Sharpton]] Show'' (both from Radio One) air middays through early afternoon (Sharpton's show is simulcast on sister station [[WJMO]] AM 1300); local program ''America's Workforce'' hosted by Ed &quot;Flash&quot; Ferenc in afternoon drive; ''The Roth Show'' with Dr. Laurie Roth Ph.D.; ''The Jim Sumpter Show'' and ''The Golden Age of Radio'' with Vic Ives (all from USA Radio) air late evenings and into the overnight hours.

Specialty programming includes [[high school football]] and [[high school basketball]] in season, [[gospel music]] shows, classic soul and R&amp;B during weekends, plus various ethnic programming.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Official|http://newstalkcleveland.com/}}
*{{AM station data|WERE}}
*{{Transmitter|WERE|41.513333|81.601389}}
*[http://www.cleve-radio.com/index2.htm#WJMO-AM%20&amp;%20FM Cleveland Broadcast Radio Archives: WJMO timeline (1947&amp;ndash;2007)]
*[http://www.cleve-radio.com/index2.htm#WERE-AM Cleveland Broadcast Radio Archives: WERE timeline (2007&amp;ndash;Present)]

{{Cleveland AM}}
{{News/Talk Radio Stations in Ohio}}
{{Radio One}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Were}}
[[Category:Radio One stations]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Cleveland, Ohio|ERE]]
[[Category:News and talk radio stations in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
