<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="241681" ns="0" title="Terence McKenna"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Canadian documentary filmmaker|Terence McKenna (film producer)}}
{{pp-semi-sock|expiry=June 15, 2012|small=yes}}
{{Infobox philosopher
|&lt;!-- Scroll down to edit the main text --&gt;
 &lt;!-- Philosopher Category --&gt;

 region = Western Philosophy
|era = [[20th century philosophy]]
|color = #B0C4DE
|
 &lt;!-- Image --&gt;
 image =Mckenna1.jpg
|
 &lt;!-- Information --&gt;
 name = Terence Kemp McKenna
|birth_date = {{Birth date|1946|11|16|mf=yes}}
|birth_place =[[Paonia, Colorado]], [[United States]]
|death_date = {{Death date and age|2000|4|3|1946|11|16|mf=yes}}
|death_place = [[San Rafael, California]], [[United States]]
|school_tradition = [[Metaphysics]], [[Phenomenology (philosophy)|phenomenology]]|
|main_interests = [[shamanism]], [[ethnobotany]], [[metaphysics]], psychedelic drugs, [[futurism]], [[primitivism]], [[environmentalism]], [[consciousness]], [[Phenomenology (philosophy)|phenomenology]], [[historical revisionism]], [[evolution]], [[ontology]], [[Mind at Large]], [[virtual reality]], [[dominator culture]], [[Science#Critiques|criticizing science]], the [[Logos (disambiguation)|Logos]]
|influences = [[psychedelic drugs]], [[Marshall McLuhan]], [[Alfred North Whitehead]], [[Teilhard de Chardin]], [[Aldous Huxley]], [[I Ching]], [[William Blake]], [[Riane Eisler]], [[James Joyce]], [[Vladimir Nabokov]], [[Heraclitus]]
|influenced = [[Rupert Sheldrake]], [[Robert Anton Wilson]], [[Ralph Abraham]], [[RU Sirius]], [[Cliff Pickover]], [[Timothy Leary]]
|notable_ideas = [[2012 doomsday prediction#Timewave zero and the I Ching|Novelty Theory]], [[Terence_McKenna#The &quot;Stoned Ape&quot; Theory of Human Evolution|The &quot;Stoned Ape&quot; Theory of Human Evolution]], [[Machine elves]]
}}

'''Terence Kemp McKenna''' (November 16, 1946&amp;nbsp;– April 3, 2000) was an [[Irish American|Irish-American]]&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;&gt;''True Hallucinations: Being an Account of the Author's Extraordinary Adventures in the Devil's Paradise.'' Terence McKenna, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; philosopher, [[psychonautics|psychonaut]], researcher, teacher, lecturer and writer on many subjects, such as human [[consciousness]], language, psychedelic drugs, the evolution of civilizations, the origin and end of the universe, [[alchemy]], and [[Extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial beings]].

==Biography==
===Early life===
Terence McKenna grew up in [[Paonia, Colorado]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;&gt;[http://www.tripzine.com/listing.php?id=terence1 Terence McKenna Interview, Part 1.] Tripzine.com.  Accessed on June 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; He was introduced to [[geology]] through his uncle and developed a hobby of solitary fossil hunting in the [[Arroyo (creek)|arroyos]] near his home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite speech
 | title = Under The Teaching Tree
 | author = Terence McKenna
 | first = Terence
 | last = McKenna
 | date = Unknown (1985)
 | location = Ojai Foundation, [[Upper Ojai, California]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  From this he developed a deep artistic and scientific appreciation of nature.

At age 16, McKenna moved to [[Los Altos, California]] to live with family friends for a year. He finished high school in Lancaster, CA.&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;/&gt; In 1963, McKenna was introduced to the literary world of [[psychedelics]] through ''[[The Doors of Perception]]'' and ''[[Heaven and Hell (essay)|Heaven and Hell]]'' by [[Aldous Huxley]] and certain issues of ''[[The Village Voice]]'' that talked about psychedelics.&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.erowid.org/culture/characters/mckenna_terence/mckenna_terence_interview_hightimes.shtml Erowid Terence McKenna Vault: The High Times Interview.] Accessed on June 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

McKenna claimed that one of his early psychedelic experiences with [[morning glory]] seeds showed him &quot;that there was something there worth pursuing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;/&gt;
In an audio interview Terence Mckenna claims to have started smoking cannabis regularly during the summer following his 17th birthday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Terence McKenna, I'm Stoned and I'm Proud | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=M0RCmnQcK2w&amp;feature=feedrec_grec_index | date = 2010-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Studying and traveling===
In 1965, McKenna enrolled in the [[University of California, Berkeley]]&lt;ref name=&quot;cannabisnews.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title = Terence McKenna, 53, Dies; Patron of Psychedelics | work = Cannabis News | url = http://cannabisnews.com/news/5/thread5337.shtml | date = 2000-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; to study art history.&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;/&gt; In 1967, while in college, he discovered and begun studying [[shamanism]] through the study of Tibetan folk religion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.erowid.org/culture/characters/mckenna_terence/mckenna_terence_interview_hightimes.shtml Erowid Terence McKenna Vault: The High Times Interview].&lt;/ref&gt; That year, which he called his &quot;[[opium]] and [[kabbalah|kabbala]] phase&quot;{{fact|date=December 2011}} he also traveled to [[Jerusalem]], where he met [[Kathleen Harrison (ethnobotanist)|Kathleen Harrison]], who would later become his wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;

In 1969, McKenna traveled to Nepal led by his &quot;interest in Tibetan painting and hallucinogenic shamanism.&quot;{{fact|date=November 2011}} During his time there, he studied the Tibetan language and worked as a hashish smuggler, until &quot;one of his Bombay-to-Aspen shipments fell into the hands of U.&amp;nbsp;S. Customs.&quot; He was forced to move to avoid capture by Interpol.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt; He wandered through Southeast Asia viewing ruins, collected butterflies in Indonesia, and worked as an English teacher in Tokyo. He then went back to Berkeley to continue studying biology, which he called &quot;his first love&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;

After he completed part of his studies and his mother's death from cancer in 1971,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.disinfo.com/2010/08/machine-elves-101-or-why-terence-mckenna-matters/&lt;/ref&gt; McKenna, his brother [[Dennis McKenna|Dennis]], and three friends traveled to the Colombian Amazon in search of ''[[oo-koo-hé]]'', a plant preparation containing [[Dimethyltryptamine]] (DMT). Instead of [[oo-koo-hé]] they found various forms of ''[[ayahuasca]]'', or ''yagé'', and gigantic ''[[psilocybe cubensis]]'' which became the new focus of the expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt; In [[La Chorrera, Colombia|La Chorrera]], at the urging of his brother, he was the subject of a psychedelic experiment which he claimed put him in contact with &quot;[[Logos]]&quot;: an informative, divine voice he believed was universal to visionary religious experience.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt; The voice's reputed revelations and his brother's simultaneous peculiar experience prompted him to explore the structure of an [[King Wen sequence|early form]] of the [[I Ching]], which led to his &quot;[[2012_phenomenon#Timewave_zero_and_the_I_Ching|Novelty Theory]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;
During their stay in the Amazon, McKenna also became romantically involved with his translator, Ev.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;&gt;''True Hallucinations: Being an Account of the Author's Extraordinary Adventures in the Devil's Paradise'', Terence McKenna, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1972, McKenna returned to Berkeley to finish his studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;cannabisnews.com&quot;/&gt; There he decided to switch majors to a Bachelor of Science in ecology and conservation, in a then new experimental section of the same university called the Tussman Experimental College.&lt;ref name=&quot;tripzine&quot;/&gt; During his studies, he would also develop techniques for cultivating psilocybin mushrooms with Dennis.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt;

In 1975, he parted with his girlfriend, Ev, when she left him for one of his friends from Berkeley. Their parting left him &quot;tormented with migraines and living alone&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt; He graduated in 1975.&lt;ref name=&quot;erowid.org&quot;&gt;https://www.erowid.org/culture/characters/mckenna_terence/mckenna_terence.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; That same year, he began a relationship with Kathleen Harrison, whom he had met in Jerusalem.

Soon after graduating, McKenna and Dennis published a book inspired by their Amazon experiences, ''The Invisible Landscape: Mind, Hallucinogens and the I Ching''. He also began lecturing.&lt;ref name=&quot;cannabisnews.com&quot;/&gt; The brothers' experiences in the Amazon would later play a major role in McKenna's book ''True Hallucinations'', published in 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;true&quot;/&gt; In 1976, the brothers published what they had learned about the cultivation of mushrooms in a book entitled ''Psilocybin - Magic Mushroom Grower's Guide'' under the pseudonyms &quot;OT Oss&quot; and &quot;ON Oeric&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Psilocybin - Magic Mushroom Grower's Guide'', OT Oss and ON Oeric, 1976.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later life===
In the early 1980s, McKenna began to speak publicly on the topic of psychedelic drugs, lecturing extensively and conducting weekend workshops. Though associated with the [[New Age]] and [[Human Potential Movement|human potential movement]]s, McKenna himself had little patience for New Age sensibilities. He repeatedly stressed the importance and primacy of felt experience, as opposed to dogma.&lt;ref name=invisible&gt;{{cite web | title = The Invisible Landscape (lecture) | work = Terence Mckenna | url = http://www.futurehi.net/media/McKenna_The_Invisible_Landscape_1-A.mp3}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Timothy Leary]] once introduced him as &quot;one of the five or six most important people on the planet.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stone&quot;&gt;Introduction by Timothy Leary to &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zMPamVaTjJE Unfolding the Stone]&quot; lecture by Terence McKenna, c. 1992&lt;/ref&gt; {{Rquote|right|&lt;small&gt;It's clearly a crisis of two things: of consciousness and conditioning.  These are the two things that the psychedelics attack. We have the technological power, the engineering skills to save our planet, to cure disease, to feed the hungry, to end war; But we lack the intellectual vision, the ability to change our minds.  We must decondition ourselves from 10,000 years of bad behavior.  And, it's not easy.&lt;/small&gt; |Terence McKenna, &quot;This World...and Its Double&quot;|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = Terence McKenna| title = This World...and Its Double | medium = | publisher = Sound Photosynthesis | location = [[Mill Valley, California]] | date = 1993-09-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}He soon became a fixture of popular counterculture. His growing popularity culminated in the early to mid-1990s with the publication of several books: ''True Hallucinations'', relating the tale of his 1971 [[La Chorrera, Colombia|La Chorrera]] experience; ''Food of the Gods'';  and ''The Archaic Revival''. He became a popular personality in the psychedelic rave/dance scene of the early 1990s, with frequent spoken word performances at [[rave]]s and contributions to psychedelic and [[goa trance]] albums by [[The Shamen]], [[Spacetime Continuum]], [[Alien Project]], [[Capsula]], [[Entheogenic (band)|Entheogenic]], Zuvuya, [[Shpongle]], and Shakti Twins. His speeches were, and are, sampled by many. In 1994 he appeared as a speaker at the [[Starwood Festival]], documented in the book ''Tripping'' by Charles Hayes. His lectures were produced on both cassette tape and CD.&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt;[http://www.psychedelicadventures.com Tripping: An Anthology of True-Life Psychedelic Adventures by Charles Hayes.] Accessed on April 26, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

McKenna was a colleague of [[chaos theory|chaos mathematician]] [[Ralph Abraham]], and [[biologist]] [[Rupert Sheldrake]], creator of the theory of &quot;[[morphogenetic field (Rupert Sheldrake)|morphogenetic fields]]&quot;, not to be confused with the [[morphogenetic field|mainstream usage of the same term]]. He conducted several public debates known as ''trialogues'' with them from the late 1980s until his death. Books containing transcriptions of some of these events were published. He was also a friend and associate of [[Ralph Metzner]], Nicole Maxwell, and [[Riane Eisler]], participating in joint workshops and symposia with them. He was a personal friend of [[Tom Robbins]], and influenced the thought of many [[scientist]]s, [[writer]]s, [[artist]]s, and [[entertainer]]s. His influences include comedian [[Bill Hicks]], whose routines about psychedelic drugs drew heavily from McKenna's works. He is also the inspiration for the [[Twin Peaks]] character Dr. Jacoby.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Twin Peaks (1990) - Trivia | work = IMDB | url =http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0098936/trivia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition to psychedelic drugs, McKenna spoke on the subjects of [[virtual reality]], which he saw as a way to artistically communicate the experience of psychedelics; [[techno-paganism]]; [[artificial intelligence]]; [[evolution]]; [[extraterrestrials]]; and [[aesthetic]] theory, specifically about art/visual experience as ''information'' representing the significance of hallucinatory visions experienced under the influence of psychedelics.

In 1985,&lt;ref name=&quot;erowid.org&quot;/&gt; McKenna co-founded Botanical Dimensions with his then-wife Kathleen, a nonprofit [[ethnobotanical]] preserve in [[Hawaii (island)|Hawaii]], where he lived for many years before he died. In 1997 he and Kathleen divorced.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;http://cannabisnews.com/news/5/thread5337.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; Before moving to Hawaii permanently, McKenna split his time between Hawaii and [[Occidental, California|Occidental]], located in the [[Coast Redwood|redwood]]-studded hills of [[Sonoma County, California]].

===Death===
A longtime sufferer of [[migraine]]s, in mid-1999 McKenna returned to his home on the big island of Hawaii after a long lecturing tour. He began to suffer from increasingly painful headaches. This culminated in three brain seizures in one night, which he claimed were the most powerful psychedelic experiences he had ever known. Upon his emergency trip to the hospital on Oahu, Terence was diagnosed with [[glioblastoma multiforme]], a highly aggressive form of [[Brain tumor|brain cancer]]. For the next several months he underwent various treatments, including experimental [[gamma knife]] radiation treatment. According to [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] magazine, McKenna was worried that his tumour was caused by his 35-years of smoking cannabis; though his doctors assured him there was no causal relation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; 

In late 1999, [[Erik Davis]] conducted what would be the last interview of McKenna.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/8.05/mckenna.html Wired 8.05: Terence McKenna's Last Trip&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; During the interview McKenna also talked about the announcement of his death:

{{cquote|
I always thought death would come on the freeway in a few horrifying moments, so you'd have no time to sort it out. Having months and months to look at it and think about it and talk to people and hear what they have to say, it's a kind of blessing. It's certainly an opportunity to grow up and get a grip and sort it all out. Just being told by an unsmiling guy in a white coat that you're going to be dead in four months definitely turns on the lights. ... It makes life rich and poignant. When it first happened, and I got these diagnoses, I could see the light of eternity, a la William Blake, shining through every leaf. I mean, a bug walking across the ground moved me to tears.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.techgnosis.com/chunkshow-single.php?chunk=chunkfrom-2005-01-13-1713-1.txt Terence McKenna Vs. the Black Hole: by Erik Davis&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

McKenna died on April 3, 2000, at the age of 53, with his loved ones at his bedside. He is survived by his brother Dennis, his son Finn, and his daughter Klea.

===Library fire===
On February 7, 2007, McKenna's library of rare books and personal notes was destroyed in a fire which burned offices belonging to Big Sur's [[Esalen Institute]] which was storing the collection. An [[Collection catalog|index]] maintained by his brother Dennis survives, though little else.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.boingboing.net/2007/02/22/terence-mckennas-lib.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ideas==
{{Rquote|right|&lt;small&gt;There are these things, which I call &quot;self transforming machine elves,&quot; I also call them self-dribbling basketballs. They are, but they are none of these things. I mean you have to understand: these are metaphors in the truest sense, meaning that they're lies! [...] I name them 'Tykes' because tyke is a word that means to me a small child, ... and when you burst into the DMT space this is the Aeon - it's a child, and it's at play with colored balls, and I am in eternity, apparently, in the presence of this thing. &lt;/small&gt; |Terence McKenna, &quot;Time and Mind&quot;|&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| last      = McKenna
| first     = Terence
| year      = 1990
| month     = May
| title     = Time and Mind
| url       = http://deoxy.org/timemind.htm
| work      = - Partial transcription of a taped workshop held in New Mexico
| publisher = The Deoxyribonucleic Hyperdimension (deoxy.org)
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}Terence McKenna advocated the exploration of altered states of mind via the ingestion of naturally occurring psychedelic substances. For example, and in particular, as facilitated by the ingestion of high doses of [[psychedelic mushrooms]], and [[Dimethyltryptamine|DMT]], which he believed was the [[apotheosis]] of the psychedelic experience. He spoke of the &quot;jeweled, self-dribbling basketballs&quot; or &quot;self-transforming [[Machine Elves|machine elves]]&quot; that one encounters in that state.

Although he avoided giving his allegiance to any one interpretation (part of his rejection of [[monotheism]]), he was open to the idea of psychedelics as being &quot;trans-dimensional travel&quot;; literally, enabling an individual to encounter what could be [[ancestor]]s, or [[spirit]]s of earth.&lt;ref name=invisible /&gt; He remained opposed to most forms of [[organized religion]] or [[guru]]-based forms of spiritual awakening.

Either philosophically or religiously, he expressed admiration for [[Marshall McLuhan]], [[Pierre Teilhard de Chardin]], [[Gnostic Christianity]], [[Alfred North Whitehead]] and [[Alchemy]]. McKenna always regarded the Greek philosopher [[Heraclitus]] as his favorite philosopher.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stone&quot;/&gt;

He also expressed admiration for the works of [[James Joyce]] (calling ''[[Finnegans Wake]]'' &quot;the quintessential work of art, or at least work of literature of the 20th century&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Surfing Finnegans Wake | work = Terence Mckenna | url = http://www.lancerules.com/terence/finneganswake.mp3}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Vladimir Nabokov]]: McKenna once said that he would have become a Nabokov lecturer if he had never encountered psychedelics.

===&quot;Stoned Ape&quot; theory of human evolution===
In his book ''Food of the Gods'',&lt;ref name=&quot;McKenna 1992&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|first=Terrence|last=McKenna|title=Food of the Gods: the Search for the original Tree of Knowledge|publisher=Bantam|origyear=1993|isbn=0553371304|year=1992}}&lt;/ref&gt; McKenna proposed that the transformation from humans' early ancestors ''[[Homo erectus]]'' to the species ''[[Homo sapiens]]'' mainly had to do with the addition of the mushroom ''Psilocybe cubensis'' in its diet - an event which according to his theory took place in about 100,000 BC (this is when he believed that the species diverged from the [[Homo]] genus). He based his theory on the main effects, or alleged effects, produced by the mushroom. One of the effects that comes about from the ingestion of low doses, which agrees with one of scientist Roland Fischer's findings from the late 60s-early 70s,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Fischer |first1=Roland |last2=Hill |first2=Richard |year=1970 |title=Psilocybin-Induced Contraction of Nearby Visual Space |journal=Agents and Actions |volume=1 |issue=4 |pages=190–197 |pmid=5520365}}&lt;/ref&gt; is it significantly improves the visual acuity of humans - so theoretically, of other human-like mammals too. According to McKenna, this effect would have definitely prove to be of evolutionary advantage to humans' omnivorous [[hunter-gatherer]] ancestors that would have stumbled upon it &quot;accidentally&quot;; as it would make it easier for them to hunt.

In higher doses, McKenna claims, the mushroom acts as a sexual stimulator, which would make it even more beneficial evolutionarily, as it would result in more offspring. At even higher doses, the mushroom would have acted to &quot;dissolve boundaries&quot;, which would have promoted community-bonding and group sexual activities-that would result in a mixing of genes and therefore greater genetic diversity. Generally McKenna believed that the periodic ingestion of the mushroom would have acted to dissolve the [[Ego (spirituality)|ego]] in humans before it ever got the chance to grow in destructive proportions. In this context he likened the ego to a cancerous [[tumor]] that can grow uncontrollable and become destructive to its host. In his own words:

{{quote|text=Wherever and whenever the ego function began to form, it was akin to a cancerous tumor or a blockage in the energy of the [[Psyche (psychology)|psyche]]. The use of psychedelic plants in a context of [[shamanic]] initiation dissolved-as it dissolves today-the knotted structure of the ego into undifferentiated feeling, what Eastern philosophy calls the [[Tao]].|sign=Terence McKenna|source=Food of the Gods}}

The mushroom, according to McKenna, had also given humans their first truly religious experiences (which, as he believed, were the basis for the foundation of all subsequent religions to date). Another factor that McKenna talked about was the mushroom's potency to promote linguistic thinking. This would have promoted vocalisation, which in turn would have acted in cleansing the brain (based on a scientific theory that vibrations from speaking cause the precipitation of impurities from the brain to the cerebrospinal fluid), which would further mutate the brain. All these factors according to McKenna were the most important factors that promoted evolution towards the ''Homo sapiens'' species. After this transformation took place, the species would have begun moving [[Recent African origin of modern humans|out of Africa]] to populate the rest of the planet &lt;ref name=&quot;McKenna 1992&quot;/&gt; Later on, this theory by McKenna was given the name &quot;The 'Stoned Ape' Theory of Human Evolution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;http://www.lycaeum.org/~sputnik/McKenna/Evolution/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bibliography==
* 1975 - ''The Invisible Landscape: Mind, Hallucinogens, and the I Ching'' (with [[Dennis McKenna]]) (Seabury; 1st Ed) ISBN 0-8164-9249-2.
* 1976 - ''The Invisible Landscape'' (with [[Dennis McKenna]], and Quinn Taylor) (Scribner) ISBN 0-8264-0122-8
* 1976 - ''Psilocybin - Magic Mushroom Grower's Guide'' (with [[Dennis McKenna]]: credited under the pseudonyms OT Oss and ON Oeric) (2nd edition 1986) (And/Or Press) ISBN 0-915904-13-6
* 1992 - ''Psilocybin - Magic Mushroom Grower's Guide'' (with [[Dennis McKenna]]: (credited under the pseudonyms OT Oss and ON Oeric) (Quick American Publishing Company; Revised edition) ISBN 0-932551-06-8
* 1992 - ''The Archaic Revival'' (HarperSanFrancisco; 1st edition) ISBN 0-06-250613-7
* 1992 - ''Food of the Gods: The Search for the Original Tree of Knowledge - A Radical History of Plants, Drugs, and Human Evolution'' (Bantam) ISBN 0-553-37130-4
* 1992 - ''Synesthesia'' (with [[Timothy Ely|Timothy C. Ely]]) (Granary Books 1st Ed) ISBN 1-887123-04-0
* 1992 - ''Trialogues at the Edge of the West: Chaos, Creativity, and the Resacralization of the World'' (with Ralph H. Abraham, Rupert Sheldrake and Jean Houston) (Bear &amp; Company Publishing 1st Ed) ISBN 0-939680-97-1
* 1993 - ''True Hallucinations: Being an Account of the Author’s Extraordinary Adventures in the Devil’s Paradise'' (HarperSanFrancisco 1st Ed) ISBN 0-06-250545-9
* 1994 - ''The Invisible Landscape'' (HarperSanFrancisco; Reprint edition) ISBN 0-06-250635-8
* 1998 - ''True Hallucinations &amp; the Archaic Revival: Tales and Speculations About the Mysteries of the Psychedelic Experience'' (Fine Communications/MJF Books) (Hardbound) ISBN 1-56731-289-6
* 1998 - ''The Evolutionary Mind : Trialogues at the Edge of the Unthinkable'' (with Rupert Sheldrake and Ralph H. Abraham) (Trialogue Press; 1st Ed) ISBN 0-942344-13-8
* 1999 - ''Food of the Gods: A Radical History of Plants, Drugs, and Human Evolution'' (Rider &amp; Co; New edition) ISBN 0-7126-7038-6
* 1999 -  ''Robert Venosa: Illuminatus'' (with Robert Venosa, Ernst Fuchs, H. R. Giger, and Mati Klarwein) (Craftsman House) ISBN 90-5703-272-4
* 2001 -  ''Chaos, Creativity, and Cosmic Consciousness'' (with Rupert Sheldrake and Ralph H. Abraham) (Park Street Press; revised ed) ISBN 0-89281-977-4 (Revised edition of Trialogues at the Edge of the West)
* 2005 - ''The Evolutionary Mind: Trialogues on Science, Spirit &amp; Psychedelics'' (Monkfish Book Publishing; Revised Ed) ISBN 0-9749359-7-2

==Spoken word==
* ''History Ends In Green: Gaia, Psychedelics and the Archaic Revival'', 6 audiocassette set, [[Mystic Fire]] audio, 1993, ISBN 1-56176-907-x (recorded at the [[Esalen Institute]], 1989)
* ''TechnoPagans at the End of History'' (transcription of rap with [[Mark Pesce]] from 1998)
* ''Psychedelics in the Age of Intelligent Machines'' (1999) [http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-335621086425739066# 90 minutes video]
* ''Alien Dreamtime'' with [[Spacetime Continuum]] &amp; [[Stephen Kent (musician)|Stephen Kent]] ([http://www.magiccarpetmedia.com Magic Carpet Media]) (CD) [http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-2395498051948678069# video]
* ''Conversations on the Edge of Magic'' (1994) (CD &amp; Cassette) [[Association for Consciousness Exploration|ACE]]
* ''Rap-Dancing Into the Third Millennium'' (1994) (Cassette) (Re-issued on CD as ''The Quintessential Hallucinogen'') [[Association for Consciousness Exploration|ACE]]
* ''Packing For the Long Strange Trip'' (1994) (Cassette) [[Association for Consciousness Exploration|ACE]]
* [[Coast to Coast AM]] with [[Art Bell]], broadcast on May 22, 1997, Five hour interview covering various topics
* ''Global Perspectives and Psychedelic Poetics'' (1994) (Cassette) Sound Horizons Audio-Video, Inc.
* ''The Search for the Original Tree of Knowledge'' (1992) (Cassette) [[Sounds True]]

==Discography==
* ''Re : Evolution'' with [[The Shamen]] (1992)
* ''Alien Dreamtime'' with [[Spacetime Continuum]] &amp; [[Stephen Kent (musician)|Stephen Kent]] ([http://www.magiccarpetmedia.com Magic Carpet Media]) (DVD)
* 2009 - [http://cognitionfactor.net ''Cognition Factor'' (2009)]

==See also==
* [[Ethnomycology]]
* [[Exopheromone]]
* [[List of notable brain tumor patients]]
* [[Machine Elf]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
* [http://deoxy.org/mckenna.htm Terence McKenna Land at Deoxy.org]
* [http://www.levity.com/eschaton/tm.html Terence McKenna at Levity.com]
* [http://www.erowid.org/culture/characters/mckenna_terence/mckenna_terence.shtml Erowid's Terence McKenna Vault]
* [http://www.well.com/user/dpd/botdim.html Botanical Dimensions]
* [http://www.rotten.com/library/bio/mad-science/terence-mckenna/ Rotten.com bio]
* [http://floatingworldweb.com/plex/#-2328 FloatingWorldWeb's McKenna Pages]
* [http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/8.05/mckenna.html Terence McKenna's Last Trip] 2000 Wired Magazine article by Erik Davis
* [http://www.disinfo.com/archive/pages/article/id1515/pg2/ &quot;Mind contagions&quot; (2001) at disinfo.com]
* [http://www.lysergia.com/FeedYourHead/McKenna/TerenceMcKenna.htm Psychedelics, Evolution &amp; Fun] 2008 essay by Patrick Lundborg
* [http://www.realitysandwich.com/machine_elves_101 Machine Elves 101, or Why Terence McKenna Matters - Reallity Sandwish] by Daniel Moler
* [http://www.dope-smoker.co.uk/quotes-from-terrance-mckenna/ Transcription from 1991 interview regarding cannabis]

===Audio and video resources===
* [http://www.hazarddp.com/?page_id=2 Terence McKenna's interview] Conducted by John Hazard in October 1998
* [http://deoxy.org/media/McKenna Audio and video archive] at Deoxy.org
* [http://erocx1.com/TerenceMcKenna.aspx Terence McKenna media archive] at EROCx1.com
* [http://www.futurehi.net/media.html FutureHi.net MP3 Downloads] - Terence McKenna, Albert Hoffman, Robert Anton Wilson, and more
* [http://www.matrixmasters.com/pn/MiscMP3s/TerenceMcKenna1999.html McKenna at the 1999 Entheobotany Seminar] - Audio Podcast
* [http://www.surrealstudio.com/mckenna.html Psychedelics in the Age of Intelligent Machines] - Video samples from the 1999 DVD
* [http://floatingworldweb.com/plex/index.html#-4428 McKenna Video on FloatingWorldWeb] - McKenna Video Portal
* [http://www.matrixmasters.net/salon/?category_name=terence-mckenna Over 100 podcasts of Terence McKenna talks] - Audio Podcast

===Transcripts===
* [http://www.mindofmckenna.com MindofMcKenna] - McKenna audio excerpts, transcriptions and quotes

{{Cannabis resources}}
{{Hallucinogenic mushrooms}}
{{Recreational drug use}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Mackenna, Terence
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 16, 1946
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Paonia, Colorado]], [[United States]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = April 3, 2000
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Hawaii]], [[United States]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mackenna, Terence}}
[[Category:2012 theorists]]
[[Category:Deaths from brain cancer]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in Hawaii]]
[[Category:Psychedelic drug advocates]]
[[Category:Psychedelic researchers]]
[[Category:American cannabis activists]]
[[Category:American book and manuscript collectors]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:Contemporary philosophers]]
[[Category:Counterculture festivals activists]]
[[Category:1946 births]]
[[Category:2000 deaths]]
[[Category:American anarchists]]
[[Category:Philosophers of science]]
[[Category:Mystics]]
[[Category:Ethnobotanists]]
[[Category:Religious skeptics]]

[[bs:Terrence McKenna]]
[[cs:Terence McKenna]]
[[de:Terence McKenna]]
[[es:Terence McKenna]]
[[fr:Terence McKenna (écrivain)]]
[[hr:Terrence McKenna]]
[[it:Terence McKenna]]
[[nl:Terence McKenna]]
[[ja:テレンス・マッケナ]]
[[pl:Terence McKenna]]
[[pt:Terence McKenna]]
[[ru:Маккенна, Теренс Кемп]]
[[sk:Terence McKenna]]
[[fi:Terence McKenna]]
[[sv:Terence McKenna]]
[[tr:Terence McKenna]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
