<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24200198" ns="0" title="WNOC"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox radio station
| name                 = WNOC
| image                = [[File:WHRQ logo.png|200px]]
| city                 = [[Bowling Green, Ohio]]
| area                 = [[Toledo Metropolitan Area]]
| slogan               = &quot;Faith with Frequency&quot;
| branding             = Annunciation Radio
| frequency            = 89.7 mHz
| repeater             = 
| airdate              = August 14, 2010
| format               = Religious radio
| erp                  = 3800 watts
| haat                 = 312 feet
| class                = 
| facility_id          =
| coordinates          =
| owner                = [[Our Lady of Guadalupe]] Radio Inc.
| licensee             =  dba:Annunciation Radio
| callsign_meaning     = '''N'''orthwest '''O'''hio '''C'''atholics
| sister_stations      = [[WHRQ]], [[Sandusky, Ohio|Sandusky]]
| webcast              = [http://75.125.83.198:7070/armp3.m3u Listen Live]
| website              = [http://www.annunciationradio.com Annunciation Radio.com]
| affilliations        = [[EWTN]] Glocal Catholic Radio Network&lt;br&gt;[[WDEO|Ave Maria Radio Network]]
}}

'''WNOC''' (89.7 [[FM broadcasting|FM]], &quot;Annunciation Radio&quot;) is a [[non-commercial educational]] radio station licensed to serve the community of [[Bowling Green, Ohio]] and serving the Toledo and Bowling Green areas with Catholic programming within the northern portion of the Toledo diocese. It is the second Catholic station to make its debut in the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Toledo, Ohio|Toledo Diocese]] in the summer of 2010, the other being [[WJTA]] &quot;Holy Family Radio&quot; licensed in [[Glandorf, Ohio]] and transmitting from [[Leipsic, Ohio|Leipsic]]. WNOC airs local programming in addition to programs from [[EWTN]] Radio, and [[Ave Maria Radio]].

==History==
Annunciation Radio began in 2006 as a venture by Toledo businessman and Deacon Mike Learned who, on February 3, 2008, launched a Sunday afternoon program on Toledo daytime talk station WTOD 1560 AM until it was sold by [[Cumulus Media]] to CSN Radio in March 2010 which is now [[WWYC]]....hence the program briefly moved to Cumulus-owned [[WLQR]] (1470 AM) until the new station made its initial sign-on on August 14, 2010. More information can be found on its website. The construction permit was at first held by MCCR Inc.(for: Ministry for Catholic Charismatic Renewal)

WNOC serves the Bowling Green and Toledo areas while sister station [[WHRQ]] in Sandusky at 88.1 FM made it on-air debut on Monday April 25, 2011 (initially as a WNOC simulcast). The Annunciation Radio audiostream commenced on its website on August 26, 2010.

==Call sign history==
WNOC's call letters were previously used at 94.1 FM in Old Forge New York (later WNOB now defunct),on Channel 26 in Jamestown,New York (which is now [[WNYB]]),on Channel 24 in Flora,Illinois (later WNOI-LP now defunct),at 720 AM in Wake Forest, North Carolina (now defunct since 1986) and before that at 1310 AM in Norwich, Connecticut..the present-day [[WICH]].

==References==
* [http://www.toledoblade.com/article/20100821/NEWS10/100829978 Toledo Blade story of WNOC sign-on (August 21, 2010)]
* [http://www.catholicchronicle.org/index.php/diocesan/annunciation-radio-now-broadcasting-full-time.html Toledo Catholic Chronicle story of WNOC sign-on (August 30, 2010)]
* [http://www.toledoblade.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090530/NEWS10/905300385 Toledo Blade story of Annunciation Radio's fundraiser and planned launch. (May 30, 2009)]
* [http://www.annunciationradio.com/images/annunciation%20radio%20raymond%20fliers%20final.pdf Promotional flyer of New York Times author Raymond Arroyo's appearance at WNOC's launch.(in PDF format)]

==External links==
* [http://www.annunciationradio.com Official Annunciation Radio site (with streaming audio)]
* {{FM station data|WNOC}}
* [http://cdbs.recnet.com/fmq.php?call=wnoc Additional WNOC information from REC Networks site]
* [http://www.ewtn.com/radio/index.asp EWTN Radio official site]
* [http://www.avemariaradio.net Ave Maria Radio official site]

==See also==
* [[WHRQ]] 88.1 FM serving Sandusky/Port Clinton,Fremont and northcoast areas as a WNOC simulcast.
* [[WJTA]] 88.9 FM owned by Holy Family Communications in [[Leipsic, Ohio|Leipsic]] compliments both the WNOC and WHRQ signals in the Ottawa,Findlay,Napoleon,Paulding,Lima and Definace areas as an EWTN affiliate.

{{Toledo Radio}}

[[Category:Catholic radio stations]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Ohio|NOC]]
[[Category:Wood County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Toledo metropolitan area]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
