<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24273362" ns="0" title="Star Air Service"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Airline
| airline        = Star Air Service &lt;br&gt;Star Air Lines &lt;br&gt;Alaska Star Airlines
| image          = 
| image_size     = 
| logo           = Alaska_Star_Airlines_LogoD.jpg
| logo_size      = 225px
| IATA           = 
| ICAO           = 
| callsign       = ASA (1942–)
| founded        = April 14, 1932
| commenced      = 
| ceased         = 1944 (renamed [[Alaska Airlines]])
| hubs           = 
| secondary_hubs = 
| focus_cities   = [[Anchorage, Alaska]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fairbanks, Alaska]]&lt;/br&gt;[[Nome, Alaska]]
| frequent_flyer = 
| lounge         = 
| alliance       = 
| subsidiaries   = 
| fleet_size     = 
| destinations   = Numerous
| parent         = 
| company_slogan = 
| headquarters   = Anchorage, Alaska
| key_people     = Steven E. &quot;Steve&quot; Mills&lt;br&gt;John E. &quot;Jack&quot; Waterworth&lt;br&gt;Charles H. &quot;Charlie&quot; Ruttan &lt;br&gt;Raymond W. Marshall&lt;/br&gt;
| website        = 
}}

'''Star Air Service''', later '''Star Air Lines''' and '''Alaska Star Airlines''' was an [[USA|American]] air service in [[Alaska]] from 1932 to 1944. With financial help from a wealthy Alaska miner, three pilots who had started a flying school and charter business in [[Seattle]], shipped an open-cockpit biplane by steamship to Alaska in March 1932. Star Air Service was incorporated in April, 1932 in [[Anchorage, Alaska|Anchorage]] with capitalization of $4,000. The company had some early success training student pilots, but their airplane was destroyed in a crash. Their financial backer helped them purchase a larger plane with an enclosed cabin which supported winter operations.

Three air services were founded in Anchorage in 1932. There was a surplus of airplanes, and not enough business to support them all, which prompted the 1934 merger of [[McGee Airways]] with Star Air Service. Star became the largest carrier in Alaska. A lack of financial resources and poor management continued to haunt the company. One of the founders lost his pilot’s license and another died in a  plane crash in 1936. With a change in management, the company was sold to a new group of investors in 1937, and renamed Star Air Lines.

Government regulation of Alaska airline routes which began in 1938, along with continued financial instability of Alaska’s air carriers prompted a consolidation within the industry. In 1942, Star Air Lines was purchased by [[New York]] businessman Raymond Marshall.

The new owners acquired three smaller Alaska carriers, gaining additional scheduled routes to [[Fairbanks, Alaska|Fairbanks]], [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]] and the [[Kuskokwim Delta|Kuskokwim]] area. The expanded company was renamed Alaska Star Airlines. In September 1943, after narrowly beating a competitor who was also filing for the name, the company was renamed again, becoming [[Alaska Airlines]], which continues to operate today.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Bagoy, John P.|year=2001|title=Legends &amp; Legacies Anchorage 1910-1935|isbn=1-888125-91-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Satterfield, Archie|year=1981|title=The Alaska Airlines Story|publisher=Alaska Northwest Publishing Company, Anchorage, Alaska|isbn=0-88240-165-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref 
name=&quot;Aerofiles&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Airlines of North America|url=http://www.aerofiles.com/airlines-am.html|accessdate=2009-08-23|work=Airlines of North America|publisher=AeroFiles}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Link&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Alaska Airlines|url=http://www.historylink.org/index.cfm?DisplayPage=output.cfm&amp;file_id=2107|accessdate=2009-08-23|publisher=History Link|last=Crowley|first=Walt | date=1 February 2000}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.atwonline.com/magazine/article.html?articleID=2148|title=Alaska Airlines 75th Anniversary|last=Glab |first=Jim|date=December 2007|publisher=Air Transport World|accessdate=2009-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Company founders==

Steven E. &quot;Steve&quot; Mills was born in [[Dayton, Wyoming]], in 1896 and moved to [[Seattle]] after serving in [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt; He worked as a furnace inspector for the Seattle Gas Company while taking flying lessons at Washington Aircraft Company at [[Boeing Field]]. In 1928 he went to work for the firm’s flying school and was chief instructor until he went to Alaska in 1932.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

John E. &quot;Jack&quot; Waterworth was born in [[Oelwein, Iowa]], reared in Seattle and attended the [[University of Washington]] studying to be a pharmacist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt; With financial help from the industrialist [[Norton Clapp]], Jack took flying lessons from Steve Mills at Washington Aircraft Company. Instead of becoming a pharmacist, Waterworth decided to stay in aviation and he worked as an instructor and charter pilot. He made numerous flights throughout the northwest and an occasional cross-country trip to ferry planes from the east coast to Seattle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

Charles H. &quot;Charlie&quot; Ruttan was a 22 year-old Canadian from [[Winnipeg|Winnipeg, Manitoba]], who had moved with his family to [[Victoria, British Columbia]], and took flying lessons from Steve Mills.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

Wesley Earl Dunkle was a wealthy Alaska mining engineer with several mining claims, as well as being superintendent of the Lucky Shot Mine in the [[Chugach Mountains]] north of Anchorage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Mac McGee The Beginnings|url=http://www.alaskaair.com/as/www2/company/History/MacMcGee.asp|accessdate=2009-08-29|work=Company History|publisher=Alaska Airlines - Horizon Group}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dunkle was interested in aviation and went to Seattle to take flying lessons, where he became friends with Mills and Waterworth. With aviation becoming popular in Alaska, many Alaskans wanted to learn to fly, but could not afford to go to Seattle for lessons. Dunkle encouraged Mills and Waterworth to open a flying school in Anchorage and offered to make them a loan in exchange for free flying lessons when they moved to Alaska.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

==History==
===Early history in Seattle===

Mills and Waterworth were anxious to start a flying school and charter business in Seattle with hopes of expanding to Alaska. Mills, who was married and the father of two sons, mortgaged his home, and he and Waterworth purchased a two-place Davis monoplane, and started Northern Air Service. Waterworth completely destroyed the plane in a crash in [[Centralia, Washington]]. Their new company was without an airplane, and they needed a new partner to help finance the purchase of another airplane.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

Charlie Ruttan was an ideal prospect. He already had his transport pilot's license when the Davis crashed. He joined the company and loaned enough money to purchase a two-place [[Fleet Aircraft|Fleet]] Deluxe B-5 biplane in [[Glendale, California]], in 1931. By then, it was too late in the year to take the plane to Alaska, so the trio kept working in Seattle through the winter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

===Early operations in Alaska===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:StarAirServiceIreneIrvine.jpg|left|thumb|Student pilot Irene Irvine with the Star Air Service Fleet 7 Biplane.{{ffdc|1=StarAirServiceIreneIrvine.jpg|log=2009 October 28}}]] --&gt;
In the early spring of 1932, they shipped the Fleet biplane to Seward, Alaska, on the ''SS Yukon'' steamship, arriving March 26, 1932.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt; They incorporated their new Alaska company Star Air Service in Anchorage on April 14, 1932 with capitalization of $4,000.  Mills was chief pilot, Waterworth was an instructor, and Ruttan was business manager. Earl Dunkle along with a small group of miners and local flying enthusiasts made investments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;

Star Air Service had a lot of flight instruction business and also did some charter flying. Al Monsen, who flew for Pacific International Airways, the [[Pan American Airways|Pan American]] subsidiary, borrowed the Fleet for a local charter flight. When he returned to [[Merrill Field]], he overshot the runway by a large margin, crashing in willow brush past the field.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt; This put Star Air Service temporarily out of business. With more financial help from Earl Dunkle, they purchased a three-place [[Curtiss Robin]] which had an enclosed cockpit, allowing better winter operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;

Three airlines were started in 1932 in Anchorage when it was a small frontier town of about 2,200 residents. They were [[McGee Airways]], [[Woodley Airways]] and Star Air Service. These companies helped make Anchorage the major city in Alaska, overtaking [[Fairbanks]] in the competition for business, government contracts and international attention. Originally these Anchorage air services were entirely unscheduled &quot;bush&quot; operations. They flew trappers, hunters, tourists, salesmen, sport fishermen, commercial fisherman and game hunters to destinations throughout the Territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;/&gt; They flew from place to place delivering and picking up passengers and cargo, until getting a charter back to Anchorage. The pilots were often gone for weeks at a time before returning to home base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Star Air Service CurtissRobinA.jpg|right|thumb|Star Air Service Curtiss Robin.]]
The pilots were paid on a commission basis, and since the major industries in Alaska were seasonal, they also issued credit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;/&gt; The commercial fishermen, miners and trappers settled their credit accounts at the end of their seasons. When the [[Post Office Department]] began giving the air services air mail contracts, the steady income helped the companies, and expanded the flights into additional remote villages. Previously mail had been delivered by steamships in the summer and dog teams in winter. In winter months from October 1 until May 1 only letters, cards, packages of seeds weighing less than a pound, and newspapers going to libraries or newspaper publishers were carried. Packages were held in Seattle until the summer months when they could be delivered by boat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

By 1934, all the airlines were suffering financially.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Alaska Air Group Company History|url=http://www.fundinguniverse.com/Company-Histories/Alaska-Air-Group-Inc-Company-history.html|accessdate=2009-08-29|work=Company History|publisher=FundingUniverse(American Fork,Utah)}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; There was a surplus of airplanes and not enough business to allow the companies to accumulate sufficient cash reserves to survive through difficult times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

===Merger with McGee Airways===

In the winter of 1934, &quot;Mac&quot; McGee, founder of McGee Airways, was anxious to return to mining the several mines he had staked and felt that a consolidation of air services in Anchorage was necessary. He approached Star Air Service, who purchased McGee Airways for $50,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt; McGee stipulated that if he was not paid on time, he would return to manage the combined company until he received his full payment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kipnotes airlines&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Business History of Carriers|url=http://www.kipnotes.com/Airlines.htm|accessdate=2009-08-29|work=Business History, Airlines|publisher=Kipnotes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The merger made Star Air Service the largest airline in Alaska, but money was not coming in as hoped for, and McGee was called back from his [[Kobuk, Alaska|Kobuk]] mining operation to take over management of the company. He paid himself three percent of gross income until he accumulated all the money due him, then went back to mining. In 1935, Jack Waterworth’s pilot's license was suspended for 6 months for flying stunts over [[Palmer, Alaska|Palmer]] during the &lt;!--what fair?--&gt;fair.{{Dubious|date=November 2011|reason=&quot;What fair?&quot; is a good question.  Most references to the history of the Palmer fair (currently known as the Alaska State Fair) indicate that it didn't begin until 1936.}}  He left Star to work at [[Zachariah J. Loussac|Loussac]]'s Drugstore as a pharmacist, the profession he had studied in college.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

In 1936, Star Air Service was operating 15 planes with a gross income of $190,000 per year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt; By August 1936, McGee had left Star and returned to his mining operations. Kenneth W. &quot;Kenny&quot; Neese, one of the Star pilots, took over management of the company, and Steve Mills was chief pilot. On Sunday August 30, 1936, Mills took a group of two married couples and a single man on an all-day fishing trip to [[Russian River (Alaska)|Russian River]] on the [[Kenai Peninsula]]. They crashed on a ridge 2,000 feet above Upper Russian Lake.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt; All were killed instantly. This was the worst aviation disaster in Alaska’s history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:StarBellancaInSnow.jpg|left|thumb|Star Air Lines Bellanca in the snow.]]
Kenny Neese was attempting to put the air service on a scheduled basis. Don Goodman and Oscar Winchell, two of Star’s pilots, did not agree with this strategy, and left Star to purchase airplanes and start Alaska Interior Airlines in November 1936. In the Spring of 1937, Neese quit as Star manager and returned to flying. McGee was called back to manage the struggling company for the last time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt; Charlie Ruttan, the last of the Star founders, left the company.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt; McGee bought Alaska Interior Airlines, adding two pilots and two planes to the fleet, and got the company back into good condition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kipnotes airlines&quot;/&gt;

Don Goodman approached several miners and businessmen and put together a corporation to buy Star Air Service, renaming it Star Air Lines on November 27, 1937. David Strandberg, a successful miner, and his sons were the major stockholders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aerofiles&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kipnotes airlines&quot;/&gt;

===Era of government regulation===

In 1938, the [[Civil Aeronautics Act]] was passed, creating the [[Civil Aeronautics Authority]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt; This ended the free-wheeling bush flying era of Alaska aviation, and assigned specific routes to the air carriers. The new law established a &quot;grandfather clause&quot; which entitled existing carriers to receive certificates for routes where the carrier could prove that it had provided continuous service on a route during the period May 14, 1938 to August 22, 1938. This regulation resulted in the consolidation of several airlines; the big ones got bigger, and the small ones disappeared. Goodman and the Strandbergs determined to make Star Air Lines one of Alaska’s major carriers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:StarBellancaAtMerrill.jpg|right|thumb|Star Air Lines Bellanca at Merrill Field in Anchorage.]]
At its peak before World War II, Star Air Lines had a fleet of 15 planes and had radio stations scattered across the [[Kuskokwim Delta|Kuskokwim]] and [[Yukon Delta|Yukon]] deltas and down to [[Bristol Bay]]. It was the largest airline in Alaska, but as usual, was chronically short of capital and unable to invest adequately in new equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

The [[Civil Aeronautics Board]] (CAB) hearings in 1940 increased government control over Alaska's airlines which completely reshaped the industry.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt; Both Star Air Lines and Woodley Airways did everything possible to obtain approval for a route from Alaska to Seattle. The CAB ruled in favor of a Seattle route for Star in March 1941, but President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] vetoed the ruling.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt; Pan American Airways started a Seattle – [[Ketchikan, Alaska|Ketchikan]] – [[Juneau, Alaska|Juneau]] service with a [[Sikorsky Aircraft|Sikorsky]] flying boat in 1940, but the route was discontinued when World War II started.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

===Consolidation and acquisition===
[[File:Star Airline Fleet video.ogg|thumbtime=19 | thumb| 200px |left|alt=A color video of the Star Air Line Fleet in 1939.|A color video of the Star Air Line Fleet from 1939.]]
In 1942, Art Woodley, founder and operator of Woodley Airways in Anchorage, wanted to buy Star Air Lines, and knew he could purchase the company for its debts, about $80,000. Due to the intense rivalries between the companies, he needed to be anonymous in any negotiations. He hired Homer Robinson, a New York attorney experienced in aircraft sales and aviation transactions, as a broker. Robinson was a close associate of Raymond W. Marshall, a wealthy international junk dealer who had made a fortune selling scrapped railroad equipment to South American companies, as well as other ventures. Robinson successfully concluded the negotiations, but then informed Woodley that Raymond Marshall would be the purchaser, not Art Woodley. Marshall was the new owner of the company!&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Link&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt;

The new owners expanded the company acquiring three active Alaska air services. On May 15, 1942, they acquired Mirow Air Service for $60,000, gaining the [[Nome, Alaska|Nome]] to Fairbanks route, and Lavery Air Service for $60,000, gaining the Fairbanks–Anchorage route. On July 6, 1942, they renamed the expanded company Alaska Star Airlines.&lt;ref name=&quot;History Link&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kipnotes airlines&quot;/&gt; On December 8, 1942, they acquired Pollack Flying Service for $125,000, gaining the Fairbanks to Kuskokwim area routes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aerofiles&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt;
Mirow Air Service was founded by Hans Mirow, a German sailor who learned to fly in the late 1920s at Tex Rankin's Flying School in [[Portland, Oregon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Cats&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Bohrer, Walt|year=1989|title=Black Cats and Outside Loops, Tex Rankin Aerobatic Ace|publisher=Piere Publishers, Inc.(Oregon City)}}&lt;/ref&gt; He went to Alaska in 1934 and started his successful operation in Nome, initiating the first scheduled flights between Nome and Anchorage.&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Anchorage Centennial Commission Aviation Committee|year=1967|title=Honoring 100 Alaska Bush Pilots|publisher=Alaska Purchase Centennial 1867-1967, Anchorage Centennial Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mirow was killed when he crashed while searching for one of his pilots who had been forced down between Nome and Fairbanks with passengers.&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt; His widow continued to operate the service until selling to Star Air Lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;
[[Image:StarBellancaOnFloats.jpg|right|thumb|Star Air Lines Bellancas at Lake Spenard, Anchorage.]]

Lavery Air Service was founded in Fairbanks in 1935 by William L. &quot;Bill&quot; Lavery who was born and raised in Fairbanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt; At age 15, Bill went to [[California]] to learn to fly, founded Lavery Air Service at age 20, and started the first scheduled service from Fairbanks to Anchorage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;

Pollack Flying Service was founded in Fairbanks in 1933 by Frank Pollack who began his Alaska flying with [[Noel Wien]]’s Northern Air Transport, flying out of [[Valdez, Alaska|Valdez]], Fairbanks and Nome.&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt; After selling his company to Alaska Star Airlines he became their operations manager in Fairbanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

===Birth of Alaska Airlines===

Art Woodley had been advised that he would have to change the Woodley Airways name to something other than his own name in order to be considered a serious contender for new routes by the CAB regulators. Woodley sent his attorney to Juneau to file papers that would change the name to Alaska Airlines. The attorney filed the documents, but neglected to pay the $15 filing fee. Alaska Star Airlines quickly filed the legal documents to rename their company, becoming Alaska Airlines on September 16, 1943, and the company was incorporated under its new name on May 2, 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Link&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATW&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mac McGee The Beginnings&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAG Company History&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;kipnotes airlines&quot;/&gt;

Woodley Airways changed its name to Pacific Northern Airways (PNA) in 1945, changing again in 1947 to Pacific Northern Airlines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Delta&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Davis, 
R.E.G.|year=1990|title=Delta - An Airline and Its Aircraft: The Illustrated History of a Major U.S. Airline and the People Who Made It|publisher=Paladwr Press (Miami, Florida)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Livery and logos==

[[Image:Star Air Lines LogoB.jpg|150px|right|thumb|Star Air Lines Logo]]
The original Star Air Service plane, the Fleet 7 open-cockpit biplane had a three-line identification painted on the side with a barnstar between the words &quot;Flight&quot; &amp; &quot;Instruction&quot; in the middle line. Each point of the barnstar was two colors, light one half, dark on the other. The barnstar was to be emblematic of the North Star, which in the Arctic sky shines almost directly overhead. The company founders named the airplane the Northstar, and had originally considered naming their company North Star Airlines, but instead chose Star Air Service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

The company's second airplane, the Curtiss Robin, had a different three line identification painted on the side of the airplane: &quot;STAR&quot; in very large letters, the second line &quot;AIR SERVICE INC.&quot;, and the third line &quot;ANCHORAGE ALASKA&quot;, with no barnstar.

[[Image:Star Air Service LogoA.jpg|left|thumb|Star Air Service Logo]]
During the 1937 to 1942 Star Air Lines era, the fleet of Bellanca airplanes were all painted orange, with a large barnstar painted on the side of the airplanes. Each point in the barnstar was two colors, light brown on one half and black on the other. The star was within a black border which circled the star, with the interior the same orange color as the rest of the airplane.

When the company was sold and renamed Alaska Star Airlines, a new logo was adopted with several variations. The new logo contained a symbol of the north star directly over a partial image of the world.

==Routes and destinations==

In 1942, the CAB granted Star temporary certificates for the following routes:&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;
{{columns-list|2|&lt;!-- column start --&gt;
* Anchorage - [[McGrath, Alaska|McGrath]]
* Anchorage - [[Pilot Point, Alaska|Pilot Point]]
* Fairbanks - McGrath
* Anchorage - [[Seward, Alaska|Seward]]
* Anchorage - Fairbanks
* Anchorage - [[Seldovia, Alaska|Seldovia]]
* McGrath - [[Bethel, Alaska|Bethel]]
* McGrath - [[Ruby, Alaska|Ruby]]
* All points east of the [[Yukon River]], south of [[64th parallel north|64th parallel]] latitude, and west of [[Prince William Sound]]
}}&lt;!-- Column End --&gt;
Star acquired a certificate for a Nome - Fairbanks route with the purchase of Mirow Air Service in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

It would not be until 1951, after the company had become Alaska Airlines, that a certificate would be granted for a route between Anchorage - Fairbanks - Seattle - [[Portland, Oregon|Portland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;

==Pilots==

The bush pilots who flew in the 1930s were a most important element in the development of air services in Alaska, and indeed in the development of Alaska itself. They flew single engine aircraft all over the Territory, with no weather reports, no navigation aides, no radios in aircraft, not even good maps, and there were very few landing fields.  The pilots took the risks and their contributions to the inhabitants of Alaska were of enormous importance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;/&gt; The bush pilots who flew for Star Air Service, Star Air Lines and Alaska Star Airlines were:
{{columns-list|2|&lt;!-- column start --&gt;
* Roy S. Dickson (1901–1958)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=McLaren and Dickson|year=2009|title=Roy Dickson 1930s Alaska Bush Pilot|publisher=Plane Truth Press, Nashville, Tennessee|isbn=978-1-932-496-72-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Don Emmons (d.1959)&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Jack Elliott&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Don Glass (d.1943)&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Don H. Goodman (b.1909)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Gordon MacKenzie (1894–1963)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Steven E. &quot;Steve&quot; Mills (1896–1936)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* John W. &quot;Johnny&quot; Moore (1907–1988)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Kenneth W. &quot;Kenny&quot; Neece (1903–1944)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Raymond I. &quot;Ray&quot; Petersen (1912–2008)&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Charles H. &quot;Charlie&quot; Ruttan (d.1994)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Murrell Sasseen (1906–1974)&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Ralph Savory&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Dan Victor (1901–1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* John E. &quot;Jack&quot; Waterworth (1906–1969)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
* Oscar Winchell (1903–1987)&lt;ref name=&quot;Bagoy Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;/&gt;
}}&lt;!-- Column End --&gt;

==Aircraft==
		
{{columns-list|2|&lt;!-- column start --&gt;
* Bach T-11P Air Yacht NC219H&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Ed Coates Airline Collection|url=http://www.edcoatescollection.com/ac3/Airline/ALIndex.html|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Airline Aircraft Index &amp; Pictures}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Beech F-17-D StaggerWing NC20797 (ser# 332)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Civil Aircraft Registration|url=http://www.goldenyears.ukf.net/home.htm|accessdate=2009-08-23|work=Civil Aircraft Registration|publisher=Golden Years of Aviation}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AK Digital Archives&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=University of Alaska Digital Archives|url=http://vilda.alaska.edu/cdm4/results.php?CISOOP1=any&amp;CISOFIELD1=CISOSEARCHALL&amp;CISOROOT=/cdmg11&amp;CISOBOX1=Tony&amp;CISOSTART=1,31|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Historic Pictures|publisher=Alaska Virtual Library &amp; Digital Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Beech F-17-D StaggerWing NC19473 (ser# 245)&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Lars Opland Aviation Pictures|url=http://www.ruudleeuw.com/others-opland.htm|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Aviation Picture Collection|publisher=Ruud Leeuw}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC168N (ser# 175)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC251M (ser# 154)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Lars Opland Aviation Pictures|url=http://www.ruudleeuw.com/others-opland.htm|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Aviation Picture Collection|publisher=Ruud Leeuw}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC258M (ser# 160)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC259M  (ser# 161)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC690E (ser# 140)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-400 Skyrocket NC779W (ser# 617)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Lars Opland Aviation Pictures|url=http://www.ruudleeuw.com/others-opland.htm|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Aviation Picture Collection|publisher=Ruud Leeuw}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Bellanca CH-400 Skyrocket NC781W (ser# 619)&lt;ref name=&quot;Dickson Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-300 Pacemaker NC10365 (ser# 187)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca CH-400 Skyrocket NC10795 (ser# 622) &lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Bellanca Skyrocket F-2 NC2608 (ser# 802) &lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Lars Opland Aviation Pictures|url=http://www.ruudleeuw.com/others-opland.htm|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Aviation Picture Collection|publisher=Ruud Leeuw}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Cessna C-34 NC17054 (ser# 337) &lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Consolidated Vultee V1-AD NC14252 (ser# 18)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AK Digital Archives&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
* Curtiss Robin C-1 NC387K  (ser# 546) &lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Fairchild 100A Pilgrim&gt;100B NC709Y (ser# 6605)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AAHM Flightline&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Alaska Aviation Heritage Museum|url=http://www.alaskaairmuseum.org/explore/flightline.htm|accessdate=2009-09-12|work=Alaska Aviation History|publisher=Alaska Aviation Heritage Museum}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fairchild 100B Pilgrim NC740N (ser# 6704)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Fairchild 24W-9 NC22031 (ser# W9-204)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Fleet 7 Deluxe B-5 NC786V (ser# 367)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Ford 5-AT-C NC8410 (ser# 5-AT-48) Trimotor&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Ford 5-AT-C NC8419 (ser# 5-AT-58)  Trimotor&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Ford 5-AAT-B NC9651 (ser# 5-AT-34) Trimotor&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AK Digital Archives&quot;/&gt;
* Lockheed Lodestar NC21707&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;
* Lockheed Orion 9D NC230Y (ser# 201)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
* Lockheed Orion 9D&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;
* Lockheed Vega 5B NC162W (NC139N)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Davis-Monthan&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Davis-Monthan Aviation Field Register|url=http://www.dmairfield.com/airplanes/NC162W/index.html|accessdate=2009-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Stinson A NC15154 (ser# 9114)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC211W Stinson SM-8A (ser# 4038)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC216W Stinson SM-7A (ser# 3002)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC404M Stinson SM-1F (ser# M420)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC443M Stinson S Junior (ser# 8104)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC448H Stinson SM-1E (ser# M517)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC478M Stinson S Junior (ser# 8105)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson S Junior NC8445 (ser# 8007)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC10828 Stinson S Junior (serial# 8011)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson S Junior NC10831 (ser# 8026)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson NC13849 Stinson SR-5 (ser# 9220)&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson tri-motor NC15109 (ser# 9109)&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Stinson A NC16110 (ser# 9129)&lt;ref name=&quot;Alaska Airlines Story&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ed Coates collection&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aircraft Registration&quot;/&gt;
* Waco ZGC-7 NC17712 (ser# 4565)&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Lars Opland Aviation Pictures|url=http://www.ruudleeuw.com/others-opland.htm|accessdate=2009-10-10|work=Aviation Picture Collection|publisher=Ruud Leeuw}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Waco ZGC-7 NC17454 (ser# 4550)&lt;ref name=&quot;Opland&quot;/&gt;
}}&lt;!-- column end --&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
*Anchorage Centennial Commission Aviation Committee, &quot;Honoring 100 Alaska Bush Pilots&quot;. [[Anchorage, Alaska]], June 24, 1967
*Archie Satterfield, &quot;The Alaska Airlines Story&quot;. Alaska Northwest Publishing Company, [[Anchorage, Alaska]], 1981. ISBN 0-88240-165-3
*John P. Bagoy, &quot;Legends &amp; Legacies, Anchorage 1910-1935&quot;. 2001, ISBN 1-888125-91-8
*Robert W. Stevens, &quot;Alaskan Aviation History&quot;, Polynyas Press, [[Des Moines, Washington]], 1989, ISBN 0929427017
*McLaren &amp; Dickson, &quot;Roy Dickson 1930s Alaska Bush Pilot&quot;, Plane Truth Publishing, [[Nashville, Tennessee]], 2009. ISBN 978-1-932-496-72-7
* Satterfield, Archie (1981). &quot;The Alaska Airlines Story&quot;, Alaska Northwest Publishing Company, Anchorage, Alaska. ISBN 0-88240-165-3

==Further reading==
* International Directory of Company Histories, Vol. 29. St. James Press, 1999.
* Alaska Airlines: General Information and History, Seattle: Alaska Airlines, 1992.
* Alaska Airlines, Archie Satterfield (1981). The Alaska Airlines Story. (Anchorage, AK: Alaska Northwest Pub. Co., 207 p.). Alaska Airlines—History. ISBN 978-0882401645
* Robert J. Serling, Character &amp; Characters: The Spirit of Alaska Airlines (Seattle: Documentary Media LLC, 2008), 492 pp., hardback, ISBN 978-1-933245-11-9
* Robert W. Stevens D.D.L. (1989). Alaskan Aviation History. (Des Moines, IA: Polynyas Press, 1095 pp., hardback 2 volume set). ISBN 0929427017
* Pat Wachel (1967). Oscar Winchell Alaska’s Flying Cowboy. (Minneapolis, MN: T.S. Denison &amp; Company, Inc., 210 pp., hardback). ASIN B0006BQWQE
* Stephen E. Mills &amp; James Phillips (1969). Sourdough Sky. (Superior Publishing). ISBN 0875648568

==External links==
* [http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-33472536_ITM A diamond in the sky: Alaska Airlines celebrates 75 years of service above the clouds.], Alaska Business Monthly
* [http://www.alaskasworld.com/75thPortal/triviaAnswers.html Alaska Airlines 75th Anniversary Web Site], Alaska's World
* [http://www.alaskabushpilot.org/index.html  Roy Dickson 1930s Alaska Bush Pilot]
* [http://www.alaskaairmuseum.org/  Alaska Aviation Heritage Museum]
* [http://www.kipnotes.com/Airlines.htm AIRLINES - Business History of Carriers],  Kipnotes
* [http://www.kipnotes.com/What%27sNew.htm Alaska Air – 75th Anniversary, January 1932],  Kipnotes
* [http://www.aerofiles.com/airlines-am.html Airlines of North America]
* [http://vilda.alaska.edu/cdm4/results.php?CISOOP1=all&amp;CISOBOX1=star+air+service&amp;CISOFIELD1=CISOSEARCHALL&amp;CISOROOT=all Alaska's Digital Archives]

{{Alaska Airlines}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Star Air Service}}
[[Category:Airlines in Alaska]]
[[Category:Defunct airlines of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies based in Anchorage, Alaska]]
[[Category:Airlines established in 1932]]
[[Category:Airlines disestablished in 1944]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
