<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Closed format" to="Proprietary format" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="4404787" ns="0" title="Proprietary format"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">A '''proprietary format''' is a [[file format]] where the mode of presentation of its data is the [[intellectual property]] of an individual or organization which asserts ownership over the format.  In contrast, a [[free_software|free format]] is a format that is either not recognized as [[intellectual property]], or has had all claimants to its intellectual property release claims of ownership.  Proprietary formats can be either [[open format|open]] if they are published, or closed, if they are considered trade secrets.  In contrast, a [[free_software|free format]] is never closed.  

Proprietary formats are typically controlled by a private person or organization for the benefit of its applications, protected with [[patent]]s or as [[trade secret]]s, and intended to give the license holder exclusive control of the technology to the (current or future) exclusion of others.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/proprietary |title=Mirriam-Webster's Online Dictionary |accessdate=2008-07-11 |author= |date= |work= |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Typically such restrictions attempt to prevent [[reverse engineering]], though reverse engineering of file formats for the purposes of [[interoperability]] is generally believed to be legal by those who practice it. Legal positions differ according to each country's laws related to, among other things, [[software patent]]s.

==Privacy, ownership, risk and freedom== 
One of the contentious issues surrounding the use of proprietary formats is that of ownership of created content.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}} If the information is stored in a way which the user's software provider tries to keep secret, the user may ''own'' the information by virtue of having created it, but they have no way to retrieve it except by using a version of the original software which produced the file. Without a standard file format or [[reverse engineered]] converters, users cannot share data with people using competing software. The fact that the user depends on a particular brand of software to retrieve the information stored in a proprietary format files increases barriers of entry for competing software and may contribute to [[vendor lock-in]] concept.

The issue of risk comes about because proprietary formats are less likely to be publicly documented and therefore less future proof.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalpreservation.gov/formats/sustain/sustain.shtml#disclosure |title=&quot;Sustainability&quot; Digital Preservation |accessdate=2008-07-08 |author= |date= |work= |publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; If the software firm owning right to that format stops making software which can read it then those who had used the format in the past may lose all information in those files. This is particularly common with formats that were not widely adopted. However, even ubiquitous formats such as [[Microsoft Word]] can not be fully reverse-engineered.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

==Prominent proprietary formats==
In alphabetical order: 

===Open Proprietary Formats===
* [[AAC]] — an open standard, but owned by Via Licensing &lt;ref name=&quot;AAC&quot;&gt;[http://www.vialicensing.com/aac_licensefee.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[GEDCOM]] — an open specification for [[genealogy]] data exchange, owned by [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]]
* [[MP3]] — an open standard, but subject to patents in some countries &lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ubuntu's commitment to only include completely free software by default means that proprietary media formats are not configured 'out of the box'...including DVD, MP3, Quicktime, Windows Media, and more.&quot; https://help.ubuntu.com/community/RestrictedFormats. See also http://www.openformats.org/en5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Closed Proprietary Formats===
* [[CorelDraw#CDR file format|CDR]] — (non-documented) CorelDraw's native format primarily used for vector graphic drawings
* [[.dwg|DWG]] — (non-documented) [[AutoCAD]] drawing
* [[Adobe Photoshop#Features|PSD]] — (non-documented) [[Adobe Photoshop]]'s native image format
* [[RAR]] — (partially documented) archive and compression file format owned by Alexander L. Roshal&lt;ref&gt;The RAR Archiver EULA (End user license agreement) is embedded in installation files - [http://www.rarlabs.com/download.htm] - Quotation: &quot;''Neither RAR binary code, WinRAR binary code, UnRAR source or UnRAR binary code may be used or reverse engineered to re-create the RAR compression algorithm, which is proprietary, without written permission of the author.''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Windows Media Audio|WMA]] — a closed format, owned by [[Microsoft]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WMA&quot;&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windowsmedia/licensing/final.aspx#WindowsMediaAudioStandardVersion_Final]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controversial===
* [[DOC (computing)|DOC]] — Microsoft Word Document (formerly closed/undocumented, now [[Microsoft Open Specification Promise]])
* [[Microsoft Excel file format|XLS]] — Microsoft Excel spreadsheet file format (formerly closed/undocumented, now [[Microsoft Open Specification Promise]])
* [[Microsoft_PowerPoint#File_formats|PPT]] — Microsoft PowerPoint Presentation file format (formerly closed/undocumented, now [[Microsoft Open Specification Promise]])
* [[Rich Text Format|RTF]] — a formatted text format (proprietary&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://accessproject.colostate.edu/udl/modules/word/tut_rtf.cfm |title=tutorial: Rich Text Format (RTF) |publisher=Colorado State University |accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;e-gov-uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://archive.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/e-government/resources/handbook/html/4-3.asp |title=4.3 Non-HTML file formats |publisher=e-Government Unit |date=2002-05 |accessdate=2010-03-13}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.novell.com/news/press/archive/2004/11/complaint.pdf |format=PDF |title=Novell Files WordPerfect Antitrust Lawsuit against Microsoft |author=Novell |date=2004-11-12 |accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gl.scofacts.org/gl-20041115214025458.html |title=The Novell Antitrust Complaint (as text) &amp; A Law About Antitrust and Standards Writing |publisher= |date=2004-11-17 |accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;, published specification, defined and maintained only by Microsoft)
* [[SWF]] — Adobe Flash format (formerly closed/undocumented, now partially or completely open)
* [[XFA]] — Adobe XML Forms Architecture, used in PDF files (published specification, but not included in the PDF ISO 32000-1 standard; controlled and maintained only by Adobe&lt;ref name=&quot;gnupdf-fdf&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gnupdf.org/Forms_Data_Format |title=Gnu PDF - PDF Knowledge - Forms Data Format |quote=&quot;Apparently Adobe introduced something newer called XFA (XML Forms Architecture) which doesn't seem standardized.&quot; |accessdate=2010-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;acroforms-appligent&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.appligent.com/files/faq-whatisthedifferencebetweenacroformaxfa/Acroforms%2BWhitePaper.pdf |title=A Quick Introduction to Acrobat Forms Technology |quote=&quot;Adobe's XFA Forms is a closed standard that competes with the fully open W3C Xforms standard.&quot; |date=2006-05-14 |accessdate=2010-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* [[ZIP (file format)|ZIP]] — a base version of this data compression and archive file format is in the [[public domain]], but newer versions have some patented features&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pkware.com/support/zip-app-note |title=.ZIP Application Note |accessdate=2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://orcmid.com/blog/2007/02/latest-oox-odf-fud-spat-states-prepare.asp |title= Latest OOX-ODF FUD-Spat: States Prepare to Ban Zip and PDF Files |accessdate=2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://brianlivingston.com/eweek/article2/0,4149,1257562,00.html |title=PKZip Must Open Up  |accessdate=2010-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Formerly proprietary===
* [[Graphics Interchange Format|GIF]] — CompuServe's Graphics Interchange Format (open since 2004)
* [[Portable Document Format|PDF]] — Adobe's Portable Document Format (open since 2008), but the specification allows some proprietary extensions

==See also==
* [[Open format]]

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Software-stub}}
[[Category:Computer file formats]]

[[es:Formato propietario]]
[[fr:Format propriétaire]]
[[it:Formato proprietario]]
[[pl:Format zamknięty]]
[[pt:Formato proprietário]]
[[sk:Proprietárny formát]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
