<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24373365" ns="0" title="Hawaii Democratic Revolution of 1954"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=November 2009}}
{{Refimprove|date=November 2009}}

{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = Hawaii Democratic Revolution of 1954
  |Image_Name     = Kekaha sugar mill.jpg
  |Imagesize      = 
  |Image_Alt      = 
  |Image_Caption  = [[Kekaha, Hawaii|Kekaha]] sugar mill once owned by [[Amfac, Inc.]], one of the [[Big Five (Hawaii)|Big Five]].
  |Thumb_Time     = 
  |AKA            = 
  |Participants   = 
'''People'''&lt;br /&gt;
*[[John A. Burns]]
*[[Jack Wayne Hall|Jack W. Hall]]
*[[Daniel Inouye]]
*[[William S. Richardson]]
*[[Jack Kawano]]
*[[Charles Fujimoto]]
'''Parties'''&lt;br /&gt;
*[[Democratic Party of Hawaii]]
*[[Communist Party of Hawaii]]
'''Other'''
*former [[442nd Infantry Regiment|442nd Regiment]]
*[[ILWU]]
*[[Sugar plantations in Hawaii#Importing labor|Sugar Plantation Workers]]
*[[Territory of Hawaii#Pineapple|Pineapple Plantation Workers]]
  |Location       = [[Hawaii|Hawaiian Islands]]
  |Date           = September 1, 1946 - June 6, 1958
  |Result         = overthrow of [[White people|white]] [[minority rule]]. 
*[[State of Hawaii]] established.
*Improved [[working conditions]] and [[standard of living]].
*[[Big Five (Hawaii)|Big Five]] lose political and economic control of Hawaii.
*[[Democratic Party of Hawaii|Democrats]] become [[Dominant-party system|dominant party]].
*[[Hawaii Republican Party|Republicans]] become minority party.
  |URL            = 
}}

{{Campaignbox Democratic Revolution of 1954}}

The '''Hawaii Democratic Revolution of 1954''' was a [[nonviolent revolution]] that took place in the [[Hawaii|Hawaiian Archipelago]] consisting of [[general strikes]], [[protests]], and other acts of [[civil disobedience]]. The Revolution culminated in the territorial elections of 1954 where the reign of the [[Hawaii Republican Party]] in the legislature came to an abrupt end, as they were voted out of office to be replaced by members of the [[Democratic Party of Hawaii]]. The strikes by the Isles' labor workers demanded similar pay and benefits to their [[Contiguous United States|Mainland]] counterparts. The strikes also crippled the power of the [[Sugar plantations in Hawaii|sugar plantations]] and the [[Big Five (Hawaii)|Big Five Oligopoly]] over their workers.

==Prelude==
[[Image:Filling sugar sacks, Hawaii.jpg.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Asian plantation workers filling bags of sugar during the 1910s.]]

Historically Hawaii has had a [[dominant-party system]] since the 1887 revolution. The 1887 [[Bayonet Constitution]] took most of the power away from the monarchy and allowed the [[Hawaii Republican Party|Republican Party]] to dominate the legislature. Beside a brief change of power to the [[Home Rule Party of Hawaii|Home Rule Party]] following annexation, the Republicans had run the [[Territory of Hawaii]]. The [[industrialism|industrialist]] Republicans formed a powerful sugar oligarchy, the [[Big Five (Hawaii)|Big Five]].

During the controversial [[Massie Trial|Kahahawai murder and trial]] Republicans displayed their power by reducing the 10-year sentence for [[manslaughter]] to one hour. Many felt the trial was failure of justice from political forces. But this was not the only case of the government’s abuse of power; past misdeeds were mainly centered around economic gain. Among the unhappy residents of Hawaii was [[John A. Burns]], a police officer during the trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stannard|2006|p=415}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Burns founded a movement by collecting support from the impoverished sugar plantation workers. He also restored strength to the divided and weak Democratic Party of Hawaii.

==ILWU==
[[Image:ILWU logo.png|thumb|100px|left|ILWU logo.]]

The [[Hilo Longshoremen]] led by [[Jack Kawano]] began unified [[Strike action|strikes]] in the 1930s. The Hilo Longshoremen merged with the [[ILWU]], and [[Jack Wayne Hall]] was sent to Hawaii. Among these unified strikes was the disastrous [[Hilo Massacre|1938 strike in Hilo]] against the [[Inter-Island Steamship Company]]. During [[World War II]] striking was put on hold as the members dedicated their efforts towards the war. In 1944 the ILWU and [[Communist Party of Hawaii]] put their support behind the Democratic Party, since it became apparent that Burns and his movement wanted to empower the [[working class]]. This meeting in 1944 has been considered the beginning of the movement. The movement became known as the &quot;Burns Machine&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Niiya|1993|p=415}}&lt;/ref&gt; Burns admitted in 1975 that Communist Party members in the ILWU provided vital experience in maintaining secrecy and organizing support among labor workers while keeping the early movement underground.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Boylan|Holmes|2000|p=104}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Plantations==
[[Image:'Japanese Laborers on Spreckelsville Plantation', oil on canvas painting by Joseph Dwight Strong, 1885, private collection.jpg|thumb|300px|left|Japanese laborers on [[Maui]] harvesting [[sugar cane]] in 1885.]]

After the [[overthrow of the Hawaiian Monarchy]] by the [[Legislature of the Hawaiian Kingdom|legislature]] the members were not restrained in [[industrializing]] the Islands, forming plantations and the Big Five. [[Economic inequality]] increased, largely cause by the hyper-concentration of wealth among the capitalist industrialists. On the plantations earlier strikes had failed, as when an ethnic camp went on strike the other ethnic groups' camps acted as [[strikebreakers]]; the traditional example was the Japanese and [[Filipino people|Filipino]] camps' rivalry. The next generation of workers were children of the immigrant workers, born in Hawaii: ''[[Nisei]]s'', were a major demographic factor in favor of the movement. Many immigrant workers were denied citizenship but could live and work in the islands [[Indentured servant|under contract]]. The children of these workers who were born in Hawaii [[Birthright citizenship in the United States of America|could become citizens]] and at this time they began to come of age to be registered voters and could express their dissatisfaction in their votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Cooper|Daws|1990|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the meeting in 1944 Jack Hall began organizing these plantation workers in a strike campaign known as the March Inland for better working conditions and pay.

==Post-war and 442nd==
After the war, Burns was able to gain support from [[Japanese-American]] veterans of the [[100th Infantry Battalion (United States)|100th]] and [[442nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|442nd]] returning home.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Boylan|Holmes|2000|p=66}}&lt;/ref&gt; He encouraged the veterans to become educated under the [[G.I. Bill]] and run for public office. [[Daniel Inouye]] is considered the first of the veterans recruited and was a prominent member of the movement.

==March Inland==
Hall and Kawano's strikes resumed after the war. The ILWU helped to organize the plantation workers spreading [[unionization]] from the sea to the land. This allowed the movement to organize [[general strike]]s in the [[Sugar plantations in Hawaii|sugar industry]] and [[Territory of Hawaii#Pineapple|pineapple industry]], not just strikes at the docks. The [[Great Hawaii Sugar Strike of 1946]] was launched against the [[Hawaiian Sugar Planters' Association]] and the Big Five leaving the cane fields derelict. The [[1947 Pineapple Strike]] followed on [[Lanai]] but ended in failure and was tried again in 1951. The [[1949 Hawaiian Dock Strike]] froze shipping in Hawaii for 177 days, ended with the territorial [[Dock Seizure Act]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Holmes|1994|p=148}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hawaiians==
Hawaiians were on both sides of the Revolution; they were at the time in a social limbo in having less power and rights than the Whites but more than the Orientals living in Hawaii. {{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} Older Hawaiians tended to fear change would further decline the status of Hawaiians, while youths embraced the prospect of gain by ousting the status quo.

==House Un-American Activities Committee==
As the movement developed the more [[communist]] components began to show through. The strikes were increasingly politicized and at the 1949 strike the White Republican aristocracy who were owners in the Big Five became concerned over the communist trend by workers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Holmes|1994|p=142}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 7, after the 1949 dock strike that year, the territorial legislature requested the [[House Un-American Activities Committee]] to investigate the strikes that had become frequent in the territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Holmes|1994|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt; On August 28, 1951 the FBI rounded up seven members of the movement&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Holmes|1994|p=190}}&lt;/ref&gt; including [[Jack Hall]], [[Charles Fujimoto]] chairman of the Communist Party of Hawaii, and [[Koji Ariyoshi]] editor of the [[Honolulu Record]] who had also published pro-communist work. The Hawaii 7 were charged under the [[Smith Act]] for conspiring to overthrow the government; all were released by 1958.

==1950 elections==
In the 1950 Democratic Convention [[John A. Burns]] was elected chairman of the convention decided that the Party was ready for a strong push at the 1950 elections. But with the progress the party was dividing into two factions: the right-wing &quot;Walkout&quot; who opposed Burns and the left-wing &quot;Standpat&quot; members who supported Burns. Among the Standpats was [[John H. Wilson (mayor of Honolulu)|John H. Wilson]], the founder of the Democratic Party of Hawaii himself, although he did not always agree with Burns, allied with him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Boylan|Holmes|2000|p=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the fracture of the conservative members the party began to slide farther leftward. Burns wished to re-establish the party ideology as [[Centre-left|Center-Left]]. He had Party members sign an affidavit pledging their loyalty to the Democratic Party and not the Communist Party, to deflect communist criticisms and keep the [[far left]] in check.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Boylan|Holmes|2000|p=96}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this time communists refrained from discussing their ideology.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Holmes|1994|p=215}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rivalry between the two halves of the Democratic Party lead to several defeats in the elections against the Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Boylan|Holmes|2000|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==1954 elections==
Leading up to the 1954 elections the Walkout faction had collapsed into smaller factions proving no threat to the Standpat faction who effectively took over the party. So during the 1954 territorial elections the Democrats took 11 seats in the legislature seating a total of 22 while Republicans had 8.

==Government reform==
The Democrats began to reform the government installing a [[progressive tax]], land reform, environmental protections, comprehensive health insurance plan, and expanded freedoms of collective bargaining.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Arnesen|2006|p=575}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Republican political offensive==
President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] appointed Republican [[Samuel Wilder King]] as governor. King acted as an [[obstructionist]] by using the veto 71 times during his administration. Burns commented that these times the Democrats were more focused on building the Democratic government rather than running it. Following Statehood, Burns - who, until then, had lost his elections - was elected Governor of Hawaii. The strike campaign by the ILWU continued until 1958 when another large sugar strike called the [[Aloha Strike]] took place from February 1 to June 6 and ended the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Beechert|1985|p=329}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Statehood==
{{Main|Hawaii Admission Act}}
[[Image:Hawaiivotesinset.JPG|thumb|250px|right|Copy of official ballot (inset) and referendum results approving Admission Act.]]
Statehood for Hawaii was repeatedly failed until 1953 after passing the [[United States House of Representatives]], Hawaii became a serious candidate for statehood. Burns attempted to collaborate with [[Alaska]], which was also pressing to become a state. Burns came under scrutiny by [[anti-communist]] [[Southern Democrats]] over the role of the Communist Party. Another factor against statehood was a strong possibility of a [[non-white]] senator and their opposition to [[Racial segregation]]. Back in Hawaii a vote was taken showing that 93% of the population was in support of statehood. {{USPL|86|3}}, was enacted March 18, 1959 and took effect August 21, the [[State of Hawaii]] was established.

==Notable individuals of the movement==
*[[John A. Burns]]: Leader of the movement
*[[John H. Wilson (mayor of Honolulu)|John H. Wilson]]: Founder of the [[Democratic Party of Hawaii]].
*[[Daniel Inouye]]: Incumbent senior [[United States Senator]] from Hawaii and current [[President pro tempore of the United States Senate]].
*[[William S. Richardson]]: Former [[Supreme Court of Hawaii|Chief Justice]] of the Hawaii Supreme Court
*[[George Ariyoshi|George R Ariyoshi]]: Former [[Governor of Hawaii]].
*[[Thomas Gill (U.S. politician)|Thomas Gill]]: Former [[Lieutenant Governor of Hawaii|Lieutenant Governor]] and [[Hawaii's 1st congressional district|1st Congressman]].
*[[Spark Matsunaga]]: Former [[Hawaii's 1st congressional district|1st Congressman]]
*[[Patsy Mink]]: Former [[Hawaii's 2nd congressional district|2nd Congresswoman]]
*[[Koji Ariyoshi]]: Editor of the ''[[Honolulu Record]]'', and one of the [[Territory of Hawaii#Hawaii 7|Hawaii 7]].
*[[Frank Marshall Davis|Frank M. Davis]]: Columnist for the ''[[Honolulu Record]]'' and [[poet]].

== See also ==
*[[Democratic Party of Hawaii]]
*[[ILWU]]
*[[Communist Party of Hawaii]]
*[[Big Five (Hawaii)|Big Five]]
*[[Sugar plantations in Hawaii]]
*[[Territory of Hawaii#Hawaii 7|Hawaii 7]]
*[[Nonviolent resistance]]
*[[Civil disobedience]]
*[[Nonviolent revolution]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== Bibliography ==
*{{citation|last=Arnesen|first=Eric|title=Encyclopedia of US Labor and Working Class History|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis, Inc.|year=2006|isbn=9780415968263}}
*{{citation|last=Beechert|first=Edward D.|title=Working in Hawaii: A Labor History|publisher= University of Hawaii Press|year=1985|isbn=0824808908}}
*{{citation|last=Boylan|first=Dan|last2=Holmes|first2=T. Michael|title=John A. Burns|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|year=2000|isbn=9780824822774}}
*{{citation|last=Cooper|first=George|last2=Daws|first2=Gavan|title=Land and power in Hawaii|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|year=1990|Pages= 4|isbn=9780824813031}}
*{{citation|last=Holmes|first=Michael|title=The specter of Communism in Hawaii|publisher=University of Hawaii Press|year=1994|isbn=9780824815509}}
*{{citation|last=Niiya|first=Brian|title=Japanese American history|publisher=Facts on File Inc.|year=1993|isbn=9780816026807}}
*{{citation|last=Stannard|first=David E.|title=Honor Killing|publisher= Penguin|year=2006|isbn=9780143036630}}

{{Hawaii history}}

{{Overthrows in Hawaii}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hawaii Democratic Revolution Of 1954}}
[[Category:Territory of Hawaii|Democratic Revolution]]
[[Category:20th-century revolutions]]
[[Category:Politics of Hawaii]]
[[Category:Japanese-American history]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
