<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24396286" ns="0" title="Moira Barton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|image=[[File:Moira Barton.jpg|200px]]
|caption=
|name=Moira Barton
|portrayer=[[Natalie J. Robb]]
|years=2009—
|introducer=[[Gavin Blyth]]
|home=Butler's Farm
|occupation=Barmaid (2009—)
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present characters|Present; regular]]
|first= 17 July 2009
|husband=[[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]]
|sons=[[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]]
|daughters=[[Holly Barton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hannah Barton]]
}}
'''Moira Barton''' is a [[fictional character]] from the British [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'', played by [[Natalie J. Robb]]. She made her first on-screen appearance on 17 July 2009.

==Creation and casting==
In May 2009, it was announced that ''Emmerdale's'' new series producer, [[Gavin Blyth]], would be introducing a new farming family called the Bartons, as part of an ongoing overhaul of the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a156759/emmerdale-casts-sexy-farming-family.html|title='Emmerdale' casts 'sexy' farming family|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|last=Green|first=Kris|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The family, which consists of five members - a mother, father, two daughters and a son - took over the running of Butler's Farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt; Of the family, Blyth said &quot;I don't want to make ''Emmerdale'' a show about teenagers and young people, it's about family values. The Bartons are sexy, modern and contemporary. They're almost happy - and in soapland that's quite strange!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a159417/gavin-blyth-series-producer-emmerdale.html|title=Gavin Blyth (Series Producer, 'Emmerdale')|date=12 June 2009|first=Kris|last=Green|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]] was cast in the role of [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]] and [[Adam Thomas]], [[Sophie Powles]] and [[Grace Cassidy]] were cast as [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam]], [[Holly Barton|Holly]] and [[Hannah Barton|Hannah]] respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt;

Former ''[[The Bill]]'' actress [[Natalie J. Robb]] was cast in the role of John's wife, Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;YP&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.yorkshirepost.co.uk/news/around-yorkshire/local-stories/meet_the_bartons_emmerdale_s_new_dales_dynasty_1_2358825|title=Meet the Bartons - Emmerdale's new Dales dynasty|date=7 July 2009|work=[[Yorkshire Post]]|publisher=[[Yorkshire Post Newspapers]]|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robb said a call went through her agent asking her to audition for the role of Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lastbroadcast.co.uk/soaps/interviews/v/8804-natalie-j-robb-emmerdale-interview.html|title=Natalie J Robb (Emmerdale) Interview|publisher=Last Broadcast|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She auditioned with several different actors, including Thornton.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; Robb's agent later called to tell her she had won the role. Robb explained finding out she had won the part was one of the best bits of the job.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; The actress said she was looking forward to joining because the ''Emmerdale'' team, which she described as &quot;genuine and lovely.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; She added &quot;Cast and crew have been very welcoming and that always helps. There’s nothing better than being able to really look forward to going into work.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt;

==Development==
===Characterisation===
{{Quote|text=&quot;Moira is strong and feisty but always fair, with a huge heart and great compassion. She won’t take any nonsense from anyone, but has a great sense of fun and a vivacious nature. Although she has her own sense of pride, she’s more able to back down and eat humble pie than her husband, John. She's the glue that keeps her family strongly bonded together.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MoiraITV&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/moira-barton/|title=Moira Barton|publisher=[[itv.com]]|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;|sign=[[itv.com]] on Moira}}

Upon announcement of her casting, Moira was described as being a vivacious, fun woman, who puts her family first. Though she values her independence too.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt; The ''[[Yorkshire Post]]'' described Moria as &quot;Fun-loving and feisty&quot; and said she is guaranteed to cause a stir with the locals.&lt;ref name=&quot;YP&quot;/&gt; Of Moira, ''[[What's on TV]]'' said she is a &quot;farmer's wife and looking good on it, Moira Barton is a very down-to-earth woman - and that just adds to her appeal!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/moira-barton/777|title=Moira Barton|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robb said the idea of a modern day farming family drew her to the role of Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; She explained the family being a freshness to the Butler's Farm, saying &quot;The Barton’s are very lively and young-spirited and that really appealed to me. There are families out there that do work together and aren’t dysfunctional so the chance to represent one of those groups really drew me to the role.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;YP&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; Robb said her character is independent, fun-loving and strong.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; She loves her family and is very protective of them. Moira keeps them going and coordinates their lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt;

During an interview with ''[[Inside Soap]]'' Robb said she would probably not make a good farmer's wife, unlike Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;RealLife&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=1-7 October 2011|title=I couldn't be a farmer's wife in real life!|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|issue=39|page=49|accessdate=31 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robb said she is strong and loves animals, but could not send them to slaughter.&lt;ref name=&quot;RealLife&quot;/&gt; Moira finds employment as a barmaid at [[The Woolpack]] and Robb said she was looking forward to getting behind the bar and pulling a few pints.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt; The ''Yorkshire Post'' said her most volatile relationship will be with The Woolpack's chef [[Marlon Dingle]] ([[Mark Charnock]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;YP&quot;/&gt; Robb told the paper, &quot;Moira generally gets on with everybody. However, you'll see her and Marlon develop a love-hate relationship, which will be interesting.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;YP&quot;/&gt; Robb later thought Moira would warm to Marlon, in between their battles.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt;

===Marriage to John Barton===
Moira and her husband, John, were childhood sweethearts.&lt;ref name=&quot;MoiraITV&quot;/&gt; Robb said it was love at first sight for both Moira and John and they have a &quot;great chemistry&quot; together.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; The actress added &quot;Moira really finds him attractive, fancies him a lot and loves him deeply. They have a lot of affection for each other.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; Thornton said John and Moira had a lot of fun in their youth and there have often been hints about their party lifestyle.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/scoop/a220958/bonus-bits-from-emmerdales-john-and-moira.html|title=Bonus bits from 'Emmerdale's John and Moira|last=Green|first=Kris|date=21 May 2010|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=31 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When Marlon falls in love with Moira, she tells him she has not looked at another man during her twenty years of marriage to John.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; Robb thought Moira told Marlon that because she did not want to hurt him or cheat on John.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; Moira manages to maintain a good work and family balance because she has John's support. Together they make a strong team and do not take themselves seriously.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; John encourages Moira to have her independence, but to share her experiences with the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;LB&quot;/&gt; Thornton told Kris Green of [[Digital Spy]] that John and Moira are enough for each other. John knows Moira is the boss of the house and he respects that.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; He added that while no one knows much about the Barton's backstory, they do know John and Moira have a solid marriage. &lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; 

John kisses [[Eve Jenson]] ([[Suzanne Shaw]]) and Thornton said it is because he is flattered by her interest in him.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; Robb explained John is Moira's soulmate and even though she knows he looks at other woman, she did not think he would ever act upon it.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; Robb added &quot;Moira sensed it before it happened, which made it worse!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; When asked what kind of man it would take for Moira to cheat on John, Robb opined the man would have similar values to John and she thought Marlon wouuld be a safe bet as he is loyal and trustworthy.&lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt; Thornton said he is worried the writers are going to split John and Moira up and Robb said if the characters were to split, they would find it hard to live without each other. &lt;ref name=&quot;BonusBits&quot;/&gt;

===Cain Dingle===
{{Quote box |width=20% |align=right |bgcolor=#cccfff |quote=&quot;Moira just can't help herself. So she does it. The sex is amazing – the chemistry is so powerful it's electric and she can't control it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MuckyMoira&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.people.co.uk/celebs-tv/2011/10/23/mucky-moira-gets-down-and-dirty-with-emmerdale-bad-boy-cain-102039-23507126/|title=Mucky Moira gets down and dirty with Emmerdale bad boy Cain|last=Farhoud|first=Nada|date=23 October 2011|work=[[The People]]|publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;|source=—Robb on Moira's attraction to Cain (2011)}}
In October 2011, Moria begins an affair with [[Cain Dingle]] ([[Jeff Hordley]]). Cain has been interested in Moira for a while as he knows how much she loathes him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=22-28 October 2011|title=Cain seduces Moira!|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|first=Kate|last=White|issue=42|pages=8–9|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moria decides to purchase a Land Rover from Cain and agrees to pay him the money in weekly installments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Moira asks Cain to keep the arrangement from John, as their marriage is under a lot of strain and is quite fragile at that moment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Hordley told Laura Morgan of ''[[All About Soap]]'' that Cain sees the deal as his chance to have a bit of fun with Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;MadMan&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Morgan|first=Laura|date=15-28 October 2011|title=Mad man!|journal=[[All About Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|issue=255|page=30|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He explained &quot;Cain enjoys causing friction between her and John - he just doesn't care about offending anyone. Cain keeps toying with Moira, and he knows that she secretly wants him...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MadMan&quot;/&gt; When asked if Cain and Moria could be heading towards a full-blown affair, Hordley said he did not think so as Cain is still in love with [[Charity Tate]] ([[Emma Atkins]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;MadMan&quot;/&gt; The actor added Cain is just playing with Moira like a cat plays with a mouse.&lt;ref name=&quot;MadMan&quot;/&gt;

On 23 October, Nada Farhoud of ''[[The People]]'' reported the attraction between Moira and Cain was going to &quot;explode into ''Emmerdale's'' steamiest ever fling.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MuckyMoira&quot;/&gt; The affair starts after Cain tells John about his and Moira's arrangement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Moira goes to the garage to tell Cain off and they have a huge fight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Suddenly Moira kisses Cain and they have sex.&lt;ref name=&quot;MuckyMoira&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Of the scene, Robb said &quot;The director asked me to wear a crossover dress so my breasts look very voluptuous, perfect for a seduction scene. We ripped each other's tops off, he cleared everything off his fridge, picked me up and my legs were wrapped around him. We looked at each other and then went into a clinch.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MuckyMoira&quot;/&gt; The actress told Kate White of ''Inside Soap'' that her character does not like Cain, but that is part of the attraction for her. She cannot explain why she has a thing for him, but she cannot help herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Moira is left feeling dirty and guilty after the encounter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; However, she cannot help giving into temptation again and Robb revealed Moira does not want to go back to Cain and she tries to fight it when she does. Robb opined the relationship is quite abusive, but Cain brings out a different side to Moira.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Farhoud said Moira and Cain end up having sex in a barn and on a bed. The writer said the scenes are &quot;so hot&quot; the soap's film crew became embarrassed during filming.&lt;ref name=&quot;MuckyMoira&quot;/&gt; 

Of why her character puts her marriage in jeopardy, Robb explained &quot;She still loves John, but she feels isolated and neglected because he's stopped including her in the finances of the new business. He's changed the dynamic of their relationship.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallout&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a347254/emmerdale-star-natalie-j-robb-teases-moira-affair-fallout.html|title='Emmerdale' star Natalie J Robb teases Moira affair fallout|last=Kikelly|first=Daniel|date=24 October 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robb also said the way Cain treats Moira makes her realise what she has with John.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seduces&quot;/&gt; Cain later decides to tell John what has been going on between him and Moira and Robb said it is not going to be a good Christmas for the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallout&quot;/&gt;

==Storylines==
Moira and her family have taken over the farm from the [[Sugden family]]. They made their first appearance in July 2009, when she arrived with husband [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]], and children, [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam]], [[Holly Barton|Holly]] and [[Hannah Barton|Hannah]]. In August 2009, Moira Stood up for John when he faced prison for standing up against [[Aaron Livesy (Emmerdale)|Aaron Livesy]]. She also became concerned when her daughter Hannah started to show an interest in [[Andy Sugden]], who was recovering from a breakdown. Moira had heard from a number of local residents that Andy was dangerous, and was unsure of her daughter's safety. Moira jumped to conclusions after seeing Hannah crying after leaving Andy's, and argued with him. She had misunderstood the situation however, and later apologised to Andy. Moira began working as a barmaid in the Woolpack in September 2009, and frequently clashed with [[Marlon Dingle]]. Soon after Marlon began to develop feelings for Moira, however Moira did not feel the same way, and he read too much into her flirty nature. They both soon agreed though that it was wrong and that Marlon was still trying to get over his ex-wife [[Donna Windsor-Dingle]].

Moira continued to work in the Woolpack, making more friends as time went on and becoming a great staff member and confidant to land lady [[Diane Sugden]]. Soon though, Moira revealed her nasty side as after months of torment and bullying, her daughter Hannah revealed the wicked torture she had been enduring by [[Victoria Sugden]] and her friend Kayleigh, after confronting Victoria in the pub where the two families were having a meal together. However, Moira and Diane soon made up and continued to be good friends, with Hannah and Victoria also building bridges in their friendship.

When Edna Birch's granddaughter, [[Eve Jenson]], arrived in the village and started working for the Bartons as their farmhand, Eve's constant flirting with John  made Moira suspicious, but Eve reassured her that nothing was going on, even finding it amusing.  Although Moira began to dislike her new farmhand, she put Eve's flirting down to her personality and thought her husband couldn't cheat. John however kissed Eve in the back of his car and was spotted by [[Cain Dingle]]. Cain visited Moira in [[The Woolpack]] and told her what he had seen, but Moira refused to believe him and went home to confront John. When she got home she told John what Cain had told her and John confessed that he and Eve had kissed but said there was nothing to it and he loved Moira. Moira however told John if he could kiss her he might as well have slept with her and she told him to get out of the house.
After that however they reconciled [Moira and John] and continued to battle their eldest daughter, Holly's continual drug problem. A little later, Moira could not bear to see Holly suffering, so she bought heroin and supplied her daughter with it. She was caught and cautioned by the police.

Moira finds out about her son, Adam's affair with [[Ella Hart]], she demands Adam to finish with Ella, but they decide to carry on with the affair, since then Moira has given Ella a number of dirty looks and has told her to back off from Adam. Ella's husband [[Declan Macey]] discovers the affair and goes mad, Adam comes back home to John and Moria, which then Moira makes Adam come clean to John about the affair, John's not happy about this because it could affect the deal he has with Declan about the farm, but Adam ensures that the farm will be safe.

John and Moira's relationship becomes strained, especially when Cain reveals Moira is paying him in installments for a Land Rover. Moira goes to the garage to confront Cain, but she ends up having sex with him. Moria and Cain then begin an affair. Moira tells Diane she is having an affair with someone and Diane works out it is with Cain. Cain reveals the affair to John and he throws Moira out. She then goes to stay with her mother.

==Reception==
For her portrayal of Moira, Robb was nominated for &quot;Best Newcomer&quot; at the 2010 [[Inside Soap Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a242852/in-full-inside-soap-awards-2010-nominees.html|title=In Full: Inside Soap Awards 2010 Nominees|last=Wightman|first=Catriona|date=13 July 2010|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=4 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, Robb was shortlisted for &quot;Best Serial Drama Performance&quot; at the [[16th National Television Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/news/a277960/national-television-awards-2011-nominees.html|title=National Television Awards 2011 - Nominees|last=Wightman|first=Catriona|date=21 September 2010|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=5 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/moira-barton/ Character profile] at the Official UK ''Emmerdale'' website
* [http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/moira-barton/777 Character profile] at [[What's on TV]]
* [http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0160411/ Character profile] at the [[Internet Movie Database]]

{{Emmerdale characters|present}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barton, Moira}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional bartenders]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2009]]
[[Category:Fictional chefs]]
[[Category:Fictional farmers]]
[[Category:Fictional Scottish people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
