<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="243964" ns="0" title="Gtk-gnutella"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = gtk-gnutella
| logo                   = [[Image:Gtk-gnutella.svg|48px]]
| screenshot             = [[Image:Gtk-gnutella-0.96.8-stable.png|200px|gtk-gnutella 0.96.8]]
| caption                = gtk-gnutella 0.96.8 on [[Debian]] lenny
| developer              = Raphael Manfredi, Richard Eckart
| released               = 16 April 2000
| frequently_updated     = yes&lt;!-- Release version update? Don't edit this page, just click on the version number! --&gt;
| programming language   = [[C (programming language)|C]] ([[GTK+]])
| operating system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| language               = de el es fr hu it ja nb nl uk +
| genre                  = [[Peer-to-peer file sharing]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = http://gtk-gnutella.sourceforge.net/
}}
'''gtk-gnutella''' is a [[peer-to-peer file sharing]] application which runs on the [[gnutella]] network. gtk-gnutella uses the [[GTK+]] toolkit for its [[graphical user interface]]. Released under the [[GNU General Public License]], gtk-gnutella is [[free software]].

== History ==
Initially gtk-gnutella was written to look like the original [[Nullsoft]] Gnutella client. The original author Yann Grossel stopped working on the client in early 2001. After a while [[Raphael Manfredi]] took over as the main software architect, and the client has been in active development ever since. Versions released after July 2002 do not look like the original Nullsoft client.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gtk-gnutella.sourceforge.net/en/?page=shots090 | title = gtk-gnutella 0.90 screenshot| year = 2002 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Features ==
gtk-gnutella is programmed in [[C (programming language)|C]] with an emphasis on efficiency and portability without being minimalistic but rather head-on with most of the modern features of the gnutella network. Therefore, it requires less resources (such as [[Central processing unit|CPU]] and/or [[Random-access memory|RAM]]) than the major gnutella clients. It can also be used as [[headless system|headless]] gnutella client not requiring [[Gtk+]] at all.

gtk-gnutella has a filtering engine that can reduce the amount of spam and other irrelevant results. gtk-gnutella supports a large range of the features of modern gnutella clients.  gtk-gnutella was the first gnutella client to support [[IPv6]] and encryption using [[Transport Layer Security|TLS]]. It can handle and export [[magnet link]]s. It has strong [[internationalization]] features, supporting English, German, Greek, French, Hungarian, Spanish, Japanese, Norwegian, Dutch and Chinese. gtk-gnutella also has support to prevent [[Spam (electronic)|spamming]] and other hostile peer activity.

Several software distributions provide pre-compiled packages, but they are usually outdated as many distributions version freeze old stable releases. The gnutella network benefits from running the latest version obtainable as peer and hostile IP address lists change rapidly, making building the latest SVN snapshot the best option. There are also pre-compiled packages for many Linux distributions [http://stinker.serveftp.net:8000/gtkgnutella/gtkgnutella.html available online]. Persons concerned about security might wish to compile their own.  The gtk-gnutella sources use [[dist]] as build and configuration system instead of [[Autoconf]]. Most users are only familiar with the configure scripts generated by the latter.  Another hazard for novices is configuring [[Network address translation|NAT]] devices to enable full network connectivity for gtk-gnutella.  gtk-gnutella, like any gnutella client, is still usable behind a [[Firewall (computing)|firewall]] or a [[Router (computing)|router]], but with some reduced functionality, if it cannot receive incoming [[Transmission Control Protocol|TCP]] connections or [[User Datagram Protocol|UDP]] packets.  In an attempt to mitigate the issue for newcomers, gtk-gnutalla implements the [[UPnP]] and [[NAT-PMP]] client protocols.

gtk-gnutella supports features for downloading larger files (videos, programs, and disk images).  Version 0.96.4 supports [[Tiger tree]] hash serving and versions after 0.96.5 support tiger tree hashes for uploads and downloads.  Tiger tree hashing and other gtk-gnutella features make file transfers as efficient as [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]].  Specifically, gtk-gnutella supports partial file sharing,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://gtk-gnutella.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/gtk-gnutella/trunk/gtk-gnutella/doc/gnutella/PFSP | last = Klingberg  | first = Tor| title = Partial File Sharing Protocol| publisher = Tor Klingberg  | year = 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; remote queueing &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://gtk-gnutella.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/gtk-gnutella/trunk/gtk-gnutella/doc/gnutella/PARQ | last = Manfredi | first = Raphael | title = Passive/Active Remote Queueing| publisher = Raphael Manfredi| year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; and files larger than 4 [[GiB]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://gtk-gnutella.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/gtk-gnutella/trunk/gtk-gnutella/doc/public/GGEP/LF | title = The 'LF' GGEP Extension | year = 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Overlap checking was the only mechanism to guard against bad data prior to versions 0.96.4.  Overlap checking does not guard against malicious corruption like [[Tiger tree]] hashing does.

Version 0.96.6 introduced preliminary support for a [[Kademlia]] DHT, which was completed in version 0.96.7.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=https://gtk-gnutella.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/gtk-gnutella/trunk/gtk-gnutella/ChangeLog | title = gtk-gnutella ChangeLog}}&lt;/ref&gt;   The DHT is replacing search by [[SHA-1]], when locating alternate sources for a known file or looking for push-proxies.  In version 0.96.7, the DHT is enabled by default.  LimeWire first developed the DHT and named it [http://wiki.limewire.org/index.php?title=Mojito Mojito]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}.

Version 0.96.9 introduced full native support for [[UPnP]] and [[NAT-PMP]], making the usage behind a compatible router much easier since there is no longer any need to manually forward ports on the firewall.  In this version the code was also ported to [[Microsoft Windows]] however the Windows port is still considered beta due to lack of wide testing so far.

Version 0.96.9 also introduced important DHT protection against [[Sybil attack]]s, using algorithms based on statistical properties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://hal.inria.fr/docs/00/49/05/09/PDF/HotP2P10-KAD_DHT_attack_mitigation-cholez.pdf | title = Efficient DHT Attack Mitigation Through Peer's ID Distribution}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Version 0.97 was a major release, introducing client-side support for [[HTTP pipelining]], &quot;What's New?&quot; queries, [[Internet media type|MIME]] type query filtering, GUESS support (Gnutella UDP Extension for Scalable Searches) and partial file querying.  Although many Gnutella vendors already supported server-side GUESS, gtk-gnutella introduced the client-side as well, also enhancing the original specifications of the protocol to make it truly usable.

== Release history ==
&lt;!-- This section is not meant to be exhaustive.  Just to provide a list of current clients that may be seen on the gnutella network.  The entire release list is large. --&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float: right&quot;
! Version
! Date
|-
| 0.97
| 18 July 2011
|-
| 0.96.9
| 14 March 2011
|-
| 0.96.8
| 21 March 2010
|-
| 0.96.7
| 7 March 2010
|-
| 0.96.6
| 29 March 2009
|-
| 0.96.5
| 2 April 2008
|-
| 0.96.4
| 7 July 2007
|-
| 0.96.3
| 9 November 2006
|-
| 0.96.2
| 16 October 2006
|-
| 0.96.1
| 22 February 2006
|-
| 0.96
| 24 January 2006
|}

Every year, the gtk-gnutella developers release a new &quot;'''stable'''&quot; version. Revision control versions have a &quot;'''u'''&quot; appended to the version; the &quot;'''u'''&quot; standing for unstable. Unstable versions from [[Subversion (software)|SVN]] are outdated in 3 months. Stable releases become outdated after one year.

gtk-gnutella tracks other gtk-gnutella versions seen on the [[gnutella]] network. If newer versions are seen, the user is notified, but an update is not mandated. If ancient versions of gtk-gnutella are seen, they are treated suspiciously.

== Popularity ==
gtk-gnutella does not rank as one of the most popular clients on GnutellaNet crawls.  However, until 0.96.9 it was only released for Unix-like operating systems, which are about 10% of the general computing population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://marketshare.hitslink.com/os-market-share.aspx?qprid=9 OS Market share]&lt;/ref&gt;  gtk-gnutella developers' proposals have been incorporated into many gnutella clients.  gtk-gnutella vendor extensions are the third most prolific on the GDF, following Limewire and Bearshare.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gnet-specs.gnufu.net/index.php/Known_Vendor_Messages Gnutella vendor extensions]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://groups.yahoo.com/group/the_gdf/files/Proposals/Working%20Proposals/ Gnutella working proposals]&lt;/ref&gt;
Salon listed gtk-gnutella as one of the five most popular gnutella applications in 2002.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.salon.com/tech/feature/2002/08/08/gnutella_developers/print.html Salon lists gtk-gnutella as one of the top five gnutella clients. (2002)]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[XoloX]] and [[List of historical Gnutella clients|Toadnode]], also in the list, are no longer actively developed.

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== References ==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{ cite book | last = Wang | first = Wallace | title = Steal this file sharing book | year = 2004 | publisher = No Starch Press | location = San Francisco | isbn = 1-59327-050-X }}
* {{ cite web | url = http://www.linux-magazine.com/issue/01/Gnutella.pdf | last = Ganslandt | first = Björn | title = Distributed file sharing | publisher = Linux Magazine | year = 2000 | format = PDF | accessdate = 1 October 2000 }}
* {{ cite web | url = http://www.ics.forth.gr/dcs/Activities/papers/gdos.acns06.pdf | last = Athanasopoulos | first = Elias | title = Misusing Unstructured P2P Systems to Perform DoS Attacks: The Network That Never Forgets | publisher = Institute of Computer Science | year = 2006 | format = PDF }}
* {{ cite web | url = http://www.net.in.tum.de/~vinay/iadis06.pdf | last = Aggarwal | first = Vinay | title = Analysis of overlay-underlay topology correclation using visualization | publisher = Deutsche Telekom Laboratories | year = 2006 | format = PDF }}
* {{Cite web | url = http://www.cse.lehigh.edu/~brian/pubs/2004/www/ | last = Davison | first = Brian | title = Lessons from a Gnutella-Web Gateway | publisher = ACM Press | year = 2004 }}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [http://gtk-gnutella.sourceforge.net/ gtk-gnutella homepage]
* [[IRC]]: [irc://irc.freenode.net/#gtk-gnutella #gtk-gnutella] on [[freenode]]

{{Gnutella|Gnutella clients}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}
{{File sharing}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:gtk-gnutella}}
[[Category:GTK+]]
[[Category:Free file sharing software]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in C]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[de:gtk-gnutella]]
[[es:gtk-gnutella]]
[[it:gtk-gnutella]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
