<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="244374" ns="0" title="X86-64"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect2|AMD64|Intel 64|the Intel 64-bit architecture called IA-64|Itanium}}
{{lowercase|title=x86-64}}

'''x86-64''' is an extension of the [[x86|x86 instruction set]]. It supports vastly larger virtual and physical address spaces than are possible on x86, thereby allowing programmers to conveniently work with much larger data sets. x86-64 also provides [[64-bit]] general purpose registers and numerous other enhancements. The original specification was created by [[Advanced Micro Devices|AMD]], and has been implemented by AMD, [[Intel Corporation|Intel]], [[VIA Technologies|VIA]], and others. It is fully backwards compatible with [[32-bit]] code.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://support.amd.com/us/Embedded_TechDocs/24593.pdf
  |title       =Volume 2: System Programming
  |author      =AMD Corporation
  |month       =May
  |year        =2011
  |work        =AMD64 Architecture Programmer's Manual
  |publisher   =AMD Corporation
  |format      =pdf
  |accessdate  =2011-10-29
  }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|page=13}} Because the full 32-bit instruction set remains implemented in hardware without any intervening emulation, existing 32-bit x86 [[executable]]s run with no compatibility or performance penalties,&lt;ref name=&quot;x86-compat-perf&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=ftp://ftp.software.ibm.com/software/webserver/appserv/was/64bitPerf.pdf
  |title=IBM WebSphere Application Server 64-bit Performance Demystified
  |page=14
  |quote=&quot;Figures 5, 6 and 7 also show the 32-bit version of WAS runs applications at full native hardware performance on the POWER and x86-64 platforms. Unlike some 64-bit processor architectures, the POWER and x86-64 hardware does not emulate 32-bit mode. Therefore applications that do not benefit from 64-bit features can run with full performance on the 32-bit version of WebSphere running on the above mentioned 64-bit platforms.&quot;
  |author=IBM Corporation
  |date=2007-09-06
  |accessdate=2010-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
although existing applications that are recoded to take advantage of new features of the processor design may see significant performance increases.

After launching the architecture under the &quot;x86-64&quot; name, AMD renamed it '''AMD64''' in 2003;&lt;ref name=&quot;inq-amd64&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Rust|first=Adamson|title=AMD bans use of Hammer word, X86-64|url=http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/1043982/amd-bans-use-of-hammer-word-x86-64|work=The Inquirer|accessdate=2010-10-30 |date=2003-04-24 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Intel initially used the names '''IA-32e''' and '''EM64T''' before finally settling on '''Intel 64''' for their implementation. x86-64 is still used by many in the industry as a vendor-neutral term, while others, notably [[Sun Microsystems]]&lt;ref name=&quot;solaris-x64&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Solaris 10 on AMD Opteron|url=http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/server-storage/solaris/overview/solaris10amdopteron-jsp-140575.html|publisher=Oracle|accessdate=2010-12-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (now [[Oracle Corporation]]) and [[Microsoft]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ms-x64&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Microsoft 64-Bit Computing|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windowsserver2008/en/us/64bit-computing.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|accessdate=2010-12-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; use '''x64'''.

The [[AMD K8]] core was the first to implement the architecture; this was the first significant addition to the [[x86]] architecture designed by a company other than Intel. Intel was forced to follow suit and introduced a modified [[NetBurst (microarchitecture)|NetBurst]] family which was fully software-compatible with AMD's design and specification. [[VIA Technologies]] introduced x86-64 in their VIA Isaiah architecture, with the [[VIA Nano]].

The x86-64 specification is distinct from the Intel [[Itanium]] (formerly ''IA-64'') architecture, which is not compatible on the native instruction set level with the x86 architecture.

==AMD64==
[[File:AMD64 Logo.svg|thumb|150px|right|AMD64 logo]]
The AMD64 instruction set is implemented in AMD's [[Athlon 64]], [[Athlon 64|Athlon 64 FX]], [[Athlon 64 X2]], [[Athlon II]], [[Athlon 64 X2#Athlon X2|Athlon X2]], [[Opteron]], [[Phenom (processor)|Phenom]], [[Phenom II]], [[Turion 64]], [[Turion 64 X2]], and later [[Sempron]] processors.

===History of AMD64===
AMD64 was created as an alternative to the radically different [[Itanium#Architecture|IA-64]] architecture, which was designed by Intel and [[Hewlett Packard]].  Originally announced in 1999&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
| title = AMD Discloses New Technologies At Microporcessor Forum
| publisher = AMD
| date = 1999-10-05
| url=http://www.amd.com/us/press-releases/Pages/Press_Release_751.aspx
| accessdate = 2010-11-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a full specification in August 2000,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
 | title = AMD Releases x86-64 Architectural Specification; Enables Market Driven Migration to 64-Bit Computing
 | publisher = AMD
 |date=2000-08-10
 | url = http://www.amd.com/us/press-releases/Pages/Press_Release_715.aspx
 | accessdate = 2010-11-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; the architecture was positioned by AMD from the beginning as an evolutionary way to add 64-bit computing capabilities to the existing x86 architecture, as opposed to Intel's approach of creating an entirely new 64-bit architecture with IA-64.

The first AMD64-based processor, the [[Opteron]], was released in April 2003.

===Architectural features===
The primary defining characteristic of AMD64 is the availability of 64-bit general-purpose [[processor register]]s, e.g. rax, rbx etc., 64-bit [[Integer (computer science)|integer]] arithmetic and logical operations, and 64-bit [[Protected Virtual Address Mode|virtual addresses]]. The designers took the opportunity to make other improvements as well. The most significant changes include:

*'''64-bit integer capability:''' All general-purpose registers (GPRs) are expanded from 32&amp;nbsp;[[bit]]s to 64&amp;nbsp;bits, and all arithmetic and logical operations, memory-to-register and register-to-memory operations, etc., can now operate directly on 64-bit integers. [[Stack (data structure)|Pushes and pops]] on the [[Stack register|stack]] are always in 8-byte strides, and [[Pointer (computing)|pointers]] are 8 bytes wide.

*'''Additional registers:''' In addition to increasing the size of the general-purpose registers, the number of named general-purpose registers is increased from eight (i.e. eax, ebx, ecx, edx, ebp, esp, esi, edi) in x86 to 16 (i.e. rax, rbx, rcx, rdx, rbp, rsp, rsi, rdi, r8, r9, r10, r11, r12, r13, r14, r15). It is therefore possible to keep more local variables in registers rather than on the stack, and to let registers hold frequently accessed constants; arguments for small and fast subroutines may also be passed in registers to a greater extent. However, AMD64 still has fewer registers than many common [[RISC]] ISAs (which typically have 32&amp;ndash;64&amp;nbsp;registers) or [[VLIW]]-like machines such as the [[Itanium#Architecture|IA-64]] (which has 128&amp;nbsp;registers); note, however, that because of [[register renaming]] the number of physical registers is often much larger than the number of registers exposed by the instruction set.

*'''Additional XMM (SSE) registers:''' Similarly, the number of 128-bit XMM&lt;!-- don't confuse this name with MMX; MMX has no hardware registers and is mapped to the FPU stack. Here we talk about SSE (XMM) registers --&gt; registers (used for [[Streaming SIMD Extensions|Streaming SIMD]] instructions) is also increased from 8 to 16.

*'''Larger virtual address space:''' The AMD64 architecture defines a 64-bit virtual address format, of which the low-order 48 bits are used in current implementations.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=120}} This allows up to 256&amp;nbsp;[[Terabyte|TB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt; [[byte]]s) of virtual address space. The architecture definition allows this limit to be raised in future implementations to the full 64 bits,&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=2}}{{rp|page=3}}{{rp|page=13}}{{rp|page=117}}{{rp|page=120}} extending the virtual address space to 16&amp;nbsp;[[Exabyte|EB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;64&lt;/sup&gt; bytes). This is compared to just 4&amp;nbsp;[[Gigabyte|GB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;32&lt;/sup&gt; bytes) for the x86.&lt;ref name=&quot;intel-253668&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.intel.com/Assets/PDF/manual/253668.pdf
  |title=Intel 64 and IA-32 Architectures Software Developer’s Manual, Volume 3A: System Programming Guide, Part 1
  |accessdate=2010-05-29
  |format=pdf
  |pages=4–10}}&lt;/ref&gt; This means that very large files can be operated on by [[Memory-mapped file|mapping]] the entire file into the process' address space (which is often much faster than working with file read/write calls), rather than having to map regions of the file into and out of the address space.

*'''Larger physical address space:''' The original implementation of the AMD64 architecture implemented 40-bit physical addresses and so could address up to 1&amp;nbsp;TB (2&lt;sup&gt;40&lt;/sup&gt; bytes) of RAM.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=24}} Current implementations of the AMD64 architecture (starting from [[AMD K10|AMD 10h microarchitecture]]) &lt;!--- it's &quot;10h&quot;, as in 10 hex, not 10th as in tenth. Please see the reference named amd10h, immediately following. Please do not change this back to &quot;10th&quot; ---&gt;  extend this to 48-bit physical addresses&lt;ref name=&quot;amd10h&quot;&gt;{{cite web
  |url=http://www.amd.com/us-en/assets/content_type/white_papers_and_tech_docs/31116-Public-GH-BKDG_3.20_2-4-09.pdf
  |title=BIOS and Kernel Developer’s Guide (BKDG) For AMD Family 10h Processors
  |accessdate=2010-05-29
  |format=pdf
  |page=24
  |quote=Physical address space increased to 48 bits.}} {{Dead link|date=November 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt; and therefore can address up to 256&amp;nbsp;TB of RAM. The architecture permits extending this to 52 bits in the future&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=24}}&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
  |url=http://www.amd64.org/fileadmin/user_upload/pub/64bit_Linux-Myths_and_Facts.pdf
  |title=Myth and facts about 64-bit Linux
  |accessdate=2010-05-30
  |date=2008-03-02
  |format=pdf
  |page=7
  |quote=Physical address space increased to 48 bits}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (limited by the page table entry format);&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=131}} this would allow addressing of up to 4&amp;nbsp;[[Petabyte|PB]] of RAM. For comparison, 32-bit x86 processors are limited to 64&amp;nbsp;GB of RAM in [[Physical Address Extension]] (PAE) mode,&lt;ref name=&quot;shanley-ppro&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  |title=Pentium Pro and Pentium II System Architecture
  |edition=Second
  |last=Shanley |first=Tom
  |isbn=0-201-30973-4
  |series=PC System Architecture Series
  |year=1998
  |publisher=Addison-Wesley
  |page=445}}
&lt;/ref&gt; or 4&amp;nbsp;GB of RAM without PAE mode.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=4}}

*'''Larger physical address space in legacy mode:''' When operating in [[legacy mode]] the AMD64 architecture supports [[Physical Address Extension]] (PAE) mode, as do most current x86 processors, but AMD64 extends PAE from 36 bits to an architectural limit of 52 bits of physical address. Any implementation therefore allows the same physical address limit as under long mode.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=24}}

*'''Instruction pointer relative data access:''' Instructions can now reference data relative to the instruction pointer (RIP register). This makes [[position independent code]], as is often used in shared libraries and code loaded at run time, more efficient.

*'''SSE instructions:''' The original AMD64 architecture adopted Intel's [[Streaming SIMD Extensions|SSE]] and [[SSE2]] as core instructions. [[SSE3]] instructions were added in April 2005. SSE2 is an alternative to the [[x87]] instruction set's [[IEEE floating-point standard|IEEE 80-bit precision]] with the choice of either IEEE 32-bit or 64-bit floating-point mathematics. This provides floating-point operations compatible with many other modern CPUs. The SSE and SSE2 instructions have also been extended to operate on the eight new XMM registers. SSE and SSE2 are available in 32-bit mode in modern x86 processors; however, if they're used in 32-bit programs, those programs will only work on systems with processors that have the feature. This is not an issue in 64-bit programs, as all AMD64 processors have SSE and SSE2, so using SSE and SSE2 instructions instead of x87 instructions does not reduce the set of machines on which x86-64 programs can be run. SSE and SSE2 are generally faster than, and duplicate most of the features of the traditional x87 instructions, [[MMX (instruction set)|MMX]], and [[3DNow!]]. &lt;!-- are there enough examples to say that they are considered deprecated features in &quot;some&quot; operating systems? Most? As for &quot;why this absurd insistence x87 FPU is still allowed under AMD64?&quot;, it's because the AMD doc says it is. This section is about the chip, not the way operating systems use it. --&gt;

*'''[[NX bit|No-Execute bit]]:''' The &quot;NX&quot; bit (bit 63 of the page table entry) allows the operating system to specify which pages of virtual address space can contain executable code and which cannot. An attempt to execute code from a page tagged &quot;no execute&quot; will result in a memory access violation, similar to an attempt to write to a read-only page. This should make it more difficult for malicious code to take control of the system via &quot;[[Buffer overflow|buffer overrun]]&quot; or &quot;unchecked buffer&quot; attacks. A similar feature has been available on x86 processors since the [[80286]] as an attribute of segment descriptors; however, this works only on an entire segment at a time. Segmented addressing has long been considered an obsolete mode of operation, and all current PC operating systems in effect bypass it, setting all segments to a base address of 0 and (in their 32 bit implementation) a size of 4&amp;nbsp;GB. AMD was the first x86-family vendor to implement no-execute in linear addressing mode. The feature is also available in legacy mode on AMD64 processors, and recent Intel x86 processors, when PAE is used.

*'''Removal of older features:''' A number of &quot;system programming&quot; features of the x86 architecture are not used in modern operating systems and are not available on AMD64 in long (64-bit and compatibility) mode. These include segmented addressing (although the FS and GS segments are retained in vestigial form for use as extra base pointers to operating system structures)&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=70}}, the [[Task State Segment|task state switch]] mechanism, and [[Virtual 8086 mode]]. These features remain fully implemented in &quot;legacy mode,&quot; thus permitting these processors to run 32-bit and 16-bit operating systems without modification.

===Virtual address space details===
====Canonical form addresses====
Although virtual addresses are 64&amp;nbsp;bits wide in 64-bit mode, current implementations (and all chips known to be in the planning stages) do not allow the entire virtual address space of 2&lt;sup&gt;64&lt;/sup&gt; bytes (16&amp;nbsp;EB) to be used. Most operating systems and applications will not need such a large address space for the foreseeable future (for example, Windows implementations for AMD64 are only populating 16&amp;nbsp;TB, or 44&amp;nbsp;bits' worth), so implementing such wide virtual addresses would simply increase the complexity and cost of address translation with no real benefit. AMD therefore decided that, in the first implementations of the architecture, only the least significant 48&amp;nbsp;bits of a virtual address would actually be used in address translation ([[page table]] lookup).&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=120}} Further, bits 48 through 63 of any virtual address must be copies of bit 47 (in a manner akin to [[sign extension]]), or the processor will raise an exception.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=131}} Addresses complying with this rule are referred to as &quot;canonical form.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=130}} Canonical form addresses run from 0 through 00007FFF'FFFFFFFF, and from FFFF8000'00000000 through FFFFFFFF'FFFFFFFF, for a total of 256&amp;nbsp;TB of usable virtual address space.

This &quot;quirk&quot; allows an important feature for later scalability to true 64-bit addressing:
many operating systems (including, but not limited to, the [[Windows NT]] family) take the higher-addressed half of the address space (named kernel space) for themselves  and leave the lower-addressed half (user space) for application code, user mode stacks, heaps, and other data regions. The &quot;canonical address&quot; design ensures that every AMD64 compliant implementation has, in effect, two memory halves: the lower half starts at 00000000'00000000 and &quot;grows upwards&quot; as more virtual address bits become available, while the higher half is &quot;docked&quot; to the top of the address space and grows downwards. Also, fixing the contents of the unused address bits prevents their use by operating system as flags, privilege markers, etc., as such use could become problematic when the architecture is extended to implement more bits of virtual addresses. 

{| align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
| Current 48-bit implementation
[[Image:AMD64-canonical--48-bit.svg]]
| 56-bit implementation
[[Image:AMD64-canonical--56-bit.svg]]
| Full 64-bit implementation
[[Image:AMD64-canonical--64-bit.svg]]
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; |
|}

====Page table structure====
The 64-bit addressing mode (&quot;[[long mode]]&quot;) is a superset of [[Physical Address Extension]]s (PAE); because of this, [[paging|page]] sizes may be 4&amp;nbsp;[[Kilobyte|KB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;12&lt;/sup&gt; bytes) or 2&amp;nbsp;[[Megabyte|MB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;21&lt;/sup&gt; bytes).&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=120}} Long mode also supports page sizes of 1&amp;nbsp;[[Gigabyte|GB]] (2&lt;sup&gt;30&lt;/sup&gt; bytes).&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=120}} Rather than the three-level [[page table]] system used by systems in PAE mode, systems running in [[long mode]] use four levels of page table: PAE's ''Page-Directory Pointer Table'' is extended from 4 entries to 512, and an additional ''Page-Map Level 4 (PML4) Table'' is added, containing 512 entries in 48-bit implementations.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=131}} In implementations providing larger virtual addresses, this latter table would either grow to accommodate sufficient entries to describe the entire address range, up to a theoretical maximum of 33,554,432 entries for a 64-bit implementation, or be over ranked by a new mapping level, such as a PML5. A full mapping hierarchy of 4&amp;nbsp;KB pages for the whole 48-bit space would take a bit more than 512&amp;nbsp;GB of RAM (about 0.196% of the 256&amp;nbsp;TB virtual space).

====Operating system limits====
The operating system can also limit the virtual address space. Details, where applicable, are given in the &quot;[[X86-64#Operating_system_compatibility_and_characteristics|Operating system compatibility and characteristics]]&quot; section.

===Physical address space details===

Current AMD64 implementations support a physical address space of up to 2&lt;sup&gt;48&lt;/sup&gt; bytes of RAM, or 256&amp;nbsp;TB,.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd10h&quot;/&gt; A larger amount of installed RAM allows the operating system to keep more of the workload's pageable data and code in RAM, which can improve performance,&lt;ref name=&quot;howstuffworksVirtualMemory&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://computer.howstuffworks.com/virtual-memory.htm
|title=How Virtual Memory Works
|publisher=howstuffworks
|author=Jeff Tyson
|date=2004-01-15
|accessdate=2010-06-07
|quote=The read/write speed of a hard drive is much slower than RAM, and the technology of a hard drive is not geared toward accessing small pieces of data at a time. If your system has to rely too heavily on virtual memory, you will notice a significant performance drop. The key is to have enough RAM to handle everything you tend to work on simultaneously.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; though various workloads will have different points of diminishing returns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/using/moviemaker/expert/dunn_03august11_ram.mspx
|title=Computer RAM: A Crucial Component in Video Editing
|publisher=Microsoft Corporation
|author=Jason Dunn
|date=2003-09-03
|accessdate=2010-06-09
|quote= There's a point of diminishing returns where adding more RAM won't give you better system performance.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd346700.aspx
|title=Understanding Memory Configurations and Exchange Performance
|publisher=Microsoft Corporation
|date=2003-09-03
|accessdate=2010
|quote=There is, however, a point of diminishing returns at which adding memory to the server may not be justifiable based on price and performance.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The upper limit on RAM that can be used in a given x86-64 system depends on a variety of factors and can be far less than that implemented by the processor. For example, as of June 2010, there are no known [[motherboard]]s for x86-64 processors that support 256&amp;nbsp;TB of RAM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.supermicro.com/Aplus/motherboard/Opteron6100/
|title=Opteron 6100 Series Motherboards
|publisher=Supermicro Corporation
|accessdate=2010-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.supermicro.com/products/motherboard/Xeon1333/#1366
|title=Supermicro XeonSolutions
|publisher=Supermicro Corporation
|accessdate=2010-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.supermicro.com/Aplus/motherboard/Opteron8000/
|title=Opteron 8000 Series Motherboards
|publisher=Supermicro Corporation
|accessdate=2010-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.supermicro.com/products/motherboard/Core/index.cfm#1366
|title=Tyan Product Matrix
|publisher=MiTEC International Corporation
|accessdate=2010-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The operating system may place additional limits on the amount of RAM that is usable or supported. Details on this point are given in the &quot;[[X86-64#Operating_system_compatibility_and_characteristics|Operating system compatibility and characteristics]]&quot; section of this article.

===Operating modes===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#cccccc&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Operating mode
! [[Operating system]] required
! Compiled-application rebuild required
! Default address size
! Default operand size
! Register extensions
! Typical [[General Purpose Register|GPR]] width
&lt;!--
|-
| Address&lt;br \&gt;size(bits)
| Operand&lt;br \&gt;size(bits)
--&gt;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Long mode]]
| 64-bit mode
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | OS with 64-bit support, or bootloader for 64-bit OS
| style=&quot;background: #ddffdd&quot; | Yes
| 64
| 32
| style=&quot;background: #ddffdd&quot; | Yes
| 64
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Compatibility mode
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background: #ffdddd&quot; | No
| 32
| 32
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background: #ffdddd&quot; | No
| 32
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 16
| 16
| 16
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; | Legacy mode
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | [[Protected mode]]
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | Legacy 16-bit or 32-bit OS; or bootloader for 16, 32, or 64-bit OS
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;background: #ffdddd&quot; | No
| 32
| 32
| rowspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;background: #ffdddd&quot; | No
| 32
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| 16
| 16
| 16
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| [[Virtual 8086 mode]]
| Legacy 16-bit or 32-bit OS
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 16
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 16
| rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | 16
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| [[Real mode]]
| Legacy 16-bit OS; or bootloader for 16, 32, or 64 bit OS
|}

[[File:AMD64StateDiagram.svg|thumb|375px|State diagram of x86-64 operating modes]]
The architecture has two primary modes of operation:

====Long mode====
{{main|Long mode}}
The architecture's intended primary mode of operation; it is a combination of the processor's native 64-bit mode and a combined 32-bit and 16-bit compatibility mode. It is used by 64-bit operating systems. Under a 64-bit operating system, 64-bit programs run under 64-bit mode, and 32-bit and 16-bit protected mode applications (that do not need to use either real mode or virtual 8086 mode in order to execute at any time) run under compatibility mode. Real-mode programs and programs that use virtual 8086 mode at any time cannot be run in long mode unless they are emulated in software.

Since the basic instruction set is the same, there is almost no performance penalty for executing protected mode x86 code. This is unlike Intel's [[Itanium#Architecture|IA-64]], where differences in the underlying [[Instruction Set Architecture|ISA]] means that running 32-bit code must be done either in emulation of x86 (making the process slower) or with a dedicated x86 core. However, on the x86-64 platform, many x86 applications could benefit from a 64-bit [[recompile]], due to the additional registers in 64-bit code and guaranteed SSE2-based FPU support, which a [[compiler]] can use for optimization. However, applications that regularly handle integers wider than 32 bits, such as cryptographic algorithms, will need a rewrite of the code handling the huge integers in order to take advantage of the 64-bit registers.

====Legacy mode====
The mode used by 16-bit (protected mode or real mode) and 32-bit operating systems. In this mode, the processor acts like a 32-bit x86 processor, and only 16-bit or 32-bit code can be executed. Legacy mode allows for a maximum of 32 bit virtual addressing which limits the virtual address space to 4 GB.&lt;ref name=&quot;amd-24593&quot;/&gt;{{rp|page=14}}{{rp|page=24}}{{rp|page=118}} 64-bit programs cannot be run from legacy mode.

===AMD64 implementations===
The following processors implement the AMD64 architecture:
*AMD [[Athlon 64]]
*AMD [[Athlon 64 X2]]
*AMD [[Athlon 64|Athlon 64 FX]]
*AMD [[Athlon II]] (followed by 'X2', 'X3', or 'X4' to indicate the number of cores, and XLT models)
*AMD [[Opteron]]
*AMD [[Turion 64]]
*AMD [[Turion 64 X2]]
*AMD [[Sempron]] (&quot;Palermo&quot; E6 stepping and all &quot;Manila&quot; models)
*AMD [[Phenom (processor)|Phenom]] (followed by 'X3' or 'X4' to indicate the number of cores)
*AMD [[Phenom II]] (followed by 'X2', 'X3', 'X4' or 'X6' to indicate the number of cores)

==Intel 64==
'''Intel 64''' is Intel's implementation of x86-64. It is used in newer versions of [[Pentium 4]], [[Celeron D]], [[Xeon]] and [[Pentium Dual-Core]] processors, the [[Intel Atom|Atom]] D510, N450, and N550, and in all versions of the [[Pentium Extreme Edition]], [[Core 2]], [[Intel Core i7|Core i7]], [[Intel Core i5|Core i5]], and [[Intel Core#Core i3|Core i3]] processors.

===History of Intel 64===
Historically, AMD has developed and produced processors patterned after Intel's original designs, but with x86-64, roles were reversed: Intel found itself in the position of adopting the architecture which AMD had created as an extension to Intel's own x86 processor line.

Intel's project was originally [[codename]]d '''Yamhill''' (after the [[Yamhill River]] in Oregon's Willamette Valley). After several years of denying its existence, Intel announced at the February 2004 [[Intel Developer Forum|IDF]] that the project was indeed underway. Intel's chairman at the time, [[Craig Barrett (Intel Chairman)|Craig Barrett]], admitted that this was one of their worst kept secrets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theinquirer.net/default.aspx?article=14189 &quot;Craig Barrett confirms 64&amp;nbsp;bit address extensions for Xeon. And Prescott&quot;, from The Inquirer]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.internetnews.com/ent-news/article.php/3518781 &quot;A Roundup of 64-Bit Computing&quot;, from internetnews.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

Intel's name for this instruction set has changed several times.  The name used at the IDF was '''CT''' (presumably for '''Clackamas Technology''', another codename from an [[Clackamas River|Oregon river]]); within weeks they began referring to it as '''IA-32e''' (for [[IA-32]] extensions) and in March 2004 unveiled the &quot;official&quot; name '''EM64T''' (Extended Memory 64 Technology). In late 2006 Intel began instead using the name '''Intel 64''' for its implementation, paralleling AMD's use of the name AMD64.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url = http://www.intel.com/technology/intel64/index.htm
|title = Intel 64 Architecture
|accessdate = 2007-06-29
|publisher = [[Intel]]
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intel 64 implementations===
The first processor to implement Intel 64 was the multi-socket processor [[Xeon]] code-named ''[[Xeon#Nocona and Irwindale|Nocona]]'' in June 2004. In contrast, the initial Prescott chips (February 2004) did not enable this feature. Intel subsequently began selling Intel 64-enabled Pentium 4s using the E0 revision of the Prescott core, being sold on the OEM market as the Pentium 4, model F. The E0 revision also adds eXecute Disable (XD) (Intel's name for the [[NX bit]]) to Intel 64, and has been included in then current Xeon code-named ''Irwindale''. Intel's official launch of Intel 64 (under the name EM64T at that time) in mainstream desktop processors was the N0 Stepping Prescott-2M. All 9xx, 8xx, 6xx, 5x9, 5x6, 5x1, 3x6, and 3x1 series CPUs have Intel 64 enabled, as do the [[Core 2]] CPUs, as will future Intel CPUs for workstations or servers. Intel 64 is also present in the last members of the [[Celeron D]] line.

The first Intel [[mobile processor]] implementing Intel 64 is the [[Merom (microprocessor)|Merom]] version of the [[Core 2]] processor, which was released on 27 July 2006. None of Intel's earlier notebook CPUs ([[Core Duo]], [[Pentium M]], [[Celeron M]], [[Pentium 4|Mobile Pentium 4]]) implements Intel 64.

The following processors implement the Intel 64 architecture:
*Intel [[NetBurst (microarchitecture)|NetBurst microarchitecture]]
**Intel [[Xeon]] (all models since &quot;[[Xeon#Nocona_and_Irwindale|Nocona]]&quot;)
**Intel [[Celeron]] (some models since &quot;Prescott&quot;)
**Intel [[Pentium 4]] (some models since &quot;[[Pentium 4#Prescott|Prescott]]&quot;)
**Intel [[Pentium D]]
**Intel [[Pentium Extreme Edition]]
*Intel [[Core (microarchitecture)|Core microarchitecture]]
**Intel [[Xeon]] (all models since &quot;Woodcrest&quot;)
**Intel [[Intel Core 2|Core 2]] (including Mobile processors since &quot;Merom&quot;)
**Intel [[Pentium Dual-Core]] (E2140, E2160, E2180, E2200, E2220, E5200, E5300, E5400, E6300, E6500, T2310, T2330, T2370, T2390, T3200 and T3400)
**Intel [[Celeron]] (Celeron 4x0; Celeron M 5xx; E3200, E3300, E3400)
* Intel Atom microarchitecture
**Intel [[Intel Atom|Atom]] [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors#Atom 200 series|200 series]] (not to be confused with the N200 series, widely used in [[netbook]]s)
**Intel [[Intel Atom|Atom]] [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors#Atom 300 series|300 series]]
**Intel [[Intel Atom|Atom]] [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors|N4xx, N5xx series]]
**Intel [[Intel Atom|Atom]] [[List of Intel Atom microprocessors|Dxxx series]]
* Intel [[Nehalem (microarchitecture)|Nehalem microarchitecture]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i3|Core i3]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i5|Core i5]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i7|Core i7]]
* Intel [[Sandy Bridge|Sandy Bridge microarchitecture]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i3|Core i3]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i5|Core i5]]
**Intel [[Intel Core#Core i7|Core i7]]

==VIA's x86-64 implementation==
*[[VIA Technologies]] Isaiah microarchitecture, implemented in the [[VIA Nano]]

The '''VIA Nano''' (formerly [[Code_name#Commercial_code_names_in_the_computer_industry|code name]]d '''VIA Isaiah''') is a [[64-bit]] [[CPU]] for [[personal computer]]s. The '''VIA Nano''' was released by [[VIA Technologies]] in 2008 after five years of development&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=VIA to launch new processor architecture in 1Q08|publisher=[[DigiTimes]]|url=http://www.digitimes.com/news/a20070725PD206.html|accessdate=2007-07-25 |format=subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; by its CPU division, [[Centaur Technology]]. This new Isaiah 64-bit architecture was designed from scratch, unveiled on 24 January 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Isaiah revealed: VIA's new low-power architecture|publisher=[[Ars Technica]]|url=http://arstechnica.com/articles/paedia/cpu/via-cpu-isaiah.ars|accessdate=2008-01-24 |first=Jon|last=Stokes|date=2008-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=VIA's New Centaur Designed Isaiah CPU Architecture|publisher=[[HardOCP|[H]ard|OCP]]|url=http://enthusiast.hardocp.com/article/2008/01/24/vias_new_centaur_designed_isaiah_cpu_architecture|accessdate=2008-01-24|first=Kyle|last=Bennett|date=2008-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Via launches 64-bit architecture|publisher=[[LinuxDevices.com]]|url=http://www.linuxdevices.com/news/NS5877802443.html|accessdate=2008-01-24|date=2008-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=A look at VIA's next-gen Isaiah x86 CPU architecture|publisher=[[The Tech Report]]|url=http://techreport.com/articles.x/13996|accessdate=2008-01-24|first=Scott|last=Wasson|date=2008-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and launched on May 29, including low-voltage variants and the Nano brand name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|title=VIA Launches VIA Nano Processor Family|publisher=[[VIA Technologies|VIA]]|url=http://www.via.com.tw/en/resources/pressroom/pressrelease.jsp?press_release_no=2369|accessdate=2008-05-29 |date=2008-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The processor supports a number of VIA-specific x86 extensions designed to boost efficiency in low-power appliances.
It is expected that the VIA Isaiah will be twice as fast in integer performance and four times as fast in [[floating-point]] performance as the previous-generation [[VIA Esther]] at an equivalent [[clock speed]]. Power consumption is also expected to be on par with the previous-generation VIA CPUs, with [[thermal design power]] ranging from 5&amp;nbsp;W to 25&amp;nbsp;W.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[VIA Technologies|VIA]]|url=http://www.via.com.tw/en/downloads/presentations/processors/pb_via-isaiah_080124.pdf|title=VIA Isaiah Architecture Introduction|accessdate=2008-05-28|format=[[PDF]]|date=2008-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Being a completely new design, the Isaiah architecture was built with support for features like the x86-64 instruction set and [[x86 virtualization]] which were unavailable on its predecessors, the [[VIA C7]] line, while retaining their encryption extensions.

== Differences between AMD64 and Intel 64 ==
Although nearly identical, there are some differences between the two instruction sets in the semantics of a few seldom used machine instructions (and/or situations), which are mainly used for [[system programming]].&lt;ref name=trcscott&gt;{{cite web|last=Wasson|first=Scott|title=64-bit computing in theory and practice|url=http://techreport.com/articles.x/8131/1|work=The Tech Report|publisher=The Tech Report|accessdate=2011-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Compilers generally produce [[executables]] (i.e. [[machine code]]) that avoid any differences, at least for ordinary [[application program]]s. This is therefore of interest mainly to developers of compilers, operating systems and similar, which must deal with individual and special system instructions.

=== Recent implementations ===
* Intel&amp;nbsp;64's &lt;tt&gt;BSF&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;BSR&lt;/tt&gt; instructions act differently when the source is 0 and the operand size is 32&amp;nbsp;bits. The processor sets the zero flag and leaves the upper 32&amp;nbsp;bits of the destination undefined.
* AMD64 requires a different microcode update format and control MSRs (model-specific registers) while Intel 64 implements [[microcode]] update unchanged from their 32-bit only processors.
* Intel&amp;nbsp;64 lacks some MSRs that are considered architectural in AMD64. These include &lt;tt&gt;SYSCFG&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt&gt;TOP_MEM&lt;/tt&gt;, and &lt;tt&gt;TOP_MEM2&lt;/tt&gt;.
* Intel&amp;nbsp;64 allows &lt;tt&gt;SYSCALL&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;SYSRET&lt;/tt&gt; only in 64-bit mode (not in compatibility mode). It allows &lt;tt&gt;SYSENTER&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;SYSEXIT&lt;/tt&gt; in both modes.
* AMD64 lacks &lt;tt&gt;SYSENTER&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;SYSEXIT&lt;/tt&gt; in both sub-modes of [[long mode]].
* Near branches with the 66H (operand size override) prefix behave differently. Intel&amp;nbsp;64 clears only the top 32&amp;nbsp;bits, while AMD64 clears the top 48&amp;nbsp;bits.
* AMD processors raise a floating point Invalid Exception when performing an &lt;tt&gt;FLD&lt;/tt&gt; or &lt;tt&gt;FSTP&lt;/tt&gt; of an 80-bit signalling NaN, while Intel processors do not.
* Intel&amp;nbsp;64 lacks the ability to save and restore a reduced (and thus faster) version of the [[floating-point]] state (involving the &lt;tt&gt;FXSAVE&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;FXRSTOR&lt;/tt&gt; instructions).
* Recent AMD64 processors have reintroduced limited support for segmentation to ease [[x86 virtualization#64-bit|virtualization]] of 64-bit guests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pagetable.com/?p=25 |title=How retiring segmentation in AMD64 long mode broke VMware « |publisher=Pagetable.com |date=2006-11-09 |accessdate=2010-05-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://download3.vmware.com/vmworld/2005/pac346.pdf |title=VMware and CPU Virtualization Technology |format=PDF |publisher=VMWare |date= |accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Older implementations ===
* Early AMD64 processors lacked the &lt;tt&gt;CMPXCHG16B&lt;/tt&gt; instruction, which is an extension of the &lt;tt&gt;CMPXCHG8B&lt;/tt&gt; instruction present on most post-[[80486]] processors. Similar to &lt;tt&gt;CMPXCHG8B&lt;/tt&gt;, &lt;tt&gt;CMPXCHG16B&lt;/tt&gt; allows for [[atomic operation]]s on octal words. This is useful for parallel algorithms that use [[compare and swap]] on data larger than the size of a pointer, common in [[lock-free and wait-free algorithms]]. Without &lt;tt&gt;CMPXCHG16B&lt;/tt&gt; one must use workarounds, such as a [[critical section]] or alternative lock-free approaches.[http://www.research.ibm.com/people/m/michael/disc-2004.pdf] This also prevents 64-bit [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] from having a [[user-mode]] address space larger than 8&amp;nbsp;terabytes.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;http://blogs.msdn.com/b/oldnewthing/archive/2006/11/22/1122581.aspx&quot; The Old New Thing, by Raymond Chen (see bottom paragraph of blog post)&lt;/ref&gt;
* Early AMD64 and Intel&amp;nbsp;64 CPUs lacked &lt;tt&gt;LAHF&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;SAHF&lt;/tt&gt; instructions. AMD introduced the instructions with their Athlon&amp;nbsp;64, Opteron and Turion&amp;nbsp;64 revision&amp;nbsp;D processors in March&amp;nbsp;2005&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.amd.com/us/Processor_TechDocs/25759.pdf &quot;Revision Guide for AMD Athlon 64 and AMD Opteron Processors&quot;, from AMD]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/1021373/amd-turion-64-pictured-up-and-running &quot;AMD Turion 64 pictured up and running&quot;, from The Inquirer]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/news/1042931/athlon-64-revision-e-wont-work-on-some-nforce-34--boards &quot;Athlon 64 revision E won't work on some Nforce 3/4 boards&quot;, from The Inquirer]&lt;/ref&gt; while Intel introduced the instructions with the Pentium&amp;nbsp;4&amp;nbsp;G1 stepping in December&amp;nbsp;2005.
* Early Intel CPUs with Intel&amp;nbsp;64 also lack the [[NX bit]] of the AMD64 architecture.
* Early Intel&amp;nbsp;64 implementations only allowed access to 64&amp;nbsp;GB of physical memory while original AMD64 implementations allowed access to 1&amp;nbsp;TB of physical memory. Recent AMD64 and Intel&amp;nbsp;64 implementations provide 256&amp;nbsp;TB of physical address space (and AMD plans an expansion to 4&amp;nbsp;PB.){{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} Physical memory capacities of this size are appropriate for large-scale applications (such as large databases), and high-performance computing (centrally oriented applications and scientific computing.)
* AMD64 originally lacked the &lt;tt&gt;MONITOR&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt&gt;MWAIT&lt;/tt&gt; instructions.

==Operating system compatibility and characteristics==
The following operating systems and releases support the x86-64 architecture in [[long mode]].

===BSD===
====DragonFly BSD====
Preliminary infrastructure work was started in February 2004 for a x86-64 port.&lt;ref name=dfly-amd64-prelim&gt;{{cite web|url=http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/commits/2004-02/msg00011.html|title=cvs commit: src/sys/amd64/amd64 genassym.c src/sys/amd64/include asm.h atomic.h bootinfo.h coredump.h cpufunc.h elf.h endian.h exec.h float.h fpu.h frame.h globaldata.h ieeefp.h limits.h lock.h md_var.h param.h pcb.h pcb_ext.h pmap.h proc.h profile.h psl.h ...|accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; This development later stalled. Development started again during July 2007 &lt;ref name=dfly-amd64-noah&gt;{{cite web|url=http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/users/2007-07/msg00016.html|title=AMD64 port|accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and continued during [[Google Summer of Code]] 2008 and SoC 2009.&lt;ref name=dfly-amd64-soc2008&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dragonflybsd.org/docs/developer/GoogleSoC2008/|title=DragonFlyBSD: GoogleSoC2008|accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=dfly-amd64-soc2009&gt;{{cite web|url=http://leaf.dragonflybsd.org/mailarchive/users/2009-04/msg00091.html|title=Summer of Code accepted students|accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first official release to contain x86-64 support was version 2.4.&lt;ref name=dflyamd64-release&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dragonflybsd.org/release24/|title=DragonFlyBSD: release24|accessdate=2009-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====FreeBSD====
[[FreeBSD]] first added x86-64 support under the name &quot;amd64&quot; as an experimental architecture in 5.1-RELEASE in June 2003. It was included as a standard distribution architecture as of 5.2-RELEASE in January 2004. Since then, FreeBSD has designated it as a Tier 1 platform. The 6.0-RELEASE version cleaned up some quirks with running x86 executables under amd64, and most drivers work just as they do on the x86 architecture. Work is currently being done to integrate more fully the x86 [[application binary interface]] (ABI), in the same manner as the Linux 32-bit ABI compatibility currently works.

====NetBSD====
x86-64 architecture support was first committed to the [[NetBSD]] source tree on 19 June 2001. As of NetBSD 2.0, released on 9 December 2004, ''NetBSD/amd64'' is a fully integrated and supported port.

====OpenBSD====
[[OpenBSD]] has supported AMD64 since OpenBSD 3.5, released on 1 May 2004. Complete in-tree implementation of AMD64 support was achieved prior to the hardware's initial release due to AMD's loaning of several machines for the project's [[hackathon]] that year. OpenBSD developers have taken to the platform because of its support for the [[NX bit]], which allowed for an easy implementation of the [[W^X]] feature.

The code for the AMD64 port of OpenBSD also runs on Intel 64 processors which contains cloned use of the AMD64 extensions, but since Intel left out the page table NX bit in early Intel 64 processors, there is no W^X capability on those Intel CPUs; later Intel 64 processors added the NX bit under the name &quot;XD bit&quot;. [[Symmetric multiprocessing]] (SMP) works on OpenBSD's AMD64 port, starting with release 3.6 on 1 November 2004.

===DOS===
It is possible to enter [[long mode]] under [[DOS]] without a DOS extender,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turboirc.com/asm  Tutorial for entering protected and long mode from DOS]&lt;/ref&gt; but the user must return to real mode in order to call BIOS or DOS interrupts.

It may also be possible to enter [[long mode]] with a [[DOS extender]] similar to [[DOS/4GW]], but more complex since x86-64 lacks [[virtual 8086 mode]]. DOS itself is not aware of that, and no benefits should be expected unless running DOS in an emulation with an adequate virtualization driver backend, for example: the mass storage interface.

===Linux===
{{See also|Comparison of Linux distributions#Architecture support}}

[[Linux]] was the first operating system kernel to run the x86-64 architecture in [[long mode]], starting with the 2.4 version in 2001 (prior to the physical hardware's availability).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Porting Linux to x86-64 |author=Andi Kleen |url=http://www.x86-64.org/pipermail/announce/2001-June/000020.html |date=2001-06-26 |quote=Status: The kernel, compiler, tool chain work.  The kernel boots and work on simulator and is used for porting of userland and running programs |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.halobates.de/ | title= Andi Kleen's Page |author=Andi Kleen |quote=This was the original paper describing the Linux x86-64 kernel port back when x86-64 was only available on simulators. |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Linux also provides backward compatibility for running 32-bit executables. This permits programs to be recompiled into long mode while retaining the use of 32-bit programs. Several Linux distributions currently ship with x86-64-native kernels and [[userland (computing)|userlands]]. Some, such as [[SUSE Linux|SUSE]], [[Mandriva Linux|Mandriva]], and [[Debian|Debian GNU/Linux]], allow users to install a set of 32-bit components and libraries when installing off a 64-bit DVD, thus allowing most existing 32-bit applications to run alongside the 64-bit OS. Other distributions, such as [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]], [[Slackware]], [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], and [[Arch Linux]], are available in one version compiled for a 32-bit architecture and another compiled for a 64-bit architecture. Fedora and [[RedHat  Enterprise Linux]] allow concurrent installation of all userland components in both 32 and 64-bit versions on a 64-bit system. 

x32 ABI (Application Binary Interface) is an under development Linux project that allows programs compiled for the x32 ABI to run in the 64-bit mode of x86-64 while only using 32-bit pointers and data fields.&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABIHOnline&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.h-online.com/open/features/Kernel-Log-x32-ABI-gets-around-64-bit-drawbacks-1342061.html |title=Kernel Log: x32 ABI gets around 64-bit drawbacks |publisher=www.h-online.com |author=Thorsten Leemhuis |date=2011-09-13 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABILinuxPlumbers&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://linuxplumbersconf.org/2011/ocw/proposals/531 |title=x32 - a native 32-bit ABI for x86-64 |publisher=linuxplumbersconf.org |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABIDevelopmentGroup&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://sites.google.com/site/x32abi/ |title=x32-abi |publisher=Google Sites |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though this limits the program to a virtual address space of 4 GB it also decreases the memory footprint of the program and in some cases can allow it to run faster.&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABIHOnline&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABILinuxPlumbers&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;x32ABIDevelopmentGroup&quot;/&gt;

64-bit [[Debian]] Linux allows up to 128&amp;nbsp;[[Terabyte|TB]] of virtual address space for individual processes, and can address approximately 64&amp;nbsp;TB of physical memory, subject to processor and system limitations.&lt;ref name=&quot;DebianAMD64&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.debian.org/ports/amd64/ |title=AMD64 Port |publisher=debian.org |accessdate=2011-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mac OS X===
Mac OS X v10.4.7 and higher versions of [[Mac OS X v10.4]] run 64-bit command-line tools using the POSIX and math libraries on 64-bit Intel-based machines, just as all versions of Mac OS X v10.4 and 10.5 run them on 64-bit PowerPC machines.  No other libraries or frameworks work with 64-bit applications in Mac OS X v10.4.&lt;ref&gt;[http://developer.apple.com/releasenotes/DeveloperTools/RN-CompilerTools/index.html Apple - Mac OS X Xcode 2.4 Release Notes: Compiler Tools]&lt;/ref&gt;  The kernel, and all kernel extensions, are 32-bit only.

[[Mac OS X v10.5]] supports  64-bit GUI applications using [[Cocoa (API)|Cocoa]], [[Quartz (graphics layer)|Quartz]], [[OpenGL]], and [[X11]] on 64-bit Intel-based machines, as well as on 64-bit [[PowerPC]] machines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.apple.com/macosx/technology/64bit.html Apple - Mac OS X Leopard - Technology - 64 bit]&lt;/ref&gt; All non-GUI libraries and frameworks also support 64-bit applications on those platforms.  The kernel, and all kernel extensions, are 32-bit only.

[[Mac OS X v10.6]] is the first version of Mac OS X that supports a 64-bit [[Kernel (computing)|kernel]]. However, with its first release (v10.6.0), not all 64-bit computers are currently supported. The 64-bit kernel, like the 32-bit kernel, supports 32-bit applications; both kernels also support 64-bit applications. 32-bit applications have a virtual address space limit of 4&amp;nbsp;GB under either kernel.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstechnicaMacOSX64bit&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://arstechnica.com/apple/reviews/2009/08/mac-os-x-10-6.ars/5
 |title=Mac OS X 10.6 Snow Leopard: the Ars Technica review
 |publisher=Ars Technica LLC
 |author=[[John Siracusa]] |accessdate=2010-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple64Bit&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://www.apple.com/macosx/technology/
 |title=Mac OS X Technology
 |publisher=Apple
 |accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 64-bit kernel does not support 32-bit [[loadable kernel module|kernel extensions]], and the 32-bit kernel does not support 64-bit kernel extensions.

Mac OS X uses the [[universal binary]] format to package 32- and 64-bit versions of application and library code into a single file; the most appropriate version is automatically selected at load time.  In Mac OS X 10.6, the universal binary format is also used for the kernel and for those kernel extensions that support both 32-bit and 64-bit kernels.

[[Mac OS X v10.7]] runs the 64-bit kernel by default on supported machines. Older machines that cannot run the 64-bit kernel run the 32-bit kernel. Both seamlessly support 32- and 64-bit applications.

===Solaris===
[[Solaris Operating System|Solaris]] 10 and later releases support the x86-64 architecture. Just as with the [[SPARC]] architecture, there is only one operating system image for all 32-bit and 64-bit x86 systems; this is labeled as the &quot;x64/x86&quot; DVD-ROM image.

Default behavior is to boot a 64-bit kernel, allowing both 64-bit and existing or new 32-bit executables to be run. A 32-bit kernel can also be manually selected, in which case only 32-bit executables will run. The &lt;code&gt;isainfo&lt;/code&gt; command can be used to determine if a system is running a 64-bit kernel.

===Windows===

x86-64 editions of Microsoft Windows client and server, [[Windows XP editions#Windows XP Professional x64 Edition|Windows XP Professional x64 Edition]] and [[Windows Server 2003]] x64 Edition were released in March 2005. Internally they are actually the same build (5.2.3790.1830 SP1), as they share the same source base and operating system binaries, so even system updates are released in unified packages, much in the manner as Windows 2000 Professional and Server editions for x86. [[Windows Vista]], which also has many different editions, was released in January 2007. [[Windows 7]] was released in July 2009. [[Windows Server 2008 R2]] and later versions will only be available as x86-64 versions. Windows for x86-64 has the following characteristics:

*8&amp;nbsp;TB of &quot;user mode&quot; virtual address space per process. A 64-bit program can use all of this, subject of course to backing-store limits on the system, and provided it is linked with the &quot;large address aware&quot; option.&lt;ref name=&quot;VSdocLAA&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/wz223b1z(VS.80).aspx
|title= /LARGEADDRESSAWARE (Handle Large Addresses)
|quote=The /LARGEADDRESSAWARE option tells the linker that the application can handle addresses larger than 2 gigabytes.
|work=Visual Studio 2005 Documentation - Visual C++ - Linker Options
|publisher=Microsoft
|accessdate=2010-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This is a 4096-fold increase over the default 2&amp;nbsp;GB user-mode virtual address space offered by 32-bit Windows.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pietrek64BitWindowsProgramming&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/cc300794.aspx
|title=Everything You Need To Know To Start Programming 64-Bit Windows Systems
|publisher=Microsoft
|author=Matt Pietrek
|date=2006-05
|accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MicrosoftMoveTox64&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/2006.01.insidemscom.aspx
|title=Making the Move to x64
|publisher=Microsoft
|author=Chris St. Amand
|date=2006-01 |accessdate=2010-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* 8&amp;nbsp;TB of kernel mode virtual address space for the operating system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pietrek64BitWindowsProgramming&quot;/&gt; As with the user mode address space, this is a 4096-fold increase over 32-bit Windows versions. The increased space primarily benefits the file-system cache and kernel-mode &quot;heaps&quot; (non-paged pool and paged pool).  Windows only uses a total of 16&amp;nbsp;TB out of the 256&amp;nbsp;TB implemented by the processors because early AMD64 processors lacked a CMPXCHG16B instruction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | title = Behind Windows x86-64’s 44-bit Virtual Memory Addressing Limit
  | url = http://www.alex-ionescu.com/?p=50
  | accessdate = 2009-07-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Ability to run existing 32-bit applications (&lt;code&gt;.exe&lt;/code&gt; programs) and dynamic link libraries (&lt;tt&gt;.dll&lt;/tt&gt;s) using [[WoW64]]. Furthermore, a 32-bit program, if it was linked with the &quot;large address aware&quot; option,&lt;ref name=&quot;VSdocLAA&quot;/&gt; can use up to 4&amp;nbsp;GB of virtual address space in 64-bit Windows, instead of the default 2&amp;nbsp;GB (optional 3&amp;nbsp;GB with &lt;tt&gt;/3GB&lt;/tt&gt; boot option and &quot;large address aware&quot; link option) offered by 32-bit Windows.&lt;ref name=&quot;64-bitProgrammingGameDevelopers&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 |url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ee418798(VS.85).aspx#Porting_to_64bit
 |title=64-bit programming for Game Developers}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the use of the &lt;tt&gt;/3GB&lt;/tt&gt; boot option on x86, this does not reduce the kernel-mode virtual-address space available to the operating system. 32-bit applications can therefore benefit from running on x64 Windows even if they are not recompiled for x86-64.

* Both 32- and 64-bit applications, if not linked with &quot;large address aware,&quot; are limited to 2&amp;nbsp;GB of virtual address space.

*Ability to use up to 128&amp;nbsp;GB (Windows XP/Vista), 192&amp;nbsp;GB (Windows 7), 1&amp;nbsp;TB (Windows Server 2003), or 2&amp;nbsp;TB (Windows Server 2008) of physical random access memory (RAM).

*[[64-bit|LLP64]] data model: &quot;int&quot; and &quot;long&quot; types are 32&amp;nbsp;bits wide, long long is 64&amp;nbsp;bits, while pointers and types derived from pointers are 64&amp;nbsp;bits wide.
* Kernel-mode device drivers must be 64-bit versions; there is no way to run 32-bit kernel-mode executables within the 64-bit operating system. User mode device drivers can be either 32-bit or 64-bit.
*16-bit Windows (Win16) and DOS applications will not run on x86-64 versions of Windows due to removal of the [[virtual DOS machine]] subsystem (NTVDM) which relied upon the ability to use virtual 8086 mode. Virtual 8086 mode cannot be entered while running in long mode.
*Full implementation of the [[NX bit|NX]] (No Execute) page protection feature. This is also implemented on recent 32-bit versions of Windows when they are started in PAE mode.
*Instead of FS segment descriptor on x86 versions of the [[Windows NT]] family, GS segment descriptor is used to point to two operating system defined structures: Thread Information Block (NT_TIB) in user mode and Processor Control Region (KPCR) in kernel mode. Thus, for example, in user mode &lt;tt&gt;GS:0&lt;/tt&gt; is the address of the first member of the Thread Information Block. Maintaining this convention made the x86-64 port easier, but required AMD to retain the function of the FS and GS segments in long mode — even though segmented addressing ''per se'' is not really used by any modern operating system.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/magazine/cc300794.aspx
|title=Everything You Need To Know To Start Programming 64-Bit Windows Systems
|quote=On x86-64 versions of Windows, the FS register has been replaced by the GS register.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Early reports claimed that the operating system scheduler would not save and restore the x87 FPU machine state across thread context switches. Observed behavior shows that this is not the case: the x87 state is saved and restored, except for kernel-mode-only threads (a limitation that exists in the 32-bit version as well). The most recent documentation available from Microsoft states that the x87/MMX/3DNow! instructions may be used in long mode, but that they are deprecated and may cause compatibility problems in the future.&lt;ref name=&quot;64-bitProgrammingGameDevelopers&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!--- is there a way to use quotes with named refs?
 |quote=The x87, MMX, and 3DNow! instruction sets are deprecated in 64-bit modes.---&gt;

*Some components like [[Microsoft Jet Database Engine]] and [[Data Access Objects]] will not be ported to 64-bit architectures such as x86-64 and IA-64.&lt;ref&gt;[http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa384190.aspx Microsoft Developer Network - General Porting Guidelines (64-bit Windows Programming)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnmdac/html/data_mdacroadmap.asp Microsoft Developer Network - Data Access Road Map]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Microsoft Visual Studio]] can compile [[native code|native application]]s to target either the x86-64 architecture, which can run only on 64-bit Microsoft Windows, or the [[IA-32]] architecture, which can run as a 32-bit application on 32-bit Microsoft Windows or 64-bit Microsoft Windows in [[WoW64]] emulation mode. [[Managed code|Managed application]]s can be compiled either in IA-32, x86-64 or AnyCPU modes. Software created in the first two modes behave like their  IA-32 or x86-64 native code counterparts respectively; When using the AnyCPU mode however, applications in 32-bit versions of Microsoft Windows run as 32-bit applications, while they run as a 64-bit application in 64-bit editions of Microsoft Windows.

==Industry naming conventions==
Since AMD64 and Intel 64 are substantially similar, many software and hardware products use one vendor-neutral term to indicate their compatibility with both implementations. AMD's original designation for this processor architecture, &quot;x86-64&quot;, is still sometimes used for this purpose, as is the variant &quot;x86_64&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://lists.apple.com/archives/Darwin-dev/2006/Aug/msg00095.html
  | title = re: Intel XNU bug report
  | accessdate = 2006-10-05
  | author = Kevin Van Vechten
  | date = 2006-08-09
  | work = Darwin-dev mailing list
  | publisher = [[Apple Computer]]
  | quote = The kernel and developer tools have standardized on &quot;x86_64&quot; for the name of the Mach-O architecture
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other companies, such as [[Microsoft]] and [[Sun Microsystems]], use the contraction &quot;x64&quot; in marketing material.

The term [[Itanium#Architecture|IA-64]] refers to the [[Itanium]] processor, and should not be confused with x86-64, as it is a completely different instruction set.

Many operating systems and products, especially those that introduced x86-64 support prior to Intel's entry into the market, use the term &quot;AMD64&quot; or &quot;amd64&quot; to refer to both AMD64 and Intel 64.

* [[BSD]] systems such as [[FreeBSD]], [[MidnightBSD]], [[NetBSD]] and [[OpenBSD]] refer to both AMD64 and Intel 64 under the architecture name &quot;amd64&quot;.
* The [[Linux]] kernel and [[DragonFly BSD]] refers to 64-bit architecture as &quot;x86_64&quot;.
* The [[GNU Compiler Collection]] refers to 64-bit architecture as &quot;amd64&quot;.
* [[Debian]], [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]], and [[Gentoo Linux|Gentoo]] refer to both AMD64 and Intel 64 under the architecture name &quot;amd64&quot;.
* [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]], [[PackageKit]], [[openSUSE]], and [[Arch Linux]] refer to 64-bit architecture as &quot;x86_64&quot;.
* [[Haiku (operating system)|Haiku]]: refers to 64-bit architecture as &quot;x86_64&quot;.
* [[Java Development Kit]] (JDK): The name &quot;amd64&quot; is used in directory names containing x86-64 files.
* [[Mac OS X]]: Apple refers to 64-bit architecture as &quot;x86_64&quot;, as noted with the Terminal command &lt;code&gt;arch&lt;/code&gt; and in their developer documentation. [http://developer.apple.com/documentation/Darwin/Reference/ManPages/man1/arch.1.html]
* [[Microsoft Windows]]: x86-64 versions of Windows use the AMD64 moniker internally to designate various components which use or are compatible with this architecture. For example, the system directory on a Windows x86-64 Edition installation CD-ROM is named &quot;AMD64&quot;, in contrast to &quot;i386&quot; in 32-bit versions.
* [[Solaris (operating system)|Solaris]]: The &quot;[[isalist]]&quot; command in Sun's Solaris operating system identifies both AMD64- and Intel 64&amp;ndash;based systems as &quot;amd64&quot;.
* [[T2 SDE]] refer to both AMD64 and Intel 64 under the architecture name &quot;x86-64&quot;, in source code directories and package meta information.

==Legal issues==
AMD [[license]]d its x86-64 design to Intel,{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} where it is marketed under the name '''Intel 64'''. As Intel licenses AMD the right to use the original x86 architecture (upon which AMD's x86-64 is based), these rival companies now rely on each other for 64-bit processor development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url = http://www.theinquirer.net/inquirer/opinion/759/1050759/amd-plays-antitrust-poker-intel-x86-licence
  |title = AMD plays antitrust poker for Intel's X86 licence
  |accessdate = 2009-02-26
  |date = 2009-02-03
  |work =
  |publisher = Incisive Media Limited
}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{Failed verification|date=October 2009}} &lt;!-- Comments in a source do not count as a source --&gt; Should this agreement collapse, AMD would no longer be authorized to produce any x86 processors, and Intel would no longer be authorized to produce x86-64 processors, forcing it back to the x86 architecture. However, the agreement&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  |url = http://contracts.corporate.findlaw.com/agreements/amd/intel.license.2001.01.01.html
  |title = Patent Cross License Agreement Between AMD and Intel
  |accessdate = 2009-08-23
  |date = 2001-01-01
}}&lt;/ref&gt; provides that if one party breaches the agreement, it loses all rights to the other party's technology, while the other party receives perpetual rights to all licensed technology.
In 2009, AMD and Intel settled several lawsuits and cross-licensing disagreements, extending their cross-licensing agreements for the foreseeable future and settling several anti-trust complaints.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/2488/000119312509236705/dex101.htm |title = AMD Intel Settlement Agreement}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://developer.amd.com/documentation/guides/Pages/default.aspx#manuals AMD's AMD64 Developer Guides and Manuals]
*[http://www.stanford.edu/class/ee380/Abstracts/O00927.html x86-64: Extending the x86 architecture to 64-bits] - technical talk by the architect of AMD64 ([http://stanford-online.stanford.edu/courses/ee380/000927-ee380-100.asx video archive]), and [http://www.stanford.edu/class/ee380/Abstracts/040107.html second talk by the same speaker] ([http://stanford-online.stanford.edu/courses/ee380/040107-ee380-100.asx video archive])
*[http://www.xbitlabs.com/news/other/display/20041227094638.html AMD's &quot;Enhanced Virus Protection&quot;]
*[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2005/08/23/intel_fixes_em64t/ Intel tweaks EM64T for full AMD64 compatibility]
*[http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,3973,1561875,00.asp?kc=ETRSS02129TX1K0000532 Analyst: Intel Reverse-Engineered AMD64]
*[http://marc.info/?l=linux-kernel&amp;m=107766481408468&amp;w=2 Early report of differences between Intel IA32e and AMD64]
*Porting to 64-bit GNU/Linux Systems, by Andreas Jaeger from [[GCC Summit]] 2003 [http://www.linux.org.uk/~ajh/gcc/gccsummit-2003-proceedings.pdf]. An excellent paper explaining almost all practical aspects for a transition from 32-bit to 64-bit.
*[http://techreport.com/reviews/2005q1/64-bits/index.x?pg=1 Tech Report article: 64-bit computing in theory and practice]
*[http://www.intel.com/technology/intel64/index.htm Intel 64 Architecture]
*[http://software.intel.com/en-us/articles/all-about-64-bits/ Intel Software Network, 64 bits&quot;]
*[http://www.turboirc.com/asm TurboIRC.COM tutorial of entering the protected and the long mode the raw way from DOS]
*[http://www.codeproject.com/KB/winsdk/Optimization_64_bit.aspx Optimization of 64-bit programs]
*[http://software.intel.com/en-us/articles/seven-steps-of-migrating-a-program-to-a-64-bit-system/ Seven Steps of Migrating a Program to a 64-bit System]
*[http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa366778%28VS.85%29.aspx Memory Limits for Windows Releases]

&lt;!-- [[Category:Advanced Micro Devices products]] category is added to the AMD64 redirect page instead of here, in order to make that name appear in the category listing rather than &quot;X86-64&quot;; --&gt;
[[Category:2003 introductions]]
[[Category:X86 architecture]]

[[ar:إيه إم دي 64]]
[[ca:AMD64]]
[[cs:X86-64]]
[[da:X86-64]]
[[de:AMD64]]
[[es:X86-64]]
[[fr:AMD64]]
[[ko:X86-64]]
[[id:AMD64]]
[[it:AMD64]]
[[he:X86-64]]
[[hu:X86-64]]
[[nl:X86-64]]
[[ja:AMD64]]
[[no:X86-64]]
[[pl:AMD64]]
[[pt:AMD64]]
[[ro:X86-64]]
[[ru:X86-64]]
[[sk:X86-64]]
[[sl:X86-64]]
[[fi:AMD64]]
[[sv:AMD64]]
[[th:X86-64]]
[[tr:X86-64]]
[[uk:X64]]
[[vi:X86-64]]
[[zh:X86-64]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
