<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24479685" ns="0" title="Your Hand In Mine"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television
| show_name = Your Hand In Mine &lt;br&gt; (想握你的手)
| image =  
| caption =
| genre =
| format =
| runtime = approx. 45 minutes per episode
| creator = Hong Xi 洪汐
| director = Xie Yiwen 谢益文
| producer = He Faming 何法明
| writer = Hong Xi 洪汐&lt;br&gt;Zhang Liangxing 张亮星&lt;br&gt;Wu Cuicui 吴翠翠&lt;br&gt;Chen Disheng 陈迪笙
| starring = [[Huang Wenyong]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chen Liping]]&lt;br&gt;[[Yvonne Lim]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cai Peixuan]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belinda Lee(actress)|Belinda Lee]]
| opentheme = 想握你的手 by 迷路兵 [[Milubing]]&lt;br&gt;想握你的手 by 苏智城 [[Cavin Soh]]
| endtheme = 想握你的手 by 曾咏霖 [[Teresa Tseng]]&lt;br&gt;只要你微笑 by 迷路兵 [[Milubing]]&lt;br&gt;逞强 by 曾咏霖 [[Teresa Tseng]] &lt;br&gt; 反方向 by 插班生
| country = [[Singapore]]
| language = [[Chinese Language|Chinese]]
| network = [[MediaCorp TV Channel 8]]
| first_aired = 9 November 2009
| last_aired =  16 July 2010
| num_episodes = 180
| preceded_by = [[Welcome Home, My Love]]
| followed_by = [[:zh:愛 (民視電視劇)|Love]]
| related = [[Holland V]] (2003) &lt;br&gt; [[Likeable or Not]] (2007-2008)
| website = http://yourhandinmine.mediacorptv.sg/
| website2 = xinmsn.com/yourhandinmine
}}
{{Infobox Chinese-language series and movie
| englishname             = Your Hand In Mine
| tradchinesename         = 想握你的手
| jyutpingchinesename     =
| simpchinesename         = 想握你的手
| pinyinchinesename       = Xiǎng Wò Nǐ De Shǒu
}}

'''Your Hand In Mine''' ([[Chinese language|Chinese]]: 想握你的手) was a long-running drama that was produced by [[Singapore]]'s free-to-air channel, [[MediaCorp TV Channel 8]]. It was the longest local drama that had been produced by Mediacorp to date, with 180 episodes. Originally dubbed as the 2010 version of the acclaimed 2003 serial [[Holland V (TV series)|Holland V]], it starred the veterans [[Chen Liping]] and [[Huang Wenyong]], as well as [[Yvonne Lim]], [[Belinda Lee (actress)|Belinda Lee]], [[Cai Peixuan]] and [[Joanne Peh]].

It was also the first Mediacorp production to be filmed entirely at outdoor locations like Lentor and Tanjong Katong and the second to be filmed in [[High-definition video|high definition]] after [[The Ultimatum]].

The drama started airing at the 7&amp;nbsp;pm primetime slot from 9 November 2009 and ended its run on 16 July 2010. The drama has   had acquired a loyal following since its November 2009 debut and some viewers had requested MediaCorp to extend the drama to 200 episodes and beyond.

==&quot;Chit Chat Club&quot;==
Before an episode, a three-minute so-called short clip called &quot;Chit Chat Club&quot; (叽喳棺), an appetizer for viewers to make viewers maybe tickle their funny bone.

==Synopsis Beginning==

The Zheng family lives in a five room HDB flat in Bishan. It comprises the money-minded eldest son Zheng Shanguo (Huang Wenyong), his materialistic wife Zhang Yuxiang (Chen Liping), and his daughters, the hot-tempered Aizhen (Yvonne Lim), the hypochondriac Aishan (Belinda Lee) and the slow and simple Aimei (Cai Peixuan). The other two occupants of the flat are Shanguo's elderly mother Lu Qiaomei (Hong Damu), who is always armed with a plan for every situation, and Shanguo's wayward younger brother, Shuiguo (Yao Wenlong). The Zheng family runs a coffeeshop with two outlets, one in Bishan and the other in Jurong West.

Living directly opposite them is the Li family, which comprises the bedridden Jianzhou (Liang Tian), his wife Jinyin (Jin Yinji), and their grandchildren Liqin (Shuan Chen) and Lifen (Paige Chua). They had moved to Bishan a decade ago to begin a new life after the murder of Jianzhou's son by his wife Qiumei (Jue Xi). Liqin had been at odds with Aizhen for a long time and they never fail to bicker when they meet. Jinyin is a gambler, and she had raised Liqin and Lifen with her earnings from her mahjong games, earning her the nickname 'Granny Mahjong'. Liqin and Jinyin are both very protective of Lifen, and she knows nothing about the murder of her father. She had been told from young that her parents had died in a fire.

Soon, Aizhen meets Fang Kai (Pierre Png), a rich young man who preferred to keep his immense wealth secret. Fang Kai is Liqin's best friend in university, and Aizhen tries to get more information about Fang Kai through him. Aizhen meets Fang Kai again on the set of Lifen's short film. Fang Kai poses as part of the middle class, but in fact is the son of the magnate Jason Fang. Jason is married to Janet, but the love between them has long gone. They pretend to be a happy family for the cameras, but this changes when Janet slaps Zen (Lynn Poh), a widowed film producer, who threatens to sue her. The case is later withdrawed.

Qiumei is released from prison and tries to find her family. In the process, she manages to get a job at 899, which Shanguo runs. She eventually meets her family after information from a friendly police officer, Lin Hanwen (Huang Shinan), but she is kicked out by Jinyin and Liqin, much to the horror of Qiaomei and Aizhen. They decide to take her in, but it is not long after that she is fired by Yuxiang when she learns that Qiumei was a convicted murderer.

==Cast==
===Zheng Family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Huang Wenyong]]''' || Zheng Shanguo (郑山国) || Aizhen, Aishan, Aimei and Weiren's father &lt;br&gt;Yuxiang's husband&lt;br&gt; Qiaomei's eldest son
|-
||'''[[Chen Liping]]''' ||  Zhang Yuxiang (张玉香) || Aizhen, Aishan, Aimei and Weiren's mother &lt;br&gt; Shanguo's wife&lt;br&gt;Youli's friend
|-
||'''[[Yvonne Lim]]''' || Zheng Aizhen(郑爱真) || Yuxiang and Shanguo's eldest daughter&lt;br&gt; Liqin's wife&lt;br&gt;Television newscaster&lt;br&gt;Yang Yan's enemy&lt;br&gt;Xiaolong's mother
|-
||'''[[Belinda Lee]] ''' || Zheng Aishan (郑爱善) || Yuxiang and Shanguo's second daughter&lt;br&gt;Co-owner of 899 Cafe&lt;br&gt;Youli's wife
|-
||'''[[Cai Peixuan]]''' || Zheng Aimei (郑爱美) || Yuxiang and Shanguo's youngest daughter &lt;br&gt; Yue Guang's friend &lt;br&gt; Co-owner of 899 Cafe&lt;br&gt;4D's wife
|-
||'''[[Yao Wenlong]]''' || Zheng Shuiguo (郑水国) &lt;br&gt; Aunt Suanmei (酸梅姨)|| Shanguo's brother &lt;br&gt; Qiaomei's youngest son &lt;br&gt; Chef &lt;br&gt; Qiumei's second husband
|-
||'''[[Hong Damu]]''' || Lu Qiaomei (卢巧妹) || Shanguo and Shuiguo's mother&lt;br&gt;Jinyin's friend&lt;br&gt;In a relationship with Uncle Rojak
|-
||'''[[Chen Xijie]]'''|| Zheng Weiren (鄭偉仁) || Shanguo and Yuxiang's son
|-
||'''[[Calvin Soh]]''' || Wu Youli (吴有礼) || See Wu family.
|-
||'''[[Hayden Hee]]''' || 4D&lt;br&gt;Zhu Zhongfeng (朱仲峰) || See 899 Coffee Shop.
|-
||'''[[Jess Teong]]''' || Guan Qiumei (关秋梅) || See Li family.
|-
|}

===Li family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Shaun Chen]]''' || Li Liqin (李立勤) || Qiumei's son &lt;br&gt;Previous CEO of JZ Production Company&lt;br&gt;Aizhen's husband&lt;br&gt;Xiaolong's father&lt;br&gt;Fangkai's buddy&lt;br&gt;Evil&lt;br&gt;Mastermind&lt;br&gt;Murdered Zen&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|-
||'''[[Paige Chua]]''' || Li Lifen (李立芬) || Qiumei's daughter&lt;br&gt;Roland's wife&lt;br&gt;Film director
|-
||'''[[Jin Yinji]]''' || Lan Jinyin (蓝金银) || Liqin and Lifen's grandmother&lt;br&gt;Jianzhou's wife
|-
||'''[[Liang Tian]]''' || Li Jianzhou (李建舟) || Jinyin's husband &lt;br&gt; Liqin and Lifen's grandfather&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|-
||'''[[Jess Teong]]''' || Guan Qiumei (关秋梅) || Liqin and Lifen's mother &lt;br&gt; Ex-convict&lt;br&gt;Dezhu's assistant&lt;br&gt;Shuiguo's wife
|-
||'''[[Yvonne Lim]]''' || Zheng Aizhen(郑爱真) || See Zheng family.
|-
||'''[[Adam Chen]]''' || Roland || See Yue family.
|-
||'''[[Yao Wenlong]]''' || Zheng Shuiguo (郑水国) || See Zheng family.
|}

===Wu family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Calvin Soh]]''' || Wu Youli (吴有礼) || Youqing's brother &lt;br&gt; Rag-and-bone man (Karung-guni)&lt;br&gt;Aishan's husband&lt;br&gt;Jinlian's son&lt;br&gt;Bai Shouye's biological son
|-
||'''[[Joanne Peh]]''' || Wu Youqing (吴有情)|| Youli's sister&lt;br&gt;Lawyer&lt;br&gt;Yue Guang's former fiancee&lt;br&gt;Fang Kai's wife&lt;br&gt;Jinlian's daughter&lt;br&gt;Bai Shouye's biological daughter
|-
||'''[[Belinda Lee]]''' || Zheng Aishan (郑爱善) || See Zheng family.
|- 
||'''[[Pierre Png]]''' ||  Fang Kai (方楷) || See Fang family.
|-
||'''[[Joanne Peh]]''' || Liu Jinlian (刘金莲) || Bai Shouye's former wife &lt;br&gt; Youqing and Youli's mother &lt;br&gt; Trickster&lt;br&gt;Dried Chilli's friend&lt;br&gt;Yue Guang's friend&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|}

===Yue family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Zhang Yaodong]]''' || Yue Guang (岳光) || Roland's uncle&lt;br&gt;Counsellor&lt;br&gt;Jinlian's friend&lt;br&gt;Youqing's former fiance&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|-
||'''[[Adam Chen]]''' || Roland || Yue Guang's nephew &lt;br&gt; Lifen's husband &lt;br&gt; Zen's former boyfriend&lt;br&gt;H20's guardian
|}

===Fang family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Pierre Png]]''' ||  Fang Kai (方楷) || Jason and Janet's son &lt;br&gt; Felicia's brother&lt;br&gt; Aizhen's former boyfriend&lt;br&gt;Youqing's husband&lt;br&gt;Xiaolong's godfather&lt;br&gt;Chairman of JZ Production Company
|-
||'''[[Chen Shucheng]]''' || Jason Fang (Jason方) || Fang Kai and Felicia's father &lt;br&gt; Janet's husband &lt;br&gt; Zen's former admirer
|-
||'''[[He Jie]]''' || Janet Fang (Janet方) || Jason's wife &lt;br&gt; Fang Kai's mother&lt;br&gt;Felicia's stepmother
|-
||''[[Sharon Wong]]''|| Felicia Fang (Felicia方) || Jason and Janet's daughter&lt;br&gt;Graduate&lt;br&gt;Liqin's ex-girlfriend
|}

===899 Coffee Shop===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Cai Peixuan]]''' || Zheng Aimei (郑爱美) || See Zheng family.
|-
||'''[[Huang Wenyong]]''' || Zheng Shanguo (郑山国) || See Zheng family.
|-
||'''[[Chen Liping]]''' ||  Zhang Yuxiang (张玉香) || See Zheng family.
|-
||'''[[Hayden Hee]]''' || 4D&lt;br&gt;Zhu Zhongfeng (朱仲峰) || Aimei's husband&lt;br&gt;Worker at 899 Cafe
|-
||'''[[Patricia Mok]]''' || Dried Chilli (辣椒干) || Hongzhong's former wife&lt;br&gt;Yuxiang and Shanguo's former employee&lt;br&gt;Jinlian's friend&lt;br&gt;Runs a chain of Penang Laksa stores&lt;br&gt;Yuxiang's friend
|-
||'''[[Chen Huihui]]''' || Quan Sao (全嫂) || Yuxiang and Shanguo's former employee &lt;br&gt; Quan's ex-wife&lt;br&gt;Ah Ru, Ah Hui, and Ah Xiang's mother&lt;br&gt;In a relationship with Sotong Chen
|-
||'''[[Duan Weiming]]'''|| Hongzhong (洪中) || Dried Chilli's former husband&lt;br&gt;Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;Jinyin's  friend&lt;br&gt;Tissue paper seller
|-
||'''[[Foyce Le]]''' || Wei Wei (薇薇) || Masseur&lt;br&gt;Hongzhong's former girlfriend
|-
||'''[[Asmiyah Bte Asbah]]''' || Wati || Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee
|-
||''Uncredited'' || Param || Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;Married in India
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Orbit || Obiang's sister &lt;br&gt; Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;Dezhu's admirer
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Obiang || Orbit's sister &lt;br&gt; Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;Dezhu's admirer
|-
||'''[[Yun Changling]]'''|| Uncle Rojak (Rojak叔)|| Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;In a relationship with Qiaomei
|-
||''Uncredited'' || Auntie Chicken Rice (鸡饭嫂) || Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Sotong Chen (Sotong陳)|| Shanguo and Yuxiang's former employee&lt;br&gt;In a relationship with Quan Sao
|}

===Lin Family===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Pan Lingling]]''' || Dolly Lin (林多利) || Hanwen's wife &lt;br&gt;Yuxiang's friend&lt;br&gt;Zen's best friend&lt;br&gt;Minxing's agent&lt;br&gt;President of the Women's Club&lt;br&gt;Xiaodong,Xiaoxi and Xiaonan's mother&lt;br&gt;Dedao's former girlfriend
|-
||'''[[Huang Shinan]]''' || Lin Hanwen (林汉文) || Duoli's husband&lt;br&gt;Police officer &lt;br&gt; Xiaodong,Xiaonan and Xiaoxi's father&lt;br&gt;Shuixian's former boyfriend
|-
||'''[[Chen Xingyu]]''' || Lin Xiaonan (林小南)|| Duoli and Hanwen's son&lt;br&gt;Xiaoxi's brother&lt;br&gt;Ah Ru's friend
|-
||'''[[Leron Heng]]'''|| Lin Xiaoxi (林小西)|| Duoli and Hanwen's daughter&lt;br&gt;Xiaonan's sister&lt;br&gt;In relationship with H2O
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Lin Xiaodong (林小东)|| Duoli and Hanwen's eldest son&lt;br&gt;Deceased&lt;br&gt;Banged by HanWen(accident)
|}

===Supporting cast===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Joshua Ang]]''' || H20&lt;br&gt;Gao Yongjun (高勇俊) || Zen's stepson&lt;br&gt;Xiaoxi's friend&lt;br&gt;Shuixian's former student&lt;br&gt;Vice Chairman of JZ Production Company&lt;br&gt;Vice Chairman of Zen Production Company
|-
||'''[[Lynn Poh]]''' || Zen Zhou (Zen周) || H20's stepmother&lt;br&gt;Head of JZ Production Company&lt;br&gt;Head of Zen Production Company&lt;br&gt;Jason's business partner&lt;br&gt; Roland's former girlriend&lt;br&gt; Duoli's friend&lt;br&gt;Deceased (Murdered by Liqin)
|-
||'''[[Cassandra See]]''' || Helen || Yuxiang's best friend
|-
||'''[[Wallace Ang]]''' || Nick || Liqin's ex-colleague
|-
||'''[[Pamelyn Chee]]''' || Ah Bing (阿冰) || Auntie OK's daughter
|-
||'''[[Celest Chong]]''' || Bai Shuixian （白水苋） || H20 and Xiaoxi's former form teacher&lt;br&gt;Shouye's daughter&lt;br&gt;Youli and Youqing's half-sister&lt;br&gt;Hanwen's former girlfriend&lt;br&gt;Teaching in China
|-
||'''[[Wang Yuqing]]''' || Zhao Dezhu （赵得柱） || TCM practitioner&lt;br&gt;Dedao's brother&lt;br&gt;Qiumei's admirer
|-
||'''[[Wang Yuqing]]''' || Zhao Dedao (赵得道) || Gynecologist&lt;br&gt;Dezhu's brother&lt;br&gt;Duoli's former boyfriend
|-
||'''[[Zheng Yazhu]]''' || Auntie Garbage (垃圾婆) || Youli's godmother &lt;br&gt; Rag-and-bone woman (Karung-guni) &lt;br&gt; Ben's mother
|-
||'''[[Zhang Wei]]'''|| Bai Shouye (白守业) || Bai Shuixian's father &lt;br&gt; Xiaoke and Shuiguo's boss &lt;br&gt; Leader of a
traid&lt;br&gt;Youqing and Youli's biological father&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|}

===Minor Cast===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Actor !! Role !! Description
|-
||'''[[Kanny Theng]]''' || May || Yue Guang's former employee&lt;br&gt;Aimei's friend
|-
||'''[[Huang Shuyun]]'''|| Rose || Aishan's former office compeititor
|-
||'''[[Vina Lim]]''' || Ah Ru (阿如)|| Quan Sao's daughter&lt;br&gt;Xiaonan's friend
|-
||'''[[Damus Lim]]''' || Ah Hui (阿辉)|| Quan Sao's second son
|-
||'''[[Justin Peng]]''' || Ah Xiang (阿祥)|| Quan Sao's eldest son
|-
||'''[[Lawrence Wong]]''' || Ben || Youqing's former pupil &lt;br&gt; Auntie Garbage's third son
|-
||'''[[Henry Heng]]''' || PP Yeo || Youqing's former boss&lt;br&gt;Ben's boss&lt;br&gt;Fangs' legal consultant
|-
||'''[[Le Yao]]''' || Yang Yan (杨艳) || Aizhen's rival&lt;br&gt;Television news reporter
|-
||'''[[Sun Yuhui]]''' || Auntie OK (好姨) || Ah Bing's mother&lt;br&gt;Deceased
|-
||'''[[Dawn Yeoh]]''' || Duoli's foe || Deceased
|-
||'''[[Silver Ang]]''' || Dai Minxing (戴敏星)||Duoli's protege&lt;br&gt;Actress&lt;br&gt;Imprisoned
|-
||'''[[Seth Ang]]''' || Xiaoke (小柯)|| Bai Shuixian's admirer &lt;br&gt; Bai Shouye's right-hand man&lt;br&gt;Shuiguo's former superior
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Maria || Duoli and Hanwen's former maid
|-
||'''[[Zhang Wenxiang]]'''|| Ma Shengli (马胜利) || Hong Kong film director
|-
||'''[[Wang Changli]]'''|| Mr. Han (韩主任) || Aizhen's boss
|-
||''Uncredited''||Li Xiaolong || Aizhen and Liqin's son&lt;br&gt;Fang Kai's godson
|-
||'''[[Zhu Xiufeng]]'''|| Mdm. Gao  (高老太太)|| H20's grandmother&lt;br&gt;Zen's mother-in-law
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Annie || Shanguo and Yuxiang's former maid
|-
||''Uncredited''|| Soldier || Xiaoxi's former admirer
|}

==Character Bonds==
===Yuxiang and Shanguo===
Yuxiang fancies a large bungalow at Lentor Plain, but Shanguo is miserly and refuses to even consider buying it. Yuxiang comes up with an elaborate scheme to persuade Shanguo to buy the house, and contacts Lin Duoli (Pan Lingling), her property agent friend, to help her. Eventually, they move into the bungalow, much to Qiaomei's disappointment. Shanguo decides to transfer ownership of the flat to Qiaomei and Shuiguo.

===Duoli and Hanwen===
Duoli is undergoing a divorce from Hanwen because Hanwen banged their 1st son(Xiao Dong)by accident.Ever since Duoli will not forget what Han Wen did in the past . They promise to keep this a secret from their children until Xiaoxi (Leron Heng), their eldest daughter, turns 18 and finishes her 'A' Level examinations. They continue to sleep in the same room to prevent their children from knowing anything. While packing, Xiaoxi finds out that her parents were divorced, but she keeps quiet, pretending not to know anything.

===Yuxiang and Youli===
Yuxiang moves into her new house and is happy with everything but her neighbours, the Wus- Youli (Cavin Soh) and Youqing (Joanne Peh). Youli is a rag-and-bone man who had gotten rich with his investments, while Youqing is a hot prospect in the legal world, a rising talent within PP Yeo's (Henry Heng) law firm. Yuxiang is always embroiled in quarrels with him, and they frequently threaten each other with lawsuits. Youli mocks Yuxiang for her branded clothing and accessories, calling her a 'Christmas Tree', and Yuxiang counters by giving Youli the nickname 'Weirdo'. Youli keeps a cloth around his neck at all times to hide his tumour. He refuses to have it removed as he is afraid of operations and hospitals.

===Youqing, Fang Kai and Yue Guang===
Youqing is cold on the exterior but is a warm person inside. She was kidnapped as a child and was trapped together with a young boy who had told her the story of the Tortoise Prince. This boy, as would be revealed later on in the series, was actually Fang Kai. In memory of the boy, she keeps several tortoises as pets. As a result of the trauma from the kidnapping experience, she develops claustrophobia and a general distrust towards men. She puts up a cold exterior in defense of her inner psychological scars. All this changes when she meets Yue Guang (Zhang Yaodong) a psychiatrist. She mistakes him for a pervert at first, but later falls in love with him. The feelings are mutual and they get together in a few weeks. Youli likes Yue Guang and places his stamp of approval on the relationship.

===Aizhen and Fang Kai===
Meanwhile, love blossoms between Aizhen and Fang Kai. Despite their frequent quarrels, they are deeply in love with each other. Fang Kai does not want to enter business like his father, instead deciding to run a LAN shop in a shopping centre. Yuxiang is greatly displeased with their relationship as she wants Aizhen to be with a rich man. Yuxiang thinks that Fang Kai is a gigolo and teams up with her friend Helen (Cassandra See) to sabotage their relationship. All of their attempts fail miserably.

It is not long before Yuxiang finds out about Fang Kai's real identity. She immediately endorses their relationship and Aizhen and Fang Kai can now continue their relationship openly. Lifen's friendship with Aizhen is marred when she briefly creates a love triangle between the couple, but Fang Kai has eyes only for Aizhen.

Aizhen is a job hopper who always has bad relationships with her superiors. But after meeting Yang Yan (Le Yao), a reporter, she decides to enter Clear Sky News Agency as a reporter as well. At the agency, she immediately has spats with Yang Yan and her cameraman, Ah Boon. They constantly collaborate to make trouble for Aizhen, but most of their plans are foiled. Aizhen gets the chance to appear of television, and Yuxiang is very proud of her, but is very disappointed when only her daughter's voice is heard.

''More details will be given for...''
* Aishan and Youli
* Aimei and 4D
* Shuiguo and Qiumei

==Viewership Ratings==
The drama did not fare very well in ratings. One reason is due to the fact that Korean Drama Cruel Temptation was running at the same time on Channel U which attracted many viewers.
The initial part of the drama attracted an average of 680,000 viewers, middle part 730,000 and above 800,000 towards the ending. At one time, the ratings plunged to a low of 400,000, making it the long-running drama produced by Mediacorp with the lowest ratings. Viewers of Your Hand In Mine suggested that Cruel Temptation should be aired in the weekend to fight head on with Taiwanese drama Love, instead of Glory of Family which was airing during weekends.

==Trivia==
*Se Ce was to be played by Sharon Wong; but she played Felicia Fang instead.
*Yue Caipiao was to play Yue Guang's daughter. However, due to a change in the script, her character was renamed Cui Ruanfei and separated from Yue Guang's storyline.
* [[Hayden Hee]] is the brother of [[Julian Hee]], a Mediacorp artiste.
*Jason Fang's hairstyle resembles that of [[Lucas Chia]], the Mediacorp CEO from 2005 to 2011.
* [[Joanne Peh]] playes two roles in the serial, as daughter and mother Wu Youqing and Liu Jinlian. [[Wang Yuqing]] also plays two roles, as the twins Zhao Dezhu and Zhao Dedao.
* The serial's first opening sequence ran from Episodes 1 to 90, while the second will run from Episode 91 to the finale (Episode 180).
* The theme song of the serial has three different renditions, by the band Milubing, Cavin Soh, and Teresa Tseng. They have the same lyrics but different tunes.
*[[Joanne Peh]] and [[Zhang Yao Dong]] act together for the second time after [[The Greatest Love of All]]. They made their third pair-up in [[A Tale of 2 Cities]], another TV drama.
*[[Chen Liping]] and [[Huang Wen Yong]] had made up husband and wife for [[Just in Singapore]]. This will be their last time pairing up in this drama.
*[[Zhang Yao Dong]] and [[Pierre Png]] pairs up in this drama as well as [[The Score]] and [[A Tale of 2 Cities]].

==[[Star Awards 2011]] Nominations==
* [[Shaun Chen]], the villain of this drama, was ironically nominated for the Best Actor, but lost to [[Qi Yu Wu]] in [[The Family Court]].
* [[Joanne Peh]] was nominated for the Best Actress, but lost to [[Rui En]] in With You. 
* Xie Yiwen was nominated for the Best Director, but lost to Breakout's director.

==See also==
* [[List of programmes broadcast by MediaCorp TV Channel 8]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.mediacorptv.sg/ch/buzzdetail/EDC081222-0000015]
*[http://mediacorptv.sg/English/forums/1/134071/ShowThread.aspx]

{{Navbox
|name = YourHandInMine
|title = Your Hand In Mine
|list1 = {{nowrap begin}}
{{•w}}Your Hand In Mine
{{•w}}[[List of Your Hand In Mine episodes|Episode List]]
{{•w}}[[Characters of Your Hand In Mine|Characters]]
{{nowrap end}}

}}
{{2009 Mediacorp Channel 8}}
{{2010 Mediacorp Channel 8}}
{{SGLongRunningDramas}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

[[Category:Singapore Chinese dramas]]
[[Category:2009 television series debuts]]

[[id:Your Hand In Mine]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
