<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24499377" ns="0" title="M. Victor Paul"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Christian leader
| type        = Bishop
| name        = M. Victor Paul
| title       = [[President]]
| image       = M. Victor Paul.jpg
| alt         = 
| caption     = 
| church      = [[Christianity]]
| archdiocese = 
| diocese     = 
| see         = [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]] (AELC)
| term        = [[1993]]&amp;mdash;[[1997]]
| predecessor = K. Nathaniel 
| successor   = G. Emmanuel
&lt;!--   Orders   --&gt;
| ordination     = April [[1962]]
| ordinated_by   = 
| consecration   = [[1993]]
| consecrated_by = 
| rank           = 
&lt;!--   Personal details   --&gt;
| birth_date    = 7 April [[1935]]
| birth_place   = [[Rajahmundry]], [[Andhra Pradesh]]
| death_date    = 
| death_place   = 
| previous_post = Principal, [[Andhra Christian Theological College]], [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]], [[India]]
}}

'''M. Victor Paul''' ([[Telugu language|Telugu]]: విక్టర్ పాల్ అయ్యగారు - born 7 April [[1935]]) is a biblical scholar who served as [[President]] of the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]] from [[1993]] to [[1997]].

==Early years==
Victor Paul was born on 7 April [[1935]] into a into a [[pastoral]] family&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;&gt;Victor Paul, ''The Messianic King in [[Gospel of Saint Matthew]]'', Published by the Telugu Theological Literature Board, Hyderabad, 2002.  From the back cover of the book.&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Rajahmundry]], [[East Godavari District]] in [[Andhra Pradesh]] as the eldest of nine children to [[Smt.]] Sundaramma and [[Pastor]] Mortha Sudarshanam.  After undergoing schooling at the Lutheran Boarding in [[Peddapuram]], his parents sent him to the [[Andhra-Christian College]], [[Guntur]].  Paul studied Arts (''[[Bachelor of Arts|B.A.]]'')&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt;  in the College when [[Rao Sahab]] T. S. Paulus&lt;ref&gt;The Times of India Directory and Year Book including Who's Who, Volume 36, Published by the Times of India Press, Bombay, 1950.  p.534.  [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=FagSAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=]&lt;/ref&gt; was at the helm of affairs.  After completing graduate studies in [[Guntur]], Victor Paul returned to [[Rajahmundry]] where he underwent studies in education at the local Government Training College leading to [[B.Ed.]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt;

==Divinity==
===Graduate Studies===
Continuing the [[priestly]] family tradition, Victor Paul chose to pursue divinity and his Church Society, then under G. Devasahayam, sent him to [[Madras]] during the academic year [[1959]]-[[1960]] for ministerial formation at the [[Gurukul Lutheran Theological College]] (GLTC),&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; [[Madras]] ''{affiliated to the [[Senate of Serampore College (University)]]}'' where Victor Paul pursued a graduate course in theology (''[[Bachelor of Divinity|B.D.]]'').  The [[GLTCRI]] was then headed by Dr. P. David.

===Ordination &amp; Priesthood===
At the end of the academic year [[1961]]-[[1962]], Victor Paul was awarded a [[Bachelor of Divinity|B.D.]] and ordained in April [[1962]] as a [[Priest]] of the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]] headquartered in [[Guntur]].  He was assigned a pastoral role in in [[Samalkot]] and [[Peddapuram]] parishes.  Victor Paul also replaced S. W. Schmitthenner as honorary Youth Director of the Church Society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt;

===Post-graduate studies===
After serving as a Pastor, Victor Paul's Church Society under G. Devasahayam (second term of Presidentship) sent him again to [[Madras]] where Paul was to pursue a post-graduate degree in [[New Testament]] (''[[M.Th.]]'')&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; beginning from the academic year [[1963]]-[[1964]].  Initially Victor Paul spent a year working on [[Greek language|Greek]] with Jim Bergquist&lt;ref&gt;D. A. Thangasamy, ''Towards Involvement: the Theory and Practice of Laity Education'', The Christian Literature Society, 1972.  p.ix.  [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=qI8hAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as on the revision of portions from the Westminster Dictionary of the Bible (Revised Edition) edited by Henry Snyder Gehman and John D. Davis.

From [[1964]]-[[1965]] onwards Victor Paul registered as an [[M.Th.]] student with the [[Gurukul Lutheran Theological College]] and worked out a thesis&lt;ref&gt;''Thesis Titles - M.Th., M.R.S., D.D., D.Th.'', Published by the Board of Theological Education of the Senate of Serampore College, Bengaluru, 1991.  p.6&lt;/ref&gt; entitled ''A theological exposition of 'to know' in the Johannine literature with some points of contact and contrast between John and Gita'' under the guidance of his Professor, Jim Bergquist and later at the end of the academic year [[1965]]-[[1966]], the [[Senate of Serampore College (University)]] awarded the post-graduate degree of [[M.Th.]] in [[New Testament]].

In [[1966]], Victor Paul went to the [[Jesuit]]-run De Nobili College, [[Poona]] along with Gali Bali&lt;ref&gt;Gali Bali is currently the Bishop of [[Catholic]] Diocese of Guntur.  [http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/bishop/bgali.html]&lt;/ref&gt; to attend the biennial conference of the scholarly Society for Biblical Studies in India held on the theme ''The significance of the historical in the New Testament [[Kerygma]]''.

When Victor Paul returned from [[Madras]] after his post-graduate studies, he was re-assigned his former [[ecclesiastical]] duties in [[Samalkot]] and [[Peddapuram]].  Paul continued to serve in pastoral roles from [[1966]] to [[1969]] in the assigned Parishes.

In [[1969]], Victor Paul was relieved as [[Pastor]] and made [[Lecturer]] in [[New Testament]] at the ecumenical [[Andhra Christian Theological College]] then located in [[Rajahmundry]] where he began teaching [[New Testament]] and [[Greek language|Greek]] along with Waldo Penner, [[Muriel Carder]], and K. David, then members of the faculty teaching [[New Testament]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt;

===Studies Abroad===
[[Image:Luther Giri.jpg|thumb|215px|left|Christ Church, [[Rajahmundry]].  Victor Paul was ordained here in April 1962.]]
When [[W. D. Coleman]] was Principal of the [[Andhra Christian Theological College]], [[Rajahmundry]], the Board of Governors of the College accorded study leave to Victor Paul who proceeded to [[Saint Paul, Minnesota]] and pursued an [[S.T.M.]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; in [[Counselling]] for academic years [[1970]]-[[1973]] in the [[Luther Seminary]] (''a degree granting authority accredited by the [[Association of Theological Schools in the United States and Canada]] duly recognised by the [[United States Government]] as an accrediting agency'').&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt;  James A. Bergquist&lt;ref&gt;John Henry Paul Reumann, James A. Bergquist (Edited), ''The Church emerging: a U.S. Lutheran case study'', Published by Fortress Press, Philadelphia, 1977.[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=XycRAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=]  James A. Bergquist had been teaching at the Seminary in Minnesota since [[1970]].&lt;/ref&gt; then Professor at the [[Luther Seminary]] was the guide of Paul.

Beginning from the academic year [[1973]]-[[1974]] Victor Paul resumed teaching responsibilities at the ecumenical Seminary in Hyderabad after completing studies in [[North America]].  Among the new additions to the College faculty in [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]] were [[G. Solomon]], [[R. Yesuratnam]], and [[Ravela Joseph]].  By then, [[Victor Premasagar]] had already become Principal of the College in Hyderabad.  Under the aegis of the Andhra Pradesh Council of Churches in [[1974]], a discussion was initiated on the theme ''Renewal of the ministry in Andhra Pradesh'' in which Victor Paul also participated.  The findings of the consultation were later tabled before the Churches of Andhra Pradesh.&lt;ref&gt;''Renewal of the ministry in Andhra Pradesh: Report of the consultation held in Hyderabad and Tirupati'', Published by the Andhra Christian Theological College and the Andhra Pradesh Council of Churches, Hyderabad, 1974.[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=dslLHQAACAAJ&amp;dq=]&lt;/ref&gt;

A. A. Sitompul and others of the [[Lutheran World Federation]] took cognizance&lt;ref&gt;A. A. Sitompul, '' Current Asian theological thinking
progress reports and papers from seminars conducted by Asia Programme for Advanced Studies'', Lutheran World Federation, Geneva, 1977.[http://openlibrary.org/b/OL3891411M/Current_Asian_theological_thinking]&lt;/ref&gt; of Victor Paul's paper on Parish Renewal as early as September 1975&lt;ref&gt;''[[Cf.]]'' A. A. Sitompul, ''Theological education within the whole people of God: International Consultation on Theological Education'', Second Edition, Lutheran World Federation, Geneva, 1976.[http://books.google.co.in/books?id=OiwsHQAACAAJ&amp;dq=]&lt;/ref&gt; at an international consultation held at the [[Ecumenical Institute of Bossey]] in September, 1975.

In [[1976]], A. A. Sitompul on behalf of the [[Lutheran World Federation]] invited Victor Paul to pursue doctoral studies ''([[D.Min.]])'' in Practical Ministry at the [[Luther Seminary]], [[Saint Paul, Minnesota]].&lt;ref&gt;Also see leaflet of St. Mark's Evangelical Lutheran Church, [[Saint Paul, Minnesota]].  [http://www.stmarks-nsp.org/news/assets/India%20Flyer_2008.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Victor Premasagar]], then Principal of the College put up the matter before the Board of Governors of the College which decided to accord study leave to Victor Paul.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Cf.]]'' Article on [[Victor Premasagar]]&lt;/ref&gt;  While at the [[Luther Seminary]], Victor Paul's doctoral supervisor was James A. Nestingen,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.luthersem.edu/jnesting/ Luther Seminary - James A. Nestingen]&lt;/ref&gt; currently Professor Emeritus of Church History.  By [[1979]], Victor Paul was awarded the doctoral degree [[D.Min.]] by the [[Luther Seminary]] and he returned to take up his teaching responsibilities back in [[India]].  The College in Hyderabad by then had seen new teaching staff being added onto its rolls.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACTC&quot; /&gt;  B. C. Paul, G. Sampurna Rao, B. J. Christie Kumar, and G. Babu Rao had joined the College when Victor Paul went on sabbatical at varying intervals.

==Contribution==
===Theological writings===
The Church Historian R. Joseph, a colleague of Victor Paul at ACTC, who compiled a bibliography of original Christian writings in Telugu with the assistance of B. Suneel Bhanu under the aegis of the [[Board of Theological Education of the Senate of Serampore College]] included a book by Victor Paul entitled ''The Liberated Ones: Explanations of Lutheran Catechism and Confessions'' published as early as [[1981]].&lt;ref&gt;Ravela Joseph, Suneel Bhanu (Compiled), ''Bibliography of original Christian writings in Telugu'', Board of Theological Education of the Senate of Serampore College, Bengaluru, 1993.  p. 25.  [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=3YPgAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=]&lt;/ref&gt;

Victor Paul also authored the following theological books in [[Telugu language|Telugu]] published by the Telugu Theological Literature Board, [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; which are devotional commentaries on:

* [[Gospels]]
** The Messianic King in [[Gospel of Saint Matthew]]
** [[Gospel of Saint Mark]]
** [[Gospel according to Saint Luke]]
** [[Gospel of John]] ''(also shown under Johannine Literature)''

* [[Johannine literature]][[Image:ACTC Faculty Group 1.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Victor Paul ''(seated seventh from left)'' along with the Teachers and Students of the Seminary in [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]] during the Principalship of S. Joseph.]]
** [[Gospel of John]]
** [[First Epistle of John]]
** [[Second Epistle of John]]
** [[Third Epistle of John]]
** [[Book of Revelation]]

* [[Pauline Epistles]]
** [[Epistle to the Romans]]
** [[Epistle to the Galatians]]
** [[Epistle to the Ephesians]]
** [[Epistle to the Philippians]]
** [[Epistle to the Colossians]]
** [[Epistle to the Hebrews]]

* [[General Epistles]]
** [[Epistle of James]]
** [[Epistle of Jude]]

Martin Senftleben&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.drmartinus.de/menu.php?topic=bio_bio&amp;no=0 Doctor Martinus]&lt;/ref&gt; who researched at the [[Sri Venkateswara University]] in [[Tirupati (city)|Tirupati]] acknowledged Victor Paul to be a Scholar.&lt;ref&gt;Martin Senftleben, ''Influences of Hinduism on Christianity in Andhra Pradesh'', Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Sri Venkateswara University, Tirupati, 1992.  p.8.  [http://www.drmartinus.de/bio/de/thesis1.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

Michael Bergunder, Professor of Missions at the [[Ruprecht Karl University of Heidelberg]], [[Germany]] believes that Victor Paul attempted to recognise [[Charismatic]] Christianity which was fast enveloping traditional Christianity.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Bergunder, ''The South Indian Pentecostal movement in the twentieth century: Studies in the history of Christian missions'', Published by William B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2008.  Page 242.  [http://books.google.co.in/books?id=XGiv3riaunQC&amp;pg=PA242&amp;dq=]&lt;/ref&gt;  Being a person who puts theory into practice, Victor Paul as Principal of ACTC once went ahead and invited the pioneer charismatic Pastor, Apostle P. L. Paramjyoti&lt;ref&gt;Apostle P. L. Paramjyoti was an indigenous charismatic leader who earlier studied at the [[Baptist Theological Seminary]] in [[Kakinada]].&lt;/ref&gt; to deliver the graduation address of the College in a particular year.

Excerpt from Victor Paul's article quoted by [[Prof.]] Michael Bergunder:&lt;ref&gt;Victor Paul, ''Parish Renewal'' in Reflections on Theology Today - Papers presented by the ACTC faculty during the academic year 1988-1989 on Theology and Mission and Ministry of the Church, Hyderabad, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quotation|In the midst of leadership crisis, institutionalism, materialism, corruption and spiritual lethargy, there shines a ray of hope in the form of charismatic lay movement.... Today in almost all congregations of the Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church (AELC), charismatic groups are evident and are begging for recognition....  AELC is faced with two options: one is to reject them totally as a religiously and emotionally perverted group or to recognize this lay charismatic movement as a natural reaction and a mute protest against evils and secularism existing in AELC.  It is time now to own and recognise these charismatics....  With proper investigation, study and reflection on the charismatic Lay Movement within the established churches, one may help the traditional churches to re-discover their identity and relevancy of their faith and service in today's world.}}

===Academic===
* Member of the [[Senate of Serampore College (University)]]
* Member of the Research Committee of the [[Board of Theological Education of the Senate of Serampore College]], [[Bengaluru]].

* [[Andhra Christian Theological College]] (ACTC)
Victor Paul first began teaching [[New Testament]] in ACTC from [[1969]].  Past-timers acknowledge Victor Paul as having an influence in students lives in unique&lt;ref&gt;Lankapalli Samuel John, ''Swarna Manjeeralu (Telugu)'', Published by the author, Visakhapatnam, 2009.  Samuel John was a past student of ACTC and a writer.  ''[[Cf.]]'' p. 50 of R. Joseph and B. Suneel Bhanu's compilation found elsewhere in this article for reference of Samuel John.&lt;/ref&gt; ways.  After the four-year cycle of Principalship of the [[Samavesam of Telugu Baptist Churches]] ended in the academic year [[1989]]-[[1990]], the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]]'s cycle of Principalship began.  Besides Victor Paul, there were four other faculty from this Church Society teaching in the College at that time, namely, B. W. David Raju, B. C. Paul, G. Sampurna Rao, and C. Yesupadam.  Since the participating Church agency decides the name of the Principal, the Board of Governors of the College left the decision to the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]], then under the Presidentship of K. Nathaniel, which chose to nominate Victor Paul&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; to the Principalship of the ecumenical seminary for a term of four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACTC&quot;&gt;''[[Cf.]] [[Andhra Christian Theological College]]''&lt;/ref&gt;  B. Ryder Devapriam, then Chairperson of the Board of Governors of the College appointed Victor Paul as Principal of the College for a term of four years.  As Principal, Victor Paul was able to prove himself as an able Administrator following the footsteps of his predecessors.

In the final phase of Victor Paul's tenure as Principal, he contested the bishopric of the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]] and proceeded on leave from the College.  To fill the vacancy, the AELC then nominated G. Sampurna Rao as Principal of the College.

===Church Leadership===
When the term of K. Nathaniel as President of the [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]] ended, Victor Paul contested and was elected in [[1993]] as the ninth President&lt;ref name=&quot;Biography&quot;/&gt; of the Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church headquartered in Guntur.&lt;ref&gt;''[[Cf.]]'' [[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]]&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[1997]], when Victor Paul's term ended, he returned to [[Hyderabad, India|Hyderabad]] to teach at the [[Andhra Christian Theological College]] then headed by R. Yesurathnam. Victor Paul retired in 2000.

{{s-start}}
{{s-aca}}
{{succession box | before=S. Joseph
| title=Principal&lt;/br&gt;
[[Andhra Christian Theological College]], Hyderabad
|after=G. Sampurna Rao| years=[[1990]]-[[1993]]}}
{{s-rel}}
{{succession box | before=K. Nathaniel
| title=President
[[Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church]]
|after=G. Emmanuel| years=[[1993]]-[[1997]]}}
{{s-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite journal
 | author=Kolluri Luther Richardson
 | title=''Towards Self-Reliance : A historical survey of the programmes and efforts of Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church from 1927-1969'', Published by Christopher and Kanakaiah, Vijayawada
 | year=2003
 | volume=
 | issue=
 | url =
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=Michael Bergunder
 | title=Die südindische Pfingstbewegung im 20. Jahrhundert: eine historische und systematische Untersuchung
 | year=1999
 | volume= of Studien zur interkulturellen Geschichte des Christentums
 | issue=
 
 
 | series=113| isbn=9783631337714| url =http://books.google.com/?id=Wo3YAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=R. Joseph and B. Suneel Bhanu
 | title=Bibliography of Original Christian Writings in India in Telugu
 | year=1993
 | volume=
 | issue=
 | url =http://books.google.com/?id=3YPgAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=Bibliography+of+Original+Christian+Writings+in+India+in+Telugu
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=Martin Senftleben
 | title=''Influences of Hinduism on Christianity in Andhra Pradesh.''  Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Sri Venkateshwara University, Tirupati
 | year=1992
 | volume=I
 | issue=
 | url =http://www.drmartinus.de/bio/de/thesis1.pdf
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=_______________,
 | title=''Influences of Hinduism on Christianity in Andhra Pradesh.''  Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Sri Venkateshwara University, Tirupati
 | year=1992
 | volume=II
 | issue=
 | url =http://www.drmartinus.de/bio/de/thesis2.pdf
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=M. Victor Paul
 | title=Parish Renewal in Reflections on Theology Today - Papers presented by the ACTC faculty during the academic year 1988-1989 on Theology and Mission and Ministry of the Church
 | year=1990
 | volume=
 | issue=
 | url =
}}
* {{cite journal
 | author=B. C. Paul
 | title=''The Emergence of a Church in South India: A Study of the Growth and Development of the Andhra Evangelical Lutheran Church: 1905-1927.  Unpublished [[Th. D.]] thesis submitted to the [[Lutheran School of Theology at Chicago]].
 | year=1984
 | volume=
 | issue=
 | url =http://archive.elca.org/archives/dgm/India.html
}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Victor Paul, M
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1935
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Rajahmundry]], [[Andhra Pradesh]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Victor Paul, M}}
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from East Godavari]]
[[Category:Telugu people]]
[[Category:20th-century Lutheran clergy]]
[[Category:21st-century Lutheran bishops]]
[[Category:Indian bishops]]
[[Category:Andhra University alumni]]
[[Category:Indian theologians]]
[[Category:Christian religious leaders]]
[[Category:Lutheran sermon writers]]
[[Category:Lutheran writers]]
[[Category:Senate of Serampore College (University) alumni]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
