<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24518" ns="0" title="Peter Sellers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=September 2011}}
{{About|the British actor|the American director|Peter Sellars}}
{{Infobox Person
| name         = Peter Sellers
| image        = Petersellers.jpg
| caption      = Peter Sellers as Henry Orient
| birth_name   = Richard Henry Sellers
| birth_date   = {{Birth date|1925|9|8|df=y}}
| birth_place  = [[Southsea]], [[Hampshire]], England, United Kingdom
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1980|7|24|1925|9|8|df=y}}
| death_place  = London, England, United Kingdom
| death_cause  = Heart Attack
| nationality  = [[United Kingdom|British]]&lt;ref&gt;name=&quot;britannica.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9106396/Peter-Sellers |title=Peter Sellers – Britannica Online Encyclopedia |publisher=Britannica.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| occupation   = Actor, comedian
| ethnicity     = [[Jewish people|Jewish]]
| years_active = 1948–1980
| spouse       = Anne Hayes&lt;br /&gt;(m. 1951–1961; divorced)&lt;br /&gt;[[Britt Ekland]]&lt;br /&gt;(m. 1964–1968; divorced)&lt;br /&gt;[[Miranda Quarry]]&lt;br /&gt;(m. 1970–1974; divorced)&lt;br /&gt;[[Lynne Frederick]] (m. 1977–1980; his death)
| children     = [[Michael Sellers (actor)|Michael]] (deceased), Sarah, [[Victoria Sellers|Victoria]]
}}
'''Richard Henry Sellers''', [[Commander of the Order of the British Empire|CBE]] (8 September 1925 – 24 July 1980), known as '''Peter Sellers''', was a [[United Kingdom|British]] [[comedian]] and actor.  Perhaps best known as [[Inspector Clouseau|Chief Inspector Clouseau]] in ''[[The Pink Panther]]'' film series, he is also notable for playing three different characters in ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'', as Clare Quilty in ''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]'', and as the TV-addicted man-child Chance the gardener in his penultimate film, ''[[Being There]]''. Leading actress [[Bette Davis]] once remarked of him, &quot;He isn't an actor—he's a chameleon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tcm.com/thismonth/article/?cid=354685 Peter Sellers Bio], Turner Classic Movies&lt;/ref&gt;

Sellers rose to fame on the BBC Radio comedy series ''[[The Goon Show]]''. His ability to speak in different accents (e.g., French, Indian, American, German, as well as British regional accents), along with his talent to portray a range of characters to comic effect, contributed to his success as a radio personality and screen actor and earned him national and international nominations and awards. Many of his characters became ingrained in public perception of his work. Sellers' private life was characterised by turmoil and crises, and included emotional problems and [[substance abuse]]. Sellers was married four times, and had three children from the first two marriages.

An enigmatic figure, he often claimed to have no identity outside the roles that he played, but he left his own portrait since, &quot;he obsessively filmed his homes, his family, people he knew, anything that took his fancy right to the end of his life—intimate film that remained undiscovered until long after his death in 1980.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Arena, BBC , ''The Peter Sellers Story...As He Filmed It''&lt;/ref&gt; The director [[Peter Hall (director)|Peter Hall]] has said: &quot;Peter had the ability to identify completely with another person, and think his way physically, mentally and emotionally into their skin. Where does that come from? I have no idea. Is it a curse? Often. I think it's not enough, though, in this business to have talent.  You have to have ''talent to handle the talent.'' And that I think Peter did ''not'' have.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Peter Hall, on Arena BBC TV ''The Peter Sellers Story...As He Filmed It&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
[[Image:Peter Sellers Birthplace Portsmouth.jpg|thumb|Peter Sellers' birthplace on the corner of Castle Road and [[Southsea]] terrace, in [[Southsea]]; the blue plaques read &quot;Peter Sellers, Actor and Comedian was born here&quot;]]
Sellers was born in [[Southsea]], Portsmouth, to a family of entertainers. Though christened Richard Henry, his parents always called him Peter, after his elder [[stillbirth|stillborn]] brother,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Sikov| first=Ed | title=Mr. Strangelove: a biography of Peter Sellers | year=2002 | publisher=Pan MacMillan | isbn=0283072970}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, according to [[Bryan Forbes]], &quot;was, during his formative years, totally smothered in maternal affection&quot;. He attended the North London [[Catholic school|Roman Catholic school]] [[St Aloysius College, London|St. Aloysius College]]. His father, [[Yorkshire]]-born Bill Sellers, was [[Protestant]] and his mother, Agnes Doreen 'Peg' ''née'' Marks was [[Jew]]ish, the daughter of Solomon Marks and his wife, Welcome Mendoza. Agnes was a first cousin, three times removed, of famous boxer [[Daniel Mendoza]] (1764-1836), not, as is commonly believed, his great-granddaughter.&lt;ref name=&quot;findagrave&quot;&gt;[http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=7468939]&lt;/ref&gt;  As an adult, notes film critic [[Alexander Walker (critic)|Alexander Walker]], Mendoza was the ancestor Sellers &quot;most revered,&quot; and he usually kept an engraving of him hanging in his office. At one time he planned on having Mendoza's image for his production company's logo.

According to Sellers' biographer Roger Lewis, Sellers was intrigued by Catholicism, but soon after entering Catholic school, he &quot;discovered he was a Jew—he was someone on the outside of the mysteries of faith.&quot; Sellers says that teachers referred to him as &quot;The Jew&quot;, which led to his subsequent sensitivity to anti-semitic innuendos. He was a top student at the school, and recalls that the teacher once scolded the other boys for not studying: &quot;The Jewish boy knows his [[catechism]] better than the rest of you!&quot;&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|203}}

Later in his life, Sellers is quoted as saying &quot;My father was solid [[Church of England]] but my mother was Jewish—[[Portuguese people|Portuguese]] Jewish—and Jews take the faith of their mother.&quot;&lt;ref name=Lewis&gt;Lewis, Roger. ''The Life and Death of Peter Sellers'', Hal Leonard Corp. (1997) p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; Film critic [[Kenneth Tynan]] noted after his interview with Sellers that one of the main &quot;motive forces&quot; for his ambition as an actor was &quot;his hatred of [[Anti-Semitism|anti-semitism]].&quot; Tynan explained:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In scholars, lawyers, doctors and vaudeville comedians, Jewishness is tolerated. In legitimate actors, much less often. . . . Hence [Peter Seller's refusal] to be content with the secure reputation of a great mimic and his determination to go down in history as something more—a great actor, perhaps, or a great director.&lt;ref name=Walker&gt;Walker, Alexander. ''Peter Sellers'', Macmillan Publ. N.Y. (1981) pp. 10–13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Sellers was of the opinion that &quot;becoming part of some large group never does any good. Maybe that's my problem with religion,&quot; he said during an interview. He explained:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I wasn't baptised. I wasn't Bar Mitzvahed. I suppose my basic religion is doing unto others as they would do unto me. But I find it all very difficult. I am more inclined to believe in the Old Testament than in the New . . . .&lt;ref name=Playboy&gt;''Playboy'' magazine Interview, October 1962&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Accompanying his family on the [[variety show]] circuit,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt; Sellers learned [[stagecraft]], which proved valuable later. He performed at age five at the burlesque [[Windmill Theatre]] in the drama ''Splash Me!'', which featured his mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/education/2002/oct/05/highereducation.biography | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Here, there and everywhere | date=5 October 2002 | accessdate=22 May 2010 | first=Simon | last=Louvish}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, he grew up with conflicting influences from his parents and developed ambivalent feelings about show business. His father lacked confidence in Peter's abilities to ever become much in the entertainment field, even suggesting that his son's talents were only enough to become a road sweeper, while Sellers' mother encouraged him continually.&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|18}}

Sellers got his first job at a theatre in [[Ilfracombe]], when he was 15, starting as a janitor. He was steadily promoted, becoming a box office clerk, usher, assistant stage manager, and lighting operator. He was also offered some small acting parts.&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt; Working backstage gave him a chance to see serious actors at work, such as [[Paul Scofield]]. He also became close friends with Derek Altman, and together they launched Sellers' first stage act under the name &quot;Altman and Sellers,&quot; where they played ukuleles, sang, and told jokes. They also both enjoyed reading detective stories by [[Dashiell Hammett]], and were inspired to start their own detective agency. &quot;Their enterprise ended abruptly when a potential client ripped Sellers' fake moustache off.&quot;&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;

At his regular job backstage at the theatre, Sellers began practising on a set of drums that belonged to the band &quot;[[Joe Daniels (jazz drummer)|Joe Daniels]] and His Hot Shots.&quot;  Joe Daniels began noticing his efforts and gave him some practical instructions. Sellers' biographer Ed Sikov writes that &quot;drumming suited him. Banging in time Pete could envelop himself in a world of near-total abstraction, all in the context of a great deal of noise.&quot;&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|20}}

==World War II period==
As war broke out in Europe, Sellers continued to develop his drumming skills, which strongly impressed even his father and landed Sellers his first drumming job with a band in [[Blackpool]].&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|22}}

He later enlisted, and during [[World War II]] Sellers was an airman in the [[Royal Air Force]], rising to corporal, though he had been restricted to ground staff because of poor eyesight. His tour included India and [[Burma]], although the duration of his stay in Asia is unknown and its length may have been exaggerated by Sellers himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot;/&gt; He also served in Germany and France after the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt; As a distraction from the life of a non-commissioned officer, Sellers joined the [[Entertainments National Service Association]] (ENSA), which his father had earlier also signed up with, allowing him to hone his drumming and comedy. By the end of the war in 1945, more than four out of five British entertainers had worked for ENSA, whose focus was on boosting morale of soldiers and factory workers.&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;

He occasionally impersonated his superiors,&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt; and his portrayal of RAF officer Lionel Mandrake in the film ''[[Dr. Strangelove]]'' may have been modelled on them. He bluffed his way into the Officers' Mess using mimicry and the occasional false moustache, although as he told [[Michael Parkinson]] in the 1972 interview, occasionally older officers would suspect him. The voice of ''[[Goon Show]]'' character [[Major Bloodnok|Major Dennis Bloodnok]] came from this period.{{fact|date=August 2011}}

==Early career==
===The Goon Show===
{{Main|The Goon Show}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Peter Sellers and wife 1951.jpg|thumb|With Anne Hayes after their wedding, 1951]] --&gt;After his discharge and return to England in 1948, Sellers supported himself with stand-up routines in [[variety theatre]]s whose impresarios needed to legitimise their business.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt; Sellers telephoned [[BBC]] radio producer Roy Speer, pretending to be [[Kenneth Horne]], star of the radio show ''[[Much Binding in the Marsh]]'', to get Speer to speak to him. Speer reportedly called Sellers a &quot;cheeky young sod&quot; for this.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IuaN3K4AMmk Peter Sellers/Parkinson interview]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, Sellers was given an audition, which led to his work on ''Ray's a Laugh'' with comedian [[Ted Ray (comedian)|Ted Ray]]. His principal radio work was on ''[[The Goon Show]]'' with [[Spike Milligan]], [[Harry Secombe]] and (originally) [[Michael Bentine]]. Sellers followed this with television work.

===Records===
In the late 1950s, Sellers released two comedy records produced by [[George Martin]]: ''The Best of Sellers'' and ''Songs for Swinging Sellers''. ''The Best of Sellers'' album cover (first released in 10&quot; format in 1958 and his debut LP) pictured him polishing a [[Rolls-Royce (car)|Rolls-Royce]] motor car. The most popular tracks on this album were &quot;[[Balham, Gateway to the South]]&quot; (a parody travelogue) and &quot;Suddenly It's Folksong&quot; where a group of people end up smashing up a pub after a row over someone playing a [[bum note]]. The ''Songs for Swinging Sellers'' album, released in 1959, whose title parodied [[Frank Sinatra]]'s album [[Songs for Swinging Lovers]], contained material written by [[Frank Muir]] and [[Denis Norden]], and featured Sellers performing &quot;Puttin on the Style&quot; (a parody of the [[skiffle]] movement's performer [[Lonnie Donegan]]). Sellers also appeared with guest [[Irene Handl]] on the track &quot;Shadows on the Grass&quot; where he played the part of a Frenchman befriending a lady in the park. Musical direction was by [[Ron Goodwin]].

In 1963, Sellers worked with [[Anthony Newley]], [[Leslie Bricusse]] and [[Joan Collins]] to produce the LP ''Fool Britannia''.  This comprised a series of sketches satirising the British political scandal the [[Profumo Affair]], in which the Minister for War was revealed to have lied about his relationship with a prostitute who was also involved with a Russian diplomat.  The album was controversial, in part perhaps because of material involving the royal family, and would-be buyers in the United Kingdom found it especially hard to obtain.

A 1965 hit was a spoof spoken version of the Beatles' &quot;A Hard Day's Night&quot;, in the style of Laurence Olivier. This followed up various pieces of Olivier-style speech in the Goons.

In 1979 he released a new [[gatefold]] album entitled ''Sellers' Market'' (the cover shows him standing next to traders reading the ''Financial Times'' and the ''Wall Street Journal'' whereas Sellers is reading the ''Finchley Press'') which included comic singing and a feature called the &quot;All England George Formby Finals&quot; where he parodies the late [[George Formby, Jr.|George Formby]] and his [[ukulele]] playing. Also featured was the ''Complete Guide to Accents of the British Isles''. The album was not as popular as his first two in 1958 and 1959 although it is still sought after by collectors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://music.msn.com/music/album-review/peter-sellers/sellers-market/?silentchk=1&amp; |title=Sellers Market by Peter Sellers on MSN Music |publisher=Music.msn.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; All of his albums exploited Sellers's ability to use his flexible voice to comedic effect.

==Acting technique and preparation==
In an October 1962 interview for ''[[Playboy]]'', Sellers described how he prepared for acting roles once he agreed to play the part:

{{cquote|Well, having got to the stage where one sees a final script and has discussed the part with all concerned, I start with the voice. I find out how the character sounds. It's through the way he speaks that I find out the rest about him. I suppose that approach comes from having worked in radio for so long. After the voice comes the looks of the man. I do a lot of drawings of the character I play. Then I get together with the makeup man and we sort of transfer my drawings onto my face. An involved process. After that I establish how the character walks. Very important, the walk. And then, suddenly, something strange happens. The person takes over. The man you play begins to exist. I sink myself completely into every character I play, because he has begun to live in me. I suddenly seem to know what sort of life that man has had and how he would react to a given situation.&lt;ref name=Playboy/&gt;}}

==Film career==
Sellers' film success arrived with [[British comedy|British comedies]], including ''[[The Ladykillers]]'', ''[[I'm All Right Jack]]'' and ''[[The Mouse That Roared (film)|The Mouse That Roared]]''. In his early film roles, he continued to exploit his ability to do accents and different voices, often in character parts and occasionally playing several distinct roles in a single film. In his second movie, he played two parts; in his third, six (see chart below).

In ''[[The Smallest Show on Earth]]'', the 27-year-old actor played a doddering, drunken elderly projectionist twice his actual age. In ''The Mouse That Roared'', set in a small European country, he played three major and distinct roles, the elderly queen, the ambitious Prime Minister, and the innocent and clumsy farm boy selected to lead an invasion of the United States. In the United States he received considerable publicity for playing three parts, a stunt he would do again in ''Dr. Strangelove''.

He began receiving international attention for his portrayal of an Indian doctor in ''[[The Millionairess]]'' with [[Sophia Loren]]. The film inspired the [[George Martin]]-produced [[Novelty song|novelty]] hit single ''[[Goodness Gracious Me (song)|Goodness Gracious Me]]'' and its follow-up ''Bangers and Mash'', both featuring Sellers and Loren.

===''Lolita''===
In 1962, [[Stanley Kubrick]] asked Sellers to play the role of Clare Quilty in ''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]'' opposite [[James Mason]] and [[Shelley Winters]]. Kubrick had seen Sellers in his earlier films and was intrigued by his range, also demonstrated during ''The Goon Show'' period when Sellers had done impressions of famous people, such as [[Winston Churchill]], [[Elizabeth II|the Queen]], and [[Lew Grade]].

However, Sellers felt the part of a flamboyant American television playwright was beyond his ability, mainly because Quilty was, in Sellers' words, &quot;a fantastic nightmare, part [[homosexual]], part [[drug addict]], part [[sadist]]...&quot;. He became nervous about taking on the role, and many people came up to him and told him they felt the role believable.&lt;ref&gt;The Times Newspaper; June 27, 1962&lt;/ref&gt; Kubrick eventually succeeded in persuading Sellers to play the part, however. Kubrick had American jazz producer [[Norman Granz]] record Sellers' portions of the script for Sellers to listen to, so he could study the voice and develop confidence.&lt;ref name=LoBrutto/&gt;

Unlike most of his earlier well-rehearsed movie roles, Sellers was encouraged by Kubrick to improvise throughout the filming in order to exhaust all the possibilities of his character. Moreover, in order to capture Sellers at his most creative heights, Kubrick often used as many as three cameras. Sellers and Kubrick created the multiple disguises used by Sellers, such as a state trooper and a German psychologist. As filming progressed, the other actors and the crew would notice Sellers' greatly enjoying his acting and, according to Kubrick, reaching &quot;...what can only be described as a state of comic ecstasy&quot;.&lt;ref name=LoBrutto&gt;LoBrutto, Vincent. ''Stanley Kubrick: A Biography'', Da Capo Press (1999) pp. 204–205&lt;/ref&gt; The movie's cinematographer, [[Oswald Morris]], further commented that, &quot;the most interesting scenes were the ones with Peter Sellers, which were total improvisations.&quot;&lt;ref name=LoBrutto/&gt;

Because of this experience, Sellers found that his relationship with Kubrick became one of the most rewarding of his career.&lt;ref name=LoBrutto/&gt;

===''Dr. Strangelove''===
{{Image gallery
|title=
|lines=1
|width=200
|height=
|Dr. Strangelove - Group Captain Lionel Mandrake.png||&lt;center&gt;Group Captain Mandrake&lt;/center&gt;
|Dr. Strangelove - President Merkin Muffley.png||&lt;center&gt;President Merkin Muffley&lt;/center&gt;
|Dr. Strangelove.png||&lt;center&gt;Dr. Strangelove&lt;/center&gt;
}}
In Kubrick's next film, ''[[Dr. Strangelove|Dr. Strangelove or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb]]'' he asked Sellers to be in the leading role. Sellers played three extremely different characters: U.S. President [[Merkin]] Muffley, Dr. Strangelove, a heavily German-accented nuclear scientist, and Group Captain Lionel [[Mandrake (plant)|Mandrake]] of the [[Royal Air Force|RAF]]. Sellers was initially hesitant about taking on the task, but Kubrick convinced him that there was no better actor that could play these parts.&lt;ref name=LoBrutto/&gt;

Muffley and  Dr. Strangelove appeared in the same room throughout the film, with the help of doubles mostly seen from the rear. Sellers was originally also cast to play a fourth role as bomber pilot Major T. J. &quot;King&quot; Kong, but from the beginning Sellers was reluctant. He felt his workload was too heavy and he worried he would not properly portray the character's Texas accent. Kubrick pleaded with him and asked screenwriter [[Terry Southern]] (who had been raised in Texas) to record a tape with Kong's lines spoken in the correct accent. Using Southern's tape, Sellers managed to get the accent right, and started shooting the scenes in the airplane. But then Sellers sprained an ankle and could not work in the cramped cockpit set.&lt;ref name=Southern&gt;Terry Southern, [http://www.visual-memory.co.uk/amk/doc/0081.html &quot;Notes from The War Room&quot;], ''Grand Street'', issue #49&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Southern2&gt;Lee Hill, [http://www.altx.com/int2/terry.southern.html &quot;Interview with a Grand Guy&quot;]: interview with Terry Southern&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the fictionalized biopic ''[[The Life and Death of Peter Sellers]]'', it is suggested that Sellers faked the injury as a way to force Kubrick to release him from the contractual obligation to play this fourth role.&lt;/ref&gt;This forced Kubrick to recast the part with [[Slim Pickens]]. For his performance in all three roles, Sellers was nominated for an [[Academy Award for Best Actor]]. Kubrick again gave Sellers a free rein to improvise throughout the filming. Sellers once said, &quot;If you ask me to play myself, I will not know what to do. I do not know who or what I am.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Kinn, Gail; Piazza, Jim. ''The Greatest Movies Ever'', Black Dog Publishing (2008) p. 127&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Pink Panther''===
[[File:Sellers pinkpanther7.jpg|thumb|left|175px|Peter Sellers as [[Inspector Clouseau|Chief Inspector Clouseau]] in ''[[The Pink Panther]]'']] From 1963, Sellers was cast as the bumbling [[Inspector Clouseau|Chief Inspector Clouseau]] in ''[[The Pink Panther]]'' movies. This character gave Sellers a worldwide audience, beginning with ''[[The Pink Panther (1963 film)|The Pink Panther]]'' and its sequel, ''[[A Shot in the Dark (1964 film)|A Shot in the Dark]]'', in which he featured more prominently. He returned to the character for three more sequels from 1975 to 1978. ''[[Trail of the Pink Panther|The Trail of the Pink Panther]]'', containing unused footage of Sellers, was released in 1982, after his death. His widow, [[Lynne Frederick]], successfully sued the film's producers for unauthorised use. Sellers had prepared to star as Chief Inspector Clouseau in another Pink Panther film; he died before the start of this project, ''[[Romance of the Pink Panther]]''.

===''Being There''===
In 1979, Sellers played the role of Chance, a simple gardener addicted to watching TV, in the [[black comedy]] ''[[Being There]]'', considered by some critics to be the &quot;crowning triumph of Peter Sellers's remarkable career,&quot;&lt;ref name=Smith&gt;Smith, Danny. &quot;Giving Peter Sellers a Chance: Danny Smith talks to Jerzy Kosinski&quot;, ''Third Way'', Feb. 1981 pp. 22–23&lt;/ref&gt; as well as a great achievement for novelist [[Jerzy Kosinski]]. During a [[BBC]] interview in 1971, Sellers said that more than anything else, he wanted to play the role of Chance.&lt;ref name=Smith/&gt;

Kosinski, the book's author, felt that the novel was never meant to be made into a film, but Sellers succeeded in changing his mind, and Kosinski allowed Sellers and director [[Hal Ashby]] to make the film, provided he could write the script.&lt;ref name=Smith/&gt; According to film critic Danny Smith, Sellers was &quot;naturally intrigued with the idea of Chance, a character who reflected whatever was beamed at him&quot;.&lt;ref name=Dawson&gt;Dawson, Nick. ''Being Hal Ashby: Life of a Hollywood Rebel'', Univ. of Kentucky Press (2009) p. 147, 211&lt;/ref&gt;

Sellers's performance was praised by some critics as achieving &quot;the pinpoint-sharp exactitude of nothingness. It is a performance of extraordinary dexterity&quot;,&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|361}} and &quot;...[making] the film's fantastic premise credible&quot;.&lt;ref name=Rich&gt;Rich, Frank. [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,921794-2,00.html &quot;Gravity Defied&quot;] ''Time'', Jan. 14, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Sellers-Time 3-3-80.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Cover story, March 3, 1980&lt;/center&gt;{{ifdc|File_name.ext|log=2011 April 18|date=April 2011}}]]  --&gt;Sellers's experience of working on the film was both humbling and powerful for him.&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt; During the filming, in order not to break his character, he refused most interview requests, and even kept his distance from other actors. He tried to remain in character even after he returned home.&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt; Sellers considered Chance's walking and voice the character's most important attributes, and in preparing for the role, Sellers worked alone with a tape recorder, or with his wife, and then with Ashby, to perfect the clear enunciation and flat delivery needed to reveal &quot;the childlike mind behind the words.&quot;&lt;ref name=Dawson/&gt;

Critic [[Frank Rich]] noted the acting skill required for this sort of role, with a &quot;schismatic personality that Peter had to convey with strenuous vocal and gestural technique. . . . A lesser actor would have made the character's mental dysfunction flamboyant and drastic. . . . [His] intelligence was always deeper, his onscreen confidence greater, his technique much more finely honed.&quot;&lt;ref name=Rich/&gt;

''Being There'' earned Sellers his best reviews since the 1960s, a second [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]] nomination and a [[Golden Globe]] award. A few months after the film was released, ''Time'' magazine wrote a cover-story article about Sellers, entitled, &quot;Who is This Man?&quot; The cover showed many of the characters Sellers had portrayed, including Chance, Quilty, Strangelove, Clouseau, and the Grand Duchess Glorianna XII. Sellers was pleased by the article, written by critic [[Richard Schickel]], and wrote an appreciative letter to the magazine's editor.&quot;&lt;ref name=Sikov/&gt;{{rp|373}}

=== Final projects ===

Sellers' last movie was ''[[The Fiendish Plot of Dr. Fu Manchu]]'', a comedic reimagining of the classic series of adventure novels by [[Sax Rohmer]]. In this new version, Sellers played both &quot;Fu Manchu&quot; and his arch nemesis, police inspector [[Nayland Smith]]. Production of the film ran into problems from the start, with Sellers' poor health and mental instability causing long delays and bickering between star and director [[Piers Haggard]]. With roughly 60% of the movie shot, Sellers had Haggard sacked and took over direction himself. Haggard later complained that the reshoots Sellers ordered added nothing to the production, and had resulted in the film being incoherent and unfocused. The movie contains references to Sellers' serious heart troubles, including scenes where Fu revives his ancient body with large electric shocks.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=sEAVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ZQgEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6000,6771812&amp;hl=en&lt;/ref&gt;

Sellers died shortly before ''Fu Manchu'' was released, with his very last performance being that of conman &quot;Monty Casino&quot; in a series of adverts for [[Barclays Bank]].  In 1982, Sellers returned to the big screen as Inspector Clouseau in ''[[Trail of the Pink Panther]]'', which was composed entirely of deleted scenes from his past three ''Panther'' movies, in particular ''[[The Pink Panther Strikes Again]]'', with a new story written around them.  David Niven also reprised his role of Sir Charles Lytton in this movie.  Along with what many, notably his widow [[Lynne Frederick]], saw as exploitation of Sellers, the manner in which Niven's cameo was handled has earned the movie a lasting unsavoury reputation.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} Edwards continued the series with a further instalment called the ''[[Curse of the Pink Panther]]'', which was shot back to back with the framing footage for ''Trail'', but Sellers was wholly absent from this film.

After ''The Fiendish Plot of Dr. Fu Manchu'', Sellers was scheduled to appear in another Clouseau comedy, ''[[The Romance Of The Pink Panther]]''. Its script, written by Peter Moloney and Sellers himself, had Clouseau falling for a brilliant female criminal known as 'The Frog' and aiding her in her heists with the aim to reform her character.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}  Blake Edwards did not participate in the planning of this new Clouseau instalment, as the working relationship between him and Sellers had broken down during the filming of ''Revenge Of The Pink Panther''. The final draft of the script, including a humorous cover letter signed by &quot;Pete [[Shakespeare]]&quot;, was delivered to United Artists' office less than six hours before Sellers died.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} Sellers death ended the project, along with two other planned movies for which Sellers had signed contracts in 1980. The two films—''[[Unfaithfully Yours]]'' and ''[[Lovesick]]''—were rewritten as vehicles for [[Dudley Moore]]; both performed poorly at the box office upon release.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} [[Trade papers]] such as ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' carried an elaborately curlicued advert for the former movie, with Sellers at the top of the cast list, in early June 1980.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}

===Other roles===
Director [[Billy Wilder]] hired Sellers to co-star with [[Dean Martin]] for the ribald 1964 comedy ''[[Kiss Me, Stupid]]'', but six weeks into filming, Sellers suffered a heart attack. Wilder replaced him with [[Ray Walston]].

Sellers was a versatile actor, switching from broad comedy, as in ''[[The Party (film)|The Party]]'', in which he portrayed a bumbling Indian actor Hrundi Bakshi, to more intense performances as in ''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]''.

Sellers appeared in an episode of the American television series ''[[It Takes a Thief (1968 TV series)|It Takes a Thief]]'' in 1969.  By the early 1970s he faced a downturn, however, and was dubbed &quot;box office poison&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thegroggysquirrel.com/articles/2006/07/16/peter-sellers/ |title=Dead Comics Society — Peter Sellers |date=2006-07-16 |author=Annette Slattery |publisher=[[The Groggy Squirrel]] |accessdate=2007-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sellers never won an Oscar but won the [[British Academy Award|BAFTA]] for ''I'm All Right Jack''.

Sellers appeared on ''[[The Muppet Show]]'' television series in 1977. He chose not to appear as himself, instead appearing in a variety of costumes and accents. When [[Kermit the Frog]] told Sellers he could relax and be &quot;himself,&quot; Sellers (while wearing a Viking helmet, a girdle and one boxing glove, claiming to have attempted to dress as [[Queen Victoria]]), replied, &quot;There is no me. I do not exist. There used to be a me, but I had it surgically removed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zSJc72OC7Dg |title=Peter Sellers on the Muppet Show }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Peter Sellers in Alps.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Sellers on vacation in the [[Swiss Alps]], near the end of his life.&lt;/center&gt;]] --&gt;Sellers was reticent about discussing his private life. He was invited to appear on [[Michael Parkinson]]'s [[Parkinson (TV series)|eponymous chat show]] in 1974, but agreed under the condition that he could appear in character. Sellers appeared dressed as a member of the [[Gestapo]], impersonating the [[Kenneth Mars]] character in ''[[The Producers (1968 film)|The Producers]]''. After a few lines in keeping with his assumed character, he stepped out of the role and settled down for what is considered one of Parkinson's most memorable interviews.&lt;ref&gt;''Parkinson: The Interviews'' series&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt;[http://uk.youtube.com/watch?v=TMt-WygUDnQ YouTube: Peter Sellers's 1974 interview on ''Parkinson'']&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

===Marriages===
[[File:Britt Ekland and Peter Sellers 1964 crop.jpg|right|thumb|Sellers and [[Britt Ekland]] 1964]]
Sellers was married four times and fathered three children:

* Anne Hayes (née Howe,&lt;ref name=Lewis111&gt;{{Cite book |title=The life and death of Peter Sellers |author=Roger Lewis |publisher=Applause Books N.Y. |year=1997 |page=111 |isbn=1-55783-248-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1951–1961). They had a son, [[Michael Sellers (actor)|Michael]], and a daughter, Sarah.
* Swedish actress [[Britt Ekland]] (1964–1968). They had a daughter, [[Victoria Sellers]]. The couple appeared in three films together: ''[[Carol For Another Christmas]]'' (1964), ''[[After the Fox]]'' (1966), and ''[[The Bobo]]'' (1967).
* Australian model [[Miranda Quarry]] (now the [[Miranda Macmillan, Countess of Stockton|Countess of Stockton]]; 1970–1974).
* English actress [[Lynne Frederick]] (1977–1980), who was briefly married to [[David Frost (broadcaster)|Sir David Frost]] shortly after Sellers' death.

[[Spike Milligan]] wrote Sellers' multiple marriages into his scripts, referring in one 1972 radio show to &quot;The Peter Sellers Discarded Wives Memorial&quot;. At the time, Sellers was married to Quarry.

===Depression, substance abuse, and health problems===
It has been suggested that Sellers suffered [[major depressive disorder|depression]] spurred by deep-seated anxieties of artistic and personal failure&lt;ref&gt;Sikov, Mr. Strangelove: A Biography of Peter Sellers, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; and exacerbated by [[substance abuse]].&lt;ref&gt;Sikov, p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; It is believed that his drug use, especially [[amyl nitrite]]s, contributed to [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]]s in 1964 (see below).&lt;ref&gt;Lewis. The Life and Death of Peter Sellers, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; Sellers' difficulties in his career and life prompted him to seek periodic consultations with astrologer [[Maurice Woodruff]], who seemed to have held considerable sway over his later career.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt;

===Relationships===
====Other celebrities====
Sellers had casual friendships with two of [[The Beatles]], [[George Harrison]] and [[Ringo Starr]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot;/&gt; Harrison told occasional Sellers stories in interviews, and Starr appeared with him in the anarchic movie ''[[The Magic Christian (film)|The Magic Christian]]'', which was based on Terry Southern's novel and whose theme song was [[Badfinger]]'s &quot;[[Come and Get It (Badfinger song)|Come and Get It]]&quot;, written by [[Paul McCartney]].  Starr's two-week hiatus from the Beatles during the ''[[The Beatles (album)|White Album]]'' recordings was spent aboard Sellers's yacht, where he wrote &quot;Octopus's Garden&quot;.  Starr also gave Sellers a rough mix of songs from the Beatles' ''[[The Beatles (album)|White Album]]''; the tape was auctioned and [[Bootleg recording|bootlegged]] after his death. Sellers recorded a [[cover version]] of &quot;[[A Hard Day's Night (song)|A Hard Day's Night]]&quot;, in the style of [[Laurence Olivier]]'s interpretation of [[Richard III (play)|Richard III]], as well as various versions of &quot;[[She Loves You]]&quot;, including as Dr. Strangelove, a [[cockney]], and an Irish dentist.

[[Image:Playboy April 1964.jpg|thumb|Sellers was the first male to appear on the cover of ''[[Playboy]]'' magazine.&lt;ref name=AH&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.accesshollywood.com/seth-rogen-to-grace-cover-of-playboy_article_14561 | title=Seth Rogen To Grace Cover Of Playboy | publisher=Access Hollywood | date=18 Feb 2009 | accessdate= 1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Sellers's friends included actor and director [[Roman Polanski]], who shared his passion for fast cars. Sellers had a close relationship with [[Sophia Loren]], but accounts differ on whether or not their relationship was consummated.&lt;ref&gt;Sikov, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt; Sellers was the first man on the cover of ''[[Playboy]]''—he appeared on the April 1964 cover with Karen Lynn.&lt;ref name=AH /&gt;

Sellers was a [[Freemason]] and belonged to Chelsea Lodge No 3098, a lodge whose membership consists of celebrities and performers, through which means he socialised with a number of other actors and comedians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mqmagazine.co.uk/issue-11/p-20.php |title=MQ magazine on-line |publisher=Mqmagazine.co.uk |date=1903-05-01 |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Royal Family====
In her autobiography ''[[True Britt]]'', [[Britt Ekland]] described Sellers' close relationship with the [[British Royal Family|Royal Family]].
&quot;I was completely unaware of his (Sellers) connection with the British monarchy. One afternoon before we married he had disappeared saying that he had to do something 'important'. I was to learn he had spent afternoon tea with the [[Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon|Queen Mother]] at [[Clarence House]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/0139310894 |title=Page 58, True Britt by Britt Ekland |publisher=Amazon.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was a close friend of [[Princess Margaret]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1099594.stm &quot;Margaret: Unlucky in Love&quot;, BBC World News, 9 February 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;, who appears in one of his home movies.

===Obsession with automobiles===
Sellers had a lifelong obsession with cars, briefly parodied in a fleeting cameo in the short film ''Simon Simon'', directed by friend [[Graham Stark]]. His love of cars was also referenced in ''[[The Goon Show]]'' episode &quot;The Space Age,&quot; where [[Harry Secombe]] introduces Sellers by saying, &quot;Good heavens, it's Peter Sellers, who has just broken his own record of keeping a car for more than a month.&quot; In &quot;[[The Goon Show#Radio and television|The Last Goon Show of All]]&quot;, announcer [[Andrew Timothy]] cued him with &quot;Mr. Sellers will now sell a [[gross (unit)|gross]] of his cars and take up a dramatic voice.&quot;

===Personal conflicts===
Sellers' personality was described by others as difficult and demanding and he often clashed with fellow actors and directors. He had a strained relationship with friend and director [[Blake Edwards]], with whom he worked on the ''Pink Panther'' series and ''The Party''. The two sometimes stopped speaking to each other during filming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt;

His work with [[Orson Welles]] on ''[[Casino Royale (1967 film)|Casino Royale]]'' deteriorated as Sellers became jealous of Welles's casual relationship with [[Princess Margaret]]. The relationship between the two actors created problems during filming, as Sellers refused to share the set with Welles, who himself was no stranger to strident behaviour.

Sellers could be cruel and disrespectful, as demonstrated by his treatment of actress [[Jo Van Fleet]] on the set of ''[[I Love You, Alice B. Toklas]]''. On one occasion, Van Fleet had declined an invitation to his house, soon followed by a misunderstanding between the two actors during filming. This prompted Sellers to launch a tirade against Van Fleet in front of actors and crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt;

Sellers' difficulties to maintain civil and peaceful relationships also extended into his private life. He assaulted his then wife, [[Britt Ekland]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt; prompted by jealousy. Sellers sometimes blamed himself for his failed marriages. In a 1974 ''Parkinson'' interview, he admitted that &quot;I'm not easy to live with&quot;.

==Heart condition and death==
In the spring of 1964, at age 38, Sellers suffered a series of [[myocardial infarction|heart attack]]s (13 in a few days) while working on the set of Billy Wilder's ''[[Kiss Me, Stupid]]'', and he was replaced by [[Ray Walston]].  Although Sellers survived, his heart was permanently damaged. Sellers chose to consult with [[Psychic surgery|psychic healers]] rather than seek conventional Western medical treatment, and his heart condition continued to deteriorate over the next 16 years. In late 1977, he suffered a second major heart attack, resulting in his being fitted with a [[Artificial pacemaker|pacemaker]] to regulate his heartbeat.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=Na4SAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=P_kDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3326,2291592&amp;hl=en google.com/newspapers]{{dead link|date=October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once again, Sellers refused to slow down, nor did he follow doctors' orders and consider open heart surgery, which could well have extended his life by several years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt;

A reunion dinner was scheduled in London with his ''Goon Show'' partners, [[Spike Milligan]] and [[Harry Secombe]], for 25 July 1980. But around noon on 22 July, Sellers collapsed from a massive heart attack in his [[Dorchester Hotel]] room and fell into a coma. He died in a London hospital&lt;!--which one?--&gt; just after midnight on 24 July 1980, aged 54. He was survived by his fourth wife, [[Lynne Frederick]], and his three children. At the time of his death, he was scheduled to undergo [[heart surgery]] in Los Angeles on 30 July 1980.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot; /&gt;

Although Sellers was reportedly in the process of excluding Frederick from his [[will (law)|will]] a week before he died, she inherited almost his entire estate worth an estimated [[pound sterling|£]]4.5 million while his children received £800 each.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot;/&gt; When Frederick died in 1994 (aged 39), her mother Iris inherited everything, including all of the income and royalties from Sellers' work. When Iris dies&lt;!--are we sure she is alive?--&gt; the whole estate will go to Cassie, the daughter Lynne had with her third husband, Barry Unger. Sellers' only son, Michael, died of a heart attack at 52 during surgery on 24 July 2006 (26 years to the day after his father's death).&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph&quot;/&gt; Michael was survived by his second wife, Alison, whom he married in 1986, and their two children.

In his will, Sellers requested that the [[Glenn Miller]] song &quot;[[In the Mood]]&quot; be played at his funeral. The request is considered his last touch of humour, as he hated the piece.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.petersellersappreciationsociety.com/HTML/Biography.php |title=petersellersappreciationsociety.com |publisher=petersellersappreciationsociety.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; His body was cremated and he was interred at [[Golders Green Crematorium]] in London. After her death in 1994, the ashes of his former widow Frederick were co-interred with his.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/femail/article-1138807/The-girl-got-Peter-Sellers-5m--met-him.html Mail Online] The girl who got Peter Sellers' £5m – and she never even met him&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy and influence==
The stage play, “Being Sellers,” premiered in Australia in 1998, three years after release of the biography by Roger Lewis, “The Life and Death of Peter Sellers.” The play premiered in New York in December 2010. In 2004, the book was turned into an [[HBO]] film, ''[[The Life and Death of Peter Sellers]]'', starring [[Geoffrey Rush]].&lt;ref name=JW&gt;Merwin, Ted. [http://www.thejewishweek.com/arts/theater/who_was_peter_sellers &quot;Who Was Peter Sellers?&quot;], ''The Jewish Week'', Nov. 23, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

The film ''[[Trail of the Pink Panther]]'', made by Blake Edwards using unused footage of Sellers from ''[[The Pink Panther Strikes Again]]'', is dedicated to Sellers's memory. The title reads &quot;To Peter&amp;nbsp;... The one and only Inspector Clouseau.&quot;

In a 2005 poll to find &quot;The Comedian's Comedian&quot;, Sellers was voted 14 in the list of the top 20 greatest comedians by fellow comedians and comedy insiders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/4141019.stm |title=Cook voted 'comedians' comedian' |accessdate=2008-06-15 |work=[[BBC News]] |date=2005-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt; British comedian [[Sacha Baron Cohen]] frequently referred to Peter Sellers &quot;as the most seminal force in shaping his early ideas on comedy&quot;. Cohen  was considered for the role of the biopic ''[[The Life and Death of Peter Sellers]]'' (the role went to Australian actor [[Geoffrey Rush]]).&lt;ref name=Saunders&gt;Saunders, Robert A. ''The Many Faces of Sacha Baron Cohen,'' Lexington Books (2007) p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

==Filmography==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
! style=&quot;background:#B0C4DE;&quot; | Year
! style=&quot;background:#B0C4DE;&quot; | Film
! style=&quot;background:#B0C4DE;&quot; | Role
! style=&quot;background:#B0C4DE;&quot; | Notes
|-
| 1950
|''[[The Black Rose]]''
|Alfonso Bedoya
|Voice (uncredited)
|-
|rowspan=2| 1951
|''[[Penny Points to Paradise]]''
| The Major/Arnold Fringe
|
|-
|''[[Let's Go Crazy (film)|Let's Go Crazy]]''
|Groucho/Giuseppe/Cedric&lt;br /&gt;/Izzy/Gozzunk/Crystal Jollibottom
|
|-
| 1952
|''[[Down Among the Z Men]]''
|Major Bloodnok
|
|-
| 1953
|''[[Our Girl Friday]]''
| Parrot
|Voice (uncredited)
|-
| 1954
|''[[Orders are Orders]]''
|Private Griffin
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1955
|''[[John and Julie]]''
|Police Constable Diamond
|
|-
|''[[The Ladykillers]]''
|Mr. Robinson
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1956
|''[[The Case of the Mukkinese Battle Horn]]''
|Narrator/Supt. Quilt&lt;br /&gt;/Asst. Commissioner Sir Jervis Fruit/Henry Crun
|
|-
|''[[The Man Who Never Was]]''
|[[Winston Churchill]]
|Voice only
|-
|rowspan=3| 1957
|''[[Insomnia Is Good for You]]''
|Hector Dimwiddle
|Short film
|-
|''[[The Smallest Show on Earth]]''
|Leslie Quill
|
|-
|''[[The Naked Truth (1957 film)|The Naked Truth]]''
|Sonny McGregor
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1958
|''[[Up the Creek (1958 film)|Up the Creek]]''
|CPO Doherty
|
|-
|''[[tom thumb (film)|tom thumb]]''
|Antony
|
|-
|rowspan=4| 1959
|''[[Carlton-Browne of the F.O.]]''
|Prime Minister Amphibulos
|
|-
|''[[The Mouse That Roared]]''
|Grand Duchess Gloriana XII / Prime Minister&lt;br /&gt;Count Rupert Mountjoy / Tully Bascombe
|Three roles.
|-
|''[[I'm All Right Jack]]''
|Fred Kite
|[[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role|BAFTA Award for Best British Actor]]
|-
|''[[The Battle of the Sexes (1959 film)|The Battle of the Sexes]]''
|Mr. Martin
|
|-
|rowspan=4| 1960
|''[[The Running Jumping &amp; Standing Still Film]]''
|Photographer
|Short Film&lt;br /&gt;Also Writer/Producer/Director&lt;br /&gt;[[San Francisco International Film Festival|San Francisco International Film Festival Award for Best Fiction Short]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Academy Award for Best Live Action Short Film]]
|-
|''[[Never Let Go]]''
|Lionel Meadows
|
|-
|''[[The Millionairess]]''
|Dr. Ahmed el Kabir
|
|-
|''[[Two-Way Stretch]]''
|Dodger Lane
|
|-
| 1961
|''[[Mr. Topaze]]''
|Auguste Topaze
| Also Director
|-
|rowspan=5| 1962
|''[[Only Two Can Play]]''
|John Lewis
|Nominated — [[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role|BAFTA Award for Best British Actor]]
|-
|''[[Waltz of the Toreadors (film)|Waltz of the Toreadors]]''
|General Leo Fitzjohn
|[[San Sebastián International Film Festival|San Sebastián International Film Festival Award for Best Actor]]
|-
|''[[The Road to Hong Kong]]''
|Indian Neurologist
|Uncredited
|-
|''[[Lolita (1962 film)|Lolita]]''
|Clare Quilty
|Nominated — [[Golden Globe Award for Best Supporting Actor – Motion Picture]]
|-
|''[[Trial and Error (1962 film)|Trial and Error]]''
|Wilfred Morgenhall
|
|-
|rowspan=3| 1963
|''[[The Wrong Arm of the Law]]''
|Pearly Gates
|
|-
|''[[Heavens Above!]]''
|The Reverend John Smallwood
|
|-
|''[[The Pink Panther (1963 film)|The Pink Panther]]''
|[[Inspector Jacques Clouseau]]
|First in the [[Pink Panther]] series&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role|BAFTA Award for Best British Actor]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Musical or Comedy]]
|-
|rowspan=3| 1964
|''[[Dr. Strangelove|Dr. Strangelove or: How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Love the Bomb]]''
|Group Captain Lionel Mandrake / President Merkin Muffley / Dr. Strangelove
|Three roles&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Academy Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role|BAFTA Award for Best British Actor]]
|-
|''[[The World of Henry Orient]]''
|Henry Orient
|
|-
|''[[A Shot in the Dark (1964 film)|A Shot in the Dark]]''
|Inspector Jacques Clouseau
|Sequel to the [[Pink Panther (film)|Pink Panther]]
|-
|rowspan=2| 1965
|''[[Birds, Bees and Storks]]''
|Narrator
|Voice
|-
|''[[What's New Pussycat]]''
|Doctor Fritz Fassbender
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1966
|''[[The Wrong Box]]''
|Doctor Pratt
|
|-
|''[[After the Fox]]''
|Aldo Vanucci
|
|-
|rowspan=3| 1967
|''[[Casino Royale (1967 film)|Casino Royale]]''
|Evelyn Tremble
|Also (Uncredited) Writer
|-
|''[[Woman Times Seven]]''
|Jean
|
|-
|''[[The Bobo]]''
|Juan Bautista
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1968
|''[[The Party (film)|The Party]]''
|Hrundi V. Bakshi
|
|-
|''[[I Love You, Alice B. Toklas!]]''
|Harold
|
|-
| 1969
|''[[The Magic Christian (film)|The Magic Christian]]''
| Sir Guy Grand KG, KC, CBE
|Also Writer
|-
|rowspan=4| 1970
|''[[A Day at the Beach]]''
|Salesman
|
|-
|''[[Hoffman (film)|Hoffman]]''
|Benjamin Hoffman
|
|-
|''[[Simon, Simon]]''
|Man with two cars
|
|-
|''[[There's a Girl in My Soup]]''
|Robert Danvers
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1972
|''[[Where Does It Hurt?]]''
| Dr. Albert T. Hopfnagel
|
|-
|''[[Alice's Adventures in Wonderland (1972 film)|Alice's Adventures in Wonderland]]''
|The March Hare
|
|-
|rowspan=3| 1973
|''[[Ghost in the Noonday Sun]]''
|Dick Scratcher
|
|-
|''[[The Blockhouse]]''
|Rouquet
|
|-
|''[[The Optimists (1973 film)|The Optimists]]''
|Sam
|
|-
|rowspan=2| 1974
|''[[Soft Beds, Hard Battles]]''
|Général Latour / Major Robinson / Herr Schroeder &lt;br /&gt;/ Adolf Hitler / The President / Prince Kyoto
|Played six roles.
|-
|''[[The Great McGonagall (film)|The Great McGonagall]]''
|[[Queen Victoria]]
|
|-
| 1975
|''[[The Return of the Pink Panther]]''
|Inspector Jacques Clouseau
|Third film by Sellers in the [[Pink Panther]] series&lt;br /&gt;[[List of Evening Standard British Film Awards|Evening Standard British Film Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Musical or Comedy]]
|-
|rowspan=2| 1976
|''[[Murder by Death]]''
|Sidney Wang
|
|-
|''[[The Pink Panther Strikes Again]]''
|Chief Inspector Jacques Clouseau
|Fourth film by Sellers in the [[Pink Panther]] series&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Musical or Comedy]]
|-
|rowspan=3| 1978
|''[[List of The Muppet Show episodes#Season 2 (1977–1978)|The Muppet Show]]''
|Various characters, including Inspector Clouseau, a [[Romani people|gypsy]], Queen Victoria, a masseur, and a preacher.
|Episode 43 originally aired February 27, 1978 in New York, and February 24, 1978 in Los Angeles
|-
|''[[Kingdom of Gifts]]''
|Larcenous Mayor
|Voice only
|-
|''[[Revenge of the Pink Panther]]''
|Chief Inspector Jacques Clouseau
|Fifth film by Sellers in the [[Pink Panther]] series
|-
|rowspan=2| 1979
|''[[The Prisoner of Zenda (1979 film)|The Prisoner of Zenda]]''
|Rudolf IV / Rudolf V / Syd Frewin
| Played three roles.
|-
|''[[Being There]]''
|Chance
|Fotogramas de Plata for Best Foreign Performance&lt;br /&gt;[[Golden Globe Award for Best Actor – Motion Picture Musical or Comedy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[London Film Critics Circle Award|London Film Critics Circle Special Award]]&lt;br /&gt;[[National Board of Review Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[Academy Award for Best Actor]]&lt;br /&gt;Nominated — [[BAFTA Award for Best Actor in a Leading Role|BAFTA Award for Best British Actor]]
|-
| 1980
|''[[The Fiendish Plot of Dr. Fu Manchu]]''
|Dennis Nayland Smith / Dr. Fu 'Fred' Manchu
| Last film. Played two roles.&lt;br /&gt;Also (Uncredited) Director
|-
| 1982
|''[[Trail of the Pink Panther]]''
|Chief Inspector Jacques Clouseau
| Footage of Sellers used.
|}

==Comedy singles==
Sellers released several comedy singles, many of them produced by [[George Martin]] and released on the [[Parlophone]] record label. These include the following hits:
* &quot;Any Old Iron&quot; (1957) UK # 17
* &quot;[[Goodness Gracious Me (song)|Goodness Gracious Me]]&quot; (1960) with [[Sophia Loren]] UK # 4
* &quot;Bangers and Mash&quot; (1961), a follow-up also featuring [[Sophia Loren]] UK # 22
* &quot;A Hard Day's Night&quot; (1965) UK # 14.  This consisted of him speaking the lyrics using the stereotypical voice of an actor playing Shakespeare's [[Richard III (play)|Richard III]].  He also performed the song in costume on television.  The recording was re-issued in 1993 and reached Number 52 in the [[UK Singles Chart]].
He covered several other of [[The Beatles]] hits, including &quot;[[Help! (song)|Help!]]&quot; and &quot;[[She Loves You]]&quot;. Sellers also recorded a parody version of &quot;[[Unchained Melody]]&quot;, which long went unreleased.

When asked in 1960 what he thought the music business would be like in ten years' time, Sellers retorted:
{{cquote|Ten years older!}}
''[[NME]]'', November 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;NME Rock 'N' Roll Years&quot;&gt;{{cite book
| first= John
| last= Tobler
| year= 1992
| title= NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
| edition= 1st
| publisher= Reed International Books Ltd
| location= London
| page= 89
| id= CN 5585}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Albums==
Sellers made several albums, mostly of comedy pieces using his talent for voices.

Discography:
* ''[[The Best of Sellers]]'' (1959) UK # 3
* ''Songs For Swinging Sellers'' (1959) UK # 3
* ''Peter &amp; Sophia'' (1960) UK # 5 with [[Sophia Loren]]
* ''Fool Britannia'' (1963) UK # 10 with [[Anthony Newley]] and [[Joan Collins]].
* ''How To Win An Election'' (1964) UK # 20 with [[Harry Secombe]] and [[Spike Milligan]] (Note: unlike ''[[The Goons|The Last Goon Show Of All]]'' this release was not credited to [[The Goons]].)
* ''He's Innocent of Watergate'' (1974) with [[Spike Milligan]]
* ''Sellers Market'' (1979) his final album

==Further reading==
* {{cite book | last= Lewis | first= Roger | title= The Life and Death of Peter Sellers.| year= 1995 | publisher= Arrow Books | location= London | isbn= 0-09-974700-6}} 1108 pages.  [http://www.applausepub.com/itemDetail.jsp?itemid=314323&amp;order=0&amp;keywords=peter+sellers Published in the U.S. via Applause Books] [[Roger Lewis]]'s biography of Sellers is very comprehensive, and includes a very comprehensive index.
* ''Mr Strangelove; A Biography of Peter Sellers'', a book by Ed Sikov&lt;ref name=&quot;Sikov&quot;/&gt;
* ''P.S. I Love You'' by Michael Sellers 1981&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph&quot;&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?view=DETAILS&amp;grid=&amp;xml=/news/2006/08/05/db0502.xml The Telegraph UK] Details on Michael Sellers&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''A Hard Act to Follow'' Michael Sellers (with Gary Morecambe, 1996).&lt;ref name=&quot;The Independent&quot;&gt;[http://news.independent.co.uk/people/obituaries/article1217373.ece The Independent UK] Michael Sellers Obituary 7 August 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* '' Sellers on Sellers'' Michael Sellers (2000, co-written with Gary Morecambe)&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph&quot;/&gt;
*{{citation |date=20 June 1960 |author=Zinsser, William K |authorlink=William Zinsser |title=Peter Sellers: An unpredictable, irrepressible, irreverent mimic |journal=[[Life (magazine)|Life]] |pages=63–70 (see p.66) |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=5k4EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA64&amp;dq=%22peter+sellers%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=mAJzTKC2K4qUvAO89IXbDg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22peter%20sellers%22&amp;f=false |accessdate=23 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* ''[[The Life and Death of Peter Sellers]]'' (2004), [[HBO]]/[[BBC]] movie with [[Geoffrey Rush]] in the title role.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* {{IMDb name|id=0000634}}
* {{Tcmdb name|id=173984}}
* {{Screenonline name|id=461941}}
*[http://www.webofstories.com/play/53438 Ken Adam talks about Peter Sellers on the set of Dr Strangelove] (video)

* [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1238363/Peter-Sellers-kidnapped-Jesus-Spare-thought-man-spent-Christmas-coping-deranged-comic-genius.html John Atrobus recalls his memorable Christmas with Peter Sellers] Daily Mail Dec. 27, 2009.


===Video clips===
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j30-8Pc6USs&amp;feature=related &quot;The Unknown Peter Sellers&quot;], documentary
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZPyDY5aZyXs Peter Sellers tribute]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DnW0HoFbuAE&amp;feature=related Peter Sellers on &quot;The Goon Show,&quot; playing drums]
*[http://www.youtube.com/user/thefilmprojector#p/u/7/zLEMncv140s in stage skit of &quot;A Hard Day's Night&quot;]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SX6vrnz5tJY in ''Lolita'']
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hWP_rEWG2xk as U.S. president in ''Dr. Strangelove'']
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A9ihKq34Ozc&amp;feature=related as Dr. Strangelove]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DUAK7t3Lf8s&amp;feature=related as British captain Mandrake in ''Dr. Strangelove'']
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PfWvWRqrAig&amp;feature=related in ''The Party'']
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FcPQ9gww_qc in ''Being There'']

{{BAFTA Award for Best Actor 1952-1959}}
{{GoldenGlobeAwardBestActorMotionPictureMusicalComedy 1961-1980}}
{{Goons}}
{{Pink Panther}}

{{Authority control|PND=119336197|LCCN=n/50/6864|VIAF=49387018|SELIBR=}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME = Sellers, Peter
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Sellers, Richard Henry
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = British comedian &amp; actor
|DATE OF BIRTH = 8 September 1925
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Southsea]], [[Hampshire]],  England
|DATE OF DEATH = 24 July 1980
|PLACE OF DEATH = London, England}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Sellers, Peter}}
[[Category:1925 births]]
[[Category:1980 deaths]]
[[Category:BAFTA winners (people)]]
[[Category:Best British Actor BAFTA Award winners]]
[[Category:Best Musical or Comedy Actor Golden Globe (film) winners]]
[[Category:Commanders of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Deaths from myocardial infarction]]
[[Category:English comedians]]
[[Category:English film actors]]
[[Category:English impressionists (entertainers)]]
[[Category:English Jews]]
[[Category:English radio actors]]
[[Category:English television actors]]
[[Category:Jewish actors]]
[[Category:Jewish comedians]]
[[Category:People from Southsea]]
[[Category:People from Portsmouth]]
[[Category:Royal Air Force airmen]]

[[ar:بيتر سلرز]]
[[an:Peter Sellers]]
[[az:Piter Sellers]]
[[bn:পিটার সেলার্স]]
[[bg:Питър Селърс]]
[[bs:Peter Sellers]]
[[ca:Peter Sellers]]
[[cs:Peter Sellers]]
[[cy:Peter Sellers]]
[[da:Peter Sellers]]
[[de:Peter Sellers]]
[[el:Πίτερ Σέλλερς]]
[[es:Peter Sellers]]
[[eo:Peter Sellers]]
[[eu:Peter Sellers]]
[[fa:پیتر سلرز]]
[[fr:Peter Sellers]]
[[hi:पीटर सेलर्स]]
[[hr:Peter Sellers]]
[[id:Peter Sellers]]
[[it:Peter Sellers]]
[[he:פיטר סלרס]]
[[la:Petrus Sellers]]
[[hu:Peter Sellers]]
[[nl:Peter Sellers]]
[[ja:ピーター・セラーズ]]
[[no:Peter Sellers]]
[[pl:Peter Sellers]]
[[pt:Peter Sellers]]
[[ro:Peter Sellers]]
[[ru:Селлерс, Питер]]
[[simple:Peter Sellers]]
[[sk:Peter Sellers]]
[[sr:Питер Селерс]]
[[sh:Peter Sellers]]
[[fi:Peter Sellers]]
[[sv:Peter Sellers]]
[[tl:Peter Sellers]]
[[tr:Peter Sellers]]
[[uk:Пітер Селлерс]]
[[zh:彼得·塞勒斯]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
