<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2452248" ns="0" title="Weekend Today"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television |
  | show_name = Today&lt;br/&gt;''&lt;small&gt;(weekend editions)&lt;/small&gt;''
  | show_name_2 = Weekend Today, Saturday Today, Sunday Today
  | image =  
  | caption = 
  | format = [[news program]], [[live action]]
  | runtime = 120 [[minute]]s (2 [[hour]]s) (Sat); 
60 minutes (1 [[hour]]) (Sun) 
  | presenter = [[Lester Holt]] (2003&amp;ndash;present) &lt;br&gt; [[Amy Robach]] (2007&amp;ndash;present)&lt;br&gt; Saturdays: &lt;br&gt; [[Jenna Wolfe]] (2007&amp;ndash;present)&lt;br&gt; Sundays: &lt;br&gt; [[Bill Karins]] (2009&amp;ndash;present)&lt;br&gt; Sundays: &lt;br&gt; [[Janice Huff]] (1995&amp;ndash;present)
| country = [[United States]]
  | network = [[NBC]]
  | picture_format = [[480i]] ([[SDTV]]), &lt;br&gt; [[1080i]] ([[HDTV]])
  | first_aired = September 20, 1987
  | last_aired = present
}}

'''''Weekend Today''''' is the unofficial title of the weekend editions of '''''[[Today (NBC program)|Today]]''''', an [[United States|American]] morning news and talk show which airs daily on [[NBC]]. 

==History==
The Sunday edition of ''Today'' (''Sunday Today'') premiered on September 20, 1987 hosted by [[Boyd Matson]] and [[Maria Shriver]]. The program was broadcast at 8:00 a.m. ET and was 90 minutes long with ''[[Meet the Press]]'' following at 9:30 a.m.  Five years later, on August 1, 1992, the Saturday edition made its debut, expanding the broadcast schedule of the ''Today'' show franchise to seven days a week. The program is broadcast from [[GE Building#NBC Studio productions|Studio 1A]] (also houses ''[[Dateline NBC|Dateline]]'') in Rockefeller Plaza in New York, although ''Sunday Today'' originated from [[Washington, D.C.|Washington]] for a few years.  The Sunday edition of ''Today'' scaled back to one hour while ''Meet the Press'' expanded to an hour.

The weekend editions were initially titled ''Saturday Today'' or ''Sunday Today'', as applicable, in order to distinguish them from the weekday program. Since the late 1990s, all editions of the program have officially simply carried the title ''Today'', although ''Weekend Today'' is still used for promotional purposes, in order to distinguish it from its weekday counterpart.

==Format==
The weekend broadcasts continue the ''[[Today (NBC program)|Today]]'' tradition of covering breaking news, interviewing newsmakers, reporting on a variety of popular-culture and human-interest stories, covering health and finance issues and presenting the latest weather reports. Just like the Weekday edition, the show offers visitors to New York City a chance to observe firsthand the workings of a live television broadcast with its windowed studio on [[Rockefeller Plaza]]. Interaction with the crowd outside the studio is a major part of the program.  

Unlike the weekday edition of Today where news updates are reported at the top of the hour, news updates are given every half hour.

Weekend editions are tailored to the priorities and interests of weekend viewers—offering special series such as '''''Saturday Today on the Plaza''''', featuring live performances by the biggest names in music and Broadway outside the studio throughout the summer.

Pat Burkey is the Executive Producer of ''Weekend Today''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Burkey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/29055142|title=About Today|publisher=MSNBC.com|accessdate=2009-08-09|date=May 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Show times==
The show is live from 7:00 a.m. to 9:00 a.m. ET on Saturdays, although some affiliates chose to tape-delay the program.  Some stations in the western half of the country choose to air it at 5:00 local time.

On Sunday, the show is aired live from 8:00 a.m. to 9:00 a.m. ET. Most NBC affiliates choose to air two editions of their local morning newscast around the Sunday edition of ''Weekend Today'', with the first hour of the local newscast airing before and the second hour airing after the program.

Some affiliates choose not to air part - or the entire show at all.

==Current on-air staff==
===Anchors===
*[[Lester Holt]], Co-Anchor (2003&amp;ndash;present)  
*[[Amy Robach]], Saturday Co-Anchor (2007&amp;ndash;present)
*[[Jenna Wolfe]], Sunday Co-Anchor (2007&amp;ndash;present)

===News anchors===
There is no permanent news anchor for the Weekend Edition.  Personalities from various NBC News divisions fill in on those days.

===Weather anchors===
*[[Bill Karins]] -  Saturday Weather Anchor (2009&amp;ndash;present)
*[[Janice Huff]] - Sunday Weather Anchor (1995&amp;ndash;present)

==Former on-air staff==
===Anchors===
''Sunday Today'' anchors included:
*[[Boyd Matson]] Sunday Co-Anchor (1987&amp;ndash;1988)
*[[Maria Shriver]], Sunday Co-Anchor (1987&amp;ndash;1990)
*[[Garrick Utley]], Sunday News Anchor (1987&amp;ndash;1988) Sunday Co-Anchor (1988&amp;ndash;1992)
*[[Al Roker]], Weather Anchor (1987&amp;ndash;1996)
*[[Katherine Couric]], Sunday Co-Anchor (1990&amp;ndash;1991)
*[[Mary Alice Williams]], Sunday Co-Anchor (1991&amp;ndash;1992)

''Weekend Today'' anchors included:
*[[Scott Simon]], Co-Anchor (1992&amp;ndash;1993)
*[[Jackie Nespral]], Co-Anchor (1992&amp;ndash;1995)
*[[Mike Schneider (news anchor)|Mike Schneider]], Co-Anchor (1993&amp;ndash;1995)
*[[Giselle Fernández|Giselle Fernandez]], Co-Anchor (1995&amp;ndash;1996)
*[[Jack Ford (news anchor)|Jack Ford]], Co-Anchor (1995&amp;ndash;1999)
*Carol Martin, Co-Anchor (1996)
*[[Jodi Applegate]], Co-Anchor (1996&amp;ndash;1999)
*[[Soledad O'Brien]], Co-Anchor (1999&amp;ndash;2003)
*[[David Bloom]], Co-Anchor (1999&amp;ndash;2003)
*[[Campbell Brown]], Co-Anchor (2003&amp;ndash;2007)

==Theme music==
''Scherzo for Today'' was used as the program's closing theme until [[1990 in television|1990]], and the ''Mission'' bumpers were used until [[1993 in television|1993]]. (One of them could be heard as a station break lead-in on NBC's ''[[Meet The Press]]'' until [[2004 in television|2004]].) ''The Today Show'' opening fanfare has opened the program ever since, with two exceptions. In the summer of [[1994 in television|1994]], to mark the debut of Studio 1A, the Williams-penned fanfare was replaced by another opening theme, but the Williams theme returned shortly thereafter. In 2004, the show's producers tried out yet another theme, which drew once again on the NBC chimes as its signature, but the Williams theme returned after only a few weeks. It is by far the most enduring theme in the program's history, having now been in use for over two decades.

The ''Scherzo for Today'' was iconically accompanied by [[Fred Facey]] announcing &quot;From NBC News, this is ''Today''...&quot; until his death in April 2003, except for special editions requiring special introductions.  Facey's work is now only heard on the [[MSNBC]] program ''[[Headliners and Legends]]''. 

Currently, a lighter theme employing the NBC chimes is used to open the show's 7:30 and 8:30 half-hour segments, and also used as a closing theme.

==Special editions==
Following the [[Space Shuttle Columbia disaster]] on February 1, 2003, ''Weekend Today'' aired a special edition on Sunday, February 2, with the expanded introduction {{cquote|Disaster: The Space Shuttle Columbia. From NBC News, this is a special edition of ''Today'' with Soledad O'Brien at [[Kennedy Space Center]] in [[Cape Canaveral, Florida]] and David Bloom at the [[Johnson Space Center]] in [[Houston]], [[Texas]].}}

The next day was also a special edition with [[Matt Lauer]] at Studio 1A in New York and [[Katie Couric]] at the Johnson Space Center in Houston.

On April 6, 2003, the death of Bloom in Iraq dominated that day's edition. Soledad O'Brien, Matt Lauer, and Katie Couric hosted a special edition of ''Today'' to remember Bloom.

When [[Pope John Paul II]] died on Saturday, April 2, 2005, Katie Couric and Matt Lauer anchored the weekend editions of ''The Today Show''. Lauer anchored from the Vatican with Campbell Brown offering reports by his side. On the day of the Pope's death, Couric anchored a special report on a Vatican statement updating the Pope's dire condition and Lauer reported for the special report anchored by [[Brian Williams]] when the Pope was officially dead. He returned to New York as Couric traveled to [[Vatican City]] to co-anchor coverage of the Pope's funeral with Williams.

On April 19, 2008, special edition of Weekend Today featured [[Pope Benedict XVI]]'s visit to the United States, billed as &quot;The Pope Visits the USA.&quot; [[Lester Holt]] and [[Jenna Wolfe]] moved outside to [[Rockefeller Center]] to cover the first papal mass at [[St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York|St. Patrick's Cathedral]] in [[New York City]]. However, they moved back to Studio 1A at the 7:30 half hour.

On May 10, 2008, Weekend Today featured a special split edition coveing the wedding of [[Jenna Bush]] at the President's ranch outside [[Crawford, Texas]].  Co-anchor Lester Holt remained at Studio 1A, while Amy Robach covered the wedding from Texas.

On June 14, 2008, a special edition occurred because of the death of [[Tim Russert]], NBC's Washington Bureau Chief and Moderator of ''[[Meet the Press]]''. [[Matt Lauer]] and [[Tom Brokaw]] anchored this edition of &quot;Today.&quot; [[Andrea Mitchell]], [[David Gregory (journalist)|David Gregory]], [[Pete Williams (television correspondent)|Pete Williams]], [[Lisa Myers]], [[Bob Schieffer]], host of ''[[Face the Nation]]'', [[George Stephanopoulos]], host of ''[[This Week (ABC TV series)|This Week]]'', and [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]] [[Dick Cheney]], among others, appeared on &quot;Today.&quot; The next day, there was another special edition, hosted by Gregory and Mitchell on the death of Russert.

On April 30, 2011, [[Natalie Morales]] and [[Al Roker]] anchored a special edition of “Weekend Today” from London during the wedding of [[Prince William, Duke of Cambridge|Prince William]] and the former [[Catherine, Duchess of Cambridge|Kate Middleton]].

==Viewership==
The program is watched by more viewers than [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]'s ''[[Good Morning America Weekend Edition]]'' and [[CBS]]' ''[[The Early Show#The Saturday Early Show|Saturday Early Show]]''&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen ratings from November 2007 as released with [http://www.nbcumv.com/news/release_detail.nbc/news-20071130000000-039weekendtoday.html NBC press release]&lt;/ref&gt;, but less than those of ''[[CBS News Sunday Morning]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen ratings from November 2007 as released with [http://www.cbspressexpress.com/div.php/cbs_news/release?id=17369 CBS press release]&lt;/ref&gt;

==International broadcasts==
* In Australia, ''Weekend Today'' airs at 4:00AM Mondays on the [[Seven Network]], followed by ''[[Meet The Press]]''.  
* In the Philippines, the Saturday and Sunday editions air on [[Talk TV (Philippines)|Talk TV]] on Saturdays at 7:00pm and Sundays at 8:00 pm local time.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/3688676/''Weekend Today'' official site]
*[http://imdb.com/title/tt0291679/ ''Weekend Today''] on the [[Internet Movie Database]]

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{Today}}
{{NBC News Personalities}}
}}
[[Category:1987 television series debuts]]
[[Category:NBC network shows]]
[[Category:American news television series]]
[[Category:1980s American television series]]
[[Category:1990s American television series]]
[[Category:2000s American television series]]
[[Category:NBC News]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
