<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24573" ns="0" title="Pepsi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the beverage|its manufacturer|PepsiCo|the singer|Pepsi Demacque}}
{{distinguish|PEPPSI}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Lead too short|date=November 2009}}
{{Infobox Beverage
|name=Pepsi
|image=[[Image:Pepsi logo 2008.svg|250px|Current Pepsi logo (December 2008-).]]
|type=[[Cola]]
|manufacturer=[[PepsiCo]].
|origin= North Carolina, U.S.A.
|area_served=[[Worldwide]]
|introduced=1898 (as Brad's Drink)&lt;br /&gt;June 16, 1903 (as Pepsi-Cola)&lt;br /&gt;1961 (as Pepsi)
|related= [[Coca-Cola]]&lt;br /&gt;[[7 Up]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Irn Bru]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Cola Turka]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Big Cola]]
|website= [http://pepsi.com/ pepsi.com]
}}
{{Infobox nutrition facts
|serv_size_us= 12 fl oz
|serv_size_met= 355&amp;nbsp;ml
|#_servings= 1
|calories= 150&lt;ref name=&quot;Pepsi Nutritional Info&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pepsi.ca/default.aspx?bhcp=1#/en/products | title=Pepsi Nutritional Info | accessdate=March 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|cal_from_fat= 0
|total_fat_g= 0
|sat_fat_g= 0
|trans_fat_g= 0
|cholesterol_mg= 0
|sodium_mg= 15
|potassium_mg= 0
|carb_g= 41
|fiber_g= 0
|sugars_g= 41
|protein_g= 0
|vit_a= 0
|vit_c= 0
|calcium= 0
|iron= 0
}}
'''Pepsi''' (stylized in lowercase as '''pepsi''', formerly stylized in uppercase as '''PEPSI''') is that is produced and manufactured by [[PepsiCo]]. Created and developed in 1898 and introduced as &quot;Brad's Drink&quot;, it was later renamed as Pepsi-Cola on June 16, 1903, then to Pepsi in 1961.

==History==
[[File:HMB Bern New Bern Caleb Bradham.jpg|thumb|The pharmacy of Caleb Bradham, with a Pepsi dispenser, as portrayed in a New Bern exhibition in the [[Historical Museum of Bern]].]]
Pepsi was first introduced as &quot;Brad's Drink&quot; in [[New Bern, North Carolina]], [[United States]], in 1898 by [[Caleb Bradham]], who made it at his home where the drink was sold. It was later labeled Pepsi Cola, named after the digestive enzyme [[pepsin]] and [[kola nuts]] used in the recipe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080212003647/http://www.sodamuseum.bigstep.com/generic.jhtml?pid=3 Soda Museum - The History of Pepsi Cola]&lt;/ref&gt; Bradham sought to create a fountain drink that was delicious and would aid in digestion and boost energy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepsistore.com/history.asp The History of the Birthplace of Pepsi-Cola]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1903, Bradham moved the bottling of Pepsi-Cola from his drugstore to a rented warehouse. That year, Bradham sold 7,968 gallons of [[syrup]]. The next year, Pepsi was sold in six-ounce bottles, and sales increased to 19,848 gallons. In 1909, automobile race pioneer [[Barney Oldfield]] was the first celebrity to endorse Pepsi-Cola, describing it as &quot;A bully drink...refreshing, invigorating, a fine bracer before a race.&quot; The advertising theme &quot;Delicious and Healthful&quot; was then used over the next two decades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Pepsi - FAQs
 | publisher = [[PepsiCo]]
 | url = http://www.pepsiusa.com/faqs.php?section=highlights
 | quote = 1909: Automobile racing pioneer Barney Oldfield becomes the first celebrity to endorse Pepsi when he appears in newspaper ads describing Pepsi: &quot;A bully drink...refreshing, invigorating, a fine bracer before a race.&quot; The theme &quot;Delicious and Healthful&quot; appears and will be used intermittently over the next two decades.
 | accessdate = 12 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1926, Pepsi received its first logo redesign since the original design of 1905. In 1929, the logo was changed again.

In 1931, at the depth of the [[Great Depression]], the Pepsi-Cola Company entered bankruptcy - in large part due to financial losses incurred by speculating on wildly fluctuating sugar prices as a result of [[World War I]]. Assets were sold and Roy C. Megargel bought the Pepsi trademark.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080212003647/http://www.sodamuseum.bigstep.com/generic.jhtml?pid=3 &quot;The History of Pepsi-Cola&quot;], ''sodamuseum.bigstep.com'' paragraph 8&lt;/ref&gt; Eight years later, the company went bankrupt again!! Pepsi's assets were then purchased by [[Charles Guth]], the President of Loft Inc. Loft was a candy manufacturer with retail stores that contained soda fountains. He sought to replace [[Coca-Cola]] at his stores' fountains after Coke refused to give him a discount on syrup. Guth then had Loft's chemists reformulate the Pepsi-Cola syrup formula.

On three separate occasions between 1922 and 1933, the Coca-Cola Company was offered the opportunity to purchase the Pepsi-Cola company, and it declined on each occasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Mark Pendergrast | title=For God, Country and Coca-Cola | publisher=Basic Books | year=2000 | pages=192–193 | isbn=0-465-05468-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pepsi-Cola trademark==
[[File:Pepsi-original-logo1902-trademarkia.jpeg|thumb|The original stylized Pepsi-Cola logo]]
[[File:Pepsi-original-logo1905-trademarkia.jpeg|thumb|The second stylized Pepsi-Cola logo]]
The original trademark application for Pepsi-Cola was filed on September 23, 1902 with registration approved on June 16, 1903. In the application's statement, Caleb Bradham describes the trademark as an, &quot;arbitrary hyphenated word &quot;PEPSI-COLA,&quot; and indicated that the mark was in continuous use for his business since August 1, 1901. The Pepsi-Cola's description is a flavoring-syrup for soda water. The trademark expired on April 15, 1994.

A second Pepsi-Cola trademark is on record with the USPTO. The application date submitted by Caleb Bradham for the second trademark is Saturday, April 15, 1905 with the successful registration date of April 15, 1906, over three years after the original date. Curiously, in this application, Caleb Bradham states that the trademark had been continuously used in his business &quot;and those from whom title is derived since in the 1905 application the description submitted to the USPTO was for a tonic beverage. The federal status for the 1905 trademark is registered and renewed and is owned by [[Pepsico, Inc.]] of [[Purchase, New York]].

==Rise==
During the Great Depression, Pepsi gained popularity following the introduction in 1936 of a 12-ounce bottle.  With a radio advertising campaign featuring the [[jingle]] &quot;Pepsi-Cola hits the spot / Twelve full ounces, that's a lot / Twice as much for a nickel, too / Pepsi-Cola is the drink for you,&quot; arranged in such a way that the jingle [[Infinite-loop motif|never ends]]. Pepsi encouraged price-watching consumers to switch, obliquely referring to the Coca-Cola standard of six ounces per bottle for the price of five cents (a nickel), instead of the 12 ounces Pepsi sold at the same price.&lt;ref name=&quot;alot&quot;&gt;[http://www.OldRadioFun.com/downloads/Commercials.19xx.xx.xx_Pepsi_Cola.mp3 1939 Radio Commercial (Twice as Much for a Nickel)]&lt;/ref&gt; Coming at a time of economic crisis, the campaign succeeded in boosting Pepsi's status. From 1936 to 1938, Pepsi-Cola's profits doubled.&lt;ref name=&quot;coke at home&quot;&gt;Jones, Eleanor &amp; Ritzmann, Florian. [http://xroads.virginia.edu/~class/coke/coke1.html &quot;Coca-Cola at Home&quot;]. Retrieved June 17, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Students With Pepsi.jpg|thumb|Pepsi]]

Pepsi's success under Guth came while the Loft Candy business was faltering. Since he had initially used Loft's finances and facilities to establish the new Pepsi success, the near-bankrupt Loft Company sued Guth for possession of the Pepsi-Cola company. A long legal battle, ''[[Guth v. Loft]]'', then ensued, with the case reaching the [[Delaware Supreme Court]] and ultimately ending in a loss for Guth.

==Niche marketing==
[[Image:Pepsi targeted ad 1940s.jpg|thumb|1940s advertisement specifically targeting African Americans]]

[[Walter Mack]] was named the new President of Pepsi-Cola and guided the company through the 1940s. Mack, who supported [[progressivism|progressive]] causes, noticed that the company's strategy of using advertising for a general audience either ignored [[African American]]s or used ethnic stereotypes in portraying blacks. He realized African Americans were an untapped [[niche market]] and that Pepsi stood to gain [[market share]] by targeting its advertising directly towards them.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytboyd&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/business/06boyd.html?_r=1&amp;ref=obituaries&amp;oref=slogin | last=Martin | first=Douglas | date=May 6, 2007 | title=Edward F. Boyd Dies at 92; Marketed Pepsi to Blacks. | publisher=[[The New York Times]] | accessdate=2007-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; To this end, he hired [[Hennan Smith]], an advertising executive &quot;from the Negro newspaper field&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;capparellreview&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.usatoday.com/money/books/reviews/2007-01-22-pepsi-book_x.htm?csp=34 | title=Pepsi's challenge in 1940s: Color barrier | publisher=[[USA Today]] | first=Michelle | last=Archer | date=January 22, 2007 | accessdate=2007-05-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; to lead an all-black sales team, which had to be cut due to the onset of [[World War II]]. In 1947, Mack resumed his efforts, hiring [[Edward F. Boyd]] to lead a twelve-man team. They came up with advertising portraying black Americans in a positive light, such as one with a smiling mother holding a [[six pack]] of Pepsi while her son (a young [[Ron Brown (U.S. politician)|Ron Brown]], who grew up to be [[United States Secretary of Commerce|Secretary of Commerce]])&lt;ref name=&quot;latboyd&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.latimes.com/news/obituaries/la-me-boyd5may05,0,7240282,full.story?coll=la-news-obituaries | title=Edward Boyd, 92; Pepsi ad man broke color barriers | publisher=[[Los Angeles Times]] | first=Jocelyn Y | last=Stewart | date=May 5, 2007 | accessdate=2007-05-05}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; reaches up for one. Another [[ad campaign]], titled &quot;Leaders in Their Fields&quot;, profiled twenty prominent African Americans such as [[Nobel Peace Prize]] winner [[Ralph Bunche]] and photographer [[Gordon Parks]].

Boyd also led a sales team composed entirely of blacks around the country to promote Pepsi. [[Racial segregation]] and [[Jim Crow laws]] were still in place throughout much of the U.S.; Boyd's team faced a great deal of discrimination as a result,&lt;ref name=&quot;capparellreview&quot;/&gt; from insults by Pepsi co-workers to threats by the [[Ku Klux Klan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;latboyd&quot;/&gt; On the other hand, it was able to use [[racism]] as a selling point, attacking Coke's reluctance to hire blacks and support by the chairman of Coke for segregationist [[Governor of Georgia]] [[Herman Talmadge]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytboyd&quot;/&gt; As a result, Pepsi's market share as compared to Coke's shot up dramatically. After the sales team visited Chicago, Pepsi's share in the city overtook that of Coke for the first time.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytboyd&quot;/&gt;

This focus on the market for black people caused some consternation within the company and among its affiliates. It did not want to seem focused on black customers for fear [[Caucasian race|white]] customers would be pushed away.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytboyd&quot;/&gt; In a meeting at the [[Waldorf-Astoria Hotel]], Mack tried to assuage the 500 [[bottler]]s in attendance by pandering to them, saying, &quot;We don't want it to become known as a [[nigger]] drink.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pbs.org/kcet/tavissmiley/archive/200702/20070227_boyd.html | first=Smiley | last=Tavis | date=February 27, 2007 | title=Edward Boyd | publisher=[[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] | format=interview | accessdate=2007-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Mack left the company in 1950, support for the black sales team faded and it was cut.

==Marketing==
[[File:Pepsi logo.svg|thumb|Pepsi logo (1970-1991) In 1987, the font was modified slightly to a more rounded version which was used until 1991. This logo is now used for ''[[Throwback (drink)|Pepsi Throwback]]'']]
[[File:Pepsilogo.png|thumb|Pepsi logo (2003–2008). ''Pepsi Wild Cherry'' continued to use this design through March 2010. ''Pepsi ONE'' still uses this design as of October 2011. This logo is still in use in India and other international markets. The original version had the Pepsi wording on the top left of the [[Pepsi Globe]]. In 2007, the Pepsi wording was moved to the bottom of the globe.]]

From the 1930s through the late 1950s, &quot;Pepsi-Cola Hits The Spot&quot; was the most commonly used slogan in the days of old radio, classic motion pictures, and later television. Its jingle (conceived in the days when Pepsi cost only five cents) was used in many different forms with different lyrics. With the rise of radio, Pepsi utilized the services of a young, up-and-coming actress named [[Polly Bergen]] to promote products, oftentimes lending her singing talents to the classic &quot;...Hits The Spot&quot; jingle.

Film actress [[Joan Crawford]], after marrying then Pepsi-Cola President [[Alfred N. Steele]] became a spokesperson for Pepsi, appearing in commercials, television specials and televised [[beauty pageants]] on behalf of the company. Crawford also had images of the soft drink placed prominently in several of her later films. When Steele died in 1959 Crawford was appointed to the Board of Directors of Pepsi-Cola, a position she held until 1973, although she was not a board member of the larger PepsiCo, created in 1965.&lt;ref&gt;[http://joancrawfordbest.com/latimespepsi.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

Through the intervening decades, there have been many different Pepsi theme songs sung on television by a variety of artists, from [[Joanie Summers]] to [[The Jacksons]] to [[Britney Spears]]. (See [[Pepsi#Slogans|Slogans]])

In 1975, Pepsi introduced the [[Pepsi Challenge]] marketing campaign where PepsiCo set up a blind tasting between Pepsi-Cola and rival Coca-Cola. During these blind taste tests the majority of participants picked Pepsi as the better tasting of the two soft drinks. PepsiCo took great advantage of the campaign with [[television commercial]]s reporting the results to the public.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sodamuseum.bigstep.com/generic.jhtml?pid=3 SODAmuseum.com &quot;The History of Pepsi-Cola&quot;], ''sodamuseum.bigstep.com'', paragraph 31&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976 Pepsi, RKO Bottlers in Toledo, Ohio hired the first female Pepsi salesperson, Denise Muck, to coincide with the United States bicentennial celebration.

In 1996, PepsiCo launched the highly successful [[Pepsi Stuff]] marketing strategy. By 2002, the strategy was cited by Promo Magazine as one of 16 &quot;Ageless Wonders&quot; that &quot;helped redefine promotion marketing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepsico.com/PEP_Company/Honors/index.cfm PepsiCo - Company - Honors (2002)], ''Promo'' Magazine, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, PepsiCo redesigned its cans for the fourteenth time, and for the first time, included more than thirty different backgrounds on each can, introducing a new background every three weeks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pepsigallery.com/?or=pw.474 Pepsi Can Gallery]&lt;/ref&gt; One of its background designs includes a string of repetitive numbers, &quot;73774&quot;. This is a numerical expression from a telephone keypad of the word &quot;Pepsi.&quot;

In late 2008, Pepsi overhauled its entire brand, simultaneously introducing a new logo and a [[Minimalism|minimalist]] label design. The redesign was comparable to Coca-Cola's earlier simplification of {{sic|hide=y|its can}} and bottle designs. Pepsi also teamed up with YouTube to produce its first daily entertainment show called Poptub. This show deals with pop culture, internet viral videos, and celebrity gossip.

In 2009, &quot;Bring Home the Cup,&quot; changed to &quot;Team Up and Bring Home the Cup.&quot; The new installment of the campaign asks for team involvement and an advocate to submit content on behalf of their team for the chance to have the [[Stanley Cup]] delivered to the team's hometown by [[Mark Messier]].

Pepsi has official sponsorship deals with three of the four major North American professional sports leagues: the [[National Football League]], [[National Hockey League]] and [[Major League Baseball]]. Pepsi also sponsors [[Major League Soccer]]. It also has the [[naming rights]] to the [[Pepsi Center]], an indoor sports facility in [[Denver, Colorado]].

Pepsi also has sponsorship deals in [[International Cricket Council|international cricket]] teams. The [[Pakistani national cricket team|Pakistan cricket team]] is one of the teams that the brand sponsors. The team wears the Pepsi logo on the front of their test and ODI test match clothing.

On July 6, 2009, Pepsi announced it would make a $1 billion investment in Russia over three years, bringing the total Pepsi investment in the country to $4 billion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://business2press.com/2009/07/06/pepsi-announces-1b-russian-investment/ Business2Press.com &quot;Pepsi Announces $1B Russian Investment&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 2009, Pepsi started marketing itself as Pecsi in [[Argentina]] in response to its name being mispronounced by 25% of the population and as a way to connect more with all of the population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Vescovi, Valentina|title=In Argentina, Pepsi Becomes 'Pecsi'|url=http://adage.com/globalnews/article?article_id=137946|work=AdAge.com|date=July 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2008, Pepsi announced that it would be redesigning its logo and re-branding many of its products by early 2009. In 2009, Pepsi, [[Diet Pepsi]] and [[Diet Pepsi Max|Pepsi Max]] began using all lower-case fonts for name brands, and Diet Pepsi Max was re-branded as Pepsi Max. The brand's [[Pepsi Globe|blue and red globe trademark]] became a series of &quot;smiles,&quot; with the central white band arcing at different angles depending on the product until 2010. Pepsi released this logo in U.S. in late 2008, and later it was released in 2009 in [[Canada]] (the first country outside of the United States for Pepsi's new logo), Brazil, Bolivia, Guatemala, Nicaragua, Honduras, El Salvador, Colombia, Argentina, Puerto Rico, Costa Rica, Panama, Chile, Dominican Republic, the Philippines and Australia. In the rest of the world the new logo has been released in 2010. The old logo is still used in several markets internationally, and has been phased out most recently in [[France]] and [[Mexico]]. The UK started to use the new Pepsi logo on cans in an order different from the US can. In mid-2010, all Pepsi variants, regular, diet, and Pepsi Max, have started using only the medium-sized &quot;smile&quot; Pepsi Globe.

Pepsi and Pepsi Max cans and bottles in Australia now carry the localized version of the new Pepsi Logo. The word Pepsi and the logo are in the new style, while the word &quot;Max&quot; is still in the previous style. [[Pepsi Wild Cherry]] finally received the 2008 Pepsi design in March 2010.

In 2011, for New York Fashion Week, Diet Pepsi introduced a &quot;skinny&quot; can that is taller and has been described as a &quot;sassier&quot; version of the traditional can that Pepsi says was made in &quot;celebration of beautiful, confident women.&quot; The company's equating of &quot;skinny&quot; and &quot;beautiful&quot; and &quot;confident&quot; is drawing criticism from brand critics, consumers who do not back the &quot;skinny is better&quot; ethos, and the National Eating Disorders Association, which said that it takes offense to the can and the company's &quot;thoughtless and irresponsible&quot; comments. PepsiCo Inc. is a Fashion Week sponsor. This new can was made available to consumers nationwide in March.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/leisure/2011/02/11/diet-pepsis-skinny-stirs-controversy-new-yorks-fashion-week/|work=Fox News|title=Diet Pepsi's Skinny Can Stirs Controversy at New York's Fashion Week|date=February 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2011, Pepsi announced that customers will be able to buy a complete stranger a soda at a new &quot;social&quot; vending machine, and even record a video that the stranger would see when they pick up the gift.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

In May 2011, the week before [[Memorial Day]], Pepsi launched a limited edition flavor called &quot;Memorial Day Pepsi&quot;, with [[blueberry]] and [[cherry]] flavors added to the cola.

===Rivalry with Coca-Cola===
{{Main|Cola Wars}}
According to Consumer Reports, in the 1970s, the rivalry continued to heat up the market. Pepsi conducted [[blind taste test]]s in stores, in what was called the &quot;[[Pepsi Challenge]]&quot;. These tests suggested that more consumers preferred the taste of Pepsi (which is believed to have more [[lemon]] oil, and less [[orange (fruit)|orange]] oil, and uses [[vanillin]] rather than [[vanilla]]) to Coke. The sales of Pepsi started to climb, and Pepsi kicked off the &quot;Challenge&quot; across the nation. This became known as the &quot;[[Cola Wars]]&quot;.

In 1985, [[The Coca-Cola Company]], amid much publicity, changed its [[Coca-Cola formula|formula]]. The theory has been advanced that [[New Coke]], as the reformulated drink came to be known, was invented specifically in response to the Pepsi Challenge. However, a consumer backlash led to Coca-Cola quickly reintroducing the original formula as Coke &quot;Classic&quot;.

According to ''[[Beverage Digest]]'''s 2008 report on carbonated soft drinks, PepsiCo's U.S. market share is 30.8 percent, while The Coca-Cola Company's is 42.7 percent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.beverage-digest.com/pdf/top-10_2009.pdf &quot;Special Issue: Top-10 CSD Results for 2008&quot;], ''Beverage Digest'', March 30, 2009 (PDF)&lt;/ref&gt; Coca-Cola outsells Pepsi in most parts of the U.S., notable exceptions being central [[Appalachia]], [[North Dakota]], and [[Utah]]. In the city of  [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]], New York, Pepsi outsells Coca-Cola by a two-to-one margin.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rivals4ever.com/history-of-Pepsi-vs-Coke-Rivalry-5-3.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, Coca-Cola continues to outsell Pepsi in almost all areas of the world. However, exceptions include [[Oman]]; [[India]]; [[Saudi Arabia]]; [[Pakistan]] (Pepsi has been a dominant sponsor of the [[Pakistan cricket team]] since the 1990s); the [[Dominican Republic]]; [[Guatemala]] the [[Provinces and territories of Canada|Canadian provinces]] of [[Quebec]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador]], [[Nova Scotia]], and [[Prince Edward Island]]; and [[Northern Ontario]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.strategymag.com/articles/magazine/20041015/vive.html Vive la difference], ''Strategy Magazine'', October 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Pepsi had long been the drink of Canadian [[Francophone]]s and it continues to hold its dominance by relying on local [[French-speaking Quebecer|Québécois]] celebrities (especially [[Claude Meunier]], of ''[[La Petite Vie]]'' fame) to sell its product.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cassies.ca/caselibrary/winners/PepsiMeunier.pdf|format=PDF|title=The Pepsi 'Meunier' Campaign|publisher=Canadian Advertising Success Stories (Cassies) Case Library|accessdate=2007-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; PepsiCo used the slogan &quot;here, it's Pepsi&quot; (Ici, c'est Pepsi) to answer to Coca-cola publicity &quot;Everywhere in the world, it's Coke&quot; (Partout dans le monde, c'est Coke).

By most accounts, Coca-Cola was India's leading soft drink until 1977 when it left India after a new government ordered The Coca-Cola Company to turn over its secret formula for Coke and dilute its stake in its Indian unit as required by the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act (FERA). In 1988, PepsiCo gained entry to India by creating a joint venture with the Punjab government-owned [[Punjab Agro Industrial Corporation]] (PAIC) and [[Voltas India Limited]]. This joint venture marketed and sold Lehar Pepsi until 1991 when the use of foreign brands was allowed; PepsiCo bought out its partners and ended the joint venture in 1994. In 1993, The Coca-Cola Company returned in pursuance of India's [[Liberalization]] policy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mindfully.org/Water/2005/India-Coca-Cola-Pepsi14mar05.htm &quot;India: Soft Drinks, Hard Cases&quot;], ''The Water Dossier'', March 14, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, The Coca-Cola Company and PepsiCo together held 95% market share of soft-drink sales in India. Coca-Cola India's market share was 52.5%.&lt;ref&gt;[http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/articleshow/1191706.cms &quot;Fizzical Facts: Coke claims 60% mkt share in India&quot;], ''Times News Network'', August 5, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

In Russia, Pepsi initially had a larger market share than Coke but it was undercut once the [[Cold War]] ended. In 1972, PepsiCo company struck a barter agreement with the then government of the [[Soviet Union]], in which PepsiCo was granted exportation and Western marketing rights to [[Stolichnaya]] vodka in exchange for importation and Soviet marketing of [[Pepsi-Cola]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.mg.co.za/articlePage.aspx?articleid=267835&amp;area=/insight/insight__economy__business/|title=Pepsi's comeback, Part II|accessdate=2007-07-21|author=Robert Laing|publisher=[http://www.mg.co.za Mail &amp; Guardian online]|date=2006-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.free-essays.us/dbase/b5/lvt48.shtml Free-Essays.us - Coke Vs. Pepsi&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This exchange led to Pepsi-Cola being the first foreign product sanctioned for sale in the [[U.S.S.R]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.pepsico.com/PEP_Company/History/index.cfm#|title=PepsiCo Company History (1972)|publisher=PepsiCo, Inc|accessdate=2007-07-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reminiscent of the way that Coca-Cola became a cultural icon and its global spread spawned words like &quot;[[coca colonization]]&quot;, Pepsi-Cola and its relation to the Soviet system turned it into an icon. In the early 1990s, the term &quot;[[Pepsi-stroika]]&quot; began appearing as a pun on &quot;[[perestroika]]&quot;, the reform policy of the Soviet Union under [[Mikhail Gorbachev]]. Critics viewed the policy as a lot of fizz without substance and as an attempt to usher in Western products in deals there with the old elites. Pepsi, as one of the first American products in the Soviet Union, became a symbol of that relationship and the Soviet policy.&lt;ref&gt;The word first appeared in an exhibit in the [[Harvard University]] Law School Library in December 1990 to February 1991, then in several articles and books by anthropologist [[David Lempert]], who coined the phrase. Most notable is the third book inside the two volume set, &quot;Pepsi-stroika&quot; in ''Daily Life in a Crumbling Empire: The Absorption of Russia into the World Economy,'' Columbia University Press/ Eastern European Monographs, 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; This was reflected in Russian author Victor Pelevin's book &quot;[[Generation P]]&quot;.

In 1989, [[Billy Joel]] mentioned the rivalry between the two companies in the song &quot;[[We Didn't Start The Fire]]&quot;. The line &quot;Rock &amp; Roll and Cola Wars&quot; refers to Pepsi and Coke's usage of various musicians in advertising campaigns. Coke used [[Paula Abdul]], while Pepsi used [[Michael Jackson]]. Both companies then competed to get other musicians to advertise its beverages.

In 1992, following the [[dissolution of the Soviet Union]], Coca-Cola was introduced to the Russian market. As it came to be associated with the new system, and Pepsi to the old, Coca-Cola rapidly captured a significant market share that might otherwise have required years to achieve. By July 2005, Coca-Cola enjoyed a market share of 19.4 percent, followed by Pepsi with 13 percent.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themoscowtimes.com/stories/2005/12/30/041.html &quot;Coke Versus Pepsi, Santa Versus Moroz&quot;], ''The Moscow Times'', December 30, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

Pepsi did not sell soft drinks in Israel until 1991. Many Israelis and some American Jewish organizations attributed Pepsi's previous reluctance to do battle to the Arab boycott. Pepsi, which has a large and lucrative business in the Arab world, denied that, saying that economic, rather than political, reasons kept it out of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;Israel braces for new conflict: The soda war; Chicago Tribune, January 3, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Slogans===
* 1939–1950: &quot;Twice as Much for a Nickel&quot;
* 1950: &quot;More Bounce to the Ounce&quot;
* 1950–1957: &quot;Any Weather is Pepsi Weather&quot;
* 1957–1958: &quot;Say Pepsi, Please&quot;
* 1958–1960: &quot;Don't be a Tramp, Buy a Can&quot; Zane
* 1961–1964: &quot;Now Its Pepsi for Those Who Think Young&quot; (jingle sung by [[Joanie Sommers]])
* 1964–1967: &quot;Come Alive, You're in the [[Pepsi Generation]]&quot; (jingle sung by Joanie Sommers)
* 1967–1969: &quot;(Taste that beats the others cold) Pepsi Pours It On&quot;.
* 1969–1975: &quot;You've Got a Lot to Live, and Pepsi's Got a Lot to Give&quot;
* 1975–1977: &quot;Buy a can 50p&quot;
* 1977–1980: &quot;Join the Pepsi People (Feeling Free)&quot;
* 1980–1981: &quot;Catch That Pepsi Spirit&quot; ([[David Lucas (composer)|David Lucas]], composer)
* 1981–1983: &quot;Pepsi's got your taste for life&quot;
* 1983: &quot;Its cheaper than Coke!&quot;
* 1983–1984: &quot;Pepsi Now! Take the Challenge!&quot;
* 1984–1991: &quot;Pepsi. The Choice of a New Generation&quot; (commercial with [[Michael Jackson]] and [[The Jacksons]], featuring the Pepsi version of &quot;[[Billie Jean]]&quot;, &quot;[[Bad (Michael Jackson song)|Bad]]&quot; and &quot;[[Black or White]]&quot;. &quot;Black of White&quot;'s was promoting the ''[[Dangerous World Tour]]''.)
* 1984–1988: &quot;Diet Pepsi. The Choice of a New Generation&quot;
* 1988–1989: &quot;Diet Pepsi. The Taste That's Generations Ahead&quot;
* 1989–1990: &quot;Diet Pepsi. The Right One&quot;
* 1989–1992: &quot;Diet Pepsi. The Taste That Beats Diet Coke&quot;
* 1986–1987: &quot;We've Got the Taste&quot; (commercial with [[Tina Turner]])
* 1987–1990: &quot;Pepsi's Cool&quot; (commercial with Michael Jackson, featuring Pepsi version of [[Bad (Michael Jackson song)|Bad]])
* 1990–1991: &quot;You got the right one Baby UH HUH&quot; (sung by Ray Charles for Diet Pepsi)
* 1990–1991: &quot;Yehi hai right choice Baby UH HUH&quot; ([[Hindi]] - meaning &quot;This is the right choice Baby UH HUH&quot;) (India)
* 1991–1992: &quot;Gotta Have It&quot;/&quot;Chill Out&quot;
* 1992:&quot;The Choice Is Yours&quot;
* 1992–1993: &quot;Be Young, Have Fun, Drink Pepsi&quot;
* 1993–1994: &quot;Right Now&quot; ([[Van Halen]] song for the [[Crystal Pepsi]] advertisement)
* 1994–1995: &quot;Double Dutch Bus&quot; (Pepsi song sung by Brad Bentz)
* 1995: &quot;Nothing Else is a Pepsi&quot;
* 1995–1996: &quot;Drink Pepsi. Get Stuff.&quot; [[Pepsi Stuff]] campaign
* 1996:&quot;Change The Script&quot;
* 1996–1997: &quot;Pepsi: There's nothing official about it&quot; (During the Wills World Cup (cricket) held in India/Pakistan/Sri Lanka)
* 1997–1998: &quot;Generation Next&quot; (with the [[Spice Girls]])
* 1998–1999: &quot;Its the cola&quot; (100th anniversary commercial)
* 1999–2000: &quot;For Those Who Think Young&quot;/&quot;The Joy of Pepsi-Cola&quot; (commercial with [[Britney Spears]]/commercial with [[Mary J. Blige]])
* 1999–2006: &quot;[[Yeh Dil Maange More!]]&quot; ([[Hindi]] - meaning &quot;This heart asks for more&quot;) ([[India]])
* 2003: &quot;Its the Cola&quot;/&quot;Dare for More&quot; (Pepsi Commercial)
* 2006–2007: &quot;Why You Doggin' Me&quot;/&quot;Taste the one that's forever young&quot; ([[Mary J. Blige]])
* 2007–2008: &quot;More Happy&quot;/&quot;Taste the once that's forever young&quot; (Michael Alexander)
* 2000–present: &quot;Pepsi ye pyaas heh bari&quot; ((Urdu) meaning &quot;There is a lot of thirst&quot; (Pakistan))
* 2008: &quot;Pepsi Stuff&quot; Super Bowl Commercial (Justin Timberlake)
* 2008: &quot;Рepsi is #1&quot; Тv commercial (Luke Rosin)
* 2008–present: &quot;Something For Everyone&quot;
* 2009–present: &quot;Refresh Everything&quot;/&quot;Every Generation Refreshes the World&quot;
* 2009–present: &quot;Yeh hai youngistaan meri jaan&quot; ([[Hindi]] - meaning &quot;This is our young country my baby&quot;)
* 2009–present: &quot;My Pepsi My Way&quot;([[India]])
* 2009–present: &quot;Refresca tu Mundo&quot; ([[Spanish language|Spanish]] - meaning &quot;Refresh your world&quot;) ([[Spanish Spoken countries in Latin America]])
* 2010–present: &quot;Every Pepsi Refreshes The World&quot;
* 2010–present &quot;Pepsi. Sarap Magbago.&quot; (Philippines - meaning &quot;Its nice to change&quot;)
* 2010–2011 &quot;Badal Do Zamana&quot; ([[Urdu]] - meaning &quot;Change The World&quot; by CALL)([[Pakistan]])
* 2010–present: &quot;Pode ser bom, pode ser muito bom, pode ser Pepsi&quot; (Can be good, can be very good, can be Pepsi) - [[Brazil]]
* 2011–present: &quot;Change the game&quot; ([[Bangladesh]], [[India]] for the [[2011 Cricket World Cup]])
* 2011–present &quot;Dunya Hai Dil Walon Ki&quot; ([[Pakistan]]-meaning World is For Lovers by Ali Zafar)
* 2011–present &quot;Ici, c'est Pepsi&quot; ([[Québec]]-meaning Here, it's pepsi)
* 2011-present &quot;Summer Time is Pepsi Time&quot;
* 2011-present &quot;Born in the Carolinas&quot;

===Pepsiman===
Pepsiman is an official Pepsi mascot from Pepsi's [[Japan]]ese corporate branch. The design of the Pepsiman character is attributed to Canadian comic book artist [[Travis Charest]], created sometime around the mid 1990s. Pepsiman took on three different outfits, each one representing the current style of the Pepsi can in distribution. Twelve commercials were created featuring the character. His role in the advertisements is to appear with Pepsi to thirsty people or people craving soda. Pepsiman happens to appear at just the right time with the product. After delivering the beverage, sometimes Pepsiman would encounter a difficult and action oriented situation which would result in injury.

In 1996, [[Sega-AM2]] released the [[Sega Saturn]] version of its arcade fighting game ''[[Fighting Vipers]]''. In this game Pepsiman was included as a special character, with his specialty listed as being the ability to &quot;quench one's thirst&quot;. He does not appear in any other version or sequel. In 1999, [[KID]] developed a [[video game]] for the [[PlayStation (console)|PlayStation]] entitled ''Pepsiman''. As the titular character, the player runs, skateboards, rolls, and stumbles through various areas, avoiding dangers and collecting cans of Pepsi all while trying to reach a thirsty person as in the commercials.

==Awards and recognition==
In 2011, [[The Brand Trust Report]] in India included Pepsi in the list of the most trusted brands of the country.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.afaqs.com/news/company_briefs/index.html?id=47502_The+Brand+Trust+Report+lists+Indias+Most+Trusted+Brands&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==
{{main|List of Pepsi variations}}

==Ingredients==
In the United States, Pepsi is made with carbonated water, [[high fructose corn syrup]], [[caramel color]], [[sugar]], [[Phosphoric acid]], [[caffeine]], [[citric acid]] and [[natural flavors]]. A can of Pepsi (12 fl ounces) has 41&amp;nbsp;grams of [[carbohydrates]] (all from [[sugar]]), 30&amp;nbsp;mg of [[sodium]], 0&amp;nbsp;grams of [[fat]], 0&amp;nbsp;grams of [[protein]], 38&amp;nbsp;mg of [[caffeine]] and 150 [[calories]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedailyplate.com/nutrition-calories/food/pepsi/12-oz-can The Daily Plate, Pepsi nutrition info&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pepsiproductfacts.com/infobyproduct.php Pepsi Product Facts&lt;/ref&gt; The caffeine-free Pepsi-Cola contains the same ingredients but without the caffeine.

The original Pepsi-Cola recipe was available from documents filed with the court at the time that the Pepsi-Cola Company went bankrupt in 1929. The original formula contained neither cola nor caffeine.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

In August 2010, PepsiCo entered into a 4-year agreement with Senomyx for the development of artificial high-potency sweeteners for PepsiCo beverages.  Under the contract, PepsiCo is paying $30 million to Senomyx for the research and future royalties on PepsiCo products sold using Senomyx technology. 

According to PepsiCo, PepsiCo's collaboration with Senomyx will focus on the discovery, development and commercialization of sweet enhancers, with the purpose of providing lower-calorie PepsiCo beverages. PepsiCo will have exclusive rights to the Senomyx sweet flavor ingredients developed through the collaboration. &lt;ref name=&quot;PepsiCo and Senomyx Enter Into Collaboration to Discover, Develop and Commercialize New Sweet Flavor Ingredients&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=PepsiCo and Senomyx Enter Into Collaboration to Discover, Develop and Commercialize New Sweet Flavor Ingredients|url=http://www.pepsico.com/PressRelease/PepsiCo-and-Senomyx-Enter-Into-Collaboration-to-Discover-Develop-and-Commerciali08172010.html|accessdate=31 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Diet Pepsi]]
* [[Pepsi spokespersons]]
* [[Pepsi Max Big One]] (Roller coaster)
* [[Pepsi Orange Streak]] (Roller coaster)
* [[Pepsi Python (Roller Coaster)|Pepsi Python]] (Roller coaster)
* [[Pepsi Billion Dollar Sweepstakes]]
* [[Mountain Dew]]
* [[AMP Energy]]
* [[Citrus Blast]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* ''Beverage World Magazine'', January 1998, &quot;Celebrating a Century of Refreshment: Pepsi&amp;nbsp;— The First 100 Years&quot;
* Stoddard, Bob. ''Pepsi-Cola - 100 Years'' (1997), General Publishing Group, Los Angeles, CA, USA
* &quot;''History &amp; Milestones''&quot; (1996), Pepsi packet
* Louis, J.C. &amp; Yazijian, Harvey Z. &quot;The Cola Wars&quot; (1980), Everest House, Publishers, New York, NY, USA

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://www.pepsi.com/ Pepsi website]
* [http://www.pepsiworld.com/ Pepsi World]
* [http://www.pepsigallery.com/ Pepsi Gallery - Pepsi Promotional site]
* [http://knowmore.org/wiki/index.php?title=Pepsico%2C_Inc. Pepsico, Inc. at Knowmore.org]
* [http://www.pepsico.co.uk/pepsi Pepsi page on PepsiCo UK &amp; Ireland]

{{PepsiCo}}
{{Varieties of Pepsi}}
{{colas}}

[[Category:Cola]]
[[Category:PepsiCo soft drinks]]
[[Category:1883 introductions]]

[[ar:بيبسي]]
[[ast:Pepsi]]
[[az:Pepsi]]
[[bn:পেপসি]]
[[bg:Пепси]]
[[bo:ལྦུ་སིམ་ཁུ་ནག]]
[[bs:Pepsi]]
[[ca:Pepsi]]
[[cs:Pepsi]]
[[cy:Pepsi]]
[[da:Pepsi]]
[[de:Pepsi]]
[[et:Pepsi-Cola]]
[[el:Πέπσι κόλα]]
[[es:Pepsi]]
[[eu:Pepsi]]
[[fa:پپسی‌کولا]]
[[fr:Pepsi-Cola]]
[[gl:Pepsi]]
[[ko:펩시콜라]]
[[hy:Պեպսի]]
[[hi:पेप्सी]]
[[hr:Pepsi]]
[[id:Pepsi]]
[[iu:ᐱᑉᓯ ᑰᓛ/pipsi kuulaa]]
[[is:Pepsi]]
[[it:Pepsi-Cola]]
[[he:פפסי]]
[[kn:ಪೆಪ್ಸಿ]]
[[ka:პეპსი]]
[[kk:Pepsi]]
[[la:Pepsi]]
[[arz:بيبسى]]
[[ms:Pepsi]]
[[nl:Pepsi]]
[[ja:ペプシコーラ]]
[[no:Pepsi]]
[[nn:Pepsi]]
[[pap:Pepsi]]
[[pms:Pepsi Còla]]
[[pl:Pepsi]]
[[pt:Pepsi-Cola]]
[[ro:Pepsi]]
[[ru:Пепси]]
[[sco:Pepsi]]
[[sq:Pepsi]]
[[simple:Pepsi]]
[[sk:Pepsi Cola]]
[[sr:Пепси]]
[[fi:Pepsi]]
[[sv:Pepsi]]
[[ta:பெப்சி]]
[[th:เป๊ปซี่]]
[[tr:Pepsi]]
[[uk:Пепсі]]
[[vi:Pepsi]]
[[zh-yue:百事可樂]]
[[zh:百事可樂]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
