<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="245807" ns="0" title="Cheyney University of Pennsylvania"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
 |name              = Cheyney University of Pennsylvania
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Cheyney University shield.png
 |image_size        = 150px
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = 
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = 1837
 |closed            = 
 |type              = 
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = 
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = Michelle R. Howard‐Vital, Ph.D.
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 
 |undergrad         = 
 |postgrad          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[Cheyney, Pennsylvania|Cheyney]]&lt;br&gt;[[Thornbury Township, Chester County, Pennsylvania|Thornbury Township, Chester Co.]] and [[Thornbury Township, Delaware County, Pennsylvania|Thornbury Township, Delaware Co.]]
 |state             = [[Pennsylvania]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = &lt;br&gt;United States
 |coor              = 
 |campus            = 
 |former_names      = Institute for Colored Youth (1837-1913)&lt;br&gt;Cheyney State Teachers College (1913-1921)&lt;br&gt;Cheyney State Normal School (1921-1959)&lt;br&gt;Cheyney State College (1959-1983)
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = 
 |sports            = Track &amp; field, basketball, football, tennis, volleyball, bowling

 |colors            = Blue and white&lt;br&gt;{{color box|#0000FF}} {{color box|#FFFFFF}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = Wolves
 |mascot            = 
 |athletics         = [[NCAA]]
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = [http://www.cheyney.edu www.cheyney.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = 
}}
'''Cheyney University of Pennsylvania''' is a public, co-educational [[Historically black colleges and universities|historically black university]] that is a part of the [[Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education]]. Cheyney University has a {{convert|275|acre|km2|sing=on}} campus that is located in the [[Cheyney, Pennsylvania|Cheyney]] community within [[Thornbury Township, Chester County, Pennsylvania|Thornbury Township, Chester County]] and [[Thornbury Township, Delaware County, Pennsylvania|Thornbury Township, Delaware County]]. The university offers bachelor's and master's degrees.&lt;ref name=&quot;find&quot;&gt;{{cite book
  | last =Williams  | first =Juan | authorlink =Juan Williams  | coauthors =Dwayne Ashley, Shawn Rhea
  | title =I'll find a way or make one: a tribute to historically Black colleges and universities
  | publisher =HarperCollins, 
  | year =2004 | pages =453
  | url =http://books.google.com/books?id=j3Ka2ESxQyQC&amp;pg=PA326#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | doi =
  | id =ISBN 9780060094560  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Melrose PA.JPG|thumb|left|[[Melrose (Cheyney, Pennsylvania)|Melrose Cottage]], built in 1805.]]
[[File:1909 Cheyney Library.JPG|thumb|left|Library]]
Founded as the '''African Institute''' in February 1837 and renamed the '''Institute of Coloured Youth''' (ICY) in April 1837, Cheyney University is the oldest African American school of higher education, although degrees were not granted from Cheyney until 1913. The founding of Cheyney University was made possible by [[Richard Humphreys (philanthropist)|Richard Humphreys]], a [[Society of Friends|Quaker]] philanthropist who bequeathed $10,000, one tenth of his estate, to design and establish a school to educate people of African descent. Born on a plantation in the [[West Indies]], Humphreys came to Philadelphia in 1764, where he became concerned about the struggles of free African Americans to make a living. News of a race riot in 1829 prompted Humphreys to write his will, in which he charged thirteen fellow Quakers to design an institution &quot;to instruct the descendents of the African Race in school learning, in the various branches of the mechanic Arts, trades and Agriculture, in order to prepare and fit and qualify them to act as teachers....&quot;

Founded as the African Institute, the school was soon renamed the Institute for Colored Youth. In its early years it provided a [[classical studies|classical education]] to young African Americans in Philadelphia. In 1902 the Institute moved to George Cheyney's farm, {{convert|25|mi|km}} west of Philadelphia, the name &quot;Cheyney&quot; became associated with the school in 1913. 

The school's official name changed several times during the twentieth century. In 1983, Cheyney joined the State System of Higher Education as Cheyney University of Pennsylvania.

The university offers baccalaureate degrees in more than 30 disciplines and the master’s degree in education.

==Athletics==
Cheyney University has one of the most storied basketball programs in [[NCAA Division II]] history. The men's basketball program is 7th all-time in [[NCAA]] win percentage, including 16 PSAC conference championships, four [[Final Four]]s, and one National Championship (1978).  

The women's basketball team in 1982 competed in the championship game of the inaugural [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]] tournament despite being a Division II school.
{{clear}}

In 2009, Cheyney University hired the first ever NCAA men's and women's basketball coaches who are brother and sister. The men's coach is Dominique Stephens, a North Carolina Central graduate and member of the NCAA Division II Basketball Championship team,  and the women's coach is Marilyn Stephens, the Temple University Hall of Famer.

==See also==
*[[List of Cheyney University of Pennsylvania alumni]]
*[[List of Cheyney University of Pennsylvania faculty]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Philadelphia|African American|University}}
*[http://www.cheyney.edu Official website]

{{Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education}}
{{HBCU}}
{{Thurgood Marshall Scholarship Fund}}
{{Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cheyney University Of Pennsylvania}}
[[Category:Schools on the National Register of Historic Places in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Cheyney University of Pennsylvania|*]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Historically black universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1837]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference]]
[[Category:African American history in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Delaware County, Pennsylvania]]

[[es:Universidad de Cheyney de Pensilvania]]
[[no:Cheyney University of Pennsylvania]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
