<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24607755" ns="0" title="Leonid Mikhailovich Kharitonov"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Soviet actor|Leonid Kharitonov (actor)}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject_Musicians --&gt;
| name                = Leonid Mikhailovich Kharitonov
| image                 = Leonid Kharitonov 1970s.jpg
| caption            = Leonid Kharitonov, 1970s
| image_size            = 250px
| background          = solo_singer
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1933|09|18}}
| death_date                = 
| origin              = Golumet, [[Irkutsk]], [[Soviet Union]]
| genre               = [[Opera]], [[Romantic music]], [[military music]], [[ethnic Russian music]], [[easy listening]], [[Middle of the road (music)|middle of the road]], [[folk music]], comic songs
| occupation          = [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|Alexandrov Ensemble soloist]], Operatic and concert [[bass-baritone]] soloist
| years_active        = 1950-present
| label               = [[Kultur Video|Kultur]], [[EMI Records|EMI]], [[Melodiya]] etc.
| associated_acts     = [[Alexandrov Ensemble]], [http://www.classicalmusic.ru/ Moscow Philharmonic Society]
}}

'''Leonid Mikhailovich Kharitonov''' ({{lang-ru|Леонид Михайлович Харитонов}}) is a Russian [[bass-baritone]] (баритональный бас) singer, born 18 September 1933 in the village of Golumet, [[Irkutsk Oblast]]. He has been honoured with: [[People's Artist of Russia]] and [[Honoured Artist of Russia]]. In the West he is noted for his 1965 video of the [[Song of the Volga Boatmen]].

== Early life ==
He was born in Golumet, [[Irkutsk Oblast]], in 1933. When his father went missing in World War II, his mother brought him up. Between 1934 and 1942 he was at [[Cheremkhovo]], and attended school number 25 from 1941 to 1942. Back at Golumet he attended school from 1942 to 1945, and stayed at Golumet until 1947. For a year from the age of 14 (from 1947 to 1948) he studied to be a welder in F.Z.O. and worked at a plant in Kuibysheva in the [[Irkutsk Oblast]] as a moulder and caster. From 1948 to 1950 back in Golumet again, he worked in M.T.S. as an electric welder, meanwhile beginning to perform as a singer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Officialwebsitebiography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/about/bio&amp;anno=2|en&amp;tbb=1&amp;ie=UTF-8|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|work=Biography of Singer Leonid Kharitonov|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Narod&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref Name=scanbiography&gt;[http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/wp-content/gallery/discography/disk1-2.jpg The original 3rd party source for the biography of L.M. Kharitonov, used by the narod.ru site and by L.M.Kharitonov's official site] scan of biographical information on vinyl record cover of Русские народные песни и романсы (translation: &quot;Russian Folk Songs and Ballads&quot;) in Russian&lt;/ref&gt;

From 17 years old (1950&amp;nbsp;1952) he was a soloist at [[Music of Irkutsk|Irkutsk Philharmonic]] and finally was accepted by [[Moscow Conservatory]] from 1952 to 1955. This was very difficult because as a [[Siberia]]n he did not have even a matriculation certificate, but his strong singing voice spoke for him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Narod&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kkre-45.narod.ru/haritonov-lm.htm|title=Narod.ru|work=Biography of Leonid Kharitonov|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scanbiography&quot; /&gt;

== Career ==
[[Image:Leonid Mikhailovich Kharitonov 001.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Leonid Kharitonov, early 1970s]]

=== With the Alexandrov Ensemble 1953 to 1972 ===
From 9 November 1953 to March 1965 he was a member of the choir in the Red Song and Dance Ensemble of the Soviet Army (later the [[Alexandrov Ensemble]]).  His place in the choir was always third from the right in the top row. From 1953 to 1955 he served in both the [[Red Army|army]] and the choir. From 1956 to 1959, while still with the choir, he studied at [[Gnessin State Musical College]].  His first unofficial public performance as soloist was in the [[State Kremlin Palace]] on 18 March 1965.  On that day two good friends of his, cosmonauts [[Pavel Belyayev|Pavel Belyaev]] and [[Alexey Leonov]], were blasted into space on the [[Voskhod 2]]. During this mission, Leonov became the first human to [[Extra-vehicular activity|walk in space]]. Kharitonov's first official public performance as a soloist was on 22 April 1965.&lt;ref name=&quot;Firstperformance&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/|en&amp;tbb=1&amp;ie=UTF-8|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|work=&quot;There is a cliff on the Volga&quot; video of L.M. Kharitonov's first performance with the Alexandrov Ensemble in 1965|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1967 he was awarded [[Honoured Artist of Russia]]. He continued with the Ensemble until 1972 - so he was with them for nearly 20 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Officialwebsitebiography&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Narod&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scanbiography&quot; /&gt; [[Boris Alexandrovich Alexandrov|B.A. Alexandrov]] was proud of his soloist, and would often shake his hand or hug him publicly onstage after a performance.&lt;ref&gt;For example, at the end of [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0tw3g88JtWA this performance of Ej Uhnem] at the Tchaikovsky Hall, Moscow, 1965&lt;/ref&gt; Kharitonov sometimes sang duets, but only with [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|Ivan Bukreev]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot; /&gt; Kharitonov had one singing teacher only in his life: Evgeny Avgustovich Kanger, who taught no-one in the Ensemble but the leading soloists, including [[Evgeny Belyaev]].

=== Independent career from 1972 to present ===
From 1972 to 1998 he was a soloist with the Moscow Philharmonic Society,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.classicalmusic.ru/ Moscow Philharmonic Society], i.e. not the company referred to on the Moscow Philharmonic page in Wikipedia&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1986 was awarded [[People's Artist of Russia]]. Being a soloist for the Moscow Philharmonic meant that tours were arranged; he was given bookings by them; an accompanist was provided; but he could arrange his own bookings and pay for a different accompanist outside Moscow, and could accept tours offered by his own clients.&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot; /&gt; During this time, he performed frequently on radio and television. On tour, he visited the entire country and appeared several times at the [[State Kremlin Palace]] concert hall. He was considered the pride of Russia, and sang at concerts for the government and for foreign delegations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Narod&quot; /&gt; During the 1970s, ’80s and ’90s, Kharitonov went on tour abroad to many different countries, including Czechoslovakia, England, Scotland, the United States, China and Australia. From 1998 to 2006 he performed at various venues on a contract basis, giving concerts in [[Siberia]], the German Embassy and [[:File:Moscow State Art Gallery of Ilya Glazunov.JPG|Ilya Glazunov Gallery]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Officialwebsitebiography&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scanbiography&quot; /&gt; He was a friend of [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|Anatoly Solovyanenko]] but they never sang a duet together.&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot; /&gt; Kharitonov never performed in theatrical opera, but sang operatic arias in concert performances.&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot; /&gt;

=== Worldwide recognition ===
Like many of the great Russian operatic singers of the Soviet era, this bass-baritone singer who is respected in [[Russia]] and who sings fully in the tradition of [[Feodor Chaliapin|Chaliapin]] is largely unknown in the West. This is because his career was overshadowed by the [[Cold War]]. However his recordings continue to be re-released worldwide, and this may eventually serve to redress the balance, along with the recent increased exposure of Kharitonov on YouTube.&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/user/LHaritonov|title=YouTube|work=LHaritonov's channel|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Critical commentaries on performances 1965 to 1972 ==
=== 1965 video of ''Cliff'' ===
Utyos ([[Russian Language|Russian]]: Утёс)&lt;ref&gt;The accepted UK English translation of the songtitle is: ''The Cliff on the Volga'', because it is listed as such by the BBC.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Leonid Kharitonov Utyos.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Kharitonov singing ''Cliff'' at the Tchaikovsky Hall, [[Moscow]], 1965]]
One of Kharitonov's first solo performances, at age 32 after twelve years in the choir of the [[Alexandrov Ensemble|Ensemble]], was a concert at the [[State Kremlin Palace|Kremlin Palace of Congresses]] attended by top government officials. As a chorister he was aware of the primary function of the bass part.  Whether the part actually does so or not, its effect is to appear to provide a rhythmic and tonal foundation for the musical piece.  In other words, particularly when the choir sings ''[[a cappella]]'', or when there are no drums, the bass part appears to set both the rhythm and pitch, by virtue of having the heaviest sound.  This understanding, and the understanding within [[Boris Alexandrovich Alexandrov|Boris Alexandrov's]] arrangement, is what makes Kharitonov's performance commanding. There is no destabilising ego here. When he sings he sets the melody and dynamic, and establishes all that is to come; the choir appears to settle comfortably above his voice; the choir repeats and follows his lead.  This roars to a climax, with the soloist's voice appearing to carry the weight of all Russia's revolutionary optimism.  After all, this is a song about [[Stenka Razin]]: the first revolutionary; a cross between [[Attila the Hun]] and [[Robin Hood]] - and this performance made [[Leonid Brezhnev]] cry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cliff&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/archives/2916|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|last=Kharitonov|first=Leonid Mikhailovich|work=Cliff: Stenka Razin|accessdate=2009-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The screenshot, left, from a concert given at Tchaikovsky Hall in Moscow during the same time period, is an indication of the stage presence which takes on the persona of [[Stenka Razin|Razin]] himself. Ultimately, this is a recording that demonstrates what a bass soloist really is: the musical foundation of a performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Important: Before editing this critical commentary, please read the section &quot;Critical Commentaries&quot; on the article discussion page.&lt;/ref&gt; The sound recording  of ''Cliff'' can be heard in the 2006 [[BBC]] documentary series ''Chernobyl Nuclear Disaster'': ''Surviving Disaster'' while brave men swim to their deaths, opening sluice gates below the reactor in the hope of preventing a nuclear explosion.&lt;ref name=&quot;IMDb-BBCtvseries-2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=IMDb|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0775665/|work=Surviving disaster: Chernobyl Nuclear Disaster|accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Listen
 |filename = Leonid Kharitonov - Cliff.ogg
 |title    = L. Kharitonov sings &quot;The Cliff&quot; in 1965.
 |plain    = yes
 |style    = float:right
}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

==== Historical commentary on 1965 performance of ''Cliff'' ====
This song is about the fate of the 17th century Russian rebel, [[Stenka Razin|Stepan Razin]].  The lyrics were written in 1864 by novelist Alexander Alexandrovich Navrotsky who was also a member of [[Narodnaya Volya (organization)|Narodnaya Volya]] (Russian: Народная Воля), a secret revolutionary organization perhaps best known for assassinating [[Tsar Alexander II]] on March 13, 1881. The song was an anthem for revolutionaries of the late 19th and early 20th century in [[Russia]]; [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]] often sang it with his comrades-in-arms. The song is still culturally central to Russia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cliffarticle&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/archives/2916|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|last=Kharitonov|first=Mikhail Leonid|work=History of the song &quot;Cliff&quot; (with links to third-party sources of article)|accessdate=2009-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kharitonov remembers:

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;My solo career truly began with a concert in the [[State Kremlin Palace|Kremlin Palace of Congresses]] on April 22, 1965, dedicated to the 95th anniversary of [[Vladimir Lenin|Lenin]],&lt;ref&gt;i.e. the anniversary of Lenin's birth in 1870&lt;/ref&gt; when I sang &quot;There is a cliff on the Volga.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Usually translated as &quot;Utyos&quot; or &quot;Cliff&quot;, although the [[BBC]] lists it as &quot;Cliff on the Volga&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; This was my first solo performance. [[Leonid Brezhnev|Brezhnev]] wept. He got up from his seat and wiped away the tears with his hands then applauded, and then everyone in the room stood up as well and applauded too. I do not know what my performance stirred in the hearts of [[Leonid Brezhnev|Leonid Ilyich]] and the other listeners, but I would like this song to be considered a monument to the Russian victorious spirit. After that performance, I continued to be a soloist with the [[Alexandrov Ensemble|Ensemble]] for seven years, and, from then on, I was regarded as a serious professional singer among the musical and political elite&quot;.

*:&quot;I remember how after the concert [[Kliment Voroshilov|Marshal Voroshilov]] came to see me backstage.  After expressions of gratitude he hugged me as a father would and told me that [[Joseph Stalin|Stalin]] also considered this song to be his favorite, and often played a record of it being performed by A. Pirogov,&lt;ref&gt;Alexander Pirogov (1899–1964), a Russian Soviet opera singer&lt;/ref&gt; whenever he was sad at heart. &quot;If Stalin was alive, then you would be leaving this room as a [[People's Artist of the USSR]] - because you sing it better than Pirogov,&quot; Voroshilov told me.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Cliffarticle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br clear=all&gt;

=== 1965 video of ''Song of the Volga Boatmen'' ===
Properly titled Yo, Heave, Ho! (or Ej, uhnem!), ([[Russian Language|Russian]]: Эй, ухнем!)
[[Image:LKharitonov Volga Boatmen Song.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Kharitonov singing ''Ej, Uhnem'', 1965]]
In the West Kharitonov is known for his 1965 video of ''[[The Song of the Volga Boatmen]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Boatmen&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/video/army/uhnem|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|work=Video of &quot;Song of the Volga Boatmen&quot; sung by Leonid Kharitonov, 1965|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; which resembles [[Feodor Chaliapin|Chaliapin's]] 1922 recording, especially in the upper-register roar which in the song represents the hauliers making superhuman effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chaliapin&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oGSR1jCXojI|title=YouTube|work=Feodor Chaliapin&amp;nbsp;— Song of Volga Boatmen 1922|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; He demonstrates the clean Russian bass-baritone sound: a fusion of various influences. There is the Eastern [[Orthodox Church]] singing style, inherited from [[Byzantine music]], without vibrato and demanding a clear and sonorous resonance at all times: preferably utilising the soundbox of a building space. There is also the influence of the [[Italian opera]]tic singing style with its emphasis on the resonance in the nasal cavity and the power of the diaphragm: both of which permit control of the loudest and softest vocal sounds without compromising tonal quality. The tendency of [[Russian phonology|Russian language speakers]] to create some vowels by expanding the soft palate is a great advantage for Russian basses, as it encourages their unique type of richly open resonance. This effect tells to advantage in both the upper and lower registers of this bass-baritone singer.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

The hard labor of the burlaks is portrayed by the seriousness of his expression throughout the performance, with the exception of a momentary lightening—even the shadow of a smile—when he sings: “We are singing our song to the Sun,&quot; arguably the most hopeful phrase in the entire song (see screenshot).&lt;ref name=&quot;Park21VolgaBoatmen&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://park21.wakwak.com/~sakiel/boruga.htm|title=Park 21|year=2009|work=Japanese commentary on Leonid Kharitonov singing Volga Boatmen's Song|language=Japanese|accessdate=16 January 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Listen
 |filename = Leonid Kharitonov - Ej uhnem.ogg
 |title    = L.Kharitonov sings &quot;The Song of the Volga Boatmen&quot;
 |plain    = yes
 |style    = float:right
}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

=== 1969 video of ''Dark-Eyed Cossack Girl'' ===
Chernoglazaya Kazachka ({{lang-ru|Черноглазая казачка}})
[[Image:Leonid Kharitonov Kazachka.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Kharitonov trying to make the [[bayan]] players laugh, but making [[Boris Alexandrovich Alexandrov|Boris]] laugh instead]]
Many Russian songs are serious or sad, but Kharitonov is also known for singing comic songs or arias. The composer [[Matvey Blanter]] wrote ''Dark-Eyed [[Cossacks|Cossack]] Girl'' ({{lang-ru|Черноглазая казачка}}) especially for him in 1966. Kharitonov's definitive performance was recorded in 1969.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cossack&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/video/army/kazachka|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|work=Video of &quot;Dark-Eyed Cossack&quot; sung by Leonid Kharitonov, 1969|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Again he is celebrating [[Feodor Chaliapin|Chaliapin's]] legacy as the first modern bass to successfully fuse drama&amp;nbsp;— and humour&amp;nbsp;— with pure musical technique, as in Chaliapin's performance of ''[[Dark Eyes (song)|Dark Eyes]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uAXTewbn6Vg&amp;feature=related|title=YouTube|work=Chaliapin &quot;black eyes&quot;|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover this performance of Kharitonov's demonstrates the [[Alexandrov Ensemble|Ensemble's]] style, which in the era of A.V. and B.A. Alexandrov encouraged soloists to stay in tune in spite of any vibrato, any emotional acting, or any humour.  Therefore, although the song involves laughter, he laughs elegantly in tune.  All the while he is making faces and humorous gestures, his vocal tone and pitch remain spot-on.  That is the achievement of this kind of performance: while the audience and the other musicians laugh so much at Kharitonov's clowning (see image, left), at the same time they are aware of highly disciplined singing, and the performance remains perfectly musical.

This performance demonstrates that discipline is fundamental to musical elegance.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
{{Listen
 |filename = Leonid Kharitonov - Dark Eyed Cossack Girl.ogg
 |title    = L.Kharitonov sings Dark-Eyed Cossack Girl
 |plain    = yes
 |style    = float:right
}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

== Critical commentaries on performances after 1972 ==
=== 1974 video of ''Shine, Shine My Star'' ===
Gori, Gori, Moya Zvezda ([[Russian language|Russian]]:
Гори, гори, моя звезда)
[[Image:Leonid Kharitonov Gori Gori.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Leonid Kharitonov singing ''Gori Gori'' (''Shine shine my star'') on television, 1974]]
In this song, the singer speaks to a star, asking it to have compassion on him. Kharitonov sings it as if it were a prayer, and the close-up of his face emphasises the spirituality of the performance. In an interview about this, the interviewer asked Kharitonov about his faith; whether as a child he believed. Leonid remembered that in his early years, he did not go to church, but the boy always felt a connection with the sky; with the cosmos. His star, with whom he communicated, spoke to him.
*&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;The more I live . . . the more I believe that God exists. Lord God was preparing me to be clean, kept me through homelessness, hunger, poverty. I never hurt anyone, did not deceive, did not have debts. On stage, the artist reveals himself to the spectator-listener. If a person is mean, with a dirty soul, the listener sees and feels this. I'm on stage not just performing my part. On stage, I live every romance, folk song, or aria from the opera. This brought me to the Lord God. He established everything in Man so that he learned to understand and distinguish the good from the bad.&quot; &lt;small&gt;Tatiana Kovalska, 2004&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vsp.ru/culture/2004/07/06/440822 Tatiana Kovalska: &quot;The singer's soul is longing for its homeland&quot;, East Siberian Truth, 6th July 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
{{Listen
 |filename = Leonid Kharitonov - Shine Shine My Star.ogg
 |title    = L.Kharitonov sings &quot;Shine Shine My Star&quot;
 |plain    = yes
 |style    = float:right
}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

=== 1983 video of ''Along the Peterskaya (Street)'' ===
Vdol po Piterskoy ({{lang-ru|Вдоль по Питерской}})	
[[Image:LKharitonov Vdol Po Peterskoy.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Kharitonov singing ''Along the Peterskaya'', 1983]]
This folk song, about a jolly, tipsy [[troika]]-driver indiscreetly courting the ladies, belongs to a tradition in which it was previously popularised by [[Feodor Chaliapin]] and [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|Alexei Sergeev]]&lt;ref&gt;DVD: Kultur: Soviet Army Chorus and Dance Ensemble, D1106, &quot;Along Peterskaya&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; who each made the song their own.  Sergeev's version was hilariously rumbustuous but possibly overwhelming at close quarters for the ladies. Kharitonov's inebriate is the huge and clumsy but genial [[Russian Bear]]: the symbol of [[Russia]] beloved of [[Leo Tolstoy]].&lt;ref&gt;In [[War and Peace]] (1869)&lt;/ref&gt; The tonality is kept warm and elegant, while the vocal slide from one note to the next&amp;nbsp;— and on one occasion a whole [[glissando]] - help to create an illusion of musical drunkenness. This is a musical joke, as previously [[Georgi Vinogradov (tenor)|Georgi Vinogradov]] had taken the vocal slide from drunks and tuneless club singers, and utilised it to showcase his own disciplined vocal skill and consistent vocal quality as he slid from one register to the next.&lt;ref&gt;As in the song ''Luchina'' (1940s)&lt;/ref&gt;  Kharitonov, in his prime, still has a consistent vocal quality across the registers at the age of 50 years,&lt;ref&gt;That is, he can sing up the scale without his voice suddenly sounding different as he goes from one octave to the next.&lt;/ref&gt; and can surprise the audience by taking a technique which had come to represent sobriety, and hand it back to the [[music-hall]] toper.

So this performance demonstrates the artistry behind the charm of a comedic bass solo performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
{{Listen
 |filename = Leonid Kharitonov - Along the Peterskaya.ogg
 |title    = L.Kharitonov sings &quot;Along the Peterskaya&quot;
 |plain    = yes
 |style    = float:right
}}
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

== Reviews ==
*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;There are eight solo singers whose range of songs is as wide as the convention allows&amp;nbsp;— Leonid Kharitonov chose ''Di quella pira'' as an encore and sang it magnificently&amp;nbsp;— who sing well and dispense encores lavishly, dropping charmingly into English now and again.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''The Times'' review of the Ensemble's 1967 UK tour&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Sing-for-ever Red Army Men&quot;, ''The Times'', March 31, 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Newly promoted from the ranks of the choir to that of soloist, Leonid Kharitonov sternly leads his voice into chasms of dizzying depth, displaying an impressively full sonorousness.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''L’Aurore'' review of the Ensemble's 1967 French tour&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Fraichement extrait des rangs des choristes pour celui des solistes, Leonide Kharitonov promene sa voix dans des abimes de profondeur vertigineuse, d’un air severe, avec une ronde ampleur impressionnante.&quot; ''L’Aurore'', November 25, 1967&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Leonid Kharitonov was a great success on his visit to Britain in 1967 with his rendition of the ''Volga Boat Song''. Siberian born Kharitonov is now a soloist with the Moscow State Philharmonic  Society specializing in traditional Russian songs.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Soviet Weekly'' review of UK tour, 1977&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Soviet Weekly'', October 22, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;...They were rehearsing in every corner of Hamilton Town Hall. Leonid Kharitonov is the group’s bass soloist. Built like the side of a house, with a voice to match. Like the rest of the troupe he’s a Burns fanatic. They can put most Scots to shame with Rabbie’s songs and poems&amp;nbsp;– in Russian. During his first performance at the Usher Hall , Leonid astonished the audience by sweeping the microphone aside and filling the hall to the echo with his naked voice.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Sunday Post'' review of his Scottish tour, 1977&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Sunday Post''. October 30, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The Russian opera singer Leonid Kharitonov, accompanied by the rhythm sections, sang songs such as ''I’m looking at the sky'', ''Along Peterskaya Street'' and ''Pies with cheese''. His last song had the crowd laughing, as he staggered out onto the stage as if he was drunk, making faces and losing his balance as he sang to the audience.... The audience rose to its feet to honor Kharitonov with a rousing ovation in tribute to his art.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Yorkton this week'', tour review, 1979&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Yorkton this week'', January 31, 1979&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;...The same can be said about the presentation of another remarkable singer&amp;nbsp;— People's Artist of Russia Leonid Kharitonov. An enchanting bass and an amazing dramatic actor in one person, he led his audience to a magical space of Russian and world musical classics....&quot;      - &lt;small&gt;''Moscow Magazine ({{lang-ru|Журнал &quot;Москва&quot;}})'', performance review, 2001 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moskvam.ru/2001/12/seminar.htm ''Moscow Magazine ({{lang-ru|Журнал &quot;Москва&quot;}})''], December 25, 2001 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Performances by Kharitonov at the most prestigious venues in dozens of countries around the world raised a new wave of interest in the culture of Russian songs. In France, he performed at the invitation of President Charles de Gaulle, at a charity concert of ''stars'' of the world, held to benefit less developed countries (December 1967.) Competing with such world celebrities as Franco Corelli, Fernandel, Nicolai Ghiaurov, and ''the Beatles'', Kharitonov received the title of Best Singer of the Year.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Russian Messenger ({{lang-ru|Русский Вестник }})'', interview and review, 2003 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rv.ru/content.php3?id=1228 ''Russian Messenger ({{lang-ru|Русский Вестник}})''], October 8, 2003 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;When we were at his concert at the Irkutsk Philharmonic Organ Hall, we just sat there with opened mouths&amp;nbsp;— so beautifully he sings. And what a powerful voice! Leonid sang without a microphone, but even those who sat in the back rows could hear every word so clearly as if he were not on stage, but standing right next to them.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Kopeck ({{lang-ru|Копейка}})'', performance review, 2006 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://pressa.irk.ru/kopeika/2006/18/008001.html ''Kopeck ({{lang-ru|Копейка}})''], May 10, 2006 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I am very grateful to Leonid Kharitonov, a remarkable bass, soloist of the Moscow Philharmonic Society, with whom I first went on tour. He asked me to tell the audience a short informational story about him in the beginning of the performance. He was not just a singer, but also a wonderful actor. And naturally so. After our first concert he said to me: &quot;I watched the hall when you were speaking. The man in the front row looked at his watch three times. Evidently, he was not interested.&quot; This was the main lesson: I must speak in a way that the audience was so interested that they were afraid to miss something from my story. Hence, it is not only the information itself that's important, but also how you impart it.&quot; - &lt;small&gt;''Moscow Truth ({{lang-ru|Московская Правда}})'', interview, 2006 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sir35.ru/Rus/P_611.htm  ''Moscow Truth ({{lang-ru|Московская Правда}})''], October 26, 2006 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== Private life ==
Leonid Kharitonov has a wife and two sons, and has been based in [[Moscow]] during his long career. In recent years he has been involved in returning an icon of [[Saint Nicholas]] to the Church of Saint Nicholas in his home town of Golumet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/archives/197  ''Discovering Icons ({{lang-ru|Обретение иконы}})''], December 14, 2008 (in Russian)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Recorded music ==
=== With the Alexandrov Ensemble ===
With the [[Alexandrov Ensemble]] he recorded ''The Ballad about Russian Boys'' (music: Novikov; lyrics: Oshanin L.), ''John Reed Walks Around Petrograd'' (music: Novikov; lyrics: M. Vershinin), ''War isn't Over Yet'' (music: B. Muradeli; lyrics: M. Andronov), ''Here Lenin Lived'' (music: B. Terentiev; lyrics: A. Fatyanov), ''Lenin's Guard'' (music: B Aleksandrov; lyrics: M Khotimsk), ''My Fatherland'' (music: O. Feltsman; lyrics: Oshanin L.), ''Veterans don't Grow Old in their Souls'' (music: Tulika S.; lyrics: Y. Belinsky), ''Song of Peace'' (music: B. Muradeli; lyrics: V. Kharitonov), ''Gray Hair'' (music: A. Ekimyan; lyrics: F. Laube), ''Son of the Fatherland'' (music: S. Tulika; lyrics: V. Lazarev), ''Son of Russia'' (music: St. Tulika; lyrics: V. Kharitonov), ''Vasya-Vasilyok'' duet with I.S. Bukreev (ca.1965), ''[[Song of the Volga Boatmen]]''
&lt;ref&gt;VHS: Kultur: Soviet Army Chorus and Dance Ensemble, &quot;Volga Boatmen&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
,&lt;ref&gt;DVD: Kultur: Soviet Army Chorus and Dance Ensemble, D1106, &quot;Volga Boatmen&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
''Death of Varyag''.
&lt;ref Name=&quot;Japanesesonglist&quot;&gt;[http://www.katch.ne.jp/~alexandrov/solo/kharitonov.html Red Army webpage: biography and songlist of L.M. Kharitonov] in Japanese&lt;/ref&gt; He possibly sang ''Spring of 1945'' (by Mrs.Pakhmutova) as a duet with I. Bukreev, but this was unrecorded.&lt;ref name=&quot;LHaritonov&quot; /&gt;

== Discography ==
=== 1972-present ===
''See discography navbox at bottom of page''.

=== 1965-present ===
There is a full discography on Leonid Kharitonov's official website.&lt;ref name=&quot;Officialwebsitediscography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/discography|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|work=Discography|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  All his 1965-1972 records are included in the [[Alexandrov Ensemble]] discography section of the Japanese ''Red Army'' website.&lt;ref name=&quot;Japanesediscography&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.katch.ne.jp/~alexandrov/disk/diskmenu.html|title=Japanese &quot;Red Army&quot; website|work=Alexandrov Ensemble discography section|language=Japanese|accessdate=2009-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; This Japanese site also lists individual tracks by Kharitonov, linked to full album details.&lt;ref name=&quot;Japanesesonglist&quot;/&gt;
&lt;br clear=all&gt;

== Concert repertoire ==
''The following is a small selection'':

=== Operatic arias ===
Ivan Susanin from ''Life for the Tsar'' by [[Mikhail Glinka|Glinka]]; King Rene from ''Iolanta'' by [[Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky|Tchaikovsky]]; Song of the Varangian Guest from ''Sadko'' by [[Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov|Rimsky-Korsakov]]; King Philip  from ''Don Carlos'' by [[Giuseppe Verdi|Verdi]]; Konchak from ''Prince Igor'' by [[Alexander Borodin|Borodin]]; The Old-Man’s Tale from ''Aleko'' by [[Sergei Rachmaninoff|Rachmaninov]]; Kutuzov from ''War and Peace'' by [[Sergei Prokofiev|Prokofiev]]; Serenade of Mefistofeles from ''Faust'' by [[Charles Gounod|Gounod]], Song of the Flea by [[Modest Mussorgsky|Mussorgsky]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Arias&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/music|title=Singer Leonid Kharitonov|last=Kharitonov|first=Mikhail Leonidovich|work=Music page|language=Russian|accessdate=2009-10-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
*[[Alexandrov Ensemble]]
*[[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists]]
*[[Alexandrov Ensemble choir]]
*[[Alexandrov Ensemble discography]]

== Notes ==
{{Reflist}}

== References ==
* [http://www.trud.ru/article/10-09-2004/76925_chudotvorets_vernulsja_domoj.html Alexei Komarov: &quot;the Miracle-Worker back home&quot;, ''&quot;Trud&quot; Newspaper'' No. 171, 10 September 2004.]
* [http://news.babr.ru/?IDE=15253 Marina Konstantinova: &quot;The Icon of St. Nicholas The Miracle-Worker&quot;, ''TV Company AIST'', 7 September 2004.]
* [http://www.vsp.ru/culture/2004/07/06/440822 Tatiana Kovalska: &quot;The singer's soul is longing for its homeland&quot;, ''East Siberian Truth'', 6th July 2004.]
* [http://www.arsvest.ru/archive/issue796/world/view13855.html Margo Laren: &quot;Evening of sacred chants&quot;, ''Arsenievsk News'', Issue 25 (796), 18 June 2008.]
* [http://www.d-dvv.ru/main/155-obretenie-ikony.html Rostislav Novikov: &quot;Invention of the Icon&quot;, ''Spirituality and Faith Revival''14 December 2008.]
* [http://www.rv.ru/content.php3?id=1447 Valentin Novikov: &quot;Art inspires the heart&quot;, ''Russian Messenger'',  25 December 2003.]
* [http://www.rv.ru/content.php3?id=1228 Valentin Novikov: &quot;Russian is a proud word&quot;, ''Russian Messenger'', 8 October 2003.]
* [http://soveticus5.narod.ru/leonhar.htm T.V. Sokolova: &quot;Comment&quot; (Biography of L.M. Kharitonov): ''Soviet songs'', 1972.]
* [http://www.og-irk.ru/vp300/golumet_%96_selo_s_parkom__basseynom_i_bogatoy_istoriey/print_5789.html Anna Vigovsky: &quot;Restoring the Temple of St Nicholas&quot;, ''Socio-political Regional Newspaper'', Issue 25 (300), 14 March 2008]
* [http://pressa.irk.ru/sm/2007/31/004012.html Lydia Gergesova: &quot;Golumet&quot;, ''CM Number One'', 9 August 2007]
* [http://www.poklonnik.ru/site.xp/053055124053048055124.html St Nicholas icon returned, ''Pilgrimage Center'', 2009]

== External links ==
* [http://www.lkharitonov.com Official English language website of Leonid Kharitonov]
* [http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/ Official website of Leonid Kharitonov] in Russian
* [http://kkre-45.narod.ru/haritonov-lm.htm Narod.ru biography and songlist of Leonid Kharitonov] in Russian
* [http://www.leonidharitonov.ru/about/bio Biography of L.M. Kharitonov] in Russian
* [http://www.katch.ne.jp/~alexandrov/solo/kharitonov.html Red Army webpage: Biography of Leonid Kharitonov, with discography and videos of performances] in Japanese
* [http://www.lkharitonov.com/lmkblog/bio/tour List of Leonid Kharitonov's tours 1972-2005]
* [http://kappsa.wordpress.com Wordpress: Alexandrov Ensemble blog]

{{Navbox
|navbar     = plain
|state      = collapsed
|title      = L.M. Kharitonov discography
|above      = In order of: format - date - label
|group1     =DVDs&lt;/br&gt;2008
|list1      = '''[[Kultur International Films|Kultur]] &quot;Soviet Army Chorus and Dance Ensemble&quot; D1106''': ''Ej, Uhnem'' (''[[The Song of the Volga Boatmen]]''), studio near Moscow, 1965.
|group2     =1969
|list2      = '''Yuri Saakov &quot;New Year's Abduction&quot;''': ''Dark Eyed Cossack Girl'' (''Chernoglazaya Kazachka'') recorded 1969.
|group3     =CDs&lt;br /&gt;2006
|list3      = '''[[Melodiya]] Bomba &quot;Best Lyric Songs&quot;, BoMB033-204''': ''Vasya-Vasilyok'' duet with [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|I.S. Bukreev]]
|group4     =2006
|list4      = '''Melodiya &quot;Eh Dorogi&quot;, MELCD6000615''': ''Vasya-Vasilyok'', duet with [[Alexandrov Ensemble soloists|I.S. Bukreev]]. Reissued 2006 and 2008 from 1995, but recorded 1960s.
|group5     =2002
|list5      = '''ADD &quot;Leonid Kharitonov, Russian folk songs and romances&quot;''': ''Here's the mail troika rushing; Along the Peterskaya; Lamentably moaning; [[Stenka Razin]]; Oh Nastasia; Shine shine my star; Legend of the twelve robbers; Don't awaken my memories; Coachman don't rush the horses; Only once; Drunken street; Aria of Ivan Susanin; [[List of compositions by Modest Mussorgsky|Song of the flea]]; Song about the Motherland; Alarm bells of Buchenwald; Motherland, Son of Russia; Veterans don't grow old in their souls.''
|group6     =Vinyl&lt;/br&gt;1989
|list6      = '''Melodiya &quot;Memory of the Heart&quot; C60 28375 002''': ''I love you life; Son of Russia; Alarm bells of Buchenwald; The Bryansk forest; Peacefighter's song; Memory of the Heart; Do Russians want another war?; War isn't over yet; Veterans don't grow old in their souls.''
|group7     =1989
|list7      = '''Melodiya &quot;Native Tunes&quot; SM 03327-8 (1972 reissue)''': ''A storm was raging; Not the autumnal fine rain; Glorious sea&amp;nbsp;— the sacred Baikal; Black raven; At the draw-well; Foggy morning; Oh, if only I could express it in sound; Kiss me, my darling; Drunken street; Shine, shine my star; Bored and sad; And so the soul longs (to).''
|group8     =1988
|list8      = '''Melodiya &quot;What is this heart ...&quot; C20 26893-000''': ''When I served as a mail coachman; Among the spreading vales; Small farmstead; Legend of the twelve robbers; You have forgotten; What is this heart; Lamentably moaning; I remember the delightful sound of the waltz; My joy; Here's the mail troika rushing''. Accompanied by the Osipov Orchestra of Russian folk instruments, conducted by N. Kalinin.&lt;/div&gt;
|group9     =1986
|list9      = '''Melodiya &quot;To you, my friend&quot; C60 23601 002''': ''Cliff on the Volga; Do not awake my recollections; I leave for the road on my own; Between the high corn; Only once; Here's the mail troika rushing; Shine, shine my star; Coachman, do not rush the horses; To you, my friend.'' Accompanied by the Osipov Orchestra of Russian folk instruments, conducted by N. Kalinin.
|group10    =1977
|list10     = '''Melodiya: &quot;Alexandrov Song and Dance Ensemble of the Soviet Army&quot; 2-LP set, C60-08163-6''': The album devoted to the 60th anniversary of the Revolution after 1917; Alexandrov Ensemble conducted by B.A. Alexandrov. The song ''Dark-Eyed Cossack Girl''.
|group11    =1972
|list11     = '''Melodiya &quot;Russian folk songs and romances&quot; SM 03327-8''': ''A storm was raging; Not the autumnal fine rain; Glorious sea&amp;nbsp;— the sacred Baikal; Black raven; At the draw-well; Foggy morning; Oh, if only I could express it in sound; Kiss me, my darling; Drunken street; Shine, shine my star; Bored and sad; And so the soul longs (to).''.
}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Kharitonov, Leonid Mikhailovich
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1933-09-18
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kharitonov, Leonid Mikhailovich}}
[[Category:1933 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Russian bass-baritones]]
[[Category:Music award winners]]
[[Category:Operatic bass-baritones]]
[[Category:People from Irkutsk Oblast]]
[[Category:Russian award winners]]
[[Category:Russian male singers]]
[[Category:Russian military personnel]]
[[Category:Soviet singers]]

[[ru:Харитонов, Леонид Михайлович]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
