<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24729489" ns="0" title="National City acquisition by PNC"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2010}}
[[File:National City PNC transition.png|right|thumb|300px|The transitional logo used by [[PNC Financial Services]] after it finalized the purchase of [[National City Corp.]], January 2009 – June 2010.]]
The '''National City acquisition by PNC''' was the deal by [[PNC Financial Services]] to acquire [[National City Corp.]] on October 24, 2008 following National City's untenable loan losses during the [[subprime mortgage crisis]]. The deal received much controversy due to PNC using [[Troubled Asset Relief Program|TARP funds]] to buy National City only hours after accepting the funds while National City itself was denied funds, as well as civic pride for the city of [[Cleveland]], [[Ohio]], where National City was based.&lt;ref name=&quot;NatCity&quot;&gt;{{cite web |date= November 16, 2008|url = http://blog.cleveland.com/business/2008/11/pncnational_city_bank_deal_dra.html|title = PNC-National City bank deal draws criticism|publisher = © 2009 Cleveland Live, Inc.| accessdate = October 28, 2009 | last= |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pre-merger history==
Both PNC and National City's corporate histories date to the mid-19th century, when National City was founded as the '''City Bank of Cleveland''' in 1845 while PNC was founded in longtime Cleveland rival [[Pittsburgh]] as the '''Pittsburgh Trust and Savings Company''' in 1852. Both banks would later receive national charters under the [[National Banking Act]], with National City being able to print U.S. currency until the [[United States Treasury]] assumed operations in the 1920s. Both would have strong bases in their home markets, although PNC would until the 1980s be dwarfed in Pittsburgh by [[Mellon Financial|Mellon Bank]] (now [[The Bank of New York Mellon]]) and the massive influence of the [[Mellon family]].

Both banks began interstate expansion in the 1980s, with the two eventually competing in [[Cincinnati]] and [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]] by the end of the decade. Although PNC would never enter the Cleveland market on its own before the National City deal, National City did enter Pittsburgh in late 1995 with its acquisition of Pittsburgh-based [[Integra Bank (Pittsburgh)|Integra Bank]], putting it in third in market share behind PNC and Mellon, and eventually second after Mellon sold off its [[retail banking]] division to [[Royal Bank of Scotland|RBS]]-owned [[Citizens Financial Group]] in 2001.&lt;ref name=Pittsburgh&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07252/815602-28.stm | work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | title=Smaller banks aiming to raise profiles locally | first=Dan | last=Fitzpatrick | date=September 9, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==National City problems==
The downfall of National City began in 2007 when the [[United States housing bubble]] began to burst, and consumers began to [[Default (finance)|default]] on [[Subprime lending|subprime mortgages]], which National City had gotten involved with. Although National City was otherwise healthy on paper, the mortgage business was dragging down profits into losses, with the company CEO even fearing that the bank might [[Bank failure|fail]].&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.cleveland.com/business/2008/10/national_city_sold.html&lt;/ref&gt; National City then put itself up for sale in March 2008.

Adding to the bank's problems, [[The Wall Street Journal]] reported on June 6, 2008 that National City had entered into a [[memorandum of understanding]] with federal regulators, effectively putting the bank on [[probation]].  Terms of the confidential agreement, entered into a month earlier with the [[Office of the Comptroller of the Currency]] (which regulates nationally chartered banks), were not known.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/businessNews/idUSBNG8846820080606 National City under U.S. regulatory scrutiny: report], [[Rueters]], June 6, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;  

On June 10, 2008, National City Corp. confirmed that it had reached agreements with regulators ''&quot;regarding capital levels, risk-management practices and other aspects of its business''.&quot; The company stated that there had been no material developments in these areas since these memorandums of understanding were signed in April and May 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marketwatch.com/news/story/national-city-regulators-set-memorandums/story.aspx?guid=%7B7BF7ED6D%2D0812%2D4E75%2D9D5C%2DE271DFC3DF83%7D&amp;siteid=yhoof National City confirms agreements with regulators], MarketWatch.com, June 10, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

By October 2008, National City was in serious sale discussions following the failure of [[Washington Mutual]] and the forced sale of [[Wachovia]] to [[Wells Fargo]]. Among the publicly known front-runners were [[Minneapolis]]-based [[U.S. Bancorp]], [[Toronto]]-based [[Scotiabank]], and eventual buyer PNC.&lt;ref name=&quot;NatCity&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.cleveland.com/business/2008/10/are_pnc_scotiabank_interested.html&lt;/ref&gt; Scotiabank, which has long stayed out of the U.S. market unlike its [[Canada|Canadian]] rivals, was considered the best option for the local government since Scotiabank didn't have a pre-existing presence in the United States, allowing most of the National City operations to stay in Cleveland. Although National City and PNC had minimal overlap, the close proximity of Cleveland to Pittsburgh meant massive layoffs in both cities.

[[Wells Fargo]], [[Fifth Third Bank]], and crosstown rival [[KeyBank]] all also expressed interest in National City, with Fifth Third even offering to move its corporate headquarters to Cleveland from across the state in [[Cincinnati]] if it were to buy National City.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2009/06/key_bank_fifth_third_scotiaban.html&lt;/ref&gt; Like U.S. Bancorp, Fifth Third had a redundant footprint with National City, while Wells Fargo (even after its acquisition of [[Wachovia]]) had virtually no overlap with National City at all. KeyBank and National City had very little overlap outside [[Ohio]].

==Takeover by PNC==
[[File:NationalCityPNC.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The National City branch in [[Shenango Township, Lawrence County, Pennsylvania|Shenango Township, Pennsylvania]] near [[New Castle, Pennsylvania|New Castle]] on September 19, 2009 just before its conversion to [[PNC Financial Services|PNC Bank]], complete with the new PNC sign being covered up by [[tarpaulin]] with the National City logo. This National City branch (originally an [[Integra Bank (Pittsburgh)|Integra Bank]] branch before their acquisition by National City in late 1995) was one of the few National City branches in [[Western Pennsylvania]] that PNC wasn't required to divest by order of the [[United States Department of Justice]].]]
In early October 2008, PNC had offered a deal with National City, but backed out. Combined with Scotiabank's decision to once again not enter the U.S. market, National City began preliminary merger talks with U.S. Bancorp.&lt;ref name=&quot;NatCity&quot; /&gt;

Meanwhile, the U.S. government began to issue out [[Troubled Asset Relief Program|TARP funds]] from the [[Emergency Economic Stabilization Act of 2008|$700 billion bailout plan]] to banks to help stabilize their funds and issue out loans again. On October 23, 2008, when the National City [[board of directors]] were about to decide on the U.S Bancorp deal, PNC made an [[wikt:eleventh hour|11th hour]] offer to buy National City and be its [[White knight (business)|white knight]]. The following day, after National City was denied TARP funds by the U.S. government, they accepted PNC's offer at about $5.2 billion in stock.

The acquisition was a stock purchase transaction completed before the end of 2008.  National City will be merged into PNC, and the National City brand is eventually to be dissolved.&lt;ref&gt;[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]] [http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/08298/922560-100.stm PNC acquiring National City]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[KDKA-TV|kdka.com]] [http://kdka.com/business/PNC.Financial.Services.2.847872.html PNC Financial Services To Buy National City]&lt;/ref&gt;

The deal made PNC the largest bank in [[Pennsylvania]], [[Ohio]], and [[Kentucky]], as well as the second largest bank in [[Maryland]] and [[Indiana]]. It greatly expanded the PNC presence in the [[Midwestern United States|Midwest]] as well as entering the Florida market. [[Pittsburgh]], [[Louisville, Kentucky]], and [[Cincinnati]] were the only three markets before the acquisition deal that both banks had a major presence in. Overall, the deal made PNC the fifth-largest bank in the United States.

After the acquisition, PNC conducted a review of National City's balance sheet and took write-offs and reserves of $12.6 billion on the loan portfolio, indicating how severe the problems were at National City.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.pnc.com/webapp/unsec/Requester?resource=/wps/wcm/connect/f38b79004e5c6ed48e898ffc6d630ad7/IR_AR_2008_PNC_Chairman_Letter.pdf?MOD=AJPERES&amp;CACHEID=f38b79004e5c6ed48e898ffc6d630ad7&lt;/ref&gt;

==Criticism==
While some Clevelanders didn't like the fact that National City was being taken over by a Pittsburgh-based rival because of the [[Browns–Steelers rivalry|longstanding NFL rivalry]] between the two cities,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/tipoff/index.ssf/2008/10/fighting_words_if_youre_steele.html&lt;/ref&gt; many of the reactions to the PNC-National City deal involved the fact that TARP funds were used by PNC to buy National City.

[[United States House of Representatives|U.S Representative]] [[Dennis Kucinich]] of Cleveland unsuccessfully fought against the merger, arguing that National City's TARP funds application was never seriously considered, PNC actually took National City's own allotment of TARP funds in addition to its own, and the effects on the local economy.&lt;ref&gt;http://blog.cleveland.com/business/2008/11/national_citys_bailout_applica.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TARP&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/plaindealer/stories/index.ssf?/base/business-11/1230543069185071.xml&amp;coll=2&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, National City was the only one of the 25 largest U.S. banks eligible to receive TARP funds to be denied TARP funds, with [[Omaha, Nebraska]]-based [[Lauritzen Corporation]] (ranked 37th nationally) being the next-largest bank denied funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;TARP&quot; /&gt; (Banks owned by foreign companies such as [[Citizens Financial Group]], [[HSBC Bank USA]], and [[TD Bank, N.A.]] were automatically disqualified from receiving TARP funds.) Many Cleveland-based local businesses also had an unsuccessful [[grassroots]] movement to save National City.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2quKkUbO5-A&lt;/ref&gt;

There was also criticism from National City shareholders.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i7tqSztwask&lt;/ref&gt; The deal was described as a &quot;take-under,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/home/2008/10/24/banking-mergers-credit-biz-wall-cx_lm_1024banks.html | work=Forbes | first=Liz | last=Moyer | title=Banking Faces New Wave Of Consolidation | date=October 24, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; meaning the purchase price was below National City's market value.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://money.cnn.com/news/newsfeeds/articles/djf500/200810241231DOWJONESDJONLINE000713_FORTUNE5.htm }} {{Dead link|date=August 2010|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shareholders felt that they were being undervalued for their National City stock. Eight National City stockholders received a settlement from PNC on July 31, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2009/07/plain_dealer_file_national_cit.html&lt;/ref&gt; Under terms of the settlement, investors dropped their claims in return for the release of more than 400 pages of documents in Delaware State Court.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2009/07/plain_dealer_file_national_cit.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Nonetheless, the deal was approved by shareholders of both banks on December 23, 2008, and finalized on December 31, 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biz.yahoo.com/ap/081231/pnc_national_city.html?.v=2 PNC completes National City acquisition], [[Associated Press]] via Yahoo! Finance, December 31, 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
In the case of Pittsburgh, the two banks had significant overlap to the point it would pose [[antitrust]] issues in [[Western Pennsylvania]] since both banks had the top two market shares in the Pittsburgh region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pittsburgh&quot; /&gt; As a result, the [[United States Department of Justice]] required PNC to sell off 50 National City branches in the Pittsburgh area and 11 more branches in and around [[Erie, Pennsylvania|Erie]] to competitors.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/documents/branches-divested.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Wells Fargo, KeyBank, and Fifth Third—which had inquired about acquiring National City as a whole and in the case of Fifth Third had existing branches in Pittsburgh—were all interested in buying the National City branches.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/09080/957219-28.stm | work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | title=FNB won't buy National City units | first=Patricia | last=Sabatini | date=March 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[JPMorgan Chase]], [[Huntington Bancshares]], [[First Niagara Bank]] and [[FNB Corporation]] were also in discussions for the branches, with Huntington and FNB, like Fifth Third, having existing branches in Pittsburgh.

On April 7, 2009, PNC reached a deal with [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo]]-based [[First Niagara Bank]] to buy 57 of the branches.&lt;ref name=PNC&gt;http://kdka.com/business/PNC.First.Niagara.2.978660.html&lt;/ref&gt; First Niagara officially took over those branches on September 8 after the signs were changed over from National City during [[Labor Day|Labor Day Weekend]].&lt;ref name=FirstNiagara&gt;http://kdka.com/consumer/first.niagara.switchover.2.1170342.html&lt;/ref&gt; The branches not purchased by First Niagara were the four in [[Crawford County, Pennsylvania]] that PNC had to divest; of those four, one branch in [[Titusville, Pennsylvania|Titusville]] was sold to [[Emclaire Financial Group]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601208&amp;sid=afGesS_sXPd4&lt;/ref&gt; while the other three (one in [[Conneaut Lake, Pennsylvania|Conneaut Lake]], the other two in [[Meadville, Pennsylvania|Meadville]], including the branch inside [[Wal-Mart]]) were sold to [[Marquette Savings Bank]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marquettesavings.com/MarquetteAcquisitionRelease040709.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Although employees at the branches being sold off were retained (First Niagara, in fact, established a regional office in Pittsburgh at [[11 Stanwix Street]] near National City's Pittsburgh headquarters at [[20 Stanwix Street]], adding more jobs there.),&lt;ref name=&quot;PNC&quot;/&gt; there were still heavy layoffs at National City's headquarters in Cleveland.

Because of the significant overlap in Pittsburgh that remains, PNC closed seven National City branches &amp; five PNC branches on November 6, 2009, and later closed two more PNC branches on April 23, 2010, with the accounts at those branches being moved to the nearby PNC branch that will remain.&lt;ref&gt;http://kdka.com/local/PNC.Consolidation.Closing.2.1198598.html&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the agreement to buy the 57 National City branches from PNC, First Niagara has the [[right of first refusal]] to buy the National City branches PNC closes.&lt;ref name=November&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/09248/995688-28.stm | work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | title=First Niagara arrives in Western Pa | first=Patricia | last=Sabatini | date=September 5, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the branch closures and the sale of others to First Niagara, PNC still ended up with a 46% market share in Pittsburgh,&lt;ref name=46percent&gt;{{cite news| url=http://post-gazette.com/pg/09303/1009385-28.stm | work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | title=National City brand to disappear | first=Patricia | last=Sabatini | date=October 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; over three and a half times the market share of second-place [[Citizens Financial Group]] with 13%.&lt;ref name=&quot;PNC&quot;/&gt;

Although experts&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fiercefinance.com/story/how-can-banks-best-use-tarp-funds/2008-10-31&lt;/ref&gt; had expected more TARP funds to be used by stronger banks to buy out weaker rivals, no more deals were ultimately done involving TARP funds.

==Conversion to PNC==
The National City name, as expected, lasted well into 2009 since it would take PNC some time to integrate the two banks together.&lt;ref&gt;http://kdka.com/business/National.City.PNC.2.894007.html&lt;/ref&gt; PNC began to phase out the National City name in favor of PNC on November 7, 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;November&quot; /&gt; starting with [[Pennsylvania]] (where the two had the most overlap), Florida, and the [[Youngstown, Ohio|Youngstown]] &amp; [[Steubenville, Ohio|Steubenville]], Ohio regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;46percent&quot; /&gt; That day also saw the rebranding of National City Mortgage into [[PNC Mortgage]] and NatCity Investments fully merged into [[PNC Investments]]. In addition, National City's bank charter was merged into PNC's, effectively having the [[retail banking]] branches having yet to convert being legally known as '''PNC Bank, N.A., [[Doing business as|d/b/a]] National City Bank'''.&lt;ref name=Conversion&gt;http://www.welcometopnc.com/docs/first_phase_successfully_completed.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The conversion of National City to PNC was completed in June 2010, in the following phases:&lt;ref name=&quot;Conversion&quot; /&gt;

*'''February 19, 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kentucky.com/103/story/1121523.html&lt;/ref&gt; Central &amp; Southern Ohio (including [[Cincinnati]], [[Dayton, Ohio|Dayton]], and the state capital of [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dispatch.com/live/content/business/stories/2009/11/13/PNC_Branding.ART_ART_11-13-09_A10_O1FLEH2.html?type=rss&amp;cat=&amp;sid=101&lt;/ref&gt;), Southeastern [[Indiana]], and all of [[Kentucky]].
*'''April 12, 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crainscleveland.com/article/20100219/FREE/100219800&lt;/ref&gt; Northern Ohio (including National City's home market of Cleveland,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.crainscleveland.com/article/20091105/FREE/911049959/1099/RSS01&amp;rssfeed=RSS01&lt;/ref&gt; [[Akron, Ohio|Akron]], [[Canton, Ohio|Canton]], and [[Toledo, Ohio|Toledo]]) and all of [[Michigan]].
*'''June 14, 2010'''&lt;ref&gt;http://jobmag.com/news/2010/0301/1000016021070.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The rest of Indiana and all of [[Illinois]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.chicagobusiness.com/cgi-bin/news.pl?id=36114&amp;seenIt=1&lt;/ref&gt; [[Missouri]], and [[Wisconsin]].

==Legacy==
Despite becoming the largest bank in [[Ohio]] upon acquiring National City, PNC has since slipped to second-largest in the state behind [[Fifth Third Bank]], and is neck-and-neck with third place [[Huntington Bancshares]] for the second-place spot. Much of the losses for PNC came in Cleveland, where many Clevelanders left PNC upon the April 2010 conversion of National City in the area for other banks, most notably [[KeyBank]], which became the Cleveland market's largest bank by deposits. While National City was Cleveland's top bank at the time of PNC's acquisition, PNC slipped to fourth overall in the area behind KeyBank, locally-owned [[Third Federal Savings &amp; Loan]], and [[Citizens Financial Group|Citizens Financial Group's]] Charter One brand. PNC has, however, been able to regain some of the losses back, and is currently second in the Cleveland market behind KeyBank.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2011/10/keycorp_remains_no_1_in_market.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Outside of [[Greater Cleveland]], PNC's acquisition of National City has been considered a success by experts.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.holmesreport.com/casestudy-info/10751/PNCs-Growth-Shines-During-Dark-Economic-Days.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; The move allowed PNC to experience growth in [[Chicago]], and was able to use the [[Florida]] footprint acquired from National City to expand in the [[Southern United States]]. In 2011, PNC expanded its Florida presence by acquiring branches from [[BankAtlantic]] in the [[Tampa Bay Area]], and is currently in the process of acquiring [[RBC Bank]] from the [[Royal Bank of Canada]] as well as the [[Atlanta]]-area branches of [[Flagstar Bank]]. Within Cleveland, PNC opened a museum dedicated to the history of National City within [[PNC Center (Cleveland)|National City's former headquarters]] in Cleveland.&lt;ref&gt;http://pnc.mediaroom.com/index.php?s=43&amp;item=704&lt;/ref&gt;

PNC ultimately paid back its TARP funds in full in February 2010 while the National City conversion was still underway. However, it required the bank to sell its Global Investment Servicing division to [[The Bank of New York Mellon|BNY Mellon]] in order to have the funds to buy back its shares.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bnymellon.com/pressreleases/2010/pdf/pr020210.pdf|title=BNY Mellon to Acquire PNC’s Global Investment Servicing}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[First Niagara Bank]], which had mostly been a semi-regional bank within [[Western New York]] before acquiring the National City branches in the Pittsburgh area that PNC had to divest, used the National City branches it bought as a launching pad to expand into other markets, acquiring banks in [[Philadelphia]] and [[New England]] before acquiring [[HSBC Bank USA|HSBC Bank USA's]] [[Upstate New York]] branches.

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.nationalcity.com/ National City Corporation]
* [http://www.pnc.com/ PNC Bank]
* [http://www.welcometopnc.com/ National City/PNC Customer &quot;Transition&quot; Website]
{{PNC Financial Services Group}}
{{2008 economic crisis}}
{{50 largest US banks}}

[[Category:Late-2000s financial crisis]]
[[Category:Subprime mortgage crisis]]
[[Category:History of Cleveland, Ohio]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
