<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2473033" ns="0" title="Florida Hospital Orlando"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Hospital
| Name        = Florida Hospital
| Org/Group   = [[Adventist Health]]
| Image       = 
| Caption     = 
| Logo        = 
| Logo Size   = 
| Location    = 
| Region      = 
| State       = 
| Country     = 
| Coordinates = 
| HealthCare  = 
| Type        = 
| Speciality  = 
| Standards   = 
| Emergency   = 
| Affiliation = 
| Beds        = 
| Founded     = 
| Closed      = 
| Website     = http://www.adventisthealthnw.com/index.asp
| Wiki-Links  = 
}}

Located in [[Orlando, Florida|Orlando]], [[Florida]], '''Florida Hospital''' treats over 32,000 inpatients and 53,600 outpatients annually. This 900+ bed, acute-care community hospital also serves as a major tertiary facility for much of the Southeast. It is a part of the Florida Hospital system, a group of private hospitals which is owned and operated by [[Adventist Health System]], a part of the worldwide organization of the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]]. It is home to nationally recognized institutes for cancer, cardiology, diabetes, orthopedics and neuroscience.{{Citation needed|date=December 2008}} This hospital is not a level one trauma center but it does accept transfers for specialty care. The main purpose of the Florida Hospital group is medical emergencies and in-patient care. 
 
'''Locations''':

Florida Hospital has seven campuses owned and operated by Adventist Health System:
* Florida Hospital Orlando (Main Campus) 
* Florida Hospital Altamonte 
* Florida Hospital Apopka 
* Florida Hospital Celebration Health
* Florida Hospital East Orlando 
* Florida Hospital Kissimmee 
* Winter Park Memorial Hospital 

'''Florida Hospital Employment'''

Florida Hospital manages most of its recruiting and hiring internally, constantly filling nursing and technologist positions for its network of hospitals.  Qualified applicants are able to apply for nursing, therapy and technologist jobs directly on the [http://www.nursingjobsinflorida.com Florida Hospital Nursing] website.

== See also ==
* [[Adventist Health System]]
* [[List of Seventh-day Adventist hospitals]]

== External links ==
* [http://www.flhosp.org Florida Hospital website]
* [http://www.floridahospitalfoundation.org Florida Hospital Foundation website]
* [http://www.nursingjobsinflorida.com Florida Hospital Nursing Jobs]
* [http://www.floridahospitalforchildren.com Florida Hospital For Children in Orlando, Florida]
* [http://www.globalroboticsinstitute.com Florida Hospital's Global Robotics Institute in Celebration, Florida]
* [http://www.celebrationhealth.com Florida Hospital Celebration Health in Celebration, Florida]
* [http://www.floridabariatric.com Florida Hospital Celebration Bariatric Center in Celebrataion, Florida]
* [http://www.thesportsmedicineteam.com Florida Hospital Sports Medicine in Celebration, Florida]
* [http://www.celebrationjrc.com Florida Hospital Joint Replacement Center in Celebration, Florida]
* [http://www.celebrationspinecenter.com Florida Hospital Celebration Spine Center in Celebration, Florida]
* [http://www.celebrationcolorectal.com Florida Hospital Celebration Colorectal in Celebration, Florida]

{{coord missing|Florida}}

[[Category:Hospitals affiliated with the Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
[[Category:Hospitals in Florida]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Orlando, Florida]]


{{SeventhdayAdventist-stub}}
{{US-hospital-stub}}
{{Florida-Hospital-stub}}

[[fr:Hôpital de la Floride]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
