<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24757862" ns="0" title="Symbiosis Institute of Technology"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox university
|name            = Symbiosis institute of technology
|image_name      =  
|motto           = ''Vasdhaiva Kutumbakam''
|mottoeng        = The world is one family
|image_size      = 150px
|established     = 2008
|type            = Constituent of [[Symbiosis International University]], India
|city            = [[Pune, Maharashtra|Pune]]
|state           = [[Maharashtra]]
|country         = India
|chancellor      = [[S. B. Mujumdar]]
|vice_chancellor = Dr.Bhushan Patwardhan
|dean            = Dr. T.P. Singh
|undergrad       = 1243
|faculty         = 25+
|coor            = {{Coord|18.5177|73.8148|display=inline,title|type:edu}}
|affiliations    = UGC,AICTE
|website         = http://www.sitpune.edu.in/
|display=inline,title}} 

'''Symbiosis International University''' (S.I.U) is a private co-educational, multi-institutional [[university]] located in [[Pune]], [[Maharashtra]], [[India]]. It has been given official recognition by the [[University Grants Commission (India)|UGC]] and the [[All india council for technical education|AICTE]]. The [[National Assessment and Accreditation Council]] has conferred an 'A' grade to the University. SIU is part of the [[Symbiosis Society]] which is its managing body.

The Society was established in 1971 by Padmashree [[Dr S.B. Mujumdar]]. It was given autonomous status in 2002 by the Ministry of Human Resources Development&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Notification no F-9-12/2001/U-3, Under Section 3 of the UGC Act of 1956&lt;/ref&gt; and since then has opened many more institutes affiliated to it.

Symbiosis International University has 19 Academic Institutions&lt;ref&gt;http://siu.edu.in/html/inner.asp?linkid=1&lt;/ref&gt; spread over 9 campuses in Pune, [[Noida]] , [[Bengaluru]] and [[Nashik]].&lt;ref name=&quot;siu.edu.in&quot;&gt;http://siu.edu.in/html/inner.asp?linkid=5&lt;/ref&gt; All these institutes form part of the [[Symbiosis Society]], with the other institutes in the Society being affiliated to various other bodies.

'''Symbiosis Institute of Technology''' is an [[educational institute]] under the aegis of [[Symbiosis International University]] at [[Pune, Maharashtra]], India. The institute is located in the [[Lavale]] campus, [[Pune]].

==History==

The first institutions belonging to the Symbiosis Society were established in 1971, and were affiliated to the [[University of Pune]]. Established in 1971 under the patronage of [[S. B. Mujumdar]], President and Founding Director, the Symbiosis Society is registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 and the Bombay Public Trust, Act, 1950. The Principal Director of Symbiosis Society is Mrs. Dr.[[Vidya Yeravdekar]].
[[File:Symbiosis International University.jpg|thumb|Symbiosis ]]

In 2002, as part of a larger program to grant autonomy to institutions of academic excellence, the Ministry of Human Resources Development conferred the &quot;Deemed to be University&quot; status on three institutes under the Symbiosis umbrella - the [[Symbiosis Institute of Computer Studies and Research]], [[Symbiosis Institute of Business Management]] (SIBM) and [[Symbiosis Society's Law College]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

In 2006 the University Grants Commission withdrew the word &quot;Deemed&quot; and renamed the institution as &quot;Symbiosis International University&quot;.

==Courses Offered==
SIT offers 4-year Bachelor of Technology ([[B.Tech]]) programs in the following core engineering disciplines:
#Computer Science
#Electronics and Telecommunication
#Information Technology
#Mechanical Engineering
#Civil Engineering

SIT also offers M.Tech and PhD in various fields.

==Board of management==
Members of Board of Management of SIU

Notification No. SIU/28/235 dated 24 April 2009
 
 
A.	Vice Chancellor	 
 	 	 
1.  Professor Bhushan Patwardhan
 	 	 
B.	Deans Of Faculties
 	 	 
1. Brig. K. K. Khanzode (Retd.), Faculty of Computer Studies
2. Dr. Rajiv Yeravdekar,Faculty of Health Sciences
 	 	 
C.	Nominees of the Chancellor
 	 	 
1. Dr. P. J. Lavakare	Country Partner, Institute Of International Education
2. Mr. Ravi Pandit	Chairman and Group CEO, KPIT Cummins Infosystems Ltd.
3. Dr. Sanjay Dhande	Director, IIT, Kanpur
 	 	  	 	 
D.	Nominee of the Chairman, UGC
 	 	 
1. Mr. Pradeep Bhargav	Managing Director, Cummins Generator Technologies India Ltd.
 	 	 
E.	Nominee of the Government of India
 	 	 
1. Mr. Sunil Kumar, Jt. Secretary, MHRD, New Delhi

F.	Nominee of Funding agency
 	 	 
1. Ms. Swati Mujumdar,Director, SCDL 
 	 	 
G.	Three Teachers according to Seniority
 	 	 
1. Mr. H. C. Hajare,Faculty Of Law
2. Dr. Mrs. Rajani Gupte,Faculty Of Management
3. Mr. Vinay Mundada,Faculty Of Media, Communication and Design 
 	 	 
H.	Nominee of Sponsoring Society
 	 	 
1. Dr. Mrs. Vidya Yeravdekar,Principal Director, Symbiosis Society. 
 	 	 
I.	Registrar, SIU

==Admissions==
*'''[http://www.set-test.org/ Symbiosis Entrance Test (SET)]''' is a common written test for the admission processes of undergraduate institutes of Symbiosis International University. It is a mandatory written test for admission into undergraduate programmes of all Symbiosis institutes.

In addition to the SET, admissions to Symbiosis Institute of Technology may also be secured via scores received in other entrance exams like the JEE, AIEEE or the Maharashtra CET.

==Special features==
===Additional Diplomas===
SIT through collaboration with the sister institutes offers a range of diplomas along with the 4-year B. Tech degrees.

Some of these diplomas along with the institutes offering them are as follows:
#Diploma in Business Management - [[Symbiosis Institute of Business Management]]

==Collaborations==
Symbiosis Institute of Technology has initiated steps to collaborate on research from and with Nanayang Technological University, Singapore.
Higher Colleges of Technology, Abu Dubai, UAE and Symbiosis International University are in association that covers a student faculty transfer and long term and short term academic programs through the Center for Excellence for Applied Research and Training (CERT).
American College of Dubai, UAE and Symbiosis International University are in collaboration that allows undergraduate students who wish to pursue Management and Information Technology studies in India can partake the student transfer program from the college to the SIU.
University College of Sedaya International, Malaysia and Symbiosis International University are in collaboration for promoting cooperation in education and service to the community through an international sharing of students and knowledge.

==Campus==
The campus of SIT is situated next to lupin at Lavale.
The administration is aiming for a fully residential campus but as of today it is not in a situation to provide accommodation to students  There are no staff quarters inside the campus. However the hostel blocks are located within the campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sitpune.edu.in/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Libraries, collections, and museum===
The Central Library of Symbiosis Institute of Technology houses 7500+ volumes including encyclopedias, dictionaries, handbooks, manuals, reference books, international and national journals and periodicals.

===Activities and Societies===


'''QuaeroArtis'''&lt;br /&gt;

Its an intellectual and extra-curricular umbrella society for Symbiosis Institute of Technology. Clubs And societies under Quaero Artis:&lt;br /&gt;

'''Greencell''' &lt;br /&gt;
The Symbiosis Institute of Technology's Green Cell is a body of students and faculty dedicated to the service of environment. The Green cell will help mobilize environment conservation related activities, engage in sustainability projects, participate with NGO's , companies, universities in their eco-goals.

'''SIT Literary Club'''&lt;br /&gt;
A club dedicated to enhancing the intellectualism within the students of the institute. Its a club to ignite the minds and encourage the winner inside. Improve and Expose your talent in quiz, debates, elocution, prose, poetry, publishing, writing, etc.

'''Paparazzo - S.I.T'''&lt;br /&gt;
The official photography club of Symbiosis Institute of Technology, dedicated towards budding and enthusiastic photographers.

'''SIT Entrepreneurship and Innovation Cell'''&lt;br /&gt;
An Organisation to Ignite the Spirit of Entrepreneurship in Young Individuals and Develop Future Leaders and to inculcate the art of handling and running enterprises.

'''SIT Music club'''&lt;br /&gt;
It is a place for the music lovers and musicians of SIT to talk, think and play their music.

===Athletics and Sports===


===Festivals===

==People==

===Students===
Symbiosis Institute of Technology currently has 1100+ students.  The institute has two girls' hostels and five boys' hostels. Each hostel is equipped with sports and internet facilities. 

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.siu.edu/ Official Website]

{{Symbiosis Society}}

[[Category:Universities and colleges in Maharashtra]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
