<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24768334" ns="0" title="Where the Indian Goes"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox graphic novel
&lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
|title           =Where the Indian Goes
|foreigntitle    =Là où va l'Indien...
|image           = 
|imagesize       = 
|caption         =
|publisher       =[[Dargaud]]
|date            =1985
|series          =[[XIII (comics)|XIII]]
|main_char_team  =
|origpublication =
|origlanguage    =French
|origisbn        =0-87416-081-2
|writers         =[[Jean Van Hamme]]
|artists         =[[William Vance]]
|pages           =44
|previssue       =&quot;[[The Day of the Black Sun]]&quot;
|nextissue       =&quot;[[All the Tears of Hell]]&quot;
}}
&quot;'''Where the Indian Goes'''&quot; is the second volume of the
''[[XIII (comics)|XIII]]'' comic series, written by [[Jean Van Hamme]] and drawn by [[William Vance]].
Originally released in 1985, this volume  was one of the few issues that [[Alias Enterprises|Alias comics]] released in English in 2005. The volume was released in English again on 16 October 2010 by [[Cinebook]].

==Plot==
The second volume begins with XIII's search for Kim Rowland leading to his capture by the US Army. General Carrington identifies XIII as Steve Rowland, Kim Rowland's husband and former member of SPADS (Special Assault and Destroying Sections). Carrington had created and commanded the SPADS when Rowland was supposedly killed in an helicopter crash two years before. &quot;Rowland&quot; is returned to his home in Southbourg by Carrington's aide Major Jones. While his father Jeremie Rowland, a rich land owner, and other relatives express no doubt about his identity, XIII is disappointed to not find Kim there. Amos comes to meet XIII and still holds him as his prime suspect as his fingerprints were found on the sniper rifle that shot President Sheridan. But as XIII's amnesia prevents him to be of any use to find who has sponsored Sheridan's assassination, Amos lets XIII go looking for Kim Rowland because as she's hiding, he supposes she knows something about it. XIII finally manages to find the location of &quot;where the Indian goes&quot;, but is tricked by Jeremie Rowland's young wife Felicity, who kills Jeremie Rowland and Steve's uncle Matt, implicating XIII for the murders in the aim to inherit Jeremy's fortune. XIII nevertheless escapes the police with Carrington's and Major Jones' help, and meets with Kim at her hidden cabin. Kim reveals her tattoo, number XVII, and that she doesn't know XIII's real name, who is in fact not Steve Rowland. Kim disappears as XIII is arrested by the police, tried and found guilty for the murder of the Matt and Jeremie Rowland, and sentenced to maximum security prison, setting up the next issue, &quot;All the Tears of Hell&quot;.

==Issue notes==
This issue marks the first appearance of General Ben Carrington and Major Jones in the series. Minor character Felicity Brown also first appears in this issue.

{{XIII}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Where The Indian Goes}}
[[Category:Belgian comics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
