<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="248449" ns="0" title="O&#039;Hare International Airport"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|ORD||Ord (disambiguation)}}
{{Redirect|Ohare|people with that name|O'Hare (surname)}}
{{Infobox airport
| name         = Chicago O'Hare International Airport
| image        = O'Hare International Airport (USGS).png
| caption      = [[USGS]] aerial image, 2011
| IATA         = ORD
| ICAO         = KORD
| FAA          = ORD
| type         = Public
| owner        = [[Chicago|City of Chicago]]
| operator     = Chicago Airport System
| city-served  = [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], USA
| hub          =
&lt;div&gt;
*[[American Airlines]]
*[[United Airlines]]
*[[Air Choice One]]
| elevation-f  = 668
| elevation-m  = 204
| website      = [http://www.flychicago.com/About/OHare/Default.aspx flychicago.com/About/...]
| latd = 41 | latm = 58 | lats = 43 | latNS = N
| longd= 87 | longm= 54 | longs= 17 | longEW= W
| coordinates_region  = US-IL
| pushpin_map         = Chicago
| pushpin_label       = '''ORD'''
| pushpin_map_caption = Location of airport in Chicago
| r1-number    = 4L/22R
| r1-length-f  = 7,500
| r1-length-m  = 2,286
| r1-surface   = [[Asphalt]]
| r2-number    = 4R/22L
| r2-length-f  = 8,075
| r2-length-m  = 2,461
| r2-surface   = Asphalt
| r3-number    = 9L/27R
| r3-length-f  = 7,500
| r3-length-m  = 2,286
| r3-surface   = [[Concrete]]
| r4-number    = 9R/27L
| r4-length-f  = 7,967
| r4-length-m  = 2,428
| r4-surface   = Asphalt/Concrete
| r5-number    = 10/28
| r5-length-f  = 13,001
| r5-length-m  = 3,962
| r5-surface   = Asphalt/Concrete
| r6-number    = 14L/32R
| r6-length-f  = 10,005
| r6-length-m  = 3,050
| r6-surface   = Asphalt
| r7-number    = 14R/32L
| r7-length-f  = 9,685
| r7-length-m  = 2,952
| r7-surface   = Asphalt/Concrete
| h1-number    = H1
| h1-length-f  = 200
| h1-length-m  = 61
| h1-surface   = Concrete
| stat-year    = 2010
| stat1-header = Passenger volume
| stat1-data   = 66,665,390
| stat2-header =
| stat2-data   =
| stat3-header =
| stat3-data   =
| footnotes    = Sources: [[Federal Aviation Administration|FAA]]&lt;ref name=FAA&gt;{{FAA-airport|ID=ORD|use=PU|own=PU|site=04508.*A}}, effective March 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; and airport's website.&lt;ref name=CAS&gt;[http://www.flychicago.com/Statistics/stats/1208SUMMARY.pdf Monthly Operations, Passengers, Cargo Summary By Class], For December 2008 (published January 21, 2009)&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''Chicago O'Hare International Airport''' {{Airport codes|ORD|KORD|ORD}}, also known as '''O'Hare Airport''', '''O'Hare Field''', '''Chicago Airport''', '''Chicago International Airport''', or simply '''O'Hare''', is a major [[airport]] located in the northwestern-most corner of [[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], United States, {{convert|17|mi|km|0}} northwest of the [[Chicago Loop]]. It is the primary airport serving the Chicago area, with [[Chicago Midway International Airport]], about {{convert|10|mi|km|0}} closer to the Loop, serving as a secondary airport for domestic flights.

[[United Airlines]] (including United Express) is the largest airline at O'Hare, carrying over 45% of passengers. O'Hare is the second-largest hub for [[United Airlines]] after [[George Bush Intercontinental Airport|Houston-Bush]]. [[American Airlines]] (including American Eagle) has the second largest operation at O'Hare, carrying 37.08% of passengers. O'Hare is its second-largest hub after [[Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport|Dallas/Fort Worth]].&lt;ref&gt;
  {{cite web
  | url = http://www.transtats.bts.gov/airports.asp?pn=1&amp;Airport=ORD
  | title = Chicago, IL: O'Hare (ORD)
  | publisher = [[Bureau of Transportation Statistics]]
  | date = | accessdate = November 3, 2010
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to 2005, O'Hare was the [[world's busiest airport]] in terms of takeoffs and landings. Mainly due to limits imposed by the federal government to reduce flight delays at O'Hare,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Subcommittee on Aviation: Hearing on Delay Reduction Efforts at Chicago’s O’Hare Airport | publisher = United States House of Representatives | url = http://www.house.gov/transportation/aviation/09-09-04/09-09-04memo.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hartsfield-Jackson Atlanta International Airport]] became the busiest by that metric in 2005. O'Hare is now the [[World's busiest airports by passenger traffic|third busiest airport]] in the world with 66,665,390 passengers passing through the airport in 2010, a +3.3% change from 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohare.com/Statistics/stats/1209SUMMARY.pdf Monthly Operations, Passengers, Cargo Summary By Class] For December 2009, Midway Airport&lt;/ref&gt; It is the world's second busiest airport in terms of aircraft movements. In 2008, the airport had 881,566 aircraft operations, an average of 2,409 per day (64% scheduled commercial, 33% air taxi, 3% general aviation and &lt;1% military).&lt;ref name=FAA /&gt; O'Hare has a strong international presence, with flights to more than 60 foreign destinations: it is the fourth busiest international gateway in the United States behind [[John F. Kennedy International Airport]] in New York City, [[Los Angeles International Airport]] and [[Miami International Airport]].

O’Hare has been voted the &quot;Best Airport in North America&quot; for 10 years by two separate sources: Readers of the U.S. Edition of ''Business Traveler Magazine'' (1998–2003) and ''Global Traveler Magazine'' (2004–2007).&lt;ref&gt;{{PDFlink|[http://www.flychicago.com/news/pdf/PressRelease12-6-07.pdf O'Hare wins &quot;Best Airport in North America&quot; ]|25.0&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt; Travel and Leisure magazine's 2009 &quot;America's Favorite Cities&quot; ranked Chicago's Airport System (O'Hare and Midway) the second-worst for delays, New York City's airport system (JFK, Newark Liberty, and LaGuardia) being the first.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.travelandleisure.com/afc/2009/category/17/subcategory/98 ]{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; O'Hare currently accounts for over a sixth of the nation's total flight cancellations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Table 6: Ranking of Major Airport On-Time Departure Performance Year-to-date through July 2006 | publisher = Bureau of Transportation Statistics | url = http://www.bts.gov/programs/airline_information/airline_ontime_tables/2006_07/html/table_06.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is operated by the City of Chicago Department of Aviation, associated with an umbrella regional authority. Most of O'Hare Airport is in [[Cook County, Illinois|Cook County]], but a section of the southwest part of the airport is in [[DuPage County, Illinois|DuPage County]]. The Cook County portion is located within a section of the city of Chicago contiguously connected to the rest of the city via a narrow strip of land about {{convert|200|ft|m}} wide, running along Foster Ave. from the [[Des Plaines River]] to the airport. This land was annexed into the city limits in the 1950s to assure the massive tax revenue associated with the airport being part of the city. The strip is bounded on the north by [[Rosemont, Illinois|Rosemont]] and the south by [[Schiller Park, Illinois|Schiller Park]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://egov.cityofchicago.org/webportal/COCWebPortal/COC_ATTACH/41st.pdf|title= Ward 41|accessdate=December 24, 2008|date= |year=2007|month=October|format= PDF|work= Webportal|publisher= City of Chicago}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The airport is named after [[Edward O'Hare]], the U.S. Navy's first flying ace and [[Medal of Honor]] recipient in [[World War II]].

==History==
[[File:Edward Butch O'Hare's Aircraft on display at ORD.jpg|thumb|Model of &quot;Butch&quot; O'Hare's Grumman F4F-3 Wildcat on display in Terminal 2 of the airport]]
===World War II===
{{See also|Illinois World War II Army Airfields}}
The airport was constructed in 1942–43 as a manufacturing plant for [[Douglas Aircraft Company|Douglas]] [[C-54 Skymaster|C-54]]s during [[World War II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nwchicagohistory.org&quot;&gt;http://nwchicagohistory.org/nwch_ohare.html&lt;/ref&gt; The site was chosen for its proximity to the city and transportation.&lt;ref name=&quot;nwchicagohistory.org&quot;/&gt; The two million square-foot (180,000 m²) factory needed easy access to the workforce of the nation's then-second-largest city, as well as its extensive railroad infrastructure. [[Orchard Place, Illinois|Orchard Place]] was a small nearby farming community.&lt;ref name=&quot;nwchicagohistory.org&quot;/&gt;

Douglas Company's contract ended in 1945 and though plans were proposed to build commercial aircraft, the company ultimately chose to concentrate production on the west coast. With the departure of Douglas, the airport took the name '''Orchard Field Airport''', 
the source of its three-letter IATA code '''ORD'''.

In 1945, the facility was chosen by the city of Chicago as the site for a facility to meet future aviation demands. Matthew Laflin Rockwell (1915–1988) was the director of planning for the [[U.S. Army Corps of Engineers]] and responsible for the site selection and design of O'Hare International Airport. He was the great grandson of [[Matthew Laflin]], a founder and pioneer of Chicago. The airport was renamed to &quot;O'Hare International Airport&quot; in 1949.

===Commercial development===
By the early 1950s [[Chicago Midway International Airport]], Chicago's primary airport since 1931, had become too crowded despite multiple expansions and could not handle the planned first generation of jets. The city of Chicago and the [[Federal Aviation Administration|FAA]] began to develop O'Hare as the main airport for Chicago's future.

Commercial passenger flights started in 1955 and by the following year O'Hare was served by American, BOAC, Braniff, Capital, Delta, Eastern, North Central, Pan Am, TWA and United, along with freight airlines Riddle and Slick.&lt;ref name=&quot;oharehistory&quot;&gt;http://www.ohare.com/About/History/Default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; O'Hare also opened a $1 million &quot;Skymotive&quot; terminal for corporate aircraft in 1955, the first of its kind.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,891626,00.html | work=Time | title=Business: Orphans' Home | date=October 24, 1955}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Growth was slow at first. By 1957 Chicago had invested over $25 million in O'Hare, but Midway remained the world's busiest airport and airlines were reluctant to relocate all of their services to O'Hare until better highway access and other capital improvements were completed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,937983,00.html | work=Time | title=AIRPORTS FOR THE JET AGE-: The U.S. Is Far from Ready | date=October 21, 1957}}&lt;/ref&gt; The April 1957 Official Airline Guide shows 10 weekday departures on United, 9 on American, 6 on Capital, 3 Eastern, 3 TWA, 2 Delta, 2 North Central, and 1 Braniff. Also three weekly Pan Am and one weekly BOAC (Air France and Lufthansa were at Midway). O'Hare's first dedicated international terminal opened in August 1958. By April 1959 the airport had expanded to {{convert|7,200|acre|km2}} with new hangars, terminals, parking and other facilities. The expressway link to downtown Chicago was completed in 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;oharehistory&quot; /&gt;

All fixed-wing scheduled airline service in Chicago moved from Midway to O'Hare by July 1962. President [[John F. Kennedy]] attended a dedication ceremony in 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;oharehistory&quot; /&gt; The arrival of Midway's former traffic quickly made O'Hare the world's busiest airport, serving 10 million passengers annually. Within two years that number would double, with more people passing through O'Hare in 12 months than [[Ellis Island]] had processed in its entire existence. In late 1972, Chicago city officials reached an agreement with airlines to shift some services back to Midway in order to ease the overcrowding at O'Hare.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,945164-2,00.html | work=Time | title=DISASTERS: Death at Midway | date=December 18, 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite this, O'Hare remained the world's busiest airport through the 1970s and 1980s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/1981/04/27/us/o-hare-said-to-remain-world-s-busiest-airport.html?scp=15&amp;sq=o%27hare&amp;st=nyt | work=The New York Times | title=O'Hare Said to Remain World's Busiest Airport | date=April 27, 1981}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1970s Midway was nearly abandoned; it enjoyed a revival after startup carrier [[Midway Airlines]] began low-cost service there in 1979-80.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,948903,00.html | work=Time | title=Business: Aerial Dogfight | date=July 14, 1980}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Airline Operations
|+(Takeoffs Plus Landings)
|-
! !! Midway !! O'Hare
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1958
| 337421 || 66205
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1959
| 345170 || 82417
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1960
| 298582 || 163351
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1961
| 187978 || 235908
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1962
| 46873 || 331090
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1963
| 19054 || 358266
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1964
| 19017 || 389640
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1965
| 16716 || 443026
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1966
| 5090 || 478644
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1967
| 4427 || 573506
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1968
| 26941 || 628632
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1969
| 31394 || 632030
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1970
| 43553 || 598973
|- align=&quot;right&quot;
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | 1971
| 51734 || 565826
|}

===Pre-deregulation service===
Prior to [[airline deregulation]] in 1978, a number of major airlines had focused operations at O'Hare.

[[American Airlines]], [[United Airlines]] and [[Trans World Airlines]] operated numerous routes to the West Coast, Northeast and Midwest, and TWA also served Europe nonstop from Chicago.&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/american/1978-june-8/4744&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/united/1974-july-1/7364&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/twa/1977-june-9/13630&lt;/ref&gt; [[Northwest Airlines|Northwest Orient Airlines]] offered flights to the Northeast, Pacific Northwest, Florida and Hawaii, as well as service through Alaska to Japan and the Far East.&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/northwest/1974-february-1/7010&lt;/ref&gt; [[Delta Air Lines]] served destinations in the Southeast and Midwest.&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/delta-n-east/1973-june-1/6611&lt;/ref&gt;

During this era, Terminal 1 was used for international flights. Terminal 2 (concourses D, E and F) served United, Ozark, Braniff, Eastern, Northwest, Continental and Piedmont. In Terminal 3, Concourse G served TWA and Air Canada, and Concourses H and K served American, Delta and North Central (later merged into Republic Airlines). 

===Post-deregulation developments===
In the 1980s, after deregulation, TWA replaced Chicago with St. Louis as its main mid-continent hub.&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/twa/1987-january-1/7236&lt;/ref&gt; Northwest likewise shifted to a Minneapolis and Detroit-centered network by the early 1990s following its acquisition of [[Republic Airlines (1979-1986)|Republic Airlines]] in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;http://airchive.com/html/timetable-and-route-maps/northwest/1994-domestic-route-map/7021&lt;/ref&gt;

United and American both established nationwide hubs at the airport in the 1980s which continue to operate today. United developed  a new Terminal 1 designed by [[Helmut Jahn]], which was built between 1985 and 1987 on the site of the old international terminal. American renovated its existing facilities in Terminal 3 by 1990. Delta maintained a Chicago hub for some time, and opened a new Concourse L in Terminal 3 (initially known as the &quot;Delta Flight Center&quot;) in 1983, but ultimately closed its Chicago hub in the 1990s.

Due to the construction of Terminal 1 for United, international flights were relocated to a temporary Terminal 4 from 1984 until 1993. Terminal 4 was located on the ground floor of the main parking garage; international passengers would check in there and be taken directly to their aircraft by bus. A new Terminal 5 opened in 1993 to handle all international arrivals and many international departures. Since the opening of Terminal 5, Terminal 4 has been changed into the airport's facility for [[Chicago Transit Authority|CTA]] buses, hotel shuttles, and other ground transportation; the T4 designation may be used again in the future as new terminals are developed. The [[Blue Line (Chicago Transit Authority)|CTA Blue Line]] was extended to the airport in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;oharehistory&quot; /&gt;

Total annual passenger volume at O'Hare reached 30 million in 1968, 40 million in 1976, 60 million in 1990 and 70 million in 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;oharehistory&quot; /&gt;

Delta moved from Terminal 3 to Terminal 2 in 2009 in order to align its operations with merger partner Northwest Airlines. Continental moved from Terminal 2 to Terminal 1 in 2010 as part of its merger with United Airlines.&lt;ref&gt;http://chicagobreakingbusiness.com/2010/11/continental-moving-to-uniteds-ohare-terminal-next-week.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States Air Force use===
: ''See: [[O'Hare Air Reserve Station]]''
The original Douglas Aircraft [[C-54 Skymaster]] transport manufacturing plant on the northeast side of the airport became a [[United States Air Force]] [[Air National Guard]] and [[Air Force Reserve Command|Air Force Reserve]] facility after World War II.  It was used by the USAF from 1947 until 1999 as '''O'Hare Air Reserve Station''', making the airport a joint civil-military airfield during this period.

The 1993 [[Base Realignment and Closure]] (BRAC) Commission recommended the closure of O'Hare Air Reserve Station as proposed by the municipal government of the City of Chicago and the transfer of both the [[Illinois Air National Guard]]'s [[126th Air Refueling Wing]] (126 ARW) and its [[KC-135]] aircraft, and the [[Air Force Reserve Command]]'s [[928th Airlift Wing]] (928 AW) and its [[C-130]] aircraft to new facilities to be constructed at [[Scott AFB]], Illinois.  The 126 ARW moved from the former O'Hare Air Reserve Station at O'Hare International Airport to [[Scott AFB]], Illinois in 1999 as recommended by the Base Realignment and Closure Commission's Report to Congress in conjunction with the closure of the [[Air Force Reserve Command]] and [[Air National Guard]] facilities at O'Hare.  Instead of moving to Scott AFB, subsequent BRAC action directed that the 928 AW be inactivated and its C-130 aircraft reallocated to other Air Force, Air Force Reserve and Air National Guard units.  

Following the closure of the O'Hare Air Reserve Station, the former USAF facilities were redeveloped for air cargo and general aviation. Today, Signature Flight Support services private aircraft in this area.

=== Accidents and incidents ===
1057 fatalities have occurred as a result of accidents en route to or from Chicago O'Hare.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/airport/airport.php?id=ORD |title=Aviation Safety Network &gt; ASN Aviation Safety Database &gt; Airports &gt; Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL profile |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date=July 13, 2008 |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On September 2, 2010, American Airlines Flight 1487 to Reno, Nevada was struck by lightning and forced to return. No one was hurt.
* On the afternoon of November 7, 2006, a group of United Airlines workers [[2006 O'Hare International Airport UFO sighting|reported seeing an unidentified flying object]] near gate C-17.&lt;ref name=&quot;OHareUFO&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/local/chi-0701010141jan01,1,3957154.column?coll=chi-news-hed | title = In the sky! A bird? A plane? A ... UFO? | publisher = Chicago Tribune | accessdate = January 1, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On October 8, 2001, on [[American Airlines]] Flight 1238, en route from Los Angeles to Chicago, a [[psychosis|psychotic]] passenger stormed the cockpit 40 minutes before landing in Chicago, causing the plane to drop sharply and spark panic. In light of the fear ignited by [[September 11 attacks|9/11]], flight crew and passengers were quickly able to wrestle the man to the ground and subdue him. Additionally, a [[distress signal]] was sent by the pilots, causing two [[F-16 Fighting Falcon|F-16]]s to race at [[supersonic]] speeds to intercept and escort the aircraft to O'Hare International Airport. This caused a [[sonic boom]] in Chicago's northwest suburbs, startling millions of residents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://proquest.umi.com/pqdweb?did=83625993&amp;sid=1&amp;Fmt=3&amp;clientId=8829&amp;RQT=309&amp;VName=PQD |title=ProQuest Login – ProQuest |publisher=Proquest.umi.com |date= |accessdate=March 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On April 1, 1999, a near-miss occurred on the intersection on Runways 14 right and 27 left between Korean Air Flight 36 and Air China 9018, both Boeing 747s. The Korean Air 747-400 pilot took evasive action by applying maximum power, rotating earlier than planned, and rolling slightly left once airborne to avoid the Air China Boeing 747 freighter.  The aircraft missed each other by an estimated {{convert|75|ft|m}}.  The actions of the Korean Air flight crew are credited with saving everyone on board both aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mY2576xOeww youtube1]&lt;/ref&gt; 7 years later, on July 23, 2006, another near-miss occurred between Giant 6972, an Atlas Air Boeing 747 and United Airlines Flight 1015, a Boeing 737, who missed each other by {{convert|35|ft|m}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mrSEJyYcq08 youtube2] (Part 2, 6:04 onwards in the video), [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xqdj8VJ9nH0 youtube video3]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On February 9, 1998, [[American Airlines Flight 1340]] crashed upon landing in Chicago from Kansas City International Airport injuring 22 passengers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19980209-0 |title=ASN Aircraft accident Boeing 727–223 N845AA Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On October 31, 1994, [[American Eagle Flight 4184]] crashed over northwestern Indiana en route to Chicago, killing all 68 people on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19941031-1 |title=ASN Aircraft accident Aérospatiale/Aeritalia ATR-72-212 N401AM Roselawn, IN |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On September 8, 1994, [[USAir Flight 427]] crashed on approach to [[Pittsburgh]], [[Pennsylvania|PA]], after departing O'Hare, killing all 132 people on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19940908-0 |title=ASN Aircraft accident Boeing 737-3B7 N513AU Aliquippa, PA |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On July 19, 1989, [[United Airlines Flight 232]], en route to Chicago from Denver, crash-landed in [[Sioux City, Iowa]], killing 111 people on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19890719-1 |title=ASN Aircraft accident McDonnell Douglas DC-10-10 N1819U Sioux Gateway Airport, IA (SUX) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On August 10, 1986, [[American Trans Air Flight 131]] exploded on the tarmac at O'Hare, destroying the plane.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19860810-0 |title=ASN Aircraft accident McDonnell Douglas DC-10-40 N184AT Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date=August 10, 1986 |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 19, 1982, a [[United States Air Force|USAF]] [[KC-135 Stratotanker|KC-135]] crashed upon approach to O'Hare {{convert|40|mi|km}} northwest of the city (near Woodstock), killing 27 people on board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19820319-0 |title=ASN Aircraft accident Boeing KC-135A-BN Stratotanker 58-0031 Greenwood, IL |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On May 25, 1979, [[American Airlines Flight 191]] crashed just after takeoff on runway 32R from Chicago en route to [[Los Angeles International Airport]] in [[Los Angeles|Los Angeles, California]], killing all 271 people on board and two people on the ground. The crash remains the deadliest single-aircraft crash in United States history, and the worst aviation disaster in the nation before [[September 11 attacks|September 11, 2001]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19790525-2 |title=ASN Aircraft accident McDonnell Douglas DC-10-10 N110AA Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 28, 1977, [[Douglas C-47]]A N57131 of [[Emery Worldwide]] was destroyed by fire following a taxiing accident. The aircraft was due to operate a cargo flight.&lt;ref name=ASN280377&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19770328-0 |title=N57131 Accident description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |accessdate=August 4, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 20, 1972, [[North Central Airlines Flight 575]] crashed upon takeoff, killing 10 passengers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19721220-1 |title=ASN Aircraft accident McDonnell Douglas DC-9-31 N954N Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date=December 20, 1972 |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On December 27, 1968, [[North Central Airlines Flight 458]] crashed into a hangar at O'Hare, killing 27 onboard and one on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19681227-0 |title=ASN Aircraft accident Convair CV-580 N2045 Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD) |publisher=Aviation-safety.net |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* On March 21, 1968 [[United Airlines Flight 9963]] a [[Boeing 727]] overran runway 09R on take off. None of the 3 crew on board were killed but injured and the aircraft was damaged beyond repair.&lt;ref&gt;http://aviation-safety.net/go.php?http://libraryonline.erau.edu/online-full-text/ntsb/aircraft-accident-reports/AAR69-01.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* On August 16, 1965, [[United Airlines Flight 389]] crashed {{convert|30|mi|km}} east of O'Hare while on approach, killing all 30 onboard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19650816-0 ASN Aircraft accident Boeing 727–22 N7036U Lake Michigan, MI&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* On September 17, 1961, [[Northwest Orient Airlines Flight 706]] had a mechanical failure in control surfaces and crashed upon takeoff at Chicago O'Hare killing all 37 onboard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19610917-3 ASN Aircraft accident Lockheed L-188C Electra N137US Chicago-O'Hare International Airport, IL (ORD)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Terminals ==
[[Image:O'Hare Terminal 1.jpg|thumb|right|United Airlines Terminal 1, Concourse B]]
[[Image:O-Hare-Terminal3.jpg|thumb|right|American Airlines Terminal 3 Main Hall]]
[[Image:Ohareterminal5.jpg|thumb|right|Terminal 5 – International]]

O'Hare has four numbered passenger terminals with nine lettered concourses and a total of 182 aircraft gates. Two or more additional terminal buildings are envisioned; there is the possibility of a large terminal complex for the west side of the field, with access from I-90 and/or the [[Elgin-O'Hare Expressway]], if the runway reconfiguration is completed and passenger numbers require additional terminals.

'''Note:''' All international arrivals at O'Hare (except flights from destinations with [[United States border preclearance|border preclearance]]) are handled at Terminal 5.
[[File:Planes in Chicago - 22.JPG|300px|thumb|Aircraft taxiing in Chicago]]

===Terminal 1===
Terminal 1 houses the hub of [[United Airlines]] and departures for some of its [[Star Alliance]] partners. It has 53 gates on two concourses:
*'''Concourse B''' - 23 gates
*'''Concourse C''' - 30 gates

Concourses B and C are linear concourses located in separate buildings parallel to each other. Concourse B is adjacent to the airport roadway and houses passenger check-in, baggage claim and security screening on its landside and aircraft gates on its airside. Concourse C is a satellite concourse with gates on all sides. Passengers transit between the two concourses via a pedestrian tunnel under the tarmac and are treated to a neon light show and music while riding on moving walkways.

United Airlines runs a post-security shuttle service between Concourse C (Gate C-9) and Concourses E &amp; F (Gate E-2A) in Terminal 2. United operates three United Clubs in Terminal 1 (two in Concourse B, one in Concourse C) as well as a United First International Lounge and United Arrivals Suite in Concourse C.

Terminal 1 houses [[All Nippon Airways]]'s Chicago office.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ana.co.jp/wws/japan/e/asw_common/contact/america.html ANA City offices America].&quot; ''[[All Nippon Airways]]''. Retrieved on August 13, 2011. &quot;Chicago O'hare International Airport Terminal 1, Chicago, IL, 60666-0467&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Terminal 2===
Terminal 2 houses [[US Airways]] and [[Delta Air Lines]]. [[United Express]] also operates a number of flights from Terminal 2, but check-in for these flights is conducted in Terminal 1. Terminal 2 has 38 gates on two concourses:
:*'''Concourse E''' - 16 gates
:*'''Concourse F''' - 22 gates

United Airlines runs a United Club in Concourse F near gate F4A, while Delta has a SkyClub on Concourse E.

===Terminal 3===
Terminal 3 houses the [[American Airlines]] hub, as well as departing flights for certain [[oneworld]] alliance carriers and unaffiliated domestic low-cost carriers. Terminal 3 has 80 gates on four concourses:
*'''Concourse G''' - 26 gates
*'''Concourse H''' - 21 gates
*'''Concourse K''' - 22 gates
*'''Concourse L''' - 11 gates

Concourse G primarily houses American Eagle operations, while concourses H and K house American mainline operations, and concourse L, the previous home of Delta, now primarily houses low-cost carrier operations. Terminal 3 has two American Airlines Admirals Clubs and a Flagship Lounge.

===Terminal 5 (International Terminal)===
All international arrivals at O'Hare (excluding flights from destinations with [[United States border preclearance|U.S. border preclearance]]) are processed at Terminal 5, which also handles most non-US carriers and certain domestic low-cost carriers. Terminal 5 has 21 gates on one concourse ('''Concourse M''').

Terminal 5 houses a number of airline lounges including the Aer Lingus Gold Circle Club, Air France Lounge, Alitalia Sala Freccia Alata, British Airways Lounge, Korean Air Lounge, SAS Business Lounge and Swiss Lounge.

==Airlines and destinations==
{{Airport-dest-list
| 3rdcoltitle = Terminal/&lt;br&gt;Concourse
| [[Aer Lingus]] | Dublin | 5M
| [[Aeroméxico]] | Guadalajara, Mexico City | 5M
| [[Aeroméxico Connect]] | Durango, Leon/El Bajio, Monterrey &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal:''' Zacatecas | 5M
| [[Air Canada]] | Montréal-Trudeau, Toronto-Pearson | 2E
| [[Air Canada Express]] operated by [[Jazz Air]] | Montréal-Trudeau, Toronto-Pearson | 2E
| [[Air Choice One]] | Burlington (IA), Decatur | 3L
| [[Air France]] | '''Seasonal''': Paris-Charles de Gaulle&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2011-07-12/travel/chi-air-france-alitalia-to-suspend-service-out-of-ohare-20110712_1_air-france-klm-alitalia-klm-and-northwest-airlines Air France, Alitalia to suspend service out of O'Hare]&lt;/ref&gt; | 5M
| [[Air India]] | Delhi, Hyderabad | 5M
| [[Alaska Airlines]] | Anchorage, Portland (OR), Seattle/Tacoma | 3L
| [[Alitalia]] | '''Seasonal''': Rome-Fiumicino&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2011-07-12/travel/chi-air-france-alitalia-to-suspend-service-out-of-ohare-20110712_1_air-france-klm-alitalia-klm-and-northwest-airlines Air France, Alitalia to suspend service out of O'Hare]&lt;/ref&gt; | 5M
| [[All Nippon Airways]] | Tokyo-Narita | 1C
| [[American Airlines]] | Austin, Beijing-Capital, Boston, Dallas/Fort Worth, Delhi, Denver, Fort Lauderdale, Fort Myers, Kansas City, Las Vegas, London-Heathrow, Los Angeles, Manchester (UK), Mexico City, Miami, Minneapolis/St. Paul, New Orleans, New York-JFK, New York-LaGuardia, Orange County, Orlando, Paris-Charles de Gaulle , Philadelphia, Phoenix, Raleigh/Durham, Reno/Tahoe, St. Louis, San Antonio, San Diego, San Francisco, San Jose (CA), San Juan, Seattle/Tacoma, Shanghai-Pudong, Tampa, Tokyo-Narita, Tucson, Tulsa, Washington-National, West Palm Beach &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Anchorage, Calgary, Cancún, Cozumel, Dublin, Eagle/Vail, El Paso, Hayden/Steamboat Springs, Helsinki, Honolulu, Jackson Hole, Montego Bay, Newark, Palm Springs, Puerto Vallarta, San José del Cabo, Toronto-Pearson | 3H, 3K, 3L
| [[AmericanConnection]] operated by [[Chautauqua Airlines]] | Bloomington/Normal, Cedar Rapids/Iowa City, Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Dubuque, Flint, Fort Wayne, Grand Rapids, Indianapolis, Kalamazoo, La Crosse, Louisville, Madison, Milwaukee, Moline/Quad Cities, Oklahoma City, Peoria, Rochester (MN), Toledo, Wausau/Stevens Point, White Plains | 3L
| [[American Eagle Airlines|American Eagle]] | Albuquerque, Atlanta, Baltimore, Blountville/Tri-Cities, Buffalo, Calgary, Champaign/Urbana, Charlotte, Charlottesville, Chattanooga, Cleveland, Columbus (OH), Dayton, Denver, Des Moines, Detroit, Dubuque, Evansville, Fargo, Fayetteville (AR), Grand Rapids, Green Bay, Harrisburg, Hartford, Houston-Intercontinental, Huntsville, Indianapolis, Jacksonville, Kalamazoo, Kansas City, Knoxville, La Crosse, Lexington, Little Rock, Madison, Manhattan (KS), Marquette, Memphis, Milwaukee, Minneapolis/St. Paul, Montréal-Trudeau, Nashville, New Orleans, Newark, Oklahoma City, Omaha, Ottawa, Pensacola, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Raleigh/Durham, Rapid City, Richmond, Rochester (MN), Rochester (NY), Salt Lake City, San Antonio, Sioux Falls, Springfield (MO), Syracuse, Toledo, Toronto-Pearson, Traverse City, Tulsa, Washington-National, Watertown (NY), Wichita, Wilmington (NC)  &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': El Paso | 3G, 3H
| [[Asiana Airlines]] | Seoul-Incheon | 5M
| [[British Airways]] | London-Heathrow | 5M
| [[Cayman Airways]] | '''Seasonal''': Grand Cayman | 5M
| [[Cathay Pacific]] | Hong Kong | 5M
| [[Copa Airlines]] | Panama City [begins December 15]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.copaair.com/sites/us/en/noticias/Pages/nuevo-destino-chicago.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; | 5M
| [[Delta Air Lines]] | Atlanta, Detroit, Minneapolis/St. Paul &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Salt Lake City | 2E
| Delta Air Lines | '''Seasonal''': Paris-Charles de Gaulle | 5M^
| [[Delta Connection]] operated by [[Atlantic Southeast Airlines]] | Atlanta, Detroit, Memphis, Minneapolis/St. Paul | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[Comair]] | Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Memphis, Minneapolis/St. Paul, New York-JFK | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[Compass Airlines (North America)|Compass Airlines]] | Minneapolis/St. Paul | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[Mesaba Airlines]] | Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Detroit, Memphis, New York-JFK | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[Pinnacle Airlines]] | Atlanta | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[Shuttle America]] | Detroit, Memphis, Minneapolis/St. Paul, New York-LaGuardia | 2E
| Delta Connection operated by [[SkyWest Airlines]] | Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Salt Lake City | 2E
| [[Etihad Airways]]| Abu Dhabi | 5M
| [[Iberia Airlines|Iberia]] | Madrid | 3K
| [[Iceland Express]] | '''Seasonal''': Reykjavik-Keflavik&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohare.com/PDF/News/061411_Iceland%20Express%20Service%20to%20ORD_FINAL.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; | 5M
| [[Japan Airlines]] | Tokyo-Narita | 3K
| [[JetBlue Airways]] | Boston, Long Beach, New York-JFK | 3L
| [[KLM]] | Amsterdam | 5M
| [[Korean Air]] | Seoul-Incheon | 5M
| [[LOT Polish Airlines]] | Warsaw | 5M
| [[Lufthansa]] | Düsseldorf, Frankfurt, Munich | 1B
| [[Pakistan International Airlines]] | Barcelona, Islamabad, Karachi, Lahore | 5M
| [[Royal Jordanian]] | Amman-Queen Alia&lt;!-- RJ has no traffic rights between ORD and DTW. Do not add Detroit as a destination. --&gt; | 5M
| [[Scandinavian Airlines]] | Copenhagen, Stockholm-Arlanda | 5M
| [[Spirit Airlines]] | Boston, Dallas/Fort Worth, Detroit, Fort Lauderdale, Fort Myers, Las Vegas, Los Angeles, New York-LaGuardia, Orlando  &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Atlantic City, Myrtle Beach | 3L
| [[Swiss International Air Lines]] | Zürich | 5M
| [[TACA Airlines]] | Guatemala City, San Salvador | 5M
| [[Turkish Airlines]] | Istanbul-Atatürk | 5M
| [[United Airlines]] | Albany, Amsterdam, Atlanta, Baltimore, Beijing-Capital, Boise, Boston, Brussels, Buffalo, Calgary, Cancún, Charlotte, Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Cleveland, Columbus (OH), Dallas/Fort Worth, Denver, Des Moines, Detroit, Fort Lauderdale, Frankfurt, Grand Rapids, Guam, Harrisburg, Hartford/Springfield, Hong Kong, Honolulu, Houston-Intercontinental, Jacksonville, Kansas City, Kona, Las Vegas, London-Heathrow, Los Angeles, Mexico City, Minneapolis/St. Paul, Munich, New Orleans, New York-LaGuardia, Newark, Omaha, Orange County, Orlando, Paris-Charles de Gaulle, Philadelphia, Phoenix, Pittsburgh, Portland (OR), Providence, Puerto Vallarta, Raleigh/Durham, Richmond, Rochester (NY), Sacramento, San Diego, San Francisco, San Juan, São Paulo-Guarulhos, Seattle/Tacoma, Shanghai-Pudong, St. Thomas, Tampa, Tokyo-Narita, Toronto-Pearson, Vancouver, Washington-Dulles, Washington-National &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Anchorage, Aruba, Bozeman, Cozumel, Jackson Hole, Kahului, Liberia (Costa Rica), Miami, Montego Bay, Palm Springs, Punta Cana, Rapid City, St. Maarten, San José del Cabo, West Palm Beach | 1B, 1C
| [[United Express]] operated by [[Atlantic Southeast Airlines]] | Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Cleveland, Columbia (SC), Columbus (OH), Dayton, Detroit, Greensboro, Greenville/Spartanburg, Huntsville, Jacksonville, Norfolk, Pensacola, Portland (ME), Roanoke, Rochester (NY), Savannah, South Bend, Syracuse| 2E*, 2F*
| United Express operated by [[Chautauqua Airlines]] | Cleveland | 1B
| United Express operated by [[Colgan Air]] | Cleveland | 1B
| United Express operated by [[ExpressJet Airlines]] | Cleveland, Newark | 1B
| United Express operated by [[ExpressJet Airlines]] | Akron/Canton, Albany, Allentown/Bethlehem, Appleton, Atlanta, Baltimore, Birmingham (AL), Bismarck, Buffalo, Burlington (VT), Cedar Rapids/Iowa City, Charlotte, Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Cleveland, Columbia (SC), Dayton, Des Moines, Detroit, Fargo, Fayetteville (AR), Grand Rapids, Green Bay, Greensboro, Greenville/Spartanburg, Harrisburg, Hartford, Huntsville, Indianapolis, Kansas City, Knoxville, Lansing, Lexington, Lincoln, Little Rock, Louisville, Madison, Manchester (NH), Memphis, Montréal-Trudeau, Nashville, Norfolk, Oklahoma City, Ottawa, Pensacola, Peoria, Pittsburgh, Portland (ME), Providence, Raleigh/Durham, Rapid City, Richmond, Roanoke, Rochester (NY), Savannah, Sioux Falls, South Bend, Springfield (MO), Syracuse, Toronto-Pearson, Traverse City, Tulsa, Wausau/Stevens Point, Wichita, Wilkes-Barre/Scranton | 1B, 1C, 2E*, 2F* 
| United Express operated by [[GoJet Airlines]] | Albany, Austin, Baltimore, Boise, Bozeman, Burlington (VT), Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Dayton, Detroit, Grand Rapids, Greensboro,Hartford, Jacksonville, Kansas City,Madison, Manchester (NH), Moline/Quad Cities, Montréal-Trudeau, New Orleans, Norfolk, Oklahoma City, Omaha, Philadelphia, Portland (ME), Providence, Richmond, Rochester (NY), St. Louis, San Antonio, Syracuse, Toronto-Pearson, Tulsa | 1B, 1C, 2F
| United Express operated by [[Mesa Airlines]] | Austin, Buffalo, Burlington (VT), Charleston (SC), Charlotte, Dallas/Fort Worth, Dayton, Des Moines, Detroit, Harrisburg, Hartford, Houston-Intercontinental, Indianapolis, Jacksonville, Kansas City, Madison, Memphis, Miami, Nashville, Norfolk, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, Portland (ME), Raleigh/Durham, Rochester (NY), San Antonio, Savannah, South Bend, Syracuse &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Grand Rapids | 1B, 1C, 2E*, 2F*
| United Express operated by [[Shuttle America]] | Albuquerque, Atlanta, Austin, Boston, Buffalo, Cedar Rapids/Iowa City, Charlotte, Columbus (OH), Dallas/Fort Worth, Des Moines, Detroit, Edmonton, Fort Myers, Grand Rapids, Halifax, Hartford, Houston-Intercontinental, Indianapolis, Jacksonville, Kansas City, Louisville, Miami, Minneapolis/St. Paul, Moline/Quad Cities, Montréal-Trudeau, New Orleans, New York-LaGuardia, Newark, Norfolk, Omaha, Ottawa, Pittsburgh, Quebec City, Raleigh/Durham, Rochester (NY), St. Louis, Salt Lake City, San Antonio, South Bend, Toronto-Pearson, Washington-National, White Plains &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Myrtle Beach, Spokane, | 1B, 1C
| United Express operated by [[SkyWest Airlines]] | Albuquerque, Allentown/Bethlehem, Asheville, Atlanta, Austin, Birmingham (AL), Boise, Calgary, Cedar Rapids/Iowa City, Charleston (WV), Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Cleveland, Colorado Springs, Dallas/Fort Worth, Dayton, Des Moines, Detroit, Duluth, Eau Claire, Edmonton, Fargo, Fort Wayne, Grand Rapids, Green Bay, Hancock/Houghton, Indianapolis, Kansas City, Knoxville, Lincoln, London (ON), Louisville, Madison, Memphis, Milwaukee, Moline/Quad Cities, Muskegon, Nashville, New Orleans, Norfolk, Oklahoma City, Omaha, Ottawa, Paducah, Peoria, Pittsburgh, Quebec City, Regina, St. Louis, Saginaw, Salt Lake City, San Antonio, Saskatoon, Sioux Falls, South Bend, Spokane, Springfield (IL), Syracuse, Traverse City, Tulsa, White Plains, Wichita, Winnipeg &lt;br&gt; '''Seasonal''': Aspen, Billings, Hayden/Steamboat Springs, Kalispell, Missoula, Rapid City| 1B, 1C, 2E*, 2F*
| United Express operated by [[Trans States Airlines]] | Cedar Rapids/Iowa City, Charleston (SC), Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky, Dayton, Greensboro, Harrisburg, Huntsville, Knoxville, Manchester (NH), Nashville, Norfolk, Oklahoma City, Richmond, Roanoke, Rochester (NY), St. Louis, Syracuse| 1B, 1C
| [[US Airways]] | Charlotte, Philadelphia, Phoenix | 2E, 2F 
| [[US Airways Express]] operated by [[Republic Airlines]] | Charlotte | 2E, 2F
| [[USA3000 Airlines]]  | Cancun, Ft. Myers, Huatulco, Liberia (Costa Rica), Montego Bay, Puerto Vallarta, Punta Cana, San José del Cabo [all service ends January 2, 2012]| 5M
| [[Virgin America]] | Los Angeles, San Francisco | 3L
| [[Virgin Atlantic Airways]] | '''Seasonal''': London-Heathrow | 5M
}}
*- Although Concourses E and F are part of Terminal 2, check-in and baggage claim for all United flights are in Terminal 1.
^- Delta check in for the flight to Paris-CDG is in Terminal 2 but the flight will depart from the International Terminal 5.

===Traffic and statistics===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%&quot;
|+ '''Busiest International Routes from O'Hare (2009–2010)'''&lt;ref name=&quot;internationalreport&quot;&gt;
  {{cite web
  | title = U.S. International Air Passenger and Freight Statistics Report
  | publisher = Office of Aviation Analysis, [[U.S. Department of Transportation]]
  | year = 2010
  | url = http://ostpxweb.dot.gov/aviation/usstatreport.htm
  | accessdate = 7 May 2011
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Rank
! Airport
! Passengers
! Carriers
|-
| 1
| [[Image:Flag of the United Kingdom.svg|20px]] [[London Heathrow Airport|London (Heathrow), United Kingdom]]
| 1,108,513
| American, British Airways, United, Virgin Atlantic
|-
| 2
| [[Image:Flag of Germany.svg|20px]] [[Frankfurt Airport|Frankfurt, Germany]]
| 919,448
| Lufthansa, United
|-
| 3
| [[Image:Flag of Canada.svg|20px]] [[Toronto Pearson International Airport|Toronto (Pearson), Canada]]
| 747,713
| Air Canada, American, United
|-
| 4
| [[Image:Flag of Japan.svg|20px]] [[Narita International Airport|Tokyo (Narita), Japan]]
| 651,643
| All Nippon, American, JAL, United
|-
| 5
| [[Image:Flag of Mexico.svg|20px]] [[Cancún International Airport|Cancún, Mexico]]
| 400,424
| American, United, USA3000
|-
| 6
| [[Image:Flag of France.svg|20px]] [[Charles de Gaulle Airport|Paris (Charles de Gaulle), France]]
| 346,940
| Air France, American, United, Delta
|-
| 7
| [[Image:Flag of Canada.svg|20px]] [[Montréal-Pierre Elliott Trudeau International Airport|Montréal (Trudeau), Canada]]
| 345,384
| Air Canada, American, United
|-
| 8
| [[Image:Flag of Germany.svg|20px]] [[Munich Airport|Munich, Germany]]
| 318,762
| Lufthansa, United
|-
| 9
| [[Image:Flag of Mexico.svg|20px]] [[Mexico City International Airport|Mexico City, Mexico]]
| 318,063
| Aeroméxico, American, United
|-
| 10
| [[Image:Flag of China.svg|20px]] [[Shanghai Pudong International Airport|Shanghai (Pudong), China]]
| 299,351
| American, United
|}

{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%&quot;
|+ '''Top 10 domestic destinations (September 2010 - August 2011)'''&lt;ref&gt;
  {{cite web
  | url = http://www.transtats.bts.gov/airports.asp?pn=1&amp;Airport=ORD&amp;End_YearMonth=24139
  | title = Chicago, IL: O'Hare (ORD)
  | publisher = [[Bureau of Transportation Statistics]]
  | date = July 2011 | accessdate = September 17, 2011
  }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! Rank
! Airport
! Passengers
! Carriers
|-
| 1
| {{flagicon|New York}} [[LaGuardia Airport|New York (LaGuardia), New York]]
| 1,261,000
| American, Delta, United
|-
| 2
| {{flagicon|California}} [[Los Angeles International Airport|Los Angeles, California]]
| 1,075,000
| American, Spirit, United, Virgin America
|-
| 3
| {{flagicon|California}} [[San Francisco International Airport|San Francisco, California]]
| 950,000
| American,United, Virgin America
|-
| 4
| {{flagicon|Texas}} [[Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport|Dallas/Fort Worth, Texas]]
| 884,000
| American, Spirit, United
|-
| 5
| {{flagicon|Massachusetts}} [[Logan International Airport|Boston, Massachusetts]]
| 786,000
| American, JetBlue, Spirit, United
|-
| 6
| {{flagicon|Minnesota}} [[Minneapolis-Saint Paul International Airport|Minneapolis/St. Paul, Minnesota]]
| 727,000
| American, Delta, United
|-
| 7
| {{flagicon|Virginia}} [[Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport|Washington (National), D.C.]]
| 701,000
| American, United 
|-
| 8
| {{flagicon|Colorado}} [[Denver International Airport|Denver, Colorado]]
| 698,000
| American, United
|-
| 9
| {{flagicon|Pennsylvania}} [[Philadelphia International Airport|Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]
| 665,000
| American, United, US Airways
|-
| 10
| {{flagicon|Georgia (U.S. state)}} [[Hartsfield–Jackson Atlanta International Airport|Atlanta, Georgia]]
| 664,000
| American, Delta, United 
|}

===Cargo carriers===
There are two main cargo areas at O'Hare that have warehouse, build-up/tear-down and aircraft parking facilities. The Southwest Cargo Area, adjacent to Irving Park Road, accommodates over 80% of the airport's all-cargo flights, divided among 9 buildings in two tiers. The North Cargo Area, which is a modest conversion of the former military base (the 1943 Douglas plant area), also receives air freighters. It is adjacent to the northern portion of [[Bessie Coleman]] Drive.

Two satellite cargo areas have warehouse and build-up/tear down facilities, but aircraft do not park at these. Freight is trucked to/from aircraft on other ramps. The South Cargo Area is along Mannheim Road. The East Cargo Area, adjacent to Terminal 5, was formerly the airport's only cargo section but has now mostly evolved into an airport support zone.

The Southwest Cargo Area partially lies in the path of one of the new runways (10C/28C). The redevelopment of the airfield will entail moving/replacing this primary cargo hub.

{{Airport-dest-list
| [[ABX Air]] | Cincinnati/Northern Kentucky  
| [[Aerologic]] | Atlanta, Leipzig/Halle
| [[AeroUnion]] | Mexico City
| [[AirBridgeCargo Airlines]] | Amsterdam, Moscow-Domodedovo&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ohare.com/PDF/News/1105416952244%5B1%5D.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Air China Cargo]] | Anchorage, Beijing-Capital
| [[Air France Cargo]] | Dublin, Glasgow-Prestwick, Paris-Charles de Gaulle
| [[Asiana Airlines]] | Seoul-Incheon
| [[Atlas Air]] | Anchorage
| [[British Airways World Cargo]] operated by &lt;BR&gt;[[Global Supply Systems]] | Houston-Intercontinental, London-Stansted, Washington-Dulles
| [[CargoItalia]] | Milan-Malpensa
| [[Cargolux]] | Anchorage, Atlanta, Hong Kong, Indianapolis, Luxembourg, New York-JFK
| [[Cathay Pacific Cargo]] | Amsterdam, Anchorage, Dallas/Fort Worth, Hong Kong, Houston-Intercontinental, San Francisco
| [[China Airlines]] | Anchorage, Taipei-Taoyuan
| [[China Cargo Airlines]] | Shanghai-Pudong
| [[China Southern Airlines]] | Shanghai-Pudong
| [[DHL]] | 
| [[EVA Air]] | Anchorage, Taipei-Taoyuan
| [[Evergreen International Airlines]]|
| [[FedEx Express]] | Indianapolis, Memphis, Newark
| [[Great Wall Airlines]] | Anchorage, Shanghai-Pudong
| [[Jade Cargo International]] | Amsterdam, Chengdu, Dubai, Seoul-Incheon, Shanghai-Pudong
| [[Kalitta Air]]|Newark, New York-JFK
| [[Korean Air|Korean Air Cargo]] | Seoul-Incheon
| [[Lufthansa Cargo]] | Anchorage, Frankfurt
| Lufthansa Cargo operated by &lt;BR&gt;[[World Airways|World Air Cargo]] | Frankfurt
| [[Nippon Cargo Airlines]] | Tokyo-Narita, Anchorage
| [[Polar Air Cargo]] | Anchorage, Tokyo-Narita
| [[Qantas Freight]] operated by &lt;BR&gt;[[Atlas Air]] | Melbourne&lt;ref&gt;http://www.qantas.com.au/freight/pdf/QFFreighterscheduleJune2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Qatar Airways Cargo]] | Amsterdam, Doha&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ameinfo.com/239240.html |title=Qatar Airways to begin Chicago freighter service &amp;#124; Qatar Airways |publisher=AMEinfo.com |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| [[Shanghai Airlines Cargo]] | Anchorage, Shanghai-Pudong
| [[Singapore Airlines Cargo]] | Anchorage, Singapore, Xiamen
| [[Southern Air]] | Anchorage, Seoul-Incheon
| [[UPS Airlines]] | Cologne/Bonn, Columbus-Rickenbacker, Louisville, Philadelphia
| [[World Airways|World Airways Cargo]] | Baltimore, Hong Kong, Milan
| [[Yangtze River Express]] | Anchorage, Shanghai-Pudong
}}

==Facilities==
===Runways===
[[Image:ORD airport map.PNG|thumb|250px|[[Runway]] layout at ORD]]
With the opening of new runway 9L/27R in November 2008, there are now seven primary air carrier runways, arranged tangentially in three parallel sets. The largest is Runway 10–28, 13,001′ x 150′. Runways 9L, 10, 14L, 14R, 27L, 27R and 28 have Category III [[instrument landing system]]s (ILS),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://flightaware.com/resources/airport/KORD/APD/AIRPORT+DIAGRAM |title=Kord Airport Diagram (Apd) |publisher=FlightAware |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  allowing trained aircrews to conduct landings with as little as {{convert|600|ft|m}} of horizontal visibility. All other runway approaches except 4L have full Category I ILS. Due to its location and prevailing winds, runway 4L is seldom used for landings. Therefore, it is equipped with a localizer, the horizontal guidance component of an ILS system, but does not have a glideslope, the vertical component.

Originally, all runways at O'Hare intersected each other with the exception of 4R/22L. This creates problems in times of inclement weather, congestion at the airport, or high winds. There have been several aircraft near-collisions at O'Hare in recent years. The ongoing redevelopment, which essentially eliminates active runway intersections, is intended to alleviate collision hazards and delays at O'Hare.

Three of the original 1943 airfield's four runways (14L/32R, 9R/27L, and 4L/22R) have been upgraded to modern standards. Runway 14R/32L was added in 1955, 9R/27L (now designated 10/28) in 1968, 4R/22L in 1971 and the new 9L/27R in 2008. In 2003, the fourth original runway (18/36) was permanently closed; its short length, lack of use, and problematic placement no longer justified continued certification. Runway 18/36 is now shown as taxiway WT on current airport charts.

The ongoing redevelopment, when completed, will remove the two northwest–southeast runways (14/32 L/R), construct four additional east–west runways (10C/28C, 10R/28L, 9L/27R, and 9C/27C), and extend the 2 existing east–west runways (9R/27L and 10L/28R, shown on current charts as 10/28). The two existing northeast–southwest (4/22 L/R) runways will be retained. Currently, one of the four new runways has been constructed (9L/27R), and one of the two extensions (10/28) has been completed. The second new runway (10C/28C) is currently under construction.

In the original airfield configuration, runway 32L was often used for departures in a shortened configuration. Planes accessed the runway from its intersection at taxiway T10 (common) or taxiway M (not common). This shortened the effective length of the runway but allowed operations on runway 10/28 to continue without restriction. The full length of the runway was available upon request, though with the extension of 10/28 it was usually not needed. As part of the ongoing reconfiguration, in May 2010 runway 14R/32L was permanently shortened to {{convert|9685|ft|m|adj=on}}, and it now starts at taxiway M.

O'Hare has a voluntary nighttime (2200–0700) noise abatement program in place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohare.com/cnrc/ohare/o_noise_flyquiet.shtm |title=O'Hare Fly Quiet Program |publisher=Ohare.com |date=June 17, 1997 |accessdate=March 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The runway reconfiguration program at O'Hare will also improve the airport for the A380 Super-Jumbo aircraft. As part of the runway reconfiguration program, on July 5, 2007, the runway previously designated 9R-27L became runway 10–28, and on August 30, 2007, runway 9L/27R became 9R/27L.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flychicago.com/ohare/runways/plans.pdf|title=Runway 9–27 Reconfiguration Plan|format=PDF|accessdate=June 22, 2009}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 25, 2008, a {{convert|2857|ft|m|adj=on}} extension to 10/28 was opened.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.suntimes.com/news/politics/1185639,runway092508.article|title=O'Hare runway opens in grand style}} {{Dead link|date=May 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Access to airport===
[[Image:CTA blue line O'Hare.jpg|thumb|right|CTA [[Blue Line (Chicago Transit Authority)|Blue Line]] station at O'Hare International Airport]]
* Road vehicles enter and exit via [[Interstate 190 (Illinois)|I-190]], which branches off [[Interstate 90 in Illinois|I-90]] [[Kennedy Expressway|(the Kennedy Expressway)]] leading to downtown Chicago. Cars may also access the airport locally from [[Mannheim Road]], the airport's eastern boundary. Aside from cargo access on its south side, all airport traffic travels through the east side of the airport. Local residents sometimes refer to I-190 as &quot;the world's busiest [[Cul-de-sac]]&quot; as a result of the one way access.
* Subway trains from the [[Blue Line (Chicago Transit Authority)|Blue Line]] of the Chicago Transit Authority's [[Chicago 'L'|'L']] depart the terminal from [[O'Hare (CTA)|an underground station]] that opened on September 3, [[1984 in rail transport|1984]].
* Commuter trains from the [[Metra]] [[North Central Service]] stop at the [[O'Hare Transfer (Metra)|O'Hare Transfer station]], which is connected to the [[Airport Transit System]] via a shuttle bus.
* Taxi and Limo Services can also get you to/from Chicago O'Hare Airport.  American Coach Limousine [http://www.americancoachlimousine.com Chicago Limo Service]

===Intra-airport transportation===
{{Main|Airport Transit System}}
[[Image:O'Hareatstower.JPG|thumb|upright|Airport Transit System with Hilton Hotel in Background]]
Access within the airport complex can be accomplished using O'Hare's Airport Transit System (ATS), a {{convert|2.5|mi|0|abbr=on}} long automated [[people mover]] system that operates 24 hours a day, connecting all four terminals and the remote parking lots. The system began operation on May 6, 1993,&lt;ref name=&quot;May 6, 1993&quot;&gt;{{cite news
  | last =Fornek
  | first =Scott
  | title =Moving Experience Ready at O'Hare
  | work =Chicago Sun-Times
  | page =4
  | date =May 6, 1993
  | accessdate =January 16, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and will be soon undergoing a [[United States dollar|US $]]90 million enhancement to add 24 new cars and to extend the line to a new remote parking garage.

===Other facilities===
A large air cargo complex on the southwest side of the field was opened in 1984, replacing most of the old cargo area, which stood where Terminal 5 now exists. This complex sits right in the middle of the footprint for new runway 10C/28C, and is to be replaced by a new facility.

The hangar area has multiple buildings capable of fully enclosing aircraft up to the size of the [[Boeing 747]].

The new North Terminal Air Traffic Control Tower was designed by [[AECOM]] (design principal Jose Luis Palacios).

== Statistics ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right; width:400px;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|+ Traffic by calendar year
|-
! style=&quot;width:75px&quot;|  !! style=&quot;width:100px&quot;| Passenger volume !! style=&quot;width:75px&quot;| Change over previous year !! style=&quot;width:125px&quot;| Aircraft operations !! style=&quot;width:100px&quot;| Cargo tonnage
|-
!2000
|72,144,244 || {{decrease}}{{0}}0.64% || 908,989 || 1,640,524.1
|-
!2001
|67,448,064 || {{decrease}}{{0}}6.51% || 911,917 || 1,413,834.4
|-
!2002
|66,565,952 || {{decrease}}{{0}}1.31% || 922,817 || 1,436,385.7
|-
!2003
|69,508,672 || {{increase}}{{0}}4.40% || 928,691 || 1,601,735.5
|-
!2004
|75,533,822 || {{increase}}{{0}}8.67% || 992,427 || 1,685,808.0
|-
!2005
|76,581,146 || {{increase}}{{0}}1.38% || 972,248 || 1,701,446.1
|-
!2006
|76,282,212 || {{decrease}}{{0}}0.30% || 958,643 || 1,718,011.0
|-
!2007
|76,182,025 || {{decrease}}{{0}}0.15% || 926,973 || 1,690,741.6
|-
!2008
|70,819,015 || {{decrease}}{{0}}7.03% || 881,566 || 1,480,847.4
|-
!2009
|64,397,782 || {{decrease}}{{0}}9.07%|| 827,899 || 1,198,426.3
|-
!2010
|67,026,191 || {{increase}}{{0}}3.83% || 950,119 || 1,577,047.8
|-
| colspan=5 align=&quot;right&quot;| ''Source: O'Hare International Airport''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.flychicago.com/BusinessInformation/Statistics/Default.aspx
|title=Statistics
|publisher=Chicago Department of Aviation
|accessdate=March 23, 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

== Modernization plan ==
O'Hare's high volume and crowded schedule can lead to long delays and cancellations that, due to the airport being a major hub, can affect air travel across North America. Official reports rank O'Hare as one of the least punctual airports in the United States based on percentage of delayed flights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.transtats.bts.gov/airports.asp?pn=1&amp;Airport=ORD&amp;Airport_Name=Chicago,%20IL:%20O%20Hare&amp;carrier=FACTS |title=RITA &amp;#124; BTS &amp;#124; Transtats |publisher=Transtats.bts.gov |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, United Airlines and American Airlines agreed to modify their schedules to help reduce congestion caused by clustered arrivals and departures. Because of the air traffic departing, arriving, and near the airport, air traffic controllers at O'Hare and its nearby facilities are among the leaders in the world in terms of number of controlled flights per hour.

City management has committed to a $6 billion capital investment plan to increase the airport's capacity by 60% and decrease delays by an estimated 79 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flychicago.com/ohare/runways/ |title=The Chicago Airport System |publisher=Flychicago.com |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This plan was approved by the [[Federal Aviation Administration|FAA]] in October 2005 and will involve a reconfiguration of the airfield and addition of terminal space. The plan includes the addition of four runways, the lengthening of two existing runways, and the decommissioning of two existing runways in order to give the airfield six parallel runways in a configuration similar to that in [[Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport|Dallas]] and other large modern hub airports. This plan was very controversial as the added improvements, at the time they were proposed, were expected to increase the airport's air traffic capacity only slightly, given existing FAA rules. Additionally, the southernmost new runway would require the city acquire additional land, which was extremely controversial as residents did not want to move.

The Modernization Plan is now being implemented; an additional runway and Air Traffic Control Tower were commissioned on November 20, 2008. The new north runway, designated 9L/27R, initially served as a foul weather arrival runway, addressing one of O'Hare's primary causes of delay, but now serves as one of three runways that can be used simultaneously for landings. An extension of Runway 10/28 (formerly 9R/27L) to {{convert|13001|ft|m}} was opened in September, 2008, facilitating the shortening and eventual closure of the {{convert|13000|ft|m}} Runway 14R/32L. At the same time, the FAA redesigned departure routes for both O'Hare and Chicago Midway International Airport, increasing the number from three shared by both airports to five from each airport. With the new runway's opening, O'Hare's maximum aircraft arrival capacity increased from 96 planes per hour to 112 planes per hour; [[United Airlines]]'s senior vice president of operations, Joseph Kolshak, told [[The Wall Street Journal]] that within a month of the runway's opening, &quot;they were consistently hitting that.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;All 2009, pages 1&quot;&gt;&quot;How a New Runway at O'Hare Makes Travel Easier for All,&quot; Wall Street Journal, Personal Journal section, July 23, 2009, pages 1 and 3&lt;/ref&gt;

Design efforts are underway for the remainder of the program, which includes three runway projects, a new western terminal complex and an automated people mover system. The O'Hare Modernization Program submitted an application to the Federal Aviation Administration to use approximately $180 million in Passenger Facility Charges to fund design work, which began in early 2009.

The second new 10,800 by 200 foot runway (10C/28C) is currently under construction.

The modernization plan has required the acquisition of {{convert|126|acre}} of land in [[Des Plaines, Illinois|Des Plaines]], [[Illinois]]; construction of runway 27R and the control tower cost $457 million and involved the rerouting of a creek and {{convert|14000000|cuyd}} of fill to build up an embankment..&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;All 2009, pages 1&quot;/&gt; 2,800 residents had to be relocated, as well as a cemetery with 900 known graves. The program ultimately is expected to expand the airport's capacity to over 3,800 operations per day, up from the present capacity of 2,700, and will vastly increase passenger throughput. It will also improve the ability of very large aircraft such as the [[Airbus A380|A380]] to operate.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

Flight caps in place since 2004 expired on October 31, 2008. Ironically, American Airlines eliminated over 60 daily flights at O'Hare because of soaring fuel prices. United announced similar cutbacks. Recent worldwide economic difficulties further complicate the forecasts for airport demand.

After initially opposing the Modernization plan, DuPage County has endorsed the plan citing the creation of jobs, commercial development, and the ability of O'Hare to regain the status as busiest airport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bobschillerstrom.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=78:chairman-economic-boom-will-come-from-elgin-ohare-extension&amp;catid=1:latest&amp;Itemid=155 |title=Economic boom will come from Elgin-O'Hare extension |publisher=Bobschillerstrom.com |date= |accessdate=November 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{legend|#1c12e5|existing runway}}{{legend|#16e80c|new runway}}{{legend|#eda213|removed runway}}
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:O'Hare International Airport (USGS) Phase1-corrected.png|Phase 1 (Complete)
Image:O'Hare International Airport (USGS) Phase2-corrected.png|Phase 2 (Extension complete, runway 14R/32L shortened to 9,685 feet (complete), future runway 10C/28C under construction)
Image:O'Hare International Airport (USGS) Phase3.png|Phase 3 (Beginning stages)
Image:O'Hare International Airport (USGS) Final.png|Final runway configuration
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

=== Resistance and alternatives ===
The neighboring communities of [[Bensenville, Illinois|Bensenville]] and [[Elk Grove Village, Illinois|Elk Grove Village]] have been centers of resistance to the expansion plan due to their proximity to the airport and because some of their residents and businesses will be required to relocate. Bensenville and Elk Grove Village formed the [[Suburban O'Hare Commission]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suburban-ohare.org Bensenville, IL – Official Website – Suburban O&amp;#39Hare Commission]{{dead link|date=November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; to fight the expansion. So far, they have not had much success. The commission did receive a temporary injunction against portions of the city's expansion project; however, it was soon overturned. The Suburban O'Hare Commission has also been instrumental in pushing for a [[Proposed Chicago south suburban airport|third regional airport in south suburban]] [[Peotone, Illinois|Peotone]], which it claims would alleviate congestion at O'Hare. However, no airline has committed to the proposed airport, and planning efforts moved very slowly during 2007–08. In 2008 Elk Grove Village ended resistance. They received assurance that a proposed highway would not be built through their business park. In November 2009, Bensenville officially ended all resistance to the expansion, ceasing all legal challenges against the city of Chicago. They received 15 million dollars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wbbm780.com/Bensenville-ends-opposition-to-O-Hare-expansion/5687989 |title=Bensenville Ends Opposition To O'Hare Expansion – WBBM 780 – Chicago's #1 source for local news, traffic and weather |publisher=WBBM 780 |date= |accessdate=March 11, 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It should also be noted that the city of Chicago is facing an issue with a historical cemetery located in the space of their planned runway expansion. Up until recently, the city was removing graves. This stopped when a state court stepped in on behalf of the buried's kin.

In 1995, the Chicago/Gary Airport Compact was signed by the cities of Chicago and [[Gary, Indiana]], creating a new administration for the [[Gary/Chicago International Airport]] just across the state line. While markedly smaller than the proposed Peotone site, this airport already has more land and a longer main runway than Midway Airport. Gary is also many miles closer than Peotone to downtown Chicago. In addition public transportation is already in place to the Loop via the South Shore Line. Indiana and the FAA have provided significant funding for a Gary runway expansion, currently under construction.

[[Chicago Rockford International Airport]] (RFD) in [[Rockford, Illinois]] has also marketed itself as an alternative for congestion at O'Hare. However, it is at least a 1-1/2 hour trip to Rockford from the Chicago Loop. Currently there is no direct transportation service from downtown Chicago or O'Hare to the Chicago Rockford International Airport, but airline service at the airport continues to grow. [[Larry Morrissey]], the current mayor of Rockford, has pushed for a [[high-speed rail]] connection between the two airports to make the Rockford airport a more convenient alternative to O'Hare.

[[General Mitchell International Airport]] (MKE) in [[Milwaukee]] has consistently attempted to increase its usage by Chicago and Northern Illinois customers. There is a direct [[Amtrak]] rail service connecting Chicago with Mitchell Airport. The trains operate seven round trips each day, taking under 75 minutes from the Chicago loop.

==See also==
{{Portal box|United States Air Force|World War II|Chicago|Aviation}}
* [[Golden Corridor]], for the region of commerce and industry surrounding O'Hare and extending west, along the [[Jane Addams Memorial Tollway]].
* [[Proposed Chicago south suburban airport]]

==References==
{{AFHRA}}
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{commons category|O'Hare International Airport}}
{{div col|2}}
* [http://www.ohare.com/About/OHare/Default.aspx O'Hare International Airport] (official web site)
* [http://www.ohare.com/MasterPlan/ O'Hare airport Modernization plan]
* [http://www.ohare-airport.org Comprehensive information about O'Hare Airport]
* [http://www.OhareModernization.org O'Hare Modernization Program] (official web site)
* [http://egov.cityofchicago.org/webportal/COCWebPortal/COC_ATTACH/41st.pdf 41st ward map] (official city web site)
* [http://nwchicagohistory.org/nwch_ohare.html The Northwest Chicago Historical Society's page on O'Hare]
* [http://www.opennav.com/airport/KORD openNav: ORD / KORD charts]
* {{FAA-diagram|00166}}
* [http://www.airportwifiguide.com/ord-ohare-international-airport/ ORD WiFi Internet Service Guide]
{{US-airport|ORD}}
*[http://www.greenbeanchicago.com/sustainable-airport-design-takes-flight-ohare-modernization-program/ An article] by [[urbanologist]] William Olson discussing the OMP's sustainable design features. Retrieved January 13, 2009
{{div col end}}

{{Chicago}}
{{Major US Airports}}
{{Aviation in Illinois}}
{{Aerospace Defense Command}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:O'hare International Airport}}
[[Category:Airports established in 1943]]
[[Category:Airports in the Chicago metropolitan area]]
[[Category:Airports in Illinois]]
[[Category:Airfields of the United States Army Air Forces Technical Service Command]]
[[Category:Airfields of the United States Army Air Forces in Illinois]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:O'Hare International Airport| ]]

[[ar:مطار أوهير الدولي]]
[[ca:Aeroport Internacional O'Hare]]
[[cs:O'Hare International Airport]]
[[da:Chicago O'Hare International Airport]]
[[de:O’Hare International Airport]]
[[es:Aeropuerto Internacional Chicago-O'Hare]]
[[eo:Flughaveno O'Hare]]
[[eu:O'Hare nazioarteko aireportua]]
[[fa:فرودگاه بین‌المللی اوهیر شیکاگو]]
[[fr:Aéroport international O'Hare de Chicago]]
[[ko:오헤어 국제공항]]
[[id:Bandar Udara Internasional O'Hare]]
[[it:Aeroporto Internazionale O'Hare]]
[[he:נמל התעופה שיקגו או'הייר]]
[[kl:O'Hare International Airport]]
[[hu:O’Hare nemzetközi repülőtér]]
[[ml:ഒ'ഹെയർ അന്താരാഷ്ട്ര വിമാനത്താവളം]]
[[mr:ओ'हेर आंतरराष्ट्रीय विमानतळ]]
[[nl:O'Hare International Airport]]
[[ja:シカゴ・オヘア国際空港]]
[[no:O'Hare internasjonale lufthavn]]
[[oc:Aeropòrt Internacionau de O'Hare]]
[[pl:Port lotniczy Chicago-O'Hare]]
[[pt:Aeroporto Internacional O'Hare]]
[[ro:Aeroportul Internațional Chicago O'Hare]]
[[ru:Международный аэропорт О’Хара]]
[[simple:O'Hare International Airport]]
[[sk:O’Hare International Airport]]
[[fi:O'Haren kansainvälinen lentoasema]]
[[sv:O'Hare International Airport]]
[[th:ท่าอากาศยานนานาชาติโอแฮร์]]
[[uk:Аеропорт О'Хара]]
[[vi:Sân bay Quốc tế O'Hare]]
[[zh:奥黑尔国际机场]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
