<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="24893" ns="0" title="Adobe Photoshop"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Photoshop}}
{{Infobox software
| name = Adobe Photoshop
| logo = [[Image:Adobe Photoshop logo.svg|64px|Adobe Photoshop CS5 Icon]]
| screenshot = [[File:Photoshopcs5.png|300px]]
| caption = Adobe Photoshop CS5 x64 running on [[Windows 7]] x64
| developer = [[Adobe Systems]]
| latest release version = CS5 (12.1, 12.0.4) {{release date|2011|5|3}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adobe - Photoshop for Windows |url=http://www.adobe.com/support/downloads/product.jsp?product=39&amp;platform=Windows|accessdate=2011-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date =
| programming language = [[C++]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adobe Photoshop language |url=http://www.daniweb.com/forums/thread446.html |date=2003-05-06 |accessdate=2010-12-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating system = Windows 3.0+ or Mac OS 6.0.3+
| platform = [[Mac OS X]], [[Microsoft Windows]]
| language = [[#Language availabilities|27 languages]]
| genre = [[Raster graphics editor]]
| license = [http://adobe.com/products/eulas/ Proprietary software]
| website = [http://adobe.com/photoshop adobe.com/photoshop]
}}
'''Adobe Photoshop''' is a [[Graphics software|graphics editing program]] developed and published by [[Adobe Systems Incorporated]].

Adobe's 2003 &quot;[[Adobe Creative Suite|Creative Suite]]&quot; rebranding led to Adobe Photoshop 8's renaming to Adobe Photoshop CS. Thus, Adobe Photoshop CS5 is the [[Adobe Photoshop release history|12th major release]] of Adobe Photoshop. The CS rebranding also resulted in Adobe offering numerous software packages containing multiple Adobe programs for a reduced price. Adobe Photoshop is released in two editions: '''Adobe Photoshop''', and '''Adobe Photoshop Extended''', with the Extended having extra 3D image creation, motion graphics editing, and advanced image analysis features.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshopextended/faq.html|title= FAQ | Adobe Photoshop CS5 Extended |publisher= Adobe Systems Incorporated|accessdate=7 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adobe Photoshop Extended is included in all of Adobe's Creative Suite offerings except Design Standard, which includes the Adobe Photoshop edition. 

Alongside Photoshop and Photoshop Extended, Adobe also publishes [[Adobe Photoshop Elements|Photoshop Elements]] and [[Adobe Photoshop Lightroom|Photoshop Lightroom]], collectively called &quot;The Adobe Photoshop Family&quot;. In 2008, Adobe released [[Adobe Photoshop Express]], a free [[Web application|web-based]] image editing tool to edit photos directly on blogs and social networking sites; in 2011 a version was released for the [[Android (operating system)|Android]] operating system and the [[iOS]] operating system.&lt;ref&gt;[https://market.android.com/details?id=com.adobe.psmobile Adobe Photoshop Express - Android Market]. [https://market.android.com/ Android Market]. Retrieved 2001-10-7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/adobe-photoshop-express/id331975235?mt=8 App Store - Adobe Photoshop Express]. [http://itunes.apple.com/us/browse iTunes]. Retried 2001-10-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

Adobe only supports Windows and Macintosh versions of Photoshop, but using [[Wine_(software)|Wine]] Photoshop CS4 can run on Linux.&lt;ref name=&quot;CS4 Linux&quot;&gt;[http://appdb.winehq.org/objectManager.php?bIsQueue=false&amp;bIsRejected=false&amp;sClass=vendor&amp;iId=12&amp;sAction=view&amp;sTitle=View+Developer supported program list of Wine].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early history==
In 1987, [[Thomas Knoll]], a PhD student at the [[University of Michigan]] began writing a program on his [[Macintosh Plus]] to display [[grayscale]] images on a monochrome display. This program, called Display, caught the attention of his brother [[John Knoll]], an [[Industrial Light &amp; Magic]] employee, who recommended Thomas turn it into a fully-fledged image editing program. Thomas took a six month break from his studies in 1988 to collaborate with his brother on the program, which had been renamed ImagePro.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.photoshopnews.com/feature-stories/photoshop-profile-thomas-john-knoll-10/ |title=Thomas &amp; John Knoll |accessdate=2007-06-15 |author=Schewe, Jeff |year=2000 |work=PhotoshopNews }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later that year, Thomas renamed his program Photoshop and worked out a short-term deal with scanner manufacturer Barneyscan to distribute copies of the program with a [[Image scanner|slide scanner]]; a &quot;total of about 200 copies of Photoshop were shipped&quot; this way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.storyphoto.com/multimedia/multimedia_photoshop.html |title=From Darkroom to Desktop—How Photoshop Came to Light |accessdate=2007-06-15 |author=Story, Derrick |date=2000-02-18 |work=Story Photography }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During this time, John traveled to [[Silicon Valley]] and gave a demonstration of the program to engineers at [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] and Russell Brown, art director at [[Adobe Systems|Adobe]]. Both showings were successful, and Adobe decided to purchase the license to distribute in September 1988.&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;/&gt; While John worked on [[Plug-in (computing)|plug-ins]] in California, Thomas remained in [[Ann Arbor, Michigan|Ann Arbor]] writing program code. ''Photoshop'' 1.0 was released in 1990 for Macintosh exclusively&lt;!--, and could fit on a single 1.44 MB [[floppy disk]]--&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://siliconuser.com/?q=node/10 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20071011051727/http://siliconuser.com/?q=node/10 |archivedate=2007-10-11 |title=How Adobe's Photoshop Was Born |accessdate=2007-06-15 |author=Hormby, John |date=2007-06-05 |work=Story Photography }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Features==
{{See|Comparison of raster graphics editors#Features}}

Photoshop uses color models [[RGB color model|RGB]], [[Lab color model|lab]], [[CMYK color model|CMYK]], [[grayscale]], binary [[bitmap]], and [[duotone]]. Photoshop has the ability to read and write [[raster graphics|raster]] and [[vector graphics|vector]] image formats such as [[Encapsulated PostScript|.EPS]], [[Portable Network Graphics|.PNG]], [[GIF|.GIF]], and [[JPEG|.JPEG]]. Photoshop has ties with other Adobe software for media editing, animation, and authoring.

== File format {{anchor|PSD}}==
The '''.PSD''' (Photoshop Document), Photoshop's native format, stores an image with support for most imaging options available in Photoshop. These include layers with [[image mask|masks]], [[color spaces]], [[ICC profile]]s, transparency, text, [[alpha channels]] and [[spot color]]s, [[clipping path]]s, and [[duotone]] settings. This is in contrast to many other file formats (e.g. .EPS or .GIF) that restrict content to provide streamlined, predictable functionality. PSD format is limited to a maximum height and width of 30,000 pixels. '''.PSB''' (Photoshop Big) format, also known as &quot;large document format&quot; within Photoshop, is the extension of PSD format to images up to 300,000 pixels in width or height. That limit was apparently chosen somewhat arbitrarily by Adobe, not based on computer arithmetic constraints (it is not close to a significant power of two, as is 30,000) but for ease of software testing. PSD and PSB formats are documented.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Adobe Photoshop File Formats Specification|author=Adobe|url=http://www.adobe.com/devnet-apps/photoshop/fileformatashtml/|date=2010-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Photoshop's popularity means that the .PSD format is widely used, and it is supported to some extent by most competing software. The .PSD file format can be exported to and from [[Adobe Illustrator]], [[Adobe Premiere Pro]], and [[Adobe After Effects|After Effects]], to make professional standard DVDs and provide non-linear editing and special effects services, such as backgrounds, textures, and so on, for television, film, and the Web. Photoshop's primary strength is as a [[raster graphic|pixel-based]] image editor, unlike [[vector graphics|vector-based]] image editors. However, Photoshop also enables the creation, incorporation, and manipulation of vector graphics through its Paths, Pen tools, Shape tools, Shape Layers, Type tools, Import command, and Smart object functions. Utilization of these tools and commands provides convenience when it is desirable to combine pixel-based and vector-based images in one Photoshop document because it can eliminate the necessity to visit more than one software program and transfer files between them. However, for the initial creation of very complex vector graphics that contain numerous shapes and numerous colors, it is much easier to use a software that was created primarily for that purpose, such as [[Adobe Illustrator]] or [[CorelDraw]]. If it is then necessary to import the complex vector object into Photoshop, it is possible to import it into Photoshop as a Smart Object. When the Smart Object is double-clicked on Photoshop's layers palette, it is opened in its original software such as [[Adobe Illustrator]] where changes can be made, then after saving it, the Smart Object will be automatically updated in Photoshop.

==Version history==
{{main|Adobe Photoshop release history}}

===CS3===
[[File:Photoshop CS3 Smart Layers.png|frame|right|Smart Objects display filters without altering the original image (here on Mac OS X)]]

New productivity features include a streamlined interface, improved Camera RAW support, better control over print options, enhanced [[PDF]] support, and better management with [[Adobe Bridge]]. Editing tools new to CS3 are the Clone Source palette and nondestructive Smart Filters. Other features such as the brightness and contrast adjustment and Vanishing Point module were enhanced. The Black and White adjustment option improves control over manual grayscale conversions with a dialog box similar to that of Channel Mixer. Compositing is assisted with Photoshop's new Quick Selection and Refine Edge tools and improved [[image stitching]] technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;features&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wwwimages.adobe.com/www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/photoshop/pdfs/photoshop_overview.pdf |title=Adobe Photoshop CS3 Product overview |accessdate=2007-06-17 |year=2007 |work=Adobe official site |format=PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

CS3 Extended contains all features of CS3 plus tools for editing and importing some [[List of file formats#3D graphics|3D graphics file formats]], enhancing video, and comprehensive image analysis tools with [[Digital Imaging and Communications in Medicine|DICOM]] file support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Adobe Photoshop CS3 Extended - Product overview | accessdate = 2007-06-17 | year = 2007 | url =
http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/photoshopextended/pdfs/photoshopex_datasheet.pdf | work = Adobe Official site | format = PDF }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===CS4===
Photoshop CS4 features a new 3D engine allowing painting directly on 3D models, wrapping 2D images around 3D shapes, converting gradient maps to 3D objects, adding depth to layers and text, getting print-quality output with the new ray-tracing rendering engine. It supports common 3D formats; the new Adjustment and Mask Panels; Content-aware scaling ([[seam carving]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-13580_3-10048014-39.html Adobe uses graphics chip for faster Photoshop CS4] - Posted by Stephen Shankland (September 22, 2008) CNET News.&lt;/ref&gt;); Fluid Canvas Rotation and File display options.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/photoshopextended/features/?view=topnew features: digital filters, image editing] - Adobe Photoshop CS4 Extended.&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 April, Adobe released Photoshop CS4 Extended, which includes all the same features of Adobe Photoshop CS4 with the addition of capabilities for scientific imaging, 3D, and high-end film and video users. The successor to Photoshop CS3, [[Adobe Creative Suite 4|Photoshop CS4]] is the first [[64-bit]] Photoshop on consumer computers (only on Windows – the OS X version is still 32-bit only.)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Haslam |first=Karen |url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,144119-c,graphicsmultimedia/article.html |title=Adobe 64-Bit Photoshop Struggle |publisher=PC World |date= |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===CS5===
Photoshop CS5 was launched on April 12, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://cs5launch.adobe.com/ | title=Adobe Creative Suite 5 Launch | publisher=Adobe Systems Incorporated | accessdate=2010-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a video posted on its official [[Facebook]] page, the development team revealed the new technologies under development, including three dimensional brushes and warping tools.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.facebook.com/video |title=Niet compatibele browser |publisher=Facebook |date= |accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2011, [[Adobe Creative Suite]]s 5.5 (CS5.5) were released which have new versions of some of the applications. However, the Photoshop that comes with them which is labeled version 12.1 is identical to the concurrently released update for Photoshop CS5, version 12.0.4, except for support for the new subscription pricing that was introduced with CS5.5.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://feedback.photoshop.com/photoshop_family/topics/what_is_the_difference_between_photoshop_cs5_and_the_version_of_photoshop_that_comes_with_creative_suite_5_5 |title=Photoshop: What is the difference between Photoshop CS5 and the version of Photoshop that comes with Creative Suite 5.5? |publisher=Feedback.photoshop.com |date=2011-04-11 |accessdate=2011-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Language availabilities==
Photoshop is available in the following languages:

Brazilian Portuguese, Chinese Simplified, Chinese Traditional, Czech, Danish, Dutch, English, Finnish, French, German, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Norwegian, Polish, Romanian, Russian, Spanish, Swedish, Turkish and Ukrainian.&lt;ref name=PhotoshopLanguages&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/photoshop/languages/ |title=language versions &amp;#124; Adobe Photoshop CS5 |publisher=Adobe.com |date= |accessdate=2010-05-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Arabic, Greek, and Hebrew versions are available from Winsoft.&lt;ref name=PhotoshopLanguages/&gt;

==Plugins==
{{Main|Photoshop plugin}}

Photoshop functionality can be extended by add-on programs called [[Photoshop plugin]]s (or plug-ins). Some of the plug-ins are created by Adobe itself, for example Adobe Camera Raw; but most of them are developed by third-party companies, according to Adobe's specifications. Some are free and some are commercial software.
Most Photoshop plug-ins can only work with Photoshop or Photoshop-compatible hosts, but a few can also be run as standalone applications.

Although Adobe allows creating a various types of the plugins, such as filter, export, import, selection, automation, etc., the most popular are the filter plugins (also known as a [[8bf]] plugins) available from under the Filter menu of Photoshop. 
These filter plugins can either modify the current image or create the all new content. Here are some popular types of such plug-ins (plus the companies whose products are the best known in the particular segment):
* Color correction plugins (Alien Skin Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.alienskin.com Alien Skin Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Nik Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.niksoftware.com Nik Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; OnOne Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ononesoftware.com OnOne Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Topaz Labs Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.topazlabs.com Topaz Labs Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; The Plugin Site,&lt;ref&gt;[http://thepluginsite.com The Plugin Site]&lt;/ref&gt; etc.)
* Special effects plugins (Alien Skin Software, Auto FX Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.autofx.com Auto FX Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; AV Bros.,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.avbros.com AV Bros. Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Flaming Pear Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flamingpear.com Flaming Pear Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; etc.)
* 3D effects plugins (Andromeda Software,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.andromeda.com Andromeda Software Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; Strata,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.strata.com Strata Web Site]&lt;/ref&gt; etc.)

Adobe Camera Raw (also known as ACR and Camera Raw) is a special plugin, supplied free by Adobe, used primarily to read and process [[Raw image format|raw image files]] so that the resultant images can be processed by Photoshop.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/cameraraw.html |title=Digital camera raw file support |publisher=Adobe.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is invoked by attempting to open such a file, rather than from the 'Filter' menu, but like other plugins is listed in the 'Help &amp;gt; About Plug-In' menu (as &quot;Camera Raw&quot;). It can also be opened via the [[Adobe Bridge]] by clicking on any image and selecting 'File &gt; Open in Adobe Camera Raw'.

==Cultural impact==
[[File:Photomontage (Forggensee Panorama) -2.jpg|right|thumb|300px|A landscape photo composited and manipulated in [[Photoshop]]]]
''Photoshop'' and derivatives such as ''Photoshopped'' (or just ''Shopped'') have become verbs that are sometimes used to refer to images edited by Photoshop,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.macworld.com/2000/08/bc/28photoshop/|title=Photoshop through the Years|author=Macworld Staff}}&lt;/ref&gt; or any image manipulating program. &quot;Photoshop&quot; is also used as a noun to refer to image editing programs [[Genericized trademark|in general]]. Such derivatives are discouraged by Adobe&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adobe.com/misc/trade.html#section-4|title=PROPER USE OF THE PHOTOSHOP TRADEMARK}}&lt;/ref&gt; because, in order to maintain validity and protect the trademark from becoming genericized, trademarks must be used as [[proper adjectives]].

''Photoshop'' art has become popular, for example [[Tao Lin]] has  a column&lt;ref&gt;http://www.viceland.com/blogs/en/tag/drug-related-photoshop-art/&lt;/ref&gt; employing only ''Photoshop'' for captioned pieces of art for [[Vice]]. Flickr features many groups devoted to ''Photoshop'' art including one with over 10,000 members.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.flickr.com/groups/artofphotoshop/&lt;/ref&gt;
=== Photoshop contest ===
{{main|Photoshop contest}}

A Photoshop contest, or sometimes photochop contest, is an [[online]] game, in which a [[website]] or user of an [[Internet forum]] will post a starting [[image]] &amp;mdash; usually a [[photograph]] &amp;mdash; and ask others to manipulate the image using some kind of [[computer graphics|graphics]] editing [[software]], such as [[Photoshop]], [[Corel Photopaint]], The [[GIMP]], [[Paint Shop Pro]], [[Paint.NET]] or [[Microsoft Paint]].

==See also==
* [[Adobe Photoshop Express]]
* [[Adobe Photoshop Elements]]
* [[Adobe Photoshop Lightroom]]
* [[Image editing]]
* [[Comparison of raster graphics editors]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

==External links==
{{Sister project links|Photoshop}}
* {{Official website|http://www.adobe.com/products/photoshop/}}
* {{dmoz|Computers/Software/Graphics/Image_Editing/Photoshop|Photoshop}}

&lt;!--======================== {{No more links}} ============================
 | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. Wikipedia |
 | is not a collection of links nor should it be used for advertising. |
 | |
 | Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED. |
 | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details. |
 | |
 | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or |
 | replacements on this article's discussion page, or submit your link |
 | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org) |
 | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template. |
 ======================= {{No more links}} =============================--&gt;

{{Raster graphics editors}}
{{AdobeCS}}
{{Adobe eLearning Suite}}
{{Adobe Technical Communication Suite}}
{{Adobe Systems}}

[[Category:Adobe Photoshop| ]]
[[Category:Adobe Creative Suite|Photoshop]]
[[Category:C++ software]]
[[Category:Vector graphics editors]]
[[Category:Raster graphics editors]]
[[Category:IRIX software]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Mac OS X software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Technical communication tools|Photoshop]]
[[Category:Graphic design]]
[[Category:Proprietary software]]
[[Category:Photo software]]
[[Category:1990 introductions]]
[[Category:Adobe software|Photoshop]]

[[ar:أدوبي فوتوشوب]]
[[az:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[bn:অ্যাডোবি ফটোশপ]]
[[bs:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[bg:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ca:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[cs:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[da:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[de:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[et:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[el:Photoshop]]
[[es:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[eu:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[fa:ادوبی فوتوشاپ]]
[[fr:Photoshop]]
[[gl:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ko:어도비 포토샵]]
[[hi:अडॉबी फोटोशॉप]]
[[hr:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[id:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[is:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[it:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[he:אדובי פוטושופ]]
[[ka:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[lb:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[hu:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ml:അഡോബി ഫോട്ടോഷോപ്പ്]]
[[mr:अ‍ॅडोबे फोटोशॉप]]
[[ms:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[nl:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ja:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[no:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[pl:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[pt:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ro:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ru:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[sq:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[simple:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[sk:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[sl:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[sr:Адоби фотошоп]]
[[sh:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[fi:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[sv:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[ta:அடோப் போட்டோசாப்]]
[[te:అడోబీ ఫోటోషాప్]]
[[th:อะโดบี โฟโตชอป]]
[[tr:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[uk:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[vi:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[zh-yue:Adobe Photoshop]]
[[zh:Adobe Photoshop]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
