<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25026929" ns="0" title="Micah Project"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Orphan|date=April 2010}}

{{Advert|date=November 2009}}
'''The Micah Project'''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.micahcentral.org&lt;/ref&gt; is a religious, [[Christian]]-based, [[non-profit organization]] in [[Tegucigalpa]], [[Honduras]] which currently supports 24 young men, all of whom spent their childhoods on the streets of Tegucigalpa or in impoverished homes.  Micah refers to the biblical [[book of Micah]] 6:8 which states &quot;act justly, love mercy, and walk humbly with their God.&quot;

==Mission and Goals==
The mission of the Micah Project is to equip children of poverty in Honduras with the spiritual, emotional, academic and physical abilities they need in order to become servant leaders in their society, profession, and faith.

The goals for the Micah Project are:

* Each project participant will develop a living, active relationship with their Savior Jesus Christ and express the fruits of this relationship in their family, among their friends, and to those who are suffering and in need.
* Each project participant will possess the ability to use higher order thinking skills, such as the ability to analyze, synthesize, and evaluate any given information, and use these skills to form ideas about the world and their responsibility in it.
* Each participant will prayerfully develop his vocation based upon God’s calling in his life, and will seek the training and experiences necessary to become servant leaders in their field.

==History and Founding==
The concept of the Micah Project was first inspired by Michael Miller in 1993, a [[Wheaton College (Illinois)|Wheaton College]] Human Needs Global Resources (HNGR) program student&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wheaton.edu/alumni/magazine/spring2004.pdf Wheaton College Alumni News - Vol 7 Issue 2 - Spring 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; and volunteer in street missions. After working with street children in Honduras during this time, he felt the call to make this his life’s vocation. Michael returned to Honduras in 1998 to continue his work with street children. In 1999, [[Hurricane Mitch]] caused widespread devastation in Tegucigalpa, prompting Michael to stay&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldmag.com/articles/3327 World Book Magazine - ''Honduras' helping hands'' featuring Michael Miller]&lt;/ref&gt; and spend time developing the Villa Linda Miller community&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gfimpact.org/gfx/awakenhonduras/vlm.html Global Fast - Villa Linda Miller]&lt;/ref&gt;, a development of 165 homes for the victims of the hurricane. During that time, he was impacted by the feelings of hopelessness among those who became homeless&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/latin_america/july-dec98/honduras_11-30.html MacNeil/Lehrer News Hour - Road To Recovery - November 30, 1998]&lt;/ref&gt; and began to plan the Micah Project.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
The Micah Project was founded in 1999 and chartered in January, 2000 in the State of Missouri. In January 2000, Micah opened the doors of its first group home inviting eight street boys and a VLM teenager to be its first residents.

==Current Outreaches==
The Micah Project has established or helped develop many outreaches within Honduras:

===Micah Boys Outreach===
In 2001, an outreach ministry of the Micah boys to the children and teens of the VLM community was established.

===Proyecto AFE===
In 2003, Jony from VLM also with Micah staff and boys began a program for the children of
the city dump. An educational program for children who live in the city dump began. The
ministry was later named Proyecto AFE&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.micahcentral.org/dumpintro.htm Proyecto AFE]&lt;/ref&gt; (AH-fay), which are the Spanish initials for Love,
Faith, and Hope.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
At the end of 2007, Proyecto AFE became administratively independent from the Micah
Project. Even so, Micah continues to maintain a close relationship with AFE, sharing staff,
volunteers and ideas. AFE is now administrated through the Santidad Evangelical
denomination, which also oversees the church in Villa Linda Miller. In the 2009 school year,
190 kids are enrolled in the AFE school, from ages four through eighteen.

===Micah Leadership House===
In 2004, the Leadership House was purchased and became operational as a transitional home
for our older participants. Because most of the young men lost many years of school while on
the streets, they turn eighteen before graduating from high school. The Leadership House
provides a place where they can experience an increased level of independence and adult
responsibility, while still benefiting from the guidance of a caring mentor who lives in an
adjoining apartment.

==Education==
Listed below are some educational achievements of the boys at the Micah Project:

* In 2004, the first 5 participants of the Micah Project graduated from the home
schooling program. With funding from the University Scholarship fund, each of them were able
to enroll in college in 2005—some in the US in Missouri, Texas and in Honduras.
* In 2005, 4 more Micah men graduated from Micah homeschooling and all these men
are now in universities in Honduras, Missouri, Costa Rica, or Mexico.
* In 2007 and 2008, 5 men and 3 men graduated from high school respectively. Most
have begun a university education; others have faced emotional and physical challenges which they
continue to work through either with the Project or at home. One student is serving 6
months with [[YWAM]] in Switzerland and another is on a full scholarship to a leading
Honduran university. Also in November, 2007 Micah’s first university graduate,
Darwin Pavon, completed [[Zamorano|Zamorano University]] and began work in the field of
Agriculture.
* In 2009, 2 Micah men graduated from [[Missouri Baptist University]] with degrees in
Business and Marketing.

==Planned Outreaches==
=== Technical School ===
In 2009, plans for a Technical School and expanding work with single moms and their
families are underway.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Older Micah men are sought for the Technical-Auto Mechanics school planned to open in
the fall of 2010, which will provide education for all the boys but is mainly targeted for those
who are not planning on university studies.

===Sewing Ministry===
The Micah Project has been able to purchase homes in VLM for several of the moms,
moving them from dangerous neighborhoods or unsafe homes. Also, a sewing ministry
is underway bringing mothers to the Micah House twice a week for bible study and classes.

==External links==
* [http://www.micahcentral.org Micah Project Homepage]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

[[Category:Tegucigalpa]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
