<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25054792" ns="0" title="Tomás Regalado (American politician)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Politician
| name = Tomás P. Regalado
| image =
| caption =
| birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1947|5|24|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Havana, Cuba]]
| residence = [[Miami, Florida|Miami]]
| order = 42&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;
| office = Mayor of Miami
| term_start = November 11, 2009
| term_end =
| predecessor = [[Manny Diaz (Florida politician)|Manny Diaz]]
| successor = [[Incumbent]]
| party = [[non-partisan]]
[[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]]
| religion = [[Roman Catholic]]
| spouse = Raquel Ferreiro (1948–2008)
| children = Tomás&lt;br&gt;Raquel&lt;br&gt;Jose Francisco
| website = [http://www.ci.miami.fl.us/Mayor/pages/ Office of the Mayor]
}}

'''Tomás Pedro Regalado''' (born '''Tomás Pedro Regalado y Valdez''' May 24, 1947 in [[Havana, Cuba]]) is a former [[broadcast journalist]] and [[List of mayors of Miami|current mayor]] of [[Miami]], [[Florida]].

He served as the news director for Radio Mambi [[WAQI]] and as a reporter for [[Univision]]. Regalado was elected mayor on November 3, 2009, and sworn in on November 11.

==Early life==
Born in Havana, Cuba, May 24, 1947, Tomás Pedro Regalado was the first born child of Tomás Regalado Molina and Carmen Rita Valdez de Regalado. The son of an attorney/journalist who was the last president of the Cuban Association of Journalist and Reporters and a political prisoner for over twenty two (22) years, his father’s absence was a constant reminder to Tomás of the responsibilities and sacrifices of the [[Fourth Estate]].

Prior to leaving Cuba, Tomas attended elementary school at La Salle Catholic School in Havana. In April 1962, at the age of fourteen (14) Tomás and his younger brother Marcos were placed on a flight to Miami, Florida as participants of [[Operation Peter Pan]]. The two brothers lived at the boys’ camp in Kendall and then [[Florida City]] for several months until their aunt, Silvia Valdez claimed them. They lived with her until their mother, Carmen Rita Valdez de Regalado, arrived in Miami a year later.

In Miami, Tomás attended high school at [[Immaculata-Lasalle High School]] in [[Coconut Grove]] and then at the Lindsey Hopkins vocational school while working full time to support his mother and younger brother. At the age of seventeen, Tomás spent what little free time he had as an unpaid intern at WFAB, La Fabulosa. Determined to be a journalist; he had a day job and also attended seminars at the [[University of Miami]] Koubek Center for journalism and continued volunteering at the radio station.

==Journalism==

Tomás became the youngest reporter on staff at WFAB, La Fabulosa. Regalado quickly ascended from reporter to assistant producer. At twenty one, Regalado was hired by [[WSVN|WCKT]] an NBC affiliate as the Latin American News Editor and host of the news program Tele-Amigo. After two years at WCKT then Channel 7, Tomás returned to WFAB as a news producer and anchor. Regalado continued in Spanish language radio and married a fellow radio commentator, Raquel Ferreiro in 1972 at St. Hugh Catholic Church in Coconut Grove. Tomás and Raquel have three children, Tomás, Raquel and Jose Francisco and were married for thirty seven (37) years. Raquel died at Mercy Hospital on February 3, 2008.

In 1974, Tomás became a reporter for WLTV Channel 23 but returned to radio in 1977 as the News Director in charge of all programming for La Fabulosa, WFAB. In 1970, Regalado decided to leave the news desk and became the stations first international news correspondent. In the years that followed, Regalado traveled to Africa and covered the civil war in Angola, the riots in Soweto, South Africa and the civil war in Mozambique.

In 1979, Tomás’ father, Tomás Regalado Molina was released from prison thanks to the intercession of the then President of Costa Rica Rodrigo Caraso. Regalado senior lived in Miami from 1979 until his death in the fall of 1995. Regalado senior worked alongside his son and daughter-in-law as a producer and news editor at WRHC, the Cadena Azul. Regalado Molina was a contributor to el [[Diario de las Americas]] and [[El Nuevo Herald]] until his sudden death in 1995 at the age of seventy four. Tomás’ mother, Carmen Rita died soon after in 1998.

In 1983, Tomás, who was no stranger to the White House and had interviewed Presidents [[Richard Nixon]], [[Gerald Ford]] and [[Jimmy Carter]] became the first Cuban American member of the [[White House Press Corps]]. As a member of the Press Corps, Regalado traveled with Presidents [[Ronald Reagan]], [[George H.W. Bush]] and [[Bill Clinton]]. Regalado accompanied the presidents on their foreign trips, including but not limited to summits from 1983 to 1993 and met such figures as [[Mikhail Gorbachev]], [[Boris Yeltsin]] and [[Anwar Al Sadat]]. In this time period, Regalado also covered the presidential campaigns and national party conventions.

In 1986, Regalado was approved as an applicant to NASA’s Journalist in Space Program which was canceled after the Challenger explosion. While a full time News Director on Spanish language radio Regalado also worked for El Miami Herald as a weekly columnist. Regalado covered the civil war in Nicaragua and El Salvador and has visited over 78 countries throughout the world. Along with his wife Raquel, Tomas spoke several times before the Human Rights Commission of United Nations in Geneva Switzerland against human rights violations in Cuba.

==Political Career==
In September 1996, Regalado was elected City wide as City Commissioner. One week after his election, the City of Miami’s economic crisis was exposed by Operation Green Palm and an oversight board was installed. Regalado was re-elected in 1999, and then again in 2003 without opposition. In his last election in 2007, Tomas was re-elected by ninety-four percent (94%) in his district. During that time, he kept the News Director position in the Spanish Broadcasting Systems by working as a daily host and commentator on WWFE la Poderosa and a host of a daily news program on the Cable Network TeleMiami.

On November 3, Regalado was elected Miami’s 33rd Mayor with a 72% margin. He keeps his promise he would lower his salary by $50,000 as well as reducing his pension by 25%.

==Personal Life==
His son, Tomas Regalado Jr. is an anchor and producer at [[TV Marti]], daughter, Raquel Regalado is a MDCPS Board member and attorney with Feldman Gale PA, and youngest son, Jose is a college student at [[Florida International University]]. Jose is also volunteering in the father’s office. Regalado currently lives with Jose in Shenandoah in [[Little Havana]]. He is also the grandfather of Tomás M. Regalado, Nicolas A. Regalado, Isabela M. and Sebastian K. Herrera Regalado.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
*http://www.tomasregalado.com/HIStory.aspx
*http://www.miamiherald.com/460/story/1328985.html
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Miami|Biography}}
*http://www.tomasregalado.com/HIStory.aspx

{{S-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Manny Diaz (Florida politician)|Manny Diaz]] | title = [[Mayor of the City of Miami]]|years=2009-| after= ''Incumbent''}}
{{S-end}}
{{Mayors of the largest 50 US cities}}
{{Florida cities and mayors of 100,000 population}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Regalado, Tomas
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =1947-24-5
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Havana, Cuba]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Regalado, Tomas}}
[[Category:1947 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Mayors of Miami, Florida]]
[[Category:American politicians of Cuban descent]]
[[Category:People from Havana]]
[[Category:Cuban emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Florida Republicans]]

[[de:Tomás Regalado (Politiker)]]
[[fr:Tomás Regalado]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
