<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2509171" ns="0" title="WGTU"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WGTU/WGTQ|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = [[Image:Wgtu variation.png|150px]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here without providing a rationale on the image description page per [[WP:FURG]] --&gt;|
  station_slogan           = ''Inspiring. Informative. Entertaining.''&lt;br&gt;''Fair. Accurate. Honest.''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  station_branding         = ABC 29&amp;8&lt;br&gt;TV 7&amp;4 &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  analog                   = |
  digital                  =&lt;br&gt;'''WGTU:''' 29 ([[UHF]])&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT2:''' 47 (UHF)&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' 8 ([[VHF]])&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT2:''' 35(UHF)|
  other_chs                = |
  subchannels              = 29.1/8.1 ABC-HD&lt;br&gt;29.2/8.2 NBC-SD&lt;br&gt;7.2/4.2 ABC-SD |
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = '''WGTU:''' August 23, 1971&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' 1976|
  location                 = '''WGTU:''' [[Traverse City, Michigan|Traverse City]]/[[Cadillac, Michigan]]&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' [[Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''WGTU:''' '''G'''rand&lt;br&gt;'''T'''raverse '''U'''HF&lt;br&gt;
                             '''WGTQ:''' '''G'''rand&lt;br&gt;'''T'''raverse '''Q'''uality|
  former_callsigns         = |
  former_channel_numbers   = '''WGTU:'''&lt;br&gt;29 (UHF analog, 1971-2009)&lt;br&gt;31 (UHF digital)&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:'''&lt;br&gt;8 (VHF analog, 1976-2009)&lt;br&gt;9 (VHF digital)|
  owner                    = Tucker Broadcasting of Traverse City, Inc. (operated through [[shared services|SSA]] by [[Barrington Broadcasting]])|
  licensee                 = |
  sister_stations          = WPBN-TV/WTOM-TV, &quot;[[WBVC (The CW Plus)|WBVC]]&quot;|
  former_affiliations      = |
  effective_radiated_power = '''WGTU:''' 68.4 [[kilowatt|kW]]&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT2:''' 500 kW&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' 15 kW&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT2:''' 78 kW|
  HAAT                     = '''WGTU &amp; WPBN-DT2:'''&lt;br&gt;393 m&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' 288 m&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT2:''' 168 m|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = '''WGTU:''' 59280&lt;br&gt;'''WPBN-DT2:''' 21253&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:''' 59279&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT2:''' 21254|
  coordinates              = '''WGTU &amp; WPBN-DT2:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|44|44|53.3|N|85|4|8.6|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}&lt;br&gt;'''WGTQ:'''&lt;br&gt;{{coord|46|3|8.2|N|84|6|38.8|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WGTQ}}&lt;br&gt;'''WTOM-DT2:''' {{coord|45|39|0.6|N|84|20|36.9|W|type:landmark_scale:2000|name=WTOM-TV}}|
  homepage                 = |
}}

'''WGTU''' is the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for the Northern [[Lower Peninsula of Michigan|Lower]] and Eastern [[Upper Peninsula of Michigan|Upper]] Peninsulas of [[Michigan]] that is licensed to [[Traverse City, Michigan|Traverse City]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 29 from a transmitter east of [[Kalkaska, Michigan|Kalkaska]]. Like other network affiliates in this vast rural area, it operates a full-time satellite, '''WGTQ'''. Licensed to [[Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan|Sault Ste. Marie]], this station airs a high definition digital signal on [[VHF]] channel 8 from a transmitter approximately thirty miles SSE of Sault Ste. Marie near [[Goetzville]] in Southeastern [[Chippewa County, Michigan|Chippewa County]]. 

Together, the two are known on-air as '''''ABC 29&amp;8''''' and serve 23 counties in the Northern Lower Peninsula, three counties in the Eastern Upper Peninsula, and portions of [[Northern Ontario]] including Sault Ste. Marie's [[Canadian]] [[Sault Ste. Marie, Ontario|sister city]]. WGTU is owned by Tucker Broadcasting of Traverse City but operated through a [[shared services]] agreement (SSA) by [[Barrington Broadcasting]], owner of [[NBC]] affiliate [[WPBN-TV]] and full-time satellite WTOM-TV. WGTU and WPBN share studios on [[M-72 (Michigan highway)|M-72]] west of Traverse City. This station operates Traverse City's  [[The CW Plus|cable-only]] [[The CW|CW]] affiliate [[WBVC (The CW Plus)|&quot;WBVC&quot;]] on [[Charter Communications|Charter]] channel 61.

==History==
'''WGTU''' began broadcasting on January 23, 1971. Before that, ABC programming in [[Northern Michigan]] was split between [[CBS]] affiliates [[WWTV|WWTV/WWUP]] ([[soap opera]]s, [[game show]]s) and WPBN/WTOM (weekend sporting events). In 1976, it added '''WGTQ''' in Sault Ste. Marie to bring the full ABC schedule to the Eastern Upper Peninsula. 

For many years, WGTQ was available in large portions of the [[Canada|Canadian]] provinces of [[Ontario]] and [[Quebec]].  However, it has not been seen in Canada since the early-2000s. In [[Greater Sudbury|Sudbury]], the [[Persona Inc.|Persona]] cable system pulled WGTQ in favor of [[WXYZ-TV]] from [[Detroit]]. In [[Rouyn-Noranda, Quebec|Rouyn-Noranda]] and [[Val-d'Or, Quebec]], [[Cablevision (Canada)|Cablevision]] replaced WGTU with [[Boston]]'s [[WCVB-TV]]. In the Canadian Sault, local cable provider [[Shaw Communications]] opted instead for [[Flint, Michigan|Flint]]'s ABC affiliate [[WJRT-TV]] though it was later replaced by WXYZ. 

From the start, WGTU was locally owned, most recently by Tom Scanlan (who also owns [[Marquette, Michigan|Marquette]]'s [[WBUP]] and [[WBKP]] as well as [[Alpena, Michigan|Alpena]]'s [[WBKB-TV]]) until its 2003 sale to [[Max Media]]. In 1998, the station began to provide promotional and advertising services for [[The WB 100+ Station Group|cable-only]] [[The WB|WB]] affiliate &quot;WBVC&quot; which was based at WGTU's original studios on East Front Street in Downtown Traverse City. In early-November 2006, WGTU and WGTQ upgraded their digital signals to begin offering ABC in high definition which can also be seen on Charter digital channel 788. 

On September 19, 2007, an application was filed to the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) by Max Media to sell WGTU/WGTQ and its CW cable-only station to Tucker Broadcasting for $10 million. After FCC approval, Tucker entered into a shared sales agreement with Barrington Broadcasting. According to the FCC filing, WPBN would sell advertising time and provide other programming for WGTU. The same was approved in April 2008. After WPBN renovated its studios over the Summer, WGTU moved its operations from its longtime studios in Traverse City into WPBN's studios.

At some point in time, what had become CW affiliate &quot;WBVC&quot; was added to a new second digital subchannel of WGTU. This was done to offer non-cable viewers access to its programming. It also began using the WGTU-DT2 call sign in an official manner.  

On June 12, 2009, WGTU and WGTQ reverted their digital signals back to the previous analog signal locations as part of the switch to digital-only broadcasting.  On the same day, WGTU dropped WBVC from its second digital subchannel, replacing it with a simulcast of WPBN.  This is because WTOM's digital signal no longer covers the Upper Peninsula side of the market.   WBVC is now only available to customers of Charter Cable and not satellite or over the air viewers.

===Programming===
WGTU airs 24 hours a day during the week although it shows a [[test pattern]] for a short period overnight on the weekends. [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on the station includes: ''[[The Dr. Oz Show]]'', ''[[The Insider (TV series)|The Insider]]'', ''[[According to Jim]]'', and ''[[Judge Judy]]''. It clears the entire ABC schedule, even though through 2008, network programming on the last Sunday in January was preempted for the yearly [[Christian Broadcasting Network|CBN]]/[[The 700 Club|700 Club]] [[telethon]] as a part of its commitment to airing ''The 700 Club'' weekday mornings since the 1980s. This was also due to CBN personality Tim Robertson (son of [[Pat Robertson|Pat]]) owning an interest in former station owner Max Media. This caused complaints about the pre-empted [[ESPN on ABC|ABC Sports]] programming. The issue became moot when Tucker/Barrington discontinued airing the show in Fall 2008 when it moved to [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliates [[WFQX-TV|WFQX/WFUP]].

==Newscasts==
[[File:Wgtu news 2010.png|thumb|right|News open seen weeknights at 6:30.]]
WGTU initially had a full-fledged news department.  However, it made little headway against WWTV and WPBN.  The news department was significantly cut back in 1984, and for more than a quarter-century it aired almost no local newscasts at all.  The only local news on the station were weekday morning news, weather, and sports cut-ins at :25 and :55 past the hour during ''[[Good Morning America]]'' as well as a ten minute news and weather update seen weeknights at 11.  The update is currently anchored by Lori Puckett, the station's only on-air personality.  She appeared on WPBN in the local segments of the 2008 ''[[Jerry Lewis MDA Telethon]]''. One notable former news anchor from WGTU is Marc Schollett who is now the weeknight anchor on WPBN.

After WGTU consolidated its operations with WPBN, it became possible that a full-fledged local newscast would return to WGTU. On September 13, 2010, that station finally took advantage of this channel being housed in the same facility and launched a weeknight newscast at 6:30 on WGTU. As a result, ''[[ABC World News |ABC World News with Diane Sawyer]]'' moved to 7. The show features local news and weather but also goes into detail covering community events and various businesses. There is no sports report given in this broadcast. It originates from a secondary set. Like all CW Plus stations in the [[Eastern Time Zone]], &quot;WBVC&quot; airs the nationally syndicated morning show ''[[The Daily Buzz]]'' on weekdays from 6 until 9.

'''''UpNorthLive Tonight'''''&lt;br&gt;''(weeknights 6:30 to 7)''
*Anchor:
**Erika Erickson
*Weather:
**Mark Watkins
*Reporter:
**Jamie Kramer

'''''ABC 29&amp;8 News Break'''''&lt;br&gt;''(weeknights 11 to 11:10)''
*Anchor:
**Lori Puckett

==News/station presentation==
===Newscast titles===
*''[[Eyewitness News]]'' (1970s)
*''ABC 29&amp;8 News'' (1990s)
*''UpNorthLive Tonight'' (2009-present)

===Station slogans===
*''Inspiring. Informative. Entertaining.'' (2009-present)

==External links==
*[http://www.upnorthlive.com/ WGTU/WGTQ &quot;ABC 29&amp;8&quot;]
*[http://www.abc.com ABC]
*{{TVQ|WGTU}}
*{{TVQ|WGTQ}}

{{Northern Michigan TV}}
{{ABC Michigan}}
{{Barrington Broadcasting}}

[[Category:ABC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1971]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1976|WGTQ]]
[[Category:Television stations in Traverse City, Michigan]]
[[Category:Television stations in Michigan]]
[[Category:Channel 29 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 8 digital TV stations in the United States|WGTQ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
