<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25093964" ns="0" title="List of Hollyoaks characters (2010)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Hollyoaks'' characters (2010)}}
{{HOMinor}}
''[[Hollyoaks]]'' is a long running [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] in the [[United Kingdom]]. This is a list of characters who first appeared on the programme during 2010, listed in order of their first appearance. In January 2010, it was announced that [[Paul Marquess]] would be taking over the role of series producer from [[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]], who had been with the show for one year. Marquess fully took control on 17 January 2010, onwards. March saw the introduction of [[Jem Costello]], a new love interest for [[Gilly Roach]]. The character of [[Eva Strong]] was introduced in April as the biological mother of [[Anita Roy]], and [[Texas Longford]] joined ''Hollyoaks'' in May. Marquess' first major casting was former ''[[Footballers Wives]]'' actress [[Phina Oruche]] in the role of [[Gabby Sharpe]] along with her children [[Amber Sharpe|Amber]] and [[Taylor Sharpe|Taylor]] and husband [[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil]], all of whom appeared in June. In July, the Costellos became the second family of the year to be introduced, consisting of [[Carl Costello|Carl]] and [[Heidi Costello]] and their sons [[Seth Costello|Seth]] and [[Riley Costello|Riley]]. July also saw the arrivals of Heidi's cousin [[Mitzeee Minniver]] and student [[Kevin Smith (Hollyoaks)|Kevin Smith]]. Three characters joined in August: [[Jasmine Costello]], Heidi and Carl's daughter; [[Bart McQueen]], a member of the long-established [[McQueen family]]; and [[Brendan Brady]], [[Cheryl Brady]]'s half-brother. In September, the O'Connors were introduced, with daughter [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead]], son [[Finn O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Finn]], stepmother [[Diane O'Connor|Diane]] and father [[Rob O'Connor|Rob]], and new students [[Leanne Holiday]], [[Jamil Fadel]] and [[Doug Carter]]. [[West End theatre|London West End]] star [[Darren Day]] joined the cast in October, playing [[Danny Houston]].
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}
{{-}}

==Jamie==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series = Hollyoaks
|name = Jamie
|portrayer = [[Finn Jones]]
|image =
|introducer = [[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years = 2010
|first = 2 January 2010
|last = 11 February 2010
|classification = [[List of past Hollyoaks characters#Last appeared in 2010|Former; recurring]]
|occupation = Drug dealer (until 2010)
|home = [[Prison]]
|spinoffs = ''[[Hollyoaks Later]]'' (2009)
}}

'''Jamie''', played by [[Finn Jones]], first appeared on-screen on 28 September 2009 during the [[Hollyoaks Later (series 2)|second series]] of the ''Hollyoaks'' spin-off ''[[Hollyoaks Later]]'' as a new love interest for established character [[Hannah Ashworth]] ([[Emma Rigby]]). Jones reprised the role in main ''Hollyoaks'' episodes in 2010, which coincided with the departure of Hannah. Jamie appeared in ''Hollyoaks'' between 2 January and 11 February 2010.

The character of Jamie was created as a temporary love interest for Hannah and was intended to feature only in ''Hollyoaks Later'', the spin-off from the ''Hollyoaks'' series.&lt;ref name=&quot;laterjamie&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a183050/later-character-joins-hollyoaks.html|title=Later character joins Hollyoaks|work=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=22 October 2009|accessdate=10 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2009, it was announced that Jones was to reprise his role of Finn for the departure of Hannah.&lt;ref name=&quot;laterjamie&quot;/&gt; Of Jamie's return, a ''Hollyoaks'' source commented: &quot;Hannah's had a terrible time of late and Jamie's sudden arrival in the village next year reopens a wound that's only just started to heal.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;laterjamie&quot;/&gt;

Hannah Ashworth goes to a music festival with her brothers [[Rhys Ashworth|Rhys]] ([[Andrew Moss]]) and [[Josh Ashworth]] ([[Sonny Flood]]) where she meets Jamie. When Hannah falls off a podium, Jamie catches her and they begin to develop feelings for each other. Jamie and his friend Imogen (Holly Gilbert) invite Hannah to stay at their house for the night. Jamie and Hannah spend the night on the beach together. Jamie begs an angry Hannah to stay after Imogen tells her that Jamie is a drug dealer. Jamie and Hannah each take an ecstasy pill and they sleep together. Jamie asks Hannah to stay with him, to which she agrees. When Hannah discovers that Imogen is prostituting herself, Imogen's pimp Kev (James Cartwright) hits her. Jamie is woken by the shouting and rushes downstairs, where he distracts Kev as Hannah escapes. Hannah hides in the ice cream van and lets Jamie in, where they drive away. Jamie finds Kev's drugs in the ice cream van and thinks he can sell them, but Hannah tells him Kev will want revenge. They then plan to leave together. Hannah throws away the drugs that Jamie found and tells him that he does not need to deal drugs anymore. Jamie then frantically tries to retrieve them and Hannah realises that he has chosen drugs over her. Hannah decides to leave.

In February 2010, Hannah arrives at [[The Dog in the Pond]] public house and finds Jamie talking to her mother [[Suzanne Ashworth|Suzanne]] ([[Suzanne Hall]]). Jamie tells Hannah that he is no longer dealing drugs, however Hannah asks him to leave. Hannah tells Jamie to leave before Rhys finds him. Rhys tells Jamie to stay away from Hannah. Jamie then calls Hannah and tells her that he loves her. Hannah's friend [[Nancy Hayton]] ([[Jessica Fox]]) meets Jamie and takes a dislike to him after becoming concerned for Hannah's safety. Hannah later meets up with Jamie who is in pain, and realises that Rhys beat him up. Jamie asks Hannah to leave with him and kisses her. Hannah responds, but insists that their relationship has to be on her terms. Hannah's husband [[Darren Osborne]] ([[Ashley Taylor Dawson]]) asks Jamie for drugs after he and Rhys plan to set Jamie up. Jamie tells Darren that he does not deal drugs. Suzanne attempts to find out how serious Jamie and Hannah's relationsip is and shows him Hannah's video diary whilst she was suffering from anorexia nervosa. Jamie is shocked but tells Suzanne that he will take care of Hannah. As Jamie goes to meet Hannah, he is stopped and beaten. He is thrown into the boot of a car and dumped in the woods by Rhys and Darren, where Rhys tells him to stay away from Hannah. Jamie returns to The Dog in the Pond and when Hannah asked him what happened, he points at Rhys and Darren. 

Jamie is worried when he gets a text from Blue (Kyle Rees) and begins to panic. Jamie then persuades Hannah to leave the following day. At Hannah's leaving party, Jamie receives a call from Blue and quickly begins to pack his bag. Whilst packing, Jamie discovers that the money from his bag is missing. When Blue calls again for the missing money, Jamie begins to panic and sends Hannah out whilst he looks for it. Jamie finds out that Rhys has the money and Rhys gives him an ultimatum, to leave with the money alone, or leave without it with Hannah. When Hannah's family say goodbye to her, Jamie arrives late. Jamie and Hannah stay in a hotel after there flight is delayed and Hannah finds their room trashed. Jamie returns to find Blue with Hannah and admits that he stole the money and explains that he no longer has it. Jamie calls Rhys to prove that he does not have the money, but Rhys denies any involvement. Jamie and Blue fight and as Jamie struggles to defend himself, he reaches for a letter opener and stabs Blue. Hannah begs Jamie to call an ambulance, but he refuses and asks her to leave Blue and go on the run with him. Hannah says she is not leaving until an ambulance is called and Jamie agrees. Jamie then tries to leave and when Hannah refuses, he grabs their bags and drags Hannah to the door. Jamie finds Darren at the door and attempts to leave, but Darren refuses to move. Hannah tells Darren she loves Jamie and they rush down the corridor, but the police confront them. Jamie becomes angry and thinks that Darren called them, but Hannah tells him that she called them. Jamie then pulls the letter opener from his pocket and points it in Hannah's back. He begins to usher her out of the building and warns the police that if they try to stop him, he will kill Hannah. Darren then jumps to save Hannah, but Jamie stabs him. Jamie is arrested by the police. 
{{-}}

==Martin Campbell==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series = Hollyoaks
|name = Martin Campbell
|portrayer = Grant Masters
|image =
|introducer = [[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years = 2010
|first = 19 February 2010
|last = 18 June 2010
|classification = [[List of past Hollyoaks characters#Last appeared in 2010|Former; recurring]]
|occupation = 
|home =
|spinoffs = 
|sons = [[Ricky Campbell]]
}}

'''Martin Campbell''', played by Grant Masters, is the father of established character [[Ricky Campbell]] ([[Ashley Margolis]]). He made his first on-screen appearance on 19 February 2010. He made his final appearance on 18 June 2010.

In December 2009, in an interview with ''[[Digital Spy]]'' series producer [[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]] revealed that Ricky had a secret, commenting: [...] &quot;And Ricky has a secret, so we'll meet elements of his family...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/scoop/a190457/bonus-scoop-hollyoaks-spoilers-for-2010.html|title=Bonus Scoop: 'Hollyoaks' spoilers for 2010|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|author=Green, Kris|date=10 December 2009|accessdate=2010-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In early 2010, ''[[Inside Soap]]'' revealed that a new character called Martin would be joining the show and that ''Hollyoaks'' producers were not revealing any information about the character.&lt;ref name=&quot;insidesoap&quot;&gt;Moon, Katy (2 February 2010). &quot;Who's in? Who's out?&quot;. [[Inside Soap]], Issue 5: 6–12 February 2010. Retrieved 2010-02-06.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2010, it was revealed that Martin was Ricky's father who suffers from [[Multiple sclerosis]], and that Ricky is his full-time carer.&lt;ref name=&quot;martin&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a203506/oaks-star-grateful-for-carer-storyline.html|title='Oaks star &quot;grateful&quot; for carer storyline|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|author=Green, Kris|date=16 February 2010|accessdate=2010-12-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

When Ricky Campbell begins to disappear frequently, his best friend [[Duncan Button]] ([[Dean Aspen]]) decides to find out what he is doing. Duncan sees Ricky making a transaction with someone and follows him. When Ricky enters a flat, Duncan hears raised voices and sees Martin on the floor with Ricky standing over him with blood on his hands. Ricky helps Martin and sees to his injuries. Duncan then demands to be let in the flat and accuses Ricky of being a drug dealer and attacking Martin. Ricky reveals that Martin is his father. Martin tells Ricky to get rid of Duncan and Ricky pushes Duncan out of the door. Ricky later admits to Duncan that Martin is suffering from Multiple sclerosis. When Ricky is given detention at school, Duncan visits Martin and tells him that he is there to wait for Ricky. Martin pretends not to be ill and offers to cook dinner for Duncan. Martin struggles whilst reaching for the tomato ketchup and falls. He tells Duncan to keep his fall a secret. Duncan helps Martin before Ricky arrives. Ricky decides to audition to be a DJ at Duncan's birthday party and when he returns home to get his records he finds Martin on the floor. Martin realises that Ricky has something to do and tells him to go. 

Ricky gets detention at school and Martin calls him needing help. Ricky attempts to leave but school mentor [[Kris Fisher]] ([[Gerard McCarthy]]) mistakenly hurts his arm. Martin discovers bruises on Ricky's arm and is angry when he hears that a staff member at school was responsible for the injury. Kris visits Martin to discuss Ricky's school attendance. Ricky begins to worry that Kris will find out Martin illness and Duncan causes a distraction. Martin then discovers that Kris was responsible for hurting Ricky. Martin attempts to hit Kris, but falls out of his wheelchair. Martin is later rushed to hospital and Kris learns that he is suffering from Multiple sclerosis. Kris tries to persuade Ricky to get help for Martin, but he refuses. When Kris tells Ricky that he is going to phone social services, Ricky threatans to tell them that Kris hurt his arm. Kris begins to give daily help to Martin and Ricky. When it becomes apparent that Kris and Ricky are spending more time together, Kris resigns to protect Martin and Ricky's secret.

Ricky begins to struggle caring for Martin. Kris urges Martin to tell Ricky that his condition is worsening. Martin refuses as he does not want Ricky to fail his GCSE examinations. Martin then asks Kris to assist him in suicide but Kris says he cannot, which leaves Martin trying to find other methods of suicide. Kris calls for professional help and Martin is taken to hospital, leaving Ricky angry. Duncan overhears Martin talking about his planned suicide and makes him promise that he will never go through with it. When Ricky visits Martin, he realises that his condition has worsened.
{{-}}

==Meriel Vaughn==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Meriel Vaughn
|image=
|portrayer=Emily Corselli
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first=26 February 2010
|last=29 July 2010
|occupation=[[Journalist]]
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
}}
'''Meriel Vaughn''' played by Emily Corselli, is an ambitious journalist, trying to get exclusive details from the Holly abduction case. She left on 2 March 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.limemanagement.tv/latest_news/latestnews.asp|title=Latest News|publisher=Lime Pictures|author=|date=26 February 2010|accessdate=2010-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meriel returns when Michaela McQueen starts working for the Chester Herald, where they begin a feud. In June 2010, Meriel is angry when Michaela gains an exclusive interview with her sister Carmel over the murder of [[Calvin Valentine]] gets on the front page of the Herald. When Michaela goes along with a gang of thugs for another story, Meriel follows her, and sees Michaela being locked in a shed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=2844: Michaela finds herself in a spot of bother|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a223623/2844-michaela-finds-herself-in-a-spot-of-bother.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=2010-12-02|date=17 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Michaela is unavailable, Meriel tries to get Zak to talk about his attack on Tariq Mistry, and when he rebuffs her, she calls the police about Zak's crime. By the time Michaela is freed, Zak has been arrested, and Meriel gloats that the story will be on the front page of the paper. She was not seen again.
{{-}}

==Jem Costello==
{{Main|Jem Costello}}
'''Jem Costello''', played by Helen Russell-Clark, made her first on-screen appearance on 5 March 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a204682/2770-jacqui-tells-des-that-she-loves-him.html|title=2770: Jacqui tells Des that she loves hi|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=5 March 2010|accessdate=2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character was created as the love interest of [[Gilly Roach]] ([[Anthony Quinlan]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.five.tv/hollyoaks/extras/helen-jems-great-for-gilly-5839|title=Helen: Jem's great for Gilly!|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=([[Five (TV channel)|Five]])|accessdate=2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is the daughter of [[Carl Costello]] ([[Paul Opacic]]), stepdaughter of [[Heidi Costello]] ([[Kim Tiddy]]) and the half sister of [[Riley Costello|Riley]] (Rob Norbury), [[Seth Costello|Seth]]&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; and [[Jasmine Costello|Jasmine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;/&gt; Jem has been described as quite fiesty and a &quot;freespirit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.e4.com/video/J33B04pWgCf68b0SrzEIhs/play.e4|title=Hollyoaks, Helen Russell-Clark Interview|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=[[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]]|accessdate=2010-12-02|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Caroline==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Caroline
|image=
|portrayer=Amber Hodgkiss
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first= 26 March 2010
| last= 2 April 2010
| classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
| occupation=
| mother=
| sons= [[#Johnny|Johnny]]
}}
'''Caroline''', played by Amber Hodgekiss, is a nurse who helped care for [[Jake Dean]] ([[Kevin Sacre]]) when he was in a mental hospital. Jake later goes to stay with Caroline, she then sleeps with him. After deciding she wanted revenge on Jake for wanting to leave her, she tied him up, drugged him, tried to cause a gas explosion in her caravan. After drugging Jake up once more she set out to attack [[Holly Hutchinson]] (Lydia Walters). When she visits Holly, she finds [[Loretta Jones]] ([[Melissa Walton]]) at her bedside, angry with Loretta because of her relationship with Jake, she tries to stab Loretta with a medicinal needle. Jake comes to her aid and in the process Caroline is stabbed with the needle. Loretta learns Jake had slept with Caroline and leaves Jake.

Amber Hodgkiss had originally been cast to play a different character, Chrissy, during 2009. Chrissy was supposed to be an old childhood friend of Loretta and they were intended to have been involved in a storyline where they would be revealed as having murdered someone as children, which mirrored [[James Patrick Bulger|James Bulger]]'s murder in 1993. The first few scenes of Loretta meeting Chrissy were recorded, but the storyline was later axed, as it had caused too much controversy. The scenes with Chrissy were cut, but Hodgkiss was recast as Jake's ex-nurse, Caroline, and scenes with her new character were hastily recorded to replace those of the axed storyline.
{{-}}

==Olly Larkin==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Olly Larkin
|portrayer=Oliver Watton
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first=31 March 2010
| last= 4 June 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
}}
'''Olly Larkin''', played by Oliver Watton, is the new love interest of [[Amy Barnes]] (Ashley Slanina-Davies). Olly comes across as being perfect, even being fine with Amy having two children. On a date with Amy, [[Ste Hay]] ([[Kieron Richardson]]) and [[Josh Ashworth]] ([[Sonny Flood]]) try and ruin their date, but they get along despite their afforts, he also wins Josh over offering to buy him tickets for a gig. Olly leaves Amy when he finds out Josh and Ste aren't just her flat mates but her exes. However, the two reconcile and get back together.

Olly starts to show a bad side when he constantly riles Ste, and he becomes increasingly angry when Amy does not want to have sex with him. He gets her extremely drunk at the SU Bar, but when they return home, Ste makes sure nothing happens. Soon, during a night home alone with Amy, Olly locks Ste in Il Gnosh so that they will not be interrupted. When Olly returns to the flat, Amy explains she's not ready to have sex with him, which makes him angry. Olly tries to force himself onto Amy, but Ste escapes from Il Gnosh and saves her. The next day Amy reports him to the police for attempted rape and he was not seen again.
{{-}}

==Tariq Mistry==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Tariq Mistry
|portrayer=Rudi Dharmalingham
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first= 20 April 2010
|last= 3 August 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
}}
'''Tariq Mistry''', played by Rudi Dharmalingham first appears talking to [[Zak Ramsey]] ([[Kent Riley]]), about his brother, [[List of minor Hollyoaks characters (2009)#Caleb Ramsey|Caleb Ramsey]]'s death. Tariq was a friend of Caleb's. When Tariq met [[Des Townsend]], Des didn't like him. It is revealed that Tariq actually caused Caleb's death as while they were on patrol, a little boy was in trouble. Tariq decided to save him and tells Caleb to drive the opposite direction, which led him to a roadside bomb, killing him. Zak is outrageously furious and strongly beats Tariq in a park and he is hospitalised. He was last seen when Meriel Vaughn and [[Michaela McQueen]] were interviewing him about his attack. However, Michaela found out it was her boyfriend, [[Zak Ramsey]] who attacked him. Tarig left in May. He later return in August and told Zak he would not go to the police after he could see he was sorry for attacking him.
{{-}}

==Eva Strong==
{{Main|Eva Strong}}
'''Eva Strong''', played by former ''[[Emmerdale]]'' actress [[Sheree Murphy]], made her first on-screen appearance on 23 April 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a212762/2805-spencers-date-goes-awry.html|title=Spencer's date goes awry|work=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris |last=Green|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=23 April 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Murphy's casting was announced on 24 February 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;sheree&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a204983/sheree-murphy-joins-hollyoaks-cast.html|title=Sheree Murphy joins Hollyoaks cast|work=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=24 February 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is the biological mother of [[Anita Roy]] ([[Saira Choudhry]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;sheree&quot;/&gt; Eva has been described as &quot;free-spirited and enigmatic&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;free&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Holy Soap &gt; Hollyoaks &gt; Cast &gt; Eva Strong|url=http://holysoap.five.tv/hollyoaks/cast/eva-strong-9532|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=([[Channel 5 (UK){{!}}Five]])|accessdate=2010-12-01&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5tnntUCc1|archivedate=27 October 2010 --&gt;|year=2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Kyle Ryder==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Kyle Ryder
|portrayer=Neil Toon
|creator=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]] (2010)&lt;br/&gt;[[Paul Marquess]] (2011)
|years=2010, 2011
|first= 28 April 2010
|last=11 February 2011
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters#Last appeared in 2011|Former; recurring]]
|death= 10 February 2011}}
'''Kyle Ryder''', played by Neil Toon, first appears trying to start his car after it breaks down in the village. [[Theresa McQueen]] and [[Anita Roy]] see Kyle and Theresa fixes his car. Kyle and Theresa grow close, despite her cousin [[Jacqui McQueen]] ([[Claire Cooper]]) discovering his drug dealing. Kyle is caught drug dealing by ex-police officer [[Calvin Valentine]], who then bars him from The Loft nightclub. Kyle and his gang then attempt to beat Calvin up. Calvin accuses Kyle of sending him death threats, but later buys a gun from him for his own protection. On Calvin's wedding day, Kyle returns for the gun, unaware it was stolen. On the same day, Theresa, who is pregnant with Calvin's child, shoots and kills Calvin. Kyle discovers Theresa's pregnancy and that she lied he was the father. Suspicious, Kyle threatens Theresa and shouts at her until she admits she killed Calvin. Kyle is later arrested for Calvin's murder.

Months later, Theresa feels pressured as Kyle's trial approaches. Police officer [[Ethan Scott]] tells her Kyle is continuing to say Theresa killed Calvin. [[Warren Fox]] agrees to help Theresa, so pays men to beat Kyle up in prison and free him once he is taken to hospital. [[Brendan Brady]] pretends to be Warren and questions Kyle, who tells him Theresa killed Calvin.

Kyle visits Brendan, telling him that he's going to get a confession out of Theresa. He later kidnaps her and her baby Kathleen-Angel, taking her to an abandoned bank, where Theresa attempts to escape, but is re-captured. [[Warren Fox]] arrives, but is tricked by Kyle and gets knocked out and locked in a vault. Kyle and Theresa are met by Ethan and Carmel, where he forces Theresa to confess to killing Calvin to Ethan. Ethan then attacks Kyle, but Kyle throws him down an elevator shaft. Kyle panics and takes Kathleen-Angel, but Warren has escaped from the vault and shoots him in the back. As Kyle turns and falls into the shaft, Warren sees the baby in his arms. As Theresa, Carmel and Warren look down the shaft, they see Ethan holding the baby on top of an elevator only a few metres down. Kyle lies motionless on top of Ethan. Theresa falls into the shaft and the platform holding them up falls, and Kyle's lifeless body is thrown to the bottom of the building.
{{-}}

==Texas Longford==
{{Main|Texas Longford}}
'''Texas &quot;Tex&quot; Longford''', played by Bianca Hendrickse-Spendlove, made her first on-screen appearance on 17 May 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a217592/2821-calvins-shocked-by-the-cctv-footage.html|title=2821: Calvin's shocked by the CCTV footage|work=[[Digital Spy]]|first=Kris |last=Green|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=17 May 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 May 2010, it was announced that [[India Longford]]'s ([[Beth Kingston]]) older sister would arrive for her birthday.&lt;ref name=&quot;india&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e4.com/blog/hollyoaks/post/afm27ab6urzvnggf90qbzu/view.e4|title=SPOILER: India's sister to arrive in Hollyoaks!|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=([[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]])|date=3 May 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Texas initially appeared as a guest character between 17 and 21 May. It was announced on 7 July 2010 that Hendrickse-Spendlove would be reprising the role of Texas full-time.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.metro.co.uk/tv/834401-hollyoaks-unveils-nine-new-cast-members-as-part-of-soap-shake-up|title=Hollyoaks unveils nine new cast members as part of soap shake up|first=Amy|last=Duncan|date=7 July 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01|publisher=[[Metro (British newspaper)|Metro]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character made her on-screen return on 24 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a259692/2892-a-dramatic-mix-up-benefits-cindy.html|title=2892: A dramatic mix-up benefits Cindy |first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=24 August 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Texas has been described as a &quot;force of nature&quot; and &quot;vulnerable at heart&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;india&quot;/&gt;

==Adam==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Adam
|portrayer=Vlach Ashton
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first=31 May 2010
|last=26 July 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|occupation= [[Realtor]]
}}
'''Adam''', played by Vlach Ashton, is a realtor who was once involved with [[Loretta Jones]]. [[Frankie Osborne]] hears Loretta making an appointment to see a realtor, and tells her son [[Jake Dean]], who is dating Loretta. Jake follows her, assuming they're going to look for a home, but finds Adam and Loretta arguing. Loretta tells Jake that Adam has been harassing her. The next day, Jake confronts Adam, but Adam warns him about Loretta, saying she tried to control him, threatened to kill him, still watches him, and had told him about Jake months ago, in hopes that Adam would take her back. A few days later, Adam showed up in Chester to once again warn Jake about Loretta, and showed him the restraining order he had taken out against her. Adam was last seen in late July, when [[Nancy Hayton]] met with him to confirm Jake's accusations against Loretta.
{{-}}

==DI Andrews==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= DI Andrews
|portrayer=Maggie Norris 
|introducer=[[Lucy Allan (producer)|Lucy Allan]]
|years=2010
|first=25 May 2010 
|last=16 July 2010 
Classification Former; recurring 
|classification= Former; recurring 
|Occupation= Police Officer 
}}
DI Andrews, played by Maggie Norris, is a Police Officer investigating Calvin Valentine's shooting. She arrives after he passes away. She interviews all of the suspects straight after the shooting. She takes Carmel Valentine's dress away for examining. On Friday 28 May 2010, Malachy Fisher (Glen Wallace) confessed to her that he shot Calvin. A month later she formally charges Gaz Bennett of murdering Calvin when he was found with a gun that was linked to Calvin's murder.
{{-}}

==Gabby Sharpe==
{{Main|Gabby Sharpe}}
'''Gabby Sharpe''', played by former ''[[Footballers Wives]]'' actress [[Phina Oruche]], made her first on-screen appearance on 18 June 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a223625/2845-raes-attacked.html|title=2845: Rae's attacked|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=18 June 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oruche's casting was announced on 29 March 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a211351/footballers-wives-actress-joins-hollyoaks.html|title=Exclusive: 'Footballers' Wives' actress joins 'Hollyoaks'|first=Kris|last=Green|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=29 March 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gabby was the first character created and introduced as part of Marquess' rejuvenation of the serial.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a213947/hollyoaks-announces-raft-of-new-castings.html|title='Hollyoaks' announces raft of new castings |first=Kris|last=Green|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=12 April 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is the wife of [[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil]] (Andonis Anthony) and the mother of [[Amber Sharpe|Amber]] (Lydia Lloyd-Henry) and [[Taylor Sharpe|Taylor]] (Shaun Blackstock).&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; Gabby has been described as &quot;strong yet nurturing&quot; and &quot;extremely tolerant&quot; unless pushed to breaking point.&lt;ref name=&quot;official&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/cast/girls/gabbysharpe.html|title=Gabby Sharpe (played by Phina Oruche)|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=([[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]])|author=|date=June 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Amber Sharpe==
{{Main|Amber Sharpe}}
'''Amber Sharpe''', played by Lydia Lloyd-Henry, made her first on-screen appearance on 21 June 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a227050/2846-tony-rushes-to-help-gabby.html|title=2846: Tony rushes to help Gabby|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=21 June 2010|accessdate=26 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lloyd-Henry's casting was announced on 12 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; She is the daughter of [[Gabby Sharpe|Gabby]] and [[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil Sharpe]] and the sister of [[Taylor Sharpe|Taylor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; Amber has been described as &quot;a real live wire&quot; and a &quot;spitfire&quot; who questions everything.&lt;ref name=&quot;e4&quot;&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/cast/girls/ambersharpe.html|title=Amber Sharpe (played by Lydia Lloyd Henry)|publisher=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|work=[[Hollyoaks]]|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Taylor Sharpe==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Taylor Sharpe
|portrayer=Shaun Blackstock
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|first=21 June 2010
|last=17 December 2010
|years=2010
|born= May 1994
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
|father=[[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil Sharpe]]
|mother=[[Gabby Sharpe]]
|sisters=[[Amber Sharpe]]
|halfbrothers=[[Arlo Davenport]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tré Davenport]]
|nieces=Bella Sharpe 
}}
'''Taylor Sharpe''', played by Shaun Blackstock, is the son of [[Gabby Sharpe|Gabby]] and [[#Phil Sharpe|Phil Sharpe]].

[[Tony Hutchinson]], who helps Gabby after she is run over, tries to support Taylor and Amber whilst Gabby is in hospital. Taylor is initially not sure about Tony but warms to him when they have a cooking lesson. Taylor and Amber are surprised when they return home and find their belongings missing, not realising their mother had planned to run away with them while their father was gone. They Sharpes eventually move in with Tony. Taylor befriends [[Duncan Button]] and invites him home to play computer games. However, Taylor pushes Duncan out after he discovers Duncan's attraction for Gabby. Taylor later urges Gabby and Tony to get together, which they do.

Taylor becomes friends with [[Arlo Davenport]] and is invited to his house, where he meets Arlo's mother [[Helen Davenport|Helen]] and younger brother [[Tré Davenport|Tré]]. Taylor is shocked when Phil arrives at Arlo's house and is referred to as Arlo's father. Phil takes Taylor home and makes him swear not to say anything. However, Taylor tries to tell Amber, who refuses to believe him. Taylor tells Gabby and Phil admits everything. The Davenports discover the truth and Taylor and Arlo agree to be friends. However, Taylor becomes jealous when Arlo takes [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead O'Connor]] to a school dance. The Sharpes leave Hollyoaks to live with Gabby's father after the O'Connors discover Amber's obsession with [[Rob O'Connor]].
{{-}}

==Phil Sharpe==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Phil Sharpe
|portrayer=Andonis Anthony
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|first=25 June 2010
|last=13 December 2010
|years=2010
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|daughters=[[Amber Sharpe]]
|sons=[[Arlo Davenport]]&lt;br&gt;[[Taylor Sharpe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tré Davenport]]
|wife=[[Gabby Sharpe]]
|granddaughters = Bella Sharpe
}}
'''Phil Sharpe''', played by Andonis Anthony, is the husband of [[Gabby Sharpe]] who first appears when he visits his wife in hospital following an accident on 25 June 2010.

Phil is next seen when he and Gabby have dinner at Il Gnosh. However, the night does not end well when Phil loses his temper. After this, Gabby, who had already been planning to leave Phil, moves out and into [[Tony Hutchinson]]'s home in Hollyoaks with [[Amber Sharpe|Amber]] and [[Taylor Sharpe|Taylor]]. Amber calls Phil after catching Tony and Gabby kissing, and tells him they are having an affair. Phil argues with Gabby and Tony and ends up punching Tony. Phil is annoyed and embarrassed after he finds out that Amber was lying and that they only kissed that night. Taylor is shocked when Phil arrives at [[Arlo Davenport]]'s house, and is called 'daddy' by Arlo's younger brother [[Tré Davenport|Tré]]. Taylor soon realises that Phil has another family, and storms out. Phil makes Taylor keep quiet, but he eventually tells Amber, Tony and Gabby. Phil pleads for his family to forgive him, but after learning of Amber's pregnancy, he rejects his children.
{{-}}

==Rose Townsend==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Rose Townsend
|portrayer=[[Libby Davison]]
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|first= 28 June 2010
|last=6 August 2010
|years=2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|brothers=[[Des Townsend]]
}}
'''Rose Townsend''', played by [[Libby Davison]], is the older sister of [[Des Townsend]]. Rose brought up Des after their parents passed away. Des's girlfriend [[Jacqui McQueen]] sees Rose and Des alone and assumes they are having an affair. Des explains their relationship and Rose goes to the McQueens for tea and seems to enjoy herself. Rose is disturbed to learn Jacqui had a mixed-race sister, [[Tina Reilly]], and it is revealed Rose and Des share racist views. Rose succeeds in her efforts to turn Des against Asian [[Ravi Roy]]. When Des is still slightly ambivalent, Rose threatens to disown him. She then helps him in his efforts to plant a smoke bomb inside Ravi's restaurant, Relish. She was again much more angry when Des proposed to Jacqui. To her relief, Jacqui declines his proposal when discovering about his racist attacks and this causes him to subsequently leave the village. Rose is not seen again.
{{-}}

==Carl Costello==
{{Main|Carl Costello}}
'''Carl Costello''', played by former ''[[Emmerdale]]'' actor [[Paul Opacic]], made his first on-screen appearance on 19 July 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a234167/2866-carmels-stunned-by-theresas-revelation.html|title=2866: Carmel's stunned by Theresa's revelation|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=19 July 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Opacic's casting was announced on 12 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; He is the husband of [[Heidi Costello|Heidi]] ([[Kim Tiddy]]) and the father of [[Jem Costello|Jem]] (Helen Russell-Clark), [[Riley Costello|Riley]] (Rob Norbury), [[Seth Costello|Seth]] (Miles Higson)&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; and [[Jasmine Costello|Jasmine]] ([[Victoria Atkin]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title='Hollyoaks' to tackle Gender Dysphoria|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a234896/hollyoaks-to-tackle-gender-dysphoria.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=2010-12-01|date=1 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carl has been described as a &quot;self-assured smooth operator who's charming, but will play things underhand&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Carl Costello (played by Paul Opacic)|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/cast/boys/carlcostello.html|work=[[E4 (channel){{!}}E4]]|publisher=([[Channel 4{{!}}Channel 4 Television Corporation]])|accessdate=2010-11-14|date=July 2010&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uEimjdpE|archivedate=14 November 2010 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Seth Costello ==
{{Main|Seth Costello}}

==Riley Costello==
{{Main|Riley Costello}}
'''Riley Costello''', played by former ''[[Grange Hill]]'' actor Rob Norbury, made his first on-screen appearance on 20 July 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a234178/2867-the-costellos-cause-a-stir-in-the-village.html |title=2867: The Costellos cause a stir in the village |work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=20 July 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Norbury's casting was announced on 12 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; He is the son of [[Carl Costello|Carl]] ([[Paul Opacic]]) and [[Heidi Costello]] ([[Kim Tiddy]]) and the brother of [[Jem Costello|Jem]] (Helen Russell-Clark), [[Seth Costello|Seth]] (Miles Higson)&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; and [[Jasmine Costello|Jasmine]] ([[Victoria Atkin]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;/&gt; Riley has been described as a &quot;Jack-the-lad&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/scoop/a237626/kim-tiddy-interview-exclusive-part-two.html |title=Kim Tiddy Interview Exclusive - Part Two |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |first=Kris |last=Green |date=9 July 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a &quot;lothario&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/interviews/2010/robnorbury.html |title=Interview with Rob Norbury (Riley Costello) |work=[[Hollyoaks]] |publisher=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|date=July 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Heidi Costello==
{{Main|Heidi Costello}}
'''Heidi Costello''', played by former ''[[The Bill]]'' actress [[Kim Tiddy]], made her first on-screen appearance on 20 July 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Green&quot;/&gt; Tiddy's casting was announced on 12 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; She is the wife of [[Carl Costello]] ([[Paul Opacic]]) and the mother of [[Riley Costello|Riley]] (Rob Norbury), [[Seth Costello|Seth]] (Miles Higson)&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; and [[Jasmine Costello|Jasmine]] ([[Victoria Atkin]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;/&gt; Heidi has been described as &quot;strong, glamorous and slightly insecure&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/interviews/a237611/kim-tiddy-heidi-costello-hollyoaks.html|title=Kim Tiddy (Heidi Costello, 'Hollyoaks')|date=9 July 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mitzeee==
{{Main|Mitzeee}}
'''Anne &quot;Mitzeee&quot; Minniver''', played by [[Rachel Shenton]], made her first on-screen appearance on 23 July 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a234212/2870-carls-hiding-a-secret.html|title=2870: Carl's hiding a secret|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=23 July 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shenton's casting was announced on 12 April 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; She is the cousin of [[Heidi Costello]] ([[Kim Tiddy]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;raft&quot;/&gt; Mitzeee was created by Marquess for a different television series which was never commissioned and instead introduced her to ''Hollyoaks''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Murphy|first=Steven|title=Inside Soap meets the Producers - Hollyoaks|url=http://www.insidesoap.co.uk|work=[[Inside Soap]], Issue 11-17 Sept 2010|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=2010-12-01|date=11 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; She has been described as an &quot;aspiring glamour model&quot; who is likely to cause havoc in the village.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/cast/girls/mitzeee.html|title=Mitzeee (played by Rachel Shenton)|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=([[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]])|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Kevin Smith==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Kevin Smith
|portrayer= [[Cameron Crighton]]
|creator=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first= 29 July 2010
|last= 4 November 2010
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
|occupation= [[Student]]
}}
'''Kevin Smith''', played by [[Cameron Crighton]], first appeared on 29 July 2010. He arrives during a storyline with [[Elliot Bevan]], where Kevin tries to convince everyone he is an alien.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=[[Inside Soap]]|date=10–16 July 2010|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|pages=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is set to become a fresher student along with [[Lee Hunter]], [[Doug Carter]], [[Jamil Fadel]] and [[Leanne Holiday]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=Watch Video - Interview: Cameron Crighton|url=http://www.e4.com/video/goUQqfADq2dKCwWiVxSDQ/play.e4|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=[[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]]|accessdate=2010-07-15|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Information on the character first surfaced during Paul Marquess' reinvention of the serial. The  storyline was publicised by the media, who described it as an odd alien storyline.&lt;ref name=&quot;alien&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|last=Love|first=Ryan|title=Hollyoaks character 'to befriend alien'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a223753/hollyoaks-character-to-befriend-alien.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=21 July 2010|date=6 June 2009&lt;!--|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uGkhoiqp|archivedate=15 November 2010--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; At that point in time there was no official confirmation of the storyline being true, until actress [[Hollie-Jay Bowes]] who played [[Michaela McQueen]] confirmed details of the plot, which contributed in her dismisal from the serial.&lt;ref name=&quot;sack&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=Hollie-Jay Bowes sacked from 'Hollyoaks'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a232110/hollie-jay-bowes-sacked-from-hollyoaks.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=2010-09-12|date=25 June 2010&lt;!--|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uGka0p24|archivedate=15 November 2010--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Actor Cameron Crighton was cast in the role and he expressed his delight to be joining a show that was widely known and stated he it took ages to sink in.&lt;ref name=&quot;vid&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Watch video - Interview: Cameron Crighton|url=http://www.e4.com/video/goUQqfADq2dKCwWiVxSDQ/play.e4|work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|publisher=([[Channel 4|Channel 4 Television Corporation]])|accessdate=21 July 2010|date=July 2010&lt;!--|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uGkRRe7M|archivedate=15 November 2010--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later revealed that Crighton had finished filming with the serial by September 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Littlejohn|first=Georgina|title=Hollyoaks' Carley Stenson says goodbye to the soap with fancy dress cast party in Liverpool|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/tvshowbiz/article-1311304/Hollyoaks-Carley-Stenson-says-goodbye-soap-fancy-dress-cast-party-Liverpool.html?ito=feeds-newsxml|work=[[Daily Mail]]|publisher=([[Associated Newspapers{{!}}Associated Newspapers Ltd]])|accessdate=2010-09-13|date=12 September 2010&lt;!--|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uGkUvPX3|archivedate=15 November 2010--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Crighton's final scenes were due to be aired on the 9 November 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;soapshow&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Hollyoaks Catch Up|url=http://www.thesoapshow.com/soaps/hollyoaks-catch-up.htm|work=Thesoapshow.com|publisher=The Soap Show|accessdate=2010-11-14&lt;!--|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5uGkCwoFa|archivedate=15 November 2010--&gt;|date=1 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; But they did not make the final cut.

On his arrival, after he befriends [[Elliot Bevan]] he begins telling him that he is desperate to get home to his planet which he claims to have been sent from. [[Nancy Hayton]] and [[Kris Fisher]] have a hard time believing this. He later makes friends with a young [[Tom Cunningham]] and cheers him up and helping him believe in life after death. In Fresher's week, Kevin and Doug clash, meanwhile the other students think he is odd. He sees Leanne and Doug kiss and decides to tell Lee of their infidelity. Doug then finds out some secrets about Kevin's past. Despite his housemates finding out the truth, Kevin still keeps up the pretence of being an alien and attempts to build a [[Beacon]], with the help of Elliot, in order for his parents to find him. Elliot finds Kevin's birth certificate and works out the truth. When the beacon is finally turned on he gives Tom a telescope as a gift. Kevin also secures Elliot a new job at [[NASA]] before leaving Hollyoaks.
{{-}}

==Jason Costello==
{{Main|Jasmine Costello}}
'''Jason Costello''', played by [[Victoria Atkin]], made her first on-screen appearance on 2 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a250142/2876-des-proposes-to-jacqui.html|title=2876: Des proposes to Jacqui|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=2 August 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Atkins's casting was announced on 1 July 2010 where it was revealed that &quot;Jasmine&quot; would suffer from [[Gender Identity Disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;/&gt; He is the son of [[Carl Costello|Carl]] ([[Paul Opacic]]) and [[Heidi Costello]] ([[Kim Tiddy]]), the brother of [[Jem Costello|Jem]] (Helen Russell-Clark) and [[Riley Costello|Riley]] (Rob Norbury) and the twin of [[Seth Costello|Seth]] (Miles Higson).&lt;ref name=&quot;jas&quot;/&gt; &quot;Jasmine&quot; has been described as a &quot;cosseted, overly protected little girl&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/cast/girls/jasminecostello.html|work=[[Hollyoaks]]|publisher=[[E4 (channel)|E4]]|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Bart McQueen==
{{Main|Bart McQueen}}
'''Bart McQueen''', played by [[Jonny Clarke]], made his first on-screen appearance on 4 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a250150/2878-bart-is-taken-in-by-the-mcqueens.html|title=2878: Bart is taken in by the McQueens|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=4 August 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clarke's casting was announced on 25 June 2010, as an extension of the established [[McQueen family]].&lt;ref name=&quot;confirms&quot;&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a233106/hollyoaks-confirms-more-new-cast.html|title='Hollyoaks' confirms more new cast|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kris|last=Green|date=25 June 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bart is named after ''[[The Simpsons]]'' character [[Bart Simpson]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/interviews/a220221/paul-marquess-producer-hollyoaks.html |title=Paul Marquess (Producer, Hollyoaks) |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]] |first=Kris |last=Green |date=18 May 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is described as &quot;lad's lad&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.e4.com/hollyoaks/later/2010/blogs/jonnyclarke.html |title=Interview with Jonny Clarke (Bart McQueen) |work=[[E4 (channel)|E4]] |publisher=([[Channel 4 Television Corporation]]) |date=25 October 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Brendan Brady==
{{Main|Brendan Brady}}
'''Brendan Brady''', played by Irish actor [[Emmett J. Scanlan]], made his first on-screen appearance on 5 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a250151/2879-zak-threatens-to-contact-the-police.html|title=2879: Zak threatens to contact the police|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|date=5 August 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scanlan's casting was announced on 25 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;confirms&quot;/&gt; He is the brother of [[Cheryl Brady]] ([[Bronagh Waugh]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;confirms&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;new bad boy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a215499/new-bad-boy-for-hollyoaks.html |title=New bad boy for Hollyoaks |work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |author=Daniel Kilkelly and Kris Green |date=20 April 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5td4LPnLr|archivedate=20 October 2010 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brendan has been described as a &quot;dodgy dealer&quot; and &quot;a complex character&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://holysoap.five.tv/hollyoaks/news/brendans-just-misunderstood-9806 |title=Brendan's just misunderstood! |work=[[Holy Soap]] |publisher=([[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5 Broadcasting]]) |date=17 September |accessdate=2010-12-01&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5td2XhKwI|archivedate=20 October 2010 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Veronica==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Veronica
|portrayer= Lynsey McLaren
|introducer= [[Paul Marquess]]
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|years=2010
|first= 6 August 2010
|last = 8 October 2010
}}
'''Veronica''', played by Lynsey McLaren, first appeared on 9 August 2010. She is first seen outside The Dog in the Pond when [[Brendan Brady]] catches her eye. Brendan offers to buy her a drink and she accepts. She then gets talking to [[Malachy Fisher]] and they share a couple of drinks together. She later goes home with Malachy, kissing him and they head upstairs. She ties him to his bed, tricking him into thinking they were about to have sex, when she actually did it to trap him whilst she could steal money and items of jewellery from the McQueens. She admits Malachy is a nice person, kissing him before leaving him tied up.&lt;ref name=&quot;wavee&quot;/&gt; Veronica steals everything from the McQueen home then went on to rob Evissa. Malachy manages to track her down, and ties her up. She plays on his marital problems with [[Mercedes McQueen]] to get him to leave the keys to the van full of stolen goods, but later, he sends Mercedes to the address, and she attacks Veronica for helping break up her marriage. Brendan, who had been working with Veronica, shows up later, and Veronica berates him for getting her involved with insane Mercedes.

Veronica later blackmails Brendan, who sets her up to get arrested by [[Carmel Valentine]]. She makes another appearance when Brendan uses her to try and split up [[Rae Wilson]] and [[Ste Hay]].
{{-}}

==Trish Minniver==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Trish Minniver
|portrayer= Paula Wolfenden
|creator=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010—
|first= 10 August 2010
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Present; recurring]]
|daughters=[[Mitzeee Minniver]]
|nieces= [[Heidi Costello]]&lt;br&gt;Wendy Blissett
|halfsisters=Joan Blisset
|relatives=[[Riley Costello]]&lt;br&gt;[[Seth Costello]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jason Costello]]&lt;br&gt; Bobby
|born=10 August 1971
}}
'''Trish Minniver''', played by Paula Wolfenden, is the mother of [[Mitzeee Minniver]], who arrives on her birthday to see her family. It is revealed that she has bitter feelings towards her niece &quot;that she treated like a sister&quot; [[Heidi Costello]], this is because Trish used to date [[Carl Costello]] before he left her for Heidi. She appears to be using her daughter Mitzeee in her plan to make Carl and his familys life hell. Trish reappears at Christmas 2010 with Mitzeee and makes peace with Heidi and Carl, before befriending [[Myra McQueen]]. Trish encourages Heidi to be more accepting of her transgender son [[Jason Costello]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wavee&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|title=Hollyoaks - Waveguide TV and Radio News|url=http://www.waveguide.co.uk/hollyoaks.htm|work=Waveguide|accessdate=28 July 2010|date=26 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 2011 Mitzeee is shocked to discover tat Ethan has arrested Trish, and blackmails her into getting Warren to confess to the murder of [[Louise Summers]] or Trish will be sent down for 2 year's. However this later backfires and Trish is released without charge.
{{-}}

==Alistair Longford==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name= Alistair Longford
|portrayer= Terence Harvey
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first= 24 August 2010
|last=  24 September 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|born= 1938
|death= 2011
|occupation= Retired
|sons=Teddy Longford
|mother=[[Blanche Longford]]
|granddaughters=[[India Longford]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Texas Longford]]
|wife=Pamela Longford&lt;br&gt; [[Cindy Hutchinson]] (2010&amp;ndash;11)
}}
'''Alistair Longford''', played by Terence Harvey, was a wealthy pensioner and grandfather of [[Texas Longford|Texas]] and [[India Longford]] who first appears when he chokes on food at Il Gnosh. He is saved by [[Myra McQueen]] using the [[Heimlich maneuver]]. Myra tells Alistair that [[Cindy Hutchinson]] was responsible for saving him, not realising his reward. Believing Cindy was responsible, Alistair gives Cindy a handful of £50 notes. This leaves Myra feeling insolent and upset. Alistair and Cindy grow closer until they begin a relationship.

Alistair charms Cindy. However, after she realises that he is India's grandfather, she leaves. After this event, he visits his granddaughters to discuss their allowance and Texas's spending issues. The next day, India tells Cindy that her grandfather lives in [[Sandbanks]], a highly upmarket area. Cindy then realises that Alistair is a millionaire and returns to him to try and rekindle their relationship. Just then, Alistair asks Cindy to marry him. Cindy is left gobsmacked and speechless. After numerous attempts to sabotage the wedding from his mother [[Blanche Longford|Blanche]], Alistair and Cindy marry and leave for their honeymoon.

Cindy returns to Hollyoaks on 9 March 2011 and explains that during their honeymoon in [[Switzerland]], Alistair fell of an [[Mountain|Alp]] and died.
{{-}}

{{-}}

==Sinead O'Connor==
{{Main|Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)}}
'''Sinead O'Connor''', played by [[Over the Rainbow (2010 TV series)|Over the Rainbow]] contestant [[Stephanie Davis (actor)|Stephanie Davis]], made her first on-screen appearance on 1 September 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;impact&quot;/&gt; Davis casting was announced on 16 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a228059/hollyoaks-unveils-third-new-family.html|title='Hollyoaks' unveils third new family|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|author=Kilkelly, Daniel|date=16 June 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is the daughter of [[Rob O'Connor]] (Gary Cargill), stepdaughter of [[Diane O'Connor|Diane]] ([[Alexandra Fletcher]]) and the sister of [[Finn O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Finn]] (Connor Wilkinson).&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt; Sinead has been described as very mischievous and a &quot;typical teenager&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;stephanie&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/interviews/a263126/stephanie-davis-sinead-oconnor-hollyoaks.html |title=Stephanie Davis (Sinead O'Connor, Hollyoaks) |work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|first=Daniel |last=Kilkelly |date=27 August 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Finn O'Connor==
{{Main|Finn O'Connor (Hollyoaks)}}
'''Finn O'Connor''', played by Connor Wilkinson, made his first on-screen appearance on 1 September 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;impact&quot;&gt;{{cite gf,h back int the day bwe dance like t hisnews|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a263954/2898-sinead-vows-to-make-an-impact.html|title=2898: Sinead vows to make an impact|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|author=Kilkelly, Daniel|date=1 September 2010|accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wilkinson's casting was announced on 16 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt; He is the son of [[Rob O'Connor]] (Gary Cargill), stepson of [[Diane O'Connor|Diane]] ([[Alexandra Fletcher]]) and the brother of [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead]] ([[Stephanie Davis (actor)|Stephanie Davis]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt;

==Diane O'Connor==
{{Main|Diane O'Connor}}
'''Diane O'Connor''', played by former [[Brookside]] [[Alexandra Fletcher]], made her first on-screen appearance on 1 September 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;impact&quot;/&gt; Fletcher's casting was announced on 16 June 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt; She is the wife of [[Rob O'Connor]] (Gary Cargill) and the stepmother of [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead]] ([[Stephanie Davis (actor)|Stephanie Davis]]) and [[Finn O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Finn]] (Connor Wilkinson).&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt; Diane has been described as desperate for a child of her own.&lt;ref name=&quot;third family&quot;/&gt;

==Rob O'Connor==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name = Rob O'Connor
|portrayer = Gary Cargill
|introducer = [[Paul Marquess]]
|years = 2010–2011
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
|first = 1 September 2010
|last = 10 January 2011
|wife = [[Diane O'Connor]]
|romances=Morag
|sons = [[Finn O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Finn O'Connor]]
|daughters = [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead O'Connor]]
|granddaughters = Bella Sharpe
|occupation= [[Headmaster]]
}}
'''Robert &quot;Rob&quot; O'Connor''', played by Gary Cargill, is a character who arrived on 1 September 2010 along with the rest of his family. Rob and his family move to Hollyoaks due to his new job as deputy headmaster. However, soon after, daughter [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead O'Connor]] knocks the headteacher unconscious with the water bucket trick. Rob is promoted to acting head. Rob's wife [[Diane O'Connor|Diane]] steals a baby from a hospital. With the help of [[Lynsey Nolan]] and Sinead, Rob convinces Diane to give the baby back. 

[[Amber Sharpe]] becomes pregnant by Finn, but starts to write in her diary saying that Rob is the father. Amber kisses Rob, which is seen by [[Eva Strong]]. Eva then steals Ambers diary and threatens to blackmail him with it. Feeling sorry for Rob, Eva's daughter [[Anita Roy]] decides to give him the diary so he can dispose of it, but Anita is unaware that Eva had taken out the important pages. Anita takes Rob back to her flat to try find the missing pages, Eva returns home and finds Rob alone in the flat with Anita, Eva then calls the police and has Rob arrested. Sinead is devastated that he is arrested, and Diane informs Sinead that Rob started seeing her when she was his 15-year-old student. Diane also tells her that Sinead and Finn's real mother is still alive. Sinead is furious with Rob for not telling her. Diane and Rob decide to split up and Rob plans to take Sinead and Finn away with him, but Sinead decides to stay with Diane, so Rob leaves.
{{-}}

==Trent Harvard==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Trent Harvard 
|portrayer=Olivier Blanc 
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]] 
|years=2010 
|first= 26 August 2010 
|last = 10 September 2010 
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
}}

Trent Harvard is a character who arrived during Hollyoaks: Freshers, played by Olivier Blanc. It is soon revealed that he used to date India Longford. He is described as &quot;nasty and manipulative&quot; and is set to cause trouble for Texas Longford.[62]

Trent notices Texas at a music festival after she is thrown out. He gets her free entry and they begin to discuss his failed relationship with India. They begin to flirt and it becomes apparent they have an attraction. India is annoyed at Texas for spending time with her ex. He asks Texas to visit him in his hotel room, they spend the night together. Trent starts blackmailing Texas, that if she doesn't give him money, he will show a video of him and Texas having sex to India.

Texas fools him by handing him a envelope filled with paper instead of money. After this he Emails India the video footage. She and Texas argue, but she forgives her knowing Trent is trying to come between them.
{{-}}

==Viv==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Viv
|portrayer=Venetia Fawcett 
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|Duration 2010 
|first= 2 September 2010 
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
}}

Vivienne is a character whom arrives during Hollyoaks: Freshers, played by Venetia Fawcett. Viv is described as wanting to show everyone a good time, but not who she makes out to be.[63]

When Viv hitchhikes, the male students take an instant liking to her. Charlotte however is wary of her, later Jamil takes a dislike to her. Charlotte and Viv kiss, although Charlotte feels intimidated. Charlotte later decides to ignore her and have a good time. Viv can speak French and English. Viv then tries to steal from Charlotte, but Dave ruins her plan. She steals Doug's camper van. She later returns and tries to get Charlotte to leave with her, but Charlotte punches her and they fight. Viv then leaves.
{{-}}

==Jamil Fadel==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Jamil Fadel
|portrayer=Sikander Malik
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010–11
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters#Past characters|Former; regular]]
|first= 13 September 2010
|last= 9 September 2011
|occupation= [[Student]]/radio presenter
|brothers=Rashad Fadel
}}
'''Jamil Fadel''', played by Sikander Malik, arrived in September 2010 as part of the new students. Jamil is characterised as being &quot;very nice&quot;. Jamil arrives in Hollyoaks along with [[Doug Carter]] after their trip to France. He moves into Student Halls alongside Doug, [[Jem Costello]], [[Lee Hunter]], [[Leanne Holiday]], [[Kevin Smith]] and [[Darren Osborne]]. Jamil soon asks [[Charlotte Lau]] out on a date, but is embarrassed when he realises that she is a lesbian. After failed attempts with Charlotte, [[India Longford]] sleeps with Jamil following their growing friendship. Meanwhile, [[Brendan Brady]] steals goods from the halls in return for drugs which he gives to Doug Carter. Later, Jamil is confronted by a woman. She is revealed to be Jamil's wife, [[Lanika Fadel]]. Jamil reveals that he and Lanika are however not legally married, as he fled on the wedding day. After talking, Lanika and Jamil agree to get married. However, he lies to his friends by saying it was an arranged marriage. Jamil and Lanika agree not to go through with the wedding. Jamil has a one night stand with [[Mercedes Fisher]] and is shocked when he discovers she may be HIV positive. He has a brief relationship with [[Texas Longford]] although she soon after ends it. Jamil and Lee are offered jobs as radio presenters from the college dean and they later hire nurse [[Lynsey Nolan]] as the agony aunt for their show thus putting her in great danger as murderer [[Silas Blissett]] is not impressed with her advice.

In September, he has a go at his housemates for their selfish behaviour and soon, because of what he said, decides to leave his course and work for his brother. His housemates catch up with him, make amends and see him off.

Malik revealed via Twitter on June 23 that he was departing Hollyoaks after a year on screen, and will depart the series on 9 September 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jamil departure&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a326453/hollyoaks-actor-confirms-jamil-departure.html|title='Hollyoaks' actor confirms Jamil departure|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=23 June 2011|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|accessdate=23 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{-}}

==Doug Carter==
{{Main|Doug Carter}}
'''Doug Carter''', played by [[PJ Brennan]] initially appears in the programme's online spin-off series [[Hollyoaks: Freshers]], before debuting in the main series in the episode airing 13 September 2010. He left on 17 September before returning on 13 January 2011, this time as a regular. He was introducd as an American character and one of the new student group for September 2011. His storylines have included drug dealing and a relationship with Jenny which ended in her murder at the hands of serial killer. Doug has been described as a fan favourite.
{{-}}

==Eileen Brady==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Eileen Brady
|portrayer=Rachel Doherty
|creator=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010, 2011
|first= 27 September 2010
|last=2 August 2011 
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Present; recurring]]
|husband=[[Brendan Brady]]
|sons= Declan Brady&lt;br&gt;Paddy Brady
|daughters= Niamh Brady
|nephews=[[Macca (Hollyoaks)|Macca]]
}}

'''Eileen Brady''', played by Rachel Doherty, arrived on 27 September. She is the wife of [[Brendan Brady]]. She reveals that she and Brendan are separated as he cheated on her. Eileen pushes Brendan to give her money for their ill son, who needs an operation. After receiving the money, [[Malachy Fisher]] informs her that Brendan's sister [[Cheryl Brady|Cheryl]] was mugged, and money was stolen, and that he suspects Brendan. Eileen returns to let [[Declan Brady]] (Jay Duffy) stay with Brendan whilst she is on holiday. She walks in on Brendan and [[Ste Hay]] ([[Kieron Richardson]]) having slept together.

{{-}}

==Arlo Davenport==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Arlo Davenport
|portrayer=[[Travis Yates]]
|creator=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first= 12 October 2010
|last= 14 December 2010
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
|occupation= Student
|born= 20 February 1995
|mother=Helen Davenport
|father=[[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil Sharpe]]
|brothers=Tré Davenport
|halfsisters=[[Amber Sharpe]]
|halfbrothers=[[Taylor Sharpe]]
|nieces=Bella Sharpe 
}}
'''Arlo Davenport''', played by [[Travis Yates]], arrived on 11 October 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;opi&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=PHA Model &amp; Casting|url=http://www.pha-agency.co.uk/casting/youth/news/article.aspx?ID=5188|work=pha-agency.co.uk|publisher=(PHA Agency)|accessdate=2010-06-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yates' casting was announced in April 2010 at the same time as his on-screen half-sister [[Amber Sharpe]] and it was also revealed that Arlo is a regular character.&lt;ref name=&quot;opi&quot;/&gt;

Arlo makes friends with Taylor Sharpe whilst at school, he later invites him around for dinner. He is shocked when Taylor's father turns out to be his father too.&lt;ref name=&quot;wavess&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Waveguide - Hollyoaks|url=http://www.waveguide.co.uk/hollyoaks.htm|work=waveguide.co.uk|accessdate=2010-09-29|date=29 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Taylor and Arlo initially become friends, but when Arlo catches Taylor in a clinch with his love interest [[Sinead O'Connor (Hollyoaks)|Sinead O'Connor]], he tells Taylor he never wants to see him again.
{{-}}

==Macca==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Macca
|portrayer=Drew Dillon
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first= 12 October 2010
|last= 22 November 2010
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|aunts=[[Eileen Brady]]
|cousins=[[Declan Brady]]&lt;br&gt; Paddy Brady &lt;br&gt; Niamh Brady
}}
'''Macca''', played by Drew Dillon, arrived on 12 October 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Dillon|first=Drew|title=Drew Dillon Official|url=http://drewdillon.co.uk/|work=drewdillon.co.uk|accessdate=2010-09-19|date=7 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The nephew of [[Brendan Brady]]'s wife [[Eileen Brady|Eileen]]. It becomes clear that Macca had been having an affair with Brendan. Macca becomes friends with [[Ste Hay]] Brendan's new secret boyfriend. Brendan has Macca beaten up and tells everyone he went back home to Ireland. Macca returns a few weeks later at the hospital where he has been staying since the beating. Brendan threatens Macca to go home however Macca makes it clear he is not going anywhere as he is still in love with Brendan. Macca takes Ste to a gay bar where they kiss.
{{-}}

==Danny Houston==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
||name=Danny Houston
|portrayer=[[Darren Day]]
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first= 19 October 2010
|last= 28 December 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|occupation= Nightclub owner (2010)
|death=28 December 2010
}}
'''Danny Houston''', played by [[Darren Day]], is a friend of [[Brendan Brady]] ([[Emmett J. Scanlan]]) and partner in ownership of club Chez Chez with Brendan's sister [[Cheryl Brady]] ([[Bronagh Waugh]]). He first appeared on 19 October 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;wr&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|last=Love|first=Ryan|title=Darren Day joins 'Hollyoaks'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a277965/darren-day-joins-hollyoaks.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=21 September 2010|date=21 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The character was first announced in September 2010, with [[West End theatre|London West End]] star Darren Day being cast in the role.&lt;ref name=&quot;darren interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/interviews/a282461/darren-day-danny-houston-hollyoaks.html |title=Darren Day (Danny Houston, 'Hollyoaks') |first=Daniel |last=Kilkelly |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |date=16 October 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/scoop/a282462/more-hollyoaks-chat-from-darren-day.html |title=More 'Hollyoaks' chat from Darren Day |first=Daniel |last=Kilkelly |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |date=16 October 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was revealed that Danny would appear in only one episode, returning later in the year.&lt;ref name=&quot;darren interview&quot;/&gt; Of his casting and character, Day stated, &quot;I've really enjoyed filming with ''Hollyoaks'' and I'm excited about coming back. Danny is the type of character any actor would kill to play and the part has been made even better as I'm working with great talent such as Claire, Emmett and Bronagh.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wr&quot;/&gt; He later spoke about the character in an interview with [[Digital Spy]], &quot;There is going to be no-one badder than Danny Houston — he's about as bad as it gets and is the epitome of a soap villain really. I've been told that some soap magazines are nicknaming him Dirty Dan! For me, that's really exciting.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a282400/darren-day-teases-hollyoaks-role.html |title=Darren Day teases 'Hollyoaks' role |first=Daniel |last=Kilkelly |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |date=18 October 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Series producer Paul Marquess also described the character: &quot;Danny Houston is a dangerous but very charming character who makes an aggressive impact in his first episodes. Darren plays the part brilliantly and I’m delighted that we're able to bring him back later this year.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wr&quot;/&gt; Scanlan mentioned Day was a &quot;great addition to the cast&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/scoop/a282709/more-from-hollyoaks-star-emmett-scanlan.html |title=More from 'Hollyoaks' star Emmett Scanlan |first=Daniel |last=Kilkelly |work=[[Digital Spy]] |publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]) |date=18 October 2010 |accessdate=2010-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Storylines===

Before he arrives on-screen, Danny is made a silent partner of Chez Chez with [[Cheryl Brady]]. [[Carl Costello]] ([[Paul Opacic]]) tells [[Malachy Fisher]] ([[Glen Wallace]]) that he knows of Danny and warns him that he is potentially dangerous. Danny later accompanies Brendan and [[Jacqui McQueen]] ([[Claire Cooper]]) for lunch. After which, he asks to take Jacqui out. He offers to meet Jacqui numerous times and the pair start a relationship, annoying [[Rhys Ashworth]] ([[Andrew Moss]]). In Danny's first on-screen appearance, he arrives in Hollyoaks to visit Chez Chez. Danny becomes jealous of Jacqui and Rhys, and shouts at her, after which she angrily warns him not to talk to her as he did. He later catches Jacqui and Rhys kissing, before threatening them. Jacqui later dumps Danny and embarks on a relationship with Rhys. Danny swears he will make their lives hell.

Danny attends a poker game along with Brendan, Rhys and Jacqui and soon realises that Jacqui is cheating. Danny's thugs take Rhys and hang him upside down from a balcony. Danny tells Jacqui that she has 24 hours to pay him a sum of money or he will kill Rhys. However, Danny gives Jacqui another option, if she sleeps with Danny, he will wipe the debt and give her money she needs. Jacqui agrees to sleep with Danny, but she explains she loves Rhys. Danny decides to let Jacqui go. Danny reveals to Brendan he knows he is gay, and tells him he killed an old lover of Brendan's in the past. Brendan and Danny decide to kill [[Warren Fox]] ([[Jamie Lomas]]) after they find him in Chez Chez. Brendan, however, double crosses Danny and makes a deal with Warren. Warren and Brendan tell Danny to sign his half of Chez Chez to Brendan, to which he agrees. However, Danny threatens to reveal Brendan is gay and to kill his lover [[Ste Hay]] ([[Kieron Richardson]]). An angry Brendan lashes out and beats Danny with a hammer, which causes his death. Warren and Brendan then dump Danny's body in a river. On 18 March 2011, Ste goes fishing with Leah and Lucas at the river. When he thinks he has caught a fish, he reels his line in and discovers he has caught Danny's body at the end of his rod. Ste then calls the police.
{{-}}

==Liam McAllister==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Liam McAllister
|portrayer=Chris Overton
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first=20 October 2010
|last=30 November 2010
|spinoffs=''[[Hollyoaks Later]]''
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|brothers=Nathan McAllister
|romances=[[Jem Costello]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mitzeee Minniver]]
}}
'''Liam McAllister''', played by Chris Overton, first appeared 20 October 2010 as [[Jem Costello]]'s ex-boyfriend.&lt;ref name=&quot;ft&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Overton|first=Chris|title=Chris Overton Official|url=http://www.freewebs.com/chrisoverton/|work=chrisoverton.co.uk|accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character was mentioned several times before his appearance. Liam was a footballer, who went out with Jem. His football career ended after Jem's father [[Carl Costello]] broke Liam's leg for going out with her.

Liam arrives in Hollyoaks, where he spies on Jem's brothers, [[Riley Costello|Riley]] and [[Seth Costello|Seth]]. Jem and Liam go on a date, and Jem explains why she left him. Liam then invites Riley and Seth to a cage fighting party, where Liam is fighting. At the party, Liam and older brother Nathan plot their revenge on the Costellos. At a house party later in the night, Liam drowns Seth in a jacuzzi. However, he survives. Meanwhile, Riley is drugged. Nathan locks Seth and Riley in a cage and forces them to fight, as Carl is tied up by a noose. Seth and Riley reluctantly fight each other. However, Nathan's girlfriend Sami enters and frees them. Seth, Riley and Carl leave and run through woods. Liam and Nathan follow with a gun. They follow onto a rooftop and Nathan falls onto a spike, killing him, as Liam is arrested. Liam returns and rekindles his relationship with Jem, plotting to destroy Carl by getting [[Mitzeee Minniver]] to sleep with him. However, Liam cheats on Jem with Mitzeee. 
{{-}}

'''Nathan Mcallister'''
Nathan apears in Hollyoaks later and kidnaps carl costello. He forces seth and riley to cagefight and they do but are reluctant.
Carl escapes and him,riley and seth run through a woods, and nathan and brother liam have a gun. Then on a roof nathan is about to break carl's legs as he broe liams legs, but seth pushes nathan and he falls into an oil tank, and is impaled on  a spike, dying.

==Fern==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Fern
|portrayer=Amy Gavin
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010-11
|first=25 October 2010
|last=6 January 2011
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|spinoffs=''[[Hollyoaks Later]]''
}}
'''Fern''', played by Amy Gavin, arrived on 25 October 2010&lt;ref name=&quot;wavess&quot;/&gt; and appeared in ''[[Hollyoaks Later]]''.

Fern discovers [[Jasmine Costello]] is transgender, and threatens to reveal the secret to her family after Jasmine rejects a kiss from Fern. Fern accidentally stabs [[Bart McQueen]] during a fight and frames Jasmine's alter-ego 'Jason'. Jasmine's brother [[Seth Costello]] asks Fern to go with him as his date to the school disco, to annoy Jasmine. Later, at the school disco, Fern provokes Jasmine further by threatening to reveal her secret, yet again, on the sound system, as she had a copy of the recording on CD. Fern uses this to blackmail Jasmine to expose her secret, but along with Bart, Jasmine reports her to the police, forcing her to tell the truth about Jason. Despite Jasmine's attempt to tell the whole family about it, Seth meets Fern where she tells him all about Jasmine being Jason. Fern appears a few weeks later, when she apologises and tells Bart and Jason that she will plead guilty at her trial but only if they say that Bart's stabbing was an accident. After a heart-to-heart with Fern, Jason tells her she should come out as lesbian.
{{-}}

==Logan Fairhurst==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Logan Fairhurst
|portrayer=Thomas Sean Hughes
|creator=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first=25 October 2010
|last=1 November 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; Recurring]]
|occupation=[[Police constable]]
}}
'''Logan Fairhurst''', played by Thomas Sean Hughes, is a character that arrived on 25 October 2010, during ''Hollyoaks Later''. He takes a shine to [[Theresa McQueen]] straight away. He is a policeman and best friend of [[Riley Costello]]. 

Logan first sees Theresa whilst at the cage fighting event. He is instantly attracted to Theresa as he sees her from across the room. Riley tells her that he is a footballer. Logan and Theresa grow close during a party at a footballer's house and eventually share a kiss. However, pregnant Theresa's waters break and she goes into labour. Logan arrives at hospital to see Theresa, but Theresa's cousin [[Jacqui McQueen]] makes her end their relationship in worry they may be found out for Theresa's murder of [[Calvin Valentine]].
{{-}}

==Kathleen-Angel McQueen==
{{Infobox soap character 2 | series = Hollyoaks
| name = Kathleen-Angel McQueen
| portrayer = Uncredited
| years = 2010—
| introducer = [[Paul Marquess]]
| first = 29 October 2010
| born = 30 October 2010
| spinoffs = ''[[Hollyoaks Later]]''
| classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters#Recurring characters|Present; recurring]]
| home = [[List of Hollyoaks locations#26 Leigh Road|26 Leigh Road]]
| father = [[Calvin Valentine]]
| mother = [[Theresa McQueen]]
| grandmothers = [[Diane Valentine]]&lt;br&gt; [[Kathleen McQueen]]
| grandfathers= [[Leo Valentine]]&lt;br&gt; [[William Alexander (Hollyoaks)|William Alexander]]
| aunts= [[Sasha Valentine]]&lt;br&gt; [[Lauren Valentine]] &lt;br&gt; [[Jacqui McQueen]] &lt;br&gt; [[Mercedes McQueen]] &lt;br&gt; [[Emily Alexander (Hollyoaks)|Emily Alexander]] &lt;br&gt; [[Myra McQueen]] (great)
| uncles= [[Danny Valentine]]&lt;br&gt; [[Sonny Valentine]]
| cousins   = Bobby&lt;!--Do not add a second name - Wait until Hollyoaks or another source confirms that his second is Costello or McQueen.--&gt;
|relatives [[Niall Rafferty]] &lt;br&gt; [[Tina Reilly]] &lt;br&gt; [[Carmel Valentine]] &lt;br&gt; [[John Paul McQueen]] &lt;br&gt; [[Michaela McQueen]] &lt;br&gt; [[Bart McQueen]]  &lt;br&gt; [[Max McQueen]]
}}
'''Kathleen-Angel McQueen''' is the daughter of [[Calvin Valentine]] ([[Ricky Whittle]]) and [[Theresa McQueen]] ([[Jorgie Porter]]), who is born on-screen in episode five of ''[[Hollyoaks Later]]'', broadcast on 29 October 2010.

After her birth, Theresa's cousin [[Carmel Valentine]] ([[Gemma Merna]]) visits her in hospital and tells Theresa that she wants to raise the baby as her own daughter, as Theresa had killed Calvin months before, but Myra says no. Carmel wants to get the baby baptised as &quot;Angel Valentine&quot;, but the girl's grandmother [[Kathleen McQueen]] has other ideas, and, while Carmel is out, she locks [[Myra McQueen|Myra]] and [[Mercedes Fisher|Mercedes]] upstairs while she has her granddaughter christened as &quot;Kathleen Khloe McQueen&quot; to spite Carmel. Though they rename her Kathleen-Angel

On the 8th of February 2011, Theresa decides to leave with Kathleen-Angel and they try to leave the next day when they are kidnapped by [[Kyle Ryder]] ([[Neil Toon]]). They are held hostage in an old bank and when Theresa tries to run away and ends up on the roof, Kyle takes them back inside and ties Theresa to a chair. When Carmel and [[Ethan Scott]] turn up after a distressed phone call from Theresa, Ethan and Kyle fight and Ethan falls down a lift shaft and breaks his leg. Kyle is left holding baby Kathleen-Angel, but he is then shot by [[Warren Fox]] ([[Jamie Lomas]]) and both Kyle and Kathleen-Angel end up in the lift sharf too. Ethan passes Kathleen-Angel to Warren where she is reunited with Theresa and Carmel. Then whilst in hospital, she takes a turn for the worse and is moved to intensive care and placed on life support and Theresa blames herself for everything. Calvin then appears to Carmel as a ghost holding the baby saying she is safe. In the hospital the doctor decides to take out Kathleen-Angel's breathing tube to see if she can do it unaided. The test is successful as she begins to breathe on her own.

==Trev Costello==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Trev Costello
|portrayer=[[Scott Neal]]
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010
|first=5 November 2010
|last=31 December 2010
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; recurring]]
|occupation=[[Interior designer]]
|wife=Tanya Costello
|childrens= 3 unknown
|brothers=[[Carl Costello]]
|nephews=[[Riley Costello]]&lt;br&gt;[[Seth Costello]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jason Costello]]&lt;br&gt;Bobby (great nephew)
|nieces=[[Jem Costello]]
}}
'''Trevor &quot;Trev&quot; Costello''' (known as '''Alphonse'''), played by [[Scott Neal]], first appears on 5 November 2010.

Trev introduces himself as a camp French interior designer named Alphonse. He redecorates the kitchen and living area of the Costellos' house in [[The Dog in the Pond]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.waveguide.co.uk/hollyoaks.htm&lt;/ref&gt; His nephew [[Seth Costello]] convinces [[Duncan Button]] that Alphonse fancies him. He later appears when [[Cheryl Brady]] hires him to redecorate Chez Chez at the SU Bar. Cheryl's brother [[Brendan Brady]] is homophobic towards Alphonse and tries to attack him when Alphonse suggests Brendan is gay. Trev sleeps (still posing as Alphonse) with Cheryl. The day after his nephew [[Riley Costello]] convinces him to come clean about who he really is to Cheryl. He reveals to Cheryl his name is Trev and is married with three kids.

When Cheryl invites Trev for a drink on New Year's Eve, he agrees. However, they kiss passionately until Trev realises his mistake and regrets it causing him to leave, leaving Cheryl heartbroken. Trevor hasn't appeared since.
{{-}}

==Ethan Scott==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Ethan Scott
|portrayer=[[Craig Vye]]|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|first=8 December 2010
|born=18 July &lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.ie/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a326986/3126-the-net-closes-in-on-two-timing-ethan.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|years=2010—
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters|Present; regular]]
|home=3 Oakdale Drive
|occupation=Detective constable
}}
'''Detective Constable Ethan Scott''', played by [[Craig Vye]], first appears on 8 December 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;signings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|title='Hollyoaks' confirms three new signings|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a290960/hollyoaks-confirms-three-new-signings.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|date=2 December 2010|accessdate=2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ethan arrests and questions [[Warren Fox]], convinced he faked his own death. He goes to question [[Carmel Valentine]], but instead talks to Carmel's cousin [[Theresa McQueen]]. After he catches [[Kathleen McQueen]] trying to use fake money, Ethan takes her to the McQueen's and asks Theresa if she wants to go with him for a drink. Theresa soon takes a shine to him, but when she meets a woman named [[Liberty Savage]] at her school for enrolment, he appears at the school gates; waiting for Liberty. She then identifies him as her fiancée, leaving Theresa slightly heartbroken. Ethan continues to be suspicious of Theresa. Theresa and her daughter Kathleen Angel were kidnapped by [[Kyle Ryder]], Ethan &amp; Kyle get in a fight which leads to Ethan falling down an elevator shaft breaking his leg. Theresa then tells Ethan that she killed [[Calvin Valentine]].

Theresa and Ethan grow closer and share many kisses, but try to avoid being seen by Liberty. When Liberty's family arrive, her brother, [[Will Savage]] (James Atherton) is set up on a date with Theresa by Liberty, and the two grow very close, much to Ethan's jealousy. However, Will descovers the two kissing and at a hotel room, assaults Ethan. Will soon tells Liberty about the kiss and Liberty dumps Ethan. He and Theresa continue their relationship, but also continues a new relationship with Liberty, and struggles to juggle the two. Theresa confronts Ethan after a text he meant to send to Liberty was sent to Theresa instead. He worms his way out of the problem though. Theresa still doesn't believe him though, so she seeks the help of Dodger - together they find out not only has Ethan been cheating on Theresa with Liberty, he's also cheated on Theresa with Rae.

Liberty, Rae and Theresa begin to play with Ethan's head; with Theresa telling him that she is pregnant with his baby, Rae telling him she has an [[Sexually transmitted disease|STD]] and Liberty telling him she has told her brothers they are back together and have set a date for their wedding. Later, all three girls confront him and Ethan realises they know the truth. He tries to get out of it by telling them nobody is perfect, but they decide to get their revenge on him by gunging him and many of the residents enjoy watching him get pink gunge thrown all over him. The week after, Ethan tries to talk to Liberty but is warned off by Will. Ethan returns and drives while texting Theresa and Liberty. He knocks [[Rob Edwards (Hollyoaks)|Rob Edwards]] over and drives off. He enlists the help of Thesera who gets Warren to repair his car. Rob regains consciousness and Ethan questions him and attempts to blur his memory of the accident. He later threatens Theresa to keep quiet about what she knows.

{{-}}

==Liberty Savage==
{{Main|Liberty Savage}}
'''Liberty Savage''' is a [[fictional character]] from the British [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Hollyoaks]]'', played by actress and singer-songwriter [[Abi Phillips]]. She made her first on-screen appearance on 10&amp;nbsp;December&amp;nbsp;2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;epi3&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a290478/2970-mercedes-makes-life-tricky-for-carl.html|title=2970: Mercedes makes life tricky for Carl|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=10 December 2010|accessdate=22 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phillips was approached by ''Hollyoaks'' producers after she submitted one of her songs to be played on the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;three&quot;/&gt; Following a strong response to the song, producers invited her to audition for the role of Liberty, in which she was successful.&lt;ref name=&quot;three&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a290960/hollyoaks-confirms-three-new-signings.html|title='Hollyoaks' confirms three new signings|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|author=Kilkelly, Daniel|date=2 December 2010|accessdate=10 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Liberty was introduced to ''Hollyoaks'' along with her fiancé, [[Ethan Scott]] (Craig Vye).&lt;ref name=&quot;three&quot;/&gt;

Her main storylines have been in the love triangle between Ethan, her and her best friend [[Theresa McQueen]] ([[Jorgie Porter]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;nasty&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a293018/hollyoaks-newcomer-wont-be-nasty.html|title='Hollyoaks' newcomer 'won't be nasty'|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=13 December 2010|accessdate=11 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Phillips said that Ethan is in love with Liberty, but does not love her enough to marry her.&lt;ref name=&quot;whats on tv&quot;&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/hollyoaks/interviews/hollyoaks-ethan-loves-theresas-ditzy-moments/12372|title= Hollyoaks' Ethan 'loves Theresa's ditzy moments'|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|date=6 April 2011|accessdate=15 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On her arrival her on-screen family was introduced, her two brothers, [[Dodger Savage|Dodger]] (Danny Mac) and [[Will Savage|Will]] (James Atherton) and her father [[Dirk Savage|Dirk]] ([[David Kennedy]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;chaos&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a310241/savage-clan-to-cause-havoc-in-hollyoaks.html|title=Savage clan to cause havoc in 'Hollyoaks'|first=Daniel|last=Kilkelly|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|date=21 March 2011|accessdate=12 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liberty performed at [[T4 on the Beach]], she performed as two people, as while Liberty got her big break, Phillips also performed her own solo material.&lt;ref name=&quot;t4&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/news/a325579/hollyoaks-to-film-t4-on-the-beach-scenes.html|title='Hollyoaks' to film T4 On The Beach scenes|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi Médias|Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|last=Kelly|first=Kristy|date=18 June 2011|accessdate=22 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Melody Longford==
{{Infobox soap character 2|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Melody Longford
|portrayer=Sandy Hendrickse
|introducer=[[Paul Marquess]]
|years=2010—2011
|first=28 December 2010
|last=4 February 2011
|born=13 July
|classification=[[List of Hollyoaks characters#Present characters|Former; regular]]
|occupation=[[Singer]]
|husband=Teddy Longford
|daughters=[[Texas Longford]]&lt;br&gt;[[India Longford]]
}}
'''Melody Longford''', played by Sandy Hendrickse,&lt;ref name=&quot;tv guide&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Hollyoaks TV Cast List|url=http://www.tvguide.co.uk/cast.asp?title=Hollyoaks|work=TV Guide UK|accessdate=21 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; is [[India Longford|India]] ([[Beth Kingston]]) and [[Texas Longford]]'s (Bianca Hendrickse-Spendlove) mother. She made her first on-screen appearance on 28 December 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s13/hollyoaks/spoilers/a294051/2982-texas-is-grief-stricken-over-india.html|title=Texas is grief-stricken over India}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When India is murdered and her body is uncovered, Texas tells [[Nancy Hayton]] ([[Jessica Fox]]) her that Melody is arriving. Melody arrives in Hollyoaks village and asks [[Lee Hunter]] ([[Alex Carter (British actor)|Alex Carter]]) for directions. Lee recognises her and realises she was a famous singer in the 1980s. Lee takes Melody to Texas's flat and she signs an autograph for him.

Melody attends India's funeral and leaves after helping Texas grieve over her sisters death.
{{-}}

==Others==
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Character 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date(s) 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Actor 
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Circumstances
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Jack Welsh'''}}
| 5–8 January
| Himself
| {{Anchor|Jack Welsh}} The [[Liverpool]]-based artist appeared as himself when he examined [[Leila Roy]]'s artwork, and gave her a job in [[Paris]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://jackwelsh.co.uk/hollyoaks/|publisher=Jack Welsh Official|title=Hollyoaks|first=Jack|last=Welsh|date=3 November 2009|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Patrick'''}}
| 12 January
| Daniel Yarnold
| {{Anchor|Patrick}} A man who interviewed [[Loretta Jones]] for an office job in the probation service. Former lap dancer Loretta did not inform him of her previous job, and was insulted when he revealed he had no intentions of giving her the job as he wanted to meet a lap dancer.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Dr. Ford'''}}
| 20 January
| Glen Cunningham
| {{Anchor|Dr. Ford}} A doctor at the anorexia clinic, who weighed and assessed [[Hannah Ashworth]], before releasing her.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Policeman'''}}
|  11 February
|  Phil Jervis
| {{Anchor|Policeman}} A police officer who arrived to arrest [[Jamie (Hollyoaks)|Jamie]] for the stabbing of Blue. Jamie then stabbed [[Darren Osborne]] whilst trying to escape and was arrested.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Johnny'''}}
|  March
|  Luca Hyde
| {{Anchor|Johnny}} [[#Caroline|Caroline]]'s young son.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Steve'''}}
| 26 March
| [[Anthony Crank]]
| {{Anchor|Steve}} A TV producer recording [[Duncan Button|Duncan Button's]] 16th birthday party. He also kisses [[Theresa McQueen]], but she slaps him and walks off.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.uk.castingcallpro.com/view.php?uid=256775|title=Anthony Crank|publisher=Casting Call Pro|author=|year=2010|accessdate=2010-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Laura'''}}
| 19–22 April
| Laura Ainsworth
| {{Anchor|Laura}} Laura first appeared dressed as a playboy bunny in The Dog. She later slept with [[Charlotte Lau]] ([[Amy Yamazaki]]). Soon after, she slept with [[Zak Ramsey]] ([[Kent Riley]]), unaware that Charlotte was spying on her.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.uk.castingcallpro.com/portfolio.php?uid=142683&amp;image=166469|title=Laura Ainsworth|publisher=Casting Call Pro|author=|year=2010|accessdate=2010-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a213612/eastenders-pregnancy-edale-violence-and-oaks-infidelity.html|title=Eastenders pregnancy, Edale violence and Oaks infidelity|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|author=Green, Kris|date=11 April 2010|accessdate=2010-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was not seen again.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Glen Turner'''}}
| May
| Drew Horner
| {{Anchor|Glen Turner}} Calvin's former police colleague. Glen helps Calvin set up Gaz Bennett for sending him death threats a few days before his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;ccp&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.uk.castingcallpro.com/tvshow_view.php?uid=8|title=TV Show Database : Hollyoaks|publisher=Casting Call Pro|author=|year=2010|accessdate=2010-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Molly Montgomery'''}}
| 17–23 May
| Sophie Isaacs
| {{Anchor|Molly Montgomery}} A host who appears at a murder mystery birthday surprise for [[India Longford]]. She becomes close to [[Charlotte Lau]] and sleeps with her.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''DI Andrews'''}}
| 25 May–16 July
| Maggie Norris
| {{Anchor|DI Andrews}} A police officer who investigates the murder of [[Calvin Valentine]] and charges [[Gaz Bennett]] after finding him with the gun used to kill Calvin.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Dr. Julian Bashir'''}}
| May–June
| Amerjit Deu
| {{Anchor|Dr. Julian Bashir}} A doctor who tells [[Steph Dean]] her cancer was progressive, and that she would need to have an operation within days.&lt;ref name=&quot;ccp&quot;/&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Jensen Newton'''}}
| 21–25 June
| Unknown
| {{Anchor|Jensen Newton}} The baby brother of [[Barry Newton]] who appears with his mother Shelly, who claims to have stopped her drug use because of Jensen. and leaves him with Newt when she goes for a job interview. Just as Newt, assuming Shelly has abandoned them, is about to run away with the baby, Shelly returns announcing she has found a job in Scotland. The reunited family then relocate. Shelly, Newt and Jensen move to Scotland.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Louis'''}}
| 4 August–3 December
| Des O'Malley
| {{Anchor|Louis}} A 15-year-old cancer patient who [[Steph Cunningham]] meets at radiotherapy. They both support each other and Louis films Steph's diaries of her battle with cancer. Louis is given the all clear and later appears at Steph's funeral.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Lanika'''}}
| 17 September–6 October
| Sarah Patel
| {{Anchor|Lanika}} The apparent wife of [[Jamil Fadel]], who reveals he left her on their arranged wedding day. They eventually agree to go through with the marriage. On their wedding day, Lanika has second thoughts, and does not marry Jamil.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Blanche Longford'''}}
| 20 September–1 October, 2 February 2011
| [[Georgina Hale]]
| {{Anchor|Blanche Longford}} [[Alistair Longford]]'s mother who arrives to stop his wedding to [[Cindy Hutchinson]]. Blanche returns in February 2011 for great-granddaughter [[India Longford]]'s funeral.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Mark Rushton'''}}
| 23 September–25 October
| Daniel Gallagher
| {{Anchor|Mark Rushton}} [[Jasmine Costello]]'s friend whilst she is dressed as her alter-ego Jason.&lt;ref name=&quot;wavee&quot;/&gt; He later appears when [[Bart McQueen]] questions why he has Jasmine's mobile number. Eva Strong refers to him by his second name in 2010.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Vicar'''}}
| 24 September
| John Elkington
| {{Anchor|Vicar}} The vicar who marries [[Alistair Longford]] and [[Cindy Hutchinson]].
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Rashad Fadel'''}}
| 5–6 October
| Leon Jan
| {{Anchor|Rashad Fadel}} [[Jamil Fadel]]'s older brother, who arrives with Jamil's fiancée, Lanika, and persuades him to marry her. However, Lanika does not go through with it.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Helen Davenport'''}}
| 12 October–November
| Emma Vaudrey
| {{Anchor|Helen Davenport}} The mother of [[Phil Sharpe (Hollyoaks)|Phil Sharpe]]'s other two children, Arlo and Tré. Helen has secretly mothered a family by Phil, who has a family elsewhere.[[66]] Helen discovers Phil's lies, and meets his other family.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Tré Davenport'''}}
| 12 October
| Charlie Behan
| {{Anchor|Tré Davenport}} He is one of Phil Sharpe's secret sons and arrives when Taylor Sharpe visits their house for dinner, after receiving an invite from Arlo.[[66]]
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Dale Greer'''}}
| 1 December
| [[Chris Geere]]
| {{Anchor|Dale Greer}} A soldier who appears in a flashback episode explaining how [[Warren Fox]] survived a fire at The Loft nightclub during May 2009. Homeless, Dale starts working for Warren. On the day of The Loft fire, Dale finds Warren trapped in the cellar and helps him get out. Realising everyone believes he is still in The Loft, Warren stabs Dale and places him in the cellar. Dale's body is later recovered and buried as Warren.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Ciara'''}}
| 16 December
| Cammie Stadage
| {{Anchor|Ciara}} A girl who believes [[Seth Costello]] is really his older brother [[Riley Costello|Riley]]. They go joyriding and catch a car thief.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Cameron'''}}
| 23 December
| Cameron Moore
| {{Anchor|Cameron}} A man who [[India Longford]] meets online on a dating website. He appears in dream sequences, when he and India agree to meet each other in person. It is later revealed that Cameron is not a real person, but is instead a middle aged man called [[Silas Blissett]], who murders India.
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{nowrap|'''Lenny McLaverty'''}}
| 30 December
| Scott Ryan Vickers
| {{Anchor|}} An acquaintance of [[Kathleen McQueen]] who she knows from prison. Kathleen trades sexual favours with Lenny so he will baptise [[Kathleen-Angel McQueen]].
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Hollyoaks}}
{{Hollyoaks characters|year}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Hollyoaks Characters (2010)}}
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2010|*, Hollyoaks]]
[[Category:Hollyoaks characters|*, 2010]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
