<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25122293" ns="0" title="Bhavan&#039;s Lloyds Vidya Niketan"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox School
| name              = Bhavan's Lloyds Vidya Niketan
| image             = BLVNlogo.png
| imagesize         = Lloyds Vidya Niketan
| city              = [[Wardha]]
| country           = [[India]]  
| coordinates       =  
| schoolboard       = 
| authority         = Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan
| affiliation       = [[CBSE]]
| founder           = Surendra Dass
| chairperson       = 
| principal         = (Smt.) Janki Mani Iyer
| director          = 
| motto             = Knowledge is Nector
}}

==Overview==
'''Bhavan's Lloyds Vidya Niketan''' (BLVN) is a private secondary school in Bhugaon, [[Wardha]], [[India]], established in 1995. It is the most reputed Engish medium [[CBSE]] school in Wardha.

==History==
The school was started for the children for the employees of Lloyds Steel Industry. In 1995, it was run in the residential colony and had classes till class IV. It moved to the current location in 1996 when the classes were expanded to class IX. Class X was added the next year. Class XI and XII were added around 2004 but were soon scraped due to poor response. They have been restarted since 2009. The school building is being upgraded to accommodate the growing strength.

==Organisation==
The institute comprises two wings - Primary and Higher Secondary. The Primary wing consists of classes from LKG to Std. IV. The Higher Secondary wing consists of classes from Std. V to Std. X. The school has a very spacious playground which has separate fields for Football, Cricket, Basketball, Handball and also junior recreational facilities. The school has good classrooms with comfortable and sturdy furniture. The school has well trained teaching staff as well as non-teaching staff.

==All-Round Development==
School believes in all-round development of children. To promote this motto School has also started hobby classes.

==External links==
* [http://www.blvn.org Official Website]

[[Category:High schools in India]]


{{India-school-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
