<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2514806" ns="0" title="Symbols of Scientology"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Merge to| Scientology|date=November 2010}}
This is an incomplete list of the '''symbols of [[Scientology]]''', the [[Church of Scientology]], and related organizations.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!| Name
!| Image
!| Description
|-
!| Scientology symbol
||  
|| The &quot;new-era&quot; Scientology symbol is an &quot;S&quot; curving through two triangles. The &quot;S&quot; stands for Scientology. The top triangle represents a set of Scientology factors — knowledge, responsibility and control. Collectively the first three factors make up the KRC triangle. The lower triangle consists of the ARC triangle of affinity, reality and communication.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}
|-
!| Dianetics symbol
|| 
|| The stripes of this symbol represent green for growth, and yellow for life. The four green stripes recall the four divisions of a human's urge to survive which are revealed in [[Dianetics]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

The triangle is also reminiscent of the [[volcano]] present on post-1968 editions of the book ''Dianetics'' and in advertising for ''Dianetics'' since that time.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}
|-
!| Infinite Dianetics symbol
|| 
|| Scientology teaches that all beings have an &quot;urge towards the infinite.&quot; This symbol reflects the belief in Scientology that Dianetic processing (the triangle) aids in the attainment of the infinite.  Some variants of this symbol have an [[infinity symbol]] overlapping a triangle, while others place the infinity within the triangle's boundaries, as on the front cover of some versions of Route to Infinity.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}
|-
!| Operating Thetan symbol
|| 
|| The [[Operating Thetan]] symbol is patterned after the [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|Egyptian hieroglyphic]] of a [[Scarabaeus sacer|scarab beetle]]. Scarab beetles were symbolic of resurrection and renewal, and are also an important part of [[Rosicrucianism]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crossroad.to/articles2/2002/carl-teichrib/11scarab.htm Scarab - The Magical Beetle of Egypt], by Carl Teichrib&lt;/ref&gt;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.conspiracyarchive.com/NewAge/Hubbard_Occult.htm Factnet Report:  Hubbard and the Occult], by Jon Atack&lt;/ref&gt; The Operating Thetan symbol is prominently displayed on the side of the Scientology cruise ship ''[[Freewinds]]'' (see [[:Image:Freewinds logo.jpg]]).
Operating Thetans are said to be in a spiritual state above ''[[Clear (Scientology)|Clear]]''.  Scientologists say that one who has achieved the state of Operating Thetan is essentially a being able to operate free of the encumbrances of the material universe, as outlined in ''Scientology 8-8008''.
|-
!| Church of Scientology cross symbol
||  [[File:Scientology_symbol.png|thumb|80px|Stylized version of cross symbol]]
|| This symbol is mainly used to specifically denote the Church of Scientology, and may or may not represent the practice of Scientology in general. The cross's eight points represent the eight [[Scientology beliefs and practices#dynamics|dynamics]] in Scientology.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} See [[Scientology cross]] for more details on this symbol.
|-
!| Sea Org symbol
|| [[File:Sea Org logo.svg|75px|The Sea Org symbol]]
|| The [[Sea Org]] is the central management organisation of the Church of Scientology. The Sea Org was founded by Scientology leader L. Ron Hubbard in 1968, as an organisation for implementing Scientology technology around the world through the operation of a fleet of ships. Members of the Sea Org sign an employment contract with the organisation for one billion years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/media/acrobat/2005-12/21006456.pdf Copy of Sea Org agreement form], [[LA Times]].&lt;/ref&gt;

This symbol originated in [[Operating Thetan]] level III, the [[Xenu]] story, as a symbol representing the [[Galactic Confederacy]] of 75 million years ago.&lt;ref&gt;Hubbard, &quot;Ron's Talk to Pubs Org World Wide&quot;, tape of April 1968&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!| L. Ron Hubbard symbol
|| 
|| This symbol is a pictograph made of a cursive &quot;L&quot;, &quot;R&quot; and &quot;H&quot;. Designed to imitate an [[assay office]] [[hallmark]], it is used to authenticate L. Ron Hubbard's many works.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}
|-
!| Church of Spiritual Technology logo
|| [[File:ChurchOfSpritualTechnologyLogo.svg|100px]]
||
The symbol for the [[Church of Spiritual Technology]] is engraved into the Earth's surface in Scientology's [[Trementina Base]], in a mountainous region of New Mexico &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/26/AR2005112601065_pf.html  A Place in the Desert for New Mexico's Most Exclusive Circles], Washington Post, 11/27/2005&lt;/ref&gt;, large enough to be seen from a high altitude. Former Church member [[Michael Pattinson]] has said that the circles are intended as signposts for reincarnated Scientologists who will come from outer space.&lt;ref&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0512/02/acd.01.html Transcript from ''Anderson Cooper 360''], 12/2/2005&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Trademarks==
All official symbols of Scientology are trademarks held by the [[Religious Technology Center]] (RTC). They are said by the center to be used &quot;on Scientology religious materials to signify their authenticity ... and provide a legal mechanism to ensure the spiritual technologies are orthodox and ministered according to Mr. Hubbard's Scripture. These marks also provide the means to prevent anyone from engaging in some distorted use of Mr. Hubbard's writings, thereby ensuring the purity of the religion for all eternity.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://davidmiscavige.rtc.org/ENG/CORP/rtc.htm Biography of David Miscavige], from the Religious Technology Center, a Scientology organization&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* {{cite web
  | title = Understanding the Scientology Religious Doctrine
  | work = A description of the symbols, lectures etc... of Dianetics and Scientology
  | url= http://www.scripturalscientology.org
  | publisher = }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Google hybrid map of Trementina site
  | work = Aerial shot of interlinked circles with diamonds and other structures
  | url = http://maps.google.ca/maps?q=trementina&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;ll=35.511269,-104.571562&amp;spn=0.033326,0.058365&amp;t=h&amp;z=14&amp;om=1
  | publisher = }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Factnet Report: Hubbard and the occult
  | work = A description of the Scientological symbols and the occult
  | url= http://www.sweenytod.com/cos/huboccult3.html
  | format = personal site
  | publisher = Sweenytod.com }}

__NOTOC__

{{DEFAULTSORT:Symbols Of Scientology}}
[[Category:Lists of symbols|Scientology]]
[[Category:Religious symbols]]
[[Category:Scientology beliefs and practices]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
