<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25197709" ns="0" title="Air warfare of World War II"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Lead too short|date=January 2011}}

'''Air warfare of World War II''' was a major component of [[World War II]] in all theatres, and (with anti-air defense) consumed a large fraction of the industrial output of the major powers.
[[File:B-29 in flight.jpg|thumb|250px|The B-29 was the very long range U.S. strategic bomber used against Japan]]
{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

Germany and Japan depended on air forces that were closely integrated with land and naval forces; they downplayed the advantage of a large strategic bombers, and were late in appreciating the need for a defensive error system against Allied strategic bombing. By contrast Britain and the United States had a more complex approach that gave enormous weight to strategic bombing, as well as tactical  control of the battlefield and adequate air defenses. They both built a strategic force of a large long-range bombers that could carry the air war to the enemy's homeland. Simultaneously they built tactical air forces that could win air superiority over the battlefields, thereby giving vital assistance to ground troops. They both built a powerful naval-air component based on aircraft carriers, as did Japan; these played the central role in the war at sea.&lt;ref&gt;R.J. Overy, ''The Air War: 1939-1945'' (1980) ch 1&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prewar planning==
Before 1939 all sides operated under largely theoretical models of air warfare. The Italian theorist [[Giulio Douhet]] in the 1920s summarized the faith that airmen in [[World War I]] developed in the efficacy of [[strategic bombing]]. Many said it alone could win wars,&lt;ref name=Shiner&gt;{{citation| journal = Air University Review| date = January–February 1986| title = Reflections on Douhet: the classic approach| url = http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/aureview/1986/jan-feb/shiner.html| first = John F. | last = Shiner}}&lt;/ref&gt; as &quot;[[the bomber will always get through]]&quot;. The Americans were sublimely confident that the [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]] bomber could reach targets, protected by its own weapons, and bomb, using the [[Norden bombsight]], with &quot;pickle barrel&quot; accuracy&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Lee McFarland, ''America's pursuit of precision bombing, 1910-1945'' (1995) p 68&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese aviation pioneers felt that they had developed the finest naval aviators in the world. But they fought to the death and their skills were not transmitted to the next generation of pilots, so the quality of Japanese aviators declined rapidly after 1942.

To bomb Germany, the Allies depended on close-by unsinkable airfields in Britain.  To attack Japan the U.S. needed both very long range bombers and bases within range, which were won in mid-1944.

==Air forces==
===Germany: The Luftwaffe===
{{main|History of the Luftwaffe during World War II}}

The '''[[Luftwaffe]]''' was the German Air Force. The pride of [[Nazi Germany]] under its bombastic leader [[Hermann Göring]], it learned new combat techniques in the Spanish Civil War and was seen by Hitler as the decisive strategic weapon he needed.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson Murray, ''Luftwaffe: Strategy for Defeat, 1933-1945'' (1985)&lt;/ref&gt; Its advanced technology and rapid growth led to exaggerated fears in the 1930s that helped to persuade the British and French into appeasement. In the war the Luftwaffe performed well in 1939-41, as its Stuka dive bombers terrified enemy infantry units. But the Luftwaffe was poorly coordinated with overall German strategy, and never ramped up to the size and scope needed in a total war. It never built large bombers, was deficient in [[radar]], and could not deal with the faster, more agile [[P-51 Mustang]] pursuit planes after 1943, or Britain's increasingly lethal defensive fighter screen after the Battle of Britain.

When its gasoline supply ran dry in 1944, it was reduced to anti-aircraft flak roles, and many of its men were sent to infantry units.  By 1944 it operated 39,000 flak batteries staffed with a million people in uniform, both men and women.

The Luftwaffe lacked the bomber forces for strategic bombing, because it did not think such bombing was worth it.  They did attempt some strategic bombing in the east.  Their one success was destroying an airbase at Poltava, Russia, which housed 43 new B-17 bombers and a million tons of aviation fuel.&lt;ref&gt;Richard J. Evans, ''The Third Reich at War'' (2009) 436-7&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Germany's allies, especially Italy and Finland, had air forces of their own, there was very little coordination with them.  Not until very late in the war did Germany share its blueprints with its ally Japan—too late for Japan to improve its weapons systems or to make synthetic oil.&lt;ref&gt;James S. Corum, &quot;The Luftwaffe and Its Allied Air Forces in World War II: Parallel War and the Failure of Strategic and Economic Cooperation,&quot; ''Air Power History''  Volume: 51#2 (2004).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Britain: The Royal Air Force===
{{main|History of the Royal Air Force}}
The British had their own very well-developed theory of strategic bombing, and built the long-range bombers to implement it.&lt;ref&gt;Tami Davis Biddle, &quot;British and American Approaches to Strategic Bombing: Their Origins and Implementation in the World War II Combined Bomber Offensive,&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies,'' March 1995, Vol. 18 Issue 1, pp 91-144&lt;/ref&gt;

Before 1944, however, the main German industrial targets were out of range, so the RAF bombers concentrated on military and transportation targets in France and Belgium.&lt;ref&gt;Richard J. Overy, ''The Air War, 1939-1945'' (1981)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tami Davis Biddle, &quot;Bombing By The Square Yard: Sir Arthur Harris At War, 1942-1945,&quot; ''International History Review,'' vol 9#1 1999, pp 626-664&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAF underwent rapid expansion following the outbreak of war against Germany in 1939. This included [[British Commonwealth Air Training Plan|the training in other Commonwealth nations]] (particulary Canada) of half of British and Commonwealth aircrews, some 167,000 men in all. The RAF also integrated Polish and other airmen who had escaped from Hitler's Europe. In Europe, the RAF was in operational control of Commonwealth aircrews and Commonwealth squadrons although these retained some degree of independence (such as the formation of [[No. 6 Group RCAF]] to put Canadian squadrons together in a nationally identifiable unit)

The RAF had three major combat commands based in the United Kingdom: [[RAF Fighter Command]] charged with defence of the UK, [[RAF Bomber Command]] which operated the bombers that would be offensive against the enemy, and [[RAF Coastal Command]] which was to protect Allied shipping and attack enemy shipping. The Royal Navy's [[Fleet Air Arm]] operated land-based fighters in defence of naval establishments and carrier-based aircraft. Later in the war the RAF's fighter force was divided into two [[Air Defence of Great Britain]] (ADGB) for protecting the UK and the [[Second Tactical Air Force]] for ground offensive support in North West Europe.

Bomber Command participated in two areas of attack - the strategic bombing campaign against German war production, and the less well known mining of coastal waters off Germany to contain its naval operations and prevent the U-boats from freely operating against Allied shipping. In order to attack German industry by night the RAF developed navigational aids, tactics to [[bomber stream|overwhelm the German defences control system]], tactics directly against German night-fighter forces, [[Pathfinder (RAF)|target marking techniques]], many [[List of World War II electronic warfare equipment|electronic aids in defence and attack]], and [[No. 100 Group RAF|supporting electronic warfare aircraft]]. The production of heavy aircraft competed with resources for the Army and the Navy, and it was a source of disagreement as to whether the effort could be more profitably expended elsewhere.

===Soviet Union: Soviet Air Force===
{{main|Soviet Air Forces#World War II|Eastern Front (World War II)}}

[[Image:Yak1.jpg|thumb|250px|Early-model [[Yakovlev Yak-1|Yak-1]] fighter; the USSR built 37,000 of them]]

By the end of the war, [[World_War_II_aircraft_production|Soviet annual aircraft production]] had risen sharply with annual Soviet production peaking at 40,000 aircraft in 1944. Some 157,000 aircraft were produced, of which 126,000 were combat types, while the others were transports and trainers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hardesty |first=Von |title=Red Phoenix: The Rise of Soviet Air Power 1941–1945 |origyear=1982  |year=1991 |publisher=Smithsonian Institution |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=0-87474-510-1 |page=225 |chapter=Barbarossa to Berlin: A Summing Up}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy, 1980 p 150&quot;&gt;R.J. Overy, ''The Air War: 1939-1945'' (1980) p 150&lt;/ref&gt;

During the war the Soviets employed 7500 bombers to drop 30 million bombs on German targets, with a density that sometimes reaching 100-150 tons/ sq kilometer.&lt;ref&gt;A. A. Sidorenko, ''The Offensive'' (Moscow, 1970;  USAF translation) p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James Sterrett, ''Soviet Air Force theory, 1918-1945'' (2007) pp 86-131&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States: AAF===
{{main|United States Army Air Forces}}
Before the [[Battle of Pearl Harbor]], President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] gave command of the Navy to an aviator, Admiral [[Ernest King]], with a mandate for an aviation-oriented war in the Pacific. FDR allowed King to build up land-based naval and Marine aviation, and seize control of the long-range bombers used in antisubmarine patrols in the Atlantic. Roosevelt basically agreed with [[Robert A. Lovett]], the civilian Assistant Secretary of War for Air, who argued, &quot;While I don't go so far as to claim that air power alone will win the war, I do claim the war will not be won without it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Walter Isaacson and Evan Thomas, [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0684837714?v=search-inside&amp;keywords=claim+that+air+power&amp;go=Go%21# ''The Wise Men: Six Friends and the World They Made'' (1997) p. 203]&lt;/ref&gt;

Army Chief of Staff [[George C. Marshall]] rejected calls for complete independence for the [[United States Army Air Corps|Air Corps]], because the land forces generals and the Navy were vehemently opposed. In the compromise that was reached it was understood that after the war the aviators would get their independence. Meanwhile, the Air Corps became the [[United States Army Air Forces|Army Air Forces]] (AAF) in June, 1941, combining all their personnel and units under a single commanding general, an airman. In 1942 the Army reorganized into three equal components, one of which was the AAF, which then had almost complete freedom in terms of internal administration. Thus the AAF set up its own medical service independent of the Surgeon General, its own WAC units, and its own logistics system. It had full control over the design and procurement of airplanes and related electronic gear and ordnance. Its purchasing agents controlled 15% of the nation's Gross National Product. Together with naval aviation, it recruited the best young men in the nation. General [[Henry H. Arnold]] headed the AAF. One of the first military men to fly, and the youngest colonel in World War I, he selected for the most important combat commands men who were ten years younger than their Army counterparts, including [[Ira Eaker]] (b. 1896), [[Jimmy Doolittle]] (b. 1896), [[Hoyt Vandenberg]] (b. 1899), [[Elwood Quesada|Elwood &quot;Pete&quot; Queseda]] (b. 1904), and, youngest of them all, [[Curtis LeMay]] (b. 1906). Although a West Pointer himself, Arnold did not automatically turn to Academy men for top positions. Since he operated independent of theater commanders, Arnold could and did move his generals around, and speedily removed underachievers.&lt;ref&gt;Alfred Goldberg. A History of the United States Air Force, 1907-1957'' (1972)&lt;/ref&gt;

Aware of the need for engineering expertise, Arnold went outside the military and formed close liaisons with top engineers like rocket specialist [[Theodore von Karmen]] at Cal Tech. Arnold was given seats on the US Joint Chiefs of Staff and the US-British [[Combined Chiefs of Staff]]. Arnold, however, was officially Deputy Chief of [Army] Staff, so on committees he deferred to his boss, General Marshall. Thus Marshall made all the basic strategic decisions, which were worked out by his &quot;War Plans Division&quot; (WPD, later renamed the Operations Division). WPD's section leaders were infantrymen or engineers, with a handful of aviators in token positions.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas M. Coffey, ''Hap: The Story of the U.S. Air Force and the Man Who Built It, General Henry H. &quot;Hap&quot; Arnold'' (1982).&lt;/ref&gt;

The AAF had a newly-created planning division, whose advice was largely ignored by WPD. Airmen were also underrepresented in the planning divisions of the Joint Chiefs of Staff and of the Combined Chiefs. Aviators were largely shut out of the decision-making and planning process because they lacked seniority in a highly rank-conscious system. The freeze intensified demands for independence, and fueled a spirit of &quot;proving&quot; the superiority of air power doctrine. Because of the young, pragmatic leadership at top, and the universal glamor accorded aviators, morale in the AAF was strikingly higher than anywhere else (except perhaps Navy aviation.)

The AAF provided extensive technical training, promoted officers and enlisted faster, provided comfortable barracks and good food, and was safe. The only dangerous jobs were voluntary ones as crew of fighters and bombers—or involuntary ones at jungle bases in the Southwest Pacific. Marshall, an infantryman uninterested in aviation before 1939, became a partial convert to air power and allowed the aviators more autonomy. He authorized vast spending on planes, and insisted that American forces had to have air supremacy before taking the offensive. However, he repeatedly overruled Arnold by agreeing with Roosevelt's requests in 1941-42 to send half of the new light bombers and fighters to the British and Soviets, thereby delaying the buildup of American air power.&lt;ref&gt;Eric Larrabee, ''Commander in Chief: Franklin Delano Roosevelt, His Lieutenants, and Their War'' (2004) pp 206-55&lt;/ref&gt;

The Army's major theater commands were given to infantrymen [[Douglas MacArthur]] and [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]. Neither had paid much attention to aviation before the war (though Ike learned to fly).

Offensive counter-air, to clear the way for strategic bombers and an eventually decisive cross-channel invasion, was a strategic mission led by escort fighters partnered with heavy bombers. The tactical mission, however, was the province of fighter-bombers, assisted by light and medium bombers.

American theater commanders became air power enthusiasts, and built their strategies around the need for tactical air supremacy. MacArthur had been badly defeated in the Philippines in 1941-42 primarily because the Japanese controlled the sky. His planes were outnumbered and outclassed, his airfields shot up, his radar destroyed, his supply lines cut. His infantry never had a chance. MacArthur vowed never again. His island hopping campaign was based on the strategy of isolating Japanese strongholds while leaping past them. Each leap was determined by the range of his air force, and the first task on securing an objective was to build an airfield to prepare for the next leap.&lt;ref&gt;Eric M. Bergerud, ''Fire in the Sky: The Air War in the South Pacific'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stanley Sandler, ''World War II in the Pacific: an encyclopedia'' (2001) p. 463&lt;/ref&gt;

==Doctrine and technology==
Some issues were clearly strategic, and some clearly tactical.

The issue of establishing air superiority and air supremacy, however, depends on the context. Air superiority, rather than supremacy, over fast-moving ground forces might be all that was needed. The strategic bombing command was more dependent on suppressing defensive fighters, but there would always be [[anti-aircraft artillery]] and thus losses.

The Allies won battlefield air supremacy in the Pacific in 1943, and in Europe in 1944. That meant that Allied supplies and reinforcements would get through to the battlefront, but not the enemy's. It meant the Allies could concentrate their strike forces wherever they pleased, and overwhelm the enemy with a preponderance of firepower. There was a specific campaign, within the overall strategic offensive, for [[suppression of enemy air defenses]], or, specifically, Luftwaffe fighters.

===Aircrew training===
While the Japanese began the war with a superb set of naval aviators, trained at the Misty Lagoon experimental air station, their practice, perhaps from the warrior tradition, was to keep the pilots in action until they died. The U.S. position, at least for naval aviation, was a strict rotation between sea deployments and shore duty, the latter including training replacements, personal training, and participating in doctrinal development. The U.S. strategic bombing campaign against Europe did this in principle, but relatively few crews survived the 25 missions of a rotation.

Other countries had other variants. In some countries, it seemed to be a matter of personal choice if one stayed in combat or helped build the next generation. Even where there was a policy of using skills outside combat, some individuals, eg [[Guy Gibson]] VC insisted on returning to combat after a year. Both Gibson's successors at 617 Squadron were ordered off &quot;ops&quot; permantly (Leonard Cheshire after 102 operations, &quot;Willie Tait&quot; after 101)

===Logistics===
====Airfield construction====
Arnold correctly anticipated that the U.S. would have to build forward airfields in inhospitable places. Working closely with the Army Corps of Engineers, he created Aviation Engineer Battalions that by 1945 included 118,000 men. Runways, hangars, radar stations, power generators, barracks, gasoline storage tanks and ordnance dumps had to be built hurriedly on tiny coral islands, mud flats, featureless deserts, dense jungles, or exposed locations still under enemy artillery fire. The heavy construction gear had to be imported, along with the engineers, blueprints, steel-mesh landing mats, prefabricated hangars, aviation fuel, bombs and ammunition, and all necessary supplies. As soon as one project was finished the battalion would load up its gear and move forward to the next challenge, while headquarters inked in a new airfield on the maps.&lt;ref&gt;Bergerud, ''Fire in the Sky'' pp 49-93&lt;/ref&gt;

The engineers opened an entirely new airfield in North Africa every other day for seven straight months. Once when heavy rains along the coast reduced the capacity of old airfields, two companies of Airborne Engineers loaded miniaturized gear into 56 transports, flew a thousand miles to a dry Sahara location, started blasting away, and were ready for the first [[B-17]] 24 hours later. Often engineers had to repair and use a captured enemy airfield. The German fields were well-built all-weather operations.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate, 2:250, 253&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the Japanese island bases, built before the war, had excellent airfields. Most new Japanese installations in the Pacific were ramshackle affairs with poor siting, poor drainage, scant protection, and narrow, bumpy runways. Engineering was a low priority for the offense-minded Japanese, who chronically lacked adequate equipment and imagination. On a few islands, local commanders did improve aircraft shelters and general survivability, as they correctly perceived the danger of coming raids or invasions.&lt;ref&gt;Bergerud, ''Fire in the Sky'' pp 5-48&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tactical===
Tactical air power involves gaining control of the airspace over the battlefield, directly supporting ground units (as by attacks on enemy tanks and artillery), and attacking enemy supply lines, and airfields. Typically, fighter planes are used to gain air supremacy, and light bombers are used for support missions.&lt;ref&gt;Richard P.  Hallion, ''Strike From the Sky: The History of Battlefield Air Attack, 1911-1945'' (1989); Daniel R. ed. Mortensen, ''Airpower and Ground Armies: Essays on the Evolution of Anglo-American Air Doctrine, 1940–1943'' (1998)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Air supremacy====
Tactical air doctrine stated that the primary mission was to turn tactical superiority into complete [[air supremacy]]--to totally defeat the enemy air force and obtain control of its air space. This could be done directly through dogfights, and raids on airfields and radar stations, or indirectly by destroying aircraft factories and fuel supplies. [[Anti-aircraft artillery]] (called &quot;ack-ack by the British, &quot;flak&quot; by the Germans, and &quot;Archie&quot; by the Yanks) could also play a role, but it was downgraded by most airmen. The Allies won air supremacy in the Pacific in 1943, and in Europe in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Charles F. Brower, ''World War II in Europe: the final year'' (1988) p, 126&lt;/ref&gt; That meant that Allied supplies and reinforcements would get through to the battlefront, but not the enemy's. It meant the Allies could concentrate their strike forces wherever they pleased, and overwhelm the enemy with a preponderance of firepower. This was the basic Allied strategy, and it worked.

Air superiority depended on having the fastest, most maneuverable fighters, in sufficient quantity, based on well-supplied airfields, within range. The RAF demonstrated the importance of speed and maneuverability in the [[Battle of Britain]] (1940), when its fast [[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfire]] and [[Hawker Hurricane]] fighters easily riddled the clumsy Stukas as they were pulling out of dives. The race to build the fastest fighter became one of the central themes of World War II. 

Once total [[air supremacy]] in a theater was gained the second mission was interdiction of the flow of enemy supplies and reinforcements in a zone five to fifty miles behind the front. Whatever moved had to be exposed to air strikes, or else confined to moonless nights. (Radar was not good enough for nighttime tactical operations against ground targets.) A large fraction of tactical air power focused on this mission.

====Close air support====
The third and lowest priority (from the AAF viewpoint) mission was &quot;[[close air support]]&quot; or direct assistance to ground units on the battlefront which consisted of bombing targets identified by ground forces, and strafing exposed infantry.&lt;ref&gt;Ian Gooderson, ''Air Power at the Battlefront: Allied Close Air Support in Europe 1943-45'' (1998)&lt;/ref&gt; Airmen disliked the mission because it subordinated the air war to the ground war; furthermore, slit trenches, camouflage, and flak guns usually reduced the effectiveness of close air support. &quot;[[Operation Cobra]]&quot; in July, 1944, targeted a critical strip of 3,000 acres of German strength that held up the breakthrough out of Normandy.&lt;ref&gt;Steven J. Zaloga, ''Operation Cobra 1944: Breakout from Normandy'' (2001)&lt;/ref&gt; General [[Omar Bradley]], his ground forces stymied, placed his bets on air power. 1,500 heavies, 380 medium bombers and 550 fighter bombers dropped 4,000 tons of high explosives. Bradley was horrified when 77 planes dropped their payloads short of the intended target:
:The ground belched, shook and spewed dirt to the sky. Scores of our troops were hit, their bodies flung from slit trenches. Doughboys were dazed and frightened....A bomb landed squarely on [[Lesley J. McNair|McNair]] in a slit trench and threw his body sixty feet and mangled it beyond recognition except for the three stars on his collar.&lt;ref&gt;Omar Bradley, ''A general's life: an autobiography'' (1983) p.  280; Craven and Cate 3:234&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans were stunned senseless, with tanks overturned, telephone wires severed, commanders missing, and a third of their combat troops killed or wounded. The defense line broke; [[Joe Collins]] rushed his VII Corps forward; the Germans retreated in a rout; the Battle of France was won; air power seemed invincible. However, the sight of a senior colleague killed by error was unnerving, and after the completion of operation Cobra, Army generals were so reluctant to risk &quot;friendly fire&quot; casualties that they often passed over excellent attack opportunities that would be possible only with air support. Infantrymen, on the other hand, were ecstatic about the effectiveness of close air support:
:&quot;Air strikes on the way; we watch from a top window as P-47s dip in and out of clouds through suddenly erupting strings of Christmas-tree lights [flak], before one speck turns over and drops toward earth in the damnest sight of the Second World War, the dive-bomber attack, the speck snarling, screaming, dropping faster than a stone until it's clearly doomed to smash into the earth, then, past the limits of belief, an impossible flattening beyond houses and trees, an upward arch that makes the eyes hurt, and, as the speck hurtles away, WHOOM, the earth erupts five hundred feet up in swirling black smoke. More specks snarl, dive, scream, two squadrons, eight of them, leaving congealing, combining, whirling pillars of black smoke, lifting trees, houses, vehicles, and, we devoutly hope, bits of Germans. We yell and pound each other's backs. Gods from the clouds; this is how you do it! You don't attack painfully across frozen plains, you simply drop in on the enemy and blow them out of existence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Brendan Phibbs, ''The Other Side of Time: A Combat Surgeon in World War II'' (1987) p 149&lt;/ref&gt;

Some forces, especially the [[United States Marine Corps]], emphasized the air-ground team. The airmen, in this approach, also are infantrymen who understand the needs and perspective of the ground forces. There was much more joint air-ground training, and a given air unit might have a long-term relationship with a given ground unit, improving their mutual communications.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Lee Sherrod, ''History of Marine Corps Aviation in World War II'' (1987)&lt;/ref&gt;

==German bombers and missiles==
Britain and the United States built long-range heavy bombers; Germany, Japan, and the Soviet Union did not. The decision was made in 1933 by the German General general staff, the technical staff, and the aviation industry that there was a lack of sufficient labor, capital, and raw materials.&lt;ref&gt;Edward L. Homze, &quot;The Luftwaffe's Failure to Develop a Heavy Bomber before World War II,&quot; ''Aerospace Historian,'' 1977, Vol. 24 Issue 1, pp 20-26&lt;/ref&gt;  During the war Hitler was insistent on bombers having tactical capability, which at the time meant dive bombing, a maneuver then impossible for any heavy bomber. His aircraft had limited effect on Britain for a variety of reasons, but low payload was among them.  Lacking a doctrine of strategic bombing, the Luftwaffe never built quantities of an appropriate heavy bomber. Early in the war, it had excellent tactical aviation, but when it faced Britain's integrated air defense system, the medium bombers did not have the numbers or bomb load to do major damage of the sort the RAF and AAF inflicted on German cities.&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Denis Lepage, ''Aircraft of the Luftwaffe, 1935-1945''  (2009) p 162&lt;/ref&gt;

===Failure of German secret weapons===
Hitler believed that new high-technology &quot;secret weapons&quot; would give Germany a strategic bombing capability and turn the war around. The first of 9,300 [[V-1 (flying bomb)|V-1]] flying bombs hit London in mid- June, 1944, and together with 1,300 [[V-2]] rockets caused 8,000 civilian deaths and 23,000 injuries. Although they did not seriously undercut British morale or munitions production, they bothered the British government a great deal—Germany now had its own unanswered weapons system. Using proximity fuzes, British [[anti-aircraft artillery]] gunners learned how to shoot down the 400&amp;nbsp;mph V-1s; nothing could stop the supersonic V-2s. The British government, in near panic, demanded that upwards of 40% of bomber sorties be targeted against the launch sites, and got its way in &quot;Operation CROSSBOW.&quot; The attacks were futile, and the diversion represented a major success for Hitler.&lt;ref&gt;David Mets, ''Master of Airpower: General Carl A. Spatz'' (1997) &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate, 3:540 calls CROSSBOW a &quot;failure&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;

Every raid against a V-1 or V-2 launch site was one less raid against the Third Reich. On the whole, however, the secret weapons were still another case of too little too late. The Luftwaffe ran the V-1 program, which used a jet engine, but it diverted scarce engineering talent and manufacturing capacity that were urgently needed to improve German radar, air defense, and jet fighters. The German Army ran the V-2 program. The rockets were a technological triumph, and bothered the British leadership even more than the V-1s. But they were so inaccurate they rarely could hit militarily significant targets.&lt;ref&gt;T. D. Dungan, ''V-2: A Combat History of the First Ballistic Missile'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pacific air war==
Japan did not have a separate air force.  Its aviation units were integrated into the Army and Navy,  which were not well coordinated with each other.  Japanese industry [[Military production during World War II#Aircraft]] produced 76,000 warplanes, of which 30,000 were fighters and 15,000 were light bombers.&lt;ref name=&quot;R.J. Overy, 1980 p 150&quot;/&gt;

===China, 1937-1944===

Japan launched a full-scale war in China in 1937 and soon controlled the major cities and the seacoast. The U.S. sent help through Burma, and after 1942 flew in supplies over the &quot;[[The Hump]]&quot; (the Himalaya Mountains) from India.

In 1940-41, well before Pearl Harbor, the United States decided on an aggressive air campaign against Japan using Chinese bases and American pilots wearing Chinese uniforms.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Schaller, &quot;American Air Strategy in China, 1939-1941: The Origins of Clandestine Air Warfare,&quot; ''American Quarterly'' Vol. 28, No. 1 (Spring, 1976), pp. 3-19 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/2712474 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; The United States created funded and provided crews and equipment for the &quot;[[Flying Tigers]]&quot;, a nominally Chinese Air Force composed almost entirely of Americans, led by General [[Claire Lee Chennault]].&lt;ref&gt;Martha Byrd, ''Chennault: Giving Wings to the Tiger'' (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;  The Flying Tigers racked up a strong record of tactical attacks on the Japanese Air Force.  Chennault called for strategic bombing against Japanese cities, using American bombers based in China.  The plan was approved by Roosevelt and top policy makers in Washington, and equipment was on the way in December 1941.  It proved too little, too late.  American strategic bombing of Japan from Chinese bases began in 1944, using B-29s under the command of General [[Curtis Lemay]], but the distances and the logistics made an effective campaign impossible.&lt;ref&gt;Herman S. Wolk, ''Cataclysm: General Hap Arnold and the Defeat of Japan'' (2010) p. 88&lt;/ref&gt;

===Japanese air war 1941-42===
Washington tried to deter Japanese entry into the war by threatening the firebombing of Japanese cities using B.-17 strategic bombers based in the Philippines.  The US sent too little too late, as the Japanese easily overwhelmed the American &quot;Far Eastern Air Force&quot; the day after Pearl Harbor.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel F. Harrington, &quot;A Careless Hope: American Air Power and Japan, 1941,&quot; ''Pacific Historical Review,'' Feb 1979, Vol. 48 Issue 1, pp 217-238 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/3639273 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;

Japanese naval air power proved unexpectedly powerful, sinking the American battleship fleet at [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|Pearl Harbor]] in December 1941, then raging widely across the Pacific and Indian oceans to defeat elements of the British, American, Dutch, and Australian forces.  Land-based airpower,  coordinated efficiently with land forces, enabled Japan to overrun Malaya, Singapore.,&lt;ref&gt;Brian P. Farrell, ''The Defence and Fall of Singapore 1940-1942'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt; and the Philippines by spring 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Koichi Shimada, &quot;Japanese Naval Air Operations in the Philippines Invasion,&quot; ''U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings,'' Jan 1955, Vol. 81 Issue 1, pp 1-17&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Doolittle Raid]] used 16 B-25 bombers (taking off from aircraft carriers&lt;ref&gt;Paolo E. Coletta, &quot;Launching the Doolittle Raid on Japan, April 18, 1942,&quot; ''Pacific Historical Review'' Vol. 62, No. 1 (Feb., 1993), pp. 73-86 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/3640523 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt;) to bomb Tokyo in April 1942.  Little physical damage was done, but the episode shocked and stunned the Japanese people and leadership.&lt;ref&gt;Clayton Chun and Howard Gerrard, ''The Doolittle Raid 1942: America's first strike back at Japan'' (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;

===1942 ===
[[Image:UmpCADH270K.jpg|300px|thumb|Japanese warplanes bombing the Dutch light cruiser [[HNLMS Java|HNLMS ''Java'']] during the Battle of Java Sea]]
At the [[Battle of the Java Sea]], February 27, 1942, the Japanese Navy destroyed the main ABDA naval force. The Netherlands East Indies campaign resulted in the surrender of Allied forces on Java.  Meanwhile, Japanese aircraft had all but eliminated Allied air power in South-East Asia and began attacking Australia, with a major raid on [[Bombing of Darwin|Darwin, February 19]]. A raid by a powerful Japanese Navy aircraft carrier force into the Indian Ocean resulted in the Battle of Ceylon and sinking of the only British carrier, HMS Hermes in the theatre as well as 2 cruisers and other ships effectively driving the British fleet out of the Indian ocean and paving the way for Japanese conquest of Burma and a drive towards India.&lt;ref&gt;H. P. Willmott, ''Empires in the Balance: Japanese and Allied Pacific Strategies to April 1942'' (2008)&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese seemed unstoppable.  However, the [[Doolittle Raid]] caused an uproar in the Japanese Army and Navy commands—they had both lost face in letting the Emperor be threatened. As a consequence, the Army relocated overseas fighter groups to Japan, groups needed elsewhere. Even more significantly, the Naval command believed it had to extend its eastern defense perimeter, and they focused on Midway as the next base.

====Coral Sea and Midway====
By mid-1942, the Japanese Combined Fleet found itself holding a vast area, even though it lacked the aircraft carriers, aircraft, and aircrew to defend it, and the freighters, tankers, and destroyers necessary to sustain it. Moreover, Fleet doctrine was incompetent to execute the proposed &quot;barrier&quot; defense.&lt;ref&gt;H. P. Willmott, ''Barrier and the Javelin: Japanese and Allied Strategies, February to June 1942'' (2008)&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, they decided on additional attacks in both the south and central Pacific.  In the [[Battle of the Coral Sea]], fought between May 4–8, 1942  off the coast of Australia, the opposing fleets never saw one another; it was an air exchange. While the Americans had greater losses and arguably a tactical loss,  they gained a strategic victory, as Japan cancelled a planned offensive.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Stille and John White, ''The Coral Sea 1942: The first carrier battle'' (2009)&lt;/ref&gt;

In  the [[Battle of Midway]],  the Japanese split their fleet, sending much of their force and a feint toward Alaska.  The Americans realized  Alaska was not the main target, and desperately concentrated its resources to defend Hawaii. Japan had 272 warplanes operating from four carriers; the U.S. had 348 of which 115 were AAF land-based and the rest flew from three carriers.   In an extraordinarily close battle, the Japanese suddenly lost their four main aircraft carriers, and were forced to return home.  They never again launched a major offensive in the Pacific.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon W. Prange, ''Miracle at Midway'' (1982)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For the Japanese perspective see Jonathan Parshall and Anthony Tully, ''Shattered Sword: The Untold Story of the Battle of Midway'' (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

====Guadalcanal====
{{main|Guadalcanal Campaign}}
The Japanese had built a major air base at on the island of [[Rabaul]],  but had difficulty keeping it supplied.  American naval and Marine aviation made Rabaul a  frequent bombing target.
[[File:GuadHendersonManyAircraft.gif|300px|thumb|Cactus Air Force warplanes on [[Henderson Field (Guadalcanal)|Henderson Field]], Guadalcanal in October, 1942]]
A Japanese airfield was spotted under construction at [[Guadalcanal]]. The Americans made an amphibious landing in August 1942 to seize it, send in the [[Cactus Air Force]] and start to reverse the tide of Japanese conquests. As a result, Japanese and Allied forces both occupied various parts of Guadalcanal. Over the following six months, both sides fed resources into an escalating battle of attrition on the island, at sea, and in the sky, with eventual victory going to the Americans in February 1943. It was a campaign the Japanese could ill afford. A majority of Japanese aircraft from the entire South Pacific area was drained into the Japanese defense of Guadalcanal. Japanese logistics, as happened time and again, failed; only 20% of the supplies dispatched from Rabaul to Guadalcanal ever reached there.&lt;ref&gt;Richard B. Frank, ''Guadalcanal: The Definitive Account of the Landmark'' (1992)&lt;/ref&gt;

===1943-45===
After 1942 the United States made a massive effort to build up its aviation forces in the Pacific,  and began island-hopping to push its airfields closer and closer to Tokyo.  Meanwhile, the Japanese were unable to upgrade their aircraft, and they fell further and further behind in numbers of aircraft carriers.  The forward island bases were very hard to supply—often only submarines could get through—and the Japanese forces worked without replacements or rest, and often with inadequate food and medicine.  Their morale and performance steadily declined. Starvation became an issue in many bases.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Parillo, &quot;The Pacific  War: An Interpretation,&quot; in Richard Jensen, Jon Davidann, and Yoneyuki Sugita, eds. ''Trans-Pacific Relations: America, Europe, and Asia in the Twentieth Century'' (Praeger, 2003) pp 93-103; Bergerud, ''Fire in the Sky'' pp 341, 347.&lt;/ref&gt;

The American airmen were well fed and well supplied, but they were not rotated and faced increasingly severe stress that caused their performance to deteriorate.  They flew far more often in the Southwest Pacific than in Europe, and although rest time in Australia was scheduled, there was no fixed number of missions that would produce transfer back to the states.  Coupled with the monotonous, hot, sickly environment, the result was bad morale that jaded veterans quickly passed along to newcomers.&lt;ref&gt;Bergerud, ''Fire in the Sky'' p 344-49.&lt;/ref&gt;  After a few months, epidemics of combat fatigue would drastically reduce the efficiency of units. The men who had been at jungle airfields longest, the flight surgeons reported, were in the worst shape:
:Many have chronic dysentery or other disease, and almost all show chronic fatigue states. . . .They appear listless, unkempt, careless, and apathetic with almost masklike facial expression.  Speech is slow, thought content is poor, they complain of chronic headaches, insomnia, memory defect, feel forgotten, worry about themselves, are afraid of new assignments, have no sense of responsibility, and are hopeless about the future.&lt;ref&gt;Mae Mills Link and Hubert A. Coleman, ''Medical Support of the Army Air Forces in World War II'' (1955) p. 851&lt;/ref&gt;

===Strategic Bombing of Japan===
{{main|Air raids on Japan}}
The flammability of Japan's large cities, and the concentration of munitions production there, made strategic bombing the favorite strategy of the Americans.  The first efforts were made from bases in China. Massive efforts (costing $4.5 billion dollars) to establish B-29 bases there had failed when in 1944 the Japanese Army simply moved overland and captured them. The Marianas (especially the islands of [[Saipan]] and [[Tinian]]), captured in June 1944, gave a close secure, base  for the very-long-range B-29. The &quot;Superfortress&quot; (the B-29) represented the highest achievement of traditional (pre-jet) aeronautics. Its four 2,200 horsepower Wright R-3350 supercharged engines could lift four tons of bombs 3,500 miles at 33,000 feet (high above Japanese flak or fighters). Computerized fire-control mechanisms made its 13 guns exceptionally lethal against fighters. However, the systematic raids that began in June, 1944, were unsatisfactory, because the AAF had learned too much in Europe; it overemphasized self-defense. Arnold, in personal charge of the campaign (bypassing the theater commanders) brought in a new leader, brilliant, indefatigable, hard-charging General [[Curtis LeMay]]. In early 1945, LeMay ordered a radical change in tactics: remove the machine guns and gunners, fly in low at night. (Much fuel was used to get to 30,000 feet; it could now be replaced with more bombs.) The Japanese radar, fighter, and anti-aircraft systems were so ineffective that they could not hit the bombers. Fires raged through the cities, and millions of civilians fled to the mountains.

Tokyo was hit repeatedly, and suffered a fire storm in March that killed 83,000. On June 5, 51,000 buildings in four miles of Kobe were burned out by 473 B-29s; Japanese opposition was fierce, as 11 B-29s went down and 176 were damaged. Osaka, where one-sixth of the Empire's munitions were made, was hit by 1,733 tons of incendiaries dropped by 247 B-29s. A firestorm burned out 8.1 square miles, including 135,000 houses; 4,000 died.&lt;ref&gt;William W. Ralph, &quot;Improvised Destruction: Arnold, LeMay, and the Firebombing of Japan,&quot; ''War in History'' Vol. 13, No. 4, 495-522 (2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thomas R. Searle, &quot;'It Made a Lot of Sense to Kill Skilled Workers': The Firebombing of Tokyo in March 1945&quot; The Journal of Military History, Vol. 66, No. 1 (Jan., 2002), pp. 103-133 [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2677346 in JSTOR]&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese local officials reported:
:Although damage to big factories was slight, approximately one-fourth of some 4,000 lesser factories, which operated hand-in-hand with the big factories, were completely destroyed by fire.... Moreover, owing to the rising fear of air attacks, workers in general were reluctant to work in the factories, and the attendance fluctuated as much as 50 percent.

The Japanese army, which was not based in the cities, was largely undamaged by the raids. The Army was short of food and gasoline, but, as Iwo Jima and Okinawa proved, it was capable of ferocious resistance.  The Japanese also had a new tactic that it hoped would provide the bargaining power to get a satisfactory peace, the Kamikaze.

====Kamikaze====
In late 1944 the Japanese invented an unexpected and highly effective new tactic, the Kamikaze suicide plane aimed like a guided missile at American ships. The attacks began in October 1944 and continued to the end of the war.  Most of the aircraft used in kamikaze attacks were converted obsolete fighters and dive-bombers.  The quality of construction was very poor, and many crashed during training or before reaching targets.  Experienced pilots were used to lead a mission because they could navigate; they were not Kamikazes, and they returned to base for another mission. The Kamikaze pilots were inexperienced and had minimal training; however most were well educated and intensely committed to the Emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Syohgo Hattori, &quot;Kamikaze: Japan's Glorious Failure.&quot; ''Air Power History'' 1996 43(1): 14-27. Issn: 1044-016x&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rikihei Inoguchi and Tadashi Nakajima, ''The Divine Wind: Japan's Kamikaze Force in World War II'' (1994)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:D4Y Yoshinori Yamaguchi col.jpg|thumb|right|A &quot;Judy&quot; in a suicide dive against {{USS|Essex|CV-9|6}}. The [[Dive bomber|dive brakes]] are extended and the port wing tank is trailing fuel vapor and smoke November 25, 1944.]]

Kamikaze attacks were highly effective at the [[Battle of Okinawa]] in spring 1945. During the three-month battle, 4000 kamikaze sorties sank 38 US ships and damaged 368 more, killing 4,900 sailors in the American 5th Fleet.  Destroyers and destroyer escorts, doing radar picket duty, were hit hard, as the inexperienced pilots dived at the first American ship they spotted instead of waiting to get at the big carriers.&lt;ref&gt;Robin L. Rielly, ''Kamikazes, Corsairs, and Picket Ships: Okinawa, 1945'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt; Task Force 58 analyzed the Japanese technique at Okinawa in April, 1945:
:&quot;Rarely have the enemy attacks been so cleverly executed and made with such reckless determination. These attacks were generally by single or few aircraft making their approaches with radical changes in course and altitude, dispersing when intercepted and using cloud cover to every advantage. They tailed our friendlies home, used decoy planes, and came in at any altitude or on the water.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;quoted in Norman Friedman, ''U.S. naval weapons: every gun, missile, mine, and torpedo used by the U.S. Navy from 1883 to the present day'' (1982) p 93&lt;/ref&gt;

The Americans decided best defense against Kamikazes was to knock them out on the ground, or else in the air long before they approached the fleet. The Navy called for more fighters, and more warning. The carriers replaced a fourth of their light bombers with Marine fighters; back home the training of fighter pilots was stepped up. More combat air patrols circling the big ships, more radar picket ships (which themselves became prime targets), and more attacks on airbases and gasoline supplies eventually worked. Japan suspended Kamikaze attacks in May, 1945, because it was now hoarding gasoline and hiding planes in preparation for new suicide attacks if the Yankees dared to invade their home islands.

The Kamikaze strategy allowed the use of untrained pilots and obsolete planes, and since evasive maneuvering was dropped and there was no return trip, the scarce gasoline reserves could be stretched further. Since pilots guided their airplane like a guided missile all the way to the target, the proportion of hits was much higher than in ordinary bombing. Japan's industry was manufacturing 1,500 new planes a month in 1945.

Expecting increased resistance, including far more Kamikaze attacks once the main islands of Japan were invaded, the U.S. high command rethought its strategy and used atomic bombs to end the war, hoping it would make a costly invasion unnecessary.&lt;ref&gt;John Ray Skates, ''The invasion of Japan: alternative to the bomb'' (2000) p. 241&lt;/ref&gt;

Toward the end of the war the Japanese press encouraged civilians to emulate the kamikaze pilots who willingly gave their lives to stop American naval forces. Civilians were told that the reward for such behavior was enshrinement as a warrior-god and spiritual protection in the afterlife.&lt;ref&gt;David C. Earhart, &quot;All Ready to Die: Kamikazefication and Japan's Wartime Ideology.&quot; ''Critical Asian Studies'' 2005 37(4): 569-596. Issn: 1467-2715&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe, 1939-1941==
The Luftwaffe gained significant combat experience in the [[Spanish Civil War]],  where it was used to provide close air support for infantry units. The success of the Luftwaffe's [[Ju-87 Stuka]] [[bomber aircraft|dive bomber]]s in the blitzkriegs that shattered Poland in 1939 and France in 1940, gave Berlin  inordinate confidence in its air force.
Military professionals could not ignore the effectiveness of the Stuka, but also observed that France and Poland had minimal effective air defense. Outside Britain, the idea of an integrated air defense system had not emerged; most militaries had a conflict between the advocates of [[anti-aircraft artillery]] and [[fighter aircraft]] for defense, not recognizing that they could be complementary, when under a common system of [[command and control]]; a system that had a [[common operational picture]] of the battle in progress.

===Polish campaign  1939===
Luftwaffe aircraft closely supported the advance of the Army mechanized units, most notably with dive bombers, but also with light observation aircraft, such as [[Fieseler Storch]], that rapidly corrected the aim of artillery, and gave commanders a literal overview of the battle. Allied analysts noted that Poland lacked an effective air defense, and was trying to protect too large an area.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Hargreaves, ''Blitzkrieg Unleashed: The German Invasion of Poland, 1939'' (2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

===France and the low countries; Dunkirk===
German air-ground coordination was also evident in the next campaign, as well as the value of [[air assault]] by parachute and gliders. It was noted that the continental air defenses were not well organized.

While German aircraft inflicted heavy losses at the [[Battle of Dunkirk]], and soldiers awaiting evacuation, while under attack, bitterly asked &quot;Where was the [[Royal Air Force]]&quot;, the RAF had been operating more effectively than other air defenses in the field, meeting the German attacks before they reached the battlefield.

===Battle of Britain===
{{main|Battle of Britain}}
Air superiority or supremacy was a prerequisite to [[Operation Sea Lion]], the planned German invasion of Britain. The Luftwaffe had to destroy the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF).  The warplanes on both sides were comparable. Germany had more planes, but they used much of their fuel getting to Britain, and so had more limited time for combat.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen Bungay, ''Most Dangerous Enemy: The Definitive History of the Battle of Britain'' (2000)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:hurricane mk1 r4118 fairford arp.jpg|thumb|right|Hawker Hurricane, workhorse of the British defence in the Battle of Britain]]

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1978-066-11A, Flugzeuge Heinkel He 111.jpg|thumb|left|204px|A formation of Heinkel He 111 light bombers, the most numerous German bomber of the Battle of Britain]]
The Luftwaffe used 1300 medium bombers guarded by 900 fighters; they made 1500 sorties a day from bases in France, Belgium and Norway.  The Germans realized their [[Ju-87 Stuka]]s and [[Heinkel He 111]]'s were too vulnerable to modern British fighters.  The RAF had 650 fighters, with more coming out of the factories every day. Three main fighter types were involved in the battle - the German [[Messerschmitt Bf109]], and the British [[Hawker Hurricane]] and [[Supermarine Spitfire]]. The Hurricane accounted for most of the British kills throughout the battle owing to the fact that it made up the majority of the RAF fighter force - however, its kill-loss ratio was inferior to that of its counterpart the Spitfire, it is generally accepted that of the three aircraft, it was the least capable, having been designed much earlier than the Bf109 and the Spitfire - indeed, the Bf109 and in particular the Spitfire, an aircraft that has become synonymous with the Battle of Britain and during the battle became somewhat of a symbol of resistance in the minds of the British public, went on to serve in the remainder of the war in a variety of different marks.

The Royal Air Force also had at its disposal a complex and integrated network of reporting stations and operations rooms incorporating the new innovation of Radar. Known as the Dowding system (after [[Hugh Dowding]], the commander of RAF fighter command during the battle and the man who ordered its implementation), it is often credited with giving the RAF the ability to effectively counter German raids without the need for regular patrols by fighter aircraft, increasing the efficiency with which the RAF fighter force could operate. As such, the Dowding system is also often credited with a significant role in the overall outcome of the battle, and comparisons with the air warfare that occurred over France in the spring and early summer of 1940, in which there was no such system and in which the allied air forces were comprehensively defeated, seem to support this.

At first the Germans focused on RAF airfields and radar stations.  However when the RAF bomber forces (quite separate from the fighter forces) attacked Berlin, Hitler swore revenge and diverted the Luftwaffe to attacks on London. Using limited resources to attack civilians instead of airfields and radar proved a major mistake. The success the Luftwaffe was having in rapidly wearing down the RAF was squandered, as the civilians being hit were far less critical than the airfields and radar stations that were now ignored.  London was not a factory city and British aircraft production was not impeded; indeed it went up. The last German daylight raid came on September 30; the Luftwaffe realized it was taking unacceptable losses and broke off the attack; occasional blitz raids hit London and other cities from time. In  all some 43,000 civilians were killed. The Luftwaffe lost 1,887 planes, the British, 1,547. The British victory resulted from more concentration, better radar, and better ground control.

===1941: Invasion of Russia===
[[Operation Barbarossa]] opened in June 1941, with striking initial German successes. In the air, the inferiority of many of their aircraft was still somewhat better than their pilot quality.  The purges of military leadership during the [[Great Purge|Great Terror]] heavily impacted command and control in all services.

The Luftwaffe operated  from bases in Norway against the convoys to Russia. Long-range reconnaissance aircraft, circling the convoys out of their [[anti-aircraft artillery]] range, guided in attack aircraft, submarines, and surface ships.

===Soviet Union===
{{main|Soviet Air Forces#World War II}}
At the outbreak of the war  [[Military of the Soviet Union|VVS (Soviet Airforce)]] had just been purged of most of its top officers and was unready, Stalin in 1939-41 vetoed efforts to prepare for a war with Germany, which he believed could not happen. By 1945 [[Military_production_during_World_War_II#Aircraft|Soviet annual aircraft production]] outstripped that of the [[German aircraft production during World War II|German Reich]];  157,000 aircraft were produced.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hardesty |first=Von |title=Red Phoenix: The Rise of Soviet Air Power 1941–1945 |origyear=1982  |year=1991 |publisher=Smithsonian Institution |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=0874745101 |page=225 |chapter=Barbarossa to Berlin: A Summing Up}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first few days of [[Operation Barbarossa]] in June 1941, the Luftwaffe destroyed 2000 Soviet aircraft, most of them on the ground, at a loss of only 35 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Lonnie O. Ratley, III, &quot;[http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/aureview/1983/mar-apr/ratley.htm A Lesson of History: The Luftwaffe and Barbarossa]&quot;. ''Air University Review''  (March–April 1983).&lt;/ref&gt;  The main weakness accounting for the heavy large aircraft losses in 1941 was the lack of experienced generals, pilots and ground support crews, the destruction of many aircraft on the runways due to command failure to disperse them, and the rapid advance of the Wehrmacht ground troops, forcing the Soviet pilots on the defensive during [[Operation Barbarossa]], while being confronted with more modern German aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|title=Air Power in the Age of Total War
|first=John
|last=Buckley
|publisher=Indiana University Press
|year=1999
|isbn=0-253-33557-4
|pages=134, 143
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviets relied heavily on  [[Ilyushin Il-2]] ''Shturmovik'' ground assault model and the [[Yakovlev Yak-1]] fighter in its many variants;&lt;ref name=&quot;buckley&quot;/&gt; each of which became the most produced aircraft of all time in its class, together accounting for about half the strength of the VVS for most of the Great Patriotic War. The Yak-1 was a modern 1940 design and had more room for development, unlike the relatively mature design of the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]. The [[Yak-9]] brought the VVS to parity with the Luftwaffe, eventually allowing it to gain the upper hand over the Luftwaffe until in 1944, when many Luftwaffe pilots were deliberately avoiding combat.

Chief Marshal of Aviation [[Alexander Novikov]] led the VVS from 1942 to the end of the war, and was credited with introducing several new innovations and weapons systems. For the last year of the war German military and civilians retreating towards Berlin were hounded by constant strafing and light bombing. In one strategic operation the [[Jassy–Kishinev Offensive (August 1944)|Yassy-Kishinev Strategic Offensive]], the [[5th Air Army|5th]] and 17th [[Air army (Soviet Union)|Air Armies]] and the Black Sea Fleet Naval Aviation aircraft achieved a 3.3:1 superiority in aircraft over the [[Luftflotte 4]] and the [[Royal Romanian Air Force]], allowing almost complete freedom from air harassment for the ground troops of the [[2nd Ukrainian Front|2nd]] and [[3rd Ukrainian Front]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Ray Wagner, ed., ''The Soviet Air Force in World War II: The Official History''. Melbourne: Wren Publishing, 1973, p.301. ISBN 0-85885-194-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

==North Africa 1942-43==
{{see also|Operation Torch}}
The [[Operation Torch|American invasion of North Africa]]  was under command of General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]. in November, 1942, at a time when the Luftwaffe was still strong. One of Ike's corps commanders, General [[Lloyd Fredendall]], used his planes as a &quot;combat air patrol&quot; that circled endlessly over his front lines ready to defend against Luftwaffe attackers. Like most infantrymen, Fredendall assumed that all assets should be used to assist the ground forces. More concerned with defense than attack, Fredendall was soon replaced by George Patton.&lt;ref&gt;Wesley Frank Craven and James L. Cate, ''The Army Air Forces in World War II: v. 2. Europe: Torch to Pointblank'' (1949) pp 41-165 [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/fulltext/aaf_wwii-v2.pdf online]&lt;/ref&gt;

Likewise the Luftwaffe made the mistake of dividing up its air assets, and failed to gain control of the air or to cut Allied supplies. The RAF in North Africa, under General [[Arthur Tedder]], concentrated its air power and defeated the Luftwaffe. The RAF had an excellent training program (using bases in Canada), maintained very high aircrew morale, and inculcated a fighting spirit. Senior officers monitored battles by radar, and directed planes by radio to where they were most needed.

The RAF's success convinced Eisenhower that its system maximized the effectiveness of tactical air power; Ike became a true believer. The point was that air power had to be consolidated at the highest level, and had to operate almost autonomously. Brigade, division and corps commanders lost control of air assets (except for a few unarmed little &quot;grasshoppers;&quot; observation aircraft that reported the fall of artillery shells so the gunners could correct their aim. With one airman in overall charge, air assets could be concentrated for maximum offensive capability, not frittered away in ineffective &quot;penny packets.&quot; Eisenhower—a tanker in 1918 who had theorized on the best way to concentrate armor—recognized the analogy. Split up among infantry in supporting roles tanks were wasted; concentrated in a powerful force they could dictate the terms of battle.

The fundamental assumption of air power doctrine was that the air war was just as important as the ground war. Indeed, the main function of the sea and ground forces, insisted the air enthusiasts, was to seize forward air bases. ''Field Manual 100-20,'' issued in July 1943, became the airman's bible for the rest of the war, and taught the doctrine of equality of air and land warfare. The idea of combined arms operations (air, land, sea) strongly appealed to Eisenhower and Douglas MacArthur. Eisenhower invaded only after he was certain of [[air supremacy]], and he made the establishment of forward air bases his first priority. MacArthur's leaps reflected the same doctrine. In each theater the senior ground command post had an attached air command post. Requests from the front lines went all the way to the top, where the air commander decided whether to act, when and how. This slowed down response time—it might take 48 hours to arrange a strike—and involved rejecting numerous requests from the infantry for a little help here, or a little intervention there.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate, ''The Army Air Forces in World War II: v. 2. Europe: Torch to Pointblank'' (1949) pp 205-6&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operations against Allied convoys===
German air reconnaissance against North Atlantic and Russian convoys increased, with CAM fighters still the main defense. The Luftwaffe's first major attack on the convoys began on 25 April 1942 when the 34-ship convoy PQJ6 was attacked. PQ17 to Murmansk started with 36 ships; only two made it through when the Admiralty falsely thinking Germany was attacking with a battleship ordered the convoy, and its escort, to scatter. There was no battleship but Luftwaffe sank 1 cruiser, 1 destroyer, 2 patrol boats (4, 000 tons), and 22 merchant ships (139,216 tons).  Nevertheless most convoys did get through.&lt;ref&gt;Max Hastings, ''The Second World War: A World in Flames'' (2004) p 131&lt;/ref&gt;

==1943==
In some areas, such as the most intense part of the Battle of the Atlantic, the Germans enjoyed fleeting success. Grueling operations wasted the Luftwaffe away on the eastern front after 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Manfred Griehl, ''Fighters Over Russia'' (1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1943 the Allied strategic bombers were directed against U-boat pens, which were easy to reach and which represented a major strategic threat to Allied logistics. However, the pens were very solidly built—it took 7,000 flying hours to destroy one sub there, about the same effort that it took to destroy one-third of Cologne.&lt;ref&gt;Webster &amp; Franklin, 4:24&lt;/ref&gt;

Japan was also still recovering from Midway. It kept producing planes but made few innovations and the quality of its new pilots deteriorated steadily. Gasoline shortages limited the training and usage of the air forces.

===Mediterranean Theater===
In the Mediterranean, the Luftwaffe tried to stop the invasions of Sicily and Italy with tactical bombing. They failed because the Allied air forces systematically destroyed most of their air fields. The Germans ferociously opposed the [[Operation Shingle|American landing at Anzio]] in February, 1944, but the Luftwaffe was outnumbered 5 to 1 and so totally outclassed in equipment and skill that it inflicted little damage. Italian air space belonged to the Allies, and the Luftwaffe's strategic capability was nil. The Luftwaffe threw everything it had against the [[Allied invasion of Italy|Salerno beachhead]], but was outgunned ten to one, and then lost the vital airfields at [[Foggia]].

Foggia became the major base of the 15th Air Force. Its 2,000 heavy bombers hit Germany from the south while the 4,000 heavies of the 8th Air Force used bases in Britain, along with 1,300 RAF heavies. While bad weather in the north often canceled raids, sunny Italian skies allowed for more action. After that the Luftwaffe had only one success in Italy, a [[Air raid on Bari|devastating raid on the American port at Bari]], in December 1943. Only 30 out of 100 bombers got through, but one hit an ammunition ship which was secretly carrying a stock of [[mustard gas]] for retaliatory use should the Germans initiate the use of gas. Clouds of American mustard gas caused over 2,000 Allied and civilian casualties.&lt;ref&gt;George Southern, ''Poisonous inferno: World War II tragedy at Bari Harbour'' (2002)&lt;/ref&gt;

==1944-45==
In early 1944, the Allies continued to bomb Germany, while carefully attacking targets in France that could interfere with the invasion, planned for June.

===Destroying the Luftwaffe, 1944===
In late 1943 the AAF suddenly realized the need to revise its basic doctrine: strategic bombing against a technologically sophisticated enemy like Germany was impossible without air supremacy. (The B-29 did not need escorts against Japan.) General Arnold replaced Ira Eaker with Carl Spaatz and Jimmy Doolittle, who fully appreciated the new reality. They provided fighter escorts all the way into Germany and back, and cleverly used B- 17s as bait for Luftwaffe planes, which the escorts then shot down. Doolittle's slogan was &quot;The First Duty of 8th AF Fighters is to Destroy German Fighters.&quot;, one aspect of modern &quot;Offensive Counter-Air&quot; (OCA).  In one &quot;Big Week&quot; in February, 1944, American bombers protected by hundreds of fighters, flew 3,800 sorties dropping 10,000 tons of high explosives on the main German aircraft and ball-bearing factories. The US suffered 2,600 casualties, with a loss of 137 bombers and 21 fighters. Ball bearing production was unaffected, as Nazi munitions boss Albert Speer repaired the damage in a few weeks; he even managed to double aircraft production. Sensing the danger, Speer began dispersing production into numerous small, hidden factories.&lt;ref&gt;Craven &amp; Cate,  3:43-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Horst Boog, ed. ''Germany and the Second World War: Volume VII: The Strategic Air War in Europe and the War in the West and East Asia, 1943-1944/5'' (2006) pp 159-256&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-377-2801-013, Flugzeug Messerschmitt Me 110.jpg|thumb|250px|Bf 110 built to shoot down heavy Allied bombers]]
Paradoxically, the Luftwaffe would have to come out and attack or see its planes destroyed at the factory. Before getting at the bombers the Germans had to confront the more numerous American fighters. The heavily armed [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]] could kill a bomber, but its slower speed made it easy prey for Thunderbolts and Mustangs. The big, slow twin-engine [[Junkers Ju 88]] was dangerous because it could stand further off and fire its rockets into the tight B-17 formations; but it too was hunted down. Germany's severe shortage of aviation fuel had sharply curtailed the training of new pilots, and most of the instructors had been sent into battle. Rookie pilots were rushed into combat after only 160 flying hours in training compared to 400 hours for the AAF, 360 for the RAF and 120 for the Japanese. The low quality German pilots of this late stage in the war never had a chance against more numerous, better trained Allied pilots.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, ''Strategy for Defeat'' p 308-9&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans began losing one thousand planes a month on the western front (and another 400 on the eastern front). Realizing that the best way to defeat the Luftwaffe was not to stick close to the bombers but to aggressively seek out the enemy, Doolittle told his Mustangs to &quot;go hunting for Jerries. Flush them out in the air and beat them up on the ground on the way home.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Stephen L. McFarland and Wesley Phillips Newton, ''To Command the Sky: The Battle for Air Superiority Over Germany, 1942-1944 '' (2006) p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; On one occasion German air controllers identified a large force of approaching B-17s, and sent all the Luftwaffe's 750 fighters to attack. The bogeys were all Mustangs, which shot down 98 interceptors while losing 11. The actual B-17s were elsewhere, and completed their mission without a loss. In February, 1944, the Luftwaffe lost 33% of its frontline fighters and 18% of its pilots; the next month it lost 56% of its fighters and 22% of the pilots. April was just as bad, 43% and 20%, and May was worst of all, at 50% and 25%. German factories continued to produce many new planes, and inexperienced pilots did report for duty; but their life expectancy was down to a couple of combat sorties. Increasingly the Luftwaffe went into hiding; with losses down to 1% per mission, the bombers now got through.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate 3:664&lt;/ref&gt;

By April, 1944, Luftwaffe tactical air power had vanished, and Eisenhower decided he could go ahead with the invasion of Normandy. He guaranteed the invaders that &quot;if you see fighting aircraft over you, they will be ours.&quot;.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;McFarland and Newton, ''To Command the Sky: The Battle for Air Superiority Over Germany, 1942-1944 '' (2006) p. 239&lt;/ref&gt;

===Normandy===
As the Luftwaffe disintegrated in 1944, escorting became less necessary and fighters were increasingly assigned to tactical ground-attack missions, along with the medium bombers. To avoid the lethal fast-firing [[20mm antiaircraft gun|20mm flak guns]], pilots come in fast and low (under enemy radar), made a quick run, then disappeared before the gunners could respond. The main missions were to keep the Luftwaffe suppressed by shooting up airstrips, and to interdict the movement of munitions, oil and troops by attacking at railway bridges and tunnels, oil tank farms, canal barges, trucks and moving trains. Occasionally a choice target was discovered through intelligence. The  three days after D-Day [[Ultra (cryptography)|Ultra]] intelligenve pinpointed the location of [[Panzer Group West]] headquarters. A quick raid destroyed its radio gear and killed many key officers, ruining the Germans' ability to coordinate a panzer counterattack against the beachheads.

On D-Day itself, Allied aircraft flew 14,000 sorties, while the Luftwaffe managed a mere 260, mostly in defense of its own battered airfields. In the two weeks after D-Day, the Luftwaffe lost 600 of the 800 planes it kept in France. From April through August, 1944, both the AAF's and the RAF's strategic bombers were placed under Eisenhower's direction, where they were used tactically to support the invasion. Airmen protested vigorously against this subordination of the air war to the land campaign, but Eisenhower forced the issue and used the bombers to simultaneously strangle Germany's supply system, burn out its oil refineries, and destroy its warplanes. With this accomplished, Eisenhower relinquished control of the bombers in September.&lt;ref&gt;Murray, ''Luftwaffe'' 183, 207, 211; Craven &amp; Cate, 3:47&lt;/ref&gt;

In Europe in summer 1944 the AAF started operating out of bases in France. It had about 1,300 light bomber crews and 4,500 fighter pilots. They claimed destruction of 86,000 railroad cars, 9,000 locomotives, 68,000 trucks, and 6,000 tanks and armored artillery pieces. P-47 Thunderbolts alone dropped 120,000 tons of bombs and thousands of tanks of napalm, fired 135 million bullets and 60,000 rockets, and claimed 3,916 enemy planes destroyed. Beyond the destruction itself, the appearance of unopposed Allied fighter-bombers ruined morale, as privates and generals alike dived for the ditches. Field Marshal [[Erwin Rommel]], for example, was seriously wounded in July, 1944, when he dared to ride around France in the daytime. The commander of the elite 2nd Panzer Division fulminated:&lt;ref&gt;Craven &amp; Cate  3:227, 235&lt;/ref&gt;
:&quot;They have complete mastery of the air. They bomb and strafe  every movement, even single vehicles and individuals. They  reconnoiter our area constantly and direct their artillery  fire....The feeling of helplessness against enemy aircraft  has a paralyzing effect, and during the bombing barrage the  effect on inexperienced troops is literally 'soul-shattering.'&quot;

===Battle of the Bulge===
At the [[Battle of the Bulge]] in December 1944, the Allies were caught by surprise by a large scale German offensive.  In the first days bad weather grounded all planes. When the skies cleared, 52,000 AAF and 12,000 RAF sorties against German positions and supply lines immediately doomed Hitler's last offensive. General [[George Patton]] said the cooperation of XIX TAC Air Force was &quot;the best example of the combined use of air and ground troops that I ever witnessed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Craven &amp; Cate 3:272&lt;/ref&gt;

===Strategic operations===
An around-the-clock campaign attacked Germany, with British bombers at night and U.S. aircraft during the day. The aircraft, tactics, and doctrines were different; there is argument how complementary they were in achieving strategic effect.

The Luftwaffe reached maximum size of 1.9 million airmen in 1942.  Grueling operations wasted it away on the eastern front after 1942.&lt;ref&gt;British Air Ministry, ''Rise and Fall of the German Air Force'' (1948)&lt;/ref&gt; It lost most of its fighter planes to Mustangs in 1944 while trying to defend against massive American and British air raids, and many of the men were sent to the infantry. The Luftwaffe in 1944-45 concentrated on ant-aircraft defenses, especially the flak batteries&lt;ref&gt;Edward B. Westermann, ''Flak: German Anti-Aircraft Defenses, 1914-1945'' (2005) pp 257-84&lt;/ref&gt; that surrounded all major German cities and war plants. They consumed a large fraction of all German munitions production in the last year of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Overy, ''Air War'' p 121&lt;/ref&gt;  The flak units employed hundreds of thousands of women, who engaged in combat against the Allied bombers.&lt;ref&gt;D'Ann Campbell, &quot;Women in Combat: The World War Two Experience in the United States, Great Britain, Germany, and the Soviet Union,&quot; ''Journal of Military History'' (April 1993), 57:301-323 [http://americanhistoryprojects.com/downloads/ww2/combat.htm online]
&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[jet engine|jet-powered]] German [[Me-262]] ''Schwalbe'' far outclassed the P-51 on an individual basis.&lt;ref&gt;The British aand American jets were in the development stage when the war ended.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, its protracted development history – Hitler personally ordered design modifications to make the aircraft functional as a fighter-bomber – ensured that it was produced too late and in too small numbers to stem the Allied tide. The Germans also developed [[air-to-surface missile]]s (''[[Fritz X]]'', ''[[Henschel Hs 293|Hs 293]]'',) [[surface-to-air missiles]] (''[[Wasserfall]]'',) [[cruise missile]]s (''[[V-1 (flying bomb)|V-1]]'') and [[ballistic missile]]s (''[[V-2]]'',) and other advanced technologies of air warfare, to little strategic effect. Captured examples of these weapons, and especially of [[Operation Paperclip|their designers]], contributed to Allied and Soviet military technologies of the [[Cold War]], and also of the [[space race]].

===Destroying Germany's Oil and Transportation===
Besides knocking out the Luftwaffe, the second most striking achievement of the strategic bombing campaign was the destruction of the German oil supply. Oil was essential for U-boats and tanks, while very high quality aviation gasoline was essential for piston planes.&lt;ref&gt;Jet planes ran on cheap kerosene, and rockets used plain alcohol; the railroad system used coal, which was in abundant supply.&lt;/ref&gt; Germany had few wells, and depended on imports from Russia (before 1941) and Nazi ally Romania, and on synthetic oil plants that used chemical processes to turn coal into oil. Heedless of the risk of Allied bombing, the Germans had carelessly concentrated 80% of synthetic oil production in just 20 plants. These became a top priority for the AAF and RAF in 1944, and were targets for 210,000 tons of bombs. The oil plants were very hard to hit, but also hard to repair. As graph #1 shows, the bombings dried up the oil supply in the summer of 1944. An extreme oil emergency followed, which grew worse month by month.

The third notable achievement of the bombing campaign was the degradation of the German transportation system—its railroads and canals (there was little truck traffic.) In the two months before and after D-Day the American Liberators (B-24), Flying Fortresses and British Lancasters hammered away at the French railroad system. Underground Resistance fighters sabotaged some 350 locomotives and 15,000 freight cars every month. Critical bridges and tunnels were cut by bombing or sabotage. Berlin responded by sending in 60,000 German railway workers, but even they took two or three days to reopen a line after heavy raids on switching yards. The system deteriorated quickly, and it proved incapable of carrying reinforcements and supplies to oppose the Normandy invasion. To that extent the assignment of strategic bombers to the tactical job of interdiction was successful. When Bomber Command hit German cities, it inevitably hit some railroad yards. The AAF made railroad yards a high priority, and gave considerable attention as well to bridges, moving trains, ferries, and other choke points. The &quot;transportation policy&quot; of targeting the railroad system came in for intense debate among Allied strategists. It was argued that enemy had the densest and best operated railway system in the world, and one with a great deal of slack. The Nazis systematically looted rolling stock from conquered nations, so they always had plenty of locomotives and freight cars. Furthermore, most traffic was &quot;civilian,&quot; and urgent troop train traffic would always get through. The critics exaggerated the resilience of the German system. As wave after wave of bombers blasted away, repairs took longer and longer. Delays became longer and more frustrating. Yes, the troop trains usually got through, but the &quot;civilian&quot; traffic that did not get through comprised food, uniforms, medical equipment, horses, fodder, tanks, fuel, howitzers, flak shells and machine guns for the front lines, and coal, steel, spare parts, subassemblies, and critical components for munitions factories. By January, 1945, the transportation system was cracking in dozens of places, and front-line units had more luck trying to capture Allied weapons than waiting for fresh supplies of their own.

===Effect of the strategic bombing ===
Germany and Japan were burned out and lost the war in large part because of strategic bombing.&lt;ref&gt;Richard Overy, ''Why the Allies Won'' (1997) pp 2, 20&lt;/ref&gt; Targeting became somewhat more accurate in 1944, but the real solution to inaccurate bombs was more of them. The AAF dropped 3.5 million bombs (500,000 tons) against Japan, and 8 million (1.6 million tons) against Germany.&lt;ref&gt;The RAF expended about the same tonnage against Germany; Navy and Marine bombs against Japan are not included, nor are the two atomic bombs.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Hamburg after the 1943 bombing.jpg|thumb|right|Typical bomb damage in [[Bombing of Hamburg in World War II|Hamburg, Germany 1945]]]]

While it can be calculated that strategic bombing cost the US and Britain more money than it cost Germany, that calculation is irrelevant. The Allies had plenty of money. The cost of the US tactical and strategic air war against Germany was 18,400 planes lost in combat, 51,000 dead, 30,000 POWs, and 13,000 wounded. Against Japan, the AAF lost 4,500 planes, 16,000 dead, 6,000 POWs, and 5,000 wounded; Marine Aviation lost 1,600 killed, 1,100 wounded. Naval aviation lost several thousand dead.&lt;ref&gt;Office of Statistical Control, ''Army Air Forces Statistical Digest: World War II'' (1945) table 34 [http://www.usaaf.net/digest/t34.htm online]&lt;/ref&gt;

One fourth of the German war economy was neutralized because of direct bomb damage, the resulting delays, shortages and roundabout solutions, and the spending on anti-aircraft, civil defense, repair, and removal of factories to safer locations. The raids were so large and so often repeated that in city after city the repair system broke down. In 1944 the bombing prevented the full mobilization of the German economic potential.&lt;ref&gt;R. J. Overy, ''The Air War: 1939-1945'' (1980) p 122-25&lt;/ref&gt; Planning minister [[Albert Speer]] and his staff were brilliant in improvising solutions and work-arounds, but their challenge became more difficult every week as one backup system after another broke down.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Speer, ''Inside the Third Reich: Memoirs'' (1970) pp 278-91&lt;/ref&gt; By March, 1945, most of Germany's factories, railroads and telephones had stopped working; troops, tanks, trains and trucks were immobilized. With all their great cities crumbling into rubble, with the awareness the Allies had a weapons system they could not answer, Germans suddenly realized they were going to lose the war. In February 1945, General Marshall overruled the ethical objections of Air Force commanders and ordered a terror attack on Berlin. The goal was to help the Soviet advance and to convince the Nazis their cause was hopeless; 2,900 died (both sides exaggerated the total to 25,000 for propaganda purposes).  Far more civilians died at Dresden Feb. 13-14, where a firestorm erupted.&lt;ref&gt;Mark Clodfelter, ''Beneficial Bombing: The Progressive Foundations of American Air Power, 1917-1945'' (2011) pp. 148, 174, 178&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joseph Goebbels]], Hitler's propaganda minister, was disconsolate when his beautiful ministry buildings were totally burned out: &quot;The air war has now turned into a crazy orgy. We are totally defenseless against it. The Reich will gradually be turned into a complete desert.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Trevor-Roper, ed. ''Final entries, 1945: the diaries of Joseph Goebbels'' (1978) p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;

By July, 1945, Japan was almost totally shut down. The American and British airmen had achieved the goals of strategic bombing — but neither Berlin nor Tokyo would surrender.

==See also==
{{See also|Battle of Britain|Battle of the Atlantic}}

==References==
''This article incorporates material from the [http://www.citizendium.org Citizendium] article &quot;[http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/World_War_II,_air_war World War II, air war]&quot;, which is licensed under the [[Wikipedia:Text of Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License|Creative Commons Attribution/Share-Alike 3.0 Unported License]] but not under the [[Wikipedia:Text of the GNU Free Documentation License|GFDL]].''

{{Citizendium}}

{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
Based on [http://en.citizendium.org/wiki/World_War_II%2C_air_war/Bibliography Citizendium bibliography]

* Boog, Horst, ed. ''The Conduct of the Air War in the Second World War: An International Comparison'' (1992)
* Murray, Williamson. ''Luftwaffe: Strategy for Defeat, 1933-1945'' (1985), standard history [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Murray_B12.htm online edition]
* Overy, Richard J. ''The Air War, 1939-1945'' (1981), sophisticated standard interpretation, covering all major countries
* Werrell, Kenneth P. &quot;The Strategic Bombing of Germany in World War II: Costs and Accomplishments,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 73 (1986) 702-713; good place to start. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1902984 in JSTOR]

===By country===
====America====
* Craven, Wesley Frank and J. L. Cate. ''The Army Air Forces in World War II'' (1949), vol 1-5 standard, very thorough history of strategy and operations in Europe and Pacific [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/ online edition]
* Futtrel, Robert Frank. ''Ideas, Concepts, Doctrines: Basic Thinking in the United States Air Force, 1907-1960'' (1989) influential overvieww [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/fulltext/ideas_&amp;_weapons.pdf online edition]
* Golberg, Alfred ed. ''A History of the United States Air Force, 1907-1957'' (1957) [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/goldberghistory.htm online edition]
* Official Guide to the Army Air Forces'' (1944), reprinted as ''AAF: A Directory, Almanac and Chronicle of Achievement'' (1988)

====Britain====
* Bungay, Stephen. ''The Most Dangerous Enemy: The Definitive History of the Battle of Britain'' (2nd ed. 2010)
* Fisher, David E, ''A Summer Bright and Terrible: Winston Churchill, Lord Dowding, Radar, and the Impossible Triumph of the Battle of Britain'' (2005) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/1593760477?p=S00N excerpt online]
* Hough, Richard and Denis Richards. ''The Battle of Britain (1989) 480 pp
* Messenger, Charles, &quot;Bomber&quot; Harris and the Strategic Bombing Offensive, 1939-1945'' (1984), defends Harris
* Overy, Richard. ''The Battle of Britain: The Myth and the Reality'' (2001) 192 pages [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0393322971 excerpt and text search]
* Richards, Dennis, et al. ''Royal Air Force, 1939-1945: The Fight at Odds - Vol. 1'' (HMSO 1953), official history [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=64821947 vol 1 online edition] [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=54046342 vol 2 online edition]
* Terraine, John. ''A Time for Courage: The Royal Air Force in the European War, 1939-1945'' (1985)
* Verrier, Anthony. ''The Bomber Offensive'' (1969), British
* Webster, Charles and Noble Frankland, The Strategic Air Offensive Against Germany, 1939-1945 (HMSO, 1961), 4 vol.  Important official British history
* Wood, Derek, and Derek D. Dempster. ''The Narrow Margin: The Battle of Britain and the Rise of Air Power 1930-40'' (1975) [https://www.questia.com/library/book/the-narrow-margin-the-battle-of-britain-and-the-rise-of-air-power-1930-40-by-derek-d-dempster-derek-wood.jsp online edition]

====Germany====
* British Air Ministry. ''Rise and Fall of the German Air Force (1948, reprint 1969), excellent official history; reprint has introduction by H. A. Probert, who was not the author
* Fritzsche, Peter.  &quot;Machine Dreams: Airmindedness and the Reinvention of Germany.&quot; ''American Historical Review'', 98 (June 1993): 685-710.  Air warfare was seen as a growing threat to Germany, and it became a means of national mobilization and redemption. Nazi Germany believed that air warfare would allow the country to rebuild itself in a racial compact. During World War II, air warfare became a means for rejuvenating authority domestically and increasing imperial influence abroad.
* Galland, Adolf. ''The First and the Last: German Fighter Forces in World War II'' (1955)
* Irving, David. ''The Rise and Fall of the Luftwaffe: The Life of Erhard Milch'' (1973) [http://www.fpp.co.uk/books/Milch/Milch.pdf online edition]
* Murray, Williamson. ''Luftwaffe: Strategy for Defeat, 1933-1945'' (1985), standard history [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Murray_B12.htm online edition]
* Overy, Richard. ''Goering'' (1984)
* Wilt, Alan F. ([[Alan F. Wilt]]) ''War from the Top: German and British Military Decision Making During World War II'' (1990)
* Overy R. J. &quot;The German Pre-War Aircraft Production Plans: November 1936-April 1939,&quot; ''The English Historical Review'' Vol. 90, No. 357 (Oct., 1975), pp.&amp;nbsp;778–797 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0013-8266%28197510%2990%3A357%3C778%3ATGPAPP%3E2.0.CO%3B2-5 in JSTOR]

====Japan====
* Coox, Alvin D. &quot;The Rise and Fall of the Imperial Japanese Air Forces,&quot; in Alfred F. Hurley and Robert C. Erhart, eds. ''Air Power and Air Warfare'' (1979) 84-97.
* Inoguchi, Rikihei and Tadashi Nakajima, The Divine Wind: Japan's Kamikaze Force in World War II'' (1958)

====Russia====
* Gordon, Yefim. ''Soviet Air Power in World War 2'' (2008)
* Wagner, Ray, ed. ''Soviet Air Force in World War ll: The Official History'' (1973)
* Whiting, Kenneth R. &quot;Soviet Air Power in World War II,&quot; in Alfred F. Hurley and Robert C. Erhart, eds. ''Air Power and Air Warfare'' (1979) 98-127

===Airmen===
* Byrd, Martha. ''Chennault: Giving Wings to the Tiger'' (1987) 451 pp., the standard biography
* Ford, Daniel. ''Flying Tigers: Claire Chennault and the American Volunteer Group'' (1991).
* Caine, Philip D. ''American Pilots in the RAF: The WWII Eagle Squadrons'' (1993)
* Craven, Wesley Frank and J. L. Cate. ''The Army Air Forces in World War II'' (1949), vol. ''6: Men and Planes; vol 7. ''Services Around the World (including medical, engineering, WAC)  [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/cravenAAFWWII.htm online edition]
* Davis, Benjamin O. ''Benjamin O. Davis, Jr., American: An Autobiography.’’ (1991), prominent black flier
* Dunn, William R. ''Fighter Pilot: The First American Ace of World War II'' (1982)
* Francis, Charles E., and Adolph Caso. ''The Tuskegee Airmen: The Men Who Changed a Nation'' (1997) [http://books.google.com/books?id=VyuedRwZre8C&amp;pg=PA19&amp;ots=L6LyvPNUkL&amp;dq=black+airmen+world+war&amp;num=30&amp;sig=Sk95THRu_ik4-uPvGa8USx3EvZY#PPP1,M1 online excerpt]; African American airmen who fought in Europe
* Francis, Martin. ''The Flyer: British Culture and the Royal Air Force, 1939-1945'' (2009), culture and ideology of flying
* Freeman, Roger. ''The American Airman in Europe'' (1992)
* Freeman, Roger. ''The British Airman'' (1989)
* Hawkins, Ian ed. ''B-17s Over Berlin: Personal Stories from the 95th Bomb Group (H)'' (1990)
* Link, Mae Mills and Hubert A. Coleman. ''Medical Support of the Army Air Forces in World War II'' (GPO, 1955)
* McGovern, James R. ''Black Eagle: General Daniel &quot;Chappie&quot; James, Jr.'' (1985), leading black pilot.
* Miller, Donald L. ''Masters of the Air: America's Bomber Boys Who Fought the Air War Against Nazi Germany'' (2006) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0743235444?p=S017 excerpt]
* Morrison, Wilbur H. ''Point of No Return: The Story of the 20th Air Force'' (1979)
* Nanney, James S. ''Army Air Forces Medical Services in World War II'' (1998) [http://www.usaaf.net/ww2/medical/ online edition]
* Newby, Leroy W. ''Target Ploesti: View from a Bombsight'' (1983)
* Nichol, John. ''Tail-End Charlies: The Last Battles of the Bomber War, 1944—45'' (2006) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0312349874?p=S00V excerpt]
* Osur, Alan M. ''Blacks in the Army Air Forces during World War II : The Problem of Race Relations'' (1986) [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/osurblacks.htm online edition]

===Commanders===
====Air Commanders: American====
* Byrd, Martha.''Chennault: Giving Wings to the Tiger'' (1987) 451 pp.
* Davis, Richard G. ''Carl A. ''Spaatz and the Air War in Europe (1993)
* Frisbee, John L. ''ed. ''Makers of the United States Air Force’’ (USAF, 1987), short biographies
* Kenney, George C. ''General Kenney Reports: A Personal History of the Pacific War'' (1949), primary source
* Leary, William ed. ''We Shall Return! MacArthur's Commanders and the Defeat of Japan, 1942-1945'' (1988)
* LeMay, Curtis. ''Mission with LeMay'' (1965), autobiography, primary source
* Meilinger, Phillip S. ''Hoyt S. ''Vandenberg: The Life of a General'' (1989)
* Mets, David R. ''Master of Airpower: General Carl A. Spaatz (1988) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=82380683 online edition]

====HAP Arnold and Stimson====
* Arnold, Henry H. ''Global Mission'' (1949), autobiography.
* Bonnett, John. &quot;Jekyll and Hyde: Henry L. Stimson, Mentalite, and the Decision to Use the Atomic Bomb on Japan.&quot; ''War in History'' 1997 4(2): 174-212. Issn: 0968-3445 Fulltext: [[Ebsco]]
* Coffey, Thomas. ''Hap: General of the Air Force Henry Arnold’’ (1982)
* Davis, Richard G. ''HAP: Henry H. Arnold, Military Aviator'' (1997) 38 pp [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/davishap.htm online edition]
* Huston, John W. &quot;The Wartime Leadership of 'Hap' Arnold.&quot; In Alfred F. Hurley and Robert C. Erhart, eds. ''Air Power and Air Warfare'' (1979) 168-85.
* Huston, John W.,  ''American Airpower Comes of Age: Gen Henry H. Arnold's World War II Diaries,'' (2002), primary source; [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Huston_B84.htm vol. 1 online] [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Huston_B85.htm vol. 2 online]
* Larrabee, Eric. ''Commander in Chief: Franklin Delano Roosevelt, His Lieutenants, and Their War'' (1987), chapters on Arnold and LeMay.
* Malloy, Sean L. ''Atomic Tragedy: Henry L. Stimson and the Decision to Use the Bomb Against Japan'' (2008)

====Air Commanders: Other====
* Messenger, Charles. ''Bomber&quot; Harris and the Strategic Bombing Offensive, 1939-1945'' (1984), defends Harris
* Irving, David. ''The Rise and Fall of the Luftwaffe: The Life of Erhard Milch'' (1973) [http://www.fpp.co.uk/books/Milch/Milch.pdf online edition]
* Overy, Richard. ''Goering'' (1984)

===Technology: Jets, Rockets, Radar, Proximity Fuze===
* Baxter, James Phinney. ''Scientists Against Time'' (1946)
* Brown, Louis. ''A Radar History of World War II: Technical and Military Imperatives'' (1999) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0750306599?p=S00J online excerpt]
* Constant II, Edward W. ''The Origins of the Turbojet Revolution'' (1980)
* Longmate, Norman. ''Hitler's Rockets: The Story of the V-2s'' (1985).
* Moye, William T. &quot;Developing the Proximity Fuze, and Its Legacy'' (2003) [http://www.amc.army.mil/amc/ho/studies/fuze.html online version]
* Neufeld, Michael J. &quot;Hitler, the V-2, and the Battle for Priority, 1939-1943.&quot; ''The Journal of Military History,'' 57 (July 1993): 5-38. [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0899-3718(199307)57%3A3%3C511%3AHTVATB%3E2.0.CO%3B2-L in JSTOR]
* Neufeld, Michael J. ''The Rocket and the Reich: Peenemunde and the Coming of the Mallistic Missile Era'' (1995)
* Swords, Seán S. ''Technical History of the Beginnings of Radar'' (1986)

===Tactical Planes, Weapons, Tactics &amp; Combat===
* Batchelor, John and Bryan Cooper. ''Fighter: A History of Fighter Aircraft'' (1973)
* Cooling, Benjamin Franklin ed. ''Close Air Support'' (1990) GPO
* Craven, Wesley Frank and J. L. Cate. ''The Army Air Forces in World War II'' (1949), ''vol. 6: Men and Planes'' [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/cravenAAFWWII.htm online edition]
* Francillon, R. ''J. ''Japanese Aircraft of the Pacific War'' (1970)
* Gruen, Adam L. ''Preemptive Defense: Allied Air Power Versus Hitler’s V-Weapons, 1943–1945'' (1999) [http://www.usaaf.net/ww2/preemptivedefense/ online edition]
* Hallion, Richard P. ''D Day 1944: Air Power Over the Normandy Beaches and Beyond'' (1998) [http://www.usaaf.net/ww2/dday/ online edition]
* Hallion, Richard P. ''Strike From the Sky: The History of Battlefield Air Attack, 1911-1945'' (1989)
* Hogg, I.V. ''Anti-Aircraft: A History of Air Defence'' (1978)
* ''Jane's Fighting Aircraft of World War II'' (1989)
* Lundstrom, John B. ''The First Team: Pacific Naval Air Combat From Pearl Harbor to Midway'' (1984)
* McFarland, Stephen L. and Wesley Phillips Newton. ''To Command the Sky: The Battle for Air Superiority over Germany, 1942-1944'' (1991)
* Mikesh, Robert C. ''Broken Wings of the Samurai: the Destruction of the Japanese Airforce'' (1993)
* Mixon, Franklin G. &quot;Estimating Learning Curves in Economics: Evidence from Aerial Combat over the Third Reich.&quot; ''KYKLOS'' 46 (Fall 1993) 411-19. ''Germans learned faster (if they survived)
* Mortensen. Daniel R. ed.  ''Airpower and Ground Armies: Essays on the Evolution of Anglo-American Air Doctrine, 1940–1943,'' (1998) [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Mortenson_B50.htm online edition]
* Okumiya, Masatake and Jiro Horikoshi, with Martin Caidin, ''Zero!'' (1956)
* Schlaifer, Robert. ''Development of Aircraft Engines'' (1950)
* Sherrod, Robert. ''History of Marine Corps Aviation in World War II'' (1952)
* Spire, David N. ''Air Power for Patton's Army: The 19th Tactical Air Command in the Second World War'' (2002) [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/spireair.htm online edition]
* Warnock, A. Timothy. ''Air Power versus U-boats: Confronting Hitler's Submarine Menace in the European Theater'' (1999) [http://www.usaaf.net/ww2/uboats/ online edition]
* Werrell, Kenneth P. ''Archie, Flak, AAA, and SAM: A Short Operational History of Ground-Based Air Defense'' (GPO 1988) [http://www.maxwell.af.mil/au/aul/aupress/catalog/books/Werrell_B28.htm online edition]

===Strategic bombing===
====Atomic Bomb &amp; Surrender of Japan====
* Allen, Thomas B. and Norman Polmar. ''Code-Name Downfall: The Secret Plan to Invade Japan-And Why Truman Dropped the Bomb'' (1995)
* Bernstein, Barton. &quot;Eclipsed by Hiroshima and Nagasaki: Early Thinking About Tactical Nuclear Weapons,&quot; ''International Security'' (Spring 1991) 149-173 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0162-2889(199121)15%3A4%3C149%3AEBHANE%3E2.0.CO%3B2-P in JSTOR]
* Bernstein, Barton F. &quot;The Atomic Bombings Reconsidered.&quot; ''Foreign Affairs'', 74 (Jan-Feb 1995) 135-52.
* Feis, Herbert. ''Japan Subdued: The Atomic Bomb and the End of the War in the Pacific'' (1961)
* Gordin, Michael D. ''Five Days in August: How World War II Became a Nuclear War'' (2007) 209 pages [http://books.google.com/books?id=N7eq7AgZKokC  excerpt and text search]
* Holley, I. B. ''ed. ''Hiroshima After Forty Years'' (1992)
* Jones, Vincent C. ''Manhattan: The Army and the Bomb'' (GPO, 1985), official construction history
* Libby, Justin. &quot;The Search for a Negotiated Peace: Japanese Diplomats Attempt to Surrender Japan Prior to the Bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki.&quot; ''World Affairs'', 156 (Summer 1993): 35-45.
* Miles, Rufus E. Jr. &quot;Hiroshima: The Strange Myth of a Half Million American Lives Saved&quot; ''International Security'' 10 (Fall 1985): 121-40.
* Pape, Robert A. &quot;Why Japan Surrendered.&quot; ''International Security'' 18 (Fall 1993): 154-201 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0162-2889(199323)18%3A2%3C154%3AWJS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-C in JSTOR]
* Rhodes, Richard. ''The Making of the Atomic Bomb'' (1986), good overview [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0684813785 excerpt and text search]
* Rotter, Andrew J. ''Hiroshima: The World's Bomb'' (2008) [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0192804375  excerpt and text search]
* Skates, John. ''The Invasion of Japan'' (1994), excellent military history of the greatest non-battle of all time
* VanderMuelen, Jacob. &quot;Planning for V-J Day by the U.S. Army Air Forces and the Atomic Bomb Controversy.&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies'' 16 (June 1993), 227-39. AAF did not expect quick surrender; bomb was military use
* Walker, J. Samuel. &quot;The Decision to Drop the Bomb: A Historiographical Update,&quot; ''Diplomatic History'' 14 (1990) 97-114. Especially useful.
* Walker, J. Samuel. ''Prompt and Utter Destruction: Truman and the Use of Atomic Bombs Against Japan'' (2004) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/080785607X?p=S00L online excerpt]

====Ethics &amp; Civilians====
* Childers, Thomas. &quot;'Facilis descensus averni est': The Allied Bombing of Germany and the Issue of German Suffering,&quot; ''Central European History'' Vol. 38, No. 1 (2005), pp. 75-105 [http://www.jstor.org/stable/4547498 in JSTOR]
* Crane, Conrad C. ''Bombs, Cities and Civilians: American Airpower Strategy in World War II'' (1993)
* Crane, Conrad C. ''&quot;Evolution of U.S. ''Strategic Bombing of Urban Areas,&quot; Historian 50 (Nov 1987) 14-39, defends AAF
* Davis, Richard G. &quot;Operation 'Thunderclap': The US Army Air Forces and the Bombing of Berlin.&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies'' (March 1991) 14:90-111.
* Garrett, Stephen A., ''Ethics and Airpower in World War II: The British Bombing of German Cities'' (1993)
* Havens, Thomas R. H. ''Valley of Darkness: The Japanese People and World War Two'' (1978)
* Hopkins, George F. &quot;Bombing and the American Conscience During World War II,&quot; ''The Historian'' 28 (May 1966): 451-73
* Lammers, Stephen E. &quot;William Temple and the bombing of Germany: an Exploration in the Just War Tradition.&quot; ''The Journal of Religious Ethics,'' 19 (Spring 1991): 71-93. Explains how the Archbishop of Canterbury justified strategic bombing.
* Markusen, Eric, and David Kopf. ''The Holocaust and Strategic Bombing: Genocide and Total War in the Twentieth Century'' (1995)
* Schaffer, Ronald. &quot;American Military Ethics in World War II: The Bombing of German Civilians,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 67 (1980) 318-34 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0021-8723(198009)67%3A2%3C318%3AAMEIWW%3E2.0.CO%3B2-F in JSTOR]
* Schaffer, Ronald. ''Wings of Judgment: American Bombing in World War II'' (1985)
* Spaight, J. ''M. ''Air Power and War Rights'' (1947), legal
* Speer, Alfred. ''Inside the Third Reich'' (1970), memoir of top Nazi economic planner
* Walzer, Michael. ''Just and Unjust Wars: A Moral Argument with Historical Illustrations'' (1977), philosophical approach

====Strategic bombing: Doctrine====
* Boog, Horst. ''ed. ''The Conduct of the Air War in the Second World War'' (1992)
* Clodfelter, Mark. &quot;Aiming to Break Will: America's World War II Bombing of German Morale and its Ramifications,&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies,'' June 2010, Vol. 33 Issue 3, pp 401–435
* Davis, Richard G. &quot;Bombing Strategy Shifts, 1944-45,&quot; ''Air Power History'' 39 (1989) 33-45
* Griffith, Charles. ''The quest Haywood Hansell and American strategic bombing in World War II'' (1999) [http://books.google.com/books?id=VMjqpOmQbesC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=hansell+air+war+plan#PPP2,M1 online edition]
* Hansell, Jr., Haywood S. ''Air Plan That Defeated Hitler'' (1980) [http://books.google.com/books?id=yIvxVcOTmkEC&amp;dq=hansel+air+war+plan online version]
* Kennett, Lee B. ''A History of Strategic Bombing'' (1982)
* Koch, H. W. &quot;The Strategic Air Offensive against Germany: the Early Phase, May–September 1940.&quot; ''The Historical Journal'', 34 (March 1991) pp 117–41. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/2639710 online at JSTOR]
* Levine, Alan J. ''The Strategic Bombing of Germany, 1940-1945'' (1992) [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=15370919 online edition]
* MacIsaac, David. ''Strategic Bombing in World War Two'' (1976)
* McFarland, Stephen L. &quot;The Evolution of the American Strategic Fighter in Europe, 1942-44,&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies'' 10 (1987) 189-208
* Messenger, Charles, &quot;Bomber&quot; Harris and the Strategic Bombing Offensive, 1939-1945'' (1984), defends Harris
* Overy. Richard. &quot;The Means to Victory: Bombs and Bombing&quot; in Overy, ''Why the Allies Won'' (1995), pp 101–33
* Sherry, Michael. ''The Rise of American Air Power: The Creation of Armageddon'' (1987), important study 1930s-1960s
* Smith, Malcolm. &quot;The Allied Air Offensive,&quot; ''Journal of Strategic Studies'' 13 (Mar 1990) 67-83
* Verrier, Anthony. ''The Bomber Offensive'' (1968), British
* Webster, Charles and Noble Frankland, The Strategic Air Offensive Against Germany, 1939-1945 (HMSO, 1961), 4 vol.  Important official British history
* Wells, Mark K. ''Courage and air warfare: the Allied aircrew experience in the Second World War'' (1995)
* Werrell, Kenneth P. &quot;The Strategic Bombing of Germany in World War II: Costs and Accomplishments,&quot; ''Journal of American History'' 73 (1986) 702-713; good place to start. [http://www.jstor.org/pss/1902984 in JSTOR]
* Werrell, Kenneth P. ''Death From the Heavens: A History of Strategic Bombing'' (2009)

====Strategic bombing: Planes and Targets====
* Beck, Earl R. ''Under the Bombs: The German Home Front, 1942-1945'' (1986)
* Berger, Carl. ''B-29: The Superfortress'' (1970)
* Bond, Horatio, ed. ''Fire and the Air War'' (1974)
* Boog, Horst, ed. ''Germany and the Second World War: Volume VII: The Strategic Air War in Europe and the War in the West and East Asia, 1943-1944/5'' (Oxford UP, 2006), 928pp official German history vol 7 [http://www.amazon.com/Germany-Second-World-War-Strategic/dp/0198228899/  excerpt and text search]; [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=115474949 online edition]
* Charman, T. C. ''The German Home Front, 1939-45'' (1989)
* Craven, Wesley Frank and J. L. Cate. ''The Army Air Forces in World War II'' (1949), ''vol. 6: Men and Planes'' [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/Annotations/cravenAAFWWII.htm online edition]
* Cross, Robin. ''The Bombers: The Illustrated Story of Offensive Strategy and Tactics in the Twentieth Century'' (1987)
* Daniels, Gordon ed. ''A Guide to the Reports of the United States Strategic Bombing Survey (1981)
* Davis, Richard G. ''Bombing the European Axis Powers: A Historical Digest of the Combined Bomber Offensive, 1939-1945'' (2006) [http://web.archive.org/web/20090305023036/http://aupress.au.af.mil/Books/Davis/Davis_B99.pdf  online edition]
* Edoin, Hoito. ''The Night Tokyo Burned: The Incendiary Campaign against Japan'' (1988), Japanese viewpoint
* Hansen, Randall. ''Fire and Fury: The Allied Bombing of Germany, 1942-1945'' (2009), says AAF was more effective than RAF
* Hastings, Max. ''Bomber Command'' (1979)
* Haulman, Daniel L. ''Hitting Home: The Air Offensive Against Japan,'' (1998) [http://www.usaaf.net/ww2/hittinghome/ online edition]
* Hecks, Karl. ''Bombing 1939-45: The Air Offensive Against Land Targets in World War Two'' (1990)
* Jablonsky, Edward. ''Flying Fortress'' (1965)
* ''Jane's Fighting Aircraft of World War II'' (1989), reprint of 1945 edition
* Johnsen, Frederick A.  ''B-17 Flying Fortress: The Symbol of Second World War Air Power'' (2000) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0071344454?p=S00K excerpt]
* MacIsaac, David,  ed. ''The United States Strategic Bombing Survey (10 v, 1976) reprints of some reports
* Madej, Victor. ed. ''German war economy: the motorization myth'' (1984) (based on v. 64a, 77, and 113 of the U.S. Strategic Bombing  reports on oil and chemical industry.)
* Madej, Victor. ed. ''The War machine: German weapons and manpower, 1939-1945'' (1984)
* Middlebrook, Martin. ''The Schweinfurt-Regensburg Mission: American Raids on 17 August 1943'' (1983)
* Mierzejewski, Alfred C. ''The Collapse of the German War Economy, 1944-1945: Allied Air Power and the German National Railway'' (1988)
* Pape, Robert A. ''Punishment and Denial: The Coercive Use of Air Power'' (1995)
* Ralph, William W. &quot;Improvised Destruction: Arnold, LeMay, and the Firebombing of Japan,&quot; ''War in History'', Vol. 13, No. 4, 495-522 (2006) [http://wih.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/13/4/495 online at Sage]
* Read, Anthony, and David Fisher. ''The Fall of Berlin'' (1993)
* Searle, Thomas R. &quot;'It Made a Lot of Sense to Kill Skilled Workers': The Firebombing of Tokyo in March 1945&quot; ''The Journal of Military History,'' Vol. 66, No. 1 (Jan., 2002), pp.&amp;nbsp;103–133 [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0899-3718(200201)66%3A1%3C103%3A%22MALOS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-Q in JSTOR]
* United States Strategic Bombing Survey. ''The Campaigns of the Pacific War. ''(1946) [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/USSBS/PTO-Campaigns/index.html Online edition]
* United States Strategic Bombing Survey. ''Summary Report: (European War)'' (1945) [http://www.anesi.com/ussbs02.htm online edition] key primary source
* United States Strategic Bombing Survey. ''Summary Report: (Pacific War)'' (1946) [http://www.anesi.com/ussbs01.htm online edition] key primary source
* Westermann, Edward B. ''Flak: German Anti-Aircraft Defenses, 1914-1945'' (2005)

===Online books===
* [http://www.airforcehistory.hq.af.mil/Publications/titleindex.htm Air Force official histories (mostly pamphlets)]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Air Warfare Of World War Ii}}
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II]]

[[de:Luftkrieg im Zweiten Weltkrieg]]
[[fr:Aviation dans la Seconde Guerre mondiale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
