<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25219204" ns="0" title="Korea University Business School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University 
|name           = Korea University Business School
|native_name    = {{lang|ko|고려대학교 경영대학 (高麗大學校 經營大學)}}
|image_name     = KoreaUniversityIntlShield.png
|image_size     = 200px
|established    = May 5, 1905
|type           = [[Private university|Private]]
|city           = [[Seoul]]
|country        = [[South Korea]]
|dean           = Lee, Jin Kyu
|faculty        = 87 (full-time)
|undergrad      = 
|postgrad       = 
|website        = [http://biz.korea.edu/ biz.korea.edu]
}}

'''Korea University Business School''' located in [[Seoul]], [[South Korea]] is the [[business school]] of [[Korea University]], a member of the [[SKY (universities)|SKY]] universities. It was established in 1905 and is the country's first collegiate business school. KUBS is the first and only school in Korea to be accredited by both AACSB and EQUIS.

==History==
In 1905, the school was founded as the nation's first Commerce Department. (Commerce Department and Law Department are the first two departments of Bosung College, the prototype of Korea University) Korea University Business School has traditionally been one of the strongest business schools not only in Korea but also in Asia. The business schools of Seoul National University and Yonsei University are Korea University Business School's long competitors. Recently however, due to aggressive investments from the school administration and generous endowments from the alumni, Korea University Business School has established itself as the top business school domestically. One of the more prestigious economic publications of Korea, Hankook Economy (한국경제), which ranks domestic business schools annually, ranked Korea University Business School to be the top business school of Korea for three consecutive years 2008, 2009, and 2010, with considerable point differences with the second in rank, Yonsei University Business School. With the exception of the field of accounting, it is nowadays generally accepted that Korea University Business School holds superiority over all other business schools of Korea.

==Notable alumni==
* Chang Ha Sung
* Lee Myung Bak
* Kim Seung-you

{{Korea University}}
{{SKY business schools}}

{{coord missing|South Korea}}

==References==

http://www.hankyung.com/

{{DEFAULTSORT:Business School}}
[[Category:Korea University]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Seoul]]
[[Category:Education in Seoul]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
