<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25235167" ns="0" title="Embassy of Poland, London"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Diplomatic_Mission
  | name = Ambasada Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Londynie
&lt;small&gt;Embassy of the Republic of Poland in London&lt;/small&gt;

[[Image:Polish Governmental and Diplomatic Plaque.png|175px]]
  | image =
  | address = 47 Portland Place, London W1B 1JH
  | location = [[Portland Place]], [[London]], [[United Kingdom]]
  | ambassador = [[Barbara Tuge-Erecińska]]
}}
{{further|[[Poland – United Kingdom relations]]}}
The '''Embassy of Poland''' in [[London]] ({{lang-pl|Ambasada Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Londynie}}) is the diplomatic mission of [[Poland]] to the [[United Kingdom]]. The chancery is located at 47 [[Portland Place]], [[London]].

==Main chancery building==
[[Image:Polish Embassy 47 Portland Place London.jpg|thumb|300px|left|The Polish Embassy Chancery building at 47 Portland Place, London]]

Shortly after the [[Second Polish Republic]] gained independence in 1919, there seemed to be a general feeling of ambivalence to Britain demonstrated by most Polish statesmen. Believing that good relations with traditional ally [[French Third Republic|France]], and neighbour [[Weimar Republic|Germany]], were of more importance, the Polish government largely neglected relations with the United Kingdom and it was not until 1929 that the first Polish legation was sent to establish a permanent embassy in London.

Since 1929, the Polish embassy in London has played an important role in Polish history. With the realisation in the late 1930s that war with Germany was inevitable, the Polish government set about requesting military aid from the British government; the government also signed a three-way mutual defence pact with the United Kingdom and France in order to make sure Poland would never have to stand alone against a German invasion. Thus, much of the bureaucracy surrounding these pre-war pacts found itself centred in the halls and corridors of number 47, Portland Place.

As the war progressed and with the transfer of the [[Polish government-in-exile]] to London, Portland Place again became not only the nerve centre of Polish relations with the United Kingdom, but of the entire [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Poland)|Polish Foreign Office]]. The embassy soon had to acquire a number of other buildings throughout the city in order to house the large number of diplomats and politicians required to make the government in exile work. For a long time, the building represented a democratic Poland, fighting for its freedom and its territorial integrity. However, in the post-war world (in which the [[People's Republic of Poland]] became a [[satellite state]] of the [[Soviet Union]]) the British government refused any longer to recognise the government in exile&lt;ref&gt;Editor Peter D. Stachura Chapter 4 by Wojciech Rojek The Poles in Britain 1940-2000 ISBN 0 7146 8444 9 Page 33&lt;/ref&gt; and thus the London Poles (Officials of the Polish government in exile) had to vacate the Polish embassy on Portland Place and were left only with the exile-president's private residence at 43 Eaton Place, whilst in the meantime officials of the new communist regime moved into the Georgian-era embassy building.

Since the fall of the [[Polish United Workers' Party]] in 1989 and the re-establishment of democratic rule in 1990 under President [[Lech Wałęsa]], the embassy at 47 Portland Place has again been the seat of the primary diplomatic legation of the Polish Republic to the United Kingdom. It was here that the initial process to repatriate the official presidential seal and symbols of office (they had previously been evacuated to London with the government in exile at the beginning and for the duration of the war) to the Polish people was begun.

The embassy is located on [[Portland Place]], a wide Georgian boulevard in central London which also hosts a number of other major embassies such as the Chinese and Portuguese embassies.

==Other sections and the Sikorski Institute==

The Sikorski Institute and Museum is a Polish cultural information centre and the embassy's section for the promotion of Polish tourism, culture and history. To this end the institute also includes, at its Kensington site, a museum of Polish history. The museum is largely dedicated to Polish military history and includes a large number of exhibits relating to the time spent by the Polish authorities as the 'Polish Government in Exile' in London.

Other Polish embassy sections in London include the consular section, located in close vicinity to the main chancery at Portland Place; the consular section is located on New Cavendish Street. This section of the embassy deals with all documentation for foreigners requiring a visa or other permission whose intent it is to travel to Poland or the Schengen area. Additionally the consular officers deal with passport applications and confirmations of Polish citizenship made both by foreigners and Polish nationals, they offer birth registration services and can offer information and guidance on many other topics ranging from death of a loved one abroad or transfer of the body to Poland to legal services and recommendations for personal safety.

==HE the Ambassador==

The Current ambassador of the Republic of Poland to the Court of Saint James is Mrs [[Barbara Tuge-Erecińska]]; she presented her credentials to HM Queen Elizabeth II on 24 October 2006.

[[Polish ambassadors to the United Kingdom|List of all previous Polish ambassadors to the Court of St James]]

==See also==
*[[Poland – United Kingdom relations]]
*[[List of diplomatic missions of Poland]]
*[[Foreign relations of Poland]]
*[[Polish nationality law]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.londyn.polemb.net/index.php?document=18 Embassy of Poland in London] {{pl icon}} {{en icon}}

{{Polish diplomatic missions}}

[[Category:Diplomatic missions in London]]
[[Category:Diplomatic missions of Poland]]
[[Category:Poland–United Kingdom relations]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
