<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25248034" ns="0" title="Embassy of Poland, Canberra"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox_Diplomatic_Mission
  | name = Ambasada Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Canberze
&lt;small&gt;Embassy of the Republic of Poland in Canberra&lt;/small&gt;

[[Image:Polish Governmental and Diplomatic Plaque.png|175px]]
  | image =
  | address = 7 Turrana Street, Yarralumla, ACT 2600,  Australia
  | location = Turrana Street, [[Yarralumla]], [[Canberra]], [[Australia]]
  | ambassador = Andrzej Jaroszyński
}}

The '''Polish Embassy''' in [[Canberra]] is the diplomatic mission of the [[Republic of Poland]] to the [[Commonwealth of Australia]]. The chancery is located at 7 Turrana Street, Yarralumla, Canberra.

The main building of the Polish embassy in Canberra is based on a large green site in the Yarralumla area of the city. The embassy, which was built in the 1990s provides space for all sections of the embassy including both the chancery and the consular department. Being based on a large site, there is apt space for a garden and the embassy even has its own recreation area for staff complete with swimming pool. To the rear there is also a private residence belonging to the embassy which was constructed at the same time and in the same style, it is here that the ambassador resides with his family.

Interestingly, Australia's largest mountain, [[Mount Kosciuszko]], is named for Polish national hero [[Tadeusz Kościuszko]]. To reflect this interesting quirk of fate there is a hall at the Polish embassy named after the famous general and a plaque which marks its significance.

The current ambassador of the Polish Republic to the Commonwealth of Australia is Mr Andrzej Jaroszyński.

{{Image gallery
|title=
|lines=4
|width=160
|height=140
|Embassy of the Republic of Poland.jpg|The chancery of the Polish embassy in Canberra|The Polish embassy's chancery in Canberra
}}

==See also==
*[[List of diplomatic missions of Poland]]
*[[Foreign relations of Poland]]
*[[Polish nationality law]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.canberra.polemb.net/ Embassy of Poland in Canberra] {{pl icon}} {{en icon}}

{{Polish diplomatic missions}}

[[Category:Diplomatic missions in Canberra]]
[[Category:Diplomatic missions of Poland]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
