<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25247313" ns="0" title="Embassy of Poland, Beijing"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Diplomatic_Mission
  | name = Ambasada Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Pekinie
&lt;small&gt;Embassy of the Republic of Poland in Beijing&lt;/small&gt;

[[Image:Polish Governmental and Diplomatic Plaque.png|175px]]
  | image =
  | address = 1, Ritan Rd, 100600 Beijing
  | location = Ritan Road, [[Beijing]], [[People's Republic of China]]
  | ambassador = Tadeusz Chomicki
}}

The '''Polish Embassy''' in [[Beijing]] is the diplomatic mission of the [[Republic of Poland]] to the [[People's Republic of China]]. The chancery is located at 1, Ritan Rd, Beijing.

The main cancery of the Polish embassy in Beijing is located, as with many other embassies, in the special diplomatic quarter of the city. Situated behind a large and ornate screen fence, the embassy is guarded night and day by officers of the [[People's Armed Police]]. The building was originally designed in a socialist realist style, but upon construction was actually built in a largely modernist style with a few elements of classicism, notably the columns supporting the portico. This was to make the embassy more distinguishable as the permanent seat of an important European nation and not present a less 'prestigious' facade to the average passerby.

The current ambassador of the Polish Republic to the People's Republic of China is Mr Tadeusz Chomicki.

{{Image gallery
|title=
|lines=4
|width=160
|height=140
|Polish Embassy Beijing 9361.JPG|Polish embassy in Beijing from front|The chancery of the Polish embassy in Beijing seen from in front of the gates
||Building of the Polish Embassy consular section in Beijing|The Polish embassy in Beijing as seen from Ritan Road
||The state flag of Poland|The state flag of Poland, as used on all Polish Embassy buildings
}}

==See also==
*[[List of diplomatic missions of Poland]]
*[[Foreign relations of Poland]]
*[[Polish nationality law]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.pekin.polemb.net/ Embassy of Poland in Beijing] {{pl icon}} {{cn icon}}

{{Polish diplomatic missions}}

[[Category:Diplomatic missions in Beijing]]
[[Category:Diplomatic missions of Poland]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
