<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25255521" ns="0" title="Haitian general election, 2010–2011"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Election
| election_name      = Haitian presidential election, 2010–2011
| country            = Haiti
| type               = presidential
| ongoing            = no
| previous_election  = Haitian presidential election, 2006
| previous_year      = 2006
| next_election      = Next presidential election
| next_year          = Next
| election_date      = 28 November 2010 and 20 March 2011
| colour1 =#FF7070
| colour2 = A50B5E
| colour3 = CF1020
| image1             = [[File:Martelly 2011.jpg|100px]]
| nominee1           = [[Michel Martelly]]
| colour1            =
| party1             = Repons Peyizan
| popular_vote1      = 234,617 (1st Round)&lt;br&gt;716,986 (2nd Round)
| percentage1        = 21.84% (1st Round)&lt;br&gt;67.57% (2nd Round)
| image2             = [[File:Manigat.JPG|120px]]
| nominee2           = [[Mirlande Manigat]]
| colour2            =
| party2             = Rally of Progressive National Democrats
| popular_vote2      = 336,878 (1st Round)&lt;br&gt;336,747 (2nd Round)
| percentage2        = 31.37% (1st Round)&lt;br&gt;31.74% (2nd Round)
| image3             = [[File:Celestin.jpg|114px]]
| nominee3           = [[Jude Célestin]]
| colour3            =
| party3             = Unity (Haiti)
| popular_vote3      = 241,462  
| percentage3        = 22.48%
| map_image          =
| map_size           =
| map_caption        =
| title              = President
| before_election    = [[René Préval]]
| before_party       = Lespwa
| after_election     = [[Michel Martelly]]
| after_party        = Repons Peyizan
}}
{{Politics of Haiti}}

The '''Haitian general election''', originally scheduled in [[Haiti]] for 28 February 2010, was postponed to 28 November. Ten [[Senate of Haiti|senators]] and all 99 [[Chamber of Deputies of Haiti|deputies]] were to be elected.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSTRE5AP03K20091126 | work=Reuters | title=Aristide party barred from Haiti's February ballot | date=2009-11-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Presidential elections were also held. A run-off was originally scheduled for 16 January as no candidate received 50 percent of the votes cast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/28/world/americas/28haiti.html?ref=americas | work=The New York Times | first=Randal C. | last=Archibold | title=Haiti Election, Set for Sunday, Marred by ID Card Problems | date=2010-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was postponed until 20 March 2011 as election officials said they could not hold the runoff while awaiting results from re-polling,&lt;ref  name=&quot;postponement&quot;&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2011/01/201114234022990732.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;english.people.com.cn&quot;&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90855/7273565.html&lt;/ref&gt; with results expected on 31 March.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2011/01/201112943130670652.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Official results, announced on 21 April, 2011, showed [[Michel Martelly]] defeating [[Mirlande Manigat]] in the second round of the presidential election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-13163550 | work=BBC News | title=Michel Martelly officially declared Haitian president | date=2011-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/05/world/americas/05haiti.html?hp | work=The New York Times | first=Randal C. | last=Archibold | title=Singer Michel Martelly Elected Haiti's President | date=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Due to the [[2010 Haitian earthquake|January 2010 earthquake]], election was indefinitely postponed;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSN27162845._CH_.2400 | work=Reuters | title=INTERVIEW-Haitian president says Feb. 28 elections postponed | first=Patricia | last=Zengerle | date=2010-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; although November 28 was then decided as the date to hold the [[President of Haiti|Presidential]] and [[National Assembly of Haiti|legislative]] [[Elections in Haiti|election]]s.  Following the earthquake, there were concerns of instability in the country, and the election came amid international pressure over instability in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz&quot;/&gt; The election was termed in the media as a &quot;seismic&quot; one. This would be the third democratic election in Haitian history.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazreview&quot;&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/peopleandpower/2010/11/20101117839903761.html Haiti: Seismic Election - PEOPLE AND POWER - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidential candidates==
The deadline to file candidacy for the elections was August 7.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Daniel |first=Trenton |url=http://www.miamiherald.com/2010/08/08/1766529/at-least-20-candidates-file-to.html |title=At least 20 candidates file to run in Haiti's presidential elections - Haiti |publisher=MiamiHerald.com |date=2010-01-24 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The list of presidential candidates was to have become official on August 17 after the nine-member provisional electoral council was to announce the eligibility criteria.&lt;ref name=&quot;belpo&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.belpolitik.com/haitianpolitics.php/25 |title=2010 Haiti Presidential Candidates List |publisher=Belpolitik.com |date=2006-12-15 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the election commission postponed its ruling until August 19 because of disagreement on the electoral law which stipulates that candidates must hold an Haitian passport and have five consecutive years of residence in Haiti, among other requirements. This was to affect Wyclef Jean, Jacques Edouard Alexis, and Leslie Voltaire.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz3&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/2010818183714693940.html |title=Haiti presidential list delayed - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The absence of the [[Fanmi Lavalas]] (FL) party was notable because of its popular support. [[Peter Hallward]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://links.org.au/files/hallward-haiti-2010-exploiting-disaster-23-sept-2010.pdf |title=Haiti 2010: Exploiting Disaster 2010 - Haiti |accessdate=2010-12-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; explained: &quot;The final FL list of candidates was endorsed by the party leader ([[Jean Bertrand Aristide]]) by fax, but at the last minute the CEP invented a new requirement, knowing FL would be unable to meet it: Aristide, still exiled in South Africa and denied entry to Haiti, would have to sign the list in person.&quot;

===Wyclef Jean===
Musician [[Wyclef Jean]] left Haiti for the [[Haiti – United States relations|United States]] at the age of 9, he said he is qualified to run for President and was in Haiti to initiate the legal process with lawyers and have his fingerprints taken by the judicial police to run for president. He did, however, declare that &quot;There are a lot of rumors that I am running for president. I have not declared that. If we decide to move forward, I am pretty sure that we [would] have all our paperwork straight.&quot; He added that after discussions with his family he would &quot;decide on what we're going to do because it is a big sacrifice.&quot; His aides said he would officially announce his candidacy on [[CNN]] in the United States before flying back to Haiti to enter the race. Some analysts predicted Jean's popularity with the youth of Haiti could help him &quot;easily win the presidential election if his candidacy were approved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE66Q5TX20100730 | work=Reuters | title=Wyclef Jean steps toward Haitian presidential race | date=2010-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.usmagazine.com/moviestvmusic/news/wyclef-jean-to-run-for-president-of-haiti-2010267|title=Wyclef Jean to Run for President of Haiti?|publisher=UsMagazine.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 August, he officially registered as a candidate for [[Viv Ansanm]] (&quot;Live Together&quot;)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Wyclef Jean files papers to stand for Haiti president|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-10888173|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=6 August 2010 | date=2010-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; party with the motto &quot;''Fas a Fas''.&quot; (&quot;Face to Face&quot;)&lt;!--sourced TV--&gt; The head of the party, [[Daniel Jean Jacques]], confirmed Jean would be the party's candidate for President. Jean spoke of his nomination as &quot;a moment in time and in history. It's very emotional. The United States has Barack Obama and Haiti has Wyclef Jean.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/20108522481897583.html |title=Hip-hop star vies for Haiti top job - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-08-06 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He told [[CNN]]'s [[Wolf Blitzer]] that he was running, despite Blitzer's questions about Jean's actual citizenship and passport facts. He also resigned from the chairmanship of ''[[Yéle Haiti]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.exclaim.ca/articles/generalarticlesynopsfullart.aspx?csid1=146&amp;csid2=844&amp;fid1=48631 Exclaim! Magazine]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Wikinews|Wyclef Jean considering standing for president of Haiti}}
He was criticised by [[Pras Michel]], one of his former bandmates in the [[Fugees]], for the decision to run for president.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz2&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/20108843010173527.html |title=Ex-bandmate criticises Wyclef Jean - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-08-08 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others criticised him for his lack of political experience and a vague platform he was to have run on. In the United States he was also criticised by [[Sean Penn]] and [[Arcade Fire]]'s [[Win Butler]] who said &quot;Technically, [Wyclef Jean] shouldn't be eligible because he hasn't been a resident of Haiti. And I think him not speaking French and not being fluent in [[Creole language|Creole]] would be a really major issue in trying to run a really complex government, like the government in Haiti. It would kind of be like [[Arnold Schwarzenegger]] only speaking [[Austrian German|Austrian]] and being elected president of the United States after [[New York City]] and [[Los Angeles|L.A.]] had burned to the ground...I think he is a great musician and he really passionately cares about Haiti. I really hope he throws his support behind someone who is really competent and really eligible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://exclaim.ca/articles/generalarticlesynopsfullart.aspx?csid1=146&amp;csid2=844&amp;fid1=48988 |title=Exclaim News: Arcade Fire’s Win Butler Adds Opposition to Wyclef Jean’s Haitian Presidential Plans |publisher=Exclaim.ca |date=2004-03-03 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 20, 2010, he was deemed ineligible to run for the presidency and his candidacy was rejected by Haiti's Electoral Council. While he accepted the ruling, many supporters protested the decision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/2010821175952666775.html |title=Haitians rally for Jean's candidacy - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; He asked his supporters to stay calm in the wake of the ruling. He also responded in saying he would file an appeal and that &quot;[The political establishment] are trying to keep us out of the race.&quot; He argued that he could not comply with the law so strictly because President René Préval had appointed him as a roving ambassador in 2007 and he was allowed to travel and live outside the country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/201082302330863719.html Hip-hop star to appeal poll bid - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haitielections2010.com/details.php?id=360 Haïti Elections 2010 :: Toutes les infos sur les élections haïtiennes de 2010&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final list of candidates===
There were supposed to have been 34 candidates in the preliminary race but a Haitian political website came up with 38.&lt;ref name=&quot;belpo&quot;/&gt;

*[[Charles Henri Baker]], a prominent businessman in the apparel industry. Charles Henri Baker is running under the [[Respect (Haiti)|Respè Party]].
*[[Jean Henry Ceant]], a prominent notaire and founder of Aimer Haiti which operated one of the few hospitals after the January 12 quake.
*[[Jacques-Édouard Alexis]], a two-time former prime minister&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz3&quot;/&gt; who was forced to resign in the aftermath of food riots in 2008.
*[[Jude Célestin]], Executive director of the government's road-building outfit, the National Center of Equipment, and member of President René Préval's Unity (Inite) party.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
*[[Eddy Delaleu]], President, Founder, and Chief Executive Officer of the NGO ''Operation Hope for Children of Haiti'' since its inception in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://delaleuforhaiti2011.com/ | title=Dr. Eddy Delaleu President for Haiti 2011|date=|accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lavarice Gaudin]], an Aristide ally and Miami activist and radio commentator.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
*[[Wilson Jeudi]], mayor of Delmas who organized a sister-city relationship with North Miami.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
*[[Chavannes Jeune]], development agent, civil engineer and evangelist who came in 3rd place in 2006 election.
*[[Raymond Joseph]], former ambassador to the United States and Wyclef Jean's uncle.
*[[Mirlande Manigat]], a longtime opposition leader, professor, and former [[first lady]].{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}
*[[Michel Martelly]], a compas musician and entertainer whose lyrics have poked fun at the concept of the Haitian presidency.&lt;ref&gt;Wadner, Pierre (2010). [http://www.dominionpaper.ca/weblogs/wadner_pierre/3799 &quot;Michel Martelly, Stealth Duvalierist&quot;] ''[[The Dominion (newspaper)|The Dominion]]''. Dec 16, 2010. Retrieved Jan 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Yvon Neptune]], an architect and ex-senator who served as prime minister under former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide.
*[[Leslie Voltaire]], an US-educated urban planner, former minister,&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz3&quot;/&gt; and government liaison to the United Nations.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

Other candidates include: [[Axan Abellard]], [[Charles Voigt]], [[Claire Lydie Parent]], [[Dejean Belizaire]], [[Duroseau Vilaire Cluny]], [[Eric Charles]], [[Francois Turnier]], [[Garaudy Laguerre]], [[Gary Guiteau]], [[Genard Joseph]], [[Gerard Blot]], [[Guy Theodore]], [[Jacques Philippe Eugene]], [[Jean Bertin]], [[Jean Hector Anacacis]], [[Josette Bijou]], [[Kesnel Dalmacy]], [[Leon Jeune]], [[Mario Eddy Rodriguez]], [[Menelas Vilsaint]], [[Olicier Pieriche]], [[Rene Saint-Fort]], [[Wilkens C. Gilles]], [[Yves Christalin]], [[Paul Arthur Fleurival]].

==Campaign==
President René Préval told the UN, &quot;It is important that we take this difficult process to a conclusion, with rigour, equality, and transparency, essential conditions for consolidating our young democracy. I therefore call on all the national stakeholders and our overseas friends so we can successfully cross this electoral crossroads together.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://gadebate.un.org/Portals/1/statements/634209430444531250HT_fr.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Two issues for candidates to answer were considered rebuilding from the earthquake earlier in the year and an [[2010 Haiti cholera outbreak|outbreak of cholera]] less than two months before the election, which was blamed on the United Nations by many Haitians.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazreview&quot;/&gt; The UN alleged that the outbreak was used for &quot;political reasons because of forthcoming elections,&quot; as the government in Haiti sent its own forces to &quot;protect&quot; the peacekeepers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/video/americas/2010/11/20101117123020447605.html Haiti riots against UN heat up - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The election was termed in the media as a &quot;seismic&quot; one.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazreview&quot;/&gt;

==Controversy==
Following demonstration and demands by the opposition to hold elections amid a parliamentary call that he can stay beyond his 7 February mandate, President [[René Préval]] issued decrees ordering the country's nine-member provisional electoral council to organise the election. However he still did not address calls for the council itself to be replaced before a vote is held.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljaz&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/06/201062821156633689.html |title=November polls for Haiti - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-06-28 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the constitutional legitimacy and impartiality of the [[Provisional Electoral Council|CEP]] having been challenged.&lt;ref name=&quot;IJDH&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://ijdh.org/archives/13138 |title=The International Community Should pressure the Haitian Government For Prompt and Fair Elections |publisher=Institute for Justice and Democracy in Haiti |date=2010-06-30 |accessdate=2011-01-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some questioned whether Haiti was ready to hold an election following the earthquake that left more than a million people in makeshift camps and without IDs. There was also a fear that the election could throw the country into a political crisis due to a lack of transparency and voting fraud.&lt;ref name=&quot;al jaz&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/08/201088152649176110.html |title=Haiti presidential poll concerns - Americas |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2010-08-08 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Foreign relations of Canada|Canada]] had also pressured Haiti to hold elections as stipulated in its [[Constitution of Haiti|constitution]]. It wanted a firm commitment to holding elections by the end of the year as domestic opposition grew to incumbent President René Préval's response to the earthquake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=The Canadian Press |url=http://www.cbc.ca/canada/montreal/story/2010/05/21/mtl-cannon-haiti-elections.html#ixzz0w3iOKgnL |title=CBC News - Montreal - Canada presses for Haitian elections |publisher=Cbc.ca |date=2010-05-21 |accessdate=2010-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the elections and allegedly accepted instability, Haitian security services were given special training by foreign forces.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/video/americas/2010/10/2010101172027910500.html Haiti security tight ahead of poll - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations]] voted to extend [[MINUSTAH]]'s mandate amid fears of instability. This was greeted with protesters in [[Port-au-Prince]] carrying banners reading &quot;Down with the occupation,&quot; and burning the [[flag of Brazil]], as they had the largest contingent in MINUSTAH. Despite months of relative calm after the earthquake, this represented a &quot;chorus of opposition to René Préval, Haiti's president, and to UN forces.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/10/2010101516941370819.html Anti-UN protesters block Haiti base - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the cholera outbreak, there were fears that the election could be postponed. However, the head of MINUSTAH, [[Edmond Mulet]], said that it should not be delayed as that could lead to a political vacuum with untold potential problems.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/11/2010112005720398357.html Unrest 'must not stop Haiti polls' - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-1st round===
There have also been calls for Martelly to be included in the run-off; however, he has stated that he would not take part if Célestin is also a candidate in the run-off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-11950240 | work=BBC News | title=Haiti ruling party HQ set alight by election protesters | date=2010-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; A recount was announced on 10 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-11964180 | work=BBC News | title=Haiti orders recount of disputed presidential election | date=2010-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, both Manigat and Martelly then rejected the proposed recount, with only Célestin accepting it. Manigat and Martelly also criticised the lack of clear procedures or a timetable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5g0OKR9baj4XncqCNhRcdLbHrKlaw?docId=61d22e48698542cc9342cb191fba788b The Associated Press: Candidates reject recount in sloppy Haiti election&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a deal reached in late December 2010 to look into the vote counting process and have re-polling in certain constituencies,{{Which?|date=January 2011}} the run-off was postponed until at least February 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/31/opinion/31fri2.html | work=The New York Times | title=Haiti's Presidential Election | date=2010-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pierre-Louis Opont, the director general of the Provisional Electoral Council said: &quot;It will be materially impossible to hold the run-off on January 16. From the date of the publication of the final results of the first round, we will need at least one month to hold the run-off.&quot; He also said that a report by the [[Organisation of American States]] and a completion of review for the results that had been challenged would be needed first.&lt;ref name=&quot;postponement&quot;/&gt;

The OAS report proposed that Manigat and Martelly advance to the run-off, dropping Célestin from the second round.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-12158139 | work=BBC News | title=OAS to give Haiti presidential election verdict | date=2011-01-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Provisional Electoral Council rejected that suggestion on 19 January 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90852/7267259.html&lt;/ref&gt; Célestin was reportedly likely to drop out of the run-off by himself, however, as stated by a member of his party on 25 January 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.english.rfi.fr/americas/20110125-celestin-withdraw-haiti-elections&lt;/ref&gt; The official withdrawal statement came on 26 January 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90852/7274183.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jean Claude Duvalier|Baby Doc]] returned to Haiti on 16 January, 2011 in what was seen as possibly more uncertainty.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/video/americas/2011/01/201111783025206463.html&lt;/ref&gt; Corruption and theft charges were then filed against him.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2011/01/2011118161223307617.html&lt;/ref&gt; Jean-Bertrand Aristide returned in March amidst concern for stability by both the runoff candidates.&lt;ref name=&quot;celestin&quot;/&gt; The rumour of his return led to several thousand of his supporters in [[Port-au-Prince]] demanding that without Aristide there should not be a second round election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haitian-truth.org/aristide-backers-march-amid-talk-of-haiti-return/]&lt;/ref&gt; The protest even reached as far as Miami, where approximately 60 protesters gathered in front of the offices of ''[[The Miami Herald]]''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.radiotelevisioncaraibes.com/nouvelles/nouvellesdiaspora/3426.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Questions were then asked about the effect the former presidents could have on the political process.

Jude Celestin, backed by the incumbent government, was also dropped from the runoff race as a result of international pressure.&lt;ref name=&quot;celestin&quot;&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/programmes/rizkhan/2011/02/20112972730729805.html&lt;/reF&gt;

Campaigning for the second round of the presidential election officially commenced on Thursday, 17 February. While [[Mirlande Manigat]] discussed her future plans for Haiti in a hotel with reporters, Martelly took to the streets of [[Cap-Haïtien]], the second largest city in Haiti, where he and his followers danced and sang in the streets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.miamiherald.com/2011/02/21/2078278/campaign-opens-for-haitis-presidential.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Martelly even went as far as to campaign in [[Miami]] in the [[United States of America]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.realclearpolitics.com/news/ap/politics/2011/Feb/24/haitian_candidate__sweet_micky__campaigns_in_fla_.html]&lt;/ref&gt;, which is home to a large number of Haitian [[expatriate]]s.

On 17 February, Wyclef Jean announced his support for Martelly in the second round of the presidential election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.belpolitik.com/blog.php/248]&lt;/ref&gt; Wyclef Jean was also shot at and grazed by a bullet the day before the second round vote during campaigning for Martelly. He was wounded and taken to a hospital.&lt;ref name=&quot;electionface&quot;/&gt;

;International factor
U.S. Secretary of State Hillary Clinton arrived in Haiti during the campaign for second round voting to meet the incumbent president and presidential candidates.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-01-30/clinton-visits-haiti-beset-by-undecided-election-delayed-earthquake-aid.html&lt;/ref&gt;

U.S. President [[Barack Obama]] pressured the [[government of South Africa]] to delay former president Jean-Bertrand Aristide's attempt to return to Haiti,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/15/world/americas/15briefs-ART-Haiti.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | title=Haiti: U.S. Asks South Africa to Delay Aristide's Departure | date=2011-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, the request which was rejected by Aristide himself.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ayitinou.com/article-posts/29-haitian-articles/2967-president-jean-bertrand-aristide-rejects-us-request-to-qpostpone-his-returnqin-haiti.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Polls==
2 October 2010:&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90852/7156560.html Woman candidate leads presidential election polls in Haiti - People's Daily Online&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mirlande Manigat ([[Rally of Progressive National Democrats]]):  23.0%
* Charles-Henri Baker ([[Respect (Haiti)|Respect]]): 17.3%
* Jude Célestin ([[Unity (Haiti)|Unity]]: 7.8%

14 November 2010:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prensa-latina.cu/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=237903&amp;Itemid=1 Noticias de Prensa Latina&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Charles-Henri Baker ([[Respect (Haiti)|Respect]]): 24.38%
* Mirlande Manigat ([[Rally of Progressive National Democrats]]): 17.58%
* Jeune Léon ([[Rally for Economic Liberation]]): 14.51%
* Michel Martelly ([[Farmers' Response]]): 14.10%

6–10 February 2011 (runoff):&lt;ref&gt;http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90852/7301363.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* Michel Martelly ([[Farmers' Response]]): 60.3%
* Mirlande Manigat ([[Rally of Progressive National Democrats]]): 38.9%

==Election==
Ten of the thirty senators were to be elected, as well as all 99 deputies.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;/&gt;

During the first round of voting, two people were killed in a firefight between rival parties' supporters in [[Aquin]], with several injured in violence across the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;electionface&quot;/&gt;

During voting for the second round some polling stations failed to open on time as they lacked the necessary equipment and documents.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2011/03/2011320151736845750.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In a January 2011 report the [[Center for Economic and Policy Research]] concluded that 71.5% of the eligible Haitian population did not vote  during the first round of the election on November 28th 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;CEPR&quot;&gt;[http://www.cepr.net/documents/publications/haiti-2011-01.pdf Haiti's Fatally Flawed Election] CEPR, January 1, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, from the remaining votes 8.1% were considered to be invalid, leaving only 20.1% of the votes being cast on one of the candidates in the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;CEPR&quot;&gt;[http://www.cepr.net/documents/publications/haiti-2011-01.pdf Haiti's Fatally Flawed Election] CEPR, January 1, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The result for the first round presidential poll was announced on 3 February, 2011, with the run-off set for 20 March&lt;ref name=&quot;english.people.com.cn&quot;/&gt; between Manigat and Martelly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/02/03/government-backed-candidate-haitis-election/ | work=Fox News | title=Government-Backed Candidate Out of Haiti's Election | date=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Haitian general election, 2010–2011}}
{{Haitian Chamber of Deputies election, 2010–2011}}
{{Haitian Senate election, 2010–2011}}

===Fraud allegations===

Despite the Provisional Election Council sanctioning the election, protests continued the next day. Almost two-thirds of the candidates also called for the election to be annulled alleging fraud and many voters being refused ballots.&lt;ref name=&quot;electionface&quot;/&gt; Despite this, international election monitors declared the polls valid and said the results should not be invalidated.&lt;ref name=&quot;DemocracyNow&quot;&gt;[http://www.democracynow.org/2010/11/30/headlines/election_monitors_ok_haiti_election Election Monitors OK Haiti Election&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; This opinion was not shared by the [[Organization of American States|OAS]] and the [[Caribbean Community|CARICOM]] who, after a preliminary report, said that there many problems surrounding the election.{{Clarify|date=April 2011}}&lt;ref name=&quot;OAS&quot;&gt;[http://www.oas.org/en/media_center/press_releas.asp?sCodigo=E-461/10] OAS, November 29, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Following further protests by several candidates, the UN called for calm and urged candidates to call on their supporters not to instigate trouble. It also said that a deteriorating security situation could undermine containment of the cholera epidemic.&lt;ref name=&quot;electionface&quot;&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/americas/2010/11/201011295115818229.html Haiti vote chaos continues - Americas - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; [[CBC News]] reporters also alleged that there was &quot;massive fraud,&quot; though they did no clarify what they meant.&lt;ref name=&quot;CBCNews&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbc.ca/world/story/2010/11/28/haiti-election-candidates457.html Haiti Election Massive Fraud] CBC World News, November 28, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; Protests continued in Port-au-Prince and Gonaives, with barricades in the streets.{{Citation needed|date=December 2010}} Port-au-Prince had four consecutive days of protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;TRNN&quot;&gt;[http://therealnews.com/t2/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=31&amp;Itemid=74&amp;jumival=5953 Protests over Haiti poll turn violent] [[The Real News]] (TRNN), December 3, 2010 (video 2:28)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reactions===
Following Martelly's win in the run-off, Greg Grandin of [[New York University]] called Martelly a &quot;friend of coup-plotters, fascists, and armed right-wing groups in his country and abroad.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/opinion/2011/05/20115413435816393.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://twitpic.com/3p4228 Haiti's 2010 Presidential Election Results] Graphic from ''[http://www.cepr.net/documents/publications/haiti-2011-01.pdf Haiti's Fatally Flawed Election]'' by Jake Johnston and Mark Weisbrot. pdf file.
*[http://www.haitiobserver.com/blog.php/117 The Entire Debate Between Martelly And Manigat - Live In Video], ''Haiti Observer'', March 10, 2011
* [http://www.cepr.net/documents/publications/haiti-oas-2011-10.pdf The Organization of American States in Haiti:  Election Monitoring or Political Intervention?], from the [[Center for Economic and Policy Research]], October 2011

{{Haitian elections}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Haitian General Election, 2010}}
[[Category:Elections in Haiti]]
[[Category:2010 in Haiti]]
[[Category:2011 in Haiti]]
[[Category:2010 elections in the Caribbean]]
[[Category:2011 elections in the Caribbean]]
[[Category:Article Feedback Additional Articles]]

[[de:Wahlen in Haiti 2010/11]]
[[es:Elecciones presidenciales de Haití de 2010]]
[[fr:Élections législatives et présidentielle haïtiennes de 2010-2011]]
[[pt:Eleição presidencial no Haiti em 2010]]
[[ru:Президентские выборы в Гаити (2010—2011)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
