<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25264074" ns="0" title="Pacific Buddhist Academy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
|name           = Pacific Buddhist Academy
|image          = pacific buddhist academy logo.png
|image_size   = 177px
|image_alt    = Pacific Buddhist Academy logo 
|established    = 2003
|type           = Independent Co-educational Preparatory Day (high school)
|religion       = Buddhist
|grades         = 9-12
|accreditation    = [[Western Association of Schools and Colleges|WASC]], HAIS
|head of school      = Pieper Toyama
|students       = 64
|faculty       = 10
|athletics     = [[Interscholastic League of Honolulu]]
|mascot       = Dragon
|colors         = Teal, Indigo &amp; Gold
|campus type    = Urban
|coordinates    = {{coord|21.3167|-157.8516}}
|website        = http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/
}}

The '''Pacific Buddhist Academy''' is a private, co-educational college preparatory high school in [[Honolulu]], [[Hawai'i]]. 

The school’s stated mission is &quot;To prepare students for college through academic excellence, enrich their lives with Buddhist values, and develop their courage to nurture peace.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mission&quot; /&gt; Students of all beliefs and religious backgrounds are welcome; conversion to Buddhism is not part of the school’s mission.

Founded in 2003,&lt;ref name=&quot;hsb-focus&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-revival&quot; /&gt; the school is the only [[Jōdo Shinshū]] [[Buddhism in the United States#Buddhist Education in the United States|Buddhist high school]] in North America.&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-fr&quot; /&gt;

Pacific Buddhist Academy's first class of 14 students graduated in 2006; its total enrollment as of the 2009-2010 school year, in grades 9 through 12, is 64 students.

The school won accreditation in 2009 from the Hawai{{okina}}i Association of Independent Schools&lt;ref name=&quot;HAIS-ltr&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HAIS-list&quot;/&gt; and the [[Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]&lt;ref name=WASC-dec /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-list&quot;/&gt; for a six-year-term through June 2015, with a mid-term visit scheduled in spring 2012.

==Affiliations==
Pacific Buddhist Academy was founded with an initial $1.5 million endowment&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-fr&quot; /&gt; from the [[Jōdo Shinshū]] Buddhist Church of Kyoto, Japan. The school also receives significant financial support from the temples and individual members of the [[Honpa Hongwanji Mission of Hawai'i]], which operates [[Hongwanji Mission School]], covering preschool through grade 8.  Pacific Buddhist Academy and Hongwanji Mission School are affiliated academically, but the academy was founded as a separate [[501(c)3#501.28c.29.283.29|501(c)3]] nonprofit organization to allow for independent fundraising efforts. Team sports are conducted through the academy's membership in the [[Interscholastic League of Honolulu]].

==Curriculum==
Pacific Buddhist Academy's curriculum aims to combine traditional college preparatory content with group projects and a global, applied approach to learning. Instructors seek to recognize and build upon students’ individual learning processes as they teach students to think critically and creatively, and to collaborate. The school works to integrate basic Buddhist principles—including interdependence, compassion, mindfulness, and gratitude—into the courses as well as daily academic life.

Pacific Buddhist Academy class sizes do not exceed 24 students. Coursework makes extensive use of on-campus wireless Internet access.

===Core academic curriculum===
Pacific Buddhist Academy offers core academic courses, electives, and co-curricular opportunities. Core academic offerings include:

* English
* Math
* Science
* Social studies
* Japanese Language
* Buddhist Education

Electives are divided into four related strands: budō or martial arts, emphasizing spiritual &amp; philosophical development, the expressive arts, the visual arts, and academically-based electives (standard and honors track). Students also have the opportunity to participate in academic, community service and social clubs.

===Peace education and spiritual development===
Peace Studies, fine, performing, and [[budō]] arts classes, service learning projects, and Buddhist education comprise the peace education program at Pacific Buddhist Academy. The foundation for these programs is derived from Buddhist principles that focus on wisdom and compassion. The perspectives of all schools of Buddhism are recognized, but with an emphasis on [[Shin Buddhism|Shin Buddhist]] teachings. Buddhist Living classes are required for four years, and students attend temple services each Friday.

As freshmen, students focus on personal spiritual development through experiential learning. They enroll in courses such as [[taiko]] (Japanese drumming), [[kendo]] (swordmanship), and [[judo]] that foster self-awareness and the unity of mind, body and spirit. In their sophomore and junior years, students focus on interpersonal communication, mediation, and conflict resolution skills that directly apply to their developing and intensifying relationships with peers and parents. Finally, in their senior year, their attention moves to clarification and application of their personal values at the community, national and international levels as they engage in peace projects.

===Athletics===
Pacific Buddhist Academy students can compete on the [[Interscholastic League of Honolulu]]'s Pac-Five teams in baseball, girls’ softball, judo, swimming, tennis, track and field, water polo, and wrestling. In addition, the academy fields its own cross-country, boys’ basketball and girls’ bowling teams. Students also can participate on Pac-Five member teams in girls’ basketball and volleyball.

==Campus==
The Pacific Buddhist Academy campus fronts Pali Highway in the Nu'uanu area of Honolulu on the grounds of the Hawai'i Betsuin, the main temple of the Honpa Hongwanji Mission of Hawai'i. Classrooms and administrative offices occupy a remodeled annex building of the Betsuin. The academy also shares a gymnasium, martial-arts dojo, swimming pool, science labs and art and music classrooms with Hongwanji Mission School, a Betsuin-run elementary school located on the opposite side of Pali Highway. The campuses are connected by a pedestrian tunnel.

In 2010 the academy will launch a capital campaign for the construction of a new classroom building along the Lusitana Street side of its campus, as part of a plan to expand to a maximum of 240 students over the next 10 years. The first phase of the construction, which will accommodate 120 students, is tentatively scheduled for completion in Fall 2012.

==Demographics==
Reflecting Hawai'i's diverse ethnic heritage, 42 percent of the academy's students identify themselves with more than one ethnic group, with the overall breakdown as follows: American Indian, 5.45 percent; Asian, 89.09 percent; Filipino, 14.55 percent; Hispanic or Latino, 18.18 percent; Pacific Islander, 16.36 percent; White, not of Hispanic origin, 25.45 percent, and Other, 1.82 percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-fr&quot; /&gt;

One-third of student families identify themselves as Buddhist, one-third Christian and the rest specify no religious affiliation.&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-fr&quot; /&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;mission&quot;&gt;[http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/mission.html PBA mission statement]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;hsb-focus&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last = Essoyan
| first = Susan
| title = Buddhist school to focus on peace
| pages =
| newspaper = Honolulu Star-Bulletin
| location = Honolulu
| date = 18 February 2003
| url =http://starbulletin.com/2003/02/18/news/index1.html
| accessdate = 1 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt-revival&quot;&gt;{{Citation
| last = Kayal
| first = Michele
| pages=
| title = Buddhist Academy Stirs Hope of Revival in Hawaii
| newspaper = New York Times
| location = New York City
| date = 23 August 2003
| url =http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/23/national/23RELI.html
| accessdate = 18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-fr&quot;&gt;[http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/downloads/PBA%20Final%20Visiting%20Com%20Report%203-21-09.pdf WASC final report]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;HAIS-ltr&quot;&gt;[http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/downloads/HAIS_AccreditationDecision.pdf HAIS letter]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;HAIS-list&quot;&gt;[http://www.hais.org/member_findinfo.asp?school=76 HAIS accreditation listing]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-dec&quot;&gt;[http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/downloads/WASC_AccreditationDecision.pdf WASC accreditation decision]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;WASC-list&quot;&gt;[http://www.acswasc.org/directory_searchdetail.cfm?O=3587&amp;Schl=buddhist&amp;City=&amp;Cat=0&amp;Cnty=0&amp;SchoolCat=Religious%20School&amp;Name=Pacific%20Buddhist%20Academy&amp;Page=1 WASC accreditation listing]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.pacificbuddhistacademy.org/ Pacific Buddhist Academy]
* [http://www.hais.org/ Hawaii Association of Independent Schools]
* [http://www.acswasc.org/ Western Association of Schools and Colleges]
* [http://www.hongwanjihawaii.com/ Honpa Hongwanji Mission of Hawai'i]
* [http://www.hongwanji.or.jp/english/ Jōdo Shinshū Buddhist Church]

{{Interscholastic League of Honolulu}}

[[Category:Schools in Honolulu, Hawaii]]
[[Category:Private high schools in Hawaii]]
[[Category:Preparatory schools in Hawaii]]
[[Category:Religious schools in the United States]]
[[Category:Buddhist schools]]
[[Category:Buddhist schools in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
