<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25289759" ns="0" title="University of Sydney School of Mathematics and Statistics"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_University
|image_name     = University of Sydney new logo stacked.png
|image_size     = 
|name           = School of Mathematics and Statistics
|established    = 1991
|type           = [[Public]]
|city           = [[Camperdown, New South Wales|Camperdown]] / [[Darlington, New South Wales|Darlington]]
|state          = [[New South Wales]]
|country        = [[Australia]]
|affiliations   = [[University of Sydney]]
|students       =
|staff          =
|campus         =
|website        = [http://sydney.edu.au/science/maths sydney.edu.au/science/maths]
}}

The '''School of Mathematics and Statistics''' is a constituent body of the [[Sydney Faculty of Science|Faculty of Science]] at the [[University of Sydney]], [[Australia]]. It was established in its present form in 1991.

As of December 2010, the Head of School is Professor Neville Weber and the Deputy Head of School is Associate Professor David Easdown.&lt;ref name=&quot;about_school&quot;&gt;http://www.maths.usyd.edu.au/u/About/&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Magma computer algebra system]] is produced and distributed by the Computational Algebra Group within the School.

==History==
Mathematics has been taught at the University since its establishment. The first Professor of Mathematics was [[Morris Birkbeck Pell|Morris Pell]], one of the University's three foundation professors. Pell gave the first lecture in mathematics on 13 October 1852, two days after the University's inauguration, to all 24 students at the time. At least two years of mathematics were still required of all the University's students at the time of Pell's retirement in 1877.&lt;ref name=&quot;about_school&quot; /&gt;

The School of Mathematics and Statistics was established on 1 January 1991 with the merging of the departments of Applied Mathematics, Pure Mathematics, and Mathematical Statistics.&lt;ref name=&quot;about_school&quot; /&gt;

The School is located in the Carslaw Building, which was completed in the early 1960s, and is named after mathematician [[Horatio Scott Carslaw|Horatio Carslaw]] (1870-1954), who was once Professor of Mathematics at the University.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.maths.usyd.edu.au/u/About/Carslaw.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.maths.usyd.edu.au/ School of Mathematics and Statistics at the Faculty of Science, University of Sydney]

{{University of Sydney}}
{{USydSci}}

{{coord missing|New South Wales}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sydney School of Mathematics and Statistics}}
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1991]]
[[Category:Schools of mathematics]]
[[Category:Schools of the University of Sydney|Mathematics and Statistics, School of]]

{{Australia-university-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
