<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="253025" ns="0" title="Jhonen Vasquez"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name                      = Jhonen Vasquez
| image                     = jhonen vasquez.jpg
| image_size                = 200px
| alt                       =
| caption                   = Vasquez in 2007
| birth_name                =
| birth_date                = {{Birth date and age|1974|09|01}}
| birth_place               = [[San Jose, California|San Jose]], [[California]], [[United States]]
| death_date                =
| death_place               =
| death_cause               =
| body_discovered           = 
| resting_place             =
| resting_place_coordinates =
| monuments                 =
| residence                 =
| nationality               = {{flagicon|United States}} American
| other_names               = Chancre Scolex &lt;/br&gt; Mr. Scolex
| ethnicity                 = [[Hispanic and Latino Americans|Latino American]]
| citizenship               =
| education                 =
| alma_mater                = [[De Anza College]]
| occupation                = [[Cartoonist]], [[music video director]], [[comic book]] writer
| years_active              = 1993-present
| employer                  =
| organization              =
| agent                     =
| known_for                 =
| notable_works             = ''[[Johnny the Homicidal Maniac]]'', ''[[Squee!]]'', ''[[I Feel Sick]]'', ''[[Invader Zim]]''
| style                     = 
| influences                = [[David Cronenberg]], [[Chester Brown]], [[Kurt Vonnegut]], [[Franz Kafka]], [[H. R. Giger]], [[Terry Gilliam]], [[David Lynch]]
| influenced                =
| home_town                 =
| salary                    =
| net_worth                 =
| height                    =
| weight                    =
| television                =
| title                     =
| term                      =
| predecessor               =
| successor                 =
| party                     =
| movement                  =
| opponents                 =
| boards                    =
| religion                  =
| denomination              =
| criminal_charge           = 
| criminal_penalty          =
| criminal_status           =
| spouse                    =
| partner                   =
| children                  =
| parents                   =
| relatives                 =
| callsign                  =
| awards                    = See [[#Awards and nominations|below]]
| signature                 =
| signature_alt             =
| signature_size            =
| module                    = 
| module2                   = 
| module3                   = 
| module4                   = 
| module5                   = 
| module6                   = 
| website                   = {{URL|www.questionsleep.com}}
| footnotes                 =
}}
'''Jhonen Vasquez''' (born September 1, 1974), also known as '''Chancre Scolex''' or simply '''Mr. Scolex''', is an [[United States|American]] [[comic book]] writer, [[cartoonist]] and [[music video director]]. He is best known for creating the [[animated cartoon|animated series]] ''[[Invader Zim]]'', which aired on [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]], as well as the comic book series ''[[Johnny the Homicidal Maniac]]'' and its spin-offs ''[[Squee!]]'', and ''[[I Feel Sick]]'', all published under [[Slave Labor Graphics]] label.

==Early life==
Jhonen Vasquez was raised in [[East San Jose]]. He attended [[Mount Pleasant High School (San Jose, California)|Mount Pleasant High School]], where he often spent much of his class time drawing in sketchbooks. Taking part in a contest to design a new look for his school's [[mascot]], the [[cardinal (bird)|Cardinal]], he submitted an entry that the judges rejected. On the back of a preliminary drawing for the contest, he drew his first sketch of the character who would later become [[List of Johnny the Homicidal Maniac characters#Johnny &quot;Nny&quot; C.|Johnny C.]]. His high school's [[student newspaper]] published a number of his [[comic strips]] titled ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac''. Vasquez created [[List of Johnny the Homicidal Maniac characters#Happy Noodle Boy|Happy Noodle Boy]] while attending Mount Pleasant. According to Vasquez, &quot;[S]o many years ago, [my little romantical friend in high school] was the unwitting reason Happy Noodle Boy was created. [She] always asked me for comics, but I couldn't draw as fast as she requested. Thus, I tried to create the worst abomination of a comic that I could, so as to make her not want comics anymore. That abomination, my friends, was Happy Noodle Boy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Johnny The Homicidal Maniac: Director's Cut'' trade paperback (SLG Publishing, 1997) ISBN 0943151163&lt;/ref&gt;

While Vasquez read his older brother's superhero comics as a child, he first became interested in the medium through the original independent ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (Mirage Studios)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]'' comics by [[Peter Laird]] and [[Kevin Eastman]].

{{Quotation|It wasn't until he started collecting &quot;Ninja Turtles&quot; comics that something switched over in my head. To me, there was something just so different about those books that I ''did'' start to obsess over them — the way the books felt dirtier in my hands, the filthy artwork and hero characters that never seemed healed over from their last battles. There was a sense of person just behind the printed page that I had never felt before, a thinner separation from production to my hands and eyes that just fired hooks out into me... It felt unsafe, ya know? It's like, the book itself was less removed from the initial moment a creator is excited about having just come up with some great idea to when they finally finish a thing, nice and polished and just a little dulled from before the thing was just another book. To me, anyhow. It's just what I interpreted the experience like, and I'm sure to a lot of people it was just a book about big mutant turtles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jhonen Vasquez On M.O.D.O.K. &amp; Marvel&quot;&gt;[http://www.comicbookresources.com/?page=article&amp;id=23234 Jhonen Vasquez On M.O.D.O.K. &amp; Marvel] An October 8, 2009 interview for Comic Book Resources''&lt;/ref&gt;}}

After graduating in 1992, Vasquez went on to become a film student at [[De Anza College]] in [[Cupertino, California|Cupertino]]. Though he had little formal artistic training, he soon dropped out of De Anza to pursue a career as a professional cartoonist. He met [[Roman Dirge]], [[Rosearik Rikki Simons]] and his wife Tavisha Wolfgarth-Simons at Alternative Press Expo in 1995. Dirge later became a writer on Vasquez's ''[[Invader Zim]]'', while Rikki Simons became the voice of the show's crazed robot GIR, as well as a member of the show's coloring team. Rikki Simons also worked with Vasquez on the coloring seen in his two-issue comic ''I Feel Sick''.

By September 1996, Vasquez announced in his introductory text to the sixth issue of ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac'' he had reached sufficient success in his artistic career to be able to quit his day-job and devote himself full-time to his art.

==Comics==
His comic works often feature an outside narrative in the form of notes and comments left in the corners of his strips. This can be found in the vast majority of Vasquez's comics, such as in issue #5 of ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac'': a large monster is shown bursting through a wall, arms and hands flailing, tentacles sweeping through the air. It is a scene that surely conveys a sense of violence and danger, yet in the corner of the panel, a small box contains the text &quot;Kids - Don't be scared! He don't bite!&quot; These small touches help with emotional connection to Vasquez's work, and are likely one of the factors in his cult following. 

''[[Carpe Noctem]]'' magazine published early one-page strips featuring Johnny in the early 1990s. In 1995, Slave Labor Graphics began publishing a series of Johnny comics after Vasquez submitted samples of his artwork to them. Vasquez's first comic, ''[[Johnny the Homicidal Maniac]]'', ran for seven issues and was collected as a hardcover and a trade paperback book, ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac: Director's Cut''. The cover features the logo &quot;Z?&quot;, meaning &quot;question sleep&quot;, which appears frequently throughout Vasquez's work and relates to his characters' [[insomnia]] and his own [[hypnophobia]]. The series follows Johnny as he searches for meaning in his life, a quest that frequently leads to the violent deaths of those around him as well as, briefly, his own. A photograph of one of Vasquez's friends, Leah England, serves as the middle of a portrait collection on the cover for the second issue of ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac''. England also gave Vasquez the inspiration for a filler strip about a child who was dangerously afraid of losing sight of his mother, as well as the notorious &quot;Meanwhile&quot; filler piece in the second issue of ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac''.

Vasquez's next project was ''The Bad Art Collection'', a 16-page one-shot comic. Vasquez stated that he did the book's art while he was in high school to discourage classmates from asking him to draw for them.

In 1997, Vasquez gave [[Squee]], a supporting character from ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac'', his own four-issue series. It chronicles Squee's encounters with aliens, [[Satan]]'s son, and eventually Satan himself. The trade version (which features a cover image of Squee with the words &quot;Buy me or I'll die!&quot;) contains, in addition to the actual Squee comics, the Meanwhiles that were left out of the Director's Cut of ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac'', as well as comics of Vasquez's &quot;real life&quot; and ''[[List of Johnny the Homicidal Maniac characters#Wobbly-Headed Bob|Wobbly-Headed Bob]]''.

Vasquez's next project was ''[[I Feel Sick]]'', colored by Rikki Simons. ''I Feel Sick'' follows a tortured artist named Devi (another character introduced in ''Johnny the Homicidal Maniac'') as she tries to maintain her sanity in an insane vision of society, despite conversing with Sickness, one of her own paintings.

Slave Labor has published three ''Fillerbunny'' mini-comics, the third having been released in March 2005. The mini-comic was a spin-off of a filler comic designed to replace a vacant page usually reserved for advertising space in the ''Squee!'' comics. Vasquez said at the 2007 [[New York Comic Con]] that the original ''Fillerbunny'' comics would be done in a single night and he would rush through and do whatever he could in a small amount of time. The third issue, however, broke this mold. According to the introduction, it took over nine months to complete, and he feels it is of much higher quality than the first two.

At Comic-Con 2005, Vasquez mentioned that his next comic was a love story. Since this, however, he attended an event in early 2007 and stated he was not working on his &quot;own&quot; comics — he was collaborating on two comics in the style of ''Everything Can Be Beaten'', acting only as author. The first, titled ''Jellyfist'', was intended for release on July 25, 2007. However, the initial print run of ''Jellyfist'' was incredibly poor, and so it was re-released in October 2007.

In 2009, Vasquez collaborated with other alternative artists in [[Marvel Comics]]' ''[[Strange Tales]]'', issue 2 of 3, with a story about [[MODOK]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jhonen Vasquez's Strange Tales&quot;&gt;[http://www.newsarama.com/php/multimedia/album.php?aid=30925 Strange Tales]&lt;/ref&gt; It sold extremely well and all three issues have been collected into a hardcover [[trade paperback]]. The next year he returned for Marvel's ''Strange Tales'' II, issue 1 of 3, with a story about [[Wolverine (comics)|Wolverine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Jhonen Vasquez's Strange Tales II&quot;&gt;[http://theheroicage.com/tag/jhonen-vasquez/ Strange Tales II]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Television==
{{Main|Invader Zim}}
After the success of ''Squee!'', the children's cable network [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] approached Vasquez about producing an animated television series. The series, ''[[Invader Zim]]'', which airs on Nicktoons currently, focused on the daily life of [[Zim (Invader Zim)|Zim]], a naïve [[extraterrestrial life|alien]] from the planet Irk who tries to conquer [[Earth]] — however, his attempts are constantly thwarted in a humorous manner by [[List of Invader Zim characters#Dib|Dib]], a young paranormal investigator and the only one (along with his sister [[List of Invader Zim characters#Gaz|Gaz]]) who knows with certainty Zim is an alien (although no one believes him), or by his own naïveté.

The first episode aired on [[March 30]], [[2001 in television|2001]]. The series would last for two seasons, until it was abruptly cancelled by Nickelodeon, saying that the main causes of the show's cancellation were low ratings, over-budget production and lack of interest in continuation of the series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://dvd.ign.com/articles/543/543764p1.html | title=An Interview with Jhonen Vasquez and Rikki Simons | publisher=[[IGN]] | author=Tierney, Adam | date=2004-09-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last episode prior to the show's cancellation, &quot;The Most Horrible X-Mas Ever&quot; (a [[Christmas by medium|Christmas special]]), aired on [[December 10]], [[2002 in television|2002]]. Episodes for a possible third season, as well as a show's finale, then remained unproduced or unfinished.

Vasquez provided the voices for [[List of Invader Zim characters#Computer|Zim's computer]] and [[List of Invader Zim characters#Minimoose|Minimoose]], as well as many other additional voices, being credited under the name '''Mr. Scolex'''.

==Other works==
Vasquez collaborated with Crab Scrambly to produce the storybook ''Everything Can Be Beaten'', published by Slave Labor in 2002. Vasquez, credited as Chancre Scolex, wrote the story and Crab Scrambly illustrated it. ''Everything Can Be Beaten'' is about a strange person who lives in a room in which he can do nothing but beat kittens. However, an adventure into the outside world changes his perspective, and he discovers that &quot;everything can be beaten&quot;. The storybook inspired Urban Squall in 2008 to create the [[puzzle video game|puzzle]] [[browser game]] ''[[Bloody Fun Day]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://yayitsandrew.com/2009/03/13/bloody-fun-day/| title = Bloody Fun Day| author = Pellerano, Andrew| publisher = YAY! it's Andrew!| date = 2009-03-13| accessdate = 2009-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vasquez did the entire artwork for the deluxe edition of the new [[Mindless Self Indulgence]] album ''[[If (Mindless Self Indulgence album)|If]]'' as well as the digital single, &quot;Mastermind&quot;. He also directed the music videos for Mindless Self Indulgence's &quot;[[Shut Me Up]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dxCPCteWZqw/ Mindless Self Indulgence - &quot;Shut Me Up&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the Left Rights' &quot;White&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8VqJGRHuKUE |title=The Left Rights - WHITE |author=msivideo |date=19 November 2010 |work= |publisher=[[YouTube]] |accessdate=9 Jan 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He has also indicated that he shows his artwork in galleries from time to time.&lt;ref&gt;Johnny the Homicidal Maniac, Issue #6&lt;/ref&gt;

He also did an art rendition of ''[[BioShock 2]]'' called &quot;The Sisters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://kotaku.com/5317128/bioshock-2s-the-sisters-by-jhonen-vasquez BioShock 2's&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; He was quoted saying the following about the rendition: {{Quotation| Who says kids are good for nothing other than emergency food in disaster conditions? I don't, because at this point my badass nieces helped out quite a bit for reference. I dragged them, much like Big Sister there, out for a quick photo session and we had a damn fine time in freezing winds posing like the little, demonic wee ones that they are. Being my niece, the youngest had no problem finding that place in her heart that allowed her to simulate the howling face of a child being dragged down a nightmare alley by an unspeakable horror. Throw in a tall, monstrous friend of mine to stand in for Big Sister and you have four people with chattering teeth and trying to steal my jacket. After that, the line-art came pretty easily enough, save for an adjustment period of finding the balance between a more realistic style and not losing the strange cartoonishness.}}

==Style==
Many of the characters in Vasquez's cartoons are highly geometric and thin, nearly to the point of being [[stick figure]]s. The [[protagonist]]s in his comics are typically insane characters who live in dysfunctional societies, and whose manias are able to speak through other objects (as with Johnny and the Doughboys, or Devi and Sickness). His storylines tend to follow the basic [[black comedy]] formula. His art style is very edgy and eccentric and [[Smiley|Happy faces]] are often found in his artwork, trying to evoke an ironic sense of happiness in a world of chaos and darkness. 

Vasquez's writing often conveys [[misanthropy|misanthropic]] and [[pessimism|pessimistic]] themes, often used for the purposes of [[parody]] and [[satire]]. Similar styles and mannerisms can be found in many of his characters as well as [[running gag]]s and common themes, including repeated references to [[moose]], [[meat]], [[bee]]s, [[chihuahua (dog)|chihuahuas]], [[monkey]]s, [[taco]]s, [[pig]]s, [[cheese]], morbid [[obesity]] and &quot;[[feces|dookie]]&quot;. Vasquez also frequently sneaks cameo appearances of characters such as Happy Noodle Boy and Johnny C., as well as himself, into unrelated works. His influences include [[David Cronenberg]], [[Chester Brown]], [[Kurt Vonnegut]], [[Franz Kafka]], [[H. R. Giger]], [[Terry Gilliam]], and [[David Lynch]].{{citation needed|date=August 2011}}

Several of Vasquez's works have featured [[goth subculture|gothic]] characters or depictions of the goth subculture for the purpose of [[satire]]. In an interview on the show ''[[The Screen Savers]],'' Vasquez responded to host [[Kevin Pereira]]'s comment that fans considered him &quot;a goth king&quot;, saying disdainfully: &quot;King, yeah, but goth... I mean, that's just arrogant.&quot;

==Awards and nominations==
* ''Squee!'' was nominated for 1998 [[Eisner Awards]] for Best New Series and Best Humor Publication.&lt;ref&gt;[http://users.rcn.com/aardy/comics/awards/eisner98.shtml 1998 Will Eisner Comic Industry Award Nominees]&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''I Feel Sick'' won an International Horror Guild Award in 2000 for Best Illustrated Narrative.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The Mammoh Book of Best New Horror&quot; by Stephen Jones, Carroll and Graf, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Invader Zim'' won an Emmy, an Annie, and the award for Best Title Sequence at the 2001 World Animation Celebration awards. It also garnered seven other nominations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0235923/awards &quot;Invader ZIM&quot; (2001) Awards]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Vasquez and his work were honored in the National Design Triennial: Inside Design Now, a 2003 exhibition at the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, Smithsonian Institution.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cooperhewitt.org/EXHIBITIONS/triennial/site/content/VASQUEZ.html] &quot;National Design Triennial&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected bibliography==
* ''[[Johnny the Homicidal Maniac]]'' (1995–1997)
* ''The Bad Art Collection'' (1996)
* ''[[Squee!]]'' (1997–1998)
* ''[[I Feel Sick]]'' (1999–2000)
* ''[[Fillerbunny]]'' (2000–2005)
* ''Everything Can Be Beaten'' (2002 — with Crab Scrambly)
* ''Jellyfist'' (2007 — with Jennifer Goldberg)

==Filmography==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Title
! Position
! Airdates
|-
| ''[[Invader Zim]]''
| Creator, Head Writer, Original Character Designer, Voice Actor
| March 30, 2001 – December 10, 2002 &lt;br&gt; June 10, 2006 – August 19, 2006
|-
| ''[[Mindless Self Indulgence]]'''s &quot;Shut Me Up&quot; music video
| Director
| Not Applicable
|-
| ''[[The Left Rights]]'''s &quot;White&quot; music video
| Director
| Not Applicable
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.questionsleep.com}}
* {{twitter|JhonenV}}
* {{imdb name|id=0890679|name=Jhonen Vasquez}}
* [http://suicidegirls.com/words/Jhonen+Vasquez+invades+SuicideGirls/ An Interview on SuicideGirls.com]
* [http://www.revolutionsf.com/article.php?id=552 Revolution Science Fiction (October 26, 2001): &quot;Death and Morons: The Jhonen Vasquez Story&quot;] (online-chat transcript)
* [http://nycccast.com/?p=55 Jhonen Vasquez Spotlight (2007 New York Comic Con speech Podcast. 54:12m)] [http://www.nycccast.com/wp-podcasts/VasquezPodcast.mp3 Downloadable mp3]
* [http://suicidegirls.com/interviews/Jhonen+Vasquez Interrogation Special with Zoetica Ebb] (August 22, 2007)

{{Jhonen Vasquez}}
{{Invader Zim}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME = Vasquez, Jhonen
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Mr. Scolex, Chancre Scolex
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = American cartoonist and music video director
|DATE OF BIRTH = September 1, 1974
|PLACE OF BIRTH = [[San Jose, California]], [[United States]]
|DATE OF DEATH =
|PLACE OF DEATH =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Vasquez, Jhonen}}
[[Category:1974 births]]
[[Category:American comics artists]]
[[Category:American comics writers]]
[[Category:People from San Jose, California]]
[[Category:American people of Mexican descent]]
[[Category:De Anza College alumni]]
[[Category:American artists of Mexican descent]]
[[Category:Slave Labor Graphics]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Invader Zim|Vasquez]]
[[Category:Hispanic and Latino American people]]
[[Category:American writers of Mexican descent]]

[[de:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[es:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[fr:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[la:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[ja:ジョーネン・バスケス]]
[[pt:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[fi:Jhonen Vasquez]]
[[sv:Jhonen Vasquez]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
