<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2536257" ns="0" title="Working holiday visa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Working holiday|the album and music festival|Working Holiday!}}
A '''working holiday visa''' is a travel permit which allows travellers to undertake employment in the country issuing the visa for the purpose of supplementing their travel funds.

Most working holiday visas are offered under reciprocal agreements between certain countries, to encourage travel and cultural exchange between their citizens.

There are often several restrictions on this type of visa:
* many are intended for young travellers, and as such have an age restriction (usually 18-30 or 35)
* there are usually limits on the type of employment taken, or the length of time the traveller can be employed.
* the visa holder is expected to have sufficient funds to live on while they seek employment

The originating countries in this were [[Japan]], [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]] and [[Canada]], which all wished to allow their young people to visit the [[United Kingdom]].

It allows young people to experience living in a foreign country, without undergoing the usual costly expenses of finding work sponsorship in advance, or going on expensive university exchange programmes.  

In [[Japan]] there is a Working Holiday Maker Alumni association, which gives seminars and orienteering to Japanese working holiday goers.

==Countries offering working holiday visas==

*ASIA：{{HKG}}、{{JPN}}、{{KOR}}、{{ROC-TW}}、{{SIN}}, {{THA}}
*AMERICA：{{ARG}}、{{CAN}}、{{CHL}}, {{URU}}
*EUROPE：{{AUT}}、{{BEL}}、{{CZE}}、{{DNK}}、{{EST}}、{{FIN}}、{{FRA}}、{{DEU}}、{{IRL}}、{{ITA}}、{{LVA}}、{{NLD}}、{{NOR}}、{{POL}}、{{SWE}}、{{CHE}}、{{TUR}}、{{GBR}}
*OCEANIA：{{AUS}}、{{NZL}}

===Argentina===
* Argentina's Working Holiday Program [http://www.arg.org.nz/consular/visas.htm] provides opportunities for people aged between 18 and 30 years (inclusive) to holiday in Argentina and to supplement their travel funds through incidental employment.
* The visa allows a stay of up to 12 months and is available to New Zealand, Ireland and France [http://forum.pvtistes.net/largentine/60867-argentine-conditions-et-caracteristiques-de-ce-pvt.html#post519157] Citizens.

===Australia===
{{Main|Working Holidays in Australia}}
* Australia's Working Holiday program [http://www.visabureau.com/australia/working-holiday-visa.aspx] provides opportunities for people aged between 18 and 30 years (inclusive) to holiday in Australia and to supplement their travel funds through short-term employment.
* The visa allows a stay of up to 12 months from the date of first entry to Australia, regardless of whether the holder spends the whole time in Australia.  There is an optional 12 month extension available for individuals that have completed three months specified work in designated rural areas of Australia.
* Any kind of work of a temporary or casual nature is allowed, but work for more than six months with any one employer is not permitted.
*Working holiday visa holders are entitled to study or embark on a training course for a maximum of four months.
* Individuals may be subject to medical checks prior to coming to Australia particularly if seeking employment in healthcare or teaching. Applicants will be informed by the online application system if they require medical checks.
*The Australian working holiday visa is only available to eligible candidates once in a lifetime, although by undertaking work in a specified industry in regional Australia, it is possible to gain eligibility to an additional 12 month working holiday visa.
* Australia has reciprocal Working Holiday maker arrangements in effect with the [[United Kingdom]], [[Canada]], the [[Netherlands]], [[Japan]], [[Republic of Ireland]], [[Republic of Korea]], [[Malta]], [[Germany]], [[Denmark]], [[Sweden]], [[Norway]], [[Hong Kong]] , [[Finland]], the [[Republic of Cyprus]], [[France]], [[Italy]], [[Belgium]], [[Estonia]] and [[Taiwan]]. Passport holders from these nations may apply for a Working Holiday Visa subclass 417.
*Passport holders from the [[United States]], [[Chile]], [[Turkey]], [[Malaysia]] and [[Thailand]], can apply for a work and holiday visa subclass 462, provided they have a tertiary education (except for individuals from the [[United States]]). [[Bangladesh]] has signed a work holiday visa agreement with Australia, which will be included with subclass 462, this program was implemented in October 2007.  For more information, visit www.immi.gov.au .
* New Zealand passport holders can work in Australia without restriction.

===Austria===
Austria currently has a Youth Workers Exchange Program available to Canadian graduates aged between 18 and 30. The program is called Swap [http://www.swap.ca/].

===Belgium===
*Citizens of Australia, Canada, and New Zealand who are between the ages of 18 and 30 may be eligible for a working holiday visa [http://www.diplomatie.be/canberra/default.asp?id=28&amp;mnu=28&amp;ACT=5&amp;content=122][http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Belgium%20ENG.pdf].

===Canada===
* Citizens of Australia [http://www.whpcanada.org.au/], Austria, Belgium, Chile, Czech Republic [http://canada.cz/am3/asp/text.asp?pageID=7YRcLhlO&amp;lang=3], Denmark, Estonia [http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/canada_estonia_agreement-accord_de_canada_estonie.aspx?lang=eng], France, Germany, Hong Kong, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Republic of Korea [http://www.international.gc.ca/korea/new-announcement-ko.asp], Latvia, The Netherlands, New Zealand [http://www.dfait-maeci.gc.ca/asia/whp/intro-en.asp], Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, Taiwan, the United Kingdom and the US are eligible for a Canadian working holiday visa, so long as they fulfil certain criteria which are specific to each country.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/programs-programmes.aspx?lang=eng&amp;menu_id=4&amp;menu=R List of Working Holiday Visas for Canadians]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Citizens of Poland between the ages of 18 and 35 are eligible from 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://geo.international.gc.ca/canada-europa/poland/youth_jeunes/menu-en.aspx Youth Mobility Programmes: Canada and Poland]&lt;/ref&gt; Canada has also signed an agreement with [[Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;w01.international.gc.ca&quot;&gt;[http://w01.international.gc.ca/minpub/Publication.aspx?isRedirect=True&amp;publication_id=386921&amp;language=E&amp;docnumber=66 Welcome Page | Page d'accueil&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Citizens of Ukraine between the ages of 18 and 25 are eligible from 2010. There are no restriction for applicants status (non-students).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.studentland.ua/ru/type/change_prog/Working_Holiday_Canada.html Exchange programs: Canada and Ukraine]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Age limits are from 18-30 for most countries; 18-35 for citizens of Chile, Czech Republic, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, Ireland and Switzerland. Some countries' programs specify that the applicant must be a full-time student; others do not, and some have separate programmes for students and non-students.
* The type of work allowed and the maximum duration of stay depends on the applicant's country of residence.
[http://www.workpermit.com/canada/working_holiday.htm]

===Chile===
Chile offers working holiday visas to citizens of Australia, Canada and New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.anyworkanywhere.com/visas_cl.html Chile Visa Information At Anywork Anywhere&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
To be eligible a person must:
* Be aged between eighteen (18) and thirty (30) years of age, both inclusive, at the time of application.
* Possess a valid Canadian, New Zealand or Australian passport.
* Provide evidence of holding a medical and comprehensive hospitalisation insurance to remain in force throughout his/her stay in Chile.

===Czech Republic===
* Canadian citizens between the ages of 18 and 35 may be eligible for a working holiday
* New Zealand citizens between the ages of 18 and 30
visa [http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Czech%20Republic%20ENG.pdf].

===Denmark===
Denmark offers a working holiday visa to Australian, Canadian, Chilean, Japanese, Korean and New Zealand passport holders.

===Finland===
Finland offers a working holiday visa to Australians and New Zealanders. Information can be found on the website of the finnish embassy. Applicant must be between 18 and 30 years of age when applying for the permit. [http://www.finland.org.au/public/default.aspx?nodeid=35622&amp;contentlan=2&amp;culture=en-US]

===France===
France offers a working holiday visa (Permis Vacances Travail, usually called PVT) to Australian, Canadian, Japanese, New Zealand, South Korean, Argentinian, Taiwanese citizens [http://forum.pvtistes.net/forum.php]. Information can be found on the website of the French embassy of each country. [http://www.ambafrance-ca.org/spip.php?article1950] [http://www.ambafrance-jp.org/article.php3?id_article=2181]

===Germany===
Citizens of Australia, New Zealand, Japan, Hong Kong, South Korea and Taiwan aged between 18 and 30 may apply for a Working Holiday Visa.  Citizens of Canada between 18 and 35 years of age may apply as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vancouver.diplo.de/Vertretung/vancouver/en/01/Visabestimmungen/YMP__Seite.html Welcome to the Homepage of the German Consulate General in Vancouver! - Youth Mobility Programme Visa&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  There is no limit on the duration of employment, during the stay of up to 12 months. Evidence of sufficient funds for the first three months are required (i.e. 250 euro per month).
Among other nationalities Canadians, Australians and New Zealanders can remain in the country indefinitely if they find long-term work they are uniquely qualified to do. This is subject to approval by the government employment office - Bundesagentur für Arbeit. (See §16 AufenthV [http://www.info4alien.de/])

===Hong Kong===
Hong Kong SAR government has working holiday agreements with Australia, Canada, New Zealand, Ireland, Germany, Japan, and Korea (South).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.immd.gov.hk/ehtml/hkvisas_10a.htm#n1 The Government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region - Immigration Department&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Applicants may be granted a stay of up to 12 months.

To obtain a Hong Kong Working Holiday Visa you must :
* Be an Australian, Canadian, New Zealand, Irish, German, Japanese, or Korean (South) citizen who is holder of valid passport and ordinarily resident in their home country.
* Intend primarily to holiday in Hong Kong
* Be aged between 18 and 30 at the time of application
* Have sufficient funds and return or onward ticket when you arrive in Hong Kong
* Be of good health and of good character

Separately, Hong Kong residents 18 to 30 ages who are British National (Overseas) can apply for UK Youth Mobility Scheme without sponsors.&lt;ref name=&quot;ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk&quot;&gt;http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/workingintheuk/tier5/youthmobilityscheme&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ireland===
* Citizens of Australia, Canada, Japan, Hong Kong, and New Zealand [http://www.dfa.ie/home/index.aspx?id=8778#holidays] , aged 18–30 (inclusive) may be eligible for an Irish Working Holiday Visa.
* Republic of Korea has signed &quot;working holiday&quot; program with Ireland. (Dec.21,2009)
* Now US citizens are eligible to apply for Working Holiday Authorization in Ireland. US citizens applying for this visa must have the following documentation:
** Valid United States passport that will be valid for the entirety of the stay in Ireland.
** 2 recent identical passport photographs with your name on the reverse
** Current curriculum vitae (with references)
** Original bank statement showing that you have access to €1,500 (or equivalent) plus a return ticket; or €3,000 (or equivalent)
** Originals of any qualifications obtained or letter from school/college/university (where applicable)
** The relevant fee of €250 or dollar equivalent as advised by the relevant Mission
** Return airline tickets
** Certificate of medical/travel  insurance valid for the duration of the trip (based on dates on tickets)
* Applicants must have sufficient funds to support themselves for at least the initial part of the holiday or in the event of failing to secure employment. Immigration officials may request evidence of sufficient funds at the point of entry to Ireland.
* No one person may make use of the scheme on more than one occasion.

===Italy===
* Australian citizens between the ages of 18 and 30 and Canadian citizens between the ages of 18 and 35 are eligible for a working holiday visa [http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Italy%20ENG.pdf].
[http://www.ambcanberra.esteri.it/NR/rdonlyres/12400342-615B-426D-8D30-7364457FC126/0/Infoworkingholidayvisa.pdf]

===Japan===
* Citizens from Australia, Canada, France, Germany, Korea, New Zealand, Taiwan, Hong Kong and the United Kingdom who are between the ages of 18 and 30, and citizens from Ireland who are between the ages of 18 and 25 may apply for a Working Holiday Visa. Irish citizens over 25 years of age are in some cases allowed to apply for the visa.[http://www.mofa.go.jp/j_info/visit/w_holiday/index.html]
* A one-year visa may be granted to citizens of France, Germany, Korea, Ireland, and the UK—with no extension possible. A six-month visa may be granted to citizens of Australia which can be extended twice and once for citizens of New Zealand and Canada.

===Latvia===
* Canadian citizens between the ages of 18 and 35 are eligible for a working holiday visa [http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Latvia%20ENG.pdf].

===The Netherlands===
*Citizens of Australia, Canada and New Zealand between the ages of 18-30 are eligible.[http://www.ind.nl/en/Images/4012_tcm6-595.pdf]

===New Zealand===
* Available to citizens of Argentina, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Chile, China, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Hong Kong Special Administrative Region, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Korea, Latvia, Malaysia, Malta, Mexico, Netherlands, Norway, Peru, Poland, Singapore, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Taiwan, Thailand, United Kingdom, United States of America, and Uruguay.
* Australia has reciprocal visa arrangements with New Zealand and Australian citizens are able to live and work in New Zealand at any time and for any duration, regardless of their age or education.  Although entry may be denied on the basis of prior criminal convictions.
* Conditions vary between countries.
* Most travellers can enroll in one training or study course of up to three months duration during their visit.

===Norway===
* Citizens of Australia and New Zealand who are between the ages of 18 and 30 (inclusive) are eligible for a one-time, Norwegian working holiday visa.
* Citizens of Canada who are between the ages of 18 and 35 are eligible for a Norwegian working holiday visa.[http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Norway%20ENG.pdf].
For citizens of Canada: The processing time for Norway visa can be long or the limit reached because of high demand.

===Poland===
*Citizens of Canada between the ages of 18-35 are eligible http://geo.international.gc.ca/canada-europa/poland/youth_jeunes/menu-en.aspx]

*Citizens of New Zealand between the ages of 18-30 will be eligible after the programme is ratified in late 2009. [http://www.nzembassy.com/news.cfm?CFID=27914990&amp;CFTOKEN=89405775&amp;c=45&amp;l=115&amp;i=4806]

===South Korea===
{{main|Visa policy of South Korea}}
* Citizens of Australia, Canada, France, Germany, Japan, Hong Kong, New Zealand, Ireland, Sweden, Taiwan and the United States who are between the ages of 18 and 30 are eligible for a South Korean working holiday visa (H-1 visa).
* Ireland has signed &quot;working holiday&quot; program with Republic of Korea. (Dec.21,2009)
* Hong Kong and Taiwan(ROC) have signed &quot;working holiday&quot; program with Republic of Korea and Effective from Jan,1, 2011
* The visa is valid for 12 months (18 months for the US citizens)
* A working holiday visa holders cannot be employed in certain job such as receptionist, dancer, singer, musician, acrobat, or in places of entertainment where they may endanger good morals and manners.
* To teach a foreign language the same qualification requirements as a &quot;E-2 Language instructor visa&quot; applies and permission must be granted by the chief of immigration office.

===Singapore===

Singapore offers a working holiday visa (6 months validity) for soon-to-be or existing undergraduates and graduates, aged between 18 and 30, from Australia, France, Germany, Hong Kong, Japan, New Zealand, the United Kingdom and the United States to engage in short working stints in Singapore. For more information, go to: http://www.mom.gov.sg/foreign-manpower/passes-visas/work-holiday-programme/before-you-apply/Pages/default.aspx

===Spain===
Spain has signed an agreement with Canada.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.treaty-accord.gc.ca/text-texte.asp?lang=eng&amp;id=105130 Canada Treaty Information - View Treaty&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
As of December 2010, the Spanish authorities have failed to apply this agreement within Spain and most Canadian citizens in Spain under this agreement have not been able to confirm their legal status nor been able to work. Canadian citizens wishing to apply for this visa should be aware of this current situation and should not plan their year upon receiving the visa because they might have to return to Canada after 90 days. 

Spain also has an agreement with New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/2526600/Working-holidays-unveiled-in-Spanish-Royal-visit Working holidays unveiled in Spanish Royal visit | Stuff.co.nz&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sweden===
* Sweden offers a working holiday visa to Australian and New Zealand passport holders.
* Canadian citizens between the ages of 18 and 30 are eligible for a working holiday visa*
* Korean ( South ) between the ages of 18 and 30 ( unmarried ) are eligible for a working holiday visa since 1 Nov 2010
[http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Sweden%20ENG.pdf].

===Switzerland===
* Canadian citizens between the ages of 18 and 35 are eligible for a working holiday visa [http://www.international.gc.ca/iyp-pij/assets/pdfs/Canada-Switzerland-en.pdf].

===Republic of China (Taiwan)===
*citizens of the following countries are eligible for a working holiday visa: New Zealand (Effective from June 1, 2004);Australia(Effective from November 1, 2004) ;Japan (Effective from June 1, 2009);Canada(Effective from July 1, 2010);Germany(Effective from Oct, 2010), Republic of Korea(Effective from Jan 1, 2011)
*In accordance with the Working Holiday Scheme Arrangements signed between Taiwan and other countries, citizens of contracting countries who have meet the following qualifications may apply for working holiday visas:
*1.Purpose(Applicants must prove to the ROC(Taiwan)Embassy, Consulate and overseas missions issuing the visas that their primary intention is to holiday in the ROC, with employment being an incidental rather than a primary reason for the visit and will leave the ROC before the visa expires.); 2.Age: The age of applicants shall between 18 and 30 years, both inclusive, at the time of application; 3. Family members of working holiday visa holders, including spouse and children, shall not apply for visas as dependents to come along; 4. Valid passport: (When submitting an application, the applicants’ passport should be valid for more than 12 months upon planned arrival in the ROC.); 5.Valid flight ticket; 6. Living expenses: (Applicants shall be required to have at least NT$ 100,000 or an equivalent amount of foreign currency as their living expenses during their stay in the ROC.); 7. Medical insurance: Applicants shall have full medical and hospitalization insurance during their stay in the ROC.

===Thailand===
*Citizens of Australia [http://thaisydney.idx.com.au/Consular_services/Visa/working%20holiday.html] and New Zealand [http://www.thaiembassynz.org.nz/Visa/WorkingHolidayVisa.htm] are eligible for a 1-year Thai Working Holiday Visa.
*Applicants must be aged between 18 and 30, and have tertiary qualifications (full time courses with at least 3 years of study).
*Applicants must have an Australian passport valid for at least 6 months or a New Zealand passport valid for at least 12 months, a return ticket or sufficient funds to purchase one, and funds of at least AU$5,000 or NZ$7,000, and must be in good health and hold comprehensive medical insurance.
*Applications must be made at the Thai Embassy in Canberra or the Thai Consulate in Sydney for Australian nationals, or at the Thai Embassy in Wellington for New Zealand nationals.

===Turkey===
*Turkey's Working Holiday Program provides opportunities for people aged between 18 and 30 years (inclusive) to holiday in Turkey and to supplement their travel funds through incidental employment.
*The visa allows a stay of up to 12 months and is available to Australian citizens.

===United Kingdom===
On 27 November 2008, a number of youth mobility schemes were combined into Tier 5 (Youth Mobility), as part of the Points-Based Immigration System. The previous Working Holidaymaker Scheme for [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] nationals was merged with other schemes:  au pairs, BUNAC, the Gap Year entrants concession, the Japan Youth Exchange Scheme and the concession for research assistants to MPs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk/sitecontent/documents/managingourborders/pbsdocs/statementofintent/temporaryworkersunderpbs.pdf?view=Binary&lt;/ref&gt;  Participating countries must offer a reciprocal scheme to young British nationals.  The scheme has launched with just four participating countries:  Australia, Canada, Japan, Taiwan and New Zealand.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ukinnewzealand.fco.gov.uk/en/newsroom/?view=PressR&amp;id=8213445 Young New Zealanders benefit from changes in UK Visa scheme&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Hong Kong residents with British National (Overseas) passport can also apply, so are British overseas citizen, British overseas  territories citizen living across the globe.&lt;ref name=&quot;ukba.homeoffice.gov.uk&quot;/&gt;

The 24 month validity period runs continuously from the date from which the [[Entry Clearance]] is valid. Regardless of any time spent travelling outside the UK. This period cannot be extended nor can it be put on hold.

Although participants can undertake self-funded study while they are in the UK, either part-time or full-time, they cannot switch in the UK to student immigration status.  Someone who wishes to stay longer in the UK to complete a full-time course must apply in their home country for a student visa.  If someone does complete a course of study in the UK during their Tier 5 leave, they will not be eligible to switch to the [[Tier 1 (Post Study Work)]] scheme within the UK.

===Uruguay===
* Uruguay's Working Holiday Program provides opportunities for people aged between 18 and 30 years (inclusive) to holiday in Uruguay and to supplement their travel funds through incidental employment.
* The visa allows a stay of up to 12 months and is available to New Zealand Citizens.

==Non-participating countries==
While most [[developed countries]] participate in a Working Holiday scheme with a number of foreign partners, the [[United States]] does not.&lt;ref&gt;http://sydney.usconsulate.gov/consular/visas/niv/faq.html#workvisa&lt;/ref&gt; Most countries offering these visas exclude Americans in response. There are opportunities for US citizens to work in Ireland, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, Singapore and South Korea under similar [[Bilateralism|bilateral]] programs, however.

South Africa, from where 17,000 young people previously came to the UK under the Working Holiday scheme, is also not part of the British Tier 5 Youth Mobility Scheme.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.1stcontactvisas.com/visa-news/post/The-end-of-the-working-holiday-visa-for-South-Africans.aspx&lt;/ref&gt; However, university level students and recent graduates of any nationality are eligible to apply for a 6-month Internship in Britain through BUNAC (officially known as the BUNAC Blue Card Internship Programme). 

Other non-participating countries where the previous UK scheme was popular include India, Bangladesh, Malaysia and Ghana.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ukvisas.gov.uk/en/statistics/ UK Border Agency | Home Page&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Gap year]]

== References ==

&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.ukvisas.gov.uk/servlet/Front?pagename=OpenMarket/Xcelerate/ShowPage&amp;c=Page&amp;cid=1018721068240 UK Visas (Home Office website)]
* [http://www.immi.gov.au/visitors/working-holiday/index.htm Working Holiday Maker Visas for Australia]
* [http://www.immigration.govt.nz/migrant/stream/work/workingholiday/ A Working Holiday in New Zealand]
* [http://www.diy-oe.co.nz Applying for working holiday visa yourself]

[[Category:Visas]]
[[Category:Employment]]
[[Category:Lists by country]]

[[de:Working Holiday Visa]]
[[fr:Programme Vacances Travail]]
[[ko:워킹홀리데이 비자]]
[[ja:ワーキング・ホリデー]]
[[ru:Working holiday visa]]
[[zh:工作假期签证]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
