<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25373740" ns="0" title="List of Hollyoaks characters (2000)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of ''Hollyoaks'' characters (2000)}}
{{HOMinor}}
The following is a list of minor characters that first appeared on the [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Hollyoaks]]'' in [[2000]], by first appearance.
{{TOClimit|limit=2}}
{{-}}

==Matt Musgrove==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Hollyoaks
|name=Matt Musgrove
|portrayer=Kristian Ealey
|years=1998–2000 (Brookside)&lt;br&gt;2000–03, 2004 (Hollyoaks)
|first=11 November 1998
|last=12 August 2004
|born=1981
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
|occupation=[[Sailor]]
|father=[[Joey Musgrove]]
|mother=[[Niamh Musgrove]]
|brothers=[[Luke Musgrove]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ryan Musgrove]]
|sisters=[[Kelly Musgrove]]
|grandfathers=Alec O'Brien
|aunts=Rose Gannon
|nieces = Lia
|spinoffs= ''Hollyoaks: Indecent Behaviour''&lt;br&gt;''Hollyoaks: After Hours''
}}

'''Matthew &quot;Matt&quot; Musgrove''' is a [[fictional character]] from the long-running [[Channel 4]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Brookside]]'', and later ''[[Hollyoaks]]'', played by Kristian Ealey. After his initial appearance in ''Brookside'', the character transferred as a regular on its sister show ''Hollyoaks''.

===''Brookside''===
Matt first appears on Brookside Close when he and his family move into Number 8 in October 1998. During his time on the close, Matt befriends [[Tim O'Leary]], [[Leo Johnson (Brookside)|Leo Johnson]] and his cousin [[Jerome Johnson (Brookside)|Jerome]]. Matt becomes involved in [[marijuana]], and various fights. Matt's older brother, [[Luke Musgrove|Luke]] is accused of raping neighbour [[Nikki Shadwick]], which leads to a feud between the Musgrove and Shadwick families. In early 2000, The Musgroves leave Brookside Close due to Luke's confession to raping Nikki.

===''Hollyoaks''===
During 2000, Matt moves to Hollyoaks village in [[Chester]] as a janitor at [[Hollyoaks Community College]], where he becomes close friends with [[Theo Sankofa]] and [[Alex Bell (Hollyoaks)|Alex Bell]]. He then falls for student and radio show host [[Chloe Bruce]]. However, he is not keen on asking Chloe out as he feels that she may dislike him due to his occupation. Therefore, Matt decides to phone her on her radio show and pretend to be someone else. When Matt finally reveals himself, Chloe is disappointed — leaving Matt's worst fears confirmed.

Despite this setback, Chloe decides to give Matt a chance and the pair become a couple. The relationship is going well, until Chloe has self-image issues and begins to push Matt away. This results in the pair breaking up, which leaves Matt disappointed due to his love for her. Matt ends up having a one-night-stand with new student Eve Crawford, but he is reluctant not to carry on with the relationship, as it is Chloe who he wants to be with. Eventually, Matt and Chloe get back together, as Matt supports her through her problems. Matt eventually proposes to Chloe. The pair become engaged and Chloe's demands for the wedding prove to be expensive. However, Matt is adamant to give her the best wedding ever. He turns to The Loft owner [[Scott Anderson (Hollyoaks)|Scott Anderson]], and soon becomes involved in Scott's counterfeit money scam. Matt manages to pay for the wedding with counterfeit money, but it proves costly. On his wedding day, the police turn up and Chloe learns the truth about Matt's dealings with Scott. Knowing about Matt lies, Chloe decides she does not want to go through with the wedding, leaving Matt to face the police on his own. Despite attempting to persuade Chloe to take him back, she refuses, leaving Matt to depart away from Hollyoaks.

Matt makes a brief return in 2004, in the late night spin-off ''[[Hollyoaks: After Hours]]'', where he is working as a sailor and helps [[Ben Davies (Hollyoaks)|Ben Davies]], [[Jake Dean]], [[Joe Spencer (Hollyoaks)|Joe Spencer]] and [[Dan Hunter]] escape from a mob who are running after them.
{{-}}

==Mark Gibbs==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Hollyoaks
| name = Mark Gibbs
| years = 2000–01
| first = 2000
| last = 2001
|classification=[[List of past Hollyoaks characters|Former; regular]]
| portrayer = [[Colin Parry]]
}}

'''Marcus &quot;Mark&quot; Gibbs''' was a cruel, spiteful [[bullying|bully]]. Mark takes special delight in tormenting [[Luke Morgan]], eventually attacking him. It had all started at a football training session when Mark was giving trouble, and Luke inadvertently injured Mark’s leg. It left Mark angered because he could not play football professionally. Mark was recovering in hospital and decided to get even with Luke by calling his brothers to beat him up. Mark and his friends continued to trouble Luke when he was training; however, with help from [[Darren Osborne]], Luke put Mark in his place. Still, it made no difference to Mark when he kept on hassling and bullying Luke and soon became friends with Darren. Mark still continued to hassle Luke.

In the late night special ''[[Hollyoaks: Breaking Boundaries]]'', after a football match Luke participated in, Mark and his friends beat Luke up in the changing rooms. Mark begins to chase Luke in the streets of Chester. The pair begin a fight when Luke faces up to him, but Mark [[rape]]s him over the bonnet of his car. The following day Mark calls around to the Morgan house to see Luke and denies that he raped him; He is eventually charged pending trial, however. Luke’s rape case against Mark goes to court for four days. Mark [[perjury|lies in court]], claiming that Luke is making it all up; however, Mark is found guilty and sentenced to eight years in [[prison]].
{{-}}

==External links==
{{Hollyoaks}}
{{Hollyoaks characters}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2000|*, Hollyoaks]]
[[Category:Hollyoaks characters|*, 2000]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Hollyoaks, 2000]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
