<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25419031" ns="0" title="Dorothy Schroeder"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox baseball biography
| name       = Dorothy Schroeder
| image      = Dorothy Schroeder.jpg
| image_size      = 200px
| team       = [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League]] 
| position   = [[Shortstop]]
| birth_date  = {{birth date|1928|4|11|mf=y}}
| birth_place = [[Champaign, Illinois]]
| death_date  = {{death date and age|1996|12|8|1928|4|11}}
| death_place = [[Champaign, Illinois]]
| bats       = Right
| throws     = Right
| debutyear  = {{by|1943}},
| debutteam  = [[South Bend Blue Sox]] 
| finalyear  = {{by|1954}},
| finalteam  = [[Kalamazoo Lassies]]
| stat1label = [[Games played]]
| stat1value = 1249
| stat2label = [[Run batted in]]
| stat2value = &amp;nbsp; 431
| stat3label = [[Base on balls|Walks]]
| stat3value = &amp;nbsp; 696
| stat4label = [[Hit (baseball)|Hits]]
| stat4value = &amp;nbsp; 870
| stat5label = [[Home run]]s
| stat5value = &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; 42
| stat6label = [[Run (baseball)|Runs]]
| stat6value = &amp;nbsp; 571
| stat7label = [[Stolen base]]s
| stat7value = &amp;nbsp; 372
| teams      =&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[South Bend Blue Sox]] (1943-1945)
*[[Kenosha Comets]] (1945-1947)
*[[Fort Wayne Daisies]] (1947-1952)
*[[Kalamazoo Lassies]] (1953-1954)
| highlights = &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*Three-time [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League All-Star Team|All-Star Team]] (1952-1954)
*[[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League#League Champions|AAGPBL Championship]] (1943, 1954)
*[[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League batting records|All-time leader]] in games, RBI and walks
*Second all-time in hits and third in home runs
*Women in Baseball – AAGPBL Permanent Display&lt;br&gt;Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum (1988)
}}

'''Dorothy Schroeder''' [″Dottie″] (April 11, 1928 - December 8, 1996) was a [[shortstop]] who played from {{by|1943}} through {{by|1954}} in the [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League]]. Listed at 5' 7&quot;, 150&amp;nbsp;lb., Schroeder batted and threw [[right-handed]]. She was born in [[Champaign, Illinois]].

==Career==
At age fifteen, Schroeder became the youngest founding member of the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League, thus having the distinction of being the only girl to play in the league for its twelve full seasons. A three-time All-Star and ranked in the Top-10 in several offensive categories, she was arguably the top shortstop in league history.  After the league folded in 1954, she played four more years on a touring team of 11 All-Americans piloted by Bill Allington across [[Canada]] and [[United States]]. When the lack of finances caused the tour to end after four summers, Schroeder had played a record 15 seasons of professional baseball, a mark no woman will ever equal.
[[File:Dottie Schroeder, catcher, shouting play ball behind mask.jpg|left|thumb|Schroeder in 1948.]]
The AAGBL flourished in the 1940s when the [[Major League Baseball|Major Leagues]] went on hold as men went to war. Women have been playing professional baseball since the late 1930s, yet it was not really a well know fact until the [[1992 in film|1992 film]] ''[[A League of Their Own]]'', directed by [[Penny Marshall]] and starred by [[Geena Davis]], [[Tom Hanks]], [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]], [[Lori Petty]] and [[Rosie O'Donnell]], that brought these ballplayer's women into the public eye.

Schroeder was the daughter of a [[Germans|German]] farmer and local postmaster at Champaign. She had an older brother, Walter, and a twin brother, Don. Dorothy was nine years old when their family moved to [[Sadorus, Illinois]]. She attended St. Paul's Lutheran Church in nearby Sadorus and sang in the choir. By then, she started to play baseball with her two brothers and her father, who had also [[manager (baseball)|managed]] a semi-pro baseball team of Champaign. In 1939, the young girl played on a [[fastpitch softball]] team and joined the Illinois Commercial College team in 1940. 

At 15, Schroeder decided to play professional baseball after reading about the AAGPBL in a ''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' advertisement. She personified the family background, values, dreams and aspirations that the AAGPLB founders attempted to cultivate, so that her parents insisted on close supervision before permitting her to join the new league. In 1943, she attended the first tryout camp at [[Sportsman's Park]] in [[Saint Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]], where she competed against 60 girls for one of two roster spots. The final tryouts were held at [[Wrigley Field]] in [[Chicago, Illinois|Chicago]].

Schroeder entered the league in 1943 with the [[South Bend Blue Sox]], playing for them two and a half years before joining the [[Kenosha Comets]] (1945-'47), [[Fort Wayne Daisies]] (1947-'52) and [[Kalamazoo Lassies]] (1953-'54). In her first season, she led the league shortstops in [[fielding average]], collected 32 [[stolen base]]s and hit a respectable .211 of [[batting average]], considering that the league used an [[Vintage base ball#Rules and game play|underhand pitch]] in what could only be called classic [[Dead-ball era|dead-ball-era]] fashion. She also had 56 [[hit (baseball)|hits]] with 44 [[run (baseball)|runs]] and 56 [[base on balls|walks]] to her credit.

In 1944 Schroeder stole 70 bases. Failing to hit .200 in each of her first six seasons and totalling four [[home run]]s in that time, she became a fine hitter with power in her later years after the league switched to overhand pitching. From 1949 through 1954 she hit a combined .242 average (509-for-2095); tying for third place with five home runs in 1950, and finishing fourth in 1951 with four homers. In 1952, she was again fourth with six dingers and his average raised to .245, while earning her first of three consecutive selections to the [[All-American Girls Professional Baseball League All-Star Team|AAGPBL All-Star Team]]. 

In 1953, Schroeder saw her average climb to .285 and tied for fourth with six home runs. She also was named the Most Valuable Player of the Daisies, after helping her team to win the regular season title with a 67-42 mark. But after an exciting series, [[Jean Faut]] led the South Bend club to win the Championship Title. 

Schroeder enjoyed her  most productive season in 1954, when she posted career-highs with .304, 17 homers and 65 [[runs batted in]]. In that season, she was part of a Lassies All-Star slick infield that included [[June Peppas]] at [[first base]], [[Nancy Mudge]] at [[second base|second]], and [[Fern Shollenberger]] at [[third base|third]]. Meanwhile, the called ''Home Run Twins'', [[Chris Ballingall]] (17) and [[Carol Habben]] (15), powered the offense with 32 [[home run]]s; Peppas enjoyed a year career, and Kalamazoo advanced to the Championship Series. As a result, the Lassies defeated the Daisies in a best-of-five games series, with a decisive eight-inning RBI [[double (baseball)|double]] by Schroeder in Game 5, during what turned out to be the AAGPBL final season.

In addition to playing 16 professional baseball seasons, Schroeder holds all-time records for most [[games played]] (1,249), [[at-bats]] (4,129), RBI (431) and walks (696) in AAGPBL history. She also ranks second in hits (870) and third in home runs (42). Defensively, she was impenetrable, leading three times the AAGPBL shortstops in fielding, collecting 2,579 [[putout|outs]] and 3,376 [[assist (baseball)|assists]] for a .913 career average.

==Allington All-Stars==
When the league was unable to continue in 1955, Schroeder joined several other players selected by former Daisies manager [[Bill Allington]] to play in the national touring team known as the All-Americans All-Stars. The team played 100 games, each booked in a different town, against male teams, while traveling over 10,000 miles in the manager's [[station wagon]] and a [[Ford Country Sedan]]. Besides Schroeder, the Allington All-Stars included players as [[Joan Berger]], [[Gloria Cordes]], [[Jeanie Descombes]], [[Gertrude Dunn]], [[Betty Foss]], [[Jean Geissinger]], [[Katie Horstman]], [[Maxine Kline]], [[Dolores Lee]], [[Magdalen Redman]], [[Ruth Richard]], [[Jean Smith (baseball)|Jean Smith]] and [[Joanne Weaver]], among others.

==Life after baseball==
Schroeder, who never married, is one of the few All-Americans pictured individually in the exhibit on Women in Baseball at the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum]] in [[Cooperstown, New York]], which was created in {{by|1988}}. She lived the rest of her life in her homeland of Champaign, working for Collegiate Cap &amp; Gown Company for 36 years until retiring in 1993. She died three years later, at the age of 68, following complications of a [[brain aneurysm]].

==Batting statistics==
{| border=&quot;2&quot; cellpadding=&quot;8&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;margin: 1em 1em 1em 0; background: #F9F9F9; border: 1px #aaa solid; border-collapse: collapse; font-size:100%;&quot;
|- align=center style=&quot;background: #F2F2F2;&quot;
![[Games played|GP]]!![[At bat|AB]]!![[Run (baseball)|R]]!![[Hit (baseball)|H]]!![[Home run|HR]]!![[Run batted in|RBI]]!![[Stolen base|SB]]!![[Base on balls|BB]]!![[Strikeout|SO]]!![[Batting average|BA]]!![[On-base percentage|OBP]]
|-align=center
| 1249 || 4129 || 571 || 870 || 42 || 431 || 372 || 696 || 566 || .211 || .325
|}

==Commentary==
* ''Dottie Schroeder probably received more media attention and signed more autographs than any other All-American. An appropriate symbol of the feminine character of a league which wanted girls to look like women but play ball like men, her pretty portrait adorned the cover of [[Parade (magazine)|Parade Magazine]] in August 1948''. [http://bioproj.sabr.org/bioproj.cfm?a=w&amp;w=v&amp;biogID=5 Jim Sargent], baseball researcher and historian. [http://www.aagpbl.org/articles/biographies.cfm?ID=1 ]

==Sources==
*''All-American Girls Professional Baseball League Record Book'' – W. C. Madden. Publisher: McFarland &amp; Company, 2000. Format: Paperback, 294pp. Language: English. ISBN 0-7864-3747-2. ISBN 978-0-7864-3747-4
*''Women of the All-American Girls Professional Baseball League: A Biographical Dictionary'' - W. C. Madden. Publisher:  McFarland &amp; Company, 2005. Format: Paperback, 295 pp.&amp;nbsp;Language: English. ISBN 0-7864-3747-2. ISBN 978-0-7864-2263-0
*''Biographical Dictionary of American Sports. Vol. 3: Baseball, Q-Z'' - David L. Porter. Publisher: Greenwood Pub Group, 1987. Language: English. ISBN 0-313-31176-5. ISBN 978-0-313-31176-5

==External links==
*[http://www.aagpbl.org/ AAGPBL Official Site]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xKK92sDwbaQ AAGPBL clip at YouTube]
*[http://www.baseball-reference.com/bullpen/All-American_Girls_Professional_Baseball_League_Records AAGPBL Records]
*[http://ibistro.dos.state.fl.us/uhtbin/cgisirsi/x/x/0/5?library=PHOTO&amp;item_type=PHOTOGRAPH&amp;searchdata1=c009837 Florida Memory State Library and Archives]

{{All-American Girls Professional Baseball League}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Schroeder, Dottie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = April 11, 1928
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Champaign, Illinois]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = December 8, 1996
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Champaign, Illinois]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Schroeder, Dottie}}
[[Category:All-American Girls Professional Baseball League players]]
[[Category:American baseball players]]
[[Category:People from Illinois]]
[[Category:1928 births]]
[[Category:1996 deaths]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
