<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25420627" ns="0" title="Ninite"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Software 
| name = Ninite 
| logo = 
| screenshot = [[File:Ninite_2011.png|235px|]]
| caption = Ninite website
| developer = Secure By Design Inc. 
| operating_system = [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Ubuntu]]
| genre =  [[Installer]]
| operating system       = Windows, Linux
| status    = Active
| license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website = [http://ninite.com/ http://ninite.com/]
}}

'''Ninite''' is a service that lets users automatically install popular applications for their [[operating system]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pcworld.com/article/181329/free_tools_for_finetuning_your_windows_7_setup.html&lt;/ref&gt;. It allows users to make a selection from a list of applications and bundles the selection into a single installer package. There are currently two versions of the service, for [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] and [[Linux]]. It is free for personal use. A paid version, Ninite Pro, is available for business use. Ninite is developed by Patrick Swieskowski and Sascha Kuzins.

== Features ==

Ninite works on Windows XP, Windows Vista, Windows 7 and [[Debian]]-based variants of Linux, such as [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]]. It presents the user with a list of programs and generates a custom installer executable based on the user's selection &lt;ref&gt;http://lifehacker.com/5388408/ninite-bulk+installs-great-free-windows-apps&lt;/ref&gt;. When run, the installer downloads and installs the selected applications. The authors of this program claim that their installer does not interfere with your system when you use it to install software chosen from their service&lt;ref&gt;http://ninite.com/&lt;/ref&gt;, although the Linux version does send some information back to the developers.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.omgubuntu.co.uk/2010/09/ninite-for-linux-beta-released-installs-apps-for-you-though-can-it-be-trusted&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other names ==
Ninite was called Volery during the private beta. The name was changed to Ninite when the authors released the official version on their site. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.howtogeek.com/howto/4774/getvolery-makes-installing-software-incredibly-simple&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
[http://ninite.com/ Official site]

[[Category:Freeware]]

[[ru:Ninite]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
