<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25427431" ns="0" title="Wind Mobile"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
|company_name   = Wind Mobile
|company_logo   = [[File:WIND-logo.png|175px|WIND Mobile logo]]
|company_type   = [[Private Company|Private]] ([[subsidiary]] of [[Globalive]])
|foundation     = [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]] ([[2009]])
|location       = [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]]
|key_people     = Anthony Lacavera - [[Chairman]] and [[CEO]]
|industry       = [[Wireless]] Services
|parent  = [[Globalive]] Communications Corporation
|assets         = 
|revenue        = 
| net_income     = 
|num_employees  = 800+ (2009)&lt;ref&gt;[http://ca.tech.yahoo.com/cell_phones/phones/canadianpress/article/3994 Globalive to keep 800 of its cellphone division employees on payroll]&lt;/ref&gt;
|products       = [[BlackBerry]] and other [[smartphone]]s 
|services       = [[High Speed Packet Access|HSPA]], voice, [[SMS]], [[mobile broadband]] 
|homepage       = [http://www.windmobile.ca www.WindMobile.ca]
}}

'''Wind Mobile''' (styled as '''WIND''') is a [[Canada|Canadian]] wireless telecommunications provider operated by [[Globalive|Globalive Communications Corporation]]. The company initially launched mobile data and voice services in [[Toronto]] on December 16, 2009 and two days later in [[Calgary]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thestar.com/business/article/739543--wind-launches-with-cheaper-phone-rates Wind launches with cheaper phone rates]&lt;/ref&gt;. Wind expanded their network to include [[Edmonton]] on February 26, 2010, [[Ottawa]] on March 27, 2010, metropolitan [[Vancouver]] on June 3, 2010, and the [[Kitchener, Ontario|Kitchener]]-[[Waterloo, Ontario|Waterloo]] area on August 16, 2011. {{As of|2011|09}}, Wind Mobile has 358,000 active subscribers Canada-wide&lt;ref name=&quot;Wind_Q3_2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mobilesyrup.com/2011/11/13/wind-mobile-q3-2011-results-show-a-total-of-358000-subscribers/|title=WIND Mobile ends Q3 2011 with 358,000 active subscribers|last=Hardy|first=Ian|date=2011-11-13|publisher=MobileSyrup.com|accessdate=13 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;http://www.cwta.ca/CWTASite/english/facts_figures_downloads/SubscribersStats_en_2010_Q4.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;.

==History==

===Spectrum bid, CTRC overview and launch delays (2008)===
[[File:Wind launch tony speaks.jpg|thumb|right|Tony Lacavera speaks at Wind's Toronto launch event]]
Globalive, a Canadian company which also runs &quot;Yak Communications&quot;, is primarily owned by an Egyptian corporation, [[Orascom Telecom Holding]], managed by [[Wind Telecom S.p.A.]], which owns a number of other &quot;Wind&quot; brand telecommunications companies. Globalive bid $442-million (CAD) in 2008 to secure the [[Advanced Wireless Services|wireless spectrum]] required for the launch of the network&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dwpv.com/en/17620_24366.aspx Decision Reached in Rare Public Hearing Proceeding into the Ownership and Control of a Canadian Telecommunications Carrier]&lt;/ref&gt;.  The launch of the company was delayed due to a public ownership review by the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]]. The regulatory body stated that Globalive did not meet Canadian ownership requirements&lt;ref&gt;Robertson, Grant. [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/globalive-fails-ownership-test-crtc/article1344210/ Globalive fails ownership test: CRTC]. ''[[Globe and Mail]]''. October 29, 2009. Retrieved October 29, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;. The most prominent issue was Globalive's reliance on [[Orascom Telecom Holding|Orascom]] for its debt, which stands at $508-million (CAD)&lt;ref&gt;Sturgeon, Jamie. [http://www.nationalpost.com/news/story.html?id=2331650 Wind Mobile takes off]. ''National Post''. December 11, 2009. Retrieved on December 14, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;.

=== Network tests, government approval, retail partnership and launch (2009) ===
Globalive completed its first test call on the network in June 2009&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marketnews.ca/content/index/page?pid=5512 Globalive Places First Successful Test Call in Canada]&lt;/ref&gt;.

On December 11 of that year, the Governor in Council (acting on suggestion of [[Tony Clement]], [[Minister of Industry (Canada)|Industry Minister of Canada]]) issued a final decision deeming that Globalive does meet ownership requirements, allowing Globalive to enter the Canadian market immediately&lt;ref&gt;Government of Canada. [http://news.gc.ca/web/article-eng.do?crtr.sj1D=&amp;mthd=tp&amp;crtr.mnthndVl=&amp;nid=501719&amp;crtr.dpt1D=&amp;crtr.tp1D=1&amp;crtr.lc1D=&amp;crtr.yrStrtVl=&amp;crtr.kw=&amp;crtr.dyStrtVl=&amp;crtr.aud1D=&amp;crtr.mnthStrtVl=&amp;crtr.yrndVl=&amp;crtr.dyndVl= Government of Canada Varies CRTC Decision on Globalive]. ''[[Government of Canada]]''. December 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;.

On December 14, shortly before the peak of the [[Christmas and holiday season]], Wind announced an alliance with [[Blockbuster Inc.]] in Canada to offer Wind kiosks within Blockbuster stores at 16 locations, 13 in Ontario and 3 in Calgary&lt;ref&gt;Wind Mobile’s launched their new kiosks inside Blockbuster stores – selling nothing! [http://www.thetelecomblog.com/2009/12/04/wind-mobiles-launched-their-new-kiosks-inside-blockbuster-stores-selling-nothing/]&lt;/ref&gt;.

On December 16, Wind Mobile officially launched their service in Toronto. A launch event was hosted at their Queens Quay location in downtown Toronto.

=== Robbins resigns, network expansion, 100K subscribers and WINDtab (2010) ===
Chris Robbins, chief customer officer resigned from Wind Mobile on March 4, 2010. Both Robbins and Wind Mobile said that the departure was due to strategic changes and the former wanting to pursue other business opportunities. Analysts assessed the change negatively speculating that an executive departure so early reflected disappointing market penetration&lt;ref&gt;Marlow, Iain. [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/wind-mobiles-chris-robbins-leaves-telecom-start-up/article1489533/ Wind Mobile's Chris Robbins leaves telecom start-up ]. ''[[Globe and Mail]]''. March 4, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;.

On March 27, 2010, Wind Mobile officially launched their service in Ottawa. A launch event was hosted at the Rideau St location.

Wind Mobile announced on August 13 that in early July, they had reached &quot;the 100,000 mark in terms of new wireless subscribers&quot;&lt;ref&gt;WIND Mobile [http://www.windmobile.ca/community/WIND-news/detail/100000-just-beginning/ 100,000 is Just the Beginning! ]. WIND Mobile. August 16, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;. Orascom's third-quarter financial report, released in November 2010, listed Wind's subscriber base as 139,681&lt;ref name=&quot;Globe-Wind&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/technology/wind-mobile-subscriber-numbers-climb/article1790255/|title=Wind Mobile subscriber numbers climb|last=Marlow|first=Iain|date=2010-11-08|work=[[The Globe and Mail]]|accessdate=11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MobileSyrup&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mobilesyrup.com/2010/11/08/wind-subscriber-base-reaches-139681/|title=WIND subscriber base reaches 139,681|last=O'Brien|first=Kate|date=2010-11-08|publisher=MobileSyrup.com|accessdate=11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

=== Court proceedings, VimpelCom, network expansion and WINDtab+ (2011) ===
On February 4, 2011, the [[Federal Court (Canada)|Federal Court]] ruled in a suit brought by competitor [[Public Mobile]] and [[Telus]] that The Governor in Council's decision overriding the CRTC's determination that Wind Mobile did not meet Canadian ownership requirements was improper. Wind was granted a 45-day stay of the decision to file arguments.&lt;ref name=&quot;fedcourtcrtcruling&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/telecom-ruling-puts-a-leash-on-tory-cabinet-authority/article1895099/|title=Telecom ruling puts a leash on Tory cabinet authority|last=Chase|first=Steven|date=2011-02-04|work=[[The Globe and Mail]]|accessdate=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Federal Court of Appeal has set May 18, 2011 as the date it will hear arguments by Wind and the federal government as to why a recent federal court decision should be quashed.&lt;ref name=&quot;fedcourtcrtcrulingdelayed&quot; &gt;http://www.ottawasun.com/money/2011/03/02/17464761.html&lt;/ref&gt;

On March 17, the shareholders of Russian mobile telephone operator VimpelCom voted in support of a $6 billion deal to acquire WIND Telecom, whose assets include Orascom Telecom, a significant shareholder in WIND Mobile. The parties are now moving to close the deal, likely sometime in the first half of 2011. This transaction would create the world’s fifth largest mobile operator by subscribers - more than 173 million subscribers&lt;ref name=&quot;VimpelComMerge&quot; &gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.windmobile.ca/community/WIND-news/detail/new-telecom-merger-what-it-means-wind-mobile-customers/|title=VimpelCom voted to acquire WIND Telecom}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

Wind's network in the region of [[Kitchener, Ontario|Kitchener]] and [[Waterloo, Ontario|Waterloo]] (K-W) was launched on August 16&lt;ref&gt;[http://windmobileblog.com/2011/08/launch-day-in-kw/ Launch Day in KW! - WIND Mobile Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;, just in time for the [[Back to school (marketing)|back to school season]] of 2011. In conjunction with this launch, the company introduced a [[Wind Mobile#WINDtab|WINDtab+]] option for Pay After customers, as well as a promotional Super Smart plan for all customers.  Both services are available to all WIND subscribers in any WIND zones.  [[Guelph]] coverage was officially announced on September 9&lt;ref&gt;[http://windmobileblog.com/2011/09/0-blackberry-bold-smartphones-exclusive-weekend-sale/ $0 BlackBerry Bold Smartphones: Exclusive Weekend Sale! - WIND Mobile Blog]&lt;/ref&gt; and two stores opened in Guelph by the end of the month.  The [[St. Catharines]] and [[Welland]] zones were officially launched on October 15, and one store was opened in each city.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10150487081569152 WIND Mobile - Facebook]&lt;/ref&gt;  The provider claims that they will add &quot;[m]ore [s]tores in October&quot; for all these regions, along with new handsets and special promotions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://windmobileblog.com/2011/09/more-savings-more-stores-in-october/ Move Savings &amp; More Stores in October - WIND Mobile Blog]&lt;/ref&gt;

The carrier launched a new advertising campaign on November 7, adopting the slogan &quot;That's the power of WIND&quot; and reinforcing orange as its official colour. Service in [[Niagara Falls, Ontario|Niagara Falls]] was officially launched on November 23.  To celebrate, the company offered 30 [[Nokia C7-00|Nokia C7]] [[smartphone]]s at the price of $7 each at their store in [[The Pen Centre]] shopping mall.&lt;ref name=&quot;NiagaraBlog&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://windmobileblog.com/2011/11/here-we-come-niagara-region/comment-page-1/#comment-491 | title=Here We Come, Niagara Region | publisher = WIND Mobile | accessdate=2011-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wind plans to connect the [[Regional Municipality of Niagara|Niagara region]] coverage with that of the [[Greater Toronto Area]].  Additionally, the operator plans to launch coverage in the [[Barrie]] and [[London, Ontario|London]] cities at a later time.

==Network==
Wind Mobile provides [[Universal Mobile Telecommunications System|UMTS]] wireless services with [[High Speed Packet Access]] (HSPA) for data, using its license on the [[UMTS frequency bands|UMTS IV frequency band]], also known as [[Advanced Wireless Services]] (AWS). Using this band, user equipment transmits at 1710–1755&amp;nbsp;MHz, and receives at 2110–2155&amp;nbsp;MHz.  [[Evolved HSPA]], also known as HSPA+, was activated on WIND's network during the summer of 2011.

Wind Mobile is the first Canadian wireless service provider to make use of the AWS spectrum for its network. In North America, [[T-Mobile USA]] is the largest provider to use this spectrum.  Wind's use of AWS requires that customers use an AWS-capable handset, which are less common than band II and V handsets, which predate band IV by more than 10 years.

Since Wind's launch in Canada, other service providers have begun operations using AWS. {{As of|2010}}, this includes [[Mobilicity]] and [[Vidéotron]].  Although [[Rogers Wireless]] and [[Bell Mobility]] also have an AWS network since 2011, they are currently only available in select cities for use with a LTE [[mobile broadband modem]].  Other devices are coming soon.

===Coverage===
Currently, Wind's network coverage in [[Ontario]] includes the [[Greater Toronto and Hamilton Area]], [[Ottawa]], [[Kitchener, Ontario|Kitchener]], [[Waterloo, Ontario|Waterloo]], [[Guelph]], and part of the [[Regional Municipality of Niagara|Niagara Region]], London. Outside of Ontario, Wind has coverage in [[Gatineau]], [[Calgary]], [[Edmonton]], and the [[Greater Vancouver]] area including [[Whistler, British Columbia|Whistler]].

The operator will also expand the edges of their current home zones, and increase the density within each zone.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windmobile.ca/community/WIND-news/detail/making-progress-and-more-come/ Ken Campbell, Chief Executive Officer of Wind -Making Progress (and More to Come)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://windmobileblog.com/2011/07/coverage-update-news-for-k-w/ Coverage Update &amp; News for K-W&lt;/ref&gt;  Service will also be launched in the [[Barrie]] and [[London, Ontario|London]] cities in Ontario.  Outside of that province, Wind plans to launch its network in the [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax]], [[Saskatoon]] and [[Winnipeg]] cities in 2012.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://m.itworldcanada.com/story.aspx?id=144255 |title=Wind Mobile continues expansion across the country |last1=Solomon |first1=Howard |publisher=IT World Canada |accessdate=November 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wind formerly called their coverage areas ''home zones''.  {{As of|2011|11|7|df=us}}, they now use the term &quot;our network&quot; instead.  Customers traveling outside of this network automatically roam on a national GSM partner network.

==Products==
Wind Mobile offers various devices for use on their network.  These include [[feature phone]]s, [[smartphone]]s and [[mobile broadband]] modems.

===Feature phones===
[[File:Huawei U1250.jpg|thumb|150px|right|The [[Huawei U1250]] is a budget feature phone.]]
WIND's device lineup currently includes five feature phones.  Three are from [[Huawei]], one is manufactured by [[Samsung]], and one comes from [[LG Electronics|LG]]:
* [[Huawei U1250]]
* Huawei U3200
* Huawei U6150
* LG dLite
* Samsung C414

The U1250 is a very basic [[Mobile phone form factors#Bar|candybar]] phone, while the U3200 is similar but has a [[Mobile phone form factors#Slider|slider]] keypad instead.  The U6150 is a feature phone with a [[QWERTY]] [[Computer keyboard#Thumb-sized|keyboard]].  The phone's candybar design closely resembles that of a [[BlackBerry]].

Previously, WIND offered the [[T-Mobile Tap|Huawei U7519]], a feature phone available at launch for $130.  Its price was lowered to $70, then to $35 in October 2010 before being discontinued.  &lt;!-- During that month, select [[Loblaw]] stores sold ---&gt;

Another launch device is the [[Samsung Gravity 2]].  Its original price was $150, and it was lowered to $78 before being discontinued recently.

===Smartphones===
[[File:Blackberry bold 9700 front.jpg|thumb|right|A Wind branded [[BlackBerry Bold 9700]]]]
Nearly a dozen smartphones are currently available from Wind Mobile.  These include [[BlackBerry OS]]- and [[Symbian]]- as well as various [[Android (operating system)|Android]]-powered devices:
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:3; column-count:3;&quot;&gt;
* [[Alcatel One Touch]] 908s
* [[BlackBerry Bold]] 9900
* [[BlackBerry Curve]] 9360
* BlackBerry Curve 9300
* [[BlackBerry Torch 9810]]
* [[Google]] [[Nexus S]]
* Huawei U8350
* [[LG Optimus 2X]]
* [[Nokia 500]]
* [[Nokia C7-00|Nokia C7]]
&lt;/div&gt;

WIND is Canada's first carrier to offer [[Alcatel-Lucent|Alcatel]]-branded phones.  The [[Alcatel One Touch 980|Alcatel Tribe]], an Android similar to the [[Palm Pre]], was previously available.  Wind is also the only provider in that country to sell a Huawei smartphone.

The BlackBerry Bold 9700 smartphone was available at launch, but has been replaced by the newer 9780, which was replaced by the 9900 in October 2011.  Another smartphone available at launch was the HTC Maple, Wind's only device to run the legacy [[Windows Mobile]] 6.5 operating system.  The device was later offered by [[Mobilicity]] and both carriers have now discontinued its sale.  There are no immediate plans to sell [[Windows Phone 7]] smartphones.

===Internet access devices===
[[File:WIND Mobile USB.png|thumb|125px|right|The [[Huawei]] E1691 is a USB modem providing a [[mobile broadband]] connection.]]
Currently, Wind Mobile sells three devices that are exclusively designed for [[mobile broadband]]:
* Huawei E1691
* Huawei E366
* Huawei E583

The E1691 and E366 are USB devices that are officially supported by computers using the [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]], [[Mac OS X]] [[Mac OS X Tiger|10.4]] or higher, or [[Linux]] operating systems.  The E1691 and the E583 can download at speeds up to 7.2 Mbit/s, while the E366 can reach speeds up to 21.1 Mbit/s.  The E583 is a portable device, similar to the [[MiFi]], that allows any [[Wi-Fi]] device to connect to mobile Internet.

===SIM cards===
For those who already own a compatible phone, SIM cards cost $25 each.  These can be used to access Wind's network with any unlocked [[UMTS]] hardware supporting [[Advanced Wireless Services|AWS]] ([[UMTS frequency bands|UMTS band IV]]), such as the [[Nokia N900]] or the [[Nexus One|Google Nexus One]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://network.nationalpost.com/np/blogs/fpposted/archive/2010/01/07/why-wind-can-offer-google-s-nexus-one-and-others-can-t-a-3g-band-primer.aspx FP Tech Desk: Why Wind can offer Google's Nexus One: A 3G band primer]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://twitter.com/Windmobile/statuses/7416935672 #NexusOne: Works on AWS, we're chatting with them, confirming config works with Wind, more to come...]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wind Mobile FAQ [http://www.windmobile.ca/support/faq/phones-wind/#question-1]. ''Wind Mobile''&lt;/ref&gt;.  When the SIM is inserted into a device supporting older [[GSM]] (2G) technology, one can access the [[Rogers Wireless]] network, regardless of whether or not AWS frequencies are supported by the device.  [[Wind Mobile#Roaming|Roaming fees]], however, will be charged, so a payment method is required to pay these fees.

===WINDmagazine===
[[File:WINDmagazine.png|thumb|right|WINDmagazine is a promotional [[magazine]] available at Wind Mobile stores.]]
WINDmagazine is an advertising publication created by St. Joseph Media.  It is available at Wind Mobile stores for customers and non-customers alike.  Issues are themed after a certain word.  For example, the words &quot;heroes&quot;, &quot;nice&quot;, and &quot;change&quot; were used as themes for the company's publications.  Although there are 15 centre pages showcasing WIND's products and services, the rest of the magazine consists of articles related to the magazine's theme word.

==Services==

===Voice plans===
Wind entered the Canadian market offering three mobile voice plans at $15, $35, and $45 monthly.  These include a low-cost plan with limited minutes and two plans with unlimited province-wide and nation-wide calling respectively.  Various promotional $25 monthly plans were added to this lineup over time, before settling for a regular retail plan. 

Current plans are named after [[intelligence]] levels.  They are similar to those offered by competitor [[Mobilicity]]:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;
|-
! width=&quot;180&quot;|Plan name
! width=&quot;180&quot;|Local minutes
! width=&quot;180&quot;|Province-wide minutes
! width=&quot;180&quot;|Canada-wide minutes
! width=&quot;180&quot;|[[SMS]]/[[Multimedia Messaging Service|MMS]] to Canada/USA
! width=&quot;180&quot;|[[SMS]] sent worldwide
! width=&quot;180&quot;|[[Voicemail]]
|-
| '''Clever'''
| colspan = &quot;2&quot; | 100 roll-over
| {{cross}}
| 50 SMS
| {{cross}}
| {{cross}}
|-
| '''Smart'''
| {{tick}} 
| {{cross}}
| {{cross}}
| {{tick}}
| {{cross}}
| {{cross}}
|-
| '''Oh Canada'''
| {{tick}} 
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{Check mark|color=yellow}}
| {{cross}}
| {{cross}}
|-
| '''Brilliant'''
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{cross}}
| {{tick}}
| {{cross}}
| {{tick}}
|-
| '''Genius'''
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
| {{tick}}
|}
A yellow check mark indicates that sent SMS and MMS to USA are excluded.

Features listed in the above table can only be used within a Wind Home zone.  Note the the promotional &quot;Oh Canada&quot; plan is identical to the Smart plan, but excludes SMS and MMS to USA, and includes the Infinite Mobile Internet and unlimited Canadian long distance add-ons at a reduced cost for one year.  After one year, the regular rate of $45 applies.

Another plan available is &quot;Pay Your Way&quot; which has no monthly fee.  Instead, customers pay only for features they use on their phone.  Regular calling rates are currently 20¢ for a call from Canada, to Canada or to the United States.  Sending an SMS from Canada to Canada or the USA costs 15¢ per message, while an MMS costs $1 per message sent and an international SMS is 25¢ per message sent.  Receiving a message is always free.  Data costs 10¢ per 25 KB, which is equivalent to $4.096/MB or $4194.304/GB.  The service can be used at these rates on both WIND's own network and Rogers Wireless' EDGE network.  &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windmobile.ca/en/Pages/Pay-Your-Way-Prepaid-Cell-Phone-Service.aspx Pay Your Way - WIND Mobile]&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 10, 2010, the company began offering a promotional plan called &quot;Holiday Miracle&quot; for the [[Christmas and holiday season]] to new and existing subscribers. The plan provides unlimited incoming and outgoing North American calls, global SMS, MMS, and data services from Wind home zones, along with [[voicemail]] and tethering.  This plan is no longer available.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.windmobile.ca/en/Pages/unlimitedtalktextdata.aspx Holiday Miracle Plan].&lt;/ref&gt;  Variations of this plan known as &quot;Winter WonderPlan&quot; or &quot;My Unstoppable Plan&quot; were later released before being discontinued as well.  Both of these did not include tethering.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.windmobile.ca/en/pages/unlimited45.aspx Winter Wonder Plan].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.windmobile.ca/en/Pages/myunstoppableplan.aspx My Unstoppable Plan].&lt;/ref&gt;

All Wind Mobile voice plans include the following four features: [[Caller ID]], [[Call forwarding]],  [[Conference call]]ing, and [[Missed call]] notifications.  Also included are incoming text and picture messages&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.windmobile.ca/support/faq/call-control-and-voicemail/#question-1 Call Control]&lt;/ref&gt;.  When a Wind customer calls another Wind customer, and when both are in any Wind zone, there are no charges or minutes deducted for that call.  Pay Your Way customers, however, must pay airtime when they call any other Wind customer, unless they have the optional &quot;Unlimited WIND-to-WIND&quot; add-on.

Wind does not charge [[system access fee]]s or carrier 911 fees.  There is also no activation fee for new subscriptions. In a departure from the other providers' core offerings Wind also does not require customers to sign contracts for service.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbc_launch&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Wind Mobile launches service
  | publisher = [[CBC News]]
  | date = 2009-12-16
  | url = http://www.cbc.ca/technology/story/2009/12/16/wind-mobile-cellphone-launch.html
  | accessdate = 2010-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mobile Internet plans===
[[File:WIND throttled.jpg|thumb|Those with unlimited plans who exceed their full-speed allowance may receive this message, informing them that their Internet access will be [[Bandwidth throttling|throttled]].]]
For mobile phones, mobile Internet access plans include:
* $5 for Social BlackBerry which includes [[Facebook]], [[Twitter]], [[MySpace]] and instant messaging
* $5 for Social Mobile which includes 50 MB of data
* $10 for Infinite Mobile or Infinite BlackBerry
* $10 for Data Tethering (requires Infinite Mobile or Infinite BlackBerry)
These add-ons may only be used with a Smart, Brilliant or Genius plan, except for the Social BlackBerry or Social Mobile which can also be used with the Clever plan.  Customers with the Social Mobile add-on who use more than 50 megabytes will be charged 20¢/MB for the additional data.  If any of the 50 megabytes are unused, they cannot be carried over to the next month.

For mobile Internet data sticks and Pocket Hotspot devices, Wind offers several monthly plans:
* Surf a little for $15/month and 1 GB/month
* Surf a lot for $25/month and 3 GB/month
* Surf a ton for $35/month and 10 GB/month
Customers with the 1 GB or 3 GB plans who use more data in a month than they are entitled to will be charged 1¢/MB for additional data.  If any included allowance is unused, it cannot be carried over to the next month.

Another plan available is &quot;Pay Your Way&quot; which has no monthly fee.  Instead, customers pay only for the time they use the Internet connection at a rate of 20¢ for 6 minutes, up to a maximum of $5 for an entire day from midnight to midnight. 

All data plans, however, are subject to a &quot;Fair Usage Policy&quot;.  Only personal use of the Internet service by an individual is allowed.  If more than 10 GB of data is used, Wind Mobile may implement a &quot;soft-cap&quot; to slow or &quot;[[Bandwidth throttling|throttle]]&quot; data speed in certain cases to share the network with other customers.  Those with an Infinite Mobile or Infinite BlackBerry add-on but without the Data Tethering add-on have a limit of 5 GB instead. Should the throttling be enforced, an SMS will be sent to the device in question, and the download speed will be no higher than 256 kilobits per second, while the upload speed will be no higher than 128 kilobits per second&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation
  | title = Wind Mobile Data Plans
  | publisher = Wind Mobile
  | year = 2010
  | url = http://shop.windmobile.ca/ProductCatalog/DataPlans/
  | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/query?id=1276956586132843
  | archivedate = 2010-06-19
  | accessdate = 2010-06-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;. This policy still provides faster speeds than [[dial-up Internet access]] while allowing reliable service to all customers.

===WINDtab===
{{See also|Koodo Mobile#Koodo Tab|Virgin Mobile Canada#Acquisition by Bell Mobility (2009-present)}}
The WINDtab is a billing method introduced on November 5, 2010, well before the [[Christmas and holiday season]] of that year.  It is very similar to [[Koodo Mobile]]'s Tab payment system in that it subsidizes up to $150 off the retail price of a device by placing the amount of the subsidy on a tab balance.  Like Koodo, it only works on postpaid activations, known as Pay After.

During the K-W launch day on August 16, 2011, WIND introduced another contract option called the WINDtab+. Similarly to the Virgin Mobile Canada's SuperTab, it provides a subsidy greater than $150 for phones that cost more than that amount.  For example, the BlackBerry Bold on the WINDtab+ would cost $169 instead of its regular price of $569 because $400 of the retail cost is placed on a tab balance. Unlike the regular WINDtab, however, WINDtab+ can currently only be used with the promotional Super Smart plan or the pricier Genius plan. The tab balance is cleared off after three years of service for accounts in good standing.

===Long distance===
Many of the voice plans offered by Wind Mobile already include province-wide or Canada-wide long distance.  Those wishing to call other countries, however, can add one of several long distance plans for low or unlimited calling rates.

Unlimited calling to Canada or USA can be added for $10/month per country.  If a customer makes a call to either country without its respective add-on, they will be charged 15¢/minute when calling from a Wind Home zone.  These long distance options can be added to the Smart, Brilliant or Genius monthly plans.  The only exception is that unlimited Canada-wide long distance is already included at no extra cost in the Genius plan.

Unlimited calling to Bangladesh, China, Hong Kong, India, Singapore or South Korea can be added for $20/month per country.  The long distance options can be added to the Brilliant or Genius monthly plans.  Another option, called &quot;My Country&quot;, costs $5/month and can be added to any Wind Mobile plan.  It allows pay-per-minute calling to one of the of the countries listed below, except for Bangladesh, at 5¢/minute.

Customers with a Clever plan can add unlimited sent [[SMS]] and [[Multimedia Messaging Service|MMS]] to Canada and USA for $5/month.  Those with a Clever, Smart or Brilliant plan can add unlimited sent [[SMS]] worldwide for $5/month.

All these long distance add-ons and rates apply only in Wind Home zones to personal individual calls made to regular [[landline]] and mobile phone numbers.

===Roaming===
Wind has dubbed its calling zones &quot;Wind Home&quot; and &quot;Wind Away&quot;, its own network and its roaming networks respectively.  This is normally clearly indicated on the device, and the user normally has the option of disabling either or both types of network by using the network or [[flight mode]] settings.

In Canada, Wind Mobile has negotiated with Rogers Wireless to provide roaming services at these rates:
* 25¢ per minute for incoming and outgoing calls to Canada and the USA
* 15¢ per sent [[SMS]] to Canada and the USA
* 10¢ per 25KB of [[mobile broadband]] (equivalent to $4.096/MB or $4194.30/GB)

Wind roaming in the [[United States]] is done with T-Mobile USA as of February 12, 2010, at these same rates.  After [[Mobilicity]], this is the second lowest roaming rate available to Canadian subscribers&lt;ref&gt;Wind Mobile Store [http://shop.windmobile.ca/ProductCatalog/VoicePlans/PlanDetails.aspx?id=Always+Shout]. ''Wind Mobile''&lt;/ref&gt;.

There is also a &quot;Canada/U.S. Preferred Roaming Rates&quot; add-on available.  It costs $10/month and provides lower roaming rates for Canada and USA:
* 16¢ per minute for incoming and outgoing calls to Canada and the USA
* 10¢ per sent SMS to Canada and the USA
* $1 per MB of mobile broadband (equivalent to $1024/GB)

Whether or not the customer has a roaming plan, received text messages are free throughout the world.  For comparison of voice rates, Rogers, Bell, and Telus all charge $1.45 per minute (as of May 2010) at their regular rates for voice calls when roaming in the United States&lt;ref&gt;http://mobilesyrup.com/2010/03/25/bell-increasing-roaming-rates-may-1st-2010/&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Unlocking===
Handsets sold by Wind Mobile are locked initially&lt;ref&gt;http://www.windmobile.ca/support/faq/phones-wind/#question-17&lt;/ref&gt;, but a free unlock code can be requested after three consecutive months of service, the only provider in Canada to currently offer such a service for free.

===Get Satisfaction===
Wind Mobile also operated a webpage where users can interact with each other and with Wind moderators to discuss issues related to the service.  It is similar to the [[Fido Solutions#FidoANSWERS|Fido Forums]] available from [[Fido Solutions|Fido]].  In 2011, Wind stopped hosting the service on their own servers.  The company now hosts its online community on [[Get Satisfaction]].

==Philanthropy==
Wind's philanthropic arm is called '''WINDthanks''' and has a web page at [http://WIND.ca/windthanks www.wind.ca/windthanks].  This started during the [[Back to school (marketing)|back-to-school]] season of 2011 in conjunction with the Kitchener-Waterloo launch.  Those living in the region could nominate a charitable project to win a $10,000 grant from Wind.  The winner was MobileED,  and received complimentary [[mobile broadband]] products and services from Wind in addition to the grant.  To commemorate its recent launch in the [[Regional Municipality of Niagara|Niagara region]] and the upcoming launch in the city of [[London, Ontario|London]], Wind similarly plans to award one $10,000 grant per region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.windmobile.ca/en/pages/WINDthanks.aspx | title=WINDthanks | publisher=WIND Mobile | accessdate=2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The winner in the Niagara region will be announced in January 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://windmobileblog.com/2011/11/help-bring-positive-change-to-niagara/ | title = Help Bring Positive Change to Niagara | last1 = Lacavera | first1 = Tony | publisher = WIND Mobile | accessdate = 2011-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Advertising==
Wind Mobile advertises its products and services on the radio, television and public transit.  They also have various contests where they give away promotional prizes such as sweatshirts, or a smartphone with a month of service.

===Logo===
[[File:WIND_logo.png|right|thumb|Wind Mobile logo used from December 2009 until November 7, 2011.]]
The current logo, introduced on November 7, 2011, consists of the name WIND in orange, with a W-shaped wave on top and a dot placed above the wave and the letter &quot;I&quot;, all placed inside of a curved, parallelogram-shaped white [[speech balloon]].

===Slogans===
* December 2009-October 2011 : &quot;The power of conversation.&quot; (English) / &quot;Le pouvoir de la communication.&quot; (French)
* November 2011-present : &quot;That's the power of WIND.&quot;

==See also==
*[[Globalive|Globalive Communications Corporation]], the [[Canadian]] [[telecommunications]] provider that operates Wind Mobile (Canada).
*[[Wind (Italy)|Wind Telecomunicazioni S.p.A.]], the third largest mobile operator in Italy.
*[[Wind Hellas]] (formerly TIM Hellas), the third largest mobile operator in Greece.

==References==
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
{{Reflist}}
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.windmobile.ca}}
*{{YouTube user|WindMobileCAN|Wind Mobile}}

{{Canadian mobile phone companies}}

__FORCETOC__

[[Category:Companies established in 2009]]
[[Category:Companies based in Toronto]]
[[Category:Mobile phone companies of Canada]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
