<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25433158" ns="0" title="William J. McCormack (businessman)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox officeholder
|name = William J. McCormack
|image 
}}

'''William J. McCormack''' (1890-1965), was a successful New York City businessman of the first half of the twentieth century.  McCormack began life as a grocer's “wagon-boy” along the West Side docks, but went on to establish Penn Stevedoring, one of the most important produce handlers in the United States.  Standing 6' 3&quot; tall and with &quot;fists the size of hams,&quot; McCormack forced his way into a position of vast power, wealth and political influence along New York's brawling West Side.  For almost thirty years McCormack would be known as &quot;Big Bill McCormack,&quot; or the mysterious &quot;Mr. Big.&quot; &lt;ref&gt; Mr. Big Becomes Less Mysterious, Life Magazine, February 9, 1953.&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 1950s, details of McCormack’s relationship with International Longshoreman’s Association President Joseph P. Ryan, as well as various organized crime figures, were revealed in a series of [[New York Sun]] articles by [[Malcolm Johnson (journalist)|Malcolm Johnson]] entitled “Crime on the Waterfront.” These articles, and the 1953 Waterfront Crime Commission hearings which followed, would provide [[Elia Kazan]] with the factual background for his classic 1954 film &quot;[[On The Waterfront]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;James T. Fisher, On the Irish Waterfront, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chairman of the Licensing Committee of the State Athletic Commission==
[[Image:Bellows_George_Dempsey_and_Firpo_1924.jpg|thumb|left|Firpo sending Dempsey outside the ring; painting by George Bellows]]
McCormack grew up on the brawling West Side docks and had been a fight promoter early in his career. McCormack once knocked-out [[Gene Tunney]], the Heavyweight Champion of the World, outside The [[21 Club]] in a dispute over Mr. Tunney’s wife, [[Polly Lauder Tunney]]. In 1923, McCormack's friend and former business partner in the United States Trucking Company [[Alfred E. Smith]] was re-elected governor of New York. Upon his return to Albany, Smith appointed McCormack Chairman of the Licensing Committee of the [[New York State Athletic Commission]]. At the time, the Committee ran boxing in New York and the commissionership was a powerful appointment coveted by Tammany boyos.&lt;ref&gt;Robert A. Caro, The Power Broker, 1974.&lt;/ref&gt; And McCormack may have abused that power, because on January 30, 1924, not long after his appointment McCormack resigned under mysterious circumstances. Speculation was that Governor Smith had forced McCormck out when allegations surfaced that McCormack had extorted $81,500 from promoters before he would grant a license for the [[Jack Dempsey]] – [[Luis Firpo]] fight in New York City. In 1953, under oath, McCormack dismissed the charge as an “alcoholic’s dream” and, although McCormack was never formally charged, the alleged extortion was one of the many questionable practices that would plague the athletic commissions and the boxing profession.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffery T. Sammons Beyond the Ring, The Role of Boxing in American Society , 1990.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Business ventures==
In 1920, McCormack founded the United States Trucking Company. McCormack served as the company’s vice-president and appointed [[Alfred E. Smith]] as chairman of the board. The appointment of Smith made good political sense, because Smith had served as New York’s Governor from 1918-1920 and had powerful ties to [[Tammany Hall]]. In 1927, McCormack sold his interest in United States Trucking and entered the sand and gravel business by obtaining an interest in United Sand and Gravel, a company owned by former Assistant District Attorney Edward J. Chapman and McCormack's close friend, Bronx politician [[Robert L. Moran (Politician)]].  

McCormack was also partners with the politically hefty Sam Rosoff in a number of contracting and bus ventures, including the [[Fifth Avenue Bus Company]]. “Subway Sam,” as Rosoff was known, arrived in New York from [[Russia]] by himself and sold newspapers under the [[Brooklyn Bridge]] before becoming a construction millionaire before age 30. The story is told, that McCormack and Rosoff got their starts in a unique partnership. Rosoff had a contract to remove all the cinders and ashes from city buildings, including schools and McCormack had a contract to pave city streets. Rosoff would dump the cinders on an empty lot on the West Side, where they would be picked up by McCormack’s trucks and used to pave the streets. &lt;ref&gt;Daniel Bell, The End of Ideology: On the Exhaustion of Political Ideas in the Fifties, 1960.&lt;/ref&gt; 

McCormack also operated New York’s biggest chain of independent filling stations and in 1944 he incorporated and became president of Morania Oil Co. which, in 1952, was responsible for $2.25 of the City's $2.5 million purchases of gas and oil. McCormack also owned a contracting company, a barge company, a dredging company and ran an Illinois race track.&lt;ref&gt;Mr. Big Becomes Less Mysterious, Life Magazine, February 9, 1953.&lt;/ref&gt;  

His largest enterprise by far, however, was Penn Stevedoring. Founded in 1930, Penn would eventually hold a virtual monopoly on unloading all freight brought into the city via the [[Pennsylvania Railroad]], principally all the fruit and vegetables freighted daily into the metropolis. In effect, McCormack acted as the agent of the [[Pennsylvania Railroad]] in New York politics and became something of an expert in labor relations and a major power behind Mayor Impelliteri. On the waterfront, where flash-strikes were common, McCormack’s companies were struck only once.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel Bell, The End of Ideology: On the Exhaustion of Political Ideas in the Fifties, 1960.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
==Crime on the waterfront==
[[Image:On_the_Waterfront_poster.jpg|thumb|right|Movie Poster for &quot;On The Waterfront&quot;]]
McCormack was paternalistic toward his men, powerful in politics and wielded enormous influence over Joe Ryan, the President of the International Longshoreman’s Association. Ryan did the bidding of McCormack and the shipping companies, providing labor peace in exchange for personal financial gain. All the while, the men in Ryan's union suffered low wages and underemployment that made them vulnerable to [[loan sharking]] and [[extortion]] from the hiring bosses. McCormack, along with Ryan and their underworld associates, pocketed millions of dollars from bribes, protection rackets and stolen merchandise and their rule went unchallenged for decades because the men of the waterfront held firm to the &quot;Irish code of silence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Edward T. O’Donnell, Pier Pressure: A Tough Fight Against Corruption and the Movie that Tried to Capture it All, Wall Street Journal, September 8, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1949, the [[New York Sun]] published &quot;Crime on the Waterfront,&quot; a 24-part series of articles written by [[Malcolm Johnson (journalist)|Malcolm Johnson]] which detailed the widespread corruption, extortion, and racketeering that existed on the waterfront. The series won the 1949 [[Pulitzer Prize]] for Local Reporting and lead to the establishment of the 1953 Waterfront Crime Commission. When called before the Commission, McCormack denied any role in the alleged labor racketeering and denied knowing anything about theft, loan-sharking, gambling, union corruption or any other evils associated with the docks.  However, McCormack was not a particularly credible witness. During the five years prior to 1953, McCormack and members of his family had made payments to unknown parties totaling almost $1 million, none of which could be accounted for by business receipts or invoices. Moreover his dock employees, although members of the International Longshoreman’s Association, earned fifty cents per hour less than other dockworkers and the conclusion was that these payments had gone to labor racketeers.&lt;ref&gt;“Mr. Big Becomes Less Mysterious, Life Magazine, February 9, 1953.&lt;/ref&gt; 

&quot;Crime on the Waterfront&quot; and the resulting 1953 Waterfront Crime Commission provided Elia Kazan with the factual background for his 1954 film &quot;[[On The Waterfront]]&quot; and &quot;Mr. Upstairs,&quot; the corrupt leader who directs Johnny Friendly from afar, is based on the real-life McCormack.&lt;ref&gt;James T. Fisher, On the Irish Waterfront, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Years later, Bud Schulberg, who wrote the screenplay, recalled bringing Kazan to meet with Father John, the real life &quot;Father Barry&quot; played by Karl Malden in the movie.

:&quot;That day he was going up in smoke. He was furious that Spellman was giving an award to John McCormack--the 'Mr. Big' of the waterfront. Mr. McCormack was a respectable man. He had lots and lots of money. He put Mayor Impellitteri in office. But the people under McCormack were monsters and killers. Anyway, the day I brought Kazan, Father John was yelling, 'I'm going to stop Spellman.' He was cursing--'McCormack, that son of a bitch'--and shouting.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;American Legends Interviews, Budd Schulberg, The Making of On The Waterfront available at http://www.americanlegends.com/Interviews/budd_schulberg.html&lt;/ref&gt;.

Mr. Upstairs’s face is never shown, and we see only the plush estate (with television set and butler) where he lives. The director's script, housed at Wesleyan Cinema Archives, includes a double page Newsday Report, &quot;Death on the Docks,&quot; of May 18, 1953 and, opposite the script section depicting the reaction of &quot;Mr. Upstairs&quot; to Terry Malloy's testimony, and unidentified magazine picture of McCormack.

==Transit Mix Concrete==
[[Image:Jfkairport.jpg|thumb|left|TWA Flight Center]]McCormack also owned several concrete companies, including United Sand and Gravel, later Transit Mix, which, as one of only two concrete plants located within the city, provided millions of cubic feet of concrete for public and private construction projects including: the [[Chrystler Building]]the and [[New York Central Building]], the [[United Nations]], [[Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum|Guggenheim Museum]], [[Lincoln Center]], 1969 Worlds Fair Grounds in [[Flushing, Queens|Flushing]], the [[Cross Bronx Expressway]], [[Major Deegan Expressway]] and [[Long Island Expressway]], the [[TWA Flight Center]] at JFK Airport designed by [[Eero Saarinen]], the [[Whitestone]], [[Throgsneck]] and [[Verrazano Narrows]] bridges and the [[World Trade Center]].  

After his death, Transit Mix was left to McCormack’s daughter who sold the corporation to Edward J. Halloran, the owner of the Halloran House Hotel on [[Lexington Avenue]] at 49th Street. In 1986 Halloran and Transit Mix were indicted, along with [[Anthony Salerno]] and other members of the [[Genovese Crime Family]], for [[bid rigging]], [[extortion]], [[gambling]] and [[murder]] conspiracies.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold H. Lubasch, Reputed Mob Leader Among 15 Indicted on Racketeering Counts, The New York Times, March 22, 1986.&lt;/ref&gt; Mr. Halloran disappeared under mysterious circumstances in 1998 and remains missing to this day.&lt;ref&gt;Selwyn Raab, Ex Hotel Owner With  Former Ties to Mobsters Disappears, The New York Times, October 30, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Maccormack, William J.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1890
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Maccormack, William J.}}
[[Category:American construction businesspeople]]
[[Category:American transportation businesspeople]]
[[Category:1890 births]]
[[Category:1960s deaths]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
