<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25543203" ns="0" title="Japan Airlines Flight 472 (1972)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the hijacking of Flight 472|Japan Airlines Flight 472}}
{{Expand Japanese|日本航空ボンベイ空港誤認着陸事故|date=December 2009}}

{{Refimprove|date=December 2009}}

{{Infobox Airliner accident
| name = Japan Airlines Flight 472
| image          = DC-8 Japan Airlines.JPG
| caption        = A [[Douglas DC-8]] used by Japan Airlines, similar to the aircraft involved
| Date           = {{start-date|24 September 1972}}
| Type           = 
| occurrence_type = Accident
| Site           = [[Bombay]], [[India]]
| Injuries       = 11
| Fatalities     = 0
| Aircraft Type  = [[Douglas DC-8]]-53
| Operator       = [[Japan Airlines]]
| tail_number    = JA8013
| Passengers     = 108
| Crew           = 14
| Survivors      = 122 (all)
| Origin = [[London Heathrow Airport|London]] 
| stopover         = [[Frankfurt Airport|Frankfurt]]
| stopover0        = [[Leonardo da Vinci-Fiumicino Airport|Rome]]
| stopover1        = [[Beirut Rafic Hariri International Airport|Beirut]]
| stopover2        = [[Tehran Imam Khomeini International Airport|Tehran]]
| stopover3        = [[Santacruz Airport|Bombay]]
| stopover4        = [[Don Mueang International Airport|Bangkok]]
| stopover5        = [[Kai Tak Airport|Hong Kong]]
| Destination = [[Tokyo International Airport|Tokyo]]
}}
'''Japan Airlines Flight 472''' was a flight from [[London]] to [[Tokyo]] via [[Frankfurt]], [[Rome]], [[Beirut]], [[Tehran]], [[Bombay]], [[Bangkok]] and [[Hong Kong]]. On September 24, 1972, the flight landed at [[Juhu Aerodrome]] near [[Bombay]], India instead of the city's much larger [[Santacruz Airport]] (now Chhatrapati Shivaji International Airport) and overran the runway, resulting in the aircraft being written off.

==Aircraft==
The aircraft involved was a [[Douglas DC-8|Douglas DC-8-53]], registration JA8013. The aircraft was c/n 45681. It had first flown in 1964.&lt;ref name=ASN240972&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19720924-1 |title=Accident description |publisher=Aviation Safety Network |accessdate=24 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Accident==
The flight departed London 20 minutes late. By the time it left Tehran for Bombay, it is already 80 minutes (one hour and 20 minutes) behind schedule.

In the morning of Sep 24, 1972, the flight planned to execute an [[Instrument Landing System|ILS]] approach to Santacruz Airport, Bombay. However, the [[Air Traffic Controller|ATC]] asked the crew, &quot;Can you see the runway?&quot;, to which they replied, &quot;Yes, we can&quot;. Since the weather was good around the airport that day, the ATC instructed &quot;[[Visual flight rules|VFR]] approach please&quot;. 

After this, Flight 472 flew past Runway 09 (on the west side) of Santacruz Airport while descending, and executed a 360 degree turn, in order to land from the west side, that is, the side where the Arabian sea lies. However, when it did land at 06:50 [[UTC+5:30|local time]] (01:20 [[Coordinated Universal Time|UTC]]), instead of landing at Santacruz, it was in fact landing on Runway 08 of Juhu Aerodrome, which is 3.7 km west of Santacruz, and for use by small aircraft only.&lt;ref name=ASN240972/&gt; Runway 08 of Juhu was only {{convert|1143|m|ft}} long, making it impossible for a large aircraft like JL472 to land on.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}} 

After deploying the [[thrust reverser]]s, the captain of Flight 472 realized the mistake, and immediately deployed the spoilers and applied the brakes to the maximum extent possible, but an overrun was inevitable. The DC-8 overshot the runway, breaking off both engines on the [[Port (nautical)|port]] wing, and damaging the front and main [[landing gear]]s, resulting in the nose of the aircraft to plunge into the ground. The wreckage caught fire, but was soon put out by fire extinguishers.

At the time of the accident, there were 14 crew and 108 passengers on board. 2 cockpit crew and 9 passengers (all foreigners) were injured, and the aircraft was damaged beyond economic repair.&lt;ref name=ASN240972/&gt;

==Cause==
The accident itself was nothing more than [[pilot error]], mistaking the airports. However, the Indian authorities were also blamed for building an airport for small aircraft so close to Santacruz, causing confusion (see similar incidents below), even though it had been built before India's independence, in the colonial era. Another factor is during the 360-degree turn while facing the sun, the cockpit crew of Flight 472 lost sight of the runway due to the morning mist around the surface reflecting sunlight. So, when they suddenly saw the runway of Juhu Aerodrome, they mistook it for the runway of Santacruz, and landed on it.

==Similar accidents and incidents==
There have been many instances of aircraft being landed at airports other than the intended destination. In the majority of cases the aircraft is not damaged and was returned to service.

On July 15, 1953, a [[British Overseas Airways Corporation|BOAC]] [[de Havilland Comet|DH.106 Comet]] also landed at Juhu Aerodrome instead of Santacruz Airport. The aircraft was flown out some nine days later.&lt;ref name=Wrong&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thirdamendment.com/wrongway.html |title=The Legacy of Douglas Corrigan: &quot;Wrong Way&quot; Landings By Commercial Airliners |publisher=Third Amendment |accessdate=25 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 May 1968, the pilot of a [[Garuda Indonesia]] [[Convair 990]] had also mistaken the same Juhu Aerodrome for Santacruz Airport and tried to land his aircraft. It overshot the runway falling just short of the traffic road ahead and several residential buildings when its nose wheel got stuck in a ditch at the end of the runway. All passengers survived.

Only four months after the Japan Airlines Flight 472 incident, another similar incident happened when an [[Ilyushin Il-18]] ([[turboprop]] airliner) of [[Interflug]], an airline of the [[German Democratic Republic]] (East Germany), landed on the wrong airport and stopped in immediate front of a parked Japan Airlines aircraft, narrowly escaped a collision.

On March 29, 2006, an [[Airbus A320]] being operated by [[Eirjet]] on behalf of [[Ryanair]] landed at [[Shackleton Barracks|Ballykelly Airfield]] instead of its intended destination of [[City of Derry Airport]].&lt;ref name=BBC4857962&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/northern_ireland/4857962.stm |title=Plane lands at airbase by mistake |publisher=BBC News Online |accessdate=25 December 2009 | date=2006-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Portal box|Japan|Mumbai|Aviation}}
{{Reflist}}

{{Aviation accidents and incidents in 1972}}

[[Category:Aviation accidents and incidents in 1972]]
[[Category:Accidents and incidents involving the Douglas DC-8]]
[[Category:Japan Airlines accidents and incidents]]
[[Category:Airliner accidents and incidents caused by pilot error]]
[[Category:Aviation accidents and incidents in India]]
[[Category:1972 in India]]
[[Category:1972 in Japan]]

[[ja:日本航空ボンベイ空港誤認着陸事故]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
