<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2562517" ns="0" title="Opposition to the legalization of abortion"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Pro-life}}
{{Globalize|date=November 2011}}
{{pp-protected|reason=of Arbitration case decisions|expiry=November 28, 2014|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{| style=&quot;float:right; width:270px; border:#fff solid 1px;&quot;
|-
|[[Image:UK Pro-life demonstrators.jpg|thumb|300px|Pro-life protesters at [[Parliament Square]], [[London]] on 20 May 2008]]
|}
'''Opposition to the legalization of abortion''' is centered around the '''pro-life''', or '''anti-abortion''', '''movement''', a social and political movement opposing elective [[abortion]] on moral grounds and supporting its legal prohibition or restriction. The modern pro-life movement began as a [[countermovement]] in response to the decriminalization and legalization of elective abortion in various [[U.S. state|states]], and it grew following the [[U.S. Supreme Court]]'s 1973 decision in ''[[Roe v. Wade]],'' which struck down most state laws restricting abortion.&lt;ref name=Staggenborg&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3oRBOuEvz30C&amp;pg=PA188 |page=188 |title=The Pro-Choice Movement: Organization and Activism in the Abortion Conflict |first=Suzanne |last=Staggenborg |publisher=Oxford University Press US |year=1994 |isbn=0195089251}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://www.brennancenter.org/blog/archives/Greenhouse_and_Reva_B._Siegel |page= |title=Before Roe v. Wade: Voices that Shaped the Abortion Debate Before the Supreme Court's Ruling |first=Linda|last=Greenhouse |publisher=Kaplan Publishing |year=2010 |isbn=1607146711}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the United States this movement is frequently, but not exclusively, allied with the [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=Mc1bdEtBWRYC&amp;pg=PA150 |page=150 |title=Understanding American Government |publisher=Cengage Learning |year=2009 |edition=12 |isbn=0495568392 |author=Susan Welch, John Gruhl, John Comer, Susan M. Rigdon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democratsforlife.org/ |title=Democrats for Life |publisher=Democrats for Life |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and seeks to restrict abortion with legislation such as the [[Human Life Amendment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;/&gt; Advocates generally maintain that the human [[fetus]] (and in most cases the human [[embryo]]) is a [[person]] and therefore has a right to life. 

On the other side of the [[abortion debate]] is the [[Support for the legalization of abortion|pro-choice movement]].  Subscribing to different moral grounds than the pro-life movement, pro-choicers hold the view  that a woman should have the right to terminate her pregnancy; they also advocate legal abortion as an important facet of women's [[reproductive rights]]. 

The &quot;pro-life&quot; concept is sometimes broadened to include positions on other issues, such as opposition to [[euthanasia]] and [[embryonic stem-cell research]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Ziad W. Munson&quot;&gt;{{cite book| url = http://books.google.com/?id=UFaCtYtIAjgC&amp;pg=PA212&amp;dq=pro-life+euthanasia+abortion+capital+punishment#v=onepage&amp;q=pro-life%20euthanasia%20abortion%20capital%20punishment&amp;f=false|title=The Making of Pro-life Activists: How Social Movement Mobilization Works|author=Ziad W. Munson|quote=The pro-life issue to include not only abortion but also opposition to euthanasia, capital punishment, and support for a living wage and other economic positions of the Church.|accessdate =2007-12-31| isbn = 9780226551203| year = 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Ronald J. Sider&quot;&gt;{{cite book| url = http://books.google.com/?id=16G--xmqYFwC&amp;pg=PA155&amp;dq=pro-life+euthanasia+abortion+capital+punishment#v=onepage&amp;q=pro-life%20euthanasia%20abortion%20capital%20punishment&amp;f=false|title=The Scandal of Evangelical Politics|author=Ziad W. Munson|quote=Christians to a consistently pro-life agenda. Abortion, euthanasia, smoking, starvation in a world of abundance, and capital punishment all destroy persons created.|accessdate =2007-12-31| isbn = 9780801068379| date = 2008-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The term &quot;pro-life&quot; was coined by U.S. leaders of the [[Right to life|right-to-life]] (anti-abortion) movement following the January 1973 U.S. Supreme Court case ''[[Roe v. Wade]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LOzfQEP3H8AC&amp;pg=PA195 |page=195 |title=Encyclopedia of women in American politics |first1= Jeffrey D. |last1=Schultz |first2=Laura A. |last2=Van Assendelft |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |year=1999 |isbn=1573561312 |series=The American political landscape |edition=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; which held that a mother may abort her pregnancy in the first trimester, and may also abort &quot;subsequent to viability&amp;nbsp;... for the preservation of the life or health of the mother.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roe v Wade&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/historics/USSC_CR_0410_0113_ZS.html ''Roe v. Wade'' (98–1856) 410 U.S. 113 (1973)]. Retrieved April 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;pro-life&quot; was adopted instead of &quot;anti-abortion&quot; to highlight the belief that they consider abortion the taking of a human life, rather than an issue concerning the restriction of women's [[reproductive rights]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;/&gt; The first organized action was initiated by U.S. Catholic bishops who recommended in 1973 that the U.S. Constitution should be amended to ban abortion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;/&gt;

''Roe v. Wade'' led to the growth of a largely religious-based anti-abortion movement even as Americans became, in the 1970s and 80s, increasingly pro-choice. The first major pro-life success came in 1976 with the passing of the [[Hyde Amendment]] prohibiting the use of certain federal funds for abortions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Making America&quot;/&gt; In ''[[Harris v. McRae]]'', pro-life advocates won a 1980 challenge to the Hyde Amendment. That same year, the pro-life movement gained control of the Republican Party's [[Party platform|platform]] committee, adding pro-life planks to the Republican position, and calling for a Human Life Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, banning abortion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;/&gt; Two pro-life U.S. Presidents&amp;nbsp;– [[Ronald Reagan]] and [[George H. W. Bush]]&amp;nbsp;– were elected, although according to M. McKeegan, the majority of Reagan voters were pro-choice.&lt;ref name=mckee/&gt;

Some in the media have noted a revitalization of the pro-life movement in the 21st century. In 2011, [[Fred Barnes]] of ''[[The Weekly Standard]]'' wrote:

{{blockquote|That the pro-life movement is bigger is a given. It’s also younger, increasingly entrepreneurial, more strategic in its thinking, better organized, tougher in dealing with allies and enemies alike, almost wildly ambitious, and more relentless than ever. Pro-lifers have captured the high moral ground, chiefly thanks to advances in the quality of sonograms. Once fuzzy, sonograms now provide a high-resolution picture of the unborn child in the womb. Fetuses have become babies.&lt;ref name=&quot;TWS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/articles/hidden-persuaders_604174.html?page=1 |title=Hidden Persuaders |publisher=Weeklystandard.com |date=2011-11-07 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Barnes also discussed the rise in opposition to abortion among the younger generations, especially the [[Generation Y|millennials]], the prevalence of crisis pregnancy centers, and the rejuvenation of old pro-life groups, such as [[Students for Life]], and the rise of new ones, such as [[40 Days for Life]] and [[Live Action (organization)|Live Action]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TWS&quot;/&gt; Lisa Miller of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' wrote about the younger, more feminine face of the pro-life movement with the rise of leaders such as [[Lila Rose]] of Live Action, [[Marjorie Dannenfelser]] of the [[Susan B. Anthony List]], Charmaine Yoest of [[Americans United for Life]], Penny Nance of [[Concerned Women for America]], and Kristan Hawkins of [[Students for Life]], all &quot;youngish Christian working mothers with children at home&quot; who offer a pro-life perspective on the women's rights aspect of the abortion issue instead of focusing exclusively on the fetus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/on-faith/a-feminine-face-for-the-anti-abortion-movement/2011/11/02/gIQAwd7kiM_story.html |title=A feminine face for the anti-abortion movement |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date=2011-10-24 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The pro-life movement has been highly successful in recent years in advancing new laws against abortion within the states. The [[Guttmacher Institute]] said eighty laws restricting abortion were passed in the first six months of 2011, &quot;more than double the previous record of 34 abortion restrictions enacted in 2005—and more than triple the 23 enacted in 2010&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guttmacher.org/media/inthenews/2011/07/13/index.html |title=States Enact Record Number of Abortion Restrictions in First Half of 2011 |publisher=Guttmacher.org |date=2011-07-13 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Roman Catholics===
Before the ''Roe v. Wade'' decision, the right-to-life movement in the U.S. consisted of lawyers, politicians, and doctors, almost all of whom were Catholic.&lt;ref name=munson&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=UFaCtYtIAjgC&amp;pg=PA85&amp;dq=history+catholic+church+pro-life&amp;client=firefox-a#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false The making of pro-life activists: how social movement mobilization works]  By Ziad W. Munson&lt;/ref&gt; The only coordinated opposition to abortion during the early 1970s came from the [[United States Conference of Catholic Bishops]] and the Family Life Bureau, also a Catholic organization. Mobilization of a wide-scale pro-life movement among Catholics began quickly after the ''Roe v. Wade'' decision with the creation of the [[National Right to Life Committee]] (NRLC). The NRLC also organized non-Catholics, eventually becoming the largest pro-life organization in the United States.&lt;ref name=munson/&gt;

===Evangelicals===
{{Unbalanced|section|date=December 2010}}
[[Randall Balmer|Randall Herbert Balmer]], Ph.D., argues in his book, ''Thy Kingdom Come,'' that despite the popular belief that pro-life sentiments galvanized the fundamentalist evangelical movement, what actually galvanized the movement was evangelical opposition to the American [[Internal Revenue Service]] (IRS). The IRS stripped evangelical universities, like [[Bob Jones University]], from their tax-exempt status for remaining racially [[Racial segregation|segregated]].&lt;ref name=balmer&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=LSO5YDifWz8C&amp;pg=PA209&amp;vq=history+baptist+abortion&amp;sig=KZgjPsS22v-Yl0bLPRrl6eu-Etk#PPA12,M1 ''They Kingdom Come'']  a book by Randall Herbert Balmer, Professor of Religion and History at [[Columbia University]].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=18429953 NPR.org] &quot;Church Meets State in the Oval Office&quot; on [[Fresh Air]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=1073173 NPR.org] &quot;Charismatic Movement&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

Before 1980, the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] officially advocated for loosening of abortion restrictions.&lt;ref name=balmer2&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=LSO5YDifWz8C&amp;pg=PA209&amp;vq=history+baptist+abortion&amp;sig=KZgjPsS22v-Yl0bLPRrl6eu-Etk#PPA12,M1 ''They Kingdom Come''] pg. 12, a book by Randall Herbert Balmer, Professor of Religion and History at [[Columbia University]].&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1971 and 1974 Southern Baptist Conventions, Southern Baptists were called upon &quot;to work for legislation that will allow the possibility of abortion under such conditions as rape, incest, clear evidence of severe fetal deformity, and carefully ascertained evidence of the likelihood of damage to the emotional, mental, and physical health of the mother.&quot;&lt;ref name=balmer2 /&gt; W. Barry Garrett wrote in the ''[[Baptist Press]]'', &quot;Religious liberty, human equality and justice are advanced by the &lt;nowiki&gt;[Roe v. Wade]&lt;/nowiki&gt; Supreme Court Decision.&quot;&lt;ref name=balmer2 /&gt;

By 1980, conservative Protestant leaders became vocal in their opposition to legalized abortion,&lt;ref name=balmer/&gt; and by the early 1990s [[Pat Robertson]]'s [[Christian Coalition of America]] became a significant pro-life organization.&lt;ref name=mckee&gt;McKeegan, M. (1993), &quot;The politics of abortion: A historical perspective&quot;, ''Women's Health Issues'' 3 (3), pp. 127–131&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, [[Richard Land]], president of the Southern Baptist Convention’s [[Ethics and Religious Liberty Commission]], said that making abortion illegal is more important than any other issue.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bpnews.net/bpnews.asp?ID=22064 Baptist Press]&quot;Sparks fly in Land’s appearance at black columnists’ meeting&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Overview==
{{See also|Abortion debate|Ethical aspects of abortion|Emergency contraception}}
Pro-life individuals generally believe that human life should be valued either from [[fertilization]] or [[implantation (human embryo)|implantation]] until natural death. The contemporary pro-life movement is typically, but not exclusively, influenced by [[Conservative Christian]] beliefs, especially in the United States, and has influenced certain strains of bioethical utilitarianism.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Holland, S. |year=2003 |title=Bioethics: a Philosophical Introduction |location=Cambridge |publisher=Polity Press }}&lt;/ref&gt; From that viewpoint, any action which destroys an [[embryo]] or [[fetus]] kills a [[person]]. Any deliberate destruction of human life is considered ethically or morally wrong and is not considered to be mitigated by any benefits to others, as such benefits are coming at the expense of the life of what they believe to be a person. In some cases, this belief extends to opposing abortion of fetuses that would almost certainly expire within a short time after birth, such as [[anencephaly|anencephalic]] fetuses.

Some pro-life advocates oppose certain forms of [[birth control]], particularly [[hormonal contraception]] such as [[emergency contraception]] (ECPs), and copper IUDs which prevent the [[implantation (human embryo)|implantation]] of an embryo. Because they believe that the term &quot;[[Beginning of pregnancy controversy|pregnancy]]&quot; should be defined so as to begin at fertilization, they refer to these [[contraceptive]]s as [[abortifacients]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Finn |first=J.T. |title=&quot;Birth Control&quot; Pills cause early Abortions |work=Pro-Life America — Facts on Abortion |publisher=prolife.com |date=2005-04-23 |url=http://www.prolife.com/BIRTHCNT.html |accessdate=2009-01-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{primary source-inline|date=September 2011}} The Catholic Church endorses this view,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Emergency 'Contraception' and Early Abortion |publisher=United States Conference of Catholic Bishops |date=1998-08-01 |url=http://www.usccb.org/prolife/issues/abortion/fact1098.shtml |accessdate=2009-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{primary source-inline|date=September 2011}} but the possibility that hormonal contraception has post-fertilization effects is disputed within the scientific community, including some pro-life physicians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |first=Susan A. |last=Crockett | coauthors = Donna Harrison, Joe DeCook, and Camilla Hersh |title=Hormone Contraceptives Controversies and Clarifications |publisher=American Association of Pro Life Obstetricians and Gynecologists |date = April 1999|url=http://www.aaplog.org/position-and-papers/oral-contraceptive-controversy/hormone-contraceptives-controversies-and-clarifications/ |accessdate=2011-02-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{primary source-inline|date=September 2011}}

Attachment to a pro-life position is often but not exclusively connected to religious beliefs about the [[sanctity of life]] (see also [[culture of life]]). Exclusively [[secular humanism|secular-humanist]] positions against abortion tend to be a minority viewpoint among pro-life advocates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.godlessprolifers.org/home.html |title=Atheist and Agnostic Pro-Life League Homepage |accessdate=November 4, 2006 |last=Wallace |first=James Matthew}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://secularprolife.org/ |title=Secular ProLife |accessdate=2010-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{primary source-inline|date=September 2011}} Many holding the pro-life position also tend toward a [[complementarianism|complementarian]] view of [[gender roles]], though there is also a self-described [[feminism|feminist]] element inside the movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Feminists for Life  |url=http://www.feministsforlife.org/who/aboutus.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{primary source-inline|date=September 2011}}

Moreover, conservative publications, such as ''[[American Thinker]]'', cite studies, such a comprehensive review of literature, published in the ''[[British Journal of Psychiatry]]'', which suggests that among women, &quot;there is a significant increase in mental health problems after abortion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DavenportMD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.americanthinker.com/blog/2011/09/major_study_links_suicide_and_other_mental_health_problems_to_abortion.html|title =Major Study Links Suicide and Other Mental Health Problems to Abortion|publisher = [[American Thinker]]|quote=An important meta-analysis published today in the prestigious British Journal of Psychiatry demonstrates that nearly 10% of mental health problems in women are directly attributable to abortion.  &quot;Abortion and mental health: quantitative synthesis and analysis of research published 1995-2009,&quot; by Priscilla Coleman of Bowling Green University, shows that women with an abortion history have an 81% increased risk of mental health problems and 155% increased risk of suicide.  This meta-analysis combines 22 studies of 877,181 women, 163, 831 of whom have had abortions.  A meta-analysis is an especially powerful type of study because it includes a large number of subjects, and by combining studies is much more reliable than a single study.|author=Davenport ML|accessdate = 1 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BJP&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://bjp.rcpsych.org/content/199/3/A11.full#sec-3|title =Abortion, mental health and dental disease|publisher = [[British Journal of Psychiatry]]|quote=A comprehensive review of the literature suggests that there is a significant increase in mental health problems after abortion. Coleman (pp. 180–186) suggests that these risks need to be reflected in the delivery of abortion services, and raises the thorny issue that 90% of UK abortions are justified on the presumption that abortion actually reduces the risk to mental health associated with continuing the pregnancy. There is an increasing awareness of increased comorbid physical illness in patients with severe mental illness. Kisely and colleagues (pp. 187–193) found that the levels of advanced dental disease were increased threefold in patients with severe mental illness. The authors suggest that there needs to be improved recognition of this problem – reflected in a more proactive approach to dental hygiene in these patients.|accessdate = 1 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the [[Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists]] responded to the review with a position statement in which they said  that three previously published systematic reviews and the RCOG guideline development group (who reviewed all available literature up to February 2011) have concluded that women who have an abortion are not at increased risk of mental health problems when compared with women who continue an unintended pregnancy.  Furthermore, they questioned the fact that while the paper’s findings pointed to increased substance misuse and suicidal behaviors among the groups of women, the research did not fully examine if these women had pre-existing mental health complications such as dependency issues and mood disorders before the abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rcog.org.uk/what-we-do/campaigning-and-opinions/statement/rcog-statement-bjpsych-paper-mental-health-risks-and-a |title=RCOG statement on BJPsych paper on mental health risks and abortion |publisher=Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists  |date=2011-09-01 |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Religion and pro-life movements==
{{See also|Religion and abortion|Sanctity of life|Culture of life}}
The variety in opinion on the issue of abortion is reflected in the diverse views of religious groups. For example, the Roman Catholic Church condemns every procured abortion as morally evil,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/archive/ccc_css/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a5.htm ''Catechism of the Catholic Church''] para.2271, &quot;Since the first century the Church has affirmed the moral evil of every procured abortion. This teaching has not changed and remains unchangeable. Direct abortion, that is to say, abortion willed either as an end or a means, is gravely contrary to the moral law: 'You shall not kill the embryo by abortion and shall not cause the newborn to perish'&quot;. Vatican website. Accessed 2011-02-05.&lt;/ref&gt; while traditional Jewish teachings allow abortion as a means of safeguarding the life and well-being of the pregnant woman.&lt;ref name=PewForum&gt;{{cite web|author=ANALYSIS September 30, 2008 |url=http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=351 |title=Pew Forums |publisher=Pewforum.org |date=2008-09-30 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
{{See also|Christianity and abortion|History of early Christian thought on abortion}}
[[Image:BentoXVI-37-10052007.jpg|thumb|right|Two people holding a pro-life sign at a meeting with [[Pope Benedict XVI]] at the [[Estádio do Pacaembu]] in [[São Paulo]], [[Brazil]] in 2007. Translation: &quot;No to abortion&quot;.]]
[[Image:Placa Catedral Castrense.jpg|thumb|right|Memorial for the aborted children, Military Cathedral of Chile, Providencia, Santiago, Chile.]]
[[Image:Monument to the Unborn.jpg|thumb|right|A monument to the unborn in Sainte Geneviève, Missouri.]]
Much of the pro-life movement in the United States and around the world finds support in the [[Catholicism and abortion|Roman Catholic Church]], [[Christian right]], the [[Lutheran Church-Missouri Synod]] and the [[Wisconsin Evangelical Lutheran Synod]], the [[Church of England]], the [[Anglican Church in North America]], the [[Eastern Orthodox Church]], and [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] (LDS).&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;id=R9UNAAAAQAAJ&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PA509&amp;dq=history+christian+opposition+to+abortion&amp;ots=XQF-Jfvf1v&amp;sig=n6wXPZmkutHUi5sqz2arM09Kw6w#v=onepage&amp;q=religous&amp;f=false Mapping the social landscape: readings in sociology]  By [[Susan J. Ferguson]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://scholar.google.com/scholar?q=info:sZdDDkTKT_EJ:scholar.google.com/&amp;output=viewport&amp;pg=1&amp;hl=en Sex, Politics, and Religion: The Clash Between Poland and the European Union over Abortion] by Alicia Czerwinski in the ''Denver Journal of International Law and Policy'', 2003&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mospat.ru/index.php?mid=192 |title=Официальный сайт Русской Православной Церкви |publisher=Mospat.ru |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://library.lds.org/nxt/gateway.dll/Curriculum/home%20and%20family.htm/true%20to%20the%20faith%20a%20gospel%20reference.htm/abortion.htm?f=templates$fn=document-frame.htm$3.0$q=$x= True to the Faith (LDS) article on abortion]. Retrieved 2006-05-06.&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the pro-life teachings of these denominations vary considerably.  The Eastern Orthodox Church and Roman Catholic Church consider abortion to be immoral in all cases, but permit acts which indirectly result in the death of the fetus in the case where the mother's life is threatened. In Pope John Paul II's Letter to Families he simply stated the Roman Catholic Church's view on abortion and euthanasia: &quot;Laws which legitimize the direct killing of innocent human beings through abortion or euthanasia are in complete opposition to the inviolable right to life proper to every individual; they thus deny the equality of everyone before the law.&quot;

The [[National Association of Evangelicals]] and the LDS Church oppose abortion on demand; however, the NAE considers abortion allowable in cases with clear evidence of severe fetal deformity, dire threat to the life/physical health of the pregnant woman, or when a pregnancy results from rape or incest.&lt;ref name=pew&gt;[http://pewforum.org/docs/?DocID=351 &quot;Religious Groups’ Official Positions on Abortion&quot;] Pew Forum&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nae.net/government-affairs/policy-resolutions/59-abortion-1973 |title=Abortion 1973 |publisher=Nae.net |date= |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nae.net/government-affairs/policy-resolutions/446-abortion-2010 |title=Abortion 2010 |publisher=Nae.net |date=2008-09-16 |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Taskforce of United Methodists on Abortion and Sexuality]] (TUMAS) was formed in 1987 to further the pro-life ministry in [[The United Methodist Church]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas C. Oden&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url = http://books.google.com/books?id=pB6BrgQRjbQC&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=Taskforce+of+United+Methodists+on+Abortion+and+Sexuality&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=Taskforce%20of%20United%20Methodists%20on%20Abortion%20and%20Sexuality&amp;f=false| title = The rebirth of orthodoxy: signs of new life in Christianity|publisher = [[HarperCollins]]|accessdate = 2009-01-04|isbn = 9780060097851|date = 2002-12-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Southern Baptist Convention]] believes that abortion is allowable only in cases where there is a direct threat to the life of the woman.&lt;ref name=pew/&gt; Other [[Mainline Protestant|mainstream Protestant]] denominations in the United States, such as the [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal Church]], the [[Evangelical Lutheran Church in America]], the [[Presbyterian Church (U.S.A.)]], and the [[United Church of Christ]], are pro-choice.&lt;ref name=pew/&gt;

===Islam===
{{See also|Islam and abortion}}
There is very little discussion about the [[abortion debate]] in Islamic countries.&lt;ref name=brockopp&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=agqtUUoOgQoC&amp;pg=PA73&amp;dq=muslim+%22pro-life%22+movement&amp;lr=&amp;client=firefox-a#v=onepage&amp;q=pro-life&amp;f=false Islamic ethics of life: abortion, war, and euthanasia] By Jonathan E. Brockopp&lt;/ref&gt; In many Muslim countries, women must gain consent (medical, religious, state or spousal) for an abortion.&lt;ref name=brockopp/&gt; Although there are different opinions among Muslim scholars on the topic of '''Islam and abortion''', most agree that the termination of a pregnancy after four months—the point at which, in Islam, a fetus is thought to become a living soul—is not permissible. Many Islamic thinkers contend that in cases prior to four months of gestation, abortion should be permissible only in instances in which a mother's life is in danger or in cases of rape.&lt;ref name=brockopp/&gt;

===Hinduism===
{{See also|Hinduism and abortion|Abortion in India|Sex-selective abortion and female infanticide}}
Although traditional Hindu texts and teachings have opposed elective abortions,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/hinduism/hinduethics/abortion_1.shtml BBC] &quot;Hinduism and abortion&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; a vocal pro-life movement is limited in India, the nation with the largest [[Hindu]] population.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Pro-life_movement&amp;action=edit&amp;section=8 &quot;Legal but not available&quot;] India Together&lt;/ref&gt; Most abortions in India are done for sex selection, with boys being favored.&lt;ref name=&quot;business&quot;/&gt; As a result, activists who argue against abortion in India are typically women's rights activists. Recently, these pro-life activists took [[Google]], [[Yahoo]], and [[Microsoft]] to court, suing to remove web ads that sell products that enable parents to determine the sex of a fetus.&lt;ref name=business&gt;{{cite web|last=Einhorn |first=Bruce |url=http://www.businessweek.com/globalbiz/blog/eyeonasia/archives/2008/08/india_anti-abor.html |title=Business Week |publisher=Business Week |date=2008-08-19 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some Hindu institutions oppose abortion,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hinduismtoday.com/archives/1985/09/1985-09-07.shtml |title=Hinduism Today |publisher=Hinduism Today |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and teach that abortion prevents a soul in its [[karma|karmic]] progress toward God.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-95764442.html Feminism &amp; Nonviolence Studies] | Date: 9/22/1998 | Author: Derr, Mary Krane; Murti, Vasu&lt;/ref&gt; Other Hindu theologians believe personhood begins at 3 months and develops through to 5 months of gestation, possibly implying permitting abortion in extenuating circumstances up to the third month and considering any abortion past the third month to be destruction of the soul's current incarnate body.&lt;ref&gt;Chapter 1: Dilemmas of Life and Death: Hindu Ethics in a North American Context | Date: 1995 | Author: Crawford, S. Cromwell&lt;/ref&gt;

===Judaism===
{{See also|Judaism and abortion}}

In Judaism, views on abortion draw primarily upon the legal and ethical teachings of the [[Hebrew Bible]], the [[Torah]], the case-by-case decisions of [[responsa]], and other rabbinic literature. In the modern period, moreover, Jewish thinking on abortion has responded both to [[Liberalism|liberal]] understandings of personal autonomy as well as Christian opposition to abortion.&lt;ref&gt;Jakobovits, Sinclair&lt;/ref&gt; Polls of Jews in America report that 88% of American Jews are pro-choice.&lt;ref name=cjcs&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjcs.net/survey4.htm |title=Religion and the Public Square: Attitudes of American Jews in Comparative Perspective – A Follow-Up Study: Table 2 |publisher=Cjcs.net |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prominent Jewish pro-life activist [[Michael Medved]] has said, &quot;Jewish law for millennia has been extremely clear, that abortion is only permitted when the life of the mother is directly threatened... To link Jewish tradition to the pro-choice position is 'ludicrous and ignorant'.&quot;&lt;ref name=jcrhon&gt;[http://www.jewishchronicle.org/article.php?article_id=3308 &quot;Jewish pro-life activist Medved says children are ‘a gift, not a choice’&quot;] Jewish Chronicle&lt;/ref&gt; In Israel, the major pro-life organization is [[Efrat (organization)|Efrat]],&lt;ref name=efrat&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.friendsofefrat.org/pro-choice-pro-life.php |title=Efrat |publisher=Friendsofefrat.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; which primarily raises funds to relieve the &quot;financial and social pressures&quot; on pregnant women so that they will not terminate their pregnancies.&lt;ref name=efrat/&gt;

==Current activity==
=== In the United States ===
The pro-life movement in the U.S. includes a variety of organizations, with no single centralized decision-making body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Encyclopedia of women in American politics&quot;/&gt; There are diverse arguments and rationales for the pro-life stance. American Catholics generally agree that the right to life extends to the unborn child; this belief is in line with Catholic opposition to [[capital punishment]]. Pro-life American Protestants and Jews do not all agree on the death penalty, and their opposition to abortion is typically on moral, economic or legal grounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Making America&quot;&gt;{{cite book |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=_7YeBPdFAAkC&amp;pg=PA716 |page=716 |title=Making America: A History of the United States |publisher=Cengage Learning |year=2010 |isbn=0618471391 |edition=5 |author=Carol Berkin, Christopher Miller, Robert Cherny, James Gormly, Douglas Egerton, Kelly Woestman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Major organizations in the U.S. that support the pro-life movement include [[Focus on the Family]], [[Concerned Women for America]], [[Family Research Institute]], [[National Right to Life Committee]], [[American Family Association]], and [[Live Action (anti-abortion group)|Live Action]].

=== In Europe ===
[[Image:AntiAbortionDemonstration.jpg|thumb|right|Pro-life demonstration ''Each Life Matters'' in [[Madrid]], [[Spain]], on 17 October 2009.]]
Contrary to the United States, in Europe abortion has been legalized through parliamentary acts. In Western Europe this has had the effect at once of both more closely regulating the use of abortion, and at the same time mediating and reducing the impact pro-life campaigns have had on the law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Outshoorn96&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Outshoorn|first=Joyce|title=Abortion politics: public policy in cross-cultural perspective|year=1996|publisher=Routledge|editor=Marianne Givens and Dorothy M. Stetson|page=161|chapter=The stability of compromise: Abortion politics in Western Europe|quote=...parliamentary decision are sustained by political parties which, in comparison to the United States, are deeply rooted in European society. The political parties have managed to regulate and pacify the political reform process, which in the decision-making stage marginalized opposition outside parliament.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In [[France]], the first specifically pro-life organization, [[Laissez-les-vivre-SOS futures mères]], was created in 1971 during the debate that was to lead to the [[Simone Veil#Minister of Health|Veil Law]] in 1975. Its main spokesman was the geneticist [[Jérôme Lejeune]]. Since 2005, the French pro-life movement has organized an annual [[March for Life (Paris)|March for Life]] in [[Paris]] attracting several thousand demonstrators.
*In the [[United Kingdom]], the most prominent pro-life organization is the [[Society for the Protection of Unborn Children]].
*In [[Spain]], over one million demonstrators took part in a march in [[Madrid]] in October 2009 to protest plans by the government of [[José Luis Rodríguez Zapatero|José Luis Zapatero]] to legalize elective abortions and eliminate parental consent restrictions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jkOSVB9MchL7LwqJLWOQ1YoiLHww |title='&amp;#39;Agence France Presse'&amp;#39;, 17 October 2009 |publisher=Google.com |date=2009-10-17 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In Israel ===

In Israel, the major pro-life organization is [[Efrat (organization)|Efrat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;efrat&quot;/&gt; Efrat activists primarily raise funds to relieve the &quot;financial and social pressures&quot; on pregnant women so that they will not terminate their pregnancies.&lt;ref name=efrat/&gt;  Efrat is not known to do any other kind of activism.&lt;ref name=efrat/&gt;

==&quot;Consistent Life Ethic&quot;==
A major stated goal within the pro-life movement is to &quot;restore legal protection to innocent human life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrlc.org/Missionstatement.htm National Right to Life Mission Statement].&lt;/ref&gt; This protection would include fetuses and embryos, persons who cannot communicate their wishes due to physical or mental incapacitation, and those who are too weak to resist being euthanized.

Some pro-life advocates, such as those subscribing to the philosophy of a [[Consistent Life Ethic]] (formerly known as the Seamless Garment), oppose virtually all acts that end human life. They would argue that [[abortion]], [[euthanasia]], [[capital punishment]], and unjust war are all wrong. Prominent organizations advocating a Consistent Life Ethic include [[Democrats For Life of America]] (which includes dozens of Congressmen), [[Sojourners|Sojourners Magazine]], and [[Priests for Life]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.consistent-life.org/members.html Member Organizations], Consistent Life.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.priestsforlife.org/consistentethic/ |title=Abortion - Pro Life - Priests for Life's Position on &quot;The Consistent Ethic of Life&quot; |publisher=Priestsforlife.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Others argue that the death penalty can be a fair punishment for [[murder]], justifiably inflicted by lawful authority, whereas abortion is an attack on an innocent.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}  The increasing attention paid to this controversial position may result from the large Roman Catholic membership of the pro-life movement, striving to adhere to Catholic Church teachings on the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usccb.org/sdwp/national/deathpenalty/ The Catholic Campaign to End the Use of the Death Penalty], United States Conference of Catholic Bishops.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The debate==
{{Refimprove|date=September 2009}}
{{POV-section|date=November 2010}}
[[Image:Bytom33.JPG|thumb|A pro-life memorial in [[Bytom]], [[Poland]]. Partial translation: &quot;Dedicated in memory of unborn children&amp;nbsp;– victims of abortion&quot;.]]
{{main|Abortion debate}}
In some countries, the abortion issue remains one of the broader and more controversial societal issues. A broad spectrum of positions exists on this issue, from those who advocate abortion-on-demand at any point during a pregnancy until birth on the one end, to those who oppose every form of abortion on the other. Between these two there is a considerable range of positions. Some oppose abortion, but are content to work at reducing the number of abortions through prevention of unwanted pregnancies, a task they accomplish through encouraging abstinence, targeted [[sex education]] and/or increased availability of [[contraception]]. Current legislation in [[United States Congress]], the [[Pregnant Women Support Act]], seeks to reduce the abortion rate in the U.S. without making any procedure illegal and without overturning ''Roe v. Wade''. There are many who support legal abortion within the first [[trimesters]] but oppose [[late-term abortion]]s. Those who oppose late-term abortions usually take the view that once a fetus has reached the point where it could live independently from the woman, the balance of rights swings in favour of the fetus.  Some oppose most abortions but make exception for cases where the woman's life is in serious risk. In this category, some likewise make an exception for severe [[birth defect|fetal deformities]].  Others make exceptions when the pregnancy was not caused by consensual sexual activity or may violate social taboos, as in cases of [[rape]] and [[incest]]. Some allow for all these exceptions, but stop short of abortion-on-demand.

Another issue is that of mandatory notification and consent. Some believe that a pregnant minor should not be allowed to abort her pregnancy without notifying her parent or guardian because of the risks and possible medical complications.  Likewise, some believe that notifying the woman's husband should be required because of parental rights.  In a 2003 [[Gallup poll]] in the United States, 72% of respondents were in favour of spousal notification, with 26% opposed; of those polled.&lt;ref&gt;[http://people-press.org/commentary/display.php3?AnalysisID=122 Pew Research Centre] &quot;Public Opinion Supports Alito on Spousal Notification Even as It Favors Roe v. Wade&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; In many states, such restrictions are mandated by law, though often with the right of judicial oversight. Others believe that the child's biological father must be notified.

Generally speaking, the pro-life position regards abortion as a form of [[infanticide]], and thus seeks legal restrictions on abortions. Pro-life advocates typically argue that if a pregnant woman is unable or unwilling to raise the child, there is the option of placing the child up for [[adoption]].

One analysis suggests that, since pro-life families may be expected to have fewer abortions (and more children) than their pro-choice counterparts and they may pass their beliefs on to their children, this will change the voter demographic of future generations. In this way, legal abortion-on-demand may ''also'' serve to ''increase'' the dominance of the pro-life position in society. This hypothesis has been called the &quot;[[Roe effect]],&quot; and may explain the trend towards more widespread support of the pro-life movement.

The debate is often presented{{By whom|date=May 2011}} as between those who believe fetuses are persons and  should therefore have rights, vs. those who believe fetuses are not persons but &quot;future persons&quot; or &quot;potential persons&quot;.  However, not all pro-choice advocates claim that fetuses are non-persons; there are also those who say that even if fetuses are persons, their position inside the body of another person entitles that other person to kill them anyway.  This is sometimes called{{By whom|date=May 2011}} the &quot;Body-Ownership Argument&quot; or the &quot;Abortion-As-Justifiable-Homicide Argument&quot;.  It need not be based only on the fetus' location; it can also be justified by citing the fact that the fetus is taking nutrients from the mother's bloodstream, and injecting metabolic end-products into her bloodstream, and preparing to subject her to a major medical/surgical trauma (childbirth), all of which she is entitled to prevent, even by means of deadly force.&lt;ref&gt;(See, e.g., Judith Jarvis Thompson, &quot;A Defense of Abortion,&quot; Journal of Philosophy and Public Affairs, 1 (1971), p.&amp;nbsp;47.)&lt;/ref&gt;

Some pro-choice advocates also point out that, while they too would prefer to see abortion not happen, when abortion is illegal, women who want abortions seek [[unsafe abortion]]s, placing their own lives at risk.&lt;ref&gt;World Health Organization paper: 'Unsafe abortion: the preventable pandemic' http://www.who.int/reproductivehealth/publications/general/lancet_4.pdf.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal and political aspects==
[[Image:DFLA March.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Democrats for Life of America]] demonstrates at the 2006 [[March for Life]].]]
The United States [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican Party]] platform advocates a pro-life position,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gop.com/media/2004platform.pdf ''2004 Republican Party Platform: A Safer World and a More Hopeful America''] p. 84.&lt;/ref&gt; though there are some pro-choice Republicans. The Republican group [[The Wish List (political organization)|The Wish List]] supports pro-choice Republican women just as [[EMILY's List]] supports pro-choice Democratic women. The [[Susan B. Anthony List]] (SBA List) is dedicated to &quot;increasing the percentage of pro-life women in Congress and high public office,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Its connected Candidate Fund increases the percentage of pro-life women in politics.'', http://www.suzyb.org/blog/Elections Retrieved 25 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and seeks to eliminate abortion in the U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;SBA List Mission Statement&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sba-list.org/about-sba-list/our-mission |title=SBA List Mission: Advancing, Mobilizing and Representing Pro-Life Women |year=2008 |publisher=Susan B. Anthony List |accessdate=October 18, 2010 |quote=To accomplish our ultimate goal of ending abortion in this country...}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Democrats for Life of America]] are a group of pro-life Democrats on the [[Left-wing politics|political left]] who advocate for a pro-life plank in the [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic Party]]'s platform and for pro-life Democratic candidates.  Former vice-presidential candidate [[Sargent Shriver]], the late [[Robert P. Casey|Robert Casey]], a former two-term governor of [[Pennsylvania]], and former Rep. [[Bart Stupak]] (D-Mich), a vocal pro-life proponent and leader of the Democratic pro-life caucus in the [[United States House of Representatives]], have been among the most well-known pro-life Democrats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By PATRICK O'CONNOR |url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0310/34767.html |title=&quot;Historic win close after Bart Stupak deal&quot; |publisher=Politico.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16|unused_data=3/21/10 3:10 PM EDT}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, following his vote in favor of the [[Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act]], Marjorie Dannenfelser of the SBA List reported that her organization was revoking a pro-life award it had been planning to give to Stupak,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2010/03/21/stupak-says-health-care-deal-looming-abortion-funding/ | work=Fox News | title=Choice, Life Groups Slam Obama Order on Abortion Funding | date=2010-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; and pro-life organizations accused Stupak of having betrayed the pro-life movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsmax.com/InsideCover/stupak-gop-pro-life/2010/03/22/id/353491 |title=Pro-Life Groups Help Stupak's GOP Opponents |publisher=Newsmax.com |date=2010-03-22 |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianitytoday.com/ct/2010/marchweb-only/22-13.0.html |title=Stupak: From Prolife Groups' Hero to Villain 'In a Nanosecond' &amp;#124; Christianity Today &amp;#124; A Magazine of Evangelical Conviction |publisher=Christianity Today |date=2010-03-22 |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.christianpost.com/article/20100410/pro-life-groups-offer-mixed-tribute-to-bart-stupak/ |title=Bart Stupak's Retirement Stirs Mixed Reactions, Christian News |publisher=Christianpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/03/23/AR2010032302841.html | work=The Washington Post | first=Kathleen | last=Parker | title=Stupak's fall from pro-life grace | date=2010-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Controversies over terminology ==
Pro-life and pro-choice individuals often use political framing to convey their perspective on the issues and, in some cases, to discredit opposing views.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}  Pro-life advocates tend to use terms such as &quot;unborn baby&quot;, &quot;unborn child&quot;, or &quot;pre-born child&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Chamberlain, Pam and Jean Hardisty. (2007) [http://www.publiceye.org/magazine/v14n1/ReproPatriarch-07.html &quot;The Importance of the Political 'Framing' of Abortion&quot;]. ''The Public Eye Magazine'' Vol. 14, No. 1. Retrieved January 18, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/05/weekinreview/05greenhouse.html?scp=1&amp;sq=infanticide &quot;The Roberts Court Takes on Abortion&quot;.] ''New York Times.'' November 5, 2006. Retrieved January 18, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; while some pro-choice advocates use scientific terminology (often distinguishing between a [[zygote]], a [[blastula]], an [[embryo]], and a [[fetus]], and objecting to &quot;fetus&quot; as a blanket term).{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}  Pro-life individuals may also prefer to refer to the pregnant woman as a &quot;mother&quot;, while some pro-choice individuals consider this inappropriate, and some in the medical community may see its usage as insensitive and biased in certain narrowly defined contexts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last1=de Crespigny| first1=L| year=2003| title=Words matter: nomenclature and communication in perinatal medicine| journal=Clinics in perinatology| volume=30| issue=1| pages=17–25| issn=0095-5108| pmid=12696783|quote=The language proposed is not intended to be rigidly adhered to in all situations but rather is an appropriate starting point after which one needs to be responsive to the position of the pregnant woman. It is important to individualize language to cater to the views of individual patients.| doi=10.1016/S0095-5108(02)00088-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Both &quot;pro-choice&quot; and &quot;pro-life&quot; are examples of terms labeled as [[framing (social sciences)|political framing]]: they are terms which purposely try to define their philosophies in the best possible light, while by definition attempting to describe their opposition in the worst possible light. &quot;Pro-choice&quot; implies that the alternative viewpoint is &quot;anti-choice&quot;, while &quot;pro-life&quot; implies the alternative viewpoint is &quot;pro-death&quot; or &quot;anti-life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rnclife.org/reports/2009/spring/RNC-Spring09.pdf |title=Example of &quot;anti-life&quot; terminology |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly each side's use of the term &quot;rights&quot; (&quot;reproductive rights&quot;, &quot;right to life of the unborn&quot;) implies a validity in their stance, given that the presumption in language is that rights are inherently a good thing and so implies an invalidity in the viewpoint of their opponents.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

The [[Associated Press]] encourages journalists to use the terms &quot;abortion rights&quot; and &quot;anti-abortion&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Goldstein, Norm, ed. The Associated Press Stylebook. Philadelphia: Basic Books, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2009 [[Gallup Poll]], a majority of U.S. adults (51%) called themselves &quot;pro-life&quot; on the issue of abortion—for the first time since Gallup began asking the question in 1995—while 42% identified themselves as &quot;pro-choice&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Lydia|last=Saad|title=More Americans &quot;Pro-Life&quot; Than &quot;Pro-Choice&quot; for First TimeAlso, fewer think abortion should be legal &quot;under any circumstances&quot;|date=May 15, 2009|publisher=Gallup, Inc|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/118399/More-Americans-Pro-Life-Than-Pro-Choice-First-Time.aspx|accessdate=2011-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; although pro-choice groups noted that acceptance of the &quot;pro-life&quot; label did not in all cases indicate opposition to legalized abortion, and that another recent poll had indicated that a plurality were pro-choice.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/30771408/ns/us_news-life/ |agency=Associated Press |title=Majority of Americans now ‘pro-life,’ poll says |date=May 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A March 2011 [[Rasmussen Reports]] poll concluded that Americans are &quot;closely divided between those who call themselves pro-life&quot; and those who consider themselves as &quot;pro-choice&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Americans Think New State Laws Will Reduce Number of Abortions|date=March 10, 2011|publisher=Rasmussen Reports, LLC|url=http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/current_events/abortion/americans_think_new_state_laws_will_reduce_number_of_abortions|accessdate=2011-03-15|quote=While the country remains closely divided between those who call themselves pro-life and those who view themselves as pro-choice, the majority of Likely U.S. Voters think abortion is morally wrong in most cases.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a February 2011 Rasmussen Reports poll of &quot;Likely U.S. Voters&quot;, fifty percent view themselves as
&quot;pro-choice&quot; and forty percent &quot;say they are pro-life&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Half of U.S. Voters are Pro-Choice, But 53% Say Abortion's Usually Morally Wrong|date=February 17, 2011|publisher=Rasmussen Reports, LLC|url=http://www.rasmussenreports.com/public_content/politics/current_events/abortion/half_of_u_s_voters_are_pro_choice_but_53_say_abortion_s_usually_morally_wrong|accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of advocacy==
{{Refimprove|date=May 2007}}
'''Pro-life advocacy''' involves a variety of activities, from promoting the pro-life position to the public in general, lobbying public officials, or attempting to dissuade individual women to forgo abortions. Some efforts involve distributing literature, providing counseling services, conducting public demonstrations or protests and private or public prayer.

[[Image:Prolife-DC.JPG|thumb|Pro-life protesters make a silent demonstration in front of the [[United States]] [[Supreme Court of the United States|Supreme Court]] in [[Washington, D.C.]]]]

===Demonstrations and protests===
*'''Mass demonstrations''': every year, American pro-life advocates hold a [[March for Life]] in Washington, D.C., on 22 January, the anniversary date of the ''Roe v. Wade'' Supreme Court decision legalizing abortion in the United States. Similar events take place on a smaller scale in other U.S. cities, such as the [[Walk for Life West Coast|Walk for Life]] in [[San Francisco]], California. In Spain, over a million people took part in a demonstration on 17 October 2009 protesting the legalization of abortion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=lefigaro.fr |url=http://www.lefigaro.fr/international/2009/10/17/01003-20091017ARTFIG00704-grande-manifestation-anti-avortement-a-madrid-.php |title='&amp;#39;Le Figaro'&amp;#39;, 17 October 2009 |publisher=Lefigaro.fr |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; On a lesser scale, the Paris [[March for Life (Paris)|March for Life]] gathers thousands of French pro-life marchers every year in January. Also, thousands of Pro Life supporters hold a march for life in Ottawa, Canada every May, the anniversary of R v. Morgertaller
*'''The [[Life Chain|life chain]]:''' The &quot;Life Chain&quot; is a public demonstration technique that involves standing in a row on sidewalks holding signs bearing pro-life messages. Messages include &quot;Abortion Kills Children&quot;, &quot;Abortion stops a beating heart&quot; or &quot;Abortion Hurts Women&quot;. Participants, as an official policy, do not yell or chant slogans and do not block pedestrians or roadways.  Many [[Right to Life]] chapters hold Life Chain events yearly&lt;ref&gt;http://nationallifechain.org Retrieved 25 September 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and the annual worldwide [[40 Days For Life|40 Days for Life]] campaigns also use this technique.
*'''The rescue''': A &quot;rescue operation&quot; involves pro-life activists blocking the entrances to an [[abortion clinic]] in order to prevent anyone from entering. The stated goal of this practice is to force the clinic to shut down for the day. Often, the protesters are removed by law enforcement. Some clinics were protested so heavily in this fashion that they closed down permanently. &quot;The rescue&quot; was first attempted by [[Operation Save America|Operation Rescue]]. Ever since President [[Bill Clinton]] signed the [[Freedom of Access to Clinic Entrances Act]] into law, the rescue has become prohibitively expensive, and has rarely been attempted.

[[Image:Prolifevan.jpg|right|thumb|A pro-life van parked outside of an [[abortion clinic]].]]
*'''The truth display''': In conducting a &quot;truth display&quot;, protesters publicly display highly-magnified pictures of aborted fetuses. Some pro-life groups believe that publicizing the graphic results of abortion is an effective way of making their case. The [[Pro-Life Action League]] has used this form of activism in its ''Face the Truth'' displays. Members of one group, [[Survivors of the Abortion Holocaust]], have been jailed numerous times for these types of displays which they set up both legally and illegally on [[university]] campuses. &quot;Truth displays&quot; are a controversial tactic, including within the pro-life movement.&lt;ref&gt;Pavone, Frank A.[http://www.priestsforlife.org/articles/shouldweuse.htm &quot;Should We Use Graphic Images?&quot;] ''Priests for Life'' Retrieved September 7, 2007. Quote: &quot;Even among those who oppose abortion, answers to this question [Should we use graphic images?] vary&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Picketing (protest)|Picketing]]''': The majority of the facilities that perform abortions in the United States experience some form of protest from pro-life demonstrators every year, of which the most common form is picketing.  Besides the clinics themselves, other sites for right-to-life picketing include abortion workers' homes, churches, and second-job workplaces, and abortion workers' children's schools.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} Most facilities that perform abortions experience picketing at least 20 times a year;{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} in 2007, 11,113 instances of picketing were either reported to, or obtained by, the [[National Abortion Federation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;naf&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.prochoice.org/pubs_research/publications/downloads/about_abortion/violence_statistics.pdf |title=NAF Violence and Disruption Statistics |format=PDF |accessdate=2008-07-28 |publisher=National Abortion Federation}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Counseling===
*'''[[Sidewalk counseling]]''': &quot;Sidewalk counseling&quot; is a form of pro-life advocacy which is conducted outside of [[abortion clinic]]s. Activists seek to communicate with those entering the building, or with passersby in general, in an effort to persuade them not to have an [[abortion]] or to reconsider their position on the [[abortion debate|morality of abortion]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hillvcolorado&quot;&gt;[http://www.law.cornell.edu/supct/html/98-1856.ZO.html#FN2 Hill v. Colorado (98-1856) 530 U.S. 703 (2000)]. Retrieved December 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; They do so by trying to engage in conversation, displaying signs, distributing [[Pamphlet|literature]], or giving directions to a nearby [[crisis pregnancy center]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hillvcolorado&quot; /&gt;  The &quot;Chicago Method&quot; is an approach to sidewalk counseling that involves giving those about to enter an abortion facility copies of [[lawsuit]]s filed against the facility or its [[physician]]s. The name comes from the fact that it was first used by [[Pro-Life Action League]] in [[Chicago]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prolifeaction.org/news/2002v21n2/controversy.htm &quot;Controversy in the Activist Movement&quot;, ''Pro-Life Action News'', August 2000].&lt;/ref&gt; The intent of the Chicago Method is to turn the woman away from a facility that the protesters deem &quot;unsafe&quot;, thus giving her time to reconsider her choice to abort.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.priestsforlife.org/articles/chicagomethod.html &quot;The &quot;Chicago Method&quot;: Sidewalk Counseling that appeals to the Mother's concerns for her own well-being,&quot; Priests for Life].&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Crisis pregnancy center]]s:''' &quot;Crisis pregnancy centers&quot; are non-profit organizations, mainly in the United States, usually established with the goal of presenting pregnant women with alternatives to abortion. Though many CPCs refrain from engaging in the public debate on abortion,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.birthright.org/htmpages/philo.htm |title=Birthright International - 800-550-4900 - About Birthright |publisher=Birthright.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  they are nearly always staffed by supporters of the pro-life movement. The total number of CPCs has been estimated at several thousand in the U.S.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Nancy |last=Gibbs|title=The Grass-Roots Abortion War|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1590444-2,00.html|work=[[Time Magazine]]|publisher=[[Time Magazine]]|page=html|date=2007-02-15|accessdate=2009-12-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Care Net]] network as well as the National Institute of Family and Life Advocates each claim over a thousand affiliated centers, [[Heartbeat International (Christian organization)|Heartbeat International]] 900 and [[Birthright International]] several hundred. While originally these centers concentrated on providing direct material support or information on available social help, a growing number have more recently acquired medical and paramedical equipment: an estimated one CPC in four offers free sonograms in the hope of convincing pregnant women not to abort.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sonograms&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Michael Alison |last=Chandler|title=Antiabortion Centers Offer Sonograms to Further Cause|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/09/08/AR2006090801967.html|work=[[Washington Post]]|publisher=Washington Post|page=html|date=2006-09-09|accessdate=2008-02-24|quote=&quot;By many accounts, the ultrasound exams have proven effective in convincing women to stay pregnant. A 2005 survey by Care Net, a Sterling-based network of about 1,000 antiabortion pregnancy centers in the United States and Canada, found that 72 percent of women who were initially &quot;strongly leaning&quot; toward abortion decided to carry their pregnancies to term after seeing a sonogram. Fifty percent made the same choice after counseling alone.
A report in July from congressional Democrats found that the federal government has contributed $30 million to antiabortion pregnancy centers since 2001. Most of that money paid for sexual abstinence education. But some was distributed as grants to help pay for ultrasound machines, the report found. For example, Life Line Pregnancy Care Center in Loudoun County received a $50,000 federal grant last year to buy a machine. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics have claimed that many CPCs engage in deceptive tactics to attract and persuade women contemplating abortion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/ac2/wp-dyn/A42118-2002Feb20?language=printer &quot;Abortion Battle: Prenatal Care or Pressure Tactics?&quot;] The Washington Post&lt;/ref&gt; Some CPCs have been court ordered to stop representing themselves as providing a complete range of health services, including abortion.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6D91331F931A15757C0A962958260&amp;scp=9&amp;sq=crisis%20pregnancy%20centers&amp;st=cse &quot;Anti-Abortion Center's Ads Ruled Misleading&quot;] ''The New York Times''&lt;/ref&gt;

===Specialty license plates===
In the United States, some states issue [[Vehicle registration plates of the United States#Vanity and specialty plates|specialty license plates]] that have a pro-life theme. [[Choose Life (organization)|Choose Life]], an advocacy group founded in 1997, was successful in securing a pro-life automobile tag in Florida. Subsequently, the organization has been actively helping groups in other states pursue &quot;Choose Life&quot; license plates.&lt;ref&gt;Burge, Kathleen: [http://www.boston.com/news/local/articles/2006/05/05/driving_force/ &quot;Driving force&quot;] Boston Globe, May 5, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Madigan, Erin: [http://www.stateline.org/live/ViewPage.action?siteNodeId=136&amp;languageId=1&amp;contentId=15079 &quot;Choose Life Car Tags Spark Debate&quot;] Stateline.org, November 25, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;

===Violence===
====Against abortion providers====
{{Main|Anti-abortion violence}}

Violent incidents directed against abortion providers range from the [[murder]]s and [[attempted murder]]s of physicians and clinic staff to [[arson]] and [[bomb]]ings of [[abortion clinic]]s, to ordinary fisticuffs.  G. Davidson Smith of the [[Canadian Security Intelligence Service]] (CSIS) defined violence related to abortion extremism, [[animal rights]], and [[eco-terrorism|environmentalism]] as &quot;[[single issue terrorism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.csis-scrs.gc.ca/en/publications/commentary/com74.asp Single Issue Terrorism].&lt;/ref&gt; Acts of violence against abortion providers and facilities in North America have largely subsided following a peak in the mid-1990s.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.religioustolerance.org/abo_viol.htm Violence at US Abortion Clinics].&lt;/ref&gt; The National Clinic Violence Survey, conducted by the pro-choice [[Feminist Majority Foundation]], reported in 2006 that severe violence affected 18.4% of abortion providers and facilities in the preceding year, 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.feminist.org/research/cvsurveys/clinic_survey2005.pdf |title = 2005 National Clinic Violence Survey |date = May, 2006 |publisher = Feminist Majority Foundation {{PDFlink|&amp;#8203;|80.4&amp;nbsp;KB}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; This figure is lower than at any time since 1994, which is consistent with statistics from the [[National Abortion Federation]] that show violence against abortion clinics or providers has steadily decreased since 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;naf&quot; /&gt;

A notable example of anti-abortion violence in the United States is the [[Murder of George Tiller|murder]] of [[George Tiller|Dr. George Tiller]], a physician who provided late term abortions as part of his practice. He was shot and killed in the foyer of the church where he was a member.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/26/us/26tiller.html?ref=georgertiller &quot;An Abortion Battle, Fought to the Death&quot; NYT 25 July 2009], New York Times 25 July 2009&lt;/ref&gt; A large number of pro-life leaders and groups condemned the killing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrlc.org/press_releases_new/Release053109.html |title=National Right to Life Condemns the Killing of Dr. George Tiller |publisher=Nrlc.org |date=2009-05-31 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbn.com/cbnnews/us/2009/May/Pro-life-Community-Condemns-Tiller-Shooting/ |title=Pro-Life Leaders Respond to Tiller Shooting |publisher=Cbn.com |date=2009-06-01 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lifenews.com/state4192.html |title=Pro-Life Tiller Response Continues: Shooting Abortion Practitioner Not Pro-Life |publisher=Lifenews.com |date=2009-06-01 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Right to Life Committee]], the largest pro-life organization in the [[United States]], has stated that it &quot;unequivocally condemns any acts of violence used by individuals regardless of their motivation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nrlc.org/press_releases_new/Violence_condemnation.htm |title=National Right To Life Condemns Violence |publisher=Nrlc.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[American Life League]] has issued a &quot;Pro-life Proclamation Against Violence&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.all.org/article.php?id=10357 Pro-life proclamation against violence].&lt;/ref&gt; 

Nearly all pro-life leaders condemned the use of violence in the movement even before Tiller's death, describing violence as an aberration and saying that no one in their organizations was associated with acts of violence. In the 1990s, the Revered Patrick Mahoney addressed the issue of violence, saying, &quot;I think that extremists opposed to abortion got frustrated, felt they were losing the battle and felt it was incumbent upon themselves to resort to violence.&quot; In the same era, the [[Flip Benham]], director of [[Operation Save America]], also addressed the issue, saying &quot;This whole thing isn't about violence. It's all about silence&amp;nbsp;– silencing the Christian message. That's what they want.&quot; He also stated, &quot;They screech and scream about us crying fire in a crowded theater. And I agree it is wrong, unless there is a fire. If there's a fire in that theater, we better call it that. Our inflammatory rhetoric is only revealing a far more inflammatory truth.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/national/longterm/abortviolence/stories/salvi3.htm |title=Clinic Killings Follow Years of Antiabortion Violence |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date=1995-01-17 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Against pro-life people====
On September 11, 2009, pro-life activist [[Murder of Jim Pouillon|James Pouillon was shot and killed]] as he was displaying pictures of aborted fetuses in front of a school in [[Owosso, Michigan|Owosso]], [[Michigan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/CRIME/09/11/michigan.shooting/ |title= Police: Shooting suspect offended by anti-abortion material |accessdate=2010-05-13 |author=Eden Pontz |coauthors=Laura Dolan, Jean Shin |date=2009-09-11 |work= CNN |publisher=CNN.com |page=1 }}&lt;br /&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2009/09/11/anti-abortion-activist-targeted-killing/ |title=Anti-Abortion Activist 'Targeted' in Killing |accessdate=2010-05-13 |author= |date=2009-09-11 |agency= Associated Press |publisher=FOXNews.com |page=1 }}&lt;br /&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mlive.com/news/flint/index.ssf/2009/09/owosso_antiabortion_activists.html |title=Owosso anti-abortion activist's identity released as victim of homicide in front of Owosso, Michigan high school |accessdate=2010-05-13 |author=Liz Shaw |date=2009-09-11 |work= Flint Journal |publisher=MLive.com |page=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Harlan James Drake was charged with two murders: Pouillon's murder and the murder of a gravel pit contractor against whom Drake bore a grudge. Drake reportedly &quot;didn't like Pouillon's graphic antiabortion signs&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| title=3rd target flees after anti-abortion activist killed| url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/32809907/ns/us_news-crime_and_courts/| work=Crime &amp; courts on msnbc.com| publisher=msnbc.com| date=2009-09-13| accessdate=2011-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two days after the murder, president [[Barack Obama]] issued a statement saying that &quot;[w]hichever side of a public debate you're on, violence is never the right answer&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Obama: Killing of anti-abortion activist 'deplorable'|publisher=The Associated Press|date=[[Sep 13]] [[2009]] |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2009/sep/13/obama-killing-anti-abortion-activist-deplorable/|accessdate=July 15, 2009|postscript=.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wiktionary}}
{{Commons category|Pro-life movement}}
*[http://www.nrlc.org/ National Right to Life Committee]
*[http://www.aul.org/ Americans United for Life]
*[http://www.all.org/ American Life League]
*[http://physiciansforlife.org/ Physicians for Life]
*[http://www.frc.org/ Family Research Council]
*[http://www.hli.org/ Human Life Interational]
*[http://www.lifecanada.org/ Life Canada]
*[http://www.spuc.org.uk/ UK Society for the Protection of Unborn Children]
*[http://www.uklifeleague.com/ UK Life League]
*[http://www.prolifecampaign.ie/ Pro-life Campaign of Ireland]
*[http://www.priestsforlife.org/plgroups/prolifegroups.html List of international pro-life organizations]

{{Abortion}}
{{American Social Conservatism}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pro-Life Movement}}
[[Category:Pro-life movement| ]]
[[Category:Abortion]]

[[cs:Hnutí pro-life]]
[[de:Lebensrechtsbewegung]]
[[es:Pro vida]]
[[fo:Pro Vita]]
[[fr:Mouvement pro-vie]]
[[hr:Pro-life pokret]]
[[it:Movimento pro-life]]
[[la:Pro-vita]]
[[nl:Pro-life]]
[[ja:プロライフ]]
[[pl:Pro-life]]
[[pt:Pró-vida]]
[[ru:Движение «В защиту жизни»]]
[[sah:Prolife]]
[[simple:Pro-life]]
[[sk:Pro-life hnutie]]
[[sh:Pro-life pokret]]
[[fi:Pro-life-liike]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
