<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25740899" ns="0" title="Timeline of the presidency of John F. Kennedy"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--
Please remove the comments surrounding empty sections once you have populated them with data.
--&gt;
{{Infobox officeholder
|name = Presidency of John F. Kennedy
|image = John F Kennedy Official Portrait.jpg
|order = [[List of Presidents of the United States|35th]]
|office = President of the United States
|term_start = January 20, 1961
|term_end = November 22, 1963
|birth_date = {{birth date|1917|5|29|mf=y}}
|birth_place = [[Brookline, Massachusetts]]
|birthname = John Fitzgerald Kennedy
|death_date = {{death date and age|mf=yes|1963|11|22|1917|5|29}}
|death_place = [[Dallas]], [[Texas]]
|vicepresident = [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]
|predecessor = [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]
|successor = [[Lyndon B. Johnson]]
|nationality = American
|party = [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]]
|religion = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]]
|spouse = [[Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis|Jacqueline Lee Bouvier Kennedy]]
|children = [[Arabella Kennedy]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Caroline Bouvier Kennedy]]&lt;br/&gt;[[John Fitzgerald Kennedy, Jr.]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Patrick Bouvier Kennedy]]
|alma_mater = [[Harvard University]]
|signature = John F Kennedy Signature 2.svg
|occupation = Naval officer, politician
}}
[[File:John F Kennedy Official Portrait.jpg|thumb|right|[[President of the United States|President]] [[John F. Kennedy]]]]

The following is a '''timeline of the [[Presidency of John F. Kennedy|Presidency]] of [[John Fitzgerald Kennedy]]''', also known as the '''Kennedy Administration''', which took place from [[Inauguration of John F. Kennedy|his inauguration]] on January 20, 1961, to [[John F. Kennedy assassination|his assassination]] on November 22, 1963 - a span of 1,036 days. The timeline also includes major events preceding and succeeding his presidency.

The timeline begins on January 2, 1960, just over a year before Kennedy's inauguration on January 20, 1961, when then-Senator John F. Kennedy first announced his intention to run for the Democratic nomination for [[President of the United States]], and concludes on November 25, 1963, just three days after his assassination in Dallas, Texas abruptly ended his Presidency, when the slain President Kennedy's funeral was held, attended by representatives from over 90 countries.

After Kennedy's assassination, in accordance with [[United States presidential line of succession#Constitutional foundation|Constitutional procedure in the case of the death of the President]], his Vice President, [[Lyndon B. Johnson]], succeeded to the Office of the Presidency and took the [[oath of office of the President of the United States]] aboard [[Air Force One]] less than an hour after Kennedy died. Johnson served out the remainder of Kennedy's term, and was elected to the Presidency in his own right in a landslide in the [[United States presidential election, 1964|1964 presidential election]], setting an electoral victory result which has not been exceeded by a Democratic presidential nominee since.

Kennedy was the first Catholic President, the youngest elected President ([[Theodore Roosevelt]], who succeeded to the Presidency after [[William McKinley assassination|William McKinley's assassination]], was younger), and the fourth President to be assassinated.

==Pre-presidency==
===1960===
====January====
{{wikisource|Statement of Senator John F. Kennedy Announcing His Candidacy for the Presidency of the United States}}
[[File:John F. Kennedy Remarks Announcing Presidential Candidacy Draft 2.jpg|thumb|right|Kennedy's second draft of his written remarks announcing his presidential candidacy, January 2, 1960.]]

* '''January 2''' - Senator Kennedy officially announces his intention to run for the [[President of the United States|Presidency of the United States]].
&lt;!--
====February====
====March====
====April====
====May====
====June====
--&gt;

====July====
{{wikisource|John F. Kennedy's Presidential Nomination Acceptance Speech}}
* '''July 15''' - Senator Kennedy is officially nominated as the Democratic presidential candidate on the last day of the [[1960 Democratic National Convention]] in Los Angeles, California.
&lt;!--
====August====
--&gt;

====September====
[[File:Kennedy Nixon Debat (1960).jpg|thumb|left|'''September 26:''' Senator Kennedy and Vice President Nixon participate in the first television [[United States presidential election debates|presidential debate]].]]
{{wikisource|1960 U.S. Presidential Debate - September 26}}
{{wikisource|Address of Senator John F. Kennedy to the Greater Houston Ministerial Association}}

* '''September 12''' - Senator Kennedy delivers a campaign speech in which he strongly reaffirms his support for [[separation of church and state]], which successfully cooled tensions surrounding his Catholicism. When inaugurated, he became the first Catholic President in American history.
* '''September 26''' - Senator Kennedy and Vice President Nixon participate in the first televised presidential debate.

====October====
{{wikisource|1960 U.S. Presidential Debate - October 7}}
{{wikisource|1960 U.S. Presidential Debate - October 13}}
{{wikisource|1960 U.S. Presidential Debate - October 21}}

* '''October 7''' - Kennedy and Nixon participate in the second presidential debate, held in [[Washington, D.C.]]; NBC journalist [[Frank McGee (journalism)|Frank McGee]] moderates.
* '''October 13''' - Senator Kennedy and Vice President Nixon debate each other for the third time; former [[Face the Nation]] anchor [[Bill Shadel]] moderates. Kennedy participates from a New York studio, while Nixon participates from a Los Angeles studio.
* '''October 21''' - Kennedy and Nixon participate in the fourth and final presidential debate in New York; [[ABC News (America)|ABC News]] journalist [[Quincy Howe]] moderates.

====November====
* '''November 8''' - The [[United States presidential election, 1960|1960 presidential election]] is held, the first to have both candidates born in the 20th century, and the first in which the two most recently admitted states, Alaska (January 3, 1959) and Hawaii (August 21, 1959), participated.
* '''November 9''' - Current Vice President and [[Republican Party (United States)|Republican]] presidential candidate [[Richard Nixon]] concedes the presidency to Kennedy. Kennedy's official popular vote margin is 0.1% (112,827 votes) and his electoral margin is 84 electoral votes. Nixon won more states, 26 to 22. The electoral result proves to be the closest since the [[United States presidential election, 1916|1916 presidential election]]. The election of Kennedy and Johnson as President and Vice President was the last time until the [[United States presidential election, 2008|2008 election]] of [[Barack Obama]] and [[Joe Biden]] that two sitting senators were elected on the same ticket.

====December====
[[File:Eisenhower and Kennedy.jpg|thumb|left|'''December 6:''' President-elect Kennedy meets with President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]].&lt;ref name=&quot;eisenhower_meeting&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eisenhowermemorial.org/presidential-papers/second-term/chronology/1960-12.htm|title=December 1960 Chronology - Eisenhower Presidential Papers - Eisenhower Memorial Commission|date=February 1, 2006|accessdate=January 9, 2010|publisher=''[[Dwight D. Eisenhower Memorial]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;
]]
* '''December 6''': President-elect Kennedy meets with President Eisenhower.&lt;ref name=&quot;eisenhower_meeting&quot;/&gt;
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both;&quot; /&gt;

==1961==
===January===
[[File:Jfk inauguration.jpg|thumb|right|'''January 20:''' John F. Kennedy is inaugurated as the [[List of Presidents of the United States|35th President of the United States]].]]
[[File:John F. Kennedy Inaugural Ball, 20 January 1961.jpg|thumb|left|'''January 20:''' President and Mrs. Kennedy attend an inaugural ball.]]
[[File:First JFK Presidential Press Conference January 25, 1961.jpg|thumb|right|'''January 25:''' President Kennedy holds the first regular live televised press conference in the State Department Auditorium.]]
{{wikisource|John F. Kennedy's Inaugural Address}}
{{wikisource|John F. Kennedy's first presidential press conference}}

* '''January 20''' - Kennedy's presidency begins with his inauguration at the [[United States Capitol]] in Washington, D.C. Kennedy is [[Inauguration of John F. Kennedy|sworn in]] by Chief Justice [[Earl Warren]] and delivers a [[Inaugural address of John F. Kennedy|widely praised]] inaugural address, asking Americans to &quot;ask not what your country can do for you, but what you can do for country&quot; and for the people of the world to &quot;ask not what America will do for you, but what together we can do for the freedom of man&quot;. He is congratulated by Soviet Premier [[Nikita Khrushchev]]. Kennedy also formally nominates his [[United States Cabinet|cabinet]] and attends the inaugural balls.
* '''January 21''' - Kennedy meets with former President [[Harry S. Truman]] and issues [[wikisource:Author:John F. Kennedy/Executive orders#1961|Executive Order 10914]] directing a doubling of the quantity of surplus food distributed to needy families. Kennedy also attends a meeting at the [[Democratic National Committee]] and hosts the swearing-in of his cabinet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/White+House+Diary/1961/January/21.htm?d=21&amp;m=1&amp;y=1961|title=January 21, 1961|date=October 30, 2005|accessdate=January 9, 2010|author=Whealan, Ronald E.|publisher=''[[John F. Kennedy Library]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''January 22''' - Kennedy meets with the poet [[Robert Frost]]. President Kennedy, Ted Kennedy, and [[Paul B. Fay]] attend [[Mass (liturgy)|mass]] at the [[Holy Trinity Catholic Church (Washington, D.C.)|Holy Trinity Catholic Church]] in Washington, D.C. Kennedy establishes the three-member ''Government Ethics Committee''. Kennedy appoints Hickman Price, Jr. and Roland Burnstan as Assistant [[United States Secretary of Commerce|Commerce Secretaries]].
* '''January 23''' - Kennedy meets with several defense, foreign policy, and intelligence advisers, including [[United States Secretary of Defense|Defense Secretary]] [[Robert McNamara]], [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[Dean Rusk]], [[National Security Advisor (United States)|National Security Advisor]] [[McGeorge Bundy]], [[Director of the Central Intelligence Agency|CIA Director]] [[Allen Dulles]], and [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff|Chairman of the Joint Chiefs]] [[Lyman Lemnitzer]]. Kennedy nominates [[Frank Burton Ellis]] for a federal judgeship on the [[United States District Court for the Eastern District of Louisiana]].
* '''January 24''' - Kennedy meets with then-former Congressman (later Senator) [[George McGovern]] of South Dakota. He also meets with Democratic legislative leaders, and receives a tour of the shelter areas of the [[White House]] from Naval Aide, Cmdr. Tazewell Shepard. He is presented plans for what would become the [[Food for Peace]] program and designates McGovern Director.
* '''January 25''' - Kennedy holds his first regular live televised press conference in the State Department Auditorium. He announces [[RB-47#Strategic operations|the release]] of two surviving [[United States Air Force|USAF]] crewman by the Soviet Union after being captured when their [[RB-47 Stratojet]] was shot down on July 1, 1960.
* '''January 30''' - Kennedy delivers his first [[State of the Union address]].

===February===
* '''February 1''' - President Kennedy holds his second presidential news conference; he announces the establishment of five pilot food stamp distribution projects. He later meets with economic and budget advisers. President Kennedy holds the first meeting of the [[United States National Security Council|National Security Council]] and sends a letter to Defense Secretary McNamara marking the scheduled launch of the [[USS Sam Houston (SSBN-609)]] the next day.
* '''February 2''' - President Kennedy meets with [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe#Supreme Allied Commander Europe (SACEUR)|NATO Supreme Allied Commander]] [[Lauris Norstad]], Joint Chiefs Chairman [[Lyman Lemnitzer]], and later with his cabinet. Kennedy appoints [[Burke Marshall]] as [[United States Assistant Attorney General|Assistant Attorney General]] for [[United States Department of Justice Civil Rights Division|Civil Rights]], [[David K. E. Bruce]] as [[United States Ambassador to the United Kingdom|Ambassador to the United Kingdom]]. Kennedy telegrams the mayors of 297 cities urging an increase in [[urban renewal]] activities.
* '''February 3''' - President Kennedy meets with [[United States Ambassador to Laos|Ambassador to Laos]] Winthrop G. Brown. Kennedy and [[Paul B. Fay]] attend the movie ''[[Spartacus (1960 film)|Spartacus]]'' at the Warner Theater. After meeting with [[United States Department of Health and Human Services|Health, Education, and Welfare Secretary]] [[Abraham A. Ribicoff]], Kennedy orders money and surplus food totalling $4 million for Cuban refugees in fiscal year 1961.

===March===
[[File:US-PeaceCorps-Logo.svg|thumb|left|'''March 1:''' Kennedy establishes the [[Peace Corps]].]]

* '''March 1''' - Emphasizing the theme of public service in his inaugural address, President Kennedy issues [[Executive order (United States)|Executive Order]] 10924, establishing the [[Peace Corps]] on a &quot;temporary pilot basis&quot;. Kennedy also sends to Congress a message requesting authorization of the Peace Corps as a permanent organization. President Kennedy holds his fifth presidential news conference. President Kennedy and [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] make a tape recording promoting the Youth Peace Corps. President Kennedy records a message for the [[American Red Cross]]. President Kennedy signs into law a joint resolution (H.J. Res. 155) to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the [[first inauguration of Abraham Lincoln]] on March 4, 1861 (PL87-1).
* '''March 4''' - President Kennedy meets with [[Council of Economic Advisers]] Chairman [[Walter Heller]] and later appoints [[Sargent Shriver]] to head the Peace Corps. He also dines at the home of his brother, Attorney General [[Robert F. Kennedy]] and meets with [[United States Ambassador to the United Kingdom|Ambassador to the United Kingdom]] [[David K. E. Bruce]].

===April===
* '''April 1''' - Kennedy meets with [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]] [[Dean Rusk]]. Kennedy also declares parts of eastern [[Iowa]] flooded by the [[Cedar River (Iowa River)|Cedar River]] to be a major disaster area.
* '''April 2''' - Kennedy meets with journalists [[Albert Merriman Smith]] and Marvin Arrowsmith. The First Family view the film ''[[All in a Night's Work (film)|All in a Night's Work]].
* '''April 12''' - The [[Soviet Union]]'s launch of [[Yuri Gagarin]] into low Earth orbit aboard ''[[Vostok 1]]'' marks the first time a human being is launched into outer space. Kennedy messages Soviet Premier [[Nikita Khrushchev]], congratulating him on the successful launch of ''Vostok 1''.
* '''April 17''' - Continuing a concept originating in the administration of his predecessor, [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], Kennedy orders the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion|invasion of Cuba]] in an unsuccessful attempt to overthrow the communist regime.
* '''April 19''' - The invasion of Cuba fails and results in a Cuban revolutionary victory. Kennedy's administration is severely embarrassed, so much so that Kennedy stated he wanted to &quot;splinter the CIA into a thousand pieces and scatter it into the wind&quot;.

===May===
[[File:Kennedy Giving Historic Speech to Congress - GPN-2000-001658.jpg|thumb|left|'''May 25:''' Kennedy sets out the goal to &quot;land a man on the Moon and return him safely to the Earth&quot;.]]
[[File:Kennedy, Johnson, and others watching flight of Astronaut Shepard on television, 05 May 1961.jpg|thumb|right|'''May 5:''' President Kennedy, [[Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis|Jackie Kennedy]], and Vice President Johnson watch the launch of ''Freedom 7'' from the [[White House Situation Room]].]]
[[File:Mercury-Redstone 3 Launch MSFC-6100884.jpg|thumb|left|'''May 5''': [[Alan Shepard]] becomes the first American in space, when he is launched aboard a [[Mercury-Redstone Launch Vehicle]] on ''Freedom 7''.]]
[[File:Kennedy and Shepard in Washington D.C. - GPN-2000-001659.jpg|thumb|right|'''May 6:''' President Kennedy meets with Alan Shepard at the White House.]]
{{wikisource|Special Message to the Congress on Urgent National Needs}}

* '''May 2''' - The ''[[Mercury-Redstone 3|Freedom 7]]'' spacecraft is readied for a launch attempt which would have resulted in the first American [[human spaceflight]]; it is canceled due to poor weather and rescheduled for May 5.
* '''May 5''' - [[Alan Shepard]] is launched on ''Freedom 7'' on a [[sub-orbital spaceflight]] aboard a [[Mercury-Redstone Launch Vehicle|Mercury-Redstone rocket]], and becomes the first American in outer space. The flight lasts 15 minutes 22 seconds, and reaches an [[apsis|apogee]] of {{convert|187.42|km|mi}}, and a maximum speed of {{convert|8277|km/h|mph}} (Mach 6.94).
* '''May 6''' - Kennedy meets with Alan Shepard at the White House, to congratulate him on becoming the first American in space. He awards him the [[NASA Distinguished Service Medal]] in a ceremony on the White House lawn. The six other [[Mercury Seven]] astronauts attends the ceremony, the next of which, [[Gus Grissom]], would launch into space less than three months later.
* '''May 25''' - In an address to a [[Joint session of the United States Congress]], Kennedy announces full presidential support for the goal to &quot;commit...before this decade is out, to landing a man on the Moon and returning him safely to the Earth&quot; and urges Congress to appropriate the necessary funds, eventually consuming the largest financial expenditure of any nation in peacetime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/centers/langley/news/factsheets/Apollo.html|title=NASA Langley Research Center's Contributions to the Apollo Program|date=November 21, 2004|accessdate=January 10, 2010|quote=Answering President Kennedy's challenge and landing men on the moon by 1969 required the most sudden burst of technological creativity, and the largest commitment of resources ($24 billion), ever made by any nation in peacetime. At its peak,  the Apollo program employed 400,000 Americans and required the support of over 20,000 industrial firms and universities.|publisher=[[Langley Research Center]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though Kennedy had initially been convinced that [[NASA]] should attempt a [[manned mission to Mars]], NASA Associate Administrator [[Robert Seamans]] spent three days and nights working, ultimately successfully, to convince him otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://techtv.mit.edu/videos/3083|title=Robert C. Seamans Jr.|date=June 10, 2009|accessdate=January 10, 2010|publisher=[[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]|quote=President Kennedy had been convinced that America needed to send a man to Mars and back before the decade was out. Bob [Seamans] told me the story of working three days and nights trying to put together, clearly and succinctly, the case for the President that we cannot hit that goal, we need to go to the Moon.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
===June===
===July===
===August===
===October===
===November===
===December===
--&gt;&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both;&quot; /&gt;
===September===
* '''September 25''' - Address before the United Nations General Assembly (JFK's first of two) announcing the US intention to &quot;challenge the Soviet Union, not to an arms race, but to a peace race&quot;.

==1962==
===January===
* '''January 11''' - Kennedy delivers his second [[State of the Union address]].

===February===
[[File:Launch of Friendship 7 - GPN-2000-000686.jpg|thumb|right|'''February 20:''' [[John Glenn]], later a Democratic United States Senator from Ohio, is launched into space on ''[[Mercury-Atlas 6|Friendship 7]]'' and becomes the first American to orbit the Earth.]]

* '''February 12''' - As [[Commander-in-chief]], Kennedy commutes the military death sentence of seaman Jimmie Henderson to life imprisonment, marking the last time in the 20th century that an American president was faced with such a decision (the most recent such decision came on July 28, 2008, when President [[George W. Bush]] decided to deny clemency to Private [[Ronald A. Gray]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abclocal.go.com/wtvd/story?section=news/local&amp;id=6293376|title=Bush: Former Army cook's crimes warrant execution|work=[[ABC News]]|author=Riechmann, Deb|agency=Associated Press|date=2008-07-29|accessdate=2008-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''February 20''' - [[John Glenn]] is launched on ''[[Mercury-Atlas 6|Friendship 7]]'' on an [[orbital spaceflight]] aboard a [[Atlas LV-3B|Mercury-Atlas rocket]], and becomes the first American to orbit the Earth.

===March===
* '''March 22''' - Kennedy signs into law HR5143 (PL87-423), abolishing the mandatory [[Capital punishment in the United States|death penalty]] for [[Murder#Degrees of murder in the United States|first degree murder]] in the [[Washington, D.C.|District of Columbia]], the only remaining jurisdiction in the United States with a mandatory death sentence for first degree murder, replacing it with life imprisonment with parole if the jury could not decide between life imprisonment and the death penalty, or if the jury chose life imprisonment by a unanimous vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/White+House+Diary/1962/March/22.htm|title=March 22, 1962 - The White House Diary|author=Whealan, Ronald E.|date=2005-12-05|accessdate=2009-08-28|publisher=[[John F. Kennedy Library]]}}{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/Historical+Resources/Archives/Reference+Desk/jfk_leg_record2.html.htm|title=Kennedy Legislative Record, Page 2 - Summary of the Three Year Kennedy Record (Legislation)|date=2006-01-19|accessdate=2009-08-28|publisher=[[John F. Kennedy Presidential Library]]|author=Whealan, Ronald E.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The death penalty in the District of Columbia has not been applied since 1957, and has now been abolished.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.norton.house.gov/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=478|title=Norton Letter to U.S. Attorney Says Death Penalty Trial That Begins Today Part of Troubling and Futile Pattern|date=2007-01-08|accessdate=2009-08-28|publisher=Office of Congresswoman [[Eleanor Holmes Norton]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
===April===--&gt;

===May===
* '''May 19''' - [[Marilyn Monroe]] sings ''[[Happy Birthday, Mr. President]]'' to President Kennedy in [[Madison Square Garden]] as part of the President's 45th birthday celebrations (the birthday itself was on May 29).
&lt;!--
===June===
===July===
===August===--&gt;

===September===
[[File:JFK at Rice University.jpg|thumb|right|'''September 12:''' President Kennedy visits Rice University to deliver a speech on the nation's space program.]]
[[File:Jfk rice university we choose to go to the moon.ogg|thumb|right|'''September 12:''' President Kennedy declares &quot;we choose to go to the Moon in this decade&quot; during a speech on the nation's space program at [[Rice University]].]]
{{wikisource|We choose to go to the Moon}}

* '''September 12''' - Kennedy delivers a speech at [[Rice University]] on the subject of the nation's [[Apollo program|plans to land humans on the Moon]]. Kennedy announces his continued support for increased space expenditures, saying &quot;we choose to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things, not because they are easy, but because they are hard.&quot;
&lt;!--
===October===--&gt;

===November===
{{see also2|[[United States House of Representatives elections, 1962]]|[[United States Senate elections, 1962]]}}

* '''November 6''' - The [[United States elections, 1962|1962 elections]] are held. The Democrats lose seats in the [[United States House of Representatives|House]] to Republicans, but maintain their majority; they increase their majority in the [[United States Senate|Senate]]. Kennedy's brother [[Ted Kennedy|Ted]] wins a [[United States Senate special election in Massachusetts, 1962|special election in Massachusetts]] to represent the state as junior senator, in the seat his brother formerly held and was at the time occupied by [[Benjamin A. Smith II]] who had been appointed to the seat upon President-elect Kennedy's victory.

===December===
[[File:1962 Entrance Hall (Official White House) Christmas tree - Jack and Jacqueline Kennedy.jpg|thumb|left|'''December 12:''' President and Mrs. Kennedy standing next to the [[White House Christmas tree]], located in 1962 in the [[Entrance Hall]].]]

* '''December 25''' - President and Mrs. Kennedy attend [[Mass (liturgy)|mass]] at St. Ann's Church in [[Palm Beach, Florida]]. The Kennedys later hold a party for members of the [[United States Secret Service|Secret Service]] and their families.
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both;&quot; /&gt;

==1963==
===January===
[[File:JFK delivers State of the Union Address, 14 January 1963.jpg|thumb|left|'''January 14:''' President Kennedy delivers his third and final State of the Union address.]]
{{wikisource|John F. Kennedy's Third State of the Union Address}}

* '''January 10''' - Kennedy meets with President-elect [[Juan Bosch]] of the [[Dominican Republic]].
* '''January 11''' - Kennedy meets with [[United States Secretary of Labor|Labor Secretary]] [[W. Willard Wirtz]] and [[AFL-CIO]] President [[George Meany]].
* '''January 12''' - Kennedy announces the appointment of [[David L. Lawrence]] as Chairman of the President's Committee on Equal Opportunity in Housing. Kennedy also appoints Phil N. Bornstein as [[Assistant Secretary of Housing and Urban Development for Housing|Federal Housing Commissioner]].
* '''January 14''' - Kennedy delivers the annual [[State of the Union address]] to a [[Joint session of the United States Congress]].

===February===
* '''February 10''' - The President and the First Lady attend the play [[Beyond the Fringe]] in [[New York City]].
* '''February 20''' - In a letter to [[Attorney General of the United States|Attorney General]] [[Robert F. Kennedy]], President Kennedy denies clemency to Victor Feguer, a convicted murderer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thesmokinggun.com/archive/feguer3.html|title=Victor Harry Feguer -- Petition for Commutation of Death Sentence|date=February 20, 1963|accessdate=January 9, 2010|archivedate=January 9, 2010|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5mem3uXTUj5|quote=I have reviewed your letter of January 21 regarding the application for clemency in behalf of Mr. Feguer. Taking all factors into account, it is my decision that the petition should be and is hereby denied.|author=J. F. Kennedy|publisher=''[[The Smoking Gun]]''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===March===
* '''March 15''' - [[Victor Feguer]] is executed after Kennedy's February 20 denial of clemency. The execution marks the last [[Capital punishment by the United States federal government|federal execution]] until the execution of [[Timothy McVeigh]] on June 11, 2001.
&lt;!--
===April===
===May===--&gt;

===June===
[[File:JFK speech lch bin ein berliner 1.jpg|thumb|right|'''June 26:''' President Kennedy delivers his now-famous ''[[Ich bin ein Berliner]]'' speech.]]
[[File:Wallace at University of Alabama edit2.jpg|thumb|left|'''June 11:''' [[United States Deputy Attorney General|Deputy Attorney General]] [[Nicholas Katzenbach]] confronts Alabama Governor [[George Wallace]] after Wallace refuses to allow the Court-ordered admittance of African–American students to the [[University of Alabama]]. After the confrontation, the students are admitted peacefully.]]
[[File:President Kennedy American University Commencement Address June 10, 1963.jpg|thumb|right|'''June 10''': President Kennedy delivers the commencement address at [[American University]].]]
{{wikisource|Civil Rights Message}}
{{wikisource|Ich bin ein Berliner}}

* '''June 10''' - Kennedy delivers the [[American University speech|commencement address at American University]] in Washington, D.C.
* '''June 11''' - Kennedy delivers a televised address on [[African-American Civil Rights Movement (1955–1968)#Birmingham Campaign, 1963–1964|Civil Rights]] on his orders regarding the [[Stand in the Schoolhouse Door]].
* '''June 26''' - Kennedy visits [[West Berlin]] and delivers his now-famous ''[[Ich bin ein Berliner]]'' speech advocating [[representative democracy]] and [[capitalism]] as a replacement for [[communism|communist]] regimes around the world.

===July===
{{Empty section|date=January 2011}}

===August===
[[File:Martin Luther King - March on Washington.jpg|thumb|right|'''August 28:''' [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|Martin Luther King]] delivers his ''[[I Have A Dream]]'' speech at the [[Lincoln Memorial]] in [[Washington, D.C.]]]]

* '''August 28''' - The [[March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom]] occurs in [[Washington, D.C.]], culminating in the now-famous ''[[I Have A Dream]]'' speech by [[Martin Luther King, Jr.|Martin Luther King]]. Estimates of the number of marchers range from 200,000 to 300,000.

===September===
* '''September 20''' - Address before the United Nations General Assembly (JFK's second) stating various specific recommendations to &quot;move the world to a just and lasting peace&quot;.

===October===
* '''October 3''' - President Kennedy visits [[Cleburne County, Arkansas]] to dedicate the [[Greers Ferry Dam]]. This is the last public appearance before he was shot in Dallas.

[[File:President Kennedy signs Nuclear Test Ban Treaty, 07 October 1963.jpg|thumb|left|'''October 7:''' President Kennedy signs the [[Partial Test Ban Treaty]], a major milestone in early [[nuclear disarmament]], despite occurring in the [[Nuclear Age]].]]


* '''October 7''' - President Kennedy signs the [[Partial Test Ban Treaty]], prohibiting all [[nuclear weapons testing]] providing an exception for [[underground nuclear testing]] only.
* '''October 8''' - President Kennedy announces an agreement with the [[Soviet Union]] to open negotiations for the sale of American wheat.

===November===
* '''November 21''' - On the final full day of the Kennedy administration, the President asks his economic advisers to prepare the [[War on Poverty]] for 1964. Less than two months after the President's assassination, President Johnson introduces the legislation in his first State of the Union address on January 8, 1964, and two of the major pieces of related legislation – the [[Economic Opportunity Act of 1964]] and the [[Social Security Act of 1965]] – are signed into law on August 20, 1964 and July 30, 1965, respectively.
* '''November 22''' - Kennedy's administration abruptly ends after [[John F. Kennedy assassination|he is assassinated]] in Dallas, Texas. [[Lee Harvey Oswald]] is arrested and charged with the murder. Oswald is shot and killed two days later by nightclub owner [[Jack Ruby]].

==Post-presidency==
===1963===
====November====
[[File:JFKeastRoomnov23'63.jpg|thumb|right|'''November 23:''' Kennedy lies in repose in the [[East Room (White House)|East Room]] of the White House.]]
[[File:Lyndon B. Johnson taking the oath of office, November 1963.jpg|thumb|left|'''November 22:''' Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson is sworn in aboard Air Force One as the nation's 36th President hours after the Kennedy assassination.]]
{{see also|State funeral of John F. Kennedy}}

* '''November 22''' - Vice President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] [[United States presidential line of succession|succeeds to the Presidency]] and is sworn in aboard [[Air Force One]].
* '''November 23''' - Kennedy lies in repose in the White House East Room for a period of 24 hours. At 4:45 pm, President Johnson issues [[wikisource:Proclamation 3561|Proclamation 3561]], declaring November 25, the day of the funeral service, to be a [[National day of mourning#State officials|national day of mourning]].
* '''November 24''' - Kennedy [[Lying in state#United States|lies in state]] for a period of 18 hours. NBC broadcasts live uninterrupted coverage of people passing through the [[United States Capitol rotunda|Capitol rotunda]] during the overnight hours.
* '''November 25''' - Kennedy's funeral service is held. Representatives from over 90 countries attend the ceremony. The President is laid to rest at [[Arlington National Cemetery]]. Upon the request of the now-former First Lady [[Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis|Jacqueline Kennedy]] on the day before, an [[eternal flame]], inspired by the [[Arc de Triomphe#The Unknown Soldier|Tomb of the Unknown Soldier]] at the Arc de Triomphe in Paris, known later as the [[John F. Kennedy Eternal Flame]], is set up by the [[United States Army Corps of Engineers]], and first lit by Mrs. Kennedy.
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: left;&quot; /&gt;
{{clear}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.jfklibrary.org/jfkl/modules/diary/default.aspx?null White House Diary] at the website of the [[John F. Kennedy Library]]

{{John F. Kennedy}}
{{Kennedy cabinet}}
{{US Presidents}}
{{Include-USGov|agency=[[National Archives and Records Administration]]
|url=http://www.jfklibrary.org/White+House+Diary/
|article=The White House Diary
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Timeline Of The Presidency Of John F. Kennedy}}
[[Category:Wikipedia articles incorporating text from the National Archives and Records Administration]]
[[Category:Presidency of John F. Kennedy]]
[[Category:1961 in the United States]]
[[Category:1962 in the United States]]
[[Category:1963 in the United States]]
[[Category:Timelines of United States history by period]]
[[Category:Presidencies of the United States|Kennedy]]
[[Category:Massachusetts Democrats]]
[[Category:1961 establishments]]
[[Category:1963 disestablishments]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
