<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25857054" ns="0" title="Humanitarian response by non-governmental organizations to the 2010 Haiti earthquake"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{TOC right}}
[[File:Zilda Arns2.jpg|thumb|upright|Brazilian pediatrician and Nobel Peace Prize nominee [[Zilda Arns]] was killed in the earthquake.]]

The '''humanitarian response by non-governmental organizations to the [[2010 Haiti earthquake]]''' included many [[non-governmental organization]]s, such as international, religious and regionally based NGOs, that immediately pledged support in the aftermath of the [[2010 Haiti earthquake]]. Besides a large multi-contingency contribution by national governments, NGOs contributed a significant deal to both on-the-ground rescue efforts and external solicitation of aid for those rescue efforts.

==International==

* [[Oxfam International]] - International relief and development agency Oxfam International swung into action to raise emergency funds to assist relief and rehabilitation efforts on the ground. Oxfam is committed to assisting in the rebuilding efforts in Haiti, and the agency will be on the ground for the long haul. This along with the immediate response of providing clean water, shelter, and sanitation means that the level of need continues to be great.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.oxfam.org/en/emergencies/haiti-earthquake |title=Major earthquake in Haiti|accessdate=2010-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[International Committee of the Red Cross]] - sent tonnes of supplies, hundreds of personnel, and field hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://newsroom.redcross.org/category/haiti-earthquake-Jan-2010/ |title=ICRC aid to Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of emergency teams sent to Haiti equals the total sent to all 14 countries affect by the [[2004 Indian Ocean earthquake|2004 Indian Ocean tsunami]].

* [[Food For The Poor]] - Food For The Poor has been able to provide relief to Haiti through the acquisition and delivery of more than 7,100 tons of food, medical supplies, pharmaceuticals, building materials and other goods. The 359 containers have provided lifesaving goods to those suffering from the effects of the earthquake. The people of Haiti have been provided with more than 20 million meals from the rice, beans, canned goods and water shipped into Haiti.

* [[World Vision International]] - World Vision had relief items stored in Haiti in preparation for hurricane season and began distributing those immediately, but the medical supplies, blankets, tents and other supplies from the [[Pétionville]] office quickly ran low.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.wvi.org/wvi/wviweb.nsf/updates/F2D16C2A8138D7F9882576AC00211028?opendocument |title=Haiti: World Vision facing obstacles, 'running marathon' to provide relief}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first flight with 18 metric tonnes of World Vision relief supplies left the organization's Denver, Colorado, USA warehouse on 14 Jan, and arrived in Port-au-Prince the following night, providing emergency goods for more than 1,000 families, including tarps for temporary shelter; blankets, collapsible water containers, cooking sets and hygiene kits that contain a month’s supply of soap, toilet paper, toothbrushes and more for a family of five.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.wvi.org/wvi/wviweb.nsf/updates/271D5437B59D596D882576AD002D4009?opendocument |title=Haiti: Distributions continue, new aid arriving|accessdate=2010-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The organization's facility in Haiti was damaged, but none of the staff were injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url= http://edition.cnn.com/2010/WORLD/americas/01/12/haiti.earthquake/index.html |title=7.0 quake hits Haiti; 'Serious loss of life' expected | work=CNN | accessdate=2010-05-04 | date=2010-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the gravity of the situation World Vision subsequently coordinated additional relief flights from their warehouses in Dubai, Panama, Germany, Canada and Denver, carrying the following supplies: tarps, collapsible water containers, shovels, hygiene kits, kitchen sets, blankets, radio equipment, and mosquito nets. World Vision then signed an agreement with [[Air Serv International]] to provide one light aircraft to transport people and cargo (14,000&amp;nbsp;lbs capacity) between Santo Domingo and Port-au-Prince. The first flights began 19 Jan, making two rotations per day. According to relief staff, these flights will radically improve transports of staff and goods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.wvi.org/wvi/wviweb.nsf/updates/418DB0A42FFA0FDC882576B0006FF4DC?opendocument |title=Haiti: Additional details on World Vision's response}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Télécoms sans frontières]] sent teams to establish two calling centers each in the southwestern Port-au-Prince regions of [[Place Saint Pierre]] and Boyer.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tsfi.org/en/action/emergencies/112-seisme-en-haiti-tsf-deploie-ses-equipes ''Earthquake in Haïti: TSF deploys its teams'']&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[SOS Children]] delivered 21 tonnes of aid to Haiti by road as of 21 January. They also brought supplies to Haiti by cargo plane and have around 60 staff present there. In support of their work, they received a £1 million donation from [[HSBC]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ft_donations&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/00cdb160-0512-11df-aa2c-00144feabdc0.html?nclick_check=1|title=Banks pledge aid to help Haiti relief effort|last=Goff|first=Sharlene|coauthors=Murphy, Megan|date=19 January 2010|publisher=[[Financial Times]]|accessdate=22 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Swedish businessman [[Roger Hakelius]] donated US $14 million  to support and educate approximately 400 orphan children in Haiti over a 25-year period.&lt;ref name=&quot;SR_Hakelius&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sr.se/cgi-bin/international/artikel.asp?ProgramID=166&amp;Nyheter=1&amp;artikel=3383141|title=Fees for Top Charity Officials Criticised|date=19 January 2010|publisher=[[Radio Sweden]] International|accessdate=22 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Humanity First]] particularly from Canada, USA and UK set out teams of doctors to Haiti. 10,000 patients have been seen so far by the team of doctors. The Humanity First team has also shipped 5 tonnes of aid to Haiti. It has also deployed water infrastructure at a camp to provide daily water to 7,000 people and is in the process of installing 2 more filtration units elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.humanityfirst.org.uk/Haiti/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Africa==
==={{flag|South Africa}}===
*The South African relief organisation Gift Of The Givers (GOTG) departed for Haiti on 14 January. The head of South Africa's Gift of the Givers Foundation, Emtiaz Sooliman, says his group is sending up to three teams of search and rescue specialists to Haiti to help victims of the earthquake and hopefully save some lives. This whole project adds up to over R10 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Scott Bobb | Johannesburg 14 January 2010 |url=http://www1.voanews.com/english/news/africa/South-Africa-Sends-Search-Rescue-Teams-to-Haiti-81492202.html |title=South Africa Sends Search, Rescue Teams to Haiti &amp;#124; Africa &amp;#124; English |publisher=.voanews.com |date=2009-08-20 |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jacarandafm.com/kagiso/content/en/jacaranda/jacaranda-news?oid=531171&amp;sn=Detail&amp;pid=399938&amp;South-Africa-support-Haiti |title=South Africa support Haiti - News - Jacaranda 94.2 |publisher=Jacarandafm.com |date=2009-12-10 |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Rescue South Africa have sent 40 medical professionals&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mg.co.za/article/2010-01-15-sa-gives-aid-after-haiti-quake&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Zambia}}===
*Miracle Life Family Church, [[Lusaka]], raised [[Zambian kwacha|ZMK]]20 million ({{US$|4,400}}) for the humanitarian aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://allafrica.com/stories/201001220584.html |title= Zambia: Church Donates K20 Million to Haiti |publisher=AllAfrica.com|date=2010-01-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Lusaka top ten businessman Isse Gester who his origin is Somalia also sends 10 million aid to Haitian government for relief.

==Asia==
==={{flag|Bangladesh}}===
* [[BRAC (NGO)]] (Bangladesh Rural Advancement Committee), the Bangladesh based world's largest [[NGO]]'s USA wing is mobilizing resources to support the relief and rehabilitation efforts working with its two partners in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://s71165.gridserver.com/content/devasting-earthquake-haiti-requires-everyone-respond|title=Devasting Earthquake in Haiti Requires Everyone to Respond|publisher=BRAC USA|date=2010-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|China}}===
====[[Special Administrative Region of the People's Republic of China|Special Administrative Regions]]====
*{{flag icon|Hong Kong}} Local charitable and humanitarian organizations have raised over [[Hong Kong dollar|HK$]]21 million (US$2.7 million) for Haitian relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90776/90882/6874428.html ''Hong Kong raises over 21 mln HKD for Haiti''] from ''english.people.com.cn'' 21 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flag|Macau}}
**{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The Macau Red Cross has donated [[Macanese pataca|$M]]200,000 (US$25,000) while local aid organization Caritas has given another $M150,000 (US$19,000). Local businessman António Ferreira has donated an additional M$500,000 (US$62,000) to Macanese efforts in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jtm.com.mo/view.asp?dT=336603010 ''População de Macau solidária com o Haiti''] from ''www.jtm.com.mo'' 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Iran}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|crescent}} Iran's Red Crescent announced plans to send about 30 tonnes of aid including food, tents and medicine to Haiti on Jan. 14.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alertnet.org/thenews/newsdesk/LDE60D24J.htm |title=Reuters AlertNet - FACTBOX-Countries, aid agencies seeking to help Haiti |publisher=Alertnet.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Israel}}===
*[[IsraAid]], an Israeli humanitarian organization sent a 15-person search-and-rescue team, which includes emergency medical staff and arrived in Haiti on Friday, January 15. The IsraAid team set up treatment rooms to treat the injured at the collapsed main hospital in Port-au-Prince.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/1142348.html |title=Israel sends aid as Haiti braces for massive death toll in quake - Haaretz - Israel News |publisher=[[Haaretz]] |date=13 January 2010 |accessdate=2010-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/briefs/israaid-team-treats-injured-in-haiti IsraAID team treats injured in Haiti] (January 17, 2010) in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''] Retrieved 2010–01–18&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[ZAKA]], an organization of voluntary community emergency response teams, dispatched a six person team to assist with identification, extraction and rescue of victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/135528 |title=One Israeli Still Missing in Haiti Earthquake - Defense/Middle East - Israel News |publisher=Israel National News |date= |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Solomont, E.B., (14 January 2010) [http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1263147906183&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull Israelis race to save lives in devastated Haiti] ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/briefs/8-saved-during-qshabbat-from-hellq 8 saved during &quot;Shabbat from hell&quot;] (January 17, 2010) in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''] Retrieved 2010–01–18&lt;/ref&gt;
* A [[Magen David Adom]] delegation was dispatched on January 17 to establish field clinics in cooperation with local rescue groups and as part of a larger American Red Cross mission. Israeli volunteers will help search for the thousands thought to be buried under the rubble.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-3835205,00.html |title=Magen David Adom delegation to leave for Haiti Sunday |publisher=Ynetnews |date= |accessdate=2010-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rettig-Gur, Haviv (14 January 2010) [http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1263147885750&amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull &quot;Israel readies aid following Haiti quake&quot;] ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/briefs/israelis-rescue-top-haitian-official Israelis rescue top Haitian official] (January 17, 2010) in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''] Retrieved 2010–01–18&lt;/ref&gt;
*Israeli volunteers of the Natan Israeli Coalition for International Humanitarian Aid opened a makeshift school in early February to provide education and counseling for 800 pupils in Port-au-Prince, in conjunction with the local government and with aid from the neighboring [[Dominican Republic]].&lt;ref name=Israschools&gt;Heyman, Jeffrey [http://www.israel21c.org/201002117688/social-action/qthe-resilience-of-the-people-is-stronger-than-we-expectedq ''The resilience of the people is stronger than we expected''], (10 February 2010), in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''], Retrieved 2010-02-11&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[IsraAid]] opened a child education center in February in the [[Pétionville]] refugee camp, the largest refugee camp in Port-au-Prince area, together with other agencies, such as [[Operation Blessing International|Operation Blessing]]. The center was set up initially in the tents from the [[Israel Defense Forces|IDF]]’s field hospital.&lt;ref name= Israschools/&gt;
*The Natan organization has announced that another 12 delegations will be sent to Haiti in 2010 to assist with the multidisciplinary rehabilitation needed in Haiti.&lt;ref name= Israschools/&gt;
*In February, a team of medical experts from [[ALYN Hospital]] in Jerusalem, one of Israel's premier rehabilitation centers, and specializing in the [[Physical medicine and rehabilitation|rehabilitation]] of amputees, arrived in Haiti, under the auspices of IsraAid, along with professionals from the Israel Center for the Treatment of Psychotrauma and other volunteers. The team will assess needs for providing rehabilitation for the injured and training potential Haitian therapists in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israel21c.org/201002217715/briefs/alyn-hospital-joins-israaid-in-haiti ALYN Hospital joins IsraAID in Haiti], (21 February 2010), in [http://www.israel21c.org/ ''Israel 21c Innovation News Service''], Retrieved 2010-02-21&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Japan}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The [[Japanese Red Cross]] dispatched its staff to Haiti to collect information of the disaster. It also donated ¥20 million ([[United States dollar|US$]]220,000) to the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.asahi.com/international/update/0113/TKY201001130351.html|title=官房長官がハイチ支援策の検討指示　日赤は職員派遣へ|date=13 January 2010|publisher=[[Asahi Shimbun]]|language=Japanese|accessdate=13 January 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also sent, on 17th Jan., medical team of eight staffs going to be operated for 4 weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jrc.or.jp/foreignrescue/l3/Vcms3_00001455.html|title=（速報）ハイチ大地震|accessdate=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*TMAT, a nonprofit organization, sent 11 members of medical staffs to a border city of Jimani, Dominica.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tmat.or.jp/tdmat/report/201001_4haichi.html|title=ハイチ大地震　本隊第一陣11名出発|accessdate=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Nepal}}===
*The Nepalese nonprofit organization Lovers’ Association created a Haiti relief fund with a R10,000 deposit and initiated a fundraising drive that will support UNICEF’s relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://china.org.cn/world/haitiquake/2010-01/21/content_19280257.htm |publisher=Xinhua |title= Nepal launches campaign to help children of Haiti |accessdate=2010-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Pakistan}}===
*[[Edhi Foundation]] plans to send relief teams to affected areas while US$500,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/urdu/pakistan/2010/01/100114_edhi_haitti.shtml|title=ایدھی کی طرف سے پانچ لاکھ ڈالر کی امداد|date=January 14, 2010|publisher=BBC News|language=Urdu|accessdate=28 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; worth of medicines and general supplies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.onlinenews.com.pk/details.php?id=157135|title=Edhi to participate in relief activities in Haiti |publisher=Online - International News Network |accessdate=24 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.daily.pk/edhi-to-leave-for-haiti-soon-14753/&lt;/ref&gt;

*Pakistan Doctors Association announced to send doctors and aid to help victims of quake.

==={{flag|South Korea}}===&lt;!-- Alphabetically ordered as Korea, South --&gt;
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The [http://www.redcross.or.kr/eng/ Korean Red Cross] donated [[South Korean won|₩]]100 million ([[United States dollar|US$]]90,000) through the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.joins.com/article/290/3968290.html?ctg=12|title=한적, `지진 피해` 아이티에 1억원 지원|date=14 January 2010|publisher=[[Yonhap News Agency]]|language=Korean|accessdate=17 January 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also started public fund-raising campaign aiming to raise ₩3 billion (US$2.7 million) to help with relief efforts in the quake-stricken Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;http://english.yonhapnews.co.kr/national/2010/01/18/97/0302000000AEN20100118006900320F.HTML&lt;/ref&gt;
*Civilian medial service team, jointly formed by [[Korea University]] and [[Chosun Ilbo]] will be dispatched on 19 January.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.nate.com/view/20100118n01093&lt;/ref&gt;
*South Korean companies, including [[Samsung]], [[Hyundai]] and [[LG]], responded by donating fund to relief aids.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ytn.co.kr/_ln/0102_201001181510025500&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Taiwan}}===
*[[Tzu Chi]] - Chinese in Taiwan Buddhist foundation sent 400,000 packs on instant rice, 30 tons of corn meal, 50,000 blankets, 10,000 boxes bottled water, 150,000 anti-inflammatories, 5,000 body bags and other canned food and medical supplies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/asiapacific/news/article_1526004.php/Taiwan-Buddhist-groups-sending-aid-to-Haiti#ixzz0dBOUkRxm Taiwan Buddhist groups sending aid to Haiti]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Vietnam}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The Vietnam Red Cross Society’s Central Committee donated US$20,000 to the relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = | title =Red Cross raises US$20,000 for Haiti quake victims | publisher =VOV News  | date =January 25, 2010 | url =http://english.vovnews.vn/Home/Red-Cross-raises-US20000-for-Haiti-quake-victims/20101/112118.vov | accessdate=2010-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==
==={{flag|Armenia}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The [[Armenian General Benevolent Union]] has donated $50,000 to the International Red Cross in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.agbu.org/pressoffice/article.asp?ID=662]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Belarus}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[Belarusian Red Cross]] allocated an immediate aid of [[Swiss franc|CHF]] 5,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.belta.by/ru/news/society?id=474298 Белорусский Красный Крест выделяет Br14 млн. пострадавшим в Гаити и объявляет сбор пожертвований]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Bulgaria}}===
* {{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The [[Bulgarian Red Cross]] has opened up bank accounts and [[phone]] lines for making donations and up to now there are at least 10000 [[euro]]s gathered for the cause.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

==={{flag|Croatia}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[Croatian Red Cross]] has opened bank accounts for regular people to help, collecting [[Croatian kuna|HRK]] 5,645,757 (USD$ 1,040,000) by March 22.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hck.hr/?path=hr/novosti/opsirnije/371 HCK - Pomoć za Haiti]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Croatian Military Invalids of the Homeland War Association organized the concert ''Svi za Haiti'' (Everyone for Haiti) in [[Split (city)|Split]]'s [[Spaladium Arena]]. Performers included [[Gibonni]], [[Oliver Dragojević]], [[Thompson (band)|Thompson]], Vinko Coce, [[Jelena Rozga]], Tedi Spalato, Jole, and [[Luka Nižetić]]. The concert raised [[Croatian kuna|HRK]] 1,076,397 (USD$ 200,000).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slobodnadalmacija.hr/Spektakli/tabid/79/articleType/ArticleView/articleId/91386/Default.aspx PREKO MILIJUN KUNA ZA HAITI Oliver: Split je večeras najveći grad! (FOTOGALERIJA)], [[Slobodna Dalmacija]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Estonia}}===
* {{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} The [[Estonian Red Cross]] received $230,000 from the Estonian government for its effort in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;http://uudised.err.ee/index.php?06191329&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Finland}}===
* Finn Church Aid and Finland’s [[World Vision]] have pledged €150,000 and €100,000, respectively, to help Haiti. Several organizations are preparing to send aid and rescue workers to Haiti.&lt;ref name=finnish_organisations_plead_for_haiti_aid&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.yle.fi/uutiset/news/2010/01/finnish_organisations_plead_for_haiti_aid_1366061.html|title=Finnish Organisations Plead for Haiti Aid|date=2010-01-13|publisher=[[YLE]]|accessdate=13 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[Finnish Red Cross]] (SPR) has pledged €200,000 to help Haiti.&lt;ref name=finnish_organisations_plead_for_haiti_aid/&gt;

==={{flag|Netherlands}}===
* The Dutch [[Samenwerkende Hulporganisaties]] (Joined Aid Organizations) have raised €83.500.000.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl}}[http://www.trouw.nl/nieuws/nederland/article2969120.ece/Actie_voor_Ha_iuml_ti_levert_ruim_83_5_miljoen_euro_op.html SHO haalt ruim 83,5 miljoen op voor Haïti], Trouw.nl, 22 January&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Poland}}===
*Poland's [[UNICEF]] division has already given 100,000 [[Polish złoty|zł]] (around [[Euro|€]]25,000&lt;ref name=&quot;złoty-to-euro by Google&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/search?q=100000+Polish+z%C5%82oty+in+euro|title=100000 Polish złoty in euro - Google Search|date=2010-01-13|publisher=Google.com|accessdate=14 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;) to help victims of the earthquake, while [[Caritas (charity)|Caritas Poland]] has sent €30,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.rp.pl/artykul/419315_Stosy_zwlok_na_ulicach_.html | title=Stosy zwłok na ulicach|publisher=rzeczpospolita.pl | date=2010-01-13 |accessdate=2010-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.caritas.pl/news.php?id=9766 | title=Caritas pomaga ofiarom na Haiti | publisher=Caritas w Polsce | date=2010-01-14 |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Polish Medical Mission will send field hospital with medical supplies and 14-member emergency medical team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.polskieradio.pl/trojka/wiadomosci/default.aspx?id=131866 | title=Polski szpital polowy na Haiti | publisher=polskieradio.pl | date=2010-01-15 |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Polish Humanitarian Organisation]] raised over 800,000 [[Polish złoty|zł]] (around [[Euro|€]]200,000&lt;ref name=&quot;złoty-to-euro by Google&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.co.uk/search?hl=en&amp;q=800000+pln+to+euro|title=800000 pln to euro - Google Search|date=2010-01-18|publisher=Google.com|accessdate=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;) in donations.
* [[Caritas (charity)|Caritas Poland]] started public fund-raising campaign. Caritas donated over 1 million [[Polish złoty|zł]] (US$360,000) and more aid is coming to help with relief efforts in the quake-stricken Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://wiadomosci.gazeta.pl/Wiadomosci/1,81048,7466533,Caritas_Polska__ponad_milion_zl_na_pomoc_dla_Haiti.html | title=Caritas Polska: ponad milion zł na pomoc dla Haiti z indywidualnych wpłat Polaków | publisher=gazeta.pl | date=2010-01-18 |accessdate=2010-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The total amount collected by Caritas Poland, Poland's UNICEF division and Polish Humanitarian Organisation already exceeded 5 million [[Polish złoty|zł]] (around [[Euro|€]] 1.23 million) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://wiadomosci.gazeta.pl/Wiadomosci/1,80269,7492974,Mamy_juz_ponad_800_tys__zl_dla_Haiti__Zbierzmy_milion.html | title=Mamy już ponad 800 tys. zł dla Haiti. Zbierzmy milion | date=2010-01-25 | accessdate=2010-01-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Sweden}}===
* The [[Livets Ord|Livets Ord Church]] (Word of Life Church) sent a 9-person medical staff team, including surgeons, emergency-care nursing staff, anesthetists and support workers, that arrived in Haiti on Thursday, January 21.&lt;ref&gt;{{nl}}[http://www.livetsord.se/default.aspx?idStructure=9069 Medical Team to Haiti], 22 January&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Turkey}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|crescent}} The [[Turkish Red Crescent]] has sent two crews that include psychologists and disaster experts to make an assessment and provide urgent assistance in coordination with the Red Cross officials in the field. The Red Crescent will send further humanitarian aid teams in the light of the initial team’s report.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=turkish-red-crescent-to-aid-quake-devastated-haitians-2010-01-13 |title=Turkish Red Crescent to aid quake devastated Haitians |date=14 January 2010|publisher=Hurriyet Daily News|accessdate=14 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[IHH (İnsani Yardım Vakfı)|Humanitarian Aid Foundation]] said that their aid was sent to Haiti from the United States by two cargo planes. The 33 tons of aid includes blankets, clothes, foodstuff, medical equipment and infant food.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}} Additionally Turkish Ministry Of Health sent a fully equipped mobile hospital with 19 staff, including doctors, nurses and technicians. Two ambulances are included in this mobile hospital.

==={{flag|United Kingdom}}===
*The [[Disasters Emergency Committee]] (DEC), an umbrella organisation for 13 UK-registered humanitarian aid agencies, launched an appeal for relief efforts in Haiti which as of 10 July 2010 has raised £101 million (US$152 million) in donations.  Interventions which have so far been provided from these funds include: clean drinking water for over 250,000 people; emergency shelter for over 100,000 people; building 3,000 latrines; over 2,500 ‘cash for work’ public service projects; medical consultations for over 100,000 people; and supplementary feeding for 1,890 malnourished children.&lt;ref name=&quot;DEC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dec.org.uk/item/433|title=DEC press release 433 |accessdate=10 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A poll conducted on behalf of the DEC by the [[Charities Aid Foundation]] over the 23rd and 24 January indicated that 48% of the UK public had so far donated, and of those that hadn't yet, 62% might or were planning to.&lt;ref name=&quot;DEC2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=DEC press release 414 |url=http://www.dec.org.uk/item/414}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Humanity First|Humanity First UK]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.humanityfirst.org.uk/&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[St Eugene's Cathedral]] in [[Derry]], [[Northern Ireland]] raised almost £25,000 by 20 January 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author =|title=Church raises £25,000 for Haiti|publisher =BBC News|date =January 20, 2010 | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/northern_ireland/foyle_and_west/8468265.stm| accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*United Haitians in the UK (UHUK) have been collecting donations of supplies to send out and helping Haitians in the UK make contact with their relatives.&lt;ref&gt;UHUK website http://www.uhuk.org/&lt;/ref&gt;

==North America==
A combination of Canadian and United States medical staff used [[Anís Zunúzí Bahá'í School]] as its headquarters and  some of its Haitian staff were able to use the site as a makeshift clinic.&lt;ref name=&quot;BWN755&quot;&gt;Information is in the body of the article as well as comments in the captions of the photos at right after you click &quot;enlarge&quot;. {{Cite news  | title = Amid wreckage in Haiti, new birth brings hope | newspaper = Bahá'í World News Service | location = | pages = | language = | publisher = Bahá'i International Community | date = 5 February 2010 | url =  http://news.bahai.org/story/755 | accessdate = 2010-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 18 team members came with donated medical supplies, including more than 2,000 packages of antibiotics and other medicine. The members of the team were one professional nurse, two pediatricians, two orthopedic surgeons, four obstetrician/gynecologists, an intensive care specialist, a hospital doctor, a respiratory therapists, and a fourth-year medical student. They all took commercial flights to the Dominican Republic and then traveled by bus to Haiti and were able to stay for a week (leaving about Feb 5th.) The team traveled to other localities, including hospitals, orphanages, and temporary medical stations set up in nearby villages. Some of the staff of the Zunuzi school provided translation services to aid the medical staff. The group spontaneously organized mostly through [[Facebook]]. The group are planning on a return trip in March.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| last =  Carroll | first = Timothy J. | title = Hands-on in Haiti Local women need supplies for relief effort | newspaper = Hudson Reporter | location =Hoboken New Jersey | publisher = | date = February 14, 2010 | url = http://hudsonreporter.com/view/full_story/6223834/article-Hands-on-in-Haiti-Local-women-need-supplies-for-relief-effort-?instance=secondary_stories_left_column | accessdate = 2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Haiti}}===
*Haiti Arise, an organization based in Grand-Goave, Haiti, with branches in Canada and the United States, has established an earthquake relief fund.  The Canadian branch has undertaken a significant fund-raising campaign with every dollar raised being matched by the Canadian government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haitiarise.org/]&lt;/ref&gt; Also they continue to work hard to distribute much needed water, rice and other supplies. A group of high school students from B.C., Canada, who arrived just hours before the earthquake, used CA$2,500 of their own money to buy and distribute rice to local residents affected by the quake.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.kelowna.com/2010/01/16/stranded-b-c-students-help-feed-locals-teens-spent-2500-to-buy-rice-at-inflated-prices-and-distribute-it-to-villagers/&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Aruba}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[Red Cross Aruba]] is in the process of collecting funds from Aruban citizens and companies, and has been receiving an overwhelming number of calls from those looking to donate. Red Cross Aruba has opened bank accounts at all local banks for direct donations and will send the collected funds to Red Cross International, which is coordinating relief efforts with emergency supplies, technical assistance and other support to those in urgent need in Haiti. Red Cross Aruba is also organizing a relief effort to send local doctors and surgeons to Haiti to provide medical assistance along with Red Cross volunteers from Aruba.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.travelagentcentral.com/aruba/aruba-helps-bring-aid-haiti-19325 Aruba Helps Bring Aid to Haiti ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Canada}}===
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[Canadian Red Cross]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.redcross.ca/article.asp?id=33900&amp;tid=001 |title=Red Cross responds to devastating earthquake in Haiti |publisher=Canadian Red Cross |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**The Canadian Red Cross reported (as of January 17, 2010) receiving $22 million dollars from Canadians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ctv.ca/servlet/ArticleNews/story/CTVNews/20100117/redcross_haiti_100117/20100117?hub=Canada Canadians donate millions to quake-ravaged Haiti]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Guru Nanak Sikh Gurdwara Society, a [[Sikh]] temple from [[Surrey]], [[British Columbia]], along with local South Asian radio stations, managed to raise over $100,000 CAD in donations on January 14, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Diakiw |first=Kevin |url=http://www.bclocalnews.com/surrey_area/surreyleader/news/81746007.html |title=Surrey Leader - Temple raises $100K first day |publisher=Bclocalnews.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-16}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**As of January 21, $1,500,000 had been raised by the temple and radio stations. A portion of the money will be given to the Governor General of Canada to be given directly to the Haitian government, while the remainder will go to support [[Médecins Sans Frontières]] (Doctor's Without Borders) and United Sikhs, an NGO which provides disaster relief Haiti&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unitedsikhs.org/haitiearthquake/ |title=Recognize the Human Race as One |publisher=United Sikhs |date= |accessdate=2010-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ferguson |first=Dan |url=http://www.bclocalnews.com/surrey_area/surreyleader/news/82307862.html |title=Surrey Leader - Surrey temple fundraiser collects $1.5 million for Haitian relief |publisher=Bclocalnews.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-21}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Humanity First|Humanity First Canada]] &lt;ref&gt;http://www.humanityfirst.ca/&lt;/ref&gt; held several fundraising events for Haiti appeal.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.newswire.ca/en/releases/archive/January2010/23/c3456.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Inuit Tapiriit Kanatami]] collected $90,000 to the relief effort.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/blogs/bureau-blog/inuit-chip-in-on-haitian-relief/article1433065/ Inuit chip in on Haitian relief ]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Canadian Salvation Army.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flickr.com/photos/salvationarmy/sets/72157623203832664/ Canadian Salvation Army on Flickr]&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|Dominican Republic}}===
*VICINI and the INICIA Foundation announced an immediate cash donation of US$1 million. In addition, another US$5 million is being donated by VICINI in products, services and technical personnel.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.benzinga.com/press-releases/b89855/vicini-to-donate-significant-aid-to-haiti Vicini to Donate Significant Aid to Haiti.]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Government:'''

*The Dominican Republic was the first country in the world to support Haiti with aids, and the Dominican Government approve a special budget to Haiti Aids of US$6,4 million focus on Heath programs (US$1,7&amp;nbsp;mm), Food Programs (US$1,4mm), to Army (US$1,5mm), among others.
*SESPAS - (Heath Ministry) send ambulance, doctors and nurses to the border and Haiti. Also operates diversify hospitals and heath center to help Haitians. The worst patients (like Haitian President of Congress, others) were sending to Santiago and Santo Domingo for specials cares.
*FFAA - (National Army) send diversify aid like personal, trucks, helicopters, planes, other to the border to help and coordinate the distributions to Haiti.
*IDAC - (Instituto de Aviación Civil) create a special fleet with public and private airplanes (23) and helicopters (14) to send aids to the border.
*DGA - (Dirección General de Aduanas) approve a free tax to all aids arrive to DR thought airports and ports focus in equipments, water, medicines, aids materials, other
*SEOPC - (Secretaria Obras Públicas) send equipments to remove and clean streets, bridges, other for better distributions of aid by land.
*INDOTEL - (Telecommunication Institute) send digital phone and technicians to recover communications.
*Gustavo Lara, Executive Director Red Cross Dominicana informs that the institution is presents in the border coordinating aid for 100,000 families given them free medical attentions.

'''Private Sector:'''

*Vicini, Free Trade Zone Association (ADOZONA), Labor Ministry, Public Energy Corporation (CDEEE) and Conep President Lizandro Macarrulla announced a special conjoint program for help Haiti.
*Fundación Inicia, from Vicini, announce a US$1million dolar cash contribution and US$5 millon grant in in-kind products, servicies, other like rebards, milk, water, technicians, equipment, others
*INCA - (Industrias Nacionales) will give 50,000 zinc pieces for rebuilt houses (roof, walls, other)
*Grupo Leon Jimenes will donated RD$5,000,000 pesos in aids for Haiti
*Codetel, Orange, Viva and Tricom (Telecommunication companies) using text messages (SMS) to collect money for Haiti
*Escogido Baseball Club makes collects at baseball stadiums with baseball players, executives and public
*Grupo M (one of the biggest free trade zone) sends containers with food and medicines
*Nacional, Pola and Cadena Supermarkets are making food and water collects in all supermarkets countrywide
*Junta Agroempresarial Dominicana creates a special programs to send food with agricultural business producers.

==={{flag|Mexico}}===
The [[Topos de Tlatelolco]] volunteer search and rescue group is participating in relief efforts.  This group specialized in finding victims under rubble and giving first aid. The first group of six left on 14 January for the country from Cancún. This group is called the advance team or the beachhead because their job is to make initial assessments of the situation for the teams that follow. The next group scheduled to leave is the canine unit. A total of 18 to 24 are expected to go, with transportation being provided by the [[Mexican navy]]. The group plans to be there until 28 January.&lt;ref name=&quot;etoro&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Viajan Topos mexicanos a Haití |first= Evangelina |last= del Toro  |url=http://mx.news.yahoo.com/s/14012010/7/negocios-viajan-topos-mexicanos-haiti.html |newspaper=Yahoo News |date=14 January 2010 |accessdate=14 January 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Mexican Topos travel to Haiti }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, doctors from the [[University of Montemorelos]] have departed to help as a direct response to a request from the Seventh-Day Adventist Hospital in Port-au-Prince.&lt;ref name=&quot;comunicando&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title= Parten médicos de la UM hacia Haití  |first= Benjamín |last= García   |url=http://um.edu.mx/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=1191%3Aparten-medicos-de-la-um-hacia-haiti&amp;catid=93%3Adestacado&amp;Itemid=155&amp;lang=es |newspaper=UM Comunicando |date=14 January 2010 |accessdate=16 January 2010 |language=Spanish |trans_title=Parten médicos de la UM hacia Haití }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==={{flag|United States}}===
In the USA, the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]] and [[Better Business Bureau]] have issued a warning about phony charities, and implored prospective donors to check the reputation of a charity before making a donation due to previous incidents of fraudulent charities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/HaitiEarthquake/haiti-earthquake-careful-impulse-donations/story?id=9551890 |title=Help Haiti but Beware: Watch Out for Those 'Impulse' Donations - ABC News |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date= |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fbi.gov/pressrel/pressrel10/earthquake011310.htm |title=Federal Bureau of Investigation - Press Release |publisher=Fbi.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-01-14}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbb.org/us/article/bbb-advises-donors-on-how-to-vet-haiti-earthquake-charity-appeals-14644 |title=BBB Advises Donors on How to Vet Haiti Earthquake Charity Appeals - BBB News Center |publisher=Bbb.org |date=2009-11-24 |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On January 13, 2010, the Better Business Bureau released a list of charities requesting aid for Haiti relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.bbb.org/us/article/charities-providing-haiti-earthquake-relief-14690 |publisher=Better Business Bureau (U.S.) |title=Charities Providing Haiti Earthquake Relief |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This list only contained charities that met the BBB's standards for &quot;Wise Giving.&quot;

The following organizations have publicly announced their intentions or actions to help Haitian victims:
*[[AARP]] - Offered a dollar-for-dollar match on donations to its foundation, reaching $500,000 in donations for the relief efforts through this endeavor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://bucks.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/01/19/aarp-will-double-your-haiti-donation/|title=AARP will double your Haiti donation |publisher=The New  York Times| accessdate=2010-01-21 | first=Ron | last=Lieber | date=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Action Against Hunger]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.actionagainsthunger.org/pressroom/releases/2010/01/14 |publisher=Action Against Hunger |title=Haiti: Access to Water and Sanitation Urgently Needed |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Adventist Development and Relief Agency]] - Created a Haiti Earthquake Response Fund. Initial pledge of {{US$|1,000,000}} was announced on January 14, 2010&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.adra.org/site/News2?page=NewsArticle&amp;id=10732&amp;security=1&amp;news_iv_ctrl=1141 |publisher=ADRA International |title=Update: ADRA Commits $1 Million to Earthquake Response in Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Adventist Health International]] - Supports Hopital Adventiste d'Haiti, one of the few fully functioning hospitals in Port-au-Prince.
*[[Aid For Haiti (AFH)]] - A faith-based effort providing and coordinating medical relief in Petit Goave, Haiti.
*[[American Humane Association]] participated in the relief efforts through the Animal Relief Coalition for Haiti, a coalition created by the [[World Society for the Protection of Animals]] and the [[International Fund for Animal Welfare]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = | title = American Humane Association joins Haiti international response team | publisher =San Francisco Chronicle | date =January 15, 2010 | url = http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/blogs/pets/detail?entry_id=55397#ixzz0dHkA14Kl| accessdate=2010-01-21 | first=Amelia | last=Glynn}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[American Jewish World Service]] - Created a Haiti Earthquake Relief Fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://ajws.org/who_we_are/news/haiti_emergency.html |publisher=American Jewish World Service |title=Haiti Earthquake Relief Fund |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{flag icon|ICRC|cross}} [[American Red Cross]] - Initial contribution of {{US$|1,000,000}}, which was increased to {{US$|10,000,000}} million on January 14, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.redcross.org/portal/site/en/menuitem.94aae335470e233f6cf911df43181aa0/?vgnextoid=1782005e7cb26210VgnVCM10000089f0870aRCRD |title=American Red Cross Releases $10 Million to Help Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[AmeriCares]] - Sent {{US$|3,000,000}} worth of medical aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.americares.org/ |title=AmeriCares |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The American Methodist Church through [[UMCOR]] is donating over {{US$|1,000,000}} US dollars and more aid is coming.
*[[Armenian National Committee of America]] - Has urged Armenian-Americans to pledge money and send aid to the American Red Cross.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.asbarez.com/2010/01/14/anca-calls-on-armenian-americans-to-help-haiti-earthquake-rescue-and-relief/ |title=ANCA call to action}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Broadway Cares/Equity Fights AIDS]] donated US$100,000 to the Haiti relief efforts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thestage.co.uk/news/newsstory.php/26940/broadway-raises-400-000-to-help-haiti |title= Broadway raises $400,000 to help Haiti |publisher=The Stage News|date=2010-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[CARE (relief agency)|CARE USA]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.care.org/emergency/haitiearthquake/index.asp |publisher=CARE |title=Earthquake Strikes Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Catholic Relief Services]] - Initial contribution of {{US$|5,000,000}}. US$200,000,000 over the next five years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.crs.org/ |title=Catholic Relief Services |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Christian Reformed Church in North America|Christian Reformed World Relief Committee]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.crcna.org/news.cfm?detailid=3556&amp;newsid=1722 |publisher=Christian Reformed World Relief Committee |title=CRWRC Responds to Urgent Needs In Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]] - {{convert|225000|lb|kg}} of tents, clothes, food, medical supplies, hygiene and newborn kits.  A team of doctors was also sent and LDS chapels are being used as shelters for over 5,000 Haitian residents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.newsroom.lds.org/ldsnewsroom/eng/news-releases-stories/despite-challenges-church-aid-reaching-needy-more-is-on-the-way |publisher=Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints |title=Despite Challenges, Church Aid Reaching Needy; More Is on the Way |accessdate=2010-01-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Clinton Bush Haiti Fund]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clintonbushhaitifund.org/ Clinton Bush Haiti Fund]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Compassion International]] - &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbb.org/us/article/charities-providing-haiti-earthquake-relief-14690 |title=Charities Providing Haiti Earthquake Relief - BBB News Center |publisher=Bbb.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Direct Relief International]] - Sent two shipping containers of medical supplies, and {{US$|2,000,000}} in aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.directrelief.org/EmergencyResponse/2010/EarthquakeHaiti.aspx |publisher=Direct Relief International |title=Earthquake Response - Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Episcopal Church (United States)|Epispocal Relief &amp; Development]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.er-d.org/HaitiEarthquakeResponse|title= Episcopal Relief &amp; Development Responds to Devastating Earthquake in Haiti |date=13 January 2010|publisher=Episcopalian Life Online |accessdate=16 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Family Health International]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.fhi.org/hld/Haiti_relief/Haiti_Needs_Your_Help_Fund_Haiti_Relief.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Florida Baptist Building|Florida Baptist Convention]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://jacksonville.com/news/metro/2010-01-15/story/jacksonville_buddhist_center_hosts_tibetan_retreat_master_abbot|title= Jacksonville Buddhist center hosts Tibetan retreat master, abbot |date=15 January 2010|publisher=Florida Times-Union |accessdate=18 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Flying Doctors of America]] - Medical Teams &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ajc.com/news/georgians-helping-in-haiti-276753.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Food For The Poor]] - Raising 20 Million to address a wide variety of needs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foodforthepoor.org/newsroom/news/food-for-the-poor-one-month.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Grassroots International, which has worked in Haiti for over 20 years, established an Earthquake Response Fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://grassrootsonline.org/haiti |title=Haiti Earthquake Updates  |publisher=Grassroots International |accessdate=2010-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ford Foundation]] - {{US$|1,000,000}} in grants to support urgent humanitarian relief efforts. The grants, for $500,000 each, will go to [[Oxfam]] International and [[Partners in Health]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://pr-usa.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=317718&amp;Itemid=95 Ford Foundation Commits Initial $1 Million in Emergency Aid for Haiti]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Giving Children Hope]] has been working to get much-needed medicines and supplies on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://abclocal.go.com/kabc/story?section=weather/earthquake_center&amp;id=7217433 |author=Eileen Frere |title=Buena Park charity pack supplies for Haiti |publisher=Abclocal.go.com |date=13 January 2010 |accessdate=15 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Habitat for Humanity]] - Sent an assessment team on January 13, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.habitat.org/newsroom/2010archive/01_13_2010_Haiti_Earthquake.aspx |title=Addressing housing needs in Haiti after major earthquake  |publisher=Habitat for Humanity |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Hands On Disaster Response]] has a mission of staff and up to eighty volunteers in Leogane conducting inter-organization coordination and logistical support, medical support, demolition of damaged houses, and temporary and transitional shelter design, fabrication and disbursement. The mission is slated to run until August, 2010.
*[[Humanity First|Humanity First USA]]&lt;ref&gt;http://usa.humanityfirst.org/&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[International Bottled Water Association]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.watertechonline.com/news.asp?N_ID=73284 |title= BOTTLED WATER INDUSTRY PROVIDES ASSISTANCE TO HAITIAN EARTHQUAKE RELIEF EFFORTS |publisher=WaterTech Online|date=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Islamic Relief]], to fly a {{US$|1,000,000}} shipment to Haiti, in coordination with [[The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.wjla.com/news/stories/0110/695706.html|title=Islamic Relief USA to Fly Aid to Haiti|accessdate=2010-01-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Konbit Sante]] - A Maine/Haiti partnership to improve healthcare in northern Haiti held a telethon to raise money for relief efforts in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;Konbit Sante  http://www.konbitsante.org/&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lance Armstrong Foundation]] - {{US$|250,000}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/01/14/2792233.htm?section=justin Lance donates to Haiti quake victims]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Lutheran World Relief]] - Committed an initial {{US$|1,000,000}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.lwr.org/emergencies/10/HaitiEarthquake/ |title=Haiti Earthquake |publisher=Lutheran World Relief |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mennonite Central Committee]] - committed {{US$|100,000}} for immediate needs with an additional {{US$|1,000,000}} anticipated  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mcc.org/stories/news/mcc-respond-haiti-earthquake-donations-welcome |title=MCC to respond to Haiti earthquake, donations welcome &amp;#124; Mennonite Central Committee |publisher=Mcc.org |date= |accessdate=2010-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Mercy Corps]] - Sent supplies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mercycorps.org/haiti |title=Haiti Earthquake |publisher=Mercy Corps |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Not on our Watch]] - donated $1,000,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salem-news.com/articles/january162010/pitt_clooney.php 'Not On Our Watch' Donates $1 Million to Haiti Efforts]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Operation USA]] - Sent medical aid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.opusa.org/featured/news-release-operation-usa-prepares-emergency-aid-in-response-to-earthquakes-in-haiti/ |title=Operation USA Prepares Emergency Aid in Response to Earthquakes in Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Oxfam America]] - Following a major 7.0 earthquake on January 12, 2010, near the Haitian capital of Port-au-Prince, international relief and development agency Oxfam America swung into action to raise emergency funds to assist relief and rehabilitation efforts on the ground. Oxfam is committed to assisting in the rebuilding efforts in Haiti, and the agency will be on the ground for the long haul. This along with the immediate response of providing clean water, shelter, and sanitation means that the level of need continues to be great.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.oxfamamerica.org/emergencies/earthquake-in-haiti|title=Haiti Earthquake|publisher=Oxfam America |accessdate=2010-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Partners In Health]] - PIH has been working in Haiti for 20 years to provide health care and train health providers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://standwithhaiti.org/haiti#about-pih |title=PIH Haiti Background |publisher=Partners In Health |accessdate=2010-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is currently prioritizing the deployment of additional surgical teams&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://standwithhaiti.org/haiti/news-entry/how-you-can-help-volunteer-and-donate-supplies/ |title=How You Can Help - Volunteer and Donate Supplies |publisher=Partners In Health |accessdate=2010-01-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Rainbow World Fund, an international relief agency based in the [[LGBT]] community, set up a Haiti relief fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = | title = LGBT organization sets up Haiti relief fund| publisher =Dallas Voice |  date =January 14, 2010 | url = http://www.dallasvoice.com/instant-tea/2010/01/14/lgbt-organization-sets-up-haiti-relief-fund/| accessdate=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Salvation Army]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://blog.salvationarmyeds.org/?p=256 |title=Haiti |publisher=Salvation Army |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Save the Children]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.savethechildren.org/newsroom/2010/haiti-relief.html |publisher=Save the Children |title=Save the Children Launches Emergency Relief Effort to Assist Children and Families in Haiti |accessdate=2010-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Seacoast Church]] raised more than $287,000, which was donated to Water Missions International to provide a new water purification system for use in Haiti.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.citizen-times.com/article/20100203/LOCAL/100203021 |publisher=Citizen-Times |title= Seacoast Church raises over $287,000, helps Haiti with water issues |accessdate=2010-02-03}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[ShelterBox USA]] - ShelterBox USA provides victims of disaster with shelter and basic provisions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shelterboxusa.org |publisher=ShelterBox USA |title=ShelterBox USA provides victims of disaster with shelter and basic provisions. |accessdate=2010-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Southern Baptist Convention]] - Sending an assessment team made up of representatives from Baptist Global Response, the [[North American Mission Board]] and disaster relief specialist from the Kentucky, Mississippi and South Carolina state conventions. A second team is being sent by the Florida state convention. Both teams will assess both immediate and long-term needs and will report their findings and recommended actions to Southern Baptist Disaster Relief. Funding for the relief effort will be coordinated through the [[International Mission Board]] disaster relief fund.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.bpnews.net/bpnews.asp?id=32035 |title=Haiti Assessment Teams Focus On Urgent &amp; Long-Term Needs |publisher=Baptist Press |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Unitarian Universalist Service Committee]] and the [[Unitarian Universalist Association]] of Congregations created a Haiti relief fund on January 14, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=
http://www.uuworld.org/news/articles/154691.shtml |title= UUSC, UUA create Haitian relief fund |date=14 January 2010|publisher=Unitarian Universalist World |accessdate=15 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Individual congregations of the [[United Church of Christ]], [[United Methodist Church]] and [[Baptists]] have all contributed thousands of meals and are planning to give more though the Methodist Church's response is hampered by the fate of its disaster relief chairman the [[Rev. Sam Dixon]] who was in Haiti's capital at the time of the earthquake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.decaturdaily.com/detail/51463.html |title=Local churches assisting with relief efforts |publisher=Decaturdaily.com |date=2007-02-20 |accessdate=2010-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[YMCA]] World Service - Working in collaboration with the [[Red Cross]], Action Churches Together and other relief and emergency agencies, YMCAs around the world are responding to the urgent basic needs of those displaced by providing food, water, medicines, blankets; and in the longer term, care and psycho-social counseling. In addition, the Dominican Republic YMCA and the Latin American and Caribbean Alliance of YMCAs, with support from the global [[YMCA]] movement, is planning to deliver critical supplies and support to those impacted.
* Website [[Reddit.com]] has launched a campaign with its users and raised over $116,000 dollars&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://dri.convio.net/site/TR/Events/Tributes?pg=fund&amp;amp;fr_id=1030&amp;amp;pxfid=1511&amp;amp;JServSessionIdr004=r7t58phav1.app245b |title=Reddit.com Direct Relief International| date=16 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[University of Pittsburgh Medical Center|University of Pittsburgh Medical Center's]] [[Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh|Children's Hospital]] took in 53 orphans for treatment. The children, as young as six months, had been living in the Port-au-Prince Bresma Orphanage run by two Pittsburgh-native sisters. Pennsylvania Governor [[Ed Rendell]] and Representative [[Jason Altmire]] flew with a group of medical staff to Haiti and returned with the 53 children.&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/10019/1029323-100.stm?cmpid=localstate.xml | work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette | title=Children's gets ready for arrival of Haitian orphans | first=Sadie | last=Gurman | date=2010-01-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;post-gazette.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/news/specialreports/trib-in-haiti/s_662827.html&lt;/ref&gt; 47 of the children had adoption cases in progess from the United States, Canada and Spain, many of which were in the final stages.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2010/US/01/19/haiti.orphans/index.html?iref=mpstoryview | work=CNN | title=Orphans from quake-ravaged Haiti arrive in U.S. - CNN.com | accessdate=2010-05-04 | date=2010-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Humanitarian response by national governments to the 2010 Haiti earthquake]]
*[[Humanitarian response by for-profit organizations to the 2010 Haiti earthquake]]

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

==External links==
*Humanitarian response by non-governmental organizations to the 2010 Haiti earthquake
*[http://ocha.unog.ch/fts/pageloader.aspx?page=emerg-emergencyDetails&amp;emergID=15797 HAITI - Earthquakes - January 2010 Total Humanitarian Funding]
*[http://ocha.unog.ch/fts/reports/daily/ocha_R10_E15797_asof___1002021855.pdf HAITI - Earthquakes - January 2010 Table A: List of all commitments/contributions and pledges as of 3 February 2010], [[Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs|OCHA]]

{{2010 Haiti earthquake}}

[[Category:2010 Haiti earthquake relief|*]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
