<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="258719" ns="0" title="Puppy mill"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Puppy mill02.JPG|thumb|right|A puppy mill in rural US]]
{{Unreliable sources|date=August 2011}}
A '''puppy mill''', sometimes known as a '''puppy farm''',&lt;ref&gt;[http://montereycountydemocrats.org/node/621 Farr Introduces Bill to Regulate Puppy Farms]&lt;/ref&gt; is a commercial [[dog breeding]] facility that is operated with an emphasis upon profits above animal welfare and is often in substandard conditions regarding the well-being of dogs in their care.&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_puppy_mills&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aspca.org/site/PageServer?pagename=cruelty_puppymills |accessdate=2007-12-13 |year=2007 |author=ASPCA |title=Fight Animal Cruelty: Puppy Mills}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;redeye_20071119&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://docs.newsbank.com/openurl?ctx_ver=z39.88-2004&amp;rft_id=info:sid/iw.newsbank.com:NewsBank:CREB&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=11D0B2F033A603F0&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated4&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2 |title=Buy or adopt? Where you get your pet is a big decision—and a big controversy |author=Swartz, Tracy |publisher=Chicago Tribune RedEye Edition |date=2007-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar types of operations exist for other animals commonly kept as pets or used as feed for other animals.
The term can be applied to operations involving other animals commercially bred for profit, e.g. &quot;kitty mills.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_glossary&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.aspca.org/site/PageServer?pagename=cruelty_crueltyglossary |title=ASPCA: Fight Animal Cruelty: Cruelty Glossary |author=ASPCA |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are an estimated 4,000 puppy mills in the U.S. that produce more than half a million puppies a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;mlb.ilstu.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.mlb.ilstu.edu/cgi-bin/redirect.cgi?http://wf2dnvr8.webfeat.org:80/bOMzK1961/url=http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=hxh&amp;AN=14054225&amp;loginpage=Login.asp&amp;site=ehost-live&amp;scope=site&lt;/ref&gt; Commercial kennels may be licensed by the United States Department of Agriculture which may inspect the kennels routinely.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aphis.usda.gov/publications/animal_welfare/content/printable_version/faq_animal_dealers.pdf Questions and Answers on Animal Care’s Regulation of Commercial Animal Dealers]&lt;/ref&gt;

For-profit breeding on a smaller scale is sometimes referred to as '''backyard breeding'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_glossary&quot; /&gt;

== Differences in breeding conditions ==

The American and Westminster kennel clubs state that responsible breeders raise their animals with the intent to produce healthy dogs, and to ensure that all animals are provided responsible homes and [[socialization]].&lt;ref name=&quot;akc_breed_to_improve&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.akc.org/breeders/resources/guide_to_breeding_your_dog/step_2.cfm |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-12-13 |title=Step Two - Breed to Improve |author=American Kennel Club}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wkc&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.westminsterkennelclub.org/2008/show/news/breeders.html |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-12-13 |title=Buy Dogs from a Breeder |author=Westminster Kennel Club}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In puppy mills, females are sometimes bred every time they are in heat to increase profits, resulting in gradually decreasing sizes of litters.&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_puppy_mills&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boston_animal_control&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cityofboston.gov/animalcontrol/ready.asp |author=City of Boston |title=Are you ready to adopt a pet? |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; As puppies, mill dogs are also often [[weaning|wean]]ed from their mothers well before the eight to ten weeks recommended.&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_responsible_breeding&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aspca.org/site/PageServer? pagename=cruelty_puppymills_statement |title=Puppy Mills: Responsible Breeding |author=ASPCA |year=2007 |accessdate=2007-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bark Rescue in Belleview, IL also explains, “Puppies are taken from their mother when they are 5 to 6 weeks old and sold to brokers who pack them in crates for resale to pet stores all over the country.” Only half of the puppies survive during this exhausting travel only to make it to the pet shop until they are sold.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.barkrescue.net/puppymills.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Dogs in puppy mills are often bred indiscriminately. While the puppies produced may come with pedigrees, the pedigree itself is neither an indication of quality nor authenticity.&lt;ref name=&quot;kennel_club_uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/item/208 |title=Where NOT to buy a puppy or a dog |author=The Kennel Club (UK) |date=2006-05-16 |accessdate=2007-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most pet stores selling these dogs are aware of breeding conditions and where their dogs are coming from. The American Kennel Club is by law not held responsible nor do they guarantee the health of the dogs they sell. Most of the time the dogs are in poor health.

== Treatment at puppy mills ==

Puppy mills usually house dogs in overcrowded and unsanitary conditions, without adequate veterinary care, food, water and socialization. Puppy mill dogs do not receive treats, toys, exercise or basic grooming. To minimize waste cleanup, dogs are often kept in cages with wire flooring that injures their paws and legs. It is not unusual for cages to be stacked up in columns. Breeder dogs at mills might spend their entire lives outdoors, exposed to the elements, or kept inside indoor cages all their lives.  Often after the breeder dog has hit the age of 4 years old, it is no longer needed and killed.  Sometimes the puppy mill owners will have a contact person who collaborates with rescues.  The rescue will receive a phone call with the number of breeder dogs and types.  The rescue then can save the breeder dogs from death.  Once adopted, it can take up to or over a year for the dog to relax and allow human touch.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aspca.org/fight-animal-cruelty/puppy-mills/what-is-a-puppy-mill.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005 an investigation was conducted on pet shops and puppy mills in California, 44% of the locations visited had were sick and neglected animals, 32% of the animals were confined in unhealthy, cramped, or crowded conditions and 25% of the animals didn’t even have adequate food or water.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Smith|first=Kimberly K.|title=A Pluralist-Expressivist Critique of the Pet Trade|journal=Journal of Agricultural and Environmental Ethics|year=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Common problems ==

Due to the frequently poor breeding conditions in puppy mills, puppies bred there often suffer from health and/or social problems. Puppies raised in a cramped environment shared by many other dogs become poorly socialized to other dogs and to humans. Dogs are then transported over long distances in poor conditions, sometimes resulting in animal stress and death. As the surviving mill dogs grow older, they are more prone to developing respiratory ailments and [[pneumonia]], as well as hereditary defects such as [[Hip dysplasia (canine)|hip dysplasia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aspca_puppy_mills&quot; /&gt; In addition, mill dogs are more prone to have problems with their temperament. Puppies from mills are usually sold as purebred dogs in an attempt to attract the higher prices associated with purebreds. However, due to the indiscriminate breeding practices of puppy mills, the dog may not actually be a purebred puppy.&lt;ref name=&quot;kennel_club_uk&quot; /&gt; The vast majority of puppy mill animals are sold to pet stores by &quot;dealers&quot;. Some puppies are sold by dealers masquerading as authentic breeders.

It has been found that pet stores purchase the majority of their puppies from puppy mills. The Pet Industry Joint Advisory Council (PIJAC) explained that roughly 3,500 to 3,700 of the 11,500 to 12,000 pet stores in the United States purchased their animals from puppy mills. They also predict pet stores to sell up to 300,000 to 500,000 puppies a year. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.petfinder.com/how-to-help-pets/animal-cruelty-puppy-mills.html?printer_friendly=1&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==

According to Canis Major V. publications, puppy mills originated in the post-[[World War II]] era. Midwestern farmers looking for an alternative crop reacted to a growing demand for puppies, resulting in the development of the first commercial puppy business. As the business grew, both small and large retail outlets began to sell puppies through pet departments. At around the same time, the first pet store chains were born.&lt;ref name=&quot;canis_major_dilemma&quot; /&gt;

Through indifference or ignorance, many puppies were left unsocialized or exposed in existing chicken coops or rabbit hutches. In addition, veterinary care for these puppies was often overlooked because of an inability to pay. As a result, organizations such as the [[Humane Society of the United States]] began to investigate breeding kennels, leading to the passage of the [[Animal Welfare Act of 1966|Animal Welfare Act]] of August 24, 1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;canis_major_dilemma&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;usda&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nal.usda.gov/awic/legislat/usdaleg1.htm |title=Animal Welfare Act |author=United State Department of Agriculture |date=2003-08-21 |accessdate=2007-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Humane Society of the United States, thousands of puppy mills are located around the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;hsus_faq&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://stoppuppymills.org/frequently_asked_questions.html#6_Where_can_I_find_a_list_of_known_puppy |title=FAQs |author=Humane Society of the United States |date=2007-07-17 |accessdate=2007-12-26 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071124031432/http://www.stoppuppymills.org/frequently_asked_questions.html#6_Where_can_I_find_a_list_of_known_puppy &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; A high concentration of both puppy mills and breeders has been reported to be in the states of [[Pennsylvania]], [[Arkansas]], [[Kansas]], Nebraska and [[Missouri]].&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.turlochkennels.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=21&amp;Itemid=18&amp;rft_val_format=info:ofi/fmt:kev:mtx:ctx&amp;rft_dat=10E4D24055CCA0A0&amp;svc_dat=InfoWeb:aggregated4&amp;req_dat=AA98CDC331574F0ABEAFF732B33DC0B2 |title=Curbing the Puppy Trade: Dog lovers are divided over new efforts to ensure that all breeders treat their pooches humanely |date=2005-12-12 |author=Hamilton, Anita |publisher=Time}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Lancaster County, PA, has the highest concentration of puppy mills of any county in the nation and has earned the dubious nickname of “Puppy Mill Capital of the East.”

== Hobby breeders ==

[[File:Puppy mill 01.JPG|thumb|left|Miniature breeds at a US puppy mill]]

The term &quot;puppy mill&quot; has been widely used by [[list of animal rights groups|animal rights group]]s in protests against breeders who have substandard breeding conditions. Such breeders, sometimes labeled hobby breeders, are often cited by animal rights groups as puppy mills. Hobby breeders claim that emotional rhetoric, sensationalism, and pictures of dirty kennels are used to justify additional legislation or additional restrictive licensing that travels well beyond the initial goal of removing dogs from truly deplorable conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;canis_major_dilemma&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.canismajor.com/dog/puppymil.html |title=Just what is a puppy mill? |accessdate=2007-12-14 |year=2007 |author=Canis Major Publications}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some hobby breeders argue that many attempts to legislate puppy mills would put them out of business. Many hobby breeders argue the laws, which often require extra paperwork and inspections, would be more of a nuisance than help in shutting down puppy mills. Such breeders often cite existing [[lemon law]]s for puppies as sufficient protection for both dogs and prospective buyers.&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot; /&gt;

== Media coverage ==

On May 29, 2008, [[MSNBC]] aired a report about puppy mills, in which talk show host [[Oprah Winfrey]] revealed an industry fraught with problems and apparent cruelty. The broadcast showed puppy mills with small cages, with [[chicken wire]] floors, stacked in rows from floor to ceiling, and stated that many dogs spend their entire lives within these tiny cages. Many of these dogs are sold on the [[internet]] or by [[pet store|pet retailers]] to buyers who are unaware of the dogs' backgrounds. The report claimed that customers who object to this treatment of puppies unknowingly allow the industry to thrive.{{Clarify|date=February 2010}} It also pointed out that many of the puppy mill bred dogs suffer long-term health problems.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.alv.org.au/issues/puppyfactories.php&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legislative response ==

=== United States of America ===

In the [[United States]], some elements of the dog breeding industry are regulated by the [[Animal Welfare Act of 1966|Animal Welfare Act]] of August 24,&amp;nbsp;1966.&lt;ref name=&quot;awa&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nal.usda.gov/awic/legislat/usdaleg1.htm |date=2003-08-21 |accessdate=2008-01-03 |title=Animal Welfare Act and Regulations |author=Animal Welfare Information Center - United States Department of Agriculture - Agricultural Research Service - National Agricultural Library}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years, state legislatures have passed new laws aimed at eliminating the worst abuses at puppy mills. New laws include limits on the number of breeding females, requirements that facilities be licensed and inspected, and requirements that dogs be given proper veterinary care. Louisiana, Pennsylvania and Virginia passed puppy mill laws in 2008, and 10 states passed laws in 2009 to crack down on abusive puppy mills. In 2010, Missouri voters passed Proposition B, the &quot;Puppy Mill Cruelty Prevention Act&quot;, which establishes minimum standards of humane care and limits breeders to 50 intact dogs. &lt;ref name=&quot;new laws&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.humanesociety.org/news/press_releases/2010/03/iowa_puppy_mill_bill_signed_030910.html |date=2010-03-09 | access date+2009-03-18 |title=Iowa Gov. Culver Signs Bill to Combat Puppy Mills | author=The Humane Society of the United States}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, voters experienced push-back from the industry in the state of Missouri.  Dog breeders and other farmers, worried about costly animal welfare measures spreading to their farms, pressured the state to repeal the law.  In April 2011 Proposition B was repealed.&lt;ref name=&quot;puppy mill politics&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/living/2015150141_webanimal.html|date=2011-05-25 | title=Missouri's puppy mill politics: dog breeders outmaneuver animal-rights movement | author=Pamela M. Prah, stateline.org |work=The Seattle Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

A compromise, dubbed the ''Missouri Solution'', was signed by Missouri Governor Jay Nixon.&lt;ref name=&quot;missouri solution&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stltoday.com/news/local/metro/article_6e5b5f7e-96ad-11e0-982f-0019bb30f31a.html|date=2011-06-14 | title=State Officials Outline New Dog Breeding Law | author=Joel Currier St. Louis Post Dispatch}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

It retained some of the provisions of Proposition B, and made available some state funding for inspections.  Humane Society of Missouri President Kathy Warnick reacted favorably, seeing a step in the right direction for animal welfare&lt;ref name=&quot;missouri solution&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stltoday.com/news/local/metro/article_6e5b5f7e-96ad-11e0-982f-0019bb30f31a.html|date=2011-06-14 | title=State Officials Outline New Dog Breeding Law | author=Joel Currier St. Louis Post Dispatch}}&lt;/ref&gt;.  

Detractors, which include the President and CEO of the Humane Society of the United States, point to the &quot;shameful&quot; overturn of the voter's will to weaken Propsition B.&lt;ref name=&quot;shameful&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kplr11.com/news/kplr-humane-society-president-prop-b-pacelle-061511,0,7162016.story|date=2011-06-15 | title=Humane Society President Calls Prop B Overturn, &quot;Shameful&quot; | author=KPLR.11.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

“Lawmakers should never have substituted their judgment for the people of Missouri and gutted core provisions of Prop B,” said Wayne Pacelle, president and CEO of the Humane Society of the United States. “The so-called compromise was not about protecting animals, it was about placating agri-business.”&lt;ref name=&quot;missouri solution&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stltoday.com/news/local/metro/article_6e5b5f7e-96ad-11e0-982f-0019bb30f31a.html|date=2011-06-14 | title=State Officials Outline New Dog Breeding Law | author=Joel Currier St. Louis Post Dispatch}}&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Below is a set of lists describing some of the key differences between Proposition B and the so-called ''Missouri Solution''.&lt;ref name=&quot;puppy mill politics&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/living/2015150141_webanimal.html|date=2011-05-25 | title=Missouri's puppy mill politics: dog breeders outmaneuver animal-rights movement | author=Pamela M. Prah, stateline.org |work=The Seattle Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Proposition B''' (approved by Missouri voters in November, 2010)	
''Wire flooring for cages eliminated by November 2011; ''	
''Maximum allowable breeding females per business = 50; ''
''Cage height = taller than any dog standing erect; ''	
''Maximum number of times a female may be bred within 18 months time = 2; ''	
''Larger enclosures by November 2011.''	

'''the “Missouri Solution”''' (compromise law signed by Missouri Gov. Jay Nixon, April 2011, after repealing Proposition B)
''No wire flooring for new enclosures in  2016, existing wire flooring permitted to remain indefinitely; ''
''No limit on number of breeding females; ''
''No restriction on cage height; ''
''No restrictions on how often females are impregnated; ''
''Larger enclosures in 2016.''


=== Australia ===

Sydney Lord Mayor Clover Moore has responded to the problem of puppy mills in [[Australia]] by proposing the Animals Regulation of Sale Bill.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.leadtheway.org.au/aboutthebill.html About the Bill | Lead The Way | Support the Animals (Regulation of Sale) Bill | Animal Welfare | Against Puppy Farms&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It would ban the sale of dogs through pet shops, the internet or newspapers. The aim is to crack down on impulse purchases and shut down unregistered backyard breeders. These breeders should no longer easily profit from the sale of the dogs and the number of unwanted and abandoned animals could drop.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://www.leadtheway.org.au/clovermoore.html Clover Moore | Lead The Way | Support the Animals (Regulation of Sale) Bill | Animal Welfare | Against Puppy Farms&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Opposition to the bill comes from the Australian Veterinary Association and the Pet Industry Association. They say that the bill makes no difference to shelter admissions or euthanasia rates.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://news.ninemsn.com.au/article.aspx?id=580080 'Puppy mills' under fire for cruelty&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some claim that the bill will only serve to push unregistered breeders further underground.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

In [[New South Wales]] alone, more than 60,000 animals are put down each year.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt; Australia-wide the number is over a quarter of a million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sunday.ninemsn.com.au/sunday/cover_stories/article_2476.asp Death Row Pets&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== United Kingdom ===

In 1996, Britain passed [[List of Acts of the Parliament of the United Kingdom, 1980–1999|the Breeding and Sale of Dogs Act]] which requires annual veterinary inspections for anyone breeding five or more litters in one year. Breeding females are restricted to one litter per year and six per lifetime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://cfhs.ca/info/puppy_mill_victory_in_uk/|title=Puppy Mill Victory in UK|date=Spring 2000|accessdate=2009-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Breeders who choose to be members of the UK [[Kennel club|Kennel Club]] are required to register purebred puppies for sale with that organization and must certify the conditions under which the puppies were raised.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/download/375/form1.pdf Litter registration form]&lt;/ref&gt; Breeders who sell puppies by misrepresenting these standards may be liable to prosecution under the Sale of Goods Act 1979.

== See also ==

* [[Factory farming]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Dog breeding]]
[[Category:Animal cruelty]]

[[nl:Broodfokker]]
[[pl:Pseudohodowla]]
[[fi:Pentutehtailu]]
[[zh:繁殖場]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
