<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25903744" ns="0" title="Verona Porta Nuova railway station"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Italy station
|name         = Verona Porta Nuova
|image        = Stazione Verona.jpg
|caption      = The station and city bus stop.
|locale       = Piazzale 25 Aprile, 6&lt;br&gt;37138 Verona
|comune       = [[Verona]]
|province     = [[Province of Verona|Verona]]
|region       = [[Veneto]]
|line         = [[Milan–Venice railway|Milan–Venice]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Verona–Bologna railway|Verona–Bologna]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Brenner railway|Verona–Innsbruck]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Verona–Mantua–Modena railway|Verona–Mantua–Modena]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Verona–Legnago–Rovigo railway|Verona–Legnago–Rovigo]]
|distance     = 
|elevation    = 
|coordinates  = {{coord|45.429167|N|10.982222 |E |type:railwaystation_region:IT-VR |display=inline,title|format=dms}}
|opened       = 1851&lt;!--{Start date|1851|||df=y}}--&gt;
|architect    = 
|electrified  = 
|rebuilt      = 
|closed       = 
|platforms    = 
|owner        = [[Rete Ferroviaria Italiana]]
|manager      = [[Grandi Stazioni]]
|operator     = [[Trenitalia]]
|iata         = 
|services = [[File:Feature parking.svg|20px|parking]]&lt;!-- [[File:RWB-RWBA Information.svg|20px|Information]]--&gt; [[File:Feature ticket office.svg|20px|tickets]] [[File:Italian traffic signs - sottopassaggio pedonale.svg|20px|pedestrian underpass]] [[File:Aiga escalator.svg|20px|escalators]] [[File:Feature elevators.svg|20px|elevators]] &lt;!--[[File:Feature accessible.svg|20px|disabled access]] [[File:Euro symbol.svg|20px|cash machine]]&lt;br&gt;--&gt;[[File:RWBA Verkaufskiosk.svg|20px|cafeteria]] [[File:RWB-RWBA Gasthaus.svg|20px|restaurant]] [[File:News.svg|20px|newsstand]] [[File:RWBA WC.svg|20px|WC]] [[File:Aiga taxi.svg|20px|taxi stand]] [[File:Feature suburban buses.svg|20px|public transportation]]&lt;!-- [[File:Italian traffic signs - strada riservata ai veicoli a motore.svg|20px|car rentals]] [[File:Italian traffic signs - attraversamento ciclabile 2.svg|20px|bike rentals]]--&gt;
|airport      = 
|metro        = 
|tram         = 
|bus          = Urban / long distance / airport
|ship         = 
|location map = 
{{Location map
 |Italy | label=Verona Porta Nuova railway station
 |alt=Verona Porta Nuova railway station
 |mark=&lt;!--dot--&gt;
 |lat_deg=45|lat_min=25|lat_sec=45
 |lon_deg=10|lon_min=58|lat_sec=56
 |position=
 |width=250
 |float=center
}}
|map locator  = 
|map loc cap  = 
|}}

'''Verona Porta Nuova''' is the main railway station of the Italian city of [[Verona]] near the city centre in the square of ''Piazzale 25 Aprile''. It was originally opened in 1852, but was substantially rebuilt between 1910 and 1922. It was rebuilt again between 1946 and 1949 after being largely destroyed by allied bombing during [[World War II]]. The station serves a number of lines including to [[Milan–Venice railway|Milan, Venice]], [[Verona–Bologna railway|Bologna]] and [[Brenner railway|the Brenner pass]].  It currently handles 25 million passengers annually. Work has recently begun in preparation for it being linked to the [[Milan–Verona high-speed railway]] (on which work is now beginning) and the [[Verona–Venice high-speed railway]] (on which planning is under way).

==History==
The first train arrived at Verona Porta Nuova station, in 1852, driven by the locomotive &quot;Verona&quot; on the [[Milan–Venice railway|new line from Venice]] and crossing the [[Adige]] river on a bridge that had just been completed. As early as 1853 it was possible to go from the station to [[Mantua]] via a single track line and in the same year work started in the station on the construction of the [[Brenner railway]]. The first station was built as a temporary wooden structure in 1851 but was replaced in 1852 by a small masonry building. This building has an odd shape, with part of its front further forward that the other and with unequal sides, one with eight arched openings, and the other with only three openings. At first the station was less important than [[Verona Porta Vescovo railway station|Porta Vescovo station]], which was near a major [[Austrian Empire|Austrian]] military camp. At the time Verona was one of the main military strongholds of Europe with a capacity of 120,000 troops.  It was initially used only by the two of the three classes of passenger trains then in use in Italy: &quot;omnibus&quot; and &quot;mixed&quot; trains. It did not handle the fastest and most expensive &quot;direct&quot; trains or offer baggage services.

[[Verona–Mantua–Modena railway|A line]] was opened to [[Porto Mantovano|Sant'Antonio Mantovano]] north of the [[Mincio]] river near [[Mantua]] in 1853 and was connected through to Modena in 1874, where it connected with [[Milan–Bologna railway|the line to Bologna]]. The line from Venice was extended to [[Brescia]] and [[Bergamo]] in 1854. The Brenner railway to [[Bolzano]] in 1859 and was extended to [[Innsbruck]] in 1867. The construction of these railways gave further  impetus to the expansion of the massive Austrian defences in Verona until the transfer of [[Veneto]] to Italy as a result of the [[Third Italian War of Independence]]. The [[Verona–Legnago–Rovigo railway|line to Rovigo]] opened in 1877.  A [[Verona–Bologna railway|more direct line to Bologna]] was opened in 1924.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=L.|last=Facchinelli|title= La ferrovia Verona-Brennero. Storia della linea e delle stazioni nel territorio (The Verona–Bologna railway, history of the line and its stations)|year=1995|publisher=Athesia|location=Bolzano|language=Italian| pages=86–88}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=trenidicarta&gt;{{cite web | title=Chronological overview of the opening of railway lines from 1839 to 31 December 1926|publisher= Trenidicarta.it |url=http://www.trenidicarta.it/aperture.html |language=Italian |accessdate=22 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the absorption of Veneto into Italy in 1866 the Milan–Venice railway came, under the management of the [[Società per le strade ferrate dell'Alta Italia|Upper Italian Railways]]. The early 19th century station was no longer sufficient to handle traffic. It was to make Porta Nuova the main station. In 1900 it was temporarily enlarged with a central wooden building, while projects were being developing for the new station. Initially it was envisaged as including six platforms with several other tracks for the storage of rollingstock and for freight train operations. On 31 December 1915 a  contract was signed for the building of work for with an estimated cost of 8 million [[Italian lira|lire]], including a temporary building for passenger services.

Work on building the new station, designed by the architect Dini, began in 1910 and the station was opened in 1913, although in a preliminary form. The proposed building would be 114 metres long and 20 metres high, with a central dome and two smaller buildings on its side, with a canopy along its facade. The central section would have included the ticket office and luggage facility; there would have been a waiting room on the left was and a buffet the right. Offices would have occupied the second floor. However, the plans were not popular in Verona.

By early 1915 work was well advanced. The new freight facilities were already in operation, including the commissioning of a large goods yard and locomotive depot. The outbreak of [[Italy in World War I|World War I]] stopped work of the station and its opening was delayed until 22 March 1922. Its interior was decorated with mosaics by the master mosaic artist Amedeo Mantellato of Venice. In 1920s a connection was built between the Brenner line and the goods yard, while in 1930s a new depot for locomotives was built. Electrification of the lines was completed  in 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=L.|last=Facchinelli|title= La ferrovia Verona-Brennero. Storia della linea e delle stazioni nel territorio (The Verona–Bologna railway, history of the line and its stations)|year=1995|publisher=Athesia|location=Bolzano|language=Italian| pages=89–96}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Italian Railways|first=P. M. |last=Kalla-Bishop | year=1971 |publisher= David &amp; Charles|location =Newton Abbott, Devon, England | isbn=0-7153-5168-0 |page=113 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The station was partially destroyed by bombing during [[Military history of Italy during World War II|World War II]]. The first isolated bombing raid of the station was carried out by a formation of four aircraft on 21 October 1940 and consisted of cluster bombs and incendiaries. In total, the city suffered twenty bombing raids. The hardest attacks on the railway station and the city were on 4 and 28 January 1945. Eventually the station was rendered unusable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=L.|last=Facchinelli|title= La ferrovia Verona-Brennero. Storia della linea e delle stazioni nel territorio (The Verona–Bologna railway, history of the line and its stations)|year=1995|publisher=Athesia|location=Bolzano|language=Italian| pages=97–98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The station was then rebuilt on the same site to a design by the architect [[Roberto Narducci]], with reconstruction beginning in September 1946. The new station, aesthetically very different from the original, though structurally similar, was completed in March 1949. In the building many types of marble from Verona were used, covering an area of 4,000 m²; the floors were laid out with mosaics composed of ceramic tiles and the furniture was installed that was designed to harmonise with the building.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=G.|last=Priante|title=L'Arena e Verona: 140 anni di storia (The Arena and Verona: 140 years of history)|year=2006|publisher=Athesis|location=Verona|language=Italian| page=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=fs&gt;{{cite web | title= Verona Porta Nuova |work=Italy’s major stations | publisher=[[Ferrovie dello Stato]] | url= http://www.grandistazioni.it/cms/v/index.jsp?vgnextoid=e3ea644f4419a110VgnVCM1000003f16f90aRCRD |accessdate= 22 January 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The new station carried over from the previous station a gap between its elevated platforms and the level of the pedestrian areas outside the station. This peculiarity has forced services to be organised on two floors: on the ground floor there are services for business travellers and the public, while rail-related services are on the upper floor. The platforms have metal roofs in [[Art Nouveau]]  style, even those that survived from the previous station, while the roofs of the central and two lateral buildings are made of [[reinforced concrete]]. The current station does not include any elements of historical and architectural heritage.

==Passenger node==
[[File:Veronaportanuova.jpg|thumb|Platforms]]
Verona Porta Nuova is used by about 68 thousand passengers each day, for a total of 25 million users annually, and it is the ninth busiest train station in Italy.&lt;ref name=fs/&gt; The station area is the centre of the transport network, incorporating urban and suburban [[public transport]]: the complex is located near the major bus terminal of the Verona public transport company (“Azienda Trasporti Verona”, ATV) which connects Verona with towns in the provinces of Verona and the Veneto. In the future it will also probably connect to the town centre by [[trolleybus]].

==Station==
The Verona Porta Nuova station is built on several levels:&lt;ref name=fs/&gt;
*the basement is occupied by ''Ferrovie dello Stato'' offices;
*the ground floor is composed of several buildings, including passenger services. The side next to the square is occupied by commercial activities and passenger services, while there are technical rooms and offices in the other buildings on the west side;
*the platform level is used for passenger services;
*the first and second floor are occupied by offices.

==The future==
The station was included in the program of rehabilitation of the main Italian stations, carried out by Grandi Stazioni, a subsidiary of FS. It must be renovated under the guidelines for the to the [[Milan–Verona high-speed railway]] (on which work is now beginning) and the [[Verona–Venice high-speed railway]] (on which planning is under way). The area managed by Grandi Stazioni, extends over an area of 127,500 m², with buildings occupying 22,840 m². Of these, 2730 m² will be involved in the first phase of renovation.&lt;ref name=fs/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Railway stations in Italy]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commonscat-inline|Verona Porta Nuova train station|Verona Porta Nuova railway station}}

&lt;br&gt;
{{Grandi Stazioni}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Verona Porta Nuova Railway Station}}
[[Category:Railway stations in Veneto]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Verona|Porta Nuova railway station]]

[[it:Stazione di Verona Porta Nuova]]
[[hu:Verona Porta Nuova]]
[[nl:Station Verona Porta Nuova]]
[[pl:Verona Porta Nuova]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
