<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="25969016" ns="0" title="Amir Dossal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Wikify|date=February 2011}}

'''Amir A. Dossal''' (born September 29, 1950), a British chartered accountant, is Founder and Chairman of the [http://www.globalpf.org Global Partnerships Forum], a new global initiative to address economic &amp; social challenges through innovative partnerships. He qualified from Deloitte, Haskins &amp; Sells, London in 1975 and lives in [[New York]]. He is married to Tas Dossal, and the couple has one son, Zecki. Amir is also Co-Initiator of the [http://www.pearlinitiative.org Pearl Initiative], which promotes transparency and accountability in the Gulf Region. He is also Special Representative of the Secretary-General of the [http://www.itu.int International Telecommunication Union] for Global Partnerships. Mr. Dossal was recently appointed Ambassador for [http://www.peace-sport.org/index.php?lang=en Peace and Sport] by H.S.H. Prince Albert II of Monaco, Patron of the organization, and by Joël Bouzou, its President and Founder.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.peace-sport.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=342%3Aamir-dossal-devient-ambassadeur-de-peace-and-sport&amp;catid=14%3Aactualites&amp;lang=en&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 2010 Amir Dossal, together with Mr. Feike Sijbesma, CEO [http://www.dsm.com/en_US/html/home/dsm_home.cgi DSM], received the prestigious Humanitarian Award of the [http://www.unanyc.org United Nations Association of New York] for their accomplishments in Partnerships to End Poverty and World Hunger.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unanyc.org/news/2010/20101021_unany_awards_dinner.html&lt;/ref&gt;   



==Activities==
Until very recently, Amir was the United Nation’s Chief Liaison for Partnerships&lt;ref&gt;http://www.un.org/partnerships/&lt;/ref&gt;. He developed strategic alliances with governments, corporations, foundations and philanthropists to achieve the Millennium Development Goals. One of Amir’s many responsibilities was as the UN's Representative for the partnership with media mogul Ted Turner's $1 billion donation, through the [http://www.unfoundation.org/ UN Foundation], supporting over 450 programmes and projects for women and children’s health; population; climate change; and biodiversity. This partnership attracted social investments of over $560 million from other donors and partners, such as American Red Cross, Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, Coca-Cola, Rockefeller Foundation, Rotary International etc. In addition, Amir oversaw management of the [http://www.un.org/democracyfund/ UN Democracy Fund], which he established in 2005, to strengthen institutions and enhance democratic governance in new or restored democracies. 

Amir works globally across sectors, including Health, Education, Environment, Peace, Security and Human Rights. He has built strong links with governments, multilateral agencies, business group, foundations and networks, such as the [http://www.arabfoundationsforum.org Arab Foundations Forum], [http://www.bciu.org Business Council for International Understanding], Chambers of Commerce, [http://www.cwpf.org.cn China World Peace Foundation], [http://www.corporatephilanthropy.org Committee Encouraging Corporate Philanthropy], [http://www.cbcglobal.org Commonwealth Business Council], [http://www.efc.be European Foundation Centre], Foreign Policy Association, [http://www.internationalsport.com Institute for International Sport], [http://www.idpfoundation.org IDP Foundation], [http://www.icaew.com Institute of Chartered Accountants in England &amp; Wales], [http://www.ltbfoundation.org LTB Foundation], [http://www.nepadbusinessgroup.org NEPAD Business Group], [http://www.rbf.org Rockefeller Brothers Fund], [http://www.synergos.org The Synergos Institute], [http://www.unanyc.org United Nations Associations], [http://www.uscib.org US Council for International Business], US Department of State, etc. 

Amir has spearheaded the UN's engagement with leaders in the finance, technology and pharmaceutical sectors, including 3Com, BT, Cisco, Ericsson, Google, GSK, Merck, Microsoft, Nestle, Novartis, Pfizer, Standard Chartered Bank, Telefonica, Vodafone, and Walmart. He also works with high-profile personalities to support humanitarian causes, such as the Countess Sondes, [http://www.cherieblairfoundation.org Cherie Blair], [http://www.thegeenadavisinstitute.org Geena Davis], the Duchess of York, [http://www.happyheartsfund.org Petra Němcová]&lt;ref&gt;Amir Dossal is a member of the Advisory Board of the Happy Hearts Fund; http://www.happyheartsfund.org/advisory-board.php&lt;/ref&gt;, Julia Ormond, Joan Rivers, Russell Simmons, Joss Stone, Christy Turlington Burns, and others.  Since 2010 he has also served as a Commissioner for the [[Broadband Commission for Digital Development]] which leverages broadband technologies as a key enabler for social and economic development&lt;ref&gt;http://www.broadbandcommission.org/commissioners.html&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Since joining the United Nations in 1985, Amir has led a number of new initiatives: 
1997: Set-up the Management Policy Office to oversee reform within the United Nations. 
1999: Established the UN Fund for International Partnerships, as the interface for the UN Foundation. 
2004: Set-up Diaspora Networks for Africa and the Caribbean, to promote innovation &amp; investments. 
2005: Established the UN Democracy Fund. 
2006: Set-up the Peace-Building Support Office to spur development in post-conflict countries. 
2007: Established the UN Office for Partnerships, to oversee multiple partnership functions. 
2007: Created a Business Advisory Council for Greater Tumen Region, to attract investment in NE Asia. 
2008: Launched Digital Health Initiative focused on m-health applications &amp; services, and telemedicine. 
2008: Spearheaded key report of public &amp; private sector commitments for MDG Summit ($1.6 billion). 
2009: Substantially increased UN engagement with private sector and civil society in the Middle East. 
2009: Launched several new initiatives in Arts, Culture and Inter-Faith. 

Prior to joining the United Nations, he worked in business for over 15 years. He has lived and worked in Asia, the Caribbean, Europe, Middle East, and North America. Amir regularly undertakes speaking engagements, and serves on several non-profit boards.

Amir Dossal is today an Ambassador for [[Peace and Sport]], a [[Monaco]]-based international organization,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.peace-sport.org/ Peace and Sport]&lt;/ref&gt; committed to serving peace in the world through sport.

==References==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*http://www.globalpf.org
*http://www.pearlinitiative.org
* http://www.un.org/partnerships/

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Dossal, Amir
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = September 29, 1950
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dossal, Amir}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1950 births]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
