<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26034" ns="0" title="René Magritte"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Magritte|the asteroid named after the artist|7933 Magritte}}
{{Infobox artist
| name = René Magritte
| image = Wolleh magritte.jpg
| imagesize = 220px
| caption = Portrait of Magritte by [[Lothar Wolleh]], 1967
| birth_name = René François Ghislain Magritte
| birth_date = {{birth date|1898|11|21|df=y}}
| birth_place = [[Lessines]], [[Belgium]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|1967|8|15|1898|11|21|df=y}}
| death_place = [[Brussels]], [[Belgium]]
| nationality = [[Demographics of Belgium|Belgian]]
| field = [[Painting|Painter]]
| training =
| movement = [[Surrealism]]
| works = [[The Treachery of Images]]&lt;br /&gt;[[On the Threshold of Liberty]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Son of Man]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Empty Mask]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Difficult Crossing]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Human Condition (painting)|The Human Condition]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Not to be Reproduced]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Time Transfixed]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Elective Affinities (painting)|Elective Affinities]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Portrait (painting)|The Portrait]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Golconda (painting)|Golconda]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Mysteries of the Horizon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[The Menaced Assassin]]
| patrons =
| awards =
}}
'''René François Ghislain Magritte'''[[#Notes|&lt;sup&gt;[p]&lt;/sup&gt;
]] (21 November 1898 – 15 August 1967) was a [[List of Belgians|Belgian]] [[surrealist]] artist. He became well known for a number of witty and thought-provoking images.  His work challenges observers' preconditioned perceptions of reality.

==Early life and career==
Magritte was born in [[Lessines]], in the province of [[Hainaut (province)|Hainaut]], in 1898, the eldest son of Léopold Magritte, who was a [[tailor]] and textile merchant,&lt;ref name=&quot;Meuris216&quot;&gt;Meuris 1991, p 216.&lt;/ref&gt; and Régina ([[née]] Bertinchamps), a [[Hatmaking|milliner]] until her marriage.  Little is known about Magritte's early life. He began lessons in drawing in 1910. On 12 March 1912, his mother committed [[suicide]] by [[drowning]] herself in the [[Sambre|River Sambre]].  This was not her first attempt; she had made many over a number of years, driving her husband Léopold to lock her into her bedroom.  One day she escaped, and was missing for days. She was later discovered a mile or so down the nearby river, dead. According to a legend, 13-year-old Magritte was present when her body was retrieved from the water, but recent research has discredited this story, which may have originated with the family nurse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cal9&quot;&gt;Calvocoressi 1990, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; Supposedly, when his mother was found, her dress was covering her face, an image that has been suggested as the source of several of Magritte's paintings in 1927–1928 of people with cloth obscuring their faces, including ''Les Amants''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nga&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nga.gov.au/International/Catalogue/Detail.cfm?IRN=148052 |title=National Gallery of Australia &amp;#124; Les Amants [The lovers&amp;#93; |publisher=Nga.gov.au |date= |accessdate=2010-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Magritte's earliest paintings, which date from about 1915, were [[Impressionism|Impressionistic]] in style.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cal9&quot; /&gt; From 1916 to 1918, he studied at the [[Académie Royale des Beaux-Arts]] in [[Brussels]], under [[Constant Montald]], but found the instruction uninspiring. The paintings he produced during the years 1918–1924 were influenced by  [[Futurism]] and by the offshoot of [[Cubism]] practiced by [[Jean Metzinger|Metzinger]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cal9&quot; /&gt; Most of his works of this period are female nudes.

In 1922, Magritte married [[Georgette Berger]], whom he had met as a child in 1913.&lt;ref name=&quot;Meuris216&quot; /&gt;  From December 1920 until September 1921, Magritte served in the Belgian infantry in the Flemish town of Beverlo near [[Leopoldsburg]].
In 1922–1923, he worked as a [[draughtsman]]  in a [[wallpaper]] factory, and was a poster and advertisement designer until 1926, when a contract with Galerie le Centaure in [[Brussels]] made it possible for him to paint full-time. In 1926, Magritte produced his first surreal painting, ''The Lost Jockey'' (''Le jockey perdu''), and held his first exhibition in Brussels in 1927. Critics heaped abuse on the exhibition. [[Depression (mood)|Depressed]] by the failure, he moved to [[Paris]] where he became friends with [[André Breton]], and became involved in the [[surrealism|surrealist]] group.

[[Image:Magritte autograph.png|thumb|right|200px|Magritte's signature used on his work.]]

Galerie la Centaure closed at the end of 1929, ending Magritte's contract income. Having made little impact in Paris, Magritte returned to Brussels in 1930 and resumed working in advertising.&lt;ref&gt;Meuris 1991, p. 217.&lt;/ref&gt; He and his brother, Paul, formed an agency which earned him a living wage.

Surrealist patron [[Edward James]] allowed Magritte, in the early stages of his career, to stay rent free in his London home and paint. James is featured in two of Magritte's pieces, ''Le Principe du Plaisir (The Pleasure Principle)'' and ''La Reproduction Interdite'', a painting also known as ''[[Not to be Reproduced]]''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Professor Bram Hammacher&quot;, The Edward James Foundation souvenir guide, edited Peter Sarginson, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[World War II#1940: Denmark and Norway, France and Low Countries, Baltic Republics, Britain and Atlantic, Greece|German occupation]] of Belgium in [[World War II]] he remained in Brussels, which led to a break with Breton. He briefly adopted a colorful, painterly style in 1943–44, an interlude known as his &quot;[[Pierre Auguste Renoir|Renoir]] Period&quot;, as a reaction to his feelings of alienation and abandonment that came with living in German-occupied Belgium. In 1946, renouncing the violence and [[pessimism]] of his earlier work, he joined several other Belgian artists in signing the manifesto ''Surrealism in Full Sunlight''.&lt;ref&gt;Meuris 1991, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; During 1947–48, Magritte's  &quot;Vache Period&quot;, he painted in a provocative and crude [[Fauvism|Fauve]] style. During this time, Magritte supported himself through the production of fake [[Picasso]]s, [[Georges Braque|Braque]]s and [[Giorgio de Chirico|Chirico]]s—a fraudulent repertoire he was later to expand into the printing of forged banknotes during the lean postwar period.  This venture was undertaken alongside his brother Paul Magritte and fellow Surrealist and 'surrogate son' [[Marcel Mariën]], to whom had fallen the task of selling the forgeries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/ceci-nest-pas-an-artist-1147477.html | work=The Independent | location=London | title=Ceci n'est pas an artist | first=Andrew | last=Lambith | date=28 February 1998 | accessdate=22 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 1948, he returned to the style and themes of his prewar surrealistic art.

His work was exhibited in the United States in [[New York]] in 1936 and again in that city in two retrospective exhibitions, one at the [[Museum of Modern Art]] in 1965, and the other at the [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]] in 1992.

Magritte died of [[pancreatic cancer]] on 15 August 1967 in his own bed, aged 68, and was interred in [[Schaerbeek Cemetery]], [[Evere]], Brussels.

Popular interest in Magritte's work rose considerably in the 1960s, and his imagery has influenced [[Pop art|pop]], [[Minimalist art|minimalist]] and [[conceptual art]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Calvocoressi 1990, p. 26&quot;&gt;Calvocoressi 1990, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005 he came 9th in the [[French Community of Belgium|Walloon]] version of ''[[De Grootste Belg]]'' (''The Greatest Belgian''); in the [[Flanders|Flemish]] version he was 18th.

==Philosophical and artistic gestures==

{{cquote2|It is a union that suggests the essential mystery of the world. Art for me is not an end in itself, but a means of evoking that mystery.|René Magritte on putting seemingly unrelated objects together in juxtaposition&lt;ref&gt;Glueck, Grace, &quot;A Bottle Is a Bottle&quot;; ''[[The New York Times]]'', December 19, 1965&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Magritte's work frequently displays a collection of ordinary objects in an unusual context, giving new meanings to familiar things. The  use of objects as other than what they seem is typified in his painting, ''[[The Treachery of Images]]'' (''La trahison des images''), which shows a [[smoking pipe (tobacco)|pipe]] that looks as though it is a model for a tobacco store advertisement. Magritte painted below the pipe &quot;Ceci n'est pas une pipe&quot; (&quot;This is not a pipe&quot;), which seems a contradiction, but is actually true: the painting is not a pipe, it is an ''image'' of a pipe. It does not &quot;satisfy emotionally&quot;—when Magritte once was asked about this image, he replied that of course it was not a pipe, just try to fill it with tobacco.&lt;ref&gt;Spitz 1994, p.47&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Magritte675.jpg|thumb|Image of pipe and passport of René Magritte]]
[[File:Fr-Ceci-n-est-pas-une-pipe.ogg|right]]
Magritte used the same approach in a painting of an apple: he painted the fruit and then used an internal caption or framing device to deny that the item was an apple. In these &quot;Ceci n'est pas&quot; works, Magritte points out that no matter how closely, through realism-art, we come to depicting an item accurately, we never do catch the item itself.

Among Magritte's works are a number of surrealist versions of other famous paintings. Elsewhere, Magritte challenges the difficulty of artwork to convey meaning with a recurring motif of an easel, as in his ''The Human Condition'' series (1933, 1935) or ''The Promenades of Euclid'' (1955) (wherein the spires of a castle are &quot;painted&quot; upon the ordinary streets which the canvas overlooks). In a letter to André Breton, he wrote of ''The Human Condition'' that it was irrelevant if the scene behind the easel differed from what was depicted upon it, &quot;but the main thing was to eliminate the difference between a view seen from outside and from inside a room.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Sylvester 1992, p.298&lt;/ref&gt; The windows in some of these pictures are framed with heavy drapes, suggesting a theatrical motif.&lt;ref&gt;Spitz 1994, p.50&lt;/ref&gt;

Magritte's style of surrealism is more representational than the [[Surrealist automatism|&quot;automatic&quot;]] style of artists such as [[Joan Miró]]. Magritte's use of ordinary objects in unfamiliar spaces is joined to his desire to create poetic imagery. He described the act of painting as &quot;the art of putting colors side by side in such a way that their real aspect is effaced, so that familiar objects—the sky, people, trees, mountains, furniture, the stars, solid structures, graffiti—become united in a single poetically disciplined image. The poetry of this image dispenses with any symbolic significance, old or new.”&lt;ref&gt;Frasnay, Daniel. The Artist’s World.  “Magritte.”  New York: The Viking Press, 1969. pp. 99-107&lt;/ref&gt;

René Magritte described his paintings as &quot;visible images which conceal nothing; they evoke mystery and, indeed, when one sees one of my pictures, one asks oneself this simple question, 'What does that mean?'. It does not mean anything, because mystery means nothing either, it is unknowable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.visitflanders.us/index.php?page=NewMagritteMuseumBrussels
|title=Flanders - New Magritte Museum Brussels |publisher=www.visitflanders.us |accessdate=2009-03-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Magritte's constant play with reality and illusion has been attributed to the early death of his mother. Psychoanalysts who have examined bereaved children have said that Magritte's back and forth play with reality and illusion reflects his &quot;constant shifting back and forth from what he wishes—'mother is alive'—to what he knows—'mother is dead' &quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Bradley I. Jr.  &quot;Psychoanalysis and Art History&quot;.  ''Art Journal'', Vol. 49, No. 2, College Art Association. pp. 182-186.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Artists influenced by Magritte==
Contemporary artists have been greatly influenced by René Magritte's stimulating examination of the fickleness of images. Some artists who have been influenced by Magritte's works include [[John Baldessari]], [[Ed Ruscha]], [[Andy Warhol]], [[Jasper Johns]], [[Vija Celmins]], [[Marcel Broodthaers]], [[Jan Verdoodt]], [[Martin Kippenberger]] and [[Storm Thorgerson]]. Some of the artists' works integrate direct references and others offer contemporary viewpoints on his abstract fixations.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document | title= Los Angeles: Magritte by Baldessari, Road Trips and Rock 'n' Roll | author=Amra Brooks | publisher=ARTINFO | date= 27 December 2006 | url=http://www.artinfo.com/news/story/24140/los-angeles-magritte-by-baldessari-road-trips-and-rock-n-roll/| accessdate=2008-04-24 | postscript= &lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Magritte's use of simple graphic and everyday imagery  has been compared to that of the [[Pop art]]ists. His influence in the development of Pop art has been widely recognized,&lt;ref name=&quot;Meuris202&quot;&gt;Meuris 1991, p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt; although Magritte himself discounted the connection. He considered the Pop artists' representation of &quot;the world as it is&quot;  as &quot;their error&quot;, and contrasted their attention to the transitory  with his concern for &quot;the feeling for the real, insofar as it is permanent.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meuris202&quot; /&gt; The 2006–2007 [[LACMA]] exhibition “Magritte and Contemporary Art: The Treachery of Images&quot; examined the relationship between Magritte and contemporary art.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document | title=Magritte and Contemporary Art: The Treachery of Images | author=Stephanie Brown | publisher=Los Angeles county Museum of Art and Ludion | year=2006 | postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
&lt;!--  A few examples suffice here to make the point that Magritte's work is often referenced in popular culture. It is neither possible nor desirable to list every pop culture reference to Magritte in this article. Wikipedia is not an indiscriminate collection of trivia; please consider whether any proposed addition will shed important new light on the subject: Magritte. Unsourced examples may be deleted as Original Research--&gt;

The 1960s brought a great increase in public awareness of Magritte's work.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calvocoressi 1990, p. 26&quot;/&gt; Thanks to his &quot;sound knowledge of how to present objects in a manner both suggestive and questioning,&quot; his works have been frequently adapted or plagiarized in advertisements, posters, book covers and the like.&lt;ref&gt;Meuris 1991, pp. 199–201.&lt;/ref&gt; Examples include album covers such as ''[[Beck-Ola]]'' by [[The Jeff Beck Group]] (reproducing Magritte's ''[[The Listening Room]]''), [[Jackson Browne]]'s 1974 album ''[[Late for the Sky]]'', with artwork inspired by Magritte's ''[[L'Empire des Lumières]]'', [[Oregon (band)|Oregon]]'s album ''[[Out of the Woods]]'' referring to ''[[Carte Blanche (painting)|Carte Blanche]]'', and the [[Firesign Theatre]]'s album ''[[Just Folks . . . A Firesign Chat]]'' based on ''[[The Mysteries of the Horizon]]''.

[[Tom Stoppard]] has written a surrealist play called ''[[After Magritte]]''.

[[Douglas Hofstadter]]'s book ''[[Gödel, Escher, Bach]]'' uses Magritte works for many of its illustrations.

[[Paul Simon]]'s song &quot;[[Rene and Georgette Magritte with Their Dog after the War]]&quot;, inspired by a photograph of Magritte by [[Lothar Wolleh]], appears on the 1983 album ''[[Hearts and Bones]]''.

Magritte's imagery has inspired [[filmmaker]]s ranging from the surrealist [[Marcel Mariën]]
to mainstream directors such as [[Jean-Luc Godard]], [[Alain Robbe-Grillet]], [[Bernardo Bertolucci]], [[Nicholas Roeg]], and [[Terry Gilliam]].&lt;ref&gt;Levy 1997, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bertolucci, Gérard, &amp; Kline 2000, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fragola &amp; Smith 1995, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Ellen Burstyn]], in the 1998 documentary ''The Fear of God: 25 Years of &quot;The Exorcist&quot;'', the iconic poster shot for the film ''[[The Exorcist (film)|The Exorcist]]'' was inspired by Magritte's ''L'Empire des Lumières''.

In 2010, the music video of ''Koolhaus'' by [[Markus Schulz]] under his Dakota guise was inspired from the works of Magritte.
&lt;!--A few examples suffice here to make the point that Magritte's work is often referenced in popular culture. It is neither possible nor desirable to list every pop culture reference to Magritte in this article. Wikipedia is not an indiscriminate collection of trivia; please consider whether any proposed addition will shed important new light on the subject: Magritte.--&gt;

==Magritte Museum==
[[File:Bruxelles Musée Magritte.jpg|thumb|left|The Magritte Museum in Brussels]]
The Magritte Museum opened to the public on 30 May 2009 in [[Brussels]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musee-magritte-museum.be Magritte Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; Housed in the five-level neo-classical Hotel Altenloh, on the Place Royale, it displays some 200 original Magritte paintings, drawings and sculptures&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.time.com/time/arts/article/0,8599,1901775,00.html| work=Time | title=Two New Museums for Tintin and Magritte | date=30 May 2009 |accessdate=2009-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; including ''The Return'', ''Scheherazade'' and ''[[The Empire of Light]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Victor Zak October 2009 page 20  Westways Magazine&lt;/ref&gt;

Another museum is located at rue Esseghem 135 in Brussels in Magritte's former home, where he lived with his wife from 1930 to 1954. A painting by Magritte was stolen from this museum on the morning of 24 September 2009 by two armed men. The robbery occurred just after 10 a.m., shortly after the museum opened.  A man rang the doorbell, inquired if visiting hours had begun, and then pointed a gun at the museum attendant while an accomplice went inside. The thieves made museum workers and visitors kneel in a courtyard while they left on foot with a 1948 painting, ''Olympia'', a nude portrait of Magritte’s wife. The two men, who spoke English and French, set off an alarm when they broke a glass plate that protected the painting, but had already escaped by the time the police arrived. The stolen work is said to be worth about $1.1 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2009/sep/24/magritte-painting-stolen-brussels-olympia The Guardian] Retrieved 24 September 2009&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/09/24/magritte-painting-stolen/ NY Times]. Retrieved 24 September 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Selected list of works==
*1920 ''Landscape''
*1922 ''The Station'' and ''L'Écuyère''
*1923 ''Self-portrait'', ''Sixth Nocturne'', ''Georgette at the Piano'' and ''Donna''
*1925 ''The Bather'' and ''The Window''
*1926 ''The Lost Jockey'', ''The Mind of the Traveler'', ''Sensational News'', ''[[The Difficult Crossing]]'', ''The Vestal's Agony'', ''The Midnight Marriage'', ''The Musings of a Solitary Walker'', ''After the Water the Clouds'', ''Popular Panorama'', ''Landscape'' and ''The Encounter''
*1927 ''Young Girl Eating a Bird'', ''The Oasis'' (started in 1925), ″Le Double Secret&quot;, ''The Meaning of Night'', ''Let Out of School'', ''The Man from the Sea'', ''The Tiredness of Life'', ''The Light-breaker'', ''A Passion for Light'', ''[[The Menaced Assassin]]'', ''Reckless Sleeper'', ''La Voleuse'', ''The Fast Hope'', ''L'Atlantide'' and ''The Muscles of the Sky''
*1928 ''The Lining of Sleep'' (started in 1927), ''Intermission'' (started in 1927), ''The Flowers of the Abyss'', ''Discovery'', ''The Lovers I &amp; II'',&lt;ref name=&quot;nga&quot; /&gt; ''The Voice of Space'', ''The Daring Sleeper'', ''The Acrobat's Ideas'', ''The Automaton'', ''[[The Empty Mask]]'', ''Reckless Sleeper'', ''The Secret Life'' and ''Attempting the Impossible''
*1929 ''[[The Treachery of Images]]'' (started in 1928), ''Threatening Weather'' and ''[[On the Threshold of Liberty]]''
*1930 ''Pink Belles, Tattered Skies'', ''The Eternally Obvious'', ''The Lifeline'', ''The Annunciation'' and ''Celestial Perfections''
*1931 ''The Voice of the Air'', ''Summer'' and ''The Giantess''
*1932 ''The Universe Unmasked''
*1933 ''[[Elective Affinities (painting)|Elective Affinities]]'', ''The Human Condition'' and ''The Unexpected Answer''
*1934 ''The Rape''
*1935 ''The Discovery of Fire'', ''[[The Human Condition (painting)|The Human Condition]]'', ''Revolution'', ''Perpetual Motion'', ''Collective Invention'', ''The False Mirror'' and ''[[The Portrait (painting)|The Portrait]]''
*1936 ''Surprise Answer'', ''Clairvoyance'', ''The Healer'', ''The Philosopher's Lamp'', ''Spiritual Exercises'', ''Portrait of Irène Hamoir'', ''La Méditation'' and ''Forbidden Literature''
*1937 ''The Future of Statues'', ''The Black Flag'', ''[[Not to be Reproduced]]'', ''Portrait of Edward James'' and ''Portrait of Rena Schitz'', ''[[On the Threshold of Liberty]]''
*1938 ''[[Time Transfixed]]'', ''The Domain of Arnheim'' and ''Steps of Summer''
*1939 ''Victory''
*1940 ''The Return'', ''The Wedding Breakfast'' and ''Les Grandes Espérances''
*1941 ''The Break in the Clouds''
*1942 ''Misses de L'Isle Adam'', ''L'Ile au Tréson'', ''Memory'', ''Black Magic'', ''Les compagnons de la peur'' and ''The Misanthropes''
*1943 ''The Return of the Flame'', ''Universal Gravitation'' and ''Monsieur Ingres's Good Days''
*1944 ''The Good Omens''
*1945 ''Treasure Island'', ''Les Rencontres Naturelles'' and ''Black Magic''
*1946 ''L'Intellience'' and ''Les Mille et une Nuits''
*1947 ''La Philosophie dans le boudoir'', ''The Cicerone'', ''The Liberator'', ''The Fair Captive'', ''La Part du Feu'' and ''The Red Model''
*1948 ''Blood Will Tell'', ''Memory'', ''The Mountain Dweller'', ''The Art of Life'', ''The Pebble'', '' The Lost Jockey'', ''God's Solon'', ''Shéhérazade'', ''L'Ellipse'' and ''Famine'' and ''The Taste of Sorrow''
*1949 ''Megalomania'', ''Elementary Cosmogany'', and ''Perspective, the Balcony''
*1950 ''Making an Entrance'', ''The Legend of the Centuries'', ''Towards Pleasure'', ''The Labors of Alexander'', ''[[The Empire of Light II]]'', ''The Fair Captive'' and ''The Art of Conversation''
*1951 ''David's Madame Récamier'' (parodying the ''[[Portrait of Madame Récamier]]''), ''Pandora's Box'', ''The Song of the Violet'', ''The Spring Tide'' and ''The Smile''
*1952 ''Personal Values'' and ''Le Sens de la Pudeur''
*1953 ''[[Golconda (painting)|Golconda]]'', ''[[The Listening Room]]'' and a fresco for the [[Knokke]] Casino
*1954 ''The Invisible World'', ''The Explanation'' and ''[[The Empire of Light]]''
*1955 ''Memory of a Journey'' and ''[[The Mysteries of the Horizon]]''
*1956 ''The Sixteenth of September''
*1957 ''The Fountain of Youth'' and ''The Enchanted Domain''
*1958 ''The Golden Legend'', ''Hegel's Holiday'', ''The Banquet'' and ''The Familiar World''
*1959 ''The Castle in the Pyrenees'', ''The Battle of the Argonne'', ''The Anniversary'', ''The Month of the Grape Harvest'' and ''The Glass Key''
*1960 ''The Memoirs of a Saint''
*1962 ''The Great Table'', ''The Healer'', ''Waste of Effort'', ''Mona Lisa'' (circa 1962) and ''L'embeillie'' (circa 1962)
*1963 ''The Great Family'', ''The Open Air'', ''The Beautiful Season'', ''Princes of the Autumn'', ''Young Love'', ''La Recherche de la Vérité'' and ''The Telescope''
*1964 ''Evening Falls'', ''The Great War'', ''[[The Son of Man]]'' and ''Song of Love''
*1965 ''Carte Blanche'', ''The Thought Which Sees'', ''Ages Ago'' and ''The Beautiful Walk'' (circa 1965)
*1966 ''The Shades'', ''The Happy Donor'', ''The Gold Ring'', ''The Pleasant Truth'', ''The Two Mysteries'', and ''The Mysteries of the Horizon''
*1967 ''Les Grâces Naturelles'', ''La Géante'', ''The Blank Page'', ''Good Connections'', ''The Art of Living'' and several bronze sculptures based on Magritte's previous works.

==See also==
{{Portal|Art}}
*[[List of Belgian painters]]

==Notes==
:&lt;small&gt;[p]&lt;/small&gt; - The name ''René Magritte'' is pronounced as &quot;Ruh-nay Ma-greet&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;C.U.S.D. Art Masterpiece Manual&quot;, Mary Lynne Lasure, p.37, web: [http://www.cusdcommunity.com/docs/artmasterpiece_completemanual.pdf CUSD-artm-PDF].&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book | author=Allmer, Patricia | title=René Magritte - Beyond Painting | location=Manchester | publisher=Manchester University Press | year=2009 | isbn=0719079284}}
*{{cite book | author=Bertolucci, Bernardo; Gérard, F. S.; Kline, T. J. | title=Bernardo Bertolucci: Interviews | location=Jackson: Miss | publisher= | year=2000 | isbn=1-5780-6205-5}}
*{{cite book | author=Calvocoressi, Richard | title=Magritte | location=New York | publisher=Watson-Guptill | year=1990 | isbn=0-8230-2962-X}}
*{{cite book | author=Fragola, Anthony; Smith, Roch C.| title=The Erotic Dream Machine: Interviews with Alain Robbe-Grillet on His Films | location= | publisher= SIU Press| year=1995 | isbn=0809320045}}
*{{cite book | author=Kaplan, Gilbert E. and Baum, Timothy | title=The Graphic Work of René Magritte | publisher=Two Editions | year=1982 | isbn=0-6863-9199-3}}
*{{cite book | author=Levy, S | title=Surrealism: Surrealist visuality | location=Edinburgh | publisher=Keele University Press | year=1997 | isbn=1853311936}}
*{{cite book | author=Meuris, Jacques | title=René Magritte | location=Cologne | publisher=Benedikt Taschen | year=1991 | isbn=3-8228-0546-7}}
*{{cite book | author=Roisin, Jacques | title=Ceci n'est pas une biographie de Magritte| location=Bruxelles| publisher=Alice Editions| year=1998 | isbn=2-930182-05-9
}}
*{{cite book | author=Spitz, Ellen Handler | title=Museums of the Mind | publisher=Yale University Press | year=1994 | isbn=0-3000-6029-7}}
*{{cite book | author=Sylvester, David | title=Magritte | publisher=Abrams | year=1992 | isbn=0-5000-9227-3}}
*{{cite book | author=West, Shearer | title=The Bullfinch Guide to Art | location=UK | publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing Plc | year=1996 | isbn=0-8212-2137-X}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikiquote}}
*[http://www.magritte.be/ Foundation Magritte]
*[http://www.all-art.org/art_20th_century/magritte1.html The biography and works of Rene Magritte]
*[http://www.magrittemuseum.be/ René Magritte Museum] in [[Brussels]]
*{{MoMAartist|3692}}
*[http://www.artcyclopedia.com/artists/magritte_rene.html Magritte at Artcyclopedia]
*[http://www.tate.org.uk/liverpool/exhibitions/renemagritte/default.shtm Rene Magritte: The Pleasure Principle - Exhibition at Tate Liverpool, UK 2011]
*[http://www.uiowa.edu/~c008g001/gallery/ University of Iowa Art Gallery]
*[http://www.fine-arts-museum.be/site/EN/default.asp Musée Magritte Museum] at [[Brussels]]
*[http://www.museumchick.com/museum-chick/2010/03/the-mus%C3%A9e-magritte-museum-brussels-surrealism.html A visit to the Musée Magritte Museum]
*[http://www.surrealismcentre.ac.uk/publications/papers/journal5/index.htm Patricia Allmer, &quot;La Reproduction Interdite: René Magritte and Forgery&quot; in ''Papers of Surrealism'', Issue 5, Spring 2007.]

{{Rene Magritte}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = Magritte, René
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Magritte, René François Ghislain
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = [[Painting|Painter]]
|DATE OF BIRTH     = 21 November 1898
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Lessines]], [[Belgium]]
|DATE OF DEATH     = 15 August 1967
|PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Brussels]], [[Belgium]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Magritte, Rene}}
[[Category:1898 births]]
[[Category:1967 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Lessines]]
[[Category:René Magritte| ]]
[[Category:Belgian artists]]
[[Category:Belgian painters]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in Belgium]]
[[Category:Deaths from pancreatic cancer]]
[[Category:Modern painters]]
[[Category:Surrealist artists]]
[[Category:Walloon people]]
[[Category:20th-century painters]]

[[ar:رينيه ماغريت]]
[[az:Rene Maqrit]]
[[zh-min-nan:René Magritte]]
[[be:Рэнэ Магрыт]]
[[be-x-old:Рэнэ Магрыт]]
[[bg:Рене Магрит]]
[[ca:René Magritte]]
[[cs:René Magritte]]
[[cy:René Magritte]]
[[da:René Magritte]]
[[de:René Magritte]]
[[et:René Magritte]]
[[el:Ρενέ Μαγκρίτ]]
[[es:René Magritte]]
[[eo:René Magritte]]
[[fa:رنه ماگریت]]
[[fr:René Magritte]]
[[gl:René Magritte]]
[[ko:르네 마그리트]]
[[hy:Ռենե Մագրիտ]]
[[hr:René Magritte]]
[[io:René Magritte]]
[[it:René Magritte]]
[[he:רנה מגריט]]
[[ka:რენე მაგრიტი]]
[[lv:Renē Magrits]]
[[lb:René Magritte]]
[[lt:René Magritte]]
[[li:René Magritte]]
[[hu:René Magritte]]
[[mk:Рене Магрит]]
[[nah:René Magritte]]
[[nl:René Magritte]]
[[ja:ルネ・マグリット]]
[[no:René Magritte]]
[[pms:René Magritte]]
[[pl:René Magritte]]
[[pt:René Magritte]]
[[ro:René Magritte]]
[[ru:Магритт, Рене]]
[[scn:René Magritte]]
[[sk:René Magritte]]
[[sl:René Magritte]]
[[fi:René Magritte]]
[[sv:René Magritte]]
[[tr:René Magritte]]
[[uk:Рене Магрітт]]
[[vi:René Magritte]]
[[wa:René Magritte]]
[[vls:René Magritte]]
[[zh:雷內·馬格利特]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
