<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26065296" ns="0" title="The Real Global Warming Disaster"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox book
| name          = The Real Global Warming Disaster
| image         = [[File:Real Global Warming Disaster book cover.jpg|200 px]]
| image_caption = Cover of the book
| author        = [[Christopher Booker]]
| country       = United Kingdom
| language      = English
| series        =
| subject       = [[Climate change]]
| genre         = [[Non-fiction]]
| publisher     = [[Continuum International Publishing Group|Continuum]]
| pub_date      = 17 October 2009
| media_type    = Print ([[Hardcover]])
| pages         = 368 pages
| isbn          = 1441110526
}}

'''''The Real Global Warming Disaster''''' (''Is The Obsession With 'Climate Change' Turning Out To Be the Most Costly Scientific Blunder In History?'') is a 2009 book by English journalist and author [[Christopher Booker]] written from a standpoint of [[environmental scepticism]] which aims to show how scientists and politicians came to believe in [[global warming|anthropogenic global warming]].

In the book, Booker seeks to combine the science of the subject with its political consequences, and writes that, as governments become poised to make radical changes in [[Energy policy|energy policies]], the [[scientific evidence]] for global warming is becoming increasingly challenged. He states that global warming is not [[scientific opinion on climate change|supported by a significant number of the world's climate scientists]], and criticises how the [[United Nations|UN]]'s [[Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change]] (IPCC) presents evidence and [[data]], citing its reliance on potentially inaccurate [[global climate models]] to make temperature projections. He concludes &quot;it begins to look very possible that the nightmare vision of our planet being doomed&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-342&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=342}}&lt;/ref&gt; may be imaginary, and that, if so, &quot;it will turn out to be one of the most expensive, destructive, and foolish mistakes the human race has ever made&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-342&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=342}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Booker in particular refers to the cost of implementing the UK's [[Climate Change Act 2008|Climate Change Act of 2008]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The book's claims were strongly criticised by [[science journalist|science writer]] [[Philip Ball]],&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2009/nov/15/real-global-warming-christopher-booker
| date = 15 November 2009
| title = The Real Global Warming Disaster by Christopher Booker
| author = [[Philip Ball]]
| work = [[The Observer]]
| accessdate = 4 February 2010
| quote = But much, including the central claim, is bunk. [...] Booker's position would require that you accept something like the following: 1) Most of the world's climate scientists, for reasons unspecified, decided to create a myth about human-induced global warming and have managed to twist endless measurements and computer models to fit their case, without the rest of the scientific community noticing. George W Bush and certain oil companies have, however, seen through the deception. 2) Most of the world's climate scientists are incompetent and have grossly misinterpreted their data and models, yet their faulty conclusions are not, as you might imagine, a random chaos of assertions, but all point in the same direction.
}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the book was praised by several [[columnist]]s. The book opens with an erroneous quotation,&lt;ref name=&quot;independent&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.independent.co.uk/environment/climate-change/fabricated-quote-used-to-discredit-climate-scientist-1894552.html
| date = 10 February 2010
| year = 2010
| title = Fabricated quote used to discredit climate scientist
| author = Steve Connor
| work = [[The Independent]]
| accessdate = 10 February 2010
| quote = The quotation has since become the iconic smoking gun of the climate sceptic community. The words are the very first to appear in the &quot;manual&quot; of climate denialism written by the journalist and arch-sceptic Christopher Booker. They get more than a 100,000 hits on Google, and are wheeled out almost every time a climate sceptic has a point to make [...]
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which Booker subsequently acknowledged and promised to correct in future editions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker retraction&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/columnists/christopherbooker/7280369/What-the-weatherman-never-said.html?state=target#postacomment&amp;postingId=7285182
| date = 20 February 2010
| title = What the weatherman never said
| author = [[Christopher Booker]]
| work = [[The Daily Telegraph]]
| accessdate = 21 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The book was [[Amazon.com|Amazon UK]]'s fourth bestselling environment book of the decade 2000-10.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/environment/damian-carrington-blog/2010/dec/17/bestselling-green-books-decade-2
| date = 17 December 2010
| year = 2010
| title = Bestselling green books of the decade
| author = Damian Carrington
| work = [[The Guardian]]
| accessdate = 12 July 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==

{{Quote box
| quoted = true
| style = width: 33em;
| quote = If one accepts the thesis that the planet faces a threat unprecedented in history, the implications are mind-boggling. But equally mind-boggling now are the implications of the price we are being asked to pay by our politicians to meet that threat. More than ever, it is a matter of the highest priority that we should know whether or not the assumptions on which the politicians base their proposals are founded on properly sound science&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker The Sunday Telegraph&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/6425269/The-real-climate-change-catastrophe.html
| date = 2 December 2009
| title = The real climate change catastrophe
| author = [[Christopher Booker]]
| work = [[The Sunday Telegraph]]
| accessdate = 5 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

| salign = right
| source = — Christopher Booker, 2009
}}
Before the book's publication, Booker wrote in ''[[The Sunday Telegraph]]'' that the motivation behind it lay in a consideration of &quot;the supposed menace of global warming—and the political response to it&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker The Sunday Telegraph&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/6425269/The-real-climate-change-catastrophe.html
| date = 2 December 2009
| title = The real climate change catastrophe
| author = [[Christopher Booker]]
| work = [[The Sunday Telegraph]]
| accessdate = 5 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the book's introduction, Booker also describes how ''The Real Global Warming Disaster'' became for him a necessary continuation of a brief analysis he had made of the anthropogenic global warming issue in his previous book, ''Scared to Death'', and followed a similar theme he had explored there, i.e., that of the media overstating the danger of an issue facing the public, and governments overreacting to the issue by passing legislation entailing considerable economic cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-4&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Synopsis ==

The book consists of three parts and an epilogue.

=== Part One: Forging the 'consensus': 1972–1997 ===
[[File:James Hansen.jpg|thumb|right|James Hansen giving testimony before the United States Congress in 1988]]
Drawing from [[Fred Singer]] and [[Dennis Avery]]'s ''[[Unstoppable Global Warming: Every 1,500 Years|Unstoppable Global Warming]]'', Booker presents a [[Information graphics|graph]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-21&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=21}}&lt;/ref&gt; showing changes in temperature and carbon dioxide concentration over the last 11,000 years. In his analysis, rising carbon dioxide concentrations in the 1970s led scientists such as [[Paul R. Ehrlich|Paul Ehrlich]] to postulate that the earth, as a result of the [[greenhouse effect]], may have been heating up or cooling down, either of which could have potentially disastrous consequences. Figures such as the environmental activist [[Maurice Strong]] and scientist [[Bert Bolin]] are then introduced, who would, according to Booker, &quot;play a crucial role in what lay ahead&quot; in influencing governmental policy and helping form the scientific basis for global warming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-32&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=32}}&lt;/ref&gt; Booker contends that 1988 was a key year in which the IPCC was set up and [[James Hansen]] appeared at the [[United States Senate Committee on Energy and Natural Resources|Senate Committee of Natural Resources]] in [[Washington, D.C.|Washington]], where he stated that he was &quot;99 percent certain&quot; that man's contribution to the greenhouse effect was the cause of global warming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-41&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Booker, &quot;on all sides 'global warming' became the cause of the moment&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-38&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt; after Hansen's appearance. He then describes how:

* in 1990, the IPCC published its [[IPCC First Assessment Report|first assessment report]] which made projections of future temperature rises;
* at the [[Earth Summit (1992)|Rio de Janeiro Earth Summit]] &quot;politicians from 154 countries queued up to sign a '[[United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change|UN Framework Convention on Climate Change']]&quot; that would &quot;commit all the signatory governments to a voluntary reduction of greenhouse gas emissions&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-53&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=53}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* the [[IPCC Second Assessment Report|second IPCC report]] (SAR) in 1995 found that the &quot;body of statistical evidence now points to a discernible human influence on the global climate&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-63&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Booker writes that the SAR was criticised by [[Frederick Seitz]], who alleged that &quot;more than 15 sections in Chapter 8 of the report—the key chapter setting out the scientific evidence for and against a human influence over climate—were changed or deleted after the scientists charged with examining this question had accepted the supposedly final text&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-65&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Part one ends with an account of the signing of the 1997 [[Kyoto Protocol]] and the setting of new targets for reduced {{chem|CO|2}} emissions.

[[File:2000 Year Temperature Comparison.png|thumb|left|250px|Northern hemisphere temperature reconstructions for the past 2,000 years]]

=== Part Two: The 'consensus' carries all before it: 1998–2007 ===
Booker begins part two by asserting that the [[Medieval Warm Period|medieval warm period]] &quot;contradicted the idea that late twentieth century temperatures had suddenly shot up to a level never known before in history&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-80&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=80}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that this problem was [[Hockey stick controversy|dealt with by a 1999 graph]] depicting temperatures &quot;suddenly shooting up in the twentieth century to a level that was quite unprecedented. Familiar features such as the Medieval Warm Period and the little ice age simply vanished&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-83&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; Booker writes that the graph became the &quot;supreme iconic image for all those engaged in the battle to save the world from global warming&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-84&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=84}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then states that the IPCC's methods, and in particular the [[IPCC Summary for Policymakers|draft summary]] of its [[IPCC Third Assessment Report|next report]], came in for serious criticism from scientists such as [[Richard Lindzen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-88&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Booker then examines [[Davis Guggenheim]]'s [[Academy Award|Oscar]]-winning film ''[[An Inconvenient Truth]]'' and the subsequent questioning of many of its assertions, including [[Retreat of glaciers since 1850|retreating glaciers]], drowning [[polar bear]]s, use of the &quot;hockey stick&quot; graph, the melting of the [[Polar ice cap|ice caps]] and snows of [[Mount Kilimanjaro|Kilimanjaro]] and [[Current sea level rise|rising sea levels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-144-150&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| pp=144–150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Part Three: The 'consensus' begins to crumble: 2007–2009 ===
[[File:HenrikSvensmark.jpg|thumb|125px|right|Henrik Svensmark, who carried out research into a link between solar and temperature trends]]

Booker begins part three by quoting the statement of the then [[Secretary of State for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs|British Environment Secretary]] that the [[IPCC Fourth Assessment Report|IPCC's fourth assessment report]] was &quot;another nail in the coffin of the climate change deniers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-173&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=173}}&lt;/ref&gt; Booker contrasts this assertion with what he sees as evidence emerging to the contrary: that the earth had in fact [[surface temperature record|begun to cool]], possibly as a result of [[solar variation]], and that {{chem|CO|2}} may thus not be the only driver of climate change. However, the results of research into this theory by the scientists Knud Lassen, [[Eigil Friis-Christensen]] and [[Henrik Svensmark]] were dismissed by Bert Bolin as &quot;scientifically extremely naïve and irresponsible&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-180&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=180}}&lt;/ref&gt; Booker then alleges that a &quot;consensus&quot; and &quot;counter-consensus&quot; had begun to form, and gives details of a 2007 report by the US Senator [[James Inhofe]] that claimed to list 400 scientists &quot;now prepared to express their dissent, sometimes in the strongest terms, from the IPCC's 'consensus' view of global warming&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-208&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=208}}&lt;/ref&gt; Booker then quotes the June 2007 [[International Energy Agency]] announcement that the cost of halving {{chem|CO|2}} emissions by 2050 (the US and UK governments were intending 80% cuts&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-255&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=255}}&lt;/ref&gt;) would be US$ 45 trillion—equivalent to &quot;two thirds of the world's entire current annual economic output&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-233&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=233}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Booker sums up the book's content in a long epilogue, which quotes [[Theseus]] in ''[[A Midsummer's Night Dream]]'':

&quot;In the night, imagining some fear,
How easy is a bush supposed a bear&quot;.

Booker contends that in this quote [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]] is identifying that &quot;when we are not presented with enough information for our minds to resolve something into certainty, they may be teased into exaggerating it into something quite different from what it really is&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker-341&quot;&gt;{{harvnb |Booker|2009| p=341}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reception ==

The book received a mixed reception by press reviewers.

In his review in ''[[The Observer]]'', [[Philip Ball]] (former editor of ''[[Nature (journal)|Nature]]'') stated the book was &quot;the definitive climate sceptics' manual&quot; in that it makes an uncritical presentation of &quot;just about every criticism ever made of the majority scientific view&quot; on global warming. Though expressing &quot;a queer kind of admiration for the skill and energy with which Booker has assembled his polemic&quot;, Ball called the claims made by the author &quot;bunk&quot;. Ball also criticised Booker's tactic of introducing climate sceptics &quot;with a little eulogy to their credentials, while their opponents receive only a perfunctory, if not disparaging, preamble&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian.co.uk&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2009/nov/15/real-global-warming-christopher-booker
| date = 15 November 2009
| title = The Real Global Warming Disaster by Christopher Booker
| author = [[Philip Ball]]
| work = [[The Observer]]
| accessdate = 4 February 2010
| quote = But much, including the central claim, is bunk. [...] Booker's position would require that you accept something like the following: 1) Most of the world's climate scientists, for reasons unspecified, decided to create a myth about human-induced global warming and have managed to twist endless measurements and computer models to fit their case, without the rest of the scientific community noticing. George W Bush and certain oil companies have, however, seen through the deception. 2) Most of the world's climate scientists are incompetent and have grossly misinterpreted their data and models, yet their faulty conclusions are not, as you might imagine, a random chaos of assertions, but all point in the same direction.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[The Spectator]]'', [[Rodney Leach]] wrote that &quot;the shelf of sceptical books keeps filling and Booker's belongs there with the best&quot;, remarking that Booker &quot;narrates this story with the journalist's pace and eye for telling detail and the historian's forensic thoroughness which have made him a formidable opponent of [[humbug]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leach The Spectator&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.spectator.co.uk/books/5503548/a-wild-goose-chase.thtml
| date = 4 November 2009
| title = A wild goose chase
| author = [[Rodney Leach]]
| work = [[The Spectator]]
| accessdate = 2 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Columnist [[James Delingpole]] described the book as &quot;another of those classics which any even vaguely intelligent person who wants to know what's really going on needs to read&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Delingpole Spectator&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.spectator.co.uk/columnists/all/5482258/you-know-it-makes-sense.thtml
| date = 28 October 2009
| title = You Know It Makes Sense
| author = [[James Delingpole]]
| work = [[The Spectator]]
| accessdate = 5 April 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing in ''[[The Herald (Glasgow)|The Herald]]'', [[Brian Morton (Scottish writer)|Brian Morton]] was largely sympathetic to the position taken by Booker in the book: &quot;The question isn't whether climate is changing, but what is to blame. A crippling tithe of international political effort and social action is directed to the assumption that we are&quot;, and &quot;the climate change debate—or enforced consensus—concerns the way science is done and perceived. As Booker says, 'consensus' is not a term in science but in politics&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Morton The_Herald&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.heraldscotland.com/arts-ents/non-fiction-reviews/the-real-global-warming-disaster-by-christopher-booker-continuum-16-99-1.930081
| date = 3 November 2009
| title = Is a climate-change sceptic more like a flat-earther or a Holocaust denier, merely out of touch or mendacious and evil?
| author = [[Brian Morton (Scottish writer)|Brian Morton]]
| work = [[The Herald (Glasgow)|The Herald]]
| accessdate = 3 April 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A positive review by [[Henry Kelly]] in ''[[The Irish Times]]'', referring to the book as &quot;meticulously researched, provocative and challenging&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Kelly_Irish Times&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2009/1119/1224259112575.html
| date = 19 November 2009
| title = Myths of global warming skilfully debunked
| author = [[Henry Kelly]]
| work = [[The Irish Times]]
| accessdate = 12 April 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; was criticised by Irish environmental campaigner and ''climatechange.ie'' website founder [[John Gibbons (environmental campaigner)|John Gibbons]], who said that the decision by ''The Irish Times'' to allow Kelly to review ''The Real Global Warming Disaster'' was part of a recent trend of &quot;the media giving too much coverage to 'anti-science' climate change deniers and failing to convey the gravity of the threat, making readers and viewers apathetic&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Monaghan_Times&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/ireland/article7086902.ece
| date = 4 April 2010
| title = A little warming under the collar
| author = Gabrielle Monaghan
| work = [[The Times]]
| accessdate = 12 April 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[The Scotsman]]'', writer and environmentalist [[John Lister-Kaye|Sir John Lister-Kaye]] chose ''The Real Global Warming Disaster'' as one of his books of the year, writing that &quot;though barely credible in places&quot; this was an &quot;important, brave book making and explaining many valid points&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lister-Kaye The Scotsman&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://thescotsman.scotsman.com/features/Books-of-the-year-Writers39.5886342.jp
| date = 5 December 2009
| title = Books of the year: Writers' choice
| author = [[John Lister-Kaye]]
| work = [[The Scotsman]]
| accessdate = 5 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Houghton misquotation==

The book opens with an incorrect quotation which wrongly attributes to [[John T. Houghton]] the words &quot;Unless we announce disasters, no one will listen&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.independent.co.uk/environment/climate-change/fabricated-quote-used-to-discredit-climate-scientist-1894552.html
| date = 10 February 2010
| title = Fabricated quote used to discredit climate scientist
| author = Steve Connor
| work = [[The Independent]]
| accessdate = 10 February 2010
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; The publishers apologised for this misquotation, confirmed that it would not be repeated, and agreed to place a corrigendum in any further copies of the book. In an article which appeared in ''[[The Sunday Telegraph]]'' on 20 February 2010, Booker wrote &quot;we shall all in due course take steps to correct the record, as I shall do in the next edition of my book&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Booker retraction&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/columnists/christopherbooker/7280369/What-the-weatherman-never-said.html
| date = 20 February 2010
| title = What the weatherman never said
| author = [[Christopher Booker]]
| work = [[The Daily Telegraph]]
| accessdate = 21 February 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Houghton referred the matter to the [[Press Complaints Commission]] (PCC Reference 101959), following whose involvement ''The Sunday Telegraph'' published on 15 August a letter of correction by Houghton stating his actual position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Houghton letter&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/comment/letters/7944874/Trident-shouldnt-lead-to-more-defence-cuts.html
| date = 15 August 2010
| title = Letters
| work = [[The Daily Telegraph]]
| accessdate = 28 September 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
An article supportive of Houghton appears in the ''[[New Scientist]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news|url=http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg20627606.300-living-in-denial-unleashing-a-lie.html|title=Giving life to a lie|author=Jim Giles|work=[[New Scientist]]|date=15 May 2010|accessdate=24 June 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==

* [[Global warming controversy]]
* [[Public opinion on climate change]]
* [[The Hockey Stick Illusion]]
* [[The Deniers]]
* [[The Great Global Warming Swindle]]

== Bibliography ==

* {{cite book
  | last = Booker
  | first = Christopher
  | title = The Real Global Warming Disaster
  | publisher = Continuum International Publishing Group Ltd
  | year = 2009
  | isbn = 1441110526
  | ref = harv
  }}

== Notes ==

{{Reflist
| colwidth = 30em
| refs =

}}

== Further reading ==

* {{cite book|author=Booker, Christopher; North, Richard|title=Scared To Death: From BSE To Global Warming, Why Scares Are Costing Us The Earth|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group Ltd|year=2007|isbn=0826486142}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Montford
  | first = Andrew
  | title = [[The Hockey Stick Illusion|The Hockey Stick Illusion; Climategate and the Corruption of Science]]
  | publisher = [[Stacey International]]
  | year = 2010
  | isbn = 1906768358
  | pages = 482
  | ref = harv
  }}

== External links ==

* [http://www.dailymail.co.uk/debate/article-1230113/The-devastating-book-debunks-climate-change.html Booker's synopsis of the book] in ''[[The Daily Mail]]''

{{global warming}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Real Global Warming Disaster}}
[[Category:2009 books]]
[[Category:Environmental non-fiction books]]
[[Category:Environmental skepticism]]
[[Category:Climate change books]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
