<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2607217" ns="0" title="WTVX"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WTVX|
  station_logo             = [[Image:Wtvx 2008.png|150px]]|
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = The CW West Palm|
  digital                  = 34 ([[UHF]])|
  subchannels              = 34.1 [[The CW Television Network|The CW]] (2006-Present)&lt;br&gt;[[WWHB-CA|34.2]] [[Azteca America]]&lt;br&gt;[[WTCN-CA|34.3]] [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br&gt;34.4 [[LATV]]|
  airdate                 = [[1962 in television|April 5, 1962]]|
  location                 = [[Fort Pierce, Florida|Fort Pierce]]-[[West Palm Beach, Florida]]|
  callsign_meaning         = disambiguation of [[WTVJ]] (which WTVX replaced at sign-on)|
  former_channel_numbers   = Analog:&lt;br&gt;34 (UHF, 1962-2009)&lt;br&gt;Digital: 50 (UHF)|
  owner                    = [[Four Points Media Group]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(operated through [[local marketing agreement|LSA]] by&lt;br&gt; [[Nexstar Broadcasting Group]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;''(sale to [[Sinclair Broadcast Group|Sinclair Broadcast Group, Inc.]] pending)''|
  licensee                 = West Palm Beach Television Licensee Corporation|
  sister_stations          = WTCN-CA&lt;br&gt;WWHB-CA|
  former_affiliations      = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1962 &amp; 1989-1995)&lt;br&gt;[[CBS]] (1962-1989)&lt;br&gt;[[UPN]] (1995-2006)&lt;br&gt;[[The WB Television Network|The WB]] (secondary, 2001-2005)&lt;br&gt;[[Retro Television Network|RTV]] (on DT4)|
  effective_radiated_power = 1,000 [[kilowatt|kW]] |
  HAAT                     = 455.7 m|
  facility_id              = 35575|
  coordinates              = {{coord|27|7|19|N|80|23|20|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|}}  

'''WTVX''' is the [[The CW Television Network|CW]]-affiliated [[television station]] for [[West Palm Beach, Florida]] that is licensed to [[Fort Pierce, Florida|Fort Pierce]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 34 from a transmitter southwest of [[Palm City, Florida|Palm City]] and [[Interstate 95 in Florida|I-95]] in [[Martin County, Florida|Martin County]]. Owned by the [[Four Points Media Group]] and operated by the [[Nexstar Broadcasting Group]] through a [[local marketing agreement|local service agreement]] (LSA), the station is a sister to [[Class A television service|Class A]] [[MyNetworkTV]] affiliate [[WTCN-CA]] and Class A [[Azteca America]] affiliate [[WWHB-CA]].  All three share studios in a [[high-rise]] office building at the corner of Palm Beach Lakes Boulevard and North Congress Avenue in West Palm Beach.

Despite WTVX's call sign, it was never owned by the [[TVX Broadcast Group]] which coincidentally was a predecessor to former owner [[Paramount Stations Group]], now called [[CBS Television Stations]]. [[Television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on WTVX includes: ''[[Friends]]'', ''[[That '70s Show]]'', ''[[Two and a Half Men]]'' and ''[[Judge Judy]]''. It can be seen on [[Comcast]] channel 4 (in [[Palm Beach County, Florida|Palm Beach]], Martin, southern [[St. Lucie County, Florida|St. Lucie]] and [[Indian River County, Florida|Indian River]] Counties).

===Digital programming===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! [[Video resolution|Video]]
! [[Aspect ratio|Aspect]]
! Name
! Programming
|-
| 34.1 || [[1080i]] || [[16:9]] || WTVX-HD || Main WTVX programming / The CW
|-
| 34.2 || rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[480i]] || rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[4:3]] || WWHB || [[Azteca America]]
|-
| 34.3 || WTCN || &quot;My 15&quot;
|-
| 34.4 || WTVX-DT4 || [[LATV]]
|}

The station transmitted on UHF channel 50 during the [[DTV_transition_in_the_United_States|DTV transition]], but switched to transmitting digital television exclusively on channel 34 before the June 12 cut-off date.

WTVX added the [[Retro Television Network]] (RTV) on its fourth digital subchannel and [[Comcast]] digital channel 225, though this was dropped in favor of [[LATV]] on June 29, 2010;&lt;ref name=&quot;tvbr-rtvtolatv&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rbr.com/tv-cable/25350.html|title=Nexstar/Four Points fired up to add 4th network in West Palm|date=June 24, 2010|work=Television Business Report|accessdate=June 25, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[WHDT]] became the area's RTV affiliate several months later.

==History==
[[Image:TVXlogo.png|thumb|left|300px|WTVX logo during most of the 1980s.]]

WTVX began operations as an [[independent station (North America)|independent station]] on [[April 5]], [[1962]] and soon after became a [[CBS]] affiliate. The station was originally owned by Indian River Television and based out of a small building along [[U.S. Route 1 in Florida|U.S. 1]] just south of the St. Lucie/Indian River County line. Prior to the station becoming a CBS affiliate, the network was seen via [[Miami, Florida|Miami]] affiliate [[WTVJ]]. Even after WTVX signed on, its signal wasn't nearly as powerful as WTVJ, who continued to be recognized as the CBS affiliate for the Palm Beaches; it was not until the 1980s that cable penetration allowed WTVX to gain a Palm Beach audience. In 1987, [[NBC]] bought WTVJ. CBS needed a new Miami affiliate and purchased [[WFOR-TV|WCIX]], which had a Grade B signal in [[Fort Lauderdale, Florida|Fort Lauderdale]]. West Palm Beach stations [[WPTV (TV)|WPTV]] and [[WPEC]] had Grade A signals there; this forced CBS to switch its West Palm Beach affiliate on [[January 1]], [[1989]] to WPEC. As [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] decided to go from WPEC to new sign-on [[WPBF]], WTVX was forced to become an independent station once again. 

During the day, the station showed movies, drama shows and talk shows. By the summer of 1989, it became more of a traditional independent station with sitcoms and cartoons being added to its schedule. Most of WTVX's shows were to have originally aired on WPBF before that station made the decision to affiliate with ABC. In 1990, WTVX was sold to Krypton Broadcasting. In 1995, [[Paramount Pictures|Paramount]]/[[Viacom]] joined with [[Chris-Craft Industries#Chris-Craft/United Television|Chris Craft/United Television]] to form the United Paramount Network ([[UPN]]). WTVX immediately became an affiliate of this network and became an [[owned-and-operated station]] upon Viacom's acquisition of the station in 1997. By the late-1990s, it had started to move away from cartoons and sitcoms adding more talk/reality and court shows. In the early-2000s, WTVX started to carry [[The WB Television Network|The WB]] on a secondary basis. Programming from that network aired after UPN prime time. The station soon rebranded from &quot;UPN 34&quot; to &quot;TVX 34&quot; which was based on its call letters. In Fall 2005, [[WTCN-CA]] (then a little-known community access channel) became the area's new WB affiliate after Viacom's acquisition of that station. As a result, WTVX reverted to solely being a UPN station and returned to the &quot;UPN 34&quot; branding. 

On January 24, 2006, The WB and UPN announced that they would end broadcasting and merge. The new combined network would be called [[The CW Television Network|The CW]]. WTVX was announced as becoming the area's affiliate of the new network because it was full-powered and owned by CBS. On February 7, 2007, CBS agreed to sell seven of its smaller-[[media market|market]] stations to [[Cerberus Capital Management]] (including WTVX, WTCN, and WWHB) for $185 million. Cerberus formed a new holding company for the stations, [[Four Points Media Group]], who took over the operation of the stations through [[local marketing agreement]]s in late June 2007. The group deal closed on January 10, 2008. Until the sale to Four Points, WTVX was one of three former CBS affiliates that later became CW stations that were owned by CBS; the other two are [[KSTW]] in [[Seattle, Washington|Seattle]]/[[Tacoma, Washington]] and [[WPCW]] in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]], both of which are still owned by the network. During CBS ownership, some internal operations of WTVX, WTCN, and WWHB were based at [[WFOR-TV]]'s studios in Miami. As of February 25, 2008, these three stations are now being operated from Four Points' hub facilities at [[KUTV]] in [[Salt Lake City, Utah]]. 

On September 8, 2011, [[Sinclair Broadcast Group]] announced its intent to purchase Four Points from Cerberus Capital Management for $200 million; Sinclair will begin managing the stations, including WTVX, under local marketing agreements following antitrust approval, until the close of the sale, which is expected in early 2012.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tvnewscheck.com/article/2011/09/08/53840/sinclair-buys-four-points-media-for-200m Sinclair Buys Four Points Media For $200M], ''TVNewsCheck'', September 8, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Sinclair subsequently announced the acquisition of the television station division of [[Freedom Communications]], owner of WPEC, which will result in WTVX becoming a sister station to WPEC.&lt;ref name=tvnc-wtvxwpecduopoly&gt;{{cite news|last=Colman|first=Price|title=Sinclair Buying Freedom For $385 Million|url=http://www.tvnewscheck.com/article/2011/11/02/55148/sinclair-buying-freedom-for-385-million?utm_source=Listrak&amp;utm_medium=Email&amp;utm_term=Sinclair+Buying+Freedom+For+%24385+Million&amp;utm_campaign=Sinclair+Buying+Freedom+For+%24385+Million|accessdate=November 2, 2011|newspaper=TVNewsCheck|date=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==News operation==
[[Image:Wtvx news.png|thumb|right|Its logo for the 6:30 news.]]

As a CBS affiliate, WTVX operated a news department from its studios in Fort Pierce and maintained newsrooms in Stuart and West Palm Beach. Soon after the loss of the affiliation, it began to phase out its newscasts eventually ceasing completely by Summer 1989. At one point as a CW affiliate, the station aired news updates under the title ''CW News Now'' on its website. In Summer 2008, WTVX created a new news department (and on August 4) debuted ''CW West Palm News At 10''. This production initially aired seven nights a week for 35 minutes and in [[high-definition television|high definition]] starting on September 15. As its first news broadcast to air in nearly twenty years, it competed with the well-established 10 o'clock news on [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliate [[WFLX]]. As was the case with that station, WTVX's broadcast also rated in the [[Miami]]/[[Fort Lauderdale]] market where it competed with similar newscasts on [[WSVN]] and [[WBFS-TV]]. 

At some point in time, the Saturday night broadcast was dropped. On March 2, 2009, WTVX moved the show to weeknights at 6:30 when the national news programs air on the big three stations. On June 8, 2009, the station discontinued its newscast altogether. Throughout its life, the CW newscast was produced by owner Four Points Media Group in conjunction with sister station KUTV. The news originated from a secondary set at that station's studios on Main Street in downtown Salt Lake City. WTVX's studios functioned as a news bureau with two reporters local to West Palm Beach. It continues to air the nationally [[television syndication|syndicated]] morning show ''[[The Daily Buzz]]'' on weekday mornings from 7 to 8 that is produced from studios on the campus of [[Full Sail University]] in [[Orlando, Florida]]. There is also a public affairs show called ''Around Our Town'' that is aired Tuesday and Thursday mornings at 8 and on Sunday mornings at 7 hosted by Aneta Sewell.

With Sinclair's purchase of WTVX and its subsequent purchase of WPEC, it is unknown if another attempt at a 10 p.m. newscast will be aired on WTVX.

===Newscast titles===
*''X•34'' (1962-1980)
*''News Source 34'' (1980-1984)
*''WTVX News'' (1984-1988)
*''CW West Palm News at 10'' (2008-2009)
*''CW West Palm News at 6:30'' (2009)

===Station slogans===
*&quot;I got to know 'em!&quot; (1974-1986)
*&quot;The Spirit of the Treasure Coast&quot; (1986-1992)
*&quot;Good Time TV!&quot; (2002-2006)
*&quot;Free to be CW&quot; (2006-2007, used to promote switch to The CW)
*&quot;All Your News in Half the Time&quot; (2008-2009)

===References===
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://wearewestpalm.com WTVX &quot;The CW West Palm&quot;]
*[http://www.cwtv.com The CW]
*{{TVQ|WTVX}}

{{WPB TV}}
{{CW Florida}}
{{LATV stations}}
{{Four Points Media Group}}
{{NXST TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wtvx}}
[[Category:The CW Television Network affiliates]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1962]]
[[Category:West Palm Beach, Florida]]
[[Category:Channel 34 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television stations in Florida]]
[[Category:Cerberus Capital Management companies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
