<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26090" ns="0" title="Richard Myers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the U.S. Air Force general|other people with the same name|Richard Myers (disambiguation)}}
{{BLP sources|date=August 2009}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Richard Bowman Myers
|birth_date = {{birth date and age|1942|3|1|mf=y}}
|death_date=
|birth_place= [[Kansas City, Missouri]]
|death_place=
|placeofburial=
|image= [[Image:Richard Myers official portrait 2.jpg|250px|Richard Myers]]
|caption= Gen Richard B. Myers, USAF
|nickname=
|allegiance=[[United States of America]]
|branch= [[United States Air Force]]
|serviceyears= 1965–2005
|rank= [[General officer|General]]
|commands= [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]&lt;br/&gt;
[[North American Aerospace Defense Command]]&lt;br/&gt;
[[U.S. Space Command]]&lt;br/&gt;
Commander, [[Pacific Air Forces]]
|unit=
|battles=[[Vietnam War]]
|awards= [[Defense Distinguished Service Medal]] (4)&lt;br/&gt;[[Air Force Distinguished Service Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Legion of Merit]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]] (2)&lt;br/&gt;[[Air Medal]] (19)&lt;br/&gt;[[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]
|laterwork=[[Northrop Grumman]], Board of Directors
}}
'''Richard Bowman Myers''' (born March 1, 1942) is a retired four-star [[General (United States)|general]] in the [[United States Air Force]] and served as the 15th [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]. As Chairman, Myers was the United States military's highest ranking uniformed officer.

General Myers became the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs on October 1, 2001. In this capacity, he served as the principal military advisor to the [[President of the United States|President]], the [[Secretary of Defense of the United States|Secretary of Defense]], and the [[United States National Security Council|National Security Council]] during the earliest stages of the [[War on Terror]], including planning and execution of the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]]. On September 30, 2005, he retired and was succeeded by General [[Peter Pace]].  His Air Force career included operational command and leadership positions in a variety of Air Force and Joint assignments.

==Early life==
Myers was born in [[Kansas City, Missouri|Kansas City]], [[Missouri]]. He graduated from [[Shawnee Mission School District|Shawnee Mission North High School]] in 1960. He graduated from [[Kansas State University]] with a [[bachelor's degree|B.S.]] in [[mechanical engineering]] in 1965 where he was a member of [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]] fraternity. He was commissioned by Detachment 270 of the [[Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps]] at KSU. &lt;ref&gt;Ceremony program, Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps Distinguished Alumni Induction, Maxwell AFB, Alabama, 26 July 2011, page 4.&lt;/ref&gt; He graduated from [[Auburn University Montgomery]] with a [[Master of Business Administration|M.B.A.]] in 1977. The General has attended the [[Air Command and Staff College]] at [[Maxwell Air Force Base]], [[Alabama]]; the [[U.S. Army War College]] at [[Carlisle Barracks]], [[Pennsylvania]]; and the Program for Senior Executives in National and International Security at [[Harvard University]]'s [[John F. Kennedy School of Government]].

General Myers entered the Air Force in 1965 through the [[Reserve Officer Training Corps]] program.  He received pilot training from 1965 to 1966 at [[Vance Air Force Base]], [[Oklahoma]].  Myers is a command pilot with more than 4,100 flying hours in the [[T-33 Shooting Star]], [[C-37 Gulfstream V|C-37]], [[C-21 Learjet|C-21]], [[F-4 Phantom II|F-4]], [[F-15 Eagle]] and [[F-16 Fighting Falcon]], including 600 combat hours in the F-4.

==Commander and Chairman==
Prior to becoming Chairman, he served as the [[Vice Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] from March 2000 to September 2001. As Vice Chairman, General Myers served as the Chairman of the Joint Requirements Oversight Council, Vice Chairman of the Defense Acquisition Board, and as a member of the [[National Security Council Deputies Committee]] and the Nuclear Weapons Council. In addition, he acted for the Chairman in all aspects of the Planning, Programming and Budgeting System including participation in the Defense Resources Board.

From August 1998 to February 2000, General Myers was Commander in Chief of the [[North American Aerospace Defense Command]] and [[U.S. Space Command]]; Commander of the [[Air Force Space Command]]; and Department of Defense manager of the space transportation system contingency support at [[Peterson Air Force Base]], [[Colorado]]. As commander, General Myers was responsible for defending America through space and intercontinental ballistic missile operations. Prior to assuming that position, he was Commander, Pacific Air Forces, [[Hickam Air Force Base]], [[Hawaii]], from July 1997 to July 1998. From July 1996 to July 1997 he served as Assistant to the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff at [[the Pentagon]]; and from November 1993 to June 1996 General Myers was Commander of U.S. Forces Japan and 5th Air Force at [[Yokota Air Base]], [[Japan]].

He was the acting chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (CJCS) during the September 11th, 2001, terror attacks because CJCS Shelton was en route to Europe. However, at the time the Pentagon was attacked, he was on Capitol Hill and not in the Pentagon. He did leave Capitol Hill and spent the remainder of the day in the Pentagon. His office was not damaged during the attack. He officially took position as Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (CJCS) on October 1, 2001. he served as the principal military advisor to the [[President of the United States|President]], the [[Secretary of Defense of the United States|Secretary of Defense]], and the [[United States National Security Council|National Security Council]] during the earliest stages of the [[War on Terror]], including planning of the [[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|War in Afghanistan]] and planning and execution of the [[2003 invasion of Iraq]].

==Retirement and Post-retirement==
On 27 September 2005, only three days before leaving his post as Chairman, Myers said of the [[Iraq War|war in Iraq]] that, &quot;the outcome and consequences of defeat are greater than [[World War II]].&quot; His rise to and stint as Chairman are chronicled in ''[[Washington Post]]'' reporter [[Bob Woodward]]'s book, ''[[State of Denial]]'', as well as his own book &quot;Eyes on The Horizon&quot;. On September 30, 2005, he retired and was succeeded by General [[Peter Pace]].  His Air Force career included operational command and leadership positions in a variety of Air Force and Joint assignments.
[[Image:MyersRichard PresidentialMedalofFreedom.jpg|left|thumb|Myers receiving the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]].]]

On November 9, 2005, Myers received the [[Presidential Medal of Freedom]]. His citation reads:
{{cquote|For four decades, General Richard Myers has served our Nation with honor and distinction. He flew some 600 combat hours in the Vietnam War. He later served as Commander in Chief of North American Aerospace Defense Command and U.S. Space Command. As Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, General Myers played a central role in our Nation's defense while devoting himself to the well-being of the men and women who wear the uniform of the United States Armed Forces. The United States honors General Richard Myers for his dedication to duty and country and for his contributions to the freedom and security of our Nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2005/11/20051109-10.html
|publisher=Office of the Press Secretary, White House
|title=Citations for Recipients of the 2005 Presidential Medal of Freedom
|date=November 9, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

In 2006, General Myers accepted a part-time appointment as a Foundation Professor of Military History at Kansas State University. That same year, he was also elected to the Board of Directors of [[Northrop Grumman]] Corporation, the world’s third largest defense contractor. On 13 September 2006, he also joined the board of directors of [[United Technologies Corporation]]. He also resides on the boards of [[Aon Corporation]], [[Deere &amp; Company|John Deere]], the [[United Service Organizations|USO]] and holds the Colin L. Powell Chair for National Security, Leadership, Character and Ethics at the [[National Defense University]]. He also has advised the Defense Health Board and served on the Army War College Board of Visitors.&lt;ref&gt;http://bellum.stanfordreview.org/?p=2679&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 July 2011, Myers was inducted into the [[Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps]] Distinguished Alumni in a ceremony at [[Maxwell AFB]], Alabama, officiated by Lt. Gen. Allen G. Peck, Commander, [[Air University (United States Air Force)|Air University]]. &lt;ref&gt;Ceremony program, Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps Distinguished Alumni Induction, Maxwell AFB, Alabama, 26 July 2011, page 4.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
[[Image:US Navy 040909-N-2568S-003 The Secretary of the Navy Gordon England, and the Chairman, Joint Chiefs of Staff Gen. Richard Myers, joined by his wife Mary Jo Myers, pose next to a model of a San Antonio-class amphibious dock land.jpg|thumb|right|[[Gordon R. England]], Mary Jo Myers, and General Richard Myers in 2004]]

General Myers and his wife, the former Mary Jo Rupp, have three children: two daughters and a son. General Myers appeared on [[Mad Money with Jim Cramer]] on March 16, 2009.

==Quotes==
*&quot;We train our people to obey the Geneva Conventions, it's not even a matter of whether it is reciprocated - it's a matter of who we are&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=[[Torture Team]] |last=Sands |first=Philippe |authorlink=Philippe Sands |coauthors= |year=2008, 2009 |publisher=Penguin Books |location=London |isbn=978-0-141-03132-3 |page=40 |pages=335 |url= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|United States Air Force}}
{{Commons category|Richard Myers}}
* [http://www.af.mil/information/bios/bio.asp?bioID=6123 General Richard Myers Biography]

{{S-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{Succession box|title=Commander of the [[North American Aerospace Defense Command]]|before=[[Howell M. Estes III]]|after=[[Ralph Eberhart]]|years=14 August 1998 &amp;ndash; 22 February 2000}}
{{Succession box|before = [[Joseph W. Ralston]] |title = [[Vice Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] |years = 2000&amp;mdash;2001 |after = [[Peter Pace]]}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]|before=[[Hugh Shelton]]|after=[[Peter Pace]]|years=2001&amp;ndash;2005}}
{{S-end}}
{{VCJCS}}
{{JCS}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Myers, Richard
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = March 1, 1942
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Kansas City, Missouri]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Myers, Richard}}
[[Category:1942 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Kansas City, Missouri]]
[[Category:Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Chairmen of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Vice Chairmen of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:United States Air Force generals]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Directors of Northrop Grumman]]
[[Category:People from Johnson County, Kansas]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Meritorious Service Decoration]]
[[Category:Presidential Medal of Freedom recipients]]
[[Category:Kansas State University alumni]]
[[Category:Auburn University at Montgomery alumni]]
[[Category:John F. Kennedy School of Government alumni]]
[[Category:United States National Security Council staffers]]
[[Category:United States Army War College alumni]]

[[bg:Ричард Майърс]]
[[de:Richard B. Myers]]
[[ja:リチャード・マイヤーズ]]
[[sl:Richard Bowman Myers]]
[[fi:Richard Myers]]
[[sv:Richard B. Myers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
