<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26099195" ns="0" title="West Alabama Tigers"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox college athletics
| name           = West Alabama Tigers
| logo           =  
| logo_width     =  
| university     = [[University of West Alabama|The University of West Alabama]]
| conference     = [[Gulf South Conference]]
| division       = [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]]
| director       = Stan Williamson
| city           = Livingston
| state          = Alabama
| stateabb       = AL
| teams          = 13 (14 in 2012-2013)
| stadium        = [[Tiger Stadium (West Alabama)|Tiger Stadium]]
| arena          = Pruitt Hall
| baseballfield  = Tartt Field
| mascot         = Luie the Tiger
| nickname       = Tigers
| fightsong      = The Fight Song
| color1 = Red
| hex1   = FF0000
| color2 = White
| hex2   = FFFFFF
| pageurl  = http://www.uwaathletics.com/
| pagename = UWA Athletics
}}

[[University of West Alabama|The University of West Alabama]] currently features 13 sports teams.  Men's soccer will become the 14th sport in the fall of 2012.  Both the male and female athletic teams are called the '''West Alabama Tigers'''.  Eleven of the thirteen teams participate in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] as a member of the [[Gulf South Conference]] East Division.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/about.asp?page=schools|title=Gulf South Conference-About the Gulf South Conference|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|date=2007-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Men's and women's rodeo compete in the Ozark Region of the [[National Intercollegiate Rodeo Association]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.collegerodeo.com/membership/RegionInfo.asp?Region=OZ|title=NIRA - Membership for Ozark Region|publisher=''National Intercollegiate Rodeo Association''|date=2007-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Athletics facilities on the campus include 7,000-seat [[Tiger Stadium (West Alabama)|Tiger Stadium]], James P. Homer Fieldhouse, Pruitt Hall, Tartt Field, UWA Softball Complex, Dora Dahlberg Beard Indoor Practice Facility, Howard R. Vaughan Tennis Complex, Don C. Hines Rodeo Complex, and UWA Cross Country Facility.

Main rivalries for the program include those with the [[University of North Alabama|North Alabama Lions]] and [[Delta State University|Delta State Statesmen]].  The rivalry with North Alabama is especially heated as the two compete annually in nearly all sports.  Other rivalries include those against the [[University of Alabama in Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville Chargers]], [[Valdosta State University|Valdosta State Blazers]], [[University of West Florida|West Florida Argonauts]], and [[University of West Georgia|West Georgia Wolves]].  The Tigers had a rivalry against the [[University of Montevallo|Montevallo Falcons]] before they left the [[Gulf South Conference|GSC]] to join the [[Peach Belt Conference]].

The University's Director of Athletics is Stan Williamson.  The school's official mascot is Luie the Tiger.

== Fall sports ==
=== Football ===
West Alabama's football team was first fielded in 1931 when the school was known as Livingston State Teachers College.  However, intercollegiate competition for all the university’s athletics was not scheduled until seven years later.  In 1938, they competed in four games against Marion Institute, [[Jacksonville State University|Jacksonville State]], Demopolis A.S, and [[Troy University|Troy State]], all of whom were local teams.  LSTC finished the season 2-2.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/uwa_football_media_guide|title=2009 UWA Football Media Guide|page=53|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01 |accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; That year also marked the start of [[World War II]] which led to a decline in college enrollment across the United States.  Therefore, LSTC fielded no athletic teams from 1942-1945.  In 1944, Dr. William Wilson Hill became president of the university and instantly started recruiting students to enroll.  The return of males to campus reestablished an interest in sports.  After a three year hiatus, the football team returned to action under the guidance of new head coach E.G McCollum.  They opened their season with the first of many future match-ups against [[Mississippi College]], which resulted in a 24-14 loss.  Also, that season, LSTC renewed its rivalry with, eventual Gulf South Conference foes, Troy State and [[Delta State University|Delta State]].  The team concluded the season with a 6-3 record.  Due to success of the season, McCollum resigned to pursue a bigger opportunity elsewhere.  Following two dismal seasons from 1947 and 1948, LSTC made a bold move and hired former [[University of Alabama]] star Vaughn Mancha as the fourth head coach in team history.  Mancha at the time was only 28 years old with no prior coaching experience.  The former two-time All-American had also recently completed his first and only season in the [[National Football League|NFL]] as a member of the Boston Yanks.  Under Mancha, the team experienced immediate success.  In his first season, he led LSTC to one of the biggest accomplishments in school history, a 13-6 win over [[Florida State University|Florida State]].  The team also concluded the regular season 7-1-1, which at the time marked the best record in school history.  The historical season earned LSTC right to play in the Paper Bowl against Jacksonville State.  JSU won the hard fought defensive affair, 12-7.  Up until 1952, the Tigers played home games at Livingston High School.  From then on, all their home games were played at [[Tiger Stadium (West Alabama)|Tiger Stadium]], a 7,000-capacity stadium located on filled in land that was previously known as &quot;Crawdad Creek.&quot;  The stadium was built to fill the need for an on-campus stadium.  Next season was once again successful as the team finished 6-3-1.  However, they could not duplicate the accomplishments of the previous season.  During Mancha’s third season, the team started off 2-4 and showed heavy signs of decline until putting on a strong finish to end the season 5-5.  This season would mark the last in Mancha’s tenure at LSTC as he decided to take over as defensive coordinator at Florida State.  Mancha departed with an 18-10-2 overall record. 

The Tigers underwent a 15 year long drought without a winning season after the departure of Mancha.  The team’s most success came in 1965 when they finished 5-4.  Their luck finally started to change after hiring Morris Higginbotham in 1967.  Before coming to Livingston, he was one of the most successful high school coaches in Alabama, compiling a 111-27-8 record.  The native of [[Birmingham, Alabama|Birmingham]], earned Alabama Collegiate Conference Coach of the Year honors for the efforts of his 1968 team that featured a 9-2 mark and an appearance in the Peanut Bowl in [[Dothan, Alabama]].  Higginbotham only remained at the school for three seasons leading the Tigers to a 19-9-2 record.  Higginbotham was succeeded by assistant head coach Mickey Andrews.  Similar to the path of former LU head coach, Vaughn Mancha, Andrews starred in football and baseball at the University of Alabama from 1961-1964 before being hired at the university in 1967.  Andrews spent three seasons guiding the UWA football team, leading the Tigers to a 24-7-2 record during his tenure.  The team also won their first and only championship in school history during the 1971 season defeating [[Arkansas Tech University|Arkansas Tech]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=5v0cAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=IJwEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5660,2766987&amp;dq=livingston+university+football&amp;hl=en|title=Happy Tigers win big one|last=Trimm|first=Mickey|date=12 December 1971|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=1B|accessdate=7 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; LU's bid for a second consecutive [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] National Championship came up short to [[Carson-Newman University|Carson-Newman]] in the 1972 NAIA semi-final.  Both teams battled to a 7-7 tie.  However, a controversial tiebreaker ruling went in favor of Carson-Newman.  In 1973, Andrews became the second LU head coach to resign and accept the defensive coordinator position at Florida State.  With the next coach, once again, LU made a decision to hire a coach from within the program as they selected Andrews’ top assistant, Jim King.  King, a native of [[Adamsville, Alabama]], came to LU in 1970.  In 1975, he led the Tigers to the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] playoffs with a 10-3 record.  In the NCAA Quarter Finals, the team faced a tough task of taking on '''#1''' ranked [[University of North Dakota|North Dakota]].  The game was nearly cancelled due to heavy [[snow]].  Nevertheless, LU prevailed in a huge upset to move on.  During the Semi-Finals, they faced a tough [[Northern Michigan University|Northern Michigan]] team on national television.  Although LU jumped out to a 10-0 lead, they eventually fell short 28-26.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/uwa_football_media_guide|title=2009 UWA Football Media Guide|page=62|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01 |accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; King, like several successful LU coaches before him, moved on to a new opportunity elsewhere.  In only three seasons, he compiled a 29-14-1 record.  Since that time, the Tigers have faced their share of good but mostly bad seasons.

The hiring of [[Bobby Wallace (American football)|Bobby Wallace]] in 2006 marked a new era within the football program.  Wallace’s first head coaching stint came in the GSC when he was the head coach at the [[University of North Alabama]] from 1988-1997.  During his time at UNA, he led the Lions to three consecutive national championships from 1993-1995 as his squads finished with an overall record of 41-1 during the course of those three seasons.  The 1995 team was selected as the &quot;Best Team of the Quarter Century&quot; in [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]].  Wallace also led UNA to Gulf South Conference Championships during the 1993-1995 seasons, while his Lions also qualified for the NCAA Division II Playoffs six times during his tenure.  Over his 10 seasons at the helm, he compiled an overall mark of 82-36-1, and he also produced a total of 12 NFL players.  Prior to arriving in Livingston, he had served as the head coach at [[Temple University]] since 1997.  Upon hiring Wallace, many around UWA hoped he could lead the football team back to its glory days. The Wallace Era began with a great glimmer of hope as UWA recorded its first winning season in 14 years. The Tigers finished 6-5 on the season. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.waff.com/Global/story.asp?s=11431073&amp;clienttype=printable|title=Lions No.1 Entering Regular Season Finale|date=2 November 2009|publisher=''WAFF48 News''|accessdate=7 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; UWA also ended several streaks picking up wins at [[Lambuth University|Lambuth]], against [[Southern Arkansas University|Southern Arkansas]], and at [[University of Arkansas at Monticello|Arkansas-Monticello]].  The excitement was put on hold, however, as the team finished the 2007 season with a 1-9 record and posted a 4-7 record in 2008.  allace and his team put together a memorable season in 2009.  The season began with three consecutive victories including a televised home win over Arkansas Tech.  Unfortunately, three consecutive losses followed.  A couple of wins over '''#22''' Delta State and Arkansas-Monticello put UWA right back in the thick of the playoff race, but a loss to [[University of West Georgia|West Georgia]] the following week nearly derailed their hopes.  During the season finale, UWA was locked in a battle for their playoff lives against longtime rival and Wallace’s former team, North Alabama. At the time, UNA was ranked '''#1''' in all the Division II polls.  Through a fearless and courageous effort, UWA sent the game to [[overtime (sports)|overtime]] after losing the lead they held throughout the game.  After four overtimes, it appeared UNA was set to claim the victory until a forced fumble gave UWA the ball.  From that, they took advantage and kicked the game winning field goal.  It was the first win for the Tigers at [[Braly Municipal Stadium]] in [[Florence, Alabama|Florence]] since the 1987 season. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/news.asp?sport=&amp;id=388970|title=2009 GSC Football Week In Review, Nov. 9|date=9 November 2009|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|accessdate=7 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The NCAA rewarded UWA's efforts with a berth in the [[2009 NCAA Division II National Football Championship playoffs|NCAA Division II playoffs]].  In the first round, the Tigers upset '''#20''' Albany State 24-22 on the road. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ncaa.com/sports/m-footbl/recaps/111409aaf.html=en|title=West Alabama Edges Albany State|date=14 November 2009|publisher=NCAA.com|accessdate=6 February 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; After falling behind early against '''#10''' Carson-Newman, the Tigers mounted a rally before falling short 59-41. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ncaa.com/sports/m-footbl/recaps/112109aau.htmlen|title=No. 10 Carson-Newman Holds Off West Alabama|date=21 November 2009|publisher=NCAA.com|accessdate=6 February 2010}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers gathered an 8-5 record, the most wins since 1975, and had eight All-GSC honors.  UWA posted a 5-1 record at Tiger Stadium, the best since 1985, and tallied the most wins over GSC opponents since 1981 with six.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/news/2009/11/30/FB_1130094925.aspx?path=football|title=Five Named to Daktronics All-Super Region 2 Team|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-11-30|accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; They received their first two rankings in school history at the end of the season.  The [[American Football Coaches Association|AFCA]] placed them '''#21''', while the [http://www.d2football.com/ D2Football.com] poll placed them higher two spots at '''#19'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afca.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=9300&amp;ATCLID=204848389
|title=Northwest Missouri State Ends Season at No. 1 Division II Poll|publisher=''American Football Coaches Association''|date=2009-12-14 |accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.d2football.com/top25poll/11/|title=2009 D2Football.com Top 25 Media Poll - Final Poll|publisher=''D2Football.com''|date=2010-01-25|accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UWA entered the 2010 season ranked 12th nationally by [[USA Today]].  The team was also ranked 23rd in the Lindy’s Preseason Top 25 poll and 24th in the Sporting News Preseason Top 25 poll.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/news.asp?action=form&amp;recordID=459107&amp;sport=FOOTBALL|title=GSC Football in National Pre-Season Publications|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|date=2010-07-23|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UWA football team recorded its highest pre-season ranking since 1976 as the Tigers were selected second by the head coaches of the 2010 Gulf South Conference in the GSC Pre-Season Poll.  The Red and White previously entered as the top ranked team in 1976 and 1972.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/news.asp?action=form&amp;recordID=473970&amp;sport=FOOTBALL
|title=2010 GSC Football Pre-Season Release|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|date=2010-08-03|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; West Alabama opened the season on August 28 against NAIA member [[Shorter University|Shorter]] in nearby [[Demopolis, Alabama]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2010/01/19/uwa-to-play-season-opener-in-demopolis/|title=UWA to play season opener in Demopolis|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2010-01-19|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tiger Stadium saw a major renovation as a synthetic surface was recently installed. The Tigers played their first contest on the new surface on September 18 against Lambuth but were narrowly defeated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20100728/NEWS/100729569/1015?p=1&amp;tc=pg
|title=UWA to play on synthetic surface|publisher=''Tuscaloosa Times''|date=2010-07-28|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; UWA opened Gulf South Conference play with a home win over West Georgia but fell short to Delta State on the road.  After a 3-2 start, the Tigers reeled off three consecutive wins including a last-second Homecoming triumph over [[Henderson State University|Henderson State]]. It appeared the game had ended, but officials put a second back on the clock.  Quarterback Deon Williams connected to wide receiver Gerald Worsham in the back of the endzone for the game-winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101017/NEWS/101019670|title=UWA pulls off miracle with last-second score
|last=Carroll|first=Andrew|date=17 October 2010|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team dropped back-to-back heartbreakers the following two weeks before returning home to face Valdosta State in the season finale.  The day before the contest, Bobby Wallace announced to his players that he would be stepping down as head coach upon the end of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101111/NEWS/101119976|title=UWA’s Wallace retiring|last=Carroll|first=Andrew|date=11 November 2010|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After falling behind and trailing at the half, the Tigers upset the '''#7''' ranked Blazers to give Wallace a victory in his final game. The team notched its second win ever against Valdosta State and picked up their first win in the series since 1985. UWA finished the season 7-4 to earn consecutive winning seasons for the first time since 1991 and 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2010/11/12/uwa-sends-wallace-out-with-a-w/|title=UWA sends Wallace out with a ‘W’|last=Cannon|first=Jason|date=12 November 2010|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Deon Williams was recognized as one of 24 candidates for the Harlon Hill Trophy, the [[NCAA Division II|Division II]] equivalent to [[NCAA Division I|Division I]]'s [[Heisman Trophy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101113/NEWS/101119898?tc=ar|title=Williams a Harlon Hill Trophy candidate
|date=13 November 2010|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Offensive coordinator [[Will Hall (American football)|Will Hall]] was named Bobby Wallace's successor a week after the season concluded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101117/NEWS/101119690?tc=ar|title=Will Hall to take over West Alabama football program|last=Carroll|first=Andrew|date=17 November 2010|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bobby Wallace was inducted into the Division II Hall of Fame in December to close out a storied career.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.timesdaily.com/article/20101218/SPORTS110/101219811?Title=Wallace-8217-s-Hall-of-Fame-homecoming|title=Wallace’s Hall of Fame homecoming|last=App|first=Bryan|date=18 December 2010|publisher=''Times Daily''|accessdate=30 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Volleyball ===
The first known volleyball team for the University of West Alabama came in 1979.  UWA struggled throughout the 1980s and early part of the 1990s.  At this time, only season schedules beginning in 1994 are available.  Under the direction of head coach Pam Gailbreath, the team won 9 games that year.  The following year, UWA improved on its previous season finishing at 17-18.  In 1996, the Tigers reached an all-time high going 32-14 to set a school record for wins.  The next four seasons proved difficult for the Tigers as they could not get over the .500 point.  Then, in 2001, UWA won 23 games to finish with a .575 winning percentage.  They improved even more in 2002 when they went 25-13.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/2009_media_guide|title=2009 UWA Volleyball Media Guide|pages=35–36|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After another cold spell through 2006, the 2007 season brought highlights setting the tone for years to come.  UWA started the campaign 18-0 and was the only [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] undefeated team in [[United States of America|America]].  For their efforts, the [[American Volleyball Coaches Association|AVCA]] placed them '''#25''', the first ranking in the program's history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/news.asp?sport=Volleyball&amp;id=239008|title=West Alabama Volleyball Ranked For The First Time In School History|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|date=2007-10-01 |accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; A sweep over [[Albany State University|Albany State]] broke the school record for most consecutive wins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070930/NEWS/71001018|title=UWA volleyball team sweeps Albany State|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2007-09-30|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; They went on to finish the season 27-6 in head coach Ron Arenz's final year.  UWA recorded 8 conference wins, the most for the team since 2002.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20071104/NEWS/71104010|title=UWA volleyball team gets 3-1 win|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2007-11-04|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although the season ended in the opening round of the GSC Tournament, the Tigers broke several school records throughout the season.  In 2008, UWA continued their winning ways and achieved a 22-11 record.  However, the Tigers learned they would be losing another head coach.

Assistant coach Tabitha Turner was promoted to head coach for 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/coaches.aspx?rc=8&amp;path=wvball|title=2009 Women's Volleyball Coaching Staff|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-06-01|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  UWA was picked to finish third in the annual preseason poll.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090806/NEWS/908059921|title=UWA volleyball team picked third in GSC East|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-08-06|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; After starting the season slow through 14 games, the Tigers reeled off a 16-match winning streak pushing their record to 25-5 and 5-0 in the GSC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20091022/NEWS/910219922|title=Turner enjoying new duties as UWA coach|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-10-22|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the third consecutive season in which UWA had won at least 20 matches.  The team won the GSC East Division crown with a win at [[Valdosta State University|Valdosta State]] to close out regular season play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/news/2009/11/30/WVB_1130095714.aspx?path=wvball|title=UWA Claims GSC East Division Championship With 3-1 Win Over Valdosta State|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-11-07|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--The reference says 11/30/2009, but this was added when the new UWA website debuted.  Therefore, the date is not valid, and the original story came from 11/07/2009.--&gt; At the GSC Tournament, the Tigers fought back from a 2-1 deficit to top [[Arkansas Tech University|Arkansas Tech]] and advance to the semi-finals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20091114/NEWS/911149997?tc=ar|title=UWA volleyball advances to semifinals|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-11-14|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the semi-finals, the team blanked [[Harding University|Harding]] in a convincing sweep on their home court.  A bid for the school's first GSC Championship ended in heartbreak to [[University of West Florida|West Florida]].  UWA finished the season 30-8 and 8-2 in GSC play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20091115/NEWS/911149939?tc=ar|title=UWA volleyball falls in championship game|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-11-15|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the season, Tabitha Turner was selected by the [[American Volleyball Coaches Association|AVCA]] Thirty Under 30 list for 2010.  Created in 2009, the award honors the top 30 at all volleyball levels.  Instrumental in her first season at the helm and first as a head coach, Turner was also named Co-Coach of the Year in the East Division.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/news/2010/2/8/WVB_0208104734.aspx|title=UWA's Tabitha Turner Named To AVCA's Thirty Under 30 List|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2010-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2010 season was a rebuilding year for the Tigers as the squad finished with a 10-21 overall record.

=== Men's soccer ===
Beginning the fall of 2012, the University of West Alabama will start a men's soccer program.  The first head coach will be Matthew Thorne.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/news/2011/7/26/GEN_0726114015.aspx|title=UWA Adds Men's Soccer; Thorne Named Head Coach
|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2011-07-27|accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Women's soccer ===
Effective September 2011, the University of West Alabama will introduce its first ever women's soccer program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/news/2010/5/25/GEN_0525101306.aspx|title=UWA to Add Women's Soccer in 2011|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2010-05-25|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Graeme Orr, a native of [[Eaglesham]], [[Scotland]] has been announced as the school's first head coach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20100720/NEWS/100719571/1015|title=UWA hires women’s soccer coach|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2010-07-20|accessdate=2010-08-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first signing class was announced in March 2011 and features seven high school seniors and a pair of junior-college transfers.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20100720/NEWS/100719571/1015|title=UWA signs first soccer players|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011 3 March|accessdate=2011 30 May}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Winter sports ==
=== Men's basketball ===
The Tiger men’s basketball team was originally formed in 1939, but their first unofficial season took place after [[World War II]] in 1945.  From 1945–1955, the team was led by future UWA Athletic Hall of Famers Pop Wagoner, Jack Jones, and Milton Johnson.  The UWA record book, however, counts 1956–1957 as the official first men’s basketball season.  Jones, who was a three-sport for UWA (then Livingston University) from 1947–1951, returned to the university to coach the basketball team in 1956.  Although there were coaches before him, Jones is the first known head coach of Tiger men’s basketball.  The team faced constant struggles under him.  In his eight years at the helm, the 1956–1957 season was the only one in which the team accomplished more than 10 wins.  That season, they finished with an 11–10 record.  At the conclusion of the 1962–1963 season, Jones took a two-year hiatus away from coaching before returning for one last season in 1965.  During that hiatus, Travis Clark tried his hand at turning the team around.  With the help of a rising star in M.K Turk, Clark led the team to their second 11-win season in his first season.  Turk led LU in scoring his junior and senior seasons. He was also named All-Conference twice. The 1964–1965 season saw LU return to mediocrity as they finished 8–16. They recorded the same record during the following season, which was Jones’ last at the helm.  He finished his coaching career at LU with a 56–113 record.

LU men’s basketball underwent a drastic change with the hiring of future UWA Athletics Hall of Famer, Jack Powell, in 1966. Under his tutelage, the team gradually formed in a contender.  In Powell’s first two seasons as coach, the team made positive improvements but were still in need of a spark.  That spark arrived when Bob Drake, Dave Harvey, Larry Cantrell and Butch Stafford made their way to the LU campus.  Drake served two years as the Tiger team captain and was later an All-Alabama Collegiate Conference (ACC) selection.  He made the All-ACC Tournament Team twice and was chosen for the All-Alabama Small College Team. During the 1969-1970 season, LU recorded their first 16-win season.  Later that season, they were crowned ACC tournament champions.  With the addition of Elton Reece in 1970, the team built on the previous season’s success and finished with a school record 21 wins and four losses.  The mark still stands as the most single-season wins in West Alabama history. It earned Powell Coach of the Year in the ACC and earned Coach of the Year honors from Alabama Small Colleges and Universities as well as NAIA District 27.  Also that season, the Tigers won their second consecutive ACC crown.  Stafford was named the ACC Tournament MVP.  However, they were defeated in the NAIA District 27 finals.  For the 1971-1972 season, which turned out to be Powell’s last as head coach, LU finished 15-8 and won their third straight ACC championship.  The team also returned to the NAIA District 27 finals where they once again suffered a defeat.  Drake average 21.1 points per game in his senior campaign and made 166-of-205 [[free throw]]s, which still stands as the second highest total for free throws made in a season at UWA.  He also posted two 40-point games as a senior.  Stafford was selected the first-ever GSC Player of the Year in basketball and garnered All-American honors.  He finished his career with 1,143 points scored.  Harvey is currently fifth all time in the UWA record books with 452 field goals made.  Cantrell is the UWA all-time leader in rebound average with 16.35 and second all-time in [[rebound (basketball)|rebounds]] with 785.  Powell was selected as the first-ever Gulf South Conference Coach of the Year in basketball.  After six seasons with LU, he retired from coaching with an 83-57 record.  Powell’s 83 wins is currently ranked third all time in the UWA record books.  He is also ranked fourth all time in GSC coaching wins. 

After Powell’s retirement, LU men’s basketball went through a heavy downslide.  The team faced several coaching changes and dismal seasons.  LU began to regain respectability during the magical and history making 1977-1978 season.  The season also marked a time of tragedy.  On January 14, 1978, the team had just defeated Nicholls State in a conference match-up when they learned head coach Ken Brackett died after a long battle with [[cancer]].  A few weeks prior, Brackett was forced to take a medical leave as his condition began to weaken.  Artie McIntosh, who had been serving as the interim head coach in Brackett’s absence, took over coaching duties for the remainder of that season.  McIntosh, along with the trio of Rodney McKeever, Perry Smith and Cheyenne Jones, helped complete Brackett’s dramatic turnaround of the team finishing 18-8.   Prior to his arrival in 1976, the team had only won 22 total games in three seasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1817&amp;dat=19790128&amp;id=D0cgAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=4p4EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4982,5909716|title=New football coach Frank North brings optimism to Livingston program|date=1979-01-28|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=18F|accessdate=2010-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In Brackett’s first season, the Tigers finished 10-16 which was their best record since the 1973-1974 season.  McKeever garnered First Team All-Gulf South Conference honors while Jones earned second team honors.  The team as a whole finished second in the GSC with an 11-4 conference record.  LU also earned a trip to the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] Men’s Basketball Tournament for the first in school history.  The team opened tournament play in a South Regional match-up against [[Florida A&amp;M University]].  FAMU was heavily favored because of the game being played in Orlando, Florida.  Despite that, LU gave the Rattlers all they could handle before coming up short in a 72-69 nail biter.  With the loss, the Tigers played in a [[consolation game]] against [[Augusta State University|Augusta College]] which also resulted in a classic finish.  LU came away with a 91-90 victory.
 
After the season, LU hired [[Wichita State University|Wichita State]] assistant head coach, Ed Murphy, as the new head coach and athletic director.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1891&amp;dat=19780423&amp;id=EXQpAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=TdYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5413,3609671|title=Murphy is new cage coach at Livingston University|date=1978-04-23|publisher=''The Gadsden Times''|page=38|accessdate=2010-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  One of the top recruits Murphy brought in his first season was big man Tony Andre.  With his signing, Perry Smith and Cheyenne Jones were able to once again form a big three and hoped to fill a void after McKeever’s graduation.  In his first season, Murphy was able to keep up the previous season’s momentum as the team finished 15-11 and third in the GSC.  However, they failed to earn their second straight trip the NCAA tournament.  Jones was named the First Team All-Gulf Conference.  Andre was named to the Second Team.  The following season, Murphy picked up his second major freshman acquisition with the signing of Will Cotchery.  Cotchery allowed LU to immediately fill the presence left by Cheyenne Jones.  However, the 1979-1980 campaign was a forgetful one as the team took a step back.  Cotchery and Andre did not perform up to expectations.  Senior Perry Smith was the lone bright spot for the team.  He later earned First Team All-GSC Conference honors for the first time in his career.  LU as a team, meanwhile, finished fifth in the conference and 14-12 overall.  Murphy’s third season at the helm started off with his third straight major freshman acquisition as he recruited Dennis Williams to play Tiger men’s basketball.  He also picked up Randy Terry, who was a prospect from Jones County Junior College, to replace Smith at shooting guard.  Terry was a native of nearby [[Tuscaloosa, Alabama|Tuscaloosa]] and known for his phenomenal shooting ability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1817&amp;dat=19800514&amp;id=YC8dAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Ap4EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3869,3224278|title=Randy Terry:  Shooting star with freebies|date=1980-05-14|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=18F|accessdate=2010-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  That season was a huge step in the right direction for LU basketball.  Williams, Cotchery, Andre, and Terry formed a solid core, which carried the team to a 19-9 season.  Cotchery and Andre received First Team All-GSC Conference honors.  Williams was named the GSC Freshman of the Year.  Murphy was named the GSC Coach of the Year.  Although the team was successful, they still finished third in the conference and failed to reach the NCAA tournament for a third straight season.

The team finally struck gold in the 1981-1982 season, finishing 20-10 and winning the GSC championship for the first time in school history.  Cotchery was named the tournament MVP.  He also earned First Team All-GSC Conference honors along with teammates Randy Terry and Marvin Wesley.  Murphy was once again named GSC Coach of the Year.  The conference championship earned LU their first trip back to the NCAA Division II Men’s Basketball Tournament since 1978. In similar fashion to their last NCAA tournament trip, the South Regional was once again hosted by a Florida school.  This time around, it was [[Florida Southern College|Florida Southern]].  Their appearance in the tournament also had an atmosphere of déjà vu.  The Tigers first game was against Biscayne College, who was also a local team.  Despite the crowd being heavily behind BC, this time around, LU was greatly prepared for the challenges and obstacles they faced.  Cotchery and the gang fought from beginning to end as they walked away with a 75-72 victory.  The victory earned the Tigers a regional match-up against host and defending Division II national champions.  It would go down as one of the best games in NCAA Division II Men’s Basketball Tournament history.  Both teams were locked in a defensive battle for most of the game.  FSU carried a desire to repeat as champions and refused to lose on their home court.  LU, on the other hand, was trying to earn their first ever NCAA championship in school history.  The game eventually went into three [[Overtime (sports)|overtimes]].  After a long and hard fought battle, FSU came out victorious 86-79.  That game would mark the last NCAA tournament appearance to date for LU.  With the departures of Andre and Terry, Cotchery carried the team on his back during his senior season.  The team finished with an 18–9 record and runner-up finish in the GSC.  Cotchery earned another First Team conference honor.  That season would also be the last at LU for Murphy who resigned at the end of the 1982-1983 campaign to take over at GSC rival [[Delta State University|Delta State]].  He coached LU for five seasons.  Murphy is currently ranked second in the school’s record book with 86 wins coaching and 41 GSC victories.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/2009-10_uwa_men_s_basketball_media_guide|title=2009-2010 West Alabama Men's Basketball Media Guide|pages=43–51|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Two years after Murphy’s departure, former assistant coach Rick Reedy took over the program in time for the 1984-1985 season.  Former Tiger standout Tony Andre also joined him as an assistant coach.  After three dismal seasons to start his career at the helm, Reedy got the Tigers going in a positive direction during the 1987-1988 season.  The team finished 18-9 and tied for fifth place in the GSC.  Over the years, Reedy became known as a good recruiter as he brought many talented players to Livingston.  A majority of those players currently hold accomplishments in the UWA record book.  Despite the talent, Reedy only had eight winning seasons during his 23 seasons as the coach.  Also, during his tenure, the team finished in the GSC top 3 only three times.  In 1993, the Gulf South Conference underwent a huge expansion with the addition of ten new members.  The change allowed the GSC to divide into two separate divisions called East and West.  For two years, the Tigers were apart of the West division.  They moved to the East after [[University of Arkansas at Monticello|Arkansas-Monticello]], [[Southern Arkansas University|Southern Arkansas]], [[Arkansas Tech University|Arkansas Tech]], and [[University of Montevallo|Montevallo]] joined the conference in 1995.  Also, Jacksonville State and Mississippi College departed, thus leaving the conference with 18 members.  Reedy’s best conference record came during 1992-1993 when they earned an 8-4 record and finished as the GSC runner-up.   In the 1991-1992 season, the Tigers earned the school's largest margin of victory with a 61-point win over Selma.  The 2004-2005 team finished a game over .500 at 14-13, which was the last winning season for the Tigers.  In Reedy's final season, the team finished 10-17.  The 23 seasons he spent at the helm earned him the honor of UWA’s longest-tenured men’s basketball coach.  Upon retirement, he ranked first in the UWA history books with 276 overall wins and 116 of those coming in conference play.

After nearly a quarter century, a new face emerged as Eddie McCarter was hired to take Reedy's place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070308/NEWS/703080361|title=McCarter new basketball coach at UWA
|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2007-03-08|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  McCarter’s first recruiting class featured Ryan Cross and Daniel Scott.  Both were on the list of Alabama’s top players.  However, academics put a damper in their recruitment.  McCarter also brought along Roderick Ollie from UAB.  All three were red-shirted their first season.  Overall, the roster was made up of mostly new faces and a few holdovers from the Reedy era.  The McCarter era began on the road at Stillman where UWA registered an 88-82 win.  It became apparent after a while that the season was one of rebuilding.  With a lack of team chemistry and other issues, the team finished with a 10-17 mark.  The Tigers saw improvement in McCarter’s second season.  However, the roster was once again filled with new faces.  Cross and fellow redshirt freshman Jacquezz Brown left the team.  Ollie, Maurice Naylor, Glenn Miles, and Kevin Johnson left the team as well.  The biggest acquisition was [[Troy, Alabama|Troy]] native Jason Swanson.  Swanson had previously played at nearby Shelton State Community College where he was a two-year starter. The 6'7&quot; forward averaged 16.8 points a game and was also known for his rebounding, which was an area McCarter heavily emphasized.  Brian Murphy, the Tigers leading scorer in 2007-2008, suffered a torn ACL before the season and was given a medical redshirt.  His injury left McCarter in need of a new go to scorer which he had hoped to find in newcomers Herman Mains, Jamaine Nance, Terrence Benson and Chris Davis.  UWA had an up and down start to the season.  The team could never find a consistence rhythm.  In similar fashion to McCarter’s first year as the coach, the team never developed a strong chemistry, and it strongly showed once again on the court.  Despite that, the Tigers finished the regular season 13-13 and clinched their first GSC tournament appearance since the 1997-1998 season. The excitement was short lived as Harding eliminated UWA in the opening round.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulfsouthconference.org/news.asp?sport=Men's%20Basketball&amp;id=343388|title=2009 GSC Men's Basketball Tournament Home Page|publisher=''Gulf South Conference''|date=2007-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  McCarter added nine and returned five for the 2009-2010 campaign.  The team also featured three redshirt freshmen.  McCarter also once again lost several key players who decided to transfer including Daniel Scott.  This year’s squad was noticeably much improved over the two previous teams.  However, they never played up to potential.  The Tigers carried the momentum and a lead in almost every game they lost but was often defeated after their opponent staged a late rally.  Swanson led the team most of the way leading them in almost every category.  Newcomers Richard Sirju and Alquan Mendenhall also gave the team a major lift.  The season also saw the emergence of redshirt freshman Ryan Fitch.  Fitch broke into the starting lineup a couple games into the season.  McCarter will likely look to replace Jason Swanson going into the next season. The Tigers concluded this year’s season with a 13–14 record. However, after a loss to [[University of Alabama at Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville]] during the season's final game, UWA was eliminated from earning a second straight berth in the GSC tournament.  Swanson earned First Team All-GSC honors which occurred for the first team since 2005 when Stan Gill received the honor.

The 2010-2011 campaign opened with a home match-up against Carver Bible College.  Alquan Mendenhall, Jonathan Griffin, Ryan Fitch, and Richard Dixon led the scoring as each topped double figures in the opening triumph.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101114/NEWS/101119826|title=West Alabama men beat Carver Bible
|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2010-11-14|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers dropped their first road game at [[Jacksonville State University|Jacksonville State]] but posted consecutive home wins over [[Huntingdon College|Huntingdon]] and [[Concordia College (Alabama)|Concordia]]. UWA moved to 3-1 but endured a rough stretch to close out 2010.  The team faced each team from the Gulf South Conference West Division and came away with a pair of wins. The men came up short to Georgia Southwestern to kick off 2011 in the second to last non-conference game of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110107/NEWS/110109713|title=UWA falls to Georgia Southwestern|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-01-07|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers went 4–6 to open conference play including a road thriller at [[University of West Florida|West Florida]].  The win was the team's first season sweep of the Argonauts since 1996–1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110217/NEWS/110219653?tc=ar|title=UWA men earn sweep against West Florida
|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-02-17|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; They stepped out of the GSC to face [[Oakwood University|Oakwood]] and were victorious in that one, posting 90 points to rout their opponent.  A few days later, the men knocked off [[University of West Georgia|West Georgia]] and concluded the season hosting [[Valdosta State University|Valdosta State]]. The Tigers fell by two points to finish their season 11–15 overall and 5–7 in the Gulf South Conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110227/NEWS/110229604?tc=ar|title=UWA finishes season with loss|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-02-27|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2011, the Department of Athletics announced the hiring of Mike Newell to take over the reins of the program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2011/04/12/newell-tabbed-uwa-mens-coach/|title=Newell tabbed UWA men’s coach|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2011-04-12|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Women's basketball ===
The first known University of West Alabama women's basketball team is currently unknown.  However, detailed season results first became available for the 1978-1979 season.  That year, the Tigers struggled to a 5-16 mark.  The following three years provided many highlights for the program when the women went on a hot streak.  During 1979-1980, the team put up 24 wins to only 12 losses.  1980-1981 got even better when UWA tallied a 25-4 overall record.  The Tigers won 12 of their final 13 games and collected an impressive 11-game winning streak.  The old saying, &quot;third time's a charm&quot; rang true in 1981-1982.  The program set a school record collecting 30 wins to only seven defeats.  The team fought hard all year, and it showed because of the seven losses, five came by 10 points or less.  The 30-win season ranks first in the history books to this day.  The successful season also saw UWA claim the GSC Championship.  Afterwards, a cold snap rendered the Tigers' chances the next couple of seasons before more achievements were reached.  The 1985-1986 campaign opened with six straight wins en route to an 18-9 record for UWA.  Another outstanding year followed suit in 1986-1987 as the women totaled 19 victories.  The winning ways returned to campus after the team brushed the .500 mark a few seasons later.  Over the course of the next three seasons, the Tigers tallied 51 wins and saw defeat only 29 times.  The 20-win plateau was achieved in 1997-1998 for the first time since the school's 30-win year.  Amanda Marks came on board in 2001-2002 leading UWA to another historic year.  UWA's first-ever berth in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Tournament came this year.  With a 22-6 overall record and 14-2 mark in the GSC, the Tigers claimed the East Division championship.  They headed to the tournament and picked up their first win there since 1987.  Although they lost their next tournament game to [[Delta State University|Delta State]], they were rewarded with a trip to the NCAA Regional.  A last-second shot rimmed out at the buzzer ending a magical run in Marks' first season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/media_guide_print|title=2009-10 Women's Basketball Media Guide|pages=57–60, 62|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The team finished below .500 the next season but rebounded in 2003-2004 to notch another 22-win season.  Marks earned her 150th career win in a matchup against [[The University of Alabama in Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville]].  UWA claimed the fifth spot in the season's initial South Region rankings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/news/2004/jan/23/uwa-ranked-in-regional-poll/|title=UWA ranked in regional poll|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2004-01-23|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers earned another East Division championship by virtue of a 12-2 conference record.  They travelled to [[Rollins College|Rollins]] to take part in the NCAA Tournament and played a different hand this time around making history in the process.  UWA garnered their first ever NCAA win narrowly escaping against [[Christian Brothers University|Christian Brothers]] in [[Overtime (sports)|overtime]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/news/2004/oct/23/uwa-basketball-season-less-than-a-month-away/|title=UWA basketball season less than a month away|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2004-10-23|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately, the season came to a close at the hands of Rollins when they fell short 63-45.  The 2006-2007 season looked to be another promising year with the women getting off to a hot start.  They were 12-3 through 15 games, but a late season collapse and early tournament exit ended a 19-9 year.  Marks tallied career win #200 with a road win at [[University of Montevallo|Montevallo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070128/NEWS/701280370|title=UWA coach Amanda Marks gets 200th victory|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2007-01-28|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Tigers could not get past .500 either of the following years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://issuu.com/uwa_athletics/docs/media_guide_print|title=2009-10 Women's Basketball Media Guide|page=61|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2009-08-01|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2009-2010 season was a rebuilding year for the Tigers.  After struggling early on, UWA ended the regular season on a high note winning six of their final eight.  The women finished 5-5 in GSC action and qualified for the conference tournament.  After trailing by only seven at [[halftime]], the Tigers could not overcome a tough Delta State squad.  Their season concluded with an overall record of 9-19.  Latashia Greer was named the East Division's Co-Player of the Year and became the program's first-ever player to receive the honor.

Craig Roden took over for Amanda Marks for the 2010-2011 season.  An alum of the University, Roden came back for his second stint as Head Coach.  He previously led the squad in the 1980's.  The season began with a home matchup against [[Barry University|Barry]] from the [[Sunshine State Conference]] in a region game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wtok.com/sports/headlines/UWA_Women_Rolling_Along_112974199.html?ref=199|title=UWA Women Rolling Along|last=Adam|first=Nick|publisher=''WTOK News 11''|date=2011-01-05|accessdate=2010-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; UWA came away with an eight-point win to turn away the Buccaneers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.barry.edu/athletics/articles/details.aspx?ID=18052|title=Women's Basketball Falls In Opener To Tigers|publisher=''Barry University Sports Information''|date=2004-11-13|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers went on to post three more victories to start the season 4-0.  In the third game, UWA upset '''#1''' ranked [[Arkansas Tech University|Arkansas Tech]] in Livingston.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20101128/NEWS/101129675|title=ROUNDUP: UWA women upset No. 1 Arkansas Tech|date=2010-11-28|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The women almost pulled off another upset but fell by two to '''#1''' ranked Delta State at home.  The team dropped their following game to [[Talladega College]] before reeling off ten straight wins.  With their win over [[University of West Florida|West Florida]] in January 2011, the Tigers improved to 14-2, the best record after 16 games in program history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2011/01/21/dale-fueling-uwa/|title=Dale fueling UWA|last=Smith|first=Jeremy|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2011-01-21|accessdate=2010-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; UWA posted a 4-6 record to close out regular season play and claimed the East Division's third seed.  They opened the Gulf South Conference Tournament against West Division two seed Delta State but dropped a tough four-point decision.  The squad posted an 18-9 overall record and went 6-6 in conference action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110304/NEWS/110309874|title=UWA basketball team ousted in Gulf South Conference Tournament
|date=2011-03-04|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mystee Dale, a transfer from East Central Community College in Mississippi, dazzled for UWA posting several accomplishments during the season.  She garnered six Player of the Week accolades, the most of any player in the entire conference.  Dale was named the GSC Player of the Year and led the conference in scoring with an impressive 21.2 points per game.  She connected on almost 87 percent of her free throw attempts, which was also the highest mark in the GSC.  Dale also finished in the top ten of seven other statistical categories.  Latasha Greer and LaShandra McCoy also shined by putting up effective statistics to aid the turnaround from a year ago.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2011/02/28/uwas-dale-named-gsc-player-of-year/|title=UWA’s Dale named GSC Player of Year
|last=Smith|first=Jeremy|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2011-02-28|accessdate=2010-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dale was also named to the Daktronics All-South Region team.  She was further recognized as UWA's first-ever All-American in the NCAA era.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/2011/03/25/dale-named-all-american/|title=Dale named all-american|date=2011-03-25|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Spring sports ==
=== Baseball ===
The University of West Alabama baseball team is arguably the school's best sport.  It started in the 1940s, but the first season results were not printed until the 1964 season.  That year, the Tigers finished two games over .500 at 12–10.  At this time, records are not known for the 1965–1967 seasons.  The following six years were all winning seasons, and UWA won 153 games out of 211 for a .725 percentage.  They closed out the 1970s with only two losing seasons.  After dominating the previous decade, the team ran into speed bumps{{What|date=October 2011}} during the 1980s.  In the early 1990s, the team returned to their winning ways going 30-24 in 1990 and 32-13-1 in 1991.  1992 proved to be one of the most historic seasons in school history for a number of reasons.  That year, UWA notched 37 wins, which was a school record at the time.  They also brought the first [[Gulf South Conference|GSC]] Championship trophy to Livingston.  The highlights did not stop there as the Tigers earned a bid to the South Central Regional.  A close win over rival [[University of North Alabama|North Alabama]] in the regional championship sent UWA to its only [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] [[College World Series]].  Their chances for the school's first baseball national championship ended in tough luck as they dropped two of three games.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/sports/2010/2/2/BB_0202105949.aspx?path=baseball|title=2010 UWA Baseball Media Guide|pages=41–45|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2010-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current head coach for the Tigers is Gary Rundles.  He took the reins beginning in 2001 and has been instrumental in his tenure at UWA.  He led the team to a .500 finish his first year and encountered his only losing season in 2002.  The 2000s without question{{Fact|date=October 2011}} were the school's best decade.  In 2003, the Tigers pulled off one of the greatest upsets in school history.{{Fact|date=October 2011}}  They rallied from a seven-run deficit to knock off #20 [[University of Alabama|Alabama]] in [[Tuscaloosa, Alabama|Tuscaloosa]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tidefans.com/forums/baseball/3890-diamond-notes-west-alabama-rallies-upset-alabama-9-7-a.html|title=West Alabama Rallies to Upset Alabama, 9-7|publisher=''Diamond Notes''|date=2003-04-02|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers finished 2003 with a 31-24 record and improved that to 33-22 in 2004.  In 2005, memories from the 1992 season returned as the team had a record-setting year.  They earned their second GSC Championship and like before, it was done against North Alabama.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20050512/NEWS/505120354?tc=ar|title=UWA wins baseball championship|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2005-05-12|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers earned the automatic bid to the South Central Regional, but their run abruptly ended the season at 45-19.  UWA came close to repeating in 2006 but lost to [[Southern Arkansas University|Southern Arkansas]] in the final inning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20060512/NEWS/605120347?tc=ar|title=UWA falls in GSC tourney title game, 6-5|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2006-05-12|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the South Central Regional, the Tigers knocked out top seed [[Abilene Christian University|Abilene Christian]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20060520/NEWS/605200345?tc=ar|title=UWA beats top seed to avoid elimination|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2006-05-12|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, the team was eliminated by [[Incarnate Word College|Incarnate Word]].  UWA's record wound up at 42-22.  During the season, the Tigers set a school record dismantling [[Lincoln Memorial University|Lincoln Memorial]] with a program-best 29 runs in one game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20060416/NEWS/604160372?tc=ar|title=UWA sets record with 29 runs in victory|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2006-04-16|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

2007 saw UWA claim the East championship at 14–4 in the division and another berth in the GSC Championship.  However, it was not enough as [[University of West Florida|West Florida]] took the honors cutting the season short at 41-16.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070510/NEWS/705100350|title=UWA falls to West Florida in GSC tourney|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2007-05-10|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another monumental season came during 2008 as more records were either tied or broken.  The season's highlight was when UWA earned the school's highest ranking ever at '''#2''' in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseballnews.com/polls/divII/archives/2008/ncaadivIIpoll3-17-08.htm|title=NCAA Division II Poll:  3-17-08|publisher=''Collegiate Baseball Newspaper''|date=2008-03-17|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; After an early exit from the GSC Tournament, the team saw its season come to an end in the South Central Regional.  However, with a 45-13 mark, they became the first program in the Gulf South Conference to have four consecutive 40-win seasons.  UWA's record during that span was 173-70 for a .712 winning percentage.  In 2009, the Tigers knocked off '''#1''' [[University of Tampa|Tampa]] and later reeled off a 12-game winning streak.  During that streak, Gary Rundles claimed his 300th win with the program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090323/NEWS/903229896/1015?Title=SMALL-COLLEGE-BASKETBALL-West-Alabama-s-Rundles-gets-300th-victory|title=West Alabama’s Rundles gets 300th victory
|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-03-23|accessdate=2010-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; They went on to clinch the East Division title with a 14-2 conference record.&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090426/NEWS/904269974?tc=ar|title=UWA baseball claims GSC East title|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-04-26|accessdate=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the NCAA South Regional, the team ousted [[Barry University|Barry]] but ultimately fell short to Southern Arkansas.  UWA closed the 2010 season on a high note by winning their last four and ending the year 26-17 overall.  The Tigers endured a rough 2011 season finishing at 19-22.  The team's finish was the first time in nine years that the team failed to have a winning season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110502/NEWS/110509954?p=2&amp;tc=pg|title=UWA ROUNDUP: Tigers clinch spot in GSC Tournament|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-05-02|accessdate=2010-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Softball ===
The first-ever University of West Alabama [[fast-pitch softball]] team was christened in 1986.  The Tigers managed to win only one game during their inaugural season.  After Wayne Dees left, Liz Kelley took over leading the team to a 17-25 record in 1987.  For her efforts, she claimed Gulf South Conference Coach of the Year honors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=by8zAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Z6UEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4705,4710173&amp;dq=livingston+university+softball&amp;hl=en|title=League leaders keep records unblemished|last=Prince|first=David|date=1987-05-17|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Liz Kelley then left to take a similar position at [[Miami University]] in [[Ohio]].  Janet Koenig (later Janet Montgomery), a 1986 graduate of [[University of Wisconsin-Parkside|Wisconsin-Parkside]], was selected as the new head coach.  The next four years would be some of the best the program would see in their history.  UWA won four consecutive GSC Championship crowns from 1988 through 1991.  During this span, the Tigers were an outstanding 146-62 for a .701 winning percentage.  In 1991, five team members were named to the GSC Spring Sports All-Academic Team.  They not only succeeded in the classroom but also on the field with dominating statistics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=KTgdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=xKUEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6036,165189&amp;dq=livingston+university+softball&amp;hl=en|title=League honors LU stars|date=1991-07-02|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=3B|accessdate=2010-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992, the '''#16''' ranked Tigers swept a doubleheader from '''#12''' [[Valdosta State University|Valdosta State]] and played a hard-fought championship game.  Unfortunately, they could not pick up their fifth consecutive GSC championship falling 1-0 to [[Jacksonville State University|Jacksonville State]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=oDQdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=kKUEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6780,7613164&amp;dq=livingston+university+softball&amp;hl=en|title=Tigers sweep Valdosta; JSU eliminates Lady Tigers|date=1992-04-26|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=8C|accessdate=2010-02-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The next four seasons proved tough for the team as they encountered losing records and hovered around the .500 mark.  However, in 1995, the team swept through the GSC Tournament field to notch their fifth tournament title.

The 1997 season brought many highlights as UWA dominated the GSC Tournament to win their sixth crown.  The Tigers then received news they had been selected to play in the South Regional.  It was the program's first and only berth in the NCAA Tournament.  UWA made the trip to [[Miami Shores, Florida|Miami Shores]] on the campus of [[Barry University|Barry]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=UDsdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=BaYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6786,1024906&amp;dq=livingston+university+softball&amp;hl=en|title=UWA softball selected to play in regionals|date=1997-05-06|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=3C|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; After posting a 1-2 record, their season came to a close with 32 wins to only 18 losses.  During the 1999 season, UWA dropped the first game of a doubleheader to [[Mississippi University for Women]].  They rebounded in the second game with a no-hitter to knock off their opponent in a low-scoring affair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=t8wdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=MqYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4965,5519909&amp;dq=university+of+west+alabama+softball&amp;hl=en|title=Lenz pitches UWA to a twinbill split|date=1999-04-26|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=3C|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tigers encountered tough seasons from 2000 to 2006.  Janet Montgomery's final season as head coach came in 2007.  She led the team to a 26-33 record and then took over athletic duties as associate athletic director.  Assistant head coach Will Atkinson was promoted to take over the program in 2008.  In his first season, UWA finished at .500 with a 29-29 mark.  In the Tigers' regular season finale, they rallied to knock off '''#2''' [[University of Alabama in Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville]] at the UWA Softball Complex.  The season's other highlight came when Brittany McGee tossed the program's first-ever perfect game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/news/2008/apr/18/demopolis-native-pitches-perfect-game-for-uwa/|title=Demopolis native pitches perfect game for UWA|publisher=''Demopolis Times''|date=2008-04-18|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Seven players earned conference honors for their season efforts.

When 2009 rolled around, the highlights kept on coming in Will Atkinson's second year.  The Tigers recorded their best start ever at 25-2 steamrolling several opponents along the way.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/sports/2010/2/25/SB_0225101401.aspx?path=softball|title=2010 UWA Softball Media Guide|pages=45–53|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department''|date=2010-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the remarkable run, they put together two seven-game winning streaks and an 11-game winning streak.  When conference play started, the team encountered a few speed bumps when facing [[University of West Florida]] and Alabama-Huntsville.  UWA got hot again at the annual GSC Crossover in [[Decatur, Alabama|Decatur]].  The Tigers posted a 6-1 record against West Division foes falling only to [[University of Arkansas at Monticello|Arkansas-Monticello]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090407/NEWS/904069881|title=UWA softball splits two at Crossover|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-04-07|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a fourth place finish in the East Division, the team made their first appearance at the GSC Tournament since 1997.  In a rain-shortened tournament, their season concluded with a loss to [[Arkansas Tech University|Arkansas Tech]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090502/NEWS/905019898|title=UWA drops softball tournament opener|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-05-02|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; UWA tied the school record for wins with a 42-17 record and placed six players on the All-GSC squad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090430/NEWS/904299919|title=Six UWA sofball players earn conference honors|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-04-30|accessdate=2010-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the team's 12 conference wins equaled the school record, and 80 [[home run]]s broke a school record.  That number was good for third in the GSC and sixth in the entire country.  The Tigers posted a 38-23 record for the 2010 season.  In 2011, UWA won the NCAA South Two Regional to advance to the school's first ever South Super Regional at Alabama-Huntsville.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110517/NEWS/110519743|title=UWA advances to Division II Super Regional|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-05-17|accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team posted impressive wins over [[Rollins College|Rollins]], [[University of Tampa|Tampa]], and Arkansas-Monticello.  The Tigers defeated two top 15 teams in succession to set up their regional title game berth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110515/NEWS/110519787|title=UWA softball team advances to regional title game|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-05-15|accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; After claiming game 1 in the best-of-three series, the Tigers fell short to end their dream season at 38-19.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20110522/NEWS/110529869|title=UWA’s postseason run comes to an end
|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2011-05-22|accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Men's and women's tennis ===
The University of West Alabama men's tennis team began in 1974.  The women followed suit a decade later in 1984.  Both programs were dropped in 1997.  After an eight-year hiatus, the Tigers were reinstated in the fall of [[2005]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://itatenniscom.siteprotect.net/news_archives04.htm|title=Univ. of West Alabama reinstates men's and women's tennis|date=2004-08-01|publisher=''Intercollegiate Tennis Association''|accessdate=2010-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Howard R. Vaughan Tennis Complex was added to the University campus in time for UWA to begin the 2006 season.  Rod Hartzog was chosen as the head coach and went right to work recruiting players.  After a grueling schedule, both teams had many wins to show for their efforts.  The season's highlight came when the Tigers swept [[University of Alabama in Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville]], and the women dispatched [[University of Montevallo|Montevallo]] in fine fashion at the GSC Jamboree.  In 2007, as part of Super Tiger Day festivities, the men and women both claimed victories over [[Transylvania University|Transylvania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=AJI1AAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=oxMGAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1462,2070850&amp;dq=university+of+west+alabama+tennis&amp;hl=en|title=West Alabama tennis teams sweeps Transylvania|date=2007-03-22|publisher=''The Democrat-Reporter''|page=10|accessdate=2010-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spring Break saw the Tigers match up against several nationally-ranked opponents.  UWA fought hard in each match but could not come up with a win in any of them.  The women's final match came at [[University of Montevallo|Montevallo]] where they picked up their only conference win.  Their season ended at 5-12 overall, 1-4 in the conference.  The UWA men concluded their season at the GSC Tournament to close a 7-11 mark and 1-3 in GSC action.

After two short seasons as head coach, Rod Hartzog resigned paving the way for Glen Fanelli to take over as head coach.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=tCIlAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=2BQGAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=615,2045549&amp;dq=university+of+west+alabama+tennis&amp;hl=en|title=West Alabama hires Fanelli|date=2007-06-14|publisher=''The Democrat-Reporter''|page=7|accessdate=2010-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, both the men and women got off to impressive starts.  After seven matches, UWA's men stood undefeated, while the women had only dropped one match.  The teams' first conference action took them to Alabama-Huntsville.  The Tigers fought hard and came away with close 5-4 margins in both matches.  The rest of GSC action proved difficult as division foes [[Valdosta State University|Valdosta State]] and [[University of West Florida|West Florida]] were both ranked in the nation's top 5.  In the initial NCAA South Region rankings, the Tiger women placed sixth with the women right behind at seventh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20080404/NEWS/246315915|title=UWA tennis teams ranked|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2008-04-04|accessdate=2010-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both teams went on to qualify for the GSC Tournament where UWA's women made their first-ever appearance.  Unfortunately, they dropped both of their matches, but the Tiger men picked up a win against [[Harding University|Harding]] in the consolation semi-finals.  Glen Fanelli's first season came to an end as he led both teams to winning records.  On the women's side, they posted a school-record 15 wins.  The men followed close behind with 13 victories to their credit.

A conference road trip sent UWA to [[Pensacola, Florida|Pensacola]] for the 2009 opener where the Tigers dropped matches to nationally-ranked West Florida.  Both the men and women notched wins in their home openers against [[Mississippi College]].  UWA then hit the road again for a tough ten-match span.  Along the way, they faced several region opponents and had much success.  The Tiger men won their first nine before dropping the finale to a tough [[Columbus State University|Columbus State]] squad.  The women picked up four victories, and both teams returned to Livingston after several days away from campus.  In front of their home crowd, the Tigers picked up key wins and turned back [[University of Missouri in St. Louis|Missouri-St. Louis]].  The regular season concluded with a four-match homestand and two makeup matches in [[Tennessee]].  UWA's men and women both swept region opponents [[Stillman College|Stillman]] and [[Tuskegee University|Tuskegee]] in 9-0 fashion.  For the second consecutive year, the women returned to the GSC Tournament, but the men did not earn a bid.  Despite their efforts, the Tiger women ended the season just under the .500 mark at 14-15.  The men's squad received a bid to the NCAA South Regional for the first time in school history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20090501/NEWS/905019984|title=UWA will play in Division II tennis|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|date=2009-05-01|accessdate=2010-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The excitement was short lived when [[Rollins College|Rollins]] eliminated them, but their 18-7 record set a school record for wins.  In the 2010 slate, the women finished at 16-11 overall, as the men are 18-9 and have earned their second consecutive NCAA Tournament bid.  With a 2-2 conference record, the Tiger women earned their third consecutive berth in the GSC Tournament.  Their 16 wins set a school record for wins in a season breaking the mark set in 2008.  The UWA men earned the program's first win in NCAA Tournament action with a close win over Alabama-Huntsville in the South Regional.  The win also broke a school record for victories in a season as the men recorded their 19th on the year.  In 2011, the Tiger men finished with a 14-9 overall mark.  The women's squad eclipsed their 16 wins in 2010 by earning a 17-9 record and going 2-2 in conference action.

== Other sports ==
=== Men's and women's cross country ===
The first University of West Alabama cross country teams made their way to campus in 1997.  Early in their inaugural campaign, the teams took part in the [[Delta State University|Delta State]] Cross Country Invitational.  Both teams put up great efforts as the men finished third, and the women earned a fourth place nod.  The entire men's team and two of the women all posted top 25 finishes at the file-mile event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=CYMfAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=FqYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1411,5738044&amp;dq=university+of+west+alabama+cross+country&amp;hl=en|title=UWA cross country places fourth|date=1997-09-30|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=3C|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, results from the 1998-2004 seasons are unavailable.  2005 opened at the Argo Invitational in [[Pensacola, Florida|Pensacola]] where the Tiger men garnered 101 points overall.  The women's team was unable to compete due to injuries.  The season concluded at the GSC Championships with an 11th place nod on the men's side and a 16th place finish for the women at the GSC Championships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20051023/NEWS/510230355?tc=ar|title=Tigers wrap up cross-country season|date=2005-10-23|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the spring of 2006, Dr. Don Medeiros came on board as the program's first-ever fulltime head coach.  UWA tallied fourth place finishes for both teams as the men earned 104 points, and the women followed suit at 105.  At the NCAA South Regional in [[Memphis, Tennessee|Memphis]], the Tigers picked up 14th and 22nd place finishes.

Three new members came on board in time for 2007.  Two were from the state of [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], and the other was from [[Mississippi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20070516/NEWS/705160337?tc=ar|title=UWA signs three for cross country|date=2007-05-16|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The season commenced in fine fashion at the [[University of Southern Mississippi|Southern Mississippi]] Invitational when UWA's men won the event.  The highlights did not stop there as six Tiger individuals earned top 25 times.  The Tiger women were equally impressive as they raked in third place.  At the [[Mississippi State University|Mississippi State]] Invitational, UWA continued their hot start with a runner-up finish.  Two players received All-GSC honors to lead the men's team to a 13th place finish at the NCAA South Regional.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20071104/NEWS/71104011?tc=ar|title=UWA men 13th at cross country regional|date=2007-11-04|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; When 2008 rolled around, the NCAA awarded the program a Coaching Enhancement Grant and was one of only 18 [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] schools nationwide to receive the honor.  With that, Erin Heeder was hired as assistant head coach for the women's team.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20080816/NEWS/427683219?tc=ar|title=UWA hires cross country assistant|date=2008-08-16|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; A host of new faces for both teams kicked off the year at [[Mississippi College]].  Both squads were successful in their openers as the men and women completed the event in third and fourth, respectively.  Later, at the [[Auburn University|Auburn]] Invitational, their hard work paid off again with the Tiger men placing sixth and the women earning ninth place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=v5YnAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Mr0EAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2852,3416292&amp;dq=university+of+west+alabama+cross+country&amp;hl=en|title=West Alabama runners compete in Hoover|date=2008-10-24|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=3C|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the GSC Championships in [[Hoover, Alabama|Hoover]], the men of UWA were awarded sixth, while the women tallied a program-best 10th place.  Each team put the finishing touches on an exciting season at the NCAA South Regional.  A top-10 finish for the men and 13th place nod on the women's side closed the door on yet another successful season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20081109/NEWS/811090291?tc=ar|title=UWA cross country advances to championship|date=2008-11-09|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|accessdate=2010-02-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the success kept on rolling in for the Tigers.  In their first action at Southern Mississippi, the Tiger men outran their opponents to post first place honors.  UWA's women captured third at the event to get their season off to a good start as well.  A strong showing a few weeks later saw both squads finish in fourth at Mississippi State.  They almost knocked off their conference opponent [[University of Alabama in Huntsville|Alabama-Huntsville]].  In [[Jacksonville, Alabama|Jacksonville]] at the [[Jacksonville State University|Jacksonville State]] Foothills Invitational, the Tigers improved upon their previous marks by both posting third.  At the conference championship run, the women earned their highest ever finish in program history at fifth place.  The men followed close behind as they returned home in seventh place.  The 2009 season wrapped up in [[Tampa, Florida|Tampa]] as both sets of Tigers took part in the NCAA South Regional.

=== Men's and women's rodeo ===
The University of West Alabama rodeo teams were established in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=VTwdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=KaYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=6670,4949393&amp;dq=livingston+university&amp;hl=en|title=LU to field rodeo team|date=18 January 1995|publisher=''Tuscaloosa News''|page=6C|accessdate=8 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=qmAeAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=-scEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2075,2274449&amp;dq=livingston+university&amp;hl=en|title=Livingston adds rodeo as sport|date=18 January 1995|publisher=''Times Daily''|page=2C|accessdate=9 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their first-ever event took them to [[Southern Arkansas University|Southern Arkansas]].  David Rickman, a native of Tennessee was introduced by the University of West Alabama Trustees to lead the program.  The first teams were made up of 22 members including 17 men and five women.  The early stages of the rodeo arena began thanks in large part to boosters donating around $60,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=6zsdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=MaYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5026,3686895&amp;dq=west+alabama+rodeo&amp;hl=en|title=Rodeo Coach|last=Watkins|first=Ed|date=12 September 1995|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|page=5A|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1998, UWA competed at the Abraham-Baldwin Agricultural College Rodeo in [[Tifton, Georgia]].  Both the men's and women's teams racked in first place finishes at the event.  The men picked up 338 points, and the women earned 310 total.  A number of Tiger wranglers posted good showings in their respective events.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=ec4dAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=1KcEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5363,1435746&amp;dq=west+alabama+rodeo&amp;hl=en|title=Tiger Wranglers win rodeo titles|date=7 April 1998|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|page=10|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few seasons later, the rodeo teams took part in a regional rodeo showdown in [[Enid, Oklahoma]].  They faced qualifying teams from the Central Plains Region and put up very respectable numbers.  The UWA women ended the event in fourth place out of 20 teams.  The men were equally impressive and also placed fourth but out of 23 teams.  Head coach Jayson Schoenfeld commented that he was satisfied with each team's performances.  Both teams went on later that year to compete at the College National Finals Rodeo in [[Casper, Wyoming]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=hzwdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=LqYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2622,4864245&amp;dq=west+alabama+rodeo&amp;hl=en|title=Tiger Wranglers finish fourth in regional rodeo|date=22 May 2001|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|page=42|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following campaign, more highlights came for the Tiger wranglers.  UWA's men raked in back-to-back first place honors with the women following suit in impressive fashion.  Everyone on both teams chipped in to aid the cause and lead the Tigers to their good finishes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=ZD4dAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=gKYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5064,3929032&amp;dq=west+alabama+rodeo&amp;hl=en|title=West Alabama rodeo wins again|date=8 October 2002|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|page=42|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the summer of 2005, UWA competed at the College National Finals Rodeo in Casper with an outstanding turnout.  Seven players in all took part in the event.  The Tigers' regional placings propelled them to the finals with four women and three men making the long road trip.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.demopolistimes.com/news/2005/jun/08/uwa-rodeo-team-heads-to-nationals/?print|title=UWA Rodeo team heads to Nationals|date=8 June 2005|publisher=Demopolis Times|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every year, the people of Livingston get the unique opportunity to attend a rodeo in Livingston.  This is because the Tiger wranglers host the UWA College Rodeo Showdown at the Don C. Hines Rodeo Complex.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20051020/NEWS/510200340|title=Tiger Wranglers host for rodeo event
|date=20 October 2005|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Teams from all over make their way to Livingston for the annual event. As they had in 2005, the Tigers made the trek back to Casper for the College National Finals Rodeo.  The men garnered a 15th place finish with the women at 32nd.  UWA brought a second place finish in the nation back to Livingston for the bull riding event.  The steer wrestling event saw a solid fourth place finish.  On the women's side, the Tigers posted 12th place in barrel racing.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.tuscaloosanews.com/article/20060621/NEWS/606210350|title=UWA rodeo teams compete in nationals|date=21 June 2006|publisher=[[Tuscaloosa News]]|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The current head coach of the men's and women's rodeo teams is Chad Phipps.  An avid rodeo player throughout high school, Phipps was offered a scholarship to the [[University of Tennessee at Martin|University of Tennessee-Martin]].  In 2001 and 2002, he received special recognition from the team when he received [[most valuable player|MVP]] honors.  A native of [[Dalton, Georgia]], his career was cut short when a bull stepped on him.  Although he can no longer compete in bull riding, that did not keep him away from the sport.  After Jayson Schoenfeld left, he took over the Tiger wrangler program at UWA.  Since the inception of rodeo on the University campus, the Tiger women have won the Ozark Region championship five times.  The men have been runner-up three years.  Both teams finished in fifth place for the 2009 season.  They take part in ten events a year, five coming in the fall and the other five during the spring semester.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.alafarmnews.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=1845:rodeo-injury-propels-bullrider-into-college-coaching-career&amp;catid=1:news&amp;Itemid=23|title=Rodeo Injury Propels Bullrider into College Coaching Career|date=1 January 2010|publisher=''Turner Publishing''|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Tigers have seen their share of highlights, the University community lost one of their own in mid-2009.  Dr. Don C. Hines died on August 26 after battling cancer.  Dr. Hines made significant contributions during his tenure at UWA, most notably bringing rodeo to campus.  The rodeo complex on campus is named in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.uwa.edu/newsEvents/newsDetails.aspx?Channel=%2fChannels%2fAdmissions+and+Campus+Wide&amp;WorkflowItemID=91f23dbd-0274-452d-a62e-1a82d8ff0ca6|title=UWA community remembers Hines|last=Gordon|first=Meaghan|date=2009-08-28|publisher=''The University of West Alabama Public Relations''|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the fall semester, the UWA men have picked up 1,840 total points and sit in third place in the Ozark Region.  The Tiger women stake 315 points to their claim for a seventh place mark.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.collegerodeo.com/Rodeos/Regional_Standings.asp?Region=OZ|title=2009-2010 Ozark Region Standings|date=2 November 2009|publisher=''National Intercollegiate Rodeo Association''|accessdate=10 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both teams have kicked off the spring slate of their schedules.

== Athletic facilities ==
The University of West Alabama has several facilities on campus including outdoor stadiums and an indoor arena as well as training and practice facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uwaathletics.com/sports/2010/1/27/BB_0127104454.aspx?|title=University of West Alabama Athletics - UWA Athletic Facilities|publisher=''UWA Athletic Department|date=2010-01-01|accessdate=2010-02-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are as follows:

*'''Tiger Stadium''' is the home of the Tiger football team since 1952, but renovations have been completed in recent years.  The home side contains concrete bleachers and red chairback seats for fans who purchase reserved tickets or season passes.  A new scoreboard was added on the right side a few years back.  The Tiger Room, a place for Tiger Club members, is located underneath the bleachers.  Concessions can be found behind the bleachers on the home side.  The stadium saw a major renovation as a synthetic surface was recently installed.  The women's soccer program will play their home games at the stadium beginning in fall 2011.

*'''James P. Homer Fieldhouse''' is used primarily for athletic training purposes and adjacent to Tiger Stadium.  A weight room as well as coaches' offices are located inside.

*'''Pruitt Hall''' is the gymnasium for volleyball as well as the men's and women's basketball teams.  Coaches' offices can be found inside the building.  Major renovations including the locker rooms, bleachers, and floor have been completed in the last few years.  A new scorer's table was recently added as well.  Logos of the other GSC schools are placed on the walls behind the bleachers all around the gym.  Concessions are located outside the entrances as spectators walk in the doors.

*'''Tartt Field''' is the home of the Tiger baseball team.  Both sides of the field contain bleachers for spectators to sit.  More bleachers and the official pressbox can be found directly behind home plate.  Wooden decks for grilling and barbecuing are located beyond the outfield walls.  The home dugout and locker room also contains an upstairs area with a complete kitchen, bathrooms, game room, and living room.  Concessions are found directly beneath the pressbox.  The home side also contains the Dora Dahlberg Beard Indoor Practice Facility.

*The '''UWA Softball Complex''' is the home of the Tiger softball team.  A locker room has been recently built adjacent to the home dugout.  Batting cages can be found on both sides of the field.  Bleachers for spectators are located on either side.  Like Tartt Field, the official pressbox and more bleachers are located behind home plate.  Concessions can be found behind the pressbox in a separate building.  Flags representing the other GSC schools fly behind the center field wall.

*The '''Dora Dahlberg Beard Indoor Practice Facility''' is a state-of-the-art practice facility used by the baseball and softball teams.  It contains pitching mounds, batting cages, and weight stations.  It was recently completed a few years back.  The building can be located adjacent to Tartt Field on the home side.

*The '''Howard R. Vaughan Tennis Complex''' was completed in 2006 in time for the restoration of the men's and women's tennis programs.  It contains six lighted tennis courts.  Each has its own scoring system to keep track of matches.  Bleachers for spectators can be found on the opposite side of the courts.

*The '''Don C. Hines Rodeo Complex''' is used by the men's and women's rodeo teams.  It contains an indoor arena with bleachers for spectators to watch events.  The building is the home of the annual UWA Rodeo Showdown held in the fall semester of each year.

*The '''UWA Cross Country Facility''' can be found close to Lake LU on campus.  It contains locker rooms for the men's and women's cross country teams.  There are also areas reserved for running and practicing.

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.uwaathletics.com/ UWA Athletics Homepage]
*[http://www.facebook.com/pages/Livingston-AL/UWA-Athletics/287361361532/ UWA Athletics on Facebook]
*[http://twitter.com/uwaathletics/ UWA Athletics on Twitter]
*[http://www.youtube.com/UWAAthletics/ UWA Athletics YouTube Channel]
*[http://www.uwatigers.com/ UWA Tigers Message Board]

{{Alabama Sports}}

[[Category:University of West Alabama|Athletics]]
[[Category:Multi-sport clubs in the United States]]
[[Category:College sports teams in the United States by team]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
