<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="261047" ns="0" title="Enda Kenny"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}
{{For|the Australian singer|Enda Kenny (singer)}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name             = Enda Kenny
|honorific-suffix = &lt;small&gt;[[Teachta Dála|TD]]&lt;/small&gt;
|image            = EndaKenny.jpg
|office           = [[Taoiseach]]
|1blankname       = [[Tánaiste]]
|1namedata        = [[Eamon Gilmore]]
|term_start       = 9 March 2011
|term_end         = 
|predecessor      = [[Brian Cowen]]
|successor        = 
|office2          = [[Leader of Fine Gael]]
|deputy2          = [[Richard Bruton]]&lt;br&gt;[[James Reilly (Irish politician)|James Reilly]]
|term_start2      = 5 June 2002
|term_end2        = 
|predecessor2     = [[Michael Noonan]]
|successor2       = 
|office3          = [[Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht|Minister for Tourism and Trade]]
|term_start3      = 15 December 1994
|term_end3        = 6 June 1997
|predecessor3     = [[Charlie McCreevy]]
|successor3       = [[Jim McDaid]]
|office5          = [[Teachta Dála]]
|term_start5      = June 1997
|term_end5        =
|predecessor5     = Constituency established
|successor5       =
|constituency5    = [[Mayo (Dáil Éireann constituency)|Mayo]]
|term_start6      = November 1975
|term_end6        = June 1997
|predecessor6     = [[Henry Kenny]]
|successor6       = Constituency abolished
|constituency6    = [[Mayo West (Dáil Éireann constituency)|Mayo West]]
|birth_date       = {{birth date and age|1951|4|24|df=y}}
|birth_place      = [[Castlebar]], [[County Mayo]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]
|death_date       =
|death_place      =
|party            = [[Fine Gael]]
|spouse           = Fionnuala O'Kelly &lt;small&gt;(m. 1992–present)&lt;/small&gt;
|children         = 1 daughter&lt;br&gt;2 sons
|alma_mater       = [[St Patrick's College of Education (Drumcondra)|St Patrick's College of Education, Dublin]]&lt;br&gt;[[National University of Ireland, Galway|University College, Galway]] (UCG)
|religion         = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://katharineblake.com/2007/07/27/enda-kenny/ |title=Enda Kenny |work=Katharine Blake |date=27 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''Enda Kenny''' (born 24 April 1951) is an [[Irish people|Irish]] [[Fine Gael]] politician, and has been the [[Taoiseach]] since 2011. He has led [[Fine Gael]] since 2002. He served as [[Minister for Tourism, Culture and Sport|Minister for Tourism and Trade]] from 1994 to 1997. He is also a two-term Vice President of the [[European People's Party]].

Kenny has been a [[Teachta Dála]] (TD) for [[Mayo (Dáil Éireann constituency)|Mayo]] since 1975, having succeeded his father [[Henry Kenny]].&lt;ref name=oireachtas_db&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;HouseNum=30&amp;MemberID=580&amp;ConstID=141|title=Mr. Enda Kenny|work=Oireachtas Members Database|accessdate=24 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is the [[Records of members of the Oireachtas|longest-serving TD]] currently in Dáil Éireann, which makes him the incumbent [[Father of the Dáil]].

Kenny led Fine Gael in the [[Irish general election, 2011|2011 general election]]. He subsequently brokered an agreement with the [[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]] and formed a coalition government on 9 March 2011.&lt;ref name=Coalition&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/europe/03/05/ireland.government |title=Irish parties agree to form coalition government |date=5 March 2011 |accessdate=5 March 2011 |work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is Fine Gael's first Taoiseach since [[John Bruton]] from 1994 to 1997, and the first Fine Gael leader to win government in an election since [[Garret FitzGerald]] in 1982.

==Early and private life==
Enda Kenny was born in the village of [[Islandeady]] near [[Castlebar]], [[County Mayo]] in 1951, the third child of five. He was educated locally at St. Patrick's [[National school (Ireland)|National School]] in Cornanool and [[St. Gerald's College]] ([[Lasallian educational institutions|De La Salle]]) in Castlebar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.herald.ie/national-news/the-clongowes-and-other-top-schools-boys-back-in-charge-2577057.html |title=The Clongowes (and other top schools) boys back in charge |work=[[Evening Herald]] |date=12 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny subsequently attended [[St Patrick's College of Education (Drumcondra)|St Patrick's College of Education]] in [[Dublin]] and [[National University of Ireland, Galway|University College Galway]].&lt;ref name=whoisendakenny&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0302/kennyendanew.html |title=Who is Enda Kenny? |work=[[RTÉ News]] |date=2 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He briefly worked as a [[primary school]] teacher, and is a [[Gaeilgeoir]].&lt;ref name=whoisendakenny/&gt;

Kenny has been married to Dubliner Fionnuala O'Kelly since 1992. She has been decribed by the media as his &quot;best asset&quot; and his &quot;secret weapon&quot;.&lt;ref name=endas_partys_best_asset&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/endas-been-hiding-his-partys-best-asset-his-wife-124054.html|title=Enda's been hiding his party's best asset: his wife|date=8 April 2007|first=Jerome|last=Reilly|work=Sunday Independent|accessdate=8 April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=endas_secret_weapon&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/fionnuala-kenny-endas-secret-weapon-2526481.html|title=Fionnuala Kenny -- Enda's secret weapon|date=5 February 2011|first=Gemma|last=O'Doherty|work=Irish Independent|accessdate=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; O'Kelly is first cousin to sitting [[Member of the European Parliament|MEP]] [[Seán Kelly (Irish politician)|Seán Kelly]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2011/0315/1224292162995.html |title=Labour to choose between Higgins and Finlay as presidential candidate |work=[[The Irish Times]] |date=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; former President of the [[Gaelic Athletic Association]] (GAA). The Kelly family originally come from the parish of Kilcummin near [[Killarney]], [[County Kerry]]. Enda and Fionnuala have three children, one daughter and two sons. The couple met in [[Leinster House]] where O'Kelly worked as a press officer for [[Fianna Fáil]]. She later worked with [[Raidió Teilifís Éireann]] (RTÉ).&lt;ref name=endas_partys_best_asset/&gt;&lt;ref name=endas_secret_weapon/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sheridan, Kathy. [http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/magazine/2009/0829/1224253224420.html &quot;Keeper Of Castlebar&quot;]. ''The Irish Times''. 8 August 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny has climbed [[Mount Kilimanjaro]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rte.ie/tv/therestaurant/endakenny/kenny_enda.html |title=The Restaurant: Enda Kenny |work=[[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTÉ Television]] |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is a keen supporter of his native [[Mayo GAA|Mayo]] [[Gaelic football]] team. He played Gaelic football for his local club, Islandeady,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hoganstand.com/Mayo/ArticleForm.aspx?ID=90799 |title=Islandeady club notes |publisher=Hoganstand.com |date=2008-03-10 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; of which he is the current club president. His father, [[Henry Kenny]], won an [[All-Ireland Senior Football Championship|All-Ireland]] medal with the inter-county team in 1936. His grandfather was a [[lighthouse keeper]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.independent.ie/national-news/taoiseach-shows-off-his-true-focus-2812819.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political career==
===Early political career===
From an early age Kenny was exposed to politics as his father, Henry Kenny, became a Fine Gael TD in 1954.  In the early 1970s he became directly involved in politics when he started helping his father with constituency clinics.  In 1975 Henry Kenny, who was at this stage a [[Minister of State (Ireland)|Parliamentary Secretary]] in the government, died after a short battle with cancer.  The Fine Gael party wanted one of his sons to stand as their candidate at the [[Mayo West by-election, 1975|subsequent by-election]], and so Enda Kenny was chosen.  He was elected on the first count with 52% of the vote, and at 24 he was the youngest member of the 20th Dáil.&lt;ref name=elecs_irl&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://electionsireland.org/candidate.cfm?ID=3199
|title=Enda Kenny
|work=ElectionsIreland.org
|accessdate=24 September 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny remained on the backbenches of the Dáil for almost a decade.  He was appointed party spokesperson firstly on youth affairs and sport, then western development, however, he failed to build a national profile as he concentrated more on constituency matters.  Kenny was left out in the cold when [[Garret FitzGerald]] became [[Taoiseach]] for the first time in 1981 and again in 1982.  He was, however, appointed as a member of the Fine Gael delegation at the [[New Ireland Forum]] in 1983 and later served on the British-Irish Parliamentary Association. In 1986 he became a [[Minister of State (Ireland)|Minister of State]] at the Departments of Education and Labour. Fine Gael lost the [[Irish general election, 1987|1987 general election]] resulting in Kenny being on the opposition benches for the next seven years.  In spite of this his national profile was raised as he served in a number of positions on the party's [[Fine Gael Front Bench|front bench]], including Education, Arts, Heritage, [[Gaeltacht]] and the Islands. He was also the Fine Gael [[Chief Whip]] for a short period.

===Government minister===
In late 1994 the [[Fianna Fáil]]–[[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]] government collapsed; however, no general election was called. Instead a [[Fine Gael]]–[[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]]–[[Democratic Left (Ireland)|Democratic Left]] &quot;[[Government of the 27th Dáil#24th Government of Ireland|Rainbow Coalition]]&quot; came to power. Kenny, as Fine Gael chief whip, was a key member of the team, which negotiated the programme for government with the other two parties prior to the formation of the new government.  Under [[Taoiseach]] [[John Bruton]], Kenny joined the cabinet and was appointed [[Minister for Arts, Sport and Tourism (Ireland)|Minister for Tourism and Trade]]. During his tenure as minister, Ireland saw a significant growth in tourism business and in its international trade position{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}. As minister he chaired the [[European Union]] Council of Trade Ministers during Ireland's six-month [[President of the European Council|Presidency of the European Council]] as well as co-chairing a round of the [[World Trade Organization]] talks  in 1996. Among Kenny's other achievements were the rejuvenation of the [[Saint Patrick's Day]] parade in Dublin and the successful negotiations to bring a stage of the 1998 [[Tour de France]] to Ireland.  In 1997 the government was defeated at the general election and Kenny returned to the opposition benches.

===2001 Fine Gael leadership election===
In 2001 [[John Bruton]] resigned as leader of Fine Gael following a vote of no confidence in his ability.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.breakingnews.ie/ireland/bruton-resigns-as-fine-gael-leader-3068.html &quot;Bruton resigns as Fine Gael leader&quot;]. ''breakingNEWS.ie''. 01/02/2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny was one of a number of candidates who stood in the subsequent leadership election, promising to &quot;electrify the party&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/kenny-supported-by-one-third-of-fg-501559.html &quot;Kenny supported by one third of FG&quot;]. ''Sunday Independent''. 9 June 2002. &quot;16 months after he famously said during his failed attempt to beat Michael Noonan that he would electrify the party, Enda Kenny is now in charge of Fine Gael.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In the final ballot it was [[Michael Noonan]] who emerged victorious (it is Fine Gael's custom not to publish ballot results for leadership elections). Noonan subsequently failed to give a spokesperson's assignment to Kenny. This led Kenny to accuse Noonan of sending a &quot;dangerous message&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/news/2001/0215/finegael.html?view=print &quot;Fine Gael leaders sending &quot;dangerous message&quot; - Kenny&quot;]. ''RTÉ News''. 15 February 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fine Gael leader===
At the [[Irish general election, 2002|2002 general election]] Fine Gael suffered its worst electoral performance ever, losing 23 seats, a figure larger than expected and with its overall vote down 5%. Kenny himself came close to losing his seat and even went so far as to prepare a concession speech. In the end [[Mayo (Dáil Éireann constituency)#2002 general election|he won the third seat in the five-seat constituency]]. Noonan resigned as Fine Gael leader on the night of the result, an action which triggered another [[Fine Gael leadership election, 2002|leadership election]]. Protest meetings were held by members of the party against the speed with which the leadership election had been called and the failure to broaden the franchise to the membership. It was suggested that it was foolish to choose a leader before conducting an electoral post-mortem.

Kenny once again contested the Fine Gael leadership and emerged successful on that occasion.&lt;ref name=rte_fg_leader&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2002/0605/finegael.html|title=Enda Kenny elected Fine Gael leader|work=[[RTÉ News]]|date=5 June 2002|accessdate=14 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On becoming leader he faced an unenviable task.  He not only had to rebuild a demoralised party that had been cut down to 31 seats, but also had to face a very popular Taoiseach, [[Bertie Ahern]]. In the beginning his leadership style was also criticised. The tide began to turn for Fine Gael in 2003 as the Fianna Fáil-led government's popularity took a downturn. Fine Gael's membership increased and the party became a much more united entity. Kenny's first major televised conference speech in November 2003 was well received by the media and, for many, marked a turn in Fine Gael's fortunes as it began to offer more vigorous opposition to Ahern's government.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

[[File:Flickr - europeanpeoplesparty - EPP Summit 11 December 2008 (39).jpg|thumb|left|[[Viktor Orbán]], [[Jacek Saryusz-Wolski]] and Enda Kenny during an EPP Summit on 11 December 2008.]]

In September 2002, Kenny was accused of making racist remarks after he used the word &quot;nigger&quot; in a joke relating to [[Patrice Lumumba]], the assassinated first Prime Minister of [[Republic of the Congo (Léopoldville)|Congo]]. Kenny wanted his &quot;obscure joke&quot; to be suppressed and specifically asked journalists not to report it, though Enda's &quot;chortling repetition of the inflammatory word&quot; was carried by the ''[[Sunday Independent]]'' newspaper.&lt;ref&gt;Kenny, Colum. [http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/nigger-joke-reveals-ignorance-of-racism-503626.html &quot;'Nigger' joke reveals ignorance of racism&quot;]. ''Sunday Independent''. 15 September 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; He was subsequently condemned by race campaigners at home, in Britain and further abroad.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2002/sep/15/world.race
|title=Fury at Kenny 'joke' spreads
|work=[[The Guardian]]
|date=15 September 2002
|accessdate=13 October 2009
| location=London
| first=Martin
| last=Bright
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/lumumbas-many-lovers-503773.html &quot;Lumumba's many lovers&quot;]. ''Sunday Independent''. 22 September 2002. &quot;Patrice Lumumba was the subject of an anecdote by Enda Kenny...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Matters were made worse when it emerged that several of Lumumba's relatives, including a son and several grandchildren, lived in [[Tallaght]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.joe.ie/news-politics/newsmakers/5-things-you-might-not-know-about-enda-kenny-002688-1 &quot;Why Enda Kenny is not quite as dull as people make out: Enda Kenny likes to tell racist jokes&quot;]. JOE.ie. 15 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Fine Gael out-performed expectations at the 2004 [[Irish local elections, 2004|Local]] and [[European Parliament election, 2004 (Ireland)|European]] elections, which saw Fine Gael increase it representation from 4 [[Member of the European Parliament|MEPs]] of 15 from Ireland, to 5 from 13. This was the first time Fine Gael had ever defeated Fianna Fáil in a national election, as well as the first time Fianna Fáil had lost a national election since it finished second in the [[Irish general election, September 1927]] to [[Cumann na nGaedheal]], Fine Gael's immediate predecessor.

In July 2005, [[Rossport Five|five men]] from the north of Kenny's Mayo constituency were jailed over their opposition to the Fianna Fáil-led government's plans for the [[Corrib gas project]]. One of the men, Philip McGrath, worked for Kenny as an election agent for [[Rossport]] during general elections. Unlike his fellow Mayo Fine Gael TD, [[Michael Ring]], Kenny was cautious about backing the men's stance (Ring would later be forced to adopt the same policy).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.unison.ie/irish_independent/stories.php3?ca=9&amp;si=1710340&amp;issue_id=14795
|title=SF accused of hijacking Corrib oil pipeline protest
|work=[[Irish Independent]]
|date=21 October 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Shell to Sea]] campaign that was founded to help release the men and get the government to change its mind shut down work on the project for fifteen months. When [[Garda Síochána|Gardaí]] were brought in to remove protesters with tactics that saw many hospitalised,  Kenny said: &quot;The law must be obeyed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2006/1110/mayo.html
|title=Serious confrontation at Corrib gas site
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=10 November 2006
|accessdate=9 April 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2005, Kenny called for the abolition of compulsory Irish for the [[Leaving Certificate]] examinations. This was opposed by all the major [[Irish language]] organisations.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2005/1116/irish.html
|title=150 protest against Fine Gael's Irish policy
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=16 November 2005
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In March 2006 Kenny was elected Vice-President of the [[European People's Party]] (EPP), the largest European political group to which Fine Gael is affiliated.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2006/0331/kennye.html
|title=Enda Kenny elected Vice-President of EPP
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=31 March 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his speech to the EPP he stated that Fine Gael would be in Government within two years.

During the first half of 2006 Kenny went aggressively after a more populist line on the cost of immigration, street crime, paedophilia and homeowner's rights. A graphic description of a mugging he had experienced was given to the Dáil in the context of a crime discussion, only for it to be revealed a day later that the incident had occurred in Kenya not Ireland.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/kennys-comment-on-attack-misleading-85842.html
|title=Kenny's comment on attack 'misleading'
|work=[[Irish Independent]]
|date=1 July 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Responding to the [[2008–2011 Irish banking crisis]] in [[County Cork]] on 15 February 2009, Kenny asked the entire board of the [[Central Bank of Ireland]]'s Financial Regulation section to resign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenny wants Regulator board to resign&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2009/0215/kennye.html|title=Kenny wants Regulator board to resign|date=2009-02-15|accessdate=2009-02-15|publisher=[[Radio Telefís Éireann|RTÉ]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2007 general election====
[[File:EndaKenny2007FineGael.jpg|thumb|Kenny, speaking at the [[Young Fine Gael]] conference in 2007.]]
Under Kenny the Fine Gael Party agreed to enter a pre-election pact with the [[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]] in order to offer the electorate an alternative coalition government at the [[Irish general election, 2007|2007 general election]] held on 24 May. The so-called 'Mullingar Accord' was agreed in September 2004 following the European and Local elections that year.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2004/0906/opposition.html
|title=Opposition leaders unveil 'Mullingar Accord'
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=6 September 2004
|accessdate=9 April 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Green Party (Ireland)|Green Party]] also signalled via the media to be in favour of membership of such a coalition government after the election.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} They refused to commit to an agreement prior to polling day however.

Kenny's leadership has attempted to define Fine Gael as a party of the progressive centre. Its policy initiatives have concentrated on value for money, consumer rights, civil partnerships, reform of public spending, reward and enterprise and preventative health care policy. The party has sought to retake its former mantle as the law-and-order party committed to defending the institutions of the state. At the Fine Gael [[Ardfheis]] in March 2007 Kenny outlined his platform for the forthcoming general election entitled the 'Contract for a Better Ireland.'&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2007/0331/finegael.html
|title=FG Ard-Fheis: Contract for a Better Ireland
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=31 March 2007
|accessdate=9 April 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main aspects of this 'contract' included: 2,300 more hospital beds, 2,000 more [[Garda Síochána|Gardaí]], tougher jail sentences and tougher bail for criminals, free health insurance for all children under 16 and lower income tax.

Bertie Ahern was perceived by many to have comfortably beaten Kenny in the pre-election Leaders' debate.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2007/0517/newsontwo_av.html?2249264,null,230
|title=News on Two
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=17 May 2007
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When the votes were counted it emerged that Fine Gael had made large gains, increasing its number of seats by twenty to give a total of 51 seats in the new Dáil.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/elections2007/toptens.html
|title=RTÉ Election 2007 - Election news and results
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|accessdate=9 April 2008
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080331093856/http://www.rte.ie/news/elections2007/toptens.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 31 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Labour and the Greens failed to make gains, leaving Kenny's &quot;Alliance for Change&quot; short of a majority. Despite predictions to the contrary, the Fianna Fáil vote recovered sufficiently to bring it to 78 seats, and a third term in government for Ahern.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2007/0614/election.html
|title=Ahern names new Cabinet
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=14 June 2007
|accessdate=9 April 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny is currently the [[Records of members of the Oireachtas|longest-serving TD]] in Dáil Éireann still in office, and is the incumbent [[Father of the Dáil]].

====Media commentary====
In December 2008, [[Vincent Browne]] criticised Kenny in ''[[The Irish Times]]'' for not having a grasp of the issues, notably of economic issues.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/opinion/2008/1231/1230581505096.html
|title=We are stuck with inept trio and a dismal alternative
|work=[[The Irish Times]]
|date=31 December 2008
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2010 leadership challenge====
An [[opinion poll]] published in ''[[The Irish Times]]'' on 10 June 2010 triggered a challenge to Kenny's leadership of the party. The Ipsos MRBI poll indicated that the [[Labour Party (Ireland)|Labour Party]] had become the most popular political party in the country for the first time ever,  and also showed a drop in backing for [[Fianna Fáil]] and Fine Gael, and for their leaders. It showed a five-point drop in Fianna Fáil support since January 2010, leaving that party on 17%, Fine Gael down four points to 28%, and Labour up eight points to 32%. Satisfaction with Kenny's leadership dropped 7% to 24%.&lt;ref name=&quot;RTE_15062010&quot;&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2010/0610/politics.html
|title=Labour most popular party - poll
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=10 June 2010
|accessdate=15 June 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the failure of the party's deputy leader [[Richard Bruton]] to support him, he was dismissed by Kenny on 14 June. He also tabled a motion of confidence in his leadership, to be held on 17 June.&lt;ref name=RTE_15062010/&gt;&lt;ref name=RTE_14062010&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2010/0614/finegael.html
|title=Enda Kenny says challenge is 'misjudged'
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=14 June 2010
|accessdate=17 June 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On the following day it was revealed that nine members of the Fine Gael frontbench did not have confidence in Kenny to lead their party - composed of [[Simon Coveney]], [[Denis Naughten]], [[Olwyn Enright]], [[Olivia Mitchell]], [[Fergus O'Dowd]], [[Michael Creed]], [[Billy Timmins]], [[Leo Varadkar]] and [[Brian Hayes (politician)|Brian Hayes]]. Denis Naughten said frontbench members did not have Kenny's support and would like him to withdraw his motion of confidence and stand down in the interest of the party.&lt;ref name=RTE_15062010&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2010/0615/finegael.html
|title=Nine frontbenchers have no confidence in Kenny
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=15 June 2010
|accessdate=15 June 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The motion of confidence in Kenny was passed.&lt;ref name=RTE_15062010/&gt;&lt;ref name=RTE_17062010&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2010/0617/finegael.html
|title=Kenny survives confidence vote
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|date=17 June 2010
|accessdate=17 June 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He announced a major reshuffle of his party's front bench on 1 July 2010, re-appointing Bruton, Coveney, O'Dowd and Varadkar.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2010/0701/finegael.html
|title=Bruton &amp; Noonan return to Fine Gael frontbench
|date=1 July 2010
|work=[[RTÉ News]]
|accessdate=3 July 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====2011 general election====
At the start of the [[Irish general election, 2011|2011 general election]], Kenny said Fine Gael recognised the importance of “the giving of hope and confidence to people through the taxation system”, when speaking to reporters outside party election headquarters in Dublin. “The Fine Gael party in this election is the only party that is categorically saying that there will not be any increase in income tax over our period in government,” he said. “There will be no increase in income tax.” He said the country needed strong government and not an administration that depended on the support of Independents. “I think that this is a time for courageous and strong government. It is not a time for government that might self-combust or that would be dependent on the whim of any mercenary Independents. This is a judgment call for the people.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2011/0202/1224288771169.html |title=Kenny promises not to raise income tax |publisher=Irishtimes.com |date=2011-02-02 |accessdate=2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There was several leaders debates on television during the campaign. There was uniquely three debates on stations TV3, RTÉ and TG4 between Enda Kenny, Michaél Martin and Eamon Gilmore and a five way leaders' debate on RTÉ also including Gerry Adams and John Gormley along with the other participants from the three way debates.

Kenny however refused to participate in the three-way leaders' debate proposed by [[TV3 (Ireland)|TV3]], stating his unhappiness that [[Vincent Browne]] would chair the debate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Independent.ie |url=http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/enda-puts-the-boot-into-vincent-over-threeway-debate-hoohah-2526483.html |title=Enda puts the boot into Vincent over three-way debate hoohah |publisher=Independent.ie |date= |accessdate=2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Browne is a well know critic of Fine Gael and Kenny. In 1982 Browne appeared on ''[[The Late Late Show]]'' where he poured scorn on Kenny, claiming he was &quot;purporting&quot; to be a TD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/national-news/fine-gael-leaders-feud-with-browne-goes-back-almost-30-years-2528091.html]&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2010, Browne was forced to make a public apology to Kenny after jokingly asking whether Fine Gael was requesting that he go into a dark room with a gun and bottle of whiskey. This was in reference to Fine Gael's position in the polls, where they were in second place to Labour, and a previous leadership challenge to Kenny by [[Richard Bruton]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/national-news/browne-to-apologise-for-silly-suggestion-of-kenny-suicide-2363468.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny refused to appear on the leaders debate despite an offer by Browne to be replaced by a different moderator for the debate if Kenny would appear.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.ie/national-news/defiant-kenny-digs-in-over-snub-to-tv-debate-2528065.html]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2011/0205/1224289077071.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny participated in a three party leader debate on RTÉ, moderated by [[Miriam O'Callaghan]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejournal.ie/party-leaders-spar-off-in-final-election-debate-2011-2/ |title=Party leaders spar off in final election debate |publisher=Thejournal.ie |date=2010-09-23 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also in a five way debate on RTÉ, which was a new departure involving all party leaders of the outgoing Dáil, including Kenny, moderated by [[Pat Kenny]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0214/politics.html |title=Five party leaders debate election issues |publisher=Rte.ie |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He participated in a three-way debate in the Irish language with Micheál Martin and Eamon Gilmore on TG4.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iftn.ie/news/?act1=record&amp;only=1&amp;aid=73&amp;rid=4283655&amp;tpl=archnews&amp;force=1 |title=TG4 to Host Party Leaders Debate As Gaeilge |publisher=Iftn.ie |date=2011-02-16 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Enda Kenny's 2011 General Election Victory.jpg|thumb|left|Kenny makes a speech to Fine Gael party members on the day of the election results.]]
On 14 February 2011, Kenny met [[Chancellor of Germany (Federal Republic of Germany)|German Chancellor]] [[Angela Merkel]] to discuss the Irish economy.  Kenny and Merkel have close political ties because Merkel's [[Christian Democratic Union (Germany)|CDU party]] and Fine Gael are both members of the [[centre-right]] [[European People's Party]] (EPP) and seating at EPP meetings is arranged by [[alphabetical order]] of [[surname]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news | last = Simpson | first = Mark | title = Irish election campaign diary | publisher = [[BBC News Online]]  | date = 2011-02-17  | url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12456322  | accessdate = 2011-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The close relationship between these two leaders is illustrated further by the fact that Angela Merkel also backed Enda Kenny and Fine Gael during the 2007 election.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Independent.ie |url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/merkel-makes-it-clear-who-she-wants-in-dail-41305.html |title= Merkel backs Kenny for Taoiseach |publisher=Independent.ie |date= |accessdate=2011-02-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opinion polls of 23 February 2011 sponsored by ''[[Paddy Power]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0223/politics.html|title=Enda Kenny focused on 'real poll'|work=[[RTÉ News]]|date=23 February 2011|accessdate=23 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ''[[Irish Independent]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0222/election_2011.html |title=Live - Election 2011 Debate  |work=[[RTÉ News]] |date=22 February 2011 |accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Irish Times]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0220/politics2.html|title=New poll sees FG gain at Labour's expense|work=[[RTÉ News]]|date=20 February 2011|accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; suggested that Kenny would lead Fine Gael to its largest total of seats to date in the 31st Dail, and that he would be elected Taoiseach.

In the election, Kenny led Fine Gael to a decisive victory.  The party won 76 seats, the most in its 78-year history, and will be the largest party in the Dáil for the first time ever.  Meanwhile, Fianna Fáil suffered the worst defeat of a sitting government in the history of the Irish state, its representation being reduced by 75%.  Kenny himself topped the poll in his Mayo constituency and uniquely three others from Fine Gael were elected alongside Kenny.  At a victory party in Dublin, Kenny declared Fine Gael had &quot;a massive endorsement&quot; to govern, and the election marked &quot;a transformative moment in Ireland's history.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Doyle, Kilian. [http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0227/breaking2.html Kenny leads Fine Gael to win as Fianna Fáil vote collapses]. [[The Irish Times]], 2011-02-27.&lt;/ref&gt;  Later, he told [[Raidió Teilifís Éireann]] (RTÉ) that he fully expects to become Taoiseach after what he called &quot;a democratic revolution at the ballot box.&quot;&lt;ref name=Revolution&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0226/politics.html Enda Kenny welcomes 'democratic revolution'].  [[RTÉ News]], 2011-02-26.&lt;/ref&gt; While there was some talk that Fine Gael would govern alone as a minority government, senior Fine Gael leaders indicated as soon as the election result was beyond doubt that they would likely enter a coalition government with Labour.&lt;ref name=Guardian&gt;McDonald, Henry. [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/26/fianna-fail-irish-general-election Fianna Fáil trounced as Fine Gael and Labour set to form coalition]. [[The Guardian]], 27 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Late on the night of 5 March, Fine Gael and Labour formally agreed to form a coalition government with Kenny as Taoiseach&lt;ref name=Coalition/&gt; and Labour leader [[Eamon Gilmore]] as [[Tánaiste]], with Labour being given four other seats in cabinet.&lt;ref name=Tanaiste&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0308/politics.html Eamon Gilmore set for Foreign Affairs]. [[RTÉ News]], 2011-03-08.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny said that his first priority upon taking office will be to renegotiate the bailout, calling the original deal &quot;a bad deal for Ireland and a bad deal for Europe.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-12590868 Ireland's next leader Kenny vows bailout review]. [[BBC News]], 2011-02-27.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Taoiseach 2011–present==
[[File:Barack Obama and Enda Kenny at Farmleigh.jpg|thumb|230px|Kenny with [[President of the United States|President]] [[Barack Obama]]]]
The [[members of the 31st Dáil]] convened for the first time on 9 March 2011 and elected Kenny as Taoiseach by a vote of 117–27.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0309/breaking5.html |title=Kenny elected Taoiseach of coalition Government |work=[[The Irish Times]] |date=9 March 2011 |accessdate=9 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny received his seal of office from [[President of Ireland|President]] [[Mary McAleese]]. He also announced ministerial appointees to his Government on 9 March 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0309/breaking42.html?via=mr |title=Full list of new Enda Kenny's Cabinet |publisher=Irishtimes.com |date=2011-03-09 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
At just under 59 years and 11 months on accession, Kenny is the second-oldest person to assume this office,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.independent.ie/national-news/in-brief-enda-kenny-will-be-second-oldest-taoiseach-in-history-of-the-state-2558076.html |title=Enda Kenny will be second oldest Taoiseach in history of the State |work=[[Irish Independent]] |date=27 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the oldest being [[Seán Lemass]].

On 9 March 2011, Kenny appointed 15 junior Ministries. He also appointed a Minister for political reform, and sent a request to the OPW as to how he could address ministerial transport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/av/2011/0310/media-2921722.html |title=One News: Taoiseach Enda Kenny gets down to business - Video - RTÉ News Player |publisher=Rte.ie |date=2011-03-10 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; On March 15 it was announced that only the current President, the Taoiseach, the Tánaiste and the Minister for Justice were to have Garda drivers. All other Ministers would have to make use of their own transport with a mileage allowance and a commercial chauffeur as an expense. There was no announcement as to the continuing engagement of three government jets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0315/breaking47.html |title=Ministerial fleet cost to be halved - The Irish Times - Tue, Mar 15, 2011 |publisher=The Irish Times |date=2011-03-15 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The media reported that this would reduce the ministerial motor vehicle transport bill to 7 million euro annually which is more than the combined annual tax contributions of 16,000 people on minimum wage.

According to a report in the ''[[Sunday Mirror]]'', Kenny will be the first Taoiseach to use the [[Steward's Lodge]] at [[Farmleigh]] as his official residence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4161/is_20110227/ai_n56969272/ |title=Farmleigh gets ready to welcome the Kennys |work=[[Sunday Mirror]] |date=27 February 2011 |accessdate=9 March 2011 |first=Samuel |last=Hamilton}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Government pay cuts===
In one of his first acts in the top office, Kenny slashed his own pay by €14,000 (a reduction of 7% which leaves his weekly net income at over €2,500&lt;ref&gt;http://www.deloitte.ie/tc/Default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;). The new government also decided to cut the pay of senior ministers. The Taoiseach's pay is to be cut from €214,187 to €200,000. Tánaiste Eamon Gilmore's pay is cut from €197,486 to €184,405. Ministers' pay has been reduced to €169,275 (from €181,283), while pay for Ministers of State is cut from €139,266 to €130,042. In another cost-cutting measure, Kenny asked the Garda, the Departments of Justice and Transport, as well as the Office of Public Works, to come up with a plan to reduce the amount spent on transporting ministers and their teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessandleadership.com/leadership/item/28839-14-000-pay-cut-for-enda-ke |title=€14,000 pay cut for Enda Kenny |publisher=Businessandleadership.com |date=2011-03-10 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Financial and banking policy===
On 11 March, his third day as Taoiseach, Kenny attended his first summit of [[European Union]] leaders in Brussels. During that summit he engaged in a heated confrontation with [[President of France|French President]] [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] (which Kenny termed &quot;a Gallic spat&quot;) over Ireland's comparatively low 12.5% corporate tax rate, which EU leaders have frequently posited as a condition of more favorable terms for the Irish bailout.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Irish Welcome Portuguese to the ‘Debt Club’ |work=''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' |url=http://blogs.wsj.com/source/2011/04/07/irish-welcome-portuguese-to-the-debt-club/ |date=7 April 2011 |first=Eamon |last=Quinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny held firm on his refusal to alter the corporate tax, which he reiterated in his first Leaders' Questions the following week &amp;mdash; also declaring his government's intention to withhold further state funds from Dublin banks until the EU agreed to new terms that forced banks' senior bondholders to share in the losses.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0315/kennye_speech.html &quot;Enda Kenny's Speech&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, less than three weeks later on 31 March, the [[Central Bank of Ireland]] published the results of its &quot;stress tests&quot; on Ireland's four surviving banks (Allied Irish Banks, Bank of Ireland, EBS, and Irish Life &amp; Permanent) &amp;mdash; indicating that the banks needed to raise an additional €24 billion to remain solvent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=31 March 2010 |title=Irish banks need €24bn more to survive economic shocks |publisher=''[[Daily Telegraph]]'' |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/banksandfinance/8419539/Irish-banks-need-24bn-more-to-survive-economic-shocks.html |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his earlier promise, the government announced the same day that the state would supply the necessary funds to keep the banks afloat, with Kenny stating that seeking the money from bondholders would be neither &quot;reasonable or logical.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bondholders escape as €24bn put into banks |publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]'' |date=1 April 2011 |ref=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/newsbysector/banksandfinance/8419539/Irish-banks-need-24bn-more-to-survive-economic-shocks.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Kenny was heavily criticised for his government's action, with the ''[[Irish Independent]]'' noting that &quot;this is the fifth time Irish people have been told over the past couple of years it would be the last payout they would have to endure.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=New era for banks after €24bn bailout |date=1 April 2011 |publisher=''[[The Irish Independent]]'' |url=http://www.independent.ie/business/irish/new-era-for-banks--after-euro24bn-bailout-2603998.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, the first national opinion poll since Kenny took office, published on 10 April, showed that public support for Kenny's Fine Gael party had increased since the election from 36% to 39%, although a plurality also indicated deep dissatisfaction with his rescue of the banks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Irish govt support up despite bank bailout |publisher=Reuters |date=10 April 2011 |url=http://in.reuters.com/article/2011/04/10/idINIndia-56241020110410 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 21 July 2011, Kenny announced that an agreement had been reached by [[Eurozone]] leaders to reduce Ireland's interest rate by 2% and extend the repayment period.&lt;ref&gt;&gt;{{cite news |title=Irish bailout rate cut by 2% under new euro-wide deal |date=21 July 2011 |publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]'' |url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0721/breaking6.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pension Levy controversy====
On 9 May, Kenny's government announced a new job creation program, along with plan to finance it via a 0.6% tax levy on private pension savings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Ireland to Impose Levy on Pension Funds to Finance Jobs Plan |last=Brennan |first=Joe |coauthor=Dara Doyle |work=Bloomberg |date=10 May 2011 |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-05-10/ireland-to-impose-levy-on-pension-funds.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; Public pension funds, however, would remain untouched. The pension levy caused an immediate and intense outcry, leaving Kenny to defend the initiative as &quot;a modest proposal&quot; and refuting charges that the government would next tax personal savings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Taoiseach defends private pension levy |work=RTE |date=11 May 2011 |url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0511/jobs.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Taoiseach insists our personal savings are safe |work=''[[The Irish Independent]]'' |first=Fionnan |last=Sheahan |date=12 May 2011 |url=http://www.independent.ie/business/personal-finance/pensions/taoiseach-insists-our-personal-savings-are-safe-2644493.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the controversy surrounding the levy intensified on 12 May, when Kenny admitted that the holders of Approved Retirement Funds &amp;mdash; most of whom were among the highest income earners in Ireland &amp;mdash; would not be included in the levy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Some retirement funds escape pension levy
 |work=RTE |date=12 May 2011 |url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0512/jobs.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political reforms===
On 3 May 2011, Kenny's government approved a set of political reforms that adhered to promises Kenny had made in the 2011 election.&lt;ref name=IT-TDs-fall&gt;{{cite news |title=Number of TDs could fall by 20, says Hogan |publisher=''[[The Irish Times]]'' |date=3 May 2011 |ref=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2011/0505/1224296147732.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mayoadv&gt;{{cite news |title=Kenny now walking the walk |publisher=Mayo Advertiser |date=6 May 2011 |url=http://www.advertiser.ie/mayo/article/39489/kenny-now-walking-the-walk }}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the approved reforms were a  binding Constituency Commission scheduled for June 2011, with the specific purpose of reducing the number of TDs by up to 20;&lt;ref name=IT-TDs-fall /&gt; an act to establish a six-month time limit for holding by-elections to the Dáil; a €750,000 spending limit in the [[Irish presidential election, 2011|2011 Irish presidential election]]; Legislation to ban corporate donations, to be enacted by summer 2011; establishment of a Constitutional Convention in 2011, which will include discussion of the Seanad; and a referendum to abolish the Seanad, to be held in the second half of 2012.&lt;ref name=mayoadv /&gt; The promise to cut up to 20 TDs caused some controversy and skepticism due to the Constitutional requirement that there be no less than one TD for every 30,000 people, which would necessitate a minimum of 150 TDs &amp;mdash; meaning that the current number of 166 TDs could be reduced by 16 at most.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Public is entitled to be cynical after latest government U-turn |last=Brennan |first=Michael |publisher=Irish Independent |date=5 May 2011 |url=http://www.independent.ie/opinion/analysis/michael-brennan-public-is-entitled-to-be-cynical-after-latest-government-uturn-2638066.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Vatican reprimand===
{{Wikisource|1=Dáil Motion: Commission of Investigation Report in the Catholic Diocese of Cloyne|2=Enda Kenny's Cloyne Speech}}
On 13 July 2011 the [[Sexual abuse scandal in Cloyne diocese|Cloyne Report]] was published, detailing the investigation into allegations of child sexual abuse by 19 priests in the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Cloyne]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0713/cloynetracker.html&lt;/ref&gt; Among the report's findings were the revelation that the vast majority of allegations made in the diocese were not reported to the [[An Garda Síochána|Garda]], as required by the Church's 1996 guidelines; that the Bishop of the Diocese, [[John Magee (bishop)|John Magee]], and others had withheld full cooperation with the Government's investigation and had deliberately misrepresented his own response to the allegations; and that the [[Holy See|Vatican]] itself had both refused to cooperate in the investigation and counseled the Diocese that the 1996 guidelines were not binding.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0713/breaking6.html Cloyne report finds failures by church, State agencies] ''Irish Times'', 13 July 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/216118/cloyne-report.pdf Commission of Investigation: Report into the Catholic Diocese of Cloyne] DocumentCloud.org. Retrieved: 2011-07-18.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 July, [[s:Dáil Motion: Commission of Investigation Report in the Catholic Diocese of Cloyne|Kenny condemned the Vatican]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.taoiseach.gov.ie/eng/Government_Press_Office/Taoiseach's_Speeches_20111/Statement_by_the_Taoiseach_on_the_D%C3%A1il_Motion_on_the_report_of_the_Commission_of_Investigation_into_the_Catholic_Diocese_of_Cloyne,_in_D%C3%A1il_%C3%89ireann,_.html Statement by the Taoiseach on the Dáil Motion on the report of the Commission of Investigation into the Catholic Diocese of Cloyne - 20 July 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; for its role in the scandal, stating that the Church's role in obstructing the investigation was a serious infringement upon the sovereignty of Ireland and that the scandal revealed &quot;the dysfunction, disconnection and elitism that dominates the culture of the Vatican to this day.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://debates.oireachtas.ie/dail/2011/07/20/00013.asp Commission of Investigation Report in the Catholic Diocese of Cloyne: Motion] ''Houses of the Oireachtas'', 2011-07-20.&lt;/ref&gt; He added that &quot;the historic relationship between church and state in Ireland could not be the same again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/0720/cloyne1.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0721/breaking46.html|title=Reaction to Kenny's Cloyne speech|date=21 July 2011|work=Irish Times|accessdate=21 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Kenny's attack on the Vatican was unprecedented by a high-level official in Ireland, whose formal relationship with the Catholic Church had long been viewed as intimate and inextricable.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} The speech was widely regarded as extraordinary, with Britain's ''[[Daily Mail]]'' newspaper commenting that &quot;The astonishing attack was the first time that Ireland's Parliament has publicly castigated the Vatican instead of local church leaders during the country's 17 years of paedophile-priest scandals.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/breaking/2011/0721/breaking46.html|title=Reaction to Kenny's Cloyne speech|date=21 July 2011|work=Irish Times|accessdate=21 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Guardian]]'' remarked that &quot; the political classes have...lost their fear, namely of the once almighty Roman Catholic church.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2011/jul/21/irish-political-classes-lose-fear-catholic-church|title=Irish political classes lose their fear of the Catholic church|date=21 July 2011|work=The Guardian|accessdate=21 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Vatican response====
On 3 September the [[Holy See]] issued its response to Mr Kenny's speech noting that &quot;the accusation that the Holy See attempted “''to frustrate an Inquiry in a sovereign, democratic republic as little as three years ago, not three decades ago''”, which Mr Kenny made no attempt to substantiate, is unfounded. Indeed, when asked, a Government spokesperson clarified that Mr Kenny was not referring to any specific incident&quot;. The response added that &quot;Those Reports [.........] contain no evidence to suggest that the Holy See meddled in the internal affairs of the Irish State or, for that matter, was involved in the day-to-day management of Irish dioceses or religious congregations with respect to sexual abuse issues&quot;. 

On the quoting of then Cardinal Ratzinger, the response notes &quot;The quotation in question is taken from the ''Instruction on the Ecclesial Vocation of the Theologian'', otherwise known as ''Donum Veritatis'' (The Gift of the Truth), published by the Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith on 24 May 1990, and signed by the then Prefect and Secretary of the Congregation. It is not a private text of the then Cardinal Ratzinger but an official document of the Congregation. This document is concerned with the theologian’s service to the Church community, a service which can also be of help to society at large, and not with the manner in which the Church should behave within a democratic society nor with issues of child protection, as Mr Kenny’s use of the quotation would seem to imply&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vatican.va/resources/resources_risposta-gilmore_20110903_en.html Response to Mr Gilmore]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Addressing the nation===
{{Wikisource|1=A National Address by an Taoiseach, Enda Kenny|2=Enda Kenny's address to the nation}}
He gave a [[s:A National Address by an Taoiseach, Enda Kenny|televised address to the nation]] on 4 December 2011, ahead of the delivery of the [[Irish budget, 2012|2012 Irish budget]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/business/2011/dec/04/ireland-budget-plans-live-tv|title=Enda Kenny to prepare Irish for more budget pain|date=4 December 2011|first=Henry|last=McDonald|work=The Guardian|accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He warned that Budget 2012 &quot;will be tough&quot;, and that &quot;it has to be&quot;. He also said that it will move Ireland towards a manageable deficit of 3% of GDP by 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/1204/budget.html|title=Taoiseach warns of 'tough' Budget 2012|date=4 December 2011|work=[[RTÉ News]]|accessdate=4 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was only the sixth time that a taoiseach has addressed the nation, reflecting the gravity of the Irish economic condition, in what Mr. Kenny stressed were &quot;exceptional&quot; circumstances.&lt;ref name=&quot;retriever&quot;&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/frontpage/2011/1205/1224308584654.html Kenny wants to be Taoiseach who 'retrieves Irish sovereignty'] Irish Times, 2011-12-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Families in the Oireachtas]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Enda Kenny}}
* [http://www.finegael.ie/our-people/tds/?id=59 Enda Kenny's page on the Fine Gael website]
* [http://www.rte.ie/news/2011/1204/taoiseach_address_text.html Enda's address to the nation: Sunday 4 December 2011]

{{s-start}}
{{s-par|ie/oi}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Henry Kenny]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Fine Gael]])&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Fine Gael]] [[Teachta Dála]]&lt;br&gt;for [[Mayo West (Dáil Éireann constituency)|Mayo West]]
       |years  = [[Mayo West by-election, 1975|1975]]–[[Irish general election, 1997|1997]]}}
{{s-non|reason = Constituency abolished}}
{{s-new|constituency}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Fine Gael]] [[Teachta Dála]]&lt;br&gt;for [[Mayo (Dáil Éireann constituency)|Mayo]]
       |years  = [[Irish general election, 1997|1997]]–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before = [[George Birmingham]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = Minister of State for Youth Affairs
       |years  = 1986–1987}}
{{s-aft|after  = [[Frank Fahey]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Charlie McCreevy]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht|Minister for Tourism and Trade]]
       |years  = 1994–1997}}
{{s-aft|after  = [[Jim McDaid]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Michael Noonan]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Leader of the Opposition (Ireland)|Leader of the Opposition]]
       |years  = 2002–2011}}
{{s-aft|after  = [[Micheál Martin]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Brian Cowen]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Taoiseach]]
       |years  = 2011–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Michael Noonan]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Leader of Fine Gael]]
       |years  = 2002–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-hon}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Máire Geoghegan-Quinn]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Baby of the House|Baby of the Dáil]]
       |years  = 1975–1977}}
{{s-aft|after  = [[Síle de Valera]]}}
{{s-bef|before = [[Séamus Pattison]]}}
{{s-ttl|title  = [[Father of the Dáil]]
       |years  = 2007–present}}
{{s-inc}}
{{s-end}}

{{Current Government of Ireland}}
{{Prime Ministers of Ireland}}
{{European Council}}
{{Current TDs}}
{{Bruton Cabinet}}
{{Fine Gael}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Kenny, Enda
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Irish [[Fine Gael]] politician, [[Taoiseach]] since 2011
| DATE OF BIRTH     =24 April 1951
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Castlebar]], [[County Mayo]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Kenny, Enda}}

[[Category:1951 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Alumni of St Patrick's College of Education, Drumcondra]]
[[Category:Alumni of University College Galway]]
[[Category:Current national leaders]]
[[Category:Irish schoolteachers]]
[[Category:Leaders of Fine Gael]]
[[Category:Kenny family|Enda]]
[[Category:Members of the 20th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 21st Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 22nd Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 23rd Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 24th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 25th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 26th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 27th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 28th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 29th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 30th Dáil]]
[[Category:Members of the 31st Dáil]]
[[Category:People from County Mayo]]
[[Category:Taoisigh of Ireland]]
[[Category:Teachtaí Dála]]

[[be:Энда Кені]]
[[cs:Enda Kenny]]
[[cy:Enda Kenny]]
[[da:Enda Kenny]]
[[de:Enda Kenny]]
[[et:Enda Kenny]]
[[es:Enda Kenny]]
[[eu:Enda Kenny]]
[[fr:Enda Kenny]]
[[ga:Éanna Ó Coinnigh]]
[[gv:Enda Kenny]]
[[gl:Enda Kenny]]
[[ko:엔다 케니]]
[[it:Enda Kenny]]
[[la:Endeus Kenny]]
[[lb:Enda Kenny]]
[[ms:Enda Kenny]]
[[nl:Enda Kenny]]
[[ja:エンダ・ケニー]]
[[no:Enda Kenny]]
[[pl:Enda Kenny]]
[[pt:Enda Kenny]]
[[qu:Enda Kenny]]
[[ru:Кенни, Энда]]
[[sco:Enda Kenny]]
[[sr:Енда Кени]]
[[sh:Enda Kenny]]
[[fi:Enda Kenny]]
[[sv:Enda Kenny]]
[[tr:Enda Kenny]]
[[uk:Енда Кенні]]
[[yo:Enda Kenny]]
[[zh:恩达·肯尼]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
