<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2616811" ns="0" title="List of companions in Doctor Who spin-offs"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{One source|date=January 2010}}
This is a list of fictional characters who were [[companion (Doctor Who)|companions]] of the [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|Doctor]], in various [[Doctor Who spin-offs|spin-off]] media based on the long-running British [[science fiction on television|science fiction television]] series, ''[[Doctor Who]]''. The [[canon (fiction)|canonicity]] of these spin-offs is unclear. 

{{compacttoc}}

==A==
===Amy===
'''Amy''', portrayed by [[Ciara Janson]], is a companion of the [[Fifth Doctor]] in the ''Key 2 Time'' series, which includes the plays ''[[The Judgement of Isskar]]'', ''[[The Destroyer of Delights]]'' and ''[[The Chaos Pool]]''. 

She is a human &quot;tracer&quot;, a device designed to track down the segments of the [[Story_arcs_in_Doctor_Who#The_Key_to_Time|Key to Time]] across the universe. When the Doctor meets Amy, she is just a few seconds old and recruits the Doctor as her companion to find the Key. 

At the end of ''The Chaos Pool'', [[Romana]] invites Amy to live on [[Gallifrey]] and enroll in their Academy.

Amy (now renamed Abby) and her sister Zara return in their own mini-series [[List_of_Doctor_Who_audio_plays_by_Big_Finish#Graceless|Graceless]].

===Antimony===
'''Antimony''' was a companion of the [[Seventh Doctor]] and appeared in the [[webcast]] story ''[[Death Comes to Time]]'' by Colin Meek (widely understood to be a pseudonym for [[Dan Freedman]]). At the start of the story, the listener was not aware of the circumstances of his and the Doctor's meeting. Antimony appeared to be a young humanoid male who was slightly unworldly and naive, for example believing there were still [[Allosaurus]]es roaming the Earth. 

During Antimony and the Doctor's battle against the renegade [[Time Lord]], General Tannis, it was revealed that Antimony was in fact an [[Android (robot)|android]] constructed by the Doctor. The Doctor in ''Death Comes to Time'' was very old and, saddened by the death and departure of many companions, had built Antimony as a companion who would never leave him. Tannis totally destroyed Antimony, leaving the Doctor grief-stricken over Antimony's death.

The actor [[Kevin Eldon]] provided the voice of Antimony.  The illustrations, by [[Lee Sullivan]], depicted Antimony as a humanoid with purplish skin, nonetheless bearing a slight resemblance to Eldon.

===Antranak===
'''Antranak''' was the name [[Erimem]] gave to the stray cat she brought aboard the [[Fifth Doctor]]'s TARDIS at the end of ''[[The Eye of the Scorpion]].''  Erimem had adopted the cat, who had in the course of events absorbed a malevolent alien intelligence harmlessly into its mind, and named him Antranak after her mentor in [[Egypt]].

Erimem and [[Peri Brown|Peri]] were quite fond of the cat, the Doctor less so.  Antranak quickly made himself at home in the TARDIS, much to the Doctor's chagrin, thanks to the cat's habit of jumping onto the console, and refusal to use the [[litterbox]].

Antranak departed in ''[[Nekromanteia (Doctor Who audio)|Nekromanteia]].''  An energy converter had been built on the planet Talderun to support its creator, Shara, in a [[heaven]]-like state of non-existence in a [[pocket universe]] while his body anchored the reaction on the material plane.  Due to the theft and destruction of Shara's corpse, the reaction was becoming critically imbalanced, and would soon destroy the planet, and ultimately the entire [[star system]].

The reaction could only be rebalanced by another living being mounting an [[altar]] and swapping places with Shara, allowing Shara to return to the physical world and die while the sacrificed being became trapped in Shara's pocket Universe.  The Doctor prepared to sacrifice himself to save the planet, but Erimem argued that she should be the one to make the sacrifice.  While they argued, Antranak leaped onto the altar himself, swapping places with Shara and stabilising the reaction, saving the planet and allowing Shara to die in peace.

The Doctor later wondered if the alien creature in the cat's mind forced him to act. Erimem, however, remained firm in her belief that her noble cat sacrificed himself of his own accord.

===Arnold===
'''Arnold''', a boy from the 30th century, was a short-lived companion for the [[Third Doctor]] in the pages of ''[[TV Comic]]'' in 1973. Introduced in the story ''Children of the Evil Eye'' (TVC #1133-#1138), he appeared in only one further story, ''Nova'' (TVC #1139-#1147), before being returned to his own time by the Doctor.

==B==
===Beatrice===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned only by name in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. This may be the same person as [[Trix MacMillan]].

===Emily Blandish===
{{Main|Emily Blandish}}

===Thomas Brewster===
Thomas Brewster, portrayed by [[John Pickard (British actor)|John Pickard]], was the travelling companion of the [[Fifth Doctor]] and Nyssa during a limited story arc in the [[Big Finish Productions]] audio dramas.  Brewster, a Victorian orphan, meets the Doctor in ''[[The Haunting of Thomas Brewster]]'', which culminates with his theft of the TARDIS.  He returns it during the events of ''[[The Boy That Time Forgot]]'', travelling with the Doctor in the subsequent three-part story ''[[Time Reef &amp; A Perfect World|Time Reef]]''.  In the accompanying single-part story, ''[[Time_Reef_%26_A_Perfect_World#A_Perfect_World|A Perfect World]]'', Brewster leaves the TARDIS to live in [[2008|the present day]].  The 12-part mini-series ''[[The Three Companions]]'' reveals an adventure he had with [[Alistair Gordon Lethbridge-Stewart]] and [[Polly Wright]] during the time he had the TARDIS.  Later in his life, he starts traveling with the [[Sixth Doctor]] and [[Evelyn Smythe]] in ''[[The Crimes of Thomas Brewster]]''.  The Doctor leaves Brewster in Victorian [[Lancashire]], but Brewster ends up leaving Earth with an alien trader in ''[[Industrial Evolution]]''.

===Catherine Broome===
'''Catherine &quot;Cat&quot; Broome''' was a companion of the [[Seventh Doctor]] from the [[Telos Doctor Who novellas|Telos novella]] ''[[Companion Piece]]'' by [[Robert Perry (writer)|Robert Perry]] and [[Mike Tucker]]. The Doctor and Cat are already travelling together at the start of the novella. Needing mercury links for the [[TARDIS]], they tried to steal some from the Wierdarbi, a race of cybernetically enhanced insects. When cornered by the Wierdarbi, Cat defeated them by releasing a swarm of prototype robots built by the Doctor. 

Still in need of the mercury links, they next travelled to Haven, a planet controlled by the [[Roman Catholic Church]]. The Doctor was nearly burnt at the stake because the [[Time Lord]]s had been to the planet before, and the Church declared them to be witches. He was temporarily spared by the arrival of a giant cross shaped spaceship belonging to the Holy [[Inquisition]]. Whilst the Doctor was being tortured, Cat sneaked into the Cathedral on Haven and encountered an elderly priest named Father Julian. Believing herself to be Roman Catholic, she gave her confession to Julian, who offered to try to save the Doctor's life. After Cat was arrested for the murder of an Archbishop, she and the Doctor were taken to Rome (in fact a space station) to be tried by the [[Pope]]. On the journey, Cat relived many childhood memories with a friendly priest named Paddy, and noted the coincidence of many shared experiences. She later saw that he was in fact a robot. When the Bishop programming the Paddy robot tried to strangle Cat, he let go at the last moment and began laughing.

When the space ship came under attack by a barbarian horde, the Doctor reprogrammed its robots to defend it. As the battle raged, access to the control room was cut off to all except robots, and the TARDIS was trapped in a stasis field. The Doctor noted that there was only one robot left who could get there, one which he had something to tell. The novella ended there, with the implication that Cat was the robot.

==C==
===C'rizz===
{{Main|C'rizz}}

===Tom Campbell===
[[File:Tom Campbell.jpg|right|thumb|100px|Tom Campbell]]
Special Constable Tom Campbell (portrayed by [[Bernard Cribbins]], who later played [[Wilfred Mott]] in the revived television series in 2007-2010) travelled with [[Dr. Who (Dalek films)|Dr Who]] in the feature film ''[[Daleks - Invasion Earth 2150 AD]]''. His role replaced that of [[Ian Chesterton]] in the television serial ''[[The Dalek Invasion of Earth]]'', on which the film was based.

Tom mistook the [[TARDIS]] for a real [[police box|police telephone box]] while attempting to foil a jewel robbery. Tom accompanied Dr Who, along with his niece Louise and his granddaughter [[Susan Foreman|Susan]], to the year 2150, where they discovered that the [[Dalek]]s had invaded Earth. After the Daleks were defeated, The Doctor returned him to London a few minutes before the robbery was due to take place, enabling him to catch the robbers.
{{-}}

===Alison Cheney===
[[Alison Cheney]] was a companion of the &quot;unofficial&quot; [[Shalka Doctor|Ninth Doctor]] who appeared in the [[Macromedia Flash|flash]]-animated serial ''[[Scream of the Shalka]]'' by [[Paul Cornell]] and the short story [http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/vampires/newstory/scottwright.shtml ''The Feast of the Stone''] by [[Cavan Scott]] and [[Mark Wright (writer)|Mark Wright]]. Her voice was provided by [[Sophie Okonedo]], who was also the visual model for the character, animated by [[Cosgrove Hall Films|Cosgrove Hall]].

Alison was a barmaid from the 21st century who lived in the village of Lannet in [[Lancashire]] with her boyfriend Joe, a doctor. Out of all the village inhabitants she was the only one who did not live in fear of the [[Scream of the Shalka#Shalka|Shalka]]. 

She was instrumental in helping the Doctor defeat the Shalka. At the end of the adventure she admitted she was going to leave Joe even before all of the Shalka problems started, and broke up with him. When the Master asked her to join the Doctor on his travels, she accepted.
{{-}}

===Claudia===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned in [[Lance Parkin]]'s eighth Doctor novels ''Father Time'' and ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]''. The name '''Claudia''' is thought to be an in-joke on Parkin's part, referring to ''The Stranger'' by [[Portia Da Costa]] (Wendy Wootton), an erotic novel in Virgin Publishing's [[Black Lace (books)|Black Lace]] range. ''The Stranger'' recounts the affair between a widow named Claudia Marwood and a mysterious amnesiac named &quot;Paul&quot;, whom da Costa based on [[Paul McGann]]'s performance as the Doctor.  Claudia is said in ''Father Time'' to be a widow.

===Compassion===
{{Main|Compassion (Doctor Who)}}

===Rachel Cooper===
Rachel, played by [[Lenora Crichlow]] was a companion of the [[Seventh Doctor]] in an alternate timeline. In the Big Finish audio [[The Architects of History]] Rachel was working with the Doctor in an effort to put right an alternate reality created by [[List_of_companions_in_Doctor_Who_spin-offs#Klein|Elizabeth Klein]], in which the Nazis had won World War II and then created a Galactic Reich. In the reality where time has run it's correct course, she and the Doctor have never met.

===Raine Creevey===
Raine, played by [[Beth Chalmers]], is a companion to the [[Seventh Doctor]], starting with [[The Lost Stories]] audio drama ''[[Crime Of The Century (Doctor Who audio)|Crime Of The Century]]''.  The character was originally intended to be the television companion just after [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]] left, however the series was canceled before Ace's character was even given a departure story.  In the audio series, Raine travels alongside Ace, rather than replacing her.  Raine's father was an English smuggler and her mother was a Russian [[KGB]] agent.  The Doctor met them 22 years earlier in ''[[Thin Ice (Doctor Who)|Thin Ice]]'', where he helped deliver infant Raine.  She gestated for only fifteen weeks because her mother's biology was accelerated by ancient [[Ice Warrior]] technology.  Raine is adept at [[safecracking]], [[burglary]], [[fencing]] as well as being a [[helicopter pilot]].  She is cultured and high class, in contrast to Ace.

===Chris Cwej===
{{Main|Chris Cwej}}

===Crystal===
'''Crystal''', a nightclub singer, appeared in the stage play ''[[Doctor Who - The Ultimate Adventure]]'', written by [[Terrance Dicks]]. She was portrayed by [[Rebecca Thornhill]].

In the [[Big Finish Productions]] audio adaptation she was portrayed by [[Claire Huckle]].

During the course of the play, she developed a friendship with [[#Zog|Zog]] and also formed a close relationship with fellow companion [[#Jason|Jason]] which eventually became romantic. At the end of the play, Jason persuaded her to accompany them on their travels in the [[TARDIS]].

&lt;br style=&quot;clear:both&quot; /&gt;

==D==
===Dave===
'''Dave''' was the alternative name for [[#Jimmy|Jimmy]] in the 1981 and 1984 regional revivals of the 1974 play ''[[Doctor Who and the Daleks in the Seven Keys to Doomsday]]''. The character was named Dave in the script by [[Terrance Dicks]] but this had been changed for the original production after actor James Matthews was cast in the role.

===Oliver Day===
'''Oliver Day''' is a companion of the [[Fourth Doctor]] introduced in the [[Big Finish Short Trips]] anthology ''[[Short Trips: Snapshots]]''. He first appears in ''Attachments'' and features in ''Flight of the Monkrah'' and ''Puppeteer''.&lt;ref name=&quot;DWM&quot;&gt;{{Citation
  | last = Michael
  | first = Matt
  | author-link =
  | last2 =
  | first2 =
  | author2-link =
  | title = [[Doctor Who Magazine]]
  | journal = 
  | volume =
  | issue = 387
  | pages = 62
  | date = 17 October 2007, released 19 September 2007
  | url =
  | doi =
  | id =  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deborah===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned only by name in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. The name may refer to the character of Debbie Castle from the novel ''Father Time'', also by Parkin.

===Delilah===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned only by name in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. Nothing more is known about this person.

===Destrii===
{{Main|Destrii}}

===Tamsin Drew===
Making her debut in the audio play ''[[Situation Vacant]]'', Tamsin Drew was a failed actress who answered an advert for a companion to a time traveller. She approached it as a type of audition and affected the persona of Juliet Walsh, a professional career woman. Although he didn't place the ad, the [[Eighth Doctor]] spotted it as being intended for him and played along. After finding out the truth about Tamsin, (and after dispatching all the other applicants for their respective secrets and betrayals) he invited her to travel with him, having recently split from [[Lucie Miller]].  Lucie meanwhile has been traveling with [[Meddling Monk|The Monk]], but when she leaves him, he manipulates Tamsin to coerce her into being his new companion.  She eventually meets back up with the Doctor during a Dalek invasion of Earth (featured in ''[[Lucie Miller (audio drama)|Lucie Miller]]'' / ''[[To the Death (audio drama)|To the Death]]''), where she finds out the truth about the Monk. She agrees to help the Doctor, but is killed by a Dalek shortly after, leaving the Monk devastated.  Tamsin is played by [[Niky Wardley]].

==E==
===Maxwell Edison===
Max is a character that originated in the [[Doctor Who Magazine]] comics.  He is a resident of the small [[west country]] town of Stockbridge, which the Doctor often visits.  A UFO spotter and amateur psychic investigator, Max is awkward and often derided by the other locals.  He does, however, have some actual psychic abilities, although he doesn't fully understand how to use them.  He first met the [[Fifth Doctor]] in the 1982 comic ''Stars Fell on Stockbridge'', when a starship disintegrated over the town.  Roughly a decade later, he befriended [[Izzy Sinclair]], a teenage girl who shared his interest in space and science fiction.  In the 1996 comic ''End Game'', they both encountered the [[Eighth Doctor]], at which point Izzy began traveling in the TARDIS.  The [[Tenth Doctor]] encountered him in the 2009 comic ''The Stockbridge Child'', which ended with Max being badly stricken while riding his moped.  Later that year, he was reunited with the Fifth Doctor in the Big Finish audio story ''[[The Eternal Summer]]''.  Voiced by [[Mark Williams (actor)|Mark Williams]], this story involved a complex time trap that ultimately resulted in Max surviving his road incident.

===Emma===
'''Emma''' was the companion of the Ninth Doctor portrayed by [[Rowan Atkinson]] in the 1999 spoof charity serial ''[[Doctor Who and the Curse of Fatal Death]]'' written by [[Steven Moffat]] and produced for the charity ''[[Comic Relief (charity)|Comic Relief]]''. She was portrayed by [[Julia Sawalha]], who had previously auditioned for the role of [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]].

The circumstances of their meeting were never explained, but the Doctor had planned to marry her and retire. However, the [[Master (Doctor Who)|Master]] (played by [[Jonathan Pryce]]) and the [[Dalek]]s had other plans, and by the end of the story the Doctor had used up all of his remaining [[Doctor (Doctor Who)#Changing faces|regenerations]]. The Doctor's thirteenth (and final) incarnation turned out to be a woman (played by [[Joanna Lumley]]) &amp;mdash; a form that Emma was not interested in marrying, as the Doctor was literally no longer the man she fell in love with. The Doctor, finding the Master suddenly quite attractive, departed with him instead.

===Erimem===
{{Main|Erimem}}

==F==
===Jeremy Fitzoliver===
A companion of the [[Third Doctor]], introduced in the [[BBC Radio 4|Radio 4]] audio drama ''[[The Paradise of Death]]'' and played by [[Richard C. Pearce]]. Jeremy is a photographer for ''Metropolitan'', the magazine [[Sarah Jane Smith]] works for, and is assigned to the story Sarah is investigating. Jeremy is an inexperienced and somewhat clueless photographer, reflecting the editor's scepticism about Sarah's story, and is used as a comic relief character whom the regular cast find annoying. 

Jeremy subsequently appears in the follow-up drama ''[[The Ghosts of N-Space]]'', in which he gives Sarah his spare ticket on a trip to [[Sicily]] (his mother decided not to go), thereby bringing them into the story, and the [[Past Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[Island of Death]]'' in which Sarah enlists the Doctor and the Brigadier to rescue him from an alien cult. This novel also explains that he owes his job to his uncle owning 30% of the magazine. Several [[Big Finish Short Trips]] stories see Jeremy travel with the Third Doctor as his Companion during an unclear period of time where the Third Doctor appears not to be travelling with Sarah.

One of the villains in the [[Sixth Doctor]] Past Doctor Adventures novel ''[[Instruments of Darkness]]'' is &quot;John Doe&quot;, a paranoid amnesiac with a grudge against the Doctor and UNIT. At the end of the novel, following his death, it is revealed he was Jeremy, whose mental problems began when he carelessly activated the Doctor's [[Planet of the Spiders|Image Reproduction Integrating System]].

===Jimmy Forbes===
Jimmy was one of the Doctor's companions in the stage play ''[[Doctor Who and the Daleks in the Seven Keys to Doomsday]]'', played by James Matthews. In the [[Big Finish Productions|Big Finish]] audio adaptation, he was played by Joseph Thompson.

===Roz Forrester===
{{Main|Roz Forrester}}

===Frank===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned only by name in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. Nothing more is known about this person.

===Frobisher===
{{Main|Frobisher (Doctor Who)}}

==G==
===Gus Goodman===
'''Angus Goodman''', or simply '''Gus''', was a companion of the [[Fifth Doctor]] in the ''[[Doctor Who Magazine|Doctor Who Monthly]]'' comic strips. He first appeared in the story ''Lunar Lagoon'' (DWM #76-#77), although he did not meet the Doctor until the start of the next story, ''4-Dimensional Vistas'' (DWM#78-#83). Gus's first appearances were written by [[Steve Parkhouse]] and illustrated by [[Mick Austin]]; he was later drawn by [[Steve Dillon]].

Gus was an American fighter pilot from an [[Parallel universe (fiction)|alternate timeline]] where World War II was still being fought in 1963. The Doctor had accidentally taken the [[TARDIS]] there, not realising that the idyllic island he had picked out as a holiday spot was not on an alien planet, but somewhere in the Pacific of that parallel Earth. Gus crashed on the island after a dogfight with a [[Japan]]ese plane, and accepted the Doctor's offer to take him off the island. 

However, as was usual for the Doctor, he did not take Gus home by the direct route. Back in the Doctor's own universe, they first encountered the Doctor's old enemy, the [[Meddling Monk]], who had allied himself with the [[Ice Warrior]]s to create a gigantic sonic cannon. After thwarting their plans, the two travelled to the planet Celeste. There they met the malevolent frog-like businessman, Dogbolter, whom the Doctor offended when he refused to sell Dogbolter the TARDIS (''The Moderator'', DWM #86-87).

Dogbolter sent a [[hitman]], the Moderator, after the Doctor. The Moderator followed the Doctor's trail back to Gus's world, and ambushed them when the Doctor was about to drop Gus off. Gus was shot in the ensuing hail of gunfire, but managed to shoot back and incapacitate the Moderator. Gus died from his wounds, much to the Doctor's sadness. The Doctor left Gus where he had fallen, but would eventually seek out and encounter Dogbolter again.

===Samson and Gemma Griffin===
'''Samson Griffin''' and his sister '''Gemma''' appeared in the [[Big Finish Productions|Big Finish]] audio adventure ''[[Terror Firma]]'', in which it was revealed that they had travelled with the [[Eighth Doctor]] before he met [[Charley Pollard]].  Samson was played by [[Lee Ingleby]], and Gemma by [[Lizzie Hopley]].  They have since appeared in the short stories ''The Long Midwinter'' by [[Philip Purser-Hallard]], published in ''[[Short Trips: The History of Christmas]]'' and ''Dear John'' published in ''[[Short Trips: The Centenarian]]''.

Samson was a librarian who lived in the town of [[Folkestone]]. He and his sister met the Doctor in the Folkestone library and followed him into the [[TARDIS]]. Their travels included visits to the planets Porteus and Murgatroyd, the Ice Caves of Shabadabadon, the court of [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]], prehistoric Earth and [[Studio 54]].  ''The Long Midwinter'' details another of Samson and Gemma's adventures during this time, set on the brown dwarf world of Yesod.  The three then travelled to 1956 to visit the Doctor's old friend, Edward Grainger. Samson called the Doctor &quot;Skipper&quot;, and greatly enjoyed his adventures.

After a visit to the planet Valuensis, the TARDIS encountered a Nekkistani time cruiser in the Time Vortex. Samson and Gemma went to explore the ship and encountered [[Davros]], who gained control of their minds. Davros forced Samson to knock the Doctor out, and operated on the TARDIS and the Griffins, linking Samson's mind to the TARDIS. Davros returned Samson and Gemma to Earth and altered the Doctor's memories so that he had no recollection of the two siblings.

Samson remained subconsciously aware of the Doctor's further travels with Charley and [[C'rizz]] via his link with the TARDIS, and remained under Davros' partial control. This allowed Davros to monitor the Doctor while leaving Samson disoriented and confused. Davros also infected Gemma with a deadly virus that mutates humans into Daleks, using her to spread the disease around the world and paving the way for Davros to conquer the planet with a new race of [[Dalek]]s. When the Doctor, Charley and C'rizz arrived on Earth, Davros (who was struggling against having his personality consumed by the Dalek Emperor programming) sprung his elaborate trap.

Unknown to Davros, Gemma had encountered and become allied with a faction of rebel Daleks. On their orders, she tested C'rizz's killing instincts, which were proven when he killed a human test subject. Gemma then brought C'rizz to the Dalek resistance, who tried unsuccessfully to make C'rizz their new [[Dalek variants#Dalek Emperor|Emperor]]. Gemma's exact fate is unknown, although C'rizz told the Doctor she had died and it is implied that C'rizz killed her.

Eventually, the Doctor blackmailed the Daleks into releasing C'rizz and leaving Earth, taking Davros (now fully the Dalek Emperor) with them. The Doctor then freed Samson from Davros's control and severed his link to the TARDIS. Samson remained in Folkestone with his mother Harriet, a leader of the human resistance, to help rebuild Earth.

In the play ''[[Minuet in Hell]]'', a litany of the Doctor's previous companions includes the name &quot;Sam&quot;. At the time of the play's release, this was intended as a reference to [[Sam Jones (Doctor Who)|Sam Jones]], the Eighth Doctor's companion from the [[Eighth Doctor Adventures|novels]]; this placed the books and the audios in the same continuity.  Producer [[Gary Russell]] subsequently decided that the two continuities should be separate (partly because of different directions taken between the two ranges).  ''Terror Firma'' now provides the possibility that &quot;Sam&quot; was a reference to Samson instead, although this is undermined somewhat by the Doctor constantly addressing Samson by his full name and never once as &quot;Sam&quot;.

''[[The_Company_of_Friends#Mary.27s_Story|The Company of Friends: Mary's Story]]'' reveals that at some point during their travels, the Doctor dropped Samson and Gemma off in [[Vienna]] and then spent years travelling with [[Mary Shelley]] before going finally returning to pick them up.  His first attempt to reunite with them was in ''[[The Silver Turk]]'', which reveals that he left them in June, 1816, the same day he met Mary in [[Switzerland]].

==H==
===Oliver Harper===
Played by [[Tom Allen (comedian)|Tom Allen]], Oliver Harper was a [[Trader (finance)|city trader]] from 1966.  He joined the [[First Doctor]] and [[Steven Taylor (Doctor Who)|Steven Taylor]], in the audio play ''[[The Perpetual Bond]]''.  He was motivated to escape with the Doctor as he was in immediate danger of being arrested for [[Buggery Act 1533|homosexual behaviour]], as revealed in his second story, ''[[The Cold Equations (Doctor Who)|The Cold Equations]]''.  In his third adventure, ''[[The First Wave]]'', he is killed by Vardans, beings of pure energy.  His mind continued to exist without form or ability to interact with others.  He stayed with the Doctor, unbeknownst to him, finally fading out of existence during the Doctor's first [[regeneration (Doctor Who)|regeneration]].  Oliver is the first ongoing companion created for the [[List_of_Doctor_Who_audio_plays_by_Big_Finish#The_Companion_Chronicles|Companion Chronicles]] range

===Hex===
{{Main|Hex (Doctor Who)}}

==I==
===Isaac===
:''See [[#William|William]] ''

==J==
===Flip Jackson===
'''Flip (Philippa) Jackson''' was a young girl who boarded a [[London Underground|tube train]] with her boyfriend, Jared.  The train went through a temporal breach, transporting it from modern day London to a [[Sentience|sentient]] planet called Symbios.  There, Flip briefly met the [[Sixth Doctor]], whose companion at the time was [[Evelyn Smythe]].  In this first appearance, the 2011 audio drama ''[[The Crimes of Thomas Brewster]]'', Flip and Jared return to Earth while the Doctor and Evelyn leave in the TARDIS.  Flip reunites with the Sixth Doctor and journeys with him, starting with the January 2012 release, ''[[The Curse of Davros]]''.  She is played by [[Lisa Greenwood]].

===Jason===
'''Jason''', a young nobleman from [[French Revolution|Revolutionary France]], appeared in the stage play ''[[Doctor Who - The Ultimate Adventure]]'', written by [[Terrance Dicks]].

Jason was originally played by [[Graeme Smith (actor)|Graeme Smith]] up until 15 July 1989, except from 21–23 April 1989 (where he was portrayed by [[David Bingham (actor)|David Bingham]]). Bingham carried on in the role from 17 July 1989 until the end of the stage production. 

Jason was rescued from the [[Guillotine]] by the Doctor and was already a companion with the Doctor at the start of the play. When [[#Crystal|Crystal]] joined them he developed a close friendship with her which eventually became romantic. At the end of the play, Jason persuaded her accompany them on their travels in the [[TARDIS]]. 

In the [[Big Finish Productions]] audio adaptation he is played by former [[Hear'say]] member [[Noel Sullivan]].

Jason was also the name of the new [[List of Doctor Who villains#Master of the Land of Fiction|Master of the Land of Fiction]] in the [[Virgin New Adventures]] novels ''Conundrum'' and ''Head Games'' by [[Steve Lyons (writer)|Steve Lyons]], and briefly accompanied a fictional version of the Doctor known as &quot;Dr. Who&quot; before the [[Seventh Doctor]] set things right.

Neither Jason should be confused with [[Jason Kane (Doctor Who)|Jason Kane]], the ex-husband of [[Bernice Summerfield]].

===Jemima-Katy===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned only by name in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. The name is the same as that of a companion (played by [[Mel Giedroyc]]) being &quot;auditioned&quot; by [[Jon Pertwee]] in a sketch from the 1990s BBC radio comedy, ''The Skivers''.

===Angela Jennings===
'''Angela Jennings''' was a companion of the [[Sixth Doctor]], who  met her on the planet Torrok in 2191 in the [[Virgin Missing Adventures]] novel ''Time Of Your Life'' by [[Steve Lyons (writer)|Steve Lyons]].

Angela was born in 2171 and had black hair and green eyes.  Her ID number was 9/12/44.  Her father was killed by &quot;outside perils&quot; and her sister Ruth was taken away by Peace Keepers.  Angela's time with [[Doctor (Doctor Who)|the Doctor]] was sadly cut short when he left her aboard the abandoned [[space station]] used by the Meson Broadcasting Company. Although this was to keep her safe, Angela's body was killed by a techno-organic, data consuming entity known as Krllxk. The last bits of Angela's consciousness absorbed by Krllxk died after the Meson station vaporised.

===John and Gillian===
{{Main|John and Gillian (Doctor Who)}}

===Sam Jones===
{{Main|Sam Jones (Doctor Who)}}

===June===
A university student who travels with the [[Tenth Doctor]] to the time of King [[Actaeus]] of [[Athens]] in the novel ''[[The Slitheen Excursion]]''.

===Sir Justin===
[[Image:Sirjustin.jpg|thumb|120px|Sir Justin]]
'''Sir Justin''', a medieval knight, accompanied the [[Fifth Doctor]] in the ''[[Doctor Who Magazine|Doctor Who Monthly]]'' comic strip story ''The Tides of Time'' (DWM#61-#67), written by [[Steve Parkhouse]] and illustrated by [[Dave Gibbons]].

Justin was a pious [[Christianity|Christian]] knight from [[England in the Middle Ages|medieval England]] who was transported to the 20th century by the actions of the demon Melanicus. Melanicus had wrested control of a vast biomechanical complex known as the Event Synthesizer (which could control all of time, space, and reality) from its guardian, the [[cosmological argument|Prime Mover]], using the Synthesizer to wreak havoc with time. Justin was plucked from a [[jousting|joust]] in his own time, and collided with the Doctor's [[TARDIS]] outside of the village of Stockbridge.  The Doctor brought the unconscious Justin into the TARDIS, and when Justin recovered the Doctor was impressed with the ease with which he accepted his strange surroundings.  Justin also believed the Doctor to be an angel of God, the TARDIS a miracle and their quest a [[crusade]], despite the Doctor's attempts to disabuse him of the notion.

Justin accompanied the Doctor to [[Gallifrey]] and the Althrace system, which was situated inside a [[white hole]], to attend a meeting with the High Evolutionaries of Althrace who explained the situation with Melanicus. Eventually, with the help of [[Rassilon]], [[Merlin (wizard)|Merlin]], and the [[Matrix (Doctor Who)|Matrix]]-powered [[Time Lord]] agent known as [[Shayde]], the Doctor was able to confront Melanicus, who had hidden the Event Synthesizer in a time-altered version of a Stockbridge church. Justin, the Doctor and Shayde fought Melanicus, and Justin gave the killing blow at the cost of his own life, all in a blinding flash.  

With time set right, the Doctor regained consciousness in the restored church &amp;mdash; now named St. Justinian's &amp;mdash; in the 20th century, wondering if it had all been a dream. There, he saw a statue of Sir Justin, with an inscribed epitaph referring obliquely to his adventures in time and space. It was suggested that Merlin was responsible for the memorial.

==K==
===Anji Kapoor===
{{Main|Anji Kapoor}}

===Fitz Kreiner===
{{Main|Fitz Kreiner}}

===Klein===
Elizabeth Klein (voiced by [[Tracey Childs]]) was first heard in the 2001 [[Big Finish Productions]] audio story ''[[Colditz (Doctor Who audio)|Colditz]]''.  She was a British citizen of German descent who came from an alternate timeline in which the [[Nazis]] had won World War II.  She was a scientist, working for the Reich, and put in charge of studying the Doctor's captured TARDIS.  In it, she traveled from her version of 1965, back to the original version of 1944, where she was ultimately stranded by the [[Seventh Doctor]].  She returns as the Seventh Doctor's traveling companion in the 2010 story ''[[A Thousand Tiny Wings]]'' and continues in ''[[Survival of the Fittest &amp; Klein’s Story]]'', but is subsequently erased from history in ''[[The Architects of History]]'' after she steals the TARDIS in an attempt to recreate her own history, resulting in Earth and the 'Thousand Year Reich' being destroyed in a brief war with the Selachians. Her erasure undoes the damage she had caused to history, the story ending with the Doctor meeting the Klein that exists in the 'true' history, now working for UNIT, although it is unclear how much he remembers of his time with the original Klein.

===Kroton===
{{Main|Kroton (Cyberman)}}

==L==
===Larna===
'''Larna''' was a [[Time Lord]] who assisted the Doctor during ''[[The Infinity Doctors]]'', and later appeared in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]''. A Larna also appeared in ''[[Unnatural History (Doctor Who)|Unnatural History]]'', and recognised the Doctor, but it is unclear if this was the same character. A short story, &quot;Birth of a Renegade&quot; by [[Eric Saward]] published in the ''[[Radio Times]]'' special commemorating the 20th anniversary of ''Doctor Who'', had previously established Lady Larna as the true Gallifreyan name of [[Susan Foreman]].

===Lorenzo===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] first mentioned in a flashback sequence in the novel ''The Year of Intelligent Tigers'' by [[Kate Orman]], which took place in the [[Pacific Ocean|South Sea]]s in 1935. Lorenzo is mentioned again in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]].

===Louise===
'''Louise''' (portrayed by [[Jill Curzon]]) was the niece of &quot;[[Dr. Who (Dalek films)|Dr. Who]]&quot; in the film ''[[Daleks - Invasion Earth 2150 AD]]''. In the film's plot, Louise took the role filled by [[Barbara Wright (Doctor Who)|Barbara Wright]] in the television serial ''[[The Dalek Invasion of Earth]]'', on which the film was based.

==M==
===Trix MacMillan===
{{Main|Trix MacMillan}}

===Grant Markham===
{{Main|Grant Markham}}

===Ellie Martin===
'''Ellie Martin''' (played by [[Juliet Warner]]) is the companion of the [[Valeyard]] in the Big Finish play ''[[He Jests at Scars...]]'', set in an [[Parallel universe (fiction)|alternate universe]] where the Valeyard won the Sixth Doctor's remaining incarnations in &quot;[[Trial of a Time Lord]]&quot;. An &quot;eco-warrior&quot;, the Valeyard rescued her from being hit by a police car during an environmental protest, and she accompanied him on his quest to conquer time. He later killed her, to make the point that he was no longer the Doctor. It is hinted she might have known the Doctor before he became the Valeyard as she frequently refers to him, much to the Valeyard's annoyance, as the Doctor, &quot;Champion of Justice&quot;.

In Big Finish's regular ''Doctor Who'' continuity, Martin is a friend of [[Sarah Jane Smith]], and appeared in the first series of ''Sarah Jane'' audio adventures. When the ''Sarah Jane'' audios were initially announced, the role of Ellie Martin was listed as (books companion) Sam Jones; her &quot;eco-warrior&quot; past may be a reference to that former origin.

===Heather McCrimmon===
Heather McCrimmon is a companion of the [[Tenth Doctor]] in the comic strips printed in the Doctor Who Adventures magazine. A history student at [[Edinburgh]] university, she was created by a reader as part of a competition. She debuted in the issue on sale December 31, 2008. It's suggested she's a descendent of [[Jamie McCrimmon]].

===Robert McIntosh===
Played by [[Christian Coulson]], '''Robert McIntosh''' was a young science student from Scotland, who assisted the [[Fifth Doctor]] in ''[[The Haunting of Thomas Brewster]]''.  This took place while the Doctor was spending a year in Victorian London, accidentally separated from [[Nyssa (Doctor Who)|Nyssa]].  Robert sacrificed his life for the Doctor, in the same story he was introduced.

===Mila===
Played by [[Jess Robinson]] and [[India Fisher]], Mila appeared in three audio stories, ''[[Patient Zero (Doctor Who audio)|Patient Zero]]'', ''[[Paper Cuts (Doctor Who audio)|Paper Cuts]]'' and ''[[Blue Forgotten Planet]]''. Mila was a human prisoner of the [[Daleks]], who experimented on her using bio-engineered viruses.  As a result of these endeavors, she lost most of her memories and eventually became invisible and non-corporeal, as well as gaining other strange abilities.  She escaped from the Daleks and snuck on board the [[First Doctor]]'s TARDIS, possibly during the events of [[The Chase (Doctor Who)|The Chase]].  She remained in the TARDIS, unseen by anyone for centuries.  She silently watched the Doctor, growing obsessed by his heroics and longing to be a real companion.  During the [[Sixth Doctor]]'s life, she met [[Charley Pollard]], the only companion unprotected by the TARDIS' biological defenses.  Mila managed to transfer her afflictions to Charley, while simultaneously adopting Charley's physical form.  She was then able travel with the Doctor, pretending to be Charley, while the real Charley was left invisible and alone.  Eventually Charley was cured by the [[Creatures_and_aliens_in_Doctor_Who#Viyrans|Viyrans]] and Mila gave her life to save the Doctor.  The Viyrans also altered the Sixth Doctor's memories so that he remembers his adventures with Charley as being with Mila's name and face.

===Lucie Miller===
{{Main|Lucie Miller}}

===Ruth Mills===
'''Ruth Mills''' (played by [[Siri O'Neal]]) was the companion and foster daughter of an alternate version of the Doctor in the [[Big Finish Productions]] ''Doctor Who Unbound'' [[radio drama|audio play]] ''[[Full Fathom Five (Doctor Who audio)|Full Fathom Five]]'' by [[David Bishop]]. 

This Doctor (played by [[David Collings]]) had raised Ruth since 2039, when her father, Dr Vollmer, was lost in the destruction of the Deep-sea Energy Exploration Project (DEEP) undersea naval base. When the DEEP was rediscovered in 2066, the Doctor hired a mini-sub to get to the base before the naval recovery team. However, Ruth stowed away on board the mini-sub against the Doctor's wishes.  

After Ruth and the Doctor reached the base, Ruth eventually discovered that the Doctor was responsible for her father's death. There had been illegal genetic experimentation going on in the base and the Doctor had killed Vollmer to prevent any information on the experiments from getting out. Still believing that the ends justified the means, the Doctor had simply returned to the DEEP base to regain his [[TARDIS]], which had been left there when he abandoned the base.

Horrified that the man who raised her had been lying to her, Ruth shot the Doctor and watched his face [[Doctor (Doctor Who)#Changing faces|change]]. Ruth shot the new incarnation of the Doctor, and as he changed again, wondered how many times she would have to shoot him before he stayed dead.

===Miranda===
{{Main|Miranda (Doctor Who)}}

==N==
===Nina===
A companion of the [[Eighth Doctor]] mentioned in ''[[The Gallifrey Chronicles (2005 novel)|The Gallifrey Chronicles]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]] and possibly taken from the [[Telos Doctor Who novellas|Telos novella]] ''[[Rip Tide]]'' by [[Louise Cooper]].

==O==
===Olla===
'''Olla''' was very briefly a companion of the [[Seventh Doctor]] in the ''[[Doctor Who Magazine]]'' comic strips. Olla was a Dreilyn, a heat [[vampire]] whose race drew sustenance from draining the heat from other beings, although never enough to kill. She first met the Doctor and [[Frobisher (Doctor Who)|Frobisher]] on A-Lux in the story ''A Cold Day in Hell'' (DWM#130-#133), written by Simon Furman and drawn by [[John Ridgway (comic artist)|John Ridgway]]. A-Lux was a resort planet which the [[Ice Warrior]]s were planning to freeze and turn into a new [[Mars (Doctor Who)|Mars]]. Olla helped the Doctor and Frobisher defeat the Ice Warriors, and when Frobisher elected to stay behind, the Doctor took her on board as his newest companion. The Doctor, however, was mildly disturbed by the way Olla kept waiting on him hand and foot.

Her stint in the TARDIS was short-lived. In the very next story, ''Redemption'' (DWM #134), Olla's former master, the Vachysian warlord Skaroux (a legal enforcer for the Galactic Federation), intercepted the TARDIS and demanded her return. It transpired that Olla had stolen Skaroux's money and then become a fugitive. The Doctor agreed to hand her over on the condition that she receive a fair trial, and Skaroux and Olla left together.

==P==
===Majenta Pryce===
Majenta Pryce is introduced in the ''[[Doctor Who Magazine]]'' comic strip in #394, &quot;Hotel Historia&quot;, as an alien entrepreneur running an illegal time-travel operation on Earth. Her organisation is shut down by the Tenth Doctor, and she gets taken away by the &quot;cosmic baliffs&quot;, saying she likes the Doctor, but will get her revenge. 

She returns &quot;Thinktwice&quot;, a three-part story beginning in #400, as a convict on a space-station prison. The convicts have no recollection of their past lives due to repeated memory wipes, supposedly to rehabilitate them, but actually to feed parasitic lifeforms called the Memeovax. The Doctor enters the station undercover and is surprised to find Majenta there, having assumed she was sent to a &quot;cushy&quot; debtor's prison. He manages to defeat the Memovax and rescue Majenta.

However, Majenta's memories of her time prior to her first encounter with the Doctor do not return. Holding the Doctor responsible for this, she insists she will stay with him until he finds a way to reverse the process. The Doctor is taken aback by this, especially when she tells him she's in charge. She has little patience with the Doctor's insistence on stopping to help people, especially when it does not appear to have anything to do with her problem.

Since then, elements of Majenta's past have come to light; in the story &quot;Mortal Beloved&quot; (DWM #406-407) it transpires she was previously engaged to a powerful businessman named Wesley Sparks, who since her departure has become an insane cyborg. With the help of the Doctor and an artificial intelligence based on Sparks' earlier self, she manages to stop him and leaves the business in the hands of Violet, an android based on herself. The Doctor insists he did not intentionally take her back to Sparks, and she sees a mysterious figure on the scanner telling her to &quot;remember the Hand&quot;. 

Following this, in &quot;The Age of Ice&quot; (DWM# 408-410), Majenta is reunited with Fanson, her business associate from &quot;Hotel Historia&quot;, now working for the [[List of Doctor Who monsters#Skith|Skith]]. Fanson seemingly persuades her to betray the Doctor, and eventually tells her he was the one who erased her memories, claiming he did it to save her sanity. She eventually becomes the Skith Queen, but returns to normal by the end of the story. Unfortunately, Fanson was killed when he intercepted an attack meant for her. At story's end, she's made her peace with the Doctor, and the two head to the next adventure.

In &quot;The Crimson Hand&quot; (DWM# 416-420), Majenta is being pursued by the Intersol Fleet, an intersteller police force which can somehow hack into the TARDIS systems. It is revealed that she is part of a powerful crime organisation called the Crimson Hand. Majenta is captured by Zephyr, an Intersol agent who was her cellmate on Thinktwice. 

Commander Dargo forces his way into Majenta's mind, accessing her suppressed memories of the Crimson Hand - and thereby attracting the Hand themselves; four powerful beings who destroy Intersol's Justice Computer. Majenta tells the Doctor and Zephyr her new memories: The Crimson Hand were a group of four ruthless beings who possessed the Manus Mallificus, a machine shaped like a crimson hand that could reshape reality, but required five users. Majenta accepted their invitation to be the fifth member, but was horrified by their use of the Malus to destroy the Ownworld of the Skith. She fled, limiting the Hand's use of the Manus. Fanson found her, and realised that the Hand could psychically trace her, hence his removal of her memory. The Doctor, Majenta and Zephyr try to escape, but at the last minute, Majenta accepts the Crimson Hand's offer, and seemingly destroys the Doctor.

With the power of the Manus, Majenta attempts to convert her home planet, Vessica, into a utopia. Zephyr is her personal assistant (and, it's implied, lover) and her life is a constant stream of parties. Her desire to make life better for her people puzzles the other members of the Hand, who realise she is not like them. When a spatial rift threatens Veccia, and a rebellion against her rule turns out to be led by Wesley Sparks, Majenta admits she only sent the Doctor away, and calls him back. With the Doctor's help, Majenta cuts the rest of the Hand off from their power source, and destroys them, nearly dying in the attempt. Majenta and Zephyr settle on the planet Redemption (from &quot;The Deep Hereafter&quot;, DWM #412).

===Charley Pollard===
{{Main|Charley Pollard}}

==Q==
{{Empty section|date=July 2010}}

==R==
===Ramsay===
A [[Vortisaur]] that the [[Eighth Doctor]] encountered in the [[Time vortex (Doctor Who)|Time Vortex]] in the [[Big Finish Productions|Big Finish]] audio play ''[[Storm Warning (Doctor Who audio)|Storm Warning]]'', taking place in 1930. The Doctor's companion [[Charley Pollard|Charley]] named it '''Ramsay''', after its resemblance to then-[[Prime Minister]] [[James Ramsay MacDonald]].

However, Ramsay soon began to weaken, being away from the vortex for so long. Despite finding a temporary solution in ''[[Sword of Orion]]'', the Doctor and Charley knew they had to return him to his natural habitat. As they approached the centre of the vortex, however, he attacked Charley. Ramsay sensed the fracturing web of time around her as she had been fated to die in the [[Airship R101]] crash but escaped that fate due to the Doctor. The Doctor managed to expel Ramsay through the open doors of the TARDIS but the ship &amp;mdash; and the Doctor &amp;mdash; were damaged in the process, leading to the events of ''[[Minuet in Hell]]''. Charley's paradoxical existence was eventually resolved in ''[[Neverland (Doctor Who audio)|Neverland]]''.

===Ria===
'''Ria''' was a companion of the unspecified future incarnation of the Doctor seen in the ''[[Doctor Who Magazine]]'' comic strip ''Party Animals'' (DWM #173), where she attended the birthday party of the Doctor's friend Bonjaxx on the space station Maruthea, situated at the centre of the [[Time vortex (Doctor Who)|space-time vortex]]. Along with that future Doctor, she met the [[Seventh Doctor]] and [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]] who were also attending the party and was involved in the subsequent brawl provoked by an inebriated [[Beep the Meep]]. Nothing else is known about her, although her Doctor's appearance was subsequently used as a disguise in a complex ruse by the [[Eighth Doctor]] against the time-travelling mercenaries known as the [[Threshold (Doctor Who)|Threshold]]. 

The appearance of Ria was a sly reference to the series of unofficial audio plays produced as the [[Audio Visuals]] series in the 1980s, which featured [[Nicholas Briggs]] as the Doctor. Ria was played by several different actresses including [[Liz Knight]], [[Patricia Merrick]] and [[Heather Barker]].

==S==
===Lady Serena===
The '''Lady Serena''', or more completely, the '''Lady Serenadellatrovella''', was the companion of the [[Second Doctor]] for the duration of the [[Past Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[World Game (Doctor Who)|World Game]]''. 

Serena was a member of an eminent but uninfluential [[Time Lord]] family who had ambitions to some day become President of the High Council of Time Lords, spending her days working in the Capitol Library, studying records of the presidential election as a means of learning more about Time Lord politics. She is assigned to accompany the Second Doctor (after his conviction by the Time Lords in ''[[The War Games]]'') on a mission for the [[Celestial Intervention Agency]] to improve her own political credentials (see also: [[Season 6B]]).

Unlike the later [[Fourth Doctor]]'s relationship with [[Romana]], Serena is effectively the Doctor's [[parole officer]], the two of them using, for the duration of the mission, a newer Type 97 [[TARDIS]] that only she knows how to operate (Allegedly because the CIA felt that the Doctor's TARDIS was too obsolete for such work). Because of the terms of the Doctor's reprieve from execution, she also has the authority to give him orders. There was thus a certain hostility between the Doctor and Serena from the moment they met; the Doctor objected to having a companion forced on him like this, resenting Serena's claims that she would be his supervisor, while Serena was opposed to The Doctor calling her his assistant, and insisted that The Doctor was merely a convict on parole. 

However, during the course of the mission, they gradually begin to appreciate each other's talents. Even before meeting The Doctor face-to-face, Serena felt that he'd been treated unfairly; upon learning that he'd only been captured because he wished to save the humans involved in the War Games, she commented that his original sentence of execution seemed an unfair reward for his altruism. As they continued to work together, Serena came to understand more about The Doctor's reasons for leaving Gallifrey, and began to see that, for all the charges put against him at his trial, he had only interfered because he believed it to be right, not because he simply felt like it, and had left Gallifrey mainly because there was no place on it for someone with his principles. She even seemed to come to care for The Doctor in her own way, apparently exhibiting jealousy of the fondness that the Countess- a member of the race known as the Players whom the Doctor had encountered in the past- had for the Time Lord. 

Serena's time with The Doctor was cut tragically short after only one adventure with him. Having learned that the Countess intended to assassinate the Duke of Wellington at a ball held on the eve of Waterloo, The Doctor and Serena attended the ball to find out what had happened, and Serena took the shot intended for Wellington herself; the musket ball, fired at her from practically point-blank range, destroyed both her hearts, thus preventing her from [[Regeneration (Doctor Who)|regenerating]]. She was buried in a simple grave, the only thing on her gravestone being SERENA, and, after the battle of Waterloo, it was visited by the Doctor and Wellington, who assured the Doctor that he would always remember the role he and Serena had played in the battle. Once back on Gallifrey, having unmasked a Time Lord who'd been collaborating with the Players, the Doctor refused to go on any more missions for the Agency until certain conditions were met, including an order that Serena's name be placed on the Gallifreyian Honour Roll and that he be allowed to tell her family how she had died.

===Sharon===
{{Main|Sharon (Doctor Who)}}

===Izzy Sinclair===
{{Main|Izzy Sinclair}}

===Evelyn Smythe===
{{Main|Evelyn Smythe}}

===Ssard===
{{Main|Ssard}}

===Bernice Summerfield===
{{Main|Bernice Summerfield}}

==T==
===Bev Tarrant===
'''Bev Tarrant''' is an art thief from the 43rd century, whose first appearance was in the [[Big Finish Productions]] audio drama ''[[The Genocide Machine]]''.  She reappeared in the audio drama ''[[Dust Breeding]]'', at the end of which she travels to the 20th century with the [[Seventh Doctor]] and [[Ace (Doctor Who)|Ace]].  She seems to have made at least one more journey in the [[TARDIS]], as she is next heard of in the 27th century in Big Finish's ''[[Bernice Summerfield]]'' audio drama ''[[The Bellotron Incident]]'', where it is revealed that &quot;a mutual friend&quot; has brought her to Bernice's time. All three of these stories were written by [[Mike Tucker]].

Tarrant has since become a regular character in the ''Bernice Summerfield'' books and audio dramas, where she is played by [[Louise Faulkner]]. Her surname is an in-joke based on the fact that [[Terry Nation]], the creator of the [[Dalek]]s, was overly fond of using the name &quot;Tarrant&quot; in his scripts.

===Stacy Townsend===
{{Main|Stacy Townsend}}

===Fey Truscott-Sade===
{{Main|Fey Truscott-Sade}}

==U==
{{Empty section|date=July 2010}}

==V==
{{Empty section|date=July 2010}}

==W==
===Mrs Wibbsey===
Fenella Wibbsey, played by [[Susan Jameson]], was the [[Fourth Doctor]]'s housekeeper in the ''[[Hornets' Nest (Doctor Who)|Hornets' Nest]]'' CD dramas.  Formerly a possessed pawn of the Hornet Queen, she first encountered the Doctor in [[Cromer]] in 1932, where she was the curator of the Palace of Curios, a small curiosity shop.  Released from the Hornets' influence, she was taken by the Doctor to his house in [[Sussex]], in the early 21st century.  She joined him and [[Mike Yates]] in their descent into the [[papier-mâché]] brain of a [[Taxidermy|stuffed]] [[zebra]] where the Hornets had built their primary nest.  After they defeated the Queen and put paid to the Hornets' nefarious schemes, she settled into the house and took care of it while the Doctor continued his travels.  He returned to check in on her a year later in the sequel, ''[[Demon Quest]]'', whereupon she traded one of the vital components of his [[TARDIS]] to a mysterious figure.  The Doctor insisted that she accompany him on a chase through time to retrieve it. While on the journey, she exhibited odd flashes of insight, such as making a prescient prediction while posing as the goddess &quot;Wibbsentia&quot; in pre-Roman Britain.  This was later shown to be an effect of the Demon and the Hornets, who were trying to lure the Doctor to the dead world Sepulchre, there to turn the Doctor into a dimensional [[atlas]]. Mrs Wibbsey was nearly killed in the attempt to rescue the Doctor after she was again infested with the Hornets.  She returns in ''[[Serpent Crest]]''.

===William===
'''William''' (surname unknown), also known as '''Isaac''', first appeared in the short story ''Euterpe: An Overture Too Early'' by [[Simon Guerrier]] in the [[Big Finish Short Trips]] anthology ''[[Short Trips: The Muses|The Muses]]''.  He later appeared in most of the short stories in ''[[Short Trips: Time Signature]]'', edited by Guerrier.

When William first met the Doctor, he was a young man living with his mother in [[Slough]], in near-contemporary England, following his parents' separation.  Though the Doctor had met him previously in his own timeline, William's association with the Time Lord began when he encountered the [[Sixth Doctor]] in a fishing shop and agreed to join him on a fishing trip.  This expedition turned out to be to a far-future Earth populated by an advanced [[hunter-gatherer]] society.

Together, William and the Doctor visited London in William's near future, and a walking city in the very distant future, although they never achieved William's ambition of meeting [[Viking]]s.  During their travels William developed his previously latent talent for music, and became fascinated with a tune which turned out to act directly upon the [[Time vortex (Doctor Who)|time vortex]].  They parted company in an unnamed Eastern European country resembling [[Albania]] in the 1950s, after William (who now began using the name &quot;Isaac&quot;) fell in love with a local woman and became involved in a counter-revolutionary movement against the local [[Communism|Communist]] regime.

Isaac became a prominent composer in his adopted country, his compositions incorporating the music of the vortex.  He met the Doctor on two subsequent occasions, both of them earlier in the Doctor's timeline than their original meeting.  His meeting with the [[Third Doctor]] in London in the 1970s (their first, from the Doctor's point of view) took place shortly before Isaac's murder at the hands of forces wishing to protect the vortex.

The Doctor seems to have remembered Isaac late in his [[Eighth Doctor|eighth incarnation]].  After scattering his friend's ashes from a Viking [[longship]], he finally dealt with the murderous powers attempting to excise Isaac's compositions from the universe.  This process eventually entailed changing the young William's timeline so that he never joined the sixth Doctor on his fishing trip, but instead developed his musical talent without the influence of the vortex.

The exact effects of this on history are unclear.  While it seems that the Doctor still remembered his travels with William, the young man's life was altered so that he became a prominent composer in his own time.  Whether the events they experienced together still happened, happened differently or did not occur at all is a matter of speculation.

===Jenny Wilson===
Jenny was one of the Doctor's companions in the stage play ''[[Doctor Who and the Daleks in the Seven Keys to Doomsday]]''. She was played by [[Wendy Padbury]], who had previously played [[Zoe Heriot]]. Not to be confused with [[Jenny (Doctor Who)|Jenny]] from the 2008 episode &quot;[[The Doctor's Daughter]].&quot;

In the [[Big Finish Productions|Big Finish]] audio adaptation, she was played by Wendy Padbury's daughter Charlie Hayes.

===Guinevere Winchester===
'''Guinevere Winchester''', known as '''Guin''', appears in the short story &quot;Revenants&quot; by [[Peter Anghelides]]. She was a historian, before becoming a companion of the red-haired future Doctor mentioned in ''[[Battlefield (Doctor Who)|Battlefield]]'', and has an ex-husband named Lance. Given that this Doctor took the identity of [[Merlin]], it is unlikely that her name, and that of her husband, is a coincidence.

===Wolsey===
[[Image:Wolsey (Doctor Who).jpg|right|thumb|120px|Wolsey the Cat, in a humanoid form from ''Oh No It Isn't!'']]
'''Wolsey''' (named for [[Thomas Wolsey|Cardinal Wolsey]]) was a cat given to the [[Seventh Doctor]] by Joan in the novel ''[[Human Nature (Doctor Who novel)|Human Nature]]'' by [[Paul Cornell]]. Wolsey travelled in the TARDIS until the events of ''[[The Dying Days]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]]. The [[Eighth Doctor]] then gave Wolsey to [[Bernice Summerfield]], and the cat remained with her for the remainder of the [[Virgin New Adventures|New Adventures]]. Wolsey also appeared in some of the ''Bernice Summerfield'' audio dramas and books from [[Big Finish Productions]].

In the audio drama ''[[Oh No It Isn't!]]''  by Paul Cornell, Wolsey was portrayed by [[Nicholas Courtney]], the actor better known for his role as [[Brigadier Lethbridge-Stewart]], as the cat acquired the power of speech for part of the story.

The version of the Doctor seen in the [[Past Doctor Adventures]] novel ''[[The Infinity Doctors]]'' by [[Lance Parkin]] had a cat named Wycliff, a reference to the New Adventures' Wolsey by way of reforming theologian [[John Wycliffe]].

==Y==
{{Empty section|date=July 2010}}

==Z==
===Zog===
'''Zog''', an [[Extraterrestrial life in popular culture|alien]] slave, appeared in the stage play ''[[Doctor Who - The Ultimate Adventure]]'', written by [[Terrance Dicks]].

Zog was a slave who served at the Bar Galactica run by Madame Delilah. When the Doctor, [[#Jason|Jason]] and [[#Crystal|Crystal]] arrived, they found Karl and his mercenaries there waiting for them. Crystal formed a friendship with Zog and the three took Zog with them when they fled the bar. Zog continued to travel with the Doctor, Jason and Crystal at the end of the play. In the short story ''Face Value''  by [[Steve Lyons (writer)|Steve Lyons]], published in ''[[BBC Short Trips|Short Trips and Sidesteps]]'', it is revealed that Zog is an Aldeberian tyrant, and unbeknownst to this travelling companions is planning to enslave the universe. Zog also appeared alongside assorted monsters in the 1993 charity special ''[[Dimensions in Time]]''.

==See also==
*[[List of Doctor Who supporting characters#Companions|List of Doctor Who supporting characters: Companions]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{doctor-who}}

[[Category:Doctor Who spin-off companions| ]]
[[Category:Lists of Doctor Who characters|Spin-off companions]]
[[Category:Lists of fictional sidekicks|Doctor Who spin-off]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
