<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26179" ns="0" title="Ron Popeil"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{BLP sources|date=March 2007}}
{{Infobox person
| image =
| image_size =
| name        = Ronald M. Popeil
| caption     =
| birth_date  = {{Birth date and age|1935|05|03}}
| birth_place = [[New York City]]
| known_for   = [[Ronco]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Infomercials]]&lt;br /&gt;&quot;But wait, there's more!&quot;&lt;br /&gt;[[Chop-O-Matic]]
| occupation  = [[Inventor]] and [[infomercial]] [[salesman]]
}}

'''Ronald M. Popeil''' (born May 3, 1935 in [[New York City]]; {{IPAc-en|icon|p|oʊ|ˈ|p|iː|l}})&lt;ref name=nyt&gt;{{cite news | title= Profile: He's Back! The Amazing Human Selling Machine! | work=New York Times | last=McGeehan | first=Patrick | date=December 11, 1994 | url=http://www.nytimes.com/1994/12/11/business/profile-he-s-back-the-amazing-human-selling-machine.html?sec=&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all | accessdate=2008-10-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
is an [[United States|American]] [[inventor]] and [[marketing]] personality, best known for his [[direct response marketing]] company [[Ronco]]. He is well known for his appearances in [[infomercial]]s for the Showtime Rotisserie (&quot;Set it, and forget it!&quot;) and for using the phrase, &quot;But wait, there's more!&quot; on television as early as the mid-1950s.

== Personal life and career ==

Popeil learned his trade from his father, Samuel, who was also an inventor and [[carny]] salesman of kitchen-related [[gadget]]s such as the [[Chop-O-Matic]] and the [[Veg-O-Matic]]. The Chop-O-Matic retailed for [[United States dollar|US$]]3.98 and sold over two million units. The [[invention]] of the Chop-O-Matic caused a problem that marked the entrance of Ron Popeil into television. It turned out that the Chop-O-Matic was so efficient at chopping vegetables, that it was impractical for salesmen to carry the vegetables they needed to chop. The solution was to tape the demonstration. Once the demonstration was taped, it was a short step to [[broadcasting]] the demonstration as a [[Advertising|commercial]].

Popeil received the [[Ig Nobel Prize]] in Consumer Engineering in 1993. The awards committee described him as the &quot;incessant [[inventor]] and perpetual pitchman of [[infomercials|late night television]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://improbable.com/ig/ig-pastwinners.html#ig1993] {{Dead link|date=April 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and awarded the prize in recognition of his &quot;redefining the industrial revolution&quot; with his devices.

In August 2005, he sold his company, Ronco, to [[Fi-Tek VII]], a Denver [[holding company]], for US$55 million. He said he plans to continue serving as the [[spokesman]] and [[inventor]], but wants to spend more time with his family. As of 2006, he lives in [[Beverly Hills, California]], with his wife, [[Robin Popeil]] and two of his five daughters. [[Ashley Tisdale]] is his cousin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hollywood.com/celebrity/1123530/Ashley_Tisdale|title= Ashley Tisdale Biography|accessdate= 2009-06-30|publisher= Hollywood.com}}, expand bio on other side of link.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Popeil often receives credit for having been the first to use this phrase, &quot;But wait, there's more,&quot; its origin is attributed to the State Fair JAM Auctioneers. The JAM Auctioneers also were the first to use the phrase, &quot;How much would you pay?&quot; [[Ed Valenti]], founder and seller of the Ginsu knife added the word, &quot;Now&quot; to that phrase in the 1970s. Like the JAM Auctioneers of past, each time that question was asked, another item would be added to the sale, thus enhancing the audience's and potential buyers' perceived value of the purchase.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

== Inventions ==

Some of his better-known products, and their original sale pitches, include:

* Chop-O-Matic hand food processor.  &quot;Ladies and gentlemen, I'm going to show you the greatest kitchen appliance ever made&amp;nbsp;... All your onions chopped to perfection without shedding a single tear.&quot;
* Dial-O-Matic, successor to the Veg-O-Matic (and very similar to a mandolin slicer).  &quot;Slice a tomato so thin it only has one side.&quot;
* Popeil Pocket Fisherman. &quot;The biggest fishing invention since the hook&amp;nbsp;... and still only $19.95!&quot; (According to the program ''[[Biography (TV series)|Biography]]'', the original product was the invention of Popeil's father and only ''marketed'' by Ronco, but as of 2006, Popeil had introduced a redesigned version of the product.)&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;&gt;Ron Popeil, ''Biography'', aired August 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mr. Microphone: a short-range hand-held radio transmitter that broadcast over FM radios. A convertible rolls up to a curb and an enthusiastic young man shouts out &quot;Hey, good looking, I'll be back to pick you up later!&quot; followed by the pitch &quot;Broadcast your voice on any FM radio!!!&quot;
* Inside-The-Shell Egg Scrambler. &quot;Gets rid of those slimy egg whites in your scrambled eggs.&quot; Popeil has said the inspiration for this product was his lifelong revulsion toward incompletely blended scrambled eggs.&lt;ref name=&quot;biography&quot;/&gt;
* Six Star 20-Piece Cutlery Set
* Showtime Rotisserie, a small [[rotisserie]] oven designed for cooking smaller sized portions of meat such as whole [[chicken]] and [[lamb (food)|lamb]]. &quot;Set it, and forget it!&quot;
* Solid Flavor Injector. This product accompanied the Showtime Rotisserie and was used to inject solid ingredients into meat or other foods. A similar product, called the [[Liquid Flavor Injector]], allowed for the injecting of liquid ingredients into meat, ''e.g.'', lime juice into chicken.
* GLH-9 Hair in a Can Spray (Great Looking Hair Formula #9)
* Drain Buster
* Smokeless Ashtray: &quot;Does cigar and cigarette smoke irritate your eyes?&quot; Commercials showed this device drawing smoke from burning cigarettes back into the ashtray itself.
* Electric Food Dehydrator: &quot;Instead of giving kids candy, give them apple snacks or banana chips. And it's great if you're a hunter, fisherman, backpacker, or camper. Makes beef jerky for around $3 a pound, and you know what went in it, because you made it yourself!&quot;
* Ronco Popeil Automatic Pasta Maker
* The Cap Snaffler: &quot;Snaffles caps off any size jug, bottle, or jar&amp;nbsp;... and it really, really works.&quot;
* The Showtime Six Star Plus 25 Knife Set and the Solid Flavor Injector: &quot;Three easy payments of $13.33!&quot;

== Popular culture ==
Ron Popeil's success in infomercials, memorable marketing personality, and ubiquity on American television have allowed him and his products to appear in a variety of popular media environments including cameo appearances on television shows such as the ''[[X-Files]]'',&lt;ref&gt;In the episode &quot;[[Beyond the Sea (The X-Files)|Beyond the Sea]]&quot;, Scully is shown sleeping while Ron Popeil touts the wonders of his Spray-On Hair (Great Looking Hair Formula #9) for only $39.92. The ad continues for a few seconds, displaying the product's fabulous abilities before shifting to show Scully awakening to the ghost of her recently deceased father.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Futurama]]''&lt;ref&gt;In the episode &quot;[[A Big Piece of Garbage]]&quot;, from the television series  Popeil is said to be the inventor of technology that allows heads to be [[isolated brain|kept alive in jars]] indefinitely (Popeil's own head, voiced by himself, appears in the episode).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the episode &quot;[[The Luck of the Fryrish]]&quot; Fry keeps his lucky seven-leaf-clover in a &quot;Ronco Record Vault&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[King of the Hill]]'',&lt;ref&gt;In the episode &quot;[[Won't You Pimai Neighbor?|Won’t You Pimai Neighbor?]]&quot;,  Dale Gribble states that if Bobby Hill incorrectly chooses from among the items possibly owned by the late Lama Sanglung, Bobby Hill will win a cap snaffler and that the cap snaffler, &quot;Snaffles caps of any size jug, bottle or jar...and it really really works.&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In the episode &quot;[[The Perils of Polling]]&quot;  Dale Gribble asks if Hank got him a cap snaffler while Hank and Dale are being escorted to the polling place by the police.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Simpsons]]'',&lt;ref&gt;In the episode  entitled &quot;[[Radio Bart]]&quot;,  Bart Simpson receives a &quot;Superstar Celebrity Microphone&quot; for his birthday.  The toy and the TV advertisements for it were modeled after Ronco's &quot;Mr. Microphone&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Sex and the City]]''&lt;ref&gt;[[List of Sex and the City episodes#Season 4: 2001–2002|Season 4 Episode 13]] where the character Miranda is seen watching a Ron Popeil infomercial&lt;/ref&gt; and ''[[The Daily Show]]''.&lt;ref&gt;The famous line &quot;Set it and forget it!&quot;, from the Showtime Rotisserie commercial, was used after showing the &quot;catch phrase&quot; discussions of the Senate debating over the War in Iraq.&lt;/ref&gt; Parodies of Popeil's infomercials were done on the comedy show ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' by [[Dan Aykroyd]]&lt;ref&gt;The &quot;Veg-O-Matic&quot; was parodied by  in an episode of  as the &quot;Super Bass-O-Matic '76&quot;. This parody is mentioned in the ''Biography'' episode on Popeil.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Eddie Murphy]]&lt;ref&gt;(September 25, 1982) [[Saturday Night Live commercial]] for the &quot;Popeil Galactic Prophylactic&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; and the &quot;Veg-O-Matic&quot; may have provided comedian [[Leo Gallagher|Gallagher]] inspiration for the &quot;Sledge-O-Matic&quot; routine since the 1980s. Additionally, the [[professional wrestling]] [[tag team]] [[The Midnight Express (professional wrestling)|The Midnight Express]] dubbed their Finishing Move the [[Professional wrestling double-team maneuvers#Bearhug hold, top rope legdrop combination|Veg-O-Matic]]. 
In [[Futurama]] he is said to have invented the technology to keep heads alive in jars.

Ron was voted by Self Magazine readers as one of the 25 people who have changed the way we eat, drink and think about food.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=http://www.ronco.com/index.aspx|accessdate=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Popeil has been referenced in the music of [[Alice Cooper]], [[The Beastie Boys]], [[&quot;Weird Al&quot; Yankovic]] who wrote a parody song entitled &quot;Mr. Popeil&quot; which was a tribute to Ron Popeil's father, [[Samuel Popeil]]. Ron Popeil later used this song in some of his infomercials.

In [[Malcolm Gladwell]]'s book ''[[What the Dog Saw: And Other Adventures]]'', Ron Popeil is interviewed and many of his products, most notably the Veg-O-Matic and Showtime Rotisserie, are discussed. The article was first published in ''The New Yorker'' in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;Malcolm Gladwell, [http://www.gladwell.com/2000/2000_10_30_a_pitchman.htm &quot;The Pitchman&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==

{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Further reading ==

* {{Cite book|author=Timothy Samuelson|title=But Wait! There's More!|publisher=Rizzoli|year=2002|isbn=0-8478-2431-4}}
* {{Cite book|author=Rob Popeil|title=The Salesman of the Century|isbn=978-0385313780|publisher=Delacorte Press|year=1995}}
* {{Cite book|author=Malcolm Gladwell|title=What the Dog Saw: And Other Adventures|isbn=978-0316076326|publisher=Little, Brown and Company|year=2009}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.biography.com/articles/Ron-Popeil-177863 Synopsis of the Biography of Ron Popeil on A &amp; E]
* [http://www.ideafinder.com/history/inventors/popeil.htm A short biography of Ron Popeil]
* [http://www.ronco.com/ Ronco.com]
* [http://www.FreeEnterpriseLand.com/BOOK/RONCO.html But Wait, There's More! from FreeEnterpriseLand.com]
* [http://images.businessweek.com/ss/05/09/ronco/index_01.htm Slide show of Ronco products]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20051213014554/http://uk.biz.yahoo.com/051003/244/ftjc7.html He Invents! Markets! Makes Millions!]
* [http://www.idfuel.com/index.php?p=41&amp;more=1&amp;c=1 All Things Popeil gallery]
* [http://www.npr.org/programs/morning/features/2002/june/ronco/ But Wait! There's More! NPR coverage of a 2002 biography by that title]
* [http://www.biography.com/broadband/results.do?keyword=ron+popeil Watch Classic Ronco Infomercials]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Popeil, Ron
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = May 3, 1935
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[New York City]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Popeil, Ron}}
[[Category:1935 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:American inventors]]
[[Category:American businesspeople in retailing]]
[[Category:Salespeople]]
[[Category:Ig Nobel Prize winners]]
[[Category:People from New York City]]
[[Category:University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign alumni]]
[[Category:Infomercials]]

[[pt:Ron Popeil]]
[[sv:Ron Popeil]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
