<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26219828" ns="0" title="Carlo&#039;s Bake Shop"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:1.20.10Carlo'sBakeShopByLuigiNovi1.jpg|thumb|right|Carlo's Bake Shop]]
'''Carlo's Bake Shop''', commonly known as '''Carlo's Bakery''' and also known as '''Carlo's City Hall Bake Shop''', is a bakery located at 95 Washington Street in [[Hoboken, New Jersey]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carlosbakery.com/ContactUs.php Contact Us], Carlo's Bake Shop, accessed April 26, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; opposite the [[Hoboken City Hall|City Hall]]. It is currently run by Buddy Valastro Jr. The bakery has gained public attention as the setting of the [[TLC (TV channel)|TLC]] television series, ''[[Cake Boss]]''.

==History==
In 1910, Carlo's Bakery was founded by Carlo Guastaferro, and in 1964, it was purchased by Bartolo &quot;Buddy&quot; Valastro Sr.&lt;ref name=&quot;official&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Carlo’s City Hall Bake Shop|url=http://carlosbakery.com/About.php|work=carlosbakery.com|accessdate=9 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bartolo &quot;Buddy&quot; Valastro Jr. currently runs the bakery, with help from his four older sisters, three brother-in-laws, and other assorted family members and friends. One notable employee was Sal Picinich, who began working at the bakery shortly after the Valastro family purchased it, and continued until his death on January 30, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nj.com/hobokennow/index.ssf/2011/02/cake_boss_and_family_mourn_los.html | title='Cake Boss' and family mourn loss of 'Employee-of-the-Century' Salvatore Picinich | publisher=[[The Jersey Journal]]| date=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.northjersey.com/obituaries/115162429_Salvatore_Picinich.html | title=Salvatore Picinich | publisher=The Bergen Record | date=2011-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The bakery rose to fame in April 2009 with the premiere of ''Cake Boss'', a [[reality television]] series on TLC that depicts the staff of the Bake Shop creating elaborate custom-order novelty cakes. As of July 25, 2011, there have been a total of four seasons and 77 episodes of the show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Meet the Bakery Staff|url=http://tlc.discovery.com/tv/cake-boss/bios/bios.html|work=discovery.com|accessdate=9 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of the popularity of ''Cake Boss'', Carlo's Bakery is building a new factory at Lackawanna Center, a mixed industrial/retail complex now under construction in nearby [[Jersey City, New Jersey|Jersey City]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lackawannacenter.com/retail.php |title=Lackawanna Center - Retail |publisher=Lackawanna Center |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carlo's Bakery has leased space at the complex, which will be used for additional space to make specialty cakes, as well as the ability to make baked goods for shipment across the country. Currently, because of the limited space at the Hoboken location, Carlo's Bakery is unable to ship cakes beyond normal driving distance from the bakery; the bakery had conducted a limited trial internet sale of pies in October 2010, to test the viability of selling baked goods on the internet.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Ships, Sonograms and Sister Drama&quot; ''[[Cake Boss]]'', [[TLC (TV channel)|TLC]], February 21, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; When the Jersey City factory opens, there are plans to expand the Hoboken location to accommodate additional customers.&lt;ref name=NYDailyNews&gt;Huff, Richard. [http://www.nydailynews.com/entertainment/tv/2011/05/09/2011-05-09_cake_boss_buddy_valastro_expands_with_cake_boss_cafe_in_times_square_new_show_ne.html?r=entertainment &quot;'Cake Boss' Buddy Valastro expands with Cake Boss Cafe in Times Square, new show 'Next Great Baker'&quot;], ''[[Daily News (New York)|Daily News]]'', May 9, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The new factory will also be the venue of Buddy's reality competition series, ''[[Next Great Baker]]'', beginning with its second season.&lt;ref&gt;''Cake Boss: Dear Buddy''. TLC. October 10, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 12, 2011, Carlo's Bakery opened its first branch location, called Cake Boss Cafe, at the [[Discovery Times Square Exposition]] at 226 West 44th Street in [[New York City]]'s [[Times Square]]. This location offers Carlo's Bakery's smaller baked goods, as well as bakery and ''Cake Boss'' merchandise.&lt;ref name=NYDailyNews/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.carlosbakery.com/ Official website]
*[http://tlc.discovery.com/tv/cake-boss/bios/bios.html Cake Boss website]

{{Coord|40.73711|-74.0309|display=title}}
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Hoboken, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Bakeries of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies based in Hudson County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1910]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Hudson County, New Jersey]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
