<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26215470" ns="0" title="History of Iraq (1968–2003)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox former country 
| native_name =  &lt;span style=&quot;line-height:1.33em;&quot;&gt;{{lang|ar|جمهورية العراق}}&lt;br /&gt;''Jumhūriyat Al-Irāq'' {{ar icon}}
| conventional_long_name = Republic of Iraq
| common_name = Iraq
| continent = Asia
| region = Middle East
| country = Iraq
| era = [[Cold War]]
| life_span = 1968–2003
| event_start = [[17 July Movement|Ba'athist coup]]
| year_start = 1968
| event_end = [[2003 invasion of Iraq|U.S.-led invasion]]
| year_end = 2003
| date_end = 
| p1 = History of Iraq (1958–1968)
| flag_p1 = Flag of Iraq 1959-1963.svg
| p2 = Iran
| flag_p2 = Flag of Iran.svg
| p3 = Republic of Kuwait
| flag_p3 = Flag of Kuwait.svg
| s1 = Coalition Provisional Authority
| flag_s1 = Flag of Iraq, 1991-2004.svg
| flag_s2 = Flag of Iran.svg
| s2 = Iran
| flag_s3 = Flag of Kuwait.svg
| s3 = Kuwait
| flag_s4 = Flag_of_Iraq,_1991-2004.svg
| image_flag = Flag_of_Iraq,_1991-2004.svg
| flag = Flag of Iraq 
| image_coat = Coat of arms (emblem) of Iraq 1991-2004.svg
| symbol_type = Coat of arms
| symbol_type_article = Coat of arms of Iraq
| image_map = Iraq (orthographic projection).svg
| image_map_caption = Location of Iraq.
| national_motto = ''Wahda, Hurriyah, Ishtirakiyah''&lt;br&gt;(&quot;Unity, Freedom, Socialism&quot;, 1968–1991)&lt;br&gt;''[[Takbir|Allāhu Akbar]]''&lt;br&gt;(&quot;God is the Greatest&quot;, 1991–2003)
&lt;small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
| national_anthem = ''[[Ardulfurataini Watan]]'' &lt;br&gt;(''&quot;The Land of The Two Rivers&quot;'', 1981–2003)
| capital = [[Baghdad]]
| largest_city = capital
| common_languages = [[Arabic]]
| government_type = [[Ba'athism|Ba'athist]] [[Single-party system|single-party state]]
&lt;!-- If there are more than 4 leaders, only give first and last&amp;amp;nbsp;— the infobox is not intended to list everything. --&gt;
|leader1                = [[Ahmed Hassan al-Bakr|Hassan al-Bakr]] &lt;small&gt;(first)&lt;small&gt;
|leader2                = [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam&amp;nbsp;Hussein]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;(last)&lt;small&gt;
|year_leader1           = 1968–1979
|year_leader2           = 1979–2003
|title_leader           = [[List of Presidents of Iraq|President]]
|
|deputy1                = [[Abd ar-Razzaq an-Naif|Abd an-Naif]] &lt;small&gt;(first)&lt;small&gt;
|deputy2                = [[Saddam Hussein]] &lt;small&gt;(last)&lt;small&gt;
|year_deputy1          = 1968
|year_deputy2          = 1994–2003
|title_deputy           = [[List of Prime Ministers of Iraq|Prime Minister]]
| legislature= [[National Assembly]]
| stat_area1 = 
| stat_pop1 = 25,175,000
| stat_year1 = 2003
| ref_area1 =&lt;
| currency = [[Iraqi dinar]] (IQD)
&lt;sup&gt;
|cctld = [[.iq]]
|calling_code = 964
}}
The '''History of Iraq (1968–2003)''', referred to as '''Ba'athist Iraq''', covers the period of the [[Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party – Iraq Region|Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party]]'s rule over Iraq. Ba'athist rule in Iraq first occurred briefly in 1963 under [[Ahmed Hassan al-Bakr]] until overthrown that same year. Ba'athism was restored to power five years later after al-Bakr and the Ba'ath Party overthrew [[Abdul Rahman Arif]]. Ba'athism became entrenched in Iraq's government as a [[single-party system]] committed to [[Pan-Arabism|pan-Arab]] unification, [[Iraqi nationalism]], [[state socialism]], [[secularism]] and most importantly, [[ba'athism]]. Al-Bakr resigned as President in 1979 and was replaced by [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam Hussein al-Tikriti]]. The Ba'athist regime was overthrown in 2003 after the invasion of Iraq by a multinational coalition, and formally dissolved by the [[Coalition Provisional Authority]] that year.

== Territory ==
During the Ba'athist era, Iraq officially maintained most of the territory currently part of Iraq. A border dispute existed with [[Saudi Arabia]] until 1981. From 1980 to 1988, during the [[Iran-Iraq War]], Iraq occupied and annexed portions of [[Iran]]. From 1990 to 1991, Iraq occupied and annexed [[Kuwait]]. The annexation of Kuwait was not recognized and was declared an illegal violation of Kuwait's sovereignty by the [[United Nations]]. A UN-authorized international military coalition forced Iraqi military forces to retreat from Kuwait during the [[Gulf War]] and subsequently Kuwait's sovereignty was restored.

== Culture and Society ==
[[File:Saddam1970s.jpg|left|thumb|200px|Saddam Hussein and women students. Ba'athism promoted greater participation of women in Iraqi society.]]
The Ba'athist era was a period of official secularization in Iraq. The government included people from multiple religious affiliations including [[Sunni]] Muslims, [[Shiite]] Muslims, and [[Christianity|Christians]]. However, the period was marked, especially under Saddam Hussein (after 1991), with sectarian religious and ethnic strife between the dominant Sunni Muslim minority [[Arab people|Arabs]] versus the Shiite Muslim majority Arabs and minority [[Kurdish people|Kurds]]. The government promoted women's rights including allowing women to access education and serve in the armed forces. The government sought the restoration of Iraqi cultural heritage, such as rebuilding replicas of sections of the ancient city of [[Babylon]]. Under Saddam Hussein, glorification of Hussein and the Ba'athist government was common in state-sponsored artwork. The Ba'ath Party dominated the political life of the country, though a [[National Progressive Front (Iraq)|National Progressive Front]] was proclaimed in 1974 to allow for the mostly nominal participation of non-Ba'athist figures and parties in Iraqi politics.

During the Gulf War, Saddam Hussein sought to gain support from the Muslim religious community for the government and inscribed the [[Takbir]] to the flag, and coat of arms, and motto of Iraq.

== Military ==
By the end of the Iran–Iraq War, Iraq fielded the world's 4th largest military, with more than 70 [[division (military)|army division]]s, over 800 aircraft in the [[Iraqi Air Force]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/iraq/army.htm Iraqi Army] GlobalSecurity.org&lt;/ref&gt; and a small navy, thanks to funding from the surrounding Persian Gulf states and billions in loans and funding given or secured by the United States to support Iraq's war with Iran.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB82/iraq61.pdf Statement by former NSC official Howard Teicher] to the U.S. District Court, Southern District of Florida. [http://www.webcitation.org/5flvP0UgC Plain text version]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB82/ Shaking Hands with Saddam Hussein:The U.S. Tilts toward Iraq, 1980-1984]&lt;/ref&gt; Losses during the [[Gulf War]] from the United States-led coalition resulted in the reduction of Iraq's ground forces to 23 divisions and the air force to less than 300 aircraft.

== History ==
=== The coup of 1968 ===
{{Ba'athism sidebar}}
In contrast to previous coup d'etats in Iraq's history, the 1968 coup was, according to [[Con Coughlin]], &quot;a relatively civil affair&quot;. The coup started in the early hours of 17 July, when a number of military units and civilian Ba'athists seized several key government and military buildings; these included amongst others the [[Ministry of Defence (Iraq)|Ministry of Defence]], the electricity station, radio stations, all the city's bridges and &quot;a number of military bases&quot;. All telephone lines were cut at 3 [[A.M.]], and by this time several tanks had been given the command to halt in front of the Presidential Palace. [[Abdul Rahman Arif]], the then-[[President of Iraq]], first knew of the coup when jubilant members of the [[Republican Guard (Iraq)|Republican Guard]] started shooting up in the air in &quot;a premature triumph&quot;. [[Ahmed Hassan al-Bakr]], the leader of the operation, told Arif about his situation through military communication hardware at the base of operations. Arif asked for more time; he used this time to contact other military units to seek support. As he soon found out, the odds were against him, and surrendered. Arif telephoned al-Bakr and told him that he was willing to resign, to show his gratitude, al-Bakr guaranteed his safety. al-Bakr's deputies,  [[Hardan al-Tikriti]] and [[Saleh Omar al-Ali]], were ordered to give Arif this message in person.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 53 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arif was quickly sent on the first plane to London, UK along with wife and son. Later that morning, a ba'athist broadcast announced that a new government had been established. The coup was carried out with such ease that not even one single life was lost during the coup.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 54 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The coup succeeded because of contributions made by the military; the [[Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party – Iraq Region|Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party]] was not strong enough to take power by itself. The Ba'ath Party managed to make a deal with with [[Abd ar-Razzaq an-Naif]], the deputy head of military intelligence, and [[Ibrahim Daud]], the head of the Republican Guard. Both Naif and Daud knew the Arif's government chance of long-time survival looked bleak, but also knew that the ba'athist needed them if the coup was to be successful. Naif demanded to be given the post of Prime Minister after the coup as a reward, and a symbol for his strength, for his participation in the coup. Daud was also &quot;rewarded&quot; with a post; he became Minister of Defence. However, not everything was going according to Naif's and Daud's plan, al-Bakr had told the Ba'ath leadership in a secret meeting that the two would be either liquidated &quot;during, or after, the revolution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 55 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; al-Bakr, as the leader of the coup's military operation, retained his position as Regional Secretary of the Ba'ath Party, and was elected to the posts of President and Chairman of the [[Iraqi Revolutionary Command Council|Revolutionary Command Council]]. In the immediate aftermath of the coup, a power struggle developed between al-Bakr and Naif. In all practicality, Naif should have had the upper hand; he was a respected officer and was supported by the common soldier. al-Bakr would, however, prove to be a more cunning, persuading and more organised then Naif, Daud and their supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  pages = 56–57 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of al-Bakr's first decisions in office was to appoint over 100 new officers to the Republican Guard. [[Saddam Hussein]] worked, in the meantime, to establish the party's security and intelligence organisation to combat the enemies. On 29 July, Daud left for a tour to Jordan to inspect the Iraqi troops located their following the [[Six Day War]] with Israel. The following day, on 30 July, Naif was invited to eat lunch at the Presidential Palace with al-Bakr. During their lunch, Hussein bursted into the room with three accomplishes and threatened Naif with death. Naif responded by crying out; &quot;I have four children&quot;. Hussein ordered Naif to leave Iraq immediatley if he wanted to live, a order in which Naif complied.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 57 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; Naif was exiled to [[Morocco]], and later assasinated on the orders of Hussein in 1978 in London, after an earlier failed assasination attempt in 1973. Daud shared a similar fate, and was exiled to [[Saudi Arabia]]. The ba'athist were by no means ensured of victory, if any of Naif's supporters had known of the operation against him, Baghdad could have become the centre, in the words of historian Con Coughlin, &quot;of an ugly bloodbath&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 58 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early years and Hussein's rise to power (1968–1979)===
al-Bakr managed to strengthen his position within the party with the help of Hussein's newly-established party security apparatus and the intelligence services. Most of 1968 was used to repress none-ba'athist thoughts and groups, for instance, a campaign against [[nasserist]] and [[communist]] was initiated under the command of Hussein.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 188 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several spy plots were created by the government, spies that were &quot;caught&quot; were accused of being a part of a [[zionist]] plot agains the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 188–189 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Iraqi Communist Party]] (ICP) was skeptical of the new ba'athist government, as many of it's members remembered the anti-communist campaign launched against them by the ba'athist government of 1963. After taking power, al-Bakr offered the ICP cabinet positions in the new government, the ICP rejected this offer. al-Bakr responded by initiated a systematic campaign against the ICP and communist sympathisers. However, as historian [[Charles R. H. Tripp|Charles Tripp]] notes in his ''A History of Iraq'', the campaign started &quot;a curious game whereby the government alternately persecuted and courted the party until 1972–1973, when the ICP was offered, and accepted, membership in the [[National Progressive Front (Iraq)|National Progressive Front]]. (NPF). The reason for this &quot;curious game&quot; was the Ba'ath Party's belief that the ICP was more dangerous then it really was. When [[Aziz al-Haji]] broke away from the ICP, and established the [[Iraqi Communist Party (Central Command)]] and initated a &quot;popular revolutionary war&quot; against the regime, it was dully crushed. By April 1969 the &quot;popular revolutionary&quot; uprising had been crushed, and al-Haji recanted his believes publicly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 189 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another reason for this anti-communist policy was that many Ba'ath Party openly sympathised with communists or other socialist forces. However, at this stage, neither al-Bakr nor Hussein had enough support within the party to initiate a policy unpopular within it; at the Seventh Regional Congress of the Ba'ath Party both al-Bakr and other leading ba'athist expressed their support for &quot;radical [[socialism]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 189–190 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By the mid-to-late 1970s Hussein's power within the Ba'ath Party and the government, and became the ''[[de facto]]'' leader of the country, even if al-Bakr still was both President, Ba'ath Party leader and Revolutionary Command Council chairman. In 1977, following a wave of shiites protest against the government, al-Bakr relinquished his control over the [[Ministry of Defence (Iraq)|Ministry of Defence]]; [[Adnan Khairallah Tulfah]], Hussein's brother-in-law, was appointed defence minister. The appointment underlined the clannish character of the Ba'ath Party and government. In contrast to Hussein's fortunes, those of al-Bakr's were on the wane. Rumours of al-Bakr bad health started to circulate the country. By the end of 1977, al-Bakr had little ''de facto'' control over the country through his office as president. The reason why Hussein became president in 1977, but 1979, can be explained by Hussein's own insecurity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 209 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Before making himself ''de jure'' head of state, Hussein initiated an anti-communist campaign; the ICP at this had no real power, most of it's leading officials had left the country, or been imprisoned or killed by the regime. However, the campaign was not centered on the ICP, but fellow ba'athists who did not support Hussein. Hussein had initiated a similar campaign in 1978, that time to check were the loyalties of certain left-wingers were; [[ba'athism]] or socialism. Following the campaign, entered the Arab world stage for the first time under the banner of [[nasserism]] and [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]] by criticising the [[Camp David agreement]] between [[Anwar Sadat]] of Egypt and the state of Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 210 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the [[Iranian Revolution|Islamic Revolution]] in [[Iran]] several Iraqi shi'ites revolted against what they saw as a sunni-led government. This revolt led to the collapse of the Ba'ath Party in certain areas of the country. It was in this situation that Hussein took over the office of President, Ba'ath Party leader and Revolutionary Command Council chairman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 212–213 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Izzat Ibrahim al-Duri]] was promoted to the office of vice-chairman, synonymous with the post of vice-president in the west. However, the shia revolt was not the only reason to take over as formal leader, their were rumours within top echelons of power that al-Bakr, with the assistance of those Iraqi ba'athists who opposed Hussein, was planning to designate [[Hafez al-Assad]] as his successor. Immediatley after seizing power, over 60 members of the Ba'ath Party and government leadership had been charged with fomenting an anti-Iraqi ba'athist plot in collaboration with al-Assad and the [[Ba'ath Party (Damascus)|Damascus-based Ba'ath Party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 214 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iraq during the Iran–Iraq War (1980–1988)===
Once he assumed the presidency, a [[cult of personality]] was created and centered around Hussein. He was represented as the [[father of the nation]] and all it's people. National institutions, such as the [[National Assembly of Iraq]], to strengthen this image of him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 217 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ba'ath Party also contributed to the cult of personality; the Ba'ath Party was by 1979 a nationwide organisation,  and became a propaganda center for pro-Hussein literature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 217–218 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; This propaganda campaign did, at least in the beginning, create a common sense of nationhood for many Iraqis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 218–219 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The shi'ites protests were not quelled by these propaganda campaigns, and the establishment of a [[Islamic Republic]] in Iran, influenced many shi'ites to stand up against the sunni dominated government. At first, relations between Iran and Iraq were fairly good, but ideological difference could not remain concealed forever. The new Iranian leadership were muslim fundamentalists, while the Iraqi ba'athists were [[secular]] by nature. Another major obstacle for relations was the Iraqi governments continued repression and discrimination of shi'ites.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 221–222 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of 1980 several border clashes took place between the two countries. The Iraqi regime considered the newly-established Iran to be &quot;weak&quot;; the country was in a state of continued [[civil unrest]], and the Iranian leaders had purged thousands of officers and soldiers because of their political views.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 223 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Iran–Iraq War]] was in theory, going to be a quick Iraqi victory. Hussein's plans was to strengthen Iraq's position in both the [[Persian Gulf]] and at the Arab world stage. A quick victory would restore Iraq's control over the whole of the [[Shatt al-Arab]], an area which Iraq had lost to Iran in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 224 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hussein abrogated the treaty of 1975 in a meeting of the National Assembly on 17 September 1980. This abrogation was followed shortly after by several pre-emptive strikes on Iran and by the invasion of Iran. Hussein believed that the Iranian regime would have &quot;to disengage in order to survive&quot;. Not only was this view faulty, but it overestimated the strength of the [[Military of Iraq|Iraqi military]] and the Iranian regime saw the invasion as a test of the revolution itself and all it's achievements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 224 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; The short way which Hussein planned for some time, proved just after a couple of weeks, proved to be something very different in reality. Hussein, &quot;in a rare moment of frankness, [...] admitted as much&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 224–225 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the war not going as planned, the regime reasserted its view on the situation, and claimed that winning the war was a matter of &quot;national honour&quot;. The majority of the ba'athist leadership, and Hussein himself, still believed that Iran would collapse under the weight of pure Iraqi force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 225 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1982 Iran counter-attacked and was successful in driving the Iraqis back into Iraq. That year alone, an estimated 40,000 Iraqis had been taken prisoners. The defeats of 1982 were a blow to both Hussein and the ba'ath regime. With the economic situation worsening because of falling oil prices, and the rising military budget, the Iraqi standard of living worsened. The [[Iraqi Revolutionary Command Council|Revolutionary Command Council]] and the Ba'ath Military Command, Regional Command and National Command meet in one extraordinary session in 1982, with Hussein absent, to discuss the possibilties of a [[ceasefire]] proposal to the Iranian government. The ceasefire proposal made at the meeting was rejected by the Iranian regime. If the proposal had been accepted, Hussein would have not have survived politically, the proposal was supported by all the members of the Regional Command, National Command and the Revolutionary Command Council. It was at this time that rumours started circulating that Hussein would step down as president to make place for al-Bakr, the former president. As events showed, this did not happen, and al-Bakr died in 1982 under mysterious circumstances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 227 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; Major losses of life in the conflict,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  pages = 209/218–219 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; nearly led to a military mutinity led by [[Maher Abdul Rashid]], the father-in-law of Saddam's second son.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 219 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rashid started to criticise publicy, and claimed that loss of life could have been averted if it wasn't for Hussein's meddling into military affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Con Coughlin|Coughlin, Con]] |  page = 220 | title = Saddam: His Rise and Fall | location = | publisher = [[Harper Perennial]] | year = 2005 | isbn = 978–0060505435}}&lt;/ref&gt; This confrontation with the military led to greater independence of military planning from ba'athist leadership interference. Shortly after the [[Iraqi Air Force]] once again established air superiority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  page = 233 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; These changes in organisation led to Hussein focusing most of his energy on [[Iraqi Kurdistan]], which had revolted. Hussein appointed his cousin [[Ali Hasan al-Majid]] as military chief in Kurdistan. al-Majid initiated the [[al-Anfal campaign]]; chemical weapons were used against civilians.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 234–235 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1988, after a series of Iraqi military victories, a ceasefire was agreed upon between Iraq and Iran; the war is commonly considered a ''[[Status quo ante bellum]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Charles R. H. Tripp |Tripp, Charles]] |  pages = 238–239 | title = A History of Iraq | location = | publisher = [[Cambridge University Press]] | year = 2010 | isbn = 978–052152900X}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Gulf War and the troubled 1990s (1988–1999)===
In August 1990, Hussein declared war on [[Kuwait]], basing the attack on the claim that Kuwait was illegally slant-drilling its oil wells into Iraqi territory. Upon occupying Kuwait, Hussein declared that Kuwait was annexed to Iraq. The United Nations denounced the occupation as illegal and repeatedly ordered Iraq to withdraw its military forces from Kuwait and recognize Kuwait's sovereignty. Sanctions were imposed on Iraq by the UN to pressure Iraq to withdraw. In 1991, The UN Security Council approved international military action to restore Kuwait's sovereignty. The coalition led by the United States attacked and defeated Iraqi forces in Kuwait, inflicting serious casualties on Iraq. Iraq in response launched [[tactical ballistic missile]] attacks against [[Israel]] and [[Saudi Arabia]], both US' Middle Eastern allies. Retreating Iraqi forces sabotaged Kuwaiti oil wells causing massive fires across Kuwait's oil fields. Coalition forces inflicted serious damage on both the state and civilian infrastructure of Iraq.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

Shortly after the end of the Gulf War in 1991, members of Iraq's Shiite community rebelled against the Iraqi government. Iraqi government forces forcefully crushed the revolt.

Upon being militarily defeated in the Gulf War, Hussein submitted to allow UN weapons inspection, disarmament of [[Weapons of mass destruction]], and no-fly-zones over northern and southern areas of Iraq.

In 1998 Iraq accused UN weapons inspections of being infiltrated by spies and forced UN weapon inspectors to leave Iraq. In 2002, the UN Security Council issued [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 1441|Resolution 1441]], ordering Iraq to immediately restore UN weapons inspections and commit to demonstrate its commitment to disarmament of weapons of mass destruction. Resolution 1441 was presented to Iraq as a &quot;a final opportunity to comply with its disarmament obligations&quot; that had been set out in several previous resolutions.[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/US/11/08/resolution.text/] Iraq permitted UN weapon inspectors led by [[Hans Blix]], head of [[United Nations Monitoring, Verification and Inspection Commission]] (UNMOVIC), to investigate sites suspected of potentially having weapons or weapon material.

===Last years and US invasion (2000–2003)===
The United States, United Kingdom and other countries were not satisfied with Iraq's commitment to Resolution 1441 and claimed that Iraq had failed to fulfill its obligations, thus authorizing military action under the authorization of Resolution 1441, and claimed that it would pursue military action regardless of the position of the UN Security Council. However the position by the United States and the United Kingdom, both permanent members in the UN Security Council was challenged by other permanent members including the People's Republic of China, France, and Russia that opposed military intervention in Iraq. Among non-permanent members, Spain supported military intervention, Germany opposed military intervention. The remaining non-permanent members including Angola, Cameroon, Chile, Germany, Guinea, Mexico, Pakistan, and Syria were neutral on the issue, favouring more time for UN weapon inspections to identify whether Iraq was in compliance of its obligations. It was highly suspected that a resolution to authorize military action against Iraq would fail in the Security Council due to vetoes by the People's Republic of China, France, and Russia as permanent members. The vote was never cast however as proponents of military intervention abandoned pressing for the new resolution. Furthermore the United States, United Kingdom and other countries had already amassed military forces around Iraq, prepared for invasion.

The United States, United Kingdom, and a coalition of other countries that referred to themselves as the &quot;[[Coalition of the Willing]]&quot; declared war on Iraq, claiming that Resolution 1441 was not upheld by Iraq and that under Resolution 1441, the coalition was authorized to force Iraq to comply with its obligations. United States President [[George W. Bush]] stated that such compliance could only come by the removal of Hussein and the [[Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party – Iraq Region|Ba'ath Party]] from power and the establishment of a new government that would comply with the responsibilities of the United Nations.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Iraq topics}}
[[Category:Ba'athism]]

[[pt:Iraque Baathista]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
