<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2622736" ns="0" title="Alan Beddoe"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|image=[[File:AlanBeddoe.png|200px]]
|name=Alan Brookman Beddoe 
|caption=Alan Brookman Beddoe
|rank= [[Lieutenant Colonel]]
|branch= 
|commands= 
|battles= 
|family=
|nickname=
|allegiance=[[Canada]]
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1893|06|01}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1975|12|02|1893|06|01}}
|birth_place= [[Ottawa, Ontario]]
|death_place= 
|serviceyears=
|laterwork=artist, war artist, consultant in Heraldry and founder and first President of the [[Royal Heraldry Society of Canada|Heraldry Society of Canada]]
|awards=[[Order of Canada|OC]], [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]], [[The Heraldry Society|HFHS]], [[Royal Heraldry Society of Canada|FHSC]] 
}}

[[Lieutenant-Commander]] '''Alan Brookman Beddoe''', [[Order of Canada|OC]], [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]], [[The Heraldry Society|HFHS]], [[Royal Heraldry Society of Canada|FHSC]] (June 1, 1893 &amp;ndash; December 2, 1975) was a [[Canada|Canadian]] artist, war artist, consultant in heraldry and founder and first president of the [[Royal Heraldry Society of Canada|Heraldry Society of Canada]] in 1965. 

Born in [[Ottawa, Ontario]], in 1893, he studied at [[Ashbury College (Ottawa)|Ashbury College]]. During [[World War I]], he was captured at [[Second Battle of Ypres]] in 1915 and spent two and a half years in the [[prisoner of war]] camps at [[Gießen]] and [[Zerbst]]. He studied art at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts in Paris. After the war, he studied at the [[Art Students League of New York]] under DuMond and Bridgman. In 1925, he opened the first commercial art studio in Ottawa.  He was also an expert in [[heraldry]]. The Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada contains designs and studies for the Book of Remembrance, postage stamps, posters, crests, money, architecture and coats-of-arms. His [[fonds]] include slides, colour transparencies, prints, watercolours and drawings related to Canadian heraldry.&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;&gt;http://collectionscanada.gc.ca/ourl/res.php?url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;url_tim=2010-03-07T21%3A52%3A20Z&amp;url_ctx_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Actx&amp;rft_dat=104827&amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fcollectionscanada.gc.ca%3Apam Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada&lt;/ref&gt;

==Books of Remembrance==
[[Image:Books of Remembrance.jpg|Books of Remembrance|left|thumb]]
Beddoe was instrumental in the creation of the [[Books of Remembrance]], now housed in the Peace Tower on Parliament Hill in Ottawa.  The artist originally chosen for the job, James Purves, died in 1940, at which time Beddoe took on the task.  He supervised a team of artists over the next 30 years to illuminate and hand-letter  the books, listing the names of Canadians who lost their lives serving their country's military during [[World War II]], and the campaign in Korea. He was inducted to the [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]] and received the Allied Arts Medal awarded by the Royal Architectural Institute for his work on the Books of Remembrance. He was instrumental in the creation of the Ontario Book of Remembrance n.d.; Perth Book of Remembrance 1932–1934; South Africa Book of Remembrance 1956–1966; Korea Book of Remembrance 1957–1958 and the Newfoundland Book of Remembrance 1972.

==Ships badges==
The Royal Canadian Navy formed a Ships Badge Committee in 1942, and commissioned Beddoe to design official badges for the navy's ships.  He designed badges for over 180 ships and establishments of the Royal Canadian Navy.&lt;ref&gt;
http://readyayeready.com/badges/heraldry-on-the-high-seas/index.htm  Royal Canadian Navy Badges&lt;/ref&gt; In 1957, the [[Royal Canadian Navy]] appointed him its heraldic advisor. His designs for ship's badges including the designs for {{HMCS|Kapuskasing}}, {{HMCS|Magnificent}}, {{HMCS|Sioux}} and {{HMCS|Rockcliffe}} are in the Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

==Images==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:HMCS Nipigon Crest.png|HMCS ''Nipigon''
Image:HMCS Oriole crest plaque.JPG|HMCS ''Oriole'' 

Image:Quesnel crest.jpg|HMCS ''Quesnel''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Coats of arms==
===Provinces and territories===

He painted watercolours of the coats of arms for Canada, provinces and territories. His fonds include preliminary sketches for the coat of arms of [[Newfoundland and Labrador]], [[Quebec]], [[New Brunswick]], and [[Yukon]]. In 1956, he designed coats of arms for the [[Coat of arms of Yukon|Yukon]] and [[Coat of arms of Northwest Territories|Northwest Territories]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.collectionscanada.gc.ca/genealogy/022-914.006-e.html Coats of Arms&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Coat of arms of Yukon.svg|Coat of arms of Yukon
Image:Coat_of_arms_of_Northwest_Territories.svg|Coat of arms of North West Territories

image:Stemma del New Brunswick.jpg|Coat of Arms New Brunswick
&lt;/gallery&gt;

In 1957, he was asked to revise the [[Coat of arms of Canada|Coat of Arms of Canada]], and his version was in use until further changes were made in 1994. 

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Coat of Arms of Canada (1957).jpg|Coat of arms of Canada 1957
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Municipalities===
He painted watercolours of municipal coats of arms for many Canadian municipalities. His fonds include the designs for the Township of Esquimalt (Vancouver Island), the City of [[Hamilton, Ontario]] and the Township of Gloucester, Ontario.

===Universities===
He designed coats of arms for a number of university coats of arms including [[Memorial University of Newfoundland]], the [[University of Moncton]] and the [[University of Manitoba]]. Photographs of his watercolours entitled &quot;Arms of the [[University of Windsor]]&quot; and &quot;The Bearings Massey College in the [[University of Toronto]]&quot; (coat of arms) are in the Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada.
&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

===Individuals===
He designed the coats of arms for a number of individuals including [[Georges Vanier]], Viscount Monk and Charles [[Vincent Massey]]. His fonds include a colour slide of the Earl of Dufferin's coat of arms and the armorial bearings of Georges Vanier, Governor General of Canada 1959–1967. He also designed the arborial bearings for [[R. B. Bennett|Richard Bedford Bennett&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;The Viscount Bennett&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lib.unb.ca/archives/bennett1/bennett.html Viscount Richard Bedford Bennett&lt;/ref&gt;

===Institutions===
He designed the arms for a number of institutions including the [[Royal Canadian Geographical Society]] and the [[Royal Society of Canada]] and his fonds includes black and white photographs of the letters patent.&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

==Flag of Canada==
During the [[Great Flag Debate]] of 1964, Beddoe was one of the primary artists working on potential designs for the new flag. He designed the [[Pearson Pennant]] design with three red maple leaves on a white background, with blue bars on either side representing &quot;From sea to sea.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://scaa.usask.ca/gallery/flagdisplay/pearson.htm Flag of Canada&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Flag of Canada 1964.svg|Flag of Canada competition 1964
Image:Canada flag Group C Finalist.svg|Canada flag competition 1964
Image:Canada Pearson Pennant 1964.svg|Canada flag competition 1964 
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Art==
Alan Beddoe was an artist. A drawing by Alan Beddoe entitled 'The Condemned Bridge' is in the Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada. He created individual photographic portraits of Major Forbes Thrasher and [[John Wilfred Kennedy]]. He created group portraits of the Ottawa Choral Society, 1898, the [[Canadian Expeditionary Force]], the Provincial Model School, Ottawa, Ontario, 1904–1905, and the 7th Officers' Disciplinary Training Class, Halifax, Nova Scotia, 1942.
&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

==Book plates==
He designed several hundred book plate designs. His book plate designs for Charles Clement Tudway, Henry J. Turner, Edward Milner, and George Stacey Gibson are in the Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;collectionscanada.gc.ca&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
In 1968, he was made an Officer of the [[Order of Canada]]. In 1943, he was made an Officer of the [[Order of the British Empire]] for services as a [[war artist]]. Alan Beddoe died in 1975.

==Publications==
One of his most important contributions to the heraldry of Canada was Lt. Cdr. Alan Beddoe's book, ''Beddoe's Canadian Heraldry'' Rev. by Col. Strome Galloway, Belleville, Ontario: Mika Publishing Company, 1981.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lib.unb.ca/archives/bennett1/bennett.html ''Beddoe's Canadian Heraldry''&lt;/ref&gt;

*&quot;Address on Heraldry&quot; - by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“A Brief on the Subject of Heraldry in Canada” by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“A Commentary on Heraldry in Canada” - by A. Beddoe n.d.
*&quot;Flags used in Canada&quot; - by A.Beddoe n.d.
*“Heraldry in Canada” by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“Heraldry and Its Relation to Genealogy” by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“Some Notes about Heraldry in Canada” - by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“The Coat-of-Arms” - by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“The Heraldry of Canada” - by A. Beddoe n.d.
*“The Legal and Constitutional Position of Heraldry in Canada” by A. Beddoe

==See also==
* [[Canadian official war artists]]
* [[War artist]]
* [[War art]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{cite web|url=http://www.collectionscanada.ca/war-artists/05100202_e.html|title=Alan Brookman Beddoe|work=Library and Archives Canada|accessdate=5 September 2005 }} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
* {{cite web|url=http://data2.archives.ca/pdf/pdf001/p000000941.pdf|title=Alan Beddoe Fonds at Library and Archives Canada|work=Library and Archives Canada|accessdate=7 March 2010}}
{{Heraldry in Canada}}
{{Coat of arms of North America}}
{{Heraldry}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Beddoe, Alan
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =June 1, 1893
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Ottawa, Ontario]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =December 2, 1975
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Beddoe, Alan}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1975 deaths]]
[[Category:War artists]]
[[Category:Heraldic artists]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of Canada]]
[[Category:People from Ottawa]]
[[Category:Artists from Ontario]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Art Students League of New York alumni]]
[[Category:Canadian designers]]
[[Category:Canadian alumni of the École des Beaux-Arts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
