<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2625001" ns="0" title="Bryan Habana"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox rugby biography
|                   name = Bryan Habana
|                  image = [[Image:Habana, Bryan (Canon).jpg|220px]]
|                caption = 
|              birth_name = Bryan Gary Habana
|            birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1983|6|12|df=y}}
|           birth_place = [[Johanesburg, Gauteng]], [[South Africa]]
|            death_date =
|           death_place =
|                 height = {{convert|1.80|m|ftin|abbr=on}} &lt;ref name=&quot;saru&quot;&gt;{{Springboks|id=25452|name=Bryan Habana}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|                 weight = {{convert|94|kg|lb stlb|abbr=on}} &lt;ref name=&quot;saru&quot; /&gt;
|            ru_position = [[Wing (rugby union)|Wing]]
|        ru_nationalteam = {{nrut|South Africa}}
|       ru_nationalyears = 2004–present
|        ru_nationalcaps = 73
|      ru_nationalpoints = (200)
|            ru_ntupdate = 1 January 2011
|                super14 = [[Bulls (rugby)|Bulls]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Stormers]]
|           super14years = 2005–2009 &lt;br /&gt; 2010–
|            super14caps = 61 &lt;br /&gt; 29
|          super14points = (185) &lt;br /&gt; (55)
|          super14update = 1 January 2011
|            ru_province = [[Golden Lions]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Blue Bulls]]&lt;br /&gt;{{nowrap|[[Western Province (rugby team)|Western Province]]}}
|       ru_provinceyears = 2004–2005 &lt;br /&gt; 2005–2009 &lt;br /&gt;2010–
|        ru_provincecaps = 21 &lt;br /&gt; 14 &lt;br /&gt; 3
|      ru_provincepoints = (15) &lt;br /&gt; (15) &lt;br /&gt; (5)
|      ru_provinceupdate = 1 January 2011
|                  other = yes
|                 school = [[King Edward VII School (Johannesburg)|King Edward VIII School]]
|             university = [[Rand Afrikaans University]]
}}
'''Bryan Gary Habana''' (born {{Birth date|1983|6|12|df=y}}&lt;ref name=&quot;bryanhabana.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bryanhabana.com/About.aspx|title= bryanhabana.com: About|accessdate=2006-12-06 |format= |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Benoni, Gauteng|Benoni, Gauteng Province)]] is a [[South Africa]]n [[rugby union]] player who plays as a [[Wing (rugby union)|wing]] for the [[Western Province (rugby team)|Western Province]] in the [[Currie Cup]], the [[Stormers]] in [[Super 14]], and the [[2007 Rugby World Cup]] champions [[South Africa national rugby union team|Springboks]]. Habana was one of the stars of the World Cup, his eight tries equalling the record set by [[Jonah Lomu]] in 1999, and was named the 2007 [[IRB International Player of the Year|IRB Player of the Year]].

Named after former [[Manchester United F.C.|Manchester United]] footballers [[Bryan Robson]] and [[Gary Bailey]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Paul |last=Kimmage |title=Bryan Habana has a spring in his step |url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/rugby/article2652989.ece |publisher=TimesOnline |date=2007-10-14 |accessdate=2007-10-14  | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; he played [[outside centre]] and [[Scrum-half (rugby union)|scrumhalf]] in provincial and age group rugby, but once he was moved to the wing a vast improvement was seen. Prior to his first year of Super Rugby he was selected for the Springboks, scoring a try with his first touch of the ball in test rugby in the end-of-season match against [[England national rugby union team|England]] at [[Twickenham Stadium|Twickenham]] in 2004. Habana won international acclaim for his championship-winning try in the 2007 [[Super 14]] final, as one sportswriter put it: &quot;It was one of the most amazing finales to a major game ever seen … Habana's swerving run was brilliant.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rugbyheaven.smh.com.au/articles/2007/05/20/1179601241429.html Guinness, Rupert: &quot;Bulls say better team lost.&quot;] ''Sydney Morning Herald/Rugby Heaven'' (Monday, May 21, 2007).&lt;/ref&gt; Habana became an international rugby superstar in his own right with his record equaling 8 tries in the 2007 Rugby World Cup (the record set by [[Jonah Lomu]] in 1999).

== Career ==
=== Early career ===
Habana, developed by the [[Golden Lions]] and educated at [[King Edward VII School (Johannesburg)|King Edward VII School]] and [[Rand Afrikaans University]] (now known as the [[University of Johannesburg]]), made his first senior international appearances as a member of the [[South Africa national rugby union team (sevens)|South African Sevens]] side in the 2003–04 [[World Sevens Series]]. He made his Currie Cup debut for the Lions in 2004, doing well enough to be voted the country's most promising player that year. That November, he made his Test debut against England at Twickenham as a 21-year-old. Though the game was lost 32–16, Habana came on as a reserve to score a try on debut against the then world champions. The following week Habana was moved into the starting line-up, where he contributed two tries to the 45–10 win over [[Scotland national rugby union team|Scotland]] at [[Murrayfield Stadium|Murrayfield]]. The next week, he was selected in the same position, on the left wing, in that year's final match against [[Argentina national rugby union team|Argentina]] in [[Buenos Aires]]. Although he did not score any tries in the Argentina game, his current record stood at three tries from three tests.

=== 2005–2007 ===

In 2005, he moved to the Blue Bulls. Following the [[2005 Super 12 season]], Habana was, as expected, included in the 2005 Springboks squad. He played on the left wing in South Africa's opening match of 2005 against [[Uruguay national rugby union team|Uruguay]], whom the Springboks defeated 134–3, with Habana scoring two tries. South Africa then hosted [[France national rugby union team|France]] for a two test series; drawing the first 30-all, and winning the second 27–13, with Habana, scoring two tries in both games. In the lead-up to the [[2005 Tri Nations Series|2005 Tri Nations]], Habana played in two tests against [[Australia national rugby union team|Australia]], the first, a loss at [[Telstra Stadium]], and then a 33–20 win at home at [[Coca-Cola Park (Johannesburg)|Ellis Park]], with Habana scoring in the second Test.

Habana made his [[Tri Nations Series|Tri Nations]] debut on 30 July against the Wallabies at the Bulls' home of [[Loftus Versfeld]] in [[Pretoria]]. South Africa won the match 22–16. The subsequent match against the [[All Blacks]] at [[Newlands Stadium|Newlands]] was also a win for South Africa. In the second match against Australia in [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]], Habana scored two tries in the 22–19 win. The All Blacks won the last match of the series, a thrilling 31–27 win for the New Zealanders at [[Carisbrook]]. Although South Africa did not win the series, Habana had established himself on the international stage, finishing as the tournament's joint highest try-scorer with New Zealands' [[Doug Howlett]], [[Joe Rokocoko]] and Xandre du Plooy. In the Currie Cup, the Blue Bulls made it to the final, which was played at home at Loftus Versfeld, against the [[Free State Cheetahs]]. The Cheetahs, somewhat underdogs, won the final. In November of that year, Habana earned caps for South Africa against Argentina, [[Wales national rugby union team|Wales]] and France, scoring two tries in the Welsh match. Habana was named to the five-man shortlist for 2005 [[International Rugby Board|IRB]] World Player of the Year, and was also selected by [[South African Rugby Union|SA Rugby]] as 2005 South Africa Player of the Year in 2005.

The Springboks endured a poor year in 2006 as they lost four of their six tri nations matches. They also lost to [[France national rugby union team|France]] in the midyear test and lost to [[Ireland national rugby union team|Ireland]] 32–15 – a game in which Habana was averted to centre for the first time in a Springbok shirt. He scored a try. They then lost to [[England national rugby union team|England]] in the first test but gained revenge in the second test.

In April 2007 Habana competed against a cheetah in a 100-meter race to help raise awareness of the imminent danger of the cheetah being classified as an endangered species, according to De Wildt officials. He lost, because cheetahs can run 70&amp;nbsp;mph, instead of 22&amp;nbsp;mph.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2007/WORLD/africa/04/13/cheetah.race/index.html Man Races World's Fastest Cat]. CNN.com, April 16, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 2007 Super 14 ===
Habana's most dramatic act of the 2007 Super 14 season was his last minute try in the final, enabling flyhalf Derick Hougaard to make an easy conversion and giving the Bulls a dramatic 20–19 victory over the Sharks. The try was especially hard to take for Sharks fans as it is debatable if Habana should have even been on the field after dangerously tackling Fullback [[Percy Montgomery]] in the air, in the opening minutes of the game. Habana later admitted in an interview that despite not intending to cause Montgomery harm, he should have been sent off for the challenge.

=== 2007 World Cup ===
Habana was selected on the wing for the Springboks first game of the [[2007 Rugby World Cup]],  where he scored four tries in the 59–7 win over Samoa in Paris. He also scored two tries against Argentina in the semifinal, equalling [[Jonah Lomu]]'s record of 8 tries in one World Cup. He was a part of the world cup winning side contributing to the defeat of England in the 2007 final. Habana was awarded the [[IRB International Player of the Year|IRB Player of the Year Award]] at the 2007 IRB Awards, held in Paris on 21 October.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irb.com/newsmedia/index.html Habana named IRB Player of the Year]. 22 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Habana, while claiming many accolades during this tournament, was also the victim of what was arguably the try of the tournament from USA winger [[Takudzwa Ngwenya]].

=== 2008 Season ===

[[Image:Bryan Habana in Springbok change kit.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Habana in the [[South Africa national rugby union team|Springbok]] change kit]]The 2008 season wasn't Habana's greatest. Although he kept his spot in the Springboks side, he failed to make an impact like he did in the previous year. He only scored two tries in the whole year, one against [[New Zealand national rugby union team|the All Blacks]] in their 19–8 loss and one against [[England national rugby union team|England]] in the 42–6 win. The team struggled to adapt to new coach Peter de Villiers incoherent model for an expansive game, and thus the Springbok backline failed to find attacking impetus throughout that season. The Springboks had a poor year, only winning two of their six games in the [[2008 Tri Nations Series|2008 Tri Nations]] but came back at the end of the year to win all of their [[2008 end-of-year rugby tests|Tour Matches]] against [[Wales national rugby union team|Wales]], [[Scotland national rugby union team|Scotland]] and [[England national rugby union team|England]].

=== 2009 Super 14 ===
Habana had a mixed super 14 season. He was quiet on attack, but was a rock on defence, later he found his attacking form and finished the season second top try scorer, with 8 tries. This lead to the Blue Bulls regaining their title as Champions of the Southern Hemisphere.

=== 2009 British and Irish Lions Tour of South Africa ===
Habana had targeted the [[2009 British and Irish Lions tour to South Africa|Lions tour]] as one the biggest moments of his career, possibly bigger than the World Cup. In a close first test the South Africans defeated the Lions 26–21, but Habana failed to show the form he had displayed in the Super 14. In the second test, the Lions were more fired up and led 19–8 with 20 minutes to go before Habana burst through their defence and scored one of his most memorable tries. The Springboks went onto win after his Bulls team-mate [[Morne Steyn]] kicked a last gasp penalty from 53m. Habana was rested for the final test, a game which South Africa would rather forget as they lost 28–9 but with their series win they gained revenge after losing the [[1997 British and Irish Lions tour to South Africa|1997 Tour]].

=== 2009 Tri Nations ===
After the Lions series came the Tri-Nations. [[New Zealand national rugby union team|New Zealand]] beat [[Australia national rugby union team|Australia]] in the opening game 22–16, so the pressure was on South Africa to claim a victory over the All Blacks in their opener at [[Vodacom Park|Bloemfontein]]. They did this with a 28–19 win. They played [[New Zealand national rugby union team|the All Blacks]] at [[ABSA Stadium|Durban]] the following week. This was Habana's 50th test and South Africa won 31–19 with [[Morne Steyn]] scoring all 31 points. This was the first time they'd beaten the All Blacks in successive games at home in 33 years (South Africa won 3 out of 4 home tests against New Zealand in 1976). The next week they took on [[Australia national rugby union team|Australia]] in [[Newlands Stadium|Cape Town]]. South Africa once again came home with a 29–17 win. This meant they'd won all of their home games in the tournament for the first time since [[2005 Tri Nations Series|2005]] putting them on course for their first championship win since [[2004 Tri Nations Series|2004]]. If South Africa take the 2009 Tri-Nations title it would be Habana's first tournament win meaning he would have won every tournament in professional southern hemisphere rugby. South Africa then won their first away-game and their 4th match out of 4 in the Tri Nations with a 32–25 victory over the [[Australia national rugby union team|Wallabies]] at [[Subiaco Oval]] in [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]]. Habana scored 2 of the 4 tries. The Springboks would take on the [[Australia national rugby union team|Wallabies]] in [[Suncorp Stadium|Brisbane]] a week later, but this time they were outmuscled 21–6. This kept [[New Zealand national rugby union team|New Zealand]] in with a chance of claiming the tournament. Habana played well, making a try-saving tackle on [[Lachie Turner]], but came off at halftime with an injury. He was however declared fit for the visit to New Zealand as the [[South Africa national rugby union team|Springboks]] claimed victory by 32–29, to win their first [[Tri Nations Series|Tri Nations]] title since 2004. It was also Habana's first success in that tournament meaning he has won every southern hemisphere competition available. Some in the media believe that Habana will retire after the [[2011 Rugby World Cup]] to go to the northern hemisphere, as he had hinted{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}. Habana still has the all-time try-scoring record to beat, as he is five tries away from taking it (as of end of 2009 season).

===Barbarians 2009===
On 5 December, Habana played on the left wing for the star-studded [[Barbarians F.C.|Barbarians]] for their Final challenge against the [[All Blacks]]. He scored 3 tries for the Barbarians&lt;ref&gt;[http://planetrugby.com/story/0,25883,3831_5748458,00.html Habana hails his fellow Barbarian]&lt;/ref&gt; as they defeated the All Blacks, who had not lost a match in the Northern hemisphere in 2 years.

=== Provincial Move ===
In 2009 Habana finalized a move which saw him pack his bags in Pretoria and relocating down to the coast to take up a spot next to [[Rassie Erasmus]] at Western Province and the Stormers starting in 2010.

== Personal life ==
{{Refimprove|section|date=October 2011}}
On 20 September 2009, he married his long time girlfriend, Janine Viljoen,&lt;ref name=&quot;Independent Online - 24Jul2010 -  Bok who just wants to give back&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.iol.co.za/sport/bok-who-just-wants-to-give-back-1.674595|title=Bok who just wants to give back|date=July 24 2010|work=[[Independent Online (South Africa)|Independent Online]]|publisher=[[Independent News &amp; Media]]|accessdate=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; at Sorex estate's chapel in Centurion. The wedding made headlines for its strict security policy. Guests were asked to leave their cameras and mobile phones outside, and no vehicles were allowed onto the estate.
adherence

==See Also==
*[[List of international rugby union tries by Bryan Habana]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.thestormers.com/profiles.asp?id=256 Stormers profile]
*[http://www.sarugby.co.za/playerprofile.aspx?id=25452 SA rugby profile]
*[http://rugbydump.blogspot.com/search/label/Bryan%20Habana A whole load of Bryan Habana videos on Rugbydump.com]
*[http://www.itsrugby.co.uk/joueur_1707.html statistics on itsrugby.co.uk]
*[http://www.genslin.us/bokke/PlayerData.aspx?PlayerID=707 Springbok Hall of Fame]
*[http://www.scrum.com/southafrica/rugby/player/14660.html Scrum – International stats]

{{s-start}}
{{s-ach|aw}}
{{s-bef|before={{flagicon|NZL}} [[Richie McCaw]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[IRB International Player of the Year]]|years=2007}}
{{s-aft|after={{flagicon|WAL}}[[Shane Williams]]}}
{{end}}

{{South Africa Squad 2011 Rugby World Cup}}
{{South Africa Squad 2007 World Cup}}
{{Stormers squad}}
{{Western Province squad|Western Province (rugby team)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Habana, Bryan}}
[[Category:1983 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Benoni]]
[[Category:Cape Coloureds]]
[[Category:Rugby union wings]]
[[Category:South African rugby union players]]
[[Category:South Africa international rugby union players]]
[[Category:Bulls rugby union players]]
[[Category:Stormers rugby union players]]
[[Category:Golden Lions rugby union players]]
[[Category:Barbarian F.C. players]]
[[Category:Old Edwardians (Johannesburg)]]
[[Category:IRB Awards winners]]
[[Category:IRB World Player of the Year]]

[[af:Bryan Habana]]
[[de:Bryan Habana]]
[[es:Bryan Habana]]
[[fr:Bryan Habana]]
[[gl:Bryan Habana]]
[[it:Bryan Habana]]
[[ja:ブライアン・ハバナ]]
[[pl:Bryan Habana]]
[[pt:Bryan Habana]]
[[sv:Bryan Habana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
