<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26301553" ns="0" title="António de Oliveira Salazar"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox prime minister
|honorific-prefix=
|name            =António de Oliveira Salazar
|honorific-suffix=
|image           =Antonio Salazar-1.jpg
|imagesize       =220px
|caption         =António de Oliveira Salazar
|order           =
|order
|order1          =[[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal|101st]] [[Prime Minister of Portugal]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(47th of the [[5 October 1910 revolution|Republic]])&lt;br&gt;(7th since the [[28 May 1926 coup d'état|1926 coup d'état]])&lt;br&gt;(1st of the [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]])&lt;/small&gt;
|office1         =
|term_start1     =5 July 1932
|term_end1       =25 September 1968
|president1      =[[António Óscar Carmona]] &lt;small&gt;(5 July 1932&amp;ndash;18 April 1951)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Himself (interim) &lt;small&gt;(18 April 1951&amp;ndash;9 August 1951)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Francisco Craveiro Lopes]] &lt;small&gt;(9 August 1951&amp;ndash;9 August 1958)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Américo Tomás]] &lt;small&gt;(9 August 1958&amp;ndash;25 September 1968)&lt;/small&gt;
|predecessor1    =[[Domingos Oliveira]]
|successor1      =[[Marcelo Caetano]]
|office2         =[[Ministry of Finance and Public Administration|Minister for Finances]]
|term_start2     =3 June 1926
|term_end2       =19 June 1926
|primeminister2  =[[José Mendes Cabeçadas]]
|predecessor2    =[[Armando Manuel Marques Guedes]]
|successor2      =[[Filomeno da Câmara de Melo Cabral]]
|order3          =
|office3         =
|term_start3     =28 April 1928
|term_end3       =28 August 1940
|primeminister3  =[[José Vicente de Freitas]] &lt;small&gt;(28 April 1928&amp;ndash;8 July 1928)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Artur Ivens Ferraz]] &lt;small&gt;(8 July 1928&amp;ndash;21 January 1930)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Domingos Oliveira]] &lt;small&gt;(21 January 1930&amp;ndash;5 July 1932)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;Himself &lt;small&gt;(5 July 1932&amp;ndash;28 August 1940)
|predecessor3    =[[João José Sinel de Cordes]]
|successor3      =[[João Pinto da Costa Leite, 4th Conde de Lumbrales]]
|order4          =
|office4         =Minister for the Colonies&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(interim)&lt;/small&gt;
|term_start4     =21 January 1930
|term_end4       =20 July 1930
|primeminister4  =[[Domingos Oliveira]]
|predecessor4    =[[José Bacelar Bebiano]]
|successor4      =[[Eduardo Augusto Marques]]
|order5          =
|office5         =[[Ministry of National Defence (Portugal)|Minister for Defence]]
|term_start5     =5 July 1932
|term_end5       =2 August 1950
|primeminister5  =Himself
|predecessor5    =Post created
|successor5      =[[Santos Costa]]
|order6          =
|office6         =
|term_start6     =13 April 1961
|term_end6       =4 December 1962
|primeminister6  =Himself
|predecessor6    =[[Júlio Botelho Moniz]]
|successor6      =[[Gomes de Araújo]]
|order7          =
|office7         =Minister for War
|term_start7     =11 May 1936
|term_end7       =6 September 1944
|primeminister7  =Himself
|predecessor7    =[[Abílio Passos e Sousa]]
|successor7      =[[Santos Costa]]
|birth_date      ={{Birth date|mf=yes|1889|4|28}}
|birth_place     =[[Santa Comba Dão|Vimieiro]], [[Santa Comba Dão]], Portugal
|death_date      ={{Death date and age|mf=yes|1970|7|27|1889|4|28}}
|death_place     =[[Lisbon]], Portugal
|party           =[[Academic Centre of Christian Democracy]], later [[National Union (Portugal)|National Union]]
|spouse          =[[Single person|Single]]; [[Bachelor|Never married]]
|religion        =[[Roman Catholicism|Roman Catholic]]
|profession      =[[Professor]] ([[economics]] and [[political economy]])&lt;br /&gt; and [[economist]]
}}
'''António de Oliveira Salazar''', &lt;small&gt;[[Order of Infante D. Henrique|GColIH]]&lt;/small&gt;, &lt;small&gt;[[Order of the Tower and Sword|GCTE]]&lt;ref&gt;367th Grand Cross in 1932&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;, &lt;small&gt;[[Order of St. James of the Sword|GCSE]]&lt;/small&gt; ({{IPA-pt|ɐ̃ˈtɔniu ðɨ oliˈvɐjɾɐ sɐlɐˈzaɾ}}; 28 April 1889 &amp;ndash; 27 July 1970) served as the [[President of the Council of Ministers|Prime Minister]] of [[Portugal]] from 1932 to 1968. He also served as acting [[President of Portugal|President of the Republic]] briefly in 1951. He founded and led the [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]] (New State), the [[authoritarianism|authoritarian]], [[Right-wing politics|right-wing]] government that presided over and controlled Portugal from 1932 to 1974. [[Life Magazine]] called Salazar &quot;the greatest Portuguese since Prince [[Henry the Navigator]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=xz8EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA65&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=2#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false &quot;Portugal: The War Has Made It Europe's Front Door&quot;], [[Life Magazine]], July 29, 1940.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Opposed to [[communism]], [[socialism]], [[anarchism]] and [[liberalism]], Salazar's regime was [[Corporatism|corporatist]], [[conservative]], and [[Nationalism|nationalistic]]. Its policy envisaged the perpetuation of [[Portuguese Empire|Portugal as a pluricontinental empire]] under the doctrine of [[lusotropicalism]], with [[Angola (Portugal)|Angola]] and [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]] as main colonies (as well as Portuguese provinces after 1951), and a [[Civilizing mission|source of civilization and stability to the overseas societies in the African and Asian possessions]].

Possession of [[Goa]], [[Daman and Diu]] was lost following [[Operation Vijay (1961)|Operation Vijay]] in 1961, prompting the international community to turn in opposition to Salazar's colonial affairs as well as initiating a [[Portuguese Colonial War|lengthy struggle for the control of the colonies]], involving hundreds of thousand Portuguese soldiers which ended only in 1975.&lt;ref&gt;JAN PALMOWSKI. &quot;Estado Novo.&quot; A Dictionary of Contemporary World History. 2004. Encyclopedia.com. 2 March 2010 &lt;http://www.encyclopedia.com&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/523512 Portugal in Africa: A Noneconomic Interpretation, by Thomas Henriksen, 1973 African Studies Association]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jstor.org/pss/20081702 Portugal's First Domino: 'Pluricontinentalism' and Colonial War in Guiné-Bissau, 1963-1974, by Norrie Macqueen, 1999 Cambridge University Press.]&lt;/ref&gt; 

At home, Salazar's regime and its secret police [[PIDE]] repressed [[civil liberties]] and [[political freedom]]s in order to remain in control of Portugal, including the murder of [[Humberto Delgado]], declared winner by the opposition in the [[Portuguese presidential election, 1958|1958 presidential election]]. The political suppression, although claiming far fewer deaths than neighboring [[Francoist Spain]], resulted in widespread migration, border control and isolation, although the regime co-founded the [[United Nations]] and [[NATO]] as well as other international organizations. Also in opposition to the Francoist regime, control of economy, citizens as well as colonial policy was only cosmetically relaxed before the [[Carnation Revolution]] in 1974, which led to the restoration of democracy.&lt;ref name=gallagher&gt;{{cite journal|last=Gallagher|first=Tom|title=Controlled represion in Salazar's Portugal|journal=Journal of Contemporary History|year=1979|volume=14|issue=3|pages=385–402|jstor=260013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
Salazar was born in Vimieiro, near [[Santa Comba Dão]] ([[Viseu (district)|Viseu District]]), to a family of modest income. His father, a small landowner, had started as an agricultural labourer and became the [[Management|manager]] of a distinguished family of rural landowners of the region of Santa Comba Dão, the Perestrelos, who possessed lands and other assets scattered between [[Viseu]] and [[Coimbra]]. He had four older sisters, and was the only male child of two fifth cousins, António de Oliveira (17 January 1839 to 28 September 1932) and wife Maria do Resgate Salazar  (23 October 1845 to 17 November 1926), whose paternal grandfather was a landowner and a nobleman. Despite the knowledge of his ancestry, Salazar always preferred to claim humble origins. His older sisters were Maria do Resgate Salazar de Oliveira, an [[elementary school]] [[teacher]]; Elisa Salazar de Oliveira; Maria Leopoldina Salazar de Oliveira; and Laura Salazar de Oliveira, who in 1887 married Abel Pais de Sousa, whose brother Mário Pais de Sousa was Salazar's [[Interior Minister]], sons of a family of Santa Comba Dão.

==Education==
Salazar studied at the [[Viseu]] [[Seminary]] from 1900 to 1908 and considered becoming a [[priest]], but changed his mind. He went to [[Coimbra]] in 1910 in order to study [[law]] at the [[University of Coimbra]], during the first years of [[Portuguese First Republic|the republican government]]. During his student years in Coimbra he developed a particular interest for [[finance]]. Although becoming a law graduate with distinction and specializing in finance and economic policy at the Law School, Salazar was not an economist ([[economics]] in its modern sense was a relatively new [[academic discipline]] in Portugal and was not thought at the time as an independent field in the University of Coimbra (the first pure Portuguese university degree in economics was created in 1949 by the modern-day [[Technical University of Lisbon|ISEG/UTL]]; the University of Coimbra founded its own autonomous School of Economics (FEUC) just in 1972). In 1914, he graduated with a 19 mark out of 20, and in the meanwhile became an [[assistant professor]] of [[economic policy]] at the Law School. In 1917, he became the regent of economic policy and finance by appointment of the professor [[José Alberto dos Reis]]. In the following year Salazar was awarded his [[doctorate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://www.historiadeportugal.info/antonio-de-oliveira-salazar/ António de Oliveira Salazar], HistóriaDePortugalinfo&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rise to power==
As a young man, his involvement in politics stemmed from his [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] views, which were aroused by the new anti-clerical [[Portuguese First Republic]]. Writing in Catholic newspapers and fighting in the streets for the rights and interests of the Church and its followers were his first forays into public life.

During [[Sidónio Pais]]'s brief dictatorship from 1917 to 1918, Salazar was invited to become a minister, but declined. He formally entered politics in the following years, joining the conservative Catholic Centre Party. He was elected to Parliament in 1921 but left it after one session. He continued to teach political economy at the University of Coimbra.

After the [[28th May 1926 coup d'état]], he briefly joined [[José Mendes Cabeçadas]]'s government as the 71st [[Minister of Finance]] on 3 June 1926, but quickly resigned, explaining that since disputes and social disorder existed in the government, he could not do his work properly. Later again, he became the 81st [[Finance Minister]] on 26 April 1928, after the [[Ditadura Nacional]] was consolidated, paving the way for him to be appointed the 101st Prime Minister in 1932. He remained Finance Minister until 1940, when [[World War II]] consumed his time.

His rise to power is due to the image he was able to build as an honest and effective Finance Minister, President [[António Óscar Carmona|Carmona]]'s strong support, and political positioning. The authoritarian government consisted of a right-wing coalition, and Salazar was able to co-opt the moderates of each political current while fighting the extremists, using censorship and repression. The conservative Catholics were his earliest and most loyal supporters. The conservative republicans who could not be co-opted became his most dangerous opponents during the early period. They attempted several coups, but never presented a united front, so these coups were easily repressed.  Never a true monarchist, Salazar nevertheless gained most of the monarchists' support, as the exiled [[Manuel II of Portugal|deposed king]] was given a state funeral at the time of his death. The [[National Syndicalists (Portugal)|National Syndicalists]] were torn between supporting the regime and denouncing it as bourgeois. They were given enough symbolic concessions to win over the moderates, and the rest were repressed by the political police. They were to be silenced shortly after 1933, as Salazar attempted to prevent the rise of [[National Socialism]] in Portugal. Salazar also supported [[Francisco Franco]] and the [[Spain under Franco|Nationalists]] in their fight against the left-wing groups of the Spanish Republic. The Nationalists lacked ports early on, and Salazar's Portugal helped receive armaments shipments from abroad - including ammunition early on when certain Nationalist forces were virtually out. Because of this, &quot;the Nationalists referred to Lisbon as 'the port of Castile.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, Antony. ''The Spanish Civil War.'' p. 97. ISBN 0-911745-11-4&lt;/ref&gt;

The prevailing view, at the time, of political parties as elements of division and parliamentarism as being in crisis led to general support, or at least tolerance, of an authoritarian regime.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

In 1933, Salazar introduced a new constitution which gave him wide powers, establishing an anti-parliamentarian and authoritarian government that would last four decades.

==Estado Novo==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
[[Image:Elementos da escola salazarista.JPG|thumb|left|240px|Required elements of primary schools during the ''Estado Novo'': a portrait of Salazar, a crucifix and a portrait of [[Américo Thomaz]].]]
Salazar developed the &quot;[[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]]&quot; (literally, ''New State''). The basis of his regime was a platform of stability.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}  Salazar's early reforms allowed financial stability and therefore economic growth.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}  This was then known as &quot;A Lição de Salazar&quot; - Salazar's Lesson.

Although Portugal had a high level of illiteracy, Salazar regime didn't consider education a high priority and for many years didn't spend much on it, beyond granting basic education to all citizens. However, in the final years of Salazar's rule and the six years from his incapacity to the fall of the Estado Novo regime in 1974, [[Education in Portugal|educational development was prioritized]] and there was substantial investment in educational infrastructure. At this stage, secondary, vocational/technical and university education reached record high enrollments. Many of the schools created by Salazar were still in operation many decades after the end of the regime in 1974.

Salazar's regime was rigidly authoritarian. He based his political philosophy around a close interpretation of [[Catholic social doctrine]], much like the contemporary regime of [[Engelbert Dollfuß]] in Austria. The economic system, known as [[corporatism]], was based on a similar interpretation of the papal encyclicals [[Rerum Novarum]] (Leo XIII, 1891) and [[Quadragesimo Anno]] (Pius XI, 1931), which was supposed to prevent class struggle and supremacy of economics.  Salazar himself banned Portugal's [[National Syndicalists]], a more true Fascist party.  Salazar's own party, the [[National Union (Portugal)|National Union]], was formed as a subservient umbrella organisation to support the regime itself, and was therefore lacking in any ideology independent of the regime. At the time many European countries feared the destructive potential of [[communism]]. Salazar not only forbade [[Marxism|Marxist]] parties, but also revolutionary fascist-syndicalist parties.

Salazar relied on the [[secret police]], first the [[PVDE]] (Polícia de Vigilância e de Defesa do Estado - &quot;State Defence and Surveillance Police&quot;) set up in 1933 and modeled on the [[Gestapo]] and later the [[PIDE]] (Polícia Internacional e de Defesa do Estado) established in 1945 and lasting till 1969 (until 1974, under [[Marcelo Caetano]], the Estado Novo's police would be called DGS - ''Direcção Geral de Segurança'', &quot;General Security Directorate&quot;). The job of the secret police was not just to protect national security in a typical modern sense but also to suppress the regime's political opponents, especially those related to the international communist movement or the [[Soviet Union|USSR]] which was seen by the regime as a menace to Portugal. The PIDE was efficient, however, it was less overtly brutal than its predecessor and the foreign polices that were the model for its creation.  A number of prisons were set up by Salazar's right-wing authoritarian regime after the outbreak of the [[Spanish Civil War]] (1936), where opponents of ''[[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]]'' were sent. The [[Tarrafal camp|Tarrafal]] in [[Cape Verde]] archipelago was one of them. [[anarchy|Anarchists]], [[communism|communists]], [[African independence movements]] guerrillas and other opponents of Salazar's regime died or were made prisoners for many years in those prisons.

Salazar was able to stay in power because the political structure was heavily rigged in favour of regime candidates.

==Neutrality during World War II==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
During [[World War II]], Salazar steered Portugal down a middle path, but nevertheless provided aid to the Allies: naval bases on Portuguese territory were granted to Britain, in keeping with the traditional [[Anglo-Portuguese Alliance]], and the United States, letting them use [[Terceira Island]] in the [[Azores]] as a military base; although he only agreed to this after the alternative of an American takeover by force of the islands was made clear to him by the British{{Verify source|date=April 2008}}. Portugal, particularly Lisbon, was one of the last European exit points to the U.S., and a huge number of refugees found shelter in Portugal, many of them with the help from the Portuguese consul general in Bordeaux, [[Aristides de Sousa Mendes]], who issued visas against Salazar's orders. Siding with the [[Axis Powers|Axis]] would have meant that Portugal would have been at war with [[United Kingdom|Britain]], which would have threatened Portuguese colonies, while siding with the Allies might prove to be a threat to Portugal itself. Portugal continued to export [[tungsten]] and other goods to both the Axis (partly via Switzerland) and Allied countries.

Large numbers of Jews and political dissidents, including [[Abwehr]] personnel after the 20 July plot of 1944, sought refuge in Portugal, although until late 1942 immigration was very restricted.

==Post-war Portugal==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
[[Image:MatasdorioOnzo.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Portuguese soldiers on patrol in Angola.]]
The colonies were in disarray after the war. In 1945, Portugal had an extensive colonial Empire, including [[Cape Verde]] Islands, [[São Tomé|São Tomé e Principe]], [[Angola (Portugal)|Angola]] (including [[Cabinda (province)|Cabinda]]), [[Portuguese Guinea]], and [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]] in Africa; [[Goa (state)|Goa]], [[Damão]] (including [[Dadra and Nagar Haveli]]), and [[Diu, India|Diu]] in India (the [[Portuguese India]]); [[Macau]] in China; and [[Portuguese Timor]] in [[Southeast Asia]]. Salazar, a fierce integralist, was determined to retain control of Portugal's colonies.

The overseas provinces were a continual source of trouble and wealth for Portugal, especially during the [[Portuguese Colonial War]]. Portugal became increasingly isolated on the world stage as other European nations with African colonies gradually granted them independence.

Salazar wanted Portugal to be relevant internationally, and the country's overseas colonies made this possible, while Salazar himself refused to be overawed by the Americans. Portugal was the only non-democracy among the founding members of [[NATO]] in 1949, which reflected Portugal's role as an ally against [[communism]] during the [[Cold War]]. Portugal was offered help from the [[Marshall Plan]] because of the aid it gave to the Allies during the final stages of World War II; aid it initially refused but eventually accepted.

Throughout the 1950s, Salazar maintained the same [[import substitution]] approach to economic policy that had ensured Portugal's neutral status during World War II. The rise of the &quot;new technocrats&quot; in the early 1960s, however, led to a new period of economic opening up, with Portugal as an attractive country for international investment. Industrial development and economic growth would continue all throughout the 1960s. During Salazar's tenure, Portugal also participated in the founding of [[OECD]] and [[EFTA]].

The Indian possessions were the first to be lost in 1961. After [[India]] gained [[Independence of India|independence]] on August 15, 1947, the [[United Kingdom|British]] and the [[France|French]] vacated their colonial possessions in [[India]]. Indian nationalists in [[Goa]] launched a struggle for Portugal to leave, involving a series of strikes and [[civil disobedience]] movements by Indians against the Portuguese administration, which were ruthlessly suppressed by Portugal. India made numerous offers to negotiate for the return of the colonies, but Salazar repeatedly rejected the offers. With an Indian military operation imminent, Salazar ordered Governor General [[Manuel António Vassalo e Silva]] to fight till the last man, and adopt a [[scorched earth policy]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.goacom.com/culture/history/church.html&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually, India launched [[Operation Vijay (1961)|Operation Vijay]] in Dec 1961 to evict Portugal from [[Goa]], [[Daman and Diu]]. 31 Portuguese soldiers were killed in action and a Portuguese Navy frigate [[NRP Afonso de Albuquerque]] was destroyed, before General Vassalo e Silva surrendered. Salazar forced the General into exile for disobeying his order to fight to the last man and surrendering to the [[Indian Army]].

In the 1960s, armed revolutionary movements and scattered guerrilla activity had reached Mozambique, Angola, and Portuguese Guinea. Except in Portuguese Guinea, the Portuguese army and naval forces were able to effectively suppress most of these insurgencies through a well-planned counter-insurgency campaign using light infantry, militia, and special operations forces. Most of the world ostracized the Portuguese government because of its colonial policy, especially the newly-independent African nations.

At home, Salazar's regime remained unmistakably authoritarian. He was able to hold onto power with reminders of the instability that had characterized Portuguese political life before 1926. However, these tactics were decreasingly successful, as a new generation emerged which had no collective memory of this instability. In the 1960s, Salazar's opposition to decolonization and gradual [[freedom of the press]] created friction with the Franco dictatorship.

==Economic policies==
[[File:Foto 3 Visita Salazar obras Ponte Coimbra015.jpg|thumb|right|Salazar observing [[Edgar Cardoso]]'s Santa Clara Bridge maquette in [[Coimbra]].]]
Economically, the Salazar years were marked by immensely increased growth.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} From 1950 until Salazar's death, Portugal saw its GDP per capita rise at an average rate of 5.66% per year.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} The Salazar era was marked by an economic program based on the policies of [[autarky]] and [[economic interventionism|interventionism]], which were popular in the 1930s as a response to the [[Great Depression]]. During his tenure, Portugal was co-founder of [[OECD]] and [[EFTA]]. Financial stability was Salazar's highest priority.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} In order to balance the Portuguese budget and pay off external debts, he instituted numerous taxes. Having adopted a policy of neutrality during World War II, Portugal could simultaneously loan [[Lajes Field|Lajes Air Base]] in the Azores to the Allies and export military equipment and metals to the [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis powers]]. In 1960, at the initiation of Salazar's more outward-looking economic policy, Portugal's per capita GDP was only 38 percent of the European Community (EC-12) average; by the end of the Salazar period, in 1968, it had risen to 48 percent; and in 1973, under the leadership of [[Marcelo Caetano]], Portugal's per capita GDP had reached 56.4 percent of the EC-12 average.&lt;ref&gt;[Problems of Democratic Transition and Consolidation, Juan José Linz http://books.google.com/books?id=TqRn1lAypsgC&amp;pg=PA128&amp;dq=Financial+crisis+1974+Portugal#PPA129,M1]&lt;/ref&gt; On a long term analysis, after a long period of economic divergence before 1914, and a period of chaos during the [[Portuguese First Republic]], the Portuguese economy recovered slightly until 1950, entering thereafter on a path of strong economic convergence until the [[Carnation Revolution]] in April 1974. Portuguese economic growth in the period 1950–1973 under the Estado Novo regime (and even with the effects of an expensive war effort in African territories against independence guerrilla groups), created an opportunity for real integration with the developed economies of Western Europe. Through emigration, trade, tourism and foreign investment, individuals and firms changed their patterns of production and consumption, bringing about a structural transformation. Simultaneously, the increasing complexity of a growing economy raised new technical and organizational challenges, stimulating the formation of modern professional and management teams.&lt;ref name=&quot;ideas.repec.org&quot;&gt;[http://ideas.repec.org/p/ave/wpaper/382006.html], Joaquim da Costa Leite ([[Aveiro University]]) - Instituições, Gestão e Crescimento Económico: Portugal, 1950–1973&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sedes.pt&quot;&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://www.sedes.pt/conteudo.aspx?args=1,2 Fundação da SEDES - As primeiras motivações], &quot;Nos anos 60 e até 1973 teve lugar, provavelmente, o mais rápido período de crescimento económico da nossa História, traduzido na industrialização, na expansão do turismo, no comércio com a EFTA, no desenvolvimento dos sectores financeiros, investimento estrangeiro e grandes projectos de infra-estruturas. Em consequência, os indicadores de rendimentos e consumo acompanham essa evolução, reforçados ainda pelas remessas de emigrantes.&quot;, [[SEDES]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Colonialist ideology==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2010}}
[[Image:Portuguese colonial war map1.PNG|thumb|right|Portuguese overseas territories in Africa during the [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|Estado Novo]] regime (1933 - 1974): [[Angola (Portugal)|Angola]] and [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]] were by far the two largest of those territories.]]
His reluctance to travel abroad, his increasing determination not to grant independence to the [[colonies]] and to stand against the [[Wind of Change (speech)|&quot;winds of change&quot;]] announced by the British in their move to liberate their major [[colonies]], and his refusal to grasp the impossibility of his regime outliving him, marked the final years of his tenure. &quot;Proudly alone&quot; was the motto of his final decade. For the Portuguese ruling regime, the overseas empire was a matter of national identity.

In order to support [[civilising mission|his colonial policies]], Salazar adopted [[Gilberto Freyre]]'s notion of [[Lusotropicalism]], maintaining that since Portugal had been a multicultural, multiracial and pluricontinental nation since the 15th century, if the country were to be dismembered by losing its overseas territories, that would spell the end for Portuguese independence. In geopolitical terms, no critical mass would then be available to guarantee self-sufficiency to the Portuguese State. Salazar had strongly resisted Freyre's ideas throughout the 1930s, partly because Freyre claimed the Portuguese were more prone than other European nations to miscegenation, and only adopted Lusotropicalism after sponsoring Freyre on a visit to Portugal and its colonies in 1951-2. Freyre's work &quot;Aventura e Rotina&quot; was a result of this trip.

Salazar was a close friend of [[Rhodesia]]n [[Prime Minister of Rhodesia|Prime Minister]] [[Ian Smith]]: after [[Rhodesia]] proclaimed its [[Unilateral Declaration of Independence (Rhodesia)|Unilateral Declaration of Independence]] from Britain, Portugal - though not officially recognizing the new Rhodesian state - supported Rhodesia economically and militarily through the neighbouring Portuguese colony of [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]] until 1975, when [[Mozambican Liberation Front|FRELIMO]] took over Mozambique after negotiations with the new Portuguese regime which had taken over after the Carnation Revolution. Ian Smith later wrote in his [[The Great Betrayal]] that had Salazar lasted longer than he did, the Rhodesian government would have survived to the present day, ruled by a moderate black majority government under the name of 'Zimbabwe-Rhodesia'.

==Salazar and the Catholic Church==
[[File:Cristo Rei (vista lateral).jpg|thumb|right|200px|Lateral view of [[Cristo-Rei]], [[Almada]].]]
Salazar's goal was to establish a Catholic Social Order even in a nominally secular state. In this process, Salazar dissolved [[Freemasonry in Portugal|Freemasonry]] in Portugal in 1935. He permitted the Catholic religion to be taught in all schools, not just parochial schools (however, non-Catholic parents who did not wish their children to receive this instruction could have their children removed from these classes); but throughout Portugal, the Catholic education of the youth was greatly favored. Another policy at this time was Salazar's legislation on marriage which read “The Portuguese state recognizes the civil effects of marriages celebrated according to canonical laws.” He then initiated into this legislation articles which frowned upon divorce. Article 24 reads, “In harmony with the essential properties of Catholic marriages, it is understood that by the very fact of the celebration of a canonical marriage, the spouses renounce the legal right to ask for a divorce.” Divorce was only allowed if it has been purely a civil marriage. The effect of this law was that the number of Catholic marriages went up. So that by 1960, nearly 91 percent of all marriages in the country were canonical marriages.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

On July 4, 1937, Salazar was on his way to Mass at a private chapel in a friend's house in the Barbosa du Bocage Avenue in Lisbon. As he stepped out of the car, a [[Buick]], a bomb exploded only 10 feet away (the bomb had been hidden in an iron case). The bomb-blast left Salazar untouched (his chauffeur was rendered deaf). The bishops argued in a collective letter in 1938, that it was an &quot;act of God&quot; that had preserved Salazar's life in this attempted assassination. Emídio Santana was the [[anarcho-syndicalist]], founder of the Metallurgists National Union (Sindicato Nacional dos Metalúrgicos), behind the assassination attempt. The official car was replaced by an armoured [[Chrysler Imperial]].&lt;ref&gt;{{pt icon}} [[Agência Lusa]], [http://www.destak.pt/artigos.php?art=1842 Único atentado contra o ditador Oliveira Salazar foi há 70 anos], in [[Destak.pt]]&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 13, 1938, when the bishops of Portugal fulfilled their vow and renewed the National Consecration to the [[Immaculate Heart of Mary]], [[Cardinal Cerejeira]] acknowledged publicly that [[Our Lady of Fatima]] had, &quot;Spared Portugal the scourge of Communism&quot;. After Portugal avoided the devastation of both the [[Spanish Civil War]] and  the [[Second World War]], Salazar's propaganda machine and the Catholic Church also connected this to a miraculous dimension which made them profit from the Catholic fervor of the masses. The [[Cristo-Rei]], a Catholic monument in [[Almada]], was inaugurated on 17 May 1959 by Salazar. Its construction was approved by a Portuguese Episcopate conference, held in [[Fátima]] on 20 April 1940, as a plea to God to prevent Portugal from entering World War II. However, the idea had originated on a visit by the Cardinal Patriarch of Lisbon to Rio de Janeiro in 1934, soon after the inauguration of the statue of [[Christ the Redeemer (statue)|Christ the Redeemer]] in 1931.

The relationship of Salazar with some sectors of the Catholic Church, more in accordance with the social doctrine of the Holy See, worsened after World War II. Some prominent oppositionist priests, like Abel Varzim and Joaquim Alves Correia, openly supported the [[MUD]] in 1945 and the granting of more social rights to the workers. Abel Varzim, who had been a supporter of the regime, had his newspaper closed, while Joaquim Alves Correia was forced into exile in the United States, where he died in 1951. The Democratic Opposition main candidate in the 1958 Presidential Elections, General [[Humberto Delgado]] was a Roman Catholic and a dissident of the regime, who quoted [[Pope Pius XII]] to show how the social policies of the regime were against the social teachings of the Church. The same year, Salazar suffered a severe blow from the bishop of Porto, Dom [[António Ferreira Gomes]], who wrote a critical letter to the Council President in July 1958 being forced to exile for 10 years. After the [[Second Vatican Council]], a large number of Catholics became active in the Democratic Opposition.

==Death==
In 1968, Salazar suffered a brain haemorrhage. Most sources maintain that it occurred when he fell from a chair in his summer house. In February 2009 though, there were anonymous witnesses who confessed, after some research about Salazar's best-kept secrets, that he had fallen in a bathtub instead of from a chair.&lt;ref&gt;[http://dn.sapo.pt/inicio/interior.aspx?content_id=1149435 &quot;Salazar fell in a bathtub, not from a chair&quot; (portuguese language)]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the injury, Salazar lived for a further two years; as he was expected to die shortly after his fall, President [[Américo Thomaz]] replaced him with [[Marcello Caetano]]. When Salazar unexpectedly recovered lucidity, his intimates did not tell him he had been deposed, instead allowing him to &quot;rule&quot; in privacy until his death in July 1970.&lt;ref&gt;Meneses, Filipe de. ''Salazar: A Political Biography.'' pp. 608-609. ISBN 978-1929631902&lt;/ref&gt; Tens of thousands paid their last respects at the funeral and the [[Requiem Mass]] that took place at the [[Jerónimos Monastery]] and at the passage of the special train that carried the coffin to his hometown of Vimieiro near Santa Comba Dão, where he was buried according to his wishes in his native soil, in a plain ordinary grave. As a symbolic display of his views of Portugal and the colonial empire, there is well-known footage of several members of the &quot;[[Mocidade Portuguesa]],&quot; of both African and European ethnicity, paying homage at his funeral.

==Post-Salazar Portugal and interpretation==
After Salazar's death, his [[Estado Novo (Portugal)|''Estado Novo'']] regime persisted under the direction of Thomaz as well as his successor and longtime aide, [[Marcelo Caetano]], who co-wrote the [[Portuguese Constitution of 1933|Constitution of 1933]]. Despite tentative overtures towards an opening of the regime, Caetano balked at ending the colonial war, notwithstanding the condemnation of most of the international community. Eventually the ''Estado Novo'' fell on April 25, 1974, after the [[Carnation Revolution]]. The retreat from the colonies and the acceptance of its independence terms which would create newly-independent communist states in 1975 (most notably the [[People's Republic of Angola]] and the [[People's Republic of Mozambique]]) prompted a mass exodus of Portuguese citizens from Portugal's African territories (mostly from Portuguese [[Angola (Portugal)|Angola]] and [[Mozambique (Portugal)|Mozambique]]),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/world/mideast-africa/displayStory.cfm?story_id=12079340 Flight from Angola], [[The Economist]] (August 16, 1975).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,913229-1,00.html Dismantling the Portuguese Empire], [[Time Magazine]] (Monday, July 07, 1975).&lt;/ref&gt; creating over a million destitute Portuguese [[refugee]]s&amp;nbsp;— the ''[[White African#Portuguese in Africa|retornados]]''.

The ''Estado Novo'' regime has been described by the American socialist author David L. Raby as a far-right leaning regime of [[Para-fascism|para-fascist]] inspiration, although general labeling of Portugal as fascist declined after the defeat of [[Nazi Germany]] and [[Fascist Italy]] in [[World War II]], in which Portugal remained strictly neutral.&lt;ref&gt;David L. Raby, [http://books.google.pt/books?id=FA4NAQAAIAAJ&amp;dq Fascism and Resistance in Portugal: Communists, Liberals and Military Dissidents in the Opposition to Salazar, 1941-1974],&lt;/ref&gt; According to some Portuguese [[far-right politics|far-right leaning]] or conservative scholars like [[Jaime Nogueira Pinto]]&lt;ref&gt;{{pt icon}} [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EYzsZUEo8g0 Grandes Portugueses - Entender Salazar e o Estado Novo.], [[Jaime Nogueira Pinto]] in the [[The Greatest Portuguese]]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Rui Ramos (historian)|Rui Ramos]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ionline.pt/conteudo/31720-historia-portugal-luta-faccoes-os-salazaristas História de Portugal. A luta de facções entre os salazaristas] &quot;Até os americanos já o tinham abandonado, temendo &quot;recriar o caos que existia em Portugal antes de Salazar tomar o poder&quot;.&quot;, from História de Portugal (2009), Rui Ramos, Bernardo de Vasconcelos e Sousa, and Nuno Gonçalo Monteiro, Esfera dos Livros, cited in ionline.pt&lt;/ref&gt; his early reforms and policies allowed political and financial stability and therefore [[social order]] and [[economic growth]], after the politically unstable and financially chaotic years of the [[Portuguese First Republic]] (1910–1926). Other historians like [[far-left politics|far-left politician]] [[Fernando Rosas]], point out that Salazar's policies from the 1930s to the 1950s, led to economic and social stagnation and rampant emigration, turning Portugal into one of the poorest countries in Europe, that was also thwarted by scoring lower on literacy than its peers of the [[Northern Hemisphere]].{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} The [[Estado Novo]] and António de Oliveira Salazar are often misinterpreted mainly because of rather tendencious analysis. Today, even though over 30 years have passed since the [[Carnation Revolution]] the leftist analysis of the [[Estado Novo]] still dominates public opinion and even though the [[dictator]] António de Oliveira Salazar was democratically elected [[The Greatest Portuguese]] it is still very controversial not to &quot;demonize&quot; the Portuguese statesman. Most of modern Salazar supporters hide their views in fear of being labelled as [[Neo-Fascist]] or [[Nationalist]]. 

==See also==
{{Sister project links|António de Oliveira Salazar}}
*[[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal]]
*[[List of Presidents of Portugal]]
*[[Politics of Portugal]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
* [[Filipe Ribeiro de Meneses]], ''Salazar: A Political Biography'' (Enigma Books: New York, 2009). ISBN 978-1-929631-90-2
* [[Antonio Macieira Coelho]], ''Salazar, o fim e a morte, Historia de uma mistificação'', Editora D. Quixote, Lisboa. ISBN 972-20-1272-X
* [[Michael Derrick]], ''The Portugal of Salazar'', 2nd edition, IHS Press, Norfolk, Virginia, 2009. ISBN 978-1932528589
* [[Hugh Kay]], ''Salazar and Modern Portugal''
* [[Franco Nogueira]], ''Salazar'', 6 vols., Coimbra, 1977-85.
* [[George Wright]], ''The Destruction of a Nation'', ISBN 074531029X

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Domingos Oliveira]]| title = [[List of Prime Ministers of Portugal|Prime Minister of Portugal]]|years=1932&amp;ndash;1968| after = [[Marcelo Caetano]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[António Óscar Carmona]]| title = [[List of Presidents of Portugal|President of Portugal]]&lt;br&gt;(interim)|years=1951| after = [[Francisco Higino Craveiro Lopes|Craveiro Lopes]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{PortuguesePresidents}}
{{Prime Ministers of Portugal}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME=Oliveira Salazar, António de
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Salazar, António
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=[[Prime Minister of Portugal]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=April 28, 1889
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Vimieiro]], [[Santa Comba Dão]], Portugal
|DATE OF DEATH=July 27, 1970
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Lisbon]], Portugal
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Salazar, Antonio De Oliveira}}
[[Category:1889 births]]
[[Category:1970 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Viseu District]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Deaths from stroke]]
[[Category:Disease-related deaths in Portugal]]
[[Category:Portuguese economists]]
[[Category:Portuguese politicians]]
[[Category:Portuguese Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Presidents of Portugal]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Portugal]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany]]
[[Category:University of Coimbra alumni]]
[[Category:World War II political leaders]]
[[Category:National Union (Portugal) politicians]]

[[ar:أنطونيو سالازار]]
[[an:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[az:Antoniu di Oliveyra Salazar]]
[[bg:Антониу ди Оливейра Салазар]]
[[ca:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[cs:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[da:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[de:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[et:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[es:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[eo:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[eu:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[fa:آنتونیو ده الیویرا سالازار]]
[[fr:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[gl:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[ko:안토니우 드 올리베이라 살라자르]]
[[hr:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[io:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[id:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[is:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[it:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[he:אנטוניו דה אוליביירה סלזר]]
[[ka:ანტონიუ დი სალაზარი]]
[[la:Antonius de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[lb:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[hu:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[nl:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[ja:アントニオ・サラザール]]
[[no:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[nn:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[oc:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[pl:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[pt:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[ro:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[ru:Салазар, Антониу ди]]
[[sco:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[simple:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[sk:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[sl:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[fi:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[sv:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[tr:António de Oliveira Salazar]]
[[uk:Антоніу де Олівейра Салазар]]
[[wa:Salazar]]
[[zh:萨拉查]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
