<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2637370" ns="0" title="PC Conectado"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''PC Conectado''', or '''Computador para Todos''', is a tax-free computer initiative launched by the [[Brazil]]ian government, since 2003.

PCs available through the project are relatively low-end, but therefore are cheap enough to satisfy most of the population, at [[Brazilian real|R$]]1200 (or about [[United States dollar|US$]]500). Most PCs available have:

*128 or 256 [[Megabyte|MB]] [[Random access memory|RAM]]
*A low end [[central processing unit|processor]], usually a [[Celeron]] processor.
*40 [[Gigabyte|GB]] or 80 [[Gigabyte|GB]] [[hard disk]]
* [[Linux]], usually Insigne Linux, a [[Fedora (operating system)|Fedora]] based distribution fully compatible with [[software repositories]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.computadorparatodos.gov.br/noticias/20060216_01 Insigne fornece Linux para 55 mil PCs populares]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In the initial phases of the project, [[Microsoft]] offered the Brazilian government the use of its [[Windows XP#Windows XP Starter Edition|Windows XP Starter Edition]], a cut down version of their popular OS for developing countries. The offer was rejected due to the severe limitations of the Starter Edition. Since then, the project has used only free and open source software for general work, like [[Inkscape]], [[OpenOffice.org|OpenOffice]], [[GIMP]] and [[Amarok (software)|Amarok]]. 

The Brazilian government's decision to reject Microsoft's proprietary and limited (i.e. cut-down) version of Windows XP in favor of a full featured and free [[Linux]] operating system was widely reported in the US media and IT periodicals.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/29/technology/29computer.html&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/computing/hardware/in-brazil-its-pcs-to-the-people&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.informationweek.com/blog/main/archives/2005/03/open_source_vs.html;jsessionid=SW3UHKXWPA10BQE1GHPSKH4ATMY32JVN&lt;/ref&gt; This decision could be interpreted as a severe, humiliating and embarrassing rejection for Microsoft. The president of the Brazilian agency in charge of the governments technology initiatives, Sérgio Amadeu, unequivocally stated that he was against spending Brazilian tax-payers money on furthering Microsoft's monopoly:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;We're not going to spend taxpayers' money on a program so that Microsoft can further consolidate its monopoly. It's the government's responsibility to ensure that there is competition, and that means giving alternative software platforms a chance to prosper.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/29/technology/29computer.html&lt;/ref&gt;

An option providing cheap [[dial-up access]] to the [[Internet]] may be available soon, costing R$7 (about US$2.50). Also, a project to offer a popular broadband internet access (512 kbps), charging a monthly fee between 15 and 35 reais (between 8.5 and 20 U.S. dollars).&lt;ref&gt;http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/90001/90777/90852/6975581.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Where to buy==

PC Conectado can be acquired in many major Brazilian department stores. Many Brazilian stores have an independent Linux vendor on site from whom a user can choose the hardware configuration and distro.

==See also==
* [[FIC Conectado]]
* [[$100 laptop]]

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.softwarelivre.gov.br/noticias/pcconectado/view Official website] {{pt icon}}

[[Category:Science and technology in Brazil]]

{{Brazil-stub}}

[[de:PC Conectado]]
[[pt:PC Conectado]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
