<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26444385" ns="0" title="Revolutionary Socialist Party (Australia)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox Australian Political Party
|party_name       = Revolutionary Socialist Party
|party_logo       =
|party_wikicolourid  = Revolutionary Socialist Party|
|leader           = John Percy
|foundation       = 2008
|ideology         = [[Revolutionary socialism]] &lt;br&gt;[[Marxism]] &lt;br&gt;[[Leninism]] &lt;br&gt;[[Marxism-Leninism]] &lt;br&gt;[[Trotskyism]]
|headquarters     = [[Sydney]], [[Australia]]
|holds_government = Nowhere
|website          = [http://rsp.org.au/ rsp.org.au]|}}

The '''Revolutionary Socialist Party''' (RSP) is a small [[socialist]] organisation in [[Australia]], formed in 2008 by a split from the former [[Democratic Socialist Perspective]] (DSP). Members of the split were expelled from the DSP over debates about the organisation's participation in the [[Socialist Alliance (Australia)|Socialist Alliance]].&lt;ref name=split&gt;[http://www.dsp.org.au/node/199 DSP National Executive statement on LPF split ], ''Democratic Socialist Perspective'', 13 May 2008. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; While the RSP sees the project of the Alliance as [[Liquidationism|liquidationist]], it still maintains the basic politics of the DSP.&lt;ref name=launched&gt;[http://www.rsp.org.au/node/7 Revolutionary Socialist Party (RSP) launched], ''Revolutionary Socialist Party'', 28 May 2008. Accessed: 6 March 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Van Thanh Rudd]], the nephew of former [[Labor Party of Australia|Labor Party]] (ALP) [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] [[Kevin Rudd]] is a member and unsuccessfully ran against ALP Prime Minister [[Julia Gillard]] in the [[Victoria, Australia|Victorian]] seat of [[Division of Lalor|Lalor]] in the [[Australian federal election, 2010|2010 federal election]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/austory/specials/ourselection/default.htm Our New Selection], ''Australian Story'', 16 August 2010. Accessed: 22 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
On 13 May 2008, The DSP National Executive expelled 39 members of the '''Leninist Party Faction''' (LPF) of whom went on to form the RSP.&lt;ref name=launched/&gt; They claim to have established branches in [[Brisbane]], [[Canberra]], [[Melbourne]], [[Perth, Western Australia|Perth]] and [[Sydney]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://rsp.org.au/?q=node/17 Contact us], ''Revolutionary Socialist Party''. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Unfortunately because of slow growth six members left the party in September 2011 and called for broad left support instead behind  ''Green Left Weekly'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greenleft.org.au/node/48776], ''Let’s unite behind Green Left Weekly''.&lt;/ref&gt;-- a journal which supports the Socialist Alliance.

==Politics==
The RSP claim to stand against [[greed]], [[exploitation]], [[war]], [[oppression]] and [[environmental destruction]] and for a [[revolution|revolutionary]] overthrow of [[capitalism]] based on the ideas of [[Karl Marx]], [[Frederick Engels]] and other socialists. They support what they call &quot;the [[Bolivia|Bolivarian]] socialist [[Bolivarian revolution|revolution]] now unfolding in [[Venezuela]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://rsp.org.au/?q=node/18 About the RSP], ''Revolutionary Socialist Party''. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Like the former DSP who broke with [[Leon Trotsky]]'s theory of [[permanent revolution]] in the 1980s, the RSP are advocates of the [[Two Stage Theory|two stage theory]], as Doug Lorimer of the RSP outlines in ''In Defence of Lenin's Marxist Policy of a Two-Stage, Uninterrupted Revolution:''

:''&quot;A [[Political power|state power]] which organises the [[proletariat|working class]], in alliance with the [[peasant|peasantry]] as a whole [...] to carry to completion a democratic revolution would also be a form of [[Dictatorship of the proletariat|proletarian dictatorship]], of working-class state power. But it would not yet be a socialist dictatorship of the proletariat [...] It would be a special form of proletarian state power in a [[bourgeoisie|bourgeois]]-democratic revolution, a revolutionary-democratic dictatorship of the proletariat and the peasantry.&quot;'' &lt;ref&gt;[http://rsp.org.au/content/november-1999-defence-lenins-marxist-policy-two-stage-uninterrupted-revolution November 1999: In Defence of Lenin's Marxist Policy of a Two-Stage, Uninterrupted Revolution], ''Revolutionary Socialist Party'', (First published by the DSP) November 1999. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other Australian socialist organisations have labelled this theory &quot;[[Stalinist]]&quot; and in contrast with classical [[Marxism]]. The [[Socialist Party (Australia)|Socialist Party]], affiliated with the [[Committee for a Workers International]] claims the theory is &quot;a policy of deception, consistent misquotation, [and] half quotations of Trotsky’s ideas and innuendo&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistpartyaustralia.org/archives/2407 The Permanent Revolution today], ''Socialist Party'', 23 February 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Socialist Alternative (Australia)|Socialist Alternative]], who follows the core politics of (but not formally affiliated with) the [[International Socialist Tendency]] claims of the same theory &quot;[a] capitalist hell-hole by any other name is just as shit, surely!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sa.org.au/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=2060&amp;Itemid=1 Is Vietnam socialist?] ''Socialist Alternative'', 26 July 2009. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campaigns==
On [[Australia Day]] 2010, RSP members, Van Thanh Rudd and Sam King, dressed in [[Ku Klux Klan]] outfits holding signs &quot;Racism - Made in Australia&quot;, outside the [[Rod Laver Arena]] during the [[Australian Open]] to protest what they said was the refusal of the [[Australian Government]] &quot;to acknowledge that [[Violence against Indians in Australia controversy|attacks on Indians]] were [[racist]] and that locking up [[asylum seekers]] was wrong.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/national/pms-nephew-marks-invasion-day-with-antiracism-protest-20100126-mvhj.html PM's nephew marks 'Invasion Day' with anti-racism protest], ''The Age'', 26 January 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Rudd and King were arrested within 10 minutes and charged with inciting a riot.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2010/01/26/2801852.htm?site=local Rudd's nephew fined for 'inciting riot'], ''ABC News'', 26 January 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Rudd also told the Indian weekly newsmagazine ''[[Outlook (magazine)|Outlook]]'' that the &quot;dominant culture in Australia is a racist culture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.outlookindia.com/article.aspx?264017 The Dominant Culture In Australia Is A Racist Culture], ''Outlook India'', 8 February 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==Elections==
Although the split within the former DSP and the current RSP was due to the electoral project of the Alliance,&lt;ref name=launched/&gt; the RSP still ran candidates in the 2010 federal election.&lt;ref&gt;[http://directaction.org.au/issue25 Putting revolutionary socialism on the map], ''Direct Action'', August 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; However, as both candidates, Van Thanh Rudd contesting the Victorian seat of Lalor against Julia Gillard&lt;ref name=VIC&gt;[http://vtr.aec.gov.au/HouseDivisionFirstPrefs-15508-222.htm House of Representatives: VIC Division - Lalor], ''Australian Electoral Commission'', 7 September 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and Hamish Chitts contesting the [[Queensland]] seat of [[Division of Griffith|Griffith]] against Kevin Rudd,&lt;ref name=QLD&gt;[http://vtr.aec.gov.au/HouseDivisionFirstPrefs-15508-163.htm House of Representatives: QLD Division - Griffith], ''Australian Electoral Commission'', 7 September 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; were not registered with the [[Australian Electoral Commission]] as RSP candidates, this signifies the RSP's failure, unlike the Alliance,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aec.gov.au/Parties_and_Representatives/Party_Registration/Registered_parties/sa.htm Socialist Alliance], ''Australian Electoral Commission'', 27 July 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; to generate the 500-member minimum required to register as an official political party.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aec.gov.au/Parties_and_Representatives/party_registration/files/party-registration-guide-april2010-v1.pdf Party Registration Guide], ''Australian Electoral Commission'', April 2010. Accessed: 8 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Both candidates polled very poorly. Rudd garnered a total of 516 votes, scoring 0.50% of the overall vote, with a +0.50% swing, placing him as the second least preferred candidate, ahead of [[Regional Australia|regional]] tourism developer, Marc Aussie-Stone, compared to Gillard as first preference, who garnered 66,060 votes, scoring 64.26% of the overall vote, with a +4.37% swing.&lt;ref name=VIC/&gt; Chitts garnered a total of 600 votes, scoring 0.75% of the overall vote, with a +0.75% swing, also placing him as the second least preferred candidate, ahead of [[far-right]] [[Citizens Electoral Council]] candidate, Jan Pukallus, compared to Kevin Rudd as first preference, who garnered 35,286 votes, scoring 44.06% of the overall vote, with a -9.03% swing.&lt;ref name=QLD/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://rsp.org.au/ Revolutionary Socialist Party (Australia)]

==References==

&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:Communist parties in Australia]]


{{Australia-org-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
