<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26557726" ns="0" title="Women Surrealists"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[Image:SourceoftheOrinocoRiver.jpg|right|thumb|[[Remedios Varo]], ''Exploration of the Source of the Orinoco River'', 1959.]]

'''Women Surrealists''' are women [[artists]], [[photographers]], [[filmmakers]] and [[authors]] of the [[Surrealism|Surrealist]] Movement which began in the early 1920s.  Many of them were part of, or connected to, the official [[Surrealist]] movement.  Others were inspired but more distantly connected.

==Painters==
*[[Eileen Forrester Agar]] (1899–1991) was born in Argentina and moved to [[United Kingdom|Britain]] in childhood.  She was prominent among British surrealists; Agar made intricate collages and paintings of abstract organic shapes.&lt;ref name=Colvile&gt;Colvile, Georgiana, ''Scandaleusement d'elles: trente-quatre femmes surréalistes'', Jean-Michel Place, Paris, 1999 ISBN 978-2858934966&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Leonora Carrington]] (1917-2011) was a British-born Surrealist painter. She met the Surrealist [[Max Ernst]] in 1937, and had a painful and complicated relationship with him. Much of her work is autobiographical.&lt;ref name=Heller /&gt;.  

*[[Leonor Fini]] (1907–1996), born in [[Buenos Aires]] and raised in [[Trieste]], met the Surrealists in 1936 but never officially joined. She paints startling images, often with [[sphinxes]] or apparitions.&lt;ref name=Heller/&gt;  

*[[Kay Sage]] (1898–1963) began painting surrealist landscapes in the late 1930s, met and married fellow surrealist[[Yves Tanguy]] in 1940.&lt;ref name=Heller&gt;Heller, Nancy G., ''Women Artists: An Illustrated History'', Abbeville Press, Publishers, New York 1987 ISBN 0-89659-748-2&lt;/ref&gt;  

*[[Dorothea Tanning]] (born 1910) was unable to join the Surrealists in Paris in 1940 because of the threat of war; she worked in New York, Arizona, and then Paris after the war.  Her work has a rumpled, &quot;juicy&quot; look.&lt;ref name=Heller /&gt;  

*[[Remedios Varo]] (1908–1963), a Spaniard who moved to Mexico, was known for her dreamlike paintings of scientific apparatus.  She was married to the Surrealist poet [[Benjamin Peret]].&lt;ref name=Heller /&gt;&lt;ref name=Kaplan&gt;Kaplan, Janet A. ''Unexpected Journeys: The Art and Life of Remedios Varo'', Abbeville Press, New York 1988 ISBN 0-89659-797-0&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Gertrude Abercrombie]] (1909–1977) was a [[Chicago]] artist inspired by the Surrealists, who became prominent in the 1930s and 1940s.  She was also involved with the [[jazz]] music scene and was friends with musicians such as [[Dizzy Gillespie]], [[Charlie Parker]], and [[Sarah Vaughan]].&lt;ref name=Vine&gt;Richard Vine, &quot;[http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1248/is_/ai_19385182 Where the Wild Things Were]&quot;, ''[[Art in America]]'', May 1997, pp. 98-111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Warren&gt;Warren, Lynn, ''Art in Chicago 1945-1995'', Thames &amp; Hudson, 1996 ISBN 978-0500237281&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sculptors==
*[[Méret Oppenheim]] (1913–1985) was a German-Swiss sculptor, famous as one of [[Man Ray]]'s models.  Her most famous sculpture is ''[[Object (Le Déjeuner en fourrure)|Object (Breakfast in Fur)]]'', a teacup, saucer and spoon completely encased in soft brown fur.&lt;ref name=Heller/&gt;

==Photographers==
*[[Claude Cahun]] (1894-1954) was a French photographer and writer, associated with the surrealist movement.
*[[Lee Miller]] (1907-1977) was an American photographer, photojournalist and model.

==Fashion==
Although not commonly classed with other fine arts, fashion also produced at least one Surrealist woman artist.  [[Elsa Schiaparelli]], (1890–1973) was an Italian fashion designer, a colleague of, friend of, and collaborator with [[Salvador Dalí]] and [[Leonor Fini]], among others.&lt;ref name=Martin&gt;Martin, Richard, ''Fashion and Surrealism'', Rizzoli International Publications, 1996 ISBN 978-0847810734&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Women artists]]
*[[List of 20th century women artists]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Women Surrealists| ]]
[[Category:Women artists]]
[[Category:Surrealism]]
[[Category:Art history]]
[[Category:Gender studies]]
[[Category:Women and the arts]]
[[Category:Feminism and the arts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
