<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26621308" ns="0" title="University College Dublin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university|
|name            =University College Dublin
|native_name     =An Coláiste Ollscoile, Baile Átha Cliath
|image           =[[File:UCDFormalArms.png|140px]]&lt;!--  Note: this is the UCD coat of arms, not the corporate logo which is shown below --&gt;
|latin_name      =Universitas Collegium apud Dublinum
|motto           =Ad Astra&lt;br&gt;Cothrom Féinne
|mottoeng        =To the stars&lt;br&gt;Fair play
|established     =18 May 1854, 1880, 1908
|staff           =3,267
|faculty         =1,322
|president       =Dr [[Hugh R. Brady]]
|head_label      =[[Registrar (academic)|Registrar]]
|head            =Professor Mark Rogers
|students        =17,214 (2010) &lt;ref name=&quot;studentnumbers&quot;&gt;[http://www.universityobserver.ie/advertise/]&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       =13,547 (2008/2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;studentnumbers&quot; /&gt;
|postgrad        = 3,667 (2008/2009)&lt;ref name=&quot;studentnumbers&quot; /&gt;
|city            = {{flagicon|Ireland}} [[Dublin]]
|country         =[[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]
|campus          = [[urban area|Urban]], 148 hectares (365 [[acres]])
|colours         ={{scarf|start}}
{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|#000000}}{{scarf|end}}
|affiliations    =[[Association of MBAs|AMBA]]&lt;br /&gt; [[European University Association|EUA]]&lt;br /&gt; [[National University of Ireland|NUI]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Irish Universities Association|IUA]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Universitas 21]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Universities Ireland|UI]]
|website         =http://www.ucd.ie
|address         =Belfield&lt;br&gt;Dublin 4
|logo =          [[File:UCD Dublin.png|100px]]
}}

'''University College Dublin (also known as UCD)''' ({{lang-ga|An Coláiste Ollscoile, Baile Átha Cliath}} (''COBÁC'')) - formally known as  '''University College Dublin - National University of Ireland, Dublin''' ({{lang-ga|An Coláiste Ollscoile, Baile Átha Cliath - Ollscoil na hÉireann, Baile Átha Cliath}}) is the [[Republic of Ireland]]'s largest, and [[Ireland]]'s second largest, [[university]], with over 1,300 faculty and 17,000 [[student]]s. It is located in [[Dublin]], the Irish capital.

The university originates in a body founded in 1854 as the [[Catholic University of Ireland]] with [[John Henry Newman]] as the first rector, re-formed in 1880 and chartered in its own right in 1908. The Universities Act, 1997 renamed the ''constituent university'' as the &quot;National University of Ireland, Dublin&quot;, and a ministerial order of 1998 renamed the institution as &quot;University College Dublin - National University of Ireland, Dublin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nui.ie/about/history.asp History of the NUI - Constituent Universities]&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally located in the centre of the metropolis, most of the university's faculties have since been relocated to a 148 hectares (365 acre) park campus at [[Belfield, Dublin|Belfield]], four kilometres to the south of the city.

==History==
The university can trace its history to the institution founded in 1854 as the [[Catholic University of Ireland]], was established as UCD in 1880 under the auspices of the Royal University, and received its charter in 1908.

[[File:John Henry Newman by Sir John Everett Millais, 1st Bt.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Blessed [[John Henry Newman]], first rector of the University]]

===Catholic University of Ireland===
{{See also|Catholic University of Ireland}}
[[File:UCDNewmanHouse.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Newman house, St Stephen's Green, Dublin. The original location of UCD.]]
[[File:Iveagh Gardens Wasserfallblick.JPG|thumb|250px|right|The Gardens located behind Earlsfort Terrace donated and renamed in his honour by UCD in 1908]]
In the years following Catholic emancipation in Ireland, a movement led by Cardinal [[Paul Cullen (cardinal)|Paul Cullen]] attempted to provide for the first time in Ireland higher-level education that was both accessible to Irish Catholics and taught by fellow-Catholics. In the 19th century, the question of denominational education in Ireland was a contentious one. It had divided [[Daniel O'Connell]] and the [[Young Ireland]] Movement for many years. The Catholic Hierarchy wanted to counteract the &quot;Godless Colleges&quot; established in [[University College Galway|Galway]], [[Queens University|Belfast]] and [[University College Cork|Cork]] and to provide a Catholic alternative to [[Trinity College, Dublin]].  Trinity was Anglican in its origins and, though Catholics had studied there since the 1780s, Trinity had maintained a religious test that excluded them from membership of the college's governing bodies (see [[Denis Caulfield Heron]]).  In 1850 at the [[Synod]] of [[Thurles]] it was decided to open a Catholic University. 

As a result of these efforts a new Catholic University of Ireland was opened in 1854 and Blessed [[John Henry Newman]] was appointed as its first rector. Newman had been an integral figure in the [[Oxford Movement]] in the 19th Century. The Catholic University opened its doors on the feast of St Malachy, 3 November 1854. On that day the names of seventeen students were entered on the register and Newman gave the students an address &quot;What are we here for&quot; and prophesied that in later years they would look back with pride on the day. The university opened with three houses: 86 St Stephen's Green, with was known as St Patrick's or University House, under the care of Rev. Dr Michael Flannery; 16 Harcourt Street, known as St Lawrence's under the care of Rev. Dr James Quinn, who also had his school there; and Newman's own house, 6 Harcourt Street, known as St Mary's under Newman's personal supervision.

Amongst the first students enrolled it included the grandson of [[Daniel O’Connell]]. Another included [[William O'Shea]] who would go onto become a Captain in the British Army and was central to the divorce crises which brought down [[Charles Stewart Parnell]]'s career in trying to establish Home Rule for Ireland. O'Shea though clashed with Newman and left to go to Trinity, however, after one year. Of the eight original students in Newman's own home, two were Irish, two English, two Scottish and two French. Among them were a French viscount, and Irish baronet Sir Reginald Barnewall, the son of a French countess, the grandson of a Scottish marquis, and the son of an English lord. Later were added to his care two Belgian princes and a Polish count. Many were attracted to the University on the basis of the reputation of Newman. 

As a private university the Catholic University was never given a royal charter, and so was unable to award recognized degrees and suffered from chronic financial difficulties. Newman left the university in 1857 and it subsequently went into a serious decline. Dr Bartholomew Woodlock appointed Rector and served until he became Bishop of Ardagh and Clonmacnoise in 1879. In this period he attempted to secure a site of 34 acres at Clonliffe West but the scheme collapsed when expansion of the railway system on the north side of Dublin cut across the site. He then turned his attention to expanding along St Stephen's Green and over these years bought from No. 82 to 87.

This trend was reversed in 1880 with the establishment of the Royal University of Ireland. The Royal Universities charter entitled all Irish students to sit the Universities examinations and receive its degrees. Although in many respects the Catholic University can be viewed as a failure, the future University College inherited substantial assets from it including a successful medical school (Cecilia Street) and two beautiful buildings, Newman House on St Stephen's Green and the adjoining University Church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.universitychurch.ie/ University Church]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foundation of University College, Dublin===
[[File:Gbuildings.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Government buildings, Dublin. The former location of the UCD science and engineering faculties. Opened by [[King George V]] in 1905]]
In order to avail of the benefits of the [[Royal University of Ireland]] arrangement, the Catholic University was re-formed as University College, Dublin. The college rapidly attracted many of the best students and academics in Ireland including [[Gerard Manley Hopkins]] and [[James Joyce]] and quickly began to outperform the other three colleges in the Royal University system - in the fifteen years before the establishment of the National University the number of first class distinctions in Arts awarded by the Royal University to University College was 702 compared with a total of 486 awarded to the combined Queen's Colleges of [[Queen's University Belfast|Belfast]], [[National University of Ireland, Galway|Galway]] and [[University College Cork - National University of Ireland, Cork|Cork]]. Many of the college’s staff and students during this period would later contribute substantially to the formation and development of the future Irish state, the most famous being  [[Francis Sheehy-Skeffington]], [[Pádraig Pearse]], [[Hugh Kennedy]], [[Eoin MacNeill]], [[Kevin Christopher O'Higgins|Kevin O’Higgins]], [[Tom Kettle]], [[James Ryan (Irish politician)|James Ryan]], [[Douglas Hyde]] and [[John A. Costello]]. Student unrest occurred  during this period, especially during loyalist speeches by the Chancellor, the Earl of Meath and the playing of &quot;God Save the King&quot; at conferring ceremonies.

In 1908, the Royal University was dissolved and a new [[National University of Ireland]] founded to replace it. This new University was brought into existence with three constituent University Colleges - Dublin, Galway and Cork. By this time the college campus consisted of a number of locations in and around St Stephens Green in Dublins city centre, the main sites being Earlsfort Terrace, Cecilia Street, College of Science Merrion Street, and Newman House on St Stephen's Green.
Under the Universities Act, 1997, University College Dublin was established as a constituent university within the National University of Ireland framework.

===UCD and the Irish War of Independence===
[[File:Belfield Arts Block 1445w.jpg|thumb|250px|right|The Tierny (Administration) and Newman (Arts) Buildings, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
In 1913 in response to the formation of the [[Ulster Volunteer Force (1966)|Ulster Volunteer Force]], [[Eoin MacNeill]], professor of early Irish history (who viewed the movement as a threat to the Home Rule movement), called for the formation of an Irish nationalist force to counteract it. The [[Irish Volunteers]] were formed later that year and MacNeill was elected its Chief-of-staff. At the outbreak of the [[First World War]] in view of the [[Home Rule Act 1914]] the majority of the volunteers opted to support the British war effort, including many UCD staff and students. Many of those who opposed this move later participated in the [[Easter Rising]].

In this way UCD was a reflection of the Irish nationalist community in general, with several staff and students participating in the rising, such as [[Patrick Pearse]], [[Thomas MacDonagh]], [[Michael Hayes (politician)|Michael Hayes]] and [[James Ryan (Irish politician)|James Ryan]], and a smaller number, including [[Tom Kettle]] and [[Willie Redmond]], fighting for the British in [[World War I]] during the same period.

Many UCD staff, students and alumni fought in the [[Irish War of Independence]] that followed the rising. Following the signing of the [[Anglo-Irish Treaty]] four UCD graduates joined the [[government of the Irish Free State]]. It is notable that the [[First Dáil Éireann]]  was located in UCD's Earlsfort Terrace campus from 1919 to 1922, when they moved to their current location in [[Leinster House]].

The university's graduates have since had a large impact on Irish political life - four of the eight [[President of Ireland|Presidents of Ireland]] and six of the twelve [[Taoiseach|Taoisigh]] have been either former staff or graduates. Of the fifteen current members of the Irish cabinet, nine are former UCD students.

===Move to Belfield===
[[File:UCDEgg.jpg|thumb|right|250px|'Noah's egg' outside the Veterinary School by  [[Rachel Joynt]] (2004)]]
By the early 1940s the College had become the largest third level institution in the state. In an effort to cope with the increased numbers unsuccessful attempts were made to expand the existing city centre campus. It was finally decided that the best solution would be to move the College to a much larger greenfield site outside of the city centre and create a modern [[campus university]]. This move started in the early 1960s when the faculty of science moved to the new {{convert|1.4|km2|acre}} park campus at [[Belfield, Dublin|Belfield]] in a suburb on the south side of Dublin. The Belfield campus has since developed into a complex of modern buildings and inherited Georgian town houses, accommodating the colleges of the University as well as its student residences and many leisure and sporting facilities. One of UCD's previous locations, the ''Royal College of Science'' on Merrion Street is now the location of the renovated [[Irish Government]] Building, where the Department of the [[Taoiseach]] (Irish prime minister) is situated. University College Dublin had also a site in [[Glasnevin]] for much of the last century, the [[Albert Agricultural College]], the southern part of which is now occupied by [[Dublin City University]], the northern part is where [[Ballymun]] town is located.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/gsi/pdf/33-2/ballymun.pdf The development of the Ballymun housing scheme, Dublin, 1965-1969,Sinéad Power, Department of Geography, University of Edinburgh]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Timeline===
*'''1854''' - The [[Catholic University]] of Ireland opens with Blessed [[John Henry Newman]] as the first rector. It is located on [[St Stephen's Green]].
*'''1855''' - The Catholic University Medical School was opened in 1855 in Cecilia Street.
*'''1856''' - University Church was opened in 1856. Apart from religious services it was used also for public university functions and occasions such as the opening of academic sessions and the making of awards.
*'''1861''' - Dr [[Bartholomew Woodlock]] appointed Rector and served until he became Bishop of Ardagh and Clonmacnoise in 1879.
*'''1879''' - Monsignor Henry Neville, Dean of Cork appointed Rector (while still retaining his role as Parish Priest in a Cork parish).
*'''1880''' - The University Education (Ireland) Act 1879 brought in by Disraeli's government led to the establishment of the Royal University of Ireland (incorporated by charter in 1880) which was a non-teaching, degree-awarding institution.
*'''1882/83''' - The Catholic University reorganized in order to avail of the indirect endowment from the state through the Royal University of Ireland. The St Stephen's Green institution was renamed University College and its management was transferred to the [[Jesuits]].
*'''1883-1888''' - Fr William Delany SJ appointed first president of University College.
*'''1908''' -  Irish Universities Act brought into being the [[National University of Ireland]] with its constituent University Colleges - Dublin, Galway and Cork, and led to the demise of the Royal University and the Jesuit-run University College. Dr Denis Coffey appointed first president of reformed UCD. Coffey was to hold the position for 30 years. The Medical School in Cecilia Street became the UCD Medical Faculty. The campus covers, Earlsfort Terrace, Cecilia Street, College of Science Merrion Street, Albert College Glasnevin and St Stephen's Green.
*'''1908''' - The Faculty of Commerce established.
*'''1911''' - Land donated by Lord Iveagh helps the university expand in Earlsfort Terrace/Hatch Street/ St Stephen's Green. [[Iveagh Gardens]] are apart of this donation.
*'''1913''' - University Park, Terenure became the base of UCD sports clubs between 1913 and 1934 - although the landlord would not sell the site to the university.
*'''1916''' - A number of junior staff and students participated in the [[Easter Rising]].
*'''1926'''- University Education (Agriculture and Dairy Science) Act transferred the [[Royal College of Science]] in [[Merrion Street]] and Albert Agricultural College in Glasnevin to UCD.
*'''1933 ''' - Belfield House on 44 acres is bought for sporting purposes.
*'''1940''' - Dr Arthur Conway appointed president. During this period various plans were developed but failed to succeed to expand along Iveagh Gardens, Hatch Street and Earlsfort Terrace.
*'''1964''' - Dr Jeremiah Hogan appointed president (1964–1972). Science moves in to new campus at Belfield. UCD becomes the first University in Europe to launch a [[MBA]] programme.
*'''1967''' - Minister for Education, [[Donogh O'Malley]], proposes plan to merge UCD and Trinity.
*'''1969-1970''' - Faculties of Commerce, Arts and Law move to Belfield.
*'''1972''' - Dr Thomas Murphy appointed president (1972–1985).
*'''1973''' - The Library (Now known as the James Joyce Library) opens.
*'''1980''' - Richview and 17.4 acres bought. Architecture moves in there.
*'''1981''' - Sports Complex opens.
*'''1986''' - Dr Patrick Masterson appointed president. (1986–1993)
*'''1990''' - Engineering building opens. Most, but not all of the Earlsforth terrace, Engineering department moves to Belfield.
*'''1990''' - Carysfort College, Blackrock on 19 acres bought and is the location of the Smurfit Graduate School of Business. First student village (Belgrove) opened.
*'''1992''' - Second student village (Merville) opened. The Centre for Film Studies established.
*'''1993''' - Dr Art Cosgrove appointed president (1994–2003).
*'''1994''' - O'Reilly Hall opened.
*'''2003''' - NovaUCD, a 110 million Euro Innovation and Technology Transfer Centre opened. The purpose-built centre was funded by a public/private partnership. UCD purchased the Philips site and buildings adjacent to the Belfield campus at Clonskeagh, to facilitate the relocation of the Departments of Civil and Agricultural &amp; Food Engineering from Earlsfort Terrace, bringing more of the remaining off campus elements of the University to Belfield.
*'''2004''' - Dr Hugh Brady appointed president. UCD celebrates 150th Anniversary.
*'''2006''' - UCD Horizons begins.
*'''2007''' - With the completion of the final phase of the Health Sciences Building, the last of the departments remaining at Earlsfort terrace relocate to Belfield.
*'''2009''' - Innovation Alliance announced between Trinity and UCD.
*'''2010''' - [[NCAD]] and [[UCD]] forge stronger links. The two institutions will form an academic alliance with new joint courses and research across common areas of interest. NCAD will become a ''constituent college'' of UCD once the NUI is dissolved in 2011 whilst remaining on its current site and retaining institutional autonomy.
*'''2012''' - Expanded and merged Student and Sports Centre to open containing Olympic Swimming pool, cinema and new gym.
*'''2013''' - Sutherland School of Law to open to replace Roebuck castle for the Law faculty.

==Academic==
===Colleges and schools===
[[File:Belfield 1449w.JPG|thumb|250px|The biological and geological sciences building of the Science Centre, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
[[File:UCDhealthScience.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Health Sciences building, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
[[Image:Our Lady of Mercy College, Carysfort.JPG|thumb|Michael Smurfit Graduate School of Business, Blackrock]]
[[Image:UCD Quinn School of Business.jpg|thumb|UCD Quinn School Of Business]]
The University consists of five colleges, their associated schools (34 in total) and eighteen research institutes and centres. Each college also has its own [[Graduate School]], for postgraduates.

List of colleges and their respective schools:
* [http://www.ucd.ie/artsceltic/index.html College of Arts &amp; Celtic Studies]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/archaeology/index.html School of Archaeology]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/arthistory/index.html School of Art History &amp; Cultural Policy]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/classics/index.html School of Classics]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/englishanddrama/index.html School of English, Drama &amp; Film]
:[[University College Dublin School of History and Archives|School of History &amp; Archives]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucd.ie/historyarchives/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
:[http://www.ucd.ie/icsifl/index.html School of Irish, Celtic Studies, Irish Folklore &amp; Linguistics]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/sllf/index.html School of Languages &amp; Literatures]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/music/index.html School of Music]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/businessandlaw/index.html College of Business &amp; Law]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/business/index.html School of Business]
::[[UCD Quinn School of Business|Quinn School of Business]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucd.ie/quinn&lt;/ref&gt;
::[[Michael Smurfit Graduate School of Business]]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/law/index.html School of Law]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/engscience/index.html College of Engineering, Mathematical &amp; Physical Sciences]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/arcel/index.html School of Architecture, Landscape &amp; Civil Engineering]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/chembioeng/index.html School of Chemical &amp; Bioprocess Engineering]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/csi/index.html School of Computer Science &amp; Informatics]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/eem/index.html School of Electrical, Electronic &amp; Mechanical Engineering]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/geology/index.html School of Geological Sciences]
:[http://mathsci.ucd.ie/ School of Mathematical Sciences]
:[[School of Physics (University College Dublin)|School of Physics]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucd.ie/physics/preston/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.ucd.ie/humansciences/index.html College of Human Sciences]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/appsocsc/index.html School of Applied Social Science]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/economics/index.html School of Economics]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/education/index.html School of Education]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/gpep/index.html School of Geography, Planning &amp; Environmental Policy]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/sils/index.html School of Information &amp; Library Studies]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/philosophy/index.html School of Philosophy]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/politics/index.html School of Politics &amp; International Relations]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/psychology/index.html School of Psychology]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/socialjustice/index.html School of Social Justice]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/sociology/index.html School of Sociology]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/lifesciences/index.html College of Life Sciences]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/agfoodvet/index.html School of Agriculture, Food Science &amp; Veterinary Medicine]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/bioenvsci/index.html School of Biology &amp; Environmental Science]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/sbbs/index.html School of Biomolecular &amp; Biomedical Science]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/chem/index.html School of Chemistry &amp; Chemical Biology]
:[[School of Medicine and Medical Science (University College Dublin)|School of Medicine &amp; Medical Science]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ucd.ie/medicine/index.html&lt;/ref&gt;
:[http://www.ucd.ie/nmhs/index.html School of Nursing, Midwifery &amp; Health Systems]
:[http://www.ucd.ie/phpps/ School of Public Health, Physiotherapy &amp; Population Science]

===UCD Horizons===
At the beginning of the 2005/2006 academic year, UCD introduced the ''Horizons'' curriculum,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/horizons UCD&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; which completely semesterised and modularised all undergraduate programmes enhancing the quality and flexibility of the standard university education. Under the Horizons curriculum, new undergraduate students have greater choice in what exactly they study in their programme. Under the new curriculum, students choose ten core modules from their specific subject area and two other modules, which can be chosen from any other programme across the entire University (this applies in the majority of programmes, however some exceptions, as in Arts Omnibus and Business &amp; Law, can apply). For example, a student studying Stage 1 Commerce as his primary degree programme can also choose one module (or two) from the Stage 1 Law programme (subject to space availability, timetable constraints and so on).

==Reputation==
===Alumni===
{{Infobox Awards
 | title =
 | halign = center
 | award1 = {{multiple image
 | align = center
 | direction = horizontal
 | header = Famous UCD graduates
 | header_align = center
 | header_background = 
 | footer =
 | footer_align = left/right/center
 | footer_background =
 | width =
 | image1 = Revolutionary Joyce.jpg
 | width1 = 118
 | caption1 = [[James Joyce]] 1903, writer
 | image2 = 
 | width2 = 105
 | caption2 = [[V V Giri]], the 4th [[President of India]]
 | image3 = Brian O'Driscoll 2.jpg
 | width3 = 129
 | caption3 = [[Brian O'Driscoll]] 2001, rugby player
}}
 | award2 = {{multiple image
 | align = center
 | direction = horizontal
 | header = 
 | header_align = center
 | header_background = 
 | footer =
 | footer_align = left/right/center
 | footer_background =
 | width =
 | width1 = 107
 | image2 = Gabriel Byrne 07TIFF.jpg
 | width2 = 119
 | caption2 = [[Gabriel Byrne]], actor
 | image3 = Neil Jordan by David Shankbone.jpg
 | width3 = 126
 | caption3 = [[Neil Jordan]], [[Academy Award|Oscar]] winning Film Director and Producer

}}
 }}
{{Main|List of University College Dublin people}}

Among its most accomplished alumni and faculty are four former presidents of Ireland; [[Douglas Hyde]], [[Patrick Hillery]], [[Cearbhall Ó Dálaigh]] and [[Éamon de Valera]]. [[V. V. Giri]], the fourth [[President of India]] studied law between 1913 to 1916 before being expelled from Ireland. Six former [[Taoiseach|Taoisigh]] (Prime Ministers) of Ireland attended UCD: [[Éamon de Valera]]{{Citation needed|reason: while de Valera took his degree from the Royal University, is there any evidence that he attended UCD?|date=March 2011}}, [[John A. Costello]], [[Charles Haughey]], [[Garret FitzGerald]], [[John Bruton]] and [[Brian Cowen]]. Since the foundation of the Irish state in 1922, UCD has produced the most Justices of the [[Supreme Court of Ireland]], the most Chief Justices and the most [[Attorney Generals]] of Ireland. Examples of other well known UCD alumni include writers [[James Joyce]] the author of ''[[Ulysses (novel)|Ulysses]]'', [[Flann O'Brien]], [[John Jordan (poet)|John Jordan]] and [[Roddy Doyle]]. Actors [[Gabriel Byrne]], [[Dan O'Herlihy]] and [[Brendan Gleeson]]. Film directors include [[Academy Award|Oscar]] winner [[Neil Jordan]] and [[Jim Sheridan]]). Comedians to attend include [[Dermot Morgan]] (noted for playing the title role in ''[[Father Ted]]'') and [[Dara Ó Briain]]. Amongst the number of humanitarians to attend include, [[John O'Shea (humanitarian)|John O'Shea]]) founder of [[GOAL (charity)]] and [[Tom Arnold (economist)|Tom Arnold]] the CEO of [[Concern Worldwide]]. Cardinals include (e.g. [[Tomás Ó Fiaich]] and [[Desmond Connell]]. Noted businessmen include [[David J. O'Reilly]], formerly CEO and Chairman of the [[Chevron Corporation]], [[Tony O'Reilly]], who previously served as the CEO of [[H.J. Heinz Company]] and noted for his ownership of Irish businesses, and [[Peter Sutherland]] (former [[EU]] Commissioner, head of the [[WTO]] and chairman of [[BP]]). Others include [[Eddie O'Connor (businessman)|Eddie O'Connor]], economists (e.g. Dr.[[Garret FitzGerald]] and Prof.[[Patrick Lynch (Irish Economist)|Patrick Lynch]]) and sportspeople (e.g. [[Brian O'Driscoll]]).

===Rankings===
The university is consistently ranked as one of the best universities in the Republic of Ireland on worldwide metrics.
*'''Financial Times Global MBA Ranking 2011.'''
:'''78th''' globally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rankings.ft.com/businessschoolrankings/global-mba-rankings Financial Times Global MBA Ranking 2011. Retrieved 2011-2-12.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Financial Times European Business School Rankings 2010.'''
:'''30th''' in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://rankings.ft.com/businessschoolrankings/european-business-school-rankings Financial Times European Business School Rankings 2010. Retrieved 2010-11-12.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''The Economist (Full-time MBA ranking) 2010.'''
:'''31st''' globally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.economist.com/whichmba/2010/free-ranking-tool The Economist (2009 full-time MBA ranking). Retrieved 2011-03-10.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2011-2012. '''
:'''159th''' globally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2011-2012/top-400.html 'Times Higher Education World University Rankings 2011-2012.]&lt;/ref&gt; '''67th''' in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2011-2012/europe.html#score_OS%7Csort_rank%7Creverse_false]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''QS World University Rankings 2011.'''
:'''134th''' globally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011 results QS World University Rankings 2011 Results&quot;. 'QS World University Rankings 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''Academic Ranking of World Universities 2011.'''
:'''301-400''' globally.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.shanghairanking.com/Institution.jsp?param=University%20College%20Dublin Academic Ranking of World Universities 2011.]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Awards===
*'''The Sunday Times University of the Year 2006'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/news/media/2006/sept06/mon11sept.pdf Sunday Times]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research and innovation==
The University is a leading research centre within Ireland with a research income of €114.7&amp;nbsp;million during 2007/8. UCDs research community of approximately one thousand faculty members, one thousand post doctoral researchers and two thousand PhD students work in the various schools and research institutes of the University.

===Research Institutes===
[[File:UCDResearchBuilding.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Research administration building, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
[[File:ConwayInstitute.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The Conway Institute, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
[[File:UCDNova.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Front entrance, NovaUCD]]
Amongst the research institutes of the university are:

* Centre for Research in Infectious Diseases
* [http://www.ucd.ie/cscb/ Centre for Synthesis and Chemical Biology]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/amerstud/ Clinton Institute for American Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/research/charlesinstitute/ Charles Institute]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/china/ Irish Institute for Chinese Studies]
* [[Complex and adaptive systems laboratory|Complex and Adaptive Systems Laboratory]]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/conway/ Conway Institute of Biomolecular and Biomedical Research]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/cds/ Centre for Development studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/include/ Centre for Disability Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/dramastd/ Centre for Drama Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/mediahis/ Centre for the History of the Media]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/crc/ UCD Clinical Research Centre]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/dei/ Dublin European Institute]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/earth/ Earth Systems Institute]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/esc/ Equality Studies Centre]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/foodandhealth/ Institute of food and health]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/geary/ Geary Institute (Research for the Social Sciences)]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/hii/ Humanities Institute of Ireland]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/ibis/ Institute for British-Irish Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/criminol/ Institute of Criminology]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/iccls/ Irish Centre for Commercial Law Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/johnhume/ John Hume Institute for Global Irish Studies]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/mocleirigh/index.htm Mícheál Ó Cléirigh Institute (Irish History &amp; Civilisation)]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/sport/homeISH.html National Institute of Sport and Health]
* [http://www.urbaninstitute.net/ Urban Institute of Ireland]
* [http://www.ucd.ie/film/ O'Kane Centre For Film Studies]

===External collaborations===
Wide partnerships in which the university is involved include:
* [http://www.adaptiveinformation.ie/ Adaptive Information Cluster] (with [[Dublin City University|DCU]])
* [http://www.cisc.ie/ Centre for Innovation and Structural Change] (with [[National University of Ireland, Galway|NUI Galway]] and [[Dublin City University|DCU]])
* [http://www.crann.tcd.ie/index Centre for research on adaptive nanostructures and nanodevices] (with [[Trinity College, Dublin|TCD]] and [[University College Cork|UCC]])
* [http://ctvr.ie/partners.php CTVR Centre for Telecommunications Value-Chain-Driven Research] (with [[Dublin City University|DCU]], [[Trinity College, Dublin|TCD]], [[National University of Ireland, Maynooth|NUI Maynooth]], [[University College Cork|UCC]], [[University of Limerick|UL]], [[Dublin Institute of Technology|DIT]] and [[Institute of Technology, Sligo|Sligo IT]]).
* [[National Digital Research Centre]] (with [[Dublin City University]] and [[Trinity College, Dublin]]).
* [http://www.nibrt.ie/ National Institute for Bioprocessing Research and Training] (with [[Dublin City University]], [[Trinity College, Dublin]] and [[Institute of Technology, Sligo|Sligo IT]]).
*[http://www.cosmogrid.ie Programme for Research on Grid-enabled Computational Physics of Natural Phenomena] (with [[Dublin City University|DCU]], [[Trinity College, Dublin|TCD]], [[University College Cork|UCC]] [[Dublin Institute for Advanced Studies|DIAS]], [[National University of Ireland, Galway|NUI Galway]], [[HEAnet]], [[Met Éireann]], [[Armagh Observatory]] and Grid Ireland).
* [http://www.ucd.ie/research/newsevents/latestnews/mainbody,6932,en.html Advanced Biomimetic Materials for Solar Energy Conversion] {with the [[University of Limerick]], [[Dublin City University]], [[Airtricity]], OBD-Tec and [http://www.celticcatalysts.com Celtic Catalysts].

===Current and former campus companies===
The most prominent university-related company is the [[IE Domain Registry]]; many of the university's academics continue to sit on the board of directors. The university originally gained control of the [[.ie]] domain in the late 1980s.

There are a number of related companies, many concentrated as the [http://www.ucd.ie/nova/ NovaUCD] initiative, to commercialise research results and opportunities; many of these reflect the university's expertise in the [[life science]]s and information technology. These companies include:

* Analytical Drug and Data (ADD) (specialising in [[brain]] research)
* [http://www.berand.ie/ Berand] (concentrating on the development of new chemicals for disease treatment)
* [http://www.biancamed.com/ BiancaMed] (health technology solutions for everyday living)
* [[Biosensia]] (Point-of-Care in vitro diagnostics company)
* [http://www.broadcast.ie/ Broadcast Learning]
* [http://www.businesscale.com/DesktopDefault.aspx?swidth=1024&amp;sheight=768 Businesscale]
* [http://www.celticcatalysts.com/ Celtic Catalysts] (involved in [[chirality (chemistry)|chiral]] chemistry research)
* [http://www.changingworlds.com/ ChangingWorlds] (develops multi-access, intelligent portal platforms for mobile operators)
* [http://www.cornerstone-international.com/ Cornerstone Knowledge International]
* [http://www.crovan.com/ Crovan]
* [[Duolog]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.duolog.com/index.asp&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.elearningunion.com/ (e)Learning Union]
* Enzolve (an [[enzyme]] and [[protein]] commercialisation group)
* [http://www.eventznet.ie/ Eventznet]
* [http://www.healthsystems.ie/ Intelligent Health Systems]
* ''Ildana Biotech'' is a joint group with [[Dublin City University]].
* [http://www.javacr.com/ Java Clinical Research]
* Lightwave Technologies
* [http://www.locumotion.com/ Locumotion]
* [http://www.allavoce.com/ AllaVoca]
* [http://www.neosera.com/ Neosera]
* Novus (financial services management and consultancy company)
* [http://www.ucd.ie/spectral/index_ns.htm Spectral Signatures]
* [http://www.visor.ie/ Visor Consulting]

==Student life==
===Sport===
[[File:UCDStudentCentre.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The Student Centre, Belfield campus, UCD]]
UCD has very strong sporting traditions and a very successful competitive record in a great range of sports. The most successful clubs during 2005/2006 were the Senior Hurling team (winners of the Dublin County Championship), the Senior Hockey team (winners of the Leinster Senior Cup), the Senior Basketball team (University Championship winners), the Ladies Volleyball team (which won the University Championships and the English Student Cup), the Under-20 Rugby team (which won a league and cup double), the table tennis team (which won the Irish Universities Championships for the 7th year in a row), the Soccer teams (winning a variety of cups and leagues), the Senior Men's Cricket Team (Varsity Plate Winners) and the Ultimate Frisbee Open Team (winners of Div 2 UK Nationals). The current U.C.D. five a side soccer champions are Five Young Fun Boys managed by Ciaran Fisher and assisted by Patrick Coman.

The most successful clubs in 2006/2007 were the Table Tennis Club (Irish Universities Champions for the 8th year in a row, Leinster Cup Champions &amp; SuperLeague Champions, qualifying for the ETTU European Cup), the Fencing Club (Intervarsity winners 5th year in a row, Colours winners 10th year in a row, Darius Vasseghi Team Foil Cup winners, Trinity Team Cup Winners) and the Cricket Club (joint inter-varsity winners).

The Belfield campus is home to a wide range of sports facilities, but notably lacks a swimming pool and a running track. Facilities include the national hockey stadium (which has previously hosted the [[World Hockey Cup|Women's Hockey World Cup Finals]] and the Men's Hockey European Championship Finals), two other stadia (one for rugby and one for soccer), one of the largest fitness centres in the country, squash courts, tennis courts, an indoor rifle range, over twenty sports pitches (for rugby, soccer and gaelic games), an indoor climbing wall and two large sports halls. It is hoped that a swimming pool will be added before 2010. There are currently over fifty sports clubs in UCD.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ucd.ie/sport/clublist.htm UCD - UCD Sport&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; These cater for archery to windsurfing and just about everything in between. Probably the three largest and most successful clubs are the [[University College Dublin A.F.C.|soccer club]] (currently the only university team to compete in the top division of the national league in Western Europe), the [[University College Dublin RFC|rugby club]] (currently playing in the [[AIB League]] Division 2) and the [[UCD GAA|Gaelic Sports club]].

The University hosted the [[IFIUS]] [[World Interuniversity Games]] in October 2006.
* [http://www.ucd.ie/sport/clubslist.htm Sport Clubs in UCD]
:[[University College Dublin RFC]]
:[[University College Dublin A.F.C.]]
:[[UCD GAA]]
:[[UCD Marian]]
:[[UCD Fencing Club]]

===Societies===
[[File:Belfield 1414w.JPG|thumb|250px|The main restaurant building, with the corner of the Quinn School of Business visible on the left, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
There are currently over fifty [http://www.ucd.ie/socs.htm student societies] in the university. They cater for many interests ranging from large-scale party societies such as Ag Soc, [http://www.artssoc.com Arts Soc], [http://www.cesociety.com/ Commerce and Economics Society] and [http://www.qsoc.ie/ Qsoc]. There are religiously-interested groups such as the [http://www.ucd.ie/cunion Christian Union], the [http://www.ucdisoc.com/ Islamic Society] and the [http://www.ucdhumanistsociety.wordpress.com Secular Humanist Society], a television station [http://www.ctn.ie Campus Television Network], academic-oriented societies like the [http://www.ucd.ie/philsoc/ Philosophy Society], [http://www.ucd.ie/mathsoc/ Mathsoc], [http://www.ucdclassicalsociety.org Classical Society], Filmsoc and everything in between, including An Cumann Gaelach, an Irish-language society and such charities as St. Vincent de Paul, [http://www.ucd.ie/svdp UCDSVP]. All Irish political parties are represented on campus including Young Fine Gael, Ógra Fianna Fáil, The Socialist Party, Sinn Féin, The Green Party and [http://www.labour.ie/youth/oncampus/index/20030909085645.html UCD Labour Youth]. The college has two debating unions. The oldest student society is the [[Literary and Historical Society (University College Dublin)|Literary and Historical Society]], which is currently in its 156th session. The [[University College Dublin Law Society]], however, is both the largest debating society in the University, and also holds the largest membership of any society; having 5,248 members in the 09/10 Academic Year{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}. It is now in its Centenary Session and aside from debating it also acts as a mooting, entertainment and professional development society.  Away from politics and debating the [[UCD Dramsoc]] is the university drama society, it is noted for an active membership and a number of notable alumni. The university also has a successful sinfonia called [[University College Dublin Symphony Orchestra]].

===Students' Union===
[[File:Glenomena3.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Glenomena student residences, Belfield campus, UCD.]]
The [[students' union]], [[UCDSU]] in the college has been an active part of campaigns run by the National Union, [[Union of Students in Ireland|USI]], and has played a highly significant role in the life of the college since its foundation in 1974.

The Union has also taken significant stances on issues of human rights that have hit the headlines in Ireland and around the world, particularly in becoming the first institution in the world to implement a ban of [[Coca-Cola]] products in Student Union controlled shops on the basis of alleged human and trade union rights abuses in [[Colombia]]. This ban was overturned in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.universityobserver.ie/2010/03/05/ucd-students-overturn-coke-ban-as-lynam-wins-students-union-presidency/]&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Union's main Governing Body is the Union Council which meets every two weeks during term. Council membership consists of 180+ seats for Class Representatives, ten directly elected officers of the Union Executive and five Executive officers elected by Union Council at its first meeting each year. Their term commences on 1 July in the year of their election and lasts for twelve months. Sabbatical elections take place in late February of each year. To date, students from Arts, Social Science and Law have predominated in holding council seats.

===Student publications and media===
====Newspapers====
The university has two student papers, the broadsheet ''[[The University Observer]]'' and the tabloid [[College Tribune]]. Both papers are usually published on a fortnightly basis throughout the academic year.

=====''The University Observer''=====
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[File:Universityobserver.gif|right|250px|]] --&gt;
''[[The University Observer]]'' won the Newspaper of the Year award at the National Student Media Awards in April 2006, an accolade it has achieved many times. Founded in 1994, its first editors were Pat Leahy and comedian [[Dara Ó Briain]]. Many figures in Irish journalism have held the position of editor including ''The Irish Times'' deputy news editor Roddy O'Sullivan, ''The Sunday Business Post'' political correspondent Pat Leahy, AFP business reporter Enda Curran, ''[[Sunday Independent]]'' Chief Reporter [[Daniel McConnell (journalist)|Daniel McConnell]], [[RTÉ]] News reporter Samantha Libreri and TV researcher Alan Torney. The efforts of its staff were noted by the prestigious ''[[The Guardian|Guardian]]'' Student Media Awards with a nomination for &quot;Best Newspaper&quot;, the first Irish student publication to receive such recognition. In 2001, in addition to several Irish National Student Media Awards, the ''University Observer'' under McConnell and Curran took the runner up prize for &quot;Best Publication&quot; at the Guardian Student Media Awards in London. To date, ''The University Observer'' has won 29 [[Irish Student Media Awards]].

The main sections within the paper are: campus, national and international news, comment, opinion and sport. In addition, each edition includes a pullout arts and culture supplement called ''O-Two'', with music interviews, travel, fashion and colour pieces. ''The University Observer'' is funded by the UCD Students' Union, but its content remains editorially independent, barring one 'Union Page' per issue.

=====[[College Tribune]]=====
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:College Tribune Issue 4.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Front page of issue 4 of the 'College Tribune', 2006]] --&gt;
The [http://www.collegetribune.ie ''College Tribune''] was founded in 1988, with the assistance of noted political commentator [[Vincent Browne]], then an evening student in the college, who noted the lack of an independent media outlet for students and the college in general. Financially, it is supported by commercial advertising in the paper and is completely independent of college and union authorities. Former editors include Conor Lally, Crime Correspondent of the ''Irish Times'', ''The Sunday Times'' journalist Richard Oakley, former ''Sunday Tribune'' reporter Eoghan Rice, Paul Lynch, film critic of the ''Sunday Tribune'', ''Irish Independent'' soccer correspondent Daniel McDonnell, and brothers Gary and Fergus O'Shea, both now in the ''Irish Sun'', who were editors in 1996-97 and 2001-02 respectively.

Other past contributors include Dave Kelly, now rugby correspondent with the ''Irish Independent'' and Katherine Smyth a former associate producer with BBC Current Affairs. The ''College Tribune'' was tied to the national ''Sunday Tribune'' through its connections with Vincent Browne, but such links ended in 1999. The ''Tribune'' has also been distinguished on several occasions at national student media awards, particularly in sportswriting, where it has a strong tradition. The paper won the Student Newspaper of the Year at the USI/Irish Independent media awards in 1996. The then editor, Conor Lally, won Student Journalist of the Year in 1996. ''Tribune'' stalwart Peter Lahiff was a recipient of a Guardian Award for Diversity in 2003, the only Irish-based recipient of any ''Guardian'' award to date.

''College Tribune'' sections include news, features, opinion, music, film, sport and colour writing, and it is famous for the launch of the satirical page The Evil Gerald, a 'paper within a paper'. The ''Gerald'' was succeeded by ''The Turbine'' in 2003, and they have featured such satirical stories as the [[Provisional IRA]] dropping its pursuit of a United Ireland in favour of occupation of the [[Isle of Man]], and [[Osama Bin Laden]] stealing the Magic Door from [[Bosco]] which allowed him access to anywhere in the world.

====Radio and Television====

UCD also has a student radio station,  [http://www.belfieldfm.ie/ Belfield FM], broadcasting at selected times throughout the academic year across the campus on 107.8 FM and online at the station's website. The station is funded by the students' union and has nurtured current [[Raidió Teilifís Éireann|RTE]] presenters [[Ryan Tubridy]] and [[Rick O'Shea]]. BelfieldFM has become widely recognised as a leader in Irish student media.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}}.
&lt;ep&gt;
Belfield FM was a successor to UCD FM, which had been run out of the Students' Union entertainments office. Launched by [[Gearoid O'Connor]] and [[Enda Curran]] in 2000 along with senior producers [[Laura Fletcher]] (now of RTE), [[Barry Ward]] (now councillor for FG and Senior Counsel), [[Aidan Meaghen]], [[Eoghan Casey]], [[Daniel McConnell]] (now of Sunday Independent), it applied for and was granted capital funding of over €20,000 from the college to purchase studio equipment. 

At the beginning of the academic year 2005-2006, the creation of a student television station, titled Campus Television Network (CTN) was announced. The station began creating programmes in November 2006 and distributing them online, at its old [http://www.ucd.ie/campustv/ website], and across the campus in the student bars and student centre. CTN does not actually broadcast any shows themselves, either through the college network or via traditional analogue or satellite methods, rather it allows downloads and viewing of programmes on their website and distributes DVDs to on campus venues. It currently produces a variety of shows from their entertainments show 'Ent...This!' to their fashion shows 'Nu Look' and 'Slick'. CTN can be viewed on its new website at [http://www.ctn.ie www.ctn.ie].

====Historical Newspapers====
=====[[The Student]]=====
=====University Gazette=====
=====Confrontation=====
=====Campus=====
=====UCD News=====
=====Student Voice=====
=====Gobshout=====
=====Hibernia=====
=====Comhthrom Feinne=====
=====Comhar=====
===University College Dublin scarf colours===

{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width:90%; font-size: 0.86em&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | University College Dublin
|-
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|#000000}}
{{scarf|end}}
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
|-
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;margin: 0 auto; width:90%; font-size: 0.86em&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;3&quot; | University College Dublin, [[Colours Match|Colours]]
|-
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell|#66CCFF}}
{{scarf|end}}
| style=&quot;width: 33%;&quot; |
|-
|&amp;nbsp;
|-
! Sailing and Swimming Clubs
! [[University College Dublin RFC|Rugby Club]]
! Boat Club
|-
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell3|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell3|green}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|#66CCFF}}{{cell2|black}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell2|black}}{{cells|5|#66CCFF}}{{cell2|black}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell2|black}}{{cell3|#66CCFF}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cells|4|navy}}{{cell2|navy}}{{cell2|#66CCFF}}{{cell|yellow}}{{cell2|#66CCFF}}{{cells|4|navy}}{{cell2|navy}}
{{scarf|end}}
|-
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
! [[Agricultural Science]]
! [[Arts]]
! [[Chemical Engineering]]
|-
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell2|#800000}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell2|#800000}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#66CCFF}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|white}}{{cell|#000000}}{{cell|#66CCFF}}{{cell|#000000}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|#800000}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cells|6|#800000}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cell3|#800000}}
{{scarf|end}}
|-
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
! [[Civil and Environmental Engineering]]
! [[Commerce]]
! [[Electronic, Electrical, or Mechanical Engineering]]
|-
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|navy}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|navy}}{{cells|6|navy}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell|#800000}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|navy}}{{cell3|navy}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|black}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell3|black}}{{cells|6|red}}{{cell3|black}}{{cell|#FFCC00}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell3|black}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|green}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cells|6|green}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|white}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cell3|green}}
{{scarf|end}}
|-
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
! [[Law]]
! [[Medicine]]
! [[Radiography]]
|-
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell2|green}}{{cell|#9C2770}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|#9C2770}}{{cell2|green}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|black}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|red}}{{cell2|black}}{{cells|6|black}}{{cell2|black}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|red}}{{cell3|black}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|black}}{{cells|6|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|black}}{{cell3|black}}
{{scarf|end}}
|-
| &amp;nbsp;
|-
! [[Science]]
! [[Social Science]]
! [[Veterinary Medicine]]
|-
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|black}}{{cells|6|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|#87CEFA}}{{cell|red}}{{cell|green}}{{cell|black}}{{cell3|black}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|green}}{{cell2|white}}{{cell3|purple}}{{cells|6|purple}}{{cell3|purple}}{{cell2|white}}{{cell3|green}}
{{scarf|end}}
|
{{scarf|start}}
{{cell3|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|blue}}{{cell|yellow}}{{cell|blue}}{{cell|black}}{{cells|6|black}}{{cell|black}}{{cell|blue}}{{cell|yellow}}{{cell|blue}}{{cell|black}}{{cell3|black}}
{{scarf|end}}
|}

==Presidents of UCD==
* Dr Denis Coffey, Dean of Medicine (1910&amp;ndash;1940)
* Dr [[Arthur W. Conway]], (1940&amp;ndash;1947)
* Dr [[Michael Tierney (Professor of Greek)|Michael Tierney]] (1947&amp;ndash;1964)
* Dr Jerimiah Hogan, (1964&amp;ndash;1972)
* Dr Thomas Murphy, (1972&amp;ndash;1985)
* Dr [[Patrick Masterson]], (1986&amp;ndash;1993)
* Dr [[Art Cosgrove]], (1994&amp;ndash;2003)
* Dr [[Hugh R. Brady]], (2004 - )

== UCD in popular culture ==
=== In literature ===
[[James Joyce]]’s novel ''[[A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man]]'' is partially set in UCD (when it was sited on [[Earlsfort Terrace]]) where [[Stephen Dedalus]] is enrolled as a student. Joyce's posthumously-published autobiographical novel ''[[Stephen Hero]]'' contains stories of his time in UCD. [[Brian O'Nolan|Flann O'Brien]]’s novel [[At Swim-Two-Birds]] features a UCD student who writes a meta-novel wherein the author is put on trial by the characters of his novel.[[Maeve Binchy]]'s novel, ''[[Circle of Friends (novel)|Circle of Friends]]'', deals with three female friends starting college in UCD in the 1950s. However, shots of Trinity College were used in the ''[[Circle of Friends (1995 film)|1995 film]]''.  The second [[Ross O'Carroll-Kelly]] novel, ''The Teenage Dirtbag Years'', follows Ross as he enters UCD.

=== In music ===
[[Christy Moore]] wrote a tongue in cheek song about UCD's [[Literary and Historical Society (University College Dublin)|Literary and Historical Society]] called &quot;The Auditor of the L and H&quot;. Johnny Jurex &amp; The Punk Pistols, predecessors to Rocky De Valera &amp; The Gravediggers had a song called &quot;Anarchy in Belfield&quot; which they played at their only gig during Rag Week in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.irishrock.org/irodb/bands/jurex.html&lt;/ref&gt;

=== In film and television ===
[[Conor McPherson]]'s third film ''Saltwater'' was filmed in Belfield, UCD. In ''[[Boston Legal]]'', Season 2, Episode 21 &quot;Word Salad Day&quot;, there is a reference to a study from UCD that &quot;found that the effects of divorce on children are far more damaging than the death of a parent&quot; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.boston-legal.org/script/BL02x21.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Education in the Republic of Ireland]]
* [[List of universities in the Republic of Ireland]]
* [[List of University College Dublin people]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.ucd.ie}}
*[http://ucdhiddenhistory.wordpress.com/ Hidden History of UCD - Blog dedicated to collating the radical and social history of UCD]
*[http://www.ucdrugby.com UCD Rugby]
*[http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/15200a.htm Catholic encyclopedia: University College Dublin]
*[http://www.ucdsu.net Students' Union website]
*[http://www.ucd.ie/observer/ The University Observer Online]
*[http://www.ucd.ie/tribune/ The College Tribune Online]
*[http://acollegemiscellany.com/scarves/nui/ University Scarf Colours]

{{Schools and colleges in County Dublin}}
{{UNICA}}
{{Universitas 21}}
{{CESAER}}
{{IrishUni}}
{{University College Dublin}}

{{Coord|53|18|30|N|6|13|20|W|region:IE_type:edu|display=title}}

[[Category:University College Dublin| ]]
[[Category:National University of Ireland]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in the Republic of Ireland]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1908]]
[[Category:Education in Dun Laoghaire-Rathdown]]

[[da:University College Dublin]]
[[de:University College Dublin]]
[[es:University College Dublin]]
[[fr:University College Dublin]]
[[ga:An Coláiste Ollscoile, Baile Átha Cliath]]
[[it:University College Dublin]]
[[nl:Nationale Universiteit van Ierland, Dublin]]
[[ja:ユニバーシティ・カレッジ・ダブリン]]
[[no:University College Dublin]]
[[ru:Дублинский университетский колледж]]
[[zh:都柏林大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
