<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="266226" ns="0" title="Cough medicine"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">:''Cough syrup redirects here. For the Young the Giant song, see [[Cough Syrup (song)]].

[[Image:Cough medicine.jpg|thumb|Cough medicine often contains cough suppressants or expectorants.]]

A '''cough medicine''' (or '''linctus''', when in syrup form) is a medicinal [[medication|drug]] used in an attempt to treat [[cough]]ing and related conditions. For dry coughs, treatment with cough suppressants ('''antitussives''') may be attempted to suppress the body's urge to cough. However, in productive coughs (coughs that produce [[phlegm]]), treatment is instead attempted with [[expectorants]] (typically [[guaifenesin]], in most commercial medications) in an attempt to loosen [[mucus]] from the [[respiratory tract]].

There however is no good evidence for or against the use of these medications in those with a cough.&lt;ref name=Cochrane08/&gt; Even though they are used by 10% of American children weekly, they are not recommended in children 6 years of age or younger due to lack of evidence showing effect, and concerns of harm.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.cfp.ca/cgi/content/full/55/11/1081 |title=Use of over-the-counter cough and cold medications in children|first2=RD|last2=Goldman|author=Shefrin and Goldman|volume=55|issue=11|date=November 2009|pages=1081–1083|journal=Canadian Family Physician |pmid=19910592|pmc=2776795}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2007/HEALTH/10/19/coldmed.fda/index.html|title=FDA panel: No cold medicines to children under 6|work=[[CNN]]|accessdate=2009-11-27|location=Washington}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Examples==

===Pharmaceuticals===
;Dextromethorphan
[[Dextromethorphan]] (DXM) may be modestly effective in decreasing cough in adults with viral upper respiratory infections.  In children however it has not been found to be effective.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19874728&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Dealleaume L, Tweed B, Neher JO |title=Do OTC remedies relieve cough in acute upper respiratory infections? |journal=J Fam Pract |volume=58 |issue=10 |pages=559a–c |year=2009 |month=October |pmid=19874728 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Codeine
[[Codeine]] was once viewed as the gold standard in cough suppressants. Some recent [[placebo]]-controlled trials have found however that it may be no better than placebo for some etiologies including acute cough in children.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Bolser DC, Davenport PW |title=Codeine and cough: an ineffective gold standard |journal=Current Opinion in Allergy and Clinical Immunology |volume=7 |issue=1 |pages=32–6 |year=2007 |month=February |pmid=17218808 |pmc=2921574 |doi=10.1097/ACI.0b013e3280115145 |url=http://journals.lww.com/co-allergy/Abstract/2007/02000/Codeine_and_cough__an_ineffective_gold_standard.7.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=CFP10/&gt; It is thus not recommended for children.&lt;ref name=CFP10&gt;{{cite journal|last=Goldman|first=RD|title=Codeine for acute cough in children|journal=Canadian Family Physician|date=2010 Dec|volume=56|issue=12|pages=1293–4|pmid=21156892|pmc=3001921}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- added eph section below partly to have a case to get rid of orphan tag on mollipect article! --&gt;
;Ephedrine
[[Ephedrine]] is used in cough medicine, such as [[Mollipect]], in some countries.
;Others
Other commercially available cough treatments have not been shown to be effective in viral upper respiratory infections, including in adults: [[antihistamines]], antihistamine-decongestant combinations, [[Benzonatate]], and [[guaifenesin]]; and in children: antihistamines, [[decongestants]] or combinations of these.&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19874728&quot; /&gt;

===Alternative medicine===
[[Honey]] may be a minimally effective cough treatment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2007/12/071203164750.htm |title=Honey A Better Option For Childhood Cough Than Over The Counter Medications |accessdate=2009-11-27 |date=2007-12-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; However a Cochrane review found insufficient evidence to recommend for or against its use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Oduwole O, Meremikwu MM, Oyo-Ita A, Udoh EE |title=Honey for acute cough in children |journal=Cochrane Database Syst Rev |volume= |issue=1 |pages=CD007094 |year=2010 |pmid=20091616 |doi=10.1002/14651858.CD007094.pub2 |url= |editor1-last=Oduwole |editor1-first=Olabisi}}&lt;/ref&gt; The evidence is a single study of Buckwheat honey given before bedtime which provided better cough relief at night and improved sleep difficulty in children more than no treatment or [[dextromethorphan]] based over-the-counter cough medicine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.consumeraffairs.com/news04/2007/12/honey_cough.html|title=Honey May Help Relieve Children’s Cough|date=December 3, 2007|publisher=consumeraffairs.com|accessdate=14 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://live.psu.edu/story/27584|title=Honey proves a better option for childhood cough than OTCs|date=December 3, 2007|work=Penn State Live|accessdate=14 September 2010|location=Hershey, Pa.}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, honey's use as a cough treatment has been linked on several occasions to infantile [[botulism]] and as such should not be used in children less than one year old.&lt;ref name=&quot;ap01&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|coauthors=Sung, Valerie; Cranswick, Noel |title=Cough and cold remedies for children |journal=Australian Prescriber |issue=32 |pages=122–4 |url=http://www.australianprescriber.com/magazine/32/5/122/4/ |accessdate=27 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many alternative treatments are used to treat the [[common cold]]. However, a 2007 review states that, &quot;Complementary and alternative therapies (i.e., [[Echinacea]], [[vitamin C]], and [[zinc]]) are not recommended for treating common cold symptoms... Vitamin C prophylaxis may modestly reduce the duration and severity of the common cold in the general population and may reduce the incidence of the illness in persons exposed to physical and environmental stresses.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Simasek M, Blandino DA |title=Treatment of the common cold |journal=Am Fam Physician |volume=75 |issue=4 |pages=515–20 |year=2007 |month=February |pmid=17323712 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2009 review found that the evidence supporting the effectiveness of [[zinc]] is mixed with respect to cough,&lt;ref name=&quot;pmid19874728&quot; /&gt; and a 1999 [[Cochrane review]] found the evidence of benefit in the common cold inconclusive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Marshall I |title=Zinc for the common cold |journal=Cochrane Database Syst Rev |volume= |issue=2 |pages=CD001364 |year=2000 |pmid=10796643 |doi=10.1002/14651858.CD001364 |url= |last2=Marshall |first2=Ian|editor1-last=Marshall|editor1-first=Ian}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, a 2003 review concluded: &quot;Clinical trial data support the value of zinc in reducing the duration and severity of symptoms of the common cold when administered within 24 hours of the onset of common cold symptoms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Hulisz D |title=Efficacy of zinc against common cold viruses: an overview |journal=J Am Pharm Assoc (2003) |volume=44 |issue=5 |pages=594–603 |year=2004 |pmid=15496046 |doi= 10.1331/1544-3191.44.5.594.Hulisz|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nasally applied zinc gel may lead to long-term or permanent loss of smell. The FDA therefore discourages its use.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/SafetyInformation/SafetyAlertsforHumanMedicalProducts/ucm166996.htm |title=Zicam Cold Remedy Nasal Products (Cold Remedy Nasal Gel, Cold Remedy Nasal Swabs, and Cold Remedy Swabs, Kids Size) |work= |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A review of sixteen trials of [[echinacea]] was done by the [[Cochrane Collaboration]] in 2006 and found mixed results.  All three trials that looked at prevention were negative. Comparisons of echinacea as treatment found a significant effect in nine trials, a trend in one, and no difference in six trials. The authors state in their conclusion: &quot;Echinacea preparations tested in clinical trials differ greatly. There is some evidence that preparations based on the aerial parts of Echinacea purpurea might be effective for the early treatment of colds in adults but results are not fully consistent. Beneficial effects of other Echinacea preparations, and for preventative purposes might exist but have not been shown in independently replicated, rigorous randomized trials.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;Linde K, Barrett B, Wölkart K, Bauer R, Melchart D 2006 CD000530&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Linde K, Barrett B, Wölkart K, Bauer R, Melchart D |title=Echinacea for preventing and treating the common cold |journal=Cochrane Database Syst Rev |volume= |issue=1 |pages=CD000530 |year=2006 |pmid=16437427 |doi=10.1002/14651858.CD000530.pub2 |url=|editor1-last=Linde|editor1-first=Klaus}}&lt;/ref&gt; A review in 2007 found an overall benefit from echinacea for the common cold&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Shah SA, Sander S, White CM, Rinaldi M, Coleman CI |title=Evaluation of echinacea for the prevention and treatment of the common cold: a meta-analysis |journal=Lancet Infect Dis |volume=7 |issue=7 |pages=473–80 |year=2007 |month=July |pmid=17597571 |doi=10.1016/S1473-3099(07)70160-3 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; however further analysis found problems with the interpretations of this review.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=von Maxen A, Schoenhoefer PS |title=Benefit of echinacea for the prevention and treatment of the common cold? |journal=Lancet Infect Dis |volume=8 |issue=6 |pages=346–7; author reply 347–8 |year=2008 |month=June |pmid=18501849 |doi=10.1016/S1473-3099(08)70107-5 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While a number of plants and Chinese herbs have been purported to ease cold symptoms, including [[ginger]], [[garlic]], [[hyssop]], [[mullein]], and others, scientific studies have either not been done or have been found inconclusive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Linde K, Barrett B, Wölkart K, Bauer R, Melchart D 2006 CD000530&quot;/&gt;

==Toxicity==
{{Main|Toxic cough syrup}}
According to the [[New York Times]], at least eight mass poisonings have occurred as a result of counterfeit cough syrup, substituting inexpensive [[diethylene glycol]] in place of [[glycerin]]. In May 2007, 365 deaths were reported in [[Panama]], which were associated with cough syrup containing diethylene glycol.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/06/world/06poison.html | work=The New York Times | title=From China to Panama, a Trail of Poisoned Medicine | first1=Walt | last1=Bogdanich | first2=Jake | last2=Hooker | date=2007-05-06 | accessdate=2010-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Efficacy==
The efficacy of cough medication is questionable, particularly in children.&lt;ref&gt;Medsafe cough and cold grouphttp://www.medsafe.govt.nz/hot/alerts/CoughandCold/Minutes2CoughandCold.asp&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;healthminutes1&quot;&gt;{{cite video |people=Swan, Norman |date=20 June 2010 |title=Health Mninutes - Cough and Cold Medicines |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rP_yx-2LDJo |accessdate=27 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A 2008 Cochrane review concluded that &quot;There is no good evidence for or against the effectiveness of OTC medicines in acute cough&quot;.&lt;ref name=Cochrane08&gt;{{cite journal |author=Smith SM, Schroeder K, Fahey T |title=Over-the-counter medications for acute cough in children and adults in ambulatory settings |journal=Cochrane Database Syst Rev |volume= |issue=1 |pages=CD001831 |year=2008 |pmid=18253996|doi=10.1002/14651858.CD001831.pub3 |url= |editor1-last=Smith |editor1-first=Susan M}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2001, a [[meta-analysis]] indicated that some cough medicines may be no more effective than [[placebo]]s for acute coughs in adults, including coughs related to upper respiratory tract infections.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Knut Schroeder and Tom Fahey  |title=Systematic review of randomised controlled trials of over the counter cough medicines for acute cough in adults  |journal=[[British Medical Journal]]  |year=2002  |volume=324  |pages=329&amp;ndash;331  |url=http://bmj.bmjjournals.com/cgi/content/full/324/7333/329 | pmid=11834560  |doi=10.1136/bmj.324.7333.329  |issue=7333  |pmc=65295}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2006, the [[American College of Chest Physicians]] published a guideline for [[Pertussis|whooping cough]], a cough that is caused by bacteria and can last for months. The guideline pointed out that available cough medicines are not designed to treat whooping cough or its causative bacterium.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release|publisher = [[American College of Chest Physicians]]|date = January 9, 2006|title = New Cough Guidelines Urge Adult Whooping Cough Vaccine; Many OTC Medications Not Recommended for Cough Treatment|url =http://www.chestnet.org/about/press/releases/2006/010906a.php}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the efficacy is inconclusive for children over 2 years of age, a number of factors including accidental overdoses and well-documented adverse effects suggested caution in the pediatric prescription of cough syrups and medicines.&lt;ref&gt;Sung, Valerie and Cranswick, Noel (2009). &quot;Cough and cold remedies for children&quot;. ''Australian Prescriber'', Vol. 32. pp 122-124. Available at http://www.australianprescriber.com/upload/pdf/articles/1047.pdf.&lt;/ref&gt; No over the counter cough medicines have been found to be effective in cases of pneumonia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Chang CC, Cheng AC, Chang AB |title=Over-the-counter (OTC) medications to reduce cough as an adjunct to antibiotics for acute pneumonia in children and adults |journal=Cochrane Database Syst Rev |volume= |issue=4 |pages=CD006088 |year=2007 |pmid=17943884 |doi=10.1002/14651858.CD006088.pub2 |url=|editor1-last=Chang|editor1-first=Christina C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Cough drop]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.cnn.com/HEALTH/library/DI/00052.html Cough medicines not helpful] - from [http://www.cnn.com CNN.com]

{{Major drug groups}}
{{Cough and cold preparations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cough Medicine}}
[[Category:Antitussives|*]]

[[ca:Antitussigen]]
[[de:Antitussivum]]
[[es:Antitusígeno]]
[[fr:Antitussif]]
[[nl:Hoestdrank]]
[[ja:鎮咳去痰薬]]
[[no:Hostemedisin]]
[[pl:Leki przeciwkaszlowe]]
[[pt:Antitússico]]
[[ru:Противокашлевые средства]]
[[sl:Antitusik]]
[[fi:Yskänlääke]]
[[sv:Hostmedicin]]
[[wuu:咳嗽药]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
