<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2665890" ns="0" title="Marlinspike Hall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
[[Image:Marlinspike.jpg|thumb|250px|Tintin, Captain Haddock and Snowy approach Marlinspike Hall.]]
[[Image:Cheverny 01.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[Château de Cheverny]] was used as a model for Marlinspike Hall. The two outermost wings are not present, but the remaining central tower and two wings are identical.]]
[[Image:Moulinsart.jpg|thumb|200px|Simulation of Cheverny with the outer wings removed]]

'''Marlinspike Hall''' (''Le château de Moulinsart'' in the original [[French language|French]]) is [[Captain Haddock]]'s [[country house]] in [[Hergé]]'s [[comic book]] series ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''.

The hall is modeled after the central section of the [[Château de Cheverny]]. The French name is derived from [[Sart-Moulin]], a village near [[Braine-l'Alleud]] in [[Walloon Brabant]], [[Belgium]]; in an allusion to the Haddock family's maritime history, the hall's English name refers to the [[Marlinspike]], a tool used in [[seamanship]] to [[rope splicing|splice ropes]].

Marlinspike Hall first appears in ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'' as the home of the story's villains, the [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#The Bird brothers|Bird Brothers]]. At the end of ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]'', the manor (found to have been built by an illustrious ancestor of Haddock's) is purchased by [[Professor Calculus]] on behalf of the Captain; the fabled treasure itself is found hidden in the manor's old chapel, in the cellars. In the following years, Marlinspike provides a home base for Tintin and Haddock in between their various adventures. In ''[[The Castafiore Emerald]]'', virtually all of the action takes place in the hall, its grounds, or the surrounding countryside.

Marlinspike Hall is presented as a large and luxurious dwelling adorned with numerous works of art, antique furniture, and a gallery of the Haddock family's treasures. The grounds comprise a park with extensive woodlands, wide lawns, a rose garden, a high surrounding wall, at least two gates, a neighbouring meadow, and at least one adjacent building (used by Professor Calculus as a laboratory in ''[[The Calculus Affair]]'' ). The size of the house and park would appear to require a number of domestic and gardening staff but only one - the faithful [[Nestor (Tintin character)|Nestor]], who serves as butler to the Hall - is ever seen, although a gardener is mentioned once in the last pages of ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]''.

In ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'' Calculus blows up parts of the hall while conducting experiments to try and find an antidote to a chemical that causes fuel to become explosive.

The Belgian corporation organized to manage the rights to Hergé's work (principally ''Tintin'') is called Moulinsart [[S.A. (corporation)|S.A.]] after the name of Marlinspike in the original French.

==Location==
The original English language translators of the ''Tintin'' books caused some confusion by giving the address of Marlinspike Hall as &quot;Marlinshire, England&quot; in ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]''. However details such as traffic travelling on the right hand side of the road and the appearance of the Marlinspike police (who wear the black and red uniforms of the [[Belgian Gendarmerie]]) confirm that Hergé's intention was to locate the Hall in his native Belgium. Moreover, it is explained in ''The Red Rackham's Treasure'' that the Manor was built by an ancestor of Captain Haddock's, the Chevalier François de Hadoque, a Ship-of-the-Line Captain in [[La Royale]] under King [[Louis XIV]].

==Translations==
* [[Arabic language| Arabic]]: Mulan
* [[Bengali language|Bengali]]: মার্লিনস্পাইক (Marlinspike) 
* [[Catalan language|Catalan]]: Molins de dalt
* [[Chinese language|Chinese]]: 马林斯派克
* [[Danish language|Danish]]: Møllenborg Slot (literally: Millburg Castle)
* [[Dutch language|Dutch]]: Kasteel Molensloot
* [[Finnish language|Finnish]]: Moulinsartin linna
* [[French language|French]]: Château de Moulinsart (original)
* [[German language|German]]: Schloss Mühlenhof
* [[Icelandic language|Icelandic]]: Myllusetur
* [[Italian language|Italian]]: Castello di Moulinsart
* [[Persian language|Persian]]: کاخ مولنسار (Ka'kh-e-Moulansar)
* [[Polish language|Polish]]: Księżymłyn
* [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]: Castelo de Moulinsart
* [[Russian language|Russian]]: Замок Муленсар
* [[Spanish language|Spanish]]: Castillo de Moulinsart, Castillo del Molino, Mansión Pasador
* [[Swedish language|Swedish]]: Moulinsarts slott
* [[Turkish language|Turkish]]: Mulensar Şatosu

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

[[Category:Tintin locations]]
[[Category:Fictional houses]]

[[da:Møllenborg]]
[[es:Moulinsart]]
[[eu:Moulinsart]]
[[fa:مارلین اسپایک]]
[[fr:Château de Moulinsart]]
[[gl:Moulinsart]]
[[id:Marlinspike Hall]]
[[is:Myllusetur]]
[[nl:Molensloot]]
[[pt:Moulinsart]]
[[ru:Муленсар]]
[[sv:Moulinsart]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
