<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2676075" ns="0" title="WSJU-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{update|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WSJU-TV|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = |
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = PlayTV|
  analog                   = 30 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])|
  digital                  = 31 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])|
  subchannels              = TIVA, FOX, PETTV, TELEMICRO, FRANCE24
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = |
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = [[1984]]|
  location                 = [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''S'''an '''Ju'''an|
  former_callsigns         = WRWR-TV (1984-2000)|
  former_channel_numbers   = |
  owner                    = Aerco Broadcasting Corporation|
  licensee                 = |
  sister_stations          = |
  former_affiliations      = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1984-1986)&lt;br&gt;[[Univision]] (1986-1991)&lt;br&gt;[[Dark (broadcasting)|silent]] (1991-1999)&lt;br&gt;[[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1999-2008)|
  effective_radiated_power = 2630 [[kilowatt|kW]] (analog)&lt;br&gt;66 kW (digital)|
  HAAT                     = 287 m (analog)&lt;br&gt;267 m (digital)|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = 4077|
  coordinates              = {{coord|18|16|23|N|66|5|35|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.playtvpr.com|
}}

'''WSJU-TV''' is a full-power television station in [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]] transmitting over channel 30. During most of the 2000s, the station's programming mostly consisted of music videos. It is carried by all three cable systems and covers 80 percent of the national territory.

Before the year [[2000]], the station's [[callsign]] was WRWR-TV.  When the station first started, it was branded as ''Cinema 30 TV'' and was broadcasting older movies, then in 1986, became an affiliate of Univisión.  The station went off the air around 1991.  It then reappeared around 1999-2000.

In august 2009, WSJU_TV became the first national television station to broadcast over-the-air international television stations from the Dominican Republic. WSJU TV became the dominant television station for young-adults by airing music videos in partnership with the major record companies (Sony, Universal, etc). In 2010, WSJU TV introduced new television stations that proved to have significant value to the tv viewers.

WSJU also developed new media platforms to compliment its electronic media offering. Adding Iphone, Android, Internet, Games and many more digital platforms that now receive WSJU's host of stations regardless of the viewers locations. PlayTV also allows viewers to send text messages to friends, which are displayed on air. PlayTV differentiates itself though, in that they assign numeric codes to each music videos, and viewers can send a text message to the station using those codes to request a particular video.

WSJU reaches 80 percent of the 1,000,000 households directly over-the-air and 100% of the territory via the three major cable providers. 

==Digital television==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! Programming
|-
| 31.1 || PLAYTV
|-
| 31.2 || TIVA
|-
| 31.3 || FOX
|-
| 31.4 || PETTV
|-
| 31.5 || TELEMICRO
|-
| 31.6 || FRANCE24
|-
|}

== External links ==

*{{TVQ|WSJU-TV}}
*{{BIA|WSJU|TV|TV}}

{{Puerto Rico TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wsju-Tv}}
[[Category:Television stations in Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:San Juan, Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:Channel 30 TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 31 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1984]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
