<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="267730" ns="0" title="Mike Schmidt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Mike Schmidt
|image=Mike Schmidt.jpg
|position=[[Third baseman]]
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1949|9|27}}
|birth_place=[[Dayton, Ohio]]
|death_date=
|debutdate=September 12
|debutyear=1972
|debutteam=Philadelphia Phillies
|finaldate=May 28
|finalyear=1989
|finalteam=Philadelphia Phillies
|stat1label=[[Batting average]]
|stat1value=.267
|stat2label=[[Home runs]]
|stat2value=548
|stat3label=[[Runs batted in]]
|stat3value=1,595
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[Philadelphia Phillies]] ({{By|1972}}–{{By|1989}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1980}})
*1980 [[World Series MVP]]
*12× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] ([[1974 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1974]], [[1976 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1976]], [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977]], [[1979 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1979]], [[1980 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1980]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]], [[1982 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1982]], [[1983 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1983]], [[1984 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1984]], [[1986 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1986]], [[1987 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1987]], [[1989 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1989]])
*8× [[List of Major League Baseball home run champions|National League Home Run Champion]] ({{by|1974}}, {{by|1975}}, {{by|1976}}, {{by|1980}}, {{by|1981}}, {{by|1983}}, {{by|1984}}, {{by|1986}})
*4× [[National League]] RBI Leader (1980, 1981, 1984, 1986)
*10× [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1976, {{by|1977}}, {{by|1978}}, {{by|1979}}, 1980, 1981, {{by|1982}}, 1983, 1984, 1986)
*6× [[Silver Slugger Award]] winner (1980, 1981, 1982, 1983, 1984, 1986)
*3× [[NL MVP]] (1980, 1981, 1986)
*5× NL Player of the Month (April 1976, July 1979, May 1980, August 1981, July 1982)
*1983 [[Lou Gehrig Memorial Award]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball hitters with four home runs in one game|4 home runs in one game]] (April 17, 1976)
*[[Philadelphia Phillies#Retired numbers|Philadelphia Phillies #20]] retired
* [[Major League Baseball All-Century Team]]
* [[Major League Baseball All-Time Team]]
|hofdate={{By|1995}}
|hofvote=96.5% (first ballot)
}}
'''Michael Jack Schmidt''' ({{IPA-en|ˈʃmɪt|pron}}; born September 27, 1949) is a [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum|Hall of Fame]] [[third baseman]] popularly considered among the greatest third basemen in the history of [[Major League Baseball]]. He played his entire [[career]] for the [[Philadelphia Phillies]].

Schmidt had an unusual batting stance, turning his back somewhat to the [[pitcher]] and waving his posterior while waiting for the pitch. By standing far back in the batter's box, he made it impossible to jam him by pitching inside. Schmidt was one of the best athletes of his time; teammate [[Pete Rose]] once said, ''&quot;To have his body, I'd trade him mine and my wife's, and I'd throw in some cash.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Pete Rose: A Biography  |last=Jordan |first=David M.  |authorlink= |coauthors= |year= |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |location= |isbn= |page=91 |pages= |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=dYjWQWvwI0kC&amp;pg=PA91&amp;lpg=PA91 |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early days==
Upon graduation from [[Dayton_Public_Schools,_Montgomery_County,_Ohio#Former_school_buildings|Fairview High School]] in [[Dayton, Ohio]] in {{by|1967}}, Schmidt attended [[Ohio University]] in [[Athens, Ohio|Athens]], where he joined [[Beta Theta Pi]] [[Fraternity]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mikeschmidt.com/|title=Mike Schmidt Official Website}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schmidt led the [[Ohio Bobcats]] [[baseball]] team to the [[College World Series]] in {{by|1970}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://espn.go.com/sportsnation/chat/_/id/38777|title=Chat with Mike Schmidt|publisher=[[ESPN]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was drafted by the Phillies in the second round of the [[1971 Major League Baseball Draft]] with the 30th overall pick.

On June 11, {{by|1971}}, he was signed by [[Scout (sport)|scout]] [[Tony Lucadello]], who had followed him since [[Little League Baseball]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=This Scout Was Truly Great At Judging A Player's Heart |author=Frank Dolson |newspaper=Philadelphia Inquirer |date=May 10, 1989|url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Six days later, Schmidt made his professional debut in an exhibition game between the Phillies and the [[Reading Phillies]] in [[FirstEnergy Stadium|Reading]]. Schmidt played the whole game at [[shortstop]] for the Phillies and hit a game-winning [[home run]] against Reading.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Palmer Doesn't Mind The Exhibition Games |author=Duke DeLuca |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=ZuSUVyMx-TgC&amp;dat=19710618&amp;printsec=frontpage |newspaper=Reading Eagles |date=1971-06-18 |accessdate=2011-03-09|pages=26, 28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Along with shortstop and third base, Schmidt also played some [[second baseman|second base]] in the minors.

Schmidt spent two seasons in the Phillies' [[farm system]], where he batted .263 with 34 home runs and 122 [[runs batted in]]. He received a September call-up to the Phillies in {{by|1972}}, and made his major league debut against the [[New York Mets]] on September 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/PHI/PHI197209120.shtml|title=New York Mets 4, Philadelphia Phillies 3|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=September 12, 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four days later, Schmidt ended [[Montreal Expos]] [[pitcher]] [[Balor Moore]]'s streak of 25 scoreless innings pitched with his first career home run.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/PHI/PHI197209160.shtml|title=Philadelphia Phillies 3, Montreal Expos 1|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=September 16, 1972}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Philadelphia Phillies==
Following the 1972 season, the Phillies dealt third baseman [[Don Money]] to the [[Milwaukee Brewers]] to open a spot for Schmidt on their [[infield]]. Schmidt batted only .196 with 136 strikeouts his first full season, however, he did demonstrate his power potential with 18 home runs.

Schmidt's [[batting average]] climbed as high as .356 in {{by|1974}} to received the first of his twelve [[All-Star]] nods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/NLS/NLS197407230.shtml|title=1974 All-Star Game|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=July 23, 1974}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 10, Schmidt hit a ball into a public address speaker suspended 117 feet above and 329 feet away from home plate in the [[Astrodome]] in [[Houston, Texas]]. The ball then fell to the field, and by the Astrodome's ground rules, it remained in play. Schmidt was held to a [[single (baseball)|single]], and the runners on first and second each advanced just one base. It is believed that had it not hit the speaker, the ball would have carried beyond 500 feet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Gutman|first=Bill|title=Baseball's Belters: Jackson Schmidt Parker Brett|pages=80–81|publisher=Ace Books|year=1981}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the season, Schmidt finished sixth in [[National League]] [[Most Valuable Player]] balloting as he batted .282 with 106 RBIs and a league leading 36 home runs to help the Phillies avoid a last place finish in the [[National League East]] for the first time since {{by|1970}}. His 404 [[Baseball statistics|assists]] in 1974 remain a record for third basemen. He also filled in at shortstop and [[first base]].

Schmidt's batting average hovered below .200 through the month of May {{by|1975}}. Solid months of July and August saw his average rise to .249 by the end of the season as he led the league in home runs for the second year in a row with 38. Schmidt started the {{by|1976}} season off by hitting twelve home runs in Philadelphia's first fifteen games, including four in one game on April 17,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/CHN/CHN197604170.shtml|title=Philadelphia Phillies 18, Chicago Cubs 16|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=April 17, 1976}}&lt;/ref&gt; a feat accomplished only 15 times in the history of baseball. For the season, Schmidt drove in 107 [[run (baseball)|runs]], and led the league in home runs for the third year in a row (38), and won his first of ten Gold Gloves to lead the Phillies to their first division crown since division play started in {{by|1969}}.

The Phillies captured the NL east crown three years in a row, however, the were swept by [[Cincinnati Reds|Cincinnati's]] &quot;[[Big Red Machine]]&quot; in 1976, and lost to the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]] in {{by|1977}} and {{by|1978}}. On December 5, 1978, the Phillies signed Pete Rose as a [[free agent]], temporarily making Rose the highest-paid athlete in team sports when they signed him to a four-year, $3.2-million contract. With Rose on board, the Phillies were early favorites to repeat as division winners in {{by|1979}}. Instead, the Phillies finished the season at 84-78, and in fourth place in NL East. For his part, Schmidt broke the club record for home runs in a season with 45, eclipsing [[Chuck Klein]]'s 43 hit in {{by|1929}}.

===National League MVP===
On October 3, {{by|1980}}, the Phillies went into [[Montreal]] tied with the Expos for first place in the NL East. With a [[sacrifice fly]] in the first, and a solo home run in the sixth, Schmidt led the Phillies to a 2-1 victory to capture first place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/MON/MON198010030.shtml|title=Philadelphia Phillies 2, Montreal Expos 1|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=October 3, 1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; A day later, Schmidt hit his 48th home run of the season in the 11th inning to give the Phillies the 6-4 [[extra innings]] victory over the Expos, and clinch the division.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/MON/MON198010040.shtml|title=Philadelphia Phillies 6, Montreal Expos 4|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=October 4, 1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; His 48 home runs broke his own team record, and led the National League by a margin of thirteen over his nearest competitor (His home run mark would stand for 26 years until [[first baseman]] and {{by|2006}} National League MVP [[Ryan Howard]] hit 58 in 2006). Coupled with a league leading 121 RBIs, Schmidt was a unanimous choice for the [[MLB Most Valuable Player award|National League's Most Valuable Player Award]]. 

The Phillies defeated the [[Houston Astros]] in the [[1980 National League Championship Series]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/postseason/1980_NLCS.shtml|title=1980 National League Championship Series|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=October 7-12, 1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; to reach the [[World Series]] for the third time in franchise history. Though Schmidt had just a career .191 post-season batting average with no home runs and five RBIs, his bat came alive in the {{wsy|1980}} World Series, hitting two homers and driving in seven runs against the [[Kansas City Royals]] to earn him the [[World Series MVP Award]]. Following the World Series, Schmidt and four of his Phillies teammates appeared on [[Family Feud]] for one week in 1980. He, [[Larry Bowa]], [[Garry Maddox]], [[Dick Ruthven]] and [[Del Unser]] took on five members of the Kansas City Royals: [[Dennis Leonard]], [[Dan Quisenberry]], [[Paul Splittorff]], [[John Wathan]] and [[Willie Wilson (baseball)|Willie Wilson]].

Schmidt's best season may have been the strike shortened {{by|1981}} season. His 31 home runs were seven more than anyone else in the league. He also led the NL in [[runs scored]], RBIs, [[total bases]] and walks, and sett personal highs in batting average, on-base average and slugging average. He won his second consecutive MVP award, this time with 96% of the vote.

The Phillies led the NL East by 3.5 games when the [[1981 Major League Baseball strike]] hit. As a result, the Phillies were named NL East champions for the first half of the season, however, they lost to the second half champion Montreal Expos in the [[1981 National League Division Series]].

In {{by|1983}}, in celebration of the team's 100th anniversary, Schmidt was voted by fans the greatest player in the history of the franchise. That year, he led the league in home runs for the sixth time in his career to lead the Phillies back to the post season. Schmidt led his team with a .467 batting average and scored five runs as they defeated the Los Angeles Dodgers in the [[1983 National League Championship Series]]. It was, however, a way different story against the [[Baltimore Orioles]] in the [[1983 World Series]]. The Phillies were held to a .195 team batting average; Schmidt went just 1-for-20 with a single.

Following the 1983 season, the Phillies dealt Pete Rose to the Montreal Expos. [[Tim Corcoran]] and [[Len Matuszek]] platooned at first in {{by|1984}}, however, neither provided to the offensive spark Rose did. In {{by|1985}}, Schmidt was moved to [[first baseman|first base]] from late May through the end of the season with [[Rick Schu]] assuming third base duties. The Phillies finished with a below .500 record for the first time since 1974.

In {{by|1986}}, the Phillies moved [[outfielder]] [[Von Hayes]] to first base and shifted Schmidt back to his natural position. He responded by winning his third MVP award, a record for third basemen,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Thomas|last=Rogers|title=Schmidt Joins an Elite Club|page=D27|newspaper=[[New York Times]]|date=November 20, 1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a league leading 37 home runs and 119 RBIs.

===Retirement===
[[Image:Mike Schmidt HR vs. Cincinnati Reds at Veterans Stadium July 20, 1987.jpg|thumb|325px|Schmidt homers against the Reds on July 20, 1987, at the Vet]]
Trailing the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]] 6-5 at [[Three Rivers Stadium]] on April 18, {{by|1987}}, Schmidt hit his career 500th home run, a three run shot off of [[Don Robinson (baseball)|Don Robinson]] to win the game, 8-6.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/PIT/PIT198704180.shtml|title=Philadelphia Phillies 8, Pittsburgh Pirates 6|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=April 18, 1987}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Injuries to Schmidt's rotator cuff caused him to miss the last month and a half of the {{by|1988}} season. He returned healthy for the {{by|1989}} season, however, after a poor start, Schmidt suddenly chose to announce his retirement in [[San Diego, California|San Diego]], on May 29. He demonstrated little emotion on the field, and was known as &quot;Captain Cool&quot; by many in Philadelphia sports circles, however, Schmidt surprised many with an emotional, and occasionally tearful, retirement speech. His last game was May 28, 1989, against the [[San Francisco Giants]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/SFN/SFN198905280.shtml|title=San Francisco Giants 8, Philadelphia Phillies 5|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=May 28, 1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite his poor start and subsequent retirement, fans again voted Schmidt to the NL All-Star team. He decided not to play, but he did participate in the game's opening ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/boxes/ALS/ALS198907110.shtml|title=1989 All-Star Game|publisher=Baseball-Reference.com|date=July 11, 1989}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career stats==
&lt;div align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|Games
|[[Plate appearances|PA]]
|[[At-bat|AB]]
|[[Run (baseball)|Runs]]
|[[Hit (baseball)|Hits]]
|[[double (baseball)|2B]]
|[[triple (baseball)|3B]]
|[[Home runs|HR]]
|[[Runs batted in|RBI]]
|SB
|[[Walk (baseball)|BB]]
|[[Strikeout|SO]]
|[[Batting average|Avg.]]
|[[Slugging percentage|Slg.]]
|[[On base percentage|OBP]]
|OPS
|[[fielding percentage|Fld%]]
|-
|2404
|10062
|8352
|1506
|2234
|408
|59
|548
|1595
|174
|1507
|1883
|.267
|.527
|.380
|.908
|.961
|}
&lt;/div&gt;

Over his career Schmidt set a vast array of hitting and fielding records. In addition to his MVP Awards, Schmidt won ten [[Gold Glove]]s, led the league in home runs eight times, in RBIs four times, [[Baseball statistics|OPS]] five times, and walks four times. He was named to twelve All-Star teams. He is the Phillies all-time leader in games played, at-bats, plate appearances, runs scored, hits, home runs, RBI, walks, strikeouts, total bases, runs created, sacrifice flies, outs, Adj. Batting Runs, Adj. Batting Wins, Extra Base Hits, Times On Base, and Power-Speed number.

Schmidt's 548 home runs are the most ever hit by a player who spent his entire career with just one team.

==Post playing career==
{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = PhilsSchmidt.PNG
|Name   = Mike Schmidt
|Number = 20
|Team   = Philadelphia Phillies
|Year   = 1990
}}
Schmidt opted, at first, to pursue a more private lifestyle after his career, rather than to become a [[Manager (baseball)|manager]] or [[Sports coaching|coach]]. He has written a number of articles on baseball for [[CBS]] and regularly participates in [[Golf|charity golf]] tournaments. He spent one season as a member of the Phillies broadcast team on the now-defunct PRISM network. He was known as a very candid and honest broadcaster despite his limited experience in the area.

In 1991, he and Nolan Ryan were inducted into the [[Peter J. McGovern Little League Museum]]'s Hall of Excellence (established in 1988), thereby becoming only the second and third MLB players inducted into the Hall.

In 1995, Schmidt was elected into the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame and Museum]] with what was then the fourth highest percentage ever, 96.52%.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=BASEBALL; Schmidt Again Puts Up Big Numbers|author=Claire Smith |newspaper=New York Times|date=January 10, 1995 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1995/01/10/sports/baseball-schmidt-again-puts-up-big-numbers.html |accessdate=January 4, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Nolan Ryan]] and [[George Brett (baseball)|George Brett]] surpassed his percentage in {{by|1999}}).

In 1999, he ranked number 28 on ''[[The Sporting News]]'''s list of the 100 Greatest Baseball Players,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.baseball-almanac.com/legendary/lisn100.shtml|title=Baseball's 100 Greatest Players|publisher=Sporting News|date=1998}}&lt;/ref&gt; the highest-ranking third baseman, and the highest-ranking player whose career began after 1967. Later that year, he was elected to the [[Major League Baseball All-Century Team]]. His uniform number 20 has been retired by the Phillies, and he has been honored with a statue outside the third-base gate at the team's home, [[Citizens Bank Park]].

Schmidt has publicly expressed his thoughts on various baseball controversies. He has been a vocal advocate for the reinstatement of Pete Rose to baseball. In July 2005, he appeared on [[Bob Costas]]' [[HBO]] show ''[[Costas Now]]'' to discuss steroids, and said, &quot;Let me go out on a limb and say that if I had played during that era I would have taken steroids... We all have these things we deal with in life, and I'm surely not going to sit here and say to you guys, 'I wouldn't have done that.'&quot;

In his 2006 book, ''Clearing the Bases: Juiced Players, Shrinking Ballparks, Sham Records, and a Hall of Famer's Search for the Soul of Baseball'', he somewhat recanted that statement, saying that he understood the desire to get a competitive advantage even though he could not condone breaking the rules to do so.

===Coaching===
In 2002, Schmidt was hired by the Phillies to work for several weeks as a hitting coach each [[Spring training]]. In October 2003, Schmidt was named the manager of the Phillies' [[List of minor league baseball leagues and teams#High-A leagues|Single A]] [[Florida State League]] affiliate, the [[Clearwater Threshers]]. He managed them for just the 2004 season, then resigned. In 2009, he served as third base coach for Team USA in the [[World Baseball Classic]].

===Philanthropy===
In {{by|2001}}, Schmidt began sponsoring an annual [[fishing]] tournament known as the Mike Schmidt Winner's Circle Invitational at Old Bahama Bay in West End, [[Grand Bahama Island]]. The first event raised $27,000, and has since raised over $1.5 million for [[cystic fibrosis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mikeschmidtevents.com/index.html|title=Mike Schmidt Winner's Circle Invitational}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Schmidt released a charity [[wine]] called Mike Schmidt 548 [[Zinfandel]], a reference to his 548 career home runs, with proceeds also going to the [[Cystic Fibrosis Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eventwines.com/Mike_Schmidt_s_548_Zinfandel_p/1243-06.htm|title=Mike Schmidt 548 Zinfandel|publisher=Event Wines}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Major League Baseball Home Run Records]]
*[[List of top 300 Major League Baseball home run hitters]]
*[[500 home run club]]
*[[List of major league players with 2,000 hits]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 400 doubles]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 runs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 RBI]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball RBI champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball home run champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball runs scored champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career stolen bases]]
*[[Batters with four home runs in one game]]
*[[Major League Baseball titles leaders]]
*[[DHL Hometown Heroes]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Further reading===
*{{Cite news|title=Mike Schmidt of the Phillies: Player of the 1980s! |author=Dolson, Frank |newspaper=Baseball Digest |date=1982-05 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=BDQDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA59&amp;dq=mike+schmidt&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;cd=6#v=onepage&amp;q=mike%20schmidt&amp;f=false|accessdate= }}
*{{Cite book|title=Always on the Offense|last=Schmidt|first=Mike|authorlink= |coauthors= Barbara Walder |year=1982|publisher=Macmillan Pub Co|location=|isbn=0-6891-1165-7 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}
*{{Cite book|title=Mike Schmidt: Philadelphia's Hall of Fame third baseman|last=Kashatus |first=William C. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2000 |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company, Inc. |location=Jefferson, NC|isbn=0-7864-0713-1 |page=94 |pages= |url= |accessdate=}}

===External links===
{{Baseballstats |mlb=121836 |espn=256 |br=s/schmimi01 |fangraphs=1011586&amp;position=3B |cube=Mike-Schmidt}}, or [http://www.baseballlibrary.com/ballplayers/player.php?name=mike_schmidt_1949 BaseballLibrary.com]
*{{bbhof|schmidt-mike}}
{{Bullpen|Mike Schmidt}}

{{Navboxes|title=Mike Schmidt|list1=

{{S-start-collapsible|header={{S-ach}}}}
{{Succession box| before=[[Willie Stargell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dave Kingman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dave Kingman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dale Murphy]] | title=[[List of Major League Baseball home run champions|National League Home Run Champion]] | years= 1974-1976&lt;br /&gt;1980-1981&lt;br /&gt;1983-1984(with [[Dale Murphy]]&lt;br /&gt;1986 | after=[[George Foster (baseball)|George Foster]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dave Kingman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dale Murphy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Andre Dawson]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Willie Mays]]|title = [[Batters with 4 home runs in one game]]| years = April 17, 1976 | after = [[Bob Horner]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Keith Hernandez]] and [[Willie Stargell]]|title = [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|National League Most Valuable Player]]| years = 1980, 1981 | after = [[Dale Murphy]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Willie Stargell]]|title = [[World Series MVP Award|World Series MVP]]| years = 1980|after = [[Ron Cey]], [[Pedro Guerrero (baseball)|Pedro Guerrero]], and [[Steve Yeager]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Ron Cey]]|title = [[Lou Gehrig Memorial Award]] | years = 1983 | after = [[Steve Garvey]]}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Willie McGee]]|title = [[MLB Most Valuable Player Award|National League Most Valuable Player]]| years = 1986 | after = [[Andre Dawson]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{MLBACT}}
{{MLBATT}}
{{NL MVPs}}
{{NL home run champions}}
{{World Series MVPs}}
{{Lou Gehrig Memorial Award}}
{{NL 3B Silver Slugger Award}}
{{NL 3B Gold Glove Award}}
{{4 HR game}}
{{500 home run club}}
{{Philadelphia Phillies}}
{{1980 Philadelphia Phillies}}
{{Phillies Retired Numbers}}
{{Philadelphia Phillies HOF}}
{{Philly Baseball Wall of Fame}}
{{1995 Baseball HOF}}
{{Baseball Hall of Fame third basemen}}
{{2004 Philadelphia Sports HOF}}
{{United States 2009 World Baseball Classic roster}}
}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Schmidt, Mike
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =September 27, 1949
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =Dayton, Ohio
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Schmidt, Mike}}
[[Category:1949 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:500 home run club]]
[[Category:American people of German descent]]
[[Category:Baseball players from Ohio]]
[[Category:Eugene Emeralds players]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:Minor league baseball managers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball announcers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball third basemen]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball World Series Most Valuable Player award winners]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National League Most Valuable Player Award winners]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:National League home run champions]]
[[Category:National League RBI champions]]
[[Category:Ohio Bobcats baseball players]]
[[Category:People from Dayton, Ohio]]
[[Category:Philadelphia Phillies broadcasters]]
[[Category:Philadelphia Phillies players]]
[[Category:Reading Phillies players]]

[[es:Mike Schmidt]]
[[fr:Mike Schmidt]]
[[ko:마이크 슈미트]]
[[ja:マイク・シュミット]]
[[pt:Mike Schmidt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
