<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2686404" ns="0" title="League of Coloured Peoples"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''The League of Coloured People''' was a [[United Kingdom|British]] [[civil rights]] organization. The league was founded in [[1931]] in [[London]] with the goal of racial equality around the world. Though the league's primary focus was black rights in [[UK|Britain]], it also was involved in other civil-rights issues, such as the persecution of the [[Jews]] in [[Germany]]. In [[1933]], '''The League of Coloured Peoples''' began publication of the civil-rights journal ''[[The Keys (Journal)|The Keys]]'', and was a powerful civil rights force until its dissolution in [[1951]].

==The beginning==
[[Harold Moody]], a [[physician]] and devout [[Christian]], was frustrated with the prejudice he experienced in Britain, from finding employment to simply obtaining a residence. Through his involvement with [[London Christian Endeavour Federation]], Moody began to confront employers who were refusing jobs to black Britons. On March 13, 1931 in a [[London]] [[YMCA]], Moody called a meeting with the contacts he had made over the years. On this night, they formed '''The League of Coloured Peoples'''. 

The inaugural executive committee of '''The League of Coloured Peoples''' included:
*[[Belfield Clark|Dr. C. Belfield Clark]] of [[Barbados]]
*[[George Roberts]]{{dn|date=October 2011}} of [[Trinidad]]
*[[Samson Morris]] of [[Grenada]]
*[[Robert Adams (British Guiana)|Robert Adams]] of [[British Guiana]]
*[[Desmond Buckle]] of [[Gold Coast (British colony)|The Gold Coast]]
Also present at the inaugural meeting was [[Stella Thomas]], who would go on to become the first woman magistrate in West Africa.

==Aims==
At the inaugural meeting, the '''The League of Coloured Peoples''' established four main aims:
&lt;blockquote&gt;1. To protect the social, educational, economic and political interests of its members&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;2. To interest members in the welfare of coloured peoples in all parts of the world&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;3. To improve relations between the races &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;4. To cooperate and affiliate with organisations sympathetic to coloured people&lt;/blockquote&gt;
In [[1937]], a fifth aim was added:
&lt;blockquote&gt;5. To render such financial assistance to coloured people in distress as lies within our capacity&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Accomplishments==
===The Colour Bar in the Workplace===
From the league's inception in [[1931]] until the outbreak of [[World War II]], the primary focus of '''The League of Coloured Peoples''' was eliminating the [[colour bar]] in the British workplace, in social life, and in housing. The [[colour bar]] refers to the restrictions placed on a group of people due to their race (or colour). Throughout Britain in the 1930s, black people were refused service in many restaurants, hotels, and lodging houses. They also found it extremely difficult to find employment in many industries; the medical profession in particular drew the attention of the league, most likely due to founder and president [[Harold Moody|Harold Moody's]] personal struggles in that area. By [[1935]]. a branch of the league focusing on equality in the shipping industry had grown to over 80 members. During the 1930s, '''The League of Coloured Peoples''' struck many blows for blacks in the workplace.

=== The Colour Bar in the Military ===
=== The Charter of Coloured People ===
== During the second world war ==

During the Second world war the LCP continued to highlight discrimination. Authorities organizing the evacuation of childrne from the big towns found it very difficult to find families who would accept to take in coloured children, and the LCP lobbied against this sort of discrimination.

== References ==
*{{cite web
 | url=http://www.100greatblackbritons.com/bios/harold_moody.html
 | title=Settling - The Keys and the League of Coloured Peoples
 | accessdate=September 15, 2005
 }} 
*{{cite web
 | url=http://www.movinghere.org.uk/galleries/histories/caribbean/settling/keys.htm
 | title=100 Great Black Britons - Harold Moody
 | accessdate=September 15, 2005
 }}

{{DEFAULTSORT:League Of Coloured Peoples}}
[[Category:Civil rights organisations in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 1931]]
[[Category:Black British history]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
