<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26903214" ns="0" title="2010 Grand National"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Horse race
|class           = 2010 Grand National
|horse race      = [[Grand National]]
|image           = 
|caption         = 
|location        = [[Aintree Racecourse]]
|date            = 10 April 2010
|winning horse   = {{Flagicon|Ireland}} [[Don't Push It]]
|starting price  = 10/1 joint-favourite
|winning jockey  = {{Flagicon|Northern Ireland}} [[Tony McCoy]]
|winning trainer = {{Flagicon|Ireland}} [[Jonjo O'Neill]]
|winning owner   = {{Flagicon|Ireland}}[[J. P. McManus]]
|conditions      = Good (good to soft in places)
}}
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 275px
| video1 = [http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8613399.stm Replay of the 2010 Grand National in full]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8613399.stm | work=BBC News | title=Full Replay - Don't Push It wins Grand National | date=10 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; BBC Sport
}}

The '''2010 Grand National''' (known as the [[John Smith's Brewery|John Smith's]] Grand National for sponsorship reasons) was the 163rd renewal of the world-famous [[Grand National]] [[Horse racing|horse race]] that took place at the [[Aintree Racecourse]] near [[Liverpool]], [[England]], on 10 April 2010.

The main race was held at 16:15 [[British Summer Time|BST]] and was won by [[Don't Push It]], ridden by [[Tony McCoy]], five lengths ahead of Black Apalachi in second, and twenty ahead of State of Play in third.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tony McCoy wins Grand National on Don't Push It&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8611001.stm|title=Tony McCoy wins Grand National on Don't Push It|date=2010-04-10|publisher=''[[BBC News]]''|accessdate=11 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

It was McCoy's first win in the Grand National at his fifteenth attempt.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Unreal McCoy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8613763.stm|title=The Unreal McCoy|date=2010-04-10|publisher=''[[BBC News]]''|accessdate=11 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Don't Push It started the race as 10-1 joint-favourite, having been backed down from 20-1 in the hours prior to the race.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tony McCoy wins Grand National on Don't Push It&quot; /&gt; In the process of winning, McCoy avoided equalling the record for most rides in the National without winning, held by Jeff King.

The main race was seen by the largest attendance at Aintree since [[2005 Grand National|2005]], with a crowd of 70,341 on the day, and a total of 150,426 attending over the course of the three-day meeting.&lt;ref&gt;www.aintree.co.uk/docLib/2009_pages010109.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

== Race card ==

&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8606938.stm  BBC Grand National colour guide]&lt;/ref&gt;

*1: '''Madison Du Berlais'''
:Weight: 11-10. Jockey: Tom Scudamore; trainer: David Pipe. Colours: purple with hoop of yellow diamonds, yellow sleeves with red armband and cap.

*2: '''Mon Mome'''
:Weight: 11-7. Jockey: Aidan Coleman; trainer: Venetia Williams. Colours: green jacket and cap, blue armbands on sleeves.

*3: '''Vic Venturi'''
:Weight: 11-6. Jockey: Roger Loughran; trainer: Dessie Hughes ([[Irish people|Ireland]]). Colours: black, yellow diamond on body and cap, diamonds on sleeves.

*4: '''Black Apalachi'''
:Weight: 11-6. Jockey: Denis O'Regan; trainer: Dessie Hughes (Ireland). Colours: green, blue chevrons on sleeves, blue star on cap.

*5: '''Joe Lively'''
:Weight: 11-6. Jockey: Joe Tizzard; trainer: Colin Tizzard. Colours: yellow with red diamond, quartered cap.

*6: '''Don't Push It'''
:Weight: 11-5. Jockey: Tony McCoy; trainer: Jonjo O'Neill. Colours: green and yellow hoops, white cap.

*7: '''Comply or Die'''
:Weight: 11-5. Jockey: Timmy Murphy; trainer: David Pipe. Colours: blue, green sleeves, white cap with blue spots.

*8: '''Niche Market'''
:Weight: 11-4. Jockey: Harry Skelton; trainer: Bob Buckler. Colours: orange and blue quarters, hooped sleeves, quartered cap.

*9: '''Tricky Trickster'''
:Weight:11-4. Jockey: [[Richard Johnson (jockey)|Richard Johnson]]; trainer: Paul Nicholls. Colours: pink with purple spotted sash, hooped sleeves. &lt;small&gt;Note: Johnson replaced [[Barry Geraghty]] as the jockey of Tricky Trickster following an injury to [[Ruby Walsh]]. Geraghty switched to ride joint-favourite Big Fella Thanks.&lt;/small&gt;

*10: '''Made in Taipan'''
:Weight: 11-4. Jockey: Niall Madden; trainer: Tom Mullins (Ireland). Colours: orange with black star, diablo sleeves, white and black hooped cap.

*11: '''Dream Alliance'''
:Weight: 11-3. Jockey: Tom O'Brien; trainer: Philip Hobbs. Colours: grey with white epilettes and armbands, hooped cap.

*12: '''Cloudy Lane'''
:Weight: 11-3. Jockey: Jason Maguire; trainer: Donald McCain, Jr. Colours: green and yellow quarters, white sleeves and cap.

*13: '''Nozic'''
:Weight: 11-3. Jockey: Liam Treadwell; trainer: Paul Nicholls. Colours: blue, white disc, stars on sleeves and star on cap.

*14: '''My Will'''
:Weight: 11-2. Jockey: Nick Scholfield; trainer: Paul Nicholls. Colours: black and white halves, red sleeves and cap.

*15: '''Pablo Du Charmil'''
:Weight: 11-2. Jockey: Danny Cook; trainer: David Pipe. Colours: blue, yellow chevron, diablo sleeves.

*16: '''Ballyholland'''
:Weight: 11-0. Jockey: Andrew McNamara; trainer: Colin McBratney (Ireland). Colours: white, yellow stripe, quartered cap.

*17: '''Backstage'''
:Weight: 11-0. Jockey: Davy Condon; trainer: Gordon Elliott (Ireland). Colours: sky, orange epilettes, sky and purple checked cap.

*18: '''Beat the Boys'''
:Weight: 11-0. Jockey: Brian Hughes; trainer: Nigel Twiston-Davies. Colours: pink, blue diamond, diablo sleeves, pink star on blue cap.

*19: '''Preists Leap'''
:Weight: 11-0. Jockey: Philip Enright; trainer: Tom O'Leary (Ireland). Colours: blue, yellow star, stars on sleeves, star on cap.

*20: '''Snowy Morning'''
:Weight: 10-13. Jockey: David Casey; trainer: Willie Mullins (Ireland). Colours: yellow, black braces, yellow and white quartered cap.

*21: '''Can't Buy Time'''
:Weight: 10-13. Jockey: Richie McLernon; trainer: Jonjo O'Neill. Colours: green and yellow hoops, white star on green cap.

*22: '''Big Fella Thanks'''
:Weight: 10-12. Jockey: Barry Geraghty; trainer: Paul Nicholls. Colours: purple with grey hooped sleeves. &lt;small&gt;Note: Twice-winning jockey [[Ruby Walsh]] was originally scheduled to ride Big Fella Thanks but was ruled out when he was injured in a heavy fall on Celestial Halo in the 2:50pm race earlier in the day.&lt;/small&gt;

*23: '''State of Play'''
:Weight: 10-11. Jockey: Paul Moloney; trainer: Evan Williams. Colours: blue with pink hoop.

*24: '''Character Building'''
:Weight: 10-11. Jockey: Nina Carberry; trainer: John Quinn. Colours: cerise with purple crossbelts, hooped sleeves and cap.

*25: '''Ellerslie George'''
:Weight: 10-10. Jockey: Christian Williams; trainer: Nick Mitchell. Colours: blue with green hoop and cap, red sleeves.

*26: '''Eric's Charm'''
:Weight: 10-9. Jockey: Wayne Hutchinson; trainer: Oliver Sherwood. Colours: yellow with pink diamond chequered body.

*27: '''King Johns Castle'''
:Weight: 10-9. Jockey: Paul Carberry; trainer: Arthur Moore (Ireland). Colours: green and yellow hoops, red cap.

*28: '''Conna Castle'''
:Weight: 10-9. Jockey: Sean Flanagan; trainer: Jimmy Mangan (Ireland). Colours: orange with sky diamond chequered body and stars on cap.

*29: '''Ballyfitz'''
:Weight: 10-9. Jockey: David England; trainer: Nigel Twiston-Davies. Colours: sky and claret diablo and quartered cap, sky sleeves.

*30: '''Ollie Magern'''
:Weight: 10-9. Jockey: Tom Molloy; trainer: Nigel Twiston-Davies. Colours: sky, claret stars and sleeves.

*31: '''Arbor Supreme'''
:Weight: 10-8. Jockey: Paul Townend; trainer: Willie Mullins (Ireland). Colours: green and yellow hoops, blue cap.

*32: '''Maljimar'''
:Weight: 10-8. Jockey: Daryl Jacob; trainer: Nick Williams. Colours: orange with black star on body and cap.

*33: '''The Package'''
:Weight: 10-7. Jockey: Graham Lee; trainer: David Pipe. Colours: green, blue sleeves, red cap.

*34: '''Piraya'''
:Weight: 10-7. Jockey: Johnny Farrelly; trainer: David Pipe. Colours: white, red spotted sash, armbands and quartered cap.

*35: '''Irish Raptor'''
:Weight: 10-7. Jockey: Paddy Brennan; trainer: Nigel Twiston-Davies. Colours: green, yellow stars, striped sleeves and cap.

*36: '''Cerium'''
:Weight: 10-5. Jockey: Davy Russell; trainer: Paul Murphy. Colours: green, white star, black striped sleeves, white cap with black star.

*37: '''Palypso De Creek'''
:Weight: 10-6. Jockey: Tom Siddall; trainer: Charlie Longsdon. Colours: blue, green sleeves and cap.

*38: '''Hello Bud'''
:Weight:10-6. Jockey: Sam Twiston-Davies; trainer: Nigel Twiston-Davies. Colours: white, blue spotted body and sleeves, striped cap.

*39: '''Flintoff'''
:Weight: 10-5. Jockey: Andrew Tinkler; trainer: Venetia Williams. Colours: blue, pink hooped sleeves and cap.

*40: '''Royal Rosa'''
:Weight: 10-5. Jockey: Wilson Renwick; trainer: Howard Johnson. Colours: chocolate and cream quarters.

Originally, Cerium and Royal Rosa were reserves, but were run because of the withdrawals of Mr. Pointment and Abbeybraney. Silver Birch was originally due to be the first reserve, but was drawn-out so that he could run in the Topham Chase instead.

== Finishing order ==
&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Grand National rerun&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8613445.stm  BBC Grand National rerun]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Result&quot;&gt;[http://horses.sportinglife.com/Full_Results/0,12493,357099,00.html Full Result] SportingLife.com&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
|'''Position'''
|'''Name'''
|'''Rider'''
|'''Age'''
|'''Weight'''
|'''Starting price'''
|'''Distance'''
|'''Prize money'''
|-
|1st
|[[Don't Push It]]
|[[Tony McCoy]]
|10
|11-05
|10/1 JF
|Winner by 5 lengths
|£521,052
|-
|2nd
|Black Apalachi
|Denis O'Regan
|11
|11-06
|14/1
|5 lengths
|£196,285
|-
|3rd
|State of Play
|Paul Moloney
|10
|10-11
|16/1
|20 lengths
|£98,235
|-
|4th
|Big Fella Thanks
|[[Barry Geraghty]]
|8
|10-12
|10/1 JF
|3 lengths
|£49,117
|-
|5th
|Hello Bud
|Sam Twiston-Davies
|12
|10-06
|20/1
|7 lengths
|£24,605
|-
|6th
|Snowy Morning
|David Casey
|10
|10-13
|14/1
|1½ lengths
|£12,302
|-
|7th
|Character Building
|[[Nina Carberry]]
|10
|10-11
|16/1
|Neck
|£6,105
|-
|8th
|Cloudy Lane
|[[Jason Maguire]]
|10
|11-03
|25/1
|12 lengths
|£3,145
|-
|9th
|Tricky Trickster
|[[Richard Johnson (jockey)|Richard Johnson]]
|7
|11-04
|16/1
|¾ length
|Nil
|-
|10th
|Joe Lively
|Joe Tizzard
|11
|11-06
|33/1
|Short head
|Nil
|-
|11th
|Cerium
|[[Davy Russell]]
|9
|10-06
|50/1
|A distance
|Nil
|-
|12th
|[[Comply or Die]]
|[[Timmy Murphy]]
|11
|10-05
|12/1
|8 lengths
|Nil
|-
|13th
|Piraya
|Johnny Farrelly
|7
|10-07
|100/1
|A distance
|Nil
|-
|14th
|Preists Leap
|Philip Enright
|10
|11-00
|100/1
|Last to complete
|Nil
|}

== Non-finishers ==
&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Grand National rerun&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Result&quot;/&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
|'''Fence'''
|'''Name'''
|'''Rider'''
|'''Age'''
|'''Weight'''
|'''Starting price'''
|'''Fate'''
|-
|Start line
|King John's Castle
|[[Paul Carberry]]
|11
|10-09
|28/1
|Refused to start
|-
|1st
|Eric's Charm
|Wayne Hutchinson
|12
|10-09
|33/1
|Fell
|-
|2nd
|Pablo Du Charmil
|Danny Cook
|9
|11-02
|100/1
|Fell
|-
|4th
|My Will
|Nick Scholfield
|10
|11-02
|20/1
|Fell
|-
|5th
|Made in Taipan
|[[Niall Madden]]
|8
|11-04
|100/1
|Fell
|-
|8th &lt;small&gt;([[Canal Turn]])&lt;/small&gt;
|Can't Buy Time 
|Richie McClernon
|8
|10-13
|33/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|14th
|Irish Raptor
|[[Paddy Brennan (jockey)|Paddy Brennan]]
|11
|10-07
|33/1
|Fell
|-
|14th
|Royal Rosa
|Wilson Renwick
|11
|10-05
|66/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|15th &lt;small&gt;([[The Chair (Aintree Racecourse)|The Chair]])&lt;/small&gt;
|Arbor Supreme
|Paul Townend
|8
|10-08
|16/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|19th
|Madison Du Berlais
|[[Tom Scudamore]]
|9
|11-10
|50/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|19th
|Beat The Boys
|Brian Hughes
|9
|11-00
|66/1
|Pulled up
|-
|19th
|The Package
|[[Graham Lee (jockey)|Graham Lee]]
|7
|10-07
|14/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|20th
|Vic Venturi
|Roger Loughran
|10
|11-06
|25/1
|Fell when hampered
|-
|20th
|Nozic
|[[Liam Treadwell]]
|9
|11-03
|40/1
|Unseated rider when hampered
|-
|20th
|Backstage
|[[Davy Condon]]
|8
|11-00
|25/1
|Unseated rider when hampered
|-
|21st
|Flintoff
|Andrew Tinkler
|9
|10-05
|50/1
|Pulled up
|-
|22nd &lt;small&gt;([[Becher's Brook]])&lt;/small&gt;
|Ballyfitz
|David England
|10
|10-09
|50/1
|Fell
|-
|22nd &lt;small&gt;([[Becher's Brook]])&lt;/small&gt;
|Maljimar
|Daryl Jacob
|10
|10-08
|28/1
|Fell
|-
|23rd &lt;small&gt;([[Foinavon]]'s)&lt;/small&gt;
|Ellerslie George
|Christian Williams
|10
|10-10
|66/1
|Unseated rider
|-
|24th &lt;small&gt;([[Canal Turn]])&lt;/small&gt;
|Dream Alliance
|[[Tom O'Brien (jockey)|Tom O'Brien]]
|9
|11-03
|16/1
|Pulled up
|-
|26th
|[[Mon Mome]]
|[[Aidan Coleman]]
|10
|11-07
|14/1
|Fell
|-
|27th
|Palypso De Creek
|Tom Siddall
|7
|10-06
|66/1
|Fell 
|-
|28th
|Ballyholland
|Andrew McNamara
|9
|11-00
|28/1
|Pulled up
|-
|29th
|Niche Market
|Harry Skelton
|9
|11-04
|16/1
|Pulled up 
|-
|29th
|Conna Castle
|Sean Flanagan
|11
|10-09
|100/1
|Pulled up
|-
|29th
|Ollie Magern
|Tom Molloy
|12
|10-09
|100/1
|Pulled up
|}

==Trivia==
For the first time since 2005, there were no equine fatalities in the main race. In each of the previous four years there was one casualty.

Plaisir d'Estruval and Prudent Honour both died instantly after jumping ''Valentine's'', the 13th fence in the Topham Chase on 9 April, a handicap over two miles and 5½ furlongs. Both horses broke their necks. Earlier the same day, in the grade one Melling Chase over standard chase fences on the Mildmay track, Schindlers Hunt was put down after fracturing a leg in a fall at the third fence. Schindlers Hunt's jockey Paddy Flood broke his collarbone in the fall; the other jockeys were unhurt.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/2010/apr/09/deaths-grand-national-aintree Three horses die at Aintree] guardian.co.uk&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Gala_Coral_Group#Coral|Coral bookmakers]] took the decision to refund bets placed on race-day for King John's Castle. The horse was bidding to become the first grey to win the National since 1961,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/sport/racing/article7093606.ece | location=London | work=The Times | first=Rob | last=Wright | title=King Johns Castle primed for Grand National glory | date=10 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; but refused to run when the race started. Although under betting rules customers bets should have been classified as losers, Coral took the decision to make a goodwill refund gesture to their customers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bettingpro.com/category/Racing/Coral-Refund-Stakes-on-King-Johns-Castle-2010041000145/ Coral Refund stakes on King Johns Castle]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Jockeys and quotes==
Selected quotes from the jockeys including winner at the fifteenth attempt, Tony McCoy, 17-year-old Sam Twiston-Davies who was aiming to become the second-youngest winning jockey ever, and Nina Carberry attempting to be first female rider to win the race:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sportinglife.com/racing/news/story_get.cgi?STORY_NAME=racing/10/04/10/RACING_National_Jockeys.html Quote...unquote] Sportinglife.com&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Tony McCoy''' (Don't Push It, first): &quot;If you get enough goes at something and you keep going, once you're in there you've always got a chance. I'm delighted for JP [McManus, owner] as he's the best supporter this game has ever had and ever will have, and I'm very privileged to ride a Grand National winner in his colours.&quot;

*'''Denis O'Regan''' (Black Apalachi, second): &quot;My fella's a tremendous horse and he gave me a tremendous feel. He just loves bowling along and loves this place. He was a bit keen early on but once he settled into a lovely rhythm he was fantastic. It's a pleasure to ride a horse like him round here.&quot;

*'''Paul Moloney''' (State Of Play, third): &quot;It was a serious run from a serious horse who's been very good to me - and he might win it next year, please God.&quot;

*'''Barry Geraghty''' (late replacement jockey for Big Fella Thanks, fourth): &quot;That was brilliant. He galloped from end to end, the best ride I've ever had round here. But if you can't have the winner then it's good to see AP [McCoy] win it.&quot;

*'''Sam Twiston-Davies''' (Hello Bud, fifth): &quot;That was brilliant. The horse has been a real star and has jumped from fence to fence.&quot;

*'''Nina Carberry''' (Character Building, seventh): &quot;He couldn't lay up and the plan was to give him a chance. I thought I had a really great chance of being in the money and in the first three over the Canal Turn, but he got tapped for toe and in the end I just got done for sixth. He ran a great race had it been softer he might have come back to them a bit more. Hopefully he'll come back next year.&quot;

Tony McCoy lined up as the most experienced rider in the race for the fourth consecutive year, having taken over as senior rider from Carl Llewellyn after the 2006 National. It had also been an honour he had shared for a time with [[Mick Fitzgerald]] and Paul Carberry. 2010 also marked McCoy's fifteenth ride in the National, a feat previously achieved by only nine other riders, however, defeat this year would have seen McCoy become only the seond rider to take fifteen rides in the race without ever winning. His ultimate victory saw this dubious honour remain solely Jeff King's.

At the opposite extreme, nine riders made their Grand National debut, though only one, Sam Twiston-Davies managed to complete the course, finishing fifth. Danny Cook's first National ended at the second fence while Ritchie McLernon, Brian Hughes, Roger Loughran, Tom Siddall, Harry Skelton and Tom Molloy were also taking part for the first time.

==Broadcasting==
As the [[Grand National]] was accorded the status as an event of national interest within the United Kingdom and was listed on the [[Ofcom Code on Sports and Other Listed &amp; Designated Events]], the event had to be shown on free-to-air terrestrial television in the UK. As with previous years the rights to broadcast the race were held by the [[BBC]] and the race, along with several others were shown on [[BBC One]]. It was also the first horse race in the UK to be broadcast in [[high-definition television|high definition]] on the [[BBC HD]] channel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand National to be UK's first horse race broadcast in HD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.how-do.co.uk/north-west-media-news/north-west-broadcasting/grand-national-to-be-uk's-first-horse-race-broadcast-in-hd-201003297776/|title=Grand National to be UK's first horse race broadcast in HD|date=2010-03-29|publisher=''HowDo''|accessdate=11 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BBC's coverage was produced by [[Sunset and Vine]] who, with the aid of the SiS outside broadcast unit, provided coverage of fifteen races throughout the three-day meeting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/horseracing/7578481/Grand-National-2010-Good-work-BBC-now-do-more-of-it.html  SIS OB support announcement for HD Grand National Broadcast]&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{Quote box
 |quote  = '''Black Apalachi and Don't Push It race towards the elbow; a titanic struggle. They're clear of Big Fella Thanks. They're on the run-in for home. McCoy is rousting Don't Push It. He's galvanising him; he's started to get a real tune out of him! He's going to at last win the Grand National. It's Don't Push It, Tony McCoy at the fifteenth attempt. He wins the Grand National!'''
 |source = BBC commentator [[Jim McGrath (Australian commentator)|Jim McGrath]] describes the climax of the 2010 Grand National
 |width  = 35%
 |quoted = 1
 |align  = right
}}

[[Clare Balding]] served as anchor presenter for the fifth consecutive year with Rishi Persad providing interviews from the jockey's room as well as taking a closer look at the horses in the paddock with [[Richard Dunwoody]]. [[Mick Fitzgerald]] guided viewers through the course as well as providing post-race analysis from all the build-up races. [[Richard Pitman]] provided nostalgia with interviews with several famous names from the history of the race, including an interview with his ex-wife [[Jenny Pitman]] while [[Lizzie Greenwood-Hughes]] interviewed spectators in the stands for unusual and interesting stories. [[John Parrott]] and Gary Wiltshire completed the team with news from the betting ring.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.4rfv.co.uk/industrynews.asp?id=109198  UK film and television news]&lt;/ref&gt;

The commentary team for the 2010 Grand National consisted of [[Ian Bartlett]], [[Darren Owen]] and [[Jim McGrath (Australian commentator)|Jim McGrath]], who called the winner home for the thirteenth consecutive year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8613378.stm  BBC closing stages]&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first time for six years that the team had been reduced from four to three with Tony O'Hehir being dropped in what the BBC called a cost-cutting exercise.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.racingpost.com/news/horse-racing/aintree-grand-national-bbc-cuts-grand-national-commentary-team/677988/ BBC announce three man commentary team]&lt;/ref&gt; As is tradition, anchor presenter Balding conducted the interviews with the winning connections while Bartlett, Dunwoody and Fitzgerald then took the viewers through a detailed rerun of the race.

BBC radio also covered the race live for the seventy-ninth time as part of its wider Five Live Sports broadcast. [[Mark Pougatch]] presented the programme live from Aintree with race commentary called by [[Cornelius Lysaght]] and [[John Hunt]]. The race was also covered by Racing UK into bookmakers' offices throughout the UK and Ireland using alternative camera shots from the BBC with their own commentary team.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G4aYO1YBpq0  Race coverage as broadcast to bookmakers]&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport1/hi/other_sports/horse_racing/8606938.stm Grand National runners and riders], ''BBC Sport'', 10 April 2010
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/2010/apr/10/grand-national-2010-live Grand National 2010 - as it happened ''The Guardian'']

{{Grand National}}

[[Category:Grand National| 2010]]
[[Category:2010 in horse racing|Grand National]]
[[Category:2010 in the United Kingdom|Grand National]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
