<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26903628" ns="0" title="Bulletstorm"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox video game
|title = Bulletstorm
|image = [[File:Bulletstorm.jpg|256px]]
|caption= European box art
|developer = [[People Can Fly]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Epic Games]]&lt;ref name=&quot;epicgames.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.epicgames.com/news/epic-games-and-ea-unleash-the-bulletstorm/ |title=and EA Unleash the Bulletstorm &amp;#124; News |publisher=Epic Games |date=2010-04-12 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|publisher = [[Electronic Arts]]
|engine = [[Unreal Engine 3|Unreal Engine 3.5]]&lt;ref name=&quot;epicgames.com&quot;/&gt;
|producer = Adrian Chmielarz&lt;br /&gt;[[Cliff Bleszinski]]&lt;br /&gt;Tanya Jessen
|writer = [[Rick Remender]]
|designer = Adrian Chmielarz
|composer = Krzysztof Wierzynkiewicz, Michał Cielecki
|series =
|version =
|released={{vgrelease new|NA|2011-02-22|AU|2011-02-24|EU|2011-02-25}}
|genre=[[First-person shooter]]
|modes=[[Single-player video game|Single-player]], [[Multiplayer video game|multiplayer]]
|ratings = {{vgratings|ESRB=M|ACB=MA15+&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.classification.gov.au/www/cob/find.nsf/5b6ebdff7f5b9a24ca2575ca00062226/43c2bc0ff66df8b1ca2577ee0057eb92?OpenDocument |title=BULLETSTORM (MA 15+) |publisher=Classification Database |date= |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;|PEGI=18}}
|platforms = [[Microsoft Windows]]&lt;br /&gt;[[PlayStation 3]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Xbox 360]]
|media = [[Optical disc]], [[Online distribution|download]]
|requirements =
'''Recommended requirements'''
*OS: Windows Vista (SP2) or Windows 7
*Processor: Quad Core 2.0&amp;nbsp;GHz
*Memory: 2&amp;nbsp;GB
*Video Card: DirectX 9.0c compatible, 512&amp;nbsp;MB of VRAM

'''Minimum requirements'''

*OS: Windows XP/Vista/7
*Processor: Intel Core 2 Duo E2140 @ 1.6 GHz/AMD Athlon 64 X2 3200+
*Memory: 1.5&amp;nbsp;GB
*Hard Drive: 9&amp;nbsp;GB free
*Video Memory: 256&amp;nbsp;MB
*Video Card: Nvidia GeForce 7600/ATI Radeon HD 2400 Pro
*Sound Card: DirectX 9.0c Compatible
*Network: Broadband Internet Connection
*Keyboard
*Mouse
*DVD Rom Drive
}}

'''''Bulletstorm''''' is a {{vgy|2011}} [[first-person shooter]] [[video game]] developed by [[People Can Fly]] and [[Epic Games]],&lt;ref name=&quot;epicgames.com&quot;/&gt; and is published by [[Electronic Arts]] for the [[PlayStation 3]], [[Xbox 360]] and [[Microsoft Windows]]. The game was released on February 22, 2011 in North America and on February 25, 2011 in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Announcement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5513826/first-look-at-gears-of-war--painkiller-creators-bloody-brutal-bulletstorm |title=First Look At Gears Of War &amp; Painkiller Creators' Bloody, Brutal Bulletstorm|first=Michael|last=McWhertor|date=2010-04-09|publisher=Kotaku|accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The game is distinguished by its sense of style and crass humor, rewarding players with points for performing increasingly ludicrous kills. ''Bulletstorm'' does not have any competitive multiplayer modes, preferring instead to include cooperative online play as well as [[score attack]] modes.

==Plot==
Bulletstorm takes place in the 26th century, where the universe is run by the Confederation of Planets. Star General Saranno sends his secret black ops team to do his dirty work, the Dead Echo team, led by Grayson Hunt ([[Steven Blum]]), having been following Sarrano's orders in assassinating what they believe are drug traffickers and mass murderers, kill a man known as Bryce Novak, but soon discover he was a civilian reporter, having documented other civilian deaths caused by Dead Echo. Grayson and his team realize they have been duped by Sarrano and [[desertion|desert]], becoming space pirates on the run from Sarrano's forces.

Ten years later, Grayson drunkenly attacks Sarrano's battlecruiser, the ''Ulysses'', while near the planet of Stygia. With their ship's systems failing, Grayson, in a last effort attack, rams the ''Ulysses'', hoping to gain revenge on Sarrano. The ships collide, forcing both down and causing them to crash land on the surface of Stygia. One of Grayson's men, Ishi Sato ([[Andrew Kishino]]), is critically wounded in the crash and Grayson is forced to find an energy cell to drive the ship's medical equipment. On the planet, a former popular tropical-like resort destination, the population has mutated into feral tribes and carnivorous plants. Grayson fights through to one of the ''Ulysses'' escape pods, where a Final Echo soldier succumbs to a horde of mutants. After dispatching the attackers, Grayson retrieves the escape pod's energy cell, as well as an &quot;instinct leash&quot; that, when worn, begins to provide him strange tactile information, such as points for each enemy he kills.

Grayson returns with the cell, and while Ishi is under operation, the mutants attack their ship. The operation is cut short by an explosion during battle, leaving Ishi a disfigured cyborg. Grayson and Ishi, the only survivors, decide to work together to get off the planet, despite Ishi's disapproval of Grayson's thirst for revenge. The instinct leash leads Grayson to another escape pod, where they find Trishka ([[Jennifer Hale]]), another Final Echo soldier who agrees to work with Grayson and Ishi, but only after they rescue Sarrano. As they battle through the ravaged city, Trishka explains that Stygia has been used by Final Echo as a sort of training grounds, with the instinct leashes the soldiers wear as a means of ranking those within the test; those that scored kills would be the only ones that could get ammunition and other supplies to survive. When Grayson learns that Trishka was Novak's daughter, he tells her that Sarrano was responsible for her father's death, but claims he does not know who actually killed him.

The three make their way to the top of a skyscraper where Sarrano's pod landed. Trishka accuses Sarrano of her father's death, but he simply pushes her off the side of the building. Sarrano then warns Grayson and Ishi that there is an armed DNA bomb on the ''Ulysses'' that will wipe out all life on the planet, and that they must go and disarm it, as his rescue ship will not arrive in time. Sarrano leads them through the underground areas of the city, encountering radioactive waste and a giant prison. Sarrano snidely explains that that shields used to protect the planet's surface from its deadly electrical storms created the waste, and in turn, began to mutate the population of the surface; the changes occurred too quickly for most of the surface population to be rescued, and thus many of the feral mutants that Grayson has been fighting were more innocent civilians. Grayson is furious at this revelation, but continues to help Sarrano to reach the remains the ''Ulysses''. Aboard, Sarrano tricks Grayson and Ishi once again, having them actually arm the DNA bomb, while his rescue ship will arrive in time to save him. As fire breaks out aboard the fallen ship, the two are saved by Trishka, who survived the fall by catching a power line on her way down.

The three race to where Sarrano's rescue ship is landing and manage to get on board. They make their way through Sarrano's elite troops and eventually face Sarrano alone. Trishka demands to know who actually killed her father, to which Sarrano indicts Grayson. In the confusion, Sarrano hijacks Ishi's computer systems, forcing him to turn on his friends. Grayson manages to break Sarrano's control of Ishi, and Ishi sacrifices himself to prevent Sarrano from killing Grayson. Grayson then impales Sarrano on the wall of a ship. As Grayson and Trishka regroup, Sarrano performs one final act: ejecting Grayson, Trishka and several of his men from the ship back onto the planet. With the DNA bomb soon to detonate, Grayson and Trishka race back to the ''Ulysses'' where one escape pod remains unlaunched; they are able to board it and escape into low orbit, out of range of the DNA bomb when it goes off. Grayson and Trishka have a short chat in the escape pod concerning Grayson's revenge, the loss of his team, and Sarrano's escape. The scene fades after Trishka asks Grayson what he is going to do about Sarrano escaping.

After the credits, it is revealed that Sarrano was revived, now a cyborg like Ishi, and Ishi has also been revived now under Sarrano's control.

==Gameplay==
[[File:Bsss.gif|thumb|left|Screenshot of the &quot;skillshot&quot; system]]
Players use a sizable arsenal consisting of over-the-top combat moves and large weapons. ''Bulletstorm'' also has a variety of &quot;skillshots&quot;. The skillshot gameplay system rewards the player for creating and inciting mayhem in the most creative and destructive ways possible, from killing an enemy in midair to pushing an enemy into a carnivorous plant to executing an enemy after shooting him in the [[testicle]]s. The more unusual the skillshot, the more points players acquire to purchase weapons and upgrades. The weapons are unlocked at set points throughout the game, and after a weapon has been &quot;re-armed&quot; by purchasing it, a &quot;charge shot&quot; for the gun is unlocked at another set point.

Points are used as currency at &quot;dropkits&quot; scattered across the planet, which the player can use to replenish munitions. The dropkits include a gun shop, a skillshot checklist, and gameplay statistics. The player cannot upgrade their weapons, but can equip different guns, purchase ammunition, upgrade the amount of ammunition they can carry, and even purchase special-ammunition &quot;charges&quot;. The player can equip up to three weapons, the assault rifle being the default weapon; it is always equipped, and is considered the main prop weapon in cutscenes.

The weapons range from a pistol to a cannon that shoots a [[bolas]] weighted by grenades. Each weapon has an &quot;alternate fire&quot; mode which uses charges; for example, the assault rifle's alternate fire is a single blast of bullets that destroy almost everything in its path. A device the player carries for most of the game is the &quot;energy leash&quot;, a rope of energy projected from a device on his left hand. The leash allows him to pull enemies towards him, activate certain devices and traps, and slam down a ball of energy that launches all nearby enemies into the air. The player can also kick enemies and run and slide into them. Usually, when an enemy is launched into the air by the player, their descent is slowed down by the leash's energy when grappled or by the gravity boot when kicked. This allows the player to pull an enemy into kicking range with the leash, aim at something dangerous, and kick.

==Development==
Development began in June 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gry-online.pl/S018.asp?ID=678|title=Interview with Adrian Chmielarz|first=Krystian|last=Smoszna|date=2010-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, [[Electronic Arts]] announced that it would be publishing a new [[Intellectual property|IP]] from independent game developer [[Epic Games]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5037277/ea-to-publish-new-ip-title-from-epic|title=EA To Publish New IP Title From Epic|first=Stuart|last=Houghton|date=2008-08-14| publisher=Kotaku|accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; A trademark for the name &quot;Bulletstorm&quot; was revealed when game developer [[People Can Fly]] filed a trademark for the name in December 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotaku.com/5436469/painkiller-developers-predicting-a-bulletstorm|title=Painkiller Developers Predicting A Bulletstorm |first=Michael|last=McWhertor|date= 2009-12-29|publisher=Kotaku|accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Epic Games designer [[Cliff Bleszinski]] was originally scheduled to announce the game alongside ''[[Gears of War 3]]'' during an appearance on ''[[Late Night with Jimmy Fallon]]'' on April 8, 2010. However, his appearance was delayed to April 12, 2010 after his slot was taken by pop singer [[Justin Bieber]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://kotaku.com/5512082/gears-of-war-designers-late-night-game-reveal-bumped-the-bieber-steps-in|title=Gears of War Designer's 'Late Night' Game Reveal Bumped, The Bieber Steps In |first=Michael|last=McWhertor|date=2010-04-07|publisher=Kotaku| accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after Bleszinski announced on social networking website [[Twitter]] that he would be announcing two games on the show on April 12, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://twitter.com/therealcliffyb/status/11900944054|title= Newsflash: Two announcements|last=Bleszinski|first=Cliff|authorlink=Cliff Bleszinski|date=2010-04-09|publisher=[[Twitter]]| accessdate=2010-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the game was revealed before the scheduled appearance when gaming magazine, ''[[Game Informer]]'', released its May 2010 issue cover which revealed the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;Announcement&quot;/&gt;

On December 17, 2010, two months prior to its release, Epic Games announced that there would be a limited edition for ''Bulletstorm'' exclusively for Xbox 360 known as the ''Epic Edition''. The ''Epic Edition'' includes bonus in-game content for ''Bulletstorm'' when playing online, including 25,000 experience points, visual upgrades for the leash, Peace Maker Carbine, boots and armor as well as access to multiplayer beta of ''[[Gears of War 3]]''.

On January 14, 2011, Electronic Arts announced that a demo of the game would be available on January 25, 2011 for the [[Xbox 360]] and on January 26, 2011 for the [[PlayStation 3]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2011-01-14-bulletstorm-demo-confirmed | title=Bulletstorm demo confirmed | date=2011-01-14 | publisher=[[Eurogamer]] | quote=A demo of People Can Fly's first-person shooter Bulletstorm will release on 25th January on Xbox Live PSN, EA has announced. No mention was made of a PC demo. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; No demo was announced to be planned for the PC, which was described as odd by some reviewers, especially for an unproven video game franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.maximumpc.com/article/news/more_drizzle_bulletstorm_demo_skipping_pc | title=More of a Drizzle: Bulletstorm Demo Skipping PC | date=2011-01-16 | publisher = [[Maximum PC]] | quote=Still though, seems like a rather unfortunate move on Epic's part. We're hardly businessmen, but putting a tangible piece of your new, unproven IP into as many gamers' hands as possible as quickly as possible seems like a no-brainer. Also—while we definitely don't endorse it—too many PC gamers tend to have a &quot;No demo? Ok then, piracy!&quot; policy. Bulletstorm may have gained a reputation for being goofy and somewhat mindless, but that doesn't mean its pre-release build-up should follow suit. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was remarked that [[Mark Rein]], president of [[Epic Games]], previously described ''Bulletstorm'' as &quot;a full-blown, oh-my-god amazing PC game&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.fragland.net/news/_/25157/ | title = Bulletstorm gets a demo! But not on PC! | date=2011-01-15 | publisher=fragland.net | quote=Joke of the day: although Epic's Mark Rein once described Bulletstorm as &quot;a full-blown, oh-my-god amazing PC game&quot;, there are no plans for a PC demo. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.1up.com/news/gears-war-creator-epic-games | title=Gears of War Creator Epic Games Still Devoted to PC Development | date=2010-07-02 | publisher=[[1UP.com]] | quote=Bulletstorm is PC, PS3 and Xbox 360 and you'll see when it comes out, it will be a full-blown, oh-my-god amazing PC game. I think that's a myth that we’ve abandoned the PC, it's just not true. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following this announcement, [[Cliff Bleszinski]], producer for the game, wrote a [[Twitter|tweet]] on January 14, 2011 about how the demo was only for [[PlayStation 3]] and [[Xbox 360]], which was considered by game reviewers as a way of making fun of PC players.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://twitter.com/therealcliffyb/status/25979475304906752 | title=BULLETSTORM DEMO COMING TO 360/PS3 JANUARY 25th | date=2011-01-14 | author=[[Cliff Bleszinski]] | quote=BULLETSTORM DEMO COMING TO 360/PS3 JANUARY 25th. In other news, PC gamers are grumpy about this. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nofrag.com/2011/jan/17/36703/ | title=Bulletstorm : une légion d'ennemis | date=2011-01-17 | publisher=[[NoFrag]] | quote=Pendant ce temps, CliffyB se moque des joueurs qui se plaignent de l'absence de démo PC pour Bulletstorm. Rappelons qu'Epic Games est l'un des rares membres de la PC Gaming Alliance et est donc censé promouvoir le jeu PC... | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.destructoid.com/no-pc-demo-for-bulletstorm-pc-gamers-reported-grumpy--191877.phtml | title=No PC demo for Bulletstorm, PC gamers reported 'grumpy',| date=2011-01-17 | publisher=[[Destructoid]] | quote=Sir Clifford of Bleszinski, who I think is handsome and has great hair, upset a few PC gamers today by making a little jab about the lack of a non-console Bulletstorm demo(...)You'd think PC gamers would've gotten used to being screwed by now, but it doesn't take much to set off the hornet's nest. | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.mcvuk.com/news/42574/Bulletstorm-demo-upsets-grumpy-PC-gamers | title=Bulletstorm demo upsets &quot;grumpy&quot; PC gamers | date=2011-01-17 | publisher=mcvuk.com | quote=''PC fans of upcoming shooter Bulletstorm have been described as &quot;grumpy&quot; as disputes emerge over the game’s demo. Epic Games’ Cliff Bleszinski has teased consumers that have already expressed disappointment that only Xbox 360 and PS3 owners will be able to sample the studio’s over-the-top FPS.''| accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both [[Mark Rein]] and the official developer blog have later stated that a PC demo will still happen.&lt;ref&gt;http://twitter.com/MarkRein/status/38750641157443584&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.peoplecanfly.com/blog/2011/02/pc-demo-in-the-works/&lt;/ref&gt; The PC demo was finally released on April 4, and featured the same level as the console versions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newgamenetwork.com/news/2528/bulletstorm-pc-demo-released/ |title=Bulletstorm PC demo released|publisher=[[New Game Network]]|date=2011-04-04|accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 30, 2011, [[Destructoid]] discovered that the [[Electronic Arts]] disclosure page for the game announced that a permanent internet connection was required to play.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.destructoid.com/bulletstorm-pc-requires-persistent-internet-connection-192844.phtml |title=Bulletstorm PC requires persistent Internet (update)| date=2011-01-17 | publisher=[[Destructoid]] | quote=''Fans of PC DRM have something to celebrate today, with news that Bulletstorm will demand a constant online connection in order to be played. More like Bullshitstorm, right guys?'' | date=2011-01-30| accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adrian Chmielarz, a designer at [[People Can Fly]], denied it on his twitter page.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://twitter.com/adrianchm/status/31782783235923968 | title=Bulletstorm | date=2011-01-30 | author=Adrian Chmielarz | quote=''Fucking Internets... No, Bulletstorm PC does not require any constant connection, only for install and for online play (duh!).'' | accessdate=2011-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Marketing and release==
In January 2011, a [[viral video]] for ''Bulletstorm'' was released, parodying the [[Halo 3 marketing|''Halo 3'' &quot;Believe&quot; diorama]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eurogamer.net/videos/bulletstorm-diorama-trailer-looks-familiar |title=Bulletstorm diorama looks very familiar |publisher=Eurogamer Videos |date= |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Television advertisements were aired on major networks and blocks such as [[Spike TV]] and [[Adult Swim]].

This was followed up in February with the release of ''Duty Calls'', a free downloadable PC game that parodies the ''[[Call of Duty]]'' series, as well as general first-person shooter clichés.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Fahey|first=Mike|title=Bulletstorm Mocks Call Of Duty With A Free PC Game|url=http://kotaku.com/5749967/bulletstorm-mocks-call-of-duty-with-a-free-pc-game|publisher=Kotaku|accessdate=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Film director John Stalberg, Jr. was hired to shoot two short films and four 30 second commercial spots that aired on the game's launch program on G4 network. The short films star [[R. Lee Ermey]] and comedian [[Brian Posehn]].

Some of the game footage is featured in the comedy ''[[Bridesmaids (2011 film)|Bridesmaids]]''.

=== Downloadable content ===
On February 22, 2011, Electronic Arts announced ''Gun Sonata'', the first [[downloadable content]] (DLC) for ''Bulletstorm''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ea.com/au/news/epic-unleash-bulletstorm-today|title=Kill with Skill Year-Round as First Bulletstorm Downloadable Content Is Announced|date=2011-02-23|publisher=[[Electronic Arts]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.destructoid.com/paid-gun-sonata-bulletstorm-dlc-announced-194781.phtml|title=Paid 'Gun Sonata' Bulletstorm DLC announced|author=Nick Chester|date=2011-02-22|publisher=[[Destructoid]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The DLC was released on April 14, 2011 on [[PlayStation Store]] and [[Xbox Live Marketplace]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epicgames.com/community/2011/04/bulletstorm-dlc-gun-sonata-pack-brings-more-mayhem-maps/|title=Bulletstorm DLC: Gun Sonata Pack Brings More Mayhem, Maps|date=2011-04-12|publisher=[[Epic Games]] Community}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on May 19, 2011 on [[Games for Windows Marketplace]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shacknews.com/article/68507/bulletstorm-gun-sonata-dlc-comes|title=Bulletstorm 'Gun Sonata' DLC comes to PCs|author=Steve Watts|date=2011-05-19|publisher=[[Shacknews]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The content includes three &quot;Anarchy&quot; maps, two &quot;Echo&quot; missions and two &quot;Leash&quot; colors and adds five [[Xbox Live#Gamerscore|achievements]]/[[PlayStation Network#Trophies|trophies]] (on Games for Windows – Live/Xbox Live and PlayStation Network, respectively).

''Blood Symphony'' was released on June 10, 2011 on [[Games for Windows Marketplace]] and [[Xbox Live Marketplace]], and in July 2011 on the [[PlayStation Store]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://epicgames.com/community/2011/06/over-the-top-mayhem-with-the-bulletstorm-blood-symphony-pack/|title=Over-the-Top Mayhem With the Bulletstorm Blood Symphony Pack|author=Flak|date=2011-06-10|publisher=[[Epic Games]] Community}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.peoplecanfly.com/blog/2011/06/blood-symphony-dlc-pack/|title=Blood Symphony DLC Pack|author=Arcade|date=2011-06-10|publisher=[[People Can Fly]] blog}}&lt;/ref&gt; The content includes 2 &quot;Echoes&quot; maps, 3 &quot;Anarchy&quot; maps, a new mode called &quot;The Ultimate Echoes&quot; and five additional achievements/trophies.

==Reception==
{{VG reviews
|CVG = 9.1/10&lt;ref name=&quot;computerandvideogames1&quot;/&gt;
|GR =
|MC = Xbox 360: 84/100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.metacritic.com/game/xbox-360/bulletstorm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;PC: 82/100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.metacritic.com/game/pc/bulletstorm&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;PS3: 83/100&lt;ref&gt;http://www.metacritic.com/game/playstation-3/bulletstorm&lt;/ref&gt;
|1UP = B-&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/reviews/bulletstorm-review |title=Bulletstorm Review for PS3, 360 from |publisher=1UP.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|DigitalChumps =
|Edge = 9/10
|EuroG = 9 out of 10&lt;ref name=&quot;eurogamer2&quot;/&gt;
|Fam =
|GI = 9.25 out of 10&lt;ref name=&quot;gameinformer1&quot;/&gt;
|XPlay = {{Rating|4|5}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Merrie |url=http://www.g4tv.com/games/ps3/63517/bulletstorm/ |title=Bulletstorm for PS3 |publisher=G4tv |date=2011-02-09 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|GMaster =
|GRadar = 10 out of 10&lt;ref name=&quot;gamesradar1&quot;/&gt;
|GT = 8.6/10&lt;ref name=&quot;GT Review&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gametrailers.com/video/review-bulletstorm/710809 | title=gametrailers.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|GSpot = 8/10&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamespot.com/ps3/action/untitledpeoplecanflyproject/review.html?tag=topslot;thumb;2 |title=Bulletstorm Review for PlayStation 3 |publisher=GameSpot |date= |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|GT =
|IGN = 8 out of 10&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;
|GamePro =
|The Gaming Liberty = 6 out of 10 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thegamingliberty.com/index.php/2011/02/22/bulletstorm-review/ |publisher=The Gaming Liberty.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|VG = 9 out of 10 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.videogamer.com/xbox360/bulletstorm/review.html |title=Bulletstorm Review|publisher=VideoGamer.com |date=2011-02-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

''Bulletstorm'' has received a rather positive reception from critics. The game scored 9.1/10 from CVG,&lt;ref name=&quot;computerandvideogames1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerandvideogames.com/289871/reviews/bulletstorm-review/ |title=Bulletstorm review |publisher=ComputerAndVideoGames.com |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 8/10 from [[IGN]],&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Arthur Gies |url=http://xbox360.ign.com/articles/115/1151242p2.html |title=Bulletstorm Review |publisher=Xbox360.ign.com |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 9/10 from ''Eurogamer'',&lt;ref name=&quot;eurogamer2&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Christian Donlan |url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2011-02-22-bulletstorm-review?page=2 |title=Bulletstorm Review |publisher=Eurogamer.net |date=2011-02-09 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 9.25/10 from ''[[Game Informer]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;gameinformer1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Joe |first=Aronius |url=http://www.gameinformer.com/games/bulletstorm/b/xbox360/archive/2011/02/22/bulletstorm-review-the-fps-genre-gets-a-billion-shots-in-the-arm.aspx |title=Bulletstorm Gives The FPS Genre A Billion Shots In The Arm |publisher=www.GameInformer.com |date=2011-01-28 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; 10/10 from [[GamesRadar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gamesradar1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/xbox360/bulletstorm/review/bulletstorm-review/a-2011021610101452071/g-20100412105850796030/p-3 |title=Bulletstorm review, Bulletstorm Review, Xbox 360 Reviews |publisher=Games Radar.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 8/10 from Jeuxvideo.fr.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jeuxvideo.fr/jeux/bulletstorm/ |title=Bulletstorm Test, Bulletstorm Review, Xbox 360, PS3 and PC Reviews |publisher=JeuxVideo.fr |date= |accessdate=2011-02-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Game Informer''s Tim Turi gave Bulletstorm a 9.25/10, praising the game's degree of character control, which he compared to ''[[Mirror's Edge]]''. He also praised the game's darkly humorous storyline, calling it a &quot;goofy sci-fi romp that doesn't deserve to have its cut-scenes skipped&quot;, and also liked ''Bulletstorm''s complex Skillshot-based combat and weapons system, praising them as very creative. However, he criticized the game's lack of multiplayer maps and the final hours of the campaign, calling it &quot;stale&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gameinformer1&quot;/&gt; [[Eurogamer]] synthesis of the game was that it was &quot;an astonishingly clever game folded up inside an exquisitely stupid one&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/2011-02-22-bulletstorm-review |title=Bulletstorm  |publisher=[[Eurogamer]] |date=2011-02-22 |accessdate=2011-03-02| quote=''Bulletstorm is an astonishingly clever game folded up inside an exquisitely stupid one.''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, several reviewers criticized the game design. For example, [[1UP.com]] and ''[[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]]'' judged that the plot was overly serious considering the focus put by the designers on the gameplay, &quot;dragging the game down.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/reviews/bulletstorm-review |title=Bulletstorm Review |publisher=[[1UP.com]] |date=2011-02-22 |accessdate=2011-03-02| quote=''There's a discrepancy between the Skillshot-heavy gameplay and the overtly serious plot that drags the campaign down. (...)Bulletstorm is a game unsure of what it wants to achieve. When it lets itself, it's a fantastic adrenaline rush through well-constructed set-pieces and gloriously fun-to-watch violence. But it too often drags itself down with overly structured situations and restrictive, strategy-heavy gameplay. (...)as it stands, Bulletstorm is a mechanically enjoyable game that's missing what it needed to be great. ''}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.escapistmagazine.com/articles/view/editorials/reviews/8665-Review-Bulletstorm |title=Review: Bulletstorm |publisher=[[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]]|date=2011-02-22 |accessdate=2011-03-02| quote=''The worst part about Bulletstorm is, in fact, the story, or more precisely the imprecise interjection thereof. It's as if the team couldn't decide if they wanted to make a space opera or a mindless videogame and compromised. Their mistake. Between cutscenes, intentional slowing of the pace and annoying in-mission jabber, the story interrupts the high-octane fun just enough to continually remind you it's there&amp;nbsp;— and is terrible.''}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others considered that the multiplayer part of the game was limited and &quot;gets tiresome&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalbattle.com/2011/02/25/bulletstorm-review/ |title=Bulletstorm review |publisher=digitalbattle.com|date=2011-02-25 |accessdate=2011-03-02| quote=''Multiplayer is quite limited and the mode that’s available quickly gets tiresome ''}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[NoFrag]] found the plot fairly conventional and the dialogues not really funny, and the end of the solo campaign &quot;sugary&quot; contrary to the developers which said that the game was not taking itself too seriously.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nofrag.com/2011/mar/13/37253/ |title=Netsabes et Dr.Loser testent Bulletstorm |publisher=[[NoFrag]]|date=2011-02-25 |accessdate=2011-03-13| quote=''Durant la promo du jeu, Epic n’a cessé de nous répéter que Bulletstorm ne se prenait pas au sérieux : c’est faux. Le scénario est convenu, les dialogues ne sont pas drôles et la campagne se termine dans un mièvre élan dramatique qui n’a rien à envier à un épisode des Feux de l’Amour (During the promotion of the game, Epic repeatedly told us that Bulletstorm did not take himself seriously: it is false. The scenario is conventional, the dialogues aren't funny and the campaign ends in a sugary dramatic momentum that looks like an episode of The Young and the Restless)''}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game was also using too many [[Quick time event|quick time]] and scripted events for their liking, often breaking the flow of the gameplay.

In March 2011, ''Bulletstorm'' sold over 1 million copies.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gamingunion.net/news/bulletstorm-to-top-1-million-fox-news-controversy-kinda-helped--4300.html&lt;/ref&gt;

As of July 25, 2011, Epic Games declared that they had failed to turn a profit on the game.&lt;ref name=&quot;profit&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gamingunion.net/news/bulletstorm-fails-to-turn-profit-for-epic-games--5889.html | title=Bulletstorm Fails To Turn Profit For Epic Games |publisher=GamingUnion.net |date=2011-07-25 |accessdate=2011-07-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controversy===
On February 8, 2011, the game came under scrutiny by [[Fox News Channel|Fox News]] through an article on their website&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/02/08/bulletstorm-worst-game-kids | work=Fox News | title=Is Bulletstorm the Worst Video Game in the World? | date=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; by John Brandon and later on February 20, 2011 through their televised broadcast and another article.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/02/20/bulletstorm-censored-germany-videogame-esrb/ | work=Fox News | title=Bulletstorm: Censored in Germany, Coming to America | date=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game was targeted because of its profanity, crude behavior (examples of which including the game's skill-shot system, which has a move that rewards players for shooting at an enemy's genitals), and sexual innuendo. Alongside the panel of Fox News was psychologist [[Carole Lieberman]], who remarked: &quot;Video games have increasingly, and more brazenly, connected sex and violence in images, actions and words. This has the psychological impact of doubling the excitement, stimulation and incitement to copycat acts. The increase in rapes can be attributed, in large part, to the playing out of such scenes in video games.&quot; Other claims include that the game could reach audiences as young as nine years old, and that the gore and profanity could seriously traumatize a child of that age group. Another argument was offered by a [[University of Maryland]] professor, Melanie Killen, who claimed that the gameplay videos were targeted towards &quot;young adolescents and children.&quot;{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

EA responded to this argument:&lt;ref name = &quot;Fox News Fiasco&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gameinformer.com/b/news/archive/2011/02/08/ea-responds-to-foxnews-39-bulletstorm-slam.aspx| title = EA Responds To FoxNews' Bulletstorm Slam}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Brandon |first=John |url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/02/08/bulletstorm-worst-game-kids/#ixzz1Dbn2pBVZ |title=Is Bulletstorm the Worst Video Game in the World? |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=2010-04-07 |accessdate=2011-02-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;As you know, ''Bulletstorm'' is a work of entertainment fiction... The game and its marketing adhere to all guidelines set forth by the ESRB; both designed for people 17+... Much like Tarantino's ''[[Kill Bill]]'' or Rodriguez's ''[[Sin City (film)|Sin City]]'', this game is an expression of creative entertainment for adults.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Fox News Fiasco&quot; /&gt;

In an interview &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chmielarz|first=Adrian|url=&quot;http://www.telegraaf.nl/digitaal/games/10685638/__Gescheld_in_Bulletstorm_gaat_te_ver__.html&quot;|publisher=telegraaf.nl|date=2011-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; the main developer Adrian Chmielarz stated that English isn't their mother language and that they didn't realise how crude the swearing was. &quot;Swearwords in another language have less impact than in your own language. Those F-words just sounded funny to us. We didn't feel the impact.&quot; However he also admitted: &quot;I swear often, and by that I mean really a lot, and yet I feel a little ashamed for the language in the game.&quot;

Hal Levy of the [[National Youth Rights Association]] said that the game promotes innovative thinking through dispatching enemies in unique ways, and that &quot;Plenty of emotionally unstable adults will play the game and they'll be fine.&quot;{{fact|date=November 2011}}

No legal action was taken by the respective developers, producers, distributors, or the [[ESRB]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Fox News Fiasco&quot; /&gt;

[[Rock, Paper, Shotgun]] analysed Lieberman's claims, and found only one of eight sources she provided had anything to do with the subject at hand.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rockpapershotgun.com/2011/02/15/bulletstormgate-lieberman-offers-evidence/&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.bulletstorm.com/}}

{{Epic}}

[[Category:2011 video games]]
[[Category:Comedy video games]]
[[Category:Electronic Arts games]]
[[Category:Epic Games games]]
[[Category:First-person shooters]]
[[Category:Games for Windows certified games]]
[[Category:PlayStation 3 games]]
[[Category:Science fiction video games]]
[[Category:Unreal Engine games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in Poland]]
[[Category:Windows games]]
[[Category:Xbox 360 games]]

[[cs:Bulletstorm]]
[[de:Bulletstorm]]
[[es:Bulletstorm]]
[[fr:Bulletstorm]]
[[it:Bulletstorm]]
[[ms:Bulletstorm]]
[[pl:Bulletstorm]]
[[ru:Bulletstorm]]
[[simple:Bulletstorm]]
[[fi:Bulletstorm]]
[[sv:Bulletstorm]]
[[uk:Bulletstorm]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
