<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26920" ns="0" title="Sammy Sosa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Sammy Sosa
|image=Sosa swinging4.png
|caption=
|position=[[Right fielder]]
|bats=Right
|throws=Right
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1968|11|12}}
|birth_place=[[San Pedro de Macorís, Dominican Republic]]
|debutdate=June 16
|debutyear=1989
|debutteam=Texas Rangers
|finaldate=September 29
|finalyear=2007
|finalteam=Texas Rangers
|stat1label=[[Batting average]]
|stat1value=.273
|stat2label=[[Home run]]s
|stat2value=609
|stat3label=[[Hit (baseball)|Hits]]
|stat3value=2,408
|stat4label=[[Run batted in|Runs batted in]]
|stat4value=1,667
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] ({{By|1989}})
* [[Chicago White Sox]] ({{By|1989}}–{{By|1991}})
* [[Chicago Cubs]] ({{By|1992}}–{{By|2004}})
* [[Baltimore Orioles]] ({{By|2005}})
* [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] ({{By|2007}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 7× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1995 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1995]], [[1998 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1998]], [[1999 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1999]], [[2000 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2000]], [[2001 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2001]], [[2002 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2002]], [[2004 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|2004]])
* 6× [[Silver Slugger Award]] winner (1995, 1998, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2002)
* 1998 [[NL MVP]]
* 1998 [[Roberto Clemente Award]]
* 1999 [[NL Hank Aaron Award]]
* 2000 [[Home Run Derby]] winner
}}
'''Samuel Peralta &quot;Sammy&quot; Sosa''' (born November 12, 1968) is a [[Dominican Republic|Dominican]] former professional [[baseball]] [[right fielder]]. Sosa played with four [[Major League Baseball]] teams over his career which spanned from 1989-2007.

Sosa's Major League career began with the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]] in {{By|1989}}. After a stint with the [[Chicago White Sox]], Sosa became a member of the [[Chicago Cubs]] in 1992 and subsequently became one of the league's best hitters. In 1998, Sosa and [[Mark McGwire]] achieved national fame for their [[home run]]-hitting prowess [[1998 Major League Baseball home run record chase|in pursuit of Roger Maris' home run record]]. Although a fan favorite, Sosa fell out of favor in Chicago after he was caught using a [[corked bat]] in a 2003 game and later left the team during the final game of the 2004 season. Sosa finished his career with brief stints with the [[Baltimore Orioles]] and the [[Texas Rangers (baseball)|Texas Rangers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBREF.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.baseball-reference.com/s/sosasa01.shtml Sammy Sosa career stats.] Baseball-reference.com. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; With the Rangers, Sosa hit his 600th career home run to become the fifth player in MLB history to reach the milestone. He is also the all-time home run leader among foreign-born MLB players. Furthermore, Sosa is one of only two National League Players to ever reach 160 RBI, a milestone he reached in 2001. The other was Cubs player and RBI Champion [[Hack Wilson]] during his record setting 1930 season in which he hit 191 RBI. Sosa is the only player to have hit 60 or more home runs in a single season three times.

Sosa has long been the subject of speculation about suspected [[anabolic steroid]] use during his playing career. On June 16, 2009, ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported that Sosa had failed a test for performance enhancing drugs in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/17/sports/baseball/17doping.html?_r=1&amp;hp | work=The New York Times | title=Sosa Is Said to Have Tested Positive in 2003 | first=Michael S. | last=Schmidt | date=June 17, 2009 | accessdate=April 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal life==
Sosa is known to family and friends as &quot;Mikey.&quot; His maternal grandmother, who had suggested his birth name of Samuel, also came up with his nickname: &quot;[She] heard the name on a [[soap opera]] she liked and decided from that moment on he would be Mikey.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Sosa: An Autobiography'', Sammy Sosa and Marcos Bretón, Time Warner, 2000, p.16&lt;/ref&gt;

Sosa was born in the [[Dominican Republic]].  Although his officially registered birthplace is San Pedro de Macorís, Sosa was actually born in [[Consuelo, Dominican Republic|Consuelo]]. San Pedro de Macorís was &quot;the largest town nearby.&quot; Both Consuelo and San Pedro de Macorís are in [[San Pedro de Macorís Province]].&lt;ref&gt;''Sosa: An Autobiography,'' Sammy Sosa and Marcos Bretón, Time Warner, 2000, p.23.&lt;/ref&gt; 
Sosa is married to Sonia Sosa.

Sammy Sosa was the source of attention in late 2009 when he appeared publicly with skin that had been lightened. Sosa claims that the cause of this is a skin cream he had been using.&lt;ref name=&quot;ny_daily_2009&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/baseball/2009/11/11/2009-11-11_sammy_sosa.html|title=Former Cubs slugger Sammy Sosa denies suffering from skin condition that plagued Michael Jackson|last=Red|first=Christian |coauthors=Isaac Lopez |date=11 November 2009|work=[[New York Daily News]]|accessdate=12 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;espn_cream&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=4642952|title=Sosa: Cream has bleached skin|last=Rojas|first=Enrique|date=10 November 2009|work=ESPNDeportes.com|accessdate=17 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Major league career==
===Texas Rangers, Chicago White Sox (1989&amp;ndash;1991)===
Sosa made his major league debut on June 16, 1989, with the Texas Rangers, and he hit first career home run off [[Roger Clemens]]. Later in the season, the Rangers traded Sammy to the [[Chicago White Sox]]. He played two full seasons for the White Sox and was traded, along with pitcher [[Ken Patterson]], to the [[Chicago Cubs]] for [[outfielder]] [[George Bell (outfielder)|George Bell]] before the {{By|1992}} season.

===Chicago Cubs (1992&amp;ndash;2004)===
After years as a respected power/speed threat with a rocket arm in right field, he emerged during the {{By|1998}} as one of baseball's greatest. It was in this season that both Sosa and [[Mark McGwire]] were involved in the &quot;[[1998 Major League Baseball home run record chase|home run record chase]]&quot;, when both players' prowess for hitting [[home run]]s drew national attention as they attempted to pass [[Roger Maris]]' single season home run mark of 61 home runs that had stood since {{By|1961}}. Sosa ended the season with 66 (still a team record), behind McGwire's 70. However, Sammy had become the first Major League batter ever to hit 65 homers in a season. Then, McGwire passed him late in the season to become the first ever to hit 70. It was during that season, that Cubs announcer [[Chip Caray]] nicknamed him &quot;'''Slammin' Sammy''',&quot; a nickname that quickly spread.  [[Image:Sosa cubs jersey.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Sosa wore the iconic #21 with the Cubs in honor of his childhood idol [[Roberto Clemente]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last = Cunniff | first = Bill | title = Sosa plays host at party at his island mansion | page = 3 | work = Chicago Sun-Times | date = 1999-11-26 | url = http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=CSTB&amp;p_theme=cstb&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&amp;p_topdoc=1&amp;p_text_direct-0=0EB424463A5BF794&amp;p_field_direct-0=document_id&amp;p_perpage=10&amp;p_sort=YMD_date:D&amp;s_trackval=GooglePM | accessdate = 2008-10-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]  Also in 1998, Sosa's 416 total bases were the most in a single season since [[Stan Musial]]'s 429 in {{By|1948}}. Sosa's performance in the month of June, during which Sosa belted 20 home runs, knocked in 47 runs, and posted an .842 [[slugging percentage]], was one of the greatest offensive outbursts in major league history. Sosa won the [[MLB Most Valuable Player award|National League Most Valuable Player Award]] for leading the Cubs into the playoffs in 1998, earning every first-place vote except for the two cast by [[St. Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]] writers, who voted for McGwire. He and McGwire shared ''[[Sports Illustrated]]'' magazine's 1998 &quot;[[Sportsman of the Year]]&quot; award. Sosa was honored with a [[ticker-tape parade]] in his honor in [[New York City]], and he was invited to be a guest at US President [[Bill Clinton]]'s 1999 [[State of the Union Address]]. 1998 was also the first time the Cubs made the post-season since 1989. The Cubs qualified as the NL Wild Card team, but were swept by the [[Atlanta Braves]] in the [[1998 National League Division Series#Atlanta Braves vs. Chicago Cubs|NLDS]].

In the {{By|1999}} season, Sosa hit 63 home runs, again trailing Mark McGwire who hit 65. In the {{By|2000}} season, Sammy led the league by hitting 50 home runs. He received the [[Babe Ruth Home Run Award]] for leading MLB in homers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=MacMullan |first=Jackie |title=A bronze homage to Babe |date=October 17, 2002 |newspaper=[[The Boston Globe]] |page=E3 |url=http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/boston/access/214273981.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Oct+17%2C+2002&amp;author=JACKIE+MACMULLAN&amp;pub=Boston+Globe&amp;desc=A+BRONZE+HOMAGE+TO+BABE&amp;pqatl=google |accessdate=November 8, 2011 |quote=By 2001, they were paying their own way to present Sammy Sosa with his Babe Ruth Award.}}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In {{By|2001}}, he hit 64 home runs, becoming the first player to hit 60 home runs in three seasons in his career. However, he did not lead the league in any of those seasons; in 2001, he finished behind [[Barry Bonds]], who hit 73 homers, breaking the single-season home run record set by McGwire in 1998 (70). In the same season he set personal records in [[Run (baseball)|runs]] scored (146), [[Run batted in|RBI]] (160), [[Base on balls|walks]] (116), [[on base percentage]] (.437), [[slugging percentage]] (.737), and [[batting average]] (.328).&lt;ref name=&quot;BBREF.com&quot; /&gt; He led the majors in runs and RBI, was 2nd in home runs, 2nd in slugging percentage, 1st in total bases, 3rd in walks, 4th in on base percentage, 12th in batting average, and 15th in [[Hit (baseball)|hits]]. He also surpassed his 1998 number in total bases, racking up 425. Sosa once again led the league in home runs with 49 in {{By|2002}}. Known as a free-swinger in his early years, and as a good [[strikeout]] candidate, Sammy became an effective hitter for average. He owns numerous team records for the Cubs, and he holds the major-league record for the most home runs hit in a month (20, in June 1998). In recognition of his accomplishments as a hitter, Sosa won the [[Silver Slugger]] award (an award for offensive output, voted on by managers and coaches) in {{By|1995}} and in 1998 through 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBREF.com&quot; /&gt;

[[Image:Howmanyout.JPG|thumb|left|200px|Sammy Sosa had three 60+ home run seasons with the Cubs ('98, '99, &amp; '01)]]
In {{By|2003}}, the Cubs won the National League Central Division title. The year was not all good news for Sosa, however. In May, he spent his first period on the [[disabled list]] since {{By|1996}} after having an injured toenail removed. On June 3, 2003, Sosa was ejected from a Chicago Cubs-[[Tampa Bay Rays|Tampa Bay Devil Rays]] game in the first inning when umpires discovered he had been using a [[corked bat]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://static.espn.go.com/mlb/news/2003/0603/1562772.html Sosa ejected after cork is found in shattered bat.] (June 4, 2003) ESPN.com. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt;  Major League Baseball confiscated and tested 76 of Sosa's other bats after his ejection; all were found to be clean, with no cork. Five bats he had sent to the Hall of Fame in past years were also tested, and were all clean as well.&lt;ref&gt;[http://static.espn.go.com/mlb/news/2003/0604/1563115.html Seventy-six Sosa bats found to be clean.] (June 5, 2003). ESPN.com. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; Sosa stated that he had accidentally used the corked bat, which he claimed he only used during batting practice. But they soon interviewed the Cubs' manager, who said that any use of corked bats on his team is strictly prohibited. On June 6, Sosa was suspended for eight games.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/other_sports/us_sport/2970198.stm Sosa banned over bat.] (6 June 2003) BBC Sport. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the suspension was reduced to seven games after appeal on June 11.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/other_sports/us_sport/2983350.stm Sosa has ban reduced.] (12 June 2003) BBC Sport. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; Sosa finished the season with 40 home runs, and he hit two more in the [[2003 National League Championship Series|2003 NLCS]] against the [[Florida Marlins]], but overall, the Cubs lost the series in seven games. According to the ''New York Times'' of June 16, 2009, Sosa had also tested positive for steroids at some point during the season.

In May {{By|2004}}, Sosa suffered an odd injury while sitting next to his locker chatting with reporters before a game in San Diego's [[PETCO Park]]. He sneezed very violently, causing severe back pain. He was diagnosed with back spasms and placed on the disabled list. Later, he fell into one of the worst slumps of his career, only snapping out of it during the last week of the season. He was greatly depressed when the officials told him he couldn't play. He finished with 35 homers, far below his numbers of his best years. The final straw for the Cubs seemed to be an incident in late 2004. Sosa requested to sit out the last game of the season, which was at home against the [[Atlanta Braves]], and he left [[Wrigley Field]] early in the game. It was his last time in a Cubs uniform.

===Baltimore Orioles and year off (2005&amp;ndash;2006)===
[[Image:Sosa Spring training.jpg|thumb|140px|Sosa in spring training with the Orioles in 2005.]]
On January 28, 2005, the Cubs traded Sosa to the [[Baltimore Orioles]] in exchange for [[infielder]]/outfielder [[Jerry Hairston, Jr.]], infielder [[Mike Fontenot]], and RHP Dave Crouthers. To facilitate the deal, Sosa and his [[sports agent|agent]] agreed to waive the clause that guaranteed his 2006 salary, and the [[Major League Baseball Players Association|players' union]] indicated it would not object to that agreement. Under the deal, Sosa earned $17,875,000 for the 2005 season, with the Cubs paying $7 million of his salary. By playing for the 2005 Orioles alongside fellow 500-home-run batter [[Rafael Palmeiro]], Sosa and Palmeiro became the first [[500 home run club]] members in history to play together on the same team after reaching the 500 home run plateau.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hank Aaron]] reached 500 homers shortly after his teammate [[Eddie Matthews]] (512 homers) retired.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sosa finished the 2005 season batting .221 with 14 home runs, his worst performance since 1992, and continuing his post-2001 trend of declines in batting average, homers, total bases, and RBI. On December 7, 2005, the Orioles decided not to offer him an arbitration contract, effectively ending his Baltimore Orioles tenure and making him a free agent.

In 2005, ''[[The Sporting News]]'' published an update of their 1999 book ''Baseball's 100 Greatest Players''. Sosa did not make the original edition, but for the 2005 update, with his career totals considerably higher, he was ranked at Number 95. During a stretch of nine consecutive years, Sosa hit 35+ home runs and 100+ RBIs, all with the Chicago Cubs.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBREF.com&quot; /&gt;

At the end of January 2006, the [[Washington Nationals]] offered Sosa two different minor-league offers, both of which he turned down. On February 15, 2006, Sosa's agent Adam Katz stated: &quot;We're not going to put him on the retirement list. We decided that [not putting him on that list] was the best thing to do. But I can say, with reasonable certainty, that we've seen Sammy in a baseball uniform for the last time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jayson Stark (February 16, 2006). [http://espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=2332063 Sosa passes on Nats; likely to end career.] ESPN.com. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt;

During this year, Sosa accompanied [[Leonel Fernández|President Fernandez]] of the Dominican Republic on several diplomatic trips including to the [[United States]], [[Japan]], and [[Taiwan]].

===Recent years (2007-2009)===
The Texas Rangers, Sosa's original team, signed him to a minor league deal worth $500,000 on January 30, 2007. This was the same contract that Sosa turned down the previous year from the Nationals. The contract included an invitation to [[spring training]], where Sosa competed for a spot in the lineup with [[Nelson Cruz (outfielder)|Nelson Cruz]], [[Jason Botts]], and other rookies/prospects.&lt;ref&gt;T. R. Sullivan (January 17, 2007). [http://texas.rangers.mlb.com/NASApp/mlb/news/article.jsp?ymd=20070117&amp;content_id=1780982&amp;vkey=news_tex&amp;fext=.jsp&amp;c_id=tex Sosa, Rangers agree in principle to deal.] MLB.com. Accessed 2007-06-05.&lt;/ref&gt; Sosa was successful during spring training and was added to the team's 25-man roster. He started the 2007 season as the Rangers' designated hitter and occasional right fielder.

At the same time, the Chicago Cubs awarded Sosa's # 21 to new pitcher [[Jason Marquis]], despite the fact that it was formerly worn by Sosa, who coincidentally later hit his 600th home run against Marquis.  This caused some concern, due to Sosa's accomplishments with the Cubs, including his status as the Cubs' all-time home run leader.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.suntimes.com/sports/deluca/268111,CST-SPT-deluca22.article De Luca, Chris, &quot;Sosa's 21 a long-distance number,&quot; ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', accessed 6/6/07]&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 26, 2007, Sosa made history by hitting a home run in his 45th major league ballpark. He has also homered in [[Champion Stadium|The Ballpark at Disney's Wide World of Sports]], near [[Orlando, Florida]], a usually minor-league and [[Spring Training]] park that hosted a regular season series between the Rangers and the [[Tampa Bay Rays|Tampa Bay Devil Rays]] in May 2007, although he did not hit a homer at the two regular season games the Cubs played at the Tokyo Dome in 2000 vs. the Mets.

On June 20, 2007, Sosa hit a home run off of [[Jason Marquis]] during an inter-league game against the Chicago Cubs. Sammy became only the fifth man in history, following [[Babe Ruth]], [[Willie Mays]], [[Hank Aaron]], and [[Barry Bonds]], to hit 600 regular season home runs. 

The home run was the first one that Sosa had recorded against the Cubs, and as a result he has hit a home run against every active MLB team. Sosa is the Cubs' all-time home run leader, having hit 545 with that team.

On May 28, {{By|2008}}, Sosa announced that he instructed his agent not to offer his services to any Major League team for the 2008 season, and planned on filing for retirement, but never did.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=3415614|title=Sosa not pursuing MLB job, says he intends to retire in 2009|accessdate=2008-10-03 |work=ESPN.com|publisher= |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 25, 2008, Sosa announced he intended to unretire and play in the [[World Baseball Classic]] and once again test the free agent market in hopes of signing for a Major League ballclub in 2009. Sosa said that he had been keeping in shape at his home, and was hoping that after a strong World Baseball Classic he would prove to major-league teams that he was still capable of playing in the MLB. However, he was not selected as part of the Dominican Republic's roster.  He remained a free agent and did not actively look for a team.

On June 3, 2009, Sosa announced his intention to retire from Major League Baseball. He made the announcement in the Dominican Republic and said that he was calmly looking forward to his induction into the Baseball Hall of Fame since his statistics were up to par.&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=4229022&lt;/ref&gt;

== Drug test controversy ==
On June 16, 2009 the ''[[New York Times]]'' reported Sosa was on a list of players who tested positive for performance-enhancing drugs in 2003. The paper did not identify the drug.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/17/sports/baseball/17doping.html | work=The New York Times | title=Sosa Is Said to Have Tested Positive in 2003 | first=Michael S. | last=Schmidt | date=June 17, 2009 | accessdate=April 10, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sosa's agent, Adam Katz, told The [[Associated Press]] he had no comment on the report. Rich Levin, commissioner [[Bud Selig]]'s office spokesman, declined to comment on the situation, claiming that the MLB did not have a copy of the test results. Michael Weiner, the union general counsel, also declined comment. The union, while fighting to get the list back from the government, has mostly refused to discuss reports about the list because it does not want to confirm or deny who is on it.

Previously, Sosa sat alongside [[Rafael Palmeiro]], [[Jose Canseco]] and [[Mark McGwire]] at a 2005 hearing before Congress. His attorney testified on his behalf,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Michael | last=McCann | coauthors= |authorlink= | title=Will steroids report lead to perjury investigation of Sammy Sosa? | date=2009-06-16 | publisher=[[Sports Illustrated]] | url =http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2009/writers/michael_mccann/06/16/sammy.sosa/index.html | work = | pages = | accessdate = 2009-06-18 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; stating &quot;To be clear, I have never taken illegal performance-enhancing drugs. I have never injected myself or had anyone inject me with anything. I have not broken the laws of the United States or the laws of the Dominican Republic. I have been tested as recently as 2004, and I am clean.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://sports.espn.go.com/mlb/news/story?id=4264062&lt;/ref&gt;

In a recent interview with [[ESPN Deportes]], Sosa said he would &quot;calmly wait&quot; for his induction into baseball's Hall of Fame, for which he will become eligible in 2013. His comment angered many people and again brought up the argument of positive drug testing players being accepted into the Hall of Fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://insider.espn.go.com/espn/blog/index?entryID=4265535&amp;name=olney_buster&amp;action=login&amp;appRedirect=http%3a%2f%2finsider.espn.go.com%2fespn%2fblog%2findex%3fentryID%3d4265535%26name%3dolney_buster|title= Sosa a reason to re-examine PED blame game|date=2009-06-17|work=ESPN|accessdate=2009-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Commons category}} 
{{wikiquote}}
*[[30-30 club]]
*[[50 home run club]]
*[[500 home run club]]
*[[Maris–McGwire–Sosa pair]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball Home Run Records]]
*[[List of top 300 Major League Baseball home run hitters]]
*[[List of major league players with 2,000 hits]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 runs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball players with 1000 RBIs]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career stolen bases]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball RBI champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball home run champions]]
*[[List of Major League Baseball runs scored champions]]
*[[1998 Major League Baseball home run record chase]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Baseballstats |mlb= |espn=2187 |br=s/sosasa01 |fangraphs= 302|cube=s/sammy-sosa|brm=sosa--001sam}}
*[http://www.latinosportslegends.com/sosa.htm Latino Sports Legends] - extended biography and photos

{{s-start-collapsible|header={{s-ach}}}}
{{succession box | before = [[Dante Bichette]]&lt;br&gt;[[Mark McGwire]]&lt;br&gt;[[Matt Williams (third baseman)|Matt Williams]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jeff Kent]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jeff Bagwell]] | title = [[MLB Player of the Month|National League Player of the Month]]| years = July 1996&lt;br&gt;June 1998&lt;br&gt;May 1999&lt;br&gt;July 2000&lt;br&gt;August 2001 | after = [[Ken Caminiti]]&lt;br&gt;[[Vladimir Guerrero]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jeromy Burnitz]]&lt;br&gt;[[Todd Helton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Barry Bonds]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball home run champions|National League Home Run Champion]] | before=[[Mark McGwire]]&lt;br&gt;[[Barry Bonds]] | years={{By|2000}}&lt;br&gt;{{By|2002}}| after=[[Barry Bonds]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jim Thome]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball RBI champions|National League RBI Champion]] | before= [[Andrés Galarraga]]&lt;br&gt;[[Todd Helton]]| years={{By|1998}}&lt;br&gt;{{By|2001}} | after= [[Mark McGwire]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lance Berkman]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Larry Walker]] | title = [[MLB Most Valuable Player award|National League Most Valuable Player]]| years = 1998 | after = [[Chipper Jones]]}}
{{succession box | before = None | title = [[Hank Aaron Award|National League Hank Aaron Award]]| years = {{By|1999}} | after = [[Todd Helton]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Ken Griffey, Jr.]] | title = [[Home Run Derby|Home Run Derby Champion]]| years = 2000 | after = [[Luis Gonzalez (outfielder)|Luis Gonzalez]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Commissioner's Historic Achievement Award}}
{{NL MVPs}}
{{NL home run champions}}
{{NL OF Silver Slugger Award}}
{{Roberto Clemente Award}}
{{Marvin Miller Man of the Year Award}}{{SI Sportsman of the Year}}{{SN Sportsman of the Year}}
{{NL Hank Aaron Award Winners}}
{{Home Run Derby champions}}
{{500 home run club}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Sosa, Sammy
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 12, 1968
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[San Pedro de Macorís, Dominican Republic]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Sosa, Sammy}}
[[Category:American people of Dominican Republic descent]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players from the Dominican Republic]]
[[Category:Dominican Republic emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Baltimore Orioles players]]
[[Category:Chicago Cubs players]]
[[Category:Chicago White Sox players]]
[[Category:Texas Rangers players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball right fielders]]
[[Category:Drugs in sport in the United States]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:National League home run champions]]
[[Category:National League RBI champions]]
[[Category:500 home run club]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball controversies]]
[[Category:Naturalized citizens of the United States]]
[[Category:Gulf Coast Rangers players]]
[[Category:Gastonia Rangers players]]
[[Category:Charlotte Rangers players]]
[[Category:Tulsa Drillers players]]
[[Category:Vancouver Canadians players]]
[[Category:Oklahoma City 89ers players]]
[[Category:Iowa Cubs players]]
[[Category:West Tennessee Diamond Jaxx players]]
[[Category:People from San Pedro de Macorís]]
[[Category:1968 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[de:Sammy Sosa]]
[[es:Sammy Sosa]]
[[fr:Sammy Sosa]]
[[ko:새미 소사]]
[[it:Sammy Sosa]]
[[mr:सॅमी सोसा]]
[[nl:Sammy Sosa]]
[[ja:サミー・ソーサ]]
[[ru:Соса, Самми]]
[[simple:Sammy Sosa]]
[[fi:Sammy Sosa]]
[[sv:Sammy Sosa]]
[[zh:萨米·索萨]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
