<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="26957914" ns="0" title="Adam Barton (Emmerdale)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">''For the English footballer see [[Adam Barton]]''
{{in-universe|date=April 2010}}
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|name= Adam Barton
|introducer=Gavin Blyth
|image=[[File:Adam BartonED.jpg|200px]]
|caption= Adam Thomas as Adam Barton (2010)
|portrayer=[[Adam Thomas]]
|born= &lt;!--21 April 1992--&gt;
|years= 2009—
|first=17 July 2009
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|mother=[[Moira Barton]]
|father=[[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]]
|occupation=Farmer 
|home=Butlers Farm
|sisters=[[Holly Barton]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hannah Barton]]
}}
'''Adam Barton''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] from the British soap opera ''[[Emmerdale]]'', played by [[Adam Thomas]]. He made his first on-screen appearance on 17 July 2009. He is the son of [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John]] and [[Moira Barton]].

==Creation and casting==
In May 2009, it was announced that ''Emmerdale's'' new series producer, [[Gavin Blyth]], would introduce The Bartons, a new farming family, as part of an ongoing overhaul of the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a156759/emmerdale-casts-sexy-farming-family.html|title='Emmerdale' casts 'sexy' farming family|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|last=Green|first=Kris|date=22 May 2009|accessdate=8 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The family, which comprises of five members - mother, father, two daughters and a son - took over the running of Butler's Farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt; Of the family, Blyth said &quot;I don't want to make Emmerdale a show about teenagers and young people, it's about family values. The Bartons are sexy, modern and contemporary. They're almost happy - and in soapland that's quite strange!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a159417/gavin-blyth-series-producer-emmerdale.html|title=Gavin Blyth (Series Producer, 'Emmerdale')|date=12 June 2009|first=Kris|last=Green|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=8 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Natalie J. Robb]] and [[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]] were cast in the roles of parents, [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John]] and [[Moira Barton|Moira]]. [[Sophie Powles]] and [[Grace Cassidy]] were cast their daughters, [[Holly Barton|Holly]] and [[Hannah Barton|Hannah]] respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewFamily&quot;/&gt;

Speaking of his casting, Thomas said that &quot;Adam's a family man... Whatever his dad says, he does. The whole family is really close. Even with his sisters, he's the middle child but he wants to be the older brother and look after them all.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a163689/adam-thomas-adam-barton-emmerdale.html http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/a163689/adam-thomas-adam-barton-emmerdale.html].&lt;/ref&gt;

==Storylines==
Towards the end of 2009, [[Holly Barton]] starts flirting with Aaron and it looks as though a relationship is brewing between them. At first, Adam isn't keen on the idea but comes round, making friends with [[Aaron Livesy]]. When Aaron suddenly starts playing hard to get with Holly, Adam questions it, but Aaron says its all part of the plan, but everything slots into place when the boys and Holly go on a &quot;lads&quot; night out. When Aaron and Adam are on the way back, they are involved in a car crash and Aaron cuts his head. As Adam is checking it out, Aaron leans in for a kiss.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/spoilers/a188626/aaron-tries-to-kiss-adam.html http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/spoilers/a188626/aaron-tries-to-kiss-adam.html].&lt;/ref&gt; Adam is horrified and pulls away, questioning Aaron's sexuality, but Aaron makes him think it's all in his head. Not completely convinced, he tells Holly after realising that she has slept with Aaron but his parents insist he drops it when Holly, refusing to believe Adam, gets annoyed with him. Aaron watches jealously as Adam gets closer to [[Scarlett Nicholls]] and starts dating her.

In the beginning of 2010 Adam is still convinced that Aaron is gay, but begins to lay off Aaron. Adam also learns of Hannah's bullying, but is confused as to why Victoria did it.
When sheep on the Bartons' farm are being born dead John is certain something's up doesn't know what. When [[Carl King]]'s kids Thomas and Anya are hospitalised the blame is pointed at the Jai and Nikhil, but test are done that prove their not to blame. Adam remembers moving some toxic filled barrels a few months back and when he investigates where he moved them he's shocked to discover he's to blame for it all. When he confesses to his parents John goes mad and after shouting at Adam decided they must come clean to the village. After being fined by [[Nathan Wylde]] for the spillage clean up John stops Adam's wages until the bill is paid. Adam is left gutted by his actions.
In April Adam witness Aaron kissing secret boyfriend Jackson and is positive of his sexuality. But tells Aaron whether he's gay or not he'll still be his mate and promises not to tell any one. On his birthday Adam and punters at the Woolpack witness Aaron punch Jackson, after Aaron thinks he's coming on to him in public, resulting in Aaron being arrested. When released Aaron decides he can no longer risk people finding out he's gay and attempts suicide in the garage. When Adam and [[Cain Dingle]] discover him they try to save him and they succeed, but Aaron later reveals in hospital he wishes he had died.

Adam (along with his whole family) struggles to come to terms with his sister Holly's addiction to heroin. Sometimes accompanying her to methadone handouts, enduring the toughness of living with an addict. He takes her to see Jackson Walsh who (after a horrific accident) has lost his ability to walk, Adam tries to show Holly that, she (unlike Jackson) can choose to get better and has gotten herself into this mess all of her own doing. The message doesn't really sink in with Holly however. Aaron is also annoyed the Adam used Jackson to get this message across to his sister.

Towards the end of 2010. Scarlett discovers Adam has less and less time for her, ignoring her phone calls and text messages. This decline in their relationship finally culminates in Adam kissing Mia Macey on new years' eve. Devastated by this, Scarlett leaves for a holiday in Canada. 
With the current situation as it is Adam is currently trying to pursue [[Mia Macey]] she however so far, is playing hard to get.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Emmerdale characters|present}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Barton, Adam}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2009]]
[[Category:Fictional farmers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
