<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27024" ns="0" title="Economy of South Korea"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox economy
|country              = South Korea
|image                = Teheran Ave night.jpg
|width                = 
|caption              = 
|currency             = [[South Korean Won]] (KRW)
|fixed exchange       =
|year                 = 
|organs               = [[Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation|APEC]], [[WTO]], [[OECD]], [[G-20]]
|rank                 = [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|15th]] (nominal) / [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|12th]] (PPP)
|gdp                  = [[Purchasing power parity|PPP]]: $1.423 trillion (2010 est.)&lt;br /&gt;Nominal: $1.007 trillion (2010 est.)
|growth               = 6.1% (2010 est.)
|per capita           = PPP: $30,200 (2010 est.)&lt;br&gt;Nominal: $20,265 (2010 est.)
|sectors              = agriculture (3.0%), industry (39.4%), services (57.6%) (2008 est.)
|components           = 
|inflation            = 3% (2010 est.)
|poverty              = 2% (2004 est.)
|gini                 = 31.4 (2009)
|labor                = 24.62 million (2010 est.)
|occupations          = agriculture: 7.3%; industry: 24.3%; services: 68.4% (2010 est.)
|unemployment         = 3.3% (2010 est.)
|average gross salary = 
|average net salary   = 
|industries           = [[electronics]], [[telecommunications]], [[automobile]] production, [[chemicals]], [[shipbuilding]], [[steel]]
|edbr                 = 8th&lt;ref name=&quot; World Bank and International Financial Corporation &quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.doingbusiness.org/data/exploreeconomies/korea/|title= Doing Business in Korea, Rep. 2012|publisher=[[World Bank]]|accessdate=2011-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|exports              = $466.3 billion ([[List of countries by exports|6th]]; 2010 est.)
|export-goods         = semiconductors, wireless telecommunications equipment, motor vehicles, computers, steel, ships, petrochemicals
|export-partners      = [[People's Republic of China|China]] 23.2%, [[United States]] 10.1%, [[Japan]] 5.8%, [[Hong Kong]] 5.3% (2009 est.)
|imports              = $417.9 billion ([[List of countries by imports|8th]]; 2010 est.)
|import-goods         = machinery, electronics and electronic equipment, oil, steel, transport equipment, organic chemicals, plastics
|import-partners      = [[People's Republic of China|China]] 16.8%, [[Japan]] 15.3%, [[United States]] 9%, [[Saudi Arabia]] 6.1%, [[Australia]] 4.6% (2009 est.)
|FDI                  = abroad: $115.6 billion (31 December 2009)
|gross external debt  = $380.6 billion (31 December 2010 est.)
|debt                 = 23.7% of GDP (2010 est.)
|deficit              = 
|revenue              = $248.3 billion (2010 est.)
|expenses             = $267.3 billion (2010 est.)
|aid                  = ODA, $900 million ([[Development Assistance Committee|donor]]) (2009)&lt;ref name=oda /&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;aid to North Korea excluded&lt;/small&gt;
|credit               =
*[[Standard &amp; Poor's]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Sovereigns rating list |publisher=Standard &amp; Poor's |url=http://www.standardandpoors.com/ratings/sovereigns/ratings-list/en/eu/?subSectorCode=39 |accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;A+ (Domestic)&lt;br&gt;A (Foreign)&lt;br&gt;AA- (T&amp;C Assessment)&lt;br&gt;Outlook: Stable&lt;ref name=guardian&gt;{{cite news |title=How Fitch, Moody's and S&amp;P rate each country's credit rating |date=15 April 2011 |first1=Simon |last1=Rogers |first2=Ami |last2=Sedghi |work=The Guardian |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/datablog/2010/apr/30/credit-ratings-country-fitch-moodys-standard |accessdate=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Moody's]]:&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt;&lt;br&gt;A1&lt;br&gt;Outlook: Stable
*[[Fitch Group|Fitch]]:&lt;ref name=guardian/&gt;&lt;br&gt;A+&lt;br&gt;Outlook: Stable
|reserves             = US$298.806 billion (March 2011)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=International Reserves and Foreign Currency Liquidity - KOREA, REPUBLIC OF |date=22 April 2011 |publisher=International Monetary Fund |url=http://www.imf.org/external/np/sta/ir/IRProcessWeb/data/kor/eng/curkor.htm |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|cianame              = ks
|spelling             = 
}}

[[South Korea]] has a [[market economy]] which ranks [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|15th]] in the world by [[nominal GDP]] and [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|12th]] by [[purchasing power parity]] (PPP), identifying it as one of the [[G-20 major economies]]. It is a [[High-income economies|high-income]] [[developed country]], with a [[developed market]], and is a member of [[OECD]]. South Korea is one of the [[Four Asian Tigers|Asian Tigers]], and is the only developed country so far to have been included in the group of [[Next Eleven]] countries. South Korea had one of the world's fastest growing economies from the early 1960s to the late 1990s, and South Korea is still one of the fastest growing developed countries in the 2000s, along with [[Hong Kong]], [[Singapore]], and [[Taiwan]], the other three members of Asian Tigers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2010/01/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2008&amp;ey=2015&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=18&amp;pr1.y=5&amp;c=193%2C542%2C122%2C137%2C124%2C181%2C156%2C138%2C423%2C196%2C935%2C142%2C128%2C182%2C172%2C576%2C132%2C936%2C134%2C961%2C174%2C184%2C532%2C144%2C176%2C146%2C178%2C528%2C436%2C112%2C136%2C111%2C158&amp;s=NGDP_RPCH&amp;grp=0&amp;a=|title=Economic Growth Rates of Advanced Economies|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Koreans refer to this growth as the [[Miracle on the Han River]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=nTCC2ZheFu0C&amp;pg=PA254&amp;lpg=PA254&amp;dq=han+river+miracle&amp;q=han%20river%20miracle|title=Korea, A Century of Change|isbn=9789810246570|author1=Kleiner, JüRgen|year=2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having almost no natural resources and always suffering from overpopulation in its small territory, which deterred continued population growth and the formation of a large internal consumer market, South Korea adapted an export-oriented economic strategy to fuel its economy, and in 2010, South Korea was the [[List of countries by exports|seventh largest exporter]] and [[List of countries by imports|tenth largest importer]] in the world. 

Despite the South Korean economy's high growth potential and apparent structural stability, South Korea suffers perpetual damage to its credit rating in the stock market due to the belligerence of [[North Korea]] in times of deep military crises, which has an adverse effect on the financial markets of the South Korean economy.&lt;ref name=kcredit&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.chosun.com/site/data/html_dir/2010/08/02/2010080201090.html|title=Moody's Raises Korea's Credit Range|publisher=Chosun Ilbo|date=2010-08-02|accessdate=2010-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hani.co.kr/arti/english_edition/e_business/422572.html|title=Financial markets unstable in S.Korea following Cheonan sinking|publisher=Hankyeoreh|date=2010-05-26|accessdate=2010-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, renowned financial organizations, such as the [[International Monetary Fund]], also compliment the resilience of the South Korean economy against various economic crises, citing low state debt, and high fiscal reserves that can quickly be mobilized to address any expected financial emergencies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/business/2010-09/07/c_13482842.htm|title=S Korea stands among world's highest-level fiscal reserve holders: IMF|publisher=Xinhua|date=2010-09-07|accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korea was one of the few developed countries that was able to avoid a [[recession]] during the [[Financial crisis of 2007–2010|global financial crisis]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/blogs/wealth-of-nations/2010/05/10/south-korea-survived-recession-with-ceo-tactics.html|title=South Korea Survived Recession With CEO Tactics|publisher=Newsweek|date=2010-05-10|accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; and its economic growth rate will reach 6.1% in 2010,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.chosun.com/site/data/html_dir/2010/09/02/2010090200971.html|title=IMF Raises Growth Forecast for Korea to 6.1%|publisher=Chosun Ilbo|date=2010-09-02|accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; a sharp recovery from economic growth rates of 2.3% in 2008 and 0.2% in 2009 when the global financial crisis hit.

South Korea was a historical recipient of official development assistance (ODA) from OECD. Throughout the 1980s until the mid 1990s, South Korea's economic prosperity as measured in GDP by PPP per capita was still only a fraction of industrialized nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2010/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=1980&amp;ey=2015&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=54&amp;pr1.y=10&amp;c=193%2C542%2C122%2C137%2C124%2C181%2C156%2C138%2C423%2C196%2C935%2C142%2C128%2C182%2C172%2C576%2C132%2C936%2C134%2C961%2C174%2C184%2C532%2C144%2C176%2C146%2C178%2C528%2C436%2C112%2C136%2C111%2C158&amp;s=PPPPC&amp;grp=0&amp;a=|title=Advanced Economies GDP by PPP per capita|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, the South Korean GDP per capita was $2,300, about one-third of nearby developed Asian economies such as Singapore, Hong Kong, and Japan. Since then, South Korea has advanced into a developed economy to eventually attain a GDP per capita of $30,000 in 2010, almost thirteen times the figure thirty years ago. The whole country's GDP increased from $88 billion to $1,460 billion in the same time frame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2010/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=1980&amp;ey=2015&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=43&amp;pr1.y=20&amp;c=542&amp;s=PPPGDP&amp;grp=0&amp;a=|title=Korea: Gross domestic product based on purchasing-power-parity (PPP)|publisher=International Monetary Fund|accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, South Korea officially became the first major recipient of ODA to have ascended to the status of a major donor of ODA.&lt;ref name=oda&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/nation/2010/08/120_56004.html|title=Korea to Join Donors Club Wednesday|publisher=Korea Times|date=2009-11-23|accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Between 2008 and 2009, South Korea donated economic aid of $1.7 billion to countries other than [[North Korea]]. South Korea's separate annual economic aid to North Korea has historically been more than twice its ODA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.odakorea.go.kr/eng/include/faq.php|title=Why is Korea’s ODA disbursements relatively smaller than those of other donor countries?|publisher=ODA Korea|accessdate=2010-10-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:A Whale.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|[[Shipbuilding#Modern worldwide shipbuilding industry|Shipbuilding]] is a flagship industry of South Korea that boomed since the 1960s.]]

The growth of the industrial sector was the principal stimulus to economic development. In 1986, manufacturing industries accounted for approximately 30 percent of the gross domestic product (GDP) and 25 percent of the work force. Benefiting from strong domestic encouragement and foreign aid, Seoul's industrialists introduced modern technologies into outmoded or newly built facilities at a rapid pace, increased the production of commodities—especially those for sale in foreign markets—and plowed the proceeds back into further industrial expansion. As a result, industry altered the country's landscape, drawing millions of laborers to urban manufacturing centers.

A downturn in the South Korean economy in 1989 spurred by a sharp decrease in exports and foreign orders caused deep concern in the industrial sector. Ministry of Trade and Industry analysts stated that poor export performance resulted from structural problems embedded in the nation's economy, including an overly strong won, increased wages and high labor costs, frequent strikes, and high interest rates. The result was an increase in inventories and severe cutbacks in production at a number of electronics, automobile, and textile manufacturers, as well as at the smaller firms that supplied the parts. Factory automation systems were introduced to reduce dependence on labor, to boost productivity with a much smaller work force, and to improve competitiveness. It was estimated that over two-thirds of South Korea's manufacturers spent over half of the funds available for facility investments on automation.

===Rapid growth from 1960s to 1980s===
South Korea's real [[gross domestic product]] expanded by an average of more than 8 percent per year, from US$2.7 billion in 1962&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/eco_gdp-economy-gdp&amp;date=1962&lt;/ref&gt; to US$230 billion in 1989,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/eco_gdp-economy-gdp&amp;date=1989&lt;/ref&gt; breaking the trillion dollar mark in 2007. Nominal GDP per capita grew from $103.88 in 1962&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/eco_gdp_percap-economy-gdp-per-capita&amp;date=1962&lt;/ref&gt; to $5,438.24 in 1989,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nationmaster.com/graph/eco_gdp_percap-economy-gdp-per-capita&amp;date=1989&lt;/ref&gt; reaching the $20,000 milestone in 2007. The manufacturing sector grew from 14.3 percent of the GNP in 1962 to 30.3 percent in 1987. Commodity trade volume rose from US$480 million in 1962 to a projected US$127.9 billion in 1990. The ratio of [[saving (money)|domestic savings]] to GNP grew from 3.3 percent in 1962 to 35.8 percent in 1989.

The most significant factor in rapid industrialization was the adoption of an outward-looking strategy in the early 1960s. This strategy was particularly well suited to that time because of South Korea's poor natural resource endowment, low savings rate, and tiny domestic market. The strategy promoted economic growth through labor-intensive manufactured exports, in which South Korea could develop a competitive advantage. Government initiatives played an important role in this process. The inflow of foreign capital was greatly encouraged to supplement the shortage of domestic savings. These efforts enabled South Korea to achieve rapid growth in exports and subsequent increases in income.

By emphasizing the industrial sector, Seoul's export-oriented development strategy left the rural sector relatively underdeveloped. Except for mining, most industries were located in the urban areas of the northwest and southeast. Heavy industries generally were located in the south of the country. Factories in Seoul contributed over 25 percent of all manufacturing value-added in 1978; taken together with factories in surrounding Gyeonggi Province, factories in the Seoul area produced 46 percent of all manufacturing that year. Factories in Seoul and Gyeonggi Province employed 48 percent of the nation's 2.1 million factory workers.  Increasing income disparity between the industrial and agricultural sectors became a serious problem by the 1970s and remained a problem, despite government efforts to raise farm income and improve rural living standards.

====Shipbuilding====
During the 1970s and 1980s, South Korea became a leading producer of ships, including oil supertankers, and oil-drilling platforms. The country's major shipbuilder was Hyundai, which built a 1-million-ton capacity drydock at Ulsan in the mid-1970s. Daewoo joined the shipbuilding industry in 1980 and finished a 1.2-million-ton facility at Okpo on Geoje Island, south of Busan, in mid-1981. The industry declined in the mid-1980s because of the oil glut and because of a worldwide recession. There was a sharp decrease in new orders in the late 1980s; new orders for 1988 totaled 3 million gross tons valued at US$1.9 billion, decreases from the previous year of 17.8 percent and 4.4 percent, respectively. These declines were caused by labor unrest, Seoul's unwillingness to provide financial assistance, and Tokyo's new low-interest export financing in support of Japanese shipbuilders. However, the South Korean shipping industry was expected to expand in the early 1990s because older ships in world fleets needed replacing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-12311.html|title=South Korea: Shipbuilding|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korea eventually became the world's dominant shipbuilder with a 50.6% share of the [[Shipbuilding#World shipbuilding industry in the 21st century|global shipbuilding market]] as of 2008. Notable Korean shipbuilders are [[Hyundai Heavy Industries]], [[Samsung Heavy Industries]], [[Daewoo Shipbuilding &amp; Marine Engineering]], and [[STX Offshore &amp; Shipbuilding]], the world's four largest shipbuilding companies. South Korea also owns [[STX Europe]], which is [[Europe]]'s largest shipbuilder.

====Automobile====
The automobile industry was one of South Korea's major growth and export industries in the 1980s. By the late 1980s, the capacity of the South Korean motor industry had increased more than fivefold since 1984; it exceeded 1 million units in 1988. Total investment in car and car-component manufacturing was over US$3 billion in 1989. Total production (including buses and trucks) for 1988 totaled 1.1 million units, a 10.6 percent increase over 1987, and grew to an estimated 1.3 million vehicles (predominantly passenger cars) in 1989. Almost 263,000 passenger cars were produced in 1985—a figure that grew to approximately 846,000 units in 1989. In 1988 automobile exports totaled 576,134 units, of which 480,119 units (83.3 percent) were sent to the United States. Throughout most of the late 1980s, much of the growth of South Korea's automobile industry was the result of a surge in exports; 1989 exports, however, declined 28.5 percent from 1988. This decline reflected sluggish car sales to the United States, especially at the less expensive end of the market, and labor strife at home.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-12312.html|title=South Korea: Automobiles and Automotive Parts|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korea today has developed into one of world's [[List of countries by motor vehicle production|largest automobile producers]]. [[Hyundai Kia Automotive Group]] is Korea's largest automaker.

====Mining====
Most of the mineral deposits in the Korean Peninsula are located in North Korea, with the South only possessing an abundance of tungsten and graphite. Coal, iron ore, and molybdenum are found in South Korea, but not in large quantities and mining operations are on a small scale. Much of South Korea's minerals and ore are imported from other countries. Most South Korean coal is low-grade anthracite that is only used for heating homes and boilers.

====Construction====

Construction has been an important South Korean export industry since the early 1960s and remains a critical source of foreign currency and ''invisible'' export earnings. By 1981 overseas construction projects, most of them in the Middle East, accounted for 60 percent of the work undertaken by South Korean construction companies. Contracts that year were valued at US$13.7 billion. In 1988, however, overseas construction contracts totaled only US$2.6 billion (orders from the Middle East were US$1.2 billion), a 1 percent increase over the previous year, while new orders for domestic construction projects totaled US$13.8 billion, an 8.8 percent increase over 1987. The result was that South Korean construction companies concentrated on the rapidly growing domestic market in the late 1980s. By 1989 there were signs of a revival of the overseas construction market—the Dong Ah Construction Company signed a US$5.3 billion contract with Libya for the second phase of Libya's [[Great Manmade River|Great Man-Made River Project]], which, when all five phases were completed, was projected to cost US$27 billion. South Korean construction companies signed over US$7 billion of overseas contracts in 1989.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-12314.html|title=South Korea: Construction|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt; Korea's largest construction companies include [[Samsung C&amp;T Corporation]], who had built noteworthy constructs such as [[Petronas Towers]], and [[Burj Khalifa]]

====Armaments====
[[File:US Navy 100727-N-2013O-128 An SH-60F Sea Hawk helicopter flies by Dokdo (LPH 6111).jpg|thumb|right|Korea's remarkable technological advancements and industrialization allowed Korea to produce increasingly powerful military equipment.]]

Situated in the most heavily militarized region of the world, South Korea is an important manufacturer of armaments, both for domestic use and for export. During the 1960s, South Korea was largely dependent on the United States to supply its armed forces, but after the elaboration of President Richard M. Nixon's policy of Vietnamization in the early 1970s, South Korea began to manufacture many of its own weapons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-12313.html|title=South Korea: Armaments|publisher=Library of Congress}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the 1980s, South Korea, now in possession of more modern military technology than in previous generations, has actively began shifting its defense industry's areas of interest more from its previously homeland defense-oriented militarization efforts, to the promotion of military equipments and technology as mainstream products of exportation to boost its international trade. Some of its key military export projects include [[T-155 Firtina]] self-propelled artillery for [[Turkish Army|Turkey]]; [[Daewoo K11|K11]] air-burst rifle for [[United Arab Emirates Union Defence Force|United Arab Emirates]]; [[BNS Bangabandhu|Bangabandhu class]] guided-missile frigate for [[Bangladesh Navy|Bangladesh]]; fleet tankers such as [[HMAS Sirius|Sirius class]] for the navies of [[Royal Australian Navy|Australia]], [[Royal New Zealand Navy|New Zealand]], and [[Bolivarian Armada of Venezuela#Amphibious and service ships|Venezuela]]; [[Makassar class landing platform dock|Makassar class]] amphibious assault ships for [[Indonesian Navy|Indonesia]]; and [[KT-1]] trainer for [[Turkish Air Force|Turkey]] and [[Indonesian Air Force|Indonesia]].

South Korea has also outsourced its defense industry to produce various core components of other countries' advanced military hardware. Those hardware include modern aircraft such as [[F-15K]] fighters and [[AH-64]] attack helicopters which will be used by [[Singapore]] and [[Japan]], whose airframes will be built by [[Korea Aerospace Industries]] in a joint-production deal with Boeing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.koreaaero.com/english/business/fuselage_01.asp|title=KAI Major Programs: Airframe|publisher=Korea Aerospace Industries}}&lt;/ref&gt; In other major oursourcing and joint-production deals, South Korea has jointly produced the [[S-300 (missile)|S-300]] air defense system of [[Russia]] via [[Samsung Group]], and will facilitate the sales of [[Mistral class]] amphibious assault ships to Russia that will be produced by [[STX Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-10740291|title=France to sell two Mistral-class warships to Russia|publisher=BBC| date=2010-07-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korea's defense exports were $1.03 billion in 2008 and $1.17 billion in 2009, and South Korea aims to increase the figure to $1.5 billion in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/nation/2010/08/205_67771.html|title=Korea emerges as arms development powerhouse|publisher=Korea Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1990s and the Asian Financial Crisis===
For the first half of the 1990s, the South Korean economy continued a stable and strong growth in both private consumption and GDP. Things changed quickly in 1997 with the Asian Financial crisis. After several other Asian currencies were attacked by speculators, the Korean Won started to heavily depreciate in October 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; The problem was exacerbated by the problem of non-performing loans at many of Korea's merchant banks. By December 1997, the IMF had approved a USD $21 billion loan, that would be part of a USD $58.4 billion bailout plan.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; By January 1998, the government had shut down a third of Korea's merchant banks.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; Throughout 1998, Korea's economy would continue to shrink quarterly at an average rate of -6.65%.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; Korean chaebol Daewoo became a casualty of the crisis as it was dismantled by the government in 1999 due to debt problems. American company [[General Motors]] managed to purchase the motors division. Indian conglomerate [[Tata Group]], purchased the trucks and heavy vehicles division of Daewoo.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal
 | title = Recovery from a financial crisis: the case of South Korea
 | url = http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0DKI/is_4_2001/ai_84799965/?tag=content;col1
 | year = 2001
 | journal = Economic &amp; Financial Review
 | format = w
 | last1 = Koo	 | first1 =  Jahyeong
 | last2 =  Kiser	 | first2 =  Sherry L.
 | accessdate = 2009-05-05
 | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;	}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Actions by the South Korean government and debt swaps by international lenders contained the country's financial problems. Much of South Korea's recovery from the Asian Financial Crisis can be attributed to labor adjustments (i.e. a dynamic and productive labor market with flexible wage rates) and alternative funding sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; By the first quarter of 1999, GDP growth had risen to 5.4%, and strong growth thereafter combined with deflationary pressure on the currency lead to a yearly growth of 10.5%. In December 1999, president [[Kim Dae-jung]] declared the currency crisis over.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt;

===2000s===
After the bounce back from the crisis of the late nineties, the economy continued strong growth in 2000 with a GDP growth of 9.08%.&lt;ref name=&quot;a&quot; /&gt; Growth fell back to 3.8% in the early 2000s because of the slowing global economy, falling exports, and the perception that corporate and financial reforms had stalled.&lt;ref name=&quot;b&quot;&gt;{{cite web
 | title = Total Economy Database
 | url = http://www.conference-board.org/economics/database.cfm
 | year = 2009
 | accessdate = 2009-06-05
 | postscript = &lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;	}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thanks to industrialization GDP per hour worked (labor output) more than tripled from US$2.80 in 1963 to US$10.00 in 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;b&quot; /&gt; More recently the economy stabilized and maintain a growth rate between 4-5% from 2003 onwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;b&quot; /&gt;

Like most industrialized economies, Korea suffered significant setbacks during the [[global financial crisis|late-2000s recession]] that began in 2007. Growth fell by 3.4% in the fourth quarter of 2008 from the previous quarter, the first negative quarterly growth in 10 years, with year on year quarterly growth continuing to be negative into 2009.&lt;ref name=chang&gt;{{cite journal |last=Chang |first=Jaechul |title=The Contours of Korea's Economic Slowdown and Outlook for 2009 |journal=SERI Quarterly |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=87–90 |publisher=Samsung Economic Research Institute }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Most sectors of the economy reported declines, with manufacturing dropping 25.6% as of January 2009, and consumer goods sales dropping 3.1%.&lt;ref name=chang /&gt; Exports in autos and semiconductors, two critical pillars of the economy, shrank 55.9% and 46.9% respectively, while exports overall fell by a record 33.8% in January, and 18.3% in February 2009 year on year.&lt;ref name=kkw&gt;{{cite journal |author1=Kim Kyeong-Won |author2=Kim Hwa-Nyeon |title=Global Financial Crisis Overview |journal=SERI Quarterly |volume=2 |issue=2 |pages=13–21 |publisher=Samsung Economic Research Institute }}&lt;/ref&gt; As in the 1997 crisis, Korea's currency also experienced massive fluctuations, declining by 34% against the dollar.&lt;ref name=kkw/&gt; Annual growth in the economy slowed to 2.3% in 2008, and was expected to drop to as low as -4.5% by [[Goldman Sachs]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/2009/03/12/korea-rate-economy-markets-currency-won.html Korea's Choice: Currency Or Economy?]&lt;/ref&gt; but South Korea was able to limit the downturn to a near standstill at 0.2% in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;US Department of State. [http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/2800.htm “Background Note: South Korea”]&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the global financial crisis, the South Korean economy, helped by timely stimulus measures and strong domestic consumption of products that compensated for a drop in export,&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.yonhapnews.co.kr/business/2010/07/09/45/0503000000AEN20100709006500320F.HTML (News Focus) Rate hike heralds start of Korea's stimulus exit]&lt;/ref&gt; was able to avoid a recession unlike most industrialized economies, posting positive economic growth for two consecutive years of the crisis. In 2010, South Korea made a strong economic rebound with a growth rate of 6.1%, signaling a return of the economy to pre-crisis levels. South Korea's export has recorded $424 billion in the first eleven months of the year 2010,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.buykorea.org/ Korea Current Trade Volume]&lt;/ref&gt; already higher than its export in the whole year of 2008. The South Korean economy of the 21st century, as a [[Next Eleven]] economy, is expected to grow from 3.9% to 4.2% annually between 2011 and 2030,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adb.org/Documents/Books/ADO/2010/Update/ado2010-update-part2.pdf The Future of Growth In Asia]&lt;/ref&gt; similar to growth rates of developing countries such as Brazil or Russia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2010/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy=2011&amp;ey=2015&amp;scsm=1&amp;ssd=1&amp;sort=country&amp;ds=.&amp;br=1&amp;pr1.x=69&amp;pr1.y=18&amp;c=223%2C922%2C542&amp;s=NGDP_RPCH&amp;grp=0&amp;a= Gross Domestic Product, Constant Prices: Percent Change]&lt;/ref&gt;

====High-tech industries in the 1990s and 2000s====
[[File:2010 Hyundai Genesis Coupe 1.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|The automotive line is a key sector in South Korea's industry.]]

In 1990, South Korean manufacturers planned a significant shift in future production plans toward high-technology industries. In June 1989, panels of government officials, scholars, and business leaders held planning sessions on the production of such goods as new materials, mechatronics—including industrial robotics—bioengineering, microelectronics, fine chemistry, and aerospace. This shift in emphasis, however, did not mean an immediate decline in heavy industries such as automobile and ship production, which had dominated the economy in the 1980s.

South Korea relies largely upon exports to fuel the growth of its economy, with finished products such as electronics, textiles, ships, automobiles, and steel being some of its most important exports.  Although the import market has liberalized in recent years, the agricultural market has remained largely [[protectionist]] due to serious disparities in the price of domestic agricultural products such as rice with the international market.  As of 2005, the price of rice in South Korea is about four times that of the average price of rice on the international market, and it was generally feared that opening the agricultural market would have disastrous effects upon the South Korean agricultural sector.  In late 2004, however, an agreement was reached with the [[WTO]] in which South Korean rice imports will gradually increase from 4% to 8% of consumption by 2014.  In addition, up to 30% of imported rice will be made available directly to consumers by 2010, where previously imported rice was only used for processed foods.  Following 2014, the South Korean rice market will be fully opened.

===Recent years===
[[File:479563754 8ef9e978a7.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.8|The South Korean economy of 1990s and beyond was marked by the development of high-tech industries, in fields such as information display and electronics.]]

In the early 1980s, in order to control inflation, a conservative [[monetary policy]] and tight fiscal measures were adopted. Growth of the [[money supply]] was reduced from the 30 percent level of the 1970s to 15 percent. Seoul even froze its budget for a short while. Government intervention in the economy was greatly reduced and policies on imports and foreign investment were liberalized to promote competition. To reduce the imbalance between rural and urban sectors, Seoul expanded investments in public projects, such as roads and communications facilities, while further promoting farm [[mechanization]].

These measures, coupled with significant improvements in the world economy, helped the South Korean economy regain its lost momentum in the late 1980s. South Korea achieved an average of 9.2 percent real growth between 1982 and 1987 and 12.5 percent between 1986 and 1988. The double digit [[inflation]] of the 1970s was brought under control. [[Wholesale]] price inflation averaged 2.1 percent per year from 1980 through 1988; consumer prices increased by an average of 4.7 percent annually. Seoul achieved its first significant surplus in its balance of payments in 1986 and recorded a US$7.7 billion and a US$11.4 billion surplus in 1987 and 1988 respectively. This development permitted South Korea to begin reducing its level of [[foreign debt]]. The trade surplus for 1989, however, was only US$4.6 billion dollars, and a small negative balance was projected for 1990.

In recent years, Korea's economy moved away from the centrally planned, government-directed investment model toward a more market-oriented one. South Korea bounced back from the 1997-98 Asian financial crisis with assistance from the International Monetary Fund (IMF), but its recovery was based largely on extensive financial reforms that restored stability to markets. These economic reforms, pushed by President [[Kim Dae-jung]], helped Korea maintain one of Asia's few expanding economies, with growth rates of 10.8% in 1999 and 9.2% in 2000. Growth fell back to 3.3% in 2001 because of the slowing global economy, falling exports, and the perception that much-needed corporate and financial reforms have stalled. Led by industry and construction, growth in 2002 was 5.8%, despite anemic global growth. Restructuring of Korean conglomerates (''[[chaebol]]s''), bank privatization, and creating a more liberalized economy with a mechanism for bankrupt firms to exit the market remain Korea's most important unfinished reform tasks. Growth slowed again in 2004, but production expanded 5% in 2006, due to popular demand for key export products such as [[HDTV]]s and [[mobile phone]]s.

==Tourism==
{{Main|Tourism in South Korea}}
[[File:Incheon International Airpot (interesting architecture).jpg|thumb|left|200px|[[Incheon International Airport]], rated the best airport worldwide consecutively since 2005 by [[Airports Council International]].&lt;ref name=&quot;airport.kr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airport.kr/notice/NoticeView.iia?functioncode=46&amp;bulletinid=4994|title=Incheon International Airport, Best Airport Worldwide for 4 Years Straight|publisher=Incheon International Airport Corp.|accessdate=2005-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In 2007, South Korea had 6.4 million visitors making it the 36th most visited country in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tourismroi.com/Content_Attachments/27670/File_633513750035785076.pdf |title=UNTWO World Tourism Barometer, Vol.5 No.2 |accessdate=2008-10-15 |last=UNTWO |date=June 2008 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Recently, the number of tourists from China, Taiwan, Hong Kong, and Southeast Asia has grown dramatically due to the increased popularity of the [[Korean wave]] (&quot;hallyu&quot;).

[[Seoul]] is the principal tourist destination for visitors; popular tourist destinations outside of Seoul include [[Seorak-san]] national park, the historic city of [[Gyeongju]] and semi-tropical [[Jeju-do|Jeju Island]].

==See also==
{{Portalbox|South Korea|Economics}}
*[[Four Asian Tigers]]
*[[List of South Korean regions by GDP]]
*[[Economy of North Korea]]
*[[List of banks in South Korea]]
*[[List of Korea-related topics]]
*[[List of South Korean companies]]
*[[Heavy-Chemical Industry Drive]]

==References and notes==
{{loc}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |author=O. Yul Kwon |title=The Korean Economy in Transition: An Institutional Perspective |year=2010 |location=Northampton, MA |publisher=Edward Elgar |isbn=9781840642681 }}
*{{cite book |editor=T. Youn-Ja Shim |title=Korean Entrepreneurship: The Foundation of the Korean Economy |location=New York |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |year=2010 |isbn=9780230107076 }} Essays on such topics as American-educated technocrats in the 1960s and their role in South Korea's economic growth, and entrepreneurial family companies in South Korea, as well as China and Japan.
*{{cite book |author=Byung-Nak Song |title=The Rise of the Korean Economy |year=2003 |edition=3rd |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=019592827X }}
*{{cite book |author=Sang Chul Suh |title=Growth and Structural Changes in the Korean Economy, 1910-1940 |series=Harvard East Asian Monographs |location=Cambridge |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=1978 |isbn=0674364392 }}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Economy of South Korea}}
*[http://kosis.nso.go.kr/cgi-bin/SWS_1021.cgi?KorEng=2&amp;A_UNFOLD=1&amp;TableID=MT_ETITLE&amp;TitleID=G&amp;FPub=4&amp;UserID=/ Korea Statistical Information System]
*[http://cdm164001.cdmhost.com/krogh/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/p164001coll21&amp;CISOPTR=50&amp;CISOBOX=1&amp;REC=1 South Korean-US Economic Policies] from the [http://cdm164001.cdmhost.com/krogh/ Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives]
*[http://www.seriworld.org/ Samsung Economic Research Institute]
*[http://www.oecd.org/korea/ OECD South Korea]
*[http://www.monthlyreview.org/090427-hart-landsberg.php/ The Promise and Perils of Korean Reunification by Martin Hart-Landsberg.]
{{APEC}}
{{Economy of South Korea}}
{{Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development}}
{{World Trade Organization}}
{{Asia in topic|Economy of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Economy Of South Korea}}
[[Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats]]
[[Category:World Trade Organization member economies|South Korea]]
[[Category:Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development member economies|Korea]]
[[Category:Economy of South Korea| ]]

[[bg:Икономика на Южна Корея]]
[[ca:Economia de Corea del Sud]]
[[de:Südkorea#Wirtschaft]]
[[es:Economía de Corea del Sur]]
[[eu:Hego Koreako ekonomia]]
[[fr:Économie de la Corée du Sud]]
[[gl:Economía da Corea do Sur]]
[[ko:대한민국의 경제]]
[[io:Ekonomio di Sud-Korea]]
[[he:כלכלת קוריאה הדרומית]]
[[lt:Pietų Korėjos ekonomika]]
[[ja:大韓民国の経済]]
[[oc:Economia de la Corèa del Sud]]
[[pt:Economia da Coreia do Sul]]
[[ru:Экономика Республики Корея]]
[[fi:Etelä-Korean talous]]
[[uk:Економіка Південної Кореї]]
[[vi:Kinh tế Hàn Quốc]]
[[zh:韓國經濟]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
