<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27087" ns="0" title="Kes (Star Trek)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Star Trek character
|Title       = Kes
|Image       = Kes.jpg
|Species     = [[Ocampa]]
|Sex         = Female
|Planet      = Ocampa
|Affiliation = [[Starfleet]]
|Posting     = Medical assistant,&lt;br /&gt;[[USS Voyager (Star Trek)|USS ''Voyager'']]
|portrayer   = [[Jennifer Lien]]
}}
'''Kes''' ({{IPA-en|ˈkɛs|pron}}) is a character in the television series ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'', played by [[Jennifer Lien]].  

She was a regular for the first three seasons, leaving the show in the season four episode &quot;[[The Gift (Voyager episode)|The Gift]]&quot;. She made one guest appearance two seasons later.

==Character biography==
Kes is an [[Ocampa]], a race native to the Delta Quadrant, with a lifespan of only 9 years. In the series pilot, Kes is taken on board the [[USS Voyager (NCC-74656)|USS ''Voyager'']] crew with her partner, [[Neelix]], who was responsible for rescuing her from the [[Kazon]]. Kes had been a slave of the Kazon after her attempt to escape the tedium of normal Ocampan life. She had also hoped to develop her [[psionic]] powers, which her ancestors were rumored to have possessed with great proficiency. The Ocampa's psionic powers were relatively unknown by that time because of the Ocampa lifestyle, which depended solely on the [[Caretaker (Voyager episode)|Caretaker]] for provisions and protection.

During her time aboard ''Voyager'', Kes develops a close friendship with [[the Doctor (Star Trek)|the Doctor]] while working as his assistant medical technician. Kes receives medical training and helps the Doctor learn how to interact more easily with the crew. She also helps him develop social skills, such as helping him get a date with [[Vidiian]] Dr. Denara Pel (&quot;[[Lifesigns]]&quot;), and supporting him when he deals with the loss of his &quot;daughter&quot; in a holographic family simulation (&quot;[[Real Life (Voyager episode)|Real Life]]&quot;). Kes also becomes a friend and student of [[Tuvok]], who helps her develop and learn to control her psionic abilities.

In the episode &quot;[[Warlord (Voyager episode)|Warlord]]&quot;, Kes treats an Ilaran man carrying the consciousness of former Ilaran tyrant Tieran. Sensing Kes' powers, Tieran transfers his mind into her for his own goal of re-conquering Ilara, prompting Kes to steal a shuttlecraft to go to Ilara. Tieran is finally purged from her mind, but Kes is left somewhat traumatized from the violent acts she participated in. Tuvok tells her that she will have to learn and adapt from the experience, and that she will never be quite the same again.  It is during this episode that Kes calls off her long-term romantic relationship with Neelix after she decides he is too jealous, suffocating, and protective.

In the episodes &quot;[[Scorpion (Voyager episode)|Scorpion]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Gift (Voyager episode)|The Gift]]&quot;, ''Voyager'' becomes entangled in a major conflict between the [[Borg (fictional aliens)|Borg]] and the mysterious aliens referred to as '[[Species 8472]]'. Due in part to her exposure to the powerful telepathic influx of Species 8472, Kes begins to &quot;evolve&quot; into a different state of being. She can no longer remain with ''Voyager'', but before leaving, she uses her newly acquired powers to hurl ''Voyager'' and crew safely beyond Borg space, 9,500 light-years closer to [[Earth (Star Trek)|Earth]]. 

Kes later revisits ''Voyager'' in a story involving [[time travel]] (&quot;[[Fury (Voyager episode)|Fury]]&quot;). At this point she appears much older, is much more powerful, and is vengeful towards the Voyager crew. She travels to the past and attempts to hand the past ''Voyager'' over to the Vidiians while she takes her past self home, but this attempt is thwarted. Using their new foreknowledge of these events, the present Janeway and Tuvok create a hologram of Kes at the time who reminds her future self about her affection for the crew and how much they had cared for her, thus showing Kes how irrational her hatred is. The episode ends with her taking her ship back to Ocampa.

===Alternate bio===
In the episode &quot;[[Before and After (Voyager episode)|Before and After]]&quot;, Kes participates in ''Voyager's'' year-long battle with the [[Krenim]], becoming infected with particles from a [[chronoton]] torpedo. She later marries [[Tom Paris]], and they have a daughter [[Linnis]] (named after Kes' mother). Linnis is married to [[Harry Kim (Star Trek)|Harry Kim]] and they have a son named Andrew, grandson of Kes. At the beginning of the episode, Kes is nine years old and ready to accept her death at the normal age for Ocampans. The Doctor, however, is not, so he devises a bio-temporal chamber, which has the unintentional effect of reactivating chronotons dormant in Kes' body from her exposure to the chronoton torpedo several years earlier. This begins sending Kes on a backwards journey through her life. Kes becomes aware of what is happening, and once she has traveled back to the time corresponding to an earlier part of Voyager's conflict with the Krenim, she informs the Doctor in the past what is happening to her and relays the exact temporal frequency of the chronoton torpedo. This enables the Doctor to devise a treatment and restore Kes to normal temporal sync. It also renders the events of Kes' future, including her marriage to Tom Paris as well as her daughter Linnis, into an alternate timeline that never comes to pass. She is, however, still able to inform Captain [[Kathryn Janeway]] about the coming &quot;[[Year of Hell (Voyager episode)|Year of Hell]]&quot;.  It's left unexplained why ''Voyager'''s crew is unaware of Kes' warning when they encounter the Krenim later in season 4, during the episodes of the same name (Season 4, episodes 8 and 9).

==External links==
{{Memoryalpha|Kes}}

{{Star Trek VOY}}
{{Star Trek navbox}}

[[Category:Fictional characters with precognition]]
[[Category:Fictional nurses]]
[[Category:Fictional telepaths]]
[[Category:Star Trek alien characters]]
[[Category:Star Trek: Voyager characters]]
[[Category:Fictional medical personnel]]
[[Category:Starfleet nurses]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1995]]

[[ca:Kes]]
[[cs:Kes]]
[[es:Kes (Star Trek)]]
[[fr:Kes (Star Trek)]]
[[hr:Kes]]
[[it:Kes (personaggio di Star Trek)]]
[[hu:Kes (Star Trek)]]
[[nl:Kes]]
[[ja:ケス (スタートレック)]]
[[pt:Kes (Star Trek)]]
[[ru:Кес (Звёздный путь)]]
[[sv:Kes]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
