<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27097" ns="0" title="Star Trek: First Contact"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{confuse|First Contact (Star Trek: The Next Generation)}}
{{Infobox film
| name           = Star Trek: &lt;br /&gt; First Contact
| image          = Star Trek 08-poster.png
| caption        = Theatrical poster and home video art
| alt            = Movie poster for ''Star Trek: First Contact'', showing head shots of Patrick Stewart as Captain Jean Luc Picard, Brent Spiner as Data, and Alice Krige as the Borg Queen, from bottom to top; the bottom shows an image of the starship Enterprise E speeding to the background over an army of Borg drones.
| screenplay     = [[Brannon Braga]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Ronald D. Moore]]
| story          = Rick Berman &lt;br /&gt;Brannon Braga&lt;br /&gt;Ronald D. Moore
| director       = [[Jonathan Frakes]]
| producer       = [[Rick Berman]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Marty Hornstein]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Peter Lauritson]]
| starring       = ''[[#Cast|See Cast]]''
| distributor    = [[Paramount Pictures]]
| music          = [[Jerry Goldsmith]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Joel Goldsmith]]
| cinematography = [[Matthew F. Leonetti]]
| editing        = Anastasia Emmons &lt;br /&gt;John W. Wheeler
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $46,000,000
| gross          = $146,000,000 (worldwide)
| released       = {{Film date|1996|11|22}}
| runtime        = 111 minutes
}}

'''''Star Trek: First Contact''''' is the eighth feature film in the ''[[Star Trek]]'' [[science fiction]] franchise, released in November 1996, by [[Paramount Pictures]]. ''First Contact'' is the first film in the franchise to feature no cast members from the [[Star Trek: The Original Series|original Star Trek television series]] of the 1960s. The primary cast for ''First Contact'' is from the ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' television series, to which the film's producers added [[Alice Krige]], [[Neal McDonough]], [[James Cromwell]] and [[Alfre Woodard]]. In the film's plot, the crew of the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise'']] travel from the 24th to 21st century to save their future after the [[cyborg|cybernetic]] [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] conquered Earth by changing the timeline.

After the release of the seventh film, ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'', in 1994, Paramount tasked writers [[Brannon Braga]] and [[Ronald D. Moore]] with developing a sequel. Braga and Moore wanted to feature the Borg in the plot, while producer [[Rick Berman]] wanted a story involving time travel. The writers combined the two ideas; they initially set the film during the European Renaissance, but changed the time period the Borg corrupted to the mid-21st century after fearing the Renaissance idea would be too kitschy. After two better known directors turned down the job, cast member [[Jonathan Frakes]] was chosen to direct to make sure the task fell to someone who understood ''Star Trek''. It was Frakes' first theatrical film.

The script required the creation of new starship designs, including a new USS ''Enterprise''. Production designer [[Herman Zimmerman]] and illustrator [[John Eaves]] collaborated to make a sleeker ship than its predecessor. Principal photography began with weeks of location shooting in Arizona and California before production moved to new sets for the ship-based scenes. The Borg were redesigned to appear as though they were converted into machine beings from the inside-out; the new makeup sessions took four times as long as on the television series. Effects company [[Industrial Light &amp; Magic]] rushed to complete the film's special effects in less than five months. Traditional optical effects techniques were supplemented with [[computer-generated imagery]]. [[Jerry Goldsmith]] and his son [[Joel Goldsmith|Joel]] collaborated to produce the film's score.

''First Contact'' was the highest-grossing film on its opening weekend, making $30.7&amp;nbsp;million. The film made $92&amp;nbsp;million in the United States and an additional $57.4&amp;nbsp;million in other territories, for a theatrical run of about $146&amp;nbsp;million worldwide. Critical reception was mostly positive; critics including [[Roger Ebert]] considered it one of the best ''Star Trek'' films. The Borg and the special effects were lauded, while characterization was less evenly received. ''First Contact'' was nominated for an [[Academy Award]] for [[Academy Award for Best Makeup|Best Makeup]] and won three [[Saturn Awards]]. The film has been released on [[VHS|videotape]], [[LaserDisc]], [[DVD]], and [[Blu-ray]] home video formats. Scholarly analysis of the film has focused on Captain [[Jean Luc Picard]]'s parallels to [[Herman Melville]]'s [[Moby-Dick#Ahab|Ahab]] and the nature of the Borg.

==Plot==
Captain [[Jean-Luc Picard]] awakens from a nightmare in which he relived his assimilation by the cybernetic [[Borg (Star Trek)|Borg]] six years earlier (previously shown in the two-part television episode [[The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|&quot;The Best of Both Worlds&quot;]]). Starfleet informs him of a new Borg attack against Earth, but orders the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise''-E]] to patrol the [[Romulan Neutral Zone]] so as to not introduce an &quot;unstable element&quot; to the fight. Learning that the fleet is losing the battle, the ''Enterprise'' crew disobeys orders and heads for Earth, where a single, damaged [[Borg Cube]] opposes a group of Starfleet vessels. The ''Enterprise'' arrives in time to save the crew of the [[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'']] which is being commanded by Lieutenant Commander [[Worf]]. After Picard hears Borg communications in his mind, he orders the fleet to concentrate its firepower on a seemingly unimportant section of the Borg ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-326&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 326.&lt;/ref&gt; The Cube is destroyed after launching a smaller sphere ship towards the planet.

The ''Enterprise'' pursues the sphere into a temporal vortex.  Picard orders the ''Enterprise'' to follow it, and as they are enveloped in the vortex, the crew briefly glimpses an Earth populated entirely by Borg.  Picard realizes that the Borg have used [[time travel]] to change the past.&lt;ref name=&quot;startrek-synopsis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/series/MOV/008/synopsis/88.html|title=Movie Detail: First Contact Synopsis|work=StarTrek.com|publisher=Viacom|accessdate=2009-04-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Enterprise'' arrives in the past, on April 4, 2063, the day before humanity's [[First contact (science fiction)|first encounter with alien life]] after [[Zefram Cochrane]]'s historic [[warp drive (Star Trek)|warp drive]] flight.  The Borg sphere fires on the planet; realizing that the Borg are trying to prevent first contact, the ''Enterprise'' crew destroy the sphere and send an [[away team]] to the [[Montana]] site where Cochrane is building his ship, the ''Phoenix'', to look for survivors.  Picard sends Cochrane's assistant Lily Sloane to the ''Enterprise'' for medical attention, then returns to the ship and leaves Commander [[William Riker]] on Earth to make sure the ''Phoenix''{{'}}s flight proceeds as planned.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-327&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 327.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Enterprise'' crew sees Cochrane as a legend, but the real man is reluctant to assume his historical role.&lt;ref name=&quot;startrek-synopsis&quot;/&gt;

Borg survivors invade the ''Enterprise'', and begin to assimilate its crew and modify the ship. Picard and a team attempt to reach engineering to disable the Borg with its corrosive coolant, but the android [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]] is captured. A frightened Sloane seizes the captain but he gains her trust, and they escape the Borg-infested area of the ship by creating a diversion in the [[holodeck]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-327&quot;/&gt; Picard, Worf, and the ship's navigator, Lieutenant Hawk, stop the Borg from calling reinforcements with the [[deflector dish]], but Hawk is assimilated. As the Borg continue to assimilate, Worf suggests destroying the ship, but Picard angrily calls him a coward and vows to continue the fight. Sloane confronts the captain and makes him realize he is acting irrationally due to his [[Moby-Dick#Ahab|desire for revenge]]. Apologizing to Worf, Picard activates the ship's [[self-destruct]]. While the crew heads to [[escape pod]]s, the captain stays behind to rescue Data.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-328&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 328.&lt;/ref&gt;

As Cochrane, Riker, and engineer [[Geordi La Forge]] prepare to activate the warp drive on the ''Phoenix'', Picard discovers that the [[Borg (Star Trek)#Borg Queen|Borg Queen]] has grafted human skin onto Data, giving him an array of new sensations. She has presented this modification as a gift to the android, hoping to obtain his encryption codes to the ''Enterprise'' computer. Although Picard offers himself in Data's place, the android refuses to leave. He deactivates the self-destruct and fires torpedoes at the ''Phoenix'', but they miss and the Queen realizes Data betrayed her.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-328&quot;/&gt; The android ruptures a coolant tank, and the corrosive gas dissolves the Borg's biological components. Cochrane completes his warp flight,&lt;ref name=&quot;startrek-synopsis&quot;/&gt; and the next day the crew watches as [[Vulcan (Star Trek)|Vulcans]], attracted by the ''Phoenix'' warp test, land on Earth and greet Cochrane. Having repaired history, the ''Enterprise'' crew returns to the 24th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;startrek-synopsis&quot;/&gt;

==Cast==
''First Contact'' is the first film in the ''Star Trek'' film series in which none of the ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]'' main characters appear.&lt;ref name=&quot;ew&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,295114,00.html|title=Holiday Movie Preview|accessdate=2008-02-08| first = David | last = Hochman | work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]|date=1996-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather, the main cast of the 1987–1994 ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'' fill the main roles. [[Patrick Stewart]] plays [[Jean-Luc Picard]], the captain of the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|USS ''Enterprise''-E]] who is haunted by his time as a member of the Borg. Stewart was one of the few cast members who had an important role in developing the script, offering suggestions and comments.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-22&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Picard's character was changed from the &quot;angst-ridden character [viewers have] seen before&quot;, to an action hero type. Stewart noted that Picard was more physically active in the film compared with his usual depiction.&lt;ref name=ew/&gt;

Other ''Enterprise'' crewmembers include the ship's first officer [[William Riker]], played by director [[Jonathan Frakes]]. Frakes said he did not have much difficulty directing and acting at the same time, having done so on the television series.&lt;ref name=making/&gt; [[Brent Spiner]] portrays the android [[Data (Star Trek)|Data]]; rumors before the film's release suggested that since Data's skin had been largely removed at the end of the story, it would allow another actor to assume the role.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-31&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 31.&lt;/ref&gt; [[LeVar Burton]] plays [[Geordi La Forge]], the ship's chief engineer. La Forge is a blind character, and for the television series and previous film had worn a special [[VISOR|visor]] to see. Burton lobbied for many years to have his character's visor replaced so that people could see his eyes, since the &quot;air filter&quot; he wore prevented the audience from seeing his eyes and limited his acting ability. Moore finally agreed, giving the character ocular implants that were never explained in the film, beyond showing they were artificial.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-22&quot;/&gt; [[Gates McFadden]] plays [[Beverly Crusher]], the ship's doctor. McFadden considered ''Star Trek'' women finally on par with the men: &quot;We've come a long way since [[Majel Barrett]] was stuck in the sick bay as [[Christine Chapel|Nurse Chapel]] in the [1960s] and made to dye her hair blond.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;themirror-space girls&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Grant |first=Brigit |date=1996-12-12 |title=The Space Girls; Women break male domination in latest Star Trek movie |work=[[Daily Mirror|The Mirror]] |pages=2–3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ship's counselor [[Deanna Troi]] is portrayed by [[Marina Sirtis]]. The actress missed working on the television show, and was acutely aware that expectations and stakes for ''First Contact'' were high; &quot;we were scared that people thought we couldn't cut it without the original cast&quot;, she said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Slotek | first = Jim | date=1996-11-17|title=Generation Next; will the Star Trek franchise survive The Next Generation's first solo attempt at a feature?|work=[[The Toronto Sun]]|page=S3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other Starfleet members included former ''Enterprise'' chief of security, and commander of the [[USS Defiant|USS ''Defiant'']], [[Worf]] ([[Michael Dorn]]). The ''Defiant'' is badly damaged in the battle with the Borg but is left salvageable. An early screenplay draft called for the ''Defiant'' to be destroyed, but ''Deep Space Nine'' executive producer [[Ira Steven Behr]] objected to the destruction of his show's ship and so the idea was dropped.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; [[Neal McDonough]] plays [[Sean Hawk]], the ''Enterprise'' helmsman who aids in the defense of the ship until he is assimilated and killed. McDonough was cavalier about his role as an expendable &quot;[[redshirt (character)|redshirt]]&quot;, saying that since one of the characters in the deflector dish battle had to die, &quot;that would be me&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-30&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 30.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[James Cromwell]] was cast as [[Zefram Cochrane]], the pilot and creator of Earth's first warp capable vessel. The character of Zefram Cochrane had first appeared in the ''Original Series'' episode &quot;[[Metamorphosis (Star Trek episode)|Metamorphosis]]&quot;, played by [[Glenn Corbett]].&lt;ref name=&quot;chicago tribune-cromwell&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=As Scientist, Cromwell Has Key Role In 'Contact'|accessdate=2008-03-21|date=1996-12-06| last = Spelling | first = Ian | work=[[Chicago Tribune]]|page=9A}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cromwell's Cochrane is much older and has no real resemblance to Corbett's, which did not bother the writers.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-29&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 29.&lt;/ref&gt; They wanted to portray Cochrane as a character going through a major transition; he starts out as a cynical, selfish drunk who is changed by the characters he meets over the course of the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; Although the character was written with Cromwell in mind, [[Tom Hanks]], a big fan of ''Star Trek'', was approached for the role by Paramount first, but he had already committed to the film ''[[That Thing You Do!]]'' and had to reject the part.&lt;ref name=&quot;chicago tribune-cromwell&quot;/&gt; Frakes commented that it would have been a mistake to cast Hanks as Cochrane due to his being so well known.&lt;ref name=record/&gt; Cromwell had a long previous association with ''Star Trek'', having played characters in ''The Next Generation'' episodes &quot;[[The Hunted (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|The Hunted]]&quot; and &quot;[[Birthright (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|Birthright]]&quot;, as well as a role in ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''. &quot;[Cromwell] actually came in and read for the part&quot;, Frakes said. &quot;He nailed it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;/&gt; Cromwell described his method of portraying Cochrane as always playing himself. Part of the actor's interest in the film was his involvement in Steven M. Greer's [[Steven M. Greer|Center for the Study of Extraterrestrial Intelligence]], which offers training for first contact scenarios.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-30&quot;/&gt; [[Alfre Woodard]] plays Lily Sloane, Cochrane's assistant. When Frakes first moved to [[Los Angeles]], Woodard was one of the very first people he met. During a conversation at a barbecue Woodard said she would become Frakes' godmother, as he did not have one. Through this relationship, Frakes was able to cast Woodard in the film; he considered it a coup to land an Academy Award-nominated actress.&lt;ref name=frakes/&gt; Woodard considered Lily to be the character most like herself out of all the roles she has played.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Her 'First Contact' with sci-fi|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-11-10| first = Ian | last = Spelling | work=[[The Washington Post]]|page=D7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Borg Queen is portrayed by [[Alice Krige]]. Casting for the part took time as the actress needed to be sexy, dangerous and mysterious. Frakes cast Krige after finding that she had all of the mentioned qualities, and being impressed by her performance in ''[[Ghost Story (film)|Ghost Story]]'';&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; the director considers her the sexiest ''Star Trek'' villain of all time.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; Krige suffered a large amount of discomfort filming her role; her costume was too tight, causing blisters, and the painful silver contact lenses she wore could only be kept in for four minutes at a time.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt;

The film features minor roles for many of ''The Next Generation''{{'}}s recurring characters; [[Dwight Schultz]] reprised his role of Lieutenant [[Reginald Barclay]], while [[Patti Yasutake]] briefly appeared as Nurse [[List of minor recurring characters in Star Trek: The Next Generation#Alyssa Ogawa|Alyssa Ogawa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 322.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Whoopi Goldberg]] was not asked to return as [[Guinan (Star Trek character)|Guinan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Whoopi's Star Trek love affair over|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-10-02|work=[[The Toronto Star]]|page=B6}}&lt;/ref&gt; a wise bartender whose homeworld was destroyed by the Borg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Hastie | first = A. | chapter=Fabricated Space: Assimilating the Individual on Star Trek: The Next Generation|title=Enterprise Zones: Critical Positions on Star Trek|editor=Harrison, et al|publisher=Westview Press|location=Boulder, Colorado|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt; Goldberg only learned about the decision through the newspapers. &quot;What can I say? I wanted to do it because I didn't think you could do anything about the Borg without [my character]&quot;, she said, &quot;but apparently you can, so they don't need me.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Janusonis | first = Michael | date=1997-01-03|title=Whoopi Goldberg passed the Myrlie Evers test for 'Ghosts' role|work=Providence Journal-Bulletin}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Horton appears as a bloodied and stoic Starfleet defender; his character would be given the name of Daniels in the [[Star Trek: Insurrection|next ''Star Trek'' film]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt;

The third draft of the script added cameos by two actors from the sister television series ''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;/&gt; [[Robert Picardo]] appears as the ''Enterprise''{{'}}s [[Emergency Medical Hologram]]; Picardo played the holographic [[Doctor (Star Trek)|Doctor]] in ''Voyager''. His line &quot;I'm a doctor, not a door stop&quot;, is an allusion to the ''Star Trek'' original series character Dr. [[Leonard McCoy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; Picardo's fellow ''Voyager'' actor [[Ethan Phillips]], who played [[Neelix]], cameos as a nightclub Maitre d' in the holodeck scene. Phillips recalled that the producers wanted the fans to be left guessing whether he was the person who played Neelix or not, as he did not appear in the credits; &quot;It was just kind of a goofy thing to do.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Staff; [[Ethan Phillips]]|year=2002|month=August|title=Interview: Ethan Phillips|work=[[Star Trek: The Magazine]]|volume=3|issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; During production there were incorrect rumors that [[Avery Brooks]] would reprise his role as ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' captain [[Benjamin Sisko]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-30&quot;/&gt; As with many ''Star Trek'' productions, new, disposable redshirt characters are killed off over the course of the plot.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;&gt;Frakes.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
===Development===
[[Image:RonaldDMoore.jpg|alt=A man talks to an audience using a microphone held in his hand. He has a light complexion, full beard and long brown hair.|thumb|200px|Writer [[Ronald D. Moore]] (pictured) and Brannon Braga combined separate ideas involving time travel and the Borg in developing ''First Contact''{{'}}s story.]]
In February 1995, two months after the release of ''[[Star Trek Generations]]'', Paramount decided to produce another ''Star Trek'' feature for a winter holiday 1996 release.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot; /&gt; Paramount wanted writers [[Brannon Braga]] and [[Ronald D. Moore]], who had written the ''Generations'' script and a number of ''Next Generation'' episodes,&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; to pen the screenplay.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;&gt;Braga &amp; Moore.&lt;/ref&gt; Producer [[Rick Berman]] told Braga and Moore that he wanted them to think about doing a story involving [[time travel]]. Braga and Moore, meanwhile, wanted to use the Borg. &quot;Right on the spot, we said maybe we can do both, the Borg and time travel,&quot; Moore recalled.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt; The Borg had not been seen in full force since the fourth season episode of ''The Next Generation'', &quot;[[The Best of Both Worlds (Star Trek: The Next Generation)|The Best of Both Worlds]]&quot;, and had never been heavily featured in the series due to budget constraints and the fear that they would lose their scare factor.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; &quot;The Borg were really liked by the fans, and we liked them,&quot; Moore said. &quot;They were fearsome. They were ''unstoppable''. Perfect foils for a feature story.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt;

In deciding to combine the two story ideas, the writers decided that the time travel element could play out as the Borg attempt to prevent humanity from ever reaching space and becoming a threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt; &quot;Our goals at that point were to create a story that was wonderful and a script that was [...] producible within the budget confines of a ''Star Trek'' film&quot;, said Berman.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-17&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 17.&lt;/ref&gt; One major question was identifying the time period to which the Borg would travel. Berman's suggestion was the [[Renaissance]]; the Borg would attempt to prevent the dawn of modern European civilization. The first story draft, titled ''Star Trek: Renaissance'', had the crew of the ''Enterprise'' track the Borg to their hive in a castle dungeon. The film would have featured sword fights alongside phasers in 15th century Europe, while Data became [[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s apprentice. Moore was afraid that it risked becoming campy and over-the-top,&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt; while Stewart refused to wear tights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Restaino | first = Mike | date=2009-09-22|url=http://www.dvdfile.com/reviews/review/star-trek-the-next-generation-movie-collection-bd-86325/5|title=Star Trek: The Next Generation Movie Collection - BD|accessdate=2009-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Braga, meanwhile, wanted to see the &quot;birth of ''Star Trek''&quot;, when the Vulcans and humans first met; &quot;that, to me, is what made the time travel story fresh&quot;, he said.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt;

With the idea of ''Star Trek''{{'}}s genesis in mind, the central story became Cochrane's warp drive test and humanity's first contact. Drawing on clues from previous ''Star Trek'' episodes, Cochrane was placed in mid-21st century Montana, where humans recover from a devastating world war. In the first script with this setting, the Borg attack Cochrane's lab, leaving the scientist comatose; Picard assumes Cochrane's place to continue the warp test and restore history.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-322&quot;/&gt; In this draft Picard has a love interest in the local photographer Ruby, while Riker leads the fight against the Borg on the ''Enterprise''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-323&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 323.&lt;/ref&gt; Another draft included [[John de Lancie]]'s omnipotent character [[Q (Star Trek)|Q]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=New 'Trek' film big on the Borg|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-09-01|work=[[Mobile Register]]| last = Bassave | first = Roy | page=G3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Looking at the early scripts, the trio knew that serious work was needed. &quot;It just didn't make sense [...] that Picard, the one guy who has a history with the Borg, never meets them,&quot; Braga recalled. Riker and Picard's roles were swapped, and the planetside story was shortened and told differently. Braga and Moore focused the new arc on Cochrane himself, making the ideal future of ''Star Trek'' come from a flawed man. The idea of Borg fighting among period costumes coalesced into a &quot;Dixon Hill&quot; holographic novel sequence on the holodeck. The second draft, titled ''Star Trek: Resurrection'', was judged complete enough that the production team used it to plan expenses.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-323&quot;/&gt; The film was given a budget of $45&amp;nbsp;million, &quot;considerably more&quot; than ''Generations''{{'}} $35&amp;nbsp;million price tag; this allowed the production to plan a larger amount of action and special effects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Llamas | first = Cora | date=1996-11-26|title=Hollywood's last hurrah|work=Business Daily}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Wilonsky | first = Robert | date=1999-10-26|url=http://www.salon.com/ent/feature/1999/10/29/trek/|title=The trouble with Trek|work=[[Salon (magazine)|Salon]]|accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;losangelestimes-werts and frakes&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Werts | first = Diane | date=1996-11-29 |title=A 'First' for Him : Jonathan Frakes takes directing controls of the latest 'Star Trek' film enterprise|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|page=F1 | url = http://articles.latimes.com/1996-11-29/entertainment/ca-4037_1_star-trek }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=oc&gt;{{cite news|title=Calling His Shots - Movies: Jonathan Frakes is second banana in front of the camera, but top dog behind it in 'Star Trek: First Contact'|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-11-20| first = Barry | last = Koltnow | page=F04|work=[[The Orange County Register]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Staff|date=1994-11-28|url=http://www.businessweek.com/archives/1994/b340152.arc.htm|title=This Season has Fangs|work=[[BusinessWeek]]|accessdate=2009-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Jonathan Frakes cropped1.jpg|230px|alt=Bearded man in a black jacket gesturing while talking into a microphone.|left|thumb|Having directed several episodes of ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', [[Jonathan Frakes]] made his feature film directorial debut with ''First Contact''.]]
Braga and Moore intended the film to be easily accessible to any moviegoer and work as a stand-alone story, yet still satisfy the devoted ''Star Trek'' fans. Since much of Picard's role made a direct reference to his time as a Borg in ''The Next Generation'' episodes &quot;The Best of Both Worlds&quot;, the opening [[dream sequence]] was added to explain what happened to him in the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; The pair discarded an opening which would have established what the main characters had been doing since the last film in favor of quickly setting the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-20&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 20.&lt;/ref&gt; While the writers tried to preserve the idea of the Borg as a mindless collective in the original draft, Paramount head Jonathan Dolgen felt that the script was not dramatic enough. He suggested adding an individual Borg villain with whom the characters could interact, which led to the creation of the Borg Queen.&lt;ref name=braga/&gt;

Cast member Jonathan Frakes was chosen to direct. Frakes had not been the first choice for director; [[Ridley Scott]] and [[John McTiernan]] reportedly turned the project down.&lt;ref name=&quot;oc&quot;/&gt; Stewart met a potential candidate and concluded that &quot;they didn't know ''Star Trek''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;making&quot;&gt;{{cite video|people=''Star Trek'' cast and crew|date=2005-03-15|title=Star Trek: First Contact; Making First Contact|publisher=[[Paramount Pictures]]|medium=DVD; Disc 2/2}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was decided to stay with someone who understood the &quot;[[Gestalt psychology|gestalt]] of ''Star Trek''&quot;, and Frakes was given the job.&lt;ref name=improved&gt;{{cite news|title=A New, Improved 'Star Trek' Film - Flagging Franchise Gets Big Boost With Frakes-Helmed 'First Contact'|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-11-22|work=[[Daily News of Los Angeles]]| first = Bob | last = Strauss | page=L3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Frakes reported to work every day at 6:30&amp;nbsp;am. A major concern during the production was security—the script to ''Generations'' had been leaked online, and stronger measures were taken to prevent a similar occurrence. Some script pages were distributed on red paper to foil attempted photocopies or faxes; &quot;We had real trouble reading them,&quot; Frakes noted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Croal, N'gai; Brad Stone|date=1996-05-20|title=Star Trek; it's not easy being Frakes|work=[[Newsweek]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Frakes had directed multiple episodes of ''The Next Generation'', ''Deep Space Nine'' and ''Voyager'', but ''First Contact'' was his first feature film.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Star Trek, First Contact: Commander Riker takes the starship helm as Jonathan Frakes directs Star Trek Movie|accessdate=2008-03-21|date=1996-11-21| first = Jamie | last = Portman | work=[[Waterloo Region Record|The Record]]|page=E1/Front}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas Frakes had seven days of preparation followed by seven days of shooting for a given television episode, the director was given a ten week preparation period before twelve weeks of filming, and had to get used to shooting for a 2.35:1 anamorphic ratio instead of the television standard 1.33:1.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-60&quot;&gt;Thompson, 60.&lt;/ref&gt; In preparation, he watched ''[[Jaws (film)|Jaws]]'', ''[[Close Encounters of the Third Kind]]'', ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]'' and the works of [[James Cameron]] and [[Ridley Scott]].&lt;ref name=oc/&gt;

Throughout multiple script revisions a number of titles were considered, including ''Star Trek: Borg'', ''Star Trek: Destinies'', ''Star Trek: Future Generations'' and ''Star Trek: Generations II''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|date=2005|title=This is a List of Titles Applied to Star Trek: First Contact Before the Final Title Was Decided| medium=DVD|publisher=Paramount Pictures}}&lt;/ref&gt; The planned title of ''Resurrection'' was scrapped when Fox announced the title of the [[Alien Resurrection|fourth ''Alien'' film]]; the movie was rebranded ''First Contact'' on May 3, 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;/&gt;

===Design===
[[Image:St08-uss enterprise e.png|alt=A spaceship glides out of a vibrant, multicolored nebula. The ship is composed of an saucer-shaped primary hull, connected to a thicker secondary hull. Paired glowing engines are attached to the secondary hull via swept-back struts.|thumb|The new [[Sovereign class starship|''Sovereign''-class]] ''Enterprise''-E was designed to be sleeker than its predecessor.&lt;ref name=ew/&gt; The ship was the last element added to the above scene; the computer-generated nebula background was built first, with the starship composited in later.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-68&quot;/&gt;]]
''First Contact'' was one of the first ''Star Trek'' films to use purely computer-generated models, rather than physical miniatures.&lt;ref name=&quot;eaves&quot;/&gt; With the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-D)|''Enterprise''-D]] destroyed during the events of ''Generations'', the task for creating a new starship fell to veteran ''Star Trek'' production designer [[Herman Zimmerman]]. The script's only guide on the appearance of the vessel was the line &quot;the new ''Enterprise'' sleekly comes out of the nebula&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-323&quot;/&gt; Working with illustrator [[John Eaves]], the designers conceived the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-E)|''Enterprise''-E]] as &quot;leaner, sleeker, and mean enough to answer any Borg threat you can imagine&quot;.&lt;ref name=ew/&gt; Braga and Moore intended it to be more muscular and militaryesque.&lt;ref name=braga/&gt; Eaves looked at the structure of [[Starship Enterprise|previous ''Enterprise'' iterations]], and designed a more streamlined, capable war vessel than the ''Enterprise''-D, reducing the neck area of the ship and lengthening the [[nacelle]]s. Eaves produced 30 to 40 sketches before he found a final design he liked and began making minor changes.&lt;ref name=&quot;eaves&quot;/&gt; Working from blueprints created by Paramount's [[Rick Sternbach]], the model shop at effects house [[Industrial Light &amp; Magic]] (ILM) fabricated a {{convert|10.5|ft|msp=us|adj=on}} miniature over a five-month period. Hull patterns were carved out of wood, then cast and assembled over an aluminum armature. The model's panels were painted in an alternating matte and gloss scheme to add texture.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-68&quot;&gt;Magid, 68.&lt;/ref&gt; The crew had multiple difficulties in prepping the miniature for filming; while the model shop originally wanted to save time by casting windows using a clear fiberglass, the material came out tacky. ILM instead cut the windows using a laser.&lt;ref name=&quot;eaves&quot;/&gt; Slides of the sets were added behind the window frames to make the interior seem more dimensional when the camera tracked past the ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-68&quot; /&gt;

In previous films, Starfleet's range of capital ships had been predominantly represented by the [[Constitution class starship|Constitution class]] ''Enterprise'' and just five other ship classes: the [[Miranda class starship|''Miranda'' class]] from ''[[Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan]]'' (represented by the [[USS Reliant|USS ''Reliant'']]), the ''[[Excelsior class starship|Excelsior]]'' and the [[Oberth class starship|''Oberth'' class]] ''[[USS Grissom (Star Trek)|Grissom]]'' from ''[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock]]'', and the [[Galaxy Class|''Galaxy'']] and [[Nebula class starship|''Nebula'' classes]] from ''The Next Generation''. ILM supervisor [[John Knoll]] insisted that ''First Contact''{{'}}s space battle prove the breadth of Starfleet's ship configurations. &quot;Starfleet would probably throw everything it could at the Borg, including ships we've never seen before&quot;, he reasoned. &quot;And since we figured a lot of the background action in the space battle would need to be done with computer-generated ships that needed to be built from scratch anyway, I realized there was no reason not to do some new designs.&quot; [[Alex Jaeger]] was appointed visual effects art director to the film and assigned the task of creating four new starships. Paramount wanted ships that would look different from a distance, so the director devised multiple hull profiles.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-70&quot;/&gt; Knoll and Jaeger had decided that the ships had to obey certain ''Star Trek'' ship precedents, with a saucer-like primary hull and elongated warp nacelles in pairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-23&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 23.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Akira class starship|''Akira'' class]] featured the traditional saucer section and nacelles combined with a catamaran-style double hull; the ''Norway'' class was based on the [[USS Voyager (Star Trek)|USS ''Voyager'']]; the ''Saber'' class was a smaller ship with nacelles trailing off the tips of its saucer section; and the ''Steamrunner'' class featured twin nacelles trailing off the saucer and connected by an engineering section in the rear. Each design was modeled as a three-dimensional digital [[wire-frame model]] for use in the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-70&quot;&gt;Magid, 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

The film also required a number of smaller non-Starfleet designs. The warp ship ''Phoenix'' was conceived as fitting inside an old nuclear missile, meaning that the ship's nacelles had to fold into a space of less than {{convert|10|ft|m|sp=us}}. Eaves made sure to emphasize the mechanical aspect of the ship, to suggest it was a highly experimental and untested technology. Eaves considered the Vulcan ship a &quot;fun&quot; vessel to design. Only two major Vulcan ships had been previously seen in ''Star Trek'', including a courier vessel from ''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture|The Motion Picture]]''. Since the two-engine ship format had been seen many times, the artists decided to step away from the traditional ship layout, creating a more artistic than functional design. The ship incorporated elements of a starfish and a crab. Because of budget constraints, the full ship was realized as a computer-generated design. Only a boomerang-shaped landing foot was fabricated for the actors to interact with.&lt;ref name=&quot;eaves&quot;&gt;Eaves.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Enterprise'' interior sets were mostly new designs. The [[bridge (ship)|bridge]] was designed to be comfortable-looking, with warm colors.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot;/&gt; The set had all the bridge stations face a single captain's chair at the center. Among the new additions was a larger holographic viewscreen that would operate only when activated, leaving a plain wall when disabled. New flatscreen computer monitors were used for displays, using less space and giving the bridge a cleaner look. The new monitors also allowed for video playback that could simulate interaction with the actors.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-332&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 332.&lt;/ref&gt; The designers created a larger and less spartan ready room, retaining elements from the television series; Zimmerman added a set of golden three-dimensional ''Enterprise'' models to a glass case in the corner. The observation lounge was similar to the design in the ''Enterprise''-D; its windows were reused from the television show. Engineering was simulated with a large, three-story set, corridors, a lobby, and the largest warp core in the franchise to date.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-324&quot;/&gt; For its Borg-corrupted state, the engineering section was outfitted with Borg drone alcoves, conduits and Data's &quot;assimilation table&quot; where he is interrogated by the Queen.&lt;ref name=&quot;okuda&quot;&gt;Okuda.&lt;/ref&gt; Some existing sets were used to save money; sickbay was a redress of the same location from ''Voyager'', while the USS ''Defiant'' scenes used ''Deep Space Nine''{{'}}s standing set.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-324&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 324.&lt;/ref&gt; Some set designs took inspiration from the ''[[Alien (franchise)|Alien]]'' film series, ''Star Wars'' and ''2001: A Space Odyssey''.&lt;ref name=frakes/&gt;&lt;ref name=improved/&gt;

The [[Extra-vehicular activity|spacewalk]] scene on the ''Enterprise'' exterior was one of the most challenging sets to envision and construct for the film. The production had to design a [[space suit]] that looked practical rather than exaggerated. Fans were built into the helmets so that the actors would not get overheated, and neon lights built into the front so that the occupant's faces could be seen. When the actors first put the helmets on, the fully enclosed design made it hard to breathe; after a minute of wearing the suit Stewart became ill, and shooting was discontinued.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 330.&lt;/ref&gt; The set for the ship's outer hull and deflector dish were built on [[gimbals]] at Paramount's largest [[sound stage]],&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-72&quot;&gt;Magid, 72.&lt;/ref&gt; surrounded by [[bluescreen]] and rigged with wires for the [[zero gravity]] sequences.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot; /&gt; The stage was not large enough to accommodate a full-sized replica of the ''Enterprise'' dish, so Zimmerman had to scale down the plans by 15&amp;nbsp;percent.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot; /&gt;

===Costumes and makeup===
The [[Starfleet uniforms]] were redesigned for the film by longtime ''Star Trek'' costumer Bob Blackman. Since Blackman was also handling the costumes for the television series, non-Starfleet design clothes were delegated to [[Deborah Everton]],&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 325.&lt;/ref&gt; a newcomer to ''Star Trek'' who was responsible for more than 800 costumes during production.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-28&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Everton was tasked with updating the Borg's costumes to something new, but reminiscent of the television series. The bulky suits were made sleeker and outfitted with [[Optical fiber|fiber optic]] lights.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot;&gt;Kaplan, 24.&lt;/ref&gt; The time travel aspect of the story also required period costumes for the mid 21st century and the 1940s &quot;Dixon Hill&quot; nightclub holodeck recreation. Everton enjoyed designing Woodard's costumes because the character went through many changes during the course of the film, switching from a utilitarian vest and pants in many shots to a glamorous dress during the holodeck scene.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-28&quot;/&gt;

{{rquote|right|I became aware, one day on the set, that whenever a Borg moved up to the coffee table, whoever was there would sort of slowly retreat. So the Borg were not only in pain, but they were kind of ostracised. Everyone just uncomfortable in their presence. Which was terribly interesting for me, but I did feel heartbroken for my minions.|Alice Krige, on people's reaction to the Borg&lt;ref name=&quot;bbckrige&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/st/interviews/krige/printpage.html | title=Alice Krige - First Contact's Borg Queen | publisher=BBC | accessdate=May 07, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
Everton and makeup designers [[Michael Westmore]], [[Scott Wheeler (makeup artist)|Scott Wheeler]], and Jake Garber wanted to upgrade the pasty white look the Borg had retained since ''The Next Generation''{{'}}s second season, born out of a need for budget-conscious television design. &quot;I wanted it to look like they were [assimilated or &quot;Borgified&quot;] from the inside out rather than the outside in,&quot; Everton said.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;/&gt; Each Borg had a slightly different design, and Westmore designed a new one each day to make it appear that there was an army of Borg; in reality, between eight to twelve actors&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt; filled all the roles as the costumes and makeup were so expensive to produce.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; Background Borg were simulated by half-finished [[mannequin]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; Westmore reasoned that since the Borg had traveled the galaxy, they would have assimilated other races besides humans. In the television series, much of the Borg's faces had been covered by helmets, but for ''First Contact'' the makeup artist removed the head coverings and designed assimilated versions of familiar ''Star Trek'' aliens such as [[Klingon]]s, [[List of Star Trek races#Bolian|Bolians]], [[Romulan]]s, [[Bajoran]]s, and [[Cardassian]]s. Each drone received an electronic eyepiece. The blinking lights in each eye were programmed by Westmore's son to repeat a production member's name in [[Morse code]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot;/&gt;

The makeup time for the Borg expanded from the single hour needed for television to five hours, in addition to the 30&amp;nbsp;minutes necessary to get into costume and 90&amp;nbsp;minutes to remove the makeup at the end of the day.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt; While Westmore estimated a fully staffed production would have around 50 makeup artists, ''First Contact'' had to make do with less than ten people involved in preparation, and at most 20 artists a day.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot;/&gt; Despite the long hours, Westmore's teams began to be more creative with the prosthetics as they decreased their preparation times. &quot;They were using two tubes, and then they were using three tubes, and then they were sticking tubes in the ears and up the nose,&quot; Westmore explained. &quot;And we were using a very gooey caramel coloring, maybe using a little bit of it, but by the time we got to the end of the movie we had the stuff dripping down the side of [the Borg's] faces—it looked like they were leaking oil! So, at the very end [of the film], they're more ferocious.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt;

The Borg Queen was a challenge because she had to be unique among Borg but still retain human qualities; Westmore was conscious of avoiding comparisons to films like ''Alien''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-325&quot;/&gt; The final appearance involved pale gray skin and an elongated, oval head, with coils of wire rather than hair.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-24&quot;/&gt; Krige recalled the first day she had her makeup applied: &quot;I saw everyone cringing. I thought, great; they made this, and they've scared themselves!&quot;&lt;ref name=improved/&gt;{{r|bbckrige}} Frakes noted that the Queen ended up being alluring in a disturbing way, despite her evil behavior and appearance.&lt;ref name=&quot;making&quot;/&gt; Zimmerman, Everton and Westmore combined their efforts to design and create the borgified sections of the ''Enterprise'' to build tension and to make the audience feel that &quot;[they are being fed] the Borg&quot;.&lt;ref name=frakes/&gt;

===Filming===
Principal photography took a more leisurely pace than on ''The Next Generation'' due to a less hectic schedule; only four pages of script had to be filmed each day, as opposed to eight on the television series.&lt;ref name=making/&gt; ''First Contact'' saw the introduction of cinematographer [[Matthew F. Leonetti]] to the ''Star Trek'' franchise; Frakes hired the director of photography out of admiration for some of Leonetti's previous work on films such as ''[[Poltergeist (film)|Poltergeist]]'' and ''[[Strange Days (film)|Strange Days]]''. Leonetti was unfamiliar with the ''Star Trek'' mythos when Frakes approached him; to prepare for the assignment, he studied the previous four films in the franchise, each with a different cinematographer—''[[Star Trek IV: The Voyage Home|The Voyage Home]]'' ([[Donald Peterman]]), ''[[Star Trek V: The Final Frontier|The Final Frontier]]'' ([[Andrew Laszlo]]), ''[[Star Trek VI: The Undiscovered Country|The Undiscovered Country]]'' ([[Hiro Narita]]), and ''Generations'' ([[John Alonzo]]). The cameraman also spent several days at the sets of ''Voyager'' and ''Deep Space Nine'' to observe filming.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-60&quot; /&gt;

Leonetti devised multiple lighting methods for the ''Enterprise'' interiors for ship standard operations, &quot;[[Red alert (Star Trek)|Red Alert]]&quot; status, and emergency power. He reasoned that since the ship was being taken over by a foreign entity, it required more dramatic lighting and framing. While much of the footage was shot at 50–70&amp;nbsp;mm focal lengths using anamorphic lenses, 14&amp;nbsp;mm spherical lenses were used for Borg's-eye-view shots. Leonetti preferred shooting with long lenses to provide a more claustrophobic feel, but made sure the length did not flatten the image. Handheld cameras were used for battle sequences so that viewers were brought into the action and the camera could follow the movements of the actors.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-61&quot;&gt;Thompson, 61.&lt;/ref&gt; The Borg scenes were received positively by [[test screening]] audiences, so once the rest of the film had been completed a Borg assimilation scene of the ''Enterprise'' crew was added in using some of the money left in the budget to add action.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Tucson05 TitanICBM.jpg|thumb|right|A fiberglass capsule was fitted over this decommissioned missile to convert it into Cochrane's ''Phoenix''.|alt=View looking down a textured metal cylindrical enclosure. Inside sits a long, thin missile that is cylindrical in shape with a conical nose.]]
Since so many new sets had to be created, the production commenced filming with location photography. Four days were spent in the [[Titan Missile Museum]], south of [[Tucson, Arizona]]—the disarmed nuclear missile was fitted with a fiberglass capsule shell to stand in for the ''Phoenix''{{'}}s booster and command module.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-329&quot;/&gt; The use of the old missile silo created a large set the budget would have prohibited building from scratch, but the small size created difficulties.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-62&quot;/&gt; Each camera move was planned in advance to work around areas where the lighting would be added, and electricians and grips donned rock-climbing harnesses to move down the shaft and attach the lights. To give greater dimension to the rocket and lend the missile a futuristic appearance, Leonetti chose to offset the missile's metallic surface with complementary colors. Using different-colored gels made the rocket appear longer than it actually was; to complete the effect, shots from the ''Phoenix''{{'}}s nose downwards and from the engines up were filmed with a 30&amp;nbsp;mm lens to lengthen the missile.&lt;ref name=&quot;thomspon-64&quot;&gt;Thompson, 64.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the completion of the ''Phoenix'' shots, the crew moved to two weeks of nighttime shooting in the Angeles National Forest. Zimmerman created a village of fourteen huts to stand in for Montana; the cast enjoyed the scenes as a chance to escape their uniforms and wear &quot;normal&quot; clothes.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; The last location shoot was at an [[art deco]] restaurant in Los Angeles' [[Union Station (Los Angeles)|Union Station]], which stood in for the Dixon Hill holonovel; Frakes wanted a sharp contrast with the dark, mechanical Borg scenes.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; While the cinematographer wanted to shoot the scene in black-and-white, Paramount executives deemed the test footage &quot;too experimental&quot; and the idea was dropped.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-66&quot;/&gt; The site made using high-watt lights impractical, so Leonetti opted to use dimmer master lights near the ceiling and took advantage of a large window to shine diffused lights through. To give the scene a black-and-white feel, Leonetti made sure to use light without any coloration. &quot;I like creating separation with lighting as opposed to using color,&quot; he explained. &quot;You can't always rely on color because the actor might start to melt into the background.&quot; By separating the backlights, Leonetti made sure that the principal actors stood out of the backdrop.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-66&quot;&gt;Thompson, 66.&lt;/ref&gt; The shoot used a ten-piece orchestra, 15&amp;nbsp;stuntmen, and 120&amp;nbsp;extras to fill the seats.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-329&quot;&gt;Nemecek, 329.&lt;/ref&gt; Among the nightclub patrons were Braga, Moore, and the film's stunt coordinator, Ronnie Rondell.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt;

After location shooting was completed, shooting on the new engineering set began May 3. The set lasted less than a day in its pristine condition before it was &quot;Borgified&quot;. Filming then proceeded to the bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-329&quot;/&gt; During normal operation scenes, Leonetti chose to cast crosslighting on the principals; this required the ceiling of the set to be removed and lighting grids situated around the sides. These lights were then directed towards the actors' faces at 90&amp;nbsp;degree angles. The set was lined with window paneling backed by red lights which would blink intermittently during red alert status. These lights were supplemented by what Leonetti called &quot;interactive light&quot;; these were off-stage, red-gelled lights that cast flashing rims on the bridge set and heads of the crew. For the Borg intrusion, the lighting originated solely from instrument panels and red alert displays. The [[fill light]] on these scenes was reduced so that the cast would pass through dark spots on the bridge and interiors out of the limited range of these sources. Small 30 and 50&amp;nbsp;watt lights were used to throw localized shafts of light onto the sets.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-61&quot;/&gt;

Next came the action sequences and the battle for the ''Enterprise'', a phase the filmmakers dubbed &quot;Borg Hell&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-329&quot;/&gt; Frakes directed the Borg scenes similar to a [[horror film]], creating as much suspense as possible. To balance these elements he added more comedic elements to the Earth scenes, intended to momentarily relieve the audience of tension before building it up again.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; Leonetti reconfigured the lighting to reflect the takeover of the ship interiors. &quot;When the ship gets Borgified, everything is changed into more of a squared-off, robotic look with sharp edges but rounded images,&quot; he explained. To give the corridor walls more shape, Leonetti lit them from underneath. Since the halls were so small and the ceilings would be visible in many of the shots, special attention was paid to hiding the light fixtures.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-61&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box|width=30%|align=left|quote=We were on a circle, which has no geography to it. We had our three heroes [Picard, Worf and Hawk] in space suits, which look identical so you couldn't tell who was who until you got in real close. But the minute you get in close, you defeat the whole purpose of being on the outside of the ship, so you can see the cells and the stars and [[Earth]] looming in the background. It was a shooting and editing nightmare.|source= Jonathan Frakes on the difficulty of the spacewalk scene.&lt;ref name=improved/&gt;}}
For the live-action spacewalk scenes, visual effects supervisor Moore spent two weeks of bluescreen photography at the deflector set.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-72&quot;/&gt; Frakes considered filming the scene to be the most tedious in the film due to the amount of preparation it took to start each day's shoot.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; Since the rest of the ''Enterprise''-E, as well as the backdrop of Earth, were to be added later in post-production, coordinating shots became confusing. Moore used a laptop with digital reproductions of the set to orient the crew and help Frakes understand what the finished shot would look like.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-72&quot;/&gt; A one-armed actor portrayed the Borg whose arm Worf slices off to accurately portray the effect intended,&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; and the actors' shoes were fitted with lead weights to remind the actors they were to move slowly as if actually wearing gravity boots. McDonough recalled that he joined Stewart and Dorn in asking whether they could do the shots without the {{convert|10|to|15|lb|kg|adj=on}} weights, as &quot;they hired us because we are actors&quot;, but the production insisted on using them.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-29&quot;/&gt;

The last scene filmed was the film's very first, Picard's Borg nightmare.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt; One shot begins inside the iris of Picard's eyeball and pulls back to reveal the captain aboard a massive Borg ship. The shot continues to pull back and reveal the exterior of a Borg ship. The scene was inspired by a [[New York City]] production of ''[[Sweeney Todd, the Demon Barber of Fleet Street]]'' in which the stage surrounded the audience, giving a sense of realism.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; The shot was filmed as three separate elements merged together with digital effects. The crew used a 50&amp;nbsp;mm lens to make it easier for the effects team to dissolve the closeup shots with the other elements. Starting from Stewart's eye, the camera pulled back {{convert|25|ft|m|sp=us}}, requiring the key light to increase in intensity up to 1000&amp;nbsp;[[Foot-candle|footcandles]] so that there was enough depth to keep the eye sharp. The surface of the stage proved too uneven to accomplish the smooth dolly pullback required by the effects team, who needed a steady shot to blend a computer-generated version of Picard's eye with the pullback. The {{convert|135|ft|m|sp=us|adj=on}} dolly track was raised off the stage floor and layered with pieces of double-thick birch plywood, chosen for its smooth finish. The entire set for the scene was {{convert|100|ft|m|sp=us}} wide and {{convert|25|ft|m|sp=us}} high; gaps left by the dolly reveal were filled in later digitally.&lt;ref name=&quot;thompson-62&quot;&gt;Thompson, 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Principal photography finished on July 2, 1996,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Making First Contact With Frakes' 'First Contact'|accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-08-09| first = Ian | last = Spelling | work=[[Chicago Tribune]]|page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; two days over schedule but still under budget.&lt;ref name=&quot;nemecek-330&quot;/&gt;

===Effects===
The majority of ''First Contact''{{'}}s effects were handled by [[Industrial Light and Magic]] under the direction of [[John Knoll]]. Smaller effects sequences, such as phaser fire, computer graphics, and transporter effects were delegated to a team led by visual effects supervisor David Takemura.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-28&quot;/&gt; Used to directing episodes for the television series, Frakes was frequently reminded by effects artist Terry Frazee to &quot;think big, blow everything up&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; Most of the effects sequences were planned using low-resolution computer-generated [[animatic]]s. These rough animated storyboards established length, action and composition, allowing the producers and director to ascertain how the sequences would play out before they were shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-68&quot;/&gt;

For the ''Enterprise''{{'}}s dramatic introduction, the effects team combined [[motion control]] shots of the ''Enterprise'' model with a computer-generated background. Sequence supervisor Dennis Turner, who had created ''Generations''{{'}} energy ribbon and specialized in creating natural phenomena, was charged with creating the star cluster, modeled after the [[Eagle Nebula]]. The nebular columns and solid areas were modeled with basic wireframe geometry, with surface shaders applied to make the edges of the nebula glow. A particle render ILM devised for the earlier tornado film ''[[Twister (1996 film)|Twister]]'' was used to create a turbulent look within the nebula. Once the shots of the ''Enterprise'' had been captured, Turner inserted the ship into the computer-generated background and altered its position until the images matched up.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-69&quot;&gt;Magid, 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

The opening beauty pass of the new ''Enterprise'' was the responsibility of visual effects cinematographer Marty Rosenberg, who handled all the other miniatures, explosions, and some live-action [[bluescreen]] elements. Rosenberg had previously shot some of the ''Enterprise''-D effects for ''Generations'', but had to adjust his techniques for the new model; the cinematographer used a 50&amp;nbsp;mm lens instead of the 35&amp;nbsp;mm used for ''Generations'' because the smaller lens made the new ''Enterprise''{{'}}s dish appear stretched out. Knoll decided to shoot the model from above and below as much as possible; side views made the ship appear too flat and elongated.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-69&quot;/&gt; The effects supervisor enjoyed motion control passes of ships over computer-generated versions, as it was much easier to capture a high level of detail with physical models rather than trying to recreate it by computer graphics.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-23&quot;/&gt;

For the Borg battle, Knoll insisted on closeup shots that were very near the alien vessel, necessitating a physical model.&lt;ref name=&quot;kaplan-23&quot;/&gt; ILM layered their {{convert|30|in|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} model with an additional five&amp;nbsp;inches of etched brass over a glowing neon lightbox for internal illumination. To make the ship appear even larger than it was, Knoll made sure that an edge of the Borg vessel was facing the camera like the prow of a ship and that the Cube broke the edges of the frame. To give the Cube greater depth and texture, Rosenberg shot the vessel with harsher light.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-69&quot;/&gt; &quot;I created this really odd, raking three-quarter backlight coming from the right or left side, which I balanced out with nets and a couple of little lights. I wanted it to look scary and mysterious, so it was lit like a point, and we always had the camera dutched to it; we never just had it coming straight at us,&quot; he said.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-70&quot;/&gt; Small lights attached to the Cube's surface helped to create visual interest and convey scale; the model was deliberately shot with a slow, determined pacing to contrast with the Federation ships engaged in battle with the Borg. The impact of Federation weaponry on the Borg Cube was simulated using a {{convert|60|in|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} model of the Cube. The model had specific areas which could be blown up multiple times without damaging the miniature. For the final explosion of the Cube, Rosenberg shot ten {{convert|30|in|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} Cube miniatures with explosive-packed lightweight skins. The Cubes were suspended from pipes sixty&amp;nbsp;feet above the camera on the ground. Safety glass was placed over the lens to prevent damage, while the camera was covered with plywood to protect it from bits of plastic that rained down after each explosion. The smaller Borg Sphere was a {{convert|12|in|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} model that was shot separately from the Cube and digitally added in postproduction. The time-travel vortex the Sphere creates was simulated with a rocket re-entry effect; bowshock forms in front of the ship, then streams backwards at high speed. Interactive lighting was played across the computer-generated ''Enterprise'' model for when the ship is caught in the time vortex.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-70&quot;/&gt;

The miniature ''Enterprise'' was again used for the spacewalk sequence. Even on the large model, it was hard to make the miniature appear realistic in extreme close-up shots.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-70&quot;/&gt; To make the pullback shot work, the camera had to be within one-eighth of an inch from the model. Painter Kim Smith spent several days on a tiny area of the model to add enough surface detail for the close-up, but even then the focus was barely adequate. To compensate the crew used a wider-angle lens and shot at the highest [[F-number|f-stop]] they could. The live-action scenes of the spacewalking crew were then digitally added. Wide shots used footage of photo doubles walking across a large bluescreen draped across ILM's parking lot at night.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-72&quot;/&gt;

ILM was tasked with imagining what the immediate assimilation of an ''Enterprise'' crewmember would look like. Jaeger came up with a set of cables that sprang from the Borg's knuckles and buried themselves in the crewmember's neck. Wormlike tubes would course through the victim's body and mechanical devices break the skin. The entire transformation was created using computer-generated imagery. The wormlike geometry was animated over the actor's face, then blended in with the addition of a skin texture over the animation. The gradual change in skin tone was simulated with [[shader]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-74&quot;&gt;Magid, 74.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:S08-first contact borg queen assembled.ogv|thumbtime=14|220px|thumb|alt=Video clip from the film, showing the disembodied head and shoulders of a woman being lowered into a tight black suit by cables. The woman has pale, mottled skin and wires protruding from the back of her head; a mechanical spine hangs from the rest of her upper body.|right|The lowering of the [[Borg Queen]]'s head into her body took ILM five months to produce.&lt;ref name=&quot;improved&quot;/&gt;]]
Frakes considered the entrance of the Borg Queen—where her head, shoulders, and steel spine are lowered by cables and attached to her body—as the &quot;signature [[visual effect]] in the film&quot;. The scene was difficult to execute, taking ILM five months to finish.&lt;ref name=&quot;improved&quot;/&gt; Jaeger devised a rig that would lower the actress on the set, and applied a prosthetic spine over a blue suit so that ILM could remove Krige's lower body. This strategy enabled the filmmakers to incorporate as many live-action elements without resorting to further digital effects. To make the prosthetics appear at the proper angle when her lower body was removed, Krige extended her neck forward so it appeared in line with the spine. Knoll did not want it to seem that the Queen was on a hard, mechanical rig; &quot;we wanted her to have the appropriate 'float',&quot; he explained. Using separate motion control passes on the set, Knoll shot the lower of the upper torso and the secondary sequence with Krige's entire body. A digital version of the Borg body suit was used for the lowering sequence, at which point the image was morphed back to the real shot of Krige's body. The animated claws of the suit were created digitally as well using a very detailed model.&lt;ref name=&quot;magid-74&quot;/&gt; As reference to the animators, the shot required Krige to realistically portray &quot;the strange pain or satisfaction of being reconnected to her body&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt;

===Music===
Film composer [[Jerry Goldsmith]] scored ''First Contact'', his third ''Star Trek'' feature. Goldsmith wrote a sweeping main title which begins with [[Alexander Courage]]'s classic [[Theme from Star Trek|''Star Trek'' fanfare]].&lt;ref name=&quot;norman&quot;/&gt; Instead of composing a menacing theme to underscore the Borg, Goldsmith wrote a pastoral theme linked to humanity's hopeful first contact. The theme uses a four-note motif used in Goldsmith's ''[[Star Trek V: The Final Frontier]]'' score, which is used in ''First Contact'' as a friendship theme and general thematic link.&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-155&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-156&quot;&gt;Bond, 156.&lt;/ref&gt; A menacing march with touches of synthesizers were used to represent the Borg. In addition to composing new music, Goldsmith utilized music from his previous ''Star Trek'' scores, including his theme from ''The Motion Picture''.&lt;ref name=&quot;norman&quot;&gt;Norman.&lt;/ref&gt; The Klingon theme from the same film is used to represent Worf.&lt;ref name=&quot;larson&quot;/&gt;

Because of delays with Paramount's ''[[The Ghost and the Darkness]]'', the already-short four week production schedule was cut to just three weeks. While Berman was concerned about the move,&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-158&quot;&gt;Bond, 158.&lt;/ref&gt; Goldsmith hired his son, [[Joel Goldsmith|Joel]], to assist.&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-155&quot;&gt;Bond, 155.&lt;/ref&gt; The young composer provided additional music for the film, writing three cues based on his father's motifs&lt;ref name=&quot;larson&quot;&gt;Larson.&lt;/ref&gt; and a total of 22&amp;nbsp;minutes of music.&lt;ref name=&quot;norman&quot;/&gt; Joel used variations of his father's Borg music and the Klingon theme as Worf fights hand-to-hand&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-156&quot;/&gt; (Joel said that he and his father decided to use the theme for Worf separately).&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-159&quot;&gt;Bond, 159.&lt;/ref&gt; When the Borg invade sickbay and the medical hologram distracts them, Joel wrote what critic [[Jeff Bond]] termed &quot;almost Coplandesque&quot; material of tuning strings and clarinet, but the cue was unused. While Joel composed many of the film's action cues, his father contributed to the spacewalk and ''Phoenix'' flight sequences. During the fight on the deflector dish, Goldsmith used low-register electronics punctuated by stabs of violent, dissonant strings.&lt;ref name=&quot;bond-156&quot;/&gt;

In a break with ''Star Trek'' film tradition, the soundtrack incorporated two licensed songs: [[Roy Orbison]]'s &quot;Ooby Dooby&quot; and [[Steppenwolf (band)|Steppenwolf]]'s &quot;Magic Carpet Ride&quot;. [[GNP Crescendo Record Co.|GNP Crescendo]] president Neil Norman explained that the decision to include the tracks was controversial, but said that &quot;Frakes did the most amazing job of integrating those songs into the story that we had to use them&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;billboard-sprague nothing like the reel thing&quot;/&gt;

GNP released the ''First Contact'' soundtrack on December 2, 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;billboard-sprague nothing like the reel thing&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Sprague | first = David | date=1996-12-14|title=Nothing like the reel thing; Soundtrack and film score news|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The album contained 51&amp;nbsp;minutes of music, with 35&amp;nbsp;minutes of Jerry Goldsmith's score, 10&amp;nbsp;minutes of additional music by Joel Goldsmith, &quot;Ooby Dooby&quot; and &quot;Magic Carpet Ride&quot;. The compact disc shipped with [[CD-ROM]] features only accessible if played on a personal computer,&lt;ref name=&quot;filmscoremonthly-first contact&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last = Herries | first = Iain | year=1997|month=March/April|title=Score; the latest in soundtrack releases|journal=[[Film Score Monthly]]|volume=2|issue=2|pages=34–35}}&lt;/ref&gt; including interviews with Berman, Frakes, and Goldsmith.&lt;ref name=&quot;billboard-sprague nothing like the reel thing&quot;/&gt;

==Themes==
Frakes believes the main themes of ''First Contact''—and ''Star Trek'' as a whole—are loyalty, friendship, honesty and mutual respect. This is evident in the film when Picard chooses to rescue Data rather than evacuate the ship with rest of the crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; The film makes a direct comparison between Picard's hatred of the Borg and refusal to destroy the ''Enterprise'' and that of [[Moby-Dick|Captain Ahab]] in [[Herman Melville]]'s novel ''[[Moby-Dick]]''. The moment marks a turning point in the film as Picard changes his mind, symbolized by his putting down his gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;frakes&quot;/&gt; A similar ''Moby-Dick'' reference was made in ''[[Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan]]'', and although Braga and Moore did not want to repeat it, they decided it worked so well they could not leave it out.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt;

In ''First Contact'', the individually inscrutable and faceless Borg fulfill the role of the equally unreadable titular white whale in Melville's work. Picard, like Ahab, has been hurt by his nemesis, and author Elizabeth Hinds said it makes sense that Picard should &quot;opt for the perverse alternative of remaining on board ship to fight&quot; the Borg rather than take the only sensible option left, to destroy the ship.&lt;ref name=&quot;hinds&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|author=Hinds, Elizabeth Jane Wall|year=1997|url=http://www.br.vccs.edu/library/guides/wrath%20of%20ahab.pdf|title=The Wrath of Ahab; Or, Herman Melville meets Gene Roddenberry|journal=Journal of American Culture|volume=20|issue=1|pages=45–46}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several lines in the film refer to the 21st century dwellers being primitive, with the people of the 24th century having evolved to a more [[utopia]]n society. In the end it is Lily (the 21st century woman) who shows Picard (the 24th century man) that his quest for revenge is the very primitive behavior that humans had evolved to not use.&lt;ref name=&quot;braga&quot;/&gt; Lily's words cause Picard to reconsider, and he quotes Ahab's words of vengeance, recognizing the death wish embedded therein.&lt;ref name=&quot;hinds&quot;/&gt;

The nature of the Borg, specifically as seen in ''First Contact'', has been the subject of critical discussion. Author Joanna Zylinska notes that while other alien species are tolerated by humanity in ''Star Trek'', the Borg are viewed differently due to their cybernetic alterations and the loss of personal freedom and autonomy. Members of the crew who are assimilated into the Collective are subsequently viewed as &quot;polluted by technology&quot; and less than human. Zylinska draws comparisons between the technological distinction of humanity and machine in ''Star Trek'' and the work of artists such as [[Stelarc]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Zylinska | first = Joanna | year=2002|title=The cyborg experiments: the extensions of the body in the media age|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=082645903X |pages=46–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; Oliver Marchart drew parallels between the Borg's combination of many into an artificial one and [[Thomas Hobbes]]'s concept of the [[Leviathan (book)|Leviathan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Marchart | first = Oliver | title= Inclusion/ Exclusion|editor= Dirk Baecker, Urs Stäkeli|publisher=Lucius &amp; Lucius DE|year=2002|isbn=3828202306|page=70}}&lt;/ref&gt; The nature of perilous first contact between species as represented by films such as ''[[Independence Day (film)|Independence Day]]'', ''[[Aliens (film)|Aliens]]'' and ''First Contact'' is a marriage of classic fears of national invasion and the loss of personal identity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Caldwell | first = Patrice | series=Take me to your leader&quot;|year=2000|title=Space and beyond: the frontier theme in science fiction|editor=Gary Westfahl|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0313308462|page=103}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
===Release===
1996 marked the 30th anniversary of the ''Star Trek'' franchise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bold as ever As 'Star Trek' approaches its 30th anniversary, the cast and crew prepare for future generations |accessdate=2008-03-23|date=1996-08-18 | first = Mark A. | last = Perigard|work=[[Boston Herald]] | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/bostonherald/access/17318641.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Aug+18%2C+1996&amp;author=Mark+A.+Perigard&amp;pub=Boston+Herald&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=006&amp;desc=Bold+as+ever+As+`Star+Trek%27+approaches+its+30th+anniversary%2C+the+cast+and+crew+prepare+for+future+generations }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''First Contact'' was heavily marketed, to an extent not seen since the release of ''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]]'' in 1979. Several novelizations of the film were written for different age groups. [[Playmates Toys]] produced six- and nine-inch [[action figure]]s in addition to ship models and a phaser. Two &quot;making of&quot; television specials premiered on [[HBO]] and the [[SyFy|Sci-Fi Channel]], as well as being promoted during a 30th anniversary television special on [[UPN]].&lt;ref name=&quot;trekmovie-marketing&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Tenuto | first = John | date=2008-02-03|url=http://trekmovie.com/2008/02/03/history-of-trek-movie-merchandising/|title=History of Trek Movie Merchandising|publisher=TrekMovie|accessdate=2009-06-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The theatrical trailer to the film was included on a ''Best of Star Trek'' music compilation, released at the same time as the ''First Contact'' soundtrack.&lt;ref name=&quot;billboard-sprague nothing like the reel thing&quot;/&gt; [[Simon &amp; Schuster Interactive]] produced a Borg-themed video game for personal computers (separate Macintosh and Windows95 versions were available). The game, ''[[Star Trek: Borg]]'', functioned as an [[interactive movie]] with scenes filmed at the same time as ''First Contact''{{'s}} production.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Snider | first = Mike | date=1996-12-05|title=Be the Borg in 'Star Trek' adventure|work=[[USA Today]]|page=6D | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/USAToday/access/16342862.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Dec+5%2C+1996&amp;author=Mike+Snider&amp;pub=USA+TODAY+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=06.D&amp;desc=Be+the+Borg+in+%27Star+Trek%27+adventure }}&lt;/ref&gt; Paramount heavily marketed the film on the internet via a ''First Contact'' web site that averaged 4.4&amp;nbsp;million hits a week during the film's opening run, the largest amount of traffic ever on a motion picture site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Sheinkopf | first = Evelyn | date=1996-12-16|title=Online hype boosts awareness|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film premiered November 18, 1996 at [[Mann's Chinese Theater]] in [[Hollywood, Los Angeles]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-directing&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/12/18/garden/a-starship-chief-goes-bravely-into-directing.html |title=A Starship Chief Goes Bravely Into Directing|accessdate=2008-03-22|date=1996-12-18|work=[[The New York Times]]| first = Michel | last = Marriott}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main cast save Spiner were in attendance, as were Moore, Braga, Jerry Goldsmith, and producer [[Marty Hornstein]]. Other ''Star Trek'' actors present included [[DeForest Kelley]], [[René Auberjonois (actor)|René Auberjonois]], [[Avery Brooks]], [[Colm Meaney]], [[Armin Shimerman]], [[Terry Farrell (actress)|Terry Farrell]], [[Kate Mulgrew]], [[Roxann Dawson]], [[Jennifer Lien]], [[Robert Duncan McNeill]], Ethan Phillips, [[Tim Russ]], [[Garrett Wang]] and Robert Picardo. After the screening 1,500 guests crossed the street to the Hollywood Colonnade, where the interiors had been dressed to match settings from the film: the holodeck nightclub, part of the bridge, a &quot;star room&quot;, the Borg hive and the &quot;crash 'n' burn lounge&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;variety-premiere&quot;&gt;{{cite news|date=1996-11-20|title='First' Class|work=[[Daily Variety]]|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film received a royal premiere in the United Kingdom, with the first screening attended by [[Charles, Prince of Wales]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-directing&quot;/&gt;

''First Contact'' opened in 2,812 theaters beginning November 22, grossing $30.7&amp;nbsp;million its first week and making it the top movie at the US box office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Vigoda | first = Arlene | date=1996-11-26|title='First Contact' in 1st place|work=[[USA Today]]|page=1D | url = http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/USAToday/access/16336415.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;date=Nov+26%2C+1996&amp;author=Arlene+Vigoda&amp;pub=USA+TODAY+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=01.D&amp;desc=%27First+Contact%27+in+1st+place }}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was knocked out of the top place the following week by ''[[101 Dalmatians (1996 film)|101 Dalmatians]]'', earning $25.5&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff|date=1996-12-03|title=Top Ten Films|work=[[The Washington Post]]|page=E2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film went on to gross $77&amp;nbsp;million in its first four weeks, remaining in the top ten box office during that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-directing&quot;/&gt; It closed with a domestic gross of $92,027,888&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=main&amp;id=startrek8.htm|title=Star Trek: First Contact|accessdate=2008-03-24|publisher=[[Box Office Mojo]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a international gross of $57.4&amp;nbsp;million,&lt;ref name=&quot;hollywood reporter-box office&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last = Segers | first = Frank|date=2009-06-07|url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/news/terminator-tops-overseas-boxoffice-85044 |title='Terminator' tops overseas boxoffice|work=[[The Hollywood Reporter]]|accessdate=2009-08-01 | agency=Associated Press }}&lt;/ref&gt; for a total of $146&amp;nbsp;million worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Tiwari | first = Neha | date=2006-10-06|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-10784_3-6123301-7.html|title='Star Trek' movies: Which is best?|publisher=[[CNET Networks]]|accessdate=2009-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was the best-performing ''Star Trek'' film in international markets until 2009's ''[[Star Trek (film)|Star Trek]]'' reboot,&lt;ref name=&quot;hollywood reporter-box office&quot;/&gt; and Paramount's best showing in markets such as New Zealand, making $315,491 from 28 sites by year's end.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Woods | first = Mark | date=1996-12-31|title='Daylight' in money o'seas|work=[[Daily Variety]]|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''First Contact'' earned an [[Academy Award]]-nomination for [[Academy Award for Makeup|Best Makeup]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff|date=1997-02-12|title=The Nominees are...|work=[[The Toronto Sun]]|page=51}}&lt;/ref&gt; losing to ''[[The Nutty Professor (1996 film)|The Nutty Professor]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last1 = Waxman | first1 = Sharon | first2 = Rob | last2 = Givham |date=1997-03-25|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/movies/features/oscars/oscars.htm|title=Oscar winners: 'Patient' Is Its Own Reward|work=[[The Washington Post]]|accessdate=2009-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the [[Saturn Awards]], the film was nominated in ten categories including [[Saturn Award for Best Science Fiction Film|Best Science Fiction Film]], [[Saturn Award for Best Actor|Best Actor]] for [[Patrick Stewart]], and [[Saturn Award for Best Direction|Best Director]] for [[Jonathan Frakes]]. It won three, for [[Saturn Award for Best Costume|Best Costumes]], [[Saturn Award for Best Supporting Actor|Best Supporting Actor]] ([[Brent Spiner]]), and [[Saturn Award for Best Supporting Actress|Best Supporting Actress]] ([[Alice Krige]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.saturnawards.org/past.html|title=Past Saturn Awards|publisher=Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films|accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jerry Goldsmith]] won a [[BMI Film Music Award]] for his score,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|date=2004-07-22|url=http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/news/article/6199.html|title=Jerry Goldsmith Virtually Defined the Music of Star Trek|work=StarTrek.com|publisher=CBS Studios|accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the film was nominated for the [[Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thehugoawards.org/?page_id=23|title=1997 Hugo Awards|publisher=World Science Fiction Society|accessdate=2009-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical response===
''First Contact'' garnered positive reviews on release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Werts | first = Diane | date=1996-11-29|title=A 'First' for Him; Jonathan Frakes takes directing controls of the latest 'Star Trek' film enterprise|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]|page=F1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ryan Gilbey of ''[[The Independent]]'' considered the film wise to dispense with the cast of ''The Original Series''; &quot;For the first time, a ''Star Trek'' movie actually looks like something more ambitious than an extended TV show,&quot; he wrote.&lt;ref name=&quot;independent-gilbey review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Gilbey | first = Ryan | date=1996-12-12|title=Alien nation; Star Trek: First Contact|work=[[The Independent]]|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, critic Bob Thompson felt that ''First Contact'' was more in the spirit of the 1960s television series than any previous installment.&lt;ref name=&quot;torontosun-thompson review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Thompson | first = Bob | date=1996-11-22|title=All A-Borg The New Star Trek; 'First Contact' says goodbye to the old with an all-new generation cast|work=[[The Toronto Sun]]|page=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Globe and Mail]]''{{'s}} Elizabeth Renzeti said that ''First Contact'' succeeded in improving on the &quot;stilted&quot; previous entry in the series, and that it featured a renewed interest in storytelling.&lt;ref name=&quot;globeandmail-renzeti review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Renzetti | first = Elizabeth | date=1996-11-22|title=Also opening; Star Trek: First Contact|work=[[The Globe and Mail]]|page=D2}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Kenneth Turan]] of the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' wrote, &quot;''First Contact'' does everything you'd want a ''Star Trek'' film to do, and it does it with cheerfulness and style.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;latimes-turan review&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-movie961122-6,0,3974523.story|title=Star Trek: First Contact|accessdate=2008-03-24|date=1996-11-22|work=[[Los Angeles Times]]| first = Kenneth | last = Turan | authorlink = Kenneth Turan | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080409230925/http://www.calendarlive.com/movies/reviews/cl-movie961122-6,0,3974523.story |archivedate = April 9, 2008|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adrian Martin of ''The Age'' noted that the film was geared towards pleasing fans; &quot;Strangers to this fanciful world first delineated by Gene Roddenberry will just have to struggle to comprehend as best they can,&quot; he wrote, but &quot;cult-followers will be in heaven&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;theage-martin review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Martin | first = Adrian | date=1996-11-28|title=Final frontier for fans|work=[[The Age]]|page=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The New York Times]]''{{'}} [[Janet Maslin]] said that the &quot;film's convoluted plot will boggle all but hard-core devotees&quot; of the series,&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-maslin review&quot;/&gt; while ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]''{{'s}} Joe Leydon wrote that the film did not require intimate knowledge of the series and that fans and non-fans alike would enjoy the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;variety-leydon review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Leydon | first = Joe | date=1996-11-18|url=http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117911494.html |title=Star Trek: First Contact|work=[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]|accessdate=2008-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Renzetti considered the lack of old characters from the previous seven movies a welcome change,&lt;ref name=&quot;globeandmail-renzeti review&quot;/&gt; Maslin said that without the original stars, &quot;The series now lacks [...] much of its earlier determination. It has morphed into something less innocent and more derivative than it used to be, something the noncultist is ever less likely to enjoy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes-maslin review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Maslin | first = Janet | authorlink = Janet Maslin | date=1996-11-22|url=http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9A0CE4DA163DF931A15752C1A960958260 |title=Zap! And off to do battle with aliens|work=[[The New York Times]]|page=C3|accessdate=2009-08-01 | quote = The series now lacks all of its original stars and much of its earlier determination. It has morphed into something less innocent and more derivative than it used to be, something the noncultist is ever less likely to enjoy. &lt;br /&gt; For one thing, this film's convoluted plot will boggle all but hard-core devotees. }}&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, [[Roger Ebert]] called ''First Contact'' one of the best ''Star Trek'' films,&lt;ref name=&quot;ebert-review&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19961122/REVIEWS/611220304/1023|title=Star Trek: First Contact |date=1996-11-22|accessdate=2008-03-24|work=[[Chicago Sun-Times]]| first = Roger | last = Ebert | authorlink = Roger Ebert }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[James Berardinelli]] found the film the most entertaining ''Star Trek'' feature in a decade; &quot;It has single-handedly revived the ''Star Trek'' movie series, at least from a creative point-of-view,&quot; he wrote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.reelviews.net/movies/s/st8.html|title=Star Trek: First Contact|accessdate=2008-04-02|year=1996| last = Berardinelli | first = James | authorlink = James Berardinelli | publisher=ReelViews}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film's acting was conflictingly received. [[Lisa Schwarzbaum]] of ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' appreciated that guest stars Woodard and Cromwell were used in &quot;inventive contrast&quot; to their better known images, as a &quot;serious dramatic actress&quot; and &quot;dancing farmer in ''[[Babe (film)|Babe]]''&quot;, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;entertainmentweekly-schwarz review&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,295263,00.html|title=Space Jammin' (1996)| last = Schwarzbaum | first = Lisa | authorlink = Lisa Schwarzbaum | accessdate=2008-03-25|date=1996-11-29|work=[[Entertainment Weekly]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lloyd Rose]] of ''[[The Washington Post]]'' felt that while Woodard and Cromwell managed to &quot;take care of themselves&quot;, Frakes' direction of other actors was not inspired;&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost-rose review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Rose | first = Lloyd | authorlink = Lloyd Rose | date=1996-11-22|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/style/longterm/review96/startrekfirstcontactrose.htm|title=First Contact: A Stellar Fantasy|work=[[The Washington Post]]|accessdate=2009-07-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Steve Persall of the ''[[St. Petersburg Times]]'' opined that only Cromwell received a choice role in the film, &quot;so he steals the show by default&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;petersburg times-persall review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Persall | first = Steve | date=1996-11-22|title=Lost in space|work=[[St. Petersburg Times]]|page=8}}&lt;/ref&gt; A couple of reviews noted that Data's interactions with the Borg Queen were among the most interesting parts of the film;&lt;ref name=&quot;ebert-review&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-review&quot;/&gt; critic John Griffin credited Spiner's work as providing &quot;ambivalent frisson&quot; to the feature.&lt;ref name=&quot;gazette-griffin review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Griffin | first = John | date=1996-11-22|title=Star Trek leaves old gang behind but gives a few new twists|work=[[The Gazette (Montreal)|The Gazette]]|page=D3}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]'' magazine's Adam Smith wrote that some characters, particularly Troi and Crusher, were lost or ignored, and that the rapid pacing of the film left no time for those unfamiliar with the series to know or care about the characters.&lt;ref name=&quot;empire-scott review&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?DVDID=10616|title=Star Trek: First Contact (12)|accessdate=2008-03-24| last = Smith | first = Adam | work=[[Empire (magazine)|Empire]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, Emily Carlisle of the [[BBC]] praised Woodard's, Spiner's, and Stewart's performances, but felt the film focused more on action than characterization.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc-review&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2001/02/07/star_trek_first_contact_1996_review.shtml|title=Star Trek: First Contact (1996)|accessdate=2008-03-24|date=2001-02-07| last = Carlisle | first = Emily | work=[[BBC]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stewart, who Thompson and Renzetti considered overshadowed by [[William Shatner]] in the previous film,&lt;ref name=&quot;torontosun-thompson review&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;globeandmail-renzeti review&quot;/&gt; received praise from [[Richard Corliss]] of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'': &quot;As Patrick Stewart delivers [a] line with a majestic ferocity worthy of a [[Royal Shakespeare Company]] alumnus, the audience gapes in awe at a special effect more imposing than any [special effect]. Here is real acting! In a ''Star Trek'' film!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;time-review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Corliss | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Corliss | date=1996-11-25|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,985589,00.html|title=Aliens! Adventure! Acting!|work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|accessdate=2008-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The special effects were generally praised. Jay Carr of ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' said that ''First Contact'' successfully updated ''Star Trek'' creator [[Gene Roddenberry]]'s concept with more elaborate effects and action.&lt;ref name=&quot;bostonglobe-carr review&quot;/&gt; Thompson's assessment mirrored Carr's; he agreed that the film managed to convey much of the original 1960s television show, and contained enough &quot;special effects wonders and interstellar gunplay&quot; to sate all types of viewers. Ebert wrote that while previous films had often looked &quot;clunky&quot; in the effects department, ''First Contact'' benefited from the latest in effects technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebert-review&quot;/&gt; A dissenting opinion was offered by Scott, who wrote that aside from the key effects sequences, Frakes &quot;aims to distract Trekkers from the distinctly cheap-looking remainder&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;empire-scott review&quot;/&gt;

Critics reacted favorably to the Borg, describing them as akin to creatures from ''[[Hellraiser (film series)|Hellraiser]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;bostonglobe-carr review&quot;&gt;{{cite news| last = Carr | first = Jay | date=1996-11-22|work=[[The Boston Globe]]|title=New 'Star Trek' makes comfy contact|page=E5 | url = https://secure.pqarchiver.com/boston/access/16191768.html?FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Nov+22%2C+1996&amp;author=Jay+Carr%2C+Globe+Staff&amp;pub=Boston+Globe+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;edition=&amp;startpage=E.5&amp;desc=New+`Star+Trek%27+makes+comfy+contact }}&lt;/ref&gt; Renzetti credited them with breathing &quot;new life&quot; into the crew of the ''Enterprise'' while simultaneously trying to kill them.&lt;ref name=&quot;globeandmail-renzeti review&quot;/&gt; The Borg Queen received special attention for her combination of horror and seduction; Ebert wrote that while the Queen &quot;looks like no notion of sexy I have ever heard of&quot;, he was inspired &quot;to keep an open mind&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ebert-review&quot;/&gt; Carr said, &quot;She proves that women with filmy blue skin, lots of external tubing and bad teeth can be sleekly seductive.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bostonglobe-carr review&quot;/&gt;

===Home media===
''First Contact'' was released on videotape in late 1997 as one of several titles expected to boost sluggish sales at video retailers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Lieber | first = Ed | date=1997-07-21|title=Stores see video relief; new video titles to be released|work=HFN; The Weekly Newspaper for the Home Furnishing Network Article}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[LaserDisc]] version was also released.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-olddvdrev&quot;/&gt; ''First Contact'' was among the first titles announced for the [[DVD]]-alternative rental system [[DIVX (Digital Video Express)|Digital Video Express]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff|date=1998-06-08|title=More than 30 titles listed for DIVX launch|work=Audio Week}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was launched with five other test titles in the select markets of [[Richmond, Virginia]] and [[San Francisco]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Fitzpatrick | first = Eileen | date=1998-06-20|title=Paramount foresees 4Q surge with 'Titanic' video|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When Paramount announced its first slate of DVD releases in August 1998, ''First Contact'' was one of the first ten titles released in October,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Goldstein | first = Seth | date=1998-08-22|title=Picture this; Fox and Paramount end DVD Holdouts|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; announced in a conscious effort to showcase effects-driven films.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Garrett | first = Diane | date=1998-09-19|title=Kids' Video gets slow start on DVD|work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This version contained the feature and two trailers, but no other special features. The film was presented in a 2.35:1 anamorphic aspect ratio, with a [[surround sound]] Dolby Digital 5.1 audio mix.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-olddvdrev&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Conrad | first = Jeremy | date=2001-10-31|url=http://dvd.ign.com/articles/315/315636p1.html|title=Star Trek: First Contact; Find out why we feel this film is on the same level as The Wrath of Khan|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''First Contact'' &quot;Special Collector's Edition&quot; two-disc set was released in 2005 at the same time as three other ''Next Generation'' films and ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]''{{'}}s fourth season, marking the first time that every film and episode of the franchise was available on home video.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Staff|date=2005-12-14|title=Star Trek burns up|work=[[Herald Sun]]|page=H10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the feature, presented with the same technical specifications as the previous release and a new [[DTS (sound system)|DTS]] soundtrack,&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-dvdreview2&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Patrizio | first = Andrew | date=2005-03-07|url=http://dvd.ign.com/articles/594/594096p2.html|title=Star Trek: First Contact - Special Collector's Edition|page=2|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; the first disc contains Frakes' director's commentary and a track by Moore and Braga.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-dvdreview2&quot;/&gt; As with other special edition DVD releases, the disc includes a text track by [[Michael Okuda|Michael]] and [[Denise Okuda]] that provides production trivia and relevant facts about the ''Star Trek'' universe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| last = Szadkowski | first = Joseph | date=2005-03-07|title=Star Fox unleashes adorably furry fury|work=[[The Washington Times]]|page=B4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-dvdreview3&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Patrizio | first = Andrew | date=2005-03-07|url=http://dvd.ign.com/articles/594/594096p3.html|title=Star Trek: First Contact - Special Collector's Edition|page=3|publisher=[[IGN]]|accessdate=2009-07-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The second disc contains six making-of featurettes, storyboards, and trailers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign-dvdreview3&quot;/&gt;

Paramount announced that all four ''The Next Generation'' films would be released on high-definition [[Blu-ray]] on September 22, 2009. ''First Contact'' is presented in [[1080p]] high definition enhanced for widescreen television. The Blu-ray transfer features 5.1&amp;nbsp;Dolby TrueHD audio in English, French, and Spanish languages. In addition to previous content, the version contains &quot;Scene Deconstruction&quot; featurettes and new commentary by writers [[Damon Lindelof]] and Anthony Pascale.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| last = Pascale | first = Anthony | date=2009-07-20|url=http://trekmovie.com/2009/07/20/details-on-star-trek-tng-movie-blu-ray-dvd-tos-season-two-sets-more/|title=Details On Star Trek TNG Movie Blu-Ray &amp; DVD + TOS Season Two Sets + more|publisher=TrekMovie|accessdate=2009-07-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book| last = Bond | first = Jeff | year=1999|title=The Music of Star Trek|publisher=Lone Eagle Publishing Company|isbn=1580650120}}
* {{cite video |people=[[John Eaves|Eaves, John]] |date=2005-03-15 |title=Star Trek: First Contact; The Art of First Contact |publisher=[[Paramount Pictures]] |medium=DVD; Disc 2/2}}
* {{cite video |people=Frakes, Jonathan |date=2005-03-15 |title=Star Trek: First Contact; Audio commentary |publisher=[[Paramount Pictures]] |medium=DVD; Disc 1/2}}
* {{cite journal | last = Kaplan | first = Anna | date=December 1996 |title=The Next Generation goes Solo; Data; Writing the Script; Special Effects; Borg; Production Design; Zephram Cochrane |journal=[[Cinefantastique]] |volume=28 |issue=6 |pages=18–31}}
* {{cite journal |last=Magid |first=Ron |date=December 1996 |title=Where No Trek Has Gone Before |journal=[[American Cinematographer]]|issn=0002-7928|volume=77|issue=12|pages=68–74}}
* {{cite book |last=Nemecek |first=Larry |year=2003 |title=Star Trek: The Next Generation Companion |publisher=Pocket Books |edition=3rd |isbn=0743457986}}
* {{cite video |people=[[Michael Okuda|Okuda, Michael]] |date=2005-03-15 |title=Star Trek: First Contact; Text commentary |publisher=[[Paramount Pictures]] |medium=DVD; Disc 1/2}}
* {{cite album-notes |title=Star Trek: First Contact Original Motion Picture Soundtrack |artist=[[Jerry Goldsmith]] |year=1996 |notestitle=Liner notes |first=Neil |last=Norman |format=CD booklet |publisher=GNP Crescendo}}
* {{cite journal |last=Thompson |first=Andrew O |date=December 1996 |title=Battling the Borg |journal=[[American Cinematographer]] |issn=0002-7928 |volume=77 |issue=12 |pages=58–66}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Star Trek: First Contact|Star Trek: First Contact}}
* {{official website|http://www.startrek.com/page/star-trek-first-contact}}
* {{IMDb title|0117731}}
* {{amg title|136562}}
* {{rotten tomatoes|star_trek_first_contact}}
* {{mojo title|startrek8}}
* {{memoryalpha}}

{{Star Trek navbox}}
{{Jonathan Frakes}}
{{Star Trek Borg Stories}}
{{Star Trek time travel stories}}
{{Star Trek Vulcan stories}}
{{Star Trek TNG}}
{{featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Star Trek 08: First Contact}}
[[Category:1990s action films]]
[[Category:1990s science fiction films]]
[[Category:1996 films]]
[[Category:Alien visitation films]]
[[Category:Directorial debut films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Jonathan Frakes]]
[[Category:Films set in Montana]]
[[Category:Films set in the 2060s]]
[[Category:Films set in the 24th century]]
[[Category:Films set in the future]]
[[Category:Films shot in California]]
[[Category:Films shot in Arizona]]
[[Category:Robot films]]
[[Category:Sequel films]]
[[Category:Space adventure films]]
[[Category:Star Trek films]]
[[Category:Star Trek time travel episodes]]
[[Category:Time travel films]]

[[bg:Стар Трек VIII: Първи контакт]]
[[ca:Star Trek VIII: Primer contacte]]
[[cs:Star Trek: První kontakt]]
[[de:Star Trek: Der erste Kontakt]]
[[et:Star Trek: Esimene kontakt]]
[[es:Star Trek VIII: primer contacto]]
[[fr:Star Trek : Premier Contact]]
[[id:Star Trek: First Contact]]
[[it:Primo contatto (film)]]
[[he:מסע בין כוכבים 8: המפגש]]
[[hu:Star Trek: Kapcsolatfelvétel]]
[[nl:Star Trek: First Contact]]
[[ja:スタートレック ファーストコンタクト]]
[[pl:Star Trek: Pierwszy kontakt]]
[[pt:Star Trek: First Contact]]
[[ro:Star Trek: Primul contact]]
[[ru:Звёздный путь: Первый контакт]]
[[simple:Star Trek: First Contact]]
[[sk:Star Trek VIII: Prvý kontakt]]
[[sl:Zvezdne steze: Prvo srečanje]]
[[fi:Star Trek – ensimmäinen yhteys]]
[[sv:Star Trek: First Contact]]
[[uk:Зоряний шлях: Перший контакт]]
[[zh:星艦奇航記VIII：戰鬥巡航]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
