<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27092" ns="0" title="Star Trek: The Animated Series"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Television
| bgcolor            = #D6B97A
| show_name          = Star Trek
| image              = [[Image:TAS title.jpg|250px]]
| caption            = ''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' intertitle
| format             = [[Animated cartoon|Animated Series]]&lt;br&gt;[[Science fiction]]
| camera             = 
| picture_format     = [[NTSC]] [[480i]]
| audio_format       = [[Monaural]]
| runtime            = 30 minutes
| creator            = [[Gene Roddenberry]]
| developer          = 
| director           = [[Hal Sutherland]] (Season 1)&lt;br&gt;Bill Reed (Season 2)
| executive_producer = [[Gene Roddenberry]]&lt;br&gt;[[D. C. Fontana]]
| producer           = [[Norm Prescott]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lou Scheimer]]
| company            = [[Filmation]]&lt;br&gt;[[Norway Corporation|Norway Productions]]
| distributor        = [[Paramount Television]]&lt;br&gt;[[CBS Television Distribution]] (''current'')
| voices             = [[William Shatner]]&lt;br&gt;[[Leonard Nimoy]]&lt;br&gt;[[DeForest Kelley]]&lt;br&gt;[[James Doohan]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nichelle Nichols]]&lt;br&gt;[[George Takei]]&lt;br&gt;[[Majel Barrett]]
| narrated           = 
| opentheme          = 
| endtheme           = 
| country            = United States
| language           = English
| network            = [[NBC]]
| first_run          = 
| first_aired        = {{Start date|1973|9|8}}
| last_aired         = {{End date|1974|10|12}}
| num_episodes       = 22
| num_seasons        = 2
| list_episodes      = List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes
| preceded_by        = ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]''
| followed_by        = ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]''
| related            = ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'',&lt;br&gt;''[[Star Trek: Voyager]]'',&lt;br&gt;''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]''
| website            = http://www.startrek.com/page/star-trek-the-animated-series
| website_title      = The Animated Series at StarTrek.com
}}

'''''Star Trek: The Animated Series''''' (originally known as simply ''Star Trek'' but also known as ''The Animated Adventures of Gene Roddenberry’s'' Star Trek) is an  [[animation|animated]] [[science fiction]] [[Television program|television series]] set in the ''[[Star Trek]]'' universe following the events of ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]'' of the 1960s. The animated series was aired under the name '''''Star Trek''''', but it has become widely known under this longer name (or abbreviated as ''ST: TAS'' or ''TAS'') to differentiate it from the original [[live-action]] ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series|Star Trek]].'' The success in syndication of the original live action series and fan pressure for a ''Star Trek'' revival led to ''The Animated Series'' from 1973–1974, as the source of new adventures of the ''Enterprise'' crew, the next being the 1979 live-action feature film  ''[[Star Trek: The Motion Picture]]''. ''TAS'' was the first ''Star Trek'' series to win an [[Emmy Award]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0069637/awards ''Star Trek: TAS'' - Awards&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
The series was produced by [[Filmation]] in association with [[Paramount Television]] and ran for two seasons from 1973 to 1974 on [[NBC]], airing a total of twenty-two half-hour episodes. An early Filmation proposal for this series had children assigned to each of the senior officers as cadets, including a young Vulcan for Mr. Spock. According to interviews with [[Norm Prescott]], Paramount offered Roddenberry a substantial sum of money to abandon creative control of the project and let Filmation proceed with their &quot;kiddy space cadet&quot; idea. Roddenberry refused. Filmation would later develop the idea into its own original live action program, ''[[Space Academy]]'', in 1977.

The writers of the animated series used, essentially, the same writers' guide that was used for the live-action ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series]]''. (A copy of the &quot;[[Bible (writing)|series bible]]&quot;, as revised for ''TAS'', is held in the science fiction research collection at the [[Samuel Paley Library]], [[Temple University]], [[Philadelphia]].) 

While the freedom of animation afforded large alien landscapes and believable non-humanoid aliens, budget constraints were a major concern and, as was typical of most Filmation productions, the animation quality was generally only fair, with very liberal use of stock shots (as was often the case with many of Filmation's shows). There were also occasional mistakes, such as characters appearing on screen who were elsewhere, or a character supposed to appear on the bridge's main viewing screen, but then appeared in front, indicating bad ordering of animation plates.  These were typically isolated errors however. Occasionally, though, parts of episodes would be animated at a near-theatrical quality level.

==Broadcast history==
Airing on [[NBC]], the series premiered on September 8, 1973 and was broadcast until October 12, 1974, although only twenty-two episodes were produced. The series aired Saturday mornings at 10:30am Eastern/9:30am Central in 1973 and at 11:30am Eastern/10:30am Central the following year.

The series was later shown in reruns on [[Nickelodeon]] in the 1980s and on the [[Syfy|Sci Fi Channel]] in the 1990s as part of [[Cartoon Quest|Sci Fi Cartoon Quest]]. [[CBS Television Distribution]] currently holds rights to the series; it is (as of 2011) currently broadcast on [[CBS Innertube|CBS.com's video archives]] and is not broadcast on any linear channel but is currently available via Netflix streaming (as of November 2011.)

As with all ''[[Star Trek]]'' series, the episodes were subsequently telecast in countries throughout the world, in both [[American English]] and also translated into several different languages.

==Voice casting==
The series featured most of the original cast performing the voices for their characters, except for [[Pavel Chekov]] ([[Walter Koenig]]), who was omitted because the show's budget could not afford the complete cast. He was replaced by two animated characters who made semi-regular appearances: Lieutenant [[Arex (Star Trek)|Arex]], whose Edosian species had three arms and three legs; and Lt. [[M'Ress]], a female [[List of Star Trek races#Caitian|Caitian]]. [[James Doohan]], and [[Majel Barrett]], besides performing their characters [[Montgomery Scott]] and [[Christine Chapel]], performed the voices of Arex and M'Ress, respectively.

Initially, Filmation was only going to use the voices of [[William Shatner]], [[Leonard Nimoy]], [[DeForest Kelley]], [[James Doohan]] and [[Majel Barrett]]. Doohan and Barrett would also perform the voices of Sulu and Uhura. Leonard Nimoy refused to sign up to lend his voice to the series unless [[Nichelle Nichols]] and [[George Takei]] were added to the cast — claiming that [[Hikaru Sulu|Sulu]] and [[Uhura]] were of importance as they were proof of the ethnic diversity of the 23rd century and should not be recast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=To the Stars: The Autobiography of George Takei|author=George Takei|publisher=Pocket Books}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Koenig was not forgotten, and later wrote an episode of the series, becoming the first ''Star Trek'' actor to write a ''Star Trek'' story. Koenig wrote &quot;[[List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes#Season 1 (1973–1974)|The Infinite Vulcan]]&quot;, which had plot elements of the original ''Star Trek'' episode &quot;Space Seed&quot; blended into it.

As is usual for animation, the [[Voice acting|voice actor]]s did not perform together but recorded their parts separately to avoid clashing with other commitments. For instance, [[William Shatner]], who was touring in a [[Play (theatre)|play]] at the time, would record his lines in whatever city he happened to be in and have the tapes shipped to the studio. Doohan and Barrett, besides providing the voices of their ''Original Series'' characters and newcomers Arex and M'Ress, performed virtually all of the &quot;guest star&quot; characters in the series, except for a few notable exceptions such as [[Sarek]], [[Tribble|Cyrano Jones]] and [[List of Star Trek characters#Harry Mudd|Harcourt Fenton Mudd]], who were performed by their original actors from ''The Original Series''. Occasional other guest voice actors were also used, such as [[Ed Bishop]] (Commander Straker on ''[[UFO (TV series)|UFO]]'') who voiced the Megan Prosecutor in &quot;[[The Magicks of Megas-tu]]&quot;, and [[Ted Knight]] who voiced Carter Winston in &quot;[[List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes#Season 1 (1973–1974)|The Survivor]]&quot;. Nichelle Nichols also performed other character voices in addition to Uhura in several episodes, including &quot;[[The Time Trap]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Lorelei Signal]]&quot;.

==Episodes==
{{Main|List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes}}

[[Image:ST-The AS.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The characters of ''TAS''.]]

The 22 episodes of ''TAS'' were spread out over two brief seasons, with copious reruns of each episode. Most were directed by [[Hal Sutherland]].

All the episodes of this series were novelized by [[Alan Dean Foster]] and released in ten volumes under the ''Star Trek Logs'' banner. Initially, Foster adapted three episodes per book, but later editions saw the half-hour scripts expanded into full novel-length stories.

''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' was the only ''Star Trek'' series to not feature a [[cold open]] (&quot;teaser&quot;) and started directly with the title sequence (although some overseas versions of the original live action series, such as that run by the [[BBC]] in the U.K. in the 1960s and 1970s, ran the teaser after the credits).{{clarify|date=January 2010}}

The writing in the series benefited from a [[Writers Guild of America, East]] strike in 1973, which did not apply to animation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Introduction to Star Trek: The Classic Episodes, Volume 1|year=1991|author=D.C. Fontana}}&lt;/ref&gt;  A few episodes are especially notable due to contributions from well-known science fiction authors:

* &quot;[[More Tribbles, More Troubles]]&quot; was written by [[David Gerrold]] as a sequel to his famous episode &quot;[[The Trouble With Tribbles]]&quot; from the original series. Here Cyrano Jones is rescued from the [[Klingon]]s, bringing with him a genetically-altered breed of [[tribble]]s which do not reproduce but do grow extremely large. (It is later discovered that these are really [[Rat king (folklore)|clusters of tribbles who function as a single tribble]], and it is decided that the large numbers of smaller tribbles are preferable to the larger ones.) The Klingons, due to their hatred of tribbles, are eager to get Jones back because he stole a creature they created: a predator called a &quot;glommer&quot; that feeds on tribbles. This episode was originally written with the intention of being an episode of the live-action original series during the third season, but this was vetoed by [[Fred Freiberger]] who wanted serious sci-fi episodes instead, stressing that ''Star Trek'' is not a comedy.{{Citation needed|date=May 2008}}

* &quot;[[Yesteryear (Star Trek: The Animated Series)|Yesteryear]]&quot; is a time-travel episode in which [[Spock|Mr. Spock]] uses &quot;[[Guardian of Forever|The Guardian of Forever]]&quot;, a time gateway from the original series episode &quot;[[The City on the Edge of Forever]]&quot;, to travel to his own childhood past. This is the only animated ''Trek'' episode written by original series and later ''Next Generation'' writer [[D. C. Fontana]]. This was the first actual appearance of Spock's pet [[List of Star Trek animals#Sehlat|sehlat]], first mentioned in &quot;[[Journey to Babel]]&quot; and finally named I-Chaya in this episode. One element from ''Yesteryear'' that has become canon by depiction within ''Star Trek: The Original Series'' is the Vulcan city of ShiKahr, depicted in a background scene wherein Kirk, Spock and McCoy walk across a natural stone bridge (first depicted in ''[[Star Trek III: The Search for Spock]]'') in the [[Star Trek: The Original Series#Star Trek: The Original Series “Remastered”|remastered]] &quot;[[Amok Time]]&quot;.

* [[Larry Niven]]'s &quot;[[The Slaver Weapon]]&quot;, adapted from his own short story &quot;The Soft Weapon&quot;. It includes some elements from his ''[[Known Space]]'' mythos such as the [[Kzin]]ti and the [[Thrint|Slavers]]. This is the only Kirk-era TV or movie story in which Kirk didn't appear. This episode also has the distinction of being the only exception to the animated episodes usually showing nobody dying or being killed onscreen.

* &quot;[[The Magicks of Megas-tu]]&quot;, by [[Larry Brody]], sends the [[Starship Enterprise|''Enterprise'']] to the center of the galaxy. Its crew find themselves befriended by a devil-like alien named Lucien, whom they must defend against accusations that he has brought evil to the world of Megas-tu.

==Influence on later ''Star Trek'' and Filmation series==

[[File:PracticaljokerTAS.jpg|thumb|200px|Scotty faces problems with the food replicator in the episode &quot;The Practical Joker&quot;. This episode featured an early use of the holodeck.]]

The USS ''Enterprise'' in this series, while supposedly the same ship as from the original series, had a [[holodeck]] very similar to the one introduced on ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', which was set approximately eighty years later. It only appeared once, in Chuck Menville's &quot;The Practical Joker&quot;, and was known as the &quot;Rec Room&quot;. This feature was originally proposed for the original series (see, e.g., Gerrold, ''The World of Star Trek'') but was never used.

Filmation later went on to produce the hit ''[[He-Man and the Masters of the Universe]]'' (1983–85), which occasionally used modified character and set designs from ''Star Trek: The Animated Series'', mostly as background material. (''He-Man and the Masters of the Universe'' also had several ''Trek''-similar stories, most notably &quot;The Arena&quot;, which is very similar to ''Star Trek: The Original Series'''s first season episode, &quot;Arena&quot;; regular ''Trek'' writer [[D.C. Fontana]] also penned the second season ''He-Man'' episode &quot;Battlecat&quot;). Later series also shared many of the stock sound effects from both ''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' and ''Star Trek: The Original Series''. Filmation also recycled some of the background music for ''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' in their later shows ''[[Shazam! (TV series)|Shazam!]]'', ''[[Tarzan and the Super 7]]'' and ''Sport Billy''. (Some of the music had already been reused from the previous season's ''[[The Brady Kids]]'' and the ''[[Treasure Island (1972 animated film)|Treasure Island]]'' feature, and were shared with that season's ''[[Lassie's Rescue Rangers]]'').

In addition, a few story and character elements that were introduced in the animated series were incorporated into subsequent live-action productions: 
*[[List of Star Trek characters (G–M)#G|Amanda]]'s maiden name, Grayson.
*A second exit for the bridge, referred to in [[Franz Joseph (artist)|Franz Joseph]]'s ''[[Star Trek Star Fleet Technical Manual|Star Fleet Technical Manual]]'' and seen in the refitted ''Enterprise'' and the [[USS Enterprise (NCC-1701-A)|NCC-1701-A]] from the first six ''Star Trek'' movies.
*The ''kahs-wan'' ritual Spock endures in &quot;Yesteryear&quot;.
*Klingon commander [[Kor (Star Trek)|Kor]]'s command of the battlecruiser ''Klothos''.
*[[Phlox (Star Trek)|Doctor Phlox]] uses Edosian slugs in his medical bay, and Chef once served up Edosian sucker fish, similar to Earth's catfish, as a meal, in the series ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]''. They come from the same planet as Lieutenant Arex, as do Edosian orchids mentioned by [[Elim Garak]] in ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]''.
*The Vulcan city, ShiKahr, has been referred to in multiple series (sometimes misspelled &quot;ShirKahr&quot;), and can be seen in an episode of ''Enterprise''. A Vulcan city which looks very similar to the ShiKahr of ''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' was shown in the new CGI establishing shots used in the special edition of &quot;[[Amok Time]]&quot;.
*Some of the worlds and aliens in the series were included in the 1989 book called ''Star Trek: The Worlds of the Federation''.
*Some of Spock's dialog from [[Yesteryear (Star Trek: The Animated Series)|&quot;Yesteryear&quot;]], and young Spock being bullied by Vulcan classmates, are given homage in the 2009 feature film, ''[[Star Trek (film)|Star Trek]]''.
* Kirk's middle name was revealed in this series as Tiberius, answering the question of what the 'T.' in his name stood for in the original live action series.

==Novelties in the series==
A personal force field technology known as the life support belt was seen only in ''Star Trek: The Animated Series''. In addition to supplying the wearer with the appropriate atmosphere and environmental protection it permitted the animators to simply draw the belt and yellow glow around the existing characters, instead of having to redraw them with an environmental suit. A version of the life support belt later appeared in an early ''Star Trek: The Next Generation'' novel, ''[[The Peacekeepers]]'', where they were referred to as &quot;field-effect suits&quot;.

The episode &quot;[[The Lorelei Signal]]&quot; provides a rare instance in early ''[[Star Trek]]'' in which a female took (temporary) command of a starship. Due to the incapacitation of the male members of the crew, [[Uhura]] assumes command of the ''Enterprise'' from Scotty. Other instances occurred on the very first and very last adventures ever filmed of the original series: 
* &quot;[[The Cage (Star Trek: The Original Series)|The Cage]]&quot;, in which Number One took command after the abduction of Captain Christopher Pike, and
* &quot;[[Turnabout Intruder]]&quot;, in which Dr. Janice Lester took over the body of Captain Kirk and assumed command.

&quot;The Lorelei Signal&quot; and &quot;[[List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes#Season 1 (1973–1974)|The Infinite Vulcan]]&quot;, the latter written by Walter Koenig, are rare occurrences where Captain Kirk comes close to actually saying, &quot;[[Beam me up, Scotty]]&quot; (long erroneously believed to be a ''Star Trek'' [[catchphrase]]), when he commands &quot;Beam us up, Scotty.&quot; ''[[Star Trek IV: The Voyage Home]]'' arguably comes closer to it by having Kirk say &quot;Scotty, beam me up&quot;.

An anti-pollution public service announcement was created for nonprofit [[Keep America Beautiful]] featuring the ''ST:TAS'' characters and original cast voices. In the ad, the Enterprise encounters the &quot;Rhombian Pollution Belt&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;It can be viewed [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vy5M5Xo4wcQ here]&lt;/ref&gt; The ad ran during Saturday morning network programming during the series' run. At least one other PSA was produced for the American Dental Association, featuring Dr. McCoy and Nurse Chapel, but it has yet to resurface.

==Canon issues==
{{main|Star Trek canon}}
At the end of the first season of ''[[Star Trek: The Next Generation]]'', all licenses for [[Star Trek spin-off fiction]] were renegotiated and the animated series was essentially &quot;decanonized&quot; by [[Gene Roddenberry]]'s office. Writers of the novels, comics and role-playing games were prohibited from using concepts from the animated series in their works.&lt;ref name=ayers&gt;{{cite book|author=Ayers, Jeff|title=Voyages of the Imagination: The Star Trek Fiction Companion|publisher=Pocket Books|year=2006|isbn=1416503498}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the facts established within the animated series that were called into question by the &quot;official canon&quot; issue was its identification of [[Robert April]] as the first captain of the USS ''Enterprise'' in the episode &quot;The Counter-Clock Incident&quot;.

The ''[[Timeline of Star Trek|Star Trek Chronology]]'' by production staffers [[Michael Okuda]] and [[Denise Okuda]] does not include the animated series, but does include certain events from &quot;Yesteryear&quot; and acknowledges Robert April as first captain of the ''Enterprise''.&lt;ref name=okuda&gt;{{cite book|last=Okuda|first=Mike|authorlink=Mike Okuda|coauthors=Okuda, Denise|title=Star Trek Chronology: The History of the Future|isbn=0671536109|publisher=Pocket Books|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The timeline in ''Voyages of the Imagination'' dates the events of the series to 2269-2270, assuming the events of the show represented the final part of Kirk's five-year mission, and using revised [[Alan Dean Foster]] stardates. In the updated October 1999 edition of their book: 'The Star Trek Encyclopedia: A Reference Guide to the Future', 
Michael and Denise Okuda state that:
:'In a related vein, this work (ie. book) adheres to Paramount studio policy that regards the animated Star Trek series as not being part of the &quot;official&quot; Star Trek universe, even though we count ourselves among that show's fans. Of course, the final decision as to the &quot;authenticity&quot; of the animated episodes, as with all elements of the show, must clearly be the choice of each individual reader.'&lt;ref&gt;Michael &amp; Denise Okuda, The Star Trek Encyclopedia: A Reference Guide to the Future, Updated and expanded edition, October 1999, Pocket Book (a division of Simon and Shuster), p.iii&lt;/ref&gt;

Since Roddenberry's death in 1991 and the consequent firing of Richard H. Arnold (who vetted the licensed tie-ins for Roddenberry's &quot;Star Trek Office&quot; at Paramount during its later years), there have been several references to the animated series in the various live-action series.  In the ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine]]'' episode &quot;[[Once More Unto the Breach]]&quot;, Kor referred to his ship, the ''Klothos'', which was first named in the ''TAS'' episode &quot;[[List of Star Trek: The Animated Series episodes#Season 1 (1973–1974)|The Time Trap]]&quot;. Other DS9 episodes to make reference to the animated series include &quot;[[Broken Link (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Broken Link]]&quot;, where [[Elim Garak]] mentions Edosian orchids (Arex is an Edosian) and &quot;[[Tears of the Prophets]]&quot; where a [[Miranda class starship]] is called the USS ''ShirKahr'' (sic) after Shikahr, the city from &quot;Yesteryear&quot;. [[David Gerrold]], who contributed two stories to ''TAS'', stated in an interview his views on the canon issue:

{{quotation|Arguments about &quot;canon&quot; are silly. I always felt that ''Star Trek Animated'' was part of ''Star Trek'' because Gene Roddenberry accepted the paycheck for it and put his name on the credits. And DC Fontana—and all the other writers involved—busted their butts to make it the best ''Star Trek'' they could. But this whole business of &quot;canon&quot; really originated with Gene's errand boy. Gene liked giving people titles instead of raises, so the errand boy got named &quot;archivist&quot; and apparently it went to his head. Gene handed him the responsibility of answering all fan questions, silly or otherwise, and he apparently let that go to his head.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.startrekanimated.com/tas_david_gerrold.html The David Gerrold TAS Interview]&lt;/ref&gt;}} 

Writer-producer [[D. C. Fontana]] discussed the ''TAS'' Canon issue in 2007: 

{{quotation|I suppose &quot;canon&quot; means what Gene Roddenberry decided it was. Remember, we were making it up as we went along on the original series (and on the animated one, too). We had a research company to keep us on the straight and narrow as to science, projected science based on known science, science fiction references (we didn’t want to step on anyone’s exclusive ideas in movies, other TV shows, or printed work). They also helped prevent contradictions and common reference errors. So the so-called canon evolved in its own way and its own time. For whatever reason, Gene Roddenberry apparently didn’t take the animated series seriously (no pun intended), although we worked very hard to do original STAR TREK stories and concepts at all times in the animated series.&lt;ref&gt;[http://trekmovie.com/2007/07/22/dc-fontana-on-tas-canon-and-sybok/ DC Fontana and TAS Canon]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

More ''[[Star Trek: Deep Space Nine|DS9]]'' references to the animated series include the episode &quot;[[Prophet Motive]]&quot; where the title of healer is resurrected from &quot;Yesteryear&quot; as well. Vulcan's Forge is also mentioned in &quot;[[Change of Heart (Star Trek: Deep Space Nine)|Change of Heart]]&quot;, in which [[Worf]] wants himself and [[Jadzia Dax]] to honeymoon there, as well as in episodes &quot;[[The Forge (Star Trek: Enterprise)|The Forge]]&quot;, &quot;[[Awakening (Star Trek: Enterprise)|Awakening]]&quot; and &quot;[[Kir'Shara]]&quot; from ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]''.

The ''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]'' episodes &quot;[[The Catwalk]]&quot; and &quot;[[The Forge (Star Trek: Enterprise)|The Forge]]&quot; included references to &quot;[[Yesteryear (Star Trek: The Animated Series)|Yesteryear]]&quot;, the latter featuring a [[Computer-generated imagery|CGI]] rendition of a wild [[List of Star Trek animals#Sehlat|sehlat]]. The remastered Original Series episode &quot;[[Amok Time]]&quot; featured Shikahr in the background as Spock beams up at the episode's end,&lt;ref&gt;http://trekmovie.com/wp-content/uploads/amoktime/new_spock_beamout.jpg&lt;/ref&gt; and the remastered version of &quot;[[The Ultimate Computer]]&quot; replaced the ''Botany Bay''-style ''Woden'' with an automated grain carrier from &quot;[[More Tribbles, More Troubles]].&quot;

Carter Winston, from &quot;[[The Survivor (Star Trek: The Animated Series)|The Survivor]]&quot;, has a small but important role late in the 1984 tie-in novel ''[[The Final Reflection]]'' by [[John M. Ford]].  In recent years, references to ''The Animated Series'' have also cropped up again in the licensed books and comics. [[M'Ress]] and [[Arex]], characters from the animated series, appear in the ''[[Star Trek: New Frontier]]'' novels by [[Peter David]], in which M'Ress and Arex are transported through time to the 24th Century, and are made officers on board the USS ''Trident''. (David's previous use of these characters, in TOS movie-era comics published by [[DC Comics]], had been prevented by Gene Roddenberry's office.&lt;ref&gt;''Star Trek'', Series II issue #1 lettercol, DC Comics, September 1989&lt;/ref&gt;) 

A race introduced in the episode &quot;[[The Jihad]]&quot;, represented by a character named M3 Green, is named the Nasat in the [[Starfleet Corps of Engineers]] [[e-book]] novellas. These stories feature a regular Nasat character, [[Starfleet Corps of Engineers|P8 Blue]]. The Vulcan city of ShiKahr also appears in many books. [[Paula Block]], then of [[CBS Consumer Products]], was responsible for approving proposals and all completed manuscripts for the licensed media tie-ins, and granted many such uses of ''TAS'' material since Roddenberry's passing.

[[Amarillo Design Bureau]] has—as part of its license for the [[Star Fleet Universe]] series of games—incorporated many aspects  of ''The Animated Series'' into its works, not least being the inclusion of the [[Kzin]]ti, although in a modified form. In addition [[FASA]] used elements from ''The Animated Series'' in its sourcebooks and modules for its [[Star Trek role-playing game (FASA)|''Star Trek'' role-playing game]].

''[[Star Trek: Enterprise]]'' producer [[Manny Coto]] has commented that had that show been renewed for a fifth season, the [[Kzin]]ti would have been introduced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory-alpha.org/en/wiki/Star_Trek:_Enterprise#The_Would-Be_Season_5 The Would-Be Season 5]&lt;/ref&gt; Starship designs were produced which closely resemble the Kzinti/[[Kzin|Mirak]] ships from the [[Star Fleet Universe]], a gaming universe that includes the boardgame ''[[Star Fleet Battles]]'' and its [[Personal computer|PC]] analogue ''[[Star Trek: Starfleet Command|Star Fleet Command]]''.

On June 27, 2007, ''Star Trek''&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;s official site incorporated information from ''The Animated Series'' into its library section,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.startrek.com/startrek/view/features/specials/article/66895.html The Animated Series Gets Real]&lt;/ref&gt; although it is unclear here if ''TAS'' is indeed part of Star Trek canon or not.

==Reception==
''Star Trek: The Animated Series'' was named the 96th best animated series by [[IGN]]. They declared that although the series suffered from technical limitations, its format allowed the writers far greater freedom and creativity than was possible in the original live-action series.&lt;ref name=&quot;ign100&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=96, Star Trek: The Animated Series |url=http://tv.ign.com/top-100-animated-tv-series/96.html |publisher=[[IGN]] |accessdate=2009-01-23 |date=2009-01-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ratings===
This was Filmation's only hit series on NBC.  The eight other shows (''[[The Secret Lives of Waldo Kitty]]'', ''Archie/Sabrina Hour'', ''Young (Space) Sentinels'', ''[[Fabulous Funnies]]'', ''Tarzan &amp; The Super 7'', ''Kid Super Power Hour With Shazam'', and ''[[Sport Billy]]'') lasted one season or less. ''[[The New Adventures of Flash Gordon]]'' lasted two seasons.

The animated series was, according to the [[Nielsen ratings]], not popular enough with young children. According to series' producers it was intended to be enjoyed by the entire family. Although the accuracy of the ratings system conducted by the [[ACNielsen]] company has been vehemently disputed by its supporters and detractors since their first implementation, these results have been cited by fans and critics as justification for the show's brief run of only 22 episodes. However, in the 1970s, very few animated series went beyond a few seasons as it was usually more profitable to start a new series. The series did receive critical acclaim and a Daytime [[Emmy Award|Emmy]] award, the first such award for the franchise. According to both Roddenberry and an NBC press release, this was the justification for six additional episodes being ordered by the network for the series' second season.

==Video and DVD releases==
[[Image:tas dvd.jpg|thumb|right|150px|Region 1 DVD Set]]
* The complete series was first released in the USA on eleven volumes of [[VHS]] tapes in 1989. For UK, seven volumes (1x4 episodes and 6x3 episodes on PAL [[VHS]]) from [[CIC Video]] completed the series (Released in 1992 in the UK). Although CIC-Taft Australia negotiated an Australasian release, they did not proceed with their plans.
* A boxed set of the complete series on [[laserdisc]] was released for the US market in 1990, then re-released in 1997.
* A Region 1 (USA) [[Box set|DVD box set]] of the show was released on November 21, 2006, and has since been released internationally for other Regions. It was the last series of Paramount's ''Star Trek'' television franchise to be released to DVD.
* The series was added to Netflix streaming on September 2, 2011. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Star Trek: TAS announced on Netflix Twitter account|url=http://twitter.com/#!/instant_netflix/status/109469397462171649}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Star Trek|Television|Animation}}
*[[List of animated spin-offs from prime time shows]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cbs.com/classics/star_trek_animated/video Star Trek: The Animated Series] - official episode archive
* {{IMDb title|0069637|Star Trek: The Animated Series}}
* {{bcdb|Filmation_Associates/S-Z/Star_Trek|Star Trek: The Animated Series}}
* {{tv.com|2363|Star Trek: The Animated Series}}
* {{memoryalpha article|Star_Trek:_The_Animated_Series|''Star Trek: The Animated Series''}}
* [http://www.startrek.com/page/star-trek-the-animated-series ''Star Trek: The Animated Series''] at StarTrek.com
* [http://www.startrekanimated.com/tas_main.html ''StarTrekAnimated.com'']
* [http://tas.trekcore.com ''Star Trek: The Animated Series''] at TrekCore.com
* [http://www.danhausertrek.com/AnimatedSeries/Main.html ''Guide to the Animated Star Trek''] at danhausertrek.com
* [http://www.ex-astris-scientia.org/tas.htm ''Star Trek: The Animated Series''] at Ex Astris Scientia
* [http://andorfiles.blogspot.com/2009/10/toon-trek.html ''Toon Trek: References to TAS in the Licensed Tie-ins'']
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/03/arts/television/03vinc.html ''Star Trek, the Forgotten Frontier: 1970s Animation''], New York Times DVD review

{{Star Trek navbox}}
{{Star Trek TAS}}
{{Star Trek TOS}}
{{Children's programming on NBC in the 1970s}}

[[Category:Star Trek: The Animated Series| ]]
[[Category:1970s American animated television series]]
[[Category:1973 television series debuts]]
[[Category:1974 television series endings]]
[[Category:NBC network shows]]
[[Category:American science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Star Trek television series]]
[[Category:Television series by Filmation]]
[[Category:Television series by CBS Paramount Television]]
[[Category:Television spin-offs]]
[[Category:Space adventure television series]]

[[bs:Star Trek - The Animated Series]]
[[bg:Стар Трек: Анимационният сериал]]
[[ca:Star Trek (sèrie animada)]]
[[cs:Star Trek (animovaný seriál)]]
[[de:Die Enterprise]]
[[et:Star Trek (animasari)]]
[[es:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[fr:Star Trek : La série animée]]
[[id:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[it:Star Trek (serie animata)]]
[[he:מסע בין כוכבים: סדרת האנימציה]]
[[ro:Star Trek: Seria animată]]
[[nl:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[ja:まんが宇宙大作戦]]
[[pl:Star Trek: Animowana Seria]]
[[pt:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[ru:Звёздный путь: Анимационный сериал]]
[[simple:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[sr:Звездане стазе: Анимирана серија]]
[[sh:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[fi:Star Trek (animaatiosarja)]]
[[sv:Star Trek: The Animated Series]]
[[tr:Uzay Yolu: Animasyon Seri]]
[[uk:Зоряний шлях: Анімаційний серіал]]
[[zh:星艦奇航記動畫版]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
