<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2711325" ns="0" title="Grave Creek Mound"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox nrhp
 | name = Grave Creek Mound
 | nrhp_type = nhl
 | image = Grave Creek Mound.jpg
 | caption = Grave Creek Mound in 2006
 | location = Tomlinson and 9th Streets, [[Moundsville, West Virginia|Moundsville]], [[West Virginia]]
 | coordinates = {{coord|39|55|00.86|N|80|44|40.49|W|region:US-WV_type:landmark|display=inline,title}}
 | area = 
 | architect = 
 | architecture = 
 | built = 
 | designated_nrhp_type= July 19, 1964&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tps.cr.nps.gov/nhl/detail.cfm?ResourceId=561&amp;ResourceType=Structure|title=Grave Creek Mound |accessdate=2007-10-14|work=National Historic Landmark summary listing|publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | added = October 15, 1966&lt;ref name=nrhp&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationalregisterofhistoricplaces.com/WV/Marshall/state.html|title=National Register of Historical Places - West Virginia (WV), Marshall County|date=2007-02-08|work=National Register of Historic Places|publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 | refnum = 66000751&lt;ref name=nrhp/&gt;
 | visitation_num = 
 | visitation_year = 
 | governing_body = State
}}
At {{convert|62|ft|m}} high and {{convert|240|ft|m}} in diameter, the '''Grave Creek Mound''' is one of the largest conical type burial mounds in the [[United States]]. The builders of the site moved more than 60,000 tons of dirt to create it. It is located in [[Moundsville, West Virginia|Moundsville]], [[West Virginia]] near the banks of the Ohio River. The first recorded excavation of the mound took place in 1838, and was conducted by local amateurs. To gain entrance to the mound, two shafts, one vertical and one horizontal were created. This led to the most significant discovery of two burial vaults. This mound along with many others, e.g. the [[Criel Mound]], was the product of the [[Adena culture]]. It is actually the largest mound amongst the mounds built by the Adena.

==Description==
Grave Creek Mound is the largest ass type of any of the [[mound builder (people)|mound builder]] structures. Construction of the mound took place in successive stages from about 250-150 B.C., as indicated by the multiple burials at different levels within the structures. In 1838, road engineers measured its height at {{convert|69|ft|m}} and its at the base as {{convert|295|ft|m}}. Originally a moat of about {{convert|40|ft|m}} in width and five feet in depth with one causeway encircled it. Inside the mound, Adena Hopewell remains and ornaments were discovered, along with a small sandstone tablet. The authenticity of this tablet and the meaning of its inscription have become quite controversial.

==History==
Grave Creek mound was created during the Woodland time period (late Adena Period around 1000 B.C. to about 1 A.D.) The people that lived in West Virginia during this time have been coined the term Mound Builders. This particular mound was built in successive stages over a period of a hundred years. Maybe due to the massive amount of work it took to create these mounds. 
The Grave Creek Mound was believed probably first discovered by Joseph Tomlinson between 1770, when he and his brother built a log cabin at Grave Creek Flats, and 1772 when he built a cabin {{convert|300|ft|m}} from the mound for his family.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Observations respecting the Grave Creek Mound&quot; by Henry R Schoolcraft, ''Transactions of the American Ethnological Society'' Vol. 1, 1843 p.278&lt;/ref&gt; There was also a recording on a tree located on the site, a carving in the tree was dated 1734.  This was a full 33 years before [[Lewis and Clark Expedition|Lewis &amp; Clark]] wrote about the mound in their journals during their expedition after the [[Louisiana Purchase]].&lt;ref&gt;The Journals of the Lewis &amp; Clark Expedition By Meriwether Lewis, William Clark, Thomas W. Dunlay,  Gary E. Moulton p.77&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lewis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://libxml1a.unl.edu/lewisandclark/read/?_xmlsrc=1803-09-10&amp;_xslsrc=LCstyles.xsl|author=Lewis, Meriwether|date=September 10, 1803|accessdate=2009-05-06|title=The Journals of the Lewis and Clark Expedition|quote=This remarkable mound of earth stands on the east bank of the Ohio 12 miles below Wheeling and about 700 paces from the river, as the land is not cleard the mound is not visible from the river—this mound gives name to two small creeks called little and big grave creek|authorlink=Meriwether Lewis}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Tomlinson discovered the mound while hunting and later he and Briggs gutted the mound destroying much of the archaeological evidence. They found extensive amounts of jewelry.
It was saved from demolition in 1908 by the Wheeling Chapter of the [[Daughters of the American Revolution]] who were able to raise enough funds to acquire an option on the property, and in 1909 the state of West Virginia purchased the site.&lt;ref&gt;Schramm, Robert W, ''Moundsville'' Arcadia Publishing, Moundsville (W. Va.) 2004&lt;/ref&gt; It was declared a [[National Historic Landmark]] in 1964.&lt;ref name=&quot;nhlsum&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv2&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Text/66000751.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory-Nomination: Grave Creek Mound|date=October 15, 1985 |author=Denise L. Grantz |publisher=National Park Service|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}} and {{PDFlink|[http://pdfhost.focus.nps.gov/docs/NHLS/Photos/66000751.pdf Accompanying 1 photo, aerial view, from 1967.]|780&amp;nbsp;KB}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nrhpinv1&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|url=http://www.wvculture.org/shpo/nr/pdf/marshall/66000751.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory-Nomination: Grave Creek Mound (Accessed via West Virginia Department of Culture and History|date=October 15, 1985 |author=Denise L. Grantz |publisher=National Park Service|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Delf Norona Museum==
  The Delf Norona Museum displays many artifacts found at the site, 
and is operated by the West Virginia Division of Culture and History. 
 Opened in 1978, the museum's exhibits focus on the culture of the 
[[Adena culture|Adena]] people and theories about the mound's construction. 
 The museum is open year round and admission is free. There is also a
 gift shop inside the Museum containing trinkets and other souvenirs. 
 Nearly 450,000 artifacts excavated by the U.S. Army Corps
 of Engineers were turned over to the 
museum for archival. The artifacts were mostly 
uncovered at the Marment 
Lock site and include stone projectile knives, 
sandstone cooking bowls, and stone jewelry from a Fort Ancient village.[http://sundaygazettemail.com/News/201009220672 1]

==See also==
*[[Criel Mound]]
*[[Grave Creek Stone]]
*[[List of National Historic Landmarks by state|List of National Historic Landmarks]]
*[[List of Registered Historic Places in West Virginia]]
*[[List of burial mounds in the United States]]
*[[Prehistory of West Virginia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.wvculture.org/sites/gravecreek.html Grave Creek Mound Archaeology Complex]
* [http://publications.ohiohistory.org/ohstemplate.cfm?action=detail&amp;Page=0107125.html&amp;StartPage=125&amp;EndPage=170&amp;volume=107&amp;notes=&amp;newtitle=Volume%20107%20Page%20125 &quot;In search of the Mound-Builders&quot; by Terry A. Barnhart, '''Ohio History, the Scholarly Journal of the Ohio Historical Society''', Vol 107]
*[http://www.econ.ohio-state.edu/jhm/arch/grvcrk.html]
{{Adena culture}}
{{Northern Panhandle of West Virginia}}
{{National Register of Historic Places in West Virginia}}

&lt;br /&gt;
[[Category:Adena culture]]
[[Category:Mounds of West Virginia]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites in West Virginia]]
[[Category:National Historic Landmarks in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Archaeology museums in the United States]]
[[Category:Native American museums in West Virginia]]
[[Category:Museums in Marshall County, West Virginia]]
[[Category:Protected areas of Marshall County, West Virginia]]
[[Category:Archaeological sites on the National Register of Historic Places in West Virginia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
