<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27142140" ns="0" title="The Annoying Orange"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Multiple issues |confusing=July 2011|copyedit=July2011 |tone = July 2011}}&lt;!-- this tag is supposed to be here and *STAY HERE* unless the problems are fixed --&gt;
{{Infobox television
 |bgcolour             = #FFFFFF
 |show_name            = The Annoying Orange
 |image                = [[File:Annoying-orange-logo.png|250px]]
 |caption              = The Annoying Orange current logo
 |genre                = [[Comedy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Joke]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Humour]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Suspense]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pun]]
 |runtime              = Less than 1 minute minimum to about 6 minutes maximum
 |creator              = Dane Boedigheimer
 |director             = Robert Jennings&lt;br /&gt;Kevin Brueck
 |writer               = Spencer Grove&lt;br /&gt;Dane Boedigheimer&lt;br /&gt;Robert Jennings
 |composer             = Dane Boedigheimer&lt;br /&gt;The Convictions&lt;br /&gt;Emma Kenny&lt;br /&gt;Event Banditt&lt;br /&gt;Kevin McLeod
| producer             = Kevin Brueck
| executive_producer   = Aaron Massey&lt;br&gt;Kevin Nalty
| supervising_producer = Robert Jennings
| language             = [[English Language|English]]
| country              = [[California]], [[United States]]
| company              = Gagfilms&lt;br /&gt;Roman-5 Studios&lt;br /&gt;10th Cross Entertainment&lt;br /&gt;Wicked Awesome Films
| distributor          = [[Google]]
| network              = [[YouTube]]
| first_aired          = October 9, 2009–present
| num_seasons          = 4
| num_episodes         = 112
| list_episodes        = List of The Annoying Orange episodes
| website              = http://www.annoyingorange.com
| voices               = Dane &quot;Daneboe&quot; Boedigheimer&lt;br/&gt;Robert &quot;Bobjenz&quot; Jennings&lt;br/&gt;Kevin Brueck&lt;br/&gt;Aaron Massey&lt;br/&gt;[[Justine Ezarik|Justine &quot;iJustine&quot; Ezarik]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kevin Nalty|Kevin &quot;Nalts&quot; Nalty]]&lt;br /&gt;Various guest stars
}}

'''The Annoying Orange''' is a comedy [[web series]] created by Dane Boedigheimer. The first episode of the series was uploaded on October 9, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=
http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703404004575198410669579950.html?mod=WSJ_hpp_sections_tech#articleTabs%3Darticle | title= Now Playing on a Computer Near You: A Fruit With an Obnoxious Streak  | author= Geoffrey A. Fowler | publisher=The Wall Street Journal | date= April 26, 2010 | accessdate=April 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://edition.cnn.com/2010/TECH/web/06/25/annoying.orange.taking.over/?fbid=BGdt6Q0BIQx | title= How 'Annoying Orange' is taking over the world | author= Brown, Damon | publisher=CNN | date= June 28, 2010 | accessdate=June 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first few episodes were uploaded to Boedigheimer's YouTube channel under the name ''Daneboe'', each getting more than ten million views. Following the success of the series, he created a channel dedicated to The Annoying Orange on January 11, 2010.

As of June 2011, the channel is ranked as the eighth most subscribed and 30th most viewed, with more than 2,000,000 subscribers. &lt;ref name = &quot;realannoyingorange Channel&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/user/realannoyingorange Channel of realannoyingorange]. YouTube (2010-12-17). Retrieved on 2010-12-22.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Channels&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/channels?p=1&amp;s=ms&amp;gl=&amp;t=a&amp;g=0 Channels]. YouTube. Retrieved on 2010-12-22.&lt;/ref&gt; It has been confirmed that an ''Annoying Orange'' [[television series]] is currently under production.&lt;ref name=&quot;tv&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.deadline.com/2011/04/hit-youtube-series-the-annoying-orange-to-become-animated-tv-show/#utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=Feed:+mediaredef+%28jason+hirschhorn%27s+Media+ReDEFined%29 | title= Hit YouTube Series 'The Annoying Orange' To Become Animated TV Show | author= Nellie Andreeva | publisher=[[Deadline.com]] | date= April 13, 2011 | accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been picked up by [[Cartoon Network]] and will premiere in 2012.

==Plot==
The series is centered on an [[anthropomorphic]] orange named The Annoying Orange, (often simply referred to as  &quot;orange&quot;) voiced by Dane Boedigheimer. Boedigheimer's partner, Spencer Grove, writes the plot of the majority of the episodes.

Orange resides on a kitchen counter, which he shares with his best friend Pear, a [[Williams pear|Bartlett pear]], also voiced by Boedigheimer. Other fruits on the counter include Passion, a female [[passionfruit]] played by [[Justine Ezarik]], Grapefruit, the &quot;tough&quot; guy in the kitchen, a tiny apple known to everyone as Midget Apple, a small marshmallow called Marshmallow, and an elderly lemon called Grandpa Lemon. Most episodes consist of Orange heckling other characters, the latter of which  often become annoyed and meet a sudden and gruesome end, usually by [[evisceration]] with a [[chef's knife]] (although the implements used to cut them up range from a [[blender]] to a toy [[pinwheel]]). Comically, Orange tries to warn them about it before it happens, by blurting out the weapon-in-use, such as &quot;Knife!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot; /&gt;

Orange has several recurring mannerisms. He often begins an episode by stating &quot;Hey, (name of character)!&quot; until they get frustrated enough to respond, and often refers to said character as a play on the object's name or appearance. He uses various tactics annoys people, usually by telling rude and offensive jokes, burping, and making childish noises with his tongue. Orange has a braying laugh as annoying as his voice, and he often tells the objects he annoys, &quot;You're an apple!&quot; if he does not like them.

==Production==
To animate the characters, Boedigheimer superimposes the voice actor's eyes and mouth onto the object they are playing. For instance, Boedigheimer uses his own eyes and mouth to play both Orange and Pear (although Orange's mouth has been slightly modified, so that it has a distinctive orange tint to it, while the color of Pear's mouth is unadjusted) and does the same for all guest actors who voice the animated characters.&lt;ref name = &quot;Daneboe Exposed 5&quot;&gt;{{cite video | url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aGETqrLGm7Y | title=Daneboe Exposed #5: Annoying Orange Exposed | publisher=[[Youtube]] | date=March 8, 2011 | people=Dane Boedigheimer}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the pilot episodes, Dane Boedigheimer played the annoying orange and all the fruits and vegetables, but this has since changed to include at least one guest actor/YouTuber in each episode. These have included Robert Jennings/bobjenz who played Grapefruit, Ginger, and Liam the Leprechaun (which spun off into his own series – see below), [[Justine Ezarik]]/iJustine (which led to her becoming a recurring cast member), [[Lucas Cruikshank]], [[Take180]]'s Evan Ferrante, and [[Weezer]]. Two crossovers were created as the result of guest appearances. In June 24, 2010 Boedigheimer guest-starred as Orange in Lucas Cruikshank's ''[[Fred Figglehorn|Fred]] Goes Grocery Shopping!'' Cruikshank soon returned the favor by playing Fred Figglehorn in the episode ''Annoying Orange vs. FRED!!!'''. In August 20, 2010, Ferrante appeared as the leader of a race of broccoli aliens in the episode ''Close Encounters of the Annoying Kind'' one day after Boedigheimer appeared in Ferrante's Take180 series &quot;Not Tom Cruise&quot; as Orange. Three of Weezer's members appeared as objects on a party platter in ''Wazzup 3: Bonsai Tree'', with lead singer [[Rivers Cuomo]] appearing as the title object. The appearance was part of Weezer's promotion of their album ''[[Hurley (album)|Hurley]]'', where they took to several YouTube channels including daneboe and Fred to promote the record. In December 17, 2010, in honor of his website [[Openfilm]], actor [[James Caan]] appeared as a [[jalapeño pepper]] in ''Jalapeño''.

==Characters==
[[Image:Annoying_Orange_Characters.png|left|thumb|From left to right: Midget Apple, Pear, Annoying Orange, Grapefruit, Passion Fruit, Marshmallow and Lemon.]]
Boedigheimer provides the voices of the main characters Orange, Pear, Midget Apple, and Marshmallow. The voice of Passion Fruit is provided by [[Justine Ezarik]], while Robert Jennings voices Grapefruit and Liam the Leprechaun. Kevin Brueck provides the role of Grandpa Lemon. The character &quot;Knife&quot; is voiced by [[Kevin Nalty]]. Other celebrities and internet personalities have provided guest voices, and a contest was launched in ''Be a star!'' that led to the awarding of a cameo role. The winner of the contest was Mark Boyanowski, who performed on June 9, 2011.

===Main Characters===
====Orange====
'''Orange''' is the lead protagonist and main character of the series, appearing in every episode since the series began on October 9, 2009. He has yellow teeth, grey eyes, and a braying laugh. His standard reply, uttered after being taken to task for being so annoying, is &quot;No, I'm not. I'm an orange!&quot;. Boedigheimer describes the character as a composite of people in his life, saying &quot;Everyone knows somebody like him: They don't listen, they are annoying, and at the same time they are kind of lovable&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot;/&gt;

====Pear====
'''Pear''' makes his initial (albeit brief) appearance in the pilot episode, before becoming a regular character from ''Passion of the Fruit'' onwards. He is a [[Williams pear|Bartlett pear]] who inhabits the same [[kitchen]] counter as Orange, his best friend. Despite their friendship, he is often annoyed by Orange, to the point where he initially wants to die, although subtly warming up to Orange's antics afterwards. He is a very kind character who tries to help others maintain control, and is depicted as being more intelligent than Orange.

====Passion Fruit====
'''Passion Fruit''' (voiced by YouTube vlogger [[Justine Ezarik|iJustine]]), or simply &quot;Passion&quot;, first appeared on February 19, 2010 in ''Passion of the Fruit''. Passion is offended by frequent insults and will try to settle issues to stop Orange from being annoying and scolds the other characters. Orange has a crush on her, much to the unbeknownst of Passion. Passion has a twin sister named Mandy, noticed in ''Wishful Thinking'', who is in love with Pear.

====Midget Apple====
'''Midget Apple''' is first seen in the episode ''Crabapple''. Also voiced by Dane Boedigheimer, he is a tiny [[Red Delicious]] [[apple]]. A friend of Orange, Pear, Passion, and especially Marshmallow, he dislikes being called &quot;Midget Apple&quot;, preferring the term &quot;''Little'' Apple&quot;.

====Marshmallow====
'''Marshmallow''' debuted in the episode ''Annoying Saw 2: The Annoying Death Trap'' on September 24, 2010. He is a small, childlike, squeaky-voiced marshmallow that Orange befriends in the former's very first episode. Marshmallow is typically presented as cheerful and happy, and claims to love &quot;puppies, and unicorns, and bunnies, and rainbows, and clouds, and kittens, and bunnies, and rainbows&quot;. The character is shown to absorb significant damage to his body, such as from cuts, fire, and [[Shuriken|throwing stars]], and emerge largely unscathed. Marshmallow can also sneeze glitter and will explode if he is sufficiently angered. He is also part unicorn as confirmed in the episode ''Mommy and Me''. Marshmallow's gender is never revealed.

===Recurring characters===
====Grapefruit====
'''Grapefruit''', voiced by Robert Jennings, first appears in ''Passion of the Fruit'' as Orange's archenemy. He often engages in juvenile insults with Orange. The character is killed by Knife in his debut, but became a recurring character after returning as part of the Frankenfruit monster in ''Frankenfruit''.

====Grandpa Lemon====
'''Grandpa Lemon''', played by Kevin Brueck, is an elderly [[lemon]] who is forgetful and has a habit of falling asleep. First appearing in ''Grandpa Lemon'' on June 4, 2010, he is unfazed by Orange's taunts due to his memory loss and sleeping habit. Sliced in half by Knife in his debut, he becomes part of the Frankenfruit monster in ''Frankenfruit'', only for the former to fall apart, resurrecting him in his previous state.

====Knife====
'''Knife''', voiced by [[Kevin Nalty]], is initially introduced simply as a kitchen tool in ''The Annoying Orange''. He appears when Orange announces his presence, proceeding to slice up the other fruits and vegetables. His first appearance as a character is in ''No More Mr. Knife Guy''. Knife is shown to be at odds with his role in the series, hating his life because of how he is used. His mortal enemy is a knife sharpener due to the pain involved. 

====Liam the Leprechaun====
'''Liam the Leprechaun''', played by Robert Jennings, first appears in ''Luck o' the Irish'' on March 12, 2010 as a bad-tempered [[leprechaun]], who loses his pot of gold to Orange. Crushed by his pot of gold at the end of the episode, Liam has returned in several episodes and is also the title character of a spin-off series on his own [[YouTube]] channel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.youtube.com/user/leprechaun | title=&quot;leprechaun&quot; Youtube Channel. | publisher=[[Youtube]] | accessdate=November 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Episodes==
{{main|List of The Annoying Orange episodes}}
New episodes of ''The Annoying Orange'' are released on a weekly basis, with a few exceptions. The episodes are released every Friday afternoon on realannoyingorange's YouTube channel. Episodes are characterized by Orange's taunting and annoying his victims-to-be with his adolescent behavior that includes burping, pestering, puns, and plays on words.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot;/&gt; These actions often infuriate the other character to the point where they start yelling at him to shut up. This results in Orange warning them of their impending doom: evisceration with a chef's knife, a blender or other kitchen devices.&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot;/&gt;

==Reception==
On August 13, 2010, one million people subscribed to The Annoying Orange. The series was rated as the most viewed web series of February and March 2010 by [[Mashable]], with over 52 million views in March.&lt;ref name=&quot;feb-mash&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://mashable.com/2010/03/05/top-10-web-series-february/ | title= The Top 10 Most Watched Web Series, February 2010  | author= Samuel Axon | publisher=[[Mashable]] | date= March 5, 2010 | accessdate=April 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mar-mash&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://mashable.com/2010/04/08/top-10-web-series-march/ | title= The Top 10 Most Watched Web Series, March 2010  | author= Samuel Axon | publisher=[[Mashable]] | date= April 8, 2010 | accessdate=April 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On April 26, 2010, the series had over 108 million views on [[YouTube]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wsj-orange&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;oz1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.news.com.au/technology/annoying-orange-a-certified-youtube-citrus-smash-for-dane-boedigheimer/story-e6frfro0-1225858639419 | title= Annoying Orange a certified YouTube citrus smash for Dane Boedigheimer  | author= | publisher=[[News Limited]] | date= April 27, 2010 | accessdate=April 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;vv1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url= http://blogs.villagevoice.com/forkintheroad/archives/2010/04/annoying_orange.php | title= Annoying Orange Seeks to Irritate a Wider Audience via Television | author= Chantal Martineau | publisher=[[The Village Voice]] | date= April 26, 2010 | accessdate=April 28, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As of June 2011, the channel is ranked as the eighth most subscribed and 30th most viewed, with more than 2,000,000 subscribers.&lt;ref name = &quot;realannoyingorange Channel&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Channels&quot;/&gt; Despite being the most popular web show on [[youtube]], it received poor reviews. Liz Shannon Miller stated the show to be &quot;annoying for many reasons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://gigaom.com/video/no-1-web-series-annoying-orange-is-annoying-for-many-reasons/ | title=No. 1 Web Series ''Annoying Orange'' is Annoying for Many Reasons | publisher=Online Video News | date=May 10, 2010 3:40 | accessdate=November 25, 2011 | author=Shannon Miller, Liz}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the web series column ''Pass the Mustard'', Ned Hepburn called the show &quot;pure, pure unfunny highly concentrated, in droplet form, just purely nonsensical riffing from an Annoying Orange.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://news.tubefilter.tv/2010/03/10/annoying-orange-wiener-the-basement-copy-pastry-try-to-pass-the-mustard/ | title=‘Annoying Orange’, ‘Wiener’, ‘The Basement’, ‘Copy &amp; Pastry’ Try to Pass The Mustard | publisher=Tubefilter News | date=March 10, 2010 | accessdate=November 25, 2011 | author=Hepburn, Ned}}&lt;/ref&gt; while 411mania.com said the show was &quot;idiotic&quot; and &quot;creepy as hell&quot;.&lt;ref name = &quot;411mania&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.411mania.com/movies/columns/211594/Movies-TV%5C%5Cs-3Rs-11.22.11:-Dark-Knight-Rises,-The-Amazing-Spider-Man,-Twilight,-Ricky-Gervais,-More.htm | title=Movies/TV's 3R’s 11.22.11: Dark Knight Rises, The Amazing Spider-Man, Twilight, Ricky Gervais, More | publisher=411mania.com | date=November 22, 2011 | accessdate=November 27, 2011 | author=Diaz, Porfirio}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Give Away==
On November 10, 2011 GeekDad announced to began a give away for Annoying Orange prizes. People had to fill a form to win one of three prize packages, including an Annoying Orange t-shirt from [[JCPenney]] and  a toy from [[Toys R Us]]. GeekDad started taking entries through Friday at 11:59 PM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.wired.com/geekdad/2011/11/annoying-orange/ | title=Hey! Hey! It’s Annoying Orange — Exclusive Preview &amp; Giveaway! | publisher=[[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] | date=November 10, 2011 | accessdate=November 27, 2011 | author=Cranford Teague, Jason}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Games==
{{main article|Annoying Orange: Kitchen Carnage}}
[[File:Annoying Orange Kicthen Carange icon 175x175.png|right]]
A video game named ''Kitchen Carnage'' was released for the [[iPod Touch]] and [[iPhone]] on April 7, 2011. The game was later released in [[HD]] for the [[iPad]] on May 6, 2011&lt;ref&gt;[http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/annoying-orange-kitchen-carnage/id410333317?mt=8 Annoying Orange: Kitchen Carnage for iPhone, iPod Touch, and iPad on the iTunes Store]&lt;/ref&gt; and for [[Android (operating system)|Android]] devices on October 14, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.amazon.com/dp/B005UOK2KY Annoying Orange: Kitchen Carnage: Appstore for Android]&lt;/ref&gt; Players throw various produce items across the kitchen at a series of blenders and other kitchen utensils. The game was developed by Bottle Rocket Apps.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bottlerocketapps.com/apps/annoying-orange Bottle Rocket Apps]&lt;/ref&gt;

==TV series==
Boedigheimer has confirmed that he and production companies ''Gagfilms'' and ''The Collective'' have started producing six episodes for a weekly ''Annoying Orange'' television spin-off. The series' executive producers are Dane Boedigheimer, [[Conrad Vernon]] and Tom Shepherd; the co-executive producers are Spencer Grove, Robert Jennings and Kevin Brueck.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://onlinejournal.com/artman/publish/article_8368.shtml | title=&quot;Annoying Orange&quot; Web Series is Coming to TV | publisher=[[Online Journal]] | date=April 14, 2011 | accessdate=November 19, 2011 | author=Stacy, Greg}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pilot is currently being written by Dane Boedigheimer, Spencer Grove and [[Tom Shepherd]].&lt;ref name = &quot;New York Times 1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/03/business/media/annoying-orange-tries-for-a-tv-career.html?_r=4&amp;pagewanted=1 | title='Annoying Orange' Tries for a TV Carrer | publisher=[[The New York Times]] | date=October 2, 2011 | accessdate=November 25, 2011 | author=Barnes, Brooks}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;tv&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.beet.tv/2011/11/the-collective-lands-the-annoying-orange-cable-deal-.html | title=The Collective Lands the &quot;Annoying Orange&quot; Cable Deal | publisher=Beet.TV | date=November 18, 2011 | accessdate=November 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Boedigheimer, the show contains the main characters as in the Internet series, but it takes place on a fruit-vending cart rather than in the kitchen as it was in the YouTube series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://mashable.com/2011/04/15/annoying-orange-tv/ | title= Popular YouTube Series Annoying Orange Moves to TV | author= Brenna Ehrlich | publisher=[[Mashable]] | date= April 15, 2011 | accessdate=May 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The deal has been picked up and signed by [[Cartoon Network]] and will premiere in 2012.&lt;ref name = &quot;411mania&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/showtracker/2011/11/the-annoying-orange-rolls-to-cartoon-network.html | title='The Annoying Orange' rolls to Cartoon Network | publisher=[[The Los Angeles Times]] | date=November 17, 2011 | accessdate=November 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://mediadecoder.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/18/annoying-orange-parlays-youtube-success-into-a-tv-series/ | title=Annoying Orange’ Parlays YouTube Success Into a TV Series | publisher=[[The New York Times]] | date=November 18, 2011 | accessdate=November 18, 2011 | author=Branes, Brooks}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bakersfield.com/blogs/bakosphere/x986930791/Cartoon-Network-signs-Annoying-Orange | title=Cartoon Network signs &quot;Annoying Orange&quot; | publisher=[[Bakosphere]] | date=November 22, 2011 1:01 PM | accessdate=November 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;New ‘Expendables 2′ Poster, Star Wars Supercut, &amp; The Annoying Orange Are All On The Radar&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://theflickcast.com/2011/11/19/new-expendables-2-poster-star-wars-supercut-the-annoying-orange-are-all-on-the-radar/ | title=New ‘Expendables 2′ Poster, Star Wars Supercut, &amp; The Annoying Orange Are All On The Radar | publisher=The Flickcast | date=November 19, 2011 | accessdate=November 25, 2011 | author=Raub, Matt}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | url=http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/video/citrus-superstar-annoying-orange-14859567 | title=A Citrus Superstar: The Annoying Orange | publisher=[[ABC News]] Video | date=November 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://television.cosmicbooknews.com/content/annoying-orange-half-hour-television-series-comes-cartoon-network-2012 | title=Annoying Orange Half-Hour Television Series Comes To Cartoon Network in 2012 | publisher=[[Comic Book News]] | date=November 17, 2011 | accessdate=November 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.annoyingorange.com/ The Annoying Orange official website]
*[http://www.youtube.com/profile?user=realannoyingorange The Annoying Orange official YouTube channel]

{{S-start}}
{{s-ach|ach}}
{{s-bef|before=[[MysteryGuitarMan]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=Most Subscribed Channel on YouTube|years=Ranked 8th as of April 2011}}
{{s-aft|after=[[collegehumor]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Annoying Orange, The}}
[[Category:Web series]]
[[Category:Internet memes]]
[[Category:YouTube videos]]
[[Category:Viral videos]]

[[ar:أنوينغ أورنج]]
[[bg:Досадният портокал]]
[[es:The Annoying Orange]]
[[fr:The Annoying Orange]]
[[ko:어노잉 오렌지]]
[[it:The Annoying Orange]]
[[he:The Annoying Orange]]
[[lv:Kaitinošais Apelsīns]]
[[hu:The Annoying Orange]]
[[nl:The Annoying Orange]]
[[ja:アノーイング・オレンジ]]
[[pl:Annoying Orange]]
[[pt:The Annoying Orange]]
[[ru:Надоедливый апельсин]]
[[simple:The Annoying Orange]]
[[fi:The Annoying Orange]]
[[tl:The Annoying Orange]]
[[zh-yue:煩橙頭]]
[[zh:柳丁擱來亂]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
