<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27154720" ns="0" title="Silent Show"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox television
| show_name            = Silent Show
| image                = [[Image:Ernie kovacs 1956.JPG|200px|alt=Ernie Kovacs on the set]]
| caption              = Ernie Kovacs on the set of his television show-1956.
| show_name_2          = Eugene,&lt;br&gt;Saturday Color Carnival:&lt;br&gt;The Ernie Kovacs show&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.paleycenter.org/collection/item/?q=ernie+kovacs&amp;f=all&amp;c=all&amp;advanced=1&amp;p=1&amp;item=T81:0132|title=Saturday Color Carnival: The Ernie Kovacs Show|publisher=Paley Center for Media|accessdate=12 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| genre                = Comedy
| format               = 
| creator              = Ernie Kovacs
| developer            = 
| writer               = Ernie Kovacs
| director             = 
| creative_director    = 
| presenter            = 
| starring             = Ernie Kovacs
| judges               = 
| voices               = 
| narrated             = 
| theme_music_composer = 
| opentheme            = 
| endtheme             = 
| composer             = 
| country              = United States
| language             = English
| num_seasons          = 
| num_episodes         = 1 episode
| list_episodes        = 
| executive_producer   = 
| producer             = 
| editor               = 
| location             = 
| cinematography       = 
| camera               = 
| runtime              = 30 minutes
| company              = 
| distributor          = 
| channel              = NBC
| picture_format       = 
| audio_format         = 
| first_run            = 
| first_aired          = January 19, 1957
| last_aired           = 
| status               = 
| preceded_by          = 
| followed_by          = 
| related              = 
| website              = 
| production_website   = 
}}
''Silent Show'' was a half-hour television comedy special created by, and starring, [[Ernie Kovacs]].  It was broadcast in the United States on the [[NBC]] network in 1957, and on the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] network in 1961. It was selected by the United States as the only television program screened at the [[Expo 58|1958 Worlds Fair]] in [[Brussels]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TV&quot;/&gt;

== Background ==
In 1956, NBC, wanting to present to the public an example of the new technology of color television, hired Ernie Kovacs to write and star in one of the first color television shows to be broadcast.  Although NBC was more interested in the &quot;visual splendor&quot; of what would be shown, Ernie Kovacs went one step further and, aside from his opening monologue and the Dutch Masters cigar commercials, decided to banish all human conversation from the show.&lt;ref name=&quot;TV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Crosby&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=ugUdAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=14oEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7113,2850782&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs+eugene&amp;hl=en|title=Radio &amp; TV|author=Crosby, John|date=24 January 1957|publisher=Sarasota Journal|accessdate=12 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=OBrian&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=DxxSAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=N3YDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7240,3165591&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs&amp;hl=en|title=Lewis Show Didn't Get Off Ground|author=O'Brian, Jack|date=22 January 1957|publisher=St. Petersburg Times|accessdate=14 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NBC had another reason for this special: a hole in its lineup for a particular Friday night.  After [[Jerry Lewis]] broke up his longtime partnership with [[Dean Martin]], NBC had offered Lewis the opportunity to host his own ninety-minute color TV special 9:30&amp;ndash;11 PM (EST) on Friday January 19, 1957.  Lewis decided to use only the first sixty minutes, leaving the network thirty minutes to fill.  No one could be found to take over a time slot following the solo television premiere of a comedy superstar, other than Kovacs, who was more than willing to try something new.&lt;ref name=&quot;MusTV&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=OBrian/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20060208071526/http://users.rcn.com/manaben/Klifemag.html Ben Model, &quot;Ernie's Life Magazine cover,&quot; Silent Clowns Film Series]&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview prior to the show's airing, Kovacs described his work as &quot;radio in reverse&quot;, saying that radio provided dialogue, leaving listeners to use imagination to fill in the visual details.  In presenting a silent half-hour with Eugene, he supplied the pictures and left the dialogue up to the viewer's imagination.&lt;ref name=Crosby/&gt;

Kovacs began the show with this:&lt;ref name=&quot;TV&quot;&gt;{{Citation|editor-last=Spigel|editor-first=Lynn|title=TV by design: modern art and the rise of network television|year=2009|publisher=University of Chicago Press|pages=409|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=q_dekIDkPtMC&amp;pg=PA178&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=T-U4TKC0Bc39nQfHl5mGBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=ernie%20kovacs&amp;f=false|isbn=0226769682|accessdate=17 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;There's a great deal of conversation that takes place on television. From way in the morning 6 AM...to all hours of the night.  I thought perhaps...you might like to spend a half hour without hearing any dialogue at all.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The NBC version aired live; a rare color kinescope survives and is included on the DVD box set, &quot;The Ernie Kovacs Collection.&quot;  A second version of the show was created on B&amp;W videotape and broadcast November 10, 1961, on the ABC network.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ki&quot;&gt;[http://kinescopehd.blogspot.com/2010/02/portrait-of-genius-in-black-white.html   Portrait of a Genius in Black &amp; White] posting on the Kinescope HD website&lt;/ref&gt;  An excerpt of the color show was aired as part of the NBC 50th Anniversary Special in 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0301644/|title=NBC 50th Anniversary|year=1976|publisher=Internet Movie Database|accessdate=18 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Comment [[NBC]]-founded in 1926--&gt;

When Kovacs outlined his plan for a 30 minute silent broadcast to NBC, the network's reaction was one of disbelief.  During rehearsals for the program, network executives made disparaging remarks.  Kovacs became angry and walked out, telling them to show a western film they had in reserve instead; he was then able to proceed as he wanted. Kovacs' wife, [[Edie Adams]], recalled that this experience was the reason Ernie wrote the novel ''Zoomar''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=kG4pAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=lswEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=881,2773436&amp;dq=edie+adams+silent&amp;hl=en|title=Edie Adams Laments Decline of Satire|date=16 February 1960|author=Thomas, Bob|publisher=Daytona Beach Morning Journal|accessdate=12 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br clear=right&gt;

==Summary ==
[[Image:ernie milktable.jpg|200px|thumb|left|Kovacs as Eugene. The milk camera trick as seen by television viewers.]]Excluding Kovacs' opening monologue, commercials, and closing credits, the main body of the show runs about twenty minutes. Kovacs played &quot;Eugene&quot;, a bumbling character he had created during his 1956 stint as a continuing guest host of the [[Tonight Show]], filling in for [[Steve Allen]] on Monday and Tuesday nights.  A case can be made that this show is actually called ''Eugene'', because that word is the title that appears when the main part of the show starts.

Within the show, no one talks.  Eugene unwittingly annoys the people around him with his noisy antics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=7hRUAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=pDkNAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=3789,2560910&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs&amp;hl=en|title=TV Key Previews|date=19 January 1957|publisher= St. Joseph News-Press|accessdate=18 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He is befuddled by simple activities that don't turn out quite right, yet he can perform actions that seem magical with little effort.  Sets are minimal.
[[Image:Ernie Kovacs milk visual 1957.jpg|175px|thumb|right|Kovacs at rehearsal. The tilted set is visible.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=v1ZIAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=ygAEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7016,1936684&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs&amp;hl=en|title=On the Beam|author=Oviatt, Ray|date=22 January 1957|publisher=Toledo Blade|accessdate=14 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Eugene draws a table and lamp on a blank wall and is puzzled when the drawn light won't turn on, until it dawns on him to draw a power outlet with a plugged-in electrical cord leading to the lamp &amp;mdash; and the drawn bulb lights up.  Books on a library shelf are filled with sound:  ''War and Peace'' is all cannons and gunfire, until Eugene finds, at the end of the volume, a live dove, which flies away; the pages of ''Camille'' cough; removing the volume of &quot;The Old Man and the Sea&quot; from the shelf causes a flood of water.&lt;ref name=Crosby/&gt;

Sight gags, sound effects, and musical montages abound, as do intriguing possibilities of what's possible with the new combined technology of color, sound, film cuts, and video effects.  A repairman works with a screwdriver on thin air, and, when done, flips a invisible switch &amp;mdash; a television screen (showing, of course, a western) materializes out of nowhere, then vanishes when the repairman flips the unseen switch off.  Marble statues come to life, then crumble to pieces.  A maid sucks up pieces of crumpled paper with an invisible vacuum cleaner.&lt;ref name=Crosby/&gt;
&lt;!-- [[Image: ernie milktable.jpg|thumb|125px|center|Milk missing the cup]] --&gt;

Throughout, Eugene, at worst, is only mildly perplexed—at least until the end, when, seated at the side of a long table, he finds the contents of his lunchbox keep rolling away, a plumb-bobbed plum is at an angle off vertical, and milk from a thermos misses the cup directly below it.&lt;ref name=Crosby/&gt;
&lt;br clear=right&gt;

== Critical Reception ==
In 1957, Ernie Kovacs received the Sylvania Award&lt;ref name=&quot;Syl&quot;&gt;The Sylvania Award was issued between 1952 and 1958 to those who made a significant contribution to the American television industry.  See an example: [http://uv201.com/TV_Pages/sylvania_award.htm Sylvania award 1952  webpage of the &quot;Reverse Time Page&quot; website]&lt;/ref&gt; for his work on the 1957 NBC special.&lt;ref name=&quot;MusTV&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vision&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=5NcVAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=sBIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1118,3817667&amp;dq=ernie+kovacs&amp;hl=en|title='Vision of Ernie Kovacs' honors first video artist|author=Dudek, Duane|date=16 June 1986|publisher=Milwaukee Journal|accessdate=17 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of the publicity for this TV special, Kovacs received a movie offer from Columbia Studios (which resulted in his role in the film [[Operation Mad Ball]]), and appeared on the cover of the April 15, 1957 issue of [[LIFE]] magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;MusTV&quot; /&gt; 

In 1962, Kovacs and his co-director, Joe Behar, received the [[Directors Guild of America Award]] for the second version of this program shown over the ABC network.&lt;ref name=&quot;MusTV&quot;&gt;[http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/K/htmlK/kovaksernie/kovacsernie.htm   Ernie Kovacs ] webpage at the Museum of Broadcast Communications website&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== Sources ==
* Newcomb, Horace &amp; Museum of Broadcast Communications  (2004) &quot;Encyclopedia of Television&quot; CRC Press, ISBN 1579583946, pp.&amp;nbsp;1286–1287

== External links ==
* [http://www.erniekovacs.net Ernie Kovacs Dot Net: A Tribute To Television's Original Genius]
* [http://www.erniekovacs.com The Official Ernie Kovacs Website]
{{Ernie Kovacs}}
[[Category:American television specials]]
[[Category:1957 television specials]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
