<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27307730" ns="0" title="Qabil Ajmeri"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Qabil Ajmeri''' ({{lang-ur|قابل اجميري}}, {{lang-hi|क़ाबिल अजमेरी}}) was an Indian-Pakistani [[Urdu]] poet.

==Early life==
Qabil Ajmeri was born on August 27, 1931, as Abdul Rahim in Churli, a town located 24 miles from [[Ajmer]], [[Rajistan]]. His father was Abdul Kareem, and his mother was Gulab Bugem. He received his early education in Ajmer. Ajmeri was orphaned at age seven; his father died of [[tuberculosis]], and his mother died shortly afterwards. His younger sister, Fatma, died within a few years.

In January 1948, Ajmeri migrated to [[Pakistan]] with his brother, Sharif, without any provisions, after joining a caravan headed across the border. They then settled in Hyderabad, Sindh. After a while, Qabil’s brother contracted tuberculosis and died.

==Career==
Ajmeri began writing poetry at an early age, and become famous in his locality for his poetry by age 14. His major breakthrough came in a poetry session featuring the well known poet [[Molana Mani Ajmeri]], who had been reciting poems for some time and intended to go on hiatus.

After migrating to [[Hyderabad, Sindh]], Pakistan in December 1947, he became popular at [[mushairas]], and was recognized as a &quot;senior&quot; poet of Urdu at the age of 21, along with other veterans of Hyderabad, including Akhter Ansari Akberabadi, Mohsin Bhopali, and Himayat Ali Shaer. After migrating to Pakistan, he began writing a &quot;qataa&quot;, or quatrain, every day in the daily ''Javed, Hyderabad''. Later on, his quatrains were published in the weekly ''Aftab, Hyderabad''.

Ajmeri wrote both [[ghazal]]s and [[nazm]]s. He published compilations of Urdu poetry and a volume on philosophy, named the &quot;Deeda e Baydar&quot;. He is known as one of Urdu's last romantic poets.{{fact|date=November 2010}}

==Personal life==
Ajmeri was admitted to several hospitals, and in 1960, he was sent to a Quetta sanatorium, where he met Nargis Susan, a nurse who was impressed with his poetry and who later converted to Islam. Afterwards, they married, and had an only son, [[Zafar qabil]]. 

Ajmeri died of tuberculosis in Hyderabad on October 3, 1962, at the age of 31.

==External links==
* [http://www.dawn.com/2008/09/23/fea.htm]
* [http://www.hallagulla.com/urdu/qabil-ajmeri-1029/ Qabil Ajmeri] at UrduWorld.com
* [http://www.dawn.com/2005/05/01/fea.htm Qabil Ajmeri remembered] at www.dawn.com
* [http://poetry.urdustuff.com/qabil.html Qabil Ajmeri] at Urdustuff.com 
* [http://www.shers.in/writers/qabil-ajmeri/ Qabil Ajmeri] at www.shers.in
* [http://www.desiwriters.com/writings.asp?wid=314 Best of Qabil Ajmeri] at www.desiwriters.com
* [http://www.aalmiakhbar.com/blog/?p=2684#comments A blog including poetry by Quabil Ajmeri, added by his son, Zafar.]
* [http://openlibrary.org/works/OL5861961W/%CA%BBIshq_ins%C4%81n_k%C4%AB_z%CC%A4ar%C5%ABrat_hai]

{{Persondata
|NAME=Ajmeri, Qabil
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=قابل اجميري (Urdu); क़ाबिल अजमेरी (Hindi)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Indian-Pakistani Urdu poet
|DATE OF BIRTH=August 27, 1931
|PLACE OF BIRTH=Churli, Rajistan
|DATE OF DEATH=October 3, 1962
|PLACE OF DEATH=Hyderabad, Sindh
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ajmeri, Qabil}}
[[Category:1931 births]]
[[Category:1962 deaths]]
[[Category:Pakistani poets]]
[[Category:Urdu poets]]
[[Category:Muhajir people]]
[[Category:Pakistani Muslims]]
[[Category:Pakistani Sunni Muslims]]
[[Category:Pakistani linguists]]
[[Category:Urdu scholars]]
[[Category:Urdu linguists]]
[[Category:Urdu critics]]
[[Category:Indian poets]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
