<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2731583" ns="0" title="Adolf Hitler"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Hitler}}
{{Pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
&lt;!--ATTENTION! PLEASE READ BEFORE EDITING.
This article is frequently vandalized, which is reverted immediately. If you wish to try test editing, please go to the sandbox located at [[Wikipedia:Sandbox]].

This article is frequently scrutinized and debated. If you wish to edit it with factual, neutral information, scroll down, but before adding to it please check if there is a sub-article on the aspect of Hitler's life you are editing about. Adding to that sub-article rather than this summary article will help keep this article a reasonable length.--&gt;
{{Infobox president
| name = Adolf Hitler
| nationality = {{ubl|Austrian citizen until 7 April 1925&lt;ref name=&quot;citizenship&quot; /&gt;|German citizen after 25 February 1932}}
| image = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S33882, Adolf Hitler retouched.jpg
| imagesize = 200px
| caption = Hitler in 1937
| birth_date = {{birth date|1889|4|20|df = y}}
| birth_place = [[Braunau am Inn]], [[Austria–Hungary]]
| death_date = {{death date and age|1945|4|30|1889|4|20|df = y}}
| death_place = Berlin, [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
| death_cause = Suicide
| party = [[Nazi Party|National Socialist German Workers' Party]] (1921–1945)
| otherparty = [[German Workers' Party]] (1920–1921)
| religion = See [[Adolf Hitler's religious views]]
| spouse = {{ubl|[[Eva Braun]]|(29–30 April 1945)}}
| occupation = Politician, soldier, artist, writer
| order = [[Führer|Führer of Germany]]
| term_start = 2 August 1934
| term_end = 30 April 1945
| predecessor = {{ubl|[[Paul von Hindenburg]]|(as President)}}
| successor = {{ubl|[[Karl Dönitz]]|(as President)}}
| order2 = [[Chancellor of Germany#Chancellor of the Third Reich (1933–1945)|Chancellor of Germany]]
| term_start2 = 30 January 1933
| term_end2 = 30 April 1945
| president2 = {{ubl|[[Paul von Hindenburg]]}}
| deputy2 = {{ubl|[[Franz von Papen]]|Vacant}}
| predecessor2 = [[Kurt von Schleicher]]
| successor2 = [[Joseph Goebbels]]
| signature = Hitler Signature2.svg
| footnotes = 
| allegiance = {{flag|German Empire}}
| branch = {{flagdeco|German Empire|naval}} [[German Army (German Empire)|''Reichsheer'']]
| unit = 16th Bavarian Reserve Regiment
| serviceyears = 1914–1918
| rank = ''[[Gefreiter]]''
| battles = [[World War I]]
| awards = {{ubl|[[Iron Cross|Iron Cross First Class]] |Iron Cross Second Class| [[Wound Badge]]}}
}}

'''Adolf Hitler''' ({{IPA-de|ˈadɔlf ˈhɪtlɐ|lang|Adolf_Hitler.ogg}}; 20 April 1889 – 30 April 1945) was an [[Austria–Hungary|Austrian]]-born [[Germans|German]] politician and the leader of the [[Nazi Party|National Socialist German Workers Party]] ({{lang-de|Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei}} (NSDAP), commonly referred to as the Nazi Party). He was [[Chancellor of Germany#Chancellor of the Third Reich (1933–1945)|chancellor of Germany]] from 1933 to 1945, and [[head of state]] (as ''[[Führer|Führer und Reichskanzler]]'') from 1934 to 1945. Hitler is most commonly associated with the rise of [[fascism]] in Europe, [[World War II]], and [[the Holocaust]].

A decorated veteran of [[World War I]], Hitler joined the [[German Workers' Party]], precursor of the Nazi Party, in 1919, and became leader of the NSDAP in 1921. In 1923 Hitler attempted a coup d'état, known as the [[Beer Hall Putsch]], at the [[Bürgerbräukeller]] [[beer hall]] in Munich. The failed coup resulted in Hitler's imprisonment, during which time he wrote his memoir, ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' (''My Struggle''). After his release in 1924, Hitler gained support by promoting [[Pan-Germanism]], [[antisemitism]], and [[anti-communism]] with [[charismatic authority|charismatic]] [[oratory]] and [[Nazi propaganda|propaganda]]. He was appointed chancellor in 1933 and transformed the [[Weimar Republic]] into the [[Nazi Germany|Third Reich]], a [[Single-party state|single-party]] dictatorship based on the [[totalitarianism|totalitarian]] and [[autocratic]] ideology of [[Nazism]].

Hitler's avowed aim was to establish a [[New Order (Nazism)|New Order]] of absolute Nazi German [[hegemony]] in continental Europe. His foreign and domestic policies had the goal of seizing ''[[Lebensraum]]'' (''living space'') for the [[Nazism and race|Germanic people]]. He oversaw the rearmament of Germany and the [[invasion of Poland]] by the ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' in September 1939, which led to the outbreak of [[European Theatre of World War II|World War II in Europe]].{{sfn|Keegan|1989|p=141}}

Under Hitler's direction, in 1941 German forces and their [[Axis powers|European allies]] occupied most of Europe and North Africa. These gains were gradually reversed after 1941, and in 1945 the [[Allies of World War II|Allied armies]] defeated the German army. Hitler's [[Supremacism#Racial|racially motivated]] policies resulted in the deaths of as many as 17&amp;nbsp;million people,&lt;ref name=&quot;Niewyk2000&quot; /&gt; including an estimated six million [[Jew]]s and between 500,000 and 1,500,000 [[Romani people|Roma]] targeted in [[the Holocaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hancock2004&quot; /&gt;

In the final days of the war, during the [[Battle of Berlin]] in 1945, Hitler married his long-time mistress, [[Eva Braun]]. On 30 April 1945—less than two days later—the two [[Death of Adolf Hitler|committed suicide]] to avoid capture by the [[Red Army]], and their corpses were burned.{{sfn|Linge|2009|pp=199–200}}

==Early years==
===Ancestry===

Hitler's father, [[Alois Hitler]] (1837–1903), was the [[illegitimacy|illegitimate]] child of [[Maria Schicklgruber|Maria Anna Schicklgruber]]. Alois's birth certificate did not list the name of the father, and the child bore his mother's surname.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=6}}&lt;ref name=&quot;RosenbaumR1999&quot; /&gt; In 1842 [[Johann Georg Hiedler]] married Maria, and in 1876 Johann testified before a notary and three witnesses that he was the father of Alois.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=7}} Nazi official [[Hans Frank]] suggested the existence of letters claiming that Alois' mother was employed as a housekeeper for a [[Jew]]ish family in [[Graz]] and that the family's 19-year-old son, [[Leopold Frankenberger]], had fathered Alois.&lt;ref name=&quot;RosenbaumR1999&quot; /&gt; However, no Frankenberger, Jewish or otherwise, is registered in Graz for that period.{{sfn|Hamann|2010|p=50}} Historians now doubt the claim that Alois' father was Jewish;{{sfn|Toland|1992|pp=246–47}}{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=8–9}} all Jews had been expelled from Graz under [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Maximilian I]] in the 15th century, and were not allowed to settle in [[Styria]] until the [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany|Basic Laws]] were passed in 1849.{{sfn|Hamann|2010|p=50}}{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=8–9}}

At age 39 Alois assumed the surname ''Hitler'', also spelled as ''Hiedler'', ''Hüttler'', or ''Huettler''; the name was probably regularised to its final spelling by a clerk. The origin of the name is either &quot;one who lives in a hut&quot; ([[German language|Standard German]] ''Hütte''), &quot;shepherd&quot; (Standard German ''hüten'' &quot;to guard&quot;, English ''heed''), or is from the [[Slavic languages|Slavic]] words ''Hidlar'' and ''Hidlarcek''.{{sfn|Jetzinger|1976|p=32}}

===Childhood===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1989-0322-506, Adolf Hitler, Kinderbild.jpg|upright|thumb|Adolf Hitler as an infant (c.&amp;nbsp;1889/1890)]]
[[File:Klara Polz Hitler.jpg|thumb|upright|Adolf's mother, Klara]]

Adolf Hitler was born on 20 April 1889 at around 6:30&amp;nbsp;pm at the Gasthof zum Pommer, an inn in Ranshofen,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCNews2011&quot; /&gt; a village annexed in 1938 to the municipality of [[Braunau am Inn]], [[Upper Austria]]. He was the third of five children to Alois Hitler and [[Klara Pölzl]] (1860–1907). Adolf's older siblings&amp;nbsp;– Gustav and Ida&amp;nbsp;– died in infancy.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=9}} When Hitler was three, the family moved to [[Passau]], Germany.{{sfn|Rosmus|2004|p=33}} There he would acquire the distinctive [[Bavarian language|lower Bavarian dialect]], rather than [[Austrian German]], which marked his speech all of his life.{{sfn|Keller|2010|p=15}}{{sfn|Hamann|2010|pp=7–8}}{{sfn|Kubizek|2006|p=37}} In 1894, the family relocated to [[Leonding]] near [[Linz]], and in June 1895, Alois retired to a small landholding at Hafeld near [[Lambach]], where he tried his hand at farming and beekeeping. Adolf attended school in nearby [[Fischlham]], and in his free time, he played &quot;[[Cowboys and Indians]]&quot;. Hitler became fixated on warfare after finding a picture book about the [[Franco-Prussian War]] among his father's belongings.{{sfn|Kubizek|2006|p=92}}{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=6}}

The move to Hafeld appears to have coincided with the onset of intense father-son conflicts, caused by Adolf's refusal to conform to the strict discipline of his school.{{sfn|Fromm|1977|pp=493–498}} Alois Hitler's farming efforts at Hafeld ended in failure, and in 1897 the family moved to Lambach. Hitler attended a Catholic school in an 11th-century [[Benedictine]] cloister, the walls of which bore engravings and crests that contained the symbol of the [[swastika]].{{sfn|Rosmus|2004|p=35}} In Lambach the eight-year-old Hitler took singing lessons, sang in the church choir, and even entertained thoughts of becoming a priest.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=10–11}} In 1898 the family returned permanently to Leonding. The death of his younger brother [[Edmund Hitler|Edmund]] from [[measles]] on 2 February 1900 deeply affected Hitler. He changed from being confident and outgoing and an excellent student, to a morose, detached, and sullen boy who constantly fought with his father and his teachers.{{sfn|Payne|1990|p=22}}

Alois had made a successful career in the customs bureau and wanted his son to follow in his footsteps. Hitler later dramatised an episode from this period when his father took him to visit a customs office, depicting it as an event that gave rise to a unforgiving antagonism between father and son who were both equally strong-willed.{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=8}}{{sfn|Keller|2010|pp=33–34}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Fest1977&quot; /&gt; Ignoring his son's desire to attend a classical high school and become an artist, in September 1900 Alois sent Adolf to the ''[[Realschule]]'' in [[Linz]], a technical high school of about 300 students. (This was the same high school that [[Adolf Eichmann]] would attend some 17 years later.)&lt;ref name=&quot;Lipstadt2011&quot; /&gt; Hitler rebelled against this decision, and in ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' revealed that he did poorly in school, hoping that once his father saw &quot;what little progress I was making at the technical school he would let me devote myself to my dream.&quot;{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=10}}

Hitler became obsessed with [[Pan-Germanism|German nationalism]] from a young age as a way of rebelling against his father, who was proudly serving the [[Austria-Hungary|Austrian government]]. Although many [[Austrians]] considered themselves [[Germans]], they were loyal to Austria. Hitler expressed loyalty only to [[German Empire|Germany]], despising the declining [[Habsburg Monarchy]] and its rule over an ethnically variegated empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bendersky2000&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ryschka2008&quot; /&gt; Hitler and his friends used the German greeting &quot;[[Nazi salute|Heil]]&quot;, and sang the German anthem &quot;[[Deutschland Über Alles]]&quot; instead of the [[Gott erhalte Franz den Kaiser#Austria-Hungary|Austrian Imperial anthem]].{{sfn|Hamann|2010|p=13}}

After Alois' sudden death on 3 January 1903, Hitler's behaviour at the technical school became even more disruptive, and he was asked to leave in 1904.&lt;!-- presumably June&amp;nbsp;– [http://books.google.ca/books?id=t-tQ9V2--1kC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;lpg=PA8&amp;dq=hitler+linz+realschule&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=It7UujPIjU&amp;sig=e00eG6t11BOUSwfq4CopmVJfsIk&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=AAyuTZTBNIGisAO1u6ySAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=hitler%20linz%20realschule&amp;f=false Zalampas] says he failed French &amp; retook exam on condition he would not return--&gt; He enrolled at the ''Realschule'' in [[Steyr]] in September 1904, but upon completing his second year, he and his friends went out for a night of celebration and drinking. While drunk, Hitler tore up his school certificate and used the pieces as toilet paper. The stained certificate was brought to the attention of the school's principal, who &quot;... gave him such a dressing-down that the boy was reduced to shivering jelly. It was probably the most painful and humiliating experience of his life.&quot;{{sfn|Payne|1990|p=41}} Hitler was expelled, never to return to school again.

===Early adulthood in Vienna and Munich===
From 1905, Hitler lived a [[bohemianism|bohemian]] life in [[Vienna]] financed by orphan's benefits and support from his mother. The [[Academy of Fine Arts Vienna]] rejected him twice, in 1907 and 1908, because of his &quot;unfitness for painting&quot;, and the director recommended that he study architecture.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=30–31}} However, he lacked the academic credentials required for architecture school. He would later write:

&lt;blockquote&gt;In a few days I myself knew that I should some day become an architect. To be sure, it was an incredibly hard road; for the studies I had neglected out of spite at the ''Realschule'' were sorely needed. One could not attend the Academy's architectural school without having attended the building school at the ''Technik'', and the latter required a high-school degree. I had none of all this. The fulfillment of my artistic dream seemed physically impossible.{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=20}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:The Courtyard of the Old Residency in Munich - Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|''The Courtyard of the Old Residency in Munich''. Adolf Hitler, 1914]]
On 21 December 1907, Hitler's mother died at age 47. He worked as a casual labourer and eventually as a painter, selling watercolours. After being rejected a second time by the Academy of Arts, Hitler ran out of money. In 1909, he lived in a shelter for the homeless, and by 1910, he had settled into a [[Meldemannstraße dormitory|house for poor working men on Meldemannstraße]].{{sfn|Bullock|1999|pp=30–33}}

Hitler stated that he first became an [[antisemite]] in Vienna,{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=52}} which had a large Jewish community, including [[Orthodox Judaism|Orthodox Jews]] who had fled the [[pogrom]]s in [[Russia]].

{{Block quote|There were few Jews in Linz. In the course of centuries their outward appearance had become [[Europeanisation|Europeanised]] and had taken on a human look; in fact, I even took them for Germans. The absurdity of this idea did not dawn on me because I saw no distinguishing feature but the strange religion. The fact that they had, as I believed, been persecuted on this account sometimes almost turned my distaste at unfavorable remarks about them into horror. Thus far I did not so much as suspect the existence of an organized opposition to the Jews. Then I came to Vienna.{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=52}}}}

{{Block quote|Once, as I was strolling through the Inner City, I suddenly encountered an apparition in a black caftan and black hair locks. Is this a Jew? was my first thought. For, to be sure, they had not looked like that in Linz. I observed the man furtively and cautiously, but the longer I stared at this foreign face, scrutinizing feature for feature, the more my first question assumed a new form: Is this a German?{{sfn|Hitler|1999|p=56}}}}

Hitler's account has been questioned by his childhood friend, [[August Kubizek]], who suggested that Hitler was already a &quot;confirmed antisemite&quot; before he left Linz for Vienna. [[Brigitte Hamann]] has challenged Kubizek's account, writing that &quot;of all those early witnesses who can be taken seriously Kubizek is the only one to portray young Hitler as an anti-Semite and precisely in this respect he is not trustworthy.&quot;{{sfn|Hamann|1999|p=176}} If Hitler was an antisemite even before settling in Vienna, apparently he did not act on his views. He was a frequent dinner guest in a wealthy Jewish home; he interacted well with Jewish merchants, and sold his paintings almost exclusively to Jewish dealers.{{sfn|Hamann|2010|pp=347–359, 350}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Beller2000&quot; /&gt;

At the time Hitler lived there, Vienna was a hotbed of traditional religious prejudice and 19th-century racism. Fears of being overrun by immigrants from the East were widespread, and the populist mayor, [[Karl Lueger]], was adept at exploiting the rhetoric of virulent antisemitism for political effect. [[Georg Ritter von Schönerer|Georg Schönerer]]'s [[Pan-Germanism|pangermanic]] ethnic antisemitism had a strong following and base in the [[Mariahilf|Mariahilf district]], where Hitler lived.{{sfn|Hamann|2010|pp=243–246}} Local newspapers such as the ''Deutsches Volksblatt'', which Hitler read, fanned prejudices, as did Rudolf Vrba's writings, which played on Christian fears of being swamped by an influx of eastern Jews.{{sfn|Hamann|2010|pp=341–345}} He probably read occult writings, such as the antisemitic magazine ''[[Ostara (magazine)|Ostara]]'', published by [[Lanz von Liebenfels]].{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=50–51}} Hostile to what he saw as Catholic &quot;Germanophobia&quot;, he developed a strong admiration for [[Martin Luther]].{{sfn|Hamann|2010|p=350}} Luther's foundational antisemitic writings were to play an important role in later Nazi propaganda.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haynes2010&quot; /&gt;

Hitler received the final part of his father's estate in May 1913 and moved to [[Munich]]. He wrote in ''Mein Kampf'' that he had always longed to live in a &quot;real&quot; German city. In Munich, he further pursued his interest in architecture and studied the writings of [[Houston Stewart Chamberlain]], who, a decade later, was to become the first person of national—and even international—repute to align himself with Hitler and the Nazi movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Field1981&quot; /&gt; Hitler also may have left Vienna to avoid [[conscription]] into the Austrian army; he was disinclined to serve the [[Habsburg Empire|Habsburg]] state and was repulsed by what he perceived as a mixture of &quot;races&quot; in the Austrian army.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=27}} After a physical exam on 5 February 1914, he was deemed unfit for service and returned to Munich.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=27, footnote}} When Germany entered World War I in August 1914, he successfully petitioned King [[Ludwig III of Bavaria]] for permission to serve in a [[Bavaria]]n regiment.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=27–30}}

===World War I===
{{Main|Military career of Adolf Hitler}}

Hitler served as a [[runner (soldier)|runner]] on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in France and Belgium in the [[6th Bavarian Reserve Division (German Empire)|Bavarian Reserve Infantry Regiment 16]]. He experienced major combat, including the [[First Battle of Ypres]], the [[Battle of the Somme]], the [[Battle of Arras (1917)|Battle of Arras]], and the [[Battle of Passchendaele]].{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=30}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1974-082-44, Adolf Hitler im Ersten Weltkrieg.jpg|left|thumb|Hitler with his army comrades of the Bavarian Reserve Infantry Regiment 16 (c.&amp;nbsp;1914–1918)]]
He was decorated for bravery, receiving the [[Iron Cross]], Second Class, in 1914. Recommended by [[Hugo Gutmann]], he received the Iron Cross, First Class, on 4 August 1918,{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=59}} a decoration rarely awarded to one of Hitler's rank (''[[Gefreiter]]''). Hitler's post at regimental headquarters, where he had frequent interactions with senior officers, may have helped him receive this decoration.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=52}} The regimental staff, however, thought Hitler lacked leadership skills, and he was never promoted. He also received the [[Wound Badge]] on 18 May 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steiner1976&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Hitler 1914 1918.jpg|thumb|upright|Adolf Hitler as a soldier during the First World War (1914–1918)]]
While serving at regimental headquarters Hitler pursued his artwork, drawing cartoons and instructions for an army newspaper. In October 1916 he was wounded either in the groin area&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph2008&quot; /&gt; or the left thigh when a shell exploded in the dispatch runners' dugout during the [[Battle of the Somme]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=57}} Hitler spent almost two months in the Red Cross hospital at [[Beelitz]]. He returned to his regiment on 5 March 1917.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=58}} On 15 October 1918, Hitler was temporarily blinded by a [[mustard gas]] attack.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=59, 60}} It has been suggested that his blindness may have been an hysterical symptom brought on by the shock at the rapid reversal of Germany's war fortunes.&lt;ref name=&quot;FestHitler&quot; /&gt; He was hospitalised in [[Pasewalk]].

Hitler became embittered over the collapse of the war effort. It was during this time that his ideological development began to firmly take shape.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=61, 62}} He described the war as &quot;the greatest of all experiences&quot;, and was praised by his commanding officers for his bravery.{{sfn|Keegan|1987|pp=238–240}} The experience made Hitler a passionate German patriot, and he was shocked by Germany's [[capitulation (surrender)|capitulation]] in November 1918.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=60}} Like many other German nationalists, he believed in the ''Dolchstoßlegende'' ([[Stab-in-the-back legend]]), which claimed that the German army, &quot;undefeated in the field,&quot; had been &quot;stabbed in the back&quot; on the [[home front]] by civilian leaders and [[Marxism|Marxists]], later dubbed the ''November Criminals''.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=61–63}}

The [[Treaty of Versailles]] stipulated that Germany must relinquish several of its territories and [[demilitarization|demilitarise]] the [[Rhineland]]. The treaty imposed economic sanctions and levied reparations on the country. Many Germans perceived the treaty—especially Article 231, which declared Germany responsible for the war—as a humiliation.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=96}} The economic, social, and political conditions in Germany effected by the war and the Versailles treaty were later exploited by Hitler for political gains.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=80, 90, 92}}

==Entry into politics==
{{Main|Adolf Hitler's political views}}
After World War I, Hitler remained in the army and returned to Munich.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=61}} In July 1919 he was appointed ''Verbindungsmann'' (intelligence agent) of an ''Aufklärungskommando'' (reconnaissance commando) of the ''Reichswehr'', both to influence other soldiers and to [[Espionage|infiltrate]] the [[German Workers' Party]] (DAP). While he studied the activities of the DAP, Hitler became impressed with founder [[Anton Drexler]]'s antisemitic, nationalist, [[Anti-capitalism|anti-capitalist]], and anti-Marxist ideas.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=82}} Drexler favoured a strong active government, a &quot;non-Jewish&quot; version of [[socialism]], and solidarity among all members of society. Impressed with Hitler's oratory skills, Drexler invited him to join the DAP. Hitler accepted on 12 September 1919,&lt;ref name=&quot;Stackelberg2007&quot; /&gt; becoming the party's 55th member.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitcham1996&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Hitlermember.png|thumb|left|A copy of Adolf Hitler's [[German Workers' Party]] (DAP) membership card]]
At the DAP, Hitler met [[Dietrich Eckart]], one of its early founders and a member of the occult [[Thule Society]].{{sfn|Fest|1970|p=21}} Eckart became Hitler's mentor, exchanging ideas with him and introducing him to a wide range of people in Munich society.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=94, 95, 100}} Hitler thanked Eckart and paid tribute to him in the second volume of ''Mein Kampf''. To increase the party's appeal, the party changed its name to the ''Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei'' ([[National Socialist German Workers Party]] – NSDAP).{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=87}} Hitler designed the party's banner of a [[swastika]] in a white circle on a red background.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=88}}

After his discharge from the army in March 1920, Hitler began working full time for the party. In February 1921—already highly effective at speaking to large audiences—he spoke to a crowd of over six thousand in Munich.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=89}} To publicise the meeting, two truckloads of party supporters drove around town waving swastika flags and throwing leaflets. Hitler soon gained notoriety for his rowdy, [[polemic]] speeches against the Treaty of Versailles, rival politicians, and especially against Marxists and Jews.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=89–92}} At the time, the NSDAP was centred in Munich, a major hotbed of anti-government German nationalists determined to crush Marxism and undermine the [[Weimar Republic]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=81}}

In June 1921, while Hitler and Eckart were on a fundraising trip to Berlin, a mutiny broke out within the DAP in Munich. Members of the DAP's executive committee, some of whom considered Hitler to be too overbearing, wanted to merge with the rival [[German Socialist Party]] (DSP).{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=100, 101}} Hitler returned to Munich on 11 July 1921 and angrily tendered his resignation from the DAP. The committee members realised that his resignation would mean the end of the party.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=102}} Hitler announced he would rejoin on the condition that he would replace Drexler as party chairman, and that the party headquarters would remain in Munich.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=103}} The committee agreed; he rejoined the party as member 3,680. He still faced some opposition within the DAP: [[Hermann Esser]] and his allies printed 3,000 copies of a pamphlet attacking Hitler as a traitor to the party.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=103}}{{#tag:ref| Hitler also won settlement from a [[libel]] suit against the socialist paper the ''Münchener Post'', which had questioned his lifestyle and income.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=99}}|group=lower-alpha}} In the following days, Hitler spoke to several packed houses and defended himself to thunderous applause. His strategy proved successful: at a general DAP membership meeting, he was granted absolute powers as party chairman, with only one nay vote cast.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=83, 103}}

Hitler's vitriolic beer hall speeches began attracting regular audiences. Early followers included [[Rudolf Hess]], the former air force pilot [[Hermann Göring]], and the army captain [[Ernst Röhm]]. The latter became head of the Nazis' paramilitary organisation, the ''[[Sturmabteilung]]'' (SA, &quot;Storm Division&quot;), which protected meetings and frequently attacked political opponents. A critical influence on his thinking during this period was the [[Aufbau Vereinigung]],{{sfn|Kellogg|2005|p=275}} a conspiratorial group formed of [[White émigré|White Russian]] exiles and early National Socialists. The group, financed with funds channelled from wealthy industrialists like [[Henry Ford]], introduced him to the idea of a Jewish conspiracy, linking international finance with [[Bolshevism]].{{sfn|Kellogg|2005|p=203}}

===Beer Hall ''Putsch''===
{{Main|Beer Hall Putsch}}
[[File:Drawing of Adolf Hitler.jpg|upright|thumb|Drawing of Hitler (30 October 1923)]]
Hitler enlisted the help of World War I General [[Erich Ludendorff]] for an attempted coup known as the &quot;[[Beer Hall Putsch|Beer Hall ''Putsch'']]&quot; (also known as the &quot;Hitler ''Putsch''&quot; or &quot;Munich ''Putsch''&quot;). The Nazi Party had used [[Italian Fascism]] as a model for their appearance and policies, and in 1923, Hitler wanted to emulate [[Benito Mussolini]]'s &quot;[[March on Rome]]&quot; by staging his own &quot;Campaign in Berlin&quot;. Hitler and Ludendorff sought the support of ''Staatskommissar'' (state commissioner) [[Gustav von Kahr]], Bavaria's ''de facto'' ruler. However, Kahr, along with Police Chief [[Hans Ritter von Seisser]] (Seißer) and [[Reichswehr]] General [[Otto von Lossow]], wanted to install a nationalist dictatorship without Hitler.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=126}}

Hitler wanted to seize a critical moment for successful popular agitation and support.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=125}} On 8 November 1923, he and the SA stormed a public meeting of 3,000 people that had been organised by Kahr in the [[Bürgerbräukeller]], a large beer hall in Munich. Hitler interrupted Kahr's speech and announced that the national revolution had begun, declaring the formation of a new government with Ludendorff.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=128}} With his handgun drawn, Hitler demanded and got the support of Kahr, Seisser, and Lossow.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=128}} Hitler's forces initially succeeded in occupying the local Reichswehr and police headquarters; however, neither the army nor the state police joined forces with him.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=129}} Kahr and his consorts quickly withdrew their support and fled to join Hitler's opposition.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=71–72}} The next day, Hitler and his followers marched from the beer hall to the [[Ministry of War (Kingdom of Bavaria)|Bavarian War Ministry]] to overthrow the Bavarian government on their &quot;March on Berlin&quot;, but the police dispersed them.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=130–131}} [[Beer Hall Putsch#Nazis who died in the Putsch|Sixteen NSDAP members]] and four police officers were killed in the failed coup.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=73–74}}

Hitler fled to the home of [[Ernst Hanfstaengl]], and by some accounts he contemplated suicide.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=132}} He was depressed but calm when he was arrested on 11 November 1923 for [[high treason]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=131}} His trial began in February 1924 before the special [[People's Court (Bavaria)|People's Court]] in Munich,&lt;ref name=&quot;MunichCourt1924&quot; /&gt; and [[Alfred Rosenberg]] became temporary leader of the NSDAP.  On 1 April Hitler was sentenced to five years' imprisonment at [[Landsberg Prison]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulda2009&quot; /&gt; He received friendly treatment from the guards and a lot of mail from supporters. The Bavarian Supreme Court issued a pardon and he was released from jail on 20 December 1924, against the state prosecutor's objections.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|p=239}} Including time on remand, Hitler had served just over one year in prison.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=121}}

[[File:Mein Kampf dust jacket.jpeg|thumb|left|[[Dust jacket]] of ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' (1926–1927)]]
While at Landsberg, Hitler dictated most of the first volume of ''[[Mein Kampf]]'' (''My Struggle''; originally entitled ''Four and a Half Years of Struggle against Lies, Stupidity, and Cowardice'') to his deputy, [[Rudolf Hess]].{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=121}} The book, dedicated to Thule Society member Dietrich Eckart, was an autobiography and an exposition of his ideology. ''Mein Kampf'' was influenced by ''[[The Passing of the Great Race]]'' by [[Madison Grant]], which Hitler called &quot;my Bible&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Spiro2008&quot; /&gt; Published in two volumes in 1925 and 1926, it sold 228,000 copies between 1925 and 1932. One million copies were sold in 1933, Hitler's first year in office. {{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=80–81}}

===Rebuilding the NSDAP===
[[File:Hitler 1928.jpg|upright|thumb|Hitler (left), standing behind [[Hermann Göring]] at a Nazi rally in [[Nuremberg]] (c. 1928)]]

At the time of Hitler's release from prison, politics in Germany had become less combative, and the economy had improved. This limited Hitler's opportunities for political agitation. As a result of the failed ''Beer Hall Putsch'', the NSDAP and its affiliated organisations were banned in Bavaria. In a meeting with Prime Minister of Bavaria [[Heinrich Held]] on 4 January 1925, Hitler agreed to respect the authority of the state: he would only seek political power through the democratic process. The meeting paved the way for the ban on the NSDAP to be lifted.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=158, 161, 162}} However, Hitler was barred from public speaking, {{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=162, 166}} a ban that remained in place until 1927.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=129}} To advance his political ambitions in spite of the ban, Hitler appointed [[Gregor Strasser]], [[Otto Strasser]], and [[Joseph Goebbels]] to organise and grow the NSDAP in northern Germany. A superb organiser, Gregor Strasser steered a more independent political course, emphasising the socialist element of the party's programme.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=166, 167}}

Hitler ruled the NSDAP autocratically by asserting the ''[[Führerprinzip]]'' (&quot;Leader principle&quot;). Rank in the party was not determined by elections—positions were filled through appointment by those of higher rank, who demanded unquestioning obedience to the will of the leader.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=170, 172}}

The stock market in the United States crashed on 24 October 1929. The impact in Germany was dire: millions were thrown out of work and several major banks collapsed. Hitler and the NSDAP prepared to take advantage of the emergency to gain support for their party. They promised to repudiate the Versailles treaty, strengthen the economy, and provide jobs.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=136–137}}

==Rise to power==
{{Main|Adolf Hitler's rise to power}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders sortable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;
|-
|+ Nazi Party election results&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolb2005&quot; /&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Date
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Total &lt;br /&gt; votes
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Votes, &lt;br /&gt; percentage
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Reichstag &lt;br /&gt; seats
! scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1924|5|1}}[[German federal election, May 1924|May 1924]]
| {{Number table sorting|1918300}}
| {{Number table sorting|6.5}}
| {{Number table sorting|32}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Hitler in prison
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1924|12|1}}[[German federal election, December 1924|December 1924]]
| {{Number table sorting|907300}}
| {{Number table sorting|3.0}}
| {{Number table sorting|14}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | Hitler released from prison
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; |{{dtsh|format=dmy|1928|5|1}}[[German federal election, 1928|May 1928]]
| {{Number table sorting|810100}}
| {{Number table sorting|2.6}}
| {{Number table sorting|12}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | &amp;nbsp;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1930|9|1}}[[German federal election, 1930|September 1930]]
| {{Number table sorting|6409600}}
| {{Number table sorting|18.3}}
| {{Number table sorting|107}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | After the financial crisis
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1932|7|1}}[[German federal election, July 1932|July 1932]]
| {{Number table sorting|13745000}}
| {{Number table sorting|37.3}}
| {{Number table sorting|230}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | After Hitler was candidate for presidency
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1932|11|1}}[[German federal election, November 1932|November 1932]]
| {{Number table sorting|11737000}}
| {{Number table sorting|33.1}}
| {{Number table sorting|196}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|&amp;nbsp;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | {{dtsh|format=dmy|1933|3|1}}[[German federal election, March 1933|March 1933]]
| {{Number table sorting|17277180}}
| {{Number table sorting|43.9}}
| {{Number table sorting|288}}
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot; | During Hitler's term as chancellor of Germany
|}

===Brüning administration===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 119-0289, München, Hitler bei Einweihung &quot;Braunes Haus&quot;.jpg|thumb|Hitler and [[NSDAP]] treasurer [[Franz Xaver Schwarz]] at the dedication of the renovation of the Palais Barlow on [[Brienner Straße (Munich)|Brienner Straße]] in Munich into the [[Brown House, Munich|&quot;Brown House&quot;]] headquarters, December 1930]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S38324, Tag von Potsdam, Adolf Hitler, Paul v. Hindenburg.jpg|thumb|[[Paul von Hindenburg]] and Adolf Hitler, 21 March 1933]]
The [[Great Depression]] in Germany in 1930 provided a political opportunity for Hitler. Germans were ambivalent to the [[parliamentary republic]], which faced strong challenges from right- and left-wing extremists. The moderate political parties were increasingly unable to stem the tide of extremism, and the [[German referendum, 1929|German referendum of 1929]] had helped to elevate Nazi ideology.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolb1988&quot; /&gt; The elections of September 1930 resulted in the the break-up of a [[grand coalition]] and its replacement by a minority cabinet. Its leader, chancellor [[Heinrich Brüning]] of the [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]], governed through [[emergency powers|emergency decrees]] from the president, [[Paul von Hindenburg]]. Governance by decree would become the new norm and paved the way for [[authoritarian]] forms of government.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|p=403 ''et. seq''}} The NSDAP rose from obscurity to win 18.3% of the vote and 107 parliamentary seats in the 1930 election, becoming the second-largest party in parliament.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|pp=434–446 ''et. seq.''}}

Hitler made a prominent appearance at the trial of two Reichswehr officers, Lieutenants Richard Scheringer and Hans Ludin, in the autumn of 1930. Both were charged with membership of the NSDAP, at that time illegal for Reichswehr personnel.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=218}} The prosecution argued that the NSDAP was an extremist party, prompting defence lawyer [[Hans Frank]] to call on Hitler to testify in court.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=216}} While testifying on 25 September 1930, Hitler stated that his party would pursue political power solely through democratic elections.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|pp=218–219}} Hitler's testimony won him many supporters in the officer corps.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=222}}

Brüning's austerity measures brought little economic improvement and were extremely unpopular.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|p=449 ''et. seq.''}} Hitler exploited this weakness by targeting his political messages specifically to the segments of the population that had been affected by the inflation of the 1920s and the Depression, such as farmers, war veterans, and the middle class.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|pp=434–436, 471}}

Hitler formally renounced his Austrian citizenship on 7 April 1925, but at the time did not acquire German citizenship. For almost seven years Hitler was stateless, unable to run for public office and faced the risk of deportation.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=130}} On 25 February 1932 the interior minister of [[Free State of Brunswick|Brunswick]], who was a member of the NSDAP, appointed Hitler as administrator for the state's delegation to the [[Reichsrat (Germany)|Reichsrat]] in Berlin, making Hitler a citizen of Brunswick,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinrichs2007&quot; /&gt; and thus of Germany.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|p=476}}

In 1932 Hitler ran against von Hindenburg in the [[German presidential election, 1932|presidential elections]]. The viability of his candidacy was underscored by a 27 January 1932 speech to the Industry Club in [[Düsseldorf]], which won him support from many of Germany's most powerful industrialists.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|pp=468–471}} However, Hindenburg had support from various nationalist, monarchist, Catholic, and [[republicanism|republican]] parties and some social democrats. Hitler used the campaign slogan &quot;''Hitler über Deutschland''&quot; (&quot;Hitler over Germany&quot;), a reference to both his political ambitions and to his campaigning by aircraft.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=201}} Hitler came in second in both rounds of the election, garnering more than 35% of the vote in the final election. Although he lost to Hindenburg, this election established Hitler as a strong force in German politics.{{sfn|Halperin|1965|pp=477–479}}

===Appointment as chancellor===
The absence of an effective government prompted two influential politicians, [[Franz von Papen]] and [[Alfred Hugenberg]], along with several other industrialists and businessmen, to write a letter to von Hindenburg. The signers urged Hindenburg to appoint Hitler as leader of a government &quot;independent from parliamentary parties&quot;, which could turn into a movement that would &quot;enrapture millions of people&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Industrialists1932&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FoxNews2003&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1972-026-11, Machtübernahme Hitlers.jpg|thumb|Hitler, at the window of the [[Reich Chancellery]], receives an ovation on the evening of his inauguration as [[Chancellor of Germany|chancellor]], 30 January 1933]]
Hindenburg eventually and reluctantly agreed to appoint Hitler as chancellor after two further parliamentary elections—in July and November 1932—had not resulted in the formation of a majority government. Hitler was to head a short-lived coalition government formed by the NSDAP and Hugenberg's party, the [[German National People's Party]] (DNVP). On 30 January 1933 the new cabinet was sworn in during a brief and simple ceremony in Hindenburg's office. The NSDAP held three of the eleven posts: Hitler was named chancellor, [[Hermann Göring]] was named [[minister without portfolio]], and [[Wilhelm Frick]] was appointed [[minister of the interior]].{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=184}}

===Reichstag fire and March elections===
As chancellor, Hitler worked against attempts by the NSDAP's opponents to build a majority government. Because of the political stalemate, Hitler asked President Hindenburg to dissolve the Reichstag again, and elections were scheduled for early March. On 27 February 1933, the [[Reichstag fire|Reichstag building was set on fire]]. Göring blamed a communist plot, because Dutch communist [[Marinus van der Lubbe]] was found in incriminating circumstances inside the burning building.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=262}} At Hitler's urging, Hindenburg responded with the [[Reichstag Fire Decree]] of 28 February, which suspended basic rights, including ''[[habeas corpus]]''. Activities of the [[Communist Party of Germany|German Communist Party]] were suppressed, and some 4,000 communist party members were arrested.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=194}} Researchers, including Shirer and Bullock, are of the opinion that the NSDAP itself was responsible for starting the fire.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=192}}{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=262}}

In addition to political campaigning, the NSDAP engaged in paramilitary violence and the spread of anti-communist propaganda in the days preceding the election. On election day, 6 March 1933, the NSDAP's share of the vote increased to 43.9%, and the party acquired the largest number of seats in parliament. However, Hitler's party failed to secure an absolute majority, necessitating another coalition with the DNVP.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=265}}

===Day of Potsdam and the Enabling Act===
On 21 March 1933, the new Reichstag was constituted with an opening ceremony at the [[Garrison Church (Potsdam)|Garrison Church]] in [[Potsdam]]. This &quot;Day of Potsdam&quot; was held to demonstrate unity between the Nazi movement and the old Prussian elites and military. Hitler appeared in a [[morning coat]] and humbly greeted President von Hindenburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Potsdam1933&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=196–197}}

To achieve full political control despite having failed to gain an absolute majority in the prior parliamentary election, Hitler's government brought the ''Ermächtigungsgesetz'' ([[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]]) to a vote in the newly elected Reichstag. The legislation gave Hitler's cabinet full legislative powers for a period of four years and allowed deviations from the constitution.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=198}} Since the bill required a two-thirds majority to pass, it needed very broad support. The position of the [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]], the third largest party in the Reichstag, turned out to be decisive. In return for Hitler's oral guarantees that President von Hindenburg would retain his power of veto,{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=199}} and under the leadership of [[Ludwig Kaas]], the Centre Party supported the Enabling Act. 

On 23 March, the Reichstag assembled in a replacement building under turbulent circumstances. Ranks of SA men served as guards inside the building, while large groups outside opposing the proposed legislation shouted slogans and threats toward the arriving members of parliament.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=269}} At the end of the day, all parties except the Social Democrats voted in favour of the bill—the Communist Party, as well as several social democrats, were barred from attending the vote. The Enabling Act, along with the Reichstag Fire Decree, transformed Hitler's government into a ''de facto'' dictatorship.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=199}}

===Removal of remaining limits===
{{quotation|At the risk of appearing to talk nonsense I tell you that the National Socialist movement will go on for 1,000 years! ... Don't forget how people laughed at me 15 years ago when I declared that one day I would govern Germany. They laugh now, just as foolishly, when I declare that I shall remain in power!|Adolf Hitler to a British correspondent in Berlin, June 1934&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1934&quot; /&gt;}}

Having achieved full control over the legislative and executive branches of government, Hitler and his political allies embarked on systematic suppression of the remaining political opposition. After the dissolution of the Communist Party, the Social Democratic Party was also banned and all its assets seized.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=201}} Many trade union delegates were flown to Berlin for [[May Day]] activities, and while they were there, SA stormtroopers demolished trade union offices around the country. On 2 May 1933 all trade unions were forced to dissolve, and their leaders were arrested, with some sent to [[concentration camp]]s.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=202}} A new union organisation was formed, representing all workers, administrators, and company owners together as one group. This new trade union reflected the concept of national socialism in the spirit of Hitler's &quot;[[Volksgemeinschaft]]&quot; (community of all German people).&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans2003&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Adolf Hitler-1933.jpg|thumb|upright|In 1934, Hitler became Germany's president under the title of ''[[Führer und Reichskanzler]]'' (leader and chancellor of the Reich).]]
On 14 July 1933 Hitler's Nazi Party was declared the only legal party in Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans2003&quot; /&gt; Hitler used the SA to pressure Hugenberg into resigning.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=201}} The demands of the SA for more political and military power caused much anxiety among military, industrial, and political leaders. Hitler was prompted to purge the entire SA leadership, including [[Ernst Röhm]], and other political adversaries (such as [[Gregor Strasser]] and former chancellor [[Kurt von Schleicher]]). These actions took place from 30 June to 2 July 1934, in what became known as the [[Night of the Long Knives]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=309–314}} While some Germans were shocked by the killing, many others saw Hitler as the one who restored order to the country.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=309–315}}

On 2 August 1934 President von Hindenburg died. In contravention of the [[Weimar Constitution]], which called for presidential elections, Hitler's cabinet had enacted a law the previous day combining the offices of chancellor and president. The office of president was eliminated, and Hitler became head of state, styled as [[Führer#State and party leader Hitler|Führer und Reichskanzler]] (leader and chancellor).{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=220}} As head of state, Hitler now became Supreme Commander of the armed forces. The traditional loyalty oath of soldiers and sailors was altered to affirm loyalty directly to Hitler rather than to the office of [[commander-in-chief]].{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=309}} On 19 August, the merger of the presidency with the chancellorship was approved by a [[plebiscite]] with support of 84.6% of the electorate.{{sfn|Fest|1974|p=476}}&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes1932&quot; /&gt;

In early 1938, Hitler brought the armed forces under his direct control by forcing the resignation of his War Minister, [[Werner von Blomberg]], when a police dossier was discovered showing that Blomberg's new wife had a record for prostitution.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=392, 393}}{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=312}} Hitler also removed army commander Colonel-General [[Werner von Fritsch]] after the [[Schutzstaffel]] (SS) provided false allegations he had taken part in a homosexual relationship, which had led to blackmail.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=393–397}} The episode became known as the [[Blomberg–Fritsch Affair]]. Hitler replaced the Ministry of War with the [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]] (High Command of the Armed Forces, or OKW), headed by General [[Wilhelm Keitel]]. By early February 1938, twelve other generals had been removed.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=397–398}}

==Third Reich==
{{Main|Nazi Germany}}
Having consolidated his political powers, Hitler suppressed or eliminated his opposition by a process termed ''[[Gleichschaltung]]'' (&quot;bringing into line&quot;). He attempted to gain additional public support by vowing to reverse the effects of the Depression and the Versailles treaty.

===Economy and culture===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-04062A, Nürnberg, Reichsparteitag, SA- und SS-Appell.jpg|thumb|left|upright| &quot;Totenehrung&quot; (honouring of dead): on the terrace in front of the &quot;Ehrenhalle&quot; (Hall of Honour); in the background: the crescent-shaped &quot;Ehrentribüne&quot; (&quot;tribune of honour&quot;). September 1934, [[Nazi party rally grounds]], [[Nuremberg]]]]
In 1935 Hitler appointed [[Hjalmar Schacht]] as Plenipotentiary for War Economy, in charge of preparing the economy for war.  Reconstruction and rearmament were financed through [[Mefo bills]], printing money, and seizing the assets of people arrested as enemies of the State, including Jews.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=259–260}} Unemployment fell substantially, from six million in 1932 to one million in 1936.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=258}} Hitler oversaw one of the largest infrastructure improvement campaigns in German history, leading to the construction of dams, [[autobahn]]s, railroads, and other civil works. Wages were slightly reduced in the pre–World War II years over those of the Weimar Republic, while the cost of living increased by 25%.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=262}}

Hitler's government sponsored architecture on an immense scale. [[Albert Speer]], instrumental in implementing Hitler's classicist reinterpretation of German culture, was placed in charge of the proposed architectural renovations of Berlin.{{sfn|Speer|1971|pp=118–119}} In 1936 Hitler opened the [[1936 Summer Olympics|summer Olympic games]] in Berlin. He made some contributions to the design of the [[Volkswagen Beetle]] and charged [[Ferdinand Porsche]] with its design and construction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wistrich2002&quot; /&gt;

Historians such as [[David Schoenbaum]] and [[Henry Ashby Turner]] argue that Hitler's social and economic policies were modernisation that had anti-modern goals.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000a|pp=166–168}} Others, including [[Rainer Zitelmann]], have contended that Hitler had the deliberate strategy of pursuing a revolutionary modernisation of German society.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000a|pp=244–245}}

===Rearmament and new alliances===
{{Main|Axis powers|Tripartite Pact|German re-armament}}
In a meeting with German military leaders on 3 February 1933, Hitler spoke of &quot;conquest for ''[[Lebensraum]]'' in the East and its ruthless Germanisation&quot; as his ultimate foreign policy objectives.{{sfn|Weinberg|1970|pp=26–27}} In March 1933 State Secretary at the ''[[Auswärtiges Amt]]'' (Foreign Office) Prince Bernhard Wilhelm von Bülow issued a major statement of German foreign policy aims. The statement advocated ''[[Anschluss]]'' with Austria, the restoration of Germany's national borders of 1914, rejection of Part V of the Treaty of Versailles, the return of the former German colonies in Africa, and a German zone of influence in Eastern Europe. Hitler found Bülow's goals to be too modest.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=490–491}}

In his &quot;peace speeches&quot; of the mid-1930s, Hitler stressed the peaceful goals of his policies and willingness to work within international agreements.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=492, 555–556, 586–587}} At the first meeting of his Cabinet in 1933, Hitler prioritised military spending over unemployment relief.{{sfn|Carr|1972|p=23}} In October 1933 Hitler withdrew Germany from the [[League of Nations]] and the [[World Disarmament Conference]], and his Foreign Minister Baron [[Konstantin von Neurath]] stated that the French demand for ''sécurité'' was a principal stumbling block.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000a|pp=145–147}}

[[File:Hitlermusso2 edit.jpg|thumb|upright|On 25 October 1936 an Axis was declared between Italy and Germany]]
In March 1935 Hitler rejected Part V of the Versailles treaty by announcing an expansion of the [[Wehrmacht|German army]] to 600,000 members (six times the number stipulated in the Treaty of Versailles), including development of an Air Force (''[[Luftwaffe]]'') and increasing the size of the Navy (''[[Kriegsmarine]]''). Britain, France, Italy, and the League of Nations condemned these plans.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=601–602}}

On 18 June 1935 the [[Anglo-German Naval Agreement]] (AGNA) was signed, allowing German tonnage to increase to 35% of that of the British navy. Hitler called the signing of the AGNA &quot;the happiest day of his life&quot; as he believed the agreement marked the beginning of the Anglo-German alliance he had predicted in ''Mein Kampf''.{{sfn|Hildebrand|1973|p=39}} France and Italy were not consulted before the signing, directly undermining the League of Nations and putting the Treaty of Versailles on the path towards irrelevance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts1975&quot; /&gt;

On 13 September 1935 Hitler ordered Dr. Bernhard Lösener and Franz Albrecht Medicus of the Interior Ministry to start drafting antisemitic laws for Hitler to bring to the floor of the ''Reichstag''.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=567–568}} On 15 September, Hitler presented two laws—known as the [[Nuremberg Laws]]—before the ''Reichstag''. The laws banned marriage between non-Jewish and Jewish Germans, and forbade the employment of non-Jewish women under the age of 45 in Jewish households. The laws deprived so-called &quot;non-Aryans&quot; of the benefits of German citizenship.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=567–568}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 119-5243, Wien, Arthur Seyß-Inquart, Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Hitler with [[Arthur Seyss-Inquart]], Heinrich Himmler, and [[Reinhard Heydrich]] in Vienna, 1938]]
In March 1936 Hitler [[Remilitarization of the Rhineland|reoccupied]] the [[demilitarized zone]] in the [[Rhineland]], in violation the Versailles treaty. Hitler sent troops to Spain to support [[General Franco]] after receiving an appeal for help in July 1936. At the same time, Hitler continued his efforts to create an Anglo-German alliance.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=630–631}}

In August 1936, in response to a growing economic crisis caused by his rearmament efforts, Hitler issued a memorandum ordering [[Hermann Göring]] to carry out a [[Four Year Plan]] to have Germany ready for war within the next four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Martel1999&quot; /&gt; The &quot;Four-Year Plan Memorandum&quot; laid out an imminent all-out struggle between &quot;Judeo-Bolshevism&quot; and German National Socialism, which in Hitler's view required a committed effort of rearmament regardless of the economic costs.{{sfn|Carr|1972|pp=56–57}}

On 25 October 1936 Count [[Galeazzo Ciano]], foreign minister of [[Benito Mussolini]]'s government, declared an axis between Germany and Italy, and on 25 November, Germany signed the [[Anti-Comintern Pact]] with [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]. Britain, China, Italy, and Poland were also invited to join the Anti-Comintern Pact, but only Italy signed in 1937. By late 1937 Hitler had abandoned his dream of an Anglo-German alliance, blaming &quot;inadequate&quot; British leadership.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|p=642}}

On 5 November 1937 Hitler held a secret meeting at the Reich Chancellery with his war and foreign ministers and military chiefs. As recorded in the [[Hossbach Memorandum]], Hitler stated his intention of acquiring ''Lebensraum'' (&quot;living space&quot;) for the German people, and ordered preparations for war in the east, which would commence no later than 1943. Hitler stated that the conference minutes were to be regarded as his &quot;political testament&quot; in the event of his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aigner1985&quot; /&gt; Hitler said that the crisis of the German economy had reached a point that a severe decline in living standards in Germany could only be stopped by a policy of military aggression—seizing Austria and [[Czechoslovakia]].{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=636–637}}{{sfn|Carr|1972|pp=73–78}} Hitler urged quick action, before Britain and France obtained a permanent lead in the [[arms race]].{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=636–637}}

In early 1938, in the wake of the [[Blomberg–Fritsch Affair]], Hitler asserted control of the military-foreign policy apparatus and the abolition of the War Ministry and its replacement by the [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]] (OKW). He dismissed Neurath as Foreign Minister on 4 February 1938, and assumed the role and title of the ''Oberster Befehlshaber der Wehrmacht'' (supreme commander of the armed forces).&lt;ref name=&quot;Martel1999&quot; /&gt; From early 1938 onwards, Hitler was carrying out a foreign policy that had war as its ultimate aim.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|p=638}}

===The Holocaust===
{{The Holocaust}}
{{Main|The Holocaust}}
One of Hitler's central and most controversial [[ideologies]] was the concept of what he and his followers termed ''[[racial hygiene]]''. Hitler's [[Nazi eugenics|eugenic]] policies initially targeted children with physical and developmental disabilities in a programme dubbed [[Action T4]].{{sfn|Overy|2005|p=252}}

Hitler's idea of ''Lebensraum'', espoused in ''Mein Kampf'', focused on acquiring new territory for German settlement in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gellately1996&quot; /&gt; The ''[[Generalplan Ost]]'' (&quot;General Plan for the East&quot;) called for the population of occupied Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union to be deported to West Siberia, used as slave labour, or murdered;{{sfn|Snyder|2010|p=416}} the conquered territories were to be colonised by German or &quot;Germanized&quot; settlers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steinberg1995&quot; /&gt; American historian [[Timothy D. Snyder]] wrote that:

{{Block quote|Hitler imagined a colonial demodernization of the Soviet Union and Poland that would take tens of millions of lives. The Nazi leadership envisioned an eastern frontier to be depopulated and deindustrialized, and then remade as the agrarian domain of German masters. This vision had four parts. First, the Soviet state was to collapse after a lightning victory in summer 1941, just as the Polish state had in summer 1939, leaving the Germans with complete control over Poland, Belarus, Ukraine, western Russia, and the Caucasus. Second, a ''[[Hunger Plan]]'' would starve to death some thirty million inhabitants of these lands in winter 1941–1942, as food was diverted to Germany and western Europe. Third, the Jews of the Soviet Union who survived the starvation, along with Polish Jews and other Jews under German control, were to be eliminated from Europe in a ''[[Final Solution]]''. Fourth, a ''Generalplan Ost'' foresaw the deportation, murder, enslavement, or assimilation of remaining populations, and the resettlement of eastern Europe by German colonists in the years after the victory. ... As it became clear in the second half of 1941 that the war was not going according to plan, Hitler made clear that he wanted a Final Solution to be effected immediately.{{sfn|Snyder|2010|p=416}}
}}

Between 1939 and 1945, the SS, assisted by [[Collaboration with the Axis Powers during World War II|collaborationist]] governments and recruits from occupied countries, were responsible for the deaths of eleven to fourteen million people, including about six million [[Jews and Judaism in Europe|Jews]], representing two-thirds of the Jewish population in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;YadVashem&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HolocaustMemorialMuseum&quot; /&gt; Deaths took place in [[Nazi concentration camps|concentration camps]], [[Ghettos in Nazi-occupied Europe|ghettos]], and through mass executions. Many victims of the Holocaust were [[gas chamber|gassed]] to death, whereas others died of starvation or disease while working as [[Forced labour under German rule during World War II|slave]] labourers. {{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=946}}

Hitler's policies also resulted in the killings of [[Poles]] and [[Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs|Soviet prisoners of war]], communists and other political opponents, homosexuals, [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]], the physically and mentally disabled,&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldhagen1996&quot; /&gt; [[Jehovah's Witnesses and the Holocaust|Jehovah's Witnesses]], [[Adventists]], and trade unionists. One of the largest centres of mass killing was the [[extermination camp]] complex of [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz-Birkenau]]. Hitler never appeared to have visited the concentration camps and did not speak publicly about the killings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Downing2005&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Buchenwald Corpses 60623.jpg|thumb|left|An American soldier stands near a wagon piled high with corpses outside the crematorium in the newly liberated [[Buchenwald concentration camp]] (April 1945)]]

The Holocaust (the &quot;''[[Final Solution|Endlösung der jüdischen Frage]]''&quot; or &quot;Final Solution of the Jewish Question&quot;) was organised and executed by [[Heinrich Himmler]] and [[Reinhard Heydrich]]. The records of the [[Wannsee Conference]]—held on 20 January 1942 and led by Reinhard Heydrich, with fifteen senior Nazi officials (including [[Adolf Eichmann]]) participating—provide the clearest evidence of the systematic planning for the Holocaust. On 22 February Hitler was recorded saying to his associates, &quot;we shall regain our health only by eliminating the Jews&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Naimark2002&quot; /&gt;

Although no specific order from Hitler authorising the mass killings has surfaced,{{sfn|Megargee|2007|p=146}} he approved the ''[[Einsatzgruppen]]'', killing squads that followed the German army through Poland and Russia, and he was well informed about their activities.{{sfn|Megargee|2007|p=144}} During interrogations by Soviet [[intelligence officer]]s declassified over fifty years later, Hitler's valet, [[Heinz Linge]], and his [[adjutant]], [[Otto Günsche]], stated that Hitler had a direct interest in the development of gas chambers.&lt;ref name=&quot;YadVashemRemembrance&quot; /&gt;

==World War II==
===Early diplomatic successes===
====Alliance with Japan====
{{Main|German–Japanese relations}}
[[File:Matsuoka visits Hitler.jpg|thumb|Hitler and the Japanese Foreign Minister, [[Yōsuke Matsuoka]], at a meeting in Berlin in March 1941. In the background is [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]].]]
In February 1938, on the advice of his newly appointed Foreign Minister, the strongly pro-Japanese [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]], Hitler ended the [[Sino-German cooperation (1911–1941)|Sino-German alliance]] with the [[Republic of China]] to instead enter into an alliance with the more modern and powerful Japan. Hitler announced German recognition of [[Manchukuo]], the Japanese-occupied state in [[Manchuria]], and renounced German claims to their former colonies in the Pacific held by Japan.{{sfn|Bloch|1992|pp=178–179}} Hitler ordered an end to arms shipments to China, and recalled all German officers working with the Chinese Army.{{sfn|Bloch|1992|pp=178–179}} In retaliation, Chinese General [[Chiang Kai-shek]] cancelled all Sino-German economic agreements, depriving the Germans of many Chinese raw materials, though they did continue to ship [[tungsten]], a key metal in armaments production, through to 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Plating2011&quot; /&gt;

====Austria and Czechoslovakia====
On 12 March 1938 Hitler declared unification of Austria with Nazi Germany in the ''[[Anschluss]]''.{{sfn|Butler|Young|1989|p=159}}{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=434}} Hitler then turned his attention to the [[ethnic German]] population of the [[Sudetenland]] district of [[Czechoslovakia]].{{sfn|Overy|2005|p=425}}

On 28–29 March 1938 Hitler held a series of secret meetings in Berlin with [[Konrad Henlein]] of the Sudeten ''Heimfront'' (Home Front), the largest of the ethnic German parties of the Sudetenland. Both men agreed that Henlein would demand increased autonomy for Sudeten Germans from the Czechoslovakian government, thus providing a pretext for German military action against Czechoslovakia. In April 1938 Henlein told the foreign minister of [[Hungary]] that &quot;whatever the Czech government might offer, he would always raise still higher demands&amp;nbsp;... he wanted to sabotage an understanding by all means because this was the only method to blow up Czechoslovakia quickly&quot;.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=334–335}} In private, Hitler considered the Sudeten issue unimportant; his real intention was a war of conquest against Czechoslovakia.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=338–340}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 137-004055, Eger, Besuch Adolf Hitlers.jpg|thumb|left|upright|October 1938: Hitler (standing in Mercedes) drives through the crowd in [[Cheb]] ({{lang-de|Eger}}), part of the German-populated [[Sudetenland]] region of [[Czechoslovakia]], which was annexed to Nazi Germany due to the [[Munich Agreement]]]]
In April 1938 Hitler ordered the OKW to prepare for ''[[Fall Grün (Czechoslovakia)|Fall Grün]]'' (&quot;Case Green&quot;), the code name for an invasion of Czechoslovakia.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|p=366}} As a result of intense French and British diplomatic pressure, on 5 September 1938 Czechoslovakian President [[Edvard Beneš]] unveiled the &quot;Fourth Plan&quot; for constitutional reorganisation of his country, which agreed to most of Henlein's demands for Sudeten autonomy.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=418–419}} Henlein's ''Heimfront'' responded to Beneš' offer with a series of violent clashes with the Czechoslovakian police that led to the declaration of martial law in certain Sudeten districts.{{sfn|Kee|1988|pp=149–150}}{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|p=419}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R69173, Münchener Abkommen, Staatschefs.jpg|thumb|From left to right: [[Neville Chamberlain|Chamberlain]], [[Édouard Daladier|Daladier]], Hitler, [[Benito Mussolini|Mussolini]], and [[Galeazzo Ciano|Ciano]], pictured before signing the [[Munich Agreement]], which gave the Sudetenland to Germany]]
Germany was dependent on [[History of Petroleum|imported oil]]; a confrontation with Britain over the Czechoslovakian dispute could curtail Germany's oil supplies. Hitler called off ''Fall Grün'', originally planned for 1 October 1938.{{sfn|Murray|1984|pp=256–260}} On 29 September 1938 Hitler, [[Neville Chamberlain]], [[Édouard Daladier]], and [[Benito Mussolini]] attended a one-day conference in Munich that led to the [[Munich Agreement]], which handed over the Sudetenland districts to Germany.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=469}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy1999&quot; /&gt;

Chamberlain was satisfied with the Munich conference, calling the outcome &quot;[[peace for our time]]&quot;, while Hitler was angered about the missed opportunity for war in 1938.{{sfn|Kee|1988|pp=202–203}}{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=462–463}} Hitler expressed his disappointment over the Munich Agreement in a speech on 9 October 1938 in [[Saarbrücken]].{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|p=672}} In Hitler's view, the British-brokered peace, although favourable to the ostensible German demands, was a diplomatic defeat which spurred Hitler's intent of limiting British power to pave the way for the eastern expansion of Germany.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=671, 682–683}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Rothwell2001&quot; /&gt; As a result of the summit, Hitler was selected ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine's [[Person of the Year|Man of the Year]] for 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1939-2&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1970-083-42, Magdeburg, zerstörtes jüdisches Geschäft.jpg|thumb|Jewish shops destroyed in [[Magdeburg]], following [[Kristallnacht]] (November 1938)]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-2004-1202-505, Prag, Burg, Besuch Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|Hitler on his visit to [[Prague Castle]] shortly after the occupation of the Czech lands. 15 March 1939]]
In late 1938 and early 1939, the continuing economic crisis caused by the rearmament efforts forced Hitler to make major defence cuts.{{sfn|Murray|1984|p=268}} On 30 January 1939 Hitler made an &quot;Export or die&quot; speech, calling for a German economic offensive to increase German foreign exchange holdings to pay for raw materials such as high-grade iron needed for military weapons.{{sfn|Murray|1984|p=268}}

{{quotation|One thing I should like to say on this day which may be memorable for others as well for us Germans: In the course of my life I have very often been a prophet, and I have usually been ridiculed for it. During the time of my struggle for power it was in the first instance the Jewish race which only received my prophecies with laughter when I said I would one day take over the leadership of the State, and that of the whole nation, and that I would then among many other things settle the Jewish problem. Their laughter was uproarious, but I think that for some time now they have been laughing on the other side of the face. Today I will be once more the prophet. If the international Jewish financiers outside Europe should succeed in plunging the nations once more into a world war, then the result will not be the bolshevisation of the earth, and thus the victory of Jewry, but the annihilation of the Jewish race in Europe!{{sfn|Marrus|2000|p=37}}|Adolf Hitler, address to German parliament, 30 January 1939}}

On 15 March 1939, in violation of the Munich accord and possibly as a result of the deepening economic crisis requiring additional assets,{{sfn|Murray|1984|pp=268–269}} Hitler ordered the ''Wehrmacht'' to invade [[Prague]], and from [[Prague Castle]] proclaimed [[Bohemia]] and [[Moravia]] a German [[Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia|protectorate]].

===Start of World War II===
In private discussions in 1939, Hitler described Britain as the main enemy that had to be defeated. In his view, Poland's obliteration as a sovereign nation was a necessary prelude to that goal. The eastern flank would be secured, and land would be added Germany's ''Lebensraum''.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=579–581}} Hitler wanted Poland to become either a German satellite state or be otherwise neutralised to secure the ''Reich''{{'}}s eastern flank, and to prevent a possible British blockade.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=688–690}} Initially, Hitler favoured the idea of a satellite state; this was rejected by the Polish government. Therefore, Hitler decided to invade Poland; he made this the main German foreign policy goal of 1939.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=537–539, 557–560}} Hitler was offended by the British &quot;guarantee&quot; of Polish independence issued on 31 March 1939, and told his associates that &quot;I shall brew them a devil's drink&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maiolo1998&quot; /&gt; In a speech in [[Wilhelmshaven]] for the launch of the battleship ''[[German battleship Tirpitz|Tirpitz]]'' on 1 April 1939, Hitler first threatened to denounce the [[Anglo-German Naval Agreement]] if the British persisted with their guarantee of Polish independence, which he perceived as an &quot;encirclement&quot; policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maiolo1998&quot; /&gt; On 3 April 1939 Hitler ordered the military to prepare for ''[[Fall Weiss (1939)|Fall Weiss]]'' (Case White), the plan for a German invasion on 25 August 1939.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=537–539, 557–560}} In a speech before the ''Reichstag'' on 28 April 1939 Hitler renounced both the Anglo-German Naval Agreement and the [[German–Polish Non-Aggression Pact]]. In August 1939 Hitler told his generals that his original plan for 1939 was to &quot;... establish an acceptable relationship with Poland in order to fight against the West&quot;. Since Poland refused to become a German satellite, Hitler believed his only option was the invasion of Poland.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|p=558}}

[[File:Adolf Hitler 42 Pfennig stamp.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Depiction of Adolf Hitler as the Führer of the Reich on a 42&amp;nbsp;[[pfennig]] stamp, 1944. The country's name was changed to the &quot;Greater German Reich&quot; (''Grossdeutsches Reich'') in 1943.]]
Hitler was initially concerned that a military attack against Poland could result in a premature war with Britain.{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|pp=688–690}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Robertson1985&quot; /&gt; However, Hitler's foreign minister—and former Ambassador to London—Joachim von Ribbentrop assured him that neither Britain nor France would honour their commitments to Poland, and that a German–Polish war would only be a limited regional war.{{sfn|Bloch|1992|p=228}}{{sfn|Overy|1989|p=56}} Ribbentrop claimed that in December 1938 the French foreign minister, [[Georges Bonnet]], had stated that France considered Eastern Europe as Germany's exclusive sphere of influence;{{sfn|Bloch|1992|pp=210, 228}} Ribbentrop showed Hitler diplomatic cables that supported his analysis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig1983&quot; /&gt; The German Ambassador in London, [[Herbert von Dirksen]], supported Ribbentrop's analysis with a dispatch in August 1939, reporting that Chamberlain knew &quot;the social structure of Britain, even the conception of the British Empire, would not survive the chaos of even a victorious war&quot;, and so would back down.{{sfn|Overy|1989|p=56}} Accordingly, on 21 August 1939 Hitler ordered a military mobilisation against Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy1999-2&quot; /&gt;

Hitler's plans for a military campaign in Poland in late August or early September required tacit Soviet support.{{sfn|Robertson|1963|pp=181–187}} The [[non-aggression pact]] (the [[Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact]]) between Germany and the Soviet Union, led by [[Joseph Stalin]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Beloff1949&quot; /&gt; included secret protocols with an agreement to partition Poland between the two countries. In response to the German-Soviet Non-Aggression Pact—and contrary to the prediction of Ribbentrop that the newly-formed pact would sever Anglo-Polish ties—Britain and Poland signed the Anglo-Polish alliance on 25 August 1939. This, along with news from Italy that Mussolini would not honour the [[Pact of Steel]], caused Hitler to postpone the attack on Poland from 25 August to 1 September.{{sfn|Bloch|1992|pp=252–253}} In the days before the start of the war, Hitler tried to manoeuvre the British into neutrality by offering a non-aggression guarantee to the British Empire on 25 August 1939 and by having Ribbentrop present a last-minute peace plan with an impossibly short time limit in an effort to then blame the war on British and Polish inaction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1995&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Bloch|1992|pp=255–257}}

As a pretext for a military aggression against Poland, Hitler claimed the [[Free City of Danzig]] and the right to extraterritorial roads across the [[Polish Corridor]], which Germany had ceded under the Versailles treaty.{{sfn|Weinberg|1980|pp=561–562, 583–584}} Despite his concerns over a possible British intervention, Hitler was ultimately not deterred from his aim of invading Poland,{{sfn|Messerschmidt|1990|p=714}} and on 1 September 1939 Germany [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|invaded western Poland]]. In response, Britain and France declared war on Germany on 3 September. This surprised Hitler, prompting him to turn to Ribbentrop and angrily ask &quot;Now what?&quot;{{sfn|Bloch|1992|p=260}} France and Britain did not act on their declarations immediately, and on 17 September, Soviet forces invaded eastern Poland.{{sfn|Hakim|1995}}

{{quotation|Poland never will rise again in the [[Second Polish Republic|form]] of the Versailles treaty. That is guaranteed not only by Germany, but also&amp;nbsp;... Russia.|Adolf Hitler, public speech in [[Danzig]] at the end of September 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1939&quot; /&gt;}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-2008-0922-500, Reichstag, Begrüßung Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|upright|Members of the [[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]] salute Hitler at the [[Kroll Opera House]] on 6&amp;nbsp;October 1939, at the end of the [[Invasion of Poland|campaign against Poland]]]]

The fall of Poland was followed by what contemporary journalists dubbed the &quot;[[Phoney War]]&quot; or ''Sitzkrieg'' (&quot;sitting war&quot;). Hitler instructed the two newly-appointed ''Gauleiters'' of north-western Poland, [[Albert Forster]] and [[Arthur Greiser]], to &quot;[[Germanization|Germanise]]&quot; the area, and promised them &quot;There would be no questions asked&quot; about how this &quot;Germanisation was accomplished.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=141–145}} Forster had local Poles sign forms stating that they had German blood, and required no further documentation. Greiser carried out a brutal [[ethnic cleansing]] campaign on the Polish population in his purview.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=141–145}} Greiser complained to Hitler that Forster was allowing thousands of Poles to be accepted as &quot;racial&quot; Germans thus, in Greiser's view, endangering German &quot;racial purity&quot;. Hitler told Himmler and Greiser to take up their difficulties with Forster, and not to involve him.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=141–145}} Hitler's handling of the Forster–Greiser dispute has been advanced as an example of [[Ian Kershaw]]'s theory of &quot;Working Towards the Führer&quot;: Hitler issued vague instructions and expected his subordinates to work out policies on their own.

Another dispute broke out between different factions. One side, represented by Himmler and Greiser championed carrying out ethnic cleansing in Poland, and another side, represented by Göring and Hans Frank, called for turning Poland into the &quot;granary&quot; of the ''Reich''.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=148–149}} At a conference held at Göring's [[Karinhall]] estate on 12 February 1940, the dispute was initially settled in favour of the Göring-Frank view of economic exploitation, which ended the economically disruptive mass expulsions.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=148–149}} On 15 May 1940, however, Himmler presented Hitler with a memo entitled &quot;Some Thoughts on the Treatment of Alien Population in the East&quot;, which called for expulsion of the entire Jewish population of Europe into Africa and reducing the remainder of the Polish population to a &quot;leaderless class of labourers&quot;.{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=148–149}} Hitler called Himmler's memo &quot;good and correct&quot;;{{sfn|Rees|1997|pp=148–149}} he scuttled the so-called Karinhall agreement and implemented the Himmler–Greiser viewpoint as German policy for the Polish population.

[[File:Adolf Hitler in Paris 1940.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Hitler visits Paris with architect [[Albert Speer]] (left) and artist [[Arno Breker]] (right), 23&amp;nbsp;June 1940]]

Hitler commenced building up military forces on Germany's western border, and in April 1940, German forces invaded [[Operation Weserübung|Denmark and Norway]]. In May 1940, Hitler's forces [[Battle of France|attacked France]], and conquered [[German invasion of Luxembourg in World War II|Luxembourg]], the [[Battle of the Netherlands|Netherlands]], and [[Battle of Belgium|Belgium]]. These victories prompted Mussolini to have Italy join forces with Hitler on 10 June 1940. France [[surrender (military)|surrendered]] on 22 June 1940.

Britain, whose forces were forced to leave France by sea from [[Dunkirk evacuation|Dunkirk]], continued to fight alongside [[Commonwealth of Nations|other British dominions]] in the [[Battle of the Atlantic (1939–1945)|Battle of the Atlantic]]. Hitler made peace overtures for to the British, now led by [[Winston Churchill]], and when these were rejected Hitler ordered [[bombing raid]]s on the United Kingdom. Hitler's prelude to a planned invasion of the UK were widespread aerial attacks in the [[Battle of Britain]] on [[Royal Air Force]] airbases and [[radar]] stations in South-East England. However, the German ''Luftwaffe'' failed to defeat the Royal Air Force.

On 27 September 1940 the [[Tripartite Pact]] was signed in Berlin by [[Saburō Kurusu]] of [[Imperial Japan]], Hitler, and Italian foreign minister Ciano. The agreement was later expanded to include Hungary, [[Romania]], and [[Bulgaria]]. They were collectively known as the [[Axis powers]]. The purpose of the pact was to deter the United States from supporting the British. By the end of October 1940, air superiority for the invasion [[Operation Sea Lion]] could not be achieved, and Hitler ordered the [[The Blitz|nightly air raids]] of British cities, including London, [[Plymouth]], and [[Coventry]].

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 121-0721, Marburg-Drau, Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|Hitler visiting [[Maribor]] ({{lang-de|Marburg an der Drau}}), [[Yugoslavia]], with [[Otto Dietrich]], [[Siegfried Uiberreither]], and [[Martin Bormann]] in 1941]]

In the Spring of 1941, Hitler was distracted from his plans for the East by military activities in North Africa, the [[Balkans]], and the Middle East. In February, [[Operation Sonnenblume|German forces arrived in Libya]] to bolster the Italian presence. In April, Hitler launched the [[invasion of Yugoslavia]], quickly followed by the [[Battle of Greece|invasion of Greece]]. In May, German forces were sent to support [[Anglo-Iraqi War|Iraqi rebel forces fighting against the British]] and to [[Battle of Crete|invade Crete]]. On 23 May, Hitler released [[Führer Directive No. 30]].{{sfn|Kurowski|2005|pp=141–142}}

A major historical debate about Hitler's foreign policy preceding the war in 1939 centres on two contrasting explanations: one, by the Marxist historian [[Timothy Mason]], suggests that a structural economic crisis drove Hitler into a &quot;flight into war&quot;, while another, by economic historian [[Richard Overy]], explains Hitler's actions with non-economic motives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason1997&quot; /&gt; Historians such as William Carr, [[Gerhard Weinberg]], and Kershaw have argued that a non-economic reason for Hitler's rush to war was Hitler's morbid and obsessive fear of an early death, and hence his feeling that he did not have long to accomplish his work.{{sfn|Carr|1972|pp=76–77}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2000b|pp=36–37, 92}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1955&quot; /&gt;

===Path to defeat===
On 22 June 1941, contravening the Hitler-Stalin non-aggression pact of 1939, three million German troops attacked the Soviet Union in [[Operation Barbarossa]]. The invasion seized a huge area, including the [[Baltic region|Baltic]] states, [[Belarus]], and [[Ukraine]]. However, the German advance was stopped barely short of Moscow in December 1941 by the [[Russian Winter]] and [[Battle of Moscow|fierce Soviet resistance]].
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-771-0366-02A, Russland, Lagebesprechung mit Hitler.jpg|thumb|With generals [[Wilhelm Keitel|Keitel]], [[Friedrich Paulus|Paulus]] and [[Walther von Brauchitsch|von Brauchitsch]], discussing the situation on the Eastern Front in October 1941]]
Some historians, such as [[Andreas Hillgruber]], have argued that ''Operation Barbarossa'' was merely one stage of Hitler's ''Stufenplan'' (stepwise plan) for world conquest, which Hitler may have formulated in the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilgruber1981&quot; /&gt; Others, such as [[John Lukacs]], suggest that Hitler did not have a ''Stufenplan'', and that the invasion of the Soviet Union was an ''ad hoc'' move in response to Britain's refusal to surrender.{{sfn|Lukacs|1998|p=133}} Lukacs argues that Churchill had hoped that the Soviet Union might enter the war on the Allied side, and so to dash this hope and force a British surrender, Hitler had started Operation Barbarossa.{{sfn|Lukacs|1998|pp=149–151}} On the other hand, [[Klaus Hildebrand]] has maintained that both Stalin and Hitler had planned to attack each other in 1941.{{sfn|Evans|1989|p=43}} Soviet troop concentrations on its western border in the spring of 1941 may have prompted Hitler to engage in a ''Flucht nach vorn'' (&quot;flight forward&quot;), to get in front of an inevitable conflict.{{sfn|Evans|1989|p=43}} [[Viktor Suvorov]], Ernst Topitsch, [[Joachim Hoffmann]], [[Ernst Nolte]], and [[David Irving]] have argued that the official reason for ''Barbarossa'' given by the German military was the real reason—a preventive war to avert an impending Soviet attack scheduled for July 1941. This theory, however, has been faulted; American historian [[Gerhard Weinberg]] once compared the advocates of the preventive war theory to believers in &quot;fairy tales&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1989&quot; /&gt;

The Wehrmacht invasion of the Soviet Union reached its peak on 2 December 1941, when the 258th Infantry Division advanced to within {{convert|15|mi|km|0}} of Moscow, close enough to see the spires of the Kremlin.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=863}} However, they were not prepared for the harsh conditions of the Russian winter, and Soviet forces drove back German troops over {{convert|320|km|mi}}.

On 7 December 1941 [[attack on Pearl Harbor|Japan attacked Pearl Harbor]], Hawaii. Four days later, Hitler's formal declaration of war against the United States officially engaged him in war against a coalition that included the world's largest empire (the British Empire), the world's greatest industrial and financial power (the United States), and the world's largest army (the Soviet Union).

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1987-0703-507, Berlin, Reichstagssitzung, Rede Adolf Hitler.jpg|thumb|left|Hitler during his speech to the Reichstag opposing the actions of American President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], 11&amp;nbsp;December 1941]]

On 18 December 1941 Himmler met with Hitler, and in response to Himmler's question &quot;What to do with the Jews of Russia?&quot;, Hitler replied &quot;''als Partisanen auszurotten''&quot; (&quot;exterminate them as partisans&quot;).{{sfn|Bauer|2000|p=5}} Israeli historian [[Yehuda Bauer]] has commented that the remark is probably as close as historians will ever get to a definitive order from Hitler for the genocide carried out during the Holocaust.{{sfn|Bauer|2000|p=5}}

In late 1942 German forces were defeated in the [[Second Battle of El Alamein|second battle of El Alamein]], thwarting Hitler's plans to seize the [[Suez Canal]] and the Middle East. In February 1943 the [[Battle of Stalingrad]] ended with the destruction of the German [[German Sixth Army|6th Army]]. Thereafter came the [[Battle of Kursk]]. Hitler's military judgment became increasingly erratic, and Germany's military and economic position deteriorated along with Hitler's health. Kershaw and others believe that Hitler may have suffered from [[Parkinson's disease]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC1999&quot; /&gt; [[Syphilis]] has also been suspected as a cause of at least some of his symptoms.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=717}}

Following the [[allied invasion of Sicily]] (Operation Husky) in 1943, Mussolini was deposed by [[Pietro Badoglio]], who surrendered to the Allies. Throughout 1943 and 1944, the Soviet Union steadily forced Hitler's armies into retreat along the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. On 6 June 1944 the Western Allied armies landed in northern France in what was one of the largest [[amphibious warfare|amphibious]] operations in history, [[Operation Overlord]]. As a result of these significant setbacks for the German army, many of its officers concluded that defeat was inevitable and that Hitler's misjudgement or denial would drag out the war and result in the [[total war|complete destruction of the country]]. Several high-profile assassination attempts against Hitler occurred during this period.

===Attempted assassinations===
{{main|Assassination attempts on Adolf Hitler}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1972-025-12, Zerstörte Lagerbaracke nach dem 20. Juli 1944.jpg|thumb|The destroyed '[[Wolf's Lair]]' barracks after the [[20 July plot]]]]

During the period of 1939–1945 there were 17 attempts or plans to assassinate Hitler, some of which proceeded to significant degrees. The most well-known attempt on Hitler's life came from within Germany during World War II and was at least partly driven by the increasing prospect of a German defeat in the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Duncan2011&quot; /&gt;

In July 1944, in the [[Operation Valkyrie]] or [[20 July plot]], [[Claus von Stauffenberg]] planted a bomb in one of [[Führer Headquarters|Hitler's headquarters]], the [[Wolfsschanze]] (Wolf's Lair) at [[Rastenburg]]. Hitler narrowly survived because someone had unknowingly pushed the briefcase that contained the bomb behind a leg of the heavy conference table. When it exploded, the table deflected much of the blast away from Hitler. Later, Hitler ordered savage reprisals, resulting in the executions of more than 4,900&amp;nbsp;people.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|loc=§29}}

===Defeat and death===
{{Main|Death of Adolf Hitler}}

By late 1944, the Red Army had driven the German army back into Western Europe, and the [[Western Allies]] were advancing into Germany. After being informed of the twin defeats&amp;nbsp;– Operation ''Wacht am Rhein'' and [[Operation Nordwind|Operation ''Nordwind'']]&amp;nbsp;– in his [[Ardennes Offensive]] at his [[Adlerhorst]] command complex, Hitler realised that Germany was about to lose the war. He did not permit an orderly retreat of his armies. His hope, buoyed by the death of [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] on 12 April 1945, was to negotiate peace with America and Britain.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=753, 763, 778, 780–781}} Acting on his view that Germany's military failures had forfeited its right to survive as a nation, Hitler ordered the destruction of all German industrial infrastructure before it could fall into Allied hands.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=774–775}} Execution of this [[scorched earth]] plan was entrusted to arms minister Albert Speer, who quietly disobeyed the order.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=774–775}}

On 20 April 1945 Hitler celebrated his 56th birthday in the ''[[Führerbunker]]'' (&quot;Führer's shelter&quot;) below the ''Reichskanzlei'' ([[Reich Chancellery]]) gardens. By 21 April, [[Georgi Zhukov]]'s [[1st Belorussian Front]] had broken through the last defences of German General [[Gotthard Heinrici]]'s [[Army Group Vistula]] during the [[Battle of the Seelow Heights]]. Facing little resistance, the Soviets advanced into the outskirts of Berlin.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=255–256}} In denial about the increasingly dire situation, Hitler placed his hopes on the units commanded by Waffen SS General [[Felix Steiner]], the ''Armeeabteilung Steiner'' (&quot;[[Army Detachment Steiner]]&quot;). Although &quot;Army Detachment Steiner&quot; was more than a corps, it was less than an army. Hitler ordered Steiner to attack the northern flank of the [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] made up of Zhukov's 1st Belorussian Front. At the same time, the German [[Ninth Army (Germany)|Ninth Army]], which had been pushed south of the salient, was ordered to attack northward in a [[pincer attack]].{{sfn|Le Tissier|2010|p=45}}

Late on 21 April, Gotthard Heinrici called [[Hans Krebs (general)|Hans Krebs]], chief of the ''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'' (Supreme Command of the Army or OKH), to inform him that Hitler's defence plans could not be implemented. Heinrici told Krebs to impress upon Hitler the need to withdraw the 9th Army.{{sfn|Le Tissier|2010|p=46}}

On 22 April, during military conference, Hitler asked about Steiner's offensive. After a long silence, Hitler was told that the attack had never been launched and that the Russians had broken through into Berlin. This news prompted Hitler to ask everyone except Wilhelm Keitel, Hans Krebs, [[Alfred Jodl]], [[Wilhelm Burgdorf]], and [[Martin Bormann]] to leave the room.{{sfn|Dollinger|1995|p=231}} Hitler then launched a tirade against the treachery and incompetence of his commanders, culminating in Hitler's declaration—for the first time—that the war was lost.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=275}} Hitler announced that he would stay in Berlin, to direct the defence of the city and then shoot himself.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=783–784}}

Before the day ended, Hitler again found fresh hope in a new plan that included General [[Walther Wenck]]'s [[Twelfth Army (Germany)|Twelfth Army]].{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=784}} This new plan had Wenck turn his army&amp;nbsp;– currently facing the Americans to the west&amp;nbsp;– and attack towards the east to relieve Berlin.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=784}} The Twelfth Army was to link up with the Ninth Army and break through to the city. Wenck did attack and made temporary contact with the Potsdam garrison. But the link with the Ninth Army was unsuccessful.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=790}}

On 23 April, Joseph Goebbels made a proclamation urging the citizens of Berlin to courageously defend the city.{{sfn|Dollinger|1995|p=231}} Also on 23 April, Göring sent a telegram from ''[[Berchtesgaden]]'' in Bavaria, arguing that since Hitler was cut off in Berlin, he, Göring, should assume leadership of Germany. Göring set a time limit, after which he would consider Hitler incapacitated.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=787}} Hitler responded angrily by having Göring arrested, and when writing his [[will (law)|will]] on 29 April, he removed Göring from all his positions in the government.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=787, 795}}{{sfn|Butler|Young|1989|pp=227–228}} Hitler appointed General der Artillerie [[Helmuth Weidling]] as the commander of the Berlin Defence Area, replacing Lieutenant General (''Generalleutnant'') [[Helmuth Reymann]] and Colonel (''[[Oberst]]'') [[Ernst Kaether]]. Hitler appointed Waffen-SS [[Brigadeführer]] [[Wilhelm Mohnke]] the Battle Commander (&quot;Kommandant&quot;) for the defence of the government district (Zitadelle sector) that included the Reich Chancellery and Führerbunker.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=42–43}}

On 27 April, Berlin became completely cut off from the rest of Germany. As the Soviet forces closed in, Hitler's followers urged him to flee to the mountains of Bavaria to make a last stand in the [[national redoubt]]. However, Hitler was determined to either live or die in the capital.

On 28 April, Hitler discovered that Himmler was trying to discuss surrender terms with the Western Allies (through the Swedish diplomat Count [[Folke Bernadotte]]).{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=791}} Hitler ordered Himmler's arrest and had [[Hermann Fegelein]] (Himmler's SS representative at Hitler's HQ in Berlin) shot.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=792, 795}} Adding to Hitler's woes was Wenck's report that his Twelfth Army had been forced back along the entire front and that his forces could no longer support Berlin.

[[File:Stars &amp; Stripes &amp; Hitler Dead2.jpg|left|thumb|Front page of the U.S. Armed Forces newspaper, ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]'', 2&amp;nbsp;May 1945]]

After midnight on 29 April, Hitler married [[Eva Braun]] in a small civil ceremony in a map room within the Führerbunker. [[Antony Beevor]] stated that after Hitler hosted a modest wedding breakfast with his new wife, he then took secretary [[Traudl Junge]] to another room and dictated [[last will and testament of Adolf Hitler|his last will and testament]].{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=343}}{{#tag:ref | [https://www.mi5.gov.uk/output/hitlers-last-days.html Hitler's last days: &quot;Hitler's will and marriage&quot;] on the website of [[MI5]], using the sources available to Trevor Roper (a WWII MI5 agent and historian/author of ''The Last Days of Hitler''), records the marriage as taking place after Hitler had dictated his last will and testament. | group=lower-alpha}} Hitler signed these documents at 4:00&amp;nbsp;am. The event was witnessed and documents signed by Hans Krebs, Wilhelm Burgdorf, Joseph Goebbels, and Martin Bormann.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=795}} Hitler then retired to bed.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=950}} That afternoon, Hitler was informed of the assassination of Italian dictator Benito Mussolini, which presumably increased his determination to avoid capture.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=798}}

On 30 April 1945, after intense [[Urban warfare|street-to-street combat]], when Soviet troops were within a block or two of the Reich Chancellery, Hitler and Braun committed suicide; Braun bit into a [[cyanide]] capsule{{sfn|Linge|2009|p=199}} and Hitler shot himself with his 7.65&amp;nbsp;mm [[Walther PPK]] pistol.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=160–180}}{{#tag:ref|&quot;... Günsche stated he entered the study to inspect the bodies, and observed Hitler ...sat...sunken over, with blood dripping out of his right temple. He had shot himself with his own pistol, a PPK 7.65.&quot;{{sfn | Fischer | 2008 | p=47}}|group=lower-alpha}}{{#tag:ref|&quot;...Blood dripped from a bullet hole in his right temple...&quot;{{sfn | Kershaw | 2008 | p=955}}|group=lower-alpha}}{{#tag:ref|There have been different accounts citing the cause of his death with one alternative suggesting that Hitler died by a self-inflicted gunshot, while biting down on a cyanide capsule of poison. &quot;... we have a fair answer ... to the version of ... Russian author Lev Bezymenski ... Hitler did shoot himself and did bite into the cyanide capsule, just as Professor Haase had clearly and repeatedly instructed ...&quot;{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|pp=322–323}}|group=lower-alpha}} Hitler had at various times contemplated suicide, and the Walther was the same pistol that his niece, [[Geli Raubal]], had used in her suicide in 1931.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelken1997&quot; /&gt; The lifeless bodies of Hitler and Eva Braun were carried up the stairs and through the bunker's emergency exit to the bombed-out garden behind the Reich Chancellery, where they were placed in a bomb crater&lt;ref name=&quot;Trevor-Roper1992&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Kershaw|2000b|pp=829–831}} and doused with petrol. The corpses were set on fire{{sfn|Linge|2009|p=200}} and the [[Red Army]] shelling continued.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=799–800}}

On 2 May, Berlin surrendered, and there were conflicting reports about what happened to Hitler's remains. Records in the Soviet archives— obtained after the fall of the Soviet Union—showed that the remains of Hitler, Eva Braun, Joseph and [[Magda Goebbels]], the six [[Goebbels children]], General Hans Krebs, and Hitler's dogs, were repeatedly buried and exhumed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vinogradov2005&quot; /&gt; On 4 April 1970 a Soviet KGB team with detailed burial charts secretly exhumed five wooden boxes which had been buried at the [[SMERSH]] facility in Magdeburg. The remains from the boxes were thoroughly burned and crushed, after which the ashes were thrown into the Biederitz river, a tributary of the nearby [[Elbe]].{{sfn|Vinogradov|2005|pp=333–336}}

According to the Russian Federal Security Service, a fragment of human skull stored in its archives and displayed to the public in a 2000 exhibition came from Hitler's remains. However, the authenticity of the skull fragment was challenged by historians and researchers,&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCskull2000&quot; /&gt; and DNA analysis conducted in 2009 showed the skull fragment to be that of a woman. Analysis of the sutures between the skull plates indicated that it belonged to a 20–40-year-old individual.&lt;ref name=&quot;DailyMailSkull2009&quot; /&gt;

==Legacy==
{{See|Consequences of German Nazism|Neo-Nazism}}
[[File:Mahnstein.JPG|thumb|Outside the building in [[Braunau am Inn]], Austria where Adolf Hitler was born is a [[Hitler birthplace memorial stone|memorial stone]] warning of the horrors of World War II]]
Hitler's policies and orders resulted in the death of approximately 40 million people,&lt;ref name=&quot;DelTesta2003&quot; /&gt; including about 27&amp;nbsp;million in the [[Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dear2001&quot; /&gt; The actions of Hitler, and Hitler's ideology, [[Nazism]], are almost universally regarded as gravely immoral.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000a|pp=1–6}} Historians, philosophers, and politicians have often applied the word ''[[evil]]'' to describe Hitler's ideology and its outcomes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Welch2001&quot; /&gt; Historical and [[Hitler in popular culture|cultural portrayals of Hitler]] in the west are overwhelmingly condemnatory. In Germany and Austria, the [[Holocaust denial|denial of the Holocaust]] and the display of [[Nazi symbolism|Nazi symbols]] such as swastikas are prohibited by law.

Outside of Hitler's birthplace in Braunau am Inn, Austria, the [[Memorial Stone Against War and Fascism]] is engraved with the following message:
{{col-begin|width=65%}}
{{col-break}}
&lt;poem&gt;

Für Frieden Freiheit
Und Demokratie
Nie Wieder Faschismus
Millionen Tote Mahnen&lt;/poem&gt;
{{col-break}}
&lt;poem&gt;Loosely translated, it reads:

For peace, freedom
and democracy
never again fascism
millions of dead remind [us]&quot;&lt;/poem&gt;
{{col-end}}

Following World War II, the [[toothbrush moustache]] fell out of favour in the West because of its strong association with Hitler, which earned it the nickname &quot;Hitler moustache&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohen2007&quot; /&gt; The use of the name &quot;[[Adolf]]&quot; also declined in post-war years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell-BehindTheName&quot; /&gt;

Hitler and his legacy are occasionally described in more neutral or even favourable terms. Former [[Egypt]]ian President [[Anwar El Sadat]] spoke of his 'admiration' of Hitler in 1953, when he was a young man, but it is possible that Sadat's views were shaped mainly by his anti-British sentiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Finklestone1996&quot; /&gt; [[Bal Thackeray]], leader of the right-wing [[Hindu nationalist]] [[Shiv Sena]] party in the Indian state of the [[Maharashtra]], declared in 1995 that he was an admirer of Hitler.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsiaWeek1995&quot; /&gt; German historian [[Friedrich Meinecke]] said that Hitler's life &quot;is one of the great examples of the singular and incalculable power of personality in historical life&quot;.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=6}}

==Religious views==
{{Main|Adolf Hitler's religious views}}
Hitler's parents were [[Roman Catholics]], but after leaving home he never attended [[Mass (liturgy)|Mass]] or received the [[Sacraments of the Catholic Church|sacraments]].{{sfn|Rißmann|2001|pp=94–96}} Hitler favoured aspects of [[Protestantism]] that suited his own views. However, he adopted some elements of the Catholic Church's hierarchical organisation, [[liturgy]], and phraseology in his politics.{{sfn|Rißmann|2001|p=96}}{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=219}} After his move to Germany, where Catholic and Protestant churches are largely financed through a [[church tax]], Hitler did not leave his church, leading the historian [[Richard Steigmann-Gall]] to conclude that Hitler &quot;can be classified as Catholic&quot;,{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|p=XV}} but that &quot;nominal church membership is a very unreliable gauge of actual piety in this context.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Steigmann-Gall2007&quot; /&gt;

In public, Hitler often praised Christian heritage and German Christian culture, and professed a belief in an &quot;Aryan&quot; [[Jesus Christ]]—a Jesus who fought against the Jews.{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|pp=27, 108}} In his speeches and publications, Hitler spoke of his interpretation of Christianity as a central motivation for his antisemitism, stating that &quot;As a Christian I have no duty to allow myself to be cheated, but I have the duty to be a fighter for truth and justice.&quot;{{sfn|Hitler|1942}}{{Page needed|date=October 2011}}{{sfn|Hitler|1973|p=23}} In private, Hitler was more critical of traditional Christianity, considering it a religion fit only for slaves; he admired the power of Rome but maintained a severe hostility towards its teaching.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=219, 389}} Hitler's critical views on Catholicism resonated with [[Julius Streicher|Streicher]]'s contention that the Catholic establishment was allying itself with the Jews.{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|p=65}}{{#tag:ref|He is referring to [[Otto Wagener]], ''Hitler: Memoirs of a Confidant'', Henry Ashby Turner, ed. (New Haven, 1985), p. 65.|group=lower-alpha}} In light of these private statements, for [[John S. Conway]] and many other historians, it is beyond doubt that Hitler held a &quot;fundamental antagonism&quot; towards the Christian churches.{{sfn|Conway|1968|p=3}} However, some researchers have questioned the authenticity of Hitler's private statements; for instance, [[Hermann Rauschning]]'s ''Hitler speaks'' is considered by most historians to be an invention.{{sfn|Rißmann|2001|p=22}}{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|pp=28–29}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1987-004-09A, Amin al Husseini und Adolf Hitler.jpg|right|thumb|210px|Hitler meeting the [[Grand Mufti of Jerusalem]], December 1941]]
In political relations with the churches in Germany, Hitler adopted a strategy &quot;that suited his immediate political purposes&quot;.{{sfn|Conway|1968|p=3}} According to a US [[Office of Strategic Services]] report, Hitler had a general plan, even before his rise to power, to destroy the influence of Christian Churches within the Reich.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharkey2002&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonney2001&quot; /&gt; The report titled &quot;The Nazi Master Plan&quot; stated, &quot;the destruction of Christianity was explicitly recognised as a purpose of the National Socialist movement&quot; from the start, but &quot;considerations of expedience made it impossible&quot; to express this extreme position publicly.&lt;ref name=&quot;OSS1945&quot; /&gt; His intention, according to [[Alan Bullock]], was to wait until the war was over to destroy the influence of Christianity.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=219, 389}}

Hitler for a time advocated a form of the Christian faith he called &quot;[[Positive Christianity]]&quot;,{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|p=passim}}{{sfn|Overy|2005|p=278}} a belief system purged of what he objected to in orthodox Christianity, and featuring racist elements. By 1940, however, Hitler had abandoned advocating even the [[syncretism|syncretist]] idea of a positive Christianity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Poewe2006&quot; /&gt; Hitler maintained that the &quot;terrorism in religion is, to put it briefly, of a Jewish dogma, which Christianity has universalised and whose effect is to sow trouble and confusion in men's minds.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler1942&quot; /&gt;{{page needed|date=October 2011}}

Hitler articulated his view on the relationship between religion and national identity as &quot;We do not want any other god than Germany itself. It is essential to have fanatical faith and hope and love in and for Germany&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heiden1935&quot; /&gt;

Hitler expressed admiration for the [[Muslim]] military tradition. [[Stanley G. Payne]] wrote:

{{quote|Hitler generally had a high opinion of Islam and once proclaimed it the best of religions because of its theological simplicity and emphasis on holy war. ... Hitler expressed regret that Islam had not swept over all western Europe. Had it replaced Christianity in Germany, the innate racial superiority of the Germans in conjunction with Islam would have enabled them to conquer much of the world during the Middle Ages.{{sfn|Payne|2008|p=171}}}}

==Attitude towards occultism==
Some researchers suggest that Hitler did not follow esoteric ideas, occultism, or [[Ariosophy]],{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=219, 389}} and Hitler does ridicule such beliefs in ''Mein Kampf''.{{sfn|Steigmann-Gall|2003|p=passim}}{{sfn|Overy|2005|p=282}}&lt;!--see also Goodrick-Clarke, the occult roots.. p. 202; Rißmann, p. 123--&gt; Others have suggested that Hitler's views, particularly on race, had been strongly influenced by works that promulgated a mystical superiority of the Germans; these works included the occult and antisemitic magazine ''[[Ostara (magazine)|Ostara]]'',{{sfn|Rosenbaum|1998|p=333}} whose publisher [[Lanz von Liebenfels]] claimed that Hitler had visited him in 1909 and had praised his work. Historians are divided on the question of the reliability of von Liebenfels' claim.{{sfn|Rißmann|2001|p=122}} [[Nicholas Goodrick-Clarke]] considers his account reliable, [[Brigitte Hamann]] leaves the question open{{sfn|Rißmann|2001|p=249 (footnote 539)}} and Kershaw, although questioning the degree to which Hitler was influenced by it, notes that, &quot;Most likely, Hitler did read ''Ostara'', along with other racist pulp which was prominent on Vienna newspaper stands.&quot;{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=50–51}} Kershaw notes that it is usually accepted that Hitler did read and was influenced by this occult publication, pointing to Hitler's account of his conversion to antisemitism after reading antisemitic pamphlets.{{sfn|Kershaw|1999|pp=50–51}}

==Health==
Hitler's health has frequently been the subject of speculation. It has been suggested that he suffered from [[irritable bowel syndrome]], [[skin lesion]]s, [[irregular heartbeat]], [[Parkinson's disease]],{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=717}} [[syphilis]],{{sfn|Bullock|1962|p=717}} [[tinnitus]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Redlich2000&quot; /&gt; and [[Asperger syndrome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald2004&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fries2009&quot; /&gt; Hitler had dental problems—his personal dentist, [[Hugo Blaschke]], fitted a large [[bridge (dentistry)|dental bridge]] to Hitler's upper jaw in 1933, and in 1944, Blaschke removed the left rear section of the bridge to treat an infection of Hitler's gums that coincided with a [[sinusitis|sinus infection]].{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=229–230}}

Hitler followed a vegetarian diet, and never ate meat.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=388}} At social events Hitler sometimes gave graphic accounts of the slaughter of animals in an effort to make his dinner guests shun meat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson1998&quot; /&gt; A fear of cancer (from which his mother died) is the most widely cited reason for Hitler's dietary habits. An [[antivivisection]]ist, Hitler may have followed his selective diet out of a profound concern for animals.{{sfn|Dietrich|2010|p=172}} [[Martin Bormann]] had a greenhouse constructed near the ''[[Berghof (Hitler)|Berghof]]'' (near ''[[Berchtesgaden]]'') to ensure a steady supply of fresh fruit and vegetables for Hitler throughout the war.

Hitler was a non-smoker and promoted aggressive anti-smoking campaigns throughout Germany. (See [[Anti-tobacco movement in Nazi Germany]].){{sfn|Toland|1992|p=741}} Hitler strongly despised alcohol.{{sfn|Dietrich|2010|p=171}}

===Syphilis===
Since the 1870s it was common for the [[völkisch movement|völkisch right]] to associate Jews with diseases such as syphilis. In ''Mein Kampf'', Hitler wrote about the temptation of prostitution and the spreading of syphilis, specifically in volume 1, chapter 10, &quot;Causes of the Collapse&quot;, where he called it a &quot;Jewish disease&quot;.{{sfn|Hitler|1999|loc=Volume 1, Chapter 10}} This has led to speculation he may have contracted the disease himself.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=392}}

During the last years of his life, Hitler suffered from tremors and irregular heartbeat, which could have been symptoms of tertiary (late-stage) syphilis. Journalist [[Joseph Kessel]] reports that in the winter of 1942 renowned [[masseur]] [[Felix Kersten]] was shown a top-secret 26-page report that indicated that Hitler had contracted syphilis in his youth and was treated for it at a hospital in [[Pasewalk]], Germany. Hitler first displayed late-stage symptoms in 1937, and by the start of 1942, progressive syphilitic paralysis (''[[Tabes dorsalis]]'') was occurring. According to the report, Hitler was treated by [[Theodor Morell|Morell]], and his disease was kept a state secret.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kessel2004&quot; /&gt; The only people privy to the report's content were Bormann and Göring.

===Monorchism===
{{See also|Hitler's possible monorchism}}
It has been alleged that Hitler had [[monorchism]], the medical condition of having only one [[testicle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams1987&quot; /&gt; Hitler's personal doctor, Johan Jambor, supposedly described this condition to a priest whose records were uncovered in 2008, 23 years after the doctor's death.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peake2008&quot; /&gt;

Soviet journalist Lev Bezymensky stated in a 1967 book that the [[Death of Adolf Hitler|Soviet autopsy]] of Hitler's remains revealed his left testicle was missing,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bezymenski1968&quot; /&gt; but he later admitted to have falsified this claim.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bezymenski1995&quot; /&gt; Hitler had been examined by many doctors throughout his life, and no mention of this condition has been discovered. Records show that he was wounded in 1916 during the [[Battle of the Somme]], with some sources describing his injury as a wound to the groin.

===Parkinson's disease===
It has been speculated Hitler had [[Parkinson's disease]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC1999&quot; /&gt; Newsreel footage of Hitler shows tremors of his hand and a shuffling walk, which began before the war and worsened towards the end of his life. Morell treated Hitler with a drug that was commonly used in 1945 to treat the condition. [[Ernst-Günther Schenck]] and several other doctors who met Hitler in the last weeks of his life each formed a diagnosis of  Parkinson's disease.{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|p=37}}

===Other complaints===
From the 1930s, Hitler suffered from stomach pains. In 1936, a non-cancerous [[polyp (medicine)|polyp]] was removed from his throat and he developed [[eczema]] on his legs.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000b|p=36}} He suffered [[ruptured eardrum]]s as a result of the [[20 July plot]] bomb blast in 1944, and two hundred wood splinters had to be removed from his legs.{{sfn|Linge|2009|p=156}} Hitler's [[otology|otologist]] observed that Hitler had developed tinnitus after the Röhm Putsch, and considered it [[psychogenic pain|psychogenic]] in origin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Redlich2000&quot; /&gt; Hitler treated the condition with the prescription-free lipid [[lecithin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Redlich2000&quot; /&gt;

===Addiction to amphetamine===
Hitler began using [[amphetamine]] occasionally after 1937 and became addicted to the drug after the late summer of 1942.{{sfn|Heston|Heston|1980|pp=125–142}} Albert Speer linked Hitler's use of amphetamines to his increasingly inflexible decision making (for example, never to allow military retreats).{{sfn|Heston|Heston|1980|pp=11–20}}

===Historians' views===
German historian [[Hans-Ulrich Wehler]] dismisses theories that link the rise of Nazi Germany to Hitler's medical conditions and mental states. The theories about Hitler's medical condition are difficult to prove, and according them too much weight may have the effect of attributing many of the events and consequences of the Third Reich to the possibly impaired physical health of one individual.{{sfn|Kershaw|2000a|p=72}} Kershaw agrees that it is better to take a broader view of German history by seeking to examine what social forces led to the Third Reich and its policies rather than to pursue narrow explanations for the Holocaust and World War II based on only one person.{{sfn|Evans|1989}}{{page needed|date=October 2011}}

==Family==
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F051673-0059, Adolf Hitler und Eva Braun auf dem Berghof.jpg|thumb|right|Hitler with his long-time mistress [[Eva Braun]], whom he married 29 April 1945]]
{{Main|Hitler family|Sexuality of Adolf Hitler}}
To the public, Hitler promoted his own image as that of a man without a domestic life, dedicated entirely to his political mission.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=130}}{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=563}} He was engaged to [[Mimi Reiter]] in the 1920s,{{citation needed|date=November 2011}} and later had a mistress, [[Eva Braun]].{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=395}}

In September 1931 Hitler's niece, [[Geli Raubal]], committed suicide with Hitler's gun in his Munich apartment. Geli was believed to be in a romantic relationship with Hitler, and it is believed that her death was a source of deep, lasting pain for him.{{sfn|Bullock|1962|pp=393–394}}

[[Paula Hitler]], the last living member of Adolf Hitler's immediate family, died in 1960. The most prominent and longest-living closest relative was Adolf Hitler's nephew, [[William Patrick Hitler]], the son of Adolf's half-brother, Alois Hitler Jr.

Over the years, various investigative reporters have attempted to track down other living relatives of Hitler. Many are presumed to be living inconspicuous lives and have changed their last name.

[[File:Hitlerfamilytree.png|thumb|350px|Adolf Hitler's [[family tree]]]]
* [[Klara Hitler]], mother
* [[Alois Hitler]], father
* [[Alois Hitler, Jr.]], half-brother
* [[Angela Hitler|Angela Hitler Raubal]], half-sister
* [[Bridget Dowling]], sister-in-law
* [[Eva Braun]], mistress and then wife
* [[Geli Raubal]], niece
* [[Gretl Braun]], sister-in-law through Hitler's marriage to Eva Braun
* [[Heinz Hitler]], nephew
* [[Hermann Fegelein]], brother-in-law through Hitler's marriage to Eva Braun
* [[Ilse Braun]], sister-in-law through Hitler's marriage to Eva Braun
* [[Johann Georg Hiedler]], presumed grandfather
* [[Johann Nepomuk Hiedler]], maternal great-grandfather, presumed great uncle and possibly Hitler's true paternal grandfather
* [[Leo Rudolf Raubal Jr|Leo Raubal Jr]], nephew
* [[Maria Schicklgruber]], grandmother
* [[Paula Hitler]], sister
* [[William Patrick Hitler]], nephew

==Hitler in media==
[[File:Adolf Hitler at Berchtesgaden.ogg|thumb|thumbtime=3|Video of Adolf Hitler at [[Berchtesgaden]] (c. 1941)]]
[[File:Hitler Mannerheim.png|thumb|upright|Hitler and [[Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim|Baron Mannerheim]], [[Marshal of Finland]] (June 1942)]]

{{See also|Adolf Hitler in popular culture}}

===Oratory and rallies===
{{Main|List of speeches given by Adolf Hitler}}

Hitler honed his oratory skills by giving speeches to military audiences in 1919 and 1920. He became adept at using [[populism|populist]] themes targeted to his audience, including the use of popular [[scapegoat]]s who could be blamed for the economic hardships of his listeners.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=376}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Frauenfeld1937&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goebbels1936&quot; /&gt; He had personal magnetism, hypnotic eyes, and an exceptionally good memory, traits he used to advantage while engaged in public speaking.{{sfn|Bullock|1999|p=377}}

===Recorded in private conversation===
Hitler visited Finnish [[Field Marshal]] [[Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim|Mannerheim]] on 4 June 1942. During the visit, an engineer of the Finnish broadcasting company [[YLE]], Thor Damen, recorded Hitler and Mannerheim in conversation. Damen did so secretly, since Hitler did not permit recordings of him off the record.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moring2004&quot; /&gt; The 11½ minutes-long recording is the only audio record of Hitler in casual conversation.&lt;ref name=&quot;YLE2006&quot; /&gt; Most of the recording is a monologue of Hitler, which he delivers in a slightly excited, but detached manner. Hitler concedes that he had underestimated the Soviet Union's ability to conduct effective warfare. Audio recordings of Hitler and Mannerheim's [http://www.archive.org/details/OnlyKnownRecordingOfHitlerSpeakingInAnUnofficialTone-PublicVersion public] and [http://www.archive.org/details/OnlyKnownRecordingOfHitlerSpeakingInAnUnofficialTone private] talk ([http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o64QOynq0_Q w/English text]) are available online.

===Documentaries during the Third Reich===
Documentary films were another propaganda tool for Hitler. Hitler was involved and appeared in a series of films by the pioneering filmmaker [[Leni Riefenstahl]] via [[Universum Film AG]] (UFA):
* ''[[Der Sieg des Glaubens]]'' (''Victory of Faith'', 1933)
* ''[[Triumph of the Will|Triumph des Willens]]'' (''Triumph of the Will'', 1934), co-produced by Hitler
* ''[[Tag der Freiheit: Unsere Wehrmacht]]'' (''Day of Freedom: Our Armed Forces'', 1935)
* ''[[Olympia (1938 film)|Olympia]]'' (1938)

Hitler was the central figure of the first three films; they focused on the [[Nuremberg rally|party rallies]] of the respective years and are considered propaganda films. For example, [[Leni Riefenstahl]]'s ''[[Triumph of the Will]]'', shot during the 1934 Nuremberg Rally, shows Hitler from high and low angles, and only twice head-on. Some of the people in the film were paid actors, but most of the participants were not. Hitler also featured prominently in the ''Olympia'' film.

===Television===
As a prominent politician, Hitler was featured in many newsreels. His attendance at public functions, including the 1936 Olympic Games and Nuremberg Rallies, appeared on television broadcasts made between 1935 and 1939. These events, along with other programming that highlighted activity by public officials, were often repeated in public viewing rooms. Samples from a number of surviving television films from Nazi Germany were included in the 1999 documentary ''Das Fernsehen unter dem Hakenkreuz (Television Under the Swastika)''.

==See also==
{{Portal box|World War II|Fascism}}
* [[Führermuseum]]
* [[Mein Kampf#Online versions of Mein Kampf|''Mein Kampf'' (online versions)]]
* [[Poison Kitchen]]
* [[Vorbunker]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em|group=lower-alpha}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|20em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;citizenship&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.ns-archiv.de/personen/hitler/oesterreich/staatsbuergerschaft.php
| title = Hitler ersucht um Entlassung aus der österreichischen Staatsangehörigkeit
| trans_title = Hitler's official application to end his Austrian citizenship
| date = 7 April 1925
| publisher= NS-Archiv
| language = German
| accessdate=2011-10-16
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Niewyk2000&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last1 = Niewyk
| first1 = Donald L.
| last2 = Nicosia
| first2 = Francis R.
| title = The Columbia Guide to the Holocaust
| year = 2000
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| location = New York
| isbn = 978-0-231-11200-0
| page = 45
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hancock2004&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Hancock
| first = Ian
| authorlink = Ian Hancock
| editor1-last = Stone
| editor1-first = Dan
| title = The Historiography of the Holocaust
| year = 2004
| publisher = Palgrave Macmillan
| location = New York; Basingstoke
| isbn = 978-0-333-99745-1
| chapter = Romanies and the Holocaust: A Reevaluation and an Overview
| pages = 383–396
| url=http://radoc.net/radoc.php?doc=art_e_holocaust_porrajmos&amp;lang=en&amp;articles=true
| accessdate = 2011-06-07
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;RosenbaumR1999&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Rosenbaum
| first = Ron
| authorlink = Ron Rosenbaum
| title = [[Explaining Hitler: The Search for the Origins of His Evil]]
| year = 1999
| publisher = Harper Perennial
| isbn = 978-0-06-095339-3
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCNews2011&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Adolf Hitler's Austrian hometown revokes honour title
| url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-14084913
| publisher = [[BBC News Online]]
| date = 8 July 2011
| accessdate = 2011-07-08
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fest1977&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Fest
| first = Joachim
| title = Hitler
| year = 1977
| origyear = 1973
| publisher = Penguin
| location = Harmondsworth
| isbn = 9780140219838
| page = 32
| quote = ... the description of the allegedly prolonged conflict, which Hitler dramatized as a grim struggle between two men of iron will, has since been exposed as pure fantasy.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lipstadt2011&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Lipstadt
| first = Deborah E.
| title = The Eichmann Trial
| year = 2011
| publisher = Random House
| location = New York
| isbn = 978-0-8052-4260-7
| page = 272
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bendersky2000&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Bendersky
| first = Joseph W
| title = A History of Nazi Germany: 1919–1945
| year = 2000
| publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
| page = 26
| isbn=978-1-4422-1003-5
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ryschka2008&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Ryschka
| first = Birgit
| title = Constructing and Deconstructing National Identity: Dramatic Discourse in Tom Murphy's the Patriot Game and Felix Mitterer's in Der Löwengrube
| date = 29 September 2008
| publisher = Peter Lang
| isbn = 978-3-631-58111-7
| page = 35
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=Vsl6mwMXl4YC&amp;pg=PA35
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Beller2000&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Beller
| first = Steven
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=pKlWyYA26GMC&amp;pg=PA534
| title = Brigitte Hamann: ''Hitler's Wien: Lehrjahre eines Diktators'' (Munich: R. Piper, 1996)
| editor1-first = Günter
| editor1-last = Bischof
| editor2-first = Anton
| editor2-last = Pelinka
| editor3-first = Dieter
| editor3-last = Stiefel
| journal = The Marshall Plan in Austria
| series = Contemporary Austrian Studies
| volume = 8
| publisher = Transaction Publishers
| year = 2000
| pages = 533–543, 534
| isbn = 9780765806796
| quote = Hitler chose to stress in ''Mein Kampf'' the role Vienna played in prompting his &quot;conversion&quot;, even though, as Hamann emphasizes and illustrates with impressively marshalled evidence, Hitler had Jewish business partners, Jewish discussion partners, and Jewish patrons. He even attended the musical salon of a Jewish family, the Jahodas, and was never reported by a credible witness as having uttered any anti-Semitic remarks, indeed, is reported as having said many positive things about the Jews.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Haynes2010&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Haynes
| first = Stephen R.
| title = Christianity
| editor1-first = Peter
| editor1-last = Hayes
| editor2-first = John K.
| editor2-last = Roth
| journal = The Oxford Handbook of Holocaust Studies
| year = 2010
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| location = London; New York
| series = Oxford Handbooks
| pages = 620–634, 626–627
| isbn = 9780199211869
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Field1981&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Field
| first = Geoffrey G.
| title = Evangelist of Race: The Germanic Vision of Houston Stewart Chamberlain
| year = 1981
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| location = New York
| pages = 436–438
| isbn = 9780231048606
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Steiner1976&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Steiner
| first = John Michael
| title = Power Politics and Social Change in National Socialist Germany: A Process of Escalation into Mass Destruction
| year = 1976
| publisher = Mouton
| location = The Hague
| page = 392
| isbn = 9027976511
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Telegraph2008&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Jamieson
| first = Alastair
| title = Nazi leader Hitler really did have only one ball
| newspaper = [[The Daily Telegraph]]
| date = 19 November 2008
| url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/newstopics/howaboutthat/3481932/Nazi-leader-Hitler-really-did-have-only-one-ball.html
| accessdate = 2011-05-27
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;FestHitler&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Fest
| first = Joachim
| title = Hitler
| pages = 116–119
}}&lt;!--Please provide a publisher name and date. Thanks --&gt;
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stackelberg2007&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Stackelberg
| first = Roderick
| title = The Routledge Companion to Nazi Germany
| year = 2007
| publisher = Routledge
| location = New York, NY
| page = 9
| isbn = 978-0-415-30860-1
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitcham1996&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Mitcham
| first = Samuel W.
| title = Why Hitler?: The Genesis of the Nazi Reich
| year = 1996
| publisher = Praeger
| location = Westport, Conn
| page = 67
| isbn = 9780275954857
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MunichCourt1924&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| title = Der Hitler-Prozeß vor dem Volksgericht in München
| trans_title = The Hitler Trial Before the People's Court in Munich
| year = 1924
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fulda2009&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Fulda
| first = Bernhard
| title = Press and Politics in the Weimar Republic
| year = 2009
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| isbn = 978-0-19-954778-4
| pages = 68–69
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=StNY-71yVXQC&amp;pg=PA68
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Spiro2008&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Spiro
| first = Jonathan Peter
| title = Defending the Master Race: Conservation, Eugenics, and the Legacy of Madison Grant
| year = 2008
| publisher = University Press of Vermont
| location = Lebanon, NH
| isbn = 978-1-58465-715-6
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=4NoE2VyfN70C&amp;pg=PA357
| accessdate = 2010-01-25
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolb2005&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Kolb
| first = Eberhard
| authorlink = Eberhard Kolb
| title = The Weimar Republic
| origyear = 1984
| year = 2005
| isbn = 9780415344418
| publisher = Routledge
| location = London; New York
| pages = 224–225}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kolb1988&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Kolb
| first = Eberhard
| year = 1988
| origyear = 1984
| title = The Weimar Republic
| location = New York
| publisher = Routledge
| page = 105
| isbn = 9780415090773
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinrichs2007&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Hinrichs
| first = Per
| publisher = Spiegel Online
| title = Des Führers Pass, Hitlers Einbürgerung
| trans_title = Hitler's Naturalisation: Pass the Leader
| date = 10 March 2007
| language = German
| url = http://www.spiegel.de/panorama/zeitgeschichte/0,1518,470844,00.html
| accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Industrialists1932&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Eingabe der Industriellen an Hindenburg vom November 1932
| trans_title = Letter of the industrialists to Hindenburg, November 1932
| publisher=Glasnost–Archiv
| url=http://www.glasnost.de/hist/ns/eingabe.html
| accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;FoxNews2003&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Documents: Bush's Grandfather Directed Bank Tied to Man Who Funded Hitler
| date = 17 October 2003
| publisher = Fox News
| url = http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,100474,00.html
| accessdate = 2011-10-16
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Potsdam1933&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = 1933&amp;nbsp;– Day of Potsdam
| publisher = City of Potsdam
| url = http://www.potsdam.de/cms/beitrag/10000945/33981/
| accessdate= 2011-06-13
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1934&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Germany: Second Revolution?
| date = 2 July 1934
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,754321,00.html
| publisher = ''Time'' magazine
| accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans2003&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Evans
| first = Richard J.
| title = The Coming of The Third Reich
| year = 2003
| publisher = Penguin Group
| isbn = 978-0-14-303469-8
| pages = 350–374
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimes1932&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Birchall
| first = Frederick T.
| title = Hitler Endorsed by 9 to 1 in Poll on His Dictatorship, But Opposition is Doubled: Absolute Power is Won
| date = 20 August 1932
| work = New York Times
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/big/0819.html
| accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wistrich2002&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Wistrich
| first = Robert S.
| authorlink = Robert S. Wistrich
| title = Who's Who in Nazi Germany
| year = 2002
| publisher = Routledge
| location = New York
| page = 193
| isbn = 978-0-415-12723-3
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts1975&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Roberts
| first = Martin
| title = The New Barbarism&amp;nbsp;– A Portrait of Europe 1900–1973
| year = 1975
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| isbn = 978-0-19-913225-6
}}{{Page needed|date=October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Martel1999&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Overy
| first = Richard
| authorlink = Richard Overy
| editor1-first = Gordon
| editor1-last = Martel
| title = The Origins of the Second World War Reconsidered
| year = 1999
| publisher = Routledge
| location = London
| chapter = Misjudging Hitler
| pages = 93–115
| isbn = 978-0-415-16324-8
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Aigner1985&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Aigner
| first = Dietrich
| editor1-last = Koch
| editor1-first = H.W
| title = Aspects of the Third Reich
| year = 1985
| publisher = Macmillan
| location = London
| chapter = Hitler's ultimate aims&amp;nbsp;– a programme of world dominion?
| page = 264
| isbn = 9780312057268
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gellately1996&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Gellately
| first = Robert
| title = Reviewed work(s): Vom Generalplan Ost zum Generalsiedlungsplan by Czeslaw Madajczyk. Der &quot;Generalplan Ost.&quot; Hauptlinien der nationalsozialistischen Planungs- und Vernichtungspolitik by Mechtild Rössler; Sabine Schleiermacher
| journal = Central European History
| volume = 29
| issue = 2
| year = 1996
| pages = 270–274
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Steinberg1995&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Steinberg
| first = Jonathan
| title = The Third Reich Reflected: German Civil Administration in the Occupied Soviet Union, 1941-4
| journal = The English Historical Review
| year = 1995
| month = June
| volume = 110
| issue = 437
| pages = 620–651
| oclc = 83655937
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;YadVashem&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = How many Jews were murdered in the Holocaust? How do we know? Do we have their names?
| publisher = [[Yad Vashem]]
| url = http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_holocaust/faqs/answers/faq_3.html
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080519014604/http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_holocaust/faqs/answers/faq_3.html
| archivedate = 19 May 2008
| accessdate= 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;HolocaustMemorialMuseum&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Introduction to the Holocaust
| publisher = [[United States Holocaust Memorial Museum]]
| url = http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/article.php?lang=en&amp;ModuleId=10005143
| accessdate = 2011-10-17
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldhagen1996&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Goldhagen
| first = Daniel
| authorlink = Daniel Goldhagen
| title = [[Hitler's Willing Executioners|Hitler's Willing Executioners: Ordinary Germans and the Holocaust]]
| year = 1996
| publisher = Knopf
| location = New York
| page = 290
| isbn = 9780679446958
| quote = 2.8 million young, healthy Soviet POWs [killed by the Germans,] mainly by starvation ... in less than eight months [of 1941–42, before] the decimation of Soviet POWs ... was stopped [and the Germans] began to use them as laborers
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Downing2005&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Downing
| first = David
| title = The Nazi Death Camps
| year = 2005
| publisher = Gareth Stevens
| series = World Almanac Library of the Holocaust
| page = 33
| isbn = 978-0-8368-5947-8
| url=http://books.google.com/?id=SNN48OKqUdsC&amp;pg=PA33
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Naimark2002&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Naimark
| first = Norman M.
| year = 2002
| title = Fires of Hatred: Ethnic Cleansing in Twentieth-Century Europe
| publisher = Harvard University Press
| page = 81
| isbn = 978-0-674-00994-3
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;YadVashemRemembrance&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| author = Yad Vashem Martyrs' and Heroes' Remembrance Authority
| title = Yad Vashem Studies
| year = 2006
| volume = 34
| publisher = [[Yad Vashem]]
| location = Jerusalem
| url = http://books.google.com/?id=oLxtAAAAMAAJ&amp;q#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false
| oclc = 610688434
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Plating2011&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Plating
| first = John D.
| title = The Hump: America's Strategy for Keeping China in World War II
| year = 2011
| publisher = Texas A&amp;M University Press
| location = College Station
| series = Williams-Ford Texas A&amp;M University military history series, no. 134
| page = 21
| isbn = 9781603442381
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy1999&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Overy
| first = Richard
| editor1-last = Lukes
| editor1-first = Igor
| editor2-last = Goldstein
| editor2-first = Erik
| title = The Munich Crisis, 1938: Prelude to World War II
| year = 1999
| publisher = Frank Cass
| location = London; Portland, OR
| chapter = Germany and the Munich Crisis: A Mutilated Victory?
| page = 207
| oclc = 40862187
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Rothwell2001&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Rothwell
| first = Victor
| title = The Origins of the Second World War
| year = 2001
| publisher = Manchester University Press
| location = Manchester
| pages = 90–91
| isbn = 978-0-7190-5957-5
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1939-2&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Man of the Year
| work = Time Magazine
| publisher = Time
| date = 2 January 1939
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,760539-1,00.html
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Maiolo1998&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Maiolo
| first = Joseph
| title = The Royal Navy and Nazi Germany 1933–39: Appeasement and the Origins of the Second World War
| year = 1998
| publisher = Macmillan Press
| location = London
| page= 178
|isbn = 9780333720073
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Robertson1985&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Roberston
| first = E.M.
| editor1-first = Koch
| editor1-last = H.W
| title = Aspects of the Third Reich
| year = 1985
| publisher = Macmillan
| location = London
| chapter = Hitler Planning for War and the Response of the Great Powers
| page= 212
| isbn = 9780312057268
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Craig1983&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Craig
| first = Gordon
| authorlink = Gordon A. Craig
| editor1-last = Craig
| editor1-first = Gordon A.
| editor2-last = Gilbert
| editor2-first = Felix
| editor2-link = Felix Gilbert
| title = Documents on German foreign Policy, 1918–1945, from the archives of the German Foreign Ministry
| chapter = The German Foreign Office from Neurath to Ribbentrop
| origyear = 1949
| year = 1983
| pages = 435–436
| oclc = 21151259
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Overy1999-2&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Overy
| first = Richard
| editor1-last = Leitz
| editor1-first = Christian
| title = The Third Reich: The Essential Readings
| year = 1999
| publisher = Blackwell
| location = Oxford
| chapter = Economy Germany, 'Domestic Crisis' and War in 1939
| page = 125
| isbn = 9780631206996
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Beloff1949&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Beloff
| first = Max
| title = The Foreign Policy of Soviet Russia
| volume = II, I936–4I
| year = 1949
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| oclc = 264346
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1995&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Weinberg
| first = Gerhard
| title = Germany, Hitler, and World War II: Essays in Modern German and World History
| year = 1995
| publisher = Cambridge University Press
| location = Cambridge
| chapter = Hitler and England, 1933–1945: Pretense and Reality
| pages = 85–94
| isbn = 9780521474078
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Time1939&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Seven Years War?
| publisher = ''Time'' magazine
| date = 2 October 1939
| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,789000,00.html
| accessdate = 2008-08-30
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mason1997&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last1 = Mason
| first1 =Tim
| last2 = Overy
| first2 = R.J.
| editor1-last = Finney
| editor1-first = Patrick
| title = The Origins of The Second World War
| year = 1997
| publisher = Arnold
| location = London
| chapter = Debate: Germany, 'domestic crisis' and the war in 1939
| pages = 91–98
| isbn = 9780340676417
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1955&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Weinberg
| first = Gerhard
| title = Hitler's Private Testament of 2 May 1938
| journal = The Journal of Modern History
| date = December 1955
| volume = 27
| issue = 4
| pages = 415–419
| oclc = 482752575
| doi = 10.1086/237831
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilgruber1981&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Hillgruber
| first = Andreas
| title = Germany and the Two World Wars
| year = 1981
| publisher = [[Harvard University Press]]
| location = Cambridge, Mass
| pages = 53–55 and 81–82
| isbn = 9780674353213
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg1989&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Weinberg
| first = Gerhard
| title = Review of ''Stalin's War: A Radical New Theory of the Origins of the Second World War'' by Ernst Topitsch
| journal = The American Historical Review
| date = June 1989
| volume = 94
| issue = 3
| pages = 800–801
| oclc = 486363416
| doi = 10.2307/1873876
| last2 = Topitsch
| first2 = Ernst
| last3 = Taylor
| first3 = A.
| last4 = Taylor
| first4 = B.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC1999&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Parkinson's part in Hitler's downfall
| publisher = BBC
| date = 29 July 1999
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/health/406713.stm
| accessdate = 2011-06-13
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Duncan2011&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Duncan
| first = George
| title = Assassination Attempts on Hitler's Life
| work = members.iinet.net.au
| year = 2011 [last update]
| url = http://members.iinet.net.au/~gduncan/assassination_attempts.html
| accessdate = 2011-10-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelken1997&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Nelken
| first = Michael
| title = Hitler Unmasked: The Romance of Racism and Suicide
| year = 1997
| publisher = Darkside Press
| location = Glastonbury, Conn
| page = 276
| isbn = 9780964997905
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Trevor-Roper1992&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Trevor-Roper
| first = Hugh R.
| title = The Last Days of Hitler
| year = 1992
| origyear = 1947
| publisher = University of Chicago Press
| pages = 179–182
| isbn = 9780226812243
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Vinogradov2005&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last1 = Vinogradov
| first1 = V. K
| last2 = Pogonyi
| first2 = J. F
| last3 = Teptzov
| first3 = N.V
| last4 = Roberts
| first4 = Andrew
| title = Hitler's Death: Russia's Last Great Secret from the Files of the KGB
| year = 2005
| publisher = Chaucer Press
| pages = 111, 333
| isbn = 9781904449133
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCskull2000&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| title = Russia displays 'Hitler skull fragment'
| publisher = BBC News
| date = 26 April 2000
| url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/725537.stm
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DailyMailSkull2009&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Fresh doubts over Hitler's death after tests on bullet hole skull reveal it belonged to a woman
| publisher = Daily Mail Online
| date = 28 September 2009
| url = http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/worldnews/article-1216455/Hitlers-skull-really-womans-Fresh-doubts-death-tests-bullet-hole.html
| accessdate = 2009-09-28
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DelTesta2003&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last1 = Del Testa
| first1 = David W
| last2 = Lemoine
| first2 = Florence
| last3 = Strickland
| first3 = John
| title = Government Leaders, Military Rulers, and Political Activists
| year= 2003
| publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group
| page = 83
| isbn = 978-1-57356-153-2
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Dear2001&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last1 = Dear
| first1 = Ian
| last2 = Foot
| first2 = Michael Richard Daniel
| title = The Oxford Companion to World War II
| year = 2001
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| page = 341
| isbn = 978-0-19-860446-4
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Welch2001&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Welch
| first = David
| title = Hitler: Profile of a Dictator
| year = 2001
| publisher = Routledge
| page = 2
| isbn = 978-0-415-25075-7
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohen2007&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Cohen
| first = Rich
| title = Becoming Adolf
| date = November 2007
| work = [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]]
| publisher = [[Condé Nast Publications]]
| url = http://www.vanityfair.com/culture/features/2007/11/cohen200711
| accessdate = 2011-10-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Campbell-BehindTheName&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Campbell
| first = Mike
| title = Meaning, Origin and History of the Name Adolph
| publisher = Behind the Name
| url = http://www.behindthename.com/name/adolf
| accessdate = 2011-06-13
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Finklestone1996&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Finklestone
| first = Joseph
| title = Anwar Sadat: Visionary Who Dared
| year = 1996
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 978-0-7146-3487-6
}}{{page needed|date=October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AsiaWeek1995&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Portrait of a Demagogue
| work = [[Asiaweek]]
| date = 22 September 1995
| url = http://www.asiaweek.com/asiaweek/95/0922/nat5.html
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20010709213551/http://www.asiaweek.com/asiaweek/95/0922/nat5.html
| archivedate = 9 July 2001
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Steigmann-Gall2007&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last1 = Steigmann-Gall
| first1 = Richard
| authorlink1 = Richard Steigmann-Gall
| title = Christianity and the Nazi Movement: A Response
| journal = [[Journal of Contemporary History]]
| year = 2007
| month = April
| volume = 42
| issue = 2
| pages = 185–211
| doi = 10.1177/0022009407075560
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharkey2002&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Sharkey
| first = Joe
| title = Word for Word/The Case Against the Nazis; How Hitler's Forces Planned To Destroy German Christianity
| newspaper = The New York Times
| date = 13 January 2002
| url = http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/13/weekinreview/word-for-word-case-against-nazis-hitler-s-forces-planned-destroy-german.html?pagewanted=all
| accessdate = 2011-06-07
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonney2001&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Bonney
| first = Richard
| authorlink = Richard Bonney
| title = The Nazi Master Plan, Annex 4: The Persecution of the Christian Churches
| journal = Rutgers Journal of Law and Religion
| date = Winter 2001
| url = http://www.leics.gov.uk/the_nazi_master_plan.pdf
| accessdate = 2011-06-07
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;OSS1945&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| author = Office of Strategic Services
| title = The Nazi Master Plan: The Persecution of the Christian Churches
| journal = Rutgers Journal of Law and Religion
| year = 1945
| publisher = Cornell Law Library
| location = Ithaca, NY
| pages = 6–7
| oclc = 320083040
| url = http://org.law.rutgers.edu/publications/law-religion/nurinst1.shtml
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Poewe2006&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Poewe
| first = Karla
| title = New Religions and the Nazis
| year = 2006
| publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis
| location = London
| page = 30
| isbn = 978-0-415-29025-8
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hitler1942&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Hitler
| first = Adolf
| title = [[Hitler's Table Talk]]
| year = 1953
| publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson
| location = London
| chapter = Christianity: 4 April 1942
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Heiden1935&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Heiden
| first = Konrad
| authorlink = Konrad Heiden
| title = A History of National Socialism
| year = 1935
| publisher = A.A. Knopf
| location = New York
| page = 100
| oclc = 975514
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Redlich2000&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Redlich
| first = Fritz R.
| title = Hitler: Diagnosis of a Destructive Prophet
| year = 2000
| month = September
| publisher = Oxford University Press
| pages = 129–190
| isbn = 978-0-19-513631-9
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fitzgerald2004&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Fitzgerald
| first = Michael
| title = Autism and Creativity: Is There a Link between Autism in Men and Exceptional Ability?
| date = 7 January 2004
| publisher = Routledge
| isbn = 978-1-58391-213-3
}}{{page needed|date = October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Fries2009&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal
| last = Fries
| first = Andreas
| title = Did Adolf Hitler suffer of Asperger syndrome?
| journal = Läkartidningen
| date = 22 April 2009
| volume = 106
| issue = 17
| pages = 1201–1204
| url = http://www.lakartidningen.se/store/articlepdf/1/11854/LKT0917s1201_1204.pdf
| accessdate = 2009-08-03
| issn = 0023-7205
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson1998&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Wilson
| first = Bee
| title = Mein Diat&amp;nbsp;– Adolf Hitler's diet
| publisher = [[FindArticles]]
| work = New Statesman
| location = UK
| date = 9 October 1998
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
| url = http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FQP/is_n4406_v127/ai_21238666
| archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050321091219/http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0FQP/is_n4406_v127/ai_21238666
| archivedate = 21 March 2005
| format = &lt;!-- {{Dead link|date=September 2009}} *''not'' a dead link, merely slow to load from wayback*--&gt;
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kessel2004&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Kessel
| first = Joseph
| title = The Man With the Miraculous Hands: The Fantastic Story of Felix Kersten, Himmler's Private Doctor
| year = 2004
| publisher = Burford Books
| location = Springfield, NJ
| series = Classics of War Series
| isbn = 978-1-58080-122-5
}}{{page needed|date=October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Adams1987&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Adams
| first = Cecil
| title = Did Hitler have only one testicle?
| newspaper = [[The Straight Dope]]
| date=20 February 1987
| url = http://www.straightdope.com/columns/read/881/did-hitler-have-only-one-testicle
| accessdate = 2011-06-06
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Peake2008&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
| last = Peake
| first = Alex
| title = Hitler HAD only got one ball
| publisher = The Sun
| date = 19 November 2008
| location = London
| url = http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/homepage/news/article1945960.ece
| accessdate = 2011-10-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bezymenski1968&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Bezymenski
| first = Lev A.
| title = The Death of Adolf Hitler: Unknown Documents from Soviet Archives
| year = 1968
| publisher = Michael Joseph
| location = London
| isbn = 978-0-7181-0634-8
}}{{page needed|date=October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bezymenski1995&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| last = Bezymenski
| first = Lev A.
| title = Operaciâ &quot;mif&quot;, Ili Skol'ko Raz Horonili Gitlera
| year = 1995
| publisher = Meždunarodnye otnošeniâ
| location = Moscow
| isbn = 978-5-7133-0839-1
}}{{page needed|date=October 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Frauenfeld1937&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Frauenfeld
| first = A. E
| title = The Power of Speech
| publisher = [[Calvin College]]
| date = August 1937
| url = http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/machtrede.htm
| accessdate = 2011-10-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goebbels1936&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Goebbels
|first = Joseph
| title = The Führer as a Speaker
| publisher = [[Calvin College]]
| year = 1936
| url = http://www.calvin.edu/academic/cas/gpa/ahspeak.htm
| accessdate = 2011-10-19
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Moring2004&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| last = Moring
| first = Kirsikka
| title = Conversation secretly recorded in Finland helped German actor prepare for Hitler role
| date = 21 September 2004
| publisher = [[Helsingin Sanomat]]
| url = http://www.hs.fi/english/article/1076153999513
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;YLE2006&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
| title = Hitlerin salaa tallennettu keskustelu Suomessa
| publisher = YLE
| date = 9 August 2006
| language = Finnish
| url = http://www.yle.fi/elavaarkisto/?s=s&amp;g=1&amp;ag=3&amp;t=22&amp;a=376
| accessdate = 2008-05-22
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

}}

===References===
{{refbegin|colwidth=30em}}

* {{cite book
  | last = Bauer
  | first = Yehuda
  | title = Rethinking the Holocaust
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | year = 2000
  | page = 5
  | isbn = 9780300082562
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | title = [[Berlin: The Downfall 1945]]
  | last = Beevor
  | first = Antony
  | authorlink = Antony Beevor
  | year = 2002
  | publisher = Viking-Penguin Books
  | location = London
  | isbn = 0-670-03041-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bloch
  | first = Michael
  | title = Ribbentrop
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Crown Publishing
  | year = 1992
  | isbn = 978-0-517-59310-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bullock
  | first = Alan
  | authorlink = Alan Bullock
  | title = Hitler: A Study in Tyranny
  | location = London
  | publisher = Penguin Books
  | year = 1962
  | origyear = 1952
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=ybklscomuGQC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | isbn = 978-0-14-013564-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bullock
  | first = Alan
  | authorlink = Alan Bullock
  | title = Hitler: A Study in Tyranny
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1952
  | publisher = Konecky &amp; Konecky
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 1-56852-036-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Butler
  | first1 = Ewan
  | last2 = Young
  | first2 = Gordon
  | title = The Life and Death of Hermann Göring
  | publisher = [[David &amp; Charles]]
  | location = Newton Abbot, Devon
  | year = 1989
  | isbn = 978-0-7153-9455-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Carr
  | first = William
  | title = Arms, Autarky and Aggression
  | publisher = Edward Arnold
  | location = London
  | year = 1972
  | isbn = 978-0-7131-5668-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Conway
  | first = John S.
  | author-link = John S. Conway
  | title = The Nazi Persecution of the Churches 1933–45
  | year = 1968
  | location = London
  | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson
  | isbn = 978-0-297-76315-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Dietrich
  | first = Otto
  | authorlink = Otto Dietrich
  | title = The Hitler I Knew: Memoirs of the Third Reich's Press Chief
  | publisher = Skyhorse
  | location = New York
  | year = 2010
  | isbn = 978-1-60239-972-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Dollinger
  | first = Hans
  | title = The Decline and Fall of Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan: A Pictorial History of the Final Days of World War II
  | isbn = 978-0-517-12399-7
  | year = 1995
  | origyear = 1965
  | publisher = Gramercy
  | location = New York
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Evans
  | first = Richard
  | title = In Hitler's Shadow : West German Historians and the Attempt to Escape from the Nazi Past
  | year = 1989
  | publisher = Pantheon
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 9780394576862
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fest
  | first = Joachim C.
  | author-link = Joachim Fest
  | title = The Face of the Third Reich
  | location = London
  | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson
  | year = 1970
  | isbn = 978-0-297-17949-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fest
  | first = Joachim C.
  | title = Hitler
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Harcourt Brace Jovanovich
  | year = 1974
  | isbn = 978-0-15-602754-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fischer
  | first = Thomas
  | year = 2008
  | title = Soldiers of the Leibstandarte: SS-Brigadefuhrer Wilhelm Mohnke and 62 Soldiers of Hitler's Elite Division
  | publisher = J.J. Fedorowicz
  | location = Winnipeg
  | isbn = 978-0-921991-91-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fromm
  | first = Erich
  | authorlink = Erich Fromm
  | title = The Anatomy of Human Destructiveness
  | year = 1977
  | origyear = 1973
  | publisher = Penguin Books
  | location = London
  | isbn = 9780140042580
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hakim
  | first = Joy
  | authorlink = Joy Hakim
  | series = [[A History of US]]
  | title = War, Peace, and All That Jazz
  | volume = 9
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | year = 1995
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-19-509514-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Halperin
  | first1 = Samuel William
  | title = Germany Tried Democracy: A Political History of the Reich from 1918 to 1933
  | publisher = W.W. Norton
  | location = New York
  | year = 1965
  | origyear = 1946
  | isbn = 978-0-393-00280-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Hamann
  | first1 = Brigitte
  | authorlink1 = Brigitte Hamann
  | title = Hitler's Vienna: A Dictator's Apprenticeship
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = New York
  | year = 1999
  | others = Trans. Thomas Thornton
  | isbn = 978-0-19-512537-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hamann
  | first = Brigitte
  | title = Hitler's Vienna: A Portrait of the Tyrant as a Young Man
  | publisher = Tauris Parke Paperbacks
  | location = London; New York
  | year = 2010
  | origyear = 1999
  | others = Trans. Thomas Thornton
  | isbn = 978-1-848-85277-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Heston
  | first1 = Leonard L.
  | last2 = Heston
  | first2 = Renate
  | title = The Medical Casebook of Adolf Hitler: His Illnesses, Doctors, and Drugs
  | year = 1980
  | origyear = 1979
  | publisher = Stein and Day
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-8128-2718-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hildebrand
  | first = Klaus
  | author-link = Klaus Hildebrand
  | title = The Foreign Policy of the Third Reich
  | location = London
  | publisher = Batsford
  | year = 1973
  | isbn = 978-0-7134-1126-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hitler
  | first = Adolf
  | title = [[Mein Kampf]]
  | location = Boston
  | publisher = Houghton Mifflin
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1925
  | others = Trans. [[Ralph Manheim]]
  | isbn = 978-0-395-92503-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hitler
  | first = Adolf
  | year = 1973
  | origyear = 1941
  | title = My New Order
  | publisher = Octagon Books
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-374-93918-2
  | editor1-first = Raoul de
  | editor1-last = Roussy de Sales
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hitler
  | first = Adolf
  | year = 1942
  | title = [[The Speeches of Adolf Hitler, April 1922&amp;nbsp;– August 1939]]
  | location = London
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | isbn = 978-0-86527-493-8
  | editor1-first = Norman H.
  | editor1-last = Baynes
  | editor1-link = Norman H. Baynes
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Jetzinger
  | first = Franz
  | authorlink = Franz Jetzinger
  | title = Hitler's Youth
  | year = 1976
  | origyear = 1956
  | publisher = Greenwood Press
  | location = Westport, Conn
  | isbn = 978-0-8371-8617-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Joachimsthaler
  | first = Anton
  | others = Trans. Helmut Bögler
  | title = The Last Days of Hitler: The Legends, the Evidence, the Truth
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1995
  | publisher = Brockhampton Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-86019-902-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kee
  | first = Robert
  | authorlink = Robert Kee
  | title = Munich: The Eleventh Hour
  | publisher = Hamish Hamilton
  | location = London
  | year = 1988
  | isbn = 978-0-241-12537-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Keegan
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Keegan
  | title = The Mask of Command: A Study of Generalship
  | publisher = Pimlico
  | location = London
  | year = 1987
  | isbn = 978-0-7126-6526-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Keegan
  | first = John
  | title = The Second World War
  | location = London
  | publisher = [[Hutchinson (publisher)|Hutchinson]]
  | year = 1989
  | isbn = 978-0-09-174011-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Keller
  | first = Gustav
  | title= Der Schüler Adolf Hitler: die Geschichte eines lebenslangen Amoklaufs
  | trans_title = The Student Adolf Hitler: The Story of a Lifelong Rampage
  | publisher = LIT
  | language = German
  | location = Münster
  | year = 2010
  | isbn = 9783643109484
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kellogg
  | first = Michael
  | title = The Russian Roots of Nazism White Émigrés and the Making of National Socialism, 1917–1945
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 9780521845120
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Ian
  | author-link = Ian Kershaw
  | title = Hitler: 1889–1936: Hubris
  | location = New York
  | publisher = [[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]]
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=62xSFkgjAdUC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1998
  | isbn = 0393046710
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Ian
  | title = The Nazi Dictatorship: Problems and Perspectives of Interpretation
  | edition = 4th
  | location = London
  | publisher = Arnold
  | year = 2000a
  | origyear = 1985
  | isbn = 978-0-340-76028-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Ian
  | title = Hitler, 1936–1945: Nemesis
  | location = New York; London
  | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=B5fJYMxufVcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | year = 2000b
  | isbn = 0393322521
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Ian
  | title = Hitler: A Biography
  | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company
  | location = New York
  | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=YadFavyLuGEC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | year = 2008
  | isbn = 0-393-06757-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kubizek
  | first = August
  | title = The Young Hitler I Knew
  | authorlink = August Kubizek
  | year = 2006
  | origyear = 1953
  | publisher = MBI
  | location = St. Paul, MN
  | isbn = 978-1-85367-694-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kurowski
  | first = Franz
  | title = The Brandenburger Commandos: Germany's Elite Warrior Spies in World War II
  | publisher = Stackpole Books
  | series = Stackpole Military History series
  | location = Mechanicsburg, PA
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-0-8117-3250-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | year = 2009
  | origyear = 1980
  | last1 = Linge
  | first1 = Heinz
  | authorlink1 = Heinz Linge
  | others = Intro. [[Roger Moorhouse]]
  | title = With Hitler to the End: The Memoirs of Adolf Hitler's Valet
  | publisher = Skyhorse Publishing
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-1-60239-804-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Lukacs
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Lukacs
  | title = The Hitler of History
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Vintage Books
  | origyear = 1997
  | year = 1998
  | isbn = 9780375701139
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Marrus
  | first = Michael
  | authorlink = Michael Marrus
  | title = The Holocaust in History
  | location = Toronto
  | publisher = Key Porter
  | year = 2000
  | isbn = 978-0-299-23404-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Megargee
  | first = Geoffrey P.
  | title = War of Annihilation: Combat and Genocide on the Eastern Front, 1941
  | location = Lanham, Md
  | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
  | year = 2007
  | isbn = 978-0-7425-4482-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Messerschmidt
  | first = Manfred
  | title = [[Germany and the Second World War]]
  | volume = 1
  | chapter = Foreign Policy and Preparation for War
  | location = Oxford
  | publisher = Clarendon Press
  | year = 1990
  | editor1-last = Deist
  | editor1-first = Wilhelm
  | isbn = 978-0-19-822866-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Murray
  | first = Williamson
  | title = The Change in the European Balance of Power
  | location = Princeton
  | publisher = Princeton University Press
  | year = 1984
  | isbn = 978-0-691-05413-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = O'Donnell
  | first = James P.
  | authorlink = James P. O'Donnell
  | title = [[The Bunker]]
  | publisher = Da Capo Press
  | location = New York
  | year = 2001
  | origyear = 1978
  | isbn = 978-0-306-80958-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Overy
  | first = Richard
  | author-link = Richard Overy
  | title = The Road To War
  | location = London
  | publisher = Macmillan
  | year = 1989
  | isbn = 978-0-14-028530-7
  | coauthor = Wheatcroft, Andrew
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Overy
  | first = Richard
  | title = The Dictators: Hitler's Germany, Stalin's Russia
  | publisher = Penguin Books
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-0-393-02030-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Payne
  | first = Robert
  | authorlink = Pierre Stephen Robert Payne
  | title = The Life and Death of Adolf Hitler
  | publisher = Hippocrene Books
  | location = New York, New York
  | year = 1990
  | origyear = 1973
  | isbn = 978-0-88029-402-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Payne
  | first = Stanley G.
  | authorlink = Stanley G. Payne
  | title = Franco and Hitler: Spain, Germany, and World War II
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | location = New Haven
  | year = 2008
  | isbn = 0300122829
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Rees
  | first = Laurence
  | authorlink = Laurence Rees
  | title = [[The Nazis: A Warning From History]]
  | location = New York
  | publisher = New Press
  | year = 1997
  | isbn = 978-0-563-38704-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Rißmann
  | first = Michael
  | title = Hitlers Gott. Vorsehungsglaube und Sendungsbewußtsein des deutschen Diktators
  | location = Zürich München
  | publisher = Pendo
  | year = 2001
  | isbn = 978-3-85842-421-1
  | language = German
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Robertson
  | first = Esmonde M.
  | title = Hitler's Pre-War Policy and Military Plans: 1933–1939
  | publisher = Longmans
  | location = London
  | year = 1963
  | oclc = 300011871
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Rosenbaum
  | first = Ron
  | authorlink = Ron Rosenbaum
  | title = [[Explaining Hitler: The Search for the Origins of His Evil]]
  | publisher = [[Macmillan Publishers]]
  | year = 1998
  | isbn = 978-0-06-095339-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
| last = Rosmus
| first = Anna Elisabeth
| title = Out of Passau: Leaving a City Hitler Called Home
| year = 2004
| publisher = University of South Carolina Press
| location = Columbia, S.C
| isbn = 9781570035081
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Shirer
  | first = William L.
  | authorlink = William L. Shirer
  | title = [[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]]
  | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster
  | location = New York
  | year = 1960
  | isbn = 978-0-671-62420-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Snyder
  | first = Timothy
  | authorlink = Timothy D. Snyder
  | title = [[Bloodlands: Europe Between Hitler and Stalin]]
  | publisher = Basic Books
  | location = New York
  | year = 2010
  | isbn = 0-465-00239-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Speer
  | first = Albert
  | authorlink = Albert Speer
  | origyear = 1969
  | year = 1971
  | title = [[Inside the Third Reich]]
  | publisher = Avon
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-380-00071-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Steigmann-Gall
  | first = Richard
  | authorlink = Richard Steigmann-Gall
  | title = The Holy Reich: Nazi Conceptions of Christianity, 1919–1945
  | location = Cambridge; New York
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | year = 2003
  | isbn = 978-0-521-82371-5
  | doi = 10.2277/978-0-521-82371-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Le Tissier
  | first = Tony
  | title = Race for the Reichstag
  | publisher = Pen &amp; Sword
  | year = 2010
  | origyear = 1999
  | isbn = 978-1-84884-230-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Toland
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Toland (author)
  | title = Adolf Hitler: The Definitive Biography
  | publisher = [[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]]
  | year = 1992
  | origyear = 1976
  | isbn = 978-0-385-42053-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Vinogradov
  | first = V. K.
  | title = Hitler's Death: Russia's Last Great Secret from the Files of the KGB
  | publisher = Chaucer Press
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-1-904449-13-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Weinberg
  | first = Gerhard
  | author-link = Gerhard Weinberg
  | title = The Foreign Policy of Hitler's Germany Diplomatic Revolution in Europe 1933–1936
  | publisher = University of Chicago Press
  | location = Chicago, Illinois
  | year = 1970
  | isbn = 978-0-226-88509-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Weinberg
  | first = Gerhard
  | title = The Foreign Policy of Hitler's Germany Starting World War II
  | publisher = University of Chicago Press
  | year = 1980
  | isbn = 978-0-226-88511-7
  | location = Chicago, Illinois
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Wheeler-Bennett
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Wheeler-Bennett
  | title = The Nemesis of Power
  | location = London
  | publisher = Macmillan
  | year = 1967
  | isbn = 978-1-4039-1812-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{see also|List of books by or about Adolf Hitler|List of speeches given by Adolf Hitler|Adolf Hitler in popular culture}}
{{refbegin|30em}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Cornish
  | first = Kimberley
  | title = [[The Jew of Linz|The Jew of Linz: Wittgenstein, Hitler, and Their Secret Battle for the Mind]]
  | year = 1998
  | location = London
  | publisher = Century
  | isbn = 978-0-7126-7935-0
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Crozier
  | first = Andrew J.
  | title = Appeasement and Germany's Last Bid for Colonies
  | publisher = Macmillan Press
  | location = London
  | year = 1988
  | isbn = 978-0-312-01546-6
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Dawidowicz
  | first = Lucy
  | author-link = Lucy Dawidowicz
  | title = A Holocaust Reader
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Behrman House
  | year = 1976
  | isbn = 978-0-87441-219-2
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Dawidowicz
  | first = Lucy
  | title = [[The War Against the Jews]]
  | publisher = Bantam Books
  | year = 1986
  | origyear = 1975
  | isbn = 978-0-553-34532-2
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Doerr
  | first = Paul W.
  | title = British Foreign Policy, 1919–1939
  | publisher = Manchester University Press
  | location = Manchester, UK
  | year = 1998
  | isbn = 978-0-7190-4671-1
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Haffner
  | first = Sebastian
  | author-link = Sebastian Haffner
  | title = [[The Meaning of Hitler]]
  | publisher = Harvard University Press
  | location = Cambridge, Mass
  | year = 1979
  | isbn = 978-0-674-55776-5
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Krausbeck
  | first = Erich
  | title = Sein Lieblingswort war Ich—Wie krank war Adolf Hitler? Ein literarisch-kulturhistorisches Sachbuch zur Psychopathologie
  | publisher = VDM Verlag
  | location = Saarbrücken
  | language = German
  | year = 2011
  | isbn = 978-3-639-35318-1
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Langer
  | first = Walter C.
  | authorlink = Walter Charles Langer
  | title = [[The Mind of Adolf Hitler]]
  | publisher = Basic Books
  | location = New York
  | year = 1972
  | isbn = 978-0-465-04620-1
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Lewis
  | first = David
  | author-link = David Lewis (psychologist)
  | title = The Man Who Invented Hitler
  | publisher = [[Headline Publishing Group]]
  | year = 2003
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-7553-1148-4
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Machtan
  | first = Lothar
  | authorlink = Lothar Machtan
  | title = [[The Hidden Hitler]]
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Basic Books
  | year = 2001
  | isbn = 978-0-465-04308-8
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Roberts
  | first = Andrew
  | authorlink = Andrew Roberts (historian)
  | title = The Holy Fox
  | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson
  | location = London
  | year = 1991
  | isbn = 978-0-297-81133-6
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Röpke
  | first = Wilhelm
  | author-link = Wilhelm Röpke
  | title = The Solution to the German Problem
  | publisher = [[G. P. Putnam's Sons]]
  | year = 1946
  | oclc = 403661
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Strobl
  | first = Gerwin
  | title = The Germanic Isle
  | publisher = Cambridge University Press
  | location = Cambridge, United Kingdom
  | year = 2000
  | isbn = 978-0-521-78265-4
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tooze
  | first = Adam
  | authorlink = Adam Tooze
  | title = [[The Wages of Destruction]]
  | location = New York
  | publisher = Viking Press
  | year = 2006
  | isbn = 978-0-670-03826-8
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Waite
  | first = Robert G. L.
  | authorlink = Robert G. L. Waite
  | title = [[The Psychopathic God: Adolf Hitler]]
  | publisher = [[Da Capo Press]]
  | year = 1993
  | origyear = 1977
  | isbn = 978-0-306-80514-1
  }}
{{refend}}

==External links==

{{Sister project links}}

* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n79-46200}}
* {{IMDb name|id=0386944}}&amp;nbsp;– real life footage in documentaries
* {{IMDb character|id=0027857|character=Adolf Hitler (Character)}}&amp;nbsp;– as portrayed in film and TV
* {{cite web|title=Adolf Hitler|url=http://vault.fbi.gov/adolf-hitler|work=The Vault|publisher=FBI Records}}
* {{cite web|title=All About Adolf Hitler|url=http://www.life.com/topic/adolf_hitler|work=LIFE magazine}}
* {{cite web|title=Hitler and his officers |url=http://www.ww2incolor.com/gallery/movies/hitler_color|work=World War II Movies in Color|publisher=WW2inColor}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Kurt von Schleicher]]}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Chancellor of Germany (German Reich)|Chancellor of Germany]]{{sup|(1)}} | years = 1933–1945}}
{{s-aft | after = [[Joseph Goebbels]]}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Paul von Hindenburg]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;As President&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Führer|''Führer'' of Germany]]{{sup|(1)}} | years = 1934–1945}}
{{s-aft | after = [[Karl Dönitz]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;As President&lt;/small&gt;}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-ppo}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Anton Drexler]]}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[National Socialist German Workers Party|Leader of the NSDAP]] | years = 1921–1945}}
{{s-mil}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Franz Pfeffer von Salomon]]}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Oberste SA-Führer|Leader of the SA]] | years = 1930–1945}}

{{s-break}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Walther von Brauchitsch]]}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Oberkommando des Heeres|''Oberbefehlshaber des Heeres'' (Army Commander)]] | years = 1941–1945}}
{{s-aft | after = [[Ferdinand Schörner]]}}
{{s-break}}
{{s-hon}}
{{s-bef | before = [[Chiang Kai-shek]] and [[Soong May-ling]]}}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Time Person of the Year]] | years = 1938}}
{{s-aft | after = [[Joseph Stalin]]}}
{{s-ref|The positions of Head of State and Government were combined 1934–1945 in the office of Führer and Chancellor of Germany}}
{{Time Persons of the Year 1927–1950}}
{{Adolf Hitler|state=collapsed}}
{{Navboxes
| state = collapsed
| list1 =
{{GermanChancellors}}
{{German Presidents (1919–1945)}}
{{Hitler's Cabinet}}
{{Final occupants of the Führerbunker}}
{{Time Persons of the Year|27–50}}
{{Fascism|state=collapsed}}
{{Nazism}}
{{The Holocaust (end)}}
}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

{{Authority control|LCCN=n/79/046200}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME = Hitler, Adolf
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = [[Führer]] of the National Socialist German Workers Party; [[Reichskanzler]] of Germany
| DATE OF BIRTH = 20 April 1889
| PLACE OF BIRTH = [[Braunau am Inn]], Austria
| DATE OF DEATH = 30 April 1945
| PLACE OF DEATH = Berlin, Germany
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Hitler, Adolf}}
[[Category:Adolf Hitler| ]]
[[Category:1889 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:Antisemitism in Germany]]
[[Category:Attempted assassination survivors]]
[[Category:Austrian anti-communists]]
[[Category:Austrian emigrants to Germany]]
[[Category:Austrian expatriates in Germany]]
[[Category:Austrian Nazis]]
[[Category:Austrian painters]]
[[Category:Chancellors of Germany]]
[[Category:Conspiracy theorists]]
[[Category:German anti-communists]]
[[Category:German founders of automobile manufacturers]]
[[Category:German military leaders]]
[[Category:German military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:German painters]]
[[Category:German people of Austrian descent]]
[[Category:German people of World War II]]
[[Category:German political writers]]
[[Category:German politicians who committed suicide]]
[[Category:German presidential candidates]]
[[Category:Historians of fascism]]
[[Category:Hitler family]]
[[Category:Holocaust perpetrators]]
[[Category:Leaders of political parties in Germany]]
[[Category:Naturalized citizens of Germany]]
[[Category:Nazi leaders]]
[[Category:Nazis who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Nazis who participated in the Beer Hall Putsch]]
[[Category:People convicted of treason against Germany]]
[[Category:People from Braunau am Inn]]
[[Category:Persecution of homosexuals]]
[[Category:Political writers who committed suicide]]
[[Category:Presidents of Germany]]
[[Category:Recipients of German pardons]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Iron Cross]]
[[Category:Suicides by firearm in Germany]]
[[Category:Suicides by poison]]
[[Category:World War II political leaders]]

{{Link FA|ceb}}
{{Link FA|he}}
{{Link FA|no}}
{{Link FA|sh}}
{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link GA|eo}}
{{Link GA|simple}}
{{Link GA|sr}}
{{Link GA|sv}}
{{Link GA|uz}}

[[kbd:Адолф Гитлер]]
[[af:Adolf Hitler]]
[[als:Adolf Hitler]]
[[am:አዶልፍ ሂትለር]]
[[ang:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ar:أدولف هتلر]]
[[an:Adolf Hitler]]
[[arc:ܐܕܘܠܦ ܗܝܛܠܪ]]
[[roa-rup:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ast:Adolf Hitler]]
[[gn:Adolf Hitler]]
[[az:Adolf Hitler]]
[[bn:আডলফ হিটলার]]
[[bjn:Adolf Hitler]]
[[zh-min-nan:Adolf Hitler]]
[[be:Адольф Гітлер]]
[[be-x-old:Адольф Гітлер]]
[[bcl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[bg:Адолф Хитлер]]
[[bar:Adolf Hitler]]
[[bo:ཨྰ་སྦྲོལ་ཧྥུ་ཧི་ཐུ་ལུར།]]
[[bs:Adolf Hitler]]
[[br:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ca:Adolf Hitler]]
[[cv:Адольф Китлĕр]]
[[ceb:Adolf Hitler]]
[[cs:Adolf Hitler]]
[[cbk-zam:Adolf Hitler]]
[[cy:Adolf Hitler]]
[[da:Adolf Hitler]]
[[de:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nv:Dágháilchįįh]]
[[et:Adolf Hitler]]
[[el:Αδόλφος Χίτλερ]]
[[eml:Adolf Hitler]]
[[es:Adolf Hitler]]
[[eo:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ext:Adolf Hitler]]
[[eu:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fa:آدولف هیتلر]]
[[hif:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fo:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fr:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fy:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ga:Adolf Hitler]]
[[gd:Adolf Hitler]]
[[gl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[gan:希特勒]]
[[ko:아돌프 히틀러]]
[[ha:Hitler]]
[[hy:Ադոլֆ Հիտլեր]]
[[hi:एडोल्फ हिटलर]]
[[hsb:Adolf Hitler]]
[[hr:Adolf Hitler]]
[[io:Adolf Hitler]]
[[id:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ia:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ie:Adolf Hitler]]
[[os:Гитлер, Адольф]]
[[is:Adolf Hitler]]
[[it:Adolf Hitler]]
[[he:אדולף היטלר]]
[[jv:Adolf Hitler]]
[[kn:ಅಡೋಲ್ಫ್ ಹಿಟ್ಲರ್]]
[[ka:ადოლფ ჰიტლერი]]
[[kk:Адолф Гитлер]]
[[sw:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ku:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ky:Адольф Гитлер]]
[[lad:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ltg:Adoļfs Hitlers]]
[[la:Adolphus Hitler]]
[[lv:Ādolfs Hitlers]]
[[lb:Adolf Hitler]]
[[lt:Adolfas Hitleris]]
[[li:Adolf Hitler]]
[[lmo:Adolf Hitler]]
[[hu:Adolf Hitler]]
[[mk:Адолф Хитлер]]
[[mg:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ml:അഡോൾഫ് ഹിറ്റ്‌ലർ]]
[[mt:Adolf Hitler]]
[[mr:अ‍ॅडॉल्फ हिटलर]]
[[arz:ادولف هيتلر]]
[[mzn:آدولف هیتلر]]
[[ms:Adolf Hitler]]
[[mwl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[mn:Адольф Гитлер]]
[[my:ဟစ်တလာ]]
[[nah:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nds-nl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ja:アドルフ・ヒトラー]]
[[nap:Hitler]]
[[no:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nn:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nov:Adolf Hitler]]
[[oc:Adolf Hitler]]
[[mhr:Гитлер, Адольф]]
[[uz:Adolf Hitler]]
[[pnb:ہٹلر]]
[[ps:اډولف هټلر]]
[[pms:Adolf Hitler]]
[[nds:Adolf Hitler]]
[[pl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[pt:Adolf Hitler]]
[[kaa:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ksh:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ro:Adolf Hitler]]
[[rm:Adolf Hitler]]
[[qu:Adolf Hitler]]
[[rue:Адолф Гітлер]]
[[ru:Гитлер, Адольф]]
[[sah:Адольф Хитлер]]
[[sa:ऐडॉल्फ़ हिटलर]]
[[sco:Adolf Hitler]]
[[stq:Adolf Hitler]]
[[st:Adolf Hitler]]
[[sq:Adolf Hitler]]
[[scn:Adolf Hitler]]
[[si:ඇඩොල්ෆ් හිට්ලර්]]
[[simple:Adolf Hitler]]
[[sk:Adolf Hitler]]
[[sl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[szl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[so:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ckb:ئادۆڵف ھیتلەر]]
[[sr:Адолф Хитлер]]
[[sh:Adolf Hitler]]
[[su:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fi:Adolf Hitler]]
[[sv:Adolf Hitler]]
[[tl:Adolf Hitler]]
[[ta:இட்லர்]]
[[kab:Adolf Hitler]]
[[tt:Adolf Hitler]]
[[te:ఎడాల్ఫ్ హిట్లర్]]
[[th:อดอล์ฟ ฮิตเลอร์]]
[[tg:Адолф Ҳитлер]]
[[tr:Adolf Hitler]]
[[uk:Адольф Гітлер]]
[[ur:ہٹلر]]
[[vec:Adolf Hitler]]
[[vi:Adolf Hitler]]
[[fiu-vro:Hitleri Adolf]]
[[wa:Adolf Hitler]]
[[vls:Adolf Hitler]]
[[war:Adolf Hitler]]
[[wuu:希特拉]]
[[yi:אדאלף היטלער]]
[[yo:Adolf Hitler]]
[[zh-yue:希特拉]]
[[diq:Adolf Hitler]]
[[bat-smg:Aduolfos Hitleris]]
[[zh:阿道夫·希特勒]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
