<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2732318" ns="0" title="WXPO-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|an early 1970s television station|the current occupant of channel 50 in southern [[New Hampshire]] and northern [[Massachusetts]]|WBIN-TV}}
{{Infobox Broadcast
| call_letters             = WXPO-TV
| station_logo             = &lt;!-- Do NOT place a non-free image here without providing a rationale on the image description page per [[WP:FURG]] --&gt;
| location                 = [[Manchester, New Hampshire]]/[[Lowell, Massachusetts]]
| city                     =
| station_branding         =
| station_slogan           =
| analog                   = 50 ([[Ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| digital                  =
| virtual                  =
| subchannels              =
| other_chs                =
| affiliations             = [[Dark (broadcasting)|Defunct]]
| owner                    = Merrimack Valley Communications
| licensee                 =
| founded                  =
| airdate                  = October 1969
| enddate                  = June 1970
| callsign_meaning         =
| sister_stations          =
| former_callsigns         =
| former_channel_numbers   =
| former_affiliations      = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]] (1969-1970)
| former_locations         =
| former_cities            =
| effective_radiated_power =
| HAAT                     =
| class                    =
| facility_id              =
| coordinates              =
| homepage                 =
}}
'''WXPO-TV''' was a short-lived television station that was licensed to [[Manchester, New Hampshire]], but mainly targeted the [[Boston]] market. Owned by Merrimack Valley Communications, the station aired on channel 50.

==History==
WXPO-TV signed on early in October 1969, from two studios.  Its offices and master production facilities were located on Dutton Street in downtown [[Lowell, Massachusetts]]; however, its transmitter and &quot;main&quot; studio was on Governor Dinsmore Road in [[Windham, New Hampshire]] to comply with [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) regulations requiring that a station's transmitter be located within 15 miles of the city of license.  The original vision was to air business news during the daytime, and a [[Independent station (North America)|general entertainment format]] — including sports — late in the afternoon and in the evening.

Its ''Treehouse 50'' program in the afternoons gained a cult following with Boston-area college students, as it had [[slapstick comedy]] and the [[Warner Bros.]] [[Warner Bros. Cartoons|cartoons]] that had been released to television stations at that time. The station also attempted to do live remotes with some mixed success. In addition, WXPO was infamous for a [[New Year's Eve]] show that by 1:00 a.m. had started to become particularly strange.

WXPO also attempted a news operation; in addition to the financial news programming, it was the first station to have news updates every hour (a precursor to the [[24 Hour News Source]] format used by many stations in the 1990s), and was the first New England television station to air a ten o'clock newscast (WKBG-TV, now [[WLVI-TV]], also attempted such a newscast during this time, but did not launch it for another two months); however, it did not have any newsfilm and relied solely on [[Associated Press|AP]] slides to provide visuals.

However, the station's coverage in many parts of [[Greater Boston]] was spotty at best.  The Lowell studio was located less than 1,000 feet from the [[WLLH]] transmitter, making high-quality production impossible during the day due to RF interference with the cameras.  Advertisers were scared off when the ''[[Lowell Sun]]'' blacklisted anyone who advertised on the station.  Bills went unpaid for several months.

By early 1970, the vast majority (90%) of the staff was removed from the payroll, although many continued with the station, believing it could pull through. However, the spring of that year saw the closure of the Lowell studio.  Finally, in June the power company pulled the plug at the Windham studios during a ''[[Maverick (TV series)|Maverick]]'' rerun, taking WXPO off the air.

On July 17, 1973, channel 50 returned to the air with a test transmission, with plans to return the station to the air later that year, possibly as New Hampshire's [[CBS]] affiliate. Those plans were never realized, and the WXPO-TV license was deleted in 1975.  The channel would remain [[Dark (broadcasting)|silent]] until September 1983, when WNDS (now [[WBIN-TV]]) began operations.

==External links==
* [http://radiodxer.bravehost.com/wxpo.html WXPO-TV 50 at UHF Morgue]

{{Boston TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wxpo-Tv}}
[[Category:Television stations in New Hampshire]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1969]]
[[Category:1970 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Defunct terrestrial television stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television stations in Massachusetts]]
[[Category:Defunct companies based in Massachusetts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
