<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27330315" ns="0" title="Conservative – Liberal Democrat coalition agreement"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Conservative – Liberal Democrat Coalition Agreement''' (also called '''The Coalition: Our Programme For Government''') was a policy document drawn up following the [[United Kingdom general election, 2010|2010 general election]] in the [[United Kingdom]]. It formed the terms of reference governing the [[Cameron Ministry]], the newly formed [[coalition government]] comprising MPs from the [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]] and the [[Liberal Democrats]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.conservatives.com/News/News_stories/2010/05/Coalition_Agreement_published.aspx Conservative Liberal Democrat Coalition Agreement], [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative Party]], Published 12 May 2010, Accessed 13 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://libdems.org.uk/latest_news_detail.aspx?title=Conservative_Liberal_Democrat_coalition_agreements&amp;pPK=2697bcdc-7483-47a7-a517-7778979458ff Conservative Liberal Democrat Coalition Agreement], [[Liberal Democrats]], Published 12 May 2010, Accessed 13 May 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2010/may/12/lib-dem-tory-deal-coalition |title=Full text of the Conservative-Liberal Democrat coalition deal |date=12 May 2010 |accessdate=12 May 2010|publisher=[[The Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The general election resulted in a [[hung parliament]], with no party emerging with an overall majority in the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]], for the first time since 1974. As a result, the first and third parties in terms of votes and seats, the Conservatives and Liberal Democrats respectively, entered into negotiations with the aim of forming a full coalition, the first since the [[Second World War]].

An initial [[Coalition agreement|agreement]] was published on 12 May 2010 (dated 11 May), detailing what had been agreed in the various policy areas, in order for a coalition government to be able to be formed, with a final agreement published 20 May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/8693535.stm |title=Cameron and Clegg set out 'radical' policy programme|date=Thursday, 20 May 2010|accessdate=|publisher=[[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Initial agreement==
The initial agreement was published on 12 May 2010. It consisted of a 7 page document, in 11 sections. In the foreword, it stated &quot;These are the issues that needed to be resolved between us in order for us to work together as a strong and stable government&quot;. The 11 sections were as follows:

#[[#Deficit|Deficit Reduction]]
#[[#Spending|Spending Review - NHS, Schools and a Fairer Society]]
#[[#Tax|Tax Measures]]
#[[#Banking|Banking Reform]]
#[[#Immigration|Immigration]]
#[[#Political reform|Political Reform]]
#[[#Pensions and welfare|Pensions and Welfare]]
#[[#Education|Education]]
#[[#European Union|Relationship with the EU]]
#[[#Civil liberties|Civil liberties]]
#[[#Environment|Environment]]

===Deficit===
In order to tackle the [[budget deficit]] and [[national debt]], the agreement detailed &quot;significantly accelerated reduction in the structural deficit&quot; over the Parliament, with £6 billion cuts to be made in the financial year 2010-11, with plans to be published in an [[June 2010 United Kingdom budget|emergency budget]] within 50 days.

===Spending===
In spending, the agreement committed the government to a full Spending Review of government including a full Strategic Security and [[Defence Review]] to be completed by the Autumn, an increase in [[National Health Service]] funding in real terms and funding of disadvantaged pupils from outside the normal education budget. It would also establish an independent commission to review the long term affordability of public sector pensions, and restore the earnings link for the basic state pension from April 2011. Britain's [[Nuclear weapons and the United Kingdom|independent nuclear deterrent]] would be maintained, but the proposed [[British replacement of the Trident system|replacement of the Trident system]] would be reviewed for value for money.

===Tax===
{{seealso|Budget Responsibility and National Audit Act 2011}}
In [[Taxation in the United Kingdom|taxation]], the agreement committed to increasing the personal income tax allowance to £10,000 by 2015 to take many of those on the lowest salaries out of the tax system. The de-prioritising [[Inheritance Tax (United Kingdom)|Inheritance Tax]] cuts, and also laid out measures and arrangements on the issues of marriage, aviation, non-business capital gains taxes, and tax avoidance. The planned 1% rise in [[National Insurance]] will be partially scrapped.

===Banking===
In the [[Banking in the United Kingdom|banking system]], the agreement announced various reforms to &quot;avoid a repeat of Labour's financial crisis&quot; and stimulate the flow of credit, including the introduction of a banking levy, and controlling unacceptable [[bankers' bonuses]] and regulatory reform. 

===Immigration===
The section regarding [[Immigration to the United Kingdom since 1922|Immigration]], markedly shorter than all others, merely stated in one paragraph that there would be an annual cap on the number of non-EU workers admitted to live and work, with the mechanism decided later. Child detention for immigration purposes would also end.

===Political reform===
{{seealso|Fixed-term Parliaments Act 2011|Parliamentary Voting System and Constituencies Act 2011|Scotland Bill 2010-11}}
As part of reform of the political system, the parties agreed to creating [[Fixed-term election|fixed-term parliaments]]. An early motion would set the date of the [[next United Kingdom general election]] as the first Thursday of May 2015, with later legislation establishing five year fixed terms and introducing a new minimum of 55% of MPs supporting a motion before [[Dissolution of the Parliament of the United Kingdom|Parliament could be dissolved]] outside this timetable.

Both parties would [[Whip (politics)|ensure their MPs voted for]] the introduction of a [[Referendums in the United Kingdom|Referendum Bill]] on [[United Kingdom alternative vote referendum|the question of whether]] the electoral system for electing MPs to the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] should change from [[first-past-the-post]] to [[Alternative Vote]], and whether MPs constituencies should be changed in size or number.

On the issue of [[devolution]], the parties agreed to establish a committee on the [[West Lothian question]] (Scottish MPs in Westminster voting on English issue), implement the [[Commission on Scottish Devolution]] proposals, and offer a referendum on further devolution for [[Wales]].

Other political reform measures included introducing the power to recall MPs, bringing forward the [[Wright Committee]] proposals for Commons reform, and introducing proposals for reform of the [[House of Lords]] by December 2010, review local government and voter registration.

===Pensions and welfare===
{{seealso|Equitable Life (Payments) Act 2010}}
In pensions, compulsory retirement at 65 would be abolished, although the earliest age for the state pension would be increased from 65 to 66, from a date no earlier than 2016 for men, 2020 for women. Changes would be made to the [[Jobseeker's Allowance]] and welfare to work systems, including a rule that receipt of benefits would be conditional on willingness to work. Payments would be made to [[The Equitable Life Assurance Society|Equitable Life]] policy holders.

===Education===
{{seealso|Academies Act 2010}}
A 'significant' funding premium for children from poorer backgrounds will be established, incentivising schools to take them in and giving them more resources to devote to them. In [[Education in the United Kingdom|schools]], [[Free school (England)|new providers]] would be allowed to enter the state schooling system where demanded, schools would be granted greater freedom over the [[National Curriculum (England, Wales and Northern Ireland)|National Curriculum]], and schools would be &quot;held properly accountable.&quot; The parties would await [[John Browne, Baron Browne of Madingley|Lord Browne's]] [[Browne Review|proposals]] for [[Higher education in the United Kingdom|higher education]] with the agreement stating the Liberal Democrats may abstain if they do not like proposed changes (i.e. if there was to be an increase in tuition fees).

===European Union===
{{seealso|European Union Act 2011}}
As part of the agreement the parties ruled out joining the [[euro]] while the coalition was in force. The parties agreed Britain would be a &quot;positive participant&quot; in the [[European Union]], although there would be &quot;no further transfer of sovereignty or powers over the course of the next Parliament&quot;, ensured by amendment of the [[European Communities Act 1972 (UK)|1972 European Communities Act]] requiring referendums on future treaties, and requiring [[primary legislation]] before any [[Passerelle Clause]] could be enacted, and through examination of a possible [[United Kingdom Sovereignty Bill]]. Other measures include non-participation in establishment of a [[European Public Prosecutor]], limiting the [[Working Time Directive]], deciding the stance on the forthcoming EU budget, and pressuring the [[European Parliament]] to abolish its [[Seat of the European Parliament in Strasbourg|seat]] in [[Strasbourg]] and maintain only a [[Espace Léopold|single seat]] in [[Brussels]].

===Civil liberties===
{{seealso|Identity Documents Act 2010|Protection of Freedoms Bill 2011}}
Agreement on [[Civil liberties in the United Kingdom|civil liberties]] included measures to &quot;reverse the substantial erosion of civil liberties under the Labour Government and roll back state intrusion.&quot; This included the scrapping of the [[National identity card (United Kingdom)|National Identity Card]] and register, the [[British passport#Next Generation biometric passports and national identity registration|next generation biometric passport]] and the [[ContactPoint]] database. The Scottish model of implementation of the [[United Kingdom National DNA Database]] was to be extended to the whole of the United Kingdom. The [[Freedom of Information Act 2000|Freedom of Information Act]] would be extended, and a Freedom (Great Repeal) Bill is to be introduced. Other reviews, reinforcements and repeals would take place in the fields of the right to [[jury trial|trial by jury]], the right to [[Demonstration (people)|non-violent protest]], [[English defamation law|libel laws]] and [[freedom of speech]], [[anti-terrorism legislation]], regulation of [[CCTV]], storage of internet and email records, and creation of new [[criminal law|criminal offences]]. Fingerprinting of children at school without parental permission was to be outlawed.

===Environment===
In pursuit of the parties' policies on creation of a &quot;a low carbon and eco-friendly economy&quot;, a range of measures would be adopted.

In [[Transport in the United Kingdom|transport]], a [[High-speed rail in the United Kingdom|high speed rail network]] would be established, while the [[Expansion of London Heathrow Airport|proposed third runway]] at [[London Heathrow Airport]] would be cancelled, and no new runways would be approved for [[London Gatwick Airport]] or [[London Stansted Airport]].

The legislation required for the [[Nuclear power in the United Kingdom|building new nuclear power stations]] would proceed, without public subsidy for the projects. Any new [[coal-fired power station]]s would be required to implement [[carbon capture and storage]], while the targets for energy from renewable sources would be increased, subject to the advice of the [[Climate Change Committee]].

Other measures include a [[smart grid]], [[smart meter|smart meters]] and [[feed-in tariff]]s, a green investment bank would be created, and promotion of [[anaerobic digestion]] of waste for energy, [[marine energy]], home energy improvement, green spaces and wildlife corridors, and electric car recharging networks. [[Home Information Pack]]s would be abolished, albeit retaining the energy performance certificates. Import or export of illegal timber would be criminalised.

==Final agreement==
The initial agreement published on 12 May 2010 stated that it would be followed &quot;in due course by a final Coalition Agreement, covering the full range of policy and including foreign, defence and domestic policy issues&quot; which were not covered in the initial agreement. [[David Cameron]], [[Nick Clegg]], [[George Osborne]], [[Theresa May]] and [[Vince Cable]] held a press conference at [[HM Treasury]] to unveil the final Coalition Agreement. The final agreement is based around three core-values shared by both parties &quot;'''Freedom, fairness and responsibility'''&quot;.

==See also==
*[[Local Government Act 2010]]
*[[Postal Services Act 2011]]
*[[Savings Accounts and Health in Pregnancy Grant Act 2010]]
*[[Superannuation Act 2010]]
*[[United Kingdom coalition government 2010 to present]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/election_2010/8677088.stm At-a-glance: Cameron coalition's policy plans] BBC News, 13 May 2010

==External links==
*[http://programmeforgovernment.hmg.gov.uk/ '''The Coalition: Our Programme For Government]
*[http://www.conservatives.com/~/media/Files/Downloadable%20Files/agreement.ashx?dl=true Interim agreement (pdf)]
*[http://programmeforgovernment.hmg.gov.uk/files/2010/05/coalition-programme.pdf Final agreement (pdf)]

{{David Cameron}}
{{Nick Clegg}}
{{Cameron Cabinet}}
{{UK Conservative Party}}
{{UK Liberal Democrats}}

[[Category:British ministries]]
[[Category:Coalition governments of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:David Cameron]]
[[Category:Nick Clegg]]
[[Category:2010 in British politics]]
[[Category:2010 establishments in the United Kingdom]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
