<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27367747" ns="0" title="Bakersfield City Council"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|current elected officials|List of elected officials in Bakersfield}}
{{Infobox Legislature
 | background_color   = #FFC94B
 | name               = Bakersfield City Council
 | legislature        =
 | coa_pic            =  
 | coa_res            =
 | coa_alt            =
 | house_type         = unicameral
 | leader1_type       = Presiding Officer
 | leader1            = [[Mayor of Bakersfield|Mayor]]
 | members            = 7
 | committees1        = Budget &amp; Finance,&lt;br&gt;Community Services,&lt;br&gt;Legislative &amp; Litigation,&lt;br&gt;Personnel,&lt;br&gt;Planning &amp; Development,&lt;br&gt;Safe Neighborhoods,&lt;br&gt;Water Resources
  | voting_system1     = [[Single-winner voting systems|Single-winner]]
 | last_election1     = November 2, 2010
 | session_room       =
 | session_res        =
 | session_alt        =
 | meeting_place      = City Council Chambers&lt;br&gt;Bakersfield City Hall&lt;br&gt;1501 Truxtun Ave.&lt;br&gt;Bakersfield, CA 93301
 | website            = [http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/mayor_council/index.htm Mayor &amp; City Council Homepage]
}}

The '''Bakersfield City Council''' is the main governing body for [[Bakersfield, California|Bakersfield]], [[California]]. Under the [[council-manager]] form of government, the city council is the most powerful branch of government. It has seven members who represent seven wards. The city council meetings are presided over by the elected mayor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/mayor_council/formofgovt.htm About Bakersfield's Form of Government]. City of Bakersfield. Accessed: 05-14-2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Powers and duties==
The powers and duties are listed in Article III of the Bakersfield City Charter. Their primary function is the passing of ordinances for: raising revenue, appropriating money from the treasury, and regulations for the city. The specific duties, which ordinances passed to fulfill, are listed in Article III, section 12. There are too many to list here, but generally include all powers a city would need to provide proper services and maintain order for its citizens.&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article III, Section 12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Ordinances are voted on by the city council and a majority vote is needed to pass it. However, approval by the mayor or other official is not needed for the measure to become active. As a result, any measure with enough votes will become active 30 days after the vote, unless the council votes to repeal it.&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article III, Section 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

Council members are elected to four year terms. Elections are staggered every two years. As a result, only half of the members are up for reelection during one election cycle.&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article III, Section 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Representative Districts (Wards)==
City council members are elected from one of seven wards. Each ward is drawn to represent an equal number of citizens. They are redrawn from time to time (typically after the [[United States Census]]) to update changes in population and boundaries.&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article II, Section 3.&lt;/ref&gt; Wards are drawn to represent different regions of Bakersfield; however, the boundaries are not exact. This is primarily for two reasons. Bakersfield’s regions have sections that are not apart of the city, and do not have representation. Also, each region is not of equal size. For example, the southwest, which is densely populated, requires two wards. The northeast, which is sparsely populated, shares its ward with part of the northwest.

The seven wards generally represent the following regions:
*Ward 1:[[List of neighborhoods in Bakersfield#Southeast|Southeast]]
*Ward 2:[[Downtown Bakersfield|Downtown]] and [[East Bakersfield]]
*Ward 3:[[Northeast Bakersfield|Northeast]]
*Ward 4:[[Northwest Bakersfield|Northwest]]
*Ward 5:[[Southwest Bakersfield#Seven Oaks|Southwest (Seven Oaks)]]
*Ward 6:[[Southwest Bakersfield#Stockdale|Southwest (Stockdale)]]
*Ward 7:[[List of neighborhoods in Bakersfield#South Bakersfield|South Bakersfield]]

==Committees==
The city council has several committees. Each committee examines potential ordinances and issues related to specific topics. Each is made up of three council members, one of which is the chairman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/mayor_council/council_committees.htm Council Committees]. City of Bakersfield. Accessed:05-14-2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The committees are:
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
*Budget &amp; Finance
*Community Services
*Legislative &amp; Litigation
*Personnel
{{col-break}}
*Planning &amp; Development
*Safe Neighborhoods
*Water Resources
{{col-end}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/mayor_council/index.htm Mayor &amp; City Council Homepage]

{{City of Bakersfield}}
{{Government of Bakersfield}}

[[Category:Government of Bakersfield, California|c]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
