<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27379479" ns="0" title="Bakersfield City Manager"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{notability|date=June 2010}}
{{Infobox Political post
|post            = City Manager
|body            = Bakersfield
|insignia        =  
|insigniasize    =  
|image           =
|alt             =
|incumbent       = Alan Tandy
|appointer       = [[Bakersfield City Council|City Council]]
|appointerpost   = Head of Executive Branch
|termlength      =
|formation       = {{startdate|1957}}
|salary          = $220,000
|website         = [http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/citymanager/index.htm City Manager's Office]
}}

The '''City Manager''' of Bakersfield is the appointed head of the [[executive branch]]. The position was created after 1957, when the role of [[Mayor of Bakersfield|mayor]] (which was the previous head) was split into two new positions. Under the [[council-manager]] form of government, the City Manager is responsible for executing ordinances passed by the [[Bakersfield City Council|city council]] and running the departments that make up the city. His office is currently located in [[Bakersfield City Hall|City Hall North]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/citymanager/index.htm City Manager's Office]. City of Bakersfield. Accessed: 05-15-2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The city manager is appointed by the city council. His service can end in one of two ways. Either he: resigns, or by a vote of removal by the city council. The vote to appoint and remove is one of the few votes the mayor can cast.&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article III, Section 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Duties==
The city manager has eight responsibilities, as laid out in the City Charter. They are:
{{&quot;|
#To see that all the laws and ordinances are faithfully enforced by the heads of the departments;
#To attend all meetings of the Council at which his attendance may be required by that body;
#To recommend for adoption to the Council such measures as he may deem necessary or expedient;
#To keep the Council fully advised of the financial condition of the municipality and its future needs;
#To prepare and submit to the auditor a tentative budget for the next fiscal year;
#To appoint and remove, except as herein otherwise provided, all officers and subordinate officers and employees of the Department, in both the classified and unclassified service; all appointments to be upon merit and fitness alone;
#To exercise control over all other departments and divisions that may be hereafter created by the Council, and assigned to his management, not in conflict with the provisions of this charter;
#To investigate all complaints, in regard to the service maintained by any and all public utilities in the City, and to take such proceedings as may be necessary to correct the abuse, if any.|''Bakersfield City Charter''|&lt;ref&gt;''Bakersfield City Charter''. Article IV, Section 36.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Separation of Powers vs. Check and Balance==
There is [[separation of power]] between the [[legislative branch]] (city council) and the [[executive branch]] (city manager), as only the city manager and not the city council can carry out the eight responsibilities listed above. However, there is no check and balance system between the two branches. Since the city manager is appointed by the city council, the executive branch is subordinate to the legislative branch. Also, the city council has the authority to vote for the removal of the city manager.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.bakersfieldcity.us/administration/citymanager/index.htm City Manager's Office]
{{City of Bakersfield}}
{{Government of Bakersfield}}

[[Category:Government of Bakersfield, California|c]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
