<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2739286" ns="0" title="Bulls–Knicks rivalry"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float: right; clear: right; margin: 0 0 1em 1em; width: 23em;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; background-color: {{{Color|LightSteelBlue}}};&quot; | Chicago Bulls-New York Knicks
|-
! style=&quot;background: #E0E7EF;&quot; colspan=&quot;3&quot; | History
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align: top;&quot; | '''Post Season Meetings''' || 24-12 (CHI)
|-
|[[1981 NBA Playoffs|1981 Eastern Conference First Round]] || Bulls won, 2–0
|-
|[[1989 NBA Playoffs|1989 Eastern Conference Semifinals]] || Bulls won, 4–2
|-
|[[1991 NBA Playoffs|1991 Eastern Conference First Round]] || Bulls won, 3–0
|-
|[[1992 NBA Playoffs|1992 Eastern Conference Semifinals]] || Bulls won, 4–3
|-
|[[1993 NBA Playoffs|1993 Eastern Conference Finals]] || Bulls won, 4–2
|-
|[[1994 NBA Playoffs|1994 Eastern Conference Semifinals]] || Knicks won, 4–3
|-
|[[1996 NBA Playoffs|1996 Eastern Conference Semifinals]] || Bulls won, 4–1
|}
The '''Bulls-Knicks rivalry''' was an American [[National Basketball Association rivalries|professional basketball rivalry]] between the [[Chicago Bulls]] and the [[New York Knicks]] over a roughly six year period from [[1989 NBA Playoffs|1989]]-[[1996 NBA Playoffs|1996]]. The intensity of the rivalry was unique due to a number of factors. These included the frequency with which the teams competed against one another in high-stakes contests, the reputations of the team's respective cities, and personnel changes and conflicts between the teams.

==Origins==
The early days of the Bulls-Knicks rivalry began when the teams met in the [[1989 NBA Playoffs]]. The Knicks won their first Atlantic Division title since 1971 with a 52-30 record and also clinched the 2nd seed in the Eastern Conference. Meanwhile, 6th-seeded Chicago won just 47 games, but were led by reigning NBA MVP and Defensive Player of the Year Michael Jordan. The Bulls stole Game 1 at [[Madison Square Garden|the Garden]], and won all 3 games in [[Chicago Stadium]] to upset the favored Knicks in 6. The teams met again two years later in the [[1991 NBA Playoffs]], and this time the roles were reversed. The Bulls won an Eastern Conference-best 61 games, their previous franchise-high, as well as the Central Division title. On the opposite end of the spectrum, the Knicks limped into the playoffs at 39-43 with the 8th seed. Chicago cruised past New York in a 3-game sweep, winning each game by an average of 20 points.

==Bulls First Three-Peat==
In {{nbay|1991|end}}, the [[Chicago Bulls|Bulls]], led by [[Michael Jordan]] and [[Scottie Pippen]], were on their way to their [[1992 NBA Finals|second straight title]] when they met up with the physical play of the [[New York Knicks]] led by [[Patrick Ewing]] and new head coach [[Pat Riley]] in the Eastern Conference Semifinals. The series went to a decisive [[List of NBA game sevens|Game 7]] which the Bulls won 110-81 to advance. This series kick-started the intense rivalry between the Bulls and Knicks in the 1990s. It also made the Knicks into an Eastern Conference powerhouse, replacing the [[Detroit Pistons]] and [[Boston Celtics]]. This series was the first of two times the Bulls faced a Game 7 in the six seasons they won a championship, the other with the [[Indiana Pacers]] in the [[1998 NBA Playoffs|1998 Eastern Conference Finals]]. This particular series became heated, with several players, particularly [[Michael Jordan]], [[Xavier McDaniel]], [[Scottie Pippen]], and [[Greg Anthony]] getting into arguments.

Shortly afterwards, there was a moment of peace in the rivalry, with Ewing, Jordan, and Pippen winning gold medals as members of the &quot;[[United States men's national basketball team|Dream Team]]&quot; at the [[1992 Summer Olympics|Summer Olympics in Barcelona]]. Ewing and Jordan, along with [[Chris Mullin (basketball)|Chris Mullin]] of the [[Golden State Warriors]], are the only basketball players to have won gold medals as both amateurs and professionals, having won at the [[1984 Summer Olympics|Los Angeles Olympics in 1984]]. Jordan and Pippen are the only players to have won an NBA championship and Olympic gold medal in the same year, though Pippen became the only player to accomplish this feat twice, as he would play for the Bulls in {{nbafy|1996}} and for Team USA at the [[1996 Summer Olympics|Atlanta Olympics]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Dream Team's Sleepwalk Ends with Gold Medal|date=August 4, 1996|first=Sam|last=Smith|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[1992-93 NBA season|following season]], the Knicks were able to finish ahead of the Bulls in the regular season and had home court advantage against the Bulls in the Eastern Conference Finals. The series had the notable highlight of [[John Starks (basketball)|John Starks]] dunking over Horace Grant and several Bulls defenders late in Game 2. However, despite losing the 1st 2 games, the Bulls made a remarkable comeback by winning the next four in a row (by doing so, they became the first team in NBA history to overcome a 2-0 series deficit in a best-of-7 series, and the fourth team overall), including a 97-94 Game 5 victory in [[Madison Square Garden]]. The game was quite notable as Knicks [[Forward (basketball)|forward]] Charles Smith was stopped four straight times by a series of blocked shots and stripped balls in the final seconds while trying to score. The Bulls won Game 6 96-88 to advance to the [[1993 NBA Finals|NBA Finals]] where they beat the [[Phoenix Suns]] in 6 for their first [[three-peat]].

==Continuation of rivalry==
With Michael Jordan's absence in {{nbay|1993}}, the Knicks now had the upper hand against the Bulls and they proved that by winning the second best record in the East in the regular season. The Bulls, now led by Pippen and newcomer [[Toni Kukoč]], met the Knicks in the second round of the playoff where the series went to seven games. In one of the most argued calls in NBA history a questionable foul was called by [[Hue Hollins]] (who ironically was the same referee who officiated a controversial finish in Game 5 of the 1993 Eastern Conference Finals, and arguably opted not to call a foul on Charles Smith's multiple putback attempts in the waning seconds) in the closing seconds of Game 5 against Pippen which gave the Knicks [[Hubert Davis]] two free throws to turn a one-point deficit into a one-point victory for the Knicks.

After a blowout Bulls win in game six, the Knicks were able to advance past the Bulls with a series-clinching 87-77 win, but would eventually lose to the [[Houston Rockets]] in the [[1994 NBA Finals|NBA Finals]], which denied New York City the distinction of having both NBA and [[Stanley Cup|NHL championship]]s in the same year (Chicago saw this same verdict in 1992. Though the Bulls won their championship that year, the [[Chicago Blackhawks|Blackhawks]] lost [[1992 Stanley Cup Finals|theirs]]), as the [[Madison Square Garden|Knicks home court]] hosted the [[New York Rangers]] [[Curse of 1940|first Stanley Cup celebration in 54 years]], following their win over the [[Vancouver Canucks]] in Game 7 of the [[1994 Stanley Cup Finals|Stanley Cup Finals]] during the NBA Finals. This was the only time the Knicks were able to beat the Bulls in the playoffs during this rivalry. Also, all the games in the series were won by the home team and the Knicks had home court advantage in the series.

In {{nbay|1994}}, Jordan returned in the latter half of the regular season. In his return to Madison Square Garden, Jordan scored 55 points and picked up the victory for the Bulls. This game lifted Jordan's confidence after a mediocre performance in his &quot;comeback game&quot; against the Indiana Pacers. The two teams didn't meet in the playoffs that season but the animosity between the two teams still grew.

During the Bulls' record-setting [[1995–96 Chicago Bulls season|1995–96 season]], they suffered their worst loss of the season to the Knicks, 102-74 in March.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=So Much for Karma. Knicks Stomp Bulls|date=March 11, 1996|first=Mike|last=Wise|newspaper=New York Times|page=C1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=New York Nightmare: Knicks Return to Old Ways in Rout of Bulls|date=March 11, 1996|first=Terry|last=Armour|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two months later, they defeated the Knicks in the Eastern Conference Semifinals in 5.

During the Bulls' second three-peat run, the Bulls only met the Knicks once in the playoffs; specifically in 1996 when the Bulls once again defeated the Knicks. It was also during this period that other teams in the East grew to be contenders, such as the [[Indiana Pacers]], [[Orlando Magic]], and the [[Miami Heat]].  All of these teams had their own heated battles with either the Bulls or Knicks in the playoffs. The rivalry died out after the second departure of Michael Jordan in which the Bulls fell out of prominence. The Knicks themselves started to rebuild when veterans such as John Starks, [[Anthony Mason (basketball)|Anthony Mason]], [[Charles Oakley]],  and [[Derek Harper]] were all traded. However, in 1999, a year after the Bulls' second three-peat, the Knicks made history by become the first #8 seed to ever make the NBA Finals.

In the 1990s both Knicks finals appearances (1994 and their [[Cinderella (sports)|Cinderella]] march of {{nbafy|1999}}) followed a Bulls' three-peat, but the Knicks lost both times to a team from Texas.

==Christmas Day Appearances==
The two teams faced each other on Christmas Day for the first time in {{nbay|1986|start}}, with the Knicks winning 86-85 on a last second jumper by Patrick Ewing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ewing, at Buzzer, Steals the Show|date=December 26, 1986|first=Sam|last=Goldaper|newspaper=New York Times|page=D7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Knicks, Ewing Get Better of Bulls|date=December 26, 1986|first=Bob|last=Sakamoto|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first of two meetings between Ewing and [[Michael Jordan]] on [[National Basketball Association Christmas games|Christmas Day]].

During the 1990s, each Christmas (except for {{nbay|1998|start}}) revived the rivalry, as it featured a game involving either (or both) team(s).&lt;ref name=Christmas/&gt; Both teams played against each other in {{nbay|1992|start}} and {{nbay|1994|start}},&lt;ref name=Christmas/&gt; and would have played each other in 1998, if there had not been a lockout.&lt;ref name=Lockout&gt;{{cite news|title=Selling Point|date=November 29, 1998|first=Steve|last=Rosenbloom|newspaper=Chicago Tribune|page=1|quote=The NBA told NBC it has canceled the Bulls and the rest of the traditional Christmas doubleheader&amp;mdash;Bulls-Knicks and Lakers-Suns.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The only year during the 1990s in which neither team played on Christmas Day was {{nbay|1995|start}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Magic ground Rockets 92-90|date=December 26, 1995|first=David|last=DuPree|newspaper=USA Today|page=1C}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Bulls also played on Christmas in {{nbay|1990|start}}, {{nbay|1991|start}}, {{nbay|1993|start}}, {{nbay|1996|start}}, and {{nbay|1997|start}}, the Knicks in {{nbay|1999|start}}.&lt;ref name=Christmas/&gt; Both teams met again in {{nbay|2010|start}}, their first Christmas confrontation in 16 years, with the Knicks winning 103-95.&lt;ref name=Christmas&gt;{{cite news|title=Feeling Fuzzy About Holiday Slot|date=December 25, 2010|first=Howard|last=Beck|newspaper=New York Times|page=B11}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://sports.yahoo.com/nba/recap?gid=2010122518&amp;print=1|title=Christmas surprise: Knicks win one with defense|date=December 25, 2010|accessdate=December 26, 2010|first=Brian|last=Mahoney|agency=Associated Press|publisher=Yahoo! Sports}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Recent developments==
Prior to the 2005 season, the Knicks traded first-round draft choices in 2006 and 2007 to the Bulls for center [[Eddy Curry]], who missed the Bulls' 2005 playoff run with a congenital heart defect.  When the Knicks finished the 2005-06 season at 23-59, the Bulls' good fortune turned into a gold mine, as the 2006 pick became the second overall choice following the draft lottery. The Bulls used the selection on [[LaMarcus Aldridge]] but traded him to the [[Portland Trail Blazers]] for the fourth overall selection, [[Louisiana State University|LSU]] forward [[Tyrus Thomas]]. Thomas struggled in his time in Chicago before being traded to the [[Charlotte Bobcats]] in 2010, while Aldridge has blossomed into a young star.

However, the Bulls still got the much better end of deal as Curry has struggled in New York. Additionally, the Bulls swapped picks with the Knicks in the 2007 NBA draft, and yielded the #9 pick. They used their pick to draft of the [[University of Florida]] forward [[Joakim Noah]]. In the summer of 2008, the Bulls and Knicks both heavily courted former Suns coach [[Mike D'Antoni]]. D'Antoni's style was said to better suit the Bulls roster, but in the end, D'Antoni opted for the Knicks. Despite the Knicks having better odds, the Bulls won the [[2008 NBA Draft]] lottery and selected [[Derrick Rose]] with the 1st overall pick, putting a temporary dent in D'Antoni's rebuilding plans in New York.

==Causes==
Many felt that the significance of the rivalry was due to the bragging rights of the two biggest cities in the East: the [[Big Apple]] vs. the [[Windy City]]. Many also believed that the rivalry started when the Bulls traded Charles Oakley to New York for [[Bill Cartwright]]&lt;!--reasons why to be cited--&gt;. While others felt that the rivalry was between Jordan and Ewing, since they were rivals since their college days. It was also the hardnosed physical play of the two teams that made the rivalry intense, especially when both teams were battling it out in the playoffs. The matchup between Jordan and Knicks shooting guard John Starks also brought the rivalry a bit of drama as the two were often in each other's face, while both players also showcased a number of highlight dunks on the opposing team. Despite the Knicks not winning an NBA title or beating the Bulls in a series while Jordan was in the league, this rivalry was still considered the most contentious of the mid-1990s.

==Head to head==
The results in brackets concern the play-off games.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:95%&quot;
|-
! Season
! at [[Chicago Bulls]]&lt;br&gt;Bulls-Knicks
! at [[New York Knicks]]&lt;br&gt;Knicks-Bulls
! Total&lt;br&gt;Bulls-Knicks
|-
| [[1966-67 NBA season|1966-67]]
| 105-'''124''', 98-'''103''', '''110'''-107, '''131'''-116, 103-'''106'''
| '''116'''-104, '''133'''-132, '''122'''-121, 103-'''117'''
| '''3-6''' 
|-
| [[1967-68 NBA season|1967-68]]
| '''106'''-96, '''102'''-100, 118-'''126''', 103-'''112'''
| '''125'''-123, '''121'''-99, '''109'''-101
| '''2-5'''
|-
| [[1968-69 NBA season|1968-69]]
| 83-'''94''', '''102'''-101, 98-'''105'''
| 96-'''100''', '''119'''-97, '''114'''-107
| '''2-4''' 
|-
| [[1969-70 NBA season|1969-70]]
| 87-'''116''', 99-'''108''', 117-'''120'''
| '''114'''-99, '''116'''-96, '''123'''-104
| '''0-6''' 
|-
| [[1970-71 NBA season|1970-71]]
| 98-'''106''', '''109'''-103
| 96-'''99''', '''98'''-87, 102-'''109'''
| '''3-2''' 
|-
| [[1971-72 NBA season|1971-72]]
| '''122'''-96, '''116'''-91, 99-'''102'''
| '''100'''-99, 108-'''113''', 
| '''3-2''' 
|-
| [[1972-73 NBA season|1972-73]]
| '''90'''-86, '''84'''-83
| '''97'''-83, 98-'''100'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[1973-74 NBA season|1973-74]]
| '''115'''-97, 80-'''108''', 
| 69-'''85''', '''89'''-80
| '''2-2''' 
|-
| [[1974-75 NBA season|1974-75]]
| 91-'''104''', '''101'''-84
| 90-'''95''', 94-'''97'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[1975-76 NBA season|1975-76]]
| 93-'''94''', 95-'''110'''
| '''96'''-89, '''93'''-85
| '''0-4''' 
|-
| [[1976-77 NBA season|1976-77]]
| '''108'''-88, '''105'''-87
| '''108'''-91, '''123'''-103
| '''2-2''' 
|-
| [[1977-78 NBA season|1977-78]]
| 97-'''99''', '''129'''-117
| '''112'''-103, '''108'''-96
| '''1-3''' 
|-
| [[1978-79 NBA season|1978-79]]
| 94-'''118''', '''107'''-104
| 96-'''101''', 143-'''148'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[1979-80 NBA season|1979-80]]
| 102-'''120'''
| '''124'''-117
| '''0-2''' 
|-
| [[1980-81 NBA season|1980-81]]
| '''130'''-121, '''117'''-114, 94-'''112'''&lt;br&gt;''('''115'''-114)''
| '''105'''-97, 97-'''101''', '''127'''-117&lt;br&gt;''(80-'''90''')''
| '''3-3'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(2-0)'''''
|-
| [[1981-82 NBA season|1981-82]]
| 108-'''111''', '''131'''-107
| '''121'''-106, 139-'''140''', 116-'''120'''
| '''3-2''' 
|-
| [[1982-83 NBA season|1982-83]]
| '''91'''-85, 91-'''93''', 103-'''120'''
| '''119'''-109, '''94'''-79
| '''1-4''' 
|-
| [[1983-84 NBA season|1983-84]]
| '''102'''-96, 111-'''113''', 96-'''113'''
| 107-'''113''', '''109'''-92, '''115'''-113
| '''2-4''' 
|-
| [[1984-85 NBA season|1984-85]]
| '''95'''-93, '''113'''-97, '''109'''-104
| 106-'''121''', '''119'''-113, '''106'''-97
| '''4-2''' 
|-
| [[1985-86 NBA season|1985-86]]
| 96-'''113''', '''114'''-101, '''111'''-98
| 94-'''97''', '''118'''-111, 96-'''106'''
| '''4-2''' 
|-
| [[1986-87 NBA season|1986-87]]
| '''101'''-99, 109-'''110''', '''115'''-96
| 103-'''108''', '''86'''-85, 108-'''112''', 
| '''4-2''' 
|-
| [[1987-88 NBA season|1987-88]]
| '''97'''-95, '''131'''-122
| '''90'''-89, '''110'''-98, 118-'''121'''
| '''3-2''' 
|-
| [[1988-89 NBA season|1988-89]]
| '''108'''-106, '''129'''-124, '''104'''-100&lt;br&gt;''('''111'''-88, '''106'''-93, '''113'''-111)''
| '''126'''-117, '''122'''-104 &lt;br&gt;''(109-'''120''', '''114'''-97, '''121'''-114)''
| '''3-2'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(4-2)''''' 
|-
| [[1989-90 NBA season|1989-90]]
| '''117'''-109, '''107'''-106
| '''109'''-106, 108-'''111'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[1990-91 NBA season|1990-91]]
| '''108'''-98, '''108'''-106&lt;br&gt;''('''126'''-85, '''89'''-79)''
| 92-'''102''', 91-'''101'''&lt;br&gt;''(94-'''103''')''
| '''4-0'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(3-0)''''' 
|-
| [[1991-92 NBA season|1991-92]]
| '''99'''-89, '''99'''-98&lt;br&gt;''(89-'''94''', '''86'''-78, '''96'''-88, '''110'''-81)''
| 85-'''106''', 90-'''96'''&lt;br&gt;''(86-'''94''', '''93'''-86, '''100'''-86)''
| '''4-0'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(4-3)''''' 
|-
| [[1992-93 NBA season|1992-93]]
| '''89'''-77, 98-'''104'''&lt;br&gt;''('''103'''-83, '''105'''-95, '''96'''-88)''
| '''112'''-75, '''89'''-84&lt;br&gt;''('''98'''-90, '''96'''-91, 94-'''97''')''
| '''1-3'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(4-2)''''' 
|-
| [[1993-94 NBA season|1993-94]]
| '''98'''-86, 76-'''92'''&lt;br&gt;''('''104'''-102, '''95'''-83, '''93'''-79)''
| '''86'''-68, '''87'''-78&lt;br&gt;''('''90'''-86, '''96'''-91, '''87'''-86, '''87'''-77)''
| '''1-3'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(3-4)''''' 
|-
| [[1994-95 NBA season|1994-95]]
| '''107'''-104, '''111'''-90
| '''93'''-89, 111-'''113'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[1995-96 NBA season|1995-96]]
| '''101'''-94, '''107'''-86&lt;br&gt;''('''91'''-84, '''91'''-80, '''94'''-81)''
| 79-'''99''', '''104'''-72&lt;br&gt;''('''102'''-99, 91-'''94''')''
| '''3-1'''&lt;br&gt;'''''(4-1)''''' 
|-
| [[1996-97 NBA season|1996-97]]
| '''88'''-87, 101-'''103'''
| '''97'''-93, 103-'''105'''
| '''2-2''' 
|-
| [[1997-98 NBA season|1997-98]]
| '''100'''-82, '''111'''-109
| 89-'''90''', 89-'''102'''
| '''4-0''' 
|-
| [[1998-99 NBA season|1998-99]]
| 68-'''73''', '''76'''-63
| '''79'''-63
| '''1-2''' 
|-
| [[1999-2000 NBA season|1999-00]]
| 74-'''84''', 
| '''95'''-88, '''78'''-67
| '''0-3''' 
|-
| [[2000-01 NBA season|2000-01]]
| 86-'''91''', '''81'''-72
| '''95'''-68, '''101'''-80
| '''1-3''' 
|-
| [[2001-02 NBA season|2001-02]]
| '''84'''-79, '''113'''-109
| '''78'''-71, 101-'''104'''
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[2002-03 NBA season|2002-03]]
| '''101'''-94, '''100'''-98
| '''98'''-86
| '''2-1''' 
|-
| [[2003-04 NBA season|2003-04]]
| 96-'''101''', '''87'''-81
| 99-'''104''', '''96'''-82
| '''2-2''' 
|-
| [[2004-05 NBA season|2004-05]]
| '''86'''-84, '''92'''-91
| 86-'''88''', 94-'''102'''
| '''4-0''' 
|-
| [[2005-06 NBA season|2005-06]]
| '''106'''-104, 
| '''109'''-101, 101-'''108'''
| '''2-1''' 
|-
| [[2006-07 NBA season|2006-07]]
| '''102'''-85, '''98'''-69
| 95-'''106''', '''103'''-92
| '''3-1''' 
|-
| [[2007-08 NBA season|2007-08]]
| '''101'''-96, 100-'''105'''
| '''85'''-78, 83-'''100'''
| '''2-2''' 
|-
| [[2008-09 NBA season|2008-09]]
| '''105'''-100, '''110'''-103
| '''102'''-98
| '''2-1'''
|-
| [[2009-10 NBA season|2009-10]]
| '''98'''-89, '''118'''-85
| '''88'''-81, 109-'''115'''
| '''3-1'''
|-
| [[2010-11 NBA season|2010-11]]
| 112-'''120'''
| '''103'''-95, 90-'''103'''
| '''1-2'''
|}

===Statistics===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size:95%&quot;
|-
! 
! width=150 |[[Chicago Bulls]]
! width=150 |[[New York Knicks]]
|-bgcolor=#C0C0C0
| '''Total wins'''
| '''129'''
| '''107'''
|-
| '''At Chicago Bulls'''
| 83
| 37
|-
| '''At New York Knicks'''
| 46
| 70
|-bgcolor=#C0C0C0
| '''Regular season wins'''
| '''105'''
| '''95'''
|-
| '''At Chicago Bulls'''
| 65
| 36
|-
| '''At New York Knicks'''
| 40
| 59
|-bgcolor=#C0C0C0
| '''Playoff wins'''
| '''24'''
| '''12'''
|-
| '''At Chicago Bulls'''
| 18
| 1
|-
| '''At New York Knicks'''
| 6
| 11
|}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
*[[Bulls–Pistons rivalry]]
*[[Heat–Knicks rivalry]]
*[[National Basketball Association rivalries]]

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{Chicago Bulls}}
{{New York Knicks}}
{{NBA on NBC}}
{{NBA rivalries}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bulls–Knicks Rivalry}}
[[Category:National Basketball Association rivalries]]
[[Category:Chicago Bulls]]
[[Category:New York Knicks]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
