<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2749635" ns="0" title="King family (Emmerdale)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
'''The King family''' are a [[fictional]] [[family]] appearing on the [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]''.

==About the Kings==
The Kings were one of Emmerdales most popular families and also the most tragic.
Emmerdale bosses had previously tried to introduce two large families - The Calder/Weston clan in 2001 and the Marsdens in 2003 - but they were axed after failing to impress the viewers, leading producers to attempt it for the third time.
The King Family first arrived in [[Emmerdale]] in early 2004 consisting of father Tom, eldest son Jimmy and Jimmy's wife Sadie, and younger sons Matthew and Carl. They were later joined by the youngest King brother, Max. Within months of their arrival, they became viewer favourites and were set to become Emmerdales new version of the Tate clan. Ratings for Emmerdale began to beat Eastenders on frequent occasions from 2004–2007 and the Kings proved to be extremely popular with viewers. However, by the end of 2008, actors Charlie Kemp (Max), Patsy Kensit (Sadie), Ken Farrington (Tom) and Matt Healy (Matthew) had all quit the show, leading to producers writing their characters out in shocking exit plots. The Kings biggest plot was the Who Killed Tom King storyline (2006–2007) in which Tom was murdered on Christmas Day and 10 of the shows characters were all suspects.
They will always be remembered for providing Emmerdale with some of its biggest and most popular storylines but will also be remembered for being the unluckiest family in soap history.

==Main Plots==
Tom King begins a relationship with Charity Tate (Dingle) (2004)

Carl King starts a relationship with Chastity Dingle (2004)

Carl accidentally causes the death of Paul Marsden (2004)

Carl, Jimmy and Matthew cover up Paul's death (2004)

Matthew pressures Paul's widow, Siobhan, to leave the village (2004)

A close friend of Tom's dies of a heart attack (2004)

Sadie sets Charity up to destroy the wedding (2004)

Tom and Charitys Wedding ends in disaster (2005)

Charity sleeps with Jimmy and then leaves after revealing Sadie framed her (2005)

Jimmy nearly dies after being stabbed with a pitch fork by Daz Eden (2005)

Max accidentally hits Tom while drink driving but Tom survives (2005)

The Kings finally get Home Farm but Zoe Tate blows it up on the day they're due to move in (2005)

Max King dies in a car crash (2005)

Sadie and Matthew have an affair (2006)

The Kings show home explodes, killing 3 and nearly killing Jimmy and Sadie (2006)

In the showhome wreckage, Sadie hits Jimmy with a brick but he manages to survive (2006)

Doctors tell Matthew and Tom that there's a chance Jimmy won't walk again (2006)

Tom gets engaged to Rosemary Sinclair (2006)

Tom and Sadie are kidnapped by Cain Dingle and nearly die (2006)

Sadie leaves the village after the kidnap plot (2006)

Tom is pushed through a window and killed on his Wedding day (Christmas Day 2006)

Rosemary nearly dies after falling off a balcony (2007)

Tom's secret daughter Scarlet arrives (2007)

Carl reveals to Jimmy and Matthew he murdered Tom (May 2007)

Carl and Chastity break up (2007)

Scarlets aunt Lexi is revealed to actually be her half sister (2007)

Carl begins affair with Grace Barraclough - who is investigating Tom's murder (2007)

Grace Barraclough is killed after being hit by a lorry - it was hinted that Matthew organised this (2007)

Matthew begins affair with Perdy Hyde-Sinclair (2007)

Matthew is banged up for allegedly killing Rosemary (2007)

Rosemary is revealed to be alive but she kills herself with a gun (Christmas Day 2007)

Jimmy and Kellys Wedding ends the same way as Tom and Charitys (2007)

Carl begins relationship with Lexi (2008)

Matthew almost kills Carl with a golf club (2008)

Grayson takes the King brothers hostage and Carl gets shot but survives (2008)

Matthew gets engaged to Anna De Souza (2008)

Lexi tells Carl that she knows he murdered Tom (2008)

Matthew causes Anna's father, Donald, to have a heart attack and he dies (2008)

Matthew and Anna's wedding ends in chaos and Matthew and Carl have a shocking fight (2008)

Matthew is killed after trying to run Carl over in a van which crashes into the front wall at Home Farm (2008)

The day after Matthews death, the Kings are kicked out of Home Farm (2008)

Carl and Chastity nearly get back together (2008)

Jimmy is accidentally shot the day after Matthews funeral, but survives (2009)

Jimmy sleeps with Nicola De Souza (2009)

Carl and Lexi Nicholls get married despite the fact that Carl still loves Chastity (2009)

Nicola discovers that she is pregnant with Jimmy's baby (2009)

Lexi announces that she is pregnant with Carl's baby but suffers an ectopic pregnancy days later (2009)

Nicola goes into premature labour, giving birth to daughter Angelica (2009)

Lexi, still reeling about her inability to have children, kidnaps baby Angelica, taking her hostage on the hospital roof-top, in an effort to make Carl listen to what she wants. (2009)

Carl and Chastity re-unite. (2009)

Jimmy and Nicola Marry. (2010)

Carl cheats on Chas with Eve Jenson. Chas discovers this and secretly plots revenge. (2010)

Kelly Windsor causes Jimmy to get amnesia and fakes an affair, making Nicola want a divorce. (2011)

==Family members==
*[[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Thomas Albert &quot;Tom&quot; King]] (deceased) - Patriarch of the family, died in 2006. Played by [[Ken Farrington]], 2004-2006.
**Mary Grace King (deceased) - Tom's first wife, who died in 1986.
**[[Rosemary Sinclair|Rosemary Venitia King]] (née '''Oakwell''', previously '''Sinclair''') (deceased) - Tom's second wife, Matriarch of the King family. Played by [[Linda Thorson]], 2006-2007.
*[[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|James Frederick &quot;Jimmy&quot; King]] - Eldest son of Tom and Mary. Played by [[Nick Miles]], 2004-.
**[[Sadie King]] (née '''Campbell''', previously '''Sinclair''') - Jimmy's ex-wife. Played by [[Patsy Kensit]], 2004-2006.
** [[Nicola King]] (née '''Blackstock''', previously '''DeSouza''') - Jimmy's second wife and Angelica's mother. Played by [[Nicola Wheeler]], 2001-2006, 2007-
***Angelica King - Jimmy and Nicola's daughter. Born 6 August 2009.
***[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Elliot Windsor-King|Elliot Windsor-King]] - Jimmy and Kelly's son. Born in 2007
*[[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew Thomas King]] (deceased) - Second son of Tom and Mary. Played by [[Matt Healy]], died 2008. 2004-2008.
*[[Carl King (Emmerdale)|Carl King]] - Third son of Tom and Mary. Played by [[Tom Lister]], 2004-.
**[[Colleen King]] - Carl's ex-wife and mother of his children. Played by [[Melanie Ash]], 2004, 2005, 2010.
***[[List of minor Emmerdale characters#Thomas and Anya King|Thomas King]] - Son of Carl and Colleen. Played by [[Jack Ferguson (British actor)|Jack Ferguson]], 2004, 2005, 2006, 2010.
***[[List of minor Emmerdale characters#Thomas and Anya King|Andrea &quot;Anya&quot; King]] - Daughter of Carl and Colleen. Played by [[Ceryen Dean]], 2004, 2005, 2006, 2010.
**[[Lexi King|Alexandra &quot;Lexi&quot; King]] (née '''Nicholls''') - Carl's ex-wife and Scarlett's half sister. Played by [[Sally Oliver]] 2007-2009.
*[[Max King (Emmerdale)|Maxwell Harold &quot;Max&quot; King]] (deceased) - Youngest son of Tom and Mary, twin of Georgina died in 2005. Played by [[Charlie Kemp]], 2005.
*Georgina King -  Only daughter of Tom and Mary. Never been seen on screen and is estranged from her family. Max's twin sister.
&lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[File:Max King.png|right|thumb|150px|Charlie Kemp as Max King]] --&gt;
*[[Scarlett Nicholls|Scarlett Mary Nicholls]] - Played by [[Kelsey-Beth Crossley]], Carrie's illegitimate daughter with Millionaire Tom King- 2007-2011.
* [[Carrie Nicholls|Caroline &quot;Carrie&quot; Nicholls]] - Played by [[Linda Lusardi]],Scarlett and Lexi's mother-2007-2008.
* [[Phyllis King (Emmerdale)|Phyllis King]] - Tom's aunt and great aunt to Jimmy, Matthew, Carl, Max and Scarlett. She appeared for Tom's non-wedding to [[Charity Dingle]] and Tom's funeral. Played by Sheila Burrell, 2005, 2007.

===Hierarchy===
Initially [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]] was the [[patriarch]] of his family, making sure everyone knew he was in charge both at home and within the family business, King and Sons. His eldest son [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy]] strived to be his second in command, working for his father since the age of 14, though Tom favoured Jimmy's wife [[Sadie King|Sadie]] and gave her important jobs, rather than giving them to Jimmy. Sadie later betrayed the family, and kidnapped Tom with the help of [[Cain Dingle]], leading to her departure from the village.

Tom's second son, [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew]] also wanted to have power within the business, and regularly came to blows with Jimmy about it. Tom's younger sons [[Carl King (Emmerdale)|Carl]] and [[Max King (Emmerdale)|Max]] were initially low down on the status scale, and Max didn't work for the company, instead working as a vet until his death in October 2006.

Family tree

[[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]
 m. Mary King
     c. [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]]
             m. [[Sadie King]]
             m. [[Nicola De Souza]]
                     c. [[Angelica King]]
             a. [[Kelly Windsor]]
                     c. [[List_of_minor_Emmerdale_characters_(2011)|Elliot Windsor]]
     c. [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew King]]
     c. [[Carl King]]
             m. [[Colleen King]]
                     c. [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Thomas King]]
                     c. [[Anya King]]
              m. [[Lexi King]]
     c. [[Max King (Emmerdale)|Max King]]
     c.  Georgina King

 a. [[Carrie Nicholls]]
     c. [[Scarlett Nicholls]]
 a. Charity
 m. [[Rosemary Sinclair]]

==See also==
*[[Emmerdale Cast List]]
*[[The Sinclair family|Sinclair family]]
*[[Tate family]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{EDKings}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:King Family}}
[[Category:Emmerdale families|King Family, The]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
