<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27499031" ns="0" title="Stuart period"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width:30em; text-align:left;&quot;
|+ style=&quot;padding-top:0.9em; line-height:160%;&quot;|

| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| &lt;div style=&quot;margin-top:8px;&quot;&gt;&lt;big&gt;[[House of Stuart|''The Royal House of Stuart'']]&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/div&gt; &lt;hr style=&quot;margin-top:10px; margin-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt; [[File:James VI and I (dressed in white).jpg|85px|alt=(1603–1625)]] {{pad|1em}} [[File:Charles I (1630s).jpg|90px|alt=(1625–1649)]] {{pad|1em}} [[File:Charles II (1675).jpg|89px|alt=(1660–1685)]]&lt;hr style=&quot;margin-top:10px; margin-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt; [[James I of England|James I]] {{pad|5em}} [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] {{pad|5em}} [[Charles II of England|Charles II]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr style=&quot;margin-top:10px; margin-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt; [[File:King James II from NPG.jpg|91px|alt=(1685–1688)]] {{pad|1em}} [[File:Queen Mary II.jpg|88px|alt=(1689–1702)]] {{pad|1em}} [[File:Anne Stuart.jpg|89px|alt=(1702–1714)]]&lt;hr style=&quot;margin-top:10px; margin-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt;[[James II of England|James II]] {{pad|6em}}[[Mary II of England|Mary II]] {{pad|6em}} [[Anne of Great Britain|Anne]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;hr style=&quot;margin-top:10px; margin-bottom:10px;&quot;&gt;
|-
! Preceded&amp;nbsp;by
| #ifexist: Elizabethian Era | [[House of Tudor]]
|-
! Followed&amp;nbsp;by&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
| #ifexist: Hanovarian Era | [[House of Hanover]]
|}
The '''Stuart period''' of [[English history|English]] and [[British history]] refers to the period between 1603 and 1714, while in [[Scotland]] it begins in 1371. These dates coincide with the rule of the Scottish royal [[House of Stuart]], whose first monarch to rule [[Kingdom of England|England]] was [[James I of England|James I &amp; VI]]. The death of [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]], the last of the [[House of Tudor|Tudors]], without any descendants and without an English heir, left her two kingdoms of England and [[Kingdom of Ireland|Ireland]] to be ruled by Elizabeth's closest heir, the Scottish king. The [[regicide]] of [[Charles I of England|King Charles I]] brought a temporary end to the rule of the Stuarts, when England became a [[Republic]] under [[Oliver Cromwell]]. The Stuarts were restored to the throne under [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] in 1660. The Stuart period ended with the death of [[Anne of Great Britain|Queen Anne]] and the accession of [[George I of Great Britain|George I]] of the [[House of Hanover]]. 

The Stuart era experienced many changes: the [[Gunpowder Plot]], civil and foreign wars, the regicide of a king, a republic, the great plague, the [[Great Fire of London]] and the [[Glorious Revolution]]. This was the era of [[William Shakespeare|Shakespeare]], [[Christopher Wren|Wren]], [[Galileo]], [[Isaac Newton|Newton]] and [[Samuel Pepys|Pepys]], to name but a few. The era saw the [[British colonization of the Americas|settlement of the Americas]], trade with the [[Maluku Islands|Spice Islands]], the birth of [[steam engine]]s, [[microscope]]s, [[coffee house]]s and [[newspaper]]s.

==Flags, coins and styles (1606–1707)==
[[File:King James I of England and VI of Scotland in Parliament by Renold or Reginold Elstrack (Elstracke).jpg|left|thumb|100px|alt=James I addresses the English House of Commons in 1608|Commons 1608]]
This [[James I of England|James I]] proclamation of 12 April 1606 legislated an [[amalgamation (politics)|amalgamation]] of the [[Flag of England|English]] and [[Flag of Scotland|Scottish]] flags, initiating the design of the first [[Union Flag]].

{{quote|By the King: Whereas, some differences hath arisen between Our subjects of South and North Britaine travelling by Seas, about the bearing of their Flagges: For the avoiding of all contentions hereafter. We have, with the advice of our Council, ordered: That from henceforth all our Subjects of this Isle and Kingdome of Great Britaine, and all our members thereof, shall beare in their main-toppe the Red Crosse, commonly called St. George's Crosse, and the White Crosse, commonly called St. Andrew's Cross, joyned together according to the forme made by our heralds, and sent by Us to our 'Admerall' to be published to our Subjects: and in their fore-toppe our Subjects of South Britaine shall weare the Red Crosse onely as they were wont, and our Subjects of North Britaine in their fore-toppe the White Crosse onely as they were accustomed. – 1606. '' &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Art of Heraldry – An Encyclopaedia of Armory |last=Fox-Davies |first= Arthur Charles|authorlink= Arthur Charles Fox-Davies |year=1904 &amp; 1986  |publisher=Bloomsbury Books |location=London |isbn= 0906223342|page= 399}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;flaginstitute.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flaginstitute.org/index.php?location=7 |title=British flags |publisher=Flaginstitute.org |date= |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
[[File:Union flag 1606 (Kings Colors).svg|right|100px|alt=Union Flag 1606]]
[[File:Wenceslas Hollar - Half-crown of Charles I (State 2) 2.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Half-crown of Charles II ''MAGNAE BRITANNIAE REX'']]
{{quote|The miraculous and happy Union of England and Scotland, by how 'admirable' means it is effected, how profitable to both nations, and how free of any inconvenience, either past, present, or to be discerned.&lt;ref&gt;CSPD [Imprinted for Edward Blount] Volume 10: November–December, 1604, pp. 164–182.&lt;/ref&gt;}} 
James I was the first British monarch to use the style &quot;King of [[Great Britain]].&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;flaginstitute.org&quot;/&gt; Non-statutory use of this style is found on  [[Heraldry|heraldic]] and [[Vexillology|vexillogical]] symbolism, such as the king's [[Seal (emblem)|Great Seals]] of Office, the Royal Arms, and [[Coins|coinage]]. The style &quot;King of Great Britain&quot; (''MAGNAE BRITANNIAE REX'') appears on all Great Seals instead of the more formally correct &quot;king of England and Scotland&quot; (''ANGLIAE SCOTIAE REX'') in 1625–1627, 1640–1649, 1660–1689, and 1695–1707. The coins of James I and his successors used ''MAGNAE BRITANNIAE REX'', as seen on the [[Half crown (British coin)|half crown]] of [[Charles II of England|Charles II]].
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.archontology.org/nations/uk/england/king_england/01_kingstyle_1604.php |title=England/Great Britain: Royal Styles: 1604-1707 |publisher=Archontology.org |date=2010-03-13 |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lifestyles of the period==
{{Main|Social history of England}}

===Social lifestyles===
[[File:10 The Coffee House.JPG|thumb|left|155px|Stuart period: Coffee House]]
Many strictures were placed on society by the [[Puritans]]. Amongst other things, the Puritans banned gambling, [[cockfight]]s, the theatre, and even Christmas. The arrival of [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] brought relief from the warlike and strict society that people had lived in for several years. The theatre returned, along with expensive fashions such as the [[periwig]]. The [[British Empire]] had been expanding since the [[Elizabethian era]], and along with much wealth returning to the country, expensive luxury items were appearing. Sugar and coffee from the [[East Indies]], tea from [[India]] and [[slavery|slave]]s from [[Africa]] were all essential items forming the backbone of trade, becoming the basis of [[London]] society. One person in nine  is estimated to have lived in London near the end of the Stuart period and, as a hub of trade, expensive goods from all over accumulated there. [[Coffee house]]s were becoming the centers of business and social life. Only coffee, tea and chocolate were served (no alcohol). Here news could be had, conversation, arguments, meetings, card games, wagers made, workmen could be paid. These products can be considered as beginning the consumer society which, while it promoted trade and brought development and riches to society, helped widen the gap between rich and poor. At the beginning of the Stuart period, [[James I of England|James I]] authorised a new translation of the Bible known as the [[King James Bible]] or Authorised Version. This was an important event in clearly separating the [[Anglican]] and [[Catholic]] churches, just as the [[Book of Common Prayer]] had done fifty years earlier. As a standard text it was also a major influence on [[English literature]], language and thought for centuries to come. [[Newspaper]]s, a fairly new invention, soon became important tools of social discourse, and [[diarist]]s such as [[Samuel Pepys]] are some of the best sources we have of everyday life in [[English Restoration|Restoration]] England.

===Political society===
[[File:Levellers' Manifest.jpg|thumb|150px|right| Levellers' Manifest of 1649]]
The Stuart period was plagued by political, internal and religious strife. During the [[Interregnum (England)|Interregnum]] there were two types of government: the [[Commonwealth of England|Commonwealth]] and [[the Protectorate]] of [[Oliver Cromwell]]. Both these governments were based on the rule of the same class of gentry and wealthy merchants, who had formed the majority of the electorate to Parliament before the Civil War. The old ruling class faced challenges to their position by other sections of society. The most important of these were the [[Levellers]], who wished to &quot;level&quot; society, removing [[social class|class]] distinctions to make all men equal. They wished for universal [[suffrage]] for all adult male householders, regular elections and abolition of all [[tithe]]s – which would break the power of the [[established church]].

===Public transport===

Since 1600 public carriages for hire were a feature of London life. Travel by coach was the regular public transport, which filled the road with traffic. The discarded coaches of aristocratic families, complete with their [[Heraldry|coat of arms]], were among the first [[hackney carriage]]s to ply for hire. The first hackney-carriage licences date from 1662, and applied literally to horse-drawn carriages, later modernised as [[Hansom cab]]s (1834), that operated as vehicles for hire. This public transport was first introduced to England by Captain Bailey, who standardised fares and issued licences for London Hackney Carriage. [[Road signs]] and the first [[road atlas]] by John Ogilvy further revolutionised the transport system, and standardised the mile.

===Science and technology===
{{See also|What the Stuarts Did for Us}}
[[File:Jethro Tull seed drill (1752).png|thumb|right|150px|Jethro Tull: Seed drill, 1701]]
*The [[Fire station|Fire Office]] of [[Nicholas Barbon]] led to the development of the first professional fire service.
*The ''[[seed drill]]'' allowed [[Jethro Tull (agriculturist)|Jethro Tull]] to put his revolutionary new planting techniques into practice, leading to modern [[agriculture]].
*The ''[[fountain pen]]'' was first mentioned in the diaries of [[Samuel Pepys]] and it allowed him to write on the move.
*''Colourfast [[dye]]s'' were created in Britain’s first chemical works at [[Ravenscar, North Yorkshire|Ravenscar]] when supplies of the mordant alum were cut-off.
*The ''[[three-piece suit]]'' and ''[[necktie]]'' were created by [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] as a political weapon in his war against [[France]].
*Properties of [[gas]]es investigated by [[Robert Boyle]] and [[Richard Towneley]] led to the invention of the ''[[pressure cooker]]''.
*The ''[[steam engine]]'' was invented by [[Thomas Newcomen]] to drain water from the coalmines of the Midlands.
*The ''[[pendulum clock]]'' based on [[Galileo]]'s principles was invented by [[Christiaan Huygens]] and led to the establishment of [[GMT]].
*Lunar observations of [[John Wilkins]] based on the previous observations of [[Galileo]] challenged long held views of the heavens.
*Principia by [[Isaac Newton]] established three simple laws that revolutionised our view of the [[universe]].
*The ''[[microscope]]'' as refined by [[Robert Hook]] and [[Antonie van Leeuwenhoek]] allowed the microscopic world to be viewed in detail.
*The ''[[diving bell]]'' as refined by [[Edmund Halley]] allowed the investigation of the depths of the ocean.
*The ''[[micrometer]]'' devised by [[William Gascoigne]] proved [[Johannes Kepler]]’s theories of elliptical [[planetary motion]].

===Literature and art===
[[File:First Folio.jpg|thumb|left|110px|&quot;First Folio&quot; – Plays]]
{{Quote box
 |quote= This royal throne of kings, this sceptred isle, this earth of majesty, this seat of Mars, this other Eden, demi-paradise; this fortress, built by nature for herself. This blessed plot, this earth, this realm, this England.
 |source= [[William Shakespeare|Wm. Shakespeare (1564–1616)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Richard II|url=http://www.users.waitrose.com/~uk1/shakespeare/sceptred.htm|publisher=[[William Shakespeare]]|accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |width=50%
}}
*[[William Shakespeare]] (1564–1616), English poet and playwright, is widely regarded as the greatest writer in the English language and the world's pre-eminent dramatist. He is often called England's national poet and the &quot;Bard of Avon&quot;, producing most of his known work between 1589 and 1613. His early plays were mainly comedies and histories, genres he raised to the peak of sophistication and artistry by the end of the [[Elizabethian era|sixteenth century]]. He then wrote mainly tragedies until about 1608, including [[Hamlet]], [[King Lear]], and [[Macbeth]], considered some of the finest works in the English language.
*[[John Speed]] (1552–1629) was a historian, best remembered as a [[cartographer]]. It was with the encouragement of [[William Camden]] that he began his ''Historie of Great Britaine'', first published in 1611. His atlas ''The Theatre of the Empire of Great Britaine'' was published in 1610/11, and contained the first set of individual county maps of [[England]] and [[Wales]], maps of [[Ireland]], and a general map of [[Scotland]]. Just before his death in 1627 Speed published ''A Prospect of the Most Famous Parts of the World,'' which was the first ''world atlas'' produced by an Englishman. In 1611, he also published ''The genealogies recorded in the [[Sacred Scriptures]] according to every family and tribe with the line of Our Savior [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] observed from [[Adam]] to the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]]'', a biblical [[genealogy]], reprinted several times during the 17th century.&lt;ref&gt;The Counties of Britain. John Speed (1995) ISBN 1857936124.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable events==
[[File:The Gunpowder Plot Conspirators, 1605 from NPG (2).jpg|right|260px]]

===Gunpowder Plot (1605)===
{{Main|Gunpowder Plot}}
&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#00 00 f1;font-family:Serif&quot;&gt;&lt;big&gt;''On the 5th of November we began our Parliament, to which the King should have come in person, but refrained&lt;br /&gt;through a practise but that morning discovered. The plot was to have blown up the King at such time as he should have been set on his Royal Throne, accompanied with all his Children, Nobility and Commoners and assisted with all Bishops, Judges and Doctors; at one instant and blast to have ruin'd the whole State and Kingdom of England.&lt;br /&gt;And for the effecting of this, there was placed under the Parliament House, where the king should sit,&lt;br /&gt;some 30&amp;nbsp;barrels of powder, with good store of wood, faggots, pieces and bars of iron.''&lt;br /&gt;{{pad|6em}}&lt;small&gt;Extract of a letter from Sir Edward Hoby ([[Gentleman of the Bedchamber]]) to Sir Thomas Edwards, Ambassador at Brussells [sic]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Nichols|1828|p=584}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

===English Civil War (1629-1651)===
{{campaign
|name= [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
|raw_name=Campaignbox Wars of the Three Kingdoms
|battles= [[Bishops' Wars|Bishops']] – [[Irish Confederate Wars|Irish Confederate]] – [[Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms|Scottish Wars]] – [[English Civil War]]s: [[First English Civil War|First]]{{·}}[[Second English Civil War|Second]]{{·}}[[Third English Civil War|Third]]}}
{{Campaign
|name=[[Anglo-Dutch Wars|Anglo–Dutch Wars]]
|raw_name=Campaignbox Anglo-Dutch Wars
|battles=[[First Anglo–Dutch War|First]] – [[Second Anglo–Dutch War|Second]] – [[Third Anglo–Dutch War|Third]] – [[Fourth Anglo–Dutch War|Fourth]] - [[Anglo-Dutch Java War]]}}
The [[English Civil War]](s), also known as the ''Wars of the Three Kingdoms'', took place in the reign of [[Charles I of England|Charles I]], the second 'British' Stuart monarch. This ended in victory for the [[Roundhead|Parliamentarians]] under Oliver Cromwell, when Charles I was executed in 1649.
[[Image:English civil war map 1642 to 1645.JPG|thumb|250px|alt=Territories held by Royalists (red) and Parliamentarians (green) (1642-1645|Charles I Royalists v. Cromwell Parliamentarians]]

;Charles I (1625–1649)

*1629 Charles I dissolves Parliament determined to govern without one.
*1633 Archbishop Laud translated to be Archbishop of Canterbury
*1634-40 [[Ship Money]] Case
*1637 Hampden's case supports Charles I's claim to collect Ship money
*1637-40 Breakdown of Charles's government of Scotland and two attempts to impose his will by force
*1640 [[Long Parliament]] summoned
*1641 Remodeling of the government in England and Scotland; abolition of conciliar courts.
*1642 King Charles raised standard at Nottingham. The [[Battle of Edgehill]] (Indecisive).
*1644 [[Battle of Marston Moor]] (Parliamentary Victory)
*1645 [[Battle of Naseby]] (Parliamentary Victory)
*1646 Charles I surrendered to Scottish Army.
*1648 [[Royalist]] and [[Presbyterian]] rising suppressed by Cromwell and [[New Model Army]].
*1649 Charles I beheaded.
*1649-50 Cromwell Invaded Ireland
*1650 Cromwell defeated Royalists under &quot;King Charles II&quot; at Dunbar, Scotland.
*1651 [[Battle of Worcester]], the last battle of the Civil War, Parliamentary Victory.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After this conflict the line of Stuart monarchs was temporarily displaced by the [[Commonwealth of England]] (1649–1660). This was ruled directly by [[Oliver Cromwell]] (1653–1659).  After Cromwell's death the Commonwealth fell apart and the [[Convention Parliament (1660)|Convention Parliament]] welcomed [[Charles II of England|Charles II]], to return from exile to become king. This is known as the [[Restoration (1660)|Restoration]].

===Interregnum – Restoration (1651–1660)===
[[File:Charles II of England in Coronation robes.jpg|right|160px|thumb|alt=Charles in Coronation robes circa 1661|Charles II Coronation c.1661]]
;Timeline
(1652): First Anglo-Dutch War begins (ends 1654). (1653): Cromwell dissolves Rump, becomes Protector. (1655): Major-Generals appointed to supervise districts of England. [[Jamaica]] seized by English. (1658): Death of Cromwell. (1660): [[English Restoration|Restoration]] of Charles II in Britain. (future) [[George I of Great Britain|George I]] born in [[Hanover]]. [[Royal Society]] founded. (1661): &quot;[[Clarendon Code]]&quot; beginning of persecution of Non-conformists in England. (1664): [[New York]] taken by English. Second [[Anglo-Dutch Wars|Anglo-Dutch War]] (ends 1667). (1665): [[Great Plague of London]]. (1666): [[Great Fire of London]]. [[Isaac Newton|Newton]] discovers law of gravitation. (1667): [[Anglo-Dutch Wars|Dutch Fleet]] in the Medway. (1670): [[Secret treaty of Dover]] between Charles II and [[Louis XIV]]. (1672): Third [[Anglo-Dutch Wars]] (ends 1674). [[William III of England|William of Orange]] leader of Dutch against French invasion. (1673): [[Test Act]] deprives [[Catholic]]s and [[Non-conformist]]s of public offices. (1675): [[Greenwich Royal Observatory]] founded. (1678): &quot;[[Popish Plot]]&quot; of [[Titus Oates]] utilised by Shaftsbury and [[Whig (British political party)|Whigs]] to bring pressure on Charles II. (1679): [[Bothwell Brig]]: suppression of Scottish Convenanters. [[Habeas Corpus]] Act passed. (1681): [[Oxford Parliament (1681)]]: Charles II overcomes opponents begins to rule without Parliament. (1683): [[Rye House Plot]]. (1685): [[Battle of Sedgemoor|Sedgemoor]]: Monmouths rebellion crushed by James II. [[Glorious revolution]] (1688)

===Great Plague of London (1665)===
{{Main|Great Plague of London}}
The '''Great Plague''' (1665–1666) was massive outbreak of [[bubonic plague]] in the [[Kingdom of England]] that killed an estimated 100,000 people, 20% of [[London]]'s population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britainexpress.com/History/plague.htm |title=The London Plague 1665 |publisher=Britainexpress.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1603, the plague killed 30,000 Londoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/london_plague_1665.htm |title=London and the Great Plague of 1665 |publisher=Historylearningsite.co.uk |date=2007-03-30 |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1636 plague 10,000 died; in 1625, some 35,000 died.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mason.gmu.edu/~ayadav/historical%20outline/great-plague.htm |title=The Great Plague of 1665 |publisher=Mason.gmu.edu |date=2010-07-13 |accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The English outbreak is thought to have spread from the [[Netherlands]], where the bubonic plague had occurred intermittently since 1599, with the initial contagion arriving with Dutch trading ships carrying bales of [[cotton]] from [[Amsterdam]]. Amsterdam was ravaged in 1663–1664, with a mortality given as 50,000.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.emsc.nysed.gov/ciai/socst/ghgonline/units/3/u3e.html E. Social, economic, and political impacts of the plague on Eurasia and Africa], New York State Education Department&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Dock (maritime)|dock]] areas outside of London, and the parish of [[St. Giles-in-the Fields]] where poor workers crowded into ill-kept structures, were the first areas struck by the plague. On 2 and 3 September 1666, the [[Great Fire of London]] destroyed much of the City of London. At about the same time, the plague tapered off.  
{{Panorama
|image      = Image:Panorama of London by Claes Van Visscher, 1616 no angels.jpg
|fullwidth  = 2555
|fullheight = 290
|caption    = Panorama of the City of London in 1616 by Claes Visscher. Note the [[tenement housing]] on [[London Bridge]] (far right), a notorious death-trap in case of fire, although much had been destroyed in an earlier fire in 1632.
|height     = 180
}}

===Great Fire of London (1666)===
{{Main|Great Fire of London}}
Following the Great Fire of London, the notable architect Sir [[Christopher Wren]] (1632–1723), introduced Neo-classical architecture to London, and was one of the highest acclaimed English [[architect]]s in history, responsible for rebuilding 51 churches in the [[City of London]] after the Great Fire in 1666, including his masterpiece, [[St Paul's Cathedral]], completed in 1710.&lt;br /&gt;

===Glorious Revolution (1688)===
[[File:William III Landing at Brixham, Torbay, 5 November 1688.jpg|160px|thumb|William III landing at Brixham, Torbay, 5&amp;nbsp;November 1688]]
;Timeline
(1688): [[Seven Bishops]] protest against [[James II of England|James II's]] policy of tolleration, and are acquitted, [[William III of England|William of Orange]] lands in England. Flight of James II. &quot;[[Glorious Revolution]]&quot;. (1689): [[Derry]] relieved: James II fails to subdue Irish [[Protestant]]s. [[Killiecrankie]]: death of Dundee, [[Jacobitism#Dundee's rising|Highland rising]] collapses. [[Bill of Rights]] defines liberties established by &quot;Glorious Revolution.&quot; (1690): [[Beachy Head]]: French defeat over Anglo-Dutch fleet. [[Battle of the Boyne|Boyne]]: William III defeats James II. (1691): [[Limerick]] capitulates: James II Irish supporters surrender. (1692): [[Massacre of Glencoe]]: Government &quot;lesson&quot; to [[Gàidhealtachd|Highlander]]s. (1693): [[National Debt]] of England begun. (1694): [[Bank of England]] founded. (1695): Press licensing ended: [[Freedom of the press]] in England. (1700): [[Great Northern War]] (1700–1721) (1701): [[War of the Spanish Succession]] begins. [[Act of Settlement 1701]] establishes [[Protestant]] [[House of Hanover|Hanoverian]] [[Succession (conflict)|Succession]] in England. (1704): [[Gibraltar]] taken by [[Rooke]]. [[Battle of Blenheim|Blenheim]]: [[John Churchill, 1st Duke of Marlborough|Marlborough]] stops France from winning war. (1706): [[Battle of Ramillies|Ramillies]]: Marlborough's second victory.

===Acts of Union (1707)===
(1707): [[Acts of Union 1707|Acts of Union]] ratify the 1706 [[Treaty of Union]], uniting the English and Scottish Parliaments and creating the [[Kingdom of Great Britain]]. (1708): [[Oudenarde]]: Marlboroughs third great victory. (1709): [[Battle of Malplaquet|Malplaquet]]: Marlboroughs fourth great victory (at great cost in lives) (1710): [[Tory]] government in England. (1711): Dismissal of Marlborough. (1714): Death of [[Anne of Great Britain|Queen Anne]]. Accession of [[George I of Great Britain|George I]], and [[House of Hanover|Hanoverian Dynasty]]. Whig [[oligarchy]] rules.
&lt;br /&gt;
[[File:Anne, Queen of Great Britain.jpg|left|140px|thumb|[[Anne of Great Britain|Anne (1665-1714)]]]]
[[File:Bakhuizen, Battle of Vigo Bay.jpg|right|War of the Spanish Succession|318px]]
{{Campaignbox Queen Anne's War}}

&lt;center&gt;''Act of Union 1707: That the two kingdoms of Scotland and England shall,&lt;br /&gt;upon the Ist day of May next ensuing the date hereof, and for ever after,&lt;br /&gt;be united into one kingdom by the name of Great Britain,&lt;br /&gt;and that the ensigns armorial of the said United Kingdom be such&lt;br /&gt;as Her Majesty shall appoint,&lt;br /&gt;and the crosses of St. Andrew and St. George be conjoined in such manner&lt;br /&gt;as Her Majesty shall think fit,&lt;br /&gt; and used in all flags, banners, standards and ensigns, both at sea and land.''&lt;/center&gt;
{{clear}}

==Stuart family Monarchs (1603–1714)==
The [[House of Stuart]] produced six [[List of English monarchs|English monarchs]] who ruled during this period. The succession of [[James I of England|James VI of Scotland]] to the English throne in 1603, brought both the kingdoms of England and Scotland under his rule, in what was known as the [[Union of Crowns]]. Over a century later, the [[Acts of Union 1707]], passed during the reign of the last Stuart monarch, [[Anne of Great Britain|Anne]], amalgamated the two kingdoms, England and Scotland, into a single [[Kingdom of Great Britain]].

{| border=0&quot; style=&quot;width:160px; height:350px; float:left;&quot;
|-
! [[File:Portrait of King James I &amp; VI.jpg|70px|center|(1603–1625)]] &lt;small&gt; [[James I of England|James I]] &lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:Charles I (1625).jpg|75px|center|(1625–1649)]]  &lt;small&gt; [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] &lt;/small&gt;
|- 
! [[File:Charles II (by Gerrit van Honthorst).jpg|72px|center|(1649–1685)]]  &lt;small&gt; [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] &lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:James Stuart, Duke of York.jpg|75px|center|(1685–1688)]] &lt;small&gt; [[James II of England|James II]] &lt;/small&gt;
|-
! [[File:Queen Mary II.jpg|74px|center|(1689–1694)]]  &lt;small&gt; [[Mary II of England|Mary II]] &lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:Queen Anne.jpg|72px|center|(1702–1714)]] &lt;small&gt; [[Anne of Great Britain|Anne]] &lt;/small&gt;
|-
!
|}
{| border=0&quot; style=&quot;width:160px; height:350px; float:right;&quot;
|-
! [[File:Royal Arms of England (1603-1707).svg|70px|center]] &lt;small&gt; Arms of the Stuart monarchs 1603-1707&lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:Arms of the Commonwealth of England (1649-1660).svg|70px|center]]  &lt;small&gt; Commonwealth &lt;/small&gt;
|- 
! [[File:Royal Arms of England (1198-1340).svg|70px|center]] &lt;small&gt;England Arms&lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:Cross demo.svg|70px|center]] &lt;small&gt; St. George &lt;/small&gt;
|-
! [[File:Royal Arms of the Kingdom of Scotland.svg|70px|center]] &lt;small&gt; Scotland Arms &lt;/small&gt;
! [[File:Blason ville fr Longaulnay 35.svg|70px|center]] &lt;small&gt; Scots saltire &lt;/small&gt;
|-
!
|}
{{pad|1em}}[[James I of England|King James I]] (1603 to 1625). Son of [[Mary Queen of Scots]] and [[Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley]]. King of Scotland alone, 1567–1603, until inheriting the titles King of England and Ireland, including claim to France from the extinct [[Tudor dynasty|Tudor]]s.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
{{pad|1em}}[[Charles I of England|King Charles I]] (1625 to 1649). Son of [[James VI of Scotland]] &amp; I of England &amp; Ireland. After the [[English Civil War]], Charles I was executed in 1649. The country then became a [[Republic]] under [[Oliver Cromwell]], until the [[English restoration|restoration]] of Charles II in 1660.
&lt;br /&gt;
{{pad|1em}}[[Charles II of England|King Charles II]] (1660 to 1685). Son of Charles I of England, Scotland &amp; Ireland. In exile from 1649 to 1660, during a republican period of government known as the [[Commonwealth of England]].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
{{pad|1em}}[[James II of England|King James II]] (1685 to 1688). Brother of [[Charles II of England]], Scotland &amp; Ireland, who died with no legitimate issue. Son of Charles I. Overthrown at the [[Glorious revolution|Revolution]] of 1688.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
{{pad|1em}}[[Mary II of England|Queen Mary II]] (1689 to 1702).  Daughter of [[James II of England]] and Ireland &amp; VII of Scotland, (deemed as having abdicated). ''Reigned with [[William III of England|William III]] of [[House of Orange-Nassau]].'' who outlived his wife.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
{{pad|1em}}[[Anne of Great Britain|Queen Anne]] (1702 to 1714). Sister of Mary II. daughter of James II of England and Ireland &amp; VII of Scotland. Died without surviving issue, [[Succession (conflict)|succession]] passes to George I of the [[House of Hanover]].
&lt;br /&gt;
{{nowrap end}}&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both; width: 100%; padding: 0; text-align: left; border: none;&quot; class=&quot;NavFrame&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#ccf; text-align:center; border:1px solid #676;&quot; class=&quot;NavHead&quot;&gt;[[Anne of Great Britain|Queen Anne's Family Tree]]
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;NavContent&quot; style=&quot;display:none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#dcdcdc; margin-left:2px; margin-right:2px; margin-top:2px; margin-bottom:2px; border-style:ridge; border-width:3px; border-color:blue; padding:4px;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;center&gt;{{ahnentafel-compact5
|style=font-size: 90%; line-height: 110%;
|border=1
|boxstyle=padding-top: 0; padding-bottom: 0;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;

|1= 1. '''Anne of Great Britain'''
|2= 2. [[James II of England]]
|3= 3. [[Anne Hyde]]
|4= 4. [[Charles I of England]]
|5= 5. [[Henrietta Maria of France|Princess Henrietta Maria of France]]
|6= 6. [[Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon]]
|7= 7. [[Frances Hyde, Countess of Clarendon|Frances Aylesbury]]
|8= 8. [[James I of England]]
|9= 9. [[Anne of Denmark|Princess Anne of Denmark]]
|10= 10. [[Henry IV of France]]
|11= 11. [[Marie de' Medici]]
|12= 12. [[Henry Hyde (ancestor of Mary II of England)|Henry Hyde]]
|13= 13. [[Mary Langford]]
|14= 14. [[Thomas Aylesbury]]
|15= 15. [[Anne Denman]]
|16= 16. [[Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley]]
|17= 17. [[Mary, Queen of Scots]]
|18= 18. [[Frederick II of Denmark]]
|19= 19. [[Sofie of Mecklenburg-Schwerin (d. 1631)|Sofie of Mecklenburg-Schwerin]]
|20= 20. [[Antoine of Navarre|Antoine of Bourbon, Duke of Vendôme]]
|21= 21. [[Jeanne III of Navarre]]
|22= 22. [[Francesco I de' Medici, Grand Duke of Tuscany]]
|23= 23. [[Johanna of Austria|Archduchess Johanna of Austria]]
|24= 24. [[Henry Hyde (ancestor of Mary II of England)#Life|Lawrence Hyde]]
|25= 25. [[Anne Sibell]]
|26= 26. [[Edward Langford]]
|27= 27. [[Mary Hyde (ancestor of Mary II of England)|Mary Hyde]]
|28= 28. [[William Aylesbury]]
|29= 29. [[Anne Poole]]
|30= 30. [[Francis Denman]]
|31= 31. [[Anne Blount]]

}}&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
{{nowrap end}}&lt;br /&gt;

[[File:Queen Anne and William, Duke of Gloucester by studio of Sir Godfrey Kneller.jpg|left|92px|alt=Queen Anne, and her son William Duke of Gloucester]]
[[File:George, Prince of Denmark by John Riley.jpg|right|92px|alt=George Prince of Denmark; Consort to Queen Anne]]

&lt;center&gt;[[Anne of Great Britain|Anne]] became Queen regnant of [[England]], [[Scotland]] and [[Ireland]] in 1702, succeeding [[William III of England|William III]].  When James II was deemed abdicated during the Glorious Revolution (1688–89), her sister and brother-in-law became joint monarchs William III and Mary II. After Mary's death in 1694, William was monarch until his death in 1702. [[Queen Anne's War]] (1702–1713), between [[France]] and England (later [[Great Britain]]) was fought in [[North America]], as part of the [[War of the Spanish Succession]], primarily fought in [[Europe]]. Anne reigned until 1714; The last Stuart Queen of England and Scotland - and of this Stuart period.&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;noinclude&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div/&gt;

==See also==
{{campaign
|name= [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
|raw_name=Campaignbox Wars of the Three Kingdoms
|battles= [[Bishops' Wars|Bishops']] – [[Irish Confederate Wars|Irish Confederate]] – [[Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms|Scottish Wars]] – [[English Civil War]]s: [[First English Civil War|First]]{{·}}[[Second English Civil War|Second]]{{·}}[[Third English Civil War|Third]]}}
{{Campaignbox Theatres of the War of the Grand Alliance}}
{{Campaignbox Williamite war in Ireland}} 
{{Campaignbox War of the Spanish Succession}}

* [[House of Stuart]]
* [[Kingdom of England]]
* [[Kingdom of Scotland]]
* [[Jacobitism]], for further information on the House of Stuart and their decline
* The family trees of the Stuarts: [[Scottish monarchs family tree|Scottish branch]] – [[British monarchs family tree|England and Scotland united]]
* [[Clan Stuart]]

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both; width: 100%; padding: 0; text-align: left; border: none;&quot; class=&quot;NavFrame&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#ccf; text-align:center; border:1px solid #676;&quot; class=&quot;NavHead&quot;&gt;[[Stuart period|English Navy Battles (1605–1692)]]
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;NavContent&quot; style=&quot;display:none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#dcdcdc; margin-left:2px; margin-right:2px; margin-top:2px; margin-bottom:2px; border-style:ridge; border-width:5px; border-color:blue; padding:4px;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

[[File:England COA.svg|30px|alt=Three gold lions: Coat of arms, and flag, of English kings.]] [[England]] [[File:Blason Anglais.svg|30px|alt= St George's cross; The emblem of England's patron saint. From C.1277, the national flag of England and Wales.]] {{pad|20em}} &lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;[[Stuart period|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000f1;font-family:Serif&quot;&gt; ''English Navy Battles (1605–1692) &lt;font style=&quot;color:#009ef2;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
;Naval Battles (1605–1692)
&lt;br /&gt;

;James I

* 1605 Dover: Dutch fleet attacks and partly destroys a Spanish fleet of transport ships.
::Swally: British East India Company fleet defeats Portuguese fleet near Surat, India
* 1615 English defeat Portuguese in mainly minor skirmishes
::English vs Dutch near Jakarta+
::English defeat Portuguese
* 1622 English and Dutch defeat Portuguese near Mozambique
::English naval bombardment of Algiers
::English and Dutch defeat Portuguese+
&lt;br /&gt;
;Charles I

* 1626 French with hired English and Dutch ships defeat Huguenot fleet near Rochelle
::English defeat Venetians/French at Scanderoon +
* 1629 Dutch under Piet Heyn defeat Dunkirkers off Scotland; Heyn is killed
::Battle of the Downs – Dutch under Tromp defeat Spanish under D'Oquendo in the English Channel
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;big&gt;English Civil War&lt;/big&gt;

The [[English Civil War]](s) took place in the reign of [[Charles I of England|Charles I]], the second Stuart monarch. This ended in victory for the [[Roundhead|Parliamentarians]] and Charles was executed in 1649.  

;Charles I

*1629 Charles I dissolves Parliament determined to govern without one.
*1633 Archbishop Laud translated to be Archbishop of Canterbury
*1634–40 Ship Money Case
*1637 Hampden's case supports Charles I's claim to collect Ship money
*1637–40 Breakdown of Charles's government of Scotland and two attempts to impose his will by force
*1640 Long Parliament summoned
*1641 Remodeling of the government in England and Scotland; abolition of conciliar courts.
*1642 King Charles raised standard at Nottingham. The Battle of Edgehill (Indecisive).
*1644 Battle of Marston Moor (Parliamentary Victory)
*1645 Battle of Naseby (Parliamentary Victory)
*1646 Charles I surrendered to Scottish Army.
*1648 Royalist and Presbyterian rising supressed by Cromwell and New Model Army.
*1649 Charles I beheaded.
*1649–50 Cromwell Invaded Ireland
*1650 Cromwell defeated Royalists under &quot;King Charles II&quot; at Dunbar, Scotland.
*1651 Battle of Worcester, the last battle of the Civil War, Parliamentary Victory.
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After this conflict the line of [[Stuart]] monarchs was temporarily displaced by the [[Commonwealth of England]] (1649 to 1660). This was ruled directly by [[Oliver Cromwell]] in the period 1653 to 1659.  After Cromwell's death the Commonwealth fell apart and the [[Convention Parliament (1660)|Convention Parliament]] welcomed [[Charles II of England|Charles II]], son of Charles I to return from exile and become king. This event was known as the [[English Restoration]].&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
;James II

*1689 Battle of Bantry Bay: French defeat English off SW Ireland
::French vs English near Casquets
::Beachy Head: (Beveziers) French defeat Anglo-Dutch fleet
::French vs English and Dutch near Madras
&lt;br /&gt;
;Mary II

*1692 Barfleur and La Hougue Decisive defeat of French by English and Dutch in the War of the Grand Alliance
::French defeat English+
::Dogger Bank: French defeat Dutch
::French and English fight in Newfoundland
::Fight near San Domingo &lt;/center&gt;
{{nowrap end}}&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both; width: 100%; padding: 0; text-align: left; border: none;&quot; class=&quot;NavFrame&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#ccf; text-align:center; border:1px solid #676;&quot; class=&quot;NavHead&quot;&gt;Scottish Wars (1603–1715)
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;NavContent&quot; style=&quot;display:none;&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background:#dcdcdc; margin-left:2px; margin-right:2px; margin-top:2px; margin-bottom:2px; border-style:ridge; border-width:5px; border-color:blue; padding:4px;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

[[File:Blason ville fr Longaulnay 35.svg|30px|alt= Saint Andrew's Cross (Saltire); National flag of Scotland]] [[Scotland]]{{pad|0em}} [[File:Royal coat of arms of Scotland.svg|30px|alt=Red Lion: Royal coat of arms of Scotland]]{{pad|20em}} &lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;[[Stuart period|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000f1;font-family:Serif&quot;&gt;''Scottish wars (1603–1714) &lt;font style=&quot;color:#009ef2;&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms
|image=
|partof=the [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
|date=1644—1651
|place=[[Scotland]]
|casus=Conflict between Covenanters and Royalists, supporters of [[Charles I of England|Charles I]]
|result=[[Covenanters]] defeat [[Cavalier|Royalists]] but are themselves defeated by an English [[Roundhead|Parliamentarian]] conquest of Scotland in 1650–51.
|combatant1=Scottish [[Cavalier|Royalists]] and [[Confederate Ireland|Irish Catholic Confederate]] troops
|combatant2=Scottish [[Covenanters]]
|commander1='''[[James Graham, 1st Marquess of Montrose]]'''
|commander2='''[[Archibald Campbell, 1st Marquess of Argyll]] and [[David Leslie (Scottish general)|David Leslie]]'''
|strength1=Fluctuating, 2000–4000 troops at any one time
|strength2=over 30,000 troops, but many based in England and Ireland
|casualties3=Total of 28,000 battlefield deaths on both sides, more soldiers die from disease, c. 45,000 civilian deaths, both from disease and deliberate targeting
|}}
{{Campaignbox Scottish Civil War}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict=The Battle of Glen Fruin
| image=
| caption = 
| partof = the [[Scottish clan]] wars
| coordinates ={{gbmapping|NS27608940}} &lt;ref name=&quot;RCAHMS&quot;&gt;{{citation | url=http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/41400/ | title=Site Record for Glenfruin, Auchengaich; Glen Fruin; Battle Of Glen Fruin | publisher=Royal Commission on the Ancient and Historical Monuments of Scotland   }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{Coord|56|3|59|N|4|46|11|W|display=title}}
| date = 7 February 1603
| place =[[Glen Fruin]], [[Scotland]]
| result=[[Clan Gregor]] victory
| combatant1=[[Clan Gregor]], &lt;br&gt; allied men
| commander1 = Alasdair MacGregor of Glenstrae
| strength1 = 300–400 combined force
| casualties1 =very light
|combatant2=[[Clan Colquhoun]], &lt;br&gt; allied men
| commander2 = Sir Humphrey Colquhoun of Luss
| strength2 = 600–800 combined force, including a large proportion of [[cavalry]]
| casualties2 =200–300 dead
| notes=
}} 
{{Main|Royalist rising of 1651 to 1654}}

*1603 [[Battle of Glen Fruin]]: 400 MacGregors ambush a large number of Colquhouns, they took no prisoners and killed 140. Two days before he assumed the title King of England,  King James VI held a judicial review of the incident. The MacGregor name was banned

*1644 [[Battle of Tippermuir]]: Marching towards Perth, the Duke of Montrose was blocked by Covenanters led by Lord Elcho, who commanded the garrison at Perth. Montrose was victorious and marched into Perth, to the discomfort of local clergy.

*1645 [[Battle of Inverlochy (1645)|Battle of Inverlochy]]: The Marquis of Montrose, after his success at the Battle of Tippermuir (see below), was being pursued by a Covenanting force led by the Marquis of Argyll and his Campbell clan (though a General Baillie also though he was in command and the two men could not stand the sight of one another!). Argyll's forces amounted to 3,000 experienced Highland fighters; Montrose had about half that but they were also well trained – and included a contingent of MacDonalds who had scores to settle with the Campbells. Montrose showed his skill as a general and confused Covenanters who were subsequently routed – it is said that 1,500 Campbells and their alliers were killed that day.

*1645 [[Battle of Aldearn]]: While encamped at Auldearn, outside Nairn,  Montrose was surprised by a large force of Covenanters but fought back and defeated them. The Covenanter army lost 2,000 men that day.

*1645 [[Battle of Kilsyth]]: The Marquis of Montrose leads his royalist force of Highlanders and Irish to another victory at Kilsyth, leaving him in control of much of Scotland. In England, King Charles I was defeated at the [[Battle of Naseby]] against Cromwell.

*1650 [[Battle of Dunbar (1650)|Battle of Dunbar]]: Oliver Cromwell advanced into Scotland, with 16,000 men, supported by ships along the east coast, in pursuit of King Charles I. The Scots army, led by David Leslie, thwarted his attempts to take the port of Leith and Cromwell retired to Dunbar. The pursuing Scottish army was badly organized for the battle, and Cromwell won not only won the battle, but was able to hold sway over most of Lowland Scotland.

*1651 [[Battle of Worcester]]: After the Royalists were defeated by Cromwell at Dunbar in 1650, Charles II was nevertheless crowned at Scone in 1651. Harried by Cromwell, the King decided to march south into England, hoping for a popular rising in his favour. He was unsuccessful and Cromwell cornered him and his army at Worcester in September. The 28,000 &quot;New Model Army&quot; overwhelmed the 16,000 Royalist forces of Cromwell.

*1666 [[Battle of Rullion Green]]: After the Restoration of Charles II in 1660, the king attempted to impose his Episcopalian ideas on the Church of Scotland, replacing clergy who would not co-operate. The new ministers were not popular and in November 1666 and there was a rebellion, starting in Galloway but spreading throughout the south-west. As the Covenanters advanced towards Edinburgh they were pursued by Sir Thomas (Tam) Dalyell who fought with 1,000 of them in the Pentland Hills at Rullion Green. The rebels were overwhelmed. Some were hung, many others were transported abroad.

*1679 [[Battle of Bothwell Bridge]]: 10,000+ government forces, led by Monmouth and Graham of Claverhouse, dispersed 6,000 Covenanters who had gathered at Hamilton.

*1689 [[Battle of Killiecrankie]]: The Jacobites, led by James Graham, Viscount Dundee, gathered at Killiecrankie. Many of the Highland clans assembled there in support of James VII, including; Cameron of Lochiel, MacLean of Duart, MacDonald, Stewart, McNeil, MacLeods and Fraser. The government forces of King William, under Hugh Mackay of Scourie, advanced through the Pass of Killiecrankie and joined battle. After a fierce conflict, government forces retreated. But the cost to the Jacobites was high, their commander, Viscount Dundee was killed by a musket shot. Just at this moment of victory, the Jacobite cause was lost as there was no-one of his stature to lead them.

*1689 [[Battle of Dunkeld]]: After the death of James Graham, Viscount Dundee, at Killiecrankie, the Jacobite army had no leader of quality. In August, 5,000 clansmen attacked Dunkeld, held by a much smaller Government force of Cameronians. They fought a determined rear-guard action through the town, killing many of the attacking Jacobites in the process. Eventually, the Jacobites withdrew and, with the onset of winter, the Highlanders dispersed. With the defeat of James VII at the Battle of the Boyne in Ireland the following year, Dunkeld was the last battle in Scotland in the 17th century to restore the Stewarts to the throne.

*1690 [[Battle of the Boyne]]: Using finance and troops supplied by Louis XIV of France, James VII made a final attempt to regain his throne. He landed in Ireland where he had a large number of supporters amongst the Catholic community. King William (of Orange) personally led an army of 30,000 men, outnumbering the Jacobites. As James advanced towards Dublin, the armies met west of Drogheda, at the river Boyne. James was defeated and fled back to France.

*1715 [[Battle of Sherrifmuir]]: The Earl of Mar, leading the Jacobite forces in support of James Francis Edward Stewart (the &quot;Old Pretender&quot;), had taken control of most of Scotland north of Perth. The government forces led by the Duke of Argyll advanced from the south and the two armies met on the hills of Sherrifmuir, east of Dunblane in November 1715. After an inconclusive battle, the Jacobites withdrew. The Old Pretender arrived in Scotland (much later than expected) in December 1715 but stayed only six weeks before being persuaded to return to France. &lt;/center&gt;{{nowrap end}}&lt;/noinclude&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
==References==
[[Image:Coat of Arms of England (1603-1649).svg|210px|thumb|right|Armorial of the Stuart monarch for use in England, 1603 onwards]]
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{imdb title|0462147|What the Stuarts Did for Us}}
* [http://www.heraldica.org/topics/britain/britstyles.htm#1604 Proclamation styling James I King of Great Britain on October 20, 1604]
* [http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=14987 The Calendar of State Papers Domestic: James I, 1603–1610]
*{{gutenberg author|id=James+I+King+of+England|name=James I of England}}
* [http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/Page72.asp Stewart Scotland] on the official website of the British monarchy
* [http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/Page74.asp Stuart Britain] on the official website of the British monarchy
* [http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/Page73.asp Jacobites] on the official website of the British monarchy
* [http://www.stewartsofcampbeltown.com] official Stuart website

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | House of Stuart ||||| name='''[[Royal house]]''' }}
{{s-bef | before=[[Clan Bruce|House of Bruce]] }}
{{s-ttl | title=[[Dynasty|Ruling house]] of the [[Kingdom of Scotland]] | years=1371–1649 }}
{{s-vac | reason=[[Covenanter|The Covenanters]] }}
|-
{{s-bef | before=[[Tudor dynasty|House of Tudor]]}}
{{s-ttl | title=Ruling house of the [[Kingdom of England]] | years=1603–1649 }}
{{s-vac | reason=[[Commonwealth of England]] }}
|-
{{s-vac | reason=[[Covenanter|The Covenanters]] }}
{{s-ttl | title=Ruling house of the Kingdom of Scotland | years=1660–1707 }}
{{s-non | rows=2 | reason=Titles merged by the&lt;br&gt;[[Acts of Union 1707]] }}
|-
{{s-vac | reason=[[Commonwealth of England]] }}
{{s-ttl | title=Ruling house of the Kingdom of England | years=1660–1707 }}
|-
{{s-new | reason=England and Scotland united }}
{{s-ttl | title=Ruling house of the {{nowrap|[[Kingdom of Great Britain]]}} | years=1707–1714 }}
{{s-aft | after=[[House of Hanover]] }}
{{end}}
{{English, Scottish and British monarchs}}
{{Kingdom of England}}
{{Royal houses of Europe}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stuart Period}}
[[Category:House of Stuart| ]]
[[Category:Stuart England| ]]
[[Category:Stuart Scotland| ]]

[[af:Huis van Stuart]]
[[ar:ستيوارت]]
[[bs:Dinastija Stuart]]
[[ca:Època estuardiana]]
[[ca:Dinastia Estuard]]
[[cs:Stuartovci]]
[[de:Haus Stuart]]
[[et:Stuartid]]
[[el:Περίοδος των Στιούαρτ (Αγγλία)]]
[[el:Οίκος των Στιούαρτ]]
[[es:Casa de Estuardo]]
[[eo:Stuartoj]]
[[fr:Maison Stuart]]
[[gl:Casa de Estuardo]]
[[ko:스튜어트 왕가]]
[[hr:Dinastija Stuart]]
[[id:Wangsa Stuart]]
[[it:Stuart]]
[[it:Inghilterra degli Stuart]]
[[he:בית סטיוארט]]
[[lv:Stjuartu dinastija]]
[[hu:Stuart-ház]]
[[mk:Стјуартска династија]]
[[nl:Huis Stuart]]
[[ja:ステュアート朝]]
[[no:Huset Stuart]]
[[pl:Stuartowie]]
[[pt:Casa de Stuart]]
[[ru:Стюарты]]
[[simple:House of Stuart]]
[[sk:Stuartovci]]
[[fi:Stuart-suku]]
[[sv:Huset Stuart]]
[[th:สมัยสจวต]]
[[th:ราชวงศ์สจวต]]
[[zh:斯图亚特王朝]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
