<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="275181" ns="0" title="Bowling Green State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Bowling green (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox university
|name =Bowling Green State University
|image_name = Bowling Green State University seal.svg
|motto =
|established =1910
|type =Public
|endowment = [[United States dollar|$]]118.7 million&lt;ref&gt;As of August 31, 2010.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2010 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2009 to FY 2010| work = 2010 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = March 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff =1915
|faculty = 918
|president =[[Mary Ellen Mazey]]
|students = 19,764.&lt;ref name=&quot;iesenrollment&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nces.ed.gov/collegenavigator/?q=Bowling+Green+State&amp;s=all&amp;id=201441#enrolmt|title=Enrollment|publisher=[[U.S. Department of Education|U.S. Department of Education Institute of Education Sciences]]|accessdate=March 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad =16,773
|postgrad =2,991
|doctoral =
|city =[[Bowling Green, Ohio|Bowling Green]]
|state =[[Ohio]]
|country =[[United States]]
|campus =[[Rural|Small town]]&lt;br /&gt;{{convert|1338|acre|km2}}
|colors =Orange &amp; Brown {{color box|#FF7300}} {{color box|#613005}}
|mascot =[[Freddie and Frieda Falcon]]
|nickname =[[Bowling Green Falcons|Falcons]]
|affiliations =[[Mid-American Conference|MAC]] ([[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA DI]])
|website =http://www.bgsu.edu/
|coor = {{Coord|41.38|-83.64|type:landmark_region:US-OH|display=inline,title}}
|logo= [[File:Bowling Green State University wordmark.svg|200px]]
}}
'''Bowling Green State University''', often referred to as '''Bowling Green''' or '''BGSU''', is a [[Public university|public]], [[coeducational]] research university located in [[Bowling Green, Ohio]], [[United States]]. The institution was granted a charter in 1910 by the State of Ohio as part of the [[Lowry Bill]], which also established [[Kent State University]]. The {{convert|1338|acre|km2|adj=on}} main academic and residential campus is located {{convert|22|mi|km}} south of [[Toledo, Ohio]] in Bowling Green along [[I-75]]. In addition BGSU operates a satellite campus, known as [[BGSU Firelands]], in [[Huron, Ohio]] {{convert|60|mi|km}} east of the main campus.

Fielding athletic teams known as [[Bowling Green Falcons]], the university competes at the [[Division I (NCAA)|NCAA Division I]] level ([[NCAA Division I-A]] for football) as a member of the [[Mid-American Conference]] all sports except [[College ice hockey|ice hockey]], in which the university is a member of the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]]. BGSU is one of only thirteen universities in the nation that plays Division I FBS football and Division I ice hockey. The official school and athletic colors are orange and brown.

Bowling Green offers over 200 [[Undergraduate education|undergraduate programs]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://go2.bgsu.edu/choose/about/ | title=BGSYou at a Glance | publisher=Bowling Green State University Office of Admissions | accessdate=2008-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as various master's and doctoral degrees through eight academic colleges. The university has an enrollment of about 20,000 students,&lt;ref name=&quot;steadyenroll&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Hal|last=Brown|work=Bowling Green Sentinel Tribune|url=http://www.sent-trib.com/local-news/bgsu-enrollment-nearly-steady-from-jan-2010|title=BGSU enrollment nearly steady from Jan. 2010|date=January 26, 2011|accessdate=March 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an on-campus student population of 6,500 students.&lt;ref name=&quot;newdorms&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Lori|last=King|work=[[The Toledo Blade]]|url=http://m2.toledoblade.com/Education/2011/01/27/BGSU-s-new-dorms-draw-students-to-campus.html|title=BGSU's new dorms draw students to campus|date=January 27, 2011|accessdate=March 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of Bowling Green's students are from Ohio, with close to 90% of the total enrollment made up of in-state students.&lt;ref name=&quot;iesenrollment&quot;/&gt;

BGSU is home of the national literary journal [[Mid-American Review]], which publishes new works of fiction, poetry, and nonfiction, and which also sponsors Winter Wheat and The Festival of Writing each November. The university offers a large number of extracurricular activities to its students, including athletics, honor societies, clubs and student organizations, as well as [[fraternities]] and [[sororities]]. Alumni and former students have gone on to prominent careers in government, business, science, medicine, education, sports, and entertainment.

==History==
=== Early history ===
{{expand section|date=July 2011}}
[[File:BowlingGreenNormalCollege1915.jpg|thumb|Bowling Green Normal School in 1915]]
The university was one of several institutions established in the [[Progressive Era]] to meet demands for training and professional development of [[teacher]]s when representatives of the [[Ohio]] chose Bowling Green in 1910 as the location for a northwest Ohio normal school.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=[[Ohio Historical Society]]|title=Ohio History Central|url=http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=657|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;10timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/alumni/timeline/1910/|title=Timeline: 1910's Decade|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The representatives established the school at a site on the eastern side of the town on {{convert|82.5|acre|km2}} of land that included a town park.&lt;ref name=&quot;10timeline&quot;/&gt; The school opened in 1914 and was originally known as '''Bowling Green State Normal School''' and enrolled 304 students in 1914, primarily from [[Ohio]], [[Michigan]], and [[New York]] who were taught by the original faculty of 21.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohc&quot;/&gt; The school graduated 35 certified teachers in 1915, the same year that the campus’ first two buildings, University Hall and Williams Hall, opened their doors. Two years later the first baccalaureate degrees were awarded. Setting the pace for teacher education in Ohio with four-year degree programs, Bowling Green State Normal School achieved the status of college in 1929 and expanded its curriculum through the addition of the College of Liberal Arts, now known as the ''College of Arts and Sciences''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;a&amp;scollege&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|title=College of Arts and Sciences|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/as/page23385.html|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 28, 1927, the nickname “Falcons” was originated by the sports editor of the Daily Sentinel-Tribune. He thought the [[Falcon]] was fitting because it was indicative of a powerful bird that was small in stature, its coloring represented the Bowling Green school colors, and like the athlete, the falcon is a bird that goes through a long period of training before battle. At the time the school was still named Bowling Green State Normal College, Common nicknames, used by sports writers throughout the state, were “B.G. Normals,” “Teachers,” and the “B.G. Pedagogues&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Bowers|first1=Ann|last2=Swaisgood|first2=Linda K.|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/mc/magazine/fall03/BGSU_History_and_Traditions.pdf|title=The History And Traditions of BGSU|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university was briefly in danger of closure in 1933, as the state legislature explored the idea of converting the school into a mental institution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/alumni/timeline/1930/ | title=BGSU::Timeline::1930's Decade | publisher=Bowling Green State University Alumni and Friends | accessdate=2011-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As word spread about the proposed closure and conversion, many students, faculty, and administrators worked together with the Bowling Green community to protest such a move by the state. The Student Protest Committee, coordinating with the faculty and administration, orchestrated a campus rally and subsequent march through the heart of Bowling Green. Members of the Protest Committee then engaged in a letter writing campaign to different community leaders in northwest Ohio, which helped convince the state legislature that the closure of the school would be counterproductive. Later, in 1935, the school was granted university status, which led to the addition of graduate programs and the College of Business Administration. Such additions helped to raise the status of the institution from the college level when it was designated Bowling Green State University.&lt;ref name=&quot;30timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/alumni/timeline/1930/|title=Timeline: 1930s|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During [[World War II]], Bowling Green was one of 131 colleges and universities nationally that took part in the [[V-12 Navy College Training Program]] which offered students a path to a Navy commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;histCoEHD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Bowling Green State University|work=College of Education and Human Development|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/edhd/page80935.html|title=Our History|accessdate=September 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; With continued growth in the post-war era, enrollment grew rapidly and by 1950, the university's enrollment reached 4,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;histCoEHD&quot;/&gt; The [[Graduate School]] was formed, and BGSU awarded its first doctoral degree in English in 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;30timeline&quot;/&gt;

=== Recent history ===
{{expand section|date=July 2011}}
The 1970s represented a hallmark of progress with the addition of three new colleges. The [[Health|College of Health and Human Services]] opened in 1973 to offer degree programs in a variety of health and community services.&lt;ref name=&quot;setting&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/registrar/cat99/front/intro/theu.html|title=History and setting of the University|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1975, the ''School of Music'' was elevated to the [[music|College of Musical Arts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;setting&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/registrar/cat05/University/University12.html|title=History and setting of the University|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The School of Technology was given college status in 1985 and renamed the [[technology|College of Technology]]. The university expanded many of the technology and science facilities during the 1980s, including constructing the Planetarium and Physical Sciences Building.&lt;ref name=&quot;80timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/alumni/timeline/1980/|title=Timeline: 1980s|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1985 [[Ronald Reagan]] became the seventh president or president to-be to visit the university after [[Warren G. Harding]], [[Theodore Roosevelt]], [[William Howard Taft]], [[John F. Kennedy]], [[Richard Nixon]], and [[Gerald Ford]]. The founding tradition of teacher preparation is now maintained in the university's ''College of Education and Human Development''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;histCoEHD&quot;/&gt;

During the 1990s the university renovated and constructed a number of buildings on campus. The BGSU Fine Arts Center received a $9.8 million addition in the early 1990s. Founders Hall was reopened in 1994 after extensive renovations at a cost of $15 million, that same year BGSU opened Olscamp Hall.&lt;ref name=&quot;90timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/alumni/timeline/1990/|title=Timeline: 1990s|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1997 The university began construction on East Hall, which opened in 1998. All residence halls received wiring for [[Ethernet]] connections.&lt;ref name=&quot;90timeline&quot;/&gt; Following seven past presidents, [[Bill Clinton]] made two campaign stops at the university in 1993 and 1997.&lt;ref name=&quot;90timeline&quot;/&gt;

In 2008, the university began the first phase of a $200 million campus renovation project, as part of the master plan. BGSU first announced plans for the [[Stroh Center]], a new 5,000-seat arena to replace the aging [[Anderson Arena]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Strohplan&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[Toledo Blade]]|url=http://m2.toledoblade.com/Education/2008/12/04/BGSU-shows-plans-for-arena.html|title=BGSU shows plans for arena|date=December 4, 2008|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The $36 million arena will be the new home of Falcon basketball and volleyball games and be used for graduation ceremonies, concerts, and other events beginning in the 2011-12 academic year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strohplan&quot;/&gt; The arena is named for Kermit Stroh and Mary Lu Stroh, who donated $7.7 million for the project, amounting to the largest private gift in BGSU's history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strohplan&quot;/&gt;  In 2009 the university began construction on the [[Wolfe Center for the Arts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfeSn&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Jordana|first=Sebastian|work=ArchDaily|url=http://www.archdaily.com/21642/wolfe-center-for-the-arts-sn%C3%B8hetta/|title=Wolfe Center for the Arts / Snøhetta|date=May 10, 2009|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The {{convert|93000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} facility will include performance space, as well as work and classroom areas for art studies of the School of Art, the Department of Theatre and Film, and the School of Musical Arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfecollab&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Bohnert|first=Brian|publisher=[[BG News]]|url=http://bgnews.com/campus/wolfe-center-to-collaborate-with-arts/|title=Wolfe Center to collaborate with arts|date=June 7, 2011|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The facility is designed by [[Norway|Norwegian]] architectural firm [[Snøhetta (company)|Snøhetta]], the firm's first American project.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfeSn&quot;/&gt; That same year, BGSU began work on a $40 million residence hall project that included two new residence halls.&lt;ref name=&quot;2dorms&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Gilbert-Cunningham|first=Meghan|publisher=[[Toledo Blade]]|url=http://m2.toledoblade.com/Education/2009/11/17/BGSU-plans-for-2-new-dormitories.html|title=BGSU plans for 2 new dormitories|date=November 17, 2009|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; one a traditional-style dorm and a second suite-style designed for upperclassmen.&lt;ref name=&quot;2dorms&quot;/&gt; The residence hall project will add more than 800 beds to on-campus living.&lt;ref name=&quot;setnewres&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[WTVG|ABC 13]]|url=http://abclocal.go.com/wtvg/story?section=news/local&amp;id=7123929|title=BGSU set to build new residence halls|date=November 17, 2009|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2010, BGSU broke ground on The Oaks.&lt;ref name=&quot;oakspeak&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[WUPW|Fox Toledo]]|url=http://www.foxtoledo.com/dpp/news/local/bowling_green/Peak-into-The-Oaks-dining-hall-at-BGSU|title=Peak into The Oaks dining hall at BGSU|date=April 6, 2011|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The building opened in the Fall 2011 semester;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=Sentinel-Tribune|url=http://www.sent-trib.com/local-news/oaks-dining-hall-open-house-is-tuesday|title=Oaks dining hall open house is Tuesday |date= August 27, 2011|accessdate=September 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; it includes hybrid solar and wind power fulfilling  [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] (LEED), uses an electric-powered truck to distribute food on campus and has a rooftop garden. Additionally, the building uses sustainable and recycled construction materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;groundbrkdining&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Brown|first=Harold|publisher=[[WUPW|Fox Toledo]]|url=http://www.foxtoledo.com/dpp/news/local/BGSU-breaks-ground-for-new-dining-hall|title=BGSU breaks ground for new dining hall|date=July 1, 2010|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Presidents===
Presidents of BGSU have included Homer B. Williams (1912–1937), R.E. Offenhauer (1937–1938), Frank J. Prout (1938–1951), Ralph W. McDonald (1951–1961), Ralph G. Harshman (1961–1963), William Travers Jerome III (1963–1970), Hollis A. Moore, Jr. (1970–1981), Michael R. Ferrari ''(Interim)'' (1981–1982), Paul J. Olscamp (1982–1995), [[Sidney A. Ribeau]] (1995–2008), and [[Carol A. Cartwright]]  (2008–2011), and [[Mary Ellen Mazey]] (2011–present).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[WUPW|Fox Toledo]]|url=http://www.foxtoledo.com/dpp/news/Mazey-to-lead-BGSU|title=Mazey to lead BGSU|date=March 22, 2011|accessdate=April 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Campus ==
The main academic and residential campus of Bowling Green State is located on the Northeast side of [[Bowling Green, Ohio]]. The campus is laid out in a [[rectangle]] roughly one and a half miles long and a mile wide and includes over 116 buildings on {{convert|1338|acre|km2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;setting&quot;/&gt; The main portion of campus is bordered by [[Ohio State Route 64|Wooster Street]] to the South, Thurstin Ave to the West, Poe Rd to the North, and [[I-75]] to the East. The university also owns a number of other buildings and parking lots throughout Bowling Green and the Bowling Green Research Enterprise Park just east of [[I-75]]. Ridge Street and East Merry Street run East-West through campus and Mercer Street bisects campus on a North-South axis. Oak Grove Cemetery is located in the North-central portion of campus.

[[Image:MoseleyHall.JPG|thumb|right|Mosley Hall built in 1916]]
This portion of the BGSU campus is located in the southwest corner of campus. It contains the oldest buildings on campus and the historical location of the entire university. The part of campus has vast green space with many large trees and a number of [[historic buildings]] built in the early 1900s and original to the university. A number of administrative services occupy the buildings in old campus as well as classroom space. Although not part of the historic section, Founders Hall, a large residence hall is located on the Southwest corner of campus. Hanna Hall houses the The Dorothy and Lillian Gish Film Theater and Gallery.  Dedicated to BGSU in 1976, it features film paraphernalia that honors early film history and the careers of both [[Lillian Gish]] and [[Dorothy Gish]].  Ralph Evan Wolfe currently oversees The Gish Film Theater and Gallery and contributes films, movie posters, and funds to the collection.  It was renovated and rededicated in 1990.  It seats 168 and is home to Tuesdays at the Gish, International Film Series, and Sunday Matinee Series], which are all free and open to the community.&lt;ref name=&quot;gish&quot;&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/gish/|title=Gish Theater|accessdate=September 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Science Research Complex is located on northwest side of campus. The buildings of the science research complex are much newer, built in the mid 1960s. They include the Mathematical Science Building, Life Science, Psychology Building, Physical Science Building, and Technology Building([[engineering]]), are all located in this portion of BGSU. In addition The [[Geology]], [[Chemistry]], and [[Earth Science]] Departments are located in Overman Hall on the Northwest portion of campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/library/cac/uarchives/uatour/page49968.html&lt;/ref&gt; Two large residence hall occupy the Western edge of campus. The Offenhauer Towers consist of a 10 story tower and an 11 story tower. They are the two largest buildings on campus. The McDonald Quadrangle houses over 1,300 students.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/library/cac/uarchives/uatour/page49974.html&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Bgsnow.JPG|thumb|left|Fresh snow covers the lawn near the Student Union.]]
The Bowen-Thompson Student Union opened in 2002 and is located in the West-central part of campus. It houses a number of places to eat: Falcon's Nest [[food court]], The Bowling Greenery, [[Starbucks]], [[Wendy's]], and The Black Swamp Pub, an on-campus pub. Other facilities include the Campus Bookstore, The Peregrine Shop (a [[convenience store]]), an on-campus [[post office]], computer labs, meeting rooms, a 250-seat [[movie theater]], ball rooms, and student lounges.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/map/buildings/page14091.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Central Campus is made up of a number of large lecture halls and classroom buildings. One of the most prominent is the {{convert|95,000|sqft|m2|abbr=on|sigfig=1}} Olscamp Hall, which contains 28 classrooms and lecture halls capable of seating a total of 2,000 students. Other large lecture halls include, The Business Administration Building, The  Education Building, and Eppler Complex, home to the [[Sport Management]] department. [[Anderson Arena]] is a 5,000-seat arena and the home for BGSU Men's and Women's [[basketball]] and women's [[gymnastics]] and [[volleyball]]. Memorial Hall is connected to Anderson and houses the [[ROTC]] programs.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/map/buildings/page23792.html&lt;/ref&gt; [[University Libraries at Bowling Green State University|Jerome Library]] is the main library on campus and the second tallest building at nine stories.

University Health Services is located along Ridge Street and the BGSU campus police station as well as parking and traffic is located near the intersection of Wooster Street and College Ave on the southern edge of campus. Kohl Hall and Rodgers Quadrangle are two residence halls located along Wooster Street in the central portion of campus. Located along Wooster Street is a complex of individual on-campus [[fraternity houses]] as well as a few [[sorority houses]], although the majority of Sorority living spaces are near the Student Union on the western edge of BG.
[[Image:Jerome Library.jpg|thumb|right|Jerome Library on BGSU's main Campus]]
Arts programs are located to the East of Anderson Arena and [[University Libraries at Bowling Green State University|Jerome Library]] in the East-central portion of campus. Fine Arts Center is home to the School of Art and houses classroom, studio, and workshop spaces, art galleries, and faculty offices. Moore Musical Arts Center is located along Ridge and is the home to the College of Musical Arts. Moore includes classrooms, recording studios, rehearsal halls, and the [[MidAmerican Center for Contemporary Music]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/music/MACCM/&lt;/ref&gt; The Centerpiece for the Arts portion of campus will be the Wolfe Center. The modern facility will house the Department of Theatre and Film. The {{convert|93,000|sqft|m2|abbr=on|sigfig=1}} building will include classrooms, rehearsal space, performance/theater space, as well as design and office space. Construction will begin in April 2009 with completion set for 2011.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sent-trib.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=10396&amp;Itemid=94&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Wolfe Center for the Arts]] opens in 2011 and includes {{convert|93000|sqft|m2|}} of space for the School of Art, the Department of Theatre and Film, and the School of Musical Arts.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfecollab&quot;/&gt; The Wolfe Center contains and features the 400-seat Thomas and Kathleen Donnell Theatre,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[Toledo Blade]]|url=http://m2.toledoblade.com/frontpage/2007/05/04/Findlay-pair-give-750-000-to-BGSU-for-theater-plans.html|title=Findlay pair give $750,000 to BGSU for theater plans|date=May 4, 2007|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; a [[black box theatre|black-box stage]], editing and digital laboratories, classrooms, studios, faculty space, and choral rehearsal rooms.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfecollab&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Staff|publisher=[[Toledo Blade]]|url=http://m2.toledoblade.com/frontpage/2009/10/19/Bowling-Green-State-University.html|title=Frontpage Bowling Green State University|date=October 19, 2009|accessdate=July 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Athletic and recreation facilities ===
[[Image:BGvMIhky.jpg|thumb|left|BGSU vs. [[University of Michigan|U. of Michigan]] hockey game]]
The majority of Athletic and recreation facilities are located on the Eastern half of campus along and to the East of Mercer Street. The Student Recreation Center is a {{convert|185,000|sqft|m2|abbr=on|sigfig=2}} facility that includes two swimming pools, four weight rooms, a cardio room, an elevated running track, an Activity Center for [[aerobics]] and a large Sports Center which accommodates [[basketball]], [[tennis]], [[volleyball]], and [[badminton]] and other sports. The Perry Field House is a {{convert|127,000|sqft|m2|abbr=on|sigfig=2}} athletic facility with a 100 x 60 indoor [[synthetic turf]], four batting cages, and a 200-meter track encircling four courts for basketball, volleyball, or tennis. The [[BGSU Ice Arena]] is a 5,000-seat [[ice hockey]] arena that is used by various teams and clubs as well as public use. In addition to the main ice surface the arena also includes a smaller ice sheet for [[curling]], [[figure skating]], [[ice hockey|youth ice hockey]], and [[ice skating|public skating]]. The Eppler complex is oldest building on campus for athletics and is main practice area for [[cheerleading]], [[gymnastics]], [[dancing]] and [[fencing]]. At one time it housed the original nautorium. [[Doyt Perry Stadium]] is a 28,600 seat [[college football]] stadium located on the Eastern edge of campus along [[I-75]]. The [[Stroh Center]] is a new on-campus venue for athletics, concerts, commencement, lectures, and numerous campus and community events. The facility serves as the home for the Falcons men’s and women’s basketball and volleyball programs. Notably, the new structure will be one of the most environmentally friendly buildings on campus, designed to achieve challenging Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|(LEED)]] certification.&lt;ref name=&quot;strohcompletion&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| last = Emmons | first = Donald | title = A BGSU jewel Stroh Center on pace for completion in 2011 | newspaper = Toledo Blade | pages =  | date = June 28, 2010 | url = http://www.toledoblade.com/BGSU/2010/06/28/A-BGSU-jewel-Stroh-Center-on-pace-for-completion-in-2011.html | accessdate = June 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Transportation ===
The campus fare-free bus transit system began in 1990 and that runs throughout campus and [[Bowling Green, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=&quot;90timeline&quot;/&gt; The system is made up of three routes (not including the special shortened Sunday-only route). The main route includes major stops on campus and buses run every 10 minutes. Off Campus North Route runs from the bus stop at the Student Union North through The Science Research Complex before leaving campus and running North to the Woodland Mall before heading back southeast with stops at major apartment complexes and downtown Bowling Green. The Off Campus South Route is the third route and runs through the southern portion of campus and the neighborhoods South of the university.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/safety/page25627.html&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the bus system, the university also runs a free ride service for students to go to destinations off campus.

===BGSU Firelands Campus===
{{Main|BGSU Firelands}}
Extension services are integral to the University’s rich curricular texture and rural history. First offered in 1946 in the Sandusky, Ohio, area and later expanded to serve [[Erie County, Ohio|Erie]], [[Huron County, Ohio|Huron]], [[Lorain County, Ohio|Lorain]], and [[Ottawa County, Ohio|Ottawa]] counties, extension programs established a foundation for [[BGSU Firelands]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.firelands.bgsu.edu BGSU: Firelands College&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; the University's regional campus. Located near the shores of [[Lake Erie]] in [[Huron, Ohio]], and about {{convert|60|mi|km}} east of Bowling Green, Ohio, This college was established in 1968, when the first building (now Foundation Hall) at the Huron location was opened. BGSU Firelands is home to approximately 2,000 students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/ir/factbook/student/headcount-en/campus.htm | title=Headcount Enrollment by Campus | publisher=Bowling Green State University Office of Institutional Research | accessdate=2008-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The college grants mostly 2-year degrees, but students are able to complete 4-year degrees in Early Childhood Education, Criminal Justice, Business Administration, Liberal Studies, Visual Communication Technology, Applied Health Science, Nursing, and Advanced Tech Ed.

In 2003, the Cedar Point Center, BGSU’s most technologically sophisticated facility, opened its doors on the Firelands campus to serve constituents of the University and the community. For instance, The Women's Center, founded in 1998, provides a place for the community to gather and serves as a resource center. Many student organizations meet at the center. The center hosts brown bag lunches once a month where all are welcome to join in informal discussions on topics of broad interest.

==Academics and organization==
{{Infobox US university ranking
| USNWR_NU             = 170
| Wamo_NU              = 143
}}
Colleges and schools at BGSU include [[Bowling Green State University College of Arts and Sciences|College of Arts and Sciences]], [[Bowling Green State University College of Business Administration|College of Business Administration]], [[Bowling Green State University College of Education and Human Development|College of Education and Human Development]], [[Bowling Green State University Graduate College|Graduate College]], [[Bowling Green State University College of Health and Human Services|College of Health and Human Services]], [[Bowling Green State University College of Musical Arts|College of Musical Arts]], and [[Bowling Green State University College of Technology|College of Technology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/colleges/ | title=BGSU Colleges  | accessdate=2009-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are two schools within the College of Arts and Sciences: [http://www.bgsu.edu/departments/sees/ the School of Earth, Environment and Society] and [http://www.bgsu.edu/departments/smc/index.html the School of Media and Communication].

For 2011, BGSU was ranked 170th by ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' as a ''Tier 1'' university.&lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/bowling-green-oh/bowling-green-state-university-3018&lt;/ref&gt;

BGSU's degree programs include the nation's first [[Ph.D.]] program in [[photochemical]] science, one of the first undergraduate programs in [[neuroscience]], the first masters degree in Organizational Development and the first executive MBA program in the State of Ohio.{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} The college of Business recently opened a facility at Levis Commons in Perrysburg Ohio for its Professional MBA program. In addition, BGSU has accreditation from the [[Higher Learning Commission]] (HLC) of the [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]] to offer full degree programs online.

BGSU remains a leader in [[teacher]] preparation institution. Students enrolled in the [[Education|College of Education and Human Development]] may choose majors from among several teacher licensure areas, including early childhood (grades Pre-K to 3), Middle Childhood (grades 4 - 9), Adolescent-Young Adult (grades 7 - 12), Special Education (grades K - 12), and foreign language (grades K - 12).  In addition, BGSU continues to have one of the top four programs in the United States for Industrial &amp; Organizational Psychology per U.S. News and World Report.&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-humanities-schools/industrial-organizational-psychology-rankings&lt;/ref&gt;

BGSU currently is the home of Ohio's largest student-run philanthropy, Dance Marathon. Dance Marathon is run entirely by college students nationwide to benefit local children's hospitals, and Bowling Green State University is proud to have one of the largest and most active Dance Marathon organizations in the nation. Funds raised through BGSU's Dance Marathon benefit ill or injured children at the Mercy Children's Hospital in Toledo via the Children's Miracle Network. The 2011 event will be held April 2 &amp; 3 at the Student Recreation Center. For more information visit www.bgdancemarathon.com

In 1979, American [[author]] [[James Baldwin (writer)|James Baldwin]] taught at BGSU for one quarter as a Distinguished Visiting Professor in the Ethnic Studies Department, after a month-long stint as writer-in-residence in 1978.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bgsu.edu/departments/ethn/page38981.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{main|Bowling Green Falcons}}
{| style=&quot;float:right; margin:0.5em 0em 0.5em 0.5em; width:16em; border:1px solid #a0a0a0; text-align:center; line-height:12px; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;line-height:16px; font-size:small;&quot;
| bgcolor=&quot;#FF7300&quot;| Sports at &lt;br&gt;Bowling Green
|-
| valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| width=&quot;100%&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| width=&quot;50%&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; |
{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| '''MEN'S'''
|-
| Baseball
|-
| Basketball
|-
| Cross County
|-
| Football
|-
| Golf
|-
| Ice Hockey
|-
| Soccer
|}
| width=&quot;50%&quot; |
{| align=&quot;center&quot;
|-
| '''WOMEN'S'''
|-
| Basketball
|-
| Cross County
|-
| Golf
|-
| Gymnastics
|-
| Soccer
|-
| Softball
|-
| Swimming
|-
| Tennis
|-
| Track &amp; Field
|-
| Volleyball
|}
|}
|}
Bowling Green's sports teams are called the Falcons. The Falcons participate in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] (Division I-A for [[american football|football]]) and in the [[Mid-American Conference]] and the [[Central Collegiate Hockey Association]]. BGSU is one of only 13 universities in the country offering NCAA division I-A football, division I men's and women's [[basketball]], and division I [[ice hockey]]. The Falcons have won three conference championships in a row in women's basketball in 2005, 2006, and 2007. In advancing to the [[NCAA Women's Division I Basketball Championship]] each of those years, the Falcons lost in the first round in 2005 and 2006, but then won their first two games on their way to the &quot;Sweet Sixteen&quot; in 2007. The women's soccer team won the conference crown in 2005.

The Falcons' main rivals are the Rockets of the [[University of Toledo]]. Separated by just {{convert|20|mi|km}} on [[Interstate 75]], the two schools celebrate a heated rivalry in several sports. The most well-known of these games is the [[Battle of I-75]], a football game held each year in which the winner takes home the [[Peace Pipe (college football)|Peace Pipe]], an American Indian peace pipe placed upon a wood tablet. The 1984 Falcons hockey team defeated the [[University of Minnesota-Duluth]], in the longest college hockey championship game in history, to win the NCAA National Championship. Former BGSU head football coach Doyt L. Perry lead the Falcons to a NCAA Football National Title in the year of 1959. Former BGSU head football coach [[Urban Meyer]] went on to great success at the [[University of Florida]], earning two [[BCS National Championship Game]] appearances in a three year span, winning in both [[2007 BCS National Championship Game|2007]] and [[2009 BCS National Championship Game|2009]].  Former BGSU head hockey coach Jerry York went on to become the winningest active coach in NCAA hockey and win three NCAA National Championships at [[Boston College]] in [[2001 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2001]], [[2008 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2008]], and [[2010 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|2010]] after his first at Bowling Green in [[1984 NCAA Men's Division I Ice Hockey Tournament|1984]].

In 2008, Bowling Green State University released plans for the new [[Stroh Center]], which is intended to be the new home for BGSU basketball and volleyball.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://media.www.bgnews.com/media/storage/paper883/news/2008/12/05/Campus/University.Reveals.Plans.For.New.Stroh.Center-3571970.shtml | title=University reveals plans for new Stroh Center | publisher=BGNews | accessdate=2008-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Another important entity of BGSU Athletics is the musical contributions from the 270 member [[Falcon Marching Band]] and the BGSU Athletic Band. They perform at most, if not all, &quot;home&quot; athletic events.

==Student life==
[[Image:Bgsustudentunion.JPG|thumb|The Student Union]]
For the fourth consecutive year in 2007, BGSU was listed for its residential living/learning communities in ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'s'' “America's Best Colleges”  under  “Programs to Look For,” a section of the guide that notes “outstanding examples of academic programs believed to lead to student success.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/usnews/edu/college/rankings/brief/acadprogs02_brief.php | title=America's Best Colleges 2008: Learning Communities| publisher=US News and World Report | accessdate=2008-03-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; In BGSU's residential learning communities, students with similar interests and goals live and study together. In the academically based communities students work closely with faculty members who teach classes and have offices right in the residence hall.

BGSU's Career Center provides comprehensive career services to its students and alumni including career planning, on- and off-campus student employment, co-op and internships opportunities, and post-graduate and graduate school planning. The following services are provided: (1) individual consultations to discuss academic and career planning or job search strategies, (2) career development courses including UNIV 131-Career &amp; Life Planning, UNIV 141-Effective Strategies in the Workplace, and UNIV 141-Career Implementation, (3) career assessments that measure interests, personality characteristics and preferences for various work environments, (4) the Career Resource Library, (5) on-campus recruiting, (6) job fairs, (7) workshops related to interviewing, resume writing, job search techniques, and networking, (8)WorkNet, an online job listing software, and (9) career related publications. The Career Center can help students develop career goals, identify academic and experiential program that achieve these goals, and help students gain employment in their chosen field.

GeoJourney is a nine-week field trip/camping trip/road trip across the United States to many national parks and monuments for a full semester of college credit. The course content taught as a part of the GeoJourney field program includes geology, environmental studies and Native American studies.    &quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.geojourney.org | title=GeoJourney| publisher=GeoJourney}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004 the first GeoJourney trip went to 24 states 30 national parks and covered over 14,500 miles across the United States. Since then the GeoJourney program has run every year and taken 24 students around the country for BGSU course credit.

From its beginning in 1999 as a student run organization under the University Activities Organization, the BGSU Outdoor Program &quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/sa/recsports/outdoor/ | title=BGSU Outdoor Program| publisher=Bowling Green State University | accessdate=2008-12-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; has evolved into a valuable additional to campus life as a part of the Department of Recreational Sports.  The OP, as it is often referred, offers outdoor trips, an indoor climbing wall, team-building, and an outdoor equipment rental center to BGSU students, faculty, staff and surrounding community members.  In August 2008 the BGSU Outdoor Program introduced the Freshman Wilderness Experience.  This program couples a week-long backpacking trip on the Appalachian Trail with a monthly class to assist students in transitioning from high school to college life. In 2009 The Outdoor Program won the David J Web award for being an outstanding [[non-profit]] outdoor program by AORE&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aore.org/awards/default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

Bowling Green hosts an annual event for three days in February similar to other [[Winter City|winter cities]] to celebrate winter, [[snow]], and [[winter sports|cold weather activities]]. Winterfest in Bowling Green centers around the rich [[ice skating]] and [[ice hockey]] traditions of the town.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sent-trib.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=11270&amp;Itemid=81&lt;/ref&gt; Winterfest events are held all over Bowling Green, and on and off campus. Many of the on campus events are held at the [[BGSU Ice Arena]], curling, skating, [[Bowling Green Falcons men's ice hockey|BGSU ice hockey]] and figure skating exhibitions are just a few of the events held during the weekend on campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.toledoblade.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090215/NEWS16/902150299/-1/NEWS24&lt;/ref&gt;

===Greek life===
[[File:KA-TKE.jpg|thumb|thumb|Greek life at BGSU]]
Bowling Green hosts many ''social'' fraternities and sororities. Greek student comprise 12% of all undergraduate students at the university. Fraternities and sororities are apart of one of four councils: Inter-Fraternity Council (IFC), Panhellenic Council (Panhel), National Pan-Hellenic Council (NPHC), or Multicultural Greek Council (MGC). IFC members include: [[Alpha Sigma Phi]], [[Alpha Tau Omega]], [[Delta Chi]], [[Delta Tau Delta]], [[Kappa Alpha Order]], [[Kappa Sigma]], [[Lambda Chi Alpha]], [[Phi Delta Theta]], [[Phi Gamma Delta]], [[Phi Kappa Psi]], [[Pi Kappa Alpha]], [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], [[Sigma Nu]], [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]], &amp; [[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]. Panhel members include: [[Alpha Chi Omega]], [[Alpha Omicron Pi]], [[Alpha Phi]], [[Alpha Xi Delta]], [[Chi Omega]], [[Delta Gamma]], [[Delta Zeta]], [[Gamma Phi Beta]], [[Kappa Delta]], [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]], [[Phi Mu]], [[Pi Beta Phi]], [[Sigma Kappa]]. NPHC members include eight of the [[Divine nine]]: [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] sorority, [[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity, [[Delta Sigma Theta]] sorority, [[Iota Phi Theta]] fraternity, [[Kappa Alpha Psi]] fraternity, [[Omega Psi Phi]] fraternity, [[Phi Beta Sigma]] fraternity, &amp; [[Zeta Phi Beta]] sorority. MGC members include: [[Delta Lambda Phi]] fraternity (Gay, Bisexual and Progressive Men), [[Delta Xi Phi]] sorority (Multicultural), [[Omega Phi Alpha]] sorority (service), [[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]] fraternity, [[Sigma Lambda Beta]] International fraternity, Inc, and [[Sigma Lambda Gamma]] sorority

==Media and publications==
The student operated, independent daily newspaper [[The BG News]], which has been published since 1920. The BG News's web portal BG Views was launched in 2009. The university's independent, student operated yearbook was first published in 1918 as the Bee Gee. Publication stopped after 1918 for 6 years and in 1924 the yearbook resumed production under a new name, The KEY and was published every year since 1924 as the only comprehensive record of students, activities, and events for a given year. In 2008, the yearbook was replaced with a magazine, The Key Magazine. This is the only magazine sponsored by BGSU and fully run by BGSU students and supported by local advertising only. The campus is home to two student-operated radio stations as part of the Department of Telecommunications. [[WBGU-FM|WBGU 88.1 FM]] serves as an [[independent radio]], [[non-commercial educational]] (NCE), FCC-licensed [[college radio]] station, while [[WFAL Falcon Radio]], formerly WFAL 1610 AM, is a student-run [[commercial radio]] station. Bowling Green Radio News Organization (BGRNO)-BGRNO provides up-to-the minute radio news coverage Monday-Friday on WBGU-FM AND WFAL-AM. Students write, produce, and report live on the air the latest local and national news, sports and weather stories. Bowling Green Radio Sports Organization (BGRSO)-BGRSO broadcasts BGSU's football, hockey, men's and women's basketball, and baseball games on WBGU-FM and WFAL-AM. WBGU-FM is also the flagship station for women's basketball and hockey. BGSU is also home to BG24 News, a student-run [[television news]]cast airing live at 5:30pm three days a week.

''[[Mid-American Review]]'' (MAR), published through the BGSU Department of English since 1980, is nationally recognized for publishing contemporary fiction, poetry, nonfiction, and translations. Preceding MAR was Itinerary, a magazine that was established by editor Robert Early in 1972 to publish the works of BGSU's MFA students. However, the students tired of publishing nothing but their own work and suggested broadening into an international publication. Itinerary was retired in 1980 when the first issue of MAR was released. No BGSU student work is included in MAR (with the exception of occasional reviews of newly released literary titles). ''Prairie Margins'' is a national undergraduate literary journal published by students in the Creative Writing Program at BGSU. The annual journal features literary work by both BGSU students and undergraduate creative writers from other institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|publisher=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/studentlife/organizations/prairiemargins/prairiemargins.html|title=Prairie Margins|accessdate=September 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Projector'' is a peer-reviewed electronic journal on film, media and culture published twice a year by the Department of Theatre &amp; Film.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|publisher=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/departments/theatrefilm/projector/page30082.html|title=About The Projector|accessdate=September 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Traditions and events==
* BGSU's official spirit crew is called [[Sic Sic|SICSIC]] which began in 1946.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/sa/life/traditions/page11733.html | title=SICSIC | publisher=Bowling Green State University | accessdate=2008-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; New members are chosen during the end of their freshman year in order to replace that year's graduating seniors. SICSIC members are always masked and their identities are not revealed until the last home basketball game of their senior year, where they are unmasked in front of the student body.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=The Spirit Crew | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/sa/life/sicsic/page11685.html | work=Sic Sic | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* BGSU's official mascots are [[Freddie and Frieda Falcon]]. Freddie began appearing at athletic events in 1950. Frieda first appeared in 1966, but officially re-emerged in 1980.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/sa/life/freddie_frieda/page10459.html | title=History of Freddie and Frieda Falcon | publisher=Bowling Green State University | accessdate=2008-04-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Buckeye Boys State - Bowling Green is the current home for the [[American Legion]] Buckeye Boys State, which gathers high-school students from all over [[Ohio]] for a nine-day program. At Buckeye Boys State, the students operate a full [[government]] modeled after the [[Government of Ohio]]. Buckeye Boys State is held each June.

== Alumni ==
&lt;!-- DO NOT ADD PEOPLE TO THIS SECTION WITHOUT A VERIFIABLE CITATION.
Additions without a citation are subject to removal. 
If a citation link is broken, please replace it with one that works.
--&gt;
&lt;!-- PLEASE DO NOT ADD NON-NOTABLE PEOPLE TO THIS SECTION
A good rule of thumb is to check whether the person has an article on Wikipedia. If not, consider starting an article on the subject before adding him/her to this list.
--&gt;
{{main|List of Bowling Green State University alumni}}
BGSU has seen many of its former students go on to local and national prominence. This includes many athletes that have excelled at the collegiate and professional levels, including: [[Kevin Bieksa]], [[Scott Hamilton (figure skater)|Scott Hamilton]], [[Mike McCullough (golfer)|Mike McCullough]], [[Nate Thurmond]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.nba.com/history/players/thurmond_bio.html | title=Nate Thurmond Bio| publisher=National Basketball Association | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Rob Blake]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.geocities.com/robblake4/information.htm | title=Information| publisher=Rob Blake Fansite | accessdate=2008-03-04|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20091026021847/http://geocities.com/robblake4/information.htm|archivedate=2009-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Orel Hershiser]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.spiritus-temporis.com/orel-hershiser/ | title=Biography of Orel Hershiser| publisher=Spiritus Temporis | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ken Morrow]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.hockeydb.com/ihdb/stats/pdisplay.php3?pid%5B%5D=3813 | title=Ken Morrow| publisher=Hockeydb.com | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Don Nehlen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://bgsufalcons.cstv.com/school-bio/bgu-varsityclub-lifetime.html | title=Lifetime Members| publisher=Varsity BG Club | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jordan Sigalet]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.hockeygoalies.org/bio/sigalet.html | title=Jordan Sigalet| publisher=HockeyGoalies.org | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[George McPhee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://capitals.nhl.com/team/app?service=page&amp;page=NHLPage&amp;bcid=tea_mcphee | title=George McPhee - Vice President and Gernal Manager| publisher=Washington Capitals | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, many state politicians have graduated from Bowling Green, including current Ohio congressman [[Tim Ryan (politician)|Tim Ryan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://timryan.house.gov/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=27&amp;Itemid=49 | title=Biography| publisher=Congressman Tim Ryan | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; former Israeli ambassador [[Daniel Ayalon]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.israelemb.org/articles/2002/July/2002073000.htm | title=Daniel Ayalon Biography| publisher=Embassy of Israel Briefing | date=2002-07-30 |accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and current Ohio state senators [[Randy Gardner (Ohio politician)|Randy Gardner]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.votesmart.org/bio.php?can_id=8121 | title=Representative Randall L. Gardner | publisher=Project Vote Smart | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kevin Coughlin]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.kevincoughlin.com/about/ | title=About Kevin Coughlin | publisher=Kevin Coughlin - Ohio's State Senator, 27th District | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other notable [[alumni]] include [[actress]] [[Eva Marie Saint]], author [[Philana Marie Boles]], NYU economic professor [[William Easterly]], [[actor]] [[Tim Conway]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.biography.com/search/article.do?id=9542241 | title=Tim Conway Biography | publisher=Biography.com | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Group President for Discovery Communications Eileen O'Neill,&lt;ref&gt;http://corporate.discovery.com/leadership/eileen-oneill/&lt;/ref&gt; ESPN sportscasters [[Jay Crawford]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.espnmediazone.com/bios/Talent/Crawford_Jay.htm | title=Jay Crawford - Bio| publisher=ESPN Media Zone | accessdate=2008-03-04 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080530233323/http://www.espnmediazone.com/bios/Talent/Crawford_Jay.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Jason Jackson]], [[CBS News]] Correspondent [[Steve Hartman]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2002/05/16/broadcasts/main509349.shtml | title=Steve Hartman 'Assignment America' Correspondent| publisher=CBS News | accessdate=2008-03-04 | date=2002-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Texas Christian University|TCU]] Chancellor [[Victor Boschini|Dr. Victor J. Boschini]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.chancellor.tcu.edu/chancellor.htm | title=About the Chancellor| publisher=Texas Christian University - Office of the Chancellor | accessdate=2008-03-04 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070910230053/http://www.chancellor.tcu.edu/chancellor.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Adobe Systems]] President and CEO [[Shantanu Narayen]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |  url=http://www.adobe.com/aboutadobe/pressroom/executivebios/shantanunarayen.html | title=Executive Profiles-Shantanu Narayen| publisher=Adobe Systems | accessdate=2008-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Colonel Brenda Joyce Hollis]] (Ret., U.S. Air Force) who was inducted into the Ohio Women’s Hall of Fame for her efforts as an international criminal prosecutor who was a pivotal figure during the Yugoslav Tribunal in 1994 — the first international trials in which rape was categorized as torture and recognized as a war crime. Col. Hollis was recently appointed as prosecutor to the Special Court for Sierra Leone by the United Nations Secretary-General.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=Bowling Green State University|url=http://www.bgsu.edu/offices/mc/news/2011/news100339.html|title=BGSU alumna inducted into the Ohio Women’s Hall of Fame|date=September 1, 2011|accessdate=September 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bgsu.edu Official BGSU website]
* [http://www.bgsufalcons.com/index.aspx Official Falcons Athletics website]

{{Bowling Green State University}}
{{Colleges and universities in Ohio}}
{{Mid-American Conference}}
{{Central Collegiate Hockey Association}}
{{Public universities in Ohio}}

[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1910]]
[[Category:Bowling Green State University| ]]
[[Category:Education in Wood County, Ohio|*Bowling Green State University]]
[[Category:Mid-American Conference]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Ohio]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Wood County, Ohio]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Wood County, Ohio]]

[[ar:جامعة بولينغ غرين ستيت]]
[[de:Bowling Green State University]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی بولینگ گرین]]
[[fr:Université d'État de Bowling Green]]
[[ja:ボーリング・グリーン州立大学]]
[[no:Bowling Green State University]]
[[simple:Bowling Green State University]]
[[zh:鮑林格林州立大學]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
