<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27576770" ns="0" title="Afghan civil war"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Military Conflict
|conflict    = Afghan civil war
|image       =
|caption     =
|date        =27 April 1978 - present
|place       = [[Afghanistan]]
|result      = Ongoing. Military coup - Democratic Republic of Afghanistan (1978) - popular uprising - Soviet invasion (1979) - 'mujahideen' resistance - Soviet withdrawal (1989) - collapse of the [[Democratic Republic of Afghanistan]] (1992) - establishment of the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]] (1992) - foreign (military) interference - internal war - establishment of the [[Taliban]] [[Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan]] (1996) - resistance to the Taliban Emirate by the [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Front]] - 9/9 and 9/11 (2001) - [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|NATO intervention]] (2001) - fall of the Taliban government and establishment of the [[Islamic Republic of Afghanistan]] (2001) - [[Taliban insurgency]]. 
|casualties3 = 600,000 - 2,000,000 {{Citation needed|date=November 2011}} }}
{{Campaignbox Afghanistan}}
The '''Afghan civil war''' began when the [[communist party|communist]] [[People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan]] (PDPA) took power in a military coup, known as the [[Saur Revolution]], on 27 April 1978. Most of [[Afghanistan]] subsequently experienced uprisings against the unpopular Marxist-Leninist PDPA government. The [[Soviet war in Afghanistan|Soviet Union invaded Afghanistan]] in December 1979 to keep the Afghan PDPA communists in power. Afghanistan's resistance forces, known as the [[Mujahideen#Afghanistan|mujahideen]], fought against the [[Soviet invasion of Afghanistan]]. Some factions received support by the United States, with the Pakistani [[ISI]] serving as the U.S. middleman, and Saudi Arabia. The [[Soviet Union]] had to withdraw its troops in February 1989. The Soviet-backed Afghan communist regime survived for three more years until the fall of Kabul in 1992.

In 1992, the Afghan political parties agreed on the [[Javed_Nasir#Enforcement_of_Peshawar_Accord|Peshawar Accords]] which established the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]] and appointed an interim government. Militia leader [[Gulbuddin Hekmatyar]] was opposed to the agreement and with Pakistani support started a bombardment campaign against Kabul. Additionally, three militias who had been able to occupy some suburbs of Kabul engaged in a violent war against each other. Regional powers such as [[Pakistan]], [[Iran]], [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Uzbekistan]] seeking influence over the geostrategically located Afghanistan each supported and in some cases controlled one of those militias. While Kabul and some other major cities witnessed most of the fighting during that period most of the more rural parts of Afghanistan, which had seen especially massive bombardment by the Soviets and Communists, remained relatively calm. In late 1994/early 1995 as the Islamic State's minister of defense [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] had been able to defeat most of the militias militarily in Kabul and had restored some calm to the capital, the Taliban emerged as a new faction threatening Kabul.

The [[Taliban]] had initially emerged as a new force in the southern city of [[Kandahar]] conquering many southern and central provinces not under Islamic State control in the course of 1994. In early 1995, as they launched a major operation against the capital Kabul, they suffered a devastating defeat against the Islamic State forces of Massoud in what many analysts saw as the movement's end. By 1996, however, they had regrouped with massive military support by Pakistan and financial support by Saudi Arabia. In September 1996 they took power in Kabul and established the [[Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan]]. The [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Islamic Front]] (Northern Alliance) was created under the leadership of [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] as a military-political resistance force against the Taliban Emirate which was backed militarily by [[Pakistan Army|Pakistan's Army]] and enforced by several thousand [[Al Qaeda]] fighters from [[Arab]] countries and [[Central Asia]].
{{History of Afghanistan}}
Following the [[September 11 attacks]] inside the United States in 2001, [[2001-present war in Afghanistan|NATO invaded Afghanistan]] under [[Operation Enduring Freedom]]. The purpose of the invasion was to defeat [[Al-Qaeda]], remove the Taliban from power and create a viable democratic state.

== Rise and fall of communism ==
{{Main|Saur Revolution|Soviet war in Afghanistan|Civil war in Afghanistan (1989-1992)}}
[[Mohammed Zahir Shah|Zahir Shah]], who became the last [[List of monarchs of Afghanistan|king of Afghanistan]], was overthrown by his cousin [[Mohammed Daoud Khan]] in 1973. The nation transformed from a [[monarchy]] to a [[republic of Afghanistan|republic]], with Daoud Khan becoming the first [[president of Afghanistan]] until his assassination in a 1978 [[Military of Afghanistan|military]] [[coup d'état]] ([[Saur Revolution]]), which was organized by the [[communist party|communist]] [[People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan]] (PDPA). 

The first communist leader in Afghanistan, [[Nur Muhammad Taraki]], was assassinated by fellow communist [[Hafizullah Amin]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AFG&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/83854.stm |title=World: Analysis Afghanistan: 20 years of bloodshed |publisher=''BBC News'' | accessdate=2009-03-13 | date=1998-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amin was known for his independent and nationalist inclinations, and was also seen by many as a ruthless leader. He has been accused of killing tens of thousands of Afghan civilians at [[Pul-e-Charkhi prison|Pul-e-Charkhi]] and other national prisons. 27,000 politically motivated executions reportedly took place at [[Pul-e-Charkhi prison]] alone.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://books.google.com/books?ei=EEY4TZ2GGsXTrQfdsZmZCA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=-4oHrInacy8C&amp;dq=%27%27Soldiers+of+God%3A+With+Islamic+Warriors+in+Afghanistan+and+Pakistan%27%27&amp;q=Pul-i-Charki Soldiers of God: With Islamic Warriors in Afghanistan and Pakistan]'' by Robert D. Kaplan. Vintage, 2001. ISBN 1400030250 p.115&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Soviet Union]] looked at him as a threat for communism in Afghanistan and [[Soviet Central Asia]]. In December 1979, Amin and 200 of his guards were [[massacre]]d by teams of [[Soviet Army]]'s [[Spetsnaz]].
[[File:Evstafiev-spetsnaz-prepare-for-mission.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Soviet Army|Soviet]] [[Spetsnaz]] group prepares for a mission in 1988]]

The Soviet Union invaded Afghanistan on December 24, 1979. The [[government of the Soviet Union]] forced [[Babrak Karmal]] to leave [[Czechoslovakia]], where he lived as Ambassador from Afghanistan, to return to Kabul as the new president of his nation. Karmal's leadership was seen as a failure by the Soviet Union because of the rise of violence and crime during his administration. He was replaced with [[Mohammad Najibullah]], who was able to cling to power until 1992, three years after the withdrawal of the Soviet army.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFGH&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1569826.stm |title=Afghanistan's turbulent history |publisher=''BBC News'' | accessdate=2009-03-13 | date=2008-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Government of the Soviet Union|Soviet government]] realized that a military solution to the conflict would require far more troops. Because of this they had discussions about troop withdrawal and the search for a political peaceful solution as early as 1980, but they never took any serious steps in that direction until 1988. Early Soviet military reports confirm the difficulties the Soviet army had while fighting on the mountainous terrain, for which the Soviet army had no training whatsoever. Parallels between the [[Vietnam War]] was frequently referred to by Soviet army officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;kgb&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Svetlana Savranskaya |url=http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB57/soviet.html |title=Volume II: Afghanistan: Lessons from the Last War |publisher=''The National Security Archive'' | accessdate=2009-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The whole time during the Soviet withdrawal over the border troop convoys were coming under attack by Afghan rebel fighters. In all 523 Soviet soldiers were killed during the withdrawal. The total withdrawal of all Soviet troops from Afghanistan was completed in February 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFGHA&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/graphic/2007/07/17/GR2007071700070.html |title=How Not to End a War |publisher=''The Washington Post'' | accessdate=2009-03-13 | date=2007-07-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last Soviet soldier to leave was [[Lieutenant General]] [[Boris Gromov]], leader of the Soviet military operations in Afghanistan at the time of the Soviet invasion.&lt;ref name=&quot;last&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia/2009/02/20092158556204114.html |title=Russia marks Afghanistan retreat |publisher=''Al Jazeera'' | accessdate=2009-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Soviet withdrawal, the Republic of Afghanistan under Najibullah continued to face resistance from the various mujahideen forces. Najibullah received funding and arms from the Soviet Union until 1991 when the Soviet Empire collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFGSOV&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/14/newsid_4419000/4419833.stm |title=1988: USSR pledges to leave Afghanistan |publisher=''BBC News'' | accessdate=2009-03-15 | date=1988-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; For several years the [[Afghan army]] had actually increased their effectiveness past levels ever achieved during the Soviet military presence. But the government was dealt a major blow when [[Abdul Rashid Dostum]], a leading general, created an alliance with the [[Shura-e Nazar]] of [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]]. Large parts of the Afghan communist regime capitulated to the forces of Massoud in early 1992. After the Soviet defeat the [[The Wall Street Journal|Wall Street Journal]] had named Massoud &quot;the Afghan who won the Cold War&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Charlie Rose&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001 |url =http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=2911290068493351924# |title = Charlie Rose March 26, 2001| publisher = [[CBS]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had defeated the Soviet forces nine times in his home region of the [[Panjshir Valley]] in northeastern Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;&gt;{{cite news |year=2009 |url =http://edition.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/asiapcf/05/27/massoud.afghanistan/ |title = He would have found Bin Laden| publisher = CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Islamic State and foreign interference==
{{main|Civil war in Afghanistan (1992-1996)}}
[[File:Burhanuddin Rabbani addressing scholars-2.jpg|thumb|[[Professor]] [[Burhanuddin Rabbani]], President of the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]] from 1992 to 1996, was assassinated by a [[Taliban]] member in September 2011.]]

After the fall of Najibullah's regime in 1992, the Afghan political parties agreed on a power-sharing agreement (the [[Javed_Nasir#Enforcement_of_Peshawar_Accord|Peshawar Accords]]). The Peshawar Accords created the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]] and appointed an [[interim government]] for a transitional period to be followed by general democratic elections. According to [[Human Rights Watch]]:
{{blockquote|The sovereignty of Afghanistan was vested formally in the [[Islamic State of Afghanistan]], an entity created in April 1992, after the fall of the [[Soviet]]-backed Najibullah government. [...] With the exception of [[Gulbuddin Hekmatyar]]'s [[Hezb-e Islami]], all of the parties [...] were ostensibly unified under this government in April 1992. [...] Hekmatyar's Hezb-e Islami, for its part, refused to recognize the government for most of the period discussed in this report and launched attacks against government forces and [[Kabul]] generally. [...] Shells and rockets fell everywhere.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;}} 
Gulbuddin Hekmatyar received operational, financial and military support from [[Pakistan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Neamatollah Nojumi&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last =Neamatollah Nojumi | authorlink = | title =The Rise of the Taliban in Afghanistan: Mass Mobilization, Civil War, and the Future of the Region|edition=2002 1st |pages=| publisher = Palgrave, New York }}&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan expert [[Amin Saikal]] concludes in ''Modern Afghanistan: A History of Struggle and Survival'': 
{{blockquote|Pakistan was keen to gear up for a breakthrough in [[Central Asia]]. [...] [[Islamabad]] could not possibly expect the new Islamic government leaders [...] to subordinate their own nationalist objectives in order to help Pakistan realize its regional ambitions. [...] Had it not been for the ISI's logistic support and supply of a large number of rockets, Hekmatyar's forces would not have been able to target and destroy half of Kabul.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt;}}
In addition, [[Saudi Arabia]] and [[Iran]] - as competitors for regional [[hegemony]] - supported Afghan militias hostile towards each other.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last =Amin Saikal | authorlink = Amin Saikal| title =Modern Afghanistan: A History of Struggle and Survival|edition=2006 1st |page=352| publisher = I.B. Tauris &amp; Co Ltd., London New York | isbn=1-85043-437-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Human Rights Watch, Iran was assisting the [[Shia]] [[Hazara people|Hazara]] [[Hezb-i Wahdat]] forces of [[Abdul Ali Mazari]], as Iran was attempting to maximize Wahdat's military power and influence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date= |url =http://www.hrw.org/en/reports/2005/07/06/blood-stained-hands|title = Blood-Stained Hands, Past Atrocities in Kabul and Afghanistan's Legacy of Impunity | publisher = [[Human Rights Watch]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Roy Gutman&quot;&gt;GUTMAN, Roy (2008): How We Missed the Story: Osama Bin Laden, the Taliban and the Hijacking of Afghanistan, Endowment of the United States Institute of Peace, 1st ed., Washington D.C.&lt;/ref&gt; Saudi Arabia supported the [[Wahhabite]] [[Abdul Rasul Sayyaf]] and his [[Ittihad-i Islami]] faction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt; Conflict between the two militias soon escalated into a full-scale war. A publication by the [[George Washington University]] describes: 
{{blockquote|[O]utside forces saw instability in Afghanistan as an opportunity to press their own security and political agendas.&lt;ref name=&quot;The National Security Archive&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2003|url =http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB97/ |title =The September 11 Sourcebooks Volume VII: The Taliban File| publisher = [[gwu.edu]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}  
[[File:Abdul Rashid Dostum VOA Jan 22 2002 retouched.jpg|left|thumb|[[Abdul Rashid Dostum]], leader of [[National Islamic Movement of Afghanistan|Junbish-i-Milli Islami Afghanistan]]]]
Due to the sudden initiation of the war, working government departments, police units or a system of justice and accountability for the newly-created Islamic State of Afghanistan did not have time to form. Atrocities were committed by individuals of the different armed factions while Kabul descended into lawlessness and chaos as described in reports by Human Rights Watch and the Afghanistan Justice Project.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Afghanistan Justice Project&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2005|url=http://www.afghanistanjusticeproject.org/warcrimesandcrimesagainsthumanity19782001.pdf |title =Casting Shadows: War Crimes and Crimes against Humanity: 1978-2001 | publisher = Afghanistan Justice Project}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the chaos, some leaders increasingly had only nominal control over their (sub-)commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=|url=http://www.hrw.org/reports98/afghan/Afrepor0-01.htm#P81_13959|title =II. BACKGROUND | publisher = Human Rights Watch}}&lt;/ref&gt; For civilians there was little security from murder, rape and extortion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;/&gt; An estimated 25,000 people died during the most intense period of bombardment by Hekmatyar's Hezb-i Islami and the [[Junbish-i Milli]] forces of [[Abdul Rashid Dostum]], who had created an alliance with Hekmatyar in 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;Afghanistan Justice Project&quot;/&gt; Half a million people fled Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;/&gt; Human Rights Watch writes: 
{{blockquote|Rare ceasefires, usually negotiated by representatives of [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]], [[Sibghatullah Mojaddedi]] or [[Burhanuddin Rabbani]] [the interim government], or officials from the [[International Committee of the Red Cross]] (ICRC), commonly collapsed within days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (4)&quot;/&gt;}} 

Southern Afghanistan was under the control of neither foreign-backed militias nor the government in Kabul, but was ruled by local leaders such as [[Gul Agha Sherzai]] and their militias. In 1994, the [[Taliban]] (a movement originating from [[Jamiat Ulema-e-Islam]]-run religious schools for Afghan refugees in Pakistan) also developed in Afghanistan as a politico-religious force, reportedly in opposition to the [[tyranny]] of the local governor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matinuddin, Kamal 1999 pp.25&quot;&gt;Matinuddin, Kamal, ''The Taliban Phenomenon, Afghanistan 1994–1997'', [[Oxford University Press]], (1999), pp.25–6&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mohammed Omar|Mullah Omar]] started his movement with fewer than 50 armed [[madrassah]] students in his hometown of Kandahar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Matinuddin, Kamal 1999 pp.25&quot;/&gt; When the Taliban took control of the city in 1994, they forced the surrender of dozens of local Pashtun leaders who had presided over a situation of complete lawlessness and atrocities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;/&gt; In 1994, the Taliban took power in several provinces in southern and central Afghanistan.
[[File:Kabul during civial war of fundamentalists 1993.jpg|thumb|300px|A totally destroyed section of Kabul in 1993.]]

In late 1994, most of the militia factions (Hezb-i Islami, Junbish-i Milli and Hezb-i Wahdat) which had been fighting in the battle for control of Kabul were defeated militarily by forces of the Islamic State's [[Secretary of Defense]] [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]]. Bombardment of the capital came to a halt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Afghanistan Justice Project&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;&gt;Amnesty International. &quot;DOCUMENT - AFGHANISTAN: FURTHER INFORMATION ON FEAR FOR SAFETY AND NEW CONCERN: DELIBERATE AND ARBITRARY KILLINGS: CIVILIANS IN KABUL.&quot; 16 November 1995 Accessed at: http://www.amnesty.org/en/library/asset/ASA11/015/1995/en/6d874caa-eb2a-11dd-92ac-295bdf97101f/asa110151995en.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;International Committee of the Red Cross&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1995|url=http://www.icrc.org/eng/resources/documents/misc/57jly2.htm |title =Afghanistan: escalation of indiscriminate shelling in Kabul| publisher =International Committee of the Red Cross}}&lt;/ref&gt; Massoud tried to initiate a nationwide [[political process]] with the goal of national [[Democratic consolidation|consolidation]] and [[democratic]] elections, also inviting the [[Taliban]] to join the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Marcela Grad| authorlink = | title = Massoud: An Intimate Portrait of the Legendary Afghan Leader|edition=March 1, 2009 |pages=310  | publisher =  Webster University Press| isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Massoud had united political and cultural personalities, governors, commanders, clergymen and representatives to reach a lasting agreement. Massoud, like most people in Afghanistan, saw this conference as a small hope for democracy and for free elections. His favourite for candidacy to the presidency was Dr. [[Mohammad Yusuf (prime minister)|Mohammad Yusuf]], the first democratic prime minister under [[Zahir Shah]], the former king. In the first meeting representatives from 15 different Afghan provinces met, in the second meeting there were already 25 provinces participating.  Massoud unarmed went to talk to some Taliban leaders in Maidan Shar, but the Taliban declined to join this political process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; When Massoud returned unharmed the Taliban leader who had received him as his guest paid with his life: he was killed by other senior Taliban for failing to execute Massoud while the possibility was there.

The Taliban started shelling Kabul in early 1995 but were defeated by forces of the Islamic State government under [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]].&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt; [[Amnesty International]], referring to the Taliban offensive, wrote in a 1995 report:
{{blockquote|This is the first time in several months that Kabul civilians have become the targets of rocket attacks and shelling aimed at residential areas in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;amnesty.org&quot;/&gt;}}
The Taliban's early victories in 1994 were followed by a series of defeats that resulted in heavy losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch (5)&quot;/&gt; [[Pakistan]] provided strong support to the Taliban.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2007 |url =http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB227/index.htm#17 |title =Documents Detail Years of Pakistani Support for Taliban, Extremists | publisher = [[George Washington University]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many analysts like [[Amin Saikal]] describe the Taliban as developing into a [[proxy]] force for Pakistan's regional interests which the Taliban decline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Amin Saikal&quot;/&gt; 
On September 26, 1996, as the Taliban with military support by Pakistan and financial support by Saudi Arabia prepared for another major offensive, Massoud ordered a full retreat from Kabul.&lt;ref&gt;Coll, ''Ghost Wars'' (New York: Penguin, 2005), 14.&lt;/ref&gt; The Taliban seized Kabul on September 27, 1996, and established the [[Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan]].

==Taliban Emirate against United Front==
{{main|Civil war in Afghanistan (1996-2001)|United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|Taliban}}
[[File:1996afghan (1).png|thumb|Map of the situation in Afghanistan in 1996;Ahmad Shah Massoud (red), Abdul Rashid Dostum (green) and Taliban (yellow) territories]]

[[File:Pervez Musharraf - World Economic Forum Annual Meeting Davos 2008 number3.jpg|thumb|Former Pakistani President [[Pervez Musharraf]] sent more troops against the United Front of [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] than the Afghan Taliban]]

The Taliban imposed on the parts of Afghanistan under their control their interpretation of [[Islam]]. The [[Physicians for Human Rights]] (PHR) analyze: 
{{quote|To PHR’s knowledge, no other regime in the world has methodically and violently forced half of its population into virtual [[house arrest]], prohibiting them on pain of physical punishment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=1998 |url = http://physiciansforhumanrights.org/library/documents/reports/talibans-war-on-women.pdf |title = The Taliban's War on Women. A Health and Human Rights Crisis in Afghanistan| publisher = [[Physicians for Human Rights]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Women were required to wear the all-covering ''[[chador]]'', they were banned from public life and denied access to health care and education, windows needed to be covered so that women could not be seen from the outside, and they were not allowed to laugh in a manner they could be heard by others.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt; The Taliban, without any real court or hearing, cut people's hands or arms off when they were accused of stealing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt; Taliban hit-squads watched the streets, conducting arbitrary brutal public beatings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Physicians for Human Rights&quot;/&gt;

[[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] and [[Abdul Rashid Dostum]], two former archnemesis, created the [[United Islamic Front for the Salvation of Afghanistan|United Front]] (Northern Alliance) against the Taliban that were preparing offensives against the remaining areas under the control of Massoud and those under the control of Dostum. [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EvYglyjbHkI see video] The United Front included beside the dominantly [[Tajik people|Tajik]] forces of Massoud and the [[Uzbeks|Uzbek]] forces of Dostum, [[Hazara people|Hazara]] factions and [[Pashtun people|Pashtun]] forces under the leadership of commanders such as [[Abdul Haq (Afghan leader)|Abdul Haq]], [[Haji Abdul Qadir]], Qari Baba or diplomat [[Abdul Rahim Ghafoorzai]]. From the Taliban conquest in 1996 until November 2001 the United Front controlled roughly 30% of Afghanistan's population in provinces such as [[Badakhshan Province|Badakhshan]], [[Kapisa Province|Kapisa]], [[Takhar Province|Takhar]] and parts of [[Parwan Province|Parwan]], [[Kunar Province|Kunar]], [[Nuristan Province|Nuristan]], [[Laghman Province|Laghman]], [[Samangan Province|Samangan]], [[Kunduz Province|Kunduz]], [[Ghōr Province|Ghōr]] and [[Bamyan Province|Bamyan]]. 
[[File:Taliban-herat-2001 ArM.jpg|thumb|Taliban in Herat in July 2001]]
According to a 55-page report by the [[United Nations]], the Taliban, while trying to consolidate control over northern and western Afghanistan, committed systematic massacres against civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2001-10-12/news/0110120312_1_taliban-fighters-massacres-in-recent-years-mullah-mohammed-omar|title=Taliban massacres outlined for UN |accessdate=|author= Newsday|authorlink= |year=2001|month=October |work=|publisher= Chicago Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.papillonsartpalace.com/massacre.htm|title=Confidential UN report details mass killings of civilian villagers |accessdate=October 12, 2001|author= Newsday|authorlink= |year=2001|month= |work=|publisher= newsday.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; UN officials stated that there had been &quot;15 massacres&quot; between 1996 and 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; They also said, that &quot;[t]hese have been highly systematic and they all lead back to the [Taliban] Ministry of Defense or to [[Mohammed Omar|Mullah Omar]] himself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; In a major effort to retake the Shomali plains, the Taliban indiscriminately killed civilians, while uprooting and expelling the population. Kamal Hossein, a special reporter for the [[UN]], reported on these and other [[war crimes]]. Upon taking Mazar-i-Sharif in 1998, about 4,000 [[civilian]]s were executed by the Taliban and many more reported [[torture]]d.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unhcr.org/refworld/country,,IRBC,,AFG,,3ae6aab050,0.html |title=Afghanistan: Situation in, or around, Aqcha (Jawzjan province) including predominant tribal/ethnic group and who is currently in control|accessdate=|author= [[UNHCR]]|authorlink= [[UNHCR]]|year= 1999|month= February|work= |publisher= [[UNHCR]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hrw.org/reports98/afghan/Afrepor0-03.htm#P186_38364 |title=INCITEMENT OF VIOLENCE AGAINST HAZARAS BY GOVERNOR NIAZI |accessdate=December 27, 2007 |author= Human Rights Watch|authorlink= Human Rights Watch|year= 1998|month= November|work=AFGHANISTAN: THE MASSACRE IN MAZAR-I SHARIF |publisher= hrw.org}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Taliban especially targeted people of Shia religious or Hazara ethnic background.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; Among those killed in Mazari Sharif [[1998 Iranian diplomats assassination in Afghanistan|were several Iranian diplomats]]. Others were kidnapped by the Taliban, touching off a hostage crisis that nearly escalated to a full scale war, with 150,000 Iranian soldiers massed on the Afghan border at one time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Iranian military exercises draw warning from Afghanistan|date=1997-08-31|publisher=CNN News|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9808/31/iran.games/}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was later admitted that the diplomats were killed by the Taliban, and their bodies were returned to Iran.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Taliban threatens retaliation if Iran strikes|date=1997-09-15|publisher=CNN News|url=http://www.cnn.com/WORLD/meast/9809/15/iran.afghan.tensions.02/index.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The documents also reveal the role of Arab and Pakistani support troops in these killings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; Bin Laden's so-called [[055 Brigade]] was responsible for mass-killings of Afghan civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report by the [[United Nations]] quotes eyewitnesses in many villages describing Arab fighters carrying long knives used for slitting throats and skinning people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Newsday 2001&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;papillonsartpalace.com&quot;/&gt; 

Pakistani President [[Pervez Musharraf]] - then as Chief of Army Staff - was responsible for sending thousands of Pakistanis to fight alongside the Taliban and Bin Laden against the forces of Massoud.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;History Commons&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2010 |url =http://www.historycommons.org/entity.jsp?entity=ahmed_shah_massoud |title = History Commons| publisher = [[History Commons]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In total there were believed to be 28,000 Pakistani nationals fighting inside Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; 20,000 were regular Pakistani soldiers either from the [[Frontier Corps]] or army and an estimated 8,000 were militants recruited in [[madrassa]]s filling regular Taliban ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; The estimated 25,000 Taliban regular force thus comprised more than 8,000 Pakistani nationals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Rashid|2000|p=91}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A 1998 document by the [[U.S. State Department]] confirms that &quot;20-40 percent of [regular] Taliban soldiers are Pakistani.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt; The document further states that the parents of those Pakistani nationals &quot;know nothing regarding their child's military involvement with the Taliban until their bodies are brought back to Pakistan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington University&quot;/&gt; Further 3,000 fighters of the regular Taliban army were Arab and Central Asian militants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 1996 to 2001 the [[Al Qaeda]] of [[Osama Bin Laden]] and [[Ayman al-Zawahiri]] became a state within the Taliban state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily Times&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2008|url =http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=2008\08\31\story_31-8-2008_pg3_4 |title = BOOK REVIEW: The inside track on Afghan wars by Khaled Ahmed| publisher = [[Daily Times (Pakistan)|Daily Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bin Laden sent Arab recruits to join the fight against the United Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN&quot;&gt;{{cite web|date=unknown|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Grugy2txSvc&amp;feature=search |title = Brigade 055| publisher = CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily Times&quot;/&gt; Of roughly 45,000 Pakistani, Taliban and Al Qaeda soldiers fighting against the forces of Massoud only 14,000 were Afghan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahmed Rashid/The Telegraph&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2001|url =http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/1340244/Afghanistan-resistance-leader-feared-dead-in-blast.html |title =Afghanistan resistance leader feared dead in blast| publisher = Ahmed Rashid in the Telegraph}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Abdul Rashid Dostum]] and his forces were defeated by the Taliban in 1998. Dostum subsequently went into exile. 

The only leader to remain in Afghanistan, and who was able to defend vast parts of his area against the Taliban, was [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]]. In the areas under his control [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]] set up democratic institutions and signed the [[Women's Rights]] Declaration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| last = Marcela Grad| authorlink = Marcela Grad| title = Massoud: An Intimate Portrait of the Legendary Afghan Leader|edition=March 1, 2009 |page=310  | publisher =  Webster University Press| isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the area of Massoud, women and girls did not have to wear the Afghan burqa. They were allowed to work and to go to school. In at least two known instances, Massoud personally intervened against cases of forced marriage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; To Massoud there was reportedly nothing worse than treating a person like an object.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; He stated: 
{{quote|It is our conviction and we believe that both men and women are created by the Almighty. Both have equal rights. Women can pursue an education, women can pursue a career, and women can play a role in society — just like men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;}}

Author Pepe Escobar wrote in ''Massoud: From Warrior to Statesman'': 
{{quote|Massoud is adamant that in Afghanistan women have suffered oppression for generations. He says that 'the cultural environment of the country suffocates women. But the Taliban exacerbate this with oppression.' His most ambitious project is to shatter this cultural prejudice and so give more space, freedom and equality to women — they would have the same rights as men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;}}

While it was Massoud's stated conviction that men and women are equal and should enjoy the same rights, he also had to deal with Afghan traditions which he said would need a generation or more to overcome. In his opinion that could only be achieved through education.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; Humayun Tandar, who took part as a Afghan diplomat in the 2001 [[International Conference on Afghanistan]] in Bonn, said that &quot;strictures of language, ethnicity, region were [also] stifling for Massoud. That is why ... he wanted to create a unity which could surpass the situation in which we found ourselves and still find ourselves to this day.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt; This applied also to strictures of religion. Jean-José Puig describes how Massoud often led prayers before a meal or at times asked his fellow Muslims to lead the prayer but also did not hesitate to ask a Christian friend Jean-José Puig or the Jewish [[Princeton University|Princeton]] Professor Michael Barry: &quot;Jean-José, we believe in the same God. Please, tell us the prayer before lunch or dinner in your own language.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot;/&gt;

Human Rights Watch cites no human rights crimes for the forces under direct control of Massoud for the period from October 1996 until the assassination of Massoud in September 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Human Rights Watch&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/asia/afghan-bck1005.htm#uf |title = Human Rights Watch Backgrounder, October 2001| publisher = [[Human Rights Watch]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; One million peolple fled the Taliban, many to the area of Massoud.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|year=2007|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xpQI6HKV-ZY&amp;feature=related |title = Inside the Taliban| publisher = [[National Geographic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|year=2007 |url =http://channel.nationalgeographic.com/episode/inside-the-taliban-3274/Overview|title =Inside the Taliban | publisher = [[National Geographic]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[National Geographic]] concluded in its documentary ''&quot;Inside the Taliban&quot;'':
{{quote|The only thing standing in the way of future Taliban massacres is [[Ahmad Shah Massoud]].&lt;ref name=&quot;National Geographic&quot;/&gt;}}

The Taliban repeatedly offered Massoud a position of power to make him stop his resistance. Massoud declined. He explained in one interview: 
{{quote|The Taliban say: “Come and accept the post of prime minister and be with us”, and they would keep the highest office in the country, the presidentship. But for what price?! The difference between us concerns mainly our way of thinking about the very principles of the society and the state. We can not accept their conditions of compromise, or else we would have to give up the principles of modern democracy. We are fundamentally against the system called “the Emirate of Afghanistan”.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.orient.uw.edu.pl/balcerowicz/texts/Ahmad_Shah_Masood_en.htm |title =The Last Interview with Ahmad Shah Massoud | publisher = Piotr Balcerowicz}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

And in another:
{{quote|There should be an Afghanistan where every Afghan finds himself or herself happy. And I think that can only be assured by democracy based on consensus.&lt;ref name=&quot;St. Petersburg Times&quot; /&gt;}}

Massoud with his [http://www.peace-initiatives.com/frame.htm Proposals for Peace] wanted to convince the Taliban to join a political process leading towards nationwide democratic elections in a foreseeable future.&lt;ref name=&quot;Interview&quot;/&gt;  Massoud also stated:

{{quote|The Taliban are not a force to be considered invincible. They are distanced from the people now. They are weaker than in the past. There is only the assistance given by Pakistan, Osama bin Laden and other extremist groups that keep the Taliban on their feet. With a halt to that assistance, it is extremely difficult to survive.&lt;ref name=&quot;St. Petersburg Times&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2002|url =http://www.sptimes.com/2002/09/09/911/The_man_who_would_hav.shtml |title =The man who would have led Afghanistan| publisher = [[St. Petersburg Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In early 2001 Massoud employed a new strategy of local military pressure and global political appeals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steve Coll: Ghost Wars&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last = Steve Coll| authorlink = Steve Coll| title =Ghost Wars: The Secret History of the CIA, Afghanistan, and Bin Laden, from the Soviet Invasion to September 10, 2001 |edition=February 23, 2004 |page=720| publisher =Penguin Press HC | isbn= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Resentment was increasingly gathering against Taliban rule from the bottom of Afghan society including the Pashtun areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steve Coll: Ghost Wars&quot; /&gt; Massoud publicized their cause &quot;popular consensus, general elections and democracy&quot; worldwide. At the same time he was very wary not to revive the failed Kabul government of the early 1990s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steve Coll: Ghost Wars&quot; /&gt; Already in 1999 he started the training of police forces which he trained specifically in order to keep order and protect the civilian population in case the United Front would be successful.&lt;ref name=&quot;Webster University Press Book&quot; /&gt;

In early 2001 Ahmad Shah Massoud addressed the [[European Parliament]] in [[Brussels]] asking the [[international community]] to provide [[humanitarian]] help to the people of Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;EU Parliament (2)&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60 |title = Massoud in the European Parliament 2001| publisher = EU media}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60&amp;t=4m34s see video]) He stated that the Taliban and [[Al Qaeda]] had introduced &quot;a very wrong perception of [[Islam]]&quot; and that without the support of Pakistan and Bin Laden the Taliban would not be able to sustain their military campaign for up to a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;EU Parliament&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2001|url =http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60&amp;t=4m34s |title = Massoud in the European Parliament 2001| publisher =EU media}}&lt;/ref&gt; On this visit to Europe he also warned that his intelligence had gathered information about a large-scale attack on U.S. soil being imminent.&lt;ref name=&quot;gwu.edu&quot;&gt;Defense Intelligence Agency (2001) report http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB97/tal32.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
The president of the European Parliament, [[Nicole Fontaine]], called him the &quot;pole of liberty in Afghanistan&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=&amp;ldquo;&amp;rdquo; |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t78N6Q5VD60&amp;t=4m34s |title=see video |publisher=Youtube.com |date=March 5, 2001 |accessdate=October 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 9, 2001, Massoud, then aged 48, was the target of a [[suicide attack]] by two Arabs posing as journalists at Khwaja Bahauddin, in the [[Takhar Province]] of Afghanistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/10/world/taliban-foe-hurt-and-aide-killed-by-bomb.html |title=Taliban Foe Hurt and Aide Killed by Bomb |location=Afghanistan |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=September 10, 2001 |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Burns |first=John F. |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/09/world/threats-responses-assassination-afghans-too-mark-day-disaster-hero-was-lost.html |title=THREATS AND RESPONSES: ASSASSINATION; Afghans, Too, Mark a Day of Disaster: A Hero Was Lost |location=Afghanistan |publisher=Nytimes.com |date=September 9, 2002 |accessdate=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Massoud died in a helicopter taking him to a hospital. The funeral, though in a rather rural area, was attended by hundreds of thousands of mourning people.[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Aq-zqA1DMWs Sad day] (video clip).

The assassination was not the first time Al-Qaeda, the Taliban, the Pakistani [[Inter-Services Intelligence|ISI]], and before them the Soviet [[KGB]], the Afghan Communist [[KHAD]] and [[Hekmatyar]] had tried to assassinate Massoud. He survived countless assassination attempts over a period of 26 years. The first attempt on Massoud's life was carried out by Hekmatyar and two Pakistani ISI agents in 1975, when Massoud was only 22 years old.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roy Gutman&quot;/&gt; In early 2001, Al-Qaeda would-be assassins were captured by Massoud's forces while trying to enter his territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Steve Coll: Ghost Wars&quot; /&gt; The assassination of Massoud is considered to have a strong connection to the [[September 11, 2001 attacks]] on U.S. soil, which killed nearly 3000 people, and which appeared to be the terrorist attack that Massoud had warned against in his speech to the European Parliament several months earlier.

[[John P. O'Neill]] was a counter-terrorism expert and the Assistant Director of the [[FBI]] until late 2001. He retired from the FBI and was offered the position of director of security at the [[World Trade Center]] (WTC). He took the job at the WTC two weeks before 9/11. On September 10, 2001, O’Neill told two of his friends, &quot;We're due. And we're due for something big.... Some things have happened in Afghanistan. [referring to the assassination of Massoud] I don’t like the way things are lining up in Afghanistan.... I sense a shift, and I think things are going to happen ... soon.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot;&gt;{{cite web |year=2002 |url =http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/knew/etc/script.html|title =The Man Who Knew | publisher = [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  O'Neill died on September 11, 2001, when the [[South Tower]] collapsed.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBS&quot; /&gt;

After the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001, Massoud's United Front troops ousted the Taliban from power in Kabul with American air support in [[Operation Enduring Freedom]]. In November and December 2001 the United Front gained control of much of the country and played a crucial role in establishing the post-Taliban interim government of Hamid Karzai in late 2001.

==Islamic Republic and NATO==
{{Main|Presidency of Hamid Karzai|War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|Taliban insurgency}}
[[File:GW Bush and Hamid Karzai in Kabul 2006-03-01.jpg|thumb|Former U.S. President [[George W. Bush]] and [[Hamid Karzai]] at the Presidential Palace in [[Kabul]], Afghanistan.]]
[[File:Afghan soldiers.jpg|thumb|Soldiers of the [[Afghan National Army]], including the [[ANA Commando Brigade]] standing in the front.]]

The [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|US-led war in Afghanistan]] began on October 7, 2001, as [[Operation Enduring Freedom]]. It was designed to capture or kill [[Osama bin Laden]] and [[al-Qaeda]] militants as well as replace the Taliban with a US-friendly government. The [[Bush Doctrine]] stated that, [[Foreign policy of the George W. Bush administration|as policy]], it would not distinguish between al-Qaeda and nations that harbor them. 

Several Afghan leaders were invited to [[Germany]] in December 2001 for the UN sponsored [[Bonn Agreement (Afghanistan)|Bonn Agreement]], which was to restore stability and governance in their country. In the first step, the [[Afghan Transitional Administration]] was formed and was installed on December 22, 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;UNations&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.unama-afg.org/news/_parelection/_factsheets/_english/JEMBS%20PO%20BG%20General%20BG%20final%202005-4-1%20eng.pdf |title=UN factsheet on Bonn Agreement |publisher=''United Nations'' | accessdate=2009-03-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Chaired by [[Hamid Karzai]], it numbered 30 leaders and included a [[Supreme Court of Afghanistan|Supreme Court]], an Interim Administration, and a Special Independent Commission.

A [[loya jirga]] (grand assembly) was convened in June 2002 by former King [[Zahir Shah]], who returned from exile after 29 years. Hamid Karzai was elected President for the two years in the jirga, in which the Afghan Interim Authority was also replaced with the Transitional Islamic State of Afghanistan (TISA). A constitutional loya jirga was held in December 2003, adopting the new [[Constitution of Afghanistan|2004 constitution]], with a presidential form of government and a bicameral legislature.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCNews&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/4540756.stm |title=Afghan MPs hold landmark session |publisher=''BBC News'' | accessdate=2009-03-15 | date=2005-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Karzai was elected in the [[Afghan presidential election, 2004|2004 presidential election]] followed by winning a second term in the [[Afghan presidential election, 2009|2009 presidential election]]. Both the  [[Afghan parliamentary election, 2005|2005]] and the [[Afghan parliamentary election, 2010|2010 parliamentary election]]s were also successful.

In the meantime, the reconstruction process of Afghanistan began in 2002. There are more than 14,000 reconstruction projects under way in Afghanistan, such as the [[Kajaki Dam|Kajaki]] and the [[Salma Dam]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/featuresarticle/2007/03/642FF16A-41C2-4AF2-B314-1D7BAEDDFAE6.html Radio Free Europe] - Afghanistan: NATO Pleased With Offensive, But Goals Still Unmet&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these projects are being supervised by the [[Provincial Reconstruction Team]]s. The World Bank contribution is the multilateral Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund (ARTF), which was set up in 2002. It is financed by 24 international donor countries and has spent more than $1.37 billion as of 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFGReco&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/COUNTRIES/SOUTHASIAEXT/AFGHANISTANEXTN/0,,contentMDK:20152008~pagePK:141137~piPK:217854~theSitePK:305985,00.html |title=Afghanistan Reconstruction Trust Fund |publisher=''World Bank'' | accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 30 billion dollars have been provided by the international community for the reconstruction of Afghanistan, most of it from the United States. In 2002, the world community allocated $4 billion at the Tokyo conference followed by another $4 billion in 2004. In February 2006, $10.5 billion were committed for Afghanistan at the [[International Conference on Afghanistan (2006)|London Conference]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AFGR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irinnews.org/report.asp?ReportID=51510&amp;SelectRegion=Asia&amp;SelectCountry=AFGHANISTAN |title=Government to have greater control over aid pledged in London |publisher=''IRIN Asia'' | accessdate=2009-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; and $11 billion from the United States in early 2007.

The [[UN Security Council]] established the [[International Security Assistance Force]] (ISAF) in December 2001 to provide basic security for the people of Afghanistan and assist the [[Karzai administration]]. Since 2002, the total number of ISAF and U.S. forces have climbed from 15,000 to 150,000. The majority of them belong to various branches of the [[United States armed forces]], who are not only fighting the [[Taliban insurgency]] but also training the [[military of Afghanistan]] and the [[Afghan National Police]]. They are scheduled to withraw slowly until the end of 2014 but [[Vice President of the United States|Vice President]] [[Joe Biden]] has proposed to remain an unknown number of U.S. [[military personnel]]s after the 2014 deadline if the security situation required and the Afghan government and people desired.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20110111/wl_sthasia_afp/afghanistanunrestusbiden_20110111142049 Biden says US may stay in Afghanistan after 2014]&lt;/ref&gt; Germany has announced to keep teaching Afghan police recruits until after the 2014 withdrawal date for military troops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,,5933456,00.html Berlin to train Afghan police even after security handover ]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US Navy 100628-N-0475R-287 Seabees, Marines, Soldiers and members of the Afghan National Army take a tour of an area surrounding a newly completed Mabey-Johnson Bridge project.jpg|left|thumb|U.S. and Afghan troops prepare for a mission in 2010.]]
NATO and [[Afghan National Army|Afghan troops]] in recent years led many offensives against the Taliban, but proved unable to completely dislodge their presence. By 2009, a Taliban-led shadow government began to form complete with their own version of mediation court.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/12/07/AR2009120704127.html | work=The Washington Post | accessdate=2010-03-30 | title=Taliban shadow officials offer concrete alternative | first=Griff | last=Witte | date=2009-12-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, [[U.S. President]] [[Barack Obama]] deployed an additional 30,000 soldiers over a period of six months and proposed that he will begin troop withdrawals by 2012. At the [[International Conference on Afghanistan (2010)|2010 International Conference on Afghanistan]] in [[London]], [[President of Afghanistan|Afghan President]] [[Hamid Karzai]] said he intends to reach out to the Taliban leadership (including [[Mohammed Omar|Mullah Omar]], [[Sirajuddin Haqqani]] and [[Gulbuddin Hekmatyar]]). Supported by senior U.S. officials Karzai called on the group's leadership to take part in a [[loya jirga]] meeting to initiate peace talks. According to the Wall Street Journal, these steps have been reciprocated so far with an intensification of bombings, assassinations and ambushes.&lt;ref name=&quot;online.wsj.com&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703720004575476913015061570.html| work=The &quot;Wall Street Journal&quot;| accessdate=2010-09-11 | title=Karzai Divides Afghanistan in Reaching Out to Taliban | first=| last=| date=2010-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many Afghan groups (including the former intelligence chief [[Amrullah Saleh]] and opposition leader Dr. [[Abdullah Abdullah]]) believe that Karzai's plan aims to appease the insurgents' senior leadership at the cost of the democratic constitution, the democratic process and progess in the field of human rights especially women's rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Scotsman&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://news.scotsman.com/world/Karzai39s-Taleban-talks-raise-spectre.6557817.jp| work=The Scotsman| accessdate= | title=Karzai's Taleban talks raise spectre of civil war warns former spy chief | first=| last=| date=2010-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dr. Abdullah stated:
{{quote|I should say that Taliban are not fighting in order to be accommodated. They are fighting in order to bring the state down. So it's a futile exercise, and it's just misleading. ... There are groups that will fight to the death. Whether we like to talk to them or we don't like to talk to them, they will continue to fight. So, for them, I don't think that we have a way forward with talks or negotiations or contacts or anything as such. Then we have to be prepared to tackle and deal with them militarily. In terms of the Taliban on the ground, there are lots of possibilities and opportunities that with the help of the people in different parts of the country, we can attract them to the peace process; provided, we create a favorable environment on this side of the line. At the moment, the people are leaving support for the government because of corruption. So that expectation is also not realistic at this stage.&lt;ref name=&quot;National Public Radio (NPR)&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=130757482| work=National Public Radio (NPR)| accessdate= | title=Abdullah Abdullah: Talks With Taliban Futile | first=| last=| date=2010-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

According to a report by the United Nations, the Taliban were responsible for 76 % of civilian casualties in 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Weekly Standard&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.weeklystandard.com/blogs/taliban-responsible-76-deaths-afghanistan-un| work=The Weekly Standard| accessdate= | title=UN: Taliban Responsible for 76% of Deaths in Afghanistan | first=| last=| date=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Afghanistan is currently struggling to rebuild itself while dealing with the results of 30 years of war, corruption among high level politicians and the ongoing [[Taliban insurgency]] backed by Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://abcnews.go.com/Video/video?id=5484891&amp;tab=9482931&amp;section=8865284&amp;page=1| publisher=[[ABC News]]| accessdate=2010-09-28 | title=Pakistan Accused of Helping Taliban | first=| last=| date=2008-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/asia/afghanistan/7910687/Wikileaks-Pakistan-accused-of-helping-Taliban-in-Afghanistan-attacks.html| publisher=U.K. Telegraph| accessdate=2010-09-28 | title=Wikileaks: Pakistan accused of helping Taliban in Afghanistan attacks | first=| last=| date=26 Jul 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By end of July 2011, the Netherlands became the first NATO country to end its combat mission in Afghanistan after 4 years deployed. 1,900 Dutch troops is not much, but it is politically significant due to rising casualties and growing doubt about the war. Canada withdrew its troops in 2011 and Poland will pull out 2,600 soldiers in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.acus.org/natosource/dutch-become-1st-nato-member-quit-afghanistan&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.afghanconflictmonitor.org Afghanistan Conflict Monitor]
*[http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/asia/afghan-bck1023.htm Backgrounder on Afghanistan: History of the War October 2001]
*[http://www.rand.org/pubs/testimonies/2007/RAND_CT271.pdf Ending Afghanistan’s Civil by James Dobbins, The RAND Corporation, Testimony presented before the House Armed Services Committee on January 30, 2007]
*[http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/asia/afghanistan/afghbk.htm Fueling Afghanistan's War-Press Backgrounder]
*[http://www.csis.org/isp/pcr/ More information on Post-Conflict Reconstruction from the Center for Strategic and International Studies]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Civil War In Afghanistan}}
[[Category:Afghan Civil War|*]]
[[Category:Cold War military history of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Cold War rebellions]]
[[Category:Warlordism]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Taliban]]

[[de:Krieg in Afghanistan]]
[[es:Guerra Civil Afgana]]
[[hi:अफ़ग़ानिस्तान का गृहयुद्ध]]
[[id:Perang Saudara Afganistan]]
[[lv:Afganistānas pilsoņu karš]]
[[ja:アフガニスタン紛争]]
[[pt:Guerra Civil do Afeganistão]]
[[ru:Гражданская война в Афганистане]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
