<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27588536" ns="0" title="Far Eastern University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup|date=May 2011}}
{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox university
|name             = Far Eastern University
|native_name      = Pamantasan ng Malayong Silanganan
|image            = [[Image:FEUSealNew.png|150px]]
|motto            = ''Love of Fatherland and God''
|established      = 1928
|type             = [[Private school|Private]], non-sectarian
|president        = [[Lydia B. Echauz]], DBA
|city             = [[Manila]]
|country          = [[Philippines]]
|undergrad        = 23,928&lt;ref name=&quot;PR2008&quot;&gt;http://investors.feu.edu.ph/PR2008.PDF&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad         = 3,961&lt;ref name=&quot;PR2008&quot;/&gt;
|postgrad_label   = Graduate
|staff=
|campus           = 40,000 m²
|free_label     = Hymn
|free           = &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8vHzCDuaScI The FEU Hymn]&quot; by [[Nick Joaquin]]
|mascot           = [[FEU Tamaraws]]
|colors           =  [[Image:FEU colors.svg|15px]] Green and gold
|website= [http://www.feu.edu.ph/ www.feu.edu.ph]
|affiliations = [[Association of Southeast Asian Institutions of Higher Learning|ASAIHL]], PACU,PACUOCA, [[PAASCU]], [[UAAP]] }}

'''Far Eastern University (FEU)''' ({{pse|FEU}}) in the [[University Belt]] area, West Sampaloc, City of [[Manila]], is a nonsectarian, [[private university]] in the [[Philippines]]. Created by the merger of Far Eastern College and the Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance, FEU became a university in 1934 under the guidance of first president [[Nicanor Reyes, Sr.]] It soon became the leading proprietary university in the Philippines.&lt;ref name=Ruegg&gt;{{cite book | title= Universities in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries (1800-1945) | volume = 3 | series= A history of the university in Europe | first = Walter | last = Rüegg | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 2004 | isbn = 052136107 | page = 213}}&lt;/ref&gt; FEU's campus is noted for a number of historical buildings preserved from the first half of the 20th century.

==History==
{| style=&quot;float:left; margin:1em 1em 1em 1em; width:16em; border: 1px solid #a0a0a0; padding: 3px; bg-color=yellow; text-align:right;&quot;
|- style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;006600&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
|&lt;font color=&quot;gold&quot;&gt;'''Presidents of&lt;br/&gt; Far Eastern University'''&lt;/font&gt;
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Nicanor I. Reyes Sr., 1934-1942'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Hermenigildo B. Reyes, 1945-1946'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Clemente Q. Uson, 1946-1949'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Vidal A. Tan, 1949-1952'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Teodoro T. Evangelista, 1952-1970'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Nicanor M. Reyes Jr., 1970-1985'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Josephine Cojuangco-Reyes, 1985-1989'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''[[Felixberto C. Sta. Maria, 1989-1995]]'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''Edilberto C. de Jesus, 1995-2002'''
|- style=&quot;text-align:left; font-size:x-small;&quot;
|'''[[Lydia B. Echauz]], 2002–present'''
|}

Far Eastern University was founded in 1934 when the Far Eastern College and the Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance (IABF) merged.&lt;ref name=Ruegg/&gt;&lt;ref name=Public&gt;{{cite book | title = Elements of Public Speaking | edition = 4th | year = 1986 | editor1-last= Gupit, Jr. | editor1-first = Dr. Fortunato | publisher = [[Rex Bookstore]] | isbn = 9712304159 | page= 340}}&lt;/ref&gt; Far Eastern College, founded in 1919, had been a [[liberal arts]] college in [[Quiapo]]; the IABF had been established (originally under the name Institute of Accountancy) by Nicanor Reyes, Sr., head of the Department of Economics of the [[University of the Philippines]], with a number of other prominent educators in 1928.&lt;ref name=Public/&gt;&lt;ref name=About&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.feu.edu.ph/aboutus.php?value=2 | title = The History of FEU | work = feu.edu.ph | accessdate = 2009-09-10 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070609135048/http://www.feu.edu.ph/aboutus.php?value=2 | archivedate = 2007-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; IABF had been originally predominately used by [[night school|night students]], and the new university, which was supported by the [[tuition]] provided by its students rather than government grants.&lt;ref name=Public/&gt;&lt;ref name=About/&gt;

In its earliest days, FEU was housed in a converted tobacco factory already present on the four [[hectare]] (nearly 10 [[acre]]) plot which would eventually host the current campus.&lt;ref name=Public/&gt;&lt;ref name=About/&gt; Reyes Sr. was appointed the first president of the University, which spent its early years establishing several of its institutes, including those of Law and Technology. Reyes commissioned [[Pablo Antonio]], who would later be titled [[National Artist of the Philippines]], to construct a building for the school.&lt;ref name=Deco&gt;{{cite news | url = http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/metro/view/20070115-43427/Art_Deco_buildings_thrive_on_FEU_campus | title = Art Deco buildings thrive on FEU campus | last = Ortiz | first = Margaux | date = 2007-01-15 | work = [[Philippine Daily Inquirer]] | accessdate = 2009-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1939, the Nicanor Reyes Hall, which would later house the library and Institute of Accounting, Business and Finance, opened. Two other buildings by Antonio, the Girls’ High School Building and Boys High School Building, followed in 1940 and 1941,&lt;ref name=Deco/&gt; by which year FEU had 10,000 registered students, with an international student population of 400.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | chapter = Muddling Through: Development Under a &quot;Weak&quot; State | last = de Jesus | first = Edilberto C. | title = Local cultures and the &quot;new Asia&quot;: the state, culture, and capitalism in Southeast Asia | volume= 24 | series = Social Issues in Southeast Asia Series | editor1-last = Wan-Ling Wee | editor1-first= C.J. | publisher = Institute of Southeast Asian Studies | year = 2002 | isbn = 9812301232 | page = 70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During [[World War II]], the campus was [[Military occupation|occupied]] by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]], who left only its shell unharmed.&lt;ref name=About/&gt; Dr. Nicanor Reyes having been killed during the occupation, Dr. Hermenigildo B. Reyes was appointed the second president of the University when it reopened in 1945.&lt;ref name=About/&gt;

Thereafter, FEU continued to expand, with the opening of a Science Building and the establishment of the Institute of Medicine and the School of Nursing. In 1955, the FEU hospital was opened. Humanities were introduced in 1959, and in 1970 the Institute of Architecture and Fine Arts opened. Also in 1970, the for-profit status of the Institute of Medicine, School of Medical Technology, FEU Hospital and the Student Health Service Clinic was altered, when these were converted in the FEU Dr. Nicanor Reyes Medical Foundation, a non-stock, non-profit educational foundation.&lt;ref name=About/&gt;

1989 introduced substantial revitalization to FEU that took place over a number of years, with renovation and modernization of facilities and grounds and upgrading of the University's educational standard. This resulted in the [[accreditation]] of the Institute of Arts and Sciences, the Institute of Education, and the Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance, and, in the mid-1990s, the deregulation of the University by the [[Commission on Higher Education (Philippines)|Commission on Higher Education]]. The auditorium was upgraded to accommodate modern stage productions and the new twice-monthly presentations by local and international artists established by the President's Committee on Culture. The University also prioritized publication, launching a number of scholarly journals, and began networking with other institutions nationally and abroad.&lt;ref name=About/&gt;

==University emblems==
*The legendary Sarimanok&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
*The University Colors: Gold represents the golden opportunity for the University to serve the youth and her alumni to serve the country. Green is for hope, representing Rizals &quot;Fair hope of the Fatherland.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;IABF Bulletin of Information 2005-2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FEU Publication&quot;&gt;FEU Publication{{Nonspecific|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Tamaraw]] is the mascot of every FEU athletic team. Hence, it is the pet name of every FEU student (Tams). Known scientifically as “Bubalus mindorensis”, it is a rare animal found only in the island of Mindoro.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;advocate&quot;&gt;The FEU Advocate - University Profile{{Nonspecific|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Memorial Quadrangle&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;
*The Mace&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Campus==
Among the buildings on FEU's campus complex, five by Pablo Antonio garnered recognition for FEU in 2005 from the [[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization]] (UNESCO), who bestowed the ''Asia Pacific Heritage Award for Cultural Heritage'' on the university for &quot;the outstanding preservation of its Art Deco structures.&quot;&lt;ref name=Deco/&gt; The buildings include the Nicanor Reyes Hall, the FEU East Asia College of Engineering and Computer Studies, the Law and Nursing Building, Auditorium/Administration Building and the Science Building. The buildings were constructed over a period of years ranging from 1939 to 1950 and reflect Antonio's evolution from [[Art Deco]] to the [[International style (architecture)|International Style]] popularized in the area after World War II.&lt;ref name=Deco/&gt; The [[Cultural Center of the Philippines]] also recognized the historical legacy of the buildings with a marker. Other historical buildings on the campus include the 1950s FEU Chapel, FEU Hospital, and the Arts and Sciences Building, which also represent the International Style.


==Notable Alumni==
* [[Henry Sy]] - Chairman of SM Group of Companies
* [[Lucio Tan]] - Chairman of Philippine Airlines
* [[Corazon Aquino]] - Former Philippine President
* [[Alfonso Yuchengco]] - Chairman of Yuchengco Group of Companies
* George Yang - Founder of McDonald's Philippines (Golden Arches)
* [[Ramon Revilla Sr.]] - Former Philippine Senator, Actor
* Ernesto &quot;Ernie&quot; Baron - Filipino Broadcaster, Inventor
* Martina Aileen &quot;Ai Ai&quot; Delas Alas - Actress
* Arwind Santos - PBA player
* Elma Muros - Track and Field Athlete
* Lydia De Vega- Athlete (Asia's fastest woman in the 1980s)
* Jose Marie &quot;[[Vice Ganda]]&quot; Viceral - Comedian, Host, Actor and Recording Artist

=Buildings=
{{Gallery
|title=Images around campus
|lines=4
|Image:FEU Administration Building1.jpg|The Administration Building at FEU.
|Image:IARFA building.JPG|The Institute of Architecture and Fine Arts, FEU-East Asia College
||The FEU Chapel, representing the International Style of architecture of the 1950s
||the FEU Technology Building
|Image:FEU nursing building1.JPG|[[Far Eastern University Institute of Nursing|Far Eastern University - Institute of Nursing]]
|Image:FEU Pavilion1.jpg|FEU student pavilion
}}

==Academic institutes==

Far Eastern University- Manila&lt;ref name=About&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.feu.edu.ph/ | title = Institutes of FEU = feu.edu.ph | accessdate = 2009-09-10 | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070609135048/http://www.feu.edu.ph/ | archivedate = 2007-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Far Eastern University - Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance|Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance (IABF)]] - LEVEL III PACUCOA accreditation for Business Administration LEVEL III PACUCOA accreditation for Accountancy
*[[Far Eastern University - Institute of Architecture and Fine Arts|Institute of Architecture and Fine Arts (IARFA)]] - LEVEL II
*[[Far Eastern University - Institute of Arts and Sciences|Institute of Arts and Sciences (IAS)]] - LEVEL III PACUCOA accreditation for Liberal Arts, Biology, Psychology and Applied Mathematics
*Institute of Education (IE) - LEVEL III PACUCOA accreditation for Elementary Education and Secondary Education
*[[Far Eastern University Institute of Nursing|Institute of Nursing (IN)]] - Virtual Nursing Lab, Joint Commission compliant, First in the Philippines LEVEL II PAASCU accreditation
*[[Far Eastern University Institute of Law|Institute of Law (IL)]]
*Institute of Graduate Studies (IGS)
*Institute of Tourism &amp; Hotel Restaurant Management

==Colleges and schools==

*[[Far Eastern University – East Asia College|FEU - East Asia College (FEU-EAC), (Former FEU Institute of Technology)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;FEU East Asia College&quot;&gt;http://www.feu-eastasia.edu.ph/ FEU East Asia College Date accessed 2009-09-13&lt;/ref&gt;
**College of Engineering(CoE)
**College of Computer Studies (CCS) - CS by PAASCU Center of Development in I.T. Education by Commission on Higher Education
**Department of Graduate Studies


*[[Far Eastern University – Nicanor Reyes Medical Foundation|FEU - Dr. Nicanor Reyes MEDICAL Foundation (FEU-NRMF) (FEU Institute of Medicine)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;FEU NRMF Institute of Medicine&quot;&gt;http://www.feu-nrmf.ph/feu_im.html FEU-NRMF : Meeting the Challenges of the Changing Times Date accessed 2009-09-13&lt;/ref&gt;
**Institute of Medicine - CS by PAASCU
**School of Medical Technology - LEVEL II PACUCOA accreditation
**School of Physical Therapy - CS by PACUCOA


*[[Far Eastern University – Nicanor Reyes Educational Foundation|FEU- FERN (Nicanor Reyes Educational Foundation) College - Diliman, Quezon City]]&lt;ref name=&quot;FEU FERN College&quot;&gt;http://www.feufern.edu.ph/ FEU FERN College Date accessed 2009-09-13&lt;/ref&gt;
**Bachelor of Science in Accountancy
**Bachelor of Science in Business Administration
***Major in Financial Management (BSBA-FM)
***Major in Marketing (BSBA-Marketing)
***Major in Operations Management (BSBA-Management)
***Major in Legal Management (BSBA-LM)
**Bachelor of Science in Computer Science
**Bachelor of Science in Information Technology
**Basic Education - Level I
*** Nursery
*** Kindergarten
*** Preparatory
*** Elementary
*** High School


*Far Eastern University - [[Silang, Cavite]] [http://www.feu-silang.edu.ph/]
**Basic Education
*** Nursery
*** Kindergarten
*** Preparatory
*** Elementary
*** High School

*Tertiary Programs
** Bachelor of Science in Hotel and Restaurant Management (BSHRM)
** Bachelor of Science in Tourism Management (BSTM)
** Bachelor of Science in Business Administration, major in Financial Management (BSBA-FM)
** Bachelor of Science in Business Administration, major in Marketing Management (BSBA-FM)
** Bachelor of Elementary Education  General (BEED General)
** Bachelor of Elementary Education, Major in Early Childhood Education (BEED ECE)
** Bachelor of Elementary Education, Major in Special Education (BEED  SPED)
** Bachelor of Secondary Education, major in English (BSED English)


*FEU Makati
**Bachelor of Science in Information Technology     
**Bachelor of Science in Accountancy    
**Bachelor of Science in Accounting Technology
**Bachelor of Science in Business Administration
***Major in Business Economics
***Major in Financial Management
***Major in Marketing Management
***Major in Human Resource Development Management
***Major in Operations Management
***Major in Management
***Major in Legal Management
**Master in Business Administration
**Institute of Culinary Arts and Food Service - FEU

==Athletics==
{{see also|FEU Tamaraws}}

A member of the University Athletic Association of the Philippines, FEU participates in 19 UAAP sports, including Athletics, Badminton, Basketball, Chess Fencing, Table Tennis, Taekwondo, and Volleyball for both men and women.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} Among the many athletes who have attended FEU are [[Lydia De Vega]], [[Elma Muros]], [[Anthony Villanueva]], and [[Johnny Abarrientos]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} FEU's teams are named after the [[tamaraw]], a buffalo with a reputation for ferocity.&lt;ref name=&quot;UltimateUngulate&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last =Huffman | first =Brent | authorlink =Brent Huffman
  | title =''Bubalus mindorensis'': Tamaraw | work =www.ultimateungulate.com | publisher =Ultimate Ungulate.com | date = 2007-01-02 | url =http://www.ultimateungulate.com/Artiodactyla/Bubalus_mindorensis.html
  | doi = | accessdate = 2009-09-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Publications==
*[http://www.feuadvocate.com The FEU Advocate] (Official Student Publication of Far Eastern University)

*Ambon
*Arts and Sciences Review
*IABF The Podium (The Official Student Publication of Institute of Accounts, Business, and Finance)
*IAS Paragon (Official Publication of the Institute of Arts and Sciences)
*Cultural Forum
*FEU-CSO Report
*FEU Journal
*FEU Newsletter
*''Tambuli'' (administrative publication)
*[http://www.facebook.com/pages/Manila-Philippines/The-Lamp-Official-Student-Publication-of-the-Institute-of-Nursing/256126920064/ The Lamp (Official Publication of the Institute of Nursing)]
*Transition (published annually by the President's Committee on Culture)
*Circle Magazine (Official Publication of the Institute of Architecture and Fine Arts)
*The Podium (Official Student Publication of the Institute of Accounts, Business and Finance)

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Further reading===
*''Far Eastern University alumni achievers : diamond edition 2003''. Published by the Far Eastern University in the City of Manila, 2003.
*''Art and culture @ Far Eastern University''. Nick Agudo . . . [et al.]; Sylvia Roces Montilla, editor-in-chief, production director; Alfredo Roces, book &amp; jacket design; Rafael R. Montinolla, technical consultant; Philip Escudero, Neal Oshima, Alfredo Roces, photography. Published by the Far Eastern University in the City of Manila, 2003.
*''FEU: the practical vision of Nicanor Reyes''. By Beth Romulo, Philippine Panorama 32(10): 6 Mr 16, 2003
*''FEU Auditorium : a golden heritage : the premier cultural center, 1949-1999''. By Sylvia R. Montilla, ©2000 Published by Far Eastern University in the City of Manila
*''Breaking The Silence''. By Lourdes Montinola, ©1998 Published by University of the Philippines Press - ISBN 971-542-128-8
*''Mr. FEU: The Culture Hero That was Nicanor Reyes''. By Nick Joaquin, ©1995 Published by FEU, Manila - ISBN 971-687-001-X
*''History of the Far Eastern University''. By Lucila Amparo, (Thesis, M.A. in History, FEU - Institute of Graduate Studies) 1955
*''FEU Green and Gold, 1948-1949''. Published by the Far Eastern University in the City of Manila, 1949

==External links==
*[http://www.feu.edu.ph/ Far Eastern University-Manila, Official Website]
*[http://www.feu-nrmf.ph/feu_im.html FEU-NRMF (Institute of Medicine)]
*[http://www.feu-silang.edu.ph/ Far Eastern University - Silang, Cavite]
*[http://www.feuadvocate.com/ Far Eastern University Advocate Online]
*[http://www.feu.edu.ph/teachersacad_about.asp/ Far Eastern University Teachers Academy]
*[http://www.feunaf.com/ Far Eastern University Nursing Alumni Foundation]
*[http://www.unescobkk.org/index.php?id=3194/ 2005 UNESCO Asia-Pacific Heritage Award]
*[http://www.tamarawbayan.com/ The FEU Tamaraw Bayan]

&lt;br&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
{{FEU}}
{{UAAP}}
&lt;/center&gt;

{{University Belt}}
{{coord missing|Metro Manila}}

[[Category:Far Eastern University| ]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1928]]
[[Category:Companies listed on the Philippine Stock Exchange]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in the Philippines]]
[[Category:University Athletic Association of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Art Deco buildings]]
[[Category:Education in Cavite]]

[[pam:Far Eastern University]]
[[nl:Far Eastern University]]
[[simple:Far Eastern University]]
[[tl:Pamantasan ng Dulong Silangan]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
