<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27623129" ns="0" title="Declan Macey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series=[[Emmerdale]]
|name=Declan Macey
|introducer=Gavin Blyth
|image= 
|caption=Declan Macey in October 2011.
|portrayer=[[Jason Merrells]]
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|years=2010—
|first=15 April 2010
|last=
|born=1968
|death=
|occupation=Businessman
|home=Home Farm
|father=[[Dermot Macey]]
|wife=[[Ella Macey|Ella Hart]] (1991–2010)
|halfsisters = [[Megan Macey]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a345073/emmerdale-casts-gaynor-faye-as-new-macey.html&lt;/ref&gt;
|romances=[[Natasha Wylde]] (2010)&lt;br /&gt;[[Alicia Gallagher]] (2010)&lt;br /&gt;[[Charity Tate]] (2010)&lt;br /&gt;[[Katie Sugden]] (2011—)
|adoptivedaughters = [[Mia Macey]]
}}

'''Declan Macey''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[British television|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'', introduced on 15 April 2010. He is portrayed by [[Jason Merrells]].

==Creation==
In January 2010, it was announced that former ''[[Waterloo Road (TV series)|Waterloo Road]]'' star Jason Merrells would be joining the cast of ''Emmerdale'' as [[Natasha Wylde]]'s new love interest. When [[Amanda Donohoe]] (who played Natasha) quit the role, Declan become the new owner of Home Farm. In mid-2010, it was announced that a new dynasty would hit ''Home Farm''. The clan included Declan's estranged ex-wife Ella, their daughter Mia, and his father, Dermot. However, they departed in 2011 after the characters were axed by series producer, Stuart Blackburn. It was announced in October, 2011, that [[Gaynor Faye]] had joined the cast as [[Megan Macey]], Declan's half sister. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a345073/emmerdale-casts-gaynor-faye-as-new-macey.html&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Storylines==
===2010—===
Declan was introduced to [[Emmerdale]] in April 2010 as friend of [[Jai Sharma|Jai]] and [[Nikhil Sharma]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a202486/another-cutting-it-star-joins-emmerdale.html&lt;/ref&gt; Declan is first seen being chatted up by Mrs. [[Charity Tate]] and falls into her trap, stealing his car keys and driving off in his car. Declan later appears in the pub with Jai and Nikhil and spots Charity without her wig on. He blackmails her by saying if she goes on a date with him, he will not call the police. She did so, and they ended up kissing in the corridor of the Woolpack. Declan already knew that Charity and Cain were together, and kissed Charity to make Cain jealous after she revealed he was her partner in crime. After giving the Sharma brothers some advice about Home Farm, Declan bought a share in Home Farm from [[Natasha Wylde]], unaware it is her son [[Nathan Wylde|Nathan]]'s share of the estate.

When Nathan returns, he takes an instant dislike to Declan and informs him that he wants his share back. Declan refuses, and Nathan realises that he won't be able to push Declan around. Declan and Natasha became very close and a relationship developed between them. They decided to keep their relationship private from the rest of the village.

Declan purchased a property in the village he intended to move into, and receives a phone number from [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]] for a builder who could renovate the property. The builder turns out to be [[Jackson Walsh]], which causes tension between garage worker [[Aaron Livesy]]-Jackson's boyfriend-and [[Cain Dingle]], who already had a run-in with Declan over the car theft.

In July 2010, Declan took Natasha to a health spa as a treat, but Natasha received a phone call from Nathan informing her that the body of her husband [[Mark Wylde|Mark]], whom she had murdered, had been discovered.

In August 2010, Natasha's daughter [[Maisie Wylde]] tells Declan she thinks Nathan killed their father so he demands answers from Natasha, believing she is covering for Nathan. He offers to help, believing that Nathan is blackmailing her, but Natasha tells Declan that Nathan did not kill Mark. Declan then ends the relationship.

In September 2010, Declan sacks Nathan from his job as estate manager and gives former employee [[Nicola King]] her old job back. Declan refused Nathan and Natasha's deal to sell his 51% of Home Farm. Declan offers to help [[Faye Lamb]] contest Mark's will in order to take over the estate. He also promises to support Faye financially when her son [[Ryan Lamb|Ryan]] is accused of Mark's murder. Declan then gets a call from his ex-wife in Singapore telling him that his daughter has been injured in a road accident and he flies out to be with her.

Declan returns on the day Ryan is found guilty of Mark's murder. He comforts Faye on the courtroom steps and offers to help fund an appeal against Ryan's conviction. Declan is shocked when Natasha later confesses to Mark's murder. He apologizes to Nathan for believing he was Mark's killer and makes him an offer. Because Natasha could not benefit from Mark's will after confessing to his murder, the money would be split between Faye, Ryan, Nathan, Will and Maisie. If Nathan could convince Natasha to sell Home Farm and her 49% of the business to Declan, he would give Nathan the money, allowing him to move away from the village with Maisie and Will and make a fresh start. Nathan, however, refuses to sell Home Farm to Declan, despite being unable to get any better offers. [[Ella Hart]] arrives at ''Home Farm'', making Nathan an offer after he accepts. Ella then makes herself at home, much to Declan's fancies, but little does Nathan know that Ella is actually Declan's wife and that they have schemed Nathan into selling them ''Home Farm''.

Later in November, Ella returns home with their daughter [[Mia Macey]] to find Declan with [[Alicia Gallagher]]. Also, Declan gave [[Dale Head]] to [[Hazel Rhodes]] so that she could turn it into a home suitable for her son [[Jackson Walsh]], who is paralysed after a train crash. On 21 December 2010, Declan's unwanted father [[Dermot Macey]] arrives for Christmas at Ella's invitation, but before he arrived at Home Farm, Declan noticed him in the bus shelter and paid him to not stay. When Declan arrived home, Dermot was sitting with Ella and Mia. On 31 December 2010, Declan witnessed Mia kissing [[Adam Barton]], which didn't make Adam's girlfriend [[Scarlett Nicholls]] very happy and Declan told Ella to take Mia home.

[[Katie Sugden]], who works for Declan, was given time off after being held captive by [[Nick Henshall]]. His PA [[Nicola King]] was also given time off when her husband [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]] went missing, so he employed Mia as his temporary PA. In February 2011, [[Sam Dingle]] told Declan that one of the walls has fallen down and that he needs someone to help him do it, so Mia suggested that her on/off lover Adam could help Sam, which didn't please Adam's dad [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]] because Adam was missing so much time on the farm.

In April 2011, Declan's wife Ella began a passionate affair with Adam. After months of hiding and sneaking around, Declan finally finds out in June 2011 and throws Ella out of his house. Declan then gets together with Katie Sugden, and with the pair dating, Ella warns Katie off Declan. She fails to split them, and Ella decides to leave the village. Before she does, she tells Declan that he is not Mia's father, and that Jai is. This leaves Declan furious, and he confronts Jai and the two have a showdown. Declan tells Jai to stay away from Mia, but this doesn't happen, so Declan asks his father, Dermot, to take Mia back to Ireland.

In November 2011, Katie tells Declan to get in touch Mia. At first he doesn't because he is frightened, but after an argument with Katie, he sees sense and calls her. He arranges for Mia to stay at Home Farm the following day. However, on the day of Mia's arrival, Declan is informed by the police that Mia had died in a car accident. He breaks down and starts ignoring Katie and shouting at his PA, Nicola.

== See Also ==
*[[List of Emmerdale characters]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Macey, Declan}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional businesspeople]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2010]]
[[Category:Fictional people from London]]
[[Category:Fictional British people of Irish descent]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
