<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27686819" ns="0" title="United Continental Holdings"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| name             = United Continental Holdings
| logo             = [[File:United Continental Holdings Logo.png|220px|United Continental Holdings]]
| type             = [[Public company|Public]]
| traded_as        = {{nyse|UAL}}
| predecessor      = [[UAL Corporation]]
| foundation       = {{Start date|2010|10|01}}&lt;br&gt;[[Chicago]], [[Illinois]]
| location_city    = [[77 West Wacker]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chicago Loop]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chicago]], [[Illinois]]
| location_country = [[United States|U.S.]]
| area_served      = Worldwide
| key_people       = [[Glenn F. Tilton]] &lt;small&gt;([[Chairman]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Jeff Smisek|Jeffery A. Smisek]] &lt;small&gt;([[CEO]])&lt;/small&gt;
| industry         = [[Aviation]]
| revenue          = {{increase}} [[United States dollar|US$]] 23.229 billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/100517/000119312511042335/d10k.htm|title=2010 Form 10-K, United Continental Holdings|publisher=United States Securities and Exchange Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| operating_income = {{increase}} US$ 976 million &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| net_income       = {{increase}} US$ 253 million &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| assets           = {{increase}} US$ 39.598 billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| equity           = {{increase}} US$ 1.727 billion &lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| num_employees    = 86,852 &lt;!-- billion? NOT! --&gt;&lt;small&gt;(2010)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=10K/&gt;
| subsid           = [[United Airlines]]
| homepage         = [http://www.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/ UnitedContinentalHoldings.com]
| footnotes        = &lt;ref name=&quot;fact sheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/download.php?file=united_factsheet.pdf&amp;type=pdf &quot;United Fact Sheet&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
'''United Continental Holdings''', Inc. ({{NYSE|UAL}}), is a publicly traded airline holding company, incorporated in Delaware with headquarters in the [[77 West Wacker|United Building]] in [[Chicago]], Illinois.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=83680&amp;p=irol-govBoard Board of Directors].&quot; United Continental Holdings. Retrieved on October 3, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; UCH owns and operates [[United Airlines]], Inc. The company is the successor of [[UAL Corporation]], which agreed to change its name to United Continental Holdings in May 2010, when a merger agreement was reached between the airlines. Its stock trades under the UAL symbol. To effect the merger, Continental shareholders received 1.05 shares of UAL stock for each Continental share; at the time of closing, it was estimated that United shareholders owned 55% of the merged entity and Continental shareholders owned 45%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=83680&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=1478014&amp;highlight=|title=United Continental Holdings, Inc. - Investor Relations - News|publisher=Ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com|accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company or its subsidiary airlines also have several other subsidiaries. United, when it is completely combined, will be the world's largest airline, as measured by revenue passenger miles. United is a founding member of the Star Alliance.&lt;ref name=&quot;unitedcontinentalmerger.com&quot;&gt;http://www.unitedcontinentalmerger.com/press-release&lt;/ref&gt;

UCH has major operations at Chicago–O'Hare, Cleveland, Denver, Guam, Houston–Intercontinental, Los Angeles, Newark, San Francisco, Tokyo–Narita and Washington–Dulles. UCH's United Air Lines, Inc. controls several key air rights, including being one of only two American carriers authorized to serve Asia from Tokyo-Narita. Additionally, UCH's United is the largest U.S. carrier to the People’s Republic of China and maintains a large operation throughout Asia.&lt;ref name=&quot;unitedcontinentalmerger.com&quot;/&gt;

UCH plans to use Continental's operating certificate and United's repair station certificate. UCH plans to dissolve its Continental Airlines, Inc. subsidiary by the end of 2011 and began using its Single Operator Certificate approved by the FAA on November 30, 2011 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=83680&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=1634697|title=United Continental Holdings, Inc. - Invester Relations - News|publisher=Ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com|accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Major subsidiaries==
[[File:UnitedAirlinesBuildingChicagoIL.jpg|thumb|150px|[[77 West Wacker Drive|United Building]] in the [[Chicago Loop]] houses the headquarters of United Continental]]
*United Air Lines, Inc.
**[http://www.unitedtechops.com/ United Services] 
**UAL Loyalty Services Inc.  (loyalty programs and travel clubs, including United Cruises)
***Mileage Plus Holdings Inc.
****Mileage Plus Marketing, Inc. (administers the Mileage Plus [[frequent flyer program]])
***ULS Ventures, Inc.
**United Worldwide Corporation

==Development==
Early in February 2008, [[UAL Corporation]] and [[Continental Airlines]]  began advanced stages of merger negotiations and were expected to announce their decision in the immediate aftermath of a definitive merger agreement between rival [[Delta Air Lines]] and [[Northwest Airlines]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chicagotribune.com/travel/chi-fri_airlinesfeb15,0,3837947.story United stands ready to merge{{ndash}} chicagotribune.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The timing of the events was notable because Northwest's [[golden shares]] in Continental (that gave Northwest veto authority against any merger involving Continental) could be redeemed, freeing Continental to pursue a marriage with United. On April 27, 2008, Continental broke off merger negotiations with United and stated it was going to stand alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/04/28/business/28air.html|work=The New York Times|title=Continental Abandons Merger Talks With United|date=April 28, 2008|accessdate=May 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite ending merger talks, Continental announced that it will join United in the [[Star Alliance]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.continental.com/web/en-US/content/news/alliance.aspx Continental Airlines]&lt;/ref&gt;

United and [[US Airways]] were in advanced merger talks in late April 2008, following the announcement that [[Continental Airlines|Continental]] had broken off talks with United.&lt;ref&gt;'http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/24352806/'&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2008, [[CEOs]] of both United Airlines and [[Continental Airlines]] signed an alliance pact presaging their eventual merger. The alliance is an agreement to link international networks and share technology and passenger perks. This agreement is basically a &quot;virtual merger&quot; that includes many of the benefits of a merger without the actual costs and restructuring involved. The alliance took effect about a year after [[Delta Air Lines]] and [[Northwest Airlines]] completed their merger, as that released Continental from the [[SkyTeam]] contract and allowed for the required nine-month notice. Additionally, Continental joined the [[Star Alliance]], as Delta and Northwest merged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/business/chi-fri-united-alliance-uaua-caljun20,0,3619794.story|title=United, Continental join forces|author=Johnsson, Julie|work=Chicago Tribune|date=2008-06-20|accessdate=2008-06-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

United Airlines was reported to be in serious merger discussion with US Airways in early April 2010. A ''[[The New York Times|New York Times]]'' report indicated that a deal was close. Union consent was cited as a major hurdle for negotiators to clear.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dealbook.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/04/07/united-and-us-airways-hold-merger-talks/?ref=business|title=United and US Airways Said to be in Merger Talks|work=New York Times|date=2010-04-07|accessdate=2010-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 22, 2010, United announced that it would not pursue a merger with [[US Airways]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Reed|first=Dan|url=http://www.usatoday.com/MONEY/usaedition/2010-04-22-us-airways-ends-merger-talks-united-airlines_NU.htm?csp=34|title=Irked US Airways ends merger talks with United|publisher=Usatoday.Com|date=2010-04-22|accessdate=2010-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Board of Directors at Continental and United airlines approved a stock-swap deal that would combine them into the world's largest airline on Sunday, May 2, 2010. The airlines publicly announced the deal the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;unitedcontinentalmerger1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Press Release|url=http://www.unitedcontinentalmerger.com/press-release|title=Press Release &amp;#124; Let's Fly Together|publisher=Unitedcontinentalmerger.com|accessdate=2010-05-03}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new airline will take on the United Airlines name and be based in United's hometown of Chicago. It will be run by Continental's CEO, [[Jeff Smisek]]. UAL's CEO, [[Glenn Tilton]], will be non-executive chairman. The deal will still need final approval from labor unions and antitrust regulators before being allowed to go forward.&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews1&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/us/2010/05/02/continental-united-reportedly-approve-deal-combine/ Continental and United Reportedly Approve Deal to Combine]&lt;/ref&gt; This would re-unite [[Walter Varney]]'s airlines, which offspring includes Continental and United.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.economist.com/node/16064180|work=The Economist|title=Love is in the air|date=May 6, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Wikinews2|Continental and United Airlines to merge|Continental and United Airlines shareholders approve merger}}
Both airlines have taken losses in the recession and expect the merger to generate savings of more than {{Nowrap|$1 billion}} a year.&lt;ref name=BBCmerger&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/10095080.stm|title=United and Continental Airlines to merge|date=3 May 2010|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=3 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Combined, they fly to some 370 destinations in 59 countries from their ten hubs,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.unitedcontinentalmerger.com/worlds-most-comprehensive-network&lt;/ref&gt; and carry {{Nowrap|144 million}} passengers a year.&lt;ref name=BBCmerger /&gt; Combined revenues will be about {{Nowrap|$29 billion}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-world/united-continental-create-worlds-biggest-airline-20100503-u39b.html|title=United, Continental create world's biggest airlin|date=May 4, 2010|publisher=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]|accessdate=3 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In July, the merger of the two airlines was approved by the [[European Union]].&lt;ref name=&quot;google.com&quot;&gt;http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5iLtBZzKBc8HAtWTZlIMlpoajQZnQD9H7ILIO0&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 27, 2010, the U.S. Department of Justice approved the $3 billion merger&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/08/28/business/28air.html?hp|work=The New York Times|title=United-Continental Merger Clears Federal Hurdle|first=Jad|last=Mouawad|date=August 27, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and shareholders of both the companies approved the merger on September 17, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://ir.united.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=83680&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=1472600&amp;highlight=&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.continental.com/web/en-US/apps/vendors/default.aspx?i=http%3A%2F%2Fphx.corporate-ir.net%2Fphoenix.zhtml%3Fc%3D85779%26p%3Dirol-newsArticle%26ID%3D1472570&lt;/ref&gt; On October 1, 2010, UAL Corporation (the parent company of United Airlines) completed its acquisition of Continental Airlines and changed its name to United Continental Holdings, Inc. Although the two airlines remain separate until the operational integration is completed (by mid-2012), as of this day both airlines are corporately controlled by the same leadership. Both carriers achieved a single operating certificate from the FAA on November 30, 2011 which allowed both airlines to operate under the name &quot;United&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://news.yahoo.com/pilots-united-gets-single-operating-certificate-231520061.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Branding==
When United Airlines and Continental Airlines announced their merger in May 2010 they introduced their new corporate branding. It featured the words &quot;United Airlines&quot; in the then-current Continental typeface, and Continental's globe-like logo. United updated their branding once again in August 2010, replacing the words &quot;United Airlines&quot; with the single word '''UNITED''' and changing the font to United's traditional upper-case sans-serif font.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted Aug 12th 2010 05:13 PM|url=http://news.travel.aol.com/2010/08/12/united-continental-show-off-new-livery/|title=United, Continental Show Off New Livery - AOL Travel News|publisher=News.travel.aol.com|date=2010-08-12|accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; United's new CEO Jeff Smisek, who previously served as Continental's chairman, helped design the new font, integrating it with the existing [[Lippincott]]-designed Continental graphics. He has noted that he has received over 15,000 emails with suggestions for a new livery.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brookson|first=Ben|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/blogs/flight-international/2010/12/heres-what-uniteds-ceo-thinks.html|title=Here's what United's CEO thinks of the carrier's new livery - Flight International|publisher=Flightglobal.com|accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Continental Airlines Boeing 737-900ER series aircraft (N53442) was the first aircraft to be painted into the new livery for the combined company.

United Continental Holdings also brings its larger airline services to smaller communities via its branding rights and ownership over the [[Continental Connection]], [[Continental Express]],  and [[United Express]] trademarks. Continental Connection and Continental Express will be consolidated into the United Express marketing and branding as the [[merger integration]] moves forward.

As of late 2010, [[George Gershwin]]'s 1924 &quot;[[Rhapsody in Blue]]&quot; will remain as the new United's theme song, the song has since been featured on new safety videos on United and Continental aircraft.

It was announced February 2011 that United would maintain its P.S., or Premium Service transcontinental aircraft and update the interiors. 

The first United 747 featuring the new livery was painted in February 2011. Re-painting and branding is said to be &quot;accelerated&quot; beginning mid-2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ir.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=83680&amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;ID=1532591&amp;highlight= Boeing 747 Debuts in New United Livery] United Continental Holdings PR, 24 Feb 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bigger Map - United Airlines.png|thumb|200px|United's new interim advertisement, shown on a print ad on March 1, 2011.]]
On March 1, 2011, United unveiled an &quot;interim&quot; marketing campaign replacing the previous &quot;It's Time to Fly&quot; campaign, which included fingerpaint ads and television spots created by Fallon. On the same date, United removed the iconic 38-year-old [[Saul Bass]]-designed &quot;Tulip&quot; logo from its website and all new advertisements will feature the former Continental globe logo. This new campaign will be used until 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.suntimes.com/media/2011/03/united_airlines_launches_new_c.html|work=Chicago Sun-Times|title=United Airlines launches new campaign from Kaplan Thaler/New York}}&lt;/ref&gt; The newly released ads adopt the same concept of the former Continental ads which simply express a one-liner. As of now, United tagline is 'You're going to like where we land!&quot;

==Hubs==
The combined airline serves up to 370 destinations, from the 10 hubs listed below. This may be subject to change due to future developments and decisions. Continental and United said that Houston's [[George Bush Intercontinental Airport]] will be the largest hub for the new airline, which is a primary gateway to Latin America.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=United Continental Holdings|url=http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2010/05/continental_and_united_announc.html|title=Cleveland Hopkins to remain a hub after Continental-United merger - at least for now|publisher=cleveland.com|accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Chicago-O'Hare, Houston-Bush, and San Francisco hubs have completely rebranded. Hubs at Denver, Cleveland, Newark, Tokyo-Narita, and Washington-Dulles are currently being rebranded in phases. Guam is the only hub airport that have not rebranded.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.continental.com/CMS/en-US/travel/Pages/airportupdates.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 85%&quot;
|+ '''New United Airlines hubs'''
! Airport
! Area served
! Type/region
! Airline before merger
|-
| [[File:Flag of Guam.svg|20px]] [[Antonio B. Won Pat International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Guam.svg|20px]] [[Guam]]
| Pacific hub
| Continental
|-
| [[File:Flag of Ohio.svg|20px]] [[Cleveland Hopkins International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Cleveland, Ohio.svg|20px]] [[Cleveland]], [[Ohio]]
| Secondary Midwest hub
| Continental
|-
| [[File:Flag of Colorado.svg|20px]] [[Denver International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Denver, Colorado.svg|20px]] [[Denver]], [[Colorado]]
| Western hub
| United
|-
| [[File:Flag of Texas.svg|20px]] [[George Bush Intercontinental Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Houston, Texas.svg|20px]] [[Houston]], [[Texas]]
| Largest hub, primary gateway to Latin America
| Continental
|-
| [[File:Flag of California.svg|20px]] [[Los Angeles International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Los Angeles, California.svg|20px]] [[Los Angeles]], [[California]]
| Secondary West Coast hub
| United
|-
| [[File:Flag of Japan.svg|20px]] [[Narita International Airport]]
| [[File:PrefSymbol-Tokyo.svg|20px]] [[Tokyo]], [[Japan]]
| Asian hub
| United
|-
| [[File:Flag of New Jersey.svg|20px]] [[Newark Liberty International Airport]]
| [[File:NewarkNJ flag.jpg|20px]] [[Newark, New Jersey]], [[New York metropolitan area]]
| Primary East Coast hub
| Continental
|-
| [[File:Flag of Illinois.svg|20px]] [[O'Hare International Airport]]
| [[File:Municipal Flag of Chicago.svg|20px]] Chicago, Illinois
| Second largest hub, primary Midwest hub, 
| United
|-
| [[File:Flag of California.svg|20px]] [[San Francisco International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of San Francisco.svg|20px]] [[San Francisco, California]], [[San Francisco Bay Area]]
| Primary West Coast hub
| United
|-
| [[File:Flag of Virginia.svg|20px]] [[Washington Dulles International Airport]]
| [[File:Flag of Virginia.svg|20px]] [[Northern Virginia]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Washington, D.C..svg|20px]] [[Washington, D.C.]]
| Secondary East Coast hub
| United
|}

==Fleet==
{{Unreferenced section|date=January 2011}}
The new United is the world's second largest airline in terms of fleet size, while [[Delta Air Lines|Delta]] remains the largest. The combined airline houses a fleet of 709 aircraft, surpassing [[American Airlines]]' 621. There are also 116 aircraft on order, 50 from United, and 66 from Continental. The combined fleet features a mixture of 75% [[Boeing]] and 25% [[Airbus]] aircraft: [[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A319]]s, [[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A320]]s, [[Boeing 737]]s, [[Boeing 747]]s, [[Boeing 757]]s, [[Boeing 767]]s, and [[Boeing 777]]s with orders of [[Airbus A350]]s and [[Boeing 787 Dreamliner]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Numbers and types of aircraft, as of December 31, 2010, are in the 10K annual report, availbale on the United-Continental corporate website&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; cellpadding=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;border-collapse:collapse&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:lightblue;&quot;
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Aircraft
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Total
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Orders
!rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Notes
!colspan=&quot;6&quot; style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Livery
|- style=&quot;background:darkblue; color:black;&quot;
!style=&quot;background:darkblue; width:25px;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;United &quot;Battleship&quot;
!style=&quot;background:darkblue; width:70px;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;United &quot;Blue Rising&quot;
!style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Continental
!style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;New United
!style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Star Alliance
!style=&quot;background:darkblue;&quot;| &lt;font style=&quot;color:white;&quot;&gt;Special
|-
|[[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A319]]
|align=center|55
|align=center|0
|
|align=center|5
|align=center|16
|align=center|0
|align=center|34
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Airbus A320 family|Airbus A320-200]]
|align=center|97
|align=center|0
|N475UA in painted in United's 85th Anniversary, 1971 &quot;Friend Ship&quot; livery
|align=center|0
|align=center|49
|align=center|0
|align=center|47
|align=center|0
|align=center|1
|-
|[[Airbus A350|Airbus A350-900]]
|align=center|0
|align=center|25
|Entry into Service: 2016-2019&lt;br&gt;Replacing: [[Boeing 747-400]]
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 737 Classic|Boeing 737-500]]
|align=center|28
|align=center|0
|All have Winglets.&lt;br&gt;5 Aircraft to Exit service in 2011
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|3
|align=center|25
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Boeing 737-700]]
|align=center|36
|align=center|46
|N13720 painted in New-United Star Alliance livery: 737-700 orders can, and are, being converted to other 737NG models
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|2
|align=center|33
|align=center|1
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Boeing 737-800]]
|align=center|130
|align=center|2
|N26210 painted in New-United Star Alliance livery&lt;br&gt;N76516 painted in New-United Eco-Skies livery
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|33
|align=center|95
|align=center|1
|align=center|1
|-
|[[Boeing 737 Next Generation|Boeing 737-900]]
|align=center|12
|align=center|0
|
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|9
|align=center|3
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 737-900ER]]
|align=center|33
|align=center|19
|N75436 painted in Continental 75th Anniversary livery
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|32
|align=center|0
|align=center|1
|-
|[[Boeing 747-400]]
|align=center|23
|align=center|0
|N121UA painted in United Star Alliance Livery&lt;br&gt;Exit from Service: 2016-2019&lt;br&gt;Replacement: [[Airbus A350|Airbus A350-900]]&lt;br&gt;1 Aircraft to be retired in 2011
|align=center|0
|align=center|19
|align=center|0
|align=center|3
|align=center|1
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 757|Boeing 757-200]]
|align=center|134
|align=center|0
|Second Largest operator of 757-200 after [[Delta Air Lines]]&lt;br&gt;N14120 painted in New-United Star Alliance livery.&lt;br&gt; 1 Aircraft to Exit service in 2011
|align=center|0
|align=center|53
|align=center|0
|align=center|80
|align=center|1
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 757|Boeing 757-300]]
|align=center|21
|align=center|0
|Largest operator of the Boeing 757-300&lt;br&gt;Retrofitted with blended winglets
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|21
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 767|Boeing 767-200ER]]
|align=center|8
|align=center|0
|All feature Boeing's signature 777 style interior&lt;br&gt;Will be the only airline to operate all 3 767ER models. N68155 (Ship 155) first COA&lt;br&gt;762 to be retired, sent to Phoenix Goodyear on 5/17/11 as COA 9990&lt;br&gt; 1 Aircraft to be retired in 2011
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|8
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 767|Boeing 767-300ER]]
|align=center|35
|align=center|0
|N653UA painted in New-United Star Alliance livery&lt;br&gt;Will be the only airline to operate all 3 767ER models&lt;br&gt;To be retrofitted with blended winglets starting in early 2012&lt;br&gt;Exit from service: 2016-2019 &lt;br&gt; Replacement: [[Boeing 787|Boeing 787-8]]
|align=center|4
|align=center|13
|align=center|0
|align=center|17
|align=center|1
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 767|Boeing 767-400ER]]
|align=center|16
|align=center|0
|N76055 painted in New-United Star Alliance livery&lt;br&gt;Will be the only airline to operate all 3 767ER models
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|15
|align=center|1
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 777|Boeing 777-200]]
|align=center|19
|align=center|0
|
|align=center|0
|align=center|4
|align=center|0
|align=center|15
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 777|Boeing 777-200ER]]
|align=center|55
|align=center|0
|N218UA painted as United Star Alliance livery&lt;br&gt;N76021 N78017 N77022 painted in New-United Star Alliance livery&lt;br&gt;Largest operator of the 777-200ER.
|align=center|6
|align=center|7
|align=center|0
|align=center|38
|align=center|4
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 787-8]]
|align=center|0
|align=center|36
|Entry into Service: First quarter of 2012&lt;br&gt;Replacing [[Boeing 767|Boeing 767-200ER]] &amp; [[Boeing 767|Boeing 767-300ER]]
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
|[[Boeing 787-9]]
|align=center|0
|align=center|14
|
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|align=center|0
|-
!Total
!702
!142
|
!15
!161
!47
!466
!10
!3
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Chicago|Illinois|Companies|Aviation}}
*[[Continental Airlines]]
*[[United Airlines]]
*[[List of airline mergers and acquisitions]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.unitedcontinentalholdings.com/ United Continental Holdings]
*{{Twitter|united}}
{{United Continental Holdings}}
{{Airline holding companies of the United States}}
{{Illinois Corporations}}

[[Category:Airline holding companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Companies based in Chicago, Illinois]]
[[Category:United Airlines]]

[[de:United Continental Holdings]]
[[it:United Continental Holdings]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
