<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27715261" ns="0" title="US Presidents on US postage stamps"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About||other uses|President of the United States (disambiguation)}}

&lt;!--  notes:
Sections for presidents are placed in chronological order per term of president.

With one exception to the 1st stamps, the Introduction has been kept clean
of Wiki' links which are found in more appropriate sections of the page.

Intro has been written a bit like an essay, to set the tone for body of text, 
which is encyclopedic.
--&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;!--Washington Die Proof2 1861-10c.jpg--&gt;
[[File:George Washington2 1861 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|280px|&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:11pt&quot;&gt;- [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#George Washington|George Washington]] -&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt; &lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:10pt&quot;&gt;Engraving modeled after Gilbert Stuart portrait&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]

For more than 160 years the one subject that has appeared most frequently on the face of U.S. Postage stamps is that of American Presidents. When the U.S. Post Office released its first two postage stamps in 1847, George Washington, along with Benjamin Franklin, were the two subjects depicted on these [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States#First national postage stamps|premier issues]]. The advent of Presidential honors on postage has been definitive to U.S. Postage stamp design since the first issues were released and set the premise that U.S. stamp designs would follow for many generations.

&lt;!-- Kloetzel and William A. Jones  (Oct 10, 2009) --&gt;
The engraved portrayals of U.S. Presidents was the exclusive design and theme found on U.S. postage from 1847 until 1869, with the one exception of Benjamin Franklin, the likes of whom was presidential in his aspect to many people. Twenty two years would pass as the U.S. Post Office continued to issue various postage stamps bearing the depictions of George Washington foremost, Benjamin Franklin, Thomas Jefferson, Andrew Jackson and Abraham Lincoln, who didn't appear until 1866, one year after his death. 

There exist entire series of stamp issues whose printing was inspired by the subject alone. The portrayals of Washington and Franklin on U.S. Postage are among the most definitive of examples and have appeared on numerous postage stamps. The presidential theme in stamp designs would continue as the decades passed, each period issuing stamps with variations of the same basic presidential-portrait design theme.  The portrayals of U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage has remained the predominate subject and design theme on definitive postage throughout most of U.S. stamp issuance history. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=&lt;br/&gt;'''Scott Specialized Catalogue of United States Stamps and Covers''' |year=2010 |publisher=&lt;br/&gt;Scott Publishing Company |ISBN=9780894874468 &lt;!--|ISBN=0894874462isbn=0-89487-0424--&gt; |editor1-first=James E. |editor1-last=&lt;br/&gt;Kloetzel |coauthors=Jones, William A. }}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

In 1869, after twenty two years of issuing stamps honoring only American Presidents and [[Benjamin Franklin]], the Post Office &lt;ref&gt;References are made to ''U.S. Post Office'' for postal history prior to 1971&lt;/ref&gt; issued a series of eleven postage stamps that were generally regarded by the American public as being abruptly different from the previous issues and whose designs were considered at the time to be a break from the tradition of honoring [[Founding Fathers of the United States|American forefathers]] on the nation's postage stamps. The denominations of this [[1869 Pictorial Issue]] had other non presidential subjects and a design style that was also different, one stamp bearing a horse, another a locomotive while others depicted nonpresidential themes. Washington and Lincoln were to be found only once in this series of eleven stamps and were also considered to be below par in design and image quality. As a result this pictographic series was met with general disdain and proved so unpopular that the issues were consequently sold for only one year, after which remaining stocks were pulled from post offices across the United States. &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;&gt;'''''Kenmore'' Collectors Catalogue, #906, 2010'''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uspcs.org/uspcs1869.html |title='''The U.S. Philatelic Classics Society''' |publisher=Uspcs.org |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alexander&amp;nbsp;T.&amp;nbsp;Haimann,&amp;nbsp;National Postal Museum |url=http://www.arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2029277 |title=The 1869 issues, National Postal Museum |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date=2006-05-16 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1870 the U.S. Post Office resumed its short lived tradition of printing postage with the portraits of American Presidents and Forefathers like Franklin but now added several other famous Americans, including Henry Clay, Daniel Webster, Alexander Hamilton and General Winfield Scott among other notable Americans. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

==First appearances==
The portrayals of various American Presidents made their first appearances on U.S. postage at different times for very different reasons. Among the most definitive is [[George Washington]] and [[Benjamin Franklin]] whose engravings appeared on the [[commons:File:First US Stamps 1847 Issue.jpg|first U.S. Postage stamps]] released by the [[United States Postal Service|U.S. Post Office]], on July 1 of 1847. [[Thomas Jefferson]] first appeared on U.S. postage in March 1856, nine years after the first issues were released. Fifteen years of stamp issuance would pass before [[Andrew Jackson]] would appear on a U. S. Postage stamp. However, by this time, Jackson had already been presented on two Confederate stamps (both 2-cent values), making him the only U. S. President introduced to postage by the Confederacy rather than the U. S. Post office. [[Abraham Lincoln]] appeared for the first time on a U.S. postage stamp with the issue of 1866, released on April 14, 1866, the first anniversary of his death.  Up until this time only the portrayals of Washington, Franklin, Jefferson and Jackson were found on U.S. Postage. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:George Washington 1847 issue.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;[[George Washington]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1847&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Jefferson3b 1856-5c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;[[Thomas Jefferson]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; Issue of 1856&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson2 1862 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;[[Andrew Jackson]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;[[Black Jack (stamp)|Issue of 1863]]&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln 1866 Issue-15c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;[[Abraham Lincoln]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1866&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The First Washington postage stamp. The 5-cent Franklin and the 10-cent Washington postage stamps issued in 1847 were the first postage stamps issued and authorized for postal duty by the US Post Office. The firm of Rawdon, Wright, Hatch, and Edson of [[New York City]] were given a four year contract to print the first US Postage stamps in 1847. The initials: &quot;RWH&amp;E&quot; are clearly engraved at the bottom of both stamps. The engraving of Washington is identical to the one by the portrait engraver Asher Brown Durand on a Bank-Note issued by Fairfield County Bank of Connecticut, during a period when many banks issued their own forms of paper currency. &lt;ref name=&quot;1847usa&quot;/&gt;  Both the Washington and Franklin issues were reprinted in 1875 with subtle variations in the engravings. &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

* In March 1856 the Post Office issued the first postage stamp to feature [[Thomas Jefferson]]. The exact date of issue is not clear. ''Scott's US postage stamp catalog'' establishes the release date with the first known use of this issue, March 24 of 1856. The first issue of this stamp was in imperforate form, engraved and printed by Toppan, Carpenter, Casilear &amp; Co. The Jefferson issue saw postal duty from the spring of 1856 to the summer of 1857. The engraving of Jefferson was modeled after a portrait of the President by [[Gilbert Stuart]]. By mid-1857 the stamps were issued with the top and bottom design projections omitted and with perforations. This printing was issued in at least six major color variations. &lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* On July 1 of 1863 the U.S. Post Office issued the 2 cent Jackson stamp, commonly referred to by collectors as the '[[Black Jack (stamp)|Black-Jack]]' stamp. Printed by the [[National Bank Note Company]], it was released on the same day the new drop letter rate (the fee for mail delivered within city limits) was raised to two cents. &lt;ref&gt;Scotts United States Stamp Catalogue: Domestic Letter rates&lt;/ref&gt; Jackson is the third U.S. president to be honored on U.S. Postage. &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

* On April 14, 1866, exactly one year after Lincoln's assassination in 1865, the US Post Office issued its first postage stamp honoring the fallen President. The engraving of Lincoln was rendered by Joseph Ourdan after a photograph by C.S.German. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!--

==Presidential issue of 1938==
[[File:Presidential issue-1938.jpg|thumb|300px|&lt;center&gt;~Presidential issues of 1938]]
In 1933 President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] who was an accomplished stamp collector himself, presented the idea of a series of postage stamps that would honor all the past presidents of the United States. The idea proved popular and a national contest was held to determine the artist who would be commissioned to design the 1st stamp of this series, the 1-cent George Washington issue. There were over twelve hundred works of art submitted a number of them from famous artists. An artist from New York, Elaine Rawlinson, won the contest.  Her design for the 1-cent Washington stamp was modeled after a bust of Washington’s profile by the famous sculptor [[Jean Antoine Houdin]]. There was much debate and discussion over what designs would ultimately be used for all of the engravings on this series of 32 issues. In 1937 after design competition for the various issues took place a decision was finally made and the new definitive series was issued in 1938. &lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2033221 '''Smithsonian National Postal Museum''']&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}
--&gt;

==George Washington==
[[File:Washington Head2 W-F.jpg|thumb|240px|&lt;center&gt;~ ''Washington ~&lt;/center&gt;
----
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;As there are no photographs of Washington and his portraits usually hang in halls or museums, or tucked away in history books, this is the profile, found on several issues of US Postage stamps, that most Americans came to know Washington's appearance by.  The engraving was modeled after a bust of Washington by renowned French sculptor [[Jean Antoine Houdon]].&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]
[[George Washington]] (February 22, 1732 – December 14, 1799) was the first President of the United States, serving from 1789 to 1797, and before this served as the commander of the [[Continental Army]] in the [[American Revolutionary War]] from 1775 to 1783. The [[Electoral College (United States)|Electoral College]] elected Washington unanimously in [[United States presidential election, 1789|1789]], and again in the [[United States presidential election, 1792|1792 election]]; To this day George Washington remains the only American president to have received 100 percent of the electoral votes. Washington took his oath of office while standing on the balcony of [[Federal Hall]] on Wall Street in New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhiteHouseArchives&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/ |title=White House, Washington DC, Presidential Archives |publisher=Whitehouse.gov |date=2010-10-01 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.americaslibrary.gov/cgi-bin/page.cgi/aa/wash |title=George Washington |publisher=[[Library of Congress]] |accessdate=June 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The chronology of presidents on U.S. postage begins with George Washington. Near the end of Washington's second term as president, [[Martha Washington]] commissioned the well-known portrait artist [[Gilbert Stuart]] to paint both her portrait and the [[commons:File:Gilbert Stuart 003.jpg|president's]]. Stuart was known for the length of time it took him to complete a painting, and consequently neither the president nor his wife ever saw the finished paintings. The two portraits remained unfinished and tacked to a door in Stuart's Boston studio until his death in 1828.  In 1860 artist [[Rembrandt Peale]] [[commons:File:Gilbert Stuart Williamstown Portrait of George Washington.jpg|finished Stuart's work]], filling in where this artist had left off. Stewart's portrait of Washington &lt;ref&gt;This is Stuart's most famous and celebrated portrayal of Washington, known as 'The Athenaeum', which, was used to model the engravings on US one dollar bill and various Postage stamps of the 19th and 20th centuries.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gilbertstuartmuseum.com/ Gilbert Stuart Birthplace and Museum] ''Gilbert Stuart Biography''&lt;/ref&gt; became the model image for a good number of postage issues of the 19th and 20th centuries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alexander T. Haimann |url=http://www.arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2027665 |title=Smithsonian National Postal Museum, 1861 Issues |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date=2006-05-22 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

: George Washington remains the central figure found on US postage over the last 160 and more years. The first president appears on the face of U.S. postage more than any other American president. The engraved images of Washington found on the early issues set the precedent that all US Postage issues would follow in the following decades. Indeed, in virtually every U. S. definitive stamp series offered between 1851 and 1932, Washington appeared on the normal letter-rate value (the only exception being the shortlived 1869 pictorial issue); other presidents, statesmen and famous Americans were confined to the less commonly used denominations. Since the first U.S. postage stamp was issued by the US Post Office there have been more examples of George Washington appearing on US postage than all other American Presidents combined, including [[Thomas Jefferson]], [[Andrew Jackson]], [[Abraham Lincoln]] and even the frequently honored [[Benjamin Franklin]] (who was not President). &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; Examples of all the various Washington stamps are too numerous to include in this section, as many of the issues are very similar with only differences in color and denomination, such as the [[Washington-Franklin Issues|Washington-Franklin issues]]. Featured below are the issues that are unique in their designs and the most definitive.

===Classic period===
Postage stamp designs of this period were typically taken from paintings and other works by famous artists, that set the precedent for stamp designs in the ensuing years of American stamp production. Engravers from this period typically used the works of [[John Trumbull]], [[Gilbert Stuart]] and [[Jean Antoine Houdon]] as models for their engravings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2028276   Smithsonian National Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1851 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1851/57&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1851 Issue-12c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1851&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1855 Issue1-10c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1855&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:24centW.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1860&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1860 Issue-90c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1860&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On July 1, 1851, the US Post Office issued a 3-cent Postage stamp. Because of die recuts, double transfers from die to plate and different paper used for its printing, this issue comes in numerous varieties. The authoritative book on the issue, 'Classic US Stamps 1845-1869' was written by Carroll Chase, published in 1962. Engraving of image taken from a sculpture by [[Jean Antoine Houdon]]. The Post Office did not produce perforated versions of this stamp until 1857.

* The Post Office released the 12-cent Washington of August 4 of 1851. The engraving of Washington is modeled after a portrait by [[Gilbert Stuart]]. When the 12c issue was printed the stamp was the highest US denomination ever issued. The issue was printed by Toppan, Carpenter, Casilear &amp; Co.

* In 1855 postage for mail bound for destinations over 3,000&amp;nbsp;miles increased the cost of Postage from 6-cents to 10-cents and prompted the issue of the 1855 10c Washington stamp. This 10c green issue was printed by Toppan, Carpenter, Casilear &amp; Co. who reused the engraving of Washington (the vignette) of the 12-cent Washington 1851 Issue for this 10-cent postage stamp. Engraving was modeled after Gilbert Stuart's portrait of Washington.

* In 1857 printing plates were made for a 24-cent Washington issue, but the stamp itself was not produced until 1860; the earliest known date of usage is July 7.

* On August 13 of 1860 the Post Office issued the Washington 90c issue. Washington's engraving was modeled after a portrait by [[John Trumbull]], named [[John Trumbull#Middle years|'George Washington Before the Battle of Trenton']], painted in 1792. It was only issued in the year 1860 and because of its high denomination only 29,000 copies were made and surviving examples are scarce. There were very few occasions where the amount of postage required to mail an item cost as much as 90c and as such genuinely postally used examples of this issue are worth about twice as much as unused specimens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

===Civil War era===
[[Abraham Lincoln]] assumed office in March 1861 and just one month later the Confederate forces fired on [[Fort Sumter]] which marked the beginning of the [[American Civil War]].  Issued only months after the [[Battle of Fort Sumter]], no other series of stamps issued during the Classic Period has such an important connection to American history as the 1861 National Bank Note Company Issues. Washington occurs five times in this series, Franklin occurs twice and Jefferson once.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:George Washington2 1861 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|180px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington Pair22 1861 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|330px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The Post Office released the 10c Washington green issue on August 20 of 1861. Washington's portrayal was engraved by [[William Marshall]] who employed [[Gilbert Stuart]]'s unfinished portrait of the first American president for his model.&lt;ref name=&quot;1847usa&quot;&gt;[http://1847usa.com/ByYear/1861.htm 1847USA]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 3c Washington of this series was issued on August 19, 1861. The engraved imagery was modeled after a bust of Washington by French sculptor [[Jean Antoine Houdon]].

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:George Washington 1861 Issue-12c.jpg|thumb|170px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1862 Issue-24c.jpg|Issue of 1862|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1862&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1861 Issue-90c.jpg|thumb|170px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* 12c Washington issue of 1861.  The National Bank Note Company was founded in 1859, and William Marshall was one of the first portrait engravers hired. By early 1860, Marshall was given the task of engraving Washington's portrayal for the 1861 Issue. He was sent to Boston to use Gilbert Stuart’s portrait painting of George Washington as his model for the new engraving.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=John&amp;nbsp;Birkinbine |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2027672 |title=Smithsonian, Washington issue of 1861 |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date=2006-05-22 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 1832 24c lilac was issued January 7, 1862. The engraving was taken from same Gilbert Stuart painting. The engraver was William Marshall, the same artist who produced the 10 and 12 cent Washington 1861 Issues. William D. Nichols and Cyrus Durand (inventor of the machine used to produce intricate lathe work in engravings) was the engraver of the stamp's frame work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;img=&amp;mode=1&amp;pg=1&amp;tid=2027719 , 1862 issues, National Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 90c Washington issue was issued in the last two weeks in August 1861 to only several post offices. The earliest known use on cover is November 27, 1861. The engraving of Washington was taken from the same John Trumbull portrait as was the issue of 1861.

[[File:Washington 1869 Issue22-6c.jpg|thumb|170px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1869&lt;/center&gt;]]

:::* In 1869 the ill-fated 'pictorial issue' was released. Most of the stamp issues from this series featured scenes of various sorts. The Washington stamp of this series was criticized as much as the others but for its plain graphic features, like the checker background in the vigenette.  The stamp format was designed by E. Pitcher while the engraving was modeled after a Gilbert Stuart portrait of Washington.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* George Washington is also found on an 1863 [[Postage stamps and postal history of the Confederate States|Civil War issue]] of the Confederate States.
{{clear}}

===Post Civil War===
[[File:Bust of George Washington by Houdon.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;~ Bust of Washington ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;''by Jean Antoine Houdon''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;This sculpture served as the model for Washington engravings on a variety of postage issues of the late 19th century&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]
The ending of the American Civil War marked a beginning in US stamp subject and design change.  The Union victory brought with it a strong American nationalism among the populace throughout the north and much of the country. This national sentiment was largely responsible for the various Civil War figures to appear on US Postage. Up until 1869 with the one exception of Benjamin Franklin only American presidents were found on US Postage. In April 1870, however, the images of Henry Clay, Daniel Webster, Winfield Scott, Alexander Hamilton and Oliver Hazzard Perry appeared on new the 12¢, 15¢, 24¢, 30¢ and 90¢ stamps, and the following year [[Edwin M. Stanton]], the US Secretary of War under the Lincoln, appeared on a [[:File:Stanton 1871-7c.jpg|7-cent postage stamp]].
&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot; Post Civil War Nationalism&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.postalmuseum.si.edu/symposium2010/abstracts.html |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |title= Post Civil War Nationalism and the Designs of United States Stamps in the Nineteenth Century |author=Steven R. Boyd, Ph.D.
Professor of History, University of Texas at San Antonio |accessdate=18 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''1870s'''

The postage issued in the US during this time was printed by the [[National Bank Note Company]] (NBNCo) on white wove paper. The first printing was issued with 'grills', tiny cuts in the paper to absorb ink. Later reprintings were issued without grilling. The [[National Bank Note Company]]’s contract expired in 1873, and the [[Continental Bank Note Company]] (CBNC) won the contract to continue printing the series and took over some of the dies and plates used by NBNCo. The new printer employed secret marks to distinguish their work from the first printing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
The green Washington 3¢ issue was printed in such large quantities that postally used examples remain inexpensive to this day, from pennies to a few dollars, depending on type of cancellation and condition. (The green variety was reprinted again by the [[American Bank Note Company]] (AmBNC), also in very large quantities, and issued on July 16, 1881.) The 3-cent Washington design was printed yet a fourth time, in vermillion, in 1887. The 3-cent issues paid the domestic letter rate for a half-ounce letter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

The profile image of George Washington found on various postage issues of the late 19th century and early 20th century is modeled after a bust of Washington by the renowned sculptor [[Jean-Antoine Houdon]]. Several engravers of presidential portraits on US Postage have modeled their engravings after Houdon's sculptures.

{{clear}}

&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;'''~ Large Bank Notes of the 1870s ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:George Washington 1870 Issue33-3c.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1870&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;NBNCo&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;Engraving taken from bust by [[Jean Antoine Houdon]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;Jean Antoine Houdon's portrait sculpture of Washington was the result of a specific invitation from Benjamin Franklin to come to the United States so that Washington could model for him. Washington sat for wet clay life models and a plaster life mask in 1785.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mountvernon.org/visit/plan/index.cfm/pid/238/ |title=Mount Vernon Estate : archives |publisher=Mountvernon.org |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; These models served for many commissions of Washington and eventually were used as models for the engravings of Washington on several US Postage issues of the 1870s, 1880s and 1890s.
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington3 1870 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1887&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;(reprint of 1870 issue)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;!---
&lt;td&gt;[[file:xxx|thumb|170px|&lt;center&gt;name&lt;/center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:11pt&quot;&gt;Issue of 18xx&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]
--&gt;

'''1880s'''

In 1883 the [[United States Postal Service|US Post Office]] reduced the first-class letter rate from 3 cents to 2 cents for a half-ounce letter mailed within the continental United States, which the [[US Congress]] approved on March 3, 1883, effective October 1, 1883.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.stamps.org/directories/dir_qnausrates.htm |title=American Philatelic Society |publisher=Stamps.org |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Post Office immediately issued a 2 cent Washington stamp, so that the First President's image would remain visible on normal letters.
&lt;center&gt;'''~ American Bank Note Company ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;Engraving taken from bust by [[Jean Antoine Houdon]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington4 1883 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|165px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1883&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington CV 1883 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|147px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1883&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington2 1887Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|147px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1887&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

'''1890s'''

Stamp issues during the 1890s were first printed by the [[American Bank Note Company]] in 1890 and then by the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]] in 1894.  The image for both issues was produced by an engraving that was modeled after a bust of Washington by sculptor [[Jean Antoine Houdon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

[[File:George Washington 1890 Issue Lake-2c.jpg|thumb|left|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1890&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Washington 1895 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1895&lt;/center&gt;]]

* The American Bank Note 1890 issue, 2c, lake variety, Washington stamp (left) was issued on February 22, 1890, becoming the first stamp to be issued on a president's birthday.

* Bureau of Engraving and Printing issues, struck from the same dies as the ABN 1890 issues with minor changes in the frame work, three different styled triangles, known to collectors as the 'Bureau Triangles'. The 2c Washington paid the letter domestic letter rate and was printed in such large quantities that numerous color variations exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
{{clear}}

===Turn of the 19th - 20th centuries===

At the turn of the 20th century, [[George Washington]] continued to be the most prominent subject depicted on the face of US postage stamps. Washington would remain the most prevalent figure on US Postage for most of the 20th century.  Only [[Benjamin Franklin]] whose image also appears on numerous US postage is second to Washington for the simple reason that Franklin is depicted on the numerous denominations of the Washington-Franklin series almost as often as Washington.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wash'Frank-Armstrong&quot;&gt;Washington Franklins 1908 - 1921, 1979 by Martin Armstrong&lt;/ref&gt; Ironically, George Washington does not appear on a Commemorative issue until 1925 where he is featured on a [[commons:file:Washington at Cambridge 1925 Issue-2c.jpg|stamp]] commemorating another historical event.

[[File:Wash3.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;!--
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:Wash3.jpg|thumb|left|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[Image:George Washington2 1903 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|left|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
--&gt;
::* Issued on January 17, 1903 the 2c carmine red Washington postage stamp was issued by the US Post Office. The engraving of Washington was inspired and modeled after a painting by [[Gilbert Stuart]] which features a one quarter left image of Washington. R. Ostrander Smith designed the stamp. The vignette with its two American flags is often referred to as the Washington 'Flag' stamp.  Washington's portrait was engraved by George F. C. Smillie who has engraved a variety of stamp images for the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]]. The 1903 issue is one among the second series of stamp issues that were produced that year by the Bureau.

[[File:George Washington2 1903 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
::* On November 12th of 1903 the Post Office, because of public dissatisfaction with the 1903 2-cent Washington 'Flag' stamp, a new 2-cent stamp was issued featuring Washington’s portrait within a shield of stars and stripes. Often referred to as the 2-cent Washington 'Shield' stamp, this issue was released on November the 12th of 1903. Along with the shield background, the left numeral is enclosed with laurel leaves while the number on the right is surrounded with oak leaves, symbolizing Washington’s role as president in peace time and as general in times of war. Like the first 2c stamp of 1903 this issues was designed by [[Clair Aubrey Huston]] from a painting by [[Gilbert Stuart]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; The engraving of Washington was done by George F. C. Smillie.  The Washington 'Shield' stamp is recognized for its many shade varieties, as collectors have distinguished over a hundred shades of this particular issue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

{{clear}}

===The Washington - Franklin Issues===

[[File:Washington-1c and Franklin-1c.jpg|thumb|300px|&lt;center&gt;''~ The Washington - Franklin Issue ~''&lt;/center&gt;]]

The Washington Franklin Issues were unique in the sense that these subjects were the only ones found on definitive stamps for more than a decade. Beginning in 1908 the Washington Franklin definitive stamps were issued over a twelve-year period in denominations that occurred from 'One-Cent' to [[commons:file:Benjamin Franklin 2-Big-Bens 1918 Issue.jpg|Five-Dollars]], with different colors for each denomination, all with the same engraved profile of Washington or Franklin. While both Washington and Franklin occur on the 1-cent values, both in green, they are usually found on their own set of denominations, depending on which series they occurred in.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wash'Frank-Armstrong&quot;/&gt;  In the first issue, Franklin appeared only on the one-cent value, while the same Washington image graced the remaining eleven denominations, which ranged from two cents to one dollar.  In later issues, Washington was present only on the seven denominations between one cent and seven cents, and all the higher values were assigned to Franklin. The engraving of Washington was modeled after a bust by the renowned sculptor [[Jean Antoine Houdon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;  The few examples exhibited here are largely representative of this greater series. Franklin is displayed once here for general reference to the Washington - Franklin issues. &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:9pt&quot;&gt;See main article: [[Washington-Franklin Issues]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Wash Frank 1908 Issue-Two-Cent.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1908&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington WF 1917 Issue-7c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1917&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Wash Frank 1909 Issue-$1.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1909&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On January 29, 1909, the US Post Office issued the 1-dollar Washington Head stamp. It was the last of the first issue of Washington-Franklin stamps to appear.  The stamp remained on sale at Post Offices for more than three years before being replaced by a Franklin head 1-dollar stamp in 1916.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wash'Frank-Armstrong&quot;/&gt; The One-Dollar stamp is the highest denomination Washington is depicted with. The Two and Five Dollar denominations are on stamps that honor Franklin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-WF&quot;&gt;Scotts Specialized Catalogue of United States Stamps, Washington - Franklin Issues&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:WF Washington 1911 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|272px|center|&lt;center&gt;[[Washington-Franklin Issues#Coil stamps|Washington on coil stamps]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;issue of 1911&lt;/center&gt;]]

The denominations for the various year issues can be viewed on the [[Template:Washington-Franklin Issue|Washington-Franklin issues chart]].

===Washington on commemorative issues===

While [[George Washington]] dominated as the subject of US postage issues from the beginning, he did not appear on a [[Commemorative stamp|commemorative issue]] until 1925, some 21 years after the U.S. Post office issued the first presidential commemorative stamp honoring [[Thomas Jefferson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;&gt;Scotts Specialized Catalogue of United States Stamps: Commemorative Index&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington at Cambridge 1925 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|250px|&lt;center&gt;Washington at [[Battles of Lexington and Concord|Cambridge&lt;/center&gt;]]&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington at Prayer 1928 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;[[Valley Forge|Washington at Prayer&lt;/center&gt;]]&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1928&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington at Brooklyn 1951 Issue-3cjpg.jpg|thumb|250px|&lt;center&gt;Washington at [[Battle of Brooklyn|Brooklyn]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1951&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On the 1-cent stamp portraying the [[Battle of Lexington and Concord|Lexington - Concord issue of 1925]], Washington is shown leading the Massachusetts Militia at Cambridge against [[Thomas Gage|General Gage]] and the [[British regulars]]. This series was the first of many commemoratives celebrating the 150th anniversary of important events of the [[American Revolution]]. Like most issues of this period, this issue was printed by the Bureau of Engraving and Printing.

[[File:Washington taking Oath 1939 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Washington takes [[George Washington#Presidency|Oath]]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1939&lt;/center&gt;]]
* This [[commons:file:Two Cent Reds 150th Anniv.jpg|'2-cent red']] postage stamp was issued on May 26, 1928. This commemorative honored the 150th anniversary of George Washington at Valley Forge and depicts him kneeling in prayer before the battle.

* The US Post Office issued a 3-cent commemorative stamp, first issued at Brooklyn, New York, on December 10, 1951, to commemorate the 175th anniversary of the [[Battle of Brooklyn]]. The stamp portrays the evacuation of General Washington's troops from Brooklyn at the site of the Fulton Ferry House, with an accurate depiction of the house and the flat-bottomed ferries used to cross the East River.

* On April 30, 1789, President Washington took the oath of President of the United States. On the 150th anniversary of his inauguration, April 30, 1939, the US Post Office issued a 3c commemorative stamp celebrating this landmark historical event. The engraving depicts Washington standing on the balcony of the [[Federal Hall#Historic building|Federal Hall]] in New York reciting the oath of office.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhiteHouseArchives&quot;/&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Yorktown 1931 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|240px|&lt;center&gt;Battle of Yorktown&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1931&lt;center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington Green2 Army Issue 1937-1c.jpg|thumb|240px|&lt;center&gt;~ Washington ~ Green ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1937&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

* The 2-cent stamp issued on October 19, 1931, marked the 150th anniversary of the [[Battle of Yorktown]] (1781). This issue depicts Washington with Count de Rochambeau and Count de Grasse at his right and left, leaders of the French forces that aided in the victory of the [[American Revolution]].
[[File:Washington Valley Forge2 1977-13c.jpg|thumb|148px|&lt;center&gt;Christmas Issue, &lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;1977&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]
* The 1-cent Army Issue of December 15, 1936, features George Washington's home at [[Mount Vernon]] as its central design. Portraits of Washington and [[Nathanael Greene]] appear on either side of the image of Mount Vernon. Greene was one of Washington's most valued generals in the Revolutionary War.

* The 13-cent stamp Christmas Issue commemorates the 200th anniversary of Washington's army at [[Valley Forge]], and was based on the [[J. C. Leyendecker]] painting “George Washington at Valley Forge.” Leyendecker's painting first appeared on the cover of the [[Saturday Evening Post]] on February 23, 1935. The stamp was designed by Steven Dohanos. The stamp was first available on October 21, 1977, at Valley Forge, Pennsylvania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; {{clear}}

===Washington's 200th anniversary===
On January 1, 1932, in celebration of [[George Washington]]'s 200th anniversary of birth, the U.S. Post Office released its Washington Bicentennial Issue, a series of twelve postage stamps each with a different portrait of Washington. Each engraved portrayal was modeled from a different painting by an early American artist who portrayed Washington at different periods in his life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;  Engravings of Washington often depict his profile. In the 1932 Bi-Centennial anniversary series there are two issues that show Washington in profile, one depicting either sides of Washington's face. Information regarding quantities issued can be found on the [[1932 Washington Bicentennial|Washington Bicentennial Issue]] page.
[[File:Washington Bicentennial 1932 Issue2.jpg|thumb|center|800px|&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:12pt&quot;&gt;~ Washington Bicentennial issue of 1932 ~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]

The Washington Bicentennial issues of 1932 are the first commemorative postage stamps ever issued by the US Post Office that honor and depict George Washington by himself, and not in conjunction with other people, places and events as is the case with the [[commons:File:Washington3commemorative.jpg|three commemoratives]] with Washington's image issued before 1932. &lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt; It should be noted that the 2-cent Washington in this series total 4.2 billion stamps, a total that remains the largest stamp printing of a single issue ever to occur in U.S. Postal history. &lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2033008 Washington Bicentenial, Smithsonian National Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Washington issues, middle 20th century===

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:George Washington 1923 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|137px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1923&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1938 Issue2-1c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1954 Issue2-1c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1954&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1962 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|127px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1962&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Washington 1966 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1966&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On January 15 of 1923 the US Post Office issued another 2c red Washington postage stamp as part of its new definitive series, thus continuing the tradition of honoring Washington on every day use postage. An existing engraving of Washington made for use on the Washington-Franklin issue was used. That engraving, done by Marcus Baldwin, was modeled from a bust made by Clark Mills in 1853 which however was a reproduction of a bust sculpted by [[Jean Antoine Houdon]] at Washington’s [[Mount Vernon]], Virginia, home in 1785. [[Clair Aubrey Huston]] designed the stamp's frame, which was engraved by Edward M. Hall and Joachim C. Benzing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; [[File:720.jpg|right|thumb|100px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1932&lt;/center&gt;]] After the increase of the normal letter-rate from 2 cents to 3 cents in 1932, the public, for the first time in sixty years, no longer had a definitive Washington stamp for its daily correspondence.  Rather than converting the 1923 definitive stamp to the new rate, the Post Office redesigned the 2 cent Washington Bicentennial value as a 3 cent stamp. 

* On April 25 of 1938 the US Post Office issued a green 1-cent [[George Washington]] stamp. It was the first stamp of the famous [[:File:Presidential issue-1938.jpg|Presidential Series of 1938]], an issue that placed all of the deceased presidents in numerical order, and thus represented a break with the long-standing tradition of reserving the normal letter-rate definitive stamp for Washington. Instead, this Washington issue saw postal duty carrying postcards and letters through the late 1950s. The 1938 Presidential issue was [[Franklin D. Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]]'s idea. An avid stamp collector, Roosevelt suggested a set of stamps that would pay tribute to the various past American presidents. In 1937, after much debate, a new definitive series was issued using Roosevelt's ideas. A national contest was held, with over 1200 entries submitted, a young New York City art student's entry was chosen for the Washington stamp design. The student's name was Elaine Rawlinson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

*  The US Post Office released the 1-cent Washington stamp on August 26 of 1954 at the Post Office in Chicago, Illinois. The engraving of George Washington was modeled from a portrait by [[Gilbert Stuart]] (1755–1828).  It was designed by Charles R. Chickering, who produced his own drawing from a photograph he obtained from the National Gallery. The portrait of Washington was engraved by Richard M. Bower of the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]].

* On November 23, 1962 the Post office issued the 5-cent Washington stamp, first issued through the New York, New York, post office . Designed by William K. Schrage, the engraving of Washington, like several other engravings of this president, is based on a bust of Washington sculptured in 1785 by Jean Houdon.

* On August 19 of 1994 the Post Office issued a 5-dollar Washington-Jackson stamp in Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, at the American Philatelic Society's annual stamp exposition. The stamp was modeled after a design created in 1869 by the [[National Bank Note Company]] It was originally prepared but never was used for the 1869 US postage series. The central image or vignette features a portrait of George Washington and Andrew Jackson. The portrayals of Washington and Jackson were engraved through the intaglio process by Stamp Venturers, Inc., and issued in small sheets of twenty stamps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

===Washington, recent issues===
[[File:George Washington 1982 Issue3-20c.jpg|thumb|left|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1982&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Washington Purple Heart 2001 Issue-44c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 2001&lt;/center&gt;]]
In recent years, Washington has appeared much less frequently on US Postage stamps than he did during 19th and early 20th centuries. In the beginning of postage stamp issuance new issues were few and only presidents were found on US Postage, with the well liked exception of Ben Franklin. In recent days, issues are many and a whole array of various individuals are now found on US Postage stamps. The Post Office has been both admired and criticized for this practice.{{clear}}

* In 2001, Washington appeared on a red-brown 20-cent definitive stamp, and the same Washington image was used that year for a 23-cent definitive stamp in dark green

* The original [[Purple Heart]], designated as the [[Badge of Military Merit]], was established by [[George Washington]] then the [[commander-in-chief]] of the [[Continental Army]] on August 7, 1782.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mountvernon.org/visit/plan/index.cfm/pid/767/ Mount Vernon Estate &amp; Gardens]&lt;/ref&gt; The actual order includes the phrase, &quot;Let it be known that he who wears the military order of the purple heart has given of his blood in the defense of his homeland and shall forever be revered by his fellow countrymen.&quot; It is Washington's profile that adorns the Purple Heart, and the US Postage issue that honors them both. -- On April 28, 2009, in Washington, DC, the US Postal Service reissued the [[Purple Heart Medal|Purple Heart]] definitive stamp in a denomination of forty-four cents. Carl T. Herrman of Carlsbad, California, designed the stamp. The stamp had been previously issued in the following years: 2008, 42-cent: 2007, 41-cent: 2006, 39-cent: 2003, 37-cent. Designed by Carl T. Herrman, the stamp depicts an image of the Purple Heart medal with Washington in profile.&lt;ref&gt;USPS Postal Bulletin (April 10, 2008)&lt;/ref&gt; A similar image of the Washington purple heart medal appeared on a &quot;forever&quot; stamp issued on May 5, 2011.

* On April 11, 2011, the postal service issued a 20-cent stamp bearing a color reproduction the famous Washington portrait by Gilbert Stuart. 

* On the 250th anniversary of George Washington's birth a 20-cent commemorative stamp was issued February 22, 1982, at Mount Vernon, Virginia, in commemoration. The First Day of Issue ceremony was held in the Mount Vernon Inn at Washington's Mount Vernon estate.&lt;ref name=&quot;George Washington&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;img=&amp;mode=1&amp;pg=1&amp;tid=2038313 |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |title=George Washington 1982 Issue |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The designer, Mark English, of Kansas City, Missouri, based his design on a stylistic portrait depicting the distinctive Washington profile. 

* Washington also appears on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX Presidential issue]] of 1986.

==John Adams==
[[File:John Adams 1938 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[John Adams]] (October 30, 1735 – July 4, 1826) was the second President of the United States serving from 1797 to 1801, after being the first Vice President of the United States (1789–1797) for two terms. He was one of the most influential Founding Fathers of the United States. Adams came to prominence in the early stages of the [[American Revolution]]. As a delegate from Massachusetts to the Continental Congress, he played a leading role in convincing Congress to declare independence, and assisted Thomas Jefferson in drafting the United States Declaration of Independence in 1776.  Adams and Jefferson died on the same day, Thursday, July 4, 1826.

:::* The engraved portrayal of Adams (1735-1826) appears on the 2-cent value of the [[:File:Presidential issue-1938.jpg|1938 Presidential Series]], issued on June 3, 1938. [[Daniel Chester French]]'s marble 1889 bust of Adams displayed in the US Capitol's Senate Gallery was the model used for the engraving of Adams.

* Adams also appears on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX Presidential issue]] of 1986.
{{clear}}

==Thomas Jefferson==
[[File:Jefferson 1861 Die Proof2.jpg|Issue of 1861|thumb|245px|&lt;center&gt;~ Jefferson ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;[[Die proof (philately)|Die Proof]] 1861]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;Thomas Jefferson (April 13, 1743 – July 4, 1826) was the third President of the United States Serving from 1801 to 1809, and the principal author of the Declaration of Independence. Jefferson was one of the most prominent ad influential Founding Fathers. As president he oversaw major events that included the [[Louisiana Purchase]] in 1803 and the [[Lewis and Clark Expedition]] in 1804 &amp;ndash; 1806.

[[Thomas Jefferson]]'s likeness over the years has been finely depicted on the face of the various postage issues that honored him.  The first issue to depict Jefferson was issued in 1856, [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#First appearances|(displayed above)]] nine years after the Post Office issued its first two stamps of [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States#First stamps|Washington and Franklin]] in 1847.  (Before this time hand-stamps were used to mark and confirm payment of postage.)  Almost as popular and famous as [[George Washington]], Jefferson appears comparatively less often on US postage issues, and unlike [[George Washington|Washington]] and [[Benjamin Franklin|Franklin]], appears on just two [[List of people on stamps of the United States|commemorative issues]], one in 1904, displayed below), the other on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986. All others occurrences depict him on [[Definitive stamp|regular issues]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;

* On August 19, 1861, while the American Civil War was wreaking havoc across Virginia and elsewhere, the US Post office issued a 5c Postage stamp that honored Thomas Jefferson. The engraving used to produce the image was modeled after the famous portrait artist [[Gilbert Stuart]]. The engraver for this issue was William Marshall who also engraved Washington's image for several other issues of this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;1847usa&quot;/&gt; That year, Jefferson became the first U. S. President to appear on a Confederate stamp: a 10c value in blue, reissued in 1862 with its color changed to rose-pink.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1861 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1861&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1870 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|138px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1870&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson33 1890 Issue-30c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1890&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1894 Issue-50c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1894&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On August 19, 1861 the U.S. Post Office released the second postage stamp honoring Jefferson, a 5-cent buff (yellow-brown) colored issue, modeled after Gilbert Stuart's portrait of this president. This issue occurs in several distinct shades of brown. This image was again [[:File:Jefferson 1863 issue-5c.jpg|reprinted]] on February 3, 1863 in a dark brown color.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

* On April 12 of 1870, the third Postage stamp issued by the US Post Office to honor Thomas Jefferson was issued. The 10c stamp issue was printed by the [[National Bank Note Company]]. In 1859 the renown sculptor [[Hiram Powers]] was commissioned by the US government to create two life-size marble statues to be placed in the United States Capitol building. One was of Benjamin Franklin the other was of Thomas Jefferson, completed in 1863.  This was the image Powers used to model his engraving of Jefferson on the 10c issue of 1870.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/art/artifact/Sculpture_21_00008.htm |title=United States Senate : Art and History |publisher=Senate.gov |date=2009-03-26 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Issued on February 22, 1890 the U.S. Post office released a 30c postage stamp that once again honored Thomas Jefferson.  The engraver and artist [[Alfred Jones (engraver)|Alfred Jones]] (1819–1900) created the image of Jefferson that appears on the issue.  Jones was noted for his  engraved portraits and historic scenes during his time at [[American Bank Note Company]].

* On November 1, 1894, the first 50c definitive Postage stamp was issued. It was among a series of issues that was first printed by the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]]. Its design is based on that of the 30c black issue of 1890 that depicts the same engraved image of Thomas Jefferson by [[Alfred Jones (engraver)|Alfred Jones]]. Almost identical in design, it is readily distinguished by its orange color, and by the triangles in the upper corners.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Jefferson 1903 Issue-50c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1923 Issue-9c.jpg|Issue of 1923|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1923&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1938 Issue-3c.jpg|Issue of 1938|thumb|136px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The second 50-cent orange stamp depicting Thomas Jefferson was issued March 23, 1903. The stamp was designed by R. Ostrander Smith from the 1805 a portrait of Jefferson by Gilbert Stuart. Jefferson's portrait was engraved by George F. C. Smillie.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* Absent, of course, from the Washington-Franklin series, Jefferson returned to US postage in the next definitive series (1923), depicted on a nine-cent stamp designed by [[Clair Aubrey Huston]]. Huston reused George F.C. Simille’s engraving of Jefferson, which had appeared on the 2-cent value of the 1904 Louisiana Purchase Exposition Series. (The model for Simille's engraving was a portrait of Jefferson painted by [[Gilbert Stuart]] in 1805). Simille’s engraving was  transferred to a new die and restored by Bureau engravers John Eissler and Leo Kauffmann for use on the 1923 Jefferson issue.

* Jefferson appears on the 3-cent [[:File:Presidential issue of 1932.jpg|Presidential issue of 1938]].

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson Regular Issues 1954-2c.jpg|Issue of 1954|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1954&lt;center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson Regular Issue 1968-1c.jpg|Issue of 1968|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1968&lt;center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1993 Issue-29c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1993&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On September 15, 1954, the 2-cent Jefferson stamp from the [[Liberty Issue]] was introduced at Post Offices in San Francisco, California. The postcard rate went to 2 cents on the day of this issue was released so the stamp was very common among the mail for that reason. The engraving of Jefferson was taken from a portrait by [[Gilbert Stuart]] which hangs in the [[Bowdoin College Museum of Art]] in Brunswick, Maine.

* The 1-cent green stamp was issued January 12, 1968, at Jeffersonville, Indiana. The issue was designed by Robert Geissmann, modeled after a 1800 portrait of Jefferson by [[Rembrandt Peale]] which now hangs in the Blue Room of the White House.  Edward R. Felver crafted the engraving of Jefferson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* The US Post office issued the 29-cent Thomas Jefferson definitive stamp on April 13, 1993, in Charlottesville, Virginia. The stamp engraving features a portrait of Jefferson and is part of the [[Great Americans series]]. The stamp issue was designed by Christopher Calle while the die for the stamp was engraved by Stamp Venturers, Inc.

===Jefferson on commemorative issue===
Another oddity of US Postage is the fact that [[Thomas Jefferson]] up until recently only appeared on one US commemorative issue, which was released in 1904. It was the first commemorative issue to ever honor a U.S. President.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;
&lt;Center&gt;'''The First Presidential Commemorative'''&lt;/center&gt;
[[File:Thomas Jefferson 1904 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|center|280px|&lt;center&gt;~ Classic engraving of Jefferson ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;[[Louisiana Purchase]] Exposition&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1904.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;]]

* Unlike with the [[Definitive stamp|regular issues]] Jefferson was the first American President to be honored on a commemorative postage issue, even before Washington was when the US Post Office 21 years later finally issued its first [[Commemorative stamp|commemorative issue]] featuring Washington in its [[Battles of Lexington and Concord|Lexington-Concord]] issue of 1925.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;

* The last issue to honor Jefferson to date was a 22-cent commemorative  [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] released in 1986.

==James Madison==
[[James Madison]], 4th President of the United States, served from 1809–1817) and is considered one of the [[Founding Fathers of the United States]] and also the  &quot;Father of the Constitution&quot; as Madison was the principal author of the [[United States Constitution|U.S. Constitution]]. In 1788, he wrote over a third of the [[Federalist Papers]], still the most influential commentary on the U.S. Constitution.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=Madison Debates in Convention |date=Tuesday June 26, 1787 |url=http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/debates_626.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt; Madison appears on three [[Definitive issue]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Madison 1894 Issue-2$.jpg|thumb|165px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1894&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Madison 1903 Issue33-$2.jpg|thumb|165px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On December 10 of 1894 the Post Office issued a 2-dollar Madison stamp. The engraving of Madison was modeled after his portrayal by [[Gilbert Stuart]], who painted a total of four portraits of the president. The painting used to model the engraving is now owned by the Colonial Williamsburg Association &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museumsyndicate.com/artist.php?artist=55 |title=Museum Syndicate |publisher=Museum Syndicate |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; (In 1994, four images of this stamp appeared on a souvenir sheet commemorating the hundredth anniversary of stamp production by the Bureau of Engraving and Printing.)
[[File:James Madison 1938 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
* The dark blue 2-dollar stamp was issued June 5, 1903. The stamp image was designed by R. Ostrander Smith from a painting by an unknown artist and Madisons portrayal was engraved by George F. C. Smillie. Both the 1894 and 1903 2-dollar stamps were often used by the Post Office for internal transferring of funds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Roger&amp;nbsp;S.&amp;nbsp;Brody |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2029916 |title=Smithsonium Postal Museum / James Madison |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* The U.S. Post Office issued a 4c Madison stamp on July 1, 1938, part of the [[:File:Presidential issue of 1932.jpg|Presidential series]] that was being issued that year. The engraving of Madison on this issues was modeled after a bust by [[Frederick William Sievers]] on display in the State Capital building in Richmond, Virginia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jeff Shapiro |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2033238 |title=Smithsonium, James Madison, 1938 issue |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

:::[[File:James Madison3 2001 Issue-34c.jpg|thumb|left|265px|&lt;center&gt;1st Madison Commemorative&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 2001&lt;/center&gt;]]
:::Until relatively recently James Madison never appeared on a US commemorative postage stamp. The 200th anniversary of his birth in 1951 remained unacknowledged among the seven [[commemorative stamp|commemoratives]] postage stamps that were issued that year.  Madison was included along with the other past presidents on a 22-cent commemorative [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] released in 1986. In 2001 the US Post Office finally honored James Madison with a single commemorative stamp, issued for the 250th anniversary of his birth, first released in New York, N.Y., on October 18, 2001.  The stamp was designed and illustrated by John Thompson.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;{{clear}}

==James Monroe==
[[James Monroe]], (April 28, 1758 – July 4, 1831)  5th President of the United States, served two terms from 1817 to 1825. Monroe fought in the American Revolution.  He is most noted for his [[Monroe Doctrine]], which stated that the United States would not tolerate further European intervention in the Americas.  Monroe was considered the last Founding Father of the United States.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Monroe 1925 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Monroe 1904 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|235px|&lt;center&gt;~ First Monroe Postage stamp ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;Issue of 1904&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Monroe 1938 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;center/&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The first US Postage stamp to honor Monroe was the [[Louisiana Purchase]] Expedition commemorative 3c issue of 1904. From a series of five issues these stamps were only sold during the seven months of the Exposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

* The 10c 'orange' (yellow) regular issue was printed and issued in 1923, 1925 and 1927, and was the first [[Definitive stamp|definitive issue]] to honor Monroe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] designed the Monroe stamp after a painting by [[John Vanderlyn]] which now hangs in City Hall, New York City. For Monroe's image he used an engraving done by George F.C. Simille previously used to produce the 3-cent issue of the 1904 Louisiana Purchase Exposition Series.  Edward J. Hein transferred Simille’s engraving to a new die and restored it for the new stamp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;10-cent Monroe&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2033927 |title=10-cent Monroe   |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |accessdate=27 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 5c [[:File:Presidential issue of 1932.jpg|Presidential issue of 1938]] depicts Monroe in profile, as do all of the images of that series. The engraving of Monroe was modeled after a Congressional Medal designed by [[Mortz Furst]] and struck by the US Mint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Monroe 1958 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|180px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1958&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Monroe 1954 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1954&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On April 28, 1958 the Post Office issued a 3-cent stamp to commemorate the 200th anniversary of the birth of James Monroe, first issued through the Montross, Virginia, post office. The issue was designed by Frank Conley and was modeled after a portrait of Monroe by renowned American artist [[Gilbert Stuart]] who has also painted the portraits of Washington and other notables.

* The image of the 5c 1958 issue  was modeled after a portrait by [[Rembrandt Peale]] displayed at James Monroe Law Office and Museum in Fredericksburg, Virginia, the building in which James Monroe practiced law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* Monroe is honored on a 22-cent commemorative  [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986.

==John Quincy Adams==
[[File:John Quincy Adams 1938 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[John Quincy Adams]] (July 11, 1767 – February 23, 1848) was the sixth President of the United States from March 4, 1825, to March 4, 1829. Adams was the son of the second U.S. president, [[John Adams]]. When President [[George Washington]] appointed him minister to the Netherlands John Quincy Adams began his career in American politics at the age of twenty-seven years. Adams later served as Secretary of State in the Cabinet of President James Monroe from 1817 until 1825.

* The engraved image of Adams appears on the orange 6-cent denomination of the 1938 Presidential Series. The engraving was modeled after a bust of Adams displayed in the US Capitol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; This is the first US Postage stamp on which John Quincy Adams appeared.

* The next postage stamp presenting Adams was part of the [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|Ameripex '86 issue]], which honored all past deceased American Presidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

==Andrew Jackson==
[[Andrew Jackson]], 7th President of the United States, served from 1829–1837. He was the commander of the American forces at the [[Battle of New Orleans]] in 1815. Jackson died in 1845, however the US Post Office did not release a stamp in his honor until 18 years after his death, with the issue of 1863 (displayed in [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#First appearances|First appearances)]] above).&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;At that time, as aforesaid, he had already appeared on two different Confederate 2c stamps.

&lt;center&gt;'''~ Regular issues of the 19th century ~'''&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Jackson44 1870-2c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1873&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson2 1883 Issue-4c.jpg||thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1883&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson2 1894 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|162px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1894&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* [[Hiram Powers]] (1805–1873) was considered one of the greatest American-born neoclassical sculptors. In 1834, Andrew Jackson posed many times for Powers as he sculpted a bust of the president.  The bust was completed in January 1835. Thirty-five years later, it inspired the image of the 2-cent Jackson stamp from the [[National Bank Note Company]] 1870-1871 Issue.

* The 3c issue of 1894 features a similar image of Jackson as the issues of 1873 and 1883, taken from a bust by Hiram Powers.

&lt;center&gt;'''~ Regular issues of the 20th century ~'''&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson 1903 Issue-3c.jpg||thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson 1938 Issue-7c.jpg||thumb|135px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson2 1963 Issue-1c.jpg|thumb|135px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1963&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Andrew Jackson2 1967 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|135px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1967&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The 3c issue of 1903 was engraved by A. Sealey who modeled his image after a portrait of Jackson by renown American artist [[Thomas Sully]]. In 1824 Sully painted a study portrait from life of Andrew Jackson. By this time Jackson was a US senator and a Democratic nominee for coming presidential election of 1824. Two decades later, Jackson’s ill health prompted Sully to repaint his 1824 study portrait Jackson's portrait from this image. The painting was completed shortly before Jackson’s death in April 1845. The Sully portrait was the model for the engravings used on the postage issues of 1903 and 1967. The Sully painting is currently hanging in the National Gallery of Art in Washington DC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;&gt;'''Scotts Identifier of U.S. Definitive Issues''''&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 7-cent 1938 Presidential issue features Jackson's profile. The image of Jackson's was modeled after the Belle Kinney and Leopold F. Scholz bronze statue of Jackson which stands in the [[United States Capitol rotunda|US Capitol's Rotunda]].

* The 1c 1963 issue of Jackson was designed by William K. Schrange. Jackson's image was modeled after a medal by [[Mortz Furst]] in 1829.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* The engraving of Jackson on the 10c issue of 1967 is taken from the same Thomas Sully painting that was used to model the engraving in the 1903 issue. Lester Beal designed the overall stamp image and design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

===Andrew Jackson on commemorative issues===
Andrew Jackson appears on three commemorative issues: The Army Issue of 1937, the Tennessee Statehood issue of 1946 and the [[Battle of New Orleans]] issue of 1961.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Jackson Scott 1937 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Jackson ~ Scott&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; Issue of 1937&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Tennessee Statehood 1946 Issue3c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Tennessee Statehood&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1946&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Battle of NewOrleans 1965 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Battle of New Orleans&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1961&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
--&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
{|
|[[File:Jackson Scott 1937 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Jackson ~ Scott&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt; Issue of 1937&lt;/center&gt;]]
|[[File:Tennessee Statehood 1946 Issue3c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Tennessee Statehood&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1946&lt;/center&gt;]]
|[[File:Battle of NewOrleans 1965 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Battle of New Orleans&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1961&lt;/center&gt;]]
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

* The 2-cent Army issue, released on January 15, 1937, features portraits of Andrew Jackson and [[Winfield Scott]] on either side with Jackson's home, [[The Hermitage (Nashville, Tennessee)|the Hermitage]], depicted in the background. Jackson was a hero of the War of 1812, his troops having defeated the British in the [[Battle of New Orleans]]. Scott served as a General in the US Army longer than any other man in American history.

* Issued on June 1, 1946, the 150th anniversary of Tennessee statehood was commemorated by a 3-cent purple stamp  depicting Andrew Jackson on the left with  John Sevier on the right with the image of the Tennessee State Capitol in the center of the design. Jackson was the first U.S. President from Tennessee.

* On the 5c 'Battle of New Orleans' issue depicts then General Jackson defeating an invading British Army which was intent on seizing and taking control of New Orleans and the vast territory America had acquired with the [[Louisiana Purchase]].&lt;ref&gt;Reilly, Robin (1974). ''The British at the gates - the New Orleans campaign in the War of 1812''. New York: Putnam.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Jackson appears on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986.

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Washington Jackson 1994 Issue2-$5.jpg|thumb|right|200px]] --&gt;
* On August 19 of 1994 the Post Office issued a [[:File:Washington Jackson 1994 Issue2-$5.jpg|5-dollar Washington-Jackson stamp]] in Pittsburg, Pennsylvania, at the American Philatelic Society's annual stamp exposition. The stamp was modeled after a design created in 1869 by the [[National Bank Note Company]] It was originally prepared but never was used for the 1869 US postage series. The central image or vignette features a portrait of George Washington and Andrew Jackson. The portrayals of Washington and Jackson were engraved through the intaglio process by Stamp Venturers, Inc., and issued in small sheets of twenty stamps.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;{{clear}}

==Martin Van Buren==
[[File:Martin Van Buren3 1903 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Martin Van Buren]] (December 5, 1782 – July 24, 1862) was the eighth President of the United States from 1837 to 1841. Before his presidency, he served as the eighth Vice President (1833–1837) and the 10th Secretary of State under [[Andrew Jackson]]. Van Buren was the first US President to be born an American citizen.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hoover.nara.gov/exhibits/cottages/middleclass/vanburen.html NARA.gov], Martin Van Buren&lt;/ref&gt;

::* Van Buren appears on the 1938 issue, the 8-cent olive green denomination of the 1938 [[Presidential Issue|Presidential Series]], a series of stamps whose denominations corresponded with the number of the given President's term. A sculpted bust of Van Buren on display in the US Capitol's Senate Gallery was used as the model for the engraving of the President's image for this issue.

::* Van Buren is honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986.{{clear}}

==William Henry Harrison==

[[William Henry Harrison]] (February 9, 1773 – April 4, 1841) was the ninth President of the United States, and served in the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] as an officer and politician, and the first president to die in office. &lt;ref name=&quot;WH Harrison&quot;&gt;[http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/williamhenryharrison White House Archives]&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest president elected until [[Ronald Reagan]] in 1980, and last President to be born before the [[United States Declaration of Independence]], Harrison a hero in the [[War of 1812]], died on his thirty-second day in office. &lt;ref&gt;Harrison served as President for 30 days, 12 hours and 32&amp;nbsp;minutes, but this was spread over 32 different calendar days; part of a day upon inauguration, 30 full days, then part of the day on which he died.&lt;/ref&gt; Harrison's grandson, [[Benjamin Harrison]] of Indiana, was the 23rd president, from 1889 to 1893, making them the only grandparent–grandchild pair of presidents.&lt;ref name=&quot;calhoun&quot;&gt;{{Harvard citation no brackets|Calhoun|2005|pp=43–49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:William Henry Harrison2 1938 Issue-9c.jpg|thumb|left||140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt; . . .
&lt;td&gt;[[File:William H Harrison 1950 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb||260px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1950&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* Harrison appears on the 9-cent pink 1938 Presidential Series issue. Image of Harrison is taken from a bust displayed in the Rotunda of the Virginia State Capitol building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;  The issue was designed by William Schrage and the master engraver was C. A. Brooks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://1847usa.com/ByYear/1938.htm 1847 U.S.A., Postage Stamps of the United States First Issued in 1938]&lt;/ref&gt;

* On July 4, 1950 the US Post Office issued a 3 cent Indiana territory commemorative celebrating the 150th anniversary if Indiana statehood. First day of issue took place at [[Vincennes, Indiana]] Post office. The central design of the stamp is a portrait of William Henry Harrison who was the first governor of [[Indiana Territory]]. Behind him is an image of the First State Capitol building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* Harrison appears on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential]] commemorative issues of 1986.

==John Tyler==
[[File:John Tyler 1938 Issue-10c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[John Tyler]] (March 29, 1790 – January 18, 1862) was the tenth President of the United States (1841–1845) and the first to succeed to the office following the death of a predecessor. Tyler assumed office when President [[William Henry Harrison|William H. Harrison]] died only thirty days into his term as U.S. President.&lt;ref name=&quot;WH Harrison&quot;/&gt;

:::* The image of John Tyler (1790-1862), appears on the orange-brown 10-cent denomination of the 1938 [[Presidential Issue|Presidential Series]]. The image of Tyler was modeled after a bust by John Keck on display in the Rotunda of the Virginia State Capitol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; This issue was the first US Postage stamp that honors John Tyler.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; The Tyler postage issue of 1932 was used primarily in combination with other denominations. Finding examples of solo usage are most often found on outgoing international mail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

:::* The only other postage stamp honoring Tyler (to date) was issued in 1986, a 22-cent stamp in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]], where each President up to and including Johnson appears on his own stamp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

==James K. Polk==
[[File:James K Polk 1938 Issue-11c.jpg|thumb|left|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:James KPolk 1995 Issue-32c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1995&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[James Knox Polk]] (November 2, 1795 – June 15, 1849) was the 11th President of the United States (1845–1849). Polk was born in North Carolina. He later lived in and became Governor of the state of Tennessee. A Democrat, Polk served as Speaker of the House (1835–1839) and Governor of Tennessee (1839–1841) before becoming president. Polk was an ardent supporter of [[Andrew Jackson]].  Polk was considered the last strong pre-Civil War president.{{clear}}

* The image of Polk appears on the 11-cent denomination of the 1938 [[Presidential Issue|Presidential Series]]. Polk's profile on the stamp was modeled after a medal struck by the US Mint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; This issue was printed in ultramarine and was printed only as a sheet stamp, first issued in Washington DC on September 8, 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;
* Polk is honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986.
* The US Post Office honored the eleventh President on the 200th anniversary of Polk's birth with the 1995 issue of a 32-cent commemorative stamp, first issued on November 2, in Columbia, Tennessee, where Polk spent his adult life. The issue was engraved by the intaglio process, printed in red-brown by the [[Banknote Corporation of America]]. This is one of the few modern day issues that still spells out the full title, 'UNITED STATES POSTAGE' as did most US postage stamps up until around the 1950s when the shortened title 'US Postage' slowly began to replace the original title. It is also one of the very few modern day regular issues that honor famous Americans which has the years of birth and death of the subject inscribed on the face.&lt;ref&gt;Trend can be noted with the aid of any illustrated US postage stamp catalog.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Zachary Taylor==
[[File:Zachary Taylor 1875 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|left|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1875&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Zachary Taylor2 1938 Issue-12c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Zachary Taylor]] (November 24, 1784 – July 9, 1850) was the 12th President of the United States and an American military leader. Taylor ran as a [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig]] in the 1848 presidential election, defeating [[Lewis Cass]] and becoming the first man elected to the Presidency without having held any previous elected office. He served in the US Army for over forty years and as 'Old Rough and Ready' had a reputation for never losing a battle.  During the [[Mexican-American War]] (1846–1848) Taylor became a national hero, and with this fame he was elected to the presidency.{{clear}}

* Zachary Taylor is honored on three US postage stamps, regular issues.  The first Taylor stamp was issued in 1875. This first issue was printed by the [[Continental Bank Note Company]] on yellowish wove paper. When the [[American Bank Note Company]] received the federal contract to print postage stamps in 1879 it printed the second Taylor issue (identical in appearance to the 1875 issue) on soft porous paper, using the original dies of Continental Bank Note Company. The engraving of Taylor was modeled after a [[daguerrotype]] of Taylor by famous Civil War photographer [[Mathew Brady]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
* Taylor also appears on the 12-cent denomination of the 1938 Presidential Series. A bust displayed in the Rotunda of the [[Virginia State Capitol]] inspired the image depicted on this issue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
* There are only two commemorative issues dedicated to Taylor, one issued in the [[:File:AMERIPEX 1986.jpg|1986 AMERIPEX]] Presidential issue and the other released in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;

==Millard Filmore==
[[File:Millard Filmore Issue of 1938-13c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Millard Fillmore]] (January 7, 1800 – March 8, 1874) was the 13th President of the United States, serving from 1850 until 1853.  He became the second [[Vice President]] to assume the presidency after the death of a sitting president when he succeeded [[Zachary Taylor]], who died in Office in July 1850. As such Fillmore was never actually elected president, and was the last member of the [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig Party]] to hold that office.

* Millard Filmore appears on the 1938 [[Presidential Issue]] as the 13c denomination in that series. The engraved image of Filmore was modeled after a bust by [[Robert Cushing]] &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; displayed in the Senate Gallery of the US Capitol. This is Millard Fillmore's first appearance on a U.S. postage stamp.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;
* Filmore also appears once in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential series]], 36 commemorative stamps, issued by the Post Office on May 22, 1986.

==Franklin Pierce==
[[File:Franklin Pierce 1938 Issue-14c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Franklin Pierce]] (November 23, 1804 – October 8, 1869), an American politician and lawyer, was the 14th President of the United States, serving from 1853 to 1857, and is the only President from New Hampshire. Pierce enlisted in the volunteer [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] during the [[Mexican-American War]] and rose to the rank of colonel. In March 1847, he was appointed brigadier general of volunteers and took command of a brigade of reinforcements for [[Winfield Scott]]'s army marching on Mexico City.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hawthorn4&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eldritchpress.org/nh/fp04.html |title=The Life of Franklin Pierce, 1852, Chapter 4 |author=Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1804-1864|publisher=Eldritch Press |year=2010 |accessdate=3 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Pierce appears on the 14c issue of the 1938 Presidential Series. A medal struck by the US Mint served as the model for the engraved image of Pierce. The stamp was issued by the US Post Office on October 6, 1938. 

* Pierce did not appear on a commemorative stamp until the Post office introduced the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] on May 22, 1986.{{clear}}

==James Buchanan==
[[File:James Buchanan 1938 Issue2-15c.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[James Buchanan]], Jr. (April 23, 1791 – June 1, 1868) was the 15th President of the United States serving from 1857 until 1861 and the last President to be born in the 18th century. Buchanan served as a congressman (1821–1831), Senator (1834–1845), Minister to Russia (1832–1834), Secretary of State (1845–1849) before ascending to the presidency in 1857. Opinions by historians of Buchanan's presidency vary, as some credit him for keeping a divided nation together for so long while others fault him for failing to avert a civil war.  To date he is the only president from the state of Pennsylvania and the only one to have never married.

* The engraved portrayal of James Buchanan appears on the 15-cent issue of the 1938 Presidential Series. The image was modeled after a sculpted bust by Henry Dexter which is now on display in the [[National Gallery of Art]] in Washington, DC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; This was Buchanan's first appearance on a US Postage stamp.
* Buchanan also appears on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]] of 1986.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMERIPEX '86&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Lincoln Plate proof 1890-4c.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;~ Abraham Lincoln ~&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Die proof of 1890 issue&lt;/center&gt;]]

==Abraham Lincoln==
[[Abraham Lincoln]] (February 12, 1809 &amp;ndash; April 15, 1865) was the 16th President of the United States, serving from 1861 to 1865. He successfully led the United States through its [[American Civil War|Civil War]], thus preserving the Union and bringing an end to slavery. Lincoln was the first Republican president, elected in 1860. Lincoln issued the [[Emancipation Proclamation]] in 1863 and promoted the passage of the Thirteenth Amendment to the [[United States Constitution|Constitution]].

Second only to the number of times [[George Washington]] has been appeared on the face U.S. Postage, Abraham Lincoln appears on U.S. Postage more than all the remaining other presidents. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;{{clear}}

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abraham Lincoln 1869 Issue22-90c.jpg|thumb|205px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1869&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln NBN 1870 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|165px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1870&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln2 1882-6c.jpg|thumb|165px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1882&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The first Postage stamp to honor Abraham Lincoln was issued on April 14, 1866, one year to the day after his death in 1865, [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. Postage stamps#First appearances|displayed above]]. The engraving of this image was modeled after a photograph taken by [[Mathew Brady]].

* The 90c issue of 1869 displays an engraving of Lincoln that was fashioned after the same photograph taken by Mathew Brady used to model for the 1866 issue. A total of only 47,460 stamps were printed by the [[National Bank Note Company]].

* The 6c 1870 issue depicts an engraving of Lincoln that was modeled after a sculpture by Lenoard Wells Volk.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abraham Lincoln 1890 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|133px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1890&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln2 1895-4c.jpg|thumb|133px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1865&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abrahan Lincoln2 1898 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|138px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1898&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abraham Lincoln 1903 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* There are several other prominent artists behind the designs of Lincoln stamps. The 1890 Issue was printed by the [[American Bank Note Company]]. Alfred Jones engraved the portrait modeling it after a photo of Lincoln taken by Mathew Brady, arguably the most important photographer of the Civil War era. Among the most notable postage stamp designer-artists is [[Clair Aubrey Huston]] who designed the Bureau stamps using an existing engraving for the vignette.

* The 4c issue of 1898 was engraved by [[George F.C. Smillie]], an engraver at the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]], who had made the earlier engraving in 1898. Smillie also based his work on a photograph of Lincoln taken in 1864 by [[Mathew Brady]].

* The 5-cent blue stamp was designed by R. Ostrander Smith. The engraving was done by Marcus W. Baldwin also taken from the photograph by Mathew Brady.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Abraham Lincoln3 1909 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|200px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1909&lt;/center&gt;]]
* The 2-cent Lincoln stamp of 1909 had the same dimensions as a definitive stamp, but it was the first US single stamp commemorative issue.  Lincoln had appeared on at least one denomination of every regular issue since 1866. When the definitive issues of 1908 featured only the portraits of Washington and Franklin, there was considerable public disappointment at Lincoln's exclusion. The 100th anniversary issue of his birth created an opportunity to mollify the situation. The engraving of Lincoln on this issue is modeled after a statue by sculptor [[Augustus Saint-Gaudens]].{{clear}}
&lt;!--
Below the three issues from the left depicting Lincoln were printed by the [[National Bank Note Company]] of New York.
--&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abraham Lincoln 1923 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|137px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1926&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln 1938 Issue-16c.jpg|thumb|134px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Abraham Lincoln Airmail 1960 Issue-25c.jpg|thumb|236px|&lt;center&gt;Airmail Issue of 1960&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln 1965 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|125px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1965&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The 3c issues of 1923, 1925 and 1927 depict Abraham Lincoln. [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] designed the stamp using an existing engraving of Lincoln used by the Bureau in 1894 for the vignette. George Smillie, an engraver at the Bureau of Engraving and Printing, had made the earlier engraving in 1898. Smillie based his work on a photograph of Lincoln taken in 1864 by [[Mathew Brady]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; The issued was first released on Lincoln’s birthday, February 12, 1923, in Washington, D.C., and in Hodgenville, Kentucky, near Lincoln’s birthplace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* Lincoln appears on the 16c issue of the 1938 Presidential Series. A bust displayed in the Senate Gallery, sculpted by Sarah Fisher Ames, was the model that inspired Lincoln's likeness on the engraving for this issue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;  First issued in Washington DC on October 20, 1938.

* The next definitive series, the [[Liberty Issue]], featured Lincoln on its 4c stamp, released on November 19, 1954.

* Oddly enough, Abraham Lincoln is the only American President to ever appear on the face of a [[Airmails of the United States|US Airmail]] Postage stamp, first issued on April 22, 1960 in San Francisco, California.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts - Airpost&quot;&gt;Scotts Specialized Catalogue of United States Stamps - Air Post Stamps&lt;/ref&gt;

* On November 17, 1965 the US Post Office issued the 4-cent black stamp featuring Lincoln’s profile with the 'log cabin' background, first issued in New York City. It is the first issue among the Prominent Americans series. Though Lincoln had very little formal education, his speeches and writings are today considered masterpieces. This is the theme of the design with the log-cabin which has become synonymous with Lincoln's humble beginnings. The engraving for this issue was modeled after a photo taken by famous Civil War photographer [[Mathew Brady]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

===Lincoln on commemorative Issues===
[[File:Chinese Resistance Issue 1942 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|260px|&lt;center&gt;Chinese Resistance&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1942&lt;/center&gt;]]
Except for the memorial stamp of 1909, designed to simulate a definitive issue, Abraham Lincoln did not appear on a commemorative issue until the U.S. Post office issued the Chinese resistance issue in 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt; The first president to appear on a US commemorative Postage stamp was [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#Jefferson on commemorative issue|Thomas Jefferson]], displayed above. &lt;br /&gt;

:* On July 7, 1942, the U.S. Post Office issued a 5c postage stamp commemorating the fifth anniversary of Chinese resistance to Japanese oppression as a tribute to [[China]] and its struggle  to preserve a free government. The design of this issue depicts a map of China with an image of the sun, national symbol of China, superimposed on the map. Portraits of Abraham Lincoln and Sun Yat-sen, first president of the Republic of China, are on either side of the stamp.
&lt;br/&gt;

:[[File:Lincoln Of the People-3c.jpg|thumb|left|260px|&lt;center&gt;Gettysburg Address&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1948&lt;/center&gt;]]
:* On November 19, 1948, eighty-five years to the day after President Abraham Lincoln delivered his most famous speech, the US Post Office released the commemorative Gettysburg Address issue. Lincoln delivered the &quot;Gettysburg Address&quot; at the dedication of the Soldiers' National Cemetery in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, on Thursday, November 19, 1863, four and a half months after Union armies defeated those of the [[Confederate States of America|Confederacy]] at the [[Battle of Gettysburg]], the turn of the [[American Civil War]].{{clear}}&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;center&gt;'''~ Lincoln Sesquicentennial Issue ~'''&lt;/center&gt;

The US Post Office issued a series of four commemorative stamps during 1958 and 1959 in honor of the 150th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln's birth in 1809. The four stamps were modeled after various famous works of art.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Young Lincoln-1c.jpg|thumb|130px|The Young Abe Lincoln, Issue of 1959]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln Douglas debates of 1858 1958 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|185px|Lincoln Douglas debates of 1858, Issue of 1958]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln Memorial Issue 1959-4c.jpg|thumb|185px|&lt;center&gt;Lincoln Memorial&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1959&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln 1959 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|130px|Issue of 1959]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
[[File:Lincoln bust Gutzon Borglum.jpg|thumb|185px|&lt;center&gt;Bust of Lincoln, 1909&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;by Gutzon Borglum&lt;/center&gt;Used as model for engraving of 1959 issue.]]
* The 1c green Lincoln issue was first released to the public on February 12, 1959, the 150th anniversary of Lincoln's birth in 1809, in Hodgenville, Kentucky, near the place of Lincoln's birth. The engraving is modeled after a painting by [[George Healy]]. Robert L. Miller of the Bureau of Engraving and Printing modeled the overall stamp design. The 1-cent Lincoln stamp features the famous &quot;Beardless Lincoln&quot; portrait painted by Healy from life in 1860 in Springfield, Illinois, shortly after Lincoln was elected president.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
* The 4c Lincoln-Douglas debate postage stamp was first issued on August 27, 1958 at Freeport, Illinois.  This issue was the first in the series  and was first released on the 100th anniversary of the Lincoln-Douglas debates. The engraved image is modeled after a painting by Joseph Boggs that portrays Lincoln addressing an outdoor crowd with Douglas standing behind him. Artist William K. Schrage of the Bureau of Engraving and Printing based the stamp design on work done by Ervine Metzl of [[New York City]].
* The US Post Office issued the blue 4-cent Lincoln stamp on May 30, 1959  It was one of four Lincoln Birth Sesquicentennial commemorative stamps first issued through the Washington, DC, Post Office.  The issue features a portion of a famous statue sculpted by [[Daniel Chester French]], which sits in the Lincoln Memorial in Washington, DC.
* On February 27, 1959, the US Post Office issued the 3c Lincoln Birth Sesquicentennial commemorative stamp, the third in the series of four, first issued through the New York, New York, post office. The stamp features a sculptured bust of Lincoln by Gutzon Borglum. Done in marble in 1906, it now stands in the [[United States Capitol rotunda|rotunda of the Capitol]] in Washington, DC.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln Nation of Readers2.jpg|thumb|left|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1984&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Lincoln 1995 Issue-32c.jpg|thumb|right|190px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1995&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On October 16, 1984, the US Post office issued its 20c commemorative postage stamp commemorating the theme &quot;A Nation of Readers&quot;.  The First Day Ceremony took place in Washington, DC, in the Coolidge Auditorium of the Library of Congress. The issue was designed by Bradbury Thompson of Riverside, Connecticut, who based the design on a photograph by renown [[Photographers of the American Civil War|Civil War photographer]] [[Mathew Brady]] which shows Abraham Lincoln reading from a book to his son Thomas.
* The Postal Service issued a 20 stamp sheet of 32-cent Civil War stamps on June 29, 1995 in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania. Designed by Mark Hess of Katonah, New York, the stamps are the second installment of the Classic Collection. This issue depicts Lincoln with the Capitol under reconstruction in the background. Text about Lincoln is on the back this issue.
* Lincoln also appears once in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential series]], 36 commemorative stamps, issued by the Post Office on May 22, 1986.

&lt;center&gt;'''~ Lincoln 200th Anniversary of birth commemorative issues ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
[[File:Lincoln 2009 Anniversary 4-Issues.jpg|thumb|center|700px|&lt;center&gt;~ Issue of 2009 ~&lt;/center&gt;]]
* On February 9, 2009, the 200th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln's birth, the US Post office in Springfield, Illinois, first issued a set of four commemorative issues portraying Lincoln at different periods in his life. Lincoln's portrayal and stamp artwork was created by artist Mark Summers of Waterdown, Ontario, Canada.  The background depicted in the stamps are taken from famous themes, i.e. The Lincoln and Douglas debates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;mode=1&amp;tid=2051403 |title=National Postal Museum |publisher=Arago.si.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Andrew Johnson==
[[File:Andrew Johnson 1938 Issue-17c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Andrew Johnson]] (December 29, 1808 – July 31, 1875) was the 17th President of the United States serving from 1865 1869.  As a Unionist, he was the only Southern senator who didn't give up his post upon secession. Johnson was the most prominent War Democrat from the South and supported Lincoln's military policies during the American Civil War of 1861–1865.  Following the assassination of President Abraham Lincoln, Johnson presided over the Reconstruction era of the United States in the four years following the American Civil War.

* This rose-red stamp was issued on October 27, 1938. It marks the first appearance of Andrew Johnson on a postage stamp. The engraving of Johnson's profile was modeled after by a bust displayed in the Senate Gallery in Washington, DC.

* Johnson also appears once in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential series]], 36 commemorative stamps, issued by the US Post Office on May 22, 1986. It is the only commemorative stamp issued in his honor to date.

==Ulysses S. Grant==
[[File:Grant 1890 Proof2-5c.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;''~ Ulysses S. Grant ~''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;[[Die proof (philately)|Die proof]] of 1st Grant stamp&lt;/center&gt;]]
Ulysses S. Grant, 18th president of the United States.  A national hero of the [[American Civil War]], Grant was elected president in 1868, the youngest man theretofore elected president. He was re-elected in 1872. Grant began his life long career as a soldier after graduating from the United States Military Academy in 1843. Fighting in the Mexican American War, he was a close observer of the techniques of Generals [[Zachary Taylor]] and [[Winfield Scott]]. During [[Andrew Johnson|President Johnson]]'s term Grant was appointed to be the Secretary of War.

:[[Ulysses S. Grant]] died in 1885 and did not appear on US Postage until some five years later in 1890 when the [[American Bank Note Company]] first printed the postage stamps that depicted his portrait.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; For a Civil War hero and a President this length of time was considerably longer than that of the first Abraham Lincoln issue of 1866, whose release was only one year after Lincoln's death in 1865.
{{clear}}

&lt;center&gt; '''~ The first Grant postage stamps ~'''&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt; ''Engravings were modeled after a photograph by William Kurtz''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Grant 1890 2-5c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1890&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Ulysses S Grant 1894 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1894&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Ulysses S Grant 1898 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1898&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On June 2, 1890 the US Post Office issued a brown 5-cent Postage stamp honoring Ulysses S. Grant. It was the first US [[Postage stamp]] to depict the former President and [[American Civil War|Civil War]] General. This issue was released exactly twenty-five years after Gen. [[Edmond Kirby Smith]]’s surrender of the last major Confederate army at Galveston, Texas, on June 2, 1865. The issue was printed by the American Bank Note Company.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2032675 Grant, National Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Ulysses S Grant 1903 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Uylsses S Grant 1923 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1923&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:US Grant 1938 Issue-18c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On February 10, 1903 the Grant 4-cent brown stamp was issued. The design is by R. Ostrander Smith and was based on a tintype by Kurtz. The stamp was engraved by George F.C.Smillie

* On May 1, 1923 the US Post Office issued an 8c definitive issue honoring Ulysses S. Grant. [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] designed the stamp image. A photograph of Grant taken by renowned Civil War photographer [[Mathew Brady]] served as the model for Huston’s vignette. The die for the vignette was engraved by Louis Schofield.

* The engraved image of Ulysses S. Grant appears on the 18-cent denomination of the 1938 Presidential Series. Grant's likeness was inspired by a statue by Franklin Simmons, housed in the Rotunda of the United States Capitol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

===Grant on commemorative issues===
[[File:Sherman Grant Sheridan 1937 Issue-3c.jpg|thumb|left|235px|&lt;center&gt;Army Issue of 1937&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Ulysses S Grany 1995 Issue-32c.jpg|thumb|180px|&lt;center&gt;General Grant taken from [[Mathew Brady]] photo on Commemorative Issue of 1995&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Ulysses S. Grant]] while appearing on on a fair number of the regular (definitive) issues appears only three times on commemorative stamps.

* Grant (along with [[William T. Sherman]] and [[Philip H. Sheridan]]) appears on the 3-cent 1937 Army Issue commemorative stamp issue, one issue out of a set of five stamps among that issue.

* Grant also appears once in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential series]], 36 commemorative stamps, issued by the Post Office on May 22, 1986.

* The next commemorative stamp to honor Grant was the 32-cent issue of 1995.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;  Designed by Mark Hess of Katona, the image of Grant was taken from a [[:File:Ulysses S Grant, Cold Harbor, VA, June 1864..jpg|photo]] by Civil War photographer [[Mathew Brady]] in June 1864 at City Point in Virginia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ulysses S. Grant&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.npg.si.edu/exh/brady/gallery/56gal.html |publisher=Smithsonian Institution |title=Ulysses S. Grant |accessdate=13 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The colorized photo used in the stamp design depicts Grant wearing his Union General's uniform leaning against a post at the encampment.&lt;ref name=&quot;American Civil War Issue&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;mode=1&amp;tid=2043413 |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |title=American Civil War Issue |accessdate=13 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rutherford B. Hayes==
[[File:Hayes 1922 Issue2-11c.jpg|thumb|left|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1922&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:RB Hayes 1938 Issue2-19c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Rutherford Birchard Hayes]] (October 4, 1822 – January 17, 1893) was the 19th President of the United States serving from March 4, 1877 to March 4, 1881. In the years before his presidency he was the Governor of Ohio for two separate terms. Serving in the Civil War as Brigadier General Hayes commanded the First Brigade of the Kanawha Division of the [[Army of West Virginia]] and turned back several Confederate advances. During his military service he was wounded on five separate incidents.

* An 11c Postage stamp was issued on the 100th anniversary of Hayes’ birth, October 4, 1922, in Washington, D.C., and in Hayes’ hometown, Fremont, Ohio and was the first stamp issued in the [[Regular Issues of 1922-1931]]. The stamp was designed by [[Clair Aubrey Houston]]. The engraving of Hayes is modeled after a photograph taken by prominent Civil War photographer [[Mathew Brady]]. John Eissler engraved the die for the vignette.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* The likeness of Rutherford B. Hayes (1822–1893), the nineteenth president of the United States, appears on the 19-cent denomination of the 1938 Presidential Series. Hayes's image was derived from a medal struck by George Morgan of the US Mint in Philadelphia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; This issue was first released to the public on November 10, 1938, along with the 20-cent Presidential issue of 1938. There is only one commemorative stamp honoring Hayes, released in 1986 on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

==James Garfield==

[[James Abram Garfield]] (November 19, 1831{{ndash}} September 19, 1881) was the [[List of Presidents of the United States|20th]] [[President of the United States]] who had a distinguished military background. [[James A. Garfield assassination|An assassin's bullet]] ended his life and presidency and cut his time in office after serving only 200 days.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=381 James Abram Garfield] at [[Find A Grave]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flipkart.com/james-garfield-army-general-president/1599860414-dtx3flmm5f |title=James Garfield - Army General and President |publisher=Flipkart.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Garfield served in the [[United States Army]] as a Major General, as a member of the [[U.S. House of Representatives]],&lt;ref name=&quot;wh&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/jamesgarfield |title=White House Archives: James Garfield |publisher=Whitehouse.gov |date=2010-10-01 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and as a member of the highly controversial [[United States presidential election, 1876|Electoral Commission of 1876]].  He was the second US President to be assassinated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thelongestlistofthelongeststuffatthelongestdomainnameatlonglast.com/second15.html |title=America's second President to be Assassinated. James Garfield |publisher=Thelongestlistofthelongeststuffatthelongestdomainnameatlonglast.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Garfield was the only sitting member of the House of Representatives to have been elected President.&lt;ref name=&quot;ohc170&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=170 |title=ohiohistorycentral.org |publisher=ohiohistorycentral.org |date=2005-07-01 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Garfield is one of the few presidents to appear on a postage stamp more than the usual one or two times. The first issue to honor him was released in 1882, printed by the [[American Bank Note Company]].  The 5-cent Garfield was the second US postage stamp to honor an assassinated president within the year following his death and is also considered a 'mourning stamp' by many. Unlike the first Lincoln issue, released after one whole year after his death the 5-cent Garfield stamp was released only seven months after his death in 1881.  The 1882 issues were the first issues produced from engravings completed by the [[American Bank Note Company]] since it began producing postage stamps for the federal government. Before this time the A.B.N.C. used existing dies using slight changes to frames and portraits that were primarily the [[National Bank Note Company]]’s design. The re-engraved issues of 1881-1882 are an example.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;'''~ James A. Garfield Memorial Issues ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield2 1882 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1882&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield 1882 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1882&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Garfield 1888 issue-5c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Reprinting of 1888&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

Issues depicting Garfield released on and after 1894 were printed by the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;  &lt;center&gt;'''~ Late 19th century Issues ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield2 1890 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|142px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1890&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield2 1894 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|135px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1895&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield 1898 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|142px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1898&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

The American Bank note issues of 1890 are almost identical to the Bureau Issues that followed in 1894, with minor differences in the frame design.

* American Bank Note Co.

* Bureau Issues

&lt;center&gt;'''~ Early 20th century Issues ~'''&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield 1902 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|142px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1903&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield 1922 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|142px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1922&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:James Garfield 1938 Issue-20c.jpg|thumb|142px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The Regular Issue of 1902-03 stamp was designed by R. Ostrander Smith from a photograph, and was engraved by George F. C. Smillie. It was printed on double-line watermark paper.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* The release of the 6-cents Regular Issue Garfield stamp marked the sixth time Garfield would appear on US Postage. Slated for release on Garfield's birthday on November 19, a Sunday, when Post offices were closed, it was instead released on the 20th in Washington, DC, as there was no post office in Garfield's hometown of Orange, Ohio at the time this issue was released.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* Garfield's image on the  Presidential issue of 1938 was inspired by a medal created by the U.S. Mint. The issue was released to the public on November 10, 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

* As of 2011 there is only one commemorative stamp honoring Garfield, released in 1986 on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential issue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

==Chester A. Arthur==
[[File:Chester A Arthur 1938 Issue-21c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;CENTER&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/CENTER&gt;]]
[[Chester Alan Arthur]] (October 5, 1829 – November 18, 1886) served as the 21st President of the United States. As a member of the Republican Party Arthur worked as a lawyer before becoming the 20th Vice President under [[James Garfield]].  On July 2, 1881, President Garfield was mortally wounded by [[Charles J. Guiteau]], but Garfield did not die until September 19 of that year, at which time Arthur was sworn in as President, serving until March 4, 1885.

* The engraving of Chester A. Arthur appears on the 21-cent value of the [[Presidential Issue|1938 Presidential Series]], first issued on November 22 of 1938. The likeness was modeled after a marble bust of Arthur by [[Augustus Saint-Gaudens]] in 1891, now displayed in the US Senate Gallery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/art/artifact/Sculpture_22_00020.htm |title=U.S. Senate Archives: Art and History |publisher=Senate.gov |date=2009-03-26 |accessdate=2010-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* There is only one commemorative stamp issued in Arthur's honor, one stamp in a series in the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX Presidential issue of 1986]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

==Grover Cleveland==

[[Stephen Grover Cleveland]] (March 18, 1837 – June 24, 1908) was the 22nd and 24th President of the United States. Cleveland is the only president ever to have served two non-consecutive terms (1885–1889 and 1893–1897) as President and therefore is the only individual to be counted twice in the numbering of the presidents.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Grover Cleveland 1923 Issue-12c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1923&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Grover Cleveland 1938 Issue-22c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;!-- &lt;td&gt;[[File:Grover Cleveland-22c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1986&lt;/center&gt;]] --&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On March 20, 1923, the US Post Office issued the 12-cent Cleveland issue, first released both in Washington, D.C., and in Caldwell, New Jersey, Cleveland’s hometown. [[Clair Aubrey Huston]] designed the stamp and John Eissler engraved the portrayal of Cleveland. The model for the engraving is listed by the Bureau of Engraving and Printing as “unknown.” The 12-cent Cleveland was reprinted and issued again in 1931.
* Cleveland appeared on a presidential Issue released on November 22, 1938, the same day as the 21-cent Garfield stamp of that series. The engraving of Cleveland's portrait was modeled after a medal struck by Charles Barber of the US Mint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
* The 22-cent Cleveland stamp was issued on May 22 of 1986 as part of a series of stamps honoring US Presidents, first issued during [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX '86]], the international philatelic show held in Rosemont, Illinois. Artist Jerry Dadds of Baltimore, Maryland, designed the four sheets containing thirty-six stamps. Dadds also executed the designs in the woodcut style.

==Benjamin Harrison==
[[File:Benjamin Harrison 1903 Issue-13c.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;The 1st Harrison stamp&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1902&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Benjamin Harrison]] (August 20, 1833 – March 13, 1901) was the 23rd [[President of the United States]], serving one term from 1889 to 1893. Harrison was born in North Bend, Ohio, and at the age of 21 moved to Indianapolis, Indiana, where he became a involved with Indiana state politics. During the [[American Civil War]] Harrison served as a Brigadier General in the [[Army of the Cumberland]].  

Under Benjamin Harrison and his Postmaster General [[John Wanamaker]] the nation's first [[commemorative stamp]]s were made available and were first issued at the [[World Columbian Exposition]] in Chicago, Illinois, in 1893. Wanamaker originally introduced the idea of issuing the nation's first commemorative stamp to Harrison, the Congress and the U.S. Post Office. Contrary to the general opinion of Congress at the time Wanamaker predicted that [[commemorative stamp]]s would generate needed revenue for the country. Shortly thereafter the [[Columbian Issue|nation's first commemoartive stamps]] were issued in conjunction with the World Columbian Exposition, both of which were in commemoration of the 400th anniversary of Columbus' discovery of America.  To demonstrate his confidence in the new commemorative stamp issues Wanamaker purchased $10,000 worth of stamps with his own money. Harrison was also present at the World Columbian Exposition and ceremony and delivered a speech  &lt;ref name=&quot;Columbian Exposition&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2027851 |publisher=Smithsonian National Postal Museum |title=Columbian Exposition Issues (1893) |accessdate=19 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he said. ''&quot;In the name of the Government and of the people of the United States, I do hereby invite all the nations of the earth to take part in the commemoration of an event that is pre-eminent in human history, and of lasting interest to mankind.&quot;'' The exposition lasted several months and by the time it was over more than $40 million dollars had been generated in commemorative postage stamp sales alone.&lt;ref name=&quot;Columbian Exposition&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JOHN WANAMAKER PMG&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.usps.com/postalhistory/_rtf/PMGWanamaker.rtf. |publisher=United States Postal Service |title=JOHN WANAMAKER, Postmaster General |accessdate=19 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; From that point onward the US Post Office would issue commemorative postage on a regular basis. Harrison appears on four regular issues and on two commemorative issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Benjamin Harrison 1926 Issue-13c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1926&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Benjamin Harrison 1938 Issue-24c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Benjamin Harrison 1959 Issue-12c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1959&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

*  The 1902 13-cent postage stamp was the 1st issue to honor Benjamin Harrison, issued on November 18, 1902, less than two years after his death. It was the first 13-cent stamp issued by the US Post Office,&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; and the first of 14 stamps to be released to the public in the 1902-03 series. The stamp was designed by R. O. Smith from a photograph supplied by Mrs. Harrison. The image was engraved by Marcus W. Baldwin.
* The 1926 issue of Harrison was engraved by [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] who based the image design on the same photograph of Harrison that was used to model the 1902 stamp.
* The 24-cent 1938 issue of Harrison image was inspired by a bust by [[Adolph A. Weinman]], on view at the John Herron Art Institute.
* Harrison's image on the 12-cent 1959 issue was taken from a photograph taken by Charles Parker.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;
* The 22-cent Harrison commemorative stamp was issued on May 22 of 1986 as part of a series of stamps honoring US Presidents, first issued during [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX '86]], the international philatelic show held in Rosemont, Illinois. Artist Jerry Dadds of Baltimore, Maryland, designed the four sheets containing thirty-six stamps. Dadds also executed the designs in the woodcut style. There is only one commemorative stamp that honors Harrison.
* In 2003 the US Post Office issued a 37-cent Old Glory commemorative stamp on April 3, 2003, at the Mega Stamp Show in New York, New York. The stamp was designed by Richard Sheaff. The stamp depicts a 1888 presidential campaign badge with a photograph of Benjamin Harrison at its center. (no image available yet).&lt;ref&gt;[http://arago.si.edu/index.asp?con=1&amp;cmd=1&amp;tid=2045720 Benjamin Harrison at the Smithsonian national Postal Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umass.edu/rso/umassdx/dxabout.html Delta Chi] -- [http://www.ccudeltachi.com/page.php?pageid=2 The Delta Chi Fraternity at Coastal Carolina University ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==William McKinley==

[[William McKinley]] Jr. (January 29, 1843 – September 14, 1901) was the 25th President of the United States, and the last veteran of the [[American Civil War]] to be elected to the office of the President. He was the last American president to serve in the 19th century and was the first President to serve in the 20th century. He spent much of his adult life in politics and was a six-term congressman, and was also the governor of Ohio before wining over [[William J. Bryan]] for two terms in the White House (1897–1901). McKinley was assassinated early in his second term while attending the [[Pan-American Exposition]] in Buffalo in 1901.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:McKinley 1923 Issue-7c.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1923&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:McKinley1904-7.jpg|thumb|240px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1904&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:William McKinley 1938 Issue-25c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* William McKinley appears on three [[Regular Issues of 1922-1931|''Regular Issues'']] of, 1923, 1926 and 1927, the design, color and denomination of which are the same, and on the 1938 Presidential issue, but first appeared on U. S. Postage in a commemorative issue, the [[Louisiana Purchase]] series of 1904. &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

* McKinley was not even alive at the time of the Louisiana Purchase but is depicted on the Louisiana Purchase issue as he was the president who signed the legislation giving federal sanction to the Exposition and would have presided over the Exposition had he lived.  This issue also served as a tribute and memorial to the assassinated leader, as it came out less than than three years after his death, in what would have been nearing the end of the second term to which he was elected in 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;

* The [[Presidential Issue]] of 1938 features McKinley on the 25-cent issue, released 1938.

* The [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|'''22-cent McKinley''']] commemorative stamp was issued on May 22 of 1986 as part of a series of stamps honoring U.S. Presidents, first issued during AMERIPEX '86, the international philatelic show held in Rosemont, Illinois. Artist Jerry Dadds of Baltimore, Maryland, designed the four sheets containing thirty-six stamps. Dadds also executed the designs in the woodcut style. It is one among only two commemorative stamps that honor this president.

==Theodore Roosevelt==

[[Theodore Roosevelt]] (October 27, 1858 – January 6, 1919) was the 26th President of the United States. He served as President from September 14, 1901 – March 4, 1909. In 1901, President William McKinley was assassinated, and Roosevelt became president at the age of 42, taking office at the youngest age of any US President in history at that time. Roosevelt was a hero of the [[Spanish-American War]] and the [[Battle of San Juan Hill]] for which received the [[Medal of Honor]] and was the commander of the infamous [[Rough Riders]]. He negotiated an end to the [[Russo-Japanese War]] which later won him the Nobel Peace Prize.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick W. Marks III, ''Velvet on Iron: The Diplomacy of Theodore Roosevelt'' (1979); Greg Russell, &quot;Theodore Roosevelt's Diplomacy and the Quest for Great Power Equilibrium in Asia,&quot; ''Presidential Studies Quarterly'' 2008 38(3): 433-455&lt;/ref&gt;  Roosevelt was the first American to win the Nobel Peace Prize.
&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; [[File:Theodore Roosevelt 1925 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;The 1st Roosevelt stamp&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt; [[File:30cTR.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt; [[File:Theo Roosevelt 1955 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|160px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1955&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
* [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] designed the 5c blue issue of 1922 and 1925 stamp issues (Identical except for perforations). The Roosevelt image was engraved by John Eissler, and was modeled after a photograph taken of Roosevelt by the firm of Harris &amp; Ewing in Washington, D.C., in 1907.
* The Presidential Issue of 1938 presented Roosevelt on the 30c stamp. The engraving of the president was modeled on a bust displayed in the Senate Gallery US Capitol in Washington, D. C.
* The 6c stamp issued in 1955 was designed by Victor S. McCloskey, Jr., and Charles R. Chickering of the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
* Roosevelt oversaw the construction of the [[Panama Canal]] and consequently he later appeared on two [[Panama Canal Zone|Canal Zone]] postage stamps, printed by the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]] and issued by the U.S Government administration offices in the Canal Zone for domestic mail and for outgoing mail. The first Roosevelt stamp to depict the 26th president was issued in [[commons:File:Roosevelt Canal Zone2.jpg|1949]].

* The 22-cent Roosevelt commemorative stamp was issued on May 22 of 1986 as part of a series of stamps honoring US Presidents, first issued during [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX '86]], the international philatelic show held in Rosemont, Illinois. Artist Jerry Dadds of Baltimore, Maryland, designed the four sheets containing thirty-six stamps. Dadds also executed the designs in the woodcut style. It is the only one commemorative stamp that honors Theodore Roosevelt.

[[File:Roosevelt Canal Zone111.jpg|thumb|230px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1958&lt;/center&gt;]]
* A US Canal Zone stamp honoring Roosevelt was issued in November 1958, the 100th anniversary of his birth. Theodore Roosevelt is the only American president to be honored on a Canal Zone postage stamp.&lt;ref&gt;Scotts U.S. Stamp Catalogue, Canal Zone Postage&lt;/ref&gt;

* On February 2, 1998, the USPS issued a 32 cent stamp honoring Theodore Roosevelt as part of its [[Celebrate the Century]] series.{{clear}}

==William Howard Taft==
[[File:William H Taft 1938 Issue-50c.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:William Howard Taft 1930 Issue-4c.jpg|thumb|left|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1930&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[William Howard Taft]] (September 15, 1857 - March 8, 1930) was the 27th President of the United States and later the 10th Chief Justice of the United States. Taft is the only person to have served in both offices. Born in 1857 in Cincinnati, Ohio, into the powerful Taft family, Taft graduated from Yale College Phi Beta Kappa in 1878,[2] and from Cincinnati Law School in 1880.

* The 4c Taft stamp was issued on June 4 of 1930 in Taft's hometown of Cincinnati, Ohio, less than three months after Taft's death that year on March 8. This issue of Taft is based on the same design as are the regular issues of 1925-32, designed by [[Charles Aubrey Huston]].  The engraving of Taft is modeled after a photograph taken by Harris &amp; Ewing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://broadway.cas.sc.edu/index.php?subaction=dbPage&amp;action=About%20Us Harris &amp; Ewing was a photographic service company founded in 1905 by George W. Harris (1872 - 1964) and Martha Ewing to give Washington DC a studio of photography worthy of being of service to national and worldly dignitaries for producing official and civic portraits and for photojournalism. Dr. David S. Shields]&lt;/ref&gt;

* The 50c Taft on the Presidential issue of 1932 was released on December the 8th of 1938. The engraved profile of Taft was modeled after a bust sculpted especially for the stamp..

* Taft is honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX]] presidential issue of 1986.

==Woodrow Wilson==
[[File:Woodrow Wilson 1925 Issue-17c.jpg|thumb|left|190px|&lt;center&gt;The 1st Wilson stamp&lt;br/&gt;Issue of 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Woodrow Wilson2 1938 Issue-$1.jpg|thumb|170px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Thomas Woodrow Wilson]] (December 28, 1856 – February 3, 1924) was the 28th President of the United States. First known by the slogan &quot;he kept us out of the war&quot;, Wilson was finally pressured in to asking Congress to declare war on Germany who was attacking all US vessels at high sea.

::* Less than a year after the death of Woodrow Wilson the US Post Office on December 28th 1925 issued the black, 17-cent stamp in his honor.  Issued in such a timely manner the 1925 issue can be considered a memorial to Wilson. President Wilson’s widow provided the photograph which designer [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] used for the overall stamp design and which John Eissler of the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]] used as the model for the engraving of Wilson.

::* On August 29th 1938 the Post Office issued the 1 dollar presidential issue.  The engraved image of Wilson was modeled after a medal struck by George Morgan of the US Mint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt;

::* Wilson is honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX presidential series]], issued in 1986.

* On February 2, 1998, the USPS included a Woodrow Wilson stamp as part of its [[Celebrate the Century]] series.

==Warren G. Harding==
[[Image:Warren G Hardiing 1923 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|175px|&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:11pt&quot;&gt;~ Warren G. Harding ~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:8pt&quot;&gt;Memorial Issue of 1923&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
----
Issued only one month after death on Sept 1, 1923 in Harding’s hometown of Marion]]

[[Warren Gamaliel Harding]] (November 2, 1865 – August 2, 1923) was the 29th President of the United States, serving from 1921 until his sudden death from a heart attack in 1923. A Republican from Ohio, Harding was once an influential newspaper publisher at the Marion Daily Star in Ohio. He served in the Ohio Senate (1899–1903) and later as the 28th [[Lieutenant Governor]] of Ohio (1903–1905) and as a US Senator (1915–1921).

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Warren G Hardiing 1925 Issue-1+half-cent.jpg|thumb|133px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1925&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Warren G Hardiing 1930 Issue-1+half-cent.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1930&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Warren G Harding 1938 Issue-$2.jpg|thumb|135px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* Harding's unexpected death prompted the issue of 1923, 2c black, unofficially referred to as the Harding memorial Issue, which [[Clair Aubrey Houston]] managed to design in one day. The engraving of Harding was modeled after an etching by artist F. Pauling.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Identifier&quot;/&gt; Amazingly the Bureau of Engraving and Printing was able to print over one and one half billion of these stamps in a three month period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts Quantity Issued&quot;&gt;Scotts Specialized Catalogue of United States Stamps: Quantities issued&lt;/ref&gt;

* Two years later on May 19, 1925 the Post Office issued a similar Harding stamp, using the same die used for the 1923 Harding Memorial issue and whose color this time was brown and whose denomination was now at 1-1/2 cents. This stamp was one in a series of [[US Regular Issues of 1922-1931|regular issue stamps]] of the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt; Both of these two similar stamps were also issued in imperforate form.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

* In 1930, at the request of the widowed [[Florence Kling Harding|Mrs. Harding]], the U.S. Post Office Department issued a new Harding 1-1/2c issue whose full faced portrait replaced the 1-1/2c issue with his profile.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kenmore&quot;/&gt;

* The image of Harding also appears on the 2-dollar issue of the 1938 [[Presidential Issue|Presidential Series]]. The engraved image of Harding's likeness was modeled after a medal  struck by George Morgan of the US Mint.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt; 
* Harding was also honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX commemorative stamp]] issue of 1986, along with all other American presidents up to and including President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]].

==Calvin Coolidge==
[[File:Calvin Coolidge 1938 Issue-$5.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1938&lt;/center&gt;]]

[[John Calvin Coolidge]], Jr. (July 4, 1872 – January 5, 1933) from Plymouth, Vermont, was the 30th President of the United States serving from 1923 to 1929. Coolidge became president upon the death of [[Warren G. Harding]]. Coolidge's inauguration was the first to be broadcast on radio. On February 22, 1924, he became the first President of the United States to deliver a political speech on radio.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://oldradioshows.org/02/22/calvin-coolidge-the-first-us-president-to-do-a-radio-address-2-22-08|title=Calvin Coolidge, the first President to do a radio address 2-22-1924|date=February 22, 2008|publisher= Old Radio Shows.org|accessdate=2009-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; Known as &quot;silent Cal&quot; for being a man of few words in private while known for being an excellent orator at the pulpit.

* On November 17, 1938 the US Post Office issued the 5 dollar value of the Presidential series of that year.  This remained Coolidge's sole appearance on U. S. stamps until 1986, when the Post Office releases a series of stamps, one honoring each deceased president at that time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt; The model for this engraving was taken from a medal struck by John R. Sinnock of the US Mint. Among the Presidential Issues this stamp is the most difficult to find on cover.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* Coolidge along with all other presidents up to and including President L.B. Johnson is honored on the 1986 [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX commemorative issues]].

Up through Coolidge, every president (with the two exceptions of Monroe and McKinley) had made his first appearance on U. S. Postage in a definitive series, only later being honored by a commemorative stamp.  With subsequent presidents, the reverse is true: all have made their first appearances on commemoratives.

==Herbert Hoover==
[[File:Herbert Hoover 1965 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1965&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Herbert Clark Hoover]] (August 10, 1874 – October 20, 1964) was the 31st President of the United States serving from 1929 to 1933. Hoover was a professional mining engineer and author. A son of a Quaker blacksmith, Hoover brought to the Presidency a reputation for public service as a humanitarian.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.whitehouse.gov/about/presidents/herberthoover White House Archives]&lt;/ref&gt;  After World War I, Hoover had massive shipments of food sent to feed starving millions in central Europe. He also provided much needed aid to Soviet Russia in 1921 which was then plagued with famine.

In spite of Hoover's many humanitarian efforts, as a president, he is ranked less than favorably among many historians for his failure to bring the country out of the great depression that beset the country in 1929, the year Hoover assumed office.

* Issued on his birthday, the 5-cent commemorative issue honoring President Herbert Hoover was first placed on sale on August 10, 1965, at West Branch, Iowa, the place of Hoover's birth. The issue was released less than one year after Hoover's passing in 1964. This is the first US Postage issue Herbert Hoover has appeared on. He appears again on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX series]] issued in 1986.&lt;ref name=&quot;AMERIPEX '86&quot;&gt;Four souvenir miniature stamp sheets, with nine 22-cent stamps each, honoring deceased US presidents were first issued on May 22, 1986, during AMERIPEX '86, the international philatelic show held in Rosemont, Illinois.&lt;/ref&gt; of presidents issued in 1986 &lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts-Commemoratives&quot;/&gt;

* Hoover was honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX commemorative issue]] of 1986 along with all other presidents up to and including Johnson.

==Franklin D. Roosevelt==

[[Franklin Delano Roosevelt]] (January 30, 1882 – April 12, 1945) was the 32nd President of the United States and a leading figure in world events during the mid-20th century, leading the United States during a time of worldwide economic crisis and world war. FD Roosevelt was the only American president elected President for more than two terms.  He forged a durable coalition that realigned American politics for decades. In his first &quot;Hundred Days&quot; in office, beginning March 4, 1933, Roosevelt launched a variety of major social programs. In his first term (1933–36), FDR led Congress to enact the New Deal, a large, complex interlocking set of programs designed to produce social and economic relief.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:FDR33 1966 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|185px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1966&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:FDR 1982 Issue2-20c.jpg|thumb|203px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1982&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* The 6c issue of 1966 was designed by Richard Lyon Clark and was modeled after a photograph of the Roosevelt taken with Winston Churchill during the signing of the Atlantic Charter. This gray brown 6-cent sheet stamp was issued on January 28, 1966, at the Post Office in Hyde Park, New York, the same town where the family home is located.

* On January 30, 1982 on the 100th anniversary of his birth a 20-cent commemorative stamp honoring Franklin Delano Roosevelt was issued, first released to the public at his birthplace, Hyde Park, New York. The First Day of Issue ceremony was held at the Roosevelt estate, where he and his wife, Eleanor, are buried.

* On September 10, 1998 a [[:File:FD Roosevelt 1998 Iaaue2--32c.JPG|32-cent commemorative]] was issued in Roosevelt's honor. The issue depicts Roosevelt at a microphone during one of the &quot;fireside chats&quot; for which the President was famous.

&lt;br/&gt;
Only two months after Roosevelt's death the US Post Office issued a series of four commemorative (or memorial) Postage stamps in honor and memory of the deceased President.

[[File:FDR Set4 1945 Issue.jpg|thumb|center|720px|&lt;center&gt;~ FDR Memorial issues of 1945&lt;/center&gt;]]

* The 1-cent green Franklin D. Roosevelt memorial stamp was issued on July 26, 1945, at the Post Office at Hyde Park, New York. The design depicts an image of the Roosevelt home in Hyde Park, New York.

* The 2c red was issued on August 24, 1945, in Warm Springs, Georgia, the site of Roosevelt's favorite retreat, known as the 'Little White House'.

* Of the four issues in the Franklin memorial series it was the 3c value that was actually the first to be released. The 3c purple Franklin D. Roosevelt memorial stamp was issued on June 27, 1945. The design features the White House in the background.

* The 5c blue issue is the last of the Roosevelt memorial series, issued on January 30, 1946. The design depicts a portrait of Roosevelt and on the left surrounded by clouds, a globe showing the Americas on the right. Inscribed across the globe is an expression of the Four Freedoms — 'Freedom of Speech and Religion, From Want and Fear'.

* Roosevelt was honored on the AMERIPEX commemorative stamp issue of 1986 along with all other presidents up to and including Johnson.

==Harry S. Truman==
[[File:Harry S TRuman 1973 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1973&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Harry S. Truman]] (May 8, 1884 – December 26, 1972) was the 33rd President of the United States serving from 1945 to 1953. As President Franklin D. Roosevelt's third vice-president and the 34th Vice President of the United States, he succeeded to the presidency on April 12, 1945, when President Roosevelt died less than three months after beginning his historic fourth term. Truman began his political career in politics as a county judge in 1922. He was Franklin D. Roosevelt's running mate in 1944.

* The 8-cent Harry S. Truman postage stamp was designed by Bradbury Thompson and first placed on sale at the Post Office at Independence, Missouri, on May 8, 1973.

* The 20-cent Truman definitive stamp was issued on January 26, 1984, in Washington, DC. The 1984 stamp issue honored the centennial of the birth of the 33rd US president in 1884.

* Truman along with all other presidents up to and including President L.B. Johnson, were honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|'''AMERIPEX commemorative stamp''']] issue of 1986.

*On September 2, 1995, the USPS issued a 29 cent stamp showing Truman announcing Japan's surrender as part of its World War II 50th anniversary series.

* Truman was depicted on a 32 cent stamp issued on February 18, 1999 as part of the [[Celebrate the Century]] series.

==Dwight D. Eisenhower==

[[Dwight David Eisenhower]] (October 14, 1890 &amp;ndash; March 28, 1969) was a five-star general in the United States Army and the 34th President of the United States, serving from 1953 until 1961. During World War II, he served as Supreme Commander of the Allied forces in Europe and planned the successful invasion of France and Germany in 1944–45, from the Western Front. In 1951, he became the first supreme commander of NATO.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Eisenhower 1970 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|115px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1970&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Eisenhower 1971 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|130px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1971&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Eisenhower multi 1971 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|125px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1971&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:Eisenhower 1969 Issue-6c.jpg|thumb|155px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1969&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On August 6, 1970 the Post Office began releasing the Regular issues of 1970 &amp;ndash; 1974. President Eisenhower is depicted on the 6c denomination of these issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;
* On May 16, 1971 the domestic first-class letter rate increased to eight cents so the BEPthe 6-cent Eisenhower stamp was re-engraved with the new 8-cent denomination. The stamp was issued in sheet, coil, and booklet formats. The red and black stamp was the first and only multicolored stamp of the Prominent American Issue. The coil and booklet issues were mono-colored claret stamps printed on the Huck/Cottrell web mono-color intaglio presses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;  Two varieties exist, one with a dot between &quot;Eisenhower&quot; and &quot;USA&quot; and one without.  Both were issued in large numbers.
* In 1969 the US Post Office issued a 6-cent commemorative stamp honoring President Dwight D. Eisenhower, introduced on October 14 of that year at Abilene, Kansas, the city where he spent his youth and was eventually buried.  Uncommonly larger than the standard commemorative sizes of 1-1/2&quot; x 1&quot;  this issue's size was 2&quot; x 1-1/4&quot;.  The Eisenhower commemorative issue was designed by Robert J. Jones of the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]] and was fashioned after a photograph taken by Bernie Noble of the Cleveland Press.
* The US Post Office issued a 25c stamp on October 13, 1990, in Abilene, Kansas.  The central  image is taken from the official White House portrait, while background depicts a younger Eisenhower as a General, speaking to Allied troops on the eve of D-Day, the Normandy invasion in 1944. The stamp was designed by Ken Hodges of the [[American Bank Note Company]] &lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
* Eisenhower along with all other presidents up to and including President L.B. Johnson, were honored on the [[U.S. Presidents on U.S. postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX commemorative issue]] of 1986.{{clear}}

==John F. Kennedy==

[[John Fitzgerald Kennedy]] was the 35th President of the United States, serving from 1961 until his assassination in 1963 on November 22. Few American Presidents have quotes that are remembered long after their deaths, and Kennedy was among those few for saying to the nation, ''&quot;Ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country.&quot;''  He was the second-youngest President (after [[Theodore Roosevelt]]). Kennedy was faced with a number of important events during his term as President which include the [[Cuban Missile Crisis]], the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]], the [[Space Race]] and the  [[Berlin Wall]] crisis. Kennedy appears on three postage issues, two of them commemoratives (1964 and 1986), the other a regular issue of 1967.

&lt;center&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;[[File:John F Kennedy 1964 Issue-5c.jpg|thumb|220px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1964&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;td&gt;[[File:John F Kennedy 1967 Issue-13c.jpg|thumb|145px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1967&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

* On May 29, 1964, the US Post Office released the [[Five cents John Kennedy|5c John F. Kennedy memorial stamp]] on what would have been Kennedy's 47th birthday. The issue was designed by Raymond Loewy/William Snaith, a New York firm, based on a sketch by the [[Bureau of Engraving and Printing]] artist Robert L. Miller. Mrs. Jacqueline Kennedy made the final selection from the many postage stamp designs that were submitted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;

* The 13 cent issue of 1967 was first issued in Brookline, Massachusetts, on May 29 of that year. The issue was designed by Stevan Dohanos, modeled after a photograph by Jacques Loew in the book ''The Kennedy Years''. The 13-cent Kennedy stamp paid the rates for both foreign surface letters and air postcards.

* Kennedy, like all other presidents up to and including President L.B. Johnson, was honored on the AMERIPEX commemorative issue of 1986. 

{{clear}}

==Lyndon B. Johnson==
[[File:L B Johnson 1973 Issue-8c.jpg|thumb|140px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1973&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Lyndon B. Johnson]] (August 27, 1908 &amp;ndash; January 22, 1973), served as vice-president during the Kennedy administration. When Kennedy was assassinated in Dallas, Texas, on November 22, 1963, Johnson assumed the presidency. He won re-election in 1964 with 61 percent of the vote and served until January 20, 1969.

::* On August 27th of 1973 the US Post Office issued the 8-cent Lyndon B. Johnson memorial postage stamp, first placed on sale at the Post Office in Austin, Texas,   The stamp was designed by Bradbury Thompson.

::* Johnson's last appearance (to date) on a US Postage stamp occurred in 1986 where he is honored on one of a series of stamps called the [[US Presidents on US postage stamps#AMERIPEX issues of 1986|AMERIPEX issues of 1986]]. The Post Office declined to commemorate his centennial in 2008. {{clear}}

==Richard M. Nixon==

[[File:Richard M Nixon 1995 Issue-32c.jpg|thumb|120px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 1995&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Richard Milhous Nixon]], (January 9, 1913 – April 22, 1994) was the thirty-seventh president of the United States. Nixon's political career started as a California congressman. He was Dwight D. Eisenhower's vice president for two terms and was defeated in 1960 by John F. Kennedy for the presidential election. In 1968, Nixon won the presidency and was overwhelmingly re-elected in 1972. Nixon was the only person to be elected twice to both the Presidency and the Vice Presidency. He was also the only US President to resign the office.  Nixon was instrumental in ending U.S. involvement in the Vietnam War and establishing U.S. relations with communist China.

* On April 26, 1995, one year and four days after his death the US Postal Service honored Richard Nixon with the issuance of a 32-cent commemorative stamp, first released in Yorba Linda, California, the place of his birth, to date the only stamp depicting Nixon. The issue was designed by Daniel Schwarz, and printed in combination offset-intaglio process by the [[Banknote Corporation of America]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Smithsonian&quot;/&gt;
{{clear}}

==Gerald Ford==
[[File:Gerald Ford2-41c.jpg|thumb|left|120px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 2007&lt;center&gt;]]

[[Gerald Rudolph Ford, Jr.]] (born Leslie Lynch King, Jr.; July 14, 1913 - December 26, 2006) was the 38th President of the United States, serving from 1974 to 1977, and the 40th Vice President of the United States serving from 1973 to 1974. Ford was the first person appointed to the vice-presidency under the terms of the 25th Amendment, filling the vacancy left by [[Spiro Agnew]]. He became President upon Richard Nixon's resignation on August 9, 1974,.

::::::* Gerald Ford Memorial Commemorative issued August 31, 2007. {{clear}}

==Ronald Reagan==
[[File:Ronald Reagan 2005 Issue-37c.jpg|thumb|120px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 2005&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:Ronald Reagan stamp 2011.jpg|thumb|150px|&lt;center&gt;Issue of 2011&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[Ronald Reagan|Ronald Wilson Reagan]], born February 6, 1911, died June 5, 2004. Reagan was the 40th President of the United States and served two terms from 1981 to 1989, and the 33rd Governor of California (1967–1975). Born in  [[Tampico, Illinois|Tampico]], Illinois. Among other things, Reagan is remembered for saying on June 12, 1987.. &quot;Mr. Gorbachev, tear down this wall!&quot;

* The U.S. Postal Service issued a 37-cent Ronald Reagan commemorative stamp on February 9, 2005. The first day of issue occurred in [[Simi Valley]], California. Stamp design is by Howard E. Paine,  [[Delaplane, Virginia|Delaplane]], Virginia. The image of Reagan was modeled after a portrait painted by award-winning artist Michael J. Deas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;  However, on June 14, 2006, the stamp was reissued with a 39-cent valuation to match the new first-class postage rate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/us-postal-service-reissues-president-ronald-reagan-stamp-in-39-cent-denomination-56136597.html U.S. Postal Service Reissues President Ronald Reagan Stamp in 39 Cent Denomination]&lt;/ref&gt;

* To mark the centennial of Reagan's birth in 2011, the U.S. Postal Service issued a commemorative stamp to be officially released at the [[Reagan Presidential Library]] in Simi Valley on Feb. 10, 2011, four days after the 100th anniversary of Reagan's birth on February 6. Texas artist [[Bart Forbes]] created the portrait, based on a 1985 photograph of Reagan taken at Reagan's ranch, [[Rancho del Cielo]], near  [[Santa Barbara, California|Santa Barbara]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2010/dec/13/reagan-birth-centennial-stamp-debuts/ | work=The Washington Times | title=Postage stamp to honor Reagan | date=2010-12-13 | accessdate=2011-01-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clear}}

==AMERIPEX issues of 1986==
[[File:AMERIPEX 1986.jpg|thumb|400px|&lt;center&gt;AMERIPIC issues of 1986&lt;/center&gt;]]
&lt;br /&gt;
:On May 22nd of 1986 the US Post Office released a series of [[postage stamp]]s with a portrait of a past US President inscribed upon each one. The series of 36 stamps were issued in four separate mini-sheets, with nine stamps to the sheet, each stamp having a denomination of 22 cents. Several of the issues honor presidents who had never appeared on a US [[commemorative stamp]] before. On 'sheet IV' the stamp in the middle depicts the White House entrance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scotts&quot;/&gt;{{clear}}

== See also ==
{{Div col|cols=2}}
* [[Washington-Franklin Issues]]
* [[Template:Washington-Franklin Issue|Washington-Franklins chart]]
* [[US Regular Issues of 1922-1931]]
* [[commons:Category:George Washington on stamps|'''George Washington on stamps''']]
* [[commons:Category:Benjamin Franklin on stamps|'''Benjamin Franklin on stamps''']]
* [[commons:Category:Abraham Lincoln on stamps|'''Abraham Lincoln on stamps''']]
* '''[[Gilbert Stuart]]'''
* [[1932 Washington Bicentennial]]
* [[Bicentennial Series]]
* [[Presidential Issue]]
* [[Great Americans series]]
* [[Liberty Issue]]
* [[List of Presidents of the United States]]
* [[Founding Fathers of the United States]]
* [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States]]
* [[Postage stamps and postal history of the Confederate States]]
* [[Prominent Americans series]]
* [[:File:Stamp US 1873 3c official war dept.jpg|Washington on official War Dept stamp, 1873 issue]]
{{Div col end}}
&lt;!--&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:white; border:solid 4px steelblue&quot;&gt;
{| class=&quot;navbox collapsible collapsed&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left; border: 3px; margin-top: 0.0em;&quot;
! style=&quot;background-color:LightSteelBlue; text-align: center&quot; |'''Wiki' Policy Nav'''
|-
|&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:wheat; border:solid 3px steelblue&quot;&gt;

* [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (linking)#Repeated links|'''Repeated links''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (linking)#Overlinking and underlinking|'''Overlinking and underlinking''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style (linking)#What generally should not be linked|'''What generally should not be linked''']]

&lt;/div style&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:ivory; border:solid 3px steelblue&quot;&gt;

* [[Wikipedia:Image use policy#Displayed image size|'''MOS - Image size /''' &quot;...a good reason to do so...&quot; + &quot;...500 pixels tall and 400 pixels wide, so that they can comfortably be displayed on the smallest displays...&quot;]]

* [[Wikipedia:Writing better articles#Provide context for the reader|'''Writing better articles''']]

&lt;/div style&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:beige; border:solid 3px steelblue&quot;&gt;

* [[Wikipedia:Edit warring#The three-revert rule|'''The three-revert rule''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Reverting#When to revert|'''When to revert''']]

* [[Help:Edit summary#Always provide an edit summary|'''Always provide an edit summary''']]

&lt;/div style&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;background-color:LemonChiffon; border:solid 3px steelblue&quot;&gt;

* [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing|'''Disruptive editing''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing#Signs of disruptive editing|'''Signs of disruptive editing''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing#Signs of disruptive editing|'''Repeatedly disregards other editors' questions or requests for explanations concerning edits or objections to edits; Repeatedly disregards other editors' explanations for their edits.]]

* [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing#Signs of disruptive editing|'''Rejects or ignores community input:''']]

* [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing#Signs of disruptive editing|'''Campaign to drive away productive contributors''']]
&lt;/div style&gt;
|}
&lt;/div style&gt;--&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.americantopicalassn.org/ American Topical Association]
* [http://www.postalmuseum.si.edu/symposium2010/abstracts.html Smithsonian National Postal Museum]&lt;br /&gt; Winton M. Blount, Postal History Symposium, Post Civil War Nationalism&lt;br /&gt;and the Designs of United States Stamps in the Nineteenth Century
* [http://stampdata.com/ STAMPDATA]
* [http://learnaboutstamps.com LearnAboutStamps.com] A resource for stamp collectors
* [http://stamps.colnect.com/en/stamps/tags Topical worldwide stamps catalog]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Washington, George}}
[[Category:Postage stamps of the United States|Presidents]]
[[Category:Presidents of the United States| Postage]]
[[Category:Topical postage stamps]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
