<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27755075" ns="0" title="Meridian Knowledge Solutions"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox company
| company_name     = &lt;small&gt;Meridian Knowledge Solutions, LLC&lt;/small&gt;
| company_logo     = [[File:Meridian globe 200.jpg|Meridian Logo]]
| company_type     = Private
| industry         = [[Software]]
| slogan           = The Learning-Technology Company
| location_city    = Herndon, Va., United States U.S.
| key_people       = Roy Haythorn (Executive Vice President of Operations)
| num_employees    = Approximately 100  (2010)
| homepage         = [http://www.meridianksi.com meridianksi.com]
}}

Founded in 1997, '''Meridian Knowledge Solutions''' is a software company based in [[Herndon, Virginia|Herndon, Va.]], that provides a [[learning management system]], also known as a LMS, for delivering and tracking training via the Internet.  The Meridian LMS integrates general learning management functions (e.g., course catalogs, enrollments) with collaboration software and performance management features such as employee development plans and skill assessments&lt;ref&gt;T+D magazine, &quot;Managing Learning in More Than One Way,&quot; page 60, June 2011&lt;/ref&gt;.  The company is a wholly owned subsidiary of Visionary Integration Professionals, a Calif.-based technology and outsourcing firm&lt;ref&gt;Gartner, &quot;Magic Quadrant for Corporate Learning Systems,&quot; J. Freyermuth, J. Holincheck, T. Otter, March 24, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;.  In the fall of 2009, IT Training magazine ranked Meridian as the fifth-largest LMS/LCMS provider globally in terms of revenue behind SumTotal, Saba, Plateau and Mzinga&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bcs.org/upload/pdf/ittraining-autumn09_1.pdf IT Training magazine, page 24, Autumn 2009 edition]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Corporate history==
In 1997, Jennifer Beers, David DeVaux, Elizabeth Harris, Malcolm Patel and Paul Somerville founded Meridian KSI, now known as Meridian Knowledge Solutions, LLC. According to Harris, prior to launching Meridian, each founder was part of the senior leadership team of the training division of Universal Systems Inc.  Universal Systems' training division provided an array of training products including electronic media and distance learning software, with most of the division's work focused on custom courseware development and training management software.  In 1997, the five founders departed USI, produced a standards-based software application to track, manage and deliver web-based content and formed Meridian.  Several months later, says Harris, Meridian's founders released the first version of the newly created company's LMS, known as the Meridian Knowledge Centre.  The five founders developed and sold LMS software to capitalize on a market for [[e-learning]] as well as [[knowledge management]].  The focus on the latter differentiated Meridian from its LMS competitors and helped the organization to win a number of high-profile contracts with organizations such as the FBI in the early 2000s&lt;ref&gt;[http://fcw.com/articles/2002/12/08/fbi-creates-online-training-hub.aspx?sc_lang=en Federal Compuer Week &quot;FBI creates online training hub,&quot; Dec. 8, 2002, by Jennifer Jones]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In 2006, Meridian's co-founders agreed to become a wholly owned subsidiary of Visionary Integration Professionals.

In 2008, Beers, DeVaux, Harris, Patel and Somerville left Meridian to pursue other interests.

The year 2009 may have been difficult for some companies in the learning and development industry. Meridian, however, experienced a very strong year&lt;ref&gt;[http://members.brandon-hall.com/content/product-briefing-report-meridian-knowledge-solutions Brandon Hall Research Center, June 29, 2010, Richard Nantel and Tom Werner]&lt;/ref&gt;.  The company's revenue grew 28% and its earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization grew 40%.

==Noteworthy==
Gartner, Inc. has positioned Meridian in the “visionaries” quadrant of the 2008, 2009 and 2010 “Corporate Learning Systems Magic Quadrant“&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gartner.com/technology/media-products/reprints/saba/170409.html Gartner, &quot;Magic Quadrant for Corporate Learning Systems,&quot; Carol Rozwell, September 10, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;.

Since 2003, the U.S. Army has used Meridian's software to develop the professional skills of civilian employees of the Department of the Army who are charged with improving the quality of life for soldiers and families billeted around the globe. Meridian's work for the Army won a Bronze Award for &quot;Excellence in LMS&quot; from Chief Learning Officer magazine in 2010&lt;ref&gt;[http://clomedia.com/articles/view/excellence-in-lms/2 Chief Learning Officer magazine, page 60, December 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;.

In 2008, Chief Learning Officer magazine awarded Meridian a Gold Award for &quot;Excellence in Customer Service&quot; for the company's work in reducing the cost of training for U.S. Customs and Border Protection.  Meridian's LMS became the foundation for CBP's Virtual Learning Center&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.clomedia.com/features/2008/December/2484/index.php?pt=a&amp;aid=2484&amp;start=104774&amp;page=34 Chief Learning Officer magazine, page 71, December 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Partial List of Products==
Learning Management Software
*Meridian Global LMS is a learning management system for delivering and tracking training via the Internet.
*Meridian Anywhere Mobile LMS is a desktop software application for delivering e-learning content to students without a hardwired connection to a learning management system.  Training departments can use the tool as a mobile LMS application or a multi-user training kiosk.
Analysis Software
*Meridian's Workforce Analytics is software that managers can use to report on the number of students enrolled in training, their grades, skill level and pending training requests.

==See also==
* [[e-learning]]
* [[Knowledge management]]
* [[Knowledge management software]]
* [[Learning Management System]]
* [[List of learning management systems]]

==References==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.meridianksi.com/ MeridianKSI.com]
* [http://www.vipconsulting.com/ Visionary Integration Professionals]
* [http://washington.bizjournals.com/washington/stories/2009/05/04/story4.html/ Washington Business Journal Reports on Meridian's Marine Corps Contracts]
&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

[[Category:Software companies of the United States]]
[[Category:Educational technology]]
[[Category:Virtual learning environments]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1997]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
