<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27851220" ns="0" title="Wind ENergy Data &amp; Information (WENDI) Gateway"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''The Wind ENergy Data &amp; Information (WENDI) Gateway''' was launched by the Environmental Sciences Division of [[Oak Ridge National Laboratory]] in March 2010 to support the [[United States Department of Energy]]'s Wind &amp; Hydropower Technologies Program.&lt;ref&gt;Oak Ridge National Laboratory, [http://windenergy.ornl.gov/content/about-wendi-gateway &quot;About the WENDI Gateway&quot;]. 25 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  Because the wind energy industry is developing at a rapid pace, researchers may spend more time locating and accessing wind energy-related data than actually analyzing it.  The WENDI Gateway thus takes a standards-based, [[Digital library|virtual repository]] approach to provide users with an easier way to discover, access, and download such data.&lt;ref&gt;Kaiser, Dale, &quot;WENDI | Wind ENergy Data &amp; Information Gateway: An Online System for Discovering, Acquiring, and Visualizing
Wind Energy-Related Information and Resources.&quot; Oak Ridge National Laboratory Presentation. 2 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; As a virtual data repository, the WENDI Gateway provides access to wind energy-related data and information from a wide spectrum of sources—including data centers, scientific and technical journals, and [[geographic information system]]s (GIS), as well as the websites of government agencies, corporations, trade organizations, and more.

==Components==
Currently, the WENDI Gateway comprises two main components: the Wind Energy Metadata Clearinghouse and the Wind Energy WebGIS Application.  The WENDI Gateway now also provides pages about the basics of how wind energy works, lists of major turbine manufacturers, a list of renewable resource educational programs, and a page about wind energy's effects on wildlife.

===Wind Energy Metadata Clearinghouse===
The Wind Energy Metadata Clearinghouse already includes thousands of metadata records related to wind energy, and is continually growing.  These metadata records provide users with easy access to data and information from a variety of resources, such as peer-reviewed journal articles, government agency reports, private industry reports, GIS services, datasets, and news articles.  Users can search the Clearinghouse's metadata records by a simple keyword search or narrow their results using more specific filters, including publication date and geographic area.&lt;ref&gt;Oak Ridge National Laboratory, [http://windenergy.ornl.gov/metadata &quot;Wind Search | WENDI&quot;]. 28 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Researchers can then search and scan these metadata records to grasp the vital information—title, author, abstract, and other bibliographic elements—about each resource, quickly assessing its potential usefulness for their work.  In many metadata records, a URL to the resource itself is provided, such that those potentially useful resources may be readily viewed in their entirety.

===Wind Energy GIS===
[[File:WENDI Wiki Photo 1.jpg|thumb|WENDI Wind GIS Home]] The Wind Energy GIS allows users to view wind energy-related spatial data with a standard web browser.  The Wind Energy GIS currently features 10 categories of data layers: Background; Wind Energy-Related; Transmission &amp; Infrastructure; Geopolitical; Hydrology; Land Ownership, Designation &amp; Usage; Elevation; Land Cover; Ecosystem &amp; Climate; and Soils.

====Layers====
The user may select from five options for the Wind Energy GIS background:
* [[Terraserver]]-USGS topographic map
* [[Terraserver]] Digital Ortho-Quadrangle
* JPL Landsat Global Mosaic
* [[Terraserver]] Urban Areas
* [[Bing Maps]] Virtual Earth

Wind energy-related data layers include the location of U.S. wind energy power plants; the NREL Wind Power Classification map; state-by-state Renewable Portfolio Standards, and installed wind capacity by state. Transmission &amp; Infrastructure layers include the location of Transmission Lines (as shown by a 1993 report by [[FEMA]], [[NEXRAD]] RADAR sites, location of airports, location of railroads, and an open street map. Geopolitical layers can be used to view 110th Congressional Districts of the US, country boundary, US states, US counties, and the population of US counties. 

The Hydrology layer allows the user to view the US river network. Land Ownership, Designation &amp; Usage layers illustrate the boundaries of federal lands and Indian lands, as well as the renewable energy generation potential on [[United States Environmental Protection Agency|Environmental Protection Agency]] tracked sites according to the Office of Solid Waste and Emergency Response (OSWER) Center for Program Analysis (OCPA). Users can activate the Elevation or Land Cover layers to view related information.

The Ecosystem &amp; Climate layers can be activated to display the following:

* Average Annual Precipitation (1961–1990)
* Tornadoes (1950–2004)
* Major Landfalling Atlantic Hurricanes
* Ecoregions of North America
* Bailey [[Ecoregion]]
* [[Köppen climate classification]]

Users can also view the ranges of five bat species of concern.  Bats have been killed by wind turbines because the spinning blades cause a drop in air pressure.  This reduction in air pressure results in [[barotrauma]] in the bats.

Finally, the Soils layer illustrates [[FAO soil classification]]s across the country.

&lt;ref&gt;Oak Ridge National Laboratory, [http://windenergy.ornl.gov/gis &quot;Wind GIS | WENDI&quot;]. 25 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Target Audience==
Many factors must be considered before the construction of a wind energy facility.  Among the most important factors to consider are the potential site's wind resource; access to existing transmission lines; access to a reliable power purchaser or market; and population density around the site.  Numerous other economic, geographic, environmental, and political considerations must be taken into account as well.
&lt;ref&gt;American Wind Energy Association [http://www.awea.org/pubs/factsheets/10stwf_fs.pdf &quot;10 Steps in Building a Wind Farm&quot;]. 25 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  The WENDI Gateway has been designed to provide data and information regarding such considerations and thereby serve the needs of an array of wind energy stakeholders.  Such stakeholders likely include:

* [[Wind farm]] developers and constructors
* [[Public utilities commission]]s
* [[List of United States electric companies|Electric companies]]
* Policymakers
* [[Environmental scientist]]s
* Wind energy modelers/[[Wind power forecasting|forecasters]]
* Academia
* Students and educators

&lt;ref&gt;Oak Ridge National Laboratory, [http://windenergy.ornl.gov/content/welcome &quot;Welcome to the Wind ENergy Data &amp; Information Gateway | WENDI&quot;]. 25 June 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Wind power]]
* [[Wind power in the United States]]
* [[GIS]]

==References==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://windenergy.ornl.gov/ windenergy.ornl.gov] Enter the WENDI Gateway
* [http://twitter.com/WENDI_Gateway WENDI's Twitter]
* [http://www.facebook.com/home.php?#!/pages/WENDI-Wind-ENergy-Data-Information-Gateway/123694054338470?ref=ts WENDI's Facebook Page]

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

[[Category:Wind power]]
[[Category:Wind power in the United States]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
