<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27882935" ns="0" title="New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
|name = New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics
|image = [[Image:NewMexicoSchoolofNaturalTherapeutics-logo.gif|100 px]]
|established = 1974
|type = Non-profit education institution
|location = 202 Morningside Drive SE
|city = [[Albuquerque]] 
|state = [[New Mexico]] 
|country =  USA
|tuition       = US $8,000
|website = http://www.nmsnt.org
}}

The '''New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics''' is a [[natural therapy]] and [[massage]] school located in [[Albuquerque]], [[New Mexico]]. The school is often referred to by its initials, NMSNT.

==History==

Founded in 1974 by David Tinkle as the New Mexico School of Therapeutic Massage. In 1976 Tinkle retired leaving Robert Stevens and Charles Brown with ownership of the school. In 1978, the name was changed to the New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, and the curriculum was broadened beyond therapeutic massage, using the philosophy of [[Henry Lindlahr]], M.D. as the foundation&lt;ref name=&quot;bare_url&quot;&gt;Lindlahr, H: ''The Philosophy of Natural Therapeutics''  http://books.google.com/books?id=CCDrK08LnpgC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=The%20Philosophy%20of%20Natural%20Therapeutics&amp;pg=PP1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;.

Robert Stevens is the Director of New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics. 
Don Cornwell, who arrived at the school in 1979, is the Director of Education.

Non-profit status was granted in 1980.&lt;ref name=&quot;RobertStevens&quot;&gt;Robert Stevens, online correspondence, May 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The school's Natural Remedy Store was started in 1976 under the name Herbal Apothecary.  The name was later changed to the Herb Store, which is still in existence but no longer affiliated with the school. 

The main building on campus was purchased of the [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Santa Fe]] in 1998&lt;ref name=&quot;RobertStevens&quot; /&gt;. The Natural Remedy Store and Student Clinic annex was purchased several years later with a donation from a graduate's father.&lt;ref name=&quot;RobertStevens&quot; /&gt;

==Philosophy==

The school's core philosophy is based upon the work of [[Henry Lindlahr]] &lt;ref name=&quot;bare_url&quot; /&gt;. Considered the father of  modern, western Natural Therapeutics &lt;ref&gt;George Jean Nathan, Henry Louis Mencken (1950). ''American Mercury Magazine'', 70(543).&lt;/ref&gt;, he developed and directed a school and sanitarium that taught and tested the use of natural practices to aid the healing of disease and injury. Lindlahr’s school became the model for modern naturopathic medical colleges.&lt;ref&gt;Baer, H:  ''Toward an integrative medicine: merging alternative therapies with biomedicine'', page 36. Rowman Altamira, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lindlahr describes how nature heals and he viewed the acute process as the body’s attempt to heal itself of accumulated waste products. Accordingly, the more successful someone is at suppressing symptoms during the acute process, the weaker the body’s capacity to heal itself.

==Curriculum==

The healing modalities taught at the New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics—and the lifestyle it encourages—have been designed to promote health by supporting natural healing processes, rather than by fighting the symptoms of disease. 

The school teaches multiple aspects of natural therapeutics and massage, which have been used by indigenous cultures throughout the world&lt;ref&gt;Salvo, S: ''Massage Therapy Principles and Practice'', pages 4-9.  Saunders, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;.  Specifically, the New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics focuses on clinical practice, principally centered upon two systems of bodywork: [[Massage|Therapeutic Massage]] and [[Polarity therapy|Polarity Therapy]]. Also included are [[Anatomy]] &amp; [[Physiology]], [[Chinese Medicine]] and [[Acupressure]], [[Shiatsu]], [[Reflexology]], [[Herbalism|Herbal Medicine]], [[Bach flower remedies|Flower Remedies]] (Bach, Stevens), [[Joint mobilization|Joint Mobilization Techniques]] and others.

Introductory courses offered by the school that are atypical of most massage therapy schools include Homeopathic First Aid, Core Synchronism, [[Craniosacral therapy|Cranial-Sacral Therapy]], Principles of [[Colonics|Colon Therapy]], Living Foods [[Nutrition]], [[Essential Oils]] and [[Radionics]].

==Programs==
{{Unreferencedsection|date=November 2011}}
* '''Day program''' - Students attend this full time program Monday - Friday for 6 months. Full time &quot;Day Programs&quot; begin the second Tuesday in March and September.  Graduates receive a diploma after 800-hours of instruction with internship in clinical massage therapy and natural therapeutics.
* '''Morning program''' - Students attend this part time program 9am - 1pm Monday - Thursday. When &quot;Morning Program&quot; students begin doing their internship hours in the student clinic, class time becomes 9am - 1pm Monday - Wednesday.  The &quot;Morning Program&quot; begins mid - way through October and continues for 1 year. Graduates receive a diploma after 800-hours of instruction and internship in clinical massage therapy and natural therapeutics.
* '''Night program''' - Students attend this part time program 6pm - 10pm Monday - Thursday. When &quot;Night Program&quot; students begin doing their internship hours in the student clinic, class time becomes 6pm - 10pm Monday - Wednesday.  The &quot;Night Program&quot; begins the second Tuesday in May and continues for 1 year. Graduates receive a diploma after 800-hours of instruction and internship in clinical massage therapy and natural therapeutics.
* '''Graduate Work program''' - Upon graduating temporary licenses are issued by the New Mexico Massage Board. Graduates may then begin paid work at the student clinic as a professional therapist.
* '''Workshops''' - The New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics offers workshops on health and related therapies, open to anyone with an interest, with no prior experience necessary,  and for those interested in need of continuing education credits.

==Noteworthy==

* Among the oldest massage schools in the USA.&lt;ref&gt;The school incorporated in 1974. There were only a few other schools prior, including the Swedish Institute (1916); Central Mass School of Massage and Therapy (1970); East West College in Portland, OR (1972).&lt;/ref&gt;
* Offers certification for both massage therapy and natural therapeutics.
* Popular massage therapy textbook author [[Susan Salvo]] &lt;ref&gt;''Massage Therapy: Principles and Practice''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Mosby's Pathology for Massage Therapists''&lt;/ref&gt; graduated from the New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics in 1982.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lamassageschool.com/faculty/susangsalvo.php&lt;/ref&gt;
* Birthplace of [[Core Synchronism]].&lt;ref&gt;Stevens, R (1995):'' What Is Core Synchronism?'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Press==
* &quot;The Human Condition: Why We Cuddle,&quot; ''Los Angeles Times'' &lt;ref&gt;http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/60331728.html?dids=60331728:60331728&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Jun+30%2C+1993&amp;author=MICHAEL+HAEDERLE&amp;pub=Los+Angeles+Times+(pre-1997+Fulltext)&amp;desc=THE+HUMAN+CONDITION+%2F+WHY+WE+CUDDLE+The+Caress+We+Love+Best&amp;pqatl=google&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Hot-stone therapy heats up in D.C. | Medium is massage,&quot; ''The Washington Times'' &lt;ref&gt;http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=WT&amp;p_theme=wt&amp;p_action=search&amp;p_maxdocs=200&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;The Spiritual Side of Care ‘An Honor,’&quot; ''Albuquerque Journal'' &lt;ref&gt;http://www.accessmylibrary.com/article-1G1-107066582/spiritual-side-care-honor.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Pounding Home Message On Massage,&quot; ''Rocky Mountain News'' &lt;ref&gt;http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product=RM&amp;p_theme=rm&amp;p_action=search&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Massage Works Wonders On The Stress Ridden,&quot; ''The Pittsburgh Press'' &lt;ref&gt;http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=yeIhAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=9mIEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=new-mexico-school-of-natural-therapeutics&amp;pg=5199%2C7331702&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Life affirming artist's work is a harmony of body, spirit,&quot;  ''Star-News'' &lt;ref&gt;http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=zMUsAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=EhQEAAAAIBAJ&amp;dq=new-mexico%20therapeutic-massage&amp;pg=6925%2C366682&lt;/ref&gt;
* &quot;Former dancer quit retail job to follow her dreams,&quot; ''Bermuda Sun'' &lt;ref&gt;http://bermudasun.bm/main.asp?SectionID=72&amp;SubSectionID=205&amp;ArticleID=29188&amp;TM=46537.29&lt;/ref&gt;

==Papers &amp; published works==

# Cornwell, D (2003). ''Meridian-Based Acupressure'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Cornwell, D (2003). ''Shiatsu'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Cornwell, D (2003). ''Introduction to Windows of the Sky'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Cornwell, D (2003). ''Frequently Used Chinese Herbal Patent Formulas'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Stevens, R (1977). ''Mental/Emotional Provings'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Stevens, R and Cornwell, D (1977). ''Polarity'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Stevens, R (1976). ''Nonspecific Stretches'',  New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque
# Stevens, R (1995). ''What Is Core Synchronism?'', New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.
# Stevens, R (1990). ''Essential Essence Formulas'' New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics, Albuquerque.

== References ==
{{cleanup-link rot|date=November 2011}}{{ISBN|date=November 2011}}
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://nmsnt.org/ New Mexico School of Natural Therapeutics's homepage]
*[http://www.coresynch.org/page.cfm?p=95 Core Synchronism homepage]

{{coord|35|4|41.1|N|106|35|58.8|W|region:US|display=title}}

[[Category:Alternative medical systems]]
[[Category:Naturopathic medicine| ]]
[[Category:Simple living]]
[[Category:Vitalism]]
[[Category:Whole medical systems]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
