<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27900915" ns="0" title="Temple of Artemis"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|other shrines dedicated to Artemis|Temple of Artemis (disambiguation)}}
{{coord|37|56|59|N|27|21|50|E|type:landmark_source:dewiki|display=title}}
[[File:Miniaturk 009.jpg|thumb|300px|Model of Temple of Artemis, [[Miniatürk]] Park, Istanbul, Turkey]]

The '''Temple of Artemis''' ({{lang-gr|Ἀρτεμίσιον}}, or ''Artemision''), also known less precisely as the '''Temple of [[Diana (mythology)|Diana]]''', was a [[Greek temple]] dedicated to a goddess Greeks identified as [[Artemis]] and was one of the [[Seven Wonders of the Ancient World]]. It was situated at [[Ephesus]] (near the modern town of [[Selçuk]] in present-day [[Turkey]]), and was completely rebuilt three times before its eventual destruction in 401.&lt;ref&gt;John Freely, ''The Western Shores of Turkey: Discovering the Aegean and Mediterranean Coasts'' 2004, p. 148; Clive Foss, ''Ephesus after antiquity: a late antique, Byzantine, and Turkish city'', Cambridge University Press, 1979, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=i6Q8AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PR7&amp;ots=cz_UVafPvu&amp;dq=Artemis%20Ephesus%20John%20Chrysostom%20mob&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;pg=PA86#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false pp. 86 - 87 &amp; footnote 83.]&lt;/ref&gt; Only foundations and sculptural fragments of the latest of the temples at the site remain. 

The first sanctuary (''[[temenos]]'') antedated the Ionic immigration by many years, and dates to the [[Bronze Age]]. [[Callimachus]], in his ''Hymn to Artemis'', attributed it to the [[Amazons]]. In the 7th century the old temple was destroyed by a flood. Its reconstruction began around 550 BC, under the Cretan [[architect]] [[Chersiphron]] and his son [[Metagenes]], at the expense of [[Croesus]] of [[Lydia]]: the project took 10 years to complete, only to be destroyed in an act of arson by a young  [[arsonist]] seeking fame named [[Herostratus]]. It was later rebuilt.

[[Antipater of Sidon]], who compiled the list of the Seven Wonders, describes the finished temple:
&lt;blockquote&gt;I have set eyes on the wall of lofty [[Babylon]] on which is a road for chariots, and the [[Statue of Zeus at Olympia|statue of Zeus by the Alpheus]], and the [[Hanging gardens of Babylon|hanging gardens]], and the [[Colossus of Rhodes|colossus of the Sun]], and the huge labour of the [[Egyptian pyramids|high pyramids]], and the vast [[Mausoleum of Mausolus|tomb of Mausolus]]; but when I saw the house of Artemis that mounted to the clouds, those other marvels lost their brilliancy, and I said, &quot;Lo, apart from Olympus, the Sun never looked on aught so grand&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Antipater, ''[[Greek Anthology]]'' IX.58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Image:ArtemisEphesus.jpg|thumb|160px|Synthesizing Artemis of Ephesus: an 18th-century [[engraving]] of a Roman marble copy of a Greek replica of a lost Geometric period ''[[xoanon]]''.]]

==Location and history==
The Temple of Artemis was located near the ancient city of Ephesus, about 50&amp;nbsp;km south from the modern port city of [[İzmir]], in Turkey. Today the site lies on the edge of the modern town of [[Selçuk]].

===Earliest phase===
The sacred site (''[[temenos]]'') at Ephesus was far older than the ''Artemision'' itself. [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]]&lt;ref&gt;Pausanias, ''Description of Greece'' 7.2.6.&lt;/ref&gt; was certain that it antedated the Ionic immigration by many years, being older even than the oracular shrine of Apollo at [[Didyma]]. He said that the pre-Ionic inhabitants of the city were [[Leleges]] and [[Lydia]]ns. [[Callimachus]], in his ''Hymn to Artemis'', attributed the earliest ''[[temenos]]'' at Ephesus to the [[Amazons]], whose worship he imagines already centered upon an image (''bretas'') of Artemis, their patron goddess.

Modern archaeology cannot confirm Pausanias' Amazons, but his account of the site's antiquity seems well-founded. Before World War I, site excavations by [[David George Hogarth]]&lt;ref&gt;D.G. Hogarth, editor, 1908. ''Excavations at Ephesus''.&lt;/ref&gt; identified three successive temple buildings. Re-excavations in 1987-88&lt;ref&gt;Anton Bammer, &quot;A [[Peripteros]]&quot; of the Geometric Period in the Artemision of Ephesus&quot; ''Anatolian Studies'' '''40''' (1990), pp. 137-160.&lt;/ref&gt; confirmed that the site was occupied as early as the [[Bronze Age]], with a sequence of pottery finds that extend forward to [[Geometric art|Middle Geometric times]], when the clay-floored [[peripteral]] temple was constructed, in the second half of the 8th century BC.&lt;ref&gt;Bammer, 1990, p.142. noted some still earlier placements of stones, [[Helladic period|Mycenaean]] pottery and crude clay animal figurines, but warned &quot;it is still to early to come to conclusions about a cult sequence.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The [[peripteral]] temple at Ephesus offers the earliest example of a peripteral type on the coast of Asia Minor, and perhaps the earliest Greek temple surrounded by colonnades anywhere.

[[Image:Temple of Artemis.jpg|thumb|left|250px|The Temple of Artemis, as imagined in this hand-coloured engraving by [[Martin Heemskerck]] (1498 - 1574), has the &quot;old-fashioned&quot; look of [[Santa Maria Novella]] in Florence and other Italian ''quattrocento'' churches of the previous generation.]]

In the 7th century, a flood&lt;ref&gt;The flood is dated by fragmentary ceramics: Bammer, 1990, p.141.&lt;/ref&gt; destroyed the temple, depositing over half a meter of sand and flotsam over a floor of hard-packed clay. Among the flood debris were the remains of a carved ivory plaque of a [[griffin]] and the [[Tree of Life]], apparently North Syrian, and a number of drilled tear-shaped amber drops of elliptical cross-section. These probably once dressed a wooden effigy ''([[xoanon]])'' of the Lady of Ephesus, which must have been destroyed or recovered from the flood. Bammer notes that though the site was prone to flooding, and raised by silt deposits about two metres between the eighth and 6th centuries, and a further 2.4 m between the sixth and the fourth, its continued use &quot;indicates that maintaining the identity of the actual location played an important role in the sacred organization&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bammer, 1990, p.144.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Second phase ==
The new temple was sponsored at least in part by [[Croesus]], who founded [[Lydia]]'s empire and was overlord of Ephesus,&lt;ref&gt;Herodotus' statement to this effect is confirmed by the conjectural reading of a fragmentary dedicatory inscription, conserved in the British Museum (''A Guide to the Department of Greek and Roman Antiquities in the British Museum'' 84).&lt;/ref&gt; and was designed and constructed from around 550 BC by the Cretan [[architect]] [[Chersiphron]] and his son [[Metagenes]]. It was some 377' long and 180' wide, supposedly the first Greek temple built of marble. Its [[peripteral]] columns stood some 40 feet high, in double rows that formed a wide ceremonial passage around the ''[[cella]]'' that housed the goddess' cult image. Thirty-six of these columns were, according to Pliny, decorated by carvings in relief. A new ebony or blackened grapewood [[Cult image|cult statue]] was sculpted by Endoios,&lt;ref&gt;[[Pliny's Natural History]], 16.79.213-16; Pliny's source was the Roman [[Mucianus]], who thought that the cult image by an &quot;Endoios&quot; was extremely ancient, however. Endoios' name appears in late sixth-century Attic inscriptions, and [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] notes works attributed to him. Most importantly, the Ephesians of Mucianus' time maintained the tradition that a particular sculptor had created the remade image (LiDonnici 1992:398.)&lt;/ref&gt; and a ''[[naiskos]]'' to house it was erected east of the open-air altar.

A rich foundation deposit from this era yielded more than a thousand items, including what may be the earliest coins made from the silver-gold alloy [[electrum]]. Fragments of bas-relief on the lowest drums of the temple, preserved in the British Museum, show that the enriched columns of the later temple, of which a few survive (''illustration, below right'') were versions of this earlier feature. [[Pliny the Elder]], seemingly unaware of the ancient continuity of the sacred site, claims that the new temple's architects chose to build it on marshy ground as a precaution against earthquakes. The temple became an important attraction, visited by merchants, kings, and sightseers, many of whom paid homage to Artemis in the form of [[jewelry]] and various goods. It also offered sanctuary to those fleeing persecution or punishment, a tradition linked in myth to the Amazons who twice fled there seeking the goddess' protection from punishment, firstly by [[Dionysus]] and later, by [[Heracles]].

===Destruction by Herostratus===
The &quot;Croesus&quot; Temple was destroyed on July 21, 356 BC, probably very soon after its completion, in a vainglorious act of arson: one [[Herostratus]] set fire to the roof-beams, seeking fame at any cost, thus the term ''[[herostratic fame]]''.
&lt;blockquote&gt;A man was found to plan the burning of the temple of Ephesian Diana so that through the destruction of this most beautiful building his name might be spread through the whole world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/L/Roman/Texts/Valerius_Maximus/8*.html#14.ext.5 Valerius Maximus, VIII.14.ext.5]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The Ephesians, outraged, sentenced Herostratus to death and [[damnatio memoriae|forbade anyone from mentioning his name]], under pain of death. However, [[Theopompus]] later noted the name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=William|title=Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology|year=1849|pages=439|url=http://www.ancientlibrary.com/smith-bio/1547.html|accessdate=July 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The burning supposedly coincided with the birth of [[Alexander the Great]]; [[Plutarch]]&lt;ref&gt;Plutarch, ''Life of Alexander''.&lt;/ref&gt; remarked that Artemis was too preoccupied with Alexander's delivery to save her burning temple.

==Third phase==
The Ephesians tactfully refused Alexander's offer to pay for the temple's rebuilding, and eventually rebuilt it after his death, at their own expense. Work started in 323 BC and continued for many years. The third temple was larger than the second; 450' long by 225' wide and 60 feet high, with more than 127 columns. [[Athenagoras of Athens]] names [[Endoeus]], a pupil of Daedalus, as sculptor of Artemis' main cult image. [[Pausanias]] (c. 2nd century AD) reports another image and altar in the Temple, dedicated to Artemis ''Protothronia'' (Artemis &quot;of the first seat&quot;) and a gallery of images above this altar, including an ancient figure of [[Nyx]] (the primordial goddess of Night) by the sculptor [[Rhoecus]] (6th century BC). Pliny describes images of Amazons, the legendary founders of Ephesus and Ephesian Artemis' original proteges, carved by [[Scopas]]. Literary sources describe the temple's adornment by paintings, gilded columns of gold and silver, and religious works of renowned Greek sculptors [[Polyclitus (sculptor)|Polyclitus]], [[Pheidias]], [[Cresilas]], and [[Phradmon]].&lt;ref&gt;Pausanias, [http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Paus.%2010.38.6&amp;lang=original 10.38.6], trans Jones and Ormerod, 1918, from perseus.org. For ''Artemis Protothronia'' as a separate aspect of Ephesian cult to Artemis, see Strelan, R., ''Paul, Artemis, and the Jews in Ephesus'', de Gruyter, 1996, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=nw1xdz7fO18C&amp;pg=PA157&amp;lpg=PA157&amp;dq=Ephesus+Nyx&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=B3Uyn7lL1v&amp;sig=wVIY0axqXi_82OMkpLwl3AA1M10&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=nJJlTbyTCI-r8QOX__W9Bw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Ephesus%20Nyx&amp;f=false p. 157.]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Column drum Ephesus.JPG|thumb|left|Drum from the base of a column from the 4th-century rebuilding ([[British Museum]])]]

This reconstruction survived some 600 years, and appears multiple times in early [[Christianity|Christian]] accounts of Ephesus. According to the [[New Testament]], the appearance of the [[Paul of Tarsus|first Christian missionary]] in Ephesus caused locals to fear for the temple's dishonor.&lt;ref&gt;{{bible|Acts 19:27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd-century ''[[Acts of John]]'' includes an [[apocryphal]] tale of the temple's destruction: the apostle John prayed publicly in the Temple of Artemis, exorcising its demons and &quot;of a sudden the altar of Artemis split in many pieces... and half the temple fell down,&quot; instantly converting the Ephesians, who wept, prayed or took flight.&lt;ref&gt;Ramsay MacMullen, ''Christianizing the Roman Empire A.D. 100-400'' 1984, p 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Against this, a Roman edict of 162 AD acknowledges the importance of ''Artemesion'', the annual Ephesian festival to Artemis, and officially extends it from a few holy days over March–April to a whole month, &quot;one of the largest and most magnificent religious festivals in Ephesus' liturgical calendar&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rick Strelan, ''Paul, Artemis, and the Jews in Ephesus'', 1996, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?hl=en&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;id=nw1xdz7fO18C&amp;oi=fnd&amp;pg=PR7&amp;dq=Ephesus+Artemisia&amp;ots=B3UyoelK5D&amp;sig=IbYDOyUDwn2DUD8Ahqv-Tfly-bs#v=onepage&amp;q=Ephesus%20Artemisia&amp;f=falsepp. 57 - 58 and footnote 83.] The edict was made as a form of official apology and compensation; a senior Roman official had unwittingly offended the goddess by conducting business during one or more of her holy days. The political, economic and religious importance of Ephesian Artemis was undiminished, more than one hundred years after Paul's visit.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 268 AD, the Temple was destroyed or damaged in a raid by the [[Goths]], an East Germanic tribe.&lt;ref&gt;''268'': Herwig Wolfram, Thomas J. Dunlap, tr., ''History of the Goths'' (1979) 1988 p.52f, correlating multiple sources, corrects the date of the Gothic advance into the Aegean against the ''[[Origo Gothica]]'', which scrambles the events of several years, giving 267 for this event.&lt;/ref&gt; in the time of emperor [[Gallienus]]: &quot;Respa, Veduc and Thuruar,&lt;ref&gt;''Respa, Veduco, Thurar'': these names are otherwise unknown (Wolfram 1988, p.52 and note 84).&lt;/ref&gt; leaders of the Goths, took ship and sailed across the strait of the Hellespont to Asia. There they laid waste many populous cities and set fire to the renowned temple of Diana at Ephesus,&quot; reported [[Jordanes]] in ''Getica''.&lt;ref&gt;Jordanes, ''Getica'' xx.107.&lt;/ref&gt; 

Thereafter it may have been rebuilt, or repaired but this is uncertain, as its later history is highly unclear and the torching of the temple by the Goths may have brought it to a final end. At least some of the stones from the temple were used in construction of other buildings.&lt;ref&gt;Clive Foss, ''Ephesus after antiquity: a late antique, Byzantine, and Turkish city'', Cambridge University Press, 1979, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=i6Q8AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PR7&amp;ots=cz_UVafPvu&amp;dq=Artemis%20Ephesus%20John%20Chrysostom%20mob&amp;lr=lang_en&amp;pg=PA86#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false pp. 86 - 87 &amp; footnote 83.]&lt;/ref&gt; Some of the columns in [[Hagia Sophia]] originally belonged to the temple of Artemis,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.exploreturkey.com/exptur.phtml?id=176 St. Sophia Construction for the Third Time]&lt;/ref&gt; and the ''[[Parastaseis syntomoi chronikai]]'' records the re-use of several statues and other decorative elements throughout [[Constantinople]]. 

The main primary sources for the Temple of Artemis at Ephesus are [[Pliny the Elder]]'s ''[[Pliny's Natural History|Natural History]]'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/L/Roman/Texts/Pliny_the_Elder/36*.html#95 XXXVI.xxi.95], Pomponius Mela [http://ourworld-top.cs.com/latintexts/m117.htm i:17], &lt;!-- &quot;Ptolemy, 5&quot;: see Talk --&gt; and [[Plutarch]]'s ''Life of [[Alexander the Great|Alexander]]'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Plutarch/Lives/Alexander*/3.html#3.5 III.5] (referencing the burning of the ''Artemiseum'').

==Rediscovery of the Temple==
[[Image:Ac artemisephesus.jpg|thumb|250px|The site of the temple today.]]
After sixty years of searching, the site of the temple was rediscovered in 1869 by an expedition led by [[John Turtle Wood]] and sponsored by the British Museum. These excavations continued until 1874.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oeai.at/eng/ausland/geschichte.html|title=Ephesos - An Ancient Metropolis: Exploration and History|publisher=Austrian Archaeological Institute|date=October 2008|accessdate=2009-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; A few further fragments of sculpture were found during the 1904-06 excavations directed by [[David George Hogarth]]. The recovered sculptured fragments of the 4th-century rebuilding and a few from the earlier temple, which had been used in the rubble fill for the rebuilding, were assembled and displayed in the &quot;Ephesus Room&quot; of the British Museum.&lt;ref&gt;The sculptures were published in the British Museum ''Catalogue of Sculpture'', vol. II, part VI.&lt;/ref&gt;

Today the site of the temple, which lies just outside [[Selçuk]], is marked by a single column constructed of dissociated fragments discovered on the site.

==Cult and influence==
The archaic ''temeton'' beneath the later Temples clearly housed some form of &quot;Great Goddess&quot; but nothing is known of her cult. The literary accounts that describe it as &quot;Amazonian&quot; refer to the later founder-myths of Greek emigres who developed the cult and temple of ''Artemis Ephesia''. The wealth and splendour of temple and city were taken as evidence of Artemis Ephesia's power, and were the basis for her local and international prestige: despite the successive traumas of Temple destruction, each rebuilding &amp;ndash; a gift and honour to the goddess &amp;ndash; brought further prosperity.&lt;ref&gt;Gregory Stevenson, ''Power and place: Temple and identity in the Book of Revelation'', de Gruyter, 2001, p. 77, citing Aelius Aristides, ''Concerning Concord'', 25. For an exposition of the mechanisms involved in these social, religious and economic advantages, see Stevenson, 2001, pp. 70 - 80 ff.&lt;/ref&gt;

Artemis' shrines, temples and festivals (''Artemisia'') could be found throughout the Greek world, but Ephesian Artemis was unique. The Ephesians considered her theirs, and resented any foreign claims to her protection. Once Persia ousted and replaced their Lydian overlord [[Croesus]], the Ephesians played down his contribution to the Temple's restoration. On the whole, the [[Achaemenid Empire|Persians]] dealt fairly with Ephesus, but removed some religious artifacts from Artemis' Temple to [[Sardis]] and brought Persian priests into her Ephesian cult; this was not forgiven.&lt;ref&gt;LiDonnici, p.401.&lt;/ref&gt; When Alexander conquered the Persians, his offer to finance the Temple's second rebuilding was politely but firmly refused.&lt;ref&gt;The intended offering might have included a divine statue of Alexander himself, or simply an inscription commemorating his subsidy as a gift to the Goddess, with himself as her particular protege. The Ephesians protested with great diplomacy, it being &quot;inappropriate for a god to dedicate offerings to a god&quot;. See Strabo, Geography, 14.1.22, variously interpreted in Strelan, p. 80, and Gregory Stevenson, Power and place: Temple and identity in the Book of Revelation, de Gruyter, 2001, [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=4vRPx7Ujyn0C&amp;pg=PA79&amp;lpg=PA79&amp;dq=Strabo+14.1.22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=y_LhP8byqz&amp;sig=qXZWte419JjyEXejmrAQXKvDcso&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=eOlnTZ_cG9Cx8QOzsoCMBg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=Strabo%2014.1.22&amp;f=false p. 79.]&lt;/ref&gt; Ephesian Artemis lent her city's diplomacy a powerful religious edge. 

Under Hellenic rule, and later, under Roman rule, the Ephesian ''Artemisia'' festival was increasingly promoted as a key element in the pan-Hellenic festival circuit. It was part of a definitively Greek political and cultural identity, essential to the economic life of the region, and an excellent opportunity for young, unmarried Greeks of both sexes to seek out marriage partners. Games, contests and theatrical performances were held in the goddess' name, and [[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]] describes her procession as a magnificent crowd-puller; one of [[Apelles]]' best paintings showed the goddess' image, carried through the streets and surrounded by maidens.&lt;ref&gt;Pliny the Elder, ''Natural History'', 35 - 93.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Roman Empire|Roman Imperial era]], the emperor [[Commodus]] lent his name to the festival games, and might have sponsored them.&lt;ref&gt;Irene Ringwood Arnold, &quot;Festivals of Ephesus&quot;, ''American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 76, No. 1 (January, 1972), p 18, citing Xenophon for marriage-broking at the Ephesian ''Artemesia''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ephesian Artemis==
From the Greek point of view Ephesian Artemis is a distinctive form of their goddess [[Artemis]]. In Greek cult and myth, Artemis is the twin of [[Apollo]], a virgin huntress who supplanted the [[Titan (mythology)|Titan]] [[Selene]] as goddess of the [[Moon]]. At [[Ephesus]], a goddess whom the Greeks associated with Artemis was venerated in an archaic, certainly pre-Hellenic [[cult image]]&lt;ref&gt;The iconic images have been most thoroughly assembled by Robert Fleischer, ''Artemis von Ephesos und der erwandte Kultstatue von Anatolien und Syrien'' EPRO '''35''' (Leiden:Brill) 1973.&lt;/ref&gt; that was carved of wood and kept decorated with jewelry. Robert Fleischer identified as decorations of the primitive ''[[xoanon]]'' the changeable features that since [[Minucius Felix]] and [[Jerome]]'s Christian attacks on pagan popular religion had been read as many breasts or &quot;eggs&quot; — denoting her fertility (others interpret the objects to represent the testicles of sacrificed bulls that would have been strung on the image, with similar meaning). Most similar to Near-Eastern and Egyptian deities, and least similar to Greek ones, her body and legs are enclosed within a tapering pillar-like [[Term (architecture)|term]], from which her feet protrude. On the coins minted at Ephesus, the apparently many-breasted goddess wears a [[mural crown]] (like a city's walls), an attribute of [[Cybele]] (see ''[[polos]]''). On the coins she rests either arm on a staff formed of entwined [[Serpent (symbolism)|serpents]] or of a stack of ''[[Ouroboros|ouroboroi]]'', the eternal serpent with its tail in its mouth. Something the Lady of Ephesus had in common with [[Cybele]] was that each was served by temple slave-women, or [[hierodule]]s (''hiero'' &quot;holy&quot;, ''doule'' &quot;female slave&quot;), under the direction of a priestess who inherited her role, attended by a college of eunuch priests called &quot;Megabyzoi&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Strabo]], ''Geographica'', 14.1.23&lt;; sometimes the existence of a college is disputed and rather, a succession of priests given the title of &quot;Megabyzos&quot; is preferred.&lt;/ref&gt; and also by young virgins ([[Kore|korai]]).&lt;ref&gt;[[Xenophon]], ''Anabasis'', v.3.7.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fontana di Diana Efesina-Tivoli, Villa d'Este.jpg|thumb|left|185px|Traditional many-breasted interpretation in a 16th-century fountain of ''Diana Efesina'', [[Villa d'Este]]]]

The &quot;eggs&quot; or &quot;breasts&quot; of the Lady of Ephesus, it now appears, must be the iconographic descendants of the [[amber]] gourd-shaped drops, elliptical in cross-section and drilled for hanging, that were rediscovered in the excavations of 1987-88; they remained in situ where the ancient wooden [[cult figure]] of the Lady of Ephesus had been caught by an 8th-century flood (see ''History'' below). This form of breast-jewelry, then, had already been developed by the [[Geometric Period]]. A hypothesis offered by Gerard Seiterle, that the objects in Classical representations represented bulls' scrotal sacs&lt;ref&gt;Seiterle, &quot;Artemis: die Grosse Göttin von Ephesos&quot; ''Antike Welt'' '''10''' (1979), pp 3-16, accepted in the 1980s by [[Walter Burkert]] and Brita Alroth, among others, criticised and rejected by Robert Fleischer, but widely popularized.&lt;/ref&gt; cannot be maintained.&lt;ref&gt;Fleischer, &quot;Neues zur kleinasiatischen Kultstatue&quot; ''Archäologischer Anzeiger '''98''' 1983:81-93; Bammer 1990:153.&lt;/ref&gt;

A votive inscription mentioned by Florence Mary Bennett,&lt;ref&gt;Florence Mary Bennett, ''Religious Cults Associated with the Amazons'' (1912): Chapter III: Ephesian Artemis ([http://www.sacred-texts.com/wmn/rca/rca04.htm on-line text]).&lt;/ref&gt; which dates probably from about the 3rd century BC, associates Ephesian Artemis with Crete: &quot;To the Healer of diseases, to Apollo, Giver of Light to mortals, Eutyches has set up in votive offering [a statue of] the Cretan Lady of Ephesus, the Light-Bearer.&quot;

The Greek habits of [[syncretism]] assimilated all foreign gods under some form of the Olympian pantheon familiar to them— in ''[[interpretatio graeca]]''— and it is clear that at Ephesus, the identification with Artemis that the Ionian settlers made of the &quot;Lady of Ephesus&quot; was slender. The Christian approach was at variance with the tolerant syncretistic approach of pagans to gods who were not theirs.  A Christian inscription at Ephesus&lt;ref&gt;Quoted in [[Ramsay MacMullen]], ''Christianizing the Roman Empire AD 100-400'' 1984, ch. III &quot;Christianity as presented&quot; p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; suggests why so little remains at the site: 
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Destroying the delusive image of the demon Artemis, Demeas has erected this symbol of Truth, the God that drives away idols, and the Cross of priests, deathless and victorious sign of Christ.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Image:Artemis Efes Museum.JPG|thumb|upright|The Lady of Ephesus, 1st century AD ([[Ephesus Archaeological Museum]])]]

The assertion that the Ephesians thought that their cult image had fallen from the sky, though it was a familiar origin-myth at other sites, is only known at Ephesus from [[BibleWiki:Acts Chapter 19, Verse 35|Acts 19:35]]: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;What man is there that knoweth not how that the city of the Ephesians is a worshipper of the great goddess Diana, and of the [image] which fell down from Jupiter?&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Lynn LiDonnici observes that modern scholars are likely to be more concerned with origins of the Lady of Ephesus and her iconology than her adherents were at any point in time, and are prone to creating a synthetic account of the Lady of Ephesus by drawing together documentation that ranges over more than a millennium in its origins, creating a falsified, unitary picture, as of an unchanging icon.&lt;ref&gt;Lynn R. LiDonnici, &quot;The Images of Artemis Ephesia and Greco-Roman Worship: A Reconsideration&quot; ''The Harvard Theological Review'' '''85'''.4 (October 1992), pp 389-415.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Ephesia Grammata]]
*[[Temple of Diana]]

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
*Anton Bammer, &quot;A [[Peripteros]]&quot; of the Geometric Period in the Artemision of Ephesus&quot; ''Anatolian Studies 40'' (1990), pp.&amp;nbsp;137–160.
*Lynn R. LiDonnici, &quot;The Images of Artemis Ephesia and Greco-Roman Worship: A Reconsideration&quot; ''The Harvard Theological Review 85''.4 (October 1992), pp.&amp;nbsp;389–415.
*Irene Ringwood Arnold, &quot;Festivals of Ephesus&quot;, ''American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 76, No. 1 (January, 1972), pp.&amp;nbsp;17–22.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Temple of Artemis in Ephesus}}
*[http://www.britishmuseum.org/explore/highlights/article_index/a/the_archaic_temple_of_artemis.aspx Temple of Artemis] ([[Ephesos]]) objects at the [[British Museum]] website
*[http://www.sacred-texts.com/wmn/rca/rca04.htm Florence Mary Bennett, ''Religious Cults Associated with the Amazons:'' (1912)]: Chapter&amp;nbsp;III: Ephesian Artemis (text)
*[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/~grout/encyclopaedia_romana/greece/paganism/artemis.html James Grout: ''Temple of Artemis'', part of the Encyclopædia Romana]
*[http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Gazetteer/Places/Europe/Turkey/_Periods/Greek/_Texts/LETGKB/Ephesus*.html Diana's Temple at Ephesus] (W.&amp;nbsp;R.&amp;nbsp;Lethaby, 1908)
*[http://www.pbase.com/dosseman/artemis Pictures of the current situation]

{{Seven Wonders of the Ancient World}}

[[Category:Greek temples|Artemis]]
[[Category:6th-century BC architecture]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek buildings and structures]]
[[Category:Ancient Greek religion]]
[[Category:Artemis]]
[[Category:Destroyed landmarks]]
[[Category:Ephesus]]
[[Category:Places of worship damaged by arson]]
[[Category:Temples in ancient Ionia]]
[[Category:Architecture in Turkey]]

{{Link FA|dv}}

[[ar:هيكل آرتميس]]
[[ast:Templu d'Artemisa (Éfesu)]]
[[az:Artemida məbədi]]
[[bn:আর্টেমিসের মন্দির]]
[[be:Храм Артэміды Эфескай]]
[[bg:Храм на Артемида]]
[[bs:Artemidin hram u Efesu]]
[[ca:Temple d'Àrtemis]]
[[cv:Эфесри Артемида чиркĕвĕ]]
[[cs:Artemidin chrám v Efesu]]
[[cy:Teml Artemis (Effesus)]]
[[da:Artemistemplet i Efesos]]
[[de:Tempel der Artemis in Ephesos]]
[[dv:އާޓިމިސް ފައްޅި]]
[[et:Artemise tempel Ephesoses]]
[[el:Ναός της Αρτέμιδος στην Έφεσο]]
[[es:Templo de Artemisa (Éfeso)]]
[[eo:Templo de Artemiso]]
[[eu:Efesoko Artemisaren Tenplua]]
[[fa:نیایشگاه آرتمیس]]
[[fr:Temple d'Artémis à Éphèse]]
[[gl:Templo de Artemisa en Éfeso]]
[[ko:아르테미스 신전]]
[[hy:Արտեմիսի տաճարը Եփեսոսում]]
[[hi:अर्टेमिस का मन्दिर]]
[[hr:Artemidin hram u Efezu]]
[[id:Kuil Artemis]]
[[is:Artemismusterið]]
[[it:Tempio di Artemide]]
[[he:מקדש ארטמיס באפסוס]]
[[jv:Kuil Artemis]]
[[ka:ეფესოს ტაძარი]]
[[kk:Артемида ғибадатханасы]]
[[sw:Hekalu la Artemis mjini Efeso]]
[[lv:Artemīdas templis]]
[[lt:Artemidės šventykla]]
[[hu:Epheszoszi Artemisz-templom]]
[[mk:Храм на Артемида во Ефес]]
[[mr:आर्टेमिसचे मंदिर]]
[[ms:Kuil Artemis]]
[[mn:Артемисийн сүм]]
[[nl:Tempel van Artemis in Efeze]]
[[ja:アルテミス神殿]]
[[no:Artemistempelet i Efesos]]
[[nn:Artemistempelet i Efesos]]
[[oc:Temple d'Artèmis a Efès]]
[[pnb:ارٹیمس دا مندر]]
[[pl:Świątynia Artemidy w Efezie]]
[[pt:Templo de Ártemis]]
[[ro:Templul zeiței Artemis din Efes]]
[[qu:Ephesos Artemis manqus wasi]]
[[ru:Храм Артемиды Эфесской]]
[[sq:Tempulli i Artemidës në Efes]]
[[si:ආටිමිස් දේවස්ථානය]]
[[simple:Temple of Artemis]]
[[sk:Artemidin chrám v Efeze]]
[[sr:Артемидин храм]]
[[sh:Artemidin hram]]
[[fi:Artemiin temppeli]]
[[sv:Artemistemplet i Efesos]]
[[ta:ஆர்ட்டெமிஸ் கோயில்]]
[[th:วิหารอาร์เทอมีส]]
[[tr:Artemis Tapınağı]]
[[uk:Храм Артеміди]]
[[vi:Đền Artemis]]
[[zh:阿耳忒弥斯神庙]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
