<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="279620" ns="0" title="Benigno Aquino, Jr."><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect2|Ninoy Aquino|Sen. Ninoy Aquino|other uses|Ninoy Aquino (disambiguation)}}
{{Refimprove|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox officeholder
| name                = Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.
| image               = Ninoy2.jpg
| imagesize           =
| smallimage          =
| caption             =
| order                =
| office               = [[Senate of the Philippines|Senator of the Philippines]]
| term_start           = December 30, 1967
| term_end             = September 23, 1972&lt;ref&gt;Original Term until December 30, 1973 cut short pursuant to the Declaration of Martial Law on September 23, 1972.&lt;/ref&gt;
| order3              =
| office3             = Philippine Presidential Adviser on Defense Affairs
| term_start3         = 1949
| term_end3           = 1954
| office4             = Governor of [[Tarlac]]
| term_start4         = December 30, 1961
| term_end4           = December 30, 1967
| office5             = Vice-Governor of [[Tarlac]]
| term_start5         = December 30, 1959
| term_end5           = December 30, 1961
| order6              =
| office6             = Mayor of [[Concepcion, Tarlac]]
| term_start6         = December 30, 1955
| term_end6           = December 30, 1959
| birth_date          = November 27, 1932
| birth_place         = [[Concepcion, Tarlac]], Philippines
| death_date          = {{Death date and age|mf=yes|1983|8|21|1932|11|27}}
| death_place         = [[Ninoy Aquino International Airport|Manila International Airport]], [[Pasay]], [[Metro Manila]], Philippines
| restingplace        = Manila Memorial Park, [[Parañaque]], [[Metro Manila]], Philippines
| cause_of_death      = [[Assassination of Benigno Aquino, Jr.|Assassination]]
| nationality         = [[Philippines|Filipino]]
| party               = [[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal]] (1959–1983) &lt;br&gt; [[Lakas ng Bayan|LABAN]] (1978–1983)
| otherparty          = [[Nacionalista Party]] (1955–1959)
| spouse              = [[Corazon Aquino|Corazon C. Aquino]]
| relations           =
| children            = Ma. Elena Aquino-Cruz&lt;br&gt;Aurora Corazon Aquino-Abellada&lt;br&gt;[[Benigno Aquino III|Benigno S. Aquino III]]&lt;br&gt;Victoria Elisa Aquino-Dee&lt;br&gt;[[Kris Aquino|Kristina Bernadette Aquino-Yap]]
| residence           = Times Street, [[Quezon City]]
| alma_mater          = [[University of the Philippines]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Ateneo de Manila University]] &lt;br /&gt; [[San Beda College|San Beda College High School]] (Class of 1948) &lt;br /&gt; [[St. Joseph's College, Quezon City]]
| occupation          = Politician
| profession          = Journalist
| religion            = Roman Catholicism
| signature           =
| website             =
| footnotes           =
}}
&lt;!---The GOV.PH page on August 21, 2010 showed that the name is &quot;Benigno Simeon Aquino, Jr.&quot; See talk page for more discussion.---&gt;
'''Benigno Simeon &quot;Ninoy&quot; Aquino, Jr.'''&lt;!-- This is his full name. His mother's maiden name was also &quot;Aquino&quot; --&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Leonard, Thomas M. (2006). [http://books.google.com/books?id=3mE04D9PMpAC&amp;pg=PA65&amp;lpg=PA65&amp;dq=Benigno+Simeon+Aquino+-wikipedia+-iii&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=6yPVwEnbvY&amp;sig=CECiFq5wzVubmBeNZpLnF6AYn0w&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=mXsuTI_DK5X9nQfNjOCFBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwCDgU#v=onepage&amp;q=Simeon&amp;f=false ''Encyclopedia of the developing world, Volume 1''].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lentz, Harris M. (1988). [http://books.google.com/books?id=7lYiAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Benigno+Simeon+Aquino+-wikipedia+-iii+-noynoy&amp;dq=Benigno+Simeon+Aquino+-wikipedia+-iii+-noynoy&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=CH0uTOCpKYH8nAfAl5zWAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CE8Q6AEwCQ ''Assassinations and executions: an encyclopedia of political violence, 1865–1986''].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/31275/Benigno-Simeon-Aquino-Jr &quot;Benigno Simeon Aquino, Jr.&quot;]. ''Encyclopædia Britannica''. &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jessup, John E. (1998). [http://books.google.com/books?id=hP7jJAkTd9MC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;dq=benigno+aquino+1932&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=rbcuTOq6EJnqnQfyhaDaAw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwCDge#v=onepage&amp;q=benigno%20aquino%201932&amp;f=false ''An encyclopedic dictionary of conflict and conflict resolution, 1945–1996].&lt;/ref&gt;(November 27, 1932 – August 21, 1983) was a [[Senate of the Philippines|Filipino Senator]] and a former Governor of [[Tarlac]]. Aquino, together with [[Gerry Roxas]] and [[Jovito Salonga]], formed the leadership of the opposition to the [[Ferdinand Marcos|Marcos regime]] in the years leading to the imposition of [[martial law]] in the Philippines.  In 1973 he was arrested and incarcerated for 7 years, but was allowed to depart for the United States to seek medical treatment after he suffered a heart attack in 1980. He was [[Assassination of Benigno Aquino, Jr.|assassinated at the Manila International Airport]] upon returning home from exile in the United States in 1983. His death catapulted his widow, [[Corazon Aquino]], into the limelight, and prompted her to run for President as a member of the [[United Nationalist Democratic Organization|UNIDO]] party in [[Philippine presidential election, 1986|the 1986 elections]]. Manila International Airport has been renamed [[Ninoy Aquino International Airport]] in his honor, and the anniversary of his death is a national holiday in the Philippines, [[Ninoy Aquino Day]].


==Early life and career==
Benigno S. Aquino, Jr. was born in [[Concepcion, Tarlac]], to a prosperous family of ''hacenderos'' (landlords), original owners of Hacienda Tinang, Hacienda Lawang and Hacienda Murcia. {{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

His grandfather, [[Servillano Aquino]], was a general in the revolutionary army of [[Emilio Aguinaldo]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

His father, [[Benigno Aquino, Sr.|Benigno S. Aquino, Sr.]] (1894–1947) was a prominent member of the World War II Japanese [[Philippine Executive Commission|collaborationist government]] of [[Jose P. Laurel]], as Vice-President. In fact, his father once occupied the [[Arlegui Mansion]] guest house, originally owned by the [[Spanish-Filipino]] Laperal family of Manila and Baguio, the same house that his wife [[Corazon Aquino|Cory Aquino]] used as private quarters during her presidency and the same house his son [[Benigno Aquino III|Noynoy Aquino]] candidly refused for having &quot;too many memories&quot;. His father was one of two politicians representing Tarlac during his lifetime. The other was [[Jose Cojuangco]], father of his future wife. His  mother, Doña Aurora Aquino-Aquino, was also his father's third cousin. His father died while Ninoy was in his teens prior to coming to trial on treason charges resulting from his collaboration with the Japanese during the occupation.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Aquino was educated in private schools—[[Saint Joseph's College of Quezon City|St. Joseph's College]], [[Ateneo de Manila University|Ateneo de Manila]], [[National University (Philippines)|National University]], and [[De La Salle-College of Saint Benilde|De La Salle College]]. He finished high school at [[San Beda College]]. Aquino took his tertiary education at the [[Ateneo de Manila University|Ateneo de Manila]] to obtain a Bachelor of Arts degree, but he interrupted his studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;mvs&quot;&gt;Soliven, Maximo V. (August 26, 2008). [http://www.newsflash.org/2004/02/sb/sb005847.htm &quot;Ninoy: In the Eye of Memory&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt; According to one of his biographies, he considered himself to be an average student; his grade was not in the line of 90s nor did it fall into the 70s. At age 17, he was the youngest war correspondent to cover the Korean War for the newspaper ''[[The Manila Times]]'' of Joaquin &quot;Chino&quot; Roces. Because of his journalistic feats, he received the Philippine Legion of Honor award from President Elpidio Quirino at age 18. At 21, he became a close adviser to then defense secretary [[Ramon Magsaysay]]. Aquino took up law at the [[University of the Philippines]], where he became a member of [[Upsilon Sigma Phi]], the same fraternity as [[Ferdinand Marcos]]. He interrupted his studies again however to pursue a career in journalism. According to [[Maximo Soliven]], Aquino &quot;later 'explained' that he had decided to go to as many schools as possible, so that he could make as many new friends as possible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mvs&quot;/&gt; In early 1954, he was appointed by President [[Ramon Magsaysay]], his wedding sponsor to his 1953 wedding at the Our Lady of Sorrows church in [[Pasay]] with Corazon Cojuangco, to act as personal emissary to [[Luis Taruc]], leader of the [[Hukbalahap]] rebel group. After four months of negotiations, he was credited for Taruc's unconditional surrender.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

He became mayor of Concepcion in 1955 at the age of 22.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Political career==

Aquino gained an early familiarity with Philippine politics, as he was born into one of the Philippines' prominent oligarchic clans. His grandfather served under President Aguinaldo, while his father held office under Presidents [[Quezon]] and [[Jose P. Laurel]]. As a consequence, Aquino able to be elected mayor when he was 22 years old. Five years later, he was elected the nation's youngest vice-governor at 27, despite having no real executive experience. Two years later he became governor of Tarlac province in 1961 at age 29, then secretary-general of the [[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal Party]] in 1966. In 1967 he became the youngest elected senator in the country's history at age 34.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In 1968, during his first year as senator, Aquino alleged that Marcos was on the road to establishing &quot;a garrison state&quot; by &quot;ballooning the armed forces budget&quot;, saddling the defense establishment with &quot;overstaying generals&quot; and &quot;militarizing our civilian government offices&quot;—all these caveats were uttered barely four years before martial law, as was typical of the accusatory style of political confrontation at the time. However, no evidence was ever produced for any of these statements.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Aquino became known as a constant critic of the Marcos regime, as his flamboyant rhetoric had made him a darling of the media. His most polemical speech, &quot;A Pantheon for Imelda&quot;, was delivered on February 10, 1969. He assailed the Cultural Center, the first project of First Lady [[Imelda Marcos]] as extravagant, and dubbed it &quot;a monument to shame&quot; and labelled its designer &quot;a megalomaniac, with a penchant to captivate&quot;. By the end of the day, the country's broadsheets had blared that he labelled the President's wife, his cousin Paz's former ward, and a woman he had once courted, &quot;the Philippines' [[Eva Peron]]&quot;. President Marcos is said to have been outraged and labelled Aquino &quot;a congenital liar&quot;. The First Lady's friends angrily accused Aquino of being &quot;ungallant&quot;. These so-called &quot;fiscalization&quot; tactics of Aquino quickly became his trademark in the Senate.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Martial law, hunger strike==
It was not until the [[1971 Plaza Miranda bombing|Plaza Miranda bombing]] however—on August 21, 1971, 12 years to the day before Aquino's own assassination—that the pattern of direct confrontation between Marcos and Aquino emerged. At 9:15&amp;nbsp;pm, at the kick-off rally of the Liberal Party, the candidates had formed a line on a makeshift platform and were raising their hands as the crowd applauded. The band played, a fireworks display drew all eyes, when suddenly there were two loud explosions that obviously were not part of the show. In an instant the stage became a scene of wild carnage. The police later discovered two fragmentation grenades that had been thrown at the stage by &quot;unknown persons&quot;.  Eight people died, and 120 others were wounded, many critically. Aquino was absent at the incident.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Although suspicions pointed to the Nacionalistas (the political party of Marcos), Marcos allies sought to deflect this by insinuating that, perhaps, Aquino might have had a hand in the blast in a bid to eliminate his potential rivals within the party. Later, the Marcos government presented &quot;evidence&quot; of the bombings as well as an alleged threat of a communist insurgency, suggesting that the bombings were the handiwork of the growing [[New People's Army]]. Marcos made this a pretext to suspend the right of ''[[habeas corpus]]'', vowed that the killers would be apprehended within 48 hours, and arrested a score of known &quot;[[Maoism|Maoists]]&quot; on general principle. Ironically, the police captured one of the bombers, who was identified as a sergeant of the firearms and explosive section of the [[Philippine Constabulary]], a military arm of the government. According to Aquino, this man was later snatched from police custody by military personnel and never seen again.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

President Marcos declared martial law on September 21, 1972 and he went on air to broadcast his declaration on midnight of September 23. Aquino was one of the first to be arrested and imprisoned on trumped-up charges of murder, illegal possession of firearms and subversion. He was tried before Military Commission No. 2 headed by Major-General Jose Syjuco. On April 4, 1975, Aquino announced that he was going on a hunger strike, a fast to the death to protest the injustices of his military trial. Ten days through his hunger strike, he instructed his lawyers to withdraw all motions he had submitted to the Supreme Court. As weeks went by, he subsisted solely on salt tablets, sodium bicarbonate, amino acids, and two glasses of water a day. Even as he grew weaker, suffering from chills and cramps, soldiers forcibly dragged him to the military tribunal's session. His family and hundreds of friends and supporters heard Mass nightly at the Santuario de San Jose in [[Greenhills, San Juan]], praying for his survival. Near the end, Aquino's weight had dropped from 54 to 36 kilos. Aquino nonetheless was able to walk throughout his ordeal. On May 13, 1975, on the 40th day, his family and several priests and friends, begged him to end his fast, pointing out that even Christ fasted only for 40 days. He acquiesced, confident that he had made a symbolic gesture. But he remained in prison, and the trial continued, drawn out for several years. On November 25, 1977, the Commission found Aquino guilty of all charges and sentenced him to death by firing squad.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==1978 elections, bypass surgery, exile==
In 1978, from his prison cell, he was allowed to take part in the elections for Interim Batasang Pambansa (Parliament). Although his friends, former Senators [[Gerry Roxas]] and [[Jovito Salonga]], preferred to boycott the elections, Aquino urged his supporters to organize and run 21 candidates in [[Metro Manila]]. Thus his political party, dubbed ''[[Lakas ng Bayan]]'' (&quot;People's Power&quot;), was born. The party's acronym was &quot;LABAN&quot; (in [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]]). He was allowed one television interview on ''Face the Nation'' (hosted by Ronnie Nathanielsz) and proved to a startled and impressed populace that imprisonment had neither dulled his rapier-like tongue nor dampened his fighting spirit. Foreign correspondents and diplomats asked what would happen to the LABAN ticket. People agreed with him that his party would win overwhelmingly in an honest election. Not surprisingly, all his candidates lost due to widespread election fraud.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

In mid-March 1980, Aquino suffered a heart attack, possibly the result of seven years in prison, mostly in a solitary cell. He was transported to the [[Philippine Heart Center]], where he suffered a second heart attack. [[Electrocardiography|ECG]] and other tests showed that he had a blocked artery. Philippine surgeons were reluctant to do a [[Coronary artery bypass surgery|coronary bypass]], because it could involve them in a controversy. In additional, Aquino refused to submit himself to Philippine doctors, fearing possible Marcos &quot;duplicity&quot;; he preferred to go to the United States for the procedure or return to his cell at Fort Bonifacio and die. He also appeared in the ''[[700 Club]]'' television ministry of [[Pat Robertson]], where he narrated his spiritual life, accepted &quot;Christ as his Lord and Savior&quot; and became a born-again Christian, which sprang from a conversation with [[Charles Colson]], founder of [[Prison Fellowship]], who was involved in the [[Watergate Scandal]] during U.S. President [[Richard Nixon]]'s administration.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

On May 8, 1980, [[Imelda Marcos]] made an unannounced visit to Aquino at his hospital room. She asked him if he would like to leave that evening for the U.S., but not before agreeing on two conditions: 1) that if he left, he would return; 2) while in the U.S., he would not speak out against the Marcos regime. She then ordered General [[Fabian Ver]] and Mel Mathay to provide passports and plane tickets for the Aquino family. Aquino was placed in a closed van, rushed to his home on Times Street to pack, driven to the airport and put on a plane bound for the U.S. that same day, accompanied by his family.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Aquino was operated on at a hospital in [[Dallas]], Texas. He made a quick recovery, was walking within two weeks and making plans to fly to [[Damascus]], Syria to meet with Muslim leaders, which he did five weeks later. When he reiterated that he was returning to the Philippines, he received a surreptitious message from the Marcos government saying that he was now granted an extension of his &quot;medical furlough&quot;. Eventually, Aquino decided to renounce his two covenants with [[Malacañang]] &quot;because of the dictates of higher national interest&quot;. After all, Aquino added, &quot;a pact with the devil is no pact at all&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Aquino spent three years in self-exile, living with his family in [[Newton, Massachusetts|Newton]], a suburb of Boston, Massachusetts. On fellowship grants from [[Harvard University]] and the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]], he worked on the manuscripts of two books and gave a series of lectures in school halls, classrooms and auditoriums. He traveled extensively in the U.S., delivering speeches critical of the Marcos government.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Planning return==
[[Image:Ninoy being escorted by military.gif|thumb|left|160px|A moving screen shot of Sen. Aquino as he was being escorted out of the plane by military personnel, minutes before being killed.]]
Throughout his years of expatriation, Aquino was always aware that his life in the U.S. was temporary. He never stopped affirming his eventual return even as he enjoyed American hospitality and a peaceful life with his family on American soil. After spending 7 years and 7 months in prison, Aquino's finances were in ruins. Making up for the lost time as the family's breadwinner, he toured America; attending symposiums, lectures, and giving speeches in freedom rallies opposing the Marcos dictatorship. The most memorable was held at the [[Wilshire Ebell Theater]] in Los Angeles, California on February 15, 1981.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jHyJYcUIUjg |title=An NATv Exclusive: Ninoy Aquino's memorable speech in Los Angeles! (1 of 9) |work=''Youtube'' |accessdate=January 15, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first quarter of 1983, Aquino received news about the deteriorating political situation in his country and the rumored declining health of President Marcos (due to [[Lupus erythematosus|lupus]]). He believed that it was expedient for him to speak to Marcos and present to him his rationale for the country's return to democracy, before extremists took over and made such a change impossible. Moreover, his years of absence made his allies worry that the Filipinos might have resigned themselves to Marcos' strongman rule and that without his leadership the centrist opposition would die a natural death.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Aquino decided to go back to the Philippines, fully aware of the dangers that awaited him. Warned that he would either be imprisoned or killed, Aquino answered, &quot;if it's my fate to die by an assassin's bullet, so be it. But I cannot be petrified by inaction, or fear of assassination, and therefore stay in the side...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/august/21/newsid_2534000/2534945.stm BBC ON THIS DAY | 21 | 1983: Filipino opposition leader shot dead]&lt;/ref&gt;  His family, however, learned from a Philippine Consulate official that there were orders from Ministry of Foreign Affairs not to issue any passports for them. At that time, their visas had expired and their renewal had been denied. They therefore formulated a plan for Aquino to fly alone (to attract less attention), with the rest of the family to follow him after two weeks. Despite the government's ban on issuing him a passport, Aquino acquired one with the help of [[Rashid Lucman]], a former [[Mindanao]] legislator and founder of the Bangsamoro Liberation Front, a [[Moro people|Moro]] separatist group against Marcos. It carried the alias ''Marcial Bonifacio'' (Marcial for martial law and Bonifacio for Fort Bonifacio, his erstwhile prison).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.inq7.net/nat/2003/aug/21/nat_4-1.htm |title=Services – INQUIRER.net|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060516180338/http://www.inq7.net/nat/2003/aug/21/nat_4-1.htm |archivedate=May 16, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;  He eventually obtained a legitimate passport from a sympathizer working in a Philippine consulate through the help of Roque R. Ablan Jr, then a Congressman. The Marcos government warned all international airlines that they would be denied landing rights and forced to return if they tried to fly Aquino to the Philippines. Aquino insisted that it was his natural right as a citizen to come back to his homeland, and that no government could prevent him from doing so. He left [[Logan International Airport]] on August 13, 1983, took a circuitous route home from Boston, via Los Angeles to [[Singapore]]. In Singapore, then Tunku [[Ibrahim Ismail of Johor]] met Aquino upon his arrival in Singapore and later brought him to [[Johor]] to meet with other Malaysian leaders.&lt;ref&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6DF153BF935A25753C1A965948260&amp;sec=health&amp;spon=&amp;pagewanted=all AQUINO'S FINAL JOURNEY], KEN KASHIWAHARA,  October 16, 1983, The New York Times&lt;/ref&gt; Once in [[Johor]], Aquino met up with Tunku Ibrahim's father, Sultan [[Iskandar of Johor|Iskandar]], who was a close friend to Aquino.&lt;ref&gt;''Towards Relevant Education: A General Sourcebook for Teachers'' (1986), Education Forum, pg 305&lt;/ref&gt;

He then left for Hong Kong and on to [[Taipei]]. He had chosen Taipei as the final stopover when he learned the Philippines had severed diplomatic ties with the [[Republic of China]] (Taiwan). This made him feel more secure; the Taiwan authorities could pretend they were not aware of his presence. There would also be a couple of Taiwanese friends accompanying him. From Taipei he flew to Manila on [[China Airlines]] Flight 811.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Marcos wanted Aquino to stay out of politics, however Aquino asserted his willingness to suffer the consequences declaring, &quot;the Filipino is worth dying for.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rmaf.org.ph/Awardees/Biography/BiographyAquinoCor.htm 1998 Ramon Magsaysay Award for International Understanding – Corazon Aquino]&lt;/ref&gt;  He wished to express an earnest plea for Marcos to step down,  for a peaceful regime change and a return to democratic institutions. Anticipating the worst, at an interview in his suite at the [[Taipei Grand Hotel]], he revealed that he would be wearing a [[body armor|bullet-proof vest]], but he also said that &quot;it's only good for the body, but for the head there's nothing else we can do.&quot; Sensing his own doom, he told the journalists accompanying him on the flight, &quot;You have to be ready with your hand camera because this action can become very fast. In a matter of 3 or 4 minutes it could be all over, and I may not be able to talk to you again after this.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zuEPFt-Dd-Q |title=Ninoy Aquino: Worth Dying For (the last interview!) Original Upload |work=''Youtube'' |accessdate=October 6, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; In his last formal statement that he wasn't able to deliver, he said, &quot;I have returned to join the ranks of those struggling to restore our rights and freedom through violence. I seek no confrontation.&quot;

==Assassination==
[[File:Shot Dead on Arrival.JPG|thumb|250px|The aftermath of Aquino's assassination]]
{{Main|Assassination of Benigno Aquino, Jr.}}
Aquino was assassinated on August 21, 1983 when he was shot in the head after returning to the country. At the time, bodyguards were assigned to him by the Marcos government. A subsequent investigation produced controversy but no definitive results. After the Marcos government was overthrown, another investigation found sixteen defendants guilty. They were all sentenced to life in prison. Over the years, some were released, and the last one was let out in March 2009.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Another man present at the airport tarmac, Rolando Galman, was shot dead shortly after Aquino was killed. The Marcos government claimed Galman was the triggerman in Aquino's assassination.

==Funeral==
[[File:Cory aquino wiki.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Sen. Ninoy Aquino's grave (right) is next to his wife [[Corazon Aquino]]'s (left) at the Manila Memorial Park in [[Parañaque]], Philippines.]]
Aquino's body lay in state in a glass coffin. No effort was made to disguise a bullet wound that had disfigured his face. In an interview with Aquino's mother, Aurora, she told the funeral parlor not to apply makeup nor [[embalm]] her son, to see &quot;what they did to my son&quot;. Thousands of supporters flocked to see the bloodied body of Aquino, which took place at the Aquino household in Times St., [[Quezon City]] for nine days. Aquino's wife, [[Corazon Aquino]], and children Ballsy, Pinky, Viel, [[Noynoy Aquino|Noynoy]] and [[Kris Aquino|Kris]] arrived the day after the assassination. Aquino's funeral procession on August 31 lasted from 9&amp;nbsp;a.m., when his funeral mass was held at Santo Domingo Church in Santa Mesa Heights, [[Quezon City]], with the [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Archbishop of Manila]], [[Jaime Sin]] officiating, to 9&amp;nbsp;p.m., when his body was interred at the [[Manila Memorial Park]]. More than two million people lined the streets during the procession which was aired by the Church-sponsored [[Radio Veritas]], the only station to do so. The procession reached [[Rizal Park]], where the Philippine flag was brought to half-staff.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

[[Jovito Salonga]], then head of the [[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal Party]], said about Aquino:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Ninoy was getting impatient in Boston, he felt isolated by the flow of events in the Philippines. In early 1983, Marcos was seriously ailing, the Philippine economy was just as rapidly declining, and insurgency was becoming a serious problem. Ninoy thought that by coming home he might be able to persuade Marcos to restore democracy and somehow revitalize the Liberal Party.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.fnf.org.ph/online-exhibit/gallery14.html &quot;The Greatest President We Never Had&quot;]. Liberal Party of the Philippines.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; and called him &quot;the greatest president we never had&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot; /&gt;

==Legacy==
[[Image:Monument To Immortality.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Monument to Aquino beside the [[Philippine Stock Exchange]] building.]]
In Senator Aquino's honor, the Manila International Airport (MIA) where he was assassinated was renamed Ninoy Aquino International Airport (NAIA) and his image is printed on the [[Philippine five hundred peso bill|500-peso bill]]. August 21, the anniversary of his death, is Ninoy Aquino Day, an annual public holiday in the Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chanrobles.com/republicactno9256.htm Republic Act No. 9256]{{Verify credibility|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several monuments were built in his honor. Most renowned is the bronze memorial in [[Makati City]] near the [[Philippine Stock Exchange]], which has become a popular venue for anti-government rallies and large demonstrations. Another bronze statue is in front of the Municipal Building of [[Concepcion, Tarlac]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Although Aquino was recognized as the most prominent and most dynamic opposition leader of his generation, in the years prior to martial law he was regarded by many as being a representative of the entrenched familial elite which to this day dominates Philippine politics. While atypically telegenic and uncommonly articulate, he had his share of detractors and was not known to be immune to ambitions and excesses of the ruling political class.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} However, during his seven years and seven months imprisoned as a political prisoner of Marcos, Aquino read the book ''Born Again'' by convicted [[Watergate]] conspirator [[Charles Colson]] and it inspired him to a religious awakening.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=__ripZFVtUQ&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result, the remainder of his personal and political life had a distinct spiritual sheen. He emerged as a contemporary counterpart of [[Jose Rizal]], who was among the world's earliest proponents of the use of non-violence to combat a repressive regime. Some remained skeptical of Aquino's redirected spiritual focus, but it ultimately had an effect on his wife's political career. While some may question the prominence given Aquino in Philippine history, it was his assassination that was pivotal to the downfall of a despotic ruler and the eventual restoration of democracy in the Philippines.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

==Personal life==
On October 11, 1954, he married [[Corazon Aquino|Corazon &quot;Cory&quot; Sumulong Cojuangco]], with whom he had five children (four daughters and a son):{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}
*Maria Elena Aquino-Cruz (Ballsy, born August 18, 1955), married to Eldon Cruz, sons Justin Benigno &quot;Jiggy&quot; Cruz and Eldon &quot;Jonty&quot; Cruz, Jr.
*Aurora Corazon Aquino-Abellada (Pinky, born December 27, 1957), married to Manuel Abellada, son Miguel Abellada, daughter Nina Abellada
*[[Benigno Aquino III|Benigno Simeon Aquino III]] (Noynoy, born February 8, 1960), the [[List of Presidents of the Philippines|15th]] and current [[President of the Philippines]]
*Victoria Elisa Aquino-Dee (Viel, born October 27, 1961), married to Joseph Dee, son Francis &quot;Kiko&quot; Dee, daughter Jacinta Patricia &quot;Jia&quot; Dee
*[[Kris Aquino|Kristina Bernadette Aquino]] (Kris, born February 14, 1971), married to [[James Yap]] (2005–2010), sons Joshua Philip &quot;Josh&quot; Aquino Salvador and James &quot;Baby James/Bimby&quot; Aquino Yap, Jr.

===Ancestry===
{{ahnentafel top|width=100%}}
{{ahnentafel-compact5
|style=font-size: 100%; line-height: 110%;
|border=1
|boxstyle=padding-top: 0; padding-bottom: 0;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Benigno Aquino Jr.'''
|2= 2. [[Benigno Aquino, Sr.|Benigno '''Aquino''', Sr.]]
|3= 3. Aurora '''Aquino'''
|4= 4. [[Servillano Aquino|Servillano '''Aquino''']]
|5= 5. Guadalupe '''Quiambao'''
|6= 6. Agapito '''Aquino'''
|8= 8. Braulio '''Aquino'''
|9= 9. Petrona '''Aguilar'''
|10= 10. Pablo '''Quiambao'''
|11= 11. Lorenza '''Tañedo'''
|12= 12. M. '''Aquino'''
|13= 13. ----- '''Santos'''
|16= 16. Hilario '''Aquino'''
|17= 17. Isabela '''Lacsamana'''
|18= 18. Dionisio '''Aguilar'''
|19= 19. Juana Petrona '''Henson'''
|22= 22. Vicente '''Tañedo'''
|23= 23. Fausta '''García'''
}}&lt;/center&gt;
{{ahnentafel bottom}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Philippines|Biography}}
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite web |url=http://www.inq7.net/nat/2003/aug/21/nat_4-1.htm |title=The last time I saw Ninoy|author=Corazon Aquino|work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|date=August 21, 2003 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060516180338/http://www.inq7.net/nat/2003/aug/21/nat_4-1.htm |archivedate=May 16, 2006}}
* [http://www.youtube.com/NinoyAquinoTV Ninoy Aquino YouTube Channel]
* [http://www.iamninoy.com &quot;I Am Ninoy&quot; website]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hBzuQolq93A&amp;feature=PlayList&amp;p=20BE8D342C2F65DA&amp;playnext_from=PL&amp;index=0&amp;playnext=1 History Channel's feature documentary on Ninoy Aquino's Assassination]
* http://web.archive.org/web/20060516180338/http://www.inq7.net/nat/2003/aug/21/nat_4-1.htm
* http://www.philippinenews.com/news/view_article.html?article_id+808c5b09d7d3c4becaff5f49fd1acc09
* http://www.time.com/time/asia/covers/501060227/murder.html
* http://www.rmaf.org.ph/Awardees/Biography/BiographyAquinoCor.htm
* [http://www.mainlib.upd.edu.ph/ipn/search.php?f=subject&amp;auth=815 The good die young: Sen. Benigno S. Aquino, Jr. (1932–1983). Index to Philippine Periodicals]
* http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view/20080821-155890/Fewer-than-10-people-in-plot-5-core-5-others-in-the-know
* http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view/20080823-156342/The-Pattugalan-Memos-on-Project-Four-Flowers
* http://services.inquirer.net/print/print.php?article_id=154970
*[http://benignian.clan.su Tambayan ng mga Benignian]
{{Refend}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{Succession box|
  before= [[Arsenio A. Lugay]] |
  title= [[Tarlac|Governor of Tarlac Province]] |
  years= 1961–1967 |
  after= [[Eduardo Cojuangco, Jr.]]
}}
{{s-par|ph-upr}}
{{Succession box|
  before= not applicable |
  title= [[Philippine Senate|Senator of the Republic]] |
  after= not applicable |
  years= 1967–1972 |
}}
{{S-end}}

{{Corazon Aquino}}
{{Noynoy Aquino}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Aquino, Benigno Jr.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =November 27, 1932
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Concepcion, Tarlac]], Philippines
| DATE OF DEATH     =August 21, 1983
| PLACE OF DEATH    =[[Ninoy Aquino International Airport|Manila International Airport]], [[Pasay City]], [[Metro Manila]], Philippines
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Aquino, Benigno Jr.}}
[[Category:1932 births]]
[[Category:1983 deaths]]
[[Category:Aquino family|Benigno Aquino 2]]
[[Category:Assassinated Filipino politicians]]
[[Category:Ateneo de Manila University alumni]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Filipino democracy activists]]
[[Category:Filipino expatriates in the United States]]
[[Category:Filipino journalists]]
[[Category:Filipino Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Harvard University people]]
[[Category:Kapampangan people]]
[[Category:Liberal Party (Philippines) politicians]]
[[Category:Mayors of places in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Members of the Senate of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Nacionalista Party politicians]]
[[Category:People from Tarlac]]
[[Category:People murdered in the Philippines]]
[[Category:People's Power (Philippines) politicians]]
[[Category:Provincial governors of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Spouses of the Presidents of the Philippines]]

[[zh-min-nan:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[bcl:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[ceb:Ninoy Aquino]]
[[cbk-zam:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[da:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[de:Benigno Aquino junior]]
[[es:Benigno Aquino]]
[[fa:بنینو آکینو]]
[[fr:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[ko:베니그노 아키노]]
[[ilo:Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.]]
[[id:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[ia:Benigno Aquino Junior]]
[[it:Benigno Aquino Jr.]]
[[he:בנינו אקינו]]
[[pam:Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.]]
[[la:Benignus Aquino iunior]]
[[ms:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[nl:Benigno Aquino jr.]]
[[ja:ベニグノ・アキノ・ジュニア]]
[[no:Benigno S. Aquino]]
[[pag:Ninoy Aquino]]
[[pl:Benigno Aquino]]
[[ru:Акино-младший, Бенигно]]
[[sk:Benigno Aquino]]
[[fi:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[sv:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[tl:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[war:Benigno Aquino, Jr.]]
[[zh:班尼格諾·艾奎諾]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
