<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="279629" ns="0" title="Joseph Estrada"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the former President of the Philippines|the French company|ERAP}}
{{Infobox president
|name          = Joseph Estrada
|image         = Josephestradapentagon.jpg
|office        = [[List of Presidents of the Philippines|13th]] [[President of the Philippines]] &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[History of the Philippines (1986–present)|3rd President of the Fifth Republic]]
|vicepresident = [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]]
|term_start    =  June 30, 1998
|term_end      =  January 20, 2001
|predecessor   = [[Fidel V. Ramos]]
|successor     = [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]]
|office2       = [[List of Vice Presidents of the Philippines|11th]] [[Vice President of the Philippines]]
|president2    = [[Fidel V. Ramos]]
|term_start2   = June 30, 1992
|term_end2     = June 30, 1998
|predecessor2  = [[Salvador Laurel]]
|successor2    = [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]]
|office3       = Chairman of the Presidential Anti-Crime Commission
|president3    = [[Fidel V. Ramos]]
|term_start3   = 1992
|term_end3     = 1997
|office4       = [[Senate of the Philippines|Senator of the Philippines]]
|term_start4   = June 30, 1987
|term_end4     = June 30, 1992
|predecessor4  =
|successor4    =
|office5       = Mayor of [[San Juan, Metro Manila]]
|term_start5   = December 30, 1969
|term_end5     = March 25, 1986
|predecessor5  = Braulio Sto. Domingo
|successor5    = Adolfo Sto. Domingo
|birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|fm=yes|1937|4|19}}
|birth_place   = [[Tondo, Manila]], [[Commonwealth of the Philippines|Philippines]]
|death_date    =
|death_place   =
|party         = [[Pwersa ng Masang Pilipino|PMP]] &lt;small&gt;(1991–present)&lt;/small&gt;
|otherparty    = [[Nacionalista Party|Nacionalista]] &lt;small&gt;(1969–1987)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal Party]] &lt;small&gt;(1987–1991)&lt;/small&gt;
|spouse        = [[Loi Estrada|Luisa Pimentel]]
|alma_mater    = [[Ateneo de Manila University]],&lt;br&gt;[[Mapúa Institute of Technology]]
|profession    = Actor&lt;br&gt;Businessperson&lt;br&gt;Politician
|religion      = Roman Catholicism
|signature     = Estrada_Sig.png
|website       = [http://erap.ph/ Official website]
}}
'''Joseph &quot;Erap&quot; Ejercito Estrada''' (born '''Jose Marcelo Ejercito''' on April 19, 1937) was the [[List of Presidents of the Philippines|13th]] [[President of the Philippines]], serving from 1998 until 2001. Estrada  was the first person in the [[History of the Philippines (1986–present)|Post-EDSA era]] to be elected both to the presidency and vice-presidency.

Estrada gained popularity as a film actor, playing the lead role in over 100 films in an acting career spanning 33 years. He leveraged his popularity as an actor to make gains in politics, serving as mayor of [[San Juan City|San Juan]] for seventeen years, as [[Senate of the Philippines|Senator]] for one term, then as [[Vice President of the Philippines]] under the administration of President [[Fidel Ramos]].

Estrada was elected President in 1998 with a wide margin of votes separating him from the other challengers, and was sworn into the presidency on June 30, 1998. In 2000 he declared an &quot;all-out-war&quot; against the [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front]] and captured its headquarters and other camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;peopledaily2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/english/200007/10/eng20000710_45067.html |title=Philippine Military Takes Moro Headquarters |work=People's Daily  |date=July 10, 2000 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdn.org.ph/speech-of-former-president-estrada-on-the-grp-moro-conflict/ |title=Speech of Former President Estrada on the GRP-MORO Conflict – Philippine Human Development Network |publisher=Hdn.org.ph |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, allegations of corruption spawned an [[impeachment]] trial in the Senate, and in 2001 Estrada was ousted by People Power 2 after the prosecution walked out of the impeachment court when the Senator Judges voted no in the opening of the second envelope.

In 2007, he was sentenced by the special division of the [[Sandiganbayan]] to [[reclusion perpetua]] for [[embezzlement|plunder]], but was later granted pardon by President [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]]. He ran for president anew in the [[2010 Philippine presidential election]], but lost to then Senator [[Benigno Aquino III]].

==Early life and career==
Joseph Ejercito Estrada was born on April 19, 1937 in [[Tondo, Manila|Tondo]], an urban district of [[Manila]]. His family later moved to the wealthy suburb of San Juan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Biography |url=http://erap.ph/409/about-erap/ |title=Joseph &quot;Erap&quot; Ejercito Estrada – The Official Webpage of Joseph Ejercito Estrada » Biography |publisher=Erap.ph |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He belonged to a upper middle class family, and was the eighth of ten children of [[Emilio Ejercito]] and his wife [[Maria Marcelo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;malaya&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=...So Help Us God: The Vice Presidents of the Philippines and Their Inaugural Addresses |last=Malaya |first=J. Eduardo |coauthors=Nathan E. Malaya |year=2004 |publisher=Anvil Publishing |location=Pasig City |isbn=971-27-1487-X |pages=277–299 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He finished his primary studies at the [[Ateneo de Manila University]] and subsequently enrolled on an engineering course at the Mapua Institute of Technology in an effort to please his father, but dropped out.

In his twenties, he began a career as a drama actor. He adopted the drama name &quot;Joseph Estrada&quot;, as his mother objected to his chosen career and his decision to quit schooling.&lt;ref name=&quot;malaya&quot;/&gt; He also acquired the nickname &quot;Erap&quot; (a play on the [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]] slang &quot;pare&quot;, meaning buddy) from his friend [[Fernando Poe, Jr.]].

===Film===
{{Main|Joseph Estrada filmography}}
He played the lead role in more than 100 movies, and produced more than 70 films. He was the first FAMAS Hall of Fame recipient for Best Actor (1981) and also became a Hall of Fame award-winner as a producer (1983). He often played heroes of the downtrodden classes, making him popular among the nation's many unschooled and impoverished citizens. This proved advantageous to his political career.

In 1974 he founded the Movie Workers Welfare Foundation (Mowelfund), which helps filmmakers through medical reimbursements, hospitalization, surgery and death benefits, livelihood, and alternative income opportunities and housing. Its educational arm, the Mowelfund Film Institute, has produced some of the most skilled and respected producers, filmmakers, writers and performers in both the independent and mainstream sectors of the industry since its inception in 1979.&lt;ref&gt;Martinez-Belen, Crispina. (2009, March 27). [http://mb.com.ph/articles/200438/mowelfund-marks-35th-year Mowelfund marks 35th year]. ''The Manila Bulletin''. Retrieved September 28, 2009 from http://mb.com.ph&lt;/ref&gt;{{Failed verification|date=December 2010}} He also founded, together with Guillermo de Vega, the first Metro Manila Film Festival in 1975.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Early political career==
===Mayor of San Juan===
Estrada entered politics in 1967 when he ran for mayor of [[San Juan City|San Juan]], then a municipality of Metro Manila, and succeeded in only 1969 after winning an electoral protest against Braulio Sto. Domingo. His administration was marked by unequaled accomplishments in infrastructure development. These included the establishment of the first Municipal High School, the Agora complex, a modern slaughterhouse, a sprawling government center with a post office, a mini-park and the concreting of 98 percent of the town's roads and alleys.

As mayor, he paid particular attention to the elementary education of children by improving and renovating school buildings and constructing additional school structures, health centers, barangay halls and playgrounds in all the barangays and providing artesian wells to areas with low water supply. He relocated some 1,800 squatter families out of San Juan to Taytay, Rizal, at no cost. He was also the first mayor to computerize assessment of the Real Estate Tax in the Municipal Assessor’s Office.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://erap.ph/speakson/erap_bio.htm President Joseph Ejercito Estrada, A Biography]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When [[Corazon Aquino]] assumed the presidency in 1986, all elected officials of the local government were forcibly removed and replaced by appointed officers-in-charge, including Estrada{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}.

===Senator of the Philippines===
The following year, he won a seat in the [[Senate of the Philippines|Senate]] under the Grand Alliance for Democracy (GAD) placing 16th in the elections (out of 24 winners). In 1987, he set his sights on a Senate run and handily garnered a seat. He was appointed Chairman of the Committee on Public Works. He was Vice-Chairman of the Committees on Health, Natural Resources and Ecology and Urban Planning.

In the Senate, Estrada was credited with the passage of, among other major pieces of legislation, the bills on irrigation project and the protection and propagation of [[carabao]]s, the beast of burden in the rural areas.

As a senator, he was one of the so-called “Magnificent 12” who voted to terminate the RP-US Military Bases Agreement leading to the withdrawal of American servicemen from the Clark Air Base in Pampanga and the Subic Naval Base in Zambales.

In 1989, the Free Press cited him as one of the Three Outstanding Senators of the Year. He was conferred the degree of Doctor of Humanities, Honoris Causa by the Bicol University in April 1997, and the University of Pangasinan in 1990.

==Vice-Presidency==
{{See also|Presidency of Fidel V. Ramos}}

In 1992, Joseph Estrada ran for vice-president as the running mate of [[Eduardo Cojuangco, Jr.]] under the [[Nationalist People's Coalition]] party. Though the latter lost to former National Defense Secretary Fidel Ramos, Estrada won the vice-presidency garnering more votes than his closest opponent, [[Ramon Mitra, Jr.|Ramon Mitra, Jr.'s]] running mate, [[Marcelo Fernan]].

As Vice-President, Estrada he was the chairman of President Ramos' Presidential Anti-Crime Commission (PACC). Estrada arrested  criminal warlords and kidnapping syndicates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yehey.com/news/Article.aspx?id=181710 |title=The rise and fall of Joseph Estrada – Yehey! News |publisher=Yehey.com |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He resigned as chairman in 1997.

In the same year Estrada, together with former President [[Corazon Aquino]], Cardinal [[Jaime Sin]], Senator [[Gloria Macapagal Arroyo]] and other political leaders, led an anti-charter change rally brought in an estimated half a million people to Rizal Park against the charter change moves by Ramos and his supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/113427/Gloria-and-cha-cha |title=– Gloria and cha-cha – Research – Official Website of GMA News and Public Affairs – Latest Philippine News – BETA |publisher=Gmanews.tv |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Presidency==
{{Main|Presidency of Joseph Estrada}}
[[File:ImagePhp bill 2000 front.jpg|thumb|200px|right|The inauguration of President Estrada on June 30, 1998, featured in the Philippine piso centennial commemorative legal tender banknote.]]
Estrada was inaugurated on June 30, 1998 in the historical town of [[Malolos]] in [[Bulacan]] province in paying tribute to the cradle of the [[First Philippine Republic]]. That afternoon the new president delivered his inaugural address at the [[Quirino Grandstand]] in [[Luneta]]. He assumed office amid the [[Asian Financial Crisis]] and with agricultural problems due to poor weather conditions, thereby slowing the economic growth to −0.6% in 1998 from a 5.2% in 1997.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gov.ph/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=200020&amp;Itemid=26 |title=Philippines : Gov.Ph : The Official Government Portal of the Republic of the Philippines – General Information |publisher=Gov.Ph |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The economy recovered by 3.4% in 1999 and 4% in 2000.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6&gt;Abaya, Antonio. (2007, Jan. 17). [http://www.iskandalo.com/article.html?id=264 GMAs Successes]. Retrieved September 28, 2009. &lt;!-- Replaced original link that became invalid: http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=antonioAbaya_jan17_2008 with what I suspect is an alternate link referring to a copy of the original article --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000 he declared an &quot;all-out-war&quot; against the [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front]] and captured it's headquarters and other camps.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdn.org.ph/speech-of-former-president-estrada-on-the-grp-moro-conflict/ |title=Speech of Former President Estrada on the GRP-MORO Conflict – Philippine Human Development Network |publisher=Hdn.org.ph |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;peopledaily2&quot;/&gt; However, allegations of corruption spawned a railroaded [[impeachment]] trial in the Senate courtesy of house speaker [[Manuel Villar]], and in 2001 Estrada was ousted from a coup after the trial was aborted.

In his Inaugural Address, Estrada said:
{{cquote|One hundred years after Kawit, fifty years after independence, twelve years after EDSA, and seven years after the rejection of foreign bases, it is now the turn of the masses to experience liberation. We stand in the shadow of those who fought to make us free--free from foreign domination, free from domestic tyranny, free from superpower dictation, free from economic backwardness.&lt;ref&gt;[http://erap.ph/speakson/inagural063098.htm Untitled Document]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Domestic policies===

{{Main|Domestic_Policies of Joseph Estrada}}

===Foreign policies===
{{Main|Presidency_of_Joseph_Estrada#Foreign_Policies}}

===Economy===
[[File:Vladimir Putin at APEC Summit in Brunei 15-16 November-9.jpg|thumb|220px|right|President Joseph Estrada (7th person from right) during the [[APEC]] summit in 2000.]]

In 1998, Estrada was elected president. Even with its strong [[economic]] [[team]], the Estrada administration failed to capitalize on the gains of the previous administration. His administration was severely criticized for [[cronyism]], [[Competence (human resources)|incompetence]], and corruption, causing it to lose the confidence of [[foreign investors]]. {{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} Foreign investors' confidence was further damaged when, in his second year, Estrada was accused of exerting influence in an investigation of a friend's involvement in [[Presidency of Joseph Estrada#BW Resources Scandal|stock market manipulation]]. Social unrest brought about by bombings, bomb threats, kidnappings, etc. contributed to the economy's troubles. [[Economic]] performance was also hurt [http://www.gov.ph/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=200020&amp;Itemid=26 by climatic disturbance that caused extremes of dry and wet weather.] By the end of Estrada's administration, the fiscal deficit had reportedly doubled to more than P 100&amp;nbsp;billion from a low of P 49&amp;nbsp;billion in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iskandalo.com/article.html?id=264 |title=www.iskandalo.com |publisher=iskandalo.com |date=August 21, 1983 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite such setbacks, the rate of GNP in 1999 increased to 3.6 percent from 0.1 percent in 1998, and the GDP posted a 3.2 percent growth rate, up from a low of −0.5 percent in 1998. Debt reached P 2.1&amp;nbsp;trillion in 1999. Domestic debt amounted to P 986.7&amp;nbsp;billion while foreign debt stood at US$ 52.2&amp;nbsp;billion.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://opinion.inquirer.net/inquireropinion/letterstotheeditor/view/20081007-164968/Records-prove-Estradas-achievements &quot;Records prove Estrada's achievements&quot;] ''Philippine News for Filipinos''&lt;/ref&gt;

===War against the MILF===
During the Ramos administration a cessation of hostilities agreement was signed between the Philippine Government and the [[Moro Islamic Liberation Front]] ([[MILF]]) in July 1997. This was continued by a  series of peace talks and negotiations in Estrada administration.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; The MILF, an Islamic group formed in 1977, seeks to be an independent Islamic State from the Philippines, and, despite the agreements, a sequence of terrorist attacks on the Philippine military and civilians still continued.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt; It was later divulged in a Senate Hearing by then Lt. (now Senator) Antonio Trillanes that  the Military was behind these terrorist attacks to justify the &quot;all-out-war&quot; policy of the government which was masterminded by [http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=215752 Chief of Staff Angelo Reyes], and which included the kidnapping a foreign priest, namely Father Luciano Benedetti; the destruction by arson of Talayan, Maguindanao's municipal hall; the takeover of the Kauswagan Municipal Hall; the bombing of the Lady of Mediatrix boat at [[Ozamiz City]]; and the takeover of the Narciso Ramos Highway. By doing so, they inflicted severe damage on the country's image abroad, and scared much-needed investments away. For this reason, on
March 21, 2000, Estrada declared an &quot;all-out-war&quot; against the MILF. During the war the [[Catholic Bishops' Conference of the Philippines]] (CBCP) asked Estrada to negotiate a [[cease-fire]] with MILF, but Estrada opposed the idea arguing that a cease-fire would cause more terrorist attacks. For the next three months of the war, Camp Abubakar, headquarters of the MILF, fell along with other 13 major camps and 43 minor camps, and then all of which became under controlled by the government. The MILF leader Hashim Salamat fled to [[Malaysia]]. The MILF later declared a [[Jihad]] on the government. On July 10 of the same year, the President went to Minadanao and raised the Philippine flag symbolizing victory. After the war the President said, &quot;... will speed up government efforts to bring genuine and lasting peace and development in Mindanao&quot;. In the middle of July the president ordered the military to arrest top MILF leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;peopledaily1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/english/200007/10/eng20000710_45067.html |title=Philippine Military Takes Moro Headquarters |work=People's Daily  |date=July 10, 2000 |accessdate=March 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his [[State of the Nation Address (Philippines)|state of the nation address]], popularly called &quot;SONA&quot;, the president highlighted his vision for Mindanao:
*The first is to restore and maintain peace in Mindanao—because without peace, there can be no development.
*The second is to develop Mindanao—because without development, there can be no peace.
*The third is to continue seeking peace talks with the MILF within the framework of the Constitution—because a peace agreed upon in good faith is preferable to a peace enforced by force of arms.
*And the fourth is to continue with the implementation of the peace agreement between the government and the Moro National Liberation Front, or MNLF—because that is our commitment to our countrymen and to the international community.

In addition to this the president said his administration can move with more speed in transforming Mindanao into a progressive economic center.&lt;ref name=&quot;peopledaily1&quot;/&gt; High on the list of priorities was the plight of MILF guerrillas who were tired of fighting and had no camps left to which to report. On October 5, 2000 the first massive surrender of 669 MILF mujahideen led by the renegade vice mayor of Marugong, Lanao del Sur Malupandi Cosandi Sarip and seven other battalion commanders, surrendered to President Estrada at the 4th ID headquarters in Camp Edilberto Evangelista, Bgy. Patag, Cagayan de Oro City. They were followed shortly by a second batch of 855 surrenderees led by MILF Commander Sayben Ampaso on December 29, 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/view/8068 |title='&amp;#39;American Chronicle'&amp;#39;, &quot;AFP-MILF 2000 War in Mindanao Remembered&quot; |publisher=Americanchronicle.com |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Controversies===
{{Main|Presidency_of_Joseph_Estrada#Controversies}}

===Corruption charges and impeachment===
[[File:Joseph estrada 2000.jpg|thumb|150px|left|President Estrada in 2000.]]
In October 2000, [[Ilocos Sur]] governor [[Chavit Singson|Luis &quot;Chavit&quot; Singson]], a close friend the President, alleged that he had personally given Estrada P400&amp;nbsp;million as payoff from jueteng hidden in a bank account known as &quot;Jose Velarde&quot; – a grassroots-based numbers game, as well as P180&amp;nbsp;million from the government price subsidy for the tobacco farmers' marketing cooperative after Estrada ordered a full blown investigation into Chavit Singson's alleged misuse of millions of pesos in public funds. Singson's allegation caused controversy across the nation, which culminated in the House of Representatives' filing of an impeachment case against Estrada on November 13, 2000. House Speaker [[Manny Villar]] fast-tracked the impeachment complaint. The impeachment suit was brought to the Senate and an impeachment court was formed, with Chief Justice [[Hilario Davide, Jr.]] as presiding officer. Estrada, pleaded “not guilty”.

This was the first time the Filipino public witnessed, through radio and television, an elected president stand in trial and face possible impeachment with full media coverage. During the trial, the prosecution presented witnesses and alleged evidences to the impeachment court regarding Estrada's alleged involvement in jueteng. The existence of secret bank accounts which he allegedly uses for receiving payoffs was also brought to the fore.

===EDSA II===
{{Main|EDSA Revolution of 2001}}

====Protests====
On the evening of January 16, 2001, the impeachment court voted not to open an envelope that was alleged to contain incriminating evidence against the president simply because it was not part of the impeachment complaint. The final vote was 11–10, in favor of keeping the envelope closed. The prosecution panel (of congressmen and lawyers) walked out of the Impeachment Court in protest of this vote. The 11 senators who voted not to open the envelope are known as the &quot;Craven Eleven.&quot; That night, anti-Estrada protesters gathered in front of the [[Our Lady of Peace Quasi-Parish|EDSA Shrine]] at [[Epifanio de los Santos Avenue]], not too far away from the site of the 1986 [[People Power Revolution]] that overthrew Ferdinand Marcos.

On January 19, 2001, Armed Forces of the Philippines Chief of Staff [[Angelo Reyes]], seeing the political upheaval throughout the country, &quot;decided to withdraw his support&quot; from the president and transfer his allegiance to the vice president, Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo.

====Resignation====
The following day, the Supreme Court declared that the seat of presidency was vacant, saying that Estrada &quot;constructively resigned his post&quot;. At noon, the Chief Justice swore in Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo, as President of the Philippines. Prior to Estrada's departure from [[Malacañang]], he issued the following press release:

{{cquote|At twelve o'clock noon today, Vice President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo took her oath as President of the Republic of the Philippines. While along with many other legal minds of our country, I have strong and serious doubts about the legality and constitutionality of her proclamation as President, I do not wish to be a factor that will prevent the restoration of unity and order in our civil society.

It is for this reason that '''I now leave Malacañang Palace, the seat of the presidency of this country''', for the sake of peace and in order to begin the healing process of our nation. I leave the Palace of our people with gratitude for the opportunities given to me for service to our people. I will not shirk from any future challenges that may come ahead in the same service of our country.

I call on all my supporters and followers to join me in to promotion of a constructive national spirit of reconciliation and solidarity.

May the Almighty bless our country and beloved people.

MABUHAY!&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lawphil.net/judjuris/juri2001/mar2001/gr_146710_2001.html |title=G.R. No. 146710-15 |publisher=Lawphil.net |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Post-Presidency==
Estrada returned to his old home in San Juan. He maintained that he never resigned, implying that Arroyo's government was [[illegitimate]].

The new government ceated a special court and charged him with plunder and had him arrested in April. Filipino supporters marched to the [[Our Lady of Peace Quasi-Parish|EDSA Shrine]] demanding Estrada's release and his reinstatement as president but were dispersed by high-grade teargas and warning shots from automatic rifles. On the morning of May 1, the protesters marched straight to [[Malacanang Palace]]. Violence erupted and the government declared a [[State of Rebellion]]. Many Filipino protesters were badly injured and arrested, including politicians. The government called out the military and was able to quell the demonstration with teargas and automatic rifles. The bloody uprising came to be known as [[EDSA III]].

Estrada was initially detained at the Veteran's Memorial Medical Center in [[Quezon City]] and then transferred to a military facility in [[Tanay, Rizal]], but he was later transferred to a nearby vacation home, virtually in house arrest. Under Philippine law, plunder had a maximum penalty of death, however the death penalty was eventually repealed.

===Trial===
{{Main|Trial of Joseph Estrada}}

On September 12, 2007, the Sandiganbayan finally gave its decision, finding Estrada not guilty on his perjury case but guilty of plunder &quot;beyond reasonable doubt.&quot; He was sentenced to [[Reclusión perpetua]]. He was thus the first Philippine President who was impeached and then convicted.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gmanews.tv/story/60117/Erap-guilty-of-plunder-sentenced-to-reclusion-perpetua &quot;Erap guilty of plunder, sentenced to ''reclusion perpetua''&quot;], gmanews.tv, September 12, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 26, 2007, Joseph Estrada appealed by filing a 63-page motion for reconsideration of the [[Sandiganbayan]] judgment penned by [[Teresita de Castro]] (submitting 5 legal grounds).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/asiapacific/news/article_1359793.php/Philippines_ex-president_Estrada_appeals_conviction_for_plunder |title=Monstersandcritics.com, Philippines' ex-president Estrada appeals conviction for plunder |publisher=Monstersandcritics.com |date=September 26, 2007 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=english@peopledaily.com.cn |url=http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/6271706.html |title=English.people.com, Convicted Philippine ex-president files reconsideration motion |work=People's Daily  |date=September 26, 2007 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Estrada alleged that the court erred &quot;''when it convicted him by acquitting his alleged co-conspirators''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view_article.php?article_id=90841 |title=Inquirer.net, Estrada asks Sandiganbayan to reverse conviction, Cites acquittal of co-accused |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 5, 2007, the [[Sandiganbayan]]'s Special Division ruled to have set for October 19, [[oral argument]] (instead of a defense reply) on Joseph Estrada’s motion for reconsideration. Estrada asked for court permission to attend the hearing, since it ordered the prosecution to file comment before October 11.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mb.com.ph/MAIN20071007105086.html  ManilaBulletin, Erap wants to attend Sandigan oral arguments]{{Dead link|date=October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Perjury case===
The [[Sandiganbayan]]'s special division, on June 27, 2008, ordered Estrada to file comment within 10 days, on the motion of the Ombudsman's Special Prosecutor to re-open the trial of his [[perjury]] case regarding 1999 statement of assets, liabilities and net worth (SALN). The court will also resolve [[Banco de Oro]]'s (formerly Equitable PCI Bank), plea that it cannot determine &quot;without hazard to itself&quot; who to turn over to the P1.1&amp;nbsp;billion Jose Velarde assets due to claims by Wellex Group / William Gatchalian and a [[Bureau of Internal Revenue (Philippines)|Bureau of Internal Revenue]] stay order.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20080627-145167/Estrada-told-to-reply-to-request-to-start-perjury-trial |title=newsinfo.inquirer.net, Estrada told to reply to request to start perjury trial |publisher=Newsinfo.inquirer.net |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pardon and release from detention===
On October 22, 2007, Acting Justice Secretary Agnes Devanadera stated that Joseph Estrada is seeking a “''full, free, and unconditional pardon''” from President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo.  Estrada's lawyer Jose Flaminiano wrote Arroyo: &quot;''The time has come to end President Estrada's fight for justice and vindication before the courts. Today [Monday], we filed a withdrawal of his Motion for Reconsideration''.&quot; Estrada, 70, stressed the &quot;''delicate condition''&quot; of his mother in asking for pardon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/22/asia/AS-GEN-Philippines-Estrada.php ''IHT'', Ousted Philippine president withdraws appeal for his plunder conviction, seeks pardon]{{Dead link|date=May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 25, 2007, President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo granted [[executive clemency]] to Joseph Estrada based on the recommendation by the Department of Justice (DoJ). Acting Executive Secretary and Press Secretary Ignacio R. Bunye quoted the signed Order: &quot;''In view hereof in pursuant of the authority conferred upon me by the Constitution, I hereby grant Executive clemency to Joseph Ejercito Estrada, convicted by the Sandiganbayan of plunder and imposed a penalty of reclusion perpetua. He is hereby restored to his civil and political rights''.&quot;
Bunye noted that Estrada committed in his application not to seek public office, and he would be free from his Tanay resthouse on October 26, noon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/asiapacific/news/article_1368473.php/Philippine_leader_pardons_ex-president_Estrada__1st_Lead_ |title=news.monstersandcritics.com, Philippine leader pardons ex-president Estrada |publisher=Monstersandcritics.com |date=October 25, 2007 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view_article.php?article_id=96730 |title=Inquirer.net, Arroyo grants pardon to Estrada |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/65884/Estrada-granted-pardon |title=Gmanews.tv, Estrada granted executive clemency |publisher=Gmanews.tv |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 26, 2007, after almost 7 years of detention, Joseph Estrada was finally released after the [[Sandiganbayan]] promulgated the historical Resolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view_article.php?article_id=96897 |title=Inquirer.net, Sandigan approves Estrada release |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Activities===
When he was released he gave a message to the Filipino people that he can once again help the lives of the people, especially the poor. He also stated that he made errors as a public servant but he assured them that corruption was not one of them. After the release he had a nationwide tour called &quot;Lakbay Pasasalamat&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.senate.gov.ph/photo_release/2009/0217_04.asp |title=Photo Release – Lakbay Pasasalamat |publisher=Senate.gov.ph |date=February 17, 2009 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Philippine Headline News Online (Phno) |url=http://www.newsflash.org/2004/02/hl/hl107327.htm |title=ERAP TO ENDORSE WHOEVER TOPS SURVEY IN 2010 |work=Philippine Headline News |date=April 9, 2008 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Thank you tour) and during those trips he thanked the people for their support and gave them relief goods such as food, medicines and clothing.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/video/39976/QTV-Erap-gives-gift-bags-as-part-of-birthday-celebration |title=– QTV: Erap gives gift bags as part of birthday celebration |publisher=GMA News  |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/video/33891/Estrada-distributes-food-clothes-medicine-in-Quezon-City |title=– Estrada distributes food, clothes, medicine in Quezon City |publisher=GMA News  |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In politics, he is convincing leaders of the opposition to have unity in the party or, he said, he will run.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/video/39799/Saksi-Erap-bares-list-of-possible-senatorial-bets-for-2010 |title=– Saksi: Erap bares list of possible senatorial bets for 2010 |publisher=GMA News  |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==2010 Presidential election==
Joseph Estrada has stated in interviews that he would be willing to run for the opposition in the event that they are unable to unite behind a single candidate.&lt;ref name=&quot;philstar-clapano&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Clapano |first=Jose Rodel |title=Erap can run? Binay ready for 2010; Noli open as opposition's bet |work=[[Philippine Star]] |date=January 7, 2008 |url=http://www.newsflash.org/2004/02/hl/hl106874.htm |accessdate=January 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gmanews-estrada&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Erap gives up on opposition unity, decides to run himself |work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]] |date=September 26, 2009|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view/20090926-226941/Erap-gives-up-on-opposition-unity-decides-to-run-himself|accessdate=September 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fr. Joaquin Bernas and Christian Monsod, members of the constitutional commission that drafted the 1987 Constitution, have stated that the constitution clearly prohibits any elected president from seeking a second term at any point in time.&lt;ref name=&quot;comedy-tragedy&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=de Quiros |first=Conrado  |title=Comedy, tragedy |work=Philippine Daily Inquirer |date=January 8, 2008 |url=http://www.inquirer.net/specialreports/theestradawatch/view.php?db=1&amp;article=20080108-110964 |accessdate=January 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romulo Macalintal, election counsel of President Arroyo, has clarified that the constitutional ban doesn't prevent Estrada from attaining the presidency in the event that he were to be elevated from the vice-presidency, for example.&lt;ref name=&quot;philstar-punay&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Punay |first=Edu |title=GMA election lawyer insists Erap can't run in 2010 |work=Philippine Star |date=December 23, 2008 |url=http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?ArticleId=426264&amp;publicationSubCategoryId=63 |accessdate=January 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
However, Rufus Rodriquez, one of Estrada's lawyers, claims that the former president is within his rights to do so because the prohibition banning re-election only applies to the incumbent president.&lt;ref name=&quot;philstar-clapano&quot; /&gt;

On October 22, 2009 former President Joseph Estrada announced that he would run again for president with Makati City Mayor [[Jejomar Binay]] as his running mate.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Speeches |url=http://erap.ph/409/about-erap/speeches/tinatanggap-ko-ang-hamon/ |title=Joseph &quot;Erap&quot; Ejercito Estrada – The Official Webpage of Joseph Ejercito Estrada » TINATANGGAP KO ANG HAMON |publisher=Erap.ph |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His Senatorial lineup includes: [[Francisco Tatad]], [[Juan Ponce Enrile]], [[Jinggoy Estrada]] and [[Joey de Venecia]].

===Other activities===

In October 2010, [[Foreign Policy (magazine)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2010/10/01/bad_exes?page=0,3 |title=Bad Exes – By Joshua E. Keating |publisher=Foreign Policy |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; included Estrada in its list of five former head of states/governments who did not make &quot;a positive difference in the world&quot;, but &quot;faded away into obscurity.&quot; Also included in this &quot;Bad Exes&quot; list were Thailand's [[Thaksin Shinawatra]], Spain's [[Jose Maria Aznar]], and Germany's [[Gerhard Schroder]]. 

Estrada announced in November 2010 that he will be selling his 3,000 square-metre (0.74-acre) home in San Juan, Metro Manila for nearly seven million dollars (300&amp;nbsp;million [[Philippine peso]]) to &quot;pursue his real estate business.&quot;{{cn|date=November 2011}} [[Agence France Presse]] reported that Estrada &quot;has put up two high-rise residential condominium buildings and plans to build a third soon.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20101125/wl_asia_afp/lifestylephilippinespoliticspropertypeopleestrada_20101125042840 ]{{dead link|date=October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Electoral history==
[[File:Erap country.png|thumb|200px|Provinces in which Estrada won in 1992, 1998 and 2010 national elections.]]
'''San Juan mayoralty elections'''
*Estrada won every mayoralty election in San Juan from 1969 to 1984.
'''[[Philippine Senate election, 1987|Senatorial election, 1987]]:'''
*'''Joseph Estrada''' ([[Grand Alliance for Democracy|GAD]]) – 10,029,978 (14th, 24 candidates with the highest number of votes win the 24 seats in the Senate)
'''[[Philippine presidential election, 1992|Vice Presidential election, 1992]]:'''
*'''Joseph Estrada''' ([[Partido ng Masang Pilipino|PMP]]) – 6,739,738 (33.00%)
*[[Marcelo Fernan]] ([[Laban ng Demokratikong Pilipino|LDP]])- 4,438,494 (21.74%)
*[[Emilio Osmeña]] ([[Lakas-NUCD]])- 3,362,467 (16.47%)
*[[Ramon Magsaysay, Jr.]] ([[People's Reform Party|PRP]])- 2,900,556 (14.20%)
*[[Aquilino Pimentel, Jr.]] ([[PDP-Laban]])- 2,023,289 (9.91%)
*[[Vicente Magsaysay]] ([[Kilusang Bagong Lipunan|KBL]])- 699,895 (3.43%)
*[[Eva Estrada-Kalaw]] ([[Nacionalista Party|Nacionalista]])- 255,730 (1.25%)
'''[[Philippine presidential election, 1998|Presidential election, 1998]]:'''
*'''Joseph Estrada''' ([[Laban ng Makabayang Masang Pilipino|LAMMP]])- 10,722,295 (39.86%)
*[[Jose de Venecia]] ([[Lakas-NUCD-UMDP]])- 4,268,483 (15.87%)
*[[Raul Roco]] ([[Aksyon Demokratiko]])- 3,720,212 (13.83%)
*[[Emilio Osmeña]] ([[Probinsya Muna Development Initiative|PROMDI]])- 3,347,631 (12.44%)
*[[Alfredo Lim]] ([[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal]]) – 2,344,362 (8.71%)
*[[Renato de Villa]] ([[Partido ng Demokratikong Reporma-Lapiang Manggagawa|Reporma-LM]])- 1,308,352 (4.86%)
*[[Miriam Defensor Santiago]] ([[People's Reform Party|PRP]])- 797,206 (2.96%)
*[[Juan Ponce Enrile]] (Independent)- 343,139 (1.28%)
*[[Santiago Dumlao]] (Kilusan para sa Pambansang Pagpapanibago)- 32,212 (0.12%)
*[[Manuel Morato]] (Partido Bansang Marangal)- 18,644 (0.07%)
'''[[Philippine presidential election, 2010|Presidential election, 2010]]:'''
*[[Benigno Aquino III]] ([[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal]])- 15,208,678 (42.08%)
*'''Joseph Estrada''' ([[Pwersa ng Masang Pilipino|PMP]])- 9,487,837 (26.25%)
*[[Manny Villar]] ([[Nacionalista Party|Nacionalista]])- 5,573,835 (15.42%)
*[[Gilberto Teodoro]] ([[Lakas Kampi CMD]])- 4,095,839 (11.33%)
*[[Eddie Villanueva]] ([[Bangon Pilipinas Party|Bangon Pilipinas]])- 1,125,878 (3.12%)
*[[Richard Gordon (politician)|Richard Gordon]] ([[Bagumbayan-VNP]])- 501,727 (1.39%)
*[[Nicanor Perlas]] (independent)- 54,575 (0.15%)
*[[Jamby Madrigal]] (independent)- 46,489 (0.13%)
*[[John Carlos de los Reyes]] ([[Ang Kapatiran]])- 44,244 (0.12%)

==Personal life== 
===Family===
Estrada is the first president to be a celebrity. He is also the first mustached president. Estrada is married to (the former Doctor and first lady-turned-senator) [[Loi Estrada|Luisa Pimentel]] and had three children by her:
*Jose Ejercito, Jr. (better known as &quot;[[Jinggoy Estrada]]&quot;; former Mayor of San Juan turned Senator/married to Precy Vitug)
*Jackie Ejercito (married to Beaver Lopez, son of [[Meralco]] chairman Manuel Lopez)
*Jude Ejercito (married to Weng Ocampo)
Joseph Estrada met his wife Loi while working as an orderly at the National Center for Mental Health (NMCH) in Mandaluyong City.

He also has five more children from his out-of-wedlock relationships. All his children listed below are with his former-mistresses:  
*[[JV Ejercito]] (with San Juan City Mayor [[Guia Gomez]]) 
*[[Jojo Ejercito]] (with ex-model Joy Rowena) 
*[[Jerika Ejercito]] (with former live-in partner Laarni Enriquez) 
*[[Jake Ejercito]] (with Laarni Enriquez) 
*[[Jacob Ejercito]] (with Laarni Enriquez)

===Other relatives=== 
Several of Ejercito's relatives became prominent figures in politics and showbiz in their own right
*[[George Estregan|Emilio Ejercito, Jr. a.k.a. George Estregan]], brother of former President and former actor 
*[[E.R. Ejercito]], nephew of former President, actor and former Mayor of [[Pagsanjan, Laguna|Pagsanjan]] turned Governor of [[Laguna (province)|Laguna]] 
*[[Gary Estrada]], nephew of former President, actor and Board Member of [[Quezon]] 
*[[Gherome Ejercito]], nephew of former President and basketball player

===Ancestry===
{{ahnentafel top|width=100%}}
{{ahnentafel-compact5
|style=font-size: 100%; line-height: 110%;
|border=1
|boxstyle=padding-top: 0; padding-bottom: 0;
|boxstyle_1=background-color: #fcc;
|boxstyle_2=background-color: #fb9;
|boxstyle_3=background-color: #ffc;
|boxstyle_4=background-color: #bfc;
|boxstyle_5=background-color: #9fe;
|1= 1. '''Joseph Estrada'''
|2= 2. Emilio '''Ejército'''
|3= 3. María '''Marcelo'''
|4= 4. Telesforo '''Ejército'''
}}&lt;/center&gt;
{{ahnentafel bottom}}

==In popular culture==
Since the beginning of his political career, Estrada has been the butt of many jokes in the Philippines. Majority of the jokes about him center around his limited English vocabulary, while others focus on his corruption scandals. During his presidential campaign in 1998, Estrada authorized the distribution of the joke compilation book ''ERAPtion: How to Speak English Without Really Trial''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Robles |first=Alan C. |url=http://www.hotmanila.ph/ESP/2000/joked_to_death0300110.htm?comments_page=0 |title=Hot Manila – Joked to Death |publisher=Hotmanila.ph |date=November 22, 2000 |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and honors==
*1962 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Markang Rehas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot;&gt;http://erap.ph/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freewebs.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freewebs.com/famas_awards/winners%20circle%20page.htm |title=Winners' Circle Page |publisher=Freewebs.com |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*1964 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Geron Busabos]]&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freewebs.com&quot;/&gt;
*1965 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Ang Batang Quiapo]]
*1966 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Ito ang Pilipino]]&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freewebs.com&quot;/&gt;
*1969 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Patria Adorada]]&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freewebs.com&quot;/&gt;
*1971 Outstanding Mayor and foremost Nationalist by the Inter-Provincial Information Service&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
*1972 One of the Ten Outstanding Young Men (TOYM) in Public Administration by the Philippine Jaycees&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
*1981 FAMAS Best Actor for [[Kumander Alibasbas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freewebs.com&quot;/&gt;
*1981 FAMAS Hall of Fame&lt;ref name=&quot;erap.ph&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freewebs.com/famas_awards/ |title=The Unofficial Website of the 57th Filipino Academy of Movie Arts and Sciences (FAMAS) Awards |publisher=Freewebs.com |accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*2007 Most Outstanding Citizen of San Juan

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
*[http://www.stir.ph/LM/articles~level2/id-1240201252767_4/article.html Joseph Estrada Ang Tanging Ama]

==External links==
{{Wikisource author}}
{{Commons}}
*[http://www.erap.ph/ Official Website of Joseph &quot;Erap&quot; Estrada]
*[http://web.archive.org/web/20001207033000/http://www.opnet.ops.gov.ph/ Office of the President (Archived-Estrada Administration)]
*[http://erap.ph/409/about-erap/ Joseph Estrada Curriculum Vitae]
*[http://www.op.gov.ph/museum/pres_estrada.asp Malacañang Museum Official Biography]
*[http://www.youtube.com/user/erapdotph Official Youtube Channel of Joseph Estrada]
*{{IMDb name|id=0261825|name=Joseph Estrada}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-off}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Salvador Laurel]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Vice President of the Philippines]]|years=June 30, 1992 – June 30, 1998}}
{{S-aft|rows=2|after=[[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]]}}
|-
{{S-bef|before=[[Fidel V. Ramos]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[President of the Philippines]]|years=June 30, 1998 – January 20, 2001}}
{{S-end}}

{{Template group
|list =
{{Joseph Ejercito Estrada}}
{{Philippine presidents}}
{{Philippine Vice Presidents}}
{{Philippine Vice Presidents Succeeding Presidents}}
{{MMFF}}
}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Estrada, Joseph
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =fm=yes
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Tondo, Manila]], [[Commonwealth of the Philippines|Philippines]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Estrada, Joseph}}
[[Category:1937 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Estrada family]]
[[Category:Filipino actors]]
[[Category:Filipino actor–politicians]]
[[Category:Filipino criminals]]
[[Category:Filipino Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Filipino people of Spanish descent]]
[[Category:Impeached officials]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Manila]]
[[Category:People from San Juan, Metro Manila]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Recipients of Philippine presidential pardons]]
[[Category:Liberal Party (Philippines) politicians]]
[[Category:Nacionalista Party politicians]]

[[ar:جوزيف استرادا]]
[[bcl:Joseph Estrada]]
[[ceb:Joseph Estrada]]
[[cbk-zam:Joseph Estrada]]
[[da:Joseph Estrada]]
[[de:Joseph Estrada]]
[[es:Joseph Estrada]]
[[fa:جوزف استرادا]]
[[fr:Joseph Estrada]]
[[gl:Joseph Ejército Estrada]]
[[ko:조지프 에스트라다]]
[[io:Joseph Ejercito Estrada]]
[[ilo:Joseph Estrada]]
[[id:Joseph Estrada]]
[[it:Joseph Estrada]]
[[pam:Joseph Ejercito Estrada]]
[[la:Iosephus Ejército Estrada]]
[[mr:जोसेफ एस्ट्राडा]]
[[ms:Joseph Estrada]]
[[nl:Joseph Estrada]]
[[ja:ジョセフ・エストラーダ]]
[[no:Joseph E. Estrada]]
[[oc:Joseph Ejército Estrada]]
[[pl:Joseph Estrada]]
[[pt:Joseph Estrada]]
[[ru:Эстрада, Джозеф]]
[[fi:Joseph Estrada]]
[[sv:Joseph Estrada]]
[[tl:Joseph Estrada]]
[[vi:Joseph Estrada]]
[[war:Joseph Estrada]]
[[zh:约瑟夫·埃斯特拉达]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
