<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="279605" ns="0" title="Corazon Aquino"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Infobox Officeholder
|name          = Corazon C. Aquino
|image         = Cory Aquino during a ceremony honoring US Air Force.jpg
|caption       =
|alt           = 
|office        = [[List of Presidents of the Philippines|11th]] [[President of the Philippines]] &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[History of the Philippines (1965–1986)|2nd President of the Fourth Republic]] &lt;br&gt;[[History of the Philippines (1986–present)|1st President of the Fifth Republic]]
|primeminister = [[Salvador Laurel]]
|vicepresident = [[Salvador Laurel]]
|term_start    = February 25, 1986
|term_end      = June 30, 1992
|predecessor   = [[Ferdinand Marcos]]
|successor     = [[Fidel V. Ramos]]
|birth_date    = {{birth date|1933|1|25}}
|birth_place   = [[Paniqui, Tarlac]], Philippines
|death_date    = {{death date and age|2009|8|1|1933|1|25}}
|death_place   = [[Makati]], [[Metro Manila]], Philippines
|resting_place = Manila Memorial Park, [[Parañaque]], [[Metro Manila]], Philippines
|party         = [[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal Party]]&lt;br&gt;[[United Nationalist Democratic Organization|UNIDO]]&lt;br&gt;[[Partido Demokratiko Pilipino-Lakas ng Bayan|PDP-Laban]]
|profession    = [[Homemaking|Housewife]]
|spouse        = [[Benigno Aquino, Jr.|Benigno S. Aquino, Jr.]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1954-1983)&lt;/small&gt;
| children     = Ma. Elena Aquino-Cruz&lt;br&gt;Aurora Corazon Aquino-Abellada&lt;br&gt;[[Benigno Aquino III|Benigno S. Aquino III]]&lt;br&gt;Victoria Elisa Aquino-Dee&lt;br&gt;[[Kris Aquino|Kristina Bernadette Aquino-Yap]]
|alma_mater    = [[Far Eastern University]]
|religion      = [[Catholic Church|Roman Catholicism]]
|signature     = Aquino Sig.svg
}}
'''Maria Corazon Sumulong Cojuangco-Aquino''' (January 25, 1933 – August 1, 2009) was the [[List of Presidents of the Philippines|11th]] [[President of the Philippines]] and the first woman to hold that office in Philippine history. She is best remembered for leading the 1986 [[People Power Revolution]], which toppled [[Ferdinand Marcos]] and restored democracy in the Philippines. She is considered an icon of democracy, and was titled by [[Time (magazine)|TIME Magazine]] in 1986 as its 'Woman of the Year'.

A self-proclaimed &quot;plain housewife&quot;,&lt;ref name=fb&gt;{{cite speech|title=Corazon Aquino Speaks to Fulbrighters|author=Aquino, Corazon|date=1996-10-11|location=Washington, D.C.|url=http://www.fulbrightalumni.org/olc/pub/FBA/fulbright_prize/aquino_address.html|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Aquino was married to Senator [[Benigno Aquino, Jr.]], the staunchest critic of then President [[Ferdinand Marcos]]. Senator Aquino was assassinated on August 21, 1983 upon returning to the Philippines after three years in exile in the United States. After her husband's assassination, Aquino emerged as the leader of the opposition against the Marcos administration. In late 1985, when President Marcos called for a snap election, Aquino ran for president with former senator [[Salvador Laurel]] as her vice-presidential running mate. After the elections were held on February 7, 1986, and the [[Batasang Pambansa]] proclaimed Marcos the winner in the elections, Aquino called for massive civil disobedience protests, declaring herself as having been cheated and as the real winner in the elections. Filipinos enthusiastically heeded her call and rallied behind her. These series of events eventually led to the ousting of Marcos and the installation of Aquino as President of the Philippines on February 25, 1986 through the [[People Power Revolution]].

As President, Aquino oversaw the promulgation of a new [[Constitution of the Philippines|constitution]], which limited the powers of the presidency and established a [[Congress of the Philippines|bicameral legislature]]. Her administration gave strong emphasis and concern for civil liberties and human rights, and peace talks with communist insurgents and Muslim secessionists. Aquino's economic policies centered on bringing back economic health and confidence and focused on creating a market-oriented and socially responsible economy. Aquino's administration also faced a series of coup attempts and destructive natural calamities and disasters until the end of her term in 1992.

Succeeded by [[Fidel V. Ramos]] as President in 1992, Aquino returned to private life although she remained active in the public eye, often voicing her views and opinions on the pressing political issues. In 2008, Aquino was diagnosed with colon cancer and, after a one-year battle with the disease, died on August 1, 2009. Her son [[Benigno Aquino III]] was elected president himself and was sworn in on June 30, 2010.

==Personal life==
{{unreferenced section|date=February 2011}}
Cory Aquino was born the 6th child of [[Jose Cojuangco]] (Don Pepe), nephew of the Ysidra Cojuangco (Doña Sidra), and Demetria Sumulong (Doña Metring), a daughter of ex-Cojuangco family lawyer turned senator [[Juan Sumulong]] of [[Antipolo]], [[Rizal]]. The Cojuangcos were big landowners while the Sumulongs were influential politicians in both Lower and Upper Chambers of the Philippine Congress.

She, like her sisters [[Josephine_C._Reyes|Josephine]], Teresita (&quot;Terê&quot;) and Maria Paz, as well as their uncle Eduardo's wife Josephine &quot;Nene&quot; Murphy, studied in [[Saint Scholastica's College]], [[Manila]], an all girl's Catholic school run by German nuns in pre-war Manila. She graduated college in Far Eastern University.

Unlike her siblings, the young Cory was unassuming and simple. She wore hand-me-down uniforms used by her sister Terê. Her favorite subject was Mathematics, and upon graduating from elementary school, she received the highest honours. Her studies were interrupted when the Japanese invaded Manila. After [[World War II in the Philippines|World War II]], she and her siblings as well as her cousins [[Ramon Cojuangco]] and Lourdes (now Mrs. Luis Tirso Rivilla) were sent by her father to the United States.

The young Ms. Cory divided her time between the Cojuangco homes in New York (USA), [[Pasay]], [[Ermita, Manila|Ermita]], Punta in [[Santa Ana, Manila|Santa Ana]] district, the northern city of [[Baguio]], the [[Hacienda Luisita]] and their hometown of [[Paniqui]], [[Tarlac]].

For some summers in the United States, she was treated by her father, Don Pepe, to excursions to [[Washington, DC]] and trans-Atlantic voyages aboard the [[RMS Queen Mary]].

While studying in New England, she would develop a love of the [[French language]]. Besides English, [[Tagalog language|Tagalog]], and [[Kapampangan language|Kapampangan]], she would also remain fluent in French for the rest of her life.

Upon her own choosing, her secluded and easy years ended with her marriage to the grandson of General [[Servillano Aquino]], Sen. [[Benigno Aquino Jr]].

==Married life==
After her graduation from college in the United States, the young Cory returned to the Philippines to study law at the [[Far Eastern University]] (owned by the in-laws of her elder sister Josephine Reyes) for one year. She interrupted her law studies when she married the then rising political star Benigno Aquino, Jr., more popularly known as Ninoy, the son of the late Speaker [[Benigno Aquino, Sr.]]. Their principal wedding sponsor was President [[Ramon Magsaysay]] who on the same year was curiously the principal wedding sponsor of then Congressman Ferdinand Marcos and his wife, Imelda who was niece of current Pro Tempore Speaker [[Daniel Romualdez]] y Zialcita.

The couple produced five children, four girls and one boy, namely: Maria Elena &quot;Ballsy&quot; Aquino Cruz (born August 18, 1955), Aurora Corazon &quot;Pinky&quot; Aquino Abellada (born December 27, 1957), [[President of the Philippines|Philippine President]] [[Benigno Aquino III|Benigno Simeon &quot;Noynoy&quot; Aquino, III]] (born February 8, 1960), Victoria Elisa &quot;Viel&quot; Aquino Dee (born October 27, 1961) and [[Kris Aquino|Kristina Bernadette &quot;Kris&quot; Aquino Yap]] (born February 14, 1971).

Aquino had initial difficulty adjusting to provincial life when she and Ninoy moved to [[Concepcion, Tarlac]] in 1955, after the latter was elected the town's mayor at the age of 22. The American-educated Aquino found herself bored in Concepcion, and welcomed the opportunity to have dinner with her husband inside the [[Clark Air Base|American military facility at nearby Clark Field]].&lt;ref name=lt&gt;{{cite book|author=Lorna Kalaw-Tirol|title=Public Faces, Private Lives|year=2000|publisher=Anvil Publishing, Inc|location=Pasig City, Philippines|pages=2–23|isbn=971-27-0851-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A member of the [[Liberal Party (Philippines)|Liberal Party]], Aquino's husband Ninoy rose to become the youngest governor in the country and eventually became the youngest senator ever elected in the [[Senate of the Philippines]] in 1967. During her husband's political career, Aquino remained a housewife who helped raise their children and played hostess to her spouse's political allies who would frequent their Quezon City home.&lt;ref name=pi&gt;{{Cite news|author=Pico Iyer|title=Corazon Aquino|url=http://www.time.com/time/subscriber/personoftheyear/archive/stories/1986.html|work=Time Magazine|date=1987-01-05|accessdate=2008-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; She would decline to join her husband on stage during campaign rallies, preferring instead to stand at the back of the audience and listen to him.&lt;ref name=lt/&gt; Nonetheless, she was consulted upon on political matters by her husband, who valued her judgments enormously.&lt;ref name=pi/&gt;

Unknown to many, Cory voluntarily sold some of her prized inheritance to fund the candidacy of her husband, such as a hectare-sized lot in [[Wack Wack]] Golf and Country Club, choice commercial properties in [[Ermita, Manila|Ermita]] and [[Pasay]], and other possessions. In accordance with her and her husband's wishes, and despite much wealth, Cory led a modest existence in a bungalow in suburban Quezon City which paled in comparison with the rest of the Cojuangcos living in the high-end Forbes Park and Dasmarinas Village in Makati City.

An eloquent speaker and brilliant politician, Ninoy Aquino soon emerged as a leading critic of the government of [[President of the Philippines|President]] Ferdinand Marcos. He was then touted as a strong candidate for president to succeed Marcos in the 1973 elections. However, Marcos, being barred by the Constitution to seek a third term, declared [[martial law]] on September 21, 1972, and later abolished the existing [[Constitution of the Philippines#Commonwealth and Third Republic (1935)|1935 Constitution]], thereby allowing him to remain in office. As a consequence, Aquino's husband was among those to be first arrested at the onset of martial law, later being sentenced to death. During his incarceration, Ninoy sought strength from prayer, attending daily [[mass (liturgy)|mass]] and saying three [[rosary|rosaries]] a day and drew inspiration from his wife, Cory.&lt;ref name=lt/&gt; As a measure of sacrifice and solidarity with her husband and all other political prisoners, she enjoined her children from attending parties and she also stopped going to the [[beauty salon]] or buying new clothes until a priest advised her and her children to instead live as normal lives as possible.&lt;ref name=lt/&gt;

In 1978, despite her initial opposition, Ninoy decided to run in the [[Philippine parliamentary election, 1978|1978 Batasang Pambansa elections]]. A reluctant speaker, Cory campaigned in behalf of her husband and for the first time in her life, delivered a political speech,&lt;ref name=fb /&gt;&lt;ref name=lt/&gt; though later on she refrained from giving campaign speeches when it became clearer that her six-year-old daughter Kris was more willing than she to speak on stage to the public.&lt;ref name=lt/&gt;

In 1980, upon the intervention of US President [[Jimmy Carter]],&lt;ref name=fb/&gt; Marcos allowed Senator Aquino and his family to leave for exile in the United States, where he sought medical treatment.&lt;ref name=campaign&gt;{{cite news|title=Aquino's 'Flesh-to-Flesh Campaign'|author=Branigin, William|work=The Washington Post|date=1986-02-02|accessdate=2009-07-28|page=A1}}&lt;/ref&gt; The family settled in [[Boston]], and Aquino would later call the next three years as the happiest days of her marriage and family life.&lt;ref name=fb/&gt; On August 21, 1983, however, Ninoy ended his stay in the United States and returned without his family to the Philippines, only to be assassinated on a staircase leading to the tarmac of the [[Manila International Airport]], which was later renamed in his honor. Corazon Aquino returned to the Philippines a few days later and led her husband's funeral procession, in which more than two million people joined the procession, the biggest ever in Philippine history.&lt;ref name=fb/&gt;

==1986 Presidential campaign==
{{Main|Philippine presidential election, 1986}}

Following her husband's assassination in 1983, Aquino became active and visible in various demonstrations and protests held against the Marcos regime. She began to assume the mantle of leadership left by her husband Ninoy and started to become the symbolic figurehead of the anti-Marcos political opposition. In the last week of November 1985, Marcos surprised the nation by announcing on American television that he will hold a snap presidential election in February 1986, in order to dispel and remove doubts against his regime's legitimacy and authority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Milt Freudenheim, Henry Giniger &amp; Richard Levine|title=Marcos Moves Toward A Vote|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1985/11/17/weekinreview/the-world-marcos-moves-toward-a-vote.html?sec=health|work=New York Times|date=1985-11-17|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Reluctant at first, Aquino was eventually prevailed upon to heed the people's clamor, after one million signatures urging her to run for president were presented to her. Despite this, the erstwhile favorite opposite candidate, Laurel, did not immediately give way to his close friend's widow. Laurel was only convinced to run as Cory's Vice President upon the urging of the influential Manila Cardinal Archbishop [[Jaime Sin]]. As a compromise, Aquino agreed to run under Laurel's machinery, the [[United Nationalist Democratic Organization]] (UNIDO), then the country's largest opposition party. With that, the Aquino-Laurel tandem was formally launched to challenge Marcos and finally put an end to his twenty-year martial rule.

In the subsequent political developments and events, Marcos charged that Aquino was being supported by communists and agreed to share power with them once elected into power. A political novice, Aquino categorically denied Marcos' charge and even stated that she would not appoint a single communist to her cabinet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Milt Freudenheim &amp; Richard Levine|title=A Marcos Charge Irks Mrs. Aquino|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1986/01/12/weekinreview/the-world-a-marcos-charge-irks-mrs-aquino.html?sec=health|work=New York Times|date=1986-01-12|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Running on the offensive, the ailing Marcos also accused Aquino of playing &quot;political football&quot; with the United States with respect to the continued United States military presence in the Philippines at [[Clark Air Base]] and [[Subic Naval Base]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=United Press International|title= Marcos Says Rival Trifles With U.S. Bases|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1985/12/31/world/around-the-world-marcos-says-rival-trifles-with-us-bases.html|work=New York Times|date=1985-12-31|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Further, the male strongman derided Aquino's womanhood, by saying that she was &quot;just a woman&quot; whose place was in the bedroom.&lt;ref name=fb/&gt; In response to her opponent's sexist remark, Cory simply remarked that &quot;may the better woman win in this election.&quot; Marcos also attacked Aquino's inexperience and warned the country that it would be a disaster if a woman like her with no previous political experience would be elected president; to which Aquino cleverly and sarcastically responded, admitting that she had &quot;no experience in cheating, lying to the public, stealing government money, and killing political opponents.&quot;

The snap election called by Marcos which was held on February 7, 1986 was marred by massive electoral fraud, violence, intimidation, coercion and disenfranchisement of voters. Election Day proved to be bloody as one of Aquino's staunchest allies Antique Governor [[Evelio Javier]] was brutally murdered, allegedly by one of Marcos' supporters in his province. Further, during the counting and tallying of votes conducted by the [[Commission on Elections]] (COMELEC), 30 poll computer technicians walked out to dispute and contest the alleged election-rigging done in favor of Marcos. Despite this, the Batasang Pamabansa, which was dominated by allies of the ruling party, declared President Marcos as the winner in the recently concluded snap presidential election on February 15, 1986. In protest to the declaration of the Philippine parliament, Aquino called for a rally dubbed &quot;Tagumpay ng Bayan&quot; (People's Victory Rally) the following day, during which she claimed that she was the real winner in the snap election and urged Filipinos to boycott the products and services by companies controlled or owned by Marcos' cronies. The rally held at the historic Rizal Park in Luneta, Manila drew a mammoth-sized crowd, which sent a strong signal that Filipinos were already growing tired of Marcos' two decade-rule. Further, the dubious election results drew sharp reactions from both local quarters and foreign countries. The Catholic Bishops' Conference of the Philippines (CBCP) issued a statement strongly criticizing the conduct of the election which was characterized by violence and fraud. The [[United States Senate]] condemned the election.&lt;ref name=pi/&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite news|title=Filipino coup leaders tell Marcos to go|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/22/newsid_2519000/2519155.stm|publisher=BBC|date=1986-02-22|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Aquino rejected a power-sharing agreement proposed by the American diplomat [[Philip Habib]], who had been sent as an emissary by U.S. President [[Ronald Reagan]] to help defuse the tension.&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt;

===Installation as President===
{{Main|People Power Revolution}}

After weeks of tension following the disputed outcome of the snap election, disgruntled and reformist military officers, led by then Defense Minister [[Juan Ponce Enrile]] and General [[Fidel V. Ramos]], surprised the entire nation and the whole world when they announced their defection from President Marcos and their strong belief that Aquino was the real winner in the presidential election on February 22, 1986. Upon the urging and encouragement of the activist Cardinal Archbishop of Manila Jaime Sin, millions of Filipinos trooped to Camp Aguinaldo along [[Epifanio De los Santos Avenue]] (EDSA), where Enrile and Ramos have been holding operations, to give their moral support and prayers for the reformist soldiers. At that time, Aquino was meditating in a Carmelite convent in [[Cebu]]. Upon learning of the defection, Aquino called on Filipinos to rally behind Minister Enrile and General Ramos. Later on, Aquino flew back to Manila in order to prepare to assume the presidency upon the ouster of Marcos. Finally, to the amazement and admiration of the entire world, after twenty years of martial rule, Ferdinand Marcos was driven out from power and Corazon Aquino was formally and peacefully sworn in as the new president of a freed and liberated Philippines on February 25, 1986, a historic event which is now known and remembered as the 1986 EDSA People Power Revolution.

==Presidency==
{{refimprove section|date=February 2011}}
{{Main|Presidency of Corazon Aquino}}
[[File:Corazon Aquino 1986.jpg|thumb|left|President Aquino in 1986]]
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Cory Aquino - Woman of the Year.jpg|thumb|right|President Aquino was named by [[Time (magazine)|''Time'']] magazine as the 1986 [[Time Person of the Year|Woman of the Year]]]] --&gt;

The triumph of the peaceful People Power Revolution and the ascension of Corazon Aquino into power signaled the end of authoritarian rule in the Philippines and the dawning of a new era for Filipinos. The relatively peaceful manner by which Aquino came into power drew international acclaim and admiration not only for her but for the Filipino people, as well.

During the first months of Aquino's presidency, the country experienced radical changes and sweeping democratic reforms. One of Aquino's first and boldest moves was the creation of the [[Presidential Commission on Good Government]] (PCGG), which was tasked to go after the Marcos ill-gotten wealth. Aquino, being a revolutionary president by virtue of people power, abolished the 1973 &quot;Marcos Constitution&quot; and dissolved the Marcos allies-dominated Batasang Pambansa, despite the advice of her vice-president and only prime minister Salvador Laurel. She also immediately created a Constitutional Commission, which she directed for the drafting of a new constitution for the nation.

On the whole, the Aquino administration made important gains in the aspects of bringing back democracy, restoring investor confidence in the economy and enacting legal and constitutional reforms. Despite these achievements, her presidency faced several threats from both right-wing military elements and extreme left-wing communist rebels. Further, her administration dealt with numerous problems such as major natural disasters which struck the country and severe power shortages which took a toll on doing business in the Philippines. It was also during her tenure that the United States finally ended its military bases and presence in the country.

===Constitutional and political reforms===
Immediately after assuming the presidency, President Aquino issued Proclamation No. 3, which established a revolutionary government. She abolished the 1973 Constitution that was in force during martial law, and instead promulgated the provisional 1986 Freedom Constitution, pending the ratification of a new Constitution by the people. This allowed Aquino to exercise both executive and legislative powers until the ratification of the new Philippine Constitution and the establishment of a new Congress in 1987.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=[[Joaquin G. Bernas]]|title=The Intent of the 1986 Constitution Writers|publisher=Rex Book Store|location=Manila, Philippines|year=1995|isbn=9712319344|pages=2–4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, Aquino promulgated two landmark [[Philippine legal codes|legal codes]], namely, the [[Civil Code of the Philippines#The Family Code of 1987|Family Code of 1987]], which reformed the [[civil law (legal system)|civil law]] on family relations, and the [[Philippine legal codes#Administrative Code|Administrative Code of 1987]], which reorganized the structure of the [[Executive Departments of the Philippines|executive branch of government]]. Another landmark law that was enacted during her tenure was the 1991 [[Philippine legal codes#Local Government Code|Local Government Code]], which devolved national government powers to local government units (LGUs). The new Code also enhanced the power of LGUs to enact local taxation measures and assured them of a share in the national revenue.

Likewise, Aquino closed down the Marcos-dominated [[Batasang Pambansa]] to prevent the new Marcos loyalist opposition from undermining her democratic reforms and reorganized the membership of the Supreme Court to restore its independence. In May 1986, the reorganized Supreme Court declared the Aquino government as “not merely a de facto government but in fact and law a de jure government”, whose legitimacy had been affirmed by the community of nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Lawyers League v. President Aquino, G.R. No. 73748|court=[[Supreme Court of the Philippines]]|date=1986-05-22|url=http://elibrary.supremecourt.gov.ph/resolutions.php?doctype=Minute%20Resolutions&amp;docid=a45475a11ec72b843d74959b60fd7bd645abb094dee22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This Supreme Court decision significantly affirmed the status of Aquino as the new, legitimate and rightful leader of the Philippines.

To fast-track the restoration of a full constitutional government and the writing of a new charter, President Aquino appointed 48 members of the 1986 Constitutional Commission (Con-Com), led by retired activist Supreme Court Associate Justice [[Cecilia Muñoz-Palma]]. The Con-Com completed its final draft in October 1986.&lt;ref&gt;Bernas, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; On February 2, 1987, the new [[Constitution of the Philippines]], which put strong emphasis on civil liberties, human rights and social justice, was overwhelmingly approved by the Filipino people. The ratification of the new Constitution was followed by the election of senators and congress that same year and the holding of local elections in 1988.

===Socio-economic programs and policies===
====Economic management====

She moved quickly to tackle the issue of the US$26 billion foreign debt incurred by her predecessor. Aquino chose to honor all the debts that were previously incurred. 

Her decision proved to be unpopular but Aquino defended that it was the most practical move. It was crucial for the country at that time to regain the investors' confidence in the Philippine economy. Since 1986, the Aquino administration has paid off $4 billion of the country's outstanding debts to regain good international credit ratings and attract the attention of future markets.  Nevertheless, the administration borrowed an additional $9 billion, increasing the national debt by $5 billion within six years time since the ouster of former President Ferdinand Marcos in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Manila Plan To Cut Debt|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1992/02/21/business/manila-plan-to-cut-debt.html?pagewanted=1|accessdate=2010-02-27|work=The New York Times|date=1992-02-21|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further, the Aquino administration also sought to bring back fiscal discipline in order as it aimed to trim down the government's budget deficit that ballooned during Marcos' term through privatization of bad government assets and deregulation of many vital industries. It was also during Aquino's time that vital economic laws such as the Built-Operate-Transfer Law, Foreign Investments Act and the Consumer Protection and Welfare Act were enacted.

The economy posted a positive growth of 3.4% during her first year in office. But in the aftermath of the [[1989 Philippine coup attempt|1989 coup attempt]] by the rightist [[Reform the Armed Forces Movement]], the Philippine economy remained stagnant. In her final year in office, inflation was raging at 17%, and unemployment was slightly over 10%, higher than the Marcos years.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Her Term About to End, Aquino 'Hasn't Made Much Difference' to the Poor|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1992/06/08/world/her-term-about-to-end-aquino-hasn-t-made-much-difference-to-the-poor.html?pagewanted=all|accessdate=2010-02-27|work=The New York Times|first=DE|last=Sanger|date=1992-06-08|publisher=[[The New York Times]]|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, the economy under Aquino had an average growth of 3.8% from 1986 to 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationsencyclopedia.com/economies/Asia-and-the-Pacific/Philippines-OVERVIEW-OF-ECONOMY.html#ixzz0clOAibWu|title=Philippines Overview of economy, Information about Overview of economy in Philippines|publisher=Nationsencyclopedia.com|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Soon after taking office, Cory declared that the presence of [[US Military Forces]] in the Philippines was an affront to national sovereignty. She ordered the [[United States]] military to vacate [[U.S. Naval Base Subic Bay]] and [[Clark Air Base]]. The US objected, pointing that they had leased the property and the leases were still in effect. Also, thousands of Filipinos worked at these military facilities and they would lose their jobs and the Filipino economy would suffer if the US Military moved out. The US stated that the facilities at [[Subic Bay]] were unequaled anywhere in [[Southeast Asia]] and a US pullout could make all of that region of the world vulnerable to an incursion by the [[Soviet Union]] or by a resurgent [[Japan]].

Nevertheless, Cory refused to back down and insisted that the USA get out. The matter was still being debated when [[Mount Pinatubo]] erupted in June 1991, covering the entire area with [[volcanic ash]]. The Filipinos were suddenly willing to consider allowing the US military to stay but the destruction to the bases was so severe that the US decided that it would best to pull out after all and the bases were closed and the [[USA]] left.

====Agrarian reform====
Upon her ascension into power, President Aquino envisioned agrarian and land reform as the centerpiece of her administration's social legislative agenda. However, her family background and social class as a privileged daughter of a wealthy and landed clan became a lightning rod of criticisms against her land reform agenda.

On February 22, 1987, three weeks after the resounding ratification of the 1987 Constitution, agrarian workers and farmers marched to the historic Mendiola Street near [[Malacanang Palace]] to demand genuine land reform from Aquino's administration. However, the supposedly peaceful farmers' march turned bloody and violent when Marine forces fired at farmers who tried to go beyond the designated demarcation line set by the police. As a result, 12 farmers were killed and 19 were injured in this incident now known as the [[Mendiola Massacre]]. This tragic incident led some prominent members of the Aquino Cabinet like the nationalist and progressive senator [[Jose W. Diokno]] to quit from their government posts. Though Aquino did not have any personal and official involvement with the drastic actions taken by some police elements, her administration has been faulted since then for failing to solve land disputes in the country.

In response to calls for agrarian reform, President Aquino issued Presidential Proclamation 131 and Executive Order 229 on July 22, 1987, which outlined her land reform program, which included sugar lands. In 1988, with the backing of Aquino, the new [[Congress of the Philippines]] passed [[List of Philippine laws|Republic Act]] No. 6657, more popularly known as the Comprehensive Agrarian Reform Law.&quot; The law paved the way for the redistribution of agricultural lands to tenant-farmers from landowners, who were paid in exchange by the government through [[just compensation]] but were also allowed to retain not more than five hectares of land.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tanggol.org/environmental_laws/RA6657.html|title=Section 6, Comprehensive Agrarian Reform Law|publisher=Web.archive.org|accessdate=2010-03-13|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070823212620/http://www.tanggol.org/environmental_laws/RA6657.html|archivedate=2007-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, corporate landowners were also allowed under the law to “voluntarily divest a proportion of their [[stock|capital stock]], equity or participation in favor of their workers or other qualified beneficiaries”, in lieu of turning over their land to the government for redistribution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tanggol.org/environmental_laws/RA6657.html|title=Section 31, Comprehensive Agrarian Reform Law|publisher=Web.archive.org|accessdate=2010-03-13|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070823212620/http://www.tanggol.org/environmental_laws/RA6657.html|archivedate=2007-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the flaws in the law, the Supreme Court upheld its constitutionality in 1989, declaring that the implementation of the comprehensive agrarian reform program (CARP), provided by the said law) was “a revolutionary kind of expropriation.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite court|litigants=Association of Small Landowners v. Luz|vol=175|reporter=SCRA|opinion=343|pinpoint=386|court=[[Supreme Court of the Philippines]]|date=1989-07-14|url=http://www.lawphil.net/judjuris/juri1989/jul1989/gr_78742_1989.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the implementation of CARP, Aquino was not spared from the controversies that eventually centered on [[Hacienda Luisita]], a 6,453-hectare estate located in the Province of [[Tarlac]], which she, together with her siblings inherited from her father [[Jose Cojuangco]] (Don Pepe).&lt;ref name=pdihl&gt;{{cite news|author=Russell Arador|title=Life once 'sweeter' at Hacienda Luisita|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view_article.php?article_id=64019|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2007-05-04|accessdate=2008-03-25 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Critics argued that Aquino bowed to pressure from relatives by allowing stock redistribution under Executive Order 229. Instead of land distribution, Hacienda Luisita reorganized itself into a corporation and distributed stock. As such, ownership of agricultural portions of the hacienda were transferred to the corporation, which in turn, gave its shares of stocks to farmers.&lt;ref name=pdihl/&gt;

The arrangement remained in force until 2006, when the [[Department of Agrarian Reform (Philippines)|Department of Agrarian Reform]] revoked the stock distribution scheme adopted in Hacienda Luisita, and ordered instead the redistribution of a large portion of the property to the tenant-farmers.

The Department stepped into the controversy when in 2004, violence erupted over the retrenchment of workers in the Hacienda, eventually leaving seven people dead.&lt;ref name=pdihl/&gt;

===Natural disasters and calamities===
During her last two years in office, President Aquino's administration faced series of natural disasters and calamities. Among these were the [[1990 Luzon earthquake]], which left around 1,600 people dead and the 1991 volcanic eruption of what was then thought to be a dormant [[Mount Pinatubo]], which was the second largest terrestrial eruption of the 20th century,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=The Cataclysmic 1991 Eruption of Mount Pinatubo, Philippines|url=http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/1997/fs113-97/|accessdate=2008-03-22|publisher=[[United States Geological Survey]]|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; killing around 300 people and causing widespread long-term devastation of agricultural lands in [[Central Luzon]]. The worst loss of life occurred when [[Tropical Storm Thelma]] (also known as Typhoon Uring) caused massive flooding in [[Ormoc City]] in November 1991, leaving around 6,000 dead in what was considered to be the deadliest typhoon in Philippine history. It was also during Aquino's term that the [[MV Doña Paz|MV ''Doña Paz'']] sank, which is the World's worst peace-time maritime disaster of the 20th century. The disaster occurred in December 1987 which killed more than 1,700 people.

During Aquino's presidency, electric blackouts became common in Manila. The capital experienced blackouts of seven to 12 hours, bringing numerous businesses to a halt. By the departure of Aquino in June 1992, businesses in Manila and nearby provinces have lost nearly $800 million since March 1992.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Aquino exits after 6 tumultuous years|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=W28VAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=jOoDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7000,6590941&amp;dq=cory+philippines&amp;hl=en|accessdate=2010-02-27|publisher=[[Google News]]|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Aquino administration knew for years that country's power plants were failing, but they did not act to solve the problem.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite document|title=Cory's Deeds Marred By Her Indecisiveness|url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1309&amp;dat=19920610&amp;id=I7oTAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=dJADAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5844,4016555|accessdate=2010-02-27|publisher=[[Google News]]|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was only during the time of her successor, [[Fidel Ramos]], that the government decisively solved the severe power outages that were common during her tenure.

===Influence in 1992 presidential campaign===
[[Image:Corazon Aquino 1992.jpg|thumb|left|President Corazón Aquino addresses base workers at a rally at Remy Field concerning jobs for Filipino workers after the Americans withdraw from the U.S. facilities]]

As the end of her presidency drew near, close advisers and friends told Aquino that since she was not inaugurated under the 1987 Constitution, she was still eligible to seek the presidency again in the upcoming 1992 elections, the first presidential elections under normal and peaceful circumstances since 1965. President Aquino strongly declined the requests for her to seek reelection and wanted to set an example to both citizens and politicians that the presidency is not a lifetime position.

Initially, she named [[Ramon V. Mitra]], a friend of her husband Ninoy and then Speaker of the [[Philippine House of Representatives]], as her candidate for the presidential race in 1992. However, she later on backtracked and instead threw her support behind the candidacy of her defense secretary and EDSA Revolution hero, General Fidel V. Ramos, who constantly stood by and defended her government from the various coup attempts and rebellions that were launched against her. Her sudden change of mind and withdrawal of support from Mitra drew criticisms not only from her supporters in the liberal and [[social democratic]] sectors but also from the Roman Catholic Church, as well, which questioned her anointing of Ramos since the latter was a [[Protestant]]. Nevertheless, Aquino's candidate eventually won the 1992 elections, albeit with 23.58 percent of the total votes only, and was sworn in as the 12th President of the Philippines on June 30, 1992.

==Post-presidency and continued political activism==
[[Image:Aquino 2003.jpg|thumb|right|Mrs. Aquino speaking before the 2003 Ninoy Aquino Award ceremony at the U.S. Embassy in Manila.]]

===Activities and drives===
====Political causes====
On June 30, 1992, President Aquino formally and peacefully handed over power to her anointed candidate and democratically elected General Fidel Ramos, after six years of hard-fought democratic transition and restoration. On her way to the inauguration of President-elect Ramos, Aquino chose to ride on a simple white [[Toyota Crown]] she had purchased, rather than the lavish government-issued [[Mercedes Benz]], to make the point that she was now again an ordinary citizen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Sandra Burton|title=Time 100: Corazon Aquino|url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/asia/magazine/1999/990823/aquino1.html|work=Time Magazine|date=August 23–30, 1999|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Though Aquino retired to private life, following the end of her term, she remained active in the Philippine political scene, constantly voicing opposition and dissent to government actions and policies, which she deemed as threats to the liberal traditions and democratic foundations of the country.

In 1997, Aquino, together with the influential Cardinal Jaime Sin, led a huge rally which succeeded in thwarting then President Fidel Ramos' attempt to extend his term by amending the 1987 Constitution's restriction on presidential term limits. In 1998, Aquino endorsed the candidacy of former police general and Manila Mayor [[Alfredo Lim]] for president. Lim, however, lost to then Vice-President [[Joseph Estrada]], who won by a landslide.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Lozada misses Cory Aquino in Navotas Mass|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/86302/Lozada-misses-Cory-Aquino-in-Navotas-Mass|publisher=GMA News.TV|date=2008-03-26|accessdate=2008-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, Aquino again with Cardinal Sin successfully opposed President Estrada's plan of amending the Constitution, which he said was intended to lift provisions that 'restrict' economic activities and investments; he denied that it was another ploy for him to extend his stay in office. 

In 2000, Aquino joined the mounting calls for Estrada to resign from office, amid strong allegations of bribery chargers and gambling kickbacks and series of corruption scandals, which eventually led to his unsuccessful impeachment in December of that year.
In her Preface to [[Frank-Jürgen Richter]] and Pamela Mar’s book ''Asia’s New Crisis'' &lt;ref&gt;[[Frank-Jürgen Richter]], Pamela Mar: ''Asia’s New Crisis'', John Wiley &amp; Sons  Singapore, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; (see [http://www.amazon.co.uk/Asias-New-Crisis-Renewal-Management/dp/0470821299 Amazon]), she decries that the unique Asian way of doing business has given rise to much crony capitalism and opacity in Asia, including the Philippines. In January 2001, during the [[EDSA Revolution of 2001]] which ousted Estrada, Aquino enthusiastically supported the ascendancy of another woman, then Vice-President [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]], into power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Mark Landler|title=In Philippines, The Economy As Casualty; The ped, a Credibility Repair Job|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/09/business/philippines-economy-casualty-president-ousted-credibility-repair-job.html|work=New York Times|date=2001-02-09|accessdate=2008-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, after series of revelations and exposes alleged and implicated President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo in [[2005 Philippine electoral crisis|rigging]] the [[Philippine general election, 2004|2004 presidential elections]], Aquino called on her erstwhile ally to make the 'supreme sacrifice' of resigning in order to prevent bloodshed, violence and further political deterioration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Carlos H. Conde|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/09/international/asia/09filip.html|title=Allies of Philippine President Call on Her to Step Down|work=New York Times|date=2005-07-09|accessdate=2008-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, Aquino was once again in the streets leading massive demonstrations demanding the resignation of President Arroyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Carlos H. Conde|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4D9143BF932A35750C0A96E9C8B63|title=Ex-Presidents Join Anti-Arroyo Rally|work=New York Times|date=2008-03-01|accessdate=2008-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Philippine general election, 2007|2007 senatorial elections]], Aquino actively campaigned for the senatorial bid of her only son, [[Noynoy Aquino]], who ran and won under the triumphant opposition banner.

In December 2008, Aquino publicly expressed some regrets for her participation in the EDSA Revolution of 2001, which installed Arroyo into power. She apologized to former President Joseph Estrada for the role she played in his ouster in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Aquino says sorry to Estrada; concedes EDSA II was a mistake|author=Leah Salaverria|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/nation/view/20081223-179471/Aquino-says-sorry-to-Estrada|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2008-12-23|accessdate=2008-12-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt; For this action, many politicians criticized Aquino.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cory apologizes for EDSA 2, gets flak|url=http://angperyodiko.net/home/?p=9|accessdate=2010-02-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2009, two months before her death, Aquino issued a public statement which strongly denounced and condemned the Arroyo administration's plan of amending the 1987 Constitution, calling such attempt as a &quot;shameless abuse of power.&quot;

====International engagements====
Shortly after leaving the presidency, Aquino traveled abroad, giving speeches and lectures on issues of democracy, development, human rights and women empowerment. In 1997, Aquino attended the wake and funeral of Blessed [[Mother Teresa of Calcutta]], whom she met during the latter's visit in Manila in 1989. In early 2000s, Aquino joined various global leaders and democratic icons in urging the Government of [[Burma]] to unconditionally release Burmese democratic leader [[Aung San Suu Kyi]] from detention, whom she delivered a speech on behalf in the 1994 meeting of the [[UNESCO]] World Commission on Culture and Development in Manila. In 2005, Aquino joined the international community in mourning the death of [[Pope John Paul II]].

====Charitable and social initiatives====
Aside from being visible in various political gatherings and demonstrations, Aquino was heavily involved in several charitable activities and socio-economic initiatives. From 1992 until her death, Aquino was chairperson of the Benigno S. Aquino, Jr. Foundation which she set up in her husband's honor right after his brutal assassination in 1983. Further, she supported other causes such as the [[Gawad Kalinga]] social housing project for the poor and homeless. In 2007, Aquino helped establish the PinoyME Foundation, a non-profit organization which aims to provide microfinancing programs and projects for the poor.&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|author=Jennifer A. Ng|title=Cory Aquino-led foundation to hike lending to microenterprises to P5B|url=http://www.businessmirror.com.ph/06212007/economy02.html|work=Business Mirror|date=2007-06-21|accessdate=2008-04-15 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aquino was also a lifelong member of the [[Council of Women World Leaders]], an international organization of former and current female heads of state and government which seeks to mobilize high-profile women world leaders to make collective action on issues critical to the leadership, empowerment and development of women.

==Bout with cancer and death==
{{Main|Death and funeral of Corazon Aquino}}
{{wikinews|Former Philippine President Corazon Aquino dies at age 76}}

On March 24, 2008, the Aquino family announced that she had been diagnosed with [[colorectal cancer]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cory Aquino has colon cancer--family|url=http://www.abs-cbnnews.com/topofthehour.aspx?StoryId=112871|publisher=ABS-CBN News Online|date=2008-03-24 accessdate=2008-03-24 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon her being earlier informed by her doctors that she had only three months to live,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Maila Ager|title=Aquino blood pressure fluctuating – family|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090728-217645/Aquino-blood-pressure-fluctuating--family|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2009-07-28|accessdate=2009-07-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Aquino pursued medical treatment and [[chemotherapy]]. As a result, a series of healing masses for the devout Catholic former president were held throughout the country. In a public statement made on May 13, 2008 during a healing mass for her, Aquino said that her blood tests indicated that she was responding well to the medical treatment being administered to her; however, Aquino's hair and appetite loss became very apparent and rapid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Abigail Kwok|title=Aquino: ‘My body is responding positively to the treatment’|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20080513-136351/Aquino-My-body-is-responding-positively-to-the-treatment|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2008-05-13|accessdate=2008-05-13 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

By July 2009, Aquino was reported to be in very serious condition, suffering from loss of appetite, and was confined to the [[Makati Medical Center]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Fe Zamora|title=Prayers sought for ailing Cory Aquino; Friend says ex-leader in ‘serious’ condition|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090701-213331/Prayers-sought-for-ailing-Cory-Aquino|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2009-07-01|accessdate=2009-07-01 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Later on, it was announced that Aquino and her family had decided to cease chemotherapy and other medical interventions for her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=No more chemotherapy for Cory, says close family friend|publisher=GMA News.TV|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/166389/No-more-chemotherapy-for-Cory-says-close-family-friend|date=2009-07-02|accessdate=2009-07-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Agence France Presse]]|title=No more treatment for Aquino—spokeswoman|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090702-213497/No-more-treatment-for-Aquinospokeswoman|work=Philippine Daily Inquirer|date=2009-07-02|accessdate=2009-07-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 1, 2009, the 76-year-old Aquino died peacefully at the Makati Medical Center at 3:18 a.m., of [[cardiorespiratory arrest]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bworldonline.com/BW080109/breakingnews.php ]{{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AgerInquirer&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090801-218235/Cory-Aquino-dies|title=Cory Aquino dies|last=Ager|first=Maila|date=2009-08-01|publisher=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-07-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wake, requiem mass and burial===
Upon learning of Aquino's death, incumbent President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo, who was then on a state visit to the United States, announced a 10-day mourning period for the former President and issued Administrative Order No. 269 detailing the necessary arrangements for a state funeral.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Palace declares week of mourning on the passing of Cory|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/168753/Palace-declares-week-of-mourning-on-passing-of-Cory|work=GMANews.tv|accessdate=2009-08-01|date=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Aquino children, however, declined the government offer to hold a [[state funeral]] for their mother.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Noel Orsal &amp; Paul Mata|url=http://www.pep.ph/news/22688/Kris-Aquino-explains-why-family-chose-not-to-have-state-funeral-for-former-President-Corazon-Aquino|title=Kris Aquino explains why family chose not to have state funeral for former President Corazon Aquino|publisher=Pep.ph|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All churches in the Philippines celebrated requiem masses simultaneously throughout the country and all government offices flew the Philippine flag at half mast. Hours after her death on August 1, Aquino's body lay in state for public viewing at the [[La Salle Green Hills]] campus in [[Mandaluyong City]]. On August 3, 2009, Aquino's remains were transferred from La Salle Greenhills to the [[Manila Cathedral]] in Intramuros, during which hundreds of thousands of Filipinos lined the streets to witness and escort their former leader's funeral cortege. On its way to Manila Cathedral, Aquino's funeral cortege passed by [[Ayala Avenue]], Makati City and stopped in front of her husband Ninoy Aquino's statue, amidst throngs of thousands of Filipinos who gathered there and emotionally sang the 1986 EDSA Revolution anthem &quot;''[[Bayan Ko]].''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abs-cbnnews.com/nation/08/03/09/120000-show-cory|title=120,000 Show up for Cory|publisher=Abs-cbnnews.com|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Aquino's remains were solemnly brought inside Manila Cathedral around mid-afternoon that day. Following her death, all Roman Catholic dioceses throughout the country held requiem masses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Churches start requiem Masses for Cory Aquino|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/168757/Churches-start-requiem-Masses-for-Cory-Aquino|work=GMANews.tv|accessdate=2009-08-01|date=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Line at the Corazon Aquino wake at the Manila Cathedral.jpg|thumb|220px|Queue of mourners at the Aquino wake going to Manila Cathedral in front of the ''[[Pamantasan ng Lungsod ng Maynila]]'' campus, which opened its facilities such as the university clinic and restrooms for the mourners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=PLM opens facilities for Cory supporters|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/168980/PLM-opens-facilities-for-Cory-supporters|work=GMANews.tv|accessdate=2009-08-04|date=2009-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; For comparison, the Cathedral is the green dome in the background.]]

On August 4, in a conciliatory gesture {fact}, [[Ferdinand Marcos, Jr.]] and [[Imee Marcos]], children of the late strongman Ferdinand Marcos, paid their last respects to the woman who brought down their father in 1986. The Marcos siblings were received by Aquino's children, Maria Elena, Aurora Corazon and Victoria Eliza.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Marcos children pay last respects to Aquino|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090804-218722/Marcos-children-pay-last-respects-to-Aquino|work=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-08-04|date=2009-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following day, during mid-dawn, President Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo, who cut short her trip in the United States, briefly paid her last respects to President Aquino, who was once her closest ally.

On August 5, a final requiem mass, presided by high-ranking Filipino Catholic Church officials such as Manila Cardinal Archbishop [[Gaudencio Rosales]] and Bishop [[Socrates B. Villegas]], was offered for the eternal repose of Aquino's soul. After the Mass, Aquino's youngest daughter, [[Kris Aquino|Kris]], delivered a speech. Thereafter, Aquino's Philippine flag-draped coffin was escorted from the Manila Cathedral to the Manila Memorial Park in [[Paranaque City]], where she was interred beside her husband Ninoy's resting place. Aquino's funeral procession took more than eight hours before it reached its final destination, as tens of thousands of Filipinos lined up the streets {fact} where her cortege would pass by to pay their last respects to their beloved former leader. From Manila's harbor, all ships docked blared their sirens as a sign of respect to Mrs. Aquino.

[[File:Flags at half-mast at the Bonifacio Shrine.jpg|thumb|220px|left|A Philippine flag at half-mast beside the Martial Law Memorial Wall at the Bonifacio Shrine. All Philippine flags were at half-mast during the 10-day mourning period.]]

===Reaction===
Both local and international leaders showed respect for Aquino's achievements in the process of democratization in the Philippines.

====Local reaction====
Various politicians across the political spectrum expressed their grief and praise for the former Philippine leader. President Arroyo, once an ally of Aquino, remembered the sacrifices she made for the country and called her a &quot;national treasure.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AgerInquirer&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.inquirer.net/specialreports/coryaquino/view.php?db=1&amp;article=20090801-218238|title=Arroyo orders 10 days of mourning|last=Cabacungan, Jr.|first=Gil|date=2009-08-01|publisher=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former President Estrada said that the country had lost its mother and guiding voice with her sudden death. He also described Aquino as the &quot;Philippines' most loved woman.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Estrada: Aquino RP’s ‘most loved’ woman|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090726-217311/Estrada-Aquino-RPs-most-loved-woman|work=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-08-03|date=2009-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though once bitter political foes, Aquino and Estrada reconciled and joined hands together in opposing President Arroyo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nation lost 'mother, guiding voice'|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090801-218244/Nation-lost-mother-guiding-voice|work=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-08-01|date=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Senate President [[Juan Ponce Enrile]], Aquino's defense minister and later fierce critic, asked the public to pray for her eternal repose. Although former Aquino interior minister and Senate Minority floor leader [[Aquilino Pimentel, Jr.]] revealed that he had &quot;mixed feelings&quot; about Aquino's passing, he also said that the country &quot;shall be forever indebted to Cory for rallying the nation behind the campaign to topple dictatorial rule and restore democracy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Senators remember Cory's greatness|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/168760/Senators-remember-Corys-greatness|work=GMANews.tv|accessdate=2009-08-01|date=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further, ordinary Filipinos throughout the country wore either yellow shirts or held masses for Aquino as their way of paying tribute to the woman who once led them in a revolution that changed the course of their country's history. Yellow Ribbons, which were once used during Aquino's battle with Marcos, were tied along major national roads and streets as a sign of solidarity and support for the now deceased Aquino and her grieving family. In popular social networking sites such as [[Facebook]] and [[Twitter]], Filipinos posted yellow ribbons in their accounts as a tribute to the former Philippine leader.

Following her death, Filipino Catholics called on the Church to have Aquino canonized and declared as a [[saint]]. During her lifetime, Aquino has been known and praised for her strong spirituality and sincere devotion to the Catholic faith.

Days after her funeral, the [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] (BSP) announced that it supported calls to put the former President on the 500-Peso banknote alongside her husband, Ninoy Aquino.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=BSP backs adding Cory image to P500 bill|url=http://business.inquirer.net/money/breakingnews/view/20090806-219048/BSP-backs-adding-Cory-image-to-P500-bill|work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]]|accessdate=2009-08-06|date=2009-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====International reaction====
[[Image:Cory Aquino funeral.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Corazon Aquino's funeral march with the 4 Famous Honor Guards.]]
Across the globe, messages of sympathy and solidarity with the Filipino people were sent by various heads of state and international leaders. Pope [[Benedict XVI]], in his letter to Archbishop Rosales, recalled Aquino's &quot;courageous commitment to the freedom of the Filipino people, her firm rejection of violence and intolerance&quot; and called her a woman of courage and faith. U.S. President [[Barack Obama]], through White House Press Secretary [[Robert Gibbs]], said that &quot;her courage, determination, and moral leadership are an inspiration to us all and exemplify the best in the Filipino nation.&quot; U.S. Secretary of State [[Hillary Rodham Clinton]] expressed sadness over the passing of Aquino, to whom she had sent a personal letter of best wishes for recovery while she was still in hospital in July 2009. Clinton said that Aquino was &quot;admired by the world for her extraordinary courage&quot; in leading the fight against dictatorship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=World mourns Aquino’s death|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20090801-218251/World-mourns-Aquinos-death|work=INQUIRER.net|accessdate=2009-08-01|date=2009-08-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, South Africa President [[Jacob Zuma]] called Aquino &quot;a great leader who set a shining example of peaceful transition to democracy in her country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Aquino mourned at wake by thousands of Filipinos|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5hgwQ8MfOS2fuOym9WcK126G9-UQgD99QM71O0|last=Gomez|first=Jim|coauthor=[[Associated Press]]|publisher=[[Google News]]|accessdate=2009-08-04|date=2009-08-01|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5imI9aEUA|archivedate=2009-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Queen Elizabeth II]] of the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland]], through the British Ambassador in Manila, sent a message to the Filipino people which read: &quot;I am saddened to hear of the death of Corazon ‘Cory’ Aquino the former President of the Republic of the Philippines.&quot; She also added, &quot;I send my sincere condolences to her family and to the people of the Philippines. Signed, Elizabeth R.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.abs-cbn.com/business/08/06/09/british-queen-saddened-death-rps-true-queen|title=British Queen saddened with death of RP's 'true queen'|date=2008-08-06|newspaper=ABS-CBN News|accessdate=2009-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Furthermore, Russian President [[Dmitry Medvedev]], in a telegram to President Arroyo, said that “the name of Corazon Aquino is associated with a period of profound reforms and the democratic transformation of Filipino society.” Medvedev also lauded Aquino's sympathy to Russian people and her contribution to the improvement of [[Philippines–Russia relations|Russian-Filipino relations]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kremlin.ru/eng/text/news/2009/08/220411.shtml|title=Dmitry Medvedev expressed his condolences to President of the Philippines Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo following the passing of former President of the Republic Corazon Aquino.|date=August 1, 2009|publisher=[[Presidential Press and Information Office]]|accessdate=2009-08-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Moreover, global democratic icons such as [[Timor-Leste]] President [[Jose Ramos-Horta]] and [[Wan Azizah]], wife of Malaysian opposition leader [[Anwar Ibrahim]], came to the Philippines not just to express their sympathies but to attend their friend Aquino's death and funeral, as well.

==Honors==
After leaving the presidency, Aquino received several awards and citations. In 1994, Aquino was cited as one of ''100 Women Who Shaped World History'' in a reference book written by Gail Meyer Rolka and published by Bluewood Books in San Francisco, California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The 100 Most Influential Women of All Time: A Ranking Past and Present|url=http://www.adherents.com/people/100_women.html|publisher=Adherents.com|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1996, she received the [[Fulbright Program|J. William Fulbright Prize for International Understanding]] from the Fulbright Association, joining past recipients such as [[Jimmy Carter]] and [[Nelson Mandela]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Former Philippine President Corazon C. Aquino Receives 1996 J. William Fulbright Prize For International Understanding|url=http://www.fulbrightalumni.org/olc/pub/FBA/fulbright_prize/aquino_pr.html|publisher=Fulbright Association|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1999, Aquino was chosen by Time Magazine as one of the 20 Most Influential Asians of the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Nisid Hajari|title=Asians of the Century|url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/asia/magazine/1999/990823/cover1.html|work=Time Magazine|date=August 23–30, 1999|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The same magazine cited her in November 2006 as one of 65 great Asian Heroes, along with [[Mahatma Gandhi]], [[Deng Xiaoping]], [[Aung San Suu Kyi]], [[Lee Kuan Yew]], and King [[Bhumibol Adulyadej]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Sheila Coronel|title=60 Years of Asian Heroes: Corazon Aquino|url=http://www.time.com/time/asia/2006/heroes/nb_aquino.html|work=Time Magazine|accessdate=2008-04-15|date=2006-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 2002, Aquino became the first woman named to the Board of Governors of the Board of the [[Asian Institute of Management]], a leading graduate business school and think tank in the Asia Pacific region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Asian Institute of Management: History|url=http://www.aim.edu/aboutaim/history.asp|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080211114310/http://www.aim.edu/aboutaim/history.asp|archivedate=2008-02-11|publisher=Asian Institute of Management|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; She served on the Board until 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Asian Institute of Management: News and Announcements|url=http://www.aim.edu/home/announcementc.asp?id=727|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080124071707/http://www.aim.edu/home/announcementc.asp?id=727|archivedate=2008-01-24|publisher=Asian Institute of Management|accessdate=2008-04-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:New PHP500 Banknote (Obverse).jpg|thumb|right|220px|The &quot;New Generation&quot; 500 peso note featuring the portrait of Corazon Aquino and her husband [[Benigno Aquino, Jr.]].]]
[[File:Cory aquino wiki.JPG|thumb|right|250px|Former Philippine President Corazon Aquino's grave is next to her husband Ninoy Aquino's at the Manila Memorial Park in [[Parañaque]], [[Philippines]]]]

Aquino was portrayed by [[Laurice Guillen]] in the 1988 [[HBO]] miniseries ''[[A Dangerous Life]]''. Aquino was a main character in [[Bienvenido Noriega, Jr.|Boy Noriega]]'s 1987 stage comedy ''Bongbong at Kris'' (Bongbong and Kris), about an imagined romantic coupling between the only son of Ferdinand Marcos and the youngest daughter of the Aquinos. In the movie ''Alfredo Lim: Batas ng Maynila'' (Alfredo Lim: Law of Manila) Aquino was portrayed by Luz Valdez. She was portrayed by Tess Villarama both in the movies ''Ilaban Mo, Bayan Ko: The Obet Pagdanganan Story'' (My Fight, My Country) in 1997 and ''Chavit'' in 2003. She was also portrayed by Geraldine Malacaman in the 1998 musical play ''Lean''. In the defunct comedy gag show ''[[Ispup]]'', Madz Nicolas played a [[parody|parodized]] version of Aquino who often reminisces about life with Ninoy. In 2004, Aquino was portrayed by Irma Adlawan in the miniseries ''Sa 'Yo Lamang'' (Only Yours).

In 2008, a musical play about Aquino starring Isay Alvarez as Aquino, was staged at the [[Meralco Theater]]. Entitled ''Cory, the Musical'', it was written and directed by Nestor Torre and featured a [[libretto]] of 19 original songs composed by Lourdes Pimentel, wife of Senator [[Aquilino Pimentel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Musical on Cory Aquino to be staged at Meralco Theater|url=http://showbizandstyle.inquirer.net/entertainment/entertainment/view/20080620-143874/Musical-on-Cory-Aquino-to-be-staged-at-Meralco-Theater|date=2008-06-20|accessdate=2008-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/121033/Bing-Pimentel-writes-musical-play-for-Cory|title=gmanews.tv, Bing Pimentel writes musical play for Cory|publisher=Gmanews.tv|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.abs-cbnnews.com/entertainment/09/16/08/coming-october-cory-musical|title=abs-cbnnews, Coming this October: 'Cory' the Musical|publisher=Abs-cbnnews.com|date=2008-09-16|accessdate=2010-03-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; A two-part special of [[Maalaala Mo Kaya]] aired on January 23 and 30, 2010. [[Bea Alonzo]] played the role of Cory Aquino while Piolo Pascual portrayed Ninoy Aquino. The two-part special aired for Cory's 77th birthday.

==Legacy==
{{unreferenced section|date=May 2011}}
*On January 25, 2010. Corazon Aquino's monument was unveiled in Manila, beside her spouse [[Ninoy Aquino]].
*On February 3, 2010, Grand Prize winner Julian Eymard Paguiligan of [[Bulacan State University]]'s College of Architecture and Fine Arts (CAFA) made his painting entry entitled ''Ika-25 ng Pebrero, 1986'' presented in the last year's 24th Visual Arts National Competition for the Directories Philippines Corporation's directory cover as a paid tribute. He made a portrait of the late President Aquino in 27.5x34.25&quot; [[watercolor]] on paper, as a symbol for her contribution not only for [[democracy]], but also in the successes of the [[People Power Revolution|EDSA Revolution]] in the past.
*On June 15, 2010, Batasan Hills Elementary School (BHES) in [[Batasan Hills, Quezon City]] changed its name to the &quot;President Corazon C. Aquino Elementary School&quot; or (PCCAES).
*On August 1, 2010, the first anniversary of her death, a 200x250 [[Photographic mosaic|Photo Mosaic]] of President Cory Aquino was unveiled near the Quirino Grandstand at the Luneta Park, Manila in the presence of her son, President [[Benigno Aquino III]] and supporters of the late President. It has been submitted to the Guinness World Records to be certified as the largest photo mosaic in the world.
*On October 9, 2010, Manila Mayor Alfredo S. Lim inaugurated on Friday a public market in Baseco, Port Area named after the late President Corazon C. Aquino. The President Corazon C. Aquino Public Market, which lies at the heart of the community, has 77 stalls selling meat, fresh fruits, cooked food, rice, vegetables and a variety of dry goods including condiments, garments, and plastic wares.
*On December 16, 2010, President [[Noynoy Aquino]] and [[Bangko Sentral ng Pilipinas]] (Central Bank of the Philippines) announced the release of new 500-peso bill and presented their new design, which features both Ninoy and Cory Aquino.

==Awards and achievements==
{{refimprove section|date=May 2011}}
*1986 [[TIME|Time Magazine]] [[Person of the Year|Woman of the Year]]
*1986 [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] Human Rights Award
*1986 United Nations Silver Medal
*1986 Canadian International Prize for Freedom
*1986 International Democracy Award from the International Association of Political Consultants
*1987 [[Prize For Freedom]] Award from [[Liberal International]]
*1993 Special Peace Award from the Aurora Aragon Quezon Peace Awards Foundation and Concerned Women of the Philippines
*1995 Path to Peace Award
*1996 [[Fulbright Program|J. William Fulbright Prize for International Understanding]] from the U.S. Department of State
*1998 [[Ramon Magsaysay Award]] for International Understanding
*1998 Pearl S. Buck Award
*1999 One of Time Magazine's 20 Most Influential Asians of the 20th Century
*2001 [[World Citizenship Award]]
*2005 [[David Rockefeller]] Bridging Leadership Awards
*2005 One of the ''World's Elite Women Who Make a Difference'' by the International Women's Forum Hall of Fame
*2006 One of Time Magazine's 65 Asian Heroes
*2008 One of A Different View's 15 Champions of World Democracy
*EWC Asia Pacific Community Building Award
*Women's International Center International Leadership Living Legacy Award
*[[Martin Luther King Jr.]] Nonviolent Peace Prize
*[[United Nations Development Fund for Women]] Noel Foundation Life Award&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Noel Foundation Life Awards|url=http://www.noelfoundation.org/awards.htm|publisher=Noel Foundation|accessdate=2010-01-07 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honorary doctorates==
{{unreferenced section|date=May 2011}}
*Doctor of International Relations, honoris causa, from:
**[[Boston University]] in Boston
**[[Eastern University (United States)|Eastern University]] in St. David, PA
**[[Fordham University]] in New York
**[[Waseda University]] in Tokyo
*Doctor of Civil Law, honoris causa, from:
**[[Far Eastern University]] (59th Commencement Exercises, March 1987)
*Doctor of Laws, honoris causa, from:
**[[University of the Philippines]]
**[[University of Santo Tomas]] in [[Manila]]
*Doctor of Humane Letters, honoris causa, from:
**[[Ateneo de Manila University]]
**[[College of Mount Saint Vincent]] in New York
**[[Xavier University – Ateneo de Cagayan]] (Cagayan de Oro City, Philippines)
*Doctor of Humanities, honoris causa, from:
**[[San Beda College]] in Manila, 2000
**[[Seattle University]], 2002
**[[Stonehill College]] in [[Massachusetts]]
**[[University of Oregon]], 1995
*Doctor of Public Administration, honoris causa, from:
**[[Pamantasan ng Lungsod ng Maynila]] (University of the City of Manila), June 1994

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|Corazon Aquino}}
* [http://www.coryaquino.ph/ Official website of Corazon Aquino] – maintained by the Ninoy and Cory Aquino Foundation
* [http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,963185,00.html Time Woman of the Year: Corazon &quot;Cory&quot; Aquino]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WX9ysynaIq0 President Cory's historic speech before the U.S. Congress]
* [http://www.nytimes.com/2009/08/01/world/asia/01aquino.html?_r=1&amp;hp NYTimes obituary]
* [http://www.bayangmagiliw.info/pangulong-cory-aquino-sa-time-magazine/ President Aquino in Time Magazine's Year ender]

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ferdinand Marcos]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[President of the Philippines]]|years=February 25, 1986 – June 30, 1992}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Fidel V. Ramos]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Template group
|list =
{{Corazon Aquino}}
{{Noynoy Aquino}}
{{Philippine presidents}}
{{Time Persons of the Year 1976-2000}}
{{Cold War figures}}
}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
|NAME              = Aquino, Corazon Cojuangco
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = 11th President of the Philippines
|DATE OF BIRTH     = January 25, 1933
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = Paniqui, Tarlac, Philippines
|DATE OF DEATH     = August 1, 2009
|PLACE OF DEATH    = Makati City, Metro Manila, Philippines
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Aquino, Corazon}}
[[Category:1933 births]]
[[Category:2009 deaths]]
[[Category:Aquino family|Corazon Aquino]]
[[Category:Cancer deaths in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Deaths from colorectal cancer]]
[[Category:Female heads of government]]
[[Category:Female heads of state]]
[[Category:Filipino human rights activists]]
[[Category:Filipino democracy activists]]
[[Category:Filipino Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Filipino women in politics]]
[[Category:Politicians of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:Filipino people of Chinese descent]]
[[Category:Nonviolence advocates]]
[[Category:People from Tarlac]]
[[Category:People of Kapampangan descent]]
[[Category:Presidents of the Philippines]]
[[Category:Liberal Party (Philippines) politicians]]
[[Category:Philippine Democratic Party – People's Power politicians]]
[[Category:Order of the Precious Crown members]]

[[ar:كورازون أكينو]]
[[zh-min-nan:Corazon Aquino]]
[[bcl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[bg:Мария Корасон Акино]]
[[ca:Corazón Aquino]]
[[ceb:Cory Aquino]]
[[cs:Corazon Aquinová]]
[[cbk-zam:Corazon Aquino]]
[[cy:Corazon Aquino]]
[[da:Corazon Aquino]]
[[de:Corazon Aquino]]
[[et:Corazon Aquino]]
[[el:Κορασόν Ακίνο]]
[[es:Corazón Aquino]]
[[eo:Corazón Aquino]]
[[fa:کرازون آکینو]]
[[fo:Corazon Aquino]]
[[fr:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ga:Corazon Aquino]]
[[gl:Corazón Aquino]]
[[ko:코라손 아키노]]
[[hy:Կորասոն Ակինո]]
[[hr:Corazon Aquino]]
[[io:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ilo:Corazon Aquino]]
[[id:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ia:Corazón Aquino]]
[[it:Corazón Aquino]]
[[he:קורסון אקינו]]
[[jv:Corazon Aquino]]
[[pam:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ka:კორასონ აკინო]]
[[sw:Corazon Aquino]]
[[la:Corazon Aquino]]
[[lv:Korasona Akino]]
[[lb:Corazón Aquino]]
[[lt:Corazon Aquino]]
[[hu:Corazón Aquino]]
[[mk:Корасон Акино]]
[[mr:कोराझोन एक्विनो]]
[[ms:Corazon Aquino]]
[[my:အာကီနို]]
[[nl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ja:コラソン・アキノ]]
[[no:Corazón Aquino]]
[[oc:Corazón Aquino]]
[[pag:Corazon Aquino]]
[[km:កូរ៉ាស៊ូន អាគីណូ]]
[[nds:Corazon Aquino]]
[[pl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[pt:Corazón Aquino]]
[[ro:Corazon Aquino]]
[[qu:Corazón Aquino]]
[[ru:Акино, Корасон]]
[[sk:Corazon Aquinová]]
[[sl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[szl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[sh:Corazon Aquino]]
[[fi:Corazon Aquino]]
[[sv:Corazon Aquino]]
[[tl:Corazon Aquino]]
[[ta:கொரசோன் அக்கினோ]]
[[th:คอราซอน อากีโน]]
[[tr:Maria Corazon Aquino]]
[[uk:Корасон Акіно]]
[[ur:کوریزون اکینو]]
[[vi:Corazon Aquino]]
[[war:Corazón Aquino]]
[[yi:קארי אקינא]]
[[zh:柯拉蓉·艾奎諾]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
