<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27987066" ns="0" title="2010 G-20 Seoul summit preparations"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:2010 G-20 Seoul summit.jpg|thumb|right|World leaders at the 2010 G-20 Seoul summit]]
The '''2010 G-20 Seoul summit preparations ''' encompasses all the work which precedes the [[2010 G-20 Seoul summit|fifth summit]] of the [[G-20 major economies|G-20]] [[Head of government|heads of government]] in discussion of [[financial market]]s and the [[world economy]],&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes1&quot;&gt;Cho Jin-seo. [http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/biz/2010/07/123_69053.html  &quot;Seoul unveils G20 summit's symbol,&quot;] ''Korea Times.'' July 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; which will take place at [[Seoul]], [[South Korea]] during November 11&amp;ndash;12, 2010.

==Multiple agendas ==
The G20 summit is not construed as having a global governance role, primarily in helping to establish a new agenda to respond to new challenges.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.koreaherald.com/specialreport/Detail.jsp?newsMLId=20100315000054  &quot;'G20 Seoul Initiative' aims to pave way for global green economic order,&quot;] ''Korea Herald.'' March 31, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The government of Korea is reported to want to use the summit as a promotional opportunity, as happened with the [[1988 Summer Olympics|1988 Olympic Games]] and [[2002 World Cup]].&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes1&quot;/&gt;  

The pre-planning of others is less explicit. For example, North Korea remains a [http://idioms.thefreedictionary.com/a+cloud+on+the+horizon  &quot;cloud on the horizon.&quot;]&lt;ref&gt;Oliver, Christian. [http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/9088b6b8-7d8c-11df-a0f5-00144feabdc0.html  &quot;Seoul: S Korea looks forward to its own party,&quot;] ''Financial Times.'' June 25, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Planning for the summit encompasses nested aspects of the event, e.g., 
* Developing an understanding of each country’s perspective and ensuring that it is reflected in the agenda &lt;ref name=&quot;committee&quot;&gt;G20 Seoul summit, Presidential Committee for the G20 Summit, [http://www.seoulsummit.kr/eng/goPage.g20?menu_seq=G20MENU00070&amp;return_url=TOP04_SUB02  Introduction to the Committee]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Preparing and coordinating the venue, facilities and staff required &lt;ref name=&quot;committee&quot;/&gt;
* Organizing arrivals, departures and accommodations &lt;ref name=&quot;committee&quot;/&gt;
* Coordination  with international organizations, academia, research centers, NGOs, media, government departments, and local governments &lt;ref name=&quot;committee&quot;/&gt;
* Media Center, including support for members of the press &lt;ref name=&quot;committee&quot;/&gt;

===Timeline===
In November, sherpas representing the summit participants will have preparatory meetings  to put the finishing touches on summit planning.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.koreaittimes.com/story/8713/preparations-g20-seoul-summit-november-and-its-agenda  &quot;Preparations for the G20 Seoul Summit in November and its Agenda,&quot;] ''Korea Times.'' May 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Pre-summit events are scheduled in an orderly timeline as follows:
* November 11–12 (Seoul): '''[[G20 summit]]'''&lt;ref name=&quot;events&quot;&gt;G20 Seoul summit, [http://www.seoulsummit.kr/eng/goPage.g20?menu_seq=G20MENU00060&amp;return_url=TOP01_SUB04  Official Events and Schedule]&lt;/ref&gt;
* November 10–11 (Seoul): '''Business summit'''&lt;ref name=&quot;events&quot;/&gt; scheduled on the periphery of the G-20 Summit.  Planners anticipate that chief executives of the top 20 business firms of the G-20 member nations will attend.&lt;ref&gt;[http://chicagopressrelease.com/news/seoul-spearheads-efforts-for-supporting-the-g20-summit &quot;Seoul Spearheads Efforts for Supporting the G20 Summit,&quot;] Chicago Press Release citing Seoul Municipal Government. May 13, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* October 22–23 ([[Gwangju]]): '''G20 Finance Ministers' and Central Bank Governors' Meeting'''&lt;ref name=&quot;events&quot;/&gt;
* September 4–5 ([[Gyeongju]]): '''G20 Deputies' Meeting'''&lt;ref name=&quot;events&quot;/&gt;
* July &amp;mdash; Former Ghanaian President John Agyekum Kufuor attended the preparatory meeting in Korea as the representative of the [[Club of Madrid]], which is an organization of former democratically elected heads of state.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ghananewsagency.org/s_politics/r_17968/  &quot;Kufor leaves for G-20 meeting in Seoul,&quot;] Ghana News Agency. July 12, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sherpas===
&lt;!-- image removed [[File:Inchon G20 Civil Dialogue 2010.jpg|thumb|right|Panoramic image of delegates at &quot;The Civil G20 Dialogue 2010.&quot; G20 &quot;[[sherpas]]&quot; and [[NGO]] representatives met to talk about the G20 agenda -- [[Inchon]], October 2010. {{ffdc|Inchon G20 Civil Dialogue 2010.jpg}}]] --&gt;
Representatives or &quot;[[sherpas]]&quot; from each attending nation prepared the groundwork for discussions during the G20 summit.  They met in Inchon in October to discuss the need for &quot;civil dialogue.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Choi, Jessica Seoyoung. [http://g20.korea.net/html/news/newsview.asp?view_idx=50703&amp;view_ck=main  &quot;Civil G20 Dialog held in Incheon,&quot;] Korea.net, October 19, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Events for spouses ===
Plans were developed for the wives of leaders attending the conference.  Michelle Obama, wife of the President of the United States, and Carla Bruni, wife of the President of France, announced in early November that they would not be able to participate.&lt;ref&gt;Kim Hyun. [http://english.yonhapnews.co.kr/culturesports/2010/11/04/19/0701000000AEN20101104006300315F.HTML  &quot;Michell Obama, Bruni Sarkozy not coming to G-20 summit in Seoul,&quot;] Yonhap News Agency. November 4, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Site construction==
In conjunction with the [[2010 G-20 Seoul summit|Seoul summit]], three artificial islands and venues are being built at a cost of 96.4 billion [[South Korean won|won]].  The international leaders will meet on islands in the midst of the [[Han River (Korea)|Han River]] between the Banpo and Dongjak bridges in Seoul.&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes2&quot;&gt;Kang Shin-who. [http://www.koreatimes.co.kr/www/news/nation/2010/01/113_58782.html &quot;Seoul to Host G20 Summit on 'Floating Islands' on Han River,&quot;] ''Korea Times.'' June 27, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The islands will be connected via a secured bridge and located between the [[Banpo Bridge]] and [[Dongjak Bridge]]. The three artificial islands will be home to the main convention hall with restaurants and a park. Initial work is expected to be completed by September.&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes2&quot;/&gt;

==Website, logo, and slogan ==
[[File:2010 G20 Seoul summit logo.JPG|thumb|right|The logo reflects the summit slogan &amp;mdash; &quot;with people to the world; with the world to the future&quot;]]

The initial publicly visible preparatory steps were in the creation of a website.  After four months of test runs, the online venue became a platform for announcing the choice of a summit logo, which was chosen out of 2,279 entries in an open contest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bernama.com/bernama/v5/newsworld.php?id=511993  &quot;South Korea Unveils G-20 Summit Logo, Web Site,&quot;] Bernama (Malaysian National News Agency). July 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Korean lantern logo represents light shining in the dark and also the light which welcomes guests.&lt;ref&gt;Kim Seok. [http://www.arirang.co.kr/News/News_View.asp?nseq=104740&amp;code=Ne4&amp;category=3  &quot;G20 Seoul Summit Symbol Unveiled.&quot;] ''Arirang News'' (Korea television). July 8, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; This forward-looking theme is repeated in the official Korean slogan &amp;mdash; &quot;with people to the world; with the world to the future.&quot;  The logo incorporates an image of the sun rising over the sea, and the 20 rays coming from the center represent the 20 members of the meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes2&quot;/&gt;

==Security==
The South Korean People [[National Police Agency (South Korea)|National Police Agency]] (NPA) created a special police unit as part of its efforts to enhance security at the G-20 summit.  Th NPA-lead security committee will coordinate the work of 25 government-related agencies,&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhua1&quot;&gt;[http://findarticles.com/p/news-articles/xinhua-news-agency-ceis/mi_8007/is_20100305/south-korea-launches-security-committee/ai_n52385852/ &quot;South Korea launches security committee for G20 summit,&quot;] Xinhua. March 10, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; including:   
* [[Presidential Security Service]]&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhua1&quot;/&gt;
* [[National Intelligence Service (South Korea)|National Intelligence Service]]&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhua1&quot;/&gt;
* [[Ministry of National Defense (Republic of Korea)|Ministry of National Defense]]&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhua1&quot;/&gt;
* [[Ministry of Public Administration and Security (South Korea)|National Emergency Management Agency]]&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhua1&quot;/&gt;

This security will limit access some parts of the summit islands.  The waters of the Han River will be closely monitored. 

World leaders attending this summit will stay at various hotels around Seoul, but, for security reasons, the press have been discouraged from writing about this aspect of summit preparations.&lt;ref name=&quot;koreatimes2&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- Anticipated section see [[2010 G-20 Toronto summit preparations#Post-summit review of preparations]]?
==Post-summit review of preparations== --&gt;

== See also ==
* [[2010 G-20 Seoul summit]]
* [[2010 G-20 Toronto summit preparations]]
* [[List of G-20 summits]]
* [[United Nations Research Institute for Social Development]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.seoulsummit.kr/ Website of the G20 Seoul Summit]
* [http://www.g20.org/ G20 Home Page]
* [http://community.eldis.org/.59d667c3/14  Community Development Forum, G-20, Seoul, 2010]
* [http://www.miceseoul.com/tour/ 2010 Seoul G20(SCV)]
*{{youtube|EmIhhsouCJ8|Seoul Summit promotional video}}
{{G-20 leaders' summits}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2010 G-20 Seoul Summit Preparations}}
[[Category:G20|Summit 2010/11 Seoul]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
