<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2798541" ns="0" title="University of Eastern Africa, Baraton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|name           = University of Eastern Africa, Baraton
|image          = [[File:University_of_Eastern_Africa,_Baraton.png]]
|motto          = Mental, Physical, Spiritual
|established    = [[1980]]
|type           = [[Private school|Private]]
|president      = Prof. Miriam B. Mwita
|city           = Eldoret
|state          = Uasin Gishu County, Rift Valley
|country        = [[Kenya]]
|coor = {{Coord|0.255459|35.082561 |type:edu|format=dms|display=inline,title}} 
|campus         = {{convert|339|acre|km2}}
|undergrad      = 
|postgrad       =
|postgrad_label = 
|faculty        = 50
|free_label     =
|free           =
|colors         = Blue and gold
|website= [http://www.ueab.ac.ke/ www.ueab.ac.ke]
|}}

The '''University of Eastern Africa, Baraton''' (UEAB) is a [[Private university|private]] [[coeducational]] [[Seventh-Day Adventist]] university located about 50 km from [[Eldoret|Eldoret Kenya]]. It offers various degrees in a number of graduate and undergraduate programs in the fields of [[Business]], the [[Humanities]], [[Agriculture]], [[Technology]], [[Health Sciences]] and [[Education]]. Baraton University, as it is popularly known, is run by the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]], and is part of its system of higher education. It is fully accredited by the Commission for Higher Education, Kenya Government, and was the first private University to receive a Charter granted by the republic of [[Kenya]] on March 28, 1991. The University is also a member of the Inter-University Council for East Africa, The [[Association of Commonwealth Universities]], and the [[Association of African Universities]].

The mission of UEAB is the provision and advancement of a holistic Christian quality education for the youth with the aim of equipping them with necessary skills for service for God and humanity. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=124&amp;Itemid=54 |title=UEAB - About UEAB |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==History==
The beginning of the Seventh-day Adventist education in this part of Africa dates back to the  establishment of the [[Seventh-day Adventist Church]] in the region. The earliest church was established in [[Tanzania]] in 1903, followed by church work around [[Lake Victoria]] in Kenya in 1906.  In 1928 what is now known as [[Kamagambo Adventist College]] was established near [[Kisii town]]. 

Many primary and [[secondary schools|secondary school]] have since been established. Some of these have been offering post secondary education, but none of them has offered a full bachelor's degree program. For this reason, students desiring that level of education in an Adventist institution before 1980 had to go outside [[Eastern Africa]]. During the 1970s, the [[Middle East University]] in [[Beirut|Beirut Lebanon]] served many such students. Thus there was a great need for a full fledged university in Eastern Africa.

In October 1978, the Board of the Afro-Mideast Division of Seventh-day Adventists took an action to establish such a university in Kenya on December 21, 1978.  The Kenya Government allotted the Baraton Animal Husbandry Research Station of 339 acres (1.37 km²) in [[Nandi District]] to the Seventh-day Adventist Church for the purpose of founding what is now known as the University of Eastern Africa, Baraton.  Classes began in January 1980 in the temporary farm structures.  Some of these structures have since been replaced with new and modern buildings.

==Purpose==
The University is an integral part of society. It has the special function of lifting the vision of society by challenging and motivating its students to develop to the highest possible goals. This is done through programmes geared to serve the needs of the community and the general public.

Here, instructors and students engage in free inquiry. An important facet of this co-operative effort is the validation of knowledge. The University of Eastern Africa, Baraton is designated to serve the church by offering courses that are relevant to the training of its workers, including leaders and administrators.

The university also hosts a local research centre of the [[Ellen G. White Estate]].
UEAB Objectives 	

==Schools==

* School of Business &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=5&amp;Itemid=116 |title=UEAB - School of Business |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* School of Humanities and Social Sciences &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=145&amp;Itemid=314 |title=UEAB - School of Humanities and Social Sciences |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* School of Health Sciences &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=247&amp;Itemid=2 |title=UEAB - School of Health Sciences |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* School of Science and Technology &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=246&amp;Itemid=313 |title=UEAB - School of Science and Technology |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* School of Education &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ueab.ac.ke/home/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=21&amp;Itemid=134 |title=UEAB - School of Education |publisher=ueab.ac.ke |date= |accessdate=2011-05-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
*[[List of Seventh-day Adventist colleges and universities]]

==External links==
*[http://www.ueab.ac.ke/ University of Eastern Africa, Baraton Website]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Eastern Africa, Baraton, University of}}
[[Category:Universities and colleges affiliated with the Seventh-day Adventist Church]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Kenya]]
[[Category:Ellen G. White Estate]]
[[Category:Education in Rift Valley Province]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1980]]
[[Category:Private universities and colleges in Kenya]]

[[fr:Université d'Afrique de l'Est, Baraton]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
