<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="27985091" ns="0" title="Bristol Supertram"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Public transit
| name = Bristol Supertram
| image = Bristol Supertram.jpg
| imagesize= 
| caption= &lt;small&gt;Artist impression of Supertram in Bristol city centre&lt;/small&gt; 
| locale = [[Bristol]] and &lt;br&gt;[[South Gloucestershire]]
| transit_type = [[Light rail]]
| began_operation = 
| system_length = 16.7km
| lines = 1
| stations = 16
| ridership = 
| track_gauge = [[Standard gauge]] 
| operator = 
}}

'''Bristol Supertram''' was a proposed [[light rail]] system for the [[Bristol]] and [[South Gloucestershire]] regions of [[England]]. In 2001, the project was given backing from the [[Premiership of Tony Blair|government]] to build a line that would link the [[Bristol city centre|city centre]] with the [[Bristol North (UK Parliament constituency)|North Bristol]] region.

==History==
The Supertram project was given the go ahead in March 2001, following an announcement from the Deputy Prime Minister, [[John Prescott]]. The initial cost of £194 million was to be provided by a [[Public–private partnership| public–private partnership (PPP)]] which would include 20% funding from the private sector. The remaining funds were to come from the government and the local authorities of [[Politics of Bristol|Bristol]] and [[South Gloucestershire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.tramdev.clara.net/news.htm#mar2801| Tramdev|publisher= Tramdev|title=Government announces backing for tram scheme|date=March 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bristol was one of 25 towns and cities that had been selected for light rail development by the [[Premiership of Tony Blair|New Labour]] government. This was part of a [[A New Deal for Transport: Better for everyone|10-year plan]] to improve public transport in the UK.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/magazine/8465383.stm|title=What happened to the 10-year transport plan?|publisher=BBC News|date=2010-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Opinion polls in Bristol have consistently shown that the issues of inadequate public transport and [[traffic congestion]] are two of the biggest local concerns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.bristol.gov.uk/sites/default/files/documents/council_and_democracy/consultations/citizen_panels/citizen_panel_reports/CP%20report%20-%20Oct%202008%20-%20Best%20and%20worst%20of%20Bristol.pdf||publisher= Bristol City Council|title= Best and Worst of Bristol: October 2008 Citizens’ Panel Report|date= October 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Public interest in a light rail system had been raised by a demonstration service by Bristol Electric Railbus Ltd (BER). This was operated on [[Bristol Harbour|Bristol Harbourside]] between 1998 and 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.parrypeoplemovers.com/news_archive_2006.htm| PPM 35 RAILBUS RETURNS FOR RESTORATION TO SERVICEABLE CONDITION|publisher= Parry People Movers Ltd (PPML)|title= PPM 35 RAILBUS RETURNS FOR RESTORATION TO SERVICEABLE CONDITION|date= April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Line 1==
The first stage of the project was a route called Line 1, which was planned to run from Bristol city centre to [[Almondsbury]]. This line would use a combination of existing [[Railtrack]] operated tracks and specialised tram tracks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.lrta.org/bristol2.html|Bristol Rapid Transit|publisher=Light Rail Transit Association|title= Bristol Rapid Transit|date=March 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 30 minute journey would cover a total of 16 stops, which would include [[Bristol Parkway railway station|Bristol Parkway station]] and [[Bradley Stoke]]. At the end of Line 1, the track would terminate at an [[M5 motorway|M5]] [[park and ride]] site next to the [[Almondsbury Interchange]].

'''Line 1 stations'''
* Union Street &lt;small&gt;([[Bristol city centre|Broadmead Shopping Centre]])&lt;/small&gt;
* Quay Street &lt;small&gt;(City Centre)&lt;/small&gt;
* Broad Quay 
* [[St Mary Redcliffe]]
* [[Bristol Temple Meads railway station|Bristol Temple Meads]] {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* [[Lawrence Hill, Bristol|Lawrence Hill]] {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* [[Stapleton Road railway station|Stapleton Road]] {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* [[Ashley, Bristol|Ashley Down]] &lt;small&gt;(reopened station)&lt;/small&gt; {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* [[Lockleaze, Bristol|Bonnington Walk]] &lt;small&gt;(reopened station)&lt;/small&gt; {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* [[Filton Abbey Wood railway station|Abbey Wood]] {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}} 
* [[University of the West of England| University of the West of England (UWE)]] &lt;small&gt;(proposed extension)&lt;/small&gt; 
* [[Bristol Parkway railway station|Bristol Parkway station]] {{rail-interchange|gb|rail}}
* Parkway North &lt;small&gt;(possible M4 park and ride)&lt;/small&gt;  
* Great Meadow 
* [[Bradley Stoke|Savages Wood]]
* Patchway Brook
* [[Aztec West|Aztec West Business Park]] &lt;small&gt;(M5 park and ride)&lt;/small&gt;

The line was intended to provide an affordable and efficient transport service that would improve the economic competitiveness of the North Bristol corridor. It was predicted that the service would become operational in 2007. Four additional routes have been proposed for future light rail development in the region, all of which would connect with existing railway lines.

'''Future routes'''
* A line through the [[Bristol South (UK Parliament constituency)|South Bristol region]] 
* A line from Bristol to [[Yate]] via [[Emersons Green]]
* A link with the [[Portishead Railway]]
* A link with the [[Severn Beach Line|Severn Beach railway line]]

==Project implementation==
With a commitment from the government to provide substantial funding for the project, the [[Unitary authority|unitary authorities]] of Bristol and South Gloucestershire needed to finalise a route for Line 1. It was at this stage of the project that South Gloucestershire put forward a plan for a new route that included the [[Cribbs Causeway]] shopping centre instead of Parkway station. Bristol council remained in favour of the original route to Parkway, with a proposal for an extension that would include the [[University of the West of England|University of the West of England (UWE)]].

An independent evaluation was commissioned by both councils in order to decide between the two schemes, which was carried out by the engineering consultants, [[Atkins (company)|WS Atkins]]. The results from the study showed that the Parkway option was feasible and cost effective. The Cribbs Causeway option was shown to increase the project cost by £100 million and to also lengthen the construction time by two years. It was also demonstrated that the Cribbs Causeway route would not meet the criteria that was required in order to qualify for government funding. Following the rejection of their proposal, South Gloucestershire withdrew from the Supertram project, which had by now been running for more than two years.

==Cancellation==
With the departure of South Gloucestershire, Bristol council submitted a modified route plan in late 2003 for a new Line 1 that would terminate at Parkway station. A government feasibility study was initiated to determine whether the new project still qualified for the original level of funding. It was during this period that the council found itself under political pressure to reduce a proposed local council tax increase.

With financial pressure from the council and growing uncertainty about Line 1, the Labour and Conservative groups recommended that the project should be abandoned. In March 2004, Bristol council announced that the Supertram project would be cancelled. This allowed funds that were set aside for the project to be used to cover the council tax increase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/3760405.stm|title=City tram project to be dropped|publisher=BBC News|date=2004-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Future plans==
Since the 2004 cancellation, a number of local proposals have been made to revive the project and to look at alternative transport schemes for the region.    

===Integrated Transport Authority (ITA)===
It has been suggested that the four unitary authorities of Bristol, South Gloucestershire, [[North Somerset]] and [[Bath and North East Somerset]] should form a regional Integrated Transport Authority (ITA). This could benefit the area by offering an improved level of decision-making power with regard to local transport needs. It could also potentially avoid the kind of regional disagreements that ultimately ended the Supertram project.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.bristol247.com/2009/11/23/transport-authority-is-one-quango-bristol-desperately-needs/|Midland Metro update|publisher= Bristol 24-7|title=Transport authority is one quango Bristol desperately needs|date=2009-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;Attempts have been made within the Bristol region to call for the establishment of an ITA. So far, these have all been rejected by the three other unitary authorities of North Somerset, Bath and North East Somerset and South Gloucestershire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.bristol247.com/2009/11/13/we-dont-need-greater-bristol-transport-plan-says-councillor/|www.bristol247.com|publisher= Bristol 24-7|title=We don’t need Greater Bristol transport plan, says councillor|date=2009-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tram tax===
One idea that would enable a local authority to raise the finances necessary for a light rail system is the introduction of a “tram tax”. It has been suggested that Bristol residents would agree to a local tax increase if they fully understood what it would deliver as a result.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/4266110.stm|title=Tram tax to pay for new transport|publisher=BBC News|date=2005-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tram taxes have been proposed unsuccessfully in a number of regions within the UK for the development of new light rail systems and to provide support for existing ones.

[[Image:Bristol_BRT.jpg‎|350px|thumb|Plans to locate a diesel-powered BRT alongside the Bristol &amp; Bath cycleway were dropped following a local petition]]
===Bus Rapid Transit (BRT)===
With Bristol Council unable to continue with the development of a light rail scheme, they have changed their focus to a [[Bus rapid transit|Bus Rapid Transit (BRT)]] or “guided bus” system as a way of addressing the same congestion problems within the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Tessa Coombes|url= http://www.gwebusinesswest.co.uk/pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%208-Bus%20Rapid%20Transit.pdf|title= Bus Rapid Transit &amp; Guided Bus Schemes |publisher= GWE Business West|year=April 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007, an initial BRT route was proposed that would run alongside the [[Bristol &amp; Bath Railway Path|Bristol and Bath cycleway]], causing a narrowing of the path and a loss of natural habitat in the process. 

This led to a campaign against the plan by local cycling and environmental pressure groups, which attracted considerable support from the Bristol public and the scheme was soon frozen after a 9,500 strong petition was received.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.bristolcyclingcampaign.org.uk/campaign/bristolbathpath/|Save the Bristol &amp; Bath Railway Path|publisher= Bristol Cycling Campaign|title= Save the Bristol &amp; Bath Railway Path|date=December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; The sustainable transport charity [[Sustrans]] said the plan was the &quot;right idea, wrong route&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/7326059.stm|title=Rapid bus plan scheme is shelved|publisher=BBC News|date=2008-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; The West of England Partnership is still targeting a BRT scheme by 2013 along a different route.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.busandcoach.com/newspage.aspx?id=3713&amp;categoryid=0|Bristol BRT closer with £48m funding|publisher= Bus and Coach|title= Bristol BRT closer with £48m funding|date=2007-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==See also==
*[[Light Rail Transit Association]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{UK light rail}}

[[Category:Transport in Bristol]]
[[Category:Tram transport in England]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
