<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28055074" ns="0" title="National symbols of South Africa"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">Since unification in 1910, [[South Africa]] has used a range of '''[[National Symbols|national symbols]]''' to identify the country:  coats of arms, official seals, flags, national anthems, and floral, bird, animal, and other emblems.

==Coats of arms==
[[File:Coat of Arms of South Africa (1932-2000).svg|100px|right|Coat of arms 1910]]
* '''[[Coat of arms of South Africa|1910 coat of arms]]''' - granted by [[King George V]] in 1910, and used until 2000.&lt;ref name=nps&gt; Brownell, F.G. (1993).  ''National and Provincial Symbols''&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''[[Coat of arms of South Africa|2000 coat of arms]]''' - introduced by the [[Thabo Mbeki|Mbeki administration]] in 2000.&lt;ref name=ca&gt;''Government Gazette'' no 21131 (28 April 2000)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Seals==
* '''Great Seal of the Union''' - authorised by King George V in 1910, and used until 1937 on state documents signed by the [[Governor-General of South Africa|governor-general]].&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;
* '''Royal Great Seal of the Union''' - authorised by the Royal Executive Functions and Seals Act 1934, and used until 1961 on state documents signed by the monarch on the advice of the South African government.&lt;ref name=res&gt;Royal Executive Functions and Seals Act 1934&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Royal Signet of the Union''' - authorised by the Royal Executive Functions and Seals Act 1934, and used until 1961 on state documents signed by the monarch on the advice of the South African government.&lt;ref name=res/&gt;
* '''Governor-General's Great Seal''' - authorised by [[King George VI]] in 1937, and used until 1961 on state documents signed by the [[Governor-General of South Africa|governor-general]].&lt;ref name=lp&gt;''Government Gazette'' no 2533 (6 June 1938)&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Seal of the Republic''' - authorised by the Republic of South Africa Constitution Act 1961, and used on state documents signed by the [[President of South Africa|(state) president]].&lt;ref name=con1&gt;Republic of South Africa Constitution Acts 1961, 1983, 1993&lt;/ref&gt;  The use of the seal has not been a constitutional requirement since 1997,&lt;ref name=con2&gt;Republic of South Africa Constitution 1996&lt;/ref&gt; but its use continues nevertheless. 

==Flags==
===National===

* '''[[Flag of South Africa|National Flag of the Union]]''' - authorised by the Union Flags and Nationality Act 1927, and introduced in 1928.  Renamed the &quot;National Flag of the Republic&quot; in 1961,&lt;ref name=con3&gt;Republic of South Africa Constitution Act 1961&lt;/ref&gt; it was used until 1994.
* '''[[Flag of South Africa|National Flag]]''' - the current flag, introduced in 1994.

===Merchant ensign===
* '''[[Red Ensign]]''' defaced with the shield of the coat of arms - authorised by the [[Admiralty]] in 1910, for use on South African-registered merchant ships, and also used as an unofficial &quot;national flag&quot;.  From 1912, the shield was placed on a white disc.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;  The ensign was discontinued in 1960.&lt;ref name=msa&gt;Merchant Shipping Act 1951 w.e.f. 1 January 1960&lt;/ref&gt;
* Since 1960, the national flag has been used as the merchant ensign.&lt;ref name=msa/&gt;

===Civil ensign===
* '''[[Blue Ensign]]''' defaced with the shield of the coat of arms - authorised by the Admiralty in 1910, for use on South African government vessels.  Superseded by the National Flag of the Union.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;

===Head of state's flag===
* '''[[Union Jack]]''' defaced with the full coat of arms surrounded by acacia leaves and flowers - flown by the governor-general until 1931.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;
* '''Governor-General's flag''' - blue, displaying the royal crest between two ribands bearing the name of the country.  Used from 1931 to 1961.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;
* '''State President's flag (1)''' - blue, displaying the national coat of arms below the letters SP.  Used from 1961 to 1984.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;
* '''State President's flag (2)''' - orange, white, and blue triangles, displaying the national coat of arms below the letters SP.  Used from 1984 to 1994.&lt;ref name=nps/&gt;

==National Anthem==
* '''''God Save the King (Queen)''''' - used from 1910 to 1957.
* '''''[[Die Stem van Suid-Afrika]]''''' - used from 1938 to 1957 as joint anthem with ''God Save the King (Queen)'';  from 1957 to 1994 as the sole national anthem;  and from 1994 to 1997 as joint anthem with ''Nkosi sikelel' iAfrika''.
* '''''[[Nkosi Sikelel' iAfrika]]''''' - used from 1994 to 1997 as joint anthem with ''Die Stem''.
* '''''[[National Anthem of South Africa]]''''' - shortened versions of ''Nkosi sikelel' iAfrika'' and ''Die Stem'', with altered words, combined into a single anthem, and used since 1997.&lt;ref name=na&gt;''Government Gazette'' no 18341 (10 October 1997)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other symbols==
* [[National flower of South Africa|King Protea]]
* [[Blue Crane]]
* [[Springbok]]
* Yellowwood tree

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

* Brownell, F.G. (1993).  ''National and Provincial Symbols''.
* Burgers, A.P. (2008).  ''The South African Flag Book''.
* Pama, C. (1965).  ''Lions and Virgins''.

==See also==
* [[Coat of arms of South Africa]]
* [[Flag of South Africa]]
* [[List of South African flags]]
* [[National anthem of South Africa]]
* [[National flower of South Africa]]

==External links==
* [http://sahw.bravehost.com South African Heraldry Website]

[[Category:National symbols of South Africa]]
[[Category:National symbols by nation|South Africa]]
[[Category:South African culture]]  
[[Category:South African heraldry]]

[[af:Lys van Nasionale Simbole van Suid-Afrika]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
