<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2807519" ns="0" title="Australia at the 2002 Winter Olympics"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Olympics Australia
|games=2002 Winter
|competitors=27
|sports=
|flagbearer=[[Adrian Costa]] (opening)&lt;br&gt;[[Steven Bradbury]] (closing)  
|gold=2
|silver=0
|bronze=0
|total=2
|rank=15
}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Australia NOC symbol.png|framed|NOC symbol of Australia]] --&gt;

'''[[Australia]]''' competed at the '''[[2002 Winter Olympics]]''' in [[Salt Lake City, Utah|Salt Lake City]], [[United States]], winning two [[gold medal]]s the nation's best performance at the [[Winter Olympic Games|Winter Games]] prior to [[Vancouver]].

==Medalists==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
|-
!Medal
!Name
!Sport
!Event
|-
| {{gold medal}} || {{sortname|Alisa|Camplin}} || [[Freestyle skiing at the 2002 Winter Olympics|Freestyle skiing]] ||Women's aerials
|-
| {{gold medal}} || {{sortname|Steven|Bradbury}} || [[Short track speed skating at the 2002 Winter Olympics|Short track speed skating]] ||Men's 1000 m
|}

== Overview ==
Australia's first ever Winter Olympic gold, also the first such medal won by a competitor from any Southern Hemisphere country, was won by [[Steven Bradbury]] in the 1000m [[Short track speed skating at the 2002 Winter Olympics|short track speed skating]].  Well off the pace of the medal favourites, Bradbury was positioned at the rear in the semifinal, only to see his competitors crash into each other, allowing him through to the final.  Again well off the pace in the final all four other competitors crashed out at the final corner, leaving a shocked Bradbury to take the gold medal. Bradbury was also part of the 1994 relay team that won Australia's first Winter Olympics medal.

[[Alisa Camplin]], who hadn't won a world cup event before and was so nervous she didn't eat dinner the night before the final, won the second gold, in [[freestyle skiing at the 2002 Winter Olympics|aerial skiing]].  [[Jacqui Cooper]] was previously a favourite, but she injured herself before the competition.

[[Jenny Owens]] had a top 10 result finishing 9th in the Combined Downhill event. The second best performance by any Australian at an Olympic Games.
 
Australia competed in alpine skiing, figure skating, freestyle skiing, short-track speed skating and snowboarding. This was the fewest sports Australia had competed in since 1984. No Australian [[Cross-country skiing|cross-country skiers]] competed in the Olympics for the first time since 1976, and no bobsleigh sliders competed for the first time since Australia's debut in [[1988]]. Australian bobsleigh slider Will Alstergren said &quot;We also beat half the teams currently in Salt Lake City, but unfortunately we couldn't meet the very high standard of the AOC, the Australian Olympic Committee&quot;. Australian selection standards has also been listed as a factor for Australia not competing in cross-country skiing at Salt Lake City.

During the 2002 Winter Olympics, the Australian broadcaster, the [[Seven Network]], included in its coverage an irreverent talk show called [[The Dream with Roy and HG#The Ice Dream|The Ice Dream]], which interviewed several celebrities and promoted the [[Smiggin Holes 2010 Winter Olympic bid]]. Steven Bradbury and Alisa Camplin's triumphs were celebrated by [[Australia post]] issuing stamps of them, which followed on from them issuing stamps of Australian gold medallists at the [[2000 Summer Olympics|2000 Sydney Olympics]]. They were produced by high-speed offset stamp-printing, unlike the digitally produced 2000 stamps. Bradbury's stamp was issued on February 20, and Alisa's was issued on February 22, four days after their respective victories. Each received [[Australian dollar|A$]]20,000 for the use of their image. Steven Bradbury said “Should get me a car. I haven’t had a car for a long time.” and later described having a stamp issued as &quot;a great honour&quot;. Alisa was also delighted, saying “For us to be put in with the summer Olympians who had their stamps and the previous 39 sporting legends who’ve had their stamps is amazing.”

==Results==
===Alpine skiing===
{{details|Alpine skiing at the 2002 Winter Olympics}}
;Men
* Combined: Aaron Bear (DSQ), Craig Branch (DNC)
* Downhill: Craig Branch (45th/54), Aaron Bear (37th)
* Giant slalom: Bradley Wall (33rd/78)
* Slalom: Michael Dickson (DNF)
* Super-G: Craig Branch (27th/34), Aaron Bear (DSQ)

;Women
* Combined:[[Jenny Owens]] (9th), Alice Jones (12th), Rowena Bright (24th)
* Downhill: Alice Jones (27th), Jenny Owens (29th) &lt;!-- Source inconsistent on size of field --&gt;
* Giant slalom: Jeannette Korten (DSQ), Jenny Owens (DNF)
* Slalom: Jeannette Korten (25th/70), Rowena Bright (DNF), Kathrin Nikolussi (DNF), Zali Steggall (DNF)
* Super-G: Jenny Owens (29th/43), Alice Jones (DNF)

===Figure skating===
{{details|Figure skating at the 2002 Winter Olympics}}
* Men: [[Anthony Liu]] (10th/28)
* Women: [[Stephanie Zhang]] (25th/27)

===Freestyle skiing===
{{details|Freestyle skiing at the 2002 Winter Olympics}}
* Women's aerials: Alisa Camplin (1st/21 - gold), Lydia Ierodiaconou (8th), Jacqui Cooper (DNC - injured)
* Men's moguls: Adrian Costa (18th/30), Trennon Paynter (23rd)
* Women's moguls: Maria Despas (21st/29), Jane Sexton (25th), Manuela Berchtold (27th)

Alisa Camplin provided Australia with its second gold medal for the games.

===Short-track speed skating===
{{details|Short track speed skating at the 2002 Winter Olympics}}
* 500m: Steven Bradbury (14th/31), Andrew McNee (28th)
* 1000m: Steven Bradbury (1st/29 - gold), Mark McNee (15th)
* 1500m: Steven Bradbury (10th/29), Mark McNee (28th)
* 5000m relay: Australia (Steven Bradbury, Stephen Lee, Alex McEwan, Andrew McNee) (6th/7)

Steven Bradbury won Australia's and the Southern Hemisphere's first Winter Olympics gold medal in the 1000 metres event.

Richard Goerlitz also attended these games, but did not compete. &lt;!-- Maybe he was reserve for the relay --&gt;

===Snowboarding===
{{details|Snowboarding at the 2002 Winter Olympics}}
* Parallel giant slalom: Zeke Steggall (26th/32)

==See also==

*[[Australia at the Winter Olympics]]

==External links==
*[http://www.olympics.com.au/ Australia NOC]
*[http://www.owia.org/ Olympic Winter Institute of Australia]

== References ==

* &quot;The Compendium: Official Australian Olympic Statistics 1896-2002&quot; [[Australian Olympic Committee]] ISBN 0-7022-3425-7
* &quot;Steven Bradbury: Last Man Standing&quot; by Gary Smart and Steven Bradbury ISBN 0-9757287-8-4, 2005.
* [http://www.glenstephens.com/linnsMarch11-02.html Aussie golds in Winter games bring more instant stamps] by Glen Stephens. Linn's stamp news. March 11, 2002.
* &quot;Gold medallists get framed stamps&quot; [[Australian Olympic Committee]] February 25, 2002.
* [http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/olympics/2002/news/2002/02/18/murphy_camplin/ She comes from the land Down Under : Aussie aerialist Camplin captures gold in dramatic fashion]
* [http://www.ausport.gov.au/fulltext/2002/sportsf/s488161.asp The Sports Factor - interview with Will Alstergren]
* [http://www.hoppet.com.au/xc/xcfiles/slc/slc_index.htm XC Files: No Australian Cross Country Skiers...] February 7, 2002.

{{NOCin2002WinterOlympics}}

[[Category:Nations at the 2002 Winter Olympics]]
[[Category:Australia at the Olympics|2002]]

[[ko:2002년 동계 올림픽 오스트레일리아 선수단]]
[[hu:Ausztrália a 2002. évi téli olimpiai játékokon]]
[[nl:Australië op de Olympische Winterspelen 2002]]
[[no:Australia under Vinter-OL 2002]]
[[pl:Australia na Zimowych Igrzyskach Olimpijskich 2002]]
[[pt:Austrália nos Jogos Olímpicos de Inverno de 2002]]
[[ru:Австралия на зимних Олимпийских играх 2002]]
[[sv:Australien i olympiska vinterspelen 2002]]
[[th:ประเทศออสเตรเลียในโอลิมปิกฤดูหนาว 2002]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
