<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28132663" ns="0" title="List of Mahinda College alumni"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a list of notable '''Old Mahindians''', they being the alumni of [[Mahinda College]], [[Galle]], [[Sri Lanka]].
{{Expand list|date=July 2010}}

== Senior academics ==
* Professor Kapila Gunasekara - Vice Chancellor of the University of Vocational Technology - Former Vice Chancellor of the [[University of Peradeniya]] (2000-2006) &amp; Former Dean, Faculty of Agriculture, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka 
* Professor Harishchandra Abeygunawardena - Former Vice Chancellor of the [[University of Peradeniya]] (2006-2009)
* Professor Deshamanya [[Nandadasa Kodagoda]] - Former Vice Chancellor and former Dean of the Medical Faculty, [[University of Colombo]]
* Professor G.P. Samarawickrama - First Vice Chancellor, [[University of Ruhuna]], Sri Lanka
* Professor Emeritus M. B. Ariayapala – Former President, University of Colombo (1972 – 77), Served as Deans of the Faculties of Humanities and Arts, first Professor and Head of the Department of Sinhala, Former President - Ceylon Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society, Former President - All Ceylon Buddhist Congress 
* Professor S. D. Pathirana - Former Dean of the Faculty of Engineering, University of Peradeniya
* Professor P. L. Ariyananda - Former Dean, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ruhuna, Sri Lanka
* Professor D. Arampatta – Former Dean Faculty of Education, University of Colombo
* Professor O. A. Illeperuma - Senior Professor, University of Peradeniya
* Professor Upali Samarajeewa - Senior Professor, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Professor J.K.P. Ariyarathne - Senior Professor, [[University of Kelaniya]], Sri Lanka
* Professor Kapila Dahanayake - Senior Professor, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Professor Wijesuriya P. Dayawansa - Professor of Mathematics &amp; Statistics, [[Texas Tech University]], Texas,USA 
* Professor Daya Ahangama - Head of the Department of Agric Biology, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Professor N.T.S.Wijesekara - Professor, [[University of Moratuwa]], Sri Lanka (Also listed in Heads of government departments)
* Professor Athula B. Attygalle - Professor of Chemistry and Chemical Biology, [[Stevens Institute of Technology]], New Jersey, USA
*  Professor Jayadeva Thilakasiri - Professor emeritus of Sanskrit, University of Peradeniya,  President of the German Dharmaduta Society (GDS), Sri Lanka
* Professor Emeritus N.A. Jayawickrama - Professor and Head of the Department of Pali of the University of Peradeniya
* Professor Dharma de Silva - Professor, [[Wichita State University]], USA. - Founding Dean, Faculty of Management Studies at University of Sri Lanka &amp; Visiting Professor at the Postgraduate Institute of Management in Sri Lanka,Founder Chair~World Trade Council, Wichita, Kansas, USA http://www.wtc.wichita.edu/Project%20Activities.htm
* Professor Mrs Deemathie (Deema Danthanarayana) De Silva,Assistant Professor &amp; Director Student Support Services, Wichita State University, Wichita, Kansas, USA
* Professor P.K.S. Mahanama, Dean, Faculty of Architecture, University Of Moratuwa
* Professor David J. Kalupahana - Emeritus Professor of Philosophy at the University of Hawaii, U.S.A.
* Professor Kulathilaka Kumarasinghe - Senior Professor &amp; Dean, Faculty of Humanities, University of Kelaniya
* Professor Siripala Hettige, Senior Professor &amp; Former Dean, Faculty of Arts, University of Colombo
* Dr. Nihal Somaratne - Senior Lecturer, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka - Obtained 100 each in Pure Mathematics, Applied Mathematics &amp; Physics in 1974 [[GCE Advanced Level in Sri Lanka|G.C.E A/L]]
* Dr. P.A. Jayantha – Dean, Faculty of Science, University of Ruhuna
* Dr. M. H. Jayantha Ariyaratne - Senior Lecturer &amp; Head of the Department of Surgery, Senior Student Councellor, University of Kelaniya
* Dr. Lakshman Watawana - Senior lecturer, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Dr. Kithsiri Liyanage - University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka - Former Dean of the Engineering Faculty, [[University of Ruhuna]]
* Dr  K.K.Liyanage - Former Senior Lecturer,University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Dr. J.J. Wijetunge - Senior Lecturer, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* R. D. A. Gunasekara -  University of Ruhuna, Sri Lanka
* Dr. Kurukulasooriya -  UN Consultant, Former Lecturer in [[Open University of Sri Lanka]] 
* Dr  K.A.S Yapa  - Lecturer in [[Central University of Ecuador]]
* Dr. Ranjith Obeysekera - Former Lecturer, University of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Dr. V. Edirisinghe, Former Head &amp; Senior Lecturer of the Department of Sociology &amp; Student Counselor of the University of Colombo
* Dr. Daya Rohana Athukorala - Senior Lecturer &amp; Head, Department of Humanities, Faculty of Education, University of Colombo.
* Dr. Ms Sunethra Karunaratne, Senior Lecturer, University Of Peradeniya, Sri Lanka
* Dr. W.A.A. Wijayasiri - Senior Lecturer, Faculty of Medicine, University of Ruhuna, Sri Lanka

== Ministers and legislators ==
* Dr. S.A. Wickramasinghe - Father of [[Communist_Party_of_Sri_Lanka|Sri Lankan Communist Movement]]
* Hon. Henry Woodward Amarasuriya - Former cabinet minister of Commerce &amp; Trade and former member of parliament - Founder member of [[United National Party]] - Philanthropist 
* Hon. Thomas Amarasuriya, [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]] - Former Chairman of the Senate
* Hon. D.S.Gunasekera - Former  Minister of Labour and member of parliament Udugama &amp; Habaraduwa 
* Hon. I.A.Cadar - Former Member of Parliament for Beruwala and The Deputy speaker of the House of Parliament
* Hon. Justin Wijayawardhena – Member of Parliament for Matara (1960) - Founder member of the United National Party
* Hon. Sirisena Hettige - Former member of Parliament for Hakmana
* Hon. W.D.S.Abeygunawardane - Former Member of Parliament for Galle ( Who defeated then Prime Minister of Ceylon)
* Hon. S.S. Kulathilake - Former Minister of Cultural Affairs
* Hon. Ananda Kularathne - Former Member of Parliament for Hakmana and Deputy Minister
* Hon. Albert de Silva - Former Member of Parliament and former Mayor of Galle
* Hon. P. Gamini Ariyatilake – Former Member of Parliament for Maskeliya electorate (in 1970)
* Hon. Rupa Karunathilake - Former Minister &amp; Member of Parliament for Benthara-Elpitiya
* Hon. Dayananda Wickramasinghe – Former Minister &amp; Member of Parliament for Akuresssa
* Hon. [[Lakshman Yapa Abeywardena]] - Current Minister of Mass Media and Information
* Hon. [[Vajira Abeywardena]] - Former Cabinet Minister (Public Administration) of Sri Lanka
* Hon. [[Lionel Premasiri]] - Former Minister (Social Services) of Sri Lanka and former Mayor of Galle
* Hon. Nishantha Muthuhettigama - Current Member of Parliament
* Hon. Manusha Nanayakkara - Current Member of Parliament

==Prelates==
* Most Venerable [[Madihe Pannaseeha Thero]] - Former head of [[Amarapura Nikaya|Amarapura Sect]] 
* Venerable [[Katukurunde Nanananda Thera]] - Buddhist scholar and researcher

== Members of the defence services ==
* Major General Lakshman Wijayaratne (Lucky Wijayaratne) RWP, RSP  † - Former Commander of 22 Brigade in Trincomalee, [[Sri Lanka Army]]
* Admiral Deshamanya [[Basil Gunasekara|D. Basil Gunasekara]] - Former [[Commander of the Navy (Sri Lanka)|Navy Commander of Sri Lanka]]
* SDIG Bodhi Liyanage - First Commandant of the [[Special Task Force]], [[Sri Lanka Police]]
* Rear Admiral Ivan Kariyawasam, USP - Former Director General, Naval Engineering, Sri Lanka Navy
* SSP Neville Guruge - Sri Lanka Police
* SSP J.C.K Nanayakkara - [[Special Task Force]]
* Brigadier Lasantha Wickremasuriya, Division Commander, SLA, Killinochchiya.
* Brigadier Mahinda Mudalige, Commander - SAL, Batticaloa.
* SP Chandana Galppaththi, Negombo division, Sri Lanka Police.
* Group Captain Ananda Guruge, Defence Attach, Sri Lankan Embassy - Jakarta, Indonesia. 
* Lieutenant Colonel Dayamal Jayasooriya - Commander, 661 Brigade in Poonarine, [[Sri Lanka Army]]
* Lieutenant D.G.A. Vitharana - [[Sri Lanka Navy]]
* Squadron Leader Monath Perera (Late) - [[No. 10 Squadron SLAF|Kfir Squadron]], [[Sri Lanka Air Force]]
* Lieutenant BD Wijesekara, Sri Lanka Navy, SLN dockyard, Trincomalee

== Senior civil servants and heads of government departments ==
* T.H.Ananda Lacille de Silva (Director Administration - Sri Lanka Parliament)
* Palitha Kumarasinghe  - President's Counsel and Member of Public Service Commission
* Professor M T M Jiffry - Vice Chairman of the University Grants Commission, Senior Professor of Physiology -University of Sri Jayewardenepura, Member of Learnt and Reconciliation’ Commission
* Ananda Wijesekera – President’s Counsel
* Senerath Wije Goonewardene - Permanent Secretary to the Ministry of Social Services, Government Agent, Hambantota (1970). Director of Social Services and Commissioner of Workmen's Compensation (1973)
* S.H.C.de Silva – Former Additional Director of Irrigation Department, Consultant to the Department of Irrigation, Director - Water Resources Board and Director of ICTAD - Ex-President of the Institute of Engineers Sri Lanka (IESL)
* Lal Kumara Gamage - Head of Chancery, Embassy of Sri Lanka in Russia 
* Lilak Obaysekara - Director General,  Department of Technical Education
* Ivan de Silva - Secretary, Ministry of Irrigation &amp; Water Management, Director General, Mahaweli Authority
* Professor N.T.S.Wijesekara - Former Chairman of the Geological Survey and Mines Bureau (GSMB), Sri Lanka 
* P.P. Wijesekara - General Manager,  Sri Lanka Railway
* Vincent Panditha - Former Secretary, Ministry of Textile, Ex General Manager, Sri Lanka Broadcasting Corporation, 1st Assistant Director of Department of Cultural Affairs (1956)
* Udeni Wickremasinghe, Addl. Secretary- Misinstry of Defence (Technical)
* Dr. W. G. Weeraratne - Editor-in-Chief of the Encyclopaedia of Buddhism
* Dr. Chitral Ambewatte, Director General, Dept. of Technical Education &amp; Training
* Kapila Gamage, Chairman, Condominium Management Authority.
* B.N.I.F.A. Wickramasooriya - General Manager , Ceylon Electricity Board
* Lalitha Jayasekara, Kobbekaduwa Agrarian Reaserch &amp; Training Institute.
* P.U. Gunasinghe - Former Deputy General Manager, National Water Supply &amp; Drainage Board
* Aravinda Devasurendra – Asst. General Manager,  Ceylon Electricity Board
* Ranjith Devasurendra - Deputy General Manager, National Water Supply &amp; Drainage Board
* Nalin Wickramatunga – Deputy General Manager, National Water Supply &amp; Drainage Board
* Dayananda Kariyawasam - Director General, Department of Wildlife and Conservation
* Mali Piyasena - Deputy Director, Sri Lanka Customs
* Dr. K.T.W. Sumanasuriya – Ex Commissioner of Examinations
* Neville Guruge - Ex-Director, Investigations of Bribery Commission, Ex-Senior Superintendent of Police
* Deshamanya T.G.Jayasinghe – Ex Secretary, Finance Commission of Sri Lanka, Ex Chairman, Tertiary and Vocational Education Commission
* Dr. Dudley Gunasekera – Former Chairman of Paranthan Chemical Corporation, Ex Assistant Commissioner of Labour, Ex President of the All Ceylon Buddhist Congress
* Eric. J. de. Silva - Former Secretary to the Ministry of Education, Former Director  of  Academy of Administrative Studies (1972 – 1973) &amp; Sri Lanka Institute of  Development Administration (SLIDA)(1988 - 1990)

== Sportsmen and sports administrators  ==
* Douglas Dias-Jayasinha - Formerly of CAS , All Ceylon Cricketer - First cricketer from the Southern Province to don the All-Ceylon cap in 1937 - Selector for the Board of Control for Cricket in Sri Lanka from 1961-1973. For the ten years of 1963 to 1973, he was the chairman of the selection committee. 
* W. B. Bennett - Guinness world record holder for taking 10 victims in an innings as a wicket keeper (six stumped and four caught)
* Somasiri Ambawatte - Best all round performance in the Mahinda - Richmond Cricket history ( 10-44, 5-63 &amp; 103* in 1953) 
* Kosala Sahabandu - Former Athlete - Gold medalist at the [[1974 Asian Games]]
* [[Stanley de Silva|D. L. S. De Silva]] - Former Sri Lankan Cricketer
* [[Somachandra de Silva|D. S. de Silva]] - Chief of Sri Lanka Cricket &amp; the Chairman of the  Interim Committee - Former Sri Lankan Test cricketer and Captain
* [[Athula Samarasekera]] - Former Test Cricketer
* [[Jayananda Warnaweera]] - Former Test Cricketer and current ground manager of the [[Galle International Stadium]]
* Dileepa Wickramasinghe - Former Sri Lankan Cricketer and former member of the Cricket selection committee
* [[Marvan Atapattu]] - Former Test Cricketer &amp; Captain of Sri Lanka
* [[Upul Chandana]] - Former Test Cricketer
* [[Lasith Malinga]] - Sri Lankan Cricketer - World Record Holder for 4 wickets in 4 balls in an ODI

==Writers, poets, musicians and artists ==
* Professor [[Siri Gunasinghe]] - Premier Sinhalese poet and novelist
* Professor Vinee Vitharana - Writer and literary critic
* Dr. Lionel Edirisinghe - Founder of the University of Visual and Performing Art - First Sri Lankan scholar of Bhathkande University of India
* Jinidasa Vijayatunga (1903-89) - Author of the world famous book named “Grass for My Feet” (1935) – (He was one of the first Ceylonese writers to convey the essence of the island to the world and helped forge the identity of Ceylonese English literature.)
* Dr.[[Gunadasa Amarasekera]] - Prominent Sinhala writer, poet, and essayist &amp; one of the founding fathers of the Peradeniya school of literary tradition of modern Sri Lankan literature
* A.G.S. Kariyawasam - Author - Editor in Encyclopedia of Buddhism &amp; Buddhist Publication Society - Broadcaster of Radio Ceylon 
* [[Dhamma Jagoda]] - Play director and actor
* Justin Wijayawardhena - Writer, Novelist &amp; Translator of Russian novels ( Also listed in Legislators) 
* [[Vimukthi Jayasundara]] – An Award Winning Film Director ( First Sri Lankan to win [[Caméra d'Or]] awrad at the Cannes Film Festival)
* Kithsiri Nimal Shantha - Lyricist ( Also listed in Journalists) 
* G.W.Surendra – Actor
* Buddhi Wickrama - Actor
* Gamini G. Punchihewa - Veteran author and journalist
* Upasena Gunawardene - Veteran artist
* Thilak Palliyaguruge - Veteran architect &amp; artist
* Atula Siriwardane - Comic Book Artist
* Deepananda kudahetty -Veteran Musician- Sangeetha visharada ( Lucknow - India )Jazz &amp; Classical concert pianist ABRSM -London.

== Senior journalists and media personalities== 
* Edwin Ariyadasa - Famous Journalist
* D.B. Dhanapala - Pioneer of Newspaper Journalism in Sri Lanka
* Sundara Nihathamani  De Mel - Main Editor, Lakmiba Newspaper
* Kithsiri Nimal Shantha - Former Editor, Lakmiba Newspaper 
* Manusha Nanayakkara – TV Presenter - News Anchor,  Swarnawahini, Rupavahini ( Also listed in Legislators)
* Vinnie Hettigoda - Journalist &amp; Cartoonist
* Sanath Rohana Wickramasinghe -Creative Director, Media Consultant, Freelance Journalist
* Anura Madhawa Jayasekara-Media Consultant,TeleDrama Director/Producer
* Ashoka Jayathunga-Journalist, Lankadeepa Newspaper 
* Ramesh Warallegama – Journalist, Lakbima
* Prabath Kahaduwaarachchi – Derana, Swarnawahini
* Uvindu Illeperuma – Lakbima (English)
* Buddika Wickramadara - ITN
* Gayan Chinthaka Abeysinghe – Manager – News and Current Affairs -  ITN, Lakhanda
* Sajeewa Wijeweera – Executive Producer, Sirasa TV – Managing Director, Mihinro (Pvt) Ltd. - Freelance journalist &amp; Professional Wedding Photographer
* Madhawa Ganegoda – Senior Supervision Producer and  Presenter, TVDerana
* Sanjaya Nallaperuma – Journalist, Lakbima

== Industrialists and corporate executives ==
* Dr.  Sena Yaddehige - Chairman of [http://www.arpico.com/ Richard Pieris] and [http://www.asianalliance.lk/ Asian Alliance]

* Jayantha Karunaratne - Managing Director, [http://www.impratea.com/ Imperial Tea Exporters (Pvt) Limited]
* I. W. Senanayake – Chairman, [http://www.sampath.lk/ Sampath Bank]/IWS Holdings
* Jayantha Wimalagooneratne - Chairman, George Stuerts Group of Companies.
* Mahinda Rajapaksha - Director &amp; Chartered Engineer, DSI Group of Companies.
* Chandra Lal de Alwis - Chairman, Sri Lanka Chamber of Commerce.
* Nimal Malindu Pathirana - Southern Group of Companies. 
* Raja Nanayakkara - Nanayakkara Earth Movers.
* Ranjith Samaranayake - Director, Sampath Bank PLC
* U K Thilak de Silva - Managing Director, Laugfs Group of Companies.
* Deshabandu Albert Edirisinghe (now Ven. Ganegama Siri Devamittha Thero) – Philanthropist, Ex-Consul-General of the Kingdom of Nepal, Past President of World Buddhist Organization,Founder of Albert Edirisinghe Opticians &amp; the Vision House, Colombo
* Deshabandu W.A. Wimaladharma - Proprietor of &quot;Wimaladharma Brothers”, Colombo
* Takura Gunasinghe - Director/General Manager, Sun-up Laugfs Super Markets.
* Chandraratne Liyanage - Director, Ceylon Breweries Ltd.
* Kumar Samarasinghe - Diretor-Sales, Singer Sri Lanka,
* Punya Arambewela - Marketing Director at Lanka Property Sales &amp; Marketing (Pvt) Ltd. - Director, Business Insights &amp; Solutions (Pvt) Ltd.
* Hasitha Dissanayake - Director, [http://www.impexconsultants.net/ IMPEX Consultants]
* Chandimal Vithange – Creative Director, ICONN media ,Sera Idea Creation – Director Programme

== Medicine ==
* Dr. Bandula Wijay (Wijayarathna) - Inventor of Angioplasty Balloon Catheters &amp; Cardiac Stents
* Professor Saman Warnakulasuriya, [[Order of the British Empire|OBE]] - Professor  &amp; Head of Oral Medicine, [[King's College, University of London]], U.K. (Famous researcher in oral cancer)
* Dr. Anil Jasinghe - Director, South Colombo Teaching Hospital, Kalubowila
* Professor Saman Wimalasundara - Eye specialist and Head &amp; Professor of Community Medicine Dept., Faculty of Medicine, University of Ruhuna, Sri Lanka
* Dr. Namal Gamage - Famous Consultant Cardiothoracic Surgeon, Teaching Hospital, Karapitiya
* Dr. W.A. Bernard De Silva - Former Director of Health
* Dr. W.G. Wimaladharma - Eminent Dental Surgeon in Sri Lanka
* Dr. Tharaka Kusaladarama - Eye specialist, Teaching Hospital - Karapitiya
* Dr. M.M.A.J. Kumara – Head, Surgery Dept. Medical Faculty, Ruhuna - Consultant Surgeon
* Dr. Vasantha Devasiri - Senior Lecturer, University of Ruhuna, Consultant Pediatrician
* Dr. Ananda Wijewickrema, Consultant physician, Mulleriyawa Hospital.  
* Dr. M.B. de Silva Nanayakkara - Consultant Psychiatrist, National Health Service in Watford in North West London, U.K.
* Dr. Saman Nanayakkara, Consultant VOG, Nagoda Hospital, Kalutara.
* Dr. Laksiri Waidyaratne, Consultant JMO, Matale Hospital.
* Dr. Himashi Kularatne, Consutant Neuro Surgeon, National Hospital.
* Dr. M.M. Janapriya, Visiting Consultant Surgeon, National Hospital, Colombo
* Dr. Prasantha Gange, Consultant Obstetrician &amp; Gynecologist
* Dr. Dilshan Munidasa, Consultant Orthopedic Surgeon
* Dr. Rukshan Sooriyarachchi, Consultant Orthopedic Surgeon, Karapitiya Teaching Hospital, Galle
* Dr. Nithya S Jayawickrama Former Conultant Obstetrician &amp; Gynaecologist, Glan Hefran NHS Trust UK. Presently Senior Consultant at Lanka Hospitals, Colombo 5

==Judges==
*Hon. Justice Dr. L. M. Jayaratne - Former eminent Supreme Court Judge in Sri Lanka, scholar, researcher and former Supreme Court Judge (Puisne Judge) in Fiji - Former Governor of the Southern Province 

==Diplomats==
* Deshabandu D. P. Wijenarayana - Ambassador of Sri Lanka to the Union of Myanmar (1982-1986) - Former Mayor of Galle
* [[Rupa Karunathilake]] - Former Ambassador of Sri Lanka to the Netherlands (2002-2004)

==Educationalists==
* Henry Woodward Amarasuriya - Co-founder of Vidyaloka College, Galle - General Manager Buddhist Schools - Donated Amaragiri Walauwa in Unawatuna for a Teachers Training College, also donated Wilpita Watta at Akuressa to Mahinda College and later this land was acquired by the government and built the &quot;Nilwala National College of Education&quot;  &amp; gifted a library building to [[Visakha Vidyalaya]].
* Albert Dias Jayasinha - Former Headmaster of Mahind College (1917 - 1936)
* Edgar Albert Wijesuriya - Former principal of Mahinda College from 1932 - 1962
* Mrs. R. N. Amarasinghe - Former Principal, Visakha Vidyalaya,Colombo
* Mrs. S. Wijetunghe - Former Provincial Director of Education, Former Principal, Sanghamittha College,Galle
* Dharama Gunasinghe - Former Principal, Nalanda College,Colombo (1982-1990)
* A.M. Liyanage - Former Principal, [[Rahula College]], Matara
* J de S Jayasinghe - Former Head Master, [[St. Thomas' College, Guruthalawa]] 
* Munidasa Wickramasinghe - Former Principal of Mahinda College &amp; Former Director Of Education, Matara
* C.K. Weidyaratne - Former Principal of Mahinda College &amp; Thelijjawila Central College
* D.D. Jayasundara - Former Principal of Mahinda College &amp; Additional Director of Education
* Evan Ediriwira - First Principal of Moratu Vidyalaya, founder Principal of Gamini College, Bentota, Former Principal of the Central School (Sitawake Rajasingha Maha Vidyalaya), Hanwella, Central College, Passara &amp; Central College (Sumangala Vidyalaya), Hikkaduwa.
* L.W.N. Labutale – Former Director of Education, North Central Province, Served as the Principal of the Central College of Anuradhapura,  the first Buddhist Principal of [[Kingswood College, Kandy]] &amp; finally at the Poramadulla Central College
* Chamath Denuwan Wijehewa- Early Childhood Care Specialist , Former Technical advisor for [http://www.moe.gov.lk/ Ministry of Education] -Southern Province
* S. Illeperuma - Deputy Principal, Advanced Level, [[Royal College, Colombo]]

==Other prominent alumni==
* Dr. [[A. T. Ariyaratne]] - Founder and president of the [[Sarvodaya Shramadana Movement]] in Sri Lanka - Peace activist
* Dr. [[A. P. de Zoysa]] - Social Reformer and Buddhist Scholar
* Henry Mahendrapala Amarasuriya - Founder of Sinhala Jatiya Newspaper
* Dr. Saman Weerasinghe - Advisor to H.E. the President Mahinda Rajapaksa
* Dr. H. L. K. Caldera - Former mayor of [[Anuradhapura]]
* Sanath Rohana Wickramasinghe - Veteran Stamp Designer of Sri Lanka Post

[[Category:Sri Lanka-related lists]]
[[Category:Lists of Sri Lankan people by school affiliation|Mahinda College]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
