<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28249265" ns="0" title="Bitcoin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Copy edit|date=June 2011}}
{{technical|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox software
| name = Bitcoin
| title = Bitcoin
| logo = [[File:Bitcoin logo.svg|200px]]
| screenshot = [[File:Bitcoin-0.3.23-ubuntu.png|300px]]
| caption = The official Bitcoin client
| collapsible =
| author =
| developer = Satoshi Nakamoto (inactive, possibly a pseudonym)&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot; /&gt;, [[Con Kolivas]], Gavin Andresen, [[Amir Taaki]], [[Jeff Garzik]], David Francois, Luke Dashjr, Pavel Karoukin, Nils Schneider, John Tobey, Daniel Folkinshteyn, Patrick McFarland, Patrick Strateman, Matt Corallo, Pieter Wuille, and others
| maintainer = Gavin Andresen
| released = {{Start date|2009|01|09}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mail-archive.com/cryptography@metzdowd.com/msg10142.html Bitcoin version 0.1 release date]&lt;/ref&gt;
| discontinued =
| latest release version =
| latest release date =
| latest preview version = 0.5.0 {{Start date and age|2011|11|21}}
| latest preview date = &lt;!-- {{Start date and age|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| frequently updated = &lt;!-- DO NOT include this parameter unless you know what it does --&gt;
| programming language = [[C++]]
| operating system = Windows, [[GNU Project|GNU]]/[[Linux]], Mac OS X, FreeBSD
| platform =
| language = Dutch, English, French, Italian, German, Portuguese, Russian and Spanish.
| status = Beta
| genre = [[Electronic money]]
| license = [[MIT License]] ([[Open-source software|open-source]])
| website = {{URL|http://www.bitcoin.org/}}
}}
'''Bitcoin''' is a decentralized, [[peer-to-peer]] network over which users make transactions that are tracked and verified through this network. The word Bitcoin also refers to the [[Electronic money|digital currency]] implemented as the currency medium for user transactions over this network. In addition, the name Bitcoin refers to the client software allowing access to this network for conducting transactions.

To track and verify user transactions Bitcoin implements a type of triple-entry accounting system. To maintain a uniform transaction record in this accounting system a &quot;proof-of-work&quot; computer-code algorithm is used as the basis for a user-transaction journaling process that allows a large group of computers across the network to agree on a single consistent currency transaction account ledger without centralized coordination. The design allows the transaction process to work over differences in timing, a varying number of participants, even varying levels of honesty, and differences in perspective among the individual participants.

On January 3rd 2009 the first Bitcoins were generated,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blockexplorer.com/block/000000000019d6689c085ae165831e934ff763ae46a2a6c172b3f1b60a8ce26f|title=Block 0 - Bitcoin Block Explorer}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in the same month Bitcoin was released as [[open-source software]] written in [[C++]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mail-archive.com/cryptography@metzdowd.com/msg10142.html|title=Bitcoin v0.1 released}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sourceforge.net/news/?group_id=244765|title=SourceForge.net: Bitcoin}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Network==
The Bitcoin network allows for an amount specified in Bitcoin(s) to be transferred between Bitcoin addresses using [[digital signature]]s. All data necessary to make any valid transaction is recorded in a publicly [[distributed database]] called the ''block chain''. The block chain is built using a [[proof-of-work system]] that prevents [[double-spending]] and confirms transactions. Bitcoin transactions requires no centralized payment processing, and consequently are made at low cost.&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Davis|first=Joshua|title=The Crypto-Currency|url=http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2011/10/10/111010fa_fact_davis|accessdate=11 October 2011|newspaper=[[The New Yorker]]|date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Addresses===
Bitcoin is based on [[public-key cryptography]] using [[Elliptic Curve DSA]]&lt;ref&gt;https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/ECDSA, Dec 2011&lt;/ref&gt;. Any user in the Bitcoin network has a [[digital wallet]] containing a number of cryptographic [[keypair]]s. The wallet's public keys are transformed into Bitcoin ''addresses'', which act as the ''receiving'' endpoints for all payments. Addresses in human-readable form appear as strings of numbers and letters around 33 characters in length, always beginning with the digit 1, as in the example of &lt;!-- Do not change this intentionally invalid address. Address chosen by consensus (see talk page), it is simply SHA1(&quot;Bitcoin&quot;) in base58 with a checksum added that's off by one digit --&gt;''175tWpb8K1S7NmH4Zx6rewF9WQrcZv245W''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Address|title=Bitcoin documentation on addresses}}&lt;/ref&gt; The wallet's private keys are used to authorize transactions from that user's wallet.

===Transactions===
Any Bitcoin contains its current owner's wallet address. Users can create as many wallets as they wish. When a bitcoin belonging to user ''A'' is transferred to user ''B'', then ''A''’s ownership over that bitcoin is relinquished by adding ''B''’s address to it and signing the result with the private key that is associated with ''A''’s address.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Transactions |title=Transactions - Bitcoin |publisher=En.bitcoin.it |date=2011-06-16 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because of the asymmetric cryptographic method, nobody else can grant this signature, and the private key cannot be determined based on the signed bitcoin.&lt;ref group=&quot;Notes&quot;&gt;This statement is made on the assumption that it is infeasible to [[brute-force attack|brute force]] the keys, and that no [[side channel attack]] is possible either.&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting bitcoin is broadcast in a message, the ''transaction'', on the peer-to-peer network. The rest of the network nodes validate the cryptographic signatures and the amounts of the transaction before accepting it.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars-06-08-11&quot;/&gt;

===Confirmations===
[[File:Blockchain.svg|thumb|right|The main chain (black) consists of the longest series of blocks from the genesis block (green) to the current block. Orphan blocks (grey) exist outside of the main chain.]]
To prevent [[double-spending]], the network implements what Nakamoto describes as a ''peer-to-peer distributed timestamp server'', which assigns sequential identifiers to each transaction, which are then hardened against modification using the idea of chained [[proof of work|proofs of work]] (shown in the Bitcoin client as ''confirmations''). In his white paper, Nakamoto wrote: &quot;we propose a solution to the double-spending problem using a peer-to-peer distributed timestamp server to generate computational proof of the chronological order of transactions.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;whitepaper&quot; /&gt;

Whenever a transaction is made, it is immediately labeled as ''unconfirmed''. The confirmation status is reflective of the likelihood that the transaction could be successfully reversed in the event of a deliberate attempt to do so. Any transaction broadcast to other nodes does not become ''confirmed'' until it has been acknowledged in a collectively maintained timestamped-list of all known transactions, the ''block chain''.

===Target===
Every ''generating'' node in the Bitcoin network collects all the unacknowledged transactions it knows of in a file called a ''block'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Block_hashing_algorithm |title=Bitcoin documentation on the block hashing algorithm }}&lt;/ref&gt; which also contains a reference to the previous valid block known to that node. It then appends a [[Cryptographic nonce|nonce]] value to this previous block and computes the [[SHA-256]] [[Cryptographic hash function|cryptographic hash]] of the block and the appended nonce value. The node repeats this process until it adds a nonce that allows for the generation of a hash with a value lower than a specified ''target''. Because the hash function is not reversible, finding such a nonce is hard and requires on average a predictable amount of [[Brute-force search|repetitious trial and error]]. When a node finds such a solution, it announces it to the rest of the network. Peers receiving the new solved block validate it by computing the hash and checking that it really starts with the given number of zero bits (i.e., that the hash is within the target). Then they accept it and add it to the chain.

===Block chain===
When a transaction is first acknowledged in a block, it receives one confirmation. The transaction itself is only acknowledged once, but blocks themselves are acknowledged repeatedly as time passes and the chain grows. Each time that first block is acknowledged by future blocks, the transaction is considered to have received another confirmation. After six confirmations, the Bitcoin client switches from showing &quot;unconfirmed&quot; to &quot;confirmed&quot;. Although a transaction could be considered &quot;confirmed&quot; after a single confirmation, the client avoids reporting it as such until several further confirmations to ensure that it is overwhelmingly likely that the transactions are part of the main block chain rather than an ''orphaned'' one, and more importantly, practically impossible to reverse.

Eventually, the block chain contains the cryptographic ownership history of all coins from their creator-address to their current owner-address.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbe&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blockexplorer.com/ |title=Bitcoin Block Explorer }}&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, if a user attempts to reuse coins he already spent, the network rejects the transaction.

The whole history of transactions must be stored inside the block chain, which grows constantly as new records are added and never removed. Nakamoto conceived that as the database became larger, applications for Bitcoin without the entire database on each user's computer would be desirable. To enable this, a [[Merkle tree]] is used to organize the transaction records in such a way that a future Bitcoin client can locally delete portions of its own database it knows it will never need, such as earlier transaction records of bitcoins that have changed ownership multiple times, while keeping the cryptographic integrity of the remaining database intact. Some users will only need the portion of the block chain that pertains to the coins they own or might receive in the future. At the present time however, all users of the Bitcoin software receive the entire database over the peer-to-peer network after running the software the first time.

===Difficulty===
&lt;!-- Because block solutions arise out of an independent random process, block creation by the Bitcoin network can be described as a [[Poisson process]]. --&gt;Every 2016 blocks, the Bitcoin protocol reassigns the ''target''. As the target changes, the result is a change in the ''difficulty'' of finding a suitable nonce. The difficulty is adjusted such that the distribution mean is ''λ''&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;2016 blocks per two weeks, so that there are roughly ten minutes between the creation of new blocks on average (the wait times between events in a Poisson process follow an [[exponential distribution]]). The difficulty updates happen every 2016 blocks. The difficulty is set to the value that would have most likely caused the prior 2016 blocks to take two weeks to complete, given the same computational effort (according to the timestamps recorded in the blocks).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Difficulty|title=Bitcoin documentation on difficulty|accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; All nodes perform and enforce the same difficulty calculation.

{{anchor|Bitcoin mining}}
In addition to the pending transactions confirmed in the block, a generating node adds a &quot;generate&quot; transaction, which awards new bitcoins to the operator of the node that generated the block. The payout of this generated transaction is set according to the inflation schedule programmed into the protocol. The process of solving blocks is often referred to as ''mining'', as in [[gold mining]], in reference to the coins brought into existence by the generate transactions.&lt;ref name=&quot;whitepaper&quot;/&gt; The &quot;miner&quot; that generates a block also receives the surplus from any transactions that have input value in excess of the output value, effectively a transaction fee that provides an incentive to give a transaction priority for faster confirmation.

The proof-of-work problems are especially suitable to [[Graphics processing unit|GPUs]] and specialized hardware. Because of the growing computing power behind the system driving the difficulty to high levels, individual contributors with typical CPUs are no longer likely to solve a block on their own but can still receive small portion of the bitcoins generated in a new block by contributing their processing power to a mining pool.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Pooled_mining|title=Bitcoin Wiki: Pooled mining|accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This increased difficulty makes it cost prohibitive for an attacker to perform double-spending attacks so it is beneficial to the system.

The number of Bitcoins created per block is never more than 50&amp;nbsp;BTC, and the awards are programmed to decrease over time towards zero, such that no more than 21 million will ever exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;lwn&quot; /&gt; As this payout decreases, the motive for users to run block-generating nodes is expected to change to earning [[#Transaction fees|transaction fees]], funding from supporting auxiliary block chains,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forum.bitcoin.org/index.php?topic=7219.0|title=Bitcoin forum thread on auxiliary block chains|accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and simply to improve the security of the public Bitcoin infrastructure they depend on.

====Covert &quot;mining&quot;====
In June 2011, [[Symantec]] warned about the possibility of [[botnet]]s engaging in covert &quot;mining&quot; of bitcoins (unauthorized use of computer resources to generate bitcoins),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.symantec.com/connect/blogs/bitcoin-botnet-mining&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.zdnet.com/blog/security/researchers-find-malware-rigged-with-bitcoin-miner/8934&lt;/ref&gt; consuming computing cycles, using extra electricity and possibly increasing the temperature of the computer. Later that month, an employee of the [[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] was caught after using the company's servers to generate bitcoins without permission.&lt;ref&gt;http://thenextweb.com/au/2011/06/23/abc-employee-caught-mining-for-bitcoins-on-company-servers/&lt;/ref&gt; Some malware also uses the [[parallel computing|parallel processing]] capabilities of the [[GPU]]s built into many modern-day [[video card]]s.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/08/16/gpu_bitcoin_brute_forcing/&lt;/ref&gt; In mid August 2011, bitcoin miner botnets were found&lt;ref&gt;http://www.infosecurity-magazine.com/view/20211/researcher-discovers-distributed-bitcoin-cracking-trojan-malware/&lt;/ref&gt;; trojans infecting Mac OS X have also been uncovered.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.techworld.com.au/article/405849/mac_os_x_trojan_steals_processing_power_produce_bitcoins&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transaction fees===
Miners have no obligation to include transactions in the blocks they try to solve. A transaction fee can be associated with any transaction, giving miners an incentive to put the transaction in a block, as miners collect the transaction fees associated with all transactions included in blocks they solve. Very small transactions, or those that use relatively new coins, have low &quot;priority&quot; and may be assessed a transaction fee to reduce spam. As of version 0.3.23 of the official bitcoin client, the minimum transaction fee for low priority transactions is 0.0005 BTC.

===Anonymity===
Because transactions are broadcast to the entire network, they are inherently public. Unlike regular banking, which preserves customer privacy by keeping ''transaction records'' private, transactional anonymity is accomplished in Bitcoin by keeping the ''ownership'' of addresses private, while at the same time publishing all transactions. As an example, if Alice sends 123.45 BTC to Bob, a public record is created that allows anyone to see that 123.45 was sent from one address to another. However, unless Alice or Bob make their ownership of these addresses publicly known in some way, it is difficult for anyone else to connect the transaction with them. However, if an address is connected to a user at any point it can be possible to follow back a series of transactions because each participant likely knows who paid them and may disclose that information on request or under duress.&lt;ref name=&quot;An Analysis of Anonymity in the Bitcoin System&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Anonymity|title=Bitcoin documentation on anonymity}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,,15276051,00.html|title=Bitcoin not so anonymous, Irish researcher says – Cyrus Farivar – Science and Technology |publisher=Deutsche Welle |date=2011-06-01 |accessdate=2011-07-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jeff Garzik, one of the Bitcoin developers, explained as such in an interview and concluded that &quot;attempting major illicit transactions with bitcoin, given existing statistical analysis techniques deployed in the field by law enforcement, is pretty damned dumb&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;gawker-06-01-11&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|url=http://gawker.com/5805928/the-underground-website-where-you-can-buy-any-drug-imaginable
|title=The Underground Website Where You Can Buy Any Drug Imaginable
|first=Adrian
|last=Chen
|newspaper=Gawker
|date=June 01 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2011/06/libertarian-dream-a-site-where-you-buy-drugs-with-digital-dollars/239776/ |title=Libertarian Dream? A Site Where You Buy Drugs With Digital Dollars – Alexis Madrigal – Technology |publisher=The Atlantic |date=2011-06-01 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also said &quot;We are working with the government to make sure indeed the long arm of the government can reach Bitcoin... the only way bitcoins are gonna be successful is working with regulation and with the government&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jYiWHNkZIes |title=CBSNewsOnline: BitCoin: The Future of Currency}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Client==
[[File:bitcoin screenshot windows7.png|thumb|350px|right|Bitcoin software running under Windows 7]]

People interact with bitcoin using a &quot;wallet,&quot; which may be either stored on their computer by the bitcoin [[Client (computing)|software]] or hosted on a third-party website. The wallet shows users their available bitcoin balance, transaction history, and the collection of bitcoin addresses they may use to send and receive bitcoins with other users. Because all transactions are added to the [[transaction log]] in the bitcoin block chain, which is a distributed database formed by all the bitcoin participants, a user's bitcoin software does not need to be running for that user to receive bitcoins.

Bitcoin payments are normally displayed to the receiver [[near real-time|near-instantly]], but they are initially displayed as ''unconfirmed'', because the bitcoin system cannot yet assure that the transaction is permanent. A transaction may be invalidated due to conflicting transactions (such as the same bitcoins being sent to two different receivers). This may happen if a sender malfunctions, or if a sender intentionally attempts to [[defraud]] a receiver. When the bitcoin network processes the transaction, an increasing number of confirmations are added every time the chain containing the transaction is extended. Eventually, the bitcoin software displays the transaction as confirmed.

The process of confirming a transaction is accomplished by solving a computationally difficult [[proof-of-work]] problem.&lt;ref name=&quot;bie&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/bitcoin-inside-the-encrypted-peer-to-peer-currency.ars |title=Bitcoin: inside the encrypted, peer-to-peer digital currency |author=Thomas Lowenthal |date=8 June 2011 |work=Ars Technica |accessdate=14 June 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The problem is based on data from the transactions that must be confirmed, as well as the entire previous transaction history. This process makes it infeasible for an attacker to rewrite the transaction history without having more computing power than the rest of the bitcoin system. Nodes that process blocks of transactions are rewarded by receiving a programmed amount of bitcoin, which arises &quot;out of thin air,&quot; as well as any transaction fees associated with the transactions they process. This compensates the operators of these systems for their computational work used to secure bitcoin transactions against reversal, and also accomplishes the initial [[Distribution of wealth|wealth distribution]] for the bitcoin system as a whole. The difficulty of the proof-of-work problems is automatically adjusted by the system so that the average time between new blocks being awarded is ten minutes. All participating systems check the validity of every transaction and of every block and ignore any that violate the rules, such as blocks that bring the wrong amount of new bitcoin into existence, or transactions that would involve one sender spending the same bitcoin twice.

==={{anchor|BitCoinJ}} Alternative implementations===
Besides the original [[C++]] Bitcoin client, there is an open source implementation of the Bitcoin protocol in [[Java (programming language)|Java]] called [http://code.google.com/p/bitcoinj/ BitCoinJ].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://news.slashdot.org/story/11/03/23/0210207/Google-Engineer-Releases-Open-Source-Bitcoin-Client
|title=Google Engineer Releases Open Source Bitcoin Client
|author=angry tapir, timothy
|date=23 March 2011
|publisher=[[Slashdot]]
|accessdate=2011-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Alternative [[user interface]]s include bitcoin-js-remote, a [[JavaScript]] web user interface for Bitcoin wallets,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=https://github.com/tcatm/bitcoin-js-remote
|title=bitcoin-js-remote
|author=tcatm
|work= |publisher=[[GitHub]]
|accessdate=2011-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Spesmilo, a [[PySide]] interface more open to a diversity of users, which can run independently of an external wallet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Spesmilo |title=Spesmilo, PySide Bitcoin client |publisher=En.bitcoin.it |date=2011-05-19 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Currency==
{{as of|2011}}, there were over 7 million bitcoins in existence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Total Number of Bitcoins in Existence |url=http://blockexplorer.com/q/totalbc |newspaper=Bitcoin Block Explorer |date=2011-08-23 |accessdate=2011-08-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; This figure is algorithmically determined as described in Nakamoto's whitepaper. Because by definition the only spendable Bitcoins in existence are those represented in the block chain database passed around on the peer to peer network, the number is not only easy to determine, but can be quickly determined with precision by all participants.&lt;ref name=&quot;whitepaper&quot; /&gt;

Anyone can view the block chain and observe transactions in real-time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blockexplorer.com/|title=Home – Bitcoin Block Explorer|accessdate=2011-06-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currency exchanges also exist between bitcoins and other real and virtual currencies, such as the [[US dollar]] and the [[Linden Dollar]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://radoff.com/blog/2011/06/03/bitcoin-mining-free-legalized-lottery/ |title=Bitcoin Mining: The Free Lottery |publisher=Radoff.com |accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;By June 2011, a bitcoin was worth more than twenty-nine [[USD]]. By October 2011, the value of a bitcoin had fallen to less than three [[USD]].&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot; /&gt;

===Monetary differences===
[[Image:total bitcoins over time.png|thumb|right|Expected future bitcoin supply (for 10-minute issuance frequency).]]
Unlike conventional [[fiat currency]], Bitcoin has no centralized issuing authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars-06-08-11&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|first=Thomas
|last=Lowenthal
|title= Bitcoin: inside the encrypted, peer-to-peer digital currency
|newspaper=Ars Technica
|date=June 8, 2011
|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/bitcoin-inside-the-encrypted-peer-to-peer-currency.ars
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sponsored by |url=http://www.economist.com/blogs/babbage/2011/06/virtual-currency |title=Virtual currency: Bits and bob |publisher=The Economist |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Geere |first=Duncan |url=http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2011-05/16/bitcoin-p2p-currency |title=Peer-to-peer currency Bitcoin sidesteps financial institutions (Wired UK) |publisher=Wired.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is a limited controlled expansion of the monetary base hardcoded in the Bitcoin software.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}

Transactions are facilitated directly without the use of a centralized financial processor between nodes, which makes reversal unlikely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Myths#Bitcoin_has_no_built-in_chargeback_mechanism,_and_this_isn_t_good|title=Bitcoin documentation on chargebacks}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bitcoin transactions can represent many kinds of operations such as pure peer-to-peer [[escrow]] and deposits but user interface software for this advanced functionality is currently underdeveloped.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} The Bitcoin client broadcasts transactions to surrounding nodes, which propagate them across the network. Corrupted or invalid transactions are rejected by legitimate clients. Transactions are free; however, an optional, often necessary, fee may be paid to other nodes to prioritize transaction processing.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The total number of bitcoins is programmed to approach 21 million over time.&lt;ref name=&quot;ars-06-08-11&quot;/&gt; The money supply is programmed to grow as a [[geometric series]] every 210,000 blocks (roughly every 4 years); by 2013 half of the total supply will be generated, and by 2017, 3/4 will be generated. To ensure sufficient granularity of the [[money supply]], bitcoins are divisible down to eight decimal places (a total of 2.1&amp;nbsp;×&amp;nbsp;10&lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt; or 2.1 quadrillion units).&lt;ref name=&quot;lwn&quot;&gt;{{cite news |author=Nathan Willis |date=2010-11-10 |title=Bitcoin: Virtual money created by CPU cycles |publisher=[[LWN.net]] |url=http://lwn.net/Articles/414452/ }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The diminishing geometric expansion combined with the expansion of Bitcoin users provides an incentive for early adopters, who can obtain bitcoin at preferential exchange rates.

Bitcoin's design allows for [[pseudonymous]] [[ownership]] and transfers. Because of this, Bitcoin has [[anonymity]] properties weaker than [[cash]] but stronger than traditional [[electronic payment]] systems{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}. Although the complete history of every bitcoin transaction is public, it is not possible in general &lt;ref name=&quot;An Analysis of Anonymity in the Bitcoin System&quot;&gt;Fergal Reid and Martin Harrigan (July 24th 2011). [http://anonymity-in-bitcoin.blogspot.com/2011/07/bitcoin-is-not-anonymous.html An Analysis of Anonymity in the Bitcoin System]. An Analysis of Anonymity in the Bitcoin System.&lt;/ref&gt; to associate bitcoin identities with real-life identities. This property makes bitcoin transactions attractive to some sellers of illegal products.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forbes&quot;&gt;Andy Greenberg (April 20, 2011). [http://www.forbes.com/forbes/2011/0509/technology-psilocybin-bitcoins-gavin-andresen-crypto-currency.html Crypto Currency]. Forbes Magazine.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Madrigal | first = Alexis |title = Libertarian Dream? A Site Where You Buy Drugs With Digital Dollars | publisher = [[The Atlantic Monthly]] | date = 2011-06-01 |url = http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2011/06/libertarian-dream-a-site-where-you-buy-drugs-with-digital-dollars/239776/ | accessdate = 2011-06-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conversion to and from other currencies===
Conversion to and from other currencies can be done in person at local exchangers, but is more commonly performed online through sites such as Mt. Gox, Intersango (formerly Britcoin), and TradeHill exchange services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=How to use bitcoin|url=http://bitcoinme.com/index.php/buy/|publisher=bitcoinme}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reception and concerns===
====Adoption====
[[Wikileaks]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wikileaks.org/support.html |title=Donate |publisher=Wikileaks.org |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://twitter.com/#!/wikileaks/status/80774521350668288&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Greenberg |first=Andy |url=http://blogs.forbes.com/andygreenberg/2011/06/14/wikileaks-asks-for-anonymous-bitcoin-donations/ |title=WikiLeaks Asks For Anonymous Bitcoin Donations - Andy Greenberg - The Firewall - Forbes |publisher=Blogs.forbes.com |date=2011-06-14 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Freenet]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://freenetproject.org/donate.html |title=/donate |publisher=The Freenet Project |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Pioneer One]],&lt;ref&gt;http://twitter.com/#!/pioneeronetv/status/36119594439544832&lt;/ref&gt; and several others&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Donation-accepting_organizations_and_projects |title=Donation-accepting organizations and projects – Bitcoin |publisher=En.bitcoin.it |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; already accept donations in Bitcoin. The [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]] did for a while but stopped doing so, citing concerns about a lack of legal precedent about new currency systems, and because they &quot;generally don't endorse any type of product or service – and Bitcoin is no exception.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/06/eff-and-bitcoin |title=EFF and Bitcoin &amp;#124; Electronic Frontier Foundation |publisher=Eff.org |date=2011-06-14 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gavin Andresen, one of the &quot;core developers&quot;, is explicitly advising people &quot;not to make heavy investments in Bitcoins&quot;, as it is &quot;kind of like a high risk investment&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite episode | title=/59/Bitcoin&amp;nbsp;– a Digital, Decentralized Currency (at 31 min.)| series=omega tau podcast | url=http://omegataupodcast.net/2011/03/59-bitcoin-a-digital-decentralized-currency/ | airdate=19 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;Jered Kenna, CEO of [[TradeHill]] a major Bitcoin Exchange also cautions eager investors and stated to the [[The New York Observer]] that &quot;Bitcoin is still an experiment and not to bet the house&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.observer.com/2011/06/bit-omoney-whos-behind-the-bitcoin-bubble/&lt;/ref&gt; As of July 2011, adoption is limited, while many small businesses have started to do it.&lt;ref&gt;https://en.bitcoin.it/wiki/Trade&lt;/ref&gt; [[LaCie]], a public company, accepts Bitcoin for its [[Wuala]] service.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wuala.com/en/bitcoin&lt;/ref&gt; A frequent problem faced by retailers willing to accept Bitcoin is the high volatility of its exchange rate to the [[US dollar]] and the absence of [[Futures exchange|futures]] and [[Option (finance)|options]] permitting to hedge this volatility yet. Further, it has been suggested that hoarding by speculators could impede the adoption of bitcoins.&lt;ref name = &quot;TechReview&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| url = http://www.technologyreview.com/computing/38392/ |author= James Surowiecki |title= Cryptocurrency |journal=Technology Review|pages= 106 |date= September/October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are several services available that use bitcoins.  One such service is the Bitcoingamer Casino.  It donates 2% of losses net losses to the EFF.  The site is located at [http://www.bitcoingamer.com?donateto=1CU4bnQQKXEF1F4poY2rgiYjdDu8uBjPQS www.bitcoingamer.com]

====Initial distribution====
{{Refimprove section|date=October 2011}}
The initial bitcoin distribution is advantageous towards early-adopters. As stated, bitcoins are distributed (&quot;generated&quot;) as a reward for the solution to a difficult proof-of-work problem. However, the amount of work that must be done for one bitcoin is currently over 500,000 times more than the amount of work at which the first bitcoins were being distributed. As more people join, and also because of a reward function that halves the number of rewarded bitcoins every so many blocks, it becomes harder to generate bitcoins over time, using the same computing power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.hightechforum.org/bitcoins-a-crypto-geek-ponzi-scheme/
 | title=Bitcoins, a Crypto-Geek Ponzi Scheme
 | accessdate=15 June 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.quora.com/Bitcoin/Is-the-cryptocurrency-Bitcoin-a-good-idea
 | title=Is the cryptocurrency Bitcoin a good idea?
 | accessdate=15 June 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Prices====
Prices fluctuate relative to goods and services more than more widely accepted currencies, since the price of a bitcoin is not yet [[Sticky (economics)|sticky]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytech.com/Digital+Black+Friday+First+Bitcoin+Depression+Hits/article21877.htm |title=Digital Black Friday: First Bitcoin &quot;Depression&quot; Hits |publisher=DailyTech |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, different exchanges quote different prices, implying the market is not yet efficient.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bitcoin-prices.com/ |title=Different Bitcoin Prices on different Exchanges |date= |accessdate=2011-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On 19 June 2011, a security breach of the Mt. Gox Bitcoin Exchange caused the leaking of usernames, emails and [[MD5 hash]]ed passwords of over 60,000 users onto the Web. The price of a Bitcoin briefly dropped to $0.01 on the Mt. Gox exchange (but remained unaffected on other exchanges) after a hacker allegedly used credentials from a Mt. Gox auditor's compromised computer to illegally transfer a large number of Bitcoins to himself and sell them all, creating a massive &quot;ask&quot; order at any price. Within minutes the price rebounded to over $15 before Mt. Gox shut down their exchange and canceled all trades that happened during the hacking period.&lt;ref&gt;[http://forum.bitcoin.org/index.php?topic=24727.0 MtGox Clarification on June 19 hack]&lt;/ref&gt; The exchange rate of Bitcoins quickly returned to near pre-crash values.&lt;ref name=&quot;mick&quot;&gt;Jason Mick, 19 June 2011, [http://www.dailytech.com/Inside+the+MegaHack+of+Bitcoin+the+Full+Story/article21942.htm Inside the Mega-Hack of Bitcoin: the Full Story], DailyTech&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Timothy B. Lee, 19 June 2011, [http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/bitcoin-price-plummets-on-compromised-exchange.ars Bitcoin prices plummet on hacked exchange], Ars Technica&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mark Karpeles, 20 June 2011, [https://support.mtgox.com/entries/20208066-huge-bitcoin-sell-off-due-to-a-compromised-account-rollback Huge Bitcoin sell off due to a compromised account – rollback], Mt.Gox Support&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;register1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title=Bitcoin collapses on malicious trade – Mt Gox scrambling to raise the Titanic | url = http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/06/19/bitcoin_values_collapse_again/ | date = 2011-06-19 | author=Chirgwin, Richard |
publisher = The Register }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Security====
If an attacker can compromise the machine storing a particular Bitcoin wallet, then they can easily transfer any Bitcoins to their own wallet. On June 16, 2011, computer security companies started publishing the discovery of [[malicious software]] that locates the wallet file on Windows computers and uploads it to a remote server.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=&lt;!--start post navigation--&gt; Previous post Next post |url=http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2011/06/bitcoin-malware/ |title=New Malware Steals Your Bitcoin &amp;#124; Threat Level |publisher=Wired.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Updated: 17 Jun 2011 | Translations available: 日本語 |url=http://www.symantec.com/connect/blogs/all-your-bitcoins-are-ours |title=All your Bitcoins are ours ... &amp;#124; Symantec Connect Community |publisher=Symantec.com |date=2011-06-17 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.symantec.com/security_response/writeup.jsp?docid=2011-061615-3651-99 |title=Infostealer.Coinbit |publisher=Symantec |date=2011-06-16 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.f-secure.com/weblog/archives/00002187.html |title=Pickpocket Targets Wallets at Bitcoin Forum – F-Secure Weblog : News from the Lab |publisher=F-secure.com |date=2011-06-17 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; This attack could be prevented by encrypting the wallet file; however, this functionality was lacking until version 0.4.0 of the official Bitcoin client.&lt;ref&gt;https://github.com/bitcoin/bitcoin/commit/4e87d341f75f13bbd7d108c31c03886fbc4df56f&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Dan Kaminsky]], a leading Internet technology security researcher, investigated Bitcoin. His examination reached various conclusions on bitcoin, anonymity and its future scalability. In the area of security the basic model he concluded that bitcoin was well designed. This relates to the underlying bitcoin model rather than any particular attack against a specific client, such as described above.&lt;ref&gt;Dan Kaminsky Toorcon Seattle presentation slides, http://www.slideshare.net/dakami/bitcoin-8776098&lt;/ref&gt;

====Criminal uses====
Bitcoin is the currency used by the [[Silk Road (anonymous marketplace)|Silk Road]] online marketplace.&lt;ref name=&quot;gawker-06-01-11&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;npr-06-12-11&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|url=http://www.npr.org/2011/06/12/137138008/silk-road-not-your-fathers-amazon-com
|date=June 12, 2011
|newspaper=NPR
|title=Silk Road: Not Your Father's Amazon.com
|author=Staff
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2011 letter to Attorney General Eric Holder and the Drug Enforcement Administration, senators [[Charles Schumer]] of New York and [[Joe Manchin]] of West Virginia called for an investigation into Bitcoin and Silk Road.&lt;ref name=&quot;npr-06-12-11&quot;/&gt; Schumer described the use of Bitcoins at Silk Road as a form of [[money laundering]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ars-06-08-11&quot;/&gt; Consequently [[Amir Taaki]] from Intersango (formerly Britcoin), the UK exchange, put out a statement calling for regulation of Bitcoin exchanges by law enforcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;britcoin reuters&quot;&gt;[http://uk.reuters.com/article/2011/06/15/financial-bitcoin-idUKN1510930920110615 Reuters] – Bitcoin exchanges offer anti- money-laundering aid&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;britcoin statement&quot;&gt;[https://britcoin.co.uk/statement Britcoin.co.uk] – statement to reuters from bitomat.pl and Britcoin.co.uk&lt;/ref&gt; The hacking organization &quot;[[LulzSec]]&quot; accepted donations in Bitcoin, having said that the group &quot;needs bitcoin donations to continue their hacking efforts&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNET&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Reisinger |first=Don |url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13506_3-20070268-17/senators-target-bitcoin-currency-citing-drug-sales/ |title=Senators target Bitcoin currency, citing drug sales &amp;#124; The Digital Home – CNET News |publisher=News.cnet.com |date=2011-06-09 |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Olson |first=Parmy |url=http://blogs.forbes.com/parmyolson/2011/06/06/lulzsec-hackers-posts-sony-dev-source-code-get-7k-donation/ |title=LulzSec Hackers Post Sony Dev. Source Code, Get $7K Donation – Parmy Olson – Disruptors – Forbes |publisher=Blogs.forbes.com |date= |accessdate=2011-06-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Creator==
Bitcoin was created by a person, or group of persons, going by the name '''Satoshi Nakamoto'''&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Davis|first=Joshua|title=The Crypto-Currency|url=http://www.wired.com/magazine/2011/11/mf_bitcoin/all|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=[[Wired Magazine]]|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; who began working on the software in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;code_start&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=13.msg46#msg46 |title=Questions about Bitcoin |publisher=Bitcoin forum |date=2009-12-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Nakamoto self-published a paper&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://article.gmane.org/gmane.comp.encryption.general/12588/|title=Bitcoin P2P e-cash paper}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;whitepaper&quot;&gt;{{Citation |last=Nakamoto|first=Satoshi|title=Bitcoin: A Peer-to-Peer Electronic Cash System|url=http://www.bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf|accessdate=14 December 2010|date=24 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; outlining his work on the cryptography mailing list&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mail-archive.com/search?l=cryptography@metzdowd.com&amp;q=from:%22Satoshi+Nakamoto%22 Satoshi's posts to Cryptography mailing list]&lt;/ref&gt; and then in January 3, 2009 founded the open source project called Bitcoin. The real identity of &quot;Satoshi Nakamoto&quot; is unknown. In his P2P Foundation profile&lt;ref name=&quot;p2pUS95fUS95profile&quot;&gt;[http://p2pfoundation.ning.com/profile/SatoshiNakamoto Satoshi Nakamoto profile on P2P Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt; he said he is from [[Japan]]. He would be a thirty-nine-year old man in 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot; /&gt;

The philosophical underpinnings of Bitcoin stem from a distrust of government-controlled central banks. &quot;The root problem with conventional currency is all the trust that's required to make it work,&quot; Nakamoto wrote. &quot;The central bank must be trusted not to debase the currency, but the history of fiat currencies is full of breaches of that trust. Banks must be trusted to hold our money and transfer it electronically, but they lend it out in waves of credit bubbles with barely a fraction in reserve.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;processors&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Business and economics|Free software|Numismatics}}
* [[Anonymous Internet banking]]
* [[Complementary currency]]
* [[Digital currency exchanger]]
* [[Digital gold currency]]
* [[Ripple monetary system]]
* [[Crypto-anarchism]]
* [[Economic secession]]

'''Digital money systems:'''
* [[DigiCash]]
* [[ecash]]
* [[eCache]]
* [[Pecunix]]
* [[Ven (currency)|Ven]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;Notes&quot;}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Bitcoin}}
* [http://bitcoin.org/ Bitcoin website]
* [http://blockexplorer.com/ Bitcoin Block Explorer] (Used to search transactions inside the Bitcoin block chain.)
* [http://www.wired.com/magazine/2011/11/mf_bitcoin/all/1 The rise and fall of Bitcoin] in [[Wired magazine]] by Benjamin Wallace, December 2011.

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

[[Category:2009 introductions]]
[[Category:Electronic currencies]]
[[Category:Free software programmed in C++]]
[[Category:Peer-to-peer computing]]
[[Category:Software using the MIT license]]

[[bar:Bitcoin]]
[[cs:Bitcoin]]
[[da:Bitcoin]]
[[de:Bitcoin]]
[[et:Bitcoin]]
[[es:Bitcoin]]
[[eo:Bitmono]]
[[fa:بیت‌کوین]]
[[fr:Bitcoin]]
[[ko:비트코인]]
[[hy:Bitcoin]]
[[id:Bitcoin]]
[[it:Bitcoin]]
[[he:ביטקוין]]
[[hu:Bitcoin]]
[[nl:Bitcoin]]
[[ja:Bitcoin]]
[[no:Bitcoin]]
[[pl:Bitcoin]]
[[pt:Bitcoin]]
[[ro:Bitcoin]]
[[ru:Bitcoin]]
[[simple:Bitcoin]]
[[fi:Bitcoin]]
[[sv:Bitcoin]]
[[ta:பிட்காயின்]]
[[uk:Bitcoin]]
[[zh:Bitcoin]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
