<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28327" ns="0" title="Stargate (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|the original 1994 film that started the franchise|other franchise films|Stargate (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox film
|name = Stargate
|image = Stargateposter.jpg
|image size =260px
|caption = Theatrical release poster
|director = [[Roland Emmerich]]
|producer = [[Dean Devlin]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Oliver Eberle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mario Kassar]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Joel B. Michaels]]
|writer = Roland Emmerich&lt;br /&gt;Dean Devlin
|starring = [[Kurt Russell]]&lt;br /&gt;[[James Spader]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Jaye Davidson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Viveca Lindfors]]
|studio = [[Canal+]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Centropolis Entertainment|Centropolis Film Productions]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Carolco Pictures]]
|distributor = [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]]
|released = {{Film date|1994|10|28}}
|runtime = 121&amp;nbsp;minutes
|country = [[United States]]&lt;br /&gt;[[France]]
|language = English
|budget = $55 million&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated2&quot;/&gt;
|gross = $196,567,262&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=stargate.htm |title=Stargate (1994) |publisher=''''Box Office Mojo'' | accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.the-numbers.com/movies/1994/0SGTE.php|title=Movie Stargate - Box Office Data, News, Cast Information - The Numbers|publisher=Nash Information Services, LLC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|cinematography = [[Karl Walter Lindenlaub]]
|music = [[David Arnold]]
|editing = Derek Brechin&lt;br /&gt;Michael J. Duthie
}}
'''''Stargate''''' is a 1994 American [[adventure science fiction|adventure]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-132284|work=Allmovie|accessdate=January 4, 2010|title=Stargate: Overview|author=Brenner, Paul}}&lt;/ref&gt;-[[military science fiction]] film released through [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]] (MGM) and [[Carolco Pictures]]. Created by [[Dean Devlin]] and [[Roland Emmerich]], the film is the first release in the [[Stargate|''Stargate'' franchise]]. Directed by Roland Emmerich, the film stars [[Kurt Russell]], [[James Spader]], [[Jaye Davidson]], Carlos Lauchu, [[Djimon Hounsou]], [[Erick Avari]], [[Alexis Cruz]], [[Mili Avital]], [[John Diehl (actor)|John Diehl]], [[French Stewart]], and [[Viveca Lindfors]]. The plot centers around the premise of a &quot;[[Stargate (device)|Stargate]]&quot;, an ancient ring-shaped device that creates a [[wormhole]] enabling travel to a similar device in a universe. The film's central plot explores the theory of [[Extraterrestrials in fiction|extraterrestrial]] [[beings]] [[Ancient astronauts|having an influence upon human civilization]].

The film had a mixed initial critical reception, earning both praise and criticism for its atmosphere, story, characters, and graphic content. Nevertheless, ''Stargate'' gained a cult following and became a commercial success worldwide. Devlin and Emmerich gave the rights to the franchise to [[MGM]] when they were working on their 1996 film ''[[Independence Day (film)|Independence Day]]'' (the rights to the ''Stargate'' film are currently owned by [[StudioCanal]], with [[Lions Gate Entertainment]] handling most distribution in terms of international theatrical and worldwide home video releases); however, MGM retains the domestic television rights.

==Plot==
The film begins in 1928, where Professor Langford discovers a massive stone ring in the sands of [[Giza, Egypt]]. In the present day, Langford's daughter Catherine offers [[List of Egyptologists|Egyptologist]] [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]], a down-on-his-luck linguistics professor, the chance to translate ancient [[Egyptian hieroglyphs]] that may prove his controversial theory regarding the [[Great Pyramid of Giza|Pyramid of Khufu]]. Jackson accepts and travels to a [[US Air Force]] installation inside Creek Mountain, Colorado. Jackson translates the hieroglyphs on the stone ring's coverstones, which read: &quot;A million years into the sky is [[Ra]]. Sealed and buried for all time, his Stargate.&quot; Formerly retired [[Special forces|Special Forces]] Colonel [[Jack O'Neil]] arrives to take command of the project and declares it classified.

Jackson deduces that the symbols are star constellations that are coordinates for a location within space.  The sequence is entered into the [[Stargate (device)|stargate]], creating a wormhole to a location in another galaxy. After O'Neil leads a team through the Stargate, they find themselves inside a [[pyramid]] in the middle of vast sand dunes. Jackson reveals they cannot dial home because the Stargate coordinates to go back to Earth are missing. Some team members stay at the pyramid while Jackson, O'Neil, and others go out and discover a mining village inhabited by humans who assume them to be gods sent by [[Ra]].

Jackson realizes that the people speak a dialect of [[Egyptian language|Ancient Egyptian]] and begins communicating with them. The team develops friendships with the people; O'Neil with [[Skaara]], and Jackson begins a budding romance with [[Sha'uri]], a daughter of the leader. Jackson learns from hieroglyphs in the catacombs how the Egyptian god Ra was actually an alien life form who enslaved humans with his advanced technology. While these humans eventually rebelled and buried the Stargate, some had been taken to the other planet through the Stargate and used to mine the [[quartzite]]-like mineral on which all of Ra's technology is based. Fearing another rebellion on this planet, Ra outlawed reading and writing. At this point, the team from Earth discovers the coverstone to get back to Earth, but the seventh symbol is eroded away.

O'Neil orders the team to return to the pyramid. A short time later, a huge spacecraft lands on top of the pyramid. All team members in the pyramid are either killed or taken into the pyramidal craft. O'Neil and Jackson are escorted to the [[throne room]], where they meet Ra.  Despite wearing fearsome armor, Ra's guards and servants are human. Ra reveals his intention to send the [[atomic bomb]] brought by O'Neil, which was to be used to destroy the Stargate to prevent invasion by any threat, back to Earth; it is now enhanced with his [[Technology in Stargate#Fictional materials and elements|quartzite-like material]] to produce cataclysmic results. O'Neil attempts to disarm the guards and kill Ra, but relents when Ra uses his children courtiers as human shields. Jackson is killed during the altercation. O'Neil is thrown into a [[dungeon]] with the captured team members, while Jackson is regenerated in a [[sarcophagus]]-like device. Ra states that he will kill Jackson and everyone who has seen him unless Jackson kills the rest of the team to show the villagers that Ra is their one true god.

However, once Ra has the local people gathered before the pyramid craft, several young villagers signal to Jackson that they have recovered the team's weapons. Jackson then shoots at Ra while the kids create a distraction. O'Neil, Jackson, and the rest of the team flee Ra's ship and take shelter in a cave with the boys. The next morning, when Skaara draws a picture of the people's victory against Ra, Jackson realizes that part of this drawing depicts the seventh symbol needed to reactivate the Stargate: three moons over a pyramid.

O'Neil convinces the locals that their &quot;[[gods]]&quot; are mere mortals and, with their help, O'Neil, Jackson, and the remaining members of the team make it back to the Stargate hoping to deactivate the bomb. When the locals begin an open rebellion against Ra's troops, Ra decides to retreat and prepares his ship for takeoff. Sha'uri is killed in the battle, but Jackson resurrects her in Ra's sarcophagus and manages to escape when O'Neil activates the ship's ring transporter. Unable to deactivate the bomb, O'Neil and Jackson transport the bomb to Ra's ship in orbit via the rings where it explodes, killing Ra. The team is able to return to Earth through the Stargate, though Jackson decides to remain on the planet.

===Director's cut===
The Director's cut had several scenes which were cut from the theatrical film version. The first such scene took place immediately after the excavation of the Stargate in 1928 and showed petrified [[Horus]] guards near the cover stones; the producers had tried to introduce the idea that beings had attempted to come through the Stargate after its burial, but they cut the scene for time concerns.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;

==Cast and characters==
* [[Kurt Russell]] as Colonel [[Jack O'Neil]], an Airman who suffers a period of suicidal depression after his son accidentally shot and killed himself with O'Neil's own pistol. It was an important story for Dean Devlin and Roland Emmerich that O'Neil had become suicidal and had left the military after his son's death. When he gets the mission from which he may never return, it is okay with him since it solves his problem with suicide, which in return makes him a dangerous person for the mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;
* [[James Spader]] as Dr. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]], a professor who finds little acceptance of his theory that the [[Pyramids of Giza]] were much older than they were thought to be. James Spader was intrigued by the script because he found it &quot;awful&quot;, but accepted the role that earned him money.&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworld&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Asher-Walsh |first=Rebecca |title=Slack Happy | publisher=Entertainment Weekly |date=November 11, 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jaye Davidson]] as [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]], a power-hungry [[Extraterrestrial life|alien]] being in the form of a young boy, who voyaged across the [[galaxy]] searching for a new host that could sustain his dying body.
* [[Erick Avari]] as [[Kasuf]], the local leader of the people living in a city near the Stargate, and the father of [[Sha'uri]] and Skaara.
* [[Alexis Cruz]] as [[Skaara]], the son of Kasuf and brother to Sha'uri. Skaara and his friends aid O'Neil and his airmen fight Ra.
* [[Mili Avital]] as [[Sha'uri]], the daughter of Kasuf. Kasuf offers Sha'uri to Daniel Jackson as a gift.
* [[John Diehl (actor)|John Diehl]] as [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Charles Kawalsky]], O'Neil's second-in-command on the mission through the Stargate.
* [[French Stewart]] as [[Technical Sergeant]] [[Louis Ferretti]], a member of O'Neil's team.
* [[Viveca Lindfors]] as Dr. [[Catherine Langford]], whose father gave her the amulet depicting the [[Eye of Ra]] during the excavation of the Stargate in Giza in 1928. ''Stargate'' was Viveca Lindfors' last film.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;
* [[Leon Rippy]] as [[Major General]] W. O. West, the commanding officer of the facility housing the Stargate device.
* [[Richard Kind]] as Dr. Gary Meyers, a doctor researching the Stargate.
* [[Rae Allen]] as Dr. Barbara Shore, a doctor researching the Stargate.
* [[Derek Webster (actor)|Derek Webster]] as [[Senior Airman]] Brown, a member of O'Neil's team.
* Christopher John Fields as Staff Sergeant Freeman, a member of O'Neil's team.
* [[Jack Moore]] as Senior Airman Reilly, a member of O'Neil's team.
* Steve Giannelli as Senior Airman Porro, a member of O'Neil's team.
* [[Djimon Honsou]] as Horus Guard #1, a personal guard of Ra.
* Carlos Lauchu as [[Anubis]] Guard #1, a personal guard of Ra.

==Production==
&lt;!--The audio commentary would help a lot--&gt;
''Stargate'' had a budget of $55 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;gateworld1&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author= |title=Gate World - Stargate Movies: &quot;Stargate&quot; | url=http://www.gateworld.net/movies/01.shtml | date= 2009-04-03|publisher=''Gate World''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Development===
The film was originally planned to play out in a chronological order, but when Devlin and Emmerich edited the film to tighten the narrative, they decided to change the first scene of the film into a flashback to show who the human host of Ra was before the aliens took him. Only Jaye Davidson's upper torso was filmed because Davidson had refused to take out his nipple rings.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt; The first scene was a combination of model shots and a set in [[Yuma, Arizona]] where ''[[Rambo: First Blood Part II]]'' had been filmed. The scene of the excavation of the Stargate was also filmed in three days in Arizona. A golden look was achieved by filming near the time of sunset.&lt;ref name=&quot;acemmerich&quot;/&gt; To keep within the limit of the budget, the producers put stick figures with cloth in the distant desert to appear as humans. The original Stargate was painted black, but it looked like a giant tire so it was repainted silver at the last moment.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;

Daniel Jackson's lecture on his theories was filmed in a hotel in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=&quot;acemmerich&quot;/&gt; The scene was originally much longer and delved more into the theories that aliens had built the Egyptian pyramids, but the scene was trimmed for time concerns for the release.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt; The scenes with O'Neil at his house were the first scenes filmed with Kurt Russell; his hair was cut short afterwards. Russell requested his hair color to be brightened a little for the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;acemmerich&quot;/&gt; The fictional facility housing the Stargate was the largest set for the film, located in [[Long Beach, California]].&lt;ref name=&quot;acemmerich&quot;/&gt; Egyptologist [[Stuart Tyson Smith]] joined production to make all Ancient Egyptian hieroglyphics and spoken language as accurate as possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;

===Themes and inspirations===
Stargate began as two separate films that Emmerich and Devlin conceived separately. Emmerich's film, ''Necropolis: City of the Dead'', was about a spaceship being buried under the Great Pyramid of Egypt and Devlin's unnamed film was to be, in his words, &quot;Lawrence of Arabia on another planet.&quot; The two films were combined to become Stargate.

===Filming===
The mask of the [[pharaoh]] in the opening credits was made out of fiber glass and modeled in the workshop. The sequence used a [[Motion control photography|motion-control camera]] to give better depth of field.&lt;ref name=&quot;acemmerich&quot;&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Roland Emmerich|Emmerich, Roland]] |date=2001 |title=Audio Commentary for Stargate |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The score of ''Stargate'' was composer [[David Arnold|David Arnold's]] first work on an American feature film. When Devlin and Emmerich first flew to London to meet with Arnold, they had not yet heard the score; hearing it, they felt &quot;he had elevated the film to a whole other level&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Dean Devlin|Devlin, Dean]] |date=2001 |title=Audio Commentary for Stargate |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arnold later interviewed the actors during [[principal photography]], using the information to improve his score.&lt;ref name=&quot;acdevlin&quot;/&gt;

===Visual effects===
Jeff Kleiser and a special effects team of 40 people created the look of the [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]]. They used self-written image-creation and compositing software, as well as commercial digital packages to create the Stargate, the morphing helmets worn by Ra and the Horus guards, and the cityscape of Nagada. Footprints in the sand were often digitally removed. The creation of the wormhole, which was fully digitized, was one of the biggest challenges in the making of the film. The ripples had to be digitized to seem accurate. Scanning lasers were lined up parallel to the gate to illustrate the amount of body that passed the surface of the Stargate plane. Afterwards, the parts of the body that had or had not yet gone through the gate (depending of the side of filming) were obliterated with a digital matte program.&lt;ref name=&quot;specialeffects&quot;/&gt; The use of computers generating a big 3D storyboard allowed Emmerich to try out different shooting angles before settling on one angle.&lt;ref name=&quot;specialeffects&quot;/&gt;

===Music and soundtrack===
{{Main|Stargate (soundtrack)}}
The soundtrack was composed by [[David Arnold]], played by the [[Sinfonia of London]] and conducted by Nicholas Dodd.&lt;ref name=&quot;sol&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.sinfonia-of-london.com/ |title=Stargate soundtrack |publisher=''Synfonia of London.com'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the second motion picture Arnold had composed and the first major motion picture. At the time of Stargate's production, David Arnold had recently started to work in a local video store in London. Once Arnold got the job, he spent several months in a hotel room working on the soundtrack, spending more time rewriting the music and improving it as delays were being created due to film companies trying to get the rights to release the film.&lt;ref name=&quot;da&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=David Arnold |url=http://www.davidarnold.com|title=History - 1994 |publisher=''David Arnold.com''| accessdate=2010-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Arnold &quot;when I first read the script for StarGate, I knew what approach to take, which was to be as big and bold as possible,&quot; he kept on saying:&lt;ref name=&quot;starscore&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Kerry J. Byrnes|url=http://filmscoremonthly.com/features/timetravel1.asp |title=Stargate - David Arnold |publisher=Film Score Monthly| accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|&quot;Every time there was an amazing sight, the characters would stand back and say, 'Oh my God!' But James would just smile and walk towards it. That was the basis for the Stargate score, moving forward with a sense of majesty instead of being frightened by what's around the corner.&quot;|}}

==Marketing==
A wide amount of merchandise is available for the ''Stargate'' franchise.&lt;ref name=&quot;merch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.fansofstargate.com/ |title=Stargate merchandises |publisher=''Fans of Stargate'' | accessdate=2009-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;merchtwo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.starstore.com/acatalog/Starstore_Catalogue_STARGATE_MERCHANDISE_330.html |title=Stargate merchandises |publisher=''StarStore.com'' | accessdate=2009-04-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- ===Books=== --&gt;
&lt;!-- ===Video games=== --&gt;
&lt;!-- ===Action figures=== --&gt;

==Release==
The film received mixed reviews upon its release in 1994, though in recent years it has become a [[cult classic]] and now has a reputation as one of the best releases in the ''Stargate'' series.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} The film was released on October 28, 1994 in the United States and released internationally in December of the same year. Stargate has a MPAA Rating of PG-13 for sci-fi action violence. It is rated 14A in Canada for violence.&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;/&gt; Later in 1995 the film was released on [[VHS]] format and on [[DVD]] in June 18, 1997. However the DVD format was re-released in October 1999 under the title ''Stargate Special Edition''. The film was released on [[Blu-ray]] format on August 29, 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;formats&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B00004R6PV |title=Stargate (VHS) (1995) |publisher=''Amazon.uk'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bluray&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.blu-ray.com/movies/movies.php?id=133&amp;show=review |title=Stargate Blu-ray |publisher=''Blu-ray.com'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Box office===
The film received a warmer reception from the public, grossing $71.5 million at the US box office and $125 million in the rest of the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;estimated2&quot;/&gt; At the time, the film set a record for the highest-grossing opening weekend for a film released in the month of October.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://boxofficemojo.com/alltime/weekends/month/?mo=10&amp;p=.htm| title=Top Opening Weekends By Month | date= | publisher= boxofficemojo.com | accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Performance analysis===
In its first run, ''Stargate'' made more money than film industry insiders predicted, especially given its lukewarm reviews.&lt;ref name=&quot;time5&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Richard Corliss | title = The Invasion Has Begun!  | publisher = Time | date = July 8, 1996 | url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,984815-5,00.html | accessdate = 2008-07-08 | authorlink = Richard Corliss}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wesuf1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | author = Rebecca Ascher-Walsh | title = Space Under Fire  | publisher = Entertainment Weekly | date = July 28, 1995 | url = http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,293332,00.html | accessdate = 2008-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some regard it as Emmerich's breakthrough film.&lt;ref name=&quot;breakthrough&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Steven Goldman |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2008/mar/07/2 |title=Action Man |publisher=''The Guardian'' | accessdate=2009-04-03 | location=London | date=2008-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stargate grossed over $16,651,000 in the United States during its opening week in October 1994. It was the 35th highest-grossing film opening in the US in October.&lt;ref name=&quot;iop&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://boxofficemojo.com/alltime/weekends/month/?mo=10&amp;p=.htm |title=Top Opening Weekends By Month |publisher=''Box Office Mojo'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; From 4-6 November, the film grossed around $12,368,700, declining 25%. The film would continue this decline until the end of November, when the film garnered $4,777,198, or a 8.2% rise. The week before that the film garnered around $4,413,420, a 45.6% decline. In its last week playing theatrically, the film garnered around $1,170,500 in the US.&lt;ref name=&quot;iopus&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page=weekend&amp;id=stargate.htm |title=Stargate (1994) Weekend Box Office |publisher=''Box Office Mojo'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Critical reception===
{{Main|Stargate fandom}}
''Stargate'' has garnered mostly mixed reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/search/full_search.php?search=stargate | title=Stargate | publisher=''Rotten Tomatoes'' | accessdate=2011-01-15}} {{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though initially at 50%, in the [[Rotten Tomatoes]] main &quot;T-Meter Critics&quot; section, 48% of critics gave the film a positive review based on 40 reviews, with an [[weighted mean|average]] rating of 5.3 out of 10.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/?name_order=asc | title=Stargate | publisher=''Rotten Tomatoes'' | accessdate=2011-01-15|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20110615011810/http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/?name_order=asc |archivedate = June 15, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; On its &quot;Top Critics&quot; section, it was lower with 20% of critics giving it a positive review based on 5 reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/?critic=creamcrop |title=Stargate |publisher=''Rotten Tomatoes'' |accessdate=2011-01-15|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20100628205630/http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/?critic=creamcrop |archivedate = June 28, 2010|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the &quot;RT Community&quot; section, it has 75% of critics with a positive review based on 171,050 reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=| url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/reviews_users.php | title=Stargate | publisher=''Rotten Tomatoes'' | accessdate=2011-01-15|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20110604032444/http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/stargate/reviews_users.php |archivedate = June 04, 2011|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Allmovie]] &quot;Work Rating&quot; is 3 out of 5 stars for the film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://allmovie.com/work/stargate-132284 |title=Stargate |publisher=AllMovie |accessdate=2011-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; At [[MRQE]], which assigns a [[standard score|normalized]] rating out of 100 from most critics, the film holds a score of 64 based on 95 reviews.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mrqe.com/movies/m100046681 |title=Stargate |publisher=MRQE |accessdate=2011-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Out of Emmerich's 22 works, ''Stargate'' is currently his 3rd highest rated film.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rottentomatoes.com/celebrity/roland_emmerich/ |title=Roland Emmerich |publisher=''Rotten Tomatoes'' |accessdate=2011-01-15|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20100618013308/http://www.rottentomatoes.com/celebrity/roland_emmerich/ |archivedate = June 18, 2010|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the negative reviews focused on the overuse of special effects, thinness of plot and excessive use of [[cliché]]s with [[Roger Ebert]] going so far as to say, &quot;the movie ''[[Ed Wood (film)|Ed Wood]]'', about the worst director of all time, was made to prepare us for ''Stargate''&quot;.  Ebert awarded the film one out of four stars, and even over ten years later ''Stargate'' remains on his list of most hated films.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Roger Ebert | url=http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19941028/REVIEWS/410280308/1023 | title=Stargate | publisher=''Sun Times'' | accessdate=2009-04-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Mike DiBella from Allmovie said, &quot;there simply isn't enough spectacle in ''Stargate'' to make up for its many flaws.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author=Mike DiBella | url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-132284/review | title=Stargate | publisher=''Allmovie'' | accessdate=2009-04-04 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The film peaked at number one on the ''[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]]'' chart ''Top Video Rentals'' on April 29, 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Nielsen Business Media, Inc.| title = Billboard| url = http://books.google.com/?id=5AsEAAAAMBAJ| date = 1995-04-29| publisher = Nielsen Business Media, Inc.| isbn =  }}&lt;/ref&gt; However the positive reviews stated that it was an &quot;instant camp classic&quot;, and praised the film for its special effects and entertainment value,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Stephen | last=Farber | url=http://www.movieline.com/reviews/stargate_rvw.shtml | title=StarGate | publisher=MovieLine | date= | accessdate=2006-08-22|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20040221035710/http://www.movieline.com/reviews/stargate_rvw.shtml| archivedate=February 21, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Chris Hicks of the ''[[Deseret News]]'' calling it &quot;''[[Star Wars]]'' meets ''[[Ben-Hur (1959 film)|Ben Hur]]''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first=Chris | last=Hicks | url=http://deseretnews.com/movies/view/1,1257,1736,00.html | title=Movie review: Stargate | publisher=Deseret News, Salt Lake City | date=1994-10-28 | accessdate=2006-08-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scott McKenzie from DVDactive said this about the film &quot;it's a shame because the world created around the ''Stargate'' is compelling and detailed. It's almost enough to make me want to watch the ''[[Stargate SG-1|TV series]]'', but not quite.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;reviewone&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Scott McKenzie |url=http://www.dvdactive.com/reviews/dvd/stargate-special-edition.html |title=Stargate: Special Edition (UK - BD RB) |publisher=''DVDactive.com'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the release of the movie, Emmerich and Devlin were sued by an Egyptology student, claiming he had written the story and given them the idea.  The suit was later dropped.&lt;ref name=&quot;thieves&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.discoverychannel.co.uk/sci-files/cinema/stargate/index.shtml |title=Stargate |publisher=''Discovery Channel'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home releases===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |Product !! rowspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;padding:0 8px;&quot;|Episodes !! colspan=&quot;3&quot; |[[DVD]] release date !! colspan=&quot;2&quot;|[[Blu-Ray]] release date
|-
! [[DVD region code|Region 1]] !! [[DVD region code|Region 2]] !! [[DVD region code|Region 4]] !! [[Blu-ray Disc#Region codes|Region A]] !! [[Blu-ray Disc#Region codes|Region B]]
|-
|  style=&quot;width:10px; background:#ccf;&quot;|
| style=&quot;text-align:left;&quot;|Stargate
| Film
| June 17, 1997
| September 7, 1998
| September 15, 2004
| August 29, 2006
| August 4, 2008
|}

==Awards==
In 1995, ''Stargate'' was considered for various film awards worldwide. It won six of the ten awards it was nominated for.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0111282/awards |title=Stargate |publisher=IMDb |accessdate=2010-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Award
! Category
! Winner/Nominee
! Result
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Academy of Science Fiction, Fantasy &amp; Horror Films]] || [[Saturn Award for Best Science Fiction Film]] || ''Stargate'' || {{won}}
|-
| [[Saturn Award for Best Costume]] || Joseph A. Porro || {{nom}}
|-
| [[Saturn Award for Best Special Effects]] || Jeffrey A. Okun and [[Patrick Tatopoulos]] || {{nom}}
|-
| [[BMI Film &amp; Television Awards]] || [[BMI Film Music Award]] || [[David Arnold]] || {{won}}
|-
| [[Fantasporto]] || International Fantasy Film Award for Best Film || [[Roland Emmerich]] || {{nom}}
|-
| Germany's Golden Screen Awards || Golden Screen || ''Stargate'' || {{won}}
|-
| [[Hugo Awards]] || [[Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation]] || ''Stargate'' || {{nom}}
|-
| rowspan=&quot;3&quot; | Sci-Fi Universe Magazine: Universe Reader's Choice Awards || Best Science Fiction Film || ''Stargate'' || {{won}}
|-
| Best Special Effects in a Genre Motion Picture || Jeffrey A. Okun || {{won}}
|-
| Best Supporting Actress in a Genre Motion Picture || [[Mili Avital]] || {{won}}
|}

==Future==
Dean Devlin and Roland Emmerich always envisioned ''Stargate'' as the first part of a trilogy of films, but parts two and three were never developed.&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ukscifi.net/i/index.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=20 |title=Devlin Develops New ''Stargates''| first=Patrick| last=Lee| publisher=UK SciFi Networks|date=April 16, 2008| accessdate=2010-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; At Comic-Con 2006, 12 years after the original film was released, writer/producer Dean Devlin stated that he was in early discussions with rightsholders MGM about finally bringing the final two parts to the screen.&lt;ref name=&quot;tocoolforinternett&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Eric Vespe|url=http://www.aintitcool.com/?q=node/24247 |title=Quint chats with producer Dean Devlin about ''Flyboys'', ''Isobar'', ''Ghosting and the ''Stargate'' sequels |publisher=Ain't It Cool News| date=August 22, 2006| accessdate=2010-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sequels===
According to Devlin, the second film is intended to be set around 12 years after the original, with Daniel Jackson making a discovery that leads him back to Earth and to the uncovering of a new Stargate. The second movie would supposedly use a different mythology from the Egyptian one which formed the background to the original movie, with the third movie tying these together to reveal that &quot;all mythologies are actually tied together with a common thread that we haven't recognized before.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;comingsoon200706&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.comingsoon.net/news/movienews.php?id=15537 Devlin Announces Plans for Stargate Sequels]&quot; (20 July 2006). ''ComingSoon.net''&lt;/ref&gt; Devlin stated that he hoped to enlist original stars Kurt Russell (Col. Jack O'Neil) and James Spader (Dr. Daniel Jackson) for the sequels. The actors have reportedly expressed an interest in participating in the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;ignrusselspader&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://movies.ign.com/articles/720/720070p1.html |title=Comic-Con 2006: Devlin on Stargate Sequels |publisher=''IGN'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film trilogy would not directly tie in to the Stargate series. According to Devlin, the relationship between the movie and the series is &quot;we would just continue the mythology of the movie and finish that out. I think the series could still live on at the end of the third sequel. So we're going to try to not tread on their stories.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;comingsoon200706&quot; /&gt; Plans for sequels to the original film are unrelated to the development of three straight-to-DVD movies made as sequels to the ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' TV series. Using some of Roland Emmerich's notes, [[Bill McCay]] wrote a series of five novels, continuing the story the original creators had envisioned, which involved the Earth-humans, the locals and the successors of Ra. See ''[[Stargate literature]]''. According to Devlin, he and Emmerich had always planned to do three films with the potential for more, but MGM preferred to play out the television series first.&lt;ref name=&quot;scificool&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.scificool.com/dean-devlin-talks-possible-stargate-and-independence-day-sequels/ |title=Dean Devlin Talks Possible Stargate and Independence Day Sequels |publisher=''Sci-Ficool.com'' | accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Television spin-offs===
{{Main|Stargate}}
The CD ROM ''Secrets of Stargate'', released after the film, shows how the special effects were made. The film included behind the scenes of the film and the showing interviews with the cast and the production members.&lt;ref name=&quot;specialeffects&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/wow-how-did-they-do-that-1568272.html |title=Wow, how did they do that? |publisher=''The Independent'' | accessdate=2009-04-03 | location=London | first=Beth | last=Porter | date=1995-01-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dean Devlin eventually gave [[Metro–Goldwyn–Mayer]] (MGM) the rights over the film,&lt;ref name=&quot;newstargatefilmfromorg&quot;/&gt; and author Bill McCay wrote a [[Stargate film novels|series of five novels]] based on Emmerich's notes, continuing the story the original creators had envisioned.
In 1996, MGM hired [[Brad Wright]] and [[Jonathan Glassner]] to create a [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] television series. ''Stargate SG-1'' premiered on the American subscription channel [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] on July 27, 1997 and ended its ten-season run in 2007. ''Stargate SG-1'' itself spawned the non-canon animated television series ''[[Stargate Infinity]]'' (2002–2003), and the live-action television series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' (2004–2009) and ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' (2009–2011).

===Differences from the series===
[[File:Ra original humanoid.jpg|170px|thumb|Concept drawing of Ra's original humanoid form by [[Patrick Tatopoulos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;tataoup&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.tatopoulosstudios.net/mainpage.html |title=Stargate - Ra - Tatopoulos Studios |publisher=''Tatopoulos Studios'' | accessdate=2009-04-04|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20110718172219/http://www.tatopoulosstudios.net/mainpage.html |archivedate = July 18, 2011|deadurl=yes}} &lt;/ref&gt;]]

''SG-1'' creators and executive producers Brad Wright and Jonathan Glassner altered the canon by introducing several new concepts during production of the ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' series. Most notably, many characters were portrayed by different actors in the series, and names were spelled differently.&lt;ref name=bbc.co.uk /&gt; Daniel Jackson was played by James Spader in the movie and by [[Michael Shanks]] in the series. Kurt Russell's character Jonathan &quot;Jack&quot; O'Neil, a rather humorless Colonel, is played by [[Richard Dean Anderson]] as Jonathan &quot;Jack&quot; O'Neill (with two L's) in ''SG-1''.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Will Joyner |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D7163AF935A15754C0A961958260 |title=Through a Gate to the Far Side of the Universe: A TV Series |date=July 26, 1997 |publisher=''The New York Times'' | accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;digitalbits&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.thedigitalbits.com/reviews2/stargatesg1s1.html |title=Stargate SG-1: The Complete First Season |publisher=''thedigitalbits'' | accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[French Stewart]]'s character was named Louis Ferretti, in ''SG-1'', [[Brent Stait]]'s character is named Louis Ferretti. The spelling of Daniel Jackson's wife changes from ''Sha'uri'' to ''Sha're'', O'Neill's wife from Sarah to Sara, (similarly, the name of O'Neil's son changes from ''Tyler'' in the film to ''Charlie'').&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A765597 |title=Stargate SG-1 - the TV Show |publisher=''BBC'' | accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Stargate Command]] setting was transferred from the fictional military facility located in Creek Mountain, to the [[Cheyenne Mountain]] military complex.&lt;ref name=bbc.co.uk /&gt; The unnamed [[planet]] from the film was named [[Abydos (Stargate)|Abydos]] in the series and the distance from Earth changed from millions of [[light-year]]s away (in an entirely different [[galaxy]], &quot;the Kalium galaxy&quot;) to becoming the closest planet to [[Earth]] with a Stargate, residing in the same galaxy as Earth. Also in ''SG-1'', Stargate travel is limited to the Stargate network in the [[Milky Way galaxy]] (unless a tremendous amount of power is used to lengthen the subspace wormhole of a Stargate to another galaxy's Stargate).&lt;ref name=bbc.co.uk /&gt; Ra was the last of an unnamed race in the film, being of a humanoid species with large black eyes and a lack of facial features. In ''SG-1'' however, Ra is one of many &quot;[[Goa'uld]] [[System Lord]]s,&quot; who are a race of parasitic snake-like creatures.&lt;ref name=nytimes /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gwfaq&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=|url=http://www.gateworld.net/the_stargate_faq.shtml#movie.1 |title=The Stargate FAQ |publisher=''GateWorld'' | accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also changes to the Stargate. The unique set of 39 Stargate symbols in the film were replaced with the concept of 38 symbols that are the same for each Stargate (Earth's symbols based on Earth's constellations), plus a single point of origin symbol that is unique to that individual gate.&lt;ref name=gwfaq /&gt; While the [[kawoosh]] effect in the movie was created by filming the actual swirl of water in a glass tube, and looked like a vortex on the back of the Gate;&lt;ref&gt;DVD commentary for the ''Stargate'' film&lt;/ref&gt; on the TV series this effect was completely created in [[Computer graphics|CG]] by the Canadian [[visual effects]] company ''Rainmaker.''&lt;ref&gt;''Stargate Magic: Inside The Lab.'' Special feature on [[Stargate SG-1 DVD]] Volume 37 (Lost City).&lt;/ref&gt; At the beginning of Season 9, the original movie wormhole sequence was substituted by a new sequence similar to the one already used on ''Stargate Atlantis'', but being blue as it was in the movie and SG-1, whereas in Atlantis it's green.&lt;ref&gt;Audio commentary for &quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;, SG-1.&lt;/ref&gt;

While the Stargate device in the feature film has a plain quartzite surface, the device in the television series has lights set in each of the chevrons, red, blue, and white in ''Stargate SG-1'', ''Stargate Atlantis'', and ''Stargate Universe'' respectively.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{wikiquote|Stargate (film)}}
* [http://www.mgm.com/title_title.do?title_star=STARGATE Official website] at [[MGM|mgm.com]]
* {{IMDb title|0111282|Stargate}}
* [http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=stargate.htm ''Stargate''] at [[Box Office Mojo]]
* {{wikia|stargate|Stargate Wiki|Stargate (movie)|''Stargate''}}
* {{AllRovi movie|132284|Stargate}}
* {{Rotten Tomatoes|id=stargate|title=Stargate}}

{{Stargate}}
{{Roland Emmerich}}
{{Saturn Award for Best Science Fiction Film 1991–2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stargate (Film)}}
[[Category:1994 films]]
[[Category:Carolco Pictures films]]
[[Category:Egyptian-language films]]
[[Category:American science fiction action films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:Fictional-language films]]
[[Category:Films directed by Roland Emmerich]]
[[Category:Films shot anamorphically]]
[[Category:Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer films]]
[[Category:1990s science fiction films]]
[[Category:Space adventure films]]
[[Category:Stargate]]
[[Category:StudioCanal films]]
[[Category:Wormholes in fiction]]
[[Category:Films set in 1928]]
[[Category:Films set in Colorado]]
[[Category:Films set in Egypt]]
[[Category:Films shot in California]]
[[Category:Films shot in Arizona]]
[[Category:1990s action films]]
[[Category:Egyptian mythology in popular culture]]
[[Category:Ancient astronauts in fiction]]

{{Link FA|sh}}

[[ar:ستارغيت (فيلم)]]
[[bg:Старгейт (филм)]]
[[ca:Stargate (pel·lícula)]]
[[cs:Hvězdná brána (film)]]
[[da:Stargate (film)]]
[[de:Stargate (Film)]]
[[et:Tähevärav]]
[[es:Stargate (película)]]
[[fr:Stargate, la porte des étoiles]]
[[gl:Stargate (filme)]]
[[id:Stargate (film)]]
[[it:Stargate (film)]]
[[he:סטארגייט (סרט)]]
[[hu:Csillagkapu (film)]]
[[nl:Stargate (film)]]
[[ja:スターゲイト (映画)]]
[[no:Stargate (film)]]
[[nn:Filmen Stargate]]
[[nds:Stargate (Film)]]
[[pl:Gwiezdne wrota (film)]]
[[pt:Stargate (filme)]]
[[ro:Stargate (film)]]
[[ru:Звёздные врата (фильм)]]
[[simple:Stargate (film)]]
[[sk:Hviezdna brána (film)]]
[[sl:Zvezdna vrata (film)]]
[[sr:Звездана капија (филм)]]
[[sh:Stargate (film)]]
[[fi:Tähtiportti (elokuva)]]
[[sv:Stargate (film)]]
[[tr:Yıldız Geçidi (film)]]
[[uk:Зоряна брама (фільм)]]
[[zh:星際之門 (電影)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
