<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28332061" ns="0" title="Prenatal cocaine exposure"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- DEFINITION AND MEDIA HYPE --&gt;
'''Prenatal cocaine exposure''' ('''PCE''') occurs when a pregnant woman uses [[cocaine]] and thereby exposes her [[fetus]] to the [[drug]]. '''Crack baby''' was a term coined to describe children who were exposed to [[crack cocaine|crack]] (cocaine in smokable form) as fetuses; the concept of the crack baby emerged in the US during the 1980s and 90s in the midst of a great deal of media surrounding crack.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;  Early studies reported that people who had been exposed to crack in utero would be severely emotionally, mentally, and physically disabled; this belief became common in the scientific and lay communities.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;  Fears were widespread that a generation of crack babies were going to put severe strain on society and social services as they grew up.  Later studies failed to substantiate the findings of earlier ones that PCE has severe disabling consequences; these earlier studies had been methodologically flawed (e.g. with small [[sample size]]s and confounding factors).  Scientists have come to understand that the findings of the early studies were vastly overstated and that most people who were exposed to cocaine in utero are normal.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- EFFECTS IT DOESN'T HAVE --&gt;
No specific disorders or conditions have been found to result for people whose mothers used cocaine while pregnant.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID20159194&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|20159194}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Studies focusing on children of six years and younger have not shown any direct, long-term effects of PCE on language, growth, or development as measured by test scores.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|20142293}}&lt;/ref&gt;  PCE also appears to have little effect on infant growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg228&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- 
-- EFFECTS IT DOES HAVE --&gt;
However, PCE is associated with [[premature birth]], [[birth defect]]s, [[attention deficit disorder]], and other conditions.  Cognitive, motor, behavior, developmental, and language problems also appear to result from PCE. 
The effects of cocaine on a fetus are thought to be similar to those of tobacco and less severe than those of alcohol.&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09Encouraging&quot;/&gt;   No scientific evidence has shown a difference in harm to a fetus of crack and powder cocaine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lavoie07&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- RESEARCH --&gt;
PCE is very difficult to study because it very rarely occurs in isolation: usually it coexists with a variety of other factors, which may confound a study's results.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  For example, pregnant mothers who use cocaine often use other drugs in addition to cocaine, or they may be malnourished and lacking in medical care.  Children in households where cocaine is abused are at risk of violence and neglect, and those in foster care may experience problems due to unstable family situations.  Thus researchers have had difficulty in determining which effects result from PCE and which result from other factors in the children's histories.

==Historical context==
&lt;!-- HOW IT EMERGED --&gt;
During the [[crack epidemic]] of the 1980s and 90s in the US, fear existed throughout the country that PCE would create a generation of youth with severe behavioral and cognitive problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09&quot;/&gt;  Early studies in the mid-1980s reported that cocaine use in pregnancy caused children to have severe problems including cognitive, developmental, and emotional disruption.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;  These early studies had methodological problems including small [[sample size]], confounding factors like poor [[nutrition]], and use of other drugs by the mothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;   However, the results of the studies sparked widespread media discussion in the context of the new [[War on Drugs]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFDoweiko|Doweiko]] p.239&lt;/ref&gt;  For example a 1985 study that showed harmful effects of cocaine use during pregnancy created a huge media buzz.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|19277053}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;/&gt;  The term &quot;crack baby&quot; resulted from the publicity surrounding crack and PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;  

&lt;!-- POOR PROGNOSIS --&gt;
It was common in media reports of the phenomenon to emphasize that babies exposed to crack in utero would never develop normally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;  The children were reported to be inevitably destined to be physically and mentally disabled for their whole lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;   
&lt;!-- SOCIAL EFFECTS --&gt;
Babies exposed to crack in utero were written off as doomed to be severely disabled, and many were abandoned in hospitals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  Experts foresaw the development of a &quot;biological underclass&quot; of born criminals who would prey on the rest of the population.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt; Crime rates were predicted to rise when the generation of crack-exposed infants grew up (instead they dropped).&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  It was predicted that the children would be difficult to console, irritable, and hyperactive, putting a strain on the school system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg228&quot;/&gt;  Charles Krauthammer, a columnist from [[The Washington Post]] wrote in 1989, &quot;[t]heirs will be a life of certain suffering, of probable deviance, of permanent inferiority.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  The  president of Boston University at the time, John Silber, said &quot;crack babies ... won't ever achieve the intellectual development to have consciousness of God.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  

&lt;!-- THEORIES --&gt;
At the time, the proposed mechanism by which cocaine harmed fetuses was as a stimulant—it was predicted that cocaine would disrupt normal development of parts of the brain that dealt with stimulation, resulting in problems like [[bipolar disorder]] and [[attention deficit disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;  Reports from the mid 1980s to early 90s raised concerns about links between PCE and slowed growth, deformed limbs, defects of the kidneys and [[Genitourinary system|genitourinary]] and [[gastrointestinal tract]]s, [[neurological]] damage, [[microcephaly|small head size]], [[atrophy]] or [[cysts]] in the [[cerebral cortex]], [[intraventricular hemorrhage|bleeding into the brain's ventricles]], obstruction of blood supply in the [[central nervous system]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer05&quot;/&gt;  Studies that find that exposure has significant effects may be more likely to be published than those that do not, a factor that may have biased reporting on the effects of PCE toward indicating more severe outcomes as the [[Crack epidemic (United States)|crack epidemic]] emerged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer05&quot;/&gt;  Between 1980 and 1989, 57% of studies showing cocaine has effects on a fetus were accepted by the Society for Pediatric Research, compared with only  11% of studies showing no cocaine effects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Volpe1025&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- EVOLUTION TOWARD TODAY'S VIEW --&gt;
After the early studies which reported that PCE children would be severely disabled came studies that purported to show that cocaine exposure in utero has no important effects.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  Almost every prenatal complication originally thought to be due directly to PCE was found to result from confounding factors such as poor maternal nutrition, use of other drugs, [[major depressive disorder|depression]], and lack of [[prenatal care]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;/&gt;  More recently the scientific community has begun to reach an understanding that PCE does have some important effects but that they are not severe as was predicted in the early studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;/&gt;  Most people who were exposed to cocaine in utero are normal.&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;/&gt;  The effects of PCE are subtle but they exist.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer05&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Messinger04&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|15173491}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Eiden09&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|18822371}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pathophysiology==
[[File:Cocaine-from-xtal-1983-3D-balls.png|thumb|right|Cocaine is a small enough molecule to pass across the placental barrier into the bloodstream of the fetus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;]]

Cocaine, a small molecule, is able to cross the [[placenta]] into the bloodstream of the fetus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  In fact it may be present in a higher concentration in the [[amniotic fluid]] than it is in the mother's bloodstream.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFDoweiko|Doweiko]] p.241&lt;/ref&gt;  The skin of the fetus is able to absorb the chemical directly from the amniotic fluid until the 24th week of pregnancy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;  Cocaine can also show up in [[breast milk]] and affect the nursing baby.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Yaffe417&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFYaffe|Yaffe]] p.417&lt;/ref&gt;

Cocaine prevents the [[reuptake]] of [[neurotransmitters]] such as [[norepinepherine]] and [[epinepherine]], so they stay in the [[synapse]] longer, causing excitement of the [[sympathetic nervous system]] and evoking a stress response.&lt;ref name=&quot;Volpe1025&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFVolpe|Volpe]] p.1025&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[euphoria]] experienced by cocaine users is thought to be largely due to the way it prevents the neurotransmitter [[serotonin]] from being reabsorbed by the [[presynaptic neuron]] which released it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  

Use of cocaine during pregnancy can negatively affect both the mother and the fetus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Volpe1025&quot;/&gt;  But the ways in which cocaine affects a fetus are poorly understood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;/&gt;  There are multiple mechanisms by which cocaine exposure harms a fetus: it causes [[vasoconstriction|constriction (narrowing) of blood vessels]] and changes in [[neurochemistry|brain chemistry]], and it may alter expression of certain [[gene]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lester09&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|19372684}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Cocaine affects [[neurotransmitter]]s that are involved in the development of the fetus's brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer01&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11331686}}&lt;/ref&gt;   Cocaine may affect fetal development directly by altering the development of the [[monoaminergic]] system in the brain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;  In studies with rats, cocaine has been shown to cause [[apoptosis]] (programmed cell death) in fetuses; this could be a mechanism for some of the abnormalities of the heart associated with PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  

&lt;!-- BLOOD VESSELS --&gt;
The ways in which cocaine affects a fetus are poorly understood, but one possibility is that it harms the fetus in part by interfering with blood supply to the uterus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson08&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFAronson|Aronson]] p. 512–14&lt;/ref&gt;  The reduction in blood flow to the uterus limits the delivery of oxygen and nutrients to the fetus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;  The reduced blood flow to the uterus may also play a role in congenital malformations and slowed fetal growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  For example, it may be this reduction in blood flow that leads to gut damage in the infant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;  Cocaine causes changes in the mother's [[blood pressure]] that are thought to be the cause of [[stroke]]s in the fetus; one study found that 6% of cocaine-exposed infants had had one or more strokes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;  Such prenatal strokes may be the cause of neurological problems found in some cocaine-exposed infants after birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg228&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFGoldberg|Goldberg]] p.228&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--
-- PREMATURITY --&gt;
Blood vessel contraction can also cause [[premature labor]] and birth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;  Cocaine has also been found to enhance the contractility of the tissue in the [[uterus]], another factor that has been suggested as a possible mechanism for its contribution to increased prematurity rates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson08&quot;/&gt;  Increased contractility of the uterus may also be behind the increased likelihood of [[placental abruption]] (the placenta tearing away from the uterine wall) which some findings have linked with PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Volpe1025&quot;/&gt;

==Diagnosis==
Cocaine use during pregnancy can be discovered by asking the mother, but sometimes women will not admit to having used drugs; this &quot;maternal interview&quot; method has been found to be less reliable for discovering cocaine use than for other drugs such as marijuana.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ostrea01&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11241040}}&lt;/ref&gt; More reliable methods for detecting cocaine exposure involve testing the newborn's hair or [[meconium]] (the infant's earliest stool).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ostrea01&quot;/&gt;  Hair analysis, however, can give [[false positive]]s for cocaine exposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ostrea01&quot;/&gt;  The mother's urine can also be tested for drugs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;

==Effects and prognosis==
&lt;!-- TIMING --&gt; 
Drug use in the first trimester is the most harmful to the fetus in terms of neurological and developmental outcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;/&gt;  The effects of PCE later in a child's life are poorly understood; there is little information about the effects of in utero cocaine exposure on children over age five.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;   Cocaine exposure in utero may affect the structure and function of the brain, predisposing children to developmental problems later, or these effects may be explained by children of crack-using mothers being at higher risk for [[domestic violence]], [[insensitive parenting]], and [[major depressive disorder|maternal depression]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  Some studies have found PCE-related differences in height and weight while others have not; these differences are generally gone or small by the time children are school-age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  When researchers are able to identify effects that result from PCE, these effects are typically small.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;/&gt;

Some effects of PCE have been demonstrated with high exposures to cocaine but not with low ones.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Premature infant with ventilator.jpg|thumb|left|Prematurely born baby]]
Studies have found that children exposed to cocaine during fetal development experience problems with language, behavior, development, and attention.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lester10&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|20407981}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Some, but not all, PCE children experience [[hypertonia]] (excessive [[muscle tone]]), problems with attention, or delays in brain growth or language.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;/&gt;  However, systematic reviews have found that after controlling for other factors that could be misleading, there is no evidence that fetal crack exposure causes problems different from those caused by other risk factors to which those fetuses are exposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11268270}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As many as 17–27% of cocaine-using pregnant women deliver prematurely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson08&quot;/&gt;  There are also data showing that [[spontaneous abortion]] and [[low birth weight]] are associated with cocaine use.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;/&gt;  The increased risk of [[placental abruption]] with cocaine use has been well documented.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  Using cocaine while pregnant also heightens the chances of maternal and fetal vitamin deficiencies, [[Infant respiratory distress syndrome|respiratory distress syndrome]] for the baby, and [[infarction]] of the bowels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08241&quot;/&gt;

Early reports found that cocaine-exposed babies were at high risk for [[sudden infant death syndrome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer05&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|16143741}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, by itself, cocaine exposure during fetal development has not subsequently been identified as a risk factor for the syndrome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- Withdrawal --&gt;
While newborns who were exposed prenatally to drugs such as [[barbiturates]] or [[heroin]] frequently have symptoms of drug [[withdrawal]] ([[Neonatal withdrawal|neonatal abstinence syndrome]]), this does not happen with babies exposed to crack in utero; at least, such symptoms are difficult to separate in the context of other factors such as [[prematurity]] or prenatal exposure to other drugs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;

Unlike [[fetal alcohol syndrome]], no set of characteristics has been discovered that results uniquely from cocaine exposure in utero.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;/&gt;  Much is still not known about what factors may exist to aid children who were exposed to cocaine in utero.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFDoweiko|Doweiko]] p.240&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mental, emotional, and behavioral outcomes===
&lt;!-- IQ --&gt;
Little evidence suggests a link between fetal cocaine exposure and  problems with cognitive development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;  In [[IQ]] studies, cocaine-exposed children score no lower than others, and children exposed to marijuana and alcohol in utero were at the same level as those who were exposed to those drugs in addition to cocaine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;  In school-age and younger children, PCE does not appear in studies to predispose children to poorer intellectual performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  However, results of studies aiming to measure mental performance have been mixed, with some reporting measurable deficits in cocaine-exposed babies and others showing no differences between cocaine-exposed and control groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Messinger04&quot;/&gt;  Studies of developmental delays have also been mixed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- BRAIN GROWTH --&gt;
Cocaine causes impaired growth of the fetus's brain, an effect that is most pronounced with high levels of cocaine and prolonged duration of exposure throughout all three trimesters of pregnancy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|15380830}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Those PCE children who had slowed brain growth as fetuses are at higher risk for impaired brain growth and motor, language and attention problems after they are born.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- COGNITIVE, ATTENTION, LANGUAGE --&gt;
Cognitive and attention skills can be impacted by PCE, possibly due to effects on brain areas such as the [[prefrontal cortex]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;   Children whose mothers used cocaine during pregnancy may develop symptoms akin to those of [[attention deficit disorder]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;  Language development has also been found in some studies to be impacted by PCE,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;/&gt; but language studies have failed to reliably show a detriment caused by ''in utero'' cocaine exposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt; 

&lt;!-- BEHAVIOR --&gt;
Evidence suggests that in utero cocaine exposure leads to problems with behavior and sustained [[attention]], possibly by affecting parts of the brain that are vulnerable to [[toxin]]s during fetal development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  The changes in behavior and attention caused by PCE are measurable by standardized scales;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;/&gt; however these behavioral effects seem to be mild.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;

===Physical outcomes===
PCE may interfere with the way the motor system matures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ren04&quot;/&gt;  Reports on whether PCE affects motor functioning are mixed, with some reporting measurable deficits and others reporting none.&lt;ref name=&quot;Messinger04&quot;/&gt;  Some, but not all, studies have found impairments in development of [[motor skill]]s in cocaine-exposed babies younger than seven months (but not older); however, this finding could be attributed to a failure to control for in utero tobacco exposure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;

&lt;!-- ===Birth defects=== --&gt;
&lt;!-- WHAT --&gt;
A review of the literature reported that cocaine use causes [[congenital defect]]s between 15 and 20% of the time; however another large-scale study found no difference in rates of birth anomalies in PCE and non-PCE infants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFAronson|Aronson]] p. 517&lt;/ref&gt;  Most PCE-related congenital defects are found in the brain, heart, [[genitourinary tract]], arms and legs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt;  Abnormalities in the development of the heart both before and after birth have been linked to PCE; the mechanism by which this occurs is poorly understood.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|15685202}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Heart malformations can include a missing [[Ventricle (heart)|ventricle]] and defects with the [[septum]] of the heart, and can result in potentially deadly [[congestive heart failure]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;    Cocaine  use by pregnant mothers may directly or indirectly contribute to defects in the formation of the [[circulatory system]] and is associated with abnormalities in development of the [[aorta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson08&quot;/&gt;  Genital malformations  occur at a higher-than-normal rate with PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt; The liver and lungs &lt;!-- and genitals --&gt; are also at higher risk for abnormalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt; [[Cloverleaf skull]], a congenital malformation in which the [[human skull|skull]] has three lobes, the brain is deformed, and [[hydrocephalus]] occurs, is also associated with PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson520&quot;&gt;[[#CITEREFAronson|Aronson]] p. 520&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- WHY --&gt;
It is not well understood why cocaine exposure is associated with congenital malformations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feng05&quot;/&gt;  It has been suggested that some of these birth defects could be due to cocaine's disruption of blood vessel growth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt;

==Epidemiology==
[[File:Smoking Crack.jpg|thumb|right|Up to 3% of pregnant women worldwide use cocaine.]]

An estimated 0.5 to 3% of pregnant women worldwide use cocaine.&lt;ref name=&quot;PMID20159194&quot;/&gt;  
In some parts of North America, the rate of cocaine use by pregnant women is as much as 10–45%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt;  In the US, almost 90% of women who abuse drugs are of childbearing age.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strathearn10&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite pmid|12972835}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 1995 survey in the US found that between 30,000 and 160,000 cases of prenatal exposure to cocaine occur each year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey04&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|15019425}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By one estimate, in the US 100,000 babies are born each year after having been exposed to crack cocaine in utero.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson08&quot;/&gt;  Pregnant women in urban parts of the US and who are of a low [[socioeconomic status]] use cocaine more often.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11960537}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the real [[prevalence]] of cocaine use by pregnant women is unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doweiko08240&quot;/&gt;

==Legal and ethical issues==
The harm to a child from PCE has implications for public policy and law.  Some US states have pressed charges against pregnant women who use drugs, including [[child abuse]], [[homicide]], and distribution of drugs to a minor; however these approaches have generally been rejected in the courts on the basis that a fetus is not legally a child.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|12680368}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Between 1985 and 2001, more than 200 women in over 30 US states faced prosecution for drug use during pregnancy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;  In South Carolina, a woman who used crack in her third [[trimester of pregnancy]] was sentenced to prison for eight years when her child was born with cocaine [[metabolite]]s in its system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;/&gt;  The Supreme Court of South Carolina upheld this conviction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;/&gt;  From 1989 to 1994, in the midst of public outcry about cocaine babies, the Medical University of South Carolina tested pregnant women for cocaine, reporting those who tested positive to the police.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annas01&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|11386286}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Supreme Court of the United States|US Supreme Court]] found the policy to be unacceptable on [[United States Constitution|constitutional]] grounds in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annas01&quot;/&gt;

Some advocates argue that punishment for crack-using pregnant women as a means to treat their addiction is a violation of their right to privacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;/&gt;  According to studies, fear of prosecution and having children taken away is associated with a refusal to seek prenatal care or medical treatment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson09&quot;/&gt;

Some nonprofit organizations aim to prevent PCE with [[birth control]]. One such initiative, [[Project Prevention]], offers crack-addicted women money as an incentive to undergo long-term birth control or, frequently, [[Human sterilization (surgical procedure)|sterilization]]—an approach which has brought it under fire for [[eugenics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hardtalk&quot;/&gt;

==Social stigma==
Children who were exposed to crack prenatally face social stigma as babies and school-aged children; some experts say that the &quot;crack baby&quot; [[social stigma]] is more harmful than the PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;/&gt;   Teachers may expect these children to be disruptive and [[developmental disability|developmentally delayed]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;  Children who were exposed to cocaine may be teased by others who know of the exposure, and problems these children have may be misdiagnosed by doctors or others as resulting from PCE when they may really be due to factors like illness or abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09&quot;/&gt;  

The social stigma of the drug also complicates studies of PCE; researchers labor under the awareness that their findings will have political implications.&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09&quot;/&gt;  In addition, the perceived hopelessness of 'crack babies' may cause researchers to ignore possibilities for early intervention that could help them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldberg228&quot;/&gt;  The social stigma may turn out to be a [[self-fulfilling prophecy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Connors07&quot;/&gt;

==Research==
&lt;!-- ORIGINAL STUDIES WERE FLAWED --&gt;
A number of the effects that had been thought after early studies to be attributable to prenatal exposure to cocaine are actually due partially or wholly to other factors, such as exposure to other substances (including [[tobacco]], [[alcoholic beverage|alcohol]], or [[marijuana]]) or to the environment in which the child is raised.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt;  Some effects (such as head [[circumference]], [[body weight]], and height) that appear in studies to result from prenatal cocaine exposure disappear when studies control for prenatal exposure to other drugs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;  

&lt;!-- OTHER FACTORS --&gt;
PCE is very difficult to study because of a variety of factors that may confound the results: pre- and postnatal care may be poor; the pregnant mother and child may be [[malnutrition|malnourished]]; the amount of cocaine a mother takes can vary; she may take a variety of drugs during pregnancy in addition to cocaine; measurements for detecting deficits may not be sensitive enough; and results that are found may only last a short time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey04&quot;/&gt;   PCE is clustered with other risk factors to the child such as maltreatment, [[domestic violence]], and prenatal exposure to other substances.&lt;ref name=&quot;Aronson517&quot;/&gt;  Such environmental factors are known to adversely affect children in the same areas being studied with respect to PCE.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;  Most women who use cocaine while pregnant use other drugs too.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richardson93&quot;&gt;{{cite pmid|8513626}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Addiction to any substance, including crack, may be a risk factor for child abuse or [[child neglect|neglect]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt; Crack addiction, like other addictions, distracts parents from the child and leads to inattentive parenting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt; Many drug users do not get [[prenatal care]], for a variety of reasons including that they may not know they are pregnant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrus02&quot;/&gt;  Many crack addicts get no medical care at all and have extremely poor diets, and children who around crack smoking are at risk of inhaling [[secondary smoke]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;/&gt;  Cocaine using mothers also have a higher rate of to [[sexually transmitted infection]]s such as [[HIV]] and [[hepatitis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bauer05&quot;/&gt;  Drug use by mothers puts children at high risk for environmental problems, and PCE does not present much risk beyond these risk factors that occur alongside it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  In some cases, it is not clear whether direct results of PCE lead to behavioral problems, or whether environmental factors are at fault.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  For examples, it may be that children who have caregiver instability have more behavioral problems as a result, or it may be that behavioral problems manifested by PCE children lead to greater turnover in caregivers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackerman10&quot;/&gt;  Other factors that make studying PCE difficult include high rates of attrition (loss of participants) from studies, unwillingness of mothers to tell the truth about drug history, and uncertainty of dosages of street drugs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singer02&quot;/&gt;

The difficulties in isolating crack exposure and other difficulties with studies mean that although many effects previously thought to have been attributable to crack exposure in utero have not been found, undiscovered effects may emerge as pressures on children grow as they reach school age and puberty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frank01&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;Connors07&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Connors GJ; Maisto SA; Galizio M
|title=Drug Use and Abuse
|publisher=Wadsworth Publishing
|location=Belmont, CA
|year=2007
|pages=136
|isbn=0-495-09207-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hardtalk&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/programmes/hardtalk/8689070.stm
 |title=Sterilisation for drug addicts?
 |work=news.bbc.co.uk
|BBC News: Hardtalk
|date = May 18, 2010
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lavoie07&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url= http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2007-12-24-2050621119_x.htm
 |title=Crack-vs.-powder disparity is questioned 
|author = Lavoie D
|date = December 25, 2007
|publisher = [[USA Today]]
 |work=usatoday.com
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Mercer09&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|author=Mercer, J
|chapter=Claim 9: &quot;Crack babies&quot; can't be cured and will always have serious problems
|title=Child Development: Myths and Misunderstandings
|publisher=Sage Publications, Inc
|location=Thousand Oaks, Calif
|year=2009
|pages=62–64
|isbn=1-4129-5646-3
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=August 11, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NPR&quot;&gt;
{{Cite web
 |url= http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=126478643
|author = Martin M.
 |title=Crack Babies: Twenty Years Later 
|publisher=[[National Public Radio]]
|date=May 3, 2010
 |work=npr.org
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
|author =Okie S.
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/27/health/27coca.html
 |title=Crack Babies: The Epidemic That Wasn't
 |work=nytimes.com
|date = January 26, 2009
|publisher=[[The New York Times]]
 |accessdate=August 11, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Okie09Encouraging&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2009/01/27/world/americas/27iht-coca.3.19716510.html
 |title=Encouraging new on babies born to cocaine-abusing mothers
|publisher=[[The New York Times]]
|author = Okie S
|date = February 7, 2009
 |work=nytimes.com
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ornes&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url= http://discovermagazine.com/2006/dec/crack-baby-unfounded-stigma
|author = Ornes S
|date = December 2006
|publisher = [[Discover Magazine]]
 |title=What Ever Happened to Crack Babies? | Family Health | DISCOVER Magazine
 |work=discovermagazine.com
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Strathearn10&quot;&gt;{{cite journal 
|author= Strathearn L; Mayes LC
|title= Cocaine addiction in mothers: Potential effects on maternal care and infant development 
|journal= Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences
|volume= 1187
|issue= 
|pages= 172–85 
|year= 2010
|pmid= 20201853
|doi= 
10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.05142.x|pmc= 
|url=
|bibcode=2010NYASA1187..172S
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Vargas10&quot;&gt;{{Cite web
 |url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/04/15/AR2010041502434.html?hpid=moreheadlines
 |title=Once written off, 'crack babies' have grown into success stories
|author = Vargas T.
|date=April 18, 2010
|publisher=[[The Washington Post]]
 |work=washingtonpost.com
 |accessdate=August 12, 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

=== Selected Bibliography ===
*{{cite book
|author=Aronson JK
|chapter=Cocaine
|title=Meyler's Side Effects of Psychiatric Drugs
|publisher=Elsevier Science
|location=Amsterdam
|year=2008
|pages=
|isbn=0-444-53266-8
|oclc=
|doi=
|accessdate=August 12, 2010
|ref=CITEREFAronson
}}
*{{cite book
|author=Doweiko, HE
|title=Concepts of Chemical Dependency
|publisher=Wadsworth Publishing
|location=Belmont, CA
|year=2008
|pages=
|isbn=0-495-50580-3
|oclc=
|doi=
|ref = CITEREFDoweiko
|accessdate=
}}
*{{cite book
|author=Goldberg R
|title=Drugs Across the Spectrum
|chapter=Cocaine amphetamines 
|publisher=Brooks Cole
|location=Pacific Grove
|year=2009
|pages=
|isbn=0-495-55793-5
|oclc=
|doi=
|ref = CITEREFGoldberg
|accessdate=
}}
*{{cite book
|author=Volpe, JJ
|title=Neurology of the Newborn 
|chapter=Teratogenic effects of drugs and passive addiction
|publisher=Saunders
|location=Philadelphia
|year=2008
|pages=
|isbn=1-4160-3995-3
|oclc=
|doi=
|ref = CITEREFVolpe
|accessdate=
}}
*{{cite book
|author=Yaffe, SJ; Briggs, GG; Freeman, RA
|title=Drugs in pregnancy and lactation: A reference guide to fetal and neonatal risk
|chapter = Cocaine
|publisher=Wolters Kluwer Health/Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins
|location=Philadelphia
|year=2008
|pages=
|isbn=0-7817-7876-X
|oclc=
|doi=
|ref = CITEREFYaffe
|accessdate=
}}
*{{cite book|last=Lewis and Kestler|title=Gender Differences in Prenatal Substance Exposure|year=2011|publisher=Amer Psychological Society|isbn=978-1433810336}}
*{{cite book|last=Soby|first=Jeanette M.|title=Prenatal Exposure to Drugs/Alcohol: Characteristics And Educational Implications of Fetal Alcohol Syndrome And Cocaine/polydrug Effects|year=2006|publisher=Charles C. Thomas Ltd.|isbn=978-0398076351}}
*{{cite book|last=Steinberg, Wenzel, Kosofsky, Harvey, and Iguchi|title=Prenatal Cocaine Exposure: Scientific Considerations and Policy Implications|year=2001|publisher=RAND Drug Policy Research Center and NY Academy of Sciences|location=2001|isbn=978-0833030016}}


{{Drug use}}
{{Congenital malformation due to exogenous toxicity}}

[[Category:Cocaine]]
[[Category:Health issues in pregnancy|Cocaine]]
[[Category:Congenital malformation due to exogenous toxicity]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
