<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28413934" ns="0" title="WVSU in Janiuay"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox University
|image   =  
|name           = West Visayas State University
|nickname       = Taga-WEST
|motto          = &quot;Service, Harmony, Excellence&quot;
|established    = 1902(system)&lt;br&gt;1946 (campus)
|type = [[State University System|State University]]
|president = Dr. Pablo E. Subong, Jr. (Ed. D., Ph. D.)
|free_label = Administrator
|free = Dr. Raymund B. Gemora (Ed.D.)
|city = [[Janiuay, Iloilo|Janiuay]]
|state = [[Iloilo province|Iloilo]]
|country        = [[Image:Flag of the Philippines.svg|15px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Philippines]]
|nickname = Taga-West
|campus         = [[Sub-Urban]]
|colors         = &lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;█  &lt;/FONT&gt;&lt;font color=gold&gt;█ 
|athletics      = [[SCUAA]]
}}


BORN A HIGH SCHOOL, ONCE A COLLEGE, NOW A UNIVERSITY


	Janiuay High School came into birth on July 5, 1946 through the efforts of the late Hon. Tiburcio A. Lutero, then congressman of the Third District of Iloilo. Located on a sprawling land area of 9.7 hectares (90, 700 square meters), it was the first public high school in the municipality and strategically situated in the town center of Janiuay, Iloilo.

	The conversion of Janiuay High School into Janiuay National Vocational School on July 1, 1960 under R.A. 2411 authored by the late congressman Domitilo G. Abordo, ushered in the “Vocational Period” in the school’s history.

	In July 1972, the school became Janiuay National Comprehensive High School by virtue of the law authored by a lady congressman from the Third District of Iloilo, Hon. Gloria M. Tabiana. A two-year technical college was opened to cater to the manpower needs of the community and the country as well.

	In 1986, the school celebrated its 40th anniversary, the Ruby Jubilee Year.

	Under R.A. 6667 dated June 22, 1990, authored by then congressman, Hon. Licurgo P. Tirador, renamed the school to Don Tiburcio A. Lutero National Comprehensive High School, in honor of its founder, the late congressman Tiburcio Alianza Lutero.

	On January 1, 1996, the school was converted to Janiuay Polytechnic College, by virtue of R.A. 7974, again authored by Hon. Licurgo P. Tirador. It also celebrated its Golden Anniversary – 50 years of quality service – that same year. During the span of fifty years, several changes have taken place: the name of the school, the curricular offerings and the school heads. Despite these changes, one thing remained – its commitment to service and delivery of quality education.

	After almost five years as a Polytechnic College, it was integrated to West Visayas State University on November 23, 2000 in consonance with CHED Memorandum Order No. 27, series of 2000 which contained the implementing guidelines on integration of CHED Supervised Institutions (CSIs) to State Universities and Colleges (SUCs), by virtue of R.A. 7722, otherwise known as the “Higher Education Act of 1994” and R.A. 8292, otherwise known as the “Higher Education Modernization Act of 1997”.

	From then and onwards, Janiuay Polytechnic College has become known as West Visayas State University – Janiuay Campus.  The current campus administrator is Dr. Raymund Banquillo Gemora.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{WestVi}}

[[Category:West Visayas State University System]]
[[Category:Higher education in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1946]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
