<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28431" ns="0" title="Space exploration"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Ap4-s67-50531.jpg|thumb|260px|Saturn V rocket, used for the American manned lunar landing missions]]
'''Space exploration''' is the use of [[space technology]] to explore [[outer space]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://adc.gsfc.nasa.gov/adc/education/space_ex/exploration.html | title = How Space is Explored | publisher = NASA}}{{Dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Physical [[exploration]] of space is conducted both by [[human spaceflight]]s and by [[robotic spacecraft]].
While the observation of objects in space, known as [[astronomy]], predates reliable [[recorded history]], it was the development of large and relatively efficient [[rocket]]s during the early 20th century that allowed physical space exploration to become a reality. Common rationales for exploring space include advancing scientific research, uniting different nations, ensuring the future survival of humanity and developing military and strategic advantages against other countries. Various criticisms of space exploration are sometimes made.

Space exploration has often been used as a proxy competition for geopolitical rivalries such as the [[Cold War]]. The early era of space exploration was driven by a &quot;[[Space Race]]&quot; between the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[United States]], the launch of the first man-made object to orbit the [[Earth]], the USSR's [[Sputnik 1]], on October 4, 1957, and the first [[Moon]] landing by the American [[Apollo 11]] craft on July 20, 1969 are often taken as the boundaries for this initial period. The [[Soviet space program]] achieved many of the first milestones, including the first living being in orbit in 1957, the first [[human spaceflight]] ([[Yuri Gagarin]] aboard [[Vostok 1]]) in 1961, the first [[spacewalk]] (by [[Aleksei Leonov]]) in 1965, the [[Luna 9|first automatic landing]] on another celestial body in 1966, and the launch of the first [[space station]] ([[Salyut 1]]) in 1971.

After the first 20 years of exploration, focus shifted from one-off flights to renewable hardware, such as the [[Space Shuttle program]], and from competition to cooperation as with the [[International Space Station]] (ISS).

With the substantial completion of the ISS&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.space.com/11078-space-station-complete.html  &quot;After 13 Years, International Space Station Has All Its NASA Rooms&quot;] Denise Chow, SPACE.com, March 9, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; following [[STS-133]] in March 2011, plans for space exploration by the USA remain in flux. [[Constellation program|Constellation]], a Bush Administration program for a return to the Moon by 2020&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nasa.gov/pdf/163092main_constellation_program_overview.pdf|title=Constellation Program Overview|format=PDF|last=Connolly|first=John F.|month=October|year=2006|publisher=Constellation Program Office|accessdate=July 6, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; was judged inadequately funded and unrealistic by [[Review of United States Human Space Flight Plans Committee|an expert review panel]] reporting in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.sciencemag.org/scienceinsider/2009/10/no-nasa-augusti.html &quot;No to NASA: Augustine Commission Wants to More Boldly Go&quot; ] ''Science'', Andrew Lawler, October 22, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  The Obama Administration proposed a revision of Constellation in 2010 to focus on the development of the capability for crewed missions beyond [[low earth orbit]] (LEO), envisioning extending the operation of the [[ISS]] beyond 2020, transferring the development of launch vehicles for human crews from NASA to the private sector, and developing technology to enable missions to beyond LEO, such as  [[Lagrangian point|Earth/Moon L1]], the Moon, [[Lagrangian point|Earth/Sun L2]], near-earth asteroids, and [[Phobos (moon)|Phobos]] or Mars orbit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasa.gov/about/obamaspeechfeature_prt.htm ] Address at KSC 4/15/2010.  &quot;President Outlines Exploration Goals, Promise&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  As of March 2011, the US Senate and House of Representatives are still working towards a compromise NASA funding bill, which will probably terminate Constellation and fund development of a [[heavy lift launch vehicle]] (HLLV).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spacenews.com/policy/110307-senate-bill-provide-orion-heavy-lifter.html&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2000s, the [[People's Republic of China]] initiated a [[Chinese space program|successful manned spaceflight program]], while the [[European Union]], [[Japan]], and [[India]] have also planned future manned space missions. China, Russia, Japan, and India have advocated manned missions to the Moon during the 21st century, while the European Union has advocated [[Aurora programme|manned missions to both the Moon and Mars]] during the 21st century.  From the 1990s onwards, private interests began promoting [[space tourism]] and then private space exploration of the Moon (see [[Google Lunar X Prize]]).

==History of exploration in the 20th Century==

{{See also|Timeline of space exploration|History of astronomy|Timeline of first orbital launches by country}}
[[Image:Atmosphere layers-en.svg|thumb|left|upright|Most orbital flight actually takes place in upper layers of the atmosphere, especially in the thermosphere (not to scale)]]
[[File:Bumper8 launch-GPN-2000-000613.jpg|thumb|right|200px|In July 1950 the first Bumper rocket is launched from Cape Canaveral, Florida. The [[Bumper (rocket)|Bumper]] was a two-stage rocket consisting of a Post-War [[V-2 missile|V-2]] topped by a [[WAC Corporal]] rocket. It could reach then-record altitudes of almost 400 km. Launched by General Electric Company, this Bumper was used primarily for testing rocket systems and for research on the upper atmosphere. They carried small payloads that allowed them to measure attributes including air temperature and cosmic ray impacts.]]

The first steps of putting a man-made object into space were taken by German scientists during [[World War II]] while testing the [[V2 rocket]] which became the first human-made object in space on October 3, 1942 with the launching of V-4. After the war, the U.S. [[Operation Paperclip|used German scientists]] and their captured rockets in programs for both military and civilian research. The first scientific exploration from space was the cosmic radiation experiment launched by the U.S. on a V2 rocket on May 10, 1946. The first images of Earth taken from space followed the same year while the [[animals in space|first animal experiment]] saw fruit flies lifted into space in 1947, both also on modified V2s launched by Americans. Starting in 1947, the Soviets, also with the help of German teams, launched sub-orbital V2 rockets and their own variant, the [[R-1 (missile)|R-1]], including radiation and animal experiments on some flights. These [[Sub-orbital spaceflight|suborbital]] experiments only allowed a very short time in space which limited their usefulness.

;First flights

[[Image:Sputnik asm.jpg|thumb|right|200px|[[Sputnik 1]], the first artificial [[satellite]] orbited earth at {{convert|939|km|mi|abbr=on}} to {{convert|215|km|mi|abbr=on}} in 1957, and was soon followed by [[Sputnik 2]]. See [[Satellite#First_satellites_of_countries|First satellite by country]] (Replica Pictured) ]]

The first successful orbital launch was of the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] unmanned [[Sputnik 1|''Sputnik 1'' (&quot;Satellite 1&quot;)]] mission on October 4, 1957. The satellite weighed about 83&amp;nbsp;kg (184 pounds), and is believed to have orbited Earth at a height of about {{convert|250|km|mi|abbr=on}}. It had two radio transmitters (20 and 40&amp;nbsp;MHz), which emitted &quot;beeps&quot; that could be heard by radios around the globe. Analysis of the radio signals was used to gather information about the electron density of the ionosphere, while temperature and pressure data was encoded in the duration of radio beeps. The results indicated that the satellite was not punctured by a [[meteoroid]]. Sputnik 1 was launched by an [[R-7 Semyorka|R-7]] rocket. It burned up upon re-entry on January 3, 1958.

This success led to an escalation of the American [[space program]], which unsuccessfully attempted to launch [[Vanguard TV3|a Vanguard satellite]] into orbit two months later. On January 31, 1958, the U.S. successfully orbited [[Explorer 1]] on a Juno rocket. In the meantime, the Soviet dog [[Laika]] became the first animal in orbit on November 3, 1957.
;First human flights

The first successful human spaceflight was ''[[Vostok 1]]'' (&quot;East 1&quot;), carrying 27 year old Russian [[cosmonaut]] [[Yuri Gagarin]] on April 12, 1961. The spacecraft completed one orbit around the globe, lasting about 1 hour and 48 minutes. Gagarin's flight resonated around the world; it was a demonstration of the advanced [[Soviet space program]] and it opened an entirely new era in space exploration: [[human spaceflight]].

&lt;!-- image deleted [[Image:Gagarin space suite.jpg|thumb|right|150px|[[Yuri Gagarin]], the first man in space]] --&gt;
[[File:Apollo CSM lunar orbit.jpg|thumb|right|!50px|Apollo CSM in lunar orbit]]

The U.S. first launched a person into space within a month of [[Vostok 1]] with [[Alan Shepard]]'s suborbital flight in [[Mercury-Redstone 3]].  Orbital flight was achieved by the United States when [[John Glenn]]'s [[Mercury-Atlas 6]] orbited the Earth on February 20, 1962.

[[Valentina Tereshkova]], the first woman in space, orbited the Earth 48 times aboard [[Vostok 6]] on June 16, 1963.

China first launched a person into space 42 years after the launch of Vostok 1, on October 15, 2003, with the flight of [[Yang Liwei]] aboard the [[Shenzhou 5]] (Spaceboat 5) spacecraft.

;First planetary explorations
The first artificial object to reach another celestial body was [[Luna 2]] in 1959.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sse.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/profile.cfm?Sort=Target&amp;Target=Moon&amp;MCode=Luna_02 NASA on Luna 2 mission]&lt;/ref&gt; The first automatic landing on another celestial body was performed by [[Luna 9]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://sse.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/profile.cfm?Sort=Target&amp;Target=Moon&amp;MCode=Luna_09 NASA on Luna 9 mission]&lt;/ref&gt; in 1966. [[Luna 10]] became the first artificial satellite of another celestial body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sse.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/profile.cfm?Sort=Target&amp;Target=Moon&amp;MCode=Luna_10 NASA on Luna 10 mission]&lt;/ref&gt;

The first manned landing on another celestial body was performed by [[Apollo 11]] in its lunar landing on July 20, 1969.

The first successful interplanetary flyby was the 1962 [[Mariner 2]] flyby of [[Venus]] (closest approach 34,773 kilometers).  Flybys for the other planets were first achieved in 1965 for [[Mars]] by [[Mariner 4]], 1973 for [[Jupiter]] by [[Pioneer 10]], 1974 for [[Mercury (planet)|Mercury]] by [[Mariner 10]], 1979 for [[Saturn]] by [[Pioneer 11]], 1986 for [[Uranus]] by [[Voyager 2]], and 1989 for [[Neptune]] by Voyager 2.

The first interplanetary surface mission to return at least limited surface data from another planet was the 1970 landing of [[Venera 7]] on Venus which returned data to earth for 23 minutes.  In 1971 the [[Mars 3]] mission achieved the first soft landing on Mars returning data for almost 20 seconds.  Later much longer duration surface missions were achieved, including over 6 years of Mars surface operation by [[Viking 1]] from 1975 to 1982 and over 2 hours of transmission from the surface of Venus by [[Venera 13]] in 1982 (the longest ever Soviet planetary surface mission).

;Key people in early space exploration
The dream of stepping into the outer reaches of the Earth's atmosphere was driven by the fiction of [[Jules Verne]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.russianspaceweb.com/tsiolkovsky_bio.html Tsiolkovsky biography]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centennialofflight.gov/essay/SPACEFLIGHT/oberth/SP2.htm Herman Oberth]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://history.msfc.nasa.gov/vonbraun/bio.html Von Braun]&lt;/ref&gt; and [[H.G.Wells]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://genesismission.jpl.nasa.gov/people/biographies/goddard.pdf Goddard Biography]&lt;/ref&gt; and rocket technology was developed to try to realise this vision. The German [[V-2 rocket|V2]] was the first rocket to travel into space, overcoming the problems of thrust and material failure. During the final days of World War II this technology was obtained by both the Americans and Soviets as were its designers. The initial driving force for further development of the technology was a weapons race for intercontinental ballistic missiles ([[ICBM]]s) to be used as long-range carriers for fast [[nuclear weapon]] delivery, but in 1961 when [[USSR]] launched the first man into space, the U.S. declared itself to be in a &quot;[[Space Race]]&quot; with Russia.

* '''[[Konstantin Tsiolkovsky]], [[Robert Goddard]], [[Hermann Oberth]]''', and '''[[Reinhold Tiling]]''' laid the groundwork of rocketry in the early years of the 20th century.
*'''[[Wernher von Braun]]''' was the lead rocket engineer for [[Nazi]] Germany's World War II [[V-2 rocket]] project. In the last days of the war he led a caravan of workers in the German rocket program to the American lines, where they surrendered and were brought to the USA to work on U.S. rocket development (&quot;[[Operation Paperclip]]&quot;). He acquired American citizenship and led the team that developed and launched [[Explorer 1]], the first American satellite. Von Braun later led the team at [[NASA]]'s [[Marshall Space Flight Center]] which developed the [[Saturn V]] moon rocket.
*Initially the race for space was often led by '''[[Sergei Korolyov]]''', whose legacy includes both the [[R-7 Semyorka|R7]] and [[Soyuz spacecraft|Soyuz]]—which remain in service to this day. Korolev was the mastermind behind the first satellite, first man (and first woman) in orbit and first spacewalk. Until his death his identity was a closely guarded state secret; not even his mother knew that he was responsible for creating the Russian space program.
*'''[[Kerim Kerimov]]''' was one of the founders of the [[Soviet space program]] and was one of the lead architects behind the first [[human spaceflight]] ([[Vostok 1]]) alongside Sergey Korolyov. After Korolyov's death in 1966, Kerimov became the lead scientist of the Soviet space program and was responsible for the launch of the first [[space station]]s from 1971 to 1991, including the [[Salyut]] and [[Mir]] series, and their precursors in 1967, the [[Cosmos 186]] and [[Cosmos 188]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |last=Bond |first=Peter |publication-date=7 April 2003 |title=Obituary: Lt-Gen Kerim Kerimov |periodical=The Independent |publication-place=London |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20030407/ai_n12692130  |accessdate=2010-11-21 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080108073958/http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4158/is_20030407/ai_n12692130 |archivedate = 2008-01-08 |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Blair Betty | year = 1995 | title = Behind Soviet Aeronauts | url = | journal = [[Azerbaijan International]] | volume = 3 | issue = | page = 3 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Robert Gilruth S87-26820.jpg|thumb|right|100px|Robert Gilruth]]
Other key people included:
*'''[[Valentin Glushko]]''' held the role of Chief Engine Designer for USSR. Glushko designed many of the engines used on the early Soviet rockets, but was constantly at odds with Korolyov.
*'''[[Vasily Mishin]]''' was Chief Designer working under Sergey Korolyov and one of first Soviets to inspect the captured German V2 design. Following the death of Sergei Korolev, Mishin was held responsible for the Soviet failure to be first country to place a man on the moon.
*'''[[Bob Gilruth]]''' was the [[NASA]] head of the Space Task Force and director of 25 manned space flights. Gilruth was the person who suggested to [[John F. Kennedy]] that the Americans take the bold step of reaching the Moon in an attempt to reclaim space superiority from the Soviets.
*'''[[Christopher C. Kraft, Jr.]]''' was NASA's first [[flight controller|flight director]], who oversaw development of [[Mission Control]] and associated technologies and procedures.
*'''[[Maxime Faget]]''' was the designer of the [[Project Mercury|Mercury]] capsule; he played a key role in designing the [[Project Gemini|Gemini]] and [[Project Apollo|Apollo]] spacecraft, and contributed to the design of the [[Space Shuttle]].

==Targets of exploration==
===The Sun===
While the [[Sun]] will probably not be physically explored in the close future, one of the reasons for going into space includes knowing more about the Sun. Once above the atmosphere in particular and the Earth's magnetic field, this gives access to the Solar wind and infrared and ultraviolet radiations that cannot reach the surface of the Earth. The Sun generates most [[space weather]], which can affect power generation and transmission systems on Earth and interfere with, and even damage, satellites and space probes.

[[Image:Mercury in color - Prockter07 centered.jpg|thumb|left|125px|[[MESSENGER]] image of Mercury]][[Image:MESSENGER EN0108828359M.png|thumb|right|125px|A MESSENGER image from 18,000 km showing a region about 500 km across]]

===Mercury===
{{Main|Exploration of Mercury}}
[[Mercury (planet)|Mercury]] remains the least explored of the [[Terrestrial planet|inner planets]]. As of May 2011, the [[Mariner 10]] and [[MESSENGER]] missions have been the only missions that have made close observations of Mercury. [[MESSENGER]] entered orbit around Mercury in March, 2011, to further investigate the observations made by Mariner 10 in 1975 (Munsell, 2006b). A third mission to Mercury, scheduled to arrive in 2020, [[BepiColombo]] is to include two [[space probe|probes]]. BepiColombo is a joint mission between Japan and the [[European Space Agency]]. MESSENGER and BepiColombo are intended to gather complementary data to help scientists understand many of the mysteries discovered by Mariner 10's [[Gravitational slingshot|flybys]].

Flights to other planets within the Solar System are accomplished at a cost in [[energy]], which is described by the net change in velocity of the spacecraft, or [[delta-v]].  Due to the relatively high delta-v to reach Mercury and its proximity to the Sun, it is difficult to explore and orbits around it are rather unstable.

[[Image:Venus-real.jpg|thumb|left|125px|[[Mariner 10]] image of Venus]]

===Venus===
{{Main|Observations and explorations of Venus}}
[[Venus]] was the first target of interplanetary flyby and lander missions and, despite one of the most hostile surface environments in the solar system, has had more landers sent to it (nearly all from the Soviet Union) than any other planet in the solar system.  The first successful Venus flyby was the American [[Mariner 2]] spacecraft, which flew past Venus in 1962.  Mariner 2 has been followed by several other flybys by multiple space agencies often as part of missions using a Venus flyby to provide a [[Gravity assist|gravitational assist]] en route to other celestial bodies.  In 1967 [[Venera 4]] became the first probe to enter and directly examine the atmosphere of Venus.  In 1970 [[Venera 7]] became the first successful lander to reach the surface of Venus and by 1985 it had been followed by eight additional successful Soviet Venus landers which provided images and other direct surface data.  Starting in 1975 with the Soviet orbiter [[Venera 9]] some ten successful orbiter missions have been sent to Venus, including later missions which were able to map the surface of Venus using [[radar]] to pierce the obscuring atmosphere.

[[Image:The Earth seen from Apollo 17.jpg|thumb|left|125px|The &quot;marble&quot; Earth picture taken by [[Apollo 17]]]][[Image:TIROS-1-Earth.png|right|125px|thumb|First television image of Earth from space]]

===Earth===
{{Main|Earth observation satellite}}
Space exploration has been used as a tool to understand the Earth as a celestial object in its own right.  Orbital missions can provide data for the Earth that can be difficult or impossible to obtain from a purely ground-based point of reference.

For example, the existence of the [[Van Allen belts]] was unknown until their discovery by the United States' first artificial satellite, [[Explorer 1]]. These belts contain radiation trapped by the Earth's magnetic fields, which currently renders construction of habitable space stations above 1000&amp;nbsp;km impractical.
Following this early unexpected discovery, a large number of Earth observation satellites have been deployed specifically to explore the Earth from a space based perspective.  These satellites have significantly contributed to the understanding of a variety of earth based phenomena.  For instance, the [[Ozone depletion|hole in the ozone layer]] was found by an artificial satellite that was exploring Earth's atmosphere, and satellites have allowed for the discovery of archeological sites or geological formations that were difficult or impossible to otherwise identify.

[[Image:Full Moon Luc Viatour.jpg|thumb|left|125px|The Moon as seen from the Earth &lt;br /&gt; Luc Viatour (Belgium)]][[Image:Apollo 16 LM Orion.jpg|thumb|right|125px|[[Apollo 16]] astronaut John Young]]

===Earth's Moon===
{{Main|Exploration of the Moon}}

[[Moon|Earth's Moon]] was the first celestial body to be the object of space exploration.  It holds the distinctions of being the first remote celestial object to be flown by, orbited, and landed upon by spacecraft, and the only remote celestial object ever to be visited by humans.

In 1959 the Soviets obtained the first images of the [[far side of the Moon]], never previously visible to humans.  The U.S. exploration of the Moon began with the [[Ranger 4]] impactor in 1962. Starting in 1966 the Soviets successfully deployed a number of [[Lander (spacecraft)|landers]] to the Moon which were able to obtain data directly from the Moon's surface; just four months later, [[Surveyor 1]] marked the debut of a successful series of U.S. landers.  The Soviet unmanned missions culminated in the [[Lunokhod programme|Lunokhod program]] in the early '70s which included the first unmanned rovers and also successfully returned lunar soil samples to the Earth for study.  This marked the first (and to date the only) automated return of extraterrestrial soil samples to the Earth.  Unmanned exploration of the Moon continues with various nations periodically deploying lunar orbiters, and in 2008 the Indian [[Moon Impact Probe]].

Manned exploration of the Moon began in 1968 with the [[Apollo 8]] mission that successfully orbited the Moon, the first time any extraterrestrial object was orbited by humans.  In 1969 the [[Apollo 11]] mission marked the first time humans set foot upon another world.  Manned exploration of the Moon did not continue for long, however.  The [[Apollo 17]] mission in 1972 marked the most recent human visit to another world, and there is no further planned human exploration of an extraterrestrial body, though robotic missions are still pursued vigorously.

[[Image:Mars Hubble.jpg|thumb|left|125px|Mars as seen by the [[Hubble Space Telescope|HST]]]][[Image:Spirit rover tracks.jpg|thumb|right|125px|Part of a panorama taken by the [[Mars Exploration Rover|Spirit rover]] in 2004]]

===Mars===
{{Main|Exploration of Mars}}

The exploration of [[Mars]] has been an important part of the space exploration programs of the Soviet Union (later Russia), the United States, Europe, and Japan.  Dozens of [[robotic spacecraft]], including [[orbiter]]s, [[Lander (spacecraft)|lander]]s, and [[rover (space exploration)|rover]]s, have been launched toward Mars since the 1960s. These missions were aimed at gathering data about current conditions and answering questions about the history of Mars. The questions raised by the scientific community are expected to not only give a better appreciation of the red planet but also yield further insight into the past, and possible future, of Earth.

The exploration of Mars has come at a considerable financial cost with roughly two-thirds of all spacecraft destined for Mars failing before completing their missions, with some failing before they even began. Such a high failure rate can be attributed to the complexity and large number of variables involved in an interplanetary journey, and has led researchers to jokingly speak of ''The Great Galactic Ghoul''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last=Dinerman | first=Taylor | url=http://www.thespacereview.com/article/232/1 | title=Is the Great Galactic Ghoul losing his appetite? | work=The space review | date=September 27, 2004 | accessdate=2007-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; which subsists on a diet of Mars probes. This phenomenon is also informally known as the [[Exploration_of_Mars#Mars_Curse|''Mars Curse'']].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Knight |first=Matthew | url=http://www.cnn.com/2006/TECH/science/12/23/mwonders.mars/index.html | title= Beating the curse of Mars | work=Science &amp; Space | accessdate=2007-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Phobos====
{{Main|Exploration of Phobos}}

The Russian space mission [[Phobos-Grunt]], Scheduled to launch in 2011,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.marsdaily.com/reports/Russia_delays_Mars_probe_launch_until_2012_report_999.html&lt;/ref&gt; will begin exploration of the [[Phobos (moon)|Phobos]] and Martian circumterrestrial orbit, and study whether the moons of Mars, or at least Phobos, could be a &quot;trans-shipment point&quot; for spaceships travelling to Mars.&lt;ref&gt;http://ru.youtube.com/watch?v=W0cUvK0Dgy8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Remove groundless conjecture: It will study Phobos as a target of colonization, too.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}--&gt;

===Asteroids and comets===
{{Main|Exploration of the asteroids}}
[[File:Dawn-image-070911.jpg|thumb|125px|right|Asteroid 4 Vesta, imaged by the [[Dawn (spacecraft)|Dawn spacecraft]]]]
Until the advent of [[Spaceflight|space travel]], objects in the [[asteroid belt]] were merely pinpricks of light in even the largest telescopes,  their shapes and terrain remaining a mystery.
Several asteroids have now been visited by probes, the first of which was ''[[Galileo (spacecraft)|Galileo]]'', which flew past two: [[951 Gaspra]] in 1991, followed by [[243 Ida]] in 1993.  Both of these lay near enough to Galileo's planned trajectory to Jupiter that they could be visited at acceptable cost. The first landing on an asteroid was performed by the [[NEAR Shoemaker]] probe in 2000, following an orbital survey of the object. The dwarf planet [[Ceres (dwarf planet)|Ceres]] and the asteroid [[4 Vesta]], two of the three largest asteroids, are targets of NASA's [[Dawn (spacecraft)|Dawn mission]], launched in 2007.

While many comets have been closely studied from Earth sometimes with centuries-worth of observations, only a few comets have been closely visited. In 1985, the [[International Cometary Explorer]] conducted the first comet fly-by ([[21P/Giacobini-Zinner]]) before joining the [[Halley Armada]] studying the famous comet. The [[Deep Impact probe]] smashed into [[9P/Tempel]] to learn more about its structure and composition while the [[Stardust (spacecraft)|Stardust mission]] returned samples of another comet's tail. The [[Philae lander]] will attempt to land on a comet in 2014.

[[Hayabusa]] was an [[Robotic spacecraft|unmanned spacecraft]] developed by the [[Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency]] to [[Sample return mission|return a sample of material]] from a small near-Earth asteroid named [[25143 Itokawa]] to Earth for further analysis. Hayabusa was launched on 9 May 2003 and rendezvoused with Itokawa in mid-September 2005.  After arriving at Itokawa, Hayabusa studied the asteroid's shape, spin, topography, colour, composition, density, and history. In November 2005, it landed on the asteroid to collect samples. The spacecraft returned to Earth on 13 June 2010.

===Deep space exploration===
{{main|Deep space exploration}}

====Jupiter====
{{Main|Exploration of Jupiter}}
[[Image:Jupiter gany.jpg|thumb|left|125px|[[Voyager 1]] image of Jupiter]][[Image:Io, moon of Jupiter, NASA.jpg|thumb|right|125px|Image of [[Io (moon)|Io]] taken by the [[Galileo (spacecraft)|Galileo spacecraft]]]]

The exploration of [[Jupiter]] has consisted solely of a number of automated NASA spacecraft visiting the planet since 1973. A large majority of the missions have been &quot;flybys&quot;, in which detailed observations are taken without the probe landing or entering orbit; the ''[[Galileo spacecraft|Galileo]]'' spacecraft is the only one to have orbited the planet. As Jupiter is believed to have only a relatively small rocky core and no real solid surface, a landing mission is nearly impossible.

Reaching Jupiter from Earth requires a delta-v of 9.2&amp;nbsp;km/s,&lt;ref name=&quot;delta-v&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Wong | first = Al |date= May 28, 1998 | url = http://www2.jpl.nasa.gov/galileo/faqnav.html | title = Galileo FAQ: Navigation | publisher = NASA | accessdate = 2006-11-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt; which is comparable to the 9.7&amp;nbsp;km/s delta-v needed to reach low Earth orbit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Hirata | first = Chris | url = http://www.pma.caltech.edu/~chirata/deltav.html | title = Delta-V in the Solar System | publisher = California Institute of Technology | accessdate = 2006-11-28 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060715015836/http://www.pma.caltech.edu/~chirata/deltav.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fortunately, [[Gravitational slingshot|gravity assists]] through planetary [[Planetary flyby|flyby]]s can be used to reduce the energy required at launch to reach Jupiter, albeit at the cost of a significantly longer flight duration.&lt;ref name=&quot;delta-v&quot;/&gt;

Jupiter has over 60 [[Moons of Jupiter|known moons]], many of which have relatively little known information about them.

[[Image:Saturn (planet) large.jpg|thumb|left|125px|A picture of Saturn taken by [[Voyager 2]].]][[Image:Huygens surface color.jpg|thumb|right|75px|[[Huygens probe|Huygens]] image from the surface of [[Titan (moon)|Titan]]]]

====Saturn====
{{Main|Exploration of Saturn}}
[[Saturn]] has been explored only through unmanned spacecraft launched by NASA, including one mission ([[Cassini–Huygens]]) planned and executed in cooperation with other space agencies.  These missions consist of flybys in 1979 by [[Pioneer 11]], in 1980 by [[Voyager 1]], in 1982 by [[Voyager 2]] and an orbital mission by the Cassini spacecraft which entered orbit in 2004 and is expected to continue its mission well into 2010.

Saturn has at least [[Moons of Saturn|62 satellites]], although the exact number is debatable since Saturn's rings are made up of vast numbers of independently orbiting objects of varying sizes. The largest of the moons is [[Titan (moon)|Titan]]. Titan holds the distinction of being the only moon in the solar system with an atmosphere denser and thicker than that of the Earth.  As a result of the deployment from the Cassini spacecraft of the Huygens probe and its successful landing on Titan, Titan also holds the distinction of being the only moon (apart from Earth's own Moon) to be successfully explored with a lander.

[[Image:Uranus.jpg|thumb|left|125px|Uranus from Voyager 2]][[Image:Miranda.jpg|thumb|right|125px|Voyager 2 image showing the tortured surface of [[Miranda (moon)|Miranda]]]]

====Uranus====
{{Main|Exploration of Uranus}}
The exploration of [[Uranus]] has been entirely through the [[Voyager 2]] spacecraft, with no other visits currently planned. Given its [[axial tilt]] of 97.77°, with its polar regions exposed to sunlight or darkness for long periods, scientists were not sure what to expect at Uranus.  The closest approach to [[Uranus]] occurred on January 24, 1986. ''Voyager 2'' studied the planet's unique atmosphere and [[magnetosphere]]. ''Voyager 2'' also examined its [[Rings of Uranus|ring system]] and the [[moons of Uranus]] including all five of the previously known moons, while discovering an additional ten previously unknown moons.

Images of Uranus proved to have a very uniform appearance, with no evidence of the dramatic storms or atmospheric banding evident on Jupiter and Saturn.  Great effort was required to even identify a few clouds in the images of the planet.  The magnetosphere of Uranus, however, proved to be completely unique and proved to be profoundly affected by the planet's unusual axial tilt.  In contrast to the bland appearance of Uranus itself, striking images were obtained of the moons of Uranus, including evidence that [[Miranda (moon)|Miranda]] had been unusually geologically active.
[[Image:Neptune.jpg|thumb|left|125px|Picture of Neptune taken by [[Voyager 2]]]][[Image:Triton moon mosaic Voyager 2 (large).jpg|thumb|right|125px|[[Triton (moon)|Triton]] as imaged by Voyager 2]]

====Neptune====
{{Main|Exploration of Neptune}}
The exploration of Neptune began with the August 25, 1989 [[Voyager 2]] flyby, the sole visit to the system as of 2009. The possibility of a [[Neptune Orbiter]] has been discussed, but no other missions have been given serious thought.

Although the extremely uniform appearance of Uranus during Voyager 2's visit in 1986 had led to expectations that Neptune would also have few visible atmospheric phenomena, Voyager 2 found that Neptune had obvious banding, visible clouds, [[Aurora (astronomy)|auroras]], and even a conspicuous [[Great light Spot|anticyclone storm system]] rivaled in size only by Jupiter's small Spot.  Neptune also proved to have the fastest winds of any planet in the solar system, measured as high as 2,100&amp;nbsp;km/h.&lt;ref name=&quot;Suomi1991&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
 | author=Suomi, V. E.; Limaye, S. S.; Johnson, D. R.
 | title=High winds of Neptune: A possible mechanism
 | journal=Science
 | year=1991
 | volume=251
 | pages=929–932
 | bibcode=1991Sci...251..929S  | doi = 10.1126/science.251.4996.929
 | pmid=17847386
 | issue=4996
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Voyager 2 also examined Neptune's ring and moon system.  It discovered 900 complete rings and additional partial ring &quot;arcs&quot; around Neptune. In addition to examining Neptune's three previously known moons, Voyager 2 also discovered five previously unknown moons, one of which, [[Proteus (moon)|Proteus]], proved to be the last largest moon in the system. Data from Voyager further reinforced the view that Neptune's largest moon, [[Triton (moon)|Triton]], is a captured [[Kuiper belt]] object.&lt;ref name=&quot;Agnor06&quot;&gt;{{cite journal
| author=Agnor, C. B.; and Hamilton, D. P.
| title=Neptune's capture of its moon Triton in a binary-planet gravitational encounter
| journal=Nature
| year=2006
| volume=441
 | pages = 192–4
| doi=10.1038/nature04792
| url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v441/n7090/abs/nature04792.html
| accessdate=2006-05-10
| pmid=16688170
| issue=7090
| bibcode=2006Natur.441..192A
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Pluto====
{{Main|Pluto#Exploration of Pluto|l1=Exploration of Pluto}}
[[File:Pluto and charon.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Pluto and Charon (1994)]]
The [[dwarf planet]] Pluto (considered a planet until the IAU redefinition of &quot;planet&quot; in October 2006&lt;ref&gt;IAU 2006 General Assembly: Result of the IAU Resolution votes. International Astronomical Union (2006){{cite web | author=Staff | year=2006 | url =http://www.iau.org/iau0603.414.0.html | title =IAU 2006 General Assembly: Result of the IAU resolution votes | publisher =IAU | accessdate = 2007-05-11 }}.&lt;/ref&gt;) presents significant challenges for spacecraft because of its great distance from Earth (requiring high velocity for reasonable trip times) and small mass (making capture into orbit very difficult at present). ''[[Voyager 1]]'' could have visited Pluto, but controllers opted instead for a close flyby of [[Saturn's]] moon Titan, resulting in a trajectory incompatible with a Pluto flyby. ''[[Voyager 2]]'' never had a plausible trajectory for reaching Pluto.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://voyager.jpl.nasa.gov/faq.html| title=Voyager Frequently Asked Questions| accessdate=2006-09-08| publisher=Jet Propulsion Laboratory| date=January 14, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pluto continues to be of great interest, despite its reclassification as the lead and nearest member of a new and growing class of distant icy bodies of intermediate size, in mass between the remaining eight planets and the small rocky objects historically termed asteroids (and also the first member of the important subclass, defined by orbit and known as &quot;[[Plutino]]s&quot;). After an intense political battle, a mission to Pluto dubbed ''[[New Horizons]]'' was granted funding from the US government in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Pluto Mission a Go! Initial Funding Secured|author=Robert Roy Britt|work=space.com|url=http://www.space.com/scienceastronomy/pluto_horizons_030225.html|year=2003|accessdate=2007-04-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''New Horizons'' was launched successfully on January 19, 2006. In early 2007 the craft made use of a [[gravity assist]] from [[Jupiter]]. Its closest approach to Pluto will be on July 14, 2015; scientific observations of Pluto will begin five months prior to closest approach and will continue for at least a month after the encounter.

==Future of space exploration==
{{Systemic bias|bias=United States|date=September 2011}}{{Recentism|date=September 2011}}
[[Image:S122e008264.jpg|thumb|250px|The [[European Space Agency]]'s [[Columbus Module]] at the [[International Space Station]], launched into space on the U.S. Space Shuttle mission [[STS-122]] in 2008]]

In the 2000s, several plans for space exploration were announced; both government entities and the private sector have space exploration objectives. China has announced plans to have a 60-ton multi-module space station in orbit by 2020.

The [[NASA Authorization Act of 2010]] provides objectives for American space exploration. NASA proposes to move forward with the development of the [[Space Launch System]] (SLS), which will be designed to carry the Orion Multi-Purpose Crew Vehicle, as well as important cargo, equipment, and science experiments to Earth's orbit and destinations beyond. Additionally, the SLS will serve as a back up for commercial and international partner transportation services to the International Space Station. The SLS rocket will incorporate technological investments from the Space Shuttle program and the Constellation program in order to take advantage of proven hardware and reduce development and operations costs. The first developmental flight is targeted for the end of 2017.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nasa.gov/exploration/systems/sls/sls1.html/ &quot;NASA Announces Design for New Deep Space Exploration System&quot;] Sept 14, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rationales==
{{Main|Space advocacy}}
&lt;!--- n.b. Anything added to this section that is unreferenced is going to be deleted!!!!! ---&gt;
[[Image:Aldrin Apollo 11 original.jpg|150px|thumb|right| Astronaut [[Buzz Aldrin]], had a personal Communion service when he first arrived on the surface of the [[Moon]].]]
The research that is conducted by national space exploration agencies, such as [[NASA]] and [[Roscosmos]], is one of the reasons supporters cite to justify government expenses. Economic analyses of the NASA programs often showed ongoing economic benefits (such as [[NASA spin-off]]s), generating many times the revenue of the cost of the program.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.springerlink.com/content/mx377r26428538p8/ springerlink.com/content/mx377r26428538p8/]&lt;/ref&gt;

Another claim is that space exploration is a necessity to mankind and that staying on Earth will lead to [[Human extinction|extinction]]. Some of the reasons are lack of natural resources, comets, nuclear war, and worldwide epidemic. [[Stephen Hawking]], renowned British theoretical physicist, said that &quot;I don't think the human race will survive the next thousand years, unless we spread into space. There are too many accidents that can befall life on a single planet. But I'm an optimist. We will reach out to the stars.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2001/10/16/nhawk16.xml |publisher=Telegraph.co.uk |title=Colonies in space may be only hope, says Hawking |date=October 15, 2001 |accessdate=2007-08-05 | location=London | first=Roger | last=Highfield}}&lt;/ref&gt;

NASA has produced a series of public service announcement videos supporting the concept of space exploration.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EewrC22ysus | title = NASA &quot;Reach&quot; Public Service Announcement for Space Exploration | publisher = NASA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, the public remains largely supportive of both manned and unmanned space exploration. According to an [[Associated Press]] Poll conducted in July 2003, 71% of U.S. citizens agreed with the statement that the space program is &quot;a good investment&quot;, compared to 21% who did not.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pollingreport.com/science.htm |publisher=Pollingreport.com |title=Origin of Human Life – USA Today/Gallup Poll |date=June 1–3, 2007 |accessdate=2007-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Arthur C. Clarke]] (1950) presented a summary of motivations for the human exploration of space in his non-fiction semi-technical monograph ''Interplanetary Flight''.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur C. Clarke, ''Interplanetary Flight -- An Introduction to Astronautics'', Harper &amp; Brothers, New York, 1950,Chapter 10&lt;/ref&gt; He argued that humanity's choice is essentially between expansion off the Earth into space, versus cultural (and eventually biological) stagnation and death.

==Opposition==
Critics such as the late [[physicist]] and [[Nobel prize]] winner [[Richard Feynman]] have contended that human space travel (as distinguished from space exploration in general, such as robotic missions) has never achieved any major scientific breakthroughs.&lt;ref&gt;Feynman, Richard P., ''What Do You Care What Other People Think?'', 1988, W W Norton, ISBN 0-393-02659-0, 2001 paperback: ISBN 0-393-32092-8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Related topics==
[[Image:Deltavs.svg||thumbnail|right|[[delta-v budget|Delta-v's]] in km/s for various orbital maneuvers]]

===Spaceflight===
{{Main|Spaceflight}}
''Spaceflight'' is the use of [[space technology]] to achieve the flight of [[spacecraft]] into and through outer space.

Spaceflight is used in space exploration, and also in commercial activities like [[space tourism]] and [[telecommunications satellite|satellite telecommunications]]. Additional non-commercial uses of spaceflight include [[Space observatory|space observatories]], [[reconnaissance satellite]]s and other [[earth observation satellite]]s.

A spaceflight typically begins with a rocket [[rocket launch|launch]], which provides the initial thrust to overcome the force of [[gravity]] and propels the spacecraft from the surface of the Earth. Once in space, the motion of a spacecraft—both when unpropelled and when under propulsion—is covered by the area of study called [[astrodynamics]]. Some spacecraft remain in space indefinitely, some disintegrate during [[atmospheric reentry]], and others reach a planetary or lunar surface for landing or impact.

===Satellites===
{{Main|Satellite}}

Satellites are used for a large number of purposes. Common types include military (spy) and civilian Earth observation satellites, communication satellites, navigation satellites, weather satellites, and research satellites. [[Space station]]s and human [[spacecraft]] in orbit are also satellites.

===Commercialization of space===
{{Main|Commercialization of space}}
Current examples of the commercial use of space include [[satellite navigation system]]s, [[satellite television]] and [[satellite radio]]. [[Space tourism]] is the recent phenomenon of [[Human spaceflight|space travel]] by individuals for the purpose of personal pleasure.

===Militarization of space===
{{Main|Militarisation of space}}

While military activities have taken place in space and space is an operating location for many military spacecraft (such as imaging &amp; communications satellites) or a temporary transit medium for weapons (such as ballistic missiles), permanent placement of large-scale operational weapons in space has never been conducted.

===Astrobiology===
{{Main|Astrobiology}}
Astrobiology is the  [[interdisciplinary]] study of life in the universe, combining aspects of [[astronomy]], [[biology]] and [[geology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NASAastrobio&quot;&gt;[http://astrobiology.arc.nasa.gov/ NASA Astrobiology&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It is focused primarily on the study of the [[origin of life|origin]], distribution and [[evolution]] of life. It is also known as '''exobiology''' (from Greek: έξω, ''exo'', &quot;outside&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aleph.se/Trans/Words/x.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldwidewords.org/articles/phobias.htm World Wide Words: Fears and dreads&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itwire.com.au/content/view/11647/1066/ iTWire – Scientists will look for alien life, but Where and How?&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  The term &quot;Xenobiology&quot; has been used as well, but this is technically incorrect because its terminology means &quot;biology of the foreigners&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biocab.org/Astrobiology.html Astrobiology&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Astrobiologists must also consider the possibility of life that is chemically entirely distinct from any life found on earth.&lt;ref name=AstroDNA&gt;[http://www.astrobio.net/news/article2168.html Launching the Alien Debates :: Astrobiology Magazine – earth science – evolution distribution Origin of life universe – life beyond :: Astrobiology is study of earth science evolution distribution Origin of life in universe terrestrial&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; In the Solar System some of the prime locations for current or past astrobiology are on Enceladus, Europa, Mars, and Titan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://spacechronology.com/extra.html Astrobiology: the quest for extraterrestrial life]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Sun920607.jpg|thumb|left|125px|Image of the Sun from 7 June 1992 showing some sunspots]]

===Space colonization===
{{Main|Space colonization}}

Space colonization, also called space settlement and space humanization, would be the permanent autonomous (self-sufficient) human [[Space habitat|habitation]] of locations outside Earth, especially of natural satellites or planets such as the [[Colonization of the Moon|Moon]] or [[Colonization of Mars|Mars]], using significant amounts of [[in-situ resource utilization]].

To date, the longest human occupation of space is the [[International Space Station]] which has been in continuous use for {{age in years and days|2000|11|02}}. [[Valeri Polyakov]]'s record single spaceflight of almost 438 days aboard the [[Mir]] space station has not been surpassed. Long-term stays in space reveal issues with bone and muscle loss in low gravity, immune system suppression, and radiation exposure.

Many past and current concepts for the continued exploration and colonization of space focus on a return to the Moon as a &quot;stepping stone&quot; to the other planets, especially Mars. At the end of 2006 NASA announced they were planning to build a permanent Moon base with continual presence by 2024.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=GLOBAL EXPLORATION STRATEGY AND LUNAR ARCHITECTURE |publisher=NASA |date=December 4, 2006 |url=http://www.nasa.gov/pdf/164021main_lunar_architecture.pdf |format=PDF|accessdate=2007-08-05 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Public sector space agencies}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Spaceflight}}
{{Main|Outline of space exploration}}
* [[Discovery and exploration of the Solar System]]

&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:2; column-count:2;&quot;&gt;
; Robotic space exploration programs
*[[Robotic spacecraft]]
*[[Timeline of planetary exploration]]
*[[Landings on other planets]]
*[[Pioneer program]]
*[[Luna program]]
*[[Zond program]]
*[[Venera program]]
*[[Mars probe program]]
*[[Ranger program]]
*[[Mariner program]]
*[[Surveyor program]]
*[[Viking program]]
*[[Voyager program]]
*[[Vega program]]
*[[Phobos program]]
*[[Discovery program]]
*[[Chandrayaan-1|Chandrayaan Program]]
*[[Chinese Lunar Exploration Program|Chang'e Program]]

; Animals in space
*[[Animals in space]]
*[[Monkeys in space]]
*[[Russian space dogs]]

; Humans in space
*[[Astronaut]]s
*[[List of human spaceflights]]
*[[List of human spaceflights by program]]
*[[Vostok program]]
*[[Mercury program]]
*[[Voskhod program]]
*[[Gemini program]]
*[[Soyuz program]]
*[[Apollo program]]
*[[Salyut|Salyut program]]
*[[Skylab]]
*[[Space Shuttle program]]
*[[Mir]]
*[[International Space Station]]
*[[Vision for Space Exploration]]
*[[Aurora Programme]]
*[[Tier One]]
*[[Human adaptation to space]]
*[[Space architecture]]
*[[Space archaeology]]
*[[flexible path]] destinations set

; Recent and future developments
*[[Asia's Space Race]]
*[[Energy development]]
*[[Crew Exploration Vehicle]]
*[[Exploration of Mars]]
*[[Space tourism]]
*[[Private spaceflight]]
*[[Space colonization]]
*[[Interstellar spaceflight]]
*[[Human outpost]]
*[[Mars to Stay]]

; Other
*[[Timeline of Solar System exploration]]
*[[Spaceflight]]
*[[Atmospheric reentry]]
*[[Space station]]
*[[Space and survival]]
*[[Space disasters]]
*[[List of artificial objects on extra-terrestrial surfaces]]
*[[List of spaceflights]]
*[[Religion in space]]
*[[Russian explorers]]
*[[U.S. space exploration history on U.S. stamps]]
&lt;/div&gt;
{{Space exploration lists and timelines}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Space exploration}}
* [http://spacechronology.com Chronology of space exploration, astrobiology, exoplanets and news]
* [http://www.spaceref.com Space related news]
* [http://spaceflight.nasa.gov Nasa's website on human space travel]
* [http://www.nps.gov/history/NR/twhp/wwwlps/lessons/101space/101space.htm ''&quot;America's Space Program: Exploring a New Frontier&quot;'', a National Park Service Teaching with Historic Places (TwHP) lesson plan]
* [http://spacephotos.ru/ The Soviet-Russian Spaceflight's History Photoarchive]
* [http://www.life.com/image/first/in-gallery/30222/the-21-greatest-space-photos-ever The 21 Greatest Space Photos Ever] – slideshow by ''Life Magazine''
* &quot;''[http://www.phy6.org/stargaze/Sintro.htm From Stargazers to Starships]''&quot;, Home page of extensive educational web site and course covering spaceflight, astronomy and related physics, by David P. Stern
{{Spaceflight}}
{{Colonization}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Space Exploration}}
[[Category:Spaceflight| ]]

{{Link FA|es}}
&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;
[[ar:استكشاف الفضاء]]
[[bg:Космонавтика]]
[[ca:Exploració espacial]]
[[de:Weltraumforschung]]
[[et:Kosmoseuurimine]]
[[el:Εξερεύνηση του διαστήματος]]
[[es:Exploración espacial]]
[[eo:Kosmoesploro]]
[[eu:Esplorazio espazial]]
[[fa:فضانوردی]]
[[fr:Exploration de l'espace]]
[[gu:અવકાશ સંશોધન]]
[[ko:우주 탐사]]
[[hi:अंतरिक्ष यात्रा]]
[[id:Penjelajahan angkasa]]
[[is:Geimkönnun]]
[[it:Esplorazione spaziale]]
[[hu:Űrkutatás]]
[[mk:Истражувања на вселената]]
[[mwl:Sploraçon spacial]]
[[ja:宇宙開発]]
[[pnb:خلا دی کھوج]]
[[ps:فضانوردي]]
[[pl:Eksploracja kosmosu]]
[[pt:Exploração espacial]]
[[ru:Космонавтика]]
[[simple:Space exploration]]
[[fi:Avaruustoiminta]]
[[tl:Panggagalugad sa kalawakan]]
[[ta:விண்வெளிப் பயணம்]]
[[th:การสำรวจอวกาศ]]
[[tg:Кайҳоннавардӣ]]
[[uk:Астронавтика]]
[[ur:خلانوردی]]
[[fiu-vro:Ilmaruumiuurminõ]]
[[war:Pamiling ug Panginsayod han Kamatuoran ha Kawarayan]]
[[wo:Aakimoo jawwu ji]]
[[zh:太空探索]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
