<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28443893" ns="0" title="List of Saini recipients of military awards and decorations"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Main|Saini people}}{{See also|List of Saini people}}

This is a list of Saini recipients of military awards and decorations.

Sainis have a distinguished record as soldiers in the armies of pre-British princely states,  British India and independent India. Sainis fought in both the [[World Wars]] and won some of the highest [[military awards and decorations|gallantry awards]] for conspicuous bravery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cross of St. George&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jemadar Gurmukh Singh Saini&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh OBI&quot;/&gt;  [[Subedar Joginder Singh]], who won [[Param Vir Chakra]], [[Indian Army]]'s highest war time gallantry award, in [[1962 India-China War]] was also a Saini of Sahnan sub clan.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prof. Nanua&quot;/

The awards list given below is not exhaustive. Not all Sainis use their clan or  sub clan names and go by the last names such as 'Chaudhry', 'Singh', 'Kumar', etc. Since these names are shared by many other groups (some of which overlap Sainis) such as Sikhs, Jats, Dogras and Rajputs etc. , it is not possible to isolate Sainis among them just by their last names. The following list pertains only to those decorated soldiers and policemen who are confirmed to be Sainis. The actual list of decorated Saini army and police personnel might be much longer. More quality research is needed in this reference.

The following list contains only those soldiers and policemen who have received major wartime and peacetime awards. The list of Sainis in the Indian Army is very large and needs no inclusion here. Army and police have traditionally been major sources of employment for Sainis. British had classified Sainis as a 'martial race'. Purser recorded in a 1892 land settlement report that Sainis joined the military service quite frequently, especially as cavalrymen.&lt;ref name = &quot;Saini Cavalrymen&quot;&gt;''&quot;Men of this tribe not seldom take service especially in cavalry.&quot;'' Final report of the revised settlement of the Jullundur District in the Punjab, pp 84, W.E. Purser, BCS, THE &quot;CIVIL AND MILITARY GAZETTE&quot; PRESS, Contractors to the Punjab Government, Lahore, 1892&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;2nd Punjab&quot;&gt;''&quot;The chief areas for Saini recruitment were the Ambala, Hoshiarpur, and Jullundur Districts. &quot;,'' The Golden Galley: the story of the Second Punjab Regiment, 1761-1947, pp 313, Sir Geoffrey Betham, Herbert Valentine Rupert Geary, printed for the 2d Punjab Regiment Officers ̕Association at the University Press, by C. Batey, printer to the university, 1956&lt;/ref&gt;

Another fact that needs to be understood is the comparison of Sainis with Dogras, Pushtuns, Jats and Rajputs is not an apples to apples comparison. Sainis are merely a sub tribe of Yaduvanshi Kshatriyas (or Jadon Rajputs) who took to agriculture in Punjab and spun off with a distinct identity local predominantly to Punjab and it's bordering region. Their numbers are relatively very small compared with these groups. For example, according to the 1881 census, the entire Saini population in the whole of undivided Punjab, also all of pre-partition India for that matter, was only 132,000 while the population of just a single Jat clan of Sidhus was 208,000. The Saini population was reduced to 106,000 according to the 1901 census after mistakes of the 1881 census were corrected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Census 1901&quot;&gt;Census of India, 1901, pp 50,  By India Census Commissioner, Edward Albert Gait, Published by Office of the Superintendent of Government Printing, India, 1902&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;In the 1881 Census, there were only 132,000 Sainis in Punjab, but Sidhus, a Jat tribe, numbered 208,000.&quot; Peasant Communities of Punjab ,By Kulwant Singh Virk [http://www.ksvirk.in/english/thepeasant.html]&lt;/ref&gt; The best way to gauge proportionate Saini  contribution to feats of gallantry in armed forces would be by comparing them individually with other Rajput sub tribes such as Bhati, Chauhan, Sisodia, etc. rather than Rajputs, Jats, or Dogras which are extremely large and heterogeneous when compared to Sainis.

==Known Gallantry Awards==
During British India (World War I)&lt;ref&gt;''Note: In addition to these Wing Commander Kartar Singh Taunque was the first personnel of Indian Airforce to win a gallantry award as part of Royal Indian Airforce. The Chakra class of gallantry awards did not yet exist as Taunque won this award in 1938 during World War II before the independence of India. More information is required for the gallantry awards won by Sainis during both the World Wars.''&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Russian Cross St George 1st &amp; 2nd class.jpg|thumb|right|[[Cross of St. George]] medallion.This award was Imperial Russia's highest exclusively military honor. Gurmukh Singh, a Saini , from Ropar won this highest military honor in 1916 for his gallantry in battlefield. ]]
[[File:Indianorderofmerit1.jpg|thumb| [[Indian Order of Merit]]. First Class Indian Order of Merit won by Gurmukh Singh Saini]]
[[File:Sub Joginder Singh.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Subedar Joginder Singh Sahnan]], a Saini Sikh from Mahla Kalan, Moga (originally from Munaka, District Hoshiarpur) won [[Param Vir Chakra]] in 1962 Indo-China.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prof. Nanua&quot;&gt;Saini Jagat: Utpati Ate Vikas, pp 121, Prof. Surjit Singh Nanuan, Manjota Publications, Patiala, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; ]]
*1  [[Cross of St. George]] (''Imperial Russia's highest exclusively military award, equivalent to current [[Param Vir Chakra]] and British [[Victoria Cross]])'' &lt;ref name=&quot;Cross of St. George&quot;&gt;''&quot;The Order of St. George, Imperial Russia's highest exclusively military order, was instituted in 1769 and came to be considered among the most prestigious military awards in the world... The order was awarded to officers and generals for special gallantry, such as, personally leading his troops in rout of a superior enemy force, or capturing a fortress, etc. Before membership in the Order could be granted, a candidate's case had to be investigated by a council composed of Knights of the Order.&quot;'' Source: http://www.gwpda.org/medals/russmedl/russia.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*1 [[Order of British India]] (recipient decorated with title 'Bahadur')
*2 [[Indian Order of Merit]] (after 1912 equivalent to current [[Maha Vir Chakra]] )
*2 [[Battle of Neuve Chapelle]] (war memorial commemorations)

Since Independence

*2 [[Param Vir Chakra]] ([[Victoria Cross]] before 1947)
*1 [[Vir Chakra]]
*4 [[Shaurya Chakra]]s
*1 [[Bronze Star]] (US Army)
*19 [[Sena Medal]]s
*2 [[Purple Heart]] (US Army)
*1 Roll of Honour

==Known Meritorious Service Awards==
*2 [[Param Vishisht Seva Medal]]s
*2 [[Ati Vishist Seva Medal]]
*2 [[Yudh Seva Medal]]s
*6 [[Vishisht Seva Medal]]s

==Decorated Saini armymen and paramilitary personnel==
Order of names given below is as per the rank held at the time of retirement or martyrdom of each soldier.

* Lt Gen Harbhajan Singh Banga (Param Vishisht Seva Medal)&lt;ref&gt;Asian Recorder,pp 16492
Published by K. K. Thomas at Recorder Press, 1982, Item notes: 1982, Original from the University of Michigan, Digitized 26 Aug 2008&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Lt Gen Ashok Kumar Saini  (Param Vishisht Seva Medal, Ati Visisht Seva Metal, Sena Medal)&lt;ref&gt;http://demotemp92.nic.in/writereaddata/2007/english/may01-07/h5.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 

* Maj Gen Balbir Singh Pama (Sena Medal)  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.indianarmy.gov.in/day/rd2007/sm_dist.htm |title=IC-36200 |publisher=Indianarmy.gov.in |date=2007-01-26 |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tribuneindia.com/2009/20090725/aplus.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

*Brigadier Ram Prakash Saini (Vishisht Seva Medal) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2001/20010126/nation.htm |title=The Tribune, Chandigarh, India - Nation |publisher=Tribuneindia.com |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Brigadier SK Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry)  &lt;ref&gt;Forefront for Ever: The History of the Mahar Regiment, By V. Longer, pp 271, Published by Mahar Regimental Centre, 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

*Brigadier Jaspal Singh Pama (Sena Medal for Gallantry)   &lt;ref&gt;[http://mod.nic.in/Samachar/march01-04/html/ch3.htm IC-37328 COL JASPAL SINGH PAMA, 2/3 GR]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://frontierindia.net/the-indomitable-second-third-spirit  ''&quot;2/Lt ( now Brig, ) Jaspal Pama of 2/3rd; ...&quot; '']&lt;/ref&gt;

* Brigadier JS Saini (Vishisht Seva Medal) &lt;ref&gt;MJAFI, Medical Journal Armed Forces India, Vol 57, pp 47, Januar 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

*Captain Gurbachan Singh Salaria (Posthumous Param Vir Chakra,Battles of Congo Crisis)&lt;ref&gt;[[Gurbachan Singh Salaria]] [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/HEROISM/Salaria.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

*Group Captain S S Banga (Vishisht Seva Medal)&lt;ref&gt;Indian Air Force VSM List
Award Date 26 Jan 91, Announced 26 Jan 91 [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/Awards/db/awardspage.php?cur=600&amp;qyear=&amp;qaward=VSM]&lt;/ref&gt;

*  Group Captain Girish Saini (Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/1999/99jan26/head5.htm#15 |title=News Headings |publisher=Tribuneindia.com |date=1999-01-26 |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Wing Commander Kartar Singh Taunque (first IAF personnel ever to be decorated for gallantry)&lt;ref name = &quot;Taunque Senior Gallantry&quot;&gt;Limca Book of Records, pp 343, Published by Bisleri Beverages Ltd., 1998&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/Books/Review-EagleStrikes.html ]{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Kartar Singh Taunque.jpg|thumb|left| Wing Cdr. Kartar Singh Taunque. Saini tradition of military service is very old and distinguished. Wing Cdr. Taunque, a Saini, became the first ever personnel of Indian Air Force (then Royal Indian Air Force) to be decorated for gallantry in battle field.&lt;ref name = &quot;Taunque Senior Gallantry&quot;/&gt; Taunque, as an Air Gunner, conducted devastating precision bombing during 'Operations in Waziristan'. After this military decoration, Taunque also served in Mesopotamia (Iraq) as part of Royal Indian Air Force.]]
{{Main|Kartar Singh Taunque}}

*  Wing Commander Krishan Kant Saini (1962 War Hero, Vir Chakra, Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry &amp;  Ati Vishist Seva Medal)

{{Main|Wing Commander K K Saini, Vr.C., AVSM}}

*  Wing Commander Satya Pal Daulay (Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;Asian Recorder, pp 20467, Published by K. K. Thomas at Recorder Press, 1989&lt;/ref&gt;

* Col Satinder Kumar Saini (Vishisht Seva Medal)  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://mod.nic.in/samachar/feb01-06/h3.htm |title=IC-39436 |publisher=Mod.nic.in |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Col Vikas Saini (Vishisht Seva Medal)  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://indianarmy.nic.in/rday2009/gall.htm |title=IC-47701 |publisher=Indianarmy.nic.in |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Squadron Leader Baljeet Singh Saini (Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;Gazette of India : No.108 - Pres/72 dated 23rd September 1972&lt;/ref&gt;

* Squadron Leader Devinder Singh Saini (Shaurya Chakra &amp; Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;Gazette of India , 16th April 1977 - No.38 - Pres/77 dated 26th January 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/Database/Record/view.php?srnum=8157 |title=Service Record for Squadron Leader Devinder Singh Saini 8157 F(P) |publisher=[www.bharat-rakshak.com] |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Subedar-Major ''Bahadur'' Jagindar Singh Saini, OBI (2nd Class Order of Merit and 2nd Class of the Order of British India, Hero of Battle of Loos, Belgium, World War I) &lt;ref name = &quot;Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh OBI&quot;&gt;''&quot;his conspicuous gallantry in action on the 17th November 1914 when with a party of Sappers under the command of a British Officer he was always to the fore and led his men with great determination into the enemy's trenches. Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh, Saini Sikh of Kheri Salabatpur in Bupar, gained the 2nd Class Order of Merit at the battle of Loos in Belgium for striking leadership and conspicuous bravery in action after most of his company and all but one British Officer in his regiment had been killed or wounded. This officer was also awarded the 2nd Class of the Order of British India for distinguished conduct in the field.&quot;''War speeches (1918), pp 129, Author: O'Dwyer, Michael Francis, (Sir) 1864-, Subject: World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Punjab Publisher: Lahore Printed by the Superintendent Government Printing&lt;/ref&gt;

Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh 'Bahadur', a Saini from Ropar, distinguished himself for conspicuous gallantry and striking leadership in the [[Battle of Loos]] in Belgium during World War 1. Lieutinent Governor's citation for his military decoration as 'Bahadur' (or hero) and the twin conferring of [[Order of British India]] and [[Indian Order of Merit]] reads as follows:&lt;ref name = &quot;Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh OBI&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Punjab and the war , pp 254, Maxwell Studdy Leigh, Lahore, Printed by the Superintendent, Government Printing, Punjab, 1922&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
''&quot; ..for his conspicuous gallantry in action on the 17th November 1914 when with a party of Sappers under the command of a British Officer he was always to the fore and led his men with great determination into the enemy's trenches. Subedar-Major Jagindar Singh, Saini Sikh of Kheri Salabatpur in Rupar, gained the 2nd Class Order of Merit at the battle of Loos in Belgium for striking leadership and conspicuous bravery in action after most of his company and all but one British Officer in his regiment had been killed or wounded. This officer was also awarded the 2nd Class of the Order of British India for distinguished conduct in the field.&quot;''
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*Major Harminderpal Singh Saini (Posthumous Shaurya Chakra) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kashmir-information.com/Heroes/harminder.html |title=Shaheed Major Harminder Pal Singh-A True Soldier Of Khalsa |publisher=Kashmir-information.com |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.expressindia.com/news/ie/daily/19990818/ige18127.html |title=Major H.P. Singh does Kharar proud with Shaurya Chakra |publisher=Expressindia.com |date=1999-08-18 |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
''On 13 April 1999, Major Singh fearlessly led his column from upfront, setting a personal example for his command to emulate. He made the supreme sacrifice of his life while fighting the Pakistani ISI sponsored proxy war and safe guarding the integrity of [[India]]. His mortal remains, draped in the tri-colour of the Indian flag, were sent to his village in (Mundi Kharar) Ropar (the vicinity of which [[Anandpur Sahib]] is located) on 14 April 1999 where he was cremated with honours reserved for the bravest.

Major Harminder had been wounded in the left arm but managed to engage three militants armed with Kalashnikovs and grenades in an eyeball-to-eyeball encounter in a remote north Kashmir village on April 13.The 18 Grenadiers Major was shot through the temple by the third militant but not before he had gunned down two of them. Harminder led the commando platoon of his battalion in what has been described as a &quot;dare-devil&quot; operation in a congested locality of Sadurkotbala village in Manasbal.Major Harminder Pal Singh was honoured with the [[Shaurya Chakra]], for his exceptional gallantry and devotion to duty, posthumously''.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

*Major S L Saini (Vishisht Seva Medal)  &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://bro.nic.in/writereaddata/newsimages/SCROLL%20%20OF%20%20HONOURS%20AND%20AWARDS1373515987.pdf |title=IC-10902, 1970 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Major P.S. Gahoon (Shaurya Chakra) &lt;ref&gt;SC-00364 ,  http://indianarmy.nic.in/award/shaurya_chakra1.html&lt;/ref&gt;

*Major Rajinder Kumar Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry) &lt;ref&gt;[http://indianarmy.nic.in/awards/iday2009/gall.htm IEC-3037]&lt;/ref&gt;

*Major Ravi Kant Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry) &lt;ref&gt;Asian recorder. pp 18753, Publisher: [New Delhi, India, etc., K. K. Thomas at Recorder Press, etc&lt;/ref&gt;

* Captain Jasbir Singh Kaberwal (Shaurya Chakra) &lt;ref&gt;Where Gallantry is Tradition: Saga of Rashtriya Indian Military College : Plantinum Jubilee Volume, 1997, By Bikram Singh, Sidharth Mishra, Rashtriya Indian Military College, Contributor Rashtriya Indian Military College, Edition: illustrated, Published by Allied Publishers, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://indianarmy.nic.in/award/shaurya_chakra1.html |title=IC-50950 |publisher=Indianarmy.nic.in |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Sergeant Uday Singh Taunque (Winner of Purple Heart &amp; Bronze Star, &lt;ref&gt;http://www.illinois.gov/PressReleases/ShowPressRelease.cfm?SubjectID=1&amp;RecNum=2812&lt;/ref&gt;US Army)' 

{{Main|Uday Singh Taunque}}

*Sergeant Paul Singh Pabla, In 2006 , Sgt. Paul Singh Pabla of Fort Wayne , Indiana , another Saini soldier serving in US army laid down his life in Iraq and gained a posthumous Purple Heart. For more info about Sgt. Paul Singh Pabla, visit http://www.sainionline.com/sainis-in-army-and-police

*Subedar Joginder Singh ([[Param Vir Chakra]], 1962 Indo-China War Hero)&lt;ref name=&quot;Prof. Nanua&quot;/&gt;

{{Main|Subedar Joginder Singh Sahnan}}

[[File:Uday kuwait.jpg|thumb|Sergeant Uday Singh Taunque - KIA Iraq 1st Dec 2003]]

*[[Jemadar]] [[Gurmukh Singh Saini]] [[Cr St Geo]], IOM (Equivalencies: [[Cr St Geo]] - [[Param Vir Chakra]] &amp; [[Victoria Cross]]) &lt;ref name=&quot;Cross of St. George&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jemadar Gurmukh Singh Saini&quot;&gt;''&quot;I will give you here the names of three of those men who have earned fame by their heroism. Jamadar Gurmukh Singh, a Saini Sikh of Gadram Badi in Rupar, won the 1st Class Order of Merit and the 2nd Class Cross of the Russian [[Order of St. George]] for his splendid courage on the night of the 1st March 1916 when he advanced under the greatest difficulties, continually crawling forward and digging himself in.&quot;'' War speeches (1918), pp 128 , Author: O'Dwyer, Michael Francis, (Sir) 1864-, Subject: World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Punjab Publisher: Lahore Printed by the Superintendent Government Printing&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Main|Gurmukh Singh Saini}}

*Lt. Ravinder Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref name=&quot;indianarmy1&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://indianarmy.nic.in/day/arindpgal04.htm |title=Independence Day - Honours And Awards |publisher=Indianarmy.nic.in |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Flt. Lt. Somesh Kumar Saini (Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/Awards/db/yearpage.php?qyear=1998&amp;qaward=all |title=Indian Air Force Gallantry Awards Register [www.bharat-rakshak.com&amp;#93; |publisher=Bharat-rakshak.com |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Flt Lt S C Sandal (IAF Roll of Honour, Martyr, 1971 war)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/History/Roll/1971-1.html ]{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Sgt. Hira Singh Saini (Vayu Sena Medal for Gallantry) &lt;ref&gt;http://indianairforce.nic.in/show_unit.php?ch=38&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;21021 F(P)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Naib Subedar Gopal Singh Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref name=&quot;indianarmy1&quot;/&gt;
*Naik Janak Raj Saini (Sena Medal for Gallantry)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://indianarmy.nic.in/day/awards.htm |title=LIST OF PERSONNEL AWARDED GALLANTRY AND DISTINGUISHED SERVICES AWARDS ON REPUBLIC DAY 2002 |publisher=Indianarmy.nic.in |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Sepoy Banta Singh Saini (Battle of Neuve Chapelle War Memorial Commemoration, World War 1)  &lt;ref&gt;Date of marytyrdom: 25th September 1915. Son of Gurditt Singh, of Bhagpur, Hoshiarpur, Punjab. Panel 10 - NEUVE-CHAPELLE MEMORIAL - Pas de Calais Commonwealth War Dead 1914-1918 , NEUVE-CHAPELLE MEMORIAL REGISTER: ''Note Bhagpur (district Hoshiarpur) is 100% Saini owned village''.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Follower Devi Ditta Saini (Battle of Neuve Chapelle War Memorial Commemoration, World War 1) &lt;ref&gt;Date of marytyrdom:  2nd September 1915. Follower, 85. 69th Punjabis. Son of Rura, of Jhika Ladhana, Nawanshahr, Jullundur, Punjab. Panel 10
 - NEUVE-CHAPELLE MEMORIAL - Pas de Calais Commonwealth War Dead 1914-1918 ''Note: Ladhana(district Nawanshahr) is 100% Saini owned village''&lt;/ref&gt;

==Decorated Saini policemen==
''Gallantry medal'' is the most prestigious award for any police officer in the country. It is awarded for displaying conspicuous gallantry, courage and devotion to duty of very high order. The police officer keeps the duty before self in completing the task. This award is rare in itself as the action should match the risk involved on the occasion. The senior controlling officer assessing the task performed by the subordinate recommends to the head of the police department for the award of a gallantry medal.

*Director General of Police (DGP-Vigilance) [[Sumedh Singh Saini, IPS]] ( Gallantry Award ,1987, Punjab Police )&lt;ref name=&quot;punjabpolice.org&quot;&gt;[http://punjabpolice.org/gallantry.html ]{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Inspector General of Police [[Sadhu Ram Chaudhari]], [[OBE]], First police chief of the state of [[Himachal Pradesh]] (then a union territory) and union territories of Delhi and Ajmer in independent India. &lt;ref name= &quot;SR Chaudhari1&quot;&gt;&quot;...examination was instituted in 1922, the following IP officers who came to the Indian Punjab in 1947 had joined: SR Chaudhari, 1923&quot;, Police and politics in twentieth century Punjab, pp 57, Bhagwan Singh Danewalia,Ajanta, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;SR Chaudhari2&quot;&gt;The India Office and Burma Office list for 1945,pp 324,  Great Britain. India Office, Harrison and Sons, ltd., 1945&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;SR Chaudhari3&quot;&gt;The Times of India directory and year book including who's who, pp 698,Times of India, Bombay, The Times of India Press, 1952&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= &quot;SR Chaudhari4&quot;&gt;''&quot;The Police Administration in the State was headed by an Inspector General of Police who was also Inspector General of Police for Union Territories of Delhi and Ajmer. Sh. S.R. Chaudhary IP, was the first IGP.&quot;'' , [http://admis.hp.nic.in/himpol/Citizen/briefHistory.aspx BRIEF HISTORY OF HIMACHAL PRADESH POLICE]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Deputy Inspector General of Police (DIG) Dr. Kamal Saini, IPS, (Gallantry Award, Jammu and Kashmir Police) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://pib.nic.in/archieve/lreleng/lyr2003/raug2003/15082003/r150820032.html |title=PIB Press Releases |publisher=Pib.nic.in |date=2003-08-15 |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jandkpolice.org/RightToInfoAct.htm |title=Jammu &amp; Kashmir Police - Working for peace |publisher=Jandkpolice.org |date= |accessdate=2009-09-20}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Supdt. of Police (SP) Hari Ram Banga, (Gallantry Award ,1991, Punjab Police)&lt;ref name=&quot;punjabpolice.org&quot;/&gt; 
*Dy. Supdt. of Police (DSP) Kashmir Singh Pabla (President's Police Medal for Distinguished Service, 2009) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://andamanchronicle.com/content/view/326/27/ |title=KS Pabla &amp; Chittranjan Garu of A&amp;N Police Chosen for President’s Medal |publisher=Andamanchronicle.com |date=2009-01-26 |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mha.gov.in/writereaddata/12328936951_ppm-rd09.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
*Sub Inspector Hans Raj Saini (Police Medal For Meritorious Service, 2003, Border Security Force) &lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://jmu.bsf.gov.in/honors.htm |title=Honors |publisher=Jmu.bsf.gov.in |date=1965-12-01 |accessdate=2009-09-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Sub Inspector Vinod Kumar Saini, (Police Medal For Gallantry, 2008, Border Security Force)&lt;ref&gt;[http://india.gov.in/myindia/gal_08.html ]{{Dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of Saini people]]
*[[Saini history]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Saini Recipients Of Military Awards And Decorations}}
[[Category:Recipients of military awards and decorations]]
[[Category:Saini]]
[[Category:Military history of India]]
[[Category:Indian military-related lists]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
