<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2850803" ns="0" title="List of recurring The Mighty Boosh characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The following is a '''list of recurring characters from ''[[The Mighty Boosh]]''''', including characters from the [[The Mighty Boosh|television]] series, the [[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|radio series]], and the various stage shows. Most of the recurring characters are played by [[Julian Barratt]], [[Noel Fielding]], [[Michael Fielding]], [[Rich Fulcher]] or [[Dave Brown (comedian)|Dave Brown]]. For minor and non-recurring characters see ''[[List of minor characters from The Mighty Boosh]]''.

==Central cast==
[[File:The mighty boosh nme take over.jpg|thumb|right|The central cast of ''The Mighty Boosh''.&lt;br /&gt;From left to right:'''Howard Moon''' ([[Julian Barratt]]), '''Bollo de beer''' ([[Dave Brown (comedian)|Dave Brown]]), '''Naboo the Enigma''' ([[Michael Fielding]]), '''Vince Noir''' ([[Noel Fielding]]) and '''Bob Fossil''' ([[Rich Fulcher]]), as portrayed in Series 3]]
''The Mighty Boosh'' centres on the adventures of [[#Howard Moon|Howard Moon]] (Barratt) and [[#Vince Noir|Vince Noir]] (Fielding), aided by the other two members of the central cast, [[#Naboo the Enigma|Naboo the Enigma]] (Michael Fielding) and [[#Bollo|Bollo]] (Peter Elliott/Dave Brown), who by series 3 they share a flat with. [[#Bob Fossil|Bob Fossil]] (Rich Fulcher) is part of the central cast in series 1, becoming a recurring character thereafter.

In the course of the series a variety of bizarre and surreal recurring characters cross their paths, mostly also played by the same cast doubling up.

===Howard Moon===
'''Howard TJ Moon''' is portrayed by [[Julian Barratt]]. Howard is an aspiring [[musician]], [[actor]], [[poet]], [[novelist]] and [[photographer]]. In the first series he works at the Zooniverse as a [[zookeeper]], alongside Vince.  In the second series, Howard and Vince have left the zoo and formed a [[music ensemble|band]] together.  He is vain, despite being described as &quot;generic-looking&quot;&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; and often makes outrageous claims which often turn out to be true (he claims, for instance, to have turned down a lucrative offer extended by [[Walt Disney]] himself to sort all of Disney's felt-tip pens).&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt;  He reacts to criticism violently.&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt;  His favourite style of music is [[jazz-fusion]], and he spends part of each day in a &quot;jazz trance&quot;. He often claims different parts of his body or aspects of his style to be &quot;powerful&quot; when he is made fun of.&lt;ref name=Killeroo&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Killeroo
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647525/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-05-18
| season       = 1
| number       = 1
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is unlucky in love, and in series one is in love with [[reptile]] keeper, Mrs Gideon.  His attempts to impress her with his novel writing&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt; and snake capturing&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; are often the launching point for his and Vince's adventures. He has claimed to have &quot;deeply Spanish&quot; lineage; Vince usually counters that he is &quot;clearly from Leeds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;BooshLive2006&quot;/&gt; Despite his lack of success, he seems to see himself as a smooth-talker and while he thinks he is being cool and dashing, his attempts to smooth talk women are awkward at best.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; To impress two electro girls, he talks of animals in heat&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; and in series two, to impress Precious Lilywhite, he speaks about jazz and plays a tune on his self-made [[flute]].&lt;ref name=MilkyJoe/&gt; In series two, he does manage to earn the love of an [[hermaphrodite]] [[merman]], Old Gregg. Old Gregg proposes marriage to Howard, who acquiesces due to Old Gregg's promise to let him out of the [[cave]] he is being held [[captive]] in.&lt;ref name=OldGregg/&gt; Whilst Old Gregg is endowed with a 'mangina', it is supposed in the live tour that Howard has a 'shenis' and proposes that they were &quot;Going to make sweet, sweet love&quot;.

In the series three episode ''Party'' Howard's romantic troubles reach a new level of wretchedness, when it is revealed that he is a virgin. Later in the episode Vince and Howard share a kiss (in order to save Vince's life) leading Howard to announce that he has now discovered his own [[homosexuality]] and is in love with Vince. Vince is horrified, but he becomes jealous moments later when Howard begins flirting with a girl.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt;

[[Image:Julian Barratt.jpeg|thumb|left|Barratt portraying Howard Moon live]]

Howard believes that he has a dark, brooding, [[poetic]] side to his personality and has many artistic pretensions, although almost all of his artistic efforts come to nothing. In series two, he flirts with being a [[nature]] [[photographer]] and longs to get his pictures on the cover of ''Global Explorer'' magazine.&lt;ref name=Yeti/&gt; He briefly came close to becoming a published author, although he ruined his chances by descending into paranoia and angst as a result of his frequent failures to the point where, after being asked, Mrs Gideon criticised his writing causing him to fly into a blind rage and strike her in the face in front of his potential publisher.&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt; He is a gifted musician, thanks to selling his [[soul]] to the Spirit of Jazz, although he refuses to play instruments because the Spirit of Jazz &quot;gets inside&quot; him and makes him commit embarrassing acts.&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; This claim is short-lived as by series two he is seen playing a variety of instruments on several occasions with no threat of the Spirit of Jazz.&lt;ref name=MilkyJoe/&gt; In series two, Howard's lack of [[funk]]iness is suggested as one reason he has not garnered the success he wants.  Vince tells him he looks like 'a [[supply teacher]]' and that he is 'too white', while Old Gregg tells Howard that he is too rigid &quot;like a bread stick&quot; and has no [[rhythm]].&lt;ref name=OldGregg/&gt;

Whenever Howard is near to death, he pleads not to die, saying, &quot;Don't kill me. I've got so much to give.&quot; While Vince is always dressed very flashily and into the current fashion, Howard tends to look unkempt and shabby.  In the second series, we learn that Vince cuts Howard's hair while Howard is asleep.&lt;ref name=MilkyJoe/&gt; Vince and other characters usually comment that he has small eyes, either like a cockerel, shrimp or crab's eyes.

Howard can be [[aggressive]] (he often threatens to &quot;come at&quot; Vince, for instance) but when faced with an actual fight, he tends to fold quickly.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; He is generally a very angry and frustrated man, and while he berates Vince for having an excessively sunny outlook on life, he also relies on Vince for [[emotional]] support.  Howard often treats Vince like an inferior, although the [[laconic]] Vince is generally more amused than offended by Howard's superior attitude.  They tease each other constantly, but there is a deep bond between them and both have demonstrated repeatedly that they will risk death to rescue each other from various dangerous situations and they even share a [[kiss]] in one episode (even if only to save Vince's life).&lt;ref name=Party/&gt;  When facing death, the two will often reminisce about very silly things - &quot;like that one time they ate [[soup]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth/&gt; This usually leads into a '[[Crimp (song)|crimp]]': a short, completely [[random]] song that quickly strays off-topic and often involves [[harmony]].

Howard's age is uncertain. In &quot;Fountain of Youth&quot;, during a flashback to the pair's school days, he exclaims that he is the same age as Vince, despite looking much older, and it mentioned several times that they went to school and college together. If we are to believe his assertion in ''Party'', he is &quot;32 - ten years older than [Vince]&quot;. This may have been to indulge Vince by &quot;confirming&quot; a fake age of 22. However on a Mighty Boosch tour Vince jokes that Howard is 62, but then states he is actully 58.

===Vince Noir===
[[Image:Vince Noir Mirrorball.jpg|thumb|220px|right|Noel Fielding playing Vince Noir]]
'''Vince Noir''' was originally created by [[Noel Fielding]] for the 1998 stage show, ''[[The Mighty Boosh (1998 stage show)|The Mighty Boosh]]''. Vince Noir went on to appear in three more stage shows, a radio series, and an TV series on BBC Three.

During the course of the stage shows, the radio series and the TV series, it is implied that he was born in the mid-1980s,&lt;ref name=Party&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Party
| episodelink  = Party (The Mighty Boosh episode)
| url          =
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2007-12-14
| season       = 3
| number       = 5
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and spent much of his early life as an orphan, being raised in a forest by [[Bryan Ferry]],&lt;ref name=Hitcher&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Hitcher
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647523/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-07-06
| season       = 1
| number       = 8
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and then proceeded to spend the latter part of his childhood in civilisation in England, where he befriended Howard Moon at primary school.&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Fountain of Youth
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647528/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-08-16
| season       = 2
| number       = 4
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He left secondary school in his mid-teens, after being convinced by Howard to work at a local zoo called the Zooniverse,&lt;ref name=Jungle&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Jungle
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647524/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-15
| season       = 1
| number       = 5
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite mentioning at various points that he took a [[gap year]],&lt;ref name=CrackFox/&gt; achieved at least two [[BTEC ND|BTEC National Diplomas]],&lt;ref name=Mutants&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Mutants
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647526/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-25
| season       = 1
| number       = 2
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and went to [[college]].&lt;ref name=CrackFox&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = The Strange Tale of the Crack Fox
| episodelink  =
| url          =
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2007-12-07
| season       = 3
| number       = 4
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the Zooniverse, he befriended Naboo the Enigma, Bollo the Ape, and Bob Fossil. He and Howard also went on several adventures whilst working at the Zooniverse, including visiting the [[Tundra|Arctic tundra]],&lt;ref name=Tundra&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Tundra
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647531/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-08
| season       = 1
| number       = 4
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Limbo]],&lt;ref name=Bollo/&gt; and going on a road trip.&lt;ref name=Hitcher/&gt;  By 2005, he had left the Zooniverse, and was living in a flat in [[Dalston]] with Howard, Naboo and Bollo, to concentrate on his musical career, being in a band with Howard, writing music and playing gigs locally. He and Howard went on more adventures, including visiting Planet Xooberon&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth/&gt; and Black Lake,&lt;ref name=OldGregg&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = The Legend of Old Gregg
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647529/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-08-23
| season       = 2
| number       = 5
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and getting stranded on a small desert island.&lt;ref name=MilkyJoe&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = The Nightmare of Milky Joe
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0756940/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-08-30
| season       = 2
| number       = 6
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2007, Vince and Howard were working in the Nabootique, a small [[Charity shop|second-hand shop]] owned by Naboo.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; Although Vince and Howard do not travel much while working at the Nabootique, they still tend to have rather extraordinary adventures in England. Vince is often quite sarcastic to Howard, but when in the radio series Howard says he is going to leave the zoo, Vince tries to persuade him not to, but Howard states that &quot;or would you rather fly around in a [[chopper]], letting off flares?&quot; Overall, Vince's friendship with Howard shows that he sees him as a target to wind up and talk to, but to also act as a shoulder to cry on, but that they are the duo. 

Vince's main personality trait is his relaxed outlook on life, living with perpetually laid back ease, socialising easily with those around him. Vince is often the voice of reason when Howard is being pretentious, although Vince has also been known to have a particularly naïve&lt;ref name=Bollo/&gt; and somewhat childlike&lt;ref name=Eels&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Eels
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1141115/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2007-11-15
| season       = 3
| number       = 1
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; outlook on life. It is often implied that Vince is [[Narcissism|narcissistic]], putting great pride in his appearance, especially his [[Hairstyle|hair]],&lt;ref name=Bollo&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Bollo
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647519/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-01
| season       = 1
| number       = 3
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which he describes as &quot;a basic back-comb structure, slightly root-boosted framing with a cheeky fringe.&quot; Vince usually conforms to specific subcultures which he considers vogue, such as [[Mod (subculture)|mod]],&lt;ref name=Jungle/&gt; [[Goth subculture|goth]],&lt;ref name=Nanageddon&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Nanageddon
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647527/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-08-09
| season       = 2
| number       = 3
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Punk subculture|punk]],&lt;ref name=Punk&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Journey to the Centre of the Punk
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1142689/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2007-11-22
| season       = 3
| number       = 2
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[New Rave]],&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; adapting them to fit his [[Androgyny|androgynous]] [[Dandyism|dandyesque]] appearance. Vince is commonly mistaken for a female, and one-off characters often refer to him as Howard's wife or &quot;lady friend&quot;. He even says to Howard, &quot;I'm the confuser! Is it a man? Is it a woman? I'm not sure if I mind!&quot;, or in the Tundra episode Dixon Bainbridge says &quot;Howard Moon and his ugly girlfriend are missing from the zoo.&quot;

Though he seems much more confident and secure than Howard, Vince is desperate to be admired as an individual and a trendsetter. In one episode he invites party guests to &quot;bask in the glory of [his] outfit&quot;. When a doppelgänger calling himself Lance Dior arises, Vince's optimism crumbles and he becomes insecure.&lt;ref name=Crimping&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = The Power Of The Crimp
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1146717/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2007-11-29
| season       = 3
| number       = 3
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was implied in the third series that Vince had [[bisexual]] tendencies. Such tendencies are first noted in the episode &quot;Journey to the Center of the Punk&quot; when his singular brain cell remarks to Howard that he &quot;[[bisexuality|does swing both ways]]&quot; but didn't really feel &quot;it&quot; with him. Several such references are made in the episode &quot;Party&quot;, especially when he kisses Howard passionately to avoid being beheaded by Dennis the head shaman.

Vince is a fan of [[electro music]] (including [[Gary Numan]]&lt;ref name=Electro&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Electro
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647522/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-29
| season       = 1
| number       = 7
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[The Human League]]&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt;), [[The Rolling Stones]],&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt; [[punk rock]],&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; and [[glam rock]] (including [[Kiss (band)|Kiss]]&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt;).  [[Mick Jagger]] is Vince's hero.&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt; He is highly disdainful of [[jazz]], going as far as to claim to be allergic to it.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; Vince has sung for various bands, including a glam-folk band,&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; an electro band,&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; his and Howard's own band,&lt;ref name=&quot;PriestBeast&quot;/&gt; and a punk band.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; Vince is also a keen [[artist]] having gained a [[BTEC ND|BTEC National Diploma]] in Art,&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; as well as hair design &lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; and a novelist, writing Novellas and publishing them independently.&lt;ref name=Charlie&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = Charlie
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647521/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2004-06-22
| season       = 1
| number       = 6
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Vince Noir is also extremely proud of his hair. He reveals that he uses [[Nicky Clarke]] straighteners in the &quot;Call of the Yeti&quot; episode. Howard is also compassionate about Vince's hair, referring to it as Vince's mane.

Vince's uncle is a French Duke.&lt;ref name=Killeroo/&gt;

Vince also claims he is the &quot;King of the Mods&quot;.&lt;ref name=Jungle/&gt;
In the season two episode entitled &quot;[[Fountain of Youth]]&quot;, Howard Moon claimed to be the same age as Vince but in a later episode in season three,&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; Vince is ten years younger.

In the &quot;Call Of The Yeti&quot; episode, it is shown that Vince has a scar in his lower stomach from a Nicky Clarke straightener after he fell asleep on one of them while in a drunken state. In the same episode, Vince revealed that he cannot drive. In the episode &quot;Fountain of Youth&quot; Vince reveals that he is [[claustrophobic]].

===Naboo the Enigma===
'''Naboo''' is portrayed by [[Michael Fielding]]. He was created for the 2000 stage show, ''[[Autoboosh]]'', and later went on to appear in the pilot and all three series of the [[The Mighty Boosh|TV series]], and the 2006 stage show, ''The Mighty Boosh''.

In the pilot episode, he is mute, according to Fossil. He later disproves this when he mentions Fossil's attraction to Bainbridge.

Naboo is a [[Freelancer|freelance]] [[shaman]] with the ability and knowledge of many spells; he is also a [[recreational drug use]]r and a [[Illegal drug trade|drug dealer]].&lt;ref name=Yeti/&gt;&lt;ref name=Crack/&gt; He is a member of the Board of Shaman, and like many of them, is a heavy drinker, and a rider of the [[magic carpet]].&lt;ref name=Eels/&gt; His [[full name]]&lt;ref name=Crack/&gt; is Naboolio Randolf Roberdy Poberdy the Enigma. Naboo, like all shamans,&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; will turn his back on people to teach them a lesson.

Naboo was born in the 16th century, and raised on the planet Xooberon.&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth/&gt; He was mistakenly sent to Earth by the [[List of one-off characters from The Mighty Boosh#K|King of Xooberon]] to protect the amulet of the planet's Fountain of Youth.&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth/&gt; He became a drug dealer for Rudi &amp; Spider at one point in the 1970s.&lt;ref name=PriestBeast/&gt; He went on to work as a kiosk vendor at the Zooniverse, a zoo in England.&lt;ref name=Killeroo/&gt; While at the Zooniverse, he would often help Howard and Vince out of situations they often found themselves in, typically their explanations being followed by his catchphrase, &quot;I don't believe this!&quot; As an example, when Howard is being pursued by the Spirit of Jazz in the episode 'Electro', Naboo saves him by trapping the spirit in a vacuum cleaner.&lt;ref name=Bollo/&gt; Naboo left the Zooniverse to become a freelance shaman, moving into a flat in Dalston with Howard, Vince, and Bollo, the latter now being his familiar spirit. In the episode &quot;Party&quot; of series 3, it is revealed that Naboo has no genitals, and his groin is as &quot;smooth as the bonnet of a Porsche.&quot;&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; By the 2006 stage show, he had opened a second hand shop called the Nabootique (sometimes known as Naboo's Nik-Naks) .&lt;ref name=BooshLive2006/&gt; In the episode &quot;Fountain of youth&quot; Bollo reveals that Naboo is 406 years old.

===Bollo===
'''Bollo''' was originally portrayed by [[Dave Brown (comedian)|Dave Brown]], and also portrayed in the first TV series by Peter Elliot. He first appeared in &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|Jazz]]&quot;, an episode of the 2001 [[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|radio series]]. He went on to appear in all three series of the TV show and the [[The Mighty Boosh (2006 stage show)|2006 stage show]].

Bollo is an [[anthropomorphic]] ape who has been portrayed as inept yet immensely strong.&lt;ref name=Yeti/&gt; He and Vince are very close, a stark contrast to his relationship with Howard.&lt;ref name=MilkyJoe/&gt; His catchphrase is &quot;I've got a bad feeling about this...&quot;, said in every show since &quot;[[The Call of the Yeti]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
  | title = The Mighty Boosh: interview
  | work = Comedy
  | pages = 1
  | publisher = Time Out London
  | url =http://www.timeout.com/london/comedy/features/171.html
  | accessdate = 2007-12-30 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
He also DJs at the London nightclub Fabric on Tuesdays.

He first appeared in &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|Jazz]]&quot;, an episode of a radio series, portrayed by Dave Brown. He next appeared in &quot;[[Mutants (The Mighty Boosh)|Mutants]]&quot;, where he is stolen by Bainbridge to mutate.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; He then appeared in &quot;[[Bollo (The Mighty Boosh)|Bollo]]&quot;, where he is gravely ill, escaping death when the [[Grim Reaper]] takes Howard instead of him.&lt;ref name=Bollo/&gt; He briefly appears in &quot;[[Electro (The Mighty Boosh)|Electro]]&quot;, smashing up a guitar in the style of [[Jimi Hendrix]].&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; By the second series he has become Naboo's [[familiar spirit]], and has appeared in every episode since.
&lt;ref name=Yeti&gt;
{{cite episode
| title        = The Call of the Yeti
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647520/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-07-26
| season       = 2
| number       = 1
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bob Fossil===
'''Bob Fossil''' is portrayed by [[Rich Fulcher]]. In the radio series Fossil is the ill-tempered owner of Bob Fossil's Funworld, an inept zoo. In the TV series, he is the manager of the Zooniverse and zoo owner Dixon Bainbridge's right-hand man. He is loud and brash and is normally portrayed as Howard and Vince's enemy, often trying to set them up for disaster, although on occasion he has expressed attraction to both of them. On radio, Fossil liked Vince and hated Howard, on television he generally dislikes both of them (although he is sometimes friendly to Vince), and his radio persona is somewhat replaced by employer Bainbridge. Fossil has a desperate crush on Bainbridge, and declares that he is very interested in getting involved in Bainbridge's &quot;shady operations&quot;.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; Bainbridge often pushes Fossil roughly aside, knees him in the groin or punches him in the face but Fossil claims this is something they do all the time and it's a way of showing affection. On at least one occasion, Fossil and Bainbridge apparently rode in a pick-up truck and beat up [[midgets]], though this may be more rambling from Fossil.

In the TV series Fossil is portrayed as incompetent; for example he does not know how to dial with a phone and calls a portable tape recorder his &quot;talk box&quot;.&lt;ref name=Killeroo/&gt; He is often very childlike and emotional, and when confronted with something disturbing (such as a mysteriously floating cup, or a cage full of [[mutants]]) he will shriek horribly.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; Though Fossil is chief zoo keeper, he knows nothing about animals. He is unable to identify the animals he supposedly cares for at the zoo, even the relatively easy ones, such as the elephant (which he calls &quot;the grey leg-face man&quot;), The panda (&quot;The black eyed chinese people who eat sticks&quot;) or Ivan the bear (&quot;the hairy Russian carpet guy&quot;). According to the radio series, Fossil also had a traumatic childhood which involved his mother hiding in a bunker at breakfast while throwing eggs at him. In the series, Fossil has his own theme song for the zoo: &quot;Nicey nicey zoo zoo, for him and her and me and you!&quot;&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; In the radio series, Bob has a brother called Wilbur who reunites him and his mother, who had believed that Bob died in Vietnam.

Though Fossil and the zoo were, without explanation, absent from the second television series, he makes a brief reappearance at the end of ''The Nightmare of Milky Joe'' as the presenter of &quot;The Pie Face Showcase&quot; TV music programme. In this appearance he makes a joke about his wife; it is unclear if he actually has a wife or not, although she is also mentioned in the radio series ('I got a tiny wife to support'). He returns in the third episode of series 3, &quot;The Power of the Crimp&quot;, as the owner of the Velvet Onion club, where Vince and Howard regularly gig. It is revealed that his mother thinks he is in a Vietnamese prisoner of war camp and that he has sent a bundle of sticks to his brother, Donny.&lt;ref name=Crimping/&gt; Fossil was last seen on the TV show, in the episodes &quot;Party&quot; and &quot;The Chokes&quot;.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt;

In the live show it is revealed that he starred in the title role of a detective show called &quot;Big Leg&quot;. The character of Big Leg later appears to defeat The Hitcher.

Fossil speaks with an American accent. He does not like cricket, and communicates this through the medium of dance, particularly to [[10CC|10CC's]] ''&quot;[[Dreadlock Holiday]]&quot;''. It is possible this dislike stems from a bad experience, as he tells Naboo &quot;...that's why you should never bring a cricket bat to Greece&quot;.
Fossil also created the &quot;Pocket Cup&quot; in the episode 'Killeroo'. He was later seen selling them at the fight for 5 euros.

==Recurring characters==
===Dixon Bainbridge===
'''Dixon Bainbridge''' was originally portrayed by [[Richard Ayoade]] in the pilot episode, and later by [[Matt Berry]] throughout the first series. He originally appeared in the pilot and several episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 1)|first series]] of the TV show, and in the 2006 stage show, ''The Mighty Boosh''.

Bainbridge is the owner of the Zooniverse, as well as being an admired adventurer with an impressive moustache.&lt;ref name=Tundra/&gt; Bob Fossil is deeply in love with Bainbridge, which often results in Bainbridge beating him up.&lt;ref name=Tundra/&gt;

His first appearance is in the pilot episode of the TV series, portrayed by Richard Ayoade. He then appears in &quot;[[Mutants (The Mighty Boosh)|Mutants]]&quot;, where he steals and mutilates the various animals and keepers of the Zooniverse.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; He next appears in &quot;[[Tundra (The Mighty Boosh)|Tundra]]&quot;, a remake of the original pilot episode. He inspires Howard and Vince to travel to the Arctic Tundra and find the Egg of Mantumbi, which Bainbridge later finds himself, escaping the [[List of one-off characters from The Mighty Boosh#Black Frost|Black Frost]] by using the heat stored in his own moustache.&lt;ref name=Tundra/&gt; Bainbridge later tries to sell the Zooniverse to build a road over it in &quot;[[Jungle (The Mighty Boosh)|Jungle]]&quot;; a plan which is later averted by Howard and Vince.&lt;ref name=Jungle/&gt; Bainbridge finally appears in &quot;[[Charlie (The Mighty Boosh)|Charlie]]&quot;, where he steals credit for Vince's work as a novelist, causing Charlie, the subject of Vince's novels, to appear and attack Bainbridge and his publisher.&lt;ref name=Charlie/&gt; He was last seen delivering a box to the Nabootique.&lt;ref name=BooshLive2006/&gt;

It was revealed in ''The Mighty Book Of Boosh'' that Bainbridge had been [[knight]]ed in a story that involved Bainbridge rescuing his kidnapped wife in [[Brazil]].

===Lester Corncrake===
'''Lester Corncrake''' is portrayed by [[Rich Fulcher]]. He appeared in several episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|third series]] of the TV show.

Lester Corncrake is a [[blindness|blind]] [[vinyl]] doctor who is close friends with Howard Moon, and also an avid jazz fan.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; He mistakenly believes he is [[Black people|black]].&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt;

Lester first appeared in the 2007 episode, &quot;Journey to the Centre of the Punk&quot; in which he accompanies Howard on his microscopic journey inside Vince to eliminate the jazz virus he has ingested.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt; He next appears briefly in the 2007 episode &quot;The Power of the Crimp&quot;, disowning Howard after his and Vince's poor performance at a gig at the Velvet Onion where they were sabotaged by their new rivals, the Flighty Zeus.&lt;ref name=Crimping/&gt; His last appearance to date was in the 2007 episode, &quot;Party&quot;, where he is a guest at Howard's birthday, where he is mistakenly [[Decapitation|beheaded]] by Dennis, then [[raped]] by Tony Harrison. He is briefly mentioned in the third series finale meaning that he is still alive&lt;ref name=Party/&gt;

===Dennis===
'''Dennis''' is portrayed by Julian Barratt. He was originally created for the 2005 TV episode &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|Nanageddon]]&quot;, and later appeared in three episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|third TV series]] in 2007.

Dennis is the head of the Board of Shamen, although he sometimes wonders about the team he has assembled.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He is married to an extreme sports calendar model. (She tried to seduce Vince in the episode 'Party'). &lt;ref name=Party/&gt; He originally trained [[List of recurring characters from The Mighty Boosh#Naboo|Naboo]] in the ways of the Shaman.&lt;ref name=Crack/&gt; He beheaded Lester Corncrake at Howard Moon's birthday party.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; He is skilled with a sword, and defeats three attackers in the party episode.

===Rudi van DiSarzio===
'''Rudi van DiSarzio''' is portrayed by Rich Fulcher and Julian Barratt. He was originally created for the 1998 stage show, [[The Mighty Boosh (1998 stage show)|''The Mighty Boosh'']], and also appeared in an outtake for the &quot;Jazz&quot; episode of the 2001 radio series ''[[The Boosh (radio series)|The Boosh]]'', both portrayed by Rich Fulcher. He was then portrayed by Julian Barratt in the 2004 episode  &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (series 1)|Jungle]]&quot;, and the 2005 episode  &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|The Priest and the Beast]]&quot; of the TV series. He last appeared in the 2006 stage show, ''Boosh Live''.

Rudi is a High Priest of the Order of the Psychedelic Monks and plays guitar and sings in Rudi &amp; Spider.&lt;ref name=PriestBeast&gt;{{cite episode
| title        = The Priest and the Beast
| episodelink  =
| url          = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0647530/
| series       = [[The Mighty Boosh]]
| network      = [[BBC Three]]
| airdate      = 2005-08-02
| season       = 2
| number       = 2
| minutes      =
}}&lt;/ref&gt; He and [[List of one-off characters from The Mighty Boosh#Spyder Dijon|Spyder Dijon]] are Bongo Brothers.&lt;ref name=PriestBeast/&gt; Rudi and Spider quarrel often, but are very close despite having starkly different personalities. Rudi's behaviour and attitude is extremely [[puritanical]]; he thinks of alcohol and women as &quot;distractions&quot; (in stark contrast to the animalistic nature of his fellow band member, Spider Dijon), and even went so far as to say that he considered all women &quot;strange and evil&quot;.&lt;ref name=PriestBeast/&gt; He is also suspected of having a sexual relationship with his guitar, which he calls Miranda, though Rudy has always maintained that this was a misunderstanding on his wife's part (&quot;I was naked, it was dark, I was changing a string, I became entangled.&quot;)&lt;ref name=PriestBeast/&gt; Whenever he is asked for his name, Rudi's initial response will often be &quot;I go by many names...&quot; followed by a list of radically odd and random names.&lt;ref name=Jungle/&gt; Some of his many names include &quot;Shatoon, Bringer of Corn&quot;, &quot;Mickey Nine, The Dreamweaver&quot;, &quot;Photoshop&quot;, &quot;Trenu, The Boiler&quot;, &quot;Marjorie Keek&quot;,  &quot;Mystery Man&quot;, &quot;The Shadow Dweller&quot;, &quot;Diviner of Mysteries&quot;, &quot;Rudi the Pruney&quot;, &quot;Miraculous Mark&quot;, &quot;Domino, the Bounty Hunter&quot;, &quot;Clive&quot; and &quot;[[Cillit Bang]]&quot;, He is often called &quot;Peppercorn&quot; by the Dutch. A similar character, Howard's uncle Pedro, appears in the radio episode &quot;Tundra&quot;, also claiming to go by many names.

In ''Jungle'' and some other appearances he has a tiny (puppet) body and he appears attached to a mobile backdrop; in most appearances he is of normal size and wears a long purple robe. In all of his appearances on stage or TV, Rudy has large buck teeth, browned skin (it is not clear what ethnicity is meant to be) and an enormous afro haircut with a door in it that can open to take people on bizarre psychedelic trips. He claims to have earned his door by becoming spiritually enlightened as a monk. Rudi is allergic to wheat.

===Mrs Gideon===
'''Mrs Gideon''' is portrayed by [[Victoria Wicks]]. She was mentioned briefly in the ''[[The Boosh (radio series)|The Boosh]]'' as Howard's band partner and lover, until the smooth talking Rudy Mancheigo (based on the character of Rudy van DiSarzio) wooed her with empty wisdoms, and appeared in the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 1)|first series]] of the TV show.

Mrs Gideon was the Head of Reptiles at the Zooniverse.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; She was the chief love interest of Howard in Series 1 but as she could not remember his face, his love went unrequited. She was, however, interested in Vince, admiring his paintings, remarking that Vince's portrait of Howard (a featureless face atop a Zooniverse uniform) looked just like him, and going to Vince when her snake was stolen by Bainbridge, much to Howard's disgust and envy.&lt;ref name=Mutants/&gt; She is fond of trumpets and bookmarks. The trumpet reference is related to the Biblical legend of the [[Gideon (Bible)|Trumpet of Gideon]].

===Old Gregg===
[[Image:Old Gregg.jpg|thumb|left|Noel Fielding as Old Gregg in &quot;The Legend of Old Gregg&quot;.]]
'''Old Gregg''' is portrayed by [[Noel Fielding]]. He was created for &quot;[[The Legend of Old Gregg]]&quot;, a 2005 episode of the TV series. He later went on to appear in the 2006 stage show, ''[[The Mighty Boosh (2006 stage show)|The Mighty Boosh]]''.

Old Gregg is a [[Hermaphrodite|hermaphroditic]] [[merman]] who occasionally refers to his vagina, which emits a blinding light, as his ''&quot;mangina.&quot;'' He inhabits a cave below the lake in a village called Black Lake.&lt;ref name=OldGregg/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = Tim Hope| title = The Mighty Boosh 2 - Making of Series Two| medium = DVD| publisher = BBC DVD|date=2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Old Gregg is fond of [[Bailey's Irish Cream]], as well as being a watercolour painter.&lt;ref name=OldGregg/&gt; He owns The Funk, an [[Extraterrestrial life|extraterrestrial]] covered in 'udder-like' teats which lactate liquid [[Funk]].&lt;ref name=OldGregg/&gt; Old Gregg is in love with Howard Moon; singing a song with him entitled &quot;Love Games&quot;, chronicling his obsession and Howard's reluctance, and later [[Proposal of marriage|proposing]] to Howard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Love Games&amp;nbsp;— Old Gregg &amp; Howard Moon | work = The Mighty Boosh Lyrics | publisher = songmeanings.net | url = http://www.songmeanings.net/lyric.php?lid=3530822107858638096 | accessdate = 2006-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; A deleted scene from &quot;The Legend of Old Gregg&quot; documents many [[rumours]] about Old Gregg, including his [[Cannibalism|cannibalistic]] nature, and his age at over 1,200 years old.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = | title = The Mighty Boosh 2 - Deleted Scenes - &quot;The Legend of Old Gregg&quot; Clip 2| medium = DVD| publisher = BBC DVD|date=2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Before meeting Howard, Old Gregg was obsessed with [[Slash (musician)|Slash]], the former Guns N' Roses guitarist, to the point of kidnapping him. It was mentioned that it ended badly, involving Gregg being very upset and Slash plummeting from a helicopter down 1000 feet onto some sharp rocks. He also claims that he said, &quot;You should build a Velvet Revolver and go and live in it.&quot; - [[Velvet Revolver]] being Slash's new band.&lt;ref name=Book/&gt;

Old Gregg is first seen in the 2005 episode, &quot;The Legend of Old Gregg&quot; in which he meets and falls in love with Howard, who is then rescued by Vince. Old Gregg then joins Howard in the 2006 stage show, after tracking him down and having himself delivered in a box, where they sing a rendition of &quot;Love Games&quot; and are later seen [[kiss]]ing.&lt;ref name=BooshLive2006/&gt; Old Gregg last appeared in deleted scene from the 2007 episode, &quot;[[Party (The Mighty Boosh)|Party]]&quot;, disguised as a woman who has taken a liking to Howard.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = | title = The Mighty Boosh 3 - Deleted Scenes - &quot;Party&quot; | medium = DVD| publisher = BBC DVD|date=2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The episode became popular on [[YouTube]] and Old Gregg became something of an [[internet meme]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web
|url=http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Memes/LiveActionTV
|title=Live Action TV&amp;nbsp;— Television Tropes and Idioms
|accessdate=4 January 2009
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a legend of an Old Gregg merman that existed at Orford Castle in Suffolk.  The tale is that this merman  was caught in fishermen's nets in about 1167 and was held for six months until he escaped. The creature was naked, covered in hair and never talked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/suffolk/going_out/on_stage/2003/07/merman/preview.shtml|title=The Wild Man of Orford returns|date=2003-07-05|accessdate=2008-03-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tony Harrison===
[[Image:MightBooshTonyHarrison&amp;Saboo.jpg|thumb|right|Noel Fielding as Tony Harrison, right, with [[Richard Ayoade]] as Saboo]]
'''Tony Harrison''' is portrayed by [[Noel Fielding]]. He was originally created for a 2005 episode of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|second series]] of ''[[The Mighty Boosh]]'', &quot;[[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|Nanageddon]]&quot;, and later returned for three episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|third series]].

Tony Harrison is a disembodied pink head topped with a bulbous shape vaguely resembling a phallus,&lt;ref&gt;''The Mighty Boosh 2 -Commentary - &quot;Nanageddon&quot;'' [DVD] BBC DVD&lt;/ref&gt; or a [[squid]], with eight or so tentacle-like appendages sprouting from his neck, and a coarse, nasal East London brogue.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He is a shaman, and member of the Board of Shamen. Tony appears unable to speak without smiling, even when relaying the most dire information, such as when relaying the importance of Shaman Juice to Naboo after Naboo had the juice taken from him by Crack Fox. Although Harrison claims that his navigational skills are second to none, and to be a 'unique thinker' in the field of strategy, the other shamen are quick to point out the apparent limitations of his lack of mobility; Tony is barely mobile within the show, but is frequently outraged at suggestions that this is the case.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; Harrison's drug of choice is [[poppers]], for which he has an immense capacity.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; Tony is married, and makes frequent reference to Mrs Harrison who, as yet, has not been seen on the show ,&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; and who, in the 2008 live tour, is announced to have left him. Tony's marriage does not prevent him from appearing to indulge an apparent sexual attraction to human heads. Harrison also implies that he has given Mrs Harrison the &quot;back of his tentacle&quot; in the past, and is disgusted that Dennis seems &quot;whipped&quot; by his extreme sports calendar model wife. Tony's catchphrase, &quot;This is an outrage!&quot; has been spoken by him during every appearance in the show: Tony uses the phrase both when he feels hard-done-by, and when sexually aroused. He is an ardent fan of [[Fleetwood Mac]], to the extent of suggesting playing the album [[Tusk (album)|''Tusk'']] in its entirety while DJ-ing Howard's birthday party with Saboo.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; He also claims to have an [[Large Goods Vehicle|HGV]] licence.&lt;ref name=Eels/&gt;

====Appearances====

Tony first appeared, alongside the rest of the Board of Shaman, in the 2005 TV episode &quot;Nanageddon&quot;, where he and fellow Shaman [[List of recurring characters from The Mighty Boosh#Saboo|Saboo]] are given the task of finding and exorcising the powerful demon Nanatoo, which ends in Saboo ejecting him from his magic carpet out of annoyance.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He next appears in the 2007 TV episode, &quot;Eels&quot;, accompanying the other Shaman on [[List of recurring characters from The Mighty Boosh#Dennis|Dennis]]'s stag weekend.&lt;ref name=Eels/&gt; He then appears briefly in the 2007 TV episode, &quot;The Strange Tale of The Crack Fox&quot; being Naboo’s executioner for the crime of giving a malevolent fox access to shaman juice.&lt;ref name=Crack&gt;{{cite episode | title = The Strange Tale of the Crack Fox | url = http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1155203/| series = [[The Mighty Boosh]]| network = [[BBC Three]]| airdate = 2007-12-06| season = 3| number = 4| minutes =}}&lt;/ref&gt; His latest appearance was in the 2007 episode &quot;Party&quot; where he and Saboo DJ'd at Howard's birthday party.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt; In ''[[The Mighty Book of Boosh]]'' it is revealed that Tony is the Ents manager for the Shaman Council, and that he originates from Xooberon, the same planet as Naboo. It's also revealed that his middle name is Ian.&lt;ref name=Book /&gt;

===The Hitcher===
'''The Hitcher''' is portrayed by [[Noel Fielding]]. He was created for the 1999 stage show ''[[Autoboosh]]'', and later appeared in the 2001 [[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|radio series]], three episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh|television series]], and the 2006 stage show, ''The Mighty Boosh'', in which he is the main antagonist, [[murder|killing]] all the main characters at one point.

The Hitcher is an old [[cockney]] man with long grey hair, green skin, a large [[Polo mint]] over his left eye (which he refers to as his &quot;solo Polo peeper&quot;), a top hat and black and red clothing. He is [[evil]], threatening to kill Howard and Vince whenever he meets them, and killing the whole cast in the stage show.&lt;ref name=BooshLive2006&gt;{{cite video
  | title = The Mighty Boosh Live
  | medium = DVD
  | publisher = Universal
  |date=2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hitcher/&gt; His real name is Baboo Yagu, but he is almost always referred to as The Hitcher.&lt;ref name=Hitcher/&gt; He is also a proponent of jazz fusion, especially proficient on the bass guitar.&lt;ref name=Hitcher/&gt;  The name Baboo Yagu likely comes from the old Russian legend of [[Baba Yaga]].

The Hitcher has a confused history; he states in &quot;[[The Hitcher]]&quot; that as a child his parents were ashamed of his small thumb (prompting him to seek out the [[Hornet]] [[Shaman]]). However, in &quot;Eels&quot; he reveals that Elsie, proprietor of the Pie and Mash Shop, gave him free eels &quot;on account of [him] being an orphan n' that&quot; (Eels). In [[The Mighty Book of Boosh]], it is revealed The Hitcher trained a man called Ian in the ways of a Cockney. Ian later goes on to become [[Jack the Ripper]], and the Hitcher murders him as punishment for 'slashing Women'.
&lt;ref name=Book&gt;{{Cite book
|title=The Mighty Book of Boosh
|first1=Julian
|last1=Barratt
|first2=Noel
|last2=Fielding
|year=2008
|publisher=Canongate Books Ltd
|isbn=978-1847673220
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Hitcher is sometimes accompanied by two short, rotund henchmen called the Piper Twins.  The Piper Twins are dressed similarly to the Hitcher, with similar Polo mint eyes, but wear [[bowler hat]]s and have long red moustaches, made from [[Licorice candy#Red .22liquorice.22|strawberry bootlaces]]. They are portrayed by [[Rich Fulcher]] and [[Dave Brown (comedian)|Dave Brown]]

The Hitcher's first appearance was in ''Autoboosh'', where he encounters Howard and Vince, trapping them in a box and then rapping about doing so.&lt;ref name=Autoboosh&gt;{{cite video |people=Julian Barratt, Noel Fielding, Rich Fulcher, Dave Brown |title=Autoboosh |url=http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoboosh |accessdate=2007-12-30 |date=1998|medium=Stage show}}{{Circular-ref|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; This plot was the template for a 2001 [[The Mighty Boosh (radio series)|radio episode]] and a 2004 [[The Mighty Boosh (series 1)|television episode]], both titled &quot;Hitcher&quot;.

[[Image:thehitcher2.jpg|thumb|right|The Hitcher in series 3.]]
In the television episode, he is proprietor of the &quot;Zoo for Animal Offenders&quot;.&lt;ref name=Hitcher/&gt; He later appears in the 2005 television episode, &quot;Fountain Of Youth&quot;, where he plans to use the fountain of youth's magical qualities for himself with the motive to rule the universe.&lt;ref name=FountainOfYouth/&gt;  Next he appeared in the episode &quot;The Nightmare of Milky Joe&quot; as one of the coconut people.   He then appeared in the 2006 stage show, ''The Mighty Boosh'', which contained elements of both ''Autoboosh'' and the 1999 stage show, ''[[Arctic Boosh]]''.&lt;ref name=BooshLive2006/&gt; His latest appearance was in the 2007 television episode, &quot;Eels&quot;, in which he attempts to run a [[protection racket]] on The Nabootique.&lt;ref name=Eels/&gt;

The Hitcher's appearance, though always grotesque, alters slightly during the course of the television show. In the first series episode &quot;The Hitcher&quot; he has an abnormally large thumb, as well as nose and chin. He explains this as a result of visiting a Hornet Shaman in the bin of a primary school and asking him to enlarge his thumb. In the second series his thumbs are both normally sized. In the third series he has both a normal chin and nose, and looks altogether much younger and more spry&amp;nbsp;— a direct result of his showering in the Fountain of Youth in the episode of the same name (Series 2) - although his voice, based loosely on Noel Fielding's grandfather, remains as haggard as ever.
In the episode of &quot;the Hitcher&quot; of series one, Noel explains that the Hitcher is based on his grandfather crossed with the character Fagin from the play Oliver.

The Hitcher appeared on ''[[Friday Night with Jonathan Ross]]'' singing a song about eels. Although he dances energetically and enthusiastically, he falls to his knees at the end of the song, complaining of his &quot;old legs.&quot; The Polo came off his eye during the song and he casually tossed it aside.

===The Spirit of Jazz/Howlin' Jimmy Jefferson===
[[Image:The-Spirit-Of-Jaz.jpeg|thumb|left|The Spirit Of Jazz as he appears in Electro]]
'''The Spirit of Jazz/Howlin' Jimmy Jefferson''' is portrayed by [[Noel Fielding]].  He appears in three separate forms over the course of the series. It is revealed in the series 3 episode, [[Journey to the Centre of Punk]], that he was a famous jazz musician that lived by the swamps of [[Mississippi]]. When he was alive he had black and white skin, red eyes and wore a white suit and top hat. When he discovered he was dying of a &quot;strange swamp fever&quot; he decided to make one final record called Voodoo Scat and mixed it with a drop of his own blood.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt;

In the series 1 episode &quot;[[Electro (The Mighty Boosh)|Electro]]&quot; is the first appearance of Howlin' Jimmy Jefferson. His ghost is featured in this episode and referred to as the Spirit of Jazz. In this form he looks the same as he did when he was alive but now has a number of [[supernatural]] powers and uses them to [[Spirit possession|possess]] people such as Howard. Howard apparently made a deal with him years ago in which he would make Howard one of the greatest jazz musicians of all time. From that moment on whenever Howard played an [[Musical instrument|instrument]] the Spirit of Jazz would possess him and make him do &quot;strange things&quot; such as playing the trumpet so vigorously that his clothes tore off.&lt;ref name=Electro/&gt; The story is never fully resolved, however, subsequent episodes have shown Howard playing several instruments without any implication that he is possessed by the Spirit of Jazz.

Howard later obtains the voodoo scat record that Howlin' Jimmy made and Vince eats a piece of it which causes one of Howlin' Jimmy's blood cells (referred to as the jazz cell) to try and take over Vince's body. Howard along with Lester Corncrake shrink down and enters Vince's body in an attempt to defeat the jazz cell but end up bringing it out of Vince's body with them and making it much larger. It is eventually defeated by an [[Hepatitis C|infected]] [[safety pin]] and walks away complaining, falling over just outside the door of the Nabootique. In the form of the jazz cell, Howlin' Jimmy looks like a ball of black dreadlocks with a head and top hat.&lt;ref name=Punk/&gt;

===Kirk===
'''Kirk''' is portrayed by Kirk Gaitskell-Kendrick.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://www.tv.com/kirk-gaitskell-kendrick/person/604597/summary.html
|title= Kirk Gaitskell-Kendrick
|accessdate= 2007-01-27
|work=
|publisher= [http://www.tv.com/ TV.com]
|pages=
|doi=
|archiveurl=
|archivedate=
|quote=
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Kirk is a nephew of Noel Fielding's former girlfriend Dee Plume, although Noel referred to Kirk as his own nephew.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| title = The Mighty Boosh 3 - Making of Series Three| medium = DVD| publisher = BBC DVD|date=2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He first appeared in the 2005 episode, &quot;Nanageddon&quot;, and later appeared in three 2007 episodes.

Kirk is a child Shaman, and a member of the Board of Shaman.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He has admitted to being &quot;an erotic adventurer of the most deranged kind&quot; from the fourth dimension,&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; and a &quot;vehicular menace, mowing down all in [his] path&quot;.&lt;ref name=Eels/&gt;   Kirk is renowned by the other members of the Board of Shaman for having the greatest capacity for taking drugs.&lt;ref name=Crack/&gt; To this day Tony Harrison wonders what Kirk is looking at when he's high (as he stares off into the distance for extreme lengths of time) and is told that nobody knows. A deleted scene from &quot;Nanageddon&quot; reveals that Saboo trained Kirk in the ways of the Shaman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video| people = | title = The Mighty Boosh 2 - Deleted Scenes - &quot;Nanageddon&quot; | medium = DVD| publisher = BBC DVD|date=2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Moon===
'''The Moon''' is portrayed by [[Noel Fielding]] with his face covered in shaving foam. He was originally created for Fielding's 2002 stand-up show ''Voodoo Hedgehog'' at the Edinburgh Festival, his appearance is a tribute to/derived from [[Georges Méliès]]' [[A trip to the moon]].{{Citation needed|date=January 2009}} He later appeared in all episodes of [[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|series two]] and [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|three]] of ''The Mighty Boosh'', and in the 2006 and 2008 live shows.

The Moon talks about himself, the stars and other planets, as well as strange and often borderline incoherent things. For example, he talks about licking the Sun's back without it knowing, or the time he saw a man with a telescope.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He has a variety of poems and songs. The Moon always appears to be simple-mindedly cheerful, and he is described by Tony Harrison as &quot;an [[alabaster]] [[retard]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt;

===Tommy Nookah===
'''Tommy Nookah''' was originally portrayed by [[Richard Ayoade]]. He appeared in the radio episode &quot;Jungle&quot; and later in revised form during the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 1)|first series]] of the TV show, where he was played by Rich Fulcher rather than Ayoade. In both versions he is the previous owner of the zoo where Howard and Vince work; he is assumed by many to be dead. Howard sees him as an idol and mentor, despite Vince pointing out that he was a short, stocky character with an exceptionally wide head. Howard later enters the jungle room of the zoo to find Tommy. In the TV version Tommy has subsisted for years on nothing but cheese, and as a result his head has turned into cheese. Tommy considers himself King of the [[Rockers]], and flies into a rage when confronted by [[mod (subculture)|mods]].

===The Parka People===
'''The Parka People''' are a diminutive race of people who wear [[Anorak|parka]]s that completely obscure their features. They appear in the &quot;Tundra&quot; storyline and the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|third series]] episode &quot;Party&quot;.  By looking deep into the parka, one can see one's deepest desire. The Parka People typically guard the object of the Arctic quest (Egg of Mantumbi, Ruby of Kukundu, etc.). One of the Parka people appears in the stage show (played here by Noel Fielding); Howard takes a letter out from under the parka, but first he accidentally rips out its eye and sticks it back in its pocket. The parka person then states &quot;Oh, that's where my pen went !&quot;.

===Saboo===
'''Saboo''' is portrayed by [[Richard Ayoade]]. He was originally created for &quot;Nanageddon&quot;, an episode of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 2)|second series]] of ''[[The Mighty Boosh]]'' and later appeared in three episodes of the [[The Mighty Boosh (series 3)|third series]], &quot;Eels&quot;, &quot;The Strange Tale of the Crack Fox&quot; and &quot;Party&quot;.

Saboo is a shaman, and a member of the Board of Shaman.&lt;ref name=Nanageddon/&gt; He is also a DJ.&lt;ref name=Party/&gt;  He is close to Kirk but is unaware of his sexual adventurism, extreme road rage, and great capacity for drug consumption, and dislikes Tony Harrison, whom he has attempted to kill, and Naboo, whose propensity for getting in trouble with the Board of Shaman often results in Saboo attempting to make an example of him. He also frequently refers to his colleagues as 'plum(s)' and variations thereof when they act foolishly. During his first appearance, he frequently referred to 'the crunch,' criticising other characters for their lack of familiarity with it to the point of being accused of being 'obsessed with the crunch.' &quot;The crunch&quot;, in this sense, is a high pressure moment, which is a common usage of the term in UK English. He was Kirk's tutor.

===Leroy===
Leroy is a recurring character that only ever appears on screen once in the television series when Vince creates a band which was a glam rock/folk fusion in series 1 episode 7 electro.  He is said to have helped Howard edit the show's script in the series 1 episode &quot;Tundra&quot;, cutting out the scene where Vince has the legs of a ram. Leroy also goes on secret spy skiing missions in the Alps as is mentioned in the series 3 episode &quot;Eels&quot;. He is mentioned in the episode &quot;Electro&quot; as having tried to form a glam-folk-rock band with Vince. It is assumed the character shown in the following flashback is Leroy. He is played by Olly Ralfe in this short scene. He is also referred to very briefly in episode 1 of season 1 Killaroo when Vince states that Leroy had told him earlier he saw Howard dancing for Fossil in the moonlight in &quot;little blue pants&quot; and is later referenced in &quot;The Ape of Death&quot; talking to Vince on a cellphone when Howard is &quot;haunting&quot; him.

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{The Mighty Boosh}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Recurring Characters From The Mighty Boosh, List Of}}
[[Category:The Mighty Boosh]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
