<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2852956" ns="0" title="Market sentiment"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=June 2011}}

'''Market sentiment''' is the general prevailing attitude of [[investor]]s as to anticipated [[market trends|price development]] in a market. This attitude is the accumulation of a variety of [[fundamental analysis|fundamental]] and [[technical analysis|technical]] factors, including price history, economic reports, seasonal factors, and national and world events.

For example, if investors expect upward price movement in the stock market, the sentiment is said to be '''''bullish'''''. On the contrary, if the market sentiment is '''''bearish''''', most investors expect downward price movement.

Market sentiment is monitored with a variety of technical and statistical methods such as the number of advancing versus declining stocks and new highs versus new lows comparisons. A large share of overall movement of an individual stock has been attributed to market sentiment&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Dorsey, ''Point and Figure Charting'', Sentiment has a &quot;''66% influence on the overall movement of an individual stock''&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The stock market's demonstration of the situation is often described as ''all boats float or sink with the tide'', in the popular [[Wall Street]] phrase &quot;''the trend is your friend''&quot;.

[[File:Bulle und Bär Frankfurt.jpg|left|thumb|300px|''Bear and Bull'', Reinhard Dachlauer, [[Frankfurt]]]]

Market sentiment, as such, might be acquired from more than one sentiment analytical tool. For example there could be just simple extraction of movement on stock exchange and validly called market sentiment. Another tool is to extract the news and media information based on their polarity. Yet another sub-subject might be community sentiment about the market movements (blogs, forums).

In the last decade, investors are also known to measure market sentiment through the use of [[news analytics]], which include [[sentiment analysis]] on textual stories about companies and sectors.

&lt;br clear=both/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Pivot point]]
*[[market trend]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/sentimentindicator.asp Investopedia.com - Sentiment Indicator]
* [http://www.marketmeter.com MarketMeter.com - Market Sentiment Survey]
* [http://www.sentix-index.com sentix-Indices - Market Sentiment database]
* [http://samuelssonsrapport.se/samuelssons-sentiment/vill-du-vara-med/ Swedish Market Sentiment - Swedish Market Sentiment Survey and database]


{{stock market}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Market Sentiment}}
[[Category:Investment]]


{{econ-stub}}

[[fi:Markkinatunnelma]]
[[de:Sentiment]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
