<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2859496" ns="0" title="Thrust (Transformers)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Thrust''' is the name of several [[fictional characters]] in the various [[Transformers universes]]. The original character was an evil red Decepticon jet, with most of the following character using the name Thrust being a variation on that concept. The biggest exception being the Thrust who appeared in ''Beast Machines'' who was an evil Vehicon who turned into a motorcycle.

==Transformers: Generation 1==
{{Transformers character|
 name           = Thrust
|image          = Thrust.jpg
|caption        = The Decepticon Thrust Box Art
|affiliation    = Decepticon
|subgroup       = Convention Exclusives, Deluxe Vehicles, [[Seekers (Transformers)|Seekers]]
|rank           = 5, 4 (Timelines)
|function       = Warrior
|partner        = Dirge, Ramjet, Bug Bite, Thundercracker, and Dreadwind
|motto          = ''&quot;My engines' roar is my enemies' song of doom!&quot;'' (Generation 1)&lt;BR&gt; &quot;''I'll wash my actuators in your spilled lubricant, weakling.''&quot; (Timelines)
|alternatemodes =Cybertronian jet &lt;BR&gt; Modified [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle]]
|series         = ''[[Transformers: Generation 1]]''&lt;BR&gt;''[[Smallest Transformers]]''&lt;BR&gt;''[[Transformers: Timelines]]''&lt;BR&gt;''[[Transformers: Universe]]''&lt;BR&gt;''Transformers: Henkei''&lt;BR&gt;''[[Transformers: Generations]]''
|engvoice        = [[Ed Gilbert (actor)|Ed Gilbert]]
}}
'''Thrust''' in the original [[Transformers (toyline)|Transformers toyline]] is the name of a [[Decepticon]] who transforms into a red [[VTOL]] jet.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | title=The Unofficial Guide to Transformers 1980s Through 1990s Revised &amp; Expanded 2nd Edition | last=Alvarez | first=J.E. | year=2001 | publisher=Schiffer Publishing Ltd.| ISBN=0764313649 | page= 28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thrust, [[Ramjet (Transformers)|Ramjet]], and [[Dirge (Transformers)|Dirge]] are part of a team dubbed by Transformers fans as the &quot;Coneheads&quot; for the way their animation models were drawn to make them visually distinct from the original Decepticon jets [[Starscream (Transformers)|Starscream]], [[Skywarp]], and [[Thundercracker]] despite their toys being modifications of the same mold used to create that original trio. 

Thrust's personality is that of a braggart who tries to psyche out his opponents with the roar of his engines, but is in fact a coward when it comes to actual battle. 

Thrust was named the 24th top unfortunately named Transformer by [[Topless Robot]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.toplessrobot.com/2009/12/the_30_most_unfortunately_named_transformers.php |title=The 30 Most Unfortunately Named Transformers |author=Kevin Guhl| date=December 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Marvel Comics===
Thrust first appeared in issue 17 of the U.S. Marvel Transformers comic, acting as a bodyguard for [[Straxus]]. 

''He played a larger role in the Marvel UK storyline ''Target: 2006'', where he was portrayed as one of the Decepticons' deadliest killers, and one that needed to be taken out by the Autobot commando group the [[Wreckers (Transformers)|Wreckers]] to signal a mass-Autobot uprising on [[Cybertron]]. The Decepticons had prepared a major offensive to wipe the Autobots out and capture [[Emirate Xaaron]], unaware this was part of the Autobot trap. Megatron's summoning the [[Insecticons]] to Earth scrapped both sides’ plans.''

He subsequently joined the Decepticons on Earth. He was seen entering Earth via the Spacebridge, alongside Ramjet and Dirge around the same time as the [[Aerialbots]] were being created. Despite acquitting themselves well against the inexperienced [[Autobot]]s they were eventually forced to flee when the Aerialbots formed [[Superion]]. 

''A story called ''The Gift'' in issue 93 of the Marvel UK comics explored [[Jetfire]]'s problems fitting in with the other Autobots. Jetfire accompanied [[Jazz (Transformers)|Jazz]] to a [[G. B. Blackrock|Blackrock]] fuel plant to oversee the creation of more fuel for the Autobots. The plant was attacked by Decepticons Thrust and [[Bombshell (Transformers)|Bombshell]]. Although Jetfire was able to put out a fire at the plant before it exploded, he blamed himself for being slow to react. ''

Thrust would serve as part of the Earthbound forces under first [[Shockwave (Transformers)|Shockwave]], then [[Ratbat]], battling both the Autobots and [[Scorponok]]'s Decepticon faction. When [[Starscream (Transformers)|Starscream]] seized the power of the [[Underbase]], Dirge, Thrust and Ramjet were part of the forces sent against him. 

''Although they were not shown to be deactivated by the villain, they were not seen again in the comic continuity, although they would be seen in the UK. Earthforce tales under the command of Megatron and Shockwave. In the alternate Movie themed future of the UK comics, Thrust was indicated to have taken command of the Seekers.''

It is unclear if Thrust was revived with many of the other Decepticons deactivated by Starscream's power, but as Dirge and Ramjet were both shown to be alive and well, it is likely.

===Animated series===
In the cartoon, Thrust first appeared in the second season episode &quot;Dinobot Island&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.anime.com/Transformers/ Transformers Season Two Box Set, Part 1 by Brian Cirulnick, February 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

In the episode &quot;The God Gambit&quot; [[Cosmos (Transformers)|Cosmos]] collected data in space on a potential new power source, but was attacked by [[Astrotrain]], Thrust and [[Starscream (Transformers)|Starscream]]. Crashing on the moon [[Titan (moon)|Titan]], the local priests worshiped the Decepticons as &quot;Sky Gods&quot;, but rebels were able to reactivate Cosmos and call for aid from the Autobots. [[Optimus Prime]] sent [[Omega Supreme]] with [[Perceptor]] and [[Jazz (Transformers)|Jazz]]. Astrotrain set himself up as the chief god of the moon and forced the natives to gather energy crystals. The trip to Titan drained Omega of most of his energy, but Perceptor and Jazz were able to gather enough crystals to reactivate Omega and defeat the three Decepticons. Vowing to not let the Autobots gain the crystals, Astrotrain set up a chain reaction destroying them. The Autobots aided the natives to escape the explosion and helped them settle in another area of the moon.

In &quot;The Golden Lagoon&quot; Thrust is the one that discovers the lagoon after Beachcomber left. He was also one of the nine Transformers to be transported to the giant alien world in &quot;Child's Play&quot;. He attempted to warn the Insecticons about the Morphabots in &quot;Quest For Survival,&quot; but was simply fired upon. In &quot;Kremzeek!&quot; he was responsible for dropping Kremzeek in the Autobot base.

Thrust also appeared in the '''[[The Transformers: The Movie]]'''. Among other roles he had in the movie, Thrust is most recognized as the first Decepticon run over by [[Optimus Prime]] as the Autobot Leader made his way towards Megatron.

In his last U.S. appearance, &quot;Ghost in the Machine&quot;, Thrust and Dirge are among other Decepticons being punished by Galvatron for failing to stop a demoralizing assault by Starscream—now a ghost possessing the bodies of other Decepticons. Just before he and the other offenders are to be hunted down, [[Trypticon]], the Decepticon city is possessed, trapping Thrust, [[Dirge (Transformers)|Dirge]], [[Runamuck (Transformers)|Runamuck]] and [[Runabout (Transformers)|Runabout]] inside. He and Dirge liberates Trypticon from Starscream's control, just before the traitorous ghost was about to aid [[Unicron]] in destroying Cybertron.

Thrust appeared in episode #1 and #15 of the Japanese exclusive ''Headmasters'' series.

===Dreamwave Productions===
[[Image:Thrust-dreamwave.jpg|left|thumb|Thrust in Dreamwave comics.]]
Thrust was recruited as a Decepticon under the leadership of [[Megatron (Transformers)|Megatron]] in his war against the Autobots on the planet Cybertron. Thrust became a member of the elite [[Seekers (Transformers)|Seekers]] under Aerospace Commander [[Starscream (Transformers)|Starscream]]. He often worked with fellow Seekers [[Ramjet (Transformers)|Ramjet]] and [[Dirge (Transformers)|Dirge]].  He appeared defending Cybertron's planetary engines from [[Grimlock]]'s group, but was later seen slumped against the wall. Staying with the Decepticons during the chaos following Megatron's disappearance, Thrust was one of those who defeated the [[Chaos Trinity]]. 

In the third ''War Within'' series Thrust appeared among the Decepticon troops under the command of [[Shockwave (Transformers)|Shockwave]].

After the [[Great Shutdown]] ended, Thrust was reformatted by Shockwave into the form of an Earth-style jet, serving as one of his bodyguards. After the War between the Autobots and Decepticons ended on Cybertron, [[Ultra Magnus]] led a mission to Earth to arrest the Autobots on Earth for continuing their violent ways. Thrust was among the troops under Ultra Magnus. 

Defeated by the Autobots on Cybertron, [[Shockwave (Transformers)|Shockwave]] was forced to set up a new secret headquarters in the wastelands of Cybertron, with [[Astrotrain]], [[Blitzwing]], Dirge, Ramjet and Thrust following him. Shockwave completed work on his new warrior, [[Sixshot]]. Megatron returned to Cybertron with three clone warriors and the [[Predacons]] and was able to defeat Shockwave. Shockwave was kept alive, but restrained. All Shockwave's warriors except Blitzwing, who was destroyed, joined up with Megatron in his plan to invade the Earth.

===Devil's Due Publishing===
Thrust would appear again in the second G.I. Joe vs. the Transformers  crossover from [[Devil's Due Publishing]] with Dirge, Ramjet, [[Scourge (Transformers)|Scourge]] and [[Cyclonus]], acting as bodyguards for Shockwave. When the [[Dinobots]] returned  from different a time period they routed Shockwave's troops. Ramjet was presumably killed either during this event, or when [[Cobra Commander]] detonated a store of explosives inside [[Starscream (Transformers)|Starscream]], killing everyone present. In this story, Thrust had not received an Earthen mode and transformed into a Cybertronian jet.

Despite this Thrust (or at least a cone-headed jet Decepticon with a similar color scheme) would be seen amongst the Decepticon troops trying to hold back the Autobot/G.I. Joe force attempting to rescue [[Optimus Prime]]. Here, like most other Transformers featured, he was in his Earthen form.

===Fun Publications===
In Transformers: Timelines volume 2 #2, &quot;Games of Deception&quot; (set in the Marvel universe but not following the continuity of either ''Generation 2'' or the later Marvel UK tales) Thrust appeared under the command of [[Bugbite]]. Coming to Earth with him, Thrust  served him loyally, hitting [[Ramjet (Transformers)|Ramjet]] with a cerebro shell. However, in the final three-way battle between Bugbite's group, Megatron's forces and [[Ultra Magnus]]' Autobots, Thrust was gunned down by Magnus.

Thrust appears in ''[[At Fight's End]]''.

===IDW Publishing===
Thrust appears among the Cybertronians fighting along side Megatron in ''Megatron Origin'' #3, where he is seen fighting Ironhide. 

Thurst appears in ''[[The Transformers: Stormbringer]]'' as part of the Decepticon infiltration cell on Nebulos when [[Thunderwing]] arrived. Thrust was ordered to stay in their base in order to be able to have a recording of the events in case things went wrong. Despite the Decepticons' best efforts the monster devastated much of the planet and Thrust fled along with [[Dreadwing|Dreadwind and Darkwing]].

In ''All Hail Megatron'' #16 Thrust was among the Decepticons discovered wounded and hiding in abandoned buildings in New York by the U.S. military.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.comicscontinuum.com/stories/0910/12/idwfirsts.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toys===
*'''''Generation 1'' Thrust''' (1985)
:A remold of the toy used for Starscream and the other first year Seekers. In jet mode, the toy is 21cm long (a scale of 1:93, suggesting that Thrust's 14cm robot mode would be about 13m tall). In what is considered to be a major drawback to the toy, the majority of its parts have to be removed for transformation, and it is rare to find a totally complete one, since neither mode can hold all the parts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicron.us/tf1985/figures/thrust.htm Decepticon Jet: Thrust&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.toybin.org/search.php?q=1985+Decepticon+Thrust Transformers Thrust Robot - ToyBin&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''''Smallest Transformers'' Thrust''' (2004)
:A tiny remake of the original Thrust character, available exclusively as a blind-packaged item in Japan. This toy is a remold of Smallest Transformers Starscream. Knockoffs of this toy have been sold out of China in transparent plastic and metalized finish.

*'''''Timelines'' Deluxe Thrust''' (2007)
:A [[BotCon]] 2007 exclusive Thrust figure was announced and released at the end of June 2007 along with four other figures (including two additional seekers). The Thrust figure is a remold of Classics Ramjet (which is itself a remold of ''Classics'' Starscream; it has Ramjet's head and missiles, Starscream's body as well as newly molded wings and tail fins). The release of this figure as a high-priced, limited run convention exclusive instead of a brick-and-mortar retail release has caused a divide among fans as half the Classics Seekers are rendered unattainable for those who could not pre-order them, attend the convention or afford the set second-hand. Hasbro and Fun Publications (owners of the remolded parts) have reiterated that the set will not be made available in any other form as it would diminish the value for those that purchased it at BotCon.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seibertron.com/database/character.php?view=hasbro&amp;char_id=3687 Thrust (Decepticon Deluxe Vehicles, Convention &amp; Club Exclusives)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Loose Thrust figures sell for over $170 in online auctions.

*'''''Universe'' Classic Series Legends Thrust''' (2008)
:Thrust is part of the Aerial Rivals Legends set. He is a redeco of ''Cybertron'' Legends Starscream in Thrust's ''Generation 1'' colors.

*'''''Gentei! Gentei!'' Deluxe Thrust''' (2009)
:The Japanese version of the ''Timelines'' Deluxe figure by [[Takara Tomy]] has new wings, including spinning fan blades. Sold as a Ganbo Store exclusive.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tfw2005.com/resources/henkei-destrons-347/thrust-2503/ TFW2005.com - Gentei Thrust]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''''Universe'' Titanium Series 6&amp;nbsp;inch Thrust''' (2009)
:A redeco of the 6 inch Titanium ''War Within'' Thundercracker. A Target store exclusive. Pictures of this toy first appeared on the internet in March of 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.actoys.net/bbs/read.php?tid-342193.html ACToys.net]&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''''Generations'' Deluxe Thrust''' (2010)
:An international release of the 2009 ''Gentei'' Deluxe figure.&lt;ref&gt;http://mastercollector.com/articles/reviews/thrust-review.html&lt;/ref&gt;

{{-}}

==Beast Wars II==
{{Transformers character|
 name           = Thrust
|image          = tsthrust2.jpg
|caption        = The Predacon Thrust
|affiliation    = Predacon
|subgroup       = Basic Vehicles, Deluxe Beasts
|rank           =3 (as Thrust), 4 (as Thrustor)
|function       = Aerial Officer (As Thrust), Shock Troop Commander (as Thrustor)
|partner        =
|motto          = ''&quot;Whoah, everybody looks like ants from way up here! Wait, I haven’t taken off yet. Then . . . what the heck are those things? . . . Oh, ants. Right.&quot;''
|alternatemodes = [[F-22 Raptor]], Cybernetic Velociraptor
|series         = ''[[Beast Wars Second]]''
|japanvoice        = [[Junji Sanechika]]
}}

A second character named Thrust was introduced in the Japanese exclusive series ''Beast Wars II''. 

In the Japanese exclusive ''Beast Wars II'' series, Thrust is a Predacon who transformers into a yellow jet, and is a soldier in the forces of a transformer calling himself [[Galvatron#Beast Wars Second|Galvatron]].  

Like his best friend Dirge, Thrust has the attitude of a [[manzai]] comedian. He never calms down and hates acting serious. He’d much rather have fun and take things in stride. Thrust has a shrewd personality, though, and along with Dirge he forms a well-known duo among the Predacons. Unfortunately, the duo isn’t known for exactly what they’d like to be. For the most part they are thought of as bunglers. Thrust hates sea breezes since they tend to cause him to rust and for that reason alone he strangely has a great hatred of the Maximal Scuba.

Thrust and Dirge share a great deal in common. Thrust transforms into a stealthy fighter jet just like his partner. He also carries his weapon of choice, the Thrust Gun, in his leg compartment and can attach a barrel to it for increased power.

Thrusts inability to focus on anything for a length of time reduces him and his partner to the more menial tasks while complex assignments are left to more appropriate Predacons.

===Animated series===
Later, he is upgraded by [[Gigastorm]] using the power of the [[Angolmois energy]], thereby transforming him into '''Thrustor''', a cybernetic [[velociraptor]].

===Manga===
In &quot;[[The Maximal Brainwashing Project]]&quot; [[Starscream (other incarnations)|Starscream]] and [[BB (Transformers)|BB]] were able to capture [[Diver (Transformers)|Diver]] and the [[Tasmanian Kid]], brainwashing them into serving the [[Predacons]]. Meanwhile [[Leo Prime]], [[Apache (Transformers)|Apache]] and [[Scuba (Transformers)|Scuba]] were able to capture [[Dirge (Transformers)|Dirge]] and Thrust. The shock of being damaged in capture had the side effect of making the Predacons think they were [[Maximals]]. Diver and the Kid were able to ambush the Maximals, allowing [[Galvatron]] to gain the upper hand on Lio Convoy, but the Maximals were aided by Dirge and Thrust. Furious that Lio had seemingly stolen his brainwashing idea Starscream had BB attacked the Maximals. [[Megastorm]] found the whole turn of events amusing and planned to use his main cannon to destroy all the Maximals and Predacons in the conflict, becoming the leader of the Predacons. His attack took so long to charge Diver was able to ruin it with a water geyser. The explosion was enough to shock the brainwashed Maximals back to their senses. Galvatron and the Predacons retreated with Dirge and Thrust in tow.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tfarchive.com/comics/japanese/bw2playingbook.php&lt;/ref&gt;

===IDW Publishing===
In ''Beast Wars: The Ascending'' Shokaract's heralds [[Starscream (Transformers)|Hellscream]], [[Max-B]], [[Antagony]], [[Thrustor]] and [[Hardhead (Transformers)|Hardhead]] defended their master on Cybertron until he was shunted into limbo by the Maximal Snarl. The heralds then retreated once there was no vessel for Unicron.

Thrust had a biography printed in the ''Beast Wars Sourcebook'' by [[IDW Publishing]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.monstersandcritics.com/books/comics/news/article_1343405.php/Creators_of_Transformers_Beast_Wars_The_Gathering_are_back&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toys===
*'''Beast Wars Second Thrust''' (1998)
:He is a redeco of the mold used for ''[[Machine Wars]]'' [[Megatron (Transformers)|Megatron]] and [[Megaplex]]. The toy for Thrust stands 10 centimeters tall and the character is supposed to stand 2.6 meters tall, which means he's about 1:26 scale. He came packaged by himself and with the Maximal [[Beast Wars II#Maximals|Scuba]].

*'''Beast Wars Second Thrustor''' (1998)
:A remold of Beast Wars Dinobot.
{{-}}

==Beast Machines==
{{Transformers character|
 name           = Thrust
|image          =
|caption        = The Vehicon Thrust
|affiliation    = Vehicon
|subgroup       = Deluxe Vehicles
|function       = Cycle-Drone General
|partner        = [[Jetstorm (Beast Machines)|Jetstorm]] and [[Tankor]], later [[Obsidian (Transformers)|Obsidian]] and [[Strika]]
|motto          = ''&quot;There are no rules on the road - only victors and scrap metal.&quot;''
|alternatemodes = Cybertronian Motorcycle
|series         = ''[[Beast Machines]]''
|voiceby        = [[Jim Byrnes (actor)|Jim Byrnes]]
}}

He is a Vehicon General who was in charge of the Cycle Drones and was one of the few who remained an ally to [[Megatron (Beast Era)|Megatron]] until the very end. He carried the spark of the [[Predacon]] [[Waspinator]].

===Animated series===
Thrust was one of the original three [[Vehicon|Vehicon Generals]], and he was the last one to fall against the Maximals in the series finale.  He is the loner, mysterious and brooding, and prefers to operate on his own agenda. Thrust rarely speaks, and when he does, it usually doesn't excel above a raspy whisper. To the surprise of all, Thrust was actually the reprogrammed [[Waspinator]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicron.us/tf2000/toypics/thrust.htm Deluxe Beast Machines: Thrust&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Thrust almost never loses his cool, and is almost fearless. He'll even let his boss, Megatron, know when he disagrees with him, something which the cowardly Waspinator would never have done. Thrust even once told his leader that using the [[Spark (Transformers)|sparks]] of [[Rhinox]] and [[Silverbolt (Beast Wars and Beast Machines)|Silverbolt]] for [[Jetstorm (Beast Machines)|Jetstorm]] and [[Tankor]] had been a bad idea as they had once been “pals” of Optimus.

Each of the three original Vehicon Generals had their own personalized command codes; Thrust's was: ''&quot;Thrust Overdrive!!&quot;'' (though on one occasion he said: ''&quot;Thrust Accelerate!&quot;'')

Despite his preference for solitude, he considered his fellow Vehicon General [[Jetstorm (Beast Machines)|Jetstorm]] to be his best friend, disregarding some of their past rivalries.  As for [[Tankor]], ''&quot;He's a nice guy... little dim&quot;''. He despised the next generals, [[Obsidian (Transformers)|Obsidian]] and [[Strika]] simply because they replaced the original cast and because they treated him like an outsider, despite the fact that he had been there the longest. Not until Megatron had been thought dead and Obsidian and Strika had joined forces with the Maximals despite Thrust’s assurances that Megatron would return, did the new generals respect Thrust, for he had been loyal when they had not. While he was still not considered an equal, they from then on let him in on their plans.

Unlike all the other Generals, Thrust would remain loyal to Megatron to the bitter end. His friendship with Jetstorm would eventually turn into hatred when Jetstorm reverted back to [[Silverbolt (Beast Wars and Beast Machines)|Silverbolt]], his old Maximal self.

Thrust was the only one of the original three Vehicon Generals who was able to remember on his own that he used to be someone else. For a while, [[Blackarachnia]] believed that this someone else was Silverbolt, since Thrust kept displaying a soft spot for her. She was disappointed to learn that Thrust wasn't Silverbolt, but the [[Predacon (Transformers)|Predacon]] [[Waspinator]]. Waspinator had been left on prehistoric Earth, to be worshiped by the early humans, but Waspinator accidentally boringly flung a pebble at a human who was building a statue to worship his &quot;godlike&quot; performance, and chased him off. Somehow he returned to Cybertron where his spark was extracted by Megatron and reprogrammed into Thrust. Waspinator was actually very pleased to be inside the ''&quot;cool biker-bot&quot;'' because ''&quot;Chick-bots dig 'brooding loner' bit! &quot;''

In the final episodes, his Cycle-Drones extracted the sparks of all the Maximals except [[Optimus Primal]]. After using Silverbolt's hatred of being called Jetstorm to trick him into having a tower dropped on him, Thrust was caught in a fierce battle with [[Cheetor]], which was ended when Cheetor extracted Waspinator's spark from Thrust. When all of Cybertron had been reformatted, Thrust became Waspinator again - with a twist. He was now a tiny wasp with the Vehicon General's head.

===3H Enterprises===
''Beast Machines'' Thrust appeared in the ''Transformers: Universe'' comic book among those escaping Unicron.

===Fun Publications===
Thrust was a minor background character appearing in [[Fun Publications]] fiction &quot;Gone to Far&quot;, a text-based story set on [[Transtech]] [[Cybertron]].

===Toys===
*'''Beast Machines Thrust'''
:A Deluxe sized toy was released for Thrust by Hasbro. His Cycle-Drones were made into Basic sized figures utilizing brand new molds. Oddly enough the Cycle-Drone toys looked more like Thrust in the television series than the Thrust toy did.

*'''Happy Meal Thrust'''
:A smaller version of Thrust was also made as a toy which was included in children's fast food meals.

*'''Beast Wars Returns Thrust'''
:A redeco of the Motorcycle Drone toy that was only released in Japan, as part of their 2005 ''Beast Machines'' (called ''Beast Wars Returns'' there) line.   This version is far more show-accurate than the original, owing to its more recent mold and the fact that the show had been around for a longer time when it was released.

==Transformers: Armada==
{{Transformers character|
 name           =Thrust
|japanname      =Strato
|image =Thrust4.jpg  
|caption        =
|affiliation    =Decepticon
|subgroup       =Deluxe Vehicles
|rank           =9
|function       =Troop Instructor
|partner        =[[Inferno (Armada)|Inferno]]
|motto          =''&quot;I fight, I prevail, I conquer! &quot;'' (Hasbro), &quot;''Arrogance and ambition are shortcuts to victory.''&quot; (Takara)
|alternatemodes =Modified [[F-35 Joint Strike Fighter]]
|series         =''[[Transformers: Armada]]''
|engvoice        =[[Colin Murdock (actor)|Colin Murdock]]
|japanvoice        =[[Kōji Yusa]]
}}
In the ''Transformers: Armada'' cartoon series, Thrust is a noted Decepticon strategist called to Earth by [[Megatron (Unicron Trilogy)|Megatron]]. He becomes second in command of the Decepticons under Megatron replacing Starscream who had served that role prior to leaving the Decepticons.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.unicron.us/tf2003/toypix/thrust.htm Thrust with Inferno&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Note: According to the Japanese tech spec and animated series Thrust can become invisible, but in the Dreamwave comics, they attribute his ability to turn invisible to his Mini-Con partner Inferno.

===Animated series===
Stealthily stalking the skies in his jet mode, Thrust is aided by his optical camouflage powers that render him invisible.  He personally selected the [[Mini-Con]] [[Inferno (Transformers)|Inferno]] to be his partner when he arrived on [[Earth]] from [[Cybertron]]. In addition, he worked in conjunction with the Air Military Team ([[Terradive]], [[Thunderwing]], Gunbarrel) on several occasions.

Heralded as a master tactician and general, Thrust won numerous victories for the Decepticons on the planets Duke and Vector. The schemes he crafted for the Decepticons certainly seemed to confirm that fact, but they came crashing down when he failed to factor in the arrival of [[Jetfire]] on Earth, and later, his ability to combine with [[Optimus Prime (Unicron Trilogy)|Optimus Prime]]. 

Following these, and other disastrous encounters with the Autobots, Thrust was approached by [[Sideways (Transformers)|Sideways]] and given promises of great power and respect, Thrust began to work against Megatron. At the same time, he arranged a scheme to manipulate [[Starscream (Unicron Trilogy)|Starscream]] and eventually allow the Decepticons to gain possession of all three Mini-Con weapons, which Thrust then used to power the mighty [[Hydra-Cannon]]. Back on Cybertron, however, Thrust's treachery was revealed when he absconded with the [[Skyboom Shield]] and [[Requiem Blaster]], and delivered them to Sideways, who planned to use them to revive his master, [[Unicron]]. Following Sideways' theft of the [[Star Saber]], Unicron was fully reborn and attacked Cybertron, with Thrust perched on his shoulder cheering over the destruction of the Transformers race. When confronted by Galvatron (formerly Megatron) on Unicron's surface for his treason, Thrust is more to willing to face Galvatron, as he finds no longer to flee from him as so much damage to Cybertron by Unicron has been done. He eventually flew into a portion of Unicron's body by accident and became lodged in a shifting joint, and found that his cries for help elicited no response from the Chaos-Bringer or his former leader. Galvatron warned him that this was the fate of those who dared to dream of both power and treason, and walked away as Thrust was crushed to his death.

===Dreamwave Productions===
Thrust had a much lesser role in the accompanying [[Dreamwave Productions|Dreamwave]] comics. He first appeared in issue #9, arriving from Cybertron to equip the Decepticons with rocket boosters, providing them with some much needed mobility. He then took part in the Decepticon assault on the Mini-Con base on the moon, and also battled [[Hot Shot (Transformers)|Hot Shot]] and Red Alert alongside [[Starscream (Unicron Trilogy)|Starscream]] in order to discover the location of the Autobot base. He then became part of [[Megatron (Unicron Trilogy)|Megatron]]'s forces on Earth, hunting the Mini-Con adventure team, accidentally being taken out by a super-powered [[Cyclonus]] and accompanying Starscream and Demolishor in search of Over-Run and the Mini-Con Matrix, battling Hot Shot again. However, they ran into trouble in the most unexpected of forms - the original [[Galvatron]], who took out Thrust. Left for dead by the other two, Thrust managed to make his way to the Decepticon base on Earth. His luck didn't improve: he was confronted by Galvatron's fellow [[Heralds of Unicron]] - the original versions of [[Scourge (Transformers)|Scourge]], [[Thunderwing]] and [[Dirge (Transformers)|Dirge]] - and subsequently beaten to a pulp. He did not appear again in the ''Armada'' comics.

Although the character of Thrust did not appear in the ''Energon'' animated series he continued to appear in the ''Transformers: Energon'' comic series by [[Dreamwave Productions|Dreamwave]], allying himself with the Autobots after the disappearance of Megatron. He was one of those who aided the Autobots when Cybertron was attacked by the Four Horsemen of Unicron: [[Airazor]], [[Cheetor]], [[Rhinox]] and [[Terrorsaur]]. Subsequently, he was one of those who volunteered to head to Earth to battle the Terrorcon invasion. He was one of the defenders of [[Toronto]] alongside Hot Shot, Red Alert, [[Hoist (Transformers)|Hoist]], [[Beachcomber (Transformers)|Beachcomber]] and [[Rodimus Prime|Rodimus]], battling against [[Divebomb]] and a swarm of [[Terrorcon]] clones before receiving help from a very unlikely source: Megatron, resurrected in a new body by [[Optimus Prime (Unicron Trilogy)|Optimus Prime]]. Megatron decimated the Terrorcon invasion, and Thrust attempted to ingratiate himself with his bemused former leader. 

Thrust would make one more appearance in flashback in ''Transformers: Energon'' #30 as one of the Decepticons piloting Megatron’s battle barge as Starscream delivered a warning of Scorponok's ambitions. Unfortunately Dreamwave went out of business at this point, so any further development of Thrust remains untold.

===Toys===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:thrust-armada.jpg|right|thumb|Armada Thrust|{{deletable image-caption|1=Sunday, 26 August 2007}}]] --&gt;
*'''''Armada'' Deluxe Thrust with Inferno''' (2003)
:Came with the Mini-Con Inferno. An actual F-35 fighter is 15.47 meters long, while the Thrust toy is 16 centimeters long, making it a scale of about 1/97 scale.
:The ''Universe'' character of [[Sunstorm (Transformers)|Sunstorm]] was a [[redeco]] of ''Armada'' Thrust, painted to resemble Sunstorm from the Generation 1 series. He came with a redeco of Inferno.

*'''''Armada'' Deluxe Powerlinx Thrust with Inferno''' (2003)
:A redeco of Armada Thrust in the colors of Generation 1 Dirge.

*'''''Superlink'' Toy Dream Project Thrust''' (2003)
:A Japanese exclusive redeco of ''Armada'' Thrust in ''Generation 1'' Thrust colors.  This figure was also available in Hasbro packaging in numerous regions, including Israel and Europe, but never released in the U.S. as intended.

==Transformers: Cybertron==
{{Transformers character|
 name           =Thrust
|japanname      =
|image          =thrust-cybertron.jpg
|caption        =Cybertron Thrust
|affiliation    =Decepticon
|subgroup       =Mini-Cons
|rank           =5
|function       =
|partner        =
|motto          =
|alternatemodes =Jet
|series         =''[[Transformers: Cybertron]]'
|voiceby        =
}}
Another Thrust appeared in the ''Transformers: Cybertron'' line as a Mini-Con.

Thrust was presented as a revolutionary who enjoyed defying the pointless laws of the Mini-Con Council. Thriving on chaos, he took advantage of the black hole created by the [[Unicron]] singularity, sabotaging the Mini-Cons' ships and leaving them trapped on Cybertron as the black hole expands, then leading a rebellion.

===Fun Publications===
Thrust pays the price for his ways in the club comic. When Unicron attacks Cybertron in the midst of the Mini-Con civil war, Thrust is amongst those killed by the chaos bringer.

===Toys===
*'''''Cybertron'' Mini-Con Thrust'''
:Thrust is a redeco of ''Energon'' [[Scattor]]. He was packaged with the Autobot-aligned [[Anti-Blaze]].
{{-}}

==Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen==
{{Transformers character|
 name           =Thrust
|image          =F-35 at Edwards (Cropped).jpg
|caption        =The F-35 Lightning jet
|affiliation    =Decepticon
|subgroup       =Deluxe Vehicles
|rank           =6
|function       =
|partner        =
|motto          =
|alternatemodes =[[F-35 Lightning II]]
|series         =''[[Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen]]''
|engvoice       =
|japanvoice     =
}}
Thrust is a cowardly Decepticon jet. He prefers fighting humans to Autobots, but will fly away in terror if they attack with heavy artillery.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.tfw2005.com/resources/rotf-decepticons-384/thrust-3747/&lt;/ref&gt;

===Toys===
*'''''Revenge of the Fallen'' Deluxe Thrust''' (2009)
:Thrust appears in the Revenge of The Fallen toyline, as a redeco/remold of Deluxe class [[Breakaway (Transformers)#Transformers: Revenge of the Fallen|Breakaway]]. The figure includes a new head mold.
:Thrust is a 1:87 scale F-35 Lightning II fighter jet. As a robot this 16 centimeter toy would stand about 45 feet 8 inches tall.
{{-}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{Cite book | title=Transformers: The Ultimate Guide | last=Furman | first=Simon | year=2004 | publisher=DK Publishing Inc.| ISBN=1405304618 | page= 120}}

[[Category:Fictional Kansai characters]]
[[Category:Decepticons]]
[[Category:Mini-Cons]]
[[Category:Predacons]]
[[Category:Vehicons]]
[[Category:Unicron-related characters]]
[[Category:Fictional characters who can turn invisible]]
[[Category:Fictional henchmen]]
[[Category:Fictional generals]]
[[Category:Seekers (Transformers)]]

[[id:Thrust]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
