<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28594927" ns="0" title="Lewisham West MLR station"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Waratah Mills MLR station.jpg|thumb|Future site of the Lewisham West MLR station]]
[[File:Lewisham West MLR station, Sydney.jpg|thumb|upright|Part of the track work from Old Canterbury Road, Lewisham]]
'''Lewisham West MLR station''' is a planned light rail stop located on the border of the suburbs of [[Lewisham, New South Wales|Lewisham]] and [[Summer Hill, New South Wales|Summer Hill]] on the [[Metro Light Rail]] line in [[Sydney]], [[New South Wales]], [[Australia]]. The stop will also be an interchange with [[Lewisham railway station, Sydney|Lewisham railway station]] on the Inner West line.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ecotransit.org.au/ets/book/export/html/155&lt;/ref&gt; The stop is planned for completion in 2012. The extension will make use of the former Rozelle branch of the [[Metropolitan Goods railway line]] heavy rail freight corridor and operate from the current light rail terminus at [[Lilyfield MLR station|Lilyfield]] to [[Dulwich Hill Interchange MLR station|Dulwich Hill]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.transport.nsw.gov.au/rail/lightrail-extension.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.transport.nsw.gov.au/sites/default/file/rail/SLRE-Community-Update-July-August-2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

The new service will provide a direct service to the city though the Inner West line will be quicker. The main utility of the interchange will be providing improved access to Dulwich Hill (including Dulwich Hill railway station on the Bankstown line), Leichhardt, Haberfield, Lilyfield, Annandale, Glebe, Pyrmont and Darling Harbour. 

The light rail will also connect with another proposed route that will travel along Sussex Street, Hickson Road, [[Circular Quay]] and [[George Street, Sydney|George Street]], forming a complete city loop service. A feasibility study is currently being drafted for this route &lt;ref&gt;http://www.clovermoore.com/main/?id=3292&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ecotransit.org.au/ets/book/export/html/155&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://inner-west-courier.whereilive.com.au/news/story/tram-stops-here/&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Location==
The stop will be located in what is currently an industrial area. The area on the eastern side of the stop features various light industrial buildings, whilst the area on the western side of the stop is dominated by the former Mungo Scott flour mill. Both areas are currently the subject of redevelopment proposals to build medium density housing.  The stop will be positioned adjacent to the former flour mill and will predominately cater for the suburb's new residents - somewhat at the expense of interchanging passengers. 

The project's Product Definition Report describes the positioning of the stop:

:&quot;The site provides the most practical balance between meeting the interchange opportunity with Lewisham Station and the opportunities of the catchment and its two known developments.

:Patronage at this location is currently predicted to come approximately equally from walk-up catchment and from interchange. Future redevelopment will see this balance tip significantly in favour of catchment with the stop potentially becoming a focus of the local area.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Sydney Light Rail Extension – Stage 1, Inner West Extension - Product Definition Report - pp.19 - Transport NSW&lt;/ref&gt;

The stop is estimated to be used by 275 boarding passengers per weekday by 2016 with 115 of those arriving by train.&lt;ref&gt;[http://majorprojects.planning.nsw.gov.au/files/61649/08_Environmental%20Assessment%20-%20Volume%201%20-%20Part%20C1%20-%20Chapter%2010.pdf Environmental Assessment - Volume 1 - Part C1 - Chapter 10.] Table 10.1 p 201. Transport NSW.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Transport links==
There are two interchange connections available a short walk from Lewisham West MLR station:

[[CityRail]] runs one route via Lewisham railway station:
*[[Inner West line]] - between [[Liverpool, New South Wales|Liverpool]] and the [[City Circle]]

[[Sydney Buses]] runs one route via Old Canterbury Road:
*Route 413 - between [[Campsie railway station|Campsie station]] and the City

==Neighbouring Stops==
&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; cellpadding=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;'''Preceding Stop&lt;br&gt;(inbound)'''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;'''MetroTransport &lt;br&gt;Line'''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt; '''Following Stop&lt;br&gt;(outbound)'''&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr bgcolor = &quot;EFEEEF&quot;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;font color = &quot;black&quot;&gt;[[Taverners Hill MLR station|Taverners Hill]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;[[Metro Light Rail|'''&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;Light Rail&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;font color =&quot;black&quot;&gt;[[Waratah Mills MLR station|Waratah Mills]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{MetroTransport lines stations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lewisham West MLR station}}
[[Category:Metro Light Rail stations]]

{{coord|-33.893431|151.143551|format=dms|type:railwaystation_region:AU-NSW|display=title}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
