<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="286083" ns="0" title="San Diego State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish2|the [[University of San Diego]]}}
{{Infobox university
 |name              = San Diego State University
 |native_name       = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |image             = [[File:San Diego State University seal.svg|175px|]]
 |image_name        = 
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |motto             = Minds that move the world 
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = 1897 
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Public university|Public]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Space grant colleges|Space Grant]]
 |affiliation       = 
 |endowment         = $109.4 million (2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Recession hits colleges' endowments  | work =  | publisher = NACUBO  | date =   | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf  | doi =   | accessdate = February 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |chancellor        = 
 |president         = Elliot Hirshman
 |vice-president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = Nancy Marlin
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 
 |staff             = 1,684
 |students          = 33,790&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://collegesearch.collegeboard.com/search/CollegeDetail.jsp?match=true&amp;collegeId=951&amp;searchType=college&amp;type=qfs&amp;word=San%20Diego%20State%20University|title=San Diego State University|publisher=collegeboard.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |undergrad         = 27,537
 |postgrad          = 6,253 
 |doctoral          = 
 |other             = 
 |city              = [[San Diego]]
 |state             = [[California]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = 
 |coor              = {{Coord|32|46|31|N|117|04|20|W|region:US-CA_type:edu_source:GNIS|display=title|notes=&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite gnis|248828|San Diego State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]
 |former_names      = San Diego Normal School (1897–1923)&lt;br&gt;San Diego Teachers College (1923–35)&lt;br&gt;San Diego State College (1935–70)
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = [[Black (color)|black]], [[scarlet (color)|scarlet (red)]], and [[gold]] {{color box|black}}{{color box|#A81933}}{{color box|#D2C694}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = [[San Diego State Aztecs|Aztecs]]
 |mascot            = [[Eagle warrior|Aztec warrior]] 
 |athletics         = 17 varsity teams 
 |affiliations      = [[California State University]] system&lt;br&gt;[[Mountain West Conference]] ([[NCAA Division 1]])
 |website           = [http://www.sdsu.edu www.sdsu.edu]
 |logo              = 
 |footnotes         = &lt;center&gt;[[Image:San Diego State Seal.svg|175px]]&lt;center/&gt;
}}

'''San Diego State University''' ('''SDSU'''), founded in 1897 as San Diego Normal School, is the largest and oldest higher education facility in the greater San Diego area (generally the [[San Diego|City]] and [[San Diego County, California|County]] of San Diego), and is part of the [[California State University]] system. It is the third-oldest university in the California State University system, and one of the oldest universities in California. SDSU has a student body of approximately 29,256 (as of the beginning of the Fall 2009 academic year) and an alumni base of more than 200,000. San Diego State University received nearly 60,000 undergraduate applications for the 2011 Fall semester.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.thedailyaztec.com/2011/04/with-low-acceptance-rates-sdsu-enters-new-chapter&lt;/ref&gt; The school accepted 14,480 high school seniors and 2,748 transfers with an acceptance rate of 28.7% for the 2011 academic year.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.cbs8.com/story/14258884/sdsu-announces-13k-applicants-accepted-for-fall-semester?clienttype=printable&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|Carnegie Foundation]] has designated San Diego State University a &quot;Research University with high research activity.&quot; SDSU is the only California State University campus with this classification, which places it among the top 200 higher education institutions in the country conducting research.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=13612&amp;start=782 Carnegie Foundation: San Diego State University]&lt;/ref&gt;  Notably, pursuant to the [[Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index|''Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index'' (FSP Index)]] released by the Academic Analytics organization of [[Stony Brook, NY]], SDSU is the number one small research university in the United States as of the last four (4) academic years, from 2005-2006 through the 2009-2010 academic years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.prweb.com/releases/2007/5/prweb529904.htm Study Ranks California's Most Productive Universities (May 31, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nctimes.com/articles/2007/06/02/news/sandiego/14_57_336_1_07.txt SDSU named most productive small research school (North County Times) (June 1, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdsuniverse.info/story.asp?id=61084 SDSU Receives Top Research Distinction for Second Straight Year (SDSUniverse.com) (Nov. 26, 2007)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailyaztec1&quot;&gt;[http://www.thedailyaztec.com/campus-news/sdsu-is-no-1-in-rankings-1.2280576 SDSU is No.1 in Rankings (July 19, 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, ''[[The Daily Beast]]'' ranked SDSU No.21 in its list of &quot;Tech's 29 Most Powerful Colleges.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|publisher=[[The Daily Beast]]|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/galleries/1578/21/?redirectURL=http://www.thedailybeast.com/blogs-and-stories/2010-05-03/techs-29-most-powerful-colleges/#gallery=1578;page=21|title=Tech's 29 Most Powerful Colleges}}&lt;/ref&gt;

San Diego State University awards [[Bachelor's degree|bachelor's]], [[Master's degree|master's]], and [[Doctorate|doctoral]] degrees ([[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]], [[Doctor of Education|Ed.D]], and [[Doctor of Audiology|Au.D]]) in a total of 151 fields. SDSU offers the most doctoral degrees of any campus of the California State University system, currently in sixteen academic and research [[academic discipline|disciplines]].

San Diego State University is a member of the [[American Association of State Colleges and Universities|American Association of State Colleges and Universities (AASCU)]], the [[National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges]], the [[Southwest Border Security Consortium]], and the [[Oak Ridge Associated Universities]], a national organization of universities that promotes science and technology education and research.

==History==
{{Main|History of San Diego State University}}
Established on March 13, 1897, San Diego State University first began as the '''San Diego Normal School''', meant to educate local future female elementary school teachers. In 1923, the San Diego Normal School became '''San Diego State Teachers College''', &quot;a four-year public institution controlled by the state Board of Education.&quot;  In 1935, the school became '''San Diego State College.''' In 1960, San Diego State College became a part of the California College System, now known as the [[California State University]] system. Finally in 1970 San Diego State College became San Diego State University (SDSU).

One in seven San Diegans with a college degree attended SDSU,&lt;ref name=&quot;advancement.sdsu.edu&quot;&gt;[http://advancement.sdsu.edu/marcomm/news/sdsufacts.html SDSU Significant Rankings and Distinctions]&lt;/ref&gt; making SDSU a primary educator of the region's work force. Committed to serving the diverse [[San Diego]] region, SDSU ranks among the top ten universities nationwide in terms of ethnic and racial diversity among its student body, as well as the number of bachelor's degrees conferred upon minority students.&lt;ref name=&quot;advancement.sdsu.edu&quot;/&gt;

San Diego State University has been designated a &quot;Research University&quot; by the [[The Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|Carnegie Foundation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=13612&amp;start=782|title = San Diego State University|publisher = carnegiefoundation.org |format=database entry and article}}&lt;/ref&gt;  University faculty consistently attract hundreds of millions of U.S. dollars annually in grants and contracts for research and program administration, and SDSU's research and graduate degree programs lead all other campuses of the [[California State University]] system.&lt;ref name=&quot;advancement.sdsu.edu&quot;/&gt; In the 2009-10 academic year, the university obtained $150 million for research, including $26 million from the [[National Institutes of Health]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news | first=Gary | last=Robbins | title=Funds for research are flowing into SDSU | url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/2010/may/14/funds-for-research-are-flowing-into-sdsu/| work= | publisher=San Diego Union-Tribune | location=San Diego, California | pages= A1 | date=14 May 2010 | id= | accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the beginning of the 2006-2007 academic year, SDSU expanded its classrooms and support space by more than {{convert|200000|sqft|m2}} with the opening of three new buildings, the College of Arts and Letters, the Calpulli Center and BioScience Center. The buildings, respectively, feature high-technology classrooms, upgraded health and wellness facilities, and scientific research laboratories.

SDSU's Astronomy Department owns the [[Mount Laguna Observatory]] located in the [[Cleveland National Forest]]. It operates the observatory concurrently with the [[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Mount Laguna Observatory]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[John F. Kennedy]], then the [[President of the United States of America]], gave the graduation commencement address at San Diego State University on June 6, 1963.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sdsuniverse.info/story.asp?id=6269 Forty Years Later, the Magic of JFK Lingers on the Mesa], Coleen L. Geraghty, ''SDSUniverse'' (May 12, 2003)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://infodome.sdsu.edu/projects/buildings/aztecbowl.html ''SDSU Library'', Aztec Bowl: History of San Diego State University (accessed Jan. 16, 2009)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://scua.sdsu.edu/exhibits/online/2010/03/JFKMovie/JFKMovie.shtml John F. Kennedy commencement address (June 6, 1963), SDSU Special Collections (video)]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|As a nation, we have no deeper concern, no older commitment and no higher interest than a strong, sound and free system of education for all. In fulfilling this obligation to ourselves and our children, we provide for the future of our nation-and for the future of freedom.
|4=[[John F. Kennedy]], [[President of the United States of America]]
|5=Graduation commencement address to San Diego State College (San Diego, California), June 6, 1963}}

==Campus==
Several buildings are listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;histbldgs&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dometest.sdsu.edu/projects/buildings/bldgs.html|title=Historic Buildings of San Diego State University|work=Infodome - SDSU Historic Buildings|publisher=San Diego State University|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Scripps Cottage was finished in September 1931, funded with a donation of $6,000 from Ellen Browning Scripps matched with $5,000 from the state. It was the headquarters for the Associated Women Students and was used for meetings, women's activities, and served as a lounge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr78&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; On September 3, 1968 the building was moved to make room for the new library. It was used mainly as a conference and meeting building, and in 1993, began serving as a center for international students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr156&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Aztec Bowl (stadium)|Aztec Bowl]], costing $500,000, the stadium was dedicated on October 3, 1936 before 7,500 people, after being completed earlier that year. The stadium was initially supposed to be expanded to 45,000 seats, but instead was only expanded once with 5,000 seats in 1948. Aztec Bowl was the only state college stadium in California at the time of its construction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr94&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;
*Open Air Theatre contained 4,280 seats and was financed by the Works Progress Administration and the state for $200,000. It was dedicated in 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr96&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;
*On January 19, 1976, the Montezuma Mesa building was renamed to [[Hepner Hall|Walter R. Hepner Hall]], and on May 1, 1977 the humanities building was named after John Adams, a teacher, administrator, and archivist. The Humanities-Social Sciences building was renamed in 1986 after geographer Alvena Storm and historian Abraham P. Nasatir.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr191&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 191&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the 1980s the Open Air Theatre added new support facilities and fencing. [[Peterson Gym]] was finished in 1961, making the original gym the Women’s Gym until it was remodeled and reopened in 1990 as the Physical Education building. In 1990, {{convert|14000|sqft|m2|abbr=on}} were added to Storm and Nasatir Halls. In 1986, a large student apartment complex was added along with a 11-story $13,000,000 residence hall (west side of campus).&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr202&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 202&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hardy Memorial Tower]], in the [[Mission Revival]] style, resembles a Mediterranean church tower and is one of the most recognizable buildings on campus.  It also performed a utilitarian function: The tower concealed a 5000 gallon water tank that provided pressure for the campus plumbing system.  The building housed the university's first library, which featured [[mural]]s painted by the [[Works Progress Administration]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hardyhist&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dometest.sdsu.edu/projects/buildings/hardy.html|title=Hardy Memorial Tower|work=Infodome - SDSU Historic Buildings|publisher=San Diego State University|accessdate=2009-07-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Communications Building, Exercise &amp; Nutritional Sciences, Faculty Staff Club, Life Science Building and Annex, Little Theatre, Physical Plant Boiler Shop, and the Physical Science Building are also listed on the National Register.&lt;ref name=&quot;histbldgs&quot;/&gt;

Other buildings on campus include:
[[Image:SDSULoveLibraryNight2008.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The front entrance to [[Malcolm A. Love Library|Love Library]]]]
*The campus library, now known as the [[Malcolm A. Love Library]], acquired its 100,000th book on May 21, 1944. By the end of World War II it was adding about 8,000 books a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr125&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 125&lt;/ref&gt; In 1959, a {{convert|40000|sqft|m2|abbr=on}}. addition to the library was finished, but it was already deemed too small.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr138&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; In 1952, the library had 125,000 books, and state regulations required that old books be eliminated before new ones could be added. By 1965, there were more than 300,000 books housed in a library that could hold 230,000. This was ranked highest in state colleges in terms of library size. In the 1960s, construction of a new library began, which required the relocation of Scripps Cottage. The $8,000,000 building was designed with {{convert|300000|sqft|m2|abbr=on}}. of space to accommodate one million books.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1556&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 155-56&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1971, the library opened, housing 700,000 books, and was named after President Malcolm A. Love for his popularity on campus and his role in bringing State to university status.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr187&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; Governor [[Ronald Reagan]] said the library would &quot;...serve as a lasting memorial to the man who led the college through its growing pains...to one of the finest state colleges in California.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr188&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; The building was five stories high and was the largest building on campus. A four-story sculpture entitled &quot;Hanging Discus&quot; by sculptor George Baker was specifically designed for the library and added to an interior staircase in November 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr189&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;

*Construction of a $11 million alumni center began in May 2008. The center is expected to be opened in fall 2009 and house the SDSU Alumni Association, the Campanile Foundation, as well as the university relations and development staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlumniCenter&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Lee|first=Jaimy|title=Tucker Sadler has designs on $11m center at SDSU|publisher=[[San Diego Business Journal]]|date=2008-04-14|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-34442995_ITM|accessdate=2008-10-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Residence halls===
In 1937, Quetzal Hall, the first dormitory, opened for 40 women students and was located off campus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr96&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; In 1952, 50 college youth conducted a [[panty raid]] at Quetzal Hall, causing $1,000 in damages. Police arrested 13 of the students and the dorm girls later retaliated by attacking the [[Pi Kappa Alpha]] fraternity house.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr143&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; In 1968, the coed dorm Zura Hall was built, and more rooms were added later.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr168&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; Chapultepec Hall held 580 students when first built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr220&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 220&lt;/ref&gt;

===Branch campuses===
*[[San Diego State University Imperial Valley Campus|Imperial Valley Campus]]
** Located in [[Calexico, California]]
** Additional campus in [[Brawley, California]] along with research park and related facilities
** Upper division, teacher certification, and graduate classes only
*North County Campus
** Formerly located in northern San Diego County
** Closed; converted to [[California State University, San Marcos]]
*South Bay Campus
** Formerly located on the first floor of the parking structure across from the Holiday Inn in [[National City, California]].
** Shared facilities with [[Southwestern College (California)|Southwestern College]].
** Closed indefinitely.

==Academics==
&lt;div style=&quot;float:left&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;big&gt;'''Fall Freshman Statistics'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;admissions&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/as/stat_reports/2010-2011/apps_fall10.shtml]. ''CSU Analytic Studies, Fall 2010.''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;applicants&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/as/stat_reports/2008-2009/apps-fall08.htm]. ''CSU Analytic Studies, Fall 2008.'' 7/9/11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;applicants&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/as/stat_reports/2007-2008/apps-fall07.htm]. ''CSU Analytic Studies, Fall 2007.''&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! &amp;nbsp; !! 2010 !! 2009 !! 2008 !! 2007
|-
! Applicants
| 44,845 || 41,986 || 50,148 || 46,718
|-
! Admits
| 13,447 || 15,273 || 15,658 || 20,628
|-
! % Admitted
| 29.99 || 36.38 || 31.22 || 44.15
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
===Research affairs===
San Diego State University is the leader in the California State University system in awarding [[Ph.D.]] (joint with [[UCSD]] &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sdsu.edu/academicprogs.html San Diego State University's Academic Programs&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;) or [[Ed.D]] degrees, currently awarding such degrees in 16 academic disciplines. As a result of recent statutory changes (SB 724), SDSU intends to expand the scope and number of [[doctoral degree]] programs that it offers its graduate students. SDSU has been referred to as the research flagship campus of the California State University system.{{Citation needed|date=May 2010}}

===Rankings and distinctions===
&lt;!-- Please put department-specific rankings in the article for that particular college--&gt;
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_W = 301-400
| ARWU_N = 112-137
|
| USNWR_NU = 164
| Wamo_NU = 175
}}

*For four years in a row, SDSU has been ranked the No. 1 most productive research university, among schools with 14 or fewer Ph.D. programs based on the [[Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailyaztec1&quot;/&gt;
*SDSU has been designated a &quot;Research University&quot; with high research activity by the Carnegie Foundation.
*Since 2000, SDSU faculty and staff have attracted more than $1 billion in grants and contracts for research and program administration.
*SDSU is the largest university in San Diego and the fifth largest in California.
*SDSU ranks No. 2 among universities of its type nationwide and No. 1 in California for students studying abroad as part of their college experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.calstate.edu/impact/campus/sandiego.html |title=San Diego State University &amp;#124; The Impact of the California State University |publisher=Calstate.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*One in seven adults in San Diego who holds a college degree attended SDSU.
*SDSU is home to the first-ever MBA program in Global Entrepreneurship. As part of the program, students study at four universities worldwide, including the United States, China, the Middle East, and India. Corporate partners include [[Qualcomm]], [[Invitrogen]], [[Intel]], [[Microsoft]], and [[KPMG]].
*In 1970, SDSU founded the first [[women's studies]] program in the country.
*[[Modern Healthcare]] ranked SDSU No.2 Graduate school for physician executives in relation to their Master's in Public Health program.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url= http://newscenter.sdsu.edu/sdsu_newscenter/news.aspx?s=72190 |title=SDSU No. 2 Grad School for Physician Execs |work=newscenter.sdsu.edu |accessdate=12 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization and administration==
===Schools and colleges===
[[Image:Sdsumain.jpg|thumb|right|A landmark architecture ([[Hepner Hall]]) featured in the school's logo]]

*[[San Diego State University College of Arts &amp; Letters|College of Arts &amp; Letters]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Business Administration|College of Business Administration]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Education|College of Education]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Engineering|College of Engineering]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Health &amp; Human Services|College of Health &amp; Human Services (and Graduate School of Public Health)]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Sciences|College of Sciences]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Professional Studies &amp; Fine Arts|College of Professional Studies &amp; Fine Arts]]
*[[San Diego State University College of Extended Studies|College of Extended Studies (and American Language Institute)]]

===Endowment===
:''See also [[San Diego State University Research Foundation]] for additional information''

[[Image:SDSUPedestrian Bridge.jpg|thumb|Pedestrian bridge connecting various residence halls and parking structures to campus]]

The permanent [[financial endowment]] of San Diego State University (SDSU) is currently valued at $120.3 million U.S. dollars (USD) as of the end of the 2007 academic year.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20080212/news_1n12funds.html &quot;Raising the fundraising bar&quot; San Diego Union Tribune, February 12, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:StudentServices.jpg|thumb|left|Student Services building with clock tower]]

The primary [[philanthropy|philanthropic]] arm of San Diego State University is [http://newscenter.sdsu.edu/tcf/ The Campanile Foundation], controlled by the [http://advancement.sdsu.edu/index.html University Advancement division] of the university. The [[San Diego State University Research Foundation]], an auxiliary corporation owned and controlled by the university, is the manager and administrator of all [[philanthropy|philanthropic]] funds and external funding for the university and its affiliated and auxiliary foundations and corporations.

As of June 30, 2006, permanent assets of the SDSU Campanile Foundation totaled $134 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://advancement.sdsu.edu/tcf/download/Campanile_05-06%20final.pdf The Campanile Foundation: Financial Statements June 30, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

For the 2004-2005 academic year, SDSU received over $157 million USD in external funding from grants and contracts, as well as an additional $57 million USD in donations and charitable giving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/UA/0405externalreport/campus/san_diego.shtml 2004-2005 Annual Report on External Funding, California State University]&lt;/ref&gt; For 2005-2006, SDSU received $152 million USD in grants and contracts to support research. This is followed by $47.7 million USD in donations, gifts and other charitable giving.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/ua/0506externalreport/campus/san_diego.shtml 2005-2006 Annual Report on External Support to the CSU -- San Diego State University]&lt;/ref&gt;

An auxiliary to The Campanile Foundation is the [http://goaztecs.collegesports.com/boosters/boosters-static-info/booster-overview.html Aztec Athletic Association], which primarily raises funds for the student athletes in the San Diego State University athletics programs (see discussion of Athletics below and at [[SDSU Aztecs]]).

In addition to its permanent endowment, San Diego State University raises over $55 million U.S. dollars per year (approximately) in philanthropic gifts to support its research and academic affairs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://advancement.sdsu.edu/marcomm/news/releases/fall2005/pr100705b.html &quot;San Diego State University Reports $55.2 Million in Philanthropic Gifts for 2004-05&quot; Official SDSU Press Release, Oct. 7, 2005&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The California State University system budget is being cut by $564 million this year, with SDSU's budget being reduced by $55 million.&lt;ref&gt;Ruggero, Lorena. &quot;[http://www.palomar.edu/dsps/actc/mla/mlainternet.html Aztecs Rally Against Budget Cuts]&quot;. October 9, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of California’s state budget cuts, student enrollment is being reduced by 4,618 by Fall 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;budgetcut&quot;&gt;Weber, Stephen. &quot;[http://advancement.sdsu.edu/budgetcentral/index.html SDSU Admissions Changes]&quot;. San Diego State University. October 21, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media, newspapers, and magazines==
[[Image:Love library, entrance, SDSU.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Malcolm A. Love Library|Malcolm A. Love Library and the InfoDome]]]]
Students began publishing ''The White and Gold'' in 1902, which was a literary magazine and newspaper.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr27&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, a new newspaper was established entitled ''Normal News Weekly''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr39&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; The school newspaper ''Paper Lantern'' (''Normal News Weekly'' was renamed after the addition of the junior college) became ''The Aztec'' in September 1925.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr53&quot;/&gt; It was later expanded to its current name, ''The Daily Aztec''. The school's annual yearbook was named ''Del Sudoeste'' (Spanish for &quot;of the southwest&quot;) in the early 1920s.
''The Koala'', a comedy newspaper that is widely known around the San Diego State area, is also distributed monthly on campus but is not directly connected to the school at the moment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr53&quot;/&gt;

;SDSU media and publications
* San Diego State University Press
** The oldest university press in the California State University system with noted specializations in Border Studies, Critical Theory, Latin American Studies, and Cultural Studies.
*Hyperbole Books
** Hyperbole Books
*KPBS Public Broadcasting [[KPBS (TV)|TV]]/[[KPBS-FM|FM]]
** [[Television]], [[digital television]], and [[FM broadcasting in the USA|FM radio]] for the San Diego community
** Official site of KPBS
** An affiliate of the [[Public Broadcasting Service|Public Broadcasting Service (PBS)]] network
** &quot;A Broadcasting Service of San Diego State University&quot;
*[[KCR (AM)]]
** Student-run broadcast station
* 360 Magazine
** The quarterly SDSU alumni and San Diego community magazine

;Official SDSU campus newspapers
* The SDSU News &amp; Media webpage
* SDSUniverse news service
** News and information for the SDSU community
*[[The Daily Aztec]] - The largest daily collegiate newspaper in California, publishing daily since 1960.

==Extracurriculars==
===Athletics===
{{Main|San Diego State Aztecs}}
The first major sport on campus was [[rowing (sport)|rowing]], but it initially had no coaches or tournaments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr28&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Other sports that developed early in the campus's history were tennis, basketball, golf, croquet, and baseball.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr28&quot;/&gt; The school's football program had such a limited selection of players that faculty had to be used to fill the roster.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr28&quot;/&gt; When the college merged with the junior college in 1921, SDSU became a member of the Junior College Conference. After the school won the majority of the conference titles in a variety of sports, the league requested that SDSU leave out of fairness to the smaller schools. For its football program, the team outscored its opponents 249 to 52 in ten games, resulting in the first sales of season tickets in 1923.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr60&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; From 1925-26, SDSU played as an independent. It then joined the [[Southern California Intercollegiate Athletic Conference|Southern California Conference]] in 1926, where it did not win a football conference championship until 1936. However, in other sports including tennis and basketball, it excelled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr60&quot;/&gt; SDSU remained with the conference until 1939, when it joined the [[California Collegiate Athletic Association]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1025&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 102 &amp; 105&lt;/ref&gt;

The basketball team reached and won multiple championships games during the 1930-40s, including a conference title in 1931, 1934, 1937, and 1939. It reached the national championship in 1939 and 1940, losing in the final rounds. However, in 1941 SDSU returned and won the college's first national title.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1025&quot;/&gt; In track, the team won conference titles in 1935, 1936, 1937, 1938, and 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1025&quot;/&gt; The football team won conference titles in 1936 and 1937, and the baseball team won three conference titles and placed second three times between 1935-1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1025&quot;/&gt;

In 1955, the Aztec Club was established and raised $20,000 a year by 1957. The club worked in increasing athletic scholarships, hiring better coaches, and developing the college’s intercollegiate athletic programs. In 1956, students approved through a vote of allowing a mandatory student activity fee, with a portion going to athletics. By the end of the decade the budget had doubled to $40,000. The campus’s most successful sports program during the 1950s was cross-country as the team won eight straight conference titles, [[Amateur Athletic Union|AAU]] regional titles, and placed high in national competitions. Basketball ranged from last in the conference to multiple conference, regional, and national appearances. The football program had its first undefeated team in 1951, but in the last part of the decade earned the worst records in the school’s football program under the direction of head coach [[Paul Governali]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr1445&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 144-45&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:MarshallFaulkSDSUGameBall.jpg|thumb|right|[[Marshall Faulk]]'s game ball from the September 14, 1991 game when he ran for a NCAA-record 386 yards and scored 44 points]]

Under Governali, the campus’s football program suffered, due to Governali’s policy of not recruiting new players. To improve the program, Love hired [[Don Coryell]] in 1961, which helped the program to win three consecutive championships (1966–68), and end with a record of 104 wins, 19 losses, and 2 ties by the time he left SDSU. Coryell was assisted by [[John Madden (American football)|John Madden]], [[Joe Gibbs]], and [[Rod Dowhower]], among others. In Coryell’s first year, attendance at home games averaged 8,000 people, but by 1966 it had doubled to 16,000. This later jumped to 26,000-41,000 per game with the addition of the new San Diego stadium. At some games, attendance was larger than at [[San Diego Chargers]] games. There were several undefeated seasons and multiple players broke records for most catches, touchdowns, and passing yards, among others. In 1969, SDSU moved into [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division 1]], leaving the [[California Collegiate Athletic Association]]. In 1972, Coyrell left to pursue coaching in the NFL.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr15962&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 159-62&lt;/ref&gt;

Basketball also did well, with the 1967-68 team being ranked the number one college-level team in the nation, although it did not win a national title. The Aztecs also won the 1960 CCAA baseball title, and won multiple national championships throughout the 1960s in track, cross country, and swimming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr15962&quot;/&gt;

By 1970-71, the campus had 14 NCAA sports. The 1973 men’s volleyball team won the NCAA national championship which was the first NCAA national title since moving to Division I status.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr221&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 221&lt;/ref&gt;

SDSU competes in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] FBS. Its primary conference is the [[Mountain West Conference]]; its women's [[water polo]] team participates in the [[Mountain Pacific Sports Federation]] and its men's [[soccer]] team participates as an Associate Member of the [[Pacific-12 Conference]] (the &quot;[[Pacific-12 Conference|Pac-12]]&quot; Conference). The ice hockey team competes in the [[ACHA]] with other western region club teams (www.sdsuhockey.com). The crew team's championship regatta is in the WIRA (Western International Rowing Association). The university colors are [[scarlet (color)|scarlet (red)]] and [[black (color)|black]], SDSU's athletic teams are nicknamed &quot;[[Aztecs]]&quot;, and its current [[mascot]] is the [[Aztec army|Aztec Warrior]], historically referred to as &quot;Monty - Montezuma&quot;. Athletics revenues have been down recently.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite news
|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/uniontrib/20080222/news_1s22azbudget.html
|title=Football shy of dollar goal at SDSU 
|newspaper=[[San Diego Union-Tribune]]
|accessdate=2008-02-25
|last=Schrotenboer
|first=Brent
|date=February 22, 2008
|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

;Football
::See [[San Diego State Aztecs football]]
* The football team plays at [[Qualcomm Stadium]] (formerly known as &quot;Jack Murphy&quot; Stadium).

[[Image:Cox arena front.JPG|right|thumb|250px|[[Viejas Arena]] is used for the Aztec basketball games, speeches, convocations, and concerts]]

;Basketball
::See [[San Diego State Aztecs men's basketball]]
* The basketball teams play at [[Viejas Arena]] on the SDSU campus.

;Baseball

* The baseball team plays in [[Tony Gwynn Stadium]] on the SDSU campus, named after the SDSU baseball and basketball player and current head coach, [[Tony Gwynn]].

;Volleyball
* The women's volleyball team plays in [[Peterson Gym]] on the SDSU campus.
* The men's volleyball team won the [[NCAA Men's Volleyball Championship|NCAA Championship in 1973]], but the team has since been disbanded.

;Soccer
* Both the men's and women's teams both play at the Sports Deck on the SDSU campus. The women compete in the [[Mountain West Conference]] while the men compete in the [[Pacific-12 Conference|Pacific-12 Conference (Pac-12)]].

;Ice Hockey
* Participates in the ACHA Men's Division 2.
* Advanced to National Championship final game in 2008 for ACHA Men's Division 3 and lost 7-3 to California University of Pennsylvania.
*San Diego State University Ice Hockey

;Other sports
* The new $12 million dollar aquatic sports complex (known as the [[Aztec Aquaplex]]), includes an [[Olympic-size swimming pool]], a separate recreational pool and beach, and a hydrotherapy spa. This facility is home for the swimming and diving teams, in addition to providing recreational use for all SDSU students and community members.
**SDSU Campus Recreation pool web page
* In conjunction with the [[UCSD]], the Associated Students organization of San Diego State University runs the Mission Bay Aquatic Center (MBAC) in [[Mission Bay, California]], just a few miles west of the main campus. The MBAC provides for all manner of outdoor activities and sports for SDSU students, administration, and faculty.

===Clubs===
Initial clubs that were first started on campus including the Debating Club, the Associated Student Body, YWCA, and in 1906, an alumni association.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr27&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; The oldest club on campus was The Rowing Association.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr59&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student body and Greek life===
[[File:SDSU Green Line.jpg|thumb|left|[[SDSU Transit Center (San Diego Trolley station)|The underground San Diego Trolley station on the SDSU campus]]]]
The first fraternity on campus was the Delta chapter of Epsilon Eta, which formed on October 25, 1921. By the end of the decade there were six other fraternities and eight sororities. The fraternities and sororities were all local, and did not attain national status until after World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr59&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; In 1925, in order to encourage higher grades, the Inter-Fraternity Council and Inter-Sorority Council published the average grades of the fraternity and sorority members. On a 3.0 scale, the average GPA (grade point average) for all students was 1.49, for fraternities was 1.35, and sororities was 1.47.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr59&quot;/&gt;  By the mid-1930s there were eight fraternities and eleven sororities,&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr96&quot;/&gt; and later expanded to fifteen fraternities and twelve sororities in the 1940s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr127&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; The first fraternity to go national was [[Theta Chi]] and the first sorority was [[Alpha Xi Delta]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr127&quot;/&gt; 

On April 27, 1974, the Phi Beta Kappa honor society established a SDSU chapter. It was the first in the CSU system as well as the San Diego area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr193&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; During the 1960s and early 1970s, the Greek population had dwindled to 699, but gradually began to increase in the 1980s, reaching 2,900 in 1988. There were 20 fraternities and 13 sororities officially affiliated with the Inter Fraternity Council and Panhellenic Council as well as six independent fraternities/sororities. This made it one of the largest fraternity and sorority systems in the western U.S.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr214&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 214&lt;/ref&gt; On April 6, 1978, [[Gamma Phi Beta]] sorority hired a plane to drop [[marshmallow]]s on fraternity houses during Derby Week, but the plane crashed near Peterson Gym, injuring four students aboard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr215&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983 a ''[[USA Today]]'' article reported that SDSU Greeks GPAs were below the campus average, so SDSU tightened restrictions and supervision and by 1989 their grades had increased to slightly above University average.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr215&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1989-91, several riots among the fraternities occurred, including one numbering 3,500 people, and another requiring 34 police officers to end it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr216&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Operation Sudden Fall|2008 drug bust]] resulted in the suspension of several fraternities as well as the arrests of multiple fraternity members.&lt;ref name=&quot;SusFrat&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=McDonald|first=Jeff|coauthors=Sherry Saavedra and Tanya Sierra|title=Major SDSU drug probe nets 96 arrests in raids|publisher=[[San Diego Union Tribune]]|date=2008-05-07|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/metro/20080507-9999-1n7drugs.html|accessdate=2008-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently there are over 48 social fraternities and sororities, including both general and culturally based organizations, represented by four governing councils.

==Traditions==
[[Image:Courtyard SDSU.jpg|thumb|250px|Courtyard looking towards Hepner Hall]]

* The San Diego State Marching Aztecs and Pep and Varsity Bands are often seen at many sporting events including Football, Basketball and even Volleyball.
* The San Diego State University (SDSU) campus is known as &quot;Montezuma Mesa&quot;, as the university is situated on a [[mesa]] overlooking [[Mission Valley, California|Mission Valley]] and is located at the intersection of Montezuma Road and College Avenue.
* [[Undie run|Undie Run]] through campus that takes place during finals week each semester.

===S mountain===
&quot;S&quot; mountain was created by the Council of Twelve and initially supported by President Hardy.{{clarify|date=September 2011}} On February 27, 1931, he allowed 500 students to paint rocks, forming a 400-foot &quot;S&quot; on [[Cowles Mountain]]. The giant S was lit at night for the opening football game of a season (performed by the freshman to build school spirit) along with pep rallies, and was repainted throughout its history.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr126&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr78&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, it was the largest collegiate symbol in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr79&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; During World War II, the S was camouflaged to prevent it becoming a reference point for enemy bombing aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr112&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; It was returned to its normal state in April 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr121&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1970s students stopped painting it and brush obstructed the symbol. After a 1988 brush fire it was exposed, and students repainted it. In fall, 1997, a group of 100 volunteers climbed Cowles Mountain after dusk to commemorate the one hundredth anniversary of the school by using flashlights to once again outline the &quot;S&quot; on the side of the mountain. In 1990, a high school prank defaced the S to read as &quot;91&quot; in honor of their graduating class.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr213&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 213&lt;/ref&gt;

===School colors and mascot===
The initial [[school colors|colors of the school]] were white and gold. When the junior college was added to the campus in 1921, its colors of blue and gold were merged together, resulting in a blue, gold, and white color scheme. New colors were later chosen as gold and purple, until being replaced by crimson and black on January 28, 1928.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr50&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;

The school's prior nicknames for its mascot included &quot;Normalites&quot;, &quot;Professors&quot;, and &quot;Wampus Cats&quot;. However, after a 1924 committee met to address the issue, the name &quot;Aztecs&quot; was decided on.&lt;ref name=&quot;Starr53&quot;&gt;Starr, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003, the Aztec Warrior was approved by a student and alumni vote to become the official university mascot after the school's prior mascot, Monty Montezuma, was discontinued.&lt;ref name=&quot;AztecWarrior&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Jenkins|first=Brandon|coauthors=Melissa Berlant|title=San Diego State U.: San Diego State U. approves university mascot|publisher=[[The America's Intelligence Wire]]|date=2003-12-15|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-19718715_ITM|accessdate=2008-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable events and popular culture==
;Film and television
* The two main characters from the 2004 [[Academy Awards|Academy Award]]-winning comedy/drama film ''[[Sideways]]'' were roommates during their college days at SDSU.
* The SDSU campus is the setting of [[Hearst College]], the fictional university in [[The CW]] television network show ''[[Veronica Mars]]''.
*The exterior shots of Rancho Carne High School in the movie ''[[Bring It On (film)|Bring it On]]'' were mainly filmed at San Diego State University
*Portions of ''[[The Real World: San Diego]]'' were filmed around the SDSU campus
*SDSU is mentioned by Bart Simpson in ''[[The Simpsons]]'' episode &quot;The President Wore Pearls&quot; (Season 15, 2003). Lisa becomes president of Springfield Elementary and unknowingly strips the school of all of its recreational activities, leading Bart to say, &quot;Lisa, you made this school even worse.  And it wasn't exactly San Diego State to begin with.&quot;

;1996 campus shooting
{{Main|San Diego State University shooting}}
The San Diego State University shooting occurred on August 15, 1996. A 36-year-old graduate engineering student, while apparently defending his thesis, shot and killed his three professors, Constantinos Lyrintzis, Cheng Liang, and D. Preston Lowrey III, at San Diego State University. The shooter, who was suffering from certain mental problems, was convicted on July 19, 1997, and was sentenced to life in prison.  As a memorial, tables with a plaque with information about each victim have been placed adjacent to the College of Engineering building.

;2008 student drug arrests
{{Main|Operation Sudden Fall}}
On May 6, 2008, the [[Drug Enforcement Administration]] announced the arrest of 96 individuals, of whom 33 were San Diego State University students, on a variety of drug charges in a narcotics [[sting operation]] dubbed [[Operation Sudden Fall]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbs8.com/misc/SDSU_mug_shots.pdf|title=Mug Shots from Operation Sudden Fall|publisher=CBS News 8|accessdate=2008-05-06|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080530031254/http://www.cbs8.com/misc/SDSU_mug_shots.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally reported that 75 of the arrested were students, but the inflated number included students who had been arrested months earlier, in some cases for simple possession.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/metro/20080508-1041-bn08arrests.html|title=Officials differ on number of SDSU students snared in sting  |publisher=[[San Diego Union Tribune]]|accessdate=2008-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The bust, which was the largest in the history of [[San Diego County]], drew a mixed reaction from the community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.signonsandiego.com/news/metro/20080508-9999-1n8sdsu.html|title=SDSU drug sting draws scorn, praise |publisher=[[San Diego Union Tribune]]|accessdate=2008-05-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In addition, Associated Students President, James Poet was arrested on October 17, 2008, for driving under the influence and possession of marijuana. Poet expressed full support for the actions of Operation Sudden Fall and the Zero Tolerance Policy.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thedailyaztec.com/city/poet_arrested_for_alleged_dui_and_marijuana_possession|title=Poet arrested for alleged DUI and marijuana possession|publisher=The Daily Aztec|accessdate=2008-10-25}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni and faculty==
{{Main|List of San Diego State University alumni and faculty}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons|San Diego State University}}
*{{Official|http://www.sdsu.edu}}
*[http://www.goaztecs.com/ Official athletics website]

{{San Diego State University}}
{{Template group
|title = Links to related articles
|titlestyle = background:#D2C694;color:#A81933;border:2px solid #A81933;
|state =autocollapse
|list =
{{California State University}}
{{Mountain West Conference}}
{{San Diego County Colleges and Universities}}
{{National Register of Historic Places}}
}}

[[Category:San Diego State University| ]]
[[Category:California State University]]
[[Category:Association of Public and Land-Grant Universities]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1897]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in San Diego County, California]]
[[Category:Schools on the National Register of Historic Places in California]]
[[Category:Schools accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]
[[Category:Historic districts in California]]

[[da:San Diego State University]]
[[de:San Diego State University]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de San Diego]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی سن دییگو]]
[[fr:Université d'État de San Diego]]
[[ko:샌디에이고 주립 대학교]]
[[ms:San Diego State University]]
[[ja:サンディエゴ州立大学]]
[[simple:San Diego State University]]
[[fi:San Diego State University]]
[[sv:San Diego State University]]
[[uk:Університет штату Каліфорнія в Сан-Дієго]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
