<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2861465" ns="0" title="Slovenian euro coins"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Slovenian euro coins''' were first issued for circulation on 1 January 2007 and a unique feature is designed for each coin. The design of approximately 230 million [[Slovenia]]n [[euro coin]]s (total value of approximately €80 million) was unveiled on 7 October 2005. The designers were [[Miljenko Licul]], Maja Licul and [[Janez Boljka]]. The Mint of Finland was chosen to [[Mint (coin)|mint]] the coins through an international [[Call for bids|tender]] in 2007. Starting 2008, the [[Koninklijke Nederlandse Munt]] (Royal Dutch Mint) was chosen to mint the coins.

==Slovenian euro design==
The Slovenian euro coins were the first to feature a new common side, with a new map of Europe on the bicoloured and Nordic-gold coins.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.bsi.si/library/includes/datoteka.asp?DatotekaId=1715 | title=The effigies of the new Slovene euro coins}}&lt;/ref&gt; For [[Euro coins#Depiction of euro coinage - Reverse side|images of the common side]] and a detailed description of the coins, see [[euro coins]].

{{Coin image box 8 singles
| header = Depiction of Slovenian euro coinage &lt;nowiki&gt;|&lt;/nowiki&gt; Obverse side
| column_1_width = 157
| column_2_width = 172
| column_3_width = 165
| denom_1 = €0.01
| denom_2 = €0.02
| denom_3 = €0.05
| image_1 = 
| image_2 = 
| image_3 = 
| caption_1 = A [[stork]], a motif taken from the former 20 [[Slovenian tolar|SIT]] coin
| caption_2 = The [[Prince's stone]], where [[Carantania]]n [[dukes]] were installed
| caption_3 = [[Ivan Grohar]]'s painting ''A Sower'' sowing stars
| denom_4 = €0.10
| denom_5 = €0.20
| denom_6 = €0.50
| image_4 = 
| image_5 = 
| image_6 = 
| caption_4 = [[Jože Plečnik]]'s idea for the [[Slovenian Parliament|national parliament]], with the inscription &quot;''Katedrala svobode''&quot; (Cathedral of Freedom)
| caption_5 = A pair of [[Lipizzaner]] horses with the inscription &quot;''Lipicanec''&quot; (Lipizzaner)
| caption_6 = [[Triglav]], [[Cancer (constellation)|constellation of Cancer]]&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and inscription from [[Jakob Aljaž]]'s song &quot;''Oj Triglav moj dom''&quot; (O Triglav, My Home).
| denom_7 = €1
| denom_8 = €2
| header_9 = €2 Coin Edge
| box_9 = S L O V E N I J A
| image_7 = 
| image_8 = 
| caption_7 = [[Primož Trubar]], Slovenian Protestant reformer, and the inscription &quot;''Stati inu obstati''&quot; (To Exist and Persevere)
| caption_8 = [[France Prešeren]], Slovenian Romantic poet, and the first line of the 7th stanza of ''[[Zdravljica]]'' (Slovenian [[national anthem]])  
}}
&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Slovenia achieved independence under the [[Zodiac|zodiac sign]] of Cancer.

==Circulating Mintage quantities==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;text-align:center&quot;
|-
!|Face Value &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher=Henning Agt | url=http://www.euro-auflagen.de/index.php?lang=en | title=Circulating Mintage quantities | accessdate=2008-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!|€0.01
!|€0.02
!|€0.05
!|€0.10
!|€0.20
!|€0.50
!|€1
!|€2
|-
!|2007
||44,600,000
||44,150,000
||43,700,000
||42,700,000
||37,150,000
||32,100,000
||29,650,000
||21,250,000
|-
!|2008
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
!|2009
||17,900,000
||12,300,000
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
!|2010
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;***&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
!|2011
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
||&lt;sup&gt;**&lt;/sup&gt;
|-
| align=left colspan=9 |
&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; No coins were minted that year for that denomination&lt;br&gt;
&lt;nowiki&gt;**&lt;/nowiki&gt; Data not available yet&lt;br&gt;
&lt;nowiki&gt;***&lt;/nowiki&gt; Small quantities minted for sets only
|-
|}

== Future changes to national sides ==
The Commission of the European Communities issued a recommendation on 19 December 2008, a common guideline for the national sides and the issuance of euro coins intended for circulation. One section of this recommendation stipulates that:

:'''Article 4. Design of the national sides:'''
::&quot;''The national side of the euro coins intended for circulation should bear the 12 European stars that should fully surround the national design, including the year mark and the indication of the issuing Member State's name. The European stars should be depicted as on the European flag.''&quot;

Since Slovenian euro coins place the indication of the member's name alongside the 12 stars of the union, a new design on the Slovenian euro coins is expected in the near future to comply with these new guidelines, although nothing has officially been announced yet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ibiblio.org/theeuro/forum/viewtopic.php?f=3&amp;t=413 | title=Recommendation of 19 December 2008 on common guidelines for the national side of euro coins | publisher=The Euro Information Website | date=14 January 2009 | accessdate=14 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==€2 commemorative coins==
{{main|€2 commemorative coins}}

==Other commemorative coins (Collector's coins)==
{{main|Euro gold and silver commemorative coins (Slovenia)}}
{{main|Euro gold and silver commemorative coins}}
Slovenia joined the Eurozone on January 1, 2007. In such a short time they already built a small collection of collectors coins, with face value ranging from 3 to 100 euro.  Although they are all legal tender in Slovenia, these coins are not really intended to be used as means of payment, so generally they do not circulate (the only exception is the 3 euro coins which can be found in circulation although rarely). Here you can find some samples from the series &quot;Presidency of the European Union&quot;:

==Selection Process for the National Side==
The first stage of the selection process started in April 2004, involving preliminary discussions with numismatists, designers and experts. The general public was also invited through the mass media to participate in a public tender concerning proposals of motifs (132 tenderers proposed 699 motifs). A special expert commission (9 different individual experts and members of different institutions, including the Ministry of Finance and the Bank of Slovenia) dealt with the proposals and the process. The second stage of selection started when the Government of the Republic of Slovenia confirmed the commission's decision that invitations would be addressed to some prominent designers for the production of designs.

The commission invited five well-known Slovene designers. A special jury of reputable Slovene artists, designers, professors and connoisseurs of Slovene cultural heritage was appointed to review and assess the designs submitted for the Slovene euro coins. The commission of the Bank of Slovenia and Ministry of Finance unanimously agreed with the proposed selected designs prepared by Mr Miljenko Licul, along with Ms Maja Licul and Mr Janez Boljka. The Government of the Republic of Slovenia gave their consent and adopted the decision on 28 July 2005 to submit the selected design proposals for the national side of the Slovene euro coins to ECOFIN (Economic and Financial Committee) - Coins Sub-Committee, which acknowledged the compliance of the Slovene design proposals with European legislation on 5 October 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.evro.si/en/slo-and-euro/slovene-euro-coins/ | title=Slovene euro coins on the official website of the Slovenian adoption of the euro}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Controversy==
The use of the [[Prince's Stone]] ({{lang-sl|Knežji kamen}}, {{lang-de|Fürstenstein}}) on the 2-cent coin caused a minor political stir in the [[Carinthia (state)|Austrian State of Carinthia]]. The stone, a fragment of an ancient Roman column from nearby [[Virunum]] that was used in the ritual of installing the princes of [[Carantania]] and later of the [[Carinthia (duchy)|Duchy of Carinthia]], is kept in a museum in [[Klagenfurt]] (Slovene: Celovec), the Carinthian capital, where it is also considered a historical icon of the state. The Carinthian state government (headed by governor [[Jörg Haider]]) issued a resolution of protest on 25 October 2005, which was rejected as &quot;not to be taken seriously&quot; by the then Slovenian foreign minister, [[Dimitrij Rupel]]. However, there were also objections against its use on the Slovene side. On academic grounds, for instance, [[Peter Štih]], professor of history at the Ljubljana University and member of the Slovene Academy of Sciences, argued that the Prince's Stone cannot be considered a Slovenian but rather a Carinthian historic symbol.{{Citation needed|date=October 2008}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Euro coins (Slovenia)|Slovenian euro coins}}
{{wikinews|Slovenia adopts euro}}
*[http://www.bsi.si/library/includes/datoteka.asp?DatotekaId=1715 The effigies of the new Slovene euro coins] (from the Bank of Slovenia)
*[http://www.evro.si/en/slo-and-euro/slovene-euro-coins/ Slovene euro coins on the official website of the Slovenian adoption of the euro]
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/theeuro/files/files.nat/slovenia.s01.htm The Euro Information Website – Slovenia]

{{Euro topics}}

[[Category:Coins of the Eurozone]]
[[Category:Economy of Slovenia]]
[[Category:Slovenia and the European Union|Euro]]

[[frp:Piéces en erô de la Slovènie]]
[[bar:Slowénische Euromünzn]]
[[bs:Slovenske euro kovanice]]
[[cs:Slovinské euromince]]
[[cy:Darnau ewro Slofenia]]
[[de:Slowenische Euromünzen]]
[[et:Sloveenia euromündid]]
[[el:Σλοβενικά κέρματα ευρώ]]
[[es:Monedas de euro de Eslovenia]]
[[eo:Slovenaj eŭro-moneroj]]
[[ext:Moneas d'euru d'Eslovénia]]
[[eu:Esloveniako euro txanponak]]
[[fr:Pièces en euro de la Slovénie]]
[[ko:슬로베니아의 유로 동전]]
[[hr:Slovenske euro kovanice]]
[[it:Monete euro slovene]]
[[lb:Slowenesch Euromënzen]]
[[hu:Szlovén euróérmék]]
[[nl:Sloveense euromunten]]
[[ja:スロベニアのユーロ硬貨]]
[[no:Slovenske euromynter]]
[[pms:Monede Euro dla Slovenia]]
[[pl:Słoweńskie monety euro]]
[[pt:Moedas de euro eslovenas]]
[[ro:Monedele euro slovene]]
[[ru:Монеты евро Словении]]
[[sk:Slovinské euromince]]
[[sl:Slovenski evrokovanci]]
[[sh:Slovenske euro kovanice]]
[[fi:Slovenialaiset eurokolikot]]
[[sv:Slovenska euromynt]]
[[uk:Словенські монети євро]]
[[zh:斯洛維尼亞的歐元硬幣]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
