<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2864205" ns="0" title="La Raza Cósmica"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=October 2010}}
{{No footnotes|date=November 2010}}
Published in 1925, '''''La Raza Cósmica''''' (''The Cosmic Race'') is an essay written by late [[Mexico|Mexican]] [[philosopher]], secretary of education, and 1929 presidential candidate, [[José Vasconcelos]] to express the ideology of a future &quot;fifth [[Race (classification of human beings)|race]]&quot; in the [[Americas]]; an agglomeration of all the races in the world with no respect to color or number to erect a new civilization: ''Universópolis''. As he explains in his literary work, armies of people would then go forth around the world professing their knowledge. Vasconcelos continues to say that the people of the [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberian]] regions of the Americas (that is to say, the parts of the continent colonised by [[Portugal]] and [[Spain]]) have the territorial, racial, and spiritual factors necessary to initiate the &quot;universal era of humanity&quot;. As a form of [[race of the future|futuristic race]], the people would have major influences from [[Mongoloid]]s (native Amerindians), [[white people|Caucasians]] (colonizing Europeans), and [[Negroids]] (black slaves).

Claiming that the [[Social Darwinism|Darwinist]] ideologies are &quot;scientific&quot; theories only created to validate, explain, and justify ethnic superiority and to repress others, Vasconcelos attempts to refute these theories and goes on to recognize his words as being an ideological effort to improve the cultural morale of a &quot;depressed race&quot; by offering his optimistic theory of the future development of a cosmic race.

==Usage of phrase==
The phrase, &quot;''La raza cósmica''&quot;, in English &quot;the cosmic race&quot;, embodies the notion that traditional, exclusive concepts of race and nationality can be transcended in the name of humanity's common [[destiny]]. It originally referred to a movement by Mexican intellectuals during the 1920s{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}} who pointed out that [[Latin America]]ns have the blood of all the world's races ([[White people|White Europeans]], [[Asian people|Asian]]-descended [[Indigenous peoples of the Americas|Native-Americans]] and [[Black people|Black Africans]]), transcending the peoples of the &quot;old world&quot;.

Vasconcelos also used the term when he coined the National Autonomous University of Mexico's motto: &quot;''Por mi raza hablará el espíritu''&quot;.

It has come, often in its shortened version &quot;''[[La Raza]]''&quot;, to refer to the [[multiracial|mixed race people]] of [[Latin America]], i.e., primarily [[mestizo]]s, [[mulatto]]s, and [[zambo]]s or all three combined. Vasconcelos also used the expression, &quot;''la raza de [[Bronze (color)|bronce]]''&quot; (&quot;the [[Bronze race]]&quot;), in this same sense.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
{{dablink|See [[La Raza]] for other uses of the phrase.}}

==See also==
*[[Chicano]]
*[[Hispanic]]
*[[Latino]]
*[[Mexican American]]
*[[Mestizo]]
*[[Mulatto]]
*[[Multiracial]]
*[[Race (classification of human beings)#In Brazil|Race in Brazil]]
*[[Race (United States Census)]]
*[[Race of the Future]]

==References==
José Vasconselos, ''La Raza Cósmica'' (Mexico D.F., Espasa Calpe, S.A., 1948), 47-51

== External links ==
* [http://www.filosofia.org/aut/001/razacos.htm La Raza Cósmica Misión de la raza iberoamericana Notas de viajes a la América del SurAgencia Mundial de Librería, Madrid 1925] (Spanish)

{{DEFAULTSORT:La Raza Cosmica}}
[[Category:Spanish language|Raza]]
[[Category:Latin American culture]]
[[Category:Politics and race]]

[[de:Kosmische Rasse]]
[[es:La raza cósmica]]
[[fr:La Raza Cósmica]]
[[he:הגזע הקוסמי]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
