<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28667119" ns="0" title="Gay Nigger Association of America"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-semi|small=yes}}
{{Infobox organization
|name = Gay Nigger Association of America
|image = Gnaa-logo.png
|image_border =
|size = 300px
|alt = Gay Nigger Association of America
|caption = Gay Nigger Association of America
|abbreviation = GNAA
|type = [[Internet Trolls]]
|formation = 2002&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot; /&gt;
|years_active = 2002—
|leader_title = President
|leader_name = paz&lt;ref name=&quot;president&quot; /&gt;
|headquarters = [[Tarzana, Los Angeles]]&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot; /&gt;
|affiliations = [[Goatse Security]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;rohr&quot; /&gt;
|website = [http://www.gnaa.eu/ GNAA Corporate Website]
}}

The '''Gay Nigger Association of America''' (often referred to as the '''GNAA''') is an anti-[[blogging]] [[Internet trolling]] organization that takes their name from the 1992 Danish movie ''[[Gayniggers from Outer Space]]''. They have trolled several prominent websites and Internet commentators, including members of the [[blogosphere]], [[Slashdot]], [[Wikipedia]], and [[CNN]]. They have also released software products and leaked information about operating systems. In addition, they maintain a wiki-based site dedicated to Internet commentary in a style parodying Slashdot posts and offer a [[Apache Subversion|Subversion]]-based software repository containing various GNAA coding projects.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | title = FreeNode, allarme sicurezza | date = 2006-06-28 | url = http://punto-informatico.it/1544690/PI/News/freenode-allarme-sicurezza.aspx | work = PuntoInformatico | accessdate = 2011-08-26 | language = Italian | quote = Qualcuno ipotizza che la GNAA, un gruppo di buontemponi nato su Slashdot e dedito allo spamming, abbia firmato questo assalto.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Members of the GNAA also founded [[Goatse Security]], a [[grey hat]] information security group. Members of Goatse Security released information in June 2010 about a vulnerability located on [[AT&amp;T]]'s website that notably affected the privacy of people who pre-ordered the [[iPad]]. After the information was released, the then-president of the GNAA, [[weev]], and GNAA member &quot;JacksonBrown&quot; were arrested.

==Origins and purpose==
The group claims to have been founded in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot; /&gt; Little is known about the group's structure. New media researcher [[Andrew Lih]] has claimed that it is unclear whether there was initially a clearly defined group of GNAA members, or if founding members of the GNAA were online troublemakers united under the name in order to disrupt websites.&lt;ref name=&quot;nobodies&quot; /&gt;

The group's name has been controversial, having been described as causing &quot;immediate alarm in anyone with a semblance of good taste&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;nobodies&quot; /&gt; and as being &quot;spectacularly offensive.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;scotsman&quot; /&gt; However, the group claims that it promotes neither racism nor homophobia. GNAA members deny allegations of actual racism, implying that these statements are made only to elicit angry responses and to subvert or otherwise challenge long-standing social [[Norm (sociology)|norms]], and note that the name of the organization came from the 1992 Danish satirical [[blaxploitation]] film ''Gayniggers from Outer Space''.&lt;ref name=&quot;GLS&quot; /&gt;

==Trolling==
The GNAA uses several methods of trolling. One method involves flooding weblogs with a massive amount of repeated words and phrases, referred to as &quot;crapflooding&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GLS&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scotsman&quot; /&gt; They have also produced shock sites containing [[malware]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GLS&quot; /&gt; One such site, &quot;Last Measure&quot;, contained malware that opened up pop-up windows containing shocking pictures.&lt;ref name=&quot;porndotcom&quot; /&gt; On Wikipedia, members of the group created a page about themselves, while adhering to every rule of Wikipedia in order to use the system against itself.&lt;ref name=&quot;nobodies&quot; /&gt;

They have also attacked several [[Internet Relay Chat]] channels using [[Internet Relay Chat flood|IRC flooding]]. GNAA used an old but obscure method to force users of the [[Freenode]] network to execute disruptive commands after visiting websites containing malware.&lt;ref name=&quot;ffbug&quot; /&gt; They also have used bugs in [[Firefox]] to crapflood IRC channels.&lt;ref name=&quot;netwerk&quot; /&gt; They have also performed [[proof of concept]] demonstrations.&lt;ref name=&quot;IRC&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;obamabug&quot; /&gt; These actions have occasionally interrupted the normal operation of popular websites such as Slashdot, even forcing some websites (such as [[4chan]]) to shut down temporarily.&lt;ref name=&quot;4chan&quot; /&gt;

In [[July 2004]], two GNAA members submitted leaked [[screenshot]]s of the forthcoming [[operating system]] [[Mac OS X v10.4]] to the popular [[Apple Computer|Apple]] [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]] news website [[MacRumors]], which read &quot;With [[Worldwide Developers Conference|WWDC]] just days away, the first Tiger information and screenshots appears to have been leaked.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | title = Wie typisch | date = 06/28/2004 | url = http://www.macnews.de/software/wie-typisch-39507 | work = macnews.de | accessdate = 2011-08-26 | quote = Die Screenshots stammten allesamt aus einer Quelle: Einer merkwürdigen Anti-Slashdot-Organisation namens GNAA.}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to sources, Apple will reportedly provide developers with a Mac OS X 10.4 preview copy at WWDC on Monday. The screenshots provided reportedly come from this upcoming developer preview.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;macrumors-tiger&quot; /&gt; Later, when accusations were raised that the images were fabricated, the GNAA released a press release which claimed that the screenshots were genuine and stated that they had &quot;trolled&quot; the Apple community.&lt;ref name=&quot;gnaatiger&quot; /&gt;

In [[June 2005]], the GNAA claimed to have created a [[Mac OS X]] Tiger release for [[Intel x86]] processors which caught media attention from various sources.&lt;ref name=&quot;macdailynews&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wild&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cultofmac&quot; /&gt; The next day, the supposed leak and was mentioned on the [[G4 (television)|G4]] show ''[[Attack of the Show!|Attack of the Show]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;aots&quot; /&gt; The DVD image released via [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] merely booted an image of [[Goatse|hello.jpg]]&lt;ref name=&quot;rubygoldmine&quot; /&gt; instead of the leaked operating system as many were led to believe.&lt;ref name=&quot;bandwagon&quot; /&gt;

On February 3, 2007, the GNAA successfully convinced CNN reporter [[Paula Zahn]] that &quot;one in three Americans&quot; believe the [[September 11, 2001]] terror attacks were carried out by Israeli agents.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN3&quot; /&gt; CNN subsequently ran a story, erroneously reporting this, including screenshots of the GNAA-owned website &quot;jewsdidwtc.com.&quot; The story involved a round-table discussion regarding antisemitism and an interview with the father of a Jewish 9/11 victim.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN2&quot; /&gt; The GNAA-owned website included claims that &quot;over 4,000&quot; Jews were absent from work at the World Trade Center on 9/11.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN2&quot; /&gt;

==Goatse Security==
[[File:Goatse Security Logo.png|thumb|Goatse Security logo]]
{{Main|Goatse Security}}
Several members of the GNAA with expertise in grey-hat&lt;ref name=&quot;ipadsec&quot; /&gt; security research began releasing information about security vulnerabilities under the name &quot;Goatse Security.&quot; They chose a new name to publish their work under because they were worried that their work would not get noticed if published by the &quot;Gay Nigger Association of America.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dailytech&quot; /&gt;

In June 2010, Goatse Security attracted mainstream media attention for their disclosure of 114,000 [[email address]]es&lt;ref name=&quot;npripad&quot; /&gt; registered to Apple iPad devices for early adopters of Apple's 3G iPad service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sapo&quot; /&gt; The data was aggregated from AT&amp;T's own servers by feeding a publicly available script with [[HTTP request]]s containing randomly generated [[ICC-ID]]s, which would then return the associated email address. The [[FBI]] soon investigated the incident. This investigation led to the arrest of then-GNAA President,&lt;ref name=&quot;courtcase&quot; /&gt; Andrew 'weev' Auernheimer, on unrelated [[Drug possession|drug charges]]&lt;ref name=&quot;assassination&quot; /&gt; resulting from an FBI search of his house.&lt;ref name=&quot;dailytech&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnetdrugs&quot; /&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Internet}}
* [[Patriotic Nigras]]

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 |title=About GNAA:
 |url=http://www.gnaa.eu/wiki/about
 |publisher=GNAA
 |accessdate=10 June 2011}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;president&quot;&gt;
 {{Cite press release
 | title = New GNAA President paz is Elected
 | publisher = GNAA
 | date = August 28, 2011
 | url = http://www.gnaa.eu/wiki/pr/2011-08-28-gnaa-paz
 | accessdate = 2011-08-31}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Atlantic&quot;&gt;{{cite news
 | first = Niraj
 | last = Chokshi
 | title = Meet One of the Hackers Who Exposed the iPad Security Leak
 | date = 2010-06-10
 | publisher = [[Atlantic Media Company]]
 | url = http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2010/06/meet-one-of-the-hackers-who-exposed-the-ipad-security-leak/57969/
 | work = [[The Atlantic]]
 | accessdate = 2011-02-25
 | quote = Weev rails against Jews in his LiveJournal and he and several other members of Goatse Security claim to be members of the Gay N***** Association of America. In an oddly generous literary reference, Forbes has described him as a modern Shakesperian Puck. Make of that what you will.}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;rohr&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
 | first = Altieres
 | last = Rohr
 | title = Saiba como ocorreu falha que expôs e-mails de 114 mil usuários do iPad
 | date = 2010-06-11
 | url = http://g1.globo.com/tecnologia/noticia/2010/06/entenda-como-foi-falha-que-expos-e-mails-de-114-mil-usuarios-do-ipad.html
 | work = [[Rede Globo]]
 | language = Portuguese
 | accessdate = 2010-09-13
 | quote = “weev”, um dos integrantes do grupo, já foi citado em outras matérias do grupo Gawker Media, que deu a notícia como “exclusiva”. Ele, assim como outros membros, faz parte da GNAA, a “Associação de Gays Negros da América”. São pessoas que passam boa parte do tempo on-line tentando realizar “trotes” ou trolls. Entre os membros do grupo, e um dos principais da GNAA, está um desenvolvedor do Linux Debian. O “ex presidente” da GNAA, timecop, é conhecido na internet por fazer parte do Dattebayo – fãs que realizaram traduções dos desenhos japoneses Naruto e Bleach. Translation: weev, one of the members of the group, has been quoted by Gawker Media, which broke the news as exclusive. He, like other members, is part of the GNAA, the Gay Nigger Association of America. These are people who spend much of their time online trolling and carrying out practical jokes. One of the principal members of the GNAA is a developer of Linux Debian. The ex-president of the GNAA, timecop, is known on the internet for being part of Dattebayo, a group of fans who translated the Japanese cartoons Naruto and Bleach.}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;GLS&quot;&gt;{{cite conference
 | first = Jodi
 | last = Dean
 | authorlink = Jodi Dean
 | title = Blog Theory: Feedback and Capture in the Circuits of Drive.
 | publisher = {{nowrap|[http://www.polity.co.uk/ Polity Press]}}
 | date = 2010
 | ISBN = 9780745649702
 | location = [[Cambridge, UK]]
 | url = http://books.google.com/books?id=3wWGIvVS8JAC&amp;lpg=PR5&amp;ots=k3M2mFeTUh&amp;dq=%22gay%20nigger%20association%22&amp;lr&amp;pg=PA6#v=onepage&amp;q=%22gay%20nigger%20association%22&amp;f=false
 | accessdate = 2010-08-27
 | quote= Then I got a comment from the GNAA or Gay Nigger Association of America, a group of organized anti-blogging trolls who take their name from a 1992 Danish movie, ''Gay-Niggers from Outerspace''. GNAA claims that it promotes neither racism nor homophobia but aims rather to sow disruption on the internet. The comment on my blog was a minor instance of their more extensive disruptive practices (like &quot;crapflooding&quot; a site with a massive amount of text or data with no meaning or relevance: for example, a word, phrase, or group of letters repeated over and over, or producing hoax or shock sites and inserting links or code that redirect viewers to the site). }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;macrumors-tiger&quot;&gt;[http://www.macrumors.com/2004/06/26/mac-os-x-10-4-tiger-screenshots/ Mac OS X 10.4 (Tiger) Screenshots?]. [[Macrumors|MacRumors]]. Accessed 2010-08-27.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;rubygoldmine&quot;&gt;[http://gizmodo.com/gadgets/laptops-pcs/macindell-part-quatre-the-ruby-goldmine-107940.php MacInDell Part Quatre – The Ruby Goldmine]. [[Gizmodo]]. Accessed 2010-08-27.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN3&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Deepthi | last = Welaratna | title = Terror! Conspiracy! Hoax! | date = 2007-04-06 | publisher = [[KQED (TV)|KQED]] | url = http://www.kqed.org/arts/multimedia/article.jsp?essid=15142 | work = KQED Arts | accessdate = 2011-03-18 | quote = The conspiracy theory – found in crevices on the Internet – claims Jews are behind the 9/11 attacks. Surprise! Farfetched anti-Semitic theories abound online! The actual ugly truth here is that CNN uses the parody conspiracy site jewsdidwtc.com as a LEGITIMATE source for the piece, proof of the legions out there who buy into this theory. A cursory click through the site, aided by a sense of humor, quickly makes it clear that this is a joke site, particularly as it is owned and run by the GNAA (visit at your own peril – contains humor some will find distasteful and NSFW). The blunder made all kinds of news online, on Slashdot, Something Awful and Digg. Mostly saying ha ha, the GNAA trolls CNN. The ultimate troll, LOLZ!! It's true, it's hilarious, but it's also very very sad. Neither Boston nor CNN officials are willing to admit their mistakes}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;IRC&quot;&gt;[http://www.theregister.co.uk/2010/01/30/firefox_interprotocol_attack/ Firefox-based attack wreaks havoc on IRC users] [[The Register]]. Accessed 2010-08-27&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;julia&quot;&gt;[http://gawker.com/380138/julia-allisons-blog-is-hacked Julia Allison's Blog Is Hacked]. [[Gawker]]. Accessed 2010-08-27.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;bridge&quot;&gt;[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:eHYOyInYjUEJ:www.msa.monash.edu.au/documents/lotswife/LotsWifeEditionSix2010.pdf+filetype:pdf+GNAA+%2Bgay&amp;cd=25&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us&amp;client=firefox-a UNDER THE BRIDGE]. [[Monash University]]. Accessed 2010-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;twitterprotest&quot;&gt;[http://www.asylum.com/2010/01/29/westboro-baptist-church-protests-gets-protested-outside-twitter/ Twitter Protest]. [[Asylum]]. Access 2010-08-28&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;liberation&quot;&gt;[http://adterrasperaspera.com/blog/2006/06/28/the-liberation-of-freenode-part-13/ The Liberation of Freenode, Part 13]. Patrick McFarland. Accessed 2010-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt; XXX (Not a [[WP:RS|reliable source]]) XXX--&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ffbug&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Lucian | last = Constantin | title = Firefox Bug Used to Harass Entire IRC Network | date = 2010-01-30 | url = http://news.softpedia.com/news/Firefox-Bug-Used-to-Harass-an-Entire-IRC-Network-133613.shtml | work = [[Softpedia]] | accessdate = 2011-03-17 | quote = A group of self-declared Internet trolls, called the GNAA, has used an old but obscure attack method to wreak havoc on the Freenode IRC network. Users were forced to execute IRC commands after visiting maliciously crafted Web pages.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;netwerk&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Sander | last = van der Meijs | title = Bug in Firefox gebruikt tegen IRC netwerk | date = 2010-02-01 | publisher = IDG Netherlands | url = http://webwereld.nl/nieuws/84529/bug-in-firefox-gebruikt-tegen-irc-netwerk.html | work = [[:nl:Webwereld|Webwereld]] | accessdate = 2011-03-17 | language = Dutch | quote = Een groep die zichzelf de GNAA noemt heeft voor grote problemen gezorgd bij een IRC netwerk. Ze gebruikten een bug in Firefox om het netwerk te spammen. Translation: A group that calls itself the GNAA has caused major problems in an IRC network. They used a bug in Firefox for the network to spam.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;obamabug&quot;&gt;[http://techcrunch.com/2007/02/11/very-bad-bug-a-barackobamacom/ Very Ugly Bug at BarackObama.com]. [[TechCrunch]]. Accessed 2010-08-27.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;nobodies&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
 | last1 = Lih
 | first1 = Andrew
 | authorlink = Andrew Lih
 | title = [[The Wikipedia Revolution|The Wikipedia Revolution: How a Bunch of Nobodies Created the World's Greatest Encyclopedia]]
 | publisher = Hyperion
 | date = 17 Mar 2009
 | location = Cambridge, UK
 | pages = 170–171
 | accessdate = 2010-07-27
 | quote= What were some ways to troll and cause trouble? Create an article about something extremely controversial and offensive, but otherwise adhere to every rule of Wikipedia and use the system against itself. This was the case with creating an article that had an intentionally offensive name, the Gay Niggers Association of America. GNAA was a name that caused immediate alarm in anyone with a semblance of good taste. It was a phenomenon for many years in the online tech communities, as legions of trolls attempted to have an article in Wikipedia about the mischievous group. It's not clear a defined group ever existed as GNAA. Supposed GNAA &quot;members&quot; were simply troublemakers online who unified under a common moniker in an effort to disrupt Wikipedia for amusement.
 | isbn = 1400110769}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;porndotcom&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
| title = Porn.com: making sense of online pornography
| publisher = Peter Lang
| accessdate = 2011-03-20
| isbn = 1433102072
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=RNprMCakFf8C&amp;pg=PA137
| last7 = Attwood
| first1 = Feona
| year = 2010
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;gnaatiger&quot;&gt;
{{Cite press release
 | title = GNAA Leaks Info about Apple's Next Major OS
 | publisher = GNAA
 | date = June 26, 2004
 | url = http://www.gnaa.eu/wiki/pr/2004-06-26-gnaa-tiger
 | accessdate = 2010-09-06}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;macdailynews&quot;&gt;[http://macdailynews.com/index.php/weblog/comments/6012/ Report: Apple Mac OS X 10.4.1 for Intel hits piracy sites]. Accessed 2010-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;wild&quot;&gt;[http://www.engadget.com/2005/06/12/os-x-for-x86-already-in-the-wild/ OS X for x86 already in the wild?]. Accessed 2010-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;cultofmac&quot;&gt;[http://www.wired.com/gadgets/mac/commentary/cultofmac/2005/08/68501 Mac Hacks Allow OS X on PCs]. Wired. Accessed 2010-09-08.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;aots&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode
| title = Attack of the Show!
| series = Attack of the Show!
| network = G4
| station = G4
| airdate = June 2005}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN2&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode
 | title = Paula Zahn Now
 | series = Paula Zahn Now
 | network = CNN
 | station = CNN
 | airdate = February 3, 2007
 | transcripturl = http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0701/30/pzn.01.html
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;bandwagon&quot;&gt;[http://www.tuaw.com/2005/08/12/jumping-on-the-bandwagon-os-x-on-x86-omg/ Jumping on the bandwagon: OS X on x86! OMG!]. [[TUAW]]. Accessed 2010-09-07.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ipadsec&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/06/11/AR2010061106239_2.html Apple's iPad security breach reveals vulnerability of mobile devices]. [[Washington Post]]. Accessed 2010-09-02.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;sapo&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title = Falha de segurança que expõe donos do iPad investigada pelo FBI | date = 2010-06-11 | publisher = [[Sapo.pt]] | url = http://tek.sapo.pt/noticias/computadores/falha_de_seguranca_que_expoe_donos_do_ipad_in_1070542.html | work = tek | accessdate = 2011-03-17 | language = Portuguese | quote = A falha foi identificada pelo grupo Goatse Security , que pertence à GNAA (associação norte americana de gays e negros). Translation: The flaw was identified by the group Goatse Security, which belongs to the GNAA (Gay Nigger Association of America).}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;npripad&quot;&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=127747618 Apple's iPad Breach Raises Alarms]. [[NPR]]. Accessed 2010-09-06.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;cnetdrugs&quot;&gt;[http://news.cnet.com/8301-27080_3-20007827-245.html Hacker in AT&amp;T-iPad security case arrested on drug charges]. CNET. Accessed 2010-09-01.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;dailytech&quot;&gt;
{{cite interview
 |last=Kaiser
 |first=Leon
 |interviewer=Mick, Jason
 |title=Interview: Goatse Security on FBI Charges Following AT&amp;T iPad Breach
 |url=http://www.dailytech.com/Interview+Goatse+Security+on+FBI+Charges+Following+ATT+iPad+Breach/article20693.htm
 |format=Transcript
 |program=[[DailyTech]]
 |date=2011-01-19
 |accessdate=2011-01-21}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Jesse | last = Emspak | title = The Case Against The iPad Hackers | date = 2011-01-19 | url = http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/102701/20110119/case-against-ipad-hackers.htm | work = [[International Business Times]] | accessdate = 2011-03-19 | quote = 14. The Goatse Security website describes defendant Auernheimer as having &quot;[e]xtensive offensive web app vuln and business logic exploitation experience. Bash while drunk, perl while tripping, Ruby while living in SF SoMa. Representing anti sec, Bantown and Encyclopedia Drarnatica. President of the GNAA.&quot; Defendant Spitler is described as an &quot;embedded and mobile devices engineer. PPC assembly. GNAA, obviously.&quot; The Goatse Security website provides a hyperlink to the GNAA website. 15. The GNAA website states that &quot;[t]his website is maintained by the GNAA, world-famous trolling organization.&quot; The GNAA website provides hyperlinks to the Goatse Security website, as well as defendant Auernheimer's LiveJournal weblog.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;scotsman&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = STEWART | last = KIRKPATRICK | title = Lazy Guide to Net Culture: Dark side of the rainbow | date = 2005-11-22 | publisher = [[The Scotsman]] | url = http://news.scotsman.com/scitech/Lazy-Guide-to-Net-Culture.2680539.jp | work = news.scotsman.com | accessdate = 2011-03-20 | quote = Such people include trolling organisations. These are individuals who delight in flooding web bulletin boards with crass and offensive comments (aka &quot;crapflooding&quot;). One such group goes under the spectacularly offensive name of the &quot;Gay Nigger Association&quot; – revealing themselves to be insecure white kids who have worries about their own orientation.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;courtcase&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/48143653/Spitler-Daniel-et-al-Complaint
 |title=United States of America v. Daniel Spitler and Andrew Aurenheimer}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Not overly familiar with how I'd cite this court document, any help? --&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;4chan&quot;&gt;
{{cite web
 |last=Poole
 |first=Christopher
 |title=DING DONG, 4CHAN IS DEAD
 |url=http://www.4chan.org/news/?all#53
 |publisher=4chan
 |accessdate=10 June 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;assassination&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
 |title=Digital Assassination: Protecting Your Reputation, Brand, Or Business
 |year=2011
 |publisher=Macmillan
 |isbn=9780312617912
 |page=116
 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=-lY4ZmDEA2sC
 |author=Richard Torrenzano, Mark W. Davis
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.gnaa.eu/}}
* [http://gayniggers.blogspot.com/ Blog]
* [http://security.goatse.fr/ Goatse Security]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gay Nigger Association Of America}}
[[Category:Critics of Wikipedia]]
[[Category:Internet trolling]]
[[Category:Organizations established in 2002]]
[[Category:Slashdot]]
[[Category:Hacking (computer security)]]
[[Category:2002 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Organizations based in California]]
[[Category:Internet culture]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
