<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Al-Gama&#039;a" to="Al-Gama&#039;a (TV series)" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="28676767" ns="0" title="Al-Gama&#039;a (TV series)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">
{{Infobox television
| show_name      = Al-Gama'a
| image          = [[File:Al-Gama'a.jpg|250px]]
| caption        = Al-Gama'a &lt;br /&gt; الجماعة
| genre          = [[Drama]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Historical drama film|Historical]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Political drama]]
| runtime        = 39 - 43 minutes
| creator        = [[Wahid Hamid]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Mohammad Yasin]]
| starring       = [[Iyad Nassar]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Hassan El Raddad]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Ezzat Alayli]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Abdul Aziz Mckheon]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Yosra El Lozy]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Sawsan Badr]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Salah Abdullah]] &lt;br /&gt; [[Sami Meghawri]]
| picture_format =
| country        = [[Egypt]]
| language       = [[Arabic language|Arabic]]
| company        =
| network        =
| first_aired    = {{Start date|2010|8|11}}
| last_aired     = present
| num_seasons    = 1
| num_episodes   = 28
| list_episodes  =
| website        =
| related        =
}}

'''Al-Gama'a''' ({{lang-ar|الجماعة}} ''{{transl|ar|DIN|al-Ǧamāʿah}}'', {{IPA-arz|elɡæˈmæːʕæ|IPA}}, &quot;the society/group&quot;) is an   [[Egypt]]ian [[Drama]], [[Historical drama film|Historical]] and [[Political drama]] series written by [[Wahid Hamid]], directed by [[Mohammed Yasin]] and produced by [[Kamel Abu Ali]]. The series began filming in January 2010 with a budget of 50 million Egyptian pounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egyptian Censorship allows the series ''Al-Gama'a'' without any comments&quot;&gt;[http://www.egypty.com/art-details.aspx?art=5255 Egyptian Censorship allows the series ''Al-Gama'a'' without any comments]&lt;/ref&gt; The show deals with the rise of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], Egypt’s largest [[Islamist|Islamist political group]], which is officially banned but nonetheless tolerated to an extent. Critics have decried the show's pro-government stance, charging that it plays into the Egyptian government's agenda prior to the [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2010|2010 Egyptian parliamentary elections]].&lt;ref name=&quot;It is tradition that makes holy month memorable&quot;&gt;[http://www.thenational.ae/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20100828/WEEKENDER/708279835/1080/NATIONAL It is tradition that makes holy month memorable]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Production==
The series was filmed in the [[Egyptian Media Production City|Media Production City]] and in [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]] in [[Cairo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Egyptian Censorship allows the series ''Al-Gama'a'' without any comments&quot; /&gt; and several other Egyptian governorates.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.masreat.com/%D9%85%D8%B3%D9%84%D8%B3%D9%84-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%AC%D9%85%D8%A7%D8%B9%D8%A9/ Al-Gama'a (TV series) - the largest Artistic work done about the Muslim Brotherhood]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Series synopsis==
=== Season 1 ===
The show begins with Muslim Brotherhood student demonstrations at [[Al-Azhar University]] and [[Cairo University]] campuses in protest of vote rigging in the 2006 student union elections. At Al-Azhar, demonstrators hold a military-like parade that causes controversy as many observers question the group's claim of renouncing violence. Upon their arrest, the Muslim Brotherhood student suspects are interviewed by a police officers. One of the police officers ('''Ashraf Helal''') refuses to interview them because he knows nothing about them. Helal looks for books about the Muslim Brotherhood but finds that there are too many about the subject. Later, he meets an old female friend ('''Shirin''') and tells her about his station. She suggest that he talks to her grandfather ('''Chancellor Abdallah Kassab'''), who gives Helal a list of books to read about the Muslim Brotherhood and its founder, '''[[Hasan al-Banna]]'''. The show then depicts Hasan al-Banna's life, from his childhood to the banning of the Muslim Brotherhood in 1948. During the season, the show jumps back and forth between Al-Banna's time and the present time.

==Cast and characters==
{{Empty section|date=September 2010}}

==Reception==
=== Criticism and controversy ===
{{Expand section|date=September 2010}}

Critics of the show, led by Al-Banna's son Saif Al-Islam, have accused the series' scriptwriter Wahid Hamed of defamation, making false claims and attempting to distort the image of his father and the group as extremists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramadan series rock the boat&quot;&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=185820 Ramadan series rock the boat]&lt;/ref&gt;

Saif Al-Islam Al-Banna called for the show to be banned and demanded a copy of the script to revise it and make sure it conforms to the facts of his father's life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brotherhood founder's son files lawsuit against TV series writer, producers&quot; /&gt;

{{Quotation|
'''&quot;I sent [those in charge of the TV series] a warning last week, calling on them to suspend the broadcast and give me a copy of the script to revise. But when they did not respond, I filed the lawsuit against them a few days later&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramadan series rock the boat&quot; /&gt;'''|Saif Al-Islam Hassan al-Banna|Hassan Al-Banna’s son
}}

Saif Al-Islam filed a lawsuit against Wahid Hamed and the Egyptian television stations that broadcast the program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brotherhood founder's son files lawsuit against TV series writer, producers&quot;&gt;[http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=122293&amp;catid=1&amp;Itemid=183 Brotherhood founder's son files lawsuit against TV series writer, producers]&lt;/ref&gt; The Cairo Economic Court looked into the lawsuit filed against the scriptwriter of the TV series and its producer, the [[Egyptian Radio and Television Union]] (ERTU).&lt;ref name=&quot;Brotherhood founder's son files lawsuit against TV series writer, producers&quot; /&gt;

{{Quotation|
'''&quot;The damage of distorting his (Al-Banna’s) history hurts all Islamic movements, as well as his family&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramadan series rock the boat&quot; /&gt;'''|Saif Al-Islam Hassan al-Banna|Hassan Al-Banna’s son
}}

The Muslim Brotherhood argues that the series depicts them as a violent, fundamentalist group, whose leaders are deceptive businessmen merely hungry for authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brotherhood founder's son files lawsuit against TV series writer, producers&quot; /&gt; The Muslim Brotherhood quickly decided to retaliate by producing its own series portraying the movement's history. &quot;''Hassan Al-Banna: '''The Journey Did Not End'''''&quot; is a 32-episode series to be filmed immediately after [[Ramadan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ramadan series rock the boat&quot; /&gt;

The government of [[Hosni Mubarak]] has been accused of influencing the series to present the Brotherhood in a thoroughly negative light (and conversely to present the Egyptian regime, particularly the [[State Security Intelligence Service|State Security apparatus]], in a thoroughly positive light) ahead of the [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2010|Egyptian parliamentary elections of 28 November 2010]], in which the Brotherhood forms the larges opposition bloc to the ruling [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/news/tv-show-muslim-brotherhood-stirs-outrage |title= TV show on Muslim Brotherhood stirs outrage|author=Noha El-Hennawy |date=17 August 2010 |work= |publisher=[[Al-Masry Al-Yaum]] |accessdate=23 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====An error in the Qur'an====
In one scene during sixth episode of the series, in which Sheikh Mohammed Zahran and young Hassan al-Banna are arguing, Sheikh Mohammed Zahran recites a verse from the Qur'an, accidentally changing a word and thus causing controversy. The verse (number 199 from ''[[Sura]] [[Al-A'raf]]'') is &quot;'''''Hold to forgiveness; command what is right; But turn away from the ignorant'''''&quot;.

==External links==
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gl9prvZ5CVg Video showing the error in the Qur'an recitation in the sixth episode of the series]
* [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vi_u-EhMyFM Video shows the show mocking a youth televangelist, activist and preacher]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Al-Gama'a (Tv Series)}}
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:2010s Egyptian television series]]
[[Category:Egyptian drama television series]]
[[Category:Egyptian television series]]
[[Category:Arabic-language television series]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Egypt]]
[[Category:Islamism in Egypt]]

[[ar:الجماعة (مسلسل)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
