<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28752586" ns="0" title="Defence School of Transport"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox Government agency
|agency_name     = Defence School of Transport
|type             = Tri-Service Training School
|logo_width      =
|logo_caption    =
|seal            =  
|seal_width      =  
|seal_caption    = 
|formed          = 1977
|preceding2      =
|dissolved       =
|superseding     =
|jurisdiction    = 
|headquarters    = DST &lt;br /&gt;
Normandy Barracks&lt;br /&gt;
Leconfield&lt;br /&gt;
East Riding of Yorkshire&lt;br /&gt;
HU17 7LX
}}

The '''Defence School of Transport''' ('''DST''') is situated in [[Leconfield]], [[East Riding of Yorkshire]], England on a former RAF base ([[RAF Leconfield]]). The site is now called '''Normandy Barracks'''. 

==History==
The site was handed over to the Army in the mid 1970s and the Army School of Mechanical Transport (ASMT) was established in 1977. In 1996 the school became the Defence School of Transport when it became responsible for training the RAF and Navy as well as the Army. In 2010 DST Leconfield was awarded the Freedom of the East Riding by the East Riding of Yorkshire council. 
==DCLPA==
DST Leconfield is one of the six Schools that make up the Defence College of Logistics and Personal Administration (DCLPA). The others are:
* The Defence EOD Munitions and Search School ([[DEMSS]])
* The Defence School of Personnel Administration (DSPA)
* The Defence Food Services School (DFSS)
* The Defence Logistics School (DLS)
* The Defence Maritime Logistics School (DMLS)

==Current Role==
DST Leconfield is said to be the largest residential driving school in the World it has approximately 16km of road circuits plus 26km of off road cross country circuits, including hills and lakes. DST Leconfield has an annual through put of over 16,000 students and can train up to 1,400 students at any one time. DST has 10 satellite sites 9 in the south of England and 1 in the north at Catterick providing car licence acquisition by contract. DST issues over 10,000 driving licences each year.  

Training ranges from licence acquisition for all types of vehicles from motorcycles to LGVs. Following on from licence acquisition DST Leconfield carries out training on all matters relating to road transport including training on specialist military wheeled vehicles ranging from the Honda 1300cc Pan-American motorcycle to the 60 ton Kalmar RT240 rough terrain container handler. In addition to the military training, DST Leconfield provides specialist driver training courses for the emergency services, [[Military attaché|Defence Attaches]], and overseas customers.   

DST has a fleet of over 1,300 vehicles that cover over 5.5 million miles each year. 

Two RAF Sea King [[RAF Search and Rescue Force|Search and Rescue]] helicopters of &quot;E&quot; Flight, 202 Squadron are also located at DST Leconfield. 

The Defence School of Transport is also the home of a [http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/weather/uk/yh/leconfield_latest_weather.html Met Office weather station].

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:DST Leconfield - Mastiff.jpg|Mastiff protective patrol vehicle outside DST Headquarters

&lt;/gallery&gt;

==External links==
'''MOD'''
*[http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/WhatWeDo/TrainingandExercises/DCLPA/DefenceSchoolOfTransportdst.htm DST Leconfield ] 
*[http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/DefenceNews/TrainingAndAdventure/PreparingMilitaryDriversForHelmandsVariedTerrain.htm DST Leconfield Preparing military drivers for Helmand's varied terrain]
'''Press'''
*[http://www.thisishullandeastriding.co.uk/topics/company/defenceschooloftransport Local Press]
'''Video Links'''
*[http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/Video/DefenceSchoolOfTransportdstVideo.htm DST Leconfield Video]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5wGlXafHCmE DST Leconfield Training]
[[Category:East Riding of Yorkshire]]

[[Category:Training establishments of the British Army]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
