<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28752486" ns="0" title="Tiger–Sooner Peace Pipe"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; style=&quot;width: 28em; font-size: 95%;&quot;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center; font-size: 150%;&quot; | '''Tiger-Sooner Peace Pipe'''
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;width:13em&quot; | &lt;br /&gt;[[Image:Oklahoma Sooners logo.svg|85px]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; style=&quot;width:13em&quot; | &lt;br /&gt;[[File:MU logo.svg|115px]]
|-
{{#if: {{{image location&lt;includeonly&gt;|&lt;/includeonly&gt;}}} |
{{!}} style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; {{!}}  }}
|-
| '''Teams'''
| [[Missouri Tigers football|Missouri Tigers]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Oklahoma Sooners football|Oklahoma Sooners]]
|-
| '''Originated'''
| 1929
|-
| '''Series'''
| Oklahoma leads 65-25-5
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| &lt;hr&gt;
|-
! Oklahoma (57) || Missouri (16)
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 1933 1934 &lt;br&gt; 1935 1937 1938 1940 &lt;br&gt; 1943 1946 1947 1948 &lt;br&gt; 1949 1950 1951 1952 &lt;br&gt; 1953 1954 1955 1956 &lt;br&gt; 1957 1958 1959 1961 &lt;br&gt; 1962 1963 1967 1968 &lt;br&gt; 1970 1971 1973 1974 &lt;br&gt; 1975 1976 1977 1978 &lt;br&gt; 1979 1980 1982 1984 &lt;br&gt; 1985 1986 1987 1988 &lt;br&gt; 1989 1990 1991 1992 &lt;br&gt; 1993 1994 1995 1999 &lt;br&gt; 2002 2003 2006 2007 &lt;br&gt; 2007 2008 2011
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 1929 1931 1932 &lt;br&gt; 1936 1939 1941 1945 &lt;br&gt; 1960 1965 1966 1969 &lt;br&gt; 1972 1981 1983 1998 &lt;br&gt; 2010
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| '''Ties (4)'''&lt;br&gt; 1930 1942 1944 1964
|-
| align=center colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;white-space: nowrap;&quot;|
|}

The '''Tiger&amp;ndash;Sooner Peace Pipe''' is the [[trophy]] awarded to the winner of an American [[college football]] [[college rivalry|rivalry]] game played by the [[Missouri Tigers football]] team of the [[University of Missouri]] and the [[Oklahoma Sooners football]] team of the [[University of Oklahoma]].

==Series history==
Missouri and Oklahoma's football teams first played in 1902, and they played annually 1910 until 1995, with only a one-year interruption in 1918 during [[World War I]].  The Tiger-Sooner Peace Pipe has been awarded since 1929.&lt;ref name=&quot;missouritigers&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://mutigers.cstv.com/trads/miss-mascot-trophy.html Mascot &amp; Football Traditions]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Big 12 Conference]] was formed in 1995, and was split into two divisions.  The two universities being placed in different division (Missouri in the Big 12 North Division, Oklahoma in the South Division), which prevented an annual matchup.  After the formation of the Big 12, the teams played a home-and-home series with three years in between each series (1998&amp;ndash;1999, 2002&amp;ndash;2003, 2006&amp;ndash;2007, 2010&amp;ndash;2011).

The Oklahoma Sooners won the last meeting of the two teams, 38&amp;ndash;28, on September 24, 2011.  With the Missouri Tigers' pending withdrawal from the Big 12, and admission to the [[Southeastern Conference]] (SEC), to be effective July 1, 2012, the future of the Missouri&amp;ndash;Oklahoma rivalry series is uncertain.

==Peace Pipe trophy==
In November 1940, a genuine Indian peace pipe was donated by Dr. John S. Knight of Kansas City to become the traveling trophy of the Missouri-Oklahoma football rivalry. Dr. Knight was a 1923 graduate of the University of Missouri.  The peace pipe, in the form of a tomahawk, belonged to Chief White Eagle of the [[Pawnee people|Pawnee]] tribe. The peace pipe was believed to be over 100 years old at the time it was donated in 1940. An inscription on the peace pipe reads &quot;Mystical Seven Society Ceremonial Tomahawk Pipe, University of Missouri vs. University of Oklahoma, Dr. John S. Knight &amp;ndash; donor of peace pipe.&quot;  Winners of each game are also inscribed on the pipe.  The peace pipe was entrusted to MU's [[Mystical Seven (Missouri)|Mystical Seven]] and OU's Pe-et, who would share the peace pipe in the end zone at halftime to celebrate the two universities.  The society of the winning university would return the peace pipe to its university until the next meeting of the two teams.&lt;ref name=&quot;digital.library.umsystem.edu&quot;&gt;http://digital.library.umsystem.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=alum;cc=alum;sid=e8319a3fa1419338cf773c4bbee6e40c;q1=peace%20pipe;rgn=full%20text;idno=alum194011;view=image;seq=30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;columbiamissourian.com&quot;&gt;http://www.columbiamissourian.com/stories/2007/10/11/case-missing-peace-pipe/&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Sooners were the first to take possession of the peace pipe following their 7-0 victory over the Tigers in 1940.  In fact, Oklahoma was inscribed 19 times on the pipe from 1940 to 1963. After a tie in 1964, OU gave possession of the pipe to MU as Oklahoma had held the trophy so many more times since the trophy's inception.  Records indicate that the tradition continued through 1974, but the peace pipe exchange did not take place in 1975.  The current location of the pipe is unknown since it was last held by Oklahoma.  OU's senior associate athletic director, Kenny Mossman, has indicated that Oklahoma officials have conducted an extensive search of their archives for historical items, and the peace pipe has not been located.&lt;ref name=&quot;digital.library.umsystem.edu&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;columbiamissourian.com&quot;/&gt;

==Notable games==

===2007 Big 12 Championship Game===
The Tigers were the Big 12 North's representative to the [[2007 Big 12 Championship Game]] where they faced Big 12 South representative Oklahoma.  Missouri came into the game ranked #1 in the AP Poll and the BCS standings.  However, they were upset by their rival and then were snubbed by the BCS for another rival, Kansas.

===2008 Big 12 Championship Game===
The [[2008 Big 12 Championship Game]] featured a rematch between the two schools.  This time, Oklahoma was favored and they won again.

===October 23, 2010===
In their 2010 meeting, Mizzou defeated Oklahoma (then ranked No. 1 in the [[Bowl Championship Series|BCS standings]]).  The game was the site of ESPN's [[College GameDay (football)|College GameDay]], where Missouri set the on-campus attendance record for GameDay.&lt;ref&gt;http://espn.go.com/blog/big12/post/_/id/19822/record-turnout-for-college-gameday&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Missouri Tigers football navbox}}
{{Oklahoma Sooners football navbox}}

[[Category:College football rivalries in the United States]]
[[Category:College football rivalry trophies in the United States]]
[[Category:Missouri Tigers football]]
[[Category:Oklahoma Sooners football]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
