<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2876230" ns="0" title="Felbrigg Hall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2011}}
{{Geobox|stately home
| name =Felbrigg Hall
| category =Stately home
| image = FelbriggHall(PhilipHalling)Jul2006.jpg
| image_caption = View of the south elevation of Felbrigg Hall
| flag =
| symbol =
| country = [[England]]
| state =     [[Norfolk]]
| region =   [[East of England]]
| district =   [[North Norfolk]]
| municipality = [[Cromer]]
| location =
| elevation =
| prominence =
| lat_d =
| lat_m =
| lat_s =
| lat_NS =
| long_d =
| long_m =
| long_s =
| long_EW =
| length =
| length_orientation =
| width =
| width_orientation =
| height =
| depth =
| volume =
| area =
| author =
| style =
| material =
| established =Built in 17th Century
| date =
| owner = In the care of the National Trust
| public =
| visitation =
| visitation_date = House:25 March to 29 October: Monday to Wednesday, Saturday, Sunday, Bank Holiday Mondays 1.00pm - 5.00pm. Gardens:25 March to 29 October: Monday to Wednesday, Saturday, Sunday, Bank Holiday Mondays 11.00am - 5.00pm.
29 May to 4 June/20 July to 1 September/23 October to 29 October: All week 11.00am to 5.00pm.
27 December to 31 December: Wednesday to Sunday 11.00am to 4.00pm.
Park and Woods: Daily dawn to dusk.
| access =Near Felbrigg village, {{convert|2|mi|km}} South West of Cromer on B1436, signposted from [[A148 road|A148]] and [[A140 road|A140]].
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free = | free_type =
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map =
| map_caption =
| map_background =
| map_locator =
| map_locator_x =
| map_locator_y =
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt;
| website = [http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/main/w-vh/w-visits/w-findaplace/w-felbrigg-hall National Trust Felbrigg Hall]
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes =
}}
'''Felbrigg Hall''' is a 17th-century [[country house]] located in [[Felbrigg]], Norfolk, England. Part of a [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]] property, the unaltered 17th-century house is noted for its [[Jacobean architecture]] and fine [[Georgian architecture|Georgian interior]]. Outside the house are a walled [[garden]], an [[orangery]] and [[orchard]]s.

==History==
Felbrigg estate, originally home to the Felbrigg family, was long the home of members of the Wyndham family, since the first John Wyndham (d. 1475), acquired the estate from the Felbrigg family. Thomas Wyndham (d. 1522) was a councilor to King [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hamline.edu/brass/pdfs/y_felb_1608_engr_1611-12.pdf Hamline University (accessed Oct 2010)]&lt;/ref&gt; Later residents included [[John Wyndham (1558–1645)]], probably the builder of Felbrigg Hall. The last Wyndham of Felbrigg was William Wyndham (d. 1810).

The last owner of the house before it passed into National Trust ownership was Mr Robert Ketton-Cremer.  The original heir, Robert's brother Richard, was killed in action in the [[Second World War]].  A memorial to Richard Ketton-Cremer was constructed in the woods behind the house by Robert. Robert Wyndham Ketton-Cremer wrote a number of books, particularly about Norfolk, including ''Felbrigg: the Story of a House'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.worldcat.org/title/felbrigg-the-story-of-a-house/oclc/6325329&amp;referer=brief_results WorldCat OCLC Number: 6325329]&lt;/ref&gt; and Norfolk in the Civil War, Faber, 1969. In the latter, he indicates his health is failing. Robert Ketton-Cremer never married, and with no heirs, left the estate to the National Trust on his death. Part of the estate was acquired by the [[Beeston Regis#Beeston Hall School|Beeston Hall school]].

Christopher Mackie, husband of author Mary Mackie, was Administrator, or Houseman, of Felbrigg Hall until 1990. Mary Mackie has written a number of books on their experiences, the most successful of which are ''Cobwebs and Cream Teas'' and ''Dry Rot and Daffodils''.

==Today==
At one time{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}} Felbrigg Hall stood at the centre of one the largest estates in Norfolk. Today 2011, the Felbrigg estate covers some 1,760 [[acre]]s (approximately 7 square kilometres) of parkland including the {{convert|520|acre|km2|sing=on}} Great Wood, which shelters the house. There are a number of [[waymarking|waymarked]] walks through the estate.

==The gardens==
Felbrigg garden is laid out in two different styles. The west garden is laid out in the style of a typical Victorian pleasure ground, arranged around an 18th-century orangery. Accentuating the play between light and shade, its formal [[lawn]]s are interspersed with areas of dark shrubbery. This garden features a number of specimens from [[North America]] including [[Erythrobalanus|Red Oaks]], [[Thuja plicata|Western Red Cedar]]s, and a [[meadow]] with a walled garden. There are double borders of mixed shrubs, a herbaceous border, and more. The orchard has been planted with varieties of fruit known to have grown in the garden during the 19th century. The gardens are home to the [[NCCPG National Plant Collection|National Collection]] of [[Colchicum]]s.

==Further reading==
* ''AA's Illustrated Guide to Britain'', London, 5th edition, 1983.
* Mackie, Mary. ''Cobwebs and Cream Teas: Year in the Life of a National Trust House'',  ISBN 0-7528-3410-X
* Mackie, Mary. ''Dry Rot and Daffodils: Life in a National Trust House'',  ISBN 0-7528-3409-6
* Mackie, Mary. ''Frogspawn and Floor Polish: Upstairs and Downstairs in a National Trust House'',  ISBN 1-84024-333-3

== References ==
{{Commons category}}
{{reflist}}

{{coord|52.9074|N|1.2593|E|display=title}}

[[Category:Gardens in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Country houses in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in Norfolk]]
[[Category:National Trust properties in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Norfolk]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
