<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="28951" ns="0" title="Spyware"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!--Note to editors: DO NOT USE THIS ARTICLE AS A PLATFORM FOR
                     PROMOTIONAL OR PURELY COMMERCIAL LINKS.

Such content will be deleted. Specific software is to be mentioned in this article 
--&gt;
'''Spyware''' is a type of [[malware]] that can be installed on [[computer]]s, and which collects small pieces of information about users without their knowledge. The presence of spyware is typically hidden from the user, and can be difficult to detect. Typically, spyware is secretly installed on the user's [[personal computer]]. Sometimes, however, spywares such as [[keylogger]]s are installed by the owner of a shared, corporate, or [[public computer]] on purpose in order to secretly monitor other users.

While the term ''spyware'' suggests software that secretly monitors the user's computing, the functions of spyware extend well beyond simple monitoring. Spyware programs can collect various types of [[personally identifiable information|personal information]], such as [[Internet surfing]] habits and sites that have been visited, but can also interfere with user control of the computer in other ways, such as installing additional software and redirecting [[Web browser]] activity. Spyware is known to change computer settings, resulting in slow connection speeds, different home pages, and/or loss of [[Internet]] connection or functionality of other programs. In an attempt to increase the understanding of spyware, a more formal classification of its included software types is provided by the term  [[privacy-invasive software]].

In response to the emergence of spyware, a small industry has sprung up dealing in [[anti-spyware]] software. Running anti-spyware software has become a widely recognized element of [[computer security]] practices for computers, especially those running [[Microsoft Windows]]. A number of jurisdictions have passed anti-spyware laws, which usually target any software that is surreptitiously installed to control a user's computer.

{{TOC limit|2}}

==History and development==
The first recorded use of the term [[:wikt:spyware|spyware]] occurred on 16 October 1995 in a [[Usenet]] post that poked fun at [[Microsoft]]'s [[business model]].&lt;ref name=&quot;coinage&quot;&gt;Vossen, Roland (attributed); October 21, 1995; [http://groups.google.com/group/rec..programmer/browse_thread/thread/86a426b0147496d8/3b5d1936eb4d0f33?lnk=st&amp;q=&amp;rnum=8#3b5d1936eb4d0f33 Win 95 Source code in c!!] posted to rec..programmer; retrieved from groups.google.com November 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Spyware'' at first denoted ''[[software]]'' meant for [[espionage]] purposes. However, in early 2000 the founder of [[Zone Labs]], Gregor Freund, used the term in a [http://www.zonealarm.com/store/content/company/aboutUs/pressroom/pressReleases/2000/za2.jsp press release] for the [[ZoneAlarm|ZoneAlarm Personal Firewall]].&lt;ref name=&quot;wienbar&quot;&gt;Wienbar, Sharon. &quot;[http://news.cnet.com/2010-1032-5307831.html The Spyware Inferno]&quot;. ''News.com''. August 13, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Since then, &quot;spyware&quot; has taken on its present sense.&lt;ref name=&quot;wienbar&quot; /&gt;
According to a 2005 study by [[AOL]] and the National Cyber-Security Alliance, 61 percent of surveyed users' computers were infected with form of spyware. 92 percent of surveyed users with spyware reported that they did not know of its presence, and 91 percent reported that they had not given permission for the installation of the spyware.&lt;ref name=&quot;aolstudy&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.staysafeonline.info/pdf/safety_study_2005.pdf AOL/NCSA Online Safety Study]&quot;. ''America Online'' &amp; ''The National Cyber Security Alliance''. 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
As of 2006, spyware has become one of the preeminent security threats to computer systems running Microsoft Windows [[operating system]]s. Computers on which [[Internet Explorer]] (IE) is the primary [[web browser|browser]] are particularly vulnerable to such attacks, not only because IE is the most widely-used,&lt;ref name=&quot;pcworld-ie&quot;&gt;Spanbauer, Scott. &quot;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/id,117550-page,1/article.html Is It Time to Ditch IE?]&quot;. ''Pcworld.com''. September 1, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; but because its tight integration with Windows allows spyware access to crucial parts of the operating system.&lt;ref name=&quot;pcworld-ie&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keizer, Gregg. &quot;[http://www.techweb.com/wire/software/170100394 Analyzing IE At 10: Integration With OS Smart Or Not?]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&quot;. ''TechWeb Technology News''. August 25, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

Before [[Internet Explorer 6]] SP2 was released as part of [[Windows XP Service Pack 2]], the browser would automatically display an installation window for any [[ActiveX]] component that a website wanted to install. The combination of user naivety concerning [[malware]], and the assumption by [[Internet Explorer]] that all ActiveX components are benign, led, in part, to the massive spread of spyware. Many spyware components would also make use of [[exploit (computer security)|exploit]]s in [[Javascript]], Internet Explorer and Windows to install without user knowledge or permission.

The [[Windows Registry]] contains multiple sections where modification of key values allows software to be executed automatically when the operating system boots. Spyware can exploit this design to circumvent attempts at removal. The spyware typically will link itself from each location in the [[Windows Registry|registry]] that allows execution. Once running, the spyware will periodically check if any of these links are removed. If so, they will be automatically restored. This ensures that the spyware will execute when the operating system is booted, even if some (or most) of the registry links are removed.

==Comparison==
===Spyware, adware and tracking===
The term ''[[adware]]'' frequently refers to any software which displays advertisements, whether or not the user has consented. Programs such as the [[Eudora (e-mail client)|Eudora]] mail client display advertisements as an alternative to [[shareware]] registration fees. These may be classified as &quot;adware&quot;, in the sense of advertising-supported software, but not as spyware.  Adware in this form does not operate surreptitiously or mislead the user, and provides the user with a specific service.

Most adware is ''spyware'' in a different sense than &quot;advertising-supported software&quot;: it displays advertisements related to what it finds from spying on users. Gator Software from [[Claria Corporation]] (formerly GATOR) and Exact Advertising's [[BargainBuddy]] are examples. Visited Web sites frequently install Gator on client machines in a surreptitious manner, and it directs revenue to the installing site and to Claria by displaying advertisements to the user. The user is shown many [[pop-up advertisement]]s.

Other spyware behavior, such as reporting on websites the user visits, occurs in the background. The data is used for &quot;targeted&quot; advertisement impressions. The prevalence of spyware has cast suspicion on other programs that track Web browsing, even for statistical or research purposes. Some observers describe the [[Alexa Toolbar]], an Internet Explorer plug-in published by [[Amazon.com]], as spyware, and some anti-spyware programs such as [[Ad-Aware]] report it as such. Many of these adware-distributing companies are backed by millions of dollars of adware-generating revenues.  Adware and spyware are similar to viruses in that they can be considered malicious in nature. People are profiting from misleading adware, sometimes known as [[scareware]], such as [[Antivirus 2009]].

Similarly, software bundled with free, advertising-supported programs acts as spyware (and, if removed, disables the 'parent' program), yet people are willing to download it. This presents a dilemma for proprietors of anti-spyware products whose removal tools may inadvertently disable wanted programs. For example, [[WhenUSave]] is ignored by popular anti-spyware program [[Ad-Aware]] (but removed as spyware by most scanners) because it is part of the popular (but recently decommissioned) eDonkey client.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.better-spyware-removal.com/spyware-test-results.html |title=remove spyware free spybot removal at |publisher=Better-spyware-removal.com |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; To address this dilemma, the [[Anti-Spyware Coalition]] was formed to establish and document best practices regarding acceptable software behavior.[http://www.antispywarecoalition.org/about/index.htm] However, the Anti-Spyware Coalition website does not appear to have been updated since late 2008.

===Spyware, viruses and worms===
Unlike [[computer virus|viruses]] and [[computer worm|worms]], spyware does not usually self-replicate. Like [[e-mail spam#Using other people's computers|many recent viruses]], however, spyware—by design—exploits infected computers for commercial gain. Typical tactics include delivery of unsolicited pop-up advertisements, theft of personal information (including financial information such as [[credit card number]]s), monitoring of Web-browsing activity for [[marketing]] purposes, and routing of [[HTTP]] requests to advertising sites.

However, spyware can be dropped as a payload by a worm.

==Routes of infection==
[[File:Windows ActiveX security warning (malware).png|thumb|280px|right|[[wikt:Malicious|Malicious]] [[website]]s attempt to install spyware on readers' [[computers]].]]
Spyware does not directly spread in the manner of a computer virus or worm: generally, an infected system does not attempt to transmit the infection to other computers. Instead, spyware gets on a system through deception of the user or through exploitation of software vulnerabilities.

Most spyware is installed without users' knowledge. Since they tend not to install software if they know that it will disrupt their working environment and compromise their privacy, spyware deceives users, either by [[piggybacking (security)|piggybacking]] on a piece of desirable software such as [[Kazaa]], or by tricking them into installing it (the [[Trojan horse (computing)|Trojan horse]] method). Some &quot;rogue&quot; spyware programs masquerade as security software.

The distributor of spyware usually presents the program as a useful utility—for instance as a &quot;Web accelerator&quot; or as a helpful [[software agent]]. Users download and install the software without immediately suspecting that it could cause harm. For example, [[Bonzi Buddy]], a program bundled with spyware&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-7669487_ITM|title=Prying Eyes Lurk Inside Your PC; Spyware Spawns Efforts at Control.|publisher=The Gale Group, Inc.|accessdate=June 5, 2008| first=Brian| last=Kladko| date=March 21, 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; and targeted at children, claims that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''He will explore the Internet with you as your very own friend and sidekick! He can talk, walk, joke, browse, search, e-mail, and download like no other friend you've ever had! He even has the ability to compare prices on the products you love and help you save money! Best of all, he's FREE!''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Woods |first=Mark |title=Click, you're infected |url=http://www.f-secure.com/f-secure/pressroom/protected/prot-1-2006/17-388-2826.shtml |work=Protected |publisher=[[F-Secure]] |accessdate=August 29, 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Spyware can also come bundled with other software. The user downloads a program and installs it, and the installer additionally installs the spyware.  Although the desirable software itself may do no harm, the bundled spyware does. In some cases, spyware authors have paid shareware authors to bundle spyware with their software. In other cases, spyware authors have repackaged desirable freeware with installers that slipstream spyware.

Some spyware authors infect a system through security holes in the Web browser or in other software. When the user navigates to a Web page controlled by the spyware author, the page contains code which attacks the browser and forces the download and installation of spyware. The spyware author would also have some extensive knowledge of commercially-available anti-virus and firewall software.  This has become known as a &quot;[[drive-by download]]&quot;, which leaves the user a hapless bystander to the attack. Common [[browser exploit]]s target security vulnerabilities in Internet Explorer and in the [[Sun Microsystems]] [[Java (programming language)|Java]] runtime.

The installation of spyware frequently involves Internet Explorer. Its popularity and history of security issues have made it the most frequent target. Its deep integration with the Windows environment and scriptability make it an obvious point of attack into [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]. Internet Explorer also serves as a point of attachment for spyware in the form of [[Browser Helper Object]]s, which modify the browser's behavior to add toolbars or to redirect traffic.

In a few cases, a [[Computer worm|worm]] or [[Computer Virus|virus]] has delivered a spyware payload. Some attackers used the [[Spybot worm]] to install spyware that put pornographic pop-ups on the infected system's screen.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.symantec.com/avcenter/venc/data/w32.spybot.worm.html Security Response: W32.Spybot.Worm]&quot;. ''Symantec.com''. Retrieved July 10, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; By directing traffic to ads set up to channel funds to the spyware authors, they profit personally.

==Effects and behaviors==
A spyware program is rarely alone on a computer: an affected machine usually has multiple infections. Users frequently notice unwanted behavior and degradation of system performance. A spyware infestation can create significant unwanted [[central processing unit|CPU]] activity, disk usage, and network traffic. Stability issues, such as applications freezing, failure to boot, and system-wide crashes, are also common. Spyware, which interferes with networking software, commonly causes difficulty connecting to the Internet.

In some infections, the spyware is not even evident. Users assume in those situations that the performance issues relate to faulty hardware, Windows installation problems, or another [[Malware|infection]]. Some owners of badly infected systems resort to contacting [[technical support]] experts, or even buying a new computer because the existing system &quot;has become too slow&quot;. Badly infected systems may require a clean reinstallation of all their software in order to return to full functionality.

Only rarely does a single piece of software render a computer unusable. Rather, a computer is likely to have multiple infections. The cumulative effect, and the interactions between spyware components, causes the symptoms commonly reported by users: a computer, which slows to a crawl, overwhelmed by the many parasitic processes running on it. Moreover, some types of spyware disable software [[firewall (networking)|firewalls]] and anti-virus software, and/or reduce browser security settings, thus opening the system to further [[opportunistic infection]]s, much like an [[immune deficiency]] disease. Some spyware disables or even removes competing spyware programs, on the grounds that more spyware-related annoyances make it even more likely that users will take action to remove the programs. One spyware maker, Avenue Media, even [[lawsuit|sued]] a competitor, Direct Revenue, over this; the two later [[settlement (law)|settled]] with an agreement not to disable each others' products.&lt;ref name=&quot;competitor removal&quot;&gt;Edelman, Ben; December 7, 2004 (updated February 8, 2005); [http://www.benedelman.org/news/120704-1.html Direct Revenue Deletes Competitors from Users' Disks]; benedelman.com. Retrieved November 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some other types of spyware use [[rootkit]] like techniques to prevent detection, and thus removal. Targetsoft, for instance, modifies the &quot;[[Winsock]]&quot; Windows Sockets files. The deletion of the spyware-infected file &quot;inetadpt.dll&quot; will interrupt normal networking usage.

A typical Windows user has administrative privileges, mostly for convenience. Because of this, any program the user runs (intentionally or not) has unrestricted access to the system. As with other [[operating system]]s, Windows users too are able to follow the principle of [[least privilege]] and use non-administrator [[least user access]] accounts, or to reduce the [[privilege (computing)|privileges]] of specific vulnerable Internet-facing [[process (computing)|processes]] such as Internet Explorer (through the use of tools such as [http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms972827.aspx DropMyRights]). However, as this is not a default configuration, few users do this.

In [[Windows Vista]], by default, a computer administrator runs everything under limited user privileges. When a program requires administrative privileges, Vista will prompt the user with an allow/deny pop-up (see [[User Account Control]]). This improves on the design used by previous versions of Windows.

===Advertisements===
Many spyware programs display advertisements. Some programs simply display pop-up ads on a regular basis; for instance, one every several minutes, or one when the user opens a new browser window. Others display ads in response to the user visiting specific sites. Spyware operators present this feature as desirable to advertisers, who may buy ad placement in pop-ups displayed when the user visits a particular site. It is also one of the purposes for which spyware programs gather information on user behavior.

Many users complain about irritating or offensive advertisements as well. As with many [[Web banner|banner ads]], spyware advertisements often use animation or flickering banners, which can be visually distracting and annoying to users. Pop-up ads for [[pornography]] often display indiscriminately. Links to these sites may be added to the browser window, history or search function. When children are the users, this could possibly violate [[anti-pornography]] laws in some jurisdictions.

A number of spyware programs break the boundaries of illegality; variations of “Zlob.Trojan” and “Trojan-Downloader.Win32.INService” have been known to show undesirable child pornography, key gens, cracks and illegal software pop-up ads, which violate child pornography and copyright laws.&lt;ref&gt;http://digg.com/security/Warner_Bros_website_distributing_Zango_Spyware_Kiddy_Porn_browser&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aic.gov.au/publications/htcb/htcb011.html Australian Institute of Criminology – Error]{{dead link|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.2-spyware.com/news/post81.html |title=YapBrowser – adware and child porn – spyware news |publisher=2-spyware.com |date=April 21, 2006 |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.castlecops.com/a5863-Child_Porn_Planting_Spyware_Beware.html]{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A further issue in the case of some spyware programs concerns the replacement of [[banner ad]]s on viewed web sites. Spyware that acts as a [[web proxy]] or a [[Browser Helper Object]] can replace references to a site's own advertisements (which fund the site) with advertisements that instead fund the spyware operator. This cuts into the margins of advertising-funded Web sites.

===&quot;Stealware&quot; and affiliate fraud===
A few spyware vendors, notably [[180 Solutions]], have written what the ''[[New York Times]]'' has dubbed &quot;[[stealware]]&quot;, and what spyware researcher Ben Edelman terms ''affiliate fraud'', a form of [[click fraud]]. Stealware diverts the payment of [[affiliate marketing]] revenues from the legitimate affiliate to the spyware vendor.

Spyware which attacks [[affiliate network]]s places the spyware operator's affiliate tag on the user's activity — replacing any other tag, if there is one. The spyware operator is the only party that gains from this. The user has their choices thwarted, a legitimate affiliate loses revenue, networks' reputations are injured, and vendors are harmed by having to pay out affiliate revenues to an &quot;affiliate&quot; who is not party to a contract.&lt;ref name=&quot;edelman-180&quot;&gt;Edelman, Ben (2004). &quot;[http://www.benedelman.org/spyware/180-affiliates/ The Effect of 180solutions on Affiliate Commissions and Merchants]&quot;. ''Benedelman.org''. Retrieved November 14, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Affiliate fraud is a violation of the [[terms of service]] of most affiliate marketing networks. As a result, spyware operators such as 180 Solutions have been terminated from affiliate networks including LinkShare and ShareSale.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Identity theft and fraud===
In one case, spyware has been closely associated with [[identity theft]].&lt;ref&gt;Ecker, Clint (2005). ''[http://arstechnica.com/news.ars/post/20050805-5175.html Massive spyware-based identity theft ring uncovered]''. Ars Technica, August 5, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2005, researchers from security software firm Sunbelt Software suspected the creators of the common [[CoolWebSearch]] spyware had used it to transmit &quot;[[Internet chat room|chat sessions]], [[user name]]s, [[password]]s, bank information, etc.&quot;;&lt;ref&gt;Eckelberry, Alex. [http://sunbeltblog.blogspot.com/2005/08/massive-identity-theft-ring.html &quot;Massive identity theft ring&quot;], ''SunbeltBLOG,'' August 4, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; however it turned out that &quot;it actually (was) its own sophisticated criminal little trojan that's independent of CWS.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Eckelberry, Alex. [http://sunbeltblog.blogspot.com/2005/08/identity-theft-what-to-do.html &quot;Identity Theft? What to do?&quot;], ''SunbeltBLOG,'' August 8, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; This case is currently under investigation by the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]].

The [[Federal Trade Commission]] estimates that 27.3 million Americans have been victims of identity theft, and that financial losses from identity theft totaled nearly $48 billion for businesses and financial institutions and at least $5 billion in out-of-pocket expenses for individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2003/09/idtheft.htm FTC Releases Survey of Identity Theft in U.S. 27.3 Million Victims in Past 5 Years, Billions in Losses for Businesses and Consumers]. Federal Trade Commission, September 3, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;

Spyware-makers may commit [[wire fraud]] with ''[[dialer]]'' program spyware. These can reset a [[modem]] to dial up a premium-rate telephone number instead of the usual [[Internet service provider|ISP]]. Connecting to these suspicious numbers involves long-distance or overseas charges which invariably result in high call costs. Dialers are ineffective on computers that do not have a modem, or are not connected to a telephone line, and are now very rare due to the decline in use of dial-up internet access.

===Digital rights management===
Some copy-protection technologies have borrowed from spyware. In 2005, [[Sony BMG Music Entertainment]] was [[Sony BMG CD copy protection scandal|found to be using]] [[rootkit]]s in its [[XCP]] [[digital rights management]] technology&lt;ref name=&quot;Sony scandal&quot;&gt;Russinovich, Mark. [http://blogs.technet.com/markrussinovich/archive/2005/10/31/sony-rootkits-and-digital-rights-management-gone-too-far.aspx &quot;Sony, Rootkits and Digital Rights Management Gone Too Far,&quot;], ''Mark's Blog,'' October 31, 2005. Retrieved November 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Like spyware, not only was it difficult to detect and uninstall, it was so poorly written that most efforts to remove it could have rendered computers unable to function.
[[Texas Attorney General]] [[Greg Abbott]] filed suit,&lt;ref name=&quot;Texas AG lawsuit&quot;&gt;Press release from the Texas Attorney General's office, November 21, 2005; [http://www.oag.state.tx.us/oagnews/release.php?id=1266 Attorney General Abbott Brings First Enforcement Action In Nation Against Sony BMG For Spyware Violations]. Retrieved November 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and three separate [[class-action]] suits were filed.&lt;ref name=&quot;class-action suits&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/4424254.stm &quot;Sony sued over copy-protected CDs; Sony BMG is facing three lawsuits over its controversial anti-piracy software&quot;], ''BBC News,'' November 10, 2005. Retrieved November 22, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Sony BMG later provided a workaround on its website to help users remove it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sony workaround&quot;&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20061201162533/http://cp.sonybmg.com/xcp/english/updates.html Information About XCP Protected CDs]. Retrieved November 29, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning on 25 April 2006, Microsoft's [[Windows Genuine Advantage]] Notifications application&lt;ref&gt;[http://support.microsoft.com/kb/905474/ Microsoft.com – Description of the Windows Genuine Advantage Notifications application]. Retrieved June 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; was installed on most Windows PCs as a &quot;critical security update&quot;. While the main purpose of this deliberately uninstallable application is to ensure the copy of Windows on the machine was lawfully purchased and installed, it also installs software that has been accused of &quot;[[phoning home]]&quot; on a daily basis, like spyware.&lt;ref&gt;Weinstein, Lauren. [http://lauren.vortex.com/archive/000178.html Windows XP update may be classified as 'spyware'], ''Lauren Weinstein's Blog,'' June 5, 2006. Retrieved June 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Evers, Joris. [http://news.zdnet.com/2100-3513_22-6081286.html?tag=nl.e589 Microsoft's antipiracy (sic) tool &quot;phones home&quot; daily], ''ZDNet News,'' June 7, 2006. Retrieved June 13, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; It can be removed with the RemoveWGA tool.

===Personal relationships===
Spyware has been used to surreptitiously monitor electronic activities of partners in intimate relationships, generally to uncover evidence of infidelity. At least one software package, Loverspy, was specifically marketed for this purpose. Depending on local laws regarding communal/marital property, observing a partner's online activity without their consent may be illegal; the author of Loverspy and several users of the product were indicted in California in 2005 on charges of wiretapping and various computer crimes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usdoj.gov/criminal/cybercrime/perezIndict.htm |title=Creator and Four Users of Loverspy Spyware Program Indicted (August 26, 2005) |publisher=Usdoj.gov |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Browser cookies===
Anti-spyware programs often report Web advertisers' [[HTTP cookie]]s, the small text files that track browsing activity, as spyware. While they are not always inherently malicious, many users object to third parties using space on their personal computers for their business purposes, and many anti-spyware programs offer to remove them.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.symantec.com/security_response/writeup.jsp?docid=2006-080217-3524-99&lt;/ref&gt;

===Examples===
These common spyware programs illustrate the diversity of behaviors found in these attacks. Note that as with computer viruses, researchers give names to spyware programs which may not be used by their creators. Programs may be grouped into &quot;families&quot; based not on shared program code, but on common behaviors, or by &quot;following the money&quot; of apparent financial or business connections. For instance, a number of the spyware programs distributed by [[Claria]] are collectively known as &quot;Gator&quot;. Likewise, programs that are frequently installed together may be described as parts of the same spyware package, even if they function separately.

&lt;!-- NOTE: Please avoid turning this into an unmaintainable list of &quot;all known spyware&quot;. If you have a cited, sourced description of a piece of spyware that exhibits notably different behavior, or illustrates a typical spyware behaviour that these examples don't, please add it. However, feel free to REMOVE one of the listed examples if it becomes redundant. This list should not grow longer than (say) 20 entries (the typical maximum bars in a histogram).
 ------------- --&gt;
*'''[[CoolWebSearch]]''', a group of programs, takes advantage of Internet Explorer vulnerabilities. The package directs traffic to advertisements on Web sites including ''coolwebsearch.com''. It displays pop-up ads, rewrites [[Web search engine|search engine]] results, and alters the infected computer's [[hosts file]] to direct [[Domain Name System|DNS]] lookups to these sites.&lt;ref name=&quot;doxdb-coolwebsearch&quot;&gt;&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/CoolWebSearch.html |title=CoolWebSearch |work=Parasite information database |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060106083816/http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/CoolWebSearch.html |archivedate=January 6, 2006 |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''[[Internet Optimizer]]''', also known as '''DyFuCa''', redirects Internet Explorer error pages to advertising. When users follow a broken link or enter an erroneous URL, they see a page of advertisements. However, because password-protected Web sites (HTTP Basic authentication) use the same mechanism as HTTP errors, Internet Optimizer makes it impossible for the user to access password-protected sites.&lt;ref name=&quot;doxdb-internetoptimizer&quot;&gt;&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/InternetOptimizer.html |title=InternetOptimizer |work= Parasite information database |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060106084114/http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/InternetOptimizer.html |archivedate=January 6, 2006 |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''[[HuntBar]]''', aka '''WinTools''' or '''[http://securityresponse.symantec.com/avcenter/venc/data/adware.websearch.html Adware.Websearch]''', was installed by an ActiveX [[drive-by installation|drive-by download]] at affiliate Web sites, or by advertisements displayed by other spyware programs—an example of how spyware can install more spyware. These programs add toolbars to IE, track aggregate browsing behavior, redirect affiliate references, and display advertisements.&lt;ref name=&quot;caspywareic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www3.ca.com/securityadvisor/pest/pest.aspx?id=453072528 |title=CA Spyware Information Center – HuntBar |publisher=.ca.com |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;pchell&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pchell.com/support/huntbar.shtml |title=What is Huntbar or Search Toolbar? |publisher=Pchell.com |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''[[Movieland]]''', also known as '''Moviepass.tv''' and '''Popcorn.net''', is a movie download service that has been the subject of thousands of complaints to the [[Federal Trade Commission]] (FTC), the [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] [[State Attorney General|State Attorney General's Office]], the [[Better Business Bureau]], and other agencies.  Consumers complained they were held hostage by a cycle of oversized [[pop-up window]]s demanding payment of at least $29.95, claiming that they had signed up for a three-day free trial but had not cancelled before the trial period was over, and were thus obligated to pay.&lt;ref name=&quot;FTCNEWSRELEASE&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2006/08/movieland.htm |title= FTC, Washington Attorney General Sue to Halt Unfair Movieland Downloads |publisher= [[Federal Trade Commission]] |date= August 15, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WANEWSRELEASE&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.atg.wa.gov/pressrelease.aspx?id=4286 |title= Attorney General McKenna Sues Movieland.com and Associates for Spyware |publisher= Washington State Office of the Attorney General |date= August 14, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The FTC filed a [[complaint]], since [[Settlement (litigation)|settled]], against Movieland and [[Movieland#Defendants|eleven other defendants]] charging them with having &quot;engaged in a nationwide scheme to use [[deception]] and [[coercion]] to extract payments from consumers.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FTCCOMPLAINT&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.ftc.gov/os/caselist/0623008/060808movielandcmplt.pdf |title= Complaint for Permanent Injunction and Other Equitable Relief (PDF, 25 pages) |publisher= [[Federal Trade Commission]] |date= August 8, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''WeatherStudio''' has a plugin that displays a window-panel near the ''bottom'' of a browser window. The official website notes that it is easy to remove (uninstall) WeatherStudio from a computer, using its own uninstall-program, such as under C:\Program Files\WeatherStudio.&lt;ref name=&quot;WSt&quot;&gt;
  &quot;WeatherStudio: Privacy Policy&quot;, WeatherStudio.com,
  2009, web: [http://www.weatherstudio.com/dp/content/&lt;!--
  --&gt;weatherstudio/privacypolicy.html WStudio-policy].&lt;/ref&gt; Once WeatherStudio is removed, a browser returns to the prior display appearance, without the need to modify the browser settings.

*'''[[Zango (company)|Zango]]''' (formerly '''[[180 Solutions]]''') transmits detailed information to advertisers about the Web sites which users visit. It also alters HTTP requests for [[affiliate marketing|affiliate]] advertisements linked from a Web site, so that the advertisements make unearned profit for the 180 Solutions company. It opens pop-up ads that cover over the Web sites of competing companies (as seen in their [Zango End User License Agreement]).&lt;ref name=&quot;edelman-180&quot;/&gt;

*'''[[Zlob trojan]]''', or just '''Zlob''', downloads itself to a computer via an [[ActiveX]] [[codec]] and reports information back to '''Control Server'''{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}}. Some information can be the search-history, the Websites visited, and even keystrokes.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} More recently, Zlob has been known to hijack routers set to defaults.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Malware Changes Router Settings&quot;&gt;[http://blogs.pcmag.com/securitywatch/2008/06/new_malware_silently_changes_r.php PCMAG, New Malware changes router settings], ''[[PC Magazine]]'', June 13, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal issues==
===Criminal law===
Unauthorized access to a computer is illegal under [[computer crime]] laws, such as the U.S. [[Computer Fraud and Abuse Act]], the U.K.'s [[Computer Misuse Act]], and similar laws in other countries. Since owners of computers infected with spyware generally claim that they never authorized the installation, a ''[[prima facie]]'' reading would suggest that the promulgation of spyware would count as a criminal act. Law enforcement has often pursued the authors of other malware, particularly viruses. However, few spyware developers have been prosecuted, and many operate openly as strictly legitimate businesses, though some have faced lawsuits.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://blogs.zdnet.com/Spyware/?p=655 Lawsuit filed against 180solutions]&quot;. ''zdnet.com'' September 13, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hu, Jim. &quot;[http://news.com.com/2110-1024_3-5287885.html 180solutions sues allies over adware]&quot;. ''news.com'' [[July 28, 2004]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Spyware producers argue that, contrary to the users' claims, users do in fact give [[consent]] to installations. Spyware that comes bundled with shareware applications may be described in the [[legalese]] text of an [[end-user license agreement]] (EULA). Many users habitually ignore these purported contracts, but spyware companies such as Claria say these demonstrate that users have consented.

Despite the ubiquity of EULAs and of &quot;[[clickwrap]]&quot; agreements, under which a single click can be taken as consent to the entire text, relatively little [[caselaw]] has resulted from their use. It has been established in most [[common law]] jurisdictions that a clickwrap agreement can be a binding contract ''in certain circumstances.''&lt;ref name=&quot;clickwrap legality&quot;&gt;Coollawyer; 2001–2006; [http://www.coollawyer.com/webfront/internet_law_library/articles/law_library_user_agreement_article.php Privacy Policies, Terms and Conditions, Website Contracts, Website Agreements]; coollawyer.com. Retrieved November 28, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; This does not, however, mean that every such agreement is a [[contract]], or that every term in one is enforceable.

Some jurisdictions, including the U.S. states of [[Iowa]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://coolice.legis.state.ia.us/cool-ice/default.asp?category=billinfo&amp;service=iowacode&amp;ga=83&amp;input=715 CHAPTER 715 Computer Spyware and Malware Protection]&quot;. ''nxtsearch.legis.state.ia.us''. Retrieved May 11, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://apps.leg.wa.gov/RCW/default.aspx?cite=19.270 Chapter 19.270 RCW: Computer spyware]. ''apps.leg.wa.gov''. Retrieved November 14, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; have passed laws criminalizing some forms of spyware. Such laws make it illegal for anyone other than the owner or operator of a computer to install software that alters Web-browser settings, monitors keystrokes, or disables computer-security software.

In the United States, lawmakers introduced a bill in 2005 entitled the [[Internet Spyware Prevention Act]], which would imprison creators of spyware.&lt;ref&gt;Gross, Grant. [http://www.infoworld.com/article/07/03/16/HNspywarebill_1.html US lawmakers introduce I-Spy bill]. ''InfoWorld,'' March 16, 2007. Retrieved March 24, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Administrative sanctions===
====US FTC actions====
The US [[Federal Trade Commission]] has sued Internet marketing organizations under the &quot;[[unfairness doctrine]]&quot; &lt;ref&gt;See [[Federal Trade Commission v. Sperry &amp; Hutchinson Trading Stamp Co.]]&lt;/ref&gt; to make them stop infecting consumers’ PCs with spyware. In one case, that against Seismic Entertainment Productions, the FTC accused the defendants of developing a program that seized control of PCs nationwide, infected them with spyware and other malicious software, bombarded them with a barrage of pop-up advertising for Seismic’s clients, exposed the PCs to security risks, and caused them to malfunction, slow down, and, at times, crash. Seismic then offered to sell the victims an “antispyware” program to fix the computers, and stop the popups and other problems that Seismic had caused. On November 21, 2006, a settlement was entered in federal court under which a $1.75 million judgment was imposed in one case and $1.86 million in another, but the defendants were insolvent&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2006/11/seismicodysseus.shtm '' FTC Permanently Halts Unlawful Spyware Operations''] (FTC press release with links to supporting documents); see also [http://docs.law.gwu.edu/facweb/claw/FTCcrackSpyw.pdf ''FTC cracks down on spyware and PC hijacking, but not true lies''], Micro Law, IEEE MICRO (Jan.-Feb. 2005), also available at [http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/stamp/stamp.jsp?arnumber=1411709&amp;isnumber=30580  IEEE Xplore].&lt;/ref&gt;

In a second case, brought against  CyberSpy Software LLC, the FTC charged that CyberSpy marketed and sold &quot;RemoteSpy&quot; keylogger spyware to clients who would then secretly monitor unsuspecting consumers’ computers. According to the FTC,  Cyberspy touted RemoteSpy as a “100% undetectable” way to “Spy on Anyone. From Anywhere.” The FTC has obtained a temporary order prohibiting the defendants from selling the software and disconnecting from the Internet any of their servers that collect, store, or provide access to information that this software has gathered. The case is still in its preliminary stages.  A complaint filed by the [[Electronic Privacy Information Center]] (EPIC) brought the RemoteSpy software to the FTC’s attention.&lt;ref&gt;See [http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2008/11/cyberspy.shtm ''Court Orders Halt to Sale of Spyware''] (FTC press release Nov. 17, 2008, with links to supporting documents).&lt;/ref&gt;

====Netherlands OPTA====
An administrative fine, the first of its kind in Europe, has been issued by the Independent Authority of Posts and Telecommunications (OPTA) from the Netherlands. It applied fines in total value of Euro 1,000,000 for infecting 22 million computers. The spyware concerned is called DollarRevenue. The law articles that have been violated are art. 4.1 of the Decision on universal service providers and on the interests of end users; the fines have been issued based on art. 15.4 taken together with art. 15.10 of the Dutch telecommunications law. A part of these fines has to be paid personally by the directors of these companies, i.e. not from the accounts of their companies, but from their personal fortunes.&lt;ref&gt;OPTA, &quot;Besluit van het college van de Onafhankelijke Post en Telecommunicatie Autoriteit op grond van artikel 15.4 juncto artikel 15.10 van de Telecommunicatiewet tot oplegging van boetes ter zake van overtredingen van het gestelde bij of krachtens de Telecommunicatiewet&quot; from 5 november 2007, http://opta.nl/download/202311+boete+verspreiding+ongewenste+software.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Since an appeal has been lodged, the fines will have to be paid only after a Dutch law court makes a decision in this case. The culprits maintain that the evidence for violating the two law articles has been obtained illegally. The names of the directors and the names of the companies have not been revealed, since it is not clear that OPTA is allowed to make such information public.&lt;ref&gt;According to H. Moll and E. Schouten, [http://www.nrc.nl/economie/article868499.ece/Limburgse_ICT-baas_blijkt_spywarekoning &quot;Limburgse ICT-baas blijkt spywarekoning&quot;], in NRC Handelsblad, 21 december 2007, the companies are:&lt;br /&gt;ECS International, Worldtostart and Media Highway International. Their owners are: Arjan de Raaf and Peter Emonds. Their accomplice having the nickname &quot;Akill&quot; has been arrested in Hamilton, New Zealand, for being the manager of a huge network of zombie computers.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil law===
Former [[New York State Attorney General]] and former [[Governor of New York]] [[Eliot Spitzer]] has pursued spyware companies for fraudulent installation of software.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=State Sues Major &quot;Spyware&quot; Distributor |publisher=Office of New York State Attorney General |date=April 28, 2005 |url=http://www.oag.state.ny.us/media_center/2005/apr/apr28a_05.html |accessdate=September 4, 2008 |quote=Attorney General Spitzer today sued one of the nation's leading internet marketing companies, alleging that the firm was the source of &quot;spyware&quot; and &quot;adware&quot; that has been secretly installed on millions of home computers. }}&lt;/ref&gt; In a suit brought in 2005 by Spitzer, the California firm [[Intermix Media, Inc.]] ended up settling, by agreeing to pay US$7.5 million and to stop distributing spyware.&lt;ref&gt;Gormley, Michael. {{cite news |url=http://news.yahoo.com/news?tmpl=story&amp;u=/cpress/20050615/ca_pr_on_tc/spitzer_spyware |title= Intermix Media Inc. says it is settling spyware lawsuit with N.Y. attorney general |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050622082027/http://news.yahoo.com/news?tmpl=story&amp;u=/cpress/20050615/ca_pr_on_tc/spitzer_spyware |archivedate=June 22, 2005 |work=[[Yahoo!]] News |date=June 15, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The hijacking of Web advertisements has also led to litigation. In June 2002, a number of large Web publishers sued [[Claria]] for replacing advertisements, but settled out of court.

Courts have not yet had to decide whether advertisers can be held [[Legal liability|liable]] for spyware that displays their ads. In many cases, the companies whose advertisements appear in spyware pop-ups do not directly do business with the spyware firm. Rather, they have contracted with an [[advertising agency]], which in turn contracts with an online subcontractor who gets paid by the number of &quot;impressions&quot; or appearances of the advertisement. Some major firms such as [[Dell Computer]] and [[Mercedes-Benz]] have sacked advertising agencies that have run their ads in spyware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Gormley |first=Michael |url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/computersecurity/2005-06-25-companies-spyware_x.htm |title=Major advertisers caught in spyware net |work=USA Today |date=June 25, 2005 |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Libel suits by spyware developers===

Litigation has gone both ways. Since &quot;spyware&quot; has become a common [[pejorative]], some makers have filed [[slander and libel|libel]] and [[defamation]] actions when their products have been so described. In 2003, Gator (now known as Claria) filed suit against the website [[PC Pitstop]] for describing its  program as &quot;spyware&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Festa, Paul. &quot;[http://news.com.com/2100-1032_3-5095051.html See you later, anti-Gators?]&quot;. ''News.com''. October 22, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; PC Pitstop settled, agreeing not to use the word &quot;spyware&quot;, but continues to describe harm caused by the Gator/Claria software.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.pcpitstop.com/gator/default.asp Gator Information Center]&quot;. ''pcpitstop.com'' November 14, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;  As a result, other anti-spyware and anti-virus companies have also used other terms such as &quot;'''potentially unwanted programs'''&quot; or [[greyware]] to denote these products.

===WebcamGate===
{{Main|Robbins v. Lower Merion School District}}
In the 2010 [[Robbins v. Lower Merion School District|WebcamGate]] case, plaintiffs charged two suburban Philadelphia high schools secretly spied on students by surreptitiously and remotely activating webcams embedded in school-issued laptops the students were using at home, and therefore infringed on their privacy rights.  The school loaded each student's computer with [[LANrev|LANrev's]] remote activation tracking software.  This included the now-discontinued &quot;TheftTrack&quot;.  While TheftTrack was not enabled by default on the software, the program allowed the school district to elect to activate it, and to choose which of the TheftTrack surveillance options the school wanted to enable.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated5&quot;/&gt;  

TheftTrack allowed school district employees to secretly remotely activate a tiny webcam embedded in the student's laptop, above the laptop's screen. That allowed school officials to secretly take photos through the webcam, of whatever was in front of it and in its line of sight, and send the photos to the school's server.  The LANrev software disabled the webcams for all other uses (''e.g.'', students were unable to use [[Photo Booth]] or [[video chat]]), so most students mistakenly believed their webcams did not work at all.  In addition to webcam surveillance, TheftTrack allowed school officials to take screenshots, and send them to the school's server. In addition, LANrev allowed school officials to take snapshots of instant messages, web browsing, music playlists, and written compositions.  The schools admitted to secretly snapping over 66,000 webshots and [[screenshot]]s, including webcam shots of students in their bedrooms.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated5&quot;&gt;[http://lmsd.org/documents/news/100503_l3_report.pdf &quot;Initial LANrev System Findings&quot;], LMSD Redacted Forensic Analysis, L-3 Services – prepared for [[Ballard Spahr]] (LMSD's counsel), May 2010. Retrieved August 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USATODAY&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/ondeadline/post/2010/02/school-district-accused-of-issuing-webcam-laptops-to-spy-on-students/1|author=Doug Stanglin|title=School district accused of spying on kids via laptop webcams|date=February 18, 2010|work=[[USA Today]]|accessdate=February 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Remedies and prevention==
As the spyware threat has worsened, a number of techniques have emerged to counteract it. These include programs designed to remove or to block spyware, as well as various user practices which reduce the chance of getting spyware on a system.

Nonetheless, spyware remains a costly problem. When a large number of pieces of spyware have infected a Windows computer, the only remedy may involve backing up user data, and fully reinstalling the operating system. For instance, some versions of [[Vundo]] cannot be completely removed by Symantec, Microsoft, PC Tools, and others because it infects rootkit, Internet Explorer, and Windows' lsass.exe (Local Security Authority Subsystem Service) with a randomly-filenamed dll (dynamic link library).

===Anti-spyware programs===
{{see also|Category:Spyware removal}}
Many programmers and some commercial firms have released products dedicated to remove or block spyware. [[Steve Gibson (computer programmer)|Steve Gibson]]'s ''OptOut'' pioneered a growing category. Programs such as PC Tools' [[Spyware Doctor]], Lavasoft's ''[[Ad-Aware SE]]'' (free scans for non-commercial users, must pay for other features) and Patrick Kolla's ''[[Spybot - Search &amp; Destroy]]'' (all features free for non-commercial use) rapidly gained popularity as effective tools to remove, and in some cases intercept, spyware programs.  On December 16, 2004, [[Microsoft]] acquired the ''[[GIANT AntiSpyware]]'' software,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2004/dec04/12-16GIANTPR.mspx&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; rebranding it as ''Windows AntiSpyware beta'' and releasing it as a free download for Genuine Windows XP and Windows 2003 users.  In 2006, [[Microsoft]] renamed the beta software to [[Windows Defender]] (free), and it was released as a free download in October 2006 and is included as standard with Windows Vista as well as Windows 7.

Major anti-virus firms such as [[Symantec]], [[PC Tools (company)|PC Tools]], [[McAfee]] and [[Sophos]] have come later to the table, adding anti-spyware features to their existing anti-virus products. Early on, anti-virus firms expressed reluctance to add anti-spyware functions, citing lawsuits brought by spyware authors against the authors of web sites and programs which described their products as &quot;spyware&quot;. However, recent versions of these major firms' home and business anti-virus products do include anti-spyware functions, albeit treated differently from viruses. Symantec Anti-Virus, for instance, categorizes spyware programs as &quot;extended threats&quot; and now offers [[real-time protection]] from them (as it does for viruses).

In June 2006, the anti-virus company [[Grisoft]], creator of [[AVG Anti-Virus]], acquired anti-spyware firm Ewido Networks, re-labeling their Ewido anti-spyware program as AVG Anti-Spyware Professional Edition. AVG also used this product to add an integrated anti-spyware solution to some versions of the [[AVG Anti-Virus]] family of products, and a [[freeware]] AVG Anti-Spyware Free Edition available for private and non-commercial use. This shows a trend by anti virus companies to launch a dedicated solution to spyware and malware. Zone Labs, creator of [[Zone Alarm]] [[firewall (computing)|firewall]] have also released an anti-spyware program.

Anti-spyware programs can combat spyware in two ways:
# They can provide real time protection against the installation of spyware software on the computer. This type of spyware protection works the same way as that of anti-virus protection in that the anti-spyware software scans all incoming network data for spyware software and blocks any threats it comes across.
# Anti-spyware software programs can be used solely for detection and removal of spyware software that has already been installed onto the computer. This type of spyware protection is normally much easier to use and more popular. With this spyware protection software the user can schedule weekly, daily, or monthly scans of the computer to detect and remove any spyware software that have been installed on the computer. This type of anti-spyware software scans the contents of the windows registry, operating system files, and installed programs on the computer and will provide a list of any threats found, allowing the user to choose what to delete and what to keep.

Such programs inspect the contents of the Windows registry, the operating system files, and installed programs, and remove files and entries which match a list of known spyware components. Real-time protection from spyware works identically to real-time anti-virus protection: the software scans disk files at download time, and blocks the activity of components known to represent spyware. In some cases, it may also intercept attempts to install start-up items or to modify browser settings. Because many spyware and adware are installed as a result of browser exploits or user error, using security software (some of which are antispyware, though many are not) to [[sandbox (computer security)|sandbox]] browsers can also be effective to help restrict any damage done.

Earlier versions of anti-spyware programs focused chiefly on detection and removal. Javacool Software's [[SpywareBlaster]], one of the first to offer real-time protection, blocked the installation of [[ActiveX]]-based and other spyware programs.

Like most anti-virus software, many anti-spyware/adware tools require a frequently-updated database of threats. As new spyware programs are released, anti-spyware developers discover and evaluate them, making &quot;signatures&quot; or &quot;definitions&quot; which allow the software to detect and remove the spyware. As a result, anti-spyware software is of limited usefulness without a regular source of updates. Some vendors provide a subscription-based update service, while others provide updates free. Updates may be installed automatically on a schedule or before doing a scan, or may be done manually.

Not all programs rely on updated definitions. Some programs rely partly (for instance many antispyware programs such as Windows Defender, [[Spybot - Search &amp; Destroy|Spybot]]'s TeaTimer and Spysweeper) or fully (programs falling under the class of [[Intrusion-prevention system|HIPS]] such as BillP's WinPatrol) on historical observation. They watch certain configuration parameters (such as certain portions of the Windows registry or browser configuration) and report any change to the user, without judgment or recommendation. While they do not rely on updated definitions, which may allow them to spot newer spyware, they can offer no guidance. The user is left to determine &quot;what did I just do, and is this configuration change appropriate?&quot;

[[Windows Defender]]'s SpyNet attempts to alleviate this through offering a community to share information, which helps guide both users, who can look at decisions made by others, and analysts, who can spot fast-spreading spyware. A popular generic spyware removal tool used by those with a certain degree of expertise is [[HijackThis]], which scans certain areas of the Windows OS where spyware often resides and presents a list with items to delete manually. As most of the items are legitimate windows files/registry entries it is advised for those who are less knowledgeable on this subject to post a HijackThis log on the numerous antispyware sites and let the experts decide what to delete.

If a spyware program is not blocked and manages to get itself installed, it may resist attempts to terminate or uninstall it. Some programs work in pairs: when an anti-spyware scanner (or the user) terminates one running process, the other one respawns the killed program. Likewise, some spyware will detect attempts to remove registry keys and immediately add them again. Usually, booting the infected computer in [[safe mode]] allows an anti-spyware program a better chance of removing persistent spyware. Killing the process tree may also work.

A new breed of spyware (Look2Me spyware by NicTechNetworks is a good example) hides inside system-critical processes and start up even in safe mode, see [[rootkit]]. With no process to terminate they are harder to detect and remove. Sometimes they do not even leave any on-disk signatures. [[Rootkit]] technology is also seeing increasing use,&lt;ref name=&quot;rootkit&quot;&gt;Roberts, Paul F. &quot;[http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1829744,00.asp Spyware meets Rootkit Stealth]&quot;. ''eweek.com''. June 20, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; as is the use of [[NTFS]] [[Fork (filesystem)|alternate data streams]]. Newer spyware programs also have specific countermeasures against well known anti-malware products and may prevent them from running or being installed, or even uninstall them. An example of one that uses all three methods is Gromozon, a new breed of malware. It uses alternate data streams to hide. A [[rootkit]] hides it even from alternate data streams scanners and actively stops popular [[rootkit]] scanners from running.

===Security practices===
To detect spyware, computer users have found several practices useful in addition to installing anti-spyware programs.

Many system operators install a [[web browser]] other than IE, such as [[Opera (web browser)|Opera]], [[Google Chrome]] or [[Mozilla Firefox]]. Though no browser is completely safe, Internet Explorer is at a greater risk for spyware infection due to its large user base as well as vulnerabilities such as [[ActiveX]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

Some ISPs—particularly [[college]]s and universities—have taken a different approach to blocking spyware: they use their network [[firewall (networking)|firewall]]s and [[web proxy|web proxies]] to block access to Web sites known to install spyware. On March 31, 2005, [[Cornell University]]'s Information Technology department released a report detailing the behavior of one particular piece of proxy-based spyware, ''[[Marketscore]]'', and the steps the university took to intercept it.&lt;ref&gt;Schuster, Steve. &quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.cit.cornell.edu/computer/security/marketscore/MarketScore_rev2.html |title= Blocking Marketscore: Why Cornell Did It |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20070214111921/http://www.cit.cornell.edu/computer/security/marketscore/MarketScore_rev2.html |archivedate=February 14, 2007}}&quot;. Cornell University, Office of Information Technologies. March 31, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; Many other educational institutions have taken similar steps. Spyware programs which redirect network traffic cause greater technical-support problems than programs which merely display ads or monitor users' behavior, and so may more readily attract institutional attention.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

Some users install a large [[hosts file]] which prevents the user's computer from connecting to known spyware-related web addresses. However, by connecting to the numeric IP address, rather than the domain name, spyware may bypass this sort of protection.

Spyware may get installed via certain [[shareware]] programs offered for download. Downloading programs only from reputable sources can provide some protection from this source of attack. Recently, [[CNet]] revamped its download directory: it has stated that it will only keep files that pass inspection by Ad-Aware and [[Spyware Doctor]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

The first step to removing spyware is to put a computer on &quot;lockdown&quot;. This can be done in various ways, such as using anti-virus software or simply disconnecting the computer from the internet. Disconnecting the internet prevents controllers of the spyware from being able to remotely control or access the computer. The second step to removing the spyware is to locate it and remove it, manually or through use of credible anti-spyware software. During and after lockdown, potentially threatening websites should be avoided.

==Programs distributed with spyware==
&lt;!-- LIST ONLY SOFTWARE NOTABLE ENOUGH TO HAVE ITS OWN ARTICLE, AND CITE SOURCES. --&gt;
* [[Bonzi Buddy]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://sarc.com/avcenter/venc/data/adware.bonzi.html Symantec Security Response – Adware.Bonzi]&quot;. ''Symantec''. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dope Wars]]&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, Ben (2005). &quot;[http://www.benedelman.org/spyware/installations/dopewars-claria/ Claria's Misleading Installation Methods – Dope Wars]&quot;. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[EDonkey2000]]&lt;ref name=&quot;p2p&quot; /&gt;
* [[Grokster]]&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, Ben (2004). &quot;[http://www.benedelman.org/news/100904-1.html Grokster and Claria Take Licenses to New Lows, and Congress Lets Them Do It]&quot;. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Kazaa]]&lt;ref&gt;Edelman, Ben (2004). &quot;[http://www.benedelman.org/spyware/claria-license/ Claria License Agreement Is Fifty Six Pages Long]&quot;. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Morpheus (computer program)|Morpheus]]&lt;ref name=&quot;p2p&quot;&gt;Edelman, Ben (2005). &quot;[http://www.benedelman.org/spyware/p2p/ Comparison of Unwanted Software Installed by P2P Programs]&quot;. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Printable-Greetings (computer program)]] &quot;http://www.printable-greetings.com&quot;   ESET: Win32/AdWare.FunWeb application
* [[RadLight]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ca.com/us/securityadvisor/pest/pest.aspx?id=54732 eTrust Spyware Encyclopedia – Radlight 3 PRO]&quot;. ''Computer Associates''. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[WeatherBug]]&lt;ref name=&quot;doxdb-weatherbug&quot;&gt;&quot;{{cite web |url=http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/WeatherBug.html |title=WeatherBug |work=Parasite information database |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20050206011153/http://www.doxdesk.com/parasite/WeatherBug.html |archivedate=February 6, 2005 |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[WildTangent]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sunbelt-wild&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://research.sunbeltsoftware.com/threatdisplay.aspx?name=AdWare.WildTangent&amp;threatid=236165 |title=Adware.WildTangent |publisher=Sunbelt Malware Research Labs |date=June 12, 2008 |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;sunbelt-winpipe&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://research.sunbelt-software.com/threatdisplay.aspx?name=Winpipe&amp;threatid=15154 |title=Winpipe |publisher=Sunbelt Malware Research Labs |date=June 12, 2008 |accessdate=September 4, 2008 |quote=It is possible that this spyware is distributed with the adware bundler WildTangent or from a threat included in that bundler.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Programs formerly distributed with spyware===
*[[AOL Instant Messenger]]&lt;ref name=&quot;sunbelt-wild&quot; /&gt; (AOL Instant Messenger still packages Viewpoint Media Player, and WildTangent)
*[[DivX]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.pcpitstop.com/gator/Confused.asp How Did I Get Gator?]&quot;. ''PC Pitstop''. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[FlashGet]]&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.ca.com/us/securityadvisor/pest/pest.aspx?id=453077947 eTrust Spyware Encyclopedia – FlashGet]&quot;. ''Computer Associates''. Retrieved July 27, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://virusscan.jotti.org/nl/scanresult/c55dc7987f87f11ed55d34f09f55cdce9727399e |title=Jotti's malware scan of FlashGet 3 |publisher=Virusscan.jotti.org |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.virustotal.com/nl/analisis/c36accc705a4eb96ab03cdaf12774f3958aad93980f78270f318e1b726172e33-1258741971 VirusTotal scan of FlashGet 3.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://virusscan.jotti.org/nl/scanresult/733dbb2f598c24c1c89466f4453c5e14da57b093 |title=Jotti's malware scan of FlashGet 1.96 |publisher=Virusscan.jotti.org |date= |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.virustotal.com/nl/analisis/b9a61c8950868756bab8bb565fc7ba196643b2a4e01fcf4111d722b9e31dd67e-1258743403 VirusTotal scan of FlashGet 1.96.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Some caution is required since FlashGet 3 EULA makes mention of Third Party Software, but does not name any third party producer of software. However, a scan with SpyBot Search &amp; Destroy, performed on November 20, 2009 after installing FlashGet 3 did not show any malware on an already anti-spyware immunized system (by SpyBot and SpywareBlaster).&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[magicJack]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gadgets.boingboing.net/2008/04/14/magicjacks-eula-says.html |title=Gadgets boingboing.net, '&amp;#39;MagicJack's EULA says it will spy on you and force you into arbitration'&amp;#39; |publisher=Gadgets.boingboing.net |date=April 14, 2008 |accessdate=September 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rogue anti-spyware programs==
{{See also|List of fake anti-spyware programs|Rogue software}}

Malicious programmers have released a large number of rogue (fake) anti-spyware programs, and widely distributed Web [[banner ad]]s now spuriously warn users that their computers have been infected with spyware, directing them to purchase programs which do not actually remove spyware—or else, may add more spyware of their own.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Roberts |first=Paul F. |url=http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1821127,00.asp |title=Spyware-Removal Program Tagged as a Trap |date=May 26, 2005 |work=[[eWeek]] |accessdate=September 4, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Howes, Eric L. &quot;[http://www.spywarewarrior.com/rogue_anti-spyware.htm The Spyware Warrior List of Rogue/Suspect Anti-Spyware Products &amp; Web Sites]&quot;. Retrieved July 10, 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

The {{As of|2005|alt=recent}} proliferation of fake or spoofed antivirus products has occasioned some concern. Such products often bill themselves as antispyware, antivirus, or registry cleaners, and sometimes feature popups prompting users to install them. This software is called [[rogue software]].

It is recommended that users do not install any freeware claiming to be anti-spyware unless it is verified to be legitimate. Some known offenders include:

 {{Div col|3}}
* [[AntiVirus 360]]
* [[Antivirus 2008]]
* [[Antivirus 2009]]
* [[AntiVirus Gold]]
* [[ContraVirus]]
* [[MacSweeper]]
* [[Pest Trap]]
* [[PSGuard]]
* [[Spy Wiper]]
* [[Spydawn]]
* [[Spylocked]]
* [[Spysheriff]]
* [[SpyShredder]]
* [[Spyware Quake]]
* [[SpywareStrike]]
* [[UltimateCleaner]]
* [[WinAntiVirus Pro 2006]]
* [[Windows Police Pro]]
* [[WinFixer]]&lt;ref name=&quot;somanynames&quot;&gt;Also known as WinAntiVirusPro, ErrorSafe, SystemDoctor, WinAntiSpyware, AVSystemCare, WinAntiSpy, Windows Police Pro, Performance Optimizer, StorageProtector, PrivacyProtector, WinReanimator, DriveCleaner, WinspywareProtect, PCTurboPro, FreePCSecure, ErrorProtector, SysProtect, WinSoftware, XPAntivirus, Personal Antivirus, Home Antivirus 20xx, VirusDoctor, and ECsecure&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[WorldAntiSpy]]
* [[XP Security]]
 {{Div col end}}

Fake antivirus products constitute 15 percent of all malware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Elinor Mills|title=Google: Fake antivirus is 15 percent of all malware|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-27080_3-20003340-245.html|publisher=[[CNET]]|date=April 27, 2010|accessdate=2011-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On January 26, 2006, Microsoft and the Washington state attorney general filed suit against Secure Computer for its Spyware Cleaner product.&lt;ref&gt;McMillan, Robert. [http://www.pcworld.com/news/article/0,aid,124508,00.asp Antispyware Company Sued Under Spyware Law]. ''PC World,'' January 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;
On December 4, 2006, the Washington attorney general announced that Secure Computer had paid $1 million to settle with the state.  As of that date, Microsoft's case against Secure Computer remained pending.&lt;ref&gt;Leyden, John. [http://www.theregister.co.uk/2006/12/05/washington_anti-spware_lawsuit/ Bogus anti-spyware firm fined $1m]. ''The Register,'' December 5, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Computer insecurity]]
*[[Computer surveillance]]
*[[Cyber spying]]
*[[Defensive computing]]
*[[Employee monitoring software]]
*[[Industrial espionage]]
*[[Phoning home]]
*[[Spy-phishing]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite web |url = http://www.windowsecurity.com/articles/Spyware-Evolving.html |title = How Spyware And The Weapons Against It Are Evolving |work = WindowsSecurity.com |publisher = TechGenix Ltd |date = November 10, 2004 |accessdate = August 22, 2010 |first = Brien  |last = Posey}}

==External links==
*[http://www.stopbadware.org/ StopBadware.org] — A non-profit group (sponsored by Google, , and Sun) that aims to provide &quot;reliable, objective information about downloadable applications&quot;.

{{malware}}

[[Category:Spyware| ]]
[[Category:Malware]]
[[Category:Rogue software]]
[[Category:Computer network security]]
[[Category:Internet advertising and promotion]]
[[Category:Espionage techniques]]
[[Category:Espionage devices]]

[[ar:برامج تجسس]]
[[bs:Spyware]]
[[ca:Programari espia]]
[[cs:Spyware]]
[[da:Spyware]]
[[de:Spyware]]
[[et:Nuhkvara]]
[[el:Spyware]]
[[es:Programa espía]]
[[eu:Spyware]]
[[fa:جاسوس‌افزار]]
[[fr:Logiciel espion]]
[[ko:스파이웨어]]
[[hy:Լրտեսածրագիր]]
[[hi:स्पाइवेयर]]
[[hr:Spyware]]
[[id:Spyware]]
[[it:Spyware]]
[[he:רוגלה]]
[[ku:Spyware]]
[[lt:Spyware]]
[[hu:Kémprogram]]
[[nl:Spyware]]
[[ja:スパイウェア]]
[[no:Spionprogramvare]]
[[pl:Programy szpiegujące]]
[[pt:Spyware]]
[[ro:Program spion]]
[[ru:Spyware]]
[[sq:Spyware]]
[[simple:Spyware]]
[[sk:Spyware]]
[[sr:Рачунарски шпијун]]
[[sh:Spyware]]
[[fi:Vakoiluohjelma]]
[[sv:Spionprogram]]
[[ta:உளவுமென்பொருள்]]
[[th:ซอฟต์แวร์สอดแนม]]
[[tr:Casus yazılım (spyware)]]
[[uk:Spyware]]
[[ur:جاسوس مصنع]]
[[vi:Phần mềm gián điệp]]
[[zh:间谍软件]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
