<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2902981" ns="0" title="Windows Aero"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = Windows Aero
| logo                   = [[File:Aero.svg|125px|Windows Aero logo]]
| screenshot             = [[File:Aero Example.png|351px]]
| caption                = The &quot;glass&quot;-like window borders, a distinctive feature of Windows Aero.
| developer              = [[Microsoft]]
| released               =
| latest_release_version =
| latest_release_date    = &lt;!-- {{Start date and age|||}} --&gt;
| latest_preview_version =
| latest_preview_date    =
| operating_system       = [[Windows Vista]], [[Windows 7]], [[Windows 8]]
| genre                  = [[Desktop environment]]
| language               =
| license                = [[EULA]]
| website                = [http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows7/products/features/aero Windows 7 Aero feature page]
| working_state          = Current
}}
'''Windows Aero''' is the [[graphical user interface]] and the default [[theme (computing)|theme]] in most editions of [[Windows Vista]] and [[Windows 7]], [[operating system]]s released by [[Microsoft]]. It is also available in [[Windows Server 2008]], but is not enabled by default. Its name is a [[backronym]] for ''Authentic, Energetic, Reflective and Open''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://windowsvistablog.com/blogs/windowsvista/archive/2006/11/09/the-sounds-of-windows-vista.aspx
|title=The Sounds of Windows Vista
|accessdate=2006-11-09
|last=Allchin
|first=Jimmy
|authorlink=James Allchin
|date=November 9, 2006
|work=Windows Vista Team Blog
|publisher=Microsoft
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20061110152317/http://windowsvistablog.com/blogs/windowsvista/archive/2006/11/09/the-sounds-of-windows-vista.aspx &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-11-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; Intended to be a cleaner, more powerful, more efficient and more aesthetically pleasing user interface than the previously used theme ([[Luna (theme)|Luna]]),{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} it includes new [[Transparency (optics)|translucency]], live thumbnails, live icons, animations and [[Attractiveness#Eye candy|eye candy]]. Aero also encompasses a set of user interface design guidelines for [[Microsoft Windows]]. In [[Windows Vista]], transparency is disabled when windows are maximized but in [[Windows 7]], transparency is enabled unless the user disables it in personalization or chooses the basic or classic theme.

==History==
Like [[Windows XP]], Aero's base icons were designed by [[The Iconfactory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Windows Vista icons&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://iconfactory.com/design/detail/windows_vista |title=Iconfactory : Design : Windows Vista |accessdate=2007-05-22 |author=The Iconfactory |authorlink=The Iconfactory |coauthors= |date= |year= |month= |work= |publisher= |pages= |language= |archiveurl= |archivedate= |quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until the release of Windows Vista Beta 1 in July 2005, little had been shown of Aero in public or leaked builds. Previous user interfaces were ''Plex'', which was featured in Longhorn builds 3663-4048; ''Slate'', which was featured in build 4042 and was available until build 4094; and ''Jade'' (builds 4074, 4083 and 4093, actually an early preview of Aero). Microsoft started using ''Aero'' in public builds in build 5048. The first build with full-featured Aero was build 5219.  Build 5270 (released in December 2005) contained an implementation of Aero which was virtually complete, according to sources at Microsoft, though a number of stylistic changes were introduced between then and the operating system's release.

Originally, Aero was to have three levels available, one code-named &quot;To Go&quot;, which had the [[Desktop Window Manager]] (DWM) composition engine (previously known as DCE) disabled. The next was to be AeroExpress, lacking many features of the highest level code-named Aero Glass. However, in December 2005, Microsoft announced that there would only be two levels available, &quot;Windows Vista Aero&quot; and &quot;Windows Vista Basic&quot;, with the previous &quot;Express&quot; level integrated into the new &quot;Windows Vista Aero&quot; level. A control panel was added to enable the user to fine tune this functionality, such as being able to turn off the &quot;glass&quot; translucency effect. These levels are provided so that the Aero interface (to some extent) can be used with a relatively low-end graphics card.

===Windows 7===
[[File:Aero Peek.png|thumb|Aero Peek showing the desktop.]]
Windows Aero is revised in Windows 7, with several UI changes, a more touch-friendly UI and many new visual effects and features:

*'''Aero Peek''' - hovering over a taskbar icon shows the thumbnail of that program. Hovering over the thumbnail shows a preview of that program in full view. Aero Peek also refers to the &quot;Show desktop&quot; button to the far right of the new taskbar.
*'''Aero Shake''' - Shaking (quickly dragging back and forth) a window minimizes all other windows. Shaking it again brings them back.
*'''Aero Snap''' - Clicking and dragging a window to the right or left side of the desktop causes the window to fill the respective half of the screen. Snapping a window to the top of the desktop maximizes it. Resizing a window to touch the top or bottom edge of the screen maximizes the window to full height, whilst retaining its width; these windows will then slide horizontally if moved by the title bar, or can be pulled off, which returns the window to its original height.
*'''[[jumplist|Jump List]]''' - Right clicking on or clicking and dragging upwards an icon on the taskbar enables several options, including pinning and displaying recent documents. Program-specific options, such as opening a new window in a browser, are included if supported by the program.
*'''Touch UI''' - Windows Aero was revised to be more touch-friendly.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} For example, the title bar buttons are now slightly bigger.
*Maximized windows remain transparent instead of becoming opaque.
*When hovering over the taskbar button for a running program, the button glows the dominant RGB color of its icon. Also, a shiny effect follows the mouse as it moves across the icon of active programs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.microsoft.com/windows/windows-7/whats-new.aspx What's new in Windows 7: Faster &amp; easier] - Microsoft&lt;/ref&gt;
*When moving windows, the [[CPU]] and [[GPU]] load is reduced by limiting the frame rate that the Aero part is rendered in order to provide better performance to applications and programs.
*The blur effect in Aero on Windows 7 now has more even blending than Aero in Windows Vista.
*It is now possible to turn off window shadows.
*The cyan outline on the right and bottom side of focused windows has been changed to white in Windows 7.
*Progress bars can be used in the program's taskbar buttons. If a program is executing a process which takes significant time, its taskbar button will act as a progress bar by filling up with green as the operation progresses.

==User interface==
{| style=&quot;float:right;&quot;
|
|-
|[[Image:Windows Vista Open Dialog.png|thumb|The Open Dialog in Windows 7 demonstrates some of the new aesthetic and functional aspects of Aero.]]
|-
|[[Image:Windows Vista Connection Wizard.png|thumb|The Connect to the Internet [[Wizard (software)|Wizard]].]]
|-
|[[Image:Vista Flip 3d.png|thumb|[[Windows Vista]] Flip 3D {{keypress|Win|tab}}]]
|-
|[[Image:Windows7 flip.png|thumb|[[Windows 7]] Flip 3D {{keypress|Win|tab}}]]
|-
|[[Image:Livethumbnails.png|thumb|[[Windows Vista]] Live Thumbnails (hovering over the taskbar button)]]
|-
|[[File:ThumbnailWin7.png|thumb|[[Windows 7]]'s Live Thumbnails (hovering over the icon)]]
|-
|
|}
For the first time since the release of [[Windows 95]], Microsoft has completely revised its user interface guidelines, covering [[aesthetics]], common controls such as [[Button (computing)|buttons]] and [[radio button]]s, task dialogs, [[Wizard (software)|wizards]], common dialogs, control panels, icons, fonts, user notifications, and the &quot;tone&quot; of text used.&lt;ref name=&quot;uxguide&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa511301.aspx
|title=What's New in Windows Vista
|accessdate=2009-02-14
|work=MSDN - Windows Vista User Experience Guidelines
|publisher=Microsoft
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aero Wizards===

'''Wizard 97'''&lt;ref name=&quot;wizard97&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms738248.aspx
|title=Wizard 97
|accessdate=2009-02-14
|work=Platform SDK
|publisher=Microsoft
}}&lt;/ref&gt; had been the prevailing standard for wizard design, visual layout, and functionality used in [[Windows 98]] through to [[Windows Server 2003]], as well as most Microsoft products in that time frame. Aero Wizards are the replacement for Wizard 97, incorporating visual updates to match the aesthetics of the rest of Aero, as well as changing the interaction flow.

More specifically:
* To increase the efficiency of the wizard, The &quot;Welcome&quot; pages in Wizard 97 are no longer used. (A precursor to this change was implied in a number of wizards in products such as [[Microsoft SQL Server|SQL Server 2005]] where a check-box was added to welcome pages, allowing a user to disable the welcome page in future uses of the wizard.)
* Aero Wizards can be resized, whereas the Wizard 97 guidelines defined exact sizes for wizard window and content sizes.
* The purpose of any given Aero Wizard page is more clearly stated at the top.
* A new kind of control called a &quot;Command link&quot; provides a single-click operation to choose from a short list of options.
* The notion of &quot;Commit pages&quot; is introduced, where it is made clear that the next step will be the actual process that the wizard is being used to enact. If no follow-up information needs to be communicated, these are the last pages in a wizard. Typically a commit page has a button at the bottom-right that is labeled with the action to be taken, such as &quot;Create account&quot;.
* The &quot;Back&quot; button has moved to the top-left corner of the wizard window and matches the visual style of the back button in other Vista applications. This is done to give more focus to the commit choices. The &quot;Next&quot; button is only shown on pages where it is necessary.
* At the end of a wizard, a &quot;Follow-up page&quot; can be used to direct the user to related tasks that they may be interested in immediately after completing the wizard. For example, a follow-up for a CD burning wizard may present options like &quot;Duplicate this disk&quot; and &quot;Make a disk label&quot;.

===Notifications===
Notifications allow an application or operating system component with an icon in the notification area to create a pop-up window with some information about an event or problem. These windows, first introduced in [[Windows 2000]] and known colloquially as &quot;balloons&quot;, are similar in appearance to the [[speech balloon]]s that are commonly seen in [[comics]]. Balloons were often criticized in prior versions of Windows due to their intrusiveness, especially with regard to how they interacted with full-screen applications such as games (the entire application was minimized as the bubble came up). Notifications in Aero aim to be less intrusive by gradually fading in and out, and not appearing at all if a full-screen application or screensaver is being displayed – in these cases, notifications are queued until an appropriate time. Larger icons and multiple font sizes and colors are also introduced with Aero's notification windows.

===Font===
The [[Segoe UI]] [[Computer font|typeface]] is the new default font for Aero with languages that use Latin, Greek, and Cyrillic character sets. The default font size is also increased from 8pt to 9pt to improve readability.  In the Segoe UI typeface, the numeral zero (&quot;0&quot;) is narrow, while capital letter &quot;O&quot; is wider, and numeral one (&quot;1&quot;) has a top hook, while capital letter &quot;I&quot; has equal crown and base.

===Phrasing tone===
The Vista User Experience Guidelines also address the issue of &quot;tone&quot; in the writing of text used with the Aero user interface. Prior design guidelines from Microsoft had not done much to address the issue of how user interface text is phrased, and as such, the way that information and requests are presented to the user had not been consistent between parts of the operating system.

The guidelines for Vista and its applications suggest messages that present technically accurate advice concisely, objectively, and positively, and assume an intelligent user motivated to solve a particular problem. Specific advice includes the use of the [[grammatical person|second person]] and the [[grammatical voice|active voice]] (e.g. &quot;Print the photos on your camera&quot;) and avoidance of words like &quot;please&quot; and &quot;sorry&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa511287.aspx
|title=Windows Vista User Experience Guidelines - Text
|publisher=microsoft.com
|month=June
|year=2008
|accessdate=2008-06-08
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aero animation ==
When the full version of Aero is enabled, Aero uses animations to give an interactive experience to the user. For instance, upon minimizing a window to the taskbar, the window scales down to the size of the button in the taskbar; when restoring a window, it scales back to its original size from the button in the taskbar. Also, when a maximized windows is closed, the window will appear to be falling down. Furthermore, all windows, including dialog boxes, now contain a zoom-in effect on appearance and zoom-out effect on close, as if to suggest they were coming from the active window or the desktop. Additionally, dialog buttons in Aero pulse slowly at the user. Buttons in titlebars now quickly glow or fade when the mouse moves over or away from them, respectively. Aero also acts as if progress bars are being pushed forward by a small aura of light when completing a task to give an illusion of forward motion. This functionality is included in the Windows Explorer address bar for loading contents or searching in the active window; Windows 7 further enhanced this feature by allowing buttons in the Superbar to have a similar effect. When Windows Flip 3D is activated with the Win+Tab keys, windows and a miniature version of the desktop appear as if they are being flipped through, similar to cards. Also unique to Windows Aero is a  display of instantaneous audio volume in the volume control in the taskbar, in addition to the user setting.

The original .avi effects, which were simply updated or &quot;re-skinned&quot; with new icons with new editions of Windows, since Windows 95, for copying and deleting files, were replaced with a new animation where, upon copying files, one transparent &quot;file&quot; flies into view, and another &quot;file&quot; appears in view from the back when the first produces a hit and nova effect{{Clarify|date=April 2011}}. When deleting a file, one transparent &quot;file&quot; flies up at the user, and shreds down to the bottom. Also, in the Aero UI, if an error is encountered, the green progress bar fades to bright red until the error is resolved. (In previous versions of Windows, such an error would stop the copy or deletion process completely.)

Many Aero features can be disabled by the user.

== Requirements ==
Microsoft has listed the following requirements for what they call a ''Vista Premium Ready'' PC. A PC that meets or exceeds these requirements will be able to use the new Aero technologies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windowsvista/getready/capable.mspx
|title=Windows Vista Capable and Premium Ready PCs
|publisher=microsoft.com
|accessdate=2006-05-20
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Windows 7 Home Premium, Windows 7 Professional, Windows 7 Ultimate, Windows 7 Enterprise, Windows Vista Home Premium, Windows Vista Business, Windows Vista Ultimate, Windows Vista Enterprise. Aero is not available by default in Windows Vista Home Basic, Windows 7 Starter and Windows 7 Home Basic, although a workaround has been discovered allowing Vista Basic users to have transparency and blur effects, provided that their system meets the recommended hardware requirements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://killermole23.deviantart.com/art/Transparent-Aero-on-Home-Basic-130211498|title=Transparent Aero on Home Basic|coauthors=killermole23|date=July 20, 2009|accessdate=5 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* a 1 [[GHz]] [[32-bit]] ([[x86]]) or [[64-bit]] ([[x86-64|x64]]) [[Microprocessor|processor]]
* 1 GB of system memory
* a [[DirectX]] 9 compatible graphics processor with a [[Windows Display Driver Model]] (WDDM) driver, [[Pixel shader]] 2.0 in hardware, and a minimum of 128 MB of [[Video RAM]]
* 32 bits per pixel
* 40 GB hard drive with 15 GB free space
* DVD-ROM Drive (only for installation of Windows Vista or 7 through a DVD)
* Audio output and Internet access (preferably broadband)

The minimum requirements for graphics cards from the major vendors include the [[Radeon 9500]] from [[ATI Technologies]], the [[GeForce FX]] series from [[NVIDIA]], and even the [[Intel GMA]] 950 and 500. [[Intel GMA]] 900 theoretically supports Aero as it fulfills all hardware requirements but Intel does not offer a WDDM driver, therefore making it incompatible.  Though the last driver from NVIDIA to support the GeForce FX series on Vista was 96.85,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nvidia.com/object/winvista_x86_96.85_2.html ForceWare Release 95&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.msbetas.org/wiki/index.php/Vista_Ready_GPUs
|title=Windows Vista Ready GPUs
|publisher=msbetas.org
|month=July
|year=2007
|accessdate=2007-07-30
|archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070713114519/http://www.msbetas.org/wiki/index.php/Vista_Ready_GPUs &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Microsoft's WDDM drivers for NVIDIA graphics continue to support the GeForce FX series;&lt;ref&gt;The file C:\Windows\inf\nv_lh.inf (as found on a Vista Home Premium system with ATI graphics) provides drivers labeled &quot;(Microsoft Corporation - WDDM)&quot; for nearly all GeForce FX GPUs.&lt;/ref&gt; NVIDIA's current WDDM drivers support the [[GeForce 6]] and later series.  Though some of [[XGI Technology]]'s Volari GPUs supported DirectX 9, no Microsoft WDDM drivers shipped with Vista, and XGI no longer manufactures graphics cards.

Although Microsoft has listed 128 MB of [[Video RAM]] as a requirement for &quot;Premium Ready&quot; PCs, 128 MB of memory in an ''integrated'' graphics processor is not required: a 64 MB integrated graphics processor, combined with at least 1 GB of system memory, will be able to run Aero at certain resolutions; however, the visual effects will be slower and less smooth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc507845.aspx
|title=Windows Vista Enterprise Hardware Planning Guidance
|publisher=microsoft.com
|month=February
|year=2007
|accessdate=2009-02-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt; A WDDM driver for Windows Vista or later for any given graphics processor is required to run the Aero glass theme.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://news.com.com/Vista+wont+show+fancy+side+to+pirates/2100-1016_3-6060700.html
|title=Vista won't show fancy side to pirates
|publisher=news.com.com
|month=April
|year=2006
|accessdate=2007-02-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Features new to Windows 7]]
* [[Development of Windows 7]]
* [[Features new to Windows Vista]]
* [[Development of Windows Vista]]
* [[Desktop Window Manager]]
* [[Windows Vista#Hardware requirements|Windows Vista hardware requirements]]
* [[Compositing window manager]]
* [[Aqua (user interface)|Aqua]]
* [[Compiz]]
* [[Kwin]]
* [[Metro Design Language]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Dead link header|date=June 2011}}
* [http://www.microsoft.com/windows/products/windowsvista/features/experiences/aero.mspx Windows Vista Aero User Experience]
* [http://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/cc507845.aspx 64 MB RAM supports Aero with up to 1,310,720 total pixels (1280 × 1024) but is not Premium Ready]
* [http://www.microsoft.com/technet/security/advisory/2028859.mspx Microsoft Security Advisory (2028859)], Vulnerability in Canonical Display Driver Could Allow Remote Code Execution

{{Windows Components}}
{{Window Managers}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aero}}
[[Category:Graphical user interfaces]]
[[Category:Windows Vista]]
[[Category:Microsoft Windows]]

[[ar:ويندوز إرو]]
[[cs:Windows Aero]]
[[da:Windows Aero]]
[[de:Windows Aero]]
[[es:Windows Aero]]
[[fa:آئرو ویندوز]]
[[fr:Windows Aero]]
[[ko:윈도 에어로]]
[[id:Windows Aero]]
[[it:Windows Aero]]
[[hu:Windows Aero]]
[[ms:Windows Aero]]
[[nl:Windows Aero]]
[[ja:Windows Aero]]
[[no:Windows Aero]]
[[pl:Windows Aero]]
[[pt:Windows Aero]]
[[ro:Windows Aero]]
[[ru:Windows Aero]]
[[si:වින්ඩෝස් ගගන]]
[[sk:Windows Aero]]
[[sl:Windows Aero]]
[[fi:Windows Aero]]
[[sv:Windows Aero]]
[[th:วินโดวส์แอโร่]]
[[uk:Windows Aero]]
[[zh:Windows Aero]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
