<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29089" ns="0" title="Snuff film"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the genre|the 1976 film|Snuff (film)|the 2005 film|Snuff-Movie}}
{{Refimprove|date=December 2010}}

A '''snuff film''' is a [[motion picture]] genre that depicts the actual death or [[murder]] of a person or people, without the aid of [[special effects]], for the express purpose of distribution and entertainment or financial exploitation.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Snuff films false |url=http://www.snopes.com/horrors/madmen/snuff.asp |date=2006-10-31 |accessdate=December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; For-profit snuff films are generally regarded as an [[urban legend]], whose persistence demonstrates more about our anxieties than the reality of such films being made.  Some filmed records of executions and murders exist but have not been made or released for commercial purposes.&lt;ref name = snopes&gt;[http://www.snopes.com/horrors/madmen/snuff.htm Barbara Mikkelson, &quot;A Pinch of Snuff&quot;, Snopes.com, 31 Oct 2006, accessed 8 April 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The very first recorded use of the term &quot;snuff film&quot; is in a 1971 book by [[Ed Sanders]], ''The Family: The Story of Charles Manson's Dune Buggy Attack Battalion''.  He alleges that [[Charles Manson|The Manson Family]] was involved in making such a film in California to record their murders.&lt;ref name=snopes/&gt;

The metaphorical use of the term &quot;snuff&quot; to denote killing appears to be derived from a verb for the extinguishing of a candle flame. The word has been used as such in English slang for hundreds of years. J.C. Hotten lists the term in the fifth edition of his ''Slang Dictionary'' in 1874 as a &quot;term very common among the lower orders of London, meaning to die from disease or accident.&quot; The word is descended (via the Middle English &quot;snuffen&quot; or &quot;snuppen&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bible in [[Wyclif]] tr. (i.e. 1384) ''Exodus'' xxv.38 &quot;where the snoffes ben quenchid&quot;; cf. xxxvii.23&lt;/ref&gt;) from the Old English &quot;snithan&quot;, meaning to slaughter and dismember, from &quot;snide&quot;, meaning to kill by cutting or stabbing, from &quot;snid&quot;, to cut.

The  [[Michael Powell (director)|Michael Powell]] film ''[[Peeping Tom (film)|Peeping Tom]]'' (1960) featured a filmmaker who committed murders and used the acts as the content of his documentary films.  The concept of &quot;snuff films&quot; being made for profit became more widely known in 1976 with the commercial film ''[[Snuff (1975 film)|Snuff]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;csicop.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.csicop.org/si/show/snuff_film_the_making_of_an_urban_legend/ Scott Aaron Stine, &quot;The Snuff Film: The Making of an Urban Legend&quot;], ''Skeptical Inquirer'', Volume 23.3, May / June 1999, accessed 13 Dec 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2p7i4oL6Dk &quot;Do snuff movies exist ?&quot;, Documentary, part 1], YouTube&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;David A. Cook, ''Lost Illusions: American Cinema in The Shadow of Watergate and Vietnam'', page 233 (University of California Press, Ltd., 2000). ISBN 0-520-23265-8&lt;/ref&gt; A low budget [[exploitation film|exploitation]] horror film entitled ''Slaughter'', the film was directed by [[Michael and Roberta Findlay]]. In an interview decades later, Roberta Findlay said that the film's distributor Allan Shackleton had read about snuff films being imported from [[South America]] and retitled the film to ''Snuff''  to exploit the idea;&lt;ref name=Press&gt;[http://www.nypress.com/article-11831-the-curse-of-her-filmography.html &quot;The Curse of Her Filmography : Roberta Findlay's grindhouse legacy&quot;], ''New York Press,'' July 27, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; he also added a new ending that depicted an actress being murdered on a film set.&lt;ref name=Lees&gt;[http://www.martinalees.co.uk/?p=43 Martina Lees, &quot;Death robe of secrecy hangs around snuff films&quot;], reprinted from ''Beeld,'' 18 October 2003 (originally in [[Afrikaans]]), Martina Lees Website, accessed 13 December 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The promotion of ''Snuff'' on its second release suggested it featured the murder of an actress: &quot;The  film that could only be made in South America... where life is CHEAP.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Joan Hawkins, ''Cutting Edge: Art-Horror and The Horrific Avant-Garde'', page 136 (University of Minnesota Press, 2000). ISBN 0-8166-3413-0
&lt;/ref&gt;, but that was false advertising.&lt;ref name=Lees/&gt; Shackleton put out false newspaper clippings that reported a citizens group's crusading against the film &lt;ref name=&quot;csicop.org&quot;/&gt; and hired people to act as protesters to picket screenings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britannica.com/bps/additionalcontent/18/23189619/Snuff &quot;Snuff&quot;], ''Britannica Online Encyclopedia''&lt;/ref&gt;

In the wake of ''Snuff'', numerous films explored the idea of snuff films, or used them as a plot device. They include  ''[[Last House on Dead End Street]]'' (1977), the [[Paul Schrader]] film ''[[Hardcore (1979 film)|Hardcore]]'' (1979), ''[[Bloodline (1979 film)|Sidney Sheltons's Bloodline]]'' (1979), the [[Ruggero Deodato]] film ''[[Cannibal Holocaust]]'' (1980), [[David Cronenberg|David Cronenberg's]] ''[[Videodrome]]'' (1983), the [[Nine Inch Nails]] film ''[[Broken (1993 film)|The Broken Movie]]'' (1993), the film ''[[Henry: Portrait of a Serial Killer]]'' (1986), the [[Alejandro Amenábar]] film ''[[Tesis]]'' (1996), the film ''[[Strange Days (film)|Strange Days]]'' (1995), the [[Anthony Waller]] film ''[[Mute Witness]]'' (1994), the [[Johnny Depp]] film ''[[The Brave]]'' (1997), the [[Joel Schumacher]] film ''[[8mm (film)|8mm]]'' (1999), the [[John Ottman]] film, ''[[Urban Legends: Final Cut]]'' (2000), and Fred Vogel's film ''[[August Underground]]'' (2001) and its sequels.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

Internet snuff films are alluded to in the [[Marc Evans]] film ''[[My Little Eye]]'' (2002), and the  film ''[[Halloween: Resurrection]]''. The [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] TV series ''[[Dexter (TV series)|Dexter]]'' features an internet snuff scene. Most recently the subject has been addressed in British film director [[Bernard Rose (director)|Bernard Rose]]'s film ''[[Snuff-Movie (film)|Snuff-Movie]]'' (2005), the [[Nimród Antal]] film ''[[Vacancy (film)|Vacancy]]'' (2007) and also in the WWE film ''[[The Condemned]]'' (2007) and the [[Gregory Hoblit]] film ''[[Untraceable]]''. [[Rockstar Games]], the controversial game publisher, released the snuff-themed ''[[Manhunt (video game)|Manhunt]]'' in 2003.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}

==Recorded deaths==
Some murderers have recorded their acts on video. Documentary film makers and television news crews have also captured footage of executions or accidental deaths. The resultant footage is not usually considered to constitute a snuff film because the deaths were not enacted in a for-profit film.

===Documentary footage===
The assassination of [[Alexander I of Yugoslavia]] in 1934 was one of the first to be captured on film. The sinking of the [[HMS Barham (04)|HMS Barham]] in 1941 and the [[1955 Le Mans disaster]] were both captured on film and have been widely shown since then. The American public was gripped by the [[Zapruder film]] of the [[assassination of John F. Kennedy]]. ''[[The Passenger (film)|Professione: reporter]]'', a film directed by Michelangelo Antonioni, includes film footage of a firing squad execution. The stabbing death of [[Meredith Hunter]] by a [[Hells Angels|Hell's Angel]] at the Rolling Stones [[Altamont Free Concert|concert at Altamont Speedway]] was captured and shown in [[Albert and David Maysles]]' documentary film ''[[Gimme Shelter (1970 film)|Gimme Shelter]]''. The 1995 documentary film ''Executions'' showed several executions of people condemned to death.{{citation needed|date =December 2010}}

The [[2001 Daytona 500]] witnessed the [[Death of Dale Earnhardt|death of Dale Earnhardt]] on the final lap of the event after he was in an accident. The footage of the wreck was shown on [[live television]] to viewers at home. Although Earnhardt wasn't the first NASCAR driver to die in a wreck, due to his high-profile compared to the other drivers that have died, it forced NASCAR to implement new safety regulations, such as the [[Car of Tomorrow]]. NASCAR has not replayed Earnhardt's wreck, but many videos of the incident exist on the internet. 

On [[September 11 attacks|September 11, 2001]], millions of people saw television news coverage after the attacks that included footage of people jumping to their deaths from the burning [[World Trade Center]] in [[New York City]].  

News footage or intentional political records that captured murders, executions or suicides, including those of [[Nick Berg]], [[Saddam Hussein]], [[Paul Marshall Johnson, Jr.|Paul Johnson]], [[Kim Sun-il]], [[Eugene Armstrong]], [[John F. Kennedy]], [[Daniel Pearl]], [[Inejiro Asanuma]], [[Lee Harvey Oswald]] and [[Yitzhak Rabin]], and the suicides of [[Ricardo Alfonso Cerna|Ricardo Cerna]], and [[Budd Dwyer]] have been posted on the Internet. Such footage was either of a real event and shot for documentary purposes, or the assassins filmed a murder to use the record for political purposes. The resulting footage cannot be called a snuff film according to its definition.

===Video recordings of assault===
In several cases murderers and serial killers have recorded aspects of their crimes, although they filmed their victims while still alive.  These include:
* Between 1983-85, [[Charles Ng]] and [[Leonard Lake]] videotaped their torturing some of the women whom they would later kill.&lt;ref name=snopes/&gt;
* In the early 1990s, [[serial killer]]s [[Paul Bernardo]] and [[Karla Homolka]] separately videotaped some of their sexual assaults of victims. They did not film their murders.&lt;ref name=snopes/&gt;
* In 1997 the German murderers Ernst Dieter Korzen and Stefan Michael Mahn recorded their torture of two prostitutes whom they had kidnapped. They killed one and the other woman escaped, leading to the men's arrests. They were convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment. Prosecutors claimed there was an international market for such videos, and that Korzen and Mahn intended to sell their film. Korzen and Mahn were the first persons convicted for making a snuff film, although their video was never distributed.&lt;ref name=Channel4&gt;[http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid=-2695085153314436603 &quot;Does Snuff Exist?&quot;], ''[[The Dark Side of Porn]]'', Season 2 Episode 4, [[Channel 4]] documentary, 18 April 2006&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite news
  | last = Frew
  | first = Callum
  | title = Perverts murdered woman for snuff movie
  | work =
  | publisher = ''[[Daily Record (Scotland)|The Daily Record]]''
  | date = 1999-04-13
  | url =
  | accessdate = 2008-06-17}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
===Video recordings of murder===
*In 2001, [[Armin Meiwes]] videotaped the killing of Bernd Jürgen Armando Brandes. Brandes had met with Meiwes to be willingly killed and [[cannibalism|eaten]] by him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3230774.stm|title=German 'cannibal' tells of regret|date=November 23, 2003|publisher=BBC|accessdate=August 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In 2007, a video surfaced on the internet showing Viktor Sayenko and Igor Suprunyuck, known as the [[Dnepropetrovsk maniacs]], torturing a 48-year-old disabled [[Ukrainians|Ukrainian]], who died from his injuries. Sayenko and Suprunyuck were charged with the murders of at least 19 individuals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.unian.net/eng/news/news-204617.html|title=Three 19-year old youths committed 19 murders in Dnipropetrovsk during a month|date=July 24, 2007|publisher=Unian|accessdate=August 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In December 2009, ex-Col. [[Russell Williams]] was charged with sexually assaulting two women and killing two others. He videotaped the rapes and murders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/10/20/world/americas/20canada.html|title=Canadian Commander Videotaped Murders|date=October 19, 2010|publisher=New York Times|last=Austin|first=Ian|accessdate=August 20, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==False snuff films==
===The Guinea Pig films===
{{Main|Guinea Pig (film series)}}
The first two films in the Japanese ''Guinea Pig'' series are designed to look like snuff films; the video is grainy and unsteady, as if recorded by amateurs. In the late 1980s, the Guinea Pig films were allegedly one of the inspirations for Japanese serial killer [[Tsutomu Miyazaki]]'s murders of preschool girls.  The Guinea Pig film he owned was &quot;Mermaid in a Manhole&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.crimelibrary.com/criminal_mind/psychology/movies_made_me_kill/11.html
| title = Serial killer inspired by Guinea Pig films
| accessdate = 2008-06-17
| publisher = guineapigfilms.com
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After viewing a portion of ''[[Flower of Flesh and Blood]]'', the actor [[Charlie Sheen]] thought that the murder depicted was genuine and contacted the [[MPAA]], which contacted the [[FBI]]. FBI agent Dan Codling informed Sheen and the MPAA that the FBI and the Japanese authorities were already investigating the film makers, who were forced to prove that the murders were fake.&lt;ref name=snopes/&gt;  While the Guinea Pig films are not snuff films, two were purported to be based on snuff films. ''The Devil's Experiment'' was supposedly based on a film sent to the Tokyo police showing a group dismember a young woman. Although ''Flower of Flesh and Blood'' was supposedly made after manga artist, [[Hideshi Hino]], received snuff materials, it was based on his own ''manga''.&lt;ref name=snopes/&gt;

===Cannibal Holocaust===
{{Main|Cannibal Holocaust}}

The Italian director [[Ruggero Deodato]] was charged after rumors that the murders of people in his 1980 film ''[[Cannibal Holocaust]]'' were real. He was able to clear himself of the charges.&lt;ref name=&quot;In the Jungle&quot;&gt;{{cite video | people = Ruggero Deodato (interviewee) |date = 2003 | title = In the Jungle: The Making of Cannibal Holocaust | medium = Documentary | location = Italy | publisher = Alan Young Pictures}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other than graphic gore, the film contains several scenes of sexual violence and the [[cruelty to animals|genuine deaths]] of 6 animals onscreen and one off screen, issues which find ''Cannibal Holocaust'' in the midst of controversy to this day. It has also been claimed that ''Cannibal Holocaust'' is banned in over 50 countries,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite DVD-notes |title=Cannibal Holocaust 25th Anniversary Edition |titleyear=1980 |director=[[Ruggero Deodato]] |format=back cover |publisher=[[VIPCO (Video Instant Picture Company)]] |location=UK |publisherid=VIP666SE |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; although this has never been verified. In 2006, ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' magazine named ''Cannibal Holocaust'' as the 20th most controversial film of all-time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ew.com/ew/article/commentary/0,6115,1202623_1%7C%7C233612%7C1_0_,00.html | title=The 25 Most Controversial Films of All-Time | publisher=Entertainment Weekly | accessdate=2006-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Russian child snuff ring==
In 2000 a [[United Kingdom|British]] investigation led to an international effort to seize materials and break up a gang of [[child pornography|child pornographers]] based in [[Russia]].  They were reportedly offering pornographic films of child abuse, in which some died from torture, for sale to clients in Italy, Germany, the U.S. and Valdivia. Italian police investigators were also involved. The British paper ''The Observer'' reported, &quot;The Italian investigators say the material includes footage of children dying during abuse. Prosecutors in Naples are considering charging those who bought the videos with complicity in murder.&quot;&lt;ref name=Burke&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/uk_news/story/0,,375883,00.html Jason Burke in London, Amelia Gentleman in Moscow, Philip Willan in Rome: &quot;British link to 'snuff' videos&quot;], ''The Observer,'' 1 October 2000, accessed 13 December 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|2}}

;Further reading
*David Kerekes and David Slater. ''Killing for Culture: Death Film from Mondo to Snuff (Creation Cinema Collection)''. London: Creation Books, 1996.

==External links==
&lt;!--==========================({{NoMoreLinks}})============================
    | PLEASE BE CAUTIOUS IN ADDING MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA  |
    | IS NOT A COLLECTION OF LINKS NOR SHOULD IT BE USED FOR ADVERTISING. |
    |                                                                     |
    |           Excessive or inappropriate links WILL BE DELETED.         |
    | See [[Wikipedia:External links]] &amp; [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.  |
    |                                                                     |
    | If there are already plentiful links, please propose additions or   |
    | replacements on this article's discussion page. Or submit your link |
    | to the relevant category at the Open Directory Project (dmoz.org)   |
    | and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.         |
    =========================({{NoMoreLinks}})=============================--&gt;
*{{dmoz|Society/Folklore/Literature/Urban_Legends/Snuff_Films}}
{{Film genres}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Snuff Film}}
[[Category:Film genres]]
[[Category:Filmed deaths]]
[[Category:Murder]]
[[Category:Urban legends]]
[[Category:Violence]]
[[Category:Death hoaxes]]

[[ca:Snuff movie]]
[[da:Dødsporno]]
[[de:Snuff-Film]]
[[es:Película snuff]]
[[fr:Snuff movie]]
[[ko:스너프 필름]]
[[it:Film snuff]]
[[he:סרט סנאף]]
[[nl:Snuff]]
[[ja:スナッフフィルム]]
[[pl:Snuff film]]
[[pt:Filme snuff]]
[[ru:Снафф (видео)]]
[[fi:Snuff-elokuva]]
[[sv:Snuff]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
