<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29099572" ns="0" title="Crest of Paris Saint-Germain F.C."><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The first crest of [[Paris Saint-Germain F.C.]] appeared in 1970 and consisted of a ball and a vessel which are powerful symbols of the city of Paris. It was used during the following three seasons. After [[Paris FC]] split from Stade Saint-Germain, which kept with the name of Paris Saint-Germain, it was changed to the current and historic crest: the red silhouette of the [[Eiffel Tower]] and the white royal cradle of Louis XIV between its legs on a blue background with white edging. It was the first time that the symbols of both cities, Paris and [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]], were represented on the same crest. According to [[Robert Vicot]], the crest was the ingenious idea of professional designer Mr. Vallot. It inspired Daniel Hechter to design an [[Colors of Paris Saint-Germain F.C.|iconic shirt]] which became a strong symbol of the club.&lt;ref name=&quot;psghe&quot;&gt;{{cite news 
| title = Historique des Écussons
| url = http://psg70.free.fr/accueil.htm
| work = PSG70
| accessdate = 7 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Iconic crest==
[[File:Blason Saint-Germain-en-Laye.svg|thumb|right|120px|Coat of arms of [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]].]]
Paris Saint-Germain's first crest appeared in 1970 and had a ball and a vessel which are powerful symbols of the city of Paris. It was used during the following three seasons. In 1973, after [[Paris FC]] split from Stade Saint-Germain, which kept with the name of Paris Saint-Germain, it was changed to the current and historic crest: the [[Eiffel Tower]] in red and the royal cradle underneath it on a blue background with white edging. It was the first time that the symbols of both cities, [[Paris]] and [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]], were represented on the same crest. According to former coach [[Robert Vicot]], the crest, although claimed by [[Daniel Hechter]], was instead been invented by amateur coach and professional designer Mr. Vallot. It was him who had the ingenious idea of placing the birthplace of Louis XIV between the legs of the Eiffel Tower.&lt;ref name=&quot;psghe&quot;/&gt; 

The historic crest represents Paris, in its employment of the Eiffel Tower, and [[Saint-Germain-en-Laye]], through the ''berceau royale'' or royal cradle taken from its coat of arms. [[Louis XIV of France|Louis XIV]] was born in the [[Château de Saint-Germain-en-Laye|Château de Saint-Germain]] (the city's [[coat of arms]] consequently shows a cradle and the date of his birth). This reference to Louis XIV in the club's badge is very important because he increased the power and influence of [[France]] over [[Europe]], thus the country achieving political, military and cultural power that contributed to the prestige of France, its population and language. Also the club's crest, reflects the merger of Paris FC and Stade Saint-Germain, into a new club. This is similar to the way &quot;United&quot; in [[Football in England|English football]] reflects the merger of two or more clubs into a new one (e.g., [[Newcastle United F.C.|Newcastle United]], [[Hereford United]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title = Paris St-Germain: The Who, What, Where and How?
| url = http://www.bigsoccer.com/forum/showthread.php?t=181703
| work = [[BigSoccer]]
| date = 25 March 2005
| accessdate = 21 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Changes==
The new crest would eventually inspire Daniel Hechter to design an iconic shirt which would become a strong symbol of the club. It was composed of a blue shirt with a red central vertical bar framed by white edgings. Hechter maintained the crest but, during the mid-[[80's]], added an image of the [[Parc des Princes]] underneath it. Between 1986 and 1988, the crest changed radically as Paris Saint-Germain adopted the logo of the Paris bid to host the [[1992 Summer Olympics]]. After the end of the 1987-88 season, the crest with the [[Parc des Princes]] underneath it was restored and lasted until 1991, when [[Canal +]] bought the club. The French television channel reinstated the historic crest, dropping the image of the Parc des Princes and changing from gold to white the royal cradle. However, the following year, the club's crest was completely changed, dropping the historic design and creating a new one, with the acronym &quot;PSG&quot; and underneath it &quot;Paris Saint-Germain&quot;. 

This caused the supporters' anger and the historic crest returned to PSG's shirt. Nevertheless, Canal+'s design, persisted and was mainly used for the direction of the club's communication. In 1996, the club returned to the 'historical' crest but it suffered slight changes and was given a more modern touch. The club's name, &quot;Paris Saint-Germain&quot;, and date of foundation, &quot;1970&quot;, were added above the Eiffel Tower and underneath the royal cradle respectively. Notwithstanding, that same year, the logo was somewhat modified by [[Opel]], the club's major sponsor and partner. Even if this logo was never officially adopted, it appeared in promotional materials. PSG's current crest was unveiled for the first time in 2002. The crest suffered, once again, slight changes in its colours. The current crest consists of a red silhouette of the Eiffel Tower with Louis XIV's royal white cradle underneath it and a dark blue background, which is now a dominant color in the club's shirt.&lt;ref name=&quot;psghe&quot;/&gt;

==Special Editions==
Between 1986 and 1988, the crest changed radically as Paris Saint-Germain adopted the logo of the Paris bid to host the [[1992 Summer Olympics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psghe&quot;/&gt; During the 2006-07 season, Paris Saint Germain wore a &quot;chocolate&quot; colour away shirt that intended to represent the fashion and glamour of [[Paris]] with monograms à la [[Louis Vuitton]] that clearly embody the powerful symbols of the French capital.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news 
| title = Historique des Maillots
| url = http://psg70.free.fr/accueil.htm
| work = PSG70
| accessdate = 29 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crest was also restyled with yellow colours à la retro.&lt;ref name=&quot;psghe&quot;/&gt; In [[2010–11 Paris Saint-Germain F.C. season|2010]], PSG celebrated its 40th anniversary and the shirt commemorated this fact by presenting a special crest. A golden embroidery encircled the crest with the traditional dates 1970 and 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| title = Paris Saint-Germain 10/11 Nike kits
| url = http://s.psg.fr/psg/file/201006/Final_10123-PSGnews-400x280.pdf
| work = PSG.fr
| date = 29 June 2010
| accessdate = 23 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Paris Saint-Germain Football Club}}
;Official Websites
*{{fr icon}} {{en icon}} [http://www.psg.fr/ PSG.fr]
*{{fr icon}} {{en icon}} [http://www.ligue1.com/club/paris-saint-germain Paris Saint-Germain] at [[Ligue 1]]
*{{fr icon}} {{en icon}} [http://www.uefa.com/teamsandplayers/teams/club=52747/profile/index.html Paris Saint-Germain] at [[UEFA]]

;News Sites
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.leparisien.fr/psg-foot-paris-saint-germain.php Paris Saint-Germain News] from [[Le Parisien]]
*{{fr icon}} [http://www.lequipe.fr/Football/FootballFicheClub26.html Paris Saint-Germain News] from [[L'Equipe]]
*{{en icon}} [http://www.skysports.com/football/teams/parisstgermain/ Paris Saint-Germain News] from [[Sky Sports]]
*{{en icon}} [http://soccernet.espn.go.com/team/_/id/160/paris-saint-germain-?cc=3888 Paris Saint-Germain News] from [[ESPN]]

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Real Zaragoza]] | title = [[UEFA Cup Winners' Cup|UEFA Cup Winners' Cup Winner]] | years = 1996 &lt;br&gt; Runner up: [[SK Rapid Wien|Rapid Vienna]]| after = [[FC Barcelona|Barcelona]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Paris Saint-Germain F.C.}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:Paris Saint-Germain F.C.]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
