<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="291036" ns="0" title="Amber Room"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|The Amber Room|the book|The Amber Room (novel)}}

[[Image:Oldamberroom.jpg|thumb|The Amber Room before WWII]]
[[Image:Bernsteinzimmer02.jpg|right|thumb|Reconstructed Amber Room]]

The '''Amber Room''' (In English sometimes known as ''Amber Chamber'', {{lang-ru|''Янтарная комната''}} ''Yantarnaya komnata'', {{lang-de|Bernsteinzimmer}}) in the [[Catherine Palace]] of [[Tsarskoye Selo]] near [[Saint Petersburg]] is a complete chamber decoration of [[amber]] panels backed with [[gold]] leaf and [[mirror]]s. Due to its singular beauty, it was sometimes dubbed the &quot;[[Eighth Wonder of the World]]&quot;.
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:oldamberroom.jpg|thumb|right|375px|Amber Room, as reassembled by the Germans in the [[Königsberg Castle]] during [[World War II|WWII]].]]  --&gt;

Before it was lost, the original Amber Room represented a joint effort of German and Russian craftsmen. Construction of the Amber Room began in 1701 to 1709 in [[Prussia]]. The room was designed by German baroque sculptor [[Andreas Schlüter]] and constructed by the Danish amber craftsman [[Gottfried Wolfram]] and remained at [[Charlottenburg Palace]] until 1716 when it was given by Prussian king [[Frederick William I of Prussia|Friedrich Wilhelm I]] to his then ally, [[Tsar]] [[Peter I of Russia|Peter the Great]] of the [[Russian Empire]]. In Russia it was expanded and after several renovations, it covered more than 55 square meters and contained over six tons of amber. The Amber Room was [[looted art|looted]] during [[World War II]] by [[Nazi Germany]] and brought to [[Königsberg]]. Knowledge of its whereabouts was lost in the chaos at the end of the war. 

In 1979 efforts began to rebuild the Amber room at [[Tsarskoye Selo]]. In 2003, after decades of work by Russian craftsmen, financed by donations from Germany, the reconstructed Amber Room was inaugurated in the Catherine Palace in Saint Petersburg, Russia.

==History==
===Creation===
[[Image:Catherine Palace Amber Room.jpg|thumb|Section of the reconstructed Amber Room.]]

The Amber Room was made from 1701 onwards in order to be installed at [[Charlottenburg Palace]], home of [[Frederick I of Prussia|Friedrich I]], the first king of [[Prussia]], at the urging of his second wife, [[Sophia Charlotte of Hanover|Sophie Charlotte]]. The concept of the room and its design was by [[Andreas Schlüter]]. It was crafted by Gottfried Wolfram, master [[artisan|craftsman]] to the [[Denmark|Danish]] court of King [[Frederick IV of Denmark]], with help from the amber masters Ernst Schacht and Gottfried Turau from Danzig (now [[Gdańsk]]).&lt;ref&gt;Blumberg, Jess. [http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history-archaeology/brief_amber.html A Brief History of the Amber Room], [[Smithsonian Magazine]]. Retrieved: 3 April 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

It did not, however, remain at Charlottenburg for long. Peter the Great admired it on a visit and in 1716, [[Frederick William I of Prussia|Friedrich Wilhelm I]], the first king's son, presented it to him, and with that act cemented a Prussian-Russian alliance against [[Sweden]].
The Amber Room represented a joint effort of German and Russian craftsmen. After several other 18th-century renovations, it covered more than 55 square meters and contained over six [[tonne]]s of amber. It took over ten years to construct.

===World War II evacuation===
Shortly after the beginning of the German invasion of the [[Soviet Union]] in World War II ([[Operation Barbarossa]]), the curators responsible for removing the art treasures in [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]] tried to disassemble and remove the Amber Room. Over the years the amber had dried out and become brittle, so that when they tried to remove it, the fragile amber started to crumble. The Amber Room was therefore hidden behind mundane [[wallpaper]], in an attempt to keep [[Nazism|Nazi]] forces from seizing it. However, the attempt to hide such a well-known piece of art failed.

German soldiers disassembled the Amber Room within 36 hours under the supervision of two experts. On 14 October 1941, Rittmeister Graf Solms-Laubach commanded the evacuation of 27 crates to [[Königsberg]] in [[East Prussia]], for storage and display in the town's castle. On 13 November 1941, the newspaper ''Königsberger Allgemeine Zeitung'' reported on an exhibition of part of the Bernsteinzimmer in [[Königsberg Castle]].

===Last days in Königsberg===
Orders by Hitler given on 21 January 1945 and 24 January 1945 allowed the movement of possessions. From that day onwards, [[Albert Speer]]'s administration could move culture goods of priority &quot;I (o)&quot;. [[Erich Koch]] was in charge in Königsberg. Eyewitnesses claimed that crates had been sighted at the railway station. They might have been put aboard the ''[[Wilhelm Gustloff (ship)|Wilhelm Gustloff]]'' which left [[Gdynia|Gotenhafen (Gdynia)]] on 30 January 1945, and was sunk by a Soviet submarine.&lt;ref&gt;Lucas, Last Days of the Reich, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;

In the summer of 1944, Königsberg was heavily bombed by the [[Royal Air Force]]. It suffered further extensive damage at the hands of the advancing Soviets before and after its fall on 9 April 1945. It remained thereafter under Soviet control, eventually renamed Kaliningrad. The remains of the castle were destroyed by the Red Army during the 1960s.

===Disappearance and mystery===
The Amber Room was never seen again, though reports have occasionally surfaced stating that components of the Amber Room survived the war. Indeed, two elements of the room's decoration (but not the amber panels themselves) were eventually rediscovered (see below).

There have been numerous conflicting reports and theories, among them that the Amber Room was destroyed by bombing, hidden in a now-lost subterranean bunker in Königsberg, buried in mines in the [[Ore Mountains (Germany)|Ore Mountains]], or taken onto a ship or [[submarine]] which was sunk by Soviet forces in the [[Baltic Sea]].

Many different individuals and groups, including a number of different entities from the government of the Soviet Union, have mounted extensive searches for it at various times since the war, without any success. At one point in 1998, two separate teams (one in Germany, the other in Lithuania) announced that they had located the Amber Room, the first in a silver mine, the second buried in a [[lagoon]]; neither produced the Amber Room.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScotlandSunday2006&quot;&gt;{{cite news | first = Allan | last = Hall | url = http://scotlandonsunday.scotsman.com/index.cfm?id=577192006 | title = Amber Room hunt makes lake the Tsar attraction | work = [[Scotland on Sunday]] | date = 16 April 2006 | accessdate = 2007-06-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in 1997 one Italian stone mosaic that was part of a set of four which had decorated the Amber Room did turn up in western [[Germany]], in the possession of the family of a soldier who had helped pack up the Amber Room.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video | people = Yutaka Shigenobu (Producer) |date= 2006 | title= The Amber Room: Lost in Time (Part I) | medium= Documentary | publisher= [[NHK]] | time= approx. 31:00}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Destruction theory===
[[Image:Tsárskoye Seló - Amber Room.jpg|right|thumb|Reconstructed amber room detail]]

Recently, British [[investigative journalist]]s Catherine Scott-Clark and Adrian Levy,  conducted lengthy research on the fate of the Amber Room, including extensive archival research in Russia. In 2004 their book, ''The Amber Room: The Fate of the World's Greatest Lost Treasure'', concluded that the Amber Room was most likely destroyed when Königsberg Castle was burned down, shortly after Königsberg surrendered to occupying Soviet forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScotlandSunday2006&quot;/&gt;

Documents from the archives showed that that was also the conclusion of the report of Alexander Brusov, chief of the first formal mission sent by the Soviet government to find the Amber Room, who wrote in June, 1945: &quot;Summarizing all the facts, we can say that the Amber Room was destroyed between 9 and 11 April 1945&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | first = Catherine | last = Scott-Clark | coauthors = Adrian Levy | title = The Amber Room: The Untold Story of the Greatest Hoax of the Twentieth Century | publisher = Atlantic Books | location = London | year = 2004 | isbn = 1-84354-340-0 | oclc = 56452462 | pages = 356–57 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some years later, Brusov gave a contrary opinion; the book authors insinuate that this change of opinion was likely due to pressure from other Soviet officials, who did not want to be seen as responsible for the loss of the Amber Room.&lt;ref&gt;Scott-Clark and Levy (op cit.), pp. 330, 309&lt;/ref&gt;

Among other information from the archives was the revelation that the remains of the rest of the set of Italian stone mosaics were found in the burned debris of the castle.&lt;ref&gt;Scott-Clark and Levy (op cit.), pp. 322-323, 328&lt;/ref&gt; The authors' reasoning as to why the Soviets conducted extensive searches for the Amber Room in the years after WWII, even though their own experts had concluded that it was destroyed, is that it served the differing motives of several elements in the Soviet government: some wished to obscure (even from other branches of the Soviet government) the fact that Soviet soldiers may have been responsible for its destruction; others found the theft of the Amber Room a useful [[Cold War]] [[propaganda]] tool, and did not want to let go of a grievance that could be aired advantageously; still others did not want to share the blame for its destruction (through their failure to evacuate the Amber Room to safety at the start of the war).&lt;ref&gt;Scott-Clark and Levy (op cit.), pp. 108-109, 325&lt;/ref&gt;

Russian officials have denied the book's conclusions - angrily, in some cases. According to Adelaida Yolkina, senior researcher at the Pavlovsk Museum Estate: &quot;It is impossible to see the Red Army being so careless that they let the Amber Room be destroyed.&quot; Other Russian experts were less sceptical, and had a different emphasis in their responses. Mikhail Piotrovsky, director of the State [[Hermitage Museum]], was very cautious in his comments, and said: &quot;Most importantly, the destruction of the Amber Room during the Second World War is fault of the people who started the war&quot;. In reply, Catherine Scott-Clark, one of the authors, indicated that they only came to their conclusions with reluctance: &quot;when we started working on this issue we were hoping to be able to find the Amber Room.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Scott-Clark and Levy (op cit.), pp. 301-313&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the book came out, a Russian veteran has given an interview in which he confirmed their basic conclusion as to the fate of the Amber Room, although he denies that the fires were deliberate. &quot;I probably was one of the last people who saw the Amber Room&quot;, said Leonid Arinshtein, a literature expert with the nongovernmental Russian Culture Foundation, who was a Red Army lieutenant in charge of a rifle platoon in Königsberg in 1945. &quot;The Red Army didn't burn anything&quot;, he said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.sptimes.ru/index.php?action_id=2&amp;story_id=751 | title=Outrage At Amber Room Book | accessdate=2007-06-26 | author= | last= Stolyarova |first= Galina |date=15 June 2004 | work=[[Saint Petersburg Times (Russia)|Saint Petersburg Times]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A variation of this theory is common currency amongst present-day residents of Kaliningrad. This is that part at least of the room was found in the cellars after WWII by the Red Army, in relatively good condition. This was not admitted at the time in order that blame should continue to rest upon the Germans. To preserve this story access to the ruins of the castle, which were substantial after WWII, was restricted, even to historical/archaeological surveys. During the 1960s, access to the site was suddenly withheld and the ruins were blown up by the Army, sealing any access to the underground area. The [[Dom Sovyetov of Kaliningrad|Dom Sovetov]] was built over the central area. The remains of the room may still be sited underground; however, as mentioned above, amber which is not cared for will crumble into dust. It is presumed that this is what has happened and that the Russian authorities, even after Communism, have been unwilling to admit this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  | url = http://msnbc.msn.com/id/5174876 | first = Vladimir | last = Isachenkov | title = Mystery of the Amber Room resurfaces | work = [[MSNBC|MSNBC.com]] | date = 9 June 2004 | accessdate = 2007-06-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Reconstructions===
*In [[Kleinmachnow]], near Berlin, there is a miniature Amber Room, fabricated after the original. The Berlin miniature collector [[Ulla Klingbeil]] had this copy made of original [[East Prussia]]n amber. The exhibit fee at [[Europarc Dreilinden]] is donated to the [[Arilex-Verein Foundation]] to aid handicapped children.

*In 1979 a reconstruction effort began at [[Tsarskoye Selo]], based largely on black and white photographs of the original Amber Room. Financial difficulties to the project were solved with USD $3.5 million donated by the [[Germany|German]] company [[Ruhrgas AG]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | author = [[RIA Novosti]] | work = [[Pravda|Pravda.RU]] | title = Restoration of the Amber Chamber is Coming to an End | date =  8 May 2003  | url = http://newsfromrussia.com/science/2003/05/08/46754.html | accessdate = 2007-06-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By 2003, the titanic work of the Russian craftsmen was mostly completed. The new room was dedicated by Russian President [[Vladimir Putin]] and German Chancellor [[Gerhard Schröder]] at the 300-year anniversary of the city of Saint Petersburg.

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Bernsteinzimmer01.jpg
Image:Bernsteinzimmer05.jpg
Image:Bernsteinzimmer06.jpg
Image:Bernsteinzimmer03.jpg
Image:amberroomdetail.jpg|Detail of the reconstructed Amber Room
Image:Amber Room Reconstruction-Workshop.JPG|Reconstruction-workshop of the Amber Room
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Appearances in fiction==
The mystery of the Amber Room has been the basis for the plot of several films, books and art exhibitions.
* [http://www.amazon.com/dp/1556612850 ''The Amber Room''], novel by [[T. Davis Bunn]]
* ''[[The Amber Room (novel)|The Amber Room]]'', novel by [[Steve Berry (novelist)|Steve Berry]]
* [http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/pl.cgi?FSFAUG95 ''The Amber Room''], novelette by [[Ian Watson (author)|Ian Watson]]
* [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0956158102/ ''Death in Amber''], novel by Dean Fetzer
* ''Amber Beach'', by [[Elizabeth Lowell]]
* &quot;The Amber Secret&quot; Novel by Peter Slaney
* ''[[The Black Sun (James Twining)|The Black Sun]]'', by [[James Twining]]
* ''The Devil Dances for Gold'' by Regina Ross
* ''Mosaic'', by [[Gayle Lynds]]
* [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0671019554/ &quot;Cold Hit&quot;], by [[Linda Fairstein]]
* ''[[The 39 Clues]]: [[The Black Circle]]'', by [[Patrick Carman]]
* ''El salón de ámbar'' by [[Matilde Asensi]]
* ''The Brutal Telling'' by [[Louise Penny]]
* The USA Network television series, ''[[White Collar (TV series)|White Collar]]'', refers to the Amber Room extensively, especially in in episode 1x08, ''Hard Sell''. It is revealed to one of the series' protagonists, Neal Caffrey, that his nemesis, &quot;The Man With The Ring&quot;, and his former lover, Kate Moreau, want an amber music box that is supposedly a remnant of the room.  The alleged reason is that the box, while not overly valuable in its own right, contains some kind of secret information.  Caffrey is assumed to have stolen the music box (he did not actually do so), and must locate the box in order to free Kate from &quot;The Man With the Ring&quot;.

==See also==
* ''[[Štěchovice Treasure]]'' (believed by some to contain the room)

==References==
===Citations===
{{reflist|2}}
&lt;!-- Dead note &quot;9&quot;: Conversations by the writer with officials of the Kaliningrad Amber Mine and others in 1993/95. --&gt;
*[http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/0,1518,536358,00.html Der Spiegel interview of Heinz-Peter Haustein]

===Other sources===
* {{cite book | first = Peter | last = Bruhn | title = Das Bernsteinzimmer in Zarskoje Selo bei Sankt Petersburg : Bibliographie mit über 3800 Literaturnachweisen aus den Jahren 1790 bis 2003 : von der Schenkung des Bernsteinzimmers durch den König von Preussen an den Zar, über das ungeklärte Verschwinden des Bernsteinzimmers im Zweiten Weltkrieg, bis zur Vollendung der Rekonstruktion des Bernsteinzimmers im Jahre 2003 | location = Berlin | publisher = Bock &amp; Kübler | year = 2004 | isbn = 3-86155-109-8 | oclc = 63196950 | language = German }} (International bibliography of publications about the Amber Room)
* {{cite book | first = Suzanne | last = Massie | title = Pavlovsk: The Life Of A Russian Palace | publisher = Little Brown | location = Boston | year = 1990 | isbn = 0316549703 | oclc = 21443818 }}
* {{cite book | first = Catherine | last = Scott-Clark | coauthors = Adrian Levy | title = The Amber Room: The Untold Story of the Greatest Hoax of the Twentieth Century | publisher = Atlantic Books | location = London | year = 2004 | isbn = 1-84354-340-0 | oclc = 56452462 }}

==External links==
{{commonscat|Amber room}}
* [http://www.ib.hu-berlin.de/~pbruhn/bernzim.htm Bibliographical Database of the International literature about the Amber Room] by Peter Bruhn
* [http://www.guide-guru.com/amber_room.htm Amber Room Recreation - Recollection of an Eye-witness]
* [http://www.amberroom.org AmberRoom.Org: History, Photographs and Research]
*[http://tarotcanada.tripod.com/TheAmberRoom.html  The Amber Room: Tears of the Gods]
* [http://www.fatemag.com/2005_06art3.html Mysteries of the Lost Amber Room]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/143364.stm On the Trail of The Amber Room] - BBC, August 1, 1998
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3025833.stm Peter the Great's amber room reborn] - BBC, 14 May 2003
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/3738593.stm New theory on Russian art riddle] BBC, 24 May 2004
* [http://marketplace.publicradio.org/display/web/2008/02/21/german_amber_room What to do with a German treasure] - APM Market Place 21 Feb, 2008
* [http://www.sptimes.ru/index.php?action_id=2&amp;story_id=751 Outrage At Amber Room Book] Saint Petersburg Times
* [http://msnbc.msn.com/id/5174876 Mystery of the Amber Room resurfaces] MSNBC
*[http://www.tzar.ru/a-r/1st/ The Amber Room on the Web]
* [http://abcnews.go.com/GMA/popup?id=4189526 Photos Of Amber Room Good Morning America]
*{{cite news |first=Stephen |last=Kinzer |title=Weimar Journal; Amber-Tinted Rumors Whisper of Buried Booty |url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE1E38F934A15756C0A964958260
|publisher=New York Times |date=27 May 1992 |accessdate=2008-03-24}}

{{Showplaces in Ekaterininsky park of Tsarskoye Selo}}
{{Coord|59|42|57|N|30|23|44|E|region:RU_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:Individual rooms]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:Art museums and galleries in Russia]]
[[Category:Lost works of art]]

[[af:Barnsteenkamer]]
[[bg:Кехлибарена стая]]
[[cs:Jantarová komnata]]
[[da:Ravrummet]]
[[de:Bernsteinzimmer]]
[[es:Cámara de Ámbar]]
[[fr:Chambre d'ambre]]
[[he:חדר הענבר]]
[[lt:Gintaro kambarys]]
[[nl:Barnsteenkamer]]
[[ja:琥珀の間]]
[[no:Ravrommet]]
[[pl:Bursztynowa Komnata]]
[[pt:Câmara de Âmbar]]
[[ru:Янтарная комната]]
[[sk:Jantárová komnata]]
[[fi:Meripihkahuone]]
[[sv:Bärnstensrummet]]
[[th:ห้องอำพัน]]
[[vi:Căn phòng hổ phách]]
[[zh:琥珀宫]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
