<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29114964" ns="0" title="Genetic history of the Iberian Peninsula"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
|wikify = November 2010
|sections = November 2010
|POV-check = September 2011
|unbalanced = September 2011
}}

The ancestry of modern Iberians (Spanish and Portuguese) is consistent with the geographical situation of the [[Iberian Peninsula]] in the south-west of Europe''':''' there are strong connections with both [[Southern Europe|Mediterranean Europe]] and [[Atlantic Europe]].

[[File:Y-Haplogroup R1 distribution.png|thumb|350px|Distribution of [[Haplogroup R1a (Y-DNA)|R1a]] (purple) and '''[[Haplogroup R1b (Y-DNA)|R1b]]''' (red). (Black represents all other haplogroups)]]

== Links with other European populations ==
DNA analysis shows that the Spanish and Portuguese are most closely related to other populations of western  Europe: the [[French people|French]], the [[Italians]], the [[Irish people|Irish]], the [[United Kingdom|British]], the [[Germans]], and the [[Swiss (people)|Swiss]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1371/journal.pone.0005472 |title=Genetic Structure of Europeans: A View from the North–East |year=2009 |last1=Nelis |editor1-first=Robert C. |first1=Mari |first2=Tõnu |first3=Reedik |editor1-last=Fleischer |first4=Fritz |first5=Alexander |first6=Draga |first7=Sena |first8=Tereza |first9=Ivan |journal=PLoS ONE |volume=4 |pages=e5472 |pmid=19424496 |issue=5 |pmc=2675054 |last2=Esko |last3=Mägi |last4=Zimprich |last5=Zimprich |last6=Toncheva |last7=Karachanak |last8=Piskácková |last9=Balascák |bibcode=2009PLoSO...4.5472N}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dupanloup2004&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1093/molbev/msh135 |title=Estimating the Impact of Prehistoric Admixture on the Genome of Europeans |year=2004 |last1=Dupanloup |first1=I. |journal=Molecular Biology and Evolution |volume=21 |page=1361 |pmid=15044595 |first2=G |first3=L |first4=G |issue=7 |last2=Bertorelle |last3=Chikhi |last4=Barbujani}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Nicholas |last=Wade |date=13 August 2008 |title=The Genetic Map of Europe |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/13/science/13visual.html |work=[[The New York Times]] |accessdate=17 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1038/nature07331 |laysummary=http://www.gnxp.com/blog/2008/08/genetic-map-of-europe-again.php |laysource=Gene Expression |laydate=31 August 2008 |title=Genes mirror geography within Europe |year=2008 |last1=Novembre |first1=John |first2=Toby |first3=Katarzyna |first4=Zoltán |first5=Adam R. |first6=Adam |first7=Amit |first8=Karen S. |first9=Sven |journal=Nature |volume=456 |page=98 |pmid=18758442 |issue=7218 |pmc=2735096 |last2=Johnson |last3=Bryc |last4=Kutalik |last5=Boyko |last6=Auton |last7=Indap |last8=King |last9=Bergmann}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2007 European-wide study including Spanish Basques and Valencian Spaniards, found Iberian populations to cluster the furthest from other continental groups, implying that Iberia holds the most ancient European ancestry. In this study, the most prominent genetic stratification in Europe was found to run from the north to the south-east, while another important axis of differentiation runs east-west across the continent. It also found, despite the differences, that all Europeans are closely related.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1086/513477 |pmc=1852743 |url=http://vetinari.sitesled.com/euroaims.pdf |title=Measuring European Population Stratification with Microarray Genotype Data |year=2007 |last1=Bauchet |first1=M |journal=The American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=80 |page=948 |pmid=17436249 |last2=McEvoy |first2=B |last3=Pearson |first3=LN |last4=Quillen |first4=EE |last5=Sarkisian |first5=T |last6=Hovhannesyan |first6=K |last7=Deka |first7=R |last8=Bradley |first8=DG |last9=Shriver |first9=MD |issue=5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A controversial study, published in January 2010, claimed that Europeans (including Spaniards and Portuguese) are of a nearly equal combination of the European hunter gatherers of the earlier [[Paleolithic]] period and more recent [[Neolithic]] period ancestry from the Near East, that likely came from [[Anatolia]]. After initially focusing upon E1b1b as a Neolithic marker, the study looked at the male Y haplogroup R1b1b, which is much more common in [[Western Europe]]. Mark Jobling said: &quot;We focused on the commonest Y-chromosome lineage in Europe, carried by about 110 million men, it follows a gradient from south-east to north-west, reaching almost 100% frequency in Ireland. We looked at how the lineage is distributed, how diverse it is in different parts of Europe, and how old it is.&quot; The results suggested that the lineage [[Haplogroup R1b (Y-DNA)|R1b1b2 (R-M269)]], like [[Haplogroup E1b1b (Y-DNA)|E1b1b]] or [[Haplogroup J (Y-DNA)|J]] lineages, spread together with farming from the Near East. Dr Patricia Balaresque added: &quot;In total, this means that more than 80% of European Y chromosomes descend from incoming farmers. In contrast, most maternal genetic lineages seem to descend from hunter-gatherers. To us, this suggests a reproductive advantage for farming males over indigenous hunter-gatherer males during the switch from hunting and gathering, to farming&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Balaresque et al. 2010, [http://www.plosbiology.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000285 A Predominantly Neolithic Origin for European Paternal Lineages]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2010/jan/19/british-men-ancient-farmers Most British men are descended from ancient farmers], [[The Guardian]], 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/8467623.stm Most European males 'descended from farmers'], [[BBC News]], 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-1244654/Study-finds-Britons-descended-farmers-left-Iraq-Syria-10-000-years-ago.html Study finds Britons are descended from farmers who left Iraq and Syria 10,000 years ago], [[Daily Mail]], 20 January 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.plosbiology.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pbio.1000285 |title=A Predominantly Neolithic Origin for European Paternal Lineages |author=Balaresque P, Bowden GR, Adams SM, Leung H-Y, King TE, et al. |date=19 January 2010 |accessdate=20 March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=isogg&gt;[http://www.isogg.org/tree/ISOGG_HapgrpR.html International Society of Genetic Genealogy (ISOGG) - Y-DNA Haplogroup R and its Subclades]&lt;/ref&gt; Previous Y-chromosome and mtDNA analysis&lt;ref name=&quot;World Haplogroups Maps&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=J. D. |last=McDonald |year=2005 |title=Y Haplogroups of the World |url=http://www.scs.uiuc.edu/~mcdonald/WorldHaplogroupsMaps.pdf |accessdate=17 October 2009}}{{Self-published inline|date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; had suggested [[Paleolithic]] ancestry among populations in the Iberian Peninsula and that Iberia may have played a role in the re-population of western Europe after the last glaciation.&lt;ref name=&quot;SummarizedPercentFrequencies&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201225 |title=Reduced genetic structure of the Iberian peninsula revealed by Y-chromosome analysis: implications for population demography |year=2004 |last1=Flores |first1=Carlos |first2=Nicole |first3=Ana M |first4=Peter J |first5=Peidong |first6=Jose A |first7=Antonio |first8=Jose M |first9=Peter A |journal=European Journal of Human Genetics |volume=12 |page=855 |pmid=15280900 |issue=10 |last2=Maca-Meyer |last3=González |last4=Oefner |last5=Shen |last6=Pérez |last7=Rojas |last8=Larruga |last9=Underhill}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although this methodology does not provide strong inferences on genetic population structure, it is useful in tracing parts of the routes of migration in the populating of Europe. Both Y-chromosome haplogroup [[Haplogroup R1b (Y-DNA)|R1b]] and mitochondrial haplogroup [[Mtdna haplogroup h|H]], reach frequencies above 60% in most of [[Iberian Peninsula|Iberia]], R1b peaking at 90% in the Basque region.&lt;ref name=Dupanloup2004/&gt; This shows an ancestral bond between Iberia and the rest of [[western Europe]], and in particular with [[Atlantic Europe]], which share high frequencies of these haplogroups. R1b1b2, the most common western European haplogroup, arose 4,000 to 8,000 years ago in southwest Asia and later spread to Europe.&lt;ref name=isogg/&gt; 

However, a study by Laura Morelli ''et al.'' found the assumptions and conclusions flawed and demonstrated that cultural, not demic, diffusion was the main means by which agriculture was spread in Europe in the Neolithic period: &quot;A recent network analysis of the R-M269 Y chromosome lineage has purportedly corroborated Neolithic expansion from Anatolia, the site of diffusion of agriculture. However, the data are still controversial and the analyses so far performed are prone to a number of biases. In the present study we show that the addition of a single marker, DYSA7.2, dramatically changes the shape of the R-M269 network into a topology showing a clear Western-Eastern dichotomy not consistent with a radial diffusion of people from the Middle East. We have also assessed other Y-chromosome haplogroups proposed to be markers of the Neolithic diffusion of farmers and compared their intra-lineage variation—defined by short tandem repeats (STRs)—in Anatolia and in Sardinia, the only Western population where these lineages are present at appreciable frequencies and where there is substantial archaeological and genetic evidence of pre-Neolithic human occupation. The data indicate that Sardinia does not contain a subset of the variability present in Anatolia and that the shared variability between these populations is best explained by an earlier, pre-Neolithic dispersal of haplogroups from a common ancestral gene pool. Overall, these results are consistent with the cultural diffusion and do not support the demic model of agriculture diffusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0010419|title=A Comparison of Y-Chromosome Variation in Sardinia and Anatolia Is More Consistent with Cultural Rather than Demic Diffusion of Agriculture|author=Laura Morelli1, Daniela Contu, Federico Santoni, Michael B. Whalen, Paolo Francalacci, Francesco Cucca et al |date=9 April 2010 |accessdate=29 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to one study, the main components in the European genomes appear to derive from ancestors whose features were similar to those of modern Basques and Near Easterners, with average values greater than 35% for both these parental populations, regardless of whether or not molecular information is taken into account. The lowest degree of both Basque and Near Eastern admixture is found in Finland, whereas the highest values are, respectively, 80% ''(&quot;Basque&quot;)'' in Spain and roughly 70% ''(&quot;Near Eastern&quot;)'' in the Balkans.&lt;ref name=Dupanloup2004/&gt;

Autosomal studies using a small number of classical genetic markers, supported by more recent analysis of Microsatellite data, have lent support for a large [[Neolithic]] element in the European genome, supporting the [[demic diffusion]] model from the ancient [[Near East]]. This Neolithic component has also been detected at substantial levels in Spain, albeit at lower levels than in other European countries. Broad gradients across Europe, largely on South East/North West cline using a small number of classical genetic markers would thus link the populations of Western Europe (including Iberia) by a common &quot;paleolithic&quot; ancestry and those of eastern (and particularly south eastern) Europe by a common &quot;neolithic&quot; ancestry&lt;ref name=Dupanloup2004/&gt; Haplogroup composition of the ancient Iberians was very similar to that found in the modern Iberian Peninsula populations, suggesting a long-term genetic continuity since pre-Roman times.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1111/j.1529-8817.2005.00194.x |title=The Genetics of the Pre-Roman Iberian Peninsula: A mtDNA Study of Ancient Iberians |year=2005 |last1=Sampietro |first1=M. L. |first2=D. |first3=O. |first4=F. |first5=D. |first6=M. |first7=B. |first8=J. |first9=C. |journal=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=69 |page=535 |pmid=16138912 |issue=Pt 5 |last2=Caramelli |last3=Lao |last4=Calafell |last5=Comas |last6=Lari |last7=Agustí |last8=Bertranpetit |last9=Lalueza-Fox}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s004390000370 |title=Alu insertion polymorphisms in NW Africa and the Iberian Peninsula: evidence for a strong genetic boundary through the Gibraltar Straits |year=2000 |last1=Comas |first1=David |first2=Francesc |first3=Noufissa |first4=Ahmed |first5=Gerard |first6=Mark |first7=Mark A. |first8=Jaume |first9=Antti |journal=Human Genetics |volume=107 |page=312 |pmid=11129330 |issue=4 |last2=Calafell |last3=Benchemsi |last4=Helal |last5=Lefranc |last6=Stoneking |last7=Batzer |last8=Bertranpetit |last9=Sajantila}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Link with African populations==

=== North Africa ===
A number of studies focus on the genetic impact of the centuries of Muslim rule in the Iberian peninsula on the genetic make up of the modern Iberian population. Iberia has the greatest presence of the typically [[Northwest Africa]]n Y-chromosome haplotype marker E-M81 in Europe.&lt;ref name=capelli2009&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1038/ejhg.2008.258 |title=Moors and Saracens in Europe: estimating the medieval North African male legacy in southern Europe |year=2009 |last1=Capelli |first1=Cristian |first2=Valerio |first3=Francesca |first4=Ilaria |first5=Francesca |pmc=2947089 |first6=Mara |first7=Gianmarco |first8=Sergio |first9=Adriano |journal=European Journal of Human Genetics |volume=17 |page=848 |pmid=19156170 |issue=6 |last2=Onofri |last3=Brisighelli |last4=Boschi |last5=Scarnicci |last6=Masullo |last7=Ferri |last8=Tofanelli |last9=Tagliabracci}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1086/386295 |pmc=1181965 |pmid=15069642 |year=2004 |author1=Semino |first2=C |first3=G |first4=AA |first5=N |first6=V |first7=L |first8=C |first9=P |title=Origin, diffusion, and differentiation of Y-chromosome haplogroups E and J: inferences on the neolithization of Europe and later migratory events in the Mediterranean area. |volume=74 |issue=5 |pages=1023–34 |journal=American journal of human genetics |last2=Magri |last3=Benuzzi |last4=Lin |last5=Al-Zahery |last6=Battaglia |last7=MacCioni |last8=Triantaphyllidis |last9=Shen}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Haplotype Va.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=17216803 |year=2006 |author1=Gérard |first2=S |first3=A |first4=F |first5=G |title=North African Berber and Arab influences in the western Mediterranean revealed by Y-chromosome DNA haplotypes. |volume=78 |issue=3 |pages=307–16 |journal=Human biology; an international record of research |last2=Berriche |last3=Aouizérate |last4=Diéterlen |last5=Lucotte |doi=10.1353/hub.2006.0045}}&lt;/ref&gt; A thorough Y-chromosome analysis of the Iberian peninsula reveals that haplotype E-M81 surpasses frequencies of 10% in Southern Iberia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201225 |pmid=15280900 |url=http://hpgl.stanford.edu/publications/EJHG_2004_v12_p855.pdf |year=2004 |author1=Flores |first2=N |first3=AM |first4=PJ |first5=P |first6=JA |first7=A |first8=JM |first9=PA |title=Reduced genetic structure of the Iberian peninsula revealed by Y-chromosome analysis: implications for population demography. |volume=12 |issue=10 |pages=855–63 |journal=European Journal of Human Genetics |last2=Maca-Meyer |last3=González |last4=Oefner |last5=Shen |last6=Pérez |last7=Rojas |last8=Larruga |last9=Underhill}}&lt;/ref&gt; As for Mtdna analysis (Mitochondrial DNA), although present at only low levels, Iberia has much higher frequencies of typically North African Haplogroup U6 than those generally observed in Europe.&lt;ref name=plaza2003&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1046/j.1469-1809.2003.00039.x |title=Joining the Pillars of Hercules: mtDNA Sequences Show Multidirectional Gene Flow in the Western Mediterranean |year=2003 |last1=Plaza |first1=S. |first2=F. |first3=A. |first4=N. |first5=G. |first6=J. |first7=D. |journal=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=67 |page=312 |pmid=12914566 |issue=Pt 4 |last2=Calafell |last3=Helal |last4=Bouzerna |last5=Lefranc |last6=Bertranpetit |last7=Comas}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=plaza2003/&gt;&lt;ref name=pereira2005&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1353/hub.2005.0041 |title=African Female Heritage in Iberia: A Reassessment of mtDNA Lineage Distribution in Present Times |year=2005 |last1=Pereira |first1=Luisa |first2=Carla |first3=Cintia |first4=Antonio |journal=Human Biology |volume=77 |page=213 |last2=Cunha |last3=Alves |last4=Amorim |pmid=16201138}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pereira2005/&gt;&lt;ref name=gonzalez2003&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1002/ajpa.10168 |title=Mitochondrial DNA affinities at the Atlantic fringe of Europe |year=2003 |last1=González |first1=Ana M. |first2=Antonio |first3=José A. |first4=Nicole |first5=Carlos |first6=Vicente M. |journal=American Journal of Physical Anthropology |volume=120 |page=391 |pmid=12627534 |issue=4 |last2=Brehm |last3=Pérez |last4=Maca-Meyer |last5=Flores |last6=Cabrera}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=adams2008&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.11.007 |laysummary=http://www.sciencenews.org/view/generic/id/39056/title/Spanish_Inquisition_couldn%E2%80%99t_quash_Moorish,_Jewish_genes |laysource=[[Science News]] |laydate=3 January 2009 |title=The Genetic Legacy of Religious Diversity and Intolerance: Paternal Lineages of Christians, Jews, and Muslims in the Iberian Peninsula |year=2008 |last1=Adams |first1=Susan M. |first2=Elena |first3=Patricia L. |first4=Stéphane J. |first5=Andrew C. |first6=Eduardo |first7=Ana M. |first8=Mercedes |first9=Marina S. Gisbert |journal=The American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=83 |page=725 |pmid=19061982 |last2=Bosch |last3=Balaresque |last4=Ballereau |last5=Lee |last6=Arroyo |last7=López-Parra |last8=Aler |last9=Grifo |issue=6 |pmc=2668061}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is difficult to ascertain whether U6's presence is the consequence of Islam's expansion into Europe during the Middle Ages, or it is rather the result of ancient demic processes that predate the Islamic presence.&lt;ref name=gonzalez2003/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Gonçalves R, Freitas A, Branco M, ''et al.'' |title=Y-chromosome lineages from Portugal, Madeira and Açores record elements of Sephardim and Berber ancestry |journal=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=69 |issue=Pt 4 |pages=443–54 |year=2005 |month=July |pmid=15996172 |doi=10.1111/j.1529-8817.2005.00161.x}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2009, a study by Capelli et al.  Spanish individuals found the total contribution of specific North African male haplotypes in Spain as 7.7%.&lt;ref name=capelli2009/&gt;

According to a widely publicized recent study (December 2008) published in the [[American Journal of Human Genetics]], 19.8 percent of modern Iberians (Spain + Portugal) have DNA reflecting Levantine (possibly [[Sephardic Jewish]] ancestry) and 10.6 percent having DNA reflecting [[Moorish]] ancestors.&lt;ref name=adams2008/&gt; The study's speculation on Sephardic origin of the Levantine markers has been widely contested since it is likely that such markers also reflect other migrations from the Near East such as what medieval Andalusians called &quot;Syrians&quot;, earlier Phoenician colonization or even population movements during the Neolithic.&lt;ref name=&quot;SummarizedPercentFrequencies&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=gonzalez2003/&gt;&lt;ref name=adams2008/&gt;&lt;ref name=adams2008/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s00439-004-1168-9 |title=Y chromosomal haplogroup J as a signature of the post-neolithic colonization of Europe |year=2004 |last1=Giacomo |first1=F. |first2=F. |first3=L. O. |first4=N. |first5=N. |first6=J. |first7=R. |first8=G. |first9=F. |journal=Human Genetics |volume=115 |page=357 |pmid=15322918 |issue=5 |last2=Luca |last3=Popa |last4=Akar |last5=Anagnou |last6=Banyko |last7=Brdicka |last8=Barbujani |last9=Papola}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1080/03014460500475870 |title=Toward resolution of the debate regarding purported crypto-Jews in a Spanish-American population: Evidence from the Y chromosome |year=2006 |last1=Sutton |first1=Wesley K. |first2=Alec |first3=Peter A. |first4=Judith S. |first5=Todd R. |first6=Joanna L. |journal=Annals of Human Biology |volume=33 |page=100 |pmid=16500815 |issue=1 |last2=Knight |last3=Underhill |last4=Neulander |last5=Disotell |last6=Mountain}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=zalloua2008&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1016/j.ajhg.2008.10.012 |title=Identifying Genetic Traces of Historical Expansions: Phoenician Footprints in the Mediterranean |year=2008 |last1=Zalloua |first1=P |first2=D |first3=M |first4=J |first5=N |first6=M |first7=Y |first8=H |first9=E |journal=The American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=83 |page=633 |pmid=18976729 |last2=Platt |last3=El Sibai |last4=Khalife |last5=Makhoul |last6=Haber |last7=Xue |last8=Izaabel |last9=Bosch |issue=5 |pmc=2668035}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;La cifra de los sefardíes puede estar sobreestimada, ya que en estos genes hay mucha diversidad y quizá absorbieron otros genes de Oriente Medio&quot; ''('''&quot;The Sephardic result may be overestimated''', since there is much diversity in those genes and maybe absorbed other genes from the Middle East&quot;)''. ¿Pone en duda Calafell la validez de los tests de ancestros? “Están bien para los americanos, nosotros ya sabemos de dónde venimos” ''(Puts Calafell in doubt the validity of ancestry tests? &quot;They can be good for the Americans, we already know from where we come from)''.''''' ''&quot; [http://www.publico.es/ciencias/180536/tres/culturas/adn]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;El doctor Calafell matiza que (...) los marcadores genéticos usados para distinguir a la población con ancestros sefardíes pueden producir distorsiones&quot;.  &quot;ese 20% de españoles que el estudio señala como descendientes de sefardíes podrían haber heredado ese rasgo de movimiento más antiguos, como el de los fenicios o, incluso, primeros pobladores neolíticos hace miles de años.&quot; &quot;Dr. Calafell clarifies that (...) '''the genetic markers used to distinguish the population with Sephardim ancestry may produce distortions. The 20% of Spaniards that are identified as having Sephardim ancestry in the study could have inherited that same marker from older movements like the Phoenicians, or even the first Neolithic settlers thousands of years ago'''&quot; http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2008/12/04/ciencia/1228409780.html&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, Chris Tyler-Smith, a collaborator with the team that carried the study,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upf.edu/enoticies/home_upf_en/1206.html]{{dead link|date=July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; argues that the individual differences in Y-chromosome markers suggest that Iberians and Sephardic Jews must share ancestry more recent than several millennia,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn16200-spanish-inquisition-left-genetic-legacy-in-iberia.html Spanish Inquisition left genetic legacy in Iberia], [[New Scientist]], December 4, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; even though in also a recent study (October 2008) they attributed those same lineages in Iberia and the Balearic Islands as of [[Phoenicia]]n origin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B8JDD-4TT80P5-4&amp;_user=10&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=&amp;_orig=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;view=c&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=ad14c9c76d9eaf347a154977acfc04b0 |title=The American Journal of Human Genetics : Identifying Genetic Traces of Historical Expansions: Phoenician Footprints in the Mediterranean |publisher=ScienceDirect |date= |accessdate=2010-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A 2007 study (published 2007) had estimated the contribution of northern African lineages to the entire male gene pool of Iberia as 5.6%.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |pmid=17351267 |doi=10.1093/molbev/msm049 |year=1975 |author1=Schmoldt |first2=HF |first3=G |title=Digitoxin metabolism by rat liver microsomes. |volume=24 |issue=17 |pages=1639–41 |journal=Biochemical pharmacology |first4=P. |first5=D. |first6=E. B. |first7=J.-M. |first8=F. |first9=T. |last2=Benthe |last3=Haberland |last4=Santolamazza |last5=Sellitto |last6=Colomb |last7=Dugoujon |last8=Crivellaro |last9=Benincasa}}&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier Europe-wide genetic studies focusing had found no significant correlation between North African admixture and geography concluding genetic exchanges in the westernmost part of the Mediterranean to be been limited or very limited and establishing the North African contribution at 2.5% to 3.4%.&lt;ref name=Dupanloup2004/&gt;

An earlier European-wide study had pointed to a small North African and Arab element in modern day Iberian ancestry when compared to the pre-Islamic ancestral basis, and the Gibraltar Strait seems to have functioned much more as a genetic barrier than a bridge.&lt;ref name=pmid15044595&gt;{{cite journal |author=Dupanloup I, Bertorelle G, Chikhi L, Barbujani G |title=Estimating the impact of prehistoric admixture on the genome of Europeans |journal=Molecular Biology and Evolution |volume=21 |issue=7 |pages=1361–72 |year=2004 |month=July |pmid=15044595 |doi=10.1093/molbev/msh135}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Bosch E, Calafell F, Comas D, Oefner PJ, Underhill PA, Bertranpetit J|title=High-resolution analysis of human Y-chromosome variation shows a sharp discontinuity and limited gene flow between northwestern Africa and the Iberian Peninsula |journal=American Journal of Human Genetics |volume=68 |issue=4 |pages=1019–29|year=2001 |month=April |pmid=11254456 |pmc=1275654 |doi=10.1086/319521}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Comas D, Calafell F, Benchemsi N, ''et al.'' |title=Alu insertion polymorphisms in NW Africa and the Iberian Peninsula: evidence for a strong genetic boundary through the Gibraltar Straits |journal=Human Genetics |volume=107 |issue=4 |pages=312–9 |year=2000 |month=October |pmid=11129330 |doi=10.1007/s004390000370}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Sub-Saharan Africa ===
In 2009, an [[autosomal]] study by Moorjani et al. that used about 500k-1.5 million [[Single-nucleotide polymorphism|SNP]]s estimated that the proportion of [[sub-Saharan Africa]]n ancestry  in Spain was 2.4% consistent with the historically known movement of individuals of North African ancestry into Spain, although it is possible that this estimate also reflects a wider range of mixture times.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ashg.org/2009meeting/abstracts/fulltext/f22007.htm Characterizing the history of sub-Saharan African gene flow into southern Europe], Moorjani et al. 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

MtDNA [[Macro-haplogroup L (mtDNA)|Haplogroup L]] lineages are relatively infrequent (1% or less) throughout Europe with the exception of [[Iberia]] where frequencies as high as 22%&lt;ref&gt;Pereira V, Gomes V, Amorim A, Gusmão L, João Prata M.''[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20737604 Genetic characterization of uniparental lineages in populations from Southwest Iberia with past malaria endemicity''].Am J Hum Biol. 2010 Sep-Oct;22(5):588-95.&lt;/ref&gt; have been reported and some regions of [[Italy]] where frequencies between 2 and 3% have been found.

In [[Iberia]] the mean frequency of Haplogroup L lineages reaches 3.83%  and the frequency is higher in [[Portugal]] (5.83%) than in [[Spain]] (2.90%) and without parallel in the rest of Europe. Furthermore, in western Iberia, increasing frequencies are observed for [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]] (3.26%) and northern Portugal (3.21%), through the center (5.02%) and to the south of [[Portugal]] (11.38%).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Pereira L, Cunha C, Alves C, Amorim A |title=African female heritage in Iberia: a reassessment of mtDNA lineage distribution in present times |journal=Human Biology |volume=77 |issue=2 |pages=213–29 |year=2005 |month=April |pmid=16201138 |doi=10.1353/hub.2005.0041 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Significant frequencies were also found in the [[Autonomous regions of Portugal]], with L haplogroups constituting about 13% of the lineages  in  [[Madeira]], significantly more than in the [[Azores]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brehm A, Pereira L, Kivisild T, Amorim A 2003 77–86&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Brehm A, Pereira L, Kivisild T, Amorim A |title=Mitochondrial portraits of the Madeira and Açores archipelagos witness different genetic pools of its settlers |journal=Human Genetics |volume=114 |issue=1 |pages=77–86 |year=2003 |month=December |pmid=14513360 |doi=10.1007/s00439-003-1024-3 |ref=harv}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the Spanish archipelago of [[Canary Islands]], frequencies have been reported at 6.6%.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brehm A, Pereira L, Kivisild T, Amorim A 2003 77–86&quot;/&gt; Regarding Iberia, current debates are concerned with whether these lineages are associated with prehistoric migrations, the Islamic occupation of Iberia or the slave trade. {{Harvcoltxt|Pereira et al.|2000}} suggested that African lineages in Iberia were predominantly the result of Atlantic Slave Trade. {{Harvcoltxt|Gonzalez et al.|2003}} revealed that most of the L lineages in Iberia matched Northwest African L lineages rather than contemporary Sub-Saharan L lineages. The authors suggest this pattern indicates that most of the Sub-Saharan L lineages entered Iberia in prehistoric times rather than during the slave trade. According to {{Harvcoltxt|Pereira et al.|2005}}, the sub-Saharan lineages found in Iberia matched lineages from diverse regions in Africa. They suggest this pattern is more compatible with recent arrival of these lineages after slave trading began in the 15th century. According to the study,  alternative scenarios that invoke much older and demographically more significant introductions ({{Harvcoltxt|Gonzalez et al.|2003}}) or that claim a substantial role of the Roman and/or Islamic periods on the introduction of sub-Saharan lineages seem unlikely. {{Harvcoltxt|Casas et al.|2006}} extracted DNA from human remains that were exhumed from old burial sites in [[Al-Andalus]], Spain. The remains date to between 12th-13th century. The frequency of Sub-Saharan lineages detected in the medieval samples was 14.6% and 8.3% in the present population of [[Priego de Cordoba]]. The authors suggest the [[Umayyad conquest of Hispania|Muslim occupation]] and prehistoric migrations before the Muslim occupation would have been the source of these lineages. The highest frequencies  of Sub-Saharan lineages found so far in Europe were observed by Alvarez et al. 2010 in the [[comarca]] of [[Sayago]] (18.2%) which is according to the authors &quot;comparable to that described for the South of Portugal&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Alvarez et al. (2010), ''[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20127843 Mitochondrial DNA Patterns in the Iberian Northern Plateau: Population Dynamics and Substructure of the Zamora Province]''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''As regards sub-Saharan Hgs (L1b, L2b, and L3b), the high frequency found in the southern regions of Zamora, 18.2% in Sayago and 8.1% in Bajo Duero, is comparable to that described for the South of Portugal'', Alvarez et al. (2010)&lt;/ref&gt; and by Pereira et al. 2010 in [[Alcácer do Sal Municipality|Alcacer do Sal]] (22%).&lt;ref&gt;Pereira V, Gomes V, Amorim A, Gusmão L, João Prata M. ''[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20737604 Genetic characterization of uniparental lineages in populations from Southwest Iberia with past malaria endemicity]''.Am J Hum Biol. 2010 Sep-Oct;22(5):588-95.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Canary Islands==

The inhabitants of the [[Canary Islands]], hold a gene pool that is halfway between the Iberians and the ancient native population, the [[Guanches]] (a proto-Berber population), although with a major Iberian contribution. Guanche genetic markers have also been found, at low frequencies, in peninsular Spain, probably as a result of slavery and/or later immigration from the Canary Islands.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1046/j.1529-8817.2003.00125.x |title=A Tale of Aborigines, Conquerors and Slaves: Alu Insertion Polymorphisms and the Peopling of Canary Islands |year=2004 |last1=MacA-meyer |first1=N. |first2=J. |first3=L. |first4=A. Cabrera |first5=C. |journal=Annals of Human Genetics |volume=68 |page=600 |pmid=15598218 |issue=Pt 6 |last2=Villar |last3=Pérez-Méndez |last4=Cabrera De León |last5=Flores}}&lt;/ref&gt; MmtDna haplogroup U6 was found at rate of 14% in the present-day Canary Islands populations reflecting the Berber origin of the [[Guanches]], the aboriginal population of the Canary Islands. In this study they compared aboriginal Guanche mtDNA (collected from Canarian archaeological sites) to that of today's Canarians and concluded that, &quot;despite the continuous changes suffered by the population (Spanish colonization, slave trade), aboriginal mtDNA lineages constitute a considerable proportion [42–73%] of the Canarian gene pool&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201075 |title=Ancient mtDNA analysis and the origin of the Guanches |year=2004 |author=Maca-Meyer, Nicole |journal=European Journal of Human Genetics |volume=12 |pages=155–62 |pmid=14508507 |month=Feb |last1=Maca-Meyer |first1=N |last2=Arnay |first2=M |last3=Rando |first3=JC |last4=Flores |first4=C |last5=González |first5=AM |last6=Cabrera |first6=VM |last7=Larruga |first7=JM |issue=2 |issn=1018-4813 |format=Free full text}}&lt;/ref&gt; MtDNA haplogroup L were also found at rate of 6.6%&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |doi=10.1007/s00439-003-1024-3 |title=Mitochondrial portraits of the Madeira and Açores archipelagos witness different genetic pools of its settlers |year=2003 |author=Brehm, António |journal=Human Genetics |volume=114 |pages=77–86 |pmid=14513360 |month=Dec |last1=Brehm |first1=A |last2=Pereira |first2=L |last3=Kivisild |first3=T |last4=Amorim |first4=A |issue=1 |issn=0340-6717}}&lt;/ref&gt; and E-M81 at a mean rate of 8.28% with frequencies over 10%  in the three largest islands of [[Tenerife]] (10.68%), [[Gran Canaria]] (11.54%) and [[Fuerteventura]] (13.33%).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2728732/table/T1/ see table]&lt;/ref&gt; According to Fregel et al. 2009 the presence of autochthonous North African E-M81 lineages, and also other relatively abundant markers (E-M78 and J-M267) from the same region in the indigenous Guanche population, &quot;strongly points to that area [North Africa] as the most probable origin of the Guanche ancestors&quot;. In this study, they estimated that, based on Y-chromosome and mtDNA haplogroup frequencies, the relative female and male indigenous Guanche contributions to the present-day Canary Islands populations were respectively of 41.8% and 16.1%.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Fregel R, Gomes V, Gusmão L, ''et al.'' |title=Demographic history of Canary Islands male gene-pool: replacement of native lineages by European |journal=BMC Evolutionary Biology |volume=9 |issue= |pages=181 |year=2009 |pmid=19650893 |pmc=2728732 |doi=10.1186/1471-2148-9-181}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Caveats ==
Archaeogenetics is a new science and most of its findings are recent and remain controversial as the understanding of the issues faced expands rapidly. For instance, the issue cocerning the dating of the original R1 haplogroup mutation and its subclades has varied widely, originally dated at over 30 000 years BP (Before Present) to the later studies that show a much younger date of 18 600 BP. Such differences in dating affect conclusions about whether or not a population is largely palaeolithic or neolithic in origin.&lt;ref name=Balaresque2010&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Balaresque et al.|year=2010|title=A Predominantly Neolithic Origin for European Paternal Lineages|journal=PLoS Biol.|volume=8|issue=1|pmc=2799514|doi=10.1371/journal.pbio.1000285|editor1-first=David|last2=Teteliutina|first2=FK|last3=Serebrennikova|first3=GK|last4=Starostin|editor1-last=Penny|first4=SV|last5=Churshin|first5=AD|pages=119–22|last6=Rosser|first6=Zoë H.|last7=Goodwin|first7=Jane|last8=Moisan|first8=Jean-Paul|last9=Richard|first9=Christelle|postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;|pmid=20087410}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other problems relating to starting assumptions, genetic drift, population bottlenecks and founder effects point to the many difficulties faced by researchers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | doi = 10.1038/sj.ejhg.5201482 | author = Alonso  ''et al.'' | year = 2005 | title = The Place of the Basques in the European Y-chromosome Diversity Landscape | url = http://www.nature.com/ejhg/journal/v13/n12/full/5201482a.html | journal = European Journal of Human Genetics | volume = 13 | issue = 12| pages = 1293–1302 | pmid=16094307}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=B. Arredi, E. S. Poloni and C. Tyler-Smith |chapter=The peopling of Europe |editor=Crawford, Michael H. |title=Anthropological genetics: theory, methods and applications |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, UK |year=2007 |page=394 |isbn=0-521-54697-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Genetic history of Europe]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Genetic History Of The Iberian Peninsula}}
[[Category:Modern human genetic history|Iberian Peninsula]]
[[Category:History of Spain]]
[[Category:History of Portugal]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
