<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29128243" ns="0" title="List of Pokémon (494–545)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Incomplete|date=December 2010}}
{{TOCright}}
[[Pokémon]] has 646 (as of [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'']]) distinctive fictional species classified as the titular Pokémon. These creatures and entities reside throughout various locations of the fictional Pokémon universe and can be caught by humans designated as [[Pokémon Trainer]]s often using devices called [[Poké Ball]]s. These trainers use Pokémon for a variety of purposes, such as being pets and loyal companions and/or being pitted against other trained Pokémon in competitive Pokémon battles. Pokémon are potentially super-powered creatures that can employ a variety of talents such as [[Pyrokinesis|generating fire or heat]], [[martial arts]], [[Psychokinesis|telekinesis]], and so on. Through age and experience many of these species undergo a metamorphosis and transform into a similar but stronger species in a process referred to as [[Pokémon evolution]].

This is a selected listing of fifty-two of the Pokémon species, arranged as they are in the main game series' [[Pokédex|National Pokédex]].

==Victini==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 494
|type = Psychic/Fire
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{main|Victini}}
{{Nihongo|'''Victini'''|ビクティニ|Bikutini}}, known as the Victory Pokémon, is a small [[rodent]]-like Pokémon. Its large pointed ears shaped like letter V. It is said that a trainer with a Victini will always win any kind of battle. It produces infinite energy within itself and shares with others by touching them. Victini was designed by Mana Ibe, under the instructions from game director [[Junichi Masuda]] that it would be more appealing to women. Victini can only be obtained via a downloadable [[wi-fi]] event. It appears in the film ''[[Pokémon the Movie: Black - Victini and Reshiram and White - Victini and Zekrom]]''

==Snivy==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 495
|type = Grass
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = Servine
}}
{{nihongo|'''Snivy'''&lt;ref name=&quot;englishnamereveal&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/the-starter-pokemon/ | title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Starter Pokémon | publisher=Pokémon | date=2010-11-22 | accessdate=2010-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ツタージャ|Tsutāja|'''Tsutarja'''}}, known as the [[Grass Snake]] Pokémon, is one of the [[starter Pokémon]] in the [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'' versions]]. Its arms and tails are similar to a [[palmate]] tree with three prongs, respectively. A Snivy uses its tail to process [[photosynthesis]], and if it loses energy, its tail sags gradually.&lt;ref name=&quot;Snivywhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|They photosynthesize by bathing their tails in sunlight. When they are not feeling well, their tails droop.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When charged up with sun's energy, its movement speed sharpens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Snivyblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|It is very intelligent and calm. Being exposed to lots of sunlight makes its movements swifter.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Snivy is known to behave accordingly in situations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Snivyblack&quot;/&gt; In an interview with [[Ken Sugimori]], he explained that Snivy was based on snakes that look like vines, and would have an [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocrat]]-like personality. He also stated that Snivy's evolution would be Western style of design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pia&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Pokémon Pia | date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was first revealed as a silhouette on the May 9, 2010, episode of ''Pokémon Sunday''.&lt;ref name=&quot;SundayMay9th&quot;&gt;''[[Pokémon Sunday]]''. May 9, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]], Snivy was first seen in &quot;In the Shadow of Zekrom&quot; as the starter Pokémon of [[Trip (Pokémon)|Trip]], a beginner trainer in the [[Unova]] region.&lt;ref name=&quot;episode1bestwishesjap&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode | title=To the Isshu Region! Zekrom's Shadow!! (イッシュ地方へ！ゼクロムの影!! ''Isshu Chihō e! Zekuromu no Kage!!'') | episodelink= | url= | series=[[Pokémon: Best Wishes!]] | serieslink= | credits= | network=[[TV Tokyo]] | station= | city=Tokyo | airdate={{flag|Japan}} September 23, 2010 | began= | ended= | season=14 | seriesno=660 | number= | minutes= | transcript= | transcripturl= | quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In &quot;Snivy Plays Hard to Catch&quot;, Ash Ketchum also encounters a female Snivy and successfully captures her.&lt;!--IF THERE'S AN ENGLISH EPISODE AVAILABLE, PLEASE CHANGE THIS REFERENCE--&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite episode | title={{tooltip|ツタージャ・ゲットでメロメロ!?|Get the Tsutarja with Attract!?}} | episodelink= | url= | accessdate= | series=[[Pokémon: Best Wishes!]] | serieslink= | credits= | network=[[TV Tokyo]] | station= | city=[[Tokyo]] | airdate= | began= | ended= | season=4 | seriesno=666 | number= | minutes= | transcript= | transcripturl= | quote= | language=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Snivy is also featured along with the other starter Pokémon in the ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' manga as one of the starters in Professor Juniper's lab. Snivy is Monta's starter Pokémon in the ''[[Pokémon Master Black &amp; White]]'' manga.

In a poll by [[Official Nintendo Magazine]], it was voted as the most popular of the [[Starter Pokémon]] from ''[[Pokémon Black and White]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;poll&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.officialnintendomagazine.co.uk/17239/news/the-best-pokmon-black/white-starter-is/ | title=Nintendo News: The Best Pokémon Black/White Starter is... | work=Official Nintendo Magazine | date=2010-05-17 | accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;opinions&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.officialnintendomagazine.co.uk/17241/features/pokmon-black-white-starters-your-say/ | title=Nintendo Feature: Pokémon Black &amp; White Starters: Your Say! | work=Official Nintendo Magazine | date=2010-05-17 | accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; As such, it has been nicknamed &quot;Smugleaf&quot; by fans and has quickly become an [[internet meme]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://kotaku.com/5538319/pokemons-smugleaf-a-meme-in-the-making/ | title=Pokémon's 'Smugleaf': A Meme in the Making | work=Kotaku | date=2010-05-13 | accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gonintendo.com/viewstory.php?id=123576 | title=Pokémon Black/White's 'Tsutaja' is Quickly Becoming an Internet Sensation | work=GoNintendo | date=2010-05-14 | accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GamesRadar]]'s Gudmundson called it &quot;arguably the coolest-looking starter of the three.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamesradar p1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/pokemon-black-and-white-spotlight-the-starters-and-their-evolutions/a-20100930103547232038 | title=Pokémon Black and White Spotlight: The Starters and Their Evolutions | first=Carolyn | last=Gudmundson | work=GamesRadar | date=2010-10-02 | accessdate=2010-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gudmundson later noted its quality as a grass Pokémon due to a healthy movepool of grass-type moves.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-snivy-servine-serperior/a-20110216115253250071/g-201004091000657031 | title=Pokémon Black and White Pokédex: Snivy, Servine, Serperior, Pokémon Black/White DS Features | work=GamesRadar | date= | accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[IGN]]'s Audrey Drake and Rich George chose Snivy as their starting Pokémon; Drake chose it &quot;because he's a little badass&quot; and due to it being the most challenging, while George described him as &quot;mischievous&quot;. Drake found its final form's lack of arms to be weird, while George called it an &quot;awesome demon snake.&quot; Fellow IGN editor Sam Claiborn described Snivy as an &quot;abomination.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web | first=Richard | last=George | url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/115/1155143p1.html | title=Pokémon Black and White: Second Opinions - Nintendo DS Feature | work=IGN | date=2011-03-11 | accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Servine==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 496
|type = Grass
|evolvesfrom = Snivy
|evolvesto = Serperior
}}
{{Nihongo|'''Servine'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/servine/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Servine|accessdate=2011-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ジャノビー|Janobī|'''Janovy'''}}, a Grass Snake Pokémon, is the evolution of [[Snivy]]. Servine resembles a [[grass snake]], and its appearance is very similar to Snivy except its back is grown by three [[palmate]] leaves with three prongs each. During a battle, it can run as if gliding from the ground that may bewilder its enemies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Servineblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|It moves along the ground as if sliding. Its swift movements befuddle its foes, and it then attacks with a vine whip.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It evades attack by passing overgrown plants and then whipping the foe quickly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Servinewhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|They avoid attacks by sinking into the shadows of thick foliage. They retaliate with masterful whipping techniques.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]], a Servine is first seen battling against a Dewott in one of the Battle Clubs in the [[Unova]] region.&lt;ref name=&quot;episode4bestwishesjap&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode | title = Battle Club! A Mysterious Pokémon Appears!! (バトルクラブ！謎のポケモン現る！！ ''Batoru Kurabu! Nazo no Pokemon Arawaru!!'') | episodelink =  | url = | series = [[Pokémon: Best Wishes!]] | serieslink =  | credits =  | network =[[TV Tokyo]]  | station = | city = Tokyo | airdate = {{flag|Japan}} October 7, 2010 | began = | ended =  | season = 14 | seriesno = 663  | number =  | minutes =  | transcript  | transcripturl =  | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Trip (Pokémon)|Trip's]] Snivy was revealed to have evolved into a Servine some time before Trip's second battle against [[Ash Ketchum]].&lt;ref name=&quot;episode10bestwishesjap&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode | title = Rival Battle! Tough Enemy Pururiru!! (ライバルバトル！強敵プルリル!! ''Raibaru Batoru! Kyōteki Pururiru!!'') | episodelink =  | url =  | series = [[Pokémon: Best Wishes!]] | serieslink =  | credits =  | network =[[TV Tokyo]]  | station = | city = Tokyo | airdate = {{flag|Japan}} November 18, 2010 | began = | ended =  | season = 14 | seriesno = 669  | number =  | minutes =  | transcript  | transcripturl =  | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Serperior==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 497
|type = Grass
|evolvesfrom = Servine
|evolvesto =
}}
{{Nihongo|'''Serperior'''|ジャローダ|Jarōda|'''Jalorda'''}}, known as the Regal Pokémon, is the final evolution of [[Snivy]]. Unlike its pre-evolutions, Serperior has no legs anymore and has retained its short hands. Serperior is more snake-like than Snivy and Servine. It intimidates its foe by raising its head high and glaring them would make its enemies stun.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serperiorblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|It can stop its opponents' movements with just a glare. It takes in solar energy and boosts it internally.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Serperiorwhite&quot;/&gt; If it faces a formidable enemy, Serperior tends to battle seriously.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serperiorwhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|They raise their heads to intimidate opponents but only give it their all when fighting a powerful opponent.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It increases it power by utilizing solar energy in its body.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serperiorblack&quot;/&gt;

In a poll by [[Official Nintendo Magazine]], Serperior was voted as one of the best Pokémon from ''Black'' and ''White''. Editor Thomas East stated that &quot;not many people would dispute that choosing Snivy as a Starter is all worth it in the end for its awesome final evolution.&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.officialnintendomagazine.co.uk/25375/best-pokemon-black-and-white-pokemon/ |title=Best Pokemon Black and White Pokemon |publisher=[[Official Nintendo Magazine]] |author=Thomas East |date= 7-Apr-2011 |accessdate=2011-04-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tepig==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 498
|type = Fire
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = Pignite
}}
{{nihongo|'''Tepig'''&lt;ref name=&quot;englishnamereveal&quot;/&gt;|ポカブ||'''Pokabu'''}} is a Fire Pig Pokémon that resembles a [[pig]] and is one of the [[starter Pokémon]] for [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'' versions]]. When hungry, it uses its flame to cook for its food.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tepigblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|It can deftly dodge foe's attacks while shooting fireballs from its nose. It roasts berries before it eats them.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It blows fire from its nostrils, but this is replaced with smoke when it catches a cold.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tepigwhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|It blows fire through its nose. When it catches a cold, the fire becomes pitch-black smoke instead.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an interview with [[Ken Sugimori]], he stated that Tepig's evolution would be Chinese style of design.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pia&quot; /&gt; Tepig's original Japanese name is a portmanteau of {{nihongo|Pokapoka|ぽかぽか}}, a Japanese word that refers to the warm feeling that circulates repeatedly throughout a body, and {{nihongo|Bū|ブー}}, which refers to a pig's sound.

In the [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]], Tepig was first seen in ''In the Shadow of Zekrom!'', under the ownership of [[Professor Juniper]], as one of the starter Pokémon to be chosen by [[Trip (Pokémon)|Trip]]. One later appears as an unfortunate Pokémon that was left behind by its trainer in Battle Club, after being defeated in a challenge. [[Ash Ketchum]] befriended the Pokémon and captured it afterward.&lt;ref name=&quot;episode4bestwishesjap&quot; /&gt; In the ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' manga, Tepig, along with [[Oshawott]] and [[Snivy]] appear when [[Black (Pokémon Adventures)|Black]] accidentally drops his box containing the Pokémon. The Tepig eventually joins his team and is named &quot;Poka&quot;. Tepig is [[Cheren (Pokémon)|Cheren]]'s starter Pokémon in the ''[[Pokémon Master Black &amp; White]]'' manga series.

[[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]] criticized Tepig's evolution line for being another Fire/Fighting type starter.&lt;ref name=&quot;escapistmagazine1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=John Funk | 16 Sep 2010 21:47 |url=http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/103547-All-New-Pokemon-from-Pokemon-Black-White-Revealed |title=The Escapist : News : All New Pokemon from Pokemon Black &amp; White Revealed |publisher=Escapistmagazine.com |date=2010-09-16 |accessdate=2010-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava criticized its name for possibly being a pun of &quot;[[wikt:tepid|tepid]]&quot;, which means lukewarm.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gameinformer.com/b/features/archive/2011/02/10/analyzing-the-new-pok-233-mon.aspx |title=Analyzing The New Pokémon - Features - www.GameInformer.com |publisher=''[[Game Informer]]'' |author=Jeff Marchiafava |date=February 10, 2011 |accessdate=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[GamesRadar]]'s Carolyn Gudmundson criticized its evolutionary line; while she enjoyed the first form's design, she felt that the final form was a disappointment, as well as the use of a combination of fire and fighting as its type, a type combination used for the last three fire starters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-tepig-pignite-emboar/a-2011021621105541038/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Tepig, Pignite, Emboar, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[IGN]]'s Sam Claiborn chose Tepig as his starting Pokémon due to its final form which he described as a &quot;bipedal pig demon&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

==Pignite==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 499
|type = Fire/Fighting
|evolvesfrom = Tepig
|evolvesto = Emboar
}}
{{Nihongo|'''Pignite'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/pignite/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Pignite|accessdate=2011-03-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;|チャオブー|Chaobū|'''Chaoboo'''}}, a Fire Pig Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Tepig]]. Its appearance is somewhat similar to its pre-evolution except that it stands on its two feet and is adorned with golden features on its chest. When mad, its power increases which comes from the food it ate and converted to fuel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pignitewhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|Whatever it eats becomes fuel for the flame in its stomach. When it is angered, the intensity of the flame increases.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to that, its speed and sharpness also increases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pigniteblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|When its internal fire flares up, its movements grow sharper and faster. When it trouble, it emits smoke.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Pokémon (anime)|anime]], Pignite made its debut appearance in ''Minccino-Neat and Tidy!'' under the ownership of [[Bianca (Pokémon)|Bianca]].

==Emboar==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 500
|type = Fire/Fighting
|evolvesfrom = Pignite
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{Nihongo|'''Emboar'''|エンブオー|Enbuō|'''Enbuoh'''}} known as the Mega Fire Pig Pokémon, is the final evolution of [[Tepig]]. While it still appears to have resemblance to its pre-evolution, Emboar are much more [[boar]]-like than [[pig]]-like. Additionally, it appears to have beard-like fire that circles its neck and shoulders. It has longer tusks that protruding its jaw and golden adornment. Emboar utilizes the flames on its neck during battle, where it uses its fist to set up combined fire and fighting moves on opponents.&lt;ref name=&quot;Emboarblack&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|black|It can throw a fire punch by setting its fists on fire with its fiery chin. It cares deeply about its friends.}}&lt;/ref&gt; When leveling up, it masters up both fighting skills with speed and powers combined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Emboarwhite&quot;&gt;{{pokédex|white|It has mastered fast and powerful fighting moves. It grows a beard of fire.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[GamesRadar]] called it &quot;such a disappointment design-wise.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gamesradar p2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/pokemon-black-and-white-spotlight-the-starters-and-their-evolutions/a-20100930103547232038/p-2 |title=Pokemon Black and White spotlight: the starters and their evolutions |author=Carolyn Gudmundson |publisher=GamesRadar |date=Oct 2, 2010 |accessdate=2010-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oshawott==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 501
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = Dewott
}}
{{main|Oshawott, Dewott, and Samurott}}
{{nihongo|'''Oshawott'''|ミジュマル||Mijumaru}}, known as the [[Sea Otter]] Pokémon, has a shell on its belly made of the same components as fingernails. It can detach the shell from its body and use it as a sword. Oshawott appears in [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'']], where it is first available as a [[Starter Pokémon]] for players to choose from alongside [[Snivy]] and [[Tepig]]. After gaining enough experience in battle, Oshawott evolves into Dewott, and then into Samurott.

==Dewott==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 502
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom = Oshawott
|evolvesto = Samurott
}}
{{main|Oshawott, Dewott, and Samurott}}
{{Nihongo|'''Dewott'''|フタチマル||Futachimaru}}, known as the Discipline Pokémon, has two shells, both of which it uses as weapons. With rigorous training, Dewott acquires the ability to perform two-shell attacks with flowing [[swordsmanship]]. After gaining enough experience in battle, Dewott evolves from Oshawott, and then into Samurott.

==Samurott==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 503
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom = Dewott
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{main|Oshawott, Dewott, and Samurott}}
{{Nihongo|'''Samurott'''|ダイケンキ|Daikenki}}, known as the Formidable Pokémon, is a quadruped, [[sea lion]]-like Pokémon. It can silence its enemies by glaring at them, and it can defeat an opponent by swinging the sword on its armor. Samurott evolves from Dewott after gaining enough experience in battle.

==Patrat==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 504
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Watchog
}}
{{nihongo|'''Patrat'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/patrat/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Patrat |accessdate=2011-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ミネズミ|Minezumi}}, known as the Lookout Pokémon, is a rodent-like Pokémon that resembles a [[chipmunk]]. It continues keeping watch for several days, saving up food in its cheek pouches. It signals to its companions with its tail.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ほほの　ふくろに　エサを　ためこみ　なんにちも　みはりを　つづける。しっぽで　なかまに　あいずする。|It continues keeping watch for several days, saving up food in its cheek pouches. It signals to its companions with its tail.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; They are extremely wary and keep watch outside their burrows in turns. They become anxious if no one keeps watch.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|けいかいしんが　つよく　こうたいで　すあなの　まわりを　みはりつづける。みはりが　いないと　ふあんなのだ。|They are extremely wary and keep watch outside their burrows in turns. They become anxious if no one keeps watch.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Patrat first appeared in the first few episodes of the [[Pokémon: Black and White|''Pokémon: Black and White'' anime]]. Multiple Patrat made a brief cameo in ''Black and White'' episode 3 with multiple [[Pidove]] and [[Deerling]] where they needed help from [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] and his friends. In the ''[[Pokémon Master Black &amp; White]]'' manga, Monta captures a Patrat in the first chapter.

Patrat and its evolution Watchog were called &quot;fairly unremarkable aside from their intense facial expressions&quot; by [[GamesRadar]]'s Carolyn Gudmundson.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/pokemon-black-and-white-spotlight-minezumi-yorterii-choroneko-and-their-evolutions/a-20101008163410743059|title=Pokemon Black and White spotlight: Minezumi, Yorterii, Choroneko and their evolutions|date=2010-10-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gudmundson later noted it as a &quot;[[Bidoof]] analog&quot;, in spite of the fact that it can only learn one [[Hidden Machine]], whereas Bidoof can learn many. She adds that it is very easy to become bored of it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-patrat-watchhog/a-20110222123233440042/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Patrat, Watchhog, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Official Nintendo Magazine]]''{{'}}s Chris Schilling commented that Patrat was the &quot;new Bidoof&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;officialnintendomagazine1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.officialnintendomagazine.co.uk/24223/features/pokmon-black-and-white-weve-gone-back-to-basics/ |title=Nintendo Feature: Pokémon Black and White: 'We've gone back to basics' |publisher=Official Nintendo Magazine |date=2011-03-01 |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Watchog==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 505
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom = Patrat 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Watchog'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/watchog/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Watchog |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ミルホッグ|Miruhoggu|Miruhog}}, known as the Precaution Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Patrat]]. It attacks by hurling the seeds of berries collected in its cheek sacs. When it spots an enemy it stands its tail erect.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ほっぺの　ふくろに　ためた　きのみの　タネを　とばして　こうげき。てきを　はっけんすると　しっぽを　たてる。|It attacks by hurling the seeds of berries collected in its cheek sacs. When it spots an enemy it stands its tail erect.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; It makes the patterns on its body shine in order to intimidate enemies. It has eyes that can see its surroundings even in the dark.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|からだの　もようを　ひからせて　てきを　いかくする。くらやみでも　まわりを　みとおす　めを　もつ。|It makes the patterns on its body shine in order to intimidate enemies. It has eyes that can see its surroundings even in the dark.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the anime, Nacrene City Gym Leader Lenora has a Watchog and she uses it in &quot;A Night in the Nacrene City Museum!!&quot; where it used its ability to reveal [[Yamask]]'s presence. She then uses it against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] in his Gym Battle in &quot;The Battle Acconding to Lenora&quot; where it defeats his [[Oshawott]] with Thunderbolt. It appears once more in &quot;Rematch at the Nacrene Gym!&quot;, where it is defeated by Oshawott's Aqua Jet.

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava described Watchog as a &quot;pissed-off meerkat&quot;, and further calling it a &quot;disgruntled-looking jerk&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;  An editor for [[GamesRadar]] included it in a satirical character battle between their &quot;ultimate hated characters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gamesradar.com/f/gamesradars-ultimate-hated-character-battle/a-20110429155921785014&lt;/ref&gt;

==Lillipup==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 506
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Herdier
}}
{{nihongo|'''Lillipup'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/lillipup/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Lillipup |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ヨーテリー|Yōterī|Yorterrie}} is known as the Puppy Pokémon. The long hairs covering its face are excellent radars. It delicately senses the state of its surroundings.

In the anime, Lillipup appeared under the ownership of [[Lenora (Pokémon)|Lenora]], where it won in a battle against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]]'s [[Tepig]].

[[GamesRadar]]'s Carolyn Gudmundson noted it as being initially weak, but becomes quite powerful in its final evolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-lillipup-herdier-stoutland/a-201102221438940085/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Lillipup, Herdier, Stoutland, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Official Nintendo Magazine]]''{{'}}s Chris Schilling called Lillipup the new [[Rattata]].&lt;ref name=&quot;officialnintendomagazine1&quot;/&gt;

==Herdier==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 507
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom = Lillipup
|evolvesto = Stoutland
}}
{{nihongo|'''Herdier'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/herdier/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Herdier |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ハーデリア|Hāderia|harderrier}}, known as the Loyal Dog Pokémon, is a dog-like Pokémon with particular similarities to a [[Yorkshire Terrier]]. Its face sports an abundance of cream fur, forming a &quot;mustache&quot; and a three-pointed crest of fur on its head. Its ears are large and perked, and it has a shaggy dark blue pelt on its body and tail. Its limbs are orange-brown. The black fur that covers its body like a cape is heavy, and softens the impact of attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|The black fur that covers its body like a cape is heavy. The fur softens the impact of attacks.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Faithful to its trainer's instructions, it has helped trainers raise Pokémon since long ago.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Faithful to its Trainer's instructions. It has helped Trainers raise Pokémon since long ago.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]] commented that while much of the Pokémon in ''[[Pokémon Black and White]]'' look weird, &quot;I will readily admit to wanting to hug that Yorkshire Terrier one, though. It's just too cute!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;escapistmagazine1&quot;/&gt;

==Stoutland==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 508
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom = Herdier
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Stoutland'''|ムーランド|Mūrando|Mooland}}, known as the Big-Hearted Pokémon, is a dog-like Pokémon that is the final evolution of [[Lillipup]]. It looks very similar to [[Herdier]], its pre-evolved form, with a brown base coat, black-gray thicker fur, and white-cream thick fur on its face like a long mustache. Stoutland are very talented at saving people, especially people stranded in the mountains or at sea. Its thick fur protects it from freezing cold temperatures.

==Purrloin==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 509
|type = Dark
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Liepard
}}
{{nihongo|'''Purrloin'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/purrloin/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Purrloin |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|チョロネコ|Choroneko}}, known as the Devious Pokémon, is a purple [[Cat|feline]] Pokémon. It plays with and steals people's belongings. Even the people it steals from unconsciously forgive it due to its charming behavior.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ひとの　ものを　あそびで　ぬすむ。ぬすまれた　ひとも　あいくるしい　しぐさに　つい　ゆるしてしまうのだ。|It plays with and steals people's belongings. Even the people it steals from unconsciously forgive it due to its charming behavior.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its adorable behavior causes people to let down their guard, and it takes that opportunity to steal their belongings. If it gets mad it will fight back with its claws.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|かわいらしい　しぐさで　ゆだんさせて　その　すきに　もちものを　うばう。おこると　ツメを　たてて　はんげき。|Its adorable behavior causes people to let down their guard, and it takes that opportunity to steal their belongings. If it gets mad it will fight back with its claws.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[GamesRadar]]'s Carolyn Gudmundson noted it and its evolution as a decent Dark-type pair, though the stats are somewhat low.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-purrloin-liepard/a-20110222143543402006/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Purrloin, Liepard, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Liepard==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 510
|type = Dark
|evolvesfrom = Purrloin
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Liepard'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/liepard/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Liepard |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|レパルダス|Reparudasu|Lepardas}}, known as the Cruel Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Purrloin]]. They vanish and appear unexpectedly.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|These Pokémon vanish and appear unexpectedly. Many Trainers are drawn to their beautiful form and fur.}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also stealthily sneak up to its target, striking from behind before the victim has any time to react.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Stealthily, it sneaks up on its target, striking from behind before its victim has a chance to react.}}&lt;/ref&gt; They resemble purple [[Leopards]]. They are one of the most commonly used Pokémon in [[Team Plasma]].

==Pansage==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 511
|type = Grass
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Simisage
}}
{{nihongo|'''Pansage'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/pansage/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Pansage |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ヤナップ|Yanappu}} is known as the Grass Monkey Pokémon. It is part of a trio that seems to be inspired by the [[three wise monkeys]] motif; with its mouth open, Pansage represents &quot;speak no evil&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wisemonkey&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/f/pokemon-black-and-white-spotlight-the-monkey-trio-and-their-evolutions/a-20101015191956640075 |title=Pokemon Black and White spotlight: the monkey trio and their evolutions |publisher=GamesRadar |author=Carolyn Gudmundson |date=Oct 16, 2010 |accessdate=2011-01-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pansage lives in thick forests,&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ふかい　もりで　くらす　ポケモン。あたまに　はえた　はっぱを　たべると　つかれが　うそのように　きえる。|A Pokémon that lives in thick forests. If one eats the leaves growing on its head, their exhaustion will unbelievably vanish.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; and shares the leaves on its head with exhausted Pokémon. They have the effect of relieving from fatigue.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|げんきの　ない　ポケモンに　あたまの　はっぱを　わけあたえる。つかれを　とる　こうかが　あるのだ。|It hands out leaves from its head to tired Pokémon.  The leaves are able to alleviate exhaustion.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the anime, [[Cilan (Pokémon)|Cilan]] owns a Pansage that first appeared along with Pansear and Panpour owned by [[Chili (Pokémon)|Chili]] and [[Cress (Pokémon)|Cress]] respectively.&lt;ref&gt;''Pocket Monsters: Best Wishes!'' episode 5 &quot;San'yō Gym! Vs. Baoppu, Hiyappu and Yanappu!!&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''[[Pocket Monsters BW]]'' manga, Cilan uses a Pansage against [[Isamu Akai]]'s [[Clefairy]] in issue 3 when he tries to instigate a fight between Cilan, Chili, and Cress. In the ''[[Pokémon Master Black &amp; White]]'' manga, Cheren uses a Pansage against Monta in a triple battle.

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava stated that its ability, Gluttony, &quot;almost makes up for the broccoli growing out of its head&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt; [[GamesRadar]]'s Carolyn Gudmundson commented that it was the most appealing of the three monkeys, design-wise. She also compared it to [[Eevee]] and its evolutions, due to each one being of a different type: grass, fire, and water.&lt;ref name=&quot;pansagegr&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-pansage-simisage/a-20110222145041174060/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Pansage, Simisage, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Simisage==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 512
|type = Grass
|evolvesfrom = Pansage
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Simisage'''|ヤナッキー|Yanakkī|Yanakkie}}, known as the Thorn Monkey Pokémon, evolves from [[Pansage]] when using Leaf Stone. It is known for being a wild Pokémon which strikes out with its thorn covered tail.

==Pansear==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 513
|type = Fire
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Simisear
}}
{{nihongo|'''Pansear'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/pansear/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Pansear |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|バオップ|Baoppu}} is known as the High Tempature Pokémon. It is part of a trio that seems to be inspired by the [[three wise monkeys]] motif; with its hand by its ear, Pansear represents &quot;hear no evil&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wisemonkey&quot;/&gt; It resides in caves near volcanoes. When it is angry, the temperature of the tuft on its head increases to over 300 degrees Celsius.

In the anime, Pansear appears under the ownership of [[Chili (Pokémon)|Chili]], where it loses in a battle against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]]'s [[Tepig]].

==Simisear==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 514
|type = Fire
|evolvesfrom = Pansear
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Simisear'''|バオッキー|Baokkī|Baokkie}}, known as the Ember Pokémon, evolves from [[Pansear]] when a Fire Stone is used on it. It scatters embers from its head and tail to sear its opponents. It also enjoys sweets, as they become energy for the fire burning in its body.

==Panpour==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 515
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Simipour
}}
{{nihongo|'''Panpour'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/panpour/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Panpour |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ヒヤップ|Hiyappu}} is known as the Spray Pokémon. It is part of a trio that seems to be inspired by the [[three wise monkeys]] motif; with its eyes closed, Panpour represents &quot;see no evil&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;wisemonkey&quot;/&gt; It used to live in forests in ancient times, but its body changed so it could live on the waterside more easily. It can store water in the tuft on its head.

In the anime, Panpour appears under the ownership of [[Cress (Pokémon)|Cress]], where it wins in a battle against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]]'s [[Pikachu]].

==Simipour==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 516
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom = Panpour
|evolvesto = }}
{{Nihongo|'''Simipour'''|ヒヤッキー|Hiyakkī|Hiyakkie}}, known as the Geyser Pokémon, evolves from [[Panpour]] when a Water Stone is used on it. The tuft on its head holds water. When the water level is running low, it will siphon water using its tail.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|The tuft on its head holds water. When the level runs low, it replenishes the tuft by siphoning water up with its tail.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The water which is expelled from its tail is of such high pressure that it can destroy concrete.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|The high-pressure water expelled from its tail is so powerful, it can destroy a concrete wall.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Munna==
{{redirect|Munna|the film|Munna (film)}}
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 517
|type = Psychic
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Musharna
}}
{{nihongo|'''Munna'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/munna/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Munna|accessdate=2010-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ムンナ}} is known as the Dream Eater Pokémon. It resembles a [[tapir]]. It can smoke out what looks like a reflection after eating the dreams of people and Pokémon. It evolves into Musharna when exposed to a Moon Stone.

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava stated &quot;the fact that it can eat my dreams makes it one Pokémon that I would want as an ally rather than an enemy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Musharna==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 518
|type = Psychic
|evolvesfrom = Munna
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Musharna'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/musharna/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Musharna |publisher=[[Pokémon]] |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ムシャーナ|Mushāna}}, known as the Drowsing Pokémon, is a rounded, [[pig]]- or [[tapir]]-like Pokémon. Many of the dreams of people and Pokémon are packed into the smoke emitted from its forehead.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|おでこから　でている　けむりの　なかには　ひとや　ポケモンの　みた　ゆめが　たくさんつまっているのだ。|Many of the dreams of people and Pokémon are packed into the smoke emitted from its forehead.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; It makes the dreams it ate materialize. The smoke leaking from its forehead changes form into the things from the dreams.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|たべた　ゆめを　じったいか　させる。おでこから　もれる　けむりが　ゆめに　でてきた　ものに　すがたを　かえる。|It makes the dreams it ate materialize. The smoke leaking from its forehead changes form into the things from the dreams.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Musharna appears in ''Black and White'' episode 6, &quot;Dreams by the Yard Full&quot;, under the ownership of Fennel.

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava criticized Musharna, stating the way it emits dreams from its forehead, calling it &quot;terrifying!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Pidove==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 519
|type = Normal/Flying
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Tranquill
}}
{{nihongo|'''Pidove'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/pidove/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Pidove|accessdate=2010-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;|マメパト|Mamepato}} is also known as the Tiny [[Pigeon]] Pokémon. Though it listens to its Trainer's instructions, its nature means it doesn't always understand them.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|トレーナの　めいれいを　よく　きく　せいかくだが　むずかしい　しじは　りかい　できない　こともある。|Though it listens to its Trainer's instructions, its nature means it doesn't always understand them.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Pokémon that lives in urban areas. It loves company so many of them gather in parks and plazas.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|まちなかで　くらしている　ポケモン。ひとなつっこいので　こうえんや　ひろばに　たくさん　あつまってくる。|A Pokémon that lives in urban areas. It loves company so many of them gather in parks and plazas.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Black and White'' episode 2 &quot;Enter Iris And Axew!&quot;, after [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] was attacked by a flock of Pidove that later flew away, one was left behind. He battled and eventually caught it. It eventually evolves into Tranquill in episode 22 &quot;Hiun City! Fushide Panic!!&quot;. In the ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' manga, a Pidove is one of the Pokémon employed by [[White (Pokémon Adventures)|White]] in her BW Agency.

''[[Official Nintendo Magazine]]''{{'}}s Chris Schilling commented that Pidove was the new [[Pidgey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;officialnintendomagazine1&quot;/&gt;

==Tranquill==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 520
|type = Normal/Flying
|evolvesfrom = Pidove
|evolvesto = Unfezant
}}
{{nihongo|'''Tranquill'''|ハトーボー|Hatōbō|Hatoboh}}, known as the Wild Pigeon Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Pidove]]. It is believed that, deep within the forest where Tranquill live, there is a peaceful country without strife.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Many people believe that, deep in the forest where Tranquill live, there is a peaceful place where there is no war.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ash's Pidove evolves into a Tranquill in ''Best Wishes!'' episode 22 &quot;A Venipede Stampede!&quot; after seeing Trip's Tranquill in action. In episode 44, a flock of wild Tranquill appears, enraged at a [[Purrloin]] for stealing their berries.

==Unfezant==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 521
|type = Normal/Flying
|evolvesfrom =Tranquill
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Unfezant'''|ケンホロウ|Kenhorō|Kenhallow}}, known as the Proud Pokémon, evolves from Tranquill, and is the final form of [[Pidove]]. Unfezant are one of the few Pokémon to have very noticeable gender differences. The males have large, pink, ribbon-like [[Wattle (anatomy)|wattles]], and green underbellies. The females have a small [[Crest (feathers)|crest]], and brown underbellies. Males swing their head plumage to threaten opponents,&lt;ref name=&quot;unfezantblack&quot;/&gt; and will never let themselves feel close to anyone other than their trainers.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Males have plumage on their heads. They will never let themselves feel close to anyone other than their trainers.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The females have flying abilities that surpass those of the males.&lt;ref name=&quot;unfezantblack&quot;&gt;{{pokedex|black|Males swing their head plumage to threaten opponents. The females' flying abilities surpass those of the males.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Blitzle==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 522
|type = Electric
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Zebstrika
}}
{{nihongo|'''Blitzle'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/blitzle/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Blitzle|accessdate=2010-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;|シママ|Shimama}}, known as the Electrified Pokémon, is a [[zebra]]-like Pokémon. Its mane shines when it discharges electricity. It communicates with its comrades by the light of its mane.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ほうでんすると　たてがみが　ひかる。たてがみの　ひかりかたで　なかまと　コミュニケーションを　とっている。|Its mane shines when it discharges electricity. It communicates with its comrades by the light of its mane.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; It appears when the sky is obscured by thunderclouds. It uses its mane to catch lightning and store the electricity.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|かみなりぐもで　そらが　おおわれると　あらわれる。たてがみで　カミナリを　キャッチして　でんきを　ためる。|It appears when the sky is obscured by thunderclouds. It uses its mane to catch lightning and store the electricity.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava stated, &quot;Something about Blitzle seems like it's trying too hard.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Zebstrika==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 523
|type = Electric
|evolvesfrom = Blitzle
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Zebstrika'''|ゼブライカ|Zeburaika|Zebraika}}, known as the Thunderbolt Pokémon, is the evolved form of Blitzle.  It is known for its ill tempered nature, and when its angry, the lightning that shoots from its mane goes in all directions.

==Roggenrola==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 524
|type = Rock
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = Boldore
}}
{{nihongo|'''Roggenrola'''|ダンゴロ|Dangoro}}, known as the Mantle Pokémon, is a blue rock-like Pokémon with a yellow hexagonal &quot;ear&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;roggenrolablack&quot;/&gt; It has brown feet, and a brown rocky figure extending from the top of its body. Compressed underground, its body is as hard as steel.&lt;ref name=&quot;roggenrolablack&quot;&gt;{{pokedex|black|Its ear is hexagonal in shape. Compressed underground, its body is as hard as steel.}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were discovered a hundred years ago in an earthquake fissure. Inside each one is an energy core.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|They were discovered a hundred years ago in an earthquake fissure. Inside each one is an energy core.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''[[Pokémon Master Black &amp; White]]'' manga, Monta uses a Roggenrola against [[Cheren (Pokémon)|Cheren]] in a triple battle.

==Boldore==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 525
|type = Rock
|evolvesfrom = Roggenrola
|evolvesto = Gigalith
}}
{{nihongo|'''Boldore'''|ガントル|Gantoru|Gantol}}, known as the [[Ore]] Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Roggenrola]], and will evolve into [[Gigalith]] when traded. Boldore is a blue Rock-type Pokémon, with orange crystals on its back and feet. These crystals formed when energy leaked from Boldore's body.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Because its energy was too great to be contained, the energy leaked and formed orange crystals.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Whenever its power gets too great, the orange crystals on its body glow. It is often found underground in caves, looking for water.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|When it overflows with power, the orange crystal on its body glows. It looks for underground water in caves.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gigalith==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 526
|type = Rock
|evolvesfrom = Boldore
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Gigalith'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/gigalith/|title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Gigalith|accessdate=2010-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ギガイアス|Gigaiasu|Gigaiath}}, known as the Compressed Pokémon, is a blue quadruped Pokémon with various red crystal-like objects on its body. It evolves from [[Boldore]] when traded, and is the final form of [[Roggenrolla]]. It compresses energy in the core inside its body in order to attack with enough power to blow away mountains.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|たいないの　コアで　エネルギーを　あっしゅくして　うちだす　こうげきは　やまを　ふきとばす　いりょく。|It compresses energy in the core inside its body in order to attack with enough power to blow away mountains.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; It absorbs sunlight with its orange-colored crystal and shoots energy from its mouth.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|オレンジいろの　けっしょうで　たいようこうせんを　きゅうしゅうして　くちから　エネルギーを　うちだす。|It absorbs sunlight with its orange-colored crystal and shoots energy from its mouth.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava praised it, stating &quot;Gigalith is exactly what you would want out of a Pokémon&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Woobat==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 527
|type = Psychic/Flying
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Swoobat
}}
{{nihongo|'''Woobat'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/woobat/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Woobat |publisher=[[Pokémon]] |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;|コロモリ|Koromori}}, known as the Bat Pokémon, is a white, shaggy creature based upon the [[Honduran white bat]]. It has a piggish, large nose with a nostril in the shape of a heart. Its eyes are hidden behind two shaggy tufts of fur. It has a large mouth with a single fang, and two relatively small wings on either side of it. It lives in dark forests and caves. It explores its surroundings by releasing ultrasonic waves from its nostrils.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|It lives in dark forests and caves. It explores its surroundings by releasing ultrasonic waves from its nostrils.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It sleeps stuck on the walls of caves by its nostrils. It leaves heart marks on the places where it was stuck.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|It sleeps stuck on the walls of caves by its nostrils. It leaves heart marks on the places where it was stuck.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Woobat's first appearance in the video games is in the two games [[Pokémon Black and White|''Pokémon Black'' and ''White'']] as a common Pokémon found in the wild. It eventually evolves into the Pokémon [[Swoobat]] by leveling up when its happiness is high. Happiness can be raised by fighting through many Pokémon battles. In the games, it was described as ''Black'' and ''White''{{'}}s version of the Pokémon [[Zubat (Pokémon)|Zubat]] due to being of a similar species&lt;ref name=&quot;ZubatReplace&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Jack DeVries |url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/110/1105793p1.html |title=Even More Pokemon Revealed - Nintendo DS News at IGN |publisher=IGN |date=2010-07-13 |accessdate=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Woobat also appears in the ''Pokémon'' spin-off game ''[[Battle &amp; Get! Pokémon Typing DS]]'' where players type in the names of Pokémon that they see. In the anime, [[Team Rocket (anime)|Jessie]] catches a Woobat while in a cave with James and [[Meowth]]. She uses it to battle against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] and [[Iris (Pokémon anime)|Iris]]. It manages to defeat Ash's newly captured [[Pidove]] but is defeated by [[Oshawott]]'s Water Gun. Woobat has made other minor appearances in the anime. In the ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' manga, a Woobat is in the possession of the character [[White (Pokémon)|White]].

[[IGN]] described it as the baby of &quot;a [[Tribble]], a bat, and a pig&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;IGNJuly 13&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/110/1105793p1.html |title=Even More Pokemon Revealed - Nintendo DS News at IGN |publisher=IGN |date=July 13, 2010 |author=Jack DeVries |accessdate=2010-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava stated &quot;I kind of like the idea of having a romantic bat as a Pokémon...However, I'm not sold on its abilities&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt; Jeremy Parish of [[Retronauts]] criticized the series' use of redundant new Pokémon, commenting that Woobat was the same as [[Zubat (Pokémon)|Zubat]], referencing the uncanny similarities in name.&lt;ref&gt;http://podcast.the1upnetwork.com/flat/Retronauts/R030611.mp3&lt;/ref&gt; IGN's Jack DeVries questioned whether Woobat would act as a Zubat replacement.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZubatReplace&quot;/&gt; He later expressed that despite being unsure of Woobat's quality, he wrote that &quot;at least he's not a Zubat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jack DeVries |url=http://ds.ign.com/articles/110/1105966p1.html |title=Why We're Excited for Pokemon Black/White - Nintendo DS Feature at IGN |publisher=IGN |date=2010-07-13 |accessdate=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[1UP.com]]'s Kat Bailey wrote that Woobat was basically a Zubat with a pig's snout.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/reviews/pokmon-black-white-review |title=Pokemon Black/White Review for DS from |publisher=1UP.com |author=Kat Bailey |date=2011-03-14 |accessdate=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; 1UP.com's Michael Vreeland wrote that Woobat was &quot;a lot more interesting&quot; than Zubat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.1up.com/do/blogEntry?bId=9061884 |title=1UP's RPG Blog : Gotta Blog 'Em All #5: Poktoberfest Continues! |publisher=1UP.com |author=Michael Vreeland |date=Oct 22, 2010 |accessdate=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[G4TV]]'s Nikole Zivalich, however wrote that Woobat was derivative and inferior to Zubat and that while fans will appreciate not having to run into so many Zubats, the &quot;alternative isn't much better&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Zivalich |first=Nikole |url=http://www.g4tv.com/games/3ds/63897/pokemon-black-version/articles/74043/pokemon-black-and-white/ |title=Pokemon Black Version for Nintendo DS - Preview - Pokemon Black and White |publisher=G4tv.com |date=2011-03-25 |accessdate=2011-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carolyn Gudmundson of [[GamesRadar]] similarly described Woobat as the &quot;new Zubat&quot;, noting that based on their looks, it and its evolution are two of their favourite Pokémon; however, they do note that they have some faults gameplay-wise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gamesradar.com/ds/f/pokemon-black-and-white-pokedex-woobat-swoobat/a-20110302114515391052/g-201004091000657031 |title=Pokemon Black and White Pokedex - Woobat, Swoobat, Pokemon Black / White DS Features |publisher=GamesRadar |date= |accessdate=2011-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Swoobat==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 528
|type = Psychic/Flying
|evolvesfrom = Woobat
|evolvesto = None
}}
{{nihongo|'''Swoobat'''|ココロモリ|Kokoromori}}, known as the [[Courtship|Courting]] Pokémon, evolves from [[Woobat]] by leveling it up when its happiness is high. Happiness can be raised by fighting through many Pokémon battles. Swoobat is a blue bat-like Pokémon with a white mane of fur, a heart shaped nose, and a vaguely heart shape at the end of its tail. The sound waves it emits from its nose are of a frequency powerful enough to destroy rocks.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|It emits sound waves of carious frequencies from its nose including some powerful enough to destroy rocks.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ultrasonic waves emitted by a courting male causes people to have a positive mood.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Anyone who comes into contact with the ultrasonic waves emitted by a courting male experiences a positive mood shift.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Drilbur==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 529
|type = Ground
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Excadrill
}}
{{nihongo|'''Drilbur'''|モグリュー|Moguryū|Mogurew}},&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/drilbur/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Drilbur |publisher=[[Pokémon]] |accessdate=2011-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; known as the [[Mole (animal)|Mole]] Pokémon, burrows underground at more than 50&amp;nbsp;km/h. Its running speed above ground rivals automobiles.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|{{tooltip|ちちゅうを　ほりすすむ　スピードは　じそく５０キロいじょう。ちじょうを　はしる　じどうしゃと　いいしょうぶ。|The speed at which it burrows underground is more than 50 km/h. Its running speed above ground rivals automobiles.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; By crossing both its claws it makes itself rotate at high speeds and progresses underground at a great speed.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|{{tooltip|りょうての　ツメを　かさねあわせて　からだを　こうそく　かいてんさせると　もうスピードで　ちちゅうを　すすむ。|By crossing both its claws it makes itself rotate at high speeds and progresses underground at a great speed.}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava criticized its design, stating &quot;I just don't feel very intimidated when I look at Drilbur.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Excadrill==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 530
|type = Ground/Steel
|evolvesfrom = Drilbur
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Excadrill'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/excadrill/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Excadrill |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;|ドリュウズ|Doryūzu}}, known as the Subterrene Pokémon, is the evolved form of Drilbur. It makes a [[labyrinth]]-like burrow 100 meters below the surface. Its drills have the destructive power to pierce through any iron plate.

An Excadrill appears in the ''Black &amp; White'' season of the anime, being owned by Iris. However, Iris's Excadrill is disobedient, and will only act when it wants to.

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava praised Excadrill calling it &quot;bad-ass&quot;, and citing its steel claws and revenge-seeking expression.&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Audino==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 531
|type = Normal
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Audino'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/audino/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Audino |accessdate=2011-02-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;|タブンネ|Tabunne}}, is known as the Hearing Pokémon. With its big ears, it can access other Pokémon's emotions and health. It also has the power to understand its surroundings through slight sounds.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Its auditory sense is astounding. It has a radar-like ability to understand its surrounding through slight sounds.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Audino replaces Chansey and Blissey as the preferred companions of Pokémon Center nurses in the Unova Region, despite its gender ratio being equally balanced.

Players often search incessantly for it, as it gives a enormous amount of Experience Points when defeated, making the training of a Pokémon slightly easy. It also is a Pacifist, based on its healer ability. It can, despite being a pure-normal type, learn 9 Psychic-type moves, with 2 more from breeding.

==Timburr==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 532
|type = Fighting
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Gurdurr
}}
{{nihongo|'''Timburr'''|ドッコラー|Dokkorā}}, known as the Muscular Pokémon, is a gray-colored bipedal Pokémon that has pink vein-like bulges. It carries a piece of [[lumber]] around, which it uses to fight with.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|It fights by swinging a piece of lumber around. It is close to evolving when it can handle the lumber without difficulty.}}&lt;/ref&gt; These Pokémon often are seen at building sites helping out with construction.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|These Pokémon appear at building sites and help out with construction. They always carry squared logs.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''[[Pokémon Adventures]]'' manga, [[Team Plasma]] Grunts were assisted by many Timburr to build a stage for their rally in Accumula Town.

==Gurdurr==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 533
|type = Fighting
|evolvesfrom = Timburr
|evolvesto = Conkeldurr
}}
{{nihongo|'''Gurdurr'''|ドテッコツ|Dotekkotsu}}, known as the Muscular Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Timburr]]. Gurdurr are so strong and muscular they will not move when attacked by a group of pro wrestlers. They carry I-shaped steel beams to increase this muscle, which is shown off to friends.

==Conkeldurr==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 534
|type = Fighting
|evolvesfrom = Gurdurr
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Conkeldurr'''|ローブシン|Rōbushin}}, known as the Muscular Pokémon, is the final evolution of [[Timburr]]. They are burly humanoid Pokémon and use two stone pillars, one in each hand, as walking canes which can be freely swung around in battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|They use concrete pillars as walking canes. They know moves that enable them to swing the pillars freely in battle.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apparently, they taught humans how to make concrete over two millennia ago.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|It is thought that Conkeldurr taught humans how to make concrete more than 2,000 years ago.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tympole==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 535
|type = Water
|evolvesfrom = 
|evolvesto = Palpitoad
}}
{{nihongo|'''Tympole'''|オタマロ|Otamaro}}, known as the [[Tadpole]] Pokémon, is a tadpole-like Pokémon with a cream-colored face, a blue tail, and blue bumps on the side of its head. They vibrate their cheeks to make a high-pitched sound that warns others of danger.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|They warn others of danger by vibrating their cheeks to create a high-pitched sound.}}&lt;/ref&gt; While these sound waves are unable to be heard by humans, Tympole use them to talk with each other.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|By vibrating its cheeks, it emits sound waves imperceptible to humans. It uses the rhythm of these sounds to talk.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Palpitoad==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 536
|type = Water/Ground
|evolvesfrom = Tympole
|evolvesto = Seismitoad
}}
{{nihongo|'''Palpitoad'''|ガマガル|Gamagaru}}, known as the Vibration Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Tympole]]. Palpitoad have vibraters on their bodies that look like lumps. When they vibrate these lumps they can cause earthquakes. It possesses a sticky long tongue in which it uses to catch prey.

In the ''Best Wishes'' episode &quot;Facing Fear With Eyes Wide Open!&quot;, a Palpitoad is encountered and it leads a school of Tympole to attack Ash's Oshawott and prevent it from getting herbs to cure the company's poisoned Pokémon. After the Tympole swim away, it calls on its friend, a Stunfisk, to get rid of Oshawott. Cilan makes short work of Stunfisk with his fishing rod, so Palpitoad comes to battle Oshawott personally. After a long battle, Oshawott learns to keep its eyes open underwater, leading to the perfection of its new Aqua Jet attack, which helps Ash to catch the Palpitoad and Cilan to catch the Stunfisk.

==Seismitoad==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 537
|type = Water/Ground
|evolvesfrom = Palpitoad
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Seismitoad'''|ガマゲロゲ|Gamageroge}}, known as the Vibration Pokémon, is the final evolution of [[Tympole]]. According to the Pokédex, they shoot paralyzing liquid from their head bumps. They use vibration to hurt their opponents.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|They shoot paralyzing liquid from their head bumps. They use vibration to hurt their opponents.&lt;/ref&gt; Their vibration also increases the power of their punches. With a single punch, a boulder can be turned into a pile of rubble. &lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|It increases the power of its punches by vibrating the bumps on its fists. It can turn a boulder to rubble with one punch.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

It is the only Water-type Pokémon with a double weakness to Grass to learn no damage dealing Ice-type moves. Instead of Ice-type moves though, Seismitoad can be taught Poison-type moves such as Sludge Wave to fend off Grass-types.

==Throh==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 538
|type = Fighting
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Throh'''|ナゲキ|Nageki}}, known as the [[Judo]] Pokémon, is a red, fat human-like Pokémon wearing a white and black martial arts outfit. When it tightens its belt, it becomes stronger. Wild Throh use vines to weave their own belts.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|When it tightens its belt, it becomes stronger. Wild Throh use vines to weave their own belts.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Always traveling in packs of five, they throw foes that are bigger than them.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|When they encounter foes bigger than themselves, they try to throw them. They always travel in packs of five.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sawk==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 539
|type = Fighting
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Sawk'''|ダゲキ|Dageki}} known as the [[Karate]] Pokémon, is a blue, thin human-like Pokémon wearing a white and black martial arts outfit. The sound of Sawk punching boulders and trees can be heard all the way from the mountains where they train.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|The sound of Sawk punching boulders and trees can be heard all the way from the mountains where they train.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tying their belts gets them pumped and makes their punches more destructive. Disturbing their training angers them.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|Tying their belts gets them pumped and makes their punches more destructive. Disturbing their training angers them.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sewaddle==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 540
|type = Bug/Grass 
|evolvesto = Swadloon
}}
{{nihongo|'''Sewaddle'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pokemonblackwhite.com/en-us/pokemon/sewaddle/ |title=Pokémon Black Version and Pokémon White Version {{!}} Sewaddle |accessdate=2011-02-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;|クルミル|Kurumiru}}, known as the Sewing Pokémon, is a caterpillar-like Pokémon with a leaf around its head. Its parent makes clothes to dress it in once it hatches from its egg. It sleeps with its head covered by its hood.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|Leavanny dress in its clothes they made for it when it hatched. It hides its head in its hood while it is sleeping.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It makes its own clothes by gnawing up leaves and sewing them together with adhesive thread from its mouth.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|This Pokémon makes clothes for itself. It chews up leaves and sews them with sticky thread extruded from its mouth.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sewaddle makes its anime debut in &quot;Sewaddle and Burgh in Pinwheel Forest!&quot; where [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] catches one. It evolves into [[Swadloon]] while battling [[Burgh (Pokémon)|Burgh]]'s [[Whirlipede]].

''[[Game Informer]]''{{'}}s Jeff Marchiafava stated &quot;I don't normally like Grass-based Pokémon, but Sewaddle is alright in my book.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;GI30POKE&quot;/&gt;

==Swadloon==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 541
|type = Bug/Grass
|evolvesfrom = Sewaddle
|evolvesto = Leavanny
}}
{{nihongo|'''Swadloon'''|クルマユ|Kurumayu}}, known as the Leaf-Wrapped Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Sewaddle]].

In the ''Best Wishes!'' anime, Ash acquires a Swadloon when his Sewaddle evolves in the episode &quot;Battling for the love of Bug Types!&quot;.

==Leavanny==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 542
|type = Bug/Grass
|evolvesfrom = Swadloon 
}} 
{{nihongo|'''Leavanny'''|ハハコモリ|Hahakomori}}, known as the Nurturing Pokémon, evolves from [[Swadloon]] if it has high happiness. Happiness is gained by leveling up Pokémon, but decreases slightly if it faints. Its appearance is similar to that of a mantis. It weaves clothing for small Pokémon, especially [[Sewaddle]], using the cutters on its arm and its sticky silk.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|Upon finding a small Pokémon, it weaves clothing for it from leaves, using the cutters on its arms and sticky silk.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also keeps its eggs warm from fermenting leaves.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|It keeps its eggs warm with heat from fermenting leaves. It also uses leaves to make warm wrappings for Sewaddle.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It makes clothes by attaching mucoid string to the tips of its hands and sews leaves together.

In the ''Best Wishes'' Pokémon anime series, Burgh's Leavanny has appeared in the episodes ''Sewaddle and Burgh in Pinwheel Forest!'' and ''Battling For The Love of Bug-Types!''. In the latter episode, he uses it in battle when Ash challenges him for the Insect Badge.

==Venipede==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 543
|type = Bug/Poison
|evolvesfrom =
|evolvesto = Whirlipede
}}
{{nihongo|'''Venipede'''|フシデ|Fushide}}, known as the [[Centipede]] Pokémon, is a red insect-like Pokémon with a green band around its body. While some large birds try to prey on it, Venipede's bite has enough poison to paralyze them.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|Its bite injects a potent poison, enough to paralyze large bird Pokémon that try to prey on it.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brutally aggressive, it discovers what is going on around it by using the feelers on its head and tail.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|It discovers what is going on around it by using the feelers on its head and tail. It is brutally aggresive.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A swarm of Venipede appear in ''Best Wishes!'' episode 22 &quot;A Veinipiede Stampede!&quot;.

==Whirlipede==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 544
|type = Bug/Poison
|evolvesfrom = Venipede
|evolvesto = Scolipede
}}
{{nihongo|'''Whirlipede'''|ホイーガ|Hoīga|Wheega}}, known as the Curlipede Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Venipede]]. Protected by a hard shell, it's usually motionless, but when it's attacked, it rotates at high speed and crashes furiously into the opponent(s).&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|Protected by a hard shell, it spins its body like a wheel and crashes furiously into its enemies.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|It is usually motionless, but when attacked, it rotates at high speed and then crashes into its opponent.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Burgh (Pokémon)|Burgh]] uses a Whirlipede against [[Ash Ketchum|Ash]] in a gym battle.

==Scolipede==
{{pokeinfoboxsmall
|number = 545
|type = Bug/Poison
|evolvesfrom = Whirlipede
|evolvesto = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Scolipede'''|ペンドラー|Pendorā|Pendror}}, known as the Mega [[Centipede]] Pokémon, is the evolved form of [[Whirlipede]]. Scolipede is a centipede-like Pokémon, with bright [[magenta]] coloration with purple rings spaced evenly along its segmented upper body. It will chase down enemies with its fast movements and attack them with the horn on its head. It is to date the largest Bug-type Pokémon at 8'02&quot;. It gives no mercy until it strikes the final blow.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|black|&lt;!--Jap--&gt;It will chase down enemies with its fast movements and attack them with the horn on its head. It gives no mercy until it strikes the final blow.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It makes the claws on its neck dig into its opponent and injects poison. It has a very aggressive personality.&lt;ref&gt;{{pokedex|white|&lt;!--Jap--&gt;It makes the claws on its neck dig into its opponent and injects poison. It has a very aggressive personality.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A wild Scolipede appears in  ''The Bloom is on Axew''. [[Iris (Pokémon)|Iris]]'s [[Axew]] falls out of a tree and gets caught in Scolipede's antennae. This startles Scolipede and causes it to go on a rampage, until Iris's [[Excadrill]] decides to defeat it with its Drill Run attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;BW009&quot;&gt;{{Cite episode | title = Out of Control Pendror! Rescue Kibago! (ペンドラー暴走！キバゴを救え！！) |series = [[Pocket Monsters: Best Wishes!]] | network =[[TV Tokyo]] | airdate = September 23, 2010 | season = 14 | seriesno = 660 |credits=Atsuhiro Tomioka (writer)}}&lt;/ref&gt;
A Scolipede also appeared in ''Emolga The Irresistible'', after Bianica blasted it with her Pignite's Flamethrower.

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}
{{Pokemon directory}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Pokemon (494-545)}}
[[Category:Lists of Pokémon|494]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
