<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2912485" ns="0" title="Alisa Camplin"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}
{{MedalTableTop}}
{{MedalCountry | {{AUS}} }}
{{MedalSport|Women's [[Freestyle skiing at the Winter Olympics|Freestyle skiing]]}}
{{MedalGold|[[2002 Winter Olympics|Salt Lake City 2002]]|[[Freestyle skiing at the 2002 Winter Olympics#Women's aerials|Aerials]]}}
{{MedalBronze|[[2006 Winter Olympics|Turin 2006]]|[[Freestyle skiing at the 2006 Winter Olympics#Women's Aerials|Aerials]]}}
{{MedalSport | [[FIS Freestyle World Ski Championships]]}}
{{MedalGold| [[FIS Freestyle World Ski Championships 2003|2003 Deer Valley]]|Aerials}}
{{MedalBottom}}

'''Alisa Camplin''' [[Order of Australia|OAM]] (born 10 November 1974) is an [[Australia]]n [[Freestyle skiing|aerial skier]] who won gold at the [[2002 Winter Olympics]], the second ever winter olympic gold medal for Australia.  At the [[2006 Winter Olympics]], Camplin finished third, a bronze medal. She is the first [[Skiing in Australia|Australian skiier]] to win medals at consecutive Winter Olympics.

==Background==
Alisa is an ex-gymnast, standing at 157&amp;nbsp;cm tall. She was educated in [[Melbourne]] at the [[Methodist Ladies' College, Melbourne|Methodist Ladies' College]] and has a [[bachelor's degree]] in [[information technology]] from [[Swinburne University of Technology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AIS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Alisa Camplin|url=http://www.ausport.gov.au/ais/history/ais_alumni/where_are_they_now/alisa_camplin|publisher=Australian Institute of Sport|accessdate=7 January 2011|date=11 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a teenager, Alisa was an accomplished sailor, winning two Australian National Titles in the [[Hobie Cat]] [[catamaran]] class. Inspired by the example of three-time Olympian [[Kirstie Marshall]], Camplin approached the Olympic Winter Institute of Australia in 1994 to see the possibilities of becoming an aerial skier. She was new to skiing, and even in Salt Lake she trampled on her victory flowers when she fell over during the trip to the winner's news conference.

She practiced jumps in a pond in [[Wandin, Victoria|Wandin]] (one hour's drive from [[Melbourne]]) and was coached by Todd Ossian.

Injuries she has suffered include a [[clavicle fracture|broken collarbone]], broken hand, [[separated shoulder]], two broken ankles, torn Achilles tendon, [[Anterior cruciate ligament injury|torn ACL]], and nine [[concussion]]s.

Before the 2002 Winter Olympics, none of the dozen top 10 results she had made on the World Cup circuit included a victory, and compatriot [[Jacqui Cooper]] was viewed as the favourite for the aerials event. While most athletes use flags to mark the start of their jumps, Alisa used a wooden spoon. The rationale was that early in her career, confusion was caused by both Alisa and Jacqui using Australian flags to mark their starts, but in Australia a [[wooden spoon (award)|wooden spoon]] is a metaphorical prize for people or teams coming last in their sporting event.

Alisa studied information technology and business at [[Swinburne University of Technology]] in the 1990s.

==Salt Lake City 2002==
Alisa competed at the Olympics against doctors' advice – she had injured herself after being caught by a headwind in training a few weeks before. At the time, she was told she had bone bruising, it was not until she was examined by doctors in Salt Lake that she discovered both her ankles were fractured. The doctors were amazed that she was walking, let alone planning to jump.

[[Jacqui Cooper]] injured her knee in practice a week before the games. Alisa was so nervous she did not eat dinner the night before the final. Camplin performed a pair of triple-twisting, double backflip jumps to win the event.

Her family had been told to stay home by the athlete because she did not want distractions in the crowd, but her mother and younger sister Georgina defied her, watching her from behind a large Australian flag.

Alisa said that [[Steven Bradbury|Steven Bradbury's]] recent win in short track made things easier for her: &quot;When he came through, it almost pleased me that I didn't have to go out and do this,&quot; she said. &quot;I knew that was a big thing my nation was trying to chase. When Steven did it, I was like, 'Good, I don't have the weight of the nation on my shoulders.'&quot;

Camplin's gold was celebrated by [[Australia post]] issuing a 45 cent stamp of her. Her stamp was issued on 22 February, four days after her victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;GlenStephens&quot;&gt;[http://www.glenstephens.com/linnsMarch11-02.html Aussie golds in Winter games bring more instant stamps] by Glen Stephens. Linn's stamp news. 11 March 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; She received [[Australian dollar|A$]]20,000 for the use of her image. Camplin was delighted, saying &quot;For us to be put in with the summer Olympians who had their stamps and the previous 39 sporting legends who’ve had their stamps is amazing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AOCstamps&quot;&gt;&quot;Gold medallists get framed stamps&quot; [[Australian Olympic Committee]] 25 February 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Turin 2006==
In her preparations for the Turin Winter Olympics, Camplin incurred a serious knee injury in October 2005, requiring a [[knee reconstruction]].  To speed the healing process, she used the relatively uncommon practice of using donor tissue in the knee, and returned to limited training only 11 weeks after the surgery.  She finished fourth at a World Cup event in Lake Placid to secure her place in the team.  

On 22 February, in a night competition that was marked by a thick fog that disturbed competitions to an extent, Camplin registered a score of 94.99 in her first jump, the fourth best.  In the second jump, she received a 96.40, which temporarily placed her second, a silver medal.  She was, however, eventually dislodged by [[People's Republic of China|China]]'s [[Li Nina]], finishing third behind [[Switzerland]]'s [[Evelyne Leu]], who won the event, and Nina, who took silver.  She also benefited from the unexpected fall of China's [[Xinxin Guo]], who had received the highest score in the first jump and was expected to secure a place in the Olympic podium &amp;mdash; at which time Camplin, who was already third then, would have gone out of the medal zone.

She was selected to be the Australian flag-bearer at the [[2006 Winter Olympics Opening Ceremony|Opening Ceremony]].

==Post-skiing career==
Camplin announced her retirement from competition in July 2006.  She intends to pursue interests in the media and in the ski travel industry.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/sport/content/200607/s1688108.htm|title=Camplin hangs up skis|publisher=[[Australian Broadcasting Commission|ABC (Australia) online news]]|date=17 July 2006|accessdate=17 July 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of 30 July 2006, she is an international executive for [[IBM]], works as a motivational speaker, and does promotional and charity work. Camplin currently works as a senior executive at IBM managing a team of over 300 people. She has been the face of [[Wm. Wrigley Jr. Company|Wrigley's]] [[Extra (gum)|Extra]] [[chewing gum]] in Australia since shortly after the 2002 Winter Olympics. She is also a judge on the Australian television competition ''[[Torvill and Dean's Dancing on Ice]]'', and runs Alisa Camplin Ski Tours.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | last=Dobbin | first=Winsor | title=High flyer | date=30 July 2006 | publisher=The Age | url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/sport/high-flyer/2006/07/29/1153816427228.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 November 2009, Alisa Camplin was one of 15 international torchbearers taking part in the relay's International media program, aimed at increasing global coverage of the cross-Canada relay.  She ran on day 6 of the [[2010 Winter Olympics torch relay|Vancouver 2010 Winter Olympic torch relay]] through the town of [[Dawson City]] in the [[Yukon Territory]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.heraldsun.com.au/sport/torch-relay-stirs-up-fire-in-aussie-champ-alisa-camplin/story-e6frf9if-1225794824163&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 December 2009, It was announced that Alisa has joined the [[Collingwood Football Club]] board as a replacement for [[Sally Capp]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.theage.com.au/breaking-news-sport/camplin-joins-magpies-board-20091208-khs7.html theage.com retrieved 30 April 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Personal Life==
Camplin married Oliver Warner in December 2010. Their first child, Finnan Maximus Camplin-Warner, was born six weeks prematurely on 10th March 2011. Sadly, Finnan died 10 days later due to a congenital heart condition. Camplin and Warner have set up the charity Finnan's Gift (www.finnansgift.com.au), organised through the Royal Children's Hospital, to raise money to buy equipment that will detect heart defects in other babies. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Olympic champ Alisa Camplin celebrates double joy|url=http://www.heraldsun.com.au/entertainment/confidential/olympic-champ-alisa-camplin-celebrates-double-joy/story-e6frf96o-1225980625149|accessdate=7 January 2011|newspaper=Herald Sun|date=3 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;Alisa Camplin speaks about losing baby|http://news.ninemsn.com.au/national/8251951/alisa-camplin-speaks-about-losing-baby&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/olympics/2002/skiing/news/2002/02/18/womens_aerials_ap/ Flying high: Camplin's aerials win gives Australia another gold]
* [http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/olympics/2002/news/2002/02/18/murphy_camplin/ She comes from the land Down Under : Aussie aerialist Camplin captures gold in dramatic fashion]
* [http://www.sportal.com.au/othersports.asp?i=news&amp;id=77608 Camplin to Carry Australian Flag] - sportal.com.au, Friday 10 February
* [http://www.finnansgift.com.au/ Finnan's Gift]

{{Footer Olympic champions in freestyle skiing}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Camplin, Alisa
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 10 November 1974
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Camplin, Alisa}}
[[Category:1974 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Australian freestyle skiers]]
[[Category:Dancing on Ice participants]]
[[Category:Freestyle skiers at the 2002 Winter Olympics]]
[[Category:Freestyle skiers at the 2006 Winter Olympics]]
[[Category:Olympic freestyle skiers of Australia]]
[[Category:Olympic gold medalists for Australia]]
[[Category:Olympic bronze medalists for Australia]]
[[Category:Sportswomen from Melbourne]]
[[Category:Swinburne University of Technology alumni]]
[[Category:Olympic medalists in freestyle skiing]]

[[ca:Alisa Camplin]]
[[de:Alisa Camplin]]
[[fr:Alisa Camplin]]
[[ja:アリサ・キャンプリン]]
[[pl:Alisa Camplin]]
[[pt:Alisa Camplin]]
[[ru:Кэмплин, Алиса]]
[[fi:Alisa Camplin]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
