<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29178481" ns="0" title="We&#039;ll Bring the House Down (song)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the Slade album|We'll Bring the House Down}}
{{Infobox single
| Name = We'll Bring the House Down
| Cover = Slade We'll Bring the House Down Single UK.jpg
| Caption = UK cover of &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot;.
| Artist = [[Slade]]
| from Album = [[We'll Bring the House Down]]
| B-side = Hold On To Your Hats
| Released = 23 January, [[1981 in music|1981]]
| Format = 7&quot; Single
| Recorded =
| Genre = [[Rock music|Rock]]
| Length = 3:32
| Label = Cheapskate Records
| Writer = [[Noddy Holder]]; [[Jim Lea]]
| Producer = [[Slade]]
| Last single = &quot;[[Xmas Ear Bender (EP)]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(1980)
| This single = &quot;'''We'll Bring the House Down'''&quot;&lt;br&gt;(1981)
| Next single = &quot;[[Wheels Ain't Coming Down]]&quot;&lt;br&gt;(1981)
| Misc           =
  {{Audiosample
  | Upper caption = Audio sample
  | Name = We'll Bring the House Down
  | Audio file  = Slade_We'll_Bring_The_House_Down.ogg
  }}
{{Extra album cover
|Type = studio
|Upper caption = Alternative Cover
|Cover = Sladesingle-wellbringthehousedown.jpeg
|Lower caption = German cover of &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot;.
}}
}}

&quot;'''We'll Bring The House Down'''&quot; is a [[single (music)|single]] from rock band [[Slade]] from their 1981 album [[We'll Bring the House Down]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.discogs.com/Slade-Well-Bring-The-House-Down/master/192181 |title=Slade - We'll Bring The House Down at Discogs |publisher=Discogs.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was written by lead singer [[Noddy Holder]] and bassist [[Jim Lea]]. After years of touring in small venues and releasing a string of unsuccessful singles and albums, the single was the first Top Thirty hit for Slade since 1976, peaking at number ten in the UK during a chart run of nine weeks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chartstats.com/ |title=UK Singles &amp; Albums Chart Archive |publisher=Chart Stats |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was largely thanks to the Reading festival the year before after Ozzy Osbourne's band had pulled out at the last minute and Slade agreed to step in instead. The band stole the show and became hot news once again.&lt;ref&gt;Slade's remastered album We'll Bring The House Down booklet&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2003, the song was sampled by [[Overseer]] for the track titled Slayed which was also the name of Slade's 1972 album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whosampled.com/sampled/Slade/ |title=Slade Music Sampled by Others |publisher=WhoSampled |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As well as peaking at #10 in the UK, the single peaked at #4 in the Melody Maker charts.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1981&quot;&gt;Slade Supporters Club Newsletter March - April 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
The idea for the track originally came while the band were performing in [[Amsterdam]] at the [[Paradiso (Amsterdam)|Paradiso]] club. An enthusiastic audience who wouldn't go home kept repeating the chant heard in this song. Lea, downstairs in the dressing room, as ever, on the hunt for the next song and realised the potential of the chant. The drums on the track were completely double tracked with Powell playing in the toilet on the second track which gave the echoey sound. Holder's lyrics reflected Slade's shift towards a heavier sound.&lt;ref&gt;Slade's Greatest Hits compilation booklet&lt;/ref&gt;

The song was took two days to record on the 4th and 5 January that year. This was recorded at the Portland Recording Studios in London. To receive the distinctive vocal and drum sounds, the band recorded the parts in the Gentlemen's toilets at the studio. The band had to stop recording every time somebody flushed the toilet in the ladies' restroom, because the sound could be heard.&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/1145862_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

The track had been covered by Marshall Law, Not Fragile and Victoria's Secret advert.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crazeeworld.plus.com/slade/2011/pages/the_music.htm#covers |title=SLADE @ www.slayed.co.uk |publisher=Crazeeworld.plus.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In a early 1990 Slade fan club interview, it was announced that Lea had been working with a female singer on a new version of the track, which was later released under the name The Clout. It was backed by an instrumental composition from Lea, titled &quot;Jim Jam&quot;. The female vocal on the song was a singer of English jazz-funk band [[Shakatak]].&lt;ref&gt;Slade International Fan Club newsletter January - February - March 1990&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/7924117_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/9686983_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

A promotional video was created for the track along with TV performances on Top of The Pops, Moondogs and German show Musikladen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crazeeworld.plus.com/slade/2011/pages/tv_video.htm |title=SLADE @ www.slayed.co.uk |publisher=Crazeeworld.plus.com |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; The promotional video for &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; was filmed at the band's Ipswich Gaumont Concert on the 17th January 1981 by an independent film company. This company also recorded a documentary about the band's life on the road however this was never released.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1981&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/179131_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

BBC presenter and radio DJ [[Mike Read]] noted the band's &quot;electrifying&quot; performance on Top of the Pops. The following day, Read noted on his breakfast show that the programme seemed rather flat after Slade's performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1981&quot;/&gt;

In a 1981 fan club interview, drummer Don Powell was asked if he thought that Slade would ever make a comeback after many years of commercial failure. Powell repsonded ''&quot;The thing is we don't think of it as a comeback just because &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; made the charts. We didn't really think how long it had been since we had a hit until &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; charted, and then everyone told us that it was amazingly our first hit for four or five years, and we realised.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/1822580_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;Slade Supporters Club Newsletter May - June 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

In a 1981 fan club interview, guitarist Dave Hill mentioned performing the song on Belgian TV. &quot;We did a major TV show in Belgium to promote &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot;. The guy who makes the TV show likes us, so he let us do two extra tracks; &quot;[[Wheels Ain't Coming Down]]&quot; and &quot;I'm a Rocker&quot;, which was a hit over there.&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/6602796_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Supporters Club Newsletter September - October 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

During a 1981 televised gig that [[The Who]] were performing in Paris, the audience began singing the chant of &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; in-between songs, much to The Who's annoyance. One crowd member eventually jumped on the stage and shouted &quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/6119927_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

==Formats==
;7&quot; Single
#&quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; - 3:32
#&quot;Hold on to Your Hats&quot; - 2:33

;7&quot; Single (German only version)
#&quot;We'll Bring the House Down&quot; - 3:32
#&quot;Wheels Ain't Coming Down&quot; - 3:36

== Critical reception ==
At the time of release, reviews were overall mixed.

[[Sounds (magazine)|Sounds]] wrote ''&quot;stick down some rock hard Glamboy drums, swinging schlocko guitar, which out crasses fatty Jones, and a little spicy chant a long a football terrace toon and who can fail? Slade's current resurgence amongst the anti literati seems to have provided a much needed livener which has lifted years off their shoulders. Platforms? Its nearly here...&quot;''  

[[Melody Maker]] wrote ''&quot;Despite the impetus they've gained over the last eight weeks, they blow it with a messy live orientated song and a muddy production that does little to explain to others what all the fuss is about with this revival thing... How about re releasing 'When I'm Dancin' I aint Fightin' lads?&quot;''

[[Record Mirror]] stated ''&quot;And then Slade - nice to see the up turn in their fortunes which followed Reading, but a shame that its taken such rotten, clumsy HM to do the trick. Bring the house down should pander to the band's new headbanger following alright, but frankly it hasn't got much going for it. A crass echo of former glories.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sladeinengland.co.uk/press/singles/SINGSHOUSE.HTM |title=SLADE We'll bring the house down |publisher=Sladeinengland.co.uk |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chart performance==
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
!Chart (1981)
!Peak&lt;br&gt;position
!Total&lt;br&gt;weeks
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|German Singles Chart&lt;ref&gt;Slade Supporters Club Newsletter September - October 1981&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://sladefanclub.weebly.com/uploads/7/6/6/0/7660950/1536733_orig.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|10
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|2
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Irish Singles Chart&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jaclyn Ward - Fireball Media Group - http://www.fireballmedia.ie |url=http://www.irishcharts.ie/search/placement |title=The Irish Charts - All there is to know |publisher=Irishcharts.ie |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|11
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|4
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot;|UK Singles Chart&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chartstats.com/release.php?release=9033 |title=Slade - We'll Bring The House Down |publisher=Chart Stats |date= |accessdate=2011-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|10
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;|9
|}

== Personnel ==
*Noddy Holder: Lead vocals and guitar
*Jim Lea: Bass guitar and backing vocals
*Dave Hill: Lead guitar and backing vocals
*Don Powell: Drums

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Slade}}

[[Category:1981 singles]]
[[Category:Slade songs]]
[[Category:Songs written by Noddy Holder]]
[[Category:Songs written by Jim Lea]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
