<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29200" ns="0" title="Seattle University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{primarysources|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox university
 |name              = Seattle University
 |native_name       = 
 |image_name        = Seattle University Seal.svg
 |image_size        = 
 |caption           = 
 |latin_name        = 
 |motto             = 
 |mottoeng          = 
 |established       = 1891
 |closed            = 
 |type              = [[Private University|Private]]
 |affiliation       = [[Society of Jesus|Jesuit]] ([[Catholic Church|Catholic]])
 |endowment         = $164 Million&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2011/schools/seattle-university |title=Seattle University – Green Report Card 2011 |publisher=Greenreportcard.org |date=March 31, 2010 |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |officer_in_charge = 
 |chairman          = 
 |president emeritus= 
 |president         = [[Stephen V. Sundborg]], S.J.
 |vice_president    = 
 |superintendent    = 
 |provost           = 
 |vice_chancellor   = 
 |rector            = 
 |principal         = 
 |dean              = 
 |director          = 
 |head_label        = 
 |head              = 
 |faculty           = 653
 |staff             = 
 |students          = 7,900 (2010–2011)
 |undergrad         = 
 |graduate          = 
 |doctoral          = 
 |law school        = 982 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.seattleu.edu/Office_and_Administration/Admission/Admission_Facts_and_Figures.xml |title=Admission Facts &amp; Figures : Seattle University School of Law : Seattle, Washington |publisher=Law.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |city              = [[Seattle]]
 |state             = [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]
 |province          = 
 |country           = [[United States of America]]
 |coor              = {{Coord|47.61007|-122.319|display=inline,title|type:edu}}
 |campus            = [[Urban area|Urban]]&lt;br/&gt;48 acres (194,249 m²)
 |former_names      = Seattle College
 |free_label        = 
 |free              = yes
 |sports            = 
 |colors            = Red &amp; White {{colorbox|#B22222}}{{colorbox|white}}
 |colours           = 
 |nickname          = Redhawks  
 |mascot            = Rudy the Redhawk
 |athletics         = [[NCAA Division I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Western Athletic Conference]] (Starting in 2012)
 |affiliations      = 
 |website           = http://www.seattleu.edu
 |logo              = [[File:Seattle University Wordmark.svg|170px]]
 |footnotes         = 
}}

'''Seattle University (SU)''' is a [[Jesuit]] Catholic university located in the [[First Hill, Seattle|First Hill]] neighborhood of [[Seattle]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]], USA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.seattleu.edu/Office_and_Administration/Admission/Seattle_Living/Housing.xml |title=&quot;'&amp;#39;'First Hill'&amp;#39;'. The home of our main campus and known to many as &quot;Pill Hill,&quot; it is also the site of several hospitals, many of them nationally recognized. The area earned its name because it was one of the first established neighborhoods in Seattle.&quot; Retrieved 10 NOV 2010 |publisher=Law.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.yelp.com/biz/seattle-university-seattle-2 |title=Yelp. &quot;'&amp;#39;Category: Colleges &amp; Universities'&amp;#39;, 900 Broadway, Seattle, WA 98122. '&amp;#39;'Neighborhood: First Hill'&amp;#39;' (206) 296-1891 |publisher=Yelp |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SU is the largest independent university in the Northwest US, with over 7,500 students enrolled in undergraduate and graduate programs within eight schools, and is one of 28 member institutions of the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]]. ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'', in its &quot;Best Colleges 2011,&quot; ranked Seattle University 6th out of schools in the West that offer a full range of master's and undergraduate programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/seattle-wa/seattle-university-3790 |title=Seattle University &amp;#124; Best College |publisher=usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
In 1891, Fathers Victor Garrand, S.J., and Adrian Sweere, S.J., took over a small parish near downtown Seattle at Broadway and Madison. At first, the school was named after the surrounding Immaculate Conception parish and did not offer higher education. In 1898, the school was named Seattle College after both the city and [[Chief Seattle]], and it granted its first bachelor's degrees 11 years later. Initially, the school served as both a high school and college. From 1919 to 1931, the college moved to Interlaken Blvd, but in 1931 it returned to First Hill permanently. In 1931, Seattle College created a &quot;night school&quot; for women in order to allow them to attend; becoming coeducational was a highly controversial decision at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/history/section2.html |title=1891–1919: Early Days in Seattle – Seattle University: A History of Excellence |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/history/section3.html |title=1919–1933: Off and On Broadway – Seattle University: A History of Excellence |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1948, Seattle College changed its name to Seattle University under Father Albert A. Lemieux, S.J. In 1993, the [[Seattle University School of Law]] was established through purchase of the Law School from the [[University of Puget Sound]] in [[Tacoma, Washington]].  In 1999 the School of Law moved to the Seattle campus.

In 2009, SU completed the largest capital campaign in the university's history, raising almost $169 million and surpassing the original campaign goal by almost $20 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/campaign/ |title=Seattle University – Alumni Relations – Home |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign has resulted in new scholarships for students, academic programs and professorships, a fitness complex, an arts center and more. The centerpiece of the capital projects is the $56 million Lemieux Library and McGoldrick Learning Commons, completed in fall 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Seattle University (add vcard to contacts) |url=http://www.seattleu.edu/university_news.aspx?id=48795 |title=University News – Seattle University |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date=September 10, 2009 |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
[[File:Lemieux Library - Seattle University.jpg|thumb|[[Lemieux Library and McGoldrick Learning Commons]]]]
[[Image:Seattle U Fountain 03 A.jpg|thumb|Centennial Fountain, designed by [[George Tsutakawa]].]]
[[Image:Seattle U St Ignatius 11.jpg|thumb|Interior, Chapel of St. Ignatius, Seattle University|Chapel of St. Ignatius, designed by [[Steven Holl]].]]
The Seattle University campus is {{convert|50|acre|m2}} and is located on First Hill, near downtown Seattle, Wash. The SU campus has been recognized by the city of Seattle, the EPA and many organizations for its commitment to sustainability through pesticide-free grounds, a food waste compost facility, recycling program and energy conservation program.&lt;ref name=&quot;seattleu.edu&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/sustainability/awards.aspx |title=Seattle University – Sustainability – Awards |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The most well-known building on campus is the Chapel of St. Ignatius, designed by [[New York City|New York]] architect [[Steven Holl]], born in [[Bremerton, Washington]]: the 1997 building won a national Honor Award from the [[American Institute of Architects]] in 1998.&lt;ref&gt;John Pastier, [http://216.254.10.116/essays/output.cfm?file_id=2931 Seattle University's Chapel of St. Ignatius], HistoryLink.org Essay 2931, January 6, 2001. Accessed online 28 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The campus includes numerous works by well-known artists (including the Centennial Fountain by Seattle artist [[George Tsutakawa]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seattleu.edu/home/scenes/details.asp?elItemID=SCN_1008 Campus scene (Centennial Fountain)], captioned image on the Seattle U. web site. Accessed online 28 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;—recipient of an honorary doctorate from Seattle U.&lt;ref&gt;Mayumi Tsutakawa, [http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=3088 Tsutakawa, George (1910–1997)], HistoryLink.org Essay 3088, April 19, 2001. Accessed online 28 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;—and a large glass sculpture in the PACCAR Atrium of Piggot Hall by [[Tacoma, Washington]] artist [[Dale Chihuly]],&lt;ref name=Potterf&gt;Tina Potterf, [http://www.seattleu.edu/home/news_events/magazine/details.asp?elItemID=MAG_1079&amp;elImgPos=11 Home Is Where the Art Is], ''Seattle University Magazine'' article reproduced on the Seattle University web site. Accessed online 28 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; as well as works by [[Chuck Close]], [[Jacob Lawrence]], [[Gwendolyn Knight]], [[William Morris (glass artist)]] and [[David Mach]]&lt;ref name=Potterf/&gt;) and several architecturally notable buildings.

Almost half of the overall student body represent diverse groups, in 2009–10 the makeup of the university was:
49% Caucasian
19% Asian/Pacific Islander
7% Latino/Hispanic
5% African American
1% Native American
9.7% International Students&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/admission/undergraduate/Inner.aspx?id=39354 |title=Seattle University – Quick Facts |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lemieux Library===
The Lemieux Library was founded in 1991.  As of 2011 it contained 216,677 books and subscribed to 1604 periodicals.  It participates in the [[American Theological Library Association]] and the [[Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ALD&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=American Library Directory |edition=64th |volume=2 |year=2011-2012 |publisher=Information Today, Inc |isbn=978-1-57387-411-3 |pages=2568–2576}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
Seattle University offers 61 bachelor's degree programs, 31 graduate degree programs and 27 certificate programs, plus a [[Seattle University School of Law|law school]] and a doctoral program in education. The university consists of eight colleges: the College of Arts and Sciences, the Albers School of Business and Economics, the College of Education, [[Seattle University School of Law|the School of Law]], [[Matteo Ricci College]], the College of Nursing, the College of Science and Engineering, and the School of Theology and Ministry. A Seattle University education is estimated to cost $150,000, although much of this is covered by financial aid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.king5.com/sharedcontent/VideoPlayer/videoPlayer.php?s=y&amp;vidId=150603&amp;catId=81 King 5 News], King 5 News. Accessed online 11 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

Service-learning and social justice are components of the educational experience at Seattle University, which strives to &quot;empower leaders for a just and humane world.&quot; Each year students, faculty and staff commit hundreds of hours to service projects and community outreach through the Center for Service and Community Engagement.

===Albers School of Business and Economics===
Albers School of Business and Economics was ranked 46th in the U.S. and among the Top 25 private universities in the [[BusinessWeek]] 2010 rankings of undergraduate Business Schools. Albers' faculty received an “A” rating from students and recruiters ranked Albers as the top school in the nation. The school ranked seventh in the West and was the only private university in the Northwest appearing in the Top 50. The 2009 ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'' ranking of undergraduate business programs puts Albers in the top 30% of AACSB accredited schools and one of the top 20 private business schools in the U.S. Albers's part-time MBA program has been recognized as one of the top 50 in the nation, according to the latest issue of ''[[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'''s “America's Best Graduate Schools 2009.” The Executive Leadership Program was ranked by CRO Corporate Responsibility Officer magazine among the top 10 executive training programs in [[corporate responsibility]]. In addition, the Albers EDGE program (Education for Global Executives) was honored in 2008 as the only academic institution to receive the President's &quot;E&quot; Award, which recognizes persons, firms, or organizations that contribute significantly in the effort to increase United States exports.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.seattleu.edu/albers/inner.aspx?id=22638 |title=Seattle University – Albers School of Business – Albers At A Glance |publisher=.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Seattle University's Albers School of Business and Economics, started in 1945, was named after the Albers family. George and Eva Albers were generous donors to the university and in 1971 Eva bequeathed $3 million to the school. Their daughter, Genevieve Albers, attended SU and also sponsored a business forum, established an eponymous professorship, and donated funds to create scholarships. In 1967, the business school added an MBA program, which by 2010 has grown to be a highly ranked, nationally accredited evening program for working professionals in the Pacific Northwest. ''BusinessWeek'' ranked Albers's Part-time MBA Program #25 in the nation and the undergraduate program in the top 50 in 2010. Both the Leadership Executive MBA Program and the part-time MBA Program are recognized among the Top 25 in their categories by &quot;''U.S. News &amp; World Report's'' 2010 America's Best Graduate Schools.&quot; US News also ranks the Albers School among the top 10% of undergraduate business schools nationwide. The Albers School is accredited with the Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business [[AACSB]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/albers/inner.aspx?id=22626 |title=Seattle University – Albers School of Business – Albers Leads |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Arts and Sciences===
{{Main|Seattle University College of Arts and Sciences}}
[[Seattle University College of Arts and Sciences|The Seattle University College of Arts and Sciences in]] [[Seattle]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]] is the oldest undergraduate and graduate college affiliated with Seattle University, the Northwest's largest independent university. The College offers 33 undergraduate majors, 33 undergraduate minors, 7 graduate degrees, and 1 post-graduate certificate. In the College of Arts and Sciences, Seattle University's graduate program in psychology is notable as one of the few schools in the country to focus on [[existential phenomenology]] as a therapeutic method.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/artsci/ |title=Seattle University – College of Arts and Sciences |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date=April 11, 2010 |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Matteo Ricci College===
{{Main|Matteo Ricci College}}
The Matteo Ricci College was founded in 1973 and named after Italian Jesuit missionary, [[Matteo Ricci]]. The program allows high school students from Seattle Preparatory School and other area high schools to graduate with a bachelor's degree in [[humanities]] or [[teaching]] after as little as one year in high school and three years in college.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.seattleu.edu/mrc/ |title=Seattle University – Matteo Ricci College |publisher=.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===School of Law===
{{Main|Seattle University School of Law}}
The [[Seattle University School of Law]] states that it is the largest and most diverse in the [[Pacific Northwest]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.seattleu.edu/The_School.xml |title=The School : Seattle University School of Law : Seattle, Washington |publisher=Law.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also one of three law schools in Washington state, the other two being the [[University of Washington School of Law]] and [[Gonzaga University School of Law]]. The School of Law was founded in 1972 as part of the [[University of Puget Sound]] (UPS) in [[Tacoma, Wash.]] In 1993, the University of Puget Sound and Seattle University agreed on a transfer of the law school to Seattle University; in August 1994 the transfer was completed, and the school physically moved to the Seattle University campus in 1999. The 2009 ''US News and World Report'' Law School rankings list the School of Law in the top 100 Law Schools in the nation, and the number one legal writing program in the nation.

===College of Nursing===
Seattle University's College of Nursing celebrated its 75th anniversary in 2010.  It is housed in the completely renovated Garrand building, the site of the original Seattle College and the oldest building on campus. The {{convert|19000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} &quot;state of the art&quot; Clinical Performance Lab is located in the James Tower of Swedish Cherry Hill, a few blocks away from the main campus.  Undergraduate and Graduate students use this lab to practice skills necessary for clinical nursing.
The BSN program attracts students who begin as Freshmen as well as transfer students from community colleges and those with degrees from other universities.  The MSN program welcomes registered nurses with Bachelor's degrees. The Advanced Practice Nursing Immersion program (MSN) offers an accelerated program for those with a Bachelors degree in another field.  
Specialties available in the MSN program are Family Nurse Practitioner, Psych-Mental Health Nurse Practitioner, Geriatric Nurse Practitioner and Advanced Community/Public Health Nursing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/nursing/ |title=Seattle University – College Nursing |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Education===
Founded in 1935, the [[College of Education]] has a long and distinguished history of preparing ethical and reflective professionals. Programs offered include a Doctorate in Educational Leadership, Masters in Adult Education and Training, Counseling, Curriculum and Instruction, Educational Administration, Literacy for Special Needs, Master in Teaching, Master in Teaching with Special Education Endorsement, Special Education, Student Development Administration, and Teaching English to Students of Other Languages. Educational specialist degree programs include Educational Administration – Principal Preparation, School Psychology, and Special Education and Certificate programs offered include Superintendent, Principal, and Professional Development.
 
The College of Education is accredited by the National Council of Accreditation of Teacher Education and the National Association of School Psychologists and approved by the National Association of School Psychologists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/coe/ |title=Seattle University – College of Education |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===College of Science &amp; Engineering===
The College of Science and Engineering focuses on basic sciences, mathematics and their applications. Students can major in basic science disciplines, computer science or one of the engineering departments – civil and environmental engineering, mechanical engineering, or computer and electrical engineering. Students may also obtain an interdisciplinary general science degree, or prepare for graduate work in the health professions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/scieng/default.aspx |title=Seattle University – College of Science and Engineering |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The College of Science and Engineering is ranked among the top 50 in the nation as one of U.S. News &amp; World Report's Best Undergraduate Engineering Programs (2008 edition). The college is ranked second in the nation in terms of the percentage of women faculty members, according to Prism, a publication of the American Society for Engineering Education.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/alumni/Inner.aspx?id=35890 |title=Seattle University – Alumni Relations – University Excellence(2) |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===School of Theology &amp; Ministry===
The School of Theology and Ministry is an ecumenical program with relationships with 10 Protestant denominations and the Catholic Archdiocese of Seattle. It is committed to social justice and addressing the needs of an increasingly multicultural church. The school offers a number of master's degrees and certificates, including a Master of Divinity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/stm/default.aspx |title=Seattle University – School of Theology and Ministry |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community Investment==
Investing and partnering with Seattle and the SU neighborhood are part of the Jesuit Catholic mission of education for service and social justice. More than 3,000 students—three out of every four—take part in at least one for-credit “service learning” class by the time that they graduate; nearly 45 percent participate in a service-learning class in any given year. This translates to 185,000 hours, the equivalent of more than 80 full-time workers or $6 million. By comparison, on a national level only about one-third of college students volunteer, according to the Corporation for National &amp; Community Service.

The number of service learning courses at SU has nearly doubled since 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/CSCE/Inner.aspx?id=34732 |title=Seattle University – Center for Service and Community Engagement – Letter from the Director |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; One-third of service-learning students continue their community work even after their class has ended and they've earned a grade. Many students continue serving after graduation through an SU program called Magis:Alumni Committed for Mission. In the past two years, nearly 100 alumni have participated in Magis efforts such as the Alumni Mexico Mission Trek and the annual Serve Seattle project. And in each of the past three years, at least a dozen graduates have gone into full-time service with the Jesuit Volunteer Corps, the Peace Corps and Teach for America.

Because SU is part of Seattle's urban hub, students have easy access to a number of areas that offer a wide variety of service learning opportunities, including the Central District, the International District and Pioneer Square.

The economic impact of SU in the Seattle area in 2008 was $580.4 million. This figure is drawn from the total spending by the university, its students and visitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/csce/default.aspx?id=34720 |title=Seattle University – Center for Service and Community Engagement – Home |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seattleu.edu/uploadedFiles/GCA/SU_BenefitstoCommunityReport.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Environmental Sustainability==
Among Seattle University's many environmental undertakings, there are projects ranging from composting initiatives to water conservation. There are also solar panels on buildings, and a central recycling yard with an extensive recycling program.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.seattleu.edu/sustainability/initiatives.aspx |title=Seattle University |publisher=.seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has been composting since 1995, and in 2003 it built the first composting facility in the state on an urban campus. The University's Grounds Department is committed to fostering an organic, sustainable and environmentally friendly campus that functions as an urban wildlife sanctuary. 

SU received the Sustainability Innovator Award in 2007 from the Sustainable Endowments Institute for SU's pre-consumer food waste composting program and the Green Washington Award in 2008 from Washington CEO Magazine for SU's sustainable landscape practices and pre-consumer food waste composting program.&lt;ref name=&quot;seattleu.edu&quot;/&gt; The Princeton Review's 2009 Green Rating gave the school a 97 out of a possible 99.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Seattle University (add vcard to contacts) |url=http://www.seattleu.edu/university_news.aspx?id=41590 |title=University News – Seattle University |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date=August 7, 2008 |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

SU's move to a pesticide-free campus began in the early 1980s when Ciscoe Morris, now a local gardening celebrity, was head of the SU Grounds Department in the 1980s.  He put a halt to chemical spraying and in its place released more than 20,000 beneficial insects called [[lacewing]]s to eat the aphids that had infested trees on campus. It worked and that led to a whole host of pesticide-free gardening practices.  Cisco began a transformation that has made the university a model for ecological gardening.

==Mission statement==
Seattle University is dedicated to educating the whole person, to professional formation, and empowering leaders for a just and humane world.

===Vision===
The vision of Seattle University is to be the premier independent university of the Northwest in academic quality, Jesuit Catholic inspiration, and service to society.

===Values===
Care: We put the good of students first.
Academic Excellence: We value excellence in learning with great teachers who are active scholars.
Diversity: We celebrate educational excellence achieved through diversity.
Faith: We treasure our Jesuit Catholic ethos and the enrichment from many faiths of our university community.
Justice: We foster concern for justice and the competence to promote it.
Leaderships: We seek to develop responsible leaders committed to the common good.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/home/about_seattle_university/mission/ |title=Seattle University |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
{{Main|Seattle Redhawks}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Seattle University Redhawks.png|150px|right]] --&gt;

Between 1950 and 1971, Seattle University competed as a Division I independent school. In the 1950s, the basketball team was a powerhouse with brothers Johnny and Eddie O'Brien, who led Seattle University as the only team in history to defeat the world famous [[Harlem Globetrotters]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.seattlepi.com/othersports/55228_globe21.shtml Fifty years ago tonight, Seattle U. upset the mighty Globetrotters], accessed January 24, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In 1958, future [[NBA Hall of Fame]]r [[Elgin Baylor]] paced a men's basketball team that advanced to the [[Final Four]] and defeated top-ranked [[Kansas State Wildcats men's basketball|Kansas State University]] before losing to the [[Kentucky Wildcats men's basketball|University of Kentucky]].  Seattle University was also a leader in the area of racial diversity, with an integrated squad known as “the United Nations team.”

The success of men's basketball, in addition to men's golf and baseball, continued into to the 1960s with players [[Eddie Miles]], [[Clint Richardson]], and [[Tom Workman]], all of whom went on to successful careers in the NBA.  The 1966 basketball squad led [[Texas Western University]] to its only defeat in a championship season celebrated in the film ''[[Glory Road]]''. In the course of the 1960s, Seattle University produced more NBA players than any other school. {{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

During that time women's tennis star [[Janet Hopps]] was the first female to be the top-ranked player for both the men and women nationally. In women's golf, Pat Lesser was twice named to the Curtis Cup in the mid-1950s and was later inducted into the State of Washington Sports Hall of Fame.

Before 1980, more than 25 SU baseball players went on to play professionally in both the major and minor leagues.  Men's golf and a [[Tom Gorman (tennis)|Tom Gorman]] -led tennis team were also very strong{{Clarify|date=April 2010}} national programs.  Gorman went on to lead the US Davis Cup team, where he captained a record 18 match wins and one Davis Cup title (1972) as a player and two more Davis Cup championships as a coach (1990 and 1992). 

SU joined the [[West Coast Conference]] in 1971. In 1980, SU left the West Coast Conference and Division I membership and entered the NAIA, where it remained for nearly 20 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wccsports.cstv.com/school-bio/west-school-bio.html |title=West Coast Conference Official Athletics Site – On Campus |publisher=Wccsports.cstv.com |date=July 1, 2011 |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1990s, President Fr. Sundborg started restoring the university's NCAA membership. The athletic program moved into Division II in the fall of 2002.  

Currently, the school is reclassifying from [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] to [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]. This integration process will take five years and should be complete in 2012–2013. In 2009, the university hired men's basketball coaches [[Cameron Dollar]], former assistant at University of Washington, and women's coach [[Joan Bonvicini]], former University of Arizona coach and one of the winningest women's college basketball coaches. 

In 1938 the mascot switched from the Maroons to the Chieftains.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.seattleu.edu/history/section4.xml&lt;/ref&gt; The name was selected to honor the college's namesake, Chief Sealth. In 2000 the university changed its mascot to the Redhawks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.seattleu.edu/home/news_events/news/news_detail.asp?elYear=2000&amp;elID=521200210924 |title=Seattle University |publisher=Seattleu.edu |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 14, 2011, Seattle U accepted an invitation to join the [[Western Athletic Conference]] and will be a full member for the 2012–2013 season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Condotta |first=Bob |url=http://seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/seattleuniversity/2015316570_seattleu15.html |title=Seattle U. receives invitation to join WAC |publisher=Seattle Times |date= |accessdate=August 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni==
{{AlumniStart|width=95%}}
{{Alum|name=[[Elgin Baylor]]|year= |nota=[[National Basketball Association|NBA]] Hall of Famer; general manager, [[Los Angeles Clippers]], 2006 NBA Executive of the Year.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Anne Bremner]]|year=[[Juris Doctor|J.D.]] 1982 |nota = Seattle lawyer and television legal analyst|ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;EmployerBio&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.staffordfrey.com/a_bremner.htm|publisher=Stafford Frey Cooper|title=Attorneys: Anne M. Bremner|accessdate=October 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Alum|name=[[Hazem Salah Abu Ismail]]|year=[[Juris Doctor|J.D.]] 1990  |nota=Egyptian Presidential Candidate,politician and Islamist|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Rudy D'Amico]]|year=1990|nota=NBA basketball scout, and former college and professional ([[Euroleague]]-winning) basketball coach|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[John Juanda]]|year=1996, M.B.A.|nota=Professional Poker Player|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Dino Rossi]]|year=1982|nota=Former Washington State Senator|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Mohamed Ali Alabbar]]|year=1981|nota=Chairman of [[Emaar Properties]]; one of the world's largest real estate development firms with $25 billion in assets|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Dave Barrett]]|year=|nota=Former premier of the Canadian province of British Columbia (1972–1975)|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Major General (Ret.) [[Patrick Henry Brady]]|year=|nota=recipient of the Medal of Honor|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Gary Brinson]]|year=1966 |nota=founder and retired chair of [[Brinson Partners]]; GP Brinson Investments; The Brinson Foundation. The January 2003 issue of CFA Magazine named Brinson as one of seven living legends in the investment profession.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=General [[Peter W. Chiarelli]]|year=1972|nota=[[Vice Chief of Staff of the U.S. Army]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=William P. Foley, II|year=1970, M.B.A.|nota=Chairman and CEO, [[Fidelity National Financial]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Micheal Gilleran|year=1971; [[Juris Doctor|J.D.]] 1975|nota=Commissioner of the [[West Coast Conference]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[John E. Hopcroft]]|year=1961|nota=renowned theoretical computer scientist; co-winner 1986 Turing Award|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Carolyn Kelly|year=M.B.A.|nota=President and COO, ''[[The Seattle Times]]''|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Steve McConnell]]|year=1991, M.S. [[Software Engineering]]|nota=Chair of the [[IEEE Computer Society]]'s Professional Practices Committee|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Duff McKagan]]|year=|nota=Bassist of Velvet Revolver, former bassist of Guns N' Roses|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Stan W. McNaughton|year=1974|nota=CEO, PEMCO Insurance|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Charles Mitchell|year=1974|nota=Chancellor, Seattle Community Colleges; was president of [[Seattle Central Community College]] in 2001 when [[Time magazine|''Time'' magazine]] named it “College of the Year.” Former professional football player with the [[Denver Broncos]] and [[Buffalo Bills]].|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Frank Murkowski]]|year=1955|nota=Former Governor of [[Alaska]] and former U.S. Senator from Alaska|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Carol Nelson]]|year=1974; 1984, MBA|nota=President, CEO, Cascade Bank|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Eddie O'Brien (baseball)|Eddie O'Brien]]|year=|nota=Baseball player for [[Pittsburgh Pirates]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Johnny O'Brien]]|year=|nota=Baseball player for [[Pittsburgh Pirates]], [[St. Louis Cardinals]] and [[Milwaukee Braves]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[John D. Spellman]]|year=1949|nota=Former Governor of Washington state|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=Lieutenant Commander [[Charles Swift]]|year=[[Juris Doctor|J.D.]]; 1994|nota=Served as legal counsel for [[Salim Ahmed Hamdan]]. Listed as 100 most influential lawyers in the US.|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Calvin Tang]]|year=2000|nota=Co-founder of [[Newsvine]]|ref=}}
{{Alum|name=[[Jim Whittaker]]|year=1952|nota=First American to summit [[Mount Everest]] in 1963.|ref=}}
{{AlumniEnd}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Seattle|University}}
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.seattleu.edu/ Official Page]
*[http://www.seattleu.edu/alumni Seattle University Alumni Relations]
*[http://www.goseattleu.com/ Seattle University Athletics]
*[http://www.su-spectator.com Seattle University's official student newspaper, The Spectator]
*[http://www.ksubseattle.org Seattle University's Student-run radio station]

{{Association of Jesuit Colleges and Universities}}
{{Western Athletic Conference navbox}}
{{Private colleges and universities in Washington (state)}}

[[Category:Seattle University| ]]
[[Category:Jesuit universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic universities and colleges in the United States]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Seattle, Washington]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1891]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]

[[da:Seattle University]]
[[de:Seattle University]]
[[es:Universidad de Seattle]]
[[fr:Seattle University]]
[[nl:Universiteit van Seattle]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
