<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2921936" ns="0" title="Geordie Greig"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Geordie Greig''' (born 1960 London) is a British journalist and newspaper editor. He is the editor of the ''[[Evening Standard]]'' newspaper. He attended [[Eton College]] and [[St Peter's College, Oxford]].

==Journalism career==
He worked for the ''South East London and Deptford Mercury'' newspaper, the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' and ''[[Today (UK newspaper)|Sunday Today]]'', before joining the ''[[The Sunday Times (UK)|Sunday Times]]'' in 1987. He became the editor of ''[[Tatler]]'' magazine in 1999.

===London Evening Standard===
On 2 February 2009 it was announced by the ''[[Evening Standard]]'' that Greig had been appointed its editor, subject to ratification by the Editorial Committee. This announcement followed the announcement on 21 January 2009 by the ''[[Daily Mail]]'' group that its newspaper division, Associated Newspapers Ltd, had agreed the sale of a majority interest in the ''Evening Standard'' for a nominal sum to Evening Press Ltd, a company formed by [[Alexander Lebedev]] and his son [[Evgeny Lebedev]] and owned by Lebedev Holdings Ltd.

His first step as Evening Standard editor was to launch a series of &quot;Sorry&quot; advertisements across London, after market research showed the paper was deemed too negative and complacent about London under former editor [[Veronica Wadley]]'s leadership, a move considered to be extremely daring.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.campaignlive.co.uk/news/rss/902948/London-Evening-Standard-says-sorry-Londoners-relaunch-campaign/ London Evening Standard says sorry to Londoners in relaunch campaign] campaignlive.co.uk, 5 May 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other interests==
In addition to his editorial duties, Greig has literary interests, for instance being an admirer of the work of [[Samuel Menashe]] and [[Anthony Trollope]].

On 1 May 2005, ''[[The Observer]]'' newspaper termed Greig &quot;Britain's most connected man&quot;. 

Greig is also Vice-President of Kitab, the annual British-Indian Literary and Media Festival. He is also member of White's the London gentlemen's club.

==Personal life==
He is married to Kathryn Terry, who is originally from Texas; the Greigs have three children, Jasper, and a pair of twins Octavia and Monica. They live in Notting Hill.

Greig's great-grandfather was [[Lord Mowbray, Segrave and Stourton]], and members of his father's family have been royal [[courtier]]s for three generations.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://observer.guardian.co.uk/magazine/story/0,11913,1473412,00.html The Entertaining Mr. Sloane], The Observer Magazine
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/Archive/Article/0,4273,3910853,00.html Class Act]&quot;, The Guardian
* [http://news.independent.co.uk/media/article2667046.ece Geordie Greig: Telling tales on high society], The Independent
* [http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-23632922-details/New+editor+for+the+Evening+Standard/article.do New Editor for the Evening Standard], The Evening Standard
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2009/jan/28/geordie-greig-tatler-london-evening-standard Geordie Greig expected to join Evening Standard the Evening Standard]

{{start box}}
{{s-media}}
{{incumbent succession box | before=[[Veronica Wadley]] | title=Editor of the ''[[Evening Standard]]''| start=2009}}
{{end box}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Greig, Geordie
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1960
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Greig, Geordie}}
[[Category:1960 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Alumni of St Peter's College, Oxford]]
[[Category:British journalists]]
[[Category:Old Etonians]]
[[Category:Evening Standard people]]


{{UK-writer-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
