<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29288938" ns="0" title="WikiBhasha"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name                   = WikiBhasha
| screenshot             = [[Image:WikiBhasha screenshot.png|220px]]
| caption                = A sample instance of WikiBhasha.
| developer              = [[Microsoft]]
| released               = 18.10.2010
| latest release version = 1.0.1
| latest release date    = 25.10.2010
| programming language   = Javascript, PHP
| operating system       = Windows, Linux
| language               = 
| genre                  = 
| license                = Apache 2 License and partly GPL V2
| website                = [http://www.WikiBhasha.org www.WikiBhasha.org]
}}

'''WikiBhasha''' is a [[multi-lingual]] content creation tool for the online [[encyclopedia]] [[Wikipedia]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/gadgets-and-tech/write-wikis-in-any-language-with-new-multilingual-content-creation-tool-2111447.html &quot;Write wikis in any language with new multilingual content creation tool&quot;] ([[Relaxnews]] story), ''The Independent'', 20 October 2010. Retrieved 10 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  WikiBhasha enables contributors to Wikipedia to find content from Wikipedia articles, translate it into other languages, and then either compose new articles or enhance existing articles in the various language versions of Wikipedia.  The tool acts as a simple and intuitive user interface layer that stays on the target language Wikipedia article that is being created or enhanced during the user-session.  At the end of the session, all the additions or modifications of content are submitted to the target language Wikipedia in the updating process.

WikiBhasha supports content creation in more than 30 languages. It enables easy content creation in non-English Wikipedias by leveraging the large volume of English Wikipedia content as the source of information. Initially, the Wikimedia Foundation and Microsoft Research are working closely with the Wikipedia user communities focusing on content creation in [[Arabic]], [[German language|German]], [[Hindi]], [[Japanese language|Japanese]], [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]] and [[Spanish language|Spanish]].  The word Bhasha means language in many North Indian languages, and is related to the word Bahasa of Malaysia and Indonesia.

The software is similar to the recently released [[Google Translator Toolkit]]. The key difference between the two is that WikiBhasha runs as an overlay within the Wikipedia interface, while the Google toolkit runs elsewhere and requires a Google account.

==Workflow==
The UI layer implements a simple three-step process helping the user to gather content from source-language Wikipedia, to compose the target-language Wikipedia article, and finally, to submit new content to the target Wikipedia. The UI layer integrates content discovery, linguistic and collaborative services, transparently.   

The WikiBhasha (Beta) workflow for contribution to a Wikipedia is in three Steps – ''Collect'', ''Compose'' &amp; ''Submit''.

===Collect step===
The ''Collect'' step is meant for identifying appropriate content from English Wikipedia (say, from the Tiger article) for enhancing the target language Wikipedia article (say, its inter-wiki-linked Panthera Tigris article in Spanish Wikipedia). For example, the English Wikipedia article may contain sections (say, Conservation Efforts) that that may be missing in the Spanish article.  Once such content is identified, the default translations (in the target language) can be corrected to make the content suitable for enhancing the target article.  The search mechanism can be used to identify more source content from multiple articles.

===Compose step===
In the ''Compose'' step, focus is directed to composing a new target language article or enhancing an existing article (say, Panthera Tigris in Spanish Wikipedia), with the content sourced in the collect step.  An editable pane is provided, within which the new article can be created, or the existing one enhanced, by moving the [translated and corrected] content into the pane).  In addition to moving the sourced content, the content moved can be rearranged, modified or rewritten, or supplemented by new material until the desired target contribution is satisfactory.

===Submit step===
The ''Submit'' step brings up the edit page of the target language Wikipedia article to be addressed.  The edit box contains the material created in the compose step.  The Wikipedia edit page can be used for any final edits, preview or submission to target language Wikipedia.

==Other features==
===Search===
The Search tool can be used to explore source or target language Wikipedias for other articles containing source content to enhance the target Wikipedia article. The search tool displays relevant articles from both the source and target language Wikipedias, as returned by the default Wikipedia search mechanism.

All the previously visited topics in the user session are available for the session. Any topic from the ''Visited Topics'' list can be selected to switch to that topic. A topic selected in the source language will be opened in the Collect step. A topic selected in the target language will be opened in the Compose step.

===Collaborative Translation Framework===
In both the Collect and the Compose steps, a collaborative mechanism – Collaborative Translation Framework (CTF) – is available.  CTF is a collaborative cloud service provided by Microsoft Translator, which makes available alternative translations (provided by other users) for the highlighted sentence.

==Availability==
Currently WikiBhasha (Beta) is available as a [http://svn.wikimedia.org/viewvc/mediawiki/trunk/extensions/WikiBhasha MediaWiki Extension], under Apache 2 License and partly under GPL v2.

It is available as a user-script (from Wikipedia user, WikiBhasha.MSR).  

It is also available as an installable bookmarklet (and a Grease Monkey Script for Firefox users) from the [http://www.WikiBhasha.org WikiBhasha] site.

==Supported platforms==

WikiBhasha (Beta) currently supports all translation pairs in [http://www.microsofttranslator.com Bing Translator], in which either the source language is English.  

WikiBhasha (Beta) currently tested on Internet Explorer (7 or above) on Windows XP, Windows Vista &amp; Windows 7 and on Firefox (3.5 or above) on Windows and Linux (Fedora 11 or above).

==User guide==
The WikiBhasha beta user guide is available [http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/projects/wikibhasha/wikibhasha_beta_user_doc_1.0.pdf here].  Instructions for installation and use of WikiBhasha are provided in the User Guide.

==See also==
* Home of [http://www.WikiBhasha.org/ WikiBhasha]
* Home of [http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/projects/wikibabel WikiBABEL Project site]
* Microsoft Research [http://www.microsoft.com/Presspass/press/2010/oct10/MSWikiBhashaPR.mspx announcement] on the release of WikiBhasha
* Wikimedia Foundation [http://blog.wikimedia.org/blog/2010/10/18/wikibhasha/ announcement] on WikiBhasha

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.wikibhasha.org/ WikiBhasha Homepage]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wikibhasha}}
[[Category:Multilingualism]]
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Translation software]]
[[Category:Wikipedia tools]]

[[ar:ويكي باشا]]
[[cs:WikiBhasha]]
[[hi:विकिभाषा]]
[[hu:WikiBhasha]]
[[sk:WikiBhasha]]
[[ta:விக்கிபாசா]]
[[uk:WikiBhasha]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
