<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="292920" ns="0" title="Vodafone Romania"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Company |
  company_name   = Vodafone Romania |
  logo           =  |
  company_slogan = ''Trăieşte fiecare clipă''|
  foundation     = 1997 as '''Connex GSM''' |
  location       = [[Bucharest]], Romania |
  key_people     = [[Inaki Berroeta]], CEO |
  industry       = [[Mobile phone|Mobile]] telecommunications |
  homepage       = [http://www.vodafone.ro/ www.vodafone.ro] |
  company_type   = subsidiary of [[Vodafone]]
}}

'''Vodafone''' is a [[Romania|Romanian]] mobile phone [[telecommunications network|network]] operator. It launched in April 1997  as the first [[GSM]] network in Romania (although not the first mobile phone network). Until October 2005 (shortly after acquisition by Vodafone), it was known as '''Connex''', after which it was rebranded '''Connex-Vodafone''' and in April 2006, the Connex name was dropped, the operator being simply known as Vodafone Romania, aligning itself with the global [[Vodafone]] brand.

Vodafone covers 99.31% of the Romanian population, with 9.1 millions subscribers as of March 2011. Vodafone provides [[roaming]] agreements with 310 international operators in 143 countries.

Vodafone Romania is a wholly owned subsidiary of [[Vodafone|Vodafone Group plc]], and is the seventh-largest Vodafone subisidiary in the world by number of subscribers. Vodafone became the majority stakeholder after it brought 79% of Mobifon's shares from Canadian company [[Telesystems International Wireless]], which had been the previous majority shareholder.  Furthermore it recently acquired 5% of Mobifon's shares from Canadian Entrepreneur Elani Grobler.

The operator is in head-to-head competition with [[Orange Romania|Orange]] for the 24.6 million active mobile telephony users in Romania. Connex, the ancestor of Vodafone Romania, held the largest number of subscribers, except the year 2000, until September 2004, when Orange edged ahead.

The motto of Vodafone is ''Trăieşte fiecare clipă'' (rendered in English by the company as Make the most of now, a more accurate translation would be &quot;Live every moment&quot;). Previous mottos were: ''Tu faci viitorul'' (You create the future) and ''Viitorul sună bine'' (The future sounds good).

==Brands of Vodafone==
[[Image:A Bucuresti street scene -i.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Vodafone headquarters in [[Bucharest]], Romania]]
Vodafone Romania (and Connex before it) used numerous others brands. They include:

*[[Xnet]] – an [[internet service provider]]s, providing free unlimited dial-up for Connex mobile phone subscribers between 2000 and 2003. The brand is no longer used.
*[[myX]] – Romania's first mobile portal. Also used by the company for a short-lived venture in the fashion industry. The portal has been relabeled as Vodafone Live. 
*[[myBanking]] – [[Mobile Banking]] service
*[[myDomain]] – [[domain name]] service
*[[homemade.ro]] – [[video sharing]] website

==History==
* 1998: [[Short message service|SMS]] services introduced
* 1999: [[Xnet]] Internet service introduced; High Speed Circuit Switched Data (HSCSD) technology introduced; mobile phones running on Connex donated to ambulance service of [[Oradea]] (first Romanian company to do so)
* 2000: [[Wireless Application Protocol|WAP]] mobile Internet services launched
* 2001: [[myX]], Romania's first mobile portal launched; SMS services such as dating, ringtones and logos are introduced; [[GPRS]] service launched
[[Image:Vodafone.Iasi-Romania.JPG|right|thumb|200px|A former &quot;Connex Center&quot; rebranded as Vodafone in [[Iaşi]], Romania.]]
* 2002: [[GPRS]] prepaid introduced; first company in Europe to introduce [[World Wide Number]] (WWN) facilities; mobile banking introduced in cooperation with [[Banca Comerciala Romana]] (BCR).
* 2003: [[myBanking]] introduced – a service in collaboration with [[Raiffeisen Zentralbank|Raiffeisen]] Bank, for customers to pay Connex bills and do banking automatically
* 2003: Connex Meeting Call introduced.
* 2005: [[3G]] services based on W-CDMA introduced, giving way to video telephony and broadband internet via mobile phone.
* 2005: In partnership with [[Research In Motion|RIM]], Connex launches the second [[BlackBerry]] service in Romania.
* 2005: [[Liliana Solomon]] is named CEO of Connex.
* 2005 November 1: The name of the operator is changed to Connex-Vodafone.
* 2006 April 27: The name of the operator is changed to Vodafone Romania.

===Radio Frequency Summary===
The following is a list of known frequencies which Vodafone employs Romania:
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot;
|+Frequencies used on the Vodafone Romania Network
|-
! MCC !! MNC !! Frequency !! Protocol !! Class !! class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Notes
|-
| 226 || 01 || 900 MHz || GSM/GPRS || 2G || 
|-
| 226 || 01 || 1800 MHz || GSM/GPRS || 2G ||
|-
| 226 || 01 || 900 MHz || UMTS/HSPA/HSPA+ || 3G || 
|-
| 226 || 01 || 2100 MHz || UMTS/HSPA/HSPA+ || 3G || 
|}

==See also==
* [[List of mobile network operators]]
* [[Communications in Romania]]

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.vodafone.ro Vodafone official site]

{{Vodafone}}
{{Romania mobile phone companies}}

[[Category:Vodafone]]
[[Category:Companies based in Bucharest]]
[[Category:Mobile phone companies of Romania]]

[[pl:Vodafone România]]
[[ro:Vodafone România]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
