<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2950170" ns="0" title="Race and appearance of Jesus"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Spas vsederzhitel sinay.jpg|thumb|right|180px|The typical European depiction of Jesus shows a beard and brown hair parted in the middle, while in China he is shown as Chinese.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt;&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt; The oldest surviving ''[[Christ Pantocrator]]'' icon, 6th century, [[St. Catherine's Monastery]].&lt;ref&gt;''God's human face: the Christ-icon'' by Christoph Schoenborn 1994 ISBN 0898705142 page 154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Sinai and the Monastery of St. Catherine'' by John Galey 1986 ISBN 9774241185 page 92&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The '''race and appearance''' of '''[[Jesus]]''' have been discussed on a number of grounds since [[early Christianity]], although the [[New Testament]] includes no description of the physical appearance of Jesus before his death and its narrative is generally indifferent to racial appearances.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; 

Despite the lack of direct biblical or [[historical method|historical references]], from the second century, various theories about the [[Race (classification of humans)|race]] of Jesus were advanced and debated.&lt;ref name=Strauss114 /&gt;&lt;ref name=SKelly70 &gt;''Racializing Jesus: Race, Ideology and the Formation of Modern Biblical Scholarship'' by Shawn Kelley 2002 ISBN 0415283736 pages 70-73&lt;/ref&gt; By the [[Middle Ages]] a number of documents, generally of unknown or questionable origin, had been composed and were circulating with details of the appearance of Jesus. Now these documents are mostly considered forgeries.&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford companion to the Bible'' 1993 ISBN 0195046455 page 41&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Making Sense of the New Testament'' by Craig L. Blomberg 2004 ISBN 0801027470 pages 3-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Pontius Pilate: portraits of a Roman governor'' by Warren Carter 2003 ISBN 0814651135 pages 6-9&lt;/ref&gt; While many people have a fixed mental image of Jesus, drawn from his artistic depictions, these images often conform to stereotypes which are not grounded in any serious research on the  historical Jesus, but are based on second or third hand interpretations of spurious sources.&lt;ref name=Kidd44 &gt;''The forging of races: race and scripture in the Protestant Atlantic world'' by Colin Kidd 2006 ISBN 0521793246 pages 44-45 [http://books.google.com/books?id=aNT3q1HjY_MC&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=race+of+jesus+scholars&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=O8mKTpzlCI6K4gTEk639Aw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=race%20jesus&amp;f=false]&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 19th century theories that Jesus was European, and in particular [[Aryan race|Aryan]], were developed, as well as theories that he was of black African descent. However, as in other cases of the assignment of race to biblical individuals, these claims have been mostly subjective, based on cultural stereotypes and societal trends rather than on scientific analysis.&lt;ref name=Kidd18 /&gt; For two millennia a wide range of artistic depictions of Jesus have appeared, often influenced by cultural settings, political circumstances and theological contexts.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Perkinson30 /&gt; 

==Biblical references==
[[File:Alexandr Ivanov 015.jpg|thumb|250px|left|Transfiguration by [[Alexander Andreyevich Ivanov|Alexandr Ivanov]], 1824]]
The [[New Testament]] includes no description of the physical appearance of Jesus before his death. Its narrative is generally indifferent to peoples' racial appearance or features.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell &gt;Robin M. Jensen &quot;Jesus in Christian art&quot;, Chapter 29 of ''The Blackwell Companion to Jesus'' edited by Delbert Burkett 2010 ISBN 140519362X page 477-502&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Perkinson30 &gt;''The likeness of the king: a prehistory of portraiture in late medieval France'' by Stephen Perkinson 2009 ISBN 0226658791 page 30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kidd48 &gt;''The forging of races: race and scripture in the Protestant Atlantic world'' by Colin Kidd 2006 ISBN 0521793246 pages 48-51&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Synoptic Gospels]] include the account of the [[Transfiguration of Jesus]], during which he was glorified with &quot;his face shining as the sun.&quot; However, the Gospels do not provide details of Jesus' everyday appearance.&lt;ref name=Barton132 &gt;The Cambridge companion to the Gospels'' by Stephen C. Barton ISBN pages 132-133&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= Nobbs &gt;''The Content and the Setting of the Gospel Tradition'' by Mark Harding, Alanna Nobbs 2010 ISBN 9780802833181 pages 281-282&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Book of Revelation]] describes the features of a glorified Jesus in a vision ([[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Revelation#1:13|1:13-16]]), but the vision refers to Jesus in heavenly form, after his death, not his appearance during his earthy life.&lt;ref&gt;''Revelation'' by William C. Pender 1998 ISBN 0664228585 pages 14-16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Revelation 1-11'' by John MacArthur, Jr. ISBN pages 37-39&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Old Testament]] references about the coming Messiah (which Christians believe to be Jesus) have been projected forward to form conjectures about the appearance of Jesus on theological, rather than historical, grounds; e.g. [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Isaiah#53:2|Isaiah 53:2]] which refers to the coming Messiah as &quot;no beauty that we should desire him&quot; and [[wikisource:Bible (American Standard)/Psalms#45:2|Psalm 45:2-3]] which describes him as &quot;fairer than the children of men&quot;, often interpreted as his physical description.&lt;ref&gt;''The Cross of Christ'' by John R. W. Stott, Alister McGrath 2006 ISBN 083083320X page 145&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Christianity, art, and transformation'' by John W. De Gruchy 2001 ISBN 0521772052 page 122&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Brother Jesus: the Nazarene through Jewish eyes'' by Schalom Ben-Chorin 2001 ISBN 0820322563 page 111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Understanding early Christian art'' by Robin Margaret Jensen 2000 ISBN 0415204542 page 127&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early Church to the Middle Ages==
[[Image:Good.Shepherd.Vatican.Museum.jpg|thumb|120px|Jesus without a beard, as the [[Good Shepherd]], c. 300, Rome]]
Despite the lack of direct biblical or [[historical method|historical references]], from the second century, various theories about the race of Jesus were advanced, e.g. by [[Justin Martyr]], based on arguments on the [[genealogy of Jesus]].&lt;ref name=Strauss114 &gt;''The Life of Jesus, Critically Examined'' by David Friedrich Strauss 2010 ISBN 1616403098 pages 114-116&lt;/ref&gt; These arguments have been subject to debate for centuries.&lt;ref name=Strauss114 /&gt;&lt;ref name=SKelly70 /&gt; A hypothesis by anti-Christian philosopher [[Celsus]] that Jesus' father was a Roman soldier named [[Tiberius Iulius Abdes Pantera|Pantera]] drew responses from [[Origen]], who considered it a fabrication; and scholars continue to view the hypothesis as having no historical basis.&lt;ref&gt;''Contra Celsum'' by Origen, Henry Chadwick 1980 ISBN 0521295769 page 32&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Patrick, John ''The Apology of Origen in Reply to Celsus'' 2009 ISBN 111013388X pages 22–24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Mary in the New Testament'' by [[Raymond Edward Brown]], et al. 1978 ISBN 0809121689 page 262&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marcus Borg, John Dominic Crossan (2007). ''The First Christmas: What the Gospels Really Teach About Jesus's Birth''. HarperOne. p. 104. ISBN 0061430706.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Church Fathers]] [[Saint Jerome]] and [[Saint Augustine of Hippo]] argued from a theological perspective that Jesus must have been ideally beautiful in face and body. For Augustine he was &quot;beautiful as a child, beautiful on earth, beautiful in heaven&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''St. Augustin the Writings Against the Manicheans and Against the Donatists'' by St Augustine, Philip Schaff 2005 ISBN 0766183947 page 29&lt;/ref&gt; These theological arguments were further extended in the 13th century by Saint [[Thomas Aquinas]] in his ''[[Summa Theologica|Summa Theologiae]]'' based on his analysis of the [[Perfection of Christ]], reasoning that Christ must have embodied every possible human perfection.&lt;ref&gt;''Summa Theologica, Volume 4 (Part III, First Section)'' by St Thomas Aquinas 2007 ISBN 1602065608 pp. 2060-2062&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Thomas Aquinas: theologian of the Christian life'' by Nicholas M. Healy 2003 ISBN 0754614727 pages 98-101&lt;/ref&gt;

By the [[Middle Ages]] a number of documents, generally of unknown or questionable origin, had been composed and were circulating with details of the appearance of Jesus, as described below.

Around the 9th century, [[Epiphanius Monachus]] referred to a tall angelic figure, which has at times been interpreted as Christ, but scholars consider it an unlikely reference to Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;''The revelation of Elchasai'' by Gerard P. Luttikhuizen 1985 ISBN 3161449355 page 121&lt;/ref&gt; Other spurious references include the [[Archko Volume]] and the letter of [[Pontius Pilate]] to [[Tiberius Caesar]], the descriptions in which were most likely composed in the Middle Ages.&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford companion to the Bible'' 1993 ISBN 0195046455 page 41&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Making Sense of the New Testament'' by Craig L. Blomberg 2004 ISBN 0801027470 pages 3-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Pontius Pilate: portraits of a Roman governor'' by Warren Carter 2003 ISBN 0814651135 pages 6-9&lt;/ref&gt;

A forged letter by [[Publius Lentulus]], the Governor of Judea, to the Roman Senate dates to around the year 1300 and, according to most scholars, was composed to compensate for the lack of any physical description of Jesus in the Bible.&lt;ref name=Perkinson30 &gt;''The likeness of the king: a prehistory of portraiture in late medieval France'' by Stephen Perkinson 2009 ISBN 0226658791 page 30&lt;/ref&gt; Also in the 14th century [[Nicephorus Callistus]] quoted an unnamed antique source that described Jesus as tall and beautiful with fair, wavy hair, but his account was most likely without basis and was inspired by the prevailing artistic images of Jesus.&lt;ref&gt;''Jesus'' by Hartmut Miethe, Hilde Heyduck-Huth, ISBN 3930180219 Taylor &amp; Francis page 168&lt;/ref&gt;

The Islamic ''[[Hadith]]'', collections of 8-9th century AD sayings with no scriptural ascertainment or specific authorship, describe Jesus as &quot;reddish-white&quot; faced.&lt;ref&gt;''Hadith'', Volume 4, Book 55, Number 607, Narrated Abu Huraira; Volume 9, Book 88, Number 242, Narrated 'Abdullah bin 'Umar.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Emergence of racial theories==
In explaining the development of racial theories in the context of [[scripture]], Colin Kidd, in his book ''The forging of races'', argues that the assignment of race to biblical individuals has been a mostly subjective practice based on cultural stereotypes and societal trends rather than on scientific methods.&lt;ref name=Kidd18 &gt;''The forging of races: race and scripture in the Protestant Atlantic world'' by Colin Kidd 2006 ISBN 0521793246 page 18&lt;/ref&gt; Kidd reviews a number of theories about the race of Jesus, ranging from a white Aryan Jesus to a black African Jesus, illustrating that there is no general agreement among scholars on the race of Jesus.&lt;ref name=Kidd43 &gt;''The forging of races: race and scripture in the Protestant Atlantic world'' by Colin Kidd 2006 ISBN 0521793246 pages 43-50&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Henry Ossawa Tanner - Jesus and nicodemus.jpg|thumb||180px|A black Jesus with [[Nicodemus]], by [[Henry Ossawa Tanner|Tanner]], 1899]]
In his book ''Racializing Jesus'', Shawn Kelley states that the assignment of a specific race to Jesus has been a cultural phenomenon emanating from the higher levels of intellectual circles within societies, and draws parallels between the seemingly different approaches within different settings.&lt;ref name=SKelly &gt;''Racializing Jesus: Race, Ideology and the Formation of Modern Biblical Scholarship'' by Shawn Kelley 2002 ISBN 0415283736 pages ii-xi&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 19th century theories that Jesus was European, and in particular [[Aryan race|Aryan]], were developed and later appealed to those who wanted nothing Jewish about Jesus, e.g. [[Nazi]] theologians.&lt;ref name=Kidd48 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Aryan Jesus: Christian theologians and the Bible in Nazi Germany'' by Susannah Heschel 2008 ISBN 0691125317 page 32&lt;/ref&gt; Scholars supporting the Aryan view also argued that being a Jew by religion was distinguishable from being a Jew by race.&lt;ref&gt;''The Symbolic Jesus: Historical Scholarship, Judaism and the Construction of Contemporary Identity'' by William Edward Arnal 2005 ISBN 1845530071 pages 46-47&lt;/ref&gt; These theories usually also include the reasoning that Jesus was Aryan because Galilee was an Aryan region, but have not gained scholarly acceptance.&lt;ref name=Goguel255 &gt;''Jesus and the origins of Christianity'' by Maurice Goguel, New York, Harper, 1960 page 255&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kidd48 &gt;''The forging of races: race and scripture in the Protestant Atlantic world'' by Colin Kidd 2006 ISBN 0521793246 pages 48-51&lt;/ref&gt; 

By the 20th century, theories had also been proposed that Jesus was of [[Black people|black African]] descent, e.g. based on the argument that Mary his mother was a descendant of black Jews.&lt;ref name=WChrist &gt;&quot;The Black Christ&quot; Chapter 25 of ''The Blackwell Companion to Jesus'' edited by Delbert Burkett 2010 ISBN 140519362X pages 410-420&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kidd43 /&gt; [[Martin Luther King]] was a proponent of the &quot;Black  Christ&quot; movement and identified the struggle of Jesus against the authorities of the time with the struggle of African Americans in the southern parts of the United States, as he questioned why the white church leaders did not voice concern for racial equality.&lt;ref name=WChrist /&gt;

The issue of the race of Jesus has been also addressed in television documentaries, e.g. a 2001 [[BBC]] program that used three first-century Jewish skulls to try to depict Jesus in a new way, which according to the Guardian was &quot;likely to prove highly contentious.&quot;&lt;ref name=G1 &gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2001/mar/27/broadcasting.uknews2|title=Is this the real face of Jesus Christ?|first=Matt|last=Wells|date=March 27, 2001|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|publisher=[[Guardian News and Media|Guardian]]|location=[[London]]|issn=0261-3077|oclc=60623878|accessdate=May 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Acheiropoieta and reported visions==
{{also|Acheiropoieta}}
[[File:Jezu Ufam Tobie.jpg|thumb|130px|The ''[[Divine Mercy image|Divine Mercy depiction]]'' of Jesus]]
During the Middle Ages, a number of legendary images of Jesus began to appear, at times perhaps constructed to validate the styles of depiction of that period, e.g. the [[image of Edessa]].&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; The [[Veil of Veronica]] was accompanied by a narrative about the Passion of Jesus.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; 

A number of descriptions of Jesus have been reported by saints and mystics who claim they [[Visions of Jesus and Mary|have seen Jesus in a vision]]. Reports of such visions are more common among [[Roman Catholics]] than other Christian denominations.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Freze, 1993, ''Voices, Visions, and Apparitions'', OSV Publishing ISBN 087973454X page 91&lt;/ref&gt;

By the 20th century, some reports of miraculous images of Jesus began to receive significant attention, e.g. [[Secondo Pia]]'s photograph of the [[Shroud of Turin]], one of the most controversial artifacts in history. During its May 2010 exposition the shroud and its photograph of what some authors consider the face of Jesus were visited by over 2 million people.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur Barnes, 2003 ''Holy Shroud of Turin'' Kessinger Press ISBN 0766134253 pages 2-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=WMeacham &gt;William Meacham, ''The Authentication of the Turin Shroud:An Issue in Archaeological Epistemology'', [[Current Anthropology]], Volume 24, No 3, June 1983&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zenit.org/rssenglish-29146 Zenit, May 5, 2010]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Another 20th century depiction of Jesus, namely the [[Divine Mercy image]] is based on [[Faustina Kowalska]]'s reported vision, which she described in [[Diary: Divine Mercy in My Soul|her diary]] as a pattern that was then painted by artists.&lt;ref name=Odell /&gt; The depiction is now widely used among Catholics, and has over 100 million followers worldwide.&lt;ref name=Odell &gt;Catherine M. Odell, 1998, ''Faustina: Apostle of Divine Mercy'' OSV Press ISBN 9780879739232 page 165&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Am With You Always'' by Benedict Groeschel 2010 ISBN 9781586172572 page 548&lt;/ref&gt;

==Artistic portrayals==
{{Main|Depictions of Jesus}}
{{also|Life of Christ}}
Despite the lack of biblical references or historical records, for two millennia a wide range of depictions of Jesus have appeared, often influenced by cultural settings, political circumstances and theological contexts.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Perkinson30 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Erricker44 &gt;''Teaching Christianity: a world religions approach'' by Clive Erricker 1987 ISBN 0718826345 page 44&lt;/ref&gt; As in other [[Christian art]], the earliest depictions date to the late second or early third century, and are primarily found in [[Rome]].&lt;ref name=Benedetto51 &gt;''The New Westminster Dictionary of Church History'' by Robert Benedetto 2006 ISBN 082648011X pages 51-53&lt;/ref&gt; In these early depictions (e.g. as the [[Good Shepherd]]), Jesus is usually shown as a youthful figure without a beard and with curly hair, often with different features from the other men in the scenes, e.g. his disciples or the Romans.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; 

[[File:ChristPeterPaul detail.jpg|thumb|left|150px|A very early bearded image of Jesus, [[Catacombs of Marcellinus and Peter]], Rome, 4th century]]
Although some images exist at the synagogue at [[Dura-Europos]], Judaism forbade images, and there is no record of its influence on the depictions of Jesus.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt; Christian depictions of the 3rd and 4th centuries typically focused on New Testament scenes of healings and other miracles.&lt;ref name= Benedetto51 /&gt; Following the [[Constantine the Great and Christianity|conversion of Constantine]] in the 4th century, Christian art found many wealthy donors and flourished.&lt;ref name= Benedetto51 /&gt; In this period Jesus began to have more mature features, and was shown with a beard.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; A new development at this time was the depiction of Jesus without a narrative context, but just as a figure by himself.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt;  

By the 5th century depictions of the [[Passion (Christianity)|Passion]] began to appear, perhaps reflecting a change in the theological focus of the early Church.&lt;ref name= Benedetto51 /&gt; The 6th century [[Rabbula Gospels]] include some of the earliest images of the [[Crucifixion of Jesus|crucifixion]] and resurrection.&lt;ref name= Benedetto51 /&gt; By the 6th century the bearded depiction of Jesus had become standard, both in the [[Eastern Church|East]] and the [[Western Church|West]].&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; These depictions with reddish brown hair parted in the middle and with almond shaped eyes showed consistency for several centuries.&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; At this time various legends were developed to attempt to validate the styles of depiction, e.g. the [[image of Edessa]] and later the [[Veil of Veronica]].&lt;ref name=JensenBWell /&gt; 

The [[Byzantine Iconoclasm]] acted as a barrier to developments in the East, but by the 9th century art was again permitted.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt; The [[Transfiguration of Jesus]] was a major theme in the East and every [[Eastern Orthodox]] monk who took up iconography had to start his craft by painting the icon of the Transfiguration.&lt;ref name=Bigham226 &gt;''The image of God the Father in Orthodox theology and iconography'' by Steven Bigham 1995 ISBN 1879038153 pages 226-227&lt;/ref&gt; Whereas Western depictions aim for proportion, the abolition of perspective and alterations in the size and proportion of an image in Eastern icons aim to reach beyond man's earthly dwellings.&lt;ref&gt;[[Archimandrite]] Vasileios of [[Stavronikita]], &quot;Icons as Liturgical Analogies&quot; in ''Hymn of entry: liturgy and life in the Orthodox church'' 1997 ISBN 9780881410266 pages 81-90&lt;/ref&gt; 
 
[[File:ChineseJesus.jpg|thumb|180px|The representation of the race of Jesus has been influenced by cultural settings.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 &gt;''Jesus: the complete guide'' by Leslie Houlden 2006 082648011X pages 63-100&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Erricker44 /&gt; A Chinese illustration, [[Beijing]], 1879.]]
The 13th century witnessed a turning point in the portrayal of the powerful [[Kyrios]] image of Jesus as a [[Miracles of Jesus|wonder worker]] in the [[Western Church|West]], as the [[Order of Saint Francis|Franciscans]] began to emphasize the humility of Jesus both at his birth and his death via the [[Nativity of Jesus|Nativity scene]] as well as the crucifixion.&lt;ref name=Brooke &gt;''The image of St Francis'' by Rosalind B. Brooke 2006 ISBN 0521782910 pages 183-184&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Raab &gt;''The tradition of Catholic prayer'' by Christian Raab, Harry Hagan, St. Meinrad Archabbey 2007 ISBN 0814631843 pages 86-87&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GFinger &gt;''The vitality of the Christian tradition'' by George Finger Thomas 1944 ISBN 0836923782 page 110-112&lt;/ref&gt; The Franciscans approached both ends of this spectrum of emotions and as the joys of the [[Nativity of Jesus in art|Nativity]] of were added to the agony of crucifixion a whole new range of emotions were ushered in, with wide ranging cultural impact on the image of Jesus for centuries thereafter.&lt;ref name=GFinger /&gt;&lt;ref name=Brooke /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''La vida sacra: contemporary Hispanic sacramental theology'' by James L. Empereur, Eduardo Fernández 2006 ISBN 0742551571 pages 3-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Philippines'' by Lily Rose R. Tope, Detch P. Nonan-Mercado 2005 ISBN 0761414754 page 109&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Renaissance]] brought forth a number of artistic masters who focused on the depictions of Jesus and after [[Giotto]], [[Fra Angelico]] and others systematically developed uncluttered images that focused on the depiction of Jesus with an ideal human beauty.&lt;ref name=LHoulden63 /&gt; [[Leonardo da Vinci]]'s [[The Last Supper (Leonardo da Vinci)|Last Supper]] which is considered the first work of [[High Renaissance]] art due to its high level of harmony became well known for depicting Jesus surrounded by varying emotions of the individual apostles at the announcement of the betrayal.&lt;ref&gt;''Experiencing Art Around Us'' by Thomas Buser 2005 ISBN 9780534641146 pages 382-383&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Leonardo da Vinci, the Last Supper: a Cosmic Drama and an Act of Redemption'' by Michael Ladwein 2006 pages 27 and 60&lt;/ref&gt;

Objections to depictions of Jesus have appeared, e.g. in 1850 [[John Everett Millais]] was attacked for his painting ''[[Christ in the House of his Parents]]'' because it was &quot;painful&quot; to see &quot;the youthful Saviour&quot; depicted as &quot;a red-headed Jew boy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|date=June 1, 1850|title=The Royal Academy Exhiition|journal=[[The Builder]]|volume=8|number=382|pages=255–256|publisher=[[Publishing Office]]|location=[[London]]|editor1-first=George|editor1-last=Godwin|editor1-link=George Godwin|accessdate=June 18, 2011|url=http://www.bodley.ox.ac.uk/cgi-bin/ilej/image1.pl?item=page&amp;seq=1&amp;size=1&amp;id=bu.1850.6.x.8.x.x.255}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first cinematic portrayal of Jesus was in the 1897 film ''La Passion du Christ'' produced in Paris, which lasted five minutes.&lt;ref&gt;''The Challenge of the Silver Screen (Studies in Religion and the Arts)'' ISBN By Freek L. Bakker 2009 ISBN 9004168613 page 1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of early cinema'' by Richard Abel2005 ISBN 0415234409 page 518&lt;/ref&gt; Thereafter cinematic portrayals have continued to show Jesus with a beard in the standard western depiction that resembles Renaissance images.&lt;ref name=BWell526 &gt;''The Blackwell Companion to Jesus'' edited by Delbert Burkett 2010 ISBN 140519362X page 526&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent artistic and cinematic portrayals have also made an effort to characterize Jesus as [[Middle Eastern]]. In the 2004 movie, ''[[The Passion Of The Christ]]'', Jesus was portrayed by [[James Caviezel]] who wore a [[prosthetic]] nose during filming and had his blue eyes digitally changed to brown to give him a Middle Eastern appearance. According to designer Miles Teves, who created the prosthesis: &quot;Mel [Gibson] wanted to make the actor playing Jesus, James Caviezel, look more ethnically Middle Eastern, and it was decided that we could do it best by changing the shape of his nose.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Rickitt|first1=Richard|title=Designing Movie Creatures and Characters: Behind the Scenes With the Movie Masters|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=NH1OPgAACAAJ|accessdate=June 18, 2011|edition=illustrated|year=2006|publisher=[[RotoVision]]|location=[[Hove]]|isbn=978-2-94-036139-7|oclc=475780266|ref=harv|laysummary=http://www.graphics.com/modules.php?name=Sections&amp;op=viewarticle&amp;artid=501|laydate=February 20, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://juice.box.sk/newsread.php?newsid=717 James Caviezel was given a prosthetic nose and a raised hairline. His blue eyes were digitally changed to brown on film.]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Historical Jesus]]
* [[Life of Christ]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{Cite book|last1=Ehrman|first1=Bart D.|authorlink1=Bart D. Ehrman|editor1-first=Bart D|editor1-last=Ehrman|editor1-link=Bart D. Ehrman|title=The New Testament: a Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings, Part 1|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=oxUw86gZO4oC|accessdate=June 18, 2011|edition=3rd, illustrated|year=2004|publisher=[[Oxford University Press|Oxford University]]|location=[[New York City]]|isbn=978-0-19-515462-7|oclc=52430805|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Glasgow|first1=James|title=The Apocalypse Translated and Expounded|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=t6ebQwAACAAJ|accessdate=June 18, 2011|year=2010|origyear=1872|publisher=[[T&amp;T Clark]]|location=[[Edinburgh]]|isbn=978-1-15-328844-6|oclc=557904029|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Mosley|first1=William|title=What Color Was Jesus?|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=YHYdNAAACAAJ|accessdate=June 18, 2011|edition=1st|year=1987|publisher=African American Images|location=[[Chicago]]|isbn=978-0-91-354309-2|oclc=17281825|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Niehaus|first1=Jeffrey Jay|title=God at Sinai: Covenant and Theophany in the Bible and Ancient Near East|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=nvUUjTrGrwwC|accessdate=June 18, 2011|year=1995|publisher=[[Zondervan]]|series=Studies in Old Testament Biblical Theology|location=[[Grand Rapids, Michigan]]|isbn=978-0-31-049471-3|oclc=31434584|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Rodriguez|first1=Clara E.|title=Changing Race: Latinos, the Census, and the History of Ethnicity in the United States|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=mSj28ikZQpUC|accessdate=June 18, 2011|edition=illustrated|series=Critical America|year=2000|publisher=[[New York University]]|location=[[New York City]]|isbn=978-0-81-477547-9|oclc=43684476|ref=harv}}


{{DEFAULTSORT:Race Of Jesus}}
[[Category:Jesus]]
[[Category:Religion and race|Jesus, race of]]

[[tr:İsa'nın ırkı]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
