<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="2951089" ns="0" title="WKTC"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast |
  call_letters             = WKTC|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = [[Image:WBHQMy63logo.jpg|150px]]|
  station_slogan           = |
  station_branding         = My63|
  analog                   = |
  digital                  = 39 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br&gt;[[virtual channel|Virtual]]: 63 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])|
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br&gt;[[Telemundo]] (on DT2)&lt;br&gt;[[Antenna TV]] (on DT3)&lt;br&gt;[[Retro Television Network|RTV]] (on DT4)|
  network                  = |
  founded                  = |
  airdate                  = September 15, 1997|
  location                 = [[Sumter, South Carolina|Sumter]]/[[Columbia, South Carolina]]|
  callsign_meaning         = WK '''T'''elevision of '''C'''olumbia|
  former_callsigns         = WQHB (1997-2003)&lt;br&gt;WBHQ (2003-2006)|
  former_channel_numbers   = Analog:&lt;br&gt;63 (1997-2009)|
  owner                    = WBHQ Columbia, LLC|
  licensee                 = |
  sister_stations          = |
  former_affiliations      = [[The WB]] (1998-2006, secondary until 2001)&lt;br&gt;[[UPN]] (1998-2004, secondary from 2001)&lt;br&gt;[[Ion Television|Pax TV]] (per program, 1998-2003)|
  effective_radiated_power = 500 kW|
  HAAT                     = 391 m|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = 40902|
  coordinates              = {{coord|34|6|58.4|N|80|45|49.9|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = |
}}
'''WKTC''', '''&quot;My63&quot;''' is the [[MyNetworkTV]] affiliate for [[Columbia, South Carolina]].  It is licensed to [[Sumter, South Carolina|Sumter]], with studios in the Pontiac Business Center complex in [[Elgin, Kershaw County, South Carolina|Elgin]].  It broadcasts its digital signal on UHF channel 39, and is located on channel 4 on most Midlands cable systems.  

==Digital Television==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel !! Video !! Aspect !! Programming
|-
| 63.1 || 480i || [[16:9]] || Main WKTC programming / MyNetworkTV
|-
| 63.2 || rowspan=3| 480i || rowspan=3| [[4:3]] || Telemundo
|-
| 63.3 || Antenna TV
|-
| 63.4 || RTV
|}

==History==
The station first signed on in 1997 as '''WQHB''', a primary [[UPN]] affiliate with a secondary [[The WB Television Network|WB]] affiliation. The WB primetime programming was shown on a one-day delay from 6-8pm. It also aired select programming from Pax TV (now [[Ion Television]].  At this time the station's primary transmitter was located in Sumter.  As it was not nearly strong enough to provide a decent over-the-air signal to Columbia, WQHB set up a translator on [[W67DP]], channel 67 in Columbia.  

In 2001, the station swapped affiliations and became a WB primary/UPN secondary affiliate; UPN programming was shown at 10:00 pm nightly after WB's primetime programming. Pax programming was dropped altogether at this time.  In 2003, it changed its call letters as well to WBHQ (a reversal of its original calls, but also standing for '''WB H'''ead'''Q'''uarters) and moved its transmitter to space on WOLO's tower between [[Lugoff, South Carolina|Lugoff]] and Elgin.  This gave it an over-the-air coverage area comparable to the other major Columbia stations, enabling it to shut down the channel 67 translator.  It also changed its on-air name from &quot;WB63&quot; to &quot;Midland's WB4&quot; (a reference to its cable channel).  During this period, it moved to its current studios in Elgin.  In August 2004, WBHQ dropped UPN programming when [[WZRB]] signed on.

On January 24, 2006, it was announced that The WB and UPN would merge into a new network called [[The CW Television Network|The CW]] in September 2006.    On March 25, it was announced that WBHQ would become the Columbia affiliate of MyNetworkTV, a new network from [[News Corporation]].[http://www.thestate.com/mld/thestate/14183313.htm] 

On June 26, 2006, WBHQ changed its call letters to WKTC: it started using them two days later, on June 28.  An advertisement in this date's Free Times newspaper in Columbia depicts the stars of &quot;Desire&quot; and says &quot;September 5 / It's a whole new ballgame&quot;, with the stylized &quot;My 63&quot; logo and the new call letters.  According to the station's co-owner, WKTC stands for &quot;Television of Columbia&quot;. 

In August 2007, W67DP separated from WKTC to become a [[Telemundo]] affiliate for Columbia, using the calls &quot;WNXG&quot;.  In November 2009, WKTC began carrying W67DP/WNXG on 63.2, shifting RTV to 63.3. In November 2011, WKTC became an AntennaTV affiliate located on its 63.3 frequency, thus shifting RTV, once again, this time to 63.4.

In late August, WKTC launched its full-power digital signal on channel 39.

WKTC's owner also started a low-power station in [[Wilmington, North Carolina]], '''[[W47CK|WMYW]]''', which serves as Wilmington's MyNetworkTV affiliate, and a low-power station in [[Savannah, Georgia]], [[WHDS-LP]], that serves as a Telemundo affiliate.

The station's Website at ''wktctv.com'' went offline in 2008 and hasn't returned; however, it is still listed in MyNetworkTV's station directory.

In 2011, WKTC was named by [[Disney-ABC Domestic Television]] as the Columbia Metropolitan market's secondary affiliate for the [[Southeastern Conference]] television package.  WKTC will carry selected SEC basketball games under terms of the new affiliation, shared with [[WOLO-TV]]. &lt;REF&gt;[http://gamecocksonline.cstv.com/genrel/062111aaa.html SEC Network Announced Affiliate Change in Columbia.] &lt;/REF&gt;.

==Trivia==
	 	
*WKTC's owner did not change its name to reflect the new call letters (the company is still known as WBHQ Columbia, LLC).

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{TVQ|WKTC}}
*{{BIA|WKTC|TV|TV}}

{{Columbia TV}}
{{MNTV South Carolina}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wktc}}
[[Category:MyNetworkTV affiliates]]
[[Category:Television stations in South Carolina]]
[[Category:Channel 39 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 63 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1997]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
