<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="295238" ns="0" title="Rider University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = Rider University
|image = [[Image:Riderseal.png|Seal of Rider University Seal]]
 |motto         = In Omnia Paratus (''In all things prepared'') &lt;ref name=&quot;Motto&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.rider.edu/172_69.htm |title=Real World Learning |publisher=Rider University | accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |established   = 1865
 |type          = [[Private school|Private]]
 |endowment = $50 million&lt;ref&gt;http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2011/schools/rider-university&lt;/ref&gt;
 |president     = [[Mordechai Rozanski]]
 |faculty       = 236 full time &lt;ref name=&quot;Glance&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.rider.edu/139_55.htm | title=Rider at a Glance | publisher=Rider University | accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |students      = 5,790 &lt;ref name=&quot;Glance&quot;/&gt;
 |undergrad     = 4,050 &lt;ref name=&quot;Rider University breaks ground&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.nj.com/mercer/index.ssf/2010/05/rider_university_breaks_ground.html | title=Rider University breaks ground on environment-friendly construction | work= The Times ''(Trenton) | accessdate=2010-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |postgrad      = 1,204 &lt;ref name=&quot;Glance&quot;/&gt;
 |city          = {{Flag icon|USA}} [[Lawrenceville, New Jersey|Lawrenceville]]
 |state         = [[New Jersey|NJ]]
 |country       = [[United States|U.S.]]
 |coor          =
 |campus        = [[suburban]], {{convert|303|acre|km2}} &lt;ref name=&quot;Glance&quot;/&gt; (1.2 km&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt;)
 |sports        = baseball, cross-country, golf, soccer, tennis, wrestling, volleyball, basketball, softball, swimming &amp; diving, track &amp; field &lt;ref name=&quot;Athletics&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.rider.edu/174.htm | title=Athletics | publisher=Rider University | accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |colors        = Cranberry and white &lt;ref name=&quot;Glance&quot;/&gt; {{color box|#990033}} {{color box|#ffffff}}
|nickname       = Broncs
 |athletics     = [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference|MAAC]], [[Northeast Conference|NEC]] (field hockey only), [[Colonial Athletic Association|CAA]] (wrestling only) &lt;ref name=&quot;Athletics&quot;/&gt;
 |affiliations  = [[Council of Independent Colleges|CIC]],&lt;ref name=&quot;CIC&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.cic.org/about/membership/members.asp | title=Current Institutional, International, and Associate Members | publisher=Council of Inrependent Colleges University | accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities|NAICU]],&lt;ref name=&quot;NAICU&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| url=http://www.naicu.edu/member_center/members.asp#R| title=Member Directory | publisher=National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities | accessdate=2008-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sanda University]]
 |website       = [http://www.rider.edu www.rider.edu]
 |logo          =
}}

'''Rider University''' is a [[private university|private]], coeducational and nonsectarian [[university]] located chiefly in [[Lawrenceville, New Jersey|Lawrenceville]], in [[Mercer County, New Jersey|Mercer County]], [[New Jersey]], [[United States]]. It consists of five academic units: the College of Business Administration, the College of Liberal Arts, Education and Sciences, the College of Continuing Studies, and the Westminster College of the Arts (which has two divisions: the School of Fine and Performing Arts and [[Westminster Choir College]], the latter which is located in the nearby borough of [[Princeton, New Jersey|Princeton]]). In addition to regional accreditation, the undergraduate and graduate programs in business are accredited by [[AACSB]], and the professional education graduate programs are accredited by [[NCATE]]. Rider University is considered selective.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/lawrenceville-nj/rider-university-2628 Rider University profile], ''[[US News &amp; World Report]] America's Best Colleges'', rankingsandreviews.com&lt;/ref&gt; It was ranked in the 2012 ''[[US News &amp; World Report]] America's Best Colleges'' guide at number 21 in the Regional Universities North category.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/rider-university-2628], ''US News &amp; World Report America's Best Colleges'', rankingsandreviews.com&lt;/ref&gt; Rider University is also listed in the ''[[Princeton Review]] The Best 376 Colleges'' 2012 edition, where it is also ranked #13 Least Beautiful Campus, #18 Dorms Like Dungeons, and #11 Students Study the Least. There are 5,982 undergraduate and graduate students attending.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rider.edu/139_55.htm Rider at a Glance], Rider University. accessed April 20, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Origin===
At the conclusion of the [[US Civil War|Civil War]], '''Henry B. Bryant''' and '''Henry D. Stratton''', operators of a chain of business schools decided to open a school in New Jersey. On October 1, 1865, '''The Trenton Business College''' was established in [[Trenton, New Jersey]], located in Temperance Hall at the corner of South Broad and Front Streets. '''Andrew Jackson Rider''' became its first president.&lt;ref name=&quot;philadelphia.about.com&quot;&gt;http://philadelphia.about.com/od/colleges/p/rider_univ.htm&lt;/ref&gt; President Rider was also known as a leading force in the [[cranberry]] industry, as he owned 500 acres of cranberry bogs near [[Hammonton, New Jersey]]. (One of the school colors is cranberry, incidentally.)

President Rider steered the business school through a period of growth, and the school continued to move to larger quarters. In 1896 women were admitted to the school. In 1897, the school was renamed '''The Rider Business College'''. President Rider stepped down the following year. In 1957 Rider introduced liberal studies leading to a Bachelor of Arts degree.&lt;ref name=&quot;philadelphia.about.com&quot;/&gt; The institution officially became known as '''Rider College''' upon its move to East State Street in Trenton in 1921, and the following year the [[New Jersey Board of Education]] granted Rider College permission to confer the degrees of Bachelor of Accounts and Bachelor of Commercial Science. Rider College moved to Lawrenceville in 1964. It affiliated with nearby Princeton [[Westminster Choir College]] in 1991, merged with Westminster in 1992 and became a university in 1994.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rider.edu/about&lt;/ref&gt;

===Since 2000===
Rider has invested more than $100 million since 2004 to construct new and renovate existing facilities for teaching, performing arts, residences and recreation. In 2005 Rider completed its {{convert|63000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Student Recreation Center (SRC), a new 186-bed residence hall, and three-story additions to Ziegler and Hill Residence Halls, visually symbolizing the renewal taking place on both campuses. It contains locker rooms, a {{convert|3600|sqft|m2|adj=on}} fitness room with cardiovascular and strength training equipment, about 30 workout machines; 10 with built-in TVs, two group-exercise studios, three multi-purpose courts for basketball, tennis; and volleyball, 3-lane elevated track, and game room.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rider.edu/athletics/directions-facilities/student-recreation-center/facilities&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007 President Rozanski announced the creation of the School of Fine and Performing Arts to integrate the Lawrenceville and Princeton campuses and expand programming for the arts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://comm.rider.edu/ridernews/html/sections/2006_2007/01_09_22_06/news/01_newsstory.html The Rider News]&lt;/ref&gt;

In recent years President Rozanski announced new academic programs and new financial aid resources that will help students be able to afford to attend Rider.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.rider.edu/news/2009/09/04/rozanski-strikes-positive-notes-fall-convocation Rozanski Strikes Positive Notes at Fall Convocation]&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 2009, construction was completed on a new, environmentally-friendly 150-bed residence hall on the Lawrenceville campus, and more than 300 new parking spaces. In the summer of 2010 the University began two construction projects, a new, [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design]] (LEED)-silver certified, {{convert|21250|sqft|m2|adj=on}} academic building to be built next to Moore Library, and an {{convert|11000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} expansion of the Bart Luedeke Center Theater, that will include dressing rooms, an orchestra pit, black box theater and a dance studio.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.theridernews.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/100209_optimized.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Both are scheduled to be completed by the Fall 2011 semester.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rider University breaks ground&quot;/&gt; As of 2010 fundraising is continuing toward completion of several future facilities priorities including a new performance complex on the Princeton campus, complete with classrooms, rehearsal and performance space, a large reception lobby and a connector to the Playhouse.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Fundraising and planning are also under way to extensively renovate Alumni Gym on the Lawrenceville campus in order to enhance venues for men’s and women’s basketball, volleyball and wrestling.&lt;ref&gt;http://viewer.zmags.com/publication/9548c238#/9548c238/8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
The {{convert|280|acre|km2|sing=on}} Lawrenceville campus is in a suburban area three miles (5&amp;nbsp;km) north of [[Trenton, New Jersey|Trenton]] and five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) south of [[Princeton, New Jersey|Princeton]]. The modern facilities, designed to meet the academic, social, and recreational needs of the Rider faculty and students, are clustered and within easy walking distance of one another on the large park-like campus.

The Westminster campus is in Princeton, New Jersey.

==Academic programs==
Traditional [[liberal arts]] programs of study are offered on the Lawrenceville campus, as well as undergraduate business and education studies. The Westminster campus offers musically-based curricula.

The College of Business Administration offers two graduate degrees: the Master of Accountancy (M.Acc.) and the Master of Business Administration (MBA).

The Department of Graduate Education and Human Services offers five master of arts degrees and 25 certification programs. MA degrees are offered in Counseling Services; Curriculum, Instruction, and Supervision; Educational Administration; Reading and Language Arts; and Human Services Administration. Among the many certification programs is a Graduate-Level Teacher Certification program. In addition, two educational specialist degrees are offered: an Ed.S. degree in Counseling Services and an Ed.S. degree in School Psychology.

*Over 60 academic majors and special programs offered
*243 full-time faculty
*Student to faculty ratio: 13 to 1
*Average class size: 25 students
*4,100 full-time undergraduates representing 41 states and 72 countries
*97% of full-time faculty hold a doctorate or the highest degree in their field
*Undergraduate degrees: Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Science, and Bachelor of Business administration

==Academic buildings==
Memorial Hall, the Science and Technology Center, the Fine Arts Center, Joseph P. Vonna Academic Annex, the Stephen A. Maurer Physical Education Building, Anne Brossman Sweigart Hall (Business Administration), North Hall (History &amp; Philosophy) contain the classrooms and laboratories for all curricula. A general access lab containing terminals, microcomputers, and laser printers is located in the Fine Arts Center; other computer labs are located in Anne Brossman Sweigart Hall, Memorial Hall, and at Westminster Choir College. Central VAX systems provide electronic mail, conferencing, and Internet access tools.

==Student life==
Currently on Rider's Lawrenceville Campus, there are twelve social Greek organizations which are members of the Interfraternity Council, the Panhellenic Council or the Intercultural Greek Council. There are four fraternities, and eight sororities. In addition to these social Greek organizations, there are numerous professional and honorary fraternities. About 10% of the Rider community is involved in fraternity and sorority life.

===Fraternities===
*[[Sigma Phi Epsilon]]
*[[Tau Kappa Epsilon]]
*[[Lambda Theta Phi]]
*[[Kappa Alpha Psi]]

===Sororities===
*[[Alpha Xi Delta]]
*[[Phi Sigma Sigma]]
*[[Zeta Tau Alpha]]
*[[Delta Phi Epsilon (social)|Delta Phi Epsilon]]
*[[Delta Sigma Theta]]
*[[Lambda Tau Omega]]
*[[Lambda Theta Alpha]]
*[[Zeta Phi Beta]]

In the Spring, the Greeks hold &quot;Greek Week&quot;. During Greek Week, the Fraternities and Sororities compete in a variety of events which change from year to year; however, every year there is a philanthropy event. Past events have benefited St. Jude's Juvenile Cancer Center, as well as paralysis research, neurological disorder research, and various other causes. The 2010 winners of Greek Week were Tau Kappa Epsilon and Zeta Tau Alpha.

There are also two fraternities located on the Princeton campus ([[Westminster Choir College]]): [[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]] and [[Sigma Alpha Iota]], a men's and women's music fraternities, respectively.

===Professional and honorary fraternities===
*[[Delta Sigma Pi]]
*[[Lambda Pi Eta]]
*[[Omicron Delta Kappa]]
*[[Alpha Psi Omega]]

==Resources==
The Franklin Moore Library supports the academic programs with a collection of more than 481,000 volumes, 2,000 periodical titles, 650,000 microforms, 134 online databases, electronic access to 42,000 journals, and an audiovisual collection. Materials are cataloged in Library of Congress classification and are accessible through an online catalog, part of the library's automated catalog/circulation/acquisitions system. Online database searching is available to complement the library's on-campus holdings. Westminster Choir College’s Talbott Library has specialized music resources including 75,000 books, music scores and periodicals, a choral music reference collection of more than 80,000 titles and more than 31,000 sound and video recordings

==Publications and media==
;''[[The Shadow Yearbook]]'' : first published in 1923 two years after the institution officially changed its name to Rider College. The yearbook continues to be published each year by a student staff. The staff writes all the articles, designs the pages, comes up with its theme and takes many of the pictures. The 2010 yearbook marked its 87th volume. The book is primarily made for senior students, but can be purchased by any Rider student. Seniors that sit for a portrait receive a yearbook free of charge. The book typically is shipped to students in November. As of 2010, [[Herff Jones]] publishes the book for Rider.
;''[[The Rider News]]'' : the school's student newspaper, founded in 1930. It is published weekly between September and May, during the academic term.
;WRRC-FM 107.7 The Bronc&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.1077thebronc.com www.1077thebronc.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
;''Venture'' : literary magazine which welcomes submissions of students’ art and literature focusing on any topic
;The Rider University Network (R.U.N.) : student organization that produces television programs in the Department of Communication and Journalism’s Television Studio. Programs are regularly broadcast on the campus network and are available everywhere online.&lt;ref&gt;[http://comm.rider.edu/RUNetwork/ Rider University Network]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
[[File:RiderBroncLogo.png|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]
{{Main|Rider Broncs}}
{{See also|List of college athletic programs in New Jersey, USA#Division I}}
Athletic teams are nicknamed the Broncs. The school competes in the [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference]].

The intercollegiate sports program at Rider was started by coach [[Clair Bee]] in the 1920s. Two of the school's most famous athletic alumni are former [[University of Notre Dame|Notre Dame]] basketball coach and current [[ESPN]] sportscaster [[Digger Phelps]], who played basketball at Rider from 1959 to 1963 and [[Jason Thompson]] who played basketball at Rider from 2004 to 2008 and was drafted by the [[Sacramento Kings]] with the 12th pick of the 2008 NBA Draft while never winning a MAAC championship or appearing in the NCAA Tournament.

The university competed in [[American football|football]] until 1951, when the university was placed under investigation after allegations of paying recruits, as well as improper benefits for players on the team. The NCAA asked the school to discontinue the football program, and the Broncs have not fielded a team since.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} Rider students often proclaim their football team &quot;undefeated since 1951,&quot; as they have not existed since that time.

As of January 20, 2007, there are 78 members in the Rider University Athletics [[Hall of Fame]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gobroncs.com/ViewArticle.dbml?DB_OEM_ID=20200&amp;KEY=&amp;ATCLID=1372269 Rider Athletics Hall of Fame Nominations] (including alphabetical list of inductees). July 27, 2010. Rider University Athletics official website. Retrieved 2010-09-02.&lt;/ref&gt; The University has recently redesigned their sports logo.&lt;ref&gt;Caputo, Mike. [http://comm.rider.edu/ridernews/html/sections/2006_2007/15_02_23_07/news/03_newsstory.html &quot;University plans to revamp Bronc logo&quot;], ''The Rider News'', Rider University, 23 February 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==President==
Its current president is Dr. [[Mordechai Rozanski]], who is Rider's sixth president. Dr. Rozanski became president on August 1, 2003 following the retirement of former president, Dr. J. Barton Luedeke.

Rider has had six presidents:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rider.edu/139_5684.htm Presidents of Rider], accessed August 12, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
*Andrew Jackson Rider (1866–1898)
*Franklin Benjamin Moore (1898–1934)
*Franklin Frazee Moore (1934–1969)
*Frank N. Elliott (1969–1990)
*J. Barton Luedeke (1990–2003)
*[[Mordechai Rozanski]] (2003— )

==Notable alumni==
{{Main|List of Rider University people}}
Rider University has approximately 40,000 living alumni worldwide. Rider alumni are distinguishing themselves in the fields of [[business]], [[government]], and [[sports]].

* In the field of business, Rider graduates include: Neil B. Friedman, president of [[Mattel|Mattel Brands]];&lt;ref&gt;[http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/people/person.asp?personId=162887&amp;ticker=MAT:US BusinessWeek: Neil B. Friedman]&lt;/ref&gt; Thomas J. Lynch, CEO of Tyco Electronics;&lt;ref&gt;[http://people.forbes.com/profile/thomas-j-lynch/55035 Forbes: Thomas J. Lynch]&lt;/ref&gt; Donald Monks, Vice Chairman &amp; Chief Administrative Officer, [[The Bank of New York Mellon]];&lt;ref name=&quot;rider.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.rider.edu/139_7397.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Thomas O'Riordan, former CEO of American Sporting Goods Corporation;&lt;ref&gt;[http://people.forbes.com/profile/thomas-o-riordan/46441 Forbes: Thomas O'Riordan]&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Schimek, Senior Vice President &amp; CFO [[American International Group]];&lt;ref name=&quot;rider.edu&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.rider.edu/172_1785.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Ronald Schlosser, chairman &amp; CEO of Haights Cross Communications;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haightscross.com/dyncnt/presstxt.cfm?ID=341 HAIGHTS CROSS COMMUNICATIONS NAMES RONALD SCHLOSSER CHAIRMAN AND CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER]&lt;/ref&gt; John T. Spitznagel, chairman &amp; CEO of Oceana Therapeutics;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oceanatherapeutics.com/exclusive.html#1 Oceana Therapeutics: Management Team: John T. Spitznagel]&lt;/ref&gt; Howard Stoeckel, CEO of [[Wawa (convenience store)|Wawa]]; [[Kenneth Yen]], CEO of [[China Motor Corporation]]; and Meg Walsh, president of [[Medscape|Medscape Consumer]] and internationally-recognized authority in [[e-health]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://investing.businessweek.com/research/stocks/private/person.asp?personId=438289 BusinessWeek: Meg Walsh]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In the field of government, Rider graduates include: [[Nathaniel Barnes]], Liberian Ambassador to the United Nations; [[Frederick W. Donnelly]], former Mayor of Trenton, New Jersey; Robert E. Grossman, Judge on the U.S. Bankruptcy Court for the Eastern District of New York;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.duanemorris.com/pressreleases/pressrelease2803.html Duane Morris Partner Appointed U.S. Bankruptcy Court Judge for the Eastern District of New York]&lt;/ref&gt; David Rousseau, MBA, former [[New Jersey Department of the Treasury|New Jersey State Treasurer]]; and [[Mark S. Schweiker]], MA, [[List of Governors of Pennsylvania|44th Governor]] of [[Pennsylvania]].

* In the field of sports, Rider graduates include: [[Jack Armstrong (baseball player)|Jack Armstrong]], 1990 Major League Baseball (MLB) All-Star and World Champion; [[Al Downing (baseball)|Al Downing]], 1967 MLB All-Star and Strikout Champion, and 1971 MLB Comeback Player of the Year; [[Jeff Kunkel]], professional baseball player; [[Caroline Lind]], MBA, Olympic Gold Medal rower at the [[2008 Summer Olympics]] in Beijing; [[Digger Phelps]], ESPN college basketball analyst and former [[Notre Dame Fighting Irish]] basketball coach; [[Bobby Smith (soccer)|Bobby Smith]], National Soccer Hall of Fame member; and [[Jason Thompson (basketball)|Jason Thompson]], basketball player in the [[NBA]].

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.rider.edu/ Official website]
* [http://comm.rider.edu/ridernews/ ''The Rider News''], Rider University [[student newspaper]]
* [http://comm.rider.edu/run/ Rider University Television Network]
* [http://www.gobroncs.com/ Rider University Athletics]
* http://www.minsocam.org/ammin/AM63/AM63_365.pdf
* http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PRC/v40/i6/p2621_1
* [http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-3360(198603)60%3A2%3C273%3ARTAROS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-D Resistance to and Repair of Shell Breakagade ...] &gt; Journal of Paleontology &gt; Vol. 60, No. 2, Mar., 1986
* http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PRC/v39/i6/p2472_1
* [http://www.zwire.com/site/news.cfm?newsid=12804572&amp;BRD=1697&amp;PAG=461&amp;dept_id=44551&amp;rfi=6 Trentonian.com: Serving Trenton Local News]

{{Colleges and universities in New Jersey}}
{{Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference}}
{{NewJerseysports}}

{{Coord|40.280|-74.738|region:US-NJ_type:edu|display=title}}

[[Category:Rider University]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Mercer County, New Jersey]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in New Jersey]]
[[Category:Westminster Choir College alumni]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1865]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]

[[fr:Université de Rider]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
