<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29563712" ns="0" title="Your Shape"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{italic title}}
'''''Your Shape''''' is a series of games developed by [[Ubisoft]] for several console systems and the PC, focused on body fitness. The game was created in collaboration with [[NASA]] and is also used by them.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

==Your Shape==
[[File:Your Shape featuring Jenny McCarthy.png|left|thumb|200px|''Your Shape'' featuring Jenny McCarthy Bundle Pack - USA]]
The ''Your Shape'' game released for the Wii requires the [[Ubisoft Motion Tracking Camera]] so the game can track the body movement while performing the different exercises. 

''Your Shape'' was released on two different editions, for USA and Europe. The USA version was released as ''Your Shape featuring Jenny McCarthy'' which contains video of Jenny McCarthy telling her experience using the game. There is also the European version of the game that has a different cover and it is available in several languages. 

There are several versions of this game that has different people that recommends the product, and the covers change according to the country:
* USA: [[Jenny McCarthy]]
* Spain: [[Estela Giménez]] (Spanish former rhythmic gymnast)
* Germany: [[Annemarie Warnkross]]
* Italy: [[Maddalena Corvaglia]]
* France: [[Nathalie Simon]]
* Australia: [[Michelle Bridges]]

==''Your Shape &amp;ndash; Fitness Evolved''==
[[File:Xbox-360-Kinect-Standalone.png|thumb|200px|Microsoft Xbox 360 Kinect]]
''Your Shape Fitness Evolved'' is the latest version of this series available for the Xbox 360. It was released on November 4, 2010, and uses [[Microsoft]]'s [[Kinect]] sensor device. Users control the game using their voice and body movements. The game includes workouts created by ''[[Men's Health (magazine)|Men's Health]]'' and ''[[Women’s Health (magazine)|Women's Health]]'' magazine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yourshapegame.us.ubi.com/|on|title=UbiSoft ''Your Shape Fitness Evolved''|date=2010-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two DLC packs have been released named, ''The Toned Body Program'' and ''Cardio Boxing Platinum''. Eleven More DLC packs are planned for 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.joystiq.com/2010/11/24/your-shape-getting-12-different-dlc-packs-first-due-in-early-d/|title=''Your Shape'' getting 12 Different DLC Packs - First Due in 'early December'|date=2010-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; with the third pack coming in January 2011.

Ubisoft runs a website that keeps track of your progress online, allows you to share your progress with friends, and to set goals and challenge your friends.  Setting up a uPlay account with Ubisoft is needed to unlock some content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yourshapegame.us.ubi.com/|on|title=UbiSoft ''Your Shape Fitness Evolved''|date=2011-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A sequel was announced at E3 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yourshapegame.us.ubi.com/your-shape-fitness-evolved-2012-features|title=''Your Shape Fitness Evolved 2012''}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==

{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://yourshapegame.us.ubi.com/ ''Your Shape'' official site]
* [http://www.nintendo.com/games/detail/kWaDeezcH80LHKNQW5AcuaOxTTipXuNJ ''Your Shape'' Nintendo page]
* [http://www.gamespot.com/wii/sim/yourshape/index.html ''Your Shape''] at GameSpot

[[Category:Wii games]]
[[Category:Ubisoft]]
[[Category:2009 video games]]
[[Category:Dance video games]]
[[Category:Kinect games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the United States]]
[[Category:Xbox 360 games]]
[[Category:Windows games]]


{{videogame-stub}}

[[es:Your Shape]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
