<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29576763" ns="0" title="Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{ infobox library
| library_name       = Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library &lt;br&gt; [[University of Montana]]
| name_en            = 
| library_logo       = 
| image              =Mansfiel Library Entrance.JPG
| caption            =The entrance to the Mansfield Library on the north side of the building.
| country            = USA
| type               = [[Academic library]]
| scope              = 
| established        = 1895
| ref_legal_mandate  = 
| location           = [[Missoula, Montana]] &lt;br&gt; [[University of Montana]]
| coordinates        = 
| branch_of          = 
| num_branches       = 
| items_collected    = 
| collection_size    = 1.5 million volumes
| criteria           = 
| legal_deposit      = Federal Depository Library &lt;br&gt; Regional Depository Library for Montana
| req_to_access      = 
| annual_circulation = 
| pop_served         = 
| members            = 
| budget             = 
| director           = Fritz Snyder (Interim)
| num_employees      = 
| website            = www.lib.umt.edu
| phone_num          = (406) 243-6866  
| references         = 
}} 

The '''Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library''' is the campus library for students at the [[University of Montana]] in [[Missoula, Montana]]. The five-story library, which is located on the east side of the UM campus,  was finished in 1978, funded by the [[U.S. Department of Commerce]]. In 1979, it was dedicated to Ambassador [[Mike Mansfield]] and his wife Maureen.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lib.umt.edu/history&lt;/ref&gt; The library is home to the earliest authorized edition of the [[Lewis and Clark]] journals.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.umt.edu/urelations/mainhall/1102/journals.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The University of Montana library was established in 1895, two years after the establishment of the [[University of Montana]].  The library was temporarily housed in the old Willard School on Sixth Street in Missoula before a permanent structure was built on the UM campus. After one year at the old Willard School, library holdings totaled at 1,369 volumes, 19 periodicals, and 20 newspapers.  

Today, the library features state-of-the-art electronic access to information. It is a Federal Government Depository Collection and has an extensive Maps Collection.

==Location==
The University of Montana library has moved several times as the collection size expanded beyond the location's available capacity.  Note:(The current names of the buildings are listed here.)
*1895 - old Willard School
*1899 - [[Buildings_at_the_University_of_Montana#University_Hall|University Hall]]
*1908 - [[Buildings at the University of Montana#University Library 1908-1923 (Rankin Hall)|Jeannette Rankin Hall]]
** library designated as a depository for government documents
*1921 - [[Buildings at the University of Montana#University Library 1922-1974 (Social Science Building)|Social Science Building]]
*1974 - Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library
** construction completed in 1978

==About the Library==
The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library has the largest library collection of books and media in [[Montana]] and comprises the heart of The University of Montana’s library system. Collections exceed 1.5 million volumes, 125,000 maps, 100,000 archival photographs, 77,000 electronic books, 50,000 media items, 12,000 theses, dissertations and graduate professional papers, and over 11,000 linear feet of archival manuscripts. It also houses more than 5,000 rare and valuable books.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc/aboutus&lt;/ref&gt; Combined collections within the Montana Public Access Catalog of the Affiliated Libraries of The University of Montana exceed 1.9 million volumes. Over the last 10 years, the Mansfield Library has greatly increased access to electronic journal literature and now has over 30,000 print and [[electronic journal]]s and hundreds of [[electronic database]]s.

The library has roughly 100 computer workstations for students, staff and faculty, and has seven for the general public.  There are 64 staff and faculty members, and nearly 100 student workers. The library takes up roughly five acres.

==Mansfield Center==

The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Center of the Mansfield Library is dedicated to improving understanding of Asia, U.S. foreign relations, and ethics and public affairs.

&quot;The Center houses programs that embody the core interests and characteristics of Senator Mansfield's career, namely, Modern Asian Affairs and Ethics in Public Affairs. The Center has broadened its original focus on East and Northeast Asia to include South and Southeast Asia, an evolution that reflects growing American interests in these sub-regions of a dynamic continent with ever-growing links to the United States.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.umt.edu/mansfield/ Mansfield Center]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mansfield Center also works closely with The [[Maureen and Mike Mansfield Foundation]] (est. 1983) to &quot;promote understanding and cooperation among the nations and peoples of Asia and the United States.&quot;  The Foundation maintains offices in Washington, D.C.; Tokyo, Japan; Missoula, Montana; and a joint office in Beijing, China, with The Maureen and Mike Mansfield Center at The University of Montana.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mansfieldfdn.org/ Mansfield Foundation]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Hours of Operation==

* Monday-Thursday: 7 a.m. - 1 a.m.
* Friday: 7 a.m. - 8 p.m.
* Saturday: 10 a.m. - 8 p.m.
* Sunday: 10 a.m. - 1 a.m.

==Affiliates==
* [[University of Montana College of Technology|College of Technology of The University of Montana]]
* [[Montana Tech of the University of Montana]]
* [[Helena College of Technology|The University of Montana-Helena College of Technology]]
* The University of Montana Jameson Law Library
* [[University of Montana Western]]

== References ==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.lib.umt.edu/default.php/ Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library website]
* [http://www.umt.edu/law/library/ William J. Jameson Law Library]
* [http://my.umwestern.edu/library/ Montana Western Library]
* [http://umhelena.edu/library/default.aspx UM Helena COT Library]
* [http://www.mtech.edu/library/   Montana Tech Library]

{{University of Montana}}

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

{{coord missing|Montana}}

[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Buildings and facilities of the University of Montana]]
[[Category:Research at the University of Montana]]
[[Category:University and college academic libraries in the United States]]
[[Category:Federal depository libraries]]
[[Category:Libraries in Montana]]
[[Category:Research libraries]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Missoula County, Montana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
