<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29638619" ns="0" title="Wright-Bellanca WB-2"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
 | name=Wright-Bellanca WB-2 Columbia
 | image=Image:Bellanca wb 2.jpg
 | caption=Transatlantic flight 4th - 6th June 1927 from New York to Eisleben in Germany
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
 | type=Passenger
 | national origin=[[United States of America]]
 | manufacturer=[[Wright Aeronautical]]
 | designer=[[Giuseppe Mario Bellanca]]
 | first flight=1926
 | introduced=1926 [[National Air Races]]
 | retired=
 | status=
 | primary user=
 | more users= &lt;!--Limited to three in total; separate using &lt;br /&gt; --&gt;
 | produced= &lt;!--years in production--&gt;
 | number built=1
 | program cost= &lt;!--Total program cost--&gt;
 | unit cost=$15,000 (1927)&lt;!--Incremental or flyaway cost for military or retail price for commercial aircraft--&gt;
 | developed from=Wright-Bellanca WB-1
 | variants with their own articles=
*[[Bellanca CF]]
*[[Bellanca CH-200]]
*[[Bellanca CH-300]]
*[[Bellanca CH-400]]

}}
|}

The '''Wright-Bellanca WB-2''', named ''Columbia'', ''Miss Columbia'', and later ''Maple Leaf'', was the second in a series of aircraft designed by [[Giuseppe Mario Bellanca]], initially for [[Wright Aeronautical]] then later [[Columbia Aircraft Corp]].

==Development==
[[Image:Wright J-5 Whirlwind.JPG|100px|right|thumb|Wright-Whirlwind J-5]]
In 1925, [[Clarence Duncan Chamberlin]] was friends with, and worked as chief test pilot for, the aircraft designer [[Giuseppe Mario Bellanca]]. A flight instructor in WWI, Clarence was an early customer of Bellanca designs, purchasing the only [[Bellanca CE]] built when he was working for the [[Maryland Pressed Steel Company]]. Through Clarence, Bellanca secured a position as a consultant for the [[Wright Aeronautical]] company to produce an 5-6 passenger aircraft to demonstrate their new [[Wright R-790|Wright Whirlwind J-4 Engine]]. Bellanca built an all wood aircraft, the [[Wright-Bellanca WB-1|WB-1]] in 1926 which crashed at Curtiss Field in an attempt on the world non-refueled endurance record. The WB-2 follow-on aircraft, was made of fabric covered steel tubing was already in development to test the updated [[Wright R-790|Wright Whirlwind J-5]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RS&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Lindbergh of Canada: the Erroll Boyd story|author=Ross Smyth}}&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft had some features intended for long-distance overseas flights built in. The landing gear was able to be dropped, to prevent flipping in a water landing. Once on the water, the large gas tanks could provide floatation, and a saw was carried to drop the dead engine weight if needed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Aircraft Bellanca Columbia WB-2|url=http://www.suite101.de/content/erster-nonstop-flug-von-new-york-nach-deutschland-im-juni-1927-a99991|accessdate=13 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- ==Design== may be combined with above as &quot;Design and development&quot; --&gt;

==Operational history==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Thebestofthejun.jpg|100px|right|thumb|G.M. Bellanca]] --&gt;
[[Image:Woolaroc - Lindbergh Atlantiküberflug.jpg|100px|right|thumb|Lindbergh trumps Levine]]

The WB-2 Columbia was introduced at the 1926 [[National Air Races]] flown by Lieut C.C. Champion where it won both efficiency records.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bellanca Achievements|url=http://www.friendsofbellanca.org/Achievements.htm|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Wright Aeronautical chose to continue to develop the Whirlwind engine, but discontinue aircraft operations to avoid competition in profitable engine sales with rival aircraft manufacturers. Bellanca left Wright Aeronautical, with the rights to the WB-2, and the WB-2 prototype purchased for $15,500 and formed a new interest, [[Columbia Aircraft Corp|Columbia Aircraft Company]], with the investor [[Charles Levine]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=GIUSEPPE MARIO &quot;GM&quot; BELLANCA|url=http://www.friendsofbellanca.org/GMBellanca.htm|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Levine became a millionaire at the young age of twenty eight by reselling surplus armaments to the United States government. When partnering with Bellanca, he had plans to put the WB-2 in production. The plans never came through, and the aircraft would not see production until Bellanca manufactured an updated version with his own company later in 1928.

*

*'''Endurance record'''  Bellanca and Levine felt that the Columbia could beat the current world record for endurance held by [[Flight endurance record|Maurice Drouhin]] and [[Flight endurance record|Landry Jules]] in France. Leigh wade, a pilot of the 1924 Round the world flight in a [[Douglas World Cruiser]] was hired for publicity but soon quit in disagreements with Levine. [[Bertrand Blanchard Acosta|Bert Acosta]] was brought on as his replacement.  On April 12, 1927  [[Clarence Duncan Chamberlin|Clarence Chamberlin]] and [[Bertrand Blanchard Acosta|Bert Acosta]] set off on their endurance attempt. The aircraft was predicted to crash by Curtiss engineers, but took off in only 1200 feet of runway.&lt;ref name=&quot;RS&quot;/&gt; They stayed aloft over Roosevelt field in New York City for 51 hours, 11 minutes, and 25 seconds. The estimated distance flown was 4,100 miles, which was 500 more than was needed for the Ortieg Prize attempt between [[New York, New York]] and [[Paris, France]].

Shortly after the record flight, on April 24, 1927 the WB-2 was christened in prohibition era Ginger Ale the &quot;Columbia&quot; by Levine's 8 year old daughter. Later that day, Chamberlin safely landed the plane with two children on board with a broken landing gear.&lt;ref name=&quot;RS&quot;/&gt;

*'''Missed opportunity with Lindbergh''' In late 1926, an enterprising [[Charles Lindbergh]] had convinced [[Earl Thompson (executive)|Earl Thompson]], and [[Albert Bond Lambert|Major Albert Bond Lambert]] to back him on an attempt to win the $25,000 [[Orteig Prize]] for a non-stop transatlantic flight. He specifically wanted a single pilot, and a single engine to reduce weight and chances of failure. The ideal plane was the Wright-Bellanca WB-2. Lindbergh set out by train to New York in a new suit to look professional for a face-to-face meeting with Columbia Aircraft to buy the only WB-2. In the meeting, Levine said the aircraft was worth $25,000, but would discount it to $15,000 due to the free publicity that would be made from the flight, well above Lindbergh's $2000 budget. Lindbergh returned to St. Louis, and had a check signed to him personally for $15,000 and a request to name the WB-2 &quot;The Spirit of St. Louis&quot;. Lindbergh said he would have the plane back in St. Louis in a week.

The second meeting in New York was attended by Levine, Bellanca, and Chamberlin. With check in hand, Levine added a stipulation that Columbia Aircraft would select the crew on the flight, which Lindbergh objected to. Reminding Lindbergh that the WB-2 was the only plane that could make the flight at the time, they made him leave and call back the next day to reconsider. The terms did not change, and Lindbergh returned to St. Louis without an airplane.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Spirit of St. Louis|author=Charles A. Lindbergh, Reeve Lindbergh}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lindbergh then approached [[Travel Air|Travel Air Manufacturing Company]], asking for a [[Travel Air 5000]] modified with a Wright Whirlwind motor and was declined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tom D. Crouch&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Wings: a history of aviation from kites to the space age|author=Tom D. Crouch}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lindbergh also inquired what it would cost to buy a [[Fokker]] for the attempt, he was given a quote of $100,000 for a custom [[Fokker Trimotor|trimotor]], and was told that Fokker would not build a single engine craft for a transatlantic flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Flight of the Century: Charles Lindbergh and the Rise of American Aviation|author=Thomas Kessner}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lindbergh instead purchased a single place aircraft from Ryan aircraft, the [[Spirit of St. Louis]] for $6000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Giuseppe Mario Bellanca&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title= Giuseppe Mario Bellanca|url=http://www.nasm.si.edu/research/arch/findaids/bellanca/gmb_sec_3.html|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Orteig Prize attempt'''  Prior to the crossing, Levine planned on using Clarence Chamberlin or [[Bert Acosta]] as pilot with [[Lloyd W. Bertaud]] as copilot. The pilots were promised a settlement to their wives if they crashed, and the prize money if they completed the flight, but Levine refused to sign the document before the flight.  Bertaud first objected, then later offered to purchase the Columbia for himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The spectacle of flight: aviation and the Western imagination, 1920-1950|author=Robert Wohl}}&lt;/ref&gt; Levine bumped Bertaud from the copilot position, prompting an injunction preventing any Ortieg record flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Giuseppe Mario Bellanca&quot;/&gt; Lindbergh arrived on May 5, 1927. While Chamberlin waited for the injunction to be lifted, His other competition, [[Richard Evelyn Byrd|Admiral Byrd's]] team was repairing his Fokker C-2 Trimotor, the &quot;[[America (aircraft)|America]]&quot; after a practice run crash.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tom D. Crouch&quot;/&gt; On May 20–21, 1927, Lindbergh left [[Roosevelt Field, New York|Roosevelt Field]] and crossing the Atlantic, while leaving the 'Columbia' and 'Atlantic' behind at the adjacent [[Curtiss Field]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Bellanca Aircraft|url=http://www.centennialofflight.gov/essay/GENERAL_AVIATION/bellanca/GA1.htm|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''First transatlantic flight of the Columbia''' The Brooklyn chamber of commerce also offered $15,000 for a tranatlantic challenge. Chamberlin was given the piloting job, and picked [[Bernt Balchen]] as his co-pilot. Balchen was unavailable, so Chamberlin's wife was offered the seat for the attempt, only to be displaced by the flight's backer, Levine. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Clarence D. Chamberlin Recalls Historic Flight, Explains Why Lindbergh Beat Levine Across Atlantic|url=http://yiddishradioproject.org/exhibits/levine/chamberlin.php3?pg=1|accessdate=13 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 4, 1927 The Columbia took off on its transatlantic flight from America to [[Berlin, Germany]] with Charles Levine, as the first passenger to cross the Atlantic in an airplane, and making the Columbia the second plane to fly non-stop across the [[Atlantic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|newspaper=The News Journal|title=Delaware's Flying Machines|author=RICK MULROONEY|date=October 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an oft-repeated situation, Levine told his wife he was just going up for a test flight. His lawyer notified her by a letter of his intentions after they took off and kept going.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Conquest of the Atlantic: pioneer flights 1919-1939
|author=Phil Munson}}&lt;/ref&gt; At one point in the flight, Levine was at the controls flying at 20,000 feet [[Hypoxia (medical)|without oxygen]]. He entered a spin, and descended to 4,000 feet before recovering. The Columbia did not reach Berlin, but landed 100 miles short in a field at [[Eisleben, Germany]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Giuseppe Mario Bellanca&quot;/&gt; The flight covered 3,905 miles (6,285&amp;nbsp;km) and 42 hours and 45 minutes. The trip was 315 miles (507&amp;nbsp;km) and 9 hours and 6 minutes longer than Lindergh's transatlantic crossing&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=WB-2|url=http://1000aircraftphotos.com/HistoryBriefs/WrightBellancaWB2.htm|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''The Queen of Diamonds''' While Levine in Europe, [[Mabel Boll]] &quot;the Queen of Diamonds&quot; attempted to get Levine to fly her to America in the Columbia, which was still in France after a record setting flight from New York. The inexperinced owner of the aircraft, Levine had plans to fly it back to America with a French pilot, [[Maurice Drouhin]]. After disagreements with Droughin and Lawyers left the plane guarded and grounded. Levine took off to England claiming he was just testing the engine. Boll followed Levine to England by boat, talking Levine into letting her be a passenger. Just before the flight, Levine's new pilot Capt. Hinchcliffe, publicly refused to let Boll fly along, and instead flew to [[Rome, Italy]] dropping a present to [[Benito Mussolini]]'s son. Boll was invited to try a East-west flight from America, and she set out for New York by boat in January 1928.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=East to the dawn: the life of Amelia Earhart|author=Susan Butler}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 30, 1927 Bellanca left Columbia aircraft, to form [[Bellanca Aircraft Corporation of America|AviaBellanca Aircraft]], taking with him again the rights to the WB-2 series of aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= history in the making: 80 turbulent years in the American general aviation|author=Donald M. Pattillo|ISBN=9780070494480}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Non-stop flight to Cuba''' On March 5, 1928 [[Wilmer Stultz]], O.Le Boutilier, and [[Mabel Boll]] on a improvised seat made the first non-stop flight in the Columbia between [[New York, New York]] and [[Havana, Cuba]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-2&quot;/&gt; Mabell was soon turned down again to fly the Atlantic in the Columbia by Levine. Undeterred, She publicly announced she had hired Stultz, and was going to make the attempt. Stultz abandoned the project, and Boll attempted to recruit Admiral Byrd's Fokker for the flight. She was passed over the opportunity by the much less flamboyant, and capable Amelia Earhart. Levine and Boll eventually partnered again, this time with competition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=East to the Dawn The Life of Amelia Earhart|author=Susan Butler}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''Another missed opportunity - first female across the Atlantic attempt''' On June 26, 1928 Mabel Boll was filmed leaving [[Roosevelt Field]] in the newly re-named &quot;Miss Columbia&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=MABEL BOLL IN RACE TO FLY OVER ATLANTIC|url=http://service.nfo.ac.uk/purl/article/0005-0003-3546-0000-0-0000-0000-0|accessdate=18 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The Sound of Wings: The Life of Amelia Earhart|author=Mary S. Lovell}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mabel was later spotted in [[Harbour Grace, Newfoundland]] as a passenger in the Columbia, piloted by [[Oliver Colin LeBoutillier|Captain Oliver C. Le Boutillier]] and [[Arthur Argles]]. While Boll publicly announced aspiration to be the first woman to fly across the Atlantic, [[Amelia Earhart]] was also in Newfoundland at the same time, and the German [[Thea Rasche]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Mabel Boll|url=http://www.ctie.monash.edu.au/hargrave/boll.html|accessdate=18 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The newspapers was focused their attention on the aspirations of “the Diamond Queen of Broadway,” Preparations for the trip were done with full publicity. At the same time in relative secrecy, pilots, [[Wilmer Stultz]] and Gordon, were believed by the press to be preparing Byrd’s Fokker “Friendship” for his planned trip to the South Pole.  Stultz himself was planned to be the pilot of the Columbia, and defected to Byrds crew.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|magazine=The New Yorker|title=Missing Woman Amelia Earhart’s flight|author=Judith Thurman|date=September 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On June 17 the [[Fokker F.VII|“Friendship”]] took off from the bay at [[Trepassey|Trepassey, Newfoundland]] with Earhart on board, while the crew of the Columbia were grounded for 5 days due to the weather.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|magazine=This World, Vol. 2, No. 21 San Francisco Chronicle|date=September 11, 1938}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon learning of successful flight by Earhart and crew, Bolls returned to America in the Columbia, donating $500 to the Newfoundland airstrip for development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Columbia A Little Competition for Miss Earhart|url=http://www.hrgrace.ca/air.html|accessdate=18 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1929 the Columbia  placed second in a race from New York to [[California]] piloted by Commander John Iseman, Leuit. J Farnum. 

*'''Bermuda Record''' On June 29, 1930 the Columbia performed the first non-stop flight from New York to [[Bermuda]] and back. The flight dropped off mail, but there was not a suitable landing field on the island at the time. The flight was piloted by [[Erroll Boyd]], [[Roger Q. Williams]], and [[Harry P. Conner]] took 17 hours, 3 minutes. Williams relocated the Columbia to Montreal just two days before a hangar fire destroyed Columbia Airlines newest plane, the underperforming &quot;Uncle Sam&quot;. 

[[Image:Sperry Horizon.jpg|100px|thumb|A Sperry Horizon]]
*'''Second transatlantic flight''' The Columbia was flown to Toronto, renamed &quot;The Maple Leaf&quot; after the song &quot;[[The Maple Leaf Forever]]&quot;. The plane was then demonstrated at the 1930 [[Canadian National Exhibition]]. The aircraft had a early [[Sperry Corporation|Sperry]] [[Attitude indicator]] installed, taken out of [[Jimmy Doolittle]]'s [[Lockheed Vega]]. Pilot Roger Q. Williams, held up the flight for three weeks with legal disputes with Levine over back pay. On October 9, 1930 the Maple Leaf performed the first transatlantic flight by a Canadian between [[Harbour Grace Airport|Canada]] and [[London, England]] in 36 hours, 10 minutes. The aircraft was piloted by [[Erroll Boyd]], and Harry P. Conner, who travelled with $18 in their pockets and a unpaid Toronto Hotel bill. Upon arrival they flew a tribute flight in honor of the [[R101|R-101 crash]] victims.

*'''New York to Haiti non-stop''' In 1933 the Maple Leaf performed the first non-stop flight from New York to [[Haiti]] in 24 hours and 8 minutes. The pilots were Erroll Boyd, Robert G. Lyon, and a passenger, H.P. Davis. On June 7, 1933 the Maple Leaf left [[Port-au-Prince|Port-Au-Prince, Haiti]] non-stop to [[Washington D.C.]] with a special issue stamp. The aircraft was piloted by Erroll Boyd, and Robert G. Lyon.

The Maple Leaf was destroyed January 25, 1934 in a hangar fire at the Bellanca factory in [[Newcastle, Delaware]].&lt;ref name=&quot;WB-2&quot;/&gt;

===Artifacts===

*A [[Bellanca CH-400]] painted to resemble the WB-2 Columbia is on display at the [[Virginia Aviation Museum]].
*The Smithsonian [[National Air and Space Museum]] has in its collection an embossed aluminum ashtray made from the metal of the fuel tanks or the Columbia after the fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ashtray, Wright-Bellanca WB-2|url=http://www.nasm.si.edu/collections/artifact.cfm?id=A19610015000|accessdate=17 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A block of four stamps carried on the first transatlantic trip from Canada to England in the Columbia was valued at $20,000 in 1995. &lt;ref name=&quot;RS&quot;/&gt;

==Variants==

;Wright-Bellanca WB-1
:The all-wood forerunner to the WB-2, Using a Wright Whirlwind J-4
;Wright-Bellanca WB-2
:The record setting ''Columbia'', (later ''Maple Leaf'') developed from the WB-1

&lt;!-- ==Units using this aircraft/Operators (choose)== --&gt;

==Specifications (Wright-Bellanca WB-2) ==
{{Aircraft specs
|ref=Avistar, The Lindbergh of Canada: the Erroll Boyd story&lt;!-- for giving the reference for the data --&gt;
|prime units?=kts&lt;!-- imp or kts first for US aircraft, and UK aircraft pre-metrification, met(ric) first for all others. You MUST choose a format, or no specifications will show --&gt;
&lt;!--
        General characteristics
--&gt;
|genhide=
|crew=
|capacity=6
|length m=
|length ft=26
|length in=9
|length note=
|span m=
|span ft=
|span in=
|span note=
|upper span m=
|upper span ft=46
|upper span in=4
|upper span note=
|mid span m=
|mid span ft=
|mid span in=
|mid span note=
|lower span m=
|lower span ft=
|lower span in=
|lower span note=
|swept m=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept ft=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept in=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept note=
|dia m=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|dia ft=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|dia in=&lt;!-- airships etc --&gt;
|dia note=
|width m=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|width ft=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|width in=&lt;!-- if applicable --&gt;
|width note=
|height m=
|height ft=
|height in=
|height note=
|wing area sqm=
|wing area sqft=272
|wing area note=
|swept area sqm=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept area sqft=&lt;!-- swing-wings --&gt;
|swept area note=
|volume m3=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|volume ft3=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|volume note=
|aspect ratio=&lt;!-- give where relevant eg sailplanes  --&gt;
|airfoil=
|empty weight kg=
|empty weight lb=1850
|empty weight note=
|gross weight kg=
|gross weight lb=
|gross weight note=
|max takeoff weight kg=
|max takeoff weight lb=5400
|max takeoff weight note=
|fuel capacity=502
|lift kg=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|lift lb=&lt;!-- lighter-than-air --&gt;
|lift note=
|more general=
&lt;!--
        Powerplant
--&gt;
|eng1 number=1
|eng1 name=[[Wright R-790|Wright Whirlwind J-5]]
|eng1 type=
|eng1 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng1 hp=220&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng1 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng1 lbf=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng1 note=
|power original=
|thrust original=
|eng1 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng1 lbf-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng2 number=
|eng2 name=
|eng2 type=
|eng2 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng2 hp=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng2 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng2 lbf=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng2 note=
|eng2 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng2 lbf-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng3 number=
|eng3 name=
|eng3 type=
|eng3 kw=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng3 hp=&lt;!-- prop engines --&gt;
|eng3 kn=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng3 lbf=&lt;!-- jet/rocket engines --&gt;
|eng3 note=
|eng3 kn-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|eng3 lbf-ab=&lt;!-- afterburners --&gt;
|more power=
|prop blade number=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop name=
|prop dia m=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop dia ft=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop dia in=&lt;!-- propeller aircraft --&gt;
|prop note=
|rot number=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia m=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia ft=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot dia in=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot area sqm=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot area sqft=&lt;!-- helicopters --&gt;
|rot area note=
&lt;!--
        Performance
--&gt;
|perfhide=
|max speed kmh=
|max speed mph=126
|max speed kts=
|max speed note=
|max speed mach=&lt;!-- supersonic aircraft --&gt;
|cruise speed kmh=
|cruise speed mph=105
|cruise speed kts=
|cruise speed note=
|stall speed kmh=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|stall speed mph=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|stall speed kts=
|stall speed note=
|never exceed speed kmh=
|never exceed speed mph=
|never exceed speed kts=
|never exceed speed note=
|minimum control speed kmh=
|minimum control speed mph=
|minimum control speed kts=
|minimum control speed note=
|range km=
|range miles=
|range nmi=
|range note=
|combat range km=
|combat range miles=
|combat range nmi=
|combat range note=
|ferry range km=
|ferry range miles=
|ferry range nmi=
|ferry range note=
|endurance=&lt;!-- if range unknown --&gt;
|ceiling m=
|ceiling ft=13000
|ceiling note=
|g limits=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|roll rate=&lt;!-- aerobatic --&gt;
|glide ratio=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|climb rate ms=
|climb rate ftmin=
|climb rate note=
|time to altitude=
|sink rate ms=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|sink rate ftmin=&lt;!-- sailplanes --&gt;
|sink rate note=
|lift to drag=
|wing loading kg/m2
|wing loading lb/sqft=
|wing loading note=
|disk loading kg/m2=
|disk loading lb/sqft=
|disk loading note=
|power/mass=
|thrust/weight=
|more performance=
&lt;!--
        Armament
--&gt;
|armament=&lt;!-- add (bulleted list) here or if you want to use the following specific parameters, remove this parameter--&gt;
|guns= 
|bombs= 
|rockets= 
|missiles= 
|hardpoints=
|hardpoint capacity=
|hardpoint rockets=
|hardpoint missiles=
|hardpoint bombs=
|hardpoint other=
|other armament= 
|avionics=
}}

&lt;!-- ==See also== --&gt;
{{aircontent
&lt;!-- include as many lines are appropriate. additional lines/entries with carriage return. --&gt;
|see also=
|related=&lt;!-- related developments --&gt;
|similar aircraft=&lt;!-- similar or comparable aircraft --&gt;
|lists=&lt;!-- related lists --&gt;
}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
&lt;!-- insert the reference sources here --&gt;
*{{cite web|title=WB-2|url=http://1000aircraftphotos.com/HistoryBriefs/WrightBellancaWB2.htm|accessdate=17 November 2010}}
{{refend}}
&lt;!-- ==Further reading== --&gt;
&lt;!-- ==External links== --&gt;

&lt;!-- Navboxes go here --&gt;

{{Aviation lists}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wright-Bellanca Wb-2}}
[[Category:United States civil utility aircraft 1920–1929]]
[[Category:Bellanca aircraft]]
[[Category:Single-engine aircraft]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
