<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29659751" ns="0" title="Young Sherlock Holmes (books)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the 1985 film|Young Sherlock Holmes}}
{{Infobox Novel series
| name = Young Sherlock Holmes
| books = [[Death Cloud]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Red Leech]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Young Sherlock Holmes: Black Ice|Black Ice]]&lt;br /&gt;Fire Storm
| image =  
| image_caption =  
| author = [[Andy Lane]]
| country = United Kingdom
| language = English
| genre = [[Thriller (genre)|Thriller]], [[Spy fiction]]
| publisher = [[Macmillan Books]] (UK)
| pub_date = 4 June 2010 – Ongoing
| media_type = Print ([[hardcover]] and [[paperback]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Audiobook]]
}}
'''''Young Sherlock Holmes''''' is a series of [[Young-adult fiction|young adult]] [[Thriller (genre)|Thriller novels]] by [[Andy Lane]] featuring [[Arthur Conan Doyle]]'s detective [[Sherlock Holmes]] as a teenager in the 1860s

==Books in the series==
So far there have been four books released in the series, with potentially nine in total.

* ''[[Death Cloud]]'' (June 2010): Fourteen-year-old Sherlock Holmes is sent to live with his Aunt and Uncle in Hampshire and teams up with Matty Arnatt to investigate two mysterious deaths which appear to be somehow related to a black cloud.

* ''[[Red Leech]]'' (November 2010): A few months after the events of the first novel, Holmes investigates the possibility that John Wilkes Booth is alive and well, and living in England. The investigation takes Sherlock to America with his tutor, Amyus Crowe.

* ''[[Young Sherlock Holmes: Black Ice|Black Ice]]'' (June 2011): Mycroft invites Sherlock and his tutor to London for a visit, but when they arrive at the Diogenes Club they find Mycroft with a dagger in his hand and a dead body on the floor. The adventure takes them from the depths of the London sewers to the frozen Russian landscapes.

* ''Fire Storm'' (November 2011): Fourteen-year-old Sherlock has come up against some challenges in his time, but what confronts him now is completely baffling. His tutor, Crowe, and Crowe's daughter, Ginny, have vanished. Their house looks as if nobody has ever lived there.

==Background==
Based on the success of [[Charlie Higson]]'s bestselling [[Young Bond]] series, the estate of Sir Arthur Conan Doyle authorised a series of books detailing the life of the teenage Sherlock Holmes'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alison Flood |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2009/mar/18/young-sherlock-holmes-macmillan |title=&quot;Macmillan reveals adventures of young Sherlock Holmes&quot;: 18 March 2009 |publisher=The Guardian |date= |accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Proposal&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youngsherlock.com/behind-the-scenes/original-ideaproposal/ |title=Young Sherlock Holmes Official Site: Andy Lane's Original Proposal for the series |publisher=Youngsherlock.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One of Andy Lane's key aims is to explain some of the complexities of Holmes' character, who is scientific and analytical on the one hand, and artistic and moody on the other. Two new characters introduced in this series, his two tutors, Amyus Crowe and Rufus Stone, will help shed light on the formation of the two sides of his character evident in later life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Proposal&quot;/&gt;

Further titles in the series may include;&lt;ref name=&quot;Proposal&quot;/&gt;
* '''The Giant Rat of Sumatra''' (mentioned in [[The Adventure of the Sussex Vampire]])
* '''The Remarkable Worm Unknown to Science''' (mentioned in [[The Problem of Thor Bridge]])
* '''Colonel Warburton’s Madness''' (mentioned in [[The Adventure of the Engineer's Thumb]])
* '''The Segregation of the Queen''' (mentioned in [[His Last Bow (story)|His Last Bow]], but also the sub-title of [[Laurie R. King]]'s first Sherlock Holmes/[[Mary Russell (fictional)|Mary Russell]] book, ''[[The Beekeeper's Apprentice]]: Or On the Segregation of the Queen''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://us.macmillan.com/thebeekeepersapprentice |title=MacMillian Page on The Beekeeper's Apprentice |publisher=Us.macmillan.com |date=2009-12-04 |accessdate=2010-12-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

==Reception==
''[[Chicago Tribune]]'' gave ''Death Cloud'' a positive review stating:

{{quote|For a reader who has outgrown the Hardy Boys' adventures but still seeks mystery-solving plots, Andrew Lane's invention of a teenage Sherlock Holmes will seem timely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Mary Harris Russell |title=&quot;Death Cloud&quot; by Andrew Lane |url=http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2011-03-07/entertainment/chi-books-kids-review-death-cloud-lane_1_sherlock-holmes-death-cloud-mysterious-death |quote= |work=[[Chicago Tribune]] |date=March 7, 2011 |accessdate=March 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Graham Moore, author of ''[[The Sherlockian]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Janet Maslin |title=A Sherlock Holmes Tale That’s Hardly Elementary |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/16/books/16book.html |quote= |work=[[New York Times]] |date=December 15, 2010 |accessdate=March 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; reviewed ''Death Cloud'' for ''[[The New York Times]]'' and stated:

{{quote|Lane is attempting a curious feat: to update and adapt Sherlock Holmes for a new generation, much the way Guy Ritchie has done with a swashbuckling Sherlock on screen....Yet, in the end, the novel strives to rescue Holmes from the prejudices of his creator, and thereby expand the pool of Holmes devotees. For that we can all be grateful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Graham Moore |title=The Teenage Sherlock Holmes |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/13/books/review/childrens-books-death-cloud-by-andrew-lane.html |quote= |work=[[New York Times]] |date=March 11, 2011  |accessdate=March 16, 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.youngsherlock.com/ Official Young Sherlock Holmes site] (U.K.)
* [http://www.youngsherlockseries.com Official Young Sherlock Holmes series site] (U.S.)

{{DEFAULTSORT:Young Sherlock Holmes (Books)}}
[[Category:Victorian era]]
[[Category:Young Sherlock Holmes book series]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
