<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="29765363" ns="0" title="Hugo Gutmann"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=December 2010}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Hugo Gutmann
|birth_date= 19 November 1880
|death_date= 1971 (aged 90)
|image=[[File:GMann1917.jpg|195px]]
|caption=
|nickname=
|birth_place=[[Nuremberg]],  [[German Empire]]&lt;br/&gt;(now [[Germany]])
|death_place=[[United States of America|United States]]
|allegiance={{flagicon|German Empire}} [[German Empire]]
|branch=[[Artillery]] Branch, [[German Army (German Empire)|German Army]]
|serviceyears=1902-1919
|rank=[[Lieutenant|Leutnant]]
|unit=Regiment &quot;List&quot;
|commands=16th Bavarian Reserve Regiment
|battles=
|awards=[[Iron Cross]]&lt;br&gt;(First and Second Class)
|relations=
|laterwork=
}}
'''Hugo Gutmann''' (1880–1971) was a [[Germans|German]]-[[Jewish]] veteran of [[World War I]] who is famously known as [[Adolf Hitler]]'s superior officer during the war, as well as the man responsible for recommending Hitler for the award of the [[Iron Cross]].

==Early Life and Army career==

Gutmann was born on November 19, 1880 in [[Nuremberg]].  In 1902, Gutmann joined the [[Bavarian Army]] and had risen to the rank of ''[[Feldwebel]]'' by 1904, at which time he was transferred to the reserves.  When World War I began in 1914, Gutmann was recalled and soon after he joined the Regiment &quot;List&quot;. On April 15, 1915, he was promoted to [[Lieutenant]] (''Leutnant''), and appointed as a Company Commander and Acting Adjutant for the Regiment's artillery battalion. 

Throughout most of 1918, from January 29 to August 31, Gutmann served as Adolf Hitler's direct superior.  Gutmann later lobbied for Hitler's award of the Iron Cross First Class (an award typically reserved for commissioned officers), and the decoration was presented on August 4, 1918, near [[Soissons]], on recommendation from Gutmann.  Some accounts further state that it was Gutmann who made the actual award and pinned the medal on Hitler's chest.  Hitler would wear this medal throughout the remainder of his [[Military career of Adolf Hitler|career]], including while serving as [[Fuhrer]] of [[Nazi Germany]].

Gutmann himself was an Iron Cross recipient, having been awarded the Iron Cross 2nd Class on December 2, 1914 (incidentally the same day as Hitler), as well as the Iron Cross 1st Class on December 4, 1915.

==Post World War I and Nazi Years==

On February 8, 1919, Guttman was demobilized from the German Army but still maintained on the Army rolls as a Reserve Lieutenant. He married later that year and would go on to father two children.  During the 1920s, Guttman owned and operated an office-furniture shop in Vordere-Steingasse 3 in Nuremberg.  

In the fall of 1933, Gutmann applied for a veteran's war pension which was granted.  At this time, [[President of Germany|President]] [[Paul von Hindenberg]] had passed several verbal and written decrees allowing for the protection of Jewish war veterans from the rising tide of [[antisemitism]] in Germany.  In 1935, after the passing of the [[Nuremberg Laws]], Gutmann lost his German citizenship and was formally discharged from the veteran rolls of the German Army.  He still continued to receive a pension, however, possibly due to Hitler's influence.&lt;ref&gt;According to the historian Werner Maser, Gutmann received, by Hitler's intervention, a pension from the Third Reich down to the end of the war.&lt;/ref&gt;  

In 1938, Guttman was arrested by the [[Gestapo]] but released both due to sympathetic [[SS]] personnel, who knew Gutmann's history, as well as anti-Nazi elements in the [[Ordnungspolizei|German Police]].  In 1939, Gutmann and his family escaped to Belgium just as [[World War II]] was beginning in [[Europe]].  In 1940, he immigrated to the United States just prior to the Nazi invasion of the [[Low Countries]].

==Post World War II==

Guttman eventually settled in the city of [[St. Louis, Missouri]], where he changed his name to Henry G. Grant and went back into the furniture business.  He died in 1971.

==Portrayals in Media==

In the 2003 [[television]] mini-series &quot;[[Hitler: The Rise of Evil]]&quot;, Hugo Gutmann is portrayed by actor [[Brendan Hughes (actor)|Brendan Hughes]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://cosmos.ucc.ie/cs1064/jabowen/IPSC/php/authors.php?auid=6025 Biography of Hugo Gutmann]
* [http://www.jewishgen.org/yizkor/nuremberg2/nur009.html Hugo Gutmann (Escape from Germany)]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Gutmann, Hugo
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = November 19, 1880
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Nuremberg]],  [[German Empire]] (now [[Germany]])
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1971
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[United States of America|United States]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Gutmann, Hugo}}
[[Category:German military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1971 deaths]]
[[Category:German Jews]]

[[de:Hugo Gutmann]]
[[he:הוגו גוטמן]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
