<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3003506" ns="0" title="Shuttleworth Foundation"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=March 2011}}
{{Notability|date=March 2011}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|date=May 2009}}

{{Infobox Non-profit
|Non-profit_name=Shuttleworth Foundation
|founded_date=2001&lt;ref name=&quot;shuttleworthfoundation.org&quot;&gt;http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org/about-us/&lt;/ref&gt;
|founder=[[Mark Shuttleworth]]
|location=[[Durbanville|Durbanville, South Africa]]
|origins=
|key_people=[[Mark Shuttleworth]], founder &lt;br&gt; [http://www.helenturvey.com Helen Turvey], [[chief executive officer|CEO]]
|area_served=Global
|focus=[[Open Source]], [[Open content]], [[Open educational resources]]
|method=Fellowships
|revenue=
|endowment=
|owner=
|Non-profit_slogan=
|former name=
|homepage=[http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org/ www.shuttleworthfoundation.org/]
}}
South African entrepreneur [[Mark Shuttleworth]] established the '''Shuttleworth Foundation'''  in January 2001.  There have been various iterations of the Foundation and how it invests in social innovation.  In 2009, the Foundation moved to a fellowship model, allowing the champions of the work to drive their projects forward.


== Shuttleworth Foundation: Group Structure ==

*The Shuttleworth Foundation Trust (SF) is a purpose trust, registered in Jersey.
*The purpose of the trust is defined as follows:
**“To assist persons or projects to effect or which are otherwise involved in social change, with social change being the process whereby values, attitudes or institutions of society, such as education, family and industry become modified, to include both the natural process and action programs initiated by members of the community or any other person.”
*It is for this reason that the Trust registered an entity in the Isle of Man, SF Isle of Man Limited (SF IOM).
*SF IOM funds individuals interested in social change by offering them a Fellowship Grant and providing matching funding to the programs initiated by the Fellows.
*SF Management Team: CEO, CFO, COO and the Office Manager.

== Co-investment model ==

The Foundation provides funding for people who have an unproven idea in the form of a 'salary', travel and office expenses.  For every dollar invested by the Fellow in a project, the Foundation will put in ten or more, allowing the Fellow to own all Intellectual Property and processes once the active fellowship has ceased.  

If a commercial venture is formed during the fellowship, the Foundation will take a non-controlling interest in that entity.

== Funding ratios ==

Project pitches below a pre-determined cumulative amount are pitched to, reviewed and decided by the Foundation management team. Pitches exceeding this cumulative amount are escalated to the Foundation founder. 

Should a project pitch be approved, the Foundation will match the Fellow's personal investment in the project as follows:

* Individual investment up to 12,500 USD - Foundation matches tenfold
* Individual investments between 12,501 USD and 18,000 USD - Foundation matches fifteen-fold
* Joint investment from Fellows below 18,000 USD - Foundation matches twenty-fold (Requirement: Each Fellow must invest at least 25% of the total Fellows' share of the budget.)

== Fellows ==

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Name !! Focus !! Year !! Notable projects
|-
| [http://commonspace.wordpress.com/ Mark Surman] || Open Philanthropy || 2007 - 2008 || 
|-
| [http://aliquidnovi.org/ Andrew Rens] || Intellectual property rights || 2007 - 2010 || ACA2K
|-
| [http://manypossibilities.net Stephen Song] || Telecommunications || 2008 - 2011 || [http://www.villagetelco.org/ Village telco]
|-
| [http://vosloo.net Steve Vosloo] || 21st Century Learning || 2008 - 2011 || m4Lit, Yoza
|-
| [http://markhorner.net Mark Horner] || Open and Collaborative Resources K-12 || 2008 - || [http://www.siyavula.org.za Siyavula], [http://www.fullmarks.org.za Full Marks], [http://www.openpress.co.za Open Press], [http://www.fhsst.org FHSST]
|-
| [http://sharing-nicely.net/ Philipp Schmidt] || Open and Collaborative Resources: Higher Education  || 2009 - || [http://p2pu.org P2PU]
|-
| [http://www.billionbrainblog.com/ François Grey] || Open Science || 2010 -  || [http://www.citizencyberscience.net/ Citizen Cyberscience]
|-
| [http://rufuspollock.org/ Rufus Pollock] || Open Science: Open Data  || 2010 - || [http://www.okfn.org/ OKFN]
|-
| Gavin Weale || Sustainable user-created publishing || 2011 - || [http://www.live-magazine.co.uk Live magazine]
|-
| [http://natural-justice.blogspot.com/ Kabir Bavikatte] || Property Rights (Intellectual and Material) || 2011 - || 
|-
| [http://kefletcher.blogspot.com/ Kathi Fletcher] || Open and Collaborative Resources || 2011 - ||
|}

== Other projects ==

* [[Freedom Toaster]]
* tuXlabs
* Kusasa

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
*[http://www.shuttleworthfoundation.org Shuttleworth Foundation website]
*[http://www.tuxlabs.co.za TuXlabs website]

[[Category:Information technology and development]]
[[Category:Youth development organizations]]

{{org-stub}}

[[fr:Shuttleworth Foundation]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
