<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="300699" ns="0" title="Steve Carlton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox MLB player
|name=Steve Carlton
|image=SteveCarlton.jpg
|caption= 
|position=[[Pitcher]]
|bats=Left
|throws=Left
|birth_date={{Birth date and age|1944|12|22}}
|birth_place=[[Miami, Florida]]
|debutdate=April 12
|debutyear=1965
|debutteam=St. Louis Cardinals
|finaldate=April 23
|finalyear=1988
|finalteam=Minnesota Twins
|stat1label=[[win-loss record (pitching)|Win–Loss record]]
|stat1value=329–244
|stat2label=[[Earned run average]]
|stat2value=3.22
|stat3label=[[Strikeout]]s
|stat3value=4,136
|teams=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[St. Louis Cardinals]] ({{By|1965}}–{{By|1971}})
* [[Philadelphia Phillies]] ({{By|1972}}–{{By|1986}})
* [[San Francisco Giants]] ({{By|1986}})
* [[Chicago White Sox]] ({{By|1986}})
* [[Cleveland Indians]] ({{By|1987}})
* [[Minnesota Twins]] ({{By|1987}}–{{By|1988}})
|highlights=&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* 10× [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]] selection ([[1968 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1968]], [[1969 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1969]], [[1971 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1971]], [[1972 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1972]], [[1974 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1974]], [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977]], [[1979 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1979]], [[1980 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1980]], [[1981 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1981]], [[1982 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1982]])
* 2× [[World Series]] champion ({{wsy|1967}}, {{wsy|1980}})
* [[Gold Glove Award]] winner (1981)
* 4× [[NL Cy Young Award]] winner (1972, 1977, 1980, 1982)
* 4× [[NL TSN Pitcher of the Year]] (1972, 1977, 1980, 1982)
* [[Philadelphia Phillies#Retired numbers|Philadelphia Phillies #32]] retired
|hofdate={{By|1994}}
|hofvote=95.8% (first ballot)
}}
'''Steven Norman Carlton''' (born December 22, 1944), nicknamed '''&quot;Lefty&quot;''', is a former [[Major League Baseball]] left-handed [[pitcher]]. He pitched from 1965-1988 for six different teams in his career, but it is his time with the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] where he received his greatest acclaim as a professional and won four [[Cy Young Awards]]. He was elected to the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] in [[Baseball Hall of Fame balloting, 1994|1994]].

Carlton has the second-most lifetime [[strikeout]]s of any left-handed pitcher (4th overall), and the second-most lifetime [[win (baseball)|wins]] of any left-handed pitcher (11th overall). He was the first pitcher to win four [[Cy Young Award]]s in a career. He held the lifetime strikeout record several times between {{Baseball Year|1982}} and {{Baseball Year|1984}}, before his contemporary [[Nolan Ryan]] passed him. One of his most remarkable records was accounting for nearly half (46%) of his team's wins, when he won 27 games for the last-place (59-97) {{Baseball Year|1972}} Phillies. He is still the last National League pitcher to win 25 or more games in one season,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = List of Major League Wins Leaders by Year | url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/W_leagues.shtml | accessdate = 2007-09-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the last pitcher from any team to throw more than 300 innings in a season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = List of Major League IP Leaders by Year | url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/IP_leagues.shtml | accessdate = 2007-09-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He also holds the record with the most career balks of any pitcher, with 90 (double the second on the all time list, [[Bob Welch (baseball)|Bob Welch]]).

==Early years==
Carlton was born and raised in [[Miami, Florida]], where he played [[Little League Baseball|little league]] and [[American Legion baseball]] during his youth. He attended [[North Miami High School]], and later [[Miami-Dade Community College]]. In 1963, while a student at Miami-Dade, he signed with the [[St. Louis Cardinals (baseball)|St. Louis Cardinals]] for a $5,000 bonus.&lt;ref name=&quot;brc&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Biographical information from Baseball Reference.com|url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/players/c/carltst01.shtml|accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carltbio&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Bio on Carlton's official site|url=http://www.carlton32.com/pages/bio.html|accessdate=2010-02-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==St. Louis Cardinals==
Carlton debuted with the [[St. Louis Cardinals]] as a 20-year-old in 1965 and by {{Baseball Year|1967}} was a regular in the Cardinals rotation. An imposing (6'4&quot;/1.93 m) man with a hard [[fastball]] and [[slider]], Carlton was soon known as an intimidating and dominant pitcher. Carlton enjoyed immediate success in St. Louis, posting winning records and reaching the [[World Series]] in [[1967 World Series|1967]] and [[1968 World Series|1968]]. On September 15, {{Baseball Year|1969}}, Carlton struck out 19 [[New York Mets]], while losing to the Mets, 4-3, setting the all-time modern-day record at that time for [[List of pitchers who have struck out 18 or more batters in a nine-inning baseball game|strikeouts in a nine-inning game]]. That season, he finished with a 17-11 record with a 2.17 ERA, second lowest in the NL, and 210 strikeouts. A contract dispute with the Cardinals made Carlton a no-show at spring training in {{Baseball Year|1970}}. He proceeded to go 10-19 with a 3.73 ERA, leading the NL in losses. In {{Baseball Year|1971}}, he became a 20-game winner for the first time, going 20-9 with a 3.56 ERA.

==Philadelphia Phillies==
Following a salary dispute, Cardinals owner [[Gussie Busch]] ordered Carlton traded.  Eventually, he was traded to the [[Philadelphia Phillies]] before the {{Baseball Year|1972}} season for pitcher [[Rick Wise]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first= |last= |authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Cards, Phils Trade Aces: Carlton, Wise |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=35wMAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=r2ADAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=7196,336640&amp;dq=steve+carlton |newspaper=St. Petersburg Times |publisher= |page=3-C|date=1972-02-26 |accessdate=2009-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The trade is now considered one of the most lopsided deals in baseball history.   However, at the time, the trade appeared to make some sense from the Cardinals' perspective.  Carlton had won 77 games to Wise's 75, and both were considered the best pitchers in the game.  [[Tim McCarver]], who had caught for Carlton in St. Louis and for Wise in Philadelphia, described the trade as &quot;a real good one for a real good one.&quot;  He felt that Carlton had more raw talent, but Wise had better command on the mound.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Neyer |first=Rob |authorlink=Rob Neyer |coauthors= |title=Rob Neyer's Big Book of Baseball Blunders |year=2006 |publisher=Fireside |location=New York City |isbn=0743284917 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Nonetheless, the trade is now reckoned as an epoch-making deal for the Phillies, as well as one of the worst trades in Cardinals history.  While Wise stayed in the majors for another 11 years, only two of them (1972 and 1973) were in St. Louis.

In Carlton's first season with Philadelphia, he led the league in wins (27), complete games (30), strikeouts (310), and ERA (1.97), despite playing for a team whose final record was 59-97. His 1972 performance earned him the [[Hickok Belt]] as the top professional athlete of the year. His having won 46% of his team's victories is a record in modern major league history. Carlton attributed his success to his grueling training regime, which included Eastern [[martial arts]] techniques, the most famous of which was twisting his fist to the bottom of a 5 gallon bucket of [[rice]]. 

Some highlights of Carlton's 1972 season included starting the season with 5 wins and 1 loss, then losing 5 games in a row, during which the Phillies scored only 10 runs.
&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Imagination, It's Funny&quot; by William Leggett, Sports Illustrated, August 21, 1972&lt;/ref&gt;
At this point he began a 15-game winning streak. After it ended at a 20-6 record, he finished the final third of the year with 7 more wins and 4 losses, ending with 27 wins and 10 losses. Since he completed 30 of 41 starts, the 1972 Phillies rarely needed the bullpen when Steve Carlton pitched.  

During the 18 games of the winning streak (3 were no-decisions), Carlton pitched 155 innings, allowed 103 hits and 28 runs (only 17 in the 15 winning games), issued 39 walks, and had 140 strikeouts. From July 19, 1972 to August 13, 1972 he pitched six complete games, won six games, allowed only 1 earned run, and threw four shutouts. Over this period he pitched 56 innings, allowing only one unearned run.
&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Steve Carlton's Long Winning Streak in '72 Still Amazing&quot; by Ted Silary from Baseball Digest Nov 1992&lt;/ref&gt;
Steve had three pitches, a rising fastball, a legendary slider, and a long looping curve ball.  Baseball commentators during 1972 regularly remarked that Steve's slider was basically unhittable. He was also a good hitter for a pitcher.  At times he pinch-hit for the Phillies during 1972.
&lt;ref&gt;Paul Cheffers lived in Philadelphia in 1972, listened to the Phillies on the radio and attended several games where Steve Carlton pitched.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Carlton's relationship with the media===
Carlton slumped in {{Baseball Year|1973}}, losing 20 games. The media's open questioning of his unusual training techniques led to an acrimonious relationship between them and Carlton, and he severed all ties with the media, refusing to answer press questions for the rest of his career with the Phillies. This reached a point where, in {{Baseball Year|1981}}, while the [[Mexican people|Mexican]] rookie [[Fernando Valenzuela]] was achieving stardom with the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]], a reporter remarked, ''&quot;The two best pitchers in the National League don't speak English: Fernando Valenzuela and Steve Carlton.&quot;

===More success===
Carlton continued to enjoy many years of success with the Phillies, winning the [[Cy Young Award]] in {{Baseball Year|1972}}, {{Baseball Year|1977}}, {{Baseball Year|1980}}, and {{Baseball Year|1982}}, and pitching the Phillies to the best string of post-season appearances in club history. Carlton was the first pitcher to win four Cy Young Awards, a mark later matched by [[Greg Maddux]], and exceeded by [[Roger Clemens]] and [[Randy Johnson]]. His Cy Young Award in 1972 was by unanimous vote, and he finished fifth in balloting for the National League MVP. Gradually the Phillies improved their team, and won the National League East three consecutive times from 1976-78. In 1980, Carlton helped the Phillies win their first [[1980 World Series|World Series]], personally winning the final game. 

Carlton won a [[Gold Glove Award]] for his fielding in {{Baseball Year|1981}}, and helped the Phillies to another pennant in [[1983 World Series|1983]], but lost to the [[Baltimore Orioles]] in the World Series. 

On September 13, 1982, for the fourth time in his career, Steve Carlton hit a home run and tossed a complete game shutout in the same game. He is the only pitcher to have done so in three different decades.

On September 23, 1983, in a game against the [[1983 St. Louis Cardinals season|St. Louis Cardinals]], Carlton won the 300th game of his career, becoming the 15th pitcher to accomplish the feat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Stoic Carlton participates in excitement of No. 300 |agency=Associated Press |work=Gadsden Times |page=7 |date=25 September 1983 |accessdate=7 March 2011 |url=http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=tp8fAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=DtYEAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2636,4539451&amp;dq=steve+carlton&amp;hl=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Race with Nolan Ryan and Gaylord Perry for the all time strikeout record===
Over a three year period between {{Baseball Year|1982}}-{{Baseball Year|1984}}, Carlton was involved in an interesting pitching duel with [[Nolan Ryan]] and [[Gaylord Perry]], in which they often traded places at the top of the all-time strikeout list. 

At the start of the 1982 season, the 55-year-old mark of the great [[Walter Johnson]] still stood at 3,508 strikeouts,&lt;ref&gt;http://mlb.mlb.com/stats/historical/leaders.jsp?c_id=mlb&amp;baseballScope=mlb&amp;statType=2&amp;sortByStat=SO&amp;timeFrame=3&amp;timeSubFrame2=0&lt;/ref&gt; but now there were three pitchers who would start the season within 100 strikeouts of Johnson: [[Nolan Ryan]] (3,494), [[Gaylord Perry]] (3,452), and Carlton (3,434). Ryan would be the first to surpass Johnson on April 22, [[1983 Houston Astros season|1983]] against the [[1983 Montreal Expos season|Montreal Expos]]. However a stint on the [[disabled list]] shortly after he set the record, combined with a spectacular season by Carlton, allowed Carlton to make up ground and on June 7, [[1983 Philadelphia Phillies season|1983]], Carlton passed Ryan as the all-time strikeout king with 3,526 to Ryan's 3,524. There would be a total of 14 lead changes and one tie that season, often after each of their respective starts, before the season ended with Carlton leading 3,709 to 3,677. [[Gaylord Perry]], aging and in his final season, was never a  huge factor, although he did eventually pass Johnson to finish his career with 3,534 strikeouts. Since then five other pitchers have surpassed Johnson's mark and he has fallen to ninth place on the all time strikeout list. 

There would be five more lead changes and a tie in {{Baseball Year|1984}} before Carlton ran out of gas. His last-ever lead in the all-time strikeout race was after his start on September 4, [[1984 Philadelphia Phillies season|1984]], when he struck out four [[1984 Chicago Cubs season|Cubs]] to lead Ryan by three (3,857 to 3,854). Although the season ended with a mere two-strikeout lead for Ryan (3,874 to 3,872), Carlton had an injury-riddled season in [[1985 Philadelphia Phillies season|1985]] and an even worse season in [[1986 Philadelphia Phillies season|1986]] before being released by the Phillies just 18 strikeouts short of 4,000.

==Post-Phillies==
===San Francisco Giants===
He joined the [[1986 San Francisco Giants season|San Francisco Giants]], but pitched ineffectively save for seven shutout  innings in a game against the [[1986 Pittsburgh Pirates season|Pittsburgh Pirates]] in which he also hit a 3-run homer for his only win as a Giant. He would hang around just long enough to collect his 4,000th strikeout (against [[Eric Davis (baseball)|Eric Davis]]) before retiring. He went 1-3 with a 5.10 ERA in six games for the Giants. He did however break his self imposed boycott of the media, giving a press conference after signing with the Giants.

===Chicago White Sox===
His retirement was brief: he almost immediately signed with the [[1986 Chicago White Sox season|Chicago White Sox]] for the remainder of the {{Baseball Year|1986}} season. He was surprisingly effective, going 4-3 with a respectable 3.69 ERA, but was not offered a contract for [[1987 Chicago White Sox season|1987]].

===Cleveland Indians===
He joined the [[1987 Cleveland Indians season|Cleveland Indians]], where his most notable achievement was teaming up with [[Phil Niekro]] in a game against the [[New York Yankees]] at [[Yankee Stadium (1923)|Yankee Stadium]], where they became the first teammates and 300-game winners to appear in the same game. Both were ineffective in a 10-6 Yankee victory. It would be his first and only pitching appearance in Yankee Stadium, having spent the majority of his career in the National League before the inception of [[interleague play]]. (He was selected to the [[1977 Major League Baseball All-Star Game|1977 National League All-Star team]] which was held in Yankee Stadium, but he didn't appear in the game.)

===Minnesota Twins===
He was traded to the [[1987 Minnesota Twins season|Minnesota Twins]], where he was yet again ineffective. He went a combined 6-14 with a 5.74 ERA for both the Indians and Twins. However the Twins, who had been a bad team for most of the 1980s, would go on to a surprising win in the [[1987 World Series]], albeit without Carlton on the postseason roster, to earn him a third World Series ring and a trip to the [[White House]] to meet [[President of the United States|President]] [[Ronald Reagan|Reagan]] along with his teammates. Interestingly, when Carlton was photographed with his teammates at the White House, newspapers listed each member of the team with the notable exception of Carlton. Instead, Carlton was listed as an ''&quot;unidentified [[United States Secret Service|Secret Service]] agent.&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Steve |last=Wulf|authorlink= |coauthors= |title=Steve Carlton |url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1004780/index.htm |newspaper=Sports Illustrated |publisher= |date=1994-01-24 |accessdate=2009-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[1988 Minnesota Twins season|Twins]] brought him back in {{Baseball Year|1988}} but he lasted only a month (0-1 16.76 ERA in four games) before the Twins released him.

===Retirement===
He attempted to find work in {{Baseball Year|1989}} but found no takers. The closest thing to an offer was the [[1989 New York Yankees season|New York Yankees]] offering him the use of their facilities for training purposes but no spot on the spring training team. Nolan Ryan would pitch until {{Baseball Year|1993}} and would extend his strikeout lead over Carlton to almost 1,600 before retiring. Carlton would eventually fall to third and then fourth place on the all time strikeout list after [[Roger Clemens]] and [[Randy Johnson]] passed him.

==Legacy==
A ten-time [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|All-Star]], Carlton led the league in many pitching categories. He [[strikeout|struck out]] 4,136 batters in his career, setting a record for a left-handed pitcher (since surpassed by [[Randy Johnson]]), and holds many other records for both left-handed and Phillies pitchers. His 329 career wins are the [[Top 100 winning pitchers of all time|eleventh most in baseball history]], behind [[Greg Maddux]], [[Roger Clemens]], and [[Warren Spahn]] among pitchers of the [[Live Ball Era|live-ball era]] (post-{{Baseball Year|1920}}). 

{{MLBBioRet
|Image  = PhilsCarlton.PNG
|Name   = Steve Carlton
|Number = 32
|Team   = Philadelphia Phillies
|Year   = 1989
|}}

Carlton picked 144 runners off base, by far the most in Major League Baseball since pickoff records began being collected in 1957. [[Jerry Koosman]] is second with 82.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Pickoffs since 1957 | url=http://www.baseball-reference.com/pi/shareit/28Uz | accessdate = 2007-08-19 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

He never threw a [[no hitter]], but pitched six one-hitters. 

Carlton was elected to the [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] in {{by|1994}} with 96% of the vote, one of the highest percentages ever. The Phillies retired his number 32, and honored him with a statue outside [[Veterans Stadium]] that was later moved to [[Citizens Bank Park]] (along with a similar statue of fellow Phillies Hall of Famer [[Mike Schmidt]]). 

In 1998, ''The Sporting News'' ranked him number 30 on its list of the 100 Greatest Baseball Players. In 1999, he was a nominee for the [[Major League Baseball All-Century Team]].

Despite his career-long rivalry with Ryan, Carlton maintains his greatest rival was [[Tom Seaver]].

His losing 19-strikeout effort against the Mets was a microcosm of his career against them.  While he posted 30 wins against them during his career, they bested him 36 times.

Carlton appeared in an episode of ''[[Married... with Children]]'', playing himself in an episode where former athletes humiliate [[Al Bundy]] while filming a shoe commercial. In the episode, Bud asks him for an autograph and he is shown writing with his right hand.

==See also==
* [[300 win club]]
* [[3000 strikeout club]]
* [[4000 strikeout club]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball leaders in career wins]]
* [[Triple crown (baseball)#National League winners 2|Triple Crown]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball ERA champions]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball strikeout champions]]
* [[List of Major League Baseball wins champions]]
* [[List of pitchers who have struck out 18 or more batters in a nine-inning MLB game]]
* [[Top 100 strikeout pitchers of all time]]
* [[Major League Baseball titles leaders]]

==Hall of Fame==
Steve was inducted to the [[National Baseball Hall of Fame]] in the year 1994, his first year of eligibility.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{bbhof|carlton-steve}}
* [http://www.stevecarlton.com Steve Carlton Official Website]
* {{Baseballstats |mlb= |espn= |br=c/carltst01|fangraphs=1001964 |cube=steve-carlton}}
* [http://www.philly.com/philly/sports/phillies/mlb/Steve_Carlton_A_look_at_Lefty.html Philly.com: Steve Carlton photo gallery]

{{s-start-collapsible|header={{s-ach}}}}
{{succession box | title=[[National League]] [[Triple crown (baseball)|Pitching Triple Crown]] | before= [[Sandy Koufax]] | years=1972 | after= [[Dwight Gooden]]}}
{{succession box | before = [[Ferguson Jenkins]]&lt;br&gt;[[Randy Jones (baseball player)|Randy Jones]]&lt;br&gt;[[Bruce Sutter]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fernando Valenzuela]] | title = [[Cy Young Award|National League Cy Young Award]] | years = 1972&lt;br&gt;1977&lt;br&gt;1980&lt;br&gt;1982 | after = [[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gaylord Perry]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fernando Valenzuela]]&lt;br&gt;[[John Denny]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball ERA champions|National League ERA Champion]] | before= [[Tom Seaver]] | years=1972 | after= [[Tom Seaver]]}}
{{succession box | title=[[List of Major League Baseball strikeout champions|National League Strikeout Champion]] | before= [[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[J. R. Richard]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fernando Valenzuela]] | years=1972&lt;br&gt;1974&lt;br&gt;1980&lt;br&gt;1982-1983 | after= [[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[Fernando Valenzuela]]&lt;br&gt;[[Dwight Gooden]]}}
{{succession box
| title  = [[List of Major League Baseball wins champions|National League Wins Champion]]
| years  = 1972&lt;br&gt;1977&lt;br&gt;1980&lt;br&gt;1982
| before = [[Ferguson Jenkins]]&lt;br&gt;[[Randy Jones (baseball player)|Randy Jones]]&lt;br&gt;[[Joe Niekro]] &amp; [[Phil Niekro]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Seaver]]
| after  = [[Ron Bryant]]&lt;br&gt;[[Gaylord Perry]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tom Seaver]]&lt;br&gt;[[John Denny]]
}}
{{succession box | title=[[Hickok Belt|Hickok Belt Winner]] | before=[[Lee Trevino]] | years=1972 | after=[[O.J. Simpson]]}}
{{succession box
| before = [[Phil Niekro]]
| title = [[List of NL Gold Glove winners at pitcher|National League Gold Glove Award (P)]]
| years = {{Baseball Year|1981}}
| after = [[Phil Niekro]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{300 win club}}
{{3000 strikeout club}}
{{MLB Triple Crowns (pitchers)}}
{{1967 St. Louis Cardinals}}
{{1980 Philadelphia Phillies}}
{{NL Cy Young}}
{{NL P Gold Glove Award}}
{{Philadelphia Phillies}}
{{Phillies Retired Numbers}}
{{Philadelphia Phillies HOF}}
{{Philadelphia Phillies ODS}}
{{Philly Baseball Wall of Fame}}
{{1994 Baseball HOF}}
{{Pitchers in the Baseball Hall of Fame}}
{{2004 Philadelphia Sports HOF}}{{Florida Sports Hall of Fame}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Carlton, Steve
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = December 22, 1944
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Miami, Florida
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Carlton, Steve}}
[[Category:1944 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Baseball players from Florida]]
[[Category:National Baseball Hall of Fame inductees]]
[[Category:National League All-Stars]]
[[Category:Chicago White Sox players]]
[[Category:Cleveland Indians players]]
[[Category:Minnesota Twins players]]
[[Category:Philadelphia Phillies players]]
[[Category:San Francisco Giants players]]
[[Category:St. Louis Cardinals players]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball pitchers]]
[[Category:Cy Young Award winners]]
[[Category:Gold Glove Award winners]]
[[Category:National League Pitching Triple Crown winners]]
[[Category:National League ERA champions]]
[[Category:National League strikeout champions]]
[[Category:National League wins champions]]
[[Category:Miami Dade College alumni]]
[[Category:People from Miami, Florida]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball players with retired numbers]]
[[Category:Winnipeg Goldeyes players]]
[[Category:Rock Hill Cardinals players]]
[[Category:Tulsa Oilers (baseball) players]]

[[de:Steve Carlton]]
[[es:Steve Carlton]]
[[fr:Steve Carlton]]
[[ko:스티브 칼튼]]
[[ja:スティーブ・カールトン]]
[[sh:Steve Carlton]]
[[zh:史提夫·卡爾頓]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
