<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3020686" ns="0" title="Zak Dingle"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|image=[[Image:Zak Dingle.png|200px]]
|caption=Zak Dingle in 2009.
|name=Zak Dingle
|portrayer=[[Steve Halliwell]]
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|spinoffs= ''Emmerdale:&lt;br /&gt;The Dingles Down Under (1997)&lt;br /&gt;''The Dingles in Venice (1999)''&lt;br/&gt;''The Dingles For Richer for Poorer (2010)''
|born={{Birth-date and age|19 January 1952|df=y}}&lt;ref name=profile /&gt;
|family= [[Dingle family|Dingle]]
|home=Wishing Well Cottage                                                                                                                                 |occupation=Handyman/Pig Farmer
|father= [[Jedediah Dingle]]
|mother=[[Peg Dingle]]
|brothers = [[Shadrach Dingle]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Albert Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Caleb Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ezra Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;Zebediah Dingle&lt;br&gt;Moses Dingle
|wife = Nellie Lynch (1973–97)&lt;br/&gt;[[Lisa Dingle|Lisa Clegg]] (1998—)
|sons = Nathan Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cain Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]
|daughters=Tina Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]
|grandfather = Jonah Dingle
|granddaughters = [[Debbie Dingle]]
|grandsons=[[Samson Dingle]]
|great-granddaughters = [[Sarah Dingle]]
|uncles = Bert Dingle
|nieces and nephews = Mandy Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lilith Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Delilah Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Genesis Walker]][[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]
|cousins = Obadiah Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Solomon Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Elvis Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Marilyn Dingle]]
|first= 20 October 1994
|last=
|introducer=Mervyn Watson &lt;small&gt;(1994)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Steve Frost]] &lt;small&gt;(2003)&lt;/small&gt;
|years=1994–2002, 2003—
}}

'''Zachariah Bartholomew &quot;Zak&quot; Dingle''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[Steve Halliwell]]. He first appeared on 20 October 1994 and has remained since except for a brief break from 2002-2003. On his time in the show he has been involved in a testicular cancer storyline and becoming a father late stage in his life. Halliwell joined the show as part of the Dingle family and was only initally supposed to stay for a few episodes. Halliwell has been nominated for several awards for his portrayal of Zak.

==Casting==
He arrived with the rest of the Dingle family and along with the family was to &quot;run riot through the rural tranquillity and put the muck back into the mix&quot;. The family where originally supposed to be &quot;nothing more than a bit of spot of bother over a couple of episodes&quot; but later were kept.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=Emmerdale Family Album: The Dingles|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/spoilers/a21446/emmerdale-family-album-the-dingles.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2003 it was announced Halliwell was to take break. This led him to commented that he had &quot;no axe to grind&quot; and it wasn't &quot;about salary or storylines&quot; and added &quot;I love Zak, I love Emmerdale, but I've asked for a spell out to spend some quality time with my family and friends&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hart|first=Beth|title=&quot;Emmerdale's&quot; Zak to take a rest|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a8733/emmerdales-zak-to-take-a-rest.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Digital Spy]]|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010 Halliwell said that his casting in Emmerdale was &quot;the greatest break in my professional life&quot;.&lt;ref name=Halliwell&gt;{{cite news|title=spotlight on...Steve Halliwell.|url=http://www.thefreelibrary.com/spotlight+on...Steve+Halliwell.-a0242486101|accessdate=23 September 2011|newspaper=[[Western Mail (Wales)|Western Mail]]|date=20 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development==
===Characterisation===
[[ITV]] describe him as the &quot;patriarch&quot; of the Dingle family adding he is &quot;Ostensibly a scrap dealer and pig farmer&quot; although he sends &quot;most of his time either doing nothing at all, or dreaming up scams and schemes&quot;. They also labelled him  as occassionally being &quot;a violent man&quot; who is &quot;prone to jealousy, however, he will do anything for a quiet life and a pint in the Woolpack!&quot;&lt;ref name=profile&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.itv.com/soaps/emmerdale/castandcharactersatoe/zakdingle/|title=Cast and Characters - Zak Dingle|publisher=[[ITV]].com|accessdate=11 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Halliwell said that Zak was &quot;brought in as a violent nutter, then after they introduced the rest of the family, this workshy, loveable rogue started to emerge, and they started writing more comic elements for the Dingles&quot;.&lt;ref name=Halliwell /&gt; Halliwell described the family saying they are &quot;petty thieves&quot; and &quot;a bit part of the under class of life&quot; who &quot;still hold those old values that people are more important than money&quot; and said &quot;We do strike a chord with a lot of people. Most of us will never be rich, so they can identify with the Dingles much easier than rich characters&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rainey|first=Naomi|title=Halliwell: 'Dingles are old-fashioned' |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a288877/halliwell-dingles-are-old-fashioned.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|date=19 November 2010|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[What's on TV]] described him as a &quot;General dodgy dealer&quot; who is an &quot;all round wrong 'un&quot; and the &quot;keeper of the 'Dingle code' - which basically means that he makes sure all Dingles live on the wrong side of the law&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Home Soaps Emmerdale Who's Who Zak Dingle|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/zak-dingle/792|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=22 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Holy Soap]] described him as &quot;head of the Dingle clan, Zak is the scallywag you can't help but have a soft spot for&quot; before adding that he &quot;has had several odd jobs over the years, but he tends to fill his coffers by masterminding several dodgy deals with his brother, Shadrach.&quot;&lt;ref name=holy&gt;{{cite web|title=Holy Soap &gt; Emmerdale &gt; Cast &gt; Zak Dingle|url=http://web.archive.org/web/20100120092505/http://holysoap.five.tv/emmerdale/cast/zak-dingle-802|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=[[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]|accessdate=22 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Storylines==
===Backstory===                           
Zachariah &quot;Zak&quot; Bartholomew Dingle was born on 19 January 1952 in Liverpool&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Parkin |first=Lance |title=30 Years of Emmerdale |year=2002 |publisher=[[Granada (company)|Granada]] |location=London |isbn=0 233 05068 X |page=182 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Zak first appeared in 1994, challenging old adversery Ned Glover to a Bare-Knuckle fight, which he went on to lose. Zak was  former bare knuckle champion of the Dales and his family were notorious throughout the village for their rogueish behaviour. His original family consisted of wife [[Nellie Dingle|Nellie]], sons Butch and Sam and daughter Tina. He had another son, Ben, who had been killed in a fight with the local Doctors son Luke Mcallister, although he was found to have a heart defect, this did not stop the Dingle's pointing the finger at Luke. The family quickly established themselves in the village, and forced Luke's family away, although he stayed and ended up with Tina, much to the annoyance of Zak, who arrived in the village and began to beat Luke, and was only stopped in his tracks when Tina announced her preganancy. However, it was established she had lied to humiliate him at the altar in revenge for Bens death, leading to him killing himself in his car and nearly Tina in the process. As the head of the Dingle clan, Zak is no stranger to drama. His first wife, Nellie, left him, and he lost two sons, Ben and Butch, in tragic circumstances but Zak soldiers on. He is ever hopeful that the Dingle family can overcome all obstacles.

===1994-===

In 1996, many of Zak’s prayers were answered when he met [[Lisa Clegg]]. They were instantly smitten and, after a few hiccups, the couple married on 28 January 1998. That Christmas, the couple got an especially welcome Christmas present when Lisa - who had no idea she was pregnant - gave birth to their daughter [[Belle Dingle|Belle]]. 

In 2000, Zak and Lisa’s marriage was pushed to the limit when Nellie returned. With tensions between them rising, Lisa moved out. Tragedy then struck when Butch was killed in a bus crash. Since Lisa had serviced the bus before it was declared roadworthy, Zak blamed her for the accident and it looked like the marriage was over for good. Zak couldn’t let go that easily and an uneasy truce was declared - largely for the sake of Belle.
 
In 2001, Zak had the uneasy task of telling violent [[Cain Dingle|Cain]] that he was his real father. After some violent words, the two men accepted the situation and a bond developed between them. 

Zak’s health took a turn for the worse when he discovered he had testicular cancer. Zak's illness ensured he got his problems in perspective and his marriage was firmly back on track. Domestic harmony was shattered when his mother [[Peg Dingle|Peg]] came to stay. Zak blamed Peg for the death of his father, [[Jedediah Dingle|Jed]], believing she murdered him. When she revealed the truth about Jed deserting them, a truce was declared. When Peg left the village, there was a better understanding between them.
 
Zak shocked his family when he disappeared to Chile in search of the Dingle fortune. While he was away, Lisa became close to [[Eddie Hope]] and it looked like Zak may have lost her for good. Lisa still loved the old scoundrel and they reconciled on his return.

In 2005, Zak was saddened when his son, Sam, left to start a new life with his girlfriend [[Alice Wilson]] in Norfolk. Losing Sam made Zak more protective of the other members of his family. 

When it was revealed his granddaughter [[Debbie Dingle|Debbie]] was having an affair with  [[Andy Sugden]], Zak hit the roof - and Andy! The fling came back to haunt them when Debbie gave birth to baby [[Sarah]] after concealing her pregnancy from everyone. Like the rest of the family, Zak was delighted that Debbie and her daughter are safe and well, welcoming Sarah into the fold. However, Debbie couldn’t cope with motherhood and despite efforts to get through to her, he was devastated when she gave the baby to her foster mother, [[Emily Kirk]], who subsequently disappeared. 

With Debbie gone, Zak had a new crisis to deal with when Sam returned to Emmerdale. He told Zak that he and Alice were expecting a child. Tragedy struck when Alice was diagnosed with cancer. The family rallied round as the couple tried to come to terms with the situation. Under Zak’s guidance, Sam gave Alice the support she needed and the couple were delighted when Samson was born. Their happiness was short lived though, as Alice was told her illness was fatal just as she was preparing to marry Sam. The family were devastated by the diagnosis but Zak was determined to see Sam through the tough times ahead.

Earlier in Zak's history, the family encountered many problems with the then Home Farm owner, Frank Tate. Frank tried to evict the family unsuccessfully and one episode saw the Dingles' celebrate Frank's death with a victory chorus; 'We hate Frank Tate, he tried to evict us, the police came and nicked us, but now, you are dead'. The song was accompanied by them banging their cutlery fiercely on the table whilst at an evening meal. The more recognisable and noted members of the family were also present; Mandy Dingle, Butch Dingle and Sam Dingle.

Zak became friends with [[Rosemary King]]. He took her at face value, despite her being devious and manipulative. They got on and she asked him to keep a discreet eye on her son, Grayson, and let her know what he was doing. She hired him as gamekeeper at Home Farm and confided family secrets, knowing she could trust him. 

She also bonded with his daughter, Belle, and paid for her to attend private school. That ended when Rosemary confessed to poisoning her daughter-in-law, [[Perdita Hyde-Sinclair]] and Zak told her to stay away from him and his daughter, Belle.

In May 2008, Zak resigned as gamekeeper of Home Farm after Eli broke some advertising material for Matthew King's press launch, at a cost of £1500. Matthew insisted Zak pay for the breakages which he did, with money meant for Belle's school fees. Zak asked Matthew to refund the money, and Matthew agreed, after the insurance company had paid out. Zak told Matthew he couldn't wait but Matthew refused to pay Zak any sooner.

Since then, Zak has been keeping an eye on his family. He was concerned that Sam had developed quite a soft spot for [[Jo Sugd]]en and annoyed when Sam was beaten up by Andy Sugden. Zak warned Andy if he came anywhere near Sam again, he'd be fighting Zak. 

After Jo threw Andy out, he and the other Dingles helped Jo run the farm and were shocked by her revelation that Andy had been beating her up for months. When Jo left the village, wanting to reclaim her life, Zak and Lisa got custody of Sarah. When Andy found out, he tried to take Sarah back but Debbie wouldn't let him. Zak told him he was welcome to visit any time, though.

==Reception==
At the [[British Soap Awards]] in 2002 Halliwell was nominated for Best actor for his portrayal of the part and Zak was nominated for Hero for his testicular cancer storyline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Welsh|first=Dingle|title=British Soap Awards 2002: Nominations|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/feature/a7412/british-soap-awards-2002-nominations.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|date=16 May 2002|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2007 he was again nominated for Best Actor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=The British Soap Awards 2007: The Winners|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a58280/the-british-soap-awards-2007-the-winners.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|date=27 May 2007|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a poll to find the &quot;top soap bloke&quot; of all time which was run by [[Loaded (magazine)|Loaded]] Zak came fourth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Rowe|first=Darren|title='Neighbours' Harold &quot;top soap bloke&quot;|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a167777/neighbours-harold-top-soap-bloke.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|date=28 July 2009|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Holy Soap commented on his memorable moment as being when he &quot;made quite an entrance in 1994, when he challenged Bernard McAllister to a bare knuckle fight after he thought Bernard's son, Luke, was responsible for Ben's death.&quot;&lt;ref name=holy /&gt; Fellow Emmerdale cast member [[James Hooton]] commented that said Steve Halliwell often gets recognised for his alter ego saying &quot;Steve can't tie his shoelaces in the street without people noticing. It's the beard&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Daniels|first=Colin|title=Hooton 'likes to hide behind character'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a285165/hooton-likes-to-hide-behind-character.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi]]|accessdate=20 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/page.asp?partid=3682 Zak Dingle] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/zak-dingle/792 Zak Dingle] at ''[[What's on TV]]''
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20100120092505/http://holysoap.five.tv/emmerdale/cast/zak-dingle-802 Character profile] at [[Holy Soap]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Emmerdale characters}}
{{EDDingles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dingle, Zak}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1994]]
[[Category:Fictional taxicab drivers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
