<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30216733" ns="0" title="List of minor Emmerdale characters (1990)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Emmerdaleminor}}
The following is a '''list of minor characters''' that first appeared in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] '''''[[Emmerdale]]''''' in 1990, by order of first appearance.
{{-}}

==Elizabeth Pollard==

{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|name=Elizabeth Pollard
|image =  
|portrayer= Kate Dove
|years=1990-1993
|first=1990
|last=30 December 1993
|born=3 May 1947
|death= 30 December 1993&lt;/br&gt; (aged 46)
|death cause = [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Plane crash storyline 1993|Plane crash]]
|father =  Barry Jeffries
|husband =  [[Eric Pollard]] (1992-1993)
|sons = [[Michael Feldmann]]
|daughters =[[Elsa Chappell]]
|granddaughters = [[Alice Bates]]
}}

'''Elizabeth Pollard''' (née '''Jeffries''', previously '''Feldmann''') , played by Kate Dove, arrived in the village with her son Michael and daughter Elsa in 1990. She found herself fighting for the affections of [[Alan Turner (Emmerdale)|Alan Turner]] and [[Eric Pollard]]. Elizabeth chose Eric and married him in October 1992. She didn't know that Eric was still married to his first wife Eileen and was committing bigamy.

Eventually, Elizabeth discovered that Eric had planted a typewriter on her son, Michael, in order to disguise the fact that he himself had committed cheque fraud and was prepard to let Michael take the blame. On 30 December 1993, Elizabeth left Eric, informing him that she would report him to the police. He tried to dissuade her, saying that if she reported him, she herself would face prosecution for her role in the theft of antique vases, however, Elizabeth admitted that her own imprisonment would be worth that of Eric's. Shortly afterwards, Elizabeth was killed in the [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Plane crash storyline 1993|plane crash]] that struck the village. Her son, Michael, however, as well as a majority of villagers, believed that Eric had actually murdered her in order to stop her from exposing his fraudulent activities.

Nearly seventeen years after her death, in December 2010, Eric started to receive notes, messages and Christmas greetings, signed from Elizabeth. Originally believing them to be from [[Amy Wyatt]], it later transpired that Elizabeth's son Michael had been sending the notes and returned to the village after 16 years of absence, in order to make Eric pay for the murder of his mother.

Eric told Val on 3 January 2011 about the night of the plane crash 17 years before and stated the events leading up to her death such as about the cheque fraud and stolen Roman bracelet. He then stated that he went round to see her then after a brief row she had stormed out of the house and he followed her, caught up with her and tried to get her to listen and that she had ran off into the night screaming but a tree near her burst into flames as plane wreckage shot down and the sky lit up. Eric explains that he went back a bit later and found her dead. On the 4th January 2011 Val obtained the coroners report into Elizabeth's death which confirmed she had been killed by falling debris from the plane. In May 2011 Eric mentioned her when him and David were looking for Amy in Hotten. 
{{-}}

==Elsa Chappell==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|name=Elsa Chappell
|image= 
|caption=Natasha Gray as Elsa (2001)
|portrayer= Naomi Lewis (1990–1991, 1994, 1994)&lt;br&gt;Natasha Gray (1998–1999, 2001)&lt;/br&gt;
|years=1990–1991, 1994, 1998, 1999, 2001
|first=1990
|last=12 December 2001
|born= 1972
|death=
|mother=[[Elizabeth Pollard]]
|grandfathers=Barry Jeffries
|husband=Brett Chappell
|daughters=[[Alice Bates]] 
|brothers=[[Michael Feldmann]]
}}

'''Elsa Chappell''' (née '''Feldmann''') first appeared in 1990 with her mother Elizabeth and brother Michael after they were being evicted from their house by [[Frank Tate (Emmerdale)|Frank Tate]]. Elsa soon began a relationship with [[Nick Bates]] and they got engaged and planned to marry on Valentines Day 1991. However, Elsa was pregnant and gave birth to a daughter, [[Alice Bates|Alice]]. As they were unable to get her to the hospital in time, [[Zoe Tate]] acted as midwife and helped deliver Alice. The couple separated, with Elsa leaving Nick on Christmas Day 1991, taking Alice with her. She soon realised that she wasn't suited to motherhood, as it prevented her having a social life, so she gave Nick custody of Alice before leaving the village. 

Following the death of her mother in the Plane Crash in December 1993, Elsa returned to Emmerdale for her funeral. Elsa then attempted to gain custody of Alice again, by rumours that Nick and his best friend, [[Archie Brooks]], who had also died in the plane crash, had been gay. However, a court ruled in Nick's favour and Elsa failed to win custody and left the village again. After living in Australia for a while, Elsa returned in 1999 with a new husband, Brett, and stepson, Shane, in the hope that she could get custody of Alice and take her back to Australia to live with her permanently. During Elsa's absence, Nick had been imprisoned for manslaughter after shooting a poacher dead and custody of Alice had been given to Nick's sister [[Kathy Brookman|Kathy Glover]]. Kathy, who had become very close to her niece, had no choice but to let Elsa take Alice. Kathy visited Elsa in 2001 and brought Alice back to the village without her knowledge. Elsa followed her and after seeing that Alice was happy with Kathy, made her an offer to move to Australia with her and Alice so that she could spend a lot more time with her. Kathy agreed and she went with Elsa and Alice to Australia.
{{-}}

==Michael Feldmann==
{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series=Emmerdale
|image1= 
|name=Michael Feldmann
|image =  
|imagecaption = Michael in 2010
|portrayer= Matthew Vaughan
|years=1990-1994, 2010-2011
|first= 13 February 1990
|last= 4 January 2011
|born= 30 July 1966
|death= 
|mother=[[Elizabeth Pollard]]
|sisters=[[Elsa Chappell]] 
|grandfathers=Barry Jeffries
|wife=
|nieces=[[Alice Bates]]
}}

'''Michael Feldmann''' first appeared in 1990 with his mother, Elizabeth and sister, Elsa when they were being evicted from their house by [[Frank Tate (Emmerdale)|Frank Tate]]. 

In his early years, Michael sought employment at Emmerdale Farm, working for [[Annie Sugden|Annie]] and [[Jack Sugden]]. He was accused of arson, when one of the barns burnt down, however, this was later proven to be the work of a labourer from another estate. Michael went on to have a relationship with [[Rachel Hughes]], however, this was jeopardised after he had a one-night stand with [[Zoe Tate]], who later [[coming out|came out]] as a lesbian.

In 1992, Michael took part in an armed robbery of Home Farm, which left [[Joe Sugden]] badly injured and fighting for his life. The Robbery was organised by Neil Kincaid's stable hand, Steve. Following his mother's marriage to [[Eric Pollard]], several months later, Michael was arrested for his involvement in the attack, and was sentenced to four months imprisonment.

Michael had long disapproved of Elizabeth's relationship with Eric. Soon after the relationship began, Michael attacked Eric in [[The Woolpack]], and punched him to the floor. However, after the [[Emmerdale plane crash]] of 1993, in which Elizabeth died, Michael accused Eric of his mother's murder. Elizabeth had discovered Eric's involvement in a cheque fraud, for which Eric had framed Michael, and left him shortly afterwards to report him to the police. However, she died en-route, apparenty killed by falling debris from the plane. However, Michael, as well as other villagers, had suspected Eric of murder. This accusation was strengthened when Eric's first wife, Eileen appeared, claiming that Eric's marriage to Elizabeth had been bigamous. This led to a heated confrontation between Michael and Eric, and the two men had a fight which left Eric unconscious on the floor. Scared that he had killed Eric, Michael fled the village in Eric's car, which was later found abandoned at the airport, revealing that Michael had fled the country.

Nothing was seen or heard of Michael for 16 years until December 2010, when Eric began receiving letters, messages and cards, claiming to be from Elizabeth. Originally suspecting the messages to be sent by [[Amy Wyatt]], it was revealed on 30 December that the messages had instead been sent by Michael. Michael, who had been spending periods of time in-and-out of jail, confronted Eric at Elizabeth's grave. He later followed Eric back to The Grange, where he again confronted Eric, prompting him to reveal his history to his current wife, [[Val Pollard|Val]]. Michael then left. However, he later informed Amy that he wanted Eric to pay him a large sum or money, otherwise he would reveal Eric to be a murderer. Eric told Michael to come in his car with him, and he would pay him off. Eric drove Michael to a remote area however, and, after an exchange of words, Eric produced a [[tyre iron]], advancing on Michael, who cowered into a corner. The result of the incident was not revealed. Eric returned to Emmerdale alone, appearing at edge and nervous, telling Val that he had given Michael a lift to the station.

In fact, he hadn't dropped him off at the station but he wasn't dead either and turned up on 4 January to confront Eric again. Eric said that he couldn't have anymore money and Val told him that he had probably seen the coroner's report that stated his mother was killed by falling debris and that it was time to give up blaming Eric. He agreed and after a calm discussion, Eric persuaded Michael to take the money for looking after himself. Michael then got in a car and drove out of the village into the night.
{{-}}

==Peter Whiteley==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|color=#99CCCC
|image1= 
|name=Pete Whiteley Jr.
|portrayer=
|years=1990-1994
|first=28 August 1990
|last=4 August 1994
|born=28 August 1990
|death=
|parents=[[Pete Whiteley]], [[Lynn Whiteley]]
|grandparents=[[Bill Whiteley]]
}}

'''Peter Whiteley''' was the son of Pete and Lynn Whiteley and appeared from 1990 to 1994 during the first four years of his life. He was born on the same day of the funeral of his father, Pete, who had been run over and killed by his lover's mother [[Kate Sugden]]. Lynn began to raise Peter as a single mother. On the night of the plane crash, Lynn left Peter with a babysitter whilst she went to The Woolpack and Whiteley's Farm was hit by falling debris from the plame and set on fire. The babysitter managed to get out of the house and save Peter and he was later reunited with his mother, although their home was destroyed. Peter left the village with his mother to live with her new lover, a Swede called Olsen, in Australia in August 1994.
{{-}}

[[Category:Emmerdale characters| ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
