<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3026234" ns="0" title="KateOS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=March 2008}}
{{Advert|date=March 2008}}
{{Infobox_OS |
  name = KateOS |
  screenshot = &lt;!-- Do NOT change the screenshot unless there is BIG change in the UI. When taking screenshot, please resize your window (e.g. 640*480), disable your extensions and use the default theme. --&gt;&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:III-default.png|250px|KateOS III]]  --&gt;|
  caption = KateOS III running [[Xfce]] |
  developer = Damian Rakowski |
  family = [[Linux]] |
  source_model = [[Open source]] |
  working_state = Dormant |
  latest_release_version = 3.6 |
  latest_release_date = {{release date|2007|09|17}} |
  kernel_type = [[Monolithic kernel]] |
  license = Various |
  website = [http://www.kateos.org/ kateos.org] |
  logo = [[Image:III-logo.png|250px]]
}}
'''KateOS''' is a [[Linux distribution]] originally based on [[Slackware]]. It is designed for intermediate users. Its package management system uses so called TGZex (.tgz) packages, which unlike Slackware packages support dependency tracking (optional), internationalized descriptions, and are much easier to update. There are two native tools for package management: ''PKG'' and ''Updateos''.
The current version of KateOS is KateOS III (3.6), and is also available as a [[Live CD]].

== History ==
The KateOS project was founded at the end of 2003. The founder and current leader is Damian Rakowski.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! KateOS version
! Release date
|-
| 1.0
| 9 October 2004
|-
| 2.0
| 9 April 2005
|-
| 2.1
| 23 June 2005
|-
| 2.3
| 13 October 2005
|-
| 3.0
| 9 July 2006
|-
| 3.1
| 7 October 2006
|-
| 3.2
| 21 December 2006
|-
| 3.6
| 17 September 2007
|}

'''Kate Linux 1.0 Rabbit (series I)'''

The first version of the system was published on 2004-10-09. The system was based on Slackware 9.0 but unlike Slackware, it used the [[Pluggable Authentication Modules|PAM]] authentication mechanism, and possessed an enriched package set.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} Due to the problems with the main server which worked only infrequently, hardly anyone learned about the existence of Kate 1.0.  After a move to another server, the project has begun to gradually acquire users. After some time, Kate 1.0.1 (a fix release including UpdatePack 1), and a Live version were published.

'''Kate Linux 2.0 [[Zyklon B|Zyklon]] (series II)'''

Version 2.0 was published on 2005-04-09, and was no longer based on Slackware. It was a long-term edition, the base for further development. It was also the first edition using Linux 2.6.

On 2005-05-06 the name of the project has been changed to KateOS.

On 2005-05-22 version '''2.0.1''' was published, providing a tool for managing and remote updating the TGZex packages. The tool was called Updateos, and was written by Piotr Korzuszek.

On 2005-06-23 version '''2.1''' was published. Updateos now could install packages remotely.

On 12 August 2005  the first '''Live''' edition of series II was published. It had a more distinctive graphical design, used the [[squashfs]] technology (2 GB of data packed on just one CD) and [[unionfs]]. It detected the hardware and configured the [[X Window System|X Server]] automatically.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

On 2005-10-13 the last version of series II was published - '''2.3'''. Updateos gained new possibilities, and the system had a better hardware autodetection with the Discover tool.

'''KateOS 3.0 Virgin (series III)'''

On 12 April 2006  the first snapshot of KateOS 3.0 was published.

On 2006-07-09 the long awaited{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} version '''3.0''' was published. It has entirely been built from scratch, based on the most up-to-date components.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} The packaging system has been completely rewritten resulting in the [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/PKG-en PKG] and [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/Updateos-en Updateos2] tools, and the libupdateos and libsmarttools libraries. Again the functionality of the TGZex packages has been widened, this time to include dependency tracking and descriptions in many languages. The installation process has been simplified to allow a full install in just 15 minutes. The system used [[udev]], [[D-Bus]] and [[HAL (software)|HAL]] to detect hardware and mount devices automatically.

On 4 August 2006  the first '''Live'' edition of series III was published. It was aimed to demonstrate the possibilities of KateOS 3.0, and to be used as a data rescue system. The CD contained 2GB of data, including the [[Xfce]] desktop environment and many office and multimedia applications. It detected and configured hardware automatically, yielding a fully usable system in a few minutes' time.

On 7 October 2006  version '''3.1''' was published. It contained fixes, and the updated [[GNOME]] desktop environment. It was the first edition of Gnome adjusted especially to the KateOS system. It also included [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/Update-notifier-en Update-notifier], a [[Daemon (computer software)|daemon]] whose system trace icon changes and blinks when update possibilities are discovered. It let the user easily chose packages to be updated and update them. It was based on the libupdateos library, and only supported the KateOS packages and repositories.

On 21 December 2006  version '''3.2''' was published. Apart from fixes and updates, it included a new tool, [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/KatePKG-en KatePKG]. KatePKG is a graphical package manager written in [[PHP]] with the [[PHP-GTK]] library, making KateOS the first system to include this library in the default distribution.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} It allows the user to easily install, update, and remove packages from the system. It supports any number of repositories, including local ones (located on the user's hard drive). Also, the libsmarttools library has been thoroughly reviewed and optimized, resulting in up to a 60% speed boost in the applications using it (such as [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/Updateos-en Updateos2]).{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} With this version KateOS has switched its bootloader from [[LILO (boot loader)|LILO]] to [[GNU GRUB|GRUB]], hoping that it would better satisfy users' needs and make kernel updates easier.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}}

On 17 September 2007  version '''3.6''' was released after eight months of development. This version brought several new and updated features to KateOS such as software driven [[suspend mode]], improved internalization support,{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} and the addition of several new programs such as [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/KateLAN-en KateLAN] and [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/Realm-en Realm] to help make configuring the system more user friendly. The [[Live CD]] version of 3.6 was the first KateOS to sport an on disc installer called [http://wikidoc.kateos.org/index.php/Installos-en Install Agent], allowing the user to directly install to their hard disk after trying the system live.

== Additional information ==
All new KateOS releases are supported for around two years.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} Users are encouraged to update via the updateos command to newer versions of the distribution, although major version updates (series updates), e.g. II---&gt;III are not recommended.

Damian Rakowski, the 'project initiator, leader, and 1st developer', stated that the project was named after a friend and because the name Kate is &quot;simple, nice and everybody knows it.&quot; [http://www.tuxmachines.org/node/1611]

== Further reading ==
* Preston St. Pierre (May 10, 2005) ''[http://www.linux.com/archive/articles/44650 Review: Kate OS 2.0]'', [[Linux.com]]
* [[Michael Larabel]] (February 12, 2007) ''[http://www.michaellarabel.com/index.php?k=blog&amp;i=46 KateOS 3.2: Installation Made Easy]'', michaellarabel.com

== External links ==
* [http://kateos.org/ Official site]
* [http://kateos.org/?sekcja=relIII The official description of series III]
* {{DistroWatch|kateos|NAME=KateOS}}

{{Xfce}}
{{linux-distro}}

[[Category:Slackware]]

[[pl:KateOS]]
[[sv:KateOS]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
