<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="302812" ns="0" title="Color vision"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Psychophysical.svg|thumb|White light shone onto a green surface is perceived as green by the human eye, and processed as such in the brain's visual cortex.]]

[[File:Filterstef.JPG|thumb|[[wikt:Special:Search/colourless|Colorless]], [[green]], and [[red]] [[photographic filter]]s as imaged (&quot;[[perception|perceived]]&quot;) by [[digital camera]]]]

'''Color vision''' is the capacity of an organism or machine to distinguish objects based on the [[wavelength]]s (or [[frequency|frequencies]]) of the [[light]] they reflect, emit, or transmit. [[Color]]s can be measured and quantified in various ways; indeed, a human's perception of colors is a subjective process whereby the [[brain]] responds to the stimuli that are produced when incoming light reacts with the several types of [[Cone cell|cone photoreceptors]] in the [[eye]].

== Wavelength and hue detection ==

[[Isaac Newton]] discovered that white light splits into its component colors when passed through a prism, but that if those bands of colored light pass through another and rejoin, they make a white beam. The characteristic colors are, from low to high frequency: red, orange, yellow, green, cyan, blue, violet. Sufficient differences in frequency give rise to a difference in perceived [[hue]]; the [[just noticeable difference]] in wavelength varies from about 1&amp;nbsp;nm in the [[blue-green]] and [[yellow]] wavelengths, to 10&amp;nbsp;nm and more in the red and blue. Though the eye can distinguish up to a few hundred hues, when those pure spectral colors are mixed together or diluted with white light, the number of distinguishable [[chromaticity|chromaticities]] can be quite high.

In very low light levels, vision is [[scotopic]]: light is detected by [[rod cell]]s of the retina. Rods are maximally sensitive to wavelengths near 500&amp;nbsp;nm, and play little, if any, role in color vision. In brighter light, such as daylight, vision is [[photopic]]: light is detected by [[cone cell]]s which are responsible for color vision. Cones are sensitive to a range of wavelengths, but are most sensitive to wavelengths near 555&amp;nbsp;nm. Between these regions,  [[mesopic vision]] comes into play and both rods and cones provide signals to the [[retinal ganglion cell]]s. The shift in color perception from dim light to daylight gives rise  to differences known as the [[Purkinje effect]].

The perception of &quot;white&quot; is formed by the entire spectrum of visible light, or by mixing colors of just a few wavelengths, such as red, green, and blue, or by mixing just a pair of [[complementary color]]s such as blue and yellow.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Eye, human.&quot; ''[[Encyclopædia Britannica 2006 Ultimate Reference Suite DVD]]'', 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Physiology of color perception ==

[[File:Cone-fundamentals-with-srgb-spectrum.svg|right|thumb|287px|Normalized response spectra of human cones, S, M, and L types, to monochromatic spectral stimuli, with wavelength given in nanometers.]]

[[File:Spectrum locus 12.png|thumb|287px|The same figures as above represented here as a single curve in three (normalized cone response) dimensions]]

[[File:Eyesensitivity.png|thumb|287px|Relative brightness sensitivity of the human visual system as a function of wavelength]]

Perception of color begins with specialized retinal cells containing pigments with different [[spectral sensitivity|spectral sensitivities]], known as [[cone cell]]s. In humans, there are three types of cones sensitive to three difference spectra, resulting in [[trichromatic color vision]].

The cones are conventionally labeled according to the ordering of the wavelengths of the peaks of their [[spectral sensitivity|spectral sensitivities]]: short (S), medium (M), and long (L) cone types. These three types do not correspond well to particular colors as we know them. Rather, the perception of color is achieved by a complex process that starts with the differential output of these cells in the retina and it will be finalized in the visual cortex and associative areas of the brain.

For example, while the L cones have been referred to simply as [[red]] receptors, microspectrophotometry has shown that their peak sensitivity is in the greenish-yellow region of the spectrum. Similarly, the S- and M-cones do not directly correspond to [[blue]] and [[green]], although they are often depicted as such. It is important to note that the [[RGB color model]] is merely a convenient means for representing color, and is not directly based on the types of cones in the human eye.

The peak response of human cone cells varies, even among individuals with 'normal' color vision;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Neitz J, Jacobs GH |title=Polymorphism of the long-wavelength cone in normal human color vision |journal=Nature |volume=323 |issue=6089 |pages=623–5 |year=1986 |pmid=3773989 |doi=10.1038/323623a0 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v323/n6089/abs/323623a0.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
in non-human species this polymorphic variation is even greater, and it may well be adaptive.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Jacobs GH |title=Primate photopigments and primate color vision |journal=Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. |volume=93 |issue=2 |pages=577–81 |year=1996 |month=January |pmid=8570598 |pmc=40094 |doi=10.1073/pnas.93.2.577 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Theories of color vision ===

Two complementary theories of color vision are the [[trichromatic theory]] and the [[opponent process]] theory. The trichromatic theory, or [[Young–Helmholtz theory]], proposed in the 19th century by [[Thomas Young (scientist)|Thomas Young]] and [[Hermann von Helmholtz]], as mentioned above, states that the retina's three types of cones are preferentially sensitive to blue, green, and red. [[Ewald Hering]] proposed the opponent process theory in 1872.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|title=Zur Lehre vom Lichtsinne |journal=Sitzungsberichte der Mathematisch–Naturwissenschaftliche Classe der Kaiserlichen Akademie der Wissenschaften |issue=III Abtheilung |volume=LXVI. Band |first=Ewald |last=Hering |authorlink=Ewald Hering |year=1872 | url=http://books.google.com/?id=u5MCAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA5&amp;lpg=PA5&amp;dq=1872+hering+ewald+Zur+Lehre+vom+Lichtsinne.+Sitzungsberichte+der+kaiserlichen+Akademie+der+Wissenschaften.+Mathematisch%E2%80%93naturwissenschaftliche+Classe, |publisher=K.-K. Hof- und Staatsdruckerei in Commission bei C. Gerold's Sohn}}&lt;/ref&gt; It states that the visual system interprets color in an antagonistic way: red vs. green, blue vs. yellow, black vs. white.  We now know both theories to be correct, describing different stages in visual physiology.&lt;ref name=Ali&amp;Klyne1985p168&gt;Ali, M.A. &amp; Klyne, M.A. (1985), p.168&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cone cells in the human eye ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Cone type || Name || Range || Peak wavelength&lt;ref name=Wyszecki&gt;{{Cite book
 | first = Günther
 | last = Wyszecki
 | coauthors = Stiles, W.S.
 | year = 1982
 | title = Color Science: Concepts and Methods, Quantitative Data and Formulae
 | edition = 2nd
 | publisher = Wiley Series in Pure and Applied Optics
 | location = New York
 | isbn = 0-471-02106-7
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
 | author = R. W. G. Hunt
 | year = 2004
 | title = The Reproduction of Colour
 | edition = 6th
 | pages = 11–2
 | publisher = Wiley–IS&amp;T Series in Imaging Science and Technology
 | location = Chichester UK
 | isbn = 0-470-02425-9
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|S || β  || 400–500 [[Nanometre|nm]] || 420–440&amp;nbsp;nm
|-
|M || γ  || 450–630&amp;nbsp;nm || 534–555&amp;nbsp;nm
|-
|L || ρ  || 500–700&amp;nbsp;nm || 564–580&amp;nbsp;nm
|}

A range of wavelengths of light stimulates each of these receptor types to varying degrees. Yellowish-green light, for example, stimulates both L and M cones equally strongly, but only stimulates S-cones weakly.  Red light, on the other hand, stimulates L cones much more than M cones, and S cones hardly at all; blue-green light stimulates M cones more than L cones, and S cones a bit more strongly, and is also the peak stimulant for rod cells; and [[blue]] light stimulates S cones more strongly than red or green light, but L and M cones more weakly. The brain combines the information from each type of receptor to give rise to different perceptions of different wavelengths of light.

The opsins (photopigments) present in the L and M cones are encoded on the X [[chromosome]]; defective encoding of these leads to the two most common forms of [[color blindness]]. The [[OPN1LW]] gene, which codes for the opsin present in the L cones, is highly [[polymorphism (biology)|polymorphic]] (a recent study by Verrelli and Tishkoff found 85 variants in a sample of 236 men&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Verrelli BC, Tishkoff SA |title=Signatures of Selection and Gene Conversion Associated with Human Color Vision Variation |journal=Am. J. Hum. Genet. |volume=75 |issue=3 |pages=363–75 |year=2004 |month=September |pmid=15252758 |pmc=1182016 |doi=10.1086/423287 }}&lt;/ref&gt;). A very small percentage of women may have an extra type of color receptor because they have different alleles for the gene for the L opsin on each X chromosome. [[X chromosome inactivation]] means that only one opsin is expressed in each cone cell, and some women may therefore show a degree of [[tetrachromat]]ic color vision.&lt;ref&gt;Roth, Mark (2006). [http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/06256/721190-114.stm &quot;Some women may see 100 million colors, thanks to their genes&quot;] ''Post-Gazette.com''&lt;/ref&gt; Variations in [[OPN1MW]], which codes the opsin expressed in M cones, appear to be rare, and the observed variants have no effect on [[spectral sensitivity]].

=== Color in the human brain ===
[[File:Ventral-dorsal streams.svg|thumb|right|300px|Visual pathways in the human brain.  The [[ventral stream]] (purple) is important in color recognition.  The [[dorsal stream]] (green) is also shown.  They originate from a common source in the [[visual cortex]].]]

Color processing begins at a very early level in the visual system (even within the retina) through initial color opponent mechanisms. Both Helmholtz's trichromatic theory, and Hering's opponent process theory are therefore correct, but trichromacy arises at the level of the receptors, and opponent processes arise at the level of [[retinal ganglion cells]] and beyond.  In Hering's theory opponent mechanisms refer to the opposing color effect of red–green, blue–yellow, and light–dark. However, in the visual system, it is the activity of the different receptor types that are opposed. Some midget retinal ganglion cells oppose L and M cone activity, which corresponds loosely to red–green opponency, but actually runs along an axis from blue-green to magenta. Small bistratified retinal ganglion cells oppose input from the S cones to input from the L and M cones. This is often thought to correspond to blue–yellow opponency, but actually runs along a color axis from lime green to violet.

Visual information is then sent to the brain from retinal ganglion cells via the [[optic nerve]] to the [[optic chiasma]]: a point where the two optic nerves meet and information from the temporal (contralateral) visual field crosses to the other side of the brain. After the optic chiasma the visual tracts are referred to as the [[optic tract]]s, which enter the [[thalamus]] to synapse at the [[lateral geniculate nucleus]] (LGN).

The [[lateral geniculate nucleus|LGN]] is divided into laminae (zones), of which there three types: the M-laminae, consisting primarily of M-cells, the P-laminae, consisting primarily of P-cells, and the koniocellular laminae.  M- and P-cells received relatively balanced input from both L- and M-cones throughout most of the retina, although this seems to not be the case at the fovea, with midget cells synapsing in the P-laminae.  The koniocellular laminae receive axons from the small bistratified ganglion cells.&lt;ref name = &quot;The First Steps in Seeing&quot;&gt;R.W. Rodieck, &quot;The First Steps in Seeing&quot;. Sinauer Associates, Inc., Sunderland, Massachusetts, USA, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;The Koniocellular Pathway in Primate Vision&quot;&gt;[http://www.annualreviews.org/doi/abs/10.1146/annurev.neuro.23.1.127?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%3dncbi.nlm.nih.gov SH Hendry, RC Reid, &quot;The Koniocellular Pathway in Primate Vision&quot;. Annual Reviews Neuroscience, 2000, vol. 23, pp. 127-53]&lt;/ref&gt;

After [[Synapse|synapsing]] at the LGN, the visual tract continues on back to the primary [[visual cortex]] (V1) located at the back of the brain within the [[occipital lobe]]. Within V1 there is a distinct band (striation). This is also referred to as &quot;striate cortex&quot;, with other cortical visual regions referred to collectively as &quot;extrastriate cortex&quot;. It is at this stage that color processing becomes much more complicated.

In V1 the simple three-color segregation begins to break down. Many cells in V1 respond to some parts of the spectrum better than others, but this &quot;color tuning&quot; is often different depending on the adaptation state of the visual system. A given cell that might respond best to long wavelength light if the light is relatively bright might then become responsive to all wavelengths if the stimulus is relatively dim. Because the color tuning of these cells is not stable, some believe that a different, relatively small, population of neurons in V1 is responsible for color vision. These specialized &quot;color cells&quot; often have receptive fields that can compute local cone ratios. Such &quot;double-opponent&quot; cells were initially described in the goldfish retina by Nigel Daw;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| doi = 10.1126/science.158.3803.942 | title = Goldfish Retina: Organization for Simultaneous Color Contrast | author = Nigel W. Daw | journal = Science | date = 17 November 1967 | volume = 158 | issue = 3803 | pages = 942–4 | pmid = 6054169 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Neural Mechanisms of Color Vision: Double-Opponent Cells in the Visual Cortex | author = Bevil R. Conway | url = http://books.google.com/?id=pFodUlHfQmcC&amp;pg=PR7&amp;dq=goldfish+retina+by+Nigel-Daw | publisher = Springer | year = 2002 | isbn = 1402070926 }}&lt;/ref&gt; their existence in primates was suggested by [[David H. Hubel]] and [[Torsten Wiesel]] and subsequently proven by [[Bevil Conway]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Conway BR |title=Spatial structure of cone inputs to color cells in alert macaque primary visual cortex (V-1) |journal=J. Neurosci. |volume=21 |issue=8 |pages=2768–83 |date=15 April 2001|pmid=11306629 |url=http://www.jneurosci.org/content/21/8/2768.full }}&lt;/ref&gt; As Margaret Livingstone and David Hubel showed, double opponent cells are clustered within localized regions of V1 called [[Blob (visual system)|blobs]], and are thought to come in two flavors, red–green and blue–yellow.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book| title = Neurons and Networks: An Introduction to Behavioral Neuroscience | author = John E. Dowling | publisher = Harvard University Press | year = 2001 | isbn = 0674004620 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=adeUwgfwdKwC&amp;pg=PA376&amp;dq=Margaret+Livingstone+David+Hubel+double+opponent+blobs }}&lt;/ref&gt; Red–green cells compare the relative amounts of red–green in one part of a scene with the amount of red–green in an adjacent part of the scene, responding best to local color contrast (red next to green). Modeling studies have shown that double-opponent cells are ideal candidates for the neural machinery of [[color constancy]] explained by [[Edwin H. Land]] in his [[retinex]] theory.&lt;ref&gt;McCann, M., ed. 1993. ''[[Edwin H. Land]]'s Essays.'' Springfield, Va.: Society for Imaging Science and Technology.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:1Mcolors.png|thumb|This image (when viewed in full size, 1000 pixels wide) contains 1 million pixels, each of a different color. The human eye can distinguish about 10 million different colors.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|first=Deane B. |last=Judd |coauthors=Wyszecki, Günter|title=Color in Business, Science and Industry |publisher=[[Wiley-Interscience]] |series=Wiley Series in Pure and Applied Optics |edition=3rd |location=New York |year= 1975 |page=388 |isbn=0471452122}}&lt;/ref&gt;
]]

From the V1 blobs, color information is sent to cells in the second visual area, V2. The cells in V2 that are most strongly color tuned are clustered in the &quot;thin stripes&quot; that, like the blobs in V1, stain for the enzyme cytochrome oxidase (separating the thin stripes are interstripes and thick stripes, which seem to be concerned with other visual information like motion and high-resolution form).  Neurons in V2 then synapse onto cells in the extended V4. This area includes not only  V4, but two other areas in the posterior inferior temporal cortex, anterior to area V3, the dorsal posterior inferior temporal cortex, and posterior TEO.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway07&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Conway BR, Moeller S, Tsao DY | year = 2007 | title = Specialized color modules in macaque extrastriate cortex | url = | journal = Neuron | volume = 56 | issue = 3| pages = 560–73 | pmid = 17988638 | doi = 10.1016/j.neuron.2007.10.008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | author = Conway BR, Tsao DY | year = 2009 | title = Color-tuned neurons are spatially clustered according to color preference within alert macaque posterior inferior temporal cortex | url = | journal = Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A | volume = 106 | issue = 42| pages = 18035–18039 | pmid = 19805195 | doi = 10.1073/pnas.0810943106 | pmc = 2764907 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (Area V4 was identified by [[Semir Zeki]] to be exclusively dedicated to color, but this has since been shown not to be the case.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=John Allman and Steven W. Zucker |chapter=On cytochrome oxidase blobs in visual cortex | title = Spatial Vision in Humans and Robots: The Proceedings of the 1991 York Conference | editor =  Laurence Harris and Michael Jenkin, editors | year = 1993 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | isbn = 0521430712 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=eWBiKaOCNIYC&amp;pg=PA34&amp;dq=v4+zeki+color }}&lt;/ref&gt; Color processing in the extended V4 occurs in millimeter-sized color modules called [[glob (visual system)|glob]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway07&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway&quot;/&gt; This is the first part of the brain in which color is processed in terms of the full range of [[hue]]s found in [[color space]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway07&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway&quot;/&gt;

Anatomical studies have shown that neurons in extended V4 provide input to the inferior [[temporal lobe]] . &quot;IT&quot; cortex is thought to integrate color information with shape and form, although it has been difficult to define the appropriate criteria for this claim. Despite this murkiness, it has been useful to characterize this pathway (V1 &gt; V2 &gt; V4 &gt; IT) as the [[ventral stream]] or the &quot;what pathway&quot;, distinguished from the [[dorsal stream]] (&quot;where pathway&quot;) that is thought to analyze motion, among many other features.

=== Subjectivity of color perception ===
{{Essay-like|section|date=May 2011}}
[[File:Rainbow comparison.png|right|thumb|287px|Side by side comparison of the same rainbow photo in color and monochrome. The stripes of color, perceived vividly by most people, totally disappear when the color saturation is set to zero.]]
It has been established&lt;ref&gt;Roberson, Davidoff, Davies &amp; Shapiro. referred by Debi Roberson, University of Essex 2011&lt;/ref&gt; that the [[Himba people]] perceive colors differently from most Euro-Americans - they easily distinguish close shades of green, barely discernable for most people. The leading explanation is that the Himba created a very different color scheme which divides the spectrum to dark shades (Zuzu in Himba), very light (Vapa),  Vivid blue and green (Buru) and dry colors - probably due to their specific way of life. However other explanations exist that have not been ruled out yet.

An example of the subjectivity of color occurs in a rainbow. In a rainbow (or a spectrum of light projected from a prism), the changes between wavelengths of light are smooth and continuous; there are no breaks or boundaries corresponding to the &quot;bands of color&quot; which are seen subjectively by the eye. A black-and-white photograph of a rainbow shows no band stucture at all, demonstrating that the number of bands, and the bands themselves, are phenomena added to nature by the eye and the brain. They are not objectively real any more than &quot;hot&quot; or &quot;cold.&quot;

The cone photoreceptors, which begin the process that results in the ultimate sensation of color in the brain, are sensitive to different portions of the [[visible spectrum]]. For humans, the visible spectrum ranges approximately from 380 to 740&amp;nbsp;nm, and there are normally three types of cones. The number of colors that can be distinguished by these cones is in principle unlimited and in practice extremely large.

The sensation of color is also heavily dependent on contrast with surroundings. For example, a 'red' piece of construction paper or red filing folder does not reflect pure monochromatic &quot;red&quot; light.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=Wright, W. D. |title=The rays are not coloured: essays on the science and vision and colour |publisher=Hilger |location=Bristol |year=1967 |isbn=0-85274-068-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather, it absorbs a larger fraction of other [[frequency#Frequency of waves|frequencies]] of [[visible light]] shining upon it than those in a group of frequencies that are perceived as red when they are viewed alone. However, although the red paper reflects more of light near the red end of the spectrum, it reflects some of all frequencies (not only red), and a room lit with only the reflection from a red piece of paper would soon appear to be normally lit to an adapted eye,{{citation needed|date=May 2011}} and would allow visualization of all of the other colors present in the room. A red-colored paper is therefore perceived to be red mainly by contrast with its surroundings, because the [[human eye]] can distinguish between different wavelengths, and the brain creates the separate sensation of &quot;red&quot; as a helper in discriminating one object from another, or from its background. Color, which in nature is never constructed from pure frequencies of light, is a quality constructed by the visual brain from spectral reflectance, the objective property of objects. The advantage of color perception is the better discrimination of surfaces allowed by this aspect of visual processing, which makes quite similar surfaces into very different perceptions.

=== In animals ===
The visible range and number of cone types differ between species. Mammals in general have color vision of a limited type, and are usually red-green color-blind, with only two types of cones. Humans, some primates, and some marsupials see an extended range of colors, but only by comparison with other mammals. Most non-mammalian vertebrate species distinguish different colors at least as well as humans, and many species of birds, fish, reptiles and amphibians, as well as some invertebrates, have more than three cone types and probably superior color vision to humans.

In most [[Catarrhini]] (Old World monkeys and apes — primates closely related to humans) there are three types of [[color receptors]] (known as [[cone cell]]s), resulting in [[trichromatic color vision]]. These primates, like humans, are known as [[Trichromacy|trichromats]]. Many other primates and other mammals are [[dichromat]]s, which is the general color vision state for mammals that are active during the day (i.e., felines, canines, ungulates). Nocturnal mammals may have little or no color vision. Trichromat non-primate  mammals are rare.&lt;ref name=Ali&amp;Klyne1985&gt;{{Cite book|last=Ali|first=Mohamed Ather|last2=Klyne|first2=M.A.|title=Vision in Vertebrates|place=New York|publisher=Plenum Press|year=1985|pages=174–175|isbn=0-306-42065-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;For .pdf online review see: [http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1469-185X.1993.tb00738.x/abstract] THE DISTRIBUTION AND NATURE OF COLOUR VISION AMONG THE MAMMALS. GERALD H. JACOBS
Biological Reviews Volume 68, Issue 3, pages 413–471, August 1993. DOI: 10.1111/j.1469-185X.1993.tb00738.x&lt;/ref&gt;

Many [[Invertebrate|invertebrates]] have color vision. [[Bees|Honey- and bumblebees]] have trichromatic color vision, which is insensitive to red but sensitive in ultraviolet. In view of the importance of colour vision to bees one might expect these receptor sensitivities to reflect their specific visual ecology; for example the types of flowers that they visit. However, the main groups of hymenopteran insects excluding ants (i.e. bees, wasps and sawflies) mostly have three types of photoreceptor, with spectral sensitivities similar the honeybee’s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |author= Osorio D, Vorobyev M | title=A review of the evolution of animal colour vision and visual communication signals  journal=Vision Research | volume=48 |pages=2042–2051 |year=2008 | month = June | doi=10.1016/j.visres}}&lt;/ref&gt;''[[Papilio]]'' butterflies possess six types of photoreceptors and may have pentachromatic vision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Arikawa K |title=Spectral organization of the eye of a butterfly, Papilio |journal=J. Comp. Physiol. A Neuroethol. Sens. Neural. Behav. Physiol. |volume=189 |issue=11 |pages=791–800 |year=2003 |month=November |pmid=14520495 |doi=10.1007/s00359-003-0454-7 |url=http://www.springerlink.com/content/whjepqnhpulyeevk/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most complex color vision system in animal kingdom has been found in [[stomatopod]]s (such as the [[mantis shrimp]]) with up to 12 different spectral receptor types thought to work as multiple dichromatic units.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Cronin TW, Marshall NJ |title=A retina with at least ten spectral types of photoreceptors in a mantis shrimp |journal=Nature |volume=339 |pages=137–40 |year=1989 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v339/n6220/abs/339137a0.html |doi=10.1038/339137a0 |issue=6220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Vertebrate animals such as tropical [[fish]] and [[birds]] sometimes have more complex color vision systems than humans; thus the many subtle colors they exhibit generally serve as direct signals between fish or between birds, and are not intended to signal mammals.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Kelber A, Vorobyev M, Osorio D |title=Animal color vision—behavioural tests and physiological concepts |journal=Biol Rev Camb Philos Soc |volume=78 |issue=1 |pages=81–118 |year=2003 |month=February |pmid=12620062 |doi=10.1017/S1464793102005985}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the birds, [[tetrachromacy]] is achieved through up to four [[Cone cell|cone]] types, depending on species.Each single cone contains one of the four main
types of vertebrate cone photopigment (LWS/ MWS, RH2, SWS2 and SWS1and has a coloured oil droplet in its inner segment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal |author= Osorio D, Vorobyev M | title=A review of the evolution of animal colour vision and visual communication signals  journal=Vision Research | volume=48 |pages=2042–2051 |year=2008 | month = June | doi=10.1016/j.visres}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brightly colored [[oil droplet]]s inside the cones shift or narrow the spectral sensitivity of the cell. It has been suggested that it is likely that [[pigeon]]s are [[pentachromat]]s.

Reptiles and amphibians also have four cone types (occasionally five), and probably see at least the same number of colors that humans do, or perhaps more. In addition, some nocturnal [[gecko]]s have the capability of [[Gecko#Nocturnal vision|seeing color in dim light]].&lt;ref name=&quot;GeckoNocturnalVision&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Roth, Lina S. V.; Lundström, Linda; Kelber, Almut; Kröger, Ronald H. H.; Unsbo, Peter |title=The pupils and optical systems of gecko eyes |doi=10.1167/9.3.27 |journal=Journal of Vision | date=March 30, 2009 |volume=9 |issue=3:27 |pages=1–11 |url=http://www.journalofvision.org/content/9/3/27 |pmid=19757966}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the evolution of mammals, segments of color vision were lost, then for a few species of primates, regained by [[gene duplication]]. [[Eutherian]] mammals other than primates (for example, dogs, cats, mammalian farm animals) generally have less-effective two-receptor ([[dichromat]]ic) color perception systems, which distinguish blue, green, and yellow—but cannot distinguish oranges and reds. The adaptation to see reds is particularly important for primate mammals, since it leads to identification of fruits, and also newly sprouting reddish leaves, which are particularly nutritious.

However, even among primates, full color vision differs between New World and Old World monkeys. Old World primates, including monkeys and all apes, have vision similar to humans. [[New World monkeys]] may or may not have color sensitivity at this level: in most species, males are dichromats, and about 60% of females are trichromats, but the [[owl monkey]]s are cone [[monochromacy|monochromats]], and both sexes of [[howler monkey]]s are trichromats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Jacobs G. H., Deegan J. F. | year = 2001 | title = Photopigments and color vision in New World monkeys from the family Atelidae | url = | journal = Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B | volume = 268 | issue = 1468| pages = 695–702 | doi = 10.1098/rspb.2000.1421 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Jacobs G. H., Deegan J. F., Neitz , Neitz J., Crognale M. A. | year = 1993 | title = Photopigments and color vision in the nocturnal monkey, ''Aotus'' | url = | journal = Vision Research | volume = 33 | issue = 13| pages = 1773–1783 | doi = 10.1016/0042-6989(93)90168-V | pmid = 8266633 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Mollon J. D., Bowmaker J. K., Jacobs G. H. | year = 1984 | title = Variations of color vision in a New World primate can be explained by polymorphism of retinal photopigments | url = | journal = Proceedings of the Royal Society of London, Series B | volume = 222 | issue = 1228| pages = 373–399 | doi = 10.1098/rspb.1984.0071 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sternberg, Robert J. (2006): Cognitive Psychology. 4th Ed. Thomson Wadsworth.&lt;/ref&gt; Visual sensitivity differences between males and females in a single species is due to the gene for yellow-green sensitive [[opsin]] protein (which confers ability to differentiate red from green) residing on the X sex chromosome.

Several [[marsupial]]s such as the [[fat-tailed dunnart]] (''Sminthopsis crassicaudata'') have been shown to have trichromatic color vision.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Arrese CA, Beazley LD, Neumeyer C |title=Behavioural evidence for marsupial trichromacy |journal=Curr. Biol. |volume=16 |issue=6 |pages=R193–4 |year=2006 |month=March |pmid=16546067 |doi=10.1016/j.cub.2006.02.036 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Marine mammal]]s, adapted for low-light vision, have only a single cone type and are thus [[monochromat]]s.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

== Evolution ==
{{Main|Evolution of color vision}}
Color perception mechanisms are highly dependent on evolutionary factors, of which the most prominent is thought to be satisfactory recognition of food sources. In [[herbivorous]] primates, color perception is essential for finding proper (immature) leaves. In [[hummingbird]]s, particular flower types are often recognized by color as well. On the other hand, [[nocturnal]] mammals have less-developed color vision, since adequate light is needed for cones to function properly. There is evidence that [[ultraviolet]] light plays a part in color perception in many branches of the [[animal|animal kingdom]], especially [[insect]]s.  In general, the optical spectrum encompasses the most common [[Molecular electronic transition|electronic transitions]] in matter and is therefore the most useful for collecting information about the environment.

The [[Evolution of color vision in primates|evolution of trichromatic color vision in primates]] occurred as the ancestors of modern monkeys, apes, and humans switched to [[Diurnal animal|diurnal]] (daytime) activity and began consuming fruits and leaves from flowering plants.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Steven Pinker|Pinker, Steven]] |title=[[How the Mind Works]] |publisher=Norton |location=New York |year=1997 |page=191 |isbn=0-393-04535-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Color vision, with UV discrimination, is also present in a number of arthropods – the only terrestrial animals besides the vertebrates to possess this trait.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1007/s00239-008-9065-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some animals can distinguish colors in the ultraviolet spectrum. The UV spectrum falls outside the human visible range, except for some [[cataract surgery]] patients.&lt;ref name=Hambling&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/science/2002/may/30/medicalscience.research | title=Let the light shine in: You don't have to come from another planet to see ultraviolet light | publisher=EducationGuardian.co.uk | author=David Hambling | date=May 30, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Birds, turtles, lizards, many fish and some rodents have UV receptors in their retinas.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|author=Jacobs GH, Neitz J, Deegan JF |title=Retinal receptors in rodents maximally sensitive to ultraviolet light |journal=Nature |volume=353 |issue=6345 |pages=655–6 |year=1991 |pmid=1922382 |doi=10.1038/353655a0 |url=http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v353/n6345/abs/353655a0.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; These animals can see the UV patterns found on flowers and other wildlife that are otherwise invisible to the human eye.

UV and multi-dimensional vision{{Clarify|date=June 2009}} is an especially important adaptation in birds. It allows birds to spot small prey from a distance, navigate, avoid predators, and forage while flying at high speeds.  Birds also utilize their broad spectrum vision to recognize other birds, and in sexual selection.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|author=FJ Varela, AG Palacios, and TM Goldsmith |editor=Bischof, Hans-Joachim; Zeigler, H. Philip |title=Vision, brain, and behavior in birds |publisher=MIT Press |location=Cambridge, Mass |year=1993 |pages=77–94 |isbn=0-262-24036-X }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Advances in the Study of Behavior |author=IC Cuthill, JC Partridge, ATD Bennett, SC Church, NS Hart, and S Hunt |chapter=Ultraviolet Vision in Birds |year=2000 |volume=29 |pages=159–214 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Mathematics of color perception ==
A &quot;physical color&quot; is a combination of pure [[spectral color]]s (in the visible range).  Since there are, in principle, infinitely many distinct spectral colors, the set of all physical colors may be thought of as an infinite-dimensional [[vector space]], in fact a [[Hilbert space]].  We call this space ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;. More technically, the space of physical colors may be considered to be the (mathematical) [[cone (topology)|cone]] over the simplex whose vertices are the spectral colors, with white at the [[centroid]] of the simplex, black at the apex of the cone, and the monochromatic color associated with any given vertex somewhere along the line from that vertex to the apex depending on its brightness.

An element ''C'' of ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt; is a function from the range of visible wavelengths—considered as an interval of real numbers [''W''&lt;sub&gt;min&lt;/sub&gt;,''W''&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;]—to the real numbers, assigning to each wavelength ''w'' in [''W''&lt;sub&gt;min&lt;/sub&gt;,''W''&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;] its intensity ''C''(''w'').

A humanly perceived color may be modeled as three numbers: the extents to which each of the 3 types of cones is stimulated. Thus a humanly perceived color may be thought of as a point in 3-dimensional [[Euclidean space]]. We call this space '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;.

Since each wavelength ''w'' stimulates each of the 3 types of cone cells to a known extent, these extents may be represented by 3 functions ''s''(''w''), ''m''(''w''), ''l''(''w'') corresponding to the response of the ''S'', ''M'', and ''L'' cone cells, respectively.

Finally, since a beam of light can be composed of many different wavelengths, to determine the extent to which a physical color ''C'' in ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt; stimulates each cone cell, we must calculate the integral (with respect to ''w''), over the interval [''W''&lt;sub&gt;min&lt;/sub&gt;,''W''&lt;sub&gt;max&lt;/sub&gt;], of ''C''(''w'')·''s''(''w''), of ''C''(''w'')·''m''(''w''), and of ''C''(''w'')·''l''(''w''). The triple of resulting numbers associates to each physical color ''C'' (which is an element in ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;) to a particular perceived color (which is a single point in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;). This association is easily seen to be linear. It may also easily be seen that many different elements in the &quot;physical&quot; space ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt; can all result in the same single perceived color in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;, so a perceived color is not unique to one physical color.

Thus human color perception is determined by a specific, non-unique linear mapping from the infinite-dimensional Hilbert space ''H''&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt; to the 3-dimensional Euclidean space '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;.

Technically, the image of the (mathematical) cone over the simplex whose vertices are the spectral colors, by this linear mapping, is also a (mathematical) cone in '''R'''&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sub&gt;color&lt;/sub&gt;.  Moving directly away from the vertex of this cone represents maintaining the same [[chromaticity]] while increasing its intensity. Taking a cross-section of this cone yields a 2D chromaticity space.  Both the 3D cone and its projection or cross-section are convex sets; that is, any mixture of spectral colors is also a color.

[[File:Cie Chart with sRGB gamut by spigget.png|thumb|right|300px|The CIE 1931 xy chromaticity diagram. The Planckian locus is shown with color temperatures labeled in degrees [[Kelvin]]. The outer curved boundary is the spectral (or monochromatic) locus, with wavelengths shown in nanometers (blue). Note that the colors in this file are being specified using sRGB. Areas outside the triangle cannot be accurately rendered because they are out of the gamut of sRGB, therefore they have been interpreted. Note that the colors depicted depend on the color space of the device you use to view the image (number of colors on your monitor, etc.), and may not be a strictly accurate representation of the color at a particular position.]]

In practice, it would be quite difficult to physiologically measure an individual's three cone responses to various physical color stimuli.   Instead, a psychophysical approach is taken.  Three specific benchmark test lights are typically used; let us call them ''S'', ''M'', and ''L''.  To calibrate human perceptual space, scientists allowed human subjects to try to match any physical color by turning dials to create specific combinations of intensities (''I''&lt;sub&gt;''S''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''M''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''L''&lt;/sub&gt;) for the ''S'', ''M'', and ''L'' lights, resp., until a match was found.  This needed only to be done for physical colors that are spectral (since a linear combination of spectral colors will be matched by the same linear combination of their (''I''&lt;sub&gt;''S''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''M''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''L''&lt;/sub&gt;) matches.  Note that in practice, often at least one of ''S'', ''M'', ''L'' would have to be added with some intensity to the ''physical test color'', and that combination matched by a linear combination of the remaining 2 lights. Across different individuals (without color blindness), the matchings turned out to be nearly identical.

By considering all the resulting combinations of intensities (''I''&lt;sub&gt;''S''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''M''&lt;/sub&gt;, ''I''&lt;sub&gt;''L''&lt;/sub&gt;) as a subset of 3-space, a model for human perceptual color space is formed.  (Note that when one of ''S'', ''M'', ''L'' had to be added to the test color, its intensity was counted as negative.)  Again, this turns out to be a (mathematical) cone, not a quadric, but rather all rays through the origin in 3-space passing through a certain convex set. Again, this cone has the property that moving directly away from the origin corresponds to increasing the intensity of the ''S'', ''M'', ''L'' lights proportionately. Again, a cross-section of this cone is a planar shape that is (by definition) the space of &quot;chromaticities&quot; (informally: distinct colors); one particular such cross section, corresponding to constant ''X''+''Y''+''Z'' of the [[CIE 1931 color space]], gives the CIE chromaticity diagram.

It should be noted that this system implies that for any hue or non-spectral color not on the boundary of the chromaticity diagram, there are infinitely many distinct physical spectra that are all perceived as that hue or color. So, in general there is no such thing as ''the'' combination of spectral colors that we perceive as (say) a specific version of tan; instead there are infinitely many possibilities that produce that exact color. The boundary colors that are pure spectral colors can be perceived only in response to light that is purely at the associated wavelength, while the boundary colors on the &quot;line of purples&quot; can each only be generated by a specific ratio of the pure violet and the pure red at the ends of the visible spectral colors.

The CIE chromaticity diagram is horseshoe-shaped, with its curved edge corresponding to all spectral colors (the ''spectral [[locus (mathematics)|locus]]''), and the remaining straight edge corresponding to the most saturated [[purple]]s, mixtures of [[red]] and [[Violet (color)|violet]].

== Chromatic adaptation ==
{{Main|Chromatic adaptation}}

In color science, '''chromatic adaptation''' is the estimation of the representation of an object under a different light source than the one in which it was recorded. A common application is to find a ''chromatic adaptation transform'' (CAT) that will make the recording of a neutral object appear neutral ([[color balance]]), while keeping other colors also looking realistic.&lt;ref&gt;Süsstrunk, Sabine. [http://ivrgwww.epfl.ch/research/past_topics/chromatic_adaptation.html Chromatic Adaptation]&lt;/ref&gt; For example, chromatic adaptation transforms are used when converting images between [[ICC profile]]s with different [[white point]]s. [[Adobe Photoshop]], for example, uses the Bradford CAT.&lt;ref&gt;Lindbloom, Bruce. [http://www.brucelindbloom.com/Eqn_ChromAdapt.html Chromatic Adaptation]&lt;/ref&gt;

In color vision, chromatic adaptation refers to [[color constancy]]; the ability of the visual system to preserve the appearance of an object under a wide range of light sources.&lt;ref name=CAM&gt;{{cite book|title=Color Appearance Models|first=Mark D.|last=Fairchild|chapter=8. Chromatic Adaptation|page=146|publisher=Wiley|isbn=0470012161|year=2005| url=http://books.google.com/?id=8_TxzK2B-5MC&amp;pg=PA146&amp;dq=%22chromatic+adaptation%22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Color vision}}
* [[Color blindness]]
* [[Color theory]]
* [[Inverted spectrum]]
* [[Primary color]]
* [[Visual perception]]

== References ==&lt;!-- ZoolSci22:1145,24:611. --&gt;

{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* Peter Gouras, [http://webvision.med.utah.edu/book/part-vii-color-vision/color-vision/ &quot;Color Vision&quot;], ''Webvision'', University of Utah School of Medicine, May 2009.
* Kenneth R. Koehler, [http://www.rwc.uc.edu/koehler/biophys/6d.html &quot;Spectral Sensitivity of the Eye&quot;], ''College Physics for Students of Biology and Chemistry'', University of Cincinnati Raymond Walters College, 1996.
* James T. Fulton, [http://www.neuronresearch.net/vision/files/tetrachromat.htm &quot;The Human is a Blocked Tetrachromat&quot;], ''Neural Concepts'', July 2009.
* Vurdlak, [http://www.moillusions.com/2009/03/mega-color-blindness-test.html &quot;Mega Color Blindness Test&quot;], ''Mighty Optical Illusions'', March 2009.
* Clive Maxfield and Alvin Brown, [http://www.diycalculator.com/sp-cvision.shtml &quot;Color Vision: One of Nature's Wonders&quot;], ''DIYCalculator.com'', 2006.
* Chenguang Lu, [http://survivor99.com/colorforum/The%20Decoding%20Model.html &quot;The decoding model: a symmetrical model of color vision&quot;].
* Egopont, [http://www.egopont.com/colorvision.php &quot;Color Vision Test&quot;].

{{Color vision}}
{{Color topics}}
{{Mental processes}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Color Vision}}
[[Category:Color]]
[[Category:Image processing]]
[[Category:Visual perception]]
[[Category:Perception]]

[[ar:رؤية اللون]]
[[cs:Barevné vidění]]
[[de:Farbwahrnehmung]]
[[es:Percepción del color]]
[[fr:Vision#Vision des couleurs]]
[[ko:색채 지각]]
[[hi:संयोजी वर्ण]]
[[hu:Színlátás]]
[[ms:Penglihatan warna]]
[[nl:Kleuren zien]]
[[pl:Widzenie barwne]]
[[simple:Colour vision]]
[[fi:Väriaisti]]
[[sv:Färgseende]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
