<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="303082" ns="0" title="Arab socialism"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=July 2008}}
{{Socialism sidebar |expanded=Currents}}
{{Life in the Arab League}}

'''Arab socialism''' ({{lang-ar |الاشتراكية العربية}}, ''al-Ishtirākīya al-‘Arabīya'') is a political ideology based on an amalgamation of [[Pan-Arabism]] and [[socialism]]. Arab socialism is distinct from the much broader tradition of socialist thought in the [[Arab world]], which predates Arab socialism by as much as fifty years.  The first book on socialism in Arabic, ''Al-Ishtirākiyya'' (''The Socialism''), was published in 1913 by the [[Copts|Coptic]] [[Egyptians|Egyptian]] journalist and reformer [[Salama Musa]] (1887–1958), and republished from 1962 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Hanna|first1=Sami A |last2= Gardner |first2=George H |title= Arab socialism: a documentary survey|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=zsoUAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA49 | year=1969|publisher=Brill Archive|page=418}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term &quot;Arab socialism&quot; was coined by [[Michel ‘Aflaq]], one of the founders of the Ba'ath Party, in order to distinguish his version of socialist ideology from the [[Internationalism (politics)|internationalist]] [[Marxism|Marxist]] socialism in Eastern Europe and Eastern Asia, and the [[social democracy]] in Western Europe.
 
Arab socialism represents a political trend in the Arab world. The intellectual and political influence of Arab socialism peaked during the 1950s and 60s, when it constituted the ideological basis of the [[Baath Party|Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party]], of the [[Arab Nationalist Movement]] and, to a lesser extent, of the [[Nasserism|Nasserist]] movement.

== Ideology ==
For its adherents, Arab socialism was a necessary consequence of the quest for Arab unity and freedom, as only a socialist system of property and development would overcome the social and economic legacy of [[imperialism]] and [[colonialism]].  At the same time, Arab socialism widely differs from the Eastern Europe and Eastern Asian socialist movements, which were [[atheist]]. Unlike their Chinese counterparts, the basis of Arab nationalism is not ostensibly doctrinal, but cultural and spiritual. Thus, the &quot;anti-spiritual&quot; socialism of Eastern Europe and Eastern Asia was considered ill-adapted to the Arab World. As with socialist ideologies across the world, there has historically been a strong internationalist tendency in the  Arab socialism; however, it was based primarily on anti-imperialism, and [[non-alignment]], particularly during the [[Cold War]].

While Arab socialism in its heyday endorsed much of the economic and social programme of Eastern European-style socialism, its divergent intellectual and spiritual foundations imposed some limits on its revolutionary potential: the ownership of the [[means of production]] was to be nationalized, but only within the constraints of [[traditional values]] such as [[private property]], and [[inheritance]]. So-called primitive social structures, such as [[feudalism]], [[nomad]]ism, [[tribalism]], religious factionalism, and the oppression of women, were to be overcome, but not at the cost of severing the social ties that constituted the Arab identity.

Arguably, the most notable economic manifestations of Arab socialism were the [[land reform]]s in [[Egyptian land reform|Egypt]] (1952), [[Syria]] (1963), and [[Iraq]] (1970), and the nationalization of major industries and the banking systems in those countries. In Egypt and Syria, many of these policies were later reversed to some degree from the 1970s onwards. They were more successful in Iraq, possibly due to the country's [[Petroleum|oil]] wealth, until the beginning of the [[Iran–Iraq War]] in 1980.

== Arab socialism and women ==

Socialism and socialist parties claim that they can bring the full emancipation of women. In socialist ideology and in its [[modernization theory]] there is a need to emancipate women in order to create social equality.&lt;ref&gt;Young K., Wolkowitz C., McCullagh R., Of Marriage and the Market, 1984, London:CSE Books&lt;/ref&gt; 

Arab Socialism is different from the classical Marxism and Soviet socialism, and the term 'socialism' has been used as a regime consolidation in Arab Socialism. Rather than an ideological belief, ‘socialism’ was used to describe policies conducted out of nationalist and modernizing concerns in Arab socialism.&lt;ref&gt;Pratt, N., Democracy&amp; Authoritarianism in the Arab World, 2007, Colorado:Lynne&lt;/ref&gt; However, because of its affiliation to socialist and modernist ideologies, Arab socialism had a modernist and egalitarian perspective on gender issues, at least in rhetoric. 

For instance, the [[Ba'ath Party (Iraq)|Iraqi Ba’ath Party]] changed Iraq’s policies and rhetoric positively towards women in order to change economic, social, and political conditions in Iraq. By encouraging women to join the public sphere, especially in the educational system and labour force, the Ba’ath party made an impact on the change of relations between men and women in Iraq.&lt;ref name=&quot;Al-Ali, N. S. 2007&quot;&gt;Al-Ali, N. S.,Iraqi Women, 2007, London:Zedbooks&lt;/ref&gt; 

The ideology or at least the rhetoric of Arab socialism can be understood from [[Saddam Hussein|Saddam Hussein's]] words: ''The complete emancipation of women from the ties which held them back in the past, during the ages of despotism and ignorance, is a basic aim of the Party and the Revolution. Women make up one half of society. Our society will remain backward and in chains unless its women are liberated, enlightened and educated''…(1981).&lt;ref name=&quot;Al-Ali, N. S. 2007&quot; /&gt;

== List of Arab socialists ==

The following is a list of people who have been seen as adherents of Arab socialism, or have been influential within the Arab socialist school of thought, although some of them may not have used the term, or may even have opposed it.

{{multicol}}
Ba'thists:
*[[Zaki al-Arsuzi]]
*[[Michel ‘Aflaq]]
*[[Salah al-Din al-Bitar]]
*[[Tariq Aziz]]
*[[Saddam Hussein]]
*[[Hafez al-Assad]]
*[[Bashar al-Assad]]

Nasserites:
*[[Gamal Abdel Nasser]]
*[[Muammar al-Gaddafi]]

Algerian Socialists:
*[[Ahmed Ben Bella]]

{{multicol-break}}
Moroccans Socialists:
*[[Mehdi Ben Barka]]

Palestinian Socialists:
*[[Yasser Arafat]] 
*[[George Habash]]
*[[Nayef Hawatmeh]]

Lebanese Socialists:
*[[Kamal Jumblat]]

Syrian Socialists:
*[[Akram al-Hawrani]]
{{multicol-end}}

== See also ==
*[[African socialism]]
*[[Arab Nationalism]], more particularly [[Arab Nationalist Movement]]
*[[Baath Party]]
*[[Islamic socialism]]
*[[Melanesian socialism]]
*[[Nasserism]]
*[[Pan Arabism]]
*[[Third World Socialism]]
&lt;!--
And the categories:
*[[:Category:Algerian socialists|Algerian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Comorian socialists|Comorian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Egyptian socialists|Egyptian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Iraqi socialists|Iraqi socialists]]
*[[:Category:Lebanese socialists|Lebanese socialists]]
*[[:Category:Palestinian socialists|Palestinian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Comorian socialists|Somalian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Sudanese socialists|Sudanese socialists]]
*[[:Category:Syrian socialists|Syrian socialists]
*[[:Category:Tunisian socialists|Tunisian socialists]]
*[[:Category:Yemeni socialists|Yemeni socialists]] --&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.country-data.com/cgi-bin/query/r-4054.html Nasser and Arab Socialism]

==Bibliography==
* [[Maxime Rodinson]], Marxism and the Muslim world, Zed Press, 1979, 229 pages, ISBN 9780905762210 (transl. from the French reference book Maxime Rodinson, Marxisme et monde musulman, Paris, Éditions du Seuil, 1972, 698 pages)

{{Socialism by state}}

[[Category:Socialism]]
[[Category:Arab nationalism]]
[[Category:Arab socialism]]

[[ar:اشتراكية عربية]]
[[ast:Socialismu árabe]]
[[de:Islamischer Sozialismus]]
[[es:Socialismo árabe]]
[[fr:Socialisme arabe]]
[[he:סוציאליזם ערבי]]
[[nl:Arabisch socialisme]]
[[ja:アラブ社会主義]]
[[fi:Arabisosialismi]]
[[sv:Arabisk socialism]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
