<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30311721" ns="0" title="Canada men&#039;s national under-18 ice hockey team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{ Infobox_national_hockey_team
| Name               = Canada
| Badge              = Hockey Canada.svg
| Badge_size         = 150px
| Association        = [[Hockey Canada]]
| Nickname           =
| General Manager    = 
| Coach              = {{flagicon|CAN}} Mike Williamson
| Asst Coach         = {{flagicon|CAN}} [[Dale Hawerchuk]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|CAN}} [[Mark Lamb]]
| Captain            = [[Ryan Murray]]
| IIHF code          = CAN
| Team_Colors        = {{Color box|red}} {{Color box|white}} {{Color box|black}}
| First game         = {{ih18|RUS}} 8 - 4 {{ih18-rt|CAN}}&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Piestany]], [[Czech Republic]]; April 11, 2002)&lt;/small&gt;
| Largest win        = {{ih18|CAN}} 15 - 1 {{ih18-rt|DEN}}&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Ceske Budejovice]], [[Czech Republic]]; April 18, 2005)&lt;/small&gt;
| Largest loss       = {{ih18|USA}} 10 - 3 {{ih18-rt|CAN}}&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Piestany]], [[Czech Republic]]; April 18, 2002)&lt;/small&gt;
| World champ2 name  = [[IIHF World U18 Championship]]
| World champ2 apps  = 9
| World champ2 first = 2002
| World champ2 best  = [[Image:Gold medal with cup.svg|16px]] ''Gold'': 2 - [[2003 IIHF World U18 Championships|2003]], [[2008 IIHF World U18 Championships|2008]]
}}
{{MedalTop2}}
{{MedalCompetition|[[IIHF World U18 Championship|World U18 Championships]]}}
{{MedalGold     |[[2003 IIHF World U18 Championships|2003 Russia]]|Canada}}
{{MedalSilver   |[[2005 IIHF World U18 Championships|2005 Czech Republic]]|Canada}}
{{MedalGold     |[[2008 IIHF World U18 Championships|2008 Russia]]|Canada}}
{{MedalBottom}}

The '''Canadian men's national under 18 ice hockey team''' is the national under-18 team in Canada. This team is part of a three-stage Program of Excellence beginning with the Under-17 regional teams and ending with the National Junior Team. The primary objectives of the Under-18 program are to identify, evaluate and condition players to the rigors of international competition by giving first exposure to off-shore officiating, ice-surfaces, and travel.

The Under-18 squad traditionally competes in the month of August, during the off season, to allow players to further develop skills with their respective junior teams in the winter following a week-long camp. A 22-player roster is chosen by scouts and coaches from Hockey Canada to represent Canada on the international stage.

The first National Men’s Under-18 Team was created in 1981 with the development of the Program of Excellence and has since competed in many international competitions. For the first 10 years of the program the National Men’s Under-18 Team participated in exchange camps with the United States to provide both countries the opportunity to refine the skills of their most gifted young players against top caliber international competition. It was not until the Japanese Ice Hockey Federation introduced the Phoenix Cup, a four-nation tournament designed to improve Japan's international hockey program, in 1991 that Canada took part in an international tournament.

The Phoenix Cup (later the Pacific Cup and La Copa Mexico) was a single round robin competition between the national under-18 teams of Canada, Russia, Japan and the United States. It was competed for between 1991 and 1996, with tournaments in Japan, Mexico City and Nelson, B.C. In its six-year history, Canada took home three gold medals, two silver and one bronze.
In 1997 the National Men’s Under-18 Team competed against Slovakia and the Czech Republic in a three-nation tournament in the Czech Republic. Canada captured gold and repeated their performance the following year in Slovakia against Belarus, Slovakia, and the Czech Republic.

Since 2002, Canada’s National Men’s Under-18 Team has taken part in the [[IIHF World U18 Championship| IIHF World Under-18 Championship]], winning gold (2003, 2008) and silver (2005). &lt;ref name=CN_feature_2007&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.hockeycanada.ca/index.php/ci_id/4479/la_id/1.htm|title= National Men's Under-18 Team|publisher=hockeycanada.ca|accessdate=2011-01-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.hockeycanada.ca/ Hockey Canada home page]

{{National sports teams of Canada}}
{{IIHF}}

[[Category:Canada men's national ice hockey team|Und]]
[[Category:National under-18 ice hockey teams]]
[[Category:Youth sport in Canada]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
