<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30313270" ns="0" title="Pocket God (comics)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Primary sources|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox comic book title &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt;
| title = Pocket God
| image = Pocket God Issue 1.PNG|thumb
| imagesize =
| caption = Issue #8 (08/3/11) of ''Pocket God''.
| schedule = Irregular schedules
| ongoing = Y
| genre = [[Adventure fiction|Adventure]]
| publisher = [[Ape Entertainment]]
| date = August 3, 2010 – present
| version = 1.11
| issues = 10 (excluding 10 [[making-of]] comics)
| main_char_team =
| creators = Allan Dye &lt;/br&gt;Dave Castelnuovo
| writers = [[Jason M. Burns]] &lt;small&gt;(#1-present)&lt;/small&gt;
| artists = Rolando Mallada &lt;small&gt;(#1-4, #6-present)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/br&gt;Fernando Peniche &lt;small&gt;(#5)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/br&gt;Antonio Campo &lt;small&gt;(#5, #9)&lt;/small&gt;
| pencillers = Rolando Mallada &lt;small&gt;(#1-4, 6-present)&lt;/small&gt;
| inkers = Paul Little &lt;small&gt;(#1-present)&lt;/small&gt;
| letterers = Nick Deschenes &lt;small&gt;(#1-present)&lt;/small&gt;
| colorists = Paul Little &lt;small&gt;(#1-4)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/br&gt;J.M Ringuet &lt;small&gt;(#5)&lt;/small&gt;
| editors = [[Jason M. Burns]]&lt;/br&gt; Matt Anderson
| cover =Rolando Mallada&lt;/br&gt;Paul Little
| TPB =
| ISBN =
| subcat =
| sort =
}}

'''''Pocket God''''' is a series of [[Digital comics|digital]] and [[paperback]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tuaw.com/2010/08/05/pocket-god-comics-out-now-for-ipad-coming-soon-to-stores/|title=Pocket God Comics Out Now for iPad and Real Stores|publisher=''Tuaw''|accessdate=08-05-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[comic books]]–[[comic strips|strips]], published by [[Ape Entertainment]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ape-entertainment.com/comics/licensed-properties/pocket-god/|title=Ape Entertainment |publisher=''iVerse Media''|accessdate=2010-08-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; published and marketed by [[iVerse Media]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://itunes.apple.com/nz/app/pocket-god-comics/id380752345?mt=8|title=App Store |publisher=''iVerse Media''|accessdate=2010-08-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; released for [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]] devices, and available as a print in retailers, via contest,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/06/get-pocket-god-in-comic-shops.html|title=Pocket Blog|publisher=''Allan Dye''|accessdate=2010-08-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; on August 3, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://au.wireless.ign.com/articles/110/1108795p1.html|title=Pocket God Comic Book Release Date Announced for August 3|publisher=''IGN''|accessdate=2010-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The comic is currently written by [[Jason M. Burns]] and drawn by Rolando Mallada. It describes in the comic about &quot;an indestructible race of people who inhabit a mysterious island and are continuously (and comically) tortured by their mischievous gods&quot;. The comic is based on the best selling [[iOS (Apple)|iOS]] application ''[[Pocket God]]'', created by [[Bolt Creative|Bolt Creative's]] Allan Dye and Dave Castelnuovo. The tribe, 'Ookga Chaka', is based also off the game, with the [[Pygmy|Pygmies]], [[#Ooga|Ooga]], [[#Klik|Klik]], [[#Klak|Klak]], [[#Booga|Booga]], [[#Dooby|Dooby]], and [[Pocket God (comic book)#Nooby|Nooby]].

There are currently ten comics,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://itunes.apple.com/nz/app/pocket-god-comics/id380752345?mt=8|title=App Store|publisher=''iVerse Media''|accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; including a special Christmas issue, ''[[#Xmas Marks the Spot (Issue 5)|Xmas Marks the Spot]]'', and four 'behind-the-scenes' comics, named ''[[#The Pygmy Peril|The Pygmy Peril]]''. Although Bolt Creative had stated they were going to only publish four comics, in ''The Pygmy Peril'', however, they stated they were to publish more comics, due to popular demand. ''Pocket God'' is rated for &quot;mature readers&quot; and &quot;teen and up&quot;, currently, due to violence.

According to iVerse Media, ''Pocket God'' is the first original iOS game to have its own comic series.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://itunes.apple.com/nz/app/pocket-god-comics/id380752345?mt=8|title=App Store|publisher=''iVerse Media''|accessdate=2010-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A sneak preview of the comic was released on the official website on May 7, 2010, an almost full three months before it was released, stating about the series, and who is involved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/05/pocket-god-comic-sneak-preview.html|title=Pocket God Comic Sneak Preview|publisher=''Pocket Blog''|accessdate=06-07-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Setting==
The comics are set around six [[pygmies]], named Ooga, Klik, Klak, Booga, Dooby and Nooby, all form their tribe, Oogka Chaka, and are always [[Loyalty|loyal]] to their [[Pantheon (gods)|gods]], with the exception to Ooga, who thinks worshipping the gods is a waste of time, and [[Atheism|does not believe in them]]. Regardless of Ooga's thoughts, the tribe, Klik mainly, still believe and honour them. The story is set on a small [[archipelago]] of [[island]]s, approximately 200 [[Mya (unit)|Mya]] (million years ago, set in the [[Triassic]] period), when the [[super continent]] [[Pangaea]] was still formed. According to [[Pocket God|the game]], the islands are located in the [[Panthalassic Ocean]], opposite Pangaea. It is set mainly on Oog Island, the home of the tribe. It is a relatively small island, with a small type of forest. When the Gem of Life faded its colour, the Pygmies travel to an unnamed island, with a large rainforest and a hidden temple. Inside the temple is an [[Ancient Egypt|Egyptian]]-like setting, with hieroglyphic writing on its walls. The temple is almost like an [[Indiana Jones]] setting, especially when Nooby discovers a hat, (resembling a [[Fedora]]). According to Ooga, the islands are located in the [[tropics]].

==Plot==
===''The Gem of Life'' (August - December 2010)===
''The Gem of Life'' consists of four parts, in a total of the first four issues, it revolves around the entire tribe as they attempt to return the ''Gem of Life'' to its original pedestal, after Nooby clumsily causes their pedestal to be destroyed.

====Part 1&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://krapps.com/2010/08/03/pocket-god-comics-iphone-app/|title=Pocket God Comics Now Available – First Comic Book From An Original iPhone App|publisher=''KRAPPS''|accessdate=08-3-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;====
The comic begins with a [[Meteoroid|meteor]] hurdling towards [[Earth]], while the tribe is circled around a type of [[totem pole]], holding a gem. The tribe is honouring the gods by offering them large amounts of [[fish]]. Much to his boredom, Ooga catches his eye on the meteor that is heading straight for him. He then asks dim-witted Nooby to swap places with him. He agrees, then almost immediately, he is crushed by the meteor, killing him. Klak tries to spear the meteor, resulting the spear to [[ricochet]] off it then hit Klak in the chest. The rest, except Ooga, are executed from a [[chain reaction]]. The next day, Ooga and Klik have an argument why Ooga keeps disrupting 'the pygmy way'. Klik then explains that their ancestors discovered the Gem of Life, and brought it back to Oog Island and gave them something that they have never could have hoped for, or, in Ooga's terms, asked for. Klik tells him to grow up. [[File:Pocket God Comic Screenshot.PNG|thumb|Page 1 of ''Pocket God'', showing Ooga moving out of the way of a meteor, with Nooby willingly switching spots.]] Meanwhile, a [[great white shark]] with what is described as a [[List of applications for lasers#Military|military nitrogen laser]], approaches the [[island]]. Meanwhile, Booga is having trouble trying to light a fire on the meteor that crashed earlier; and volunteers Nooby to gather [[firewood]]. As Nooby walks into the small forest, he finds an [[anthill]] with an [[ant]] on top of it. As Nooby talks to it, Up above in a [[coconut tree]], Ooga spills [[coconut milk]] onto Nooby. Back at the meteor, Booga asks where he is. Nooby then runs out of the forest, with hundreds of fire ants crawling on him. He then manages to kill himself, Booga and Nooby. Klak then emerges; and after eating a part of a fish head, he suddenly screams towards the sea and submerges his head underwater. The &quot;Shark with Laser&quot; then lurks towards him. As it prepares to eat him, an [[octopus]] grabs Klak, and eats him. The next day, the pygmies have a tribe meeting discussing their mortality. He is then interrupted by Nooby, who needs to go to the outhouse. Lightning strikes on the outhouse and he runs out, trying to hold up his grass skirt, while so. he then hides behind the totem pole, with it holding the Gem of Life, and the lightning strikes the pole, snapping it in half. Klik, shocked, exclaims that the gods will 'cast us away once and for all', when the Gem of Life is removed from its pedestal. Klik comes up with a plan to make the gods forgive them, but all but Ooga end up electrocuted. Klik, delusional, but correct, then sees the now discoloured gem and is shocked to say that when the colour drains from the gem, the next time they die, it will be forever.

====Part 2&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/09/issue-2-of-comic-out-on-store-and.html|title=Issue 2 of the Comic out on the Store and number one in books!!|publisher=''Pocket Blog''|accessdate=2010-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;====
Klik and the tribe, much to the dismay of Ooga, journey to the neighbouring island to return the Gem of Life to its original pedestal. The &quot;Shark With Laser&quot; shoots a laser through their raft after they had been in the water for countless hours. They all &quot;abandon ship&quot;. They resurface to find that Dooby has been captured by the shark. Ooga rescues him, by throwing a spear into the shark's laser beam, electrocuting itself. When they both resurface, immediately they are pulled by a [[tsunami]], and crash on the island beach. While in the jungle, they arrive to a field of [[banana]] skins. A pack of [[apes]] terrorise the tribe and Klik is caught by one, and killed. Ooga then realises that, since the gem's power has disappeared, Klik is now deceased forever, by that one part of the gem is now a dark grey.  After the tribe craft a tombstone for Klik, Ooga decides that he will return the gem of life for Klik, with the approval of everyone, except Booga, who looks pale and delirious. A bug had sucked blood out of him, from his back. Ooga then rips it off of Booga, throws it on the ground, then jumps onto it, with a &quot;bloody&quot; result. Ooga then thinks he needs some food to regain his health, and immediately, Nooby rolls out a gigantic [[Egg (biology)|egg]], claiming it is a [[chicken]] egg. Then a [[Tyrannosaurus Rex]] emerges, extremely in aggravation.

====Part 3&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/12/issue-3-of-pocket-god-comic-is-on-app.html|title=Issue 3 of Pocket God the Comic is on the app store!|publisher=''Pocket Blog''|accessdate=2010-10-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;====
As the five remaining pygmies are evading the T. Rex, Klak suggests that they run in [[Serpentine shape|serpentine]]. Shortly after, Dooby is caught by his grass skirt by the Rex's mouth. Ooga then throws a spear, narrowly missing Dooby, but hitting the skirt instead, falling to the ground, naked. Dooby falls on Nooby, while trying to catch him. The tribe is disgusted that he is not wearing anything. The dinosaur returns, and the pygmies run into a cave, stopping the dinosaur in its tracks. Klak passes Dooby a bunch of leaves to cover himself up, and then asks how they are going to get rid of the reptile. Ooga asks Booga if he knows how to get rid of it, but he doesn't respond. Ooga approaches Booga and asks if he is alright, and Booga appears to be wrapped under snake skin. Ooga looks at the gem, and another sixth of it is now grey, resulting that Booga is dead. A giant snake had eaten him, and the Pygmies run out of the cave. 

Dooby is flabbergasted and in excitement after discovering a whole field of what appears to be [[Psilocybin mushrooms]]. Dooby is then crushed by the dinosaur's foot, leaving only Ooga, Klak, and Nooby alive. They run towards a cliff, ultimately falling off it. They fall into the water, beside the temple, and Ooga and Klak find that Nooby is being chased by a pack of [[piranha]]s. The Laser Shark shoots the piranhas, not knowing it has let the pygmies escape. When on land, they discover the temple, but there is a puzzle to open the entrance. Klak and Ooga are stumped, but to their surprise, Nooby cracks the puzzle in seconds. Inside, Ooga finds a [[skeleton]] of a pygmy, still wearing its hat, a bag and a wooden [[sword]]. Ooga takes the bag, and the sword, while Nooby takes the hat. Ooga then realises that Klak has disappeared, and shouts for him. Klak responds, and they see that Klak is stuck in a unusually large cobweb.

====Part 4&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://heavyink.com/comic/16498-Pocket-God-4|title=Pocket God #4|publisher=''Heavy Ink''}}&lt;/ref&gt;====
As Ooga fights to free Klak from the web, an extremely large [[barking spider]] emerges behind them. Nooby starts singing &quot;[[Itsy Bitsy Spider]]&quot; when it lands in front of them. They throw themselves away from the beast as it jumps towards them. It then [[cocoons]] Klak, who is still stuck. Nooby then says that he rips the legs off smaller spiders and &quot;watch legless balls wriggle&quot;. Ooga gets the idea and quickly uses his sword to chop off the spider's eight legs. As Nooby and Ooga try to get Klak out of the cocoon, another fraction of the gem has faded to grey, indicating he has suffocated in the cocoon, but as they rip it open, dozens of baby barking spiders crawl out and chase them. They run off again, both agreeing that they are tired of doing so. As they exit, they push a large circular [[door]] to stop the spiders from getting to them.  As Ooga explains they are the last hope of getting the gem to the gods, Nooby tells that he didn't believe in them though. Ooga says he does now, but he thinks the gods don't believe in them, and how they deserve to know why the gods are always killing them. As he reaches in his bag, Ooga finds a journal, it reads:

:I have travelled once again to this island to uncover the true nature of that which the gods have bestowed upon us.''&lt;/br&gt;''I have witnessed a side of their generosity that seems more sinister than sincere.''&lt;/br&gt;''Their gift not only promises '''eternal life''', but from what I have seen, '''eternal death''' as well.

As Ooga questions what 'eternal death' means, a zombified hand smashes up from the ground. As Nooby says that he doesn't like scary stories, four [[zombie]]s come up from the ground. They are the zombified remains of Klik, Booga, Dooby, and Klak, all exclaiming &quot;brains!&quot;. Nooby is excited that his friends are back, obviously not realizing they are zombies. Ooga tries to pull back Nooby, exclaiming that they are monsters. Nooby then says that the entire tribe said that Ooga was a monster anyway, except for Nooby. He breaks out of Ooga's grip, and runs towards the zombie pygmies. Ooga then screams for him to come back. As the four zombie pygmies tear the top of Nooby's head off, they question &quot;Brains?&quot; And a shot to a dead Nooby with the top of his head hinging off, there is no brain found in him. As they look at each other, they suddenly look at Ooga, exclaiming more angrily, as how Ooga treated them previously. Ooga, upset, says that it was all is fault for everything, and he failed to return the Gem of Life. As he is saying this, he falls through a hidden trap. He falls through into a chamber, inside the volcano, with five differently coloured organisms, revealing it is the gods. As Ooga asks what they are, the purple god obnoxiously says 'What do we look like, numb nards?', the yellow god tells him to calm down, as he has come a long way. Ooga asks what it all means, life, the red god says &quot;that's not exactly our field of enterprise&quot;. Ooga then asks &quot;If you don't know the meaning of life, why do you tamper with ours?&quot; They then say it's not tampering, its fun. He is then confused, then asks why the Gem is dying. They say they have to wait for the next update, but then says that he has to return it to its original pedestal, before they become &quot;nothing more than a [[Wikipedia]] page memory&quot;. As he walks across the unstable bridge, he asks for all of them back, even Klik. he puts the gem on the pedestal, and walks back, as he is, the laser shark emerges from a small part of the water, shooting a laser at the bridge making Ooga fall towards the [[magma]]. Before he does, however, he immediately asks why they were born when there are no female pygmies on the island. They reply, &quot;Who said anything about you being born?&quot;. When Ooga falls into the magma, the [[Volcano]] erupts.

Back on the home island, Booga, Klak, Klik, Nooby, and Dooby, pop out of mid-air, alive. Then Ooga. Klik then proceeds to say, that Ooga somehow has saved them and appeased the gods as well. As a wave crashes on the island, the Gem of Life is found.

===''Xmas Marks the Spot'' (December 18, 2010)===
Set after the events of ''The Gem of Life'', released on [[December]] 18, 2010, with version 1.4 on iOS. The issue is the Christmas special of the series, introducing two characters to the series, [[#Red|Red]], and [[#Newbie|Newbie]].

===''A Tale of Two Pygmies'' (March - August 2011)===
The second story arc, ''A Tale of Two Pygmies'' was released between 30 March, and 3 August 2011, with the eighth issue being released one year since the initial release of the comics. The three part comic describes how Ooga and Klik's rivalry exceeds towards &quot;catastrophe&quot;, and as a result, Ooga ends up being banished from the tribe. With Booga and Nooby joining him on the opposite side of Oog Island, they initiate a plan to steal the Gem of Life from Klik's possession. Klik, after realising that it has been stolen, immediately blames Ooga and engages in a battle, which leads to Nooby discovering another Pygmy, Sun, a female Pygmy, who was in search of the &quot;Jewel of Life&quot;, and explains that she had retrieved the Gem. Attempting to escape, Ooga and Klik, who had called a truce, managed to take back the Gem and capture Sun. The epilogue of the final issue shows [[Pocket God (comics)#Newbie|Newbie]], exclaiming, he had survived death from the fifth issue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2011/03/tale-of-two-pygmies-available-on-app.html|title=A Tale of Two Pygmies Available On the App Store|publisher=Pocket Blog|accessdate=03-30-2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Future===
Bolt Creative discussed on how they will release a further three more four-part comics, raising the issue publication number to 20.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2011/05/busy-month-much-needed-blog-post.html|title=Busy Month! Much Needed Blog Post!|publisher=Pocket Blog|accessdate= May 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Main characters==
The characters in the comic, are [[Pygmy|Pygmies]], which are unusually small. They have their hair tied up with a bone, wearing a grass skirt, or kilt, tanned skin, large eyes, and a large head. Comically, it seems to look that none of them have noses. The following six characters make up the tribe '''Oogka Chaka'''.
[[File:Final PG Concept Drawings.PNG|thumb|Final [[Concept art|concept drawings]] of (from top left to bottom right) Ooga, Klak, Dooby, Booga, Klik and Nooby.]]

===Ooga===
'''Ooga''' is the &quot;reluctant&quot; leader of the 'Oogka Chaka' tribe. He is monstrously [[mischief|mischievous]] towards the others and usually causes their deaths. Ooga looks the most similar to the Pocket God game, the only major difference is he has blue eyes, instead of the usual brown. Ooga does not respect the tribe very much, and does not believe in the gods. Ooga loathes Klik, because of his frequent conversations about the gods. Ooga is unbelievably [[selfish]], but when Klik picks on someone for doing something wrong, Ooga stands up against Klik. Most likely because he dislikes Klik. Ooga only gets along with Nooby, whose intelligence is limited and never takes negative subjects seriously, nor positively. Nooby tell Ooga that the entire tribe says that he's a monster, but that he doesn't listen to them. Although Ooga treats him the same as everyone else, Ooga is called by, Nooby, his 'bestest friend'.

===Klik===
'''Klik''' is the most intelligent Pygmy of the tribe, he respects everyone, except Ooga, because he does not believe in the gods. Once again, Klik's description is very close to the game, with brown eyes, but the major difference is his glasses, which are usually banked on the top of his head. This shows his intelligence. Klik usually picks on Ooga and Nooby for the stupid things they have done, like Ooga, for not believing in the gods, and Nooby, for his stupidity. Like bringing a [[coconut]] with a face drawn on it called  [[Cast_Away#Wilson_the_volleyball|Wilson]]. Klik thinks Ooga is a monster, along with everyone in the tribe aside from Nooby. Klik is one of the only Pygmies in the tribe who somewhat respects what Dooby has to say, like 'if it was meant to be, it was meant to be'.

===Dooby===
'''Dooby''' is described as a '[[Rastafari movement|Rastafarian]] hippy' pygmy, he is more relaxed and is always positive that the gods will turn their ways and gift them. Dooby is known to use the word 'dude' after he says a name of someone, e.g.. 'Whoa, calm down, Klik dude'. He is the only pygmy (other than Nooby) in the tribe that does not hate anyone, though he does agree that Ooga is a monster. Dooby constantly reminds Booga to be patient, and at one time, Booga cracks under Dooby's constant reminders to him and the tribe, and screams 'Bull Shark!', an alternative to the similar swear. Dooby looks significantly different than the game counterpart, with [[dreadlocks]] instead of a ponytail, which is held up by a [[gudi (instrument)|bone flute]]. His facial expression looks more relaxed, less alert, and sports a gold necklace.

===Klak===
'''Klak''' is a cheerful, and unlucky pygmy, the most major difference to him in the comics and in the game is that he is overweight in the comic, and constantly searches for food. The bone in his hair is significantly smaller than the others, comically showing that he is more afraid of dangers than anyone else. Klak usually backs up Booga's remarks, usually standing beside him while doing so. Like all of the tribe, except Nooby, he thinks that Ooga is a monster, but he does not dislike him like most of the tribe. Other than Nooby, he is killed more than any other pygmy in the tribe. He is almost always killed unusually, e.g.. He eats a fish that is too hot and sprints to the water and throws his head in to cool down. Then, a shark with what looks like a [[List of applications for lasers#Military|military nitrogen laser]] slowly lurks towards him, almost like [[Jaws (film)|Jaws]], and before the shark gets his chance, Klak is caught by an [[octopus]] and is eaten.

===Nooby===
'''Nooby''' is a, somewhat, lucky pygmy (according to himself), and he has the lowest mental intelligence in the tribe. He speaks almost entirely in [[illeism]], e.g. 'Ooga mad at Nooby?'. His appearance is again similar to the game, the most difference is that his hair bone has broken off one side, and he has two buck teeth with a wide gap between them. He is always cheerful. In ''The Pygmy Peril'', it is revealed that he becomes easily confused when in a conversation, and that he is best friends with Ooga. Although the tribe thinks of Ooga as a monster, Nooby says that he does not listen to them. Although he is dim-witted, he can be significantly smart in certain situations, such as when Ooga, and Klak were trying to decode a puzzle, and Nooby easily cracks it within seconds.

===Booga===
'''Booga''' is a constantly aggravated pygmy, showing the most difference in appearance than in the game. Instead of wearing a grass skirt/kilt, he wears a type of cloth, possibly a [[rag]], and instead of the normal, 'dog bone', he wears a type of horn to hold up his hair. He is unshaven, unclean, and has a tattoo on his right arm of a bone. He is not easily distracted, and is immediately negative to most circumstances, such as when Dooby says, 'If it's meant to be, it's meant to be', after the gem is discoloured, Booga then proceeds to yell 'Bull shark!'. While Booga agrees that Ooga is a monster, he states in ''A Tale of Two Pygmies'' that he would rather be lead by Ooga; mainly because he has increased charisma and doesn't talk as much as Klik.

==Other characters==
The following are either [[antagonists]], major or minor characters, that are not involved in the tribe '''Oogka Chaka'''. There are five antagonists, and one [[Character flaw|flawed protagonist]] Note: Some of these names are not official as their real names do not appear in the comics.

===Shark With Lasers===
The '''Shark With Lasers''' or '''Laser Shark''' is the main [[antagonist]] of the comic series. The shark first appeared in &quot;The Gem of Life: Part 1&quot; of ''Pocket God'', when it almost eats Klak, before an octopus does instead. The Shark With Lasers is featured on the cover of ''Pocket God'' Issue 1. The shark is a [[great white shark]], and as the name suggests, it has a laser apparatus strapped on its head. The shark has appeared in all comics so far, all times trying to either eat the Pygmies, or shooting them with the laser. In issue 5, the shark finally eats one of them, Booga. The shark always sneaks up on the Pygmies, such as, when the Pygmies abandon their raft, the shark sneakily grabs Dooby and pulls him underwater. Weaknesses in the shark include getting electrocuted by its laser, when Ooga throws a spear into the laser, thus, electrocuting the shark. Also, when the Pygmies are getting chased by [[piranha]]s the shark, before going for the Pygmies, it shoots the piranhas first. The shark was created in the ''Pocket God'' episode, ''Sharks With Frickin' Laser Beams Attached to Their Heads'', which references Dr. Evil's conversation about retrieving sharks with laser beams attached to their heads in ''[[Austin Powers: International Man of Mystery]]''.

===Red===
'''Saint Prickulous''', referred to as '''Red''', is a mock up of [[Santa Claus]], and is a [[Character flaw|flawed protagonist]], that first appeared in &quot;X-Mas Marks the Spot&quot;, the ''Fishmas'' special. He befriends Nooby quickly, and soon considers him family. He is a flawed protagonist, because, although he fights with the main antagonist of the issue, Newbie, he is, as seen in the middle and at the end of the issue, [[insanity|mentally insane]], by thinking Nooby is his family, along with [[personification|falsely personified]] wooden figures, that Red made in his workshop. At the end of the issue, he is seen with a wooden figure of Nooby (or Newbie), talking to him as if he were real.

===Newbie===
'''Newbie''' is a clone of Nooby, and is the main antagonist of &quot;X-Mas Marks the Spot&quot;. As a clone of Nooby, he is the same in appearance, apart from him having slightly darker skin, and different eyes, almost being completely black, apart from his pupils, which are green.  He is also mentally different to Nooby, being significantly smarter than Nooby is, faster and stronger. But according to Nooby, he is not lucky, as Newbie is impaled by a icicle. He marks his revenge on Nooby, Red and the tribe as he falls into the icy sea below. He is shown to have survived in ''[[Pocket God (comics)#A Tale of Two Pygmies (March - August 2011)|A Tale of Two Pygmies]]''.

==Character Design==
The design of the main characters has changed four times; the original concept art of the characters decepted them as more mature, taller, and very much different to the game counterparts. The final concept art (shown above) decepted them as more relatable to the game, and then altered for the comic. The first two renditions were created by Rolando Mallada. The third version of the characters were slightly different than the previous, drawn by Fernando Peniche. Their skin color is slightly altered, along with facial structure. The final rendition was actually animated for a short video posted on [[YouTube]], with the pygmies detailed much cleaner for an animated short. The animation drawings were completed by Scott Martin, from [[Peach Nova]], who took Allan Dye's rough sketchings and manufactured concept drawings and eventually animated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XGc4GFUjs80|title=YouTube - Pocket God Fishmas Special|publisher=YouTube|accessdate=2010-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Currently, Mallada is drawing the comic to the styling of the first four comics for issue six to eight.

==''The Pygmy Peril''==
''The Pygmy Peril'' is a &quot;[[Making-of]]&quot; comic discussing how ''Pocket God'' the game and comic was created,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.wikia.com/wiki/The_Pygmy_Peril|title=The Pygmy Peril|publisher=Wikipedioog}}&lt;/ref&gt; along with concepts of the Pygmies from the comic (see gallery) and the game. Segments include &quot;Letter From the Editor (and Writer)&quot; by Jason M. Burns, &quot;Developer's Corner&quot; by Allan Dye, and others, including &quot;An Intimate Conversation with Nooby&quot;, a fictional interview with Nooby by an unknown interviewer, which proves to be a confusing one, &quot;Drafting a Pygmy&quot; with artist Rolando &quot;Rolo&quot; Mallada discussing how the tribe was created, and &quot;It's All Sequential&quot;, explaining how a comic is manufactured.

==Reception==
Within a week after the comic was released, it was met with generally positive reviews from many websites and critics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/08/early-comic-reviews.html|title=Early Comic Reviews|publisher=''Pocket Blog''|accessdate=2010-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; The comic quickly reached the top 25 in the [[App Store (iOS)|App Store]], and peaking at number 1 in the books category.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/2010/09/issue-2-of-comic-out-on-store-and.html|title=Issue 2 of the Comic out on the Store and number one in books!!|publisher=''Pocket Blog''|accessdate=2010-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Review websites such as App Advice praise the comic for its engagement, interface and overall capability, but criticised it for its short storyline, quoting &quot;Minus the title page, instructions, and credits this is a 20 page comic... it goes by so quickly, and there’s nothing left to do with it.&quot; App Advice gave the comic four and a half stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://appadvice.com/appnn/2010/08/review-pocket-god-comics-pygmies-comics/|title=Reveiw: Pocket God Comics|publisher=''App Advice|accessdate=2010-08-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; 148Apps gave the comic 4 out of 5 stars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.148apps.com/reviews/pocket-god-comics-review/|title=Pocket God Comics Review|publisher=''148Apps''|accessdate=2010-08-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.iversecomics.com/ iVerse Media website]
*[http://ape-entertainment.com/ Ape Entertainment website]
*[http://pocketgod.blogspot.com/ Official Pocket God website]
*[http://s3.zetaboards.com/Pocket_God_Forums/index/ Pocket God Forums]

{{Pocket God}}

[[Category:Comics based on video games]]
[[Category:2010 comic debuts]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
