<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Edra Blixseth" to="Yellowstone Club" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="20178157" ns="0" title="Yellowstone Club"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Yellowstone Club''', also '''Yellowstone Ski Resort''', is an invitation-only residential club, [[ski resort]], and [[golf resort]] located in the state of [[Montana]], USA.  The [[Rocky Mountain]] ski and golf club is located in eastern [[Madison County, Montana|Madison County]], just west of [[Big Sky, Montana]], south of [[Bozeman]] and northwest of [[Yellowstone National Park]]. The club entered Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection in November 2008 &lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,450546,00.html |title=Yellowstone Ski Resort for Super Rich Files Bankruptcy |publisher=[[Fox News]] |date=2008-11-12 |accessdate=2009-02-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; and emerged from bankruptcy in July 2009. It is owned by investors led by CrossHarbor Capital Partners, and is operated by [[Discovery Land Company]].

==History==
During its peak season, almost 600 people are employed at the club.&lt;ref name=BDC&gt;[http://www.bozemandailychronicle.com/articles/2008/11/12/news/000club.txt Bozeman Daily Chronicle: Trickle-down economics]&lt;/ref&gt;

The club was featured on [[CNBC]]'s lifestyle show ''High Net Worth'' with [[Tyler Mathisen]].

Cyclist [[Greg LeMond]], an early investor and homeowner/member, sued the club in 2006, saying club founder [[Tim Blixseth]] and his former wife Edra Denise (Crocker) Blixseth had borrowed $375 million from [[Credit Suisse Group]] and took $209 million for themselves as a dividend, jilting him and other investors.  The suit was settled in 2008 for $39.5 million.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-resort26-2008dec26,0,3850422.story Los Angeles Times/Bloomberg News:  Cash stops flowing at Yellowstone]&lt;/ref&gt; Ms. Blixseth eventually agreed to pay Mr. LeMond and others a $21.5 million settlement; she’s paid only $8 million of that amount and Mr. LeMond and others are now among her creditors in her [[personal bankruptcy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT01&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/14/business/14yellow.html?pagewanted=1&amp;hpw &quot;Checkmate at the Yellowstone Club&quot;] by Amy Wallace, ''The New York Times'', June 13, 2009 (p. BU1 6/14/09 NY ed.). Retrieved 6/14/09.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other members identified in, or cited in, the ''Times'' report were [http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0837396/bio Burt Sugarman], a Beverly Hills businessman, and his wife, the ''[[Entertainment Tonight]]'' host [[Mary Hart]]; [[Steve Burke (businessman)|Steve Burke]], the chief operating officer of [[Comcast]]; [[Bill Frist]], the former [[U.S. Senate|Senate]] majority leader; Todd Thomson, the former head of [[Citigroup]]’s [[private banking]] unit; [http://www.greenhill.com/index.php?option=com_peoplebook&amp;Itemid=150&amp;func=grShowProfile&amp;profileid=10000096 Robert Greenhill], founder of the investment bank Greenhill &amp; Company; [[Annika Sörenstam]], the Swedish golf star; [[Frank McCourt (executive)|Frank McCourt]], the owner of the [[Los Angeles Dodgers]]; Jim Davidson, a founder of [[Silver Lake Partners]], a private equity firm in [[Menlo Park (CA)]]; [http://www.steelheadpartners.com/partner_bios.html#briank Brian Klein], a former [[Goldman Sachs]] vice president who now runs an investment management firm in Seattle; [[Peter Chernin]] of the [[News Corporation]]; [http://people.forbes.com/profile/barry-s-sternlicht/37948 Barry Sternlicht], the hotelier and CEO of Starwood Capital Group; and [http://www.qimingventures.com/en/about/mg1.htm Gary Rieschel], a venture capitalist with Qiming Venture Partners. [[Jack Kemp]], the late U.S. politician, was on the club’s honorary board of directors with Mr. Quayle, among others. 

The ''Times'' said that as of June 2009, Yellowstone Club had about 250 members. It said membership cost a minimum of $250,000 to join, plus the cost of a $5 million to $35 million mountainside home, plus annual dues of about $20,000, according to members.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT01&quot; /&gt;

===Bankruptcy protection===
On November 10, 2008, in the midst of the [[Economic crisis of 2008|economic downturn]], Yellowstone filed for [[Chapter 11]] [[bankruptcy protection]].  It emerged from protection July 19, 2009.&lt;ref&gt;http://missoulian.com/news/state-and-regional/article_9bdc90aa-35ae-11df-94c0-001cc4c002e0.html&lt;/ref&gt;  Yellowstone had been in the planning stages of an expansion, in a development partnership with the [[Discovery Land Company]] of Arizona, which was to include 450 additional houses and condos, an ice rink, a baseball field, a luxury spa and more ski runs.&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;/&gt; When filing, they owed US$343 million to creditors, such as banks and local contractors.  However the club's property was listed in court filings as being worth US$778 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;/&gt;

In advance of a June 2009, court date, [[Edra Blixseth]] spoke to a reporter for ''The New York Times'' about her and her ex-husband's business affairs from Porcupine Creek, her {{convert|30000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} estate in [[Rancho Mirage, CA]]. She hoped to retain the estate and make it income-producing with its {{convert|240|acre|km2|adj=on}} private golf course. Porcupine Creek was sold to [[Larry Ellison]] in 2011 for $42.9 million.  Edra Blixseth is currently being forced to sell [[Chateau de Farcheville]]   in [[France]] because of her bankruptcy.

The Yellowstone Club was sold for $115 million to a private equity firm, [http://www.crossharborcapital.com/ CrossHarbor Capital Partners] affiliated with a Yellowstone Club member, Sam Byrne. In 2009, negotiations with that same buyer had put a $400 million price tag on the club, but the deal did not close then. In the 2009 transaction, Byrne &quot;has pledged to invest $75 million above the purchase price in repairs and has set aside $15 million to pay the club’s creditors,&quot; according to the ''Times''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT01&quot; /&gt; The deal was brokered by Jeff Woolson, Managing Director of the CBRE Golf &amp; Resort Properties Group,&lt;ref&gt;http://cbregolf.com/&lt;/ref&gt; and Steve Lehr, Managing Director of CBRE's Land Services Group. CB Richard Ellis was selected by the U.S. Bankruptcy Court to market the property because of the firm's successful track record handling complicated transactions.

In November 2010 some parts of the bankruptcy reorganization were overturned, particularly concerning the settlement with Credit Suisse.  A judge ordered reconsideration of those aspects in bankruptcy court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/news/2010-11-03/yellowstone-club-bankruptcy-reorganization-overturned.html Yellowstone Club Bankruptcy Reorganization Overturned] Bloomberg Businessweek, November 3, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

===Location===
The ski runs are on Pioneer Mountain which is located here: {{coord|45|13|52.98|N|111|27|4.52|W|region:US|display=inline,title}}.  Pioneer Mountain is on the Sphinx Mountain USGS topographic map which indicates a summit elevation of {{convert|9859|ft|m}}.

The resort itself has several lifts and runs that tie it directly into [[Big Sky Resort]]'s lift system. Access into Yellowstone Club from Big Sky is provided via the Southern Comfort lift.

==See also==
{{Empty section|date=June 2011}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/30/us/30gated.html?hp &quot;Economy Crashes the Gates at a Club for the Rich&quot;] New York Times, Nov. 29, 2008
*[http://www.newwest.net/topic/article/yellowstone_club_financing_settled_for_now/C35/L35/ Yellowstone Club Financing Settled (For Now)] Dec. 12, 2008, New West Development website
* [http://blogs.wsj.com/bankruptcy/2010/02/24/trustee-says-blixseth-doomed-yellowstone-club/ Trustee Says Blixseth 'Doomed' Yellowstone Club] Wall Street Journal - Bankruptcy Beat, Feb. 24, 2010,
* [http://billingsgazette.com/ap/state/article_4b66055d-4333-5046-8a4d-15ffbc2d484b.html Developer seeks judge's ouster in Yellowstone Club bankruptcy case] Nov. 22, 2010, Billings Gazette

==External links==
* [http://www.theyellowstoneclub.com/ Yellowstone Club's homepage]

{{Montana Ski areas navbox}}

[[Category:Ski areas and resorts in Montana]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Madison County, Montana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
