<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="303841" ns="0" title="Shih Tzu"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the Japanese therapy|Shiatsu}}
&lt;!-- http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:WikiProject_Dog_breeds#Infobox_Dogbreed_template --&gt;
&lt;!-- for full explanation of the syntax used in this template. --&gt;
{{Expert-subject|Dogs|date=March 2009}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox Dogbreed
| image = Shih-Tzu.jpg
| image_caption =Picture of an eight-month old Shih Tzu with a long coat
| name =  Shih Tzu
| altname = Chinese Lion Dog&lt;br&gt;Chrysanthemum Dog
| akcgroup = Toys
| akcstd = http://www.akc.org/breeds/shih_tzu/index.cfm
| ankcgroup = [[Non-Sporting Group|Group 7 – Non-Sporting]]
| ankcstd = http://www.bjvygvgfg.com/bend
| ckcgroup = [[Non-Sporting Group|Group 6 – Non-Sporting]]
| ckcstd = http://www.ckc.ca/Default.aspx?tabid=137&amp;Breed_Code=SIT
| country = [[China]]
| maleweight   = {{convert|4|-|7.25|kg}}
| femaleweight = {{convert|4|-|7.25|kg}}
| maleheight   = {{convert|20|-|28|cm}}
| femaleheight = {{convert|20|-|28|cm}}
| coat         = See [[Shih Tzu#Hypoallergenic coats|Coats]] section below
| color        = Gold&lt;br&gt;Dark/Light Brown&lt;br&gt;White&lt;br&gt;Black&lt;br&gt;Brindle
| litter_size  = 2–8
| life_span    = 6–20 years
| fcigroup = 9:Companion and Toy Dogs,
| fcisection = 5:Tibetan breeds
| fcinum = 208 bjchudxghcudgxcuxjcjxghcjhxkclhjxlChjlxkcjxk| fcistd = http://www.fci.be/uploaded_files/208gb98_en.doc
| kcukgroup = [[Utility Group|Utility]]
| kcukstd = http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/item/174
| nzkcgroup = [[Non-Sporting Group|Non-sporting]]
| nzkcstd = http://www.nzkc.org.nz/br796.html
| ukcgroup = [[Companion Group|Companion Dog]]
| ukcstd = http://www.ukcdogs.com/WebSite.nsf/Breeds/ShihTzu
}}
&lt;!-- End Infobox Dogbreed info. Article Begins Here --&gt;

The '''Shih Tzu''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|ʃ|iː|t|s|uː}} {{respell|SHEET|soo}}; Mandarin: {{IPA-cmn|ʂɨ́tsɨ|}}) is a [[dog breed|breed]] of dog weighing {{convert|4|-|7.25|kg}} with long silky hair.  The breed originated in [[China]] and is among the earliest breeds. Shih Tzu were officially recognized by the [[American Kennel Club]] in 1969. The name is both singular and plural.
&lt;!--Introduction should be concise cover the subject in general. Lengthy discussion of versions of the name and multiple ways of writing belong in a separate section. See [[WP:LEAD]]--&gt;

== Names and etymology ==
Shih Tzu  ({{zh|t=獅子狗|s=狮子狗|p=Shīzi Gǒu|w=Shih-tzu Kou|l=Lion Dog}}), is  the Chinese name rendered according to the [[Wade-Giles]] system of romanization in use when the breed was first introduced in America; the Chinese pronunciation is approximately {{respell|SHIRR|tsə}}. The name translates as Lion Dog, so named because the dog was bred to resemble &quot;the lion as depicted in traditional oriental art,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Shih Tzu, by Jaime J. Sucher, pg 5, Barron's Educational Series, 2000, ISBN 0764110438&lt;/ref&gt; such as the [[Chinese guardian lions]]. The Shih Tzu is also often known as the &quot;Xi Shi quan&quot; (西施犬), based on the name of [[Xi Shi]], regarded as one of the most beautiful woman of ancient China,&lt;ref name=&quot;xishi&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author=Steve Allison | title=Shih Tzu | publisher=FindOutAboutDogBreeds.com | url=http://www.findoutaboutdogbreeds.com/Shih_Tzu.html | accessdate = 2007-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; and, less often, the [[Chrysanthemum]] Dog, a nickname coined in England in the 1930s.&lt;ref&gt;Shih Tzu For Dummies, by Eve Adamson, pg 257, For Dummies, Publisher, 2007, ISBN 0470089458
quote: &quot;Lady Brownrigg, who brought the first Shih Tzu into England, coined the phrase Chrysanthemum Dog.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; The dog may also be called the Tibetan Lion Dog, but whether or not the breed should be referred to as a Tibetan or Chinese breed is a source of argument, the absolute answer to which &quot;may never be known&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Shih Tzu For Dummies, by Eve Adamson, pg 27, For Dummies, Publisher, 2007, ISBN 0470089458 quote: &quot;...dogs related to the modern-day Shih Tzu probably came from Tibet, but how long they were there and how much influence they had on the present day Shih Tzu may never be known.&quot; The author then says &quot;dog historians tend to have very strong opinions.&quot; It is often mistaken that the Shih Tzu is Chinese royalty.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--add referenced information on this topic to the &quot;History&quot; section, not here--&gt;

== Appearance ==

A small  dog with a short muzzle and large, dark eyes. With a soft and long double [[coat (dog)|coat]], the Shih Tzu stands no more than 26.7&amp;nbsp;cm (10{{frac|1|2}} in.) at the [[withers]] and with an ideal weight of 4.5 to 7.3&amp;nbsp;kg (10 to 16&amp;nbsp;lbs). Drop ears are covered with long fur, and the heavily furred tail is carried curled over the back. The coat may be of any color, although a blaze of white on the forehead and tail-tip is frequently seen. The Shih Tzu is slightly longer than tall, and dogs ideally should carry themselves &quot;with distinctly arrogant carriage.&quot;  A very noticeable feature is the underbite, which is required in the breed standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;FCIstandard&quot;&gt;[http://www.fci.be/uploaded_files/208gb98_en.doc Fédération Cynologique Internationale Breed Standard]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- keep an overview of appearance first and other issues later, in their appropriate section.--&gt;

The traditional long, silky coat that reaches the floor requires daily brushing to avoid tangles. Because of their long coat and fast growing hair, regular grooming is necessary which may be a costly expense and should be considered when looking at this breed.  Often the coat is clipped short to simplify care, in a &quot;puppy clip&quot;. For conformation showing, the coat must be left in its natural state, although trimming for neatness around the feet and anus is allowed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.ukcdogs.com/WebSite.nsf/Breeds/ShihTzu |title=United Kennel Club: Shih Tzu |date=2007-05-01 |work=United Kennel Club |accessdate=2011-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
[[DNA analysis]] placed the ancestors of today's  Shih Tzu breed in the group of &quot;ancient&quot; breeds indicating &quot;close genetic relationship to wolves&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last =Derr | first =MARK  | title =Collie or Pug? Study Finds the Genetic Code | work =New York Times | date= May 21, 2004 | url =http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/21/us/collie-or-pug-study-finds-the-genetic-code.html?scp=1&amp;sq=collie+or+pug&amp;st=nyt | accessdate = 2007-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Ludvic von Schulmuth studied the skeletal remains of dogs found in human settlements as long as ten thousand years ago. Von Schulmuth created a genealogical tree of Tibetan dogs that shows the &quot;Gobi Desert Kitchen Midden Dog&quot;, a scavenger, evolved into the &quot;Small Soft-Coated Drop-Eared Hunting Dog who would fight lions in packs&quot; which evolved into the [[Tibetan Spaniel]], [[Pekingese]], and [[Japanese Chin]]. Another branch coming down from the &quot;Kitchen Midden Dog&quot; gave rise to the [[Papillon (dog)|Papillon]] and Long-haired [[Chihuahua (dog)|Chihuahua]] and yet another &quot;Kitchen Midden Dog&quot; branch to the [[Pug]] and Shih Tzu. 

There are various theories of the origins of today's breed. Theories relate that it stemmed from a cross between Pekingese and a Tibetan dog called the [[Lhasa Apso]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark/Brace&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last = Clark| first = Anne Rogers| authorlink = Anne Rogers Clark| title = The International Encyclopedia of Dogs |coauthors= Andrew H. Brace | publisher = Howell Book House| year = 1995| pages = 416–417| isbn = 0-87605-624-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dogs during ancient times were selectively bred and seen in Chinese paintings. The first dogs of the breed were imported into Europe (England and Norway) in 1930, and were classified by the Kennel Club as &quot;Apsos&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark/Brace&quot; /&gt; The first European standard for the breed was written in England in 1935 by the Shih Tzu Club,&lt;ref&gt;The Shih Tzu, by Audrey Dadds, pg 29, Howell Book House, 1975, ISBN 0876053096&lt;/ref&gt; and the dogs were recategorised as Shih Tzu. The breed spread throughout Europe, and was brought to the United States after World War II, when returning members of the US military brought back dogs from Europe. The Shih Tzu was recognised by the [[American Kennel Club]] in 1969 in the [[Toy Group]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Clark/Brace&quot; /&gt; The breed is now recognised by all of the major kennel clubs in the English-speaking world.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}} It is also recognised by the [[Fédération Cynologique Internationale]] for international competition in Companion and Toy Dog Group, Section 5, Tibetan breeds.&lt;ref name=&quot;FCIstandard&quot;/&gt;

== Health ==
A number of health issues, some of them hereditary, have been found in individual Shih Tzu, and are listed below. There is no data on the percentage of dogs with these ailments.

==Hypothyroidism==
This is a thyroid malfunction that occurs when the thyroid gland stops functioning and producing thyroid hormone responsible for proper metabolism. This malfunction is commonly attributed to immune system problems. It is usually affects middle-aged dogs and is seen in all breeds. Symptoms include hair loss, weight gain, muscle loss, and lethargy. If left untreated, it can result in heart problems. This disease is usually diagnosed through blood tests. It can be effectively treated with drug therapy.

==Intervertebral Disk Disease==
IVD in the dog is a common disorder manifested by acute pain, loss of movement coordination and paralysis. It commonly occurs in certain breeds of dogs called chondrodystrophoid breeds, such as Dachshund, Pekingese, French bulldog, Beagle, Basset Hound, American Cocker spaniel, Shih Tzu, Lhasa Apso, Welsh Corgi.

=== Morbidity ===
Some health issues in the breed are [[portosystemic shunt]] of the liver and [[hip dysplasia (canine)|hip dysplasia]] in standard sizes. Shih Tzu can also have brain problems, such as cancer, that they are born with. This often shortens the life span. There have been cases of Shih Tzu being epileptic, in turn this also shortens the life span.&lt;ref name=&quot;health&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=All About Shih Tzu |work=Shih Tzu Fanciers of Southern CA |url=http://stfsc.bizland.com/health.htm |accessdate=2011-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Breathing problems ====

Shih Tzu have a lot of respiratory problems related to the shape of their face and head (the brachycephalic syndrome) which affects mostly dogs with a short nose (brachycephalic breeds). Due to an obstruction in the upper airways, the dog is forced to labored breathing. Not every brachycephalic dog will develop respiratory problems but most will to some degree or the other. Severe problems may require surgery.

===Mortality ===
UK Kennel Club survey puts the average life span of a Shih Tzu at 13 years 2 months with most living between 6 and 16 years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thekennelclub.org.uk/download/1625/hsshihtzu.pdf|title=2004 Purebred Dog Health Survey|publisher=KC/BSAVA|accessdate=6 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Coat colors==
[[File:LiverandWhite.jpg|thumb|200px|right|A liver and white Shih Tzu with a liver-colored nose.]]

The Shih Tzu comes in a range of colors that include various shades of gold, white and brown.   Other colors include black mask gold, black and white, solid black, solid liver, liver and white,  brindle and white and silver and white.&lt;ref name=&quot;American Shih Tzu Club&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://americanshihtzuclub.org/colors |title=Shih Tzu Colors &amp;#124; American Shih Tzu Club |work=americanshihtzuclub.org |accessdate=2010-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though not as common there are also solid blue Shih Tzu. An interesting point (and often a point of confusion) is that while the coat color of those with black pigmented skin (nose, lips, pads, also referred to as &quot;leather&quot;) is determined by the color of the coat itself; the coat color on dogs with either liver or blue pigment is categorized by the colour of the pigment. Thus a parti colored (white and another shade) Shih Tzu with blue pigment is a &quot;blue and white&quot; regardless of the tint of the hair which might very well appear similar to a gold and white or other colors. The same principle applies to solid blue, liver and liver and white.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dixidew Shih Tzu of GA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shihtzuga.netfirms.com|title=Coat Colors |accessdate=2010-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Variations ==
=== Kennel club differences ===
There is a difference between the [[American Kennel Club]] and the [[Kennel Club (UK)]] Shih Tzu:

==== The AKC (American Kennel Club) Shih Tzu ====
* Their front legs (forequarters) are straight. Their hindquarters are muscular. Neither should be too short nor too long.
* The chest is wide or broad.
* The standard head is big and round and is set high with face looking forward or up.
* The neck and body are of the utmost importance and should not be exaggerated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.americanshihtzuclub.org/ill_neck_body |title=The Illustrated Guide To The Shih Tzu Standard &amp;#124; American Shih Tzu Club |work=americanshihtzuclub.org |accessdate=2011-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The eyes are large and face the front.
* The shoulders of the American type of Shih Tzu are frontal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.akc.org/breeds/shih_tzu/index.cfm American Kennel Club Breed Standard]&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{commons}}

*{{dmoz|Recreation/Pets/Dogs/Breeds/Toy_Group/Shih_Tzu/}}
&lt;!-- Editors: Place all breed related kennel, club, and rescue links, as well as photograph links and other information links about the breed, on the appropriate Open Directory Project (DMOZ) page, not in the Wikipedia article &quot;External links&quot; section. Instructions for submitting links are on the Open Directory Project/DMOZ page.--&gt;
* [http://www.akc.org/breeds/shih_tzu/video.cfm AKC Shih Tzu Video]
* [http://www.shitsu.info Shitsu]

{{Toy dogs}}

[[Category:Companion dogs]]
[[Category:Dog breeds originating in China]]
[[Category:Toy dogs]]

[[ca:Shih-tzu]]
[[cs:Shih-tzu]]
[[de:Shih Tzu]]
[[es:Shih Tzu]]
[[fr:Shih Tzu]]
[[ko:시추]]
[[id:Shih-Tzu]]
[[it:Shih-Tzu]]
[[he:שי טסו]]
[[lt:Ši Cu]]
[[hu:Si-cu]]
[[nl:Shih Tzu]]
[[ja:シーズー]]
[[no:Shih tzu]]
[[pnb:شی زو]]
[[pl:Shih tzu]]
[[pt:Shih-tzu]]
[[ru:Ши-тцу]]
[[simple:Shih Tzu]]
[[sl:Shih-tzu]]
[[fi:Shih tzu]]
[[sv:Shih tzu]]
[[th:ซือจื่อ]]
[[tr:Shih tzu]]
[[uk:Ши-тцу]]
[[zh:西施犬]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
