<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30479" ns="0" title="Thomas More"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=July 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Other uses}}

{{Infobox officeholder
|honorific-prefix   = &lt;small&gt;[[The Right Honourable]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
|name               = Sir Thomas More&lt;br&gt;
|honorific-suffix   =
|image              = Hans Holbein d. J. 065.jpg
|imagesize          = 220px
|office             = [[Lord Chancellor]]
|term_start         = October 1529
|term_end           = May 1532
|preceded           = [[Thomas Wolsey]]
|succeeded          = [[Thomas Audley, 1st Baron Audley of Walden|Thomas Audley]]
|office1            = [[Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster]]
|term_start1        = 31 December 1525
|term_end1          = 3 November 1529
|preceded1          = [[Richard Wingfield]]
|succeeded1         = [[William FitzWilliam, 1st Earl of Southampton|William FitzWilliam]]
|office2            = [[List of Speakers of the House of Commons of England|Speaker of the House of Commons]]
|term_start2        = 16 April 1523
|term_end2          = 13 August 1523
|preceded2          = [[Thomas Neville]]
|succeeded2         = [[Thomas Audley, 1st Baron Audley of Walden|Thomas Audley]]
|birth_date         = 7 February 1478
|death_date         = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1535|7|6|1478|2|7 }}
|birth_place        = [[City of London]], [[County of London|London]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Kingdom of England]]
|death_place        = [[Tower Hill]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Metropolitan Borough of Stepney|Stepney]], [[County of London|London]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Kingdom of England]]
|signature          = Thomas More Signature.svg
}}

'''Sir Thomas More''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|m|ɔr}}; 7 February 1478 {{ndash}}6 July 1535), also known by Catholics as '''Saint Thomas More''', was an English lawyer, [[social philosopher]], author, [[statesman]] and noted [[Renaissance humanism|Renaissance humanist]]. He was an important councillor to [[Henry VIII of England]] and, for three years toward the end of his life, [[Lord Chancellor]]. He is recognised as a [[saint]] within the Catholic Church and is commemorated by the Church of England as a &quot;Reformation martyr&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | url = http://www.churchofengland.org/prayer-worship/worship/texts/the-calendar/holydays.aspx
  | title = Holy Days
  | work=Worship – The Calendar
  | publisher=[[Church of England]]
  | year = 2011
  | accessdate =20 April 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He was an opponent of the [[Protestant Reformation]] and in particular of [[Martin Luther]] and [[William Tyndale]].

More coined the word &quot;[[utopia]]&quot; – a name he gave to the ideal and imaginary island nation, the political system of which he described in ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'' published in 1516. He opposed the king's separation from the Catholic Church and refused to accept the king as [[Supreme Head]] of the [[Church of England]], a status the king had been given by a compliant parliament through the [[Acts of Supremacy|Act of Supremacy of 1534]]. He was imprisoned in 1534 for his refusal to take the oath required by the [[First Succession Act]] because the act disparaged the power of the Pope and Henry’s marriage to [[Catherine of Aragon]]. In 1535, he was tried for treason, convicted on perjured testimony and beheaded. 

Intellectuals and statesmen across Europe were stunned by More's execution.  [[Erasmus]] saluted him as one &quot;whose soul was more pure than any snow&quot;.{{fact|date=November 2011}} Two centuries later [[Jonathan Swift]] said he was &quot;the person of the greatest virtue this kingdom ever produced&quot;,{{fact|date=November 2011}} a sentiment with which [[Samuel Johnson]] agreed.  Historian [[Hugh Trevor-Roper]] said in 1977 that More was &quot;the first great Englishman whom we feel that we know, the most saintly of humanists, the most human of saints, the universal man of our cool northern renaissance.&quot;&lt;ref&gt; Cited in Marvin O'Connell, &quot;A Man for all Seasons: an Historian's Demur,&quot; ''Catholic Dossier'' 8 no. 2 (March-April, 2002): 16-19 [http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/politics/pg0078.html online]&lt;/ref&gt; The Catholic Church proclaimed him a saint in 1935. The Franciscan order has the tradition that he was a member of the [[Third Order of St. Francis]] and venerates his memory as a member of the order.

==Early life==
{{Infobox saint
|name            = Saint Thomas More
|feast_day       = 22 June (Catholic Church)&lt;br /&gt;6 July (on some local calendars) 9 July on the traditional Catholic (Latin Mass) calendar
|venerated_in    = Catholic Church; [[Anglican Communion]]
|caption         = [[File:Thomas More Signature.svg|150px]]&lt;br /&gt;Portrait by [[Hans Holbein the Younger]] (1527).
|titles          = Martyr
|beatified_date  = 1886
|beatified_place = Florence
|beatified_by    = [[Pope Leo XIII]]
|canonized_date  = 19 May 1935
|canonized_place = Rome
|canonized_by    = [[Pope Pius XI]]
|attributes      = dressed in the robe of the [[Lord Chancellor|Chancellor]] and wearing the [[Livery collar|Collar of Esses]]; [[axe]]
|patronage       = [[KCYM (Kerala Catholic Youth Movement)]]; Adopted children; [[Ateneo Law School | Ateneo de Manila Law School]]; civil servants; [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Arlington|Diocese of Arlington]]; [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Pensacola-Tallahassee | Diocese of Pensacola-Tallahassee]]; [[University of Malta]]; [[University of Santo Tomas Faculty of Arts and Letters]]; [[court clerk]]s; lawyers, politicians, and [[statesman|statesmen]]; [[Stepfamily|stepparents]]; [[widow]]ers; difficult marriages; large families
|suppressed_date =
|issues          =
|prayer          =
|prayer_attrib   =
}}

Born in Milk Street in London on 7 February 1478, Thomas More was the son of [[Sir John More]],&lt;ref&gt; Jokinen, A. (13 June 2009). [http://www.luminarium.org/renlit/morebio.htm &quot;The Life of Sir Thomas More.&quot;]  Luminarium. Retrieved on: 2011-09-19.&lt;/ref&gt; a successful lawyer, and his wife Agnes (''née'' Graunger). More was educated at St Anthony's School, considered one of the finest schools in London at that time. He later spent the years 1490 to 1492 as a page in the household service of [[John Morton (archbishop)|John Morton]], the [[Archbishop of Canterbury]] and Lord Chancellor of England.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rebhorn&quot;&gt;{{citation | editor-last = Rebhorn | editor-first = Wayne A | title = Utopia | place = New York | publisher=Barnes &amp; Noble | series = Classics | year = 2005 | chapter = Introduction}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |xvi}}  Morton enthusiastically supported the &quot;[[New Learning]]&quot; of the Renaissance, and thought highly of the young More. Believing that More showed great potential, Morton nominated him for a place at Oxford University (either in [[Oriel College, Oxford |St. Mary's Hall (Oriel)]] or [[Canterbury College, Oxford|Canterbury College]]), where More began his studies in 1492.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot;&gt;{{citation | last = Ackroyd | first = Peter | title = The Life of Thomas More | place = New York | publisher=Anchor Books | year = 1999}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |38}}  More may have lived and studied at nearby St. Mary’s Hall. Both Canterbury College and St Mary’s Hall have since disappeared; part of Christ Church College is on the site of Canterbury, and part of Oriel College is on the site of St Mary’s. More received a classical education at Oxford and was a pupil of [[Thomas Linacre]] and [[William Grocyn]], becoming proficient in both Greek and Latin. He left Oxford in 1494 – after only two years – at the insistence of his father, to begin his legal training in London at New Inn, one of the Inns of Chancery.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rebhorn&quot; /&gt;{{rp |xvii}}&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last = Harpsfield | first = Nicholas | title = The Life and Death of Sr Thomas More | place = London | publisher=Early English Text Society | year = 1931 | pages = 12–3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1496, he became a student at Lincoln’s Inn, one of the Inns of Court, where he remained until 1502, when he was called to the bar.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rebhorn&quot; /&gt;{{rp |xvii}} 

According to his friend, the theologian [[Desiderius Erasmus of Rotterdam]], More once seriously contemplated abandoning his legal career to become a [[monk]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last = Erasmus | contribution = Letter to Ulrich von Hutten | editor-last = Adams | editor-first = Robert M | title = Utopia | place = New York | publisher=WW Norton &amp; Co | page = 125}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Between 1503 and 1504 More lived near the Carthusian monastery outside the walls of London and joined in the monks' spiritual exercises. Although he deeply admired the piety of the monks, he ultimately decided on the life of a layman upon his marriage and election to Parliament in 1504.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebhorn&quot; /&gt;{{rp |xxi}}  In spite of his choice to pursue a secular career, More continued to observe certain ascetical practices for the rest of his life, such as wearing a [[Cilice|hair shirt]] next to his skin and occasionally engaging in [[flagellation]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Rebhorn&quot;/&gt;{{rp |xxi}}

==Family life==

More married Jane Colt in 1505.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |118}}  She was nearly ten years his junior and was said by More's friends to be quiet and good-natured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |119}}  [[Erasmus]] reported that More had taken an interest early on in giving his young wife a better education than she had previously received at home, and became a personal tutor to her in the areas of music and literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |119}}  More had four children with Jane: [[Margaret Roper|Margaret]], Elizabeth, Cicely, and John.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |132}}  When Jane died in 1511, More remarried almost immediately, choosing as his second wife a rich widow named Alice Middleton. Alice More did not enjoy the reputation for docility that her predecessor had and was instead known as a strong and outspoken woman. More's friend Andrew Ammonius derided Alice as a &quot;hook-nosed harpy&quot;, although Erasmus attested that the marriage was a happy one.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |144}}  More and Alice did not have children together, although More raised Alice's daughter from her previous marriage as his own. More became the guardian of a young girl named Anne Cresacre, who would eventually marry his son, John More.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |146}}  More was an affectionate father who wrote letters to his children whenever he was away on legal or government business, and encouraged them to write to him often.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rogers&quot;&gt;{{citation | editor-last = Rogers | editor-first = Elizabeth Frances | first = St Thomas | last = More | title = Selected Letters | place = New Haven and London | publisher=Yale University Press | year = 1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |xiv}}&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |150}}

More took a serious interest in the education of women, an attitude that was highly unusual at the time. Believing women to be just as capable of academic accomplishment as men, More insisted upon giving his daughters the same classical education given to his son.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |146–47}}  The academic star of the family was More's eldest daughter Margaret, who attracted much admiration for her erudition, especially her fluency in Greek and Latin.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |147}}  More recounted a moment of such admiration in a letter to Margaret in September 1522, when the Bishop of Exeter was shown a letter written by Margaret to More:

{{quote |
When he saw from the signature that it was the letter of a lady, his surprise led him to read it more eagerly... he said he would never have believed it to be your work unless I had assured him of the fact, and he began to praise it in the highest terms... for its pure Latinity, its correctness, its erudition, and its expressions of tender affection. He took out at once from his pocket a portague [A Portuguese gold coin]... to send to you as a pledge and token of his good will towards you.&lt;ref name = &quot;Rogers&quot;&gt;{{citation | editor-last = Rogers | editor-first = Elizabeth Frances | first = St Thomas | last = More | title = Selected Letters | place = New Haven and London | publisher=Yale University Press | year = 1961}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |152}}}}

The success More enjoyed in educating his daughters set an example for other noble families. Even Erasmus became much more favourable towards the idea once he witnessed the accomplishments of More's daughters.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |149}}

==Early political career==
[[Image:Study for portrait of the More family, by Hans Holbein the Younger.jpg|thumb|right|Study for a portrait of Thomas More's family, c. 1527, by [[Hans Holbein the Younger]]]]

In 1504 he was elected to Parliament to represent [[Great Yarmouth (UK Parliament constituency)|Great Yarmouth]] and in 1510 to represent [[London (UK Parliament constituency)|London]]. &lt;ref&gt; {{cite web | url = http://www.historyofparliamentonline.org/volume/1509-1558/member/more-thomas-i-147778-1535| title = History of Parliament| publisher= History of Parliament Trust|accessdate = 2011-10-13}} &lt;/ref&gt;

From 1510, More served as one of the two [[undersheriff]]s of the [[City of London]], a position of considerable responsibility in which he earned a reputation as an honest and effective public servant. More became [[Master of Requests]] in 1514,&lt;ref&gt;Magnusson (ed.) Chambers Biographical Dictionary (1990) pg 1039&lt;/ref&gt; the same year in which he was appointed as a [[Privy Councillor]], a member of His Majesty's Most Honourable Privy Council.&lt;ref name=rebhorn&gt;Rebhorn, W. A. (ed.) pg xviii&lt;/ref&gt; After undertaking a diplomatic mission to the [[Holy Roman Emperor]], [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]], accompanying [[Thomas Wolsey]] to [[Calais]] and [[Bruges]], More was knighted and made under-treasurer of the Exchequer in 1521.&lt;ref name=rebhorn/&gt;

As secretary and personal adviser to [[Henry VIII of England|King Henry VIII]], More became increasingly influential in the government, welcoming foreign diplomats, drafting official documents, and serving as a liaison between the king and his Lord Chancellor: [[Thomas Wolsey]], the [[Cardinal (Catholicism)|Cardinal]] [[Archbishop of York]].

In 1523 he was elected as [[knight of the shire]] (MP) for [[Middlesex (UK Parliament constituency)|Middlesex]] and, recommended by Wolsey, was elected the [[List of Speakers of the House of Commons of England|Speaker]] of the [[House of Commons of England|House of Commons]].&lt;ref name=rebhorn/&gt;

He later served as [[High Steward (academia)|High Steward]] for the universities of Oxford and Cambridge. In 1525 he became [[chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster]], a position that entailed administrative and judicial control of much of northern England.&lt;ref name=rebhorn/&gt;

==Scholarly and literary work==
[[Image:Utopia.jpg|thumb|right|[[Woodcut]] by [[Ambrosius Holbein]] for a 1518 edition of ''Utopia.'' The traveller Raphael Hythlodeaus is depicted in the lower left-hand corner describing to a listener the island of [[Utopia]], whose layout is schematically shown above him.]]

Between 1512 and 1519, Thomas More worked on a ''History of King Richard III'', which was never finished, but which greatly influenced [[William Shakespeare]]'s play ''[[Richard III (play)|Richard III]]''. Both More's and Shakespeare's works are controversial to contemporary historians for their unflattering portrait of King Richard III, a bias partly due to both authors' allegiance to the reigning [[Tudor dynasty]] that wrested the throne from Richard III in the [[Wars of the Roses]]. More's work, however, little mentions [[Henry VII of England|King Henry VII]], the first Tudor king, perhaps for having persecuted his father, Sir John More. Some historians see an attack on royal tyranny, rather than on Richard III himself or on the [[House of York]].

The ''History of King Richard III'' is a [[Renaissance]] history, remarkable more for its literary skill and adherence to classical precepts than for its historical accuracy. More's work, and that of contemporary historian [[Polydore Vergil]], reflects a move from mundane [[medieval]] chronicles to a dramatic writing style; for example, the shadowy King Richard is an outstanding, archetypal tyrant drawn from the pages of [[Sallust]], and should be read as a meditation on power and corruption as well as a history of the reign of Richard III. The '''History of King Richard III'' was written and published in both English and [[Latin]], each written separately, and with information deleted from the Latin edition to suit a European readership.

===''Utopia''===
{{Main|Utopia (book)}}

More sketched out his best known and most controversial work, ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'' (completed and published in 1516), a novel in Latin. In it a traveller, Raphael Hythlodeaus (in Greek, his name and surname allude to archangel Raphael, purveyor of truth, and mean &quot;speaker of nonsense&quot;), describes the political arrangements of the imaginary island country of Utopia (Greek pun on ''ou-topos'' [no place], ''eu-topos'' [good place]) to himself and to [[Pieter Gillis]]. This novel describes the city of Amaurote by saying, &quot;Of them all this is the worthiest and of most dignity&quot;.

''Utopia'' contrasts the contentious social life of European states with the perfectly orderly, reasonable social arrangements of Utopia and its environs (Tallstoria, Nolandia, and Aircastle). In Utopia, with communal ownership of land, private property does not exist, men and women are educated alike, and there is almost complete [[religious toleration]]. Some take the novel's principal message to be the social need for order and discipline rather than liberty. The country of Utopia tolerates different religious practices but does not tolerate atheists. Hythlodeaus theorises that if a man did not believe in a god or in an afterlife he could never be trusted, because he would not acknowledge any authority or principle outside himself.

More used the novel describing an imaginary nation as a means of freely discussing contemporary controversial matters; speculatively, he based Utopia on monastic communalism, based upon the Biblical communalism in the ''[[Acts of the Apostles]]''.

''Utopia'' is a forerunner of the utopian literary genre, wherein ideal societies and perfect cities are detailed. Although Utopianism is typically a Renaissance movement, combining the classical concepts of perfect societies of [[Plato]] and [[Aristotle]] with Roman [[rhetorical]] finesse (cf. [[Cicero]], [[Quintilian]], [[epideictic]] oratory), it continued into the [[Enlightenment age|Enlightenment]]. ''Utopia'''s original edition included the symmetrical &quot;Utopian alphabet&quot; that was omitted from later editions; it is a notable, early attempt at [[cryptography]] that might have influenced the development of [[shorthand]].

''Utopia'' ironically points out, through Raphael, More's ultimate conflict between his beliefs as a humanist and a servant of the King at court. More tries to illustrate how he can try and influence courtly figures including the king to the humanist way of thinking but as Raphael points out, one day they will come into conflict with the political reality.

===Religious polemics===
In 1520 the reformer [[Martin Luther]] published three works in quick succession: ''An Appeal to the Christian Nobility of the German Nation'' (Aug.), ''Concerning the Babylonish Captivity of the Church'' (Oct.), and ''On the Liberty of a Christian Man'' (Nov.).&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |225}}  In these works Luther set out his doctrine of salvation through grace alone, rejected certain Catholic practices, and attacked the abuses and excesses of the Catholic Church.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |225–6}}  In 1521, [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] responded to Luther’s criticisms with a work known as the ''Assertio'', written with the editorial assistance of More. In light of this work, [[Pope Leo X]] rewarded Henry VIII with the title ''Fidei defensor'' (“Defender of the Faith”) for his efforts in combating Luther’s heresies.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |226–7}}

Martin Luther then attacked Henry VIII in print, calling him a “pig, dolt, and liar”.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |227}}  At the request of Henry VIII, More set about composing a rebuttal: the resulting ''Responsio ad Lutherum'' was published at the end of 1523. In the ''Responsio'', More defended the supremacy of the papacy, the sacraments, and other church traditions. More’s language, like Luther’s, was virulent, and he branded Luther an “ape”, a “drunkard”, and a “lousy little friar” amongst other insults.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |230}}

This confrontation with Luther confirmed More’s theological conservatism, and from then on his work was devoid of all hints of criticism of Church authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |230}}  In 1528, More produced another religious polemic, ''A Dialogue Concerning Heresies'' that asserted that the Catholic Church was the one true Church, whose authority had been established by Christ and the Apostles, and that its traditions and practices were valid.&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |279–81}}  In 1529, the circulation of [[Simon Fish]]’s ''Supplication for the Beggars'' provoked a response from More entitled, ''The Supplication of Souls''.

In 1531, [[William Tyndale]] published ''An Answer unto Sir Thomas More’s Dialogue'' in response to More’s ''Dialogue Concerning Heresies''. After having read Tyndale’s work, More wrote his half-a-million-word-long ''Confutation of Tyndale’s Answer'' over the next several months. The ''Confutation'' is written as a dialogue between More and Tyndale in which More responds to each of Tyndale’s criticisms of Catholic rites and doctrines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |307–9}}  These literary battles convinced More, who valued structure, tradition, and order in society above all else, that [[Lutheranism]] and the [[Protestant Reformation]] in general were dangerous, not only to the Catholic faith but to the stability of society as a whole.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |307–9}}

===Correspondence===
Most major humanists were prolific letter writers, and Thomas More was no exception. However, as in the case of his friend [[Erasmus of Rotterdam]], only a small portion of his correspondence (about 280 letters), survived. These letters include everything from personal letters to official government correspondence (mostly in English), letters to fellow humanist scholars (in Latin), including several epistolary tracts, [[verse epistles]], prefatory letters (some fictional) to several of More's own works, letters to his children and their tutors (in Latin), and the so-called &quot;Prison-Letters&quot; (in English) which he exchanged with his oldest daughter, [[Margaret Roper]] while he was imprisoned in the [[Tower of London]] awaiting execution.&lt;ref&gt;Romuald I. Lakowski, &quot;Sir Thomas More's Correspondence: A Survey and a Bibliography,&quot; in: ''The Late Medieval Epistle'', ed. Carol Poster and Richard Utz (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 1996), pp. 162–79.&lt;/ref&gt;

More wrote about the more spiritual aspects of religion. This is how he wrote ''A Treatise on the Passion'' (Treatise on the Passion of Christ), ''A Treatise to Receive the Blessed Body'' (Holy Body Treaty), and ''De Tristitia Christi'' (The Agony of Christ), which reads his own hand in the [[Tower of London]] at the time he was confined before his beheading on 6 July 1535. This last [[manuscript]], saved from the confiscation decreed by Henry VIII, passed by the will of his daughter Margaret to Spanish hands and through Fray Pedro de Soto, confessor of [[Emperor Charles V]], went to Valencia, home of [[Luis Vives]], a close friend of More. Now kept in the collection of Real Colegio Seminario del Corpus Christi Museum in [[Valencia, Spain|Valencia]], Spain.

==Chancellorship==
After [[Thomas Wolsey|Wolsey]] fell, More succeeded to the office of [[Lord Chancellor|Chancellor]] in 1529. He dispatched cases with unprecedented rapidity. Fully devoted to Henry and the [[royal prerogative]], More initially co-operated with the king's new policy, denouncing Wolsey in Parliament and joining the opinion of the theologians at Oxford and Cambridge that the marriage of Henry to Catherine had been unlawful. But as Henry began to deny the authority of the Pope, More's qualms grew.

===Campaign against the Reformation===
{{Expert-subject-multiple|Catholicism|History|Christianity|date=January 2010}}
More supported the Catholic Church and saw the [[Reformation]] as [[heresy]], a threat to the unity of both church and society. Believing in the theology, polemics, and ecclesiastical laws of the Church, More &quot;heard Luther's call to destroy the Catholic Church as a call to war.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Gerard B. Wegemer, &quot;Portrait of Courage&quot;, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

His early actions against the [[Protestant Reformation| Reformation]] included aiding Wolsey in preventing Lutheran books from being imported into England, spying on and investigating suspected Protestants, especially publishers, and arresting any one holding in his possession, transporting, or selling the books of the Protestant reformation. More vigorously suppressed the travelling country ministers who used [[William Tyndale|Tyndale's]] [[Tyndale Bible|English translation of the New Testament]]. This English language translation of the Bible challenged the Catholic monopoly of reading the Latin Bible. It contained translations of certain words—for example Tyndale used &quot;elder&quot; rather than &quot;priest&quot; for the Greek &quot;presbuteros&quot;—and some footnotes which challenged Catholic Doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;Moynahan, Brian, ''God's Bestseller: William Tyndale, Thomas More, and the Writing of the English Bible – A Story of Martyrdom and Betrayal'', St Martin's Press; 1st edition (23 August 2003).&lt;/ref&gt; It was during this time that most of his literary polemics appeared.

[[Image:HouseOfMore.JPG|left|thumb|Sir Thomas More is commemorated with a sculpture at the late 19th-century Sir Thomas More House, opposite the [[Royal Courts of Justice]], Carey Street, London.]]

Rumours circulated both during More's lifetime and posthumously regarding the treatment of heretics during his time as Lord Chancellor. The popular anti-Catholic polemicist [[John Foxe]], who &quot;placed Protestant sufferings against the background of... the Antichrist&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Diarmaid MacCulloch, 277.&lt;/ref&gt; was instrumental in spreading rumours of torture in his famous ''[[Foxe's Book of Martyrs |Book of Martyrs]]'', claiming that More had often personally used violence or torture while interrogating heretics.  More current Protestant authors, such as [[Brian Moynahan]] and [[Michael Farris]], continue to cite Foxe as a source when repeating these allegations in their own respective works.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | first = Michael | last = Farris | title = From Tyndale to Madison | year = 2007}}.&lt;/ref&gt; More himself denied these allegations:

{{quote|Stories of a similar nature were current even in More's lifetime and he denied them forcefully. He admitted that he did imprison heretics in his house – 'theyr sure kepynge' – he called it – but he utterly rejected claims of torture and whipping... 'so helpe me God.'&lt;ref name= &quot;Ackroyd&quot;&gt;{{citation | last = Ackroyd | first = P}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp |298}}}}

In total there were six heretics burned at the stake during More's Chancellorship: [[Thomas Hitton]], [[Thomas Bilney]], [[Richard Bayfield]], John Tewkesbery, Thomas Dusgate, and [[James Bainham]].&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |299–306}}  Burning at the stake had long been a standard punishment for heresy—about thirty burnings had taken place in the century before More's elevation to Chancellor, and burning continued to be used by both Catholics as well as Protestants during the religious upheaval of the following decades.&lt;ref&gt;Guy, John A. ''Tudor England'' Oxford, 1988. pg 26&lt;/ref&gt; Ackroyd notes that More explicitly &quot;approved of Burning&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;Ackroyd&quot; /&gt;{{rp |298}}  After the case of John Tewkesbury, a London leather-seller found guilty by More of harbouring banned books and sentenced to burning for refusing to recant, More declared: he &quot;burned as there was neuer wretche I wene better worthy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | publisher=Yale | series = Complete Works | first = Thomas | last = More | volume = 8 | title = The Confutation of Tyndale's Answer | editor1-last = Schuster | editor1-first = LA | editor2-last = Marius | editor2-first = RC | editor3-last = Lusardi | editor3-first = JP | editor4-last = Schoeck | editor4-first = RJ | year = 1973 | page = 20}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians have been long divided over More's religious actions as Chancellor. While biographers such as Ackroyd have taken a relatively tolerant view of More's campaign against Protestantism by placing his actions within the turbulent religious climate of the time, other equally eminent historians, such as [[Richard Marius]], have been more critical, believing that such persecutions were a betrayal of More's earlier humanist convictions. As Marius writes in his biography of More: &quot;To stand before a man at an inquisition, knowing that he will rejoice when we die, knowing that he will commit us to the stake and its horrors without a moment's hesitation or remorse if we do not satisfy him, is not an experience much less cruel because our inquisitor does not whip us or rack us or shout at us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | last = Marius | first = R | title = Thomas More: A Biography | publisher=Collins | series = Fount Paperbacks | place = London | year = 1986 | page = 407}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Resignation===
As the conflict over supremacy between the Papacy and the King reached its apogee, More continued to remain steadfast in supporting the supremacy of the Papal throne over that of his King. In 1530, More refused to sign a letter by the leading English churchmen and aristocrats asking the Pope to annul Henry's marriage to Catherine, and furthermore, quarrelled with Henry VIII over the heresy laws. In 1531, Henry had isolated More by purging most clergy who supported the Papal stance from senior positions in the Church. In addition, Henry had solidified his denial of the Papacy's control of England by passing the [[Praemunire|Statute of Praemunire]] which forbade appeals to the [[Roman Curia]] from England. Realizing his isolated position, More attempted to resign after being forced to take an oath declaring the king the Supreme Head of the English Church &quot;as far as the law of Christ allows&quot;. Furthermore, the Statute of Praemunire made it a crime to support in public or office the claims of the Papacy. Thus, he refused to take the oath in the form in which it would renounce all claims of jurisdiction over the church except the sovereign's. Nonetheless, the reputation and influence of More as well as his long relationship with Henry, kept his life secure for the time being and consequently, he was not relieved of office. However, with his supporters in court quickly disappearing, in 1532 he asked the king again to relieve him of his office, claiming that he was ill and suffering from sharp chest pains. This time Henry granted his request.

==Trial and execution==
[[Image:More famB 1280x-g0.jpg|right|thumb|270px|[[Rowland Lockey]] after [[Hans Holbein the Younger]], ''The Family of Sir Thomas More'', c. 1594]]
In 1533, More refused to attend the [[coronation]] of [[Anne Boleyn]] as the [[Queen consort|Queen of England]]. Technically, this was not an act of treason, as More had written to Henry acknowledging Anne's queenship and expressing his desire for the king's happiness and the new queen's health.&lt;ref&gt;[[Eric Ives|Eric W. Ives]], ''The Life and Death of [[Anne Boleyn]]'' (2004), p. 47. More wrote on the subject of the Boleyn marriage that &quot;[I] neither murmur at it nor dispute upon it, nor never did nor will... I faithfully pray to God for his Grace and hers both long to live and well, and their noble issue too...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Despite this, his refusal to attend was widely interpreted as a snub against Anne, and Henry took action against him.

Shortly thereafter, More was charged with accepting bribes, but the patently false charges had to be dismissed for lack of any evidence, given More's reputation as a judge who could not be bribed. In early 1534, More was accused of conspiring with the &quot;Holy Maid of Kent,&quot; [[Elizabeth Barton]], a nun who had prophesied against the king's annulment, but More was able to produce a letter in which he had instructed Barton not to interfere with state matters.

On 13 April 1534, More was asked to appear before a commission and swear his allegiance to the parliamentary [[First Succession Act|Act of Succession]]. More accepted Parliament's right to declare [[Anne Boleyn]] the legitimate queen of England, but he steadfastly refused to take the oath of supremacy of the Crown in the relationship between the Kingdom and the Church in England. Holding fast to the ancient teaching of [[Papal supremacy]], More refused to take the oath and furthermore publicly refused to uphold Henry's annulment from Catherine. [[John Fisher]], Bishop of Rochester, refused the oath along with More. The oath reads:

{{quote|...By reason whereof the Bishop of Rome and See Apostolic, contrary to the great and inviolable grants of jurisdictions given by God immediately to emperors, kings and princes in succession to their heirs, hath presumed in times past to invest who should please them to inherit in other men's kingdoms and dominions, which thing we your most humble subjects, both spiritual and temporal, do most abhor and detest;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 |last=Elton
 |first=Geoffrey Rudolph
 |title=The Tudor constitution: documents and commentary
 |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]]
 |year=1982
 |isbn=0521245060
 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CJZZzoBJOfwC&amp;pg=PA7
 |accessdate=24 July 2009
 |location=Cambridge, Cambridgeshire
 |oclc=7876927
 |page=7
 |edition=2nd
 |chapter=The Crown
 |chapterurl=http://books.google.com/books?id=CJZZzoBJOfwC&amp;lpg=PA7&amp;pg=PA1
}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

With his refusal to support the King's annulment, More's enemies had enough evidence to have the King arrest him on treason. Four days later, Henry had More imprisoned in the [[Tower of London]]. There More prepared a devotional ''Dialogue of Comfort against Tribulation''. While More was imprisoned in the Tower, [[Thomas Cromwell, 1st Earl of Essex|Thomas Cromwell]] made several visits, urging More to take the oath, which More continued to refuse.

On 1 July 1535, More was tried before a panel of judges that included the new Lord Chancellor, [[Thomas Audley, 1st Baron Audley of Walden|Sir Thomas Audley]], as well as Anne Boleyn's [[Thomas Boleyn, 1st Earl of Wiltshire|father]], [[George Boleyn | brother]], and uncle. He was charged with [[high treason]] for denying the validity of the Act of Succession. More, relying on legal precedent and the maxim &quot;''qui tacet consentire videtur''&quot; (silence presumes consent), understood that he could not be convicted as long as he did not explicitly deny that the king was Supreme Head of the Church, and he therefore refused to answer all questions regarding his opinions on the subject. [[Thomas Cromwell]], at the time the most powerful of the king's advisors, brought forth the [[Solicitor General for England and Wales | Solicitor General]], [[Richard Rich, 1st Baron Rich|Richard Rich]], to testify that More had, in his presence, denied that the king was the legitimate head of the church. This testimony was extremely dubious: witnesses [[Richard Southwell (courtier)|Richard Southwell]] and Mr. Palmer both denied having heard the details of the reported conversation, and as More himself pointed out: &quot;Can it therefore seem likely to your Lordships, that I should in so weighty an Affair as this, act so unadvisedly, as to trust Mr. Rich, a Man I had always so mean an Opinion of, in reference to his Truth and Honesty, ...that I should only impart to Mr. Rich the Secrets of my Conscience in respect to the King's Supremacy, the particular Secrets, and only Point about which I have been so long pressed to explain my self?  which I never did, nor never would reveal; when the Act was once made, either to the King himself, or any of his Privy Councillors, as is well known to your Honours, who have been sent upon no other account at several times by his Majesty to me in the Tower. I refer it to your Judgments, my Lords, whether this can seem credible to any of your Lordships.&quot; However, the jury knew where their own best interests lay, and took only fifteen minutes to find More guilty.

More was tried, and found guilty, under the following section of the [[Treason Act 1534]]:

{{quote|&lt;p&gt;If any person or persons, after the first day of February next coming, do maliciously wish, will or desire, by words or writing, or by craft imagine, invent, practise, or attempt any bodily harm to be done or committed to the king's most royal person, the queen's, or their heirs apparent, or to deprive them or any of them of their dignity, title, or name of their royal estates...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That then every such person and persons so offending... shall have and suffer such pains of death and other penalties, as is limited and accustomed in cases of high treason.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home.freeuk.net/don-aitken/ast/h8a.html#149|title=Annotated original text}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/p&gt;}}

After the jury's verdict was delivered and before his sentencing, More spoke freely of his belief that &quot;no temporal man may be the head of the spirituality&quot;. He was sentenced to be [[hanged, drawn, and quartered]] (the usual punishment for traitors who were not the nobility), but the king commuted this to execution by decapitation. The execution took place on 6 July 1535. When he came to mount the steps to the scaffold, he is widely quoted as saying (to the officials): &quot;I pray you, I pray you, Mr Lieutenant, see me safe up and for my coming down, I can shift for myself&quot;; while on the scaffold he declared that he died &quot;the king's good servant, but God's first.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/more/moreaccount.html|title=Account of trial|accessdate=27 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
===Relics===
Another comment he is believed to have made to the executioner is that his beard was completely innocent of any crime, and did not deserve the axe; he then positioned his beard so that it would not be harmed.&lt;ref&gt;David Hume, ''The history of England'' (1813) p 632 &lt;/ref&gt; More asked that his foster daughter [[Margaret Giggs]] be given his headless corpse to bury.&lt;ref&gt;Guy, John, ''A Daughter's Love: Thomas &amp; Margaret More'', London: Fourth Estate, 2008, ISBN 9780007192311, p. 266.&lt;/ref&gt; He was buried at the Tower of London, in the chapel of [[St Peter ad Vincula (London)|St Peter ad Vincula]] in an unmarked grave. His head was fixed upon a pike over [[London Bridge]] for a month, according to the normal custom for traitors. His daughter [[Margaret Roper|Margaret (Meg) Roper]] rescued it, possibly by bribery, before it could be thrown in the [[River Thames]].

The skull is believed to rest in the Roper Vault of [[St. Dunstan's, Canterbury|St Dunstan's Church, Canterbury]], though some researchers have claimed it might be within the tomb he erected for himself in Chelsea Old Church (see below). The evidence, however, seems to be in favour of its placement in St Dunstan's, with the remains of his daughter, Margaret Roper, and her husband's family, whose vault it was. 

Among other surviving relics is his [[Cilice|hair shirt]], presented for safe keeping by Margaret Clements (1508–70), his adopted daughter.&lt;ref name=&quot;r6&quot;&gt;{{citation | title = Catholic Encyclopaedia | url = http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/14689c.htm}}.&lt;/ref&gt; This was long in the custody of the community of Augustinian canonesses who until 1983 lived at the convent at [[Abbotskerswell Priory]], Devon. It is now preserved at Syon Abbey, near [[South Brent]].

==Canonisation==
[[Image:Chelsea thomas more statue 1.jpg|thumb|230px|Statue of Thomas More by Leslie Cubitt Bevis in front of [[Chelsea Old Church]], [[Cheyne Walk]], London.]]

More was [[beatification|beatified]] by [[Pope Leo XIII]] in 1886 and [[canonise]]d, with [[John Fisher]], on 19 May 1935 by Pope Pius XI, and his feast day was established as 9 July. This day is still observed as his feast day by traditional [Latin Mass] Catholics. Following a series of post-Vatican II reforms, his feast day was changed and his name was added to the [[Roman Catholic calendar of saints]] in 1970 for celebration on 22 June jointly with St John Fisher, the only remaining Bishop (owing to the coincident natural deaths of eight aged bishops) who, during the [[English Reformation]], maintained, at the King's mercy, allegiance to the Pope.&lt;ref&gt;[[Diarmaid MacCulloch]], ''The Reformation'', (New York: Viking, 2004), 194&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, [[Pope John Paul II]] declared More the &quot;heavenly patron of statesmen and politicians&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Apostolic letter]] issued ''[[moto proprio]]'' proclaiming Saint Thomas More Patron of Statesmen and Politicians [http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/motu_proprio/documents/hf_jp-ii_motu-proprio_20001031_thomas-more_en.html Vatican.va]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1980, More was added to the Church of England's calendar of Saints and Heroes of the Christian Church, jointly with [[John Fisher]]. More is commemorated on 6 July.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cofe.anglican.org/worship/liturgy/commonworship/texts/calendar/holydays.html Calendar of Holy Days of the Church of England]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence and reputation==
The steadfastness and courage with which More held on to his religious convictions in the face of ruin and death and the dignity with which he conducted himself during his imprisonment, trial, and execution, contributed much to More's posthumous reputation, particularly among Catholics. Many historians argue that his conviction for treason was unjust, and even among some Protestants his execution was viewed as heavy-handed.{{Citation needed|date=August 2009}} His friend [[Erasmus]] defended More's character as &quot;more pure than any snow&quot; and described his genius as &quot;such as England never had and never again will have.&quot; When he knew of the execution, [[Emperor Charles V]] said:  &quot;Had we been master of such a servant, we would rather have lost the best city of our dominions than such a worthy councillor.&quot;

More was greatly admired by the Anglican writer [[Jonathan Swift]]. Swift wrote that More was &quot;a person of the greatest virtue this kingdom ever produced&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.online-literature.com/swift/religion-church-vol-one/14/ ''Writings on Religion and the Church'', Chapter 14 &quot;Concerning that Universal Hatred which prevails against the Clergy&quot; by Jonathan Swift, 1736]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation | url = http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/reputation.html | publisher=Thomas More Studies | title = Reputation}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Samuel Johnson is often cited as the origin of that quote,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url = http://www.catholicculture.org/culture/library/view.cfm?recnum=7769
 | author=Kenny, Jack
 | title = A Man of Enduring Conscience
 | work=Resource Center
 | publisher=Catholic Culture via Trinity Communications
 | year = 2011
 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | author=Chambers, R. W.
 | title = Sir Thomas More's Fame Among His Countrymen
 | year = 1929
 | publisher=Sheed &amp; Ward
 | location = London
 | isbn =
 | page = 13
 | authorlink = Raymond Wilson Chambers }}&lt;/ref&gt; but mistakenly: it is not to be found in his writings or recorded by Boswell.

The English Roman Catholic writer [[G. K. Chesterton]] said of More that &quot;He may come to be counted the greatest Englishman, or at least the greatest historical character in English history.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | author= Chesterton, G. K.
 | title = The Fame of Blessed Thomas More
 | year = 1929
 | publisher=Sheed &amp; Ward
 | location = London
 | isbn =
 | page = 63
 | authorlink = G. K. Chesterton }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Popular culture==
More was portrayed as a wise and honest statesman in the 1592 play ''[[Sir Thomas More (play)|Sir Thomas More]]'', which was probably written in collaboration by [[Henry Chettle]], [[Anthony Munday]], [[William Shakespeare]], and others, and which survives only in fragmentary form after being censored by Edmund Tylney, [[Master of the Revels]] in the government of [[Elizabeth I of England|Queen Elizabeth I]] (any direct reference to the Act of Supremacy was censored out).

As the author of ''Utopia'', More has attracted the admiration of modern socialists. While Catholic scholars maintain that More's attitude in composing ''Utopia'' was largely ironic and that he was an orthodox Christian, Marxist theoretician [[Karl Kautsky]] argued in the book ''Thomas More and his Utopia'' (1888) that ''Utopia'' was a shrewd critique of economic and social exploitation in pre-modern Europe and that More was one of the key intellectual figures in the early development of socialist ideas. Others have seen in it an attempt at mythologising Indian cultures in the New World during a time when the Catholic Church was still debating over how to view the decidedly anti-Christian cultures of the Indians.

The 20th-century [[agnosticism|agnostic]] playwright [[Robert Bolt]] portrayed Thomas More as the [[tragic hero]] of his 1960 play ''[[A Man for All Seasons]]''. The title being drawn from what [[Robert Whittington]] in 1520 wrote of More:

:&quot;More is a man of an angel's wit and singular learning. I know not his fellow. For where is the man of that gentleness, lowliness and affability? And, as time requireth, a man of marvelous mirth and pastimes, and sometime of as sad gravity. A man for all seasons.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholiceducation.org/articles/politics/pg0078.html A Man for all Seasons: an Historian's Demur&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1966, the play was made into the successful film [[A Man for All Seasons (1966 film)|''A Man for All Seasons'']] directed by [[Fred Zinnemann]], adapted for the screen by the playwright himself, and starring [[Paul Scofield]] in an [[Academy Award for Best Actor|Oscar]]-winning performance. The film won the [[Academy Award for Best Picture]] for that year. In 1988, [[Charlton Heston]] starred and directed in a made-for-television film that followed Bolt's original play almost verbatim, restoring for example the commentaries of &quot;the common man&quot;.

Catholic science fiction writer [[R. A. Lafferty]] wrote his novel ''[[Past Master (novel)|Past Master]]'' as a modern equivalent to More's ''Utopia'', which he saw as a satire. In this novel, Thomas More is brought through time to the year 2535, where he is made king of the future world of &quot;Astrobe&quot;, only to be beheaded after ruling for a mere nine days. One of the characters in the novel compares More favourably to almost every other major historical figure: &quot;He had one completely honest moment right at the end. I cannot think of anyone else who ever had one.&quot;

[[Karl Zuchardt]]'s novel, ''[[Stirb du Narr!]]'' (&quot;Die you fool!&quot;), about More's struggle with [[Henry VIII of England|King Henry]], portrays More as an idealist bound to fail in the power struggle with a ruthless ruler and an unjust world.

A number of modern historians and writers, such as [[Richard Marius]], have evaluated More in his political capacity and have criticised him for [[Anti-Protestantism]] and, &quot;intolerance.&quot; The historian [[Jasper Ridley]], author of several biographies including one on [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] and another on [[Mary I of England|Mary Tudor]], goes much further in his dual biography of More and Cardinal Wolsey, ''The Statesman and the Fanatic'', describing More as &quot;a particularly nasty sadomasochistic pervert,&quot; a line of thinking followed by the late [[Joanna Denny]] in her 2004 biography of [[Anne Boleyn]].

Several authors have criticised More for his war against Protestantism. [[Brian Moynahan]], in his book ''God's Messenger: [[William Tyndale]], Thomas More and the Writing of the English Bible'', takes a similarly critical view of More, as does the American writer [[Michael Farris]]. The novelist [[Hilary Mantel]] portrays More as a religious and masochistic fanatic in her 2009 novel ''[[Wolf Hall]]''. ''Wolf Hall'' is told through the eyes of a sympathetic [[Thomas Cromwell]]. Literary critic [[James Wood (critic)|James Wood]] calls him &quot;cruel in punishment, evasive in argument, lusty for power, and repressive in politics&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | author=Wood, James
 | title = The Broken Estate, Essays on Literature and Belief
 | publisher=Random House
 | location = New York
 | year = 2000
 | isbn = 0-7126-6557-9
 | page = 16
 | pages = 270
 | format = softcover}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Aaron Zelman]]'s non-fiction book ''The State Versus the People'' includes a comparison of ''Utopia'' with Plato's ''Republic''. Zelman is undecided as to whether More was being ironic in his book or was genuinely advocating a [[police state]]. Zelman comments, &quot;More is the only Christian saint to be honoured with a statue at the [[Kremlin]].&quot;{{citation needed|date=April 2011}} By this Zelman implies that ''Utopia'' influenced [[Lenin]]'s [[Bolsheviks]], despite their brutal repression of organised religion.

Other biographers, such as [[Peter Ackroyd]], have offered a more sympathetic picture of More as both a sophisticated philosopher and man of letters, as well as a zealous Catholic who believed in the authority of the [[Holy See]] over [[Christendom]].

The protagonist of [[Walker Percy]]'s novels, ''[[Love in the Ruins]]'' and ''[[The Thanatos Syndrome]]'', is &quot;Dr Thomas More&quot;, a reluctant Catholic and descendant of More.

More is the focus of the [[Al Stewart]] song &quot;A Man For All Seasons&quot; from the 1978 album ''[[Time Passages]]'', and of the [[Far (band)|Far]] song &quot;Sir&quot;, featured on the limited editions and 2008 re-release of their 1994 album ''[[Quick (album)|Quick]]''. In addition, the song &quot;[[So Says I]]&quot; by indie rock outfit [[The Shins]] alludes to the socialist interpretation of More's ''Utopia''.

[[Jeremy Northam]] depicts More in the television series ''[[The Tudors]]''. In ''The Tudors'', More is portrayed as a peaceful man, as well as a devout Roman Catholic and loving family patriarch. He vocally expresses his loathing for Protestantism. By the order of King Henry VIII, More commissions the burning of Martin Luther's books. He is shown exercising his authority as Chancellor by burning English Protestants who have been convicted of heresy. ''The Tudors'' shows More engaging in the conversation that Richard Rich testified about regarding the King's title as [[Supreme Head of the Church of England]]. More's avowed insistence that Rich's testimony was perjured is excised from the show's depiction of the trial.

The [[cultus]] of More has been satirised. In the ''[[The Simpsons]]'' an episode, &quot;[[Margical History Tour]]&quot;, contains a [[parody]] of both [[Henry VIII]] and More. King Henry ([[Homer Simpson]]) is depicted as a gluttonous slob who stuffs his face while singing &quot;[[I'm Henery the Eighth, I am]]&quot;. He then wipes his mouth with the ''[[Magna Carta]]'' and sets out to dump Queen Catherine ([[Marge Simpson]]). Sir Thomas ([[Ned Flanders]]) objects, &quot;Divorce! Well, there's no such thing in the Cath-diddly-atholic Church! But it's the only Church we got, so what are you gonna do?&quot; King Henry retorts, &quot;I'll start my own Church... Where divorce will be so easy, more than half of all marriages will end in it!&quot; When a horrifed Sir Thomas refuses to go along, King Henry has him shot out of a cannon.

==Institutions named after More==

{{Main|List of institutions named after Thomas More}}

==Historic sites==
===Westminster Hall===
Visitors to the Houses of Parliament at the [[Palace of Westminster]] in London will notice a plaque in the middle of the floor of [[Westminster Hall]] commemorating More's trial for treason and condemnation to execution in that original part of the Palace. This building would have been well known to More, who served as Speaker of the House of Commons prior to becoming Lord Chancellor of England.

===Crosby Hall===
More's home and estate along the Thames in Chelsea was confiscated by the Crown from his wife Alice after his execution. But in later times Crosby Hall, which formed part of More's London residence, was relocated to the site in his commemoration and reconstructed there by the conservation architect, [[Walter Godfrey]]. Today after further rebuilding in the 1990s it stands out as a white stone building amid modern brick structures that aims to recapture the style of More's manor that formerly occupied the site. Crosby Hall is privately owned and closed to the public. The modern structures face the Thames and include an entry way that displays More's arms, heraldic beasts, and a Latin maxim. Apartment buildings and a park are built over the former locations of his gardens and orchard, and some are named after their former functions: Roper's Garden is the park occupying one of More's gardens, sunken as his was believed to be. Other than these, there are no remnants of the More estate.

===Chelsea Old Church===
This small park sits between Crosby Hall and [[Chelsea Old Church]], an Anglican church on Old Church Street whose southern chapel was commissioned by More and in which he sang with his parish choir. The medieval arch connecting the chapel to the main sanctuary was commissioned by More and displays on its capitals symbols associated with his person and office. On the southern wall of the sanctuary is the tomb and epitaph he erected for himself and his wives, detailing in a lengthy Latin inscription his ancestry and accomplishments, including his role as peacemaker between the Christian nations of Europe and a curiously altered portion detailing his curbing of heresy. This tomb was probably located here because it was his custom to serve Mass and he would leave by the door just to the left of it. He is not, however, buried here, nor is it entirely certain which of his family may be. Except for his chapel, the church was largely destroyed in the Second World War and was rebuilt in 1958. It is open to the public at specific times. Outside the church, facing the [[River Thames]], is a statue by L. Cubitt Bevis erected in 1969, commemorating him as &quot;saint&quot;, &quot;scholar&quot;, and &quot;statesman&quot;, the back of which displays his coat-of-arms. In the same neighbourhood, on Upper Cheyne Row, is the Catholic Church of the Holy Saviour and St. Thomas More, which honours him according to the Church he defended with his life.

===Tower Hill===
More was executed on a scaffold erected on Tower Hill, London, just outside the [[Tower of London]]. A plaque and small garden commemorate the famed execution site and all those who were executed there, many as religious martyrs or as prisoners of conscience. His body, minus his head, was unceremoniously buried in an unmarked grave in the Royal Chapel of St. Peter Ad Vincula, within the walls of the Tower of London. It was the custom for traitors executed at Tower Hill to be buried in the mass grave beneath this chapel, which is accessible to visitors to the Tower.

===St Dunstan's Church, Canterbury===
St Dunstan's Church, an Anglican parish church in Canterbury, possesses More's head, rescued by his beloved daughter [[Margaret Roper]]. This is sealed in the Roper family vault beneath the altar of the Nicholas Chapel, to the right of the church's sanctuary or main altar. The stone marking the sealed vault is to the immediate left of the altar below which it lies. [[St. Dunstan's, Canterbury|St Dunstan's Church]] has carefully investigated, preserved and sealed this burial vault of the Roper family who lived in Canterbury. The last archaeological investigation of the Roper Vault revealed that the suspected head of More rests in a niche separate from the other bodies there, possibly due to later interference.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} A few displays in the chapel record the archaeological findings in written accounts and pictures. The walls of the chapel are host to impressive stained glass donated by Roman Catholics to commemorate the events in More's life. Down and across the street from the parish the facade of the former home of Margaret Roper and her husband William Roper survives and is marked by a small plaque.

==See also==
{{Portal|Saints}}
*[[English Reformation]]

==Works==

NOTE:  The reference “CW” is to the relevant volume of the [[Yale Edition of the Complete Works of St. Thomas More]] (New Haven and London 1963–1997)

===Published during More’s life (with dates of publication)===

* ''A Merry Jest'' (c. 1516) (CW 1)
* ''[[Utopia (book)|Utopia]]'' (1516) (CW 4)
* ''Latin Poems'' (1518, 1520) (CW 3, Pt.2)
* ''Letter to Brixius'' (1520) (CW 3, Pt. 2, App C)
* ''Responsio ad Lutherum'' (1523) (CW 5)
* ''A Dialogue Concerning Heresies'' (1529, 1530) (CW 6)
* ''Supplication of Souls'' (1529) (CW 7)
* ''Letter Against Frith'' (1532) (CW 7)
* ''The Confutation of Tyndale's Answer'' (1532, 1533) (CW 8)
* ''Apology'' (1533) (CW 9)
* ''Debellation of Salem and Bizance'' (1533) (CW 10)
* ''The Answer to a Poisoned Book'' (1533) (CW 11)

===Published after More’s death (with likely dates of composition)===

* ''The History of King Richard III'' (c. 1513–1518) (CW 2 &amp; 15)
* ''The Four Last Things'' (c. 1522) (CW 1)
* ''A Dialogue of Comfort Against Tribulation'' (1534) (CW 12)
* ''Treatise Upon the Passion'' (1534) (CW 13)
* ''Treatise on the Blessed Body''  (1535) (CW 13)
* ''Instructions and Prayers''  (1535) (CW 13)
* ''De Tristitia Christi'' (1535) (CW 14)

==Translations==

* ''Translations of Lucian'' (many dates 1506–1534) (CW 3, Pt.1)
* ''The Life of Pico della Mirandola'' (c. 1510) (CW 1)

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Biographies==
* {{cite book | author=Brady, Charles A. | title = Stage of Fools: A Novel of Sir Thomas More | year = 1953 | publisher=Dutton | isbn = }}
* {{cite book | author=Basset, Bernard, S.J. | title = Born for Friendship: The Spirit of Sir Thomas More | year = 1965 | location = London | publisher=Burns and Oates | isbn = }}
* {{cite book | author=Reynolds, E. E. | title = The Trialet of St Thomas More | year = 1964 | pages = | isbn = }}
* {{cite book | author=Reynolds, E. E. | title = Thomas More and Erasmus | year = 1965 | pages = | isbn = }}
* {{cite book | author=Guy, John | title = The Public Career of Sir Thomas More | year = 1980 | pages = | isbn = 978-0300025460 | authorlink = John Guy (historian)}}
* {{cite book | author=Ridley, Jasper | title = Statesman and Saint: Cardinal Wolsey, Sir Thomas More, and the Politics of Henry VIII | year = 1983 | pages = | isbn = 0-670-48905-0 | authorlink = Jasper Ridley}}
* {{cite book | author=Marius, Richard | title = Thomas More: A Biography | year = 1984 | pages = | isbn = | authorlink = Richard Marius }}
* {{cite book | author=Wegemer, Gerard | title = Thomas More: A Portrait of Courage | year = 1985 | pages = | isbn = 978-1889334127 | authorlink = Gerard Wegemer}}
* {{cite book | author=Ackroyd, Peter | title = The Life of Thomas More | year = 1999 | pages = | isbn = | authorlink = Peter Ackroyd }}
* {{cite book | author=Guy, John | title = Thomas More | year = 2000 | pages = | isbn = 978-0340731383}}
* {{cite book | author=Guy, John | title = A Daughter's Love: Thomas More and his daughter Meg | year = 2009 | pages = | isbn = }}
* {{cite book 
| last = Berglar
| first = Peter 
| authorlink = Peter Berglar
| title = Thomas More: a lonely voice against the power of the state
| publisher = Scepter Publishers
| location = New York
| year = 2009
| url = http://books.google.com/books?id=5eAN_FrS2o4C
| isbn = 9781594170737
}}
* Wegemer, Gerard. ''Thomas More on Statesmanship'' (1996) 
===Historiography===
* Gushurst-Moore, André. &quot;A Man for All Eras: Recent Books on Thomas More&quot; ''Political Science Reviewer'', 2004, Vol. 33, pp 90-143 [http://web.ebscohost.com/ehost/pdfviewer/pdfviewer?vid=3&amp;hid=17&amp;sid=5e6fec38-1adb-4244-ae8a-477b55568a87%40sessionmgr12 online]
* Guy, John. &quot;The Search for the Historical Thomas More,&quot; ''History Review'' (2000) pp 15+ [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5001205422 online edition],
===Primary sources===
* More, Thomas. [[Yale Edition of the Complete Works of St. Thomas More]] (New Haven and London 1963–1997) [http://www.amazon.com/gp/search/ref=sr_adv_b/?search-alias=stripbooks&amp;unfiltered=1&amp;field-keywords=&amp;field-author=&amp;field-title=Yale+Edition+of+the+Complete+Works+of+St.+Thomas+More&amp;field-isbn=&amp;field-publisher=&amp;node=&amp;field-p_n_condition-type=&amp;field-feature_browse-bin=&amp;field-subject=&amp;field-language=&amp;field-dateop=&amp;field-datemod=&amp;field-dateyear=&amp;sort=relevanceexprank&amp;Adv-Srch-Books-Submit.x=0&amp;Adv-Srch-Books-Submit.y=0 links]
* More, Thomas. ''Utopia'' (Norton Critical Editions) ed. by George M. Logan and Robert M. Adams (3rd. ed. 2010) 
* More, Thomas. ''Saint Thomas More: Selected Writings'' ed. by John F. Thornton (2003) 
* More, Thomas. ''The Last Letters of Thomas More'' ed. by Alvaro de Silva (2001)

==External links==
{{wikiquote}}
{{wikisource author}}
{{Commons category|Thomas More}}
*[http://thomasmorestudies.org/ The Center for Thomas More Studies] at the [[University of Dallas]]
* [http://www.thomasmore.co.uk Thomas More Chambers] – The Chambers of Mr [[Geoffrey Cox]] QC, MP.
* [http://www.thomasmorestudies.org/library.html Thomas More Studies database]: contains several of More's English works, including dialogues, early poetry and letters, as well as journal articles and biographical material
* {{gutenberg author | id=Thomas_More | name=Thomas More}}
* {{Gutenberg | no=4243 | name=Sir Thomas More, or, Colloquies on the Progress and Prospects of Society | title = Southey, Robert (1774–1843)}}
* {{Gutenberg | no=1547 | title=Sir Thomas More | name=Sir Thomas More by William Shakespeare (spurious and doubtful works)}}
* [http://www.luminarium.org/renlit/wood.htm ''Sir Thomas More: A Man for One Season''], essay by [[James Wood (critic)|James Wood]]. Presents a critical view of More's religious intolerance
* [http://www.richard111.com/sir_thomas_more.htm More and ''The History of Richard&amp;nbsp;III'']
* [http://www.marxists.org/archive/kautsky/1888/more/index.htm ''Thomas More and his Utopia''] by [[Karl Kautsky]]
* [http://www.bl.uk/learning/histcitizen/21cc/utopia/more1/moreutopia.html Thomas More and Utopias] – a learning resource from the British Library
* [http://www.thomasmoreinstitute.org.uk/?q=node/34 ''Integrity and Conscience in the Life and Thought of Thomas More''] by Professor Gerald Wegemer
* {{CathEncy|wstitle=St. Thomas More}}
* {{worldcat id|id=lccn-n79-56176}}
* [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=6848 body] and [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=27568996 head] of Thomas More at [http://www.findagrave.com/ Find A Grave]
*[http://saints.sqpn.com/saint-thomas-more Patron Saints Index entry] – Saint Thomas More biography, prayers, quotes, Catholc devotions to him.
* [http://www.law.umkc.edu/faculty/projects/ftrials/more/more.html Trial of Sir Thomas More] at the [[University of Missouri-Kansas City]] (UMKC) School of Law

{{S-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{Succession box| title=[[List of Speakers of the House of Commons of England|Speaker of the House of Commons]] | before=[[Thomas Neville|Sir Thomas Neville]] | after=[[Thomas Audley, 1st Baron Audley of Walden|Sir Thomas Audley]] | years=1523}}

{{Succession box| title=[[Chancellor of the Duchy of Lancaster]] | before=[[Richard Wingfield|Sir Richard Wingfield]] | after=[[William Fitzwilliam, 1st Earl of Southampton|Sir William Fitzwilliam]] | years=1525–1529}}

{{Succession box| title=[[Lord Chancellor]] | before=[[Thomas Wolsey]] | after=[[Thomas Audley, 1st Baron Audley of Walden|Sir Thomas Audley]]&lt;br /&gt;'''(Keeper of the Great Seal)'''&amp;nbsp; | years=1529–1532}}

{{S-end}}

{{Speaker of the British House of Commons}}

{{Catholicism||collapsed}}
{{History of the Roman Catholic Church|collapsed}}
{{Roman Catholic Theology|uncollapsed}}

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME              = More, Thomas
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
|SHORT DESCRIPTION = English lawyer, writer
|DATE OF BIRTH     = 7 February 1478
|PLACE OF BIRTH    = London, England
|DATE OF DEATH     = 6 July 1535
|PLACE OF DEATH    = London, England
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:More, Thomas}}
[[Category:1478 births]]
[[Category:1535 deaths]]
[[Category:16th-century Christian saints]]
[[Category:16th-century Latin-language writers]]
[[Category:16th-century Roman Catholic martyrs]]
[[Category:16th-century Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:Anglican saints]]
[[Category:Anti-Protestantism]]
[[Category:Chancellors of the Duchy of Lancaster]]
[[Category:Christian humanists]]
[[Category:Early modern philosophers]]
[[Category:English Catholic poets]]
[[Category:English humanists]]
[[Category:English non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:English religious writers]]
[[Category:English Renaissance humanists]]
[[Category:English Roman Catholic saints]]
[[Category:English Roman Catholics]]
[[Category:English saints]]
[[Category:Executed English people]]
[[Category:Executed philosophers]]
[[Category:Executed writers]]
[[Category:Executions at the Tower of London]]
[[Category:Inventors of writing systems]]
[[Category:Lord Chancellors of England]]
[[Category:Members of Lincoln's Inn]]
[[Category:Members of the pre-1707 Parliament of England]]
[[Category:Members of the Privy Council of England]]
[[Category:Old Waynfletes]]
[[Category:People associated with the University of Oxford]]
[[Category:People executed by decapitation]]
[[Category:People executed for treason against England]]
[[Category:People executed under the Tudors]]
[[Category:People from the City of London]]
[[Category:People of the Tudor period]]
[[Category:Portrait by Hans Holbein the younger]]
[[Category:Prisoners in the Tower of London]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic philosophers]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic writers]]
[[Category:Early modern Christian devotional writers]]
[[Category:Saints canonized by Pope Pius XI]]
[[Category:Speakers of the House of Commons of England]]
[[Category:Utopian socialists]]
[[Category:Utopists]]
[[Category:Third Order of Saint Francis]]
[[Category:Franciscan martyrs]]
[[Category:Franciscan saints]]
{{Link FA|sv}}

[[als:Thomas More]]
[[ar:توماس مور]]
[[az:Tomas Mor]]
[[zh-min-nan:Thomas More]]
[[be:Томас Мор]]
[[be-x-old:Томас Мор]]
[[bs:Thomas More]]
[[br:Thomas More]]
[[bg:Томас Мор]]
[[ca:Thomas More]]
[[cs:Thomas More]]
[[cy:Thomas More]]
[[da:Thomas More]]
[[de:Thomas Morus]]
[[et:Thomas More]]
[[es:Tomás Moro]]
[[eo:Thomas More]]
[[eu:Tomas Moro]]
[[fa:تامس مور]]
[[fr:Thomas More]]
[[ga:Thomas More]]
[[gl:Thomas More]]
[[ko:토머스 모어]]
[[hy:Թոմաս Մոր]]
[[hr:Thomas More]]
[[id:Thomas More]]
[[it:Tommaso Moro]]
[[he:תומאס מור]]
[[ka:ტომას მორი]]
[[kk:Мор Томас]]
[[sw:Thomas More]]
[[la:Thomas Morus]]
[[lv:Tomass Mors]]
[[lb:Thomas Morus]]
[[lt:Tomas Moras]]
[[hu:Morus Tamás]]
[[mk:Томас Мор]]
[[ml:തോമസ് മൂർ]]
[[arz:توماس مور]]
[[ms:Thomas More]]
[[my:သောမတ်စ် မိုး]]
[[nl:Thomas More]]
[[ja:トマス・モア]]
[[no:Thomas More]]
[[nn:Thomas More]]
[[oc:Thomas More]]
[[pl:Thomas More]]
[[pt:Thomas More]]
[[ro:Thomas Morus]]
[[qu:Thomas More]]
[[ru:Мор, Томас]]
[[sc:Thomas More]]
[[scn:Tummasu Moru]]
[[simple:Thomas More]]
[[sk:Thomas More]]
[[sl:Thomas More]]
[[sr:Tomas Mor]]
[[fi:Thomas More]]
[[sv:Thomas More]]
[[tr:Thomas More]]
[[uk:Томас Мор]]
[[vi:Thomas More]]
[[zh:托马斯·莫尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
