<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3054033" ns="0" title="Botany Downs, New Zealand"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox New Zealand suburbs
| name           = Botany Downs
| image          =  
| caption1       =  
| city1          = Auckland City
| city2          =
| ward           = Howick
| established    =
| area           =
| population     = 4,830 &lt;ref&gt;{{NZ Quickstats|3523101|Botany Downs}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| popdate        = 2006
| trainstations  =
| ferryterminals =
| airports       =
| hospitals      =
| north          = [[Howick, New Zealand|Howick]]
| northeast      = [[Howick, New Zealand|Howick]]
| east           = [[Somerville, New Zealand|Somerville]]
| southeast      = [[Northpark, New Zealand|Northpark]]
| south          = [[Cumbria Downs]]
| southwest      = [[Golflands]]
| west           = [[Pakuranga Heights]], [[Pakuranga North]]
| northwest      = [[Highland Park, New Zealand|Highland Park]]
| map            =
| caption2       =
}}

'''Botany Downs''' is a [[suburb]] of [[Auckland City]], [[New Zealand]].This residential area was previously part of the East Tamaki area. According to the 2006 census, Botany Downs has a population of 4830, having grown 2.7% since 2001. It has one of the country's biggest shopping malls - [[Botany Town Centre, Howick|Botany Town Centre]] - attracting people from all over the greater Auckland Area.{{Citation needed|date=March 2008}} The suburb is in the Howick ward, one of the thirteen administrative divisions of Auckland City.

==Education==
* [[Sancta Maria College, New Zealand|Sancta Maria College]] is a coeducational secondary (years 7-13) school integrated with the state system, with a decile rating of 8 and a roll of 854.&lt;ref&gt;{{TKI|491|Sancta Maria College}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Elim Christian College]] is a coeducational christian school with students from new entrants to Year 13 that is integrated with the state system, it has a decile rating of 9 and a roll of 550 with first stages of roll growth beginning in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{TKI|1190|Elim Christian College}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Botany Downs Secondary College]] is a coeducational secondary (years 9-13) public school, with a decile rating of 10 and a roll of 1640.&lt;ref&gt;{{TKI|6930|Botany Downs Secondary College}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Botany Downs Primary School.
* Point View School is a coeducational state contributing Primary School (years 1-6) with a [[Socio-Economic Decile|decile rating]] of 10 and a roll of 778.&lt;ref&gt;{{TKI|6921|Point View School}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Botany Electorate==
Due to its population growth, Botany Downs is the centre of New Zealand's sixty-third and newest general electorate.  The electorate, named [[Botany (New Zealand electorate)|Botany]], will take effect from the [[New Zealand general election, 2008|2008 general election]].  Originally proposed as [[Howick, New Zealand|Howick]], the new seat was renamed after redrawing of the draft boundaries.

The [[Botany (New Zealand electorate)|Botany electorate]] is approximately 33% Asians.  Because of this, both major political parties are expected to field an Asian candidate for the seat in 2008.  National MP [[Pansy Wong]] indicated early her intention to seek the nomination for Botany, and she has subsequently won preselection to pursue the seat for National in the 2008 general election.  [[Kenneth Wang]], representing the [[Act New Zealand|Act Party]], will contest Botany also. Although media reports had floated the possibility of lawyer Raymond Huo seeking the nomination for Labour, the party fielded unionist Brendan Sheehan who was confident of defeating National's Wong. However, Sheehan withdrew his nomination due to a family illness, and the Labour nomination is open again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/4570108a11.html |title=Labour reopens Botany seat nominations |date=3 June 2008 |work=[[Stuff.co.nz]] |accessdate=21 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

National Party MP Jami-Lee Ross holds the current seat of the Botany Electorate.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.botanytowncentre.co.nz/ Botany Town Centre]
*[http://www.manukau-libraries.govt.nz/whatsinourlibraries/botany/botany.htm Botany Library]

{{coord|-36.909528|174.917454|region:NZ-AUK_type:city(4830)|display=title}}

[[Category:Suburbs of Auckland]]


{{Auckland-geo-stub}}

[[de:Botany Downs]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
