<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="306090" ns="0" title="Educational game"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
|copy edit = August 2011
|refimprove = April 2008
|original research = April 2008
}}

'''Educational games''' are [[game]]s that have been designed to teach people about a certain subject, expand concepts, reinforce development, understand an historical event or culture, or assist them in learning a skill as they play. They include [[board game|board]], [[card game|card]], and [[video game]]s.

==Board games==
A [[board game]] is a game played with counters or pieces that are placed on, removed from, or moved across a &quot;board&quot; (a premarked surface, usually specific to that game).  Frequent subject matters for educational board games are geographical, and the board is a map of the region taught about.

==Card games==
An educational [[card game]] is any game using playing cards, either traditional or game-specific.  Generally these dula expand concepts, such as the food chain, set matching, etc.  Flash card games are used to teach math, animal, and dinosaur species. Some card games improve memory.

==Video games==
{{VG Industry}}
Educational video games are considered a type of [[serious game]], as these games have a strong purpose other than pure [[entertainment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/feature/4074/the_designers_notebook_sorting_.php?page=2 | publisher = Gamasutra | author = Ernest Adams | date = 2009-07-09 | accessdate = 2009-05-23 | title = Sorting Out the Genre Muddle }}&lt;/ref&gt; Some people call these types of games [[edutainment]] because they combine [[education]] and [[entertainment]]. An educational computer game can be defined as an electronic medium with all the characteristics of a gaming environment that have intended educational outcomes targeted at specific groups of learners.

Video games can aid the development of proficiency by allowing users to interact with objects and manipulate variables.  They are said to be particularly effective when designed to address a specific problem or teach a certain skill in curriculum subjects, where specific objectives can be stated and when deployed selectively within a context relevant to the learning activity and goal.

Simple types of games can be designed to address specific learning outcomes such as recall of factual content.  For instance, the Nobel Prize Foundation website uses on-line games to aid children in understanding the discoveries made by its laureates by embedding the scientific knowledge as part of the game environment.

To aid in educating students and adults about the finer details of different political systems, numerous companies have developed simulations that immerse the player into different political systems by forcing them to make realistic political decisions.  These games vary from running an actual election campaign to games that allow the player to make the day-to-day decisions of running a country, as seen in ''[[Democracy (game)|Democracy]]''.  These types of games are targeted at students, educators and adults alike.

===Children's and adults educational computer games===
[[Video games]] have historically received more [[Video game controversy|criticism]] than other forms of recreational learning because they are often perceived as being mindless entertainment and as encouraging [[sexism]] and [[consumerism]], and turning players into social recluses.  Many children today also find these &quot;educational&quot; games to lack much interesting content to them, as they are considered by older children to be &quot;for preschoolers&quot;.  However, a shift from pure entertainment to educational tool has emerged in recent times.  Children growing up today can benefit from educational video games because they are already exposed to a society that is increasingly dependent on digital technology.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcyclopedia&quot;&gt;Dannii Foley, [http://wiki.media-culture.org.au/index.php/Computer_Games_-_Education Computer Games - Education], M/Cyclopedia of New Media&lt;/ref&gt;

Researchers today have found that computer games could become part of the school curriculum after researchers found they had significant educational value. &quot;The UK study concluded that simulation and adventure games - such as [[Sim City]] and [[RollerCoaster Tycoon]], where players create societies or build theme parks, developed children's strategic thinking and planning skills&quot;.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Recent games such as the math game [[Ko's Journey]] are standards-based to meet curriculum.

The medium of educational games provides an opportunity for teachers to introduce educational and playful elements into the learning environment. With computer-aided learning programs, teachers may assist students on social aspects such as critical learning, knowledge based communication and effective interpersonal skills that traditional methods of teaching cannot offer.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcyclopedia&quot; /&gt;

As computer games are being adapted to the education system, the issue of [[classification and content regulation is being brought to attention. The issue of regulating game content is vital as educational game are created to be effective learning tools. Thus the game developer must have a comprehensive understanding of its young audience and their particular social and educational needs. At the same time, the game developer must balance between entertainment and accordance with the education syllabus.

Below are some examples of games targeting young users from the ages of about three years to mid-teens; beyond the mid-teens, subjects become so complex (e.g. [[calculus]]) that teaching via a game can be impractical. Numerous subgenres exist, each for a different field, such as [[mathematics|maths]] games or [[typing]] games.

Adult education games are aimed at higher levels of education being targeted at young-adults and up. Like children's games, they can be in the form of mini-games, [[adventure games]], [[role-playing games]] and so on.

There can be also defined strategy war games that include historical references like the ''[[Total War (series)|Total War]]'' franchise or the ''[[Age of Empires]]'' trilogy and an in-game encyclopaedia like ''[[Civilization (video game)|Civilization]]''. These games often combine entertainment and education but without being explicitly educational.

'''Children's and adolescents' games'''
* ''[[Big Brain Academy: Wii Degree]]''
* ''[[Clickn kids|ClickN READ Phonics]]'' - Beginning Reading
* ''[[Clickn kids|ClickN SPELL]]'' - Beginning Spelling
* ''[[Carmen Sandiego]]'' series
* ''[[The ClueFinders]]''
* ''[[Dr. Kawashima's Brain Training]]'' (a series of two games)
* ''[[EcoQuest]]'' (a series of two games)
* ''[[GCompris]]'' ([[GNU General Public License|GPL]])
* ''[[Genomics Digital Lab]]''
* ''[[Gizmos &amp; Gadgets]]''
* ''[[History of Biology game]]''
* ''[[Immune Attack]]''
* ''[[Inanimate Alice]]''
* ''[[InLiving]]''
* ''[[I.M. Meen]]''
* ''[[JumpStart]]''
* ''[[Ko's Journey]]''
* ''[[Learnalot]]''
* ''[[Math Blaster]]''
* ''[[Number Munchers]]''
* ''[[The Oregon Trail (computer game)|Oregon Trail]]''
* ''[[PlaceSpotting]]''
* ''[[Quest Atlantis]]''
* ''[[Reader Rabbit]]''
* ''[[The Magic School Bus]]'' series
* ''[[Treasures of the Deep]]''
* ''[[Tuxmath]]'' ([[GNU General Public License|GPL]])
* ''[[Storybook Weaver]]''
* ''[[Urban Jungle]]''
* ''[[Zoombinis]]''
* ''[[WolfQuest]]''

'''Adult educational computer games'''
* ''[[Democracy (game)|Democracy]]''
* ''[[Food Force]]''
* ''[[Global Conflict: Palestine]]''
* ''[[Mavis Beacon Teaches Typing]]''
* ''[[Miniconomy]]
* ''[[President Forever 2008 + Primaries]]''
* ''[[The Typing of the Dead]]''
* ''[[CyberCIEGE]]''
* ''[[Close Combat: Marines]]''
* ''[[Virtonomics]]

==Generic Skins for Computer Based Games==
[[Virtual learning environment|Virtual Learning Environments]] (VLEs), such as [[Moodle]] and [[Blackboard (e-learning platform)|Blackboard]], can act as a front-end user interface for educational tests. Games based on such tests can be single or multi-player games. Such generic user interfaces are called [[Skin (computing)|skins]].&lt;ref&gt;Srinivasan Ramani et al. [http://www.hpl.hp.com/techreports/2008/HPL-2008-92.pdf Games as Skins for Online Tests], [[HP Laboratories]], July 21, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; These skins are popular with schools, an example of a school using [[Moodle]] is [[Coundon Court School and Community College]], they can be ideal as a learning environment for pupils using [[Information technology|IT]].{{Citation needed|reason=source required|date=August 2011}}

==See also==
* [[Educational toy]]
* [[Edutainment]]

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/education/1879019.stm Video games 'stimulate learning'], [[BBC News]], March 18, 2002
* Dostál, J. [http://www.jtie.upol.cz/clanky_1_2009/dostal.pdf  Educational software and computer games - tools of modern education], [[Journal of Technology and Information Education]]. 2009, [[Palacký University, Olomouc]], Volume 1, Issue 1, p.&amp;nbsp;24 - 28. {{ISSN|1803-537X}}

==External links==
* [http://nobelprize.org/educational_games/ Educational Games Nobelprize.org]
* [http://www.epistemicgames.org/ Epistemic Games Group, University of Wisconsin-Madison]
* [http://www.gamesforchange.org/ Games For Change]
* [http://www.wingz2fly.com/GameSurvey/search.html Searchable database of educational computer games]
{{VideoGameGenre}}

[[Category:Video game types]]
[[Category:Educational video games| ]]

[[cs:Didaktická hra]]
[[de:Lernspiel]]
[[fr:Logiciel ludo-éducatif]]
[[ko:교육용 게임]]
[[it:Videogioco educativo]]
[[no:Pedagogiske spill]]
[[pt:Jogos educacionais]]
[[ru:Развивающие игры]]
[[fi:Oppimispeli]]
[[zh:教育遊戲]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
