<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30637276" ns="0" title="UST Streets and Driveways"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The streets within the [[Manila]] campus of the [[University of Santo Tomas]] were completely unnamed for 32 years since the University transferred from [[Intramuros]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.varsitarian.net/features/who_cares_about_ust%E2%80%99s_streets Who cares about UST’s streets?]. Retrieved 26 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1960, the street signs and names inside the University were inaugurated after a student initiative and majority of which were named after Thomasian Alumni. As of January 2011, there are 19 named roads including Intramuros Drive, Rizal Lane, and Quezon Drive.

== Student initiative ==
In 1959, [[Luis Ablaza]], former president of the Central Board of Students, submitted a resolution for the purpose of naming the university roads. A list of notable alumni were submitted to then Rector Fr. Jesus Castañon, O.P., who referred the list to secretary general Fr. Antonio Gonzales for implementation. In March 7, 1960, the street signs were revealed bearing the name of its respective street names. Before the revision of the Roman calendar, UST used to celebrate March 7 its University Day and the Catholic Church the Feast Day of St. Thomas Aquinas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.varsitarian.net/features/20100618/visionary_model_of_entrepreneurship Visionary model of entrepreneurship]. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Pedestrian lanes within Plaza Benavides ==

Affectionately called ''Lovers' Lane'', the park in front of the Main Building has three pathways named after three of the University's notable alumni. 
* '''Rizal Lane''', it is located in the center of the plaza and named after the Philippine National Hero, [[Dr. Jose Rizal]]. Arch of the Centuries can be found on the north end of the lane and the Statue of Miguel de Benavides can be found on its south end.
* '''Burgos Lane''', it is named after Filipino martyr, [[José Burgos|'''Fr. Jose Burgos''']]. It can be found on the west side of the plaza that has a curve end towards the Fountain of Knowledge.
* '''Del Pilar Lane''', it is named after Filipino journalist and revolutionary leader, '''[[Marcelo H. Del Pilar]]'''. Opposite the Burgos Lane running on the east side of the plaza, it also has a curve end leading to the Fountain of Wisdom.

== Current roads and street names ==
=== Intramuros Drive ===
Paying homage to the University's founding site, '''[[Intramuros]]''', it is the first stretch of road from the main vehicular gate. Along this street lies the Plaza Intramuros, which houses three of the most prominent structures in the university: the Arch of the Centuries and the Fountains of Wisdom and Knowledge.

=== Quezon Drive ===
It is named after a UST alumnus and the first president of the [[Philippine Commonwealth]], President '''[[Manuel L. Quezon]]'''. It is one of the busiest streets in the University as most of the vehicles entering the campus traverses this road. It leads to Multi-deck Carpark, the densely populated college building - St. Raymund Peñafort Building, the compound of St. Martin de Porres Building, the Miguel de Benavides Library, and the Tan Yan Kee Student Center. Other places that could be found along this street are UST Health Service Center, Tinoko Park, and the Alumni Walk. The Quadricentennial Square, particularly the Quadricentennial Fountain, can be best viewed from the south end of this street.

=== Osmeña Drive ===
Named after a notable alumnus, former President '''[[Sergio Osmeña]]''', it is a one-way street from a Dapitan gate until Intramuros Drive. University-owned school buses were usually parked along this street in front the Parade Grounds opposite the Grandstand. The Botanical Garden and Benavides Building can be found along the south end of this street.

=== Arellano Drive ===
It is a one-way street parallel to [[España Boulevard]] from Beato Angelico Building until it reaches Intramuros Drive on its way out to the main vehicular entrance of the University. It is named after '''Chief Justice Cayetano Arellano''', an alumnus and the first [[Chief Justice|chief justice]] of the [[Supreme Court of the Philippines|Supreme Court]].

=== Araullo Drive ===
It is a one-way street passing from Intramuros Drive until it reaches Ruaño drive. It will service the new UST Gymnasium and Sports Complex. It is named after '''Justice Manuel Araullo'''.

=== Gonzales Drive ===

Named after '''Fr. [[Zeferino González y Díaz Tuñón|Ceferino Gonzales]], O.P.''', it services the Santissimo Rosario Parish Church and the original UST Gymnasium. Along this street, one can have the greater view of the Grandstand and Parade Grounds. It runs through the P. Noval gate until it reaches Osmeña Drive. Fr. Gonzales is a philosopher and theologian.

=== L. Ma. Guerrero Drive ===
Named after former dean of [[University of Santo Tomas Faculty of Pharmacy|Faculty of Pharmacy]], '''Dr. Leon Ma. Guerrero''', it services the UST Hospital, UST Health Service Center, and the Multi-deck Carpark. Dr. Guerrero is also a renowned Filipino botanist and linguist.

=== Tamayo Drive ===
It was named after the longest-servicing rector of the University, '''Fr. Serapio Tamayo, O.P.''' Along this street, the Beato Angelico Building could be found. The offices of Institute of Physical Education and Athletics and UST Publishing could also be found in this street. A one-way street, it runs through Gonzales Drive towards Arellano Drive.

=== Ruaño Drive ===
Named after the engineer who built the Main Building, '''Fr. Roque Ruaño''', it is a one-way street servicing the buildings of Roque Ruaño and Albertus Magnus. Along this street, elevated pedestrian lanes could be found together with a row of pavilions in front of college buildings.

=== Lladoc Drive ===
An access road from Gonzales Drive to the garage of Santissimo Rosario Parish Church, it can also be found between the church and UST Botanical Garden. Named after '''Msgr. Casimiro Lladoc''', its mouth is an additional parking space for cars and motorcycles that leads to the Botanical Laboratory, Anatomy Laboratory, rear entrance of Benavides Building, and Botanical Garden.

=== Albert Drive ===
Servicing the Miguel de Benavides Library and Tan Yan Kee Student Center, it is named after '''Dr. Alejandro Albert'''. Being a former Thomasian professor, he is one of the founders of Escuela de Farmacia del Liceo de Manila (also known today as [[Manila Central University]]).

=== Villamor Drive ===
Named after Thomasian educator '''Justice Ignacio Villamor''', the first president of [[University of the Philippines]],  it is a street parallel to Dapitan behind the Tan Yan Kee Student Center.

=== Singian Drive ===

Named after '''Dr. Gregorio Singian''', a Thomasian [[physician]], it is an access road from Quezon Drive leading to the compound where St. Martin de Porres Building is located.

=== Miciano Drive ===
Named after '''Dr. Juan Miciano''', also a Thomasian physician, it serves as a driveway between St. Martin de Porres and its pavilions.

=== Quintos Drive ===
Named after '''Dr. Joaquin Quintos''', one of those who discovered Vitamin B1 in Tiki-Tiki for cure of beriberi, it is a street between the buildings of St. Martin de Porres and UST Hospital Clinical Division. This street eventually leads to Villamor Drive on its way out to Dapitan Street.

=== L. Guerrero Drive ===
Named after former dean of [[University of Santo Tomas Faculty of Medicine and Surgery|Faculty of Medicine and Surgery]], '''Dr. Luis Guerrero''', it is a street in between the buildings of St. Martin de Porres and St. Raymond Peñafort.
{{University of Santo Tomas campus map}}

== Abolished Roads and Defunct Street Names ==
===  Benavides Drive ===
Before the construction of today's Plaza Mayor, car parking spaces and a road exist in front of the Main Building. The street was named after '''Miguel de Benavides, O.P.''', the University's founder and Manila's third archbishop.

=== Ampuero Drive ===
Between the Main Building and then Colayco Park (now Quadricentennial Square), a road once existed to service the pedestrians entering the rear entrance of the Main Building and the vehicles passing through from Quezon Drive to Osmeña Drive. Along that road, parking spaces for cars owned by faculty members and administrative staff could be found. The street was named after '''Ramon Ampuero''', the last Filipino lay secretary-general who served the University for more than 30 years.

=== Mabini Drive ===
In the 1959 edition of the University Map, Mabini Drive has existed and could be found along the Benavides Building or UST High School Building. It was named after '''[[Apolinario Mabini]]''', an alumnus, principal author of the [[Malolos Constitution]], and the first [[Prime Minister]] of the [[Philippine Government|Philippine Revolutionary Government]].

== See also ==
* [[List of University of Santo Tomas buildings]]
* [[UST Parks and Gardens]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{UST}}
{{University Belt}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Street and Driveways, UST}}
[[Category:University of Santo Tomas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
