<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30631328" ns="0" title="List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of minor ''Emmerdale'' characters (2011)}}
{{Emmerdaleminor}}
The following is a list of minor [[Character (arts)|characters]] that first appeared in the British soap opera ''[[Emmerdale]]'' in 2011, by order of first appearance.  

==Flynn Buchanan==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Flynn Buchanan
|introducer= [[Gavin Blyth]]
|portrayer= Ryan Prescott
|years= 2011
|classification = [[List of past Emmerdale characters#Last appeared in 2011|Former; recurring]]
|first= 31 January 2011
|last= 14 September 2011
|occupation= Student
}}
'''Flynn Buchanan''', played by Ryan Prescott, made his first on-screen appearance on 31 January 2011. Flynn was introduced as a love interest for [[Aaron Livesy]].

Prescott landed the role of Flynn shortly after graduating from a performing arts degree. He began filming his first scenes in late November 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Champ&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.champnews.com/html/newsstory.asp?id=8944|title=Emmerdale actor from Southport in new ITV drama|last=Young|first=Natasha|date=11 February 2011|work=[[Southport#Newspapers|The Champion]]|publisher=Champion Media Group|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prescott told ''The Champion'' that he has been recognised from being in ''[[Emmerdale]]''. He said &quot;The storyline in ''Emmerdale'' was so big already that it's brought a lot of publicity, I signed my first couple of autographs the other day which was weird.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Champ&quot;/&gt; He added that he had enjoyed his time on the set.&lt;ref name=&quot;Champ&quot;/&gt; In August 2011, it was announced Prescott would be returning to ''Emmerdale'' for a one off guest appearance in September 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/scoop/a334087/emmerdale-flynn-new-guest-appearance-confirmed.html|title='Emmerdale' Flynn: New guest appearance confirmed|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=9 August 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=10 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Flynn meets [[Aaron Livesy]] ([[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]]) in a gay nightclub in Hotten. Flynn spots Aaron playing a game of pool with his friend [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]] ([[Adam Thomas]]). Flynn challenges Aaron to a game and wins. Adam buys Flynn a drink along with Aaron's. Flynn makes a pass at Aaron and gives him his phone number. Although Aaron initially rejects him and goes home, it is later revealed that Flynn has sent a text to Aaron asking him out for another date. The two continue to date over the following weeks when Flynn comes back from a trip away and has an awkward meeting in The Woolpack with Aaron's ex-boyfriend [[Jackson Walsh]] ([[Marc Silcock]]) who had asked Aaron to introduce him to Flynn. The following week, however, whilst they are on a date, Aaron begins to feel awkward and tells Flynn that he still wants to be with Jackson and regrets ending their relationship. Flynn tells Aaron that he is glad that he was finally being honest with him. Aaron ends his relationship with Flynn and reconciles with Jackson. A few months later, Adam spots Flynn on a night out. They go over to see Aaron and Flynn tells him he is glad to see him. They talk about Jackson's death and Aaron leaves Flynn alone in the bar.

==Steve Kelly==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Steve Kelly
|introducer= [[Gavin Blyth]]
|portrayer= Andy Walker
|years= 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Recurring characters|Present; recurring]]
|first= 25 February 2011
|last=
|occupation=  
|home=
|wife= 
}}
'''Steve Kelly''', played by Andy Walker, made his first on-screen appearance on 25 February 2011. Steve is a [[quadriplegic]] who tries to show [[Jackson Walsh]] that being disabled does not have to be a negative thing.

Walker was approached about appearing in ''[[Emmerdale]]'' by the charity [[Back-Up Trust]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.channel5.com/emmerdale/news/difficulty-playing-jackson-13165|title=Difficulty playing Jackson|date=27 March 2011|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=[[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was scheduled to appear in five episodes and he said &quot;Getting a part in ''Emmerdale'' is part of me going forward in my life.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;StarRole&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.oldham-chronicle.co.uk/news-features/8/news-headlines/53179/andy-lands-star-role-in-tv-soap|title=Andy lands star role in TV soap|last=Berry|first=Marina|date=23 February 2011|work=[[Oldham Evening Chronicle]]|publisher=Hirst, Kidd and Rennie Ltd|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walker was paralysed from the neck down during an accident in Goa in 2006. He broke his neck when he dived into the sea and hit his head on the sand.&lt;ref name=&quot;StarRole&quot;/&gt; Walker's character, Steve, was introduced to ''Emmerdale'' to show [[Jackson Walsh]] ([[Marc Silcock]]) that he has a life to live after being paralysed.&lt;ref name=&quot;StarRole&quot;/&gt; Of his part, Walker said &quot;I play the same role in the programme as I do in life, showing that disability doesn't necessarily have to be a negative thing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;StarRole&quot;/&gt; He added that Steve will tell Jackson that he can still go on holiday, take him to a football game and meet him in the pub.&lt;ref name=&quot;StarRole&quot;/&gt; 
{{-}}

==Cameron Murray==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Cameron Murray
|introducer= [[Gavin Blyth]]
|portrayer= [[Dominic Power]]
|years= 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present characters|Present; regular]]
|first= 3 March 2011
|last=
|occupation= Haulage driver 
|home= Tug Ghyll
|wife= Anna Murray (until 2011)
|sons= [[#Dylan Murray|Dylan Murray]]&lt;br&gt;[[#Harry Murray|Harry Murray]]
}}
'''Cameron Murray''', played by [[Dominic Power]], made his first on-screen appearance on 3 March 2011. Cameron is a former boyfriend of [[Debbie Dingle]] whom she met and had an affair with whilst she was living in Jersey. 

In December 2010, it was announced that former ''[[The Bill]]'' actor, Power had joined the cast of ''Emmerdale''.&lt;ref name=&quot;PowerJoins&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a294283/dominic-power-joins-emmerdale.html|title=Dominic Power joins 'Emmerdale'|last=Love|first=Ryan|date=21 December 2010|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Digital Spy]] said sparks will fly between [[Debbie Dingle|Debbie]] ([[Charley Webb]]) and Cameron and it becomes clear that they have a shared history. Debbie is unhappy to see Cameron in the village.&lt;ref name=&quot;PowerJoins&quot;/&gt; Of his character, Power said &quot;Cameron is a strong, sharp-tongued and defiant character. He is essentially a good guy but has a darker, edgier side to him.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;PowerJoins&quot;/&gt;

Cameron comes to the village after tracking Debbie down, so he can tell her that he has left his wife and kids for her. Debbie tells him that their affair was a mistake. [[Carl King]] gives Cameron a job at Emmerdale Haulage and he catches the eye of [[Eve Jenson]]. Debbie finally gives into Cameron and they get back together. Debbie then asks him to move into Tug Ghyll with her and her daughter [[Sarah Sugden Jr|Sarah]]. Debbie finds out that Sarah has taken a shine to Cameron, which makes Sarah's father [[Andy Sugden]] jealous. Cameron clashes with Debbie's father, [[Cain Dingle|Cain]]. Cameron tries to persuade Cain to let him be with his daughter. Debbie learns Cameron had another affair after she left Jersey, but he tells her it meant nothing. Cameron is delighted when Debbie reveals she is pregnant. However, Debbie later suffers a miscarriage. Cameron tries to support her and not let his feelings show. His sons, [[#Dylan Murray|Dylan]] and [[#Harry Murray|Harry]], come to stay for a few days. Sarah become sick and Cameron and Debbie learn she has a rare genetic disorder. Cameron hires his own truck and starts poaching the King's customers. Carl attacks Cameron's truck and Cameron then plots to ruin the Kings. Cameron, Cain and [[Charity Dingle]] steal the King's haulage trucks and sell them off. Cameron then wipes all the files containing contracts from Carl's computer. This prompts Cain to tell Cameron he is part of the Dingle clan.

==Alex Moss==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Alex Moss
|introducer= Stuart Blackburn
|portrayer= Kurtis Stacey
|years= 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters##Present cast|Present; regular]]
|first= 12 April 2011
|last=
|born=
|occupation= [[Farmhand]]
|home = Butler's Farm
}}
'''Alex Moss''' played by Kurtis Stacey, made his first on-screen appearance on 12 April 2011. Alex is a new farmhand employed by [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]] to work at Butler's Farm. 

Stacey's part in ''Emmerdale'' is his first major television role.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woof&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/interviews/woof-meet-the-new-fitty-at-butlers-farm/12370|title=Woof! Meet the new fitty at Butlers Farm|date=5 April 2011|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stacey admitted that he was nervous about making his debut and was worried that he would be replaced by a new actor. He told [[Holy Soap]], &quot;I didn't know what to expect about working on set and how the directors would work. I tried to be as calm and cool as I could and keep my performance natural.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://holysoap.channel5.com/emmerdale/news/kurtis-stacey-overcame-nerves-13396|title=Kurtis Stacey overcame nerves|date=7 April 2011|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=[[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During a March 2011 interview with [[Digital Spy]], Executive Producer [[Steve November]] commented on Stacey's casting and his character. He described Alex as &quot;a young guy, a working-class farmhand who arrives in the village. He's not unattractive by any means, so he'll be a bit of a heart-throb and romantic lead, break a few hearts, and provide some great stories for our younger women and girls.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/scoop/a309415/more-emmerdale-chat-from-steve-november.html|title=More 'Emmerdale' chat from Steve November|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=17 March 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alex has also been called a &quot;hunk&quot; and Stacey revealed that he gets into trouble because &quot;he is single and out to enjoy himself.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Woof&quot;/&gt; The actor explained that Alex is a regular guy who comes from a troubled background, his family is a touchy subject and this results in him shutting people out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woof&quot;/&gt; Stacey also revealed that if Alex has a secret then it is most likely to have something to do with his family.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woof&quot;/&gt; 

The [[Press Association]] reported that Alex would get off on the wrong foot with [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]] ([[Adam Thomas]]) shortly after his arrival.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaky&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/ukpress/article/ALeqM5i-DnuV5DJ9He3aB9fs8KlMdfeqLA?docId=N0388091301918611301A|title=Dales newcomer gets shaky welcome|date=4 April 2011|publisher=[[Press Association]]|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Alex gains [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]]'s ([[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]]) approval as he begins working on the farm and this &quot;riles up&quot; Adam.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaky&quot;/&gt; Of the situation, Stacey said &quot;I don't think he'll get on with Adam because he replaces Adam on the farm – Adam sees him arrive and work really hard and is annoyed that he's good.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaky&quot;/&gt; Alex also catches the eye of Adam's sister, [[Hannah Barton|Hannah]] ([[Grace Cassidy]]), and Adam does not like it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaky&quot;/&gt; Stacey added that Alex will become friends with [[Andy Sugden]] ([[Kelvin Fletcher]]) and he is initially the only person Alex knows in the village. The locals are a little suspicious of Alex at first.&lt;ref name=&quot;Shaky&quot;/&gt; When asked how Alex got the job with John, Stacey explained, &quot;Andy knew his dad and knows Alex is a hard worker so he recommends him. When he gets the job as a farmhand, he moves into the caravan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Woof&quot;/&gt;

Stacey later revealed that he would be involved with another female character.&lt;ref name=more/&gt; He said &quot;she's a bit of a naughty one [...]  it could be anyone with Alex. Alex is just waiting for the next woman or girl, whoever turns up, he's after them.&quot; He stated that Alex needs a female partner with a backbone that can sort him out. If Alex enters a serious relationship, he opined viewers would then see Alex is &quot;a good boy&quot;.&lt;ref name=more&gt;{{cite web|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|title='Emmerdale' star teases Alex Moss future|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a321083/emmerdale-star-teases-alex-moss-future.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=25 May 2011|date=24 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Holy Soap]] have branded him a &quot;hunky farmhand&quot; that had &quot;shaken up Emmerdale's female folk since arriving&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Third time lucky for Alex?|url=http://holysoap.channel5.com/emmerdale/news/third-time-lucky-for-alex-14336|work=[[Holy Soap]]|publisher=([[Channel 5 (UK)|Channel 5]])|accessdate=25 May 2011|date=25 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Nicky Pritchard==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series= Emmerdale
|name= Nicky Pritchard
|introducer= Stuart Blackburn
|portrayer= Matt Milburn
|years= 2011
|classification = [[List of past Emmerdale characters#Last appeared in 2011|Former, regular]]
|first= 26 May 2011
|last= 24 November 2011
|occupation= Vet
|home = 
}}
'''Nicky Pritchard''' played by [[Matt Milburn]], made his first on-screen appearance on 26 May 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosIn&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=16–22 April 2011|title=Who's in? Who's out?|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|issue=15|page=28|accessdate=14 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nicky arrives in the village as the new locum vet, hired by [[Paddy Kirk]] ([[Dominic Brunt]]). Nicky is described as being &quot;gorgeous&quot; and Paddy's partner, [[Rhona Goskirk|Rhona]] ([[Zoe Henry]]) is impressed by him.&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosIn&quot;/&gt; Milburn has described Nicky as being &quot;very confident and cocky about pretty much everything.&quot;&lt;ref name=wot&gt;{{cite web|title=Emmerdale newcomer's love triangle!|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/interviews/emmerdale-newcomers-love-triangle/13938|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=26 October 2011|date=19 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nicky will depart in November 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=12-18 November 2011|title=Who's in? Who's out?|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|issue=45|page=32|accessdate=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Nicky develops feelings for [[Genesis Walker]] ([[Sian Reese-Williams]]). Milburn said Gennie's personality is &quot;very endearing to Nicky&quot;, he thinks she is &quot;very cute&quot;.&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Nicky does not realise that Gennie is in love with [[Nikhil Sharma]] ([[Rik Makarem]]).&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Nicky and Nikhil act &quot;quite macho and testosterone-fuelled&quot; when together, but because of Nicky is so confident, he does not see him as competition.&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Gennie accepts Nicky's offer of a date after an arguemnet with Nikhil. Nicky behaves in a &quot;cheeky, forward and no-nonsense&quot; manner, which results in the pair having a good time. However, Nikhil see them and becomes jealous.&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Milburn said that &quot;Nicky's part of a kind of love triangle he has no idea about.&quot;&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Nicky is is deeply touched by Gennie, it is the first time another woman has made &quot;him feel different&quot;.&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; While Nicky has had many previous relationships, none have compared to the effect Gennie has on him.&lt;ref name=wot/&gt; Makarem said it has &quot;taken someone of Nicky's calibre, of all his charm and charisma&quot; to take an interest in Gennie, to wake Nikhil up to his own feelings for her.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Emmerdale's Rick Makram says Gennie is perfect for Nikhil|url=http://entertainment.stv.tv/tv/271190-emmerdales-rick-makram-says-gennie-is-perfect-for-nikhil/|work=[[STV (TV network)|STV]]|publisher=([[STV Group (Scotland)|STV Group plc]])|accessdate=26 October 2011|date=21 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Makarem later said that Nikhil knows that Gennie does not love Nicky. Nikhil is &quot;suspicious that Nicky's not to be trusted because of his charm and charisma and ease with the ladies.&quot;&lt;ref name=mak/&gt; Nikhil thinks that Nicky is cheating on Gennie after he sees him kissing someone. However, this kiss was innocent while greeting his sister-in-law. Nikhil tries to prevoke Nicky into &quot;doing something that gives him away&quot;, but when the kiss is revealed to be innocent, Gennie accuses Nikhil of setting Nicky up. A fight in the woolpack then ensues - because Nikhil is &quot;scared&quot; that he has lost Gennie. Makerem opined that Nikhil thinks Nicky cannot &quot;possibly love her the way he does&quot;.&lt;ref name=mak&gt;{{cite journal|last=James|first=Alison|title=Nikhil loves Gennie! (At last)|journal=[[Soaplife]]|date=31 October - 11 November 2011|issue=262|pages=32|publisher=[[IPC Media]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Nikhil confesses his love for Gennie and she reciprocates and ends her relationship with Nicky, he decides that there is nothing else for him left in Emmerdale as even Rhona is back working at the vet's. Because of this, he leaves the village.

==Leo Goskirk==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Leo Goskirk
|portrayer = Theo Tasker&lt;br&gt;Harry
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Recurring characters|Present, recurring]]
|first = 31 May 2011
|born = 31 May 2011
|home = Smithy Cottage
|family = [[Dingle family|Dingle]]
|mother = [[Rhona Goskirk]]
|father = [[Marlon Dingle]]
|grandfathers = [[Albert Dingle]] 
|grandmothers = Delilah Dingle 
|uncles = [[Eli Dingle]]
}}
'''Leo Goskirk''',&lt;ref name=&quot;ZoeH&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mirror.co.uk/celebs/tv/soap-news/2011/05/28/emmerdale-zoe-henry-on-rhona-giving-birth-marlon-s-down-s-syndrome-baby-115875-23161494/|title=Emmerdale: Zoe Henry on Rhona giving birth, Marlon's Down's syndrome baby|last=Stewart|first=Tony|date=28 May 2011|work=[[Daily Mirror]]|publisher=[[Trinity Mirror]]|accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; played by both Theo Tasker and Harry, made his first on-screen appearance on 31 May 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/spoilers/a320856/paddy-misses-the-birth-of-rhonas-baby.html|title=Paddy misses the birth of Rhona's baby|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=31 May 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leo is son of [[Rhona Goskirk]] and [[Marlon Dingle]].

[[Rhona Goskirk]] ([[Zoe Henry]]) realises she is pregnant shortly after ending her relationship with [[Marlon Dingle]] ([[Mark Charnock]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;RhonasBaby&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/storylines/rhonas-baby/|title=Rhona's Baby|publisher=[[itv.com]]|accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a scan, Rhona and Marlon are told that their baby has [[Down's Syndrome]].&lt;ref name=&quot;RhonasBaby&quot;/&gt; Rhona chooses to keep the baby and she, Marlon and her new partner, [[Paddy Kirk]] ([[Dominic Brunt]]), decide to share the parental responsibilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;RhonasBaby&quot;/&gt; Henry told the ''[[Daily Mirror]]'' that there are two baby boys playing Leo. They are not twins, which are usually cast to portray babies on-screen, and they both have Down's syndrome.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZoeH&quot;/&gt; Henry revealed that she was &quot;really excited&quot; to get the storyline because it is telling a real story that happens to real people.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZoeH&quot;/&gt; 

The babies who portray Leo are Theo Tasker and Harry.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ballymoneytimes.co.uk/news/local/soap_star_1_2754072|title=Soap Star!|last=Farrell|first=Nevin|date=8 June 2011|work=[[Ballymoney and Moyle Times]]|publisher=[[Johnston Publishing (NI)]]|accessdate=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Theo's mother, Dee Tasker, told the ''[[Ballymoney and Moyle Times]]'' that she is delighted her twelve week old baby is helping to send out a positive message about Down's syndrome.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;/&gt; Of this, Tasker said &quot;It is great that Theo can help people see that a baby born Down's syndrome is just the same as any other child who laughs, smiles and is a great wee character.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;/&gt; Tasker revealed that a woman at the Child Development Unit said ''Emmerdale'' were looking for a Down's Syndrome baby to play the role of Leo and they were invited along to meet the crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;/&gt; Tasker explained that she and her husband did not want to get involved initially because they were unaware of what the storyline would be.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;/&gt; ''Emmerdale'' explained the storyline and said that they would be portraying the issue &quot;positively and sensitively&quot;, so the Taskers agreed to Theo appearing.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoapStar&quot;/&gt;

Rhona goes into labour at [[The Woolpack]] after she is knocked over by [[Adam Barton (Emmerdale)|Adam Barton]] ([[Adam Thomas]]) and [[Aaron Livesy]] ([[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]]), who are fighting. She is taken to the hospital accompanied by Marlon, and she gives birth to a boy. After a discussion, Rhona and Marlon name their son, Leo. Paddy comes to visit Leo and Rhona, followed by Aaron, [[Hazel Rhodes]] ([[Pauline Quirke]]) and [[Jackson Walsh]] ([[Marc Silcock]]).
{{-}}

==Rachel Breckle==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Rachel Breckle
|portrayer = Gemma Oaten
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 19 July 2011
|home = Brook Cottage
|occupation = 
|sisters = [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]]
|nieces = [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia Spencer]] 
|nephews = [[#Sean Spencer|Sean Spencer]]
}}
'''Rachel Breckle''', played by Gemma Oaten, made her first on-screen appearance on 19 July 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a322842/emmerdale-casts-feisty-newcomer-rachel.html|title='Emmerdale' casts feisty newcomer Rachel|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|first=Kristy|last=Kelly|date=3 June 2011|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;StarPromises&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a330644/emmerdale-star-promises-great-plans-for-newcomer-rachel.html|title='Emmerdale' star promises &quot;great&quot; plans for newcomer Rachel|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=19 July 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=19 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character and casting was announced on 3 June 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; Of her casting, Oaten said &quot;I'm thrilled to be joining ''Emmerdale''. I've always watched the show and getting the part of Rachel is a dream come true. She is a fantastic character and I'm so excited about filming my first scenes.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; Series producer Stuart Blackburn said he was &quot;delighted&quot; to welcome Oaten to the cast.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt;  

Rachel is described as being &quot;defensive, argumentative&quot; and &quot;feisty.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; She is insistent on defending her young niece Amelia (Daisy Campbell), who is accused of bullying [[Samson Dingle]] (Sam Hall).&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; Blackburn said Rachel will &quot;ruffle a few feathers with her straight-talking approach but beneath the surface she is fiercely loyal with a hidden heart of gold.&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; Susan Hill of the ''[[Daily Star (United Kingdom)|Daily Star]]'' reported that Rachel would storm into the Dingles' house and accuse Samson of being a bully, shocking his father [[Sam Dingle|Sam]] ([[James Hooton]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;DStar&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailystar.co.uk/soaperstar/view/200312/Emmerdale-Rachel-Breckle-storms-into-the-Dingles-/|title=Rachel Breckle Storms Into The Dingles'|last=Hill|first=Susan|date=10 July 2011|work=[[Daily Star (United Kingdom)|Daily Star]]|publisher=[[Northern &amp; Shell]]|accessdate=11 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Same tries to appease a furious Rachel and she eventually calms down and realises Sam is struggling with Samson.&lt;ref name=&quot;DStar&quot;/&gt; Hill said &quot;She knows exactly what it's like and the pair have a lot more in common than they first think.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DStar&quot;/&gt; Rachel and Sam decide to sort things out together and Sam explains that it has been a tough time for Samson and that he promises to talk to him about his behavior.&lt;ref name=&quot;DStar&quot;/&gt; In July 2011, Oaten revealed that members of Rachel's &quot;extended family&quot; would be introduced in the coming months.&lt;ref name=&quot;StarPromises&quot;/&gt; The actress said &quot;There is a nephew that is coming in too, and there's going to be an extended family that I haven't heard too much about yet, so I'm really excited to see who I'm joined by in the coming months. It'll be great!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;StarPromises&quot;/&gt; Oaten also explained that she would like to explore Rachel's lonely side and see it come out as the weeks go by. She also added Rachel has a &quot;quite a quirky sense of humor.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;StarPromises&quot;/&gt;  

After her niece, Amelia, tells her she is being bullied by Samson Dingle, Rachel confronts his father, Sam. However, Rachel is forced to apologise to Sam, when she learns Amelia was actually bullying Samson. Rachel and Sam then become friends. Rachel's teenage nephew, [[Sean Spencer|Sean]] (Luke Roskell), finds her and reveals he stole some money from the local garage and [[Aaron Livesy]] ([[Danny Miller (actor)|Danny Miller]]) had collapsed while chasing him. Rachel is angered when Aaron's mother, [[Chas Dingle|Chas]] ([[Lucy Pargeter]]), threatens Sean and tells him to stay away from Aaron. Rachel is given a job in [[The Woolpack]] by [[Diane Sugden]] ([[Elizabeth Estensen]]). She works alongside [[Marlon Dingle]] ([[Mark Charnock]]) and she begins to fall for him. However, when Marlon turns Rachel down, she discovers he has feelings for [[Laurel Thomas]] ([[Charlotte Bellamy]]). Rachel tells Sam she is interested in Brook Cottage, but [[Nicola King]] ([[Nicola Wheeler]]) tells Rachel she cannot have the house. Rachel shows her sister, [[#Ali Spencer|Ali]] ([[Kelli Hollis]]), around the cottage and they rent the house from [[Declan Macey]] ([[Jason Merrells]]). Rachel, Ali, Amelia, Sean and Ali's girlfriend, [[#Ruby Haswell|Ruby Haswell]] ([[Alicya Eyo]]), then move into Brook Cottage.

==Sean Spencer==
&lt;!--{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Sean Spencer
|portrayer = Luke Roskell 
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 10 August 2011
|home = Brook Cottage
|occupation = Student
|father = [[#Dan Spencer|Dan Spencer]]
|mother = [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]]
|auntss = [[#Rachel Breckle|Rachel Breckle]]
|sisters = [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia Spencer]] 
}} --&gt;
'''Sean Spencer''', played by Luke Roskell, made his first on screen appearance on 10 August 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a332108/emmerdale-announces-new-characters-ali-and-ruby.html|title='Emmerdale' announces new characters Ali and Ruby|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=28 July 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=28 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/spoilers/a332368/aaron-has-another-furious-outburst-at-the-pub.html|title=Aaron has another furious outburst at the pub|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=3 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Roskell's casting was announced in June 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jackiepalmeragency.co.uk/news/2011/06/24/emmerdale|title=Emmerdale|date=24 June 2011|publisher=Jackie Palmer Stage School|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sean is [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]]'s ([[Kelli Hollis]]) son and [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia]]'s (Daisy Campbell) older brother.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Much to his horror, Sean's mother left his father for [[#Ruby Haswell|Ruby Haswell]] ([[Alicya Eyo]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Sean is not happy that his mother has come out as a lesbian and she is no longer with his father.&lt;ref name=&quot;SSpencer&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/sean-spencer/|title=Sean Spencer|publisher=[[itv.com]]|accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sean enjoys winding Ruby up.&lt;ref name=&quot;SSpencer&quot;/&gt; Sean has been described as a &quot;tearaway.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; The official ''Emmerdale'' website said Sean is typical teenager, full of attitude and hates being told what to do. He is &quot;potentially trouble.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SSpencer&quot;/&gt; Ali constantly worries about Sean and hopes village life will calm him down.&lt;ref name=&quot;SSpencer&quot;/&gt;  

==Ali Spencer==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Ali Spencer
|portrayer = [[Kelli Hollis]] 
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 17 October 2011
|home = Brook Cottage
|occupation = Factory worker
|husband = [[#Dan Spencer|Dan Spencer]]
|sisters = [[#Rachel Breckle|Rachel Breckle]]
|daughters = [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia Spencer]] 
|sons = [[#Sean Spencer|Sean Spencer]]
}}
'''Alison &lt;!-- First name revealed on 27 October 2011 (episode 6063)--&gt;&quot;Ali&quot; Spencer''' (née '''Breckle'''), made her first on screen appearance on 17 October 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; The character and casting was announced on 28 July 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Of joining the cast of ''Emmerdale'', Hollis said &quot;As a Leeds girl myself, getting a role as a new regular character for ''Emmerdale'' in my home town is a dream come true. I'm really excited to be playing Ali.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Hollis told Daniel Kilkelly of [[Digital Spy]] that she received a phone call about the part of Ali.&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a345116/emmerdale-kelli-hollis-on-ali-joining-soap-and-more-interview.html|title='Emmerdale' Kelli Hollis on Ali, joining soap and more: Interview|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=12 October 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She went on to explain &quot;Alicya and I had different partners in the screen test and I was so sure she would get the part and because she had a different partner, I thought that was it for me. But when I got it, I was just over the moon. I'm from Leeds and live just ten minutes from the studio and ''Emmerdale'' is just an institution, so to get a job here is just amazing.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;/&gt;

Ali is [[#Rachel Breckle|Rachel Breckle]]'s (Gemma Oaten) sister. She is the mother of [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia]] (Daisy Campbell) and [[#Sean Spencer|Sean Spencer]] (Luke Roskell).&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Ali leaves her husband, Dan (Liam Fox), and flat on the Hotten estate for a new start in the village with her children and her girlfriend, [[#Ruby Haswell|Ruby Haswell]] ([[Alicya Eyo]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Of Ali, a show statement said &quot;Ali is determined to make her new life in Emmerdale with Ruby work, regardless of Sean's reaction and the pleas of her determined ex-husband to give their marriage another go. When faced with the reality of Ali's baggage, does Ruby really feel the same?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Series producer Stuart Blackburn said Ali and Ruby are both down to earth, funny and likeable women.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Hollis described Ali as &quot;feisty&quot; and said she would do anything for her children.&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;/&gt; While she does not have any issues about leaving her husband of fifteen years for a woman, Ali is dealing with how her choice is affecting the family.&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;/&gt; Hollis said &quot;She just wants to find a way for them all to get on together, including with her sister Rachel. For Ali, everything is about keeping the family together at the moment.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;/&gt; Of Ali's relationship with Ruby, Hollis said her character never planned to become a lesbian, but then she met Ruby and fell in love with her. Ali is fully committed to Ruby and did not take the decision to leave her husband lightly.&lt;ref name=&quot;KelliH&quot;/&gt;

==Ruby Haswell==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Ruby Haswell
|portrayer = [[Alicya Eyo]]
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 20 October 2011
|home = Brook Cottage
|occupation = Carer
}}
'''Ruby Haswell''', played by [[Alicya Eyo]], made her first on screen appearance on 20 October 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; The character and casting was announced on 28 July 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Of joining ''Emmerdale'', Eyo said &quot;I'm over the moon and can't wait to get started. Being part of a show that I've grown up watching is amazing and Ruby is going to be a lot of fun to play.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Ruby is in a relationship with [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]] ([[Kelli Hollis]]) and they move into the village with Ali's children.&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt; Both Ali and Ruby were tipped to cause a stir with their &quot;no-nonsense attitudes.&quot; Series producer, Stuart Blackburn described Ali and Ruby as &quot;down to earth, gritty, funny and likeable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RubyAli&quot;/&gt;

Eyo told ''[[Inside Soap]]'' Ruby is really comfortable with herself and her sexuality. She does not feel she has anything to prove.&lt;ref name=&quot;HotGossip&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|date=22-28 October 2011|title=Hot Gossip!|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|issue=42|page=23|accessdate=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; No one in the village is aware Ali is a lesbian, until [[Brenda Walker]] ([[Lesley Dunlop]]) and [[Nicola King]] ([[Nicola Wheeler]]) see her and Ruby kissing. Because she is not happy that Ali and Ruby moved in Brook Cottage, Nicola announces they are together in The Woolpack.&lt;ref name=&quot;HotGossip&quot;/&gt; Of this, Eyo said &quot;I don't think Ruby and Ali are expecting their new life in Emmerdale to be plain sailing by any means. But these women are really dedicated to each other, so I think they can sort anything out between them if they're on the receiving end of any hassle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;HotGossip&quot;/&gt; Eyo added Ruby is already used to gossip and she can handle herself, but if people have a go at Ali or her children, then she will not stand for it.&lt;ref name=&quot;HotGossip&quot;/&gt;    

Ruby arrives in the village to join her partner, Ali, and her two children, [[#Sean Spencer|Sean]] (Luke Roskell) and [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia]] (Daisy Campbell). Sean is not happy to learn Ruby is moving in too and while he, Ali and Ruby are arguing, Amelia wanders off and is nearly run over by [[Carl King]] ([[Tom Lister]]). [[Sam Dingle]] ([[James Hooton]]) pulls Amelia to safety and Ruby realises she has injured her shoulder. She takes everyone to the hospital. When Carl and [[#Cameron Murray|Cameron Murray]] ([[Dominic Power]]) help move Ali and Ruby's furniture, they are shocked to find out Ali and Ruby are lesbians.

==Georgia Sharma==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Georgia Sharma
|portrayer = [[Trudie Goodwin]] 
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 3 November 2011
|occupation = 
|home = Holdgate Farm
|husband = [[Rishi Sharma]]
|sons = [[Nikhil Sharma]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jai Sharma]]
|daughters = [[Priya Sharma]] 
|granddaughters = [[Mia Macey]]
}} --&gt;
'''Georgia Sharma''', played by [[Trudie Goodwin]], made her first on screen appearance on 3 November 2011. The character and casting was announced on 7 September 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/news/meet-the-parents/|title=Meet the parents|date=7 September 2011|work=Emmerdale|publisher=[[itv.com]]|accessdate=7 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Georgia is [[Nikhil Sharma|Nikhil]], [[Jai Sharma|Jai]] and [[Priya Sharma]]'s mother. She and her husband arrive in the village to meet Jai's fiancee, [[Charity Tate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; Georgia is described as being &quot;formidable, demanding and yet witty.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; Of her casting, Goodwin said &quot;I'm absolutely thrilled to be playing Georgia in ''Emmerdale''. She is a difficult-to-please woman who is set to make life difficult for Charity. I can't wait to start filming next week.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; 

==Rishi Sharma==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Rishi Sharma
|portrayer = Bhasker Patel 
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present, regular]]
|first = 3 November 2011
|occupation = 
|home = Holdgate Farm
|wife = [[Georgia Sharma]]
|sons = [[Nikhil Sharma]]&lt;br&gt;[[Jai Sharma]]
|daughters = [[Priya Sharma]] 
|granddaughters = [[Mia Macey]]
}} --&gt;
'''Rishi Sharma''', played by Bhasker Patel, made his first on screen appearance on 3 November 2011. The character and casting was announced on 7 September 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; Rishi is married to [[Georgia Sharma|Georgia]] and is father to [[Nikhil Sharma|Nikhil]], [[Jai Sharma|Jai]] and [[Priya Sharma]]. He and his wife arrive in the village to meet Jai's fiancee, [[Charity Tate]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; Rishi is described as being &quot;business-obsessed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt; Of the Sharma's casting, Stuart Blackburn said &quot;I'm delighted to welcome Trudie, Bhasker and Fiona to the cast. There are plenty of trials and tribulations in store for the ever popular Sharma family.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MeetParents&quot;/&gt;

==Dan Spencer==
&lt;!-- {{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Dan Spencer
|portrayer = Liam Fox 
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present characters|Present, recurring]]
|first = 9 November 2011
|home = 
|occupation = Builder
|wife = [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]]
|daughters = [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia Spencer]] 
|sons = [[#Sean Spencer|Sean Spencer]]
}} --&gt;
'''Dan Spencer''', played by Liam Fox, made his first on screen appearance on 9 November 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;DanS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s2/eastenders/scoop/a345018/eastenders-coronation-street-emmerdale-cast-updates.html|title='EastEnders', 'Coronation Street', 'Emmerdale': Cast updates|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=11 October 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|date=5-11 November 2011|title=What happend when?|journal=[[Inside Soap]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|issue=44|page=28|accessdate=1 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character and casting was announced on 11 October 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;DanS&quot;/&gt; Dan is the father of [[#Amelia Spencer|Amelia]] (Daisy Campbell) and [[#Sean Spencer|Sean]] (Luke Roskell). He is also [[#Ali Spencer|Ali Spencer]]'s ([[Kelli Hollis]]) estranged husband and he arrives in the village hoping to make life difficult for Ali and her new girlfriend, [[#Ruby Haswell|Ruby]] ([[Alicya Eyo]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;DanS&quot;/&gt;

==Kyle==
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series = Emmerdale
|name = Kyle
|portrayer =  
|introducer = Stuart Blackburn
|years = 2011—
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Recurring characters|Present, recurring]]
|first = 1 December 2011
|born = 1 December 2011
|home =
|father = [[Cain Dingle]]
|mother = [[Amy Wyatt]]
|halfsisters = [[Debbie Dingle]] 
|grandfathers = [[Zak Dingle]]
|grandmothers = [[Faith Dingle]]
|uncles = [[Sam Dingle]]
|aunts = [[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Belle Dingle]]
|nieces = [[Sarah Sugden]]
|cousins = [[Aaron Livesy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Samson Dingle]]
|relatives = [[Lisa Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br /&gt;[[#Leo Goskirk|Leo Goskirk]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]&lt;br&gt;[[Charity Tate]]&lt;br&gt;[[Noah Tate]]
}}
'''Kyle''' made his first on screen appearance on 1 December 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a353051/emmerdale-star-chelsea-halfpenny-on-amys-baby-arrival-interview.html|title='Emmerdale' star Chelsea Halfpenny on Amy's baby arrival: Interview|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=26 November 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a353814/potd-emmerdales-amy-gives-birth.html|title=POTD: 'Emmerdale's Amy gives birth|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|date=1 December 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hearst Magazines UK]]|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is the son of [[Amy Wyatt]] ([[Chelsea Halfpenny]]) and [[Cain Dingle]] ([[Jeff Hordley]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt;

Amy discovers she is pregnant with Cain's baby following a one-night stand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailystar.co.uk/posts/view/204973/Baby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-EmmerdaleBaby-blow-for-Amy-in-Emmerdale|title=Baby Blow For Amy In Emmerdale|last=Hill|first=Susan|date=7 August 2011|work=[[Daily Star (United Kingdom)|Daily Star]]|publisher=[[Northern &amp; Shell]]|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When asked if Amy is shocked that she is pregnant, Halfpenny told ''[[What's on TV]]'' &quot;Yes. She didn't ever imagine it would happen – especially not from just a one-night stand. And it couldn't have come at a worse time because she's fallen out with Val and Eric.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyBlues&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/interviews/emmerdales-chelsea-on-amys-baby-blues/13643|title=Emmerdale's Chelsea on Amy's baby blues|date=18 August 2011|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Halfpenny explained Amy is scared by Cain's angry reaction to the news, as she thought he would be more sympathetic.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyBlues&quot;/&gt; Cain convinces Amy to have an abortion, but after seeing an ultrasound scan of the baby, Amy realises she wants to keep it.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyBlues&quot;/&gt; Of this, Halfpenny said &quot;Because Amy hasn't had love in her life she doesn't want to do that to anybody else.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyBlues&quot;/&gt; Amy manages to keep her pregnancy a secret and she plans to give birth away from the village, but she goes into labour unexpectedly and gives birth in the local cemetery.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt; Halfpenny filmed the labour scenes during four night shoots and she called them daunting as she wanted them to look realistic.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt; Amy gives birth to a boy, but panics when he does not appear to be alive, she wraps him up and places him in a phone box. [[Hazel Rhodes]] ([[Pauline Quirke]]) finds the baby boy, who is alive, and calls an ambulance.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt; Of Amy's reaction to this, Halfpenny said &quot;She's still panicking, but the fact that he is alive is a massive relief to her. It's a big weight off her shoulders, because she never intended to harm the child at all - she's always wanted to give her baby to someone who would look after him properly.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt; Amy plans to have the baby adopted and her foster parents, [[Val Pollard|Val]] ([[Charlie Hardwick]]) and [[Eric Pollard]] ([[Chris Chittell]]), have different reactions to the announcement.&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt; Halfpenny told Daniel Kilkelly of [[Digital Spy]] that Eric wants whatever Amy wants, but Val wants to keep the baby so she can give him what she did not give her own children. Halfpenny added &quot;So Val is a lot more maternal when it comes to Kyle and wants Amy to keep him, while I think Pollard is happy with whatever Amy wants to do.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BabyArrival&quot;/&gt;

Following a one-night stand with Cain, Amy discovers she is pregnant with his child. She tells Cain, who pays her to have an abortion. Amy goes to the clinic with her friend, [[Victoria Sugden]] ([[Isabel Hodgins]]), but she cannot go through with the abortion. Amy later changes he mind, but she is told her pregnancy is too far along to have the procedure. Amy keeps her pregnancy a secret from everyone, except [[Belle Dingle]] ([[Eden Taylor-Draper]]). Amy goes into labour and gives birth in the local cemetery, she believes her baby boy is dead and she wraps him up and places him in a phonebox. The baby is found by Hazel Rhodes and taken to the hospital.

==Others==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%&quot;
! Date(s) !! Character !! Actor !! Circumstances
|-
|{{nowrap|19 January–24 June}} ||'''Joe Chappell'''|| [[Scott Taylor (actor)|Scott Taylor]] ||{{Anchor|Joe Chappell}} Joe is [[Jackson Walsh]]'s carer. Joe takes care of Jackson at home and accompanies him when he is out and about. Joe reveals that he has an overbearing mother. Joe was dismissed by Hazel so she could help care for Jackson in the run up to ending his life. Joe attends Jackson's funeral and helps carry the coffin.
|-
|1 February–February ||{{nowrap|'''Stephanie Ray'''}}|| Elianne Byrne ||{{Anchor|Stephanie Ray}} Stephanie is a midwife and an old friend of [[Rhona Goskirk]]. Stephanie conducts Rhona's scan at the hospital and Rhona sets her up on a date with [[Marlon Dingle]]. Stephanie and Marlon go for drinks at The Woolpack, but Marlon is not impressed with Stephanie.
|-
|21 February– ||'''Annie Kelly'''|| Joanna Bond&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pha-agency.co.uk/casting/actors/news/article.aspx?ID=5919|title=Emmerdale – Joanna Bond|publisher=pha casting|accessdate=14 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ||{{Anchor|Annie Kelly}} Annie is [[#Steve Kelly|Steve]]'s wife. She helps support [[Hazel Rhodes]], whose son, [[Jackson Walsh]], is a quadriplegic. She attends Jackson's funeral with Steve and tells Hazel that she did not give Jackson a chance. She also mentions that she is pregnant. 
|-
|3 March–March ||'''Josh Walsh'''|| Benjamin Murphy ||{{Anchor|Josh Walsh}} Josh is [[Jerry Walsh]]'s son from his second marriage. Jerry brings Josh to the village to introduce him to his half brother [[Jackson Walsh|Jackson]]. Jerry asks Jackson to be Josh's godfather and he initially turns down the offer. [[Aaron Livesy]] and [[Hazel Rhodes]] later convince him to do the job, but he fails to go to the christening after an argument with them. Jerry brings Josh round and Aaron gives him a toy shark as a gift.
|-
|{{nowrap|28 March–27 May}} ||'''Elliot Windsor'''|| Oliver Brooke ||{{Anchor|Elliot Windsor}} Elliot is the son of [[Kelly Windsor]] and [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]]. Kelly brings Elliot with her when she moves back to the village and introduces him to her ex-fiance [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]], whom she claims is Elliot's father. Kelly reveals that Elliot was born after she left the village and Jimmy had not known about him until Kelly got back in touch with him. Kelly and Jimmy sit down with Elliot and try to explain to him that Jimmy is his father. Elliot departs with his mother.
|-
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |23 June ||'''Dylan Murray'''|| {{nowrap|Mikey Thomasson&lt;ref name=&quot;RadioTimes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radiotimes.com/ListingsServlet?event=10&amp;channelId=26&amp;programmeId=192945779&amp;jspLocation=/jsp/prog_details_fullpage.jsp|title=Emmerdale – Thursday 23 June|work=[[Radio Times]]|publisher=BBC Magazines|accessdate=10 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zLKAJWMO|archivedate=10 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}} ||rowspan=&quot;2&quot; | {{Anchor|Dylan Murray}}{{Anchor|Harry Murray}} Dylan and Harry are [[#Cameron Murray|Cameron Murray]]'s sons. They come to stay with their father in Emmerdale. 
|-
|'''Harry Murray'''|| Alfie Middlemiss&lt;ref name=&quot;RadioTimes&quot;/&gt;  
|-
| 18 July–16 August ||'''Jared Haynes'''|| Philip Hill-Pearson&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radiotimes.com/ListingsServlet?event=10&amp;channelId=26&amp;programmeId=198695106&amp;jspLocation=/jsp/prog_details_fullpage.jsp|title=Emmerdale - Wednesday 20 July|work=[[Radio Times]]|publisher=BBC Magazines|accessdate=7 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ||{{Anchor|Jared Haynes}} Jared arrives in the village to attend a party thrown by his friend, [[Amy Wyatt]]. Jared threatens to tell Amy's guardians about her past and he starts to blackmail her for money. He later reveals Amy ruined his family, by having sex with his father. [[Zak Dingle]] tells Jared to leave and he does.
|-
| 19 July– ||{{nowrap|'''Amelia Spencer'''}}|| Daisy Campbell&lt;ref name=&quot;Feisty&quot;/&gt; ||{{Anchor|Amelia Spencer}} Amelia is [[#Rachel Breckle|Rachel Breckle]]'s young niece, who accuses [[Samson Dingle]] of bullying her. Rachel and Sam try to sort the situation out and Sam accuses Amelia of bullying Samson.
|-
| 25–28 July ||'''Prosecutor'''|| [[James Gaddas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;TrialGuests&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a328182/emmerdale-confirms-aaron-livesy-trial-guest-stars.html|title='Emmerdale' confirms Aaron Livesy trial guest stars|last=Love|first=Ryan|date=4 July 2011|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|accessdate=4 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;|| Gaddas plays the prosecutor during [[Aaron Livesy]]'s trial.
|-
| 25–28 July ||'''Defense'''|| [[Tony Maudsley]]&lt;ref name=&quot;TrialGuests&quot;/&gt;|| Maudsley is [[Aaron Livesy]]'s lawyer.
|-
| 25–28 July ||'''Judge'''|| [[Mary Jo Randle]]&lt;ref name=&quot;TrialGuests&quot;/&gt;|| Randle is the judge presiding over [[Aaron Livesy]]'s trial.
|-
|}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.itv.com/soaps/emmerdale/castandcharactersatoe/cameronmurray/ Cameron Murray] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/soaps/emmerdale/castandcharactersatoe/alexmoss/ Alex Moss] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/rachel-breckle/ Rachel Breckle] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/amelia-spencer/ Amelia Spencer] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/sean-spencer/ Sean Spencer] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/ali-spencer/ Ali Spencer] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/ruby-haswell/ Ruby Haswell] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/georgia-sharma/ Georgia Sharma] at [[itv.com]]
* [http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/rishi-sharma/ Rishi Sharma] at [[itv.com]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}

[[Category:Emmerdale characters|2011]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Emmerdale, 2011]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2011|*, Emmerdale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
