<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30673290" ns="0" title="2011 Jordanian protests"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{incomplete|date=January 2011}}
{{Infobox Civil Conflict
| conflict = 2011 Jordanian protests
| partof = the [[Arab Spring]]
| image = [[Image:Jordan Locator.png|300px]]
| caption =  Map of Jordan
| date={{Start date|2011|01|07}} – ''ongoing'' 
| place = {{flag|Jordan}}
| coordinates = {{Coord|26|01|39|N|50|33|00|E|region:BH_type:country|display=title,inline}}
| causes = &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Inflation]]
* Low [[Salaries]] 
* [[Unemployment]] 
* [[Regressive tax]]es,&lt;ref name=&quot;2feb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeeraProtestsInAmman&quot; /&gt; 
* Ethnic tensions&lt;ref name=&quot;liesbeneath&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.aljazeera.net/middle-east/2011/07/21/what-lies-beneath-jordanian-calls-reform|agency=Al Jazeera English|date=21 July 2011|accessdate=21 July 2011|title=What lies beneath Jordanian calls for reform|first=Nisreen|last=El-Shamayleh}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| status = King [[Abdullah II of Jordan|Abdullah II]] dismissed Prime Minister [[Samir Rifai|Rifai]] and his Cabinet.&lt;ref name=&quot;2feb&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimesDismissesCabinet&quot; /&gt; &lt;small&gt;(see section {{Sectionlink|New government}})&lt;/small&gt;
| goals = &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
* [[Democracy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost1&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeeraProtestersDemandChange&quot; /&gt;
| result =
| methods = [[Demonstration (people)|Demonstrations]]
| concessions =
| side1 =  {{*}}[[Muslim Brotherhood#Jordan|Muslim Brotherhood]]&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}[[Leftist]]&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt; parties&lt;ref name=&quot;4feb&quot; /&gt;&lt;br/&gt;{{*}}14 trade unions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jan/15/jordanians-protest-over-food-prices|title=Jordanians protest against soaring food prices|author=Johnny McDevitt|work=[[guardian.co.uk]]|location=London|date=15 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| side2 =  {{*}}{{flagicon|Jordan}} [[Government of Jordan]] and supporters
| side3 =
| leadfigures1 = {{*}}Retired General [[Ali Habashnah]]&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost1&quot;/&gt;
| leadfigures2 = {{*}}[[King Abdullah II]]&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}Prime Minister [[Samir Rifai]]&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt;
| leadfigures3 =
| howmany1 = {{*}}'''Protesters''': 6,000–10,000&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcJordanBiggestRally&quot; /&gt;
| howmany2 =
| howmany3 =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| casualties3 =
| arrests =
| injuries = 70&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCInjuries&quot; /&gt;
| fatalities = one due to heart failure and not injury related&lt;ref name=&quot;khaberni.com&quot;&gt;http://khaberni.com/more.asp?ThisID=52120&amp;ThisCat=1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/201121821116689870.html&lt;/ref&gt;
| notes =
}}

The '''2011 Jordanian protests''' are a series of protests occurring in [[Jordan]] in 2011, which resulted in the firing of the cabinet ministers of the government.

[[Food inflation]] and salaries were a cause for resentment in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;2feb&quot;/&gt;
The [[2010-2011 Tunisian Revolution]] and the [[2011 Egyptian Revolution]] also raised hopes for political change in the region. Together with unrest elsewhere in the Middle East and North Africa, including the disturbances in Syria and Yemen, they are part of the [[Arab Spring]].

==Background==
[[Image:Jordanian Police Car.jpg|thumb|left|Jordanian Police Ford Crown Victoria in Karak, Jordan.]]
Jordan's economy continues to struggle, weighed down by a record deficit of $2 billion this year.&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt; Inflation in Jordan has risen by 1.5% to 6.1% in December 2010, and unemployment and poverty have become rampant, estimated at 12% and 25% respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt; The government is also accused of impoverishing the working class with regressive tax codes which forced the poor to pay a higher proportion of their income as tax. The parliament is accused of serving as a &quot;rubber stamp&quot; to the executive branch.&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot; /&gt;

Jordan has a history of persecuting activists and journalists. The country amended its penal code in August 2010 and passed a Law of Information System Crimes, to regulate the Internet. Revised laws continue to criminalize peaceful expression and extend those provisions to Internet expression. Jordanian authorities prosecuted peaceful dissidents and prohibited peaceful gatherings to protest government policies. Dissidents confined by the General Intelligence Department routinely sign confessions. According to a report by Amnesty International, intelligence agents in Jordan frequently use torture to extract confessions from suspects.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Human Rights In Hashemite Kingdom Of Jordan |url=http://www.amnesty.org/en/region/jordan/report-2010 |title=Jordan - Amnesty International Report 2010 |publisher=Amnesty.org |date=18 November 2009 |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to an [[Al Jazeera]] correspondent in [[Amman]], [[Transjordan|East Bank Jordanians]] and [[Bedouin]]s form the &quot;bedrock&quot; of the government's support, while self-identifying [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]]s are generally closer to the opposition. Al Jazeera reported that many government supporters are worried that if Palestinians are allowed a greater role in the country's politics, they could drag it into the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]] against Jordan's best interests. Conversely, Palestinian-Jordanian protesters want their degree of political power to reflect their significant demographic share.&lt;ref name=&quot;liesbeneath&quot;/&gt;

==Protests==
The [[Muslim Brotherhood#Jordan|Muslim Brotherhood]], one of the largest opposition groups in Jordan, on January 26 urged Jordanians to pour into streets later in the week to protest against Prime Minister [[Samir Rifai]]'s economic policies and the political situation in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;deficit&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| last=
| first=
| url=  http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/2011128125157509196.html
| title=  Thousands protest in Jordan
| publisher=  al-jazeera
| date=28 January 2011
| accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Demonstrators protested rising prices and demanded the dismissal of the Prime Minister and his government, but they have not directly challenged the king, criticism of whom is banned in Jordan. The demonstrators have been peaceful and have not been confronted by the police. So far no deaths, injuries or riots have been reported; however the protests' leaders said that the king had failed to take substantial steps to address mounting public resentment and they warned that unless real changes are made, that unrest could worsen. [[King Abdullah II]], a key U.S. ally, has come under pressure recently from various protesters which include a coalition of Islamists, secular opposition groups and a group of retired army generals, all of whom are calling for substantial political and economic reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author= |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/01/31/AR2011013103692.html |title=Jordan's King Abdullah II ousts prime minister, cabinet in wake of mass protests |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date=1 February 2011|accessdate=2 February 2011 |first=Joel |last=Greenberg}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ali Habashnah, one of the retired generals desiring reforms, said that unrest has spread to rural areas dominated by Bedouin tribes. These tribes have been a traditional backbone of the monarchy. It was the first time, he said, that the Bedouins had joined with other groups in demands for change.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost1&quot;/&gt;

On 28 January, following [[Friday prayers]], 3,500 activists from the Muslim Brotherhood, trade unions, and communist and leftist organisations demanded that [[Samir Rifai]] step down as prime minister and that the government control rising prices, inflation and unemployment.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeeraProtestsInAmman&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/2011128125157509196.html |title=Thousands protest in Jordan - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protests were reported in Amman and six other cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/africa/02/01/jordan.government|title=Jordan's king dismisses government, appoints new PM | work=CNN}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thousands took to the streets in the capital, Amman, as well as several other cities shouting, &quot;We want change.&quot; Banners complained of high food and fuel prices and demanded the resignation of the prime minister, an appointee of the king.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimesDismissesCabinet&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/02/world/middleeast/02jordan.html|title=Jordan’s King Dismisses Cabinet as Tremors Spread Through Region | work=The New York Times | first1=Ranya|last1=Kadri|first2=Ethan|last2=Bronner|date=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 February, demonstrations continued in demanding that King Abdullah II sack his newly appointed prime minister. Hamza Mansour, one of the leaders of the Jordanian Muslim Brotherhood, demanded elections to choose another prime minister. He said that Al-Bakhit &quot;doesn't believe in democracy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;2feb&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2011-02-03-egyptregion03_ST_N.htm|title=Jordan, Yemen grapple with effects of protests | work=USA Today | date=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The day after King Abdullah met with Muslim Brotherhood leaders at the royal palace, in an attempt to defuse tensions in the country, on 4 February, hundreds of people, including members of leftist groups and the Muslim Brotherhood, congregated outside the prime minister's office to demand economic and political reforms and the dissolution of parliament. They then marched to the Egyptian embassy in support of the anti-government protesters in that country.&lt;ref name=&quot;4feb&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| last=
| first=
| url=  http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/201124141624836763.html
| title=  Rallies held in Jordan and Syria
| publisher=  [[Al-Jazeera English]]
| date=4 February 2011
| accessdate=4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 February, protesters who gathered in central Amman to demand political reform, have clashed with a small group of government supporters that eyewitnesses claim attacked the protesters with sticks and stones, before the police restored order. Eyewitnesses said about 2,000 protesters, mostly young people joined by trade unionists and others, took to the streets after prayers at the Husseini Mosque, though other reports said the number was about 300.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcClashesInJordan&quot;&gt;{{cite news
| url=  http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12507937
| title=  Middle East unrest: Clashes erupt at Jordan protest
| publisher=  BBC
| date=18 February 2011
| accessdate=18 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

About 7,000-10,000 protesters were on the streets of Amman on 25 February, in the largest protests so far.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcJordanBiggestRally&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12582869 | work=BBC News | title=Middle East protests: Jordan sees biggest reform rally | date=25 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Islamic Action Front, along with 19 other political parties, called for the protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;presstvJordanLargestRally&quot;&gt;[http://www.presstv.ir/detail/166928.html PressTV - Jordan braces for its 'largest' rally&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first week of March anti-government protesters continued where opposition groups demanded such greater political freedoms as a [[constitutional monarchy]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeeraProtestersDemandChange&quot;&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/video/middleeast/2011/03/20113123552363334.html Jordan protesters demand change - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 March, ''Al-Jazeera English'' reported that around 500 protesters, mainly university students and politically unaffiliated unemployed graduates have set up a protest camp in a main square in the capital to press demands for the ouster of the prime minister, seen as insufficiently reformist, as well as wider public freedoms. Other demands include dissolving the parliament, which is seen as too docile, dismantling the intelligence department and giving greater powers to the people, including a new, more proportional, election law. Jordan's opposition also want to strip the king of some of his powers, specifically in appointing the prime minister, as they want the premier to be elected by a popular vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Protest camp set up in Jordan capital |author=[[Al-Jazeera English]] |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/201132414304102344.html |newspaper= |date=24 March 2011 |accessdate=25 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 March, clashes occurred between supporters of the king and more than 2000 protesters camped in Gamal Abdel Nasser Circle. Some witnesses said the police stood by as government supporters moved in to the square and began throwing stones.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCInjuries&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Clashes break out at Jordan anti-government protest |author=[[BBC]] |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12857360 |newspaper= |date=25 March 2011 |accessdate=25 March 2011 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt; As many as 100 people were reported injured, most with head wounds, while two people are said to have been killed. However, the next day in a press conference, the commandant of public security, [[Lieutenant General]] [[Hussein Al-Majali]] confirmed that there was one death only, with 62 injured civilians, and 58 injured policemen (including a [[Brigadier General]] and a [[Lieutenant Colonel]]).   Forensic medicine report confirmed that there were no signs of any injury, and that the patient actually died of [[circulatory collapse]] secondary to [[chronic]] [[ischemic heart disease]].In the same press conference, Al-Majali also confirmed that 8 civilians and 17 policemen were still receiving hospital treatment at the time of the conference, and also stressed that policemen were completely unarmed and they interfered just to save the lives of people whatever their political view is.&lt;ref name=&quot;khaberni.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ammonnews.net/article.aspx?articleNO=83610&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://khaberni.com/more.asp?ThisID=52128&amp;ThisCat=1&lt;/ref&gt; On the same day of clashes, thousands gathered in Al-Hussein Gardens west of Amman to express loyalty and allegiance to the king, dancing to national songs and waving large Jordanian flags and pictures of the monarch.

On 1 April, nearly 400 policemen were deployed to separated hundreds of government supporters and pro-reform activists holding rival rallies outside municipal offices in Amman.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJJordan1Apr&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordanian police separate rival rallies |author= |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/04/2011411707284653.html |newspaper= |date=1 April 2011 |accessdate=2 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 April, more than 2,000 Jordanians took to the streets throughout the country demanding greater political representation, with half of them demonstrating in Amman, immediately after prayers. Also, a crowd of a few hundred Islamists clashed with a somewhat smaller group of monarchy loyalists in [[Zarqa]]. Eight civilians and 83 policemen were wounded, including 4 in critical condition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=
Clashes erupt in Jordanian town |author= |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/04/2011415153839185473.html |newspaper= |date=15 April 2011 |accessdate=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 June, the motorcade of King Abdullah II was attacked with stones and bottles by protesters in the city of [[Tafileh]], although this wasn later denied, a royal official stating that they were enthusiastically greeted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan: Protesters lob stones at King Abdullah II |author=[[BBC]] |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13751299 |newspaper= |date=13 June 2011 |accessdate=13 June 2011 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Some indication is that this was actually an outbreak of violence between the Darak ([[Gendarmerie|Jordanian Gendarmerie]]) and local unemployed protesters. It is alleged that the local mayor caused the Darak to force back the protesters not wanting his city to look bad, the protesters replied with stones and empty bottles. The King is alleged to have been 12km away.

On June 17, youth groups and activists will protest calling on greater reforms,&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.ammonnews.net/article.aspx?articleNO=12429 &quot;Karak Gears Up For Friday Pro-Reform Protest&quot;], Ammon News. June 16, 2011. Accessed June 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; which the kingdom has dismissed for 2-3 years, including the election of a prime minister and cabinet.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/feeds/ap/2011/06/14/general-ml-jordan_8515540.html &quot;Jordan's king: Elected PM in 2-3 years&quot;], Forbes. June 14, 2011. Accessed June 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

A rare outbreak of violence marred protests in Amman on 15 July, with police beating journalists and protesters alike. The [[Law enforcement in Jordan|Public Security Directorate]] offered a mixed response, accepting full responsibility for the violence and promising compensation to journalists who suffered injuries or damage to equipment, but blaming demonstrators for instigating hostilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;liesbeneath&quot;/&gt;

On 16 July, a more peaceful demonstration took place.&lt;ref name=&quot;liesbeneath&quot;/&gt;

An [[Al Jazeera]] correspondent covering a protest on 20 July had a mixed reaction to the way security forces handled the situation, noting that while police and gendarmes respected all attendees' [[freedom of speech]] and acted quickly and effectively to prevent clashes between pro-reform demonstrators and government supporters, police also did nothing to prevent verbal harassment and intimidation of the former group by vocal loyalists.&lt;ref name=&quot;liesbeneath&quot;/&gt;

In Amman, on July 29, around 3,000 Muslim Brotherhood activists at the demonstration raised their right hand and took an oath to continue peaceful protests until their demands for political reform in the kingdom are met.

On Sunday, Aug. 14, clashes erupted between government loyalists and pro-reform demonstrators in a street protest in Karak after midnight.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.timesunion.com/world/slideshow/Protests-in-Jordan-2956.php#photo-1103960&lt;/ref&gt;

After a lull in September, protests started again on 7 October, when former prime minister [[Ahmad Obeidat]] led over 2000 people in a march outside the Grand Husseini Mosque in central Amman. There were also marches in the cities of Karka, Tafileh, Maan, Jerash and Salt.&lt;ref&gt;http://arabnews.com/middleeast/article513447.ece&lt;/ref&gt;

There was a further march on October 15, as part of the global &quot;Occupy&quot; movement, which was held in the northern city of Salhub, which is located 50 kilometers (32 miles) from the Jordanian capital Amman. A counter-protest attacked the marchers, hurling stones and firing their guns into the air. At least 35 people were injured and 27 cars damaged in the incident.&lt;ref&gt;http://presstv.com/detail/204802.html&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, a memorandum signed by 70 out of 120 lawmakers was presented to the royal palace demanding that the prime minister and the cabinet be sacked.&lt;ref&gt;http://presstv.com/detail/205026.html&lt;/ref&gt; Much to the surprise of the opposition in the country, the king almost immediately complied, naming [[Awn Shawkat Al-Khasawneh]] to head the new government the next day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/10/20111017113326931126.html|agency=Al Jazeera English|date=17 October 2011|accessdate=17 October 2011|title=Jordan's king 'appoints new prime minister'}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Response==
===Domestic response===
[[Image:King Abdullah portrait.jpg|thumb|150px| King Abdullah II]]
{{See also|Cabinet of Jordan}}
On February 1, the Royal Palace announced that King Abdullah II has sacked the government as a consequence of the street protests and has asked [[Marouf al-Bakhit]], an ex-army general, to form a new cabinet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| last=
| first=
| url=  http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5i7CT0mQSAPfDG6qfNW8mDM7KBNpw?docId=5820261
| title=  Jordan's Royal Palace says king sacks government in wake of street protests
| agency=  Associated Press
| date=1 February 2011
| accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Abdullah told al-Bakhit his authority will be to &quot;take quick, concrete and practical steps to launch a genuine political reform process,&quot;. The reforms should put Jordan on the path &quot;to strengthen democracy,&quot; and provide Jordanians with the &quot;dignified life they deserve,&quot; the monarch said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Derhally |first=Massoud A |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-01/jordan-s-prime-minister-rifai-resigns-king-asks-bakhit-to-form-government.html |title=Jordan's King Abdullah Replaces Prime Minister |publisher=Bloomberg.com |date=|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also asked al-Bakhit for a &quot;comprehensive assessment ... to correct the mistakes of the past.&quot; and also the statement said Abdullah demanded an &quot;immediate revision&quot; of laws governing politics and public freedoms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://apnews.myway.com//article/20110201/D9L410G00.html |title=Jordan's king fires Cabinet amid protests |publisher=Apnews.myway.com |date=|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Bakhit stated that opposition groups, both Islamist and leftists, might possibly be included in the new government,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jkLFQ_FU6PiCgV7Rd8901exF7BsA?docId=CNG.4bf1d9b99ad76d5eb936170dbf8befbe.1c1|title=Jordan Islamists say talks with king 'positive'}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the [[Islamic Action Front]] immediately rejected that offer, stating that the current political conditions did not allow for them to join the government and that they were looking for real reform.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoogleHostedNewsPoliticalReforms&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5ghUWNyMXTgpARYoetwsBBBjteIwg?docId=5843256|title=Jordan's king says political reforms have stumbled, asks Muslim opposition to back government}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite calls to stay away from the new government, the Islamic Action Front and five leftists were represented in a new government sworn in on 10 February.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gavlak |first=Dale |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12415405 |title=Jordan's king swears in new cabinet after protests |publisher=BBC News |date=10 February 2001 |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There have also been talks of reforming electoral law to reduce gerrymandering in constituency boundaries and guarantee greater proportionality.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jordantimes.com/?news=34148|title=New elections law might adopt party list system}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Taher Odwan, formerly editor-in-chief of Al Arab Al Yawm, a Jordanian newspaper that was critical towards the government, has been appointed Minister of Media Affairs and Communications.  Odwan pledged enhanced press freedoms and access to information.&lt;ref name=&quot;JordanTimesPressFreedom&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Hani |last=Hazaimeh |url=http://www.jordantimes.com/?news=34409 |title=Minister pledges more press freedom, access to information |publisher=Jordan Times |date=11 February 2011 |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A $500m package of price cuts in fuel and staples, including sugar and rice, was announced, along with salary increases for civil servants and the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/201121210345525985.html |title=Middle East rulers make concessions |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=12 February 2011 |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 February, following Egyptian President [[Hosni Mubarak]]'s resignation, the Muslim Brotherhood stated that &quot;Arab regimes should learn a lesson from what has happened [in Egypt].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;AJE11&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=World reacts as Mubarak steps down |author=[[Al-Jazeera English]] |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/2011211162849852442.html |newspaper= |date=11 February 2011 |accessdate=23 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 February, the Public Gatherings Law was reformed to allow unrestricted freedom of expression; the former law required permission from the governor to hold demonstrations.  A reform of the electoral law was also promised.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nzz.ch/nachrichten/politik/international/jordanien_lockert_demonstrationsrecht_1.9542882.html |title={{lang|de |Jordanien lockert Demonstrationsrecht}} |newspaper=[[Neue Zürcher Zeitung]] |date=15 February 2011 |accessdate=19 February 2011}} {{de icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 March, King Abdullah II said a 53-member committee with government officials and opposition leaders will draft new laws for parliamentary elections and political parties, setting a three-month deadline for agreement on political reforms. However, the Muslim Brotherhood said it would not take part unless parliament is dissolved and a prime minister is elected from a parliamentary majority.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan’s king sets 3-month deadline for political reforms |author=[[Washington Post]] |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/jordans-king-sets-3-month-deadline-for-political-reforms/2011/03/15/ABTC7wW_story.html |newspaper= |date=15 March 2011 |accessdate=23 March 2011 |work=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 March, three days after deadly clashes between protesters and supporters of the king, King Abdullah II called for national unity, telling his citizens to avoid &quot;any behaviour or attitude that would affect our unity.&quot; He went on to state that economic and political reforms were on their way. However, the Parliament rejected calls to reduce the king's power.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan's king calls for national unity |author=[[Al Jazeera]] |url= http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/2011327203224334931.html |newspaper= |date=27 March 2011 |accessdate=27 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a response to the same violent clashes, 15 members of the government-appointed committee for national dialogue quit, effectively suspending its activity, although 12 of them retracted their resignations following a meeting with the king. The government decided to ban its supporters from demonstrating in the capital, while the opposition was allowed to demonstrate in specially designated areas in Amman.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJJordan1Apr&quot;/&gt;

On 12 June, in a television speech commemorating 12 years on the throne, the king said he will relinquish his right to appoint
prime ministers and cabinets, instead, elected parliamentary majority will be the ones to form future cabinets. He also said that more reforms would be announced in the future, including new election and political party laws.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Jordan's King Abdullah vows to allow elected cabinets |author=[[BBC]] |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13744640 |newspaper= |date=12 June 2011 |accessdate=13 June 2011 |work=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

PM al-Bakhit resigned on 17 October 2011, after 70 of 120 MPs had called for his resignation for failing to swiftly implement the political reform package. [[Awn al-Khasawneh]] was seen as the most likely candidate to replace him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle-east/official-jordan-pm-resigns-in-the-wake-of-parliamentary-calls-for-his-ouster/2011/10/17/gIQAdnP2qL_story.html | deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=November 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International response===
{{flagicon|US}} The [[United States]] said that it had hopes Jordan would enact reform to stave off similar protests to that of [[2011 Egyptian protests|Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/02/03/AR2011020300546.html|title=US Officials: US-Egypt discuss Mubarak quitting | work=The Washington Post}} {{Dead link|date=April 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- use cite tags like the one below to cite sources.
&lt;ref name=&quot;&quot;&gt; {{cite news
| last=
| first=
| url=
| title=
| publisher=
| date=
| accessdate=}} &lt;/ref&gt;

remove this comment tag when using.  be sure to fill in the name field with a unique name. --&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal box|Jordan|Human rights}}
* [[Adwan Rebellion]]
* [[Black September in Jordan]]
* [[Democracy in the Middle East]]
* [[Food riot]]
* [[Government of Jordan]]
*[[Freedom in the World]]
*[[List of freedom indices]]
{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==

{{Arab Spring}}
{{Anti-government protests in the 21st century}}
{{Jordan topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2011 Jordanian Protests}}
[[Category:Nonviolent revolutions]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in Jordan]]
[[Category:Arab Spring by country|Jordan]]
[[Category:2011 in Jordan|Protests]]
[[Category:2011 riots|Jordanian protests]]
[[Category:Battles and conflicts without fatalities]]
[[Category:2011 protests|Jordanian]]

[[ar:الاحتجاجات الأردنية 2011]]
[[az:2011-ci il İordaniya iğtişaşları]]
[[bg:Йордански протести (2011)]]
[[de:Arabischer Frühling#Jordanien]]
[[es:Protestas en Jordania en 2011]]
[[fa:اعتراضات در اردن (۲۰۱۱)]]
[[fr:Protestations jordaniennes de 2011]]
[[it:Proteste in Giordania del 2011]]
[[he:ההפגנות בירדן (2011)]]
[[hu:2011-es jordániai tüntetések]]
[[pl:Protesty w Jordanii (2011)]]
[[pt:Protestos na Jordânia em 2011]]
[[ru:Волнения в Иордании (2011)]]
[[sv:Protesterna i Jordanien 2011]]
[[tr:2011 Ürdün protestoları]]
[[uk:Протести в Йорданії (2011)]]
[[vi:Biểu tình Jordan 2011]]
[[zh:2011年約旦反政府示威]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
