<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30700379" ns="0" title="International reactions to the 2011 Egyptian revolution"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the international reactions to the 2011 Egyptian protests|the domestic responses|Domestic responses to the 2011 Egyptian revolution}}
{{Cleanup|date=June 2011}}
{{Use British English|date=April 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2011}}

'''International reactions to the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]]''' refer to external responses to the events that took place in Egypt between 25 January and 10 February 2011, as well as some of the events after the collapse of the government of [[President of Egypt|Egyptian President]] [[Hosni Mubarak]], such as Mubarak's trial. The reactions have generally been either measured or supportive of the [[Egyptian people]], with most governments and organisations calling for non-violent responses on both sides and peaceful moves towards reform. Whilst the protesters called for Mubarak to step down immediately,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Al-Shalchi, Hadeel; El Deeb, Sarah|title=Mubarak Says He Will Not Seek Re-Election|url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2011/feb/1/massive-crowds-across-egypt-demand-mubaraks-ouster/?page=|accessdate=2 February 2011|publisher=''[[Associated Press]]'' (via ''[[The Washington Times]]'')|date=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; most foreign governments stopped short of this demand, at least during the early phases of the protests, due to [[realpolitik]] concerns about the consequences of a power vacuum on the stability of [[Egypt]] specifically and to the wider [[Middle East]] as a whole. Some Middle Eastern leaders expressed support for Mubarak. Meanwhile many governments issued [[travel advisory|travel advisories]] and evacuated their citizens from the country.

The protests captured worldwide attention in part due to the increasing use of [[Twitter]], [[Facebook]], [[YouTube]], and other [[social media|social-media]] platforms, which empowered activists and onlookers to communicate, coordinate, and document the events as they occur. Many countries experienced their own solidarity protests in support of the Egyptians. As the levels of meta-publicity increased, the Egyptian government stepped up [[Domestic responses to the 2011 Egyptian protests#Media censorship and circumvention|efforts to limit Internet access]], especially to social media. In response there has been [[hacktivism]], with global groups attempting to provide alternative communication methods for the Egyptians.

==Supranational bodies==
* [[File:Flag African Union.svg|border|25px]][[African Union]] (AU)&amp;nbsp;– The African Union urged Mubarak to respond to the mass protests with reforms. AU Peace and Security Commissioner [[Ramtane Lamamra]] called on Mubarak to bring in reforms in response to the unrest. &quot;We believe that there are changes that are necessary in order to respond to the wishes of the people, economic reforms, social measures,and probably also issues related to the governement that need to be addressed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jHuPin2AkxVSPT6qEgxgyjwPYj0w?docId=CNG.bc937a1a30aafcea92c02296ce113ff6.5d1|title=African Union Urges Egypt Reforms|publisher=''[[Agence France-Presse]]'' (via ''[[Google News]]'')|last= Vesperini|first= Helen|date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Arab League}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Amr Moussa]], the head of the Arab League, said he wanted to see a multi-party democracy emerge but did not say how soon. Speaking to the [[BBC]]'s ''[[The World This Weekend]]'', the former Egyptian Foreign Minister said that Mubarak needed to respond to the protests with actual reform, rather than just reshuffling ministers. &quot;This new government should be just the beginning, just a new prime minister and new ministers does not necessarily mean a change, clear lines of policy will have to be declared.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Weir, Keith|url=http://af.reuters.com/article/egyptNews/idAFLDE70T0B620110130?sp=true|title=Arab League Head Wants Egypt Multi-Party Democracy|work=[[Reuters]]|date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|European Union}}&amp;nbsp;– The European Union's foreign policy chief [[Catherine Ashton]] said Egyptian authorities should listen to their people, deal with their problems, and respect their right to demonstrate. She urged the &quot;Egyptian authorities to respect and to protect the right of Egyptian citizens to manifest their political aspirations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AP Protesters Clash&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Hendawi, Hamza; Michael, Maggie|url=http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/M/ML_EGYPT_PROTEST?SITE=DCTMS&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT|title=Egypt Protesters Clash for 2nd Day with Police|work=Associated Press|date=31 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|United Nations}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|UN Secretary-General]] [[Ban Ki-moon]] said that world leaders should see the Egyptian protests as a chance to address &quot;legitimate concerns&quot; of the Egyptian people. He urged local authorities to refrain from violence. The [[High Commissioner for Human Rights]] [[Navi Pillay]] said that most of the frustration and angst has been caused by the emergency laws and urged the government to allow access to the Internet and mobile services. She said measures should be taken to guarantee rights of peaceful assembly and expression.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.presstv.ir/detail/162435.html |title=UN Warns Egypt of Rights Violations |work=[[Press TV]] |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Middle East==
* {{flag|Iran}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Supreme Leader of Iran|Iranian Supreme Leader]] [[Ayatollah Sayyed Ali Khamenei]], calling himself &quot;your brother in religion&quot; on 4 February, said that the unrest in Egypt was an &quot;explosion of sacred anger&quot; and an &quot;Islamic awakening.&quot; He called Mubarak a &quot;traitor dictator&quot; who committed a &quot;great betrayal&quot; of his people by cooperating with Israel and the United States. Khamenei told Egyptians, &quot;Do not believe in the game which is being played by the West and America; don't believe in their role, don't believe in their political manoeuvres which are taking place in the midst of your awakening. Just a few day ago...the Americans were supporting the corrupt regime, and now after they are sick of preserving him, they are speaking about the rights of the people. They are trying to replace one spy with another...Look with doubt&amp;nbsp;– always be suspicious&amp;nbsp;– regarding the American role and American intervention.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Khamenei&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.csmonitor.com/layout/set/print/content/view/print/361116|work=[[The Christian Science Monitor]]|title=Iran's Khamenei Praises Egyptian Protesters, Declares 'Islamic Awakening'&amp;nbsp;– Ayatollah Sayyed Ali Khamenei, Iran's Supreme Religious Leader, Addressed Egypt's Protesters in Arabic on Friday, Calling President Mubarak a 'Traitor Dictator' Who Has Betrayed Egyptians|author=Peterson, Scott|date=4 February 2011|accessdate=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He added that &quot;America's control over Egypt's leaders has...turned Egypt into the biggest enemy of Palestine and turned it into the greatest refuge for Zionists. This explosion we see among the people of Egypt is the appropriate response to this great betrayal that the traitor dictator committed against his people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | date=4 February 2011
 | url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/02/04/world/main7317510.shtml
 | title=Iran Leader: &quot;Traitor&quot; Mubarak Betrayed Egypt&amp;nbsp;– Ayatollah Ali Khamenei Calls Uprising Against &quot;Dictator&quot; Appropriate, Compares Unrest to 1979 Iranian Revolution
 | publisher=[[CBS News]]
 | accessdate=5 February 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 February, protesters in Cairo's Tahrir Square accused Iran of interfering in Egyptian affairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/311143 |title=Thousands flock to Tahrir to honor protests' martyrs &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date= |accessdate=8 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: [[Foreign Affairs Minister of Iran|Iranian Foreign Minister]] [[Ali Akbar Salehi]] hoped that the Egyptians' &quot;high aims, national demands and resurrection of their glory could be achieved in the very near future.&quot; [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Iran)|Iranian Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] spokesman [[Ramin Mehmanparast]] called on Egypt to &quot;abide by the rightful demands of the nation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|title=Egypt Protests Draw Mixed Reaction in Region|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/01/29/egypt.middle.east.reaction/|work=[[CNN]]|date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were &quot;solidarity&quot; protests outside the Egyptian interests section.{{clarify|date=January 2011}}&lt;!--which embassy?--&gt;
*: [[Islamic Consultative Assembly (Iran)|Iranian parliament speaker]] [[Ali Larijani]] said, &quot;The voice of the brave people of Egypt is the voice of revolution. The start of this revolution has astonished the despotic regimes of the region. The parliament supports the uprising of the Tunisian and Egyptian people.&quot; He described the protests as &quot;the revolution of the noble.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;pakistantoday1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Name * |url=http://www.pakistantoday.com.pk/2011/01/iran-backs-egypts-revolution-of-the-noble/ |title=Iran backs Egypt's 'revolution of the noble' &amp;#124; Pakistan Today &amp;#124; Latest news, Breaking news, Pakistan News, World news, business, sport and multimedia |publisher=Pakistan Today |date=2011-01-30 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iran backed the protests. Parliament speaker [[Ali Larijani]] called the uprising the &quot;revolution of the noble&quot;. He compared Western reaction to the protests with their reaction to the 1979 [[Islamic Revolution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pakistantoday1&quot;/&gt;
** [[Mir Hossein Mousavi]] and [[Mehdi Karroubi]], former presidential candidates and the leaders of the [[Iranian Green Movement|Green Movement]], released a statement from their virtual [[house arrest]] in Tehran, assuring the Egyptians, &quot;No power can suppress the people's will and demand. Sooner or later, autocratic and tyrant power[s] are sentenced to vanish.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Khamenei&quot;/&gt;
* {{flag|Iraq}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Nouri al-Maliki]] stated, &quot;The people have the right to express what they want without being persecuted... One of the characteristics of a lack of democracy is when a leader rules for 30 or 40 years. It is a difficult issue for people, it is intolerable and change is necessary.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12373767
 | title=Iraq PM Nouri Maliki 'will not seek third term'
 | publisher=BBC News
 | date=5 February 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: The Iraqi Foreign Ministry wished Egypt and its citizens &quot;progress and prosperity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mofairaq&quot;/&gt;
* {{flag|Israel}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Shimon Peres]] said Mubarak's &quot;contribution to peace will never be forgotten. I thank him for saving many people's lives by preventing war. The biggest problem isn't changing the government but changing the face of a country as poor as Egypt.&quot; He added concerns about the Muslim Brotherhood: &quot;Elections in Egypt are dangerous. Should the Muslim Brotherhood be elected they will not bring peace. Democracy without peace is not a democracy. We fear there will be a change in government without a change in the circumstances which led to this state.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Efraim, Omri (5 February 2011). [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4024283,00.html &quot;Peres Praises Mubarak for His Contribution to Peace&amp;nbsp;– In Jerusalem Conference President thanks His Egyptian Counterpart for 'Saving Many People's Lives by Preventing War'; Expresses Concern over Possibility of Muslim Brotherhood's Rise to Power&quot;]. ''[[Ynetnews]]''. Retrieved 6 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*: [[Prime Minister of Israel|Israeli Prime Minister]] [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] and the Israeli Foreign Ministry announced on 28 January that they are keeping a close track of the situation in neighbouring Egypt, but are refraining from taking a political stance. Ministers were told to refrain from commenting&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;&gt;Vick, Karl (30 January 2011). [http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2045166,00.html &quot;As Egypt's Crisis Grows, So Do the Anxieties in Israel&quot;]. ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]''. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; due to the sensitive nature of [[Egypt-Israel relations|relations]].
*: Foreign Minister [[Avigdor Lieberman]] told European diplomats at the [[Knesset]] that the root cause of the unrest was internal problems. &quot;Whoever thinks that the Palestinian-Israeli conflict is part of the problems in the Middle East is trying to escape reality. [The] big picture of the Middle East shows that major points of contention stem from challenges and confrontations within Islamic society. The Arab world is becoming increasingly weakened. At the end of the day, it is clear to everyone, even to the [[Palestinian Authority]], that the greatest danger they are facing is not Zionism, but rather Hamas and Jihad.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lis |first=Jonathan |url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/lieberman-mideast-uprisings-show-the-arab-world-is-weakening-1.341859 |title=Lieberman: Mideast uprisings show the Arab world is weakening&amp;nbsp;– Haaretz Daily Newspaper &amp;#124; Israel News |publisher=Haaretz.com |date=7 November 2010 |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the early days of the protests, the Foreign Ministry was receiving updates every few hours and Lieberman was in close contact with the Israeli ambassador to Egypt, Yitzhak Levanon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ravid, Barak (with news agencies)|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/pm-netanyahu-israel-will-monitor-but-not-comment-on-egypt-protests-1.339895 |title=PM Netanyahu: Israel Will Monitor But Not Comment on Egypt Protests&amp;nbsp;– The Foreign Ministry Is Conducting Status Updates on Egypt Every Couple of Hours and Foreign Minister Avigdor Lieberman Has Been Maintaining Close Contact with Israel's Ambassador to Egypt|work=[[Haaretz]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Ministry was concerned over &quot;substantial&quot; changes in the regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;israel evacuation&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.qassam.ps/news-4112-Israel_expresses_concern_as_protesters_continued.html |title=Israel Expresses Concern as Protesters Continued |publisher=[[Izz ad-Din al-Qassam Brigades]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Associated Press]] reported that security officials anonymously expressed concern that the violence could threaten ties with Egypt, and spread to the [[Palestinian Authority]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Federman |first=Josef |url=http://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2011/jan/29/israel-watches-egypt-uprising-fear/ |title=Israel watches Egypt uprising with fear |publisher=Washington Times |date=2011-01-29 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government was said to be pressuring the US to postpone a plan for Mubarak's departure so that it could prepare for any likely outcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloombergreactions&quot;/&gt;
** [[Binyamin Ben-Eliezer]], a [[Labor Party of Israel|Labor]] member of the Knesset (MK), said that &quot;all we can do is express our&quot; support for Mubarak and hope the riots pass quietly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|title=Ben-Eliezer: All We Can Do Is Express Support for Mubarak |url=http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=205362 |work=[[The Jerusalem Post]] |date=26 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said Mubarak &quot;had very tough things to say about the United States. [Mubarak] gave me a lesson in democracy and said: 'We see the democracy the United States spearheaded in Iran and with Hamas, in Gaza, and that's the fate of the Middle East. They may be talking about democracy but they don't know what they're talking about and the result will be extremism and radical Islam.'&quot; According to him Mubarak realised &quot;it was the end of the Mubarak era.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/02/11/us-egypt-israel-mubarak-idUSTRE71A64V20110211 |title=Mubarak slammed U.S. in phone call with Israeli lawmaker |publisher=Reuters |date=9 February 2009 |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** MK [[Ibrahim Sarsur]], who leads the [[United Arab List]], expressed &quot;full support for the protesters in Egypt. The Arab [[police state]]s have given their peoples no other option but to take to the streets for a people’s revolution to topple the suppressing regimes and to free themselves from the control of dictators.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Gedalyahu, Tzvi Ben|title=Israeli Arab MK Joins Iran and Jordan Islamists To Back Protests|url=http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/142014|work=[[Arutz Sheva]]|date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Former ambassador to Egypt Eli Shaked said that &quot;there can be no doubt that the new regime will seek to deal the peace with Israel a very public blow. The only people in Egypt who are committed to peace are the people in Mubarak's inner circle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;time&quot;/&gt;
* {{flag|Jordan}}&amp;nbsp;– Jordan's King [[Abdullah II]] &quot;wished the brotherly country of Egypt security, stability and progress.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/international/obama-future-egypt-gov-t-must-respect-the-will-of-the-people-1.340220 |title=Obama: Future Egypt Gov't Must Respect the Will of the People&amp;nbsp;– U.S. President Reiterates Importance of Universal Rights in Phone Conversations with Netanyahu, Turkey PM Erdogan, Jordan's Abdullah, and UK Premier Cameron |work=[[Haaretz]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/2011211162849852442.html World reacts as Mubarak steps down] ''[[Al-Jazeera English]]''. 11 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Kuwait}}&amp;nbsp;– Kuwait's Emir [[Sabah Al-Ahmad Al-Jaber Al-Sabah]] condemned the riots and affirmed Kuwait 's support to the Egyptian government and people. In a phone call to Mubarak, Sheikh Sabah expressed the State of Kuwait's condemnation of all acts of &quot;riots, looting and sabotage&quot; that terrified the citizens and undermined the security and stability of Egypt. Sheikh Sabah said he was confident the &quot;Egyptian brothers&quot; would overcome this &quot;critical&quot; phase to reach security and stability.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.da.gov.kw/eng/newsroom/latestNews.php#4264 |title=Welcome to the official website of Al-Diwan Al-Amiri |publisher=Da.gov.kw |date=26 January 2011 |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Lebanon}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Hezbollah]] [[Secretary-General]] [[Hassan Nasrallah]] said he supports the rights of the protesters, while he condemned external influences.{{citation needed|date=February 2011}} He praised the  struggle, saying victory would &quot;entirely change the face of our region for the interest of its own people, especially in Palestine. The US came to bring down this regime, which was a faithful friend in ensuring US interests. If we listen to the Americans from both parties&amp;nbsp;– [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrats]] and [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]]&amp;nbsp;– does it make sense that the US would try to bring down [Mubarak] as we saw in the [[Islamic revolution|1979 revolution]] in Iran? The Americans are riding the wave, trying to contain the uprising while attempting to improve their loathsome image in our world and present themselves as protectors of nations and their freedoms after decades where they got into bed with the worst dictators in the region. The US government carried out surveys in our region in order to see what people think, what they want and what they don't want. The answers were clear. The overwhelming majority is hostile towards the US policy and rejects it for its absolute slant towards Israel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4025270,00.html |title=Nasrallah: Egypt win to change region&amp;nbsp;– Israel News, Ynetnews |publisher=Ynetnews.com |date=20 June 1995 |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He called out Israel for &quot;putting pressure on every political circle in the world to protect Mubarak's regime&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presstv.ir/detail/164239.html |title=PressTV&amp;nbsp;– Nasrallah exposes Israel's Egypt plot |publisher=Presstv.ir |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and stated that the &quot;protests will push out [the] regime that has maintained peace with Israel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wertheimer |first=Stef |url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=207203 |title=Nasrallah: Unrest in Egypt will transform Middle East |publisher=Jpost.com |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; His comments were rebuked by the Egyptian Foreign Ministry, which said that he is &quot;walking in the footsteps of his mentor&quot;, a reference to Khameini. It accused both leaders of wanting &quot;to ignite the region.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wertheimer |first=Stef |url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=207456 |title=Egypt: Hizbullah and Iran want to 'ignite the region' |publisher=Jpost.com |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Libyan Arab Jamahiriya}}&amp;nbsp;– [[List of heads of state of Libya|Libyan Leader]] [[Muammar al-Gaddafi]], during a telephone conversation with Mubarak, expressed confidence in the stability of Egyptian society and preserving the gains Egypt has achieved. He expressed his wishes for the completion of Egypt's march towards the greater good and progress for its people and to continue its central role in the defence of issues of the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;&gt;{{Clarify|date=January 2011|reason=needs byline (or in absence of byline &quot;staff writer&quot; dropped into &quot;author&quot; field).}} {{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/D3BDB84E-3148-4B5E-B813-69667F22A4F3.htm|title=دعم عالمي لحق التظاهر بمصر|trans_title=''Global Support for Right To Protest in Egypt''|language=[[Arabic language|Arabic]]|author=|date=27 January 2011|work=[[Al Jazeera]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 July, months after the revolution and amidst a widespread [[2011 Libyan civil war|uprising]] in his own country, Gaddafi criticized the revolutionaries in an audio address: &quot;After you looted, destroyed and damaged the country, you want a new president?&quot; He said Mubarak &quot;should be honored&quot; and that he should not have been removed from power and suggested the revolution was meaningless.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://af.reuters.com/article/topNews/idAFJOE76N01D20110724|date=24 July 2011|accessdate=24 July 2011|title=Gaddafi criticises Egyptian, Tunisian revolutions|agency=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Palestine}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Palestinian National Authority]] President [[Mahmoud Abbas]] telephoned Mubarak to express his support.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=205766|title=Abbas Calls Mubarak To Express Support|author=Toameh, Khaled Abu|date=29 January 2011|work=[[The Jerusalem Post]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[Hamas]] said the border with Egypt was calm. The border was closed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | date=30 January 2011
 | url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/Gaza-shuts-border-with-Egypt-as-unrest-spirals/Article1-656399.aspx
 | title=Gaza Shuts Border with Egypt as Unrest Spirals
 | publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] (via [[Hindustan Times]])
 | accessdate=31 January 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*** The Gaza-Egypt [[Rafah]] border crossing was also closed during the protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | author=[[Staff writer]]
 | date=2 February 2011
 | url=http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/middle-east-north-africa/egypt/
 | title=Middle East and North Africa&amp;nbsp;– Egypt
 | publisher=[[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]]
 | accessdate=2 February 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 February continuing protests in Egypt threatened the supply of petrol into the [[Gaza strip]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/video/middleeast/2011/02/201129133520872347.html |title=Egypt events spark Gaza fuel panic&amp;nbsp;– Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** The [[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] (PFLP) declared its solidarity with the protesters and called for [[social revolution|social]] and [[political revolution]] in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.pflp.ps/english/?q=comrade-maqdesi-salutes-egyptian-people-and-their- |title=Comrade Maqdesi Salutes the Egyptian People and Their Struggle|publisher=[[Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine]] |date=undated |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Saudi Arabia}}&amp;nbsp;– [[King of Saudi Arabia|Saudi King]] [[Abdullah of Saudi Arabia|Abdullah Bin Abdul-Aziz]] expressed support for Mubarak. &quot;No Arab or Muslim can tolerate any meddling in the security and stability of Arab and Muslim Egypt by those who infiltrated the people in the name of freedom of expression, exploiting it to inject their destructive hatred. As they condemn this, the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and its people and government declares it stands with all its resources with the government of Egypt and its people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Aboudi, Sami; Fuchsurl, Martina|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/01/29/egypt-saudi-idAFLDE70S08V20110129 |title=Update 1&amp;nbsp;– Saudi King Expresses Support for Mubarak |work=[[Reuters]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He condemned the &quot;people who tried to destabilise the security and stability of Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Clarify|date=January 2011|reason=needs byline (or in absence of byline &quot;staff writer&quot; dropped into the &quot;author&quot; field).}} {{cite news|url=http://arabic.cnn.com/2011/egypt.2011/1/29/arab.egypt_rex/index.html|title=العاهل السعودي&quot; يدعم مبارك ويدين &quot;المندسين|trans_title=''Saudi King Shows His Support for Mubarak, Condemns 'the Infiltrators'&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;''|language=[[Arabic language|Arabic]]|author=|date=29 January 2011|work=[[CNN]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Americas==
* {{flag|Brazil}}&amp;nbsp;– On 31 January [[President of Brazil|President]] [[Dilma Rousseff]] said, &quot;[Brazil] hopes that Egypt becomes a democracy, leading its people to benefit from [Egyptian] development.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in portuguese. at minimum, needs english translation of headline appended in &quot;[ ]&quot; next to porteugese headline }} [[Staff writer]] (31 January 2011). [http://noticias.uol.com.br/ultimas-noticias/internacional/2011/01/31/brasil-torce-para-que-egito-seja-um-pais-democratico-diz-dilma.jhtm &quot;Brasil torce para que Egito seja um país democrático, diz Dilma&quot;] (in [[Portuguese language|Portguese]]). ''[[Universo Online|UOL Notícias]]''. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*: The [[Ministry of External Relations (Brazil)|Ministry of External Relations]] issued a statement on 1 February calling for a &quot;political evolution that meets the expectations of their people in a peaceful environment, bereft of foreign interference, so as to foster the ongoing economic and social development&quot; and pointed out that &quot;Egypt is an important [[Mercosur]] partner&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;MRE&quot;&gt;{{cite press release
 | date=28 January 2011
 | url=http://www.itamaraty.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/notas-a-imprensa/situacao-no-egito-na-tunisia-e-no-iemen
 | title=Situation in Egypt, Tunisia and Yemen
 | publisher=[[Ministry of External Relations (Brazil)|Brazilian Ministry of External Relations]]
 | accessdate= 3 February 2011
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The arrest of two Brazilian journalists in Cairo on 2 February prompted the Ministry of External Relations to raise its tone in remarks about the political crisis in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.estadao.com.br/noticias/internacional,apos-prisao-de-jornalistas-no-egito-itamaraty-eleva-tom,674951,0.htm |title=Após prisão de jornalistas no Egito, Itamaraty eleva tom (&quot;After the Arrest of Journalists in Egypt, Foreign Ministry Raises Tone&quot;) (in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]) |publisher=Estadao.com.br |date= |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; it &quot;deplore[d] the violent clashes [and] denounce[d] the arrests of Brazilian journalists Corban Costa, from [[Rádio Nacional]], and Gilvan Rocha, from [[TV Brasil]], and expects that Egyptian authorities take the appropriate measures to uphold the civil liberties and to protect the population at large and the foreigners on the ground from bodily harm.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Press release]] (3 February 2011). [http://www.itamaraty.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/notas-a-imprensa/situacao-no-egito-1 &quot;Situation in Egypt&quot;]. [[Ministry of External Relations (Brazil)|Brazilian Ministry of External Relations]]. Retrieved 3 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Obama calls Mubarak Oval Office Jan 2011.jpg|thumb|U.S. President [[Barack Obama]] speaks on the phone with Mubarak during the protests]]
{{quote box|width=216px|quote=&quot;Violence will not address the grievances of the Egyptian people, and suppressing ideas never succeeds in making them go away.... Around the world governments have an obligation to respond to their citizens.... All governments must maintain power through consent, not coercion. That is the single standard by which the people of Egypt will achieve the future they deserve.&quot;|source=— Barack Obama&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2011-01-29-obama-egypt_N.htm |title=Obama admonishes Egypt's Mubarak on protests |publisher=Usatoday.Com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20110129/ap_on_re_us/us_us_egypt |title=Obama calls for restraint, reform in Egypt&amp;nbsp;— Yahoo! News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date= |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid=88942&amp;st=&amp;st1=|title=Remarks on the Situation in Egypt|publisher=John T. Woolley and Gerhard Peters, The American Presidency Project [online]|date=28 January 2011|accessdate= 29 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
* {{flag|Canada}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Canadian Foreign Affairs Minister]] [[Lawrence Cannon]] said that Egypt remains an [[Canada-Egypt relations|important partner]] for Canada and urged &quot;the Egyptian government to ensure full freedom of political expression for its citizens.&quot; He said the Canadian government &quot;continues to stand by the people of Egypt as they demand democratic reforms and respect for human rights. We urge the Government of Egypt to begin an immediate transition toward serious democratic reform.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(2 February 2011). [http://www.international.gc.ca/media/aff/news-communiques/2011/044.aspx?lang=eng &quot;Minister Cannon Condemns Violence in Egypt&quot;]. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Chile}}&amp;nbsp;– A press release from the [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Chile)|Chilean Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] declared that it is &quot;permanently following the evolution of the events&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in spanish. at minimum, needs english translation of spanish headline appended in &quot;trans_title&quot; field}} {{cite news|title=Egipto: comunicado de prensa de Cancillería|url=http://www.minrel.gov.cl/prontus_minrel/site/artic/20110131/pags/20110131091403.php|trans_title=|language=[[Spanish language|Spanish]]|work=[[MINREL]]|accessdate=29 January 2011|date=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Colombia}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of Colombia|Colombian President]] [[Juan Manuel Santos]] asked Mubarak to ensure the situation returns to normal. He said that &quot;[the Colombian people] moves along with the Egyptian people in search of their welfare, freedom and plain use of their human rights and trusts that Mubarak and his government would promote in a short term the return to calm and the strengthening of the democratic institutions.&quot; He told their embassy to be prepared to assist Colombian citizens in Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in spanish. at minimum, needs english translation of spanish headline appended next to spanish headline}} [[Staff writer]] (31 January 2011). [http://www.eltiempo.com/politica/santos-pide-a-presidente-egipcio-fortalecer-instituciones-democraticas_8809619-4 &quot;Santos pide a presidente egipcio fortalecer instituciones democráticas&quot;] (in [[Spanish language|Spanish]]). ''[[Agence France-Presse]]'' (via ''[[El Tiempo (Colombia)|El Tiempo]]''). Retrieved 1 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Cuba}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (Cuba)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]] [[Bruno Rodríguez Parrilla]] hoped for a positive outcome to the protests as one that &quot;meets the interests of the Egyptian people and nation (''[[sic]]'').&quot;&lt;ref&gt;(3 February 2011). [http://www.cubaminrex.cu/english/Actualidad/2011/enero/Cuba%20rejects.html Cuba Rejects U.S. Meddling in Egypt&quot;]. Foreign Affairs of Cuba. Retrieved 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|United States}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of the United States|US President]] [[Barack Obama]], noting that he had spoken with the Egyptian president, stated that his first concern is preventing injury or loss of life. He remarked, &quot;What's needed right now are concrete steps that advance the rights of the Egyptian people...Ultimately the future of Egypt will be determined by the Egyptian people. The United States will always be a committed partner to that future, with the Egyptian government, and with the Egyptian people.&quot; He recalled that in his [[A New Beginning|speech in Cairo]] in June 2009 he had stated, &quot;All governments must maintain power through consent, not coercion,&quot; and called upon the Egyptian government to restore its people's access to the internet. He called on all parties to refrain from violence in their efforts to bring about a solution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barack Obama&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/blog/2011/jan/28/egypt-protests-live-updates|title=Egypt Protests Live Updates|work=[[The Guardian]]|date=28 January 2011|accessdate= 28 January 2011|location=London|first1=Matthew|last1=Weaver|first2=Haroon|last2=Siddique|first3=Richard|last3=Adams|first4=Tim|last4=Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said that the Egyptian protesters have &quot;universal&quot; rights, including the right to peaceful assembly and association, free speech, and “the ability to determine their own destiny. [...] These are human rights and the United States will stand up for them everywhere.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Johnston |first=Nicholas |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-01-28/obama-says-mubarak-must-take-concrete-steps-to-deliver-pledge-on-reforms.html |title=Obama Tells Mubarak He Must Stick to Pledge of Democratic Reforms in Egypt |publisher=Bloomberg |date= |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; White House spokesman [[Robert Gibbs]] expressed anger at the pace of change in Egypt, saying the transition should happen quickly, which he also said would determine US aid to the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://washingtonexaminer.com/politics/2011/02/us-angered-over-egypt-hopeful-over-yemen-jordan |title=US angered over Egypt, hopeful over Yemen, Jordan &amp;#124; The Associated Press &amp;#124; Politics |publisher=Washington Examiner |date=2011-02-02 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gibbs posted a statement on [[Twitter]] expressing concern &quot;about violence in Egypt&quot;, adding the &quot;government must respect the rights of the Egyptian people &amp; turn on social networking and the internet&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Twitter&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://twitter.com/PressSec/status/31026478648926208|title=Gibbs on Twitter|date=28 January 2011|accessdate= 28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: [[Vice President of the United States|US Vice President]] [[Joseph Biden]] said Hosni Mubarak &quot;has been an ally of ours in a number of things. And he’s been very responsible on, relative to geopolitical interest in the region, the Middle East peace efforts: the actions Egypt has taken relative to normalising relationship with Israel.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Joe Biden&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Murphy|first=Dan|url=http://www.pbs.org/newshour/rundown/2011/01/exclusive-biden-discusses-unrest-in-egypt-keeping-us-competitive.html|title=Exclusive: Biden Discusses Unrest in Egypt, Keeping U.S. Competitive|publisher=[[Public Broadcasting Service]]|date=26 January 2011|accessdate= 28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: [[United States Secretary of State|US Secretary of State]] [[Hillary Clinton]] said, &quot;The Egyptian government has an important opportunity to be responsive to the aspirations of the Egyptian people, and pursue political, economic and social reforms that can improve their lives and help Egypt prosper.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Clinton&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Awad, Marwa; Dziadoszurl, Alexander|url=http://www.publicbroadcasting.net/wrni/news.newsmain/article/0/0/1754229/.World./Egypt's.Mubarak.faces.unprecedented.protests|title=Egypt's Mubarak Faces Unprecedented Protests|publisher=''[[Reuters]]'' (via ''[[WRNI]]'')|date=25 January 2011|accessdate= 31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She told ''Al Jazeera'' that Mubarak has been an ally of the US in the past because he has maintained the [[Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty|peace treaty]] with Israel in maintaining stability.&lt;!--from tv--&gt;{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} She said the US supports an &quot;orderly transition.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/2011130164532649572.html |title=''Al Jazeera'' Undeterred by Egypt Curb&amp;nbsp;– Will Continue Its Comprehensive Coverage of Landmark Events There, Says Network Chief|work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 March Clinton said Egypt's transition to democracy would be incomplete if women were not equal partners with men in creating the new society. She criticised the lack of women involved in efforts to draft a new constitution, saying in part, &quot;The women in Egypt and [[Tunisia]] and other nations have just as much right as the men to remake their governments&amp;nbsp;– to make them responsive, accountable, transparent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/03/08/clinton-women-middle-east-international-womens-day_n_832974.html|date=8 March 2011|accessdate=9 March 2011|agency=The Huffington Post|title=Clinton: Women Must Get Role In Middle East Transition}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: On 26 January [[United States Ambassador to Egypt|US Ambassador to Egypt]] [[Margaret Scobey]] commented, &quot;we call on the Egyptian authorities to allow peaceful public demonstrations&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dan Murphy 0126&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Murphy|first=Dan|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Backchannels/2011/0126/The-US-response-to-Egypt-s-protests|title=The US Response to Egypt's Protests&amp;nbsp;– 'Not Much' Probably Sums It Up Best|work=[[The Christian Science Monitor]]|date=26 January 2011|accessdate= 31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: [[Frank G. Wisner]], a former United States ambassador to Egypt, was appointed{{when|date=February 2011|reason=needs context}} a [[special envoy]] to Egypt during the protests.&lt;ref&gt;Weaver, Michael; Siddique, Haroon; Adams, Richard (31 January 2011). [http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/blog/2011/jan/31/egypt-protests-live-updates &quot;Egypt Protests&amp;nbsp;– Monday 31 January&quot;]. ''News Blog'' of ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 February, he said that it is important for Mubarak stay in power for now in order to ease a transition to democracy. He said the [[constitution of Egypt]] calls for an election to be held within two months of Mubarak's resignation, and implied that this would not be sufficient time for pro-democracy forces to make themselves known to the Egyptian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{registration required|date=February 2011}} [http://www.nytimes.com/aponline/2011/02/05/world/europe/AP-EU-Germany-Security-Conference.html?_r=1&amp;ref=news &quot;US Envoy: Mubarak Has to Lead Egypt to Transition&quot;]. ''[[The New York Times]]''. 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
** [[NASA]] gave Essam Mohamed Haji, a research scientist at the [[Jet Propulsion Laboratory]], permission to write the name of Sally Zahran, who was beaten to death at Tahrir Square, on a spacecraft headed to Mars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/314995 |title=NASA to honor Tahrir Square martyr by putting name on spacecraft &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Venezuela}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of Venezuela|President]] [[Hugo Chavez]] spoke with his Syrian and Libyan counterparts, [[Bashar al-Assad]] and Muammar Gaddafi, about the political crisis. He told them that Venezuela backs a &quot;peaceful solution.&quot; He said he &quot;trust[s] that the situation will find on its own the road to harmony, justice and wellbeing.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (31 January 2011). [http://www.couriermail.com.au/news/world/egyptian-police-clash-with-opposition-protesters-in-cairo/story-e6freoox-1225996446437 &quot;Egypt Protests: 'Change Is Coming'&quot;]. ''[[The Courier-Mail]]''. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Africa==
* {{flag|Nigeria}}&amp;nbsp;– The [[National Conscience Party]] chairman Femi Falana asked Mubarak to resign. &quot;We welcome the unfolding revolution and the demonstration of peoples’ power against bad governance, corruption, poverty, and oppression...We strongly condemn the violence and repression by the Mubarak-led government...Violence against Egyptians should stop. President Mubarak must resign now, and listen to the voices of millions of Egyptians who are demanding a change for a better future. Using excessive force to crackdown on peaceful protests and torturing protesters are grave breaches of international human rights law, and the African Union must publicly condemn the practice. The AU must side with the Egyptian people if it is to show that it is completely different from the defunct Organization of African Unity, whose sole purpose was to defend African dictators and not the African peoples.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= |title= Egypt: Nigeria's National Conscience Party Asks Mubarak To Resign|url= http://www.saharareporters.com/news-page/egypt-nigeria%E2%80%99s-national-conscience-party-asks-mubarak-resign |date= 30 January 2010 |accessdate= 4 February 2010 |publisher=Sahara reporters}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|South Africa}}&amp;nbsp;– On 4 February, the ''[[Mail &amp; Guardian]]'' reported that [[Ayanda Ntsaluba]], the director general of international relations and cooperation, had said that the [[Government of South Africa|South African government]] had called for Mubarak to step down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author= Rossouw, Mandy |title=
SA Calls for Mubarak To Step Down |url= http://www.mg.co.za/article/2011-02-04-sa-calls-for-mubarak-to-step-down |date= 4 February 2011 |accessdate= 4 February 2011 |work=[[Mail &amp; Guardian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Asia==
* {{flag|People's Republic of China}}&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Ministry spokesman Hong Lei stated &quot;Egypt is a friendly country towards China. China follows the situation in Egypt and hopes it will maintain social stability and normal order&quot; at a 27 January press conference.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Transcript (law)|Transcript]]|title=Foreign Ministry Spokesperson Hong Lei's Regular Press Conference on January&amp;nbsp;27, 2011 |url=http://www.fmprc.gov.cn/eng/xwfw/s2510/t790683.htm |publisher=Office of [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China]] |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Al Jazeera'' reported that the Chinese government blocked searches of &quot;Egypt&quot; from its most-popular microblogging website, and restricted coverage of the Egyptian protests in the state media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/asia-pacific/2011/01/201112991712140318.html |title=Egypt Not Trending in China&amp;nbsp;– Beijing Blocks Searches for &quot;Egypt&quot; from Microblogging Site Following Protests There |work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bloggers in China, however, have disproved this.&lt;ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=January 2011|reason=this appears to be user-generated site. is source the underlying article (from al jazeera english)? or comments left on &quot;reddit.com&quot;? surely, mainstream media (al jazeera, nytimes, cnn, the guardian) has reported on this.}} {{cite web|url=http://www.reddit.com/r/worldnews/comments/fba0y/china_blocks_all_information_about_egypt |title=China Blocks All Information about Egypt|publisher=[[Reddit]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Verify credibility|date=January 2011|reason=this appears to be user-generated. what's to stop anyone from anywhere in world to post this? surely this topic was covered in mainstream press (nytimes, cnn, the guardian, al jazeera)?}} {{cite web|url=http://i55.tinypic.com/4kxsp5.png |title=Image of Chinese Search for Egypt |date= |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|India}}&amp;nbsp;– Joint secretary and spokesperson of the [[Ministry of External Affairs (India)|Ministry of External Affairs]] Vishnu Prakash said, &quot;We are closely following with concern the developments in Egypt. India has traditionally enjoyed close and friendly relations with Egypt. We hope for an early and peaceful resolution of the situation without further violence and loss of lives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Govt-airlifts-300-Indians-as-Egypt-crisis-worsens/articleshow/7393868.cms|title=Govt Airlifts 300 Indians as Egypt Crisis Worsens|work=[[The Times of India]]|date=31 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 February the Indian Ministry of External Affairs termed the mass protests in Egypt &quot;an articulation of the aspirations of the Egyptian people for reform&quot; and hoped for a peaceful resolution of the situation &quot;in the best interests of the people of Egypt&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://meaindia.nic.in/mystart.php?id=530217128 |title=MEA&amp;nbsp;– Ministry of External Affairs |publisher=Meaindia.nic.in |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Japan}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Prime Minister of Japan|Japanese Prime Minister]] [[Naoto Kan]] urged Mubarak to start a dialogue with his people. &quot;I hope the regime of Egypt will restore security and peace.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;test&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.directory9.net/egypt-turmoil-shakes-wef-in-davos/ |title=Egypt Turmoil Shakes WEF in Davos |publisher=''[[News Directory]]'' (directory9.net)|date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Foreign Minister [[Seiji Maehara]] urged the Egyptian government to resolve the ongoing political unrest peacefully. &quot;Japan strongly hopes the Egyptian government and the people restrain violent action and create a stable government through dialogue.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/world/20110130/162376166.html].&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Pakistan}}&amp;nbsp;– Pakistan's foreign office spokesman Abdul Basit said that Pakistan is watching events in Egypt closely and is taking steps about the safety of [[Pakistanis in Egypt|700 families in Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|title=We Are Watching Events in Egypt Closely&amp;nbsp;– FO|url=http://www.kalam.tv/ur/video/61756/index.html|work=[[Kalam TV]]|date=undated|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Philippines}}&amp;nbsp;– Philippine Deputy Presidential spokesperson Abigail Valte called for a peaceful end to the strife in Egypt. Valte said the Philippine government was particularly concerned about the safety of the more than 6,500 Filipinos in Egypt. &quot;We hope for a peaceful and just resolution to the political unrest currently taking place and the swift return to stability. We are monitoring the situation and our embassy in Cairo has contingencies in place and is prepared to relocate our citizens to safer areas. As always, the safety of our citizens is the paramount concern and we are doing what we can to anticipate and address their needs.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Bordadora, Norman|url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/nation/view/20110129-317309/Palace-calls-for-peaceful-end-to-strife-in-Egypt |title=Palace Calls for Peaceful End to Strife in Egypt |work=[[Philippine Daily Inquirer]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Sri Lanka}}&amp;nbsp;– On 15 February the [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Sri Lanka)|Sri Lankan Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] cautiously welcomed the political changes in a statement: &quot;[[Sri Lanka]] and Egypt enjoy warm and close ties. It is in this context that Sri Lanka wishes for the people of Egypt progress and stability within a democratic framework of governance,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.in.msn.com/international/article.aspx?cp-documentid=4924707 |title=In delayed reaction, Sri Lanka welcomes Egypt transition&amp;nbsp;– International News&amp;nbsp;– News&amp;nbsp;– MSN India |publisher=News.in.msn.com |date=16 February 2011 |accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;The government of Sri Lanka welcomes the smooth and peaceful transition of power in Egypt&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sri Lanka cautiously welcomes transition of power in Egypt|url=http://www.colombopage.com/archive_11/Feb16_1297794860CH.php|publisher=ColomboPage|accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{ROC}}&amp;nbsp;- the President of the Republic of China [[Ma Ying-jeou]] &quot;hopes to see the rapid establishment of democracy in Egypt in accordance with the people’s will&quot;, according to Presidential Office spokesman Lo Chih-chiang. Also, according to the director of Department of African Affairs of the ROC's Ministry of Foreign Affairs Samuel Chen, the Republic of China welcomes the coming of democracy in Egypt and hopes to &quot;enhance bilateral exchanges.&quot;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.taiwantoday.tw/ct.asp?xItem=150526&amp;CtNode=420}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Europe==
&lt;!--3 February 2011- contrary to norm, put temporary spacers between countries for easier editing; can be removed after article is more finessed--&gt;
* {{flag|Austria}}&amp;nbsp;— On 3 February [[Foreign Minister of Austria|Austrian Foreign Minister]] [[Michael Spindelegger]] condemned the violence. &quot;It is more necessary than ever for talks to be started without delay between the opposition and the government in order to prevent the situation from getting further out of control. This also entails calling those responsible for acts of violence to account, and swiftly.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Press release]]|url=http://www.bmeia.gv.at/en/foreign-ministry/news/presseaussendungen/2011/spindelegger-zu-aegypten-demonstrationen-koennen-nicht-durch-gewalt-mundtot-gemacht-werden.html|title=Spindelegger on Egypt: 'Demonstrations Cannot be Silenced by Violence'&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Minister Very Concerned About Developments in Egypt and Calls for Renunciation of Force|publisher=[[Foreign Ministry of Austria|Austrian Foreign Ministry]]|date= 3 February 2011|accessdate=4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Belarus}}&amp;nbsp;— [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Belarus)|Belarussian Foreign Ministry]] Press Secretary Andrei Savinykh declared:{{when|date=February 2011}} &quot;We are convinced that street clashes and violence is a bad way to solve pressing social and community issues. We urge the parties to solve existing problems peacefully in line with international legal norms ''[at]'' a negotiating table.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Press release]]|url=http://www.mfa.gov.by/press/news_mfa/aea7305de456e29d.html |title=Комментарий начальника управления информации&amp;nbsp;– пресс-секретаря МИД Андрея Савиных в связи с ситуацией в Египте|trans_title=The comment on the situation in Egypt from Andrey Savinykh, the Head of Informational Department and Press Secretary of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs|language=[[Russian language|Russian]]|publisher=[[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Belarus)|Belarussian Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]|date= |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Belgium}}&amp;nbsp;— In a statement released on 27 January, Belgian Deputy Prime Minister, Foreign Minister [[Steven Vanackere]] and Minister of Civil Service, Public Enterprises and Institutional Reforms deplored the deaths. He hopes that the protest will strengthen the process of democratisation and socio-economic reform in Egypt. He pointed out the importance of freedom of speech and media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Press release]]|url=http://diplomatie.belgium.be/en/newsroom/news/press_releases/foreign_affairs/2011/01/ni_270111_vanackere_betogingen_egypte.jsp |title=Steven Vanackere on the Situation in Egypt |publisher=[[FPS Foreign Affairs Belgium|FPS Foreign Affairs, Foreign Trade and Development Cooperation]] |date=27 January 2011 |accessdate=4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Bulgaria}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry condemned the violent response to the protests, and expressed  condolences for the deaths.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.bg/en/news/view/30752|title=The events of last week demonstrate the need for serious social and economic reforms that can guarantee democracy and human rights in Egypt.|publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Bulgaria|date= 30 January 2011|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Croatia}}&amp;nbsp;— [[Mario Dragun]], spokesman of the Croatian Foreign Ministry, said: &quot;We hope that the violence will cease and democratic dialogue will ensue so that the crisis could be resolved and the political, economic and social reforms carried out with full respect for the basic human.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mvpei.hr/custompages/static/hrv/templates/_frt_Priopcenja_en.asp?id=6565|title=Croatia eyes events in Egypt with concern|publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Croatia|date= 1 February 2011|accessdate=4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{quote box|width=215px|quote=&quot;He is finished as Egypt's leader. The only matter for discussion is how quickly that materialises ... We are not electing a new Egyptian leader. That is something the Egyptians themselves have to do. But what we need is that before Hosni Mubarak leaves the presidential palace he has to provide a roadmap for democracy.&quot;|source=—[[Lars Løkke Rasmussen]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Denmark&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]] |url=http://politiken.dk/newsinenglish/ECE1185609/prime-minister-mubarak-is-finished/|title=Danish Prime Minister: Mubarak Is Finished|work=[[Politiken]] |date=3 February 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=article has sub-headline which also needs english translation appended}} {{cite web|author=Bluhme, Kate |url=http://ekstrabladet.dk/nyheder/politik/article1498502.ece|title=Løkke: Mubarak er ikke præsident mere&amp;nbsp;– Egypterne vil ikke stille sig tilfredse med, at politisk ereformer er sendt til hjørnespark indtil september, erklærer statsminister Lars Løkke Rasmussen |trans_title=''Løkke: Mubarak Ain't President Anymore''|language=[[Danish language|Danish]]|work=[[Ekstra Bladet]] |date= 3 February 2011|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
* {{flag|Denmark}}&amp;nbsp;— Prime Minister [[Lars Løkke Rasmussen]] called the protesters brave,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://nyhederne-dyn.tv2.dk/article.php/id-37005534:l%C3%B8kke-egypternes-reformkrav-er-legitime.html|title=Løkke: Egypternes reformkrav er legitime|trans_title=''Løkke: Egyptians Reform Requirements Are Legitimate''|language=[[Danish language|Danish]]|publisher=''[[TV 2/Lorry]]'' (part of ''[[TV 2 (Denmark)|TV 2]]'') |date= 1 February 2011|accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and urged Mubarak to leave as quickly as possible.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in danish. at minimum, needs english translation appended in &quot;trans_title&quot; field}} {{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]] |url=http://jp.dk/udland/article2327792.ece|title=Løkke: Egyptens Hosni Mubarak er færdig|trans_title=|language=[[Danish language|Danish]]|publisher=''[[Ritzau]]'' (via ''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'') |date= 3 February 2011|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Denmark)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]] [[Lene Espersen]] strongly condemned the alleged Egyptian authorities' actions against the protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Sircic, Adnan|url=http://www.dr.dk/Nyheder/Indland/2011/01/28/222413.htm |title=Uroligheder bekymrer Lene Espersen |trans_title=''Unrests Worries Lene Espersen''|language=[[Danish language|Danish]]|work=[[DR (broadcaster)|DR]] |date= 28 January 2011|accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Danish-Palestinian politician [[Naser Khader]] urged Mubarak to resign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= Nielsen, Jes Højen |url=http://www.dr.dk/Nyheder/Andre_sprog/English/2011/01/31/140511.htm |title=Espersen Expects Strong EU Reaction|work=[[DR (broadcaster)|DR]] |date= 31 January 2011|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Danish Foreign Ministry warned against all travel to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]] |url=http://jp.dk/uknews/article2323591.ece|title=Foreign Ministry Warns Against All Travel to Egypt|publisher=''[[The Copenhagen Post]]'' (via ''[[Jyllands-Posten]]'') |date= 31 January 2011|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Estonia}}&amp;nbsp;— [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Estonia)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]] [[Urmas Paet]] said, &quot;It is vitally important that the Egyptian authorities and protestors avoid the use of violence.&quot; Estonia urged their citizens in Egypt to leave the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vm.ee/?q=en/node/10709&amp;ref=avaflash |title=Foreign Ministry Recommends Avoiding Travel to Egypt |publisher=Vm.ee |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Finland}}&amp;nbsp;— [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Finland)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]] [[Alexander Stubb]] called his counterpart [[Foreign Minister of Egypt]] [[Ahmed Aboul Gheit]] to express Finland's strong hopes that the conflict would be resolved peacefully. In a statement on the Finnish foreign ministry's website Stubb said, &quot;Everyone should now strive to steady the situation quickly so that there would be no further fatalities or injuries. Finland condemns the use of force.&quot; He expressed concern over the blocking of communications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://formin.finland.fi/Public/default.aspx?contentid=211714&amp;nodeid=15145&amp;culture=en-US |title=Statement on the situation in Egypt by Foreign Minister Alexander Stubb&amp;nbsp;— Ministry for Foreign Affairs of Finland: Current affairs |publisher=Formin.finland.fi |date= |accessdate=29 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Egypt solidarity protest in Paris, 29 January 2011 007.jpg|thumb|Solidarity protest near the Embassy of Egypt in Paris, 29 January 2011.]]
* {{flag|France}}&amp;nbsp;— Prime Minister [[Francois Fillon]]'s office said that France would be ceasing arms and tear gas sales to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=By the CNN Wire Staff |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/europe/02/06/france.egypt.arms/ |title=France suspends arms sales to Egypt&amp;nbsp;— CNN.com |publisher=Edition.cnn.com |date= 6 February 2011|accessdate=8 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Controversy arose over Fillon's links to the Mubarak regime, as he admitted having been a guest of Mubarak over the Christmas holiday at Egypt's expense.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Kim Willsher in Paris |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/feb/08/france-francois-fillon-christmas-egypt-mubarak |title=France's prime minister spent family Christmas break as guest of Mubarak &amp;#124; World news |publisher=The Guardian |date= 8 February 2011|accessdate=8 February 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] responded to the allegations by telling his ministers to take their holidays in France more often, saying &quot;What was commonplace a few years back can prove shocking nowadays.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/02/20112917101935120.html |title=Sarkozy bid to end holiday furore&amp;nbsp;– Europe |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Georgia}}&amp;nbsp;— The [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Georgia)|Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] urged its citizens to get out of Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.ge/index.php?lang_id=ENG&amp;sec_id=30&amp;info_id=13355 |title=Information on the setting up of hotline in connection with the recent developments in Egypt|publisher=Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Georgia|date= 30 January 2011|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Germany}}&amp;nbsp;— Foreign Minister [[Guido Westerwelle]] said he was &quot;very concerned&quot; and called on all involved to show restraint.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Al-Shalchi, Adeel|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/211587/egypt-protesters-clash-for-2nd-day-with-police |title=Egypt Protesters Clash for 2nd Day with Police |publisher=''[[Associated Press]]'' (via ''[[GMA News and Public Affairs]]'')|date=27 January 2011 |accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later [[Angela Merkel]] called upon all involved, and especially the Egyptian government and the president, to allow peaceful demonstrations, to give freedom of opinion a chance. &quot;We have to come to a peaceful dialogue in Egypt because the stability of the country is of extraordinary importance.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12316019 |title=In Quotes: Reaction to Egypt Protests |work=[[BBC News]] |date= 30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Greece}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry said in a statement on 30 January that it plans to evacuate its citizens from Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Greece evacuate Egypt&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/foreign-countries-evacuate-citizens-as-cairo-unrest-grows-377303.html |title=Foreign Countries Evacuate Citizens as Cairo Unrest Grows |last=Bladd |first=Joanne |work=[[Arabian Business]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Italy}}&amp;nbsp;— Prime Minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]] said that he hoped for &quot;continuity in the government&quot; as Western leaders wanted a &quot;more democratic system without ruptures with a president like Mubarak that all the Western hemisphere, including the U.S., had considered the wisest man and a reference point in all of the Middle East.&quot; He played down the scale of the protests by saying that there were &quot;really few&quot; demonstrators out of a population of 80&amp;nbsp;million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Krause |first=Flavia |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-04/berlusconi-says-west-considered-mubarak-wisest-man-in-mideast.html |title=Berlusconi Says West Considered Mubarak ‘Wisest Man’ in Mideast |publisher=Bloomberg |date=2011-02-04 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: The Foreign Ministry gave a statement where they expressed deep regret over the civilian casualties. They urged the immediate cessation of every kind of violence, and called for respect for civil rights and for freedom of speech and communication, including the right to hold peaceful rallies. They pointed out that Egypt's stability is a priority for their country.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc.co.uk&quot;/&gt;
* {{flag|Latvia}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry of Affairs was concerned about the situation in Egypt, and advised their citizens not to travel to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.lv/en/news/press-releases/2011/january/28-2/ |title=Comment by Foreign Ministry Press Secretary on situation in Egypt |publisher=Mfa.gov.lv |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Macedonia}}&amp;nbsp;— The Ministry of Foreign Affairs warned their citizens not to travel to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mfa.gov.mk/default1.aspx?ItemID=318&amp;id=1123 |title=Mfa Warns Citizens Against Travelling To Egypt |publisher=Mfa.gov.mk |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Netherlands}}&amp;nbsp;— The Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Uri Rosenthal]] called on &quot;the Egyptian authorities to stop violence, allow the media for all the people and asks the international community to stay on one line to Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of dutch headline appended next to dutch headline}} {{cite web |url=http://nos.nl/audio/215039-minister-rosenthal-reageert-op-ontwikkelingen-egypte.html |title=Minister Rosenthal reageert op ontwikkelingen Egypte |work=[[Nederlandse Omroep Stichting]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011 |language=[[Dutch language|Dutch]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Norway}}&amp;nbsp;— Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Jonas Gahr Støre]] called on the Egyptian authorities to refrain from violence, allow peaceful protests, and respect basic political and economical rights. &quot;I deeply regret that lives have been lost during these demonstrations. The right to free speech and to demonstrate are basic human rights and prerequisites for democratic development. The extensive demonstrations can be viewed as a sign that there are limits to political free speech in Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The situation in Egypt |url=http://www.regjeringen.no/en/dep/ud/press/news/2011/situation_egypt.html?id=632131 |newspaper=Norwegian Government |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Poland}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry expressed concern over the many civilian casualties, and called for respect for human rights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msz.gov.pl/Foreign,Ministry,statement,on,the,situation,in,Egypt,40688.html |title=Foreign Ministry statement on the situation in Egypt |publisher=Msz.gov.pl |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Portugal}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry condemned the violence and urged its citizens in Egypt to leave the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Ministério dos Negócios Estrangeiros |url=http://www.mne.gov.pt/mne/en/noticiasen/201101301347.htm |title=Portuguese MFA about Egypt |publisher=Mne.gov.pt |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Russia}}&amp;nbsp;— In a telephone conversation with Mubarak, [[Russian President|President]] [[Dmitry Medvedev]] expressed his hope that the situation would be resolved by peaceful and legal means. He expressed the importance of guaranteeing the security of the [[Embassy of Russia in Cairo]] and Russian citizens who are still located in the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://eng.kremlin.ru/news/1722|title=Telephone conversation with President of Egypt Hosni Mubarak|date=3 January 2011|publisher=[[Presidential Press and Information Office]]|accessdate=4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: Foreign Minister [[Sergey Lavrov]] sent a message to his Egyptian counterpart expressing concerns over the current situation and compassion with the people of Egypt. He expressed hope that the Egyptian government would stabilise the situation, stating that &quot;the stability of Egypt meets the genuine interests of both the Egyptians and the entire Middle East region.&quot; He hoped that &quot;the Egyptian side will take comprehensive measures to ensure the safety of Russian citizens located in Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mid.ru/brp_4.nsf/0/28DA98369E67F581C3257827005664EC About the message from Minister of Foreign Affairs of Russia Sergey Lavrov to Minister of Foreign Affairs of Egypt Ahmed Aboul Gheit] (in [[Russian language|Russian]]).&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:2011 Egypt protests - Madrid solidarity protest children.jpg|thumb|Solidarity protest at the Egyptian embassy in [[Madrid]], 30 January]]
* {{flag|Slovakia}}&amp;nbsp;— The Foreign Ministry condemned the violence and use of force against the protests. Slovak Minister of Foreign Affairs said that Egypt has to respect human rights and civic liberties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foreign.gov.sk/servlet/content?MT=/App/WCM/main.nsf/vw_ByID/ID_C0B1D004B5A332B2C1257627003301E7_EN&amp;OpenDocument=Y&amp;LANG=EN&amp;TG=BlankMaster&amp;URL=/App/WCM/Aktualit.nsf/(vw_ByID)/ID_205986550CAB3CE2C125782A002FC618 |title=Slovak MFA declaration on the situation in Egypt |publisher=Foreign.gov.sk |date= |accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Spain}}&amp;nbsp;— Foreign Minister [[Trinidad Jimenez]] said that the EU supports the &quot;people who are in the street&quot;. &quot;We support the claiming in the street for more reforms and more rights&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (31 January 2011). [http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/01/2011131192145725920.html%20Europe &quot;US Envoy Meets ElBaradei&amp;nbsp;– Ex-Ambassador, Who Is in Cairo To Reinforce US Message to Mubarak Government, Has Held Talks with Opposition Figure&quot;]. ''[[Al Jazeera English]]''. Retrieved 3 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Sweden}}&amp;nbsp;— Swedish Prime Minister [[Fredrik Reinfeldt]] stated in an interview that he hopes for an eventual democratic Egypt but fears what might happen instead, saying that a reformed Egypt with a harsher attitude towards Israel would be very destabilising for the region.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of swedish headline appended next to swedish headline}} {{cite web|author=Benigh, Love|url=http://svt.se/2.22584/1.2313784/reinfeldt_forsvarar_forsiktig_linje|title=Ändrade villkor för etanolbilar|language=[[Swedish language|Swedish]]|work=[[Sveriges Television]]|date=1 February 2011 |accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: Foreign Minister [[Carl Bildt]] criticised Egypt for blocking the internet, comparing it to [[Myanmar]] in 2007. &quot;In the long run, free access to information is better for confidence and stability than restrictions and prohibitions. Measures such as this that aim at short-term stability may very well lead to more long-term suppression.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.regeringen.se/sb/d/7967/a/159996 |title=Foreign Minister Carl Bildt on the events in Egypt |publisher=regeringen.se |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=29 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Switzerland}}&amp;nbsp;— [[President of the Swiss Confederation|Swiss Conferation President]] and [[Federal Department of Foreign Affairs|Foreign Affairs Minister]] [[Micheline Calmy-Rey]] said she was &quot;worried about the increasing violence in Egypt&quot;. She called on the Egyptian government to &quot;respect freedom of speech and of assembly&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.tsr.ch/info/monde/2926479-egypte-les-manifestations-repartent-de-plus-belle.html |title=''Egypte: Moubarak nomme un vice-président''|trans_title=Egypt: Mubarak Names a Vice President|language=[[French language|French]]|work=[[Télévision Suisse Romande]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: Finance Minister [[Eveline Widmer-Schlumpf]] said that the [[government of Switzerland]] was examining whether Mubarak had any assets in the country. &quot;The Federal Department of Foreign Affairs is looking into [any assets in Swiss banks]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Baldwin |first=Leigh |url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-08/switzerland-is-examining-whether-mubarak-has-assets-in-country.html |title=Switzerland Is Examining Whether Mubarak Has Financial Assets in Country |publisher=Bloomberg |date= |accessdate=8 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|Turkey}}&amp;nbsp;— [[Prime Minister of Turkey|Turkish Prime Minister]] [[Recep Tayyip Erdoğan]] was the first leader in [[Europe]] and the [[Middle East]] to call for Mubarak to heed the people’s demands and leave his post to pave the way for a more democratic regime,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=erdogan-proud-of-his-stance-against-mubarak-slams-opposition-2011-02-15 |title=Turkish PM proud of stance against Mubarak, slams opposition |work=Hurriyet Daily News |date=15 February 2011 |accessdate=17 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; saying the era of governments surviving through repression was over.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Harvey, Benjamin|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-01/erdogan-tells-egypt-s-mubarak-he-should-listen-to-his-people.html |title=Erdogan Tells Egypt's Mubarak He Should Listen to His People |work=[[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]] |date=1 February 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;No government can survive against the will of its people&quot;, Erdoğan said in a televised address to members of the ruling [[AK Party]], which was  broadcast live by some Arabic TV channels, including ''Al Jazeera''. &quot;Listen to [the] people's outcry and humanistic demands. Meet people's demand for change without any hesitation. I would like to make it clear here. You should take the first step for peace, security and stability of Egypt without giving any chance for exploiters, evil circles and those who have dark scenarios on Egypt. You should take steps that could satisfy the people.&quot; He called for anti-government protesters to refrain from violence and protect the country's cultural heritage. &quot;Everyone has the right to fight for freedom, but without violence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/201121115128839350.html |title=Turkish PM Backs Egypt Protesters&amp;nbsp;– Erdogan Urges Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak To 'Lend an Ear to the People's Cries' and Herald a New Era of Reform |work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=1 February 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*: Foreign Minister [[Ahmet Davutoğlu]] said that &quot;there can be demands of communities and they can be expressed. These demands are justified. Transparency and accountability are accepted values in the international community. If these demands are brought on the agenda, in this context, they should be understood right by those countries and by governments there.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of turkish headline in &quot;trans_title&quot; field}} {{cite web|url=http://www.milliyet.com.tr/davutoglu-bunlar-hakli-taleplerdir/dunya/haberdetay/30.01.2011/1345927/default.htm |title=Davutoğlu: Bunlar haklı taleplerdir |trans_title= |work=[[Milliyet]]|language=[[Turkish language|Turkish]]|date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**On 15 February Erdoğan called for an international donor conference to help Egypt overcome its economic woes. Erdogan, who spoke by phone with US President Barack Obama on 12 February, said Obama embraced the idea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/world/2011-02/16/c_13733622.htm |title=Turkish PM calls for int'l donor meeting for Egypt |work=Xinhua |date=16 February 2011 |accessdate=16 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|United Kingdom}}&amp;nbsp;— On 2 February Prime Minister [[David Cameron]] called for an end to the violence, describing the scenes in Cairo as &quot;despicable&quot; and said they should not be repeated. He said, &quot;We have been watching the events in Cairo with grave concern, and completely condemn the violence that is taking place. And if it turns out that the regime, in any way, has been sponsoring or tolerating this violence, that would be completely and utterly unacceptable. These are despicable scenes that we are seeing and they should not be repeated. They underline the need for political reform and, frankly, for that political reform to be accelerated and to happen quickly. We need to see a clear roadmap for that political reform, so that people in Egypt can have confidence that their aspirations for a more democratic, a future with greater rights, is met. And that change needs to start happening now, and the violence needs to stop.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Press release]] (2 February 2011). [http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;id=543389682 &quot;Prime Minister Condemns Violence in Egypt&quot;]. [[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] ([[United Kingdom]]). Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
*: Foreign Secretary [[William Hague]] called on the authorities and protesters in Egypt to show restraint and avoid violence. He urged the Egyptian authorities to &quot;listen to the concerns&quot; of demonstrators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Press release]]|url=http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/news/latest-news/?view=News&amp;id=539828682 |title=Foreign Secretary on Protests in Egypt |publisher=[[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] ([[United Kingdom]])|date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=2 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Former Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] called Mubarak a &quot;force for good.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bloombergreactions&quot;&gt;Ali, Tariq ([[essay]]) (3 February 2011). [http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-04/egypt-chaos-defines-bleeding-in-despot-arab-world-commentary-by-tariq-ali.html &quot;Egypt Chaos Defines Bleeding in Despot Arab World: Tariq Ali&quot;]. ''[[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]]''. Retrieved 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

; Joint statements
A joint statement by [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[David Cameron]], [[President of France|French President]] [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] and [[Chancellor of Germany|German Chancellor]] [[Angela Merkel]] read:
{{Quotation|
&quot;We are deeply concerned about the events that we are witnessing in Egypt. We recognise the moderating role President Mubarak has played over many years in the Middle East. We now urge him to show the same moderation in addressing the current situation in Egypt...It is essential that the further political, economic and social reforms President Mubarak has promised are implemented fully and quickly and meet the aspirations of the Egyptian people.The Egyptian people have legitimate grievances and a longing for a just and better future. We urge President Mubarak to embark on a process of transformation which should be reflected in a broad-based government and in free and fair elections&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.number10.gov.uk/latest-news/2011/01/joint-uk-france-germany-statement-on-egypt-59740 |title=Joint UK-France-Germany statement on Egypt |publisher=Number10.gov.uk |date= |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 3 February the three were joined by [[Prime Minister of Italy|Italian Prime Minister]] [[Silvio Berlusconi]] and [[Prime Minister of Spain|Spanish Prime Minister]] [[Jose Luis Zapatero]] in issuing another statement: &quot;Only a quick and orderly transition to a broad-based government will make it possible to overcome the challenges Egypt is now facing. That transition process must start now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Buckle, Eddie|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-02-03/european-leaders-demand-immediate-regime-change-amid-violence-in-egypt.html|title=Sarkozy, Merkel, Cameron Make Joint Call for Immediate Egypt Regime Change|work=[[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]]|date=3 February 2011|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flag|Ukraine}}&amp;nbsp;— On 10 February former [[Prime Minister of Ukraine]] [[Yulia Tymoshenko]] said that Egypt can learn from the [[Orange Revolution]] about how to amend the constitution to establish a civil society after a peaceful revolution, and not repeat the mistakes of Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/opinion/2011/02/201126142032991448.html |title=My revolution betrayed |publisher=Aljazeera |date= |accessdate=10 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Oceania==
[[File:Egypt Uprising solidarity Melbourne protest, 4 February 2011.jpg|thumb|right|Solidarity protest in [[Melbourne]], Australia]]
&lt;!--3 February 2011- contrary to norm, put temporary spacers between countries for easier editing; can be removed after article is more finessed--&gt;
* {{flag|Australia}}&amp;nbsp;— On 3 February, [[Prime Minister of Australia|Prime Minister]] [[Julia Gillard]] announced &quot;the time for change has come&quot; and that &quot;I absolutely condemn this violence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|title=Prime Minister Julia Gillard calls for Egypt President Hosni Mubarak to stand down now|url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/world/mubarak-supporters-clash-with-egyptian-opposition-protesters/story-e6frev00-1225999171589|date=3 February 2011 |accessdate=8 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flag|New Zealand}}&amp;nbsp;— On 5 February [[Minister of Foreign Affairs (New Zealand)|Minister of Foreign Affairs]] [[Murray McCully]] condemned the violence against the protesters and expressed concern over the targeting of foreign journalists. &quot;Reports that foreign journalists, including New Zealanders, have been targeted is extremely concerning and directly violates fundamental freedoms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Press release]]|title=McCully Condemns Violence Against Journalists in Egypt|url=http://feeds.beehive.govt.nz/release/mccully-condemns-violence-against-journalists-egypt?utm_source=feedburner&amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+beehive-govt-nz%2Fportfolio%2Fforeign-affairs+%28Foreign+Affairs+-+beehive.govt.nz%29|publisher=[[Government of New Zealand]]|accessdate=5 February 2011|work=|date=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Solidarity protests==
[[File:Egypt Uprising solidarity Melbourne protest, 30 January 2011 009.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Solidarity protest at the Egyptian consulate in [[Melbourne]], [[Australia]], 30 January]]
Protests were held at the Egyptian embassy in [[Tunis]] in solidarity and in hope that the two countries' &quot;revolutions&quot; would spark a chain of events around the Arab world. Tunisia's [[Progressive Democratic Party]] said that Egypt had &quot;called in the hour of change for an end to injustice and dictatorship. The Egyptian people supported the Tunisian people's revolution. Our heart is with you and our voices never cease to pray for victory.&quot; There was a demonstration outside the Egyptian embassy in [[Doha]], [[Qatar]].&lt;ref name=&quot;protests&quot;/&gt; There were protests in Lebanon warning of the spread of the protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= Piven, Ben |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/features/2011/01/201112920129971160.html |title=The Domino Effect: Pan-Arab Unrest&amp;nbsp;– Interactive of Anti-Government Protests from Tunisia to Egypt, Yemen and Jordan, with Pro-Western Regimes under Threat|work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 January a march held in [[Gaza]] in solidarity with the protests was suppressed by Hamas. Police officers dressed in civilian clothing arrested six women and detained some 20 others, according to [[Human Rights Watch]].&lt;ref&gt;Issacharoff, Avi (2 February 2011). [http://www.haaretz.com/news/international/hamas-worried-upheaval-in-arab-world-will-spill-into-gaza-1.340690 &quot;Hamas Worried Upheaval in Arab World Will Spill into Gaza&amp;nbsp;– Gaza Police Disperse Rally Showing Solidarity with Egyptian Protesters; Several Thousand Join Facebook Group Calling for a Protest Against Hamas Rule in the Strip&quot;]. ''[[Haaretz]]''. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Syria a peaceful demonstration was held on 29 January in front of the Egyptian embassy in Damascus to protest against the killing of protesters by Egyptian police. Syrian security forces were deployed around the embassy and blocked demonstrators from reaching it.&lt;ref&gt;{{dead link|date=January 2011|reason=link provided is to dynamic page (in arabic with english portal link offered). will requires some research to fish intended article.}} {{cite web |url=http://www.metransparent.com/spip.php?page=article&amp;id_article=12661&amp;lang=ar |title=المنتحر السوري هو &quot;حسن علي عقلة&quot;: دمشق حظرت مظاهرة لدعم مصر &quot; |translation=Syrian Security Forces Block Demonstrators from Reaching the Egyptian Embassy|date=30 January 2011|work=[[Middle East Transparent]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Arab Israeli]]s held rallies in solidarity with the Egyptian protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Raved, Ahiya|date=29 January 2011|title=Arab Israelis Back Egyptian Protestors&amp;nbsp;– Protests Held Across Nation; Former MK Makhoul: We're Showing Solidarity with Arab Nations|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4020862,00.html|work=[[Ynetnews]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 January between 200 and 400 protesters held demonstrations outside the [[Fatih Mosque]] (where political activism has become more common since the [[Gaza flotilla raid]]) after the Friday prayer in Istanbul. A small leftist group gathered outside the Egyptian embassy in [[Ankara]], Turkey.&lt;ref name=&quot;protests&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.apimages.com/OneUp.aspx?st=det&amp;ids=Turkey%20Egypt&amp;showact=details&amp;sort=date&amp;prds=10135&amp;intv=3d&amp;sh=101&amp;kwstyle=or&amp;adte=1296393346&amp;pagez=60&amp;cfasstyle=AND&amp;rids=7953b8aaa25a48829bddc873c33390a9&amp;dbm=PThirtyDay&amp;page=1&amp;xslt=1 |title=Turkey Egypt |agency=Associated Press |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Iranian students gathered in front of the Egypt's Interest Section{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=which embassy?}} in [[Tehran]] on 30 January to support the uprisings in Egypt. According to IRNA,{{who|date=February 2011|reason=what is this? no easily found wiki article}} the students, shouting slogans such as &quot;Down with US, Down with Israel, Down with UK and down with Hosni Mubarak,&quot; condemned the Egyptian government's measures to confront protesters. The students demanded that the Iranian government shut down Egypt's Interest Section in Iran.&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (30 January 2011). [http://english.irib.ir/news/political/item/70539-iranian-students-condemn-egyptian-police-measures-against-protesters &quot;Iranian Students Condemn Egyptian Police Measures Against Protesters&quot;]. ''[[Islamic Republic of Iran Broadcasting]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 January [[Egyptian Canadian|Egyptians living in Canada]] and others gathered at the embassy in Ottawa as well as the consulate in [[Montreal]]. The next day, Canadians in [[Toronto]], [[Montreal]], [[Vancouver]], and other cities peacefully demonstrated in support of the uprising, criticising the Canadian government's cautious and generic response.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|title=Demonstrators Across Canada Rally in Support of Egyptian Protesters|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/politics/hundreds-of-canadians-rally-in-support-of-egyptian-protesters/article1887588/|work=[[The Globe and Mail]]|accessdate=31 January 2010|date=29 January 2010|location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 29 January in [[Dearborn, Michigan]], 300 people expressed their solidarity for the Egyptian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Steele, Micki|url=http://detnews.com/article/20110129/METRO/101290382/Protesters-rally-in-Dearborn-to-support-Egyptian-people |title=Protesters Rally in Dearborn To Support Egyptian People |work=[[The Detroit News]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Around 150 protesters demonstrated in solidarity with the Egyptian people in [[Nashville, Tennessee]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Choudhury, Atif|url=http://www.vanderbiltorbis.com/?p=164 |title=Nashville rallies in support of protests in Egypt, Tunisia |work=[[Vanderbilt Orbis]] |date=19 February 2011 |accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:NYC Rally for Egyptian Democracy Protestors, 29 January 2011 008.jpg|thumb|Solidarity protest in [[New York City]], 29 January]]
The Egyptian embassy in Venezuela was temporarily taken over by Venezuelans of Egyptian descent,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/BT-CO-20110128-715552.html|publisher=''[[Dow Jones]]'' (via ''[[The Wall Street Journal]]'')|title=Egypt Embassy In Venezuela Sees Shortlived Protest&amp;nbsp;– Chavez|date=28 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; an action which was condemned by President [[Hugo Chavez]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Mardones, Carolina |url=http://www.panorama.com.ve/29-01-2011/avances/embajada-caracas.html |title=Manifestantes toman temporalmente embajada de Egipto en Caracas|translation=Protesters temporarily take Egyptian Embassy in Caracas |language=[[Spanish language|Spanish]]|work=panorama.com.ve |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Egyptians in Ireland and members of the [[Irish Anti-War Movement]] held a protest outside the embassy in Dublin on 28 January to &quot;show solidarity for the people in Egypt to say to them that we are behind you and we support you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bray, Allison (29 January 2011). [http://www.independent.ie/world-news/africa/protesters-demand-justice-and-democracy-at-embassy-demo-2516024.html &quot;Protesters Demand Justice and Democracy at Embassy Demo&quot;]. ''[[Irish Independent]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

In London, fifty protesters outside the Egyptian embassy called for Mubarak's regime to resign.&lt;ref name=&quot;protests&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/01/201112815843772129.html |title=Egypt Supporters Rally Worldwide&amp;nbsp;– Protests Held Across Globe in a Show of Solidarity with Egyptian Demonstrators Attempting To Oust President|work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Frankfurt]], [[Germany]], a small group protested on 29 January in the main pedestrian zone, the [[Zeil]], to show their support for the Egyptian people. In [[Munich]], Germans joined the Egyptians in a demonstration in [[Odeonsplatz]] asking Mubarak to leave.{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}} In [[The Hague]], [[The Netherlands]], 200 people protested in front of the [[Peace Palace]] against the regime of Mubarak.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of dutch headline appended next to dutch headline}} [[Staff writer]] (30 January 2011). [http://nos.nl/artikel/215312-reisbureaus-halen-toeristen-weg-chaos-op-vliegveld.html &quot;Reisbureaus halen toeristen weg, chaos op vliegveld&quot;] (in [[Dutch language|Dutch]]). ''[[Nederlandse Omroep Stichting]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

on 31 January in India's prestigious [http://www.jnu.ac.in/ Jawaharlal Nehru University]Egypt Solidarity Forum ([http://esfdelhi.blogspot.com ESF])organized a solidarity march in which some 500 students and faculty members participated.&lt;ref name=anas&gt;{{cite news|last=Gazette|first=Milli|title=India supports Egyptian people’s struggle|url=http://www.milligazette.com/news/601-india-supports-egyptian-peoples-struggle|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=Milli Gazette|date=16-28 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; The march was addressed by Professor A K Ramakrishnan, a distinguished faculty of School of International Studies at the university. Convener of the solidarity forum Omair Anas told that “We believe that Egyptian people are victims of their own rulers as well as their Western masters. Hosni Mubarak has protected interests of capitalists, multinationals and his Western masters, mainly the United States.&lt;ref name=anas&gt;{{cite web|last=TCN News|title=Delhi students hold solidarity march for Egyptian protesters|url=http://twocircles.net/node/237444|publisher=Two Cirlce|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the next day, Forum called to join mass demonstration at Embassy of Egypt in New Delhi where thousands of students from different student organizations joined the demonstrated against the Mubarak regime and some protesters including convener of the Egypt Solidarity Forum were detained by the Delhi Police.&lt;ref name=anas&gt;{{cite news|last=Gilani|first=Iftekhar|title=Egyptian crises brings Leftists and Islamists together|url=http://www.tehelka.com/story_main48.asp?filename=Ws020211INTERNATIONAL.asp|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=Tehelka|date=2 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt Solidarity Forum had also launched a Facebook campaign&lt;ref name=anas&gt;{{cite web|title=Arab Solidarity Forum|url=http://www.facebook.com/groups/151670754888053/|publisher=Facebook|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an online petition to support Casablanca call for political reform was also launched.

In [[South Africa]], on 4 February, approximately 300 demonstrators blocked Bourke Street, the location of the Egyptian embassy in [[Pretoria]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Department of International Relations and Cooperation]] (South Africa). [http://www.dfa.gov.za/foreign/forrep/fore.htm#egy &quot;Foreign Representatives in South Africa&quot;]. Retrieved 10 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; in peaceful protests organised by South African trade unions, human rights groups, and Egyptians in South Africa. The demonstrators shouted slogans such as &quot;out with Mubarak&quot; in English, [[Afrikaans]], [[Zulu language|Zulu]], and [[Arabic language|Arabic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/02/04/s-africans-rally-support-egypt-protesters/ |title=S. Africans rally to support Egypt protesters |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=2010-02-01 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 February in [[Ukraine]], [[FEMEN]] activists organised a topless protest&lt;ref&gt;[http://femen.livejournal.com/136430.html FEMEN Livejournal, photos]&lt;/ref&gt; in front of the Egyptian embassy in [[Kiev]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.allvoices.com/contributed-news/8144289-topless-femen-activist-supports-the-egyptian-revolution-at-the-egyptian-embassy-in-kiev-photos|title=Topless FEMEN activist Supports the Egyptian Revolution in kiev|date=9 February 2011|accessdate=9 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Non-governmental organisations==
* The [[AFL-CIO]] supported the protests, saying that US President Barack Obama was not &quot;on their side.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defenddemocracy.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=11792097&amp;Itemid=348 |title=AFL-CIO Backs Egyptian Worker Protests, Says Obama Policies Not Clearly 'On Their Side' |publisher=Defenddemocracy.org |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Salil Shetty]], head of [[Amnesty International]], believed Hosni Mubarak's decision to fire his cabinet would not stop the anti-government protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=205730 |title=Amnesty Int'l: Egypt Cabinet Firing Won't Quell Protests |publisher=''[[Associated Press]]'' (via ''[[The Jerusalem Post]]'') |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;!--at late jan/early feb 2011, this particular link to jpost.com can be VERY slow to load. other jpost.com links load regulary.--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Hacktivist]] group [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] attacked multiple government websites and issued press releases calling for support of the Egyptian people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Emspak|first=Jesse|title=Egyptian Gov't Web Sites Under Attack|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/105329/20110126/egyptian-government-web-sites-attacked.htm|accessdate=27 January 2011|work=[[International Business Times]]|date=26 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mohamed Abdel Dayem of the [[Committee to Protect Journalists]] condemned police violence against journalists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://cpj.org/2011/01/journalists-beaten-websites-blocked-amid-protests.php|title=Journalists Beaten, Websites Blocked Amid Protests in Egypt|publisher=[[Committee to Protect Journalists]]|date=26 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Human Rights Watch]] said Egyptian police had escalated the use of force against largely peaceful demonstrations and called it &quot;wholly unacceptable and disproportionate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/01/201112810059478272.html |title=Fresh Protests Erupt in Egypt&amp;nbsp;– Army Reportedly on the Streets of Cairo as Curfew Is Imposed from 6&amp;nbsp;pm to 7&amp;nbsp;am Local Time|work=[[Al Jazeera English]] |date=28 January 2011 |accessdate=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Militant Islamist group [[al-Qaeda]]'s Ayman al-Zawahiri said, &quot;The constitution of the regime in Egypt claims that it is democratic. But it's truth that it's a suppressive regime that rules the people with suppressive forces and fake elections and corrupt media and unjust law.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Matthew Cole]]|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/al-qaeda-message-egypt/story?id=12951313 |title=Newly Released Al Qaeda Message Blasts Mubarak |work=[[abc news]] |date=18 February 2011 |accessdate=18 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evacuations and travel advisories==
* {{flag|Argentina}}&amp;nbsp;– From 1 February until 4 February, the [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Argentina)|Argentine Ministry of Foreign Affairs]] issued a series of press releases urging Argentine citizens not to visit Egypt &quot;unless it is absolutely necessary, until the situation returns to normal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancilleria.gov.ar/portal/prensa/comunicado.php?buscar=5011 |title=Argentine Foreign Affairs Ministry Press Release, 1&amp;nbsp;Feb (in Spanish) |publisher=Cancilleria.gov.ar |date= |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancilleria.gov.ar/portal/prensa/comunicado.php?buscar=5015 |title=Argentine Foreign Affairs Ministry Press Release, 2&amp;nbsp;Feb (in Spanish) |publisher=Cancilleria.gov.ar |date= |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cancilleria.gov.ar/portal/prensa/comunicado.php?buscar=5021 |title=Argentine Foreign Affairs Ministry Press Release, 4&amp;nbsp;Feb (in Spanish) |publisher=Cancilleria.gov.ar |date= |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Austria}} sent{{when|date=February 2011|reason=needs context}} two charter planes and one military plane to evacuate its nationals from Egypt, but many Austrians on holiday in seaside resorts want to stay.&lt;ref name=&quot;eurovoice&quot;&gt;[[Staff writer]] (1 February 2011). [http://www.europeanvoice.com/page/european-voice-blogs/366.aspx?blogitemid=737 &quot;The Paper Clip, 1 February&quot;]. ''The Paper Clip'' ([[blog]] of ''[[European Voice]]''). Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Azerbaijan}} sent a special commercial [[Azerbaijan Airlines]] flight on 30 January to bring back its citizens, most of them students and embassy staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|date=31 January 2011|title=Plane with Azerbaijani Citizens Evacuated from Egypt Arrives in Baku (Update)|url=http://en.trend.az/news/incident/1820441.html|work=[[Trend News Agency]]|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Luscombe|first=Jane|title=Kiwis in Egypt Left Stranded by Govt|url=http://www.3news.co.nz/Kiwis-in-Egypt-left-stranded-by-Govt/tabid/417/articleID/196599/Default.aspx|work=[[3 News]]|date=31 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An employee of the Azerbaijani embassy in Egypt was killed in Cairo on the same day as a result of mass public disorder.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|title=Azerbaijani Official Killed in Cairo|url=http://www.news.az/articles/politics/30543|publisher=''[[Azerbaijan Press Agency]]'' (via ''[[news.az]]'')|accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|title=При беспорядках в Египте погиб сотрудник посольства Азербайджана&amp;nbsp;– ОБНОВЛЕНО|translation=An employee of the Azerbaijani Embassy was killed in the Egyptian unrest|url=http://news.day.az/politics/250550.html|language=[[Russian language|Russian]]|work=[[day.az]]|date=30 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Australia}} The Prime Minister announced that a chartered jet would be available to evacuate Australian nationals, and that extra consular staff will be provided. Two Qantas [[Boeing 747|747]] flights from [[Cairo International Airport]] removed Australian citizens to Frankfurt on 2 February and 4 February at government expense. Since many people were unable to reach Cairo quickly, another flight from [[Luxor]] was considered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.smartraveller.gov.au/zw-cgi/view/TravelBulletins/egypt |title=Australian DFAT travel Bulletin |publisher=Smartraveller.gov.au |date=31 January 2011 |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Brazil}} The Brazilian embassy discouraged any trips to Egypt until the situation returns to normal and started evacuating Brazilians in the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;MRE2&quot;&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of portuguese headline appended next to portuguese headline}} [http://www.itamaraty.gov.br/sala-de-imprensa/notas-a-imprensa/situacao-no-egito Situação no Egito] (in [[Portuguese language|Portuguese]]). Ministry of External Relations of Brazil. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Brunei}} The Brunei government had evacuated all of their 97 citizens out of Egypt via Dubai on a specially chartered flight.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| author= Siti Hajar and Azim Karim |url=http://brudirect.com/index.php/2011020238877/First-Stories/emotional-welcome-for-bruneians-from-egypt.html |title= Emotional Welcome for Bruneians from Egypt |work= Brudirect.com (Brunei Darussalam)|date= 3 February 2011 | accessdate= 4 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Canada}} launched an evacuation plan to evacuate citizens from Egypt using [[Air Canada]] charter flights contracted by the [[Government of Canada]] to [[Frankfurt]], London, and Paris. Approximately 6,500 Canadian citizens in Egypt are expected to reimburse the cost of the plane tickets to Europe and self-arrange for an ongoing flight back to Canada.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/2011/01/30/egypt-evacuation-protests.html|title=Canadians Could Begin Leaving Egypt Monday |work=[[CBC News]] |date=31 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Conflicting reports suggested that the government was willing to subsidise C$400 off ticket prices and organise flights out of the country. However, the government was unsure of how many citizens would take advantage of the offer. &quot;The government is recommending that Canadians leave Egypt,&quot; Foreign Affairs Minister [[Lawrence Cannon]] announced. &quot;... The situation is deteriorating, the situation is not under control.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Martin, Patrick; Ibbitson, John (31 January 2011). [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/crisis-in-egypt/first-stranded-canadians-ready-to-leave-cairo/article1888623/ &quot;First Stranded Canadians Ready To Leave Cairo&quot;]. ''[[The Globe and Mail]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Cyprus}} was prepared to receive foreign citizens evacuated from Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.pseka.net/index.php?module=article&amp;id=11657|title=As with Lebanon, once again Cyprus is the HUB for evacuees from a hot spot (Egypt).|publisher=PSEKA|date= 1 February 2011|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cyprus It advised its citizens currently in Egypt to avoid areas where demonstrations were being staged.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.pseka.net/index.php?module=article&amp;id=11656|title=Cypriots&amp;nbsp;– Egypt&amp;nbsp;– Advice.|publisher=PSEKA|date= 1 February 2011|accessdate=1 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Finland}} organised a 200-seater [[Finnair]] [[Airbus]] to evacuate the approximately 150 Finnish citizens living in Egypt. According to Foreign Minister Alexander Stubb, the greatest challenge was to gather all Finns into one place to be evacuated. Finland allowed nationals of other countries to take vacant seats on the evacuation flights.&lt;ref&gt;{{Clarify|date=February 2011|reason=at minimum, needs english translation of finnish headline appended next to finnish headline}} {{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.iltalehti.fi/ulkomaat/2011013113103593_ul.shtml |title=Suomi harkitsee pysyvästi Egyptissä asuvien evakuointia|language=[[Finnish language|Finnish]]|publisher=''[[Suomen Tietotoimisto]]'' (via ''[[Iltalehti]]'')|date=31 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|India}} sent a special commercial [[Air India]] flight on 30 January to bring back its citizens who wanted to return home. Some of the 3,600-odd Indians who live in Egypt had expressed an interest in returning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Special-AI-plane-to-bring-back-300-Indians-from-Egypt/articleshow/7391308.cms |title=Special AI Plane To Bring Back 300 Indians from Egypt |publisher=''[[Indo-Asian News Service]]'' (via ''[[The Times of India]]'') |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Indonesia}} called for the quick evacuation of all Indonesian citizens in Egypt, most of whom were studying at [[Al-Azhar University]], by charter flights from [[Garuda Indonesia]].{{citation needed|date=February 2011}}
* {{flag|Ireland}}&amp;nbsp;— The Department of Foreign Affairs said that as of 3 February it had &quot;given assistance to approximately 400 Irish citizens [in Egypt].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.merrionstreet.ie/index.php/2011/02/statement-on-egypt-by-department-of-foreign-affairs/ &quot;Statement on Egypt by Department of Foreign Affairs&quot;].&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagcountry|Serbia}} evacuated tourists and people who worked in Egypt with two flights.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radio5.co.rs/portal/moduli.php?naziv=Vesti&amp;file=clanak&amp;sid=80297 |title=Turisti Iz Srbije Danas Se Vraćaju Iz Egipta |publisher=RADIO 5 |date=31 January 2011 |accessdate=20 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vesti-online.com/Stampano-izdanje/02-02-2011/Dnevnik/114403/Srbija-evakuise--radnike-iz-Egipta |title=Vesti online / Štampano izdanje / 2 February 2011 / Dnevnik / Srbija evakuiše radnike iz Egipta |publisher=Vesti-online.com |date= |accessdate=13 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Iraq}} offered to transport its citizens in Egypt, many of whom fled as a result of the [[Iraq War|war]], back to [[Baghdad]] for free.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/01/30/iraq-offers-evacuate-citizens-living-egypt/ |title=Iraq offers to evacuate citizens living in Egypt |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=2010-02-01 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Foreign Ministry advised their citizens to stay away from places of tension and offered to evacuate their citizens with three military aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;mofairaq&quot;&gt;[[Press release]] (30 January 2011). [http://www.mofa.gov.iq/eng/articles/display.aspx?gid=1&amp;id=9992 &quot;Statement of Iraqi Foreign Ministry on Status of Iraqi Citizens in the Arab Republic of Egypt&quot;]. Office of [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Iraq)|Iraq Ministry of Foreign Affairs]]. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Ireland}} As of 3 February, the [[Department of Foreign Affairs (Ireland)|Irish Department of Foreign Affairs]] advised [[Ireland|Irish]] citizens to immediately leave Egypt and advised against travel to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (3 February 2011). [http://www.dfa.ie/home/index.aspx?id=44979 &quot;Situation in Egypt&quot;]. [[Department of Foreign Affairs (Ireland)|Ireland Department of Foreign Affairs]]. Retrieved 3 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Israel}} advised its citizens to refrain from non-essential travel to Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;israel evacuation&quot;/&gt; It later called on all its citizens holidaying in the Sinai to return home.
[[Greece]] called for its citizens to be evacuated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Greece evacuate Egypt&quot;/&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Kuwait}}: His Highness the [[Emir of Kuwait]] ordered the embassy to make sure all Kuwaiti citizens were brought back home free ,of cost and to make sure the embassy provides a hotel if needed. [[Kuwait Airways]] received orders from the Emir to send special flights to bring all Kuwaitis in Egypt back home. The Kuwaiti Ambassador to Egypt said that all Kuwaiti citizens are &quot;safe, and enjoy good health.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mofa.gov.kw |title=MOFA Kuwait |publisher=Mofa.gov.kw |date= |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thousands of Saudi and Egyptian passengers were stranded at the Cairo, Jeddah and Riyadh airports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Fakkar, Galal|url=http://arabnews.com/saudiarabia/article245797.ece |title=Thousands of Saudi, Egyptian Passengers Stranded |work=[[ArabNews]] |date=29 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Turkey sent two aircraft to pick up its stranded citizens.&lt;!--from tv--&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Malaysia}} On 2 February the Malaysian government announced plan to evacuate its citizens. The plan, code-named &quot;Operation Pyramid&quot; (Malay: Operasi Piramid) was supported by three [[Royal Malaysian Air Force]] [[C-130 Hercules]] planes, a [[Royal Malaysian Navy]] auxiliary ship, which was stationed at [[Gulf of Aden]]. Malaysian flag carrier [[Malaysia Airlines]] and low-cost carrier [[AirAsia]] later announced their support of the evacuation mission and sent aircraft to Egypt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Vanar, Muguntan; Mazwin, Nik Anis; Majid, Embun; Kammed, K. Ashraf; Tariq, Qishin; Rahim, Rahimy; Kulasagaran, Priya|url=http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2011/2/3/nation/7930045&amp;sec=nation | title= AirAsia and MAS on Mercy Mission| work= [[The Star (Malaysia)|The Star]]| date= 3 February 2011| accessdate= 3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first evacuees were expected to arrive on 4 February.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file=/2011/2/3/nation/20110203141435&amp;sec=nation |title=Egypt Crisis: Malaysian Evacuees Leave for Jeddah| work=[[The Star (Malaysia)|The Star]]| date=3 February 2011| accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|New Zealand}} On 31 January the [[government of New Zealand|New Zealand government]] warned its citizens to avoid all areas with protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=The Associated Press |url=http://www.1310news.com/news/world/article/176722--new-zealand-warns-of-risk-to-travellers-to-egypt-advises-citizens-to-stay-away-during-protests?ref=topic&amp;name=City-Hall&amp;title= |title=New Zealand warns of risk to travellers to Egypt, advises citizens to stay away during protests |publisher=1310News |date=2011-01-30 |accessdate=2011-04-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Nigeria}}  President [[Goodluck Jonathan]] recommended that all Nigerians evacuate from Egypt. Nigeria then dispatched a team to assist its citizens in leaving the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.vanguardngr.com/2011/02/nigeria-begins-evacuation-of-citizens-from-egypt/ |accessdate= 4 February 2010 |date= 2 February 2010 |work= [[Vanguard (Nigeria)|Vanguard]] |title= Nigeria Begins Evacuation of Citizens from Egypt |author= Akinboade, Laide }}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Russia}}'s government created an emergency team within the Foreign Ministry to form a plan for evacuating 25,000 Russian nationals. It had earlier recommended that tourists stay in their hotels and not leave the guarded resort areas.&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (29 January 2011). [http://en.rian.ru/russia/20110129/162368424.html &quot;Russia's Lavrov Urges Measures To Protect Tourists in Egypt&quot;]. ''[[RIA Novosti]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
Two major Russian oil and gas companies, [[Lukoil]] and [[Novatek]], evacuated their staff from Egypt on 30 January.&lt;ref&gt;[[Staff writer]] (30 January 2011). [http://en.rian.ru/russia/20110130/162378531.html &quot;Russia's LUKoil Oil Major, Novatek Gas Giant Evacuate Staff from Riots-Hit Egypt&quot;]. ''[[RIA Novosti]]''. Retrieved 31 January 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Kosovo}}{{ref label|status|a|}} The Kosovo Foreign Ministry urged Kosovars to leave Egypt. In the absence of diplomatic relations between the two states, citizens in distress were instructed to seek help from the Turkish embassy.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in foreign language. at minimum, needs english translation of foreign-language headline appended next to foreign-language headline}} {{cite web|url=http://www.mfa-ks.net/?page=1,4,628 |title=Fillon evakuimi i shtetasve tanë nga Egjiptit |publisher=mfa.ks.net |date=3 February 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The chairman of the [[New Kosovo Alliance]] [[Behgjet Pacolli]] organised flights back to Kosovo for some 160-odd Kosovas at his own expense.&lt;ref&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=headline in foreign language, at minimum needs english translation of foreign-language headline appended next to foreign-language headline}} {{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.telegrafi.com/?id=2&amp;a=12721 |title=Pacolli fillon evakuimin e kosovarëve nga Egjipti |work=[[telegrafi.com]] |date=3 February 2011 |accessdate=3 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|Slovakia}} On 3 February a Slovak government aircraft brought 34 Slovaks, eight Czechs, one Hungarian, and two Portuguese citizens, who were living and working in Cairo and [[Hurghada]], to Slovakia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Vilikovská, Zuzana|url=http://spectator.sme.sk/articles/view/41540/10/forty_five_people_brought_to_slovakia_from_egypt_by_government_aircraft.html |title=Forty-Five People Brought to Slovakia from Egypt by Government Aircraft |work=[[The Slovak Spectator]]|date=4 February 2011 |accessdate=5 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|South Korea}}'s flag carrier, [[Korean Air]], suspended flights to Egypt on 30 January. The Foreign Ministry suspended classes at the Korean School, which had an attendance of some forty elementary school students. The South Korean embassy put together an emergency plan to evacuate Korean nationals in the event of a serious crisis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://english.yonhapnews.co.kr/national/2011/01/30/25/0301000000AEN20110130002500315F.HTML|title=Korean Air Suspends Flights to Cairo Amid Egypt Protests|work=[[Yonhap]]|date=30 January 2011|accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|UK}} Until 30 January, the British government had advised its citizens to stay put (although advising against non-essential travel). However, the advice was then revised to say &quot;We recommend that British nationals without a pressing need to be in Cairo, Alexandria or Suez leave by commercial means, where it is safe to do so.&quot; The Foreign Ministry recommendation that citizens in other parts of the country not affected by widespread protests and violence stay where they are and stay indoors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://www.fco.gov.uk/en/travel-and-living-abroad/travel-advice-by-country/middle-east-north-africa/egypt/ |title= Middle East and North Africa&amp;nbsp;– Egypt|publisher=[[Foreign and Commonwealth Office]] ([[United Kingdom]])|date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* {{flagcountry|USA}} The US advised its citizens to take evacuation flights to safe havens in Europe.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Weaver |first=Matthew |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/blog/2011/jan/30/egypt-protests-live-updates |title=''The Guardian'' Live Update 10:38&amp;nbsp;am and 10:14&amp;nbsp;am |work=[[The Guardian]] |date=30 January 2011|accessdate=30 January 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; It later warned its citizens to leave &quot;as soon as possible&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=Gaouette, Nicole|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-01-30/clinton-visits-haiti-beset-by-undecided-election-delayed-earthquake-aid.html |title=Clinton Visits Haiti Beset by Undecided Election, Delayed Earthquake Aid |work=[[Bloomberg L.P.|Bloomberg]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=30 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It offered to send a plane to evacuate embassy personnel to reduce its &quot;diplomatic footprint&quot; in the country.&lt;!--from tv--&gt;{{Citation needed|date=January 2011}}

; Others
[[Multinational corporation]]s said they would evacuate their employees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |author=[[Staff writer]]|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/africa/01/30/egypt.evacuations/ |title=Foreign Governments, Businesses Begin Evacuations from Egypt |work=[[CNN]] |date=30 January 2011 |accessdate=31 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media and individuals==
===Media===
{{Expand section|date=February 2011}}
Austria's ''[[Der Standard]]'' said that &quot;the EU has failed to manage its response to the events in Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;eurovoice&quot;/&gt;{{clarify|date=February 2011|reason=needs context. when did editorial appear? also, this is not quoting &quot;der standard&quot;; rather, it is quoting &quot;the paper clip&quot; blog of &quot;european voices&quot; paraphrasing what &quot;der standard&quot; said. would be better with direct source to der standard&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;{{de}} Prantner, Christoph ; Printausgabe, 1.2.2011 [http://derstandard.at/1295571276077/Vergeudeter-Kairo-Moment &quot;Vergeudeter &quot;Kairo-Moment&quot;]. ''[[Der Standart]]''. Retrieved 6 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[New York Times]]'' columnist [[Nicholas Kristof]] said that &quot;it should be increasingly evident that Mr. Mubarak is not the remedy for instability in Egypt; he is its cause. The road to stability in Egypt requires Mr. Mubarak's departure, immediately.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.journalism.org/index_report/pej_news_coverage_index_january_31_february_6_2011 |title=Events in Egypt Trigger Record Coverage &amp;#124; Project for Excellence in Journalism (PEJ) |publisher=Journalism.org |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 February, during the first show after a return from Egypt, [[CNN]] reporter [[Anderson Cooper]], who had twice been beaten by pro-Mubarak protesters, criticised the government on his nightly show. He said that Mubarak's regime has &quot;blood on its hands&quot; and is lying to the world about its actions. He called Egypt a police state and accused the government of saying &quot;the direct opposite of what they have been doing.&quot; He cited the government's claim of reaching out to the opposition even though &quot;his secret police were still arresting opposition figures.&quot; He further said that while the government has denied being involved in the violence directed at protesters, the military had been conspicuously slow to react to the targeting of demonstrators by pro-Mubarak forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/02/08/anderson-cooper-egypt-blood-hands-lies_n_820403.html |title=Anderson Cooper: Egyptian Government Has 'Blood On Their Hands,' Is Lying (VIDEO) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Writing for the ''[[Saturday Mirror]]'' on 6 August, former [[Nigeria]]n head of state [[Olusegun Obasanjo]] criticised the handling of the Mubaraks' trial and defended the deposed president. &quot;I am not saying that Mubarak has not made a mistake in his almost thirty years in running the affairs of Egypt or that he has not committed any misdemeanour or offence, but decency demands that in bringing him to judgment, the good he has done should be brought side by side with the mistakes he has made and if this is done objectively, I am of the mind that the good will outweigh the mistakes,&quot; Obasanjo wrote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://saharareporters.com/news-page/olusegun-obasanjo-becomes-newspaper-columnist|publisher=Sahara Reporters|title=Olusegun Obasanjo Becomes A Newspaper Columnist!|date=11 August 2011|accessdate=11 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Individuals===
[[MIT]] linguistics professor [[Noam Chomsky]] said that &quot;[w]hat’s happening is absolutely spectacular. The courage and determination and commitment of the demonstrators is remarkable, and whatever happens these are moments that won’t be forgotten and are sure to have long-term consequences.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[Noam Chomsky|Chomsky, Noam]] (2 February 2011). [http://www.democracynow.org/2011/2/2/noam_chomsky_this_is_the_most &quot;This Is the Most Remarkable Regional Uprising That I Can Remember&quot;]. ''[[Democracy Now!]]''. (video report (requires [[Adobe Flash]]); link to &quot;rush transcript&quot; available). Retrieved 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; He later added in an article in ''The Guardian'' that:&lt;ref&gt;[[Noam Chomsky|Chomsky, Noam]] ([[essay]]; 4 February 2011). [http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2011/feb/04/radical-islam-united-states-independence &quot;It's Not Radical Islam That Worries the US&amp;nbsp;– It's Independence—The Nature of Any Regime It Backs in the Arab World Is Secondary to Control—Subjects Are Ignored Until They Break Their Chains&quot;]. ''[[The Guardian]]''. Retrieved 5 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Observers compared it to the toppling of Russian domains in 1989, but there are important differences. Crucially, no [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] exists among the great powers that support the Arab dictators. Rather, Washington and its allies keep to the well-established principle that democracy is acceptable only insofar as it conforms to strategic and economic objectives: fine in enemy territory (up to a point), but not in our backyard, please, unless properly tamed. One 1989 comparison has some validity: Romania, where Washington maintained its support for [[Nicolae Ceausescu]], the most vicious of the east European dictators, until the allegiance became untenable. Then Washington hailed his overthrow while the past was erased. That is a standard pattern: [[Ferdinand Marcos]], [[Jean-Claude Duvalier]], [[Chun Doo-hwan]], [[Suharto]] and many other useful gangsters. It may be under way in the case of Hosni Mubarak, along with routine efforts to try to ensure a successor regime will not veer far from the approved path.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Tariq Ali]] said the protests would be a &quot;rude awakening for all those who imagined that the despots of the Arab world could be kept in place provided they continued to serve the needs of the West.&quot; He said that &quot;while Western establishments lull themselves to sleep with fairy tales, ordinary citizens, who are defeated and demoralised, mull their revenge.&quot; He added that &quot;If Tunisia was a tremor, the Egyptian uprising has become an earthquake that is spreading throughout the region. The generals in Cairo are still refusing to disperse the crowds with tanks and bullets. A full-scale Tiananmen Square option, which Mubarak and his friends would have appreciated, becomes difficult in these conditions.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bloombergreactions&quot;/&gt;

[[Ralph Nader]] said that Vice-President Omar Suleiman appeared to be making the decisions, if only to give the impression that Mubarak was relenting and would be willing to remain as a figurehead president until his term ends later in the year. He believes that Mubarak was very alert to what would be needed to maintain the loyalties of the police, the intelligence agencies, the security forces and the army and that when is forced out tens of thousands of those on his payroll would lose their patronage. Nader stated that &quot;the government is striving to wait out the protesters, whose daily supplies and energies are being sapped by the overwhelming force arrayed against them to intimidate, weaken and keep their numbers down not just in [Tahrir] Square but also in other cities like Alexandria and Suez.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Nader |first=Ralph |url=http://www.commondreams.org/view/2011/02/08-5 |title=Time for Democracy in Egypt |publisher=Common Dreams |date= |accessdate=11 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
'''Notes:'''

{| class=&quot;references-small&quot; style=&quot;margin-left:13px; line-height:150%&quot;
|-
|  style=&quot;text-align:right; vertical-align:top;&quot;|a.
|{{note|status}}{{Kosovo-note}}
|}

'''References:'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/01/29/americans-protest-egypt-photos_n_815894.html#s232544&amp;title=Washington_DC Americans Protest in Support of Egypt]&amp;nbsp;– slideshow by ''[[The Huffington Post]]''

{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}
{{2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Egypt topics}}
{{Foreign relations of Egypt}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:International Reactions To The 2011 Egyptian Protests}}
[[Category:2011 Egyptian revolution|Egypt]]
[[Category:2011 in Egypt|03]]
[[Category:2011 riots|Egypt03]]
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of Egypt]]
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]
[[Category:Protests in Egypt]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in Egypt]]

[[ar:الردود الدولية على ثورة 25 يناير]]
[[fa:بازتاب جهانی انقلاب مصر (۲۰۱۱)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
