<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="307248" ns="0" title="James Traficant"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{npov|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox congressman
| name=James Traficant
| image name=James Traficant.jpg
| state=[[Ohio]]
| district=[[Ohio's 17th congressional district|17th]]
| birth_place=[[Youngstown, Ohio]]
| birth_date={{Birth date and age|1941|5|8|mf=y}}
| spouse=Patricia &quot;Tish&quot; Choppa Traficant
| party=[[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] (1981-2010)&lt;br&gt;Independent (2010-present)
| preceded=[[Lyle Williams]]
| succeeded=[[Tim Ryan (politician)|Tim Ryan]]
| term=January 3, 1985 &amp;ndash; July 24, 2002
| religion=[[Roman Catholic]]
| website=[http://traficantspeaks.com/ Traficant Speaks]
}}

'''James Anthony Traficant, Jr.''' (born May 8, 1941) is a former [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] in the [[United States Congress]] from [[Ohio]] (from 1985 to 2002).  He represented the 17th Congressional District, which centered on his hometown of [[Youngstown]] and included parts of three counties in northeast Ohio's [[Mahoning Valley]]. He was [[Expulsion from the United States Congress|expelled]] after being convicted of taking bribes, filing false tax returns, [[racketeering]], and forcing his aides to perform chores at his farm in Ohio and on his houseboat in [[Washington, D.C.]],&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://archives.cnn.com/2002/LAW/04/11/traficant.trial/ | title = Archives | publisher = CNN.com | accessdate = 2007-11-12 | date=April 11, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was released from prison on September 2, 2009, after serving a seven-year sentence.

Traficant signed a limited, three-month contract to work as a part-time weekend [[talk radio]] host for [[Cleveland]] news/talk station [[WTAM]] in January 2010.  His contract permitted him to quit if he chose to run for office.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vindy.com/news/2010/jan/05/traficant-lands-a-part-time-job-on-radio/?newswatch Traficant lands a part-time job on radio]&lt;/ref&gt;  As of July 2010, it remains unclear if Traficant will return to the station; the WTAM website currently makes no mention of him.&lt;ref&gt;http://ohiomediawatch.wordpress.com/2010/07/07/closure-is-coming/&lt;/ref&gt;

Traficant ran for his old seat in the 2010 general election as an independent;&lt;ref name=2010-election&gt;{{cite web |title=In less than a minute, Traficant is on the ballot |url=http://www.vindy.com/news/2010/sep/01/in-less-than-a-minute-traficant-is-on-th/ |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |date=2010-09-01 |accessdate=2010-09-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; he was defeated by incumbent [[Tim Ryan (politician)|Tim Ryan]].&lt;ref name=2002-election&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.vindy.com/news/2010/nov/02/election-update-ex-congressman-james-traficant-jr-/|title=ELECTION UPDATE: Ex-congressman James A. Traficant Jr. loses new bid for Congress|date=2010-11-02|work=The New York Times|accessdate=2010-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and career==
Born into a working-class, [[Roman Catholicism|Catholic]] family in [[Youngstown, Ohio]], Traficant graduated from [[Cardinal Mooney High School]] in 1959 and the [[University of Pittsburgh]] in 1963 (where he was a standout in football), was [[1963 NFL Draft|drafted]] into the NFL in the twentieth round (276th overall) by the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]] in 1963, and obtained a master's degree from the University of Pittsburgh and another from [[Youngstown State University]]. He was the executive director of the Mahoning County Drug Program from 1971 to 1981 and Sheriff of Mahoning County from 1981 to 1985. While serving as Sheriff, Traficant made national headlines by refusing to execute foreclosure orders on several unemployed homeowners, many of whom had been left unemployed by the recent closures of steel mills. This endeared him to the local population, which had long derived its wealth from steel and steel-associated businesses.&lt;ref name=&quot;peykonyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D81531F93BA15751C0A9649C8B63&amp;st=cse&amp;sq=peyko&amp;scp=1 | first = Mark C | last = Peyko |title = Notes From Youngstown: The Angry Voice of a City Left Behind | work = The New York Times | accessdate = 2008-03-24 | date=February 28, 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1983, he was charged with racketeering for accepting bribes. Traficant, who represented himself in the criminal trial, argued that he accepted the bribes only as part of an undercover investigation into corruption. Traficant was acquitted of the charges, becoming the only person ever to win a [[Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act]] (RICO) case while representing himself.

Publicity from the RICO trial increased Traficant's local visibility. He was elected as a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democrat]] to Congress from Ohio's 17th District, defeating [[Lyle Williams]], a three-term [[United States Republican Party|Republican]] incumbent. He was reelected eight times without serious opposition.

On April 12, 2002, after a two-month federal trial, a jury found Traficant guilty of bribery and other charges. He was sentenced to a federal prison, where he served seven years. He was expelled from the U.S. Congress on July 24, 2002 by a 420-1 vote. The sole Congressman voting against expulsion was [[Gary Condit]], who at the time was in the midst of a scandal involving the disappearance of his former intern, [[Chandra Levy]].

== 2010 Independent candidate for the US House of Representatives ==
In September 2010, Traficant was certified to run for the same seat he held in the US House of Representatives before his expulsion.&lt;ref name=&quot;2010-election&quot;/&gt; Traficant lost the election to former aide [[Tim Ryan (politician)|Tim Ryan]], to whom he lost an earlier race in 2002.&lt;ref name=&quot;2010-election&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/07/us/the-2002-elections-midwest-ohio.html|title=The 2002 Elections: Midwest; Ohio|date=2002-11-07|work=The New York Times|accessdate=2009-11-13 | first1=Nichole M. | last1=Christian | first2=John H. | last2=Cushman Jr | first3=Sherri | last3=Day | first4=Sam | last4=Dillon | first5=Neil A. | last5=Lewis | first6=Robert | last6=Pear | first7=Terry | last7=Pristin | first8=Philip | last8=Shenon | first9=Jacques | last9=Steinberg}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Independent voice==
{{npov|date = November 2010}}
In the House, Traficant was known for his flamboyant and eccentric style. He was a constant thorn in the side of the Democratic caucus with his eccentric behavior, an image he embraced.  He often dressed poorly {{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}, with narrow neck ties (then out of style), wide-lapelled sportcoats and an occasional [[denim]] suit.  He also sported an unkempt [[Pompadour (hairstyle)|pompadour]], which he jokingly claimed he cut with a [[weed whacker]] (it was revealed, after his conviction, that he wore a [[toupée]]).  Casting himself as a rough-hewn [[Populism|populist]] and &quot;regular guy,&quot; he gave speeches that were far outside the staid norms of political speaking. Many people tuned into [[C-SPAN]] just to watch his one-minute speeches at the beginning of each day's sitting.{{Citation needed|date=February 2008}} His trademark closing lines were &quot;[[Beam me up, Scotty|Beam me up]]... I yield back the fact...&quot; His Website featured a picture of him swinging a two-by-four with the words &quot;Bangin' away in D.C.&quot;

After the Republicans took control of the House in 1995, Traficant tended to vote more often with the Republicans than with his own party. On abortion, for instance, Traficant voted the [[pro-life]] position of the [[National Right to Life Committee]] (NRLC) 95% of the time in the 105th Congress, and 100% of the time in the 106th and 107th Congresses.  However, he voted against all four articles of impeachment against [[Bill Clinton]]. After he voted for Republican [[Dennis Hastert]] for [[Speaker of the United States House of Representatives|Speaker of the House]] in 2001, the Democrats stripped him of his seniority and refused to give him a committee assignment. Because the Republicans did not assign him to any committee, Traficant became the first member of the House of Representatives in over a century without any committee assignment who was not in a leadership position.{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}} 

Traficant championed the unpopular cause of [[John Demjanjuk]], a [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]]-born autoworker from [[Seven Hills, Ohio|Seven Hills]], who had been convicted in [[Israel]] and sentenced to hang for having been the brutal [[concentration camp]] guard &quot;Ivan the Terrible.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jta.org/news/article/2009/10/30/1008850/trafican-says-he-will-testify-for-demjanjuk Traficant says he would testify for Demjanjuk], ''[[Jewish Telegraphic Agency]]''&lt;/ref&gt; For almost a decade, Traficant (along with [[Pat Buchanan]])&lt;ref&gt;[[Pat Buchanan|Buchanan, Pat]] (2011-05-13) [http://www.amconmag.com/blog/2011/05/12/demjanjuk-convicted-by-the-kgb/ Demjanjuk Convicted — By the KGB], ''[[The American Conservative]]''&lt;/ref&gt; insisted that Demjanjuk had been denied a fair trial, and been the victim of mistaken identity; the [[Supreme Court of Israel]] eventually overturned the conviction, on the basis of doubt, in 1993. Demjanjuk was later deported to Germany on May 11, 2009, after the United States Supreme Court refused to overturn his deportation order.
  
While in Congress, Traficant was a supporter of [[immigration reduction]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://profiles.numbersusa.com/improfile.php3?DistSend=OH&amp;VIPID=647 All Immigration Votes of Representative James Traficant].&quot; [[NumbersUSA]]. Accessed January 6, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and a strong opponent of [[illegal immigration]]. In the controversy surrounding the [[Bob Dornan#Defeat|defeat of Congressman Bob Dornan]] (R-CA) by Democrat [[Loretta Sanchez]], Traficant was the only Democratic member of Congress who advocated a new election, due to possible voting in that race by illegal aliens. Sanchez would later introduce a bill expelling Traficant from the House of Representatives.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/ALLPOLITICS/07/25/cf.crossfire/index.html Congress beams up Traficant].&quot; ''[[Crossfire (TV series)|In the Crossfire]]''. [[CNN]]. July 25, 2002. Accessed January 6, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Indictment, conviction, testimony to House Ethics, and expulsion from Congress==
{{Expand section|details on charges and allegations|date=November 2010}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Traficantmug.jpg|thumb|left|150px|Summit County Ohio Jail Mugshot of James Traficant, August 1, 2002.]] --&gt;
In 2002, Traficant was indicted on federal corruption charges for taking campaign funds for personal use. Again, he opted to represent himself, insisting that the trial was part of a vendetta against him dating to his 1983 trial. On April 15, he was convicted of 10 felony counts including bribery, racketeering, and tax evasion.  As per House rules, he lost his right to vote on legislation pending an investigation by the [[U.S. House Committee on Standards of Official Conduct|House Ethics Committee]].

Eventually, the House Ethics Committee recommended that Traficant be expelled from Congress. On July 24 the House voted 420-1 to expel him. [[Gary Condit]] was the lone &quot;no&quot; vote, and nine members voted &quot;present.&quot; Traficant was the first representative to be expelled since [[Michael Myers (politician)|Michael Myers]]'s expulsion in 1980 as a result of the [[Abscam]] scandal.

After his expulsion, Traficant ran as an independent candidate for another term in the House while incarcerated at the [[Federal Correctional Institute, Allenwood]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://archives.cnn.com/2002/ALLPOLITICS/08/05/traficant.prison/|title=Traficant arrives at federal prison|date=2002-08-06|publisher=CNN|accessdate=2009-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; He received 15 percent of the vote (27,487 votes) and became one of only a handful of individuals in the history of the United States to run for a federal office from prison. The election was won by one of his former aides, Tim Ryan.&lt;ref name=&quot;2010-election&quot;/&gt;

== Prison ==
James A. Traficant, Jr. had the [[Federal Bureau of Prisons]] ID # 31213-060.&lt;ref name=&quot;TraficantBOP&quot;&gt;&quot;[http://www.bop.gov/iloc2/InmateFinderServlet?Transaction=NameSearch&amp;needingMoreList=false&amp;FirstName=James&amp;Middle=&amp;LastName=Traficant&amp;Race=U&amp;Sex=U&amp;Age=&amp;x=0&amp;y=0 JAMES A TRAFICANT JR].&quot; [[Federal Bureau of Prisons]]. Retrieved on May 29, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Traficant served his first 17 months in prison at [[FCI Allenwood]] and shortly after, he was shackled and put in [[solitary confinement]] for causing a riot after telling a guard, &quot;People can't hear you. Speak up.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Susteren&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,549164,00.html|title=Exclusive: Traficant - 'I Was a Target. ... I Must Have Been Doing Something Right'|last=Van Susteren|first=Greta|date=2009-09-10|publisher=Fox News|accessdate=2009-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; For nine months, beginning in March 2004, he served with 20 inmates in one locked room at the [[Federal Correctional Institution]] Raybrook with a public commode, and with four in a room at [[Federal Medical Center, Rochester]] for three years.  He was admonished by prison officials  in Raybrook he was only a &quot;few points away&quot; from a penitentiary.  In the seven years of incarceration, he refused any visitors because he didn't want anyone to see him.  He wore his hair in a pony tail without his trademark hairpiece. Traficant took up artwork while in prison; according to his wife, he did not have access to a computer there.&lt;ref name=&quot;davidduke&quot; /&gt; &quot;I understood the dynamics of prison life.&quot; Regarding the overcrowded prison system he said, &quot;And now what you have is, they want to keep the prisons open, keep the jobs going. They're putting 20, 30 years on some of these young people, and it's out of hand.&quot; He was released on September 2, 2009, at age 68, and is subject to three years of [[probation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cantonrep.com/ohio/x1595417268/Ex-congressman-Traficant-freed |title=Ex-congressman Traficant freed |author=Merchant, Norman |date=2009-09-02 |accessdate=2009-09-29 |publisher=[[Associated Press]] |work=Canton Rep}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While in prison, Traficant received support from [[David Duke]], who urged visitors to his personal website to donate to Traficant's canteen fund. Duke also posted a letter written by Traficant stating that he was targeted by the [[U.S. Department of Justice]] for, among other things, defending [[John Demjanjuk]]. Traficant also claimed, in the letter, that he knew facts about &quot;[[Waco Siege|Waco]], [[Ruby Ridge]], [[Pan Am Flight 103]], [[Jimmy Hoffa]] and the [[John F. Kennedy assassination|assassination of]] [[President of the United States|President]] [[John F. Kennedy]]&quot;, which he may divulge in the future. Author [[Michael Collins Piper]], who initially helped circulate Traficant's letter, said that &quot;There's stuff I've written about Traficant that's showing up in places I don't even know. It's like (six) degrees of separation with the Internet now,&quot; and denied that Traficant had any direct connections to Duke.&lt;ref name=&quot;davidduke&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tribtoday.com/page/content.detail/id/526652.html?nav=5021|title=White nationalists, conspiracy theorists join Traficant’s cause|accessdate=September 21, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Release from prison ===
Traficant was released from prison on September 2, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;TraficantBOP&quot;/&gt; On September 6, 2009, 1200 supporters welcomed him home at a banquet with an [[Elvis Presley impersonator|Elvis]] impersonator and a Traficant look-a-like contest. &quot;Welcome home Jimbo&quot; was printed on T-shirts. &quot;I think it's time to tell the FBI and the IRS that this is our country and we're tired -- tired of the pressure, tired of the political targeting, tired of a powerful central government that is crippling America,&quot; he said. Traficant said he hasn't decided yet whether he will run again for Congress.  He also said he doesn't care about what anyone did to him or does to him in the future. &quot;I'm going to say what I think is right, I'm going to do what I think is right,&quot; he said. &quot;And if it offends some people, then so be it. You see, because I'm still, I guess, the same jackass I was.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/james-traficant-ohio-congressman-released-prison/story?id=8474242 Disgraced Fmr. Rep. James Traficant Released From Prison] by Lindsey Ellerson, ABC News, September 2, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/james-traficant-ohio-democrat-mulls-reelection-prison/story?id=8570801 Ex-Con Jim Traficant Weighs Reelection to House] by Devin Dwyer, ABC News, September 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/09/02/AR2009090201497.html Traficant Completes Sentence for Bribery] by Mary Jordan, Washington Post, September 3, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Current political views ==
In an interview with [[Fox News]]' [[Greta Van Susteren]] in September, 2009,&lt;ref name=&quot;Van Susteren&quot;/&gt; he said he was the top target of [[AIPAC]] and the U.S. [[United States Department of Justice|Justice Department]]. On the subject of Israel, he stated:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
They [Israel] are controlling much of our foreign policy. They're influencing much of our domestic policy.

Wolfowitz as undersecretary of defense manipulated President Bush number two back into Iraq. They've pushed definitely, definitely to try to get Bush before he left to move into Iran.

We're conducting the expansionist policy of Israel and everybody's afraid to say it. They control much of the media, they control much of the commerce of the country, and they control powerfully both bodies of the Congress. They own the Congress.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

He claimed he had predicted another [[economic depression]], but people at the time had just laughed at him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5gjJUTTLw_kZgh3K75M4W9F5J_HwgD9AKNHI80 Traficant: I could have been hurt while in prison], Associated Press (posted on Google.com), September 10, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cleveland.com/news/plaindealer/index.ssf?/base/cuyahoga/1252312376162330.xml&amp;coll=2 Traficant rips 'enemies' at welcome-home party] by Janet Okoben, The Plain Dealer (Cleveland.com) September 07, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://jta.org/news/article/2009/09/13/1007797/traficant-says-israel-has-stranglehold-on-us-govt Traficant: Israel has ‘stranglehold’ on U.S. gov’t], Jewish Telegraphic Agency (JTA), September 13, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Traficant has also expressed his support of the [[Fair Tax]] plan and criticized President Obama's [[American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009|stimulus bill]]. He has said of Congress, &quot;I think it is a big whorehouse and they better start taking care of America and stop worrying about the [[Middle East]] and worry about the [[Midwest]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;stimulate&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0909/27505.html#ixzz0S228AuPo|title=Jim Traficant: 'Stimulate this'|accessdate=September 24, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After his release from prison, he was featured as a guest speaker at a [[Tea Party Protest]] in [[Columbiana, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=&quot;teabag&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.business-journal.com/default.asp?sourceid=&amp;smenu=1&amp;twindow=&amp;mad=&amp;sdetail=14598&amp;wpage=1&amp;skeyword=&amp;sidate=&amp;ccat=&amp;ccatm=&amp;restate=&amp;restatus=&amp;reoption=&amp;retype=&amp;repmin=&amp;repmax=&amp;rebed=&amp;rebath=&amp;subname=&amp;pform=&amp;sc=1711&amp;hn=business-journal&amp;he=.com|title=Traficant Draws Cheers at TEA Party|accessdate=September 16, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has also committed to speaking at an [[American Free Press]]-sponsored event in Washington D.C. in February.&lt;ref name=&quot;afp&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1209/31066.html|title=Jim Traficant: 'I'm going to run'|accessdate=December 30, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2010, Traficant filed petitions to [[United States House of Representatives elections in Ohio, 2010|run as an independent]] in the 17th district, and said that his platform would be to repeal the [[16th Amendment to the United States Constitution]].&lt;ref name=&quot;sixteenth&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ohio.com/news/break_news/92681999.html|title=Traficant files petitions to be candidate for Akron congressional district|accessdate=May 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Traficant ultimately received 16% of the vote, finishing third to Democratic incumbent Ryan (54%) and Republican challenger Jim Graham (30%).&lt;ref&gt;http://www.politicsdaily.com/tag/Jim%20Traficant/&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of United States Representatives from Ohio]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{CongLinks|congbio=T000350}}
*[http://www.yourcongress.com/section.asp?section=Daily_Traficant Traficant Speeches and Explusion Hearing Transcript]
*[http://www.cnn.com/2002/LAW/08/01/congress.traficant &quot;Look at what Traficant swept under the rug&quot;] — [[CNN]], August 1, 2002
*[http://www.thememoryhole.org/traficant Archive of many of Traficant's congressional speeches]
*[http://arc.republicbroadcasting.org/Piper/07/08/Piper_080307_200000.MP3 RBN Radio Broadcast on the Jim Traficant Case (8/03/07)]
*[http://wtam.com/pages/JimTraficantOnDemand.html Jim Traficant On Demand - WTAM archive]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gKrlTfMMncM Jim Traficant on The Alex Jones Show (PrisonPlanet.TV), 19 February 2010] (YouTube)
*[http://www.criticalpast.com/video/65675034000_football-match_Pittsburgh-Panthers_Pitt-Scuttles-of-Navy_spectators-watch-the-match Trafficant quarterbacking Pitt over Navy]

{{S-start}}
{{s-par|us-hs}}
{{USRepSuccession box
| state=Ohio
| district=17
| before=[[Lyle Williams]]
| after=[[Tim Ryan (politician)|Tim Ryan]]
| years=January 3, 1985 &amp;ndash; July 24, 2002
}}
{{S-end}}

{{Persondata
|NAME=Traficant, James
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=Traficant, James Anthony, Jr. (full name); Traficant, Jim (nickname)
|SHORT DESCRIPTION=Ohio politician
|DATE OF BIRTH=May 8, 1941
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Youngstown, Ohio]]
|DATE OF DEATH=living
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Traficant, James}}
[[Category:American anti–illegal immigration activists]]
[[Category:American people of Italian descent]]
[[Category:Ohio sheriffs]]
[[Category:American talk radio hosts]]
[[Category:People convicted of bribery]]
[[Category:Conspiracy theorists]]
[[Category:American people convicted of tax crimes]]
[[Category:Expelled United States Representatives]]
[[Category:Members of the United States House of Representatives from Ohio]]
[[Category:Ohio Democrats]]
[[Category:Paleoconservatism]]
[[Category:People convicted of racketeering]]
[[Category:People from Youngstown, Ohio]]
[[Category:Pittsburgh Panthers football players]]
[[Category:Prisoners and detainees of the United States federal government]]
[[Category:United States presidential candidates, 1988]]
[[Category:University of Pittsburgh alumni]]
[[Category:American football quarterbacks]]
[[Category:1941 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[de:James Traficant]]
[[fr:James Traficant]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
