<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30722713" ns="0" title="UST Parks and Gardens"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Wikify|date=March 2011}}

The university has built a handful of parks and gardens inside its campus.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.varsitarian.net/filipino/usapang_uste/20100218/mga_liwasan_sa_loob_ng_ust Mga liwasan sa loob ng UST]. Retrieved 2 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== List of Parks and Gardens ==
{{University of Santo Tomas campus map}}
[[File:UST Football Field.jpg|300px|thumb|left|The '''Plaza Mayor''' in the foreground, the '''Beato Angelico''' Bldg, Football Field and Grandstand in the background.]]

=== Plaza Intramuros ===
It is houses the [[Arch of the Centuries]], Fountain of Knowledge, Fountain of Wisdom, and the University Marker. It is located along Intramuros Drive opposite the main vehicular gate.

=== Plaza Benavides ===
It houses the Shrine of Fr. [[Miguel de Benavides]], the pedestrian lanes, and its surrounding open spaces. It is bound by Plaza Intramuros on its north side, Plaza Mayor on its south side, and Osmeña and Quezon Drives on its left and right side.

The pedestrian lanes inside the park are popularly called Lovers’ Lane. The three lanes are named Rizal Lane (center), Burgos Lane (left), and Del Pilar Lane (right). Scattered around the vicinity are ruin-stones of the University’s old school building from Intramuros. 

In December 8, 2010, the park played a huge role during the mounting of the University’s bid to put up the world’s largest living rosary. It became a venue in putting of the rosary’s cross, Our Father bead, Holy Mary beads, and Glory Be bead.

=== Plaza Mayor ===
It is a concreted park in front the [[Main Building (University of Santo Tomas)|Main Building]].

Before the plaza was built, the site is a combination of a street and a parking space.

=== Plaza Calderon ===
This used to be as wide as facade of the original gymnasium but most of which were converted into a basketball court. It is located beside the Santissimo Rosario Parish Church in front of the University Gymnasium.

=== Quadricentennial Square ===
It houses the [[UST Quadricentennial Celebration#Quadricentennial Fountain|Quadricentennial Fountain]] and [[UST Quadricentennial Celebration#Quattromondial|Quattromondial]].

=== The Alumni Walkway ===
It is a walkway housing a row of bulletin boards along Quezon Drive.

=== Tinoko Park ===
The original site of Tinoko Park is the current location of [[University of Santo Tomas Miguel de Benavides Library
|Miguel de Benavides Library]]. Today’s Tinoko Park used to be a garbage dump and used to be known as Peñafort Mall. It was designed by then Architecture dean Jose Pardo commissioned by then university treasurer Fr. Jose Tinoko.

=== Botanical Garden and Rosarium ===
It is found between the Santissimo Rosario Parish Church and the Main Building. It was previously called Pharmacy Garden as it was established by then Faculty of Pharmacy dean Fr. Lorenzo Rodriguez. In 1977, then rector Fr. Leonardo Legaspi renamed it as how it is called today.

This heavily-fenced garden houses cages for butterflies and monkeys, and various plants and trees.

== Pavilions ==
=== St. Raymund Peñafort Pavilions ===
These are the pavilions in front St. Raymund Peñafort Building.

=== St. Martin de Porres Pavilions ===
These are the pavilions in front St. Martin de Porres Building.

=== Tamayo Drive Pavilions ===
These are the pavilions found along Tamayo Drive on both sides of the UST Grandstand.

=== Ruaño Drive Pavilions ===
These are the pavilions along Roque Ruaño Drive.

=== Gonzales Drive Pavilions ===
It is a row of pavilions and benches that can be found in front of Santissimo Rosario Parish Church along Gonzales Drive.

== Defunct and Abolished Parks ==
=== Colayco Park ===
It is the predecessor of today’s Quadricentennial Square. It used to house an outdoor amphitheater, fish pond, and then-erected Cooperative Canteen. In here, the Colayco Shrine once stood.

=== Matryrs Park ===
It is was a park in front of Miguel de Benavides Library on the site of Tan Yan Kee Student Center. It used to house the monument of [[Lorenzo Ruiz|San Lorenzo Ruiz]] and his companion [[Thomasian Martyrs|Dominican martyrs]]. This monument was designed by professor Leonardo Hidalgo commissioned by then rector Fr. Norberto Castillo. The monument is set to be erected again on its new site – the open space in front the Santissimo Rosario Parish Church.

== See also ==
* [[List of University of Santo Tomas buildings]]
* [[UST Streets and Driveways]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{UST}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Parks And Gardens, Ust}}
[[Category:University of Santo Tomas]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
