<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian protests" to="Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="30886922" ns="0" title="Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=March 2011}}
{{Copy edit|date=July 2011}}
{{Politics of Egypt}}

The following is a chronological summary of the major events that took place during the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]].

== Before Mubarak's resignation ==
{{main|Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Hosni Mubarak's rule}}

=== January ===

'''25 January 2011''': The '''&quot;Day of Revolt&quot;''', nationwide protests against the government of Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak began. Tens of thousands of protestors gathered in Cairo, with thousands more in cities throughout Egypt. The protests were generally non-violent, but there were reports of some casualties among both civilians and police. After several Facebook groups were created and so-called tweets (from [[Twitter]]) facilitated mass demonstrations, the Egyptian government decided to shut down access to Twitter, although Egyptians were still able to access the website through third-party mobile applications. The Twitter block was lifted the next day.

'''26 January 2011''': (.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cowie |first=James |url=http://www.renesys.com/blog/2011/01/egypt-leaves-the-internet.shtml |title=Egypt Leaves the Internet |publisher=Renesys.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was done to impede protestors' communication. Protests across Egypt gained steam, violence continued as police attempted to force protesters off the streets. Live bullets fired at demonstrators. At least three people reported dead from violence. It was reported that injuries resulting from police violence reached 120 in Suez alone.

'''27 January 2011''': Protests on this day were not as large-scale as those of the previous two days, as many Egyptians had been preparing themselves for the planned &quot;Friday of Anger&quot; that was to take place the following day. At around 7:00 PM local time, Egyptian authorities blocked access to Facebook, although many Egyptians were still able to bypass the block through the use of proxies and third party applications.

'''28 January 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of Rage&quot;''' protests began. Just after midnight, the Egyptian authorities ordered most Communication and Internet services to be shut down in an attempt to disrupt the protests. That same morning, the authorities had also shut down the country's mobile phone carriers (namely Vodafone, Mobinil, and Etisalat). Shortly after Friday prayers, hundreds of thousands gathered in Cairo and other Egyptian cities. Opposition leader Mohammed ElBaradei traveled to Cairo to participate.  Some looting was reported. Police forces withdrew from the streets completely, and the Egyptian government ordered the military to assist the police. International fears of violence grew, but no major casualties were reported.

'''29 January 2011''': Protests continued as military presence in Cairo increased. A curfew was instituted, but protests continued throughout the night. The military showed restraint, reportedly refusing to obey orders to use live ammunition; there were no reports of major casualties.

'''30 January 2011''': [[Egyptian Air Force]] [[F-16]]s overfly Tahrir Square in a show of force.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dawn.com/2011/01/31/fighter-jets-fly-over-protesters-as-chaos-rules-cairo.html |title=Fighter jets fly over protesters as chaos rules Cairo &amp;#124; Newspaper |publisher=Dawn.Com |date=2011-01-31 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''31 January 2011''': '''&quot;The March of the Millions&quot;'''. A protest of over a million people was planned for this day. News agencies have various counts for how many protesters were actually in Tahrir Square that day (Some say there were less than a million, considering the square only holds 250,000 people, but other sources like Al Jazeera argue that there were as many as 2 million in the square and its surrounding areas).

=== February ===

'''1 February 2011''': Mubarak made a televised address once again after unceasing protests, and offered several concessions. He pledged he would not run for another term in elections planned for September, and pledged political reforms. He stated he would stay in office to oversee a peaceful transition. Small but violent clashes began that night between pro-Mubarak and anti-Mubarak groups.

'''2 February 2011''': '''&quot;Battle of the Camel&quot;'''. Violence escalated as waves of Mubarak supporters met anti-government protesters, and some Mubarak supporters rode on camels and horses into Tahrir Square, reportedly wielding swords and sticks. The clashes were believed to have been orchestrated by Habib El Adly, and there were hundreds of casualties. The military tried to limit the violence, repeatedly separating anti-Mubarak and pro-Mubarak groups. President Mubarak reiterated his refusal to step down in interviews with several news agencies. Incidents of violence toward journalists and reporters escalated amid speculation that the violence was being actively aggravated by Mubarak as a way to end the protests.

'''3 February 2011''': Gunmen fire on anti-government protesters in Cairo, where about 10 are killed and more than 830 injured in fighting. The U.N. estimates that 300 people have died in the unrest.

'''4 February 2011''': Thousands gather in Tahrir Square to again press for an end to Mubarak's rule in a &quot;Friday of Departure.&quot;

'''5 February 2011''': Protests in Cairo and throughout the nation continued.  Egyptian Christians held Sunday Mass in Tahrir Square, protected by a ring of Muslims.  Negotiations began between Egyptian Vice President Omar Suleiman and opposition representatives.  The Egyptian army increased its security role, maintaining order and protecting Egypt’s museums.  Suleiman offered political and constitutional reforms while other members of the Mubarak regime accused nations, including the US, of interfering in Egypt’s affairs.

'''6 February 2011''': Egyptian Christians held Sunday Mass in Tahrir Square, protected by a ring of Muslims. Negotiations involving Egyptian Vice President Omar Suleiman and representatives of the opposition commenced amid continuing protests throughout the nation. The Egyptian army assumed greater security responsibilities, maintaining order and guarding Egypt’s museums. Suleiman offered reforms, while others of Mubarak's regime accused foreign nations, including the US, of interfering in Egypt’s affairs.

'''7 February 2011''': MENA reports Mubarak has set up two committees to draw up changes to the constitution. The stock market remains closed. Opposition figures report little progress in talks with the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://us.mobile.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSTRE7197R920110210?feedType=RSS&amp;feedName=topNews |title=Timeline: 17 days of protests against Hosni Mubarak |publisher=Us.mobile.reuters.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''8 February 2011''': Egyptians stage one of their biggest protests. Vice President Suleiman says Egypt has a timetable for the peaceful transfer of power. He promises no reprisals against the protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.irishexaminer.com/world/kfeyojauojsn/rss2/ |title=‘The people killed the regime’ |publisher=Irish Examiner |date=2011-02-12 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''9 February 2011''': Four people are killed and several wounded in clashes between security forces and about 3,000 protesters in the western province of New Valley, south of Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allvoices.com/contributed-news/8147720-4-killed-in-clashes-between-police-and-protesters-in-egypt/content/61938034-hosni-mubarak |title=4 killed in clashes between police and protesters in Egypt |publisher=Allvoices.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''10 February 2011''': Mubarak formally addressed Egypt amid speculation of a military coup, but rather than resigning (as was widely expected), he simply stated he would delegate some of his powers to Vice President Suleiman, while continuing as Egypt's head of state. Reactions to Mubarak's statement were marked by anger, frustration and disappointment, and throughout various cities there was an escalation of the number and intensity of demonstrations.

'''11 February 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of Departure&quot;''', Egyptians did not settle for Mubarak's announcement of ceding his powers to Suleiman, and set up massive protests in many Egyptian cities. At 6:00 p.m. local time, Suleiman announced Mubarak's resignation and that the Supreme Council of Egyptian Armed Forces would assume leadership of the country.

== Post-Mubarak ==
{{main|Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Supreme Council of the Armed Forces}}

=== February ===

'''12 February 2011''': People celebrated in Tahrir Square until early morning. Pro-democracy protesters started to clean the square.
The country's new military rulers promised to hand power to an elected, civilian government and pledged that Egypt will remain committed to all international treaties - in an apparent nod to its 1979 peace treaty with Israel.
State television says travel bans are being imposed on several of the country's former ministers, including the former prime minister Ahmed Nazif, who was sacked by Mubarak before he stepped down.

'''13 February 2011''': The Supreme Council of Egyptian Armed Forces dissolved Egypt’s parliament and suspended the Constitution. The council also declared that it would hold power for six months or until elections could be held, whichever came first. ElBaradei urged the council to provide more details to the Egyptian people regarding its plans. Major protests subsided but uncertainty remained, and many pledged to keep returning to Tahrir square until all demands had been met.

'''14 February 2011''': Protesters left Tahrir Square in the morning but a few thousands returned later, most of them protesting against the police.
Police, ambulance drivers and other workers held separate demonstrations.
The military leadership issued &quot;Communique No 5&quot;, calling for national solidarity and criticizing strike action; It urged workers to play their role in reviving the economy.

'''17 February 2011''': The army stated on 17 February 2011 it would not field a candidate in the upcoming presidential elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forexyard.com/en/news/Egypt-army-says-wont-field-presidential-candidate-2011-02-17T144839Z |title=Egypt army says won't field presidential candidate |publisher=Forexyard.com |date= |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; Four important figures of the former regime were detained on that day: former interior minister [[Habib el-Adly]], former minister of housing [[Ahmed Maghrabi]] and former tourism minister [[Zuheir Garana]], as well as steel tycoon [[Ahmed Ezz]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12500968 |title=BBC News - Egypt after Mubarak: Three ex-ministers arrested |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-02-15 |accessdate=2011-02-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''21 February 2011''': On 21 February, [[David Cameron]], Prime Minister of the [[United Kingdom]], became the first world leader to visit Egypt since Mubarak was ousted as the president 10 days previously. A news blackout was lifted as the prime minister landed in Cairo for a brief five-hour stopover hastily added at the start of a planned tour of the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2011/feb/21/david-cameron-visits-egypt?CMP=twt_fd |title=David Cameron visits Egypt - The Guardian |publisher=www.guardian.co.uk |date= 21 February 2011|accessdate=2011-02-21 |location=London |first=Nicholas |last=Watt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''25 February 2011''': Protesters returned to Tahrir Square to continue to keep up the pressure on the interim government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://af.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idAFTRE70O18Y20110225 |title=Egyptians pack Tahrir for protest and celebration &amp;#124; World &amp;#124; Reuters |publisher=Af.reuters.com |date=2011-02-25 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== March ===
'''2 March 2011''': The [[Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011|constitutional referendum]] has been tentatively scheduled for 19 March 2011, but the date is yet to be officially confirmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/d67e07da-4420-11e0-931d-00144feab49a.html#axzz1FTmeSur8 |title=/ Middle East / Politics &amp; Society - Egypt sets constitutional referendum date |publisher=Ft.com |date=2011-03-01 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''3 March 2011''': A day before large protests against him were planned, [[Ahmed Shafik]] stepped down as PM and was replaced by [[Essam Sharaf]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forexyard.com/en/news/Egypts-prime-minsiter-quits-new-govt-soon-army-2011-03-03T093300Z |title=Egypt's prime minsiter quits, new govt soon-army |publisher=Forexyard.com |date=2011-03-03 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''4 March 2011''': Sharaf returned to [[Tahrir Square]] (which he had also visited during the revolution) to address the Friday mass rally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rferl.org/content/egypt_sharaf/2328017.html |title=Egypt Protesters Storm Security Facility - Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty © 2011 |publisher=Rferl.org |date=2011-03-04 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''5 March 2011''': Several SSI buildings were raided across Egypt by protesters, including the headquarters in Alexandria. Protesters state they raided in the buildings to secure documents they believed to show various crimes committed by the SSI against the people of Egypt during Mubarak's rule.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/201134228359128.html |title=Egypt security building stormed - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2011-03-05 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url = http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/spotlight/anger-in-egypt/2011/03/2011368410372200.html | title = A first step towards prosecutions? | first = Gregg | last = Carlstrom | date = 6 Mar 2011 | publisher = Al Jazeera }}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''6 March 2011''': From the Nasr City headquarters protesters acquired evidence of [[mass surveillance]] and vote rigging, and noted rooms full of videotapes, piles of shredded and burned documents, and cells where activists recounted their experiences of detention and torture.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;/&gt;

'''19 March 2011''': The [[Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011|constitutional referendum]] was held and passed by 77.27%&lt;ref name=results&gt;{{cite web |url= http://referendum.eg/84-slideshow/158-2011-03-20-19-09-58.html |title= الأرقام الفعلية للتصويت |publisher = اللجنة القضائية العليا للإشراف علي استفتاء تعديل الدستور المصري |language=[[Arabic]] |accessdate = 2011-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''22 March 2011''': Parts of Interior Ministry building catches fire during police demonstrations outside it.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Diaa Hadid, The Associated Press: Tuesday, March 22, 2011 |url=http://www.globaltoronto.com/Fire+sweeps+Egypt+Interior+Ministry+building+police+protest+outside+demand+higher/4484415/story.html |title=Fire sweeps Egypt's Interior Ministry building as police protest outside to demand higher pay |publisher=Globaltoronto.com |date=2011-03-22 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''23 March 2011''': The [[Cabinet of Egypt|Egyptian Cabinet]] orders a law criminalizing protests and strikes. Under the new law, anyone organizing or calling for a protest will be sentenced to jail and/or a fine of LE500,000 (~100,000 USD).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/371465 |title=New Egyptian law criminalizes protests &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=2011-03-23 |accessdate=2011-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''29 March 2011''': Protesters clashed in front of interior ministry headquarters in Cairo on Wednesday.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bradley |first=Matt |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304450604576415150417930250.html#articleTabs%3Darticle |title=Anger With Police Fuels Cairo Riots - WSJ.com |publisher=Online.wsj.com |date= 30 June 2011|accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== April ===
'''1 April 2011''': The '''&quot;Save the Revolution&quot;''' day, Thousands of demonstrators filled Tahrir Square on Friday for the largest protest in weeks, demanding that the ruling military council move faster to dismantle lingering aspects of the old regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/02/world/middleeast/02egypt.html?_r=1 |title=Protesters Scold Egypt’s Military Council |publisher=Neil MacFarquhar |date=2011-04-01 |accessdate=2011-04-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''2 April 2011''': Egypt urges Russia, Italy and the US to ease travel ban.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/129849/20110402/egypt-urges-us-to-ease-travel-ban-egypt-tour-egypt-tourism-russia-italy-egypt-travel-warning.htm |title=Egypt urges US to ease travel ban |publisher=Ibtimes.com |date=2011-04-02 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''3 April 2011''': Egypt apologizes to Tunisia over [[2011 CAF Champions League qualifying rounds#Zamalek v Club Africain|Champions League violence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Jack Shenker |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/03/egypt-leader-apologises-football-violence |title=Egypt apologises to Tunisia over Champions League violence &amp;#124; World news |publisher=The Guardian |date= 3 April 2011|accessdate=2011-07-01 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''4 April 2011''': Employees from the ministry of agriculture and the Amonsito Textile Company demonstrated outside Cabinet offices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/9295/Egypt/Politics-/Workers-protest-in-front-of-Egypts-Cabinet.aspx |title=Workers protest in front of Egypt's Cabinet - Politics - Egypt - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ''The popular Egyptian delegation'' held unofficial discussions with Uganda president on Nile water usage&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/9263/Egypt/Politics-/Egypts-revolution-knocks-Nile-Basin-doors.aspx |title=Egypt's revolution knocks Nile Basin doors - Politics - Egypt - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''5 April 2011''': Egypt arrests former housing minister Soliman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/04/06/us-egypt-arrest-idUSTRE7352DL20110406 |title=Egypt arrests former housing minister Soliman |publisher=Reuters |date= 6 April 2011|accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''8 April 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of Cleansing&quot;'''; Tens of thousands of demonstrators filled Tahrir Square for the largest protests in weeks, criticizing the ruling Supreme Council of the Armed Forces for not following through on revolution demands. They demanded the resignation of remaining regime figures, and the removal of Egypt’s public prosecutor due to the slow pace of investigations of corrupt former officials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/391552 |title=Tens of thousands in Tahrir as some threaten to extend protests &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date= |accessdate=2011-04-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''9 April 2011''': Egypt’s military used force early Saturday to break up a camp of protesters in Tahrir Square, as tensions continued to build between the pro-democracy movement and the military leadership that has run the country since President Hosni Mubarak’s ouster in February.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/egyptian-military-uses-force-to-break-up-tahrir-square-protest/2011/04/09/AFTVpO6C_story.html |title=Egypt’s military forcibly breaks up Tahrir Square protest; 2 reported killed |publisher=Washington Post |date=2011-04-09 |accessdate=2011-05-22 |first=Leila |last=Fadel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''12 April 2011''': Hosni Mubarak, the former Egyptian president, has been questioned in hospital by prosecutors at the Red Sea port of Sharm el-Sheikh, where he has been staying since he was ousted from power by a popular uprising on February 11.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/04/201141216755944186.html |title=Egypt's Mubarak 'hospitalised' - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2011-04-12 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''13 April 2011''': Egypt’s Prosecutor General has ordered the detention 15 days of the Egyptian former president and his two children, [[Alaa Mubarak]] and [[Gamal Mubarak]], has officially informed. A statement from the Attorney General Egyptian published on its website on Facebook, the arrest warrant was issued after the prosecution presented the charges against them and in accordance with the development of the criminal investigations around the rioting that led to the fall of the regime.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Mark Gregory |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13058855 |title=BBC News&amp;nbsp;— Egypt: Mubarak and sons detained amid corruption probe |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= 13 April 2011|accessdate=2011-04-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/mubarak-and-sons-ordered-detained-for-corruption-probe-egypts-state-television-says/2011/04/13/AFQFifUD_story.html |title=Egypt detains Mubarak and family in probe on wealth and crackdown on protests |publisher=Washington Post |date=2011-04-13 |accessdate=2011-05-22 |first=Leila |last=Fadel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''15 April 2011''': Thousands march from Shoubra to Tahrir in support of rights for Copts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/egypt/thousands-march-from-shoubra-to-tahrir-in-support-of-rights-for-copts.html |title=Thousands march from Shoubra to Tahrir in support of rights for Copts |publisher=Thedailynewsegypt.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''16 April 2011''': The Egyptian supreme administrative court ordered to dissolve the former ruling National Democratic Party (NDP) and hand its assets to the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Egypt dissolves former ruling party |author= |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/04/2011416125051889315.html |newspaper= |date=16 April 2011 |accessdate=16 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''18 April 2011''': Iran appoints first ambassador to Egypt in thirty years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://israelsurvivalupdates.wordpress.com/2011/04/18/iran-and-egypt-sitting-in-a-tree-part-two/ |title=Iran appoints first ambassador to Egypt in thirty years. « Israel Survival Updates |publisher=Israelsurvivalupdates.wordpress.com |date=2011-04-18 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''21 April 2011''': Mubarak's name was removed from all public places.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13162236 | work=BBC News | title=Egypt court: Remove Mubarak name from public places | date=21 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''23 April 2011''': Egypt orders ex-energy minister to stand trial for natural gas deal with Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By Reuters |url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/international/egypt-orders-ex-energy-minister-to-stand-trial-for-natural-gas-deal-with-israel-1.357801 |title=Egypt orders ex-energy minister to stand trial for natural gas deal with Israel - Haaretz Daily Newspaper &amp;#124; Israel News |publisher=Haaretz.com |date=2011-06-01 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''25 April 2011''': A poll released by the Pew Global Attitudes Project shows Egyptians are deeply skeptical about the United States and its role in their country, but they are also divided in their attitudes about Islamic fundamentalists. Most Egyptians distrust the United States and want to renegotiate their peace treaty with Israel, the poll found.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/poll-egyptians-have-unfavorable-view-of-us-are-divided-on-fundamentalists/2011/04/25/AFxCzFjE_story.html |title=Poll: Egyptians have unfavorable view of U.S., are divided on fundamentalists |publisher=Washington Post |date=2011-04-25 |accessdate=2011-05-22 |first=Leila |last=Fadel}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''26 April 2011''': Egypt gas pipeline to Israel, Jordan attacked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/04/27/us-egypt-attack-idUSTRE73Q0RR20110427 |title=Egypt gas pipeline to Israel, Jordan attacked: source |publisher=Reuters |date= 27 April 2011|accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''28 April 2011''': Workers to celebrate Labor Day in Tahrir, demand more freedoms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/human-a-civil-rights/workers-to-celebrate-labor-day-in-tahrir-demand-more-freedoms.html |title=Workers to celebrate Labor Day in Tahrir, demand more freedoms |publisher=Thedailynewsegypt.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''29 April 2011''': Tahrir demonstrators express solidarity with Arab uprisings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/417458 |title=Tahrir demonstrators express solidarity with Arab uprisings &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=2011-04-29 |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== May ===

'''24 May 2011''': It was announced that Egypt's ousted President Hosni Mubarak and his two sons Gamal and Alaa are to be tried over the deaths of anti-government protesters in the revolution that began on 25 January.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-13527102|title=Egypt: Hosni Mubarak and sons to be tried over deaths|date=24 May 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=24 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''27 May 2011''': The '''&quot;Second Friday of Anger&quot;''' (a.k.a '''&quot;Second Revolution of Anger&quot;''' or '''&quot;The Second Revolution&quot;'''):
Hundreds of thousands of demonstrators -yet again- filled Tahrir Square in Egypt's capital [[Cairo]], besides tens of thousands in each of Alexandra, Suez, Ismailia, Gharbeya and other areas; in the largest demonstrations since ousting Mubarak's Regime.

'''28 May 2011''': Former Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak has been fined $34m (£20m) for cutting off communications services during the uprising that ousted him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13585237|title=Egypt: Hosni Mubarak fined for cutting internet|date=28 May 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Egypt eases blockade at Gaza's Rafah border. Women, children and men over 40 are allowed to pass freely. Men aged between 18 and 40 will still require a permit, and trade is prohibited. The crossing will now be open from 0900 to 2100 every day except Fridays and holidays. The move - strongly opposed by Israel - comes some three months after Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak lost power. Egypt and Israel closed borders with Gaza when Hamas seized power in 2007. Since then almost all Palestinians have been confined to the narrow territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13581141|title=Egypt eases blockade at Gaza's Rafah border|date=28 May 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13584339|title=In pictures: Egypt-Gaza border opens at Rafah|date=28 May 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13240113|title=Gaza-Egypt border crossing to open permanently|date=29 April 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13552685|title=Gaza: Egypt 'to open Rafah crossing to Palestinians|date=25 May 2011|publisher=BBC News|accessdate=29 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== June ===
'''28 June 2011''':
There were clashes in [[Tahrir Square]] between security forces and protestors.

=== July ===

'''1 July 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of Retribution&quot;'''; Tens of thousands of protesters gathered in Suez, Alexandria and Tahrir Square in Cairo, to voice frustration with the ruling Supreme Council of the Armed Forces for what they called the slow pace of change five months after the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://channel6newsonline.com/2011/07/thousands-of-egyptians-protest-against-police-brutality/ |title=Channel 6 News » Thousands of Egyptians protest against police brutality |publisher=Channel6newsonline.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''8 July 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of Determination&quot;'''; Hundreds of thousands of protesters gathered in Suez, Alexandria and Tahrir Square in Cairo. They demanded immediate reforms and swifter prosecution of former officials from the ousted government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/15899/Egypt/Politics-/Hundreds-of-thousands-revitalise-Egypts-revolution.aspx |title=Hundreds of thousands revitalise Egypt's revolution on Determination Friday – Politics – Egypt – Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |accessdate=10 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''15 July 2011''': The '''&quot;Friday of the last ultimatum&quot;'''.

=== September ===
'''Sept 9: ''' Thousands, mostly secular and leftist activists, arrive in Tarhir square to press military rulers to keep their promises of political reform.

'''Sept 10: '''
* Protesters storm the [[Israel]]i embassy in [[Cairo]], forcing the [[Egypt–Israel relations|Israeli ambassador to Egypt]] to flee. [http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-world/egypt-on-alert-after-embassy-attack-20110911-1k3pi.html (''Sydney Morning Herald'')]
* The military restore state of emergency.
* Egyptian activists denounce a political manipulation to restore the state of emergency and the return of the ancient regime.

=== November ===
'''Nov 19:''' Clashes first erupt in [[Tahrir Square]] as demonstrators reoccupy the location in central Cairo. Central Security Forces deploy tear gas in an attempt to control the situation.&lt;ref name=&quot;facing&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/22/world/middleeast/facing-calls-to-give-up-power-egypts-military-battles-crowds.html|agency=The New York Times|date=21 November 2011|accessdate=21 November 2011|title=Egypt Clashes Enter 3rd Day as Military Faces Pressure}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
'''Nov 20:''' Police forces attempt to forcibly clear the square, but protesters soon return in more than twice their original numbers. Fierce fighting breaks out and continues through the night, with the police again using tear gas, beating and shooting demonstrators.&lt;ref name=&quot;facing&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;
'''Nov 21:''' Demonstrators return to the square, with [[Coptic Christian]]s standing guard as Muslims protesting the regime pause for prayers. The Health Ministry says at least 23 have died and over 1,500 have been wounded since 19 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;facing&quot;/&gt; Solidarity protests are held in [[Alexandria]], [[Suez]], and at least five other major Egyptian cities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.aljazeera.net/liveblog/egypt-nov-21-2011-1627|agency=Al Jazeera Blogs|title=Mon, 21 Nov 2011, 13:27 GMT+3 - Egypt}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dissident journalist [[Hossam al-Hamalawy]] tells [[Al Jazeera]] that Egyptians will launch a general strike because they have &quot;had enough&quot; of the SCAF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Al Jazeera Blogs|url=http://blogs.aljazeera.net/liveblog/egypt-nov-21-2011-1746|title=Mon, 21 Nov 2011, 14:46 GMT+3 - Egypt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

{{reflist|30em}}
{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}
{{2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Egypt Protests and Revolution}}
{{Egypt topics}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Egyptian revolution, 2011, Timeline of}}
[[Category:2011 in Egypt|01]]
[[Category:2011 riots|Egypt01]]
[[Category:21st-century revolutions]]
[[Category:2011 Egyptian revolution|Egyptian Revolution of 2011]]
[[Category:Labour disputes in Egypt]]
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]
[[Category:Protests in Egypt]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in Egypt]]
[[Category:Timelines of current events]]
[[Category:Timelines of the Arab Spring]]

[[ar:التسلسل الزمني لثورة 25 يناير]]
[[arz:ثورة مصر سنة 2011 يوم بيوم]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
