<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30738400" ns="0" title="Wael Ghonim"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| honorific_prefix          = 
| name                      = Wael Ghonim&lt;br /&gt;{{lang|ar| وائل غنيم}}
| honorific_suffix          =
| image                     = Wael_ghonim.jpg
| image_size                =
| alt                       =
| birth_name                =
| birth_date                = {{birth date and age|1980|12|23}}
| birth_place               = [[Cairo, Egypt]]
| death_date                = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} (death date then birth date) --&gt;
| death_place               =
| death_cause               =
| body_discovered           =
| resting_place             =
| resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{Coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline}} --&gt;
| residence                 = [[Dubai, United Arab Emirates]]
| nationality               = [[Egypt]]ian
| other_names               =
| ethnicity                 = [[Egyptians|Egyptian]]
| citizenship               =
| education                 =
| alma_mater                = [[Cairo University]] &lt;small&gt;([[Bachelor of Science|B.S.]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[American University in Cairo]] &lt;small&gt;([[Master of Business Administration|M.B.A.]])&lt;/small&gt;
| occupation                = Head of Marketing of [[Google|Google Middle East and North Africa]] &lt;br&gt; [[Internet activism|Internet Activist]] &lt;br&gt; [[Computer Engineer]]
| years_active              = 1998-present
| employer                  = [[Google Inc.]] (on sabbatical)
| home_town                 =
| criminal_charge           =
| criminal_penalty          =
| criminal_status           =
| religion                  = [[Muslim]]
| spouse                    =
| partner                   =
| wife                      = American Muslim 
| children                  = 2&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.amnestyusa.org/document.php?id=ENGPRE201102062141&amp;lang=eRT |title=Fears for Google employee in Egypt |publisher=Amnestyusa.org |date=2011-01-28 |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| website                   = &lt;!-- {{URL|www.example.com}} --&gt;
| footnotes                 =
| box_width                 =
}}
'''Wael Ghonim''' ({{lang-ar|وائل غنيم}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈwæːʔel ɣoˈneːm|IPA}}; other transliterations include: ''Ghoneim, Ghonaim'') (born 23 December 1980 in [[Cairo, Egypt]]) is an [[Internet activism|Internet activist]] and [[computer engineer]] with an interest in [[social entrepreneurship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cnnngo&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url= http://money.cnn.com/2011/04/25/technology/wael_ghonim_leaves_google/ | title= Wael Ghonim to leave Google, start NGO in Egypt | date= April 25, 2011 | publisher= CNN | accessdate=2011-04-25| quote= Ghonim tweeted on Saturday: 'Decided to take a long term sabbatical from @Google &amp; start a technology focused NGO to help fight poverty &amp; foster education in #Egypt' | first=Julianne | last=Pepitone}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, he became an international figure and energized pro-democracy demonstrations in Egypt after his emotional interview&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SjimpQPQDuU&amp;playnext=1&amp;list=PLA90B1900FE67C0F5 |title=An interview with him on Dream TV 2 {{Ar}}engl.subtitle|publisher=Youtube.com |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; following 11 days of secret incarceration by Egyptian police—during which he was interrogated regarding his work as the administrator of the Facebook page, &quot;We are all [[Khaled Saeed]]&quot;, which helped spark the revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e41c5faa-3475-11e0-9ebc-00144feabdc0.html#axzz1DfvBdbyf|title=Google worker is Egypt’s Facebook hero|date=February 9, 2011|work=[[Financial Times]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/egypt/8317055/Egypt-crisis-the-young-revolutionaries-who-sparked-the-protests.html|title=Egypt crisis: the young revolutionaries who sparked the protests|date=11 Feb 2011|work=[[The Daily Telegraph|The Telegraph]]|location=London|first=Jon|last=Swaine}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[TIME]]'' magazine added him in its &quot;[[Time 100]]&quot; list of 100 most influential people of 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Wael Ghonim: Spokesman for a Revolution|url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2066367_2066369,00.html |date= Apr. 21, 2011 |publisher=''[[TIME]]'' }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background==
Wael Ghonim was born to a middle-class family on 23 December 1980 in Cairo, Egypt and grew up in [[Abha]], Saudi Arabia until he was 13 years old, then he moved back to live in Cairo. In January 2010, Wael was promoted to &quot;Head of Marketing&quot; at Google in the Middle East &amp; North Africa and moved to Dubai, [[United Arab Emirates|the United Arab Emirates]].

He earned a [[Bachelor of Science|BS]] in [[computer engineering]] from [[Cairo University]] in 2004 and an [[MBA]], with honors, in marketing and finance from the [[American University in Cairo]] in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ae.linkedin.com/in/ghonim |title=Wael Ghonim - Head of Marketing @ Google - Middle East &amp; North Africa &amp;#124; LinkedIn |publisher=Ae.linkedin.com |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Career ==
From 1998–2002 Wael founded and managed one of the most visited websites in the [[Arab world]]&lt;http://www.islamway.com&gt;{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}.  Until 2005 he was Marketing and Sales Manager of [[Gawab]].&lt;ref name=&quot;alarabalyawm1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.o-a.com/archive/0306/7292.html |title=Re: Feasibility of advertising revenues (Online Advertising Discussion List Archives) |publisher=O-a.com |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, Wael left Gawab to establish [[Mubasher.info]] a pioneering financial portal in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;alarabalyawm1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.alarabalyawm.net/pages.php?news_id=280127 |title=(in Arabic) |publisher=Alarabalyawm.net |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wael joined [[Google|Google Middle East and North Africa]] as their Regional Marketing Manager in 2008 based at Google Egypt.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}.  In January 2010 Wael became Head of Marketing of [[Google|Google Middle East and North Africa]] based at Google's UAE office in [[Dubai Internet City]] in [[Dubai]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arabcrunch.com/2011/02/google-mena-marketing-head-wael-ghonim-apprehended-in-egypt-please-help-locate-him.html |title=Update: Google MENA Marketing Head Wael Ghonim Apprehended in Egypt, Please Help Locate Him |publisher=ArabCrunch |date=2011-02-02 |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.menaictforum.com/speaker/mr-wael-ghonim |title=Mr. Wael Ghonim |publisher=MENA ICT Forum |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the [[Egyptian revolution of 2011]] Wael took leave from Google to focus on his work in Egypt and the Middle East.  He has also been a consultant on the development of [http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/ the Egyptian e-government portal], and a participant in the ongoing political discussion after the resignation of Hosni Mubarak.

==Involvement in the Egyptian Revolution of 2011==

In 2010, Wael Ghonim founded a Facebook page titled, &quot;We Are All Khaled Said,&quot; supporting Khaled Said, a young Egyptian who was tortured to death by police in Alexandria. Wael Ghonim used this page in moving and integrating the anti-government protests of the 25th of Jan revolution.He first made an announcement on the page on the 14th of Jan asking members if they were going to plan on taking to the streets on 25th of Jan and do what Tunisia did? In less than 2 hours he published an event entitled: 25 يناير على التعذيب والفساد والظلم والبطالة [January 25: Revolution against Torture, Corruption, Unemployment and Injustice]. This was the first invitation and many others followed. He anonymously collaborated with activists on the ground to announce the locations for the protest. 

The page also organized interesting activities such as the Silent Stands and the Police Communication Campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/110524/20110209/wael-ghonim-google-marketing-executive-egypt-protests-detained-released-face-protestors-facebook-twi.htm |title=Google man Wael Ghonim emerges as the face of Egypt protests - International Business Times |publisher=Ibtimes.com |date=2011-02-09 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;anarchitext.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Name (required) |url=http://anarchitext.wordpress.com/2011/03/27/wael-ghonim/ |title=Wael Ghonim &quot; AnarchitexT |publisher=Anarchitext.wordpress.com |date=2011-03-27 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2011, Ghonim persuaded Google to allow him to return to Egypt, citing a &quot;personal problem&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12400529 Profile: Egypt's Wael Ghonim] BBC News 9 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt; He came to Egypt to partake in the Egyptian Revolution  &lt;ref name=&quot;anarchitext.wordpress.com&quot;/&gt; but he disappeared on 27 January during the [[2011 Egyptian protests|nationwide unrest in Egypt]].
His family told [[Al-Arabiya]] and other international media that he was missing. [[Google]] also issued a statement confirming the disappearance. Many bloggers like [[Chris DiBona]] and [[Habib Haddad]] campaigned in an attempt to identify his whereabouts. 

On 5 February 2011, [[Mostafa Alnagar]], a major Egyptian opposition figure,&lt;ref&gt;Al-Anani, Khalil,  [http://www.ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=21203 “The Young Brotherhood in Search of a New Path”], ''Ikhwahweb: The [[Muslim Brotherhood]] Official  English Website'', October 6, 2009. Retrieved 2011-02-13. “[Y]oung Brotherhood bloggers started engaging in auto-critique and openly began criticizing the movement’s leadership, its organizational structures, and its rigid and out-dated political and religious discourse. Amwaj Fi Bahr al-Taghyir (Waves in the Sea of Change) is the most prominent of these blogs, and was established by the 29-year-old dentist and reformist Mustafa al-Naggar. During the 2005 elections, Naggar participated in the Brotherhood’s electoral campaign in the hopes of mobilizing people in support of Islamist candidates. However, he has since expressed disappointment over the Brothers’ poor showing in the elections, and his writing has begun to focus increasingly on how to transform the Brotherhood into a more open movement and a more effective political party. Naggar has been especially critical of the Brotherhood’s political platform, released in August 2007, and he has also attacked the approach of the older generation in dealing with local and regional issues.[11] Naggar’s blog additionally serves as a clearinghouse for links to other blog-based critiques of the Brotherhood.[12] “ Footnotes not included.&lt;/ref&gt; reported that Wael Ghonim was alive and detained by the authorities and to be released 'within hours'.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/t/confirmation-rt-fustat-mo_33997531130101761.html |title=Confirmation?? Rt @fustat: Mostafa Alnagar: Wael @Ghonim is alive &amp; detained. We have promises that he will be released within hours |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 February 2011, [[Amnesty International]] demanded that the Egyptian authorities disclose where Ghonim was and to release him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://amnesty.org/en/for-media/press-releases/fears-google-employee-egypt-2011-02-06 |title=Fears for Google employee in Egypt &amp;#124; Amnesty International |publisher=Amnesty.org |date=2010-05-31 |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 February, Ghonim was released after 11 days in detention. Upon his release, he was greeted with cheers and applause when he stated: &quot;We will not abandon our demand and that is the departure of the regime.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;May, Theodore, [http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2011-02-08-egypt-protests_N.htm &quot;Regime won't halt, but rallies must, Egypt's VP says&quot;], ''USA Today'', February 9, 2011 updated c. February 9, 2011. Retrieved 2011-02-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

The same day, Ghonim appeared on the Egyptian channel DreamTV on the ''10:00 pm'' programme hosted by [[Mona El-Shazly]]. In the interview he praised the protesters and mourned the dead as the host read their names and showed their pictures, eventually rising, &quot;overwhelmed,&quot; and walking off camera. The host followed.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT01&quot;&gt;Fahim, Kareem and Mana El-Naggar; Liam Stack and Ed Ou contributed reporting, [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/09/world/middleeast/09ghonim.html?_r=1&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=Mona%20El-Nagger&amp;st=cse &quot;Emotions of a Reluctant Hero Galvanize Protesters&quot;], ''The New York Times'', February 8, 2011 (February 9, 2011 p. A14 NY ed.).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|title=Subtitled Video of Wael Ghonim’s Emotional TV Interview|last=Mackey|first=RobertPublisher=The New York Times|url=http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/02/08/subtitled-video-of-wael-ghonims-emotional-tv-interview/|date=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the interview, he also urged that they deserved attention more than he did, and calling for the end of the [[Hosni Mubarak|Mubarak]] regime, describing it again as 'rubbish'. He also asserted his allegiance to Egypt, saying that he would never move to the [[United States]], the homeland of his wife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blogs.aljazeera.net/middle-east/2011/02/06/live-blog-feb-7-egypt-protests |title=Live blog Feb 7 - Egypt protests &amp;#124; Al Jazeera Blogs |publisher=Blogs.aljazeera.net |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.news.maktoob.com/20090000569988/Google_Exec_held_in_Egypt_protests_has_been_freed/Article.htm |title=Google: Exec held in Egypt protests has been freed, United States General News - Maktoob News |publisher=En.news.maktoob.com |year= |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Becoming a symbol of the revolution in Egypt,&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN-20110209-revolution&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Husain|first=Ed|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/OPINION/02/09/husain.ghonim/|title=Ghonim electrified Egypt's revolution|publisher=CNN|date=February 9, 2011|accessdate=February 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ghonim stated that he is &quot;ready to die&quot; for the cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNN-20110209-ready&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=King|first=John|url=http://johnkingusa.blogs.cnn.com/2011/02/09/ghonim-im-ready-to-die/|title=Ghonim: 'I'm ready to die'|publisher=CNN|date=February 9, 2011|accessdate=February 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

At the end ..., he gathered himself for a few seconds and tried to make the most of the platform [El-Shazly] had given him. 'I want to tell every mother and every father who lost a child, I am sorry, but this is not our mistake,' he said. 'I swear to God, it’s not our mistake. It’s the mistake of every one of those in power who doesn’t want to let go of it.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT01&quot;/&gt;

On 9 February, Ghonim addressed the crowds in [[Tahrir Square]], telling the protesters: &quot;This is not the time for individuals, or parties, or movements. It's a time for all of us to say just one thing: Egypt above all.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Casavaria-20110209&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/video/2011/feb/09/wael-ghonim-tahrir-square-video|title=Wael Ghonim addresses thousands in Tahrir Square (video)|journal=[[The Guardian]]|date=February 9, 2011|accessdate=February 9, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wael Ghonim also made an appearance on &quot;[[60 Minutes]]&quot;, sitting down with Harry Smith. During his interview he said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Our revolution is like [[Wikipedia]], okay? Everyone is contributing content, [but] you don't know the names of the people contributing the content. This is exactly what happened. Revolution 2.0 in Egypt was exactly the same. Everyone contributing small pieces, bits and pieces. We drew this whole picture of a revolution. And no one is the hero in that picture.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://techpresident.com/blog-entry/ghonim-our-revolution-wikipedia |title=Ghonim: &quot;Our Revolution Is Like Wikipedia&quot; |publisher=techPresident |date=2011-07-01 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The scholar [[Fouad Ajami]] writes about the revolution:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;No turbaned ayatollah had stepped forth to summon the crowd. This was not Iran in 1979. A young Google executive, Wael Ghonim, had energized this protest when it might have lost heart, when it could have succumbed to the belief that this regime and its leader were a big, immovable object. Mr. Ghonim was a man of the modern world. He was not driven by piety. The condition of his country—the abject poverty, the crony economy of plunder and corruption, the cruelties and slights handed out to Egyptians in all walks of life by a police state that the people had outgrown and despaired of—had given this young man and others like him their historical warrant.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704132204576136442019920256.html?mod=WSJ_Opinion_LEADTop | work=The Wall Street Journal | first=Fouad | last=Ajami | title=Egypt's 'Heroes With No Names' | date=2011-02-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

== International Monetary Fund (IMF) annual meeting ==
Wael Ghonim attended the International Monetary Fund (IMF) meeting this year, stating that &quot;I feel like [[Joe the Plumber]],&quot; referring to the conservative activist who became a shorthand for populist outrage during the 2008 U.S. presidential election. &quot;When I was coming here, a lot of people were criticizing me for it. The perception is that the IMF was part of the problem. It made these regimes survive and put these countries into debt.&quot; Ghonim said he had come to the IMF to represent &quot;people like me who don't understand economics.&quot; To which Strauss-Kahn replied, &quot;Wael, you understand a lot more than you say.&quot;
  	
According to Ghonim, the kind of macroeconomic discussions at the panel were far from the mindset of activists in Tahrir Square:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot; Honestly we were just thinking of how to get rid of the nightmare, not to start dreaming. I went to the street because of two things: I hate it when I see people eating from the trash. I work for a corporation, I'm well paid, and a lot of us just sympathized with those people, but they're not willing to pay the price of really helping them out. It's not just me; it's thousands of Egyptians. One of my friends who lost his eye [during the protests] actually drives a Ferrari. He went on the day of 25th. The second was dignity. We wanted our dignity back. And dignity does have an economic aspect. &quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

He also took issue with Strauss-Kahn's characterization of &quot;mistakes&quot; made by the international community during the Mubarak era:
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot; It's such an understatement to say mistake. To me, what was happening was a crime. The way the international community was dealing with the injustice and dictators in the region was basically a crime -- partners in crime. &quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Ghonim continued his criticism of the IMF's aid to the Mubarak regime and expressed a hope that the days of Egypt relying on international aid would soon be over.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://blog.foreignpolicy.com/posts/2011/04/15/wael_the_plumber |title=Wael Ghonim and Dominique Strauss-Kahn mix it up at IMF Spring Meetings &amp;#124; FP Passport |publisher=Blog.foreignpolicy.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Role after the revolution==

In April 2011 Ghonim announce he was taking a &quot;long term [[sabbatical]]&quot; from Google in order to start a &quot;technology focused [[NGO]] to help fight poverty &amp; foster education in Egypt.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnnngo&quot;/&gt;

In May 2011 Ghonim said that he has signed &quot;Revolution 2.0&quot; book deal.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-13351284] BBC News 10 May 2011&lt;/ref&gt; All proceeds from the book will go the [[NGO]] he started in Egypt to fight poverty and provide education.

== Awards ==

Wael Ghonim topped Time magazine’s yearly list of '''the world’s 100 most influential people'''.
On 26 April, He arrived in New York to be honored at the 2011 Time 100 Gala ceremony where he begain his speech with a moment of silence to mark those killed in protests around the Arab world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,2068618,00.html |title=TIME |publisher=TIME |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/10559/Egypt/Politics-/Wael-Ghonim-tops-Times--most-influential-.aspx |title=Wael Ghonim tops Time's 100 most influential - Politics - Egypt - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date=2011-04-21 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 3 May,World Press Freedom Day, Wael Ghonim was awarded with the Press Freedom prize from the Swedish division of '''Reporters without Borders'''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.swedenabroad.com/News____70089.aspx?slaveid=125146 |title=Embassy of Sweden Cairo - News |publisher=Swedenabroad.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; http://sv.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wael_Ghonim&amp;oldid=15047271

Wael Ghonim also received the '''JFK Profile in Courage Award'''. On 23 May, Caroline Kennedy, daughter of President John F. Kennedy, presented the awards to [[Elizabeth Redenbaugh]] and Wael Ghonim, who was named a recipient on behalf of “the people of Egypt.” Kennedy said she could think of no better recipients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Contreras |first=Russell |url=http://arabnews.com/lifestyle/offbeat/article427299.ece |title=Egyptian activist gets JFK Profile in Courage Award |publisher=Arab News |date=2011-05-24 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wael Ghonim was ranked '''the second most powerful Arab''' in [[Arabian Business]]'s annual Power 500 of the world's most influential Arabs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/power500/article/387405l |title=Arabian Business |publisher=ITP Publishing|date= |accessdate=2011-07-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
	
The magazine's annual report stated Ghonim as the primary contributor to the promotion and coordination of the movement of Egyptian youth through &quot;Facebook&quot;, adding that Ghonim came to international fame via commercial news outlets word of mouth after his leadership of the Egyptian revolution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allvoices.com/contributed-news/8600263-arabian-business-wael-ghoneims-second-most-influential-arabs |title=&quot;Arabian Business&quot;: Wael Ghoneim's second most influential Arabs |publisher=Allvoices.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Your name: |url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/power500/ |title=Arabian Business Power 500 |publisher=Arabianbusiness.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; http://sv.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wael_Ghonim&amp;oldid=15047271

== Criticism ==

Ghonim's social media feeds and public statements have been attracting increasing criticism. Shortly before the resignation of former Egyptian President Hosni Mubarak, Ghonim presented a deal to the Egyptian people according to which Mubarak could have remained in Cairo with an &quot;honorary status.&quot; He later appeared on Al Arabiya TV to deny having said this, and added: &quot;I am stronger than Hosni Mubarak. I am stronger than Omar Sulaiman.&quot;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503543_162-20031473-503543.html | work=CBS News | title=Ghonim: Mubarak Must Go &quot;Immediately&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 18 May 2011, a major campaign on Twitter gained momentum with the hashtag #unfollowedghonimbecause, criticising Ghonim for various failings and an exaggerated focus on the Egyptian economy. 
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/unfollowedghonimbecause_egyptians_use_twitter_to_c.php]&lt;/ref&gt;

He has also been criticised for failing to publicly remedy doubts about the genesis of the We are all Khalid Said Facebook page, which is believed to have had at least one more initiator. 
&lt;ref&gt;[http://theeuropean-magazine.com/273-benkredda-belabbes/274-the-rise-of-wael-ghonim]&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the above criticism, some of Ghonim's supporters have launched a Facebook page, trying to declare him the spokesperson for the Egyptian revolutionaries - a role which, at any rate, Ghonim has consistently rejected. More than 400,000 people have joined the page.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.facebook.com/Authorize.Ghoneim |title=Facebook page Authorize. Ghoneim |publisher=Facebook |date= |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, more than 360,000 people joined his personal page on Facebook and more than 1,650,000 people joined &quot;we are all khaled saeed&quot; page,which is run by him and other administrators who continue to be anonymous.

== Personal life ==
Ghonim is married to an American Muslim -Ilka Johannson- &lt;ref&gt;Yaqoob, Tahira. &quot;Wael Ghonim: the voice of a generation.&quot; National 12 Feb 2011: 2. Web. 15 Aug 2011. &lt;http://www.thenational.ae/news/worldwide/africa/wael-ghonim-the-voice-of-a-generation?pageCount=2&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ghonim, Wael. Twitter, 12 Feb 2011. Web. 15 Aug 2011. &lt;http://twitter.com/#!/Ghonim/status/36118972063690752&gt;.&lt;/ref&gt; and has two children, Israa and Adam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marefa.org/index.php/%D9%88%D8%A7%D8%A6%D9%84_%D8%BA%D9%86%D9%8A%D9%85 |title=وائل غنيم - المعرفة |language={{ar icon}} |publisher=Marefa.org |date=2011-02-01 |accessdate=2011-02-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Alexia Tsotsis Feb 7, 2011 |url=http://techcrunch.com/2011/02/07/wael-ghonims-first-interview-after-jail-release-video/ |title=Wael Ghonim’s First Interview After Jail Release [Video&amp;#93; |publisher=Techcrunch.com |date=2011-02-07 |accessdate=2011-07-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

== See also ==
{{portal|Egypt|Google|Human rights}}
* [[April 6 Youth Movement]]
* [[Asmaa Mahfouz]]
* [[Death of Khaled Mohamed Saeed]]
* [[Wael Abbas]]

{{clear}}

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
*[http://conclave.intoday.in/conclave/conclave2011.php Wael Ghonim LIVE at India Today Conclave on 19th March 2011 at 12:15pm IST] India Today Conclave
*[http://www.elshaheeed.co.uk/ We Are All Khaled Said] blog
*{{Twitter|#!/Ghonim}}
*{{Facebook|ghonim}}
*[http://ae.linkedin.com/in/ghonim Wael Ghonim] on [[LinkedIn]]
*{{Aljazeeratopic|person/wael-ghonim}}
*{{NYTtopic|people/g/wael_ghonim}}
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12400529 Profile: Egypt's Wael Ghonim], [[BBC News]], 8 February 2011
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LdNEuWXiTuo&amp;NR=1 Detention of Wael Ghonim(?)], YouTube
*[http://knol.google.com/k/eric-leschinski/recover-wael-ghonim/1adbh32xy7hcl/1 Photos of Wael Ghonim and information concerning his disappearance]
*[http://www.democracynow.org/2011/2/8/the_heroes_are_the_ones_in Wael Ghonim on His Release After 12 Days in Egyptian Jail], ''[[Democracy Now!]]'', February 8, 2011
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vL8Vi6CaCCM Wael Ghonim reacts] on CNN to [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=753G0cJ90Ys Omar Soliman's ABC Interview], YouTube
* CBS &quot;60 Minutes&quot; [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/02/13/60minutes/main20031701.shtml#comments Talks To The Man Who Has Emerged As The Symbol of Egypt's Revolution], 11min, February 13, 2011
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fgw_zfLLvh8&amp;feature=player_embedded#at=25 his favorite song] (Wael: &quot;The most amazing song for the revolution&quot;)
*[http://en.qantara.de/webcom/show_article.php/_c-478/_nr-1163/i.html The Egyptian Internet Activist Wael Ghonim: The Face of the Egyptian Protest Movement] Qantara.de
* [http://www.ted.com/talks/wael_ghonim_inside_the_egyptian_revolution.html Wael Ghonim: Inside the Egyptian revolution], talk at TED conference March 2011
* Wael, one of &quot;TIME 100&quot; people 2011: [http://globalspin.blogs.time.com/2011/04/27/wael-ghonim-at-the-time-100-gala/ 5min speech at the gala], and: [http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2066367_2066369_2066437,00.html honoured from M.ElBaradei and short statement]
{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}
{{2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Egypt topics}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Ghonim, Wael
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1980-12-23
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Cairo, Egypt]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ghonim, Wael}}
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1980 births]]
[[Category:Google employees]]
[[Category:American University in Cairo alumni]]
[[Category:Cairo University alumni]]
[[Category:Missing people]]
[[Category:People from Cairo]]
[[Category:People from Dubai]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
[[Category:Internet activists]]

[[ar:وائل غنيم]]
[[az:Vael Qonim]]
[[zh-min-nan:Wael Ghonim]]
[[de:Wael Ghonim]]
[[es:Wael Ghonim]]
[[fa:وائل غنیم]]
[[fr:Wael Ghonim]]
[[it:Wael Ghonim]]
[[he:ואאיל רונים]]
[[ms:Wael Ghonim]]
[[mn:Ваел Гоним]]
[[nl:Wael Ghonim]]
[[ja:ワエル・ゴニム]]
[[no:Wael Ghonim]]
[[pt:Wael Ghonim]]
[[ru:Гоним, Ваиль]]
[[sv:Wael Ghonim]]
[[ta:வாஇல் ஃஙுனைம்]]
[[tr:Wael Ghonim]]
[[uk:Ваель Ґонім]]
[[zh:威爾·戈寧]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
