<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="307326" ns="0" title="Still life"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|Still Life (disambiguation)}}
[[File:Jan Bruegel d. Ä. 007.jpg|thumb|[[Jan Brueghel the Elder]] (1568-1625), ''Bouquet'' (1599), [[Kunsthistorisches Museum]], [[Vienna]]. Some of the earliest examples of still life were paintings of flowers by Northern Renaissance, Dutch, and Flemish painters.]]

A '''[[wikt:still life|still life]]''' (plural '''still lifes''') is a [[work of art]] depicting mostly [[wikt:inanimate|inanimate]] subject matter, typically commonplace objects which may be either natural (food, flowers, plants, rocks, or shells) or man-made (drinking glasses, books, vases, jewelry, coins, pipes, and so on). With origins in the Middle Ages and Ancient Greek/Roman art, still life paintings give the artist more leeway in the arrangement of design elements within a composition than do paintings of other types of subjects such as [[Landscape art|landscape]] or [[portrait]]ure. Still life paintings, particularly before 1700, often contained religious and allegorical symbolism relating to the objects depicted. Some modern still life breaks the two-dimensional barrier and employs three-dimensional mixed media, and uses found objects, photography, [[computer graphics]], as well as video and sound.

==History==
===Antecedents===
[[Image:Pompejanischer Maler um 70 001.jpg|thumb|Glass bowl of fruit and vases. [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] wall painting in [[Pompeii]] (around 70 AD), [[Naples National Archaeological Museum]], [[Naples]], [[Italy]]]]
Still life paintings often adorn the interior of [[ancient Egypt]]ian tombs.  It was believed that food objects and other items depicted there would, in the afterlife, become real and available for use by the deceased.  Ancient Greek vase paintings also demonstrate great skill in depicting everyday objects and animals. Similar still life, more simply decorative in intent, but with realistic perspective, have also been found in the [[Ancient Rome|Roman]] wall paintings and floor mosaics unearthed at [[Pompeii]], [[Herculaneum]] and the [[Villa Boscoreale]], including the later familiar motif of a glass bowl of fruit. Decorative mosaics termed &quot;emblema&quot;, found in the homes of rich Romans, demonstrated the range of food enjoyed by the upper classes, and also functioned as signs of hospitality and as celebrations of the seasons and of life.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; By the 16th century, food and flowers would again appear as symbols of the seasons and of the five senses. Also starting in Roman times is the tradition of the use of the skull in paintings as a symbol of mortality and earthly remains, often with the accompanying phrase ''Omnia mors aequat'' (Death makes all equal).&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; These [[vanitas]] images have been re-interpreted through the last 400 years of art history, starting with Dutch painters around 1600.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p.137&lt;/ref&gt;

The popular appreciation of the realism of still life painting is related in the [[Ancient Greece|ancient Greek]] legend of [[Zeuxis and Parrhasius]], who are said to have once competed to create the most life-like objects, history’s earliest descriptions of [[trompe-l'œil]] painting.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; As [[Pliny the Elder]] recorded in ancient Roman times, Greek artists centuries earlier were already advanced in the arts of [[portrait painting]] and still life.  He singled out Peiraikos, &quot;whose artistry is surpassed by only a very few...He painted barbershops and shoemakers’ stalls, donkeys, vegetables, and such, and for that reason came to be called the ‘painter of vulgar subjects’; yet these works are altogether delightful, and they were sold at higher prices than the greatest [paintings] of many other artists.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 15&quot;&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages and Renaissance===
[[File:Hans Memling 076.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Hans Memling]] (1430-1494), ''Vase of Flowers,'' (1480), Museo Thyssen-Bornemisza, [[Madrid]]. According to some scholars the ''Vase of Flowers'' is filled with religious symbolism &lt;ref&gt;[http://arthistory.about.com/library/weekly/sp/bl_memling_rev.htm ''Memlings Portraits'' exhibition review, Frick Collection, NYC]. Retrieved March 15, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
By 1300, starting with [[Giotto]] and his pupils, still life painting was revived in the form of fictional niches on religious wall paintings which depicted everyday objects.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p.25&lt;/ref&gt; Through the [[Middle Ages]] and the [[Renaissance]], still life in Western art remained primarily an adjunct to Christian religious subjects, and convened religious and allegorical meaning.  This was particularly true in the work of Northern European artists, whose fascination with highly detailed optical realism and symbolism led them to lavish great attention on their paintings' overall message.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; Painters like [[Jan van Eyck]] often used still life elements as part of an [[iconography|iconographic]] program.

The development of [[oil painting]] technique by [[Jan van Eyck]] and other Northern European artists made it possible to paint everyday objects in this hyper-realistic fashion, owing to the slow drying, mixing, and layering qualities of oil colors.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; Among the first to break free of religious meaning were [[Leonardo da Vinci]], who created watercolor studies of fruit (around 1495) as part of his restless examination of nature,  and [[Albrecht Dürer]] who also made precise drawings of flora and fauna.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 39, 53&lt;/ref&gt;

Petrus Christus’ portrait of a bride and groom visiting a goldsmith is a typical example of a transitional still life depicting both religious and secular content.  Though mostly allegorical in message, the figures of the couple are realistic and the objects shown (coins, vessels, etc.) are accurately painted but the goldsmith is actually a depiction of St. Eligius and the objects heavily symbolic.  Another similar type of painting is the family portrait combining figures with a well-set table of food, which symbolizes both the piety of the human subjects and their thanks for God’s abundance.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt; Around this time, simple still life depictions divorced of figures (but not allegorical meaning) were beginning to be painted on the outside of shutters of private devotional paintings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 15&quot;/&gt; Another step toward the autonomous still life was the painting of symbolic flowers in vases on the back of secular portraits around 1475.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; Jacopo de’ Barbari went a step further with his ''Still Life with Partridge, Iron Gloves, and Crossbow Arrows'' (1504), among the earliest signed and dated trompe-l'œil still life paintings, which contains minimal religious content.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sixteenth century==

The 16th century witnessed an explosion of interest in the natural world and the creation of lavish botanical encyclopædias recording the discoveries of the New World and Asia. It also prompted the beginning of scientific illustration and the classification of specimens. Natural objects began to be appreciated as individual objects of study apart from any religious or mythological associations.  The early science of herbal remedies began at this time as well, a practical extension of this new knowledge. In addition, wealthy patrons began to underwrite the collection of animal and mineral specimens, creating extensive &quot;curio cabinets&quot;.  These specimens served as models for painters who sought realism and novelty. Shells, insects, exotic fruits and flowers began to be collected and traded, and new plants such as the [[tulip]] (imported to Europe from Turkey), were celebrated in still life paintings.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, pp. 54-56&lt;/ref&gt; The horticultural explosion was of wide spread interest in Europe and artist capitalized on that to produce thousands of still life paintings. Some regions and courts had particular interests. The depiction of citrus, for example, was a particular passion of the [[Medici]] court in Florence, Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; This great diffusion of natural specimens and the burgeoning interest in natural illustration throughout Europe, resulted in the nearly simultaneous creation of modern still life paintings around 1600.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/nstl/hd_nstl.htm Metropolitan Museum of Art Timeline, Still-life painting 1600-1800]. Retrieved March 14, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

By the second half of the 16th century, the autonomous still life evolved.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p.38&lt;/ref&gt; Gradually, religious content diminished in size and placement in these painting, though moral lessons continued as sub-contexts. An example is &quot;The Butcher Shop&quot; by Joachim Beuckelaer (1568), with its realistic depiction of raw meats dominating the foreground, while a background scene conveys the dangers of drunkenness and lechery.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; [[Annibale Carracci]]’s treatment of the same subject in 1583 also called ''[[Butcher's Shop (Annibale Carracci)|Butcher's Shop]]'' begins to remove the moral messages, as did other &quot;kitchen and market&quot; still life paintings of this period.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sixteenth century gallery===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
File:Jacopo de' Barbari 001.jpg|[[Jacopo de' Barbari]] (c. 1440–before 1516), ''Still-Life with Partridge and Gauntlets'' (1504), [[Alte Pinakothek]], [[Munich]]
File:Dürer, Albrecht - Kleine Eule - 1508.jpg|[[Albrecht Dürer]] (1471-1528), ''Owl'', (1508), Watercolour and bodycolour, [[Albertina, Vienna|Albertina]], [[Vienna]]. Dürer made careful studies of nature, including paintings of plants and animals.
File:Marten van Heemskerck 003.jpg|[[Maarten van Heemskerck]] (1498–1574),, ''Family of Pieter Jan Foppesz'', prior to c.1532, considered the first family portrait, in Dutch portraiture.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.nl/books?q=Frauke%2BK.%2BLaarmann, Families in beeld] - Frauke K. Laarmann, Families in beeld: De ontwikkeling van het Noord-Nederlandse familieportret in de eerste helft van de zeventiende eeuw. Hilversum, 2002, Verloren, ISBN 978-90-6550-186-8 Retrieved December 25, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Annibale Carracci The Beaneater.jpg|[[Annibale Carracci]], ''[[The Beaneater]]'', 1580-1590, [[Galleria Colonna]], [[Rome]]
File:Carracci-Butcher's shop.jpg|[[Annibale Carracci]] (1560-1609), ''[[Butcher's Shop (Annibale Carracci)|Butcher's Shop]]'' (1580), [[Christ Church Picture Gallery]], [[Oxford]]
File:Joachim Beuckelaer 003.jpg|[[Joachim Beuckelaer]], (1533-1575), Kitchen scene, with Jesus in the house of [[Martha]] and Mary in the background, 1566.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Seventeenth century==
[[File:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn 053.jpg|thumb|[[Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn]] (1606-1669), ''Slaughtered Ox'', (1655), [[Musée du Louvre]], Paris]]
Even though Italian still life painting was gaining in popularity, it remained historically less respected than the &quot;grand manner&quot; painting of historical, religious, and mythic subjects. Prominent Academicians of the early 17th century, such as [[Andrea Sacchi]], felt that [[genre works|genre]] and still life painting did not carry the &quot;gravitas&quot; merited for painting to be considered great. On the other hand, successful Italian still life artists found ample patronage in their day.&lt;ref&gt;''La natura morta in Italia'' edited by Francesco Porzio and directed by Federico Zeri; Review author: John T. Spike. ''The Burlington Magazine'' (1991) Volume 133 (1055) page 124-125.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, women painters, few as they were, commonly chose or were restricted to painting still life;  [[Giovanna Garzoni]], [[Laura Bernasconi]], [[Maria Theresa van Thielen]], and [[Fede Galizia]] are notable examples.

Many leading Italian artists in other genre, also produced some still life paintings. In particular, [[Caravaggio]] applied his influential form of naturalism to still life. His ''Basket of Fruit'' (c. 1595-1600) is one of the first examples of pure still life, precisely rendered and set at eye level.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; Though not overtly symbolic, this painting was owned by Cardinal Borromeo and may have been appreciated for both religious and aesthetic reasons.  [[Jan Bruegel]] painted his ''Large Milan Bouquet'' (1606) for the cardinal, as well, claiming that he painted it 'fatta tutti del natturel' (made all from nature) and he charged extra for the extra effort.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; These were among many still life paintings in the cardinal’s collection, in addition to his large collection of curios. Among other Italian still life, [[Bernardo Strozzi]]’s ''The Cook'' is a &quot;kitchen scene&quot; in the Dutch manner, which is both a detailed portrait of a cook and the game birds she is preparing.&lt;ref&gt;Stefano Zuffi, Ed., ''Baroque Painting'', Barron’s Educational Series, Hauppauge, New York, 1999, p. 96, ISBN 0-7641-5214-9&lt;/ref&gt; In a similar manner, one of Rembrandt’s rare still life paintings, ''Little Girl with Dead Peacocks'' combines a similar sympathetic female portrait with images of game birds.&lt;ref&gt;Zuffi, p. 175&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italian gallery===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
File:Bodegon galizia.jpg|[[Fede Galizia]] (1578-1630), ''Apples in a dish,'' (c. 1593)
File:Caravaggio Basket of Fruit.jpg|[[Caravaggio]] (1571–1610), ''[[Basket of Fruit (Caravaggio)|Basket of Fruit]],'' (c. 1599), oil on canvas, [[Pinacoteca Ambrosiana]], [[Milan]], [[Italy]]
Image:Giovanna Garzoni.jpg|[[Giovanna Garzoni]] (1600-1670), ''Still Life with Bowl of Citrons'' (Tempera on vellum), (1640), [[Getty Museum]], [[Pacific Palisades, Los Angeles, California]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Dutch, Flemish, German, Portuguese, and Spanish still lifes===
[[Image:Fra Juan Sánchez Cotán 001.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Juan Sánchez Cotán]] (1560–1627), ''Quince, Cabbage, Melon and Cucumber'' (1602), [[San Diego Museum of Art]], [[San Diego]]]]
Still life developed as a separate category in the [[Netherlands]] in the last quarter of the 16th century,&lt;ref&gt;Slive 277-279&lt;/ref&gt; and the English term derives from ''stilleven'': ''still life'', which is a [[calque]] while Romance languages (and Russian) tend to use terms meaning ''dead nature''.  15th century [[Early Netherlandish painting]] had developed highly illusionistic techniques in both [[panel painting]] and [[illuminated manuscript]]s, where the borders often featured elaborate displays of flowers, insects and, in a work like the [[Hours of Catherine of Cleves]], a great variety of objects.  When the illuminated manuscript was displaced by the printed book, the same skills were later deployed in scientific botanical illustration; the Netherlands led Europe in both [[botany]] and its depiction in art.  [[Joris Hoefnagel]] (1542–1601) made [[watercolour]] and [[gouache]] paintings of flowers and other still life subjects for the [[Emperor Rudolf II]], and there were many engraved illustrations for books (often then hand-coloured), such as [[Hans Collaert]]'s ''Florilegium'', published by [[Plantin]] in 1600.&lt;ref&gt;Vlieghe, 207&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Diego Velázquez 017.jpg|thumb|left|[[Diego Velázquez]], ''Old Woman Frying Eggs'', 1618, ([[National Gallery of Scotland]]), is one of the earliest examples of [[bodegón]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Lucie-Smith, Edward|title=The Thames and Hudson Dictionary of Art Terms|year=1984|publisher=Thames and Hudson|location=London|page=32}} [[template:LCCN|LCCN]] 83-51331&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[File:Zurbaran - Bodegon.jpg|thumb|left|[[Francisco de Zurbarán]], ''[[Bodegón]]'' or ''Still Life with Pottery Jars'', 1636, Oil on canvas; 46 x 84 cm; [[Museo del Prado]], [[Madrid]]]]
[[Image:JosefaObidos4.jpg|thumb|left|[[Josefa de Óbidos|Josefa de Ayala (Josefa de Óbidos)]], ''Still-life'', c.1679, [[Santarém, Portugal|Santarém]], Municipal Library]]

In [[Spanish art]], a [[bodegón]] is a still life painting depicting pantry items, such as victuals, game, and drink, often arranged on a simple stone slab, and also a painting with one or more figures, but significant still life elements, typically set in a kitchen or tavern. Starting in the [[Baroque]] period, such paintings became popular in Spain in the second quarter of the 17th century.  The tradition of still life painting appears to have started and was far more popular in the contemporary [[Low Countries]], today [[Belgium]] and [[Netherlands]] (then Flemish and Dutch artists), than it ever was in southern Europe. [[Dutch Golden Age painting#Still lifes|Northern still lifes]] had many sub-genre's; the ''breakfast piece'' was augmented by the ''[[trompe-l'œil]]'', the ''flower bouquet'' , and the ''[[vanitas]]''. In Spain there were much fewer patrons for this sort of thing, but a type of ''breakfast piece'' did become popular, featuring a few objects of food and tableware laid on a table.

There was also a type of very large kitchen or market scene developed by [[Pieter van Aelst]] (1502–1550) and his nephew [[Joachim Beuckelaer]].  Amid an abundance of food and kitchenware still life, supervised by burly Flemish kitchen-maids, a small religious scene can often be made out in the distance, or a theme such as the [[season|Four Seasons]] elevates the subject.  This sort of large-scale still life continued to develop in Flemish painting after the separation of the North and South, but is rare in Dutch painting, although other works in this tradition anticipate the &quot;merry company&quot; type of [[genre painting]].&lt;ref&gt;Slive, 275; Vlieghe, 211-216&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 1600 flower paintings in oils became something of a craze; [[Karel van Mander]] painted some works himself, and records that other [[Northern Mannerist]] artists such as [[Cornelis van Haarlem]] also did so.  No surviving flower-pieces by them are known, but many survive by the leading specialists, [[Jan Brueghel the Elder]] and [[Ambrosius Bosschaert]], who both remained in the Flemish south of the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;Slive, 279, Vlieghe, 206-7&lt;/ref&gt;

While artists in the North found limited opportunity to produce the religious iconography which had long been their staple—images of religious subjects were forbidden in the [[Dutch Reformed Church|Dutch Reformed Protestant Church]]—the continuing Northern tradition of detailed realism and hidden symbols appealed to the growing Dutch middle classes, who were replacing Church and State as the principal patrons of art in the Netherlands.  Added to this was the Dutch mania for horticulture, particularly the tulip. These two views of flowers—as aesthetic objects and as religious symbols— merged to create a very strong market for this type of still life.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Taylor, ''Dutch Flower Painting 1600-1720'', Yale University Press, New Haven, 1995, p. 77, ISBN0-300-05390-8&lt;/ref&gt; Still life, like most Dutch art work, was generally sold in open markets or by dealers, or by artists at their studios, and rarely commissioned; therefore, artists usually chose the subject matter and arrangement.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; So popular was this type of still life painting, that much of the technique of Dutch flower painting was codified in the 1740 treatise ''Groot Schilderboeck'' by Gerard de Lairesse, which gave wide-ranging advice on color, arranging, brushwork, preparation of specimens, harmony, composition, perspective, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;

The symbolism of flowers had evolved since early Christian days. The most common flowers and their symbolic meanings include: rose (Virgin Mary, transience, Venus, love); lily (Virgin Mary, virginity, female breast, purity of mind or justice); tulip (showiness, nobility); sunflower (faithfulness, divine love, devotion); violet (modesty, reserve, humility); columbine (melancholy); poppy (power, sleep, death).  As for insects, the butterfly represents transformation and resurrection while the dragonfly symbolizes transience and the ant hard work and attention to the harvest.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, pp. 56-76&lt;/ref&gt;

Dutch artists also branched out and revived the ancient Greek still life tradition of trompe-l'œil, particularly the imitation of nature or ''mimesis'', which they termed ''bedriegertje'' (&quot;little deception&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to these types of still life, Dutch artists identified and separately developed &quot;kitchen and market&quot; paintings, breakfast and food table still life, vanitas paintings, and allegorical collection paintings.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

Especially popular in this period were [[vanitas]] paintings, in which sumptuous arrangements of fruit and flowers, books, statuettes, vases, coins, jewelry, paintings, musical and scientific instruments, military insignia, fine silver and crystal, were accompanied by symbolic reminders of life's impermanence.  Additionally, a skull, an [[hourglass]] or pocket watch, a candle burning down or a book with pages turning, would serve as a moralizing message on the ephemerality of sensory pleasures.  Often some of the fruits and flowers themselves would be shown starting to spoil or fade to emphasize the same point.

Another type of still life, known as &quot;breakfast paintings&quot;, represent both a literal presentation of delicacies that the upper class might enjoy and a religious reminder to avoid gluttony.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; In another Dutch innovation, around 1650 Samuel van Hoogstraten painted one of the first wall-rack pictures, trompe-l'œil still life paintings which feature objects tied, tacked or attached in some other fashion to a wall board, a type of still life very popular in the United States in the 19th century.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 164&lt;/ref&gt; Another variation was the trompe-l'œil still life depicted objects associated with a given profession, as with the Cornelis Norbertus Gysbrecht’s painting &quot;Painter’s Easel with Fruit Piece&quot;, which displays all the tools of a painter’s craft.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; Also popular in the first half of the 17th century was the painting of a large assortment of specimens in allegorical form, such as the &quot;five senses&quot;, &quot;four continents&quot;, or &quot;the four seasons&quot;, showing a goddess or allegorical figure surrounded by appropriate natural and man-made objects.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, pp. 180-181&lt;/ref&gt; The popularity of vanitas paintings, and these other forms of still life, soon spread from Holland to [[Flanders]] and Germany, and also to Spain&lt;ref&gt;See [[Juan van der Hamen]].&lt;/ref&gt; and France.

German still life followed closely the Dutch models. German painter [[Georg Flegel]] was a pioneer in pure still life without figures and created the compositional innovation of placing detailed objects in cabinets, cupboards, and display cases, and producing simultaneous multiple views.&lt;ref&gt;Zuffi, p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; Still life painting in Spain, also called [[bodegón|bodegones]], was austere. It differed from Dutch still life, which often contained rich banquets surrounded by ornate and luxurious items of fabric or glass. The game in Spanish paintings is often plain dead animals still waiting to be skinned. The fruits and vegetables are uncooked. The backgrounds are bleak or plain wood geometric blocks, often creating a surrealist air. Even while both Dutch and Spanish still life often had an embedded moral purpose, the austerity, which some find akin to the bleakness of some of the Spanish plateaus, appears to reject the sensual pleasures, plenitude, and luxury of Dutch still life paintings.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; In Catholic Italy and Spain, the pure vanitas painting was rare, and there were far fewer still life specialists.  In Southern Europe there is more employment of the soft naturalism of Caravaggio and less emphasis on hyper-realism in comparison with Northern European styles.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; In France, painters of still lifes (''nature morte'') were influenced by both the Northern and Southern schools, borrowing from the vanitas paintings of the Netherlands and the spare arrangements of Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dutch, Flemish, German and French gallery===
[[File:Pieter Claesz 002.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Pieter Claesz]] (c. 1597–1660), ''Vanitas still life'', 1630, Royal Picture Gallery [[Mauritshuis]], [[The Hague]]]]
[[Image:Dupuis Pierre Nature Morte.jpg|thumb|250px|right||[[Pierre Dupuis]] (1610-1682), ''Still Life with Plum Branch Hanging From a Wall, Grenades and Vase of Lilies on a Carved End Table,'' 1663]]
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
File:Ambrosius Bosschaert, the Elder 04.jpg|[[Ambrosius Bosschaert]] (1573-1621), ''Still-Life of Flowers,'' (1614) on [[copper]], [[Getty Museum]]
File:'Vase of Flowers with a Curtain', oil on panel painting by Jacques de Gheyn II, 1615.jpg|[[Jacques de Gheyn II]] (1565-1629), ''Vase of Flowers with a Curtain,'' (1615), [[Kimball Art Museum]], [[Fort Worth]], [[Texas]]
[[File:Ambrosius Bosschaert, the Elder 02.jpg|[[Ambrosius Bosschaert]] (1573-1621), ''	Still life with flowers in a Wan-li vase'' (1619), [[Rijksmuseum Amsterdam]]]]
File:Basket-fruits-1622.jpg|[[Balthasar van der Ast]], (c. 1593-1657), ''Basket of Fruits,'' (1622), [[National Gallery of Art]] [[Washington, DC.]]
File:Georg Flegel 001.jpg|[[Georg Flegel]] (1566-1638), ''Peach Twig'', c. 1630
Image:Hans Gillisz. Bollongier 001.jpg|[[Hans Gillisz. Bollongier]] (c. 1600-1675), ''Flower Piece'', (1644), [[Frans Hals Museum]], [[Haarlem]], [[Netherlands]]. The top flower was always the most expensive one and in this bouquet it is the tulip ''Semper Augustus''
Image:Roelant Savery 001.jpg|[[Roelant Savery]] (1576-1639), ''Still life'' (1624), with 44 different species of animals and 63 species of flowers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.centraalmuseum.nl/page.ocl?mode=&amp;version=&amp;pageid=322 Centraalmuseum.nl]&lt;/ref&gt;
Image:Heda Still Life.jpg|[[Willem Claeszoon Heda]] (1594-1680), ''Still Life with Pie, Silver Ewer and Crab'' (1658), [[Frans Hals Museum]], [[Haarlem]]
Image:stilmous1.jpg|[[Abraham van Beyeren]] (ca. 1620-1690), ''Banquet Still Life'' (c. 1660), [[Los Angeles County Museum of Art]]
[[Image:Thielen, Jan Philip van - A Vase of Flowers.jpg|[[Jan Philip van Thielen]] (1618-1667), ''Vase of Flowers'', (ca. 1660), [[Fitzwilliam Museum]], [[Cambridge]], [[England]]]]
Image:De Heem Still Life.jpg|[[Jan Davidsz. de Heem]] (1606-1684),  ''Still Life with Fruit, Flowers, Glasses and Lobster'', (c. 1660s), Musées Royaux des Beaux-Arts, [[Brussels]]
Image:MariaVanOosterwijk.jpg|[[Maria van Oosterwijk]], ''Vase of Tulips, Rose, and Other Flowers with Insects,'' (1669)
File:Still Life with Pewter Jug 1645 Jan Jansz Treck.jpg|[[Jan Jansz. Treck]] (1606-1652) ''Still Life with wanli porcelain, pewter jug, drinking glass, olives and napkin'' 1645, [[Museum of Fine Arts (Budapest)]]
File:Lubin Baugin 001.jpg|[[Lubin Baugin]] (c. 1610-1663), ''Le Dessert de gaufrettes'' (c. 1631), [[Musée du Louvre]], [[Paris]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Eighteenth century==

By the 18th century, in many cases, the religious and allegorical connotations of still life paintings were dropped and kitchen table paintings evolved into calculated depictions of varied color and form, displaying everyday foods. The French aristocracy employed artists to execute paintings of bounteous and extravagant still life subjects that graced their dining table, also without the moralistic vanitas message of their Dutch predecessors.  The [[Rococo]] love of artifice led to a rise in appreciation in France for trompe-l'œil (French:  &quot;trick the eye&quot;) painting. [[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin|Jean-Baptiste Chardin]]’s still life paintings employ a variety of techniques from Dutch-style realism to softer harmonies.&lt;ref&gt;Zuffi, p. 288, 298&lt;/ref&gt;

The bulk of [[Anne Vallayer-Coster]]’s work was devoted to the language of still-life as it had been developed in the course of the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. i&quot;&gt;Michel 1960, p. i&lt;/ref&gt; During these centuries, the genre of still-life was placed lowest on the hierarchical ladder. Vallayer-Coster  had a way about her paintings that resulted in their attractiveness. It was the &quot;bold, decorative lines of her compositions, the richness of her colors and simulated textures, and the feats of illusionism she achieved in depicting wide variety of objects, both natural and artificial&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. i&quot; /&gt; which drew in the attention of the Royal Académie and the numerous collectors who purchased her paintings. This interaction between art and nature was quite common in [[Netherlands|Dutch]], [[Flanders|Flemish]] and French still lifes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. i&quot; /&gt; Her work reveals the clear influence of [[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin]], as well as 17th-century Dutch masters, whose work has been far more highly valued, but what made Vallayer-Coster’s style stand out against the other still life painters was her unique way of coalescing representational illusionism with decorative compositional structures.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. i&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berman 2003&quot;&gt;Berman 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

The end of the eighteenth-century and the fall of the [[French monarchy]] closed the doors on Vallayer-Coster’s still life ‘era’ and opened them to her new style of florals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. ii&quot;&gt;Michel 1960, p. ii&lt;/ref&gt; It has been argued that this was the highlight of her career and what she is best known for. However, it has also been argued that the flower paintings were futile to her career. Nevertheless, this collection contained floral studies in oil, watercolor and gouache.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michel 1960, p. ii&quot; /&gt;
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
Image:RRuysch.jpg|[[Rachel Ruysch]], ''Still-Life with Bouquet of Flowers and Plums,'' 1704, [[Royal Museums of Fine Arts of Belgium]]
File:Still Life with Flowers on a Marble Tabletop 1716 Rachel Ruysch.jpg|[[Rachel Ruysch]], ''Still Life with Flowers on a Marble Tabletop,'' 1716
Image:Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin 007.jpg|[[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin]] (1699–1779), ''The Ray'' 1728, [[Musée du Louvre]], [[Paris]]
Image:Jean-Baptiste Siméon Chardin 029.jpg|[[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin]], ''Still Life with Glass Flask and Fruit'', c. 1750
Image:Attributesmusicsm.jpg|[[Anne Vallayer-Coster]], ''The Attributes of Music'', c.1770
Image:Lobstersm2.jpg|[[Anne Vallayer-Coster]], ''Still Life With Lobster,'' c. 1781
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Nineteenth century==
[[Image:Vincent Willem van Gogh 127.jpg|thumb|right|[[Vincent van Gogh]] (1853-1890), ''[[Sunflowers (series of paintings)|Sunflowers'' or ''Vase with Fifteen Sunflowers]]'' (1888), [[National Gallery (London)]]]]
[[Image:Edouard Manet 011.jpg|thumb|200px|[[Édouard Manet]] (1832-1883), ''Carnations and Clematis in a Crystal Vase'' (1883), [[Musée d'Orsay]], Paris]]

With the rise of the European Academies, most notably the [[Académie française]] which held a central role in [[Academic art]], still life began to fall from favor.  The Academies taught the doctrine of the &quot;[[Hierarchy of genres]]&quot; (or &quot;Hierarchy of Subject Matter&quot;), which held that a painting's [[artistic merit]] was based primarily on its subject.  In the Academic system, the highest form of painting consisted of images of [[History painting|historical]], Biblical or mythological significance, with still life subjects relegated to the very lowest order of artistic recognition.  Instead of using still life to glorify nature, some artists, such as [[John Constable]] and [[Camille Corot]], chose landscapes to serve that end.

When Neo-Classicism started to go into decline by the 1830s, genre and portrait painting became the focus for the Realist and Romantic artistic revolutions. Many of the great artists of that period included still life in their body of work. The still life paintings of [[Francisco Goya]], [[Gustave Courbet]], and [[Eugène Delacroix]] convey a strong emotional current, and are less concerned with exactitude and more interested in mood.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; Though patterned on the earlier still life subjects of [[Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin|Chardin]], [[Édouard Manet]]’s still life paintings are strongly tonal and clearly headed toward Impressionism. [[Henri Fantin-Latour]], using a more traditional technique, was famous for his exquisite flower paintings and made his living almost exclusively painting still life for collectors.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 299&lt;/ref&gt;

However, it was not until the final decline of the Academic hierarchy in Europe, and the rise of the [[Impressionist]] and [[Post-Impressionist]] painters, that technique and color harmony triumphed over subject matter, and that still life was once again avidly practiced by artists. In his early still life, [[Claude Monet]] shows the influence of Fantin-Latour, but is one of the first to break the tradition of the dark background, which [[Pierre-Auguste Renoir]] also discards in ''Still Life with Bouquet and Fan'' (1871), with its bright orange background. With Impressionist still life, allegorical and mythological content is completely absent, as is meticulously detailed brush work. Impressionists instead focused on experimentation in broad, dabbing brush strokes, tonal values, and color placement.  The Impressionists and Post-Impressionists were inspired by nature’s color schemes but reinterpreted nature with their own color harmonies, which sometimes proved startlingly unnaturalistic.  As Gauguin stated, &quot;Colors have their own meanings.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 318&quot;&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 318&lt;/ref&gt; Variations in perspective are also tried, such as using tight cropping and high angles, as with ''Fruit Displayed on a Stand'' by [[Gustave Caillebotte]], a painting which was mocked at the time as a &quot;display of fruit in a bird’s-eye view.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 310&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Vincent van Gogh]]'s &quot;Sunflowers&quot; paintings are some of the best known 19th century still life paintings. Van Gogh uses mostly tones of yellow and rather flat rendering to make a memorable contribution to still life history. His ''Still Life with Drawing Board'' (1889) is a self-portrait in still life form, with van Gogh depicting many items of his personal life, including his pipe, simple food (onions), an inspirational book, and a letter from his brother, all laid out on his table, without his own image present.  He also painted his own version of a vanitas painting ''Still Life with Open Bible, Candle, and Book'' (1885).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 318&quot;/&gt;

In the United States during Revolutionary times, American artists trained abroad applied European styles to American portrait painting and still life. [[Charles Willson Peale]] founded a family of prominent American painters, and as major leader in the American art community, also founded a society for the training of artists as well as a famous museum of natural curiosities. His son [[Raphaelle Peale]] was one of a group of early American still life artists, which also included [[John F. Francis]], [[Charles Bird King]], and John Johnston.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; By the second half of the 19th century, [[Martin Johnson Heade]] introduced the American version of the habitat or biotope picture, which placed flowers and birds in simulated outdoor environments.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 267&lt;/ref&gt; The American trompe-l'œil paintings also flourished during this period, created by [[John Haberle]], [[William Michael Harnett]], and [[John Frederick Peto]].  Peto specialized in the nostalgic wall-rack painting while Harnett achieved the highest level of hyper-realism in his pictorial celebrations of American life through familiar objects.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 272&lt;/ref&gt;

===Nineteenth century gallery===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
File:Francisco de Goya y Lucientes 093.jpg|[[Francisco Goya]], ''Still Life with Fruit, Bottles, Breads'', 1824-1826
File:Eugène Ferdinand Victor Delacroix 054.jpg|[[Eugène Delacroix]], ''Still Life with Lobster and trophies of hunting and fishing'', 1826-1827, [[Louvre]]
File:Cailebotte - Nature Morte.jpg|[[Gustave Caillebotte]], (1848-1894), ''Yellow Roses in a Vase'', 1882, [[Dallas Museum of Art]]
Image:Roses Grapes Tablecloth by Fantin-Latour.jpg|[[Henri Fantin-Latour]], (1836-1904), ''White Roses, Chrysanthemums in a Vase, Peaches and Grapes on a Table with a White Tablecloth'', 1867
Image:Paul Cézanne 052.jpg|[[Paul Cézanne]] (1839-1906), ''The Black Marble Clock,'' (1869-1871), Private collection
File:Cassatt Mary Lilacs in a Window 1880.jpg|[[Mary Cassatt]],(1844-1926), ''Lilacs in a Window'', 1880
File:Monet-Still-Life-with-Apples-and-Grapes-1880.jpg|[[Claude Monet]] (1840-1926), ''Still-Life with Apples and Grapes,'' (1880), [[Art Institute of Chicago]]
File:Paul Gauguin 116.jpg|[[Paul Gauguin]], ''Still Life with Apples, a Pear, and a Ceramic Portrait Jug'', 1889, [[Fogg Museum]], [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]]
File:William Michael Harnett Still life Violin and Music.jpg|[[William Harnett]] (1848-1892), ''Still life violin and music'', (1888), [[Metropolitan Museum of Art]], [[New York City]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Twentieth century==
[[Image:Compotier avec fruits, violon et verre.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Pablo Picasso]], ''Compotier avec fruits, violon et verre,'' 1912]]
[[Image:Matisse518.jpg|thumb|left|[[Henri Matisse]], ''[[Still Life with Geraniums]],'' 1910, [[Pinakothek der Moderne]], [[Munich, Germany]]]]
The first four decades of the 20th century formed an exceptional period of artistic ferment and revolution. Avant-garde movements rapidly evolved and overlapped in a march towards nonfigurative, total abstraction.  The still life, as well as other representational art, continued to evolve and adjust until mid-century when total abstraction, as exemplified by [[Jackson Pollock]]'s drip paintings, eliminated all recognizable content.

The century began with several trends taking hold in art. In 1901, [[Paul Gauguin]] painted  ''Still Life with Sunflowers'', his homage to his friend van Gogh who had died eleven years earlier. The group known as the [[Nabi]], including [[Pierre Bonnard]] and [[Edouard Vuillard]], took up Gauguin’s harmonic theories and added elements inspired by Japanese woodcuts to their still life paintings. French artist [[Odilon Redon]] also painted notable still life during in this period, especially flowers.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 321&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Henri Matisse]] reduced the rendering of still life objects even further to little more than bold, flat outlines filled with bright colors. He also simplifyied perspective and introducing multi-color backgrounds.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, pp. 323-4&lt;/ref&gt; In some of his still life paintings, such as ''Still Life with Eggplants'', his table of objects is nearly lost amidst the other colorful patterns filling the rest of the room.&lt;ref&gt;Stefano Zuffi, Ed., ''Modern Painting'', Barron’s Educational Series, Hauppauge, New York, 1998, p. 273, ISBN 0-7641-5119-3&lt;/ref&gt; Other exponents of [[Fauvism]], such as [[Maurice de Vlaminck]] and [[André Derain]], further explored pure color and abstraction in their still life.

[[Paul Cézanne]] found in still life the perfect vehicle for his revolutionary explorations in geometric spatial organization.  For Cézanne, still life was a primary means of taking painting away from an illustrative or mimetic function to one demonstrating independently the elements of color, form, and line, a major step towards Abstract art. Additionally, Cézanne's experiments can be seen as leading directly to the development of [[Cubist]] still life in the early 20th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 311&quot;&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 311&lt;/ref&gt;

Adapting Cézanne’s shifting of planes and axes, the Cubists subdued the color palette of the Fauves and focused instead on deconstructing objects into pure geometrical forms and planes. Between 1910 and 1920, Cubist artists like [[Pablo Picasso]], [[Georges Braque]], and [[Juan Gris]] painted many still life compositions, often including musical instruments, as well as creating the first Synthetic Cubist [[collage]] works, such as Picasso's oval &quot;Still Life with Chair Caning&quot; (1912).  In these works, still life objects overlap and intermingle barely maintaining identifiable two-dimensional forms, losing individual surface texture, and merging into the background—achieving goals nearly opposite to those of traditional still life.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 338&lt;/ref&gt; [[Fernand Léger]]’s still life introduced the use of abundant white space and colored, sharply defined, overlapping geometrical shapes to produce a more mechanical effect.&lt;ref&gt;David Piper, ''The Illustrated Library of Art'', Portland House, New York, 1986, p. 643, ISBN 0-517-62336-6&lt;/ref&gt;  Rejecting the flattening of space by Cubists, [[Marcel Duchamp]] and other members of the [[Dada]] movement, went in a radically different direction, creating 3-D &quot;ready-made&quot; still life sculptures. As part of restoring some symbolic meaning to still life, the [[Futurism|Futurists]] and the [[Surrealism|Surrealists]] placed recognizable still life objects in their dreamscapes. In [[Joan Miró]]’s still life paintings, objects appear weightless and float in lightly suggested two-dimensional space, and even mountains are drawn as simple lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 311&quot;/&gt; In Italy during this time, [[Giorgio Morandi]] was the foremost still life painter, exploring a wide variety of approaches to depicting everyday bottles and kitchen implements.&lt;ref&gt;David Piper, p. 635&lt;/ref&gt; Dutch artist [[M. C. Escher]], best known for his detailed yet ambiguous graphics, created ''Still life and Street'' (1937), his updated version of the traditional Dutch table still life.&lt;ref&gt;Piper, p. 639&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:'Natura Morta', oil on canvas painting by Giorgio Morandi, 1956, private collection.jpg|thumb|left|[[Giorgio Morandi]] (1890-1964), ''Natura Morta,'' oil on canvas, 1956, private collection]]
When 20th century American artists became aware of European [[Modernism]], they began to interpret still life subjects with a combination of [[American realism]] and Cubist-derived abstraction.  Typical of the American still life works of this period are the paintings of [[Georgia O'Keeffe]], [[Stuart Davis (painter)|Stuart Davis]], and [[Marsden Hartley]], and the photographs of [[Edward Weston]]. O’Keeffe’s ultra-closeup flower paintings reveal both the physical structure and the emotional subtext of petals and leaves in an unprecedented manner.
&lt;!-- Image with unknown copyright status removed: [[Image:Goings3.jpg|thumb|left|220px|[[Ralph Goings]], ''Pie with Ice Tea'',  Private Collection.]]--&gt;

In Mexico, starting in the 1930s, [[Frida Kahlo]] and other artists created their own brand of Surrealism, featuring native foods and cultural motifs in their still life paintings.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in the 1930s, [[Abstract Expressionism]] severely reduced still life to raw depictions of form and color, until by the 1950s, total abstraction dominated the art world. However, [[Pop Art]] in the 1960s and 1970s reversed the trend and created a new form of still life. Much Pop Art (such as [[Andy Warhol]]'s &quot;Campbell's Soup Cans&quot;) is based on still life, but its true subject is most often the commodified image of the commercial product represented rather than the physical still life object itself.  [[Roy Lichtenstein]]’s ''Still Life with Goldfish Bowl'' (1972) combines the pure colors of Matisse with the pop iconography of Warhol. [[Wayne Thiebaud]]’s ''Lunch Table'' (1964) portrays not a single family’s lunch but an assembly line of standardized American foods.&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, pp. 382-3&lt;/ref&gt;

The Neo-dada movement, including [[Jasper Johns]], returned to Duchamp’s three-dimensional representation of everyday household objects to create their own brand of still life work, as in Johns’ ''Painted Bronze'' (1960)  and ''Fool’s House'' (1962).&lt;ref&gt;Ebert-Schifferer, p. 384-6&lt;/ref&gt; [[Avigdor Arikha]], who began as an [[abstractionist]], integrated the lessons of [[Piet Mondrian]] into his still lifes as into his other work; while reconnecting to old master traditions, he achieved a [[modernist]] [[Formalism (art)|formalism]], working in one session and in natural light, through which the subject-matter often emerged in a surprising perspective.

A significant contribution to the development of still life painting in the 20th century was made by Russian artists, among them [[Sergei Ivanovich Osipov|Sergei Ocipov]], [[Victor Teterin]], [[Evgenia Antipova]], [[Gevork Kotiantz]], [[Sergei Yefimovich Zakharov|Sergei Zakharov]], [[Taisia Afonina]], [[Maya Kopitseva]], and others.&lt;ref&gt;Sergei V. Ivanov, Unknown Socialist Realism. The Leningrad School.'' - Saint Petersburg: NP-Print Edition, 2007. – 448 p. ISBN 5-901724-21-6, ISBN 978-5-901724-21-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

By contrast, the rise of [[Photorealism]] in the 1970s reasserted illusionistic representation, while retaining some of Pop's message of the fusion of object, image, and commercial product. Typical in this regard are the paintings of [[Don Eddy]] and [[Ralph Goings]].

===Twentieth century gallery===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;200px&quot; heights=&quot;200px&quot; perrow=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
File:Matisse - Dishes and Fruit (1901).jpg|[[Henri Matisse]] (1869-1954), ''Dishes and Fruit'' (1901), [[Hermitage Museum]], [[Saint Petersburg|St. Petersburg]], Russia
File:Redon.flowers.jpg|[[Odilon Redon]] (1840–1916), ''Flowers'', 1903
File:Violin and Candlestick.jpg|[[Georges Braque]] (1882-1963), ''Violin and Candlestick'' (1910), [[San Francisco Museum of Modern Art]]
Image:26. Bodegón.jpg|[[Juan Gris]] (1887-1927), ''Nature morte'', 1913. [[Museo Thyssen Bornemisza]]
File:Brooklyn Museum - Handsome Drinks - Marsden Hartley - overall.jpg|[[Marsden Hartley]] (1877-1943), ''Handsome Drinks'', c. 1916, [[Brooklyn Museum]]
Image:Leger beer mug.jpg|[[Fernand Léger]] (1881-1955), ''Still Life with a Beer Mug'' 1921, [[Tate]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===21st century===
[[Image:Glasses 800 edit.png|thumb|A completely synthetic, [[computer graphics|computer generated]] still life, 2006, made in the 21st century.]]
In the last three decades of the 20th century, and in the early years of the 21st century still life has expanded beyond the boundary of a frame. Especially in the wake of the [[computer age]], and the rise of [[Computer art]] and [[Digital art]] the nature and definition of still life has changed. Some mixed media still life work employing found objects, photography, video, and sound, and even spilling out from ceiling to floor, and filling an entire room in a gallery. Computer-generated graphics have expanded the techniques available to still life artists. With the use of the video camera, still life artists can even incorporate the viewer into their work.

==See also==
{{div col|colwidth=20em}}
* [[Digital illustration]]
* [[Digital painting]]
* [[Digital photography]]
* [[Dutch Golden Age painting]]
* [[Electronic art]]
* [[Graphic art software]]
* [[History of painting]]
* [[List of Dutch painters]]
* [[New media]]
* [[Software art]]
* [[Still life photography]]
* [[Tradigital art]]
{{div col end}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* Ebert-Schifferer, Sybille. ''Still Life: A History'', Harry N. Abrams, New York, 1998, ISBN 0-8109-4190-2
* Slive, Seymour, ''Dutch Painting, 1600-1800'', Yale University Press, 1995, ISBN 0-300-07451-4
* Vlieghe, Hans (1998). ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=AS_NXFoY0M4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Flemish Art and Architecture, 1585-1700]''. Yale University Press Pelican history of art. New Haven: Yale University Press. ISBN 0-300-07038-1
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category-inline|Still life paintings}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Still Life}}
[[Category:Art genres]]
[[Category:Still life painters]]

{{Link FA|ca}}

[[bg:Натюрморт]]
[[bs:Mrtva priroda]]
[[ca:Natura morta]]
[[cs:Zátiší]]
[[da:Stilleben]]
[[de:Stillleben]]
[[et:Natüürmort]]
[[es:Bodegón]]
[[eo:Fono]]
[[fa:طبیعت بی‌جان]]
[[fr:Nature morte]]
[[fy:Stillibben]]
[[gl:Natureza morta]]
[[ko:정물화]]
[[hy:Նատյուրմորտ]]
[[hr:Mrtva priroda]]
[[it:Natura morta]]
[[he:טבע דומם]]
[[ka:ნატურმორტი]]
[[kk:Натюрморт]]
[[lv:Klusā daba]]
[[lt:Natiurmortas]]
[[hu:Csendélet]]
[[mt:Natura mejta]]
[[nl:Stilleven]]
[[ja:静物画]]
[[no:Stilleben]]
[[nn:Stilleben]]
[[pl:Martwa natura]]
[[pt:Natureza-morta]]
[[ro:Natură statică]]
[[ru:Натюрморт]]
[[simple:Still life]]
[[sk:Zátišie (maliarstvo)]]
[[sl:Tihožitje]]
[[sr:Мртва природа]]
[[sh:Mrtva priroda]]
[[fi:Asetelma (maalaustaide)]]
[[sv:Stilleben]]
[[th:ภาพนิ่ง]]
[[tg:Натюрморт]]
[[tr:Natürmort]]
[[uk:Натюрморт]]
[[zh:静物画]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
