<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Makeup brushes" to="Cosmetics" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="158015" ns="0" title="Cosmetics"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Make-up}}
{{Other uses|Cosmetic (disambiguation)}}

[[File:Cosmetics.JPG|thumb|Assorted cosmetics and tools]]
[[File:Makeup femin.JPG|thumb|Woman applying makeup]]
'''Cosmetics''' are substances used to enhance the [[Human physical appearance|appearance]] or [[odor]] of the [[human body]]. Cosmetics include [[Human skin|skin]]-care [[Cream (pharmaceutical)|creams]], [[lotion]]s, [[Powder (substance)|powders]], [[perfume]]s, [[lipstick]]s, fingernail and toe [[nail polish]], [[Human eye|eye]] and facial makeup, [[Wet wipe|towelettes]], permanent waves, [[colored contact lenses]], [[hair]] colors, [[hair spray]]s and [[gels]], [[deodorants]], [[hand sanitizer]], baby products, bath oils, [[bubble bath]]s, [[bath salts]], [[butter]]s and many other types of products. A subset of cosmetics is called &quot;make-up,&quot; which refers primarily to colored products intended to alter the user’s appearance. Many manufacturers distinguish between decorative cosmetics and care cosmetics. The word ''cosmetics'' derives from the [[Greek language|Greek]] κοσμητική τέχνη (''kosmetikē tekhnē''),  meaning &quot;technique of dress and ornament&quot;, from κοσμητικός (''kosmētikos''), &quot;skilled in ordering or arranging&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dkosmhtiko%2Fs κοσμητικός], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus&lt;/ref&gt; and that from κόσμος (''kosmos''),  meaning amongst others &quot;order&quot; and &quot;ornament&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0057%3Aentry%3Dko%2Fsmos κόσμος], Henry George Liddell, Robert Scott, ''A Greek-English Lexicon'', on Perseus&lt;/ref&gt;

The manufacture of cosmetics is currently dominated by a small number of [[multinational corporations]] that originated in the early 20th century, but the distribution and sale of cosmetics is spread among a wide range of different businesses. The U.S. [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) which regulates cosmetics in the [[United States]]&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt; defines cosmetics as: &quot;intended to be applied to the human body for cleansing, beautifying, promoting attractiveness, or altering the appearance without affecting the body's structure or functions.&quot; This broad definition includes, as well, any material intended for use as a [[wikt:component|component]] of a cosmetic product. The FDA specifically excludes [[soap]] from this category.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, Carol. FDA. &quot;Clearing up Cosmetic Confusion.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Nefertiti 30-01-2006.jpg|thumb|right|[[Nefertiti bust]] with [[eye liner]] applied]]
[[File:Lautrec woman at her toilette 1889.jpg|thumb|An 1889 [[Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec]] painting of a woman applying cosmetics to her face]] 
{{Main|History of cosmetics}}
The first [[Archaeology|archaeological]] evidence of cosmetics usage was found in [[Egypt]] around [[3500 BC]] during the [[Old Kingdom]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2011}} The [[Ancient Greek]]s and [[Ancient Rome|Romans]] also used cosmetics.&lt;ref&gt;Lesley Adkins, Roy A. Adkins, ''Handbook to life in Ancient Greece'', Oxford University Press, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bruno Burlando, Luisella Verotta, Laura Cornara, and Elisa Bottini-Massa, ''Herbal Principles in Cosmetics'', CRC Press, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; The [[ancient Rome|Romans]] and [[Ancient Egyptians]] used cosmetics containing poisonous [[mercury (element)|mercury]] and often [[lead]]. The ancient kingdom of Israel was influenced by cosmetics as recorded in the [[Old Testament]]—2 Kings 9:30 where [[Jezebel]] painted her eyelids—approximately 840 BC. The Biblical book of [[Esther]] describes various beauty treatments as well.

In the [[Middle Ages]], although its use was frowned upon by [[Catholic Church|Church leaders]], many women still wore cosmetics. A popular fad for women during the Middle Ages was to have a pale-skinned complexion, which was achieved through either applying pastes of lead, chalk, or flour, or by [[bloodletting]]. Women would also put white lead pigment that was known as &quot;ceruse&quot; on their faces to appear to have pale skin.&lt;ref&gt;Rao,prathiba, cosmetics and personal care products, vol 1, pp 380-382,Elsevier inc, 1998&lt;/ref&gt;

Cosmetic use was frowned upon at many points in Western history. For example, in the 19th century, [[Victoria of the United Kingdom|Queen Victoria]] publicly declared makeup improper, [[vulgar]], and acceptable only for use by [[actor]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Lipstick: A Celebration of the World's Favorite Cosmetic | first = J | last = Pallingston | isbn = 0312199147 | publisher = St. Martin's Press | year = 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Women in the 19th century liked to be thought of as fragile ladies. They compared themselves to delicate flowers and emphasized their delicacy and femininity. They aimed always to look pale and interesting. Sometimes ladies discreetly used a little rouge on the cheeks, and used &quot;[[Atropa belladonna|belladonna]]&quot; to dilate their eyes to make their eyes stand out more. Make-up was frowned upon in general especially during the 1870s when social etiquette became more rigid. 

Actresses however were allowed to use make up and famous beauties such as [[Sarah Bernhardt]] and [[Lillie Langtry]] could be powdered. Most cosmetic products available were still either chemically dubious, or found in the kitchen amid food colorings, berries and [[beetroot]].

By the middle of the 20th century, cosmetics were in widespread use by women in nearly all [[industrial society|industrial societies]] around the world.

Cosmetics have been in use for thousands of years. The absence of regulation of the manufacture and use of cosmetics has led to negative [[adverse effect|side effects]], [[deformities]], blindness, and even death through the ages. Examples of this were the prevalent use of [[ceruse]] (white lead), to cover the face during the [[Renaissance]], and blindness caused by the [[mascara]] Lash Lure during the early 20th century.

The worldwide annual [[expenditure]]s for cosmetics today is estimated at [[USD|$]]19 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=As Consumerism Spreads, Earth Suffers, Study Says | date= | publisher= | url =http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2004/01/0111_040112_consumerism_2.html | work =[[National Geographic]] | page =2 | accessdate = 2007-08-21 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; Of the major firms, the largest is [[L'Oréal]], which was founded by [[Eugene Schueller]] in 1909 as the French Harmless Hair Colouring Company (now owned by [[Liliane Bettencourt]] 26% and [[Nestlé]] 28%; the remaining 46% is traded publicly). The market was developed in the USA during the 1910s by [[Elizabeth Arden]], [[Helena Rubinstein]], and [[Max Factor]]. These firms were joined by [[Revlon]] just before [[World War II]] and [[Estée Lauder Inc.|Estée Lauder]] just after. 

Beauty products are now widely available from dedicated internet-only retailers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | first= | last= | coauthors= | title=Lessons from categorising the entire beauty products sector (Part 1) | date= | publisher= | url =http://www.beautynow.co.uk/blog/beauty-products-part-1-522.html | work = | page =1 | accessdate = 2009-09-28 | language = }}&lt;/ref&gt; who have more recently been joined online by established outlets, including the major department stores and traditional bricks and mortar beauty retailers. 

Like most industries, cosmetic companies resist regulation by government agencies like the FDA, and have lobbied against this throughout the years. The FDA does not have to approve or review the cosmetics, or what goes in them before they are sold to the consumers. The FDA only regulates against the colors that can be used in the cosmetics and hair dyes. The cosmetic companies do not have to report any injuries from the products; they also only have voluntary recalls on products.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;cosmetics and your health.&quot; womensheatlh.gov.nd.web.4 nov 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Though modern make-up has been used mainly by women traditionally, gradually an increasing number of males are using cosmetics usually associated to women to enhance or cover their own facial features. [[Concealer]] is commonly used by cosmetic-conscious men. Cosmetics brands are releasing cosmetic products especially tailored for men, and men are using such products increasily more commonly.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cfsan.fda.gov/~dms/cos-206.html |title=FDA Authority Over Cosmetics |publisher=Cfsan.fda.gov |date= |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; There is some controversy over this, however, as many feel that men who wear make-up are neglecting traditional gender roles, and do not view men wearing cosmetics in a positive light. Others, however, view this as a sign of ongoing gender equality and feel that men also have rights to enhance their facial features with cosmetics if women could. While highly subjective, some feel the most attractive beauty is natural beauty without make up.

==Criticism and controversy==
{{See|Campaign for Safe Cosmetics|Testing cosmetics on animals}}

During the 20th century, the popularity of cosmetics increased rapidly.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}} Cosmetics are increasingly used by girls at a young age, especially in the United States. Due to the fast-decreasing age of make-up users, many companies, from high-street brands like Rimmel to higher-end products like Estee Lauder, have catered to this expanding market by introducing more flavored lipsticks and glosses, cosmetics packaged in glittery, sparkly packaging and marketing and advertising using young [[model (person)|models]].{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}} The social consequences of younger and younger [[beautification]] has had much attention in the media over the last few years.

[[Criticism]] of cosmetics has come from a variety of sources including some [[feminist]]s, [[religion|religious groups]],  [[Animal rights#History of the modern movement|animal rights activists]], [[The Beauty Myth|authors]] and public interest groups. There is a growing awareness and preference for cosmetics that are without any supposedly [[toxic]] ingredients, especially those derived from [[petroleum]], [[sodium lauryl sulfate]] (SLS), and [[paraben]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Safety_First&quot;&gt;
{{cite news
|first=
|last=
|title=Signers of the Compact for Safe Cosmetics
|url=http://www.safecosmetics.org/companies/signers.cfm 
|work=
|publisher=[[Campaign for Safe Cosmetics]]
|date=
|accessdate=2007-07-05
|quote= |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070609155356/http://www.safecosmetics.org/companies/signers.cfm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-06-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous published reports have raised concern over the safety of a few [[surfactants]]. SLS causes a number of skin issues including [[dermatitis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Agner_T&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Agner T |title=Susceptibility of atopic dermatitis patients to irritant dermatitis caused by sodium lauryl sulphate |journal=Acta Derm. Venereol. |volume=71 |issue=4 |pages=296–300 |year=1991 |pmid=1681644 |doi= |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;A._Nassif_1994&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Nassif A, Chan SC, Storrs FJ, Hanifin JM |title=Abnormal skin irritancy in atopic dermatitis and in atopy without dermatitis |journal=Arch Dermatol |volume=130 |issue=11 |pages=1402–7 |year=1994 |month=November |pmid=7979441 |doi= 10.1001/archderm.130.11.1402|url=http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/195/7/855}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marrakchi_S&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Marrakchi S, Maibach HI |title=Sodium lauryl sulfate-induced irritation in the human face: regional and age-related differences |journal=Skin Pharmacol Physiol |volume=19 |issue=3 |pages=177–80 |year=2006 |pmid=16679819 |doi=10.1159/000093112 |url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Final_Report_SLS&quot;&gt;CIR publication. Final Report on the Safety Assessment of Sodium Lauryl Sulfate and Ammonium Lauryl Sulfate. ''Journal of the American College of Toxicology.'' 1983 Vol. 2 (No. 7) pages 127–181.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Loffler_H&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Löffler H, Effendy I |title=Skin susceptibility of atopic individuals |journal=Contact Derm. |volume=40 |issue=5 |pages=239–42 |year=1999 |month=May |pmid=10344477 |doi= 10.1111/j.1600-0536.1999.tb06056.x|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Parabens]] can cause skin irritation and [[contact dermatitis]] in individuals with paraben [[allergies]], a small percentage of the general population.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Nagel JE, Fuscaldo JT, Fireman P |title=Paraben allergy |journal=JAMA |volume=237 |issue=15 |pages=1594–5 |year=1977 |month=April |pmid=576658 |doi= 10.1001/jama.237.15.1594|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Animal experiments have shown that parabens have a weak [[estrogen]]ic activity, acting as [[xenoestrogen]]s.&lt;ref name=byfordetal&gt;{{cite journal |author=Byford JR, Shaw LE, Drew MG, Pope GS, Sauer MJ, Darbre PD |title=Oestrogenic activity of parabens in MCF7 human breast cancer cells |journal=J. Steroid Biochem. Mol. Biol. |volume=80 |issue=1 |pages=49–60 |year=2002 |month=January |pmid=11867263 |doi= 10.1016/S0960-0760(01)00174-1|url=http://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0960076001001741}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prolonged use of makeup has also been linked to thinning eyelashes.&lt;ref&gt;Towards Beautiful Eyes &amp;ndash; Solutions for Thinning Lashes and Dark Patches, Kamau Austin.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Perfume|Synthetic fragrances]] are widely used in consumer products. Studies concluded from patch testing show synthetic [[fragrances]] are made of many [[allergen|ingredients which cause allergic reactions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Synthetic_Fragrances&quot;&gt;
{{cite journal |author=Frosch PJ, Pilz B, Andersen KE, ''et al.'' |title=Patch testing with fragrances: results of a multicenter study of the European Environmental and Contact Dermatitis Research Group with 48 frequently used constituents of perfumes |journal=Contact Derm. |volume=33 |issue=5 |pages=333–42 |year=1995 |month=November |pmid=8565489 |doi= 10.1111/j.1600-0536.1995.tb02048.x|url=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Cosmetics companies have been criticised for making [[pseudoscientific]] claims about their products which are misleading or unsupported by scientific evidence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://news.scotsman.com/latestnews/-Pseudo-science-can39t-cover.3606975.jp | location=Edinburgh | work=The Scotsman | first=Martyn | last=McLaughlin | title=Pseudo science can't cover up the ugly truth | date=2007-12-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.badscience.net/category/cosmetics/ |title=cosmetics – Bad Science |publisher=Badscience.net |date= |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Makeup types==
Most cosmetics are distinguished by the area of the body intended for application.
*[[Lipgloss]], is a sheer form of lipstick that is in a liquid form. 
* [[Lipstick]], [[lip gloss]], [[lip liner]], [[lip plumper]], [[lip balm]], lip conditioner, lip primer, and lip boosters.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman&gt;Reed, Sandra I. US Department of Health and Human Services. &quot;Cosmetics and Your Health.&quot; 2004. May 14, 2007. [http://www.4woman.gov/faq/cosmetics.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Lip stains have a water or gel base and may contain alcohol to help the product stay on the lips. The idea behind lip stains is to temporarily saturate the lips with a dye, rather than covering them with a colored wax. Usually designed to be waterproof, the product may come with an applicator brush or be applied with a finger.
* [[Concealer]], makeup used to cover any imperfections of the skin. Concealer is often used for any extra coverage needed to cover blemishes, or any other marks. Concealer is often thicker and more solid than foundation, and provides longer lasting, and more detailed coverage. 
* [[Foundation (cosmetics)|Foundation]], used to smooth out the [[face]] and cover spots or uneven skin coloration. Usually a liquid, cream, or powder, as well as most recently, a light and fluffy mousse, which provides excellent coverage as well.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt; Foundation primer can be applied before or after to get a smoother finish. Some primers come in powder or liquid form to be applied before foundation as a base, while other primers come as a spray to be applied after you are finished to help make-up last longer.
* [[Face powder]], used to set the foundation, giving a [[wikt:Special:Search/matte|matte]] finish, and also to conceal small flaws or blemishes.
* [[Rouge (cosmetics)|Rouge, blush or blusher]], cheek coloring used to bring out the color in the [[cheeks]] and make the [[cheekbones]] appear more defined. This comes in powder, cream, and liquid forms.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt;
* [[Bronzer]], used to give skin a bit of color by adding a golden or bronze glow.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt;
* [[Mascara]] is used to darken, lengthen, and thicken the [[eyelash]]es. It is available in natural colors such as brown and black, but also comes in bolder colors such as blue, pink, or purple. There are many different formulas, including [[waterproof]] for those prone to [[allergies]] or sudden tears. Often used after an [[eyelash curler]] and mascara primer.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt; There are now also many mascaras with certain components to help lashes to grow longer and thicker. There are specific minerals and proteins that are combined with the mascara that can benefit, as well as beautify.
[[File:Pre-wedding make-up.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Eye shadow]] being applied]]
[[File:Jim Brochu.jpg|thumb|[[Broadway theatre|Broadway]] actor [[Jim Brochu]] applies make-up before the opening night of a play.]]
[[File:Kerala kathakali makeup.jpg|thumb|right|The chin mask known as ''chutti'' for [[Kathakali]], a performing art in [[Kerala]], [[India]] is considered the thickest makeup applied for any art form.]]
* [[Eyelid glue]], [[eyelash extensions]], [[eye liner]], [[eye shadow]], eye shimmer, and glitter eye pencils as well as different color pencils used to color and emphasize the [[eyelid]]s (larger eyes give a more youthful appearance).&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt;
* [[Eyebrow]] pencils, creams, [[wax]]es, gels and powders are used to color and define the brows.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt;
* [[Nail polish]], used to color the [[finger]]nails and [[toe]]nails.&lt;ref name=USHealthandHuman/&gt;

Cosmetics can be also described by the physical composition of the product. Cosmetics can be liquid or cream [[emulsions]]; powders, both pressed and loose; dispersions; and [[anhydrous]] creams or sticks.

[[Makeup remover]] is the product used to remove the makeup products applied on the skin. It is used for cleaning the skin for other procedures, like applying any type of lotion at evening before the person go to sleep.

==Skin care products==
Also included in the general category of cosmetics are skin care products. These include creams and lotions to moisturize the face and body which are often formulated for different skin types per range, [[sunscreen]]s to protect the skin from [[UV radiation]] and damage, [[skin lightener]]s, and treatment products to repair or hide skin imperfections ([[Acne vulgaris|acne]], [[Wrinkle (skin)|wrinkles]], dark circles under eyes, etc.), [[tanning oil]]s to brown the skin.

==Ingredients==
{{Main|Ingredients of cosmetics}}

While there is assurance from the largest cosmetic companies that ingredients have passed quality tests and official regulations, and are therefore generally safe to use, there is a growing preference for cosmetics that are without any &quot;synthetic&quot; ingredients, especially those derived from petroleum. Once a [[niche market]], handmade and [[certified organic]] products are becoming more [[mainstream]].

Ingredients' listings in cosmetics are highly regulated in many countries. The [[Animal testing#Cosmetics testing|testing of cosmetic products on animals]] is a subject of some controversy. It is now illegal in the [[United Kingdom]], the [[Netherlands]], and [[Belgium]], and a [[Ban (law)|ban]] across the [[European Union]] came into effect in 2009.

===Organic and natural ingredients===
Even though many cosmetic products are regulated, there are still health concerns regarding the presence of harmful chemicals within these products.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} Aside from color additives, cosmetic products and their ingredients are not subject to FDA regulation prior to their release into the market. It is only when a product is found to violate Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (FD&amp;C Act) and Fair Packaging and Labeling Act (FPLA) after its release that the FDA may start taking action against this violation.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt; With many new products released into the market every season, it is hard to keep track of the safety of every product. Some products carry carcinogenic contaminant 1,4- dioxane. Many cosmetic companies are coming out with &quot;All natural&quot; and organic products. All natural products contain  mineral and plant ingredients and organic products are made with [[certified organic|organic]] agricultural products. Products who claim they are organic are not, unless they are certified &quot;USDA Organic.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Singer, Natasha. &quot;Natural, Organic Beauty.&quot; New York Times. 1 Nov. 2007. 18 Mar. 2008&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&lt;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/11/01/fashion/01skin.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

====Mineral makeup====
Mineral makeup, another term for loose powder makeup foundation, largely comprises earth-based Ingredients. This product contains coverage pigments like zinc oxide and titanium dioxide, both of which are also physical sunscreens.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/mineral_makeup |title=mineral makeup - Wiktionary |publisher=En.wiktionary.org |date= |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main ingredients (minerals such as mica, zinc oxide, and titanium dioxide), have been the basis of most makeup foundations for decades, but many dermatologists report that because mineral makeup frequently eliminates classic irritants such as fragrances, binders, synthetic dyes, talc, and preservatives, it is considered purer and can be kinder to the skin.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Palladino |first=Lisa |url=http://www.luxist.com/2009/12/07/what-is-mineral-makeup/ |title=What Is Mineral Makeup? |publisher=Luxist.com |date=2009-12-07 |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Benefits of mineral makeup=====
Because titanium dioxide and zinc oxide have anti-inflammatory properties, certain mineral makeups can also have a calming effect on the skin, particularly important if you suffer from inflammatory problems such as rosacea or acne. Mineral makeup also is known for being noncomedogenic, and many manufacturers claim it also offers sun protection. This is mostly due to the high content of titanium dioxide and zinc oxide -- two ingredients commonly found in traditional sunscreen.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

{{see also|natural skin care}}

==Cosmetic industry==
The cosmetic industry is a profitable business for most manufacturers of cosmetic products. By cosmetic products, we understand anything that is intended for personal care such as skin lotions or sun lotions, makeup and other such products meant to emphasize one's look. Given the technological development and the improvement of the [[manufacturing]] process of cosmetics and not least due to the constantly increasing demand of such products, this industry reported an important growth in terms of [[Profit (economics)|profit]].

The cosmetic industry has not only grown only in the [[United States]], but also in various parts of the world which have become famous for their cosmetic precuts. Some of these include [[France]], [[Germany]], [[Italy]] and [[Japan]]. It has been estimated that in Germany, the cosmetic industry generated sales of EUR 12.6 billion at [[Retail sales#Retail Sales|retail sales]], in 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosmetic Industry&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.german-business-portal.info/GBP/Navigation/en/Business-Location/Manufacturing%20Industries/cosmetics-industry,did=326082.html|title=Cosmetic Industry|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; which made of German cosmetic industry the 3rd in the world, after [[Japan]] and the United States. Also, it has been shown that in the same country, this industry has grown with nearly 5 percent in one year, from 2007 to 2008. The [[exports]] of Germany in this industry reached in 2008 EUR 5.8 billion whereas the imports of cosmetics totaled EUR 3 billion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosmetic Industry&quot;/&gt; The main countries that export cosmetics to Germany are France, [[Switzerland]], the United States and Italy and they mainly consist of makeup and fragrances or perfumes for women.

After the United States, Japan is the second largest market for cosmetics in the world, a market worth about JPY 1.4 trillion per year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.japaninc.com/article.php?articleID=1390|title=Blueprint for a Cosmetics Empire|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The worldwide cosmetics and perfume industry currently generates an estimated annual turnover of US$170 billion (according to Eurostaf - May 2007). Europe is the leading market, representing approximately €63 billion, while sales in France reached €6.5 billion in 2006, according to FIPAR (Fédération des Industries de la Parfumerie - the French federation for the perfume industry).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.clickpress.com/releases/Detailed/82987005cp.shtml|title=France continues to lead the way in cosmetics|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; France is another country in which the cosmetic industry plays an important role, both nationally and internationally. Most products on whose label it is stated &quot;Made in France&quot; are valued on the international market. According to data from 2008, the cosmetic industry has risen constantly in France, for 40 consecutive years. In 2006, this industrial sector reached a record level of EUR 6.5 billion. Famous cosmetic brands produced in France include Vichy, [[Yves Saint Laurent (brand)|Yves Saint Laurent]], [[Yves Rocher]] and many others.

The Italian cosmetic industry is also an important player in the European cosmetic market. Although not as large as in other European countries, the cosmetic industry in Italy was estimated to reach EUR 9 billion in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://researchwikis.com/Cosmetics_-_Europe_%28Italy%29_2008_Marketing_Research|title=Cosmetics - Europe (Italy) 2008 Marketing Research|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Italian cosmetic industry is however dominated by [[hair]] and body products and not makeup as in many other European countries. In Italy, hair and body products make up approximately 30% of the cosmetic market. Makeup and facial care however are the first cosmetic products to be exported in the United States.

Due to the popularity of cosmetics, especially fragrances and perfumes, many designers who are not necessarily involved in the cosmetic industry came up with different perfumes carrying their names. Moreover, some [[actors]] and [[singers]] have their own perfume line (such as [[Celine Dion]]). The designer perfumes are, like any other designer products, the most expensive in the industry as the consumer pays not only for the product but also for the brand. Famous Italian fragrances are produced by [[Giorgio Armani]], [[Dolce and Gabbana]] and so on.

Recently, [[Procter &amp; Gamble]], which sells [[CoverGirl]] and [[Dolce &amp; Gabbana]] makeup, funded a study&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0025656 |title=Cosmetics as a Feature of the Extended Human Phenotype: Modulation of the Perception of Biologically Important Facial Signals |publisher=Plos One |date= |accessdate=2011-10-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; concluding that makeup makes women seem more competent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/13/fashion/makeup-makes-women-appear-more-competent-study.html?_r=1 | work=The New York Times | title=Makeup Makes Women Appear More Competent: Study | date=2011-10-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the source of funding, the quality of this [[Boston University]] study comes into question.

The [[European Commission]] and the U.S. [[Food and Drug Administration]] (FDA) are the two bodies making legislation in what concerns cosmetic industry and its various aspects within the [[European Union]], respectively in the United States. In the European Union, the circulation of cosmetic products and their safety are law subjects since 1976. One of the newest amendments of the directive concerning cosmetic industry comes as a result of the attempt to ban [[animal testing]]. Therefore, testing cosmetic products on animals is illegal in the European Union from September 2004 and testing separate ingredients of such products on animals is also prohibited by law starting with March 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ec.europa.eu/consumers/sectors/cosmetics/animal-testing/index_en.htm|title=Regulatory context|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The FDA joined with thirteen other Federal agencies in forming the Interagency Coordinating Committee on the Validation of Alternative Methods (ICCVAM) in 1997 which is an attempt to ban animal testing and find other methods to test the cosmetic products.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fda.gov/Cosmetics/ProductandIngredientSafety/ProductTesting/ucm072268.htm|title=Animal Testing|date=|accessdate= 2010-08-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The cosmetic industry worldwide seems to be continuously developing, now more than ever with the advent of the Internet companies. Many famous companies sell their cosmetic products online also in countries in which they do not have representatives.

==Cosmetic careers==
[[File:Professional Make-up Artist.jpg|left|thumb|A professional make-up artist servicing a client]]
An account executive is responsible for visiting all department and specialty store counter sales and doors. They explain new products and &quot;gifts with purchase&quot; (free items given out upon purchase of a certain cosmetics item that costs more than a set amount).

A beauty adviser provides product advice based on the client's skin care and makeup requirements. Beauty advisers can become certified through the Anti-Aging Beauty Institute. 

[[File:Alek Wek.jpg|right|thumb|Model [[Alek Wek]] receiving make-up from a professional.]]
A [[cosmetician]] is a professional who provides facial and body treatments for clients. The term [[cosmetologist]] is sometimes used interchangeably with this term, but most commonly refers to a certified professional. A freelance [[makeup artist]] provides clients with beauty advice and cosmetics assistance—usually paid by the cosmetic company by the hour.

Professionals in cosmetics [[marketing]] careers manage research focus groups, promote the desired brand image, and provide other marketing services (sales forecasting, allocation to different retailers, etc.).

Those involved in cosmetics [[product Many involved within the cosmetics industry often specialize in a certain area of cosmetics such as special effects makeup or makeup techniques specific to the film, media and fashion sectors.

==See also==
{{div col|cols=2}}
* [http://kimterstege.nl All about make up]
* [[Airbrush makeup]]
* [[Animal testing#Cosmetics testing|Testing cosmetics on animals]]
* [[Body art]]
* [[Body hygiene kit]]
* [[Cosmeceutical]]
* [[Electrotherapy (cosmetic)]]
* [[Cosmetic surgery]]
* [[Cosmetic, Toiletry, and Fragrance Association]]
* [[Cosmetology]]
* [[DEA list of chemicals]]
* [[Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act]]
* [[Henna]]
* [[List of cosmetic ingredients]]
* [[Make-up artist]]
* [[Moulage]]
* [[Permanent makeup]]
* [[Personal care]] makeup is just a part of elegence not care

* [[Pharmaceuticals and personal care products in the environment]]
* [[Society of Cosmetic Chemists]]
{{div col end}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}
[http://skin-care-products.info/14808/are-natural-skin-care-products-more-expensive-than-other-skin-care-products/ '''The cost of natural skin care] Is natural skin care more expensive'''

==Further reading==
{{Commons category}}
* {{cite book|last=Winter|first=Ruth|authorlink=|title=A Consumer's Dictionary of Cosmetic Ingredients: Complete Information About the Harmful and Desirable Ingredients in Cosmetics (Paperback)|origyear=2005|publisher=Three Rivers Press|location=[[United States|USA]]|language=[[English language|English]]|isbn=1400052335|year=2005}}
* {{cite book|last=Begoun|first=Paula|authorlink=|title=Don't Go to the Cosmetics Counter Without Me(Paperback)|origyear=2003|publisher=Beginning Press|location=[[United States|USA]]|language=[[English language|English]]|isbn=1877988308|year=2003}}
* {{cite book|last=Carrasco|first=Francisco|authorlink=|title=Diccionario de Ingredientes Cosmeticos(Paperback)|origyear=2009|publisher=www.imagenpersonal.net|location=[[Spain]]|language=[[Spanish language|Spanish]]|isbn=9788461349791|year=2009}}

&lt;!-- spacing --&gt;

{{Cosmetics}}

[[Category:Cosmetics| ]]
[[Category:Skin care]]
[[Category:Greek loanwords]]

[[ar:مستحضر تجميل]]
[[zh-min-nan:Hoà-chong-phín]]
[[be:Касметыка]]
[[be-x-old:Касмэтыка]]
[[bg:Козметика]]
[[ca:Cosmètica]]
[[cs:Kosmetika]]
[[da:Kosmetik]]
[[pdc:Schmuck]]
[[de:Kosmetik]]
[[es:Cosmético]]
[[eo:Kosmetiko]]
[[eu:Kosmetiko]]
[[fa:لوازم آرایشی]]
[[fr:Cosmétique]]
[[ga:Smideadh]]
[[gu:સૌંદર્ય પ્રસાધનો]]
[[ko:화장품]]
[[hi:सौन्दर्य प्रसाधन]]
[[hr:Kozmetika]]
[[io:Kosmetiko]]
[[id:Tata rias wajah]]
[[it:Cosmetico]]
[[he:קוסמטיקה]]
[[jv:Kosmètik]]
[[kn:ಸೌಂದರ್ಯವರ್ಧಕಗಳು]]
[[kk:Косметология]]
[[ku:Kozmetîk]]
[[la:Medicamina faciei]]
[[lt:Kosmetika]]
[[mk:Козметика]]
[[ml:അംഗരാഗങ്ങൾ]]
[[nl:Cosmetica]]
[[ja:化粧品]]
[[no:Kosmetikk]]
[[mhr:Косметике]]
[[pl:Kosmetyki]]
[[pt:Cosmético]]
[[ro:Cosmetică]]
[[ru:Косметика]]
[[si:රූපලාවණ්‍යය]]
[[simple:Cosmetics]]
[[sl:Kozmetika]]
[[sr:Козметика]]
[[sh:Kozmetika]]
[[fi:Kosmetiikka]]
[[sv:Smink]]
[[tl:Kosmetiko]]
[[ta:ஒப்பனைப் பொருட்கள்]]
[[th:เครื่องสำอาง]]
[[tr:Kozmetikler]]
[[uk:Косметика]]
[[ur:تزویق]]
[[zh:化妝品]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
