<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30808456" ns="0" title="Yellowstone (whiskey)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox beverage
| name         = Yellowstone Bourbon 
| image        = 
| caption      = 
| type         = [[Bourbon whiskey]]
| abv          = 40.00%
| proof        = 80
| manufacturer = [[Heaven Hill]]
| origin       = [[Kentucky]], United States
| introduced   = 
| related      = [[Luxco]] of [[St. Louis]]
}}

'''Yellowstone''' is a brand of [[Kentucky]] [[Straight whiskey|Straight]] [[Bourbon Whiskey]]. It is bottled at 40.0% [[alcohol by volume|abv]] (80 [[Alcoholic proof|proof]]).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.luxco.com/public/brands/brands.asp?brandid=48&amp;brandname=Yellowstone Yellowstone web site], accessed February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Yelowstone brand is owned by [[Luxco]] of [[St. Louis]], [[Missouri]] (formerly the [[David Sherman Company]]); which doesn't own a distillery. Yellowstone is distilled, aged, and bottled in [[Kentucky]] by [[Heaven Hill Distilleries]] for Luxco. It is the same company that produces and markets [[Ezra Brooks Kentucky Bourbon Whiskey]].

The brand is sold both as a blend and as a straight bourbon. It is sold in glass in 16 oz pint bottles, glass 750ml bottles, glass 1-liter bottles and plastic 1.75L bottles.

== History ==
Yellowstone Bourbon was started by J.B. Dant (son of J.W. Dant) who teamed up with D.H. Taylor and J.T. Williams to found the Yellowstone Distillery and bottle Yellowstone (named after the national park) bourbon sometime in the 1880's. Glenmore bought the distillery in 1944 and operated it for several decades. U.D.V. (now [[Diageo]]) bought Glenmore in the early 1990's and promptly shut it down and sold off the Ezra Brooks and Yellowstone brands to David Sherman who continued to produce both brands. &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.straightbourbon.com/forums/showthread.php?t=1001/ Early history of Yellowstone from Straight Bourbon] &lt;/ref&gt; having to. Later Sherman approached [[Heaven Hill]] about distilling the bourbon whiskey and ageing in their Kentucky warehouses. It was then shipped to St. Louis in Oak Barrels where it was bottled and distributed. In 2006, the David Sherman Company re-branded itself to Luxco as a tribute to one of its co-founders, Paul Lux, and as a reflection of the current ownership of the company. As Luxco has grown it has remained family-owned.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.luxco.com/public/company/history.html Early Luxco History]&lt;/ref&gt;. 

Luxco itself was born of humble beginnings back in 1958 when Paul A. Lux and David Sherman Sr. established the David Sherman Corporation as a private label bottler to serve the needs of distributors, wholesalers and retailers in the mid-west around St. Louis, Chicago and Milwaukee. Since that time, the company has quietly grown into a major producer, bottler, importer and marketer with an impressive portfolio of over 50 wine and spirit brands. Some of the whiskey brands that Luxco produces include: [[Ezra Brooks Kentucky Bourbon Whiskey]], Bourbon Supreme, [[Old Ezra 101]], Wallstreet Whiskey, [[Rebel Yell (whiskey)|Rebel Yell]], [[Rebel Reserve]], D. Nicholson 1843 and Davies County.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{whisky-stub}}
{{Distilled-beverage-stub}}

[[Category:Bourbon whiskey]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
