<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30824721" ns="0" title="Timeline of the name Palestine"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This article presents a list of notable historical references to the name '''Palestine''', and cognates such as '''Filastin''' and '''Palaestina''', through the various time periods of the region.

The term ''Peleset'' ([[Transliteration of Ancient Egyptian|transliterated]] from [[Egyptian hieroglyphs|hieroglyphs]] as ''P-r-s-t'') is found in numerous Egyptian documents referring to a neighboring people or land starting from c.1150 BCE during the [[Twentieth dynasty of Egypt]]. The first mention is thought to be in texts of the temple at [[Medinet Habu (temple)|Medinet Habu]] which record a people called the Peleset among the [[Sea Peoples]] who invaded [[Egypt]] in [[Ramesses III]]'s reign.&lt;ref name=Fahlbuschp185/&gt; The [[Assyria]]ns called the same region ''Palashtu'' or ''Pilistu'', beginning with [[Adad-nirari III]] in the Nimrud Slab in c.800 BCE through to emperor [[Sargon II]] in his Annals approximately a century later.&lt;ref name=Sharonp4&gt;Sharon, 1988, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Roomp285/&gt;&lt;ref name=ehrlich&gt;Carl S. Ehrlich &quot;Philistines&quot;  ''The Oxford Guide to People and Places of the Bible''. Ed. Bruce M. Metzger and Michael D. Coogan. Oxford University Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt; Neither the Egyptian or Assyrian sources provided clear regional boundaries for the term.

The first clear use of the term Palestine to refer to the region synonymous with that defined in modern times was in 5th century BC [[Ancient Greece]]. [[Herodotus]] wrote of a 'district of Syria, called ''Palaistinê''&quot; in ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]]'', the first historical work clearly defining the region, which included the [[Judean mountains]] and the [[Jordan Rift Valley]].&lt;ref&gt;Jacobson, David M., ''Palestine and Israel'', Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 313 (Feb., 1999), pp. 65–74&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Southern and Eastern Borders of Abar-Nahara Steven S. Tuell Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 284 (Nov., 1991), pp. 51–57&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herodotus' Description of the East Mediterranean Coast Anson F. Rainey Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 321 (Feb., 2001), pp. 57–63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;In his work, Herodotus referred to the practice of [[History of male circumcision|male circumcision]] associated with the Hebrew people: &quot;the [[Colchis|Colchians]], the [[Egyptians]], and the [[Ethiopians]], are the only nations who have practised circumcision from the earliest times. The [[Phoenicians]] and the Syrians of Palestine themselves confess that they learnt the custom of the Egyptians.... Now these are the only nations who use circumcision.&quot; [http://classics.mit.edu/Herodotus/history.mb.txt The History of Herodotus]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Beloe, W., Rev., ''Herodotus'', (tr. from Greek), with notes, Vol.II, London, 1821, p.269 &quot;It should be remembered that Syria is always regarded by Herodotus as synonymous with [[Assyria]]. What the Greeks called Palestine the Arabs call Falastin, which is the Philistines of Scripture.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.losttrails.com/herald/messages/33.shtml Elyahu Green, Geographic names of places in Israel in Herodotos] This is confirmed by [[George Rawlinson]] in the third book (Thalia) of ''The Histories'' where ''Palaestinian Syrians'' are part of the fifth tax district spanning the territory from [[Phoenicia]] to the borders of Egypt, but excludes the ''kingdom of Arabs'' who were exempt from tax for providing the Assyrian army with water on its march to Egypt. These people had a large city called Cadytis, identified as Jerusalem.&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately a century later, [[Aristotle]] used a similar definition in ''[[Meteorology (Aristotle)|Meteorology]]'', writing &quot;Again if, as is fabled, there is a lake in Palestine, such that if you bind a man or beast and throw it in it floats and does not sink, this would bear out what we have said. They say that this lake is so bitter and salt that no fish live in it and that if you soak clothes in it and shake them it cleans them,&quot; understood by scholars to be a reference to the [[Dead Sea]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://classics.mit.edu/Aristotle/meteorology.2.ii.html Meteorology By Aristotle]&lt;/ref&gt; Later writers such as [[Polemon of Athens|Polemon]] and [[Pausanias (geographer)|Pausanias]] also used the term to refer to the same region. This usage was followed by Roman writers such as [[Ovid]], [[Tibullus]], [[Pomponius Mela]], [[Pliny the Elder]], [[Dio Chrysostom]], [[Statius]], [[Plutarch]] as well as Roman Judean writers [[Philo of Alexandria]] and [[Josephus]]&lt;ref name=Robinson/&gt;. Other writers, such as [[Strabo]], a prominent Roman-era geographer (although he wrote in Greek), referred to the region as ''Coele-Syria'' around 10-20 CE.&lt;ref&gt;Studies in Hellenistic Judaism  ：Louis H. Feldman&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Hellenistic settlements in Syria, the Red Sea Basin, and North Africa ：Getzel M. Cohen&lt;/ref&gt; The term was first used to denote an official province in c.135 CE, when the [[Roman Empire|Roman authorities]], following the suppression of the [[Bar Kokhba Revolt]], combined [[Iudaea Province]] with [[Galilee]] and other surrounding cities such as [[Ashkelon]] to form &quot;[[Syria Palaestina]]&quot; ({{lang|la|Syria Palaestina}}), which some scholars state was in order to complete the dissociation with Judaea.&lt;ref name = &quot;Lehmann&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.usd.edu/~clehmann/erp/Palestine/history.htm#135-337
| title = Palestine: History: 135–337: Syria Palaestina and the Tetrarchy
| accessdate = 2008-07-06
| last = Lehmann
| first = Clayton Miles
| year = 1998
| month = Summer
| work = The On-line Encyclopedia of the Roman Provinces
| publisher = University of South Dakota
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sharonp4n&gt;Sharon, 1998, p. 4. According to Moshe Sharon: &quot;Eager to obliterate the name of the rebellious [[Iudaea Province|Judaea]]&quot;, the Roman authorities (General Hadrian) renamed it ''Palaestina'' or ''Syria Palaestina''.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] name ''Peleshet'' ({{lang|he|פלשת}} ''Pəlésheth'')- usually translated as ''Philistia'' in English, is used in the [[Bible]] more than 250 times. In the [[Torah]] / [[Pentateuch]] the term is used 10 times and its boundaries are undefined. The later [[Books of the Bible|Historical books]] (see [[Deuteronomistic history]]) include most of the biblical references, almost 200 of which are in the [[Book of Judges]] and the [[Books of Samuel]], where the term is used to denote the southern coastal region to the west of the ancient [[Kingdom of Judah]].&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, 1993, p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sharonp4/&gt;&lt;ref name=Roomp285&gt;Room, 1997, p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Robinson&gt;Robinson, Edward, ''Physical geography of the Holy Land'', Crocker &amp; Brewster, Boston, 1865, p.15. Robinson, writing in 1865 when travel by Europeans to the Ottoman Empire became common asserts that, &quot;Palestine, or Palestina, now the most common name for the Holy Land, occurs three times in the English version of the Old Testament; and is there put for the [[Hebrew]] name פלשת, elsewhere rendered Philistia. As thus used, it refers strictly and only to the country of the [[Philistines]], in the southwest corner of the land. So, too, in the Greek form, Παλαςτίνη), it is used by [[Josephus]]. But both Josephus and [[Philo]] apply the name to the whole land of the Hebrews ; and Greek and Roman writers employed it in the like extent.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Byzantine Empire|Byzantine period]], the entire region (Syria Palestine, [[Samaria]], and the [[Galilee]]) was named ''Palaestina'', subdivided into provinces Palaestina I and II.&lt;ref name=Kaegip41/&gt; The Byzantines also renamed an area of land including the [[Negev]], [[Sinai]], and the west coast of the Arabian Peninsula as ''Palaestina Salutaris'', sometimes called ''Palaestina III''.&lt;ref name=Kaegip41&gt;Kaegi, 1995, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Arabic language|Arabic]] word for Palestine is فلسطين (commonly transcribed in English as ''Filistin'', ''Filastin'', or ''Falastin'').&lt;ref name=Marshallp559&gt;Marshall Cavendish, 2007, p. 559.&lt;/ref&gt; Moshe Sharon writes that when the [[Arab]]s took over [[Greater Syria]] in the 7th century, [[Place names of Palestine|place names]] that were in use by the Byzantine administration before them, generally continued to be used. Hence, he traces the emergence of the Arabic form ''Filastin'' to this adoption, with Arabic inflection, of Roman and [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] ([[Semitic]]) names.&lt;ref name=Sharonp4/&gt; Jacob Lassner and Selwyn Ilan Troen offer a different view, writing that ''Jund Filastin'', the full name for the administrative province under the rule of the Arab [[caliphates]], was traced by Muslim geographers back to the Philistines of the Bible.&lt;ref name=Lassnerp54&gt;Lassner and Troen, 2007, pp. 54–55.&lt;/ref&gt; The use of the name &quot;Palestine&quot; in English became more common after the European renaissance.&lt;ref&gt;Gudrun Krämer (2008) ''A History of Palestine: From the Ottoman Conquest to the Founding of the State of Israel'' Translated by Gudrun Krämer and Graham Harman Princeton University Press, ISBN 0-691-11897-3 p 16&lt;/ref&gt; It was officially revived by the British after the fall of the [[Ottoman Empire]] and applied to the territory that was placed under the [[British Mandate for Palestine|Palestine Mandate]].

==Historical references==
===Ancient period===
* c.1150 BCE: [[Medinet Habu (temple)]]: records a people called the ''P-r-s-t'' (conventionally ''Peleset'') among the [[Sea Peoples]] who invaded [[Egypt]] in [[Ramesses III]]'s reign.&lt;ref name=Fahlbuschp185&gt;Fahlbusch et al., 2005, p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.1150 BCE: [[Papyrus Harris I]]: &quot;I extended all the boundaries of Egypt; I overthrew those who invaded them from their lands. I slew the [[Denyen]] in their isles, the [[Tjeker|Thekel]] and the Peleset (Pw-r-s-ty) were made ashes&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.specialtyinterests.net/harris.html Text of the Papyrus Harris]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.1000 BCE: [[Onomasticon of Amenope]] and [[Story of Wenamun]]
* c.900 BCE: Statue of Pedeset, inscription: &quot;envoy - Canaan - Peleset&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=B2eNV68WU3YC&amp;pg=PA221&amp;dq=steindorff+%22egyptian+commissioner+in+syria%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=ykt2TqP_ApO98gOUoIiKBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CFYQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=steindorff&amp;f=false The Philistines in transition: a history from ca. 1000-730 B.C.E., Carl S. Ehrlich]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.800 BCE: [[Adad-nirari III]] in the [[Nimrud Slab]]
* c.717 BCE: [[Dur-Sharrukin]], ''Annals of [[Sargon II]]'''': records the region as ''Palashtu'' or ''Pilistu''&lt;ref name=Sharonp4&gt;Sharon, 1988, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Roomp285&gt;Room, 1997, p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Roomp285/&gt;&lt;ref name=ehrlich&gt;Carl S. Ehrlich &quot;Philistines&quot;  ''The Oxford Guide to People and Places of the Bible''. Ed. Bruce M. Metzger and Michael D. Coogan. Oxford University Press, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Classical antiquity===
====Persian (Achaemenid) Empire period====
* c.450 BCE: [[Herodotus]], ''[[Histories (Herodotus)|The Histories]]'', First historical reference clearly denoting a wider region than biblical [[Philistia]]. Refers to a &quot;district of Syria, called ''Palaistinê''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Palestine and Israel, David M. Jacobson, Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 313 (Feb., 1999), pp. 65–74&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Southern and Eastern Borders of Abar-Nahara, Steven S. Tuell, Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 284 (Nov., 1991), pp. 51–57&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Herodotus' Description of the East Mediterranean Coast, Anson F. Rainey, Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research, No. 321 (Feb., 2001), pp. 57–63&lt;/ref&gt; One important reference refers to the practice of [[History of male circumcision|male circumcision]] associated with the Hebrew people: &quot;the [[Colchis|Colchians]], the [[Egyptians]], and the [[Ethiopians]], are the only nations who have practised circumcision from the earliest times. The [[Phoenicians]] and the Syrians of Palestine themselves confess that they learnt the custom of the Egyptians.... Now these are the only nations who use circumcision&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://classics.mit.edu/Herodotus/history.mb.txt The History of Herodotus]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.340 BCE: [[Aristotle]], ''[[Meteorology (Aristotle)|Meteorology]]'', &quot;Again if, as is fabled, there is a lake in Palestine, such that if you bind a man or beast and throw it in it floats and does not sink, this would bear out what we have said. They say that this lake is so bitter and salt that no fish live in it and that if you soak clothes in it and shake them it cleans them.&quot;. This is understood by scholars to be a reference to the [[Dead Sea]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://classics.mit.edu/Aristotle/meteorology.2.ii.html Meteorology By Aristotle]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Hellenic Kingdoms (Ptolemaic/Seleucid/Hasmonean) period====
* c.150 BCE: [[Polemon of Athens]], ''Greek Histories, quoted by [[Eusebius of Caesarea]] in [[Praeparatio Evangelica]]'': &quot;In the time of [[Apis (Greek mythology)|Apis]] son of [[Phoroneus]] a part of the Egyptian army was expelled from Egypt, who took up their abode not far from Arabia in the part of Syria called Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=z3ZywMar4P0C&amp;dq=in+the+reign+of+apis+the+son+of+phoroneus&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Studies in Josephus and the varieties of ancient Judaism: Louis H. Feldman]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.130 BC: [[Pausanias (geographer)]], ''Description of Greece'': &quot;In front of the sanctuary grow palm-trees, the fruit of which, though not wholly edible like the dates of Palestine, yet are riper than those of [[Ionia]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.theoi.com/Text/Pausanias9A.html Pausanias, Description of Greece, 9. 1 - 22]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Roman Jerusalem period====
* c.2 CE: [[Ovid]], ''[[Ars Amatoria]]'': &quot;the seventh-day feast that the Syrian of Palestine observes&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/ovid/ovid.artis1.shtml Latin quote: Quaque die redeunt, rebus minus apta gerendis, culta Palaestino septima festa Syro]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.10-19 [[Tibullus]], ''Tibullus and Sulpicia: The Poems'': &quot;Why tell how the white dove sacred to the Syrians flies unharmed through the crowded cities of Palestine?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poetryintranslation.com/PITBR/Latin/Tibullus.htm Tibullus and Sulpicia: The Poems, Translated by A. S. Kline]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.17: [[Ovid]], ''[[Fasti (poem)]]'': &quot;When Jupiter took up arms to defend the heavens, came to [[Euphrates]] with the little Cupid, and sat by the brink of the waters of Palestine.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.poetryintranslation.com/PITBR/Latin/OvidFastiBkTwo.htm Ovid: Fasti, Book Two]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.40: [[Philo of Alexandria]], &quot;Moreover Palestine and Syria too are not barren of exemplary wisdom and virtue, which countries no slight portion of that most populous nation of the Jews inhabits. There is a portion of those people called Essenes.&quot; Separately, Philo identified Palestine with the area of ancient Canaan.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/yonge/book33.html Philo: Every Good Man is Free]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.43: [[Pomponius Mela]], ''De situ orbis'': &quot;Syria late litora tenet, terrasque etiam latius introrsus, aliis aliisque nuncupata nominibus: nam et Coele dicitur et Mesopotamia et Damascene et Adiabene et Babylonia et Iudaea et Commagene et Sophene. Hic Palaestine est qua tangit Arabas, tum Phoenice; et ubi se Ciliciae committit Antiochia, olim ac diu potens, sed cum eam regno Semiramis tenuit longe potentissima. Operibus certe eius insignia multa sunt; duo maxime excellunt; constituta urbs mirae magnitudinis Babylon, ac siccis olim regionibus Euphrates et Tigris immissi.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/pomponius1.html POMPONIUS MELA, DE CHOROGRAPHIA LIBER PRIMUS]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.78: [[Pliny the Elder]], ''[[Natural History (Pliny)|Natural History]], Volume 1, Book V'': Chapter 13: &quot;Next to these countries Syria occupies the coast, once the greatest of lands, and distinguished by many names; for the part which joins up to Arabia was formerly called Palaestina, Judaea, Coele, and Phoenice. The country in the interior was called Damascena, and that further on and more to the south, Babylonia.&quot;; Chapter 14: &quot;After this, at the point where the [[Serbonian Bog]] becomes visible, [[Edom|Idumea]] and Palaestina begin. This lake, which some writers have made to be 150 miles in circumference, Herodotus has placed at the foot of [[Ras Kouroun|Mount Casius]]; it is now an inconsiderable fen. The towns are [[Rhinocorura]] and, in the interior, [[Rafah]], [[Gaza]], and, still more inland, [[Anthedon (town)|Anthedon]]: there is also Mount Argaris&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?pg=PA425&amp;dq=Pliny%20the%20Elder%20palestine&amp;ei=nPxVTYOqD8aChQeRssDSDA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=MZYVAAAAYAAJ&amp;output=text Pliny's Natural History]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c. 90: [[Dio Chrysostom]], quoted by [[Synesius]], refers to the [[Dead Sea]] as being in the interior of Palestine, in the very vicinity of &quot;[[Sodom and Gomorrah|Sodoma]]&quot;&lt;ref name=Jacobson&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Jacobson|first1= David|year= 1999|title= Palestine and Israel|journal= Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research|jstor= 1357617}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Feldman/&gt;
* c.97: [[Josephus]], ''[[Against Apion]]'': &quot;Nor, indeed, was Herodotus of Halicarnassus unaquainted with our nation, but mentions it after a way of his own... This, therefore, is what Herodotus says, that &quot;the Syrians that are in Palestine are circumcised&quot;. But there are no inhabitants of Palestine that are circumcised excepting the Jews; and, therefore, it must be his knowledge of them that enabled him to speak so much concerning them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[s:Against Apion/Book I]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.94: [[Josephus]], ''[[Antiquities of the Jews]]'': &quot;...these Antiquities contain what hath been delivered down to us from the original creation of man, until the twelfth year of the reign of Nero, as to what hath befallen us Jews, as well is Egypt as in Syria, and in Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[s:The Antiquities of the Jews/Book XX]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.100: [[Statius]], ''[[Silvae]]'', refers to &quot;liquores Palestini&quot;&lt;ref name=Jacobson/&gt;&lt;ref name=Feldman/&gt;
* c.100: [[Plutarch]], ''[[Parallel Lives]]'':&quot;Armenia, where [[Tigranes]] reigns, king of kings, and holds in his hands a power that has enabled him to keep the [[Parthians]] in narrow bounds, to remove Greek cities bodily into [[Median Empire|Media]], to conquer [[Syria]] and [[Palestine]], to put to death the kings of the royal line of [[Seleucus I Nicator|Seleucus]], and carry away their wives and daughters by violence.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://classics.mit.edu/Plutarch/lucullus.html Lucullus, By Plutarch]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, during the Roman Jerusalem period &quot;Palestine&quot; was not the only geographical term for the region. For example, [[Strabo]], in his description of Jerusalem and Judea, uses the term [[Coele-Syria]], and [[Pliny the Elder|Pliny]] (as above) uses both terms.&lt;ref&gt;Studies in Hellenistic Judaism - Page 558 Louis H. Feldman - 1996 &quot;Nevertheless, Pliny (Mturalis Historia 5.74, 77) and Strabo (16.2.16.754) do draw a distinction between the Decapolis and Coele-Syria. In Josephus (Antiquities 13.355-356, 392; 14.79, 16.275; and War 1.103-104, 155) Coele-Syria, ...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A History of the Jews and Judaism in the Second Temple Period Page 174 Lester L. Grabbe - 2008 &quot;The place of Judah in [[Coele-Syria]] was readily known in geographical writings. According to Strabo, Syria includes the following areas: We set down as parts of Syria, beginning at Cilicia and Mt. Amanus, both Commagene and the Seleucis ...&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;The Hellenistic settlements in Syria, the Red Sea Basin, and North Africa 2006 p37 Getzel M. Cohen p37 “Palestine” did not come into official use until the early second century ad, when the emperor Hadrian decided to rename the province of Judaea; for its new name he chose “Syria Palaestina.”49 The new name took hold. It is found thereafter in inscriptions, on coins, and in numerous literary texts.50 Thus Arrian (7.9.8, Indica 43.1) and Appian (Syr. 50), who lived in the second century ad, and Cassius Dio (eg, 38.38.4, 39.56.6), who lived in the third, referred to the region as “Palestine.” And in the rabbinic literature “Palestine” was used as the name of the Roman province. cf p103&lt;/ref&gt;

====Roman Aelia Capitolina period====
* 135 CE: After crushing [[Bar Kochba]]'s revolt in 132-135, the [[Roman Emperor]] [[Hadrian]] applied the name [[Syria Palestina]] to the entire region that had formerly included [[Iudaea Province]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Judaism/revolt1.html The Bar-Kokhba Revolt (132-135 C.E.) by Shira Schoenberg], The Jewish Virtual Library&lt;/ref&gt; which some scholars interpret to have been an attempt to suppress Jewish national feelings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=1TA-Fg4wBnUC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=intentionally+suppressed+jewish+national+Aelia+Capitolina+Palaestina&amp;sig=xxUlDy9oYikzsdYmFHP0E-lDFE8 ''The Bar Kokhba War Reconsidered''], By Peter Schäfer, ISBN 3-16-148076-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/palname.html The Name “Palestine”], The Jewish Virtual Library&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.150: [[Appian]], ''Roman History'': &quot;Intending to write the history of the Romans, I have deemed it necessary to begin with the boundaries of the nations under their sway.... Here turning our course and passing round, we take in Palestine-Syria, and beyond it a part of Arabia. The Phoenicians hold the country next to Palestine on the sea, and beyond the Phoenician territory are Coele-Syria, and the parts stretching from the sea as far inland as the river Euphrates, namely [[Palmyra]] and the sandy country round about, extending even to the Euphrates itself&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livius.org/ap-ark/appian/appian_preface_1.html Preface of the Roman History]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.150: [[Arrian]], ''[[Anabasis Alexandri]]'': &quot;[[Tyre, Lebanon|Tyre]] then was captured, in the [[Eponymous archon|archonship at Athens]] of Anicetus in the month I lecatombacun...Alexander now determined to make his expedition to Egypt. The rest of Syrian Palestine (as it is called) had already come over to him, but a certain [[eunuch]], [[Batis (commander)|Batis]], who was master of Gaza, did not join Alexander&quot;''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/arrianar01arriuoft/arrianar01arriuoft_djvu.txt Anabasis Alexandri]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.150: [[Ptolemy]], ''[[Geography (Ptolemy)]]'', including map
* c.225: [[Cassius Dio]], ''[[Historia Romana]], The Destruction of Jerusalem by Titus in 70CE'': &quot;Such was the course of these events; and following them Vespasian was declared emperor by the senate also, and Titus and Domitian were given the title of Caesars. The consular office was assumed by Vespasian and Titus while the former was in Egypt and the latter in Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://homepages.luc.edu/~avande1/jerusalem/sources/cassiusDio-65.htm Historia Romana, The Destruction of Jerusalem by Titus in 70CE]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 311: Bishop [[Eusebius of Caesarea]], ''History of the Martyrs in Palestine''. As the &quot;Father of Church History&quot;, Eusebius' use of the name Palestine influenced later generations of Christian writers&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ccel.org/ccel/pearse/morefathers/files/eusebius_martyrs.htm Eusebius' History of the Martyrs in Palestine, translated by William Cureton]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= The Land Called Holy: Palestine in Christian History and Thought|author= Professor Robert Louis Wilken|year= 2009|isbn= 0300060831}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Late Antiquity period===
====Late Roman Empire (Byzantine) period====
* c.380: [[Ammianus Marcellinus]], ''Book XIV, 8, 11'': &quot;The last province of the Syrias is Palestine, a district of great extent, abounding in well-cultivated and beautiful land, and having several magnificent cities, all of equal importance, and rivalling one another as it were, in parallel lines. For instance, [[Caesarea]], which Herod built in honour of the [[Augustus|Prince Octavianus]], and [[Eleutheropolis]], and [[Nablus|Neapolis]], and also [[Ashkelon|Ascalon]], and [[Gaza]], cities built in bygone ages.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/ammianus_14_book14.htm Ammianus Marcellinus, Book XIV, 8, 11]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.384: Saint [[Jerome]], ''Epistle 33'': &quot;He ([[Origen]]) stands condemned by his bishop, [[Pope Demetrius of Alexandria|Demetrius]], only the bishops of Palestine, Arabia, Phenicia, and Achaia dissenting&quot;&lt;ref name=Feldman/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/3001033.htm Letters of St. Jerome, Letter 33]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.390: Palaestina was organised into three administrative units: ''Palaestina Prima'', ''Secunda'', and ''Tertia'' (First, Second, and Third Palestine), part of the [[Diocese of the East]].&lt;ref name=NYTimes&gt;{{cite news|title=Weathered by Miracles: A History of Palestine From Bonaparte and Muhammad Ali to Ben-Gurion and the Mufti|author=Thomas A. Idniopulos|year=1998|accessdate=2007-08-11|url=http://www.nytimes.com/books/first/i/idinopulos-miracles.html | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Palaestina Prima'' consisted of Judea, [[Samaria]], the coast, and [[Perea (Holy Land)|Peraea]] with the governor residing in [[Caesarea Palaestina|Caesarea]]. ''Palaestina Secunda'' consisted of the Galilee, the lower [[Jezreel Valley]], the regions east of Galilee, and the western part of the former [[Decapolis]] with the seat of government at [[Scythopolis]]. ''Palaestina Tertia'' included the Negev, southern Jordan—once part of Arabia—and most of [[Sinai Peninsula|Sinai]] with [[Petra]] as the usual residence of the governor. Palestina Tertia was also known as Palaestina Salutaris.&lt;ref name=Salutaris&gt;{{cite web|title=Roman Arabia|publisher=Encyclopedia Britannica|accessdate=2007-08-11|url= http://www.britannica.com/eb/topic-439113/Palaestina-Salutaris}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* c. 400: [[Genesis Rabba]], Jewish ''[[midrash]]'', explains that the word &quot;land&quot; in Genesis 41:54 refers to three lands in the region - Phoenicia, Arabia and Palestine.&lt;ref name=Feldman&gt;{{cite journal |last1= Feldman|first1= Louis|year= 1990|title= Some Observations on the Name of Palestine|journal= Hebrew Union College, Cincinnati, OH|volume= 61|pages= 1–23|url= http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=pACJYw0bg3QC&amp;pg=PA553&amp;dq=%E2%80%9CSome+Observations+on+the+Name+of+Palestine%E2%80%9D+feldman&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Rh5WTabOJ8K3hAfXo6GoDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate= 12 Feb 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/stream/midrashrabbahgen027557mbp#page/n47/mode/2up Midrash Rabbah Genesis Volume I at Internet Archive]&lt;/ref&gt; (ויהי רעב בכל הארצות: בשלש ארצות בפנקיא ובערביא ובפלסטיני)
* c. 400: [[Lamentations Rabbah]], Jewish ''[[midrash]]'', mentions the dukes of Arabia, Phoenicia, Palestine and Alexandria as joining forces with Roman Emperor [[Vespasian]].&lt;ref name=Feldman/&gt; (שלש שנים ומחצה הקיף אספסיאנוס את ירושלם והיו עמו ארבעה דוכסין, דוכס דערביא, דוכס דאפריקא, דוכוס דאלכסנדריא, דוכוס דפלסטיני)
* c.560: [[Procopius]], ''The Wars of Justinian'': &quot;The boundaries of Palestine extend toward the east to the sea which is called the Red Sea.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/16764/16764-h/16764-h.htm History of the Wars, Books I and II (of 8), by Procopius]&lt;/ref&gt; Procopius also wrote that &quot;[[Khosrau I|Chosroes]], king of Persia, had a great desire to make himself master of Palestine, on account of its extraordinary fertility, its opulence, and the great number of its inhabitants&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.knowledgerush.com/paginated_txt/1dfre10/1dfre10_s1_p89_pages.html The History of The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire by Edward Gibbon. Book, page 89 / 1165]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle Ages===
====Rashidun, Umayyad and Abbasid Caliphates period====
* c.770: [[Thawr ibn Yazid]], ''[[hadith]]'', as quoted in Abu Bakr Muhammad ibn Ahmad al-Wasiti's ''Fada'il Bayt al-Muqaddas'' (c.1019): &quot;The most holy spot [al-quds] on earth is [[Syria]]; the most holy spot in Syria is Palestine; the most holy spot in Palestine is Jerusalem [Bayt al-maqdis]; the most holy spot in Jerusalem is the Mountain; the most holy spot in Jerusalem is the place of worship [al-masjid], and the most holy spot in the place of worship is the Dome.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.christusrex.org/www1/ofm/sbf/dialogue/17AN.pdf Jerusalem for the Three Monotheistic Religions. A Theological Synthesis, Alviero Niccacci]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=h9qj1GODKxQC&amp;pg=PA161&amp;dq=%22Abd+al-Malik+and+the+Dome+of+the+Rock.+An+Analysis+of+Some+Texts%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QQMHTuCiL82cOprMgMsN&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFcQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22van%20ess%22&amp;f=false The Ḥaram of Jerusalem, 324-1099: temple, Friday Mosque, area of spiritual power, by Andreas Kaplony, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.870: [[Ibn Khordadbeh]], ''[[Book of Roads and Kingdoms (ibn Khordadbeh)|Book of Roads and Kingdoms]]'': &quot;Filastin Province 500,000 dinars of taxes&quot; (c.864 AD)&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title= Palestine Under the Moslems from AD 650 to 1500, Translated from the Works of the Medieval Arab Geographers|author= Guy le Strange|location=Florence|year= 1890|publisher=[[Palestine Exploration Fund]]|url= http://www.archive.org/stream/palestineundermo00lestuoft/palestineundermo00lestuoft_djvu.txt}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.870: [[al-Baladhuri]], ''[[Futuh al-Buldan|Conquests of the Lands]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* c.880: [[Qudamah ibn Ja'far]], ''Kitab Al Kharaj (The Book of the Land Tax)'': Filastin Province, 195,000 dinars (c.820 AD)
* 891: [[Ya'qubi]], ''[[Kitab al-Buldan|Book of Lands]]'': &quot;Of the Jund Filastin, the ancient capital was [[Lod|Lydda]]. The Caliph [[Sulayman ibn Abd al-Malik|Sulayman]] subsequently founded the city of [[Ramla]], which he made the capital.... The population of Palestine consists of Arabs of the tribes of Lakhm, Judham, Amilah, Kindah, Kais and Kinanah&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 903: [[Ibn al-Faqih]], ''[[Kitab al-Buldan|Concise Book of Lands]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* c.913: [[Ibn Abd Rabbih]]&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 943: [[Al-Masudi]], ''The History of Time''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;

====Fatimid Caliphate period====
* 951-978: [[Estakhri]], ''Traditions of Countries'' and [[Ibn Hawqal]], ''The Face of the Earth'': &quot;The provinces of Syria are Jund Filstin, and Jund al Urdunn, Jund Dimaskh, Jund Hims, and Jund Kinnasrin.... Filastin is the westernmost of the provinces of Syria... its greatest length from [[Rafah]] to the boundary of [[Lajjun]]... its breadth from [[Jaffa]] to [[Jericho]].... Filastin is the most fertile of the Syrian provinces.... Its trees and its ploughed lands do not need artifical irrigation... In the province of Filastin, despite its small extent, there are about 29 mosques.... Its capital and largest town in [[Ramla]], but the Holy City (of Jerusalem) comes very near this last in size&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 985: [[Al-Muqaddasi]], ''Description of Syria, Including Palestine'': &quot;And further, know that within the province of Palestine may be found gathered together 36 products that are not found thus united in any other land.... From Palestine comes olives, dried figs, raisins, the carob-fruit, stuffs of mixed silk and cotton, soap and kercheifs&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1029: Rabbi Solomon ben Judah of Jerusalem, a letter in the [[Cairo Geniza]], refers to the province of Filastin&lt;ref&gt;Moseh Gill, &quot;The Political History of Jerusalem During the Early Muslim Period&quot;, in Joshua Prawer and Haggai Ben-Shammai (eds), The History of Jerusalem, the Early Muslim Period, 638-1099, New York University Press and Yad Izhak Ben-Zvi, 1996&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1047: [[Nasir Khusraw]], ''[[Safarnama]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1051: [[Ibn Butlan]]&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;

====Crusaders period====
* 1154: [[Muhammad al-Idrisi]], ''The Book of Pleasant Journeys into Faraway Lands''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1173: [[Ali ibn abi bakr al-Harawi|Ali of Herat]], ''Book of Indications to Make Known the Places of Visitations''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* c.1180: [[William of Tyre]], ''[[Historia Hierosolymitana]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=dqjWThbyZDEC&amp;dq=palestine&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Histoire de la guerre saincte, dite proprement la Franciade orientale, 1573]&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ayyubid and Mamluk periods====
* 1185: [[Ibn Jubayr]], ''The Travels of Ibn Jubayr''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1225: [[Yaqut al-Hamawi]], ''[[Mu'jam Al-Buldan|Dictionary of Geographies]]'' &quot;Filastin is the last of the provinces of Syria towards Egypt. Its capital is Jerusalem.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1300: [[Shams al-Din al-Ansari al-Dimashqi|Al-Dimashqi]]&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1321: [[Abu'l-Fida]], ''A Sketch of the Countries'': &quot;The Nahr Abi Futrus is the river that runs near [[Ramla]] in Filastin&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1322: [[Ishtori Haparchi]], ''Sefer Kaftor Vaferach'', mentions twice that Ramla is also known as Filastin
* 1338 [[Robert Mannyng]] ''The Chronicle''
* c.1350: ''Guidebook to Palestine'' (a manuscript primarily based on the 1285-1291 account of Christian pilgrim Philippus Brusserius Savonensis): &quot;It [Jerusalem] is built on a high mountain, with hills on every side, in that part of Syria which is called Judaea and Palestine, flowing with milk and honey, abounding in corn, wine, and oil, and all temporal goods&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://faculty.colostate-pueblo.edu/beatrice.spade/seminar97/anon/guidebook.htm Palestine Pilgrims Text Society, Guidebook to Palestine]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1351: Jamal ad Din Ahmad, ''Muthir al Ghiram (The Exciter of Desire) for Visitation of the Holy City and Syria'': &quot;Syria is divided into five districts, namely: i. Filastin, whose capital is [[Aelia Capitolina|Aelia (Jerusalem)]], eighteen miles from [[Ramla]], which is the Holy City, the metropolis of David and Solomon. Of its towns are [[Ashkelon]], [[Hebron]], [[Sebastia, Nablus|Sebastia]], and [[Nablus]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1355: [[Ibn Battuta]], ''[[Rihla]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt; Ibn Battuta wrote that Ramla was also known as Filastin&lt;ref&gt;The Travels of Ibn Battuta, ed. H.A.R. Gibb (Cambridge University Press, 1954), 1:71-82&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1377: [[Ibn Khaldun]], ''[[Muqaddimah]]'': &quot;Filastin Province taxes - 310,000 dinars plus 300,000 ratls of olive oil&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1430: Abu-l Fida Ishak, ''Muthir al Ghiram (The Exciter of Desire)''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1470: [[Al-Suyuti]]&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;
* 1496: [[Mujir al-Din al-'Ulaymi]], ''The Glorious History of Jerusalem and Hebron''&lt;ref name=&quot;gds&quot;/&gt;

===Early modern period===
====Early Ottoman period====
* c.1561: [[Anthony Jenkinson]], published by [[Richard Hakluyt]], ''The Principall Navigations, Voiages, and Discoveries of the English Nation''
* 1563: [[:de:Josse van Lom|Josse van Lom]], physician of [[Philip II of Spain]]: ''A treatise of continual fevers'': &quot;Therefore the [[Scottish people|Scots]], [[English people|English]], [[Livonians]], [[Danes]], [[Poles]], [[Dutch people|Dutch]] and [[Germans]], ought to take less blood away in winter than in summer; on the contrary, the [[Portuguese people|Portuguese]], [[Moors]], [[Egyptians]], [[Palestinians]], [[Arabians]], and [[Persian people|Persians]], more in the winter than in summer&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=RacPpEOXWREC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;dq=palestinians&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=95ZqTZPSGcyGhQeJ9ZifDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=palestinians&amp;f=false A treatise of continual fevers: in four parts by Jodocus Lommius, English translation of 1732]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1563: [[John Foxe]], ''[[Foxe's Book of Martyrs]]'': &quot;Romanus, a native of Palestine, was deacon of the church of [[Caesarea Palaestina|Casearea]] at the time of the commencement of Diocletian's persecution&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=HOlCPiKO7yYC&amp;dq=palestine&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Foxe's Book of Martyrs]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1591: [[:de:Johannes Löwenklau|Johannes Löwenklau]]: ''Historiae Musulmanae Turcorum'' [[Latin]]: &quot;Cuzzimu barec ea ciuitas est Palæstinæ, quam veteres Hierosolyma dixerunt, Hebræi Ierusalem. Nomen hodiernum significa locum benedictum vel inclytum&quot;, translates as &quot;[[Al-Quds|Quds]] [[Barış]] is the city of the [[Palestinians]], also known as Hierosolyma, in Hebrew, Jerusalem. The name means the holy one or the glorious one&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=kk0VAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA151&amp;dq=Pal%C3%A6stin%C3%A6&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XZFqTdfTBIKLhQf7-MyfDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Pal%C3%A6stin%C3%A6&amp;f=false Historiae Musulmanae Turcorum, de monumentis ipsorum exscriptae, libri XVIII]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.1600: [[Shakespeare]]: ''[[The Life and Death of King John]]'': Scene II.1 &quot;Richard, that robb'd the lion of his heart, and fought the holy wars in Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://shakespeare.mit.edu/john/full.html]&lt;/ref&gt; / ''[[Othello]]'' Scene IV.3: &quot;I know a lady in Venice would have walked barefoot to Palestine for a touch of his [Lodovico's] nether lip.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://shakespeare.mit.edu/othello/full.html shakespeare.mit.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1616: [[Pietro Della Valle]]: ''Viaggi di Pietro della Valle il Pellegrino''
* 1639: [[Thomas Fuller]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Fuller|first=Thomas|title=The Historie of the Holy Warre|year=1639|publisher=Buck|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=gRw_AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA248&amp;dq=palestine&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=wThDTbmoEdSChQe--smyAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CEwQ6AEwBzgU#v=onepage&amp;q=palestine&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1647: Sadiq Isfahani, ''The Geographical Works of Sadik Isfahani'': &quot;Filistin, a region of Syria, Damascus, and Egypt, comprising [[Ramla]], [[Ashkelon]], Beit al Mukuddes ([[Jerusalem]]), Kanaan, Bilka, Masisah, and other cities; and from this province is denominated the &quot;Biaban-i Filistin&quot; (or Desert of Palestine), which is also called the &quot;Tiah Beni-Israil&quot;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?printsec=frontcover&amp;id=AgjTokhQ-psC&amp;output=text&amp;pg=PA38 The Geographical Works of Sadik Isfahani, 1832 translation]&lt;/ref&gt;
* c.1649: [[Evliya Çelebi]], ''Travels in Palestine'': &quot;All chronicles call this country the Land of Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;trans. St. H. Stephan (Ariel Publishing, 1980), p63).&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1696: [[Adriaan Reland]], ''[[Palaestina ex monumentis veteribus illustrata]]''
* 1688: John Milner&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Milner|first=John|title=A collection of the church-history of Palestine: From birth of Christ to the Beginning of the Empire of Diocletian|year=1688|publisher=Dring|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=bjQBAAAAcAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=palestine&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=NDhDTaaWN4mHhQeSobmOAg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=8&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1743: [[Richard Pococke]]: ''Description of the East''
* 1746: ''Modern History Or the Present State of All Nations'': &quot;Jerusalem is still reckoned the capital city of Palestine&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Salmon|first=Thomas|title=Modern History Or the Present State of All Nations|year=1744|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=f7I-AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA534&amp;dq=palestine&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=QDlDTaeFMp2ShAfY9tzvAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwADgo#v=onepage&amp;q=palestine&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1751: ''The London Magazine''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The London Magazine, and Monthly Chronologer|year=1741|url=http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=oF9FAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA206&amp;dq=palestine&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=eDhDTYmIKIO1hAf_6tG7AQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=palestine&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Modern period===
====Late Ottoman period====
* 1809: [[Reginald Heber]], ''Palestine: a Poem''
* 1833: [[:de:Heinrich Friedrich Pfannkuche|Heinrich Friedrich Pfannkuche]]: &quot;In the writings of the Greeks and Romans, we need not look for indications of a very familiar acquaintance with the history and language of the Palestinian Jews, since they did not even vouchsafe their attention to the language and national writings of the more civilized nations of antiquity, such as the [[Carthaginians]], [[Phoenicians]], and [[Strabo]], from whom we have quoted above the passages bearing upon our subject, is perhaps the only one who imparts this general information of the [[Syria]]ns, (to whom the Palestinians also belonged,) that they and their neighbours spoke a cognate language, but he enters on no farther explanation as to the difference between their dialects&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qp8CAAAAQAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false THE LANGUAGE OF PALESTINE IN THE AGE OF CHRIST AND THE APOSTLES. By De Rossi and Heinrich Friedrich Pfannkuche, translated and printed in Philological Tracts, London 1833]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1837: [[Alexander Lindsay, 25th Earl of Crawford|Lord Lindsay]], ''Letters on Egypt, Edom and the Holy Land'': &quot;...we bade adieu to Jerusalem... It was our intention, after exploring Palestine (properly so called), to cross the Jordan, and visit Jerash&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.archive.org/details/lettersonegypte03crawgoog Letters on Egypt, Edom and the Holy Land]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1841: [[Charles Henry Churchill]] in correspondence with Sir [[Moses Montefiore]]: &quot;Were the resources which you all possess steadily directed towards the regeneration of Syria and Palestine, there cannot be a doubt but that, under the blessing of the Most High, [the European Powers] would amply repay the undertaking, and that you would end by obtaining the sovereignty of at least Palestine.&quot;
* 1843: [[John Kitto]]: ''Palestine: the Bible history of the Holy Land''&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3MwsAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=Pietro+Della+Valle+palestine&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1856: [[James Redhouse]], ''An English and Turkish dictionary'': Regarded as the original and authoritative Ottoman-English dictionary, translates ''Holy Land'' as ''dari-filastin (House of Palestine)''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= An English and Turkish dictionary|author= James Redhouse|year= 1856|url= http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=CydMAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA155&amp;dq=filastin&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=XuBVTa-bEc-EhQfR36C0DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEAQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=filastin&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1897: [[First Zionist Congress]]: the Basel program sets out the goals of the Zionist movement: &quot;Zionism aims at establishing for the Jewish people a publicly and legally assured home in Palestine&quot;
* 1911: [[Filastin (newspaper)]]
* 1913: [[Al-Karmil (newspaper)]]: &quot;We hoped that they [the [[Ottoman Party for Administrative Decentralization]]] would rid us of Zionist threats and dangers. We comprised a group of people who had hoped the best for their leaders. This team possessed tremendous power; not to ignore that Palestine, their country, was part of the Ottoman Empire.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.passia.org/publications/research_studies/books/arab_nationalism/arabresist.html Arab nationalism and the Palestinians, 1850-1939, ʻAbd al-ʻAzīz ʻAyyād]&lt;/ref&gt;

====British Mandate period====
* 1918: [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom]]: ''Minutes'': &quot;[[Edward Turnour, 6th Earl Winterton|Major Earl Winterton]] asked the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs what facilities have been given to the Palestinian and Syrian political leaders now in Egypt to visit Palestine?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1918/jun/25/arab-political-representatives-visit-to#S5CV0107P0_19180625_CWA_29 Hansard ARAB POLITICAL REPRESENTATIVES (VISIT TO PALESTINE). HC Deb 25 June 1918 vol 107 c903W]&lt;/ref&gt; An early use of the word Palestinian in British politics, which was used often in following years in the British government&lt;ref&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/search/palestinians?sort=date Hansard search &quot;Palestinian&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1919: [[Zionist Organization]], ''Statement on Palestine at the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Paris Peace Conference]]'': &quot;The boundaries of Palestine shall follow the general lines set out below: Starting on the North at a point on the Mediterranean Sea in the vicinity south of [[Sidon]] and following the watersheds of the foothills of the Lebanon as far as [[Jisr El-Karaon]] thence to [[El-Bire]], following the dividing line between the two basins of the [[Wadi El-Korn]] and the [[Wadi Et-Teim]], thence in a southerly direction following the dividing line between the Eastern and Western slopes of the [[Mount Hermon|Hermon]], to the vicinity west of [[Beit Jenn]], then eastward following the northern watersheds of the [[Nahr Mughaniye]] close to and west of the [[Hedjaz Railway]]. In the east a line close to and west of the Hedjaz Railway terminating in the [[Gulf of Akaba]]. In the south a frontier to be agreed upon with the Egyptian Government. In the west the Mediterranean Sea.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/History/zoparis.html Zionist Organization Statement on Palestine, Paris Peace Conference, February 3, 1919]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mideastweb.org/zionistborders.htm Paris Peace Conference Zionist Organisation - proposed map of Paletine]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1919: [[Syrian National Congress]]: &quot;We ask that there be no separation of the southern part of Syria, known as Palestine, nor of the littoral western zone, which includes [[Lebanon]], from the Syrian country.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  | last = Pipes
  | first = Daniel
  | authorlink = Daniel Pipes
  | title = Greater Syria: The History of an Ambition
  | publisher = [[Oxford University Press US]]
  | series =
  | year = 1992
  | page =26
  | isbn = 0195060229, 9780195060225}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1920: [[Franco-British boundary agreement (1920)|Franco-British boundary agreement]] - the framework agreement in which the borders of the [[Mandate of Palestine]] were established, being finally approved on 7 March 1923&lt;ref&gt;[http://untreaty.un.org/unts/60001_120000/20/29/00039449.pdf  Franco-British Convention on Certain Points Connected with the Mandates for Syria and the Lebanon, Palestine and Mesopotamia]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1921: [[Syrian-Palestinian Congress]]
* 1926: [[Permanent Mandates Commission]]: &quot;M. Palacios [Spanish representative], returning to the concrete questions of a general character of which the Arabs complained, recalled those concerning the national title, the national hymn and the flag.... As regards the first point, the Arabs claimed that it was not in conformity with Article 22 of the Mandate to print the initials and even the words &quot;Eretz Israel&quot; after the name &quot;Palestine&quot; while refusing the Arabs the title &quot;Surial Janonbiah&quot; (&quot;Southern Syria&quot;). The British Government had not accepted the use of this Arab title, but gave the place of honour to the Hebrew word used for 2,000 years and decided that the official name in Hebrew was &quot;Palestina&quot; followed by the initials signifying &quot;Aleph Jod&quot;, the regular Hebrew name. Was the question still under discussion and could the accredited representative give the Commission any further information? [[Stewart Symes|Colonel Symes]] explained that the country was described as &quot;Palestine&quot; by Europeans and as &quot;Falestin&quot; by the Arabs. The Hebrew name for the country was the designation &quot;Land of Israel&quot;, and the Government, to meet Jewish wishes, had agreed that the word &quot;Palestine&quot; in Hebrew characters should be followed in all official documents by the initials which stood for that designation. As a set-off to this, certain of the Arab politicians suggested that the country should be called &quot;Southern Syria&quot; in order to emphasise its close relation with another Arab State.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/9a798adbf322aff38525617b006d88d7/1504facc47efbe05052565f0006b70bb?OpenDocument Permanent Mandates Commission, 22nd meeting, minutes of the ninth session, Geneva, June 1926]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biblical references==
The Philistines and Philistia are mentioned more than 250 times in the [[Hebrew Bible]].&lt;ref name=&quot;OTS&quot;&gt;[http://www.oldtestamentstudies.net/patriarchs/philistines.asp?item=5&amp;variant=0 The Philistines]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BG&quot;&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/keyword/index.php?search=philis*&amp;searchtype=all&amp;version1=9&amp;spanbegin=1&amp;spanend=73 Bible Gateway - All references to words beginning Philis*]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Killebrewp202&gt;Killebrew, 2005, p. 202.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Hebrew language|Hebrew]] word ''Peleshet'' ({{lang|he|פלשת}} ''Pəléshseth'') - usually translated as ''Philistia'' in English, is used in the [[Bible]] to denote the southern coastal region that was inhabited by the [[Philistines]] (&quot;Plištim&quot; ({{lang|he|פְּלִשְׁתִּים}} ''Pəlištîm'')&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, 1993, p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt; The Philistines first appear in a listing of the [[Ham (son of Noah)|Hamitic]] branch of [[Noah]]'s descendants.&lt;ref name=Smithp1546&gt;Smith, 1863, p. 1546.&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''Philistia'' is generally accepted to be a cognate of the word ''Palestine''. However, the terms for biblical ''Philistia'' and geographical ''Palestine'' have been different since at least the second century BCE. As early as the [[LXX]], thought to have been completed in 132 BCE, the biblical term for Philistines in Greek (''Philistieim'') was different to the contemporary Greek name for the region (''Palaistine'')&lt;ref&gt; Jacobson, p65&lt;/ref&gt; 

The five books of the [[Pentateuch]] / [[Torah]] include a total of 10 references, including:&lt;ref name=&quot;OTS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BG&quot;/&gt;
* {{bibleref|Genesis|10:14|9}}: (first reference) &quot;And Pathrusim, and Casluhim, (out of whom came Philistim,) and Caphtorim.&quot;
* {{bibleref|Genesis|21:32-34|9}}: &quot;Thus they made a covenant at Beersheba: then Abimelech rose up, and Phichol the chief captain of his host, and they returned into the land of the Philistines. And Abraham planted a grove in Beersheba, and called there on the name of the LORD, the everlasting God. And Abraham sojourned in the Philistines' land many days.&quot;
* {{bibleref|Exodus|13:17|9}}: &quot;And it came to pass, when Pharaoh had let the people go, that God led them not through the way of the land of the Philistines, although that was near; for God said, Lest peradventure the people repent when they see war, and they return to Egypt&quot;
* {{bibleref|Exodus|23:31|9}}: &quot;And I will set thy bounds from the Red sea even unto the sea of the Philistines, and from the desert unto the river: for I will deliver the inhabitants of the land into your hand; and thou shalt drive them out before thee.&quot;

The [[Books of the Bible|Historical books]] (see [[Deuteronomistic history]]) include over 250 references, almost 200 of which are in the [[Book of Judges]] and the [[Books of Samuel]], including:&lt;ref name=&quot;OTS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BG&quot;/&gt;
* {{bibleref|Joshua|13:1-3|9}}: &quot;Now Joshua was old and stricken in years; and the LORD said unto him, Thou art old and stricken in years, and there remaineth yet very much land to be possessed. This is the land that yet remaineth: all the borders of the Philistines, and all Geshuri, from Sihor, which is before Egypt, even unto the borders of Ekron northward, which is counted to the Canaanite: five lords of the Philistines; the Gazathites, and the Ashdothites, the Eshkalonites, the Gittites, and the Ekronites; also the Avites&quot;
* {{bibleref|1Kings|4:21|9}}: &quot;And Solomon reigned over all kingdoms from the river unto the land of the Philistines, and unto the border of Egypt: they brought presents, and served Solomon all the days of his life.&quot;

[[Books of the Bible|Wisdom books]] include only 6 references, all in the [[Psalms]], including:&lt;ref name=&quot;OTS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BG&quot;/&gt;
* {{bibleref|Psalm|87:4|9}}: &quot;I will make mention of Rahab and Babylon to them that know me: behold Philistia, and Tyre, with Ethiopia; this man was born there.&quot;

Books of the [[Major prophets]] and [[Minor prophets]] include around 20 references, including:&lt;ref name=&quot;OTS&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BG&quot;/&gt;
* {{bibleref|Zephaniah|2:5|9}}: &quot;Woe unto the inhabitants of the sea coast, the nation of the Cherethites! the word of the LORD is against you; O Canaan, the land of the Philistines, I will even destroy thee, that there shall be no inhabitant.&quot;
* {{bibleref|Amos|9:7|9}}: &quot;Are ye not as children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith the LORD. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt? and the Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir?&quot;

==See also==
* [[Geography and cartography in medieval Islam]]
* [[Place names of Palestine]]
* [[Origin of the name Khuzestan]]
* [[History of the name Azerbaijan]]

==External references==
* {{cite journal |last1= Jacobson|first1= David|year= 1999|title= Palestine and Israel|journal= Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research|jstor= 1357617}}
* {{cite journal |last1= Feldman|first1= Louis|year= 1990|title= Some Observations on the Name of Palestine|journal= Hebrew Union College, Cincinnati, OH|volume= 61|pages= 1–23|url= http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=pACJYw0bg3QC&amp;pg=PA553&amp;dq=%E2%80%9CSome+Observations+on+the+Name+of+Palestine%E2%80%9D+feldman&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Rh5WTabOJ8K3hAfXo6GoDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate= 12 Feb 2011}}
* {{cite book|title= Greek and Latin Authors on Jews and Judaism, vol. 1, From Herodotus to Plutarch|author= Menaḥem Stern|publisher= Israel Academy of Sciences and Humanities|year= 1974|url= http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=wbMKAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=From+Herodotus+to+Plutarch&amp;dq=From+Herodotus+to+Plutarch&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=EhlWTYHfEsOChQfGgrycDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA}}
* {{cite book|title= Palestine Under the Moslems from AD 650 to 1500, Translated from the Works of the Medieval Arab Geographers|author= Guy le Strange|location=Florence|year= 1890|publisher=[[Palestine Exploration Fund]]|url= http://www.archive.org/stream/palestineundermo00lestuoft/palestineundermo00lestuoft_djvu.txt}}
*[http://www.churchhistory101.com/century1-palestine.php Early Church History 101 - The First Century]
*[http://cojs.org/cojswiki/When_Palestine_Meant_Israel,_David_Jacobson,_BAR_27:03,_May/Jun_2001. When Palestine Meant Israel, David Jacobson, BAR 27:03, May/Jun 2001]
*{{cite book|title= Remembering and Imagining Palestine: Identity and Nationalism from the Crusades to the Present|author= Haim Gerber|year= 2008|isbn= 0230537014}}
*Francis Schmidt (2001). [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=u_9HFXEIj5UC&amp;pg=PA28&amp;dq=%22palestine,+judaea+or+israel%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=0U3qTcPNOJDB8QPf7KWjAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22palestine%2C%20judaea%20or%20israel%22&amp;f=false How the temple thinks: identity and social cohesion in ancient Judaism, Chapter &quot;Palestine, Judaea or Israel&quot;]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Jewish nationalism and the region of Palestine}}
{{Palestinian nationalism}}
{{Historic region of Palestine topics}}

[[Category:History of Palestine]]
[[Category:Country name etymology]]
[[Category:Etymologies of geographic names]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
