<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3083721" ns="0" title="File Manager (Windows)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the program suite with a similar name|FileMan}}
:''The &quot;File Manager&quot; is also a development [[API]] for the [[Mac OS]]''
[[Image:Filemanager31.gif|thumb|A screenshot of File Manager on [[Windows NT 3.5]] displaying a folder and the contents of drive C:]]

'''File Manager''' is a [[file manager]] program bundled with releases of [[Microsoft Windows]] between 1990 and 1999.&lt;ref name=&quot;WinHistoryDesktop&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/WinHistoryDesktop.mspx | title=Windows Desktop Products History | author=Microsoft | date=2006-03-07 | work=Windows History | publisher=Microsoft | accessdate=2006-08-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It was a single-instance graphical interface, replacing the command-line interface of [[MS-DOS]], to manage [[Computer file|files]] (copy, move, open, delete, search, etc.). No program closely similar to File Manager was  included in [[Windows 95]] and [[Windows NT 4.0]] and later versions; instead the more general [[Windows Explorer]] was introduced, with file management via a 2-pane view different from File Manager's, and a single-pane view obtained by clicking a &quot;My Computer&quot; icon.

== Overview ==
The program's interface showed a list of [[directory (file systems)|directories]] on the left hand panel, and a list of the current directory's contents on the right hand panel. File Manager allowed a user to create, rename, move, [[Computer printer|print]], copy, search for, and delete files and directories, as well as to set [[file system permissions|permissions]] ([[File attribute|attributes]]) such as archive, read-only, hidden or system, and to associate file types with programs. Also available were tools to label and [[disk formatting|format]] disks, manage folders for file sharing and to connect and disconnect from a [[network drive]]. On [[Windows NT]] systems it was also possible to set [[Access control list|ACL]]s on files and folders on [[NTFS]] partitions through the shell32 security configuration dialog (also used by Explorer and other Windows file managers). On NTFS drives, individual files or entire folders could be compressed or expanded.

The Windows NT version of File Manager allows users to change directories, files, local, network and user permissions.

From [[Windows 95]] and [[Windows NT 4.0]] onward, File Manager was superseded by [[Windows Explorer]]. However, the &lt;code&gt;WINFILE.EXE&lt;/code&gt; program file was still included with [[Windows 95]], [[Windows 98]] and [[Windows Me]] (16-bit executable), and [[Windows NT 4.0]] (32-bit executable). The last 32-bit &lt;code&gt;WINFILE.EXE&lt;/code&gt; build (4.0.1381.318) was distributed as part of [[Windows NT 4.0#Service Packs|Windows NT 4.0 Service Pack 6a (SP6a)]]. The last 16-bit &lt;code&gt;WINFILE.EXE&lt;/code&gt; build (4.90.3000) was distributed as part of [[Windows Me]] operating system. All versions of File Manager are available at [http://www.mdgx.com/bin.htm#FM this page].

[[Ian Ellison-Taylor]] was the [[Shell (computing)|shell]] developer on the Windows 3.1 team responsible for File Manager and Print Manager.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://channel9.msdn.com/ShowPost.aspx?PostID=284474|title=Dr Sneath and Ian Ellison-Taylor: Windows History|author=Microsoft|date=2007-02-20|publisher=Microsoft|accessdate=2007-03-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Versions==

===16-bit===
The original version of File Manager was a 16-bit program that supported the 8.3 file names that were in use at the time.

It did not support the extended file names that became available in Windows 95 - including [[Long filename|long file names]] and file names containing spaces. Instead, it would display only the first six characters followed by a 'tilde' character &quot;~&quot; and a number, usually 1. More numbers (2, 3, and so on) were added after the 'tilde' if more than one file name with same first characters existed in the same directory.

The 16-bit version distributed with [[Windows 3.1x]] and [[Windows 3.1x#Windows for Workgroups|Windows for Workgroups 3.1x]] installations had a [[year 2000 problem|Y2K issue]] due to lexicographic correlation between date representation and the [[ASCII]] character set; colons and semicolons replaced what should have been '2000'. Microsoft issued corrected binaries for all Windows 3.1x environments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.microsoft.com/kb/q85557/|title=File Manager Shows Garbled Date for Year 2000 or Later|author=Microsoft|date=2006-08-22|work=Microsoft Help and Support|publisher=Microsoft|accessdate=2006-08-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Windows NT===
File Manager was completely rewritten as a 32-bit application for [[Windows NT]]. This new version correctly handled long file names as well as [[NTFS]] file systems. It was included with [[Windows NT 3.1]], [[Windows NT 3.5|3.5]], [[Windows NT 3.51|3.51]], and [[Windows NT 4.0|4.0]].  It is possible to run File Manager on [[Windows 2000]], [[Windows XP]] and [[Windows Server 2003]] by extracting a copy of the &lt;code&gt;WINFILE.EXE&lt;/code&gt; program file from a Windows NT 4.0 Installation or CD-ROM, or by downloading and extracting the file from [[Windows NT 4.0#Service Packs|Windows NT 4.0 Service Pack 6a (SP6a)]].

File Manager cannot run natively under [[Windows Vista]], [[Windows Server 2008]] or [[Windows 7]] because these operating systems do not include &lt;code&gt;COMMCTRL.DLL&lt;/code&gt; and other necessary resources ([[Dynamic-link library|Dynamic Link Libraries]]). However, it is possible to create a modified version that will run on Vista, Server 2008 and 7 using manual instructions available [http://people.ee.ethz.ch/~davidsch/vistafm/ here]. This functionality (plus related help and support files) is packaged into an [[Windows Installer|MSI]] installer at [http://www.brydon.net/winfile/ this page] and into an [[Internet Explorer Administration Kit|IEAK]] installer at [http://www.mdgx.com/xptoy.htm#FMNT this page].

==See also==
*[[DOS Shell]]

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
&lt;!--See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags--&gt;
&lt;references/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

==External links==
*[http://people.ee.ethz.ch/~davidsch/vistafm/ Windows File Manager Revived] (guide for Windows Vista, should work also with Server 2008 and 7)
*[http://www.brydon.net/winfile/ Reviving Windows File Manager] (WinFile.exe [[Windows Installer|MSI]] installer for Windows Vista, works also with 7 and should work with Server 2008)
*[http://www.mdgx.com/xptoy.htm#FMNT File Manager (FM) &amp; Add-ons] (WinFile.exe [[Internet Explorer Administration Kit|IEAK]] installer for all Windows NTx OSes)
*[http://www.mdgx.com/bin.htm#FM File Manager 16-bit and 32-bit Updates] (WinFile.exe [[Internet Explorer Administration Kit|IEAK]] installers for all Windows OSes and environments)

{{Windows Components}}

[[Category:Discontinued Microsoft software]]
[[Category:File managers]]
[[Category:Windows components]]
[[Category:Discontinued Windows components]]

[[it:File Manager]]
[[kk:Файлдар диспетчері]]
[[no:Filbehandling (Windows)]]
[[ru:Диспетчер файлов]]
[[uk:Диспетчер файлів]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
