<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30866089" ns="0" title="Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Referendum
|name = Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011
|title =
|yes = 14192577
|no = 4174187
|invalid = 171190
|total = 18537954
|turnoutpct = 41.9
|mapdivision = Governorate
|map = File:Egyptian constitutional referendum 2011.svg
|notes = Source: Referendum.eg &lt;ref name=&quot;results&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://referendum.eg/84-slideshow/158-2011-03-20-19-09-58.html |title= الأرقام الفعلية للتصويت |publisher = اللجنة القضائية العليا للإشراف علي استفتاء تعديل الدستور المصري |language=[[Arabic]] |accessdate = 2011-03-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Politics of Egypt}}
A '''constitutional referendum''' was held in [[Egypt]] on 19 March 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Zayan |first=Jailan |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gLzgMRN5vmANBUJBTJJqvayXqWEg?docId=CNG.0f69b85278e292f4cec1b79291e88739.671 |title=AFP: New Egypt PM addresses crowds in Tahrir Square |publisher=Google.com |date=2011-03-04 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; following the [[2011 Egyptian revolution]]. More than 14 million (77%) were in favour, while around 4 million (23%) opposed the changes; 41% of 45 million eligible voters turned out to vote.&lt;ref name=&quot;thestar1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|first=Maggie |last=Michael |url=http://www.thestar.com/news/world/article/956926--constitutional-amendments-approved-in-egypt-referendum |title=Constitutional amendments approved in Egypt referendum |publisher=The Star |date=2011-03-11 |accessdate=2011-03-21 |location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The approved constitutional reforms included a limitation on the presidency to at most [[term limit|two six-year terms]], [[Judiciary|judicial]] supervision of elections, a requirement for the president to appoint a deputy, a commission to draft a new constitution following the parliamentary election, and easier access to presidential elections by candidates—via 30,000 signatures from at least 15 provinces, 30 members of a chamber of the legislature, or nomination by a party holding at least one seat in the legislature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/331837 |title=Commission announces proposed changes to Egyptian Constitution &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=2011-02-26 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The reforms were recognised by both sides to increase democratic safeguards, but opponents argued that they did not go far enough and that an election held too soon could favour the well-organised [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and members of the former ruling [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]] of [[Hosni Mubarak]]. Supporters cited concerns that waiting too long could increase the chances of the [[Egyptian military|military]] regaining power or risk destabilisation before an election.&lt;ref name=&quot;thestar1&quot;/&gt;

A [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2011|parliamentary election]] is planned within the next six months, with groups already working to create new political parties, promote candidates and increase turnout among their supporters.

== Background ==
{{see|History of the Egyptian Constitution}}
The 1971 [[Constitution of Egypt|constitution]] was suspended by the [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces]] on 13 February 2011, two days after the resignation of [[Hosni Mubarak]]. It then organised a [[Egypt Constitutional Review Committee of 2011|committee of jurists]] to draft amendments to pave the way for new parliamentary and presidential elections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gyvIy92hyHZzDwY3N_T-NwAdrdeQ?docId=CNG.64b40623ef755670eb1e7e108c8d3448.801 |title=Egypt cyber activists say they met military rulers |publisher=[[Agence France-Presse]] |accessdate=2011-02-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/02/27/us-egypt-referendum-idUSTRE71Q11620110227 |title=Egypt to call March referendum this week: lawyer |publisher=Reuters |date= 2011-02-27|accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Had the referendum resulted in a &quot;no&quot; vote, the 1971 constitution would have been nullified and a new one was to be drawn up before elections, which would likely have extended the planned transition period until an election to 2012.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12763313 |title=BBC News - Q&amp;A: Egypt's constitutional referendum |publisher=bbc.co.uk |date=2011-02-11 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Older constitutional articles ==

# '''Article 75''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The President of the Republic should be an Egyptian born to Egyptian parents and enjoy civil and political rights. His age must not be less than 40 [[Gregorian calendar|Gregorian]] years&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapter five: The Government, Part One: The Head of the State&quot;/&gt;
# '''Article 76''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The People's Assembly shall nominate the President of the Republic. The nomination shall be referred to the people for a [[plebiscite]]. The nomination for the President of the Republic shall be made in the People’ Assembly upon the proposal of at least one third of its members. The candidate who obtains two thirds of the votes of the members of the People's Assembly shall be referred to the people for a plebiscite. If he does not obtain the said majority the nomination process shall be repeated two days after the first vote. The candidate obtaining an absolute majority of the votes of the Assembly members shall be referred to the citizens for a plebiscite. The candidate shall be considered President of the Republic when he obtains an absolute majority of votes cast in the plebiscite. If the candidate does not obtain this majority, the Assembly shall propose the nomination of another candidate and the same procedure shall follow concerning his candidature and election&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapter five: The Government, Part One: The Head of the State&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/Constitution/chp_five/part_one.aspx |title=Chapter five: The Government, Part One: The Head of the State |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Article 77''' of the Constitution of Egypt that states: &quot;The term of the presidency shall be six [[Gregorian Calendar|Gregorian years]] starting from the date of the announcement of result of the plebiscite. The President of the Republic may be re-elected for other successive terms&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapter five: The Government, Part One: The Head of the State&quot;/&gt;
# '''Article 88''' of the Constitution of Egypt that states: &quot;The Law shall determine the conditions which members of the Assembly must fulfil as well as the rules of election and referendum, while the ballot shall be conducted under the supervision of the members of a judiciary organ&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapter five: The Government, Part Two: The People's Assembly&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/Constitution/chp_five/part_two.aspx |title=Chapter five: The Government, Part Two: The People's Assembly |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Article 93''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The People’s Assembly shall be competent to decide upon the validity of the membership of its members. The Court of Cassation shall be competent to investigate the validity of contestations on membership presented to the Assembly after referring them to the Court by the Speaker of the Assembly. The contestation shall be referred to the Court of Cassation within fifteen days as from the date on which the Assembly has been informed thereof while the investigation shall be completed within ninety days from the date on which the contestation is referred to the Court of Cassation. The result of the investigation and the decision reached by the Court shall be submitted to the Assembly to decide upon the validity of the contestation within sixty days from the date of submission of the result of the investigation to the Assembly. Memberships shall not be deemed invalid expect by a decision taken by a majority of two-thirds of the Assembly members&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapter five: The Government, Part Two: The People's Assembly&quot;/&gt;
# '''Article 139''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The President of the Republic may appoint one or more Vice-Presidents define their jurisdiction and relieve them of their posts. The rules relating to the calling to account of the President of the Republic shall be applicable to the Vice-Presidents&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;egypt1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/constitution/chp_five/part_Three.aspx |title=Egypt’s Government Services Portal - Egypt Constitution - Chapter Five |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Article 148''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The President of the Republic shall proclaim a state of emergency in the manner prescribed by the law. Such proclamation must be submitted to the People’s Assembly within the subsequent fifteen days to take a decision upon it. In case the People’s Assembly, is dissolved the matter shall be submitted to the new Assembly at its first meeting. The state of emergency in all cases, shall be for a limited period, which may not be extended unless by approval of the Assembly&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;egypt1&quot;/&gt;
# '''Article 179''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The Socialist Public Prosecutor shall be responsible for taking the measures which secure the people’s rights, the safety of the society and its political regime, the preservation of the [[socialist]] achievements and commitment to socialist behaviour. The law shall prescribe his other competences. He shall be subject to the control of the People’s Assembly in accordance with what is prescribed by law&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/constitution/chp_five/part_six.aspx |title=Egypt’s Government Services Portal - Egypt Constitution - Chapter Five |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
# '''Article 189''' of the Constitution of Egypt states: &quot;The President of the Republic as well as the People’s Assembly may request the amendment of one or more of the articles of the Constitution. The articles to be amended and the reasons justifying such amendments shall be mentioned in the request for amendment. If the request emanates from the People’s Assembly, it should be signed by at least one third of the Assembly members . In all cases, the Assembly shall discuss the amendment in principle, and the decision in this respect shall be taken by the majority of its members. If the request is rejected, the amendment of the same particular articles may not be requested again before the expiration of one year from the date of such rejection. If the People’s Assembly approves an amendment, in principle, the articles requested to be amended shall be discussed two months after the date of the said approval. If the amendment is approved by two thirds of the members of the Assembly, it shall be referred to the people for a plebiscite. If it is approved by the people it shall be considered in force from the date of the announcement of the result of the plebiscite&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/constitution/chp_six/part_one.aspx |title=Egypt’s Government Services Portal - Egypt Constitution - Chapter Six: General and Transitional Provisions |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Proposed amendments ==
{{refimprove|section|date=March 2011}}
;Summary
[[File:Women standing in line to vote on the 2011 Egyptian constitutional referendum.jpg|thumb|Women standing in line to vote on the 2011 Egyptian constitutional referendum]]
[[File:Egypt referendum_line.jpg|thumb|The men's line during the referendum, in the up-scale neighborhood of [[Mokattam|Mokattam Hill]] in [[Cairo]]]]
The proposed amendments include the following:
* ''Article 75'': A candidate would be ineligible if he or she had [[dual nationality]], parents who were citizens of countries other than Egypt or married to a non-[[Egyptian people|Egyptian]].
* ''Article 76'': Easing the requirements for being a presidential candidate.
* ''Article 77'': Limiting the terms a president can serve to two consecutive terms, each four years only.
* ''Article 88'': The juridical system is responsible for monitoring the [[Elections in Egypt|election process]].
* ''Article 93'': would give the highest appeal court the power to rule on challenges to disputed parliamentary races, whereas before only the parliament could decide.
* ''Article 139'': The president must appoint a vice-president within 60 days of the start of the term
* ''Article 148'': would impose new restrictions on the president declaring a [[state of emergency]], including requiring the approval of a [[parliamentary majority]], and says it cannot exceed six months unless it is extended through a referendum.
* ''(Article 179)'': would be canceled. The article allows the president to use military courts for &quot;[[terrorism|terror]]&quot; cases even for civilians.
* ''(Article 189)'': Require the newly elected [[Egyptian Parliament|parliament]] to write a new constitution within 60 days.

;Article 75
The committee proposed a number of qualifications for a person seeking to nominate themselves in presidential elections, including:

* The nominee must be an Egyptian citizen
* Both of the nominee’s parents must be Egyptian citizens
* The nominee must not be under a suspension of political and civic rights
* Neither the nominee nor the nominee’s parents may have held foreign citizenship
* The nominee must not be married to a foreigner
* The nominee must be at least 40 years of age

;Article 76

The committee proposed 3 tracks for nomination which candidates may choose in presidential elections:

# Nominees must win the endorsement of 30 elected members of Parliament;
# Nominees must win the endorsement of 30,000 registered voters from 15 governorates with at least 1000 endorsements from each of those governorates;
# Parties with at least one elected seat in parliament may nominate one of their members in presidential elections.

Members of Parliament and voters may not endorse the nomination of more than 1 candidate for president.

;Article 77
The committee proposed that the term of the President be reduced to four years and that a limit of two terms be adopted.

The issue of limiting presidential powers was postponed until after the elections as part of the new constitution drafting process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12589425 |title=BBC News - Egypt's army passes draft constitutional amendments |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-02-26 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;Article 88
The committee proposed that elections and referendums, from voter registration to the announcement of results, be administered and supervised by an all-judge High Elections Commission, whose composition and mandate will be defined by law.

Members of the judiciary nominated by the supreme councils of the judicial agencies and appointed by the High Elections Commission will supervise ballot casting and counting.

;Article 93
The Committee proposed that competence to determine the validity of membership of parliamentarians be transferred from parliament to the Supreme Constitutional Court. Challenges to the validity of the membership of a parliamentarian must be filed with the Court within 30 days of the election of the parliamentarian in question and decided upon by the Court within 90 days. The ruling the Court would be final.

;Article 139
The committee proposed that the president be required to appoint one or more vice-presidents within 60 days of taking office, and that the president shall determine them and of the vice-president. If the vice-president is dismissed from office, the president must appoint a replacement.

The same qualifications that apply to the presidency would also apply to the vice-president. (See Article 75)

;Article 148
The Committee proposed that the consent of a majority of the members of the People’s Assembly be required to declare a state of emergency. In addition, the Committee proposed that the state of emergency could only be declared for a period of up to 6 months. Also, a renewal of the state of emergency would require a popular referendum.

The committee proposed that if the President declares a state of emergency then the People’s Assembly must review the decision within seven days of the declaration. If the People’s Assembly is not in session at the time, the President must immediately call it to session. If the People’s Assembly is dissolved the declaration must be reviewed by it in its first session.

;Article 179
The committee proposed that the Article be stricken from the constitution. No further information available.

;Article 189 and 189 repeated
The committee proposed that that Shura Council function without it appointment members until such time as a president is elected to fill the appointment of 1/3 of its seats

The committee proposed that the president or at least half the members of the People’s Assembly and the Shura Council may request the drafting of a new constitution.

The committee proposed that within six months of their election the elected members of the People’s Assembly and the Shura Council must appoint, by majority vote, a 100-member constituent assembly to draft a new constitution. The constituent assembly would have to complete the draft within six months of its creation, and within 15 days of the completion of the draft constitution the president must call for a referendum on it.

== Polls ==
A March 13 poll by the Egyptian government on its Information and Decision Support Center website said that 24,121 Egyptians (57 percent of the total number of voters) would vote against the amendments, while 15,173 Egyptians (37 percent) supported them. Five percent were undecided.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/348851 |title=Majority of Egyptians against constitutional amendments, says poll &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=2011-03-13 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Campaign ==
[[File:2011 Egyptian Constitutional Referendum process in English.svg|thumb|A diagram that explains the 2011 Egyptian Constitutional Referendum process based on a Yes or No vote on 19 March 2011]]
The [[Egyptian military]] called for a media silence over the referendum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/360922 Egypt military calls for media silence on referendum beginning Friday], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt; It also set up a committee to review the proposed amendmends.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/348045 Armed Forces form committee to analyze opposition to amendments], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Later saying it would help to secure a vote on the proposed amendments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/352530 Army to help secure vote on Constitution changes], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Though 16,000 members of the judiciary were scheduled to supervise the referendum,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/342399 16,000 from judiciary to supervise constitutional referendum], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt; 2000 judges threatened to boycott the supervisory process.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/361608 2000 judges threaten not to supervise referendum], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

Amidst other controversy, a court ruled against canceling the referendum following an [[appeal]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/359971 Court rules against canceling constitutional referendum], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Opponents ===
{{External media
| video1 = {{YouTube|8NuqtlyHLnY|An AD asking people to vote NO by many celebrities, public and political figures}}
| video2 = {{YouTube|mVR1Bclw1fg|Another AD asking people to vote NO by many celebrities, public and political figures}}
}}
An opposition coalition (including presidential candidates [[Amr Moussa]] and [[Mohamed ElBaradei]], the [[New Wafd Party]], the [[Coalition of the Youth of the Revolution]], the [[National Progressive Unionist Party]], the [[el-Ghad Party]] and the [[Egyptian Arab Socialist Party]]) criticised the proposed amendments as not enough and that the new constitution needs to be written immediately to regulate the process and the requirements for [[members of parliament]]. They also said that the President's power was not limited enough under the proposed changes.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

The [[Christianity in Egypt|Christian Church]] was also opposed to the amendments,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/354356 Source: Church rejects proposed constitutional amendments], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt; as was the reformist faction of the Muslim Brotherhood.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/362657 Muslim Brotherhood reformist wing rejects constitutional amendments], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Proponents ===
The [[Muslim Brotherhood]] and the [[Salafi]] movement (including preachers such as {{link-interwiki|en=Sheikh Mohammed Hassan|lang=ar|lang_title=محمد حسان}} and {{link-interwiki|en=Mohammed Abdel Maksoud|lang=ar|lang_title=محمد عبد المقصود}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Religious propaganda, vote-buying flourish in Egypt ahead of vote&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/362640 |title=Religious propaganda, vote-buying flourish in Egypt ahead of vote &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher= |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;), among other Islamist groups{{Which?|date=March 2011}}, think that the amendments are suitable for the time being and that the situation in Egypt is not suitable to write a new constitution at the moment. They have suggested that Article 2 of the constitution (which states that &quot;[[Islam]] is the Religion of the State. [[Arabic language|Arabic]] is its official language, and the principal source of legislation is [[Sharia|Islamic Jurisprudence]]&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.egypt.gov.eg/english/laws/constitution/chp_one/part_one.aspx |title=Egyptâ€™s Government Services Portal - Egypt Constitution - Chapter one: The State |publisher=Egypt.gov.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;) will be removed or altered if the proposed changes are not approved even though the constitutional amendment committee said that Article 2 will not be touched.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/324621 |title=Constitutional amendment committee: Article II will not be touched &amp;#124; Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt |publisher=Al-Masry Al-Youm |date=2011-02-20 |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sheikh [[Yusuf al-Qaradawi]] advised Egyptians to approve the referendum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=422881&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=36&amp;parent_id=16 |title=Gulf Times – Qatar’s top-selling English daily newspaper - Qatar |publisher=Gulf-times.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|NDP]] also have asked their base to vote Yes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/~/NewsContent/1/64/7971/Egypt/Politics-/Egyptian-Islamists,-along-with-NDP,-campaign-hard-.aspx |title=Egyptian Islamists, along with NDP, campaign hard for a &quot;Yes&quot; vote on Constitutional amendments - Politics - Egypt - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Muslim Brotherhood and the NDP are also perceived to be in favour of an approval because early elections could benefit them the most as they already have the biggest grassroots support while smaller and newly founded parties would have little time to prepare for elections in the planned schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

== Election ==
===Voting issues===
{{External media
| video2 = {{YouTube|JE_TyVctX2w|ElBaradei Attacked by Voters}}
}}
* Some sheikhs took the platforms on Friday and focused in their sermons to call onto worshipers to vote yes.&lt;ref name=&quot;The seriousness of mixing religion with politics&quot;/&gt;
* The Egyptian [[Coptic Church]] and other Christian denominations in Egypt have called their Christian faithful to vote No.
* [[Mohamed ElBaradei]] was attacked by men throwing rocks at him as he tried to vote in [[Mokattam]]. He left without voting and later voted elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aljazeera.net/NR/exeres/926F772C-9DC7-4181-B55A-2A48A50B39AD.htm |title=الأخبار - عربي - مجموعة تمنع البرادعي من التصويت |publisher=Aljazeera.net |date=2006-11-14 |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/365228 ElBaradei, supporters attacked at polling station], ''[[Al-Masry Al-Youm]]'', 19 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12793484 Large turnout for Egypt's constitutional referendum], ''[[BBC News]]'', 19 March 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Salem |first=Mona |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gem9Kx0MIS57hXR6bplIhQAG11LA?docId=CNG.4ff2e782ea3c513ce60adb517b709f8e.6e1 |title=AFP: Hundreds of Islamists stone Egypt's ElBaradei |publisher=Google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*A [[Salafi]]st hang a sign, which distinguish between those who are voting yes, and those voting no in front of a committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;The seriousness of mixing religion with politics&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=نيفين مسعد مارس 2011 09:54:56 ص بتوقيت القاهرة |url=http://www.shorouknews.com/Columns/Column.aspx?id=413940 |title=فى خطورة تديين السياسة - نيفين مسعد - مقالات وأعمدة - جريدة الشروق |publisher=Shorouknews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-03-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The two women wearing a [[niqāb]] distributed leaflets calling for a vote yes in front of a committee.&lt;ref name=&quot;The seriousness of mixing religion with politics&quot;/&gt;

=== Overall result ===
[[File:Referendum in_the_desert.jpg|275px|thumb|Another view of the men's line in Mokattam during the referendum. The queue was so long it extended well outside the built-up area and into the desert.]]
{{Referendum
| title          = Egyptian constitutional referendum, 2011&lt;ref name=results/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Yolande Knell |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12801125 |title=BBC News - Egypt referendum strongly backs constitution changes |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= 2011-03-20|accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| yes            = 14,192,577
| yespct         = 77.27
| no             = 4,174,187
| nopct          = 22.73
| valid          = 18,366,764
| validpct       = 99.08
| invalid        = 171,190
| invalidpct     = 0.92
| total          = 18,537,954
| turnoutpct     = 41.2
}}

=== Result by governorate ===
{| class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
|-
! Governorate&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://referendum.eg/84-slideshow/160-2011-03-20-20-19-29.html |title=إستفتاء.مصر - نتيجة الاستفتاء على مستوى المحافظات |publisher=Referendum.eg |date= |accessdate=2011-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; !! Total votes !! Valid votes !! Invalid votes !! &quot;Yes&quot; votes !! &quot;Yes&quot; % !! &quot;No&quot; votes !! &quot;No&quot; %
|-
| '''[[Cairo Governorate|Cairo]]''' || 2,306,561 || 2,283,363 || 23,198 || 1,381,738 || '''59.9%''' || 901,625 || 39.1%
|-
| '''[[Alexandria Governorate|Alexandria]]''' || 1,524,387 || 1,513,552 || 10,835 || 1,015,945 || '''66.6%''' || 497,607 || 32.6%
|-
| '''[[Sharqia Governorate|Sharqia]]''' || 1,226,799 || 1,217,353 || 9,446 || 1,054,749 || '''85.9%''' || 162,604 || 13.3%
|-
| '''[[Minya Governorate|Minya]]''' || 1,121,260 || 1,106,817 || 14,443 || 848,101 || '''69.1%''' || 258,716 || 21.1%
|-
| '''[[Dakahlia Governorate|Dakahlia]]''' || 1,104,724 || 1,096,905 || 7,819 || 874,384 || '''79.1'''% || 222,521 || 20.1%
|-
| '''[[Beheira Governorate|Beheira]]''' || 1,070,733 || 1,061,796 || 8,937 || 931,338 || '''87.0%''' || 130,458 || 12.2%
|-
| '''[[Qalyubia Governorate|Qalyubia]]''' || 960,883 || 952,647 || 8,236 || 771,667 || '''80.3%''' || 180,980 || 18.8%
|-
| '''[[Gharbia Governorate|Gharbia]]''' || 933,732 || 926,005 || 7,727 || 729,920 || '''73.5%''' || 196,085 || 21.0%
|-
| '''[[Giza Governorate|Giza]]''' || 907,696 || 895,908 || 11,788 || 610,779 || '''67.3%''' || 285,129 || 31.4%
|-
| '''[[Asyut Governorate|Asyut]]''' || 803,827 || 794,085 || 9,742 || 583,304 || '''72.6%''' || 210,781 || 26.2%
|-
| '''[[Monufia Governorate|Monufia]]''' || 759,415 || 753,598 || 5,817 || 652,952 || '''86.0%''' || 100,646 || 13.3%
|-
| '''[[Sohag Governorate|Sohag]]''' || 751,180 || 744,481 || 6,699 || 585,514 || '''77.9%''' || 158,967 || 21.2%
|-
| '''[[Helwan Governorate|Helwan]]''' || 601,720 || 596,886 || 4,834 || 429,821 || '''71.4%''' || 167,065 || 27.7%
|-
| '''[[6th of October Governorate|6th of October]]''' || 574,399 || 568,256 || 6,143 || 479,716 || '''83.5%''' || 88,540 || 15.4%
|-
| '''[[Beni Suef Governorate|Beni Suef]]''' || 568,437 || 562,955 || 5,482 || 492,441 || '''86.6%''' || 70,514 || 12.4%
|-
| '''[[Kafr el-Sheikh Governorate|Kafr el-Sheikh]]''' || 568,336 || 564,392 || 3,944 || 496,191 || '''87.3%''' || 68,201 || 12.0%
|-
| '''[[Faiyum Governorate|Faiyum]]''' || 544,128 || 538,536 || 5,592 || 486,011 || '''89.3%''' || 52,525 || 9.7%
|-
| '''[[Qena Governorate|Qena]]''' || 452,480 || 449,898 || 2,582 || 387,292 || '''85.6%''' || 62,606 || 13.8%
|-
| '''[[Damietta Governorate|Damietta]]''' || 332,342 || 330,083 || 2,259 || 273,218 || '''82.2%''' || 56,865 || 17.1%
|-
| '''[[Ismailia Governorate|Ismailia]]''' || 253,328 || 250,907 || 2,421 || 195,428 || '''77.1%''' || 55,479 || 21.9%
|-
| '''[[Aswan Governorate|Aswan]]''' || 247,885 || 245,479 || 2,406 || 203,449 || '''82.1%''' || 42,030 || 17.0%
|-
| '''[[Port Said Governorate|Port Said]]''' || 213,666 || 211,377 || 2,289 || 149,635 || '''70.0%''' || 61,742 || 29.0%
|-
| '''[[Luxor Governorate|Luxor]]''' || 203,683 || 201,467 || 2,216 || 164,241 || '''80.6%''' || 37,226 || 18.3%
|-
| '''[[Suez Governorate|Suez]]''' || 173,106 || 171,075 || 2,031 || 134,864 || '''77.9%''' || 36,211 || 20.9%
|-
| '''[[Red Sea Governorate|Red Sea]]''' || 104,233 || 102,437 || 1,796 || 64,924 || '''62.3%''' || 37,513 || 36.0%
|-
| '''[[Matruh Governorate|Matruh]]''' || 84,555 || 83,628 || 927 || 77,283 || '''91.4%''' || 6,345 || 7.5%
|-
| '''[[North Sinai Governorate|North Sinai]]''' || 63,974 || 63,318 || 656 || 54,604 || '''85.4%''' || 8,714 || 13.6%
|-
| '''[[New Valley Governorate|New Valley]]''' || 41,357 || 40,890 || 467 || 37,186 || '''89.9%''' || 3,704 || 9.0%
|-
| '''[[South Sinai Governorate|South Sinai]]''' || 39,128 || 38,670 || 458 || 25,882 || '''66.1%''' || 12,788 || 32.7%
|}

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== External links ==
{{Portal box|Egypt|Politics}}
{{wikinews|Egyptian voters approve constitutional changes}}
{{Commons category-inline|Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}
*[http://referendum.eg/ Referendum.eg] official website
*[http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/7998/Egypt/Politics-/FAQs-on-Egypts-constitutional-referendum.aspx FAQs on Egypt's constitutional referendum], ''[[Ahram Online]]'', 18 March 2011 with [http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/8023/Egypt/Politics-/Live-Update-Egypt-constitutional-referendum-.aspx live update]
{{Egyptian elections}}
{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Egyptian Constitutional Referendum, 2011}}
[[Category:2011 elections in Africa]]
[[Category:2011 in Egypt|Constitutional referendum]]
[[Category:2011 referendums]]
[[Category:Egyptian law]]
[[Category:2011 Egyptian revolution|Constitutional referendum]]
[[Category:Referendums in Egypt]]

[[ar:استفتاء على تعديل دستور مصر 2011]]
[[de:Verfassungsreferendum in Ägypten 2011]]
[[fr:Référendum constitutionnel égyptien de 2011]]
[[it:Referendum costituzionale egiziano del 2011]]
[[ru:Референдум в Египте (2011)]]
[[th:การลงประชามติรัฐธรรมนูญอียิปต์ พ.ศ. 2554]]
[[vi:Trưng cầu dân ý hiến pháp Ai Cập, 2011]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
