<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30860723" ns="0" title="Jimmy King (Emmerdale)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|creator=[[Steve Frost]]
|image=[[Image:Jimmy King.png|200px]]
|caption=Nick Miles as Jimmy King (2011)
|name=Jimmy King
|portrayer=[[Nick Miles]]
|born=1 March 1965
|death=
|years=2004—
|classification= [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|spinoffs= ''Emmerdale: The Dingles, For Richer for Poorer (2010)
|home=Mill Cottage
|family=[[King family|King]]
|occupation={{nowrap|[[Businessperson|Businessman]] (since 1989)&lt;br /&gt;[[Truck driver|Haulage driver]] (since 2010)&lt;br /&gt;[[Bartender|Barman]] (2010)&lt;br /&gt;[[Public house|Pub landlord]] (2010)}}
|father = [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]]
|mother = Mary King 
|brothers = [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew King]]&lt;br&gt;[[Max King (Emmerdale)|Max King]]&lt;br&gt;[[Carl King]]
|sisters = Georgina King
|halfsisters = [[Scarlett Nicholls]]
|daughters =[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2009)#Angelica King|Angelica King]]
|sons = [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2011)#Elliot Windsor|Elliot Windsor]]
|wife = [[Sadie King|Sadie Campbell]] (1990–2005)&lt;br&gt;[[Nicola King|Nicola De Souza]] (2010—)
|nieces= [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Anya King|Anya King]]
|nephews=[[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2004)#Thomas King|Thomas King]]
|first = 19 February 2004
|last =
}}
'''James Frederick &quot;Jimmy&quot; King''' is a [[fictional character]] in the British [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]''. He is played by [[Nick Miles]]. He made his first appearance on 19 February 2004 and has appeared on the show ever since.  

==Storylines==
===Backstory===
Born when his father was building up his empire, Jimmy didn’t have the same privileges as his brothers - and it often shows. He began working for his father at fifteen, after Tom bought his boss's failing factory. Charles Maguire was a thorn between Jimmy and Tom for some time, as an idealistic Jimmy disputed his father's tactics.
===2004–08===
For many years, Jimmy was an awkward, dippy man, stumbling through business and a disastrous marriage. The closest enemy he had, apart from himself, was his brother Matthew, who coveted and eventually won Jimmy's place in the business and [[Sadie King]]'s bed. As time passed, Jimmy and Matthew became closest in the family, and Jimmy found love with [[Kelly Windsor]]. Kelly, along with the arrival of their half-sister, Scarlett, made him a more caring individual.

With the death of Tom and Max, Scarlett's arrival, business woes and increasing tension between Matthew and Carl, Jimmy found himself trying to hold together a house of cards. Cards that were scattered by a cruel twist of fate that ended the family business and killed Matthew on the same day. In spite of the setbacks, Jimmy managed to rebuild his life and start a family of his own with [[Nicola De Souza]].

His and [[Sadie King|Sadie]]'s marriage seemed perfect. She was a stunning blonde determined to see him succeed as she had chosen him over Matthew because he was the oldest and therefore more likely to inherit the family firm. Sadly they disagreed on one issue - he was desperate to be a dad but Sadie had no intention of getting pregnant. When Jimmy found out about this, he was horrified. Worried about her marriage, Sadie changed her mind but her determination to get rid of Charity ended their marriage for good. 

Sick of being made a fool of by Sadie and his family, Jimmy fell into Charity's trap. Sadie had convinced Tom that Charity was cheating on him. She cleared her name by sleeping with Jimmy and videotaped him telling her about Sadie's lies. She blackmailed Jimmy for £200,000 not to play the tape to Tom but despite Jimmy paying her, played the tape at his birthday party. The results were catastrophic. Sadie dumped Jimmy and Tom disowned him so he joined forces with a rival businessman - but this didn’t last. Tom eventually forgave him and welcomed him back into the fold. 

Relations between Jimmy and Sadie descended into war, further inflamed by Jimmy hiding his assets so Sadie's settlement was reduced. Angry, she bought land that Tom needed so he allowed her back into King &amp; Sons. Jimmy was horrified and made it clear that the divorce was still going ahead, moving on to village vixen [[Kelly Windsor]]. They enjoyed a brief romance but Sadie ruined it by digging for dirt on Kelly, which she soon found, and told Jimmy so he ditched her. 

He went on to try and pull Woolpack barmaid [[Toni Daggert]], who hoped to become his PA, but Paddy Kirk ruined that so he concentrated on the business. Jimmy wanted to make Tom proud after [[Matthew King (Emmerdale)|Matthew]] walked away, leaving Jimmy in charge of King &amp; Sons. Matthew and Sadie, however, plotted to ruin Jimmy and their scheming cost him a deal with Don Clough. Furious, he threw himself into launching the Kings River development on time. Unfortunately Jimmy's tendency to cut corners and dodgy business practices made Carl fume. Jimmy had only been back for a few months before Tom became involved with [[Rosemary Sinclair]]. All three King brothers tried to tell Tom that Rosemary was a nasty piece of work but he wouldn't listen. Their wedding was planned for Christmas Day and Tom even signed Home Farm Estates over to Rosemary but the day ended in tragedy when Tom fell out of his bedroom window.

The King brothers were among the primary suspects in Tom's murder, and were suspicious of each other. The lack of certainty about who was responsible ensured Tom's killer was never found. Matthew and Jimmy were horrified when they learned Carl was the killer, and relations between them were strained.

After the funeral, Jimmy and his brothers were shocked to find out Tom had had an affair with their mother's nurse, Carrie Nicholls, which resulted in a daughter, Scarlett. Matthew wanted to buy her out of the family firm and Carl ignored them. Family man Jimmy embraced his new sister, becoming a surrogate father in Tom's place.

Jimmy and Kelly reconciled just before Christmas. Originally, Kelly told her family she planned to bleed Jimmy dry in revenge for Dawn's death but this didn't go as intended as she fell in love with him. After initially dumping her when he discovered her original plan, Jimmy realised Kelly really did love him and took her back. She supported him after Tom died, even giving him an alibi when she thought he might have killed Tom. Jimmy and Kelly got engaged.

A few months before the wedding, Kelly discovered that she was pregnant. Initially she seemed happy to have the baby, asking her agent if her career would be affected if she took time off. Her agent realised what she was implying, telling her if she took time out to have a baby, her career would be over. Deciding she and Jimmy could have children later, Kelly had an abortion.  Scarlett, who had accompanied Kelly to the clinic, noticed that she was reluctant and suggested she not take the pill if unsure, but Kelly went ahead. Scarlett told Carrie about Kelly's abortion about Carrie found a leaflet from the clinic in Scarlett's coat pocket. Carrie angrily confronted her, disgusted by her deceit. Kelly pleaded with her not to tell Jimmy and Carrie agreed, providing Kelly stayed away from Scarlett.

On 9 October 2007 - Jimmy and Kelly's wedding day - two revelations came out, leading Jimmy to jilt Kelly. In the church, Jimmy saw Eli Dingle looking at Kelly as she walked up the aisle. Carl urged Jimmy to ignore him but he went for him. Eli admitted kissing Kelly but insisted it hadn't gone any further because she was so upset about her abortion. Despite Kelly's obvious regret, Jimmy couldn't forgive her. Donna and Paul did their best to reunite them but nothing worked. Eventually Kelly went to see Jimmy and heard him tell Carrie that he would never forgive her. Heartbroken, she left but left Jimmy a letter, telling him she would be staying at a local hotel if he wanted to discuss anything but Carrie destroyed it and Kelly left the area.
[[Image:The King's in Court.png|thumb|right|The Kings in Court]]
After [[Carrie Nicholls]] pursued him while engaged to Kelly, Jimmy gave in and they had a brief affair. However, things went sour when Carrie told Jimmy she loved him and he was unable to say the same, leaving her feeling humiliated. She realised that Jimmy had slept with her on the rebound and soon emigrated to [[Canada]] with an old flame. Scarlett chose to stay with her siblings and boyfriend.

Jimmy was devastated at losing his brother, his home and the business their father had built up. Carl was too embittered and stunned to help. Jimmy spent his time angry and drunk. He was even drunk during Matthew's funeral. When he learned that Tom's grave had been defaced, he verbally attacked everyone in the church before Scarlett dragged him out. That night, Jimmy saw [[Shadrach Dingle]] hadn't filled in Matthew's grave so, weeping, Jimmy tried to do it himself. The next morning, Carl found him passed out next to the grave.

The day after Matthew's funeral, Katie told Jimmy (thinking he already knew) that Rodney and [[Jamie Hope]] had arranged a shoot on Home Farm. Jimmy and a guest named Richard, realised Rodney was sleeping with his wife. They went after Rodney and found him at the B&amp;B. Richard had a gun, and as Richard and Jamie struggled, Richard accidentally shot Jimmy. Fortunately, only his pride was seriously injured but this snapped him out of his wallowing. He and Carl began working together to restart the business, and got a large settlement from Richard in exchange for not going to the police.

===2009—===
In February 2009, Nicola and Jimmy drowned their sorrows in the Woolpack and they ended up in the back of one of the Emmerdale Haulage vans. They kissed and events progressed further. The next morning, they woke up naked and on their way to Hull. Nicola was horrified; Jimmy was amused. 

Nicola felt she was too good for Jimmy and rebuffed his attempts at a relationship. A few weeks later, she asked him to go with her to Home Farm, as she thought the new owners, the Wyldes, wanted a sexual relationship with her. Jimmy was uneasy about going back to Home Farm and got drunk. When the Wyldes realised what Nicola had thought, they laughed at her and she spent another night with Jimmy. 

Nicola dumped Jimmy again, but when her father told her Jimmy could have some money hidden away, and she learned Jimmy was going to Switzerland, Nicola was suddenly interested. Carl told Jimmy that Nicola only cared about his money, but Jimmy refused to believe him until Nicola proved Carl right. Jimmy humiliated her by wining and dining her, then when she arrived at the Woolpack with her luggage, she found a haulage van waiting for them. Jimmy told everyone she was a golddigger and left her at the roadside.

[[Sandy Thomas]] and [[Douglas Potts]], who were living at the vicarage with Nicola, grew so tired of her presence that they wrote love letters in Jimmy's name, asking her to move in with him. Nicola genuinely did care for Jimmy, and jumped at the chance of living with him. Jimmy was shocked to hear about letters he'd never written, but his happiness at being with Nicola made him stay quiet. Unfortunately Sandy wrote a similar letter to Betty and she read it out in the Woolpack and Nicola overheard. Jimmy confessed that he hadn't written the letter as he wasn't very good at that kind of thing and Nicola insisted he write her a love letter anyway. He tried but was proved right and after another argument caused by Jimmy telling Nicola she was curvaceous, which she interpreted as fat, he dumped Nicola. She had intended to stay at Mill Cottage but Lexi insisted she move out and got Laurel to let Nicola move back into the vicarage.

In May 2009, Nicola discovered she was pregnant but decided not to tell Jimmy. Rodney told him instead and Jimmy wooed her into a reconciliation, planning to wait for her to tell him about the baby. When Nicola found out about this, she was furious and dumped him again, deciding to give the baby up for adoption. Laurel made her realise she couldn't do it. Jimmy and Nicola bonded when they went for a scan and they decided to give things another go. 

Nicola moved back into Mill Cottage with Jimmy, Carl, Lexi and Scarlett and supported Lexi after her ectopic pregnancy and shock discovery that she was unlikely to conceive again without IVF. She and Carl agreed to go for treatment and Scarlett planned to loan Lexi the money so they could go private. Carl, however, told Jimmy (as Scarlett's trustee), not to give Scarlett the money. Horrified, Nicola told Carl to come clean to Lexi or she would. He told Lexi and Lexi threw him out, leaving Nicola to comfort her. Unfortunately this led to a fight and Nicola fell down the stairs. Lexi and Carl called an ambulance and Nicola and the baby got the all-clear but Nicola blamed Carl for her and Lexi's fight and told him so. She warned him that he had to be honest with Lexi. 

On 6 August, Nicola gave birth prematurely to baby Angelica. She spent a few days in the special care baby unit but was fine. On 13th, Nicola went for a shower and Lexi took Angelica up on to the hospital roof to show her the world. Although Jimmy, Nicola and Scarlett were terrified she'd harm Angelica but Lexi convinced Nicola to trust her and only then did Carl confess that he didn't want children with her and never had. She returned Angelica to Nicola and after a verbal and physical fight with Carl, she left him and Emmerdale for good. In July 2010 Nicola and Jimmy bought the Woolpack from Diane Sugden. In February 2011 Jimmy was attacked by his former partner Kelly Windsor, he has recently been suffering from amnesia.
==Development==
===Who Killed Tom King?===
In October 2006, ITV announced plans for a fully interactive storyline, surrounding the death of [[Tom King]], who was killed on Christmas Day 2006. The ensuing weeks were be full of twists and turns as some of the show’s most popular characters were placed at the centre of the enquiry including Jimmy, facing fierce interrogation in the hunt for the killer - the police are determined to leave no stone unturned. It was later revealed it was Carl King who killed Tom.

===Amnesia storyline===
In January 2011, it was announced that Jimmy King is to lose his memory after being brutally attacked. Jimmy played by [[Nick Miles]] will stun doting wife [[Nicola King|Nicole De Souza]] ([[Nicola Wheeler]]) when he wakes up in hospital unable to recognise both her and their young daughter Angelica. 

Nicola Wheeler explained: &quot;At the hospital, Nicola rushes in and gives Jimmy a hug - but he doesn't recognise her at all. &quot;She thinks he must remember their daughter, Angelica, because she's part of him. But when Nicola shows Jimmy a picture of her, all he can say is that he thinks she's a pretty little girl. With everyone unaware as to how the attack happened, doctors tell Nicola that Jimmy has totally lost his memory of life up to and including the accident, leaving the young mum horrified at the prospect of life with a man who has no idea who she is. &quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://unrealityshout.com/blogs/emmerdales-jimmy-king-gets-amnesia-after-attack&lt;/ref&gt;

Being asked about the storyline Miles said: &quot;A long time ago! Our late producer [[Gavin Blyth]] spoke to me about this in September (2010) last year. He was very cautious about it but very excited at the same time. So it's been quite a long time that I've known it was coming up. I think they referred to it for ages as the 'Jimmy Who?' story!&quot; also asked about his reaction to the storyline he commented: &quot;I was a bit like Gav, really - I was excited but also a little bit trepidatious. It's one of those topics that it's rare to do a story about. My main concern was that I did a decent amount of research and knew what I was doing.&quot;

However, the storyline has received mostly negative responses from viewers. Many claiming the storyline is 'cringe-worthy', 'hard to watch' and 'unbelievable' due to many fans enjoying the Jimmy-Nicola match.
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/interviews/a305566/nick-miles-jimmy-king-emmerdale.html&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;http://www.holysoap.channel5.com/emmerdale/news/who-will-win-jimmys-heart-13156.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[King family (Emmerdale)|King family]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/page.asp?partid=3688 Jimmy King] at [[itv.com]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{EDKings}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:King, Jimmy}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional businesspeople]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2004]]
[[Category:Fictional bartenders]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
