<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30875081" ns="0" title="Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox university
|logo=[[File:Bloomsburg University logo.png]]
|name           = Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania
|established    = 1839
|type           = [[Public university|Public]]
|president= [[David L. Soltz, Ph.D.]]|
|city           = [[Bloomsburg, Pennsylvania|Bloomsburg]]
|state          = [[Pennsylvania]]
|country        = [[United States|USA]]
|undergrad      = 8,877
|postgrad       = 955
|staff= 520 (total full-time and part-time)
|campus         = [[Rural area|Rural]]
|mascot         = [[Huskies]]
|affiliations    = [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|D-II]]; [[Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference|PSAC]]&lt;br&gt;[[Keystone Library Network]]
|website= [http://www.bloomu.edu http://www.bloomu.edu]
|image_name     =Bloomsburg University seal.png
| image_size        = 150px
|}}

'''Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania''', commonly referred to as '''Bloomsburg''', '''BU''' or '''Bloom''', is a public [[university]] in [[Bloomsburg, Pennsylvania|Bloomsburg]], [[Pennsylvania]],&lt;ref name =&quot;PAmanual&quot;&gt;[[The Pennsylvania Manual]] [http://www.dgs.state.pa.us/pamanual/cwp/view.asp?a=437&amp;Q=129762&amp;pm=1&amp;pamanualNav= 117]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.newpa.com/download.aspx?id=82 ''Pennsylvania Local Government Fact Sheet'', 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; [[United States]]. It is one of the 14 state universities of the [[Pennsylvania State System of Higher Education]] (PASSHE).

Bloomsburg University is accredited by the [[Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]] (MSACS) and by many other relevant commissions and authorities.

==Programs==
It is noted for its education programs, including its graduate degree program in Instructional Technology, its Elementary &amp; Secondary Education programs, and the Audiology &amp; Speech Pathology program. The Bloomsburg College of Business is an AACSB accredited university, the highest level of certification for business colleges. As of 2011,it offers 54 [[undergraduate]] programs and 20 [[graduate school|graduate]] programs and a doctorate in audiology program.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bloomu.edu/current/catalog/&lt;/ref&gt;
The university  has two ROTC programs.  They are [[Air Force Reserve Officer Training Corps]] (through a cross-town agreement with Detachment 752 at Wilkes University) and the [[Army ROTC]]. It also offers many work-study programs, including food preparation and office assistance, in order to assist students financially.

During [[World War II]], Bloomsburg was one of 131 colleges nationally that took part in the [[V-12 Navy College Training Program]] which offered students a path to a Navy commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;bloomsburgv-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wesleyan.edu/libr/schome/FAs/na1000-125.html |title=Armed Forces Navy V-5/V-12 Program |publisher=[[Bloomsburg, Pennsylvania]]: Bloomsburg University |last= |first= |accessdate=September 25, 2011 |date=December 14, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Faculty==
The University  currently [[employment|employs]] approximately 520 professors.  The student-to-[[Faculty (university)|faculty]] ratio is roughly 22 to 1.

==Students==
There are 10,091 [[student]]s enrolled at the university (8877 undergraduates, 259 non-degree and 955 graduates), an increase of more than 100% increase over the past 20 years. A majority of the students live off-campus within the town limits, with a similar number of students who commute. About 88 % of the students are [[whites|Caucasian]] and 12% are of other heritage. The ratio of women to men is 60:40.

Academically, students are slightly above average, with [[median]] [[SAT]] scores of 1044. Most incoming freshmen are within the upper 29% of their graduating [[high school]] [[class (education)|class]].

The annual average [[tuition]] for a student at Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania in 2011 was about $7,498 for a student living in PA. Approximately 79% of the students receive at least some form of [[financial aid (educational expenses)|financial aid]].

==Athletics==

Women (9)
*Basketball
*Cross Country
*Field Hockey
*Soccer
*Softball
*Swimming
*Lacrosse
*Tennis
*Track &amp; Field

Men (9)
*Baseball
*Basketball
*Cross Country
*Football
*Soccer
*Swimming
*Tennis
*Track &amp; Field
*Wrestling

===Facilities===
'''Nelson Field House''', located on Bloomsburg University’s upper campus, serves as home for the university’s indoor athletic events.  The facility, constructed in 1971, is currently undergoing a $13.4 million dollar facelift. Among the renovations to the field house will be a new bleacher system for the main gym area, a new scoreboard, a new wrestling room on the lower level of the facility, a new and expanded press box, dedicated locker rooms for each sport, including an expanded football locker room, improved office space and additional storage space. In addition the '''Nelson Field House Pool''' features six competition-length lanes, automatic Colorado Timing System, and bleacher seating for nearly 800 spectators in the gallery. The pool serves as the site of Bloomsburg varsity swimming and club [[water polo]] contests as well as [[PIAA]] District IV championship meets.The project also provides for enhancements to both the upper and lower entrances that will showcase the awards the teams have won over the last three decades. 

'''Robert B. Redman Stadium''' is situated on the upper campus of Bloomsburg University as part of the university's 103-acre athletic complex and is home to the football and track &amp; field programs. Originally built in February 1974, the new facility took the place of Athletic Park in downtown Bloomsburg as Home of the Huskies. 
 
In the spring of 2008 the facility was completely renovated as a part of a $3.45 million dollar project which included a press box with elevator, new rest rooms, artificial turf field, track and field facilities, new railings and ADA compliance, new parking lot, new visitor bleachers and lights. 
 
The stadium, which overlooks the scenic Susquehanna Valley, has seating for 5,000 spectators, although attendance at several events has exceeded that total. The largest crowd to see a football game in the facility totalled 7,483 at the 1985 Homecoming contest against [[Millersville University of Pennsylvania|Millersville]].
 
Originally, when planning began for the new stadium in 1963, the proposed site was on the lower campus across from where the Rec Center is now; however, a consultant's report recommended the upper campus development. The project finally got underway in 1972 at a total cost of $725,000.

'''Sports Stadium''', a new multi-purpose, lighted field, was opened in 2006. The $1.5 million dollar facility features a state-of-the-art, Fieldturf monofilament, artificial surface used by the field hockey, men’s and women’s soccer and women’s lacrosse teams. The facility also features a brand-new press box, sound system and seating for over 700 fans. 

'''Jan M. Hutchinson Field''' is home to Bloomsburg softball.  The stadium features large block dugouts, stadium style steating behind home plate and a scoreboard.

'''Danny Litwhiler Field''' is home to Bloomsburg's baseball program and features a large mesh screen and seating behind homeplate making it a fan friendly venue to watch college baseball.

'''Bloomsburg University Tennis Courts''' provide students with 13 courts and features four with lights, allowing for evening play.

===Wrestling===

The wrestling program at Bloomsburg is the only NCAA Division-I program the university sponsors.  The wrestling program competes as a member of the [[Eastern Wrestling League]] and the [[Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference]].  Bloomsburg wrestlers have earned All-American honors at the [[NCAA]] Championships 23 times with 4 National Titles.  In addition to their success at the NCAA Championships, Bloomsburg has crowned one champion at the [[National Collegiate Open Wrestling Championship]].

==Notable alumni==
Prominent alumni of Bloomsburg University include:

*[[Richard Benyo]], journalist and long distance runner
*[[Joe Colone]], one-year NBA player for the [[New York Knicks]] (1948–1949)
*[[Chuck Daly]], NBA coach, and head coach of the first USA [[Dream Team (basketball)|Dream Team]]
*[[Jahri Evans]], Offensive guard for the [[New Orleans Saints]], Super Bowl XLIV Champion (2010)
*[[Percy W. Griffiths]] (1893–1983), [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 15th District of [[Ohio]] (1943–1949)
*[[Tim Holden]], [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 17th District of [[Pennsylvania]] (1993-current)
*[[I. Clinton Kline]] (1858–1947), [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 16th District of [[Pennsylvania]] (1921–1923)
*[[Jessica Leccia]], actress best known as Natalia Rivera on ''[[Guiding Light]]''.
*[[John V. Lesher]] (1866–1932), [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 16th District of [[Pennsylvania]] (1913–1921)
*[[Gerry P. Little]], member of the [[Ocean County, New Jersey|Ocean County]], [[New Jersey]] [[Board of Chosen Freeholders]]
*[[Frederick W. Magrady]] (1863–1954), [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 17th District of [[Pennsylvania]] (1925–1933)
*[[Charles Clarence Pratt]] (1854–1916), [[United States|U.S.]] [[United States House of Representatives|Representative]] for the 14th District of [[Pennsylvania]] (1909–1911)
*[[Phyllis Mundy]], [[Pennsylvania House of Representatives|State Representative]] for [[Pennsylvania]]'s 120th legislative district ([[1991]]-current)
*[[Susan Roman]], Canadian voice actress
*[[Michael Schearer]], Author and computer security researcher
*[[Mark S. Schweiker]], Former governor of [[Pennsylvania]] (2001–03)
*[[Jimmi Simpson]], television and film actor
*[[Bob Tucker (American football)|Bob Tucker]], a former [[NFL]] player (1970–1980)

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* {{Official website|http://www.bloomu.edu}}
* [http://library.bloomu.edu/Archives/Presidents/Galleryindex.htm A Gallery of Presidents and History of Bloomsburg University]
* [http://library.bloomu.edu/Archives/1951history/1951index.htm ''Bloomsburg Through the Years''] (edited by Marguerite W. Kehr, August 1951)
* [http://www.bloomu.edu/documents/media/Quick_Facts.pdf Quick Facts about Bloomsburg University]

{{Pennsylvania State Athletic Conference}}
{{Public universities in Pennsylvania}}

{{Coord|41.008|-76.448|region:US-PA_type:edu|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bloomsburg University Of Pennsylvania}}
[[Category:Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania|*]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Columbia County, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1839]]

[[no:Bloomsburg University of Pennsylvania]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
