<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30875541" ns="0" title="Bukit Bintang Boys&#039; Secondary School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Secondary school
| name             = Bukit Bintang Boys Secondary School
| native_name      = Sekolah Menengah Kebangsaan (L) Bukit Bintang
| logo             = [[Image:smklbb by auyong.png|Bukit Bintang Boys School Logo]]
| motto            = ''Nisi Dominus Frustra'' - 'Without God All Is Vanity'.
| established      = 1958
| type             = Public
| category         = Secondary
| gender           = Male
| founder          = Miss Mary Glasgow
| city             = Petaling Jaya
| state            = Selangor Darul Ehsan
| country          = Malaysia
| district         = Petaling
| colours          = Olive green, Yellow
| yearbook         = The Bintang
| website          = *[http://smklbb.tripod.com/ Official BBBSS website]
* [http://bbbsforum.sytes.net/ Official BBBSS forum]
}}

'''Bukit Bintang Boys Secondary School (BBBSS)''', or BB, was established in 1958, one year after Malaysia achieved independence in 1957; making it one of the oldest secondary boys school in the city of [[Petaling Jaya]], [[Selangor]]; [[Malaysia]]. It is a mission school under the umbrella of [[Christian Brethren of Malaysia Property Trust]] but is administered by the government under the grant-in-aid system.

The school holds 2 school sessions. The morning session is for Form 3, Form 4, Form 5 and Form 6 students (ages 15 to 19) while the afternoon session is for Form 1 and Form 2 students (ages 13 to 14). This is so to accommodate the large number of students attending the school. The pupils are known &quot;BBians&quot;. It welcomes students from all races and religions. Although a boys' school, girls are permitted to attend the school at the Form 6 level (age 18 to 19).

==History==

The school was founded by Miss Mary Glasgow,&lt;ref&gt;[http://3people.org/bbbssoba/?page_id=96 Mary Glasgow - school founder]&lt;/ref&gt; who was the headmistress of [[Bukit Bintang Girls' School]] (BBGS); in the time when missionaries were involved in establishing educational institutions in the young country.

The municipal council, Majlis Perbandaran Petaling Jaya ([[MPPJ]]) (now named Majlis Bandaraya Petaling Jaya, [[MBPJ]]); allocated a piece of land to Glasgow for building a school for the community. Although the land was available, no money was provided to actually build it. Glasgow and the Bukit Bintang Girls' School students swung into action; raising money by holding fun fairs, food fairs and plays. Within a short time, the girls had raised enough to build the boys' school. Miss Yeoh Kim Eng (a retired teacher of BBGS) recounted the time when BBGS teachers and students, armed with buckets and bins, came to the newly built boys' school to wash and clean the building.

At its establishment, [[The Malay Mail]], a local daily, called it the brother school of Bukit Bintang Girls' School. After deliberation with teachers and advisers to name the new school, Glasgow named it Bukit Bintang Boys' Secondary School in connection to the girls' school Glasgow founded.

As a young nation in 1957-58, the Malaysian government welcomed help from all quarters to build schools and to give its citizens an education. Christian missionaries such as Glasgow opened &quot;Christian&quot; schools in the early 1960s, usually in the rural areas. They either bought land or were granted land in outskirt areas (often rural, undeveloped areas) and were left to their own ingenuity to develop and build their schools. Although the schools were started by missionaries, the curriculum was based on government guidelines and was usually non-religious, although Bible studies were encouraged. Initially, classes were taught in English but has since changed to Bahasa Melayu in line with the government directives. Since 2003, Science and Mathematics are being taught in English.

The school's first Principal (known as the [[Headmaster]]) was Mr. Alastair L. McGregor (now Doctor) from [[Scotland]]. He served the school from 1958 to 1966. He was only a young man of 28 when he accepted the challenge to run a school halfway round the world from his home in Scotland, United Kingdom.

In 1961, the secondary school was moved to its current location in Jalan Utara, Petaling Jaya; and at that time, each form (Form 1 to 5) consisted of only one class. A year later in 1962 - the year when the first group of students sat for the Cambridge Examination, the school's opening ceremony took place and McGregor was appointed the first headmaster.

In 1976, a new science block was built at the cost of RM200,000.00. This block consists of three science laboratories and a lecture theatre. This block was named 'The Boler Block' in honour of Mr. David Boler, the headmaster at the time. Funds to build new wings were mostly raised by the students and teachers. Help was also given by certain Christian associations.

In 2006, [[Bukit Bintang Girls' School]] moved to a new location in Cheras and did not retain its original name; it is now known as SMK Seri Bintang Utara. The Pavilion shopping centre was built over the old location.

===50th Anniversary===
[[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (50th Shirt).jpg|200px|thumb|50th Anniversary T-shirt]]
In 2008, the school celebrated her 50th anniversary (Golden Jubilee). Tan Sri [[Musa Hassan]], Malaysia's Inspector-General of Police, a BB alumnus, was the guest of honour.

A special 50th Anniversary T-shirt was released and sold by the school Co-operative.
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both&quot; /&gt;

==School identity==

The school motto is the Latin phrase: ''Nisi Dominus Frustra'' – 'Without God All is Vanity'; and is derived from Psalm 127:1.

The school vision is &quot;To Be The Best in Petaling Jaya by 2015&quot;.

The school mission is &quot;To develop a world-class quality education system which will realisethe full potential of the individual and fulfill the aspiration of the Malaysian nation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.moe.gov.my/?id=42&amp;lang=en Ministry of Education Malaysia Mission]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Headteachers===
{{multiple image
| width     = 200
| image1    = McGregor-classphoto-1961.jpg
| caption1  = McGregor in a 1961 class photo
| image2    = Form1 (1971).jpg
| caption2  = 1971 class photo
| image3    = WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Principal's plaque 1).jpg
| caption3  = List of Principals}}
* Sir Alastair L. McGregor (1958–1965)
* Mr. David Boler (1966–1978)
* Mr. Oh Kong Lum (1979–1995)
* Mdm. Ishah bt. Sulaiman (1996–2005)
* Mdm. Quah Mooi Eng (2006–2011)
* Mdm. Tong Ah Ten (2011-present)

===School administration===

Currently, the school administration is headed by Mdm. Tong Ah Ten.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Mdm. Tong Ah Ten || Headmistress
|-
| Mdm. Hajah Siti Marriam Bt. Mohd. Nor || Senior Assistant
|-
| Mr. Wang Hui Ming || Senior Assistants for Students Affairs
|-
| Ms. Mah Pin Sin || Senior Assistant for Co-curriculum
|-
| Mdm. Aznida Bt. Abdul Aziz || Senior Assistant for Form 6
|-
| Ms. Lee Har Bee || Senior Assistant for Afternoon Session
|-
| Mdm. Kartini Bt. Mat Tahir || Head of Languages
|-
| Mdm. Koh Sui Kheng || Head of Humanities
|-
| Mr. Mah Chean Wah || Head of Science &amp; Mathematics
|-
| Mr. Siah Kee Kun || Head of Technical &amp; Vocational Subjects
|-
| Mr. Tan Wei Yee || Academic Teacher for Form 6
|}

===The school badge and tie===

The second headmaster, Mr. David Boler (1966–1978) designed a new school badge when he replaced Mr. McGregor. The top left hand corner of the badge depicts hills which stands for 'Bukit' followed by the top right hand corner which shows a star which stands for 'Bintang', a [[Malay language|Malay]] word meaning [[star]]. The bottom left hand corner indicates the national flower 'Bunga Raya' ([[Hibiscus]]) and thus represents '[[Malaysia]].' Finally, the last portion of the badge with the design of a roof above the letters 'P.J.' means that the school is situated in Petaling Jaya. The shape that resembles a gear below the letters 'P.J.' symbolises that [[Petaling Jaya]] is an industrialised area. Mr. Boler also redesigned the school tie by adding the design of the school badge on to the plain olive green tie.

===The school song===

The school song was written by Dr McGregor. Dr McGregor wrote the song in English originally but it has been translated to [[Malay language|Bahasa]]. Students today sing both versions during school assembly and events.

'''English version of School Song'''

BBBS ever,&lt;br /&gt;
We would pledge to thee.&lt;br /&gt;
All our high endeavour,&lt;br /&gt;
With all our loyalty.&lt;br /&gt;
May thy star grow brighter,&lt;br /&gt;
May thy fame increase,&lt;br /&gt;
May this glorious chorus never, never cease.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Here we strive for honour,&lt;br /&gt;
Here we seek for truth,&lt;br /&gt;
Learn to help the weaker,&lt;br /&gt;
With the strength of our youth.&lt;br /&gt;
Of the highest wisdom,&lt;br /&gt;
Let our watchword be,&lt;br /&gt;
Without God before us all is vanity.

'''Bahasa version of School Song'''

BBBS Jaya,&lt;br /&gt;
Kami ikrar setia,&lt;br /&gt;
Segala tenaga,&lt;br /&gt;
Kami curah untukmu,&lt;br /&gt;
Sinarlah cahayamu,&lt;br /&gt;
Terang cemerlang&lt;br /&gt;
Biarlah lagu ini kekal abadi 

Kami tuntut bahagia,&lt;br /&gt;
Serta kebenaran&lt;br /&gt;
Membantu yang lemah,&lt;br /&gt;
Kami akan usaha&lt;br /&gt;
Dengan bijaksana,&lt;br /&gt;
Itulah cogan,&lt;br /&gt;
Tanpa restu Tuhan semua akan gagal.

===School magazine===

The school magazine is named &quot;The Bintang&quot;. Students and teachers contribute most of the featured articles. The magazine reports the school's activities for the year, club activities, official school functions, news about teachers and students etc. Also, there  are photos of students and co-curricular bodies.

===Old Boys' Association===

Some of the former students, commonly referred to as “Ex-BBians”; who have left BBBSS have banded together in the group called the Old Boys' Association, or the OBA.

==Infrastructures==

In 2006, air-conditioner units were installed in the Staff Room, as there were none existing earlier. Not only that, a PA system was set up around the school in the same year. The old toilet next to the Quartermaster Room was renovated into the current PBSM Room, sometimes used also by the dental checkup team from outside the school. The Science Labs were also renovated from  wooden tables to concrete tables.
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (PBSM Room 1).jpg|thumb|New PBSM Room]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Science Lab 1).jpg|thumb|Renovated Science Lab I]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Science Lab 2).jpg|thumb|Renovated Science Lab II]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Teacher's Room 2).jpg|thumb|Teacher's Room with air-conditioners]]
|}{{-}}
Also in 2006, a covered walkway was built, extending from a newly built waiting shed in front of the school to the front of Boler's Block. In 2010, another covered walkway was built, covering the area between the classes and the Dewan Lama (now named Dewan Dr. Alastair McGregor, commonly referred to as Dewan McGregor). This area has been cleared and paved with bricks.
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Covered Walkway 1).jpg|thumb|Upgraded walkway I]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Covered Walkway 2).jpg|thumb|Upgraded walkway II]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Entrance 4).jpg|thumb|Upgraded walkway III]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Covered Walkway 3).jpg|thumb|Upgraded walkway IV]]
|}
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Side Walkway Upgrade).jpg|thumb|Upgraded side walkway I]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Side Walkway Upgrade 2).jpg|thumb|Upgraded side walkway II]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Dewan McGregor 1).jpg|thumb|Dewan McGregor]]
|}{{-}}
In 2007, the school Co-operative was formed, named &quot;Koperasi Sekolah Menengah Kebangsaan Laki-laki Bukit Bintang Berhad&quot;. The original business centre was set up at the previous counseling room. In 2008, it was moved to the room behind the Canteen Area (earlier the Music Room). The shareholders of the Co-operative are students and teachers. The products sold are mostly stationery and books, but now have included buns and ice-cream. After the Government announced that free textbooks would be given to all students, the Co-operative took over the role of school bookshop.
{|
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Cooperative 1).jpg|thumb|Co-operative signboard]]
|}{{-}}

In 2008, the road from the main gate to the squash complex was tarred. A new Computer Laboratory was made in the same year, with 30 computers that were donated by the public. The Computer Lab had earlier occupied the Auditorium, now occupy the room which was formerly the Snooker Room.{{-}}

A new Teacher's Cafe, a lounge for Teachers; unveiled on Graduation Day in August 2009, with the presence of Madam Sharon Kang, the main sponsor. Other than that, a new wall was built around the Squash Complex. Towards the end of the school year, with contributions from an ex-BBian, a gymnasium was installed in one of the Squash Complex classes.
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Teacher's Cafe 1).jpg|thumb|Outside the cafe]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Teacher's Cafe 2).jpg|thumb|Inside the cafe I]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Teacher's Cafe 3).jpg|thumb|Inside the cafe II]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Squash Area Wall).jpg|thumb|Squash Area Wall]]
|}{{-}}
In 2010, the old wiring system of the school was rewired. 7 new air-conditioners were installed in the Dewan McGregor. The stairs from the front of the Badminton Hall to the Canteen were upgraded. So were the stairs from the Canteen to the field . The old toilet near the Dewan McGregor and classes, that was closed for a long time; had been renovated into a storeroom.
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Stairs to Canteen).jpg|thumb|Upgraded Stairs I]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Stairs to Squash Court).jpg|thumb|Upgraded Stairs II]]
|}{{-}}
In 2011, the auditorium was renovated. The carpet flooring was removed and replaced with wooden flooring.

===Largest squash court complex in Petaling Jaya===

In 1985, a project to construct a new canteen and a gymnasium cum squash courts was completed at a cost nearly half a million Ringgit. Students, teachers and parents raised funds over five years from 1981 to 1985. Fund-raising projects such as &quot;Jog-a-thon&quot;, Canteen Day and School Fun Fair were conducted during the period. Upon its completion, it had the largest squash court facilities in Petaling Jaya. The old canteen was used as a temporary classroom to accommodate the increasing number of students but was eventually demolished. The new double storey block housed a hall upstairs and canteen downstairs. The new school hall also doubled as badminton courts. The batch of students sitting for their 1985 [[Sijil Pelajaran Malaysia|SPM]] examinations took their examinations in the new hall. Members of the public can rent the squash courts and the badminton hall for their private usage. The squash complex has played host and even moonlighted as a venue for various international tournaments, prominently the Milo All Stars Junior Squash Championship, in which it partners with the MBPJ Squash Complex.
{|
|-
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Squash Complex 1).jpg|thumb|Squash court main entrance]]
| [[File:WHZhang's Bukit Bintang (Squash Complex 2).jpg|thumb|Squash court side entrance]]
|}{{-}}

==Curricular==

The classes were previously named after colors; Biru, Coklat, Emas, Gangsa, Hijau, Jingga, Kuning and Putih (B, C, E, G, H, J, K &amp; P) before 2008. During the second semester of 2008, it was changed to Budi, Unggul, Kerjasama, Ikhlas, Tekun, Nekad, Amanah, and Gigih (B, U, K, I, T, N, A &amp; G).

The school hosts students of Form 1 to Form 6 (Lower &amp; Upper) students. Public government examinations such as [[PMR]] (Penilaian Menengah Rendah), [[SPM]] (Sijil Pelajaran Menengah), and [[STPM]] (Sijil Tinggi Pelajaran Menengah) are held annually.

===Subjects===
====PMR level====
Subjects in Form 1 - 3
* [[Malay Language|Bahasa Melayu]] / Malay Language
* [[English language|English]] / Bahasa Inggeris
* Islamic Education / Pendidikan Islam - for all Muslim students
* Moral Studies / Pengetahuan Moral - for all non-Muslim students
* [[History]] / Sejarah
* [[Mathematics]] / Matematik
* [[Geography]] / Geografi
* Kemahiran Hidup (Kemahiran Teknikal / Perakaunan)

====SPM level====
Core subjects in Form 4 - 5
* [[Malay Language|Bahasa Melayu]] / Malay Language
* [[English language|English]] / Bahasa Inggeris
* Modern Mathematics / Matematik Moden
* Islamic Education / Pendidikan Islam - for all Muslim students
* Moral Studies / Pengetahuan Moral - for all non-Muslim students
* [[History]] / Sejarah

Elective subjects
Science stream
* Additional Mathematics / Matematik Tambahan
* [[Physics]] / Fizik
* [[Chemistry]] / Kimia
* [[Biology]] / Biologi

Sub-science stream
* Additional Mathematics / Matematik Tambahan
* [[Physics]] / Fizik
* [[Chemistry]] / Kimia
* Principles of Accountancy / Prinsip Akaun

Commerce stream
* [[Science]] / Sains
* Additional Mathematics / Matematik Tambahan
* Basic Economics / Ekonomi Asas
* Principles of Accountancy / Prinsip Akaun

Art stream
* [[Science]] / Sains
* [[Arts]] / Pendidikan Seni Visual
* Basic Economics / Ekonomi Asas
* Principles of Accountancy / Prinsip Akaun

====SPM level====
Core subjects in Form 6
* General Studies / Pengajian Am
* [[Malaysian University English Test]] / MUET

Science stream
* Mathematics T / Matematik T
* Chemistry / Kimia
* Biology / Biologi

Art stream
* Economics / Ekonomi
* Principles of Accountancy / Perakaunan
* Business Studies / Pengajian Perniagaan

==Co-curricular==
===Sport Houses===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Beruang
|-
| Gajah
|-
| Harimau
|-
| Pelanduk
|-
| Seladang
|}

===Uniform bodies===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Scouts
|-
| Red Cross Association Malaysia (PBSM)
|-
| Boys Brigade
|-
| Kadet Polis
|-
| Kadet Remaja Sekolah
|-
| Karate-do
|-
| Silat Gayung Fatani
|-
| Taekwondo
|}

===Clubs &amp; Societies===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Kelab Bahasa Malaysia
|-
| English Language Society
|-
| Chinese Language Society
|-
| Muslim Students' Society
|-
| Buddhist' Society
|-
| Hindu Society
|-
| Christian Fellowship
|-
| Pre-University Student Council
|-
| Maths &amp; Science Club
|-
| Astro Electronics System
|-
| Photography Club
|-
| Interact
|-
| Computer Club
|-
| Modellers 4WD
|-
| Music Club
|-
| Arts Club
|-
| Pembimbing Rakan Sebaya
|-
| Crime Prevention Club
|-
| SPBT Club
|-
| Kelab Senggara
|-
| Rukun Negara Club
|}

===Sports &amp; Games===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Badminton
|-
| Basketball
|-
| Football
|-
| Chess
|-
| Olahraga
|-
| Ping Pong
|-
| Rugby
|-
| Sepak Takraw
|-
| Squash
|-
| Softball
|-
| Tennis
|-
| Health &amp; Fitness
|}

===Special Bodies===

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| Prefectorial board
|-
| Librarians' board
|-
| Presidents' board
|-
| Students council
|-
| Quartermaster board
|-
| Editorial board
|-
| Co-operative board
|}

==Events==
===Yearly events===

Every year, there will be an Annual General Meeting for the [[Parent-Teacher Association|Parents-Teachers Association]], called as the Mesyuarat Agung PIBG.

The Cross Country Run (Merentas Desa) tradition has been continued on every year, normally held early in the year. Nowadays, it is graced by the attendance of Mr. Agis as track marshall, even though he may have retired. In 2011, the school changed the schedule for Road Run from early March to late March.

The annual Sport Day is held at Stadium Kelana Jaya. Athletes compete in a variety of track races. Beforehand, there will be Sukantara and Saringan held for the Sport Houses to compete for points, in the school compounds and Astaka Field. In 2010, the school changed the schedule for Sports Day from early May to June.

Academic Excellence Day (Hari Kecemerlangan) is held annually to inaugurate students with notable achievements in academics. There is always the &quot;Piala Pusingan McGregor&quot; given to one outstanding student.

Co-curricular Day (Hari Ko-Kurikulum) is held annually to inaugurate students and athletes of the school with notable achievements and contributions in and out -side of the school co-curricular activities.

===Other notable events===

Hari Raya Open House, held in the school compound (at the front of the Boler Block in 2009, in the Dewan McGregor in 2010), celebrates the Hari Raya celebrations with all BBians invited.

Chinese New Year Open House was held in the Dewan McGregor since 2008, celebrating Chinese New Year, with [[Yee Sang]] every year. A line of BBians would form in front of Madam Quah, as she would be giving out Red Packets to students during the event.

Hari Keluarga, held in 2008; had a wide variety of guest, ranging from BBians to parents and other families. The school compound was turned into a bazaar selling items ranging from the usual food and toys, to school caps and Polo T-shirts.

Jogathon 2010 was held on 17 July, with the mission of collecting funds to upgrade the school facilities. Students were given cards to record donations. Donations were not only in the form of money, but also as items such as coupons, hampers and branded goods. The fund collection was about RM57,000.

On 22 July 2011, Mdm. Quah Mooi Eng's retirement ceremony was held. Students and peers, including principals and education officers in Petaling district; attended the event to bid farewell to Mdm. Quah.

Graduation Day (Hari Graduasi) was held for the first time in 2010, and then on 10 November 2011. In this event, the senior students, Form 5 and Upper 6; are celebrated for their years in the school, and students and teachers bid their farewells and express their thanks.

==Notable alumni==

Some notable ex- BBians include [[Musa Hassan|Tan Sri Musa Hassan]] (Inspector General of Police), [[Reshmonu]] (recording artist) and Irfan Khairi (Malaysian internet millionaire).

Dhruva Murugasu, an ex-BBian; recently achieved 5As in Cambridge International A Level,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cie.org.uk/news/announcements/detail?announcement_id=30258 Cambridge students at Taylor's University College win places at top universities]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cie.org.uk/news/features/detail?feature_id=30251 Malaysia's academic elite celebrated at Cambridge Outstanding Achiever awards ceremony]&lt;/ref&gt; and Top in the World (June 2009) in Further Mathematics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cie.org.uk/docs/pdfs/Malaysia%20list%20of%20winners.pdf Malaysia Cambridge Outstanding Achiever ceremony 2009 - Cambridge International A level]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both&quot; /&gt;

Avinaash Subramaniam, an ex-BBian; recently got admitted into the prestigious [[Harvard University]] being the only Malaysian entering the class of 2014.{{Citation needed|reason=please give a reliable source for this assertion.|date=November 2011}}

==Miscellaneous Information==

* The school's annual Sports Day used to be held at &quot;Padang Timur&quot; (The Timur Field) as the school field is unable to accommodate the number of students and sporting events. Now it is usually held at the MBPJ Stadium, [[Kelana Jaya]].

==See also==
{{commons category|Bukit Bintang Boys' Secondary School}}
Gallery of BBBSS pictures:
&lt;br style=&quot;clear: both&quot; /&gt;

==References==

{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://3people.org/bbbssoba Official BBBSS Old Boys Association] - Alumni association
* [http://3people.org/bbbssoba/BB-school-song.htm School Song] - BB School Song

{{Coord|3|6|31.28|N|101|38|28.49|E|region:MY|display=title}}

{{Selangor}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:Secondary schools in Malaysia]]
[[Category:Schools in Selangor]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1958]]

[[ms:Sekolah Menengah Kebangsaan (L) Bukit Bintang]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
