<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30922104" ns="0" title="World Environment Day Awards"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox award
| name           = World Environment Day Awards
| current_awards = 
| image          = 
| imagesize      =  
| caption        =  
| description    = Excellence in Environmental Sustainability 
| presenter      = [[United Nations Association of Australia|UNAA]]
| country        = [[Australia]] 
| location       = [[Melbourne]]
| year           = 2000
| year2          = 
| website        = [http://www.unaavictoria.org.au/pages/awards-program/world-environment-day-awards.php World Environment Day Awards]
}}

The '''World Environment Day Awards''' are presented annually by the [[United Nations Association of Australia]] in support of the [[United Nations Environment Programme]]’s World Environment Day. The awards recognise the innovative and outstanding programs and initiatives from across Australia, and the important work of Australian environmental leaders.
The annual awards program invites nominations from individuals, organisations, businesses, local councils, school, journalists and community groups whose work serves to protect, manage or restore Australia’s natural heritage. The awards aim to raise awareness about key environmental issues and challenges, and to inspire and motivate individuals, organisations and businesses to take positive steps towards sustainability and environmental excellence in their homes, school, communities and workplaces.

==Award Categories== 

Current Award categories are open to a variety of nominees depending on the award, including businesses, local governments, community organisations, individuals, school and the media. The award categories have been expanded in scope and number since the awards founding in 2000, including the most recent addition of the Peter Szental Award for Sustainability Entrepreneurship, which recognises success in commercialising new sustainability solutions, demonstrating new business models and influencing mainstream thinking.

* WSP Lincolne Scott Sustainability Leadership Award
* Peter Szental Award for Sustainability Entrepreneurship
* Virgin Blue Business Awards
* Department of Sustainability and Environment Biodiversity Award
* Green Building Award
* Local Government Awards
* Excellence in Sustainable Water Management
* Environmental Schools Award
* Sustainability Education Award
* Excellence in Marine and Coastal Management Award
* Media Award for Environmental Reporting
* Community Award
* Individual Award

In 2011 the new Peter Szental Award for Sustainability Entrepreneurship recognizes businesses that have been outstanding in commercializing new sustainability solutions, demonstrating new business models and influencing mainstream thinking.

==Theme==

Each year the Awards carry a theme to coincide with the yearly theme of the United Nations Environment Programme. In 2011, the awards conincide with the International Year of Forests which raises awareness for the conservation, sustainable development, and sustainable management of forests and their inhabitants. The UNEP World Environment Day theme 'Forests: Nature at Your Service' has been declared in support of 2011 the International Year of Forests.

==Past Recipients==

Past recipients include; Darebin Council, National Australian Bank, Bond University and the Northern Gulf Resource Management Group.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.unaavictoria.org.au/pages/awards-program/world-environment-day-awards.php World environment Day Awards]
* [http://www.unaavictoria.org.au/pages/home.php United Nations Association of Australia - Victorian Division]
* [http://www.un.org/esa/forests/index.html/ United Nations Forum on Forests]
* [http://www.unep.org/forests/ United Nations Environment Programme]

[[Category:Environmental awards]]
[[Category:Awards established in 2000]]

[[ta:உலக சுகாதார நாள் விருதுகள் (ஆஸ்திரேலியா)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
