<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3093034" ns="0" title="Oxburgh Hall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Geobox|National Trust Property
| name =Oxburgh Hall
| category = country house
| image = Oxburgh Hall 3.jpg
| image_caption = Oxburgh Hall, Oxborough, Norfolk,
| flag =
| symbol = 
| country = [[England]]
| state =     [[Norfolk]]
| region =   [[East of England]]
| district =   [[King's Lynn and West Norfolk]]
| municipality = [[Oxborough]] 
| location =  At the village of Oxborough, 7miles south west of Swaffham 
| elevation =
| prominence =
| lat_d = 
| lat_m =
| lat_s =
| lat_NS =
| long_d =
| long_m =
| long_s =
| long_EW =
| length = 
| length_orientation = 
| width = 
| width_orientation = 
| height =
| depth = 
| volume =
| area = 
| author =
| style = Medieval, Moated great house
| material =stone and slate roof
| established = 1482 onwards 
| date =
| owner = Owned by the National Trust 
| public =
| visitation = Ramped entrance. 4 wheelchairs. Ground floor accessible. Stairs with handrail to other floors. Main exit via spiral staircase. Alternative route available.
| visitation_date = Opening times vary, see NT web site
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free = | free_type = 
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map =Norfolk outline map with UK.png
| map_caption = 
| map_background = 
| map_locator =
| map_locator_x =22
| map_locator_y =40
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt; 
| website = 
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes =Map Ref: TF742012
}}

'''Oxburgh Hall'''&lt;ref&gt;Pronounced &quot;OX bru&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; is a moated [[country house]] in [[Oxborough]], [[Norfolk]], [[England]], today in the hands of the [[National Trust for Places of Historic Interest or Natural Beauty|National Trust]]. Built around 1482 by Sir Edmund Bedingfeld, Oxburgh has always been a family home, not a fortress.   The [[Lord of the Manor|manor]] of Oxborough came to the [[Bedingfeld Baronets|Bedingfeld family]] by marriage before 1446, and the house has been continuously inhabited by them since their construction of it in 1482, the date of Edward Bedingfeld's licence to [[crenellate]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Nikolaus Pevsner]], ''Northwest and South Norfolk'' (The Buildings of England), 1962:282).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
[[Image:Oxburgh-gatehouse-inside.jpg|thumb|left|The courtyard front of the gatehouse, with paired polygonal stair towers]]
A fine example of a late medieval, inward-facing great house, Oxburgh stands within a square moat about 75 metres on each side, and was originally enclosed; the hall range facing the [[gatehouse]] was pulled down in 1772 for Sir Richard Bedingfeld, providing a more open U-shaped house, with the open end of the U facing south. The entrance, reached by a three-arched bridge on the north side, is dramatised by a grand fortified gatehouse,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The tremendous gatehouse, the most prominent of the English brick gatehouses of the C15,&quot; Nikolaus Pevsner deemed it (Pevsner 1962).&lt;/ref&gt; evoking the owner's power and prestige, though as fortification its value is largely symbolic; it is flanked by tall polygonal towers rising in seven tiers, with symmetrical wings extending either side that reveal nothing on the exterior of their differing internal arrangements. About 1835&lt;ref&gt;Pevsner 1962.&lt;/ref&gt; the open end of the U was filled in with a picturesque, by no means archaeologically correct range that recreated the central courtyard. Other Victorian additions include the [[Flanders|Flemish]]-style stepped gables, the massive southeast tower, the  oriel windows overhanging the moat (''illustration, left'') and [[terracotta]] chimneys. Four towers were added to the walled kitchen garden.

The hall is well known for its [[priest hole]]. Due to the [[Roman Catholic Church|Catholic]] faith of the [[Bedingfeld Baronets|Bedingfeld family]], a Catholic priest may have had to hide within the small disguised room in the event of a raid. The room is reached via a trapdoor, which when closed blends in with the tiled floor. Unlike many similar priest holes, the one at Oxburgh is open to visitors. 

The hall is also notable for its needlework hangings by [[Mary, Queen of Scots]]. She worked on these while in the custody of the [[Earl of Shrewsbury]], following her escape to England. Other hangings on display were produced by [[Bess of Hardwick]]. 

The estate has a number of woodland walks, including a 'Woodland Explorer' trail.

Oxburgh Hall is a popular location for film and television series, including brief appearances in the ''[[Dad's Army]]'' episode &quot;[[Museum Piece]]&quot;, and later in ''[[You Rang, M'Lord?]]''. It was the major setting for the 1994 television dramatisation of ''[[Love on a Branch Line (TV series)|Love on a Branch Line]]'', a [[Love on a Branch Line (novel)|novel]] by [[John Hadfield]].
[[Image:Oxburgh Hall 2.jpg|thumb|left|Oxburgh Hall: a Victorian pattern-[[parterre]] set in lawn&lt;!---NOTE: this will not fit anywhere else, UNLESS you greatly expand this article---&gt;]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Oxburgh Hall}}
* [http://www.nationaltrust.org.uk/main/w-vh/w-visits/w-findaplace/w-oxburghhall/ Oxburgh Hall, Garden &amp; Estate information at the National Trust]
*[http://www.ghostdatabase.co.uk/articles/oxburgh/ The Ghost of Oxburgh Hall]
*[http://www.flickr.com/search/?q=Oxburgh+Hall Flickr images tagged Oxburgh Hall]

{{coord|52|34|53.0|N|0|34|15.0|E|display=title}}

[[Category:Country houses in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Tudor architecture]]
[[Category:National Trust properties in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Grade I listed buildings in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Historic house museums in Norfolk]]
[[Category:Gardens in Norfolk]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
