<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="30971764" ns="0" title="2011 Omani protests"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Civil Conflict
| title = 2011 Omani protests
| partof = the [[Arab Spring]]
| image = [[File:Lulu Hypermarket Burning.jpg|300px]]
| caption = Protesters set ablaze Lulu Hypermarket in [[Sohar]] on February 28, 2011
| place = {{flag|Oman}}
| coordinates =
| date= {{start date|2011|01|17}} – {{end date|2011|05|31}}
| status = Ended
| time =
| timezone =
| goals = Salary increases, creating jobs, fighting corruption.
| methods = [[Demonstration]]s, [[sit-in]]s, and [[riot]]s
| injuries = 20
| fatalities = 2–6 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.adnkronos.com/IGN/Aki/English/Security/Oman-Six-killed-in-Sundays-pro-democracy-protests_311735597579.html Oman: 'Six killed' in Sunday's pro-democracy protests - Adnkronos Security&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

The '''2011 Omani protests''' were a series of  protests in the [[Arab states of the Persian Gulf|Gulf]] country of [[Oman]]. They were a part of the [[revolutionary wave]] popularly known as the [[Arab Spring]]. It's the first protest to be ended among the Arab Spring.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.brecorder.com/world/global-business-a-economy/19759-oman-budget-gap-rises-to-658mn-in-q1-spending-up.html&lt;/ref&gt;

Unlike other protests in the region, Oman’s demonstrators have emphasised their loyalty to their ruler, while voicing their dissatisfaction on  corrupt officials. The sultan responded to most of the demands which focus largely on more jobs and higher minimum salaries for Omanis, in addition to more power for the legislative council and the removal of several corrupt ministers.&lt;ref&gt;http://m.gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/protesters-in-oman-happy-with-qaboos-decision-to-give-council-of-oman-powers-1.776309&lt;/ref&gt;

==Issues==
Protesters demanded salary increases and lower costs of living. On 20 February 2011, protesters welcomed a move by the government to increase the [[minimum wage]].&lt;ref&gt;Al Jazeera. Headlines.&lt;/ref&gt; The wage increase targets Omani workers in the private sector. Public sector Omani employees have received wage increases in the past, but the private sector was so far overlooked. The [[Government of Oman]] raised minimum wages for an estimated 150,000 private sector employees to $520 from $364 a month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.france24.com/en/20110226-oman-boosts-student-benefits |title=Oman boosts student benefits |publisher=France24 |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As protests continued in Sohar the demands were still jobs and political reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;1mar&quot;/&gt; The protesters also want more jobs, [[freedom of expression]], less government control over the media,&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;/&gt; political reforms, better living conditions, an abolition of taxes and the trial of all ministers.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt2&quot;/&gt;

Protesters in Muscat also demanded cabinet ministers not serve more than four years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Al |first=Saleh |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/02/19/us-oman-protests-idUSTRE71I0V920110219 |title=Oman protesters call for political reform, pay rise |publisher=Reuters |date=19 February 2011|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In several other protests, Omanis also demanded the reduction of foreign workers in order to provide more jobs for Omani citizens by private companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Omanization|url=http://www.thenational.ae/news/worldwide/pay-raise-ends-walkout-by-workers-at-300-firms-in-industrial-park-in-oman}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Anti-government protests==
About 200 protesters marched on 17 January demanding salary increases and lower costs of living. The protest shocked news reporters who have viewed Oman as a &quot;politically stable and sleepy country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.arabianbusiness.com/oman-protestors-call-for-fight-against-corruption--374524.html |title=Oman protestors call for fight against corruption - Culture &amp; Society |publisher=ArabianBusiness.com |date=|accessdate=29 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Renewed protests termed as the ''Green March'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofoman.com/innercat.asp?detail=41806&amp;rand=uVGjVlZjQUKJ2MN73tEvK9Y92v |title=Times of Oman |publisher=Times of Oman |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; occurred on 18 February, inspired by the serious unrest in fellow Gulf state Bahrain. 350 people marched, demanding an end to corruption and better distribution of oil revenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;spinner1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Spinner |first=Jackie |url=http://www.slate.com/id/2285656/ |title=Middle East protests: Oman's peaceful anti-corruption march |publisher=Slate Magazine |date=18 February 2011 |accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protesters also carried signs with slogans of support for the Sultan.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.upi.com/Top_News/World-News/2011/02/19/Oman-protests-peaceful-so-far/UPI-96551298131400/ |title=Oman protests peaceful so far |publisher=United Press International|date=|accessdate=19 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police did not intervene in the gathering, the petition calling for the reforms will be handed to Oman's Sultan Qaboos.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.rian.ru/world/20110219/162677613.html |title=Hundreds stage peaceful march in Oman demanding reforms &amp;#124; World &amp;#124; RIA Novosti |publisher=En.rian.ru |date=3 January 2011 |accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 February, nearly 500 protesters gathered around a shopping mall in the industrial city of [[Sohar]], 230 kilometres from the capital [[Muscat, Oman|Muscat]].&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/201122620711831600.html |title=Oman shuffles cabinet amid protests - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protesters stopped traffic and shoppers around the mall premises. The shops in the area including the mall remained closed on 27 February as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;gulfnews1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/sit-in-in-sohar-town-forces-hypermarkets-to-close-down-1.768284 |title=Sit-in in Sohar town forces hypermarkets to close down |publisher=gulfnews |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 February, protesters returned in Sohar for a second day, hurling stones at security forces who had cordoned them off.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/02/27/oman-protests-idUSLDE71Q04I20110227|title=Oman police clash with stone-throwing protesters|publisher=Reuters|year=|accessdate=27 February 2011|date=27 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Oman Police]] eventually used tear gas and rubber bullets to contain and disperse the protesters.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters1&quot;/&gt; According to witnesses, two protesters were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Associated |first=The |url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5gh9egWT30AUKwD6gzNoIxvkoqFMg?docId=6083540 |title=The Canadian Press: Omani protesters stage third day of anti-government unrest, latest in Gulf region |publisher=Google.com |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/2011227112850852905.html |title=Deaths in Oman protests - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12590588 |title=BBC News - Oman clashes: Two killed during protests in Gulf state |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=8 February 2011 |accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 February, protesters looted and burned a hypermarket in Sohar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.telegraphindia.com/1110303/jsp/nation/story_13661334.jsp |title=Jitters over attack on Indian mall in Oman |publisher=The Telegraph |date=1 March 1999 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The demonstrators also blocked the entrance to Sohar port, where 160,000 barrels of oil derived products are exported.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rttnews.com/Content/GeneralNews.aspx?Id=1563846&amp;SM=1 |title=Oman's Second-Largest Port Blocked By Protesters |publisher=Rttnews.com |date=28 February 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 March protests continued for a fourth day as crowds in Sohar congregated at the Globe Roundabout. Eventually, the [[Royal Army of Oman|Royal Omani Army]] forces, including tanks, peacefully dispersed protesters blocking the Sohar port and cleared them from the main coastal highway linking Muscat to Sohar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.morningstaronline.co.uk/index.php/news/content/view/full/101712 |title=Tanks roll into Sohar |publisher=Morning Star |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.middle-east-online.com/english/?id=44659 |title=ميدل ايست أونلاين: |publisher=Middle East Online |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.euronews.net/2011/03/01/army-disperses-protesters-in-oman/ |title=Army disperses protesters in Oman |publisher=Euronews.net |date=|accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The troops later pulled back, though five armored vehicles continued to watch the square.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pakobserver.net/detailnews.asp?id=79014 |title=Oman forces disperse protesters |publisher=Pakobserver.net |date=|accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Globe Roundabout had been the site of up to 2,000 demonstrators over the past three days.&lt;ref name=&quot;1mar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/201131101527815578.html |title=Fresh protests break out in Oman |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; About 50 protesters held a [[sit-in]] as well outside the [[Consultative Assembly of Oman]] to demand political reform and an end to corruption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Abouzeid |first=Rania |url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,2057061,00.html?xid=rss-mostpopular |title=Oman: Greetings from the Mideast's Relaxed Revolution |publisher=TIME |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Sunil K. |last=Vaidya |url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/peaceful-protests-in-oman-gather-steam-as-more-join-1.771606 |title=Peaceful protests in Oman gather steam as more join |publisher=Gulfnews |date=4 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group later grew to over 400 people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Rejimon K. |url=http://www.zawya.com/story.cfm/sidZAWYA20110301074616 |title=Demonstrators rally at Majlis Al Shura |publisher=Zawya |date=1 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protesters also continued to demand the Consultative Assembly be turned into a &quot;real parliament.&quot; The protests were reported to be &quot;peaceful, well-organised and very disciplined.&quot; Tents had been set up with separate accommodations for men and women. Placards with protest slogans had also been translated into English, French and German for the international media.&lt;ref name=&quot;nl&quot;/&gt;

After reports of multiple deaths, the minister of health of Oman claimed only one person had been killed and 20 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2011/03/01/3151369.htm One dead as protests spread to Oman - ABC News (Australian Broadcasting Corporation)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Facebook'' entitled &quot;March 2 Uprising for Dignity and Freedom&quot; called for further protests in all parts of Oman, beginning on 2 March, and it attracted more than 2,300 users.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt2&quot;/&gt; However, protests only occurred at the Globe Roundabout in Sohar with a smaller crowd of 50 protesters who blockaded the area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Mcdowall |first=Angus |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703409904576174571884664378.html |title=Protests in Oman Sputter |publisher=Wall Street Journal |date=2 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some people had organised community policing groups to prevent more damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timesofoman.com/echoice.asp?detail=41362 |title=Sultanate’s security forces unearth UAE spy network |publisher=Times of Oman |date=31 January 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/heavily-armed-military-vehicles-guard-sohar-1.769763 |title=Heavily-armed military vehicles guard Sohar |publisher=Gulfnews |date=|accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The army also issued a red alert to vacate the area or threatened action.&lt;ref name=&quot;gulf2mar&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/oman-sounds-red-alert-protesters-given-evening-deadline-1.770510 |title=Oman sounds red alert; protesters given evening deadline |publisher=Gulfnews |date=2 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 'Sohar Citizen Committee' as its called has started giving out numbers of its core members to people who can call upon it in case of an emergency or riots attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;gulf2mar&quot; /&gt;

On 5 March, protests in the country have spread to [[Haima]], a key oil region about {{convert|500|km|abbr=on}} southwest of the capital Muscat, with oil workers staging a sit-in and calling for more government investment in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJ-Oman-5Mar&quot;/&gt;

On 30 March, The [[Director of Public Prosecutions]] issued a statement saying that complaints were filed by some citizens about acts of rioting, vandalism and breach of public order, and destruction of public and private properties and obstructing business transactions and easy movement of people on the streets. Based in these complains, Public Prosecution give orders to crackdowns by competent authorities. The Omani army stormed the [[Globe Roundabout]] in Sohar clearing blockades and arrested a number of protesters ending a month-old sit-in.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurasiareview.com/oman-soldiers-use-force-to-end-one-month-sit-in-29032011/ Oman: Soldiers Use Force To End One Month Sit-In&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jCx0tMQLB9ylW1Ng9XB3MDM00ggg?docId=CNG.34a222e35c6a2e98d03744cee3b43b05.621 AFP: Omani army ends pro-reform sit-in&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.khaleejtimes.com/DisplayArticle08.asp?xfile=data/middleeast/2011/March/middleeast_March485.xml&amp;section=middleeast Oman’s Public Prosecution orders arrest of protesters&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/Top_News/World-News/2011/03/29/Oman-forces-crack-down-on-protesters/UPI-89971301402206/ Oman forces crack down on protesters - UPI.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://af.reuters.com/article/energyOilNews/idAFLDE72S0LO20110329?pageNumber=1&amp;virtualBrandChannel=0 | work=Reuters | title=Oman army clears roadblocks in Sohar pay protest | date=29 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The use of force to clear the roundabout occurred after protesters had blocked traffic at the roundabout for nearly five weeks. The protests at the roundabout also coincided with several acts of forced shut down of government and private sector offices and arson in Sohar and Ibri which finally forced the Omani authorities to take tougher action.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muscatdaily.com/Archive/Stories-Files/Ministry-of-Manpower-shut-down-forcibly-in-Sohar/%28language%29/eng-GB Ministry of Manpower shut down forcibly in Sohar - Oman News|Muscatdaily&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 1 April, following Friday prayers, hundreds of protesters took to streets in Sohar demanding the release of people detained in the Public Prosecution crackdowns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5gHKIGxf2JZ3o5w-LiUjdo0NE-Zhw?docId=6432720] {{Dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 50 protesters were detained by security forces. The military has also stationed units around government offices and other key buildings in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJOman2Apr&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Oman protests resume |author= |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/04/20114213219368983.html |newspaper= |date=2 April 2011 |accessdate=2 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Witnesses reported that when the army moved in to clear the demonstrators, they reacted violently - using knives, rocks and guns. The army responded by initially firing tear gas and bullets in the air. When the demonstrators continued to get violent, the army used rubber bullets which led to the death of one individual after he received a direct hit in the head.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://af.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idAFTRE7310T320110402 | work=Reuters | title=Oman detained up to 60 during clashes - witnesses | date=2 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5j1t6UcsUhhalNFSFPviQqiy3pxng?docId=CNG.1fd1c4853d22c9c6fd2476a783525b0d.6e1 AFP: Police shoot one dead in Oman protest: witnesses&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
Six others were also badly injured in the incident which had initially started off as a peaceful demonstration demanding the release of over 100 protesters detained by authorities three days before.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muscatdaily.com/Archive/Stories-Files/1-dead-6-injured-as-peace-march-turns-violent-in-Sohar/%28language%29/eng-GB 1 dead, 6 injured as peace march turns violent in Sohar - Oman News|Muscatdaily&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 April, dozens of protesters staged a sit-in in Muscat, outside the chief prosecutor's office, to demand probes into alleged state abuses after clashes with security forces a day earlier.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJOman2Apr&quot;/&gt;

On 5 April, the public prosecutor of Oman announced that it had apprehended individuals who were preparing petrol bombs and were gathering weapons. It stated that they probably planned to use these weapons in a demonstration in the northern industrial city of Sohar on Friday (8 April).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5jWiOn6yAppzR7KYiZQ408HJqGZQg?docId=6469194] {{Dead link|date=May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 April, the public prosecutor's office release details and photographs of others who were arrested including one which went by the fancy name of 'Dragon Gang'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muscatdaily.com/Archive/Stories-Files/Dragon-Gang-head-arrested-in-Sohar/%28language%29/eng-GB ‘Dragon Gang’ head arrested in Sohar - Oman News|Muscatdaily&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Following the arrest of these individuals the situation in Sohar calmed down.

On 8 April after rumours had abounded that a large number of protesters, including women and children, would take to the streets of Sohar after the Friday prayers, nothing untoward was reported by the local media. The Omani army took control of the city setting up multiple checkpoints and arresting a few wanted individuals. The situation in the port city has been calm since that day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.muscatdaily.com/Archive/Stories-Files/Sohar-peaceful-under-heavy-security-cover/%28language%29/eng-GB Sohar peaceful under heavy security cover - Oman News|Muscatdaily&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 May, protesters returned to the streets in [[Salalah]] after Friday prayers. The protesters called for democratic reform and an end to corruption.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.trust.org/trustlaw/news/hundreds-call-for-reform-end-to-graft-in-oman Hundreds call for reform, end to graft in Oman - TrustLaw&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The activists and protesters have reiterated their demands for the sacked ministers to be investigated. This was the fourth consecutive Friday to be marked by protests in Salalah.

Police broke up a protest camp in Salalah on 12 May, arresting an unknown number of protesters, possibly over 100. Several dozen more protesters were attacked by baton-wielding [[gendarmerie|gendarmes]] and arrested in Salalah on 13 May and early 14 May while demanding jobs and higher pay.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.euronews.net/newswires/920067-omani-forces-arrest-protesters-after-clashes/ Omani forces arrest protesters after clashes]&lt;/ref&gt; Omani newspaper [[Muscat Daily]] reported that protesters clashed with the army on Salalah's central Al Nahda street following the first wave of arrests. The army fired into the air and also used tear gas to break up and disperse stone throwing crowds in Salalah.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.muscatdaily.com/Archive/Stories-Files/Operation-Salalah-army-arrests-protesters/%28language%29/eng-GB|title=Operation Salalah: Omani Army arrests Salalah protesters|publisher=Muscat Daily|date=Accessed on May 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Pro-government rallies==
On 1 March a rally was organised in Muscat to show support for the Sultan and his government. There were accusations that the government itself organised the rally, though at least some support was a &quot;part genuine outpouring of affection for the sultan.&quot; However, multiple [[sms]]' were sent from the state-owned [[Omantel]] network during the nights precedeing the protests urging loyalists to attend.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Fuller |first=Thomas |title=Rallies in Oman Steer Clear Of Criticism of Its Leader |work=The New York Times |page=8 |date=2 March 2011 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/02/world/middleeast/02oman.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were also continuous reports, mostly from ''[[Twitter]]'', that supporters of the government drove around in motorcades of up to 200 cars around Muscat in massive motorcades.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iAymzdbdndBVAczRpJ13-_iQbPCg?docId=CNG.4103fec93a330f1c195d92e86c2ce8c3.281 AFP: Pro-sultan Omanis in support drive]. Google.com (2011-03-02). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/omani-tweep-who-told-the-sohar-story-1.770405 Omani tweep who told the Sohar story]. gulfnews (2011-03-02). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;

In early March rallies in support of the Sultan continued to be staged.&lt;ref name=&quot;nl&quot;/&gt;

==Responses==
===Domestic===
The [[Sultan Qaboos|Sultan of Oman]] cancelled a visit to India as a result of the unrest in the Arab world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Indrani Bagchi, TNN, Feb 18, 2011, 02.59am IST |url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Egypt-fallout-Oman-ruler-postpones-India-trip/articleshow/7518853.cms |title=Egypt fallout: Oman ruler postpones India trip – The Times of India |publisher=Timesofindia.indiatimes.com |date=18 February 2011 |accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He has up till now not made any comments on any of the problems that the country is facing .

On 26 February, the Sultan reshuffled the cabinet&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;/&gt; in response to recent protests. The 84-member [[Consultative Assembly of Oman|Shura council]] is elected by voters across 61 districts, but works in a purely advisory capacity and has no legislative powers. The cabinet reshuffle saw [[Mohammed bin Nasser al-Khasibi]] named commerce and industry minister, [[Hamoud bin Faisal al-Bousaidi]] as civil service minister and [[Madiha bint Ahmed bin Nasser]] as education minister. Sheikh [[Mohammed bin Abdullah al-Harthy]], the outgoing civil service minister, was appointed to head the environment ministry, while [[Maqboul bin Ali bin Sultan]] will be the new transport minister and [[Mohsen bin Mohammed al-Sheikh]] becomes tourism minister. Protesters had called upon the Sultan to remove [[Maqbool Bin Ali Bin Sultan]] from the post of commerce minister as they viewed him as corrupt and inadequate for the task of running the ministry.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/sultan-qaboos-reshuffles-oman-cabinet-1.768277 |title=Sultan Qaboos reshuffles Oman cabinet |publisher=gulfnews |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sultan also announced benefits for the students of [[Higher College of Technology]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.khaleejtimes.com/DisplayArticle08.asp?xfile=data/middleeast/2011/February/middleeast_February780.xml&amp;section=middleeast |title=Oman takes measures to address public grievances |publisher=Khaleejtimes.com |date=|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The students whose homes are 100&amp;nbsp;km away from the place of study, will be now given 90 [[Omani rial]] allowances while those living at a less than 100-km distance would get 25-rial allowance. The Royal decree issued stated the reason for rise in these stipends as &quot;to achieve further development and provide a decent living.&quot;

The [[Diwan of Royal Court]], on the orders of the sultan, decided to set up an independent authority for consumer protection in the country. It has also been decided to study the possibility of establishing cooperative societies in the country which does not allow formation of any political parties, unions, etc. whatsoever.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera1&quot;/&gt; There are also confirmed plans to reduce the percentage contribution of civil servants in the Civil Employees Pension Fund from eight percent to seven percent of the monthly basic salary, adding to it 75 percent of the housing, electricity and water allowances.&lt;ref name=&quot;gulfnews1&quot;/&gt;

On 28 February, Sultan Qaboos pledged to create 50,000 government jobs, provide a monthly benefit of $390 to the unemployed and ordered a committee to draft proposals for boosting the power of an elected council that advises him in state affairs.&lt;ref&gt;Charmelot, Jacques. (2011-02-27) [http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5iEbFoiaf3y5011Vp3yrALFAa0kjQ?docId=CNG.3bcc0040b48d45bb31070d5319019b17.121 AFP: Oil-rich Arab states open their coffers]. Google.com. Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt; He also promised that a legislative council would be given more powers. On 5 March, Sultan Qaboos replaced two more ministers. [[Khaled bin Hilal bin Saud al-Busaidi]] replaced [[Sayed Ali bin Hmud al-Busaidi]] as a minister of the royal court and [[Sultan bin Mohammed al-Numani]] replaced General [[Ali bin Majid al-Maamari]] as minister in the sultan's office.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJ-Oman-5Mar&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Oman's ruler dismisses ministers |author=[[Al-Jazeera English]] |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/video/middleeast/2011/03/20113565533194678.html |newspaper= |date=5 March 2011 |accessdate=5 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 7 March, Sultan Qaboos issued eight royal decrees including, reshuffling once again the council of ministers and allowing for formation of a state audit committee. Royal Decree No 38/2011 abolished the Ministry of National Economy and states that a committee shall be formed by the Council of Ministers to manage the distribution of its prerogatives, allocations, assets and employees. The ministry had been targeted by protesters for being corrupt and inefficient.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.english.globalarabnetwork.com/2011030710133/Oman-Politics/oman-sultan-qaboos-restructures-council-of-ministers.html Oman: Sultan Qaboos Restructures Cabinet Ministers | Oman Politics]. Global Arab Network (2011-03-07). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 March, a royal decree was announced granting &quot;legislative and regulatory powers&quot; to the parliament, which had previously only been a consultative body.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/qaboos-gives-legislative-powers-to-council-of-oman-1.775709 Qaboos gives legislative powers to Council of Oman]. gulfnews (2011-03-13). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt; The next day he fired Lieutenant General [[Malek Bin Sulaiman Al Ma'amari]] as Inspector General of the Police and Customs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenational.ae/news/worldwide/middle-east/sultan-qaboos-fires-omans-police-chief Sultan Qaboos fires Oman's police chief – The National]. Thenational.ae. Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 March, he also issued further [[royal decree]]s to add a &quot;cost of living allowance&quot; to all military and security apparatus as well as all government units{{Vague|date=March 2011}} in Oman.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofoman.com/innercat.asp?detail=42161&amp;rand=EMxwVAelcGNCR4KVVGWDH2Bh6G Times of Oman]. Times of Oman (2011-03-15). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt; The Sultan also give orders for raising the Social Insurance Pension by 100% for all the 51,442 persons registered at the Social Development Ministry.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesofoman.com/innercat.asp?detail=42141 Times of Oman]. Times of Oman (2011-03-14). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;
The ruling council issued a statement that condemned the &quot;sabotage&quot; and added that peaceful demonstrations were within &quot;the legal rights of citizens.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=York.|first=Nada Bakri; J. David Goodman Contributed Reporting From New|title=Protests in Oman Spread From Port City to Capital|work=The New York Times|page=10|date=1 March 2011|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/01/world/middleeast/01oman.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other responses includes creating of a second public university,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.khaleejtimes.com/DisplayArticleNew.asp?col=&amp;section=middleeast&amp;xfile=data/middleeast/2011/May/middleeast_May52.xml&lt;/ref&gt; establishing the first Islamic bank in the region&lt;ref&gt;http://www.emirates247.com/business/bank-nizwa-is-oman-s-first-islamic-bank-2011-05-16-1.393394&lt;/ref&gt; and approving Marriage Fund utility.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.khaleejtimes.com/displayarticle.asp?xfile=data/middleeast/2011/May/middleeast_May828.xml&amp;section=middleeast&amp;col&lt;/ref&gt;

;Apolitical
The [[Muscat Securities Market]]'s main index fell 4.9 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gulfnews.com/business/markets/regional-markets-extend-losses-as-unrest-grows-1.769417 |title=Regional markets extend losses as unrest grows |publisher=gulfnews |date=28 January 2009 |accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Neighbouring [[United Arab Emirates]]' two main stock markets in [[Dubai Financial Market|Dubai]] and [[Abu Dhabi Securities Exchange|Abu Dhabi]] also fell as the instability moved to the countries of the [[Gulf Cooperation Council]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lohade |first=Nikhil |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704615504576172241374081256.html |title=Gulf Markets Dive as Unrest Spreads - WSJ.com |publisher=Online.wsj.com |date=28 February 2011|accessdate=1 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Sohar Industrial Port Company]] said that the local port's functions were never disrupted by more than a few hours during periods of traffic probles caused by the protests.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

===International===
;Supranational bodies
{{flagicon|Gulf Cooperation Council}} [[Gulf Cooperation Council]] members agreed to provide Oman with an aid plan similar to the [[Marshall plan]], consisting of $10 billion aimed at upgrading housing and infrastructure over a period of 10 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;AJBahr10Mar&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Sectarian clashes at Bahrain school |author=[[Al-Jazeera English]] |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/2011310201330454225.html |newspaper= |date=10 March 2011 |accessdate=13 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also agreed that they would give more preference to GCC-member state nationals while hiring individuals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/kuwait/gcc-marshall-style-aid-package-for-bahrain-oman-1.770473 GCC marshall-style aid package for Bahrain, Oman]. gulfnews (2011-03-02). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;

;States
{{flagicon|India}} [[India]] – The Indian embassy in Muscat issued a notice to all citizens of [[India]] currently residing in Oman (estimated at more than 300,000) to register themselves with the embassy. It also requested them to avoid taking part in any pro-government or anti-government rallies and steer clear of any kind of trouble.&lt;ref&gt;[http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/oman/indians-urged-to-be-on-guard-by-mission-in-oman-1.770511 Indians urged to be on guard by mission in Oman]. gulfnews (2011-03-02). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Netherlands]] [[Queen Beatrix]] had originally postponed a state visit to Oman amidst the crisis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2011/03/02/AR2011030203039.html ]{{dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The visit later went ahead but was downgraded to a private visit amidst several political parties expressing concern the royal could be seen as supportive of the sultan. Parliament will debate the matter on Tuesday.&lt;ref name=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;[http://www.rnw.nl/english/bulletin/oman-protests-continue-ahead-royal-visit Oman protests continue ahead of royal visit | Radio Netherlands Worldwide]. Rnw.nl (2011-03-06). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{flagicon|UK}} [[United Kingdom]] – The British embassy in Oman issued a notice to all British citizens in the country to avoid visiting Sohar as the situation in the city was tense.&lt;ref&gt;[https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-ateiW7W0WGg/TWtBqXJHplI/AAAAAAAAJ_I/Ccq0-FF_ANc/s1600/Wardens+notice+27+Feb+11.jpg Wardens Note], British Embassy Muscat, 28 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

{{flagicon|USA}} [[United States of America]] – The U.S. State Department spokesman [[Philip J. Crowley|P.J. Crowley]] told reporters the U.S. encouraged the [[government of Oman]] to show restraint and resolve differences through dialogue. &quot;We have been in touch with the government and encouraged restraint and to resolve differences through dialogue. We are encouraged by the recent steps toward reform taken by the government of Oman, and we strongly encourage the government to continue to implement reforms that increase economic opportunity and move toward greater inclusion and participation in the political process.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5hRTqyfhpSPpVTcY8OU8K8bYlGYKg?docId=CNG.b5aedb71894a12facb3ae790ca3ef931.891 AFP: US encouraged by Oman's reform moves]. Google.com (2011-03-07). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;
;NGOs
[[Amnesty International]] has requested and urged the Omani government to show restraint while dealing with protesters.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sify.com/news/oman-urged-not-to-use-excessive-force-against-protesters-news-international-ldbq4wadbee.html Oman urged not to use excessive force against protesters]. Sify.com (2011-03-01). Retrieved on 2011-03-28.&lt;/ref&gt;

==External links==
*[http://en.qantara.de/webcom/show_article.php/_c-476/_nr-1495/i.html Sultan Qaboos bin Said: Oman's Renaissance Man]

==See also==
{{commons category|2011 Omani protests}}
*[[Dhofar Rebellion]]
*[[List of countries by unemployment rate|World unemployment rates]]
*[[Corruption Perceptions Index]]
*[[Freedom in the World]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{2010-2011 Middle East and North Africa protests}}
{{Anti-government protests in the 21st century}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2011 Omani Protests}}
[[Category:Arab Spring by country|Oman protests, 2011]]
[[Category:2011 in Oman|Protests]]
[[Category:2011 protests|Omani]]

[[ar:الاحتجاجات العمانية 2011]]
[[az:2011-ci il Oman iğtişaşları]]
[[de:Proteste in Oman 2011]]
[[es:Protestas en Omán de 2011]]
[[fr:Protestations omanaises de 2011]]
[[ko:2011년 오만 반정부 시위]]
[[it:Proteste in Oman del 2011]]
[[hu:2011-es ománi tüntetések]]
[[pl:Protesty w Omanie (2011)]]
[[pt:Protestos em Omã em 2011]]
[[ru:Волнения в Омане (2011)]]
[[vi:Biểu tình Oman 2011]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
