<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31066097" ns="0" title="Essam Sharaf"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Expand Arabic|عصام شرف|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox officeholder
| name           = Essam Sharaf&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;عصام شرف&lt;/small&gt;
| image          = Dr Essam Sharaf.jpg
| office         = [[Prime Minister of Egypt]]
| leader         = [[Mohamed Hussein Tantawi]] &lt;small&gt;(Acting)&lt;/small&gt;
| deputy         = 
| term_start     = 3 March 2011
| term_end       = 3 December 2011
| predecessor    = [[Ahmed Shafik]]
| successor      = [[Kamal Ganzouri]]
| office2        = [[Ministry of Transportation (Egypt)|Minister of Transportation]]
| primeminister2 = [[Ahmed Nazif]]
| term_start2    = 1 June 2004
| term_end2      = 15 December 2005
| predecessor2   = Hamdy El-Shayeb
| successor2     = Mohamed Mansour
| birth_date     = {{birth year and age|1952|2|7}}
| birth_place    = [[Giza]], [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]]
| death_date     = 
| death_place    = 
| party          = [[Independent (politician)|Independent]] &lt;small&gt;(2005–present)&lt;/small&gt;
| otherparty     = [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]] &lt;small&gt;(Before 2005)&lt;/small&gt;
| alma_mater     = [[Cairo University]]&lt;br&gt;[[Purdue University]]
| profession     = [[Civil engineer]]
| religion       = [[Sunni Islam]]
}}
'''Essam Abdel-Aziz Sharaf''' ({{lang-ar|عصام عبد العزيز شرف}}, {{IPA-arz|ʕeˈsˤɑːm ʕæbdelʕæˈziːz ʃɑɾˤɑf|IPA}}; born 1952) is an [[Egypt]]ian academic who was the [[Prime Minister of Egypt]] from 3 March 2011 to 3 December 2011. He served as [[Ministry of Transportation (Egypt)|Minister of Transportation]] from 2004 to 2005.

==Early life and education==

Sharaf was born in the Egyptian city of [[Giza]] in 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahram&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Meet Essam Sharaf: Egypt's first post-revolution Prime Minister|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/~/NewsContent/1/64/6892/Egypt/Politics-/Meet-Essam-Sharaf-Egypts-first-postrevolution-Prim.aspx|publisher=Ahram online|accessdate=4 March 2011|coauthors=Ahmed Elieba &amp; Marwa Hussein}}&lt;/ref&gt; After receiving his [[Bachelor of Science|B.Sc.]] in civil engineering from [[Cairo University]] in 1975, he went to [[Purdue University]] where he continued his studies, receiving his [[Master of Engineering|M.Sc. Engg]] in 1980 and his [[Doctor of Philosophy|Ph.D.]] in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=https://engineering.purdue.edu/Engr/People/Awards/Institutional/DEA/DEA_2006/sharaf |title=Purdue University Profile of Essam Sharaf |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political and academic career==

Sharaf took a post as a visiting assistant professor at Purdue in 1984 before becoming assistant professor of Highway and Traffic Engineering at the University of Cairo the following year. In 1990, he was an assistant professor in Civil Engineering at [[King Saud University]] in [[Saudi Arabia]]. He returned to the University of Cairo in 1991, becoming a professor of Highway Engineering in 1996 while working as senior advisor for the Transportation &amp; Aviation department in [[Zuhair Fayez Partnership]] (ZFP) in [[Jeddah]], [[Saudi Arabia]]. Sharaf was the senior adviser to the Egyptian Minister of Transport in 1999 and the Senior Technical Adviser to the municipality of [[Al Ain]] in the [[UAE]] in 2003.&lt;ref name=&quot;purdue&quot;/&gt;

He served as Egyptian Minister of Transportation from July 13, 2004 to December 31, 2005. He resigned due to differences that cropped up between him and Prime Minister [[Ahmed Nazif]]. Nazif decided to put the Egypt Engineers Association under state control, a move that meant confiscation of union funds and property by the government.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://assafir.com/Article.aspx?EditionId=1788&amp;ChannelId=42000&amp;ArticleId=502&amp;Author=|title=Essam Sharaf's biography|date=6 March 2011 |accessdate=6 March 2011}} (in Arabic)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;factbox&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/03/03/us-egypt-sharaf-idUSTRE7222KE20110303 |title=Factbox: Essam Sharaf chosen as Egypt's new prime minister |work=Reuters |date=3 March 2011 |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/03/20113393825273567.html |title=Egypt's prime minister resigns |date=3 March 2011 |work=Al-Jazeera English |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sharaf later claimed that these events led to the [[Qalyoub rail accident]] in 2006.

Following his resignation, Sharaf returned to academia, accepting a post at Cairo University, where he remained a vocal critic of the [[Hosni Mubarak|Mubarak]] regime, particularly with respect to its handling of Egypt's public transportation infrastructure.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/6859/Egypt/Politics-/Essam-Sharaf-appointed-Egypts-new-PM.aspx |title=Essam Sharaf appointed Egypt's new PM |work=Ahram on-line |date=3 March 2011 |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this time he also served as an advisor to [[Transportation in Dubai|Dubai's Roads and Transport Authority]], and established the Egypt Scientific Society together with [[Mohamed ElBaradei]], [[Ahmed Zewail]] and other Egyptian scientists.

===2011 events===

[[File:Barack Obama and Essam Sharaf G8 France 2011.jpg|thumb|Sharaf with [[President of the United States]], [[Barack Obama]]]]
Sharaf was present and active at the [[Tahrir square]] protests during the [[2011 Egyptian revolution|2011 Revolution]], which endeared him to the leaders of the democracy movement and led them to suggest his name to the Military Council as a possible replacement for Prime Minister [[Ahmed Shafik]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://fr.euronews.net/depeches/772863-egypte-demission-du-premier-ministre-ahmad-chafic/ |title=Egypte: le Premier ministre remplacé, satisfaction des opposants |work=Euronews |language=French |date=3 March 2011 |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was asked by [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces|Egypt's governing military council]] to form a government on 3 March 2011, following Shafik's resignation.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbcshafik&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12634117 |title=Egypt's prime minister Ahmed Shafiq resigns |date=3 March 2011 |work=BBC News |accessdate=3 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/04/world/middleeast/04egypt.html |title=Bowing to opposition, Egypt premier resigns |work=The New York Times |date=3 March 2011 |accessdate=3 March 2011 |first=Neil |last=MacFarquhar}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 March, he addressed crowds of pro-democracy activists at Tahrir Square shortly after Friday prayers, an unusual move for an Egyptian politician.&lt;ref name=&quot;hindustan&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.hindustantimes.com/New-PM-addresses-crowds-in-Tahrir-Square/Article1-669481.aspx|title = New Egypt PM addresses crowds in Tahrir Square|work = Hindustan Times|date = 4 March 2011|accessdate = 4 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sharaf appeared on stage with [[Mohamed Beltagy]], a [[Muslim Brotherhood]] leader. In his speech he said &quot;I draw my legitimacy from you&quot; and reiterated his commitment to democratic transition, but pleaded for patience. It is noted that he is the first Egyptian prime minister to give a monthly State-of-the-Union address (since Aziz Sedki 1972-1973).&lt;ref name=&quot;hindustan&quot;/&gt;

==Premiership==
Although, Dr. Essam Sharaf was suggested for the premiership by the crowds in Tahrir square, by the end of his term it was largely viewed as anti-revolutionary. 
During the first couple of months, he removed some very unpopular members of his cabinet, including Foreign Minister [[Ahmed AbulGheit]], dissolved the unpopular and corrupt local &amp; municipal councils, and enacted a series of decisions and policies that were met with fanfare. Even on the personal level, he was a media and street darling. He was even pictured with egyptians eating the cheap Egyptian national dish &quot;Fuul&quot; (fava beans) in a simple restaurant with his family, his son paid a traffic ticket rather than evading it as he could have, and other similar stories of a simple and humble demeanor flooded the social networks and street talk.
He was later blamed for failure to properly address a number of incidents that are crucial to national security such as the worsening security issues, reforming the security apparatus, sectarian violence, solving workers' pay grievances or reforming corrupt national media. His government had mandated a number of laws that were controversial, such as Anti-assembly and Anti-strike laws. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://egyptelections.carnegieendowment.org/2011/10/06/essam-sharaf|title = Egypt Transition|work = Carnegie|date = 6 October 2011|accessdate = 6 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cabinet===

During the first formation of the cabinet, he removed some very unpopular members of his cabinet, including Foreign Minister [[Ahmed AbulGheit]], inducted many of figures who were traditionally in the opposition during the Mubarak Era, such as minister of tourism [[Mounir Fakhry Abdel Nour]] and minister of Social Solidarity and Justice, [[Gouda Abdel Khalek]] but retaining many ministers of the last cabinet such as [[Hassan Younes]], minister of Electricity and Power, Fayza AboulNaga, Minister of Planning and International Cooperation.

Under the pressure of sit-ins in Tahrir Square calling for speedier reforms, he was forced to shuffle his cabinet accepting as many as four resignation from ministers associated with the pre-revolution era, including his deputy renowned lawmaker, Dr. [[Yehia El-Gamal]]. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2011/07/201171792956867508.html|title = Cabinet Reshuffle|work = AlJazeera|date = 17 July  2011|accessdate = 17 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Sharaf appointed veteran economist [[Hazem Beblawi]] and [[Ali El-Selmy]], a leader of the liberal Wafd party, as deputy prime ministers. Beblawi, a former undersecretary of the UN's Economic and Social Commission for Western Asia, was assigned the economic policy in the new cabinet, while ElSelmy was assigned the country's &quot;democratic transition&quot;.

===Executive Power Struggle===
As time progressed, it became apparent that full power resides in the [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces]] (SCAF). It had always been the head of state who controlled Egyptian politics, rather than the head of government. Sharaf's cabinet was laden with remnants of the Mubarak era, ministers he was still incapable of moving without SCAF support. 
As the transitional period appeared to expand, the demands became even more aggressive and he was accused from not doing enough to being inactive and complacent and even to the point of being anti-revolution. The transitional government and the SCAF were neither intended as a true wide-scale legislative body, nor was it imbued with the popular mandate to enact macroeconomic and major political &quot;decisions&quot; and &quot;policy making,&quot; beyond the deconstruction of the Mubarak State, managing the country during the transition while restoring security on the streets, and working on establishing the constitution and/or government that would lead Egypt into it's Second Republic. But instead, Sharaf and SCAF engaged in debates and policy-making on far reaching matters such as the minimum wage, progressive taxation and even recently somewhat discussing the terms of Camp David Accords, not with the acceptable purpose of stimulating discussion for future governments, but for the actual sake of immediate legislating. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/columnists/essam-sharaf-our-man-on-the-inside-part-1.html|title = Egypt PM|work = Daily News Egypt|date = 10 October 2011|accessdate = 10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Additionally, as reports came out that the SCAF had refused the resignation of unpopular ministers in the cabinet, including Sharaf himself as many as three times, he was viewed as more of a ceremonial capacity rather than having any executive power and acted solely on SCAF's mandates.

===Policy Reform===
====Security Reform====
Sharaf's greatest problem appeared to be reforming the country's security apparatus, which appeared to be more complex of a task that will require more time than what was demanded by the people. Although, he removed as many as 300 high-ranking officers, his greatest challenge was to dismantle the notorious and deeply entrenched State Security apparatus. But activists later claimed that same tactics were used against them and claimed that the only change was its name to “National Security”.

====Media Reform====
Although initially abolishing the Ministry of Media in his first cabinet, he appointed a new minister to reform the corrupt and the largely controlled state-media. 
====Social Reform====

===Sectarian Violence===
During his term, a number of sectarian incidents have flared up and he was largely seen as unable to act accordingly.  A number of churches were burnt down, including a major incident in a Cairo neighborhood in May 2011, [[Imbaba]] over what was later revealed as the kidnapping of a Christian woman who had left her Christian husband and embraced Islam and married a Muslim man. It was told that she was held against her will and her Muslim husband had gathered a number of other men and went to the church demanding her release. The situation escalated into gunshots and later into the burning of the church. &lt;BR&gt;

During violence that erupted in October 2011 near the National TV Building, known as the Maspiro Incident, he failed to deal with the demonstrations that left at least 24 dead. Prior to the incident, there were protests in Cairo against an attack on a church in Aswan province a week earlier. It was later revealed by a member of his advisory committee who had resigned after the incident, that it was suggested to him to deal with the grievances put forward by Egyptian Copts as well as human rights and civil liberties activists to prevent escalation, which included sacking the Aswan governor and putting the attackers to trial.
During the incident, the National TV was blamed to incite the public against the Coptic community even to the point of imploring “good” citizens to &quot;save&quot; the security forces against the violent “Coptic” demonstrators. The protest which began as a unity march by largely coptic protesters and some muslims, turned into full scale riots. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-15235636|title = Sectarian Violence|work = BBC News|date = 10 October 2011|accessdate = 10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Unamendable Constitution Articles Draft Law===
During the final two months of his term, he along with his deputy, Dr. [[Ali ElSelmy]] came under fire from almost all of the political forces due to a law draft that provides a framework for the much anticipated constitution, aiming at preserving civil liberties and a democratic form of government. The articles in the paper were to be binding in the drafting of the constitution as [[entrenched clauses]], that cannot be amended. The drafted paper was controversial for two different sets of reasons for the different political parties; For the right-wing Islamist parties, they feared for relinquishing any control of the powers of the next parliament including full power for forming the drafting convention who will write up the constitution, in addition to giving the army the power to &quot;preserve the country's form of democracy&quot;, which was too vague for the Islamist parties and appeared as opening the way for the power of the army to legally oust an elected parliament or government if its tendencies didn't meet the army's approval. As for the liberal and left-wing parties who were mostly content with the army's proposed new role, had other fears that the army is placing itself outside of the parliament's reach by giving itself full autonomy over the military budget, barring its military sales and deals from elected officials and even mandating the power of declaring war by the army's military council rather than the parliament.
A final decision on the drafted law is yet to be taken, as the political appear divided over their stances, and despite outcries, Dr ElSelmy has stated that the document remains on the table.

===Revolution Victims Incident===
After a massive demonstration in November 18, 2011, in Tahrir Square by mostly Islamist parties in refusal for what's been known to the media as the &quot;ElSelmy Document&quot;, families of those who died or injured in the course of violence of the police during the revolution decided to organize a sit-in in the square due to the lack of financial or moral support from the government provided to them. Some liberal and leftist movements have symbolically joined the sit-in.
The following day, the security forces attacked the protesters in an attempt to break up the sit-in. News and Images circulating through the social media showed the police attempt to be excessively violent. As more and more activists joined the protesters, violence erupted once again in the square.
For the following five days, the violence continued with images every day showing police shooting at protesters, usage of tear gas that had left at least 41 dead and as many as 1,000 injured with gunshot wounds or tear gas suffocation. Activists seemed surprised by the return of violence by the police forces and scores of citizens joined them in the streets by the images of the violence, which many have dubbed &quot;The true second revolution&quot;. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-15847140|title = Violent Clashes in Cairo|work = BBC News|date = 23 November 2011|accessdate = 23 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the outburst of the worst clashes violence since January, Sharaf again failed to address the problem directly and was unable to control or stop the aggression of security forces on the protesters. With the scores of dead and injured protesters, he along with the Minister of Interior appeared unable to diffuse the situation. In a weak attempt to calm the public, Sharaf turned to protesters asking them to leave the square to allow normality without addressing grievances that excessive force was used in breaking up the sit-in. With the inability to control the violence, the cabinet's failure to react and stop the violence by the police or convince the protesters to calm down. With the minister of interior, [[Mansour ElEssawi]] appearing on an interview on National Television saying that he'd relinquished control of the security forces to an army general for the last two days, and the ministry of culture, [[Emad Abu Ghazi]] resigning &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://english.youm7.com/News.asp?NewsID=348671&amp;SecID=97|title = Egyptian Minister of Culture resigns in protest|work = ElYoum 7|date = 20 November 2011|accessdate = 20 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;, it appeared that the cabinet was falling apart and this last outburst of violence was the final nail in Sharaf's premiership's coffin.

===Resignation===
Unable to withstand the pressure, he submitted his resignation to SCAF on November 21, 2011, just 6 days ahead of the much anticipated [[Egyptian parliamentary election, 2011–2012]]. The resignation was accepted the next day but his cabinet continued in a caretaker capacity until his successor, later revealed as Dr. [[Kamal Ganzouri]] was to be named. Officially, His last day as Prime minister was on December 2, 2011, when Ganzouri's cabinet negotiations were concluded.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/530246|title = Sharaf Officially Resigns|work = ElMasry ElYoum|date = 2 December 2011|accessdate = 2 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Political views==

Sharaf is noted for strongly opposing normalization of ties with [[Israel]]. He considers the resolution of the [[Israeli–Palestinian conflict]] to be a prerequisite to cooperation between the two states.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ahram&quot;/&gt;

==Awards==

* The State Encouragemental Prize in Engineering Sciences from the Academy of Scientific Research and Technology in 1987 and 1997
* First Class Medal of Excellence from the President of Egypt [[Hosni Mubarak]] in 1995 &lt;ref name=&quot;purdue&quot;/&gt;
* Cairo University Incentive Award for Scientific Excellence in Engineering in 1997 
* Egyptian State Prize in Engineering Sciences, 1997
* Excellence Award in Engineering from [[Purdue University]], America in 2005 &lt;ref name=&quot;purdue&quot;/&gt;
* Man of the Year Award ([[Rafiq Hariri]] Award), Beirut in 2006
* Fellow of the [[Chartered Institute of Logistics and Transport in the UK]] in 2007
* Certificate of Merit from the [[Cairo University]] in the Celebration of Scientists Day in 1988 and 1998 &lt;ref name=&quot;purdue&quot;/&gt;

==References==

{{Reflist}}

==External links==

* [http://english.ahram.org.eg/~/NewsContent/1/64/6892/Egypt/Politics-/Meet-Essam-Sharaf-Egypts-first-postrevolution-Prim.aspx Meet Essam Sharaf: Egypt's first post-revolution Prime Minister], Ahmed Elieba and Marwa Hussein, 3 March 2011
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-12668416 Profile: Egyptian Prime Minister Essam Sharaf], ''[[BBC News]]'', 7 March 2011
* [http://ikhwanweb.com/article.php?id=28148 Sharaf - the post revolution Minister], ''[[Ikhwanweb]]'', 4 March 2011
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/mar/04/egypts-new-prime-minister-tahrir-square Essam Sharaf, Egypt's new prime minister, rouses Tahrir Square crowds], Mark Tran, ''[[The Guardian]]'', 4 March 2011

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Ahmed Shafik]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Prime Minister of Egypt]]|years=2011}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Kamal Ganzouri]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{Sharaf Cabinet (Egypt)}}
{{EgyptPMs}}
{{Egyptian Revolution of 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              = Sharaf, Essam
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Egyptian engineer, politician
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 12 July 1952
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Giza, Egypt
| DATE OF DEATH     = 
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Sharaf, Essam}}

[[Category:1952 births]]
[[Category:Cairo University alumni]]
[[Category:Current national leaders]]
[[Category:Egyptian expatriates in the United States]]
[[Category:Government ministers of Egypt]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:National Democratic Party (Egypt) politicians]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Egypt]]
[[Category:Purdue University alumni]]

[[ar:عصام شرف]]
[[bg:Есам Шараф]]
[[cs:Essam Šaraf]]
[[de:Essam Sharaf]]
[[el:Εσάμ Σαράφ]]
[[eo:Essam Ŝaraf]]
[[fr:Essam Charaf]]
[[id:Essam Sharaf]]
[[it:Isam Sharaf]]
[[he:עיסאם שרף]]
[[jv:Essam Sharaf]]
[[arz:عصام شرف]]
[[ms:Essam Sharaf]]
[[nl:Essam Sharaf]]
[[no:Essam Sharaf]]
[[pl:Essam Szaraf]]
[[pt:Essam Sharaf]]
[[ru:Шараф, Эссам]]
[[sv:Essam Sharaf]]
[[ta:எசாம் சரஃப்]]
[[th:เอสซัม ชาราฟ]]
[[tr:İsam Şeref]]
[[uk:Ессам Шараф]]
[[yo:Essam Sharaf]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
