<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31078646" ns="0" title="Secularism in Egypt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{outdated|date=June 2011}}

Secularism in Egypt has had a very important role to play in both the history of Egypt and that of the Middle East.{{Citation needed|date=July 2008}} Egypt’s first experience of Secularism started with the British Occupation (1882–1952), the atmosphere which allowed the protection of debate.  In this environment pro-secularist intellectuals like Ya'qub Sarruf, Faris Nimr, Nicola Haddad whom sought political asylum from Ottoman Rule were able to publish their work.  This debate had then became a burning issue with the work of Egyptian Shaykh [[Ali abd al-Raziq]] (1888–1966), “''The most momentous document in the crucial intellectual and religious debate of modern Islamic history''”&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Fauzi Najjar, ''The debate on Islam and Secularism'', Arab Studies Quarterly; 1996, Vol. 18 Issue 2&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1919 Egypt had its first political secular entity called the ''Hizb 'Almani'' (Secular Party) this name was later changed to the [[Wafd party]]. It combined secular policies with a nationalist agenda and had the majority support in the following years against both the rule of the king and the British influence.  The Wafd party supported the allies during [[World War II]] and then proceeded to win the 1952 parliamentary elections, following these elections the prime minister was overthrown by the King leading to riots.  These riots precipitated a military coup after which all political parties were banned including the [[Wafd]] and the [[Muslim Brotherhood]].{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The government of [[Gamel Abdel Nasser]] was secularist-nationalist in nature which at the time gathers a great deal of support both in Egypt and other Arab states{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}.

Key elements of [[Nasserism]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.opendemocracy.net/conflict-middle_east_politics/egypt_mahfouz_4025.jsp Mahfouz's grave, Arab liberalism's deathbed | openDemocracy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;:

*Secularist/Nationalist dictatorship:  No religious or other political movements allowed to impact government.
*Modernization.
*Industrialization.
*Concentration on Arab values rather than Muslim values.

Following the death of Nasser, President [[Sadat]] (1970–1981) continued economic liberalization and maintained the government’s secularist policy{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, even going as far as signing peace agreements with Israel which was a first for any Middle Eastern country.   However, following further intensive clampdowns on political opposition, Sadat was assassinated and replaced by [[Hosni Mubarak]] who again faces the issue of keeping the Islamist support at bay whilst keeping his power base during increased pressure to be democratic.&lt;ref&gt;David Marquand and Ronald L. Nettler, ''Religion and democracy'', p 67&lt;/ref&gt;

Nowadays, most proponents of secularism emphasize the link between secularism and ‘national unity’ between [[Coptic Christians]] and [[Muslims]].

== See also ==

* [[Religion in Egypt]]
* [[Constitution of Egypt]]
* [[Islam in Egypt]]
* [[Christianity in Egypt]]
* [[Politics of Egypt]]
* [[Culture of Egypt]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{Africa topic|Secularism in}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Secularism In Egypt}}
[[Category:Politics of Egypt]]
[[Category:Secularism in Egypt]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
