<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3114607" ns="0" title="Balmoral, New Zealand"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox New Zealand suburbs
| name           = Balmoral
| image          = 
| caption1       = 
| city1          = Auckland City
| city2          =
| ward           = Albert-Eden-Roskill
| established    =
| area           =
| population     =
| popdate        =
| trainstations  =
| ferryterminals =
| airports       =
| hospitals      =
| north          = [[Kingsland, New Zealand|Kingsland]]
| northeast      = 
| east           = [[Mount Eden]]
| southeast      =
| south          = [[Mount Roskill, New Zealand|Mount Roskill]]
| southwest      = [[Sandringham, New Zealand|Sandringham]]
| west           = [[Saint Lukes, New Zealand|Saint Lukes]]
| northwest      =
| map            =
| caption2       =
}}

'''Balmoral''' (from {{lang-gd|Baile Mhoireil}}) is a [[suburb]] of [[Auckland]], [[New Zealand]] that is bordered by [[Mount Eden]], [[Epsom]], [[Mount Roskill, New Zealand|Mount Roskill]] and [[Sandringham, New Zealand|Sandringham]] and is located approximately 5&amp;nbsp;km from the centre of Auckland. It was named around the turn of the 20th century and derives its name from [[Balmoral Castle]], the Scottish country residence of the [[Royal family]]. Much of the housing in the area is from the 1920s and 1930s, often in the [[Californian Bungalow]] style. Balmoral was part of Mount Eden Borough Council which became a part of Auckland City in 1989. In November 2010, the area was included into the Albert-Eden-Roskill ward of the new [[Auckland Council]].

A distinctive feature is the numerous Asian restaurants that are located in the Balmoral shopping area and the surrounding Dominion Road intersection.  These restaurants have a reputation for producing great food at very reasonable prices. Auckland's historical version of Chinatown is on Queen Street opposite Myers Park but Balmoral is a solid contender for this title. There is also a [[KFC]] branch at the intersection.

The largest building in the Balmoral shops is the Capitol Picture Theatre, a cinema built in the neo-Greek style. During the 1980s it was one of Auckland's most popular art film venues, known as &quot;Charlie Greys&quot;. It is still a cinema, and after years of screening mainly [[Cinema of India|Indian films]], it has recently been refurbished and is now called the Capitol Cinema. 

The 1957 Mount Eden War Memorial Hall is located on Dominion Road near the intersection with Balmoral Road. In December 2010, [[Auckland Theatre Company]] moved into the lower ground floor of the Hall, refitting it to include their offices and two rehearsal spaces. Opposite it is Potter's Park, named after Frederick Potter, one of Balmoral's Victorian landowners who gifted a piece of land for the community. On the opposite side of Balmoral Road, there is an indoor sports centre.
==Education==
*'''Balmoral School''' has both primary and intermediate schooling on site and is almost 100 years old. It is a decile 9 school with 750 students.

*'''Maungawhau''' is a decile 10 primary school, almost 100 years old and has 640 students. The Maungawhau school fair is an annual event that is enjoyed by the whole neighbourhood.

* '''Balmoral Seventh-day Adventist School''' is a coeducational integrated full primary (years 1-8) school run by the Seventh-day Adventist church. It has a roll of 38 and a [[Socio-Economic Decile|decile rating]] of 5&lt;ref&gt;{{TKI|4100|Balmoral Seventh-day Adventist School}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{coord|-36.883|174.748|region:NZ-AUK_type:city|display=title}}

The local secondary schools are [[Mount Albert Grammar School]], [[Marist College, New Zealand|Marist College]], [[Auckland Grammar School]] and [[St Peter's College, Auckland|St Peter's College]].

==References==
{{reflist}}
==External links==
* [http://balmoral.spdwebministry.org/ Balmoral Seventh-day Adventist School]
[[Category:Suburbs of Auckland]]

{{Auckland-geo-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
