<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31153" ns="0" title="The Princess Bride (film)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = The Princess Bride
| image          = Princess bride.jpg
| caption        = Theatrical release poster
| director       = [[Rob Reiner]]
| producer       = {{Plainlist|
*Rob Reiner
*[[Andrew Scheinman]]
*[[Norman Lear]]
}}
| based on       = {{Based on|''[[The Princess Bride]]''|William Goldman}}
| writer         = [[William Goldman]]
| starring       = {{Plainlist|
*[[Cary Elwes]]
*[[Robin Wright (actress)|Robin Wright]]
*[[Mandy Patinkin]]
*[[Chris Sarandon]]
*[[André the Giant]]
*[[Christopher Guest]]
*[[Fred Savage]]
*[[Wallace Shawn]]
*[[Billy Crystal]]
*[[Carol Kane]]
}}
| narrator       = [[Peter Falk]]
| music          = [[Mark Knopfler]]
| cinematography = [[Adrian Biddle]]
| editing        = [[Robert Leighton (film editor)|Robert Leighton]]
| studio         =  ACT III Communications
| distributor    = {{Plainlist|
*[[20th Century Fox]] (US Theatrical)
*[[Vestron Pictures]] (International)
*[[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM Studios]] (VHS/DVD)
}}
| released       = {{Film date|1987|9|25}}
| runtime        = 98 minutes
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $16 million
| gross          = $30,857,814
}}
'''''The Princess Bride''''' is a 1987 American film based on the 1973 [[The Princess Bride|novel of the same name]] by [[William Goldman]], combining [[comedy film|comedy]], [[adventure film|adventure]], [[romance film|romance]], and [[fantasy film|fantasy]]. The film was directed by [[Rob Reiner]] from a screenplay by Goldman. The story is presented in the film as a book being read by a grandfather ([[Peter Falk]]) to his sick grandson ([[Fred Savage]]), thus effectively preserving the novel's narrative style. This film is number 50 on [[Bravo (US TV channel)|Bravo]]'s &quot;100 Funniest Movies,&quot; number 88 on The [[American Film Institute]]'s (AFI) &quot;[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Passions]]&quot; list of the 100 greatest film love stories, and 46 in [[Channel 4]]'s 50 Greatest Comedy Films list.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=50 Greatest Comedy Films | url=http://www.channel4.com/programmes/50-greatest-comedy-films | date=27 January 2010 | work=Channel4.com | publisher=Channel 4 | accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The film is heralded as a [[cult classic]] &lt;ref name=&quot;http://www.filmjerk.com/news/article.php?id_new=489&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.filmjerk.com/news/article.php?id_new=489 | title=&quot;The Princess Bride&quot; becomes part of the Midnight Madness at the Rialto | accessdate=October 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Plot==
The film is an enactment of the following story read by a sick boy's ([[Fred Savage]]) grandfather ([[Peter Falk]])as the boy sits in bed listening, [[frame story|framed]] and occasionally interrupted by scenes of the reading.

A beautiful young woman named Buttercup ([[Robin Wright]]) lives on a farm in the fictional country of Florin. Whenever she gives her farmhand Westley ([[Cary Elwes]]) an order, he answers &quot;as you wish,&quot; and happily complies. Eventually she realizes he loves her and admits her love for him. Westley leaves to seek his fortune so they can marry, but his ship is attacked by the [[Dread Pirate Roberts]], who has a reputation for never leaving anyone alive.

Five years later, believing Westley dead, Buttercup reluctantly agrees to marry [[Prince Humperdinck]] ([[Chris Sarandon]]), heir to the throne of Florin. Before the wedding, she is kidnapped by three outlaws: an extremely short [[Sicily|Sicilian]] boss named Vizzini ([[Wallace Shawn]]), a gigantic wrestler from [[Greenland]] named Fezzik ([[André the Giant]]), and a [[Spanish people|Spanish]] [[fencing]] master named [[Inigo Montoya]] ([[Mandy Patinkin]]), who seeks revenge against the [[polydactyly|six-fingered man]] who killed his father. The outlaws are pursued by Prince Humperdinck with a complement of soldiers, and also by a masked man in black.

The man in black catches up to the outlaws at the top of the [[Cliffs of Moher|Cliffs of Insanity]], where he defeats Inigo in a duel and knocks him unconscious, chokes Fezzik until he blacks out, and kills Vizzini by tricking him into drinking poison.  When he tells Buttercup he is Roberts, she becomes enraged at him for killing Westley and shoves him into a gorge after telling him that he should die too, but she realizes he is Westley himself when he replies &quot;As you wish!&quot; She dives into the gorge after him, and they flee through the dangerous Fire Swamp where they navigate the [[Giant_rat#Other_fictional_giant_rats|R.O.U.S. (Rodents of Unusual Size)]] and lightning sand. When they are captured on the other side by Humperdinck and his [[sadomasochism|sadistic]] six-fingered [[vizier]] Count Rugen ([[Christopher Guest]]), Buttercup agrees to return with Humperdinck in exchange for Westley's release, but Humperdinck secretly has Rugen imprison and torture Westley.

When Buttercup expresses unhappiness at marrying Humperdinck, he promises to search for Westley, but his real plan is to start a war with the neighboring country of Guilder by killing Buttercup and framing them for her death. Buttercup taunts Humperdinck after learning that he never tried to find Westley. Enraged, Humperdinck tortures Westley. Meanwhile, Inigo and Fezzik meet when Humperdinck orders a gang of goons to arrest the thieves in a nearby forest, and Fezzik informs Inigo of Rugen. Inigo decides that they need Westley's help to get into the castle, and when he hears cries of anguish, he realizes they must be from Westley. Inigo and Fezzik find Westley dead, but they bring him to a miracle man named Miracle Max ([[Billy Crystal]]), who explains that Westley is &quot;only mostly dead&quot; and revives him to a state of heavy [[paralysis]].

After Westley, Inigo, and Fezzik invade the castle, Humperdinck orders the wedding ceremony shortened and Iñigo finds and duels Rugen, repeatedly reciting his greeting of vengeance: &quot;Hello, my name is Inigo Montoya. You killed my father. Prepare to die&quot;. The duel ends with a severly wounded Inigo killing Rugen.
Westley finds Buttercup, who is about to commit [[suicide]], and assures her that her marriage is invalid because she never said &quot;I do.&quot; Still partly paralyzed, he bluffs his way out of a duel with Humperdinck, then rides away with Buttercup, Inigo, and Fezzik.

Back in the boy's bedroom, the boy asks his grandfather to read the story to him again the next day, to which the grandfather replies, &quot;As you wish.&quot;

==Cast==
* [[Cary Elwes]] as Westley, a farmboy and Buttercup's love interest. Reiner cast Elwes after seeing him in ''[[Lady Jane (film)|Lady Jane]]'' &lt;ref name=&quot;http://insidemovies.ew.com/2011/10/14/princess-bride-oral-history/2/&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://insidemovies.ew.com/2011/10/14/princess-bride-oral-history/2/ | title='The Princess Bride': The cast and director share the story behind the beloved fantasy | accessdate=November 01, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.
* [[Mandy Patinkin]] as [[Inigo Montoya]], a Spaniard who has trained in fencing for twenty years to the point of fighting left-handed so as to prolong his duels. He seeks revenge upon Count Rugen for the murder of his father.
* [[Robin Wright]] as Buttercup, Princess of Florin and Westley's love interest.
* [[Chris Sarandon]] as [[Prince Humperdinck]], heir to the throne of Florin, who becomes engaged to Buttercup so that he can murder her to start a war with Guilder.
* [[Christopher Guest]] as [[Count Rugen|Count Tyrone Rugen]], the vizier of Prince Humperdinck, who killed Inigo Montoya's father twenty years ago. He has [[polydactyly|six fingers on his right hand]].
* [[André the Giant]] as Fezzik, a giant and companion of Inigo.
* [[Wallace Shawn]] as Vizzini, a self-described criminal genius of  [[Sicily|Sicilian]] origin and the employer of Inigo and Fezzik.  He is hired by Prince Humperdinck to capture and dispose of Buttercup.
* [[Peter Falk]] as The Grandfather/Narrator, the grandfather of a sick boy.
* [[Fred Savage]] as The Grandson, a young boy who is sick.
* [[Billy Crystal]] as Miracle Max, the last miracle worker in Florin, who was fired by Humperdinck many years ago, and saves Westley's life to get revenge on the Prince.
* [[Carol Kane]] as Valerie, Max's wife.
* [[Peter Cook]] as The Impressive Clergyman, the clergyman at Humperdinck and Buttercup's wedding; he [[Rhotacism|cannot pronounce &quot;R&quot;s or &quot;L&quot;s]].
* [[Mel Smith]] as The Albino, assistant torturer to Count Rugen.
* Anne Dyson as The Queen, mother of Prince Humperdinck.
* [[Margery Mason]] as The Ancient Booer, a woman in Buttercup's dreams.
* Malcolm Storry as Yellin, a soldier of Florin.
* [[Willoughby Gray]] as The King, father of Prince Humperdinck.
* [[Betsy Brantley]] as The Mother.

==Production==
[[File:Cliffs of Moher, looking north.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The Cliffs of Insanity are actually the [[Cliffs of Moher]] in [[County Clare]], [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]].]]
The film was shot in various locations in [[England]] and [[Republic of Ireland|Ireland]]:
* [[Burnham Beeches]], [[Buckinghamshire]], England
* [[Castleton, Derbyshire|Castleton]], [[Derbyshire]], England
* [[Cliffs of Moher]], [[County Clare]], Ireland (for the Cliffs of Insanity)
* [[Haddon Hall]], [[Bakewell]], Derbyshire, England

Although Cary Elwes and Mandy Patinkin did learn to [[fencing|fence]] (both left- and right-handed) for the film (reportedly spending all their free time during the production practicing with fencing instructor [[Bob Anderson (fencer)|Bob Anderson]] and with each other), the actual swordfight scene between them was filmed using two separate, mirror-imaged, sets, allowing the illusion that they were equally skilled with either hand.  They actually performed all of the fencing in the swordfight scene; however, stunt doubles were used for the two somersaults.&lt;ref&gt;Reiner, Rob. ''The Princess Bride''. DVD Audio Commentary.  Directed by Rob Reiner. 1987; Santa Monica, CA: MGM Home Entertainment, 2001. ''(see Ch. 06, time 17:45)''&lt;/ref&gt; This amount of time spent practicing came in handy for Elwes, who later starred—and used his fencing skills—in the film ''[[Glory (1989 film)|Glory]]'' and in the [[Mel Brooks]] film ''[[Robin Hood: Men In Tights]]'', notably against [[Roger Rees]], and even going so far as to call out, 'Parry, parry, thrust, thrust—good!'

[[André the Giant]] had undergone major back surgery prior to filming, and despite his great size, could not support the weight of the much lighter Cary Elwes or Robin Wright for a scene at the end of the film. For the wrestling scene, when Elwes was pretending to hang on André's back, he was actually walking on a series of ramps below the camera during close-ups. For the wide shots, a stunt double took the place of André; on close examination, it is apparent that the double is much smaller than André.&lt;ref&gt;Reiner, Rob. ''The Princess Bride''. DVD Audio Commentary. Directed by Rob Reiner.  1987; Santa Monica, CA: MGM Home Entertainment, 2001.  ''(see Ch. 08, time 25:40)''&lt;/ref&gt;

André the Giant had trouble with both the speed and clarity of his lines, prompting Patinkin to slap him in the face to get him to concentrate harder. In the first script reading, Patinkin slapped André in the face and screamed at him, &quot;Faster, Fezzik!&quot; It worked.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, William. ''The Princess Bride''. DVD Audio Commentary. Directed by Rob Reiner.  1987; Santa Monica, CA: MGM Home Entertainment, 2001.  ''(see time 1:02:00)''&lt;/ref&gt;

Billy Crystal's interactions with André the Giant later inspired Crystal to create the film ''[[My Giant]]''. {{cn|date-October 2011|date=October 2011}}

When Count Rugen hits Westley over the head, [[Cary Elwes]] told [[Christopher Guest]] to go ahead and hit him for real. Guest hit him hard enough to shut down production for a day while Elwes went to the hospital.

In the ''As You Wish'' documentary in the special features section of the DVD release, it is stated that one of the few injuries sustained during the making of the film was when Mandy Patinkin bruised a rib by trying not to laugh at [[Billy Crystal]] (Crystal was actually on camera).&lt;ref&gt;Reiner, Rob. ''The Princess Bride''. ''As You Wish'' Documentary. Directed by Rob Reiner. 1987; Santa Monica, CA: MGM Home Entertainment, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reception==
The film was initially a modest success,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title='The Princess Bride' Turns 20|journal=[[The Palm Beach Post]]|last=Gray Streeter|first=Leslie|date=2007-12-09|[w]as a modest hit[...]}}&lt;/ref&gt; grossing $30.8 million at the United States and Canada box office,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id=princessbride.htm|title=The Princess Bride (1987|work=[[Box Office Mojo]]|accessdate=2011-09-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; on a $16 million production budget.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Reiner's 'Princess' is charming|journal=[[USA Today]]|last=Clark|first=Mike|date=1987-09-25|quote=Despite a $16 million budget, [...]}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It received highly favorable reviews from some critics, including [[Roger Ebert]] and [[Gene Siskel]] who gave the film a &quot;two thumbs up&quot; rating on their [[television program]] ''[[At the Movies (1982–1990 TV series)|At the Movies]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bventertainment.go.com/tv/buenavista/atm/reviews.html?sec=1&amp;subsec=1737 |title='&amp;#39;At the Movies with Gene Siskel and Roger Ebert'&amp;#39; review |publisher=Bventertainment.go.com |date= |accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Roger Ebert]] also wrote a very favorable print review.&lt;ref&gt;Roger Ebert, [http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/19871009/REVIEWS/710090301/1023 The Princess Bride], ''[[Chicago Sun-Times]]'', October 9, 1987&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard Corliss]] of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' felt the film was fun for the whole family,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,965565,00.html &quot;Errol Flynn Meets Gunga Din THE PRINCESS BRIDE&quot;], Richard Corliss, ''Time'', September 21, 1987.&lt;/ref&gt; and later, ''Time'' listed the film as one of the &quot;Best of '87.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,966369,00.html &quot;Best of '87&quot;], ''Time'', January 4, 1988.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-theatrical release==
===Soundtrack===
{{main|The Princess Bride (album)}}
The original soundtack album was composed by [[Mark Knopfler]], and released by [[Warner Bros. Records]] in the [[United States]] and [[Vertigo Records]] internationally in November 1987. The album contains the song &quot;Storybook Love&quot;, performed by [[Willy DeVille]] and co-written with Mark Knopfler. It was nominated for an [[Academy Award for Best Original Song]] at the [[60th Academy Awards]].&lt;ref name=&quot;allmusic&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=|first=|title=The Princess Bride|url=http://www.allmusic.com/album/the-princess-bride-original-soundtrack-r84523 ''Allmusic''|accessdate=2011-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his auduio commentary of the film on the Special Edition DVD, director [[Rob Reiner]] said that only Mark Knopfler of [[Dire Straits]] could create a soundtrack to capture the film's quirky yet romantic nature. Reiner was an admirer of Knopfler's work but did not know him before working on the film. He sent the script to him hoping he would agree to score the film. Knopfler agreed on one condition: that somewhere in the film Reiner would include the {{USS|Coral Sea|CV-43}} baseball cap (modified to say USS Ooral Sea) he wore as Marty DiBergi in ''[[This is Spinal Tap]]''. Reiner was unable to produce the original cap, but did include a similar cap in the grandson's room. Later Knopfler said he was joking.

===Musical adaptation===
It was announced that [[Tony Award]]-winning composer [[Adam Guettel]] was working with William Goldman on a musical adaptation of ''The Princess Bride'' in 2006. The project was abandoned though, in February 2007 after Goldman reportedly demanded 75 percent of the author's share, even though Guettel was writing both the music and the lyrics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Riedel |first=Michael |url=http://www.nypost.com/seven/02162007/entertainment/theater/bride_not_to_be_theater_michael_riedel.htm |title='Bride' Not to Be While Broderick Balks at 'Producers' |publisher=New York Post |date=2007-02-16 |accessdate=2007-03-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some of Guettel's music for the production has since surfaced in concert performances and workshops.

===Rights issues===
The film was released theatrically by [[20th Century Fox]] in North America, and internationally by what was then [[Vestron Pictures]]. When it was first issued on home video, Fox lost all but the television rights, and to the present day, Fox remains the TV distributor. Domestically, the ancillary rights ended up changing hands and eventually became part of the Epic Productions package acquired by [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM]], so today it is the latter studio that is responsible for most rights. Interestingly, Fox today acts as distributor for the MGM video library.

What became [[Lions Gate]] still holds international rights to the film outside North America, with Fox acting as UK video distributor (inherited from [[Sony Pictures Home Entertainment]]).

===Home video history===
In North America, the film was released on [[VHS]] and [[laserdisc]] in 1988 by [[Nelson Entertainment]], the latter being a &quot;bare bones&quot; release in [[Matte (filmmaking)|unmatted full screen]]. [[The Criterion Collection]] released a matted widescreen version, bare bones version on laserdisc in 1989, supplementing it with [[liner notes]]. in 1997 they re-released the laserdisc as a &quot;[[Special Edition]]&quot;. This edition was [[widescreen]] and included an [[audio commentary]] by Rob Reiner, William Goldman, Andrew Scheinman, Billy Crystal, and Peter Falk; excerpts from the novel read by Rob Reiner; behind the scenes footage; a production scrapbook by unit photographer Clive Coote; design sketches by production designer Norman Garwood; and excerpts from the television series ''Morton and Hayes'', directed by Christopher Guest.

[[File:The princess bride 20th anniversary edition dvd.jpg|thumb|Cover of 20th Anniversary Edition]]
By 2000, [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM]] had acquired some rights to the film (as part of the aforementioned &quot;Epic Productions&quot; package) and released the film on VHS and [[DVD]]. The DVD release featured the soundtrack remastered in [[Dolby Digital|Dolby Digital 5.1]] with the film in wide and full screen versions, and included the original US [[theatrical trailer]]. The next year MGM re-released the film in another widescreen &quot;Special Edition&quot;, this time with two audio commentaries—one by Rob Reiner, the other by William Goldman—&quot;As You Wish&quot;, &quot;Promotional&quot;, and &quot;Making Of&quot; [[featurette]]s;{{Clarify|date=December 2010}} a &quot;Cary Elwes Video Diary&quot;; the US and UK theatrical trailers; four television spots; a photo gallery; and a collectible booklet. In 2006 MGM released a two-disc set with varying covers—the &quot;Dread Pirate&quot; and &quot;Buttercup&quot; editions. Each featured their respective character, but had had identical features: in addition to the features in the previous release were, the &quot;Dread Pirate Roberts: Greatest Legend of the Seven Seas&quot;, &quot;Love is Like a Storybook Story&quot;, and &quot;Miraculous Make Up&quot; featurettes, &quot;The Quotable Battle Of Wits&quot; game, and Fezzik's &quot;Guide To Florin&quot; booklet. Another year later, to commemorate the 20th anniversary of the film, MGM and [[20th Century Fox Home Entertainment]] released the film with flippable cover art featuring the title displayed in an [[ambigram]].  This DVD did not include any of the bonus features from the older editions, but had new short featurettes and a new game. A [[Blu-ray Disc]] was released on March 17, 2009, encoded in 5.1 [[DTS-HD Master Audio]]. Special features include two audio commentaries, the original theatrical trailer and eight featurettes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hometheaterforum.com/htf/ht-software-high-definition/282196-mgm-press-release-princess-bride-blu-ray.html MGM Press Rlease: The Princess Bride (Blu-ray)], Home Theater Forum, 2009-02-04.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, the film was released for download in the [[iTunes Store]] &lt;ref name=&quot;http://itunes.apple.com/ca/movie/the-princess-bride/id263952053&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://itunes.apple.com/ca/movie/the-princess-bride/id263952053 | title=Itunes - Princess Bride | accessdate=October 31, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

The film is also available in [[DVD region code|Region 2]] where it is published by [[Lions Gate]]. Its extras are the theatrical trailer and text filmographies.

=== Legacy ===
''The Princess Bride'' was not a huge box office success, but after its home release it became a cult classic. The film is one of the most quotable films of all time, with actor Wallace Shawn admitting he is approached on a daily basis with people saying &quot;inconceivable&quot;, with Elwes approached with &quot;as you wish&quot; &lt;ref name=&quot;http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/entertainment/2011/10/princess-bride-reunion-thanks-to-entertainment-weekly-magazine/&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/entertainment/2011/10/princess-bride-reunion-thanks-to-entertainment-weekly-magazine/ | title=‘Princess Bride’ Reunion, Thanks to Entertainment Weekly Magazine | accessdate=November 01, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

In 2000, readers of ''[[Total Film]]'' magazine voted ''The Princess Bride'' the 38th greatest comedy film of all time.  In 2006, William Goldman's screenplay was selected by the [[Writers Guild of America]] as the 84th best screenplay of all time. The film has a percentage of 96 on [[Rotten Tomatoes]], with a Cream of the Crop percentage of 86. The film was selected number 88 on The [[American Film Institute]]'s (AFI) &quot;[[AFI's 100 Years... 100 Passions]]&quot; listing the 100 greatest film love stories of all time. BBC Radio 5's resident film critic, [[Mark Kermode]], is a fan of the film, frequently considering it a model to which similar films aspire.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

;[[American Film Institute]] Lists
*[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Laughs]] - Nominated&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afi.com/Docs/100Years/laughs500.pdf AFI's 100 Years...100 Laughs Nominees]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Passions]] - #88
*[[AFI's 100 Years...100 Movie Quotes]]:
**&quot;Hello. My name is Inigo Montoya. You killed my father; Prepare to die!&quot; - Nominated&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afi.com/Docs/100Years/quotes400.pdf AFI's 100 Years...100 Movie Quotes Nominees]&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[AFI's 10 Top 10]] - Nominated Fantasy Film&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.afi.com/drop/ballot.pdf AFI's 10 Top 10 Ballot]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Licensing==
In 2008, PlayRoom Entertainment released ''The Princess Bride: Storming the Castle'', a board game based on the film.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/35524 The Princess Bride: Storming the Castle | Board Game | BoardGameGeek&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Film}}
{{Wikiquote}}
* {{Official website|http://www.princessbrideforever.com/}}
* {{IMDb title|0093779|The Princess Bride}}
* {{tcmdb title|87152|The Princess Bride}}
* {{Allmovie title|39218|The Princess Bride}}
* {{mojo title|princessbride|The Princess Bride}}
* {{Rotten-tomatoes|princess_bride|The Princess Bride}}
* {{metacritic film|the-princess-bride|The Princess Bride}}

{{Rob Reiner}}
{{The Princess Bride}}
{{Hugo Award for Best Dramatic Presentation 1981–2002}}
{{Saturn Award for Best Fantasy Film 1973–1990}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Princess Bride, The}}
[[Category:1987 films]]
[[Category:American films]]
[[Category:English-language films]]
[[Category:The Princess Bride]]
[[Category:20th Century Fox films]]
[[Category:1980s adventure films]]
[[Category:1980s comedy films]]
[[Category:1980s fantasy films]]
[[Category:1987 soundtracks]]
[[Category:American adventure comedy films]]
[[Category:American fantasy-comedy films]]
[[Category:American romantic fantasy films]]
[[Category:American satirical films]]
[[Category:Films based on fantasy novels]]
[[Category:Films based on works by William Goldman]]
[[Category:Films directed by Rob Reiner]]
[[Category:Films set in a fictional country]]
[[Category:Hugo Award Winners for Best Dramatic Presentation]]
[[Category:Mark Knopfler albums]]
[[Category:Pirate films]]
[[Category:Screenplays by William Goldman]]
[[Category:Vertigo Records albums]]
[[Category:Vestron Pictures films]]

[[cy:The Princess Bride (ffilm)]]
[[de:Die Braut des Prinzen]]
[[es:The Princess Bride]]
[[fr:Princess Bride (film)]]
[[gl:The Princess Bride (filme)]]
[[it:La storia fantastica]]
[[he:הנסיכה הקסומה (סרט)]]
[[nl:The Princess Bride (film)]]
[[ja:プリンセス・ブライド・ストーリー]]
[[no:Prinsessebruden (film)]]
[[nds:The Princess Bride (Film)]]
[[pl:Narzeczona dla księcia]]
[[ru:Принцесса-невеста]]
[[fi:Prinsessan ryöstö]]
[[sv:Bleka dödens minut (film)]]
[[tr:Prenses Gelin (film)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
