<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3116952" ns="0" title="John&#039;s Children"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox musical artist &lt;!-- See Wikipedia:WikiProject Musicians --&gt;
| name = John's Children
| image = 
| caption = 
| image_size = 
| background = group_or_band
| birth_name =
| alias =
| origin = [[Leatherhead]], England
| instrument =
| genre = Rock, [[psychedelic rock]]
| occupation =
| years_active = 1966–1968&lt;br/&gt;2006–present
| label = UK: [[Columbia Records|Columbia (EMI)]], [[Track Records|Track]]&lt;br/&gt;USA: [[White Whale Records|White Whale]]&lt;br/&gt;Germany, Greece, Australia, Japan: [[Polydor Records|Polydor]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Acid Jazz Records|Acid Jazz]] (''Black &amp; White'' album)
| associated_acts = [[Jet (UK band)|Jet]], [[Radio Stars]], [[The Who]]
| website = [http://www.johnschildren.co.uk/ johnschildren.co.uk]
| current_members = [[Andy Ellison]]&lt;br/&gt;John Hewlett&lt;br/&gt;Trevor White
| past_members = [[Chris Townson]]&lt;br/&gt;Geoff McClelland&lt;br/&gt;[[Marc Bolan]]&lt;br/&gt;Chris Colville&lt;br/&gt; [[Martin Gordon]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Boz Boorer]]

}}

'''John's Children''' were a 1960s [[pop art]]/[[Mod (subculture)|mod]] rock band from [[Leatherhead]], England that briefly featured future [[T. Rex (band)|T. Rex]] frontman [[Marc Bolan]]. John's Children were known for their outrageous live performances and were booted off a tour with [[The Who]] in Germany in 1967 when they upstaged the headliners. Their 1967 single &quot;[[Desdemona (Marc Bolan song)|Desdemona]]&quot;, a Bolan composition, was banned by the [[BBC]] because of the controversial lyric, &quot;Lift up your skirt and fly&quot;. Their US record label delayed the release their album, ''[[Orgasm (John's Children album)|Orgasm]]'' for four years from its recording date due to objections from [[Daughters of the American Revolution]].

John's Children were active for less than two years and were not very successful commercially, having released only six singles and one album. But they had a big influence on [[punk rock]] and are seen by some as the precursors of [[glam rock]]. In retrospect the band has been praised for the impact they had, and their singles have become amongst the most sought-after British 1960s rock collectables.

==Biography==
===Inception===
In 1965 in [[Great Bookham]], near [[Leatherhead]], England, drummer [[Chris Townson]] and singer [[Andy Ellison]] formed a band called the Clockwork Onions, which later became The Few, and then The Silence.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; The Silence consisted of Townson and Ellison, with Geoff McClelland on guitar and John Hewlett on bass guitar.&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt; While performing in France in mid-1966, Townson met [[The Yardbirds]]'s manager [[Simon Napier-Bell]] and invited him to come and see The Silence. Napier-Bell described them as &quot;positively the worst group I'd ever seen&quot;, but still agreed to manage them.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; He changed their name to John's Children, dressed them up in white stage outfits and encouraged them to be outrageous to attract the attention of the press.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; He named the band after its bass player because he played so badly and Napier-Bell wanted to be sure the band would not fire him.&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt; Townson described their live acts as &quot;theatre&quot;, &quot;anarchy&quot; and &quot;deconstruction&quot;.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; They fought each other on stage, used fake blood and feathers, and they [[Instrument destruction|trashed their instruments]]. In general the band &quot;whip[ped] the audience into a frenzy&quot;.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; They also often posed naked for the press, with flowers covering their private parts.&lt;ref name=Times/&gt;&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; 

Napier-Bell signed John's Children to The Yardbirds's record label, [[Columbia Records]], an [[EMI]] subsidiary,&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt; and they released their first single, &quot;Smashed Blocked/Strange Affair&quot; (released as &quot;The Love I Thought I'd Found/Strange Affair&quot; in the UK) in late-1966. Napier-Bell co-wrote &quot;Smashed Blocked&quot; with Hewlett, but because of his lack of confidence in the band's musical abilities, Napier-Bell used [[session musician]]s on the recording.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; [[Allmusic]] described the single as a &quot;disorienting piece of musical mayhem&quot;, but said it was &quot;one of the first overtly psychedelic singles&quot;.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; To Napier-Bell's surprise &quot;Smashed Blocked/Strange Affair&quot; broke into the bottom of the US [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard Hot'' 100]] and reached local top ten charts in Florida and California. In early-1967 they released their second single, &quot;Just What You Want – Just What You'll Get/But You're Mine&quot;, which also featured session musicians, plus a guitar solo from The Yardbirds's [[Jeff Beck]] on the B-side. This one made it to the British Top 40.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; 

The band's third single, &quot;Not the Sort of Girl (You'd Like to Take to Bed)&quot; was rejected outright by their UK label,&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; which prompted the band to switch to [[Track Records]], publishers of artists like [[The Jimi Hendrix Experience]] and [[The Who]].&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt; In the meantime, their US label, [[White Whale Records]] asked for an album, and Napier-Bell and the group obliged, producing ''[[Orgasm (John's Children album)|Orgasm]]''. This was a fake live album they recorded in the studio with [[Overdubbing|overdubbed]] screams taken from [[The Beatles]]'s ''[[A Hard Day's Night (film)|A Hard Day's Night]]'' soundtrack.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt;&lt;ref name=Unterberger-SB/&gt;&lt;ref name=TechWebSound/&gt; It was Napier-Bell's idea to give the album a &quot;live&quot; feel to make it seem like the band was very popular in England.&lt;ref name=TechWebSound/&gt; But White Whale rejected ''Orgasm'' because of its title and pressure from [[Daughters of the American Revolution]].&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; The label did, however, release it four years later in 1971.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; 

In March 1967 Napier-Bell replaced guitarist McClelland with [[Marc Bolan]], another of his clients.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; Napier-Bell had Bolan, an acoustic guitarist, play electric guitar, and take on the role of 
the band's singer/songwriter.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt;&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; Bolan composed and sang on the band's next single, &quot;[[Desdemona (Marc Bolan song)|Desdemona]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=Faber/&gt; which was banned by the [[BBC]] because of the controversial lyric, &quot;Lift up your skirt and fly&quot;.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; He also featured on several unreleased songs and BBC radio sessions, and contributed to the band's antics by whipping the stage with a chain.

===The Who===
In April 1967 Napier-Bell arranged for John's Children to tour Germany with one of Britain's premier rock groups, [[The Who]] as the latter's [[opening act|supporting act]].&lt;ref name=Times/&gt;&lt;ref name=RollingStone/&gt; The Who were notorious for their own wild stage performances, which included [[Instrument destruction|smashing their instruments]].&lt;ref name=Eder/&gt; John's Children pulled out all the stops and upstaged The Who with performances that included Bolan whipping his guitar with a chain, Townson attacking his drums, Ellison and Hewlett pretending to fight each other, and Ellison ripping open pillows and diving into the audience.&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt;&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; In [[Düsseldorf]] they caused a riot at the venue, and in [[Ludwigshafen]] they nearly prevented The Who from playing.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; The Who were not happy and John's Children were sent home mid-tour. According to [[Pete Townshend]], they were &quot;too loud and violent&quot;.&lt;ref name=Times/&gt; 

Notwithstanding John's Children's antics in Germany, Townson was later asked to replace [[Keith Moon]] on drums near the end of The Who's UK tour in June that year after Moon had injured himself demolishing his drum kit on stage.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt;&lt;ref name=Times/&gt; With no time for rehearsal, Townson performed with The Who for five days, and did it so well, &quot;most of the audience didn't realise it wasn't Keith&quot;.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; But The Who got their revenge on Townson for John's Children's &quot;reckless behaviour&quot; on the German tour: at the end of his last gig with them, they &quot;blew [him] off the stage&quot; with [[flash powder]].&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren/&gt;

===Breakup and legacy===
John's Children played at [[The 14 Hour Technicolour Dream]] concert at the [[Alexandra Palace]] in London on 29 April 1967.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; Bolan left in June 1967, after only four months with the band, following disagreements with the way Napier-Bell was producing the band's next single, &quot;A Midsummer Night's Scene&quot;. The single was never released, but in its place the B-side of &quot;[[Desdemona (Marc Bolan song)|Desdemona]]&quot;, &quot;Remember Thomas à Becket&quot; was re-recorded with new lyrics and released as &quot;Come and Play with Me in the Garden&quot;.&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; Bolan went on to form [[glam rock]] band [[T. Rex (band)|Tyrannosaurus Rex]] (later T. Rex).

After Bolan left, Townson switched to guitar and former roadie Chris Colville took over on drums. John's Children recorded another single, &quot;Go Go Girl&quot;, a Bolan composition he later recorded with Tyrannosaurus Rex as &quot;Mustang Ford&quot;. John's Children also performed Bolan's &quot;Mustang Ford&quot; version of the song.&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; The band released one more single, &quot;It's Been a Long Time&quot; (issued as an Andy Ellison solo single) and then embarked on a &quot;disastrous&quot; tour of Germany.&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; Their last performance was at the [[Star-Club]] in Hamburg, Germany (substituting for the [[Bee Gees]]), after which they split up in 1968.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt;&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; Ellison went on to make several solo singles.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; before resurfacing in [[Jet (UK band)|Jet]] in 1974, along with drummer Chris Townson. Jet metamorphosed into [[Radio Stars]] in the mid-Seventies. 

John's Children reformed in the mid-Nineties with [[Boz Boorer]] on guitar and former [[Radio Stars (band)|Radio Stars]] member [[Martin Gordon]] on bass, performing gigs in the UK, Italy, Spain and the USA. In 1999, Ellison, Townson and Gordon were joined by guitarists Trevor White (a former member of [[Sparks (band)|Sparks]]) and Ian Macleod ([[Radio Stars (band)|Radio Stars]]) to perform a selection of John's Children, Jet and Radio Stars repertoire, released as &quot;[http://www.martingordon.de/herring.html Music for the Herd of Herring]&quot; and recorded in the UK, the Netherlands and Germany.

With Gordon and Boorer, John's Children performed at the [[Steve Marriott]] Memorial Event at the [[London Astoria]] on 20 April 2001.&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; Ellison, Hewlett and Townson plus guitarist Trevor White officially reformed John's Children in June 2006 and have been performing and recording occasionally ever since.&lt;ref name=JohnsChildren/&gt; Townson died in February 2008.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; Several compilation albums of John's Children's music have been issued retrospectively, some of which include previously unreleased material. An account of Napier-Bell's time with John's Children and Bolan is given in his 2005 book ''You Don't Have To Say You Love Me''.

==Reception and influence==
Music critic [[Richie Unterberger]] at [[Allmusic]] described John's Children as an &quot;interesting, if minor, blip on the British [[Mod (subculture)|mod]] and [[Psychedelic music|psychedelic]] scene&quot;, but added that because they were better known for their &quot;flamboyant image and antics&quot; rather than the music they made, they &quot;are perhaps accorded more reverence by '60s collectors and aficionados than they deserve&quot;.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; In a [[Chris Townson]] [[obituary]] published in ''[[The Independent]]'' in February 2008, Pierre Perrone wrote that John's Children's live performances had &quot;raw energy and power chords worthy of [[The Who]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; [[Perfect Sound Forever (magazine)|Perfect Sound Forever]] columnist Richard Mason said that John's Children &quot;made a fine upstanding racket. Guitars and drums are thrashed within an inch of their lives; vocals are intoned with, one might hazard a guess, a grin on the face of the protagonist.&quot;&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; Their lyrics were &quot;generally disrespectful and crazed&quot; and their music was &quot;eccentric, loud, irreverent and to the point&quot;.&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; Mason believes that musically the band was not as bad as generally perceived: &quot;They sound as if they can actually play but would rather enjoy themselves, which is no mean feat.&quot;&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; He said that they came from an era that is &quot;for the most part misunderstood, either cloyingly romanticised or short-sightedly vilified&quot;, and today the story of John's Children is &quot;relegated to a condescending historical footnote&quot;.&lt;ref name=Mason/&gt; 

Despite having little success, John's Children were a heavy influence on [[punk rock]], with their shambolic stage presentation and headline-grabbing controversies. Allmusic called them &quot;pre-glam rockers of sorts&quot;,&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; and ''The Illustrated New Musical Express Encyclopedia of Rock'' said that John's Children &quot;have claims to being [the] first-ever [[glam rock]] band&quot;.&lt;ref name=Logan/&gt; Notwithstanding their brief tenure in the spotlight, the group went on to achieve a cult following that persists today.&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; Their handful of singles have become amongst the most sought-after British 1960s rock collectables.&lt;ref name=Unterberger/&gt; A copy of their unreleased single, &quot;A Midsummer Night's Scene&quot; was auctioned in 2002 for [[pound sterling|£]]3,700.&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt; Their controversial song &quot;[[Desdemona (Marc Bolan song)|Desdemona]]&quot; was covered by several bands, including punk rock band, [[The Jam]].&lt;ref name=MakingTime/&gt;

==Line-up==
* [[Andy Ellison]]: vocals (b. 5 July 1946, [[Finchley]], [[North London]])
* Geoff McClelland: guitar (b. 1947)
* [[Marc Bolan]]: guitar (replaced McClelland, March 1967)
* John Hewlett: bass guitar (b. 1948)
* [[Chris Townson]]: drums/guitar (b. 24 July 1947, [[Battersea]], [[South West (London sub region)|South West London]] – d. 10 February 2008)&lt;ref name=Perrone/&gt; &lt;ref name=Gordon&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.martingordon.de/godbook.html | title = The Companion Volume to God's on His Lunchbreak | last = Gordon | first = Martin | authorlink = Martin Gordon | accessdate = 2010-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Chris Colville: drums (only at live-appearances)

===Black &amp; White album===
The 2011 album ''Black &amp; White'' features the following line up:
* Andy Ellison
* Chris Townson
* [[Boz Boorer]]
* [[Martin Gordon]]

==Discography==
===Singles===
*&quot;Smashed Blocked&quot; ([[Simon Napier-Bell|Napier-Bell]]/Hewlett) / &quot;Strange Affair&quot;
**&lt;small&gt;''(UK A-Side title: &quot;The Love I Thought I'd Found&quot;; Germany B-Side: &quot;Just What You Want...&quot;'' USA: [[Billboard Hot 100|''Billboard Hot'' 100]] and local (Florida) Top-10s; backing by L.A. [[session musician]]s) (UK: [[Columbia (EMI)]] DB 8030, October 14, 1966, USA: [[White Whale Records|White Whale]], December 1966, Germany: [[Polydor]] 59069, 1967)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;Just What You Want – Just What You'll Get&quot; (Hewlett, [[Chris Townson|Townson]], [[Andy Ellison|Ellison]], McClelland) / &quot;But She's Mine&quot;
**&lt;small&gt;''(A-side: backing by English [[session musician]]s; [[Jeff Beck]] guests on B-side)'' (UK: [[Columbia (EMI)]] DB 8124, February 3, 1967)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;[[Desdemona (Marc Bolan song)|Desdemona]]&quot; ([[Marc Bolan|Bolan]]) / &quot;Remember Thomas à Becket&quot;
**&lt;small&gt; ''(Bolan on A-side, McClelland on B-side)'' (UK: [[Track Records|Track]] 604 003, 24 May 1967; Germany: [[Polydor]] 59 104)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;Midsummer Night's Scene&quot; (Bolan) / &quot;Sara Crazy Child&quot; (full length) (Bolan) ''(release cancelled)''
**&lt;small&gt;(UK: [[Track Records|Track]] 604 005, June 1967)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;Come and Play with Me in the Garden&quot; (Ellison, Hewlett)/ &quot;Sara Crazy Child&quot; (edited) (Bolan)
**&lt;small&gt;''(Bolan plays on B-side only)'' (UK: [[Track Records|Track]] 604 005, 14 July 1967; Germany: Polydor 59 116)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;Go Go Girl&quot; (Bolan)/ &quot;Jagged Time Lapse&quot; (Hewlett, McClelland)
**&lt;small&gt;''(A-side is version of Bolan's &quot;Mustang Ford&quot; and features Bolan on guitar, B-side from remaining recordings with Geoff McClelland)'' (UK: [[Track Records|Track]] 604 010, 6 October 1967; Germany: [[Polydor]] 59 160; Greece: International Polydor 244)&lt;/small&gt;
*&quot;It's Been A Long Time&quot; / &quot;Arthur Green&quot; (B-side only, Andy Ellison solo single)
**&lt;small&gt;(UK: [[Track Records|Track]] 604 018, December 1967)&lt;/small&gt;

===Albums===
*''[[Orgasm (John's Children album)|Orgasm]]'' &lt;small&gt;([[White Whale Records|White Whale]] September 1970, projected release: 18 March 1967)&lt;/small&gt;
*''Music For the Herd of Herring'' – (John's Children/Jet/Radio Stars - live)&lt;small&gt; 2001, [[Radiant Future Records]] (REVP001CD)&lt;/small&gt;
*''Black &amp; White'' &lt;small&gt;([[Acid Jazz Records|Acid Jazz]] AJXCD 234, June 6, 2011)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=Record-Collector/&gt;&lt;ref name=Mod-Speed/&gt;

===Compilations===
*''A Midsummer Night's Scene'' – &lt;small&gt; 1988, Bam Caruso (MARI 095 CD)&lt;/small&gt;
*''Smashed Blocked!'' – &lt;small&gt; 1997, NMC (Pilot 12)&lt;/small&gt;
*''Jagged Time Lapse'' – &lt;small&gt; 1997, NMC (Pilot 18&lt;/small&gt;
*''John's Children'' (EP) – &lt;small&gt; 1999, Trash (LARD 20 07 99)&lt;/small&gt;
*''The Complete John's Children'' – &lt;small&gt; 2002, NMC (Pilot 118)&lt;/small&gt;

===Notable other releases===
*&quot;Incredible Sound Show Stories Vol.5 – Yellow Street Boutique&quot;
**&lt;small&gt;(A Sampler featuring songs recorded by &quot;The Silence&quot;)&lt;/small&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2|refs=
*&lt;ref name=Unterberger&gt;{{cite web |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=johns-children-p18542/biography|pure_url=yes}} |title=John's Children |publisher=Allmusic |first=Richie |last=Unterberger |authorlink=Richie Unterberger |accessdate=23 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Unterberger-SB&gt;{{cite web |url={{Allmusic|class=song|id=t5860576|pure_url=yes}} |title=Smashed Blocked |publisher=Allmusic |first=Richie |last=Unterberger |authorlink=Richie Unterberger |accessdate=25 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Eder&gt;{{cite web |url={{Allmusic|class=artist|id=the-who-p5822/biography|pure_url=yes}} |title=The Who |publisher=Allmusic |first1=Bruce |last1=Eder |first2=Stephen Thomas |last2=Erlew |accessdate=24 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Perrone&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.independent.co.uk/news/obituaries/chris-townson-drummer-with-johns-children-787838.html | title = Chris Townson: Drummer with John's Children  |work=The Independent |location=UK | date = 27 February 2008 | last = Perrone | first = Pierre | accessdate =19 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Times&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article3484698.ece | title = Chris Townson  |work=The Times |location=UK | date = 4 March 2008 | last = Gordon | first = Martin |accessdate =6 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=HistoryJohnsChildren&gt;{{cite web | url = http://koti.welho.com/mikkapan/jc/history.html | title = The history of John's Children | accessdate =20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=JohnsChildren&gt;{{cite web | url = http://koti.welho.com/mikkapan/jc/index.html | title = John's Children | accessdate =20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Mason&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.furious.com/perfect/johnschildren.html | title = Just What You Want – Just What You'll Get : The Gospel According To John's Children  | work=[[Perfect Sound Forever (magazine)|Perfect Sound Forever]] | date = October 1997 | last = Mason | first = Richard | accessdate =23 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=MakingTime&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.makingtime.co.uk/johns_children.html | title = John's Children | work=Making Time | accessdate =20 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=TechWebSound&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.techwebsound.com/playlistdetail.cfm?artist=295 | title = John's Children | work=Technicolor Web of Sound | accessdate =25 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=RollingStone&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.rollingstone.com/music/artists/the-who/biography | title = The Who |work=Rolling Stone | accessdate =24 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Faber&gt;{{cite book |title=The Faber Companion to 20th Century Popular Music |url=http://www.credoreference.com/entry/ffcpop/marc_bolan |publisher=[[Faber and Faber]] |year=2001 |chapter=Marc Bolan |accessdate=12 May 2011}} ([[Credo Reference]] access required.)&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Logan&gt;{{cite book |editor1-first=Nick |editor1-last=Logan |editor1-link=Nick Logan |editor2-first=Bob |editor2-last=Woffinden |editor2-link=Bob Woffinden |title=The Illustrated New Musical Express Encyclopedia of Rock |url=http://books.google.com/?id=LKE6QwAACAAJ&amp;dq=editions:w4-lAAAACAAJ |publisher=Salamander Books |year=1977 |page=36 |chapter=Marc Bolan |isbn=0-600-33147-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Record-Collector&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.recordcollectormag.com/reviews/review-detail/7236/biography | title = John's Children – Black &amp; White |last=Needs |first=Kris |work=Record Collector | accessdate =6 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name=Mod-Speed&gt;{{cite web | url = http://modspeedproduction.blogspot.com/2011/05/johns-children-new-album.html | title = ''Black &amp; White'' album review |work=Mod Speed | accessdate =6 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book |first=Simon |last=Napier-Bell |title=You Don't Have to Say You Love Me |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=azhwAAAACAAJ |publisher=[[Random House]] |year=2005 |pages=256 |isbn=0-091-90272-X}}

==External links==
* [http://koti.welho.com/mikkapan/jc/index.html Official Site]
* [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/SunsetStrip/Studio/4730/children.htm&amp;date=2009-10-25+10:59:35 Children of the Revolution – A Story of John's Children]

[[Category:Musical groups established in 1966]]
[[Category:English rock music groups]]
[[Category:Pre-punk groups]]
[[Category:Obscenity controversies]]
[[Category:British rhythm and blues boom musicians]]

[[de:John's Children]]
[[nl:John's Children]]
[[sv:John's Children]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
