<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3117" ns="0" title="Abu Zubaydah"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox War on Terror detainee
 | name = Abu Zubaydah
 | image = Abu Zubaydah.jpg
 | image_size =
 | caption =
 | birth_date = {{Birth date and age|1971|3|12}}
 | birth_place = [[Saudi Arabia]]
 | death_date =
 | death_place =
 | detained_at = [[CIA]] [[black sites]], [[Guantanamo Bay detention camp|Guantanamo]]
 | id_number = 10016
 | group =
 | alias = Abu Zubaydah&lt;br&gt; زين العابدين محمد حسين
 | charge = No charge
 | penalty =
 | status = Camp 7, Guantanamo
 | occupation =
 | spouse =
 | parents =
 | children =
}}
'''Abu Zubaydah''' ({{Lang-ar|ابو زبيدة}}, ''Abū Zubaydah''; born March 12, 1971 as '''Zayn al-Abidin Muhammad Husayn''') is a [[Saudi Arabia]]n citizen, sentenced to death in [[Jordan]] and currently held in U.S. custody in [[Guantánamo Bay (Cuba)|Guantanamo Bay]], [[Cuba]].&lt;ref name=odni14&gt;
{{Cite web
| url=http://www.odni.gov/announcements/content/DetaineeBiographies.pdf 
| title=Detainee Biographies
| publisher=[[Office of the Director of National Intelligence]]
| archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.odni.gov%2Fannouncements%2Fcontent%2FDetaineeBiographies.pdf+&amp;date=2009-08-31
| archivedate=2009-08-31
|format=PDF
}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Not neutral: Arrested in Pakistan in March 2002, he has been in US custody for more than eight years, four-and-a-half of them spent incommunicado in [[solitary confinement]] in undisclosed locations. He was subjected to the technique of [[waterboarding]] and has been subjected to numerous other interrogation techniques. These techniques, include forced nudity, [[sleep deprivation]], confinement in small dark boxes, deprivation of solid food, cold temperatures, [[stress positions]], and physical assaults. Videotapes of some of his interrogations are believed to be amongst those [[2005 CIA interrogation tapes destruction|destroyed by the CIA in 2005]].&lt;ref&gt;http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/TheLaw/story?id=4244423&amp;page=1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.andyworthington.co.uk/2010/03/15/abu-zubaydahs-torture-diary/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.democracynow.org/2009/3/30/headlines&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.propublica.org/article/do-cia-cables-show-doctors-monitoring-torture-528&lt;/ref&gt;

Abu Zubaydah was transferred to Guantanamo in September 2006 where he and other former [[CIA]] detainees are held in [[Camp_Platinum_%28Guantanamo%29#Camp_seven.2FCamp_Platinum|Camp 7]] where conditions are the most isolating. He has never been charged, despite being accused for years by US authorities.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.andyworthington.co.uk/2010/04/06/abu-zubaydah-tortured-for-nothing/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/20/world/20detain.html
| work=The New York Times
| first=Scott
| last=Shane
| title=Waterboarding Used 266 Times on 2 Suspects
| date=April 20, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.amnesty.org.au/hrs/comments/20872/&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.andyworthington.co.uk/2009/04/24/who-authorized-the-torture-of-abu-zubaydah/&lt;/ref&gt;

==Biography and his early years in Afghanistan==
Born in [[Saudi Arabia]], Abu Zubaydah moved to the [[West Bank]] as a teenager where he joined in Palestinian demonstrations against the Israelis.&lt;ref name=&quot;mayer&quot;&gt;[[Jane Mayer|Mayer, Jane]], &quot;[[The Dark Side (book)|The Dark Side: The Inside Story of How the War on Terror Turned Into a War on American Ideals]]&quot;, 2008. p. 140&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SecuringTheCity&quot;&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=100559912 Christopher Dickey ''Securing The City: Inside America's Best Counterterror Force--The NYPD'' Simon &amp; Schuster February 3, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

Abu Zubaydah is reported to have studied [[Computer Science]] in [[Pune]], [[India]] prior to his travel to Afghanistan/Pakistan in 1991.&lt;ref name=EurasiaReview2010-02-14&gt;
{{cite news
| url=http://www.eurasiareview.com/2010/02/31774-punes-past-jihadi-connections.html
| title=Pune's Past Jihadi Connections 
| publisher=[[Eurasia Review]]
| date=2010-02-14
| author=R. Raman
| archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.eurasiareview.com%2F2010%2F02%2F31774-punes-past-jihadi-connections.html&amp;date=2010-02-14
| archivedate=2010-02-14
| quote=Pune as a possible centre for jihadi activities came to notice in March 2002, when Abu Zubaidah, the then No.3 [sic] to Osama bin Laden, was arrested by the Pakistani authorities acting at the instance of the USA's Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), in the house of an activist of the Lashkar-e-Toiba [sic] (LET) at Faislabad in Pakistani Punjab and handed over to the FBI. He is now in the Guantanamo Bay Detention Centre in Cuba. Sections of the Pakistani media had reported at that time that Abu Zubaidah, a Palestinian, had studied computer science in Pune before crossing over into Pakistan and joining Al Qaeda.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Abu Zubaydah moved to Afghanistan in 1991 to fight alongside the [[mujahideen#Afghanistan|mujahideen]] in the [[Civil war in Afghanistan (1989–1992)|Afghan civil war]].&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/03/28/AR2009032802066.html Peter Finn and Joby Warrick, ''Detainee's Harsh Treatment Foiled No Plots'' The Washington Post, March 29, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1992 Abu Zubaydah was injured from a mortar shell blast which left shrapnel in his head and caused severe memory loss, as well as the loss of his ability to speak for over one year.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;&gt;
{{Cite news
| url=http://www.defenselink.mil/news/transcript_ISN10016.pdf 
| title=Abu Zubaydah Unclassified Verbatim Combatant Status Review Tribunal Transcript
| year=2007
| author=
| publisher=[[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]]
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EggenPincusFBICIADebate&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/12/17/AR2007121702151_pf.html Dan Eggen and Walter Pincus, ''FBI, CIA Debate Significance of Terror Suspect: Agencies Also Disagree On Interrogation Methods'' The Washington Post, Dec. 18, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindOnePercent&quot;&gt;Ron Suskind, ''The One Percent Doctrine: Deep Inside America's Pursuit of Its Enemies Since 9/11'' Simon &amp; Schuster, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Zubaydah eventually became involved in the jihad training camp known as the [[Khalden Camp]] where he oversaw the flow of recruits into and out of the camp. He obtained passports and paperwork for men transferring to other training camps or home. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.esquire.com/features/guantanamo-prisoner-0911?click=main_sr&lt;/ref&gt;

The Khalden Camp has been described by the U.S. Government as an al-Qaeda training facility—an assertion that has been utilized as evidence of Abu Zubaydah's, and over 50 other Guatanamo detainees' alleged connection to al-Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; This allegation has been contested, however, by multiple detainees, the 9/11 Commission Report, and [[Brynjar Lia]], head of the international terrorism and global jihadism at the [[Norwegian Defence Research Establishment]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KhalidCsrt&quot;&gt;[http://www.dod.mil/pubs/foi/detainees/csrt_arb/Set_1_0001-0097.pdf Khalid Sulaymanjaydh Al Hubayshi Unclassified Verbatim Combatant Status Review Tribunal Transcript, Pgs. 65-73 Department of Defense]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCsrt&quot;&gt;[http://www.dod.mil/pubs/foi/detainees/csrt_arb/Set_38_2608-2628.pdf Noor Uthamn Muhammed Unclassified Verbatim Combatant Status Review Tribunal, Pg. 15, Department of Defense]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;9/11CommissionReport&quot;&gt;[http://www.gpoaccess.gov/911/pdf/fullreport.pdf ''9/11 Commission Report: Final Report of the National Commission on Terrorist Attacks Upon the United States'' July 22, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobalJihad&quot;&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=WJefraeEKs4C&amp;pg=PA242&amp;lpg=PA242&amp;dq=brynjar+lia+khalden+camp&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=3SqJD2tq9c&amp;sig=dnbTxJ4SbsNKQiY_qosYHLbe1JA&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=c8_5SduyF4_SNMHfpLUE&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1 Brynjar Lia, ''Architect of Global Jihad: The Life of Al-Qaida Strategist Abu Mus'ab al-Suri'' pg. 242-243, Columbia University Press, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Zubaydah testified in his Combatant Status Review Tribunal that the Khalden Camp was at such odds with al-Qaeda and Bin Laden that is was closed by the Taliban in 2001, at al-Qaeda's request.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; This account was corroborated by two other detainees, [[Noor Uthman Muhammed]], who was alleged by the U.S. Government to have been the emir, or leader, of the Khalden Camp, and a close friend of Abu Zubaydah, [[Khalid Sulayman Jaydh Al Hubayshi]].&lt;ref name=&quot;KhalidCsrt&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCsrt&quot;/&gt; In addition, Noor Uthman Muhamed's charge sheet references the closing of the Khalden camp at the request of terrorist leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCurrentCharges&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissionsNoor.html ''Noor Uthamn Muhammed Charge Sheets'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Brynjar Lia]] states in his book that there was an ideological conflict between the leaders of the Khalden Camp on one side, and the Taliban and al-Qaeda on the other, and that this led to the closing of the Khalden Camp.&lt;ref name=GlobalJihad/&gt; Abu Zubaydah, Khalid Sulayman Jaydh Al Hubayshi, and Noor Uthman Muhammed confirmed this divide in their CSRT testimony.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KhalidCsrt&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCsrt&quot;/&gt; Of the 57 detainees the U.S. Government claims are associated with the Khalden Camp, 27 have been released, including Abu Zubaydah's good friend Khalid Sulayman Jaydh Al Hubayshi.&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoDocket&quot;&gt;[http://projects.nytimes.com/guantanamo New York Times Guantanamo Docket]&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 12, 2009 Colin Freeze, writing in the ''[[Globe and Mail]]'', reported on recent interviews with [[Mohamad Kamal Elzahabi]], a [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] citizen, US resident, and [[Permanent residence (United States)|green card]] holder, who has been held without charge in the USA since 2003.&lt;ref name=TheGlobeAndMail2009-09-12&gt;
{{Cite news
| url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/opinions/jailed-arab-details-ties-to-tortured-canadians/article1285350/#article
| title=Jailed Arab details ties to tortured Canadians 
| date=2009-09-12
| author=Colin Freeze
| publisher=[[Globe and Mail]]
| archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.theglobeandmail.com%2Fnews%2Fopinions%2Fjailed-arab-details-ties-to-tortured-canadians%2Farticle1285350%2F%23article&amp;date=2009-09-14
| archivedate=2009-09-14
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Elzahabi told the ''Globe and Mail'' that Abu Zubaydah had served under him when he was a squad commander during the war against the Soviets.  Elzahabi said that after the Soviet ouster Elzahabi worked as an instructor at Khalden.

==Early activities==
By 1999, the U.S. Government was attempting to run surveillance on Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;PressTrustIndia&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-4648752_ITM ''Pak leadership under Sharif offered to try to capture Osama'' The Press Trust of India Ltd. Through Asia Pulse. March 28, 2004] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; By March 2000, United States officials were reporting that Abu Zubaydah was a &quot;senior bin Laden official&quot;, the &quot;former head of Egypt-based Islamic Jihad&quot;, a &quot;trusted aide&quot; to bin Laden with &quot;growing power,&quot; who had &quot;played a key role in the East Africa embassy attacks.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidVise&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-513940.html David A. Vise and Lorraine Adams, ''Bin Laden Weakened, Officials Say'' The Washington Post. March 11, 2000] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; None of these allegations have been corroborated at this point, however.

Internationally Abu Zubaydah was convicted in absentia and sentenced to death &lt;ref&gt;''Six Muslim militants sentenced to death for plotting to attack tourists in Jordan'' [[The Independent]] 19 September 2000&lt;/ref&gt; by a Jordanian court for his role in plots to bomb U.S. and Israeli targets in Jordan.&lt;ref name=&quot;JamalHalaby&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-26114220.html Jamal Halaby, ''Arabs of Terror Linked to bin Laden'' AP News Online] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; A senior Middle East security official stated Abu Zubaydah had directed the Jordanian cell and was part of “bin Laden’s inner circle.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;TraineesInTerror&quot;&gt;[http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=20000305&amp;slug=4008236 ''Trainees in Terror'' The Seattle Times, Sunday, March 5, 2000]&lt;/ref&gt; 

In August, 2001 a classified FBI report entitled “Bin Laden determined to strike in U.S.”, which would not become public until much later, stated that the foiled millennium bomber, [[Ahmed Ressam]], had confessed that Abu Zubaydah had not only encouraged him to blow up the Los Angeles airport, but had facilitated his mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;BinLadenReport&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2004/ALLPOLITICS/04/10/august6.memo/index.html ''Transcript: Bin Laden determined to Strike in US'' CNN.com, Saturday April 10, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; The report also claims Abu Zubaydah was planning his own attack on the U.S.&lt;ref name=BinLadenReport/&gt; An unclassified FBI report also stated that Ahmed Ressam attempted to buy a laptop for Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;ElaineGanley&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-80592999.html Elaine Ganley, ''Terror Plot Took Typical Path'' AP Online, December 19, 2001] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; Despite all of these supposed connections, when Ahmed Ressam went to trial in December 2001 federal prosecutors did not attempt to link him to Abu Zubaydah, and did not use any of this supposed evidence in its case.&lt;ref name=ElaineGanley/&gt; He also recanted his confessions after the trial saying he was coerced into giving them.

==Capture==

It is unclear how the Government found Abu Zubaydah. U.S. officials claimed he was tracked down after making a phone call to al-Qaeda leaders in [[Yemen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;TedBridis&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-52457420.html Ted Bridis ''U.S. Will Seek Death Penalty In Spy Case'' The Columbian, April 20, 2002] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; However, this has been questioned by a CIA official who stated that the U.S. paid $10 million to the Pakistani government, who had in turn bribed the information on his whereabouts from a local driver in [[Faisalabad]].&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt; Pakistani intelligence discovered that he was traveling in disguise as a [[burka]]-clad woman.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt; Saudi Arabian officials claimed Abu Zubaydah was captured after intelligence gleaned during an interrogation by their GSS.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nowaf Obaid&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-404238.html Nowaf Obaid, ''The Saudis’ Fight Too: We’re on the same side in the war on terror'' The Washington Post, December 26, 2002] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; It was also reported in 2008 that [[Deuce Martinez]], a CIA analyst, had played an integral role in narrowing down Abu Zubaydah’s supposed hideouts to the 14 targeted by the joint raids.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneInside9/11Mastermind&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/22/washington/22ksm.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=1 Scott Shane, ''Inside a 9/11 mastermind’s interrogation'' New York Times, June 22, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Whoever was responsible for finding Abu Zubaydah, on March 28, 2002, CIA and FBI agents, in conjunction with Pakistani intelligence services, raided several safe houses in Pakistan searching for him.&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoFiles&quot;&gt;Andy Worthington ''The Guantanamo Files'' Pluto Press, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TimMcGirk&quot;&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,227584,00.html Tim McGirk, ''Anatomy of a Raid'' TIME Magazine, April 8, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnBurns&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDA123CF937A25757C0A9649C8B63 John Burns, ''A NATION CHALLENGED: THE FUGITIVES, In Pakistan’s Interior, A Troubling Victory in Hunt for Al Qaeda'' New York Times, April 14, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AntiTerrorRaid&quot;&gt;[http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=20020403&amp;slug=zub03 ''Anti-terror raids yield bonanza for U.S. intelligence'' Seattle Times, April 2, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Zubaydah was apprehended from one of the targeted safe houses in [[Faisalabad]], Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoFiles&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TimMcGirk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnBurns&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AntiTerrorRaid&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KumarArun&quot;&gt;[http://www.hindustantimes.com/StoryPage/StoryPage.aspx?id=04859c7f-8276-4944-acf6-cebaaf311614&amp;MatchID1=55&amp;TeamID1=1&amp;TeamID2=7&amp;MatchType1=5&amp;SeriesID1=1&amp;MatchID2=56&amp;TeamID3=5&amp;TeamID4=8&amp;MatchType2=5&amp;SeriesID2=1&amp;PrimaryID=55&amp;Headline=US+imposes+sanctions+on+f Arun Kumar, ''US imposes sanctions on four Lashkar-e-Toiba leaders'' Hindustan Times, May 28, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; During his apprehension he was shot in the thigh, the testicle, and the stomach with rounds from an AK-47 assault rifle.&lt;ref name=&quot;mayer&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoFiles&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BrianRoss&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/images/Blotter/brianross_kiriakou_transcript1_blotter071210.pdf Brian Ross, ''CIA- Abu Zubaydah: Interview with John Kiriakou: Transcript'' ABC News, December 10, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JJGreen&quot;&gt;[http://www.wtop.com/?sid=1368866&amp;nid=251 J.J. Green, ''Former CIA Officer: Waterboarding is Wrong, but it Worked'' WTOPnews.com, March 20, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush2006Speech&quot;&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2006/09/20060906-3.html ''President George Bush, Speech'' September 6, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; He was not recognised at first, and simply thrown into a [[pick-up truck]] along with other prisoners by the Pakistani forces, until a senior FBI agent identified him as Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;risen&quot;&gt;Risen, James. &quot;State of War: The Secret History of the CIA and the Bush Administration&quot;, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; He was taken by the FBI to a Pakistani hospital nearby and treated for his wounds, where the attending doctor admitted to [[John Kiriakou]], the co-leader of the CIA group that apprehended Abu Zubaydah, he had never before seen a patient survive such severe wounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrianRoss&quot;/&gt; The FBI and CIA flew in a doctor from Johns Hopkins University to ensure Abu Zubaydah would not succumb to his wounds during transit out of Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneInside9/11Mastermind&quot;/&gt; 

His [[pocket litter]] supposedly contained two [[bank card]]s which showed he had access to Saudi and Kuwaiti bank accounts, which was considered rare since most al-Qaeda members used the preferred untraceable [[hawala]] banking.&lt;ref name=&quot;risen&quot;/&gt; According to [[James Risen]]
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;It is not clear whether an investigation of the cards simply fell through the cracks, or whether they were ignored because no one wanted to know the answers about connections between al Qaeda and important figures in the Middle East -- particularly in Saudi Arabia.&quot; One of Risen's sources chalks up the failure to investigate the cards to incompetence rather than foul play: &quot;The cards were sent back to Washington and were never fully exploited. I think nobody ever looked at them because of incompetence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;risen&quot;/&gt; When American investigators finally did get around to looking into the cards, they worked with &quot;a Muslim financier with a questionable past, and with connections to the Afghan Taliban, al Qaeda, and Saudi intelligence.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;risen&quot;/&gt; He reported back that &quot;Saudi intelligence officials had seized all of the records related to the card from the Saudi financial institution in question; the records then disappeared. There was no longer any way to trace the money that had gone into the account.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;risen&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

A search of the safehouse turned up his personal 10,000 page diaries, in which he recorded his thoughts in seemingly [[split personalities]] of a young boy, old man, and himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;mayer&quot;/&gt;

Abu Zubaydah was turned over to the CIA,&lt;ref name=&quot;DanFroomkin&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/blog/2007/12/18/BL2007121800862.html Dan Froomkin, ''Bush’s Exhibit A for Torture'' The Washington Post December 18, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DanaPriestCIAHolds&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/01/AR2005110101644.html Dana Priest, ''CIA Holds Terror Suspects in Secret Prisons'' The Washington Post, November 2, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; and was allegedly transferred to [[Black site|secret CIA-operated prisons]] in Pakistan, [[Thailand]], [[Afghanistan]], [[Poland]], [[Northern Africa]], and [[Diego Garcia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DiegoGarcia&quot;&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/10/19/europe/EU-GEN-Britain-Diego-Garcia.php ''Lawmakers to examine claims Indian Ocean island used in secret prison network'' International Herald Tribune, October 19, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DickMarty&quot;&gt;[http://assembly.coe.int/CommitteeDocs/2007/Emarty_20070608_NoEmbargo.pdf Dick Marty, ''Secret detentions and illegal transfers of detainees involving Council of Europe member states: Second report'' Council of Europe Parliamentary Assembly, June 7, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RossAndEsposito&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/WNT/Investigation/story?id=1375123 Brian Ross and Richard Esposito, ''EXCLUSIVE: Sources Tell ABC News Top Al Qaeda Figures Held in Secret CIA Prisons'' ABC News, December 5, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAShuffledPrisoners&quot;&gt;[http://www.globalpulse.net/archives/security/cia_shuttled_pr_000087.php ''CIA Shuffled Prisoners Out of Poland'' Global Pulse December 5, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonBurke&quot;&gt;[http://observer.guardian.co.uk/international/story/0,6903,1237589,00.html Jason Burke, ''Secret World of U.S. Jails'' Observer, June 13, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EnforcedDisappearance&quot;&gt;[http://www.reprieve.org.uk/documents/FinalReprieveFASCExecutiveSummary.pdf ''Enforced Disappearance, Illegal Interstate Transfer, and Other Human Rights Abuses Involving the UK Overseas Territories: Executive Summary'' Reprieve]&lt;/ref&gt; Historically renditions to countries which commit torture have been illegal, however, a memo written by [[John Yoo]] and [[Jay Bybee]] days before Abu Zubaydah's capture, provided legal cover for renditions to places such as Thailand.&lt;ref name=&quot;BybeeRenditionMemo&quot;&gt;[http://www.usdoj.gov/opa/documents/memorandumpresidentpower03132002.pdf Jay Bybee Department of Justice, March 13, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; In March, 2009, the U.S. Senate Intelligence Committee launched a year-long study on how the CIA operated the secret prisons around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAPrisons&quot;&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601087&amp;sid=aJchF0ELduak&amp;refer=home James Rowley Bloomberg, March 5, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Interrogation of Abu Zubaydah==
{{Main|Interrogation of Abu Zubaydah}}
Abu  Zubaydah was interrogated by two separate interrogation teams, one from  the FBI and one from the CIA.

==The torture of Abu Zubaydah==


Abu Zubaydah's treatment at the hands of the CIA has been called torture by [[Ali Soufan]], the FBI interrogator who witnessed part of Abu Zubaydah's CIA interrogation, multiple U.S. officials including President Obama, and by the International Committee of the Red Cross.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanOpEd&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/23/opinion/23soufan.html Ali Soufan ''My Tortured Decision'' New York Times, April 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanNewsweek&quot;&gt;[http://www.newsweek.com/id/195089 Michael Isikoff '''We Could Have Done This the Right Way''' Newsweek, April 25, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanTestimony&quot;&gt;[http://judiciary.senate.gov/hearings/testimony.cfm?id=3842&amp;wit_id=7906 ''Congressional Testimony of Ali Soufan, May 13, 2009'' Congressional Testimony, May 13, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;&gt;[http://www.nybooks.com/icrc-report.pdf ''International Committee of the Red Cross Report on the Treatment of Fourteen &quot;High Value Detainees&quot; in CIA Custody'' International Committee of the Red Cross, February 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

The CIA subjected Abu Zubaydah to various forms of increasingly harsh interrogation techniques including temperature extremes, music played at debilitating volumes, and sexual humiliation.&lt;ref name=&quot;EggenPincusFBICIADebate&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RossAndEsposito&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidJohnston&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/10/washington/10detain.html?pagewanted=1 David Johnston ''At a Secret Interrogation, Dispute Flared Over Tactics'' New York Times, September 10, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Zubaydah was also subjected to beatings, isolation, waterboarding, long-time standing, continuous cramped confinement, and sleep deprivation.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DickMarty&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RossAndEsposito&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneICRCReport&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/07/11/washington/11detain.html?scp=1&amp;sq=zubaydah&amp;st=nyt Scott Shane ''Book Cites Secret Red Cross Report of CIA Torture of Qaeda Captives'' New York Times, July 11, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JaneMeyerBlackSites&quot;&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2007/08/13/070813fa_fact_mayer Jane Meyer ''The Black Sites: A rare look inside CIA’s secret interrogation program'' The New Yorker, August 13, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottHorton&quot;&gt;[http://harpers.org/archive/2008/07/hbc-90003234 Scott Horton ''Six Questions for Jane Meyer, Author of The Dark Side'' Harper's Magazine, July 14, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; During Abu Zubaydah's interrogation President Bush learned he was on painkillers for the wounds he suffered during his capture and was therefore difficult to get information from.&lt;ref name=&quot;PaulKoring&quot;&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/5yFpbGc1P Paul Koring ''New book slams Bush’s black ops'' Globe and Mail, January 4, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; President Bush exclaimed to then CIA director George Tenet “[w]ho authorized putting him on pain medication?”&lt;ref name=&quot;PaulKoring&quot;/&gt; It would later be reported that Abu Zubaydah was denied painkillers during his interrogation.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAGhostDetainees&quot;&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/backgrounder/usa/us1004/index.htm ''United States’ “Disappeared” CIA Long-term “Ghost Detainees”'' Human Rights Watch, October 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Impunity&quot;&gt;[http://www.hrw.org/reports/2005/us0405/6.htm ''Impunity for the Architects of Illegal Policy'' Human Rights Watch, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TurnerAndSchullhoffer&quot;&gt;[http://brennan.3cdn.net/6a0e5de414927df95e_lbm6iy66c.pdf Serrin Turner and Stephen J. Schullhoffer ''The Secrecy Problem in Terrorism Trials'' Brennan Center for Justice 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EunYoungChoi&quot;&gt;Eun Young Choi ''Veritas, Not Vengeance: An Examination of the Evidentiary Rules for Military Commissions in the War Against Terrorism'' 42 Harvard Civil Rights Civil Liberties Law Review, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CharlesBrower&quot;&gt;Charles H. Brower II ''The Lives of Animals, the Lives of Prisoners, and the Revelations of Abu Ghraib'' 37 Vanderbilt Journal of Transnational Law, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AJohnRadsan&quot;&gt;A. John Radsan ''Symposium on Reexamining the Law of War: The Collision Between Common Article Three and The Central Intelligence Agency'' 56 Catholic University Law Review, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TommyHarnden&quot;&gt;[http://www.theage.com.au/cgi-bin/common/popupPrintArticle.pl?path=/articles/2003/03/05/1046826435361.html Tommy Harnden ''Gloves off, the screws go on 9/11 suspect'' The Age, March 6, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BonnerAndVanNattaJrAndWaldman&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DC1F3FF93AA35750C0A9659C8B63 Raymond Bonner, Don Van Natta Jr, and Amy Waldman ''THREATS AND RESPONSES: INTERROGATIONS; Questioning Terror Suspects In a Dark and Surreal World'' New York Times, March 9, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the interrogation techniques used against Abu Zubaydah, including waterboarding, cold cell, long-time standing, and sleep deprivation were previously considered illegal under U.S. and international law and treaties at the time of Abu Zubaydah’s capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;EnforcedDisappearance&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WalterPincusWaterboarding&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/04/AR2006100402005.html Walter Pincus, ''Waterboarding Historically Controversial'' The Washington Post, October 5, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the United States had prosecuted Japanese military officials after World War II and American soldiers after the Vietnam War for waterboarding.&lt;ref name=&quot;WalterPincusWaterboarding&quot;/&gt; Since 1930, the United States had defined sleep deprivation as an illegal form of torture.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt; Many other techniques developed by the CIA constitute inhuman and degrading treatment and torture under the United Nations Convention against Torture and Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;EnforcedDisappearance&quot;/&gt;

At least one detainee claims to have seen pictures of the injuries caused to Abu Zubaydah during his torture.&lt;ref name=&quot;IbrahimZeidan&quot;&gt;[{{DoD detainees ARB|Set_11_1145-1178.pdf#33}} ''Ibrahim Zeidan Summarized transcripts'' Department of Defense]{{Dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International Committee of the Red Cross report===
The International Committee of the Red Cross concluded a report on the treatment of 14 high-value detainees in February 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt; The report would be made public April 7, 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;ACLUICRC&quot;&gt;[http://www.aclu.org/safefree/torture/39296prs20090407.html ''Full ICRC Report Further Underscores Extent of Torture And Abuse By U.S. Officials'' ACLU, April 4, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; The report is composed of interviews with the detainees, although the ICRC stated &quot;[t]he ICRC wishes to underscore that the consistency of the detailed allegations provided separately by each of the fourteen [detainees] adds particular weight to the information provided.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt; The ICRC outlined twelve interrogation techniques suffocation by water (waterboarding), prolonged stress standing position, beatings by use of a collar, beating and kicking, confinement in a box, prolonged nudity, sleep deprivation, exposure to cold temperature, prolonged shackling, threats of ill-treatment, forced shaving, and deprivation/restricted provision of solid food.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt; Of the 12 interrogation techniques, only Abu Zubaydah was subjected to all of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;

Abu Zubaydah was the only one of the fourteen detainees to be put into close confinement.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt; This would be corroborated, in part, by one of the Torture Memos written by the Department of Justice Office of Legal Counsel, which noted &quot;[i]n OMS's view, however, cramped confinement &quot;ha[s] not proved particularly effective&quot; because it provides &quot;a safehaven offering respite from interrogation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;&gt;[http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05302005_bradbury.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memoradnum for John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency Re: Application of United States Obligations Under Article 16 of the Convention Against Torture to Certain Techniques that May Be Used in the Interrogation of High Value al Qaeda Detainees'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 30, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; In Abu Zubaydah's case, however, this is debatable since the smaller of the close confinement boxes caused his wound to reopen and begin to bleed again.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt; He was placed in two boxes, a 'large' one in which he could stand upright, and a much smaller one, in which he had to crouch down.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;

===Waterboarding===
Abu Zubaydah was one of three high value detainees to be waterboarded.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimesProfileZubaydah&quot;/&gt; Originally the Government's position was that Abu Zubaydah had only been waterboarded once.&lt;ref name=&quot;BrianRoss&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JJGreen&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TanyaNolan&quot;&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/worldtoday/content/2007/s2116703.htm Tanya Nolan ''Former CIA Agent Reveals Use of ‘Waterboarding’ in Interrogations'' The World Today, December 12, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RayMcGovern&quot;&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/story/70490/ Ray McGovern ''Destruction of CIA Tapes Can’t Hide Barbaric U.S. Torture Methods'' AlterNet, December 13, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LauerStirsScandal&quot;&gt;[http://www.mediaresearch.org/cyberalerts/2007/cyb20071212.asp#1 ''Lauer Stirs Scandal Over How Water Boarding Saved Lives'' Media Research Center, December 12, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ExCIAAgent&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2007/POLITICS/12/11/agent.tapes/#cnnSTCText ''Ex-CIA Agent: Waterboarding ‘Saved Lives’'' CNNPolitics.com, December 11, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, John Kiriakou, a CIA officer who had seen the cables regarding Abu Zubaydah's interrogation publicly stated Abu Zubaydah was waterboarded only once for 35 seconds before he started talking.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaterboardingEffective&quot;&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2009/0420/p99s01-duts.html Liam Stack ''Is waterboarding effective? CIA did it 266 times on two prisoners'' Christian Science Monitor, April 20, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ComingFromCold&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/Story?id=3978231 Richard Esposito &amp; Brian Ross ''Coming in From the Cold: CIA Spy Calls Waterboarding Necessary But Torture'' ABC News, December 10, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BrianStetler&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/28/business/media/28abc.html?ref=business Brian Stetler ''How '07 Interview Tilted Torture Debate'' The New York Times, April 27, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Even before the May 30, 2005 Torture Memo surfaced, Government officials familiar with Abu Zubaydah's detention questioned this account of events.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EggenPincusFBICIADebate&quot;/&gt; In fact, intelligence sources claimed as early as 2008 that Abu Zubaydah had been waterboarded no less than ten times in the span of one week.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt; In reality, Abu Zubaydah was waterboarded 83 times within the month of August, 2002, which happens to be the same month waterboarding was approved for use on him.&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimesProfileZubaydah&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAInterrogations&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SchererAndGhosh&quot;&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1892708,00.html Michael Scherer and Bobby Ghosh ''How Waterboarding Got Out of Control'' Time Magazine, April 20, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneWaterboarding&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/20/world/20detain.html Scott Shane ''Waterboarding Used 266 Times on 2 Suspects'' New York Times, April 19, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TakingOnTorture&quot;&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/editorials/la-ed-torture27-2009apr27,0,6092738.story ''Taking on Torture'' Los Angeles Times, April 27, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2010, Kiriakou, in a memoir, said &quot;Now we know that Zubaydah was waterboarded eighty-three times in a single month, raising questions about how much useful information he actually supplied.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |work=Foreign Policy |date=January 26, 2010 |title=CIA Man Retracts Claim on Waterboarding; A study in &quot;enhanced reporting techniques|author=Jeff Stein |url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2010/01/26/cia_man_retracts_claim_on_waterboarding?print=yes&amp;hidecomments=yes&amp;page=full}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The May 10, 2005 torture memo stated that no more than 60 applications of water could be conducted in a 30 day period. However, that number applied only to those applications of &quot;ten seconds or more.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; A U.S. official with knowledge of the interrogation program reported to Fox News that many of the applications lasted &quot;a matter of seconds&quot; and it was these less than ten second applications &quot;that created the huge numbers.&quot; He further stated that &quot;[a]ll of those individual pours were scrupulously counted by the CIA, according to the memos, to abide by the procedures set up for the waterboardings.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;JosephAbrams&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/04/28/despite-reports-khalid-sheikh-mohammed-waterboarded-times Joseph Abrams ''Despite Reports, Khalid Sheikh Mohammed Was Not Waterboarded 183 Times'' Fox News, April 28, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

However, the May 10, 2005 torture memo reported that the Department of Justice, Inspector General report noted that &lt;blockquote&gt; [T]he waterboard technique… was different from the technique described in the DoJ opinion and used in the SERE training. The difference was in the manner in which the detainee’s breathing was obstructed. At the SERE school and in the DoJ opinion the subject’s airflow is disrupted by the firm application of a damp cloth over the air passage; the interrogator applies a small amount of water to the cloth in a controlled manner. By contrast, the Agency interrogator… applied large volumes of water to a cloth that covered the detainee’s mouth and nose. One of the psychologists/interrogators acknowledged that the Agency’s use of the technique is different from that used in SERE training because it is ‘for real’ and is ‘more poignant and convincing.’” The Inspector General further reported that “OMS contends that the expertise of the SERE psychologist/interrogator on the waterboard was probably misrepresented at the time, as the SERE waterboard experience is so different from the subsequent Agency usage as to make it almost irrelevant. Consequently, according to OMS, there was no a prior reason to believe that applying the waterboard with the frequency and intensity with which it was used by the psychologist/interrogators was either efficacious or medically safe.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Inspector General also noted that the use of waterboarding was discontinued in every armed services branch except the Navy SERE training &quot;because of its dramatic effect on the students who were subjects.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The CIA Office of Medical Services contradicted this conclusion, however, stating that “[w]hile SERE trainers believe that trainees are unable to maintain psychological resistance to the waterboard our experience was otherwise. Some subjects unquestionably can withstand a large number of applications, with no immediately discernible cumulative impact beyond their strong aversion to the experience.”&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The memo also noted that at a Senate Judiciary Committee hearing, Douglas Johnson, Executive Director of the Center for Victims of Torture, testified that some U.S. military personnel who have undergone waterboard training have apparently stated “that it’s taken them 15 years of therapy to get over it&quot;, although his claim has not substantiated.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; Despite the conflicting information the Department of Justice Office of Legal Counsel approved all of the tactics listed above.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;

Several people who have subjected themselves to controlled waterboarding have stated that it is torture.&lt;ref name=&quot;JoshWhite&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/11/08/AR2007110802150.html Josh White ''Waterboarding Is Torture, Says Ex-Navy Instructor'' The Washington Post, November 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardMezo&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/02/08/AR2008020803156.html?sub-AR Richard E. Mezo ''Why It Was Called ‘Water Torture’'' The Washington Post, February 10, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlfredMcCoy&quot;&gt;[http://hnn.us/articles/32497.html Alfred McCoy ''The U.S. has a History of Using Torture'' History News Network, December 4, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; Conservative Chicago radio host, Erich &quot;Mancow&quot; Muller agreed to be waterboarding so he could &quot;prove it wasn't torture.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;RachelWeiner&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2009/05/22/mancow-waterboarded-video_n_206906.html Rachel Weiner ''Mancow Waterboarded (VIDEO): Conservative Radio Host Say It's Torture'' Huffington Post, May 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Instead Muller stated &quot;It is such an odd feeling to have water poured down your nose with your head back... It was instantaneous... and I don't want to say this: absolutely torture.&quot;&lt;ref name=RachelWeiner/&gt;

Malcolm Wrightson Nance, an instructor at the Navy’s SERE school in California testified before congress that waterboarding “is an overwhelming experience that induces horror and triggers frantic survival instincts. As the event unfolded, I was fully conscious of what was happening: I was being tortured.”&lt;ref name=&quot;JoshWhite&quot;/&gt; Nance further testified that waterboarding is “[N]ot simulated anything. It’s slow motion suffocation with enough time to contemplate the inevitability of blackout and expiration.”&lt;ref name=&quot;JoshWhite&quot;/&gt; Richard E. Mezo, who was waterboarded during training to become a Navy flight crewmember described waterboarding as an act that is “indeed torture” which is “real drowning that simulates death.”&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardMezo&quot;/&gt; The experience was so horrific, Mezo stated that “Pulling out my fingernails or even cutting off a finger would have been preferable.”&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardMezo&quot;/&gt; Henri Alleg, who was waterboarded by the French during the Algerian War, wrote that “a terrible agony, that of death itself, took possession of me.”&lt;ref name=&quot;AlfredMcCoy&quot;/&gt;

Abu Zubaydah said of his experience:&lt;blockquote&gt; I struggled against the straps, trying to breathe, but it was hopeless. I thought I was going to die.&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; During his waterboarding Abu Zubaydah lost control of his bladder and would later admit to the ICRC that &quot;[s]ince then I still lose control of my urine when under stress.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ICRC&quot;/&gt;

Some politicians and administration officials, including Richard Armitage, the former Deputy Secretary of State, Mike McConnell, the former National Intelligence Directorate, Tom Ridge, the former Homeland Security Secretary, and former Republican Presidential Candidate John McCain, have also declared it unequivocal torture.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AmyGoodman&quot;&gt;[http://www.democracynow.org/2008/7/18/the_dark_side_jane_mayer_on Amy Goodman ''The Dark Side: Jane Mayer on the Inside Story of How the War on Terror Turned Into a War on American Ideals, Interview Transcript'' Democracy Now, July 18, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Senator John McCain stated “It is not a complicated procedure. It is torture.”&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;

===Top U.S. officials approved enhanced interrogation techniques===
In the Spring of 2002, immediately following Abu Zubaydah’s capture, top US Government officials including Dick Cheney, Colin Powell, George Tenet, Condoleezza Rice, Donald Rumsfeld, and John Ashcroft discussed at length whether or not the CIA could legally use harsh techniques against Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkMazetti&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2008/09/25/washington/25detain.html Mark Mazzetti ''Bush Aides Linked to Talks on Interrogations'' New York Times, September 24, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BushAwareInterrogations&quot;&gt;[http://abclocal.go.com/kfsn/story?section=news/national_world&amp;id=6076727 ''Bush aware of advisers’ interrogation talks'' ABC News, April 11, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Condoleezza Rice specifically mentioned the SERE program during the meeting stating “I recall being told that U.S. military personnel were subjected to training to certain physical and psychological interrogation techniques…”&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkMazetti&quot;/&gt; In addition, in 2002 and 2003, several Democratic congressional leaders were briefed on the proposed “enhanced interrogation techniques.”&lt;ref name=&quot;WarrickAndEggen&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/12/08/AR2007120801664.html?hpid=topnews Joby Warrick and Dan Eggen ''Hill Briefed on Waterboarding in 2002'' The Washington Post, December 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; These congressional leaders included Nancy Pelosi, the future Speaker of the House, and Representative Jane Harman.&lt;ref name=&quot;WarrickAndEggen&quot;/&gt; Congressional officials have stated that the attitude in the briefings ranged from “quiet acquiescence, if not downright support.”&lt;ref name=&quot;WarrickAndEggen&quot;/&gt; The documents show that top U.S. Officials were intimately involved in the discussion and approval of the harsher interrogation techniques used on Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkMazetti&quot;/&gt; Condoleezza Rice ultimately told the CIA the harsher interrogation tactics were acceptable,&lt;ref name=&quot;RiceOkayedWaterboarding&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/04/22/timeline-released-senate-shows-condoleezza-rice-okd-waterboarding/ ''As Bush Adviser, Rice Gave OK to Waterboard'' Fox News, April 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SenateReportRice&quot;&gt;''Senate Report: Rice, Cheney OK'd CIA use of waterboarding'' CNN, April 23, 2009&lt;/ref&gt; and Dick Cheney stated &quot;I signed off on it; so did others.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SenateReportRice&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonLeopold&quot;&gt;[http://www.atlanticfreepress.com/news/1/6983--cheney-admits-he-signed-off-on-waterboarding-of-three-guantanamo-prisoners.html Jason Leopold ''Cheney Admits He 'Signed Off' on Waterboarding of Three Guantanamo Prisoners'' Atlantic Free Press, December 29, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; During the discussions John Ashcroft is reported as saying “Why are we talking about this in the White House? History will not judge this kindly.”&lt;ref name=&quot;BushAwareInterrogations&quot;/&gt;

===The torture memos===
{{Very long|section|date=September 2011}}
{{main|Torture Memos}}
In 2009, President Obama released four Justice Department memos which outlined the procedures CIA operatives wished to use on Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;ObamaReleasesBushTortureMemos&quot;&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2009/apr/16/torture-memos-bush-administration Ewen MacAskill ''Obama releases Bush torture memos'' The Guardian, April 16, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MazettiAndShaneInterrogationMemos&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/17/us/politics/17detain.html Mark Mazetti and Scott Shane ''Interrogation Memos Detail Harsh Tactics by the C.I.A.'' New York Times, April 16, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JonSwaine&quot;&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/barackobama/5169211/Barack-Obama-releases-torture-memos-details-of-techniques-used-by-CIA.html Jon Swaine ''Barack Obama releases torture memos: details of techniques used by CIA'' The Telegraph, April 17, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; The memos were written at the request of Dick Cheney and the Bush White House and were written under extreme pressure from the Office of the Vice President.&lt;ref name=&quot;JimComey&quot;&gt;[http://www.truthout.org/files/Comey-emails-2005.pdf James Comey ''James Comey Internal CIA E-mails'']&lt;/ref&gt; In e-mails to former U.S. Attorney Chuck Rosenberg, Jim Comey, former Deputy Attorney General, stated that the Attorney General, Alberto Gonzalez, had informed him he was &quot;under great pressure from the Vice President to complete both [May] memos.&quot;&lt;ref name=JimComey/&gt;

====Opposition within the Bush Administration====
The memos were opposed by members of the White House and Congress. Within the White House Philip Zelikow, a top advisor to Condoleezza Rice, opposed the new, harsher interrogation techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipZelikow&quot;&gt;[http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/30369127/ ''Rachel Maddow Interview of Philip Zelikow, Transcript'' MSNBC, April 23, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Upon reading the August 1, 2002 memo which justified the torture, Zelikow authored his own memo contesting the Justice Department's conclusions, since he believed they were legally incorrect.&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipZelikow&quot;/&gt; The Bush Administration attempted to collect all of the copies of Zelikow's memo and destroy them.&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanNewsweek&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipZelikow&quot;/&gt; In addition, military advisors to the CIA declared the proposed tactics as torture thirteen times within two pages in a memo regarding the techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAIgnored&quot;&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/5221190/CIA-ignored-warnings-from-US-soldiers-that-torture-and-extreme-stress-would-not-work.html Philip Sherwell and Leonard Doyle ''CIA ignored warnings from US soldiers that torture and extreme stress would not work'' The Telegraph, April 25, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; The memo was written one month before the torture memos were drafted and the interrogation techniques were used against Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAIgnored&quot;/&gt;

In Congress, House Representative Jane Harman, who was briefed on the proposed enhanced interrogation techniques in 2002, was the sole member of Congress to object.&lt;ref name=&quot;TopMembersOk&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,316256,00.html ''Report: Top Members of Congress Were OK With Waterboarding in 2002'' Fox News, December 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

Former CIA Inspector General, John Helgerson, drafted a report in 2004 which reportedly condemns not only the legality of the torture memos, but also the effectiveness of the torture techniques used.&lt;ref name=&quot;JaneMayerCIA&quot;&gt;[http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/newsdesk/2009/06/cia-interrogations-disclosure.html Jane Mayer ''Jane Mayer: C.I.A. Former Inspector General Pushed For Disclosure on Interrogations'' The New Yorker, June 17, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; The report was so appalling it prompted then director of the Office of Legal Counsel, Jack Goldsmith, to repudiate the John Yoo, Jay Bybee, and Stephen Bradbury memos.&lt;ref name=JaneMayerCIA/&gt;

In addition, a federal judge in San Francisco has ruled that [[Jose Padilla]] has standing to sue John Yoo for his detention and torture, due to John Yoo's role in drafting the torture memos.&lt;ref name=&quot;CourtIsAdjourned&quot;&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB124681141574196601.html?mod=googlenews_wsj ''Paul Gigot Interviews'' Wall Street Journal, July 6, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Dick Cheney's order to keep secret from Congress a CIA program recently killed by CIA Director Leon Panetta may also come under legal fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;PamBenson&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2009/POLITICS/07/11/cheney.surveillance/ Pam Benson ''Senator: Cheney and alleged secret CIA program 'a problem''' CNN, July 12, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShane&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/07/12/us/politics/12intel.html?hp Scott Shane ''Cheney Is Linked to Concealment of C.I.A. Project'' The New York Times, July 11, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Under the Intelligence Authorization Act, the office of the President is required to keep the Congress completely informed of the operations of the intelligence community.&lt;ref name=PamBenson/&gt;

====August 1, 2002 memo====
In August 2002, the Department of Justice’s Office of Legal Counsel, Jay Bybee and John Yoo drafted the first Torture Memo.&lt;ref name=&quot;August02TortureMemoReleased&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2008/POLITICS/07/24/cia.torture/index.html ''Previously Secret Torture Memo Released'' CNN.com, July 24, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Addressed to CIA acting General Counsel [[John A. Rizzo]], the purpose of the memo was to gain approval for harsh interrogation tactics to be used on Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;CIAInterrogations&quot;&gt;[http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/c/central_intelligence_agency/cia_interrogations/index.html?inline=nyt-classifier ''C.I.A. Interrogations'' New York Times, April 28, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;August02TortureMemoReleased&quot;/&gt; Although some believe the harsh tactics were already in effect before the memo granting authority to use them was written,&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkMazetti&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;August02TortureMemoReleased&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WarrickAndFinn&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/04/21/AR2009042104055_2.html?sid=ST2009042101921 Joby Warrick and Peter Finn ''Harsh Tactics Readied Before Their Approval'' The Washington Post, April 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlexKoppelman&quot;&gt;[http://www.salon.com/politics/war_room/2008/07/17/ashcroft/index.html?source=refresh Alex Koppelman ''Ashcroft suggests CIA sought legal approval after torture began'' Salon, July 17, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; and was used to provide after-the-fact legal support for harsh interrogation techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnstonAndRisen&quot;/&gt; In fact, a Department of Justice report regarding prisoner abuses reportedly stated the preparation of the memos occurred one month after Abu Zubaydah was subjected to the techniques allowed in the August 1, 2002 memo.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJReportYoo&quot;&gt;[http://www.pubrecord.org/torture/701-doj-report-blasts-yoo-for-not-citing-court-case-in-torture-memo.html Jason Leopold ''DOJ Report Says Yoo's Torture Memo Failed To Cite Supreme Court Case'' The Public Record, February 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; John Kiriakou stated in July, 2009, that Abu Zubaydah was waterboarded in the early summer of 2002, months before the August 1, 2002 memo was written.&lt;ref name=&quot;HilaryAndersson&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/8148202.stm Hilary Andersson ''Did America break its torture law?'' BBC Panorama, July 13, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCWaterboarding&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/8144625.stm ''US 'waterboarding' row rekindled'' BBC, July 13, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Alberto Gonzales would later testify before Congress that the opinion was sought after the detention of Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;ZacharyCoile&quot;&gt;[http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article/article?f=/c/a/2005/01/07/MNG41AMQ8R1.DTL Zachary Coile ''Gonzales unflappable in 6 hours of testimony Bush nominee says torture will not be tolerated'' San Francisco Chronicle, January 7, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; Questions by CIA officers over which tactics could be used on Abu Zubaydah had spurred the torture memo’s existence,&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnstonAndRisen&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DA1738F934A15755C0A9629C8B63 David Johnston and James Risen ''The Reach Of War: The Interrogations; Aides Say Memo Backed Coercion Already In Use'' New York Times, June 27, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; which is reflected in the language of the memo; &quot;You have asked for this advice in the course of conducting interrogations of Abu Zubaydah.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;August2002BybeeMemo&quot;&gt;[http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_08012002_bybee.pdf Jay Bybee and John Yoo ''Memorandum for John Rizzo Acting General Counsel of the Central Intelligence Agency: Interrogation of al Qaeda Operative'' U.S. Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, August 1, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; The memo's author, John Yoo, acknowledged the memo was the basis for Abu Zubaydah’s interrogation.&lt;ref name=&quot;JeffreyRosen&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/09/magazine/09rosen.html?pagewanted=all Jeffrey Rosen ''Conscience of a Conservative'' New York Times, September 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Yoo even told an interviewer “there was an urgency to decide so that valuable intelligence could be acquired from Abu Zubaydah, before further attacks could occur.”&lt;ref name=&quot;JeffreyRosen&quot;/&gt; John Yoo would later be harshly criticized by the Department of Justice for failing to cite legal precedent and existing case law when drafting his memos.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJReportYoo&quot;/&gt; In particular, the report chastises Yoo for failing to cite [[Youngstown Sheet &amp; Tube Co. v. Sawyer]], a seminal case on the powers of the Executive in times of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJReportYoo&quot;/&gt; In addition, Jack Goldsmith, the former head of the Office of Legal Counsel who withdrew the torture memos before resigning, stated he was &quot;astonished&quot; by the &quot;deeply flawed&quot; and &quot;sloppily reasoned&quot; legal analysis in the memos.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJReportYoo&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJTortureReport&quot;&gt;[http://www.newsweek.com/id/184801 Michael Isikoff ''A Torture Report Could Spell Big Trouble For Bush Lawyers'' Newsweek, February 14, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; David Luban, a law professor at Georgetown Law School, testified before Congress on May 13, 2009 that the memos were &quot;an ethical train wreck&quot; and had been drafted to &quot;reverse engineer&quot; a defense for illegal actions already committed.&lt;ref name=&quot;BobbyGhosh&quot;&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1898125,00.html Bobby Ghosh ''Partisan Passions Dominate Interrogation Hearings'' Time, May 13, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

The memo contemplated ten techniques the interrogators wanted to use: &quot;(1) attention grasp, (2) walling, (3) facial hold, (4) facial slap (insult slap), (5) cramped confinement, (6) wall standing, (7) stress positions, (8) sleep deprivation, (9) insects placed in a confinement box, and (10) the waterboard.”&lt;ref name=&quot;August2002BybeeMemo&quot;/&gt; Many of the techniques were, until then, generally considered illegal.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EnforcedDisappearance&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WalterPincusWaterboarding&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AmyGoodman&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkMazetti&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;August02TortureMemoReleased&quot;/&gt; Many other techniques developed by the CIA constituted inhumane and degrading treatment and torture under the United Nations Convention against Torture and Article 3 of the European Convention on Human Rights.&lt;ref name=&quot;EnforcedDisappearance&quot;/&gt;

According to a psychological evaluation conducted of Abu Zubaydah upon his capture, the memo alleges that Abu Zubaydah:

*Quickly rose from very low level mujahedin to third or fourth man in al Qaeda
*Served as Usama Bin Laden’s senior lieutenant
*Managed a network of training camps
*Was instrumental in the training of operatives for al Qaeda, the Egyptian Islamic Jihad, and other terrorist elements inside Pakistan and Afghanistan
*Acted as the Deputy Camp Commander for al Qaeda training camp in Afghanistan, personally approving entry and graduation of all trainees during 1999-2000
*Approved all individuals going in and out of Afghanistan to the training camps from 1996–1999
*No one went in and out of Peshawar, Pakistan without his knowledge and approval
*Acted as al Qaeda’s coordinator of external contacts and foreign communications
*Acted as al Qaeda’s counter-intelligence officer and had been trusted to find spies within the organization
*Was involved in every major terrorist operation carried out by al Qaeda
*Was a planner for the Millennium plot to attack U.S. and Israeli targets during the Millennium celebrations in Jordan
*Served as a planner for the Paris Embassy plot in 2001
*Was one of the planners of 9/11
*Engaged in planning future terrorist attacks against U.S. interests
*Wrote al Qaeda’s manual on resistance techniques&lt;ref name=&quot;August2002BybeeMemo&quot;/&gt;

====May 10, 2005 memo====
Another subsequent memo addressed the legality of additional interrogation techniques such as nudity, dietary manipulation, abdominal slap, water dousing, and water flicking.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;&gt;[http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05102005_bradbury46pg.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memorandum for John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency, Office of Legal Counsel Re: Application of 18 U.S.C. Sections 2340-2340A to Certain Techniques That May Be Used in the Interrogation of a High Value al Qaeda Detainee'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 10, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; It also expanded on the techniques of walling, stress positions, and sleep deprivation, allowing for an additional stress position and extended sleep deprivation up to 180 consecutive hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The memo also outlined the amount of waterboarding applications a detainee could be subjected to.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; The waterboard can only be used with a given detainee during one 30-day period. During that 30-day period the waterboard can be used no more than 5 days. In any given day that waterboarding occurs interrogators may use no more than two “sessions”, with a “session” defined as the time that the detainee is strapped to the board, and that a session can last no more than 2 hours. During any session no more than six applications of water of 10 seconds or more can be used. The total cumulative time of all water applications in a 24 hour period may not exceed 12 minutes.&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====May 10, 2005 memo (combined interrogation techniques)====
Another memo penned on May 10, 2005 authorized the use of the above outlined individual techniques in conjunction with one another, but stressed the importance of constant vigilance on the part of medical observers to ensure the techniques did not cause &quot;severe physical or mental pain.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May102005BradburyCombinedMemo&quot;&gt;[http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05102005_bradbury20pg.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memorandum For John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency Re: Application of 18 U.S.C. §§ 2340-2340A to the Combined Use of Certain Techniques in the Interrogation of High Value al Qaeda Detainees'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 10, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt;

====May 30, 2005 memo====
The final memo mentioned Abu Zubaydah several times and claimed that due to the increased interrogation techniques Zubaydah also &quot;provided significant information on two operatives, [including] Jose Padilla[,] who planned to build and detonate a '[[dirty bomb]]' in the Washington DC area.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; This claim is heavily disputed, however, by Ali Soufan the FBI interrogator who first interrogated Abu Zubaydah following his capture, and other intelligence officials.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanOpEd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanNewsweek&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanTestimony&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MazettiAndJohnston&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/09/washington/09zubaydah.html?_r=1&amp;ref=world&amp;oref=slogin Mark Mazzetti and David Johnston ''Inquiry Begins Into Destruction of Tapes'' New York Times, December 9, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Ali Soufan, when asked by Senator Sheldon Whitehouse during a Congressional hearing if the memo was incorrect, testified that it was.&lt;ref name=&quot;MarkBenjamin&quot;&gt;[http://www.salon.com/news/feature/2009/05/14/torture/ Mark Benjamin ''Soufan: CIA torture actually hindered our intelligence gathering'' Salon, May 14, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, the memo itself noted that not all of the waterboarding sessions were necessary for Abu Zubaydah, since the on-scene interrogation team determined he had stopped producing actionable intelligence.&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The memo reads:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
This is not to say that the interrogation program has worked perfectly. According to the IG Report, the CIA, at least initially, could not always distinguish detainees who had information but were successfully resisting interrogation from those who did not actually have the information. See IG Report at 83-85. On at least one occasion, this may have resulted in what might be deemed in retrospect to have been the unnecessary use of enhanced techniques. On that occasion, although the on-scene interrogation team judged Abu Zubaydah to be compliant, elements within CIA Headquarters still believed he was withholding information. See id at 84. At the direction of CIA Headquarters interrogators therefore used the waterboard one more time on Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===U.S. officials defend interrogation techniques===
Dennis C. Blair, President Obama's new director of national intelligence wrote in a memo to his staff in April 2009 that &quot;high value information came from interrogations in which [enhanced interrogation] methods were used.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneEffectiveness&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/23/us/politics/23detain.html?_r=1&amp;th&amp;emc=th Scott Shane ''Interrogations' Effectiveness May Prove Elusive'' New York Times, April 22, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Former Vice-President, Dick Cheney claims there are memos in existence which show the success of the enhanced interrogation techniques.&lt;ref name=&quot;CheneyCallsForRelease&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2009/04/20/cheney-calls-release-memos-showing-results-interrogation-efforts-1862515294/ ''Cheney Calls for Release of Memos Showing Results of Interrogation Efforts'' April 20, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Cheney stated:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I haven't talked about it, but I know specifically of reports that I read, that I saw, that lay out what we learned through the interrogation process and what the consequences were for the country I've now formally asked the CIA to take steps to declassify those memos so we can lay them out there and the American people have a chance to see what we obtained and what we learned and how good the intelligence was.&lt;ref name=CheneyCallsForRelease/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Additionally, four successive CIA directors echoed these sentiments, with the most recent, Michael V. Hayden, stating that he believed the methods &quot;got the maximum amount of information&quot; from prisoners, specifically Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneEffectiveness&quot;/&gt; As noted, however, the belief that enhanced interrogation techniques were necessary to get actionable intel from Abu Zubaydah has been heavily contested. John McLaughlin, former acting CIA director, stated in 2006 &quot;I totally disagree with the view that the capture of Abu Zubaydah was unimportant. Abu Zubaydah was woven through all of the intelligence prior to 9/11 that signaled a major attack was coming, and his capture yielded a great deal of important information.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindBlitzer&quot;&gt;[http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0606/20/sitroom.02.html ''Transcript for THE SITUATION ROOM with Wolf Blitzer'' CNN, June 20, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; In his memoir, former [[Director of Central Intelligence|CIA Director]] [[George Tenet]] writes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
A published report in 2006 contended that Abu Zubaydah was mentally unstable and that the administration had overstated his importance. Baloney. Abu Zubaydah had been at the crossroads of many al-Qa'ida operations and was in position to - and did - share critical information with his interrogators. Apparently, the source of the rumor that Abu Zubaydah was unbalanced was his personal diary, in which he adopted various personas. From that shaky perch, some junior Freudians leapt to the conclusion that Zubaydah had multiple personalities. In fact, Agency psychiatrists eventually determined that in his diary he was using a sophisticated literary device to express himself. And, boy, did he express himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;GeorgeTenet&quot;&gt;George Tenet ''At the Center of the Storm: My years at the CIA'' HarperCollins, April 30, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==The changing depiction of Abu Zubaydah==
When Abu Zubaydah was captured, the Bush Administration believed he was an unparalleled source of intelligence on al-Qaeda and terrorism plots. Abu Zubaydah was touted as the biggest catch of the War on Terror until the capture of Khalid Sheikh Mohammed.&lt;ref name=&quot;9/11MastermindNabbed&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2003/03/02/terror/main542459.shtml ''Alleged 9-11 Mastermind Nabbed'' CBS News, March 1, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately after Abu Zubaydah’s capture the director of the FBI stated Abu Zubaydah’s capture would help deter future attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsSummary&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DB1E3AF937A35757C0A9649C8B63 ''NEWS SUMMARY: Arrest May Deter Attacks'' New York Times, April 4, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; Also, White House spokesman Ari Fleischer stated Abu Zubaydah could provide a treasure-trove of information about al-Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsRecap&quot;/&gt; Donald Rumsfeld echoed these sentiments claiming Abu Zubaydah was “a man who knows of additional attacks”, who has “trained people to do this”, and was a big fish who had a fountain of knowledge.&lt;ref name=&quot;RumsfeldTranscript040302&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/transcripts/transcript.aspx?transcriptid=3390 Donald Rumsfeld ''News Transcript'' Department of Defense, April 3, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;

===U.S. government accounts of Abu Zubaydah's importance===
After Abu Zubaydah's capture, officials from the U.S. Government spoke out publicly about Abu Zubaydah's supposed role in al-Qaeda. However, as would later be reported in 2009, the U.S. Government's depiction of Abu Zubaydah was overly inflated and he was, as Justice Department Officials stated, &quot;[t]he above ground support... To make him the mastermind of anything is ridiculous&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt; a &quot;personnel clerk&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;ScottShaneDivisionsArose&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/18/world/middleeast/18zubaydah.html?ref=global-home Scott Shane, ''Divisions Arose on Rough Tactics for Qaead Figure'' The New York Times, April 17, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; a &quot;logistics chief&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;ConyersTranscript&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-33608853_ITM ''Transcript of Representative John Conyers Jr. Hearing on C.I.A.’s Destruction of Tapes'' Political/Congressional Transcript Wire, December 20, 2007] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt; and a &quot;travel agent.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindOnePercent&quot;/&gt; In fact, the CIA reportedly told Abu Zubaydah during his interrogation that they discovered he was not an al-Qaeda fighter, partner, or even a member.&lt;ref name=&quot;PeterFinnJulieTate&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/06/15/AR2009061503045.html?hpid=moreheadlines Peter Finn and Julie Tate ''CIA Mistaken on 'High-Value' Detainee, Document Shows'' The Washington Post, June 16, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

The allegations included:

*Abu Zubaydah was &quot;sinister&quot; and &quot;[t]here is evidence that he is a planner and a manager as well. I think he’s a major player.” - Former State Department director of counter-terrorism, Michael Sheehan&lt;ref name=&quot;InsiderReport&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-51764739.html ''Report: Insider May Testitfy On Zubaydah'' April 2, 2002] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “extremely dangerous” and a planner of 9/11. - John B. Bellinger III in a June 2007 briefing on Guantanamo Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;USHelsinkiCommission&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-31338935_ITM ''United States Helsinki Commission Briefing Transcript'' Political/Congressional Transcript Wire, June 22, 2007] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was a trainer, a recruiter, understood bomb-making, was a forger, a logistician, and someone who made things happen, and made “al-Qaeda function.” - Former CIA station chief, Bob Grenier&lt;ref name=&quot;VideoTranscriptGTMO&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-18437742_ITM ''Transcript of Video News Story on Guantanamo Bay with Kelli Arena Reporting'' CNN, September 24, 2006] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;
*“I don’t think there’s any doubt but a man named Abu Zubaydah is a close associate of UBL’s, and if not the number two, very close to the number two person in the organization. I think that’s well established.” -Donald Rumsfeld&lt;ref name=&quot;DoDNewsBrief040202&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-25210130_ITM ''Department of Defense News Briefing'' April 2, 2002] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “a very senior al Qaeda official who has been intimately involved in a range of activities for the al Qaeda.” - Donald Rumsfeld&lt;ref name=&quot;GerryGilmore&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/newsarticle.aspx?id=44203 Gerry Gilmore ''Rumsfeld Confirms Capture of Senior Al Qaeda Leader'' Department of Defense, April 2, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was a “very senior al Qaeda operative.” - Donald Rumsfeld&lt;ref name=&quot;RumsfeldTranscript040302&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was a “key terrorist recruiter and operational planner and member of Osama bin Laden’s inner circle.” - White House spokesman Ari Fleischer&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCProfileZubaydah&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/1907462.stm ''Profile: Abu Zubaydah'' BBC News, April 2, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*The capture of Abu Zubaydah was a “very serious blow” to al-Qaeda and that one of al-Qaeda's “many tentacles&quot; was &quot;cut off.” - White House spokesman Ari Fleischer&lt;ref name=&quot;NewsRecap&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-84361428.html ''World: United States'' Western Mail, April 3, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “one of the top operatives plotting and planning death and destruction on the United States.” - Former President George W. Bush&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush04092002Speech&quot;&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2002/04/20020409-8.html George W. Bush ''Remarks by the President at Connecticut Republican Committee Luncheon'' White House website, April 9, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “one of al-Qaeda’s top leaders” who was “spending a lot of time as one of the top operating officials of al Qaeda, plotting and planning murder.” - Former President George W. Bush&lt;ref name=&quot;BushVMIComments&quot;&gt;George W. Bush’s Remarks at the Virginia Military Institute, April 17, 2002&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “al Qaeda’s chief of operations.” - President George W. Bush&lt;ref name=&quot;BushStateOfUnion2002&quot;&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2002/06/20020606-8.html George W. Bush, ''Remarks by the President in Address to the Nation'' White House website, June 6, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*“Abu Zubaydah was one of the top three leaders” in al-Qaeda. - President George W. Bush&lt;ref name=&quot;BushThaddeusComments&quot;&gt;[http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2002/10/20021014-3.html George W. Bush ''Remarks by the President at Thaddeus McCotter for Congress Dinner'' White House website, October 14, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah’s interrogation “led to reliable information”, that Abu Zubaydah was a “prolific producer” of information,&lt;ref name=&quot;BlissAndCapaccio&quot;&gt;Jeff Bliss and Tony Capaccio, ''Iraq Group May Attack Outside Nation, McConnell Says'' Bloomberg.com, February 5, 2008&lt;/ref&gt; and that roughly 25 percent of the information on al Qaeda that came from human sources originated from Abu Zubaydah. - Michael Hayden&lt;ref name=&quot;EspositoAndRyan&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/TheLaw/story?id=4244423&amp;page=1 Richard Esposito and Jason Ryan ''CIA Chief: We Waterboarded. ABC News, February 5, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was one of three individuals “best positioned to know about impending terrorist atrocities.” - Michael Hayden&lt;ref name=&quot;WhiteHousePerverseArgument&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/blog/2008/02/07/BL2008020701681_pf.html ''The White House’s Perverse Argument: Opinion Watch'' The Washington Post, February 7, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is someone who was “carefully trained in techniques of disinformation.” - Richard C. Shelby&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipShenonMideastTurmoil&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFDD123EF935A15757C0A9649C8B63 Philip Shenon ''MIDEAST TURMOIL: INTELLIGENCE; Officials Say Qaeda Suspect Has Given Useful Information'' New York Times, April 26, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Nancy Pelosi, the senior Democrat on the House Intelligence Committee would describe Abu Zubaydah as being “very skilled at avoiding interrogation. He is an agent of disinformation.”&lt;ref name=&quot;AmandaRipley&quot;&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/ALLPOLITICS/05/27/time.decoding/index.html Amanda Ripley ''A look at the evolution of a terrorist-attack warning: one part truth, one part rumor and one part fear'' CNN.com, May 27, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;

Numerous anonymous U.S. officials have also made allegations against Abu Zubaydah in the press, including:

*“One Abu Zubaydah is worth a ton of guys at Gitmo.”&lt;ref name=&quot;TerrorismNotebook&quot;&gt;[http://community.seattletimes.nwsource.com/archive/?date=20030111&amp;slug=notebook11 ''Terrorism Notebook. More attacks have been prevented, officials say'' Seattle Times, January 11, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;
*He was a “senior bin Laden official” and the “former head of Egypt-based Islamic Jihad.”&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidVise&quot;/&gt;
*He “played a key role in the East Africa embassy attacks.”&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidVise&quot;/&gt;
*He was listed as a “trusted aide” to bin Laden with “growing power.”&lt;ref name=&quot;DavidVise&quot;/&gt;
*Western officials believed al-Qaeda may have been under the control of Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;Calabresi&quot;&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/ALLPOLITICS/time/2002/03/11/next.html Massimo Calabresi and Romesh Ratnesar, ''Can we stop the next attack?'' CNN News, March 4, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was an aide of bin Laden who ran training camps in Afghanistan and “coordinated terror cells in Europe and North America.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Calabresi&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was a “key terrorist recruiter, operational planner, and member of Osama Bin Laden’s inner circle.”&lt;ref name=&quot;WhosWho&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/nolpda/ukfs_news/hi/newsid_2780000/2780525.stm ''Who’s Who in al-Qaeda?'' BBC News]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was “bin Laden’s CEO”,&lt;ref name=&quot;NickSchou&quot;&gt;[http://www.ocweekly.com/2001-10-11/news/one-degree-of-separation/ Nick Schou ''One Degree of Separation'' Orange County Weekly, October 11, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; “a central figure in Al Qaeda”,&lt;ref name=&quot;MarliseSimons&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/04/world/nation-challenged-france-ninth-man-held-suspected-plot-against-paris-embassy.html Marlise Simons ''A NATION CHALLENGED: FRANCE; Ninth Man Held in Suspected Plot Against Paris Embassy'' New York Times, October 4, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt; and a “bin Laden lieutenant.”&lt;ref name=&quot;APTopNews100501&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-47362355.html ''AP Top News at 8 p.m. EDT'' Associated Press, October 5, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is Bin Laden’s “travel planner.”&lt;ref name=&quot;BinLadenVideos&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-80592999.html ''Bin Laden Videos Suggest Location'' The Cincinnati Post, December 5, 2001]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is one of bin Laden’s “confidants.”&lt;ref name=&quot;SchmittAndEckholm&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D71639F935A35752C0A9649C8B63 Eric Schmitt and Erik Eckholm ''A NATION CHALLENGED: THE HUNTED; U.S. Takes Custody of a Qaeda Trainer Seized by Pakistan'' New York Times, January 6, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is “one of a handful of men entrusted with running the terrorism network in the event of Osama bin Laden’s death or capture.”&lt;ref name=&quot;PhilipShenon&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDD103BF930A15752C0A9649C8B63 Philip Shenon ''A NATION CHALLENGED: BALKAN TRAIL; U.S. Labels an Arab Captive a Planner of Qaeda Attacks'' New York Times, January 23, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was a senior bin Laden lieutenant who was believed “to be organizing al Qaida resources to carry out attacks on American targets.”&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobalImpactNewsAlert&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-82887691.html ''Global Impact News Alert. U.S. Seeks New Head of Al Qaida Anti-American Operations'' United Press International, February 15, 2002] (Highbeam News Database Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was the fourth ranking member of al Qaida behind Bin Laden, Ayman al-Zawahiri, and Muhamed Atef.&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobalImpactNewsAlert&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was the “successor as chief of operations for al Qaida” after Muhamed Atef’s death.&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobalImpactNewsAlert&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah knows the identities of “thousands” of terrorists that passed through al Qaida training camps in Afghanistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;GlobalImpactNewsAlert&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah briefed Richard Reid, the shoe-bomber.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCProfileZubaydah&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was one of bin Laden’s top planners of terrorist operations who knew of al Qaida plots and cells.&lt;ref name=&quot;BankTerror&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-84981557.html ''BANK TERROR ATTACK FEAR; Warning issued after interview'' Birmingham Evening Mail, April 20, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah was captured after he made a cell phone call to al-Qaeda leaders in Yemen.&lt;ref name=&quot;TedBridis&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah stated al-Qaeda knew how to smuggle a dirty-bomb into the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQaedaDirtyBomb&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/1945765.stm ''Al-Qaeda claims ‘dirty bomb’ know-how'' BBC News, April 23, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; Abu Zubaydah’s information was further proof al-Qaeda was attempting to acquire weapons of mass destruction.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQaedaDirtyBomb&quot;/&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is the “connection between bin Laden and many of al-Qaida’s operational cells.”&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnLumpkin&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-52527138.html John J. Lumpkin ''Al-Qaida Captive Talks Of Terror'' AP News, April 24, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah is linked to plots to detonate apartment buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTerrorAlert&quot;&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/nation/2002/05/23/ny-alert.htm ''NY terror alert came from bin Laden aide'' USA Today, May 23, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Abu Zubaydah confirmed the fourth September 11 flight, UA 93, was intended to hit the White House.&lt;ref name=&quot;BushFacesDissent&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0205/23/mlld.00.html ''Bush Faces Dissent on European Trip'' CNN News Transcripts, May 23, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BushNoPlans&quot;&gt;[http://archives.cnn.com/2002/US/05/23/gen.war.on.terror/index.html ''Bush: ‘No war plans on my desk’ for Iraq'' CNN.com, May 23, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; (His claim is contradicted by Khalid Sheikh Mohamed and Ramzi Bin al Shibh though, who stated UA 93 was on its way to the capitol, not the White House.)&lt;ref name=&quot;JohnLumpkinAlQaidaChiefs&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-95918094.html John J. Lumpkin ''Many Al-Qaida Chiefs Remain Unreachable'' The Cincinnati Post, December 27, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Osama bin Laden wrote a handwritten note to Abu Zubaydah in December, 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNPaulaZahn&quot;&gt;[http://premium.edition.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0207/01/ltm.02.html ''CNN American Morning With Paula Zahn'' CNN.com, July 1, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; The letter allegedly tells Abu Zubaydah to continue fighting the United States if bin Laden passes away.&lt;ref name=&quot;CNNPaulaZahn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TravelWatch&quot;&gt;[http://tvnz.co.nz/view/tvnz_portable_story_skin/112640 ''Travel Watch'' ONE News, July 1, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;

While Abu Zubaydah would provide important intelligence on the War on Terror, his value as an intel source was greatly inflated, much like his role in the global terror network.

Despite all of these allegations the U.S. Government has not officially charged Abu Zubaydah with any crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurrentChargeSheets&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissions.html Department of Defense Military Commissions Cases Website, April 30, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exploitation of Abu Zubaydah's perceived value===
President Bush personally used Abu Zubaydah’s perceived “value” as a detainee to justify the use of the CIA's harsher interrogation techniques&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush092006Speech&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/06/washington/06bush_transcript.html?pagewanted=all ''George W. Bush September 2006 Speech'' September 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; as well as Abu Zubaydah’s detention in secret CIA prisons around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;BushConcedesCIA&quot;&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=5776107 ''Bush Concedes CIA Held Suspects in Secret Prisons'' NPR, September 6, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

In a speech in 2006, President Bush claimed that Abu Zubaydah initially revealed useful intelligence, including information that allegedly helped foil a terrorist attack on American soil, but that Abu Zubaydah became uncooperative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush092006Speech&quot;/&gt; It was only then, he reported, that an “alternative set of procedures” was used on Abu Zubaydah in order to gain valuable intelligence and were “safe and lawful.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush092006Speech&quot;/&gt; He also stated that Abu Zubaydah had received training in how to resist interrogation, and thus more aggressive techniques were mandated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bush092006Speech&quot;/&gt; These claims directly conflict with the reports of the original F.B.I. agents tasked with interrogating Abu Zubaydah who had been receiving crucial pieces of information from him without the use of harsher techniques,&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanOpEd&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SoufanNewsweek&quot;/&gt; as well as other government officials.&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTimesProfileZubaydah&quot;&gt;[http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/people/z/abu_zubaydah/index.html ''Abu Zubaydah'' New York Times, April 20, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

====The Iraq War====
The U.S. Government used questionable intel from Abu Zubaydah in order to justify the invasion of Iraq. U.S. officials stated that the allegations that Iraq and al-Qaeda were linked in the training of people on chemical weapons came from Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;HutchesonAndKuhnhenn&quot;&gt;[http://www2.jsonline.com/news/nat/sep02/83149.asp Ron Hutcheson and James Kuhnhenn ''Iraq deal with Congress nears, Bush says'' Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, September 26, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BushSaysIraq&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-7430560_ITM ''Bush Says He and Congress Will Band Together on Iraq; Capitol Hill Still Sour'' Knight Ridder/Tribune Business News, September 27, 2002] (Access My Library Link, requires free membership)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TorturedLie&quot;&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/columnists/andrew_sullivan/article6168270.ece Andrew Sullivan ''One tortured lie: that's all it took for war'' The Sunday Times, April 26, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; The officials noted there was no independent verification of his claims.&lt;ref name=&quot;HutchesonAndKuhnhenn&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BushSaysIraq&quot;/&gt; The U.S. Government included statements made by Abu Zubaydah in regards to al Qaeda’s ability to obtain a dirty bomb in its attempts to show a link between Iraq and al Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;FritzUmbach&quot;&gt;[http://www.salon.com/opinion/feature/2006/04/13/document_dump/ Fritz Umbach ''Bush’s bogus document dump'' The Salon, April 13, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a Senate Intelligence Committee report Abu Zubaydah also “indicated that he had heard that an important al Qaeda associate, Abu Musab al Zarqawi, and others had good relationships with Iraqi intelligence.”&lt;ref name=&quot;StephenHayes&quot;&gt;[http://www.weeklystandard.com/Content/Public/Articles/000/000/004/803czhfn.asp?pg=2 Stephen F. Hayes ''The Rice Stuff?'' The Daily Standard, October 20, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt; However, in June, 2003 Abu Zubaydah and Khalid Sheikh Mohammed were reported as stating there was no link between Saddam Hussein and al Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;DiamondAndNichols&quot;&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2003-06-08-cia-usat_x.htm John Diamond and Bill Nichols ''CIA in spotlight over reports leading to war'' June 8, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JamesRisen&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4D61539F93AA35755C0A9659C8B63 James Risen ''THREATS AND RESPONSES: C.I.A.; Captives Deny Qaeda Worked With Baghdad'' New York Times, June 9, 2003]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the Senate Armed Services Committee report on the abuses of detainees, it was revealed that pressure from the Bush administration was applied to interrogators to find a link between Iraq and Al-Qaeda.&lt;ref name=&quot;BanalityOfBush&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2009/04/26/opinion/26rich.html Frank Rich ''The Banality of Bush White House Evil'' The New York Times, April 25, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, Major Paul Burney, a psychiatrist with the United States Army, reported that &quot;while we were [at Guantanamo] a large part of the time we were focused on trying to establish a link between Al Qaeda and Iraq and we were not being successful.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BanalityOfBush&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArmedServicesDetaineeReport&quot;&gt;[http://armed-services.senate.gov/Publications/Detainee%20Report%20Final_April%2022%202009.pdf Senate Armed Services Committee ''Inquiry Into the Treatment of Detainees in U.S. Custody'' Senate Armed Services Committee, November 20, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; He stated that higher-ups for more &quot;frustrated&quot; and applied &quot;more and more pressure to resort to measures that might produce more immediate results.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;BanalityOfBush&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArmedServicesDetaineeReport&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EdBrayton&quot;&gt;[http://scienceblogs.com/dispatches/2009/05/the_lies_on_torture_just_keep.php Ed Brayton ''The Lies on Torture Just Keep Coming'' Science Blogs, May 4, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, Colonel Lawrence B. Wilkerson, the former chief of staff for former Secretary of State Colin Powell has stated that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Likewise, what I have learned is that as the administration authorized harsh interrogation in April and May of 2002--well before the Justice Department had rendered any legal opinion--its principal priority for intelligence was not aimed at pre-empting another terrorist attack on the U.S. but discovering a smoking gun linking Iraq and al-Qa'ida.

So furious was this effort that on one particular detainee, even when the interrogation team had reported to Cheney's office that their detainee &quot;was compliant&quot; (meaning the team recommended no more torture), the VP's office ordered them to continue the enhanced methods. The detainee had not revealed any al-Qa'ida-Baghdad contacts yet. This ceased only after Ibn al-Shaykh al-Libi, under waterboarding in Egypt, &quot;revealed&quot; such contacts. Of course later we learned that al-Libi revealed these contacts only to get the torture to stop.&lt;ref name=ArmedServicesDetaineeReport/&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====The Military Commissions Act====
President Bush also asked Congress in a speech in September 2006 to formulate special rules in order to try Abu Zubaydah via military commission in Guantanamo Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;WarrenRichey&quot;&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/2006/0915/p01s02-usju.html?s=widep Warren Richey ''‘Alternative’ CIA tactics complicate Padilla case'' Christian Science Monitor, September 15, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, in late April 2002 less than one month after Abu Zubaydah’s capture, Justice Department officials stated Abu Zubaydah “is a near-ideal candidate for a tribunal trial.”&lt;ref name=&quot;NeilALewis&quot;&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DE103FF932A15757C0A9649C8B63 Neail A. Lewis ''A NATION CHALLENGED: THE DETAINEES; U.S. Is Seeking Basis to Charge War Detainees'' New York Times, April 21, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; However, only several months later US Officials acknowledged there was “no rush” to try Abu Zubaydah via military commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;FrankDavies&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-8932707_ITM Frank Davies ''U.S. readies tribunals for terrorism trials'' The Miami Herald, December 26, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2006, President Bush stated in an interview that if Congress could pass a “good bill” out of the Senate in regards to setting up a military commission system, then Abu Zubaydah “is going to go on trial.”&lt;ref name=&quot;BushCNNInterview&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-18409075_ITM Wolf Blitzer ''Interview of George W. Bush'' CNN, September 20, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Government has yet to try Abu Zubaydah by military commission, article 3 court, or in any other capacity.

====The Bush Administration's domestic spying program====
In addition to justifying the use of presently illegal torture techniques, the Bush administration used Abu Zubaydah’s capture as justification to accelerate its domestic spying program to allow quick action on the phone numbers and addresses seized during Abu Zubaydah’s capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;RisenAndLichtblau&quot;&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2005/12/16/news/spy.php?page=2 James Risen and Eric Lichtblau ''Bush altered rules on spying'' International Herald Tribune, December 17, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; Inexplicably the NSA expanded its surveillance beyond the numbers seized during Abu Zubaydah’s capture.&lt;ref name=&quot;AzizHug&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-26038899_ITM Aziz Huq ''Who’s watching whom?'' League of Women Voters, October 1, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The spying program would later be revamped in order to make it theoretically legal.&lt;ref name=mayer/&gt;

===Growing concerns about Abu Zubaydah's indefinite CIA detention===
In 2004 media coverage of Abu Zubaydah began listing him as a “disappeared” prisoner claiming he had no access to the International Red Cross.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReedBrody&quot;&gt;[http://www.iht.com/articles/2004/10/11/opinion/edbrody.php Reed Brody ''Prisoners who disappear'' International Herald Tribune, October 12, 2004]&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 2005, U.S. officials claim the CIA was growing uncomfortable keeping Abu Zubaydah in indefinite custody.&lt;ref name=&quot;JehlAndJohnstonAndLewis&quot;&gt;[http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-105455175.html Douglas Jehl, David Johnston, and Neil A. Lewis ''CIA called uncomfortable with role on war prisoners Holding terror suspects raises concerns'' International Herald Tribune, February 16, 2005]&lt;/ref&gt; Less than 18 months later Abu Zubaydah and the other high value detainees who had been in secret CIA custody were transferred to Guantanamo Bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;BartonGellman&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/06/19/AR2006061901211.html Barton Gellman ''The Shadow War, In a Surprising New Light'' Washington Post, June 20, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;

After his transfer the CIA denied access to Abu Zubaydah even to the Department of Justice's Inspector General who was investigating the United States' treatment of its detainees.&lt;ref name=&quot;EmmaSchwartz&quot;&gt;[http://www.usnews.com/articles/news/2008/05/20/justice-dept-inspector-general-claims-cia-hampered-its-investigation.html Emma Schwartz ''Justice Dept. Inspector General Claims CIA Hampered its Investigation'' US News &amp; World Report, May 20, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to U.S. officials quoted in Ron Suskind’s book, President Bush allegedly told CIA director George Tenet “I said [Abu Zubaydah] was important. You’re not going to let me lose face on this, are you?”&lt;ref name=&quot;BartonGellman&quot;/&gt; Tenet replied “No sir, Mr. President.”&lt;ref name=&quot;BartonGellman&quot;/&gt;

===U.S. government admits Abu Zubaydah was never a member of al Qaeda===
Top officials in the U.S. government refused to believe Abu Zubaydah was not the operative they believed him to be.&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The May 30, 2005 Department of Justice memo noted that while on-scene interrogators believed Abu Zubaydah no longer had any information to disclose, CIA Headquarters ordered additional waterboarding.&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; The interrogators believed the waterboarding was &quot;unnecessary.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;May302005BradburyMemo&quot;/&gt; Orders for the additional waterboarding likely came from Dick Cheney directly.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArmedServicesDetaineeReport&quot;/&gt; Additionally, the Bush White House and CIA officials couldn't believe Abu Zubaydah didn't have additional information.&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt; One official stated the pressure from upper levels of government was &quot;tremendous,&quot; and that &quot;[t]hey couldn't stand the idea that there wasn't anything new.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt; The official said, &quot;[t]hey'd say, 'You aren't working hard enough.' There was both a disbelief in what he was saying and also a desire for retribution - a feeling that 'He's going to talk, and if he doesn't talk, we'll do whatever.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;FinnAndWarrick&quot;/&gt;

However, in September 2009, the United States Government finally admitted, during Abu Zubaydah's habeas corpus petition, that Abu Zubaydah had never been a member of al-Qaeda, nor involved in the attacks on the African embassies in 1998, or the attacks on the United States on September 11, 2001.&lt;ref name=GovernmentWithdrawsCharges&gt;{{cite court
| litigants=Zayn al Abidin Muhammad Husayn v. Robert Gates
| vol=Respondents Memorandum of Points and Authorities in Opposition to Petitioner's Motion for Discover and Petitioner's Motion for Sanctions.
| reporter=Civil Action No. 08-cv-1360 (RWR)
| date=September 2009
| url=http://www.truth-out.org/files/memorandum.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt; The motion, filed by the United States Government, states:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Evidence indicating that Petitioner is not a member of al-Qaida or had ideological differences with al-Qaida is not inconsistent with the factual allegations made in the Government's factual return, because the Government has not contended in this proceeding that Petitioner was a member of al-Qaida or otherwise formally identified with al-Qaida. Pg. 35, 36
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Respondent [The United States Government] does not contend that Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] was a &quot;member&quot; of al-Qaida in the sense of having sworn a &lt;u&gt;bayat&lt;/u&gt; (allegiance) or having otherwise satisfied any formal criteria that either Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] or al-Qaida may have considered necessary for inclusion in al-Qaida. Nor is the Government detaining Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] based on any allegation that Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] views himself as part of al-Qaida as a matter of subjective personal conscience, ideology, or worldview. Pg. 36
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Government has not contended in this proceeding that Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] had any direct role in or advance knowledge of the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001. Pg. 82
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
For example, for purposes of this proceeding the Government has not contended that Petitioner [Abu Zubaydah] had any personal involvement in planning or executing either the 1998 embassy bombings... or the attacks on September 11, 2001. Pg. 34
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

====Charge sheet discrepancies====
In 2005, the U.S. Government charged several detainees at Guantanamo Bay and ordered them to stand trial in Military Commission Tribunals.&lt;ref name=&quot;ArchivedChargeSheets&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissionsarchives.html ''Department of Defense Website: Archived Charge Sheets'' Department of Defense]&lt;/ref&gt; Of the ten detainees charged, four of them, Binyam Mohamed, Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi, Sufyian Barhoumi, and Jabrad Said bin Al-Qahtani referenced Abu Zubaydah in their charge sheets.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtani2005ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Nov2005/d20051104qahtani.pdf ''Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani 2005 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbi2005ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Nov2005/d20051104sharbi.pdf ''Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi 2005 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barhoumi2005ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Nov2005/d20051104barhoumi.pdf ''Sufyian Barhoumi 2005 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Binyam2005ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Nov2005/d20051104muhammad.pdf ''Binyam Mohamed 2005 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt; Three of the four detainees, Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi, Sufyian Barhoumi, and Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani, had identical 2005 charge sheets and referenced Abu Zubaydah in six different paragraphs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtani2005ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbi2005ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barhoumi2005ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt; The fourth detainee, Binyam Mohamed, referenced Abu Zubaydah five times.&lt;ref name=&quot;Binyam2005ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;

In 2006, before the U.S. Government could hold a trial of the four detainees in a Military Commission Tribunal, the Supreme Court struck down the Tribunals as unconstitutional in Hamdan v. Bush.&lt;ref name=&quot;JosephMarguliesGuantanamo&quot;&gt;Joseph Margulies ''Guantanamo and the Abuse of Presidential Power'' Simon &amp; Schuster, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuzanneGoldberg&quot;&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2006/jun/30/usa.guantanamo Suzanne Goldenberg ''Supreme Court Rejects Bush Terror Powers'' The Guardian, June 30, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Government responded by amending the tribunals, although they were forced to recharge Binyam Mohamed, Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi, Sufyian Barhoumi, and Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani in 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurrentChargeSheets&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissions.html ''Department of Defense Military Commissions Website'' Department of Defense]&lt;/ref&gt;

The new 2008 charge sheets contained almost identical charges against each of the four detainees, as were found in their 2005 charge sheets.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtani2008ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/d20080529Qahtani.pdf ''Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani 2008 Sworn Charges'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbi2008ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/d20080529Sharbi.pdf ''Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi’s 2008 Sworn Charges'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barhoumi2008ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/d20080529Sufyian.pdf ''Sufyian Barhoumi’s 2008 Sworn Charges'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Binyam2008ChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/Mohamed%20-%20sworn0603.pdf ''Binyam Mohamed 2008 Sworn Charges'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt; However, Abu Zubaydah’s name was entirely removed from each detainee’s charge sheet.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtani2008ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbi2008ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Barhoumi2008ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Binyam2008ChargeSheet&quot;/&gt; On October 21, 2008, all charges were dropped against the four men.&lt;ref name=&quot;JaneSutton&quot;&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/topNews/idUSTRE49K65120081021?sp=true Jane Sutton ''U.S. drops charges against 5 Guantanamo captives'' Reuters, October 21, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoJudgeDefies&quot;&gt;[http://articles.latimes.com/2009/jan/30/nation/na-guantanamo-judge30?pg=1 Carol J. Williams ''Guantanamo judge defies Obama'' Los Angeles Times, January 30, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Binyam Mohamed was released from Guantanamo Bay on February 20, 2009 despite his alleged connections to Abu Zubaydah, and thus has been removed from the Department of Defense Military Commissions Page.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurrentChargeSheets&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;BBCProfileBinyam&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/7906381.stm ''Profile: Binyam Mohamed'' BBC News, February 23, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, the alleged emir of [[Khalden Camp]], [[Noor Uthman Muhammed]], was charged in 2008 with conspiring with Abu Zubaydah against the United States. However, the charges against Noor Uthman Muhammed were also completely dropped on October 21, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;JaneSutton&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GuantanamoJudgeDefies&quot;/&gt; The U.S. Government recharged Noor Uthman Muhammed on December 22, 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCurrentCharges&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah's name is not found in any of the charges even though he was a facilitator for Noor Uthman Muhammed's Khalden Camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;NoorUthmanCurrentCharges&quot;/&gt;

Abu Zubaydah’s name is also not mentioned in any other detainee’s charge sheets, not even Khalid Sheikh Mohamed, the admitted mastermind of the 9/11 attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurrentChargeSheets&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;EdPilkington&quot;&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2007/mar/15/alqaida.september11 Ed Pilkington '''I was responsible for 9/11, from A to Z' - a confession from Guantánamo Bay'' The Guardian, March 15, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Government has also failed to charge Abu Zubadyah, even though they have charged other high ranking al-Qaeda members, such as Khalid Sheikh Mohamed, who has been in custody less time than Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;CurrentChargeSheets&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;KSMCharges&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/d20080509Mohammed.pdf ''Khalid Sheikh Mohammed Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, the U.S. Government recharged two of the men, Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi and Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbiCurrentChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/alSharbi.pdf ''Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi 2009 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtaniCurrentChargeSheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/alQahtanisworn.pdf ''Jabran Said bin Al-Qahtani 2009 Charge Sheet'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt; Sufyian Barhoumi has not been recharged.&lt;ref name=&quot;BarhoumiChargesPage&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissionsBarhoumi.html ''Sufyian Barhoumi Military Commissions Page'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt; The 2009 charge sheet of al Sharbi reincorporates Abu Zubaydah in three paragraphs, while the 2009 charge sheet of Al-Qahtani reincorporated Abu Zubaydah in four paragraphs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbiCurrentChargeSheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AlQahtaniCurrentChargeSheet&quot;/&gt; Unlike the 2005 charge sheets, which are archived on the Department of Defense website, Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi's 2008 Charge Sheet has been removed from his page.&lt;ref name=&quot;AlSharbiChargesPage&quot;&gt;[http://www.defenselink.mil/news/commissionsSharbi.html ''Ghassan Abdullah al Sharbi Military Commissions Page'' Department of Defense Website]&lt;/ref&gt;

====International cases involving Abu Zubaydah====
Several individuals being held or tried internationally, who have been connected by the U.S. Government to Abu Zubaydah, have had their charges dropped, been released, or received other relief from their handlers.

=====Abousofian Abdelrazik=====
[[Abousofian Abdelrazik]] was alleged by the State Department to be closely associated with Abu Zubaydah.&lt;ref name=&quot;BradFoss&quot;&gt;[http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-16119183_ITM Brad Foss ''State Department moves against Sudanese-Canadian for alleged terror ties'' The America’s Intelligence Wire, July 26, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt; In 2008, Canada asked the United Nations to remove Abousfian Abdelrazik from its terrorism watch-list.&lt;ref name=&quot;PaulKoringOttawa&quot;&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v5/content/subscribe?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/LAC.20080502.SUDAN02/TPStory/Front&amp;ord=123654973&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;force_login=true Paul Koring ''Ottawa wants terrorism suspect taken off watch list'' Globe and Mail, February 5, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; In June, 2009, Canada agreed to repatriate Abousfian Abdelrazik from Sudan where he has been stranded since 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;MichaelComte&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5hUaf3TZSzmnZORHAtaID8uB1DNnw Michael Comte ''Canada will repatriate man said linked to Al-Qaeda'' AFP, June 18, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

=====Mohamed Harkat=====
Abu Zubaydah supposedly knew [[Mohamed Harkat]] “since the early 90’s”&lt;ref name=&quot;PeterCheney&quot;&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/ArticleNews/front/RTGAM/20021218/wxalge1218/Front/homeBN/breakingnews Peter Cheney ''Bin Laden lieutenant identified suspect in Canada'' The Globe and Mail, December 18, 2002]&lt;/ref&gt; and claimed Harkat ran a guest house in Pakistan.&lt;ref name=&quot;CanadaCourtUpholds&quot;&gt;''Court upholds Harkat’s security certificate'' CTV News, March 22, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Mohamed Harkat’s attorney sought access to Abu Zubaydah for testimony relating to Harkat’s trial, but the US refused to respond to his requests.&lt;ref name=&quot;HarkatLawyer&quot;&gt;[http://www.edmontonsun.com/News/Canada/2007/08/26/4448108.html ''Lawyer for accused terrorist seeks access to Guantanamo detainee'' Edmonton Sun, August 26, 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally in Harkat’s Canadian trial, however, Abu Zubaydah’s claims were not part of the charges brought against Harkat.&lt;ref name=&quot;ColinFreeze&quot;&gt;[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/story/RTGAM.20080222.wcertificate0222/BNStory/National/?cid=al_gam_mostdiscuss Colin Freeze, Tu Thanh Ha, and Omar El Akkad ''Secret files against terror suspects revealed'' Globe and Mail, February 23, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; After CIA director Michael Hayden’s public admittance of Zubaydah’s waterboarding, Canadian officials deleted all references to Zubaydah’s statements in its public dossier.&lt;ref name=&quot;CanadaTakesAStand&quot;&gt;[http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=87975164 The Bryant Park Project ''Canada Takes a Stand Against Alleged U.S. Torture'' National Public Radio, March 7, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; A spokesman for the Canadian Security Intelligence Service stated “The CSIS director has stated publicly that torture is morally repugnant and not particularly reliable. CSIS does not knowingly use information which has been obtained through torture.”&lt;ref name=&quot;WaterboardEvidence&quot;&gt;[http://www.npr.org/blogs/news/2008/03/canada_wont_use_waterboard_evi.html ''Canada Won’t Use “Waterboard” Evidence'' The NPR News Blog, March 6, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt; Mohamed Harkat was released on bail by Canadian authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;HarkatReleased&quot;&gt;[http://www.swissinfo.org/eng/international/ticker/detail/Canadian_court_OKs_release_of_al_Qaeda_suspect.html?siteSect=143&amp;sid=6798381&amp;cKey=1149878259000 ''Canada court OKs release of al Qaeda Suspect'' Reuters, Swiss Info, June 9, 2006]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TerrorismSuspectReleasedOnBail&quot;&gt;''Terrorism suspect released on bail'' Dose Canada, May 24, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ahmed Ressam and the Millennium Plot====
In April 2001, Ahmed Ressam was convicted of plotting to detonate a bomb at the Los Angeles International Airport.&lt;ref name=&quot;PBSAhmedRessam&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/trail/inside/cron.html ''Amhed Ressam’s Millennium Plot'' PBS]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RessamTestimony&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/trail/inside/testimony.html ''Ahmed Ressam's Testimony at Mokhtar Haouari's Trial'' PBS]&lt;/ref&gt; Ahmed Ressam had previously trained at the Khalden camp before coming to the United States to undertake his mission.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PBSAhmedRessam&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RessamTestimony&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah admits in his CSRT testimony that he recommended to the leader of Khalden Camp that Ahmed Ressam be allowed to train there.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah further testified that he facilitated Ahmed Ressam’s travel to the camp as well as to Algeria once Ressam’s training was complete.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; The U.S. Government alleges, in Abu Zubaydah’s summary of evidence, that Ahmed Ressam identified Abu Zubaydah as the leader of the Khalden camp and an associate of Usama Bin Laden “equal to and not subordinate to UBL.”&lt;ref name=&quot;AbuZubaydahSummaryOfEvidence&quot;&gt;[http://www.dod.mil/pubs/foi/detainees/csrt_arb/000784-000819.pdf ''Abu Zubaydah Summary of Evidence'' Department of Defense]&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Government further alleges that Ahmed Ressam stated that Abu Zubaydah had “known of Ahmed Ressam’s operation, although not specifically the date and exact target” and that Abu Zubaydah wanted Ressam to acquire “fraudulently-obtained Canadian passports” for himself and five others, in order to facilitate their travel into the United States to “possibly bomb several cities.”&lt;ref name=&quot;AbuZubaydahSummaryOfEvidence&quot;/&gt;

Abu Zubaydah admits he attempted to procure Canadian passports for Ahmed Ressam and other trainees, but not for &quot;terrorist-related activities.”.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah denies ever having participated in the planning of the Millennium Plot or encouraging Ahmed Ressam to attack American targets or civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;CsrtAbuZubaydahVerbatimTranscript&quot;/&gt; The U.S. Government has not produced any further evidence of Abu Zubaydah’s alleged role in the Millennium Plot, nor was this connection even mentioned in Ahmed Ressam's criminal trial.&lt;ref name=&quot;RessamCaseDocs&quot;&gt;Ressam Case Documents, Accessed via PACER, December 2008&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, Ressam's confessions were only brought up during his sentencing in an attempt to mitigate the sentence he would receive, and he later recanted them.&lt;ref name=&quot;RessamCaseDocs&quot;/&gt;

===Abu Zubaydah's mental health===
Some people contest Abu Zubaydah's mental health. Ron Suskind noted in his book, &lt;u&gt;The One Percent Doctrine&lt;/u&gt;, that Zubaydah turned out to be mentally ill, keeping a diary &quot;in the voice of three people: Hani 1, Hani 2, and Hani 3&quot; -- a boy, a young man and a middle-aged alter ego.&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindOnePercent&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah's diaries spanned ten years and recorded in numbing detail &quot;what he ate, or wore, or trifling things [people] said.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EggenPincusFBICIADebate&quot;/&gt; Dan Coleman, then the FBI's top al-Qaeda analyst, told a senior bureau official, &quot;This guy is insane, certifiable, split personality.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindOnePercent&quot;/&gt; According to Suskind, this judgment was &quot;echoed at the top of CIA and was briefed to the President and Vice President.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;SuskindOnePercent&quot;/&gt; Dan Coleman, the FBI's senior expert on al Qaeda, echoed many of Suskind's sentiments in an interview with the Washington Post. Coleman stated Zubaydah was a &quot;safehouse keeper&quot; with mental problems, who &quot;claimed to know more about al-Qaeda and its inner workings than he really did.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;EggenPincusFBICIADebate&quot;/&gt; Abu Zubaydah's co-counsel, Joseph Margulies, wrote in an OpEd in the LA Times that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Partly as a result of injuries he suffered while he was fighting the communists in Afghanistan, partly as a result of how those injuries were exacerbated by the CIA and partly as a result of his extended isolation, Abu Zubaydah's mental grasp is slipping away. Today, he suffers blinding headaches and has permanent brain damage. He has an excruciating sensitivity to sounds, hearing what others do not. The slightest noise drives him nearly insane. In the last two years alone, he has experienced about 200 seizures. Already, he cannot picture his mother's face or recall his father's name. Gradually, his past, like his future, eludes him.&lt;ref name=&quot;MarguliesZubaydah&quot;&gt;[http://www.latimes.com/news/opinion/la-oe-margulies30-2009apr30,0,3309097.story Joseph Margulies ''Abu Zubaydah's suffering'' Los Angeles Times, April 30, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Saudi and Pakistani connection allegations==
[[Gerald Posner]] in his book &quot;Why America Slept: The Failure to Prevent 9/11&quot; claimed that Abu Zubaydahwas duped by U.S. interrogators masquerading as Saudis and using painkillers and [[sodium pentathol]], sometimes called &quot;truth serum&quot;. Zubaydah, he writes, thought he was in a Saudi prison, when in fact he was in Afghanistan. Posner says Zubaydah, &quot;relieved&quot; to find he was being quizzed by people he thought were Saudis, provided them with phone numbers for a senior member of the Saudi royal family who would &quot;tell you what to do.&quot; He says the U.S. interrogators were stunned when the numbers were traced to Prince [[Ahmed bin Salman bin Abdul Aziz]], a nephew of [[Fahd of Saudi Arabia|King Fahd]]. 

When the agents accused Zubaydah of lying, he revealed more details of Saudi and Pakistani ties to bin Laden, the author says, and in the space of one week, three of the four persons named by him were dead. Prince Ahmed, 43, died of a heart attack on July 22, 2002. The next day, a car crash killed Saudi Prince [[Sultan bin Faisal bin Turki al-Saud]], 41. A week later, Prince [[Fahd bin Turki bin Saud al-Kabir]], 25, reportedly died &quot;of thirst&quot; while traveling east of [[Riyadh]]. Seven months later, a plane crash &quot;in clear weather,&quot; Posner says, killed Pakistani Air Marshal [[Mushaf Ali Mir]], his wife and several aides in Pakistan.&lt;ref&gt;[Author: Did Saudis know of 9-11 plot? by RICHARD PYLE]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;div class=&quot;references-small&quot;&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

{{Wikisource|Verbatim Transcript of Combatant Status Review Tribunal Hearing for ISN 10016}}
{{Wikisource|CSRT Summary of Evidence memo for Zayn al Abidin Muhammad Husayn}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gpoaccess.gov/911/index.html The Final 9/11 Commission Report]
* [http://armed-services.senate.gov/Publications/Detainee%20Report%20Final_April%2022%202009.pdf Committee on Armed Services United States Senate: Inquiry Into the Treatment of Detainees in U.S. Custody]
* [http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_08012002_bybee.pdf Jay Bybee and John Yoo ''Memorandum for John Rizzo Acting General Counsel of the Central Intelligence Agency: Interrogation of al Qaeda Operative'' U.S. Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, August 1, 2002]
* [http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05102005_bradbury46pg.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memorandum for John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency, Office of Legal Counsel Re: Application of 18 U.S.C. Sections 2340-2340A to Certain Techniques That May Be Used in the Interrogation of a High Value al Qaeda Detainee'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 10, 2005]
* [http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05102005_bradbury20pg.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memorandum For John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency Re: Application of 18 U.S.C. §§ 2340-2340A to the Combined Use of Certain Techniques in the Interrogation of High Value al Qaeda Detainees'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 10, 2005]
* [http://luxmedia.vo.llnwd.net/o10/clients/aclu/olc_05302005_bradbury.pdf Steven Bradbury ''Memoradnum for John A. Rizzo Senior Deputy General Counsel, Central Intelligence Agency Re: Application of United States Obligations Under Article 16 of the Convention Against Torture to Certain Techniques that May Be Used in the Interrogation of High Value al Qaeda Detainees'' Department of Justice, Office of Legal Counsel, May 30, 2005]
* [http://www.usdoj.gov/oig/special/s0805/final.pdf ''U.S. Department of Justice, Office of Inspector General: A Review of the FBI's Involvement in and Observations of Detainee Interrogations in Guantanamo Bay, Afghanistan, and Iraq'' Department of Justice, Office of Inspector General, May 2008]
*Human Rights First; [http://www.humanrightsfirst.info/pdf/08307-etn-tortured-justice-web.pdf Tortured Justice: Using Coerced Evidence to Prosecute Terrorist Suspects (2008)]
*Human Rights First; [http://www.humanrightsfirst.info/pdf/HRF-Undue-Process-Afghanistan-web.pdf Undue Process: An Examination of Detention and Trials of Bagram Detainees in Afghanistan in April 2009 (2009)]
*[http://www.andyworthington.co.uk/2011/01/20/former-cia-ghost-prisoner-abu-zubaydah-recognized-as-victim-in-polish-probe-of-secret-prison/ Former CIA “Ghost Prisoner” Abu Zubaydah Recognized as “Victim” in Polish Probe of Secret Prison] Andy Worthington
*{{NYTtopic|people/z/abu_zubaydah}}
*{{Worldcat id|np-zubaydah,%20abu}}

{{CIAPrisons}}
{{3IC}}
{{HighValue}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Abu Zubaydah
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Guananamo detainee
| DATE OF BIRTH     = March 12, 1971
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = 
| DATE OF DEATH     = 
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Zubaydah, Abu}}
[[Category:1971 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Saudi Arabian extrajudicial prisoners of the United States]]
[[Category:People held at the Guantanamo Bay detention camp]]
[[Category:Interrogations]]
[[Category:Saudi Arabian expatriates in Pakistan]]
[[Category:People subject to extraordinary rendition by the United States]]
[[Category:Saudi Arabian torture victims]]

[[de:Abu Zubaydah]]
[[es:Abu Zubaydah]]
[[fr:Abou Zoubaydah]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
