<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="311764" ns="0" title="Lawrence University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the liberal arts college in Wisconsin|the similarly named university in Michigan|Lawrence Technological University}}
{{Infobox university
|image_name     = Lawrence University seal.png
|image_size     = 190px
|name           = Lawrence University
|motto          = Light More Light!&lt;br /&gt;Veritas est lux
|mottoeng       = ''Truth is Light''
|established    = 1847
|type           = [[Private school|Private]] - [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|Liberal Arts]]
|president      = Jill Beck
|city           = [[Appleton, Wisconsin|Appleton]]
|state          = [[Wisconsin]]
|country        = [[United States]]
|students       = 1,566 undergraduates&lt;br&gt;''(fall 2010)''&lt;ref name=2010profile&gt;As of Fall 2010.  {{Cite web | title = 2010 Profile | publisher = Lawrence University | url = http://lawrence.edu/about/lu_factsheet.pdf | format = PDF | accessdate = June 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff          = 156 faculty&lt;ref name=2010profile/&gt;
|campus         = [[Urban area|Urban]] - {{convert|84|acre|ha|0}} &lt;br&gt;[[Björklunden]] - {{convert|425|acre|ha|0}}|mascot         =
|free_label     = Athletics
|free           = [[Division III (NCAA)]]&lt;br&gt;23 varsity teams
|affiliations   = [[Associated Colleges of the Midwest]]
|former_names   = Lawrence College - (1913-64)&lt;br&gt;Lawrence Institute - (1847-49)
|endowment      = $180.2 million&lt;ref name=2010profile/&gt;
|website        = [http://www.lawrence.edu/ Lawrence.edu]
}}
'''Lawrence University''' is a selective, private [[Liberal arts colleges in the United States|liberal arts college]] with a nationally recognized conservatory of music, in [[Appleton, Wisconsin|Appleton]], [[Wisconsin]]. Lawrence University is known for its rigorous academic environment. Founded in 1847, the first classes were held on November 12, 1849. Lawrence was the second college in the [[United States]] to be founded as a [[coeducational]] institution.

The {{convert|84|acre|ha|0|adj=on}} campus is located in downtown Appleton, divided into two parts by the Fox River. The academic campus is on the north shore of Fox River, and the major athletic facilities (including the 5000-seat Banta Bowl) are on the northeast shore. Lawrence University also has a {{convert|425|acre|ha|0|sing=on}} northern estate called [[Björklunden]] (full name: Björklunden vid sjön), which serves as a site for retreats, seminars, concerts, and theatrical performances.  It also contains a chapel for weddings.  Donald and Winifred Boynton of [[Highland Park, Illinois|Highland Park]], [[Illinois]], donated the property in [[Door County, Wisconsin|Door County]] to Lawrence in 1963.

The student newspaper, ''[[The Lawrentian]]'', has a history of over a century of publications. Lawrence University hosts the [[Great Midwest Trivia Contest]], webcast every January over the college radio station, [[WLFM]].

Lawrence University is part of the [[Oberlin Group]], a consortium of liberal arts college libraries.

==History==
Lawrence's first president, William Harkness Sampson founded the school with [[Henry R. Colman]], using $10,000 provided by [[philanthropist]] [[Amos Adams Lawrence]], and matched by the [[Methodist]] church. Both founders were ordained Methodist [[minister of religion|ministers]], but Lawrence was [[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopalian]]. The school was originally named '''Lawrence Institute''' in its 1847 charter from the Wisconsin Territorial Legislature, but was changed to Lawrence University before classes began in November 1849.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lawrence.edu/library/archives/history.shtml www.lawrence.edu/library/archives/history.shtml]&lt;/ref&gt; Its oldest extant building, [[Main Hall (Lawrence University)|Main Hall]], was built in 1853.&lt;ref name=hcap&gt;Council of Independent Colleges, &quot;[http://hcap.artstor.org/cgi-bin/library?a=d&amp;d=p976 Main Hall]&quot;, Historic Campus Architecture Project.&lt;/ref&gt; Lawrence University was Wisconsin’s first co-educational university.{{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

Lawrence's first period of major growth came during the tenure of [[alumnus]] [[Samuel G. Plantz]] as president.  From 1894 to 1924, when Plantz presided over the school, its student body grew from 200 to 800.

During [[World War II]], Lawrence College was one of 131 colleges and universities nationally that took part in the [[V-12 Navy College Training Program]] which offered students a path to a Navy commission.&lt;ref name=&quot;lawrence-v-12&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myhistorymuseum.org/WWII/1943/lawrence.htm |title=Call to Duty, Lawrence University's V-12 Program |publisher=Outagamie County Historical Society (OCHS) |last= |first= |accessdate=September 27, 2011 |date=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1913 until 1964, the school was named '''Lawrence College''', to emphasize its small size and [[liberal arts]] education focus. The name was changed to Lawrence University when it merged with [[Milwaukee-Downer College]]. The state of Wisconsin then purchased the Milwaukee-Downer property and buildings to expand the campus of the [[University of Wisconsin–Milwaukee]]. Initially, the university designated two entities: Lawrence College for Men and Downer College for Women. This separation has not lasted in any material form, though degrees are still conferred &quot;on the recommendation of the Faculty of Lawrence and Downer Colleges&quot; and the university by-laws still make the distinction.  The Lawrence Dean of Women was referred to as the &quot;Dean of Downer&quot;, but when the offices of Dean of Men and Dean of Women were merged to form the Dean of Students, the substantive duties of the &quot;Dean of Downer&quot; came to an end; the title is still borne by a senior female professor, but her only duty is to carry the Downer Mace in academic processions.

The Lawrence Conservatory of Music, usually referred to as &quot;the Con&quot;, was founded in 1894.  The university confers a [[Bachelor of Music]] degree and offers a five-year program leading to a [[Bachelor of Arts]] in addition to the [[music]] degree.

Lawrence University originated the idea of [[freshman studies]].{{Citation needed|date=May 2009}} Freshman Studies at Lawrence is a mandatory two-term class, in which all students study the same selected 11 classic works of literature, art, and music. President [[Nathan M. Pusey]] is credited with initiating the program in 1945, although Professor Waples chaired the Freshman Studies Committee and was responsible for implementing the program. The program continues to this day, despite being temporarily suspended in 1974, and has been adapted by many liberal arts colleges. {{Citation needed|date=May 2011}}

In 2010, [[Forbes]] ranked Lawrence 50th on the list of America's (600) Best Colleges, which combined national research universities, liberal arts colleges, and military academies in a single survey&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.forbes.com/lists/2010/94/best-colleges-10_Lawrence-University_94220_2.html | work=Forbes | title=#50 Lawrence University Page 2 of 2 | date=August 11, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lawrence is ranked 60th on the U.S. News: List of Best U.S. National Liberal Arts Colleges (the rank was 40 in 2000, 53 in 2006, 59 in 2009, 67 in 2010). Lawrence is included in [[Loren Pope]]'s, ''[[Colleges That Change Lives]]''.

In 2005 Lawrence University initiated a capital campaign called &quot;More Light!&quot;, which aimed at raising $150 million. By October 2011 the college has raised $160,272,839, with the conclusion event held on October 28th, 2011&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.lawrence.edu/mlfinale/2011/10/photos-from-the-more-light-finale-celebration.html&lt;/ref&gt;.

==Milwaukee-Downer traditions==
[[File:Lawrence University.jpg|thumb|right|250px|The cupola on [[Main Hall (Lawrence University)|Main Hall]] at Lawrence University is an Appleton landmark.]]
The [[traditions]] and heritage of Milwaukee-Downer are woven into the Appleton campus, from the grove of [[Crataegus|hawthorn]] trees (called Hawthornden) between Brokaw and Colman halls, to the [[sundial]] on the back of [[Main Hall (Lawrence University)|Main Hall]], to the bestowing upon each class a class color and banner.

When the University had separate offices for a &quot;Dean of Women&quot; and a &quot;Dean of Men&quot;, the officer overseeing women students was called the &quot;Dean of Downer.&quot;  That title is still borne by the senior woman on the faculty, but her only duty now is carrying the Downer mace in academic processions.  For many years the women's choir was called the Downer Chorus.  At one time the BA was conferred upon women in the name of &quot;Downer College of Lawrence University&quot; and upon men in the name of &quot;Lawrence College of Lawrence University&quot;; now all B.A. degrees are conferred in the name of &quot;Lawrence &amp; Downer Colleges of Lawrence University.&quot; (The B.Mus. degree is from &quot;the Lawrence University Conservatory of Music.)

==Academics==
[[Image:muddlib.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Seeley G. Mudd Library. The library contains nearly 400,000 volumes.]]
Lawrence University operates on a [[Academic term|trimester]] calendar. The academic year runs from mid-September to mid-June.

The student/faculty ratio at Lawrence is 9:1.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/admissions/about/international/&lt;/ref&gt;

Lawrence grants Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Music degrees, with a [[double degree]] possible. Lawrence offers a number of cooperative degree programs in areas such as [[engineering]], [[health sciences]] and [[environmental studies]].

The college has major programs in most of the [[liberal arts]]. The school also offers the option of [[interdisciplinary]] areas of study and allows students to design their own majors.  All students are required to take Freshman Studies, which introduces students to broad areas of study and provides a common academic experience for the college.

The school has an independent study option that allows students to design their own courses. This allows students to explore academic interests not covered by Lawrence’s classes or to explore topics more deeply. Over 90% of the students take advantage of the independent study program.

In 2005, Lawrence University began the Lawrence Fellows Program, initially selecting eight recent Ph.D.s to teach and carry out research at Lawrence for a period of two to three years.  This program seeks to develop the liberal arts faculty of the future.

In the mid-1980s the physics department built a $330,000 small laser laboratory (known as the &quot;laser palace&quot;), which includes 800 5&amp;nbsp;mW small lasers and more than 500 mirrors.

==Conservatory of Music==
The Lawrence Conservatory of Music was founded in 1874 and has been a vital part of Lawrence University ever since. The Conservatory offers Bachelor of Music degrees in Performance, Theory/Composition, Music Education, and a five year double degree option that grants both a BM degree from the Conservatory and a BA degree from the College.  Approximately 25% of the Lawrence student body, or 350 students, is in the Conservatory. The Conservatory has three choirs, two bands, two jazz ensembles, a symphony orchestra, an improvisation collective, as well as five world music ensembles, and numerous chamber music groups. 

The Lawrence Conservatory regularly receives national recongnition for the excellence of its student ensembles and individual musicians.

==Razed buildings==
The college has a long history of razing buildings on its campus, because of the limited land available for constructing new buildings. Many buildings on campus are built on the site of former buildings. Some razed buildings include:
Peabody Hall of Music (20th century),
Hamar Union (1960)
Underwood Observatory (1962),
Alexander Gym I (1962),
Carnegie Library (1964),
Worcester Art Center (1987),
Stephenson Hall of Science (1998),
Hulbert House (2004),

==Student body==
Lawrence enrolls about 1,500 students who hail from nearly every U.S. state. The total enrollment in academic year 2010-2011 was 1,566 students&lt;ref name=2010profile/&gt;, the largest student body in Lawrence University's history. Over 75% of the students identify as white.&lt;ref name=2010profile/&gt;  About 12% of the students are [[international student]]s. About 25% of students study in the conservatory of music.

==Athletics==
{{Infobox college athletics
|name             = Lawrence Vikings
|logo             = Lawrence Viking.png
|university       = Lawrence University
|conference       = [[Midwest Conference]]
|division         = [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]]
|director         = Mike Szkodzinski
|SID              = Joe Vanden Acker
|city             = Appleton
|state            = Wisconsin
|stateabb         = WI
|nation           = {{USA}}
|teams            = 23
|stadium          = Banta Bowl - (5,255)&lt;br&gt;''natural grass''
|arena            = Alexander Gymnasium
|baseballfield    = Whiting Field&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lawrence.edu/athletics/facilities.shtml lawrence.edu/athletics/facilities.shtml] - accessed 2010-03-26&lt;/ref&gt;
|mascot           =
|nickname         = [[Vikings]] - ''(1926)''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lawrence.edu/about/trads/viking.shtml www.lawrence.edu/about/trads/viking.shtml] - accessed 2010-03-26&lt;/ref&gt;
|fightsong        = &quot;Go, Lawrence, Go&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lawrence.edu/about/trads/lyrics.shtml#Waring lawrence.edu/about/trads/lyrics.shtml#Waring] - accessed 2010-03-26&lt;/ref&gt;
|marching band    =
|color1           = Blue
|color2           = White
|color3           =
|hex1             = 00009C
|hex2             = FFFFFF
|hex3             =
|pageurl          = http://www.lawrence.edu/athletics/
|pagename         = LU athletics
}}
In 2005-06, the Lawrence men's basketball team was ranked number one in [[NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]] for much of the season, after starting the season unranked. The team was the only undefeated team in all divisions of college basketball for the last six weeks of the season, ending with a record of 25-1. Star forward Chris Braier won the [[Josten's Award]] as the top player in the country for both playing ability and community service. Coach John Tharp was named Division III Midwest Coach of the Year. Attendance increased to capacity for home games, causing local fire officials to demand that Lawrence cap attendance for the NCAA tournament games that Lawrence would host. The university decided to issue passes to attendees. Following their win of the Midwest Conference Tournament in 2009, the Vikings have qualified for the NCAA Division III National Tournament in five of the last six years. Their best finish was in 2004 when they lost in the Elite 8 to eventual national champion [[University of Wisconsin–Stevens Point]] 82-81 in overtime at the University of Puget Sound in Tacoma, Wash.

In 2011 Lawremces men's cross country team won the Midwest Conference Championships for the first time since 1985, beating Grinell college and ending their 14 year winning streak.

==University presidents==
* 1849-1853 [[William Harkness Sampson]], principal
* 1853-1859 [[Edward Cooke]], president
* 1859-1865 [[Russell Zelotes Mason]], president
* 1865-1879 [[George McKendree Steele]], president
* 1879-1883 [[Elias DeWitt Huntley]], president
* 1883-1889 [[Bradford Paul Raymond]], president
* 1889-1893 [[Charles Wesley Gallagher]], president
* 1893-1894 [[L. Wesley Underwood]], acting president
* 1894-1924 [[Samuel G. Plantz]], president
* 1924-1925 [[Wilson Samuel Naylor]], acting president
* 1925-1937 [[Henry Wriston|Henry Merritt Wriston]], president
* 1937-1943 [[Thomas Nichols Barrows]], president
* 1943-1944 [[Ralph Jerome Watts]], acting president
* 1944-1953 [[Nathan Marsh Pusey]], president
* 1954-1963 [[Douglas Knight|Douglas Maitland Knight]], president
* 1963-1969 [[Curtis William Tarr]], president
* 1969-1979 [[Thomas S. Smith]], president
* 1979-2004 [[Richard Warch]], president
* 2004–present [[Jill Beck]], president

==Notable faculty==
* [[Chris Bosio]], baseball coach
* [[Mark Catlin, Sr.]], football coach
* [[Richard N. Current]], historian
* [[Charles B. Schudson]], judge
* [[Arthur Thrall]], artist

==Notable alumni==
[[Image:Hietthall.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Hiett Hall houses 183 students. Lawrence offers housing to all accepted students.]]
* [[Martha Bablitch]], Judge of the Wisconsin Court of Appeals
* [[John Miller Baer]], 1909, Congressman from [[North Dakota]]&lt;ref&gt;http://library.ndsu.edu/digital/files/2010/01/JohnBaerArticleJan2010.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Melvin Baldwin]], Congressman from [[Minnesota]]&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000094&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Myrt Basing]], [[NFL]] player&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/B/BasiMy20.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jennifer Baumgardner]], 1992, feminist writer and activist&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/alumni/profiles/baumgardner.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Sam Barry]], college basketball and baseball coach (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.usctrojans.com/genrel/101406aaa.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lynn Berry]], 1981, editor-in-chief of the ''[[Moscow Times]]''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/admissions/acaddepts/jour.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Lisle Blackbourn]], 1925, [[NFL]] head coach&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/alumni/hall_of_fame/1996.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Champ Boettcher]], [[NFL]] player&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nfl.com/players/champboettcher/profile?id=BOE692150&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Webster E. Brown]], Congressman from Wisconsin (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=B000946&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bonnie Bryant]], 1968, author of children's books &lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[Louis B. Butler, Jr.]], 1973, associate justice of the [[Wisconsin Supreme Court]]&lt;ref name=afterlu&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/admissions/about/afterlu.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Paul Driessen]], 1970, author and lobbyist&lt;ref&gt;http://www.grassrootinstitute.org/system/old/bios/driessen.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Dale Duesing]], 1967, operatic [[baritone]]&lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[Cynthia Estlund]], 1978, law professor and author&lt;ref name=luauthors&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/news/pubs/books/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Edna Ferber]], author and playwright (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.library.wisc.edu/etext/wireader/WER0050.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[James A. Frear]], Congressman from Wisconsin (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://files.usgwarchives.net/wi/history/bluebook/1907/bios/f6600001.txt&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[William Fuller (poet)|William Fuller]], 1975, Poet and senior vice president and [[Fiduciary management|chief fiduciary officer]] of [[Northern Trust Corporation]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://blogs.lawrence.edu/news/2005/02/lawrence-university-alumnus-poet-william-fuller-gives-reading.html|title=Lawrence University Alumnus, Poet William Fuller Gives Reading |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= February 16, 2005 |work= Lawrence University News Blog|publisher= |accessdate= December 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John Rankin Gamble]], 1872, Congressman from [[South Dakota]]&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=G000030&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Robert J. Gamble]], 1874, Congressman from South Dakota&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=G000032&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Carl Giordana]], 1948, Intercollegiate Athletic Hall of Fame inductee&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/alumni/hall_of_fame/2000.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Ed Glick]], [[NFL]] player (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/G/GlicEd20.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Walter Samuel Goodland]], [[governor of Wisconsin]] (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/dictionary/index.asp?action=view&amp;term_id=1310&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Suzanne Graff]], actress
* [[Michael P. Hammond]], 1954, chairman of the [[National Endowment for the Arts]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Lorena Hickok]], confidante of [[Eleanor Roosevelt]] (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nps.gov/archive/elro/glossary/hickok-lorena.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Earnest Hooton]], 1903, physical anthropologist&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/Library/archives/honalph.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Thomas R. Hudd]], Congressman from Wisconsin (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=H000902&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bruce Iglauer]], Founder of Chicago's [[Alligator Records]]
* [[Lester Johnson]], Congressman from Wisconsin
* [[Jeffrey Jones]], 1968, actor&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/dept/communications/media/lunews/fall98_win99.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Win Jones]], 1956, watercolor painter&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/Library/archives/oralhistory_merryhathaway.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Scott Klug]], 1975 former congressman from [[Wisconsin]]&lt;ref name=vfile&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/library/archives/finding_aids/fa_vertfile.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Eddie Kotal]], [[National Football League]] player
* [[Barbara Lawton]], 1987, [[Lieutenant Governor of Wisconsin]]&lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[Fred Lerdahl]], 1965, [[composer]] and [[Music theory|music theorist]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[John A. Luke, Jr.]], 1971, CEO of [[MeadWestvaco]]&lt;ref name=beckinstall&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/dept/president/inauguration/installation.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[John McDonald (American football)|John McDonald]], [[NFL]] player
* [[James H. McGillan]], Mayor of [[Green Bay, Wisconsin]]
* [[James Merrell]], 1975, Professor of History at [[Vassar College]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[John S. Mills]], [[U.S. Air Force]] Major General&lt;ref&gt;http://www.af.mil/information/bios/bio.asp?bioID=6481&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Terry Moran]], 1982, chief White House correspondent for [[ABC News]]&lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[David Mulford]], 1969, [[United States Ambassador to India]]&lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[Tom Neff]], 1975, CEO and founder of [[DOC: The Documentary Channel|The Documentary Channel]]&lt;ref name=&quot;beckinstall&quot;/&gt;
* [[Justus Henry Nelson]], Methodist missionary in the Amazon (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://books.google.com/books?id=i6ZEAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA213&amp;lpg=PA213&amp;dq=&quot;Justus+Henry+Nelson&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Harry N. MacLean]], 1964, true crime author&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lawrence.edu/news/pubs/books/maclean.shtml  Alumni Authors – Harry Maclean ’64 – Lawrence.edu – Retrieved November 23, 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Jessica Nelson North]], 1917, author&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Rip Owens]], [[NFL]] player (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pro-football-reference.com/players/O/OwenRi21.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Alice Peacock]], 1992 singer-songwriter&lt;ref name=LUcds&gt;http://www.lawrence.edu/alumni/Cds/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Scott Reppert]], 1983, member of the [[College Football Hall of Fame]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Eben Eugene Rexford]], author of stories, poems, songs, and books on gardening (attended)&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Josh Sawyer]] - video game designer at [[Obsidian Entertainment]]&lt;ref&gt;http://blogs.lawrence.edu/lawrencetoday/2010/03/a-captivated-audience-film-studies-at-lawrence/&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Campbell Scott]], 1983, actor&lt;ref name=afterlu /&gt;
* [[Michael Shurtleff]], 1942, casting director, author&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Eric Simonson]], 1982, Oscar-winning writer-director&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Red Smith (American football/baseball)|Red Smith]], 1926, [[MLB]] player, [[NFL]] player and assistant coach, head coach of the [[Georgetown Hoyas]] football team and [[Wisconsin Badgers football]] team, athletic director of [[Seton Hall University]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Janet Steiger]], 1961, chairman of the [[Federal Trade Commission]]&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Thomas A. Steitz]], 1962, professor of molecular biophysics and biochemistry at [[Yale University]], awarded the 2009 [[Nobel Prize]] in chemistry&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;
* [[Fred Sturm]], 1973, jazz composer and arranger&lt;ref name=LUcds/&gt;
* [[William Warner (Missouri)]], U.S. Senator from Missouri (attended)&lt;ref&gt;http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=W000160&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Al Zupek]], 1944, [[NFL]] player&lt;ref name=vfile/&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of NCAA fencing schools]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lawrence.edu/ Lawrence University website]

&lt;!--Spacing, please do not remove--&gt;

{{Colleges and universities in Wisconsin}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{CLAC}}
{{Associated Colleges of the Midwest}}
{{MCHA}}
{{Midwest Conference}}
{{WAICU}}
{{Wisconsin Intercollegiate Athletic Conference}}

[[Category:Lawrence University|*]]
[[Category:Associated Colleges of the Midwest]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1847]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Midwest Conference]]
[[Category:Music schools in Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Wisconsin Association of Independent Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Appleton, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Education in Outagamie County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Outagamie County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Outagamie County, Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]

[[de:Lawrence University]]
[[ja:ローレンス大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
