<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31229130" ns="0" title="SpaceShaft"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=November 2011}}
{{essay|date=September 2011}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2011}}
[[File:Lateral aerial view of a SpaceShaf.png|thumb|Artist depiction of an aerial view of a SpaceShaft]]

A '''SpaceShaft''' is a proposed atmospherically [[Levitation|levitating]] structure that would serve as an [[elevator]] system to [[Near space|near-space]] altitudes. It will support multiple platforms distributed at several elevations that would provide [[Habitation Module|habitation facilities]] for long term human operations throughout the mid-[[Atmosphere of Earth|atmosphere]] and near-space altitudes. A SpaceShaft is also a candidate of the technologies cataloged for [[non-rocket spacelaunch]].&lt;ref name=&quot;k&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ksjtracker.mit.edu/2009/07/01/space-shaft-or-the-story-that-would-have-been-a-bit-finer-if-only-one-had-known/|title=Space Shaft: Or, the story that would have been a bit finer, if only one had known...|publisher=Knight Science Journalism, Massachusetts Institute of Technology|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ss&quot;/&gt;

A SpaceShaft is comparable to a maritime [[Spar (platform)|oil spar platform]]. Although a SpaceShaft is also described as a [[Architectural structure|structure]], it is not a [[space tower]] because it does not stand on [[Foundation (engineering)|foundations]] in contact with the surface of the planet as to support [[Modal_analysis_using_FEM#Example|compressive forces]] (see image of mode 3 stretching and compression) caused by weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;esw&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://eurospaceward.org/PDF/Sat_5Dec09_Final_V2.pdf|title=3rd International Conference on Space Elevator, CNT Tether Design, and Lunar Industrialization Challenges|location=Luxembourg|date=December 5–6, 2009|publisher=EuroSpaceWard|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the contrary, it is a very dynamic system since it would be constantly moving upwards. A SpaceShaft is not an orbital insertion system, as is assumed to intrinsically be the case with the proposed centrifugally extended carbon-nanotube tether [[Space Elevator]]. However, from a platform at the top of a SpaceShaft either [[spaceplane]]s or [[spacecraft]]s with built-in [[Spacecraft propulsion|propulsion]] systems could be launched.&lt;ref name=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spaceshaft.org/iframes/content/02_technologies/0202_SpaceShaft/iFSpaceShaft1.html|title=The SpaceShaft|publisher=spaceshaft.org|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Because of the [[Orbit insertion|orbital insertion]] incapability of the SpaceShaft,&lt;ref name=&quot;gdv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gdv.gvialle.net/?p=76#more-76|title=Space Elevator|date=February 16, 2010|publisher=Greg's Daily Vision|accessdate=April 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; some people do not regard a SpaceShaft as a true space elevator.

The SpaceShaft was originally proposed at the 2nd Eurospaceward Conference on December 2008 in Luxembourg as part of a possible transportation method for the [[Carbon nanotube|CNT]] [[Space_tether#Space_elevator_.28beanstalk.29|tether]] spools that the popular ISEC space elevator system will need for its deployment from space.

==General appearance and arrangement==
The general structural appearance of a SpaceShaft is that of an upright standing [[Telescoping (mechanics)|telescopic]] system behaving as a typical oceanic [[Spar buoy|spar-buoy]] or spar type [[oil platform]]; instead of being &quot;mostly submerged in water and partially rising into the atmosphere&quot;, it is &quot;mostly submerged in the planet’s atmosphere and partially rising out into the fringes of Space&quot;. 

Because of the large volumes of displaced [[Air mass|air-mass]] resulting from the diameters of its multiple concentrically aligned, telescopic cylinders (stabilization shafts) and their different heights, thousands of tons of buoyancy would be harnessed, making it theoretically possible to support several permanent platforms at the top of each of the stabilization shafts on the outer rims and thousands of tonnes of upthrust on the cylinders at the core of the telescopic system (transportation shafts). The type of shafts and their intended uses are discussed later.

Within the conduit at the innermost transportation shaft (i.e. the [[flue]]), which would extend from near [[Sea level|sea-level]] to the highest elevation, where a platform will be located, a special [[Shuttle (weaving)|shuttling]]-[[Elevator_cab#Design|cab]](s), comparable to a vertically oriented [[Airship|air-ship]], will travel up and down the system quickly carrying personnel and light cargo, first by means of [[buoyancy]] and afterward by [[Elevator#Traction_elevators|electromechanical]] systems.

The location of the individual platforms, except for the one at the summit of the highest shaft, are mostly distributed at altitudes below the [[Mesosphere]], and so allowing for long term human activities never before possible throughout the mid-atmosphere of our planet. The reason for the distribution is that the platforms (also known as mooring platforms) also serve as the attaching points for [[Guy-wire|guy-lines]] similar to those used with [[Mast (sailing)|sailing masts]] and guyed [[Radio masts and towers|mast antennae]]. 

The platform at the top of the innermost shaft, i.e. the one within the core of the telescopic system, will be able to reach altitudes around 100&amp;nbsp;km, and perhaps above depending on the intended operation, and so potentially provide the needed support for facilities to exercise important non-orbital space operations. The platform could even provide the facilities for initiating the “assisted launch” of a typical second stage rocket or spaceplane (see Rockoon and balloon-launched self-stabilized rocket).

Besides its capability of supporting multiple platforms throughout the atmosphere, a SpaceShaft will also serve to house a more traditional elevator system consisting of a special shuttling-cab traveling through the flue of the core shaft. It is however important to note that this elevator system can be considered as just the secondary elevator system that a SpaceShaft can provide for reasons that will be explained later in the Deployment section.

==Possible uses of a SpaceShaft==
* Tourism destination with spectacular view
* Atmospheric observation station
* Communications platform
* The ultimate [[BASE jumping]] experience
* Solar power generation

==Background regarding the concept==
A SpaceShaft is one of many applications of a foundationless [[scaffolding]] system that consists of highly customized atmospherically buoyant [[Toy blocks|building blocks]] and a specialized method of assembly by which a structure can be built and which the developers describe as &quot;a combined and simultaneous method of construction and transportation&quot;. As a consequence of the [[System deployment|deployment]] method, the structure is also capable of simultaneously transporting cargo during its ascent; this simultaneous transport is done by placing the [[Cargo|payload]] within some of the building blocks, in a vertical and unidirectional [[FIFO and LIFO accounting|FIFO sequence]], which ultimately creates a large upwards-moving structure capable of constant delivery of a high tonnage of cargo contained within selected building blocks.

==Deployment and FIFO delivery==
The FIFO deployment sequence is as follows; having one of the buoyant building blocks already anchored; some slack is then given to the anchor lines as to let it further rise, i.e.; in a controlled fashion and for a limited height, as much as to allow for enough space being made as to insert a new buoyant building block right underneath the first one. These building blocks are then firmly attached to each other and so becoming a unit with the understandably incremented buoyancy. The process is then repeated for as many times as is necessary, such that: when both the desired carrying capacity and desired altitude are achieved for the building block at the top of the stack, with whatever payload is contained, is then submitted for their relocations. And so is the FIFO sequence completed.

As said, the SpaceShaft is assembled using atmospherically buoyant building blocks. These building blocks consist of specifically engineered buoyant pressure vessels. Some of which are designed for high buoyancy and [[Ballast tank|ballasting]], while others are engineered for more specific structural purposes. However, all of these building blocks are characterized by being buoyant and having internal skeletons made from composite materials, and so making these units very strong, very light, modular, and maintainable, even when they have already been integrated into the buoyant structure and have reached high atmospheric altitudes. One interesting property of such a buoyant structure is that in the event of an accident only limited amounts of debris will fall back to the ground since most of the building blocks will remain atmospherically buoyant.

Other components of the system are not as buoyant or may not be buoyant at all, (e.g. [[Anchor windlass|anchor lines]], winches, deck equipment, etc.). The design goal of the SpaceShaft is to construct a structure that is; &quot;atmospherically buoyant from sea level up to altitudes of 50km&quot;. Higher altitudes are attained by transferring excess weight as compressive loads down the SpaceShaft. 

The SpaceShaft will have net positive buoyancy which will necessitate anchoring it to the ground. Additionally, since the lower portion of the SpaceShaft is subject to atmospheric winds will therefore require mooring lines. To quickly differentiate the functionality of the systems; the anchoring system is to keep the SpaceShaft from freely flying away, while the mooring system is to counteract lateral wind forces that could toss around the structure. More about the combined effects of wind loads and upthrust is discussed later, under the section of &quot;Heave and roll behavior&quot; which would describe the similar of a spar-buoy on a [[waterway]] and on the section &quot;Wind force and [[Coriolis effect|Coriolis]]&quot;, likewise for bending and deflection on the structure. Beside the two mentioned external control systems there is an electronically controlled, self sufficient, ballasting system incorporated into every one of the buoyant building blocks.

As the SpaceShaft is constructed, the sum total of the buoyant forces of all the component rings is available to support the weight(s) of the elevated (elevating) platform(s) and payloads. Thus, as you add more component rings, you increase the load carrying capacity of the SpaceShaft.

The SpaceShaft structure is constructed with a larger number of concentric rings at the lower levels. The SpaceShaft structure is wider at the base, narrower at the top. The appearance of which resembles a telescoping device. Some of the SpaceShaft structures may resemble an elongated version of the [[Burj Khalifa]], currently the tallest building at 828 m (2,717&amp;nbsp;ft). 

While the total volume of the Burj Khalifa is not listed, the floor area is listed as 309,473 square meters. If we approximate floor height as averaging 3 meters then the volume is 928,419 cubic meters. At the bottom of the Burj Khalifa (sea level) the density of air is approximately 1.2 kilograms per cubic meter. At the top of the Burj Khalifa (828 meters) the density of air is approximately 1.1 kilograms per cubic meter. With a total displacement of 928,419 cubic meters, and considering the majority of the displacement is at the bottom, using 1.175&amp;nbsp;kg/m³ average density of displaced air, the available buoyancy is approximately 1,090 metric tons (less the mass of the SpaceShaft components). While the average density of the SpaceShaft components is unknown at this time, targeted values are in the range of 0.1 to 0.2&amp;nbsp;kg/m³. Using the higher density, a sea level based SpaceShaft of the size and shape of the Burj Khalifa could lift 905 metric tons. The Burj Khalifa represents a structure that is approximately 1% the size (height and volume) of a SpaceShaft.

[[File:Lateral view of spar-buoy.png|thumb|A spar buoy]]

==Buoyancy and upthrust==
Buoyancy is a force that exists because of a potential difference due to the density differences between at least two fluids. This potential difference reaches a point of equilibrium when the weight of the two fluids is equalized. What this means is that a vessel, with a shell of negligible mass, containing a lighter fluid than that of the environment in which it is submerged will have a higher buoyancy value at a larger depth than the value it will have when close to the surface of the containing fluid. Assuming an imaginary column of such vessels, the summation of the buoyancy harnessed from the stacked vessels at a depth larger than at the point of zero buoyancy, i.e. with respect to the surface of the surrounding liquid, is what is informally called by the developers of the SpaceShaft the upthrust of the system.

==The upthrust formula==

The total upthrust {{math|''U''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} of a SpaceShaft equals the payload that it can carry at its top while still being in a neutral floating state.  The total upthrust is computed assuming that:
* the SpaceShaft’s cross sectional area {{math|''S''}} may vary in function of the altitude {{math|''h''}}: {{math|''S'' {{=}} ''S''(''h'')}}
* the SpaceShaft’s mass per unit length {{math|''m''}} (i.e. the consolidated mass of its structure) may vary in function of the altitude: {{math|''m'' {{=}} ''m''(''h'')}}
where the altitude {{math|''h''}} is defined as {{math|''h'' {{=}} ''r''–''r''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;}} with {{math|''r''}} the distance of the Earth's center and {{math|''r''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;}} the Earth's radius.

The net vertical upthrust per unit length acting upon the SpaceShaft at a given altitude {{math|''h''}}, is composed of:
# the upward buoyancy force {{math|''B''(''h'')}};
# the upward centrifugal force {{math|''C''(''h'')}} due to the Earth's rotation;
# the downward weight force {{math|''W''(''h'')}}.
The net vertical upthrust {{math|''U''(''h'')}} per unit length becomes then:  {{math|''U''(''h'') {{=}} ''B''(''h'') + ''C''(''h'') – ''W''(''h'')}}.  The different composing forces are detailed below.

=== Upward buoyancy force ===

The [[Buoyancy|buoyancy force]] {{math|''B''(''h'')}} per unit length of the SpaceShaft at a given altitude is computed as
 
{{math|''B''(''h'') {{=}} ''S''(''h'') · ''&amp;rho;''&lt;sub&gt;''a''&lt;/sub&gt;(''h'') · ''g''(''h'')}} 

in which {{math|''&amp;rho;''&lt;sub&gt;''a''&lt;/sub&gt;(''h'')}} is the air density and {{math|''g''(''h'')}} the [[gravitational acceleration]] defined by:

&lt;math&gt;g\left( h \right) =g_{0}\cdot \left( \frac{r_{0}}{h + r_0} \right)^{2}&lt;/math&gt;

=== Upward centrifugal force ===

The [[centrifugal force]] due to the Earth's rotation is computed as:

&lt;math&gt;C\left( h \right)= m(h) \cdot \omega _{e}^{2}\cdot \left( r_0 + h\right)&lt;/math&gt;

in which {{math|''&amp;omega;''&lt;sub&gt;''e''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is the constant Earth's rotation speed given by:

&lt;math&gt;\omega _{e}\approx \frac{2 \cdot \pi}{T_{day}} = 7.27221\times 10^{-5} \;\; \mathrm{rad/s}&lt;/math&gt;

in which {{math|''T''&lt;sub&gt;''day''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is the duration of a day on Earth in seconds.

=== Downward weight force ===

The downward weight force per unit length is simply computed as:

&lt;math&gt;W(h)= m(h) \cdot g(h) = m(h) \cdot g_0 \cdot \left( \frac{r_0}{r_0 + h}\right)^2&lt;/math&gt;

=== The total upthrust ===

The total upthrust {{math|''U''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} for a SpaceShaft with bottom section at an altitude {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''b''&lt;/sub&gt;}} and top section at 
an altitude {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is then given by the integration of the vertical upthrust {{math|''U''}} over the SpaceShaft's length:

&lt;math&gt;U_t = \int_{h_{b}}^{h_{t}} U(h) \cdot dh = \int_{h_{b}}^{h_{t}} \left[ B(h) + C(h) - W(h) \right] \cdot dh&lt;/math&gt;

or, using the expressions for the respective upthrust components given above:

&lt;math&gt;U_t = \int_{h_{b}}^{h_{t}} \left\{ S\left(h \right)\cdot \rho_a \left( h \right) \cdot g_{0} \cdot \left( \frac{r_{0}}{r_0 + h} \right)^{2} - m \left( h \right) \cdot \left[ g_{0} \cdot \left( \frac{r_{0}}{r_0 + h} \right)^{2} - \omega_e^{2} \cdot 
\left( r_0 + h \right) \right] \right\} \cdot dh&lt;/math&gt;

Considering a SpaceShaft that is in a neutral floating state ({{math|''U''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt; {{=}} 0}}), the above expression in which {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is replaced by any altitude between {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''b''&lt;/sub&gt;}} and {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} gives the vertical [[Buckling|buckling force]] the upper parts of the SpaceShaft exert on the lower parts of the SpaceShaft at that altitude.  This allows to evaluate the vertical stresses in the internal of the SpaceShaft and, hence, to choose the appropriate materials and design to cope with these stresses.

In case the SpaceShaft is not in a neutral floating state ({{math|''U''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; 0}}), the SpaceShaft must be anchored as discussed above.  The anchoring force {{math|''A''(''h''&lt;sub&gt;''b''&lt;/sub&gt;)}} will then equal {{math|–''U''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt;}} for the SpaceShaft to be in [[mechanical equilibrium]].  This force can then be used to evaluate the stresses in the anchoring system.

==== Simplification ====
In many cases the weight per unit length of the SpaceShaft will be proportional to its cross sectional area: {{math|''m''(''h'') {{=}} ''&amp;rho;''&lt;sub&gt;''s''&lt;/sub&gt; · ''S''(''h'')}} where {{math|''&amp;rho;''&lt;sub&gt;''s''&lt;/sub&gt;(''h'')}} is the SpaceShaft's own density.  The total upthrust now becomes:

&lt;math&gt;U_t = \int_{h_{b}}^{h_{t}} S\left(h \right) \cdot \left\{ \left[\rho_a \left( h \right) - \rho_s \left( h \right) \right] \cdot g_{0} \cdot \left( \frac{r_{0}}{r_0 + h} \right)^{2} + \rho_s \left( h \right) \cdot \omega_e^{2} \cdot 
\left( r_0 + h \right) \right\} \cdot dh&lt;/math&gt;

=== Practical Example ===

Using the simplified global upthrust formula above, computations can be carried out for different shapes {{math|''S''(''h'')}} of a SpaceShaft placed at the equator and starting at an altitude of {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''b''&lt;/sub&gt; {{=}} 100m}} and reaching up to {{math|''h''&lt;sub&gt;''t''&lt;/sub&gt; {{=}} 150km}}.  SpaceShafts with different cross sectional variations and at equilibrium with no payload (zero global upthrust) are studied while the SpaceShaft’s proper material density is computed inversely to obtain a zero global upthrust.
The cross sectional variation {{math|''S''(''h'')}} of the SpaceShaft in this example study is given by the following formula:

&lt;math&gt;
S(h) = S_{min} + \frac{(S_{ref} - S_{min}) \cdot \left(h_t - h_b\right)}{\int_{h_b}^{h_t} \left[1 - \frac{r - h_b}{h_t - h_b}\right]^n \cdot dr}
\cdot \left[1 - \frac{h - h_b}{h_t - h_b}\right]^n
&lt;/math&gt;

in which {{math|''S''&lt;sub&gt;''min''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is the minimum remaining cross sectional area at the top of the SpaceShaft,
{{math|''S''&lt;sub&gt;''ref''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is the cross sectional area of a perfect cylindrical SpaceShaft having the same total
volume as the current SpaceShaft, the case of {{math|''n'' {{=}} 0}}.  All studied SpaceShafts will have the same total volume and, hence, will represent approximately the same material cost.  

The computations are done using {{math|''S''&lt;sub&gt;''min''&lt;/sub&gt; {{=}} 100m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}} and {{math|''S''&lt;sub&gt;''ref''&lt;/sub&gt; {{=}} 1000m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}} and {{math|''n'' {{=}} 0,1,...,5}}.  The different shapes of the studied SpaceShaft corresponding to different values of {{math|''n''}} is shown below.

[[File:Shapes-surf-1000-h0-100-htot-150000-zero-lift-density.jpeg|thumb|center|600px|alt=The different SpaceShaft shapes|The different SpaceShaft shapes.]]

The total internal vertical forces along the SpaceShaft for the different shapes and the corresponding internal vertical stresses are depicted below:

{{multiple image
   | width     = 500
   | footer    = Forces in a 150km tall SpaceShaft
   | image1    = Global-lift-surf-1000-h0-100-htot-150000-zero-lift-density.jpeg
   | alt1      = Internal forces
   | caption1  = Internal forces.
   | image2    = Sectionforces150.jpeg
   | alt2      = Vertical stresses
   | caption2  = Vertical stresses.
  }}

In the case of the cubic shape ({{math|''n'' {{=}}3}}), the internal force reaches a maximum of 185,000 kN (about 18,500 tons) at an altitude of about 15&amp;nbsp;km while the maximum vertical stresses read 73 kN/m{{math|&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}} (about 7.3 tons per m{{math|&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}}) at an altitude of about 23 km.

==Heave and roll behavior==
{{Incomplete|date=April 2011}}

=Lateral forces=
To cope with different lateral forces such as wind and [[Coriolis]] forces (for instance, when a shuttle is moving rapidly upward within the Spaceshaft), a number of stabilization techniques are envisaged that can be categorized in two main categories:

# Passive techniques:
#* application of lightweight [[tensegrity]] like structures to enhance the stiffness of the SpaceShaft artefact
# Active techniques:
#* [[Spoke#Tension_spokes|spoke]]-like mooring systems at different altitudes (much like antenna-masts)
#* computer-controlled [[Propeller (aircraft)|propeller]] nacelles at different altitudes to combat side winds

It is important to investigate how a SpaceShaft can remain in equilibrium under the effect of lateral forces in order to design appropriately the different aforementioned stabilization techniques.  [[Mechanical equilibrium]] of the SpaceShaft is reached if the sum of all forces and the sum of all moments around some reference point (in this case the anchor point at the bottom of the SpaceShaft) are zero.  In absence of any active stabilization technique, the SpaceShaft will no longer a straight vertical artefact but will have to lean against the side forces that are then compensation by the SpaceShaft's own weight force.  

To model the mechanical static equilibrium of a SpaceShaft, the different acting forces and moments are listed below:

* the external forces &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{W}&lt;/math&gt;: wind forces, Coriolis forces,...
* the SpaceShaft's own weight force &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{G}&lt;/math&gt;
* the SpaceShaft's anchor force &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{A}&lt;/math&gt;
* mooring forces and/or propeller forces at discrete altitudes &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{F}_{i}&lt;/math&gt; where {{math|''i'' {{=}} 1,...,''N''}} with {{math|''N''}} the number of mooring stations or propeller nacelles; altitude increases with the index {{math|''i''}};
* the moment &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{M}_W&lt;/math&gt; generated by the external forces;
* the moment &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{M}_G&lt;/math&gt; generated by the SpaceShaft's own weight;
* the moments &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{M}_{F,i}&lt;/math&gt; generated by the mooring stations and propeller nacelles where {{math|''i'' {{=}} 1,...,''N''}} with {{math|''N''}} the number of mooring stations or propeller nacelles;
* the moment &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{M}_S&lt;/math&gt; caused by any possible bending of the SpaceShaft whose stiffness is resisting to such bending.

The overall mechanical static equilibrium of a SpaceShaft undergoing lateral forces is then expressed by the following two equations:

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{W} + \vec{G} + \vec{F}_0 + \sum_{i=1}^{N} \vec{F}_{i} = \vec{0}
&lt;/math&gt;

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{M}_W + \vec{M}_G + \vec{M}_S + \sum_{i=1}^{N}\vec{M}_{F,i} = \vec{0}
&lt;/math&gt;

The subsequent subsections will address each of the individual terms in these equations in more detail.

==Wind forces and moments==

A very precise prediction of the wind forces with a given wind profile at different altitudes can only be done using full-blown three-dimensional [[Computational_fluid_dynamics|CFD]] packages that have the capability to model correctly the full shape of the SpaceShaft.  These packages use the three dimensional [[Navier–Stokes_equations|Navier-Stokes equations]] augmented with a decent [[turbulence model]].  Furthermore, the air flow around the SpaceShaft will in most cases be inherently unsteady as a so called [[Von_Kármán_vortex_street|von Karman vortex street]] may occur at certain altitudes with certain wind speeds.  To cope with such unsteadiness, the SpaceShaft must have enough internal damping to avoid mechanical [[resonance]] effects.

However, for overall engineering purposes, one can use the aerodynamic [[drag coefficient]] at different altitudes to evaluate the overall side wind force &lt;math&gt;\vec{W}&lt;/math&gt;:

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{W} = \int_0^L \frac{1}{2} \cdot C_d(l) \cdot D(l) \cdot \rho(l)  \cdot \left|\left|\vec{v}(l)\right|\right|  \cdot \vec{v}(l) \cdot dl 
&lt;/math&gt;

in which the aerodynamic drag coefficient {{math|''C''&lt;sub&gt;''d''&lt;/sub&gt;}}, the wind speed vector &lt;math&gt;\vec{v}&lt;/math&gt;, the atmospheric air density &lt;math&gt;\rho&lt;/math&gt; and the reference aerodynamic cross sectional length &lt;math&gt;D&lt;/math&gt; are all dependent on the position {{math|''l''}} along the SpaceShaft.  Note that {{math|''l''}} does not exactly equals the altitude {{math|''h''}} as the SpaceShaft may be bending and not take an exact vertical position when in a static mechanical equilibrium state.  {{math|''L''}} represents the total axial length of the SpaceShaft.

Assuming a SpaceShaft with a circular horizontal cross sectional shape, the value of the aerodynamic drag coefficient {{math|''C''&lt;sub&gt;''d''&lt;/sub&gt;}} will be about 0.5 if the wind direction is horizontal too.  In case the wind is not purely horizontal, the SpaceShaft will present an elliptical shape with a lower value of the aerodynamic drag coefficient.

The total moment &lt;math&gt;\vec{M}_W&lt;/math&gt; around the anchor point due to wind forces is given by (while using the vectorproduct operator &lt;math&gt;\otimes&lt;/math&gt;):

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{M}_W = \int_{0}^{L} \left[\frac{1}{2} \cdot C_d(l) \cdot D(l) \cdot \rho(l)  \cdot \left|\left|\vec{v}(l)\right|\right| \cdot \vec{v}(l) \otimes \vec{p}(l) \right] \cdot dl
&lt;/math&gt;

in which &lt;math&gt;\vec{p}(l)&lt;/math&gt; denotes the actual position vector along the axis of the SpaceShaft relative to its anchor point on the Earth’s surface.

== Weight forces and moments ==

The weight force due to gravitation is computed using the expression for the [[#Simplification|simplified upthrust]]:

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{G} = \vec{1}_z \cdot \int_{0}^{L} S(l) \cdot \left\{ \left[ \rho(r(l)) - \rho_s \right] \cdot g_0 \cdot \left(\frac{r_0}{r(l)}\right)^2 
 + \rho_s \cdot \omega ^2 \cdot r(l)\right\} \cdot dl
&lt;/math&gt;

in which the radial distance {{math|''r''}} from the Earth's center becomes now a function of the position {{math|''l''}} along the (most probably bended) SpaceShaft.

The weight force moment $\vec{M}_G$ relative to the SpaceShaft's anchor point is computed as follows:

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{M}_G = \int_{0}^{L} \left[S(l) \cdot \left\{ \left[ \rho(l) - \rho_s \right] \cdot g_0 
\left(\frac{h_0}{r(l)}\right)^2 
 + \rho_s \cdot \omega ^2 r(l)\right\} \cdot \left(\vec{1}_z \otimes \vec{p}(l)\right) \right] \cdot dl
&lt;/math&gt;

== Internal stiffness moments ==

The SpaceShaft will resist to being bended by generating an internal stiffness moment that is assumed to be linear with the local bending vector &lt;math&gt;\vec{\theta}&lt;/math&gt; representing the bending magnitude and the axis of rotation of the bending.  This assumption is valid as long as the deformation is within the range of elastic deformation.  We use {{math|''k''}} as the proportionality factor whose actual value is depending on the designed shape of the SpaceShaft and the used materials and my vary along the SpaceShaft's axis.  The total moment &lt;math&gt;\vec{M}_S&lt;/math&gt; relative to the SpaceShaft's anchor point due to internal stiffness moments is then given by:

&lt;math&gt;
\vec{M}_S = \int_{0}^{L} k(l) \cdot \vec{\theta}(l) \cdot dl
&lt;/math&gt;

== Mooring forces and moments ==

The mooring forces &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{F}_{i}&lt;/math&gt; where {{math|''i'' {{=}} 1,...,''N''}} will generate a total moment around the SpaceShaft's anchor point that is given by:

&lt;math&gt;
\sum_{i=1}^{N}\vec{M}_{F,i} = \sum_{i=1}^{N} \vec{F}_{i} \otimes \vec{p}_{i}
&lt;/math&gt;

in the mooring point or the propeller nacelle location &lt;math&gt;\vec{p}_{i} = \vec{p}(l_i)&lt;/math&gt; where {{math|''l''&lt;sub&gt;''i''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is the known length along the SpaceShaft's axis.  However the actual position &lt;math&gt;\vec{p}_{i}&lt;/math&gt; will depend on the amount of bending. 

We shall assume in the subsequent development that the mooring forces &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{F}_{i}&lt;/math&gt; are only non-zero when moving the predicted equilibrium position.  The modelling of this process requires a more complex dynamic equilibrium model that also accounts for the acceleration forces.  For now, we are only interested in predicting the static equilibrium position of the SpaceShaft whereby all mooring forces &lt;math&gt;\textstyle\vec{F}_{i}&lt;/math&gt; are equal to the null vector.

== Numerically predicting the equilibrium position ==

Using one-dimensional linear Finite Elements placed in the three dimensional space and using the appropriate and well-known [[Finite_element_method|Finite Element techniques]], to above set of equations describing the static mechanical equilibrium of the SpaceShaft can be solved for the three dimensional space coordinates of the end points of the one-dimensional Finite Elements.

In principle, the set of mechanical equilibrium equations are non-linear in the sense that for instance the aerodynamic drag coefficient {{math|''C''&lt;sub&gt;''d''&lt;/sub&gt;}} is dependent on the local bending of the SpaceShaft and that the radial distance {{math|''r''}} is a non-linear function of the length {{math|''l''}} along the axis of the (bended) SpaceShaft.  Hence, some kind of iterative Newton-Raphson technique will have to be used to solve the equations.

Nonetheless, the equations can be linearized under the assumption that the SpaceShaft is only bending a little and that it has no internal stiffness: {{math|''k'' {{=}} 0}}.  Under these assumptions, the aerodynamic drag coefficient can be considered independent on the SpaceShaft's position and the length {{math|''l''}} along the axis of the SpaceShaft is approximately equal to {{math|''h'' – ''h''&lt;sub&gt;''b''&lt;/sub&gt;}} and, hence, the differentials {{math|''dl''}} and {{math|''dh''}} will be identical.  Also, the radial distance {{math|''r''(''l'')) {{=}} ''h''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt; + ''h''}} becomes a purely linear function.

== Coriolis forces ==

Any moving object that follows a path whereby the distance to the axis of rotation of the Earth is changing, will undergo the so called [[Coriolis force]]. 
In the case of a SpaceShaft, Coriolis forces can occur in two cases:

# during deployment and FIFO delivery of the SpaceShaft whereby the SpaceShaft is intermittently moving upward  
# a nacelle is moving quickly up- or downwards within the SpaceShaft

The vertical speed during the deployment and FIFO delivery will be very slow and in the order of 0.1 m/s.  However, the mass of the SpaceShaft as such can be very large.  A SpaceShaft that is 50 km tall with a constant cross sectional area of {{math|1000m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;}} will represent a mass of about {{math|20 x 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;}} kg.
Placed at the equator, a SpaceShaft will undergo a global Coriolis force of about 300 N towards the west.  This force can be considered negligible to other lateral forces. 

If a nacelle with a mass of 5000 kg is moving upward within the SpaceShaft (placed at the equator) at a speed of 40 m/s (or 144&amp;nbsp;km/h), it will generate a coriolis force on the SpaceShaft of about 30 N, which, again, is a very small force compared to other lateral forces that may act upon the SpaceShaft.

=Relation to Space Elevator=
A Space Elevator is a [[Tether propulsion|tethered]] [[satellite]] ([[counterweight]]) located at an altitude of ~100,000&amp;nbsp;km. The tether of Space Elevator offers a purchase point for an electrically driven elevator. The advantage of a Space Elevator is that the climbers have an altitude range of 0 to 100,000&amp;nbsp;km as opposed to the SpaceShaft operating in an altitude range of 0 to 100&amp;nbsp;km, and potentially 0 to 300&amp;nbsp;km. The disadvantages of the Space Elevator (as of the time of this writing) are:

:a) it will require a Carbon Nano-Tube (CNT) tether, which exceeds our current manufacturing knowledge, and,
:b) it will require being located at or near the equator.

The SpaceShaft can be located at latitudes away from the equator. Although the altitudes reached by the SpaceShaft are significantly lower than that of the Space Elevator, many of the envisioned missions of the space elevator (listed at the top of this article) can easily be provided by a SpaceShaft. Therefore, the two distinct advantages the SpaceShaft has are: 

:a) it can be built with current knowledge of materials science, and
:b) it can be located near populated areas.

==See also==
* [[Space elevator]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://spaceshaft.org The SpaceShaft Endeavor]
* [http://eurospaceward.org/ The European Spaceward Association]

{{Non-rocket spacelaunch}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spaceshaft}}
[[Category:Megastructures]]
[[Category:Hypothetical technology]]
[[Category:Space access]]
[[Category:Vertical transport devices]]
[[Category:Space technology]]
[[Category:Space colonization]]
[[Category:Exploratory engineering]]
[[Category:Non-rocket spacelaunch]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
