<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="312239" ns="0" title="Visage"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=April 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{See Wiktionary|the band Visage}}
{{See also|Appearance (disambiguation)|face}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|name = Visage
|image = Vis-FTG 93mixes.jpg
|caption = Steve Strange, the Visage frontman
|background = group_or_band
|alias = 
|origin = London, England
|instrument = 
|genre = &lt;!--NOTE: Do not add &quot;New Romantic&quot; to the genre field. New Romantic was a fashion/culture movement, not a style of music. --&gt;[[Synthpop]], [[Electronic music|Electronic]], [[New Wave music|New Wave]]
|occupation = 
|years_active = 1978–1985, 2004–present
|label = [[Polydor Records]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Radar Records]]
|associated_acts = 
|[[Ultravox]], [[Magazine (band)|Magazine]], [[Seize (band)|Seize]]
| website = [http://www.myspace.com/visageofficial www.myspace.com/visageofficial]
|current_members = [[Steve Strange]]&lt;br /&gt;Steven Young&lt;br /&gt;Sandrine Gouriou&lt;br /&gt;Rosie Harris&lt;br /&gt;Ross Tregenza
|past_members = [[Rusty Egan]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Midge Ure]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Billy Currie]]&lt;br /&gt;[[John McGeoch]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dave Formula]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Barry Adamson]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Gary Barnacle]]&lt;br /&gt;Steve Barnacle&lt;br /&gt;Andy Barnett  
}}
'''Visage''' are a British [[New Wave music|New Wave]] rock band. Formed in 1978, the band became closely linked to the burgeoning [[New Romantic]] fashion movement of the early 1980s, and are best known for their 1980 hit &quot;[[Fade to Grey (Visage song)|Fade to Grey]]&quot;.

==History==
===New Wave years (1978–1985)===
Founder members [[Steve Strange]] and [[Rusty Egan]] were hosting club nights at Blitz nightclub in Great Queen Street, London at the time and were eager to find new music to play, ultimately opting to create music themselves. Initially, the band was composed of Strange, Egan and [[Midge Ure]]. Ure and Egan began working with Strange during their last days with the band [[The Rich Kids]], with Strange himself being at a loose end after leaving the [[New Wave music|new wave]] band The Photons. The trio recorded a demo which included a cover of the [[Zager and Evans]] hit &quot;[[In the Year 2525]]&quot;. The band's line-up was completed with the addition of [[Ultravox (band)|Ultravox]] keyboardist [[Billy Currie]] and three quarters of the post-punk band [[Magazine (band)|Magazine]] – guitarist [[John McGeoch]], keyboardist [[Dave Formula]] and bassist [[Barry Adamson]] (who left the band early on after the band's debut single, but returned as a session musician&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.electricity-club.co.uk/html/egan.html The Electricity Club - Rusty Egan Interview]&lt;/ref&gt;). Producer [[Martin Rushent]] had heard some of the band's material at Billy's nightclub and financed further recordings with a view to signing the band to his then-new Genetic Records label. Visage recorded their first album at Rushent's home studio in Berkshire, but Rushent's label collapsed before it had gotten off the ground and the band instead signed to [[Radar Records]], a new independent label run by Rushent's former colleague Martin Davis (the pair had worked together at [[United Artists Records]]). Visage released their first single, &quot;[[Tar (song)|Tar]]&quot;, on Radar in September 1979, though the single failed to chart.

Although the band's [[Visage (album)|self-titled debut album]] had been completed for several months, it was not released until November 1980 when the band was now signed to the major label, [[Polydor Records]]. The band's second single, &quot;[[Fade to Grey (Visage song)|Fade to Grey]]&quot;, was released at the same time. The single became a huge hit in early 1981, making the top ten in the UK and several other countries, and reaching no.1 in Germany and Switzerland. The album also became a Top 20 hit in the UK and was certified Silver by the [[British Phonographic Industry]]. 

After further hits with the singles &quot;[[Mind of a Toy]]&quot; and the title track &quot;[[Visage (song)|Visage]]&quot;, Strange struggled to reunite the band's members again to record a second album because of their commitments with their respective bands (Ure had now joined Currie in [[Ultravox]], Formula and Adamson with Magazine, and McGeoch with [[Siouxsie and the Banshees]]). In the autumn of 1981 Visage went into the studio again and recorded ''[[The Anvil (album)|The Anvil]]'' as a five-piece band without McGeoch and only limited guest work from Adamson. The album was released in March 1982 and became Visage's only UK top-ten album, producing two top-twenty singles with &quot;The Damned Don't Cry&quot; and &quot;Night Train&quot;. Like their first album, ''The Anvil'' earned a Silver disc in the UK.

Following this, Ure left the band to concentrate on his work with [[Ultravox]], who were by now becoming even more successful than Visage were. Creative differences with Strange were also cited as reasons for his departure at the time. Visage, now without Ure, McGeoch and Adamson (who continued collaborating with [[Pete Shelley]], and joined [[The Birthday Party (band)|The Birthday Party]]) but now with the addition of bassist Steve Barnacle, recorded the stand-alone single &quot;[[Pleasure Boys]]&quot;, which was released in October 1982. Unfortunately, the single failed to prolong their string of hits and peaked just outside the UK top 40.

Although still recording, Visage then took a two year hiatus from releasing any new material due to contractual difficulties with their management company. Polydor issued a &quot;best of&quot; compilation in 1983; ''[[Fade to Grey - The Singles Collection]]'' which included all of the singles released to date and the previously unreleased &quot;In The Year 2525&quot;. Limited quantities of the album were issued with a free &quot;Pleasure Boys&quot; 7&quot; picture disc single, whereas the cassette version of the album featured remixes of the singles. Although the album was certified Gold in the UK for pre-release sales to stores, it only peaked at no.38 after its release in November 1983.

With their contractual problems resolved, 1984 saw the return of Visage for what would become their third and final album to date. ''[[Beat Boy]]'' was released in September 1984 but was a critical and commercial failure, peaking at #79 in the UK. Two singles from the album; &quot;[[Love Glove]]&quot; and &quot;[[Beat Boy (song)|Beat Boy]]&quot; also failed to make the UK top 40. By this time, Billy Currie and Dave Formula had also departed the band (though they received a &quot;special thanks&quot; credit on the album sleeve for their input), leaving only Strange and Egan from the original line-up along with newer musicians Steve &amp; Gary Barnacle and Andy Barnett. A decision to make Visage a live band instead of a strictly studio-based project also failed to meet with success and the band subsequently split in 1985. Their final release was a ''Visage'' VHS video compilation of the band's renowned promotional videos and also included footage of Strange's trip to North Africa the year before. The compilation does not, however, include the original video for the &quot;Love Glove&quot; single which was filmed at a late-night Dockland location in London in 1984.

Following the demise of Visage, Strange then formed the short-lived band [[Strange Cruise]]. They were signed to EMI and released two singles; these being &quot;Rebel Blue Rocker&quot; and a cover version of [[Sonny and Cher]]'s hit &quot;And The Beat Goes On&quot;. Neither of these singles made the charts. The band also released one album in 1986, though this too proved unsuccessful. Visage returned to the charts once more when a Bassheads [[remix]] of &quot;Fade to Grey&quot; was a UK [[Top 40]] hit in 1993.

===Second incarnation (2004–present)===
Steve Strange reappeared on the music scene in 2002, after several years of battling a heroin addiction. Strange performed several Visage songs on the &quot;[[Here and Now Tour|Here and Now Xmas Tour]]&quot; – a revival of 1980s pop acts. Some time after the performance, noting he still had a fanbase, Strange decided to launch a &quot;Mark II&quot; of Visage with people from several electronic bands and projects: Steven Young, Sandrine Gouriou and Rosie Harris from [[Seize (band)|Seize]] and Ross Tregenza from Jetstream Lovers/[[Goteki]]. After the announcement of the formation of the new line-up and several television appearances, plans for reworking old material and releasing a new record have made slow progress. An updated version of ''Fade To Grey'' was produced in 2005. In 2006, Strange also collaborated with the electronic duo Punx Soundcheck and provided vocals on the track &quot;In the Dark&quot;, which was included on the duo's debut double album ''When Machines Ruled the World''. The first Visage mk II track was released in 2007, entitled &quot;Diary Of A Madman&quot;. Written by Strange with Visage mk II member Ross Tregenza, the track was co-produced by original Visage member Dave Formula.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.side-line.com/news_comments.php?id=27249_0_2_0_C New material for Visage finally there]&lt;/ref&gt; This song was made available for download from their official website in return for a donation to the charity [[Children in Need]]. However, since then, no further new material has surfaced.

The long-since deleted Visage VHS video collection was repackaged for release on DVD in Summer 2006, though it was mistakenly titled ''Visage Live''. 

In 2008, Strange (and Visage II keyboardist Sandrine Gouriou) made an appearance in the BBC drama series ''[[Ashes to Ashes (TV series)|Ashes to Ashes]]'' which is set in 1981. In it, they performed the song &quot;Fade to Grey&quot; in a scene set in the &quot;Blitz&quot; nightclub.

In 2009, Strange and Egan appeared in Living TV's ''Pop Goes the Band'',&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.livingtv.co.uk/shows/pop-goes-the-band.php Pop Goes the Band]&lt;/ref&gt; a series in which pop stars from the 1980s are given a complete makeover in return for a one-off performance. The Visage episode aired on 16 March 2009, and was the first time that the two men had spoken in over 20 years. The episode focussed (like others in the series) more on getting them fit in the gym than on the current state of their relationship, though they appeared to get on well enough. At the culmination of the episode, they performed &quot;Fade to Grey&quot;.

In 2010, new remixes of &quot;Fade to Grey&quot; were produced by club DJs [[Michael Gray (DJ)|Michael Gray]] and Lee Mortimer to celebrate the 30th anniversary of the song. The remixes have been included on a new [[compilation album]], ''[[The Face - The Very Best of Visage]]'', which was released in March 2010.

==Discography==
{{main|Visage discography}}
*''[[Visage (album)|Visage]]'' (1980)
*''[[The Anvil (album)|The Anvil]]'' (1982)
*''[[Beat Boy]]'' (1984)

==Media==
This section includes music samples of several Visage tracks:
{{listen 
 | filename    = Visage_-_motivation.ogg
 | title       = Motivation
 | description = Composed by [[Steve Strange]], [[Midge Ure]], [[Billy Currie]], [[Rusty Egan]] and [[Dave Formula]], this song is the B-side of single &quot;[[The Damned Don't Cry (song)|The Damned Don't Cry]]&quot; of January 1982.
 | format      = [[ogg]]
 | filename2    = Visage_-_im_still_searching.ogg
 | title2       = I'm Still Searching
 | description2 = Composed by [[Steve Strange]], [[Midge Ure]], [[Billy Currie]], [[Rusty Egan]] and [[Dave Formula]], this song is the B-side of single &quot;[[Night Train (Visage song)|Night Train]]&quot; of June 1982.
 | format2      = [[ogg]]
}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/music/sites/steve_strange BBC biography on Steve Strange]

{{Visage}}

[[Category:English electronic music groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups from London]]
[[Category:British New Wave musical groups]]
[[Category:Musical groups established in 1978]]

[[ca:Visage]]
[[da:Visage]]
[[de:Visage (Band)]]
[[es:Visage (banda)]]
[[fr:Visage (groupe)]]
[[it:Visage]]
[[nl:Visage]]
[[ja:ヴィサージ]]
[[pl:Visage]]
[[ru:Visage]]
[[sv:Visage]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
