<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31416316" ns="0" title="Illyriad"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox VG
| title          = Illyriad
| collapsible    =
| show image     =
| image          = [[File:Illyriad-logo.jpg]]
| caption        =
| aspect ratio   =
| resolution     =
| developer      = Illyriad Games Ltd
| publisher      = Illyriad Games Ltd
| distributor    =
| license        =
| series         =
| engine         = [[ASP.NET MVC Framework|ASP.NET MVC]]&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot;&gt;[http://www.illyriad.co.uk/about-illyriad-games-limited About Illyriad Games Ltd]&lt;/ref&gt;
| version        = 2
| released       = {{Start date|2010|02|22}} &lt;small&gt;(alpha)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{Start date|2011|03|31}} &lt;small&gt;(beta)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{release date|2011|05|16}} &lt;small&gt;(v1)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Launch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thirteen1.com/2011/05/16/illyriad-f2p-strategy-game-launches/|title=Illyriad F2P Strategy Game Launches! |date={{Start date|2011|05|16}} |publisher=T1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| genre          = [[Real-time strategy|Real-time]] [[Strategy video game|Strategy]] &lt;br /&gt;Fantasy [[City-building game|City-building]] [[Browser game]]
| modes          = [[Multiplayer video game|Multiplayer]] [[MMORTS#Real-time_strategy|MMORTS]]
| ratings        =
| platforms      = Platform independent&lt;br /&gt;[[Web browser]]
| media          =
| requirements   = [[Web browser]], [[Internet access]]
| input          =
}}

'''Illyriad''' is a [[Free-to-play|free to play]]&lt;ref name=&quot;webfusion&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://blog.webfusion.co.uk/2010/03/24/internet-trailblazer-james-nieswand-www-illyriad-com/|title=Internet Trailblazer: James Niesewand|publisher=[[GX Networks|Webfusion]] |date={{Start date|2010|03|24}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[massively multiplayer online game|massively multiplayer online]] [[browser-based game|browser-based]] [[MMORTS|strategy game]] developed by the UK software company Illyriad Games Ltd, the company's first full online strategy game,&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt; first released in beta in 2010,&lt;ref name=&quot;bbg&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://news.bbgsite.com/content/2010-04-25/recommended_browser_games_in_may_2010,9.shtml|title=Recommended Browser Games in May 2010: Illyriad|publisher=BBGsite.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; and launched in 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;MCV2011-05-16&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.mcvuk.com/press-releases/read/this-is-illyriad|title=This Is Illyriad|date={{Start date|2011|05|16}}|publisher=[[Market for Home Computing and Video Games|MCV]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Like many browser games, there is no set goal. The game is played on an infinite-round basis—there are no resets planned.&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ForumReset&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/the-newness-18aug10_topic929_post6698.html#6698|title=No server reset|publisher=Illyriad Forum |author=GM Stormcrow |date={{Start date|2010|08|25}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; The game uses pure [[Javascript]] Web technology, and is not based on [[Adobe Flash]], unlike many other browser-based games.

An interview by Massively with Illyriad's &quot;GM Stormcrow&quot; focused on the game's origins: Illyriad was born out of a conversation &quot;along the lines of: 'Wouldn't it be great if there was a free-to-play MMORPG and [[Real-time strategy|RTS]] empire-building game in a persistent, hand-crafted world that didn't treat players like cash cows? And -- graphics aside -- why can't you have the depth of a big-budget sandbox production like [[Eve Online|EVE Online]] in a 2-D, cross-platform, browser-based game?'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-03-20&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/04/05/mmobility-illyriad-a-kingdom-in-your-pocket|title=MMObility: Illyriad, a kingdom in your pocket |author=Hindman, Beau |date={{Start date|2011|04|05}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively (Featured) }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Illyriad was showcased in the Mozilla Labs 2010 Game On Gallery.&lt;ref name=&quot;GameOn-2010&quot;&gt;[https://gaming.mozillalabs.com/games/48/illyriad Mozilla Game On 2010] [[Mozilla Labs]]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gameplay ==
[[File:IllyriadInterfaceWideShowingCityMap.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Full Illyriad interface in widescreen, focused on City map, with undocked Global chat on left|Full Illyriad interface in widescreen, focused on City map, with undocked Global chat on right]]
[[File:Illyriad-World-Ocean-560.jpg|thumb|alt=Ocean and an archipelago in the Illyriad world map.|Ocean and an archipelago in the Illyriad world map]]

'''Illyriad''' is set in a [[Persistent world|persistent fantasy world]] – when a player logs out, the game continues. Player start with a single town in which they construct and upgrade buildings and conduct research to unlock new technologies. Player civilizations can be expanded by conquering cities, sending settlers to colonize new lands or claiming sovereignty to expand player influence. It has a gameworld of over 4 million squares - the majority of which can be settled with a city. 

&quot;I love the look of Illyriad ... It has a nice, hand-drawn feel to it and appears warm, inviting, and epic. Scrolling across the map feels like scanning an actual cloth map, complete with hidden areas and scattered empires.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-07-05&quot; /&gt;

The game has four playable races, each with their own advantages and disadvantages: Humans,&lt;ref name=&quot;HumanRace&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.illyriad.co.uk/Codex/HumansOrigins|title=Origins Humans|work=Illyriad Codex|publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Elves in fantasy fiction and games|Elves]],&lt;ref name=&quot;ElfRace&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.illyriad.co.uk/Codex/ElvesOrigins|title=Origins Elves|work=Illyriad Codex|publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt; Dwarves,&lt;ref name=&quot;DwarfRace&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.illyriad.co.uk/Codex/DwarvesOrigins|title=Origins Dwarves|work=Illyriad Codex|publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Orc]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;OrcRace&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.illyriad.co.uk/Codex/OrcsOrigins|title=Origins Orcs|work=Illyriad Codex|publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There are five main types of basic resources: Wood, Clay, Iron, Stone and Food. They are available from the Lumberjack, Clay Pit, Iron Mine, Quarry and Farmyard respectively. Mana and research are produced by the mage tower and library, and used for magic and research. Gold is the currency in the game, which pays the wages for troops, caravans and diplomats; as well as player to player trade in the marketplace. Advanced resources are built from other resources: horses, livestock, beer, books, spears, swords, bows, saddles, leather armour, chainmail, plate armour and siege blocks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Resources&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.illyriad.co.uk/resources.aspx|title=Resources in Illyriad|publisher=Illyriad}}&lt;/ref&gt; These are used in the construction of units.

[[File:Illyriad-Leather-Prices.jpg|thumb|alt=Illyriad Leather Armour market|Illyriad Leather Armour market]]
It also has magic with several spell schools; a commodities trading [[marketplace]]&lt;ref name=&quot;MobyGames&quot;&gt;{{MobyGames|id=/illyriad|name=Illyriad}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Quest (video gaming)|quests]] which are different based on player race.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/17apr11-quest-content-release_topic1812.html|title=Quest Content Release|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|04|17}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Illyriad's military unit categories are: Infantry, Spearmen, Cavalry, Archers and Siege engines; with multiple strategies including attack, [[Raid (military)|raid]], [[feint]], [[Military occupation|occupy]], reinforce, [[blockade]] and [[siege]]. Combat is both [[Player versus player|PvP]] and [[Player versus environment|PvE]]. Army commanders gain [[Experience point|experience]] from combat which the player can use to train the commander's [[Statistic_(role-playing_games)#Skills|skills]].

The &quot;diplomatic&quot; research options include: Spying, counter-intelligence, theft, sabotage and assassination.

With the right technologies researched, using an army a player can claim [[sovereignty]] on occupied territory for various advantages.

=== Technologies ===
[[File:IllyriadResearchTree.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Technology tree of Illyriad]]
''Illyriad's'' [[technology tree]] has 290 research options. They are categorized into 7 research areas: City, Diplomacy, Quest, Magic, Military, Trade and Sovereignty. There are also discoveries which are found via quests.

To research a new technology, it is first necessary to research the prerequisite technology - also some technologies have a prerequisite building level that must be built (for example, Smelting can only be researched after Craftsmanship has been researched and the town has a level 7 Quarry).

Researched technology is on a per city basis, so when a player settles a new town, they must research the technology for that town separately. The game's technology tree displays all the non-discovery techs in the game and their relation with one another, and allows the player to queue up to 2 technologies per town for research. Discoveries when found are at that point revealed to the player and do not require to be researched.

Completed researches count towards the players overall research score.

=== Terrain ===
The outcome of battles is not determined only by the size of armies, but is also influenced by the [[terrain]] of the battle ground and types of units engaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;jeuxonline&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.jeuxonline.info/jeu/Illyriad|title=Illyriad - JeuxOnLine|publisher=[[:fr:JeuxOnLine|JeuxOnLine]]}}{{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Units' offensive and defensive abilities vary with the terrain they occupy. For example: &quot;mountains favour ranged units and nimble spearmen, and penalise cavalry heavily. Attacking swordsmen are also hampered by the passes, gulleys and canyons that make frontal assaults more difficult.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Terrain1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/5-combat_topic71.html|title=Combat|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2010|03|07}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While there are many more terrain sub-types (e.g. Light Tropical Cover, Rockhewn Monastery, Dense Jungle, Dense Rainforest), the main overall terrains for combat purposes are:&lt;ref name=&quot;Terrain2&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/terrain-types_topic1803_post18574.html#18574|title=Terrain Types|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|04|17}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{| 
| 
*Buildings
*Plains
*Small Forest
*Large Forest
|
*Small Hill
*Large Hill
*Small Mountain
*Large Mountain
|
*Fresh Water
*Shallow Salt Water
*Tidal Water
*Ocean
|}

=== Evolving World ===
The world of Illyriad changes and evolves over time. Mysteries and special locations are added to the world such as The Temple of Reason, The Heroic Statues and the Steampunk brewery. &quot;For the game as a whole this is really nice. It means that players can stumble upon local oddities, and investigate (or ignore) these as they choose.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wisdomofkurdruk.wordpress.com/2011/06/14/a-changing-landscape/|title=A Changing Landscape|date={{Start date|2011|06|14}}|author=Kurdruk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Jun 2011 the geography of one part of the world became [[Infection|infected]] and changes on a daily basis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gamasutra2011-06-16&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.gamasutra.com/view/pressreleases/73672/A_World_of_Change_This_Is_Illyriad.php|title=A World of Change: This Is Illyriad|date={{Start date|2011|06|16}}|publisher=[[Gamasutra]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Alliances ===
Players can form [[alliance]]s, and are provided with alliance [[Internet forum|forums]], [[Online chat|chat]] and a central treasury. Alliances interrelationships begin neutral, but they can choose to enter different states with each other such as: [[Confederation]], [[Non-aggression pact|NAP]] or War.

As well as the &quot;hard power&quot; of alliances in war, diplomacy, protection and politics; alliances in Illyriad allow players to cooperate to achieve things that would be beyond them as individuals. This includes investigating and solving mysteries spread across the world&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wisdomofkurdruk.wordpress.com/2011/05/26/the-soft-power-of-alliances/|title=The Soft Power of Alliances|date={{Start date|2011|05|26}}|author=Kurdruk}}&lt;/ref&gt; and competing in server wide tournaments.

=== Political Intrigue ===
Alliance and players are also continuously drawing and changing territorial lines and having secret meetings that decide the fate of entire sections of the world. However with a very large world and realistic travel times for trade, diplomats and military it becomes hard for even large alliances to exert direct force at large distances from their core power blocks.

&quot;Search the map for alliances and you witness how many lines are indeed being drawn. Despite the very friendly community, I never once stop thinking about the battles and wars going on at that very moment.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-05-11&quot; /&gt;

=== Tournaments ===
''Illyriad'' also features server-wide [[tournament]]s in which players compete and players are rewarded individually and at the Alliance level.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tournament1&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/30dec10-the-kings-first-tournament_topic1402.html|title=The King's First Tournament|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2010|12|30}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; These tournaments have been also used to introduce new gameplay dynamics like creature drops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tournament2-Massively&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/04/11/illyriads-second-tournament-asks-players-to-kill-bunnies-and-ki/|title=Illyriad's second tournament asks players to kill bunnies and kittens |date={{Start date|2011|04|11}}|publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The tournaments have been month long events and have been as follows:
* Jan 2011: The first tournament was an [[Realm versus Realm|Alliance versus Alliance]] &quot;Hold the Fort&quot; event. Eight equidistant locations in the world acted as &quot;forts&quot;, which had to be held by player's armies. At the end of the month the Alliance who had held a location for the longest was the winner of that &quot;fort&quot;. Also a prize was given to the Alliance which had held the most locations for the longest time overall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tournament1&quot; /&gt;
* Apr 2011: The second tournament was a [[Player versus Environment]] event which required players to combat [[Non-player character|NPC]] animal spawns and retrieve &quot;anatomical specimens&quot;. Players were individually rewarded for being the greatest hunter of each creature type; having the largest collection and having the largest number of unique parts. Alliances received rewards for having the largest collection and having the largest number of unique parts between all the Alliances.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tournament2&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/kings-2nd-tournament-bloodthirst-for-knowledge_topic1776.html|title=Bloodthirst For Knowledge|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|04|11}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Jun 2011: The third tournament was a [[Player versus All]] &quot;Hold the Fort&quot; event. The eight locations from the first tournament acted as  spawn points for [[elemental]]s, which would bind to the player holding the square and become a unit in their town. On these squares all Alliance affiliations were suspended so all players were hostile to each other on these squares.&lt;ref name=&quot;ModDB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.moddb.com/games/illyriad/news/tournament-iii-harness-the-elementals|title=Tournament III - Harness the Elementals|publisher=[[Mod DB]]|date={{Start date|2011|06|20}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the elementals, at the end of the tournament players were also rewarded for each of the elementals they had bound and the top players from each square received a Tournament Winner's Statue placed at the winners' choice on any unoccupied map square within 10 squares of their Capital City.  This Monument bears their name and is a permanent marker on the World Map.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tournament3&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/harness-the-elementals-introduction-rules_topic2037.html|title=Harness The Elementals - Introduction Rules|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|06|16}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Compatibility==
''Illyriad'' can be played in any web browser which supports the [[HTML]]&lt;ref name=&quot;canvas&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/09aug11-map-changes-other-fixes_topic2247.html |title=Illyriad Canvas Release |publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt; standards; including mobile devices (e.g. [[iPad]], [[iPhone]], [[Android (operating system)|Android]], [[BlackBerry]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-03-20&quot; /&gt; Unlike many other browser-based online games, it doesn't depend on the proprietary [[Adobe Flash|Flash]] plug-in. Illyriad is supported by Mozilla Firefox, Google Chrome, Opera, Safari and Internet Explorer 8+. Further, the game has a special Facebook-mode,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.facebook.com/illyriad |title=Illyriad Facebook application page |publisher=Illyriad Games Ltd}}&lt;/ref&gt; using Facebook-specific features such as Facebook connect, game announcements and other community features. Illyriad is also featured in the Facebook application directory.

&quot;Illyriad shines in its ability to be played across any device, anywhere, over any connection.&quot;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-07-05&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/07/05/mmobility-how-to-real-time-strategize-your-way-into-my-heart/|title=MMObility: How to real-time-strategize your way into my heart |date={{Start date|2011|07|05}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Business model ==
The game does not use ads, and is fully funded by the optional purchase of &quot;prestige&quot; offering a slight advantage using [[Microtransaction#In_MMORPGs|microtransactions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;jeuxonline&quot; /&gt; This [[virtual currency]] can be purchased via [[PayPal]], [[mobile payment]] using [[Fortumo]]&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt;, [[Google Checkout]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GoogleCheckout&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/26aug11-new-art-google-checkout-relocate_topic2302.html|title=New Art, Google Checkout, Relocate|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|08|26}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and [[Facebook Credits]] for Facebook players.&lt;ref name=&quot;FacebookCredits&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/25apr11-facebook-credits_topic1840.html|title=Facebook Credits|publisher=Illyriad Forum |date={{Start date|2011|04|25}}}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Research, troop builds and advanced resource production ''cannot'' be sped up through the use of in game currency. &quot;Despite the fact that players can purchase &quot;prestige&quot; to help speed up deliveries [caravans] or building upgrades, research is unaffected by any boosts. This means that players have to ''wait'' to become smarter, as in real life.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-05-11&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/05/11/free-for-all-gaming-with-game-of-thrones/|title=Free for All: Gaming with Game of Thrones |date={{Start date|2011|05|11}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Development ==
=== Initial release ===
Illyriad began development in 2009, and was the first game developed by Illyriad Games Ltd.&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt; It began with 3 developers and 3 artists, however only 2 were full time - with the others working at other jobs.&lt;ref name=&quot;webfusion&quot; /&gt; The core Illyriad development team's background was from web and enterprise software, not games - and the initial content was provided by [[Volunteering|volunteers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Develop-2011-05-05&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.develop-online.net/features/1182/Development-without-a-dev-team|title=Development without a dev team |author=Crossley, Rob |date={{Start date|2011|05|05}} |work= |publisher=[[Develop (magazine)|Develop]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

James Niesewand, Illyriad Games founder, described the process: &quot;From start to finish it took us about a year to get something playable ... for us that was just the point at which we had something fun that people could enjoy. At that stage we put the game live, invited people to play, and worked on improving the game in line with the players’ feedback.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Develop-2011-05-05&quot; /&gt;

Critical development software included Microsoft ASP.NET MVC and [[jQuery]]. Illyriad uses Microsoft SQL Server for persistent game data.&lt;ref name=&quot;About&quot; /&gt;

=== Continued development ===
After initial launch, the development of Illyriad continued. The world was changed from being randomly generated into one which was [[fractal]]ly generated including topographical features:  mountain ranges, lakes, forests, hills, oceans, islands, rivers etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Topography-2010-09-14&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/major-release-14sep10-world-topography_topic1019.html|title=World Topography |date={{Start date|2010|09|14}} |publisher=Illyriad Forum }}&lt;/ref&gt; This was then followed by the introduction of [[biome]]s including [[Deserts and xeric shrublands|desert]], [[jungle]], [[Wetland|marshes]] and [[Arctic|the polar north]]; as well as [[Country|regions]] and NPC [[Political faction|Factions]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BiomeFactions-2010-10-11&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/update-11oct10-imminent-release_topic1156_page1.html|title=Release of Factions and Biomes onto the World map |date={{Start date|2010|10|11}} |publisher=Illyriad Forum }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rather than continuing the development with a single internal team, Illyriad Games used a highly distributed model; composed of remote workers in different countries and outsourced suppliers. They bought on board Quantic Labs for the graphics which were used to relaunch&lt;ref name=&quot;IndieDB&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.moddb.com/games/illyriad/news/illyriad-user-interface-v2-unleashed |title=Illyriad - User Interface v2 unleashed! |publisher=[[Mod DB]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; the user interface. Their &quot;artists and writers [were given] a lot of creative freedom&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Develop-2011-05-05&quot; /&gt; when producing new graphics and content.

==== HTML5 Canvas ====
On 09 Aug 2011 the World Map changed from HTML DOM to HTML5 [[Canvas element|Canvas]]&lt;ref name=&quot;canvas&quot; /&gt;. 
This brought a number of changes: 
* An increase of the map zoom by ten levels, allowing 25 levels of zoom and increasing the grid to 51 x 51 tiles.
* Drag and drop, and mouse wheel zoom of the world map in the style of Google Maps.
* Movement and continual updating of moving units
* 'Fog of War' visibility for diplomats

==== OpenId Support ====
On 19 Aug 2011 [[OpenID]] authentication was introduced for new and existing players to sign up or link their account using their Google, Yahoo, AOL, myOpenID, OpenId, Wordpress, LiveJournal, Blogger, Verisign, ClaimId, ClickPass or Google Profile accounts.&lt;ref name=&quot;OpenId-2011-08-19&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/19aug11-devblog-openid-and-fixes_topic2281.html|title=DevBlog, OpenId and fixes |date={{Start date|2011|08|19}} |publisher=Illyriad Forum }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Avatar Graphics Update ====
''Illyriad'' hired artists to improve their character portraits,&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-08-30&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/08/30/mmobility-what-makes-a-good-mobile-game-to-me/|title=MMObility: What makes a good mobile game to me |date={{Start date|2011|08|30}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt; which were released in August 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;GoogleCheckout&quot; /&gt;

== Reception ==

Of the three games chosen to go with [[Joystiq|Massively]] on a trip to the desert island ''Illyriad'' was one of them: &quot;...I would have to go with Illyriad, the fantastic browser-based city-builder.... Illyriad is a delight to play.&quot; and added: &quot;Given Illyriad's realistic trade, amazing community, and variable-speed gameplay, I would be insane to leave this one off the list.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-04-26&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/04/26/mmobility-survival-on-a-desert-island/|title=MMObility: Survival on a desert island |author=Hindman, Beau |date={{Start date|2011|04|26}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was also selected for the top eleven (in no particular order) of Massively's Fifty games for the mobile lifestyle: &quot;This little surprise [Illyriad] has taken hold of me. Imagine an epic RTS but with killer lore and an awesome community.&quot;
&lt;ref name=&quot;Massively-2011-06-21&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://massively.joystiq.com/2011/06/21/mmobility-fifty-games-for-the-mobile-lifestyle/|title=MMObility: Fifty games for the mobile lifestyle |date={{Start date|2011|06|21}} |work= |publisher=[[Joystiq]], Massively }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
&lt;!--- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Footnotes on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.illyriad.co.uk/ Official website of ''Illyriad'']
* [http://forum.illyriad.co.uk/ ''Illyriad'' Forums]
* [http://uk1.illyriad.co.uk/Account/Register ''Illyriad'' Player Signup]
* [https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/hnfbcdoedgikkjokbgejbgkgijnoaanb ''Illyriad'' Chrome App] on [[Chrome Web Store]]
* [http://www.facebook.com/illyriad ''Illyriad'' Facebook App] on [[Facebook]]
* [http://blog.illyriad.co.uk/ ''Illyriad'' Developer Blog]

{{Massively multiplayer online strategy video games}}

&lt;!--- Categories --&gt;

[[Category:4X video games]]
[[Category:Indie video games]]
[[Category:2011 video games]]
[[Category:Strategy video games]]
[[Category:Browser-based multiplayer online games]]
[[Category:Fantasy video games]]
[[Category:Massively multiplayer online games]]
[[Category:Massively multiplayer online real-time strategy games]]
[[Category:Video games developed in the United Kingdom]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
