<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31475827" ns="0" title="Richmond–Mahinda Cricket Encounter"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox SL Interschool Tournaments
| Tournament name          = Richmond–Mahinda Cricket Encounter ( Lovers' Quarrel )
| Image1                   =
| Size1                    = 
| Caption1                 = 
| Image2                   = 
| Size2                    = 
| Caption2                 = 
| Sport                    = [[Cricket]]
| Organizers               = 
| Timeline                 = 1905 – present
| Tournament format        = Annual two-day encounter
| Tournament participants  = [[Richmond College (Sri Lanka)|Richmond College]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mahinda College]]
| Entrants                 = 
| Teams participated       = 
| Winner                   =  Mahinda College (2008)&lt;ref name=&quot;A&quot;&gt;[http://www.nation.lk/2010/03/14/sports6.htm Richmond-Mahinda evenly matched for a draw]&lt;/ref&gt;
| Most wins                =  Mahinda College (23-21)&lt;ref name=&quot;A&quot;/&gt;
| Biggest win              = 
| Consecutive wins         = 
| Footnotes                =
}}
The '''Richmond–Mahinda Cricket Encounter''' is an annual [[cricket]] big match played between the first XI cricket teams of [[Richmond College (Sri Lanka)|Richmond College]] and [[Mahinda College]] in [[Galle]], [[Sri Lanka]].  It is one of the longest cricket match series in Sri Lanka, having been played for 106 years.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sports.dailymirror.lk/2011/03/24/sri-lanka-junior-stars-in-focus-at-lovers-quarrel/ Sri Lanka junior stars in focus at Lovers’ Quarrel]&lt;/ref&gt; The match is also known as the &quot;Lovers' Quarrel&quot; in public and it is played at the [[Galle International Stadium]]. Lovers' Quarrel was begun in 1905, under principals Rev. James Horne Darrel of Richmond and Frank Lee Woodward of Mahinda.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.island.lk/2005/05/06/sports10.html Richmond, Mahinda clash in Centenary year]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Series summary==
Out of the big matches played up to 2011, Mahinda College has won 23 matches while Richmond College has won 21 matches. Richmond College won the inaugural match in 1905 and Mahinda College's first victory was registered in 1908.
Mahinda College’s last victory in a big match was recorded in 2008, while Richmond College's last win was recorded 42 years ago, in 1969.&lt;ref&gt;[http://thepapare.com/index.php/sports/cricket/189-southern-sri-lanka-awaits-action-at-106th-lovers-quarrel Southern Sri Lanka awaits action at 106th Lover’s Quarrel ]&lt;/ref&gt; Having broken a 30 year deadlock of draws, Mahindians  registered an emphatic 10 wicket win over Richmondites in the 2008 encounter.

In 1953, Mahindian Somasiri Ambawatte captured all ten Richmond’s [[wickets]] in an [[innings]] to claim the [[Bowler (cricket)|bowling]] record of the series and in the same match he scored a century to record the finest [[All-rounder|all round]] feat in the history of the big match.&lt;ref name=&quot;B&quot;&gt;[http://sundaytimes.lk/100314/Sports/spt11.html Richmond looks to break Mahinda stranglehold]&lt;/ref&gt; In 1972, Mahindians piled up the highest score by a team, when they totaled 359 with their top order batsman P. H. K. H. Ranasinghe scoring 162. It is the highest individual score by a [[batsman]] in the big match series.&lt;ref name=&quot;B&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable players==
Following cricketers who took part in Richmond–Mahinda cricket encounter during their school days, later went on to represent the [[Sri Lanka national cricket team|national cricket team of Sri Lanka]].

{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
;Mahinda College
* Douglas Dias Jayasinha
* [[Stanley de Silva|D. L. S. de Silva]]
* [[Athula Samarasekera]]
* [[Jayananda Warnaweera]]
* [[Upul Chandana]]
* [[Lasith Malinga]]
   
{{col-3}}
;Richmond College
* [[Champaka Ramanayake]]
* [[Chamila Gamage]]
* [[Suranga Lakmal]]

{{col-end}}

==See also==
*[[Mahinda College]]
*[[Richmond College (Sri Lanka)|Richmond College]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Big Matches in Sri Lanka]]


{{SriLanka-sport-stub}}
{{Cricket-competition-stub}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
