<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31490259" ns="0" title="2011 Kurdish protests in Turkey"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Out of date|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox civil conflict
| title = 2011 Kurdish protests in Turkey
| partof = [[Serhildan]]; the [[impact of the Arab Spring|impact]] of the [[Arab Spring]]
| image =&lt;!-- Deleted image removed:  [[File:Turkey election board protest 19apr11 480.jpg|275px]] --&gt;
| caption = &lt;small&gt;Demonstrators march with yellow Peace and Democracy Party (BDP) flags and display outlawed Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) banners during a protest against the High Election Board's decision in Istanbul, April 19, 2011&lt;/small&gt;
| place = {{flag|Turkey}}
| coordinates =
| date = {{start date|2011|03|24}} – ''ongoing''
| status = Ongoing
| goals = Lifting of a ban on Kurdish candidates, reinstitution of [[Kurdish language|Kurdish-language]] education, creation of an autonomous Kurdish region, release of political prisoners, end of military operations against Kurdish dissidents&lt;ref name=&quot;RudawinEng&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rudaw.net/english/news/turkey/3539.html|agency=Rudaw|title=Call for Civil Disobedience in Turkey|date=4 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|first=Hemin|last=Khoshnaw}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IstanbulXinhua&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2011/4/turkey3190.htm|agency=Kurd Net|date=20 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Thousands of Kurds protest barring of Kurdish political candidates in Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| causes = Political repression, suppression of Kurdish language, alleged institutional racism, discrimination,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/mar/assessment.asp?groupId=64005|publisher=University of Maryland, Center for International Development and Conflict Management|date=31 December 2006|accessdate=30 April 2011|title=Minorities at Risk: Assessment for Kurds in Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt; centralization of authority, ban on several Kurdish parliamentary candidates&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/mob_n.php?n=ysk-puts-ankara-in-turmoil-exit-strategy-sought-2011-04-19 YSK ruling throws Ankara into tumultuous search for exit strategy&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
| time =
| timezone =
| methods = [[Civil disobedience]], [[civil resistance]], [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]], [[online activism]], [[protest march]]es, [[riot]]ing, [[sit-in]]s, [[strike action]]s, [[friday prayers]]
| side1 =[[Peace and Democracy Party]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Koma Civakên Kurdistan]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Kurdistan Workers' Party]]
| side2 =[[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Turkish Armed Forces]]&lt;br&gt;
[[General Directorate of Security|Turkish Police Force]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Village Guards]]
| leadfigures1 ='''Kurdish Leaders:'''&lt;br&gt;
*[[Selahattin Demirtaş]]
*[[Gülten Kışanak]]
*[[Abdullah Öcalan]]
*[[Murat Karayılan]]
*[[Zübeyir Aydar]]
*[[Bahoz Erdal]]
| leadfigures2 =
'''Government Leaders:'''
*[[Abdullah Gül]]
*[[Recep Tayyip Erdoğan]]
*[[Beşir Atalay]]
*[[İdris Naim Şahin]]
'''Turkish Army'''
*[[Necdet Özel]]
| howmany1 =
| howmany2 =
| injuries =308&lt;ref name=&quot;casualties&quot;&gt;[[Hurriyet]] [http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=thousands-detained-in-the-east-since-march-2011-05-13 Thousands detained in eastern Turkey since March], May 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
| fatalities = 3&lt;ref name=&quot;casualties&quot;/&gt; &lt;ref&gt;http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=turkish-iraqi-ties-strained-over-claims-of-civilian-deaths-2011-08-26&lt;/ref&gt;
| arrests =2,506&lt;ref name=&quot;casualties&quot;/&gt;
| concessions = Ban on some Kurdish candidates lifted&lt;ref name=&quot;welcome&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/04/2011421172713775785.html|agency=Al Jazeera English|date=21 April 2011|accessdate=28 April 2011|title=Turkish Kurds welcome poll decision}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Kurdish Rebellions}}
The '''2011 Kurdish protests in Turkey''' are ongoing protests by members of [[Republic of Turkey|Turkey]]'s [[Kurdish people|Kurdish]] minority to demonstrate against restrictions of their rights by the Turkish authorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.france24.com/en/20110420-one-killed-kurdish-protests-turkey-politician |title=One killed in Kurdish protests in Turkey: politician |publisher=FRANCE 24 |date= |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although they are the latest in a [[Kurdish rebellions|long series]] of [[Serhildan|protest actions]] by [[Kurds in Turkey]], they are strongly influenced by the concurrent [[2010-2011 Middle East and North Africa protests|popular protests]] throughout the [[Middle East]] and [[North Africa]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/22/world/europe/22kurds.html?_r=1|agency=The New York Times|title=Kurds Renew Their Movement for Rights and Respect in Turkey|first=Landon|last=Thomas|date=21 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=Alexander|last=Christie-Miller|url=http://www.eurasianet.org/node/63347|title=Turkey Drops Ban on Kurdish-Backed Candidates|agency=EurasiaNet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sundayszaman.com/sunday/columnistDetail_getNewsById.action?newsId=240580&amp;columnistId=110|agency=Zaman|date=9 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Diyarbakır and Lefkoşa|first=Ergun|last=Babahan}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.anarkismo.net/article/19377|title=Sinan Çiftyürek on the Arab Spring: &quot;the relation politics/streets has been re-forged&quot;|agency=Anarkismo|date=23 April 2011|accessdate=1 May 2011|first=José Antonio|last=Gutiérrez D.}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Turkish publication ''[[Hürriyet Daily News]]'' has suggested that the popularly dubbed &quot;Arab Spring&quot; that has seen revolutions in [[2011 Egyptian revolution|Egypt]] and [[Tunisian Revolution|Tunisia]] may lead to a &quot;Kurdish Summer&quot; in the northern reaches of the Middle East.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=the-arab-spring-the-kurdish-summer-2011-04-11|agency=Hürriyet Daily News|date=11 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=The Arab Spring, the Kurdish Summer|first=Kadri|last=Gürsel}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protesters have taken to the streets both in [[İstanbul]] and in [[southeast Turkey]], with some demonstrations also reported as far west in [[Anatolia]] as [[İzmir]].

From March 24 and May 10, a total of 2 protesters were killed, 308 injured and 2,506 detained by Turkish authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;casualties&quot;/&gt;

==Background==
[[File:Kurdish-inhabited area by CIA (1992).jpg|thumb|350px|right|Map of Kurdish populated territory. Kurdish protests also took place in [[2011 Iraqi protests|Iraq]], [[2011 Syrian uprising|Syria]], and [[2011 Iranian protests|Iran]] in early 2011.]]

There are currently 14 to 20 million [[Kurds in Turkey]], living predominantly in the southeast of the country.  The Kurdish people are a unique ethnic group with their own language and customs. In Turkey, the Kurdish uprising dates back to at least 1925, but the most recent [[Turkey – Kurdistan Workers' Party conflict|major rebellion]] started in 1978 and has crossed the border into adjacent [[Iraqi Kurdistan]] on a number of occasions. Over 3,000 Kurdish villages have been &quot;evacuated&quot; by the Turkish armed forces since the conflict began.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newyouth.com/archives/middleeast/us_nato_hypocrisy_exposed_as_tur.html |title=US/NATO Hypocrisy Exposed as Turkey Attacks Kurds |publisher=Newyouth.com |date=1999-04-21 |accessdate=2011-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Kurdistan Workers' Party]] (PKK), a Kurdish separatist group listed as a [[terrorist organization]] by the governments of Turkey and the [[United States]], demands autonomy for [[Turkish Kurdistan]]. It has also called upon Turkish authorities to release Kurdish prisoners and detainees, overturn a ban on [[Kurdish language|Kurdish-language]] education, and cease military action against Kurdish groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;ekurd1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2011/3/turkey3163.htm|agency=Kurd Net|date=24 March 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Turkey's Kurds launch protest movement for rights}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, Prime Minister [[Recep Tayyip Erdoğan]] launched a &quot;Kurdish initative&quot; aiming to broaden cultural rights for Kurds, but many Kurdish protesters have said this does not go far enough.&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/middleeast/2011/02/2011228162351651625.html Kurdish rebels end Turkey 'truce' - Middle East - Al Jazeera English&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 February 2011, the PKK announced an end to a unilateral ceasefire it had declared in August 2010, prompting Erdoğan to comment on the pro-Kurdish [[Peace and Democracy Party]] (BDP) over its alleged collusion with the militant group. &quot;A political party that is in Parliament hurling out threats ... during every election period puts pressure on people who want to exercise their democratic will and serves no other purpose,&quot; the prime minister said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.am/eng/news/50001.html|agency=NEWS.am|date=3 March 2011|accessdate=28 April 2011|title=PKK ceasefire end seen as step to help “Peace and Democracy” Party in elections}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Censorship===
[[Internet]] [[Internet censorship|censorship]] is practiced by the government of Turkey. A number of websites, including those of pro-Kurdish and alternative news outlets such as [[Voice of America]], [[Bianet]], and ''[[Azadiya Welat]]'', are subject to a filter imposed by the [[Turkish Council of State]]. Bianet reported that according to new regulations adopted by the government in late February, this filter will be expanded from blocking access to certain websites from [[Internet café]]s to affect all Internet access points and [[Internet service provider|ISP]]s in Turkey sometime in the near future.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bianet.org/english/freedom-of-expression/129279-internet-should-not-become-the-voice-of-ankara|agency=Bianet|date=15 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Internet Should not Become the &quot;Voice of Ankara&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 March 2011, ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported a turnout of &quot;thousands&quot; for a march in [[İstanbul]] protesting [[censorship]] of the press and the arrest of over a dozen journalists by Turkish authorities since the start of the month. The Turkish media advocacy group [[Freedom to Journalists Platform]] said Turkey held 68 journalists as of mid-March, including many on charges of &quot;inciting public hatred&quot; and similar offenses, though the government maintains only 27 journalists are incarcerated on unrelated charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/03/14/world/asia/14turkey.html|agency=The New York Times|date=13 March 2011|accessdate=29 April 2011|title=In Turkey, Thousands Protest a Crackdown on Press Freedom|first=Sebnem|last=Arsu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Timeline==
[[File:PKK.svg|300px|right|thumb|Flag of the outlawed [[Kurdistan Workers' Party]] or PKK (Partiya Karkerên Kurdistan), often used at Kurdish demonstrations.]]
===March===
====24 March====
In a statement published online on 24 March, the [[Peace and Democracy Party]] (BDP) announced the immediate beginning of a [[civil disobedience]] campaign, beginning with a strike and [[sit-in]] in [[Diyarbakır]], the largest city in the Kurdish region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.kurdish-info.eu/News-sid-URGENT-STATEMENT-from-Peace-and-Democracy-Party-BDP-16544.html|agency=Kurdish Info|date=24 March 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=URGENT STATEMENT from Peace and Democracy Party - BDP}}&lt;/ref&gt; The government responded by deploying soldiers and [[Turkish Army|Army]] vehicles to break up the unsanctioned demonstration, which drew about 3,000 participants. Just a fraction of these participants—a few dozen [[member of parliament|MP]]s and Kurdish city officials, including the mayor of Diyarbakır—were permitted to proceed to the sit-in venue, while thousands more demonstrators thronged outside and shouted angry slogans. Police clashed with demonstrators, some of whom attempted to attack officers with [[firework]]s, and detained five. A similar scene erupted in [[Batman, Turkey|Batman]], where a larger number of protesters were reportedly detained and protest tents were forcibly taken down.&lt;ref name=&quot;ekurd1&quot;/&gt;

====27 March====
Demonstrations spread to [[İstanbul]], [[İzmir]], [[Silopi]], and [[Antalya]] by 27 March. Protest camps also sprang up in [[Dersim]], [[Muş]], [[Van, Turkey|Van]], and [[Ağrı]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.aknews.com/en/aknews/3/227805/|agency=Kurdistan News Agency|title=Kurdish civil rebellion continues in Turkey|accessdate=27 April 2011|date=27 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several dozen protesters were arrested.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dawn&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dawn.com/2011/03/27/turkey%E2%80%99s-kurds-begin-civil-disobedience-campaign.html|agency=Dawn|date=27 March 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|first=Suzan|last=Fraser|title=Turkey’s Kurds begin ‘civil disobedience’ campaign}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Protest leader and MP [[Selahattin Demirtaş]] said that the [[Peace and Democracy Party]] was determined to carry out civil disobedience actions across the Kurdish region and condemned the governor of [[Diyarbakır Province]] for declaring the protests unlawful. Fellow Kurdish leader [[Ahmet Türk]] said they will continue the sit-in action despite the pressure from the Turkish authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;ekurd1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;RudawinEng&quot;/&gt; &quot;The prime minister who sends greetings to [[Tahrir Square]] while sending tanks and gas bombs at us should know that the [Kurdish] people have been seeking their freedom in their [own] Tahrir Squares,&quot; said Demirtaş, referring to Prime Minister [[Recep Tayyip Erdoğan]] and his [[International reactions to the 2011 Egyptian revolution|favorable stance]] toward [[Egypt]]ian [[2011 Egyptian revolution|revolutionaries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Dawn&quot;/&gt;

====28 March====
About 40,000 people marched to the alleged site of [[mass grave]]s of Kurds in [[Siirt Province]] on 28 March. The [[protest march]] spun off into [[riot]]ing in the province. In Batman and Diyarbakır, two of the original sites of protests as part of the civil disobedience campaign, media reported Turkish security forces detained several more protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.setimes.com/cocoon/setimes/xhtml/en_GB/features/setimes/features/2011/03/31/feature-03|agency=Southeast European Times|date=31 March 2011|accessdate=28 April 2011|title=Kurdish civil disobedience continues in Turkey|first=Alina|last=Lehtinen}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===April===
====6 April====
Demirtaş ratcheted up the civil disobedience campaign by Kurdish protesters on 6 April by accusing imams sent by the government to lead prayers in Turkey's [[southeast Turkey|southeast]] of supporting and spying for the ruling [[Justice and Development Party (Turkey)|Justice and Development Party]] and urging Kurds not to pray behind them. Demirtaş also said that sermons in Kurdish parts of the country should only be given in [[Kurdish language|Kurdish]], a policy Erdoğan opposes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sundayszaman.com/sunday/newsDetail_getNewsById.action?newsId=240380|agency=Zaman|date=7 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=BDP calls on Kurds not to pray behind state imams in mosques}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====8 April====
At Friday prayers in Diyarbakır on 8 April, a number of Kurds boycotted in solidarity with the BDP, with many holding signs and banners supporting Demirtaş and the protests as others prayed. At least one newspaper ran photographs of the boycott.&lt;ref name=&quot;militantimams&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.sundayszaman.com/sunday/newsDetail_getNewsById.action?newsId=240785|date=12 April 2011|title=PKK planning to disturb social peace in East, Southeast with ‘militant imams’|agency=Zaman|accessdate=27 April 2011|first=Hasim|last=Soylemez}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====11 April====
On 11 April, the conservative Turkish weekly ''[[Aksiyon]]'' published allegations that &quot;militant imams&quot; loyal to the [[Kurdistan Workers' Party|PKK]] intend to promote [[terrorism]] among Kurds by portraying PKK fighters killed in clashes with government forces as [[martyr]]s. According to the report, imprisoned PKK leader [[Abdullah Öcalan]] devised the plan from behind bars. It also alleged that the banned PKK is using the BDP as a political front.&lt;ref name=&quot;militantimams&quot;/&gt;

====19 April====
On 19 April, Turkey’s elections board ruled that 12 Kurdish politicians who had registered as independent candidates were barred from running in the June [[Turkish general election, 2011|parliamentary elections]]. The politicians included [[Leyla Zana]], who has spent ten years in prison for alleged PKK membership despite a ruling by the [[European Court of Human Rights]] that her imprisonment violated [[freedom of speech]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2011/4/turkey3189.htm Leyla Zana and 11 other Kurdish politicians barred from running for Turkish parliament&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

Kurds angry over the ban rallied in [[Hakkâri]], [[Şırnak]], İstanbul, Van, and Diyarbakır. More than 2,000 protesters gathered in [[Taksim Square]] on the [[Europe]]an side of İstanbul, Turkey's largest city.&lt;ref name=&quot;IstanbulXinhua&quot;/&gt; Police used [[tear gas]] to disperse the protest, which reportedly injured several, including at least one police officer. Shopkeepers and workers went on strike in Hakkâri and Van. Van also saw clashes between protesters and Turkish [[gendarmarie|gendarme]]s, with its Kurdish mayor being among the demonstrators injured in the fighting, and scuffles were also reported in Diyarbakır, where a 15-year-old boy was reportedly hospitalized after being shot and injured by police. The semi-official [[Anatolian Agency]] claimed significant property damage in the city of Diyarbakır and said police confiscated several [[Molotov cocktail]]s brought to the demonstration by Kurdish protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/world/2011-04/20/c_13836524.htm|agency=Xinhua|date=19 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Turkey sees protests against candidate ban}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====20 April====
On 20 April, police fired live rounds at protesters in [[Bismil]]. One protester was killed, four were injured, and at  least 16 were arrested. The incident drew outrage from the Kurdish community, with Selahattin Demirtaş canceling a planned meeting with President [[Abdullah Gül]] in [[Ankara]] over the shooting.&lt;ref name=&quot;KurdDead&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/04/2011420204329820606.html |title=Kurdish Protester Killed in Turkey Clash}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.monstersandcritics.com/news/europe/news/article_1634210.php/Political-crisis-in-Turkey-over-candidates-for-parliamentary-polls|agency=Monsters &amp; Critics|date=20 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Political crisis in Turkey over candidates for parliamentary polls}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;welcome&quot;/&gt;

====21 April====
The elections board reversed its decision to bar several Kurdish political candidates on 21 April after facing massive outcry. Some journalists expected this to be the end of intensified protests and rioting.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://articles.boston.com/2011-04-21/news/29460234_1_kurdish-rebels-pro-kurdish-leyla-zana | title=Turkey: Kurdish candidates can run for parliament - Boston.com}} {{Dead link|date=June 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nonetheless, the Anatolian Agency reported that one police officer and two civilians were injured in rioting in Batman on the same day. The semi-official news agency alleged that Kurdish protesters attacked police with rocks, firebombs, and gunfire. It also said three people were hospitalized in [[Van Province]] after Kurdish demonstrators set fire to a bank with a Molotov cocktail. Police reportedly employed [[tear gas]] and [[water cannon]]s to disperse the riot.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/90001/90777/90854/7358720.html|agency=People's Daily Online|date=22 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=One policeman, two civilians injured in Kurdish protests in Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====23 April====
According to a report in the pro-government daily ''[[Zaman]]'', alleged PKK supporters threw Molotov cocktails at a house in suburban [[Şanlıurfa]] while a family was sleeping there on the night of 23 April, seriously damaging the property but causing only minor injuries. Police detained two in connection with the incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Children narrowly escape death in Molotov cocktail attack|first=Fethi|last=Altun|url=http://www.todayszaman.com/news-241926-children-narrowly-escape-death-in-molotov-cocktail-attack.html|agency=Zaman|date=25 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====24 April====
''Zaman'' claimed pro-[[Peace and Democracy Party|BDP]] protesters in [[Ergani]] attacked buildings and gendarmes with Molotov cocktails and [[firecracker]]s. It also reported that 32 rioters in Batman were detained after a crowd of demonstrators pelted police with stones and tried to set fire to shops.&lt;ref name=&quot;YSKrev&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.todayszaman.com/news-242054-demonstrators-continue-protesting-despite-ysk-reversal.html|agency=Zaman|date=26 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Demonstrators continue protesting despite YSK reversal}}&lt;/ref&gt; These demonstrations came just days after international media reported an easing of tensions in southeast Turkey following the reversal of a ban on several Kurdish parliamentary candidates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.france24.com/en/20110422-kurdish-protests-calm-down-southeast-turkey|agency=France24|date=22 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Kurdish protests calm down in southeast Turkey}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Anatolian Agency reported that two off-duty soldiers, wearing civilian clothes, were shot from behind in [[Yüksekova]], leaving both injured. It also claimed rioting, including stone- and firebomb-throwing, in Bismil, which police reportedly used tear gas and water cannon to disperse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Kurd Net|title=Off-duty soldiers attacked in southeast Turkey|date=25 April 2011|accessdate=28 April 2011|url=http://www.ekurd.net/mismas/articles/misc2011/4/turkey3197.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====25 April====
In the early morning of 25 April, police raided and dismantled numerous &quot;democratic solution&quot; tents and arrested protesters in 17 provinces across Turkey, [[Bianet]] reported. One MP was reportedly injured in a scuffle with police.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bianet.org/english/freedom-of-expression/129566-mass-crackdowns-on-democratic-solution-tents|agency=Bianet|date=27 April 2011|accessdate=30 April 2011|title=Mass Crackdowns on 'Democratic Solution Tents'|first=Ayça|last=Soylemez}}&lt;/ref&gt;

BDP supporters protested violently in the [[Aksaray, Istanbul|Aksaray]] neighborhood of İstanbul, attacking police, vehicles, and shops, ''Zaman'' alleged.&lt;ref name=&quot;YSKrev&quot;/&gt; Turkish authorities also arrested 35 in Hakkâri on alleged PKK ties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bianet&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bianet.org/english/human-rights/129539-35-people-in-custody-tens-of-thousands-of-people-protest|agency=Bianet|title=35 People in Custody, Tens of Thousands of People Protest|date=26 April 2011|first=Nilay|last=Vardar|accessdate=27 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bianet&quot;/&gt; In response, more than 20,000 Kurds living near the international border with [[Iraq]] marched to a border crossing and threatened to enter [[Iraqi Kurdistan]] in a show of defiance unless the 35 were released, forcing Peace and Democracy Party officials to intervene. The protesters eventually returned to their homes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.firatnews.com/english/index.php?rupel=article&amp;nuceID=2047|agency=Firat News Agency|date=26 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Hakkâri to protest today against detentions}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=election-cannot-take-place-under-current-circumstances-says-bdp-2011-04-26|agency=Hurriyet Daily News|date=26 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Election impossible in current situation, says Turkey's pro-Kurdish party|first=Goksel|last=Bozkurt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====26 April====
On 26 April, about 20,000 in southeast Turkey reportedly turned out to protest the detention of alleged PKK supporters in Hakkâri, according to media. About 10,000 protesters set off on a march from Hakkâri to Van, according to Kurdish officials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bianet&quot;/&gt;

Police detained 17 in [[Manisa]]'s Kurdish quarter and tore down BDP-backed &quot;democratic solution&quot; tents and protest camps in [[Tunceli]], Manisa, İzmir, Mardin, and Şırnak. Authorities said they were searching for Molotov cocktails and took down tents where they purportedly found the makeshift firebombs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.hurriyetdailynews.com/n.php?n=kurdish-politicians8217-trial-at-southeastern-turkey-tied-up-in-gordian-knot-2011-04-27|agency=Hurriyet Daily News|date=27 April 2011|accessdate=29 April 2011|title=Defense lawyers boycott KCK trial in Turkey|first=Özgur|last=Ögret}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====27 April====
On 27 April, demonstrators hurled Molotov cocktails at riot police located near Aksaray metro station, which prompted the police to use tear gas to disperse the protesters. The demonstrators were mostly dispersed, although a small group remained in Aksaray, broadcaster NTV reported.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

====29 April====
[[Abdullah Öcalan]], the jailed PKK leader, called for a violent rebellion against the Turkish government on 29 April at a meeting with his lawyers, Turkish daily ''[[Vatan]]'' reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.tert.am/en/news/2011/04/30/ocalan/|agency=Tert.am|date=30 April 2011|accessdate=1 May 2011|title=Ocalan calls on Kurds to rebel against Turkish government}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====30 April====
Turkish police conducted raids on 30 April in Batman, İstanbul, and Mardin, among other districts, and arrested 70 &quot;agitators&quot; authorities said were trained by the PKK to organize demonstrations and exploit chaos created by Kurdish protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.upi.com/Top_News/World-News/2011/05/01/Turkish-police-detain-70-political-agitators/UPI-21071304264921/|agency=UPI|date=1 May 2011|accessdate=2 May 2011|title=Turkish police detain 70 political agitators}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Muş, Prime Minister Erdoğan said, &quot;There is no longer a Kurdish question in this country.&quot; He said Turkey only has to address the needs of individual Kurds as ordinary citizens of the republic. He called Kurds and [[Turkish people|Turks]] &quot;brothers&quot; and attacked both the PKK and the BDP, saying, &quot;We can’t get anywhere with those who try to set one brother against another. We can’t get anywhere with those who are trying to divide this country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.todayszaman.com/news-242523-turkey-no-longer-has-kurdish-issue-says-pm-erdogan.html|agency=Zaman|date=1 May 2011|accessdate=2 May 2011|title=Turkey no longer has Kurdish issue, says PM Erdoğan}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===May===
====1 May====
Kurds had a presence at the peaceful [[May Day]] demonstrations on 1 May in [[İstanbul]]'s [[Taksim Square]] and elsewhere throughout Turkey, along with several other minority and advocacy groups. Several speakers called upon authorities to release jailed journalists, [[Member of Parliament|MPs]], and city officials, including those arrested in [[Turkish Kurdistan]] during the previous months' protests, eliciting applause from the crowds in Taksim Square.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bianet.org/english/freedom-of-expression/129693-peaceful-protests-on-labour-day|agency=Bianet|date=2 May 2011|accessdate=4 May 2011|title=Peaceful Protests on Labour Day}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====4 May====
Thousands of Kurds in [[Diyarbakır]] turned out on 4 May for the funeral of alleged [[Kurdistan Workers' Party]] fighters killed the previous week as part of the [[Turkey – Kurdistan Workers' Party conflict]], [[Reuters]] reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.fox59.com/news/nationworld/sns-rt-international-us-tutre7435ks-20110504,0,915149.story|agency=FOX 59 WXIN|date=4 May 2011|accessdate=5 May 2011|title=Gunmen attack Turk police after PM's rally; one dead|first=Ece|last=Toksabay}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====16 May====
On May 15, Turkish military forces killed twelve [[PKK]] rebels who were crossing from northern Iraq ([[Kurdistan Regional Government]]) into Turkey, while losing one of their own soldiers to an exploding mine.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/05/14/us-turkey-kurd-idUSTRE74D0Z620110514 | work=Reuters | title=Turkish forces kill 12 Kurd fighters crossing from Iraq | date=14 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, thousands of protesters turned out in [[Diyarbakir]], and several hundred staged sit-ins and various other protests in [[Istanbul]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5jCLC9SnZiNjH-3VimQ2TyD4d5SPg?docId=6872304&lt;/ref&gt; Around 100 people, some allegedly from the pro-Kurdish [[Peace and Democracy Party]] contesting the upcoming Turkish elections, crossed the border to retrieve two bodies who were left at the site of the ambush. Demonstrations in [[Diyarbakir]] turned violent.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gulf-times.com/site/topics/article.asp?cu_no=2&amp;item_no=435106&amp;version=1&amp;template_id=39&amp;parent_id=21&lt;/ref&gt;

===June===
====26 June====
Pro-Kurdish protesters turned out in [[Istanbul]], marching to a major mosque to protest a ruling by the Turkish board of elections disqualifying [[Hatip Dicle]] of BDP from his seat in Parliament. Several candidates elected on the BDP slate were stripped of office over the weekend, some of them because the board determined that they could not hold office while imprisoned. Protesters claim the removed MPs are [[political prisoner]]s and that Turkish authorities are denying Kurds their elected representation. The ruling AK Party picked up several additional seats in Parliament due to the disqualifications, compounding Kurdish anger. Riot police assembled in Istanbul to block the protest march, firing tear gas. [[Al Jazeera]] reported that only after the tear gas was deployed did protesters become violent, assaulting officers with stones and metal poles, but police succeeded in dispersing the demonstration. No serious injuries were reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2011/06/2011626214739144330.html|agency=Al Jazeera English|date=27 June 2011|accessdate=27 June 2011|title=Turkey police disperse pro-Kurdish protesters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===July===
{{Expand section|date=August 2011}}

=== August ===
Another protest took place on Hakkâri after army's bombing of PKK camps in Qandil mountains, and a member of BDP who was protesting the air assault, was killed by police. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.todayszaman.com/news-255338-bdp-politician-dies-in-clash-with-gendarmerie.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==International reaction==
In April, members of the Kurdish diaspora in [[London]] staged a week-long protest camp and marched through [[London Borough of Haringey|Haringey]] to show solidarity with Kurds from Turkey.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Haringey Independent|url=http://www.haringeyindependent.co.uk/news/topstories/8977690.Kurdish_protesters_camp_outside_Finsbury_Park/|date=15 April 2011|accessdate=27 April 2011|title=Kurdish protest in Haringey calls for 'basic rights' in Turkey|first=Tristan|last=Kirk}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Anti-PKK Protests ==
====17 July====
Several hundred Turks marched in Istanbul to protest the killing of 13 Turkish soldiers in [[Diyarbakir]] by [[Kurdistan Workers' Party|PKK]] militants. Riot police endeavored to keep protesters away from an ethnically Kurdish neighborhood, fearing clashes might erupt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/europe/07/17/turkey.protest/index.html?iref=allsearch|agency=CNN|date=17 July 2011|accessdate=18 July 2011|title=Turks march in protest of Kurdish rebel group}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of modern conflicts in the Middle East]]
*[[2010-2011 Middle East and North Africa protests]]
*[[Democracy in the Middle East]]
*[[Democratic Initiative]]
*[[Kurdistan]]
*[[Kurds in Turkey]]
*[[Kurdish people]]

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

==Notes==
* &quot;Kurdistan-Turkey&quot;. Global Security.org.
* Dixon, Norm. &quot;US/NATO Hypocrisy Exposed as Turkey Attacks Kurds&quot;. New Youth. April 21, 1999.
* Barsoumian,Nanore.&quot;Nobel Laureate Fined for Mentioning Armenian, Kurdish Deaths&quot;.The Armenian Weekly.March 28, 2011.
* Toprak, Ergulen.&quot;Kurdish Civil Rebellion Continues in Turkey&quot;.AK News.March 27, 2011.
* &quot;Kurdish Civil Disobedience Campaign has begun in Turkey&quot;.KurdNet.March 24, 2011.
* &quot;Thousands of people gathered to Ocalan's birthplace&quot;.Zimbio.April 4, 2011.
* &quot;Facebook may be next victim of Turkey's Internet bans&quot;.Hurriyet Daily News.October 7, 2010.
* Sandrin, Paula. &quot;Unrest in the Middle East, the Turkish Response and the Turkish Model&quot;.Center for Strategic Research and Analysis. March 17, 2011.
* &quot;Protest at Turkish Consulate Exposes Ankara's Inhumanity to Children&quot; United Human Rights Council.March 25, 2010.

{{Arab Spring}}
{{World protests in 21st century}}

[[Category:2011 in Turkey]]
[[Category:Kurdish protests in Turkey]]
[[Category:2011 Kurdish protests|Turkey]]
[[Category:Impact of the Arab Spring]]
[[Category:2011 protests|Kurdish protests in Turkey]]

[[es:Protestas kurdas en Turquía de 2011]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
