<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31521053" ns="0" title="Dr. Seuss bibliography"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">Theodor Seuss Geisel, better known as '''[[Dr. Seuss]]''', published over 60 children's books over the course of his long career. Though most were published under his well-known pseudonym, Dr. Seuss, he also authored over a dozen books as '''Theo. LeSieg''' and one as '''Rosetta Stone'''. As one of the most popular children's authors of all time, Geisel's books have topped many bestseller lists, sold over 222 million copies, and been translated into more than 15 languages.&lt;ref name=&quot;seussville&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.seussville.com/lb/bio.html |title=Seussville: Biography |accessdate=2008-08-11 |publisher=Dr. Seuss Enterprises, L.P.}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, when ''Publishers Weekly'' compiled their list of the [[best selling books|best-selling children's books]] of all time; 16 of the top 100 hardcover books were written by Geisel, including ''[[Green Eggs and Ham]]'', at number 4, ''[[The Cat in the Hat]]'', at number 9, and ''[[One Fish Two Fish Red Fish Blue Fish]]'', at number 13, and ''[[Dr. Seuss's ABC]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://reg.publishersweekly.com/pw/print/20011217/28595-all-time-bestselling-children-s-books-.html |title= All-Time Bestselling Children's Books |accessdate=2008-04-23 |author=Debbie Hochman Turvey |date=2001-12-17 |work= |publisher=[[Publishers Weekly]]}} &lt;!-- Originally at http://www.publishersweekly.com/article/CA186995.html --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; In the years following his death in 1991, several additional books based on his sketches and notes were published, including ''[[Hooray for Diffendoofer Day!]]'' and ''[[Daisy-Head Mayzie]]''. Although they were all published under the name Dr. Seuss, only ''[[My Many Colored Days]]'', originally written in 1973, was entirely by Geisel.

{{TOClimit|limit=3}}

==Dr. Seuss books==
The bulk of Theodor Seuss Geisel's books were published under the name of Dr. Seuss.  Except for ''Great Day for Up!'', these books were illustrated and written by Geisel.
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;font-size:97%; text-align:center;&quot;
|-
!Title
!Synopsis
!Notes
!Original publication year
|-
|''[[And to Think That I Saw It on Mulberry Street]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Marco watches the sight and sounds of people and vehicles traveling along Mulberry Street and dreams up an elaborate story to tell to his father at the end of his walk.
|
|1937
|-
|''[[The 500 Hats of Bartholomew Cubbins]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|In the kingdom of Didd, King Derwin is riding through a street past Bartholomew Cubbins, a poor boy in the market. Bartholomew removes his hat, according to the laws, but another hat mysteriously appears; when he attempts to remove this one too, another one appears again, and this continues, even as he removes more and more hats, each growing in extravagance and beauty.
|
|1938
|-
|''[[The King's Stilts]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The story of King Bertram of Binn, who dedicates himself to safeguarding his kingdom, which has a precarious existence. It is surrounded by water, which is held back from flooding the land by a ring of dike trees, which are in turn subject to attack from flocks of nizzards. To protect the kingdom, a legion of Patrol Cats is organized to keep the nizzards at bay, and King Bertram sees to their care personally.
|
|1939
|-
|''[[The Seven Lady Godivas]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The seven Lady Godivas each learn a moral while taking care of a horse.
|
|1939
|-
|''[[Horton Hatches the Egg]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|An [[elephant]] named [[Horton the Elephant|Horton]] is convinced by an irresponsible bird named Mayzie to sit on her egg while she takes a short break, which proves to last for months.
|
|1940
|-
|''[[McElligot's Pool]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A boy named Marco is ridiculed for [[fishing]] in a small, polluted pool, and tries to justify himself by imagining the fish he ''might'' catch.  It is one of the few books by Geisel to utilize paintings as the medium for its illustrations, rather than his common use of pen and ink.
|'''[[Caldecott Honor Book]]'''

|1947
|-
|''[[Thidwick the Big-Hearted Moose]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Thidwick, a moose who lives in a herd &quot;about sixty or more&quot; , accepts a bug living on his antlers for free, who tells a spider of the free housing, and both accept a &quot;Zinn-a-zu&quot; bird, and this leads to a whole host of freeloaders taking up residence.
|
|1948
|-
|''[[Bartholomew and the Oobleck]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Bartholomew must rescue his kingdom from a sticky substance called oobleck. A sequel to ''The 500 Hats of Bartholomew Cubbins''.
|'''[[Caldecott Honor Book]]'''
|1949
|-
|''[[If I Ran the Zoo]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;| Gerald McGrew visits a zoo and finds that the animals are &quot;not good enough&quot; and describes how he would run the zoo. He would let all of the current animals free and find new, more bizarre and exotic ones.
|'''[[Caldecott Honor Book]]'''
|1950
|-
|''[[Scrambled Eggs Super!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A young boy named Peter T. Hooper spins a tale of an incredible meal he created by harvesting the eggs of fantastically exotic birds.
|
|1953
|-
|''[[Horton Hears a Who!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|[[Horton the Elephant]] of the Jungle of Nool hears a small speck of dust talking to him. The speck of dust is actually a tiny planet, home to a city called Who-ville, inhabited by microscopic-sized inhabitants known as Whos and led by a character known as the Mayor.
|Also a [[Horton Hears a Who! (film)|feature length CGI film]].
|1954
|-
|''[[On Beyond Zebra!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;| The young narrator, not content with the confines of the ordinary alphabet, invents additional letters beyond Z, with a fantastic creature corresponding to each new letter.
|
|1955
|-
|''[[If I Ran the Circus]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Behind Mr. Sneelock's ramshackle store, there's an empty lot. Little Morris McGurk is convinced that if he could just clear out the rusty cans, the dead tree, and the old cars, nothing would prevent him from using the lot for the amazing, world-beating, Circus McGurkus.
|
|1956
|-
|''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The Grinch, a bitter, cave-dwelling, cat-like creature tries to steal everything related to Christmas by impersonating Santa Claus. Eventually he realizes he has a heart for Christmas after all.
|Also a [[How the Grinch Stole Christmas (film)|feature length film]]
|1957
|-
|''[[The Cat in the Hat]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The Cat in the Hat brings his companions, Thing One and Thing Two, to a household of two young children one rainy day. Exotic and exuberant forms of chaos ensue while the children wonder how they are going to explain what happens to their mother.
|Also a [[The Cat in the Hat (film)|feature length film]]
|1957
|-
|''[[The Cat in the Hat|The Cat in the Hat Comes Back]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The Cat in the Hat returns and while he leaves Thing One and Thing Two at home, he does bring along Little Cat A nested inside his hat. Little Cat A doffs his hat to reveal Little Cat B, who in turn reveals C, and so on down to the microscopic Little Cat Z. Together they try to get rid of a pink ring that has spread from the bathtub to the dress, to the wall, into some shoes, and finally out onto the snow where they have to work really hard to get rid of it.
|
|1958
|-
|''[[Yertle the Turtle and Other Stories]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Consists of three stories:
*''Yertle the Turtle'': Unsatisfied with the stone that serves as his [[throne]], the king turtle commands the other turtles to stack themselves beneath him so that he can see further and expand his kingdom.
*''Gertrude McFuzz''- The &quot;girl-bird&quot; Gertrude McFuzz, has a small, plain tail and envies Lolla-Lee-Lou, who has two tail [[feather]]s.
*''The Big Brag''- A rabbit and a bear, both boast that they are the &quot;best of the beasts&quot;, because of the range of their hearing and smelling abilities, respectively.
|
|1958
|-
|''[[Happy Birthday to You!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Deals with a fantastic land, called Katroo, where the Birthday Bird throws everyone an amazing party on their special day.
|
|1959
|-
|''[[One Fish Two Fish Red Fish Blue Fish]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A simple rhyming book for learner readers, that has a freewheeling plot about a boy and a girl, and the many amazing creatures they have for friends and pets.
|
|1960
|-
|''[[Green Eggs and Ham]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Sam consistently badgers an unnamed character to try green eggs and ham. The unnamed character refuses to taste the dish, insisting that he would not like it.
|
|1960
|-
|''[[The Sneetches and Other Stories]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Consists of four stories:
*''[[The Sneetches]]'': Because the star-bellied sneetches are being prejudicial to the plain-bellied Sneetches, a &quot;fix-it-up chappie&quot; named Sylvester McMonkey McBean appears and offers the Sneetches without stars a chance to have them by going through his Star-On Machine.
*''[[The Zax]]'': A North-going Zax and a South-going Zax meet face to face in the Prairie of Prax. They refuse to move out of the way for one another and end up staying there. Teaches the value of compromise.
*''[[Too Many Daves]]'': A mother, Mrs. McCave, who named all 23 of her sons Dave and has trouble telling them apart.
*''What Was I Scared Of?'': The tale of a character who repeatedly meets up with an empty pair of pale-green pants and has to learn to accept them.
|
|1961
|-
|''[[Dr. Seuss's Sleep Book]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A small bug yawn spreads contagiously and though various creatures, including the Foona Lagoona Baboona, the Collaspable Frink, the Chippendale Mupp, The Oft, and the Krandles.
|
|1962
|-
|''[[Dr. Seuss's ABC]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|An [[alphabet book]] which features from the Aunt Annie's Alligator to the Zizzer-Zazzer-Zuzz all of the many strange funniest creatures.
|A [[Dr._Seuss%27s_ABC#Film|feature length CGI film]] based on the book is planned for 2013
|1963
|-
|''[[Hop on Pop]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|''Hop on Pop'' provides very simple rhymes to help beginner reading, such as a character named Pat who sits on a hat, a cat and a bat but must not sit on ''that'' which happens to be a cactus. Shows a variety of characters and teaches kids sentence composition.
|
|1963
|-
|''[[Fox in Socks]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Fox and his partner Mr. Knox converse almost entirely in densely rhyming tongue-twisters, which gets on Mr Knox's nerves.
|
|1965
|-
|''[[I Had Trouble in Getting to Solla Sollew]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A tale of a young person who discovers the &quot;troubles&quot; of life and wishes to escape them.
|
|1965
|-
|''The Cat in the Hat Song Book''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A book exploring a wide variety of Dr. Seuss songs.
|Music by [[Eugene Poddany]]
|1967
|-
|''[[The Foot Book]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Introduces many different creatures, with very different feet.
|
|1968
|-
|''[[I Can Lick 30 Tigers Today! and Other Stories]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The title story concerns a boy who brags that he can fight 30 tigers and win.  He makes excuse after excuse, finally disqualifying all the tigers until he must fight no tigers at all. The illustrations are notable for their use of gouache and brush strokes rather than the usual pen and ink.  Others stories include ''King Looie Katz'', another warning against hierarchical society advocating self-reliance, and ''The Glunk That Got Thunk'' about the power of run-away imagination.
|
|1969
|-
|''My Book about ME''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|This book is deliberately incomplete: There are blanks on every page where the reader is meant to fill in answers specific to him or her.
|
|1970
|-
|''I Can Draw It Myself''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A coloring book featuring rhyming instructions to help children complete various pictures, culminating in a challenge to the child to draw his or her own &quot;Big Something&quot;. The full title of the book is ''I Can Draw It Myself by Me, Myself''.
|
|1970
|-
|''Mr. Brown Can Moo! Can You?: Dr. Seuss's Book of Wonderful Noises!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The book shows the sounds &quot;Mr. Brown&quot; can make, such as a cow's &quot;moo&quot;, a frying pan's &quot;sizzle&quot;, and a hippo's &quot;grum&quot;. It was written so children would be able to learn about [[onomatopoeia]] and the sounds that they hear every day.
|
|1970
|-
|''[[The Lorax]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|''The Lorax'' chronicles the plight of the [[Natural environment|environment]] and the Lorax (a mossy, bossy man-like creature resembling an [[emperor tamarin]]), who speaks for the trees against the greedy Once-ler.
|A [[The_Lorax#Film|feature length CGI film]] based on the book is planned for 2012
|1971
|-
|''[[Marvin K. Mooney Will You Please Go Now!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Marvin K. Mooney is asked to leave in many ways.
|
|1972
|-
|''Did I Ever Tell You How Lucky You Are?''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Discusses an amusing litany of terrible predicaments which could befall a person, with the repeated admonishment that &quot;you're really quite lucky&quot;.
|
|1973
|-
|''The Shape of Me and Other Stuff''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Explores the adventures of two kids and their journey to learn about all the shapes and sizes that make up our world.
|
|1973
|-
|''There's a Wocket in My Pocket!''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A little boy talks about what strange creatures live in his house, such as the Yeps on the steps, the Nooth Grush on his toothbrush, the Yottle in the bottle and the Jertain in the curtain.
|
|1974
|-
|''Great Day for Up!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Every new day starts a new adventure.
|Illustrated by [[Quentin Blake]]
|1974
|-
|''Oh, the Thinks You Can Think!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|About the many amazing 'thinks' one can think and the endless possibilities and dreams that imagination can create.
|
|1975
|-
|''The Cat's Quizzer''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The Cat in the Hat asks many, sometimes ridiculous, questions of the reader.
|
|1976
|-
|''I Can Read with My Eyes Shut!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The Cat in the Hat shows a Young Cat the fun he can get out of reading. Also shows that reading is a useful tool to acquire knowledge.
|
|1978
|-
|''Oh Say Can You Say?''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A collection of 25 tongue-twisters such as &quot;Oh my brothers! Oh my sisters! These are Terrible Tongue Twisters!&quot;
|
|1979
|-
|''Hunches in Bunches''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A boy is approached by numerous strange creatures with enormous gloved hats on their heads. Each &quot;hunch&quot; points out a different possible course of action with some even contradicting themselves.
|
|1982
|-
|''[[The Butter Battle Book]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The conflict between the Yooks and the Zooks over which side of bread to spread butter on leads to an [[arms race]], each competing to make bigger and nastier weapons to outdo the other, which results in the threat of [[mutual assured destruction]].
|
|1984
|-
|''[[You're Only Old Once!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;| An old man journeys through a clinic and sees its inefficiency.
|
|1986
|-
|''I Am NOT Going to Get Up Today!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A lazy boy decides to stay in bed despite media coverage and the arrival of the U.S. Marines.
|
|1987
|-
|''The Tough Coughs as He Ploughs the Dough''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A collection of Dr. Seuss' early writings and cartoons, edited by Richard Marschall.
|
|1987
|-
|''[[Oh, the Places You'll Go!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;| The last book published before Dr. Seuss' death, about life and its challenges.
|
|1990
|}

==Posthumous==
Geisel also wrote four books that were posthumously published under his most recognizable pen name, Dr. Seuss.
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;font-size:97%; text-align:center;&quot;
|-
!Title
!Synopsis
!Notes
!Original publication year
|-
|-
|''[[Daisy-Head Mayzie]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The book is about a schoolgirl named Mayzie who one day suddenly sprouts a bright yellow daisy from her head. This makes her famous and she starts to miss her normal life.
|Not illustrated by Geisel
|1995
|-
|''[[My Many Colored Days]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A rhyming story, which describes each day in terms of a particular color which is in turn associated with a specific emotion.
|Paintings by [[Steve Johnson (illustrator)|Steve Johnson]] and Lou Fancher
|1996
|-
|''[[Hooray for Diffendoofer Day!]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The story surrounds a school that is well liked by its students notably because of its many eccentric teachers.
|Expanded and completed by [[Jack Prelutsky]] and illustrated by [[Lane Smith]]
|1998
|-
|''[[The Bippolo Seed and Other Lost Stories]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|This book collects seven stories published in ''[[Redbook]]'' from 1948 to 1959: &quot;The Bippolo Seed&quot;; &quot;The Rabbit, The Bear, and the Zinniga-Zanniga&quot;; &quot;Gustav, the Goldfish&quot;; &quot;Tadd and Todd&quot;; &quot;Steak for Supper&quot;; &quot;The Strange Shirt Spot&quot;; and &quot;The Great Henry McBride.&quot;
|Introduction by Charles D. Cohen
|2011
|}

==Theo. LeSieg and Rosetta Stone==
Geisel also authored several books under the [[pen name]] Theo. LeSieg, and one book under the name Rosetta Stone.  These books were written but not illustrated by Geisel.

{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;font-size:97%; text-align:center;&quot;
|-
!Title
!Synopsis
!Illustrator
!Original publication year
|-
|''Ten Apples Up on Top!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Three animals, a lion, a dog, and a tiger, who consistently pile apples on their heads for fun.
|[[Roy McKie]]
|1961
|-
|''[[I Wish That I Had Duck Feet]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A boy wishes that he could have many different animal and mechanical body parts, finding fantastic uses for each.
|B Tobey
|1965
|-
|''[[Come over to My House]]''
|align=&quot;left&quot;|The illustrations of this book portray the various styles of homes that kids from around the world.
|Richard Erdoes&lt;br/&gt;(illustrated to [[Michael K. Frith]])
|1966
|-
|''The Eye Book''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
|[[Roy McKie]]&lt;br/&gt;Joe Mathieu&lt;!--Book was re-issued in 1999 with new illustrations--&gt;
|1968&lt;br/&gt;1999
|-
|''I Can Write''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
|[[Roy McKie]]
|1971
|-
|''In a People House''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A mouse shows a bird all the amazing things one can find in the everyday home.
|[[Roy McKie]]
|1972
|-
|''Wacky Wednesday''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects to Beginners books. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Shows the adventures of a kid and how he learns to cope with an abnormal day.
|George Booth
|1974
|-
|''The Many Mice of Mr. Brice'' a.k.a. ''The Pop-Up Mice of Mr. Brice''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=left&quot;|
|[[Roy McKie]]
|1974
|-
|''Would You Rather Be a Bullfrog?''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
|[[Roy McKie]]
|1975
|-
|''Hooper Humperdink...? Not Him!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|A certain kid (the narrator) invites all his friends- whose names begin with all 26 letters of the alphabet- to a party at his house, except for Hooper Humperdink, but changes his mind as soon as the others are already having fun.
|Charles E. Martin&lt;br/&gt;Scout Nash
|1976&lt;br/&gt;2006
|-
|''Please Try to Remember the First of Octember!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|
|Art Cummings
|1977
|-
|''Maybe You Should Fly a Jet! Maybe You Should Be a Vet!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Exposes the reader to many different types of careers.
|Michael J. Smollin
|1980
|-
|''The Tooth Book''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align=&quot;left&quot;|Shows people and animals that have teeth, and ones that do not. Explains that you only get two sets of teeth, and briefly how to care for them.
|[[Roy McKie]]&lt;br&gt;Joe Mathieu&lt;!--Book was re-issued in 2000 with new illustrations--&gt;
|1981&lt;br&gt;2000
|-
|''Because a Little Bug Went Ka-Choo!!''&lt;!-- Do not wikilink. Link redirects here. --&gt;
|align= &quot;left&quot;| A bug sneezes, which sets off a series of larger and larger consequences, in the end nearly sending a whole town into chaos. Geisel wrote this book under the pen name Rosetta Stone.
|[[Michael K. Frith]]
|1975
|}

==Film==
While Geisel was most famous for his literary works, he helped write several propaganda films as well as a feature-length film.  Many of his literary works have been also been adapted for the television and as feature-length films.

*''[[Your Job in Germany]]'', (1945)
*''[[Our Job in Japan]]''
*''[[Private Snafu]]''
*''[[Design for Death]]'' (1947), ([[Academy Award for Documentary Feature]])&lt;ref name=Morgan&gt;{{cite book|last=Morgan |first=Judith |coauthors=Morgan, Neil |title=Dr. Seuss &amp; Mr. Geisel |publisher=Random House |year=1995 |isbn=0679416862 |pages=119–120}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''[[Gerald McBoing-Boing]]'' (1950),  ([[Academy Award for Animated Short Film#1950s|Academy Award for Animated Short Film]])
*''[[The 5,000 Fingers of Dr. T]]'' (1953) a feature length film
*''[[Dr. Seuss's ABC]]'' (1963) a feature full-length animated film

===Feature film adaptations===
*''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas (film)|How the Grinch Stole Christmas]]'' (2000)
*''[[The Cat in the Hat (film)|The Cat in the Hat]]'' (2003)
*''[[Horton Hears a Who! (film)|Horton Hears a Who!]]'' (2008)
*''[[The Lorax (film)|The Lorax]]'' (2012)
*''[[Dr. Seuss's ABC (film)|Dr. Seuss's ABC]]'' (2013)
*''[[Hop on Pop (film)|Hop on Pop]]'' (2015)
*''[[The Cat in the Hat Comes Back (film)|The Cat in the Hat Comes Back]]'' (2020)

==Animation==
A series of cartoon adaptations were made of Geisel's stories, beginning in 1942.

===Television adaptations===
#''[[Horton Hatches the Egg]]'' (1942) - originally released theatrically
#''[[The Cat's Tales|The Cat in the Hat's Tales]]'' (1957-present)
#''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas! (TV special)|How the Grinch Stole Christmas!]]'' (1966)
#''[[Horton Hears a Who! (TV special)|Horton Hears a Who!]]'' (1970)
#''[[The Cat in the Hat (TV special)|The Cat in the Hat]]'' (1971)
#''[[The Lorax (TV special)|The Lorax]]'' (1972)
#''[[Dr. Seuss on the Loose]]'' (1973) - ''[[The Sneetches and Other Stories|The Sneetches]]'', ''[[The Sneetches and Other Stories|The Zax]]'', and ''[[Green Eggs and Ham]]''
#''[[The Hoober-Bloob Highway]]'' (1975)
#''[[Halloween Is Grinch Night]]'' (1977)
#''[[Pontoffel Pock, Where Are You?]]'' (1980)
#''[[The Grinch Grinches the Cat in the Hat]]'' (1982)
#''[[The Butter Battle Book]]'' (1989)
#''[[In Search of Dr. Seuss]]'' (1994)
#''[[Daisy-Head Mayzie]]'' (1995)
#''Because a Little Bug Went Ka-Choo!'' (2001)
#''[[My Many Colored Days]]'' (1996) 
#''[[The Wubbulous World of Dr. Seuss]]'' (1996–1997)
#''[[Gerald McBoing-Boing (TV series)|Gerald McBoing-Boing]]'' (2005–2007)
#''[[The Cat in the Hat Knows a Lot About That!]]'' (2010–present)

===List of Dr. Seuss Beginner Book videos===
#''[[Dr. Seuss's ABC]]'' plus ''I Can Read with My Eyes Shut!'' and ''Mr. Brown Can Moo! Can You?''
#''[[One Fish Two Fish Red Fish Blue Fish]]'' plus ''Oh, the Thinks You Can Think!'' and ''[[The Foot Book]]''
#''[[The Cat in the Hat Comes Back]]'' plus ''[[Fox in Socks]]'' and ''[[There's a Wocket in My Pocket!]]''
#''I Am NOT Going to Get Up Today!'' plus ''The Shape of Me and Other Stuff'', ''Great Day for Up'' and ''In a People House''
#''[[The Cat in the Hat]]'' plus ''Maybe You Should Fly a Jet! Maybe You Should Be a Vet!''
#''[[Green Eggs and Ham]]'' plus ''The Tooth Book'' and ''[[Ten Apples Up On Top!]]''
#''[[I Wish that I had Duck Feet]]'' plus ''[[Wacky Wednsday]]'' and ''[[The Ear Book]]''

===List of Dr. Seuss Video Classics===
*''[[Horton Hatches the Egg]]'' narrated by [[Billy Crystal]] plus ''[[If I Ran the Circus]]''
*''[[Yertle the Turtle and Other Stories]]'' narrated by [[John Lithgow]]
*''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas!]]'' narrated by [[Walter Matthau]] plus ''[[If I Ran the Zoo]]''
*''[[Horton Hears a Who!]]'' narrated by [[Dustin Hoffman]] plus ''[[Thidwick the Big-Hearted Moose]]''
*''[[Did I Ever Tell You How Lucky You Are?]]'' narrated by [[John Cleese]] plus ''Scrambled Eggs Super!''
*''[[Dr. Seuss's Sleep Book]]'' narrated by [[Madeline Kahn]] plus ''Hunches in Bunches''

==External links==
*University of California San Diego's register of the materials in their Dr Seuss collection, detailing many of his works not published in (separate) books. [http://orpheus.ucsd.edu/speccoll/testing/html/mss0230a.html]
*A (possibly incomplete) list of illustrated short stories Seuss published in [[Redbook Magazine]] in the 1950s. [http://1stedition.net/blog/2006/06/dr_seuss_redbook_magazine_orig.html]
*{{Worldcat id|lccn-n79-53201|Dr. Seuss}}

==References==
{{reflist|1}}

{{Dr. Seuss}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Seuss Dr Bibliography}}
[[Category:Books by Dr. Seuss| ]]
[[Category:Bibliographies by author]]
[[Category:Bibliographies of American authors]]
[[Category:Children's literature bibliographies]]
[[Category:Poetry bibliographies]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
