<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3154365" ns="0" title="Syracuse University College of Law"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Law School
 | image          = [[Image:SU Seal.jpg|150px|Syracuse University College of Law]]
 | name           = Syracuse University College of Law
 | established    = 1895
 | type           = [[Private school|Private]]
 | parent endowment = $985 million
 | head           = Hannah R. Arterian
 | city           = [[Syracuse, New York|Syracuse]] 
 | state          = [[New York]] 
 | country        = [[United States|US]]
 | students       = 658&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.syr.edu/admissions-and-financial-aid/fast-facts.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;
 | faculty        = 60&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.syr.edu/admissions-and-financial-aid/fast-facts.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;
 | ranking        = 100&lt;ref&gt;[http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/rankings/page+4]&lt;/ref&gt;
 | bar pass rate  = 83.3%&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsandinsight.thomsonreuters.com/Legal/News/2011/11_-_November/More_than_half_of_NY_law_schools_increase_bar_passage_rate/&lt;/ref&gt;
 | annual tuition = $44,000&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.law.syr.edu/admissions-and-financial-aid/fast-facts.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;
 | homepage       = [http://www.law.syr.edu www.law.syr.edu]
 | aba profile    = [http://officialguide.lsac.org/SearchResults/SchoolPage_PDFs/LSAC_LawSchoolDescription/LSAC2823.pdf Syracuse University College of Law Profile]
}}

'''Syracuse University College of Law''' ('''SUCOL'''), founded in 1895, is a [[Juris Doctor]] degree-granting [[law school]] of [[Syracuse University]] in [[Syracuse, New York]]. It is one of only four law schools in [[Upstate New York]] (the other three being [[Albany Law School|Albany]], [[University at Buffalo Law School|Buffalo]], and [[Cornell Law School|Cornell]]. Syracuse was accredited by the [[American Bar Association]] in 1923 and is a charter member of the [[Association of American Law Schools]]. As of the 2011-2012 academic year, 658 students were enrolled in the College of Law.

Syracuse is an emerging leader in the relatively novel field of National Security Law through the [[ Institute_for_National_Security_and_Counterterrorism | Institute for National Security and Counterterrorism]].  The College of Law is also home to the New York State Science &amp; Technology Law Center. It also maintains a chapter of the [[Order of the Coif]], of which only 80 of the more than 190 ABA accredited law schools are a member.

The College of Law offers joint degree programs with, among others, the top-ranked [[Maxwell School of Citizenship and Public Affairs]], the highly-regarded [[S.I. Newhouse School of Public Communications]], the [[Martin J. Whitman School of Management]], and the [[State University of New York College of Environmental Science and Forestry]]. It offers a special first year writing program in [[international law]] and summer internship study abroad programs in [[London]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://law.syr.edu/academics/academic-programs/law-in-london-summer-program.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt;.. Students may also qualify for specialized certifications in areas of study like [[Commercial Law|Corporate Law]], [[Estate Planning]], [[Family Law]], and [[Property Law]].

The College of Law is located on the edge of the [[University Hill, Syracuse|Syracuse University Hill neighborhood]] adjacent to the [[Carrier Dome]] in Ernest I. White and Winifred MacNaughton Halls. Its library is called the H. Douglas Barclay Law Library. The library is a congressionally designated depository for federal materials and also houses a collection of former [[Supreme Court Justice]] [[Robert H. Jackson]]'s artifacts and documents.

==Dineen Hall==

On November, 5, 2010, the University and the College of Law announced and dedicated the construction of a new law school complex, to be named Dineen Hall&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.law.syr.edu/dineen/index.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;.  Syracuse University Architecture alumnus Richard Gluckman, of the [[Gluckman Mayner Architects|Gluckman Mayner ]] architectural firm in New York City, will be the lead architect.  The complex is projected to be approximately {{convert|200,000|sqft|m2}} and will be named for the Dineen family, who provided the lead gift in a fundraising campaign the University is launching for the new building. It is the largest gift in the history of the College of Law, one of the largest gifts in University history, and an important milestone in the University's current $1 billion capital campaign, of which a new law school building has been a priority.

==Notable alumni==
The College of Law's alumni includes

===Federal Government===
[[Image:Joe Biden official portrait crop.jpg|thumb|right|Vice President [[Joe Biden]] L'68]]
* [[Joseph R. Biden, Jr.]] - [[Vice President of the United States]] and former [[U.S. Senator]] from [[Delaware]]
* [[David Crane (judge)|David Crane]] - former Chief Prosecutor for the [[Special Court for Sierra Leone]]
* [[Alfonse D'Amato]] - former [[U.S. Senator]] from [[New York]]
* [[Ann Marie Buerkle]] -  [[U.S. Representative]]  for 25th District of New York
* [[Randy Kuhl]] - former [[U.S. Representative]] from the 29th District of New York
* [[Theodore S. Weiss]] - former [[U.S. Representative]] from the 20th and 17th  District of New York
* [[Richard J. Cardamone]] - Senior Judge for the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit]]
* [[Theodore A. McKee]] - Chief Judge for the [[U.S. Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit]]
* [[James E. Graves, Jr.]] - Judge for the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit]]
* [[William Q. Hayes]] - Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Southern District of California]]
* [[Thomas Blake Kennedy]] - Senior Judge for the [[United States District Court for the District of Wyoming]]
* [[Norman A. Mordue]] - Chief Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Northern District of New York]]
* [[Neal P. McCurn]] - Senior Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Northern District of New York]]
* [[Frederick J. Scullin, Jr.]] - Senior Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Northern District of New York]]
* [[Howard G. Munson]] - Senior Judge for the [[U.S. District Court, Northern District of New York]]
* [[Edmund Port]] - Senior Judge for the [[U.S. District Court, Northern District of New York]]
* [[Robert D. Mariani]] - Judge for the [[United States District Court for the Middle District of Pennsylvania]]
* [[Mae D'Agostino]] - Judge for the [[U.S. District Court, Northern District of New York]]
* [[David N. Hurd]]- Judge for the [[U.S. District Court, Northern District of New York]]
* [[Glenn T. Suddaby]] - Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Northern District of New York]]
* [[Sandra L. Townes]] - Judge for the [[U.S. District Court]], [[Eastern District of New York]]
* [[John Pajak]] - Chief Special Trial Judge, [[United States Tax Court]]
* [[Hugh Douglas Barclay]]- former [[United States Ambassador to El Salvador]]
* [[Herman W. Nickel]] - former [[United States Ambassador to South Africa]]
*  Lisa Borin Ogden - Member, Board of Governors of the [[United Service Organizations]]

===State and Local Government===
* [[Beau Biden|Joseph R. &quot;Beau&quot; Biden III]] - [[Attorney General of Delaware|Attorney General]] of [[Delaware]]
* [[Edmund H. Lewis]] - former [[Chief Judge of the New York Court of Appeals]]
* [[Michael Nozzolio]] -  [[New York Senate|New York State Senator]]
* [[Tarky Lombardi]] - former [[New York Senate|New York State Senator]]
* [[Addie Jenne Russell]] - Assemblymember, New York State Assembly, 118th Assembly District
* [[William Magnarelli]] - Assemblymember, New York State Assembly, 120th Assembly District
* [[William Barclay]] - Assemblymember, New York State Assembly, 124th Assembly District
* [[Tom O'Mara]] - Assemblymember, New York State Assembly, 137th Assembly District
* [[Joanie Mahoney]] - Onondaga County Executive
* [[Frank M. Williams]] - [[New York State Engineer and Surveyor]]
* Carl J. Mugglin - Justice, [[New York Supreme Court, Appellate Division]], Third Department
* Joseph L. Yannotti - Judge, [[New Jersey Superior Court, Appellate Division]] 
* John Daniel Dailey - Judge, [[Colorado Court of Appeals]]
* Deborah H. Karalunas - Presiding Justice, Onondaga County Commercial Division, Supreme Court
* Robert D. Lippmann - Judge, New York County Supreme Court
* Martin Schoenfeld - Judge, New York County Supreme Court
* Gloria Dabiri - Judge, Kings County Supreme Court
* Phyllis Orlikoff Flug - Judge, Queens County Supreme Court
* Marcia P. Hirsch - Judge, Queens County Supreme Court
* Elizabeth H. Emerson - Judge, Suffolk County Supreme Court
* Alfred J. Weiner - Judge, Rockland County Supreme Court
* Elma A. Bellini - Judge, Monroe County Supreme Court
* William P. Polito - Judge, Monroe County Supreme Court
* Thomas Stander - Judge, Monroe County Supreme Court
* Brian F. DeJoseph - Judge, Onondaga County Supreme Court
* James P. Murphy - Judge, Onondaga County Supreme Court
* Thomas J. Murphy - Judge, Onondaga County Supreme Court
* Anthony J. Paris - Judge, Onondaga County Supreme Court
* William R. Roy - Judge, Onondaga County Supreme Court
* Anthony F. Shaheen - Judge, Oneida County Supreme Court
* Norman W. Seiter, Jr. - Judge, Oswego County Supreme Court
* Phillip R. Rumsey - Judge, Cortland County Supreme Court
* Michael E. Daley - Judge, Herkimer County Supreme Court
* Ruth Jakubowski - Associate Judge, Maryland State Circuit Court, 3rd Judicial Circuit
* Edward O. Burke - Judge, Arizona Superior Court, Maricopa County 
* Maria L. Dantos - Judge, Court of Common Pleas of Lehigh County 
* Karen L Townsend - District Judge, Eleventh District Court of New Mexico
&lt;!--[[Image:macnaughtonhall.jpg|thumb|right|305px|MacNaughton Hall]]--&gt;
===Private Sector===
* [[Elizabeth Strout]] - [[Pulitzer Prize]] winning author of [[Olive Kitteridge]]
* [[Jay Schadler]] - [[ABC News]] correspondent and award-winning journalist
* [[Tim Green]] - former professional athlete and [[New York Times]] best-selling author
* [[Karen DeCrow]] - former President of the [[National Organization for Women]]
* William J. Brodsky - CEO and Chairman of the [[Chicago Board Options Exchange]]
* [[Deborah F. Stanley]] - President of the [[State University of New York at Oswego]]
* Susan Yu - [[Michael Jackson]]'s defence lawyer and co-founder of Mesereau &amp; Yu, LLP of Los Angeles, California
* [[Carl Paladino]] - Chief Executive Officer of Ellicott Development Company and Republican Nominee for the [[New York gubernatorial election, 2010]].
* Joanna Geraghty - Executive Vice President and Chief People Officer, [[JetBlue Airways]]

==Notable professors==
The College of Law's faculty includes: 
* Constitutional law and national security expert - William C. Banks, Board of Advisors Distinguished Professor 
* Former Chief Prosecutor of the Special Court for Sierra Leone - [[David Crane (law)|David Crane]], Professor of Practice 
* Former [[United States Attorney for the Northern District of New York]]- Thomas J. Maroney, Professor of Law 
* Noted constitutional scholar and  historian - William M. Wiecek, Chester Adgate Congdon Professor of Public Law and Legislation
* Tort and constitutional law expert - Leslie Bender, Professor of Law 
* [[United States Holocaust Memorial Council]] member - [[Menachem Z. Rosensaft]], Distinguished Visiting Lecturer 
* Chairman of the [[Burton Blatt Institute]]- Peter Blanck, University Professor

==Advocacy skills training==
&lt;!--[[Image:macnaughtoninterior.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Interior of MacNaughton Hall]]--&gt;
The College of Law was honored with the Emil Gumpert Award for the best law school advocacy program in the United States by the American College of Trial Lawyers. The New York State Bar Association cited Syracuse as the best trial skills law school in New York State 10 times in recent years by awarding the College its coveted Tiffany Cup.

Syracuse has received the highest award that the American College of Trial Lawyers gives to law schools based on the school's trial advocacy record and the strength of the school's trial training programs. In 2002 U.S. News &amp; World Report rated the College of Law's trial advocacy program in the top 10 in the United States.

==Moot court and trial team==
Because of its extensive advocacy skills program, the College of Law has won numerous national moot court competitions. In the past 16 years, its teams have won 3 national trial championships, 15 Northeast regional first place awards, and 5 best-advocate-in-the-nation awards. Five times in the past 9 years the College of Law has been invited to the National Invitational Tournament of Champions, featuring the nation's 12 best teams. Syracuse has won other national awards in appellate, minority rights, and international tax competitions.

In March 2008, the College of Law placed in the semi-finals in the National Trial Competition in [[Austin, TX]]. In addition, the College of Law finished with the best record of New York state law schools. In April 2008, Syracuse was awarded the prestigious New York State Bar Association Tiffany Cup and a $5,000 scholarship for the college.

In the Fall of 2007, Syracuse's undefeated Tournament of Champions team placed third in the nation. The Tournament of Champions is a national invitational tournament in which the nation's 16 schools with the best two year record in the National Trial Competition and the AAJ are invited to participate. The College of Law's National Appellate Team also won the Northeast regional finals. The team went undefeated and earned the highest score in the first three rounds, then won the finals in a unanimous decision. Also in the Fall of 2007, Syracuse bested 39 teams by placing 1st in the National Trial Competition, Buffalo regional.

In 2006, a team of three students won the national championship at the second annual Sexual Orientation Moot Court Competition at the [[UCLA School of Law]].  The competition included 16 law school teams from across the country.

In the Fall of 2005, the College of Law advanced to the semifinal round in the ABA Northeast Regional Criminal Justice Trial Advocacy competition in New Haven, Connecticut.  That same year, Syracuse won the Northeast Regional round for the Thomas Tang Moot Court competition in Boston, MA, and won the Best Brief Award for the [[Sojourner Truth]] National Appelllate Competition.

In 2002 a team of four students finished second in the National Civil Trial Competition and a second year student won overall best advocate. In 2002 and 2003 the College of Law participated in the 3rd Annual [[Quinnipiac University]] School of Law's Northeast Regional Criminal Justice Trial Advocacy competition. Another event was the 12th annual Cat Bennett Criminal Trial Advocacy competition, as sponsored by the [[National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers]].

From 1998-2001, Syracuse was the first place winner in three [[Sojourner Truth]] National Appellate Competitions, and won the Best Brief Award each year. In 2000, the College of Law was the national champion in the [[Thomas Tang]] Moot Court Competition and regional champions in 2001. The Tax Team won the Oral Competition in the 2001 National Tax Moot Court Competition.

For more than 30 years, Syracuse's National Trial Team achieved the best record in Region II competition, winning 15 Regional Championships, two National Championships, one National Championship Runner-Up Award, three National Best Advocate Awards, and numerous Regional Advocacy Awards. From 1989-2001, the College of Law was invited to participate in the Tournament of Champions fall competition. The competition is only open to the 16 law schools with the best trial team records over the preceding three years. From 1983-2001, Syracuse's ATLA Trial Team won one National Championship, plus numerous regional awards.

From 1998-2001, the National Appellate team won the Region I competition with the Best Brief Award and was named a Quarter-Finalist in the 1999 National Finals. Each year, teams of first year students take part in an International Law Moot Court Competition held in [[Toronto, Canada]]. Syracuse's team won the championship in 1993.

==Rankings==
[[Image:SU Law1.jpg|thumb|right|200px|White Hall]]
The College of Law is tied for 100th, placing it right at the cutoff for the first tier, in the 2011 [[U.S. News and World Report]] Best Law Schools rankings.&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-law-schools/rankings/page+4&lt;/ref&gt;

The College of Law is ranked 64th out of 180 ABA accredited law schools in the 2010 U.S. Law School Rankings by Super Lawyers&lt;ref&gt;http://www.superlawyers.com/toplists/lawschools/united-states/2010/&lt;/ref&gt;, a [[Thomson Reuters]] company.

==Publications==
* [[Syracuse Law Review]]
* Syracuse Science &amp; Technology Law Reporter [http://sstlr.syr.edu/]
* [[Syracuse Journal of International Law and Commerce]]
* The Digest: National Italian-American Bar Association Law Journal
* The Labor Lawyer (A publication of the [[American Bar Association]])
* [[Impunity Watch]]

==In-House Clinical Programs==
* Children's Rights and Family Law Clinic
* Community Development Law Clinic
* Criminal Defense Law Clinic
* Disability Rights Clinic
* Elder Law Clinic
* Low Income Taxpayer Law Clinic
* Securities Arbritration Consumer Law Clinic

==Applied learning centers==
* [[Burton Blatt Institute]]
* Disability Law and Policy
* Family Law &amp; Social Policy
* Global Law &amp; Practice
* Indigenous Law, Governance &amp; Citizenship
* Center on Property, Citizenship, and Social Entrepreneurism (PCSE)
* Corporate Counsel
* [[Institute for National Security and Counterterrorism]]
* Syracuse University New Technology Law Center; New York State Science &amp; Technology Law Center
* The Writing Center

==Student organizations==
* The Actual Innocence Society
* The Alternative Dispute Resolution
* [[American Bar Association]]/Student Bar Association
* [[American Constitution Society]]
* The Asian-Pacific American Law Students Association
* The Black Law Students Association
* The Christian Legal Fellowship
* The Communications Law and Policy Society
* The Corporate Law Society
* The Criminal Justice Society
* The Democratic Law Caucus
* The disAbility Law Society
* The Environmental Law Society
* The Entertainment &amp; Sports Law Society
* Estate Planning Society
* The Family Law Society
* [[Federalist Society]]
* The Feminist Action League
* The Health Law Society
* The Indigenous Law Students Association
* The Intellectual Property Law Society
* The International Law Students Association
* The Irish American Law Students Association
* The Jewish Law Students Association
* [[J. Reuben Clark Law Society]]
* The Korean Law Students Association
* The Latin American Law Students Association
* The Middle Eastern Law Students Association
* The Moot Court Honor Society
* The Muslim Law Students Association
* The National Italian American Bar Association
* [[National Lawyers Guild]]
* The National Women's Law Student Association
* The Outlaw (Gay/Straight Law Student Alliance)
* [[Phi Alpha Delta]]
* The Republican Law Caucus
* The South Asian Law Students Association
* The St. Thomas More Society
* The Student Association on Terrorism and Security Analysis - Law Student Division
* The Syracuse Tax Society
* The Syracuse Public Interest Network (SPIN)
* The Toastmasters - Devil's Advocate Chapter

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.law.syr.edu/ Syracuse University College of Law]
*[http://www.syr.edu/ Syracuse University]
*[http://nys-stlc.syr.edu/ New York State Science &amp; Technology Law Center]

{{Syracuse University}}
{{Law Schools of the Mid-Atlantic States}}

{{coord missing|New York}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Syracuse University College Of Law}}
[[Category:Law schools in New York]]
[[Category:Syracuse University]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
