<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31671659" ns="0" title="Wang Shixiang"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{cleanup|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox person
| name = Wang Shixiang
| birth_date = May 25 1914
| birth_place = [[Beijing]]
| death_date = November 28 2009
| occupation = Researcher &lt;br /&gt; collector
}}
'''Wang Shixiang''' ([[Beijing]], May 25 1914 - November 28 2009) was a [[People's Republic China|Chinese]] researcher of traditional [[Chinese culture]], leading [[art collector]], [[poet]] and [[Hanzi| Hanzi-calligrapher]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/cndy/2009-12/01/content_9082060.htm |title=Art collector Wang Shixiang dead at 95|work=China Daily |date=December 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.trouw.nl/krantenarchief/2003/10/24/2171908/Wang_Shixiang.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Power of Culture 01-2004&quot;&gt;The Power of Culture (January 2004) [http://www.powerofculture.nl/en/current/2004/january/pcfprijzen.html''Craftsmanship Receives central focus in Prince Claus Prizes'']&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life==
===Youth===
Wang was born into a wealthy family. So was his father was a diplomat and his mother have been possible to study abroad. His ancestors were three generations at the court of the Chinese [[Qing Dynasty]]. Its origin is described as one of the reasons for his talent and sensitivity for the detection of elements from classical Chinese culture. From puberty to the age of about 25 years he led the life of a [[dandy]], he did not, for example to school, loved playing  [[cricket| cricket fights]] and the breeding and training [[Pigeons (birds)|pigeons]] and [[Eagle (raptor)|eagles]]. When at twenty five years his mother died, his life changed radically. He dropped the revelers life behind him and he engaged in study and writing.&lt;ref name=&quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|work=China Radio International |date=December 11, 2009|url=http://english.cri.cn/4406/2009/12/11/1701s534932.htm |title=Wang Shixiang, the Capital's Most Professional Connoisseur of Traditional Arts}}&lt;/ref&gt;

His art collection was during his life an inspiration for craftsmen and scientists worldwide. During the [[Cultural Revolution]] (1966–1976), his collection was seized by the Chinese authorities. After the revolution was given back his collection. In 2003 his collection is part of the Chinese national heritage.&lt;ref Name=&quot;PCP2003&quot;/&gt;

Throughout his life he remained an avid fan of pigeons. English works as ''Beijing Pigeon Whistles''he wrote in 1999 about his passion. When he won the [[Prince Claus Award]] in 2003 in Beijing, pigeons were released as a gesture to the winner.&lt;ref name = &quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Power of Culture 01-2004&quot; /&gt;

===Career===
Wang began his career after the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] (1937–1945). He worked at this time to the Palace Museum in the [[Forbidden City]] in Beijing and later became a member of the prestigious Central Research Institute of Culture and History.&lt;ref name=&quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot; /&gt;

Later became a researcher for the State Administration of Cultural Heritage. During the [[1980-1989|eighties]] he made regular contributions to the paper [[China Daily]]. But also through other channels, he published much about the investigation he conducted, as in dozens of books he left behind. His publications are in some cases the only available information on specific topics.&lt;ref name=&quot;Power of Culture 01-2004&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PCP2003&quot;&gt;{{en}} Prince Claus Fund (2003) jury&lt;/ref&gt;

==Work==
Wang was internationally known for his extensive study of a wide range of cultural relics, artifacts and manifestations, including furniture, Chinese lacquer art, bamboo carvings, pigeon whistles, a large number of traditional [[Crafts (crafts)|crafts]] and music. His knowledge ranges from trivial matters to [[esoteric]], from Chinese manuscripts and objects to intangible cultural affairs.&lt;ref name = &quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot; /&gt;

Altogether he published over forty books. The book''Classic Chinese Furniture: Ming and Early Qing Dynasties''is considered his most influential work. It is a meticulous, precise work that includes all of his studies he made to Chinese furniture.&lt;ref name=&quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot; /&gt;

=== Bibliography (English Selection) ===
* 1989:''Bamboo Carving of China''by Wan-go Weng, ISBN 978-0295967936
* 1990:''Connoisseurship of Chinese Furniture: Ming and Early Qing Dynasties'', by Shih-Hsiang Wang, ISBN 978-9620408199
* 1991:''Classic Chinese Furniture: Ming and Early Qing Dynasties'', ISBN 978-1878529022
* 1993:''The Charms of the Gourd'', ISBN 978-9625770048
* 1995:''Masterpieces from the Museum of Classical Furnitures'', by Shih-Hsiang Wang &amp; Curtis Evarts, ISBN 978-1883662028
* 1998:''Classical and Vernacular Chinese Furniture in the Living Environment'', Kai-Yin Lo, ISBN 978-1878529473
* 1999:''Beijing''Pigeon Whistles, ISBN 978-7538256369
* 2000:''Beyond the Screen: Chinese Furniture of the 16th and 17th''Craig Clunas &amp; Malcolm Rogers, ISBN 978-0878464340
* 2000:''Rules''Craft Qing Dynasty, Part 1 (ISBN 7534723965) and 2 (ISBN 7534723973)

== Awards ==
Wang won a 1985 award from the Chinese Ministry of Culture where he was described as one of the most distinguished individuals in the fields of culture, history and museum studies.&lt;ref name=&quot;CRI11-12-2009&quot;/&gt;

Wang received the 2003 [[Prince Claus Award]] &quot;in recognition for his meticulous research into popular culture and decorative arts of the Chinese People's Republic. Knowledge of traditions and skills to document and disseminate he contributed to the recovery of the dislocation caused by the Cultural Revolution was caused in this way for current and future generations the cultural heritage preservation and transfer. &quot; Usually the main prizes of the Prince Claus Prize awarded in the Netherlands. In 2003, Wang, however, old age, 89 years, so the awards this time by the embassy in [[Beijing]] was organized.&lt;ref name=&quot;PCP2003&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;tags {{en}} The Royal Family ( 2003) [http://archief.koninklijkhuis.nl/Actueel/Nieuwsberichten/Nieuwsarchief/2003/december/Presentatie_Prins_Claus_Prijzen_2003 Prince Claus Awards] (press release)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Literature ==
* Chen Zhou (2002)''Biography''Wang Shixiang, ISBN 7501013225

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{refimprove|date=May 2011}}

[[Category:Chinese art collectors]]

[[Category:Chinese poets]]
[[Category:Chinese scientists]]


[[nl:Wang Shixiang]]
[[zh:王世襄]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
