<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31769" ns="0" title="United Nations"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{redirect|UN}}
{{pp-semi-indef}}{{pp-move-indef}}
{{Use British (Oxford) English|date=November 2010}}
{{Infobox Geopolitical organization
|name='''United Nations'''&lt;br /&gt;'''الأمم المتحدة'''&lt;br /&gt;'''联合国'''&lt;br /&gt;'''Organisation des Nations unies'''&lt;br /&gt;'''Организация Объединённых Наций'''&lt;br /&gt;'''Organización de las Naciones Unidas'''
|image_flag = Flag of the United Nations.svg
|image_symbol = Emblem of the United Nations.svg
|symbol_type = Emblem
|linking_name = United Nations
|image_map = United Nations Members.svg
|map_width = 280px
|map_caption = Map showing the [[Member states of the United Nations]]&lt;br /&gt;This map does not represent the view of its members or the UN concerning the legal status of any country,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/Depts/Cartographic/map/profile/world00.pdf|title=The World Today|format=PDF|accessdate=18 June 2009|quote=The designations employed and the presentation of material on this map do not imply the expression of any opinion whatsoever on the part of the Secretariat of the United Nations concerning the legal status of any country}}&lt;/ref&gt; nor does it accurately reflect which areas' governments have UN representation.
|membership = [[Member states of the United Nations|193 member states]]
|admin_center_type = [[United Nations Headquarters|Headquarters]]
|admin_center = [[Extraterritoriality|International territory]] in New York City, USA
|languages_type = [[Official language]]s
|languages = [[Arabic language|Arabic]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chinese language|Chinese]]&lt;br&gt;[[English language|English]]&lt;br&gt;[[French language|French]]&lt;br&gt;[[Russian language|Russian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Spanish language|Spanish]]
|leader_title1 = [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]]
|leader_name1 = [[Ban Ki-moon]]
|leader_title2 = [[Deputy Secretary-General of the United Nations|Deputy Secretary-General]]
|leader_name2 =  [[Asha-Rose Migiro]]
|leader_title3 = [[President of the United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly President]]
|leader_name3 = [[Nassir Abdulaziz Al-Nasser]]
|leader_title4= [[President of the United Nations Security Council|Security Council President]]
|leader_name4= [[José Filipe Moraes Cabral]]
|established_event1 = {{nowrap|[[United Nations Charter]] signed}}
|established_date1 = 26 June 1945
|established_event2 = {{nowrap|Entry into force of Charter}}
|established_date2 = 24 October 1945
|official_website = [http://www.un.org/ UN.org]}}

The '''United Nations''' ('''UN''') is an [[international organization]] whose stated aims are facilitating cooperation in [[international law]], [[international security]], [[economic development]], [[social change|social progress]], human rights, and achievement of [[world peace]]. The UN was founded in 1945 after World War II to replace the [[League of Nations]], to stop wars between countries, and to provide a platform for dialogue. It contains multiple subsidiary organizations to carry out its missions.

There are currently [[Member states of the United Nations|193 member states]], including every [[Diplomatic recognition|internationally recognised]] sovereign state in the world but the [[Vatican City]]. From its offices around the world, the UN and its specialized agencies decide on substantive and administrative issues in regular meetings held throughout the year. The organization has six principal organs: the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] (the main [[deliberative assembly]]); the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]] (for deciding certain resolutions for peace and security); the [[United Nations Economic and Social Council|Economic and Social Council]] (for assisting in promoting international economic and social cooperation and development); the [[United Nations Secretariat|Secretariat]] (for providing studies, information, and facilities needed by the UN); the [[International Court of Justice]] (the primary judicial organ); and the [[United Nations Trusteeship Council]] (which is currently inactive). Other prominent [[United Nations System|UN System]] agencies include the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO), the [[World Food Programme]] (WFP) and [[United Nations Children's Fund]] (UNICEF). The UN's most visible public figure is the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]], currently [[Ban Ki-moon]] of South Korea, who attained the post in 2007. 

The [[United Nations Headquarters]] resides in international territory in New York City, with further main offices at [[United Nations Office at Geneva|Geneva]], [[United Nations Office at Nairobi|Nairobi]], and [[United Nations Office at Vienna|Vienna]]. The organization is financed from assessed and voluntary contributions from its member states, and has six official languages: [[Arabic language|Arabic]], Chinese, English, French, Russian, and Spanish.&lt;ref name=langs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/en/ga/about/ropga/lang.shtml |title=General Assembly of the United Nations – Rules of Procedure |publisher=UN Department for General Assembly |accessdate=15 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
{{Main|History of the United Nations}}
[[Image:Chile signs UN Charter 1945.jpg|thumb|The [[Chile]]an delegation signing the [[United Nations Charter|UN Charter]] in San Francisco, 1945]]
The [[League of Nations]] failed to prevent [[World War II]] (1939–1945). Because of the widespread recognition that [[Humans|humankind]] could not afford a third world war, the United Nations was established to replace the flawed League of Nations in 1945 in order to maintain international peace and promote cooperation in solving international economic, social and humanitarian problems. The earliest concrete plan for a new world organization was begun under the aegis of the U.S. State Department in 1939. [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] first coined the term 'United Nations' as a term to describe the [[Allies of World War II|Allied countries]]. The term was first officially used on 1 January 1942, when 26 governments signed the [[Atlantic Charter]], pledging to continue the war effort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=David |first=Wilton |title=United Nations |work=Etymologies &amp; Word Origins: Letter U |publisher=WordOrigins.org |url=http://www.wordorigins.org/index.php/site/comments/united_nations/}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 April 1945, the [[United Nations Conference on International Organization|UN Conference on International Organization]] began in San Francisco, attended by 50 governments and a number of non-governmental organizations involved in drafting the [[United Nations Charter]]. The UN officially came into existence on 24 October 1945 upon ratification of the Charter by the five permanent members of the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]]—France, the [[Republic of China]], the [[Soviet Union]], the United Kingdom and the United States—and by a majority of the other 46 signatories. The first meetings of the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]], with 51 nations represented, and the Security Council, took place in [[Westminster Central Hall]] in London in January 1946.&lt;ref name=unmilestones&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/aboutun/milestones.htm |title=Milestones in United Nations History |publisher=Department of Public Information, United Nations |accessdate=17 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The organization was based at the [[Sperry Corporation|Sperry Gyroscope Corporation]]'s facility in [[Lake Success, New York]], from 1946–1952, before moving to the [[United Nations Headquarters]] building in Manhattan upon its completion.

Since its creation, there has been controversy and [[criticism of the United Nations]]. In the United States, an early opponent of the UN was the [[John Birch Society]], which began a &quot;get US out of the UN&quot; campaign in 1959, charging that the UN's aim was to establish a &quot;One World Government.&quot; After the Second World War, the [[French Committee of National Liberation]] was late to be recognized by the US as the government of France, and so the country was initially excluded from the conferences that aimed at creating the new organization. [[Charles de Gaulle]] criticized the UN, famously calling it ''le machin'' (&quot;the thing&quot;), and was not convinced that a global security alliance would help maintain world peace, preferring direct defence treaties between countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Gerbet|first=Pierre |year=1995|title=Naissance des Nations Unies|journal=Espoir |issue=102|language=French|url=http://www.charles-de-gaulle.org/pages/l-homme/dossiers-thematiques/1944-1946-la-liberation/restaurer-le-rang-de-la-france/analyses/naissance-des-nations-unies.php}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legal basis of establishment==
Shortly after its establishment the UN sought recognition as an [[international legal person]] due to the case of ''Reparations for Injuries Suffered in the Service of the United Nations''&lt;ref&gt;Reparations for Injuries Suffered in the Service of the United Nations. ICJ Reports. 1949. p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; with the advisory opinion delivered by the [[International Court of Justice]] (ICJ). The question arose whether the United Nations, as an organisation, had &quot;the capacity to bring an international claim against a government regarding injuries that the organisation alleged had been caused by that state.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Lindblom, Anna-Karin, ''Non-governmental organisations in international law'', Cambridge University Press, New York, 2005, p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

The Court stated: the Organization was intended to exercise and enjoy, and is in fact exercising and enjoying functions and rights, which can only be explained on the basis of the possession of a large measure of international personality and the capacity to operate upon an international plane ... Accordingly, the Court has come to the conclusion that the Organization is an international person. That is not the same thing as saying that it is a State, which it certainly is not, or that its legal personality and rights and duties are the same as those of a State ... What it
does mean is that it is a subject of international law and capable of possessing international rights and duties, and that it has capacity to maintain its rights by bringing international claims.&lt;ref&gt;Lindblom, Anna-Karin, ''Non-governmental organisations in international law'', Cambridge University Press, New York, 2005, p.59&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
{{Main|United Nations System}}
The United Nations' system is based on five principal organs (formerly six – the [[United Nations Trusteeship Council|Trusteeship Council]] suspended operations in 1994, upon the independence of [[Palau]], the last remaining UN trustee territory);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2005/org1436.doc.htm|title=Membership of Principal United Nations Organs in 2005|publisher=United Nations|date=15 March 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]], the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]], the [[United Nations Economic and Social Council|Economic and Social Council]] (ECOSOC), the [[United Nations Secretariat|Secretariat]], and the [[International Court of Justice]].

Four of the five principal organs are located at the main [[United Nations Headquarters]] located on international territory in New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://visit.un.org/wcm/content/|title=United Nations Visitors Centre|publisher=United Nations|year=2011|accessdate=25 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[International Court of Justice]] is located in [[The Hague]], while other major agencies are based in the UN offices at [[United Nations Office at Geneva|Geneva]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unog.ch/ |title=The United Nations in the Heart of Europe |publisher=Unog.ch |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[United Nations Office at Vienna|Vienna]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unvienna.org/unov/ |title=United Nations Office in Vienna |publisher=Unvienna.org |date=1980-01-01 |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[United Nations Office at Nairobi|Nairobi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unon.org/ |title=//Welcome to UNON &amp;#124; &amp;#124; The United Nations Office at Nairobi // |publisher=Unon.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other UN institutions are located throughout the world.

The six [[official language]]s of the United Nations, used in intergovernmental meetings and documents, are Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian, and Spanish.&lt;ref name=langs /&gt;  The Secretariat uses two working languages, English and French. Four of the official languages are the national languages of the [[List of members of the United Nations Security Council|permanent members of the Security Council]] (the United Kingdom and the United States share English as a ''de facto'' official language); Spanish and Arabic are the languages of the two largest blocs of official languages outside of the permanent members (Spanish being official in 20 countries, Arabic in 26). Five of the official languages were chosen when the UN was founded; Arabic was added later in 1973. The United Nations Editorial Manual states that the standard for English language documents is [[British English|British usage]] and [[Oxford spelling]], the [[written Chinese|Chinese writing]] standard is [[simplified Chinese characters|Simplified Chinese]]. This replaced [[Traditional Chinese characters|Traditional Chinese]] in 1971 when the UN representation of China was changed from the [[Republic of China]] to the People's Republic of China (see [[China and the United Nations]] for details).

===General Assembly===
[[Image:UN General Assembly hall.jpg|thumb|[[United Nations General Assembly]] hall]]
{{Main|United Nations General Assembly}}
The General Assembly is the main [[deliberative assembly]] of the United Nations. Composed of all [[Member states of the United Nations|United Nations member states]], the assembly meets in regular yearly sessions under a [[President of the United Nations General Assembly|president]] elected from among the member states. Over a two-week period at the start of each session, all members have the opportunity to address the assembly. Traditionally, the Secretary-General makes the first statement, followed by the president of the assembly. The first session was convened on 10 January 1946 in the [[Westminster Central Hall]] in London and included representatives of 51 nations.

When the General Assembly votes on important questions, a two-thirds majority of those present and voting is required. Examples of important questions include: recommendations on peace and security; election of members to organs; admission, suspension, and expulsion of members; and, budgetary matters. All other questions are decided by majority vote. Each member country has one vote. Apart from approval of budgetary matters, resolutions are not binding on the members. The Assembly may make recommendations on any matters within the scope of the UN, except matters of peace and security that are under Security Council consideration.

Conceivably, the [[representation (politics)|one state, one vote]] power structure could enable states comprising just eight percent of the world population to pass a resolution by a two-thirds vote (see [[List of countries by population]]). However, as no more than recommendations, it is difficult to imagine a situation in which a recommendation by member states constituting just eight percent of the world's population, would be adhered to by the remaining ninety-two percent of the population, should they object.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

===Security Council===
[[Image:United Nations Security Council.jpg|thumb|[[United Nations Security Council]] chamber]]
{{Main|United Nations Security Council}}
The [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]] is charged with maintaining peace and security among countries. While other organs of the United Nations can only make 'recommendations' to member governments, the Security Council has the power to make binding decisions that member governments have agreed to carry out, under the terms of [[United Nations Charter|Charter]] Article 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChapterV&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/chapter5.htm |title=UN Charter: Chapter V |accessdate=24 March 2008 |publisher=United Nations |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20080312121137/http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/chapter5.htm |archivedate = 12 March 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The decisions of the Council are known as [[United Nations Security Council resolution]]s.

The Security Council is made up of 15 member states, consisting of 5 permanent members–China, France, Russia, the United Kingdom and the United States–and 10 non-permanent members, currently [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Brazil]], [[Colombia]], [[Gabon]], [[Germany]], [[India]], [[Lebanon]], [[Nigeria]], [[Portugal]], [[South Africa]]. The five permanent members hold [[United Nations Security Council veto power|veto power]] over substantive but not procedural resolutions allowing a permanent member to block adoption but not to block the debate of a resolution unacceptable to it. The ten temporary seats are held for two-year terms with member states voted in by the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] on a [[United Nations Regional Groups|regional basis]]. The presidency of the Security Council is rotated alphabetically each month.&lt;ref name=&quot;CouncilMembers&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/sc/members.asp |title=UN Security Council Members |accessdate=23 February 2011 |publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Secretariat===
{{Main|United Nations Secretariat}}
[[Image:The United Nations Building.jpg|thumb|right|upright|The [[United Nations Secretariat Building]] at the [[United Nations Headquarters]] in New York City.]]
The United Nations Secretariat is headed by the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]], assisted by a staff of international civil servants worldwide. It provides studies, information, and facilities needed by United Nations bodies for their meetings. It also carries out tasks as directed by the UN Security Council, the UN General Assembly, the UN Economic and Social Council, and other UN bodies. The United Nations Charter provides that the staff be chosen by application of the &quot;highest standards of efficiency, competence, and integrity,&quot; with due regard for the importance of recruiting on a wide geographical basis.

The Charter provides that the staff shall not seek or receive instructions from any authority other than the UN. Each UN member country is enjoined to respect the international character of the Secretariat and not seek to influence its staff. The Secretary-General alone is responsible for staff selection.

The Secretary-General's duties include helping resolve international disputes, administering peacekeeping operations, organizing international conferences, gathering information on the implementation of Security Council decisions, and consulting with member governments regarding various initiatives. Key Secretariat offices in this area include the Office of the Coordinator of Humanitarian Affairs and the Department of Peacekeeping Operations. The Secretary-General may bring to the attention of the Security Council any matter that, in his or her opinion, may threaten international peace and security.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

====Secretary-General====
{{Main|Secretary-General of the United Nations}}
[[File:Ban Ki-moon 1-2.jpg|thumb|upright|The current [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]], [[Ban Ki-moon]]]]
The Secretariat is headed by the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]], who acts as the ''de facto'' spokesperson and leader of the UN. The current Secretary-General is [[Ban Ki-moon]], who took over from [[Kofi Annan]] in 2007 and has been elected for a second term to conclude at the end of 2016.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-13868655|title=Ban Ki-moon wins second term as UN Secretary General|publisher=BBC | date=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Envisioned by [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] as a &quot;world moderator&quot;, the position is defined in the [[United Nations Charter|UN Charter]] as the organization's &quot;chief administrative officer&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[s:en:Charter of the United Nations#Article 97|Charter of the United Nations, Article 97]].&lt;/ref&gt; but the Charter also states that the Secretary-General can bring to the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]]'s attention &quot;any matter which in his opinion may threaten the maintenance of [[world peace|international peace]] and security&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[s:en:Charter of the United Nations#Article 97|Charter of the United Nations, Article 99]].&lt;/ref&gt; giving the position greater scope for action on the world stage. The position has evolved into a dual role of an administrator of the UN organization, and a diplomat and [[mediation|mediator]] addressing disputes between [[Member states of the United Nations|member states]] and finding consensus to global issues.&lt;ref name=sgrole&gt;[http://www.un.org/sg/sgrole.shtml Office of the Secretary-General–United Nations].&lt;/ref&gt;

The Secretary-General is appointed by the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]], after being recommended by the Security Council, where the permanent members have [[United Nations Security Council veto power|veto power]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/sg/appointment.shtml United Nations–Appointment Process of the Secretary-General].&lt;/ref&gt; The General Assembly can theoretically override the Security Council's recommendation if a majority vote is not achieved, although this has not happened so far.&lt;ref name=&quot;una-usa-fact&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.unausa.org/atf/cf/%7B49C555AC-20C8-4B43-8483-A2D4C1808E4E%7D/SG%20Reform%20Fact%20Sheet-fina-logol.pdf |title=An Historical Overview on the Selection of United Nations Secretaries-General | publisher=UNA-USA | accessdate=30 September 2007|format=PDF |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071025014319/http://www.unausa.org/atf/cf/%7b49C555AC-20C8-4B43-8483-A2D4C1808E4E%7d/SG+Reform+Fact+Sheet-fina-logol.pdf &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 25 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are no specific criteria for the post, but over the years, it has become accepted that the post shall be held for one or two terms of five years, that the post shall be appointed on the basis of geographical rotation, and that the Secretary-General shall not originate from one of the five permanent Security Council member states.&lt;ref name=&quot;una-usa-fact&quot;/&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%; text-align:left;&quot;
|+ style=&quot;padding-top:1em;&quot; |Secretaries-General of the United Nations&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/sg/formersgs.shtml Former Secretaries-General–United Nations].&lt;/ref&gt;
! No. !! Name !! Country of origin !! Took office !! Left office !! Note
|-
| 1 || '''[[Trygve Lie]]''' || {{flag|Norway}} || 2 February 1946 || 10 November 1952 || Resigned
|-
| 2 || '''[[Dag Hammarskjöld]]''' || {{flag|Sweden}} || 10 April 1953 || 18 September 1961 || Died while in office
|-
| 3 || '''[[U Thant]]''' || {{flag|Burma|1948}} || 30 November 1961 || 31 December 1971 || First Secretary-General from Asia
|-
| 4 || '''[[Kurt Waldheim]]''' || {{flag|Austria}} || 1 January 1972 || 31 December 1981 ||
|-
| 5 || '''[[Javier Pérez de Cuéllar]]''' || {{flag|Peru}} || 1 January 1982 || 31 December 1991 || First Secretary-General from the Americas
|-
| 6 || '''[[Boutros Boutros-Ghali]]''' || {{flag|Egypt}} || 1 January 1992 || 31 December 1996 || First Secretary-General from Africa
|-
| 7 || '''[[Kofi Annan]]''' || {{flag|Ghana}} || 1 January 1997 || 31 December 2006 ||
|-
| 8 || '''[[Ban Ki-moon]]''' || {{flag|South Korea}} || 1 January 2007 || Incumbent ||
|}

===International Court of Justice===
[[Image:International Court of Justice.jpg|thumb|[[Peace Palace]], seat of the [[International Court of Justice]] at [[The Hague]], Netherlands]]
{{Main|International Court of Justice}}
The International Court of Justice (ICJ), located in [[The Hague]], Netherlands, is the primary judicial organ of the United Nations. Established in 1945 by the United Nations Charter, the Court began work in 1946 as the successor to the [[Permanent Court of International Justice]]. The Statute of the International Court of Justice, similar to that of its predecessor, is the main constitutional document constituting and regulating the Court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.icj-cij.org/documents/index.php?p1=4&amp;p2=2&amp;p3=0 |title=Statute of the International Court of Justice |publisher=International Court of Justice |accessdate=31 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It is based in the [[Peace Palace]] in [[The Hague]], Netherlands, sharing the building with the [[Hague Academy of International Law]], a private centre for the study of international law. Several of the Court's current judges are either alumni or former faculty members of the Academy. Its purpose is to adjudicate disputes among states. The court has heard cases related to war crimes, illegal state interference and ethnic cleansing, among others, and continues to hear cases.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.icj-cij.org/court/index.php?p1=1&amp;PHPSESSID=26e84ff7b1a8f1f3edf82cf94f3a7d68 |title=The Court |publisher=International Court of Justice |accessdate=17 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International Criminal Court===
{{Main|International Criminal Court}}
The International Criminal Court (ICC), it came into being on 1 July 2002 with the entering into force of the [[Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court]] which was adopted on 17 July 1998. It is the first permanent international court charged with trying those who commit the most serious crimes under international law, including war crimes, genocide, crimes against humanity and the crime of aggression (although it cannot exercise jurisdiction over this crime prior to 2017). The ICC is functionally independent of the UN in terms of personnel and financing, but some meetings of the ICC governing body, the [[States parties to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court|Assembly of the States Parties to the Rome Statute]], are held at the United Nations. There is a &quot;relationship agreement&quot; between the ICC and the UN that governs how the two institutions regard each other legally.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.icc-cpi.int/menus/icc/press%20and%20media/press%20releases/2004/agreement%20between%20the%20international%20criminal%20court%20and%20the%20united%20nations|title=Agreement Between the [[International Criminal Court]] and the United Nations|date=4 October 2004|publisher=International Criminal Court}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Economic and Social Council===
{{Main|United Nations Economic and Social Council}}
[[File:United Nations Economic and Social Council.jpg|thumb|right|The ECOSOC chamber]]
The Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC) assists the General Assembly in promoting international economic and social cooperation and development. ECOSOC has 54 members, all of which are elected by the General Assembly for a three-year term. The president is elected for a one-year term and chosen amongst the small or middle powers represented on ECOSOC. ECOSOC meets once a year in July for a four-week session. Since 1998, it has held another meeting each April with finance ministers heading key committees of the [[World Bank Group|World Bank]] and the [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF). Viewed separate from the specialized bodies it coordinates, ECOSOC's functions include information gathering, advising member nations, and making recommendations. In addition, ECOSOC is well-positioned to provide policy [[coherence (cognitive science)|coherence]] and coordinate the overlapping functions of the UN’s subsidiary bodies and it is in these roles that it is most active.

===Specialized institutions===
{{Main|List of specialized agencies of the United Nations}}
Many UN organizations and agencies exist to work on particular issues. Some of the most well-known agencies are the [[International Atomic Energy Agency]], the [[Food and Agriculture Organization]], [[UNESCO]] (United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization), the [[World Bank Group|World Bank]] and the [[World Health Organization]].

It is through these agencies that the UN performs most of its humanitarian work. Examples include mass vaccination programmes (through the WHO), the avoidance of famine and malnutrition (through the work of the WFP) and the protection of vulnerable and displaced people (for example, by the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|UNHCR]]).

The [[United Nations Charter]] stipulates that each primary organ of the UN can establish various specialized agencies to fulfil its duties.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%; text-align:left;&quot;
|+ style=&quot;padding-top:1em;&quot; |'''Organizations and specialized agencies of the United Nations'''
! No. !!Acronyms !! Logo !! Agency !! Headquarters !! Head !! Established in
|-
| 1 || FAO || [[File:FAO logo.svg|center|20px|Food and Agriculture Organization]] || '''[[Food and Agriculture Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|Italy}} Rome, Italy|| {{Flagicon|Senegal}} [[Jacques Diouf]] || 1945
|-
| 2 || IAEA || [[File:Flag of IAEA.svg|center|20px|International Atomic Energy Agency]] || '''[[International Atomic Energy Agency]]'''||{{flagicon|Austria}} [[Vienna]], Austria || {{Flagicon|Japan}} [[Yukiya Amano]] || 1957
|-
| 3 || ICAO || [[File:Flag of ICAO.svg|center|20px|International Civil Aviation Organization]] || '''[[International Civil Aviation Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|CAN}} [[Montreal]], Canada || {{Flagicon|FRA}} [[Raymond Benjamin]] || 1947
|-
| 4 || IFAD ||&lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt; || '''[[International Fund for Agricultural Development]]'''|| {{flagicon|Italy}} Rome, Italy || {{Flagicon|Nigeria}} [[Kanayo F. Nwanze]]|| 1977
|-
| 5 || ILO || [[File:Flag of ILO.svg|center|20px|International Labour Organization]] || '''[[International Labour Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|SUI}} [[Geneva]], Switzerland || {{Flagicon|Chile}} [[Juan Somavía]]|| 1946 (1919)
|-
| 6 || IMO || [[File:Flag of the International Maritime Organization.svg|center|20px|International Maritime Organization]] || '''[[International Maritime Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|GBR}} London, United Kingdom || {{Flagicon|GRE}} [[Efthimios E. Mitropoulos]]|| 1948
|-
| 7 || IMF || &lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt;|| '''[[International Monetary Fund]]'''|| {{flagicon|USA}} Washington, D.C., USA || {{Flagicon|FRA}} [[Christine Lagarde]]|| 1945 (1944)
|-
| 8 || ITU || [[File:Flag of ITU.svg|center|20px|International Telecommunication Union]] || '''[[International Telecommunication Union]]'''||{{flagicon|CHE}} [[Geneva]], Switzerland || {{Flagicon|MLI}} [[Hamadoun Touré]] || 1947 (1865)
|-
| 9 || UNESCO || [[File:Flag of UNESCO.svg|center|20px|United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization]] || '''[[United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|France}} Paris, France || {{Flagicon|BUL}} [[Irina Bokova]] || 1946
|-
| 10 || UNIDO ||&lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt; || '''[[United Nations Industrial Development Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|Austria}} [[Vienna]], Austria || {{Flagicon|Sierra Leone}} [[Kandeh Yumkella]] || 1967
|-
| 11 || UPU || [[File:Flag of UPU.svg|center|20px|Universal Postal Union]] || '''[[Universal Postal Union]]'''||{{flagicon|CHE}} [[Bern]], Switzerland || {{Flagicon|FRA}} [[Edouard Dayan]] || 1947 (1874)
|-
| 12 || WB || &lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt;|| '''[[World Bank]]'''||{{flagicon|USA}} Washington, D.C., USA || {{Flagicon|USA}} [[Robert B. Zoellick]]|| 1945 (1944)
|-
| 13 || WFP || [[File:WFPlogo130.svg|center|20px|World Food Programme]] || '''[[World Food Programme]]'''||{{flagicon|Italy}} Rome, Italy || {{Flagicon|USA}} [[Josette Sheeran]] || 1963
|-
| 14 || WHO || [[File:Flag of WHO.svg|center|20px|World Health Organization]] || '''[[World Health Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|CHE}} [[Geneva]], Switzerland ||{{Flagicon|Hong Kong}} [[Margaret Chan]]|| 1948
|-
| 15 || WIPO ||&lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt; || '''[[World Intellectual Property Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|CHE}} [[Geneva]], Switzerland || {{Flagicon|AUS}} [[Francis Gurry]] || 1974
|-
| 16 || WMO || [[File:Flag of the World Meteorological Organization.svg|center|20px|World Meteorological Organization]] || '''[[World Meteorological Organization]]'''|| {{flagicon|CHE}} [[Geneva]], Switzerland || {{Flagicon|RUS}} [[Alexander Bedritsky]] || 1950 (1873)
|-
| 17 || UNWTO ||&lt;!-- Do NOT place non-free images here --&gt; || '''[[World Tourism Organization]]'''||{{flagicon|Spain}} [[Madrid]], Spain || {{Flagicon|Jordan}} [[Taleb Rifai]] || 1974
|}

==Membership==
{{Main|Member states of the United Nations}}
[[Image:UN member states animation.gif|thumb|400px|An animation showing the timeline of accession of UN member states, ''according to the UN''. Note that Antarctica has no government; political control of [[Western Sahara]] is in dispute; and the territories administered by the [[Republic of China]] (Taiwan) and [[Kosovo]] are considered by the UN to be provinces of the People's Republic of China and [[Republic of Serbia]], respectively.]]

With the addition of [[South Sudan]] on 14 July 2011,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=39034&amp;Cr=South+Sudan&amp;Cr1= |title=UN welcomes South Sudan as 193rd Member State |publisher=Un.org |date=2006-06-28 |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; there are currently 193 United Nations member states, including all fully recognized independent [[List of sovereign states|states]]&lt;ref&gt;Kosovo and Taiwan are only partially recognized, and are not recognized by the UN.&lt;/ref&gt; apart from [[Vatican City]] (the [[Activities of the Holy See within the United Nations system|Holy See]], which holds sovereignty over the state of Vatican City, is a [[United Nations General Assembly observers|permanent observer]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;members&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.un.org/members/
|title=United Nations Member States
|publisher=United Nations
|accessdate=5 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[United Nations Charter]] outlines the rules for membership:
&lt;!--template syntax: {{Quote|Phrase|Somebody|''Source''}}--&gt;
{{Quote|
# Membership in the United Nations is open to all other peace-loving states that accept the obligations contained in the present Charter and, in the judgment of the Organization, are able and willing to carry out these obligations.
# The admission of any such state to membership in the United Nations will be effected by a decision of the General Assembly upon the recommendation of the Security Council.|United Nations Charter, Chapter 2, Article 4|''http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/''}}

===Group of 77===
The [[Group of 77]] at the UN is a loose coalition of [[developing country|developing nations]], designed to promote its members' collective [[economy|economic]] interests and create an enhanced joint negotiating capacity in the United Nations. There were 77 founding members of the organization, but the organization has since expanded to 130 member countries. The group was founded on 15 June 1964 by the &quot;Joint Declaration of the Seventy-Seven Countries&quot; issued at the [[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development]] (UNCTAD). The first major meeting was in [[Algiers]] in 1967, where the ''Charter of Algiers'' was adopted and the basis for permanent institutional structures was begun.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.g77.org/doc/ |title=About the G77 |publisher=Group of 77 |accessdate=30 September 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Stated objectives==
===Peacekeeping and security===
{{Main|United Nations peacekeeping}}
{{See also|List of United Nations peacekeeping missions}}
{{UN Peacekeeping Missions}}
The UN, after approval by the [[United Nations Security Council|Security Council]], sends [[peacekeeping|peacekeepers]] to regions where armed conflict has recently ceased or paused to enforce the terms of peace agreements and to discourage combatants from resuming hostilities. Since the UN does not maintain its own military, peacekeeping forces are voluntarily provided by member states of the UN. The forces, also called the &quot;Blue Helmets&quot;, who enforce UN accords, are awarded [[United Nations Medal]]s, which are considered [[international decoration]]s instead of [[military decoration]]s. The peacekeeping force as a whole received the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1988/|author=Nobel Prize|title=The Nobel Peace Prize 1988|accessdate=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The founders of the UN had envisaged that the organization would act to prevent conflicts between nations and make future wars impossible, however the outbreak of the [[Cold War]] made peacekeeping agreements extremely difficult because of the division of the world into hostile camps. Following the end of the Cold War, there were renewed calls for the UN to become the agency for achieving world peace, as several dozen [[List of ongoing military conflicts|ongoing conflicts]] continue to rage around the globe.

A 2005 RAND Corp study found the UN to be successful in two out of three peacekeeping efforts. It compared UN nation-building efforts to those of the United States, and found that seven out of eight UN cases are at peace, as compared with four out of eight US cases at peace.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rand.org/pubs/monographs/2005/RAND_MG304.sum.pdf|author=RAND Corporation|title=The UN's Role in Nation Building: From the Congo to Iraq|format=PDF|accessdate=30 December 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also in 2005, the [[Human Security Report 2005|Human Security Report]] documented a decline in the number of wars, genocides and human rights abuses since the end of the [[Cold War]], and presented evidence, albeit circumstantial, that international activism—mostly spearheaded by the UN—has been the main cause of the decline in armed conflict since the end of the Cold War.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.humansecurityreport.info/|author=Human Security Centre|title=The Human Security Report 2005|accessdate=8 February 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Situations where the UN has not only acted to keep the peace but also occasionally intervened include the [[Korean War]] (1950–1953), and the authorization of intervention in Iraq after the [[Gulf War|Persian Gulf War]] in 1990.

The UN has also drawn criticism for perceived failures. In many cases, [[Member states of the United Nations|member states]] have shown reluctance to achieve or enforce Security Council resolutions, an issue that stems from the UN's intergovernmental nature—seen by some as simply an association of 193 member states who must reach consensus, not an independent organization. Disagreements in the Security Council about military action and intervention are seen as having failed to prevent the 1994 [[Rwandan Genocide]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hrw.org/community/bookreviews/melvern.htm|publisher=Human Rights Watch|title=Book Review: A People Betrayed, the Role of the West in Rwanda's Genocide}}{{dead link|date=January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; failed to provide [[humanitarian aid]] and intervene in the [[Second Congo War]], failed to intervene in the 1995 [[Srebrenica massacre]] and protect a refugee haven by authorizing peacekeepers to use force, failure to deliver food to starving people in [[Somalia]], failure to implement provisions of Security Council resolutions related to the [[Israeli-Palestinian conflict]], and continuing failure to prevent genocide or provide assistance in [[Darfur]]. UN peacekeepers have also been accused of child rape, sexual abuse or soliciting prostitutes during various peacekeeping missions, starting in 2003, in the [[Democratic Republic of the Congo|Congo]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A3145-2004Dec15.html|title=U.N.&amp;nbsp;Sexual Abuse Alleged in Congo|work=Washington Post |author=Colum Lynch|date=16 December 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Haiti]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/6195830.stm|title=UN troops face child abuse claims|publisher=BBC News |date=30 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2007/11/02/news/UN-GEN-UN-Haiti-Sexual-Exploitation.php|title=
108 Sri Lankan peacekeepers in Haiti to be repatriated after claims they paid prostitutes
|work=International Herald Tribune |date=2 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Liberia]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.iht.com/articles/2006/05/08/news/abuse.php|title=Aid workers in Liberia accused of sex abuse|work=International Herald Tribune |date=8 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Sudan]] and what is now [[South Sudan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/main.jhtml?xml=/news/2007/01/03/wsudan03.xml|title= UN staff accused of raping children in Sudan|publisher=Telegraph|date=4 January 2007 | location=London | first=Kate | last=Holt | accessdate=1 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Burundi]] and [[Côte d'Ivoire]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/7420798.stm|title= UN staff accused of raping children in Sudan|publisher=BBC |date=28 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, former Israeli ambassador to the UN [[Dore Gold]] criticized what it called the organization's [[moral relativism]] in the face of (and occasional support of)&lt;ref&gt;Gold, 216–217&lt;/ref&gt; [[genocide]] and terrorism that occurred between the moral clarity of its founding period and the present day. Gold specifically mentions [[Yasser Arafat]]'s 1988 invitation to address the General Assembly as a low point in the UN's history.&lt;ref&gt;Gold, 38&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--Disarmament--&gt;
In addition to peacekeeping, the UN is also active in encouraging [[disarmament]]. Regulation of armaments was included in the writing of the [[United Nations Charter]] in 1945 and was envisioned as a way of limiting the use of human and economic resources for the creation of them.&lt;ref&gt;[[s:en:Charter of the United Nations|United Nations Charter, Article 26]].&lt;/ref&gt; However, the advent of [[nuclear weapon]]s came only weeks after the signing of the charter and immediately halted concepts of arms limitation and [[disarmament]], resulting in the first [[United Nations General Assembly resolution|resolution]] of the first ever [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] meeting calling for specific proposals for &quot;the elimination from national armaments of atomic weapons and of all other major weapons adaptable to mass destruction&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/documents/ga/res/1/ares1.htm |title=Resolutions Adopted by the General Assembly During its First Session|accessdate=24 March 2008 |publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt; The principal forums for disarmament issues are the [[General Assembly First Committee]], the UN Disarmament Commission, and the [[Conference on Disarmament]], and considerations have been made of the merits of a [[Comprehensive Nuclear-Test-Ban Treaty|ban on testing nuclear weapons]], [[Outer Space Treaty|outer space arms control]], the banning of [[chemical warfare|chemical weapons]] and [[Ottawa Treaty|land mines]], nuclear and conventional disarmament, [[nuclear-weapon-free zone]]s, the reduction of [[List of countries by military expenditures|military budgets]], and measures to strengthen [[international security]].

The UN is one of the official supporters of the World Security Forum, a major international conference on the effects of global catastrophes and disasters, which took place in the [[United Arab Emirates]] in October 2008.

On 5 November 2010 [[Ivor Ichikowitz]], founder and executive chairman of [[Paramount Group]], supported UN Secretary General [[Ban Ki-moon]]’s call for greater support, equipment and training for African [[peacekeeping]] forces. [[Ivor Ichikowitz|Ichikowitz]] stated that [[African Union]] troops should receive the same support as UN personnel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://en.apa.az/news.php?id=133677 |title=APA – Paramount Group CEO Ivor Ichikowitz calls for a new solution to peacekeeping, with Africa’s defence industry and governments cooperating to establish Africa as a centre for peacekeeping excellence in a bid to effectively resolve conflicts |publisher=En.apa.az |accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Human rights and humanitarian assistance===
[[Image:EleanorRooseveltHumanRights.png|thumb|right|[[Eleanor Roosevelt]] with the [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]] in 1949]]
The pursuit of human rights was a central reason for creating the UN. World War II atrocities and [[genocide]] led to a ready consensus that the new organization must work to prevent any similar tragedies in the future. An early objective was creating a legal framework for considering and acting on complaints about human rights violations. The UN Charter obliges all member nations to promote &quot;universal respect for, and observance of, human rights&quot; and to take &quot;joint and separate action&quot; to that end. The [[Universal Declaration of Human Rights]], though not legally binding, was adopted by the General Assembly in 1948 as a common standard of achievement for all. The Assembly regularly takes up human rights issues.

The UN and its agencies are central in upholding and implementing the principles enshrined in the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. A case in point is support by the UN for countries in transition to democracy. Technical assistance in providing free and fair elections, improving judicial structures, drafting constitutions, training human rights officials, and transforming armed movements into political parties have contributed significantly to democratization worldwide. The UN has helped run elections in countries with little or no democratic history, including recently in [[Afghanistan]] and East Timor. The UN is also a forum to support the right of women to participate fully in the political, economic, and social life of their countries. The UN contributes to raising consciousness of the concept of human rights through its covenants and its attention to specific abuses through its General Assembly, Security Council resolutions, or [[International Court of Justice]] rulings.

The purpose of the [[United Nations Human Rights Council]], established in 2006,&lt;ref name=&quot;UN_ARES60251&quot;&gt;{{UN document |docid=A-RES-60-251 |type=Resolution |body=General Assembly |session=60 |resolution_number=251 |accessdate=19 September 2007|date=15 March 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; is to address human rights violations. The Council is the successor to the [[United Nations Commission on Human Rights]], which was often criticized for the high-profile positions it gave to member states that did not guarantee the human rights of their own citizens.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimeseditorial&quot;&gt;{{Cite news
 | title = The Shame of the United Nations
 |work=New York Times | date = 26 February 2006
 | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/26/opinion/26sun2.html?_r=1&amp;n=Top%2fOpinion%2fEditorials%20and%20Op%2dEd%2fEditorials&amp;oref=slogin
 | accessdate =15 August 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The council has 47 members distributed by region, which each serve three-year terms, and may not serve three consecutive terms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.un.org/ga/61/elect/hrc/ | title=UN Human Rights Council Elections | publisher=United Nations | accessdate=4 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; A candidate to the body must be approved by a majority of the General Assembly. In addition, the council has strict rules for membership, including a universal human rights review. While some members with questionable human rights records have been elected, it is fewer than before with the increased focus on each member state's human rights record.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.opensocietypolicycenter.org/news/article.php?docId=110 | title=Successful UN Human Rights Council Elections Demonstrate UN Members are Taking Reform Effort Seriously. | publisher=Open Society Policy Center |date=9 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The rights of some 370&amp;nbsp;million [[indigenous peoples]] around the world are also a focus for the UN, with a [[Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples]] being approved by the [[United Nations General Assembly|General Assembly]] in 2007.&lt;ref name = &quot;UN-indigenous&quot;&gt;[http://www.un.org/ga/61/news/news.asp?NewsID=23794&amp;Cr=indigenous&amp;Cr1= UN General Assembly–61st session–United Nations adopts Declaration on Rights of Indigenous Peoples].&lt;/ref&gt; The declaration outlines the individual and collective rights to culture, language, education, identity, employment and health, thereby addressing post-colonial issues that had confronted indigenous peoples for centuries. The declaration aims to maintain, strengthen and encourage the growth of indigenous institutions, cultures and traditions. It also prohibits discrimination against indigenous peoples and promotes their active participation in matters that concern their past, present and future.&lt;ref name = &quot;UN-indigenous&quot;/&gt; The [[United Nations Permanent Forum on Indigenous Issues]] is the UN's central coordinating body for matters relating to the concerns and rights of the world's indigenous peoples. The forum is an advisory body within the framework of the United Nations System that reports to the UN's Economic and Social Council.

In conjunction with other organizations such as the [[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement|Red Cross]], the UN provides food, drinking water, shelter and other humanitarian services to populaces suffering from [[famine]], displaced by war, or afflicted by other disasters. Major humanitarian branches of the UN are the [[World Food Programme]] (which helps feed more than 100&amp;nbsp;million people a year in 80 countries), the office of the [[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees|High Commissioner for Refugees]] with projects in over 116 countries, as well as peacekeeping projects in over 24 countries.

===Social and economic development===
{| style=&quot;background:#f3f9ff; padding-left:7px; padding-bottom:7px; float:right; border:1px dashed #aaa; margin-left:1em; margin-bottom:1em;&quot;
|-
| colspan=2|
'''Millennium Development Goals'''
|-
| style=&quot;vertical-align:top; font-size:85%;&quot;|
# eradicate extreme poverty and [[malnutrition|hunger]];
# achieve universal primary education;
# promote [[gender equality]] and empower women;
# reduce [[child mortality]];
# improve [[maternal health]];
# combat HIV/AIDS, [[malaria]], and other diseases;
# ensure environmental [[sustainability]]; and
# develop a global partnership for [[International development|development]].
|}
The UN is involved in supporting [[economic development|development]], e.g. by the formulation of the [[Millennium Development Goals]]. The [[United Nations Development Programme|UN Development Programme]] (UNDP) is the largest multilateral source of grant technical assistance in the world. Organizations like the [[World Health Organization]] (WHO), [[Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS|UNAIDS]], and [[The Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria]] are leading institutions in the battle against diseases around the world, especially in poor countries. The UN Population Fund is a major provider of reproductive services. 32 UN agencies performing tasks on development are coordinating their efforts through the [[United Nations Development Group]] or UNDG.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.undg.org/index.cfm?P=2 |title=About the UNDG |publisher=Undg.org |accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The UN also promotes human development through some related agencies, particularly the UNDP.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdr.undp.org/en/humandev/ |title=Human Development &amp;#124; Human Development Reports (HDR) &amp;#124; United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) |publisher=Hdr.undp.org |accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[World Bank Group]] and [[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF), for example, are independent, specialized agencies and observers within the UN framework, according to a 1947 agreement. They were initially formed as separate from the UN through the [[Bretton Woods system|Bretton Woods]] Agreement in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.worldbank.org/WBSITE/EXTERNAL/EXTABOUTUS/0,,contentMDK:20040610~menuPK:41691~pagePK:43912~piPK:44037,00.html|title= About Us–United Nations|accessdate=2 August 2007|date=30 June 2003|publisher=The World Bank}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The UNDP annually publishes the [[Human Development Index]] (HDI), a comparative measure [[List of countries by Human Development Index|ranking countries]] by poverty, [[literacy]], education, [[life expectancy]], and other factors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdr.undp.org/en/ |title=Human Development Reports (HDR) – United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) |publisher=Hdr.undp.org |accessdate=1 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Millennium Development Goals]] (declared in the [[United Nations Millennium Declaration]], signed in September 2000)
are eight goals that all of the then 192 United Nations member states have agreed to try to achieve by the year 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/millenniumgoals/ | title=The UN Millennium Development Goals | publisher=United Nations | accessdate=4 May 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mandates===
{{See also|Category:United Nations Security Council mandates}}
From time to time, the different bodies of the United Nations pass resolutions that contain operating paragraphs that begin with the words &quot;requests&quot;, &quot;calls upon&quot;, or &quot;encourages&quot;, which the [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]] interprets as a mandate to set up a temporary organization or do something. These mandates can be as little as researching and publishing a written report, or mounting a full-scale peacekeeping operation (usually the exclusive domain of the Security Council).

Although the specialized institutions, such as the [[World Health Organization|WHO]], were originally set up by this means, they are not the same as mandates because they are permanent organizations that exist independently of the UN with their own membership structure. One could say that original mandate was simply to cover the process of setting up the institution, and has therefore long expired. Most mandates expire after a limited period and require renewal from the body, which set them up.

One of the outcomes of the [[2005 World Summit]] was a mandate (labelled [http://webapps01.un.org/mandatereview/viewBrowseMandate.do?code=17171&amp;page=1&amp;offset=16 id 17171]) for the Secretary-General to &quot;review all mandates older than five years originating from resolutions of the General Assembly and other organs&quot;. To facilitate this review and to finally bring coherence to the organization, the Secretariat has produced an [http://www.un.org/mandatereview/index.html on-line registry of mandates] to draw together the reports relating to each one and create an overall picture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/mandatereview/executive.html|title=Mandating and Delivering–Executive Summary|date=30 March 2006|author=The Secretary-General|publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Greening the Blue====
In 2007, On 5 June [[World Environment Day]] 2007, Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon made public his ambition to make the United Nations more efficient in its operations: “I would like to see our renovated Headquarters complex eventually become a globally acclaimed model of efficient use of energy and resources. Beyond New York, the initiative should include the other United Nations headquarters and offices around the globe.” The UN's progress towards achieving this goal is communicated through the initiative Greening the Blue (see external links below).

===Other===
Over the lifetime of the UN, over 80 colonies have attained independence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/Depts/dpi/decolonization/trust2.htm |title=Trust and Non-Self-Governing Territories, 1945–1999 |publisher=United Nations  |accessdate=9 October 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; The General Assembly adopted the [[Declaration on the Granting of Independence to Colonial Countries and Peoples]] in 1960 with no votes against but abstentions from all major colonial powers. Through the [[Special Committee on Decolonization|UN Committee on Decolonization]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.un.org/Depts/dpi/decolonization/special_committee_main.htm the United Nations Special Committee on Decolonization–Official Website].&lt;/ref&gt; created in 1962, the UN has focused considerable attention on [[decolonization]]. It has also supported the new states that have arisen as a result of self-determination initiatives. The committee has overseen the decolonization of every country larger than 20,000&amp;nbsp;km² and removed them from the [[United Nations list of Non-Self-Governing Territories]], besides [[Western Sahara]], a country larger than the UK only relinquished by Spain in 1975.

The UN declares and coordinates [[international observance]]s, periods of time to observe some issue of international interest or concern. Using the symbolism of the UN, a specially designed logo for the year, and the infrastructure of the [[United Nations System]], various days and years have become catalysts to advancing key issues of concern on a global scale. For example, [[World Tuberculosis Day]], [[Earth Day]] and [[International Year of Deserts and Desertification]].

==Funding==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%; white-space:nowrap; text-align:left; float:right; margin:10px;&quot;
|+Top 10 donators to the UN budget, 2011&lt;ref name=unbudget&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/ga/search/view_doc.asp?symbol=ST/ADM/SER.B/755 |title=Assessment of Member States' contributions to the United Nations regular budget for the year 2011 |publisher=[[United Nations Secretariat|UN Secretariat]] |format=PDF |date=28 December 2010 |accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! style=&quot;width:130px;&quot;| [[United Nations member states|Member state]]
! Contribution&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[Percentage|%]] of UN budget)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| '''{{flag|USA}}''' || 22.000%
|-
| '''{{flag|Japan}}''' || 12.530%
|-
| '''{{flag|Germany}}''' || 8.018%
|-
| '''{{flag|United Kingdom}}''' || 6.604%
|-
| '''{{flag|France}}''' || 6.123%
|-
| '''{{flag|Italy}}''' || 4.999%
|-
| '''{{flag|Canada}}''' || 3.207%
|-
| '''{{flag|China}}''' || 3.189%
|-
| '''{{flag|Spain}}''' || 3.177%
|-
| '''{{flag|Mexico}}''' || 2.356%
|-
| '''Other member states''' || 27.797%
|}
The UN is financed from assessed and voluntary contributions from member states. The General Assembly approves the regular budget and determines the assessment for each member. This is broadly based on the relative capacity of each country to pay, as measured by their [[gross national income]] (GNI), with adjustments for external debt and low per capita income.&lt;ref name=&quot;fifth-2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |title=Fifth Committee Approves Assessment Scale for Regular, Peacekeeping Budgets, Texts on Common System, Pension Fund, as it Concludes Session (Press Release) |publisher=United Nations |date=22 December 2006 |url=http://www.un.org/News/Press/docs/2006/gaab3787.doc.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Assembly has established the principle that the UN should not be overly dependent on any one member to finance its operations. Thus, there is a 'ceiling' rate, setting the maximum amount any member is assessed for the regular budget. In December 2000, the Assembly revised the scale of assessments to reflect current global circumstances. As part of that revision, the regular budget ceiling was reduced from 25% to 22%. For the least developed countries (LDCs), a ceiling rate of 0.01% is applied.&lt;ref name=&quot;fifth-2006&quot;/&gt; In addition to the ceiling rates, the minimum amount assessed to any member nation (or 'floor' rate) is set at 0.001% of the UN budget. Refer to the table for major contributors.

A large share of UN expenditures addresses the core UN mission of peace and security. The peacekeeping budget for the 2005–2006 fiscal year was approximately US$5&amp;nbsp;billion, €2.5&amp;nbsp;billion (compared to approximately US$1.5&amp;nbsp;billion, €995&amp;nbsp;million for the UN core budget over the same period), with some 70,000 troops deployed in 17 missions around the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;PeaceKeepingOps&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/Depts/dpko/dpko/bnote.htm |title=United Nations Peacekeeping Operations |accessdate=24 March 2008 |date=31 December 2007 |publisher=United Nations}}&lt;/ref&gt; UN peace operations are funded by assessments, using a formula derived from the regular funding scale, but including a weighted surcharge for the five permanent Security Council members, who must approve all peacekeeping operations. This surcharge serves to offset discounted peacekeeping assessment rates for less developed countries. As of 1 January 2011, the top 10 providers of assessed financial contributions to United Nations peacekeeping operations were: the United States, Japan, the United Kingdom, Germany, France, Italy, China, Canada, Spain and the Republic of Korea.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.un.org/Depts/dpko/dpko/contributors/financing.html |title=Financing of UN Peacekeeping Operations |publisher=United Nations  |accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Special UN programmes not included in the regular budget (such as [[UNICEF]], the [[World Food Programme|WFP]] and [[United Nations Development Programme|UNDP]]) are financed by voluntary contributions from other member governments. Most of this is financial contributions, but some is in the form of agricultural [[commodity|commodities]] donated for afflicted populations. Since their funding is voluntary, many of these agencies suffer severe shortages during economic recessions. In July 2009, the World Food Programme reported that it has been forced to cut services because of insufficient funding.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_depth/8179250.stm |title=BBC News, 'Dire shortage' at UN food agency |publisher=BBC  |accessdate=5 September 2009 | date=31 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has received barely a quarter of the total it needed for the 09/10 financial year.

==Personnel policy==
The UN and its agencies are immune to the laws of the countries where they operate, safeguarding UN's impartiality with regard to the host and member countries.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://diplomaticlaw.com/blog/2009/03/23/jerusalem-court-no-immunity-for-un-employee-for-private-acts/ |title=Jerusalem Court: No Immunity for UN Employee for Private Acts—Diplomatic/Consular Law and Sovereign Immunity in Israel |publisher=Diplomaticlaw.com |date=23 March 2009 |accessdate=27 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite their independence in matters of human resources policy, the UN and its agencies voluntarily apply the laws of member states regarding [[same-sex marriage]]s, allowing decisions about the status of employees in a same-sex partnership to be based on nationality. The UN and its agencies recognize same-sex marriages only if the employees are citizens of countries that recognize the marriage. This practice is not specific to the recognition of same-sex marriage but reflects a common practice of the UN for a number of human resources matters. It has to be noted though that some agencies provide limited benefits to [[domestic partnership|domestic partners]] of their staff and that some agencies do not recognise same-sex marriage or domestic partnership of their staff.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==Reform==
{{Main|Reform of the United Nations}}
[[File:Kofi Annan.jpg|thumb|upright|In 2005, then-Secretary General [[Kofi Annan]] published his report ''In Larger Freedom'', a proposal for reform of the UN.]]
Since its founding, there have been many calls for reform of the United Nations, although little consensus on how to do so. Some want the UN to play a greater or more effective role in world affairs, while others want its role reduced to humanitarian work.&lt;ref&gt;''The Future of the United Nations: Understanding the Past to Chart a Way Forward'' / [[Joshua Muravchik]] (2005) ISBN 978-0-8447-7183-0.&lt;/ref&gt; There have also been numerous calls for the [[Reform of the United Nations Security Council|UN Security Council's membership to be increased]], for different ways of electing the UN's [[Secretary-General of the United Nations|Secretary-General]], and for a [[United Nations Parliamentary Assembly]].

The UN has also been accused of bureaucratic inefficiency and waste. During the 1990s, the United States withheld dues citing inefficiency, and only started repayment on the condition that a major reforms initiative was introduced. In 1994, the [[United Nations Office of Internal Oversight Services|Office of Internal Oversight Services]] (OIOS) was established by the General Assembly to serve as an efficiency watchdog.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Reddy |first=Shravanti |date=29 October 2002 |url=http://www.globalpolicy.org/ngos/ngo-un/rest-un/2002/1029watchdog.htm |title=Watchdog Organization Struggles to Decrease UN Bureaucracy |publisher=Global Policy Forum |accessdate=21 September 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

An official reform programme was begun by [[Kofi Annan]] in 1997. Reforms mentioned include [[Reform of the United Nations Security Council|changing the permanent membership of the Security Council]] (which currently reflects the power relations of 1945), making the bureaucracy more transparent, accountable and efficient, making the UN more democratic, and imposing an international [[tariff]] on [[List of modern armament manufacturers|arms manufacturers]] worldwide.{{Citation needed|date=December 2007}}

In September 2005, the UN convened a World Summit that brought together the heads of most member states, calling the summit &quot;a once-in-a-generation opportunity to take bold decisions in the areas of development, security, human rights and reform of the United Nations.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The 2005 World Summit: An Overview|url=http://www.un.org/ga/documents/overview2005summit.pdf|publisher=United Nations|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kofi Annan had proposed that the summit agree on a global &quot;grand bargain&quot; to reform the UN, renewing the organization's focus on peace, security, human rights and development, and to make it better equipped at facing 21st century issues. The ''World Summit Outcome Document'' delineated the conclusions of the meeting, including: the creation of a [[Peacebuilding Commission]], to help countries emerging from conflict; a [[United Nations Human Rights Council|Human Rights Council]] and a democracy fund; a clear and unambiguous condemnation of terrorism &quot;in all its forms and manifestations&quot;; agreements to devote more resources to the Office of Internal Oversight Services; agreements to spend billions more on achieving the [[Millennium Development Goals]]; the dissolution of the [[United Nations Trusteeship Council|Trusteeship Council]], because of the completion of its mission; and, the agreement that individual states, with the assistance of the international community, have the &quot;[[responsibility to protect]]&quot; populations from genocide, war crimes, ethnic cleansing and crimes against humanity- with the understanding that the international community is prepared to act &quot;collectively&quot; in a “timely and decisive manner” to protect vulnerable civilians should a state &quot;manifestly fail&quot; in fulfilling its responsibility.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2005 World Summit Outcome|publisher=United Nations|url=http://www.un.org/summit2005/presskit/fact_sheet.pdf|format=PDF&lt;!-- application/pdf, 84923 bytes --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Office of Internal Oversight Services is being restructured to better define its scope and mandate, and will receive more resources. In addition, to improve the oversight and auditing capabilities of the General Assembly, an Independent Audit Advisory Committee (IAAC) is being created. In June 2007, the Fifth Committee created a draft resolution for the [[terms of reference]] of this committee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.centerforunreform.org/node/226 |author=Irene Martinetti |title=Reforming Oversight and Governance of the UN Encounters Hurdles |date=1 December 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.centerforunreform.org/node/31 |title=Oversight and Governance |publisher=Center for UN Reform Education}}&lt;/ref&gt; An ethics office was established in 2006, responsible for administering new financial disclosure and [[whistleblower]] protection policies. Working with the OIOS, the ethics office also plans to implement a policy to avoid fraud and corruption.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.centerforunreform.org/node/32 |title=Ethics Office |publisher=Center for UN Reform Education}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Secretariat is in the process of reviewing all UN mandates that are more than five years old. The review is intended to determine which duplicative or unnecessary programmes should be eliminated. Not all member states agree on which of the over 7000 mandates should be reviewed. The dispute centres on whether mandates that have been renewed should be examined.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.centerforunreform.org/node/30 |title=Mandate Review |publisher=Center for UN Reform Education}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, the obstacles identified – in particular, the lack of information on the resource implications of each mandate – constituted sufficient justification for the General Assembly to discontinue the mandate review in September 2008. In the meantime, the General Assembly launched a number of new loosely related reform initiatives in April 2007, covering international environmental governance, ‘Delivering as One’ at the country level to enhance the consolidation of UN programme activities and a unified gender organization. Whereas little was achieved on the first two issues, the General Assembly approved in September 2010 the establishment of ‘UN Women’ as the new UN organization for gender equality and the empowerment of women. UN Women was established by unifying the resources and mandates of four small entities for greater impact and its first head is Ms. Michelle Bachelet, former President of [[Chile]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

==See also==
{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
* [[Collective security]]
* [[High-level Panel on United Nations Systemwide Coherence]]
* [[International relations]]
* [[List of current Permanent Representatives to the United Nations]]
* [[Model United Nations]]
* [[Official statistics]]
* [[UNESCO Goodwill Ambassador]]
* [[Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees Goodwill Ambassador]] UNHCR Goodwill Ambassador
* [[Official languages of the United Nations]]
* [[United Nations Association]]
* [[United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea]]
{{col-break}}
* [[United Nations Group of Experts on Geographical Names]] (UNGEGN)
* [[United Nations in popular culture]]
* [[United Nations International School]]
* [[United Nations Peace Messenger Cities]]
* [[United Nations Postal Administration]]
* [[United Nations Security Council]]
* [[United Nations University]]
* [[University for Peace]]
* [[World Heritage Site]]
* ''[[Yearbook of the United Nations]]''
{{col-break}}
{{Portal|United Nations}}
{{col-end}}

===Relations between specific states and the United Nations===
&lt;!---Alphabetical order please---&gt;
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
* [[Australia and the United Nations]]
* [[Brazil and the United Nations]]
* [[Canada and the United Nations]]
* [[China and the United Nations]]
* [[Fiji and the United Nations]]
* [[France and the United Nations]]
* [[Activities of the Holy See within the United Nations system]]
* [[India and the United Nations]]
* [[Israel, Palestine, and the United Nations]]
* [[Japan and the United Nations]]
{{Col-2}}
* [[Marshall Islands and the United Nations]]
* [[Micronesia and the United Nations]]
* [[New Zealand and the United Nations]]
* [[Pakistan and the United Nations]]
* [[Russia and the United Nations]]
* [[Soviet Union and the United Nations]]
* [[United Kingdom and the United Nations]]
* [[United States and the United Nations]]
* [[Vanuatu and the United Nations]]
{{Col-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Further reading==
* [http://www.iupress.indiana.edu/catalog/index.php?cPath=1037_3130_3369 United Nations Intellectual History Project Book Series]. Indiana University Press.
* [http://foreignpolicy.com/story/cms.php?story_id=34 &quot;Think Again: The United Nations&quot;], [[Madeleine K. Albright]], ''Foreign Policy'', September/October 2004.
* [[Hans Köchler]], ''Quo Vadis, United Nations?'', in: Law Review, [[Polytechnic University of the Philippines]], College of Law, May 2005 [http://hanskoechler.com/koechler-quo-vadis-UN.htm Online version].
* ''An Insider's Guide to the UN'', Linda Fasulo, [[Yale University Press]] (1 November 2003), hardcover, 272 pages, ISBN 0-300-10155-4.
* ''United Nations: The First Fifty Years'', Stanley Mesler, Atlantic Monthly Press (1 March 1997), hardcover, 416 pages, ISBN 0-87113-656-2.
* ''Act of Creation: The Founding of the United Nations'', Stephen Schlesinger, Westview Press (1 September 2003), softcover, 374 pages, ISBN 978-0-8133-3324-3.
* [http://www.oup.com/uk/catalogue/?ci=9780199583300 ''The United Nations Security Council and War: The Evolution of Thought and Practice since 1945'', edited by Vaughan Lowe, Adam Roberts, Jennifer Welsh and Dominik Zaum], Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2010, paperback, 794 pages. ISBN 978-0-19-958330-0. [http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Politics/InternationalStudies/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780199583300#Description ''For US edition, click here.'']
* [http://www.oup.com/uk/catalogue/?ci=9780198279266 ''United Nations, Divided World: The UN's Roles in International Relations'', edited by Adam Roberts and Benedict Kingsbury], Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2nd edition, 1993, paperback, 589 pages. ISBN 0-19-827926-4. [http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Politics/InternationalStudies/InternationalOrganizations/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780198279266 ''For US edition, click here.'']
* ''A Guide to Delegate Preparation: A Model United Nations Handbook'', edited by Scott A. Leslie, The United Nations Association of the United States of America, 2004 edition (October 2004), softcover, 296 pages, ISBN 1-880632-71-3.
* &quot;U.S. At War–International.&quot; ''Time Magazine'' XLV.19 7 May 1945: 25–28.
* [http://www.us.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Politics/InternationalStudies/InternationalOrganizations/?view=usa&amp;ci=9780199279517 ''The Oxford Handbook on the United Nations'', edited by Thomas G. Weiss and Sam Daws], Oxford University Press, July 2007, hardcover, 896 pages, ISBN 978-0-19-927951-7, ISBN 0-19-927951-9.
&lt;/div&gt;
* [[Dore Gold|Gold, Dore]]. ''Tower of Babble: How the United Nations Has Fueled Global Chaos''. New York: Three Rivers Press, 2004.

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
;Official websites
* [http://www.un.org/ United Nations official homepage]
* [http://www.unsystem.org/ United Nations Systems of Organizations]
* [http://www.un.org/aboutun About the United Nations]
* [http://www.un.org/issues Global Issues on the UN Agenda]
* [http://www.un.org/events/panel/ High-level Panel on United Nations Systemwide Coherence]
* [http://www.un.org/Docs/journal/En/lateste.pdf Journal of the United Nations: Programme of meetings and agenda].
* [http://www.unric.org/ The United Nations Regional Information Centre (UNRIC)]
* [http://www.greeningtheblue.org/ Greening the Blue: The United Nations' approach to managing its own sustainability performance]
* [http://www.un.org/chronicle UN Chronicle Magazine]
* [http://www.un.org/aboutun/chart.html UN Organisation Chart]
* [http://www.un.org/works UN Works]
* [http://www.un.org/aboutun/charter/index.html United Nations Charter]–Charter text
* [http://www.un.org/documents/scres.htm United Nations Security Council Resolutions]
* [http://www.unv.org/ United Nations Volunteers]
* [http://www.un.org/webcast/index.asp# United Nations Webcasts]
* [http://www.un.org/Overview/rights.html Universal Declaration of Human Rights]
* [http://www.un.org/aroundworld/map/ World Map of UN websites and locations]

;Other
* [http://www.unrol.org/ United Nations Rule of Law], the United Nations' centralized website on the [[rule of law]].
* [http://www.warcrimes.info/ Documents and Resources on UN, War, War Crimes and Genocide]
* [http://www.eyeontheun.org/ Eye on the UN]–A Project of the Hudson Institute New York and the Touro Law Center Institute for Human Rights
* [http://uiuc.libguides.com/content.php?pid=43017 United Nations] LibGuide resources from the [[University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign]] Library
* [http://www.direct.gov.uk/Gtgl1/GuideToGovernment/InternationalBodies/InternationalBodiesArticles/fs/en?CONTENT_ID=4003089&amp;chk=aPi/oF History of the United Nations]–UK Government site
* [http://www.innercitypress.com/ Inner City Press]–UN related news.
* {{PDFlink|[http://www.un.org/summit2005/presskit/fact_sheet.pdf Outcomes of the 2005 World Summit]|82.9 KB}}
* [http://www.un.int/ Permanent Missions To The United Nations]
* [http://www.undemocracy.com/ Searchable archive of UN discussions and votes]
* [http://ckan.net/tag/read/un List of UN datasets on CKAN, a registry of open data]
* [http://www.usip.org/un/ Task Force on United Nations]–[[U.S. Institute of Peace]]
* [http://www.unwatch.org/ UN watch]–non-governmental organization based in Geneva whose mandate is to monitor the performance of the United Nations by the yardstick of its own Charter.
* [http://www.una.org.uk/ United Nations Association of the UK: independent policy authority on the UN]
* [http://www.ipsnews.net/new_focus/unitednations/index.asp United Nations: Inside the Glass House]–Independent news reports by the news agency [[Inter Press Service]]
* [http://elearning.security-research.at/flash/un United Nations eLearning Unit] created by ISRG–University of Innsbruck
* [http://library.msstate.edu/content/templates/?a=429&amp;z=83 United Nations Research Guide from the Mississippi State University Libraries]
* [http://www.globalpolicy.org/ Website] of the [[Global Policy Forum]], an independent think-tank on the UN
* [http://worldinbalance.net/intagreements/unsystem.php United Nations System explained at Spencer Hofmans' Center for a World in Balance]
* [http://www.angelfire.com/wizard/trainingnet/unw.htm United Nations Offices Worldwide]
{{United Nations|state=uncollapsed}}
{{United Nations' relations with its Member States|state=autocollapse}}
{{International organizations|state=autocollapse}}
{{Nobel Peace Prize Laureates 2001-2025}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}

[[Category:United Nations| ]]&lt;!--Keep at start of list (eponymous category) --&gt;
[[Category:Nobel Peace Prize laureates]]
[[Category:Organizations awarded Nobel Prizes]]
[[Category:Organizations based in New York City]]
[[Category:1945 establishments]]

{{Link FA|vi}}
{{Link FA|ur}}
{{Link FA|th}}
{{Link FA|sr}}
{{Link FA|nl}}

[[kbd:Лъэпкъ Зэгуэтхэр, ЛъЗ]]
[[af:Verenigde Nasies]]
[[als:Vereinte Nationen]]
[[am:የተባበሩት መንግስታት]]
[[ab:Еидгылоу Амилаҭқәа Рорганизациа]]
[[ar:الأمم المتحدة]]
[[an:Organización d'as Nacions Unitas]]
[[roa-rup:Natsiile Unite]]
[[frp:Organisacion des Nacions unies]]
[[ast:Organización de les Naciones Xuníes]]
[[az:Birləşmiş Millətlər Təşkilatı]]
[[bn:জাতিসংঘ]]
[[zh-min-nan:Liân-ha̍p-kok]]
[[map-bms:Perserikatan Bangsa-Bangsa]]
[[be:Арганізацыя Аб'яднаных Нацый]]
[[be-x-old:Арганізацыя Аб’яднаных Нацыяў]]
[[bcl:Nagkakasararong Nacion]]
[[bi:Yunaeted Nesen]]
[[bg:Организация на обединените нации]]
[[bar:UNO]]
[[bo:མཉམ་འབྲེལ་རྒྱལ་ཚོགས།]]
[[bs:Ujedinjeni narodi]]
[[br:Aozadur ar Broadoù Unanet]]
[[ca:Organització de les Nacions Unides]]
[[cv:Пĕрлешнĕ Нацисен Организацийĕ]]
[[ceb:Hiniusang mga Nasod]]
[[cs:Organizace spojených národů]]
[[cy:Y Cenhedloedd Unedig]]
[[da:Forenede Nationer]]
[[de:Vereinte Nationen]]
[[dv:އެކުވެރި ދައުލަތްތައް]]
[[nv:Nahasdzáán Bikáaʼgi Kéyah Naaznilgo Ałhidadiidzooígíí]]
[[et:Ühinenud Rahvaste Organisatsioon]]
[[el:Οργανισμός Ηνωμένων Εθνών]]
[[es:Organización de las Naciones Unidas]]
[[eo:Unuiĝintaj Nacioj]]
[[ext:Nacionis Unias]]
[[eu:Nazio Batuen Erakundea]]
[[fa:سازمان ملل متحد]]
[[hif:United Nations]]
[[fo:ST]]
[[fr:Organisation des Nations unies]]
[[fy:Feriene Naasjes]]
[[fur:Organizazion des Nazions Unidis]]
[[ga:Náisiúin Aontaithe]]
[[gv:Ny h-Ashoonyn Unnaneysit]]
[[gl:ONU]]
[[gan:聯合國]]
[[gu:યુનાઈટેડ નેશન્સ]]
[[hak:Lièn-ha̍p-koet]]
[[ko:국제 연합]]
[[ha:Majalisar Ɗinkin Duniya]]
[[hy:Միավորված Ազգերի Կազմակերպություն]]
[[hi:संयुक्त राष्ट्र]]
[[hsb:Zjednoćene narody]]
[[hr:Ujedinjeni narodi]]
[[io:Unioninta Nacioni]]
[[ilo:Dagiti Nagkaykaysa a Pagilian]]
[[id:Perserikatan Bangsa-Bangsa]]
[[ia:Organisation del Nationes Unite]]
[[os:Иугонд Нациты Организаци]]
[[is:Sameinuðu þjóðirnar]]
[[it:Organizzazione delle Nazioni Unite]]
[[he:האומות המאוחדות]]
[[jv:Perserikatan Bangsa-Bangsa]]
[[kl:FN]]
[[kn:ಸಂಯುಕ್ತ ರಾಷ್ಟ್ರ ಸಂಸ್ಥೆ]]
[[krc:Бирлешген Миллетлени Организациясы]]
[[ka:გაერთიანებული ერების ორგანიზაცია]]
[[kk:Біріккен Ұлттар Ұйымы]]
[[kw:Kenedhlow Unys]]
[[rw:Umuryango w’Abibumye]]
[[sw:Umoja wa Mataifa]]
[[kv:Ӧтувтчӧм Войтыръяслӧн Котырныс]]
[[ht:ONI]]
[[ku:Neteweyên Yekbûyî]]
[[lad:Nasyones Unidas]]
[[la:Consociatio Nationum]]
[[lv:Apvienoto Nāciju Organizācija]]
[[lb:Vereent Natiounen]]
[[lt:Jungtinių Tautų Organizacija]]
[[lij:Organizzaçion de e Naçioin Unïe]]
[[li:Verenigde Naties]]
[[jbo:gunma natmi]]
[[lmo:Urganizaziun di Naziun Ünii]]
[[hu:Egyesült Nemzetek Szervezete]]
[[mk:Обединети Нации]]
[[mg:Firenena Mikambana]]
[[ml:ഐക്യരാഷ്ട്രസഭ]]
[[mt:Ġnus Magħquda]]
[[mr:संयुक्त राष्ट्रे]]
[[arz:الأمم المتحده]]
[[ms:Pertubuhan Bangsa-Bangsa Bersatu]]
[[mwl:Naciones Ounidas]]
[[mn:Нэгдсэн Үндэстний Байгууллага]]
[[my:ကုလသမဂ္ဂ]]
[[nah:Tlacetilīlli Tlācatiyān]]
[[nl:Verenigde Naties]]
[[ne:संयुक्त राष्ट्र संघ]]
[[new:संयुक्त राष्ट्र संघ]]
[[ja:国際連合]]
[[no:FN]]
[[nn:Dei sameinte nasjonane]]
[[nov:Unionati Nationes]]
[[oc:Organizacion de las Nacions Unidas]]
[[mhr:Иктыш ушнышо Наций-влак Организаций]]
[[uz:Birlashgan Millatlar Tashkiloti]]
[[pfl:Verainde Nadsione]]
[[pnb:یونائیٹڈ نیشنز]]
[[pap:Nashonan Uni]]
[[ps:ملګري ملتونه]]
[[km:អង្គការសហប្រជាជាតិ]]
[[pms:Organisassion dle Nassion Unìe]]
[[nds:Vereente Natschonen]]
[[pl:Organizacja Narodów Zjednoczonych]]
[[pt:Organização das Nações Unidas]]
[[crh:Birleşken Milletler Teşkilâtı]]
[[ro:Organizația Națiunilor Unite]]
[[rm:Organisaziun da las Naziuns unidas]]
[[qu:Huñusqa Nasyunkuna]]
[[rue:Орґанізація Зъєдноченых Націй]]
[[ru:Организация Объединённых Наций]]
[[sah:Холбоһуктаах Нациялар Тэрилтэлэрэ]]
[[se:Ovttastuvvan Našuvnnat]]
[[sc:ONU]]
[[sco:Unitit Naitions]]
[[stq:Fereende Natione]]
[[sq:Organizata e Kombeve të Bashkuara]]
[[scn:Nazziuni Uniti]]
[[si:එක්සත් ජාතීන්ගේ සංවිධානය]]
[[simple:United Nations]]
[[ss:Mhlabuhlangene]]
[[sk:Organizácia Spojených národov]]
[[sl:Organizacija združenih narodov]]
[[so:Qaramada Midoobay]]
[[ckb:نەتەوە یەکگرتووەکان]]
[[sr:Организација уједињених нација]]
[[sh:Ujedinjeni narodi]]
[[fi:Yhdistyneet kansakunnat]]
[[sv:Förenta nationerna]]
[[tl:United Nations]]
[[ta:ஐக்கிய நாடுகள்]]
[[tt:Берләшкән Милләтләр Оешмасы]]
[[te:ఐక్యరాజ్య సమితి]]
[[th:สหประชาชาติ]]
[[tg:Созмони Милали Муттаҳид]]
[[tr:Birleşmiş Milletler]]
[[uk:Організація Об'єднаних Націй]]
[[ur:اقوام متحدہ]]
[[ug:بىرلەشكەن دۆلەتلەر تەشكىلاتى]]
[[vec:ONU]]
[[vi:Liên Hiệp Quốc]]
[[fiu-vro:Ütistünüq Rahvaq]]
[[wa:Organizåcion des Nåcions uneyes]]
[[zh-classical:聯合國]]
[[war:Nagkaurusa nga mga Nasod]]
[[wo:Kureelu Mbootayu Xeet yi]]
[[wuu:联合国]]
[[yi:פאראייניגטע פעלקער]]
[[yo:Àgbájọ àwọn Orílẹ̀-èdè Aṣòkan]]
[[zh-yue:聯合國]]
[[bat-smg:Jongtėniu Tautū Uorganėzacėjė]]
[[zh:联合国]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
