<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31814455" ns="0" title="2011 Spanish protests"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Civil Conflict
| title = 2011 Spanish protests
| partof = the [[2008–2011 Spanish financial crisis]], the [[European sovereign debt crisis]]
| image = [[Image:Puertadelsol2011.jpg|300px]]
| caption = The [[Puerta del Sol]] square in [[Madrid]] became a focal point and a symbol during the protests. In the picture, on 20 May.
| date = {{start date|2011|05|15}} &amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; ''ongoing'' ({{age in days|month1=5 |day1=15 |year1=2011}} days)
| place = {{flag|Spain}}, worldwide
| coordinates =
| causes = [[Unemployment]], economic conditions, [[welfare]] cuts, [[political corruption]], [[particracy]], [[Bipartidism|unrepresentative bipartidism]]
| status = Ongoing
| goals = [[Participatory democracy|Upgrade democracy]],{{Vague|date=June 2011}} reduce influence of economic powers in politics
| result =
| methods = [[Demonstration (people)|Demonstration]]s, [[civil disobedience]], [[civil resistance]], [[rioting]], [[sit-ins]], [[online activism]], [[protest camp]]s [[Occupation (protest)|occupation]]s
| side1 =
| side2 =
| side3 =
| leadfigures1 =
| leadfigures2 =
| leadfigures3 =
| howmany1 =
| howmany2 =
| howmany3 =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| casualties3 =
| casualties_label = Injuries and arrests
| injuries = over 310{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}
| notes =
}}
The '''2011 Spanish protests''', also referred to as the '''15-M Movement'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tahrir Square in Madrid: Spain's Lost Generation Finds Its Voice|url=http://www.spiegel.de/international/europe/0,1518,763581,00.html|accessdate=7 July 2011|newspaper=Spiegel}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the '''Indignants movement''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rainsford |first=Sarah |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-15315270 |title=BBC News - Spain's 'Indignants' lead international protest day |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date= 14 October 2011|accessdate=2011-10-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; are a series of ongoing&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpais.com/articulo/english/Majority/of/Spaniards/support/15-M/movement/elpepueng/20110627elpeng_4/Ten Majority of Spaniards support 15-M movement]&lt;/ref&gt; demonstrations in [[Spain]] whose origin can be traced to [[social networks]] and  [[Democracia Real Ya|Real Democracy NOW]] ({{lang-es|Democracia Real YA}}) among other civilian digital platforms and 200 other small associations.&lt;ref name=&quot;art1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/16/actualidad/1305578500_751064.html |title=Movimiento 15-M: los ciudadanos exigen reconstruir la política (15-M Movement: citizens demand political reconstruction) |publisher=Politica.elpais.com |date=2011-05-17 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The protests started on 15 May with an initial call in 58 Spanish cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;democraciarealya&quot;&gt;¡Democracia Real Ya!; ''[http://democraciarealya.es/?page_id=580 Calls]''&lt;/ref&gt;

The series of protests demands a radical change in [[Politics of Spain|Spanish politics]], as protesters do not consider themselves to be represented by any traditional party nor favoured by the measures approved by politicians.&lt;ref name=&quot;art3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/17/opinion/1305625181_425614.html |title=Indignados en la calle  |publisher=EL PAÍS |date=2011-05-17 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Spanish media have related the protests to the [[2008–2009 Spanish financial crisis|economic crisis]], [[Stéphane Hessel]]'s ''[[Time for Outrage!]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;art3&quot;/&gt; the [[NEET]] troubled generation and current protests in the Middle East and North Africa,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/go/em/fr/-/news/world-europe-13437819 |title=BBC News - Spanish youth rally in Madrid echoes Egypt protests |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-05-18 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[2010–2011 Greek protests|Greece]],&lt;ref name=&quot;SKAI xnaria&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.skai.gr/news/greece/article/170468/oi-aganaktismenoi-diadilonoun-stis-ellinikes-poleis-/ |title=Στα χνάρια των Ισπανών αγανακτισμένων (On the footsteps of the Spanish 'indignados') |language=Greek |date=26 May 2011 |publisher=www.skai.gr |accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[2011 Portuguese protests|Portugal]] ([[2011 Portuguese protests|Geração à rasca]] movement)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = &quot;Geração à rasca&quot; é referência para Espanha - JN| accessdate = 2011-05-22| url = http://www.jn.pt/PaginaInicial/Mundo/Interior.aspx?content_id=1857358}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the [[2009 Icelandic financial crisis protests|Icelandic protest and riots in 2009]].&lt;ref name=&quot;art9&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/17/actualidad/1305661201_570313.html |title=Los sábados de Islandia llegaron al 15-M (Icelandic saturdays appear on 15-M) |publisher=Politica.elpais.com |date=2011-05-17 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The movement drew inspiration from 2011 revolutions in Tunisia, Egypt and uprisings in 1968 France, and Greece in 2008.  The protests were staged close to the [[Spanish local and regional elections, 2011|local and regional elections]], held on 22 May.

Even though protesters form a heterogeneous and ambiguous group, they share a strong rejection of [[unemployment]], [[welfare]] cuts, Spanish politicians, the current [[two-party system]] in Spain between the [[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party]] and the [[People's Party (Spain)|People's Party]], as well as the current [[political system]], [[capitalism]], [[bank]]s and bankers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|first=EFE|title=Miles de personas exigen dejar de ser 'mercancías de políticos y banqueros'|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/15/espana/1305478324.html|accessdate=7 July 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;  [[political corruption]] and firmly support what they call basic rights: home, work, culture, health and education.&lt;ref name=&quot;art2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/espana/manifestacion/indignados/reune/varios/miles/personas/toda/Espana/elpepuesp/20110515elpepunac_12/Tes |title=La manifestación de 'indignados' reúne a varios miles de personas en toda España ('&amp;#39;Outraged'&amp;#39; demonstration brings together several thousand people in Spain) |publisher=Elpais.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to statistics published by [[RTVE]], the Spanish public broadcasting company, between 6.5 and 8 million Spaniards have participated in these protests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Ipsos Public Affairs' statistic about Spanish protests |url=http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110806/mas-seis-millones-espanoles-han-participado-movimiento-15m/452598.shtml |accessdate=5 August 2011|publisher =RTVE}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Since the beginning of the ongoing economic crisis, Spain has been hit hard with one of the highest unemployment rates in [[Europe]], reaching a [[eurozone]] record of 21.3%. The number of unemployed people in Spain stood at 4,910,200 at the end of March 2011, up about 214,000 from the previous quarter,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Unemployment in Spain rises sharply to 21.3 percent|url=http://www.eitb.com/news/detail/646452/unemployment-spain-rises-sharply-213-percent/|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Eitb}}&lt;/ref&gt;  while youth unemployment rate stands at 43.5%, the highest in the [[European Union]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=El desempleo juvenil alcanza en España su mayor tasa en 16 años|url=http://www.lavozdegalicia.es/dinero/2011/04/02/0003_201104G2P26991.htm|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=La Voz de Galicia}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In order to reduce the jobless rate, the government approved in September 2010 a sweeping overhaul of the labour market designed to slash unemployment and revive the economy. Main trade unions [[CCOO]] and [[Unión General de Trabajadores]] (UGT), as well as minor ones, rejected the plan as it made it easier and cheaper for employers to hire and fire workers. Trade unions called for a general strike on September 29, the first one in a decade in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Spain overhauls labour market, as unions plan general strike|url=http://au.finance.yahoo.com/news/Spain-overhauls-labour-market-afp-3494097690.html?x=0|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Yahoo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Manifestacio22gener.jpg|thumb|Demonstration in Barcelona on January 22 against the raise in the retirement age]]
During the rest of the year, the government went on with economic reforms and in January 2011, it agreed to raise the retirement age from 65 to 67 after reaching an agreement with the main trade unions. Despite that, [[anarcho-syndicalist]] unions and other minors ones rejected the plan and called for a strike on January 27 in [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]], [[Catalonia]] and the [[Basque Country (autonomous community)|Basque Country]]. Demonstrations were also held in Madrid and ended up in clashes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Spain retirement age going to 67 in austerity push|url=http://www.deseretnews.com/article/700104907/Spain-retirement-age-going-to-67-in-austerity-push.html|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Deseret News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hoy huelga en Euskadi, Navarra, Galicia y Catalunya|url=http://www.publico.es/dinero/358382/hoy-huelga-en-euskadi-navarra-galicia-y-catalunya|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Público}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The raise was also rejected by the majority of Spaniards.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Un 79% de los españoles, en contra del retraso de la jubilación a los 67 años|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/04/06/espana/1302086451.html|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although not related to economics, Spanish media have reported the pass in February of the so-called ''Sinde law'', an anti-internet download law which allows for a judicial order to close down any web page which shows links to illegal or illegal downloads of copyright content, as one of the reasons that led to the protests. The law, approved by PSOE, PP and [[Convergence and Union]], has been heavily criticized in Spanish forums and social networks and after the pass an anonymous campaign called #nolesvotes appeared on the Internet, calling on refusing to vote any of the parties that passed the law.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Congress has given the definitive approval to the Law Sinde|url=http://www.spainreview.net/index.php/2011/02/16/congress-has-given-the-definitive-approval-to-the-law-sinde/|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Spain Review}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to 15 May and the following camp-sites many demonstrations were held in Spain during 2011 and serving as a precedent of the protests, such as the April 7 demonstration in [[Madrid]] by the student group Youth without Future ({{lang-es|Juventud Sin Futuro}}) which gathered 5,000 people. Spanish media has linked the demonstrations with the 2008-2009 protests against the [[Bologna Process]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=El movimiento del 15-M, balance y perspectivas tras un mes de actividad|url=http://www.rebelion.org/noticia.php?id=131275|accessdate=20 August 2011|newspaper=Rebelion}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Portuguese [[2011 Portuguese protests|&quot;Geração à Rasca&quot;]] movement, also served as an inspiration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jn.pt/PaginaInicial/Mundo/Interior.aspx?content_id=1857358}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Portuguese movement attracted many Spaniards and Portuguese residents in Spain who protested in front of the Portuguese embassy in Madrid.

==Demands of Democracia Real Ya==
Democracia Real Ya and the protesters have stated that their demands of the Spanish government are: elimination of privileges for the political class, measures to combat unemployment, measures to promote rights to housing, measures to improve public services in teaching, health, and public transport, increased regulation of the banking industry, implementation of new fiscal measures, measures in favor of citizen’s rights and participatory democracy, and a reduction in military spending.  Together they believe that this culmination will bring about the change in society needed to assist those who are not among the country's privileged elite.

==Organising the protests==
{{Main|Democracia real Ya}}
On January 2011, the digital platform Democracia real YA was created on Spanish [[social networks]] and forums.&lt;ref name=sacudesistema&gt;{{cite news|title=El 15 -M sacude el sistema|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/reportajes/-M/sacude/sistema/elpepusocdmg/20110522elpdmgrep_1/Tes|accessdate=26 May 2011|newspaper=El País}}&lt;/ref&gt; Using [[Twitter]] and Facebook it called &quot;the unemployed, poorly paid, the subcontractors, the precarious, young people...&quot; to take the streets on 15 May in the following places (in alphabetical order): [[A Coruña]], [[Albacete]], [[Algeciras]], [[Alicante]], [[Almería]], [[Arcos de la Frontera]], [[Badajoz]], [[Barcelona]], [[Bilbao]], [[Burgos]], [[Cáceres, Spain|Cáceres]], [[Cadiz]], [[Castellón de la Plana|Castellón]], [[Ciudad Real]], [[Córdoba (Spain)|Córdoba]], [[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]], [[Ferrol, Spain|Ferrol]], [[Figueres]], [[Fuengirola]], [[Granada]], [[Guadalajara (Spain)|Guadalajara]], [[Huelva]], [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]], [[Lanzarote]], [[La Palma]], [[León (Spain)|León]], [[Las Palmas de Gran Canaria]], [[Lleida]], [[Logroño]], [[Lugo]], [[Madrid]], [[Málaga]], [[Menorca]], [[Mérida, Spain|Mérida]], [[Monforte de Lemos]], [[Murcia]], [[Ourense]], [[Oviedo]], [[Palma, Majorca|Palma]], [[Pamplona]], [[Plasencia]], [[Ponferrada]], [[Puertollano]], [[Salamanca]], [[San Sebastián]], [[Santa Cruz de Tenerife]], [[Santander, Cantabria|Santander]], [[Santiago de Compostela]], [[Seville]], [[Soria]], [[Tarragona]], [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], [[Torrevieja]], [[Ubrique]], [[Valencia, Spain|Valencia]], [[Valladolid]], [[Vigo]], [[Vitoria-Gasteiz|Vitoria]] and [[Zaragoza]].&lt;ref name=&quot;democraciarealya&quot;&gt;¡Democracia Real Ya!; ''[http://democraciarealya.es/?page_id=580 Convocatorias]'', 15 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el 18 de mayo de 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; That same day, small demonstrations in support of the Spanish ones were organised in [[Dublin]], [[Lisbon]], [[Amsterdam]], [[Istanbul]], [[Bologna]], [[London]] and [[Paris]].

Before the demonstrations, ''Democracia real YA'' staged several symbolic events, such as the occupation of a bank in Murcia on 13 May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=La Plataforma 15M ocupa una oficina del Banco Santander|url=http://www.tercerainformacion.es/spip.php?article24984|accessdate=30 May 2011|newspaper=Tercera Información}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At the time of the demonstrations, the Democracia real YA website had the support of over 500 diverse associations, whilst continuing to reject any collaboration from any [[political party]] or [[labour union]], defending the protests’ independence from all institutionalised political ideology.

==Protests==
===May===
====15 May====
The first protest was called under the motto &quot;''we are not goods in the hands of politicians and bankers''&quot; and was focused on opposition to what the protesters called &quot;antisocial means in the hands of bankers&quot;, partly referring to the changes made in 2010 to contain the [[2010–2011 European sovereign debt crisis|ongoing European sovereign debt crisis]] through bailout of the banks, which the Spanish society saw as responsible for the crisis, while at the same time the government kept announcing social program cutbacks. Protesters also demanded more democracy, a new electoral law and end to political corruption as well as other claims, such as [[Nationalization|banks nationalisation]].
[[File:Democracia real YA Madrid.jpg|thumb|Demonstration in Madrid]]
Protests took place in all the planned cities. According to Democracia real YA, 50,000 people gathered in Madrid alone. The [[National Police Corps of Spain|National Police]], however, placed the number at 20,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://democraciarealya.es/ |title=Comunicado de prensa de &quot;Democracia Real Ya&quot; |publisher=Democraciarealya.es |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The march started in [[Plaza de Cibeles]] and ended in [[Puerta del Sol]], where several manifestos were read. Also according to the organisers, 15,000 gathered in the demonstration in Barcelona, which ended in front of the [[Parliament of Catalonia]]. In other cities such as Granada, up to 5,000 protesters showed up and the protest took place without incident, except for an exchange of insults between some protesters and members of the Fraternity of the Virgin of Rosario, whose procession overlapped with the end of the protest after the latter had gone on longer than expected. In Santiago de Compostela, a group of eight hooded people smashed several banks and local businesses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=1.000 personas se manifiestan en Compostela reclamando Democracia Real Ya|url=http://santiago.redperiodista.es/2011/05/15/1-000-personas-se-manifiestan-en-compostela-reclamando-democracia-real-ya/|accessdate=7 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Juan Enrique Gómez|url=http://www.ideal.es/granada/v/20110516/granada/personas-toman-calles-granada-20110516.html |title=5.000 personas toman las calles de Granada para exigir &quot;democracia real, ya&quot;. |publisher=Ideal.es |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://www.ideal.es/granada/20110516/local/granada/democracia-real-ya-bronca-cruzarse-procesion-aurora-201105161109.html |title=Democracia Real Ya: Bronca al cruzarse con la procesión de la Virgen del Rosario. Ideal |publisher=Ideal.es |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is estimated that the protesters that day were followed by about 130,000 people throughout Spain.&lt;ref name=comunicado17&gt;{{cite news|title=Comunicado de Democracia real YA|url=http://www.insurgente.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=7288:comunicado-de-prensa-de-democracia-real-ya&amp;catid=232:convocatorias-y-documentos&amp;Itemid=446|accessdate=2 June 2011|newspaper=insurgente.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of Madrid's demonstration, protesters blocked the [[Gran Vía]] avenue and staged a peaceful sit-in in Callao street, to which police responded beating protesters with truncheons. As a result of the clashes and the following riots, several shop windows were destroyed and trash containers burnt. 24 people were arrested and five police officers injured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=24 detenidos y cinco policías heridos en la protesta antisistema de Madrid|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/16/madrid/1305498063.html|accessdate=2 June 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On 17 May, Democracia real YA condemned the &quot;brutal police repression&quot; and rejected having any relation with the incidents.&lt;ref name=comunicado17/&gt; After the incidents, a group of 100 people headed to [[Puerta del Sol]] and started the camping in the middle of the square, what would result in the following day's protests.&lt;ref name=acampadasol1&gt;{{cite news|title=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/16/madrid/1305541852.html|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/16/madrid/1305541852.html|accessdate=2 June 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sol power: the 15-M story so far|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/english/Sol/power/the/15-M/story/far/elpepueng/20110804elpeng_3/Ten|accessdate=20 August 2011|newspaper=El País}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====16 May====
During the day, several people gathered in Puerta del Sol and decided to stay in the square until the elections on 22 May. Meanwhile, 200 people started a similar action in Barcelona's [[Plaça Catalunya]], although police had first tried to disperse the crowds. That day the tag #spanishrevolution, as well as other ones related to the protests, became a trending topic in the social-network [[Twitter]].&lt;ref name=acampadasol1/&gt;

====17 May====
[[File:Acampada Sol ph03.jpg|thumb|right|17 May, at night in Puerta del Sol]]
On the early hours of the morning, police cleared the Puerta del Sol square and removed the 150 people who had camped out. Two protesters were arrested and one injured.&lt;ref name=17may1&gt;{{cite news|title=El colectivo 'Democracia real ya' anuncia más protestas tras el desalojo de Sol|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/17/madrid/1305630397.html|accessdate=20 August 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Spanish police break up Madrid sit-in|url=http://www.efeamerica.com/309_hispanic-world/1129105_spanish-police-break-up-madrid-sit-in.html|accessdate=20 August 2011|newspaper=EFE}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a response to the eviction and police violence, protesters called via [[SMS]], Facebook and Twitter for a mass response at 8pm in several Spanish squares.&lt;ref name=17may1/&gt; Large groups of demonstrators returned to protest in various cities, standing apart from the group in Madrid. This time the protests were not called together by Democracia real YA.&lt;ref name=&quot;art6&quot; /&gt; In a few cities, the police permitted the protesters to camp out, as took place in [[A Coruña]], where more than 1,000 people gathered.&lt;ref name=&quot;art4&quot;&gt;La Voz de Galicia; ''[http://www.lavozdegalicia.es/espana/2011/05/17/00031305646837535184832.htm Varias acampadas reavivan las movilizaciones de «indignados» en Galicia]'', 17 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; In Madrid, more than 12,000 people gathered and about 200 protesters organized into an [[Popular assembly|assembly]], during which they decided to organize themselves for spending the night in the square, creating cleaning, communication, extension, materials and legal committees. Previously they had received a great deal of help from small businesses in the form of food.&lt;ref name=&quot;art6&quot;&gt;El Diario Montañés; ''[http://www.eldiariomontanes.es/rc/20110517/mas-actualidad/nacional/cientos-indignados-vuelven-tomar-201105172059.html Miles de 'indignados' vuelven a tomar la Puerta del Sol]'', 17 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;art5&quot;&gt;Pérez-Lanzac, Carmen, de El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/17/actualidad/1305623988_837783.html Indignados y acampados]'', 17 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;art10&quot; /&gt;

Protests and nighttime camp-outs took place in 30 cities around Spain, including Barcelona and Valencia.&lt;ref name=&quot;art7&quot;&gt;El Mundo; ''[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/17/espana/1305649774.html Acampadas en cadena hasta el próximo 22-M]''&lt;/ref&gt; The protests gained the support of people in the [[United Kingdom]], who announced that they would sit outside of the Spanish embassy from 18 until 22 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;art7&quot; /&gt; The protest in Plaza del Sol on the night of the 17 May consisted of about 4,000 people according to the authorities. 300 of them stayed until the dawn of 18 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;art10&quot;&gt;Muñoz Lara, Aurora, de El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/16/actualidad/1305579962_497160.html El movimiento 15-M abarrota Sol]''&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier that day, dozens of people gathered in front of the court in Madrid where the people arrested during the 15 May demonstration had been held. All detainees were released.&lt;ref name=17may1/&gt;

====18 May====
[[File:Acampada Sol ph18.jpg|thumb|right|Sol, 18 May, early morning]]
In Madrid, the protesters put up a large tarp canopy beneath which they passed out signs with the intention of spending the night there between the 17 and 18 May. According to a reporter from ''[[El País]]'', many of them wore carnations, much as took place during the [[Carnation Revolution|Portuguese Carnation Revolution]]. In addition, they organized a food stand which provided food donated by local businesses and set up a [[webcam]] to provide news from Plaza del Sol through the website ''[[Ustream.tv]]''. The protesters were advised not to drink alcohol or to organize into groups of more than 20 people, as these acts could provoke a legal police crackdown.

The police ordered protesters to disperse in Valencia, Tenerife and Las Palmas. During the evacuation of the Plaza del Carmen in Granada there were 3 arrests.&lt;ref name=&quot;art10&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ideal.es; ''[http://www.ideal.es/granada/20110517/local/granada/democracia-real-convoca-acampada-201105171745.html La Policía Nacional retira a los 'indignados' acampados en la Plaza del Carmen de Granada]'' (consultado el 18 de mayo de 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ideal.es; ''[http://www.ideal.es/granada/20110518/local/granada/tres-indignados-detenidos-desalojo-plaza-carmen-granada-201105180936.html Tres 'indignados' detenidos tras el desalojo en la Plaza del Carmen de Granada]'' (consultado el 18 de mayo de 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; Speeches continued on throughout the afternoon. The protests grew to include [[León, Spain|León]], [[Seville]], where a camp out started as of 19 May,&lt;ref name=&quot;art10&quot; /&gt; and in other provincial capitals and cities of Spain. Support groups were created on social networks for each camp out through the social network [[Twitter]] and other national and international networks. ''Google Docs'' and other servers began to receive download requests for documents needed to legally request permission for new protests.

In the morning, the ''Federación de Asociaciones de Vecinos de Barcelona'' (FAVB) announced their support of the protests in Barcelona.&lt;ref&gt;Federación de Asociaciones de Vecinos de Barcelona (en catalán); ''[http://www.favb.cat/ La Favb crida a recolzar l'acampada de plaça Catalunya]'', 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; In Madrid, an activist created a flag that depicts a sun and a hand over a black background, which serves as an emblem for the protests, according to Belén Hernández at ''El País''.

In addition to ''The Washington Post'', which covered the protests on 15 May, news reports took place on the 18th in various media outlets, among them ''[[Le Monde]]'', the most widely circulated newspaper in French, in an article which noted the rarity of such large scale protests in Spain.&lt;ref&gt;''Le Monde'' (en francés); ''[http://www.lemonde.fr/europe/article/2011/05/18/les-jeunes-espagnols-dans-la-rue-pour-clamer-leur-ras-le-bol_1523749_3214.html Les jeunes Espagnols dans la rue pour clamer leur ras-le-bol]'', 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; The German newspaper, ''[[Der Spiegel]]'', noted the importance of the effects of what has been called &quot;The Facebook Generation&quot; and the youth on the protests.&lt;ref&gt;''Der Spiegel'' (en alemán); ''[http://www.spiegel.de/politik/ausland/0,1518,763385,00.html Job-Misere treibt Spaniens Jugend auf die Straße], 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; The Portuguese paper ''[[Jornal de Notícias]]'', reported on the protests in Madrid on 18 May as soon as it was known that they had been prohibited.&lt;ref&gt;''Jornal de Notícias'' (en portugués); ''[http://www.jn.pt/PaginaInicial/Mundo/Interior.aspx?content_id=1855373 Manifestação proibida no centro de Madrid]'', 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; And ''[[The New York Times]]'', which cited ''El País'' and noted the strong organization of the protesters, particularly the 200 people who had been placed in charge of security and the use of Twitter to ensure dissemination of their message.&lt;ref name=&quot;art12&quot;&gt;''The New York Times'' (en inglés); ''[http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/05/18/protesters-rally-in-madrid-despite-ban/?smid=tw-thelede&amp;seid=auto Protesters Rally in Madrid Despite Ban]'', 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el 19 de mayo de 2011).&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Washington Post'' again reported on the protests in Puerta del Sol, giving them the name of a &quot;revolution&quot; and estimating the presence of 10,000 people on Wednesday afternoon's protest and comparing it with those in [[Cairo]]'s [[Tahrir Square]], which had recently ousted [[Egypt]]ian president [[Hosni Mubarak]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Flock |first=Elizabeth |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/blogpost/post/spanish-revolution-thousands-gather-in-madrids-puerta-del-sol-square/2011/05/18/AFLzpZ6G_blog.html |title=Spanish ‘revolution’: Thousands gather in Madrid’s Puerta del Sol Square |publisher=The Washington Post |date=2011-05-18 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[BBC]] made reference to the peaceful nature of the protests in Puerta del Sol.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

The various protests agreed to hold meetings between their organizing committees each day at 1pm and [[Popular assembly|assemblies]] at 8pm.&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/18/actualidad/1305725291_126850.html Un ágora instalado en el kilómetro 0]'', 18 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt;

In the evening, the President of the Regional Electoral Committee of Madrid issued a statement declaring the protests illegal because &quot;calls for a responsible vote can change the results of the elections&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Elpais.es; ''[http://www.elpais.com/elpaismedia/ultimahora/media/201105/18/espana/20110518elpepunac_2_Pes_PDF.pdf Acuerdo de la Junta Electoral Provincial de Madrid]''&lt;/ref&gt; Police units at Sol, however, received orders from the Government Delegation not to take out any further action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ecodiario.eleconomista.es/politica/noticias/3080803/05/11/La-Policia-tiene-la-orden-de-no-desalojar-Sol.html |title=La Policía tiene la orden de no desalojar Sol - 3080803 - EcoDiario.es |publisher=Ecodiario.eleconomista.es |date=2011-05-18 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Protestas Puerta del Sol - Madrid - mayo 2011 - 01.jpg|thumb|Protests and tents in Madrid on 20 May.]]
[[File:Manifestations des indignés à Bastille 03.jpg|thumb|Since 18 May support protests have occurred daily in several major cities outside Spain, including Dublin, Berlin, London and Paris (shown here on 20 May).]]

====20 May====
According to Britain's ''[[The Guardian]]'', &quot;tens of thousands&quot; had camped out in Madrid and throughout the country on the night of 19–20 May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Giles Tremlett in Madrid |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/may/20/spain-bans-protest-ahead-election?intcmp=239 |title=Spain bans young protesters ahead of elections|publisher=The Guardian |date= 20 May 2011|accessdate=2011-05-22 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[United Left (Spain)|United Left]] appealed the Electoral Board's decision to ban the protests before Spain's Supreme Court,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpais.com/articulo/espana/Supremo/estudia/recurso/IU/prohibicion/concentraciones/elpepu/20110520elpepunac_13/Tes IU ha presentado ante el Tribunal Supremo un recurso contra la decisión de la Junta Electoral Central], 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; to which the State Prosecution presented its arguments shortly after.&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/20/actualidad/1305898023_980425.html El Supremo delibera sobre el recurso de IU, al que se opone la Fiscalía]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- Durante la habitual rueda de prensa de los viernes, posterior al [[Consejo de Ministros]], el vicepresidente primero y ministro del Interior, [[Alfredo Pérez Rubalcaba]], se refirió sobre las concentraciones del sábado y domingo, diciendo que : «lo que vamos a hacer es cumplir la ley».&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/20/actualidad/1305895031_420384.html El Gobierno sugiere que no desalojará Sol por la fuerza si no hay actos violentos]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt;

El comité legal de los ''indignados'' de Madrid informó a los medios de comunicación que habían decidido no convocar protestas el sábado, pero que sí lo harían el viernes 20 de mayo. Matizó que aunque el sábado no hubiera manifestaciones oficiales, podrán reflexionar colectivamente «evitando hacer referencia al voto y a los partidos políticos».&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/18/actualidad/1305752933_013731.html El Movimiento 15-M mantiene el pulso ante el veto a las manifestaciones]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt;

A lo largo del día los manifestantes de varias ciudades presentaron sendos nuevos recursos.&lt;ref&gt;Europa Press; ''[http://www.europapress.es/sociedad/noticia-15m-indignados-tenerife-presentan-recurso-contra-decision-junta-electoral-20110520191210.html Los 'indignados' de Tenerife presentan un recurso contra la decisión de la Junta Electoral]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; Mientras tanto, ''El País'' facilitaba en su página web una dirección donde pueden comprobarse la cantidad de ciudades en todo el mundo en que ha habido concentraciones o éstas se han convocado. El día 20 por la mañana eran 166 ciudades y por la tarde ya había 357.&lt;ref&gt;www.thetechnoant.info ''[http://www.thetechnoant.info/campmap/ Mapa de las concentraciones a 20 de mayo]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

A lo largo del día los acampados de Madrid, organizados, editaron un plano de la plaza diferenciando las distintas zonas y sedes de los comités,&lt;ref&gt;Europa Press; ''[http://www.europapress.es/sociedad/noticia-15m-acampados-editan-plano-diferentes-zonas-conforman-pequeno-poblado-20110520183428.html Los acampados editan un plano con las diferentes zonas que conforman su pequeño 'poblado']'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; crearon dos nuevas comisiones, una de ''Respeto'', que entre otras cosas velará por que no se beba en la plaza para que la policía no pueda aplicar la [[ley antibotellón]],&lt;ref&gt;Europa Press; ''[http://www.europapress.es/sociedad/noticia-15-comision-respeto-encarga-velar-buen-funcionamiento-acampada-20110520190012.html Una comisión de Respeto se encarga de velar por el buen funcionamiento de la acampada]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; y otra de ''Infantil'' encargada de cuidar de los niños,&lt;ref name=&quot;artpais&quot;&gt;El País; ''[http://www.elpais.com/articulo/espana/Sol/pide/madera/elpepuesp/20110520elpepunac_24/Tes Sol pide &quot;más madera&quot;]'', 20 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; y crearon normas para los medios de comunicación, a los que impidieron grabar en ciertos momentos y zonas.&lt;ref name=&quot;artpais&quot; /&gt; En Barcelona la ''[[plaza Cataluña]]'' se dividió en tres zonas, llamadas simbólicamente ''Tahir'', ''Islandia'' y ''Palestina'', donde se celebraron actuaciones de distinto tipo; entre otras cosas escenificaron cómo sería una posible carga policial.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.europapress.es/sociedad/noticia-15m-comisiones-plaza-catalunya-barcelona-reunen-planear-reaccion-desalojo-20110520145028.html&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

===== Appeal before the Supreme Court =====
Spain's public broadcaster, [[RTVE]] reported that the State Prosecutor upheld the decision taken by the Central Electoral Board&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110520/fiscalia-respalda-decision-jec-prohibir-movilizaciones-sabado-domingo/433768.shtml RTVE.es &quot;La Fiscalía respalda la decisión de la JEC de prohibir las movilizaciones el sábado y el domingo&quot;] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt; to ban the rallies.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpais.com/elpaismedia/ultimahora/media/201105/20/espana/20110520elpepunac_2_Pes_PDF.pdf Documento oficial de la desestimación del recurso presentado por Izquierda Unida]'', 20 de mayo de 2011] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the police announced that they had been given instructions not to dissolve the crowd at Puerta del Sol provided that there was no disturbance of the peace.&lt;ref&gt;Europa Press; ''[http://www.europapress.es/nacional/noticia-15m-policia-no-desalojara-puerta-sol-mientras-no-haya-incidentes-20110520203416.html La Policía no desalojará la Puerta del Sol mientras no haya incidentes]'', 20 de mayo de 2011] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Appeal before the [[Constitutional Court of Spain|Tribunal Constitucional]] =====
[[RTVE]] later reported that the country's Constitutional Court had been deliberating since 7.30pm whether to review an appeal against the decision of the Central Electoral Board.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110518/minuto-minuto-manifestacion-acampada-movimiento-15/433335.shtml &quot;Sala Segunda del Constitucional estudia desde las 19.30 hora peninsular si admite a trámite el recurso de amparo interpuesto por un abogado de Murcia contra la decisión de la JEC.&quot;] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt; At 10.08 pm (local time), RTVE informed that the Constitutional had rejected the appeal on the formality that the appellant had not appealed first to the Supreme Court.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110518/minuto-minuto-manifestacion-acampada-movimiento-15/433335.shtml 22.08 &quot;El Tribunal Constitucional rechaza admitir el recurso del abogado de Murcia porque no ha agotado todas las vías.] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt;

At 22:47 [[United Left (Spain)|United Left]] announced it would appeal the Supreme Court's decision before the Tribunal Constitucional. They had until midnight.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110518/minuto-minuto-manifestacion-acampada-movimiento-15/433335.shtml RTVE: 22.47 Izquierda Unida presentará antes de la medianoche un recurso de amparo ante el Tribunal Constitucional] Retrieved 2011-05-20&lt;/ref&gt;

At around 23:00, some 16,000 people (according to the police) and 19,000 (according to other sources) were gathered at and around Puerta del Sol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=RTVE.es&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;MADRID&amp;nbsp; |url=http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110518/minuto-minuto-manifestacion-acampada-movimiento-15/433335.shtml |title=Minuto a minuto: Los acampados debaten hoy el futuro del movimiento 15M tras las elecciones |publisher=RTVE.es |date=2011-05-18 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====21 May====
In Madrid, Barcelona, Malaga and other cities 21 May started with a minute of silence followed by cheers and applause.&lt;ref name=&quot;politica.elpais.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/20/actualidad/1305920877_763863.html |title=El movimiento 15-M acampará una semana más en Sol &amp;#124; Política &amp;#124; EL PAÍS |publisher=Politica.elpais.com |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; Smaller cities, such as Granada, decided to start before midnight to avoid disturbing the neighbors. These protests occurred even though protests on the day before elections are banned.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.voanews.com/english/news/Thousand-Defy-Protest-Ban-to-Rally-Ahead-of-Spanish-Elections-122384549.html|title=Thousand Defy Protest Ban to Rally Ahead of Spanish Elections|publisher=Voice of America|date=21 May 2011|accessdate=21 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Around 28,000 people, according to the police, crowded Puerta del Sol and the neighboring streets despite the prohibition. Other cities also gathered large numbers of people: 15,000 in Malaga, 10,000 in Valencia, 6,000 in Zaragoza, 4,000 in Seville, 1,500 in Granada, 800 in Almeria, 600 in Cadiz, 200 in Huelva, around 100 in Jaen. 8,000 people gathered in Barcelona, 1,000 in Vigo, 3,000 in Bilbao, 2,000 in Oviedo, 2,000 in Gijón, around 800 in Avilés, 3,000 in Palma.&lt;ref name=&quot;politica.elpais.com&quot;/&gt;

There were demonstrations in other European cities, with 300 protesters participating in London, 500 in Amsterdam,&lt;ref name=&quot;SPANISH WORKERS PUT CLASS BACK ON THE AGENDA&quot;&gt;[http://radecon.blogspot.com/2011/05/spanish-workers-put-class-back-on.html].&lt;/ref&gt; 600 in Brussels and 200 in Lisbon. Minor demonstrations occurred in Athens, Milan, Budapest, Tangiers, Paris, Berlin, Vienna and Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;politica.elpais.com&quot;/&gt;

====22 May====
[[image:Praza15deMaio.jpg|''Indignados'' change the occupied squares' names across Spain  (22 May, Praza 15 de Maio en [[A Coruña]])|thumb|right|170px]]
Just after 14:00 on election day, the ''indignados'' (the outraged) that had gathered at Puerta del Sol announced they had voted to stay at least another week, until noon on 29 May.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110522/indigandos-mantiene-camapadas-durante-jornada-electoral/433957.shtml RTVE: 'Los &quot;indignados&quot; de Sol deciden mantener las protestas al menos una semana más'] Retrieved 2011-05-22&lt;/ref&gt; Early analysis of the [[Spanish local and regional elections, 2011|nationwide elections]], won by the [[People's Party (Spain)|People's Party]], suggested the protest movement could have contributed to losses for the ruling [[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party|PSOE]],&lt;ref&gt;Yahoo! Noticias; ''[http://es.noticias.yahoo.com/soci%C3%B3logos-califican-22-m-tsunami-pero-no-ensayo-104409097.html Sociólogos califican 22-M de 'tsunami' pero no de ensayo general]'', 23 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt; and to increased numbers of spoilt or blank votes, which reached record levels.&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/23/actualidad/1306104164_099870.html Aumentan el voto en blanco y nulo en más de un punto]'', 23 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt;

====24 May====
In [[Murcia]], some 80 people gained access to the headquarters of the television channel [[7 Región de Murcia]], avoiding security staff, in order to read a manifesto denouncing [[media manipulation]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.europapress.es/sociedad/noticia-amp-15m-centenar-indignados-entran-sede-tv-murciana-leer-manifiesto-20110524135910.html |title=AMP.- 15M.- Un centenar de 'indignados' entran la sede de la TV murciana para leer un manifiesto |work=[[Europa Press]] |date=24 de mayo de 2011 |accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, some 30 people gained unobstructed entry to the [[Tarragona]] office of the [[Ministry of Economy and Finance (Spain)|Ministry of Economy and Finance]] and shouted slogans against the political and economic systems, before moving to several financial sites in the city centre to do the same.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.diaridetarragona.com/tarragona/055956/treintena/indignados/irrumpen/delegacion/hacienda/tarragona |title=Una treintena de 'indignados' irrumpen en la delegación de Hacienda de Tarragona |work=Diari de Tarragona |date=24 May 2011 |accessdate=26 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====25 May====
In [[Málaga]], the [[Ministry of Defence (Spain)|Ministry of Defence]] decided to relocate various activities for [[Armed Forces Day]] planned for Friday 27. Protesters had already been occupying the Plaza de la Constitución, where the events were scheduled to take place, for eight days.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cadenaser.com/espana/articulo/defensa-cambia-ubicacion-varios-actos-dia-fuerzas-armadas-15-m/csrcsrpor/20110525csrcsrnac_10/Tes Defensa cambia de ubicación varios actos del Día de las Fuerzas Armadas por el 15-M], Cadena SER&lt;/ref&gt;

====27 May====
{{external media
|width=300px
|image1=[http://www.flickr.com/photos/acampadabcnfoto/sets/72157626817385780/with/5764238511/ P. Catalunya clash gallery]
|video1={{YouTube|id=aDFdwUY2Oks|title=P. Catalunya clash (video 1)}}
|video2={{YouTube|id=9sKmFo-4Jc4|title=P. Catalunya clash (video 2)}}
|video3={{YouTube|id=3wcAujlR-6M|title=P. Catalunya clash (video 3)}}
|video4={{YouTube|id=gg_tDPkP8fw|title=P. Catalunya clash (video 4)}}
}}
At approximately 7am on 27 May a more serious incident occurred when the city council of [[Barcelona]] decided to send 350 police officers from the [[Mossos d'Esquadra]] and another one hundred or so from the [[Guàrdia Urbana de Barcelona|Guàrdia Urbana]] to temporarily vacate [[Plaça de Catalunya, Barcelona|Plaça de Catalunya]] so that it could be cleaned ahead of the final of the [[2011 UEFA Champions League Final|Champions League final]] on 28 May, in which [[FC Barcelona]] were playing.&lt;ref name=&quot;lne2705&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.lne.es/espana/2011/05/27/govern-defiende-carga-actuacion-mossos/1080981.html |title=El Govern defiende la carga y la actuación de los Mossos |work=La nueva España |accessdate=28 May 2011 |date=27 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rainsford|first=Sarah|title=Anger as Spanish police move on Barcelona protest camp|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-13582863|accessdate=29 May 2011|newspaper=BBC|date=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting violent clash ended in 121 light injuries and provoked new calls to protest in all squares still occupied across Spain.&lt;ref name=&quot;lne2705&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;art15&quot;&gt;The Washington Post; ''[http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/121-injured-as-spanish-police-clash-with-protesters-in-makeshift-camp/2011/05/27/AGSJimCH_story.html Scores injured as Spanish police clash with protesters in makeshift camp]'', 27 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of those injured suffered bruises and open wounds caused by police officers' truncheons, and one protester leaving with a broken arm.&lt;ref name=&quot;art15&quot; /&gt; By shortly after midday those protesters vacated had already returned to the square.&lt;ref&gt;El País; ''[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/05/27/actualidad/1306489864_137130.html Los 'indignados' recuperan la plaza de Catalunya tras la retirada de la policía]'', 27 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar incidents also occurred in [[Lleida]] and [[Sabadell]], where Mossos d'Esquadra officers dismantled the protesters' encampments.&lt;ref name=&quot;lne2705&quot;/&gt; According to police figures, more than 12,000 people gathered in Barcelona through the course of the day, angry about the earlier actions of the police, painting their hands white and carrying flowers as symbols of protest. They demanded, among other things, the resignation of the head of the Mossos d'Esquadra, Felip Puig. They also claimed that following the incident the encampment would likely not be taken down on Sunday 28, as had previously been stated.&lt;ref&gt;El Mundo; ''[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/27/barcelona/1306518767.html La dureza policial multiplica la indignación en Barcelona]'', 28 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt;

The clearing of the Barcelona camp was broadcast live by two Spanish television channels, including [[Antena 3 (Spain)|Antena 3]], and was also widely dispersed through social networks such as [[Twitter]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.europapress.es/tv/noticia-antena-impone-cobertura-desalojo-indignados-barcelona-mossos-20110527171123.html |title=Antena 3 se impone en la cobertura del desalojo de 'indignados' en Barcelona por los Mossos |work=[[Europa Press]] |date=27 May 2011|accessdate=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news  |url=http://www.siliconnews.es/2011/05/27/bcnsinmiedo-lidera-la-lista-de-trending-topics-mundial/ |título=#bcnsinmiedo lidera la lista de “trending topics” mundial |work=Silicon News |date=27 May 2011 |accessdate=28 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Catalonia|Catalan]] ombudsman opened an investigation into the incident to check if police action was disproportionate and if it violated citizens' rights.&lt;ref&gt;El Mundo; ''[http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/05/27/barcelona/1306498356.html El defensor del pueblo catalán investiga si los Mossos iban bien identificados en el desalojo]'', 27 May 2011 (accessed the same day).&lt;/ref&gt;

[[image:Madrid - Acampada Sol 2011 43.JPG|'Listen to the people's wrath', Puerta del Sol, Sunday morning, 29 May.|thumb|right|170px]]

===June===
====2 June====
At least 40 people gathered in [[Montcada i Reixac]], Barcelona and prevented court officials from serving a family with the order to leave their home immediately, and protesting against banks repossessing people's homes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Aplazan el segundo intento de desahuciar a una familia|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/06/02/barcelona/1307036610.html|accessdate=14 July 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====4 June====
Representatives from 53 assemblies around Spain gathered in a mass assembly in Puerta del Sol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Asamblea nacional de 'indignados' en el kilómetro cero|url=Aplazan el segundo intento de desahuciar a una familia|accessdate=14 July 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====8 June====
In Madrid, hundreds of people gathered in front of the [[Congreso de los Diputados]], with a police barrier preventing them from entering the building. Demonstrations in front of the Parliament are banned in Madrid, but the protest finished without incidents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Spanish youths take anti-crisis protests to parliament|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5hgUMzNYu_3cmZpucroDZoOBkZhgQ?docId=CNG.4b51b056239693ce4c4888dc9ef63302.e01|work=AFP|publisher=AFP|accessdate=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Valencia, dozens of people decided to stay in front of the regional Parliament.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Diario de una revolución en Valencia: Centenares de indignados pasan la noche frente al Parlamento valenciano|url=http://www.elperiodicodeaqui.com/noticias/diario-una-revolucion-en-valencia-centenares-indignados-pasan-noche-frente-pa/5317|work=El Periodico de Aqui|publisher=El Periodico de Aqui|accessdate=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Barcelona, around 50 people protested outside the Catalan Parliament against Felip Puig.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Medio centenar de personas exigen ante el Parlament la dimisión de Puig|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/06/08/barcelona/1307549312.html|accessdate=13 June 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====9 June====
{{external media
|video1={{YouTube|id=sqRjjpCBFMo|title=Valencia clash}}
}}
In the morning, police clashed with protesters in [[Valencia, Spain|Valencia]], injuring 18.&lt;ref&gt;[http://channel6newsonline.com/2011/06/18-injured-as-spanish-protesters-clash-with-police/ &quot;18 injured as Spanish protesters clash with police&quot;], Channel 6 News. 9 June 2011. Accessed 11 June 2011&lt;/ref&gt; As a response of the police violence, demonstrators called for a protest in the city later that day, which gathered around 2,000 people. Support demonstrations were held in Barcelona and Madrid, the latter ending up in front of the Parliament for a second night. Barcelona's protest finished in front of the Popular Party's office.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Indignados' de Barcelona protestan ante la sede del PP por las cargas de Valencia|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/06/09/barcelona/1307649974.html|accessdate=13 June 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Los 'indignados' abandonan la protesta frente al Congreso|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/06/09/espana/1307638845.html|accessdate=13 June 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====12 June====
On Sunday, 12 June, four weeks after the protests had begun, protestors in the [[Puerta del Sol]] in [[Madrid]], began to leave, dismantling the &quot;acampada,&quot; packing up tents, libraries, shops,  and removing protest signs from surrounding sites.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.elpais.com/articulo/espana/indignados/movimiento/15-M/levantan/lema/nos/vamos/nos/expandimos/elpepuesp/20110612elpepunac_1/Tes &quot;Los indignados del movimiento 15-M se levantan bajo el lema &quot;No nos vamos, nos expandimos&quot;, El País, 12 June 2011. Accessed 12 June 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

====14 June====
Thousands of people assembled in front of Barcelona's [[Parc de la Ciutadella]] and organised themselves to spend the night, in order to start on the following day a blockade of the [[Catalan Parliament]] (which is inside the park) and prevent deputies from entering the building, where the debate on the 2011 budget, which results in cuts in education and health, was to take place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Los 'indignados' acampan ante los agentes de policía que custodian el 'Parlament'|url=http://www.cadenaser.com/espana/articulo/indignados-acampan-agentes-policia-custodian-parlament/csrcsrpor/20110614csrcsrnac_21/Tes|accessdate=17 July 2011|newspaper=Cadena Ser}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====15 June====
[[File:Parlamentcamp barcelona.jpg|thumb|Police confront demonstrator outside Catalan Parliament on 15 June]]
Clashes between protesters and Mossos d'Esquadra occurred in the early hours of the morning when hundreds of protesters gathered in front of the police cordon, while officers fired plastic bullets in order to disperse a group of protesters who had set up barricades using rubbish containers. Hours later, scuffles broke out as Mossos de Esquadra pushed protesters back so the deputies who arrived on foot could get in. Some deputies, such as former Minister of Labour [[Celestino Corbacho]] were jostled, heckled and sprayed on their way in, while other used used police helicopters to get to the parliament. Among those, the president of Catalonia [[Artur Mas]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Catalan politicians take to the skies to avoid protesters|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/jun/15/catalan-politicians-protesters-spanish-barcelona|accessdate=16 July 2011|newspaper=The Guardian|location=London|date=15 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite that lawmakers managed to enter the Catalonian Parliament and the scheduled session started with a 15 minute delay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Una veintena de diputados acorralados se ha tenido que refugiar en una comisaría|url=http://www.elmundo.es/elmundo/2011/06/15/barcelona/1308126903.html|accessdate=17 July 2011|newspaper=El Mundo}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By midday, most of the protestes remained outside the parliament, while some confronted police with rocks and bottles. At least 36 people were injured, 12 of them Mossos d'Esquadra, and 6 people were arrested.

The protest was criticized by politicians across the country, and during a press conference, Mas warned of a possible &quot;legitimate use of force&quot; in case demonstrators stayed outside the Parliament and called on the public to be understanding. Some politicians went so far as dennouncing an attempted &quot;[[coup d'etat]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=15M Barcelona rechaza la violencia y CiU habla de un golpe de estado encubierto|url=http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20110616/15m-barcelona-rechaza-violencia-vivida-frente-parlament-ciu-habla-golpe-estado-encubierto/440559.shtml|accessdate=17 July 2011|newspaper=RTVE}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Acampadabcn, the organiser of the event, and Democracia real YA &quot;rejected&quot; the use of violence but denounced the criminalisation of the movement by the media.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Democracia real Ya' rechaza a la minoría que no representa el espíritu pacífico del movimiento|url=http://www.nacionred.com/derechos-y-libertades/democracia-real-ya-rechaza-a-la-minoria-que-no-representa-el-espiritu-pacifico-del-movimiento|accessdate=17 July 2011|newspaper=Nación Red}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On Twitter and other social networks, many users suggested the possibility that secret police, infiltrated to cause the violence, started most of the clashes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=#Spanishrevolution blockades Parliament in Barcelona, violence tinges the #15M movement #europeanrevolution|url=http://wlcentral.org/node/1892|accessdate=17 July 2011|newspaper=WL Central}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the day, demonstrators left the area and organised a march towards [[Plaça de Sant Jaume]].

====19 June====
A massive demonstration was carried out in almost 80 Spanish cities and towns. It is believe that more than a half million people rallied that day.

===July===
====1 July====
Dozens of people protested outside Barcelona's town hall during the swearing-in ceremony of Spanish [[Convergence and Union]]'s candidate [[Xavier Trias]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Xavier Trias es proclamado alcalde de Barcelona|url=http://www.lavozdeasturias.es/politica/xavier-trias-proclamado-alcalde-barcelona_0_509349204.html|accessdate=16 July 2011|newspaper=La Voz de Asturias}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====27 July====
{{external media
|video1={{YouTube|id=KCu_PQr4zYY|title=Paseo del Prado clash (video 1)}}
|video2={{YouTube|id=xSFXktMs9_s|title=Paseo del Prado clash (video 2)}}
}}
{{expand section|date=August 2011}}

===August===
====2 August====
When the 12 June assembly decision was made to dismantle the tent city in Puerta del Sol, the assembly decided by [[Consensus democracy|consensus]] to leave behind an information booth, called PuntoSol, where people interested in the movement could find information about how it had been [[Decentralization|decentralized]] to the neighborhood assemblies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By asambleapopulardevillaverde on 16 octubre, 2011 |url=http://madrid.tomalosbarrios.net/ |title=Toma los barrios &amp;#124; Asamblea Popular de Madrid: En la Asamblea Popular de Madrid nos coordinamos más de 120 asambleas populares madrileñas. Este portal es uno de los medios de comunicación colectiva de los que nos hemos dotado. ¡Todo el poder para las asambleas! |publisher=Madrid.tomalosbarrios.net |date= |accessdate=2011-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; An [[Guerrilla gardening|organic garden]] surrounding one of the fountains in Sol was also left behind in the square. At 6:30 AM on 2 August, the [[National Police Corps of Spain|national]] and [[Municipal police (Spain)|municipal police]] evicted the remaining protestors at the information booth and cleaning crews dismantled PuntoSol&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Los indignados toman las calles de Madrid contra el desalojo de Sol'|url=http://www.publico.es/espana/389877/los-indignados-toman-las-calles-de-madrid-contra-el-desalojo-de-sol|accessdate=3 August 2011|newspaper=ElPúblico}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the organic garden.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='La policía desaloja InfoSol y la acampada del Paseo del Prado'|url=http://madrid.tomalaplaza.net/2011/08/02/la-policia-desaloja-infosol-y-la-acampada-del-paseo-del-prado/}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time they evicted the tent city which had sprung up on the Paseo del Prado. The police then blocked off all access to Sol including [[Madrid Metro|Metro]] and [[Cercanías]] and filled the square with over 300 police, including riot police, and 50 police vans.&lt;ref name=&quot;elpais1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title='El cierre de Sol reaviva el 15-M y lleva a 5.000 indignados al centro de Madrid'|url= http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/08/02/actualidad/1312267048_030311.html|accessdate=3 August 2011|newspaper=EL PAÍS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response, protestors called an immediate convergence to try to access the square. The heavy police presence impeded their entry. The protestors, then numbering over 5000,&lt;ref name=&quot;elpais1&quot;/&gt; decided to turn to the streets, demonstrating from Callao, [[Gran Vía]], [[Plaza de Cibeles|Cibeles]], Paseo del Prado, all the way to the Congress of Deputies building, where they were met with more riot police, police barricades and police vans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Tensión en Sol'|url=http://www.lasextanoticias.com/noticias/ver/tension_en_sol/385723|accessdate=3 August 2011|newspaper=laSexta}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protests then turned to [[Madrid Atocha railway station|Atocha]] and once more to Sol where they were met with an overwhelming police presence. The decision was then made by the protestors to occupy [[Plaza Mayor, Madrid|Plaza Mayor]] where an emergency [[Participatory democracy|participatory]] assembly was held in order to decide what to do.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Dos detenidos durante la marcha improvisada por el centro de Madrid'|url=http://www.publico.es/espana/389893/dos-detenidos-durante-la-marcha-improvisada-por-el-centro-de-madrid|accessdate=3 August 2011|newspaper=ElPúblico}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ultimately, protestors set up a temporary information booth in Plaza Mayor while some decided to stay there camping through the night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title='Desalojada la veintena de 'indignados' que permanecía en la Plaza Mayor de Madrid'|url=http://www.cadenaser.com/espana/articulo/desalojada-veintena-indignados-permanecia-plaza-mayor-madrid/serpro/20110803csrcsrnac_2/Tes|accessdate=3 August 2011|newspaper=cadenaSER}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the night, two people were arrested, and released the day after.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Dos detenidos durante la marcha improvisada por el centro de Madrid|url=http://www.publico.es/espana/389893/dos-detenidos-durante-la-marcha-improvisada-por-el-centro-de-madrid|accessdate=13 August 2011|newspaper=Público}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====3 August====
During the Plaza Mayor assembly, it was decided that on the next day, an assembly would be held at [[Jacinto Benavente]] square at 6pm in order to attempt entering the square. The square was then cordoned off by police and metro and train stations closed, while police asked for identification to anyone trying to pass into the square. Police also asked customers from shops around Sol to close their businesses several hours earlier than usual. As the attempt failed, the protestors decided to start a new march from Atocha two hours later. The march from Atocha grew larger as people began passing through Cibeles and up the Gran Vía heading toward Puerta del Sol, where officers and police vans, prevented the demonstrators from marching up [[San Jerónimo]] street.&lt;ref name=elpais_sol_siege&gt;{{cite news|title=Third day of Sol state of siege|url=http://www.elpais.com/articulo/english/Third/day/of/Sol/state/of/siege/elpepueng/20110804elpeng_9/Ten|accessdate=14 August 2011|newspaper=El País}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Police and about 4,000 demonstrators then played a game of cat-and-mouse as the demonstrators tried to enter Puerta del Sol through different streets. There were several moments of tension at different points and by 11pm, the groups of demonstrators disbanded and retreated to Callao Square, where an assembly was held and it was decided that a demonstration would be held at 12pm on the following day and there would be another attempt to enter Sol at 8pm.&lt;ref name=elpais_sol_siege/&gt;

====4 August====
{{external media
|video1={{YouTube|id=pTo81hJxRtY|title=Carga policial frente al Ministerio del Interior}}
}}
Police charged against protesters in front of Interior Ministry in Madrid.&lt;ref&gt;[http://politica.elpais.com/politica/2011/08/04/actualidad/1312444001_073563.html La policía carga contra cientos de indignados en el Ministerio del Interior] - El País {{es}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{expand section|date=October 2011}}
{{-}}

===October===
====15 October====
As part of the [[15 October 2011 global protests|15 October movement]], (related to the [[&quot;Occupy&quot; protests]]), hundreds of thousands marched in Madrid and other cities. 

Half million people took part in the demonstration that filled the street and marched from Alcala and Cibeles toward [[Puerta del Sol]] square in [[Madrid]], home of the &quot;[[Indignants]]&quot; movement, of which this has merged, according to [[Europa Press (news agency)|Europapress media agency]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=om een reactie te plaatsen! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3OoYcSbUm0I&amp;feature=player_embedded |title=El movimiento 15-M paraliza el mundo |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-10-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; There 50 thousand people remained and most of them participated in the activities and general assembly organised. Barcelona, had as many as a quarter million.

==Political response==
The demonstration triggered reactions from the main [[political parties]], who after debating issued statements on 16 May. On 15 May, the day of the first demonstration, almost every party was willing to be quoted on the situation.&lt;ref&gt;Ríos, Sara, de 20minutos; ''[http://www.20minutos.es/noticia/1051617/0/reacciones/partidos/manifestaciones/ La mayoría de partidos miran para el otro lado y evitan pronunciarse sobre las protestas]'', 16 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el 28 de mayo de 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Jaime Mayor Oreja]], [[Member of the European Parliament]] representing the [[People's Party (Spain)|Partido Popular]], was critical of the protesters’ alleged intention of not casting ballots on the forthcoming election. So was [[Spanish Socialist Workers' Party]] (PSOE) member and [[Minister of Public Works and Transport]] [[José Blanco López|José Blanco]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lavozdegalicia.es/espana/2011/05/16/00031305564962696760777.htm |title=&quot;Democracia real ya&quot; hace reaccionar a los dos principales partidos |publisher=Lavozdegalicia.es |date= |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[United Left (Spain)|United Left]] had a positive view of the protesters’ demands, but admitted not having been capable of connecting to them. The communist party’s political coordinator [[Cayo Lara]], defended the protesters’ refusal to become a “lost generation” and was critical of their removal from the [[Puerta del Sol]] on 16 May.&lt;ref&gt;La Voz de Galicia; ''[http://www.lavozdegalicia.es/portada/2011/05/17/00031305656501088227314.htm Cayo Lara: «Zapatero ha traído más beneficios para los amos y la porra para los de abajo»], 17 de mayo de 2011 (consultado el mismo día).&lt;/ref&gt; Other politicians, such as [[José Antonio Griñán]], showed sympathy for the protests, while insisting in that not voting is not a solution. [[Esteban González Pons]], general vicesecretary of the Partido Popular linked the demonstrations to the “antisystem far left”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.20minutos.es/noticia/1052657/0/pons/democraciareal/extrema-izquierda/ |title=González Pons vincula a parte de 'Democracia Real Ya' con la &quot;extrema izquierda del PSOE&quot;|publisher=20minutos.es |date=2011-05-17 |accessdate=2011-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former [[Spanish Prime Minister]] [[Felipe González]] compared the protests, which he considered &quot;an extraordinarily important phenomenon&quot;,&lt;ref name=hartos/&gt; with those [[2010–2011 Middle East and North Africa protests|staged in Arab countries]],&lt;ref&gt;Ideal.es; ''[http://www.ideal.es/granada/rc/20110518/espana/felipe-gonzalez-compara-indignados-201105180256.html Felipe González compara a los 'indignados' con los protagonistas de las revueltas árabes]'' 18 de mayo de 2011. Retrieved 2011-05-18.&lt;/ref&gt; pointing out that &quot;in the Arab world they are demanding  the right to vote while here they are saying that voting is pointless&quot;.&lt;ref name=hartos&gt;Ideal.es; ''[http://www.publico.es/espana/376885/felipe-gonzalez-sobre-los-indignados-estan-hartos-los-partidos-no-deberian-descalificarlos-elecciones2011 Felipe González, sobre los 'indignados': &quot;Están hartos, los partidos no deberían descalificarlos&quot;]'' 17 de mayo de 2011 Retrieved 2011-05-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 July 2011, Nobel prize winning economist [[Joseph Stiglitz]] participated to the &quot;I Foro Social del 15M&quot; organised in [[Madrid]] (Spain) expressing his support to the 2011 Spanish protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;15M SPEECH&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z2iKj-1v2Cc|title=Joseph Stiglitz apoya el movimiento 15-M|accessdate=2011-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; During an informal speech, he made a brief review of some of the problems in Europe and in the United States, the serious unemployment rate and the situation in Greece. &quot;This is an opportunity for economic contribution social measures,&quot; argued Stiglitz, who made a critical speech about the way authorities are handling the political exit to the crisis. He encouraged those present to respond to the &quot;bad ideas&quot;, not with indifference, but with &quot;good ideas&quot;. &quot;This does not work, you have to change it,&quot; he said.

== See also ==
{{Commons category|Spanish Protests 2011}}
{{Div col|3}}
* [[15 October 2011 global protests]]
* [[2010–2011 Greek protests]]
* [[2010–2011 Greek protests|2011 Greek protests]]
* [[2011 Chilean protests]]
* [[2011 Israeli social justice protests]]
* [[2011 Portuguese protests|&quot;Geração à Rasca&quot;]]
* [[2011 United Kingdom anti-austerity protests]]
* [[Democracia Real Ya|Real democracy NOW]] ({{lang-es|Democracia real YA}})
* [[Kitchenware Revolution|Iceland Kitchenware Revolution]]
* [[&quot;Occupy&quot; protests]]
* [[Occupy Wall Street]]
* [[Protests of 1968]]
* [[Reacts]]
* [[Time for Outrage!]]
{{Div col end}}
{{Portal bar|Social movements|Politics|Business and economics|Society|Spain}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
* [http://tomalaplaza.net/ Official blog]
* [http://takethesquare.net takethesquare.net]
*[http://www.democraciarealya.es/ ¡Democracia real Ya! Official Web]
*[http://www.soltv.tv SolTV] (live streaming)
*[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/directo1/ RTVE (Spanish public broadcaster) Webcam: El 15M mantiene el pulso y convoca una concentración el sábado] RTVE Webcam over Puerta del Sol (live)
*[http://es.scribd.com/doc/57091274/Democracia-Real-YA-El-19-de-Junio-Volvemos-a-Tomar-Las-Calles Brochure protests convened on June 19]
*[http://www.counterpunch.org/gelderloos06072011.html Article] on the Spanish protests by [[Peter Gelderloos]]
*[http://www.kaosenlared.net/noticia/video-reportaje-inside-15m-48h-ls-indignads &quot;Inside 15m: 48h with the indignants&quot;] is a documentary (English subtitles) about the Spanish protests made by the people's assemblies of Madrid.
*[http://crimethinc.com/texts/recentfeatures/barc.php Timeline, political analysis, and eyewitness reportage] of the Spanish protests on [[crimethinc]]
* [http://www.booksandideas.net/Republican-Reflections-on-the-15-M.html Republican Reflections on the 15-M movement] by Philip Pettit

{{Anti-government protests in the 21st century}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Spanish Protests, 2011}}
[[Category:2011 in international relations]]
[[Category:Arab Spring]]
[[Category:2011 elections in Spain]]
[[Category:2011 riots]]
[[Category:Protests in Spain|2011]]
[[Category:Protest marches]]
[[Category:Impact of the Arab Spring]]
[[Category:2011 protests]]

{{Link FA|eu}}
[[ar:الاحتجاجات الإسبانية 2011]]
[[ast:Protestes de mayu de 2011 n'España]]
[[bs:Protesti u Španiji 2011]]
[[bg:Майски протести в Испания]]
[[ca:Protestes d'Espanya de 2011]]
[[cs:Protesty ve Španělsku 2011]]
[[de:Proteste in Spanien 2011]]
[[es:Protestas en España de 2011]]
[[eo:Protestoj de majo 2011 en Hispanio]]
[[eu:M-15 mugimendua]]
[[fr:Mouvement des Indignés]]
[[gl:Protestas de maio de 2011 en España]]
[[ko:2011년 스페인 시위]]
[[it:Proteste in Spagna del 2011]]
[[nl:15 mei-beweging]]
[[pl:Protesty w Hiszpanii (2011)]]
[[pt:Protestos de 2011 na Espanha]]
[[sh:Protesti u Španiji 2011]]
[[fi:Espanjan mielenosoitukset 2011]]
[[sv:Protesterna i Spanien 2011]]
[[tl:Mga protesta sa Espanya ng Mayo 2011]]
[[vi:Biểu tình Tây Ban Nha 2011]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
