<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="318864" ns="0" title="The Evergreen State College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Evergreen State|the state with that nickname (in which this college is located)|Washington (U.S. state)}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2008}}
{{Infobox University
 |name              = The Evergreen State College
 |native_name       =
 |image_name        = EvergreenStateCollegeSeal.png
 |image_size        = 200px
 |caption           =
 |latin_name        =
 |motto             = ''Omnia Extares''
 |mottoeng          = Let it all hang out
 |established       = 1967
 |closed            =
 |type              = Public
 |affiliation       =
 |endowment         = [[United States dollar|US$]]29,985,851
 |officer_in_charge =
 |chairman          =
 |chancellor        =
 |president         = Dr. Thomas L. Purce
 |vice-president    =
 |superintendent    =
 |provost          = Dr. [[Michael Zimmerman (biologist)|Michael Zimmerman]]
 |vice_chancellor   =
 |rector            =
 |principal         =
 |dean              =
 |director          =
 |head_label        =
 |head              =
 |faculty           = 267
 |staff             = 495
 |students          = 4,800
 |undergrad         = 4,468
 |postgrad          = 332
 |doctoral          =
 |other             =
 |city              = [[Olympia, Washington|Olympia]]
 |state             = [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]
 |province          =
 |country           = [[United States of America]]
 |coor              =
 |campus            = [[Suburban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|1000|acre|ha}}
 |former_names      =
 |free_label        =
 |free              =
 |sports            = 9 Varsity Teams
 |colors            = Green &amp; White {{colorbox|green}}{{colorbox|white}}
 |colours           =
 |nickname          = [[Geoduck]]s
 |mascot            =
 |athletics         = [[National Association of Intercollegiate Athletics|NAIA]] [[Cascade Collegiate Conference]]
 |affiliations      =
 |website           = [http://www.evergreen.edu/ www.evergreen.edu]
 |logo              = [[File:Wrdmrk EVERGREEN.png|250px]]
 |footnotes         =
}}

'''The Evergreen State College''' is an accredited public [[liberal arts college]] and a member of the [[Council of Public Liberal Arts Colleges]]. It is located in [[Olympia, Washington]], USA. Founded in 1967, Evergreen was formed to be an experimental and non-traditional college. Faculty issue [[narrative evaluations]] of students' work rather than grades, and Evergreen organizes most studies into largely [[interdisciplinary]] classes that generally constitute a full-time course load. The current Evergreen President is Thomas L. (Les) Purce and its Board Chair is [[Christopher Hedrick]].

Evergreen offers a [[Bachelor of Arts]] in Liberal Arts and [[Bachelor of Science]], Master of [[Environmental Studies]], [[Master of Public Administration]], [[Master of Education]], and [[Master in Teaching]]. In 2009, there were 4,696 students, 4,364 of whom were undergraduates, and 243 faculty members.&lt;ref&gt;Evergreen Fact Page: http://www.evergreen.edu/institutionalresearch/factpage.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The Evergreen State College has had a large influence on the culture and economy of Olympia as well as its surrounding areas.

==History==
In 1964, a report was issued by the Council of Presidents of Washington State baccalaureate institutions stating that another college was needed in the state to balance the geographical distribution of the existing state institutions.  This report spurred the 1965 Washington legislature to create the Temporary Advisory Council on Public Higher Education to study the need and possible location for a new state college.

In 1965-66, the Temporary Advisory Council on Public Higher Education (assisted by Nelson Associates of New York) concluded &quot;at the earliest possible time a new college should be authorized&quot;, to be located at a suburban site in Thurston County within a radius of approximately {{convert|10|mi|km}} from Olympia.

Evergreen's enabling legislation - HB 596 (Chapter 47, Laws of 1967) - stated that the campus should be no smaller than {{convert|600|acre|ha}}, making it then the largest campus in the state as well as the first public four-year college created in Washington in the 20th century.

On January 24, 1968, ''The Evergreen State College'' was selected from 31 choices as the name of the new institution.  On November 1, 1968, [[Charles J. McCann]] assumed the first presidency of the college.  McCann and the founding faculty held the first day of classes October 4, 1971 with 1178 students.  McCann served from 1968 until stepping down to join the faculty June 6, 1977 when former Governor [[Daniel J. Evans]], who signed the legislation creating Evergreen, assumed the presidency.  Evans left the president's office abruptly in 1983 when he was appointed to the [[United States Senate]] to fill the vacancy created by the death of [[Henry M. Jackson|Senator Henry M. Jackson]].  The largest building on campus is named in honor of Evans, the Daniel J. Evans Library Building.  The entrance to the campus bears McCann's name, the Charles J. McCann plaza. In 2004, the college completed the {{convert|170000|sqft|m2|sing=on}} Seminar II building, and a significant remodel of the Daniel J. Evans Library is now complete.

In 1999, [[Mumia Abu-Jamal]] was invited to deliver the keynote address by audiotape for the graduating class at the college. The event was protested heavily.

The campus contains a large tract of undeveloped land along the Puget Sound waterfront, much of it being second growth evergreen forest, which is of use to the students and faculty of the campus as a research and natural area.  The entire campus comprises about {{convert|408|ha|acre}}, much of it forested land. This total includes {{convert|11|ha|acre}} of southern Puget Sound tidelands.&lt;ref name=&quot;evergreen1&quot;&gt;http://www.evergreen.edu/policies/planningdocuments/master_plan_volume2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the main campus, there is also an organic farm as well as an urban campus located in [[Tacoma, Washington]].

{{Panorama|image=Image:The_Evergreen_State_College.jpg |fullwidth=9000 |fullheight=1487 |caption=360° panorama on the campus of The Evergreen State College in [[Olympia, Washington]]. This panorama features the Daniel J. Evans Library and the clock tower set in a brick courtyard lined with trees. |height=300}}

In 2008 the college became one of about 30 college and universities in the country to create a gender neutral option in its campus housing. This space is a designated [[safe space]] for LGBT students and allies and can also be used by married heterosexual couples.{{Citation needed|date=November 2008}}

==Rankings==
The Evergreen State College has garnered many academic accolades. According to [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]]'s 2009-2010 college rankings, Evergreen is ranked #1 in the West for Undergraduate Teaching at Masters Universities. It was ranked as the 5th best public college in the Masters West Category &quot;a region stretching from Texas to the Pacific.&quot; It was also ranked as #29th overall in the Masters West Category outranking other state schools such as Central Washington University and Eastern Washington University, as well as many other public schools in the region such as Humboldt State University, Boise State University, Eastern Oregon University, Western Oregon University, and Southern Oregon University.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/masters-west-ut-rank Best Colleges - Education - US News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Evergreen is also among the top colleges in the nation for offering the best first-year experiences to freshmen, which entails building into the curriculum first-year seminars or other programs that bring small groups of students together with faculty and staff on a regular basis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/first-year-experience-programs Best Colleges - Education - US News&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Author and former ''[[New York Times]]'' education editor [[Loren Pope]] cites Evergreen as one of two public colleges in the United States in his book ''[[Colleges That Change Lives]]''. In addition, [[The Princeton Review]] lists Evergreen as one of the Best Western Colleges for 2009-2010.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.princetonreview.com/TheEvergreenStateCollege.aspx The Evergreen State College&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Athletics==
Evergreen competes in the NAIA Cascade Collegiate Conference. The school's teams are known as the Geoducks. 

Former men's soccer star [[Joey Gjertsen]] has gone on to have professional success with the [[San Jose Earthquakes]] of [[Major League Soccer]].

==Public service centers==
Evergreen State College is the home of the Longhouse Education and Cultural Center. The Longhouse exists to provide service and hospitality to students, the college, and surrounding Native communities. With a design based in the Northwest Indigenous Nations' philosophy of hospitality, its primary functions are to provide a gathering place for hosting cultural ceremonies, classes, conferences, performances, art exhibits and community events. The Longhouse provides the opportunity to build a bridge of understanding between the regions' tribes and visitors of all cultures. The public service mission of the Longhouse is to promote indigenous arts and cultures through education, cultural preservation, and economic development.

Evergreen also serves as the home for the Northwest Indian Applied Research Center. The Evergreen State College has a proven history of educational service to the tribes. Through the development of the Northwest Indian Applied Research Institute, the college has taken its commitment to the indigenous people of Western Washington one step further. The Institute expands the services which the college can offer the tribes, enabling Evergreen to assist local tribes to meet their economic, governance and resource goals. At the same time, the Institute provides additional, real-life learning opportunities for Evergreen students.

It is also the administrative home for the Washington State Institute for Public Policy. The Institute’s mission is to carry out practical, non-partisan research—at legislative direction—on issues of importance to Washington State. The Institute conducts research using its own policy analysts and economists, specialists from universities, and consultants. Institute staff work closely with legislators, legislative and state agency staff, and experts in the field to ensure that studies answer relevant policy questions.

Other notable public service centers on campus are:
* The Evergreen Center for Educational Improvement
* Labor Education and Research Center
* Washington Center for Improving the Quality of Undergraduate Education
* Center for Community-Based Learning in Action

==Organic Farm==
The Evergreen Organic Farm annual crop production area comprises {{convert|38000|sqft|m2}}, just {{convert|5000|sqft|m2}} shy of {{convert/spell|1|acre|ha|1}}. The perennial crop production area is in addition to this. The production from this area is sold to Aramark, from a farm-stand on Red Square every Tuesday and Thursday from 11am to 5pm during the growing season, and in CSA (Community Supported Agriculture). All of the excess is given to the Thurston County Food Bank and local charities, or composted.

Proceeds from the sale of the crops are used to finance farm projects and purchase seeds and equipment. Two of the greenhouses, the cooler, compost shed, farm fencing and orchard are just a few projects made possible from farm sales. Another use for money generated on the farm is to fund student projects. Many of these projects are related to horticultural aspects of food crops.

The farm production area is divided into sections that are used to delineate cropping areas for specific types of crops. The farm practices a strict five year crop rotation. The rotating of crops creates plant diversity over time as opposed to plant diversity in space. The rotation has four general crop categories with each category occupying a given space for one growing season.

Crop rotation is just one method the farm uses to maintain diversity in the field. Other methods employed are the use of undersown ground covers and inter-cropping different types of vegetable crops. Creating diversity in the field is one of the cornerstones of sustainable agriculture. Diversity provides non-toxic, sustainable crop protection against plant diseases and insect pests.

The Evergreen Organic Farm hosts a large Composting facility that composts all compostables from the campus. It also hosts a Biodiesel facility, a community garden, demeters garden, and a large farmhouse that was partially built by students.

==Environmental reserve and beach==
The Evergreen State College has {{convert|1000|acre|ha}} of land that is mostly second growth forest. The entire campus serves as a natural laboratory for scientific field research and provides inspiration for creative work. Throughout the {{convert|1000|acre|ha|adj=on}} forest there are multiple trails leading to a variety of locations throughout the reserve and to Evergreen Beach. The coastal habitat is characterized by steep bluffs, gravelly beaches with many washed-up logs, and the marine intertidal zone which extends up to {{convert|150|ft|m|adj=on}} out into Puget Sound's Eld Inlet during low tides. Evergreen has approximately {{convert|3300|ft|km|adj=on}} of untouched beach. Students use the beach for scientific study and as a place to get away from their studies and relax. There are multiple trails leading to the beach and a small road that leads to the only building at the beach and small boat ramp. The bluffs range from 15 to 60 feet (5 to 20 meters) in height.&lt;ref name=&quot;evergreen1&quot;/&gt;

==Daniel J. Evans Library==
The main library on the Evergreen State College campus is the Daniel J. Evans Library, named after the former governor that signed the legislation that founded Evergreen, and was also the school's second president. The library is home to over 750,000 print and media items. It also houses journal titles. The library also maintains special collections of rare books, archival material, and government documents. The library also hosts a number of small viewing rooms. The Quantitative and Symbolic Reasoning Center (QuaSR), a tutoring center for the sciences, is located on the first floor of the library. The library is located in the Information Technology wing of the Daniel J. Evans Library Building. This wing is also the home for Media Services and a large Academic Computing center.

==Undergraduate programs==
Evergreen is unique in that undergraduate students select one 16 credit program for the entire quarter rather than multiple courses. Full time programs will encompass a quarter's worth of work in everything related to that program concentration, by up to three professors. There are no &quot;majors&quot;: students have the freedom to choose what program to enroll in for the entire duration of their undergraduate education, and are never required to follow a specific set of programs. Evergreen is on the &quot;quarter&quot; system. Programs are one, two, or three quarters, three quarters being September through June, generally. 

At the end of the program the professor writes a one page report (&quot;Evaluation&quot;) about the student's activity in the class rather than a letter grade, and has an end-of-program Evaluation conference with each student. The professor also determines how many credits should be awarded to the student, and students can lose credit. 

In order to obtain a Bachelors of Arts, a student must complete 180 credits. In order to obtain a Bachelors of Science, a student must obtain 180 credits, 72 of which need to be considered science credits, with 48 of the 72 credits noted as upper division science credits. This requirement can be satisfied by one year of upper-division science.

Undergraduate students often note that, while there are no official &quot;departments&quot; and teachers teach programs together across disciplines, the sciences and non-sciences tend to segregate cleanly. This is due to both program structure (the sciences grouped together in programs) and physical campus structure (the LAB I and LAB II buildings with a computer center of their own to boot). Additionally, some are of the opinion that the sciences are more stringently taught and evaluated than non-science programs. 

Areas of study include:
Aesthetics, African American Studies, Agriculture, American Studies, Anthropology, Architecture, Art History, Astronomy, Biochemistry, Biology, Botany, Business and Management, Chemistry, Communications, Community Studies, Computer Science, Consciousness Studies, Cultural Studies, Dance, Ecology, Economics, Education, Environmental Studies, Field Studies, Gender and Women's Studies, Geography, Geology, Government, Health, History, Hydrology, International Studies, Language Studies, Law and Government Policy, Law and Public Policy, Leadership Studies, Linguistics, Literature, Marine Science, Maritime Studies, Mathematics, Media Studies, Moving Image, Music, Native American Studies, Natural History, Outdoor Leadership and Education, Philosophy, Philosophy of Science, Physics, Physiology, Political Science, Psychology, Queer Studies, Religious Studies, Sociology, Somatic Studies, Sustainability Studies, Theater, Visual Arts, Writing, and Zoology.

==Graduate programs==
Unlike the undergraduate programs, the graduate programs require that students have taken a certain rotation of courses. Evergreen graduate studies include programs in:
*Master of Education
*Master of Environmental Studies
*Master in Teaching
*Master of Public Administration
*Master of Environmental Studies/Master of Public Administration Joint Degree

==Notable people==
{{Main article|List of The Evergreen State College people}}
Evergreen is notable for having produced a large number of successful musicians, writers, and cartoonists including [[Matt Groening]], the creator of ''[[The Simpsons]]'', and the author [[Lynda Barry]].

==Notable student groups==
[[File:Evergreen Seminar 2 bldg.jpg|250px|thumb|right|The Seminar II building, completed in 2004]]
* The Evergreen Rugby Football Club
* Cooper Point Journal (Student-run newspaper)&lt;ref&gt;[http://cpj.evergreen.edu/ Cooper Point Journal: Welcome to the CPJ!&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[KAOS (FM)|KAOS-FM]] (Evergreen's [[community radio]] station)&lt;ref&gt;[http://kaos.evergreen.edu/ KAOS 89.3FM Olympia Community Radio - KAOS 89.3FM: Olympia Community Radio&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Flaming Eggplant Cafe (Student run consensus based local and organic cafe on campus)
* Evergreen Socialist Alternative (Part of the national Socialist Alternative organization)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.socialistalternative.org/about/ Socialist Alternative]&lt;/ref&gt;
* MindScreen (Student run film and media group)
* Giant Robot Appreciation Society (Japanese animation club)&lt;ref&gt;[http://academic.evergreen.edu/groups/animeclub/ Giant Robot Appreciation Society&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Riot To Follow Theater Productions (Student theater society)
* Generation Friends Comedy Arts Coalition (Student comedy group)
* Slightly West (Student run school literary journal)
* [[International Solidarity Movement]]
* The Evergreen Singers (Evergreens performing Chorus)
* CASV (Coalition Against Sexual Violence)
* Evergreen Students for Sustainable Animal Agriculture (Agriculture club currently raising Ewes)
* SDS at Evergreen (Students for a Democratic Society)
* The Women of Color Coalition
* The Womyn's Resource Center

==See also==
* [[Washington State Institute for Public Policy]]
* [[History of Olympia, Washington]]

==References==
* Sevcik, Rita &amp; Stilson, Randy (1995).  [http://www.evergreen.edu/library/ARCHWWW/WebPages/sevcikr/home.htm &quot;Rita's archival page: The Evergreen State College -- Planning Milestones and Early Years&quot;]{{dead link|date=January 2011}}.  Retrieved October, 2005.
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Washington|University}}
* [http://www.evergreen.edu/ Official website]

{{Public Universities in Washington}}
{{Council of Public Liberal Arts Colleges}}

{{coord|47.072964|N|122.976151|W|source:dewiki_region:US-WA_type:landmark|format=dms|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Evergreen State College, The}}
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1967]]
[[Category:The Evergreen State College| ]]
[[Category:History of Olympia, Washington]]
[[Category:Public liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Northwest Commission on Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Olympia, Washington]]

[[cs:The Evergreen State College]]
[[de:Evergreen State College]]
[[simple:The Evergreen State College]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
