<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31934213" ns="0" title="Hermeticism (poetry)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{about|Hermetic poetry|Hermeticism (philosophical and religious beliefs)|Hermetic (disambiguation)}}

'''''Hermeticism''''' in poetry, or '''''Hermetic poetry''''', is a term used to describe obscure and difficult poetry, as of the [[Symbolist]] school. The name alludes to the mythical [[Hermes Trismegistus]],  supposed author of mystic doctrines composed in the [[Neoplatonic]] tradition.

Hermeticism was influential in the [[Renaissance]], after the translation of these [[Neoplatonic]] texts by [[Marsilio Ficino]]. More broadly, the term denotes poetry in which the language and imagery are subjective, and where the suggestive power of the sound of words is as important as their meaning.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. F. Ebeling, ''The secret history of Hermes Trismegistus: Hermeticism from ancient to modern times'' (Transl. D. Lorton), [[Cornell University Press]], 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

Within the [[Novecento Italiano]], Hermetic poetry came to refer to an [[Italy|Italian]] literary movement in the 1920s and 1930s, developing between the two world wars.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Major features of this movement were reduction to essentials, abolishment of [[punctuation]], and brief, synthetic compositions, at times resulting in short works of only two or three verses.

==Terminology==
The term '''''ermetismo''''' was coined in [[Italian language|Italian]] by [[literary critic]] [[Francesco Flora]] (although with a very generic and superficial connotation) in 1936 and recalls a mystic conception of the poetic word because it makes reference to the legendary figure of [[Hermes Trismegistus]]  (''Thrice-Great Hermes'') going back to [[hellenistic]] times, with writings such as ''[[Asclepius]]'' and the ''[[Hermetica|Corpus Hermeticum]]'' attributed to him.&lt;ref&gt;Hermes Trismegistus is described in the [[Corpus Hermeticum]] in a [[Euhemerus|Euhemerist]] fashion, as a man who became a god, or as a man who was the son of a god. During the [[Renaissance]] it was accepted that Hermes Trismegistus was a contemporary of [[Moses]], however after [[Isaac Casaubon|Casaubon’s]] dating of the Hermetic writings as no earlier than the second or third century CE, the whole of Renaissance Hermeticism collapsed. Cf. W. J. Haanegraaff, ''New Age Religion and Western Culture'', Brill, Leiden, [[New York]], 1996, p.390&lt;/ref&gt; During the same year (1936), [[Italian poetry|Italian poet]] [[Carlo Bo]] published an [[essay]] on the literary [[magazine]] ''[[Frontespizio]]'', by the title &quot;Letteratura come vita (Literature as a way of life)&quot;, containing the theoretical-methodological fundamentals of hermetic poetry.
[[File:Salvatore Quasimodo 1959.jpg|thumb|Hermetic poet and [[Nobel Prize in Literature|Nobel laureate]] [[Salvatore Quasimodo]]]]
On the literary plane, the term ''Hermeticism'' thus highlights a type of poetry which has a ''close'' (i.e., ''[[hermetic seal|hermetic]]'', hidden, sealed)&lt;ref&gt;Cf. ''Hermetic'' on [http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/hermetic Dictionary.com]&lt;/ref&gt; character, complex in its construction and usually achieved by a sequence of [[analogy|analogies]] difficult to interpret.

At the movement's core - which was modelled after the great [[France|French]] [[decadent movement|decadentist]] poets   [[Stéphane Mallarmé|Mallarmé]], [[Arthur Rimbaud|Rimbaud]] and [[Paul Verlaine|Verlaine]] - was a group of Italian poets, called ''hermeticists'', who followed the style of [[Giuseppe Ungaretti]] and [[Eugenio Montale]].

==Themes and styles==
Rejecting any direct social and political involvement, in order to detach themselves from the [[fascist]] culture, the hermetic group used a difficult and closed style in the analogic form, with a constant emotional introspection. Among these young intellectuals, some took strong [[anti-fascist]] stances, with [[Romano Bilenchi]], [[Elio Vittorini]], [[Alfonso Gatto]] and [[Vasco Pratolini]] being the main dissidents. &quot;Tradition is Hermeticism's best ally&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[Carlo Bo]], in his [[essay]] &quot;Letteratura come vita (Literature as a way of life)&quot;, ''[[Frontespizio]]'' 1936.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hermetic poetry opposes verbal manipulation and the ease of mass communication, which began taking place during [[Europe]]'s dictatorial years, with the increasing brain-wasing [[propaganda]] of the [[nazism|nazi]]-[[fascist]] regimes. Poetry therefore retreats into itself and assumes the task of returning sense to words, giving them back their [[semantics|semantic]] meaning, using them only when strictly necessary.&lt;ref&gt;The [[Japanese language|Japanese]] [[Haiku]] poetry may possess similar features and functions.&lt;/ref&gt;

The hermetic poets pursue the ideal of a &quot;pure poesy&quot;, an essential composition without educational aims. Their central theme is the desperate sense of loneliness modern man experiences, having lost the ancient values and [[myth]]s of the [[romantic]] and [[positivism|positivistic]] [[society]], no longer retaining any certitudes to refer to. Man lives in an incomprehensible world, ravaged by wars and enslaved by dictatorships, therefore the poet has a disheartened vision of life, without illusions, and repudiates the word as an act of communication in order to give it an evocative sense only. So, hermetic poetry is poetry of moods, of interior reflection expressed by a subdued and pensive tone, through a refined and evocative language, concealing direct intimations to experience in a play of allusions.
[[File:Alfonso gatto ritratto da farpi vignoli.jpg|thumb|250px|Hermetic poet [[Alfonso Gatto]] with his bust, made by sculptor [[Farpi Vignoli]] (1940)]]
To describe the fleeting course of human life, [[Quasimodo]] would compose this famous hermetic poem ''&quot;Ed è subito sera&quot;'':
:''Ognuno sta solo sul cuor della terra''
:''trafitto da un raggio di sole''
:''ed è subito sera''&lt;ref&gt;(Approx transl., ''Everyone stands alone on the heart of the earth / transfixed by a ray of sunshine / and it is suddenly night'') by [[Salvatore Quasimodo]], [[Nobel Prize]] 1959. Cf. an anthology of his [http://vagheggiando.blogspot.com/2006/05/uomo-del-mio-tempodi-salvatore.html poems].&lt;/ref&gt;

The hermetic poets took their inspiration from [[Ungaretti]]'s second book, ''[[Ungaretti#Published_volumes|Sentimento del Tempo (&quot;The Feeling of Time&quot;, 1933)]]'', with its complex analogies: one can thus consider [[Ungaretti]] as ''Hermeticism's'' first exponent.

In the field of hermetic literary critique, [[Carlo Bo]] was its main interpreter, with his discourse ''La letteratura come vita (&quot;Literature as a way of life&quot;)'' dated 1938, where he wrote the actual  [[manifesto|hermetic manifesto]] by describing poetry as a moment of [[Absolute]]. Among the other critics and theoreticians, to be mentioned are [[Oreste Macrì]], [[Giansiro Ferrata]], [[Luciano Anceschi]] and [[Mario Luzi]].

During the second half of the 1930s, and important hermetic group arose in [[Florence]], around the Italian [[magazine]]s  ''[[Frontespizio]]'' and ''[[Solaria]]'' who were inspired by the works of [[Giuseppe Ungaretti]], [[Salvatore Quasimodo]] e [[Arturo Onofri]], and directly referred to [[Europe]]an [[symbolism (arts)|symbolism]], also approaching more recent movements such as [[surrealism]] and [[existentialism]].

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==Bibliography==
*Ebeling, Florian, ''The secret history of Hermes Trismegistus: Hermeticism from ancient to modern times'' [Translated from the German by David Lorton] (Cornell University Press: Ithaca, 2007), ISBN 9780801445460.
*Festugière, A.-J.,''La révélation d'Hermès Trismégiste''. 2e éd., 3 vol., Paris 1981.
*Fowden, Garth, 1986. ''The Egyptian Hermes: A Historical Approach to the Late Pagan Mind''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (Princeton University Press, 1993): deals with Thoth (Hermes) from his most primitive known conception to his later evolution into Hermes Trismegistus, as well as the many books and scripts attributed to him.)
*[[Frances Yates|Yates, Frances A.]], ''[[Giordano Bruno and the Hermetic Tradition]]''. University of Chicago Press, 1964. ISBN 0226950077.
* {{cite book | author=Abel, Christopher R. and Hare, William O. | title=Hermes Trismegistus: An Investigation of the Origin of the Hermetic Writings | location=Sequim | publisher=Holmes Publishing Group | year=1997 | id= }}
* {{cite book | author=Anonymous | title=Meditations on the Tarot: A Journey into Christian Hermeticism | location=New York | publisher=Jeremy P. Tarcher/Penguin | year=2002 | id= }}
* {{cite book | author=Budge, E. A. Wallis | authorlink=E. A. Wallis Budge | title=The Egyptian Book of the Dead: (The Papyrus of Ani) Egyptian Text Transliteration and Translation | location=New York | publisher=Dover Publications | year=1895 | id= }}
* Churton, Tobias.  ''The Golden Builders: Alchemists, Rosicrucians, and the First Freemasons''.  New York: Barnes and Noble, 2002.
* Copenhaver, B.P. Hermetica, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1992.
* {{cite book | author=Garstin, E.J. Langford | title=Theurgy ''or'' The Hermetic Practice | location=Berwick | publisher=Ibis Press | year=2004 | id= }} ''Published Posthumously''
* Hoeller, Stephan A.  ''On the Trail of the Winged God: Hermes and Hermeticism Throughout the Ages'', Gnosis: A Journal of Western Inner Traditions (Vol. 40, Summer 1996). Also at {{cite web|url=http://www.gnosis.org/hermes.htm |title=Hermes and Hermeticism |publisher=Gnosis.org |date= |accessdate=2009-11-09}}
* {{cite book | author=Heiser, James D. | title=Prisci Theologi and the Hermetic Reformation in the Fifteenth Century | location=Texas | publisher=Repristination Press | year=2011 | id= }}
* {{cite book | author=Powell, Robert A. | title=Christian Hermetic Astrology: The Star of the Magi and the Life of Christ | location=Hudson | publisher=Anthroposohic Press | year=1991 | id= }}
* {{cite book | author=Regardie, Israel | authorlink=Israel Regardie | title=The Golden Dawn | location=St. Paul | publisher=Llewellyn Publications | year=1940 | id= }}
* {{cite book | author=Salaman, Clement and Van Oyen, Dorine and Wharton, William D. and Mahé, Jean-Pierre | title=The Way of Hermes: New Translations of The Corpus Heremticum and The Definitions of Hermes Trismegistus to Asclepius | location=Rochester | publisher=Inner Traditions | year=2000 | id= }}
* {{cite book | last=Scully |first=Nicki | authorlink=Nicki Scully | title=Alchemical Healing: A Guide to Spiritual, Physical, and Transformational Medicine | location=Rochester | publisher=Bear &amp; Company | year=2003 | id= }}

==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[Bibliotheca Philosophica Hermetica]]
* [[Hellenistic magic]]
* [[:Category:Hermeticists|Hermeticists]]
*[[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolism]]
* [[Surrealism]]
* [[Existentialism]]
* [[Decadentism]]
* [[Corrente di Vita]]
{{multicol-break}}
* [[Haiku]]
* [[Renaissance magic]]
* [[Novecento Italiano]]
* [[Sex magic]]
* [[Thelemic mysticism]]
* [[Western literature]]
* [[Western esotericism]]
* [[Recapitulation theory]]
{{multicol-end}}

==External links==
* [http://www.levity.com/alchemy/corpherm.html Online Version of the ''Corpus Hermeticum'', version translated by [[John Everard (preacher)|John Everard]] in 1650 [[Common Era|CE]] from Latin version]
* [http://www.sacred-texts.com/eso/vow/index.htm Online Version of ''The Virgin of the World of Hermes Trismegistus'', version translated by Anna Kingsford and Edward Maitland in 1885 A.D.]
* [http://www.gnostic.org/kybalionhtm/kybalion.htm Online version of ''The Kybalion'' (1912)]
* [http://www.kybalion.org The Kybalion Resource Page]
* [http://www.galilean-library.org/manuscript.php?postid=43803 An introduction to Hermeticism by Paul Newall (2004)]
* [http://www.hermetics.org  Hermetics Resource Site]—Many Hermetics texts
* [http://www.hermetic.com The Hermetic Library]—A collection of texts and sites relating to Hermeticism
* {{dmoz|society/Religion_and_Spirituality/Esoteric_and_Occult/Hermeticism}}
* [http://www.transalchemy.com TransAlchemy]-Modern scientific and [[Singularitarianism|singularitarian]] Hermetic research
*{{it}} [http://www.repubblicaletteraria.it/Ermetismo.htm Hermetic poetry in Italian literature]
*{{it}} [http://www.adrianopiacentini.it/Ermetismo.htm Hermeticism as a philosophic current]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hermeticism (Poetry)}}
[[Category:Hermeticism]]
[[Category:Poetry]]
[[Category:Italian poetry]]
[[Category:Esoteric schools of thought]]
[[Category:Literature]]
[[Category:Esotericism]]
[[Category:Mysticism]]
[[Category:Occult]]

[[it:Ermetismo (letteratura)]]
[[he:הרמטיזם (ספרות)]]
[[uk:Герметизм (поезія)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
