<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="31966269" ns="0" title="LulzSec"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox organization
| name           =Lulz Security
| bgcolor        =
| fgcolor        =
| image          = Lulz Security.svg
| image_border   =
| size           =
| alt            =
| caption        = Lulz Security logo
| map            =
| msize          =
| malt           =
| mcaption       =
| abbreviation   =LulzSec
| motto          =&quot;The world's leaders in high-quality entertainment at your expense&quot;
| formation      = May 2011
| type           = Hacking
| purpose        =
| headquarters   =
| region_served  =
| membership     =
| leader_title   =
| leader_name    =
| main_organ     =
| parent_organization =
| affiliations   = [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]], [[LulzRaft]], [[Operation AntiSec|AntiSec]]
| num_staff      =
| num_volunteers = 6
| budget         =
| website        = [http://lulzsecurity.com/ lulzsecurity.com]
| remarks        =
}}

'''Lulz Security''', commonly abbreviated as '''LulzSec''', is a [[hacker (computer security)|computer hacker]] group that claims responsibility for several high profile attacks, including the compromise of user accounts from [[Sony Pictures]] in 2011. The group also claimed responsibility for taking the [[CIA]] website offline.&lt;ref name = BBCCIA&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec hackers claim CIA website shutdown|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13787229|accessdate=17 June 2011|newspaper=BBC |date=16 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group has been described as a &quot;[[cyberterrorism|cyber terrorism group]]&quot; by the [[Arizona Department of Public Safety]] after their systems were compromised and information leaked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.azdps.gov/Media/News/View/?p=316|title=DPS Victim of Cyber Attack|date=June 27, 2011|work=Press Release|publisher=Arizona Department of Public Safety|accessdate=1 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other security professionals have applauded LulzSec for drawing attention to insecure systems and the dangers of password reuse.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Is There a Hacking Epidemic?|url=http://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2011/07/is_there_a_hack.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has gained attention due to its high profile targets and the sarcastic messages it has posted in the aftermath of its attacks.

At just after midnight ([[British Summer Time|BST]], [[Universal Time|UT]]+01) on 26 June 2011, LulzSec released a &quot;50 days of lulz&quot; statement, which they claimed to be their final release, confirming that LulzSec consisted of six members, and that their website is to be taken down.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Weisenthal|first=Joe|title=Notorious Hacker Group LulzSec Just Announced That It's Finished|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/lulzsec-finished-2011-6|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[Business Insider]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=Silicon Alley Insider|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5ziS1EJcn|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This breaking up of the group was unexpected.&lt;ref&gt; {{cite news | first = Peter | last = Svensson | title = Parting is such tweet sorrow for hacker group | date = 2011-06-27 | publisher = [[The Sydney Morning Herald]] | url = http://www.smh.com.au/technology/security/parting-is-such-tweet-sorrow-for-hacker-group-20110626-1glos.html#ixzz1QSL6wvEC | work = The Sydney Morning Herald | accessdate = 2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The release included accounts and passwords from many different sources. Despite claims of retirement, the group committed another hack against newspapers owned by [[News Corporation]] on 18 July, defacing them with false reports regarding the death of [[Rupert Murdoch]]. The [[London Metropolitan Police]] has announced the arrests of two teenagers they allege are LulzSec members [[T-flow]] and [[Topiary (hacktivist)|Topiary]]. The group helped launch [[Operation AntiSec]], a joint effort involving LulzSec, [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]], and other hackers.

== Overview ==
LulzSec draws its name from the [[neologism]] &quot;[[Lulz]]&quot;, (from [[LOL]]s), &quot;laughing out loud&quot;, which often signifies laughter at the victim of a prank, and &quot;Sec,&quot; short for &quot;Security&quot;. The ''[[Wall Street Journal]]'' has characterized its attacks as closer to Internet pranks rather than serious cyber-warfare,&lt;ref name=twsj/&gt; while the group itself claims to possess the capability of stronger attacks.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec threatens governments|date=21 June 2011|work=RT|url=http://rt.com/usa/news/lulzsec-government-group-reads|accessdate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has gained attention in part due to its brazen claims of responsibility and lighthearted taunting of corporations that have been hacked. It frequently refers to [[Internet meme]]s when defacing websites. The group first emerged in May 2011, and has successfully attacked the websites of several major corporations.&lt;ref name=twsj/&gt; It specializes in finding websites with poor security, and then stealing and posting information from them online. It has used well-known straightforward methods, such as [[SQL injection]], to attack its target websites.&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt; Several media sources have described their tactics as [[grey hat]] hacking.&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;{{cite news|title=Q&amp;A: Lulz Security|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13671195|accessdate=6 June 2011|newspaper=BBC |date=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cnnm&gt;{{cite news|last=Mitchell|first=Dan|title=Yet another hack, yet another delay in reporting it|url=http://tech.fortune.cnn.com/2011/06/09/yet-another-hack-yet-another-delay-in-reporting-it/?section=magazines_fortune|accessdate=11 June 2011|newspaper=CNN Money|date=9 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=scm&gt;{{cite news|last=Raywood|first=Dan|title=Security expert publicly backs 'grey hats' such as LulzSec, saying that public disclosure will help businesses|url=http://www.scmagazineuk.com/security-expert-publicly-backs-grey-hats-such-as-lulzsec-saying-that-public-disclosure-will-help-businesses/article/204904/|accessdate=11 June 2011|newspaper=SC Magazine|date=10 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the group may have been involved in a [[Anonymous (group)#Attack on HBGary Federal|previous attack]] against the security firm [[HBGary]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Acohido|first=Byron|title=Who's who among key LulzSec hackitivists|url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/technologylive/post/2011/06/whos-who-among-key-lulzsec-hackitivists/1|work=USA Today|accessdate=21 June 2011|date=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The group has used the motto &quot;Laughing at your security since 2011!&quot; and its website, created in June 2011, plays the theme from ''[[The Love Boat]]''.&lt;ref name=twsj&gt;{{cite news|last1=Morse|last2=Sherr|first1=Andrew|first2=Ian|title=For Some Hackers, The Goal Is Just To Play A Prank|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/BT-CO-20110605-702801.html|accessdate=6 June 2011|newspaper=The Wall Street Journal|page=B1|date=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; It announces its exploits via Twitter and its own website, often accompanied with lighthearted [[ASCII art]] drawings of boats. Its website also includes a [[Bitcoin]] donation to help fund its activities.&lt;ref name=forb&gt;{{cite news|last=Olson|first=Parmy|title=LulzSec Hackers Post Sony Dev. Source Code, Get $7K Donation|url=http://blogs.forbes.com/parmyolson/2011/06/06/lulzsec-hackers-posts-sony-dev-source-code-get-7k-donation/|accessdate=7 June 2011|newspaper=Forbes|date=6 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although exact motivation of the group is unknown,&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt; Ian Paul of ''[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]]'' has written that, &quot;As its name suggests, LulzSec claims to be interested in mocking and embarrassing companies by exposing security flaws rather than stealing data for criminal purposes.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Paul, Ian. &quot;[http://www.pcworld.com/article/229316/lulz_boat_hacks_sonys_harbor_faq.html Lulz Boat Hacks Sony's Harbor: FAQ].&quot; ''[[PC World (magazine)|PC World]]''. 3 June 2011. Retrieved on 6 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The group has also been critical of [[White hat (computer security)|white hat]] hackers, claiming that many of them have been corrupted by their employers.&lt;ref name=twsj/&gt;

Some in the security community have lauded them for raising awareness of the widespread lack of effective security against hackers.&lt;ref name=tth&gt;{{cite news|last=Ragan|first=Steve|title=One month later&amp;nbsp;– LulzSec continues their personal brand of comedy|url=http://www.thetechherald.com/article.php/201123/7251/One-month-later-%E2%80%93-LulzSec-continues-their-personal-brand-of-comedy|accessdate=9 June 2011|newspaper=The Tech Herald|date=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been credited with inspiring [[LulzRaft]], a group which has been implicated in several high-profile website hacks in Canada.&lt;ref name=tcp&gt;{{cite news|last=Beltrame|first=Julian|title=Hacker without a cause scores with Harper 'breakfast incident' hoax|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/canadianpress/article/ALeqM5haZn2PyOSvxJly0_pPXkakAc52kA?docId=7077370|accessdate=10 June 2011|newspaper=The Canadian Press|date=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The group's first recorded attack was against [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox.com]]'s website. It claimed responsibility for leaking information, including passwords, altering several employees' [[LinkedIn]] profiles, and leaking a database of [[The X Factor (U.S.)|X Factor]] contestants containing contact information of 73,000 contestants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Who is LulzSec, Hacker of PBS? Are they hacking Sony again?|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/155143/20110531/pbs-hacked-lulzsec-lulz-sony.htm|publisher=International Business Times|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Poulsen|first=Kevin|title=Sony Hit Yet Again; Consumer Passwords Exposed|url=http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2011/06/sony-lulzsec/|publisher=Wired|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They claimed to do so because the rapper [[Common (entertainer)|Common]] had been referred to as &quot;vile&quot; on air.&lt;ref name=history&gt;{{cite news|title=A Brief History of the LulzSec Hackers|url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/06/21/brief-history-lulzsec-hackers/|accessdate=21 June 2011|publisher=Fox News Channel|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[News Corporation]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbwTf458|archivedate=21 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The group has begun taking suggestions for sites to hit with [[denial-of-service attack]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Boscker|first=Bianca|title=LulzSec Hacker Group Now Taking Requests|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/06/15/lulzsec-hacker-group-now-_n_877309.html|accessdate=15 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Huffington Post]]|date=15 June 2011|agency=[[AOL]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zSjErRoF|archivedate=15 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group has also been redirecting telephone numbers to different customer support lines, including the line for [[World of Warcraft]], magnets.com, and the FBI [[Detroit]] office. The group claims this sends five to 20 calls per second to these sources, overwhelming their support officers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Albanesius|first=Chloe|title=LulzSec Call-In Line Taking Hacking Requests|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2386959,00.asp|accessdate=15 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC Magazine]]|date=15 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zSt1Dwzi|archivedate=15 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 June 2011, ''[[The Guardian]]'' released leaked logs of the one of the group's IRC chats, revealing that the core group is a small group of hackers with a leader Sabu who exercises large control over the group's activities. It also reveals that the group has connections, though is not formally affiliated with, [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]]. Some LulzSec members had once been prominent Anonymous members, including member [[Topiary (hacktivist)|Topiary]].&lt;ref name=logs/&gt;

At just after midnight (GMT) on 26 June 2011, LulzSec released a &quot;50 days of lulz&quot; statement, which they claimed to be their final release, confirming that LulzSec consisted of six members, and that their website is to be taken down.&lt;ref name=fifty&gt;{{cite news|last=Weisenthal|first=Joe|title=Notorious Hacker Group LulzSec Just Announced That It's Finished |url=http://www.businessinsider.com/lulzsec-finished-2011-6|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[Business Insider]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=Silicon Alley Insider|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5ziS1EJcn|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group claimed that they had planned to be active for only fifty days from the beginning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Moyer|first=Edward|title=Hacking group LulzSec says it's calling it quits|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1009_3-20074416-83/hacking-group-lulzsec-says-its-calling-it-quits/|accessdate=26 June 2011|newspaper=[[CNET.com]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zifBaJXe|archivedate=26 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &quot;We're not quitting because we're afraid of law enforcement. The press are getting bored of us, and we're getting bored of us.&quot; a group member said in an interview to [[The Associated Press]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Svensson|first=Peter|title=Hacker group LulzSec says it's disbanding|url=http://www.usatoday.com/tech/news/2011-06-26-lulzsec-disbands_N.htm|accessdate=27 June 2011|newspaper=[[USA Today]]|date=26 June 2011|agency=[[The Associated Press]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the group have been reported to have joined with Anonymous members to continue the AntiSec operation.&lt;ref name=newantisec&gt;{{cite news|last=Olivarez-Giles|first=Nathan|title=AntiSec 'hackers without borders' claim new hack on Arizona state police|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/06/antisec-hackers-leak-files-said-to-be-from-arizona-state-police.html|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=29 June 2011|agency=[[Tribune Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zq3OxQQv|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[Los Angeles]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, despite claiming to retire, the group attacked the websites of British newspaper ''[[The Times]]'' and ''[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]'' on 18 July, leaving a false story on the death of owner [[Rupert Murdoch]].&lt;ref name=Gayomail/&gt;

== Members and associates ==
LulzSec consists of six core members.&lt;ref name=fifty/&gt; The online handles of these six have been established through various attempts by other hacking groups to release personal information of group members on the internet, leaked IRC logs given to ''[[The Guardian]]'', and through confirmation from the group itself.&lt;ref name=members&gt;{{cite news|last=Poeter|first=Damon|title=Who Is LulzSec?|url=http://www.pcmag.com/slideshow/story/266414/Who-Is-LulzSec|accessdate=5 July 2011|newspaper=[[PC Magazine]]|date=2 July 2011|agency=[[Ziff Davis]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zx2jodqN|archivedate=5 July 2011|pages=1–9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Sabu (hacktivist)|Sabu]] &amp;ndash; One of the group's founders who seemed to act as a kind of leader for the group, often Sabu decides what targets to attack next and who could participate in these attacks. He may have been part of the Anonymous group that hacked [[HBGary]]. Various attempts to release his real identity have claimed that he is an [[Information technology consulting|information technology consultant]] with the strongest hacking skills of the group and a knowledge of the [[Python (programming language)|Python]] programming language.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;
* [[Topiary (hacktivist)|Topiary]] &amp;ndash; Topiary is also a suspected former member of the Anonymous AnonOps, where he used to perform media relations, including hacking the website of the [[Westboro Baptist Church]] during a live interview.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Goodman|first=William|title=Video: Anonymous hacks Westboro Baptist Church website during on-air confrontation|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-504784_162-20036043-10391705.html|accessdate=5 July 2011|newspaper=[[CBS News]]|date=24 February 2011|agency=[[CBS]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zx3f5f7H|archivedate=5 July 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Topiary ran the LulzSec Twitter account on a daily basis; following the announcement of LulzSec's dissolution, he deleted all the posts on his twitter page, except for one, which stated: &quot;You cannot arrest an idea&quot;.&lt;ref&gt; http://twitter.com/atopiary &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=members/&gt; Police arrested a man from [[Shetland]], [[United Kingdom]] suspected of being Topiary on 27 July 2011.&lt;ref name=topiaryarrest/&gt; The man was later identified as Jake Davis and was charged with five counts, including unauthorized access of a computer and conspiracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec: Shetland teen charged over computer hacking claims|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14359933|accessdate=31 July 2011|newspaper=[[BBC News]]|date=31 July 2011|agency=[[BBC]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60b7Z5Nyr|archivedate=31 July 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Kayla &amp;ndash; Also identified as &quot;lol&quot; in LulzSec chat logs, Kayla owns a [[botnet]] used by the group in their distributed denial-of-service attacks. The botnet is reported to consist of about 8,000 infected [[computer server]]s. Kayla also may have participated in the Anonymous operation against HBGary.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;
* T-flow &amp;ndash; The fourth founding member of the group identified in chat logs, attempts to identify him have labelled him a [[PHP]] coder, [[web developer]], and performer of scams on [[PayPal]]. The group placed him in charge of maintenance and security of the group's website lulzsecurity.com.&lt;ref name=members/&gt; London Metropolitan Police announced the arrest of a 16 year-old hacker going by the handle Tflow on 19 July 2011.&lt;ref name=tflow/&gt;
* Avunit &amp;ndash; He is one of the core six members of the group, but not a founding member. He left the group after their self-labelled &quot;Fuck the FBI Friday&quot;.  He was also affiliated with Anonymous AnonOps HQ.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;
* Pwnsauce &amp;ndash; Pwnsauce joined the group around the same time as Avunit and became one of its core members.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;

Associates and former members include:
* M_nerva &amp;ndash; M_nerva, once a member of the group, leaked some of the group's chat logs to ''The Guardian''. In response to the leak, LulzSec published M_nerva's personal information and records of the illegal hacking activity performed with them.  May also have participated with LulzSec in the attack on Fox.com.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;
* Joepie91 &amp;ndash; Though he is one of the most frequent participants in LulzSec IRC chat logs, the group stated that he is not a core member.&lt;ref name=members/&gt;. 
* Neuron &amp;ndash; Neuron is not a core member of the group, but may have supported them by building software and taking part in some of their distributed denial-of-service attacks. He is thought to be an engineering student in the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=members/&gt;
* [[LulzSec#Ryan Cleary|Ryan Cleary]] &amp;ndash; A 19-year-old from [[Essex]], [[United Kingdom]] who was arrested by [[Metropolitan Police]] on 21 June 2011 and charged with violating the [[Computer Misuse Act 1990|Computer Misuse Act]] and the [[Criminal Law Act 1977]].&lt;ref name=charged/&gt; Though not a member of the group, LulzSec admitted that he did run one of the IRC channels that they used for communicating.&lt;ref name=hardawar/&gt;

== Ideology ==
&lt;div class=&quot;thumb tright&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thumbinner&quot; style=&quot;text-align:left; width:41.5em;&quot;&gt;
&lt;pre style=&quot;font-size:smaller; margin:0;&quot;&gt;. /$$                 /$$            /$$$$$$
.| $$                | $$           /$$__  $$
.| $$       /$$   /$$| $$ /$$$$$$$$| $$  \__/  /$$$$$$   /$$$$$$$
.| $$      | $$  | $$| $$|____ /$$/|  $$$$$$  /$$__  $$ /$$_____/
.| $$      | $$  | $$| $$   /$$$$/  \____  $$| $$$$$$$$| $$
.| $$      | $$  | $$| $$  /$$__/   /$$  \ $$| $$_____/| $$
.| $$$$$$$$|  $$$$$$/| $$ /$$$$$$$$|  $$$$$$/|  $$$$$$$|  $$$$$$.$
.|________/ \______/ |__/|________/ \______/  \_______/ \_______/
                          //Laughing at your security since 2011!

+

   __
   )|     ________________________.------,_ _
 _/o|_____/  ,____________.__;__,__,__,__,_Y...:::---===````//    #anonymous
|==========\ ;  ;  ;  ;  ; \__,__\__,_____ --__,-.\   OFF  ((     #anarchists
           `----------|__,__/__,__/__/  )=))~((   '-\  THE  \\    #antisec
                        \ ==== \          \\~~\\     \  PIGS \\   #lulzsec
                        `| === |           ))~~\\     ```&quot;&quot;&quot;=,))  #fuckfbifriday
                         | === |           |'---')                #chingalamigra
                        / ==== /           `====='
                       ´------´

&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;thumbcaption&quot;&gt;An [[ASCII graphic]] used by the group in its Chinga La Migra torrent,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://thepiratebay.org/torrent/6490796/Chinga_La_Migra |title=Chinga La Migra (download torrent) |author=LulzSec |date=24 June 2011 |publisher=The Pirate Bay |accessdate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; an associated statement,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lulzsecurity.com/releases/chinga_la_migra_1.txt |title=Chinga La Migra bulletin No.1 |date=23 June 2011 |publisher=lulzsecurity.com |format=.txt |accessdate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and also appearing in press coverage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.theatlanticwire.com/technology/2011/06/lulzsec-attacks-border-patrol-leak-classified-arizona-police-documents/39209/|title=LulzSec Document Release Targets Arizona Border Patrol|author=Adam Clark Estes|publisher=The Atlantic Wire}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

LulzSec does not appear to hack for financial profit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Downie|first=James|title=Hacking For Fun More Than Profit|url=http://www.tnr.com/blog/the-study/89997/hacking-fun-more-profit|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[The New Republic]]|date=14 June 2011|agency=Mike Rancilio|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZkoXUXj|archivedate=20 June 2011|location=Washington, D.C.}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group's claimed main motivation is to have fun by causing mayhem.&lt;ref name=ind&gt;{{cite news|last=Taylor|first=Jerome|title=Who are the group behind this week's CIA hack?|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/americas/who-are-the-group-behind-this-weeks-cia-hack-2298430.html|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Independent]]|date=16 June 2011|agency=Independent Print Limited|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZlxA19Y|archivedate=20 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; They do things &quot;for the lulz&quot; and focus on the possible comedic and entertainment value of attacking targets.&lt;ref name=reasons&gt;{{cite news|last=Murphy|first=David|title=Three Reasons to Fear Lulzsec: Sites, Skills, and Slant|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387219,00.asp|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC Magazine]]|date=19 June 2011|agency=[[Ziff Davis]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZnbgTxl|archivedate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group occasionally has claimed a political message. When they hacked [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], they stated they did so in retaliation for what they perceived as unfair treatment of [[Wikileaks]] in a [[Frontline (U.S. TV series)|''Frontline'']] documentary entitled ''WikiSecrets''. A page they inserted to the PBS website included the title &quot;FREE BRADLEY MANNING. FUCK FRONTLINE!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Poulsen|first=Kevin|title=Hacktivists Scorch PBS in Retaliation for WikiLeaks Documentary|url=http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2011/05/lulzsec/|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[Wired (magazine)]]|date=30 May 2011|agency=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZjo04Uz|archivedate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 20 June announcement of &quot;Operation Anti-Security&quot; contained justification for attacks on government targets, citing supposed government efforts to &quot;dominate and control our Internet ocean&quot; and accusing them of corruption and breaching privacy.&lt;ref name=aussie/&gt; The media has most often described them as grey hat hackers.&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt;&lt;ref name=ind/&gt;

Karim Hijazi, CEO of security company Unveillance, has accused the group of [[extortion|blackmailing]] him by offering not to attack his company or its affiliates in exchange for money.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chapman|first=Stephen|title=LulzSec: Doing it more for the money than the lulz?|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/security/lulzsec-doing-it-more-for-the-money-than-the-lulz/8864|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[ZDNet]]|date=22 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdoTKovT|archivedate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec responded by claiming that Hijazi offered to pay them to attack his business opponents and that they never intended to take any money from him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ragan|first=Steve|title=Unveillance faces troubled waters in the wake of LulzSec visit|url=http://www.thetechherald.com/article.php/201123/7236/Unveillance-faces-troubled-waters-in-the-wake-of-LulzSec-visit|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Tech Herald]]|date=6 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdog2Jsa|archivedate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec has denied responsibility for misuse of any of the data they breach and release. Instead, they place the blame on users who reuse passwords on multiple websites and on companies with inadequate security in place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Lulz? Sony hackers deny responsibility for misuse of leaked data|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/lulz-sony-hackers-deny-responsibility-for-misuse-of-leaked-data.ars|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[Ars Technica]]|date=4 June 2011|agency=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZiJTPhj|archivedate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, the group released a manifesto outlining why they perform hacks and website takedowns. In it they reiterated that &quot;we do things just because we find it entertaining&quot; and that watching the results can be &quot;priceless&quot;.&lt;ref name=arsmanifesto&gt;{{cite news|last=Anderson|first=Nate|title=LulzSec manifesto: &quot;We screw each other over for a jolt of satisfaction&quot;|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/lulzsec-heres-why-we-hack-you-bitches.ars?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=rss|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[Ars Technica]]|date=18 June 2011|agency=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zZgZGcO3|archivedate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, they also claim to be drawing attention to [[computer security]] flaws and holes. They contend that many other hackers exploit and steal user information without releasing the names publicly or telling people they may possibly have been hacked. LulzSec said that by releasing lists of hacked usernames or informing the public of vulnerable websites, it gives users the opportunity to change names and passwords elsewhere that might otherwise have been exploited, and businesses will be alarmed that they should upgrade their security.&lt;ref name=arsmanifesto/&gt;

The group's latest attacks have had a more political tone. They claim to want to expose the &quot;racist and corrupt nature&quot; of the military and [[law enforcement]]. They have also expressed opposition to the [[War on Drugs]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Poulsen|first=Kevin|title=LulzSec Releases Arizona Police Documents|url=http://www.wired.com/threatlevel/2011/06/lulzsec-arizona/|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[Wired (magazine){{!}}Wired]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zflovgpH|archivedate=24 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lulzsec's Operation Anti-Security has been characterized as a protest against government censorship and monitoring of the internet.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stevenson|first=Alastair|title=Operation Anti-Security: Anonymous yet to act while LulzSec rampage|url=http://uk.ibtimes.com/articles/167639/20110622/lulzsec-lulz-security-anonymous-operation-anti-security-anti-sec-hacked-cleary-ryan-arrest-attack.htm|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[International Business Times]]|date=22 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zfn4uYd2|archivedate=24 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a question and answer session with [[BBC]] ''[[Newsnight]]'', LulzSec member Whirlpool said, &quot;Politically motivated ethical hacking is more fulfilling&quot;. He claimed the loosening of [[copyright law]]s and the rollback of what he sees as corrupt [[racial profiling]] practices as some of the group's issues.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Watts|first=Susan|title=Newsnight online 'chat' with Lulz Security hacking group|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13912836|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[BBC News]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[BBC]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zokiC5Tk|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Initial targets ==
The group's first attacks came in May 2011. Their first recorded target was Fox.com, which they retaliated against after they called Common, a rapper and entertainer, &quot;vile&quot; on the [[Fox News Channel]]. They leaked several passwords, LinkedIn profiles, and the names of 73,000 X Factor contestants. Soon after on 15 May, they released the transaction logs of 3,100 [[Automated Teller Machine]]s in the United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=history/&gt;&lt;ref name=reasons/&gt; In May 2011, members of Lulz Security gained international attention for hacking into the American [[Public Broadcasting System]] (PBS) website. They stole user data and posted a fake story on the site which claimed that [[Tupac Shakur]] and [[Biggie Smalls]] were still alive and living in New Zealand. In the aftermath of the attack, [[CNN]] referred to the responsible group as the &quot;Lulz Boat&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=CNN Wire Staff|title=Hackers pirate PBS website, post fake story about Tupac still alive|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/TECH/web/05/30/pbs.hackers/index.html?iid=EL|publisher=CNN|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lulz Security claimed that some of its hacks, including its attack on PBS, were motivated by a desire to defend [[WikiLeaks]] and [[Bradley Manning]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Olson|first=Parmy|title=Interview With PBS Hackers: We Did It For ‘Lulz And Justice’|url=http://blogs.forbes.com/parmyolson/2011/05/31/interview-with-pbs-hackers-we-did-it-for-lulz-and-justice/|work=Forbes|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Fox News]] report on the group quoted one commentator, Brandon Pike, who claimed that Lulz Security is affiliated with the [[Hacktivism|hacktivist]] group [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]]. Lulz Security claimed that Pike had actually hired it to hack PBS. Pike denied the accusation and claims it was leveled against him because he said Lulz Security was a splinter of Anonymous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Kaplan |first=Jeremy |title=Group Claims It Was 'Paid to Hack PBS,' Then Leaks a Million Sony User IDs |url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/06/02/man-denies-paying-group-to-hack-pbsorg/ |publisher=Fox News |date= 2 June 2011 |accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, members of the group claimed responsibility for an attack against [[Sony Pictures]] that took data that included &quot;names, passwords, e-mail addresses, home addresses and dates of birth for thousands of people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pepitone|first=Julianne|title=Group claims fresh hack of 1 million Sony accounts Money|url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/06/02/technology/sony_lulz_hack/?section=money_latest|publisher=CNN |date= 2 June 2011 |accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group claimed that it used a [[SQL injection attack]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ogg|first=Erica|title=Hackers steal more customer info from Sony servers|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-31021_3-20068414-260/hackers-steal-more-customer-info-from-sony-servers|publisher=CNET|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was motivated by Sony's legal action against [[George Hotz]] for [[Privilege_escalation#Jailbreaking|jailbreaking]] into the [[PlayStation 3]]. The group claims it will launch an attack that will be the &quot;beginning of the end&quot; for Sony.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Reisinger|first=Don|title=Tupac hackers to Sony: 'Beginning of the end'|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-13506_3-20067865-17.html?tag=mncol;txt|publisher=CNET|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Some of the compromised user information has since been used in scams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ars Staff|title=Lulz? Sony hackers deny responsibility for misuse of leaked data|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/lulz-sony-hackers-deny-responsibility-for-misuse-of-leaked-data.ars|publisher=Ars Technica|accessdate=3 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group claimed to have compromised over 1,000,000 accounts, though Sony claims the real number was around 37,500.&lt;ref name=lanumber&gt;{{cite news|last=Olivarez-Giles|first=Nathan|title=Sony Pictures says LulzSec hacked 37,500 user accounts, not 1 million|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/06/sony-denies-lulzsec-hacked-1-million-user-accounts-estimates-it-was-37500.html|accessdate=12 June 2011|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=9 June 2011|agency=[[Tribune Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zNXkePWU|archivedate=12 June 2011|location=Los Angeles}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Corporate attacks ==
Lulz Security attempted to hack into [[Nintendo]], but both the group and Nintendo itself report that no particularly valuable information was found by the hackers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec Hacks Nintendo: No User Information Released|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2386428,00.asp|newspaper=PCMag|date=5 June 2011|accessdate=5 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec claims that it did not mean to harm Nintendo, declaring: &quot;We're not targeting Nintendo. We like the [[Nintendo 64|N64]] too much&amp;nbsp;— we sincerely hope Nintendo plugs the gap.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Nintendo Is Hit by Hackers, but Breach Is Deemed Minor|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/06/technology/06hack.html|newspaper=New York Times|date=5 June 2011|accessdate=5 June 2011|first=Hiroko|last=Tabuchi}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 June 2011, LulzSec hacked into the website of Black &amp; Berg Cybersecurity Consulting, a small network security company, and changed the image displayed on their front page to one containing the LulzSec logo. They did so after the company had issued a &quot;Cybersecurity For The 21st Century, Hacking Challenge&quot;, in which they challenged hackers to hack the site and alter the homepage graphic. The intrusion came after Joe Black, an owner of the company posted the message &quot;Black &amp; Berg Cybersecurity Consulting appreciate all the hard work that you're putting in. Your Hacking = Clients for us. Thx&quot; to the LulzSec Twitter account. Though Black &amp; Berg offered a prize of $10,000 and a position with the company for the successful hack, members of LulzSec declined the offer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec wins hacking competition, refuses $10k award|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/159446/20110608/lulzsec-hacking-competition-black-berg-cybersecurity.htm|accessdate=8 June 2011|newspaper=[[International Business Times]]|date=8 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, the website contained the reply &quot;DONE, THAT WAS EASY. KEEP THE MONEY, WE DO IT FOR THE LULZ&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Black &amp; Berg Cybersecurity Consulting, LLC|url=http://www.blackbergsecurity.us/|publisher=Black &amp; Berg Cybersecurity Consulting|accessdate=8 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zI5xWAm8|archivedate=8 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 11 June, reports emerged that LulzSec reportedly hacked into and stole user information from the [[Internet pornography|pornography website]] www.pron.com. They obtained and published around 26,000 e-mail addresses and passwords. Among the information stolen are records of two users who subscribed using email addresses associated with the Malaysian government, three users who subscribed using United States military email addresses and 55 users who LulzSec claimed were administrators of other adult-oriented websites. Following the breach, Facebook locked the accounts of all users who had used the published e-mail addresses, and also blocked new Facebook accounts opened using the leaked e-mail addresses. They feared that users of the site would get hacked after LulzSec encouraged people to try and see if these people used identical user name and password combinations on Facebook as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Thomas|first=Keir|title=Porn Site Users Beware: Hacker Group LulzSec May Have Posted Your Email Address|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/230122/porn_site_users_beware_hacker_group_lulzsec_may_have_posted_your_email_address.html|accessdate=11 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine){{!}}PC World]]|date=11 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zMrR1kzh|archivedate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

LulzSec hacked into the [[Bethesda Game Studios]] network and posted information taken from the network onto the Internet, though they refrained from publishing 200,000 compromised accounts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Albanesius|first=Chloe|title=LulzSec Targets Bethesda Softworks, Porn Site|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2386861,00.asp|publisher=PC magizine|accessdate=13 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  LulzSec posted the following message to Twitter regarding the attack, &quot;Bethesda, we broke into your site over two months ago. We've had all of your Brink users for weeks, Please fix your junk, thanks!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ben|first=Kuchera|title=LulzSec hackers demand hats, threaten release of Brink user data|url=http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2011/06/hacker-group-lulzsec-demands-hats-threatens-release-of-brink-user-data.ars|publisher=Ars Technica|accessdate=13 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 June, LulzSec took down four websites by request of fans as part of their &quot;Titanic Take-down Tuesday&quot;. These websites were [[Minecraft]], [[League of Legends]], [[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]], and IT security company FinFisher.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bright|first=Peter|title=Titanic Takeover Tuesday: LulzSec's busy day of hacking escapades|url=http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2011/06/titanic-takeover-tuesday-lulzsecs-busy-day-of-hacking-escapades.ars|accessdate=14 June 2011|newspaper=[[Ars Technica]]|date=14 June 2011|agency=[[Condé Nast Publications]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zRduAS0h|archivedate=14 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They also attacked the login servers of the massively multiplayer online game [[EVE Online]], which also disabled the game's front-facing website, and the League of Legends login servers. Most of the takedowns were performed with [[distributed denial-of-service attack]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Peckham|first=Matt|title=LulzSec Knocks 'Minecraft,' 'EVE Online,' 'League Of Legends' and 'The Escapist' Offline |url=http://techland.time.com/2011/06/14/lulzsec-knocks-minecraft-eve-online-league-of-legends-and-the-escapist-offline/|accessdate=14 June 2011|newspaper=[[Time (magazine){{!}}Time]]|date=14 June 2011|agency=[[Time Inc.]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zRd8wlAR|archivedate=14 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 June, LulzSec took down the main server of S2 Games' [[Heroes of Newerth]] as another phone request. They claimed, &quot;Heroes of Newerth master login server is down. They need some treatment. Also, [[Defense of the Ancients|DotA]] is better.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=LulzSec|title=Tweet 81036958826102784|url=http://twitter.com/#!/LulzSec/status/81036958826102784|publisher=Twitter|accessdate=15 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 June, LulzSec posted a random assortment of 62,000 emails and passwords to [[MediaFire]]. LulzSec states they released this in return for supporters flooding the [[4chan]] [[4chan#.2Fb.2F|/b/]] board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=LulzSec|title=Tweet 81327464156119040|url=http://twitter.com/#!/LulzSec/status/81327464156119040|publisher=Twitter|accessdate=16 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group did not say what websites the combinations were for and encouraged followers to plug them into various sites until they gained access to an account. Some have reported gaining access to Facebook accounts and changing images to sexual content and others to using the [[Amazon.com]] accounts of others to purchase several books.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kobie|first=Nicole|title=LulzSec hackers leak 62,000 email logins|url=http://www.pcpro.co.uk/news/368122/lulzsec-hackers-leak-62-000-email-logins|accessdate=16 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC Pro]]|date=16 June 2011|agency=[[Dennis Publishing]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zUB48J81|archivedate=16 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Writerspace.com, a literary website, later admitted that the addresses and passwords came from users of their site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Dunn|first=John|title=LulzSec Hacker Victims Alerted|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/230683/lulzsec_hacker_victims_alerted.html|accessdate=19 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine)]]|date=19 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zYmDtKbd|archivedate=19 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--The information on the Rupert Murdoch/The Sun hack is already under the &quot;Operation Anti-Security&quot; section; the information does not need to be in multiple sections--&gt;

== Government-focused activities ==
LulzSec claims to have hacked local [[InfraGard]] chapter sites, a non-profit organization affiliated with the FBI.&lt;ref name=twsj/&gt; The group leaked some of InfraGard member e-mails and a database of local users.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec claims to have hacked FBI-affiliated website|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/06/lulz-security-claims-to-have-hacked-fbi-affiliated-website-.html|work=LA Times|accessdate=4 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group defaced the website posting the following message, &quot;LET IT FLOW YOU STUPID FBI BATTLESHIPS,&quot; accompanied with a video. LulzSec has posted the following message regarding the attack: {{quote|&quot;It has come to our unfortunate attention that NATO and our good friend Barrack Osama-Llama 24th-century Obama [sic] have recently upped the stakes with regard to hacking. They now treat hacking as an act of war. So, we just hacked an FBI affiliated website (Infragard, specifically the Atlanta chapter) and leaked its user base. We also took complete control over the site and defaced it [...].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Read|first=Max|title=LulzSec Hackers Go After FBI Affiliates|url=http://gawker.com/5808517/lulzsec-hackers-go-after-fbi-affiliates|publisher=Gawker|accessdate=4 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 9 June, LulzSec sent an email to the administrators of the British [[National Health Service]], informing them of a security vulnerability discovered in NHS systems. LulzSec stated that they did not intend to exploit this vulnerability, saying in the email that &quot;We mean you no harm and only want to help you fix your tech issues.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13712377|accessdate=9 June 2011| title= Hackers warn NHS over security|publisher=BBC|date=9 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 June, LulzSec released the e-mails and passwords of a number of users of [http://senate.gov/ senate.gov], the website of the [[United States Senate]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ogg|first=Erica|title=LulzSec targets videogame maker ZeniMax Media|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-31021_3-20070873-260/lulzsec-targets-videogame-maker-zenimax-media/|accessdate=13 June 2011|date=13 June 2011|agency=[[CNET.com]]. [[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zQ46O69V|archivedate=13 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The information released also included the [[root directory]] of parts of the website. LulzSec stated, &quot;This is a small, just-for-kicks release of some internal data from senate.gov&amp;nbsp;— is this an act of war, gentlemen? Problem?&quot; referencing a recent statement by [[the Pentagon]] that some cyberattacks could be considered an [[Casus belli|act of war]]. No highly sensitive information appears in the release.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Morse|first=Andrew|title=LulzSec Hacker Group Claims Attack On US Senate Website|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/BT-CO-20110613-710201.html|accessdate=13 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Wall Street Journal]]|date=13 June 2011|agency=[[News Corporation]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zQ4f2HSh|archivedate=13 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 June, LulzSec launched an attack on [https://www.cia.gov/ www.cia.gov], the public website of the United States [[Central Intelligence Agency]], taking the website offline with a distributed denial-of-service attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=CIA website hacked; LulzSec takes credit (again)|url=http://news.consumerreports.org/electronics/2011/06/cia-website-hacked-lulzsec-takes-credit-again.html|accessdate=16 June 2011|newspaper=[[Consumer Reports]]|date=16 June 2011|agency=[[Consumers Union]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zUA8dfRY|archivedate=16 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The website was down from 5:48&amp;nbsp;pm to 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm [[eastern time]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Nakashima|first=Ellen|title=CIA Web site hacked; group LulzSec takes credit|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/national-security/cia-web-site-hacked/2011/06/15/AGGNphWH_story.html|accessdate=16 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Washington Post]]|date=15 June 2011|agency=[[The Washington Post Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zUASjkPo|archivedate=16 June 2011|location=Washington, D.C.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 December, an offshot of LulzSec calling itself LulzSec Portugal attacked several sites related to the [[government of Portugal]]. The websites for the [[Bank of Portugal]], the [[Assembly of the Republic]], and the [[Ministry of Economy, Innovation and Development]] all became unavailable for a few hours.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Hackers voltam a atacar sites portugueses|url=http://www.tvi24.iol.pt/tecnologia/lulzsec-hackers-tvi24/1304669-4069.html|accessdate=3 December 2011|newspaper=[[TVI 24]]|date=2 December 2011|agency=[[Televisão Independente]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63eAeLaIr|archivedate=3 December 2011|language=Portuguese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Operation Anti-Security ==
{{main|Operation AntiSec}}
On 20 June, the group announced it had teamed up with Anonymous for &quot;Operation Anti-Security&quot;. They encouraged supporters to hack into, steal, and publish classified government information from any source while leaving the term &quot;Antisec&quot; as evidence of their intrusion. Also listed as potential targets were major banks.&lt;ref name=aussie&gt;{{cite news|last=Ross|first=Nick|title=Lulzsec teams up with Anonymous|url=http://www.abc.net.au/technology/articles/2011/06/20/3248520.htm|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[ABC Online]]|date=20 June 2011|agency=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[USA Today]] characterized the operation as an open declaration of [[cyberwarfare]] against big government and corporations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Acohido|first=Byron|title=LulzSec, Anonymous declare war against governments, corporations|url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/technologylive/post/2011/06/lulzsec-anonymous-declare-war-against-governments-corporations/1|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[USA Today]]|date=20 June 2011|agency=[[Gannett Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zaKQaWdZ|archivedate=20 June 2011|location=[[McLean, Virginia]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Their first target of the operation was the [[Serious Organised Crime Agency]] (SOCA), a national [[law enforcement agency]] of the United Kingdom. LulzSec claimed to have taken the website offline at about 11&amp;nbsp;am EST on 20 June 2011, though it only remained down for a few minutes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Meyer|first=David|title=LulzSec claims Soca hack|url=http://www.zdnet.co.uk/blogs/communication-breakdown-10000030/lulzsec-claims-soca-hack-10022772/|accessdate=20 June 2011|newspaper=[[ZDNet]]|date=20 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zaPT1ekX|archivedate=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the attack appeared to be a DDoS attack, LulzSec tweeted that actual hacking was taking place &quot;behind the scenes&quot;. At about 6:10&amp;nbsp;pm EST on 20 June, SOCA's website went down yet again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Soca website taken down after LulzSec 'Ddos attack'|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13848510|accessdate=20 June 2011|date=20 June 2011|newspaper=BBC  }}&lt;/ref&gt; SOCA's website was back online sometime between 20 and 21 June.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Henderson|first=Nicole|title=SOCA Website Back Online After LulzSec DDoS Attack|url=http://www.thewhir.com/web-hosting-news/062111_SOCA_Website_Back_Online_After_LulzSec_DDoS_Attack|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=Web Host Industry Review|date=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The website of the local district government of [[Jianhua District]] in [[Qiqihar]], [[People's Republic of China|China]], was also knocked offline.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Ragan|first=Steve|title=LulzSec and Anonymous: Hunting for skeletons hidden in closets|url=http://www.thetechherald.com/article.php/201125/7295/LulzSec-and-Anonymous-Hunting-for-skeletons-hidden-in-closets|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Tech Herald]]|date=21 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbHJFF18|archivedate=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Early in the morning on 22 June, it was revealed that LulzSec's &quot;[[Brazil]]ian unit&quot; had taken down two Brazilian government websites, [http://brasil.gov.br brasil.gov.br] and [http://presidencia.gov.br presidencia.gov.br].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Emery|first=Daniel|title=LulzSec hits Brazilian websites|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13878888|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=BBC |date=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Clark|first=Jack|title=LulzSec takes down Brazil government sites|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-1009_3-20073219-83/lulzsec-takes-down-brazil-government-sites/|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=CNet|date=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also brought down the website of Brazilian energy company [[Petrobras]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McMillan|first=Robert|title=Brazilian Government, Energy Company Latest LulzSec Victims|url=http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/230902/brazilian_government_energy_company_latest_lulzsec_victims.html|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine){{!}}PC World]]|date=22 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdkR3nOy|archivedate=22 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 June, two members on the &quot;Lulz Boat&quot; reportedly leaked logs that LulzSec was going to leak on 21 June. They also claimed that the two had leaked information that aided authorities in locating and arresting Ryan Cleary, a man loosely affiliated with the group.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rodriguez|first=Salvador|title=LulzSec says it's outing two who may have led to arrest of an alleged hacker|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/technology/2011/06/lulzsec-outs-snitches.html|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]]|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[Tribune Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zcS90U8D|archivedate=22 June 2011|location=Los Angeles}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec posted various personal information about the two on [[Pastebin]] including [[IP address]]es and physical addresses. Both had been involved with cyber-crimes in the past, and one had been involved with hacking the game [[Deus Ex]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Aamoth|first=Doug|title=Trouble in Paradise? LulzSec Outs Two Apparent 'Snitches'|url=http://techland.time.com/2011/06/21/trouble-in-paradise-lulzsec-outs-two-apparent-snitches-to-the-fbi/#ixzz1Pwt7oST2|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=TechLand (Time Magazine)|date=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After LulzSec encouragement, some began tagging public locations with physical [[graffiti]] reading &quot;Antisec&quot; as part of the operation. Numerous beachfronts in [[Mission Beach, San Diego]] were vandalized with the phrase.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gayathri|first=Amrutha|title=Operation Anti-Security: Mysterious serial graffiti reported; LulzSec gaining mass support?|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/166507/20110621/operation-anti-security-mysterious-serial-graffiti-reported-lulzsec-gaining-mass-support-anonymous-h.htm|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[International Business Times]]|date=21 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbDnFq7t|archivedate=21 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some local news organizations mistook the graffiti in Mission Beach as signs of the [[Antisec Movement]]. Many commenters on the local news websites corrected this.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=&quot;Anti-Sec&quot; group spreads message through graffiti in Mission Beach|url=http://www.cbs8.com/story/14941495/anti-sec-group-spreads-message-through-graffiti-in-mission-beach?redirected=true|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=CBS 8|date=20 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 June, LulzSec released a number of documents pertaining to the [[Arizona Department of Public Safety]], which they titled &quot;chinga la migra&quot;, which roughly translates to &quot;fuck the border patrol&quot;. The leaked items included email addresses and passwords, as well as hundreds of documents marked &quot;sensitive&quot; or &quot;for official use only&quot;. LulzSec claimed that this was in protest of the [[Arizona SB 1070|law]] passed in Arizona requiring some aliens to carry registration documents at all times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Tsotsis|first=Alexia|title=LulzSec Releases Arizona Law Enforcement Data In Retaliation For Immigration Law|url=http://techcrunch.com/2011/06/23/lulzsec-releases-arizona-law-enforcement-data-in-retaliation-for-immigration-law/|accessdate=23 June 2011|newspaper=TechCrunch|date=23 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Aamoth|first=Doug|title=LulzSec Claims Breach Against Arizona Law Enforcement|url=http://techland.time.com/2011/06/23/lulzsec-claims-breach-against-arizona-law-enforcement/|accessdate=23 June 2011|newspaper=Techland (Time)|date=23 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arizona officials have confirmed the intrusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lohr|first=Steve|title=Arrest Puts Spotlight on Brazen Hacking Group LulzSec|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/24/technology/24hack.html|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=23 June 2011|agency=[[The New York Times Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/mainframe.php|archivedate=24 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arizona police have complained that the release of officer identities and the method used to combat gangs could endanger the lives of police officers.&lt;ref name=damon&gt;{{cite news|last=Poeter|first=Damon|title=Will LulzSec's Hit on Arizona Cops be its Last Hurrah?|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2387566,00.asp|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC Magazine]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[Ziff Davis]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh16iRcx|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 June 2011, LulzSecBrazil published what they claimed were access codes and passwords that they used to access the Petrobras website and employee profile data they had taken using the information. Petrobras denied that any data had been stolen, and LulzSecBrazil removed the information from their Twitter feed a few hours later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rapoza|first=Kenneth|title=LulzSec Strikes Brazil Again; Petrobras Denies Being Hacked|url=http://blogs.forbes.com/kenrapoza/2011/06/25/lulzsec-strikes-brazil-again-petrobras-denies-being-hacked/|accessdate=26 June 2011|newspaper=[[Forbes Magazine]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=[[Forbes]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zjTPRtmX|archivedate=26 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group also released personal information regarding [[President of Brazil]] [[Dilma Rousseff]] and [[Mayor of São Paulo]] [[Gilberto Kassab]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Lopez|first=Luciana|title=Hackers target Brazilian statistics agency|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/06/24/us-cybersecurity-brazil-hackers-idUSTRE75N2EK20110624|accessdate=26 June 2011|agency=Reuters  |date=24 June 2011|author2=Brian Ellsworth|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zjTsNsY5|archivedate=26 June 2011|location=London|editor=Anthony Boadle}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 June 2011, LulzSec released what they described as their last data dump. The release contained an enormous amount of information from various sources. The files contained a half [[gigabyte]] of internal information from telecommunication company [[AT&amp;T]], including information relating to its release of [[4G]] LTE and details pertaining to over 90,000 personal phones used by [[IBM]]. The [[IP address]]es of several large corporations including Sony, [[Viacom]], and [[Disney]], [[EMI]], and [[NBC Universal]] were included.&lt;ref name=greenberg/&gt;&lt;ref name=whittaker/&gt; It also contained over 750,000 username and password combinations from several websites,&lt;ref name=whittaker&gt;{{cite news|last=Whittaker|first=Zack|title=LulzSec disbands: Final cache includes AT&amp;T internal data and 750,000 user accounts|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/igeneration/lulzsec-disbands-final-cache-includes-at-t-internal-data-and-750000-user-accounts/11134|accessdate=26 June 2011|newspaper=[[ZDNet]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zijhtzV4|archivedate=26 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; including 200,000 email addresses, usernames, and encrypted passwords from hackforums.net; 12,000 names, usernames, and passwords of the [[NATO]] online bookshop; half a million usernames and encrypted passwords of players of the online game ''[[Battlefield Heroes]]''; 50,000 usernames, email addresses, and encrypted passwords of various video game forum users; and 29 users of Priority Investigations, an Irish [[private investigator|private investigation]] company. Also included were an internal manual for [[AOL]] engineering staff and a screencapture of a vandalized page from [[navy.mil]], the website of the [[United States Navy]].&lt;ref name=greenberg&gt;{{cite news|last=Greenberg|first=Andy|title=LulzSec Says Goodbye, Dumping NATO, AT&amp;T, Gamer Data|url=http://blogs.forbes.com/andygreenberg/2011/06/25/lulzsec-says-goodbye-dumping-nato-att-gamer-data/|accessdate=26 June 2011|newspaper=[[Forbes Magazine]]|date=25 June 2011|agency=[[Forbes]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5ziimGwf5|archivedate=26 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; Members of the group continued the operation with members of Anonymous after disbanding.&lt;ref name=newantisec/&gt;

Despite claiming to have retired, on 18 July LulzSec hacked into the website of British newspaper ''[[The Sun (United Kingdom)|The Sun]]''.&lt;ref name=Gayomail&gt;{{cite news|last=Gayomail|first=Chris|title=LulzSec Hacks 'News of the World' and 'The Sun,' Plants Fake Murdoch Death Story|url=http://techland.time.com/2011/07/18/lulzsec-hacks-news-of-the-world-and-the-sun-plants-fake-murdoch-death-story/|accessdate=18 July 2011|newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|Time]]|date=18 July 2011|agency=[[Time Inc.]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60HMwKM98|archivedate=18 July 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group redirected the newspaper's website to an also-hacked redesign website of another newspaper ''[[The Times]]'', altering the site to resemble ''The Sun'' and posting a fake story claiming that [[Rupert Murdoch]] had died after ingesting a fatal dose of [[palladium]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rovzar|first=Chris|title=Website of Murdoch’s Sun Hacked|url=http://nymag.com/daily/intel/2011/07/website_of_murdochs_sun_hacked.html|accessdate=18 July 2011|newspaper=[[New York (magazine)|New York Magazine]]|date=18 July 2011|agency=New York Media Holdings|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60HMbQTWj|archivedate=18 July 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; They objected to the involvement of [[News Corporation]], the Murdoch-owned company that publishes ''The Sun'' and ''The Times'', in a large [[News International phone hacking scandal|phone hacking scandal]]. The hacked website also contained a webcomic depicting LulzSec deciding on and carrying out the attack.&lt;ref name=Gayomail/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Media moguls body discovered|url=http://www.new-times.co.uk/sun/|work=[[The Times]]|publisher=[[News Corporation]]|accessdate=18 July 2011|author=Anonymous|authorlink=Anonymous (group)|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60HLGySde|archivedate=18 July 2011|location=[[London]]|date=18 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group later redirected ''The Sun'' website to their Twitter feed. News International released a statement regarding the attacks before having the page the statement appeared on also redirected to the LulzSec Twitter page and eventually taken offline. The group also released the names and phone numbers of a reporter for ''The Sun'' and two others associated with the newspaper and encouraged their supporters to call them. They further included an old email address and password of former News International executive [[Rebekah Brooks]].&lt;ref name=cnetsun&gt;{{cite news|last=Mills|first=Elinor|title=Hackers target Murdoch newspaper Web site|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-27080_3-20080503-245/hackers-target-murdoch-newspaper-web-site/|accessdate=19 July 2011|newspaper=[[CNET]]|date=18 July 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60HaIaC2J|archivedate=19 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; News Corporation took the websites offline as a precaution later in the day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14196327|title=Lulz Security hackers target Sun website|newspaper=[[BBC News]]|publisher=[[BBC]]|location=[[London]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60IIHshJQ|archivedate=19 July 2011|date=18 July 2011|accessdate=19 July 2011|}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Denied attacks ==
The media reported a number of attacks, originally attributed to LulzSec, that the group later denied involvement in. On 21 June, someone claiming to be from the group posted on Pastebin that they had stolen the entire database of the [[United Kingdom Census 2011]]. LulzSec responded by saying that they had obtained no such data and that whoever posted the notice was not from the group. British officials say that they are investigating the incident but have found no evidence that any databases had been compromised or any information taken.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Paul|first=Ian|title=LulzSec Denies Taking U.K. Census Data|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/230797/lulzsec_denies_taking_uk_census_data.html|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine){{!}}PC World]]|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbvpKEdZ|archivedate=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British government, upon concluding their investigation, called the claims that any information on the census was taken a [[hoax]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Halliday|first=Josh|title=LulzSec census hacking claims 'a hoax'|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/22/lulzsec-census-hacking-claims-a-hoax|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=22 June 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdhM9Ab3|archivedate=22 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 2011, assets belonging to newspaper publisher [[News International]] were attacked, apparently in retaliation for reporting by [[The Sun (United Kingdom)|''The Sun'']] of the arrest of Ryan Cleary, an associate of the group. The newspaper's website and a computer used in the publishing process of ''[[The Times]]'' were attacked.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Rayner|first=Gordon|title=Hackers hit News International in revenge for coverage of teenager's arrest|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/news/8594823/Hackers-hit-News-International-in-revenge-for-coverage-of-teenagers-arrest.html|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=23 June 2011|agency=Telegraph Media Group|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zfnzNIFf|archivedate=24 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; However LulzSec denied any involvement, stating &quot;we didn't attack ''The Sun'' or ''The Times'' in any way with any kind of DDoS attack&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Stevenson|first=Alastair|title=LulzSec deny revenge hacks on the Sun and Times newspaper websites|url=http://uk.ibtimes.com/articles/168991/20110624/lulzsec-lulz-security-operation-anti-ryan-cleary-arrest-charge-trial-revenge-attacks-hack-hackers-ha.htm|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[International Business Times]]|date=24 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zgoT4bcO|archivedate=24 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Hacker actions against LulzSec ==
A number of different hackers have targeted LulzSec and its members in response to their activities. On 23 June 2011, [[Fox News]] reported that rival hacker group [[TeaMp0isoN]] were responsible for outing web designer and alleged LulzSec member [[Sven Slootweg]], who they said used the online nickname Joepie91,&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec sails into sunset as TeaMp0isoN terrorizes Internet|url=http://sanfrancisco.ibtimes.com/articles/169577/20110625/lulzsec-sails-into-sunset-as-teamp0ison-terrorizes-internet-antisec-anti-security-anonymous-hacker.htm|accessdate=4 July 2011|online=[[International Business Times]]|date=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that they have intentions to do the same with every member.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Winter|first=Jana|title=Exclusive: Rival Hacker Group Racing Police to Expose LulzSec|url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/06/23/hacker-vs-hacker-group-races-police-to-expose-lulzsec/|accessdate=23 June 2011|online=[[Fox News]]|date=23 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The group has expressed being motivated by what they perceive as LulzSec's low hacking abilities, bringing them media attention they do not deserve. One member of the group, Hex0010, proclaimed &quot;We're here to show the world that they're nothing but a bunch of script kiddies. You think, 'I'm a bad-ass hacker because I can knock someone offline for a few minutes.' That's bullshit. Come on.&quot;&lt;ref name=civilwar&gt;{{cite news|last=Mack|first=Eric|title=Hacker Civil War Heats Up|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/231078/hacker_civil_war_heats_up.html|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine)]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh325N6R|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A group calling themselves Team Web Ninjas appeared in June 2011 saying they were angry over LulzSec release of the e-mail addresses and passwords of thousands of normal Internet users. They have attempted to publicly identify the online and real world identities of LulzSec leadership and claim to do so on behalf of the group's victims.&lt;ref name=enemies/&gt; The group has claimed to have identified and given to law enforcement the names of a number of the group's members, including someone they claim is a [[United States Marine]].&lt;ref name=civilwar/&gt;

[[The Jester (hacktivist)|The Jester]], a hacker who generally goes by the [[leetspeak]] handle th3j35t3r, has vowed to find and expose members of LulzSec.&lt;ref name=damon/&gt; Claiming to perform hacks out of a sense of [[American patriotism]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=WikiLeaks Struggles to Stay Online After Attacks |first=Ashlee |last=Vance |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/12/04/world/europe/04domain.html |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date=3 December 2010 |accessdate=29 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; he has attempted to obtain and publish the real world [[personally identifiable information]] of key members, whom he describes as &quot;childish&quot;.&lt;ref name=enemies&gt;{{cite news|last=Halliday|first=Josh|title=LulzSec: the members and the enemies|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/24/lulzsec-members-and-enemies|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh27Q4f6|archivedate=25 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 June 2011, he claimed to have revealed the identity of LulzSec leader Sabu as an [[Information technology consulting|information technology consultant]] possibly from New York City.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Chapman|first=Stephen|title=LulzSec's leader, Sabu, revealed?|url=http://www.zdnet.com/blog/security/lulzsecs-leader-sabu-revealed/8905|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[ZDNet]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Interactive]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh1hqAmI|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 June 2011, a hacker allegedly going by the name Oneiroi briefly took down the LulzSec website in what he labelled &quot;Operation Supernova&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Halliday|first=Josh|title=LulzSec site taken down by lone-wolf hacker|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/blog/2011/jun/24/lulzsec-site-down-hacker-jester|accessdate=24 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zgouRbuf|archivedate=24 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Twitter page for the group also briefly became unavailable.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pakinkis|first=Tom|title=LulzSec hacked by anti-hacking group?|url=http://www.computerandvideogames.com/308986/lulzsec-hacked-by-anti-hacking-group/|accessdate=25 June 2011|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[ComputerAndVideoGames.com]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh3nRNnA|archivedate=25 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 June 2011, ''[[The Guardian]]'' published leaked logs from one of the group's IRC channels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Arthur|first=Charles|title=News Technology LulzSec LulzSec IRC leak: the full record|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/24/lulzsec-irc-leak-the-full-record|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=24 June 2011|author2=Ryan Gallagher|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh8gqbxW|archivedate=25 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The logs were supposedly leaked by a disgruntled former member of the group who goes by the nickname m_nerva.&lt;ref name=logs&gt;{{cite news|last=Gallagher|first=Ryan|title=Inside LulzSec: Chatroom logs shine a light on the secretive hackers|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/24/inside-lulzsec-chatroom-logs-hackers|accessdate=25 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=24 June 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zh93KYuO|archivedate=25 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; After confirming that these leaked logs were indeed theirs, and that the logs revealed personal information on two members who had recently left the group due to the implications of attacking the FBI website, LulzSec went on to threaten m_nerva on their Twitter feed.&lt;ref name=logs/&gt; LulzSec claimed that the logs were not from one of their core chatting channels, but rather a secondary channel used to screen potential backups and gather research.&lt;ref name=logs/&gt;

A short time before LulzSec claimed to be disbanding, a group calling itself the A-Team posted what they claimed was a full list of LulzSec members online along with numerous chat logs of the group communicating with each other. A rival hacker going by the name of TriCk also claimed to be working to reveal the group's identities and claimed that efforts on the part of rival hackers had pushed the group to disband for fear of being caught.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Taylor|first=Jerome|title=Hactivist collective LulzSec disbands|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/crime/hactivist-collective-lulzsec-disbands-2303095.html|accessdate=26 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Independent]]|date=26 June 2011|agency=Independent Print Limited|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zjT0nnIJ|archivedate=26 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Law enforcement response ==
{{anchor|Ryan Cleary}}On 21 June 2011, the [[Metropolitan Police]] announced that they had arrested a 19 year old man from [[Wickford]], Essex, named by LulzSec and locally as Ryan Cleary,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-13859868|title=Teenager arrested on suspicion of hacking|accessdate=21 June 2011|publisher=BBC|date=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; as part of an operation carried out in cooperation with the FBI.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://content.met.police.uk/News/eCrime-unit-arrest-man/1260269113895/1257246741786|title=e-Crime unit arrest man|accessdate=21 June 2011|publisher=[[Metropolitan Police Service]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The suspect was arrested on charges of [[Computer Misuse Act 1990|computer misuse]] and [[fraud]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Schwartz|first=Matthew|title=Scotland Yard Busts Alleged LulzSec Mastermind|url=http://www.informationweek.com/news/security/attacks/231000063|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[InformationWeek]]|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[UBM plc]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbuNvjGb|archivedate=21 June 2011|location=San Francisco}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later charged with five counts of computer hacking under the [[Criminal Law Act 1977|Criminal Law Act]] and the Computer Misuse Act.&lt;ref name=charged&gt;{{cite news|last=Dodd|first=Vikram|title=Teenager Ryan Cleary charged over LulzSec hacking|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/22/ryan-cleary-charged-lulzsec-hacking|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=22 June 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdVEI7rE|archivedate=22 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; News reports described him as an alleged member of LulzSec.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Williams|first=Christopher|title=Hackers 'steal entire 2011 census'|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/news/8589078/Hackers-steal-entire-2011-census.html|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=21 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec have since denied the man arrested was a member.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Martinez|first=Edecio|title=LulzSec responds to UK hacker arrest, says &quot;we're all still here!&quot;|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-501465_162-20072915-501465.html|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[CBS News]]|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[CBS Corporation]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbukd0Dp|archivedate=21 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; A member of LulzSec claimed that the suspect was not part of the group, but did host one of its [[IRC channel]]s on his server.&lt;ref name=hardawar&gt;{{cite news|last=Hardawar|first=Devindra|title=LulzSec denies involvement in UK Census hack, suspected member arrested|url=http://venturebeat.com/2011/06/21/lulzsec-denies-involvement-in-uk-census-hack-suspected-member-arrested/|accessdate=21 June 2011|newspaper=[[VentureBeat]]|date=21 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zbw9uGl4|archivedate=21 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; British police representatives have confirmed that he is being questioned regarding alleged involvement in LulzSec attacks against the Serious Organized Crime Agency (SOCA) and other targets. They also questioned him regarding an attack on the [[International Federation of the Phonographic Industry]] in November 2010.&lt;ref name=charged/&gt; On 25 June 2011 the court released Cleary under the bail conditions that he did not leave his house without his mother and did not use any device connected to the internet. He had been diagnosed the previous week with [[Asperger syndrome]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Halliday|first=Josh|title=Teen accused of attacking SOCA website released on conditional bail|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/27/teenager-accused-lulzsec-hacking-bail|accessdate=27 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=27 June 2011|agency=Guardian Media Group|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zlPzZ2Eh|archivedate=27 June 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At around the same time as Cleary's arrest, [[Federal Bureau of Investigation]] agents raided the [[Reston, Virginia]] facility of [[Switzerland|Swiss]] [[web hosting service]] DigitalOne.&lt;ref name=digitalone&gt;{{cite news|last=Williams|first=Christopher|title=FBI seized web servers as LulzSec suspect was arrested|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/news/8591526/FBI-seized-web-servers-as-LulzSec-suspect-was-arrested.html|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Daily Telegraph]]|date=22 June 2011|agency=Telegraph Media Group|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zdWdF4vd|archivedate=22 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The raid took several legitimate websites offline for hours as the agency looked for information on an undisclosed target.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kopytoff|first=Verne|title=F.B.I. Seizes Web Servers, Knocking Sites Offline|url=http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/06/21/f-b-i-seizes-web-servers-knocking-sites-offline/|accessdate=22 June 2011|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|date=21 June 2011|agency=[[The New York Times Company]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/mainframe.php|archivedate=22 June 2011|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt; Media reports have speculated that the raid may have been related to the LulzSec investigation.&lt;ref name=digitalone/&gt;

After LulzSec hacked into Arizona Department of Public Safety databases, law enforcement activated the [[Arizona Counter Terrorism Information Center]]. All Department of Public Safety employees had [[remote access]] of their email accounts suspended. Officers that had their personal information and that of their families released publicly were given additional protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=DPS Victim of Cyber Attack|url=http://www.azdps.gov/Media/News/View/?p=316|work=Press Releases|publisher=[[Arizona Department of Public Safety]]|accessdate=30 June 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zonSmr0O|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[Phoenix, Arizona]]|date=27 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They further reiterated that, despite having disbanded, members of LulzSec were still being pursued for criminal prosecution.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=DPS response to recent cyber attack|url=http://www.kvoa.com/news/dps-response-to-recent-cyber-attack/|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[KVOA]]|date=27 June 2011|agency=[[NBC]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zonmvIeM|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[Tucson, Arizona]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A few days before LulzSec disbanded, the FBI executed a [[search warrant]] on an [[Iowa]] home rented by Laurelai Bailey. Authorities interviewed her for five hours and confiscated her hard drives, camera, and other electronic equipment, but no charges were filed. Bailey denied being a member of the group, but did admit to chatting with members of LulzSec online and later leaking those chats.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Paul|first=Ian|title=FBI Steps Up Hunt for LulzSec|url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/231381/fbi_steps_up_hunt_for_lulzsec.html|accessdate=29 June 2011|newspaper=[[PC World (magazine){{!}}PC World]]|date=29 June 2011|agency=[[IDG]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zoZ86awM|archivedate=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were interested in having her infiltrate the group, but Bailey claimed that the members hated her and would never let her in.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Choney|first=Suzanne|title=A female hacker in the mix?|url=http://technolog.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2011/06/28/6966916-a-female-hacker-in-the-mix|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[MSNBC]]|date=28 June 2011|agency=[[NBCUniversal]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zop5K0am|archivedate=30 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The questioning by the FBI led a local [[technical support]] company to fire Laurelai, claiming that she had embarrassed the company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Finally! Hackers switch tactics and bring down Al Qaeda's communications, as FBI closes in on group after 50-day spree: FBI raids home of woman in Iowa as it continues investigation into hacking group LulzSec|url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2009594/FBI-raids-womans-home-agents-close-LulzSec-hackers-50-day-spree.html|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[Daily Mail]]|date=30 June 2011|agency=[[Associated Newspapers]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zq2L74n5|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chen|first=Adrian|title=FBI Raids Iowa Woman’s Home in Lulz Security Hacker Investigation|url=http://gawker.com/5816291/fbi-raids-iowa-womans-home-in-lulz-security-hacker-investigation|publisher=[[Gawker]]. [[Gawker Media]]|accessdate=15 July 2011|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60CG3TwKi|archivedate=15 July 2011|date=28 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 June 2011, the FBI executed another search warrant in [[Hamilton, Ohio]]. The local media connected the raid to the LulzSec investigation; however, the warrant is sealed, the name of the target was not revealed, and the FBI office in [[Cincinnati]] refused to comment on any possible connection between the group and the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=McMillan|first=Robert|title=With FBI raid, law enforcement circles LulzSec|url=http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9218040/With_FBI_raid_law_enforcement_circles_LulzSec?taxonomyId=82|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[Computerworld]]|date=29 June 2011|agency=[[International Data Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zopzRrfK|archivedate=30 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; No one in the residence was charged with a crime after the FBI served the warrant.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pack|first=Lauren|title=FBI hacking probe leads to area teen|url=http://www.middletownjournal.com/news/crime/fbi-hacking-probe-leads-to-area-teen-1195829.html|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Middletown Journal]]|date=28 June 2011|agency=[[Cox Enterprises]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zpPaX4nl|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[Middletown, Ohio]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some reports suggested the house may belong to former LulzSec member m_nerva, who leaked a number of the group's logs to the press, and information leading to the warrant supplied by Ryan Cleary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Arthur|first=Charles|title=LulzSec hacking suspect's house searched in Hamilton, Ohio|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/jun/29/lulzsec-hacking-suspect-hamilton-ohio|accessdate=30 June 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5zpQkXbNj|archivedate=30 June 2011|location=[[London]]|date=29 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 July 2011, the London Metropolitan Police announced the arrest of LulzSec member Tflow. A 16 year-old male was arrested in South London on charges of violating the Computer Misuse Act as part of an operation involving the arrest of several other hackers affiliated with Anonymous in the United States and United Kingdom.&lt;ref name=tflow&gt;{{cite news|last=Kaplan|first=Jeremy|title=Leading Member of LulzSec Hacker Squad Arrested in London|url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/07/19/leading-member-lulzsec-hacker-squad-arrested-in-london/|accessdate=20 July 2011|newspaper=[[Fox News Channel]]|date=19 July 2011|agency=[[News Corporation]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60J70ybQ5|archivedate=20 July 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Greenberg|first=Andy|title=Hacker Arrests May Have Included Core Member Of LulzSec|url=http://blogs.forbes.com/andygreenberg/2011/07/19/hacker-arrests-may-have-included-core-member-of-lulzsec/|accessdate=20 July 2011|newspaper=[[Forbes]]|date=19 July 2011|agency=Forbes Publishing|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60J6iInOP|archivedate=20 July 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; LulzSec once again denied that any of their membership had been arrested, stating &quot;there are six of us, and we're all still here.&quot;&lt;ref name=nl&gt;{{cite news|last=Sterling|first=Toby|title=Dutch give details on 4 'Anonymous' hacker arrests|url=http://news.smh.com.au/breaking-news-technology/dutch-give-details-on-4-anonymous-hacker-arrests-20110721-1hp9g.html|accessdate=21 July 2011|newspaper=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]|date=21 July 2011|agency=[[Fairfax Media]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60Lj08HZB|archivedate=21 July 2011|location=[[Sydney]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the same day, the FBI arrested 21-year-old Lance Moore in [[Las Cruces, New Mexico]]. He was accused of stealing thousands of documents and applications from AT&amp;T that LulzSec published as part of their so called &quot;final release&quot;.&lt;ref name=nl/&gt; The FBI also arrested Scott Arciszewski, a 21-year old [[University of Central Florida]] student. The criminal complaint against him claims that he hacked into and uploaded malicious files to the InfraGard website; he then informed LulzSec of the vulnerabilities he had inserted, allowing them to hack into the website as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Pelofsky|first=Jeremy|title=Hacking groups say they are back after FBI arrests|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/07/21/us-cybersecurity-response-idUSTRE76K66G20110721|accessdate=22 July 2011|newspaper=[[Reuters]]|date=21 July 2011|agency=[[Thomson Reuters]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60Mw3TEGz|archivedate=22 July 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Police National E-Crime Unit|Police Central E-Crime Unit]] arrested an 18-year-old man from [[Shetland]] on 27 July 2011 suspected of being LulzSec member [[Topiary (hacktivist)|Topiary]]. They also searched the house of and interviewed a 17-year-old from [[Lincolnshire]] possibly connected to the investigation.&lt;ref name=topiaryarrest&gt;{{cite news|title=Man arrested over computer hacking claims|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14315442|accessdate=27 July 2011|newspaper=[[BBC News]]|date=27 July 2011|agency=[[BBC]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60V2b9j2F|archivedate=27 July 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Scotland Yard later identified the man arrested as [[Yell, Shetland]] resident Jake Davis. He was charged with unauthorized access of a computer under the [[Computer Misuse Act 1990]], encouraging or assisting criminal activity under the [[Serious Crime Act 2007]], conspiracy to launch a denial-of-service attack against the Serious Organised Crime Unit contrary to the [[Criminal Law Act 1977]], and [[criminal conspiracy]] also under the Criminal Law Act 1977.&lt;ref name=topiaryid&gt;{{cite news|last=Albanesius|first=Chloe|title=Report: Scotland Yard Identifies LulzSec Hacker|url=http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2389486,00.asp|accessdate=31 July 2011|newspaper=[[PC Magazine]]|date=31 July 2011|agency=[[Ziff Davis]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60b797m4U|archivedate=31 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police confiscated a [[Dell]] laptop and a 100-gigabyte hard drive that ran 16 different [[virtual machine]]s. Details relating to an attack on Sony and hundreds of thousands of email addresses and passwords were found on the computer.&lt;ref name=topiarybail&gt;{{cite news|last=Prodhan|first=Georgina|title=UK teen cyber activist bailed without Internet access|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/08/01/us-britain-hacking-anonymous-idUSTRE7702HH20110801|accessdate=1 August 2011|newspaper=[[Reuters]]|date=1 August 2011|agency=[[Thomson Reuters]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/60cfULJNm|archivedate=1 August 2011|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; A London court released Davis on bail under the conditions that he live under curfew with his parents and have no access to the internet. His lawyer Gideon Cammerman stated that, while his client did help publicize LulzSec and Anonymous attacks, he lacks the technical skills to have been anything but a sympathizer.&lt;ref name=topiarybail/&gt;

In early September 2011, Scotland Yard made two further arrests relating to LulzSec. Police arrested a 24-year-old male in [[Mexborough]], [[South Yorkshire]] and a 20-year-old male in [[Warminster]], [[Wiltshire]]. The two are accused of conspiring to commit offenses under the Computer Misuse Act of 1990; police said that the arrests related to investigations into LulzSec member Kayla.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=LulzSec and Anonymous police and FBI investigation sees two more arrested|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2011/sep/02/lulzsec-anonymous-two-more-arrests|accessdate=2 September 2011|newspaper=[[The Guardian]]|date=2 September 2011|agency=[[Guardian Media Group]]|location=[[London]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 September 2011, the FBI arrested Cody Kretsinger, a 23-year-old from [[Phoenix, Arizona]] who has been indicted on charges of conspiracy and the unauthorized impairment of a protected computer. He is suspected of using the name recursion and assisting LulzSec in their early hack against Sony Pictures Entertainment, though he allegedly erased the hard drives he used to carry out the attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=FBI Arrests Suspected LulzSec and Anonymous Hackers|url=http://www.foxnews.com/scitech/2011/09/22/fbi-arrests-suspected-lulzsec-and-anonymous-hackers/|accessdate=22 September 2011|newspaper=[[Fox News]]|date=22 September 2011|agency= [[News Corporation]]|location=[[New York City]]|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/61uw3G620|archivedate=23 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Kretsinger was released on his own recognizance under the conditions that he not access the internet except while at work and that he not travel to any states other than Arizona, California, or Illinois. The case against him was filed in [[Los Angeles]], where Sony Pictures is located.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gorman|first=Steve|title=Suspected LulzSec hacker arrested in Sony studio breach|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/09/23/us-sony-hacking-arrest-idUSTRE78L6QO20110923|accessdate=23 September 2011|newspaper=[[Forbes]]|date=23 September 2011|agency=Forbes Publishing|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/61uwX01S9|archivedate=23 September 2011|location=[[New York City]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Operation Payback]]
* [[Hacktivism]]
* [[PlayStation Network outage]]
* [[Operation Anti-Security]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Portal box|Computer security|Internet}}
*{{twitter|lulzsec|Lulz Security}}
* [http://www.formspring.me/LulzSec LulzSec] at [[Formspring]]

{{2010's hacking}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lulz Security}}
[[Category:Cyberattacks]]
[[Category:Internet activists]]
[[Category:Internet vigilantism]]
[[Category:2011 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:Wikipedia articles with ASCII art]]

[[ar:لولزسك]]
[[de:LulzSec]]
[[es:Lulz Security]]
[[fr:LulzSec]]
[[it:LulzSec]]
[[nl:LulzSec]]
[[pt:LulzSec]]
[[ru:LulzSec]]
[[fi:Lulz Security]]
[[vi:LulzSec]]
[[zh:LulzSec]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
