<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3197987" ns="0" title="Sam Dingle"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|image=[[Image:Sam Dingle.jpg|200px]]
|name=Sam Dingle
|portrayer=[[James Hooton]]
|first = 14 February 1995
|last =
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|spinoffs= ''Emmerdale: The Dingles, For Richer for Poorer (2010)''
|years=1995–98, 2000—
|born= 16 August 1977
|introducer = Mervyn Watson (1995)&lt;br /&gt;Kieran Roberts (2000)
|home=Wishing Well Cottage
|occupation= {{nowrap|Caretaker of Home Farm Estates}}
|family=[[Dingle family|Dingle]]
|wife = [[Alice Dingle|Alice Wilson]] (2006)
|father = [[Zak Dingle]]
|mother = Nellie Dingle
|brothers = Nathan Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]
|halfbrothers= [[Cain Dingle]]
|sisters = Tina Dingle
|halfsisters = [[Belle Dingle]]
|sons = [[Samson Dingle]]
|nieces = [[Debbie Dingle]]
|nephews = [[Aaron Livesy]]
|grandfathers = [[Jedediah Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;Jimmy Lynch 
|grandmothers = [[Peg Dingle]]
|uncles = [[Shadrach Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Albert Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Caleb Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ezra Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;Zebediah Dingle
|cousins = [[Mandy Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Marlon Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Chas Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Genesis Walker]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lilith Dingle]] &lt;br&gt;[[Delilah Dingle]]
|relatives = [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2005)#Sarah Sudgen|Sarah Sugden]]&lt;br/&gt;Bert Dingle
}}
'''Samuel Jonah &quot;Sam&quot; Dingle''' is a [[fictional character]] from the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[James Hooton]].

==Storylines==
Sam first appears in 1995 and he demands ransom money from the Sugden family. After his release from prison, he worked as a dogsbody for Eric Pollard and was constantly conned out of his wages. He unwittingly helps his uncle Albert with a robbery. He is upset when his mother Nellie leaves to go to live in Ireland.

In 2005, love blossomed for him when he became involved with [[Alice Wilson (Emmerdale)|Alice Wilson]] and they left Emmerdale to start life on their own farm in Norfolk. They returned to Emmerdale soon afterwards, when Sam discovered she was pregnant. In early 2006, Alice gave birth to their son [[Samson]] via [[Caesarean]] so she could start cancer treatment. Their baby boy's name Samson was named after Belle mistook &quot;Sam's son&quot; as his name.  He later married her upon finding out about her terminal cancer. Eventually, she became so weak and unable to even hold her son, Sam obtained some drugs from Eli and delivered the dose that sent her to sleep forever. The police became suspicious as to the exact details of Alice's death when [[Louise Appleton]]'s police boyfriend Martin, heard [[Ashley Thomas]] talking to [[Diane Sugden]] about his suspicions that Sam had helped Alice die. He opened a murder investigation and when the police came to arrest Sam at Wishing Well Cottage, the Dingles barricaded themselves in the house. After gaining entry to the house and arresting Sam, Del declared that she did it. Del was then arrested but soon after, all the Dingles admitted to killing her to protect Sam. Eventually the police picked holes in each of their stories, but out of concern that [[Social Services]] would remove Samson had Sam confessed, Cain told Sam to describe to him everything about Alice's death, so he could convince the police he was telling the truth.

In early 2008, Sam was arrested for [[possession]] after Eli persuaded him to be his courier so he and Samson could live in Dale View in the village. Sam was afraid he'd lose Samson when the police charged him, and ran away with Samson, but soon turned himself in.  Unfortunately, that wasn't the only incident that alarmed the Dingles and Social Services - while living at Dale View, Samson had escaped and been run over by [[Val Pollard]]. She hadn't seen him because she had cataracts in both eyes and needed an operation. Shortly afterwards, Daz's girlfriend, Penny, left [[vodka]] lying around and Samson, thinking it was a soft drink, drank it. Panicking, Sam rushed him to hospital but was fine afterwards.
[[Image:Emily attempts suicide.jpg|thumb|left|Sam saves Emily from drowning herself (2006).]]

Sam worked at Butler's Farm, helping tend [[Jo Sugden]]'s goats, but eventually, Andy sold the goats and, annoyed at Sam and Jo's friendship, fired him. Sam also got a job at [[Eric Pollard]]'s factory shortly before Eric planned to sell the factory to the Kings. Eric let his employees believe he was simply going out of business. When he told Sam he wished the factory would go up in smoke, Sam took him literally and, along with Eli, set fire to the factory. While Andy was away, Sam spent more and more time helping Jo out at the farm for no pay. For the first time since Alice, he was falling in love. Lisa tried to warn him off, but Sam ignored her, hoping he might have a chance with Jo. A few days later, Jo invited Sam for dinner, which he misconstrued as a date. She told him how much she liked him but was shocked when he went to kiss her. Gently, she told him that she didn't feel that way about him and tried to comfort him with a hug but Andy saw them. Sam left but Andy confronted them and beat them both up, putting Jo in hospital again with broken ribs. Lisa, Zak, and Shadrach saw his bruises when they got back home and after treating his cuts, warned him to stay away from Jo and Andy's marriage. Zak also told Andy that while Sam was wrong to have approached Jo like that, Andy was wrong to have beaten him up. Andy was left in no doubt if he touched Sam again, he'd be fighting Zak. With Andy living in the Woolpack, the state of Jo and Andy's deteriorating marriage became common knowledge. He and Sam hadn't made up their differences but Sam warned [[Debbie Dingle]] (Sarah's mother) about what was happening at Butler's Farm. Debbie then kept a very close eye and proceeded to help Jo and Sarah.

[[Olena Petrovich]], an illegal immigrant from the [[Ukraine]], hid in the Dingle's barn until she was discovered by [[Will Wylde]] and [[Belle Dingle]]. She convinced the children not to give her away and they looked after her, until she went missing. They later found her in the woods, in Seth's hide. She had hurt her leg and it was infected. They tried to help her, but were eventually found by Sam. Upon hearing Olena's story, he agreed to keep her whereabouts secret and tended to her wounded leg. Eventually, he convinced Zak and Lisa to take her in and Olena lived with the Dingles, helping out around the house. Sam then persuaded [[Eric Pollard]] to give her a job at the B&amp;B. Although Pollard was apprehensive, he agreed because of his soft spot for Sam. Sam began to fall in love with Olena right away. By January, Zak asked [[Eli Dingle]] to spy on his son and Olena, in case she was a gold-digger. Eli reluctantly agreed, but decided that Olena was genuine and convinced Zak to let Sam make his own choices. Zak then gave Sam his approval to make a go of it with Olena. However, as Sam's behaviour towards Olena became more intense, it became obvious that she did not reciprocate and was feeling increasingly uncomfortable around him.    

When Shadrach half-destroyed the Dingle house by letting the bath overflow, Olena was obliged to move in with Marlon and Eli. Sam missed Olena and kept visiting her at work, but Olena was being more distant. Then, as Lisa, Sam and Olena were driving to pick up some building materials, they were pulled over by the police. Olena panicked, thinking they were after her and so Lisa covered for them as Sam and Olena fled into the woods. When the police noticed Sam and Olena running off, Lisa impulsively punched one of the officers and was arrested. Meanwhile, Olena and Eli began to develop a friendship and, seeing the two of them having a laugh together, Sam was instantly jealous. Olena confided in Eli that she although she was grateful for Sam helping her, she simply did not see him as anything more than a friend. Olena reluctantly moved back in with the Dingles, but she missed living with Eli and Sam began to snipe at his cousin, thinking he was taking Olena from him. 

Zak became increasingly irritated by Olena's presence, until she decided to move back in with Eli and Marlon. Sam was devastated, so when Olena told him that she was upset because she missed her son, he decided to propose to her. Olena turned him down, but seeing his upset, she qualified it by saying that she did not have the right papers and would just be deported. Thinking this was all that was keeping them apart, Sam asked [[Cain Dingle]] to obtain a dodgy passport for Olena. He then told Olena that he understood why she didn't want to marry him and that it would all be OK. Olena and Eli misread this as meaning that he had accepted that Olena did not return his feelings. Cain agreed to get the passport, but mentioned it to Zak, who was furious. However, Zak told Cain to get it anyway and then he went to find Olena. He told her about the passport and said that, once it came through, she was to leave town, without a word to Sam. He would not risk Sam's heart being broken. If she refused to leave, he would have her deported. Tearful, Olena went home and told Eli, who then confessed that he also loved Olena. She said she felt the same and they kissed and began to make plans to elope together once the passport arrived. 

When Olena failed to attend Lisa's Welcome Home party, Sam went looking for her and saw her kissing Eli. He was devastated and reported Olena to Border Control, then watched as she was arrested and dragged away. When a drunken Eli began to accuse people of reporting her, a guilty Sam ended up confessing that it was him. Eli was furious at Sam and launched a glass at his head that narrowly missed. Sam broke down in tears, telling his father that he knew he was nothing but he'd thought, if he tried hard enough, Olena might take a chance on him. Zak comforted his son, but Sam felt guilty and decided to leave the village, taking Samson with him. Lisa finally persuaded him to stay, saying that he could not sleep rough with a toddler. However, Eli - angry at being blamed for Sam's actions - arrived and blasted Sam for ruining Olena's life, before revealing that Zak had already told Olena to leave, or he'd have her deported. 

Sam was livid with his father for interfering in his life and refused to speak to him. He tried to apologise to Pollard for costing him a £7000 fine for hiring Olena. However, Pollard refused to forgive him this time. Sam was gutted to lose Pollard's friendship and Zak ended up convincing Pollard to forgive him and Pollard then advised Sam to forgive his father. Sam tried to make amends to Olena by paying £200 into a bank account for her before finding an unconscious Pollard at the B&amp;B and phoning an ambulance. However, he didn't realise that Eli had robbed the B&amp;B. Suspicions were raised over the missing money and Sam's earlier transaction and he was accused of stealing the money. Pollard tried to get Sam to tell him where the money really came from, but Sam was acting shiftily and lied. When Pollard uncovered his lies, he began to really believe Sam might be the thief. Then Eli confessed to the crime and apologised to Sam before going on the run and Sam admitted that he'd obtained the money through poaching from his employer, [[Natasha Wylde]]. Sam's discovers [[Mark Wylde]]'s body after his dog digs him up and he calls the police.

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/page.asp?partid=7276 Sam Dingle] at [[itv.com]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{EDDingles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dingle, Sam}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional farmers]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1995]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
