<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32001081" ns="0" title="Lance Wyman"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
|image = 
|imagesize =
| caption  = 
| name        = Lance Wyman
| birth_date   = {{birth year and age|1937}}
| birth_place  = [[Newark, New Jersey]], United States
| death_date   = 
| death_place  = 
| othername   =
| occupation  = Graphic designer
| yearsactive = 
}}

'''Lance Wyman''' (b. [[Newark, New Jersey]], 1937&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot;&gt;[http://art.webesteem.pl/9/wyman_en.php Case Study: Lance Wyman], ''WebEsteem Art &amp; Design Magazine'', 2004&lt;/ref&gt;) is an American graphic designer.  He is known for such work as the logo of the [[1968 Summer Olympic Games]] and the route map of the [[Washington Metro]].

==Life and career==
Wyman, the son of a commercial fisherman and a typist,&lt;ref name = &quot;WaPo&quot;&gt;Dana Hedgpeth, &quot;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/commuting/after-more-than-30-years-metro-map-is-being-redesigned-by-creator-lance-wyman/2011/05/31/AGeyD4IH_story.html After more than 30 years, Metro map is being redesigned by creator Lance Wyman]&quot;, washingtonpost.com, June 4, 2011; printed as &quot;An icon's midlife facelift: Metro map must be updated, so its creator goes back to the drawing board&quot;, ''The Washington Post'', June 5, 2011, p. A1.&lt;/ref&gt; grew up in [[Kearny, New Jersey]], where he worked in the factories during summers to pay for college.  He acquired an appreciation for the &quot;no-nonsense functional aesthetic of the sea and the factories&quot;, which he has described as &quot;an important influence in my approach to design.&quot;&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;  He graduated from the [[Pratt Institute]] with a degree in industrial design in 1960.  The subject of [[graphic design]] was just being introduced in American universities at the time; when Wyman met a student who studied [[logo]] design with [[Paul Rand]] at [[Yale]], he wanted to design logos.&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;

Wyman began his career in [[Detroit, Michigan]], at [[General Motors]], where he worked on a packaging system for [[Delco]] automotive parts that unified 1,200 different packages.  Later, he moved to the office of [[William Schmidt]], where he produced the graphics for the American pavilion at a 1962 trade fair in [[Zagreb, Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;

In 1963, Wyman moved to New York, where he joined the [[George Nelson]] firm.  He designed the graphics for the [[Chrysler]] Pavilion at the [[New York World's Fair]].  He later reported that devising a &quot;pointing hand&quot; theme logo and adapting it to the site directional signs convinced him that logos could play a more important role in an overall design program.&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;  In 1966, he participated in a design competition for the graphics for the 1968 [[1968 Summer Olympics|Mexico Olympic Games]].  His &quot;Mexico68&quot; logotype was the winner, and launched his career.  Wyman remained in Mexico for four and one-half years, following his Olympic work with development of graphic programs for the [[Mexico City Metro]] and the [[1970 FIFA World Cup|1970 World Cup]] competition.&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;WaPo&quot; /&gt;

After returning to New York in 1971, Wyman formed a partnership with Bill Cannan (Wyman &amp; Cannan).  In 1979, he established his own firm, Lance Wyman Ltd.  He has also taught corporate and wayfinding design at [[Parsons School of Design]] since 1973.&lt;ref name = &quot;WebEsteem&quot; /&gt;

==Work==
Wyman, who has been described as a &quot;rock star&quot; of graphic arts,&lt;ref name = &quot;WaPo&quot; /&gt; made his reputation when he designed the logo for the [[1968 Summer Olympic Games]].  He has also designed icons for museums and many other institutions, individualized signs for buildings at the U.S. [[Smithsonian National Zoological Park|National Zoo]], and many other symbols.  Stepping outside his usual genre, he designed a poster for the 2008 Barack Obama presidential campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Steven Heller, &quot;[http://imprint.printmag.com/branding/wyman-in-ireland/ Wyman in Ireland]&quot;, ''Imprint''.  Accessed 2011.06.15.&lt;/ref&gt;  Perhaps his most enduring design is the stylized route map he devised for the [[Washington Metro]] in the mid-1970s, showing routes, stations, transfer points, and certain landmarks in a clear fashion, although distances are not to scale.&lt;ref name = &quot;WaPo&quot; /&gt;  In 2011, Wyman was called on to design a new Metro map, able to depict planned new lines and route orientations, as well as some station names that have been expanded to the point of being cumbersome.&lt;ref&gt;Steve Delahoyde, [http://www.mediabistro.com/unbeige/lance-wyman-difficult-task-of-re-designing-his-original-dc-metro-map_b14488 Lance Wyman Difficult Task of Re-Designing His Original DC Metro Map], Mediabistro.com, Unbeige, June 6, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dana Hedgpeth, &quot;Metro's Main Designer&quot;, ''Express'' (Washington, D.C.), June 6, 2011, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;  It is one of the few occasions in which the original designer has a chance to revise his own creation.&lt;ref name = &quot;WaPo&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lancewyman.com/ Lance Wyman, Ltd.]
* [http://www.wmata.com/rail/maps/map.cfm The Wyman map of the Washington Metro system, slightly changed in updates]

&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
{{Persondata
|NAME= Wyman, Lace
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Graphic designer
|DATE OF BIRTH= {{birth year and age|1937}}
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Newark, New Jersey]], United States
|DATE OF DEATH= 
|PLACE OF DEATH= 
}}

[[Category:1937 births]]
[[Category:People from Newark, New Jersey]]
[[Category:American graphic designers]]
[[Category:Pratt Institute alumni]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[es:Lance Wyman]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
