<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32027856" ns="0" title="List of Jiggy McCue books"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox book series
| name             = Jiggy McCue Series
| image            = [[File:Jiggy McCue books.jpg|200px]]
| image_caption    = The twelve Jiggy McCue books as of 2011.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| language         = English
| genre            = Children's
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| media_type       = Paperback
| number_of_books  = 12
| followed by      = Jiggy's Genes
| website          = {{Official website|http://www.jiggymccue.com}}, [http://web.me.com/wordybug/ML/Jiggy_McCue.html Author's website]
}}
The '''Jiggy McCue series''' is a collection of books for young readers written by [[United Kingdom|British]] author [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]. The series currently comprises twelve books that detail the unusual encounters of a pre-teen to teenage boy named Joseph &quot;Jiggy&quot; McCue and his friends. The series has received praise for promoting reading through interesting scenarios and engaging storylines.&lt;ref name=inis /&gt; However, the series has also received criticism for the often [[scatological]] themes and situations, which some reviewers deem distasteful and inappropriate for children.&lt;ref name=TES /&gt;

The books were all reprinted in 2010 with new covers and illustrations by Steve May, the previous set of covers and illustrations having been done by Ellis Nadler. The naming and order of the books was shuffled around a little too; The Poltergoose was renamed The Curse of the Poltergoose and moved to be book 5, after The Snottle, making The Killer Underpants first, and Maggot Pie was renamed to The Meanest Genie.
{{TOC limit|2}}

==The Poltergoose==
{{Infobox book|
| name          = The Poltergoose
| image         =
| image_caption = Cover
| author        = [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator   = [[Ellis Nadler]] (cover)
| country       = [[United Kingdom]]
| language      = [[English language|English]]
| genre         = [[Children's novel]]
| series        = ''Jiggy McCue'' series
| publisher     = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date      = 1999
| media_type    = Print ([[Paperback]])
| pages         = 148
| isbn          =
| followed_by   = The Killer Underpants
}}

'''''The Poltergoose''''' is the first book in the [[Jiggy McCue]] children's series by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = The Poltergoose: A Jiggy McCue Story - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=lXNYen3WpPYC| accessdate = 6 June 2011| date = 2003-01-13| publisher = Puffin| isbn = 978-0-14-250016-3 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
This book tells the story of Jiggy McCue, a boy who has lived in Borderline Way all his life. It's a run-down neighbourhood where all the [[terraced house]]s are falling apart, and there isn't a fence without a hole in it, which comes in quite handy when Jiggy and his friends Angie Mint and Pete Garrett want to visit each other.

Despite the state it's in, Jiggy is perfectly happy in Borderline Way, but he and his family has to move when his dad gets a new job, because they bought a new car to celebrate and [[vandal]]s sprayed 'rich sod' and such things on it, so Jiggy's parents want to move to a better neighbourhood.

So they leave Borderline Way, and move to Brook Farm Estate, respectable neighbourhood where all the houses are brand new.

Things are fine at first. Jiggy warms to his new home, thinking it a [[palace]] compared to his old house, and his parents start doing up the garden. Well, his mum does. All his dad does is plant a Rhododendron bush and be amazed that something he planted is still alive.

Everything seems perfect at The Dorks (Jiggy's name for the house was the one that got pulled out of the hat), but then something strange happens when Jiggy is in bed. His duvet flies off the bed and knocks over his unwanted collection of [[toy rocking horse]]s, smashing his mum's two favourite ones.

Things carry on like this, until Jiggy finally realises he is being [[haunt]]ed. He also knows it's a [[goose]], because when the [[talcum powder]] spills everywhere, it goes on the ghost and forms the shape of a goose.

Because his parents think he is mad, and take him to a [[behavioural psychologist]], Jiggy can only trust his fellow [[Musketeers]] - One For All and All For Lunch! - to believe him. Pete doesn't, but Angie does.

They try to figure out how to stop the goose but they can't. It continues to cause havoc everywhere it turns up, including Jiggy's school, Ranting Lane.
Then the Three Musketeers have a brainwave; maybe the goose was one of Brooks'! Mr Brook is the grumpy old man that owned the farm the Brook Farm Estate is built on. Brooky tells Angie, Pete and Jiggy that yes, his beloved Aunt Hetty (a goose), which he loved more than his wife,  was buried where she died; Brook Farm Estate. But he doesn't know exactly where, because when Aunt Hetty was buried, the houses weren't built yet.

The Three Musketeers suspect that it is Jiggy's garden that the goose is buried in, seeing as it haunts Jiggy, and they turn out to be correct.
So they befriend the goose, and so begins a mission; they have to bury the goose at the farmhouse where she lived before she will go away, but there's a catch - the new [[shopping mall]] is built there.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Aunt Hetty
* Linus Brook
* Mel &amp; Peg McCue
* Oliver Garrett &amp; Audrey Mint
* Mr Dakin
* Dr Edward Pickett

{{-}}

==The Killer Underpants==

{{Infobox book|
| name          = The Killer Underpants
| image         =
| image_caption = Cover
| author        = [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator   = [[Ellis Nadler]] (cover)
| country       = [[United Kingdom]]
| language      = [[English language|English]]
| genre         = [[Comic fantasy]]
| series        = ''Jiggy McCue'' series
| publisher     = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date      = 2000
| media_type    = Print ([[Paperback]])
| pages         = 148
| isbn          =
| preceded_by   = The Poltergoose
| followed_by   = The Toilet of Doom
}}

'''''The Killer Underpants''''' is a children's book by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]],  the second book in the [[Jiggy McCue]] book series, and was first published in 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = Killer Underpants - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=OhjVOgAACAAJ| accessdate = 6 June 2011| date = 2009-07-02| publisher = Franklin Watts| isbn = 978-1-4083-0401-3 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Jiggy McCue has to go shopping with his mum for a new pair of pants. They wind up at a market stall run by Neville, a creepy looking guy with a frightening smile, and that's where Jiggy gets a pair of brand new [[y-fronts]],a perfectly normal pair of pants. Or so it seems...

When Jiggy tries to get changed for bed at the end of a long and tiring day - Saturday - he finds a problem; his new underpants won't come off. It's like they're stuck with [[superglue]], like a second skin.
There's no point telling his mum and dad; last time he told them his problems they took him to a [[psychologist]], so yet again Jiggy has to confide in his best friends and fellow Musketeers Pete and Angie and hope that they can figure out a solution to his problem.

Jiggy discovers something about his 'Little Devils' - the name of the pants - which is that they can make someone do what he says, but at a price. He gets a terrible [[itch]] and then whatever he tells someone to do, they do it. He tells his horrible old PE teacher to go take a 'running jump', and so he runs superspeed round the school field, leaping high into the air every 3&amp;nbsp;metres or so. He even tells Pete to flush his head down the [[toilet]], which he does.
However great that may be though, it doesn't make up for the problem which is that they won't come off! Everytime Jiggy tries to get them off, be it with a fish slice or himself, they shrink so Jiggy can hardly breathe.

In the end Jiggy consults Neville, the man who sold the pants. Neville explains that he is &quot;the ungrateful kid with the lucky underpants&quot; and says that they are fantastic - getting anyone to do what you want them to with a small price to pay (the itch). Then Jiggy discovers that the heather weakens the pants. With his friends Pete and Angie, he vanquishes Neville the Devil - who turns out to be [[Lucifer]]'s [[Birth order|little brother]].

Eventually Jiggy gets the pants off and as they are put out to dry, his new next door neighbour, Eejit Atkins,(who, earlier on in the book, compliments Jiggy on his underwear) steals the pants. Little does he know that what just happened to Jiggy McCue might happen to him and as he is annoying Jiggy, Pete and Angie as they walk to school he collapses, itching like crazy.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Neville
* Mr Rice
* Peg McCue
* Mel McCue
* Oliver Garret &amp; Audrey Mint

{{-}}

==The Toilet of Doom==
{{Infobox book
| name             = The Toilet of Doom
| title_orig       =
| translator       =
| image            =
| image_caption    = Front cover of the second edition.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| country          =
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| subject          =
| genre            = Children's Novel
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| pub_date         = 2001
| english_pub_date =
| media_type       = Paperback
| pages            = 240
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0404-4
| oclc             =
| dewey            =
| congress         =
| preceded_by      = The Killer Underpants
| followed_by      = Maggot Pie
}}

'''''The Toilet of Doom''''' is a children's book by [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]], the third book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = The Toilet of Doom - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=XgVWOwAACAAJ| accessdate = 3 June 2011| date = Google| publisher = Franklin Watts| isbn = 978-1-4083-0404-4| page = 1 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===

Coming home from school one day, the [[Three Musketeers]], Jiggy McCue, Pete Garret and Angie Mint walk with Milo Dakin, the son of the worst teacher in the school. While Mr Dakin, their horrible form and maths teacher is constantly tedious, Milo is one of the nicest kids there. Walking home, Milo complains about his dad and how bad it is living with him, and accidentally lets slip about a computer game called the Toilet of Life. The others pick up on this and he tells them it is nothing, but at home they have a go on it anyway. The find that the game is exceptional, because it fills with blue smoke which comes out of the screen. This smoke smells horrible, and Jiggy and Angie try to get out of the room. After, they feel dizzy and very tired.

The next day, they find they have swapped bodies with each other. Pete finds it very funny. They try several times to reverse the effect, but are unsuccessful. When they do manage to, Pete comes in and ''he'' gets swapped with Jiggy. The story ends with Pete as Jiggy's cat, Stallone, and Jiggy and Angie back to normal.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Milo Dakin
* Mr Mann
* Mr Heathcliffe
* Stallone
* Peg McCue
* Mel McCue
* Mr Dakin
* Oliver Garrett
* Audrey Mint

{{-}}

==The Meanest Genie==
{{Infobox book
| name             = The Meanest Genie
| title_orig       = Maggot Pie
| translator       =
| image            =
| image_caption    = Front cover of the second edition.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| country          =
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| subject          =
| genre            = Children's Novel
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| pub_date         = 2002
| english_pub_date =
| media_type       = Paperback
| pages            = 292
| isbn             = 978-1-84121-756-7
| oclc             =
| dewey            =
| congress         =
| preceded_by      = The Toilet of Doom
| followed_by      = The Snottle
}}

'''''The Meanest Genie''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]], the fourth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2002, as '''''Maggot Pie'''''.&lt;ref name=&quot;library&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=The School Library Association|title=Lawrence, Michael: Maggot Pie|journal=The School Librarian|year=2002|volume=50-52|page=205|url=http://books.google.com/?id=wWwPAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22maggot+pie%22+jiggy+mccue&amp;dq=%22maggot+pie%22+jiggy+mccue|accessdate=7 June 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;  In 2009 it was renamed to the Meanest Genie.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = Meanest Genie - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=MUOuPQAACAAJ| accessdate = 3 June 2011| date = 2009-07-02| publisher = Google| isbn = 978-1-4083-0403-7| page = 1 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Near where Jiggy McCue lives, there is a [[pond]] called the Piddle Pool. In town tradition, the night before they started primary school, little boys came to the Pool and peed in it.&lt;ref name=&quot;TES&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Thorn|first=Michael|title=Whizz-kids revisited|url=http://www.tes.co.uk/article.aspx?storycode=368557|accessdate=5 June 2011|newspaper=TES Magazine|date=20 September 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;  If they did so, it meant that they would have a lucky school career. Jiggy hadn't weed in the Piddle Pool, and he believed that is why he is so [[unlucky]]. So every time he passes the Pool and there’s no-one about, he makes up for not peeing in the Pool the night before school.

One day, when Jiggy is at the Piddle Pool in his town, a purple-eyed teenager with dreadlocks rises from the Piddle Pool. He claims that he’s a [[genie]]&lt;ref name=TES /&gt;  called JR (Jimmy Riddle) and because this is Jiggy’s thousand-and-first pee, he has been released from his ‘prison’ and is here to grant his master three wishes. He claims that he is not really a teenager; if he looked his true age he'd need ten [[bus pass]]es.

Of course, because Jiggy McCue is Jiggy McCue, he manages to accidentally completely waste an opportunity to turn his life around by wasting all his wishes in a single sentence. So he lets this teenage [[practical joke|prankster]] genie free, and after being trapped in a pool of pee for so long, JR is ready to cause havoc.
The Piddle Pool is about to be covered over to make way for a car park and swimming pool, so as long as no-one tells JR about it, he will hopefully disappear when the Piddle Pool is destroyed. But Pete, being Pete, tells him, which makes JR mad. He wants revenge on all three Musketeers for betraying him.

JR makes Jiggy’s life a misery first, making him [[bald]] then making him sport a head covered in grass with daisies. Then it’s his friends' Angie and Pete’s turn, and they are forced to do things they don’t want to do, like flooding their school.&lt;ref name=inis /&gt;

They need to stop JR before he starts making [[:wikt:mayhem|mayhem]] all over the place, like he does when he makes the animals from the zoo fly in the air. And Jiggy has to face his worst nightmare; eating a pie full of [[maggots]].&lt;ref name=TES /&gt;

The story ends with JR being touched by another genie, the 'Genie Touch', and is forced to stay human. Everything goes back to normal.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue&lt;ref name=inis /&gt;&lt;ref name=TES /&gt;
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* JR
* Stallone
* Peg McCue
* Mel McCue
* Oliver Garrett
* Audrey Mint
* Mr Dent
* Mr Flowerdew

===Reception===
Michael Thorn (reviewing the book under the previous title ''Maggot Pie'') reported in Times Educational Supplement (TES) Magazine that he thought the book was in poor taste and the series had, &quot;lurched in the direction of bad taste&quot; when compared to Lawrence's previous effort ''The Poltergoose''.&lt;ref name=TES /&gt; He also said the book was &quot;decidedly aimed at sending the disgust meter off the scale.&quot;&lt;ref name=TES /&gt; Mary McLaughlin of ''Inis Magazine'' said that the &quot;dialogue is fast and funny, irreverent but not offensive.&quot; She also thought that the pace and timing of humour in the book was appropriate for a young audience and the book provided the &quot;temptation to read aloud.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;inis&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=McLaughlin|first=Mary|title=Maggot Pie|journal=Inis: the children's books Ireland magazine|year= Winter 2002|issue=3|url=http://www.inismagazine.ie/reviews/book/maggot-pie|accessdate=7 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{-}}

==The Snottle==
{{Infobox book
| name             = The Snottle
| title_orig       =
| translator       =
| image            =
| image_caption    = Front cover of the second edition.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| country          =
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| subject          =
| genre            = Children's Novel
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| pub_date         = 2003
| media_type       = Paperback
| pages            = 215
| isbn             = 978-1-84362-344-1
| oclc             =
| dewey            =
| congress         =
| preceded_by      = The Meanest Genie
| followed_by      = Nudie Dudie
}}

'''''The Snottle''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the fifth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2003.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = Snottle - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=VsciOwAACAAJ| accessdate = 3 June 2011| date = 2009-07-02| publisher = Google| isbn = 978-1-4083-0408-2| page = 1 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
There's a new girl in Jiggy's class called Steffanie, or Steff for short. Whenever she snonks - sneezes really loudly - which is quite a lot, her nose 'explodes', and all her snot splashes everywhere.

Jiggy's friend Angie makes friends with Steff because Steff hasn't got anyone else, because of her snonking, constant sniffing and the fact that she's new. She discovers that Steff's [[grandmother]] was the same as Steff; she snonked, but she was a professional because she only snonked when she was working.
Steff says her grandmother told the [[future]] by snonking. Angie believes her, because she claims that when Steff snonked she saw the future. Jiggy doesn't believe her at first, but then he sees it for himself. Pete doesn't believe it at all.

When the four are walking home from school, they pass the Midden, a rubbish dump, and see a little green creature that looks like a [[grapefruit]] crawling around there. When Steff snonks, it comes out from hiding and licks all the snot off her. It sees Steff's lucky charm, a [[seed pod]] that belonged to her grandmother, and attaches itself to it, so Steff takes the little creature back to her house in Cod Lane, where there's a [[fish factory]].

The Three Musketeers and Steff decide to call the creature a Snottle, and try and clean it up as it had been living in the rubbish dump. It decides it doesn't like water, and in an attempt to wriggle out of Steff's grasp, it falls into the toilet, and Pete cruelly flushes it, so the creature goes down the U-Bend.
The Snottle comes back though, and the Musketeers, along with Steffanie, discover some interesting things about the Snottle, as well as the Future Snot, Steff's nan and the 'seed pod'.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Steff
* Peg McCue
* The Snottle
{{-}}

==Nudie Dudie==
{{Infobox book
| name             = Nudie Dudie
| title_orig       =
| translator       =
| image            =
| image_caption    = Front cover of the first edition.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| country          =
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| subject          =
| genre            = Children's Novel
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| pub_date         = 2004
| media_type       = Paperback
| pages            = 135
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0406-8
| oclc             =
| dewey            =
| congress         =
| preceded_by      = The Snottle
| followed_by      = Neville the Devil
}}

'''''Nudie Dudie''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]], the sixth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = Michael Lawrence| title = Nudie Dudie - Google Books| url = http://books.google.com/?id=B7EQOwAACAAJ| accessdate = 10 June 2011| date = 2009-07-02| publisher = Google| isbn = 978-1-4083-0406-8 }} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Jiggy is waiting to get a [[soap star]] he despises' [[autograph]] for his mum. An adult pushes ahead of all the Ranting Lane School girls, and gives Tony Baloney a present; a [[pen]].

Nothing much else happens, except the [[school bell]] goes off. Jiggy knows his mum will be mad if he returns without Tony Baloney's precious autograph, so he still waits in line. Instead of giving him and autograph, Baloney gives him the woman's gift - the pen - and rushes off.
It's a [[novelty pen]]; there's a woman in it, and when you turn the pen upside down all her clothes fall off. All of them. Every last piece.

Jiggy and his male classmates like the pen, and they try to buy it off him, but Jiggy won't sell it. That's until he tries writing with it.

Jiggy discovers that whenever he tries writing with the stripper pen, his clothes and [[underwear]] disappear. It happens in the middle of [[detention (imprisonment)|detention]] with Mr Hurley, his boring and mean [[History teacher]], and every other time he tries [[writing]] with it. He and his friends, Pete and Angie, try to work out how it works, and how to stop it.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Tony Baloney
* Mr. Hurley
* Seagull

{{-}}

==Neville the Devil==
{{Infobox book
| name             = Neville the Devil
| title_orig       =
| translator       =
| image            =
| image_caption    = Front cover of the first edition.
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| country          =
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| subject          =
| genre            = Children's Novel
| publisher        = Orchard Books
| pub_date         = 2005
| media_type       = Paperback
| pages            = 341
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0407-5
| oclc             =
| dewey            =
| congress         =
| preceded_by      = Nudie Dudie
| followed_by      = Ryan's Brain
}}

'''''Neville the Devil''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the seventh book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=MAE-OwAACAAJ|title=Neville the Devil - Google Books|publisher=Google|accessdate=26 June 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Jiggy, Pete and Angie are going on [[vacation|holiday]] to JoyWorld, an equivalent of [[Disneyland]].
Nothing runs smoothly if you're Jiggy McCue though, so the seven - Jiggy, Pete, Angie and their parents - end up missing their flight to the amazing JoyWorld, a [[theme park]] the size of a small country.

Instead, a dodgy looking bloke at the airport offers them a holiday in Wonkton-On-Sea, a seaside town. The group decide that Wonkton must be better than home, so they take the keys to the flat there and get into their cars.

The first couple of days in Wonkton-On-Sea are pretty normal, and boring. A few unfortunate things happen; like Jiggy, Angie and his parents being locked in the flat, unable to get out, and an embarrassing incident involving Jiggy dangling out of a window wearing only a [[jock-strap]] when the Wonkton Carnival is on.
Then, after watching a Ms Sweet and Mr Nicey-Nicey puppet show, similar to the real world [[Punch &amp; Judy]], the Musketeers come across one of their enemies; Neville The Devil.

He may be doll-sized, but the Musketeers know Neville is not to be messed with. They discover that Neville made Jiggy and Co. miss their JoyWorld flight, and forced the dodgy-looking guy to offer them the holiday in Wonkton. Neville wants his human size back, and he'll stop at nothing to get it. That includes [[kidnap]]ping Pete so Angie and Jiggy will do as he says.

In order to get his full power and size back, Neville needs his [[trident]]. He can't say exactly where it is, because [[devil]]s aren't allowed to say what they want, and say where it is. So Jiggy and Angie have to work out how to get Neville's trident back themselves, but they don't know where to start looking.

===Background info===
This is the Three Musketeer's last adventure as under-[[teenager|teens]]. Michael Lawrence publishes a Jiggy McCue book every year, and in each one Jiggy, Pete and Angie get a bit older. This time they are 12. To find out more about Neville, read the second Jiggy book, [[#The Killer Underpants|The Killer Underpants]].

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Meg &amp; Mel McCue
* Oliver Garrett &amp; Audrey Mint
* Armitage Shanks
* Neville

{{-}}

==Ryan's Brain==
{{Infobox book
| name             = Ryan's Brain
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler
| language         = [[English language|English]]
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| genre            = Children's novel
| publisher        = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date         = 2006
| media_type       = [[Paperback]]
| pages            = 321
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0409-9
| preceded_by      = Neville the Devil
| followed_by      = The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard
}}

'''''Ryan's Brain''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the eighth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=DrsSOwAACAAJ|title=Ryan's Brain - Google Books|accessdate=11 July 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Bryan Ryan and Jiggy McCue have been arch-enemies for as long as either can remember. Bryan - or Bry-Ry, as Jiggy calls him - is mad about [[association football|football]], and tries to be a teacher's pet for Mr Rice, the school [[Physical education|P.E.]] teacher.

One day, when the Ranting Lane School boys are practising football, Jiggy decides to start annoying Ryan. He insults football, saying something along the lines of 'it's just stupid, sweaty idiots running after a ball, trying to kick it into giant hairnets.'
Ryan gets really annoyed, and tries to headbutt Jiggy, but Jiggy moves out of the way just in time. Ryan bangs his head on the [[goalpost]], and gets taken to [[hospital]]; [[Unconsciousness|unconscious]].

People blame Jiggy, but Jiggy says it was [[self-defence]], and everything seems to be okay. But in Jiggy McCue's world, it never is.
Then the [[hallucination]]s start. Jiggy sees his classroom closing in on him, so runs to the [[toilet]], with the school getting smaller and smaller on him so that he has to crouch. He sits on the toilet and when he opens his eyes he is in a red desert.
Weird things like this keep happening to Jiggy and he and his fellow Musketeers - Pete and Angie - have to try and find a way to stop it.

They realise it's all Ryan's doing; trying to get revenge on Jiggy for putting him in hospital. So they have to convince Ryan that Jiggy is sorry - but is it really Ryan that's making the hallucinations appear?

This is the book in which Jiggy turns thirteen, in hospital, after being hit on the goalpost himself.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett
* Angie Mint
* Bryan Ryan
* Russel Ryan
* Mr. Rice
{{-}}

==The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard==
{{Infobox book
| name             = The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| language         = [[English language|English]]
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| genre            = Children's novel
| publisher        = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date         = 2007
| media_type       = [[Paperback]]
| pages            = 339
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0405-1
| preceded_by      = Ryan's Brain
| followed_by      = Kid Swap
}}

'''''The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the ninth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=wS-8OgAACAAJ|title=The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard|accessdate=11 July 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
When hiding from Mr Rice, who undoubtedly wants to shout at him, Jiggy finds himself in the [[janitor]]'s cupboard. He falls over a [[bucket]] and goes backwards. Instead of hitting his head on a stone wall though, Jiggy just keeps on going.
When he finally finds the cupboard door again, he goes out and walks back to his R.E. lesson.

But instead of finding his unruly class teasing Mr Staples, he walks into his class and finds Mr Hubbard, the [[headmaster]] teaching a silent and well-behaved class about how we were created by aliens.
Also, his friends keep asking him if something happened to his ears, and Eejit Atkins, the stupid boy who always talks out of the side of mouth, is clever and speaks normally!
Jiggy thinks this is all a [[practical joke]], but realises it's real when he can't get into his house because it belongs to Mr Rice, Miss Weeks and their baby! He lives next-door, in what would be Dawn Overton's house.
What's more, Jiggy discovers he has a sister! Suzie, or Swoozie, is the only one allowed to call Jiggy, or Juggy as he is known in this world, Joseph.
Jiggy tries to call in his fellow Musketeers, but discovers he and Pete hate each other over marbles and Angie's gone all girly!

Jiggy needs to get back to his own world, away from the nice Mr Rice, the clever Eejit and the totally mad place he's in.
To do that, Jiggy needs to get back into the janitor's cupboard, but things don't go smoothly. When did they ever?
So Jiggy ends up having to take part in Arnold Snit Compulsory's - this world's version of Ranting Lane School - 'survival weekend', and it turns out to be nothing like what Jiggy's been dreading.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Pete Garrett &amp; Angie Mint
* Peg and Mel McCue
* Juggy McCue
* Swoozie McCue
* Eejit Atkins
* Mr Rice

{{-}}

==Kid Swap==
{{Infobox book
| name             = Kid Swap
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| genre            = Children's novel
| publisher        = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date         = 2008
| media_type       = [[Paperback]]
| pages            = 236
| isbn             = 978-1-4083-0402-0
| preceded_by      = The Iron, the Switch, and the Broom Cupboard
| followed_by      = One for All and All for Lunch!
}}

'''''Kid Swap''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the tenth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=LrALOgAACAAJ|title=Kid Swap - Google Books|accessdate=11 July 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Kid Swap is the penultimate Jiggy McCue novel, and it's also quite normal, which is quite abnormal for a Jiggy McCue book, as past adventures have included teenage [[genie]]s, a [[Multiverse|parallel world]], a miniature [[devil]] and a [[ghost]] [[goose]].

Jiggy's dad is out of a job, and his mum isn't working because she's [[pregnant]], so the McCues need to find out a way of making some money quickly.

The problem is solved when a TV company contacts them asking if they would like to take part in a new programme called Kid Swap, in exchange for quite a large sum of money.

Jiggy's parents agree, even though Jiggy is totally against the idea because most of what he does shouldn't be shown to his closest friends, never mind millions of total strangers.

But, as usual, Jiggy's parents don't really care what he thinks and sign up to the show anyway.

So Jiggy is packed off to the posh part of Brook Farm Estate, swapping places with a seemingly perfect boy called Toby. We don't really hear about Toby's experience, other than hearing from Jiggy's friends and family that Toby is 'simply perfect' and 'very well mannered'.

Toby's family is very weird. The Next family are all (seemingly) strict Sans-Earthists, which means that they don't eat anything that is grown from the ground, which means no [[fruit]] or [[vegetable]]s. At first it seems like [[heaven]] to Jiggy, but then he finds himself [[longing]] for some [[broccoli]] or an [[apple]].

Then there's the matter of the [[Television director|director]], DD, a young, floppy-haired man who flirts with all the women and makes the men do what he wants. He makes Jiggy's life total hell by filming all the embarrassing stuff he does and annoying him like mad.

On top of all that, Jiggy develops a highly unattractive and bizarre skin problem which doesn't seem to be going away, even with the help of 'miracle' cream, with a quite unusual ingredient.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Peg &amp; Mel McCue
* Jess Next
* Roo &amp; Solomon Next
* Toby Next
* DD
* Carla
* Pete Garrett &amp; Angie Mint
{{-}}
==One for All and All for Lunch!==
{{Infobox book
| name             = One for All and All for Lunch!
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| genre            = Children's novel
| publisher        = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date         = 2009
| media_type       = [[Paperback]]
| pages            = 172
| isbn             = 978-1-84616-956-4
| preceded_by      = Kid Swap
| followed_by      = Rudie Dudie
}}

'''''One for All and All for Lunch!''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the eleventh book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=3sPmGgAACAAJ|title=One for All and All for Lunch! - Google Books|accessdate=16 July 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
This book is different from all the previous in that it is not one long story told by Jiggy; instead it is a collection of short ones told by him, his friends Pete and Angie, and Stallone, his cat. The stories are:

;The Bogey Man (Jiggy McCue)
Jiggy tells this story; in it there is a boy in his class called Eejit Atkins, who has a cold. He sneezes a massive sneeze and the bogeys come together to form a Bogeyman, which comes after Jiggy.

;Grandpa's Extra Hole (Pete Garrett)
Pete talks about his grandpa, who got an 'extra hole' on the back side of his neck when he was younger.

;Twinklystink (Angie Mint)
Angie discovers an 'alien purse' in her aunt and uncle's bonsai garden. It seems to respond to a dog pissing on it by throwing a big amount of twinkly dust onto people, only problem: they stink and begin dancing uncontrollably!

;My Violent Story (Stallone the Cat)
Stallone, Jiggy's cat, talks about his past life and how he has seen very weird thing, such as a three-legged ghost cat!

;Shelling Peas (Jiggy McCue)
Jiggy gets a visit from his grandparents after their holiday in Spain and they give him a few gifts, one a piece of rock (which he gives to Pete) and a conch shell. His mother is pregnant so, naturally, her tummy's huge. His grandparents tell him that if you hear the shell closely, you'll hear the sea. But he doesn't only hear that, he also hears a voice, which claimst that it's 'floating.'

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Angie Mint
* Pete Garrett
* Eejit Atkins
* The Bogeyman
* Audrey Mint
* Stallone
* Oliver Garrett
{{-}}

==Rudie Dudie==
{{Infobox book
| name             = Rudie Dudie
| author           = [[Michael Lawrence (author)|Michael Lawrence]]
| illustrator      = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| cover_artist     = Ellis Nadler&lt;br /&gt;Steve May
| language         = English
| series           = ''Jiggy McCue Stories''
| genre            = Children's novel
| publisher        = [[Orchard Books]]
| pub_date         = 2010
| media_type       = [[Paperback]]
| pages            = 161
| isbn             = 140830483
| preceded_by      = One for All and All for Lunch!
}}

'''''Rudie Dudie''''' is a [[children's book]] by [[Michael Lawrence (writer)|Michael Lawrence]], the twelfth book in the Jiggy McCue book series, and was first published in the UK in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=1BdZPgAACAAJ|title=Rudie Dudie - Google Books|accessdate=27 August 2011}} &lt;/ref&gt;

===Plot summary===
Jiggy McCue has a new Drama teacher at his school, Ms Mooney. She is producing a [[school play]] of A [[Midsummer Nights Dream]], and chooses Jiggy to play the part of [[Nick Bottom|Bottom]].

Jiggy and his friends, Pete and Angie, discover that Ms Mooney lives on a [[barge]] on the local canal. They find she has been trapped in a fold-up bed there for three days. They release her and check for a heartbeat, but when she wakes up to find Jiggy's hand in here bosom she screams and hypnotises him with her eyes to strip off his lower half and do a dance over here waving his privates about. He only stops this when a policeman looks in and takes him to the police station.

Mooney gives him a 'three strikes and you're out' system for annoying her. He used the first one on the barge and in school uses up his second one accidentally walking round the corner into her.

He finally uses up the third one a few days before the final performance of the play; he walks into the craft room to repair a donkey's head's ear and she hypnotizes him again. This time, however, Jiggy drops his sunglasses over his eyes just before she starts and the hypnotism bounces back at her and makes her do the terrible things she had lined up for Jiggy. The Head, Mr Hubbard, then fires her.

===Characters===
* Jiggy McCue
* Angie Mint
* Pete Garret
* Ophelia Mooney
* Mr Hubbard
* Mrs Gamble
----

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jiggy McCue Books}}
[[Category:Children's fantasy novels]]
[[Category:British novels]]
[[Category:Comedy novels]]
[[Category:British children's novels]]
[[Category:British comedy novels]]
[[Category:Books by Michael Lawrence]]
[[Category:Lists of books]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
