<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32234621" ns="0" title="Hazem Salah Abu Ismail"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Hazem Salah Abu Ismail.jpg|thumb|Dr.Hazem in one of his pragmatic talks]]

'''Hazem Salah Abu Ismail''' ({{lang-ar|حازم صلاح أبو إسماعيل}}; {{IPA-arz|ħæːzem sˤɑˈlɑːħ ˈæbu ʔesmæˈʕiːl|IPA}} born 1961 in Dokki, Giza) is an Egyptian scholar and Islamic thinker. As an Egyptian Muslim - and a lawyer and spokesman in the Islamic thought and political affairs, and Islamic and public,  his studies of constitutional law and legalities are extensive. He's thought to represent the [[Salafist]] movement within Egypt. As studies and research specialist, his studies are abundant in  three sciences : education, administration, and the economy,all of which he compiled for 25 years. After graduating from  the Law Faculty of [[Cairo University]] in 1982, he was the third of the merited graduates.

In a video-clip posted on 4 August 2011, he praises [[Osama bin Laden]] as a martyr, and for &quot;speaking the word of truth to power,&quot; for &quot;going to the front lines to work in the path of Allah.&quot; Ismail says &quot;I ask Almighty Allah that the Muslims may soon be able to avenge him.&quot;[www.youtube.com/watch?v=7djHoCTWvWk] 
 
Ismail was a long-standing member of the Muslim Brotherhood. He left it when he ran for President. Ismail affirmed that although he is proud of being affiliated to the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] (MB), he is not a member and has some minor differences.&lt;ref name=&quot;mb affiliation&quot;/&gt; Ismail had a well-established role as the defendant of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]], facing charges of &quot;Endangering National Security&quot; during the [[Hosni Mubarak]] reign.

His father was the well known Salah Abu Ismail, one of the most prominent Al-Azhar scholars and the only independent member of the [[Majlis]] during the Sadat reign. 

Throughout his presidential campaign, Dr.Hazem stressed the need for enhancing the cinema and tourism industries in Egypt through a variety of ways &amp; methods, a move not expected by many secular intellectuals in the political arena.{{reference needed|date=November 2011}} 

However, in November, 2011 Hazem gave two television interviews in which he called for &quot;Islamic dress&quot; for women, including the [[burqa]], saying that any woman caught wearing a bikini should be arrested.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jihadwatch.org/2011/11/egypt-islamic-supremacist-presidential-candidate-vows-to-arrest-bikini-wearing-women-if-elected.html Jihad Watch 11/15/2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

Q U O T E S (translated)
 
&quot;Some secular Egyptians have this pre-determined perception that if a Muslim activist like me governs Egypt, life will become unbearable. But, that kind of talk really saddens me. Because, he should come back. He must come back! If he won't help me to build Egypt, who will? Isn't he an Egyptian after all?&quot; Hazem Salah

&quot;No doubt that Tourism and Suez Canal Revenues constitute a great part of the national income, so we need our foreign counterparts to engage in their investments and get their hands busy with us, if they sincerely care about human development.&quot; Hazem Salah

&quot;Foreign Relations is like Jenga. If any move is un-estimated before enacted, it can make or break our political will.&quot; Hazem Salah

&quot;He also called for an end to the peace treaty with Israel, saying that restarting relations with Iran is a better solution than maintaining ties with the Jewish state.&quot; paraphrased from 90-Minutes interview, in Bikya Masr.[http://bikyamasr.com/47045/egypt-candidate-abu-ismail-no-gambling-no-bikinis-no-alcohol-islamic-dress/]

==References==

{{Reflist|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;mb affiliation&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://english.youm7.com/News.asp?NewsID=341493|title=Abou Ismail: Islamic Sharia will achieve the Coptic demand|accessdate=Saturday  July 9, 2011|date=Tuesday  Jun 28, 2011|work=[[Youm7]]|author=Rania Amer}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.hazemsalah.net HazemSalah.net] ''Official Website''
* [http://www.facebook.com/HazemSalahFB HazemSalahFB] ''Official Page on Facebook''
* [http://www.Youtube.com/HazemSalahTV HazemSalahTV] ''Official Page on Youtube''
* [http://twitter.com/HazemSalahTW HazemSalahTW] ''Official Page on Twitter''

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Hazem Salah Abu Ismail
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Dr.Hazem
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Muslim Liberal Figure within the Islamic Arena
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1961
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Cairo, Egypt
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
[[Category:Egyptian politicians]]
[[Category:Egyptian scholars]]
[[Category:Seattle University alumni]]
[[Category:Muslim reformers]]
[[Category:Middle East peace efforts]]

[[ar:حازم صلاح أبو إسماعيل]]
[[arz:حازم صلاح أبو إسماعيل]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
