<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32334557" ns="0" title="Rob Cage"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Notability|date=September 2010}}
{{Infobox wrestler
|name        =Rob Cage
|image       = 
|caption    =Rob Cage tests strength against Sean McKenzie
|names       =Rob Cage
|height      ={{height|ft=5|in=11}}
|weight      ={{convert|15|st|lb kg|abbr=on}}
|birth_date  ={{Birth date and age|1989|02|08}}
|birth_place =[[Leeds]], England, United Kingdom
|resides     =[[Penrith, Cumbria]]
|billed      =[[The Lake District]], England
|trainer     =Colin McKay&lt;br /&gt;[[Joe E. Legend]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Johnny Moss]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Iceman (WZW)|Iceman]]&lt;br /&gt; [[Cassandro El Exotico]]
|debut       =2006&lt;ref name=&quot;Cagematch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cagematch.net/?id=2&amp;nr=7441&amp;name=Rob+Cage|title=Cagematch.de|accessdate=9 August 2010|publisher=Cagematch}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

'''Robert Smith BA(Hons)''' is a British [[Professional Wrestler]] better known by his in ring name '''Rob Cage'''. Cage lives in England and competes mainly in Northern England and Central Scotland. He is best known for his appearances in [[British Championship Wrestling]]. He competes across the UK, as well as appearing in Ireland and Germany on a regular basis.

==Professional Wrestling Career==
=== Early Years ===
Rob Cage began training under the guidance of [[General Trent Steel]] and [[Iceman (WZW)|Iceman]] towards the end of 2005. The [[Wrestle Zone Wrestling|WZW]] training school closed its doors in 2007, a few months after Cage had made his debut for Carlisle based promotion TTP. Cage then moved his wrestling training to Glasgow to British Championship Wrestling.

===Career 2007-2008===
Rob had been wrestling for TTP for several months before making his Scottish debut for BCW at the annual Supershow No Blood No Sympathy 5 where he entered a Royal Rumble for the vacant BCW Heavyweight Championship, vacated from now current [[WWE]] Superstar [[Drew Mcintyre]].&lt;br&gt;
Cage continued to wrestle for the promotion, along with [[Premier British Wrestling]] where he established himself as a villainous wrestler both in singles and tag team action, where he and fellow Englishman [[Andy Wild]] aligned themselves with [[Charles Boddington]] as The Heritage.&lt;br&gt;
The duo didn't last long, however, as Cage and Wild had been noted as &quot;too similar&quot; and were forced to go into singles careers.
During 2008 Rob Cage wrestled for several promotions in England.

===Career 2009 - 2010===
Early 2009 saw Rob Cage continue competing for BCW as well as heading to Ireland, where The Heritage reformed for one night only [http://upload.bebo.com/Profile.jsp?MemberId=1339708771 NWA Ireland] at the Fight Factory.&lt;ref&gt;Fight Factory Pro Wrestling&lt;/ref&gt;
Throughout 2009 Cage began to wrestle for other promotions across Scotland and England, with [[Scottish School of Wrestling]] and [[UK Wrestling Experience]] being two family orientated promotions, along with the holiday camp circuits. As well as these, Cage made his debut in Germany for the [[Deutsch Wrestling Alliance]] in [[Visselhovede]] and [[Mad Wrestling Association]] in [[Lübeck]], [[Hamburg]]. He is also the first Englishman to wrestle in Poland for the [[Do or Die Wrestling]] promotion.

As well as making his first European appearances, 2009 was also the first time Cage appeared for [[Insane Championship Wrestling]] where he and Noam Dar attacked former trainer Colin McKay.
This storyline lead to Cage's first match for the company in 2010.&lt;br&gt;
Cage picked up his first Championship at [[UKW- UK Wrestling Experience]] in December 2009 [http://www.ukwrestlingexperience.co.uk/ukwe/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=84&amp;Itemid=83 Rob Cage]

Cage's career in 2010 began with a strong start. He appeared at the annual Wrestling Legends Tour hosted by Deutsch Wrestling Alliance, [[World Xtreme Wrestling|wXw]] and [[CWN (wrestling)|CWN]] where he faced [[Ulf Herman]] and [[Karsten Beck]] on both nights of the tour. &lt;br&gt;
Cage continued his European appearances by joining the [[Irish Whip Wrestling]] Roster, where he has competed in both singles and Tag Team bouts, as well as the King of Cork Tournament.

As well as working with IwW, Cage also wrestled several dates for LDN including a Capital Championship match against [[Alan Lee Travis]], being beaten via pinfall.  

Rob Cage's ICW in ring debut was against [[Jack Jester]] in the first ever Insane DeathMatch. The match was loosely based on matches from the [[King of the Death Match Tournament]] in Japan, and saw both men in a bloody state, something neither man had seen in such capacity.

Cage also became the first Englishman to wrestle in Poland for the [[Do or Die Wrestling]] promotion, in [[Warsaw]]

Cage featured in the UKW Wrestlebration 2 event, which was at [[Blackpool Tower]] where he pinned [[Dylan Roberts]] in the Main Event to gain his second [[UKW Championship]].
In November 2010, Rob Cage defeated [[Steve Douglas (wrestler)|Steve Douglas]] for the [[EPW (wrestling)|EPW]] Promotion in Bremen, Germany to become the first European Jr. Heavyweight Champion. The match was a 20 minute time limit and the two fought up to the 19th minute before a [[Go to Sleep]]/[[Shining Wizard]] combo was used to give Cage the win.

===Career 2011 - Present===
Cage began 2011 wrestling on a regular basis for the London based promotion [[LDN]], as well as being featured heavily on the [[UK Wrestling Experience]] television show featured on [[Sky]] TV.
Cage successfully defended the UKW Championship against Valkabious before Bruce Sheila cashed in a title shot, costing Cage his 6 month title reign. Cage recently lost the UKW Championship to [[The Great Naga]]

His first appearance for ICW in 2011 saw Absolution (Cage and Dar) taking on Chris Renfrew and B.T. Gunn, a match that saw all 4 men brawling all around the venue causing mayhem.

Competing in his second Legend Tour, Cage teamed with fellow Brit Logan Storm as [[Los Conquistadors]], as well as being featured several times as himself.

Cage has continued his work in Europe, competing for promotions such as PWF in Hamburg, and a return visit to Poland. 

With experience in the Lucha Libre style, Cage made his debut alongside fellow LDN Alumni, William Gaylord,  as Steakley Bakewell, one half of The Fabulous Bakewell Boys for the London based Cabaret Sinestro show: Lucha Britannia.
Steakley, and his &quot;brother&quot; Jerry depict Northern English miners, perform comedy hybrid style of British traditional wrestling with the acrobatic performance of Lucha Libre.

==Personal life==
Rob is a graduate from the [[University of Central Lancashire]] with a BA(Hons) Degree in Media Production. When not wrestling Rob works in the Television Industry as a freelance Editor.

==In Wrestling==
=== Finishing Moves ===
Shining Blizzard ([[Shining Wizard]])&lt;br&gt;
GTF ([[Go To Sleep]])&lt;br&gt;
Bombs Away ([[Reverse Wheelbarrow Facebuster]])

===Signature Moves===
Zenyatta Mondatta [[Shoulder Check and Capoeira Roll]]&lt;br&gt;
Synchronicity 3 [[Shoulder Roll]]/[[Spear]] Combo&lt;br&gt;
[[Ear Ringer]]&lt;br&gt;
Vain Cutter [[Diving Neckbreaker]]

===Championships===
[[UKW - UK Wrestling Experience]] Heavyweight Championship (December 2009 - December 2009) (July 2010 - February 2011) (April 2011 - July 2011) (UK)&lt;br&gt;
EPW Junior Heavyweight Championship (November 2010 - Current) (Germany) &lt;br&gt;
[[Irish Whip Wrestling]] King of Cork 2010 (Joint held with Mandrake) (Ireland) &lt;br&gt;
AWM Limit-X Championship (April 2011 - Current) (Germany) &lt;br&gt;
[[LDN Wrestling]] Capital Champion (July 2011 - July 2011)

==References==
&lt;!--- See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] on how to create references using &lt;ref&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; tags which will then appear here automatically --&gt;
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.cagematch.net/?id=2&amp;nr=7441&amp;name=Rob+Cage Rob Cage Bio on Cagematch.Net]
* [http://www.genickbruch.com/index.php?befehl=bios&amp;wrestler=9141&amp;bild=1&amp;details=7 Rob Cage Bio on Genickbruch.com]

&lt;!--- Categories ---&gt;

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Cage, Rob
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =2 August 1989
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Leeds]], England, United Kingdom
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cage, Rob}}
[[Category:1989 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
