<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="323725" ns="0" title="Oracle Database"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| name = Oracle Database
| logo = [[Image:Oracle logo.svg|250px]]
| screenshot =
| caption =
| developer = [[Oracle Corporation]]
| released =
| latest_release_version = | latest_release_date = {{release date|2009|09|01}}
| latest_preview_version =
| latest_preview_date =
| release_location = Equitable Auditorium, 787 Seventh Avenue, New York, NY 10019
| genre = [[Object-relational database management system|ORDBMS]]
| status = Active
| programming language = [[C (programming language)|C]], [[C++]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.lextrait.com/Vincent/implementations.html
| title = The Programming Languages Beacon, v10.0
| first = Vincent
| last = Lextrait
| month = January
| year = 2010
| accessdate = 14 March 2010
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| language = Multi-lingual
| license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
| website = [http://www.oracle.com/ www.oracle.com]
}}

The '''Oracle Database''' (commonly referred to as ''Oracle RDBMS'' or simply as ''Oracle'') is an [[object-relational database management system]] (ORDBMS)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E11882_01/appdev.112/e11822/whatsnew.htm#i969790 |title= What's New|author= |date= |work= |publisher= |accessdate=29 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; produced and marketed by [[Oracle Corporation]].

[[Larry Ellison]] and his friends and former co-workers [[Bob Miner]] and [[Ed Oates]] started the consultancy Software Development Laboratories (SDL) in 1977. SDL developed the original version of the Oracle software. The name ''Oracle'' comes from the code-name of a [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]]-funded project Ellison had worked on while previously employed by [[Ampex]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,3604,215072,00.html |title=Welcome to Larryland |publisher=Guardian |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Physical and logical structures==

An Oracle database system—identified by an alphanumeric system identifier or SID&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/install.111/b32077/glossary.htm?type=popup#BABEBJAG | title = Glossary | accessdate = 2008-11-17 | author = | last = Bhakthavatsalam | first = Namrata | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = 2008 | month = August | work = Oracle Database Client  quote = The SID automatically defaults to the database name portion of the global database name (sales in the example sales.us.example.com) until you reach eight characters or enter a period. You can accept or change the default value. }}&lt;/ref&gt;—comprises at least one [[Database|instance]] of the application, along with data storage. An instance—identified persistently by an instantiation number (or activation id: SYS.V_$DATABASE.ACTIVATION#)—comprises a set of operating-system [[process (computing)|processes]] and [[Computer data storage|memory]]-structures that interact with the [[Computer data storage|storage]]. Typical processes include PMON (the process monitor) and SMON (the system monitor).

Users of the Oracle databases refer to the server-side memory-structure as the SGA (System Global Area). The SGA typically holds [[cache]] information such as data-buffers, [[SQL]] commands, and user information. In addition to storage, the database consists of online [[redo log]]s (or logs), which hold [[Database transaction|transactional]] history. Processes can in turn [[archive]] the online redo logs into archive logs (offline redo logs), which provide the basis (if necessary) for [[data recovery]] and for some forms of [[replication (computer science)|data replication]].

If the Oracle [[database administrator]] has implemented [[Oracle RAC]] (Real Application Clusters), then multiple instances, usually on different [[server (computing)|servers]], attach to a central [[Disk array|storage array]]. This scenario offers advantages such as better performance, scalability and redundancy. However, support becomes more complex, and many sites do not use RAC. In version 10''g'', [[grid computing]] introduced shared resources where an instance can use (for example) [[central processing unit|CPU]] resources from another node (computer) in the grid.

The Oracle DBMS can store and execute [[stored procedure]]s and [[subroutine|functions]] within itself. [[PL/SQL]] (Oracle Corporation's proprietary procedural extension to [[SQL]]), or the object-oriented language [[Java (programming language)|Java]] can invoke such code objects and/or provide the programming structures for writing them.

=== Storage ===

'''The Oracle RDBMS''' [[data storage device|stores data logically]] in the form of [[tablespace]]s and physically in the form of data [[Computer file|files]] (&quot;[[datafile]]s&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last= Alapati
|first= Sam R.
|authorlink=
|title= Expert Oracle Database 11g Administration
|url= http://books.google.com/?id=tdRes4IdLiIC
|accessdate= 2010-07-07
|series= The expert's voice in Oracle
|year= 2008
|publisher= [[Apress]]
|isbn= 9781430210153
|page= 170
|pages= 1344
|quote= Oracle databases are logically divided into one or more tablespaces. An Oracle tablespace is a logical entity that contains the physical datafiles.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Tablespaces can contain various types of [[memory segmentation|memory segments]], such as Data Segments, Index Segments, etc. Segments in turn comprise one or more [[extent (file systems)|extents]]. Extents comprise groups of contiguous data blocks. Data blocks form the basic units of data storage.

There is also a [[Partition (database)|partitioning]] feature available on newer versions of the database, which allows tables to be partitioned based on different set of keys. Specific partitions can then be easily added or dropped to help manage large data sets.

Oracle database management tracks its [[computer data storage]] with the help of information stored in the &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt; tablespace. The &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt; tablespace contains the [[data dictionary]]—and often (by default) [[index (database)|indexes]] and [[cluster (computing)|clusters]]. A data dictionary consists of a special collection of [[table (database)|tables]] that contains information about all user-[[object (computer science)|objects]] in the database. Since version 8''i'', the Oracle RDBMS also supports &quot;locally managed&quot; tablespaces which can store space management information in bitmaps in their own [[header (information technology)|headers]] rather than in the &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt; tablespace (as happens with the default &quot;dictionary-managed&quot; tablespaces).  Version 10''g'' and later introduced the &lt;code&gt;SYSAUX&lt;/code&gt; tablespace which contains some of the tables formerly in the &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt; tablespace.

==== Disk files ====
{{Expand section|date=September 2009}}

Disk files primarily consist of the following types:
* Data and index files: Those files are necessary for the physical storage, which can consist of the data dictionary data (associated to the tablespace SYSTEM), user data, or index data. These files can be managed manually or managed by Oracle itself (&quot;Oracle-managed files&quot;). Note that a datafile has to belong to exactly one tablespace, whereas a tablespace can consist of multiple datafiles.
* Redo log files consisting of all changes to the database, used to recover from an instance failure. Note that often these files are stored multiple times, for extra security in case of disk failure. The identical redo log files are said to belong to the same group.
* Undo files: Those special datafiles, which can only contain undo information, are used for recovery, rollbacks, and read consistency.
* Archive log files: Those files are copies of the redo log files, but are usually stored at different locations. They are necessary for example to be applied to a standby database, or to perform recovery after an instance failure. It is possible to archive to multiple locations.
* Tempfiles: Those special datafiles are used exclusively for temporary storage data (used for example for large sorts)
* Control file, necessary for database startup. &quot;A binary file that records the physical structure of a database and contains the names and locations of redo log files, the time stamp of the database creation, the current log sequence number, checkpoint information, and so on.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Oracle Corporation, Oracle® Database Concepts 11g Release 1 (11.2), http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E11882_01/server.112/e25789/glossary.htm#CHDDFGEC, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

At the physical level, [[data file]]s comprise one or more [[block (data storage)|data blocks]], where the [[block (data storage)|block size]] can vary between data files.

Data files can occupy pre-allocated space in the file system of a computer server, utilize raw disk directly, or exist within [[Automatic Storage Management|ASM]] logical volumes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Bob | last = Watkins | authorlink = | title = Look inside ASM disk groups with Oracle 10''g''R2's ASMCMD | url = http://articles.techrepublic.com.com/5100-10878_11-6154262.html | archiveurl = | work = techrepublic.com | publisher = ZDNet | location = | doi = | date = 30 January 2007 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-07-30 | quote = In 10''g'', Oracle introduced a new kind of storage for its database product. Automatic Storage Management (ASM) is a logical volume manager that takes physical disk partitions and manages their contents [...] Until ASM, there were only two choices: file system storage and raw disk storage. }}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===== Control files =====
The following parameters govern the size of the control files:

 * maxlogfile
 * maxlogmembers
 * maxloghistory
 * maxinstances
 * control_file_record_keep_time

===Database Schema===
Oracle database conventions refer to defined groups of object ownership (generally associated with a &quot;username&quot;) as ''[[database schema|schemas]]''.

Most Oracle database installations traditionally came with a default schema called &lt;code&gt;SCOTT&lt;/code&gt;. After the installation process has set up the sample tables, the user can log into the database with the username &lt;code&gt;scott&lt;/code&gt; and the password &lt;code&gt;tiger&lt;/code&gt;. The name of the &lt;code&gt;SCOTT&lt;/code&gt; schema originated with Bruce Scott, one of the first employees at Oracle (then Software Development Laboratories), who had a cat named Tiger.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080116210119/http://www.orafaq.com/faqora.htm#SCOTT Oracle FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt;

Oracle Corporation has de-emphasized the use of the &lt;code&gt;SCOTT&lt;/code&gt; schema, as it uses few of the features of the more recent releases of Oracle. Most {{As of | 2009 | alt = recent}} examples supplied by Oracle Corporation reference the default HR or OE schemas.

Other default schemas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adp-gmbh.ch/ora/misc/known_schemas.html |title=Known schemas in Oracle |publisher=Adp-gmbh.ch |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcdba.com/abcdbaserver11gdefaultschema |title=11g Default Schema |publisher=ABCdba.com |date= |accessdate=2010-10-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; include:
* &lt;code&gt;SYS&lt;code&gt; (essential core database structures and utilities)
* &lt;code&gt;SYSTEM&lt;code&gt; (additional core database structures and utilities, and privileged account)
* &lt;code&gt;OUTLN&lt;/code&gt; (utilized to store metadata for stored outlines for stable query-optimizer execution plans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adp-gmbh.ch/ora/tuning/cbo/plan_stability.html |title=Optimizer plan stability definition |publisher=Adp-gmbh.ch |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* &lt;code&gt;BI&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;IX&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;HR&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;OE&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;PM&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;SH&lt;/code&gt; (expanded sample schemas&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adp-gmbh.ch/ora/misc/sample_schemas.html |title=Oracle's sample schemas |publisher=Adp-gmbh.ch |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; containing more data and structures than the older &lt;code&gt;SCOTT&lt;/code&gt; schema).

====System Global Area====
{{Main|System Global Area}}

Each Oracle instance uses a [[System Global Area]] or SGA—a [[shared memory|shared-memory]] area—to store its data and control-information.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-class-programme.com/Oracle-Architecture-2.asp |title=Oracle Architecture, System Global Area |publisher=World-class-programme.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

Each Oracle instance allocates itself an SGA when it starts and de-allocates it at shut-down time. The information in the SGA consists of the following elements, each of which has a fixed size, established at instance startup:

* the redo log buffer: this stores redo entries—a log of changes made to the database. The instance writes redo log buffers to the redo log as quickly and efficiently as possible. The redo log aids in instance recovery in the event of a system failure.
* the shared pool: this area of the SGA stores shared-memory structures such as shared SQL areas in the library cache and internal information in the data dictionary. An insufficient amount of memory allocated to the shared pool can cause performance degradation.

====Library cache====
The library cache&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-class-programme.com/Oracle-Architecture-2.asp |title=Oracle architecture, the library cache section |'''publisher=World-class-programme.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; stores shared SQL, caching the parse tree and the execution plan for every unique SQL statement. If multiple applications issue the same SQL statement, each application can access the shared SQL area. This reduces the amount of memory needed and reduces the processing-time used for parsing and execution planning.

====Data dictionary cache====
The [[data dictionary]] comprises a set of tables and  [[view (database)|views]] that map the structure of the database.

Oracle databases store information here about the logical and physical structure of the database. The data dictionary contains information such as:
* user information, such as user privileges
* integrity constraints defined for tables in the database
* names and datatypes of all columns in database tables
* information on space allocated and used for schema objects

The Oracle instance frequently accesses the data dictionary in order to [[parsing|parse]] SQL statements. The operation of Oracle depends on ready access to the data dictionary: performance bottlenecks in the data dictionary affect all Oracle users. Because of this, database administrators should make sure that the data dictionary cache&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-class-programme.com/Oracle-Architecture-2.asp |title=Oracle Architecture, data dictionary cache |publisher=World-class-programme.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; has sufficient capacity to cache this data. Without enough memory for the data-dictionary cache, users see a severe performance degradation. Allocating sufficient memory to the shared pool where the data dictionary cache resides precludes these particular performance problem.

====Program Global Area====
The Program Global Area&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.world-class-programme.com/Oracle-Architecture-2.asp |title=Oracle architecture, Program Global Area section |publisher=World-class-programme.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/mix.102/b14388/gloss-p.htm#index-PGA PGA Definition], Oracle Database Master Glossary&lt;/ref&gt; or PGA memory-area of an Oracle instance contains data and control-information for Oracle's server-processes.

The size and content of the PGA depends on the Oracle-server options installed. This area consists of the following components:
* stack-space: the memory that holds the session's variables, arrays, and so on.
* session-information: unless using the multithreaded server, the instance stores its session-information in the PGA. (In a multithreaded server, the session-information goes in the SGA.)
* private SQL-area: an area which holds information such as bind-variables and runtime-buffers.
* sorting area: an area in the PGA which holds information on sorts, hash-joins, etc.

====Dynamic performance views====
The dynamic performance views (also known as &quot;fixed views&quot;) within an Oracle database present information from virtual tables (X$ tables&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://nyoug.org/Presentations/2002/vviews.PDF
| title = V$ views - don't leave $HOME without them
| first = Mike
| last = Bell
| year = 2002
| publisher = New York Oracle users Group
| location =
| pages = 9–10
| pages = 59
| format = PDF
| accessdate = 2010-03-09
| quote = X$ tables are fixed tables created in memory at database startup [...] V$ views are created on one or more X$ tables
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;)
built on the basis of database memory.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E11882_01/server.112/e10820.pdf
| title = Overview of the Dynamic Performance Views
| first = Morales
| last = Tony
| authorlink =
| coauthors = et al.
| month = October
| year = 2009
| work = Oracle Database Reference 11g Release 2 (11.2)
| publisher = [[Oracle Corporation]]
| location =
| page = 8-1
| pages = 1222
| format = PDF
| accessdate = 2010-03-09
| quote = V$INDEXED_FIXED_COLUMN displays the columns in dynamic performance tables that are indexed (X$ tables).
}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Database users can access the V$ views (named after the prefix of their synonyms) to obtain information on database structures and performance.

===Process architectures===
====Oracle processes====
The Oracle RDBMS typically relies on a group of processes running simultaneously in the [[background process|background]] and interacting to monitor and expedite database operations. Typical operating environments might include some of the following individual processes (shown along with their abbreviated nomenclature):&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28318/process.htm#i16977 |title=Oracle Process architecture concepts |publisher=Download.oracle.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Oracle Advanced Queuing | advanced queueing]] processes (Qnnn)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Antognini
| first      = Christian
| title         = Troubleshooting Oracle Performance
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=b3DIkYO2gBQC
| accessdate    = 2011-05-05
| series    = Apress Series
| year      = 2008
| publisher = Apress
| isbn      = 9781590599174
| page      = 71
| pages     = 616
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* archiver processes (ARCn)
* checkpoint process (CKPT) *REQUIRED*
* coordinator-of-job-queues process (CJQn): dynamically spawns slave processes for job-queues
* database writer processes (DBWn) *REQUIRED*
* dispatcher processes (Dnnn): multiplex server-processes on behalf of users
* job-queue slave processes (Jnnn)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Debes
| first      = Norbert
| title         = Secrets of the Oracle Database
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=g1R96D2uO7kC
| accessdate    = 2011-05-02
| series    = Apress series
| year      = 2009
| publisher = Apress
| isbn      = 9781430219521
| page      = 173
| pages     = 450
| chapterurl    =
| quote         = The job queue is handled by the job queue coordinator process CJQ0 and job queue slave processes (JNNN).
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* log-writer process (LGWR) *REQUIRED*
* log-write network-server (LNSn): transmits redo logs in Data Guard environments
* logical standby coordinator process (LSP0): controls [[Oracle Data Guard|Data Guard]] log-application
* media-recovery process (MRP): detached recovery-server process
* memory-manager process (MMAN): used for internal database tasks such as Automatic Shared Memory Management
* memory-monitor process (MMON): process for automatic problem-detection, self-tuning and statistics-gathering&lt;ref&gt;
[http://my.safaribooksonline.com/9780072263053/new_background_processes_in_10 Safaribooksonline.com]
{{cite book | last= Niemiec | first= Richard | authorlink = | coauthors = | title= Oracle Database 10g Performance Tuning: Tips &amp; Techniques | url= http://my.safaribooksonline.com/9780072263053/new_background_processes_in_10 | accessdate= 2009-08-12 | edition = | series = | volume = | date= 25 June 2007 | origyear = | year = | month = | publisher= Oracle Press | location = | isbn= 978-0-0722-6305-3 | oclc = | doi = | bibcode = | id = | page= 967 | nopp = | chapter= 1.30. New Background Processes in 10''g'' | chapterurl = | quote= MMON Memory Monitor process is associated with the Automatic Workload Repository new features used for automatic problem detection and self-tuning. MMON writes out the required statistics for AWR on a scheduled basis. | ref = | laysummary = | laydate = | separator = | postscript = | lastauthoramp= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* memory-monitor light process (MMNL): gathers and stores Automatic Workload Repository (AWR) data
* mmon slaves (Mnnnn—M0000, M0001, etc.): background slaves of the MMON process&lt;ref&gt;
[http://my.safaribooksonline.com/9780072263053/new_background_processes_in_10 Safaribooksonline.com]{{cite book | last= Niemiec | first= Richard | authorlink = | coauthors = | title= Oracle Database 10g Performance Tuning: Tips &amp; Techniques | url= http://my.safaribooksonline.com/9780072263053/new_background_processes_in_10 | accessdate= 2009-08-12 | edition = | series = | volume = | date= 25 June 2007 | origyear = | year = | month = | publisher= Oracle Press | location = | isbn= 978-0-0722-6305-3 | oclc = | doi = | bibcode = | id = | page= 967 | nopp = | chapter= 1.30. New Background Processes in 10''g'' | chapterurl = | quote= M000 These are MMON background slave (m000) processes. | ref = | laysummary = | laydate = | separator = | postscript = | lastauthoramp= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* process-monitor process (PMON) *REQUIRED*
* process-spawner (PSP0): spawns Oracle processes
* queue-monitor coordinator process (QMNC): dynamically spwans queue monitor slaves&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Dyke
| first      = Julian
| authorlink =
| coauthors  = Steve Shaw
| title         = Pro Oracle database 10g RAC on Linux: installation, administration, and performance
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=GjYTbJTIr54C
| accessdate    = 2011-05-05
| series    = Apress Series
| year      = 2006
| publisher = Apress
| isbn      = 9781590595244
| page      = 45
| pages     = 824
| quote         = In Oracle 10.1, a queue monitor coordinator (QMNC) process [...] dynamically spawns queue monitor slaves (q000 to q009).
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* queue-monitor processes (QMNn)
* recoverer process (RECO)
* remote file-server process (RFS)
* shared server processes (Snnn): serve client-requests
* system monitor process (SMON) *REQUIRED*

====User processes, connections and sessions====
Oracle Database terminology distinguishes different [[computer science|computer-science]] terms in describing how end-users interact with the database:
* user [[process (computing)|processes]] involve the invocation of application software&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/server.102/b14220/process.htm#sthref1481 | title= Process Architecture | accessdate= 2008-08-13 | last= Cyran | first= Michele | coauthors= Paul Lane | date = | year= 2005 | month = | work= Oracle Database Concepts | publisher= Oracle Corporation | quote= When a user runs an application program (such as a Pro*C program) or an Oracle tool (such as Enterprise Manager or SQL*Plus), Oracle creates a user process to run the user's application. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* a connection refers to the pathway linking a user process to an Oracle instance&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/server.102/b14220/process.htm#sthref1481 | title= Process Architecture | accessdate= 2008-08-13 | last= Cyran | first= Michele | coauthors= Paul Lane | date = | year= 2005 | month = | work= Oracle Database Concepts | publisher= Oracle Corporation | quote=A connection is a communication pathway between a user process and an Oracle instance. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[session (computer science)|sessions]] consist of specific connections to an Oracle instance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/server.102/b14220/process.htm#sthref1481 | title= Process Architecture | accessdate= 2008-08-13 | last= Cyran | first= Suraj | first= Michele | coauthors= Paul Lane | date = | year= 2005 | month = | work= Oracle Database Concepts | publisher= Oracle Corporation | quote= A session is a specific connection of a user to an Oracle instance through a user process }}&lt;/ref&gt; Each session within an instance has a session identifier or &quot;SID&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28320/dynviews_3016.htm | title = V$SESSION | accessdate = 2008-11-17 | author = | last = Morales | first = Tony | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = 2008 | month = | work = Oracle Database Reference 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle | location = | pages = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt; (distinct from the system-identifier SID).

===Concurrency and locking===
Oracle databases control simultaneous access to data resources with [[lock (computer science)|locks]] (alternatively documented as &quot;enqueues&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Immanuel | last = Chan | coauthors = | title = Glossary | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28274/glossary.htm?type=popup#sthref1649 | archiveurl = | work = Oracle Database Performance Tuning Guide 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle Corporation | date = | year = 2008 | month = July | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-04-29 | quote = enqueue[:] This is another term for a lock. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
). The databases also utilize &quot;latches&quot; -- low-level serialization mechanisms to protect shared data structures in the System Global Area.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = | last = | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Oracle Database Master Glossary: 11''g'' Release 1 (11.1) | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/mix.111/b14388/gloss-l.htm | archiveurl = | work = | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | doi = | date = | year = | month = | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-04-24 | quote = latch[:] A simple, low-level serialization mechanism to protect shared data structures in the System Global Area. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Configuration===
Database administrators control many of the tunable variations in an Oracle instance by means of values in a parameter file.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Richard | last = Strohm | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = et al. | title = Parameter Files | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28318/intro.htm#sthref23 | archiveurl = | work = Oracle Database Concepts 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = | month = October | year = 2008 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-07-14 | quote = Parameter files contain a list of configuration parameters for that instance and database. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
This file in its ASCII default form (&quot;pfile&quot;) normally has a name of the format &lt;code&gt;init&lt;SID-name&gt;.ora&lt;/code&gt;. The default binary equivalent server paramater file (&quot;spfile&quot;) (dynamically reconfigurable to some extent)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Richard | last = Strohm | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = et al. | title = Initialization Parameter Files and Server Parameter Files | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28318/startup.htm#i9633 | archiveurl = | work = Oracle Database Concepts 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = | month = October | year = 2008 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-07-14 | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
defaults to the format &lt;code&gt;spfile&lt;SID-name&gt;.ora&lt;/code&gt;. Within an SQL-based environment, the views &lt;code&gt;V$PARAMETER&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Tony | last = Morales | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = et al. | title = V$PARAMETER | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28320/dynviews_2.htm#insertedID85 | archiveurl = | work = Oracle Database Reference 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = | month = April | year = 2009 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-07-14 | quote = V$PARAMETER displays information about the initialization parameters that are currently in effect for the session. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;V$SPPARAMETER&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Tony | last = Morales | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = et al. | title = V$SPPARAMETER | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28320/dynviews_3.htm#insertedID41 | archiveurl = | work = Oracle Database Reference 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = | month = April | year = 2009 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-07-14 | quote = V$SPPARAMETER displays information about the contents of the server parameter file. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
give access to reading parameter values.

==Internationalization==
Oracle Database software comes in 63 language-versions (including regional variations such as British English and American English). Variations between versions cover the names of days and months, abbreviations, time-symbols such as A.M. and A.D., and sorting.&lt;ref name=&quot;titleLocale Data&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/server.102/b14225/applocaledata.htm#i634428 |title=Locale Languages |accessdate=2008-02-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Oracle Corporation has translated Oracle Database error-messages into Arabic, Catalan, Chinese, Czech, Danish, Dutch, English, Finnish, French, German, Greek, Hebrew, Hungarian, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese, Romanian, Russian, Slovak, Spanish, Swedish, Thai and Turkish.&lt;ref name=&quot;titleMessages Data&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/server.102/b14225/applocaledata.htm#i634673 | title=Error Message Languages |accessdate=2008-02-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- could not find list of documentation translations yet--&gt;

Oracle Corporation provides database developers with tools and mechanisms for producing internationalized database applications: referred to internally as &quot;Globalization&quot;.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arjudba.blogspot.com | title = A complete RMAN shell script backup for Oracle 8i, 9i, 10g, 11g | accessdate = 2010-11-07 | author = | last = Arju | first = Md. Abdul | authorlink = | coauthors = ''et al.'' | date = | year = 2010 | month = November | work = A complete RMAN shell script backup for Oracle 8i, 9i, 10g, 11g
 | publisher = [[Md.Abdul Arju]] | location = | pages = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | dateformat = | quote = A complete RMAN backup shell script that will work regardless of most used oracle version as well as most used unix operating system.  In this script it is assumed that you are using recovery catalog for you rman backup.
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28298/ch1overview.htm#sthref8 | title = Overview of Globalization Support | accessdate = 2009-02-16 | author = | last = Shea | first = Cathy | authorlink = | coauthors = ''et al.'' | date = | year = 2007 | month = September | work = Oracle Database Globalization Support Guide 11g Release 1 (11.1) | publisher = [[Oracle Corporation]] | location = | pages = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | dateformat = | quote = In the past, Oracle referred to globalization support capabilities as National Language Support (NLS) features. NLS is actually a subset of globalization support. NLS is the ability to choose a national language and store data in a specific character set. Globalization support enables you to develop multilingual applications and software products that can be accessed and run from anywhere in the world simultaneously. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Corporate/technical timeline===
* 1977: [[Larry Ellison]] and friends founded Software Development Laboratories.
* 1979: SDL changed its company-name to &quot;Relational Software, Inc.&quot; (RSI) and introduced its product Oracle V2 as an early commercially available relational database system. The version did not support [[database transaction|transactions]], but implemented the basic [[SQL]] functionality of [[query language|queries]] and [[join (SQL)|joins]]. (RSI never released a version 1 - instead calling the first version ''version 2'' as a [[marketing strategy|marketing gimmick]].)&lt;ref&gt;As Larry Ellison said in an Oracle OpenWorld keynote [http://news.cnet.com/8301-10784_3-9814858-7.html presentation] on 11 November 2007: &quot;Who'd buy a version 1.0 from four guys in California?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1982: RSI in its turn changed its name, becoming known as &quot;[[Oracle Corporation]]&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/oramag/profit/07-may/p27anniv_timeline.pdf Oracle.com]&lt;/ref&gt; to align itself more closely with its flagship product.
* 1983: The company released Oracle version 3, which it had re-written using the [[C (programming language)|C programming language]] and which supported &lt;code&gt;[[Commit (data management)|COMMIT]]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;[[Rollback (data management)|ROLLBACK]]&lt;/code&gt; functionality for transactions. Version 3 extended platform support from the existing [[Digital Equipment Corporation|Digital]] [[VAX/VMS]] systems to include [[Unix]] environments.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;
* 1984: Oracle Corporation released Oracle version 4, which supported [[consistency model|read-consistency]].
* 1985: Oracle Corporation released Oracle version 5, which supported the [[client–server model]]—a sign of networks becoming more widely available in the mid-1980s.
* 1986: Oracle version 5.1 started supporting [[distributed computing|distributed]] queries.
* 1988: Oracle RDBMS version 6 came out with support for [[PL/SQL]] embedded within [[Oracle Forms]] v3 (version 6 could not store PL/SQL in the database proper), row-level [[lock (computer science)|locking]] and hot [[backup]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Compare [http://www.oracle.com/oramag/profit/07-may/p27anniv_timeline.pdf Oracle.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* 1989: Oracle Corporation entered the [[application software|application products]] market and developed its [[Enterprise resource planning|ERP]] product, (later to become part of the [[Oracle E-Business Suite]]), based on the Oracle relational database.
* 1990: the release of [[Oracle Applications]] release 8&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;
* 1992: Oracle version 7 appeared with support for [[referential integrity]], [[stored procedure]]s and [[database trigger|triggers]].
* 1997: Oracle Corporation released version 8, which supported [[Object-oriented programming|object-oriented]] development and [[multimedia]] applications.
* 1999: The release of Oracle8''i'' aimed to provide a database inter-operating better with the [[Internet]] (the ''i'' in the name stands for &quot;Internet&quot;). The Oracle8''i'' database incorporated a native [[Java Virtual Machine|Java virtual machine]] ([[Oracle JVM]], also known as &quot;Aurora&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Harrison
| first      = Guy
| title         = Oracle SQL high-performance tuning
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=bh6CLbeKQ4QC
| accessdate    = 2011-01-20
| edition   = 2
| series    = Prentice Hall PTR Oracle series
| year      = 2001
| publisher = Prentice Hall PTR
| isbn      = 9780130123817
| page      = 590
| pages     = 630
| quote         = Aurora[:] The name of the Java Virtual Machine (JVM) incorporated into Oracle8i.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;).
* 2000: Oracle E-Business Suite 11''i'' pioneers integrated enterprise application software&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;
* 2001: Oracle9''i'' went into release with 400 new features, including the ability to read and write [[XML]] documents. 9''i'' also provided an option for [[Oracle RAC]], or &quot;Real Application Clusters&quot;, a [[computer cluster|computer-cluster]] database, as a replacement for the [[Oracle Parallel Server]] (OPS) option.
* 2003: Oracle Corporation released Oracle Database 10''g'', which supported [[regular expressions]]. (The ''g'' stands for &quot;grid&quot;; emphasizing a marketing thrust of presenting 10''g'' as &quot;[[grid computing]] ready&quot;.)
* 2005: Oracle Database 10.2.0.1—also known as Oracle Database 10''g'' Release 2 (10''g''R2)—appeared.
* 2006: Oracle Corporation announces [[Unbreakable Linux]]&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot; /&gt;
* 2007: Oracle Database 10''g'' release 2 sets a new [[world record]] TPC-H 3000 GB [[benchmark (computing)|benchmark]] result&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.itmanagement.com/press-releases/oracle-tpc-h-record-060806/ |title=Oracle Database 10''g'' Sets New Record for TPC-H Three TB Benchmark |accessdate=2008-01-31 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* 2007: Oracle Corporation released Oracle Database 11''g'' for [[Linux]] and for [[Microsoft Windows]].
* 2008: Oracle Corporation acquires [[BEA Systems]].
* 2010: Oracle Corporation acquires [[Sun Microsystems]].
===Critical Patch Updates (CPUs) and Security Alerts===
[http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/topics/security/alerts-086861.html Oracle Critical Patch Updates (CPUs) and Security Alerts] are released quarterly on the Tuesday closest to 17th day of the month. The general goal of the patches is to close security holes through which data theft may occurred. 
* [http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/topics/security/securityemail-090378.html You may receive release notification by email].
* White Paper: [http://www.oracle.com/us/support/assurance/leveraging-cpu-wp-164638.pdf?ssSourceSiteId=otnen Critical Patch Update Implementation Best Practices]

===Version numbering===
Oracle products follow a custom release numbering and naming convention. With the Oracle RDBMS 10''g'' release, Oracle Corporation began using the &quot;10''g''&quot; label in all versions of its major products, although some sources refer to Oracle Applications Release 11''i'' as Oracle 11''i''.{{Clarify|date=August 2011}} The suffixes &quot;i&quot; and &quot;g&quot; do not actually represent a low-order part of the version number, as letters typically represent in software industry version numbering;  that is, there is no predecessor version of Oracle 10''g'' called Oracle 10''f''. Instead, the letters stand for &quot;internet&quot; and &quot;grid&quot;, respectively.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} Consequently many simply drop the &quot;g&quot; or &quot;i&quot; suffix when referring to specific versions of an Oracle product.

Major database-related products and some of their versions include:
* [[Oracle Application Server]] 10''g'' (also known as &quot;Oracle AS 10''g''&quot;): a [[middleware]] product;
* [[Oracle Applications]] Release 11''i'' (aka Oracle e-Business Suite, Oracle Financials or Oracle 11i): a [[software suite|suite]] of [[business]] applications;
* [[Oracle Developer Suite]] 10''g'' (9.0.4);
* [[JDeveloper|Oracle JDeveloper]] 10''g'': a [[Java (programming language)|Java]] [[integrated development environment]];

Since version 5, Oracle's [[Relational database management system|RDBMS]] release numbering has used the following codes:
* Oracle v5
* Oracle v6
* Oracle7: 7.0.16–7.3.4
* Oracle8 Database: 8.0.3–8.0.6
* Oracle8''i'' Database Release 1: 8.1.5.0–8.1.5.1
* Oracle8''i'' Database Release 2: 8.1.6.0–8.1.6.3
* Oracle8''i'' Database Release 3: 8.1.7.0–8.1.7.4
* Oracle9''i'' Database Release 1: 9.0.1.0–9.0.1.5 ([[patch (computing)|patchset]] {{As of|2003|alt=as of December 2003}})
* Oracle9''i'' Database Release 2: 9.2.0.1–9.2.0.8 (patchset {{As of|2007|alt=as of April 2007}})
* Oracle Database 10''g'' Release 1: 10.1.0.2–10.1.0.5 (patchset {{As of|2006|alt=as of February 2006}})
* Oracle Database 10''g'' Release 2: 10.2.0.1–10.2.0.5 (patchset {{As of|2010|alt=as of April 2010}})
* Oracle Database 11''g'' Release 1: 11.1.0.6–11.1.0.7 (patchset {{As of|2008|alt=as of September 2008}})
* Oracle Database 11''g'' Release 2: 11.2.0.1–11.2.0.3 (patchset {{As of|2011|alt=as of September 2011}})

The version-numbering syntax within each release follows the pattern: major.maintenance.application-server.component-specific.platform-specific.

For example, &quot;10.2.0.1 for 64-bit Solaris&quot; means: 10th major version of Oracle, maintenance level 2, Oracle Application Server (OracleAS) 0, level 1 for Solaris 64-bit.

The ''Oracle Administrator's Guide'' offers further information on Oracle release numbers.

==Marketing editions==
Over and above the different versions of the Oracle database management software developed over time, Oracle Corporation subdivides its product into varying &quot;editions&quot; - apparently for marketing and license-tracking reasons. (Do not confuse the marketing &quot;editions&quot; with the internal virtual versioning &quot;editions&quot; introduced with Oracle 11.2&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url = http://www.oracle.com/technology/deploy/availability/pdf/edition_based_redefinition.pdf
| title = Edition-Based Redefinition
| first = Bryn
| last = Llewellyn
| authorlink =
| month = July
| year = 2009
| work =
| publisher = [[Oracle Corporation]]
| location = Redwood Shores, California
| page = 6
| pages = 45
| format = PDF
| accessdate = 2010-03-09
| quote = An edition is a [...] nonschema object type, uniquely identified [...] by just its name.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;). In approximate order of decreasing scale, we find:
* Enterprise Edition&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/database/enterprise_edition.html Enterprise Edition]&lt;/ref&gt; (EE) includes more features than the 'Standard Edition', especially in the areas of performance and security. Oracle Corporation licenses this product on the basis of users or of processors, typically for servers running 4 or more CPUs. EE has no memory limits, and can utilize clustering using [[Oracle RAC]] software.
* Standard Edition&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/database/standard_edition.html Standard Edition]&lt;/ref&gt; (SE) contains base database functionality. Oracle Corporation licenses this product on the basis of users or of processors, typically for servers running from one to four CPUs. If the number of CPUs exceeds 4 CPUs, the user must convert to an Enterprise license. SE has no memory limits, and can utilize clustering with [[Oracle RAC]] at no additional charge.
* Standard Edition One,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/database/std_one.html Standard Edition One]&lt;/ref&gt; (SE1&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url         = http://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/12391/1/MPRA_paper_12391.pdf
| title       = Technologies solutions and Oracle instruments used in the accomplishment of executive informatics systems (EIS)
| first       = Vatuiu
| last        = Teodora
| date        = 2008-12-27
| work        = MPRA: Munich Personal RePEc Archive
| page        = 1555
| pages       = 1555–1559
| format      = PDF
| accessdate  = 2011-05-09
| quote       = Oracle Database 10g Standard Edition One (SE1) is intended for business mediums with quite a low request of adaptation[...]
| postscript  =
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; or SEO) introduced with Oracle 10''g'', has some additional feature-restrictions. Oracle Corporation markets it for use on systems with one or two CPUs. It has no memory limitations.
* Express Edition&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url         = http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/database/xe/index.html
| title       = Oracle Database 10''g'' Express Edition
| work        = Oracle Technology Network
| publisher   = Oracle Corp.
| accessdate  = 2010-07-25
| quote       = Oracle Database 10''g'' Express Edition (Oracle Database XE) is an entry-level, small-footprint database based on the Oracle Database 10''g'' Release 2 code base that's free to develop, deploy, and distribute [...]
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (&quot;Oracle Database XE&quot;), introduced in 2005, offers Oracle 10''g'' free to distribute on Windows and Linux platforms. It has a footprint of only 150 MB and is restricted to the use of a single CPU, a maximum of 4 GB of user data. Although it can install on a server with any amount of memory, it uses a maximum of 1 GB.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/database/xe/pdf/dbxe_faq.pdf |title=Oracle Data Sheet |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; Support for this version comes exclusively through on-line forums and not through Oracle support.
* Oracle Database Lite,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = | last = | author = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Oracle Database Lite 10''g'' | url = http://www.oracle.com/database/lite_edition.html | archiveurl = | work = oracle.com | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = | month = | year = | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-06-23 | quote = [...] for developing, deploying and managing applications for mobile and embedded environments. }}&lt;/ref&gt; intended for running on [[mobile device]]s. The embedded&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|first1= Rick
|last1= Greenwald
|author1-link=
|first2= Robert
|last2= Stackowiak
|author2-link=
|first3= Jonathan
|last3= Stern
|author3-link=
|title= Oracle Essentials: Oracle Database 11g
|url= http://books.google.com/?id=EmvWP1vgTsYC
|accessdate= 2010-06-08
|edition= 4
|series= Essential Series
|year= 2007
|publisher= O'Reilly Media
|location=
|isbn= 9780596514549
|page= 31
|pages= 386
|quote= Today, Oracle offers other embedded databases including TimesTen, Berkeley DB, and Oracle Database Lite.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; [[mobile database]] located on the mobile device can synchronize with a server-based installation.

==Host platforms==
Prior to releasing Oracle 9''i'' in 2001, Oracle Corporation ported its database product to a wide variety of platforms. More recently Oracle Corporation has consolidated on a smaller range of operating-system platforms.

{{As of|2011|11}}, Oracle Corporation supported the following operating systems and hardware platforms for Oracle Database 11''g'' (11.2.0.2.0) &lt;ref&gt;http://www.oracle.com/pls/db112/portal.portal_db?selected=11&lt;/ref&gt;:

* [[zLinux64]]
* [[Microsoft Windows (32-bit)]]
* [[Microsoft Windows (x64)]]
* [[Linux x86]]
* [[Linux x86-64]]
* [[Solaris (SPARC)]] (64-bit)
* [[Solaris]] (x86-64)
* [[HP-UX Itanium]]
* [[HP-UX PA-RISC]] (64-bit)
* [[AIX]] (PPC64)

==Related software==
=== Oracle products ===
* Oracle Database Firewall&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url         = http://www.oracle.com/secerno/index.html
| title       = Oracle and Secerno
| year        = 2010
| publisher   = Oracle Corporation
| accessdate  = 2010-10-18
| quote       = Secerno product[:] Oracle Database Firewall
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; analyzes database traffic on a network to prevent threats such as [[SQL injection]].&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url         = http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/database-firewall/overview/index.html
| title       = Oracle Database Fiorewall: Frequently Asked Questions
| work        = Oracle Technology Network
| publisher   = Oracle Corporation
| accessdate  = 2011-03-28
| quote       =  It is designed to prevent SQL Injection attacks [...]  It is [...] deployed on the network to monitor and secures database traffic coming through the network.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Database options===
Oracle Corporation refers to some extensions to the core functionality of the Oracle database as &quot;database options&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/us/products/database/options/index.html Oracle database options]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{As of|2008}} such options include:
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/active-data-guard.html Active Data Guard] (extends [[Oracle Data Guard]] physical standby functionality in 11''g'')
* Advanced Compression (compresses tables, backups and redo-data)&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Alapati
| first      = Sam R.
| coauthors  = Charles Kim
| title         = Oracle database 11g: new features for DBAs and developers
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=14ZH0eZV6G8C
| accessdate    = 2011-05-10
| series    = Expert's voice in Oracle
| year      = 2007
| publisher = Apress
| isbn      = 9781590599105
| page      = 153
| pages     = 602
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/advanced-security.html Advanced Security] (adds data encryption methods)
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/contentdb.html Content database] (provides a centralized repository for unstructured information)
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/database-vault.html Database Vault] (enforces extra security on data access)
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/bi/odm/index.html Data Mining] ( [[Oracle Data Mining|ODM]]) (mines for patterns in existing data)
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/in-memory-database-cache.html In-Memory Database Cache] (utilizes [[TimesTen]] technology)
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/label-security.html Label Security] (enforces row-level security)
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/oem/extensions/index.html Management Packs] (various). For example:
** Oracle Database Change Management Pack&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       =  Adkoli
| first      = Anand
| coauthors  = Rama Velpuri
| title         = Oracle9i for Windows handbook
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=L8K5BAt7kzcC
| accessdate    = 2011-01-26
| edition   = 2
| series    = Oracle Press Series
| year      = 2002
| publisher = McGraw-Hill Professional
| isbn      = 9780072190922
| page      = 375
| pages     = 528
| quote         = Oracle Change Management Pack[:] A new feature available on Oracle9i allows you to track and make changes to database object definitions. You can compare two objects in different schemas or different databases.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
| url         = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B14099_19/manage.1012/b16241/Management_Pack_Access.htm
| title       = Oracle Database Change Management Pack
| first       = Phil
| last        = Choi
| year        = 2005
| work        = Oracle Enterprise Manager Concepts, 10g Release 2 (10.2)
| publisher   = Oracle Corporation
| accessdate  = 2011-01-26
| quote       = This pack gives database administrators the ability to evaluate, plan for, and implement database schema changes to support new application requirements without error and data loss while minimizing downtime.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (tracks and manages schema changes)
* [http://www.oracle.com/appserver/business-intelligence/standard-edition-one.html Oracle Answers] (for ''ad-hoc'' analysis and reporting)
* [http://www.oracle.com/solutions/business_intelligence/olap.html Oracle OLAP] (adds [[Online analytical processing|analytical processing]])
* Oracle Programmer (provides programmatic access to Oracle databases via [[precompiler]]s, interfaces and [[language binding|bindings]])&lt;ref&gt;See download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/license.111/b28287/options.htm#CIHBDGAD&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/oracle9i/datasheets/partitioning.html Partitioning] (granularizes tables and indexes for efficiency)
* [[Oracle RAC|Real Application Clusters]] (RAC) (coordinates multiple database servers, together accessing the same database)
* [[Oracle Real Application Testing]] (new at version 11''g'')—including Database Replay (for testing workloads) and SQL Performance Analyzer (SPA) (for preserving SQL efficiency in changing environments)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/manageability/database/pdf/wp07/owp_real_application_testing_11g.pdf | title= Real Application Testing Overview | accessdate= 2008-05-19 | year= 2007 | month= August | publisher= Oracle Corporation }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/recordsdb.html Records database]&lt;!-- inaccessible as of 2008-07-10 Compare http://www.oracle.com/accessibility/templates/t997.html --&gt; (a [[records management]] application)
* [[Oracle Spatial]] (integrates relational data with [[geographic information systems]] (GIS))
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/oracle9i/datasheets/gateways/gateway_rel2_ds.html Transparent Gateway] for connecting to non-Oracle systems. Offers optimized solution, with more functionality and better performance than Oracle Generic Connectivity.
* [http://www.oracle.com/database/total-recall.html Total Recall] (optimizes long-term storage of historical data)
* [[Oracle Warehouse Builder]] (in various forms and sub-options)
* [http://www.oracle.com/us/products/middleware/data-integration/goldengate/index.html Oracle GoldenGate 11''g''] (distributed real-time data acquisition)

{{Expand list|date=August 2008}}

In most cases, using these options entails extra licensing costs.&lt;ref&gt;
See &quot;Term licenses&quot; at http://oraclestore.oracle.com/ for various markets/countries.
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Suites===
In addition to its [[Relational database management system|RDBMS]], Oracle Corporation has released several related suites of tools and applications relating to implementations of Oracle databases. For example:
* [[Oracle Application Server]], a J2EE-based [[application server]], aids in developing and deploying applications which utilise [[Internet]] technologies and a browser.
* [[Oracle Collaboration Suite]] contains messaging, groupware and collaboration applications.
* [[Oracle Developer Suite]] contains software development tools, including [[JDeveloper]].
* [[Oracle E-Business Suite]] collects together applications for [[enterprise resource planning]] (including [[Oracle Financials]]), [[customer relationship management]] and [[human resources]] management ([[Oracle HR]]).
* [[Oracle Enterprise Manager]] (OEM) used by [[database administrator]]s (DBAs) to manage the DBMS, and {{As of|2007|alt= recently}} in version 10''g'', a web-based rewrite of OEM called &quot;Oracle Enterprise Manager Database Control&quot;. Oracle Corporation has dubbed the super-Enterprise-Manager used to manage a grid of multiple DBMS and Application Servers &quot;Oracle Enterprise Manager Grid Control&quot;.
* Oracle Programmer/2000, a bundling of interfaces for [[Third-generation programming language|3GL programming languages]], marketed with Oracle7 and Oracle8.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.alise.lv/ALISE/mrktinfo.nsf/6022a43db1063796c22566de00392130/420e0389f8672386c225645e00344ecb/$FILE/Oracle%20Programmer%202000%20data%20sheet%20Feb97.pdf | title = Oracle Programmer/2000 | accessdate = 2009-02-25 | author = | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = | month = | format = PDF | work = | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | pages = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | dateformat = | quote = Oracle Programmer/2000 is a suite of programmatic interfaces that allows you to access and manipulate Oracle7 data and schemas. Programmer/2000 provides a rich set of interfaces and supports many programming languages, allowing the programmer to use the programming language and the programming paradigm of choice. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/A58617_01/server.804/a53717/ch1.htm#index0015 | title = Other Ways of Working with Oracle | accessdate = 2009-02-25 | author = | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = | month = | work = | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | dateformat = | quote = Programmer/2000[:] a set of 3GL programming language interfaces }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Oracle WebCenter]] Suite&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| last       = Desbiens
| first      = Frédéric
| coauthors  = Peter Moskovits, Philipp Weckerle
| title         = Oracle WebCenter 11g Handbook: Build Rich, Customizable Enterprise 2.0 Applications
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=mjiiLhfQ4s8C
| accessdate    = 2011-05-09
| series    = Osborne ORACLE Press Series
| year      = 2009
| publisher = McGraw Hill Professional
| isbn      = 9780071629324
| page      = 189
| pages     =
| nopp      = 498
| quote         = Oracle WebCenter Suite includes Content Server [...]
| postscript    =
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Database &quot;features&quot;===
Apart from the clearly defined database options, Oracle databases may include many semi-autonomous software sub-systems, which Oracle Corporation sometimes refers to as &quot;features&quot; in a sense subtly different from the normal usage of the word. For example, [[Oracle Data Guard]] counts officially as a &quot;feature&quot;, but the command-stack within SQL*Plus, though a usability feature, does not appear in the list of &quot;features&quot; in [http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B19306_01/license.102/b14199/editions.htm#CJACGHEB Oracle's list].{{Or|date=December 2009}} Such &quot;features&quot; may include (for example):

* Active Session History (ASH), the collection of data for immediate monitoring of very recent database activity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last= Alapati | first= Sam R. | authorlink = | title= Expert Oracle database 10g administration | url= http://books.google.com/?id=xxx0KAwY_ZMC&amp;pg=PA845&amp;lpg=PA845&amp;dq=ASH++Active+Session+History | accessdate= 2009-05-25 | edition = | series = | volume = | date = | origyear = | year= 2005 | month = | publisher= Apress | location = | language = | isbn= 9781590594513 | oclc = | doi = | bibcode = | id = | page= 845 | pages = | nopp = | chapter = | chapterurl = | quote= ... ASH records very recent session activity (within the last five or ten minutes). | ref = | laysummary = | laydate = | separator = | postscript = | lastauthoramp= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/pub/articles/10gdba/week6_10gdba.html Automatic Workload Repository (AWR)], providing monitoring services to Oracle database installations from Oracle version 10. Prior to the release of Oracle version 10, the Statspack facility&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite journal
| last =
| first =
| author = Sai Peck lee
| coauthors = Džemal Zildžić
| year = 2006
| title = Oracle Database Workload Performance Measurement and Tuning Toolkit
| journal = Issues in Informing Science and Information Technology
| volume = 3
| pages = 371–381
| url = http://google.com/scholar?q=cache:uPdNes3VcSAJ:scholar.google.com/
| accessdate = 2010-02-05
| quote = Statspack utility consists of a set of Programming Language/Structured Query Language (PL/SQL) scripts, executed against the database, in order to gather, store data and metrics, and generates reports of the database activity
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; provided similar functionality.
* Clusterware
* [http://www.oracle.com/solutions/business_intelligence/warehouse-builder.html Data Aggregation and Consolidation]
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/deploy/availability/htdocs/DataGuardOverview.html Data Guard] for [[high availability]]
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/products/oracle9i/datasheets/gateways/gateway_rel2_ds.html Generic Connectivity] for connecting to non-Oracle systems.
* Data Pump utilities, which aid in importing and exporting data and metadata between databases&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28319/dp_overview.htm#SUTIL100 |title=Overview of Oracle Data Pump |publisher=Download.oracle.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Database Resource Manager (DRM), which controls the use of computing resources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last= Greenwald | first= Rick | authorlink = | coauthors=Robert Stackowiak, Jonathan Stern | editor = | others = | title=Oracle Essentials: Oracle Database 11g | origdate = | origyear = | origmonth = | url = | accessdate = | edition = | series = | volume = | date = | year= 2007 | month= November | publisher= O'Reilly | location = | language = | isbn= 978-0596514549 | oclc = | doi = | id = | page= 184 | pages = | chapter = | chapterurl = | quote= The Database Resource Manager (DRM) was first introduced in Oracle 8''i'' [...] to place limits on the amount of computer resources that can be used [...] | ref= }}&lt;/ref&gt;
*  Fast-start parallel rollback&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
| first1 = Mike
| last1 = Ault
| author1-link  = Mike Ault
| first2 =  Daniel
| last2 = Liu
| first3 = Madhu
| last3 = Tumma
| editor        = Don Burleson
| title         = Oracle Database 10g New Features: Oracle 10g Reference for Advanced Tuning &amp; Administration
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=ufz5-hXw2_UC
| accessdate    = 2011-11-16
| series    = Oracle In-Focus series
| year      = 2003
| publisher = Rampant TechPress
| isbn      = 9780974071602
| page      = 51
| pages     = 544
| quote         = In the fast-start parallel rollback method, the background process SMON [...] rolls back a set of transactions in parallel [...] This feature is particularly useful when a system has transactions that run a long time before committing [...]
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
* Fine-grained auditing (FGA) (in Oracle Enterprise Edition&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/license.111/b28287/editions.htm#CJACGHEB | title= Feature Availability by Edition | accessdate= 2008-08-19 | author = | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year= 2008 | month= May | work= Oracle Database Licensing Information 11g Release 1 (11.1) Part Number B28287-08 | publisher= Oracle Corporation | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote= }}&lt;/ref&gt;) supplements standard security-auditing features&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url= http://www.oracle.com/technology/pub/articles/10gdba/week10_10gdba.html | title= Auditing Tells All | accessdate= 2008-08-19 | last= Nanda | first= Arup | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = | month = | work= Oracle Database 10g: The Top 20 Features for DBAs | publisher= Oracle Corporation | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote= ...the standard audit (available in all versions) and the fine-grained audit (available in Oracle 9''i'' and up ... }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Oracle Flashback|Flashback]] for selective data recovery and reconstruction&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oracle.com/technology/deploy/availability/htdocs/Flashback_Overview.htm Oracle.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/tech/sql_plus/index.html iSQL*Plus], a web-browser-based [[graphical user interface]] (GUI) for Oracle database [[Data Manipulation Language|data-manipulation]] (compare SQL*Plus)
* Oracle Data Access Components (ODAC), tools which consist of:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Oracle Product Accessibility Status: Database Server Enterprise Edition | url = http://www.oracle.com/accessibility/templates/t1286.html | archiveurl = | work = | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | page = | pages = | doi = | date = 2 June 2008 | year = | month = | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Oracle Data Provider for .NET (ODP.NET)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = Oracle Data Provider for .NET | url = http://www.oracle.com/technology/tech/windows/odpnet/index.html | archiveurl = | work = | publisher = Oracle Corporation | location = | doi = | date = | year = | month = | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-05-07 | quote = The Oracle Data Provider for .NET (ODP.NET) features optimized [[ADO.NET]] data access to the Oracle database. }}&lt;/ref&gt;
** Oracle Developer Tools (ODT) for Visual Studio
** Oracle Providers for ASP.NET
** Oracle Database Extensions for .NET
** Oracle Provider for OLE DB
** Oracle Objects for OLE
** Oracle Services for Microsoft Transaction Server
* [http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/server.111/b28310/omf.htm#i1007206 Oracle-managed files] (OMF) -- a feature allowing automated naming, creation and deletion of datafiles at the operating-system level.
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20051208092120/http://www.oracle.com/technology/deploy/availability/htdocs/rman_overview.htm Recovery Manager] (rman) for [[database dump|database backup]], [[Data restoration|restoration]] and [[data recovery|recovery]]
* [[SQL*Plus]], a program that allows users to interact with Oracle database(s) via [[SQL]] and [[PL/SQL]] commands on a [[command line interface|command-line]]. Compare iSQL*Plus.
* Universal Connection Pool (UCP), a [[connection pool]] based on Java and supporting [[JDBC]], LDAP, and [[Java EE Connector Architecture | JCA]]&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book 
| first1 = Rick 
| last1 = Greenwald 
| first2 = Robert
| last2 = Stackowiak 
| first3 = Maqsood 
| last3 = Alam
| first4 = Mans
| last4 = Bhuller
| title         = Achieving Extreme Performance with Oracle Exadata
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=HFJzNfWonPQC 
| accessdate    = 2011-10-12
| series    = Osborne ORACLE Press Series
| year      = 2011
| publisher = McGraw-Hill Prof Med/Tech
| isbn      = 9780071752596
| page      = 328
| pages     = 432
| quote         = The UCP is a Java-basd connection pool that supports JDBC, the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) and Java EE Connector Architecture (JCA) connection types from any middle tier.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
*  [[Virtual private database|Virtual Private Database]]&lt;ref&gt;
&quot;Virtual Private Database&quot; appears listed as a feature available as part of Oracle Enterprise Edition in:
{{cite web
| url = http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E11882_01/license.112/e10594/editions.htm
| title = Feature Availability by Edition
| author = Manmeet Ahluwalia
| coauthors = et al.
| month = October
| year = 2009
| work = Oracle Database Licensing Information 11g Release 2 (11.2)
| publisher = Oracle Corporation
| accessdate = 2010-02-09
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; (VPD), an implementation of fine-grained access control.&lt;ref&gt;
{{Cite document
 | last = Kate
 | first = Aniket
 | author-link =
 | last2 = Menezes
 | first2 = Bernard
 | author2-link =
 | last3 = Singh
 | first3 = Ashish
 | author3-link =
 | publication-date = December 2005
 | contribution = Security/Privacy Issues in Providing Database as a Service
 | title = Proceedings of 3rd International Conference on E-Governance, ICEG 2005
 | pages = 156–159
 | DUPLICATE DATA: pages = 158–159
 | publication-place = Lahore
 | publisher = Lahore University of Management Sciences
 | url = http://www.iceg.net/2006/download/E-Governance.pdf
 | accessdate = 2010-02-09
 | quote = Oracle's Virtual Private Database (VPD) [...] is a practically implemented model for fine-grained access control wherein one or more security policies are attached to each table and view in the database. These polices are sets of functions coded in PL/SQL, C or Java. A user query that accesses a table or view having a security policy, is dynamically and transparently modified by appending a predicate. This predicate is returned by the policy function for the relation/view and is a function of the user who has fired the query. A secure application context is created for each user at log in.
 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Expand list|date=August 2008}}

===Standalone tools===
Users can develop their own [[application software|applications]] in [[Java (programming language)|Java]] and [[PL/SQL]] using tools such as:

* [[Oracle JDeveloper]]
* [[Oracle Forms]]
* [[Oracle Reports]]

Oracle Corporation has started{{Clarify|date=April 2008}} &lt;!-- when ? --&gt; a drive toward &quot;wizard&quot;-driven environments with a view to enabling non-programmers to produce simple [[data-driven]] applications.

[[Oracle SQL Developer]], a free graphical tool for database development, allows developers to browse database objects, run SQL statements and SQL scripts, and edit and debug PL/SQL statements. It incorporates standard and customized reporting.

Oracle's '''OPatch''' provides [[Patch (computing) | patch]] management for Oracle databases.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book 
| first1 = Darl
| last1 = Kuhn
| first2 = Charles
| last2 = Kim
| first3 =  Bernard
| last3 = Lopuz
| title         = Linux Recipes for Oracle DBAs
| url           = http://books.google.com/books?id=oqmW4BwSteoC
| accessdate    = 2011-12-05
| series    = Apress Series
| year      = 2008 
| publisher = Apress
| isbn      = 9781430215752
| page      = 275
| pages     = 501
| quote         = OPatch is a collection of Perl scripts and Java classes providing the capability to apply and roll back interim (one-off) patches to an Oracle database environment.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other databases marketed by Oracle Corporation===
By acquiring other technology in the database field, Oracle Corporation has taken over:
* [[TimesTen]], a memory-resident database that can cache transactions and synchronize data with a centralized Oracle database server. It functions as a [[real-time computing|real-time]] infrastructure software product intended for the management of low-[[lag|latency]], high-volume data, of events and of transactions.
* [[BerkeleyDB]], a simple, high-performance, [[Embedded Database|embedded database]]
* [[Oracle Rdb]], a legacy relational database for the [[OpenVMS]] operating system
* [[MySQL]] a relational database purchased as part of its immediate previous owner, [[Sun Microsystems]]

==Use==
The Oracle RDBMS has had a reputation among novice users as difficult to install on Linux systems.{{Citation needed|date=August 2008}} Oracle Corporation has packaged {{As of|2006|alt=recent}} versions for several popular Linux distributions in an attempt to minimize installation challenges beyond the level of technical expertise required to install a database server.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Official support===
Users who have Oracle support contracts can use Oracle's &quot;My Oracle Support&quot; web site. The &quot;My Oracle Support&quot; site was known as MetaLink until a re-branding exercise completed in October 2010. The support site provides users of Oracle Corporation products with a repository of reported problems, diagnostic scripts and solutions. It also integrates with the provision of support tools, patches and upgrades.

The ''Remote Diagnostic Agent'' or ''RDA''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oracle.com/global/tr/support/051006_ADVANCEDMETALINK_CUSTOMER.pdf |title=Advanced MetaLink |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; can operate as a command-line diagnostic tool executing a script. The data captured provides an overview of the Oracle Database environment intended for diagnostic and trouble-shooting. Within RDA, the ''HCVE'' (Health Check Validation Engine)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | first = Stephen | last = Rea | author = | authorlink = | title = Upgrading Oracle 9.2.0.6 to 10.2.0.3 on AIX 5.2 | url = http://www.uaex.edu/srea/10gR2_upgrade.txt | archiveurl = | work = | publisher = University of Arkansas | location = | doi = | date = 16 September 2008 | archivedate = | accessdate = 2009-08-11 | quote = Run the PreInstall checklist for Oracle 10.2.0 (Metalink Note 250262.1: RDA 4 - Health Check / Validation Engine Guide): The Health Check Validation Engine (HCVE) rule set for Oracle Database 10''g'' R2 (10.2.0) PreInstall (AIX) is described in: [https://metalink.oracle.com/metalink/plsql/docs/HCVE_A201DB10R2_aix.htm Oracle.com] }}&lt;/ref&gt; can verify and isolate host system environmental issues that may affect the performance of Oracle software.

===Database-related guidelines===
Oracle Corporation also endorses certain practices and conventions as enhancing the use of its database products. These include:
* [http://search.techrepublic.com.com/search/Oracle+Maximum+Availability+Architecture.html Oracle Maximum Availability Architecture (MAA)], guidelines on developing high-availability systems
* [[Optimal Flexible Architecture]] (OFA), blueprints for mapping Oracle-database objects to file-systems

===Oracle Certification Program===
{{Main|Oracle Certification Program}}

The [[Oracle Certification Program]], a [[professional certification]] program, includes the administration of Oracle Databases as one of its main certification paths. It contains three levels:

# Oracle Certified Associate (OCA)
# Oracle Certified Professional (OCP)
# Oracle Certified Master (OCM)

===User groups===
A variety of official (Oracle-sponsored) and unofficial [[Oracle User Group]]s has grown up of users and developers of Oracle databases. They include:
* [[Oracle Technology Network]]
* [[Independent Oracle Users Group]]
* Geographical/regional user groups
* Product-centric user groups
* Industry-centric user groups
* The [[Oak Table Network]]
* [[Usenet newsgroup]]s

==Market position==
===Competition===
In the market for relational databases, Oracle Database competes against commercial products such as IBM's [[IBM DB2|DB2]] UDB and [[Microsoft SQL Server]]. Oracle and IBM tend to battle for the mid-range database market on UNIX and Linux platforms, while Microsoft dominates the mid-range database market on [[Microsoft Windows]] platforms. However, since they share many of the same customers, Oracle and IBM tend to support each other's products in many middleware and application categories (for example: [[WebSphere]], [[PeopleSoft]], and [[Siebel Systems]] [[Customer relationship management|CRM]]), and IBM's hardware divisions work closely{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} with Oracle on performance-optimizing server-technologies (for example, [[Linux on zSeries]]). The two companies have a relationship perhaps{{Or|date=February 2010}} best described as &quot;[[coopetition]]&quot;. Niche commercial competitors include [[Teradata]] (in data warehousing and business intelligence), Software AG's [[ADABAS]], [[Sybase]], and IBM's [[Informix]], among many others.

In 2007, competition with [[SAP AG]] occasioned litigation from Oracle Corporation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://hirek.prim.hu/cikk/61917/ About the case] in Hungarian&lt;/ref&gt;

Increasingly, the Oracle database products compete against such [[open-source software]] relational database systems as [[PostgreSQL]], [[Firebird (database server)|Firebird]], and [[MySQL]]. Oracle acquired [[Innobase]], supplier of the [[InnoDB]] codebase to MySQL, in part to compete better against open source alternatives, and acquired [[Sun Microsystems]], owner of MySQL, in 2010. Database products licensed as open source are, by the legal terms of the [[Open Source Definition]], free to distribute and free of royalty or other licensing fees.

===Pricing===
Oracle Corporation offers term licensing for all Oracle products. It bases the list price for a term-license on a specific percentage of the perpetual license price. Prospective purchasers can obtain licenses based either on the number of processors in their target server machines or on the [[Per-seat license|number of potential seats]] (&quot;named users&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last= Kreines
|first= David C.
|title= Oracle DBA Pocket Guide
|url= http://books.google.com/books?id=4FB1pZetQ-IC
|accessdate= 2010-08-10
|series= Pocket References Series
|year= 2005
|publisher= O'Reilly Media, Inc.
|isbn= 9780596100490
|page= 16
|pages= 145
|quote= Oracle products are currently licensed using two different licensing models: ''Per Named User''. [...] ''Per Processor'' [...]
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

; Enterprise Edition: {{As of|2010|alt=As of July 2010}}, the database that costs the most per machine-processor among Oracle database editions, at $47,500 per processor.  The term &quot;per processor&quot; for Enterprise Edition is defined with respect to physical cores and a processor core multiplier (common processors = 0.5*cores).  e.g. An 8-processor, 32-core server using Intel Xeon 56XX CPUs would require 16 processor licenses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Oracle Technology Global Price List|url=http://www.oracle.com/corporate/pricing/technology-price-list.pdf|publisher=Oracle Corporation |date=2010-06-14 |accessdate=2010-07-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Processor Core Factor Table|url=http://www.oracle.com/us/corporate/contracts/processor-core-factor-table-070634.pdf|accessdate=2011-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; Standard Edition: Cheaper: it can run on up to four processors but has fewer features than Enterprise Edition—it lacks proper parallelization,&lt;ref&gt;Oracle Database Licensing Information [http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/B28359_01/license.111/b28287/editions.htm#BABDJGGI Database Editions]&lt;/ref&gt; etc.; but remains quite suitable for running medium-sized applications.
; Standard ONE: Sells even more cheaply, but remains limited to two CPUs. Standard Edition ONE sells on a per-seat basis with a five-user minimum. Oracle Corporation usually sells the licenses with an extra 22% cost for support and upgrades (access to MetaLink—Oracle Corporation's support site) which customers need to renew annually.
; [http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/database/express-edition/overview/index.html Oracle Express Edition] (Oracle XE): An addition to the Oracle database product family ([[development stage#Beta|beta]] version released in 2005, production version released in February 2006), offers a free version of the Oracle RDBMS, but one limited to 11 GB of user data and to 1 GB of memory used by the database (SGA+PGA).&lt;ref&gt;[http://download.oracle.com/docs/cd/E17781_01/install.112/e18802/toc.htm#BABIECJA Licensing Restrictions]&lt;/ref&gt; XE will use no more than one CPU and lacks an internal [[Java Virtual Machine|JVM]]. XE runs only on Windows and on Linux, not on AIX, Solaris, HP-UX and the other operating systems available for other editions. Support is via a free [https://forums.oracle.com/forums/forum.jspa?forumID=251&amp;start=0 Oracle Discussion Forum] only.

As computers running Oracle often have eight or more processors, the software price can rise into the hundreds of thousands of dollars. The [[total cost of ownership]] often exceeds this, as large Oracle installations usually require experienced and trained [[database administrator]]s to do the set-up properly. Because of the product's large installed base and available training courses, Oracle specialists in some areas have become a more abundant resource than those for more exotic databases. Oracle frequently provides special training offers for database-administrators.

On Linux, Oracle's ''certified configurations'' include Oracle's own [[Oracle Linux]] and other commercial [[Linux distributions]] ([[Red Hat Enterprise Linux]] 3, 4 and 5, [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Server|SuSE SLES]] 8, 9 and 10, [[Asianux]]) which can cost in a range from a few hundred to a few thousand USD per year (depending on processor architecture and the support package purchased).

The Oracle database system can also install and run on freely available Linux distributions such as the Red Hat-based CentOS,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wiki.oracle.com/page/Installing+Oracle+on+CentOS |title=Installation centos; official Oracle Wiki |publisher=Wiki.oracle.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; or Debian-based systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wiki.oracle.com/page/Installing+Oracle+on+Debian+%2F+Kubuntu+%2F+Ubuntu |title=Installation on Debian-based systems; official Oracle Wiki |publisher=Wiki.oracle.com |date= |accessdate=2009-12-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Comparison of relational database management systems]]
* [[Comparison of object-relational database management systems]]
* [[Database management system]]
* [[List of ERP software packages]]
* [[List of relational database management systems]]
* [[Oracle Rdb]] for [[OpenVMS]]
* [[Run Book Automation]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite document | first = Kevin | last = Loney | date = 17 December 2008 | title = Oracle Database 11g The Complete Reference | edition = 1st | publisher = [[McGraw-Hill]] | page = 1368 | isbn = 0071598758 | url = http://www.mhprofessional.com/product.php?isbn=0071598758 | accessdate = 2009-09-05 | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{wikibooks|Oracle database}}
* [http://www.oracle.com/technology/software/products/database/oracle10g/ Overview provided by Oracle Corporation]

{{Databases}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}

[[Category:Relational database management systems]]
[[Category:Proprietary database management systems]]
[[Category:Oracle software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]

[[ca:Oracle Database]]
[[cs:Oracle]]
[[de:Oracle (Datenbanksystem)]]
[[el:Oracle Database]]
[[es:Oracle]]
[[eo:Oracle]]
[[eu:Oracle]]
[[fa:پایگاه داده اوراکل]]
[[fr:Oracle Database]]
[[ga:Oracle (bunachar sonraí)]]
[[ko:오라클 데이터베이스]]
[[hi:ओरैकल डाटाबेस]]
[[id:Basis data Oracle]]
[[it:Oracle]]
[[he:אורקל (בסיס נתונים)]]
[[lv:Oracle Database]]
[[lt:Oracle]]
[[hu:Oracle Database]]
[[cdo:Oracle]]
[[nl:Oracle Database]]
[[ja:Oracle Database]]
[[no:Oracle Database]]
[[pl:Oracle (baza danych)]]
[[pt:Oracle (banco de dados)]]
[[ru:Oracle Database]]
[[simple:Oracle Database]]
[[sk:Oracle (databázový systém)]]
[[sl:Oracle]]
[[sr:Oracle]]
[[sh:Oracle]]
[[fi:Oracle (tietokanta)]]
[[ta:ஆரக்கிள் தரவுத்தளம்]]
[[te:ఒరాకిల్ డేటాబేసు]]
[[tr:Oracle Database]]
[[uk:Oracle (СКБД)]]
[[zh:Oracle数据库]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
