<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32395353" ns="0" title="List of M*A*S*H characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|refimprove=July 2011|in-universe=July 2011}}

[[File:MASH TV cast 1974.JPG|thumb|250px|right|''M*A*S*H'' cast members circa 1974: (back row) [[Larry Linville]], [[Wayne Rogers]], [[Gary Burghoff]] (front row) [[Loretta Swit]], [[Alan Alda]], [[McLean Stevenson]]]]
This is a '''list of characters''' from the ''[[M*A*S*H]]'' franchise, covering the various characters appearing in [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]]'s [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|novel]], [[Robert Altman]]'s [[MASH (film)|film adaptation]] of the novel as well as the [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]].

M*A*S*H is a popular media franchise revolving around the exploits of army surgeon Benjamin Franklin &quot;Hawkeye&quot; Pierce as well as his various cohorts as they attempt to maintain sanity during the harshness of the [[Korean War]].

==Main characters==
===Hawkeye Pierce===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Hawkeye
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]&quot;
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[Donald Sutherland]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Alan Alda]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Captain (United States)#U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, and U.S. Marine Corps|Captain]] [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]] 
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Maine#Television|Crabapple Cove]], [[Maine]], [[United States|USA]]
}}
 
'''Captain Benjamin Franklin &quot;Hawkeye&quot; Pierce, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]'''  is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] and lead protagonist in the ''[[M*A*S*H]]'' [[M*A*S*H (novels)|novels]], [[MASH (film)|film]], and [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]]. The character was played by [[Donald Sutherland]] in the film and by [[Alan Alda]] on television. He is both the main character and the only character to appear in every episode of the television series.

Born and raised in [[Maine#Television|Crabapple Cove]], [[Maine]], Hawkeye is, according to the television series, the son of Dr. Daniel Pierce. Hawkeye attended [[Androscoggin County, Maine|Androscoggin]] College. After his medical residency in Boston, Hawkeye is [[conscription in the United States#The Cold War and the Korean War|drafted]] into the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] [[Army Medical Department (United States)#Medical Corps|Medical Corps]] and called to serve at the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] (M*A*S*H) during the [[Korean War]].  Between long, intense sessions of treating critically wounded patients, he makes the best of his life in an isolated Army camp with heavy drinking, carousing, and pulling pranks on the people around him, especially the unpleasantly stiff and callous [[#Frank Burns|Major Frank Burns]] and [[#Margaret Houlihan|Major Margaret “Hot Lips” Houlihan]].

It was established that Pierce’s nickname of &quot;Hawkeye&quot; was given to him by his father. It comes from the novel ''[[The Last of the Mohicans]]'', which Pierce, in Hooker's book, claimed was &quot;the only book my old man ever read.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hornberger, Richard. ''MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors'', William Morrow, 1968, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; This claim was repeated in the television episode, &quot;A Full Rich Day&quot;.

Developed for television by [[Larry Gelbart]], the series departed in some respects radically from the film and book. The character of [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|Duke Forrest]] was dropped altogether, and Hawkeye became the center of the M*A*S*H unit’s medical activity as well as the dramatic center of the series itself. In the series he is named Chief Surgeon while in the movie and novel, [[#Trapper John|Trapper John]] is named Chief Surgeon. In the book and the film, Hawkeye had played [[American football|football]] in [[college]] (Androscoggin College, based on Hornberger’s ''alma mater'' [[Bowdoin College]]); in the series, Alda’s Hawkeye was hardly the football champ type and even seemed proud of it and reveled in it, while his colleague Trapper John ([[Wayne Rogers]]) could be seen playing football in several episodes, and later [[Mike Farrell]]'s B.J. Hunnicutt could be seen lifting himself up by his arms from a metal pole post, thus suggesting that Hawkeye's friends were more physically durable than he. Alda's Pierce seemed to resemble [[Groucho Marx]], with his quick wit and “madcap” antics, sometimes even affecting a Groucho-like [[Shtick]].

At the end of the television series, Hawkeye was one of the last to leave the dismantled camp with the announced goal of returning to his hometown of Crabapple Cove, [[Maine]], to be a local doctor who has the time to get to know his patients instead of the endless flow of casualties he faced in his term of service.

In Hooker’s two sequels to ''MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors'' (''[[M*A*S*H Goes to Maine]]'' and ''[[M*A*S*H Mania]]''), Hawkeye returns to live in Crabapple Cove, near the fictional town of [[Spruce Harbor, Maine (fictional town)|Spruce Harbor]], [[Maine]].  The fictional town is described as having 30,000 residents, a large fish wharf, a café which is frequented by the protagonists, an international airport, and the Spruce Harbor General Hospital.

===Trapper John McIntyre===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Trapper John
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;Elusive Butterfly&quot; (''[[Trapper John, M.D.]]'')
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[Elliott Gould]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Wayne Rogers]] (for ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'')&lt;br/&gt;[[Pernell Roberts]] (for ''[[Trapper John, M.D.]]'')
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Captain (United States)#U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, and U.S. Marine Corps|Captain]] [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Boston|Boston, Massachusetts, USA]]
}}

'''Captain &quot;Trapper&quot; John Francis Xavier McIntyre, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]'''  is a fictional character in [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]]'s [[M*A*S*H (novels)|''M*A*S*H'' novels]], as well as [[MASH (film)|the film]] and the two TV series (''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'' and ''[[Trapper John, M.D.]]'') that followed them.  The nickname was derived from him being caught having sex with a woman in the ladies' room on a train, when said woman announced &quot;He trapped me!&quot; (The blurb on the book's cover refers to &quot;raping&quot; a beauty queen on the Boston to Maine Express, but in the context of the story it appears she was a willing participant who was concerned to protect her reputation when caught ''[[in flagrante delicto]]''.)

McIntyre was depicted by [[Elliott Gould]] in the film, [[Wayne Rogers]] in ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', and [[Pernell Roberts]] in ''[[Trapper John, M.D.]]'', making him one of only two major characters in the [[M*A*S*H|M*A*S*H Franchise]] to be played by three actors (the other being [[#Father Mulcahy|Father Mulcahy]]). 

In the book and the film, Trapper John is a graduate of [[Dartmouth College]] (having played [[quarterback]] on the school's football team) and serves as [[Thoracic surgery|thoracic surgeon]] and eventually Chief Surgeon of the 4077th. In the film, he had a very dry, sardonic deadpan sense of humor, while in the ''M*A*S*H'' TV series he was something of a class clown. Trapper spent much of his time on the series playing &quot;[[Ethel Mertz|Ethel]]&quot; to [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye Pierce's]] &quot;[[Lucy McGillicuddy Ricardo|Lucy]]&quot;, and partaking in playing practical jokes on the two majors, [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]] and [[#Margaret Houlihan|Margaret &quot;Hot Lips&quot; Houlihan]]. Trapper did spend considerable time fraternizing with the nurses, even though he apparently did love his wife and two daughters.

[[Wayne Rogers]] was told when he accepted the role of Trapper for the TV series that Trapper and Hawkeye would be equally important, almost interchangeable (much like how Hawkeye and Trapper were presented in the ''MASH'' film). However, that changed radically when [[Alan Alda]] was cast as Hawkeye. In fact, the producers gave the TV version of Hawkeye some of the character details of the film version of Trapper (in the ''MASH'' film, Trapper John is the 4077th's top chest-cutter and Chief Surgeon; in the TV series, Hawkeye is Chief Surgeon and references are made to him being the camp's top chest-cutter). 

By the end of the third season, Rogers was fed up with the fact that Trapper was being treated as a sidekick instead of an equal. He was also greatly frustrated with the producers demanding that he sign a contract that included a &quot;morality clause&quot; which stated the producers had the right to suspend him or fire him if he took part in an acting project outside of ''M*A*S*H'' without their approval, which he refused to sign because he saw it as an absurd demand. Even though the latter half of the third season started to flesh Trapper out a bit, Rogers departed, and his character was written out of the series. After he left the series, the producers sued Rogers for violating his contract, but the case was dismissed in his favor when it was revealed that he never signed his contract. In light of the series' lengthy run, Rogers later admitted he regretted leaving ''M*A*S*H''. Trapper John's final ''M*A*S*H'' episode was &quot;[[Abyssinia, Henry]],&quot; which also included the final appearance of Col. [[#Henry Blake|Henry Blake]] ([[McLean Stevenson]]).

===B.J. Hunnicutt===
{{Infobox character
| name        = B. J. Hunnicutt
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = &quot;[[Welcome to Korea]]&quot;
| last        = &quot;[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]&quot;
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: None&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Mike Farrell]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Captain (United States)#U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, and U.S. Marine Corps|Captain]] [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Mill Valley, California|Mill Valley]], [[California]], [[United States|USA]]
}}

'''Captain B. J. Hunnicutt, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]''',&lt;ref name=book&gt;This spelling is correct. {{Cite book|last=Kalter |first=Suzy |title=The Complete Book of M*A*S*H |year=1984  |publisher=Harry N. Abrams |isbn=0-8109-1319 |chapter=Year Four 1975-76 |page=100}}&lt;/ref&gt; played by [[Mike Farrell]], is a fictional character in the TV show ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', which ran from 1972-1983 on [[CBS]].

Hunnicutt resided in [[Mill Valley, California|Mill Valley]], [[California]] before he was drafted into the [[United States Army|US Army]] as a surgeon in the [[Korean War]]. He was educated at [[Stanford University]] and was a member of the [[Tau Epsilon Phi|Tau Phi Epsilon]] fraternity. B.J. is married to Peg (née Hayden) who writes many letters to him while he is in Korea. The couple has a daughter, Erin. He is also a third-generation doctor in his family. 

Hunnicutt first appeared on the show in 1975, after [[#Trapper John McIntyre|Trapper John McIntyre]] was allowed to return home from the 4077th. His debut came in the Season Four premiere episode, &quot;[[Welcome to Korea]]&quot;. For eight seasons, Farrell appeared in every episode of the series, with only one exception.

B.J. tended to be much less aggressive in his crusades than Hawkeye, usually preferring to be a quieter voice of reason to his friend. For instance, when Hawkeye tried to print a letter protesting an unfeeling Marine commander's treatment of a Dutch immigrant soldier in the military press, the letter was cut by the commander, and Hawkeye was almost arrested for arguing with the commander about it. B.J., on the other hand, watched the drama from a distance until he calmly suggested that Hawkeye take his letter to the civilian press train in Seoul which is beyond the commander's control, thus frustrating the officer.

However, Hunnicutt's mild manner did change during his time in Korea. In one episode, he threatened a wounded soldier who attacked Hawkeye in the Swamp by threatening to &quot;break [his] neck&quot;. By the end of the series, there was a darker, slightly angrier color to B.J.'s personality, brought on by prolonged separation from his family (particularly his daughter, Erin), heavy drinking, and the overall suffering of war all around him. In earlier episodes, he also appeared to be more religious, responding to Father Mulcahy's question &quot;Do you need me, B.J.?&quot; with &quot;Not until Sunday&quot;. Later, he, as with most of the 4077th, would be too tired, hungover or uninterested to attend services.

Unlike Trapper John, who was just as much of an extroverted class clown as Hawkeye, B.J. tended to play more of a wry straight man to Hawkeye's antics. However, B.J.'s easy-going manner disguised the fact that he could be an able and devious practical joker in his own right, which was first revealed in the episode &quot;Dear Sigmund,&quot; when Dr. Sidney Friedman discovers that B.J. was behind a rash of pranks happening in the camp. In &quot;The Winchester Tapes,&quot; Charles is touched by B.J.'s concern over his sudden extreme fluctuations in weight, unaware that B.J. had secretly been substituting his Army pants for ones of different waist sizes. When an amused Hawkeye asked B.J. what was next for Charles, he replied, &quot;Starting tomorrow, he gets taller.&quot;

In ''[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]'', B.J. received orders discharging him from the Army. This both puzzled and concerned [[#Colonel Potter|Colonel Potter]]. First, he was losing a surgeon and would need to replace him. Second, he wondered out loud how Hunnicutt would be allowed orders home when several 4077th unit members had been in Korea much longer than he had. At first, Potter wanted to call [[I Corps (United States)|I Corps]] to confirm the order was legitimate, but B.J. talked him into a deal, fearing I Corps would deny sending the order. B.J. agreed to personally find a replacement surgeon if Potter would allow him to leave. 

However, just as Hunnicut was pulling away from the 4077th in a helicopter, [[#Maxwell Klinger|Klinger]] showed Potter another order rescinding B.J.'s discharge. Potter watched B.J. take off in the helicopter to the States while Klinger was speaking. After B.J. left, he turned to Klinger and asked him to repeat what he said, as he &quot;couldn't hear him&quot; over the noise of the helicopter. He then instructed Klinger to put any official correspondence on his desk and he'd look at it &quot;in an hour or so.&quot;

The &quot;error&quot; was however discovered and BJ returned by helicopter as the unit was awaiting his replacement.  A shocking scene ensued when his face revealed he was his own replacement.  With Hawkeye returned to the unit, the two together produced the memorable final scene, BJ riding his motorcycle down the mountain and Hawkeye viewing from a helicopter the message BJ left using white painted stones, &quot;GOODBYE&quot;.

===Henry Blake===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Henry Blake
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;[[Abyssinia, Henry]]&quot;&lt;br&gt; (on screen)
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[Roger Bowen]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[McLean Stevenson]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Bloomington, Illinois|Bloomington]], [[Illinois]], [[United States|USA]]
}}

'''Lieutenant Colonel Henry Braymore Blake, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]'''  is  introduced in the 1968 novel, and was also a character in the film (played by [[Roger Bowen]]), and television series (played by [[McLean Stevenson]]).

A reservist called up to active duty, Blake was the happy-go-lucky, easygoing [[commanding officer]] of the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] during the [[Korean War]]. He was beloved for his down-to-earth, laid-back manner by many under his command, notably [[U.S. Army Capt|Captains]] [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Benjamin Franklin Pierce]] and [[#Trapper John McIntyre|John Francis Xavier McIntyre]] (along with their fondness for drinking), and scorned for it by those who preferred strict military discipline, such as [[Major]]s [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]] and [[#Margaret Houlihan|Margaret &quot;Hot Lips&quot; Houlihan]]. All in all, Henry was a good person and a capable [[surgeon]], but not a very forceful or competent [[commanding officer]]. Fortunately, his [[Hierarchy|subordinate]], company clerk [[Corporal]] [[#Radar O'Reilly|Radar O'Reilly]] could almost always anticipate his wishes and turn them into efficient military orders.  He attended [[University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign|University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]] as evidenced by his sweaters and coffee mug. He was the football team trainer and once confesses to Radar that he once caused his football team to lose a big game when he accidentally taped the wrong leg of an injured Quarterback.  Whenever someone calls for him, he responds with a rather soft-spoken &quot;Yo...&quot;

When McLean Stevenson left the show at the end of the third season, his character was scripted to be discharged and sent home. In the final scene of his last episode, it was reported that Blake’s plane had been shot down over the [[Sea of Japan]] and that he had been killed. 

The script pages with the scene were handed over by the producers, Larry Gelbart and Gene Reynolds, only a few minutes before filming, so none of the cast knew about that development until a few minutes before [[Gary Burghoff]] was told to go in and report that Blake had died. Up until then, as far as anyone knew, they were going to get a message that Blake had arrived safely home. This was deliberately planned so that the emotions shown by the actors during that scene would be as real as possible, and it worked well, so much so that during the second take of the scene one of the extras accidentally dropped a surgical instrument on the floor which made a loud clank.&lt;ref&gt;Gelbart, Larry. Laughing Matters: On Writing M*A*S*H, Tootsie, Oh, God!, and a Few Other Funny Things. 1998. ISBN 067942945X&lt;/ref&gt;

After the news of Colonel Blake’s death shocked the nation, the very next night on ''[[The Carol Burnett Show]]'', the opening shot was of McLean Stevenson in a smoking raft, waving his arms, hollering, &quot;I’m OK! I’m OK!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aftermash.blogspot.com/2010/01/carol-burnett-show-32275.html aftermash.blogspot.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

When Stevenson left ''M*A*S*H'' and the character of Henry Blake was written out of the story, he was replaced by [[Harry Morgan]] as [[#Sherman T. Potter|Colonel Sherman T. Potter]] in the position of commanding officer of the 4077th MASH. By contrast, Potter was a career soldier who was a consummate professional in both the command and medical fields, although easygoing, fun-loving and compassionate enough to earn the deep respect of his staff.

===Sherman T. Potter===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Sherman T. Potter 
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = &quot;[[Welcome to Korea]]&quot; (listed on opening credits) - The first episode in which he appeared as was &quot;[[Change of Command]]&quot; 
| last        = &quot;Saturday's Heroes&quot; (''[[AfterMASH]]'')
| portrayer   = [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Harry Morgan]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]] [[File:US-O6 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Hannibal, Missouri|Hannibal]], [[Missouri]], [[United States|USA]]
}}
 
'''Colonel Sherman Tecumseh Potter, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] from the ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'' and ''[[AfterMASH]]'' [[television]] series. He was portrayed by [[Harry Morgan]].

At the end of the show's third season, [[McLean Stevenson]] left the series, and his character, [[#Henry Blake|Lieutenant Colonel Henry Blake]], died on his way home. [[#Frank Burns|Major Frank Burns]] assumed command of the unit at the end of that season, although it was to be short-lived (one full episode plus parts of two others). The producers wanted a different type of commanding officer for the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] (MASH). They decided on a &quot;[[Regular Army (United States)|Regular Army]]&quot; commander, a man who had made a career out of the service, and was close to [[retirement]]. The producers chose [[Harry Morgan]] to fill the role, after the strong performance he gave as a visiting General earlier in the first episode of the third season, &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 3)|The General Flipped at Dawn]]&quot; .

Potter's first appearance on the series came in the second episode of Season Four, &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 4)|Change of Command]]&quot; (after a brief pre-view appearance, near the end of the previous episode &quot;[[Welcome to Korea]]&quot;). After joining the cast in 1975, Morgan appeared in every episode with only one exception, whose character also became the core of the series.

Col. Potter was well-liked by his subordinates, especially [[#Radar O'Reilly|Radar]], who saw Potter as a sort of mentor and father figure. He even garnered more military respect from Majors [[#Frank Burns|Burns]] and [[#Margaret Houlihan|Houlihan]] than did his [[#Henry Blake|predecessor]]. Potter was a very relaxed and laid-back commander, understanding the need for fun and games to boost morale during wartime, but unlike Col. Blake, he was not afraid to put his foot down when the camp's antics got out of hand.

With the armistice declared in Korea, the 4077th was disbanded, everyone in the unit parted ways, and they went on with their respective lives. Col. Potter retired from the military, and returned to Missouri. In the final episode, Col. Potter announced his plans to go home to Mildred, and become a semi-retired country doctor. Leaving the 4077th on his horse Sophie (whom at the request of Father Mulcahy he dropped off at the local orphanage to be used productively), he was given the second military [[salute]] by Hawkeye Pierce and B.J. Hunnicutt, as a sign of just how much respect the two doctors had for him. 

However, [[Harry Morgan]], [[William Christopher]], and [[Jamie Farr]] &amp;mdash; the three who voted to continue the series at the end of the 11th season &amp;mdash; were invited to star in a [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] series at CBS, called ''[[AfterMASH]]''. Potter became the chief of staff &amp; chief of surgery of the fictional [[John J. Pershing|General Pershing]] [[Veterans Health Administration|VA Hospital]] (a/k/a &quot;General General&quot;) in the equally fictional River Bend, Missouri. Father Mulcahy, after losing his hearing from an explosion in the ''M*A*S*H'' series finale, recovered most of his hearing through an experimental operation at a Saint Louis VA hospital at Potter's recommendation and became General General's Catholic chaplain. Max and Soon-Lee Klinger, after experiencing discrimination in [[Toledo, Ohio|Toledo]], moved to the area so that Max could take up where he left off - as Potter's assistant.

===Frank Burns===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Frank Burns
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;Margaret's Marriage&quot;
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[Robert Duvall]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Larry Linville]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| spouse      = Louise Burns
| title       = [[Major (United States)|Major]] [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|15px]] ([[Captain (United States)#U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, and U.S. Marine Corps|Captain]] [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]] in [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]]'s original novel, and [[Lieutenant Colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|15px]] after leaving Korea in the series)
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Fort Wayne, Indiana|Fort Wayne]], [[Indiana]], USA
}}

'''Major (later Lieutenant Colonel) Franklin Delano Marion &quot;Frank&quot; Burns, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]]'''  (also known as &quot;Ferret Face&quot;) is a fictional character in the ''[[M*A*S*H]]'' [[MASH (film)|film]] and [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]]. Burns first appeared in the original [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|''M*A*S*H'' novel]] by [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]], where he had the rank of captain. The character was then portrayed in the film by [[Robert Duvall]] (as a major), and in the subsequent television series by [[Larry Linville]] as first a major who is then promoted to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel after his departure from the series.

In the original novel, Captain Burns is described as a well-off doctor who had attended medical school but had no true formal training as a surgeon other than a long apprenticeship with his father in [[Indiana]]. He maintains a dismissive attitude toward those colleagues (such as the Swampmen) who went through the rigors and demands of a residency for their training. However, his belief in his own superiority masks serious shortcomings in his surgical abilities, which he invariably dismisses as the failures of others involved in the patients' care. When one of Burns' patients dies, &quot;it's either (1) God's will or (2) somebody else's fault&quot; (Hooker, p.&amp;nbsp;43). This practice comes to a head when he unjustly accuses rookie orderly Private Boone of killing a patient of his. Young Boone is emotionally crushed and an infuriated Duke, who witnesses the scene, walks with Frank to the privacy of the sluice where he delivers a nose-breaking punch and knee to the stomach. A short time later, Trapper assaults Frank after Frank's arrogance and incompetence almost costs a soldier his life. The concern of the surgeons on Frank's team regarding Frank's incompetence causes Blake to nominate Trapper as Chief Surgeon.

Later, after Burns and Houlihan commence a sexual affair, the Swampmen latch onto it, giving Houlihan the nickname of &quot;Hot Lips&quot;. One night in a room just off the OR, Hawkeye makes some ribald comments about the relationship. Burns, having reached the limit of his patience, hurls a coffeemaker at Hawkeye, just as Blake walks in. The next day, Burns is sent away for psychiatric evaluation.
 
In the film and in the subsequent TV series, Frank Burns' rank has been increased to that of Major, presumably for dramatic and story conflict and to replace the book's Major Hobson who was the resident religious zealot in the novel, but possibly also to facilitate the pun &quot;Major Burns&quot;, in addition to being the 4077's [[executive officer]]. He is portrayed as a very [[Religion|religious]] man who prays for all the souls to be saved, but is still not much of a doctor. He also is a firm believer in military discipline who dislikes the undisciplined manner of both [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye Pierce]] and [[#Trapper John McIntyre|Trapper John McIntyre]].  He also has a tendency to blame others for his mistakes; for example, when he orders a medical device for a man already dead, he blames an [[orderly]] he asked to get the device, causing the man to break down crying.  This leads to McIntyre punching him.  In the television series Burns admitted that it took him twice the normal amount of time to graduate medical school, having flunked out of two, and that he only passed his first year by buying the answers to a final exam.  He also stated that the local undertaker used to send him gifts and thank-you cards at Christmas.

===Margaret Houlihan===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Margaret Houlihan
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]&quot;
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[Sally Kellerman]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Loretta Swit]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Female]]
| title       = [[Major (United States)|Major]] [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Fort Ord]], [[California]], [[United States|USA]]
}}
'''Major Margaret J. &quot;Hot Lips&quot; Houlihan''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] first created in the book ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]'' by [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]]. Actress [[Sally Kellerman]] portrayed the character in the [[Robert Altman]] [[MASH (film)|film adaptation]] (where she is sometimes referred to as '''O'Houlihan'''). Houlihan was later portrayed by [[Loretta Swit]] in the long-running television series. 

The character of &quot;Hotlips Houlihan&quot; was inspired by real-life [[Korean War]] MASH head nurse '''Hotlips Hammerly''', also a very attractive blonde, of the same disposition, and also from [[El Paso, Texas|El Paso]], [[Texas]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.paramountcomedy.com/shows/trivia.aspx?id=40&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the run of the show, Margaret mellowed from a completely &quot;by-the-book&quot; head nurse (who was also not above using her romantic contacts with superior officers in attempts to get her way, nor going against regulations for her personal benefit), to a more relaxed member of the cast who tempered her authority with humanity. Key episodes in this development were &quot;[[The Nurses (M*A*S*H episode)|The Nurses]]&quot;, in which Margaret gave an emotional tirade to her nurses about how their disdain of her hurt her and thus stuns them, and &quot;[[Comrades in Arms (Part 1) (M*A*S*H episode)|Comrades In Arms]]&quot;, where Hawkeye and Margaret make peace once and for all while lost in the wilderness. When the show ended, Margaret was on her way back to the US to take up a position in an Army hospital. Not coincidentally, the change for her character came when [[Linda Bloodworth-Thomason]] joined the show's writing team. The last time she took a hardline stance with one of her nurses was in Episode 8.7, &quot;Nurse Doctor&quot;, where she tells nurse Gail Harris, &quot;If you think I was tough on you before you're in for 7 weeks of 'You ain't seen nothing yet'. If you even think of stepping out of line your butt will be tattooed with my boots.&quot; Unlike some other times, this chewing out was deserved and immediately after it Margaret offered to help Gail with her medical studies.

There have also been criticisms that the then contemporary [[second-wave feminism|second-wave feminist]] views she held in latter seasons were a glaring [[anachronism]] in the show's early 1950s setting.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jumptheshark.tv/thread.jspa?threadID=1272&amp;start=180 M*A*S*H - General Comments in M in in Jump The Shark]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://classicsitcoms.com/shows/mash7.html The CLASSIC SITCOMS Guide: M*A*S*H]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the series of [[M*A*S*H (novels)|novels]] co-written with (or ghosted by) William E. Butterworth, Houlihan reappears as the twice-widowed Margaret Houlihan Wachauf Wilson, both husbands having expired untimely on the nuptial couch through over-strain caused by excessive indulgence in her still-outstanding physical charms. Her career has taken a new direction as the Reverend head of the &quot;God Is Love In All Forms Christian Church, Incorporated&quot;, a cult or sect with the unusual distinction that its entire congregation consists of homosexual men. Most of these are extremely flamboyant and the Reverend Mother herself is conspicuously glitzy and glittery. However, it appears that Margaret genuinely cares for her flock and is not merely shaking them down in pursuit of material gain.

The name &quot;Hot Lips&quot; originates from an infamous scene in [[MASH (film)|M*A*S*H, the movie]], in which Margaret Houlihan is played by [[Sally Kellerman]]. During sex with Frank Burns, Margaret is initially unaware that the public address microphone has been planted beneath their cot, broadcasting graphic details of their rendezvous throughout the camp on its public address system. Other members of the camp overhear her saying to Frank &quot;kiss my hot lips.&quot;

===Charles Winchester===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Charles
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 6)|Fade Out, Fade In]]&quot;
| last        = &quot;[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]&quot;
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: None&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[David Ogden Stiers]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Major (United States)|Major]] [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], [[United States|USA]]
}}
'''Major Charles Emerson Winchester III, [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]],''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]], a principal on the [[television series]], ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', played by [[David Ogden Stiers]].  He was introduced in the first episode of the show's sixth season, &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 6)|Fade Out, Fade In]]&quot;.

Charles Emerson Winchester III was born in [[Boston]], [[Massachusetts]], a third generation of a very wealthy family of [[Boston Brahmin]]s who are anti-[[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] Republicans. After finishing his secondary studies at [[Choate Rosemary Hall|Choate]], he graduated ''[[Latin honors|summa cum laude]]'' class of '43 from [[Harvard College]] (where he lettered in [[Rowing (sport)|Crew]] and [[Polo]]), completed his MD at [[Harvard Medical School]] in Cambridge in 1943,  and worked at [[Massachusetts General Hospital]]. Before he was [[conscription|drafted]] to join the [[United States Army|US Army]] at the start of the [[Korean War]], he was on track to become Chief of [[Thoracic surgery]].  Although he shows apparent interest in [[Cardiac surgery|heart surgery]], he claims to be an expert in [[pediatrics]].

While [[#Frank Burns|Major Frank Burns]] was [[Desertion|AWOL]] following a trip to [[Seoul]] after the marriage of [[#Margaret Houlihan|Major Margaret Houlihan]] to [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[#Donald Penobscot|Donald Penobscot]], the staff at the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] (MASH) desperately needed a replacement surgeon to fill in. [[#Sherman T. Potter|Colonel Sherman T. Potter]] placed a call to Tokyo General Hospital in search of a surgeon. Winchester's commanding officer, Colonel Horace Baldwin, owed Winchester $672.17 [[cribbage]] debts. Irritated at his losses, Baldwin volunteered Winchester for duty at the 4077th, reassuring him the assignment would be for only 48 hours.

Once Winchester arrived, he found the conditions appalling, especially in comparison to the comfortable life he enjoyed at Tokyo General. His arrogance made a poor first impression, but Winchester proved his surgical expertise by performing a delicate heart operation the other doctors were unfamiliar with on a ventricular [[aneurysm]]. 

Though nowhere near as flirtatious and lustful as [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye]], Winchester, being unmarried, was not immune to desire for female companionship. (This would contrast with Stiers in real life, who in May 2009 [[Coming out|came out]] as homosexual.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/Movies/story?id=7518323|title =’M*A*S*H’ Star David Ogden Stiers Reveals He’s Gay – ABC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/30607382/|title =Former ’M*A*S*H’ star says he is gay – Access Hollywood – msnbc.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gossip-boy.com/DOS.html Gossip Boy Exclusive! Television Icon David Ogden Stiers Officially Comes Out] by Wayne Fuller; ''Gossip Boy'', March 11, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;) His surgical knowledge and gentlemanly demeanor initially attracted [[#Margaret Houlihan|Margaret Houlihan]], and several overtures towards a dating relationship were mutually attempted (the creators of the show originally intended for Charles and Margaret to have a relationship like the latter did with Frank). However, the chemistry between the two was not there, and Charles and Margaret maintained a platonic relationship for the remainder of the series.

===Radar O'Reilly===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Radar
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = ''[[W*A*L*T*E*R]]''
| portrayer   = [[Gary Burghoff]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Corporal#United States Army|Corporal]] [[File:US Army E-4.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Ottumwa, Iowa|Ottumwa]], [[Iowa]], [[United States|USA]]
}}

'''Corporal “Radar” O’Reilly''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] in the [[M*A*S*H (novels)|M*A*S*H novels]], [[MASH (film)|film]] and [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]], as well as two episodes of the series ''[[AfterMASH]]'', and the television pilot ''[[W*A*L*T*E*R]]''. The character was portrayed by [[Gary Burghoff]] in both the [[film]] and on [[television]] — the only actor from the film to reprise his role on television, aside from [[G. Wood]] as General Hammond.

While Radar's full name is never given in the original novel or film, on the TV series it is '''Walter Eugene O'Reilly'''. The later novels by [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]] and [[W. E. B. Griffin|William Butterworth]] give his full name as '''J. Robespierre O'Reilly'''.

The novel establishes that Radar was from [[Ottumwa, Iowa]] and literally dreamed of joining the [[United States Army|Army]] right after high school. (A first season TV episode (1/18), however, shows him receiving a [[high school diploma]] through a [[Distance education|correspondence course]].) He seemed to have [[Extrasensory perception|extra-sensory perception]], appearing at his commander's side before being called and finishing his sentences. He also had exceptionally good hearing, able to hear incoming [[helicopter]]s before anyone else. It was these abilities that earned him the nickname &quot;Radar.&quot; 

On television, Radar's character started off worldly and sneaky, a clerk who carried with him at all times a pocketful of passes for any potential scam that might arise. At one point, he tried to mail home a [[Jeep]], [[Salami slicing|piece by piece]]. (Hawkeye commented that once Radar's mailman found out, he'd have a retroactive [[hernia]].) He was known for his tremendous appetite for heaping portions of food. He was also not averse to drinking Col. Blake's brandy and smoking his cigars when the colonel was off-duty, and he occasionally drank the [[moonshine]] liquor that Hawkeye and McIntyre made in their [[Pot still|still]].

As the series progresses, this worldly version of Radar was apparently not wholly to the writers' liking, and Radar evolved into a naïve farm boy. Cigars and strong liquor made him ill or dizzy (despite him frequently drinking and smoking cigars previously), and despite numerous references to him losing his [[virginity]] in earlier episodes, he appeared to have regained it later in the series. His favorite beverage was [[Nehi]] Brand Grape Soda. In &quot;[[The Novocaine Mutiny]],&quot; it is revealed that Radar won $300 from Sgt. Zale in a poker game. A minor change was that he lost the ability to speak fluent Korean which should have been a blow to the camp as he was the only person who spoke it, even if in later episodes it was only a few halting sentences.

The first cast member of ''M*A*S*H'' to be hired, Gary Burghoff was the fourth and last to leave, following the departures of [[McLean Stevenson]] and [[Wayne Rogers]] in 1975, and [[Larry Linville]] in 1977.

Burghoff had appeared in every episode of the show's first three seasons. After season three, doing the series had become a strain on the actor's family life, and he had his contract changed to limit his appearances to 13 episodes per season out of the usual 24 (during these times, the character of Radar was usually on R&amp;R). By season 7, Burghoff started experiencing [[Burnout (psychology)|burnout]] and decided it was time to move on, despite co-star [[Mike Farrell]] trying to persuade him to stay on the grounds that his career would not recover. Because of that, the producers originally planned to end season 7 with Radar leaving, but CBS did not want to do that. Instead they persuaded Burghoff to come back during season 8 to do a special two-part farewell episode titled &quot;[[Good-Bye Radar]]&quot;.

===Father Mulcahy===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Father Mulcahy
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = ''[[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors]]''
| last        = &quot;Saturday's Heroes&quot; (''[[AfterMASH]]'')
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: [[René Auberjonois (actor)|René Auberjonois]]&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[William Christopher]] ([[George Morgan (actor)|George Morgan]] for the [[television pilot|pilot]])
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[First Lieutenant]] [[File:US-OF1A.svg|6px]], [[Captain (United States)#U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force, and U.S. Marine Corps|Captain]] [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]]
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]], [[United States|USA]]
}}
 
'''1st Lieutenant (later Captain) Francis John Patrick Mulcahy''' [[Society of Jesus|S.J.]], commonly called '''Father Mulcahy''', is a fictional principal character from the [[film]] ''[[MASH (film)|M*A*S*H]]'', played by [[René Auberjonois (actor)|René Auberjonois]], and the [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]], played by [[William Christopher]]. He was played by [[George Morgan (actor)|George Morgan]] in the pilot episode of the [[M*A*S*H (TV series)|television series]], but the producers decided that a quirkier individual was needed for the [[Character (arts)|role]], and Christopher was cast in his place.

During the course of the television series, Father Mulcahy's name was changed from John Patrick Francis Mulcahy to Francis John Patrick Mulcahy (as he revealed in episode 7 of Season 8 when asked by a nurse he was counseling). Either form of the name is an attempt to reconcile his identification as &quot;Father John P. Mulcahy&quot; in the pilot episode with the name &quot;Francis Mulcahy&quot; established later on.
 
In the original film (as well as the [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|Richard Hooker novel]] on which it is based), Mulcahy is familiarly known by the nickname &quot;'''Dago Red'''&quot; (a type of cheap Italian wine). In an O.R. scene in the ''M*A*S*H'' pilot episode, Trapper can be heard addressing Mulcahy as &quot;Red,&quot; and Hawkeye calls Mulcahy &quot;Red&quot; in &quot;[[Dear Dad]]&quot;; however, the nickname was quickly phased out of the series.

The [[Character (arts)|character]] Father John &quot;Johnny&quot; Patrick 'Dago Red' Mulcahy in the film is a [[United States Army|US Army]] [[chaplain]] assigned to the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] during the [[Korean War]]. While most of the staff is not religious, they treat Mulcahy with some respect. It is Mulcahy who alerts the doctors that the camp dentist, Painless, is severely depressed. Afterwards, Mulcahy reluctantly helps the doctors to stage the famous &quot;Last Supper&quot; faux suicide, to convince Painless that he should continue with life.

Throughout the film, Mulcahy seems bewildered by the doctors' amoral pranks and womanizing behavior.  When [[#Radar O'Reilly|Radar]] places a hidden microphone inside Hotlips' tent as she and [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]] make love, members of the camp listen in, and Mulcahy at first mistakes their conversation (and noises) for an episode of ''[[The Bickersons]]''—then leaves abruptly when he realizes otherwise.

===Maxwell Klinger===
{{Infobox character
| name        = Klinger
| series      = [[M*A*S*H]]
| image       =  
| caption     =  
| first       = &quot;[[Chief Surgeon Who?]]&quot;
| last        = &quot;Saturday's Heroes&quot; (''[[AfterMASH]]'')
| portrayer   = [[MASH (film)|Film]]: None&lt;br /&gt;[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|Television]]: [[Jamie Farr]]
| nickname    = 
| gender      = [[Male]]
| title       = [[Corporal#United States Army|Corporal]] [[File:US Army E-4.svg|15px]] (formerly)&lt;br/&gt;[[Sergeant#United States|Sergeant]] [[File:US Army E-5.svg|15px]] (later)
| lbl21       = Home city
| data21      = [[Toledo, Ohio|Toledo]], [[Ohio]], [[United States|USA]]
}}

'''Corporal (later Sergeant) Maxwell Q. Klinger''' is a [[Character (arts)|fictional character]] from the ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'' [[television program|television series]] played by [[United States|American]] [[actor]] [[Jamie Farr]].  A [[Lebanese American]] hailing from [[Toledo, Ohio]] (like Farr himself), Klinger serves as an orderly/corpsman (and later company clerk) assigned to the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital]] in [usually] [[Uijeongbu]] during the [[Korean War]]. The character's original defining characteristic is his attempts to gain a [[Section 8 (military)|Section 8]] psychiatric discharge from the army, by habitually wearing women's clothing and engaging in other &quot;crazy&quot; stunts, but never at the expense of his duties. He later gives up his discharge attempts and is promoted from the rank of [[corporal]] to [[sergeant]] during the course of the TV series.

Klinger first appeared in the episode &quot;[[Chief Surgeon Who?]]&quot;.  In that episode's original script, Corporal Klinger was written as an effeminate gay man.  However, the writers subsequently decided that it would be more interesting to have Klinger be heterosexual, but wear dresses in an attempt to gain a [[Section 8 (military)|Section 8]] discharge.&lt;ref name=&quot;watch29&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=CMPx-jksa6IC|title=Watching M*A*S*H, Watching America |last=Wittebols|first=James H. |page=29|accessdate=16 May 2009 | isbn=9780786417018 | year=2003 | publisher=McFarland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Series writer [[Larry Gelbart]] stated during the ''M*A*S*H 30th Anniversary Reunion'' special that Klinger's antics were inspired by stories of [[Lenny Bruce]] attempting to dodge his own military service by dressing himself as a [[WAVES]] member.

Later in the program's development, the writers of ''M*A*S*H'' gave Klinger characteristics derived from actor Jamie Farr, including the character's background as a native of [[Toledo, Ohio]].

Klinger was the first main character introduced on ''M*A*S*H'' not to have appeared in either [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]]'s original [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|''M*A*S*H'' novel]] or the subsequent [[MASH (film)|film]].
{{clear}}

==Recurring characters==
===Nurse Kellye===
'''1st Lt. Kealani Kellye''' [[File:US-OF1A.svg|6px]] was portrayed by [[Kellye Nakahara]].  She appeared in 86 episodes of the series, more episodes than some main characters, such as [[#Henry Blake|Henry Blake]] and [[#Trapper John|Trapper John]]. The character grew steadily from a background (often non-speaking) character in the first season, culminating in the season 11 episode &quot;Hey, Look Me Over&quot; which was centered around the character. In her first appearances, her name changed several times before it finally settled on &quot;Nurse Kellye&quot;; for example, she was referred to as &quot;Nurse Able&quot; in her first appearance in &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 3)|A Full Rich Day]]&quot;.  The first name &quot;Kealani&quot; was never spoken on screen, but according to interviews with the actress, that was the first name used on set when referring to the character.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mash4077.co.uk/kelly3.html ]{{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; As late as season 10, Major Winchester referred to Kellye as &quot;Lt. Nakahara&quot; in &quot;The Birthday Girls.&quot;  

She described herself as &quot;part Chinese, part Hawaiian&quot; in &quot;Life Line&quot; and speaks Japanese fluently, as revealed in &quot;Communication Breakdown&quot;. She had great pride in her [[Asian American]] heritage and frequently took umbrage at racial slurs leveled by [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]] and cultural slights exhibited by [[#Charles Winchester|Major Winchester]]. Her family lives in Honolulu according to her statements in the final episode.

===Igor Straminsky===
'''Private Igor Straminsky''' [[File:US Army E-2.svg|15px]]&lt;!---When was the name 'Straminsky' ever spoken in the series? --&gt; was generally portrayed by actor [[Jeff Maxwell]], although [[Peter Riegert]] played him in two sixth season episodes. He debuted in the second season and appeared on and off up until the series finale. He has appeared in more episodes than any non-main character except for Nurse Kellye.

Igor's role was often to serve food out in the mess and therefore also to serve as the foil for a lot of the complaints about the state of the food.

In &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 10)|Promotion Commotion]]&quot;, Igor relentlessly tries to impress Hawkeye and B.J., so he can be promoted to Corporal. He once mentioned to Father Mulcahy that he sets aside three dollars from each salary payment for the local orphanage.

In &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 4)|The Price of Tomato Juice]],&quot; Igor identifies himself as &quot;Maxwell,&quot; (a goof on the part of actor Jeff Maxwell) and Major Frank Burns also refers to him as &quot;Maxwell&quot; in the following line of dialogue.

===Luther Rizzo===
'''Staff Sergeant Luther Rizzo''' [[File:US Army E-6.svg|15px]] was played by [[G. W. Bailey]]. In the show, he was head of the [[fleet vehicle|motor pool]]. While originally written to be from [[New York City]], when the producers heard Bailey in his first [[dailies]] his character was moved to Louisiana.&lt;ref&gt;Memories of M*A*S*H (20th Anniversary) (CBS, 1991), interview with G.W. Bailey&lt;/ref&gt; He was known for his slow, deep, Louisiana drawl and his slightly disheveled look. Though the motor pool seemed to function well, it did so despite Rizzo's casual work style and frequent naps. His philosophy on success in the army was that it was possible to never do work, so long as your superiors don't see you enjoy yourself: &quot;Where else [but the Army] can you be a bum and get paid for it?&quot;

In the Season 10 episode &quot;Promotion Commotion&quot;, Rizzo was one of three 4077th enlisted that appeared before a promotion board consisting of [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye]], [[#B. J. Hunnicutt|B.J.]], and [[#Charles Winchester|Winchester]].  He was not promoted, but made it clear that he was American &quot;with an American wife and American children.&quot;

In the series finale, Rizzo claimed that he would be going home to work on a new moneymaking venture: breeding [[frog]]s to sell to [[French cuisine|French]] [[restaurant]]s. This is a minor error; Rizzo had re-enlisted in the Army service in a previous episode.

===Sidney Freedman===
'''Major Sidney Theodore Freedman''' [[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|15px]], played by [[Allan Arbus]], is a [[psychiatrist]] frequently summoned in cases of [[mental health]] problems; the name is a play on that of psychoanalyst [[Sigmund Freud]].  When Radar was written out of the series, Sidney Freedman was going to join the cast of ''M*A*S*H''. However, Allan Arbus didn't want to commit to be anything other than a guest star, so the character remained an occasionally recurring character.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} In the ''M*A*S*H 30th Anniversary Special'' that aired on [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] in 2002, Arbus was the only non-regular cast member to be featured on the special.

Freedman's first appearance was in the episode &quot;[[Radar's Report]]&quot;. He visited the camp to do a psychiatric evaluation of [[#Maxwell Klinger|Klinger]], who was aiming for a [[military discharge|discharge]] (as always). After Freedman had finished the report, he quietly took Klinger in for an interview and told him that while he is obviously not mentally ill, Freedman was willing to declare him a [[transvestism|transvestite]] and a [[Homosexuality|homosexual]]. This label would not leave him, though, as he put it: &quot;From now on, you go through life on high heels.&quot; Klinger vociferously denied, &quot;I ain't any of those things! I'm just crazy!&quot; Klinger's discharge was uniformly dropped, and Freedman left the camp.  In this first appearance in the series, Dr. Freedman's first name was Milton, not Sidney.  

Freedman appears in 12 ''M*A*S*H'' episodes: &quot;Radar's Report&quot; (as Milton Freedman), &quot;Deal Me Out&quot;, &quot;O.R.&quot;, &quot;Quo Vadis, Captain Chandler?&quot;, &quot;Dear Sigmund&quot;, &quot;Hawk's Nightmare&quot;, &quot;War of Nerves&quot;, &quot;The Billfold Syndrome&quot;, &quot;Goodbye, Cruel World&quot;, &quot;Bless You, Hawkeye&quot;, &quot;Pressure Points&quot;, and the series finale, &quot;[[Goodbye, Farewell and Amen]]&quot;. In two additional ''M*A*S*H'' episodes (&quot;Mad Dogs and Servicemen,&quot; &quot;Heal Thyself&quot; and &quot;A Holy Mess&quot;) and one episode of ''[[AfterMASH]]'' (&quot;Madness to His Method&quot;), he is mentioned but does not appear onscreen.

In the episode &quot;O.R.&quot;, Freedman told those gathered in the operating room, &quot;Ladies and gentlemen, take my advice: Pull down your pants and slide on the ice.&quot; He repeated that advice in the series finale, following his treatment of Hawkeye, who had finally cracked under the strain of the war. Freedman led Hawkeye to stop suppressing the memory of seeing a Korean mother smothering her crying baby in an effort to keep it silent (so that a nearby Chinese patrol would not find and kill or capture their group). (In Hawkeye's suppression, he had 'remembered' that the mother had killed a 'chicken', until Freedman brought the true memory into the light.) He convinced a reluctant Hawkeye that the best thing for him now was to return to duty for the last days of the war.

After leaving Korea and the Army, Dr. Freedman accepts a post at the [[University of Chicago]].  The ''[[AfterMASH]]'' episode &quot;Madness To His Method&quot; has as its frame Colonel Potter writing a letter in Missouri about the episode's situation to an unseen Freedman.

===Sam Flagg===
'''Lieutenant Colonel [[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|15px]] (later Colonel [[File:US-O6 insignia.svg|15px]]) Sam[uel] Flagg''' is played by actor [[Edward Winter (actor)|Edward Winter]]. Col. Flagg is an American intelligence agent. His behavior is paranoid and irrational and he appears to the staff of the 4077th Mobile Army Surgical Hospital to be mentally unstable; the fact that he deliberately seriously injures himself to advance an investigation seems proof of that. At one point, he tries to get into [[Counterintelligence Corps (United States Army)|Counter Intelligence Corps]] headquarters by crashing his jeep into a brick wall and setting himself on fire. (When told this, Hawkeye responds, &quot;Is this guy available for kids' parties?&quot;) Another time, to get into the 4077th, he orders a helicopter pilot to crash and then twice breaks his own arm.&lt;ref&gt;Episode 48/Season 2&lt;/ref&gt; He alternately claims to be affiliated with the [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]], the [[Counterintelligence Corps (United States Army)|CIC]], or the [[United States Army Criminal Investigation Command|CID]], and occasionally all at once, depending on to whom he is speaking. Example: &quot;I'm with the CIA, but I tell people I'm with the CIC, so they think I'm with the CID.&quot; Majors [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]] and [[#Margaret Houlihan|Margaret Houlihan]], strong [[anti-communism|anti-Communist]]s, follow his assignments with great interest, but are unable to &quot;buddy up&quot; to him as they hope.  As Flagg says, &quot;Nobody can get the truth out of me because even I don't know what it is. I keep myself in a constant state of utter confusion.&quot; At some point, however, Major Houlihan loses her respect for Flagg, as revealed in an episode in which she claims that he gives Americans a bad name.

His paranoia is so fanatical that Flagg even accuses Major Burns twice of being a communist agent on the grounds that Burns has seen a performance of the [[Bolshoi Theatre|Bolshoi Ballet]] in [[Tokyo]] and is reading ''[[Reader's Digest]]'', which Flagg notes would be &quot;Red's Digest&quot; if the 3rd, 5th, and 6th letters were eliminated. A [[running gag]] is Burns almost being beaten up by Flagg&amp;mdash;when Burns calls Flagg crazy, Flagg threatens to rip Burns' heart out. Another time, Burns tries to buddy up to Flagg by slapping him on the shoulder. Flagg icily tells Burns that his father touched him like that once: &quot;To this day, that man has to wear orthopedic shirts.&quot;

Edward Winter's first appearance on ''M*A*S*H'' is in the second season episode &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 2)|Deal Me Out]]&quot;, in which he plays a CID captain named Halloran, and is listed in the credits as such.  In the fourth season episode &quot;Quo Vadis, Captain Chandler?&quot;&amp;mdash;the next episode in which both Flagg and Sidney Freedman appear&amp;mdash;Flagg greets Sidney with the statement &quot;We played poker once,&quot; to which Sidney replies, &quot;Oh sure; with Intelligence, right?&quot;

Colonel Flagg appears in seven ''M*A*S*H'' episodes: &quot;Deal Me Out&quot; (8 December 1973) (as Capt. Halloran), &quot;[[A Smattering of Intelligence]]&quot; (2 March 1974), &quot;Officer of the Day&quot; (24 September 1974), &quot;White Gold&quot; (11 March 1975), &quot;Quo Vadis, Captain Chandler?&quot; (7 November 1975), &quot;The Abduction of Margaret Houlihan&quot; (26 October 1976), and &quot;Rally 'Round the Flagg, Boys&quot; (14 February 1979).

Flagg resurfaces a few years after the war, in a [[Hannibal, Missouri]] courtroom (on the short-lived spinoff ''[[AfterMASH]]''), in which he uses the name Flagg and asserts employment with an intelligence organisation &quot;which has initials and its members are allowed to carry fire arms in their shoes.&quot;

[[Ken Levine (TV personality)|Ken Levine]], a writer for both ''M*A*S*H'' and ''AfterMASH'', wrote in 2011, &quot;We loved writing Col. Flagg (the hilarious Ed Winter) but always felt there was a danger in going to that well too often. So we tried to use him sparingly (once a season or every other season). He was incredibly funny but that character was very broad and we didn’t want him to wear out his welcome.&quot;[http://kenlevine.blogspot.com/2011/09/friday-questions.html]

===Spearchucker Jones===
'''Captain Oliver Harmon &quot;Spearchucker&quot; Jones''' [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]]  or '''Captain Oliver Wendell &quot;Spearchucker&quot; Jones''' was portrayed by [[Fred Williamson]] in the movie and [[Timothy Brown (actor)|Timothy Brown]] in the television series. Spearchucker was shown during several episodes during the first season of the series. His full name was never mentioned in the series. The character's middle name was Harmon in the film and Wendell in the novels.  He is a [[Board certification|board-certified]] [[Neurosurgery|neurosurgeon]] in the film, and in the episode in which Hawkeye becomes chief surgeon, Spearchucker's specialty is indicated as he struggles to do surgery and when he asks Hawkeye for help he says &quot;anything outside of the brain and I'm dead&quot;.

Dr. Jones was one of the original Swampmen with [[#Trapper John McIntyre|Trapper]], [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye]], and [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]], and was the sole black surgeon at the 4077th. In the pilot episode, when planning a party, the captains jokingly considered raffling Spearchucker, but chose a date with Nurse Dish instead. During his brief run on the show, it was implied that he and nurse Ginger Bayliss (played by [[Odessa Cleveland]]) were romantically involved.

Spearchucker's role was limited. He is implied to have assisted Hawkeye and Trapper in their schemes on the sidelines. The producers decided to drop the character after the first few episodes deciding they wouldn't be able to write enough meaningful episodes for Spearchucker if they were concentrating on Hawkeye and Trapper, and because they were made aware that there is no record of African American doctors having served in [[Korean War|Korea]].&lt;ref&gt;Whitebols, James H. Watching M*A*S*H, Watching America: A Social History of the 1972-1983 Television Series, pg 17&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Spearchucker&quot; Jones was also a character in both the novel ''M*A*S*H'' (and its sequels) by [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]] and [[Robert Altman]]'s movie. In each, the Spearchucker character, who was a stand-out collegiate athlete (&quot;Spearchucker,&quot; a common [[List of ethnic slurs|racial slur]], is said to instead in this case refer to his [[Javelin throw|javelin-throwing]] prowess) as well as a surgeon, is transferred to the 4077th to help them win a [[American football|football]] game against a rival outfit. It is established in the novel that Jones is from [[MASH: A Novel About Three Army Doctors|Duke Forrest]]'s hometown of Forrest City, [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]], and knew Duke's father. Duke makes racist comments about Jones, causing Hawkeye and Trapper to punish Duke. In the novel it is related that while a poorly-paid resident he had been scouted by the [[Philadelphia Eagles]] playing semi-professional football in [[New Jersey]] for extra cash, and had been signed by the [[Philadelphia Eagles|Eagles]], playing with them until caught up in the draft.  According to the movie, his professional football career had been with the [[San Francisco 49ers]] prior to the war in Korea.

In the sequel novels, Jones joins the other doctors in their own practice in Maine, becoming a highly successful doctor and prominent citizen.

===Ugly John===
'''Captain &quot;Ugly&quot; John Black''' [[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|15px]] was portrayed by [[Carl Gottlieb]] in the movie, and [[John Orchard]] in the TV series. The character on the television show was an anesthesiologist from [[Australia]], often depicted wearing an Australian [[Slouch hat]]. In the book, he was an American who had &quot;trained in the States with [[#Trapper John McIntyre|McIntyre]].&quot; In the film, he is an American (as he can be seen wearing the insignia of a U.S. Army Captain), but his background is not discussed.
In the TV series, Ugly John was only present in the first season. He began as a significant supporting member of the cast, often engaged in poker games with Hawkeye and Trapper, but by the end of the season he was rarely seen outside of brief O.R. scenes.
Ugly John was never seen living in &quot;The Swamp&quot; and there was no fifth bunk, though it was the only quarters for subordinate male officers ever seen. In the episode &quot;[[Sometimes You Hear the Bullet]]&quot;, Hawkeye says that he shares a tent with three other doctors. The script was likely written before Spearchucker was dropped and the writers presumably overlooked editing that line of dialogue. However, Ugly John was still a recurring character, and may have been one of the “three other doctors.”
John Orchard later returned to the show for the Season 8 episode &quot;Captains Outrageous&quot;, this time playing a drunken and corrupt Australian Military Policeman &quot;Sgt. Muldoon&quot;.

===Ho-Jon===
'''Ho-Jon''' was portrayed by [[Patrick Adiarte]] in the series. In the original novel, Ho-Jon is described as a 17-year-old [[Koreans|Korean]], tall, thin, bright, [[Christian]], and living in [[Seoul]]. He is drafted into the [[South Korea]]n army, subsequently wounded and sent back to the 4077th for treatment. After rehabilitation, he resumes his position as &quot;Swampboy&quot;. The Swampmen, who are very fond of Ho-Jon, arrange to have him sent to Hawkeye's old [[college]] in the US. To raise funds, Trapper grows a beard, poses as [[Jesus|Jesus Christ]] (complete with a cross mounted on a jeep or hanging from a helicopter), and autographs thousands of photos which the Swampmen sell for a buck apiece.
In ''[[M*A*S*H Goes to Maine]]'', Ho-Jon is briefly seen again, having pursued a successful career in university administration. In &quot;[[M*A*S*H Mania]]&quot; he is shown to have become the Director of Admissions at Androscroggin College (Hawkeye's [[alma mater]]).

In the film, Ho-Jon is drafted, and Hawkeye drives him to the induction center. The Korean [[Physician|doctor]] who examines Ho-Jon discovers that Hawkeye has given him drugs to induce [[hypertension]] and [[tachycardia]] (so that he will fail the induction physical). Ho-Jon is last seen in the film being led away by South Korean soldiers while the doctor tells Hawkeye that he has seen through the trick.

In the screenplay, Ho-Jon is wounded and sent to the 4077th; however, his surgery is unsuccessful, and he dies. The final film omits this storyline, although a scene showing Ho-Jon in the operating room remains with overdubbed dialogue ''(Houlihan: &quot;That man's a prisoner of war, Doctor.&quot;  Trapper: &quot;So are you, Sweetheart, but you don't know it.&quot;)'' and a scene showing a jeep driving off with the deceased Ho-Jon, causing a brief pause in the poker game.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ring Lardner, Jr.]] &quot;MASH&quot; Screenplay; February 26, 1969 O.S.P. Publishing, Inc. ISBN 1-56693-308-0 pp. 103-104, 135-136&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Pilot (M*A*S*H)|pilot episode]] Ho-Jon is accepted at Hawkeye's old college, just as in the novel. In the TV version, the doctors raise funds for him by raffling off a weekend pass to [[Tokyo]] with Nurse Dish.

In the episode &quot;[[I Hate a Mystery]]&quot;, Ho-Jon steals many valuable items and Hawkeye's [[poker]] winnings in order to bribe the border guards to bring his family down from the [[North Korea|North]]. This contrasts with an incident in the pilot where he receives his college acceptance letter and leaves to tell his parents, who presumably live nearby.

===Lieutenant Dish===
'''1st Lieutenant Maria &quot;Dish&quot; Schneider''' [[File:US-OF1A.svg|6px]] was played by [[Jo Ann Pflug]] in the film and (as '''Lt. Maggie Dish''') by [[Karen Philipp]] in the series. She was a [[nurse]] at the 4077th [[Mobile Army Surgical Hospital|MASH]] during the [[Korean War]].

Dish's role in the finished film was limited, as a large portion of her role did not make the final cut. The same thing happened to the character in the television series. After being prominently featured as [[#Hawkeye Pierce|Hawkeye]]'s love interest in [[Pilot (M*A*S*H)|the pilot]], she was all but dropped from the show for the rest of the first season, before leaving the show entirely in its second season.

===Donald Penobscot===
'''Lieutenant Colonel Donald Penobscot''' [[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|15px]] was played by two different actors, [[Beeson Carroll]], and former football player and [[Tarzan]] actor [[Mike Henry (American football)|Mike Henry]]. His last name is perhaps inspired by the [[Penobscot River]] in [[Maine]], the state from where the novel's author, [[Richard Hooker (author)|Richard Hooker]], originally hailed.

Donald is introduced in name only at the start of the fifth season. Tall, dark, handsome, and physically very durable, he is a Lieutenant Colonel whom [[#Margaret Houlihan|Major Margaret &quot;Hot Lips&quot; Houlihan]] (Loretta Swit) meets while she is on leave in Tokyo. She falls madly in love with him on the spot, and he asks her to marry him right away. Margaret promptly accepts, leading to a falling out with her former flame [[#Frank Burns|Frank Burns]].

Penobscot is not actually seen until the season-ending episode &quot;Margaret's Marriage&quot;, wherein Donald (played by Carroll) arrives to marry Margaret at the 4077th. Hawkeye and B.J. have a bachelor party for him, and after he passes out from drunkenness, the hosts, also inebriated, decide to play a joke on Penobscot by plastering him from his chest to his toes, intending to tell him that he had broken both his legs during the night. The cast is still on during the wedding ceremony, and he is unable to move without assistance. The wedding is cut short by incoming wounded, which leaves Donald in the mess hall, unable to move in his body cast. They tried to tell Margaret the cast wasn't needed when she was leaving for her honeymoon, but she didn't hear them.

He is not seen again until &quot;The M*A*S*H Olympics&quot;, in which Donald (played this time by Henry) arrives to take part in the 4077th's amateur Olympics competition, and almost wins a race against portly Sgt. First Class Ames, but trips over himself while showing off.

He was mentioned frequently throughout the 6th and 7th seasons, particularly in reference to problems Margaret and Donald were having. For example, in the episode &quot;In Love and War&quot;, a new nurse arrives at the 4077th. After saying she was recently involved with a colonel named Donald, comes to the conclusion that Donald has cheated on her, and she flies into a rage against the nurse. The resulting rage convinces Col. Potter to transfer the nurse to ensure Margaret can still work.

===Zelmo Zale===
'''Staff Sergeant Zelmo Zale''' [[File:US Army E-6.svg|15px]] was portrayed by [[Johnny Haymer]].&lt;ref&gt;Fred L. Worth, ''Incredible Super Trivia'' (Greenwich House, 1984), [http://books.google.com/books?id =jua6vfXfS6UC&amp;q=%22Zelmo+Zale%22&amp;dq=%22Zelmo+Zale%22&amp;ei=_QGOSareLpj4MPm80LAF&amp;pgis=1 402].&lt;/ref&gt; Zale was the supply sergeant&lt;ref&gt;David Scott Diffrient, ''M*A*S*H'' (Wayne State University Press, 2008), [http://books.google.com/books?id=q6PCeV6-IxgC&amp;pg=PT56&amp;dq=%22Zelmo+Zale%22&amp;ei=_QGOSareLpj4MPm80LAF#PPT56,M1 47].&lt;/ref&gt; for the 4077th MASH and also was the camp's electrician; he was shown trying to keep the [[Military camp|camp]]'s generator going until it blew and repairing the juke box in the officers' club after the Marines busted it up. He mentions in one episode that he was from Brooklyn, which was the reason he didn't know what people who were heading to California in the late 1840s were looking for, when quizzed. He made his first appearance in the Season 2 episode, &quot;[[M*A*S*H (season 2)|For Want of a Boot]]&quot;, and his final appearance in the Season 8 episode, &quot;[[Good-Bye Radar]]&quot; (which, coincidentally enough, also marked [[Gary Burghoff]]'s last appearance on the show as Corporal [[#Radar O'Reilly|Radar O'Reilly]]). Zale's name is mentioned for the final time in &quot;Yes Sir, That's Our Baby&quot;.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Mash}}

[[Category:M*A*S*H]]
[[Category:Lists of fictional characters]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
