<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32432562" ns="0" title="R. Ashok"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Indian politician 
| name = R. Ashok
| image = 
| caption = 
| birth_date =
| birth_place =
| residence =
| death_date =
| death_place =
| order = 26th
| office = Transport Minister of Karnataka
| constituency = 
| term_start = 
| term_end = 
| predecessor = 
| successor = 
| party =[[Bharatiya Janata Party|BJP]] 
| religion = [[Hinduism]]
| spouse = 
| children = 
| website = 
| footnotes = 
| date = 
| year = 
| source = 
}}

'''R. Ashok''' is the former Minister for Home and Transport of [[Karnataka]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=BJP will launch agitation against the Congress: Ashok |url=http://www.hindu.com/2010/10/25/stories/2010102554400400.htm |work=[[The Hindu]] |date=25 October 2010 |accessdate=18 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; He represents the [[Padmanabha Nagar]] constituency in [[Bangalore]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Tight security arrangements made for bypoll |url=http://ibnlive.in.com/news/tight-security-arrangements-made-for-bypoll/162225-60-119.html |work=[[IBN Live]] |date=24 June 2011 |accessdate=18 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and belongs to the [[Vokkaliga]] community.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=BJP seeks to beard Deve Gowda in Vokkaliga den |url=http://www.dnaindia.com/bangalore/report_bjp-seeks-to-beard-deve-gowda-in-vokkaliga-den_1206894 |work=[[Daily News &amp; Analysis]] |date=16 November 2008 |accessdate=18 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

BRIEF PROFILE
Shri R. Ashoka being an active worker of RSS from the student life, developed leadership quality during college days. During Emergency he was arrested and was with senior leader Sri. L.K. Advaniji in Central Jail Bangalore. He was elected to Karnataka Legislative Assembly in 1997 bye Election from Uttarahalli Constituency, Which was the biggest constituency in Asia. He was re-elected from the same constituency in 1999 and 2004 general election. He was also associated with the youth wing of the party in his younger days.

Positions Held and Achievements:
Minister of Transport, Karnataka State Government. In this capacity, he has been instrumental in modernizing the entire Transport department and also using innovative hi-tech methods to automate the working of the department. Under his leadership, the transport department has come up with some advanced public transport vehicles with reasonable rates for the benefit of the public. Issue of bus pass and concessions for the deserved has been made simple.

Minister of Health, Karnataka State Government
As a Minister of Health, Mr. Ashoka, implemented novel schemes in the department and also streamlined the department. As a minister, he gave surprise visits to the hospitals to streamline the processes. It was during his tenure that Mr. Ashoka and his team gave an adhoc visit to the private clinics which were running in villages and caught some fake Doctors who claimed to some critical diseases.

As a transport minister Shri Ashoka has been doing a marvellous job to improve the standards in Public transport.

He is presently an MLA from the Padmanabhanagar assembly constituency of Bangalore City.

He is not the formar minister he is the current minister for Home and Transports.

Largest assembly constituency is not uttarahalli it is Villivakkam in Chennai

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;



{{Uncategorized|date=November 2011}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
