<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32491074" ns="0" title="2011 Israeli social justice protests"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Civil Conflict
| title = 2011 Israeli social justice protests
| partof = the [[2011 Israeli middle class protests]]
| image =[[File:Israel Housing Protests Tel Aviv August 6 2011b.jpg|300px]]
| caption =Demonstrators in [[Tel Aviv]] on August 6, 2011
| date =14 July 2011 – ''ongoing''&lt;br&gt;({{Age in years and days|2011|7|14}})
| place ={{flag|Israel}}
| coordinates =
| causes =
| status = Ongoing
| goals = Providing solutions to the various hardships of the [[middle class]] and [[lower class]] in Israel (such as housing costs, cost of living and the erosion of the middle class and lower class)
| result =
| methods = [[Demonstration (people)|Demonstration]]s, [[civil disobedience]], [[civil resistance]], [[sit-ins]], movement for [[recall elections]], [[online activism]], [[protest camp]]s [[Occupation (protest)|occupation]]s
| side1 =
| side2 =
| side3 =
| leadfigures1 = [[#Protest leadership|See expanded section]]
| leadfigures2 =
| leadfigures3 =
| howmany1 =
| howmany2 =
| howmany3 =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| casualties3 =
| casualties_label =
| notes =
}}
The '''2011 Israeli social justice protests''' ({{lang-he|מחאת צדק חברתי}}), [[#Naming|which are also referred to by various other names in the media]], are a series of ongoing demonstrations in [[Israel]] beginning in July 2011 involving hundreds of thousands of protesters from a variety of [[socio-economic]] and religious backgrounds opposing the continuing rise in the [[cost of living]] (particularly housing) and the deterioration of public services such as health and education. A common rallying cry at the demonstrations was the chant; &quot;The people demand social justice!&quot;.

As the protests expanded during [[August 2011]], the demonstrations began to also focus on other related issues relating to the social order and power structure in Israel. 

The housing protests which sparked the first demonstrations began as a result of a [[Facebook]] protest group that initially led hundreds of people to establish [[tents]] in the [[Rothschild Boulevard]] in the center of [[Tel Aviv]], an act which soon gained momentum, media attention and began a public discourse in Israel regarding the [[Israel's housing bubble|high cost of housing]] and living expenses. Soon afterwards, the protests spread to many other major [[cities in Israel]] as thousands of Israeli protesters began establishing tents in the middle of central streets in major cities as a means of protest. As part of the protests, several mass demonstrations have been held across the country, in which hundreds of thousands of people have participated.

A major focus of the protests have been what organizers have termed ''[[social justice]]''. Part of the movement is about changing the social order, and the economic system. Calls to topple the government were made by some parts of the protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheafer&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Scale of social justice protests surprises experts |url=http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=233324|publisher=The Jerusalem Post|author=Melanie Lidman|date=11 August 2011|accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticism of the protests includes accusations of a political agenda rather than a social one with revelations of funding from specific left-wing individuals and organizations like [[S. Daniel Abraham]] and the [[New Israel Fund]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Abraham&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=חשיפה: המיליונר האמריקני דניאל אברהם מימן את מחאת האוהלים |url=http://news.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=821074|publisher=Channel 10 (Israel)|authors=Orly Vilnai and Guy Meroz|date=9 August 2011|accessdate=17 August 2011}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Maariv (newspaper)|Maariv]] journalist Kalman Libeskind claimed that the spontaneous protests had actually been three months in the planning by [[Stan Greenberg]] and orchestrated by left-wing organizations and [[The National Left]].&lt;ref name=Libeskind&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nrg.co.il/app/index.php?do=blog&amp;encr_id=79974780b5e0d394fddbd1a00f4f21d3&amp;id=2804 |title=זו המחאה הספונטנית הכי מתוכננת שראיתם |language=Hebrew|trans_title=The most planned spontaneous protest you have ever seen |date=2 September 2011|accessdate=3 September 2011 |last=Libeskind |first=Kalman |work=nrg.co.il|publisher=Maariv}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticism within the protests accused the 'protest leaders' of not publicizing specific goals, the lack of visibility of their goals, and the damaging impact of media focus being on a few activists.&lt;ref name=&quot;Moyal&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Alternative tent protests cast doubt on 'social leaders' |url=http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=235436 |publisher= Jerusalem Post |author=Ben Hartman|date=25 August 2011|accessdate=28 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the first large-scale protests in early August, the government announced that a series of measures would taken to solve the housing shortage, some of which were already under preparation and ratification, and some which were new measures proposed in response to the demands of the protest movement leadership.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART2/263/592.html חדשות - פוליטי/מדיני nrg - ...נתניהו: נאשר 50 אלף דירות]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] appointed a team of ministers and senior staff members from his office, headed by Finance Minister [[Yuval Steinitz]], to negotiate with the protest leaders{{Or|date=August 2011}} as well as the [[Trajtenberg Committee]]. Since that time, there has been significant criticism of the Prime Minister's perceived insensitivity to the public sentiment, and there is ongoing speculation that general sympathy for the protest movement may cause one or more members of the governing coalition to leave the government, triggering national elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;Azulay&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Trajtenberg vote fiasco prelude to elections |url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4130744,00.html|publisher=Yediot Ahronot Newspaper|author=Moran Azulay|date=3 October 2011|accessdate=5 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Naming==
In Israel the protests have generally been referred to as the '''Housing Protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת הדיור}} ''Mechaat HaDiyur''),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART2/270/336.html?hp=1&amp;cat=479&amp;loc=7 חדשות - דעות - עלי קדם nrg - המחאה שייכת לצעירים]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mako.co.il/news-specials/social-protest/Article-212b10ebf91b131017.htm&amp;sCh=3d385dd2dd5d4110&amp;pId=565984153 חדשות 2 - מחאת הדיור יוצאת מת&quot;א: בשבת - הפגנות ענק ב-20 ערים]&lt;/ref&gt; '''Social justice protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת צדק חברתי}} ''Mechaat Tzedek Hevrati''),&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheafer&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.upi.com/Top_News/World-News/2011/08/14/Israeli-social-justice-protests-continue/UPI-65041313324094/ Israeli social justice protests continue]&lt;/ref&gt; the '''Cost of Living protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת יוקר המחייה}} ''Mechaat Yoker HaMekhiya''),&lt;ref name=KERSHNER&gt;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/08/07/world/middleeast/07jerusalem.html - Protests Grow in Israel, With 250,000 Marching&lt;/ref&gt; the '''Real estate protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת הנדל&quot;ן}} ''Mechaat HaNadlan''),&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4095726,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated7&gt;[http://www.globes.co.il/news/article.aspx?did=1000665858 מחאת הנדל&quot;ן: לשכנים יימאס לפני שנתניהו יחשוב על ספין - גלובס]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated7 /&gt; the '''Tents protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת האוהלים}} ''Mechaat HaOhalim'')&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.walla.co.il/?w=//1850601 מחאת האוהלים | דעה: בגידת השכבות החלשות - וואלה! חדשות]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.co.il/hasite/spages/1235430.html מחאת האוהלים בשדרות רוטשילד בתל אביב: כאן מוחים בכיף - חינוך וחברה - הארץ]&lt;/ref&gt; and less frequently the '''middle class protest''' ({{lang|he|מחאת מעמד הביניים}} ''Mechaat Maamad HaBeynaim'').&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4108044,00.html מסתכלים קדימה, חושבים אחורה. רואים חומר נפץ]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
=== Motivations ===
Numerous factors have led to the protests, in particular rising cost of housing and living expenses in Israel, but also various ongoing issues such as government corruption, rising poverty rates which the [[OECD]] defined as being twice the average of other developed countries, and a widening gap between rich and poor.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/world/2011/0815/1224302449821.html Mass protests and tent cities shake Israeli government - The Irish Times - Mon, Aug 15, 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; 

Demographic structural factors, such as a large percentage of educated but dissatisfied youth within the population, extreme poverty in the haredi Jewish sector, and high unemployment in the [[Arab-Israeli]] population have spread the cause of the protests amongst a wide swathe of the Israeli population. &lt;ref name=Rolnik&gt;[http://english.themarker.com/11-reasons-why-summer-2011-was-momentous-in-israeli-history-1.387139?localLinksEnabled=false 10 reasons why summer 2011 was momentous in Israeli history  - The Marker Business Magazine - 28 September 2011]&lt;/ref&gt; Many have also blamed the erosion of Israel's traditional egalitarian socio-economic model for the rise in public dissatisfaction, claiming that the rise of American-style social structures in Israel is incompatible with Zionist ideology.&lt;ref name=American&gt;[http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4130150,00.html Say no to the American way  - Yediot Ahronot Newspaper - 3 October 2011]&lt;/ref&gt;

A major catalyst for public anger has been the significant rise in the cost of living, particularly for the lower and middle class. Although average salaries in Israel tend to be lower than those in the Western world, the cost of many consumer goods is relatively high - particularly basic necessities on which long established price controls have gradually been lifted. Since 2007, Israel has also experienced a gradual rise in housing prices. This increase followed a decade-long period of low housing costs, between 1996 and 2005, as well as a long history of significant government involvement in the public housing sector. According to data from the [[Israel Central Bureau of Statistics]], from 2005 to 2011 apartment rental prices rose 34% on average, 49% in the Gush Dan region around Tel Aviv. A survey published by the [[Housing and Construction Minister of Israel]] revealed that in 2010, 129 average monthly salaries were required for the purchase of an average priced apartment, an amount significantly higher than countries in the Western world.

=== Events leading to the protests ===
In April 2011, about three months before the cost of living protests began, [[Boaz Gaon]], son of prominent Israeli businessman [[Benny Gaon]], presented activists with a ten point plan by Democratic pollster and political strategist [[Stan Greenberg]] to defeat the right-wing.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gJvV7DSn2JU&amp; |date=March 2011|accessdate=3 September 2011 |language=Hebrew|trans_title=This is how the right will be defeated by Stan Greenberg. Rubinger Forum |first=Boaz|last=Gaon |publisher=Rovinger Forum}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.box.net/shared/renakz014h |date=28 March 2011|accessdate=3 September 2011 |language=Hebrew|trans_title=This is how the right will be defeated if we work hard and correctly |first=Boaz|last=Gaon |publisher=Rovinger Forum}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|http://www.haaretz.com/weekend/magazine/charge-of-the-left-brigade-1.351789 |title=Charge of the Left Brigade |language=English|date=25 March 2011|accessdate=4 September 2011 |authors= Boaz Gaon and Jonathan Gurfinkel |work=www.haaretz.com|publisher=Haaretz}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was recommended that not one organization should coordinate the struggle, rather to divide up the effort with as many initiatives in as many locations as possible. [[Maariv (newspaper)|Maariv]] journalist Kalman Libeskind suggested that the protests were a result of this plan.&lt;ref name=Libeskind/&gt;

During June 2011, a month before the housing protest began, another significant large scale demonstration took place in Israel. Commonly referred to by the media as [[the cottage cheese boycott]], this event saw the Israeli public protest against the high cost of many products in Israel and specifically in this case, the high price of cottage cheese. The protest was successful and led to a drop in the retail price of cottage cheese.&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304584004576417543687962906.html Israeli Facebook Campaign Keeps Lid on Cheese Prices ]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2023688/Complaints-cottage-cheese-prices-spark-protests-Israel.html A very middle-class protest: Complaints over price of COTTAGE CHEESE spark Israel's biggest demonstration]&lt;/ref&gt; This was the first time in Israel that a public protest organized by means of social networking had such a wide public effect in Israel.

In July 2011, 25-year-old Israeli video editor [[Daphne Leef]] had to vacate the central Tel Aviv apartment where she had lived for three years due to major renovations in her building. Leef soon found out that apartment rental prices in the Tel Aviv metropolitan area had skyrocketed. Consequently, she initiated a small-scale public tent protest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4096185,00.html|title=המחאה מתפשטת: אוהלים בבאר שבע ובצפון|publisher=Ynet.co.il |date=17 July 2011|accessdate=24 July 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Check spread: tents in Be'er Sheva and north}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leef opened a Facebook protest page, inviting others to join her protest, and pitched a tent in [[Habima Square]] in Tel Aviv. In response, protesters gathered in the streets around Rothschild Boulevard in Tel Aviv, as well as in Zion Square in Jerusalem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4095171,00.html|title=מחאת הנדל&quot;ן: שקי שינה בעירייה, אוהלים בכיכר|publisher=Ynet.co.il |date=14 July 2011|accessdate=24 July 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Real estate protest: sleeping bags at City Hall, tents in the square}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4095726,00.html |title=מחאת הנדל&quot;ן: &quot;נמלא את כל ת&quot;א באוהלים&quot;|publisher=Ynet.co.il |date=15 July 2011 |accessdate=24 July 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Real estate protest: &quot;filled with all TA in tents&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The use of [[Protest camp]]s have been described by the protest leaders as being inspired by the [[Hooverville]] tent cities in the Central Park of New York City in which many Americans were forced to live during the [[Great Depression]] in the United States.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;

The use of [[social networks]] for public protests began to increase in the early 2010s, with the most significant one being the [[Arab Spring|large-scale demonstrations in Arab countries in the Middle East]] that led to a change of government in several countries such as [[Egypt]] (see [[2011 Egyptian revolution]]). Some see a connection between the Arab Spring protests and the 2011 Israeli housing protests, as the common denominator is, firstly, the use of [[social networking]] to organize public protests,&lt;ref&gt;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/babylonbeyond/2011/07/israel-protests-spread-demanding-social-justice.html ISRAEL: Is the Arab Spring spreading to the Jewish state? - latimes.com]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalpost.com/dispatches/news/regions/middle-east/israel-and-palestine/has-the-arab-spring-arrived-israel Has the Arab spring spread to Israel? | GlobalPost]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.walla.co.il/?w=/0/1846206 מחאת האוהלים מסוקרת בעיתוני ערב: &quot;האביב הערבי רודף את נתניהו&quot; - וואלה! חדשות]&lt;/ref&gt; and secondly the fact that these two waves of protests stem from the increase in the [[cost of living]], that they were organized mostly by young people, and that the protesters claims include not only economic demands but also demands for changes in the policies and practices of the ruling government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/article/158680/egypts-workers-rise Egypt's Workers Rise Up | The Nation]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Protests ==
[[File:Real Estate Protest in Tel Aviv 25.7.2011 1.jpg|thumb|250px|The protest compound on [[Rothschild Boulevard]] in Tel Aviv, July 21, 2011]]
[[File:Beer Sheva 2011 housing protests812.jpg|thumb|250px|Demonstrators in [[Beersheba]] on July 30, 2011]]
[[File:Israel Housing Protests Tel Aviv August 6 2011c.jpg|thumb|250px|Thousands gather to demonstrate in central Tel Aviv, August 6, 2011]]

=== Timeline ===
{{main|Timeline of the 2011 Israeli housing protests}}

; July
* '''14 July 2011:''' 25-year-old [[Daphne Leef]] pitches a tent in the Habima Square in Tel Aviv and in addition opens a Facebook protest page, where she invites others to join her protest.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4096185,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''15 July 2011:''' In response to Leef's protest, many protesters gathered in the streets around [[Rothschild Boulevard]] in Tel Aviv where about 50 tents were pitched.
* '''16 July 2011:''' the [[National Union of Israeli Students]] joined the protests.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4096107,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''17 July 2011:''' the [[Hashomer Hatzair]] movement joined the protests.&lt;ref name=autogenerated2&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4096290,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''23 July 2011:''' tens of thousands of demonstrators participated in a the protest movement's first rally held in the center of Tel Aviv which included a mass march from the tent compound at [[Habima Square]] to the [[Tel Aviv Museum of Art]] Plaza, where the main rally was held.&lt;ref&gt;[http://972mag.com/breaking-protesters-block-streets-in-central-tel-aviv/ Protesters block streets in Tel Aviv after landmark rally]&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''24 July 2011:''' a protest broke out in [[Jerusalem]], in which 1,000 demonstrators marched towards the [[Knesset]] while causing major traffic disruptions.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4099495,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''26 July 2011:''' Prime Minister [[Binyamin Netanyahu]] [[#July 26th new government housing plans announcements|announced new housing programs aimed at addressing the housing shortage in Israel and at supporting the students]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4100162,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''28 July 2011:''' the first &quot;strollers march&quot; took place in which thousands of Israeli parents took part, protesting against the high costs of raising children in Israel.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4101517,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''30 July 2011:''' between 85,000 and 150,000 people took part in mass rallies in major cities across Israel. Demonstrations were held in [[Jerusalem]], [[Tel Aviv]], [[Haifa]], [[Beersheba]], [[Kfar Saba]], [[Ra'anana]], [[Baqa al-Gharbiya]], [[Ashdod]], [[Nazareth]], [[Kiryat Shmona]], [[Modi'in-Maccabim-Re'ut]], [[Kfar Saba]], [[Netanya]], [[Ashkelon]], [[Tiberias]], the [[Savion]] Junction, and the [[Jordan Valley]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4102107,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

; August
* '''6 August 2011:''' between 200,000 and 350,000 protesters took part in mass rallies in major cities across Israel. Demonstrations took place in [[Tel Aviv]] (150,000 - 300,000), [[Jerusalem]] (30,000), [[Kiryat Shmona]] (3,000), [[Hod HaSharon]] (1,000), [[Modi'in-Maccabim-Re'ut]] (5,000), [[Ashkelon]] (500), [[Dimona]] (200), and [[Eilat]] (1,000).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4105195,00.html |title=National upheaval: 400,000 protestors hit streets |work=Ynet |date=6 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/more-than-300-000-demonstrate-across-israel-to-protest-high-cost-of-living-1.377295 |title=More than 300,000 demonstrate across Israel to protest high cost of living |work=Haaretz |first1=Ilan |last1=Lior |first2=Yanir |last2=Yagna |date=6 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''7 August 2011:''' some 1,300 parents staged &quot;strollers marches&quot; in [[Giv'atayim]], [[Karmiel]], and [[Pardes Hanna-Karkur]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4105763,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; In Tel Aviv, some 100 right-wing activists marched in Rothschild Boulevard, protesting what they called the &quot;anarchistic nature of the leftist housing protest&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4105786,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Israel Housing Protests Tel Aviv August 27 2011.jpg|thumb|250px|Tel-aviv protest rally, August 27, 2011]]
* '''13 August 2011:''' at most 75,000 people took part in mass rallies in major cities across Israel. Demonstrations took place in [[Haifa]], [[Beersheba]], [[Afula]], [[Eilat]], [[Rosh Pinna]], [[Nahariya]], [[Dimona]], [[Petah Tikva]], [[Modi'in-Maccabim-Re'ut]], [[Beit She'an]], [[Netanya]], [[Ramat HaSharon]], [[Hod HaSharon]], [[Rishon LeZion]], [[Beit Shemesh]], and [[Ashkelon]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4108313,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/tens-of-thousands-take-to-israel-s-streets-as-social-protests-move-out-of-tel-aviv-1.378465 Tens of thousands take to Israel's streets as social protests move out of Tel Aviv - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News]&lt;/ref&gt;
{{multiple image
 | direction = vertical
 | width     = 250
 | footer    = September 3 protest in Tel Aviv
 | image1    = March of the million rallies in tel aviv 1.jpg
 | alt1      =
 | caption1  =
 | image2    = March of the million rallies in tel aviv.jpg
}}
* '''22 August 2011:''' The activists, including Daphne Leef, decided to take over abandoned buildings. Tens of activists, including members of Knesset [[Dov Khenin]] ([[Hadash]]) and [[Nitzan Horowitz]] ([[New Movement – Meretz]]) stormed a building on Dov Hoz street in Tel Aviv and waved placards calling for affordable housing.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.inn.co.il/News/News.aspx/224802&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''26 August 2011:''' Protesters occupied a second abandoned building in Tel Aviv, on Bialik St., and had planned on staying longer but removed soon after and the building sealed by police.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=235546&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''27 August 2011:''' In Tel Aviv, around 10,000 protesters marched from Habima Square to the intersection of Ibn Gvirol and Shaul Hamelech streets, where a rally was held.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/tens-of-thousands-take-to-the-streets-in-social-protests-across-israel-1.381036&lt;/ref&gt;
; September
* '''3 September:''' A protest billed as the &quot;March of the Million&quot; sees an estimated 460,000 people taking to the streets throughout the country, 300,000 of which in Tel Aviv.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/some-450-000-israelis-march-at-massive-march-of-the-million-rallies-across-country-1.382366&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=236562&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-14777260 |title=Israelis hold renewed mass protests over living costs |date=2011-09-03 |publisher=BBC news}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''6-7 September:''' The Tel Aviv municipality visits tent sites and posts notices that the area needs to be evacuated. Early next morning, city workers arrive to clear tents and other items and are called &quot;Nazis in city hall uniforms&quot; by activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4118863,00.html |title=רוב האוהלים פונו בתל-אביב; עימות ברוטשילד |language=Hebrew|trans_title=Most tents evacuated in Tel Aviv; Confrontation on Rothschild |date=7 September 2011|accessdate=7 September 2011 |work=ynet.co.il|publisher=Ynet}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were also violent demonstrations at the Tel Aviv city hall against the evacuation of the tents and over 30 activists were arrested.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=clashes between police officers and demonstrators, 20 people arrested (in hebrew)|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4119138,00.html|publisher=ynet}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Violent protest outside TA City Hall after tents removed|url=http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=237113|publisher=Jpost}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''27 September:''' In press conference, protesters warned Prime Minister Netanyahu that he has a month to make &quot;real and serious recommendations” or “on October 29, just before the Knesset returns to session, we will take to the streets in full force. This year we will take the country back into our hands, rock and roll.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hartman|first=Ben|title=Social movement leaders threaten massive October protest|url=http://www.jpost.com/DiplomacyAndPolitics/Article.aspx?id=239718|accessdate=29 September 2011|newspaper=The Jerusalem Post|date=27 septiembre 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; October
*'''3 October:''' The symbol of the protest movement, the tent encampment on Tel Aviv Rothschild Boulevard, was dismantled by police.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Middle-East/2011/1004/Israel-s-tent-protests-transition-to-next-stage-political-fight&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''15 October:''' An &quot;occupy Tel Aviv&quot; protest held on Rothschild.  Several hundred gathered at Tel Aviv Museum plaza where opinions are voiced in &quot;Hyde Park&quot; speakers corner&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=241847&lt;/ref&gt;.
[[File:Israel social justice protests Rabin Square Tel aviv 29 october 2011.jpeg|thumb|250px|29 October protest,Tel-aviv]]
*'''29 October:''' With renewed vigor, tens of thousands of protesters took to the streets of most Israeli cities&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=243640http://www.jpost.com/NationalNews/Article.aspx?id=243640&lt;/ref&gt;, except for Bersheva, which had just been gratutitously bombed by Hamas in Gaza.

=== Cities and regions ===
{{Expand section|date=August 2011}}

;Tel Aviv
Tel Aviv has been at the epicenter of much of the crisis and has experienced ongoing protests every day from 14 July 2011 onwards. The largest protests were held in downtown Tel Aviv, which has been considered the protest movement's most effective symbol. Hundreds of thousands of people have been estimated to participate in the protests rallies in Tel Aviv.

;Rishon-Lezion
Some tents were established at Rishon-Lezion's municipal park already in late July 2011.

;Jerusalem

;Haifa and the [[North District (Israel)|North District]]
On August 13, 2011 circa 25,000 people turned out to demonstrate in the [[Haifa]] downtown protest.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/national/israel-s-periphery-proved-it-is-part-of-the-struggle-1.378601 Israel's periphery 'proved it is part of the struggle' - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News]&lt;/ref&gt;

;Beersheba and the [[Southern District (Israel)|Southern District]]
On August 13, 2011 more than 20,000 people turned out to demonstrate in [[Beersheba]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;

;Holon

There were approximately 10 illegally built shacks in Jessie Cohen neighborhood in [[Holon]], built by people from the lower class. On September 7th the shacks were evacuated.

== Government reactions ==
The Israeli Prime Minister [[Binyamin Netanyahu]] initially reacted to the protests by stating that he is aware of the crisis, and that &quot;the government is working to fix the plague that haunts us for many years. We are a small country, there is great demand and not enough apartments. Help me pass the reform in the Israel Lands Administration&quot;. Netanyahu also clarified that &quot;It would take between a year to three years until we would begin seeing results.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=נתניהו על מחאת האוהלים: &quot;מטפלים במצוקה בימים אלה&quot;|url=http://www.mako.co.il/news-israel/local/Article-d8cde530a273131004.htm|date=17 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Netanyahu protest tents: &quot;We treat distress these days&quot;|publisher=makoערוצי}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Government housing plans ===
On 26 July 2011, Prime Minister Netanyahu announced a new housing plan, including significant incentives for contractors who build smaller apartments, rent-earmarked housing and student housing, and plans to add 50,000 apartments to Israel's housing market over the next two years. The plan would allow contractors to purchase land from the [[Israel Land Administration]] up to 50% cheaper if they agree to build small apartments. Contractors bidding on rent-earmarked housing projects would be obligated to rent out 50% of their apartments built for a period of at least ten years, at 30% of their current value, and would be allowed to sell the other 50% of apartments at a price they can set. Contractors would be allowed to raise rent rates annually, in accordance with the [[consumer price index]]. Contractors and land developers who build student housing would be given land for free, but would have to agree to government-supervised rent rates for twenty years. Netanyahu's plan also called for six newly appointed national housing boards to authorize housing projects with little bureaucracy. The boards' mandate would be reviewed every eighteen months. Netanyahu also said that the government would promote the construction of 10,000 housing units for students, and would subsidize students' transportation to allow them to seek housing further away from universities.&lt;ref name=&quot;new housing plan&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=PM announces new housing plan|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4100162,00.html|publisher=ynetnews.com|author=Omri Efraim|date=26 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Trajtenberg Committee ===
{{main|Trajtenberg Committee}}
On 8 August 2011, Prime Minister Netanyahu appointed a committee to pinpoint and propose solutions to Israel's socioeconomic problems. The committee's task was to hold discussions with &quot;different groups and sectors within the public&quot;, and subsequently make proposals to the government's socioeconomic cabinet, headed by Finance Minister [[Yuval Steinitz]]. Professor [[Manuel Trajtenberg]], chairman of the Planning and Budgeting Committee of the Council for Higher Education, former head of the National Economic Council, and the former Chief Economic Adviser to the Prime Minister, was appointed to head the committee. The committee consists of 14 members, 10 of whom are government or public officials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/DiplomacyAndPolitics/Article.aspx?id=233085 Trajtenberg oversees first meetin... JPost - Diplomacy &amp; Politics]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/DiplomacyAndPolitics/Article.aspx?id=232872 PM appoints team to meet protest ... JPost - Diplomacy &amp; Politics]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/news/pm-s-expert-panel-says-no-new-budget-expected-for-2012-1.377878 Prime Minister's expert panel says no new budget expected for 2012 - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Protest leadership ==
[[File:Daphne Leef דפני ליף.jpg|180px|thumb|right|[[Daphne Leef]] speaking at a protest rally in Tel Aviv, 23 July 2011]]
{{Expand section|date=August 2011}}
The 2011 Israeli housing protests have no formal leadership.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

Amongst the most prominent activists in the protests are [[Daphne Leef]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://iwpr.net/report-news/tel-aviv’s-tahrir-square Tel Aviv’s Tahrir Square - IWPR Institute for War &amp; Peace Reporting - P50463]&lt;/ref&gt; Orly Weisselberg, Roee Neuman, Yigal Rambam,&lt;ref name=&quot;Lior&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/features/activist-yigal-rambam-aren-t-you-afraid-the-housing-protest-will-die-out-1.375091|title=Activist Yigal Rambam, aren't you afraid the housing protest will die out?|date=25 July 2011|accessdate=8 August 2011|first=Ilan|last=Lior|publisher=Haaretz.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stav Shaffir,&lt;ref name=KERSHNER/&gt; Jonathan Levy,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4102005,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; Jonathan Miller,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.walla.co.il/?w=/1/1841267|title=מחאת הדיור בת&quot;א: &quot;ממתינים לתשובות מנתניהו&quot;|date=17 July 2011|accessdate=8 August 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Housing protest in Tel Aviv, &quot;Netanyahu are waiting for answers&quot;|first=בועז|last=ווליניץ|publisher=Walla! Communications|work=http://news.walla.co.il}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regev Kontas,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mouse.co.il/CM.articles_item,778,209,62194,.aspx|title=נוער הדירות: האנשים היפים שמאחורי מחאת האוהלים|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Youth housing: the beautiful people behind the protest tents|date=21 July 2011|accessdate=8 August 2011|work=mouse.co.il|first=רגב|last=קונטס}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adam Dovz'insky,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.haaretz.co.il/captain/spages/1236524.html|title=הוויקי בשירות מחאת הדיור: &quot;הכאוס הוא הכוח של המאבק&quot;|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Housing protest service wiki: &quot;Chaos is the force of the struggle&quot;|accessdate=8 August 2011|date=29 July 2011|first=עודד|last=ירון|work=haaretz.co.il|publisher=Haaretz}}&lt;/ref&gt; Baruch Oren&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4096640,00.html|title=עוד ועוד אוהלים: חשש בליכוד מ&quot;מאסה קריטית&quot;|language=Hebrew|trans_title=More and more tents: a critical concern in the Likud M&quot;mash &quot;|date=18 July 2011|accessdate=8 August 2011|first1=אטילה|last1=שומפלבי|first2=אילנה|last2=קוריאל|first3=בועז|last3=פיילר|work=ynet.co.il|publisher=Yedioth Internet}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Boaz Gaon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.globes.co.il/news/article.aspx?did=1000676714 |title=האם בועז גאון, בנו של מיליונר, יכול להיות פעיל במחאה החברתית?|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Can Boaz Gaon, son of a milionaire, be an activist in a social protest? |date=25 August 2011|accessdate=4 September 2011|first=Tal|last=Perry|work=globes.co.il|publisher=Globes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Actively contributing and supporting the protests were newspaper columnists [[Roy Arad]] and Shlomo Kraus.

Adam Dovz'insky, who took a prominent part at the beginning of the protests with a hunger strike that ended when he collapsed and needed medical attention, would later declare that the Rothschild Blvd leadership does not want solutions but rather to topple the Netanyahu government, that the protests seemed to be the end themselves, not a means toward achieve negotiations. Dovz'insky also said he had information connected the protests with European anarchists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=מדבר מהבטן|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Talking from the stomach|date=2 September 2011|first=אראל|last=סג&quot;ל|work=Maariv {newspaper}|publisher=Mariv}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://up352.siz.co.il/up2/y1m1ixgzmymj.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://up352.siz.co.il/up1/nmogzmtyfnzk.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://up352.siz.co.il/up1/nmogzmtyfnzk.jpg&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Demands of the protesters ===
The initial objective of the leaders of the protest movement focused on reducing the costs of housing in Israel. For the most part, the protest leadership has declared that they would not offer any concrete solutions to the crisis on the grounds that it is not their role, but the government's role. However, the demonstrators in Tel Aviv have promised to work together with the Knesset members and other decision makers to promote legislation aimed at protecting apartment renters against exploitation of their hardships by landlords, in a way that would correspond to similar legislation worldwide.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.calcalist.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-3524513,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; At some of the public events, protesters call revolution, for Netanyahu's resignation, and the downfall of the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lior&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.haaretz.co.il/hasite/spages/1236548.html כ-150 אלף בני אדם הפגינו ברחבי הארץ; &quot;המדינה מתנכרת לתושביה&quot; - חינוך וחברה - הארץ]&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, in August 2011, as the protests grew significantly, the demands became more radical as they began to call for a sweeping overhaul of the [[Israeli economy]] and society which would change the current [[Neo liberal]] approach of the Netanyahu government to a more social approach. The list of demands for broader changes in the Israeli society and governance, articulated by protesters and activists, includes the following:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+
! style=&quot;width:70%;&quot;| Demand
! style=&quot;width:15%;&quot;| Ref
|-
| 1. A new [[taxation]] system would be implemented (which would include lower [[indirect taxes]] and higher [[direct taxes]]).
| &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5h2FQMmJLEz3KWXEEQ0EvpC0v19Vg?docId=CNG.b297b50cc6bfa351b47c8255989665aa.a61 AFP: Israeli protesters seek radical change]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=autogenerated3&gt;[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:QtNTQadtCkIJ:www.ft.com/cms/s/0/6b9d9c08-c299-11e0-9ede-00144feabdc0.html Swelling list of demands fuels Israel protests - FT.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 2. [[Free education|Free schooling]] from an early age.
| &lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;
|-
| 3. [[Privatization]] of state-owned enterprises would end.
| &lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;
|-
| 4. More resources would be invested on [[public housing]] and [[public transportation]].
| &lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt;
|}

== Organizations and individuals who have joined the protest ==
[[File:Jerusalem real estate protest 31.7.2011 cropped.jpg|thumb|250px|[[Meir Shalev]], [[David Grossman]] and [[Yossi Abulafia]] at the demonstration in Jerusalem]]
[[File:Demonstration against the housing prices in Haifa 30.7.2011 – Horev Square, Ahuza (36).JPG|thumb|250px|A group of demonstrators from the [[HaShomer HaTzair]] (white laces), [[HaMahanot HaOlim]] (buttons) and [[HaNoar HaOved VeHaLomed]] (red laces) Israeli Socialist youth movements in the demonstration in Haifa on July 30, 2011]]
[[File:Discours lors de la manifestation pour les habitants du sud de Tel-Aviv.jpg|thumb|250px|Speeches at the demonstration for the residents of southern Tel Aviv, a tent camp in the garden of Lewinsky]]
Many movements and organizations have joined the protest. According to the Israeli newspaper &quot;[[Israel HaYom]]&quot;, two weeks prior to the protest, the Israeli social movement &quot;[[The National Left]]&quot; sought people on Facebook &quot;who have unreasonable rent fees&quot; to start a campaign to lower the cost of housing for young people. On the day on which the protest began, the &quot;The National Left&quot; movement called its activists to get to the Rothschild Boulevard, and organized the delivery of 20 tents to the encampment. In an interview with the Israeli morning show &quot;HaOlam HaBoker&quot; the chairman of the movement, Eldad Yaniv, addressed &quot;Israel HaYom&quot;'s report and explained that the movement &quot;organizes many protests like this throughout country and it just happened that this one became popular&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://reshet.ynet.co.il/Shows/Haolam_Haboker/videomarklist,187816/ העולם הבוקר - השמאל הלאומי יצר את מחאת האוהלים]&lt;/ref&gt; Several activists posted [[Daphne Leef]]'s call on the movement's web site and invited their friends to join the encampment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://activism.org.il/node/948#comment-937 בית זה אהל | אקטיביזם]&lt;/ref&gt; The movement also initiated the establishment of a website to accompany the protest&lt;ref&gt;[http://activism.org.il/node/961 יולי 14 | אקטיביזם]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://activism.org.il/node/963 תכלס | אקטיביזם]&lt;/ref&gt; and assisted in managing the encampment, in part by the introduction of &quot;popular assemblies&quot; for making decisions on the conduct of the protest.&lt;ref&gt;[http://activism.org.il/node/962 תרומות למאבק האוהלים | אקטיביזם]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://activism.org.il/node/966 מדריך מהיר לניהול אסיפות עממיות תקציר | אקטיביזם]&lt;/ref&gt;

The protest also gained support from the [[National Union of Israeli Students]] and the local student unions throughout Israel, who helped establish the encampments and organized transportation to the demonstration in Tel Aviv. The Jewish U.S.-based non-profit organization &quot;[[New Israel Fund]]&quot; gave guidance and logistical support to the encampments in [[Kiryat Shmona]], [[Be'er Sheva]] and elsewhere.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.themarker.com/news/1.671269 הקרן החדשה תסייע במימון המחאה - חדשות - דה מרקר TheMarker]&lt;/ref&gt; The head of the Shatil activist wing of the New Israel Fund admitted that the group was working behind the scenes and coordinating multiple tent locations and published a report on its activities.&lt;ref name=Shatil&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nif.org/issue-areas/1176-a-letter-from-shatil-director-ronit-heyd |title=A Letter from SHATIL Director Ronit Heyd |publisher=New Israel Fund |accessdate=30 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Zionist extra-parliamentary{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}} group &quot;[[Im Tirtzu]]&quot;, which initially supported the protests, later announced that it would stop its involvement due to the participation of the &quot;New Israel Fund&quot;. The [[Bnei Akiva]] and the &quot;Rannim&quot; movements (both of the religious Zionism) announced that they would also stop their involvement in the protests in Tel Aviv. The &quot;Rannim&quot; movement later announced it would continue its participation in the protest but only in the Jerusalem encampment.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jerusalemnet.co.il/article/38429 עיר האוהלים הירושלמית מוקמת מול החומות - ירושלים נט]&lt;/ref&gt;

The protests were also joined by &quot;The Coalition for Affordable Housing&quot; and &quot;The Headquarters for a Liable Housing&quot; who bind the following organizations: [[Association for Civil Rights in Israel]], [[Bimkom]], [[Women Lawyers for Social Justice]], [[Society for the Protection of Nature in Israel]], [[Movement for Quality Government in Israel]], [[Greenpeace|Greenpeace Israel]], [[Mizrahi Democratic Rainbow Coalition]] and the [[Israel Union for Environmental Defense]]. Additional organizations who joined the protests include the &quot;Koach La Ovdim&quot; General trade union, the Socialist–Zionist youth movements [[HaNoar HaOved VeHaLomed]] and [[Hashomer Hatzair]], the non-Zionist left-wing organization [[Ma'avak Sotzialisti]] the Israeli human rights organization [[Rabbis for Human Rights]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://rhr.org.il/heb/?page_id=4&amp;event_id=13 שומרי משפט – רבנים למען זכויות האדם]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Physicians for Human Rights-Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.acri.org.il/he/?p=14471 מאבק הדיור: חשש שהרשויות מנסות לרסק את המחאה | האגודה לזכויות האזרח בישראל]&lt;/ref&gt; and the political parties [[Meretz]] and [[Hadash]].

The protests also gained the support of various Israeli mayors and local councils, including the mayor of Tel Aviv [[Ron Huldai]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.calcalist.co.il/home/0,7340,L-3369,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; the mayor of Jerusalem [[Nir Barkat]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mako.co.il/news-israel/local/Article-8f84911717e2131004.htm חדשות 2 - ראש עיריית ירושלים: &quot;על הממשלה לייצר דיור בר השגה&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; and the chairman of the Union of Local Authorities in Israel, [[Shlomo Bohbot]]. Knesset members from both the coalition and the opposition have expressed their support for the struggle; some even visited the various protest encampments. Two weeks after the start of the protest, the chairman of the [[Histadrut]], [[Ofer Eini]], met with protest leaders and announced that the Histadrut would assist them in their contacts with the government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globes.co.il/news/article.aspx?did=1000667958 עיני למפגיני האוהלים: &quot;נשתף עמכם פעולה&quot; - גלובס]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Jimmy Wales]], a co-founder of [[Wikipedia]], visited the tent cities in Tel Aviv where the protests were taking place. He said, &quot;It's wonderful that in the democracy here, people have the right to go out and express their opinion. I do not know if I agree with the protest or not, because I'm not familiar with the economic and social situation in Israel, but the very fact that freedom of speech and discourse are free in Israel is remarkable.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=232838 Wikipedia founder visits Tel Aviv's tent city&lt;/ref&gt;

== Public opinion ==
According to a poll by Channel 10 on 2 August 2011, there is broad public support for the protesters, including 98% of Kadima supporters, and 85% of Netanyahu's Likud supporters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=819412|title=סקר: 85% ממצביעי הליכוד ו-78% מש&quot;ס - תומכים במחאה החברתית|trans_title=Survey: 85% of Likud voters and 78% of Shas - support social protest|language=Hebrew|publisher=Nana 10|last=נדב|first=פרי|date=2 August 2011|accessdate=9 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with the massive support the housing protest has gained, as the protest kept developing and, various public figures and organizations, mostly affiliated with the political right in Israel, gradually increased their criticism of the protests and their organizers. Most of the criticism has focused on the allegations that the protests were not spontaneous, and that they were scheduled and planned by various left-wing media and political organizations in Israel. It is alleged that these organizations exploited the protests initiated by [[Daphne Leef]] as well as the economic distress that exists among large sections of the Israeli public in order to promote a political agenda that they finance, and which is primarily designed to overthrow the current right-wing government headed by [[Benjamin Netanyahu]]; it is alleged that finding actual solutions to the housing crises in Israel is only a secondary concern.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news1.co.il/Archive/003-D-62157-00.html חדשות מחלקה ראשונה - News1: מחאת האוהלים: הקול של יעקב והידיים של עשו]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.news1.co.il/Archive/003-D-62225-00.html חדשות מחלקה ראשונה - News1: מפגיני הדיור - 'אידיוטים מועילים']&lt;/ref&gt; The Tel-Aviv city hall was criticized for indirectly supporting the protests at 40,000ILS per day, price including electricity and clean services.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4106714,00.html |title=עולה עולה לנו: 40 אלף שקל לכל יום &quot;מהפכה&quot; |trans_title=It costs us: 40 000 shekel for each day of the revolution |language=Hebrew |publisher=Ynet |last=Zaitun |first=Yoav |date=9 August 2005 |accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  While the protests in general have been peaceful, some incidents of violence have been reported. On 4 August 2011, two activists were arrested following an attempt to burn down the tent of right-wing activists participating at the Rothschild location.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.walla.co.il/?w=/10/1847488|title=חשד: פעילים הציתו מאהל ימין בשד' רוטשילד|trans_title=Suspicion: Activists set right-wing tent on fire on Rothschild Boulevard|language=Hebrew|publisher=Walla!|last=Valinitz|first=Boaz|date=4 August 2011|accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4104649,00.html|title=Housing protest: Rightist tent torched |publisher=Ynetnews|last=Fyler|first=Boaz|date=4 August 2011|accessdate=17 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At a press conference held on July 26, 2011 Daphne Leef responded to the various allegations made against her and the protest organizers and stated the following:&lt;ref name=autogenerated6&gt;[http://www.mako.co.il/news-military/politics/Article-c2bb973cbd66131004.htm&amp;sCh=31750a2610f26110&amp;pId=2082585621 חדשות 2 - פרסום ראשון: אריה דרעי סירב להצטרף פומבית למחאת המאהלים]&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cquote|What hasn't been said about me in the recent days? When we came here with our tents about ten days ago, some said we are spoiled children from Tel Aviv, some said we are leftists, but after more cities from across the country and as more people from across the entire political spectrum in Israel joined the protests — all understood that we represent all the people.&lt;ref name=autogenerated6 /&gt;}}

== Responses ==
=== Political ===
* The mayor of Jerusalem [[Nir Barkat]] stated that &quot;the government must produce affordable housing&quot; and that &quot;I expect the government and the [[Israel Lands Administration]] to take responsibility for the matter.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;mayor&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=ראש עיריית ירושלים: &quot;על הממשלה לייצר דיור בר השגה&quot;|url=http://reshet.ynet.co.il/חדשות/News/Domestic/internal/Article,73435.aspx|date=15 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2011|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Mayor of Jerusalem, &quot;the government to produce affordable housing,&quot;|publisher=ynet.co.il|work=חדשות 2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barkat pointed to the model which was pioneered by the Jerusalem Municipality, which allows young people to live in affordable housing in Jerusalem.&lt;ref name=&quot;mayor&quot; /&gt;

* The mayor of Tel Aviv [[Ron Huldai]] also declared that &quot;the tent demonstrations are justified and appropriate&quot; and that &quot;the [central] government is abandoning social issues to market forces.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.calcalist.co.il/home/0,7340,L-3369,00.html{{Dead link|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Member of Parliament#Israel|MK]] [[Nitzan Horowitz]] of Meretz showed his support in the protests and referred to the protesters as &quot;the new homeless people of Netanyahu and [[Finance Minister of Israel|Finance Minister]] [[Yuval Steinitz]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=מחאת האוהלים – ההומלסים של נתניהו ושטייניץ|url=http://www.news1.co.il/Archive/001-D-272940-00.htm|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Protest tents – the homeless of Netanyahu and Steinitz|date=14 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fellow MK [[Isaac Herzog]] of the [[Israeli Labor Party|Labour party]] stated that &quot;all efforts to encourage affordable housing construction in Tel Aviv fail due to the resistance of the Israeli Finance ministry, the Israel Lands Administration, the Israeli ministers and due to the position of the prime minister against government intervention of market prices,&quot; and that &quot;it's time to examine an intervention.&quot; Herzog also stated that &quot;you deserve not only [[The Cottage boycott|to eat cottage]], but also to build a cottage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=קבלת שבת במאהל: &quot;זו יריית הפתיחה, לא נזוז&quot;|url=http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4095848,00.html|language=Hebrew|trans_title=Shabbat encampment: &quot;This is the opening shot, do not go&quot;|date=16 July 2011|accessdate=27 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Protest organizers and opposition MKs such as [[Shelly Yachimovich]] of the [[Israeli Labor Party|Labor]] party dismissed Prime Minister Netanyahu's proposed reforms as &quot;spin&quot;, and accused the Prime Minister of using the housing crisis as a cover to advance his program of land privatization.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=231036 |title=Yachimovich: State ownership is Zionist, not market failure |publisher=jpost.com |date=2011-07-26 |accessdate=2011-07-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, green organizations have warned that Netanyahu's proposals would lead to the destruction of open spaces in the centre of the country by land developers, and the removal of community input into the land development process.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/news/a-warning-to-the-tent-dwellers-before-netanyahu-presents-his-housing-plan-1.375250 |title=A warning to the tent dwellers before Netanyahu presents his housing plan |publisher=haaretz.com |date=25 July 2011 |accessdate=26 July 2011|author=Yossi Sarid}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* Knesset Speaker [[Reuven Rivlin]] announced that it is necessary to keep a [[free market]] in Israel and to be careful that the protest activists won't lead Israel towards the path of destruction and [[anarchy]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.walla.co.il/?w=/1/1846374 מחאת האוהלים | יו&quot;ר הכנסת ראובן ריבלין: &quot;מזהה ניצני אנרכיה&quot; - וואלה! חדשות]&lt;/ref&gt;

* Israeli minister [[Benny Begin]] also criticized the protests, stating that it is a political struggle &quot;with speech writers&quot;, aimed at overthrowing the Prime Minister of Israel, under the guise of protesting housing issues which &quot;did not develop recently, and which would not be solved any time soon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.walla.co.il/?w=/22/1846369 מחאת האוהלים| בני בגין: יש גורמים פוליטיים המקדמים המחאה - וואלה! חדשות]&lt;/ref&gt; Another government minister, [[Yuli Edelstein]] stated that among the organizers there are &quot;anarchists associated with the [[Communist Party]], Little [[fox]]es whom hang out along the protesters. They call Israel a [[fascist]] state, and this just shows how much they do not care for the protests.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated5&gt;[http://www.mako.co.il/news-military/politics/Article-1372d95e7698131004.htm חדשות 2 - הליכוד תוקף: &quot;המפגינים בזויים, אנרכיסטים וקומוניסטים&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

* David Amar, the Mayor of [[Nesher]], attacked the inhabitants of the encampment in Rothschild stating that &quot;You're going through the Rothschild boulevard in at 1:30 AM and all you can see is [[Hookah]]s and [[sushi]]. If they bring Sushi worth 35 NIS to the encampment - it indicates that their situation is not particularly difficult. This is not a protest&quot;.&lt;ref name=autogenerated5 /&gt;

* Knesset member [[Miri Regev]] has stated that Daphne Leef &quot;represents the extreme left&quot;.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4&gt;[http://www.israelhayom.co.il/site/newsletter_article.php?id=12053 ישראל היום]&lt;/ref&gt; In response, Leef stated that she felt embarrassed about the violent confrontation which occurred during Regev's visit to the encampment; however, Leef emphasized that contrary to Regev's belief, the protests were first and foremost a social struggle and not a political one.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=815348 נענע10 - נתניהו על מחאת הנדלן: הממשלה עושה דברים לתיקון הנגע - חדשות]&lt;/ref&gt;

* On July 20, 2011, &quot;[[Im Tirtzu]]&quot; (אם תרצו) announced that they would not take part in the housing protests any more because they claimed that the [[New Israel Fund]] and various radical left-wing groups are directly involved in the housing protests. Officials in the organization Stated that &quot;Daphne Leef's struggle, who is perceived in the media as the initiator of the struggle, is actually a video editor working for the NIF and Shatil.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.inn.co.il/News/News.aspx/223078 הקשר בין הקרן החדשה למאהל המחאה - בארץ - חדשות - ערוץ 7]&lt;/ref&gt;

* In September 2011, Knesset member [[Aryeh Eldad]] said that 'there is no doubt that the extreme-left and post-zionists are funding the protests. The thousands who are protesting their plight do not understand that they are marionettes in a game larger than housing costs and baby strollers'.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.israelhayom.co.il/site/newsletter_article.php?id=12727 ישראל היום - &quot;אנחנו הישראלים החדשים&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[Shimon Sheves]], former General Director of the [[Office of the Prime Minister (Israel)|Office of the Prime Minister]] under [[Yitzhak Rabin]] and former [[Israeli Labor Party]] activist, confirmed that a new political party was being formed in the aftermath of the summer protests but refused to reveal names other than that it would be people from the National Left organization. Disenchanted with the Labor party, he affirmed that he would stand behind the new party. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=&quot;תקום מפלגה חברתית שתשבור את הימין&quot;| url=http://www.nrg.co.il/online/1/ART2/284/666.html?hp=1&amp;cat=404 |language=Hebrew|trans_title=A social party will be created to break the right-wing|date=13 September 2011| author=Shalom Yerushalmi| publisher=Maariv| accessdate=21 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Religious figures ===
* The prominent Israeli [[modern orthodox]] [[rabbi]] [[Yuval Sherlo]] stated that in his opinion the protest movement has become anarchist in nature and therefore he personally finds it difficult to relate with it. He stated that the protest organizers need to change course: &quot;After a big burst of justified pain and anger, without which the troubling issues would not have not been brought up on to the agenda, the protests have been exhausted&quot;. Sherlo stated that despite the wide public criticism raised against the Netanyahu government, &quot;this government has done quite a few good things to promote ​​employment, balance payments, and is responsible for the fact that Israel's macro-economic situation is quite good&quot;. Later on, Sherlo gave a speech in the movement's protest rally in Jerusalem in which he called on Prime Minister Netanyahu &quot;to embrace these people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ynet.co.il/articles/0,7340,L-4105209,00.html&lt;/ref&gt;

* On August 16, 2011 prominent Israeli [[Orthodox Judaism|orthodox]] [[rabbi]] [[Israel Meir Lau]], who is the former [[Ashkenazi Jews|Ashkenazi]] [[Chief Rabbinate of Israel|Chief Rabbi of Israel]] and current [[Chief Rabbi]] of [[Tel Aviv]], held a discussion on the ongoing protests with representatives from the National Union of Israeli Students at the offices of the Rabbinate in Tel Aviv. Lau noted that the protest movement is unprecedented in Israel, and added that &quot;this is the first time I remember ever having seen this many people who didn’t know each other before, coming together – outside of a time of war. You have captured my heart.&quot; In addition, Lau promised to contact Prime Minister Netanyahu personally and tell him to honor the mandate of the Trachtenberg committee and accept its recommendations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/JewishWorld/JewishNews/Article.aspx?id=233988]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Media ===
* [[Ben-Dror Yemini]], an editor at [[Maariv]], used his 26 August 2011 weekend column to report a strong left-wing turn of the protests that would attempt to connect the 'social justice' to the events leading up to anticipated September protests on the West Bank. Yemini revealed an agreement summarized after protest leaders met with left-wing leaders and anarchists including the heads of [[The National Left]] and [[Peace Now]] to discuss combining activities such as marches to the 'border' and to bring the Palestinians into the protest.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.nrg.co.il/app/index.php?do=blog&amp;encr_id=f2b4c1b55be76d1e6d7b777256ea0370&amp;id=2785&lt;/ref&gt;

* Shay Golden, the assistant editor in chief of Maariv and former editor at the Haaretz newspaper has said that he has been made an enemy of the protests since he criticized the media coverage. He accused his media colleagues of forgetting their journalistic responsibilities and subsequtnly becoming spokespeople for the protests, and silencing opposing voices.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://media.nana10.co.il/Article/?ArticleID=827518&amp;sid=217 |date=6 September 2011|accessdate=6 September 2011 |language=Hebrew|title=שי גולדן על הסיקור התקשורתי של המחאה: &quot;אנשים שכחו את תפקידם העיתונאי&quot; |trans_title=Golden on the media coverage of the protests: &quot;People have forgotten their jobs as journalists&quot;  |first=David|last=Avraham|publisher=Maariv}}{{he icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{unclearsection|date=September 2011}}
* [[Yair Lapid]], a journalist and television personality, has supported the protest since its first days. During the second week of the protest, he published an article in his weekly [[Yedioth Ahronoth]] column titled &quot;The Slaves Revolt&quot; (a pun on Ayn Rand's [[Atlas Shrugged]] titled in Israel The Titans Revolt Mered Hanefilim, מרד הנפילים), where he sympathized with the protestors and implicitly blamed the Netanyahu government for its unjust allocation of resources. A month later, he had published a draft for a social contract, defined as an attempt to phrase the principles of a new, civil agenda. The contract, based on the [[Ten Commandments]], called for anti ostentation and exaggerated emphasis of the differences between rich and poor, and protestation against the greediness of large corporations who only care about the bottom line &lt;ref&gt;http://צדקחברתי.org.il/index.php?title=%D7%9E%D7%97%D7%90%D7%AA_%D7%A6%D7%93%D7%A7_%D7%97%D7%91%D7%A8%D7%AA%D7%99#.D7.94.D7.AA.D7.A7.D7.A9.D7.95.D7.A8.D7.AA&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Israeli housing crisis]]
*[[Impact of the Arab Spring]]
*[[15 October 2011 global protests]]
* [[Kitchenware Revolution|Iceland Kitchenware Revolution]]
*[[2010–2011 Greek protests]]
*[[2011 Spanish protests|Spanish 15M Indignants movement]]
*[[2011 United Kingdom anti-austerity protests]]
*[[2011 Chilean protests]]
*[[Occupy Wall Street]]
*[[&quot;Occupy&quot; protests]]
*[[Protests of 1968]]

== External links==
{{Wikinews|Protests over housing costs sweep across Israel}}
{{Commons category|2011 Israeli housing protests|Category:2011 Israeli housing protests}}
* [http://j14.org.il The official website of the protest organizers] (Hebrew)
* [http://www.facebook.com/J14.Israel The protests Facebook page]
* [http://www.shatil.org.il/english/shatil-israel-new-awakening/ Shatil and Israel's New Awakening]

; Collected coverage
* [http://www.jpost.com/Israel/Home.aspx Social justice protests] collected coverage at ''[[Jerusalem Post]]''
* [http://www.haaretz.com/meta/Tag/Israel%20housing%20protest Israeli housing protests] collected coverage at ''[[Haaretz]]''

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{Protests in Israel}}
{{Anti-government protests in the 21st century|state=collapsed}}

[[Category:2011 in Israel]]
[[Category:2011 in economics]]
[[Category:Housing in Israel]]
[[Category:Politics of Israel]]
[[Category:2011 Israeli housing protests]]
[[Category:2011 in international relations]]
[[Category:Arab Spring]]
[[Category:Impact of the Arab Spring]]
[[Category:2011 protests|Israeli social justice]]


[[ar:احتجاجات الإسكان الإسرائيلية 2011]]
[[de:Proteste in Israel 2011]]
[[es:Protestas sociales en Israel de 2011]]
[[fr:Mouvement israélien pour des logements accessibles]]
[[he:מחאת האוהלים]]
[[ru:Палаточный протест в Израиле (2011)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
