<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Splot (video game)" to="Humble Indie Bundle" tofragment="Humble Frozenbyte Bundle" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="27311422" ns="0" title="Humble Indie Bundle"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Humble Indie Bundles''' or '''Humble Bundles''' are a series of game bundles, that are sold and [[online distribution|distributed online]] at a [[Pay what you want|price determined by the purchaser]]. The games are [[Cross-platform|multi-platform]], [[digital rights management|DRM]]-free, and [[Independent video game development|independently developed]], and buyers can set the revenue split between the developers, charities and humble bundle organizers.

The first bundle was organized and managed by [[Wolfire Games]].  Beginning with the second bundle a separate company spun-off, Humble Bundle, Inc., with the sole purpose of making bundles.  The bundles are made available for purchase during limited time frames. Purchasers are able to set how much they wish to pay for the bundles and how they want their money to be distributed between the games' developers and two charities: [[Child's Play (charity)|Child's Play]] and the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]]. The games in the bundles run on [[Microsoft Windows]], [[Mac OS X]], and [[Linux]]-based systems and are [[downloadable content|digitally distributed]] initially without digital rights management (DRM) controls.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wired.com/gamelife/2010/05/humble-bundle/ | title = Name Your Own Price for World of Goo, Other Indie Games | first = Gus | last  =Mastrapa | date = 2010-05-04 | accessdate=  2010-05-10 | work = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the bundles are still advertised as DRM-free, three recently included games require [[product key]]s for their multi-player modes, generally considered a form of DRM.  Seven bundle drives have been held to date, breaking over $7 million in total sale and charitable donations. &lt;!-- charity amounts go here when Wolfire gives #s for HIB2--&gt;

==Concept==
[[File:Humble indie bundle creatores gdc 2011.jpg|thumb|right|[[Wolfire Games]]' John Graham (right) and Jeffrey Rosen (left) relate their experiences with the Humble Indie Bundle at the 2011 [[Game Developers Conference]]]]
The idea for the Bundle was from Jeff Rosen of [[Wolfire Games]].&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2010/05/the-greatest-indie-game-sale-ever-and-how-it-came-to-be.ars | title = Humble Bundle: greatest sale of indie games ever? | first = Michael | last = Thompson | date = 2010-05-04 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | publisher = Ars Technica}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen describes the inspiration coming to him through similar sales of bundle packages on the [[Steam (software)|Steam platform]].&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt; Rosen had noted that such sales would have viral word-of-mouth spread across the Internet.&lt;ref name=&quot;humble gdc&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/33272/GDC_2011_Humble_Indie_Bundle_Creators_Talk_Inspiration_Execution.php | title = GDC 2011: Humble Indie Bundle Creators Talk Inspiration, Execution | first = Kyle | last = Orland | date = 2011-02-28 | accessdate  =2011-02-28 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Influence also came from a previous &quot;pay-what-you-want&quot; sale for ''World of Goo'' upon the title's first anniversary;&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2009/10/2d-boy-continuing-pay-what-you-want-sale.ars | title = 2D Boy continuing &quot;pay what you want&quot; sale for World of Goo | publisher = Ars Technica | date = 2009-10-20 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | first = Michael | last = Thompson }}&lt;/ref&gt; over 57,000 copies of the game were purchased during this sale, generating over US$117,000 after considering [[PayPal]] handling fees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.shacknews.com/onearticle.x/60952 | title = Results of 2D Boy's 'Pay What You Want' World of Goo Sales Experiment Released | publisher = [[Shacknews]] | date = 2009-10-21 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | first = Nick | last = Breckon }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pcworld.com/article/195778/pay_what_you_like_say_indie_game_makers.html | title = Pay What You Like, Say Indie Game Makers | date = 2010-05-06 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | first = Jared | last = Newman | work = [[PC World (magazine)|PC World]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen by this point was well connected with other [[independent video game development|independent developers]], for example his brother David is listed as being a game tester for the [[Penumbra (video game series)|''Penumbra'' series]], and ''Penumbra's'' composer [[Mikko Tarmia]] is now contributing to Wolfire Games' upcoming game project ''[[Overgrowth]]''. Wolfire had also recently teamed with [[Unknown Worlds Entertainment]] to offer a bundle based on their ''[[Natural Selection 2]]'' game.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt; The porter of ''Lugaru'' to Linux was [[Ryan C. Gordon]], who was also responsible for porting ''[[Aquaria (video game)|Aquaria]]'' to Linux. With his close ties to these independent developers, as well as [[Ron Carmel]] of [[2D Boy]], Rosen was able to assemble the package, taking advantage of merchant sales systems offered by PayPal, [[Amazon Payments]], and [[Google Checkout]] to minimize the cost of transactions and distribution.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt;

Though achieving word of mouth was a key element of the potential success of the bundle, Rosen also recognized that the process to purchase the Bundles had to be simple; including elements like user account registration or the use of a secondary download client would have potentially driven away sales.&lt;ref name=&quot;humble gdc&quot;/&gt; Rosen also sought to include charities in the bundle, allowing the purchaser to choose how to distribute the funds between the developers and charities. Rosen believed Child's Play was a worthwhile cause that brought video games to hospitalized children and helped to fight the stigma of video games, while he selected the Electronic Frontier Foundation to support their anti-DRM stance.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt; The means of &quot;pay-what-you-want&quot; would allow purchasers to simply give the money to the charities, but Rosen felt this was not an issue and would &quot;consider that a success&quot; of the sale.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech&quot;/&gt; Rosen and Wolfire employee John Graham provided technical support during the sales, handling thousands of requests through a few all-night email and chat sessions.&lt;ref name=&quot;humble gdc&quot;/&gt;

==History==
===Humble Indie Bundle #1===

* ''[[World of Goo]]'' ([[2D Boy]])
* ''[[Aquaria (video game)|Aquaria]]'' (Bit Blot)
* ''[[Gish (video game)|Gish]]'' ([[Edmund McMillen]])
* ''[[Penumbra: Overture]]'' ([[Frictional Games]])
* ''[[Lugaru]]'' ([[Wolfire Games]])

Bonus Game:
* ''[[Samorost 2]]'' ([[Amanita Design]])

The first Humble Indie Bundle went on sale from May 4 through May 11, 2010. Furthermore, three studios offered a further incentive for purchasers during the sale, in that if more than US$1 million was raised by the effort, the [[source code]] for ''Gish'', ''Penumbra'' and ''Lugaru'' would then be offered.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;/&gt;. Midway through the sale period, Wolfire Games was approached by [[Amanita Design]] studios, who wanted to help contribute to the cause in their own way, by donating their game ''[[Samorost 2]]'' to the bundle, allowing those that already had purchased the bundle to further download that title.&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.wired.com/gamelife/2010/05/humble-indie-bundle/ | title = More Games, Source Code Join ‘Humble Indie Bundle’ | first= Gus | last = Mastrapa | date = 2010-05-10 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | work = [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Imageframe|width=250|content=[[File:Humblebundlebycount.png|250px]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Humblebundlebydonation.png|250px]]|caption=Sales breakdown across systems of the first Humble Indie Bundle by the number of donations (top) and dollar value of the donations (bottom)|align=right}}
The promotion was met with what the organisers described as a strong success, achieving more than US$1 million in sales within the week from approximately 116,000 donations.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamasutra&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/28471/Humble_Indie_Bundle_Charity_Drive_Approaches_700000.php | title = 'Humble Indie Bundle' Charity Drive Approaches $700,000 | first = Kris | last = Graft | date =2010-05-10 | accessdate =2010-05-10 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boingboing&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.boingboing.net/2010/05/11/humble-indie-bundles.html| title = Humble Indie Bundle hits $1m, goes open-source, gets 4 day extension | publisher = [[Boing Boing]] | date =2010-05-11 | accessdate = 2010-05-11 | first = Brandon | last=  Boyer }}&lt;/ref&gt; After the extension, the total amount of money raised by the effort was in excess of $1,270,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;techdirt final&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.techdirt.com/blog/entrepreneurs/articles/20100518/0844299463.shtml | title = Some Final Stats On The Humble Indie Bundle | first = Mike | last = Masnick | date = 2010-05-19 | accessdate = 2010-05-24 | publisher = [[Techdirt]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Based on the distribution set by users, the two charities received about 31% of the total money raised, while each of the five developers saw an average of US$166,000 in sales.&lt;ref name=&quot;boingboing&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;techdirt final&quot;/&gt; About half of the sales were to Microsoft Windows platforms, while the MacOS X and Linux sales roughly equally split the rest. By tracking pricing, Wolfire Games found that Linux users were the most generous, paying about US$14 per bundle, followed by MacOS X users (US$10) and Windows users (US$7–8).&lt;ref name=&quot;gamasutra&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/technology/shanerichmond/100005089/are-linux-users-more-generous-than-windows-users/ | title = Are Linux users more generous than Windows users?  | first = Shane | last= Richmond | date =2010-05-07 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | work = [[The Daily Telegraph]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen noted the presence of donations as large as $3333 and $[[Leet|1337]] near the final hours of the sale, and believes social link-sharing sites like [[Reddit]] helped them to reach the $1 million milestone.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech after&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/guides/2010/05/with-1-million-raised-humble-bundle-games-go-open-source.ars | title = With &gt;$1 million raised, Humble Bundle games go open source | first = Ben | last = Kuchera | date = 2010-05-12 | accessdate = 2010-05-12 | publisher = Ars Technica }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of reaching the US$1 million goal, the source code for the game engines for ''Gish'', ''Penumbra'', ''Lugaru'', and, due to the overwhelming success, ''Aquaria'', was made available under the [[GNU General Public License]]; art, music, and other creative assets for these games were not included.&lt;ref name=&quot;boingboing&quot;/&gt; Wolfire also extended the offer on the sale for an additional four days.&lt;ref name=&quot;boingboing&quot;/&gt;

While many of the included games were available on Valve's [[Steam (software)|Steam]] platform, the bundle was not initially integrated with Steam. On December 9, 2010, seven months after the bundle's release, a Steam [[product key]] was emailed to purchasers of the bundle that allowed most of the bundle to be downloaded from Steam.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolf_blog&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.wolfire.com/2010/12/Activate-the-Humble-Indie-Bundle-on-Steam | title = Activate the Humble Indie Bundle on Steam - Wolfire Games Blog | first = John | last = Graham | date = 2010-12-09 | accessdate=  2010-12-09 | work = [[Wolfire Games]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; This made downloading and playing the bundle more convenient for Steam users and also allowed Steam users to collect Steam [[achievement (video gaming)|achievement]]s from the bundle games that implemented them. ''Samorost 2'' was added to the Steam accounts of those who had redeemed their codes for the Humble Indie Bundle on June 1, 2011.

===Humble Indie Bundle #2===

* ''[[Braid (video game)|Braid]]'' ([[Jonathan Blow]]/Number None Studios)
* ''[[Cortex Command]]'' (Data Realms LLC)
* ''[[Machinarium]]'' ([[Amanita Design]])
* ''[[Osmos]]'' (Hemisphere Games)
* ''[[Revenge of the Titans]]'' (Puppy Games).

With the success of the first bundle, a second Humble Indie Bundle was launched on December 14, 2010, featuring a new set of five games from independent developers. Charitable donations continued to go towards Child's Play and the Electronic Frontier Foundation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/106100-Get-Into-the-Holiday-Spirit-With-the-Humble-Indie-Bundle-2 | title = Get Into the Holiday Spirit With the Humble Indie Bundle #2 | first = Mike| last = Thompson | date = 2010-12-14 | accessdate = 2010-12-14 | work = [[Escapist (Magazine)|Escapist]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new bundle included the launch of new [[Linux]] ports for ''[[Braid (video game)|Braid]]'' and ''[[Cortex Command]]'', while another game ''Revenge of the Titans'' was first made available for all three platforms as part of the bundle.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech hib2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2010/12/humble-bundle-2-is-live-5-great-games-no-drm-pay-what-you-want.ars | title = Humble Bundle 2 is live: 5 great games, no DRM, pay what you want | first = Ben | last = Kuchera | date = 2010-12-14 | accessdate = 2010-12-14 | publisher = Ars Technica }}&lt;/ref&gt; While Wolfire Studios is still hosting and managing the sale and post-sale downloads, they do not have any games in the bundle; instead, they have allowed for purchasers to tip Wolfire while paying for the games in the bundle.&lt;ref name=&quot;atlantic hib2&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.theatlantic.com/culture/archive/2010/12/beyond-radiohead-video-games-one-up-the-pay-what-you-want-model/67921/ | title = Beyond Radiohead: Video Games One-Up the Pay-What-You-Want Model | work = [[The Atlantic]] | date = 2010-12-14 | accessdate = 2010-12-14 | first = Sam | last = Machkovech }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The second Bundle was able to break $500,000 in sales within one day, including a 
$2,000 donation from ''[[Minecraft]]'' creator [[Markus Persson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.1up.com/news/humble-indie-bundle-2-sales-surpass-half-million-one-day | title = Humble Indie Bundle 2 Sales Surpass $500,000 in One Day | first = Chris | last = Pereira | date = 2010-12-15 | accessdate = 2010-12-15 | publisher = [[1UP.com]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sales surpassed $1 million about 5 days into the sale, upon which purchasers were able to unlock the games on Steam and the [[Desura]] digital download service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://news.bigdownload.com/2010/12/19/humble-indie-bundle-2-reaches-1-milllion-mark-games-can-be-red/ | title = Humble Indie Bundle 2 reaches $1 milllion mark; games can be redeemed on Steam | publisher = [[Big Download]] | date = 2010-12-19 | accessdate = 2010-12-19 | first = John  | last = Callaham }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.king5.com/news/technology/Name-your-own-price-for-computer-games-112173099.html | title = Name your own price for computer games  | first = Owen | last = Lei | date = 2010-12-20 | accessdate = 2010-12-20 | publisher = [[KING-TV]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; As a promotion for the second bundle the first bundle was added to all bundles that were purchased at that point and to all later purchases that contributed more than the average chosen price.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.wolfire.com/2010/12/Your-Humble-Bundle-just-doubled | title = Your Humble Indie Bundle just doubled | first = Jeffrey | last = Rosen | date = 2010-12-22 | accessdate = 2010-12-22 | publisher = Wolfire Blog}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the sale exceeded $1.75M, Puppy Games has also released the source code for ''Revenge of the Titans''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.boingboing.net/2010/12/23/humble-indie-bundle-3.html | title = Humble Indie Bundle 2 adds games from first bundle | first = Brandon | last = Boyer | date = 2010-12-23 | accessdate=  2010-12-24 | publisher = [[Boing Boing]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; under a BSD-like license while reserving all rights to almost all game assets. The sale cleared $1.8 million in sales after ten days of sales.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/106444-Heres-the-Final-Numbers-on-the-Humble-Indie-Bundle-2 | title = Here's the Final Numbers on the Humble Indie Bundle #2 | first = Mike | last = Thompson | date= 2010-12-27 | accessdate = 2011-01-05 | publisher = [[Escapist (magazine)|Escapist]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Similar to the first bundle, around 50% of the total donations were from MacOS X and Linux users, which Rosen later identified as a strong market for indie game developers.&lt;ref name=&quot;humble gdc&quot;/&gt;

===Humble Frozenbyte Bundle===
The third Humble Bundle sale started on April 12, 2011, and features five games from the indie developer [[Frozenbyte]], including ''[[Trine (video game)|Trine]]'', ''[[Shadowgrounds]]'', and ''[[Shadowgrounds Survivor]]'', for Microsoft Windows, MacOS X, and Linux. It also contained an executable version along with source code for an unfinished game, ''Jack Claw'', and a pre-order for their upcoming game, ''Splot''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://kotaku.com/#!5791097/this-might-be-the-best-indie-bargain-of-2011 | title = This Might Be The Best Indie Bargain Of 2011 | first = Luke | last = Plunkett | publisher = Kotaku | date = 2011-04-11 | accessdate = 2011-04-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Within three days of the launch of the sale, it had raised more than $550,000.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/34146/Humble_Frozenbyte_Bundle_Reaches_Over_576K_112K_Purchases.php | title = Humble Frozenbyte Bundle Reaches Over $576K, 112K Purchases | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] | first= Eric | last = Caoili | date =2011-04-15 | accessdate = 2011-04-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By April 22, 2011, the Bundle had surpassed $700,000, at which point Frozenbyte added the source code for both ''Shadowgrounds'' games, a level editor for ''Trine'', Mac OS and Linux versions of ''Jack Claw'' (in addition to the Windows version), and a demo for ''Splot''. The timeframe for purchasing this bundle ended at midnight on April 26, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;frozenbyte 700k&quot;&gt;{{cite web |  url =  http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/34254/Frozenbyte_Releases_Shadowgrounds_Source_Code_Trine_Level_Editor.php |  title = Frozenbyte Releases Shadowgrounds Source Code, Trine Level Editor | first = Frank | last=  Cifaldi | date = 2011-04-22| accessdate = 2011-04-22 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As to the origins of the third bundle, Frozenbyte had been considering raising money for its continued game development through a pay-what-you-want sale for quite some time, but was unsure how to implement such a payment and distribution system and were worried that if they attempted to do such a sale on their own it would not generate enough interest. Impressed by the previous bundles, they contacted John Graham and Jeffrey Rosen who agreed to the idea of making a bundle entirely composed of Frozenbyte titles.&lt;ref name=&quot;frozenbyte-ceo&quot;&gt;{{cite web |  url =  http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2011/04/humble-indie-bundle-3-focuses-on-one-dev-offers-unreleased-games.ars |  title = Humble Indie Bundle 3 focuses on one dev, offers unreleased games | first = Andrew | last=  Webster | date = 2011-04-14| accessdate = 2011-05-06 | publisher = Ars Technica }}&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the money generated by the sale will go to finishing the development of ''[[Trine 2]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;linuxgames&quot;&gt;{{cite web |  url =  http://www.linuxgames.com/archives/16904 |  title = HFB Update | first = Dustin | last= Reyes | date = 2011-04-27| accessdate = 2011-05-06 | publisher = [[LinuxGames]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Humble Indie Bundle #3===

* ''[[Crayon Physics Deluxe]]'' ([[Kloonigames]])
* ''[[Cogs (video game)|Cogs]]'' (Lazy 8 Studios)
* ''[[VVVVVV]]'' (Terry Cavanagh)
* ''[[Hammerfight]]'' (Kranx Productions)
* ''[[And Yet It Moves]]'' (Broken Rules)

Bonus Games:

* ''[[Steel Storm]]'' ([[Kot-in-Action Creative Artel]])
* ''[[Atom Zombie Smasher]]'' (Blendo Games)

The fourth Humble Bundle, but the third carrying the Indie title, was launched on July 26, 2011, featuring a new set of five games from independent developers. Charitable donations continued to go towards [[Child's Play (charity)|Child's Play]] and the [[Electronic Frontier Foundation]]. In the case of ''VVVVVV'', the game was not only updated to run on Linux machines, but featured a new completely rebuilt game engine in [[C++]] instead of on the [[Adobe Flash]] platform, and included a level editor and several levels submitted by other indie developers. These changes were prompted by the opportunity for ''VVVVVV'' to be featured as part of the upcoming bundle.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamasutra hib3 vvvvvv&quot;/&gt;  On August 1, 2011 the game ''[[Steel Storm]]'' was added as a &quot;Bonus Game&quot; for all who purchase the bundle.&lt;ref name=&quot;vg247 steelstorm&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.vg247.com/2011/08/01/steel-storm-burning-retribution-added-to-humble-indie-bundle-3/ | title= Steel Storm: Burning Retribution added to Humble Indie Bundle 3 | first =  Debabrata | last = Nath | date = 2011-08-01 | accessdate = 2011-08-01 | publisher = [[VG247]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Midway through the sale, purchasers were given the opportunity to play ''[[Minecraft]]'' until August 14, 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;vg247 steelstorm&quot;/&gt; On August 3, 2011, the Humble Indie Bundle #2 was given to those that had bought Bundle #3 before that date. To obtain it after that date, users must pay over the current Average, at the time they decide to purchase Bundle #3. On August 5th, 2011, ''[[Atom Zombie Smasher]]'' was added as a bonus game to anyone who purchased the Humble Indie Bundle 3.

Within 17 hours, the Bundle had broken $500,000 in total sales with over 107,000 bundles purchased, a significant improvement relative to the Frozenbyte bundle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/36120/Third_Humble_Indie_Bundle_See_105K_Downloads_500K_Sales_In_17_Hours.php | title = Third Humble Indie Bundle See 105K Downloads, $500K Sales In 17 Hours | first = Mike | last = Rose | date=  2011-07-27 | accessdate =2011-07-27 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; The sale broke $1 million less than a week from its onset.&lt;ref name=&quot;gamasutra hib3 vvvvvv&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/36306/Cavanaghs_VVVVVV_Lucked_Out_Humbly_Bundled_At_Last_Minute.php | title = Cavanagh's VVVVVV Lucked Out, Humbly Bundled At 'Last Minute' | first = Mike | last = Rose | date = 2011-08-02 | accessdate =2011-08-02 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Sales hit $2 million on August 8, finishing up with a grand total of $2,169,090.71.

===Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle===
On September 28, 2011, the Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle was announced. Originally the bundle only included the game ''[[Frozen Synapse]]''. On September 30, the game ''[[Trauma (video game)|Trauma]]'' was added as a free bonus;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/09/30/frozen-synapse-bundle-receives-some-trauma/ | title = Frozen Synapse bundle receives some Trauma | first = Rob | last = Zacny | date = 2011-09-30 | accessdate = 2011-10-05 | work = [[PC Gamer]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; the game ''[[SpaceChem]]'' was added in a similar manner on October 5.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.pcgamer.com/2011/10/05/spacechem-joins-the-humble-frozen-synapse-bundle/ | title = SpaceChem joins the Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle | first = Rob | last = Zacny | date = 2011-10-05 | accessdate = 2011-10-05 | work = [[PC Gamer]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Paying more than the average price would also entitle the purchaser to the Humble Frozenbyte Bundle games. The bundle closed with more than $1.1 million in total revenue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamepro.com/article/news/223915/humble-frozen-synapse-bundle-passes-1-million-mark | title = Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle Passes $1 Million Mark | first = Will | last = Herring | date = 2011-10-12 | accessdate = 2011-10-12 | publisher = [[Gamepro]] |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.gamepro.com/article/news/223915/humble-frozen-synapse-bundle-passes-1-million-mark&amp;date=2011-11-30+19:06:45|archivedate=2011-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Humble Voxatron Debut===
On October 31, 2011, the Humble Voxatron Debut was released. One game, ''[[Voxatron]]'' by [[Lexaloffle Games]], was initially included. The bundle ran for 14 days. At the time of the bundle's release, the game was labeled as ''Voxatron Alpha''. ''[[The Binding of Isaac (video game)|The Binding of Isaac]]'' and ''[[Blocks that Matter]]'' were added on the following day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blog.humblebundle.com/post/12201985676/humble-voxatron-debut-grows-by-two | title=Humble Voxatron Debut Grows by Two! | date=November 1, 2011 | accessdate=2011-11-01 | work=Humble Mumble}}&lt;/ref&gt; On November 9, 2011, four more games were added to the bundle as a free bonus, three from the developers of ''Voxatron'' - ''Zen Puzzle Garden'', ''[[Chocolate Castle]]'' and ''Jasper's Journeys'', and one co-developed by one of ''The Binding of Isaac'' developers, ''[[Gish (video game)|Gish]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blog.humblebundle.com/post/12582764151/gish-and-lexaloffle-minigames-added-to-the-humble | title=Gish and Lexaloffle minigames added to the Humble Voxatron Debut! | date=November 9, 2011 | accessdate=2011-11-09 | work=Humble Mumble}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At closing, the debut raised $902,453.

===Humble Introversion Bundle===
On November 22, 2011, the Humble Introversion Bundle was released. The bundle included four games by [[Introversion Software]]: ''[[Darwinia (video game)|Darwinia]]'', ''[[Multiwinia]]'', ''[[DEFCON (video game)|DEFCON]]'' and ''[[Uplink (video game)|Uplink]]''. If the average price was beaten, two more games were given to the buyer: ''[[Aquaria (video game)|Aquaria]]'' by [[Bit Blot]] and ''[[Crayon Physics Deluxe]]'' by [[Kloonigames]]. Two technology demos by Introversion were also included, for Windows only, one including destructible Voxel buildings, the other showing the procedural generation of a city.
On November 29, 2011, an additional game was added, ''[[Dungeons of Dredmor]]'' by [[Gaslamp Games]]. The source code of all the released Introversion games (excluding the technology demos) was also made available to the buyers. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blog.humblebundle.com/post/13505508267/new-goodies-for-the-humble-introversion-bundle | title=New Goodies for the Humble Introversion Bundle | date=November 29, 2011 | accessdate=2011-11-29 | work=Humble Mumble}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis==
=== Success ===
The first promotion was considered to be very successful. Rosen noted that they considered the million-dollar goal as a best-case scenario, but once the sale actually started, &quot;it was immediately clear that we were on to something&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech after&quot;/&gt; Rosen would later attribute part of the success to [[Ars Technica]] writer Mike Thomspon, stating that he &quot;immediately saw the potential&quot; of the Bundle in an article written for the website just prior to the Bundle's sale period.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2011/03/humble-bundle-creator-on-ars-influence-and-why-linux-is-important.ars | title = Humble Bundle creator on Ars' influence and why Linux is important | date = 2011-03-01 | accessdate = 2011-03-02 | first = Ben | last = Kuchera | publisher = Ars Technica}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brandon Boyer of [[Boing Boing]] believed that it provided a model that &quot;seems it could and should be repeated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;boingboing&quot;/&gt; The move to offer games in a price and manner that consumers were willing to buy was contrasted to larger software publishers that place artificial limitations on their content; Mike Masnick of [[Techdirt]] believed the Humble Bundle promotion worked as it &quot;focus[ed] on giving people real reasons to buy, rather than just feeling entitled to define the terms under which they buy and looking for ways to limit those who want to interact with you in a different manner&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.techdirt.com/blog/entrepreneurs/articles/20100511/1428089384.shtml | title = Humble Indie Bundle Hits One Million In Sales... Goes Open Source | publisher = [[Techdirt]] | first = Mike | last = Masnick | date =2010-05-11| accessdate = 2010-05-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The source for the promotion's website has been requested of Wolfire by several other groups, according to Rosen; Rosen continues that he believes that many similar charitable sales can be seen in the future from the Humble Bundle's success.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech after&quot;/&gt; For future Bundles, Rosen desires to include lesser-known titles in contrast to ''World of Goo'' and ''Braid'', but has had to already reject some developers' requests to be included in a Bundle, claiming the games' quality may tarnish the Humble Indie Bundle branding. Instead, he believes smaller games with no wide profile and are &quot;legitimately good&quot; would be ideal for inclusion in future Bundles.&lt;ref name=&quot;humble gdc&quot;/&gt;

In April 2011, it was announced that [[Sequoia Capital]] had provided venture capital of $4.7 million towards future Humble Indie Bundle development.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url  =http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/34255/Humble_Bundle_Backed_By_47_Million_In_Venture_Capital.php | title = Humble Bundle Backed By $4.7 Million In Venture Capital | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] | first = Frank | last = Cafaldi | first1= Kris | last2 = Graf | date = 2011-04-22 | accessdate = 2011-04-22 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Piracy ===
Despite the ability to get the games at nearly zero cost, Wolfire Games estimate that 25% of the traceable downloads for the first Bundle have come from [[Copyright infringement of software|software piracy]] by links provided in some forums that bypass the payment screen to access the games; Wolfire further surmises additional piracy occurred through [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]]-type peer-to-peer sharing services.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech piracy&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2010/05/humble-bundle-gives-pirates-what-they-want-gets-ripped-off.ars | title = Humble Bundle gives pirates what they want, gets ripped off | first = Ben | last = Kuchera | date = 2010-05-10 | accessdate = 2010-05-10 | publisher = Ars Technica}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen noted they purposely removed much of the DRM associated with games to appeal to those that would otherwise engage in software piracy, through both having the games ship without DRM and by having only limited copy protection on their website.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech piracy&quot;/&gt; Rosen also stated that for about ten users that emailed Wolfire about being unable to pay for the software, he personally donated on their behalf.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech piracy&quot;/&gt; Rosen comments that there may be legitimate reasons for those that appear to be pirating the game, including the inability to use the payment methods provided or that they had made a single large donation for multiple copies.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech piracy&quot;/&gt; However, he also considered that there are players that would simply forward the download links to &quot;take pleasure in spreading the pirated links to their friends or anonymous buddies for fun&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech piracy&quot;/&gt; Wolfire Games did take action to stop predatory sites, such as the closely named &quot;wollfire.com&quot;, from selling illegal copies of the bundle.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech ios&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url  = http://arstechnica.com/gaming/news/2011/02/halfbot-interview.ars/ | title = The clones cometh: the App Store is full of copycats, and it's indies who suffer | first = Andrew | last = Webster | date = 2011-02-16 | accessdate = 2011-02-16 | publisher = Ars Technica }}&lt;/ref&gt;

While aware of the presumed software piracy, Rosen says that Wolfire will take no steps to limit it, believing that &quot;making the download experience worse for generous contributors in the name of punishing pirates doesn't really fit with the spirit of the bundle&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/100576-Who-Would-Pirate-the-One-Cent-Humble-Indie-Bundle | title = Who Would Pirate the One-Cent Humble Indie Bundle? | first = Andy | last = Chalk | date = 2010-05-10 | accessdate= 2010-05-10 | publisher = [[The Escapist (magazine)|The Escapist]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rosen noted that by offering the source code of the games as an incentive, they would hope that &quot;the community will help build them up with the same vigor that crackers tear DRM down&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;arstech after&quot;/&gt; David Wong of ''[[Cracked (magazine)|Cracked]]'', in considering several reasons for the negative stereotypes for video game players, used the Humble Indie Bundle as an example of demonstrating the &quot;sense of entitlement&quot; that some video game players have, pointing to the high rate of piracy and use of bandwidth as alternatives to spending &quot;even one penny&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url  =http://www.cracked.com/article_18571_5-reasons-its-still-not-cool-to-admit-youre-gamer.html | title=5 Reasons It's Still Not Cool to Admit You're a Gamer  | work = [[Cracked (magazine)|Cracked]] | date = 2010-05-24 | accessdate =2010-05-24 | first = David | last = Wong }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In preparing for the second Humble Indie Bundle sale, John Graham acknowledged that some may still download the game through illegal means, but also said that the organizers of the bundle gave their best effort to make the process of purchasing the games simple, and they also wished to create a social impact with the sales by including contributions to Child's Play and the Electronic Frontier Foundation.&lt;ref name=&quot;atlantic hib2&quot;/&gt; An anonymous survey conducted by Wolfire for those who felt it necessary to acquire the second Bundle from other illegitimate sources showed that some preferred the option of using peer-to-peer sharing services like [[BitTorrent (protocol)|BitTorrent]] to improve the speed and reliability of the download; as a result, Wolfire added the option to download the games through BitTorrent, hoping to entice more people to acquire the game legitimately.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.wolfire.com/2010/12/Download-the-Humble-Indie-Bundle-2-using-BitTorrent | title=  Download the Humble Indie Bundle #2 using BitTorrent | first  = David | last = Rosen | date= 2010-12-24 | accessdate = 2010-12-28 | publisher = [[Wolfire Games]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Software &quot;counterfeits&quot;===
Several games in the Humble Indie Bundles have been released as [[open-source]] software as a result of the Bundles reaching certain sales levels.  One such game was Wolfire's own ''[[Lugaru HD]]'', where they released the engine under the [[GNU General Public License]], and also included the various art assets, level designs, and other creative elements under a freely redistributable license for personal use.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.wolfire.com/2010/05/Lugaru-goes-open-source | title =  Lugaru goes open-source | first = David | last = Rosen | date = 2010-05-11 | accessdate = 2011-02-03 | publisher = [[Wolfire Games]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Their intent was to allow programmers to experiment and improve the game's engine using the associated assets.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfire counterfeit&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.wolfire.com/2011/02/Counterfeit-Lugaru-on-Apple-s-App-Store-developing | title = Counterfeit Lugaru on Apple's App Store (developing) | first = Jeffery | last = Rosen | date = 2011-02-03 | accessdate = 2011-02-03 | publisher = [[Wolfire Games]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wolfire later began selling the title ''Lugaru HD'' on the Mac App Store for $9.99. However, some time afterwards, another company, iCoder, used the open-source resources to recreate the same game for the App Store, charging only $0.99 for their version ''Lugaru''. iCoder claims they have the right to recreate and charge for the game under the GNU license, but Jeffery Rosen notes that this did not apply to the art assets.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfire counterfeit&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =  http://kotaku.com/5750238/the-case-of-the-identical-rabbit-games | title = The Case Of The Identical Rabbit Games | first = Stephan | last = Tolito | date = 2011-02-02 | accessdate = 2011-02-03 | publisher = Kotaku }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =  http://www.gamesindustry.biz/articles/2011-02-03-humble-indie-bundle-dev-suffers-illegal-game-cloning | title = Humble Indie Bundle dev suffers &quot;illegal&quot; game cloning | date = 2011-02-03 | accessdate = 2011-02-03 | first = Alec | last = Meer | publisher = [[GamesIndustry.biz]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the GPL license is not compatible with Apple's AppStore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=More about the App Store GPL Enforcement|url=http://www.fsf.org/blogs/licensing/more-about-the-app-store-gpl-enforcement|date=26 May 2010|accessdate=3 August 2011|work=Free Software Foundation|first=Brett|last=Smith}}&lt;/ref&gt; The iCoder version was taken down from the App Store after about a week since Wolfire notified them of the issue, though so far no explanation has been given by Apple.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfire counterfeit resolved&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://twitter.com/humble/status/34771005364772864 | title = It looks like Apple has removed the counterfeit Lugaru from the Mac App Store after &gt;1 week! | date = 2011-02-08 | accessdate = 2011-02-08 | first = Jeffrey | last = Rosen }}&lt;/ref&gt; As the iCoder version of the application was popular, being the 60th most downloaded game application prior to its removal, Wolfire offered those that purchased the iCoder version a free copy of their version and codes to unlock the game from within Steam.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/32966/Apple_Pulls_Counterfeit_Lugaru_From_Mac_App_Store.php | title = Apple Pulls Counterfeit Lugaru From Mac App Store | first = Eric | last = Caolli | date = 2011-02-10 | accessdate = 2011-02-10 | publisher = [[Gamasutra]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rosen notes that the incident may discourage developers from releasing their source in the future.&lt;ref name=&quot;wolfire counterfeit&quot;/&gt;

=== Criticism ===
Alexander Zubov of [[Kot-in-Action Creative Artel]] who developed the ''[[Steel Storm]]'' games complained in an interview about the trouble he had getting his games accepted into the Bundles, originally trying to push their game's first episode as a free bonus for the second Bundle, and then trying to get their full game into the third. Zubov recalls that he had heard &quot;nothing back&quot; until they made a &quot;last minute decision&quot; to include ''Steel Storm: Burning Retribution'' in the Humble Indie Bundle 3. Even then, Zubov further described his dissatisfaction with how payment was handled, saying that they were &quot;offered a tiny-tiny fraction of what HIB3 made, a very small (compare to the profits of HIB3) fixed amount of money&quot; even though, according to Zubov, &quot;when Steel Storm was released as a bonus, their sales jumped up significantly.&quot; He also mentioned that despite claims by the organizers that their sales would &quot;sky rocket just because [they] were in the HIB3&quot;, their actual amount of sales remained relatively constant.

Zubov did however note that their inclusion in the third bundle &quot;did get a lot of users who redeemed their copy of Steel Storm on [[Steam (content delivery)|Steam]] and [[Desura]]&quot; and that they hoped this would help keep their &quot;current user base, which we gained with HIB3, interested in our upcoming games&quot;. He concluded his comments about his experiences by saying that &quot;only time will tell if HIB3 was [an] awesome deal or not. Maybe, maybe not. If it works out as a long term investment, it will be awesome indeed. If not, I will never ever participate in such capacity (as a bonus item for a small fixed payout) in the future HIB bundles. We all do have bills to pay and families to feed, don't we?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.gamingonlinux.info/index.php?threads/kot-in-action-interview.590/ | title = Kot-in-Action Interview! | first = Liam | last = Dawe | date = 2011-10-03 | accessdate = 2011-10-04 | publisher = Gaming on Linux }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The technology website [[Phoronix]] has also reported that there has also been some detractors of the Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle, with editor [[Michael Larabel]] claiming that the Bundle does not seem to be &quot;as popular as some of the past bundles&quot; and that &quot;the pace of sales isn't as fast as some of the other bundles.&quot; More importantly, he also explains that the &quot;bundle has actually resulted in some complaints among gamers&quot;, with most of the complaints centred around that fact that originally there was &quot;just one game being officially part of this bundle&quot;. Larabel does note that they did later add more games to the bundle as bonuses and that &quot;adding more value to the bundle may generate some additional sales&quot;, but does conclude that the initially small offer has caused there to be less &quot;interest among gamers this time around.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.phoronix.com/scan.php?page=news_item&amp;px=OTk3NA | title = It's Not All Roses For The Latest Humble Bundle! | first = Michael | last = Larabel | date = 2011-10-06 | accessdate = 2011-10-06 | publisher = [[Phoronix]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== List of games offered ==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! style=&quot;width:210px;&quot;| Bundle 
! style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;| Period Offered
! style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;| Game
! style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;| Developer
! style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;| Initial Release Year
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Total Raised
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Total purchases
! style=&quot;width:100px;&quot;| Average price
|-
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | '''Humble Indie Bundle 1'''
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | May 4–10*, 2010
| ''[[World of Goo]]''
| [[2D Boy]]
| 2008
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | US$1.27+ M
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | 138,813
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | $9.18
|-
| ''[[Aquaria (video game)|Aquaria]]''
| Bit Blot
| 2007
|-
| ''[[Gish (video game)|Gish]]''
| Cryptic Sea
| 2004
|- 
| ''[[Penumbra: Overture]]''
| [[Frictional Games]]
| 2007
|-
| ''[[Lugaru|Lugaru HD]]''
| [[Wolfire Games]]
| 2005
|-
| ''[[Samorost 2]]''
| [[Amanita Design]]
| 2007
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; | 
* ''Samorost 2'' added for free to the bundle on May 9, 2010.
* ''Aquaria'', ''Gish'', ''Lugaru HD'' and ''Penumbra'' were [[Open-source software|open-sourced]] as a result of the success of the sale.
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]] redemption keys for the games, except ''Samorost 2'', were distributed to the bundle customers on December 9, 2010.
* ''Samorost 2'' included [[Samorost 2 (Soundtrack)|a separate soundtrack from the game]]
* ''Samorost 2'' was, on June 1, 2011, made available on Steam, which makes the complete bundle redeemable on Steam.
* A discount for the other games in the Penumbra series was also offered.
|-
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | '''Humble Indie Bundle 2'''
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | December 14–24, 2010
| ''[[Braid (video game)|Braid]]''
| [[Jonathan Blow]]&lt;br/&gt;Number None Studios
| 2008
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | US$1.8+ M
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | 232,855
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | $7.85
|-
| ''[[Cortex Command]]''
| Data Realms LLC
| Currently in playable [[Betaware|Beta]]
|- 
| ''[[Machinarium]]''
| [[Amanita Design]]
| 2009
|- 
| ''[[Osmos]]''
| Hemisphere Games
| 2009
|-
| ''[[Revenge of the Titans]]''
| Puppy Games
| 2011
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; | 
* Purchases before Dec 22, 2010 and those after which paid more than the average price also received the contents of the first Bundle, along with [[Steam (software)|Steam]] keys for those.
* ''Cortex Command'' and ''Revenge of the Titans'' were still undergoing active development during the bundle sale; final versions would be made available to purchasers.
* The engine for ''Revenge of the Titans'' will be [[Open-source software|open-sourced]] as a result of success of the sale.
* ''Machinarium'', ''Osmos'', and ''Revenge of the Titans'' included a separate soundtrack from each game
* Steam and [[Desura]] redemption keys for all games, except ''Cortex Command'' and ''Revenge of the Titans'' (the latter two being addressed as being covered by the keys once the games were made available through Steam and Desura - as of December 2011, only ''Cortex Command'' is still unavailable), were distributed to the bundle customers. The Desura keys also included all the games from the first Bundle for the purchasers that paid above the average, excluding ''Gish'' and ''Aquaria'', which are not available on Desura.
* ''Revenge of the Titans'' was released and automatically unlocked for people who activated the Bundle on [[Steam (software)|Steam]] on March 17, 2011.
|-
| rowspan = &quot;6&quot; | '''Humble Frozenbyte Bundle'''
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | April 12–26, 2011
| ''[[Trine (video game)|Trine]]''
| [[Frozenbyte]]
| 2009
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | US$0.9+ M
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | 183,219
| rowspan = &quot;5&quot; | $4.97
|-
| ''[[Shadowgrounds]]''
| [[Frozenbyte]]
| 2005
|- 
| ''[[Shadowgrounds Survivor]]''
| [[Frozenbyte]]
| 2007
|- 
| ''Splot''
| [[Frozenbyte]]
| Unreleased Pre-Order
|-
| ''Jack Claw''
| [[Frozenbyte]]
| Unreleased Prototype Bonus
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; | 
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]] and [[Desura]] redemption keys for all games, except ''Splot'' and ''Jack Claw'', as well as an [[OnLive]] key for ''Trine'', were distributed to the bundle customers.
* Source code for ''Shadowgrounds'' and ''Shadowgrounds Survivor'' (after reaching $700k)
* Level editor for ''Trine''
* Demo for ''Splot''
|-
| rowspan = &quot;8&quot; | '''Humble Indie Bundle 3'''
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | July 26 – August 9, 2011
| ''[[Crayon Physics Deluxe]]''
| [[Kloonigames]]
| 2009
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | US$2.16+ M
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | 351,251
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | $5.83
|-
| ''[[Cogs (video game)|Cogs]]''
| Lazy 8 Studios
| 2009
|-
| ''[[VVVVVV]]''
| Terry Cavanagh
| 2010
|- 
| ''[[Hammerfight]]''
| Kranx Productions
| 2009
|-
| ''[[And Yet It Moves]]''
| Broken Rules
| 2009
|-
| ''[[Steel Storm]]''
| [[Kot-in-Action Creative Artel]]
| 2010
|-
| ''[[Atom Zombie Smasher]]''
| Blendo Games
| 2011
|- 
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; |
* Purchasers before August 3rd as well as purchasers paying more than the average price after that date received the contents of the second Bundle.
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]] and [[Desura]] redemption keys for all games, except some were not immediately available on Steam for Mac.
* Purchasers were also entitled to play ''[[Minecraft]]'' until August 14, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Humble Indie Bundle 3: Now With Humble Indie Bundle 2!|url=http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/112057-Humble-Indie-Bundle-3-Now-With-Humble-Indie-Bundle-2|first=Andy|last=Chalk|date=3 August 2011|accessdate=3 August 2011|work=The Escapist}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Steel Storm'' by Kot-in-Action Creative Artel was added for free to the bundle on August 1, 2011.
* ''Atom Zombie Smasher'' by Blendo Games was added for free to the bundle on August 5, 2011.
|-
| rowspan = &quot;4&quot; | '''Humble Frozen Synapse Bundle'''
| rowspan = &quot;3&quot; | September 28 – October 12, 2011
| ''[[Frozen Synapse]]''
| Mode 7 Games
| 2011
| rowspan = &quot;3&quot; |US$1.11+ M
| rowspan = &quot;3&quot; |231,797
| rowspan = &quot;3&quot; |$4.81
|- 
| ''[[Trauma (video game)|TRAUMA]]''
| Krystian Majewski
| 2010
|- 
| ''[[SpaceChem]]''
| [[Zachtronics Industries]]
| 2011
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; |
* Purchasers paying more than the average price received the contents of the Frozenbyte Bundle.
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]], [[Direct2Drive]], and [[Desura]] redemption keys for all games, except ''Splot'' and ''Jack Claw'', as well as an [[OnLive]] key for ''Trine''.
* ''Frozen Synapse'' included a separate soundtrack.
* ''TRAUMA'' by Krystian Majewski was added as a free bonus to the bundle on September 30, 2011.
* ''SpaceChem'' by Zachtronics Industries was added to the bundle on October 5, 2011; a separate soundtrack followed October 7, 2011.
|-
| rowspan = &quot;8&quot; | '''Humble Voxatron Debut'''
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | October 31 – November 14, 2011
| ''[[Voxatron]]''
| [[Lexaloffle]]
| [[Software release life cycle#Alpha|Alpha release]]
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | US$0.9+ M  
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | 172,261
| rowspan = &quot;7&quot; | $5.24
|-
| ''[[Blocks That Matter]]''
| Swing Swing Submarine
| 2011
|-
| ''[[The Binding of Isaac (video game)|The Binding of Isaac]]''
| [[Edmund McMillen]] and Florian Himsl
| 2011
|-
| ''[[Gish (video game)|Gish]]''
| Cryptic Sea
| 2004
|-
| ''[[Chocolate Castle]]''
| [[Lexaloffle]]
| 2007
|-
| ''Jasper's Journeys''
| [[Lexaloffle]]
| 2008
|-
| ''Zen Puzzle Garden''
| [[Lexaloffle]]
| Unknown
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; |
* ''Blocks that Matter'' and ''The Binding of Isaac'' were added on November 1, 2011 for those having already purchased the bundle and those that pay more than the average bundle price.
* ''Gish'', ''Chocolate Castle'', ''Jasper's Journeys'', and ''Zen Puzzle Garden'' were added as developer bonuses on November 9, 2011.
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]] redemption keys were made available for ''The Binding of Isaac'', ''Blocks That Matter'', and ''Gish''.
|-
| rowspan = &quot;10&quot; | '''Humble Introversion Bundle'''
| rowspan = &quot;9&quot; | November 22 – December 6, 2011
| ''[[Darwinia (video game)|Darwinia]]''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| 2005
| rowspan = &quot;9&quot; |TBD
| rowspan = &quot;9&quot; |TBD
| rowspan = &quot;9&quot; |TBD
|-
| ''[[Uplink (video game)|Uplink]]''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| 2001
|-
| ''[[Multiwinia]]''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| 2008
|-
| ''[[DEFCON (video game)|DEFCON]]''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| 2006
|-
| ''Voxel Tech Demo''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| Tech Demo
|-
| ''City Generator Tech Demo''
| [[Introversion Software]]
| Tech Demo
|-
| ''[[Aquaria (video game)|Aquaria]]''
| [[Bit Blot]]
| 2007
|-
| ''[[Crayon Physics Deluxe]]''
| [[Kloonigames]]
| 2009
|-
| ''[[Dungeons of Dredmor]]''
| [[Gaslamp Games]]
| 2011
|-
| colspan = &quot;7&quot; |
* [[Steam (software)|Steam]] redemption keys were available for all the games, except the tech demos.
* ''Voxel Tech Demo'' and ''City Generator Tech Demo'' were available only for Windows.
* ''Aquaria'' and ''Crayon Physics Deluxe'' were available for those that paid more than the average bundle price.
* The source code for all the released Introversion games was made available to the Bundle buyers on November 29, 2011.
* ''Dungeons of Dredmor'' was added to the Bundle on November 29, 2011 and was available for those that paid more than the average bundle price.
* [[Desura]] redemption keys were made available to all customers on December 2, 2011, however only for the Introversion games.
|}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==See Also==
* [[Pay what you want]]

==External links==
* [http://www.humblebundle.com Official Humble Indie Bundle website]

{{Humble Indie Bundle}}

[[Category:Charity fundraisers]]
[[Category:Indie video games]]
[[Category:Linux games]]
[[Category:Mac OS X games]]
[[Category:Video game collections]]
[[Category:Windows games]]
[[Category:2010 introductions]]
[[Category:Humble Indie Bundle games| ]]

[[de:Humble Indie Bundle]]
[[fr:Humble Indie Bundle]]
[[hu:Humble Indie Bundle]]
[[pt:Humble Indie Bundle]]
[[ru:Humble Indie Bundle]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
