<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3258842" ns="0" title="Ramin Karimloo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox musical artist
| name         = Ramin Karimloo (Rah-meen)
| image        = RaminKarimloo.jpg
| imagesize    = 250px
| caption      = 
| birth_date         = {{birth date and age|1978|9|19}}
| origin       = [[Tehran]], [[Iran]]/[[Richmond Hill]], [[Canada]]

| occupation   = [[Actor]], [[Singer]], [[Songwriter]],[[Producer]]
| website      = http://www.raminkarimloo.net
| background   = solo_singer

}}

'''Ramin Karimloo''' (born September 19, 1978) is an [[Iran]]ian-born [[Canadian]] musical theatre actor, recognized chiefly for his work in [[London]]'s [[West End theatre|West End]]. He has played the leading male roles in both of the [[West End theatre|West End’s]] longest running musicals; the Phantom in ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1986 musical)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'' and [[Jean Valjean]] in ''[[Les Misérables (musical)|Les Misérables]]'', as of 29th November 2011, after [[Alfie Boe]] signs off as the protagonist. He also originated the role of [[Erik (The Phantom of the Opera)|the Phantom]] in [[Andrew Lloyd Webber]]'s ''[[Love Never Dies (musical)|Love Never Dies]]'', which continues the story of ''The Phantom of the Opera.'' 

==Career==
In [[Canada]], Karimloo moved to [[Richmond Hill, Ontario|Richmond Hill]] from [[Peterborough, Ontario|Peterborough]] and graduated from [[Alexander Mackenzie]] High School. He began his performing career in rock bands and various theatre projects before moving on to perform in theatre companies for [[Airtours]] and [[P&amp;O Cruises]].

After moving to [[England]], his first role was in a pantomime of [[Aladdin]] in [[Chatham, Kent|Chatham]], in which he played the title role. Following this, in 2001, he went on to join the UK national tour of ''[[The Pirates of Penzance]]'', understudying and then playing the role of the Pirate King. 

In 2002, Karimloo joined the national tour of ''[[Sunset Boulevard (musical)|Sunset Boulevard]]'', playing Artie Green and covering the role of Joe Gillis. 

''[[Les Misérables (musical)|Les Misérables]]'' was his [[West End theatre|West End]] debut; he played Feuilly and understudied the roles of [[Marius Pontmercy|Marius]] and [[Enjolras]]. 

After this, in 2003, Karimloo took one of the lead roles, Raoul (Vicomte de Chagny), in ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1986 musical)|The Phantom of the Opera]]''. His final matinee performance was filmed for use on a behind-the-scenes feature on the [[DVD]] of [[Joel Schumacher]]'s ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (2004 film)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'', a film in which he also appeared, in a cameo role as Gustave Daaé, Christine's violinist father whom Christine believes has sent her an Angel of Music from the heavens after his death.

During the same period, Karimloo also appeared in two concerts of ''Les Misérables'' (as Marius), and one of ''[[Jesus Christ Superstar]]'' (as [[Simon Zealotes]], and a featured singer in &quot;[[Superstar (JCS song)|Superstar]]&quot;), as well as being involved in several theatre workshops. 

In 2004, Karimloo went back to ''Les Misérables'', this time taking on the role of Enjolras. In the December of that year, he appeared in a concert of ''Les Misérables'' at [[Windsor Castle]], in honour of the French president [[Jacques Chirac]]. Excerpts from this were shown on [[Easter Sunday]] 2005, in a behind-the-scenes documentary about Windsor Castle. He also performed as Marius in 2004 at Powderham Castle with Nicholas Pound as Jean Valjean, Fred Johanson as Javert, Rebecca Thornhill as Fantine, Dianne Pilkington as Eponine, Jamie Farr as Cosette, David Bardsley as Enjolras, Tony Timberlake as Thenardier, and Rosie Ashe as Madame Thenardier.

In June 2005, Karimloo joined the UK national tour of ''[[Miss Saigon]]'', playing the role of Christopher Scott. He appeared in the West End production of ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1986 musical)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'', this time as the Phantom, starting in September 2007. He was the show's 21st anniversary Phantom. He brought a new interpretation to the role and a vitality which was recognized by fans of the show as it earned him a Theatregoers' Choice Award Nomination for Best Actor in a Take Over Role. 

Karimloo has also released an EP, ''Within the Six Square Inch'', on which he duets with [[Hadley Fraser]] and Sophia Ragavelas, both of whom he had already appeared with in ''[[Les Misérables (musical)|Les Misérables]]'' (Marius and Éponine).

In July 2008, he was asked to take part in the [[Sydmonton Festival]] and was the first actor to play The Phantom in the workshop presentation of ''[[Love Never Dies (musical)|Love Never Dies]]''. It was the first act to the sequel of ''The Phantom of the Opera''. It was confirmed he would play the role alongside [[Sierra Boggess]] when the sequel opened in London, England, March 2010.  A Broadway production was considered, but never put into action.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title=Lloyd Webber Confirms Boggess And Karimloo For Leading Roles In 'LOVE NEVER DIES' | url=http://broadwayworld.com/article/Lloyd_Webber_Confirms_Boggess_And_Karimloo_For_Leading_Roles_In_LOVE_NEVER_DIES_20090703 | work=Broadway World | year=2009 | accessdate=2009-04-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 Karimloo recorded a song, &quot;I Only Wish for You&quot;, with Shona Lindsay and Dianne Pilkington, for the CD ''Songs from the Musicals of Alexander S. Bermange'', an album of 20 brand new recordings by 26 West End stars, released in November 2008 on Dress Circle Records.&lt;ref&gt;[http://itunes.apple.com/gb/album/act-one-songs-from-musicals/id458358848 iTunes: ''Act One: Songs from the Musicals of Alexander S. Bermange'']&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009 he was asked to take part in the recording of new musical album called ''Bluebird'', by Gareth Peter Dicks. ''Bluebird'' is a dramatic WW2 musical, in which he plays the part of US serviceman Ben Breagan. He appeared along with a host of West End stars. The 24-track album was released in four countries in September 2009.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.garethpeterdicks.co.uk Gareth Peter Dicks]&lt;/ref&gt;

Karimloo's last regular performance in ''The Phantom of the Opera'' took place on November 7, 2009. He moved on to playing the Phantom in Andrew Lloyd Webber's sequel, ''Love Never Dies'', alongside Sierra Boggess, performing the role until the show closed on 27 August 2011.

On 3 October 2010, Karimloo played the role of Enjolras in the 25th Anniversary Concert of ''Les Misérables'' at [[The O2 Arena (London)|The O2 Arena]] in London.

On October 1 and 2 2011, he played The Phantom for three performances alongside ''Love Never Dies'' co-star Sierra Boggess as Christine in the unique 25th anniversary production of ''[[The Phantom of the Opera (1986 musical)|The Phantom of the Opera]]'' at the Royal Albert Hall and was streamed live to cinemas across the world. According to an interview in ''[[The Stage]]'' magazine (May 2011), this would be his last performance behind the mask.

Between 29 November 2011 and 3 March 2012, Ramin Karimloo will return to ''[[Les Misérables (musical)|Les Misérables]]'', to play the lead role of [[Jean Valjean]] at [[The Queen's Theatre]], [[London]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lesmis.com/news/article/london_ramin_karimloo_to_star_as_jean_valjean Lesmis.com: Ramin Karimloo to star as Jean Valjean]&lt;/ref&gt;

Karimloo is also now composing music in his band, Sheytoons, with [[Hadley Fraser]].

He has been cast as the lead in 1066 Productions' UK/Canadian feature film ''Bad Town'', scheduled to shoot in Quebec in 2012.

His new solo album, ''Ramin'', will be released by Sony on 6 February 2012.

==Awards==
Karimloo won the Best Actor award for the Broadwayworld.com awards in 2010 for his portrayal of The Phantom in ''Love Never Dies''. He has also been nominated for the Best Actor category for the Viewers' Choice Theatre Awards at Whatsonstage.com in 2011. On 7 February 7 2011, Ramin Karimloo was also nominated for a [[Laurence Olivier Award for Best Actor in a Musical]]. ''Love Never Dies'' received seven nominations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-12380380 BBC News: Love Never Dies Leads Olivier Nominations]&lt;/ref&gt; 

On the 20 February 2011 Karimloo won the Whatsonstage.com award for Best Actor in a Musical for his performance in ''Love Never Dies''.

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.raminkarimloo.com/ Official site]
*{{IMDb name|1546077}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Karimloo, Ramin
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = His name is pronounced Rah-meen, alternatively called 'Noodles' by fangirls because his name sounds similar to the food, 'Ramen Noodles'.
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Ramin Karimloo is a successful vocalist and actor. He has been in various successful musicals, portraying each of his characters amazingly. He is also planned to be in a new movie, which will shoot in Quebec, Canada in 2012.
| DATE OF BIRTH     =September 19, 1978
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Karimloo, Ramin}}
[[Category:Canadian people of Iranian descent]]
[[Category:Canadian stage actors]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:1978 births]]

[[de:Ramin Karimloo]]
[[fa:رامین کریملو]]
[[it:Ramin Karimloo]]
[[nl:Ramin Karimloo]]
[[pl:Ramin Karimloo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
