<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32697" ns="0" title="Violette Szabo"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|name         = Violette Szabo
|image        = [[File:Violette Szabo IWM photo.jpg|250px|Violette Szabo]]
|caption      = 
|birth_date   = {{birth-date|26 June 1921}}
|death_date   = {{death-date and age|5 February 1945|26 June 1921}}
|birth_place  = [[Paris]], [[France]]
|death_place  = [[Ravensbrück concentration camp]], [[Germany]]
|nickname     = Louise (also: La P'tite Anglaise)
|allegiance   = [[United Kingdom]], [[France]]
|branch       = [[Special Operations Executive]],&lt;br&gt;[[First Aid Nursing Yeomanry]]
|serviceyears = 1941-1945 (FANY) /&lt;br&gt; 1942/43-1945 (SOE)
|rank         = Ensign
|unit         = [[SOE F Section networks#Salesman|F Section]]
|awards       = [[File:George Cross icon.svg|35px|]][[George Cross]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:CroixDeGuerre.jpg|25px|Croix de Guerre]] [[Croix de Guerre]]
}}

'''Violette Reine Elizabeth Bushell Szabo''', [[George Cross|GC]], (26 June 1921 &amp;ndash; c. 5 February 1945) was a [[World War II|Second World War]] [[France|French]]-[[United Kingdom|British]] secret agent.

==Early life and marriage==
She was born '''Violette Reine Elizabeth Bushell''' in [[Paris, France]] on 26 June 1921,  the second child of a [[France|French]] mother and an [[England|English]] taxi-driver father, who had met during [[World War I]]. The family moved to [[London]] and she attended school in [[Brixton]] until the age of 14.  At the start of the Second World War, she was working in the Bon Marché department store in Brixton on the perfume counter.

Violette met Etienne Szabo, a French officer of [[Hungary|Hungarian]] descent, at the [[Bastille Day]] parade in London in 1940. They married on 21 August 1940 after a whirlwind 42-day romance. Violette was 19, Etienne was 31. Shortly after the birth of their only child, Tania, Etienne died from chest wounds at the [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Battle of El Alamein]] in October 1942. He had never seen his daughter. It was Etienne's death that made Violette, having already joined the [[Auxiliary Territorial Service]] in 1941, decide to offer her services to the British [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE).

==Allied spy==
===Training and first mission===
After an assessment for fluency in the [[French language]] and a series of interviews, she was inducted into [[Special Operations Executive]]. She received intensive training in night and daylight navigation, [[escape and evasion]], both Allied and German weapons, unarmed combat, [[demolitions]], explosives, communications and [[cryptography]]. A minor accident during parachute training delayed her deployment into the field until 5 April 1944, when she was parachuted into German-occupied France, near [[Cherbourg-Octeville|Cherbourg]].

Code-named &quot;Louise&quot;, she reorganised a [[French Resistance]] network that had been smashed by the Germans. She led the new group in sabotaging road and railway bridges. Her wireless reports to SOE headquarters on the local factories producing war materials for the Germans were extremely important in establishing Allied bombing targets. She returned to England by [[Westland Lysander|Lysander]] on 30 April 1944, landing by [[Westland Lysander|Lysander]] at [[RAF Tempsford]], after an intense but successful first mission.

===Second mission===
She flew to the outskirts of [[Limoges]], France on 7 June 1944 (immediately following [[D-Day]]) from [[RAF Tempsford]]. Immediately on arrival, she coordinated the activities of the local [[Maquis (World War II)|Maquis]] (led by Jacques Dufour) in sabotaging communication lines during German attempts to stem the [[Normandy landings]].

She was a passenger in a car that raised the suspicions of German troops at an unexpected roadblock that had been set up to find [[Sturmbannführer]] [[Helmut Kämpfe]] of the [[2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich|''Das Reich'' Division]], who had been captured by the local resistance.&lt;ref name=jersey&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.jerseywartunnels.com/content/h08/Szabo.aspx | title = Violette Szabó 1921-1944 - a brief history | publisher = [[Jersey War Tunnels]] | accessdate = 2008-11-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

A brief gun battle ensued. Her Maquis minders escaped unscathed in the confusion. However, Szabo was captured when she ran out of ammunition, around midday on 10 June 1944, near [[Salon-la-Tour]]. Her captors were most likely from the 1st Battalion of the Deutschland Regiment. In R. J. Minney's biography, she is described as putting up fierce resistance with her [[Sten]] gun. German documents of the incident record no German injuries or casualties.

===Interrogation, torture and execution===
She was transferred to the custody of the [[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]] in [[Limoges]], where she was interrogated for four days. From there, she was moved to [[Fresnes Prison]] in Paris, and brought to Gestapo headquarters at [[84 Avenue Foch]] for interrogation and torture. In August 1944 she was moved to [[Ravensbrück concentration camp]], where over 92,000 women died. There, she endured hard labour and malnutrition.&lt;ref&gt;R.J.Minney, ''Carve Her Name With Pride'', 1956, pp149-158. ISBN 0862205212&lt;/ref&gt; She managed to help save the life of Belgian resistance courier [[Hortense Clews]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thefreelibrary.com/Violette%3A+A+secret+story+of+wartime+bravery%3B+BRITISH+AGENT+TORTURED...-a087393718/ The Free Library -Violette: A secret story of wartime bravery; BRITISH AGENT TORTURED AND KILLED AT THE AGE OF 23](website accessed: 09/09/2010)&lt;/ref&gt;

Violette Szabo was executed on or about 5 February 1945 and her body disposed of in the [[crematorium]]. She was 23 years old.

Three other women members of the [[Special Operations Executive|SOE]] were also executed at Ravensbrück: [[Denise Bloch]], [[Cecily Lefort]], and [[Lilian Rolfe]]. Of the SOE's 55 female agents, 13 were [[killed in action]] or died in Nazi concentration camps.

== Awards and honours ==
[[Image:George Cross.jpg|thumb|right|120px|[[George Cross]] and its [[ribbon bar]]]]
Szabo was the second woman to be awarded the [[George Cross]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gc-database.co.uk/facts.htm George Cross facts]&lt;/ref&gt; bestowed posthumously on 17 December 1946.  The citation was published in the ''[[London Gazette]]'' and read:&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=37820|supp=yes|startpage=6127|date=13 December 1946|accessdate=2008-05-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|''St. James's Palace, S.W.1. 17th December, 1946''

[[George VI of the United Kingdom|The KING]] has been graciously pleased to award the GEORGE CROSS to: —

Violette, Madame SZABO (deceased), Women's Transport Service ([[First Aid Nursing Yeomanry]]).

Madame Szabo volunteered to undertake a particularly dangerous mission in France. She was parachuted into France in April, 1944, and undertook the task with enthusiasm. In her execution of the delicate researches entailed she showed great presence of mind and astuteness. She was twice arrested by the German security authorities but each time managed to get away. Eventually, however, with other members of her group, she was surrounded by the Gestapo in a house in the south west of France. Resistance appeared hopeless but Madame Szabo, seizing a Sten-gun and as much ammunition as she could carry, barricaded herself in part of the house and, exchanging shot for shot with the enemy, killed or wounded several of them. By constant movement, she avoided being cornered and fought until she dropped exhausted. She was arrested and had to undergo solitary confinement. She was then continuously and atrociously tortured but never by word or deed gave away any of her acquaintances or told the enemy anything of any value. She was ultimately executed. Madame Szabo gave a magnificent example of courage and steadfastness.}}

The [[Croix de Guerre]] was awarded by the French government in 1947 and the [[Médaille de la Résistance]] in 1973. As one of the SOE agents who died for the liberation of France, Ensign Szabo is listed on the &quot;Roll of Honor&quot; on the [[Valençay SOE Memorial]] in the town of [[Valençay]], in the [[Indre]] département.

== Museums and memorials ==
[[Image:Burnley road.JPG|right|thumb|150px|Violette Szabo's Home with blue plaque]]
The [http://www.violette-szabo-museum.co.uk/foyer.htm Violette Szabo GC Museum] is located in the cottage in [[Wormelow Tump]], [[Herefordshire]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geograph.org.uk/photo/578871 The Violette Szabo GC Museum]&lt;/ref&gt; that Violette's English cousins formerly owned, and that Violette would visit before the war to enjoy walks in the surrounding hills. She also stayed at the farm while she was recuperating from her ankle injury and between her two missions to France. Tania Szabo attended the museum's opening in 2000, as did [[Virginia McKenna]], [[Leo Marks]] and members of SOE.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.powell-pressburger.org/Trips/Wormelow/20000624.html Opening of the Violette Szabo museum]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Hohlgangsanlage 8|The Jersey War Tunnels]] has a permanent exhibition room dedicated to Violette Szabo.&lt;ref name=jersey/&gt;

The [[Royal College of Music]] offers an annual award called the Violette Szabo GC Memorial Prize for pianists who accompany singers. The current holder is James Southall.

There is a mural dedicated to Violette Szabo in [[Stockwell]], South London, painted in 2001: Stockwell War Memorial, Stockwell Road. Painted on the exterior of the entrance to a deep level shelter, this mural was executed by Brian Barnes (with the assistance of children from Stockwell Park School). It features Stockwell's famous people such as Violette Szabo and Vincent Van Gogh. It also commemorates the local people who gave their life in the war. This mural was listed in ''Time Out'' as one of London's top ten murals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.powell-pressburger.org/Trips/London/20010626/index.html Unveiling of the Violette Szabo mural at Stockwell]&lt;/ref&gt;

A [[blue plaque]] commemorating Violette Szabo can be found in Burnley Road in [[Stockwell]], on the wall of the house where she grew up.

In 2008, a bronze bust of Szabo by sculptor [[Karen Newman (artist)|Karen Newman]] was unveiled at the [[Albert Embankment]] of the [[River Thames]], opposite [[Lambeth Palace]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.karen-newman.com/PortfolioPages/Violette1.htm Violett Szabo sculpture]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/8289847.stm |title=Secret agents' memorial unveiled |publisher=[[BBC]] |accessdate=2009-10-05 | date=4 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Book ==
Her daughter, Tania Szabo, wrote an exhaustive and careful reconstruction of her two missions in 1944 into the then most dangerous areas in France with flashbacks to her growing up. Author [[Jack Higgins]] wrote the foreword and US-French radio-operator, Jean-Claude Guiet, who had accompanied her on the mission in the [[Limousin (region)|Limousin]], wrote the introduction. On 15 November 2007, at the launch of the book, ''Young Brave and Beautiful'', at [[Hohlgangsanlage 8|The Jersey War Tunnels]], the Lieutenant Governor of Jersey said of her,  &quot;She's an inspiration to those young people today doing the same work with the risk of the same dangers&quot;. [[Odette Churchill]] GC said, &quot;She was the bravest of us all.&quot;

== In popular culture ==
Her wartime activities in German [[Occupied France]] were also dramatised in the film ''[[Carve Her Name with Pride]]'', starring [[Virginia McKenna]] and based on the 1956 book of the same name by R. J. Minney. During her time as an agent in the SOE, she met [[Leopold Samuel Marks|Leo Marks]], codes officer of the [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE), who gave her what is now thought of as the definitive Second World War [[poem code]], ''[[The Life That I Have]]''.

In 2009, [[Replay Studios]] released the stealth action video game ''[[Velvet Assassin]]'', in which the player controls a character named Violette Summer based on Szabo. The game story is fiction.

==References==
* Szabó, Tania (2007) ''Young Brave and Beautiful: the Missions of Special Operations Executive Agent, Lieutenant Violette Szabó, George Cross, Croix de Guerre avec Etoile de bronze'', St Helier: distributed by [http://www.violetteszabo.org/ Tania Szabó], ISBN 1-905095-20-1. 496 pp, index, bibliography, plus 30 pages of illustrations.
* Minney, R. J. (1956) ''Carve her Name with Pride: the Story of Violette Szabo''. London: Newnes
* Ottaway, Susan (2003) ''Violette Szabo: The Life That I Have''. Pen &amp; Sword Books ISBN 0-85052-976-X

===Notes===
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.violetteszabo.org Violette Szabó GC site] built by Tania Szabo, the daughter of Violette
*[http://www.violette-szabo-museum.co.uk Violette Szabo Museum]
*[http://www.alliedspecialforces.org/violetteszabogcmuseum.htm Violette Szabo GC Museum]
*[http://www.nigelperrin.com/violetteszabo.htm Special Operations Executive Agents in France - Profile of Violette Szabo]
*[http://www.specialforcesroh.com/browse.php?mode=viewiroll&amp;rollid=4170 Special Forces Roll Of Honour website]
* {{imdb title|id=0051454|title=Carve Her Name with Pride}}
*[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/military-obituaries/army-obituaries/6248212/Captain-Les-Fernandez.html Les Fernandez] - Daily Telegraph obituary of the man who trained Violette Szabo

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Szabo, Violette
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = La P'tite Anglaise, Violette Reine Elizabeth Bushell
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = French-British spy
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 26 June 1921
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Paris]], [[France]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = 5 February 1945
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Ravensbrück concentration camp]], [[Germany]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Szabo, Violette}}
[[Category:1921 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Paris]]
[[Category:World War II spies]]
[[Category:Female wartime spies]]
[[Category:Special Operations Executive personnel]]
[[Category:Female resistance members of World War II]]
[[Category:French Resistance members]]
[[Category:Executed spies]]
[[Category:Spies who died in Nazi concentration camps]]
[[Category:Ravensbrück concentration camp victims]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]
[[Category:French recipients of the George Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Médaille de la Résistance]]
[[Category:British military personnel killed in World War II]]

[[de:Violette Szabo]]
[[es:Violette Szabo]]
[[fa:ویولت ژابو]]
[[fr:Violette Szabo]]
[[it:Violette Szabo]]
[[ja:ヴァイオレット・ソボー]]
[[no:Violette Szabó]]
[[fi:Violetta Szabo]]
[[tr:Violette Szabo]]
[[vi:Violette Szabo]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
