<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3271212" ns="0" title="Temple Owls football"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox NCAA football school
| CurrentSeason    = 2011 Temple Owls football team
| TeamName         = [[Temple Owls]] Football
| Image            = TUOwls logo.png
| ImageSize        = 125px
| Helmet           =
| ImageSize2       = 125px
| HeadCoachDisplay = Steve Addazio| HeadCoachLink    = Steve Addazio
| HeadCoachYear    = 1st| HCWins           = 2-1
| HCLosses         = 
| HCTies           = 
| Stadium          = Lincoln Financial Field| StadCapacity     = 68,532| StadSurface      = Desso GrassMaster| Location         = Philadelphia,Pa| ConferenceDisplay= Mid-American Conference| ConferenceLink   = Mid-American Conference| ConfDivision     = East
| FirstYear        = 1894
| AthlDirectorDisp = Bill Bradshaw| AthlDirectorLink = Bill Bradshaw
| WebsiteName      = Temple Athletics
| WebsiteURL       = http://www.owlsports.com/index.aspx
| ATWins           = 416
| ATLosses         = 544
| ATTies           = 53
| ATPercentage     = .432
| BowlWins         = 1
| BowlLosses       = 2
| BowlTies         = 
| NatlTitles       = 0
| ConfTitles       = 0
| Heismans         = 0
| AllAmericans     = 1 (Paul Palmer, 1986)
| Color1           = Cherry
| Color1Hex        = A81625
| Color2           = White
| Color2Hex        = FFFFFF
| FightSong        = &quot;T For Temple U&quot;| MascotDisplay    = Hooter T. Owl
| MascotLink       = http://www.owlsports.com/sports/2009/8/31/GEN_0831095459.aspx?
| MarchingBand     = 
| PagFreeLabel     = Rivals
| PagFreeValue     = [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Penn State Nittany Lions]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Pittsburgh Panthers football|Pittsburgh Panthers]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Buffalo Bulls football|Buffalo Bulls]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Villanova Wildcats football|Villanova Wildcats]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Rutgers Scarlet Knights football|Rutgers Scarlet Knights]]
}}

The '''[[Temple Owls]] football''' team participates in the [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]'s [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Bowl Subdivision|Division I Football Bowl Subdivision]] as a member of the East Division of the [[Mid-American Conference]] (MAC).  Temple is a football-only affiliate of the MAC because their primary conference, the [[Atlantic Ten Conference]], does not currently sponsor a football league (although during the time the A-10 ''did'' sponsor football, it was in the [[Division I (NCAA)#Football Championship Subdivision|Division 1 Championship Subdivision]], and Temple's program has always been in D-I football).  The Owls were a football-only member of the [[Big East Conference]] from 1991 until 2004. Temple was forced out of the league due to poor attendance averages, non-competitiveness, and a lack of commitment to the football program from university officials. Temple played the 2005 and 2006 seasons as an independent before joining the MAC in 2007 where they currently reside.

Although Temple began playing organized football in 1894, the Owls' modern era began in 1925.  That was the year that Henry J. &quot;Heinie&quot; Miller was hired as head coach, and for a time, the Owls were a regional power.  To start the 1928 season, the Owls moved to [[Temple Stadium]].  Miller coached eight seasons and compiled a 50-15-8 record.

=== Pop Warner Era===
Following Miller's departure in 1933, the Owls made a national splash with the hiring of their next coach, the legendary [[Glenn Scobey Warner|Glenn &quot;Pop&quot; Warner]].  Warner had spent the previous 19 years at [[Pittsburgh Panthers football|Pittsburgh]] and [[Stanford Cardinal football|Stanford]], winning three national championships.  He ended his career at Temple, going 31-18-2 in six seasons.  In 1934, the Owls went 7-0-2 in the regular season and were invited to play in the inaugural [[Sugar Bowl]] on New Year's Day, 1935, where they lost to [[Tulane Green Wave football|Tulane]], 20-14.

===George Makris Era===
From the time Warner retired at the end of the 1938 season until 1963, the Owls experienced only 4 winning seasons.  The team reached a nadir in the late 1950s, enduring a school record 21-game losing streak from the last four games of the 1957 season and through the entire 1958 and 1959 seasons.  George Makris arrived as head coach to start the 1960 season and won his first game. Makris restored competitiveness to the Owl program, compiling a 10-year record of 45-44-4. Makris' tenure coincided with Temple's 10 years in the University Division of the [[Middle Atlantic Conferences|Middle Atlantic Conference]].

===Wayne Hardin Era===
After the 1969 season, the Owls became an independent again to upgrade their schedule and compete against the top teams in the East. Under new coach [[Wayne Hardin]], who coached six years at [[United States Naval Academy|Navy]], Temple was up to the challenge. Hardin led the Owls to an 80-52-3 record over 12 years.

Temple went 9-1 in 1973 and 8-2 in 1974 and won 14 straight games at one point. Temple played regular season games in Japan's [[Mirage Bowl]] twice, losing 35-32 to [[Grambling State University|Grambling]] in 1977 and beating [[Boston College Eagles football|Boston College]] 28-24 in 1978.

In 1979, the Owls had a 10-2 record and the most wins in school history. The Owls opened the season with a 38-16 win at [[West Virginia Mountaineers football|West Virginia]] and later beat [[Rutgers Scarlet Knights football|Rutgers]] (41-20) and [[Syracuse Orange football|Syracuse]] (49-17).  Temple's only losses during the regular season were to nationally ranked [[Pittsburgh Panthers football|Pittsburgh]] (10-9) and [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Penn State]] (22-7).  In the game at Penn State, before a record-setting crowd, the Owls led 7-6 at the half.  Following the 1979 season, the Owls defeated [[California Golden Bears football|California]] 28-17 in the second [[Garden State Bowl]].  The crowd who witnessed Temple beat California (55,952) was the largest in the short history of that Bowl.

Under Hardin, the Owls were one of the more stable Eastern football powers and often defeated local rivals West Virginia, Rutgers and Syracuse. In the [http://www.jhowell.net/cf/scores/Temple.htm 1970s], Temple went 4-4 against West Virginia, 2-1 against Rutgers, 1-1 against Syracuse, 4-1-1 against [[Cincinnati Bearcats football|Cincinnati]] and 2-0 against [[Connecticut Huskies football|Connecticut]].

===Bruce Arians Era===
When Hardin retired in 1982, the Owls hired [[Bruce Arians]] - then 30 years old - to succeed him. Arians had some success, beating Pitt three times in his six years on the job. Arians had two winning seasons, going 6-5 in 1984 when the defense was ranked 21st in the nation beating East Carolina, Pitt, and West Virginia and 6-5 1986.  Unfortunately, Temple's six wins in 1986 were later forfeited because the Owls' roster included an ineligible player.

===Decline===
[[Jerry Berndt]], who took over for Arians in 1989, led Temple to their last winning season for almost twenty years in 1990, when the Owls went 7-4. Temple joined the [[Big East Conference]] in 1991, but had difficulty competing against teams with better facilities and bigger budgets.  The Owls would not win a conference game until 1995, and would only win 16 conference games during their 14-year run in the league.  Temple won as many as three league games only once (1997: 3-8, 3-4 Big East) and went winless in league play six times. Overall, they had a 14-80 record against Big East foes.

Berndt (11-33), Ron Dickerson (1993-97: 8-47) and [[Bobby Wallace (football coach)|Bobby Wallace]] (1998-2005: 19-71) were unable to halt the decline. Temple went 0-11 in Wallace's final year.  In part due to the Owls' noncompetitiveness, poor fan support, and lack of institutional support, the Big East voted to expel the Owls at the end of the 2004 season.

===Al Golden Era===
On December 6, 2005, [[Al Golden (American football)|Al Golden]], then the defensive coordinator for the [[University of Virginia]] under [[Al Groh]], was named the new [[head coach]]. The Owls lost their first 8 games under Golden before beating Bowling Green during their Homecoming game on October 28, 2006. The win snapped a 20-game losing streak, one game short of the school record. The Owls finished 1-11 in Golden's first year.  The Owls won 4 games in 2007, including three straight wins at one point in mid-season. During Golden's second season, Temple's defense was ranked 49th in the nation, as opposed to 118th in 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;defenseimprovement&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sports.yahoo.com/ncaaf/stats/byteam?cat1=defense&amp;cat2=Total&amp;conference=I-A_all&amp;year=2007&amp;sort=1124|title=wNCAA Football Statistics|publisher=Yahoo! Sports|date=2007-12-06|accessdate=2007-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The offense also improved from 118th to 113th, but it was clear that Temple's defense, despite their incredible youth, was the heart of their team. The Owls won 5 games in 2008, their most since 1990. After his fourth season, Golden's record stood at 19-29. In 2009, the Owls went 9-4, their best record since 1979 with three of four losses being competitive, the lone exception being a 31-6 loss to a Penn State team that finished 11-2 and ranked #8. Temple accepted a bid to play in the [[EagleBank Bowl]], where they faced the [[UCLA Bruins football|UCLA Bruins]], which was the Owls' first post-season appearance since the 1979 [[Garden State Bowl]]. The Owls fell to the Bruins, 30-21. In 2010, the Owls lost a crucial game to Ohio University which would have given them a potential MAC championship. The week after, Temple would lose to Miami-Ohio, and including losses to rival Penn State and Northern Illinois, the Owls finished at 8-4 for the season. On December 12, 2010, Al Golden was hired as the head coach of the University of Miami.

===Steve Addazio Era===
On December 23, 2010, a press conference was held on campus to formally introduce [[Steve Addazio]], former two-year offensive coordinator at the [[University of Florida]], to the Temple community.

==Awards==

*[[Maxwell Award]]
**[[Steve Joachim]] - 1974

*[[Mid-American Conference]] Coach of the Year
**[[Al Golden (American football)|Al Golden]] - 2009

*Mid-American Conference Freshman of the Year
**[[Bernard Pierce]] - 2009

==Consensus All-Americans==

*[[Paul Palmer (football player)|Paul Palmer]] - 1986

==Retired Jerseys==
{{Empty section|date=October 2011}}

==Owls in pro football==
Zachary Dixon
*[[Andre Neblett]]
*[[Terrance Knighton]]
*[[Brian Sanford]]
*[[Joe Klecko]]
*[[Al Singleton]]
*[[Rian Wallace]]
*[[Wayne Colman]]
*[[Keith Armstrong (American football)|Keith Armstrong]]
*[[Lance Johnstone]]
*[[Steve Watson (American football)|Steve Watson]]
*[[Leslie Shepherd]]
*[[Nick Mike-Mayer]]
*[[Mike Curcio]]
*[[Randy Grossman]]
*[[Antwon Burton]]
*[[Raheem Brock]]
*[[Dan Klecko]]
*[[John Rienstra]]
*[[Jim Cooper (football player)|Jim Cooper]]
*[[James Parrish]]
*[[James Harris]]
*[[Tim Terry]]
*[[Larry Chester]]
*[[Tre Johnson]]
*[[Todd Bowles]]
*[[Anthony Young (football player)|Anthony Young]]
*[[Kevin Ross (American football)|Kevin Ross]]
*[[Paul Palmer (American football)|Paul Palmer]]
*[[Stacey Mack]]
*[[Todd McNair]]
*[[Anthony Anderson (football player)|Anthony Anderson]]
*[[Henry Burris]]
*[[Jason McKie]]
*[[Steve Maneri]]
*[[Muhammad Wilkerson]]
*[[Jaiquawn Jarrett]]

==Home Stadium==
From 1927 until 1977, the Owls played at [[Temple Stadium]].  In 1978, they moved to [[Veterans Stadium]].  During the 1986 season, the Owls averaged an all-time high of 34,543 fans to their games at [[Veterans Stadium]] and their games, regularly televised, did well in the local Nielsen ratings.  Veterans Stadium remained their home field through the 2002 season.  [[Lincoln Financial Field]] has been Temple's home field since 2003, with the first home game being the inaugural college game at Lincoln Financial Field between Temple and Villanova, which drew over 30,000 fans. 

The most attended Temple game, with 105,950 attendees, occurred November 11, 2006 at [[Beaver Stadium]], home of [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Penn State]]. Temple lost that game 47-0. Nine out of the ten most attended Temple games occurred at Penn State.&lt;ref name=&quot;gameattendance&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grfx.cstv.com/photos/schools/tem/sports/m-footbl/auto_pdf/weekly-release.pdf|title=weekly release|publisher=Temple Athletics|date=2007-11-05|accessdate=2007-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Temple Vs. Penn State.JPG|thumb|right|Temple in action vs. Penn State &lt;br&gt; November 10, 2007]]

The largest attended home game was November 10, 2007, at Lincoln Financial Field, when the Owls played host to the [[Penn State Nittany Lions]], which had an attendance of 69,029.&lt;ref name=&quot;gameattendance&quot;/&gt; Temple lost the game 31-0.

==Media coverage==
Eight Temple games were broadcast over Philadelphia television in 2005, the most in school history. The Temple radio network, which once included 12 stations from as far north as [[Sayre, PA]] to as far south as Baltimore, MD, is now down to one flagship station, [[WPHT]] 1210 (AM), in Philadelphia. Harry Donahue handles the play-by-play with former Temple Owl Steve Joachim doing the color. WHAT 1340 AM also carries the games. Past play-by-play broadcasters have included Dave Sims, who currently covers college football and basketball for ESPN; Ron Menchine, the former Navy play-by-play announcer and Howie Herman, currently a sports columnist in Massachusetts.

==Bowl Games==

*[[1935 Sugar Bowl]]
*[[1979 Garden State Bowl]]
*[[2009 EagleBank Bowl]]
*[[2011 New Mexico Bowl]]

==In the Polls==

In the [[1979 college football season|1979 season]], Temple finished 10-2 and ranked #17 in both the coaches and AP poll, their only post-season ranking ever.

==College Football Hall of Fame==

*[[Glenn Scobey Warner|Glenn Warner]] - coach
*[[Ray Morrison]] - coach

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}
*http://temple.rivals.com
*http://owlsports.com
*http://temple.scout.com
*http://www.owlstix.com

{{Temple University}}
{{Temple Owls football coach navbox}}
{{Temple bowl games}}
{{Mid-American Conference football navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Temple Owls Football}}
[[Category:Temple Owls football|*]]
[[Category:Sports clubs established in 1894]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
