<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="32787588" ns="0" title="Children of Mary Immaculate College"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{multiple issues|cleanup=August 2011|lead rewrite=August 2011}}
{{more footnotes|date=August 2011}}
{{ref improve|date=August 2011}}
'''Children of Mary Immaculate College (CMIC)''' is a private – owned, non – sectarian institution located at 22 Maysan Road, Malinta, [[Valenzuela City]]. CMIC was founded by Eleanor de Leon-Llenado&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mb.com.ph/node/73857&lt;/ref&gt;.

==History==

The Grade School Department was opened in 1979 with an initial enrolment of 29 pupils. Thenceforth, the school population students and school building facilities steadily grew. In 1985, the school opened its High School Department with only 15 students. Four years later, the school graduated its first batch of 19 pioneers at the National Shrine of Our Lady of Fatima with the energetic NCR Chief of Secondary Schools, Dr. Pilar Pascual, as guest of honor. For eight consecutive years, the High School Department take pride in the 100% passing of students in the National Secondary Aptitude Test (NSAT) formerly the National College Entrance Examination (NCEE).

It is also noteworthy to mention that the school has produced achievers who have displayed outstanding skills and talents, which enabled them to be chosen as the representative of the country to foreign lands. Olivia Dalena, a consistent scholar, student leader, winner of academic and oratorical tilts and valedictorian of class 1989 – 1990 was chosen as one of the Philippine Ambassadors of Goodwill to Singapore. Such an opportunity to have been sent abroad as a representative of the school is an achievement itself, not enjoyed by other schools.

Aside from its unquestionable emphasis on academic excellence, the school likewise encourages extra – curricular activities for the students to participate in. These include various competitions, academic to cultural contests, in order to enhance a well-rounded education. In almost all competitions joined by CMIC, it had brought home the bacon. These achievements were vivid manifestations of the kind of education and training the students are receiving from this institution of learning – to the utter amazement of some skeptics who have biased assessments about the &quot;never – been – heard&quot; school.

In 1995, the College Department was opened with an enrollment of 50 students. The department initially offered the following degree programs: Bachelor of Arts, Bachelor of Elementary Education, Bachelor of Secondary Education, Bachelor of Science in Commerce, Bachelor of Science in Computer and the two – year program, Associate in Computer Technology. To date, the College Department maintains the offering of Bachelor of Degrees in Education, for Elementary and High School and Bachelor of Science in Commerce. The rest has been gradually phased out.

Towards the end of the school year 1998 – 1999, in order to increase the capability of the school to provide quality instruction and to ensure effective management of the school administration, the Llenado family sought the assistance of the Lasallian Schools Supervision Office (LASSO), which assists schools to be managed well through the [[De La Salle Supervised Schools | Lasallian Schools Supervision Services Association, Inc. (LASSAI)]]. By the opening of school year 1999 – 2000, CMIC has become a La Salle Consultancy School with a La Salle Brother, Br. Narciso Erquiza, FSC, as its Superintendent and Rommel Salvador as its Supervisor. In school year 2000 – 2001, Salvador replaced by Judith Aldaba from the [[De La Salle University]] and Dr. Victoria Honrada, from [[De La Salle-Santiago Zobel School | De La Salle Zobel School]], became CMIC ‘s School Head. In school year 2001 – 2002, three LASSO Supervisors, namely Christopher Polanco, Rommel Sanchez and Sis. Teresita Octavio assisted the school in the preparation for the first – step LASSO Accreditation. Gloria Faraon for the College Department and Sonia Annang spearheaded and the executive committee for the Grade School and High School Departments. Recommendations were made for further evaluations. A second LASSO Accreditation was made the following year. This time the executive committee was chaired by then School Head, Eleanor de Leon – Llenado. The school passed the first phase of the and was able to get the merit of [[De La Salle Supervised Schools | De La Salle Supervised School]].


==See also==
* [[La Sallian educational institutions | Lasallian Educational Institutions]]
* [[De La Salle Supervised Schools | Philippine De La Salle Supervised Schools]]


==External links==
* [http://www.pinoyexchange.com/forums/showthread.php?t=92458&amp;page=7|Partial Partial List of '''LA SALLE''' Schools &amp; Educational Institutions Throughout the Archipelago]
* [http://www.dlsu.edu.ph/offices/mco/publications/student_handbook/SY0609/appendix.pdf De La Salle Supervised Schools]


== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord missing|Philippines}}

{{DLSSS}}
{{DLSP}}

[[Category:Roman Catholic schools in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Lasallian educational institutions]]
[[Category:De La Salle Supervised Schools]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
