<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="328801" ns="0" title="Shemale"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Transgender sidebar}}
''' Shemale''' (also '''she-male''') is a term used in [[sex work]] to describe [[trans women]] with [[male]] [[penis|genitalia]] and augmented [[female]] [[breasts]] from [[breast augmentation]] and/or use of hormones.&lt;ref name=&quot;weinberg2009&quot;&gt;Weinberg MS, Williams CJ (2009). Men Sexually Interested in Transwomen (MSTW): Gendered Embodiment and the Construction of Sexual Desire. ''[[J Sex Res.]]'' 2009 Jun 19:1-10. PMID 19544216&lt;/ref&gt; According to Professors Laura Castañeda and Shannon Campbell at the [[University of Southern California]]'s [[Annenberg School of Journalism]], &quot;Using the term ''she-male'' for a transsexual woman would be considered highly offensive, for it implies that she is working 'in the (sex) trade.'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;castaneda&quot;/&gt;

The term ''she-male'' has been used since the mid-19th century, when it was a humorous [[colloquialism]] for ''female'', especially an aggressive woman. 

== Academic use ==
Some [[biologist]]s have used ''she-male'' to refer to male non-human animals displaying female traits or behaviors, such as female pheromones being given off by male reptiles.&lt;ref&gt;Shine, R., Phillips, B., &amp; Waye, H., LeMaster, M., &amp; Mason, R. T. (2001). Benefits of female mimicry in snakes: She-male garter snakes exploit the amorous attentions of other males to warm up. ''Nature, 414'', 267.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mason, R. T., &amp; Crew, D. (1985). Female mimicry in garter snakes. ''Nature, 316'', 59-60.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rubenstein, D. I. (1985). Animal behaviour: The serpent's seductive scent. ''Nature, 316'', 18-19.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moore, M. C., &amp; Lindsey, J. (1992). The physiological basis of sexual behavior in male reptiles. In C. Gans and D. Crews, ''Hormones, brain and behavior: Biology of the reptilia'', vol. 13, physiology E, pp. 70-113.&lt;/ref&gt; Biologist [[Joan Roughgarden]] has criticised the use of the term in the reptile literature, &quot;which she says is degrading and has been borrowed from the porn industry.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;flam&quot;&gt;Flam, Faye (2008).''The Score: How the Quest for Sex Has Shaped the Modern Man. ''Avery, ISBN 9781583333129&lt;/ref&gt; She writes that ''gynomorphic male'' and ''andromorphic female'' are preferred, adding, &quot;I hope future work on these animals is carried out with more professionalism.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;roughgarden&quot;&gt;Roughgarden, Joan (2005). ''Evolution's rainbow: diversity, gender, and sexuality in nature and people.'' University of California Press, ISBN 9780520246799&lt;/ref&gt;

The term is also used by some [[psychologist]]s to refer specifically to male-to-female transsexuals who have transitioned to female at least cosmetically, such as with breast augmentation, but have not undergone genital surgery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanchard1993&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;jhp&quot;&gt;Bailey, J. Michael (2003). ''The Man Who Would Be Queen: The Science of Gender-Bending and Transsexualism''. Joseph Henry Press, ISBN 978-0309084185&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = dixon/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Olsson, S.-E., &amp; Möller, A. (2006). Regret after sex reassignment surgery in a male-to-female transsexual: A long-term follow-up. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 35, 501-506.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Related terms===

Other slang terms for ''she-male'' that emerged from [[sex work]] include ''tranny'' and ''[[Kathoey|ladyboy]]'' as well as a number of rhyming terms (not to be confused with [[rhyming slang]]), including ''chicks with dicks'', ''sluts with nuts'', ''dolls with balls'', &amp; ''dudes with boobs''.&lt;ref name=&quot;International Ex&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last =Sigel | first =Lisa Z. | pages =254–271  | isbn = 0813535190, 9780813535197  | coauthors = John Phillips|chapter=Walking on The Wild Side: Shemale Internet Pornography
 | title=International Exposure: Perspectives on Modern European Pornography, 1800-2000
 | publisher=Rutgers University Press  | year=2005 | url =http://books.google.com/?id=KiyY_nlqaQEC  | accessdate=2008-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some mental health researchers consider attraction to transgender people to be a [[paraphilia]]. [[John Money]] and [[Margaret Lamacz]] proposed a series of terms along these lines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite doi|10.1016/0010-440X(84)90074-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gynemimetophilia'' denotes [[sexual attraction]] to [[male-assigned]] people who look or act like women, including genetically male [[crossdresser]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Money, J. 1984&quot;/&gt; It can also refer to an attraction to [[trans women]]. A related term is ''gynemimesis'' which refers to a [[homosexual]] male who engages in female impersonation without sex reassignment&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=yIXG9FuqbaIC&amp;pg=PA408 Sexual deviance: theory, assessment ... - Google Books]&lt;/ref&gt; or to describe the adoption of female characteristics by a male.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=zDS9kC03x2IC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=gynandromorphy&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#PPA75,M1 ''The Illustrated Dictionary of Sex: Gynemimism'']&lt;/ref&gt; The terms were used by Money for classification purposes in his [[transgender|gender-transposition]] theory.&lt;ref&gt;John Money, ''Gender-transposition theory and homosexual genesis'', [[Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy]], Volume 10, Issue 2 Summer 1984 , pages 75 - 82&lt;/ref&gt; He also proposed ''[[gynandromorph]]'' and ''gynemimetomorph'' as technical terms for trans women.&lt;ref name=&quot;Money, J. 1984&quot;&gt;Money, J. (1984). Paraphilias: Phenomenology and classification. ''American Journal of Psychotherapy, 38'', 164-178.&lt;/ref&gt; A ''gynandromorph'' is an organism that contains both male and female characteristics. ''Gynandromorphy'' is a term of Greek etymology which means to have some of the body [[morphology (biology)|morphology]] and measurements of both an average woman and man.&lt;ref&gt;[http://books.google.com/books?id=zDS9kC03x2IC&amp;pg=PA74&amp;dq=gynandromorphy&amp;lr=&amp;as_brr=3#PPA75,M1 ''The Illustrated Dictionary of Sex: Gynandromorphy'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Psychologist [[Ray Blanchard]] and psychiatrist [[Peter Collins (psychiatrist)|Peter Collins]] coined the term ''[[gynandromorphophilia]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanchard1993&quot;&gt;Blanchard, R., &amp; Collins, P. I. (1993). Men with sexual interest in transvestites, transsexuals, and she males. ''[[Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease]]'', 181'', 570–575.&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist Richard Ekins writes that this attraction can include both identification and object choice in &quot;fantasy femaling&quot; masturbatory scripts.&lt;ref name=&quot;ekins1996&quot;&gt;Ekins, Richard (1996). ''Blending genders: social aspects of cross-dressing and sex-changing.'' Routledge, ISBN 9780415115513&lt;/ref&gt; Blanchard has proposed that this is &quot;partial [[autogynephilia]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;The she-male phenomenon and the concept of partial autogynephilia&quot;. R. Blanchard - Journal of Sex &amp; Marital Therapy, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; Psychiatrist [[Vernon Rosario]] has called labels like these &quot;scientifically [[Reification (fallacy)|reifying]]&quot; when applied to those attracted to trans women.&lt;ref name=&quot;rosario2004&quot;&gt;Rosario, Vernon (2004). &quot;Quejotobonita!&quot;: Transgender Negotiations of Sex and Ethnicity. In Ubaldo Leli, Jack Drescher (eds.) ''Transgender Subjectivities: A Clinician's Guide.'' [[Routledge]], ISBN 9780789025760&lt;/ref&gt;

As an alternative to a paraphilic model, sexologists Martin S. Weinberg and Colin J. Williams have used the term ''Men Sexually Interested in Transwomen'' (MSTW).&lt;ref name=&quot;weinberg2009&quot;/&gt; Slang terms for individuals with such preferences include ''[[transfan]]s'', ''tranny chasers'' and ''admirers.''

== Other usage ==
Since the mid-19th century, the term ''she-male'' has been applied to &quot;almost anyone who appears to have bridged [[gender]] lines&quot;, including effeminate men and [[lesbians]].&lt;ref name=&quot;herbst&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Herbst |first=Philip H. |title=Wimmin, Wimps &amp; Wallflowers: An Encyclopaedic Dictionary of Gender and Sexual orientation Bias in The United States |publisher=Intercultural Press |year=2001 |isbn=1877864803 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=8rgUeEpWfbsC&amp;pg=PA38&amp;dq=shemale+empowerment |accessdate=2007-10-25 |pages=252–3 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the early 19th century, ''she-male'' was used as a [[colloquial]]ism in American literature for female, often [[pejorative]]ly.&lt;ref name=&quot;stevens&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Cassidy |first=Frederic Gomes
 |coauthors=Joan Houston Hall
 |title=Dictionary of American Regional English.
 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=i33BWgxbvXgC
 |year=2002  |page=901 |publisher=Harvard University Press
 |isbn=0674008847, 9780674008847
 |accessdate=2008-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Davy Crockett]] is quoted as using the term in regard to a shooting match, when his opponent challenges Davy Crockett to shoot near his opponent's wife, Davy Crockett is reported to have replied: &quot;'No, No, Mike,' sez I, 'Davy Crockett's hand would be sure to shake, if his iron pointed within a hundred miles of a shemale, and I give up beat...'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;boorstin&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Boorstin |first=Daniel J. |chapter=Part Seven: &quot;Search for Symbols&quot; |title=The Americans, vol. 2 The National Experience. |place=N.Y. |publisher=Vintage |year=1965 |isbn=0394703588 |page=335f |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was used through the 1920s to describe a woman, usually a [[feminist]] or an [[intellectual]].&lt;ref name=&quot;casselss2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 |last=Green
 |first=Jonathon
 |title=Cassell's Dictionary of Slang
 |year=2006
 |publisher=Cassell
 |location=
 |isbn=9780304366361 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Flora Finch]] starred in ''The She-Male Sleuth''&lt;ref name=&quot;lowe2005&quot;&gt;Lowe, Denise (2005). ''An encyclopedic dictionary of women in early American films, 1895-1930.'' Routledge, ISBN 9780789018434&lt;/ref&gt; The term came to have a more negative connotation over time and been used to describe a &quot;hateful woman&quot; or &quot;bitch.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;spears&quot;&gt;Spears, Richard A (1991). ''A Dictionary of Slang and Euphemism.'' Signet, ISBN 0451165543&lt;/ref&gt;  Up through the mid-1970s, it was used to describe an assertive woman, &quot;especially a disliked, distrusted woman; a bitch.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wentworth&quot;&gt;Wentworth, Harold and Stuart Berg Flexner (1975). ''Dictionary of American Slang''. Crowell, ISBN 9780690006704&lt;/ref&gt;

The term later took on a tone that inferred a sexual overtone. In her 1990 book, ''From Masculine To Feminine And All points In Between'', Jennifer Anne Stevens defined&lt;!-- Note: this is a previous meaning for the term, and any discussion of it being &quot;wrong&quot; requires a reference to who said it was wrong at the time that that definition was current. --&gt; ''she-male'' as &quot;usually a [[gay]] male who lives full time as a woman; a gay transgenderist.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;stevens&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 |last=Stevens
 |first=Jennifer Anne
 |title=From Masculine To Feminine And All points In Between
 |year=1990
 |publisher=Different Path Press
 |location=Cambridge, MA 02238
 |isbn=0962626201 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Oxford English Dictionary]]'' defines ''she-male'' as &quot;a passive [[male homosexual]] or [[transvestite]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;OED&quot;&gt;{{cite book
 |last=
 |first=
 |title=Oxford English Dictionary
 |year=1989
 |publisher=Oxford University Press, USA
 |location=Cambridge, MA 02238
 |isbn=978-0198611868 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been used as gay slang for ''[[faggot (slang)|faggot]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;aman1982&quot;&gt;Aman, Reinhold (1982). ''[[Maledicta]]'', Volume 6, Issue 1,  p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Connotations ==
[[File:Shemale.png|100px|thumb|An artist's rendering of a person with female breasts and male genitalia.]]
In 1979, [[Janice Raymond]] employed the term as a derogatory descriptor for transsexual people in her controversial book, ''The Transsexual Empire: The Making of the She-Male''.&lt;ref name=&quot;raymond&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Raymond |first=J. |title=The Transsexual Empire |year=1994 |publisher=Teachers College, Columbia University |place=New York |isbn=0807762725 |postscript=&lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Raymond and other [[cultural feminism|cultural feminists]] like [[Mary Daly]] argue that a &quot;she-male&quot; or &quot;male-to-constructed female&quot; is still male and constitutes a [[patriarchy|patriarchal]] attack by males upon the female [[essentialism|essence]].&lt;ref name=&quot;daly&quot;&gt;Daly, Mary (1985). ''Beyond God the Father: toward a philosophy of women's liberation.'' Beacon Press, ISBN 9780807015032&lt;/ref&gt; In some cultures it can also be used interchangeably with other terms referring to trans women.{{Citation needed|date=November 2009}}

The term has since become an unflattering term applied to male-to-female transsexuals.&lt;ref name=&quot;herbst&quot;/&gt; Psychologists Dana Finnegan and Emily Mcnally write that the term &quot;tends to have demeaning connotations.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;finnegan2002&quot;&gt;Finnegan D, McNally E (2002). ''Counseling Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Substance Abusers: Dual Identities.'' Routledge, ISBN 9780789004031&lt;/ref&gt; French professor John Phillips writes that ''shemale'' is &quot;a linguistic [[oxymoron]] that simultaneously reflects but, by its very impossibility, challenges [[gender binary|[gender] binary]] thinking, collapsing the divide between the [[masculinity|masculine]] and the [[femininity|feminine]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;International Ex&quot;/&gt; Trans author [[Leslie Feinberg]] writes, &quot;'he-she' and 'she-male' describe the person's gender expression with the first pronoun and the birth sex with the second. The hyphenation signals a crisis of language and an apparent social contradiction, since sex and gender are 'supposed' to match.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;feinberg&quot;&gt;Feinberg, Leslie (1997). ''Transgender Warriors.'' Beacon Press, ISBN 9780807079416&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation]] has said the term is a &quot;dehumanizing slur&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;advocate2007&quot;&gt;Staff report (October 05, 2007). [http://www.advocate.com/article.aspx?id=41156 GLAAD Condemns &quot;Dehumanizing&quot; Page Six New York Post Column.] ''[[The Advocate]]''&lt;/ref&gt; and should not be used &quot;except in a direct quote that reveals the bias of the person quoted.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;glaadguide&quot;&gt;[[GLAAD]] [http://www.glaad.org/reference/defamatory GLAAD Media Reference Guide: Defamatory Language.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Some have adopted the term as a self-descriptor but this is often in context of [[sex work]].&lt;ref name=&quot;dixon&quot;&gt;Dixon, D., &amp; Dixon, J. (1998). She-male prostitutes: Who are they, what do they do, and why do they do it. In J. Elias, V. Bullough, V. Elias, &amp; G. Brewer (Eds.), ''Prostitution: On whores, hustlers, and johns'' (pp. 260-266). New York: Prometheus.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;herbst&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;carmichael2002&quot;&gt;Carmichael, Amy (June 8, 2002). Rare 'shemales' seek respect and understanding. ''[[The Toronto Star]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Transsexual author [[Kate Bornstein]] wrote that a friend who self-identified as &quot;she-male&quot; described herself as &quot;tits, big hair, lots of make-up, and a dick.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;bornstein1994&quot;&gt;Bornstein, Kate (1994). ''Gender outlaw: on men, women, and the rest of us.'' Routledge, ISBN 9780415908979&lt;/ref&gt; Sex researchers Mildred Brown and Chloe Rounsley said, &quot;She-males are men, often involved in [[prostitution]], [[pornography]], or the [[adult entertainment]] business, who have undergone breast augmentation but have maintained their genitalia.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;brown1996&quot;&gt;Brown M, Rounsley C. (1996) ''True Selves: Understanding Transsexualism-For Families, Friends, Coworkers, and Helping Professionals.'' Jossey-Bass, ISBN 9780787902711&lt;/ref&gt; According to Professors Laura Castañeda and Shannon Campbell at the [[University of Southern California]]'s [[Annenberg School of Journalism]], &quot;Using the term ''she-male'' for a transsexual woman would be considered highly offensive, for it implies that she is working 'in the [sex] trade.' It may be considered [[libel]]ous.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;castaneda&quot;&gt;Castañeda, Laura and Shannon B. Campbell ''News and Sexuality: Media Portraits of Diversity.'' SAGE, ISBN 9781412909990&lt;/ref&gt; Melissa Hope Ditmore, of the Trafficked Persons Rights Project, notes the term &quot;is an invention of the sex industry, and most transwomen find the term abhorrent.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ditmore&quot;&gt;Ditmore, Melissa Hope (2006). ''Encyclopedia of Prostitution and Sex Work.'' Greenwood Publishing Group, ISBN 9780313329685&lt;/ref&gt; Biologist and transgender activist [[Julia Serano]] notes that it remains &quot;derogatory or sensationalistic.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;serano2007&quot;&gt;Serano, Julia (2007). ''Whipping Girl: A Transsexual Woman on Sexism and the Scapegoating of Femininity.'' Seal press, ISBN 9781580051545, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; According to sex columnist [[Regina Lynn]], &quot;Porn marketers use 'she-male' for a very specific purpose — to sell porn to straight guys without triggering their homophobia — that has nothing to do with actual transgendered people (or helping men overcome their homophobia, either).&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;lynn2007&quot;&gt;Lynn, Regina (March 16, 2007). [http://www.wired.com/sex_drive_daily/2007/03/when_words_fail/ When Words Fail, So Do We.] ''Wired''&lt;/ref&gt; According to sex columnist [[Sasha (journalist)|Sasha]], &quot;The term shemale is used in this setting to denote a fetishized sexual persona and is not typically used by transgendered women outside of sex work. Many transgendered women are offended by this categorization and call themselves T-girls or trans.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sasha&quot;&gt;[[Sasha (journalist)|Sasha]] (October 9, 2008). [http://www.montrealmirror.com/2008/100208/sasha.html Green sex toys.] ''[[Montreal Mirror]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==

In addition to its use in pornography, the term has been used as a [[punch line]] or for rhetorical effect. As part of the 42nd Street Art Project in 1994, designer [[Adelle Lutz]] turned a former shop in [[Times Square]] called American Male into &quot;American She-Male&quot;, with brightly-colored mannequins and clothes made of condoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;sagalyn&quot;&gt;Sagalyn, Lynne B. (2003). ''Times Square Roulette: Remaking the City Icon.'' MIT Press, ISBN 9780262692953&lt;/ref&gt; The 2004 ''[[Arrested Development (TV series)|Arrested Development]]'' episode &quot;[[Sad Sack (Arrested Development episode)|Sad Sack]]&quot; had a gag where Maeby tricks Lindsay into wearing a shirt that says &quot;Shémale&quot;, in order to convince a suitor Lindsay is transgender. Film critic [[Manohla Dargis]] has written about the lack of &quot;real women&quot; in summer blockbusters, claiming [[Judd Apatow]] comedies feature men who act more like leading ladies: &quot;These aren't the she-males you find in the back pages of ''[[The Village Voice]]'', mind you. The Apatow men hit the screen anatomically intact: they’re emasculated but not castrated, as the repeated images of the flopping genitals in ''[[Forgetting Sarah Marshall]]'' remind you.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dargis2009&quot;&gt;Dargis, Manola (May 4, 2008). [http://www.nytimes.com/2008/05/04/movies/moviesspecial/04dargi.html Is There a Real Woman in This Multiplex?] ''[[New York Times]]''&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Wiktionary}}
* [[Futanari]] (a genre of Anime/Manga)
* [[Hermaphrodite]]

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

{{LGBT slang}}
{{Sexual slang}}

[[Category:Transgender]]
[[Category:Transphobia]]
[[Category:Pejorative terms for people]]
[[Category:Sexual slang]]
[[Category:LGBT terms]]
[[Category:Pornography terms]]

[[bg:Shemale]]
[[cs:Shemale]]
[[eo:Virin-viro]]
[[fa:شیمیل]]
[[nl:Shemale]]
[[ja:ニューハーフ]]
[[pl:Shemale]]
[[ru:Shemale]]
[[simple:Shemale]]
[[fi:Shemale]]
[[sv:Shemale]]
[[uk:Shemale]]
[[vi:Shemale]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
