<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33036769" ns="0" title="2011 attack on the Israeli Embassy in Egypt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Pp-protected|small=yes}}
{{copy edit|date=September 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox civil conflict
| title         = 2011 attack on the Israeli embassy in Egypt
| partof        = [[Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Supreme Council of the Armed Forces|events surrounding the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
| image         = &lt;div style=&quot;width:300px; float:none; clear:none;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;position:relative; padding:0; width:300px;&quot;&gt;[[File:Egypt location map.svg|300px]]
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;position: absolute; z-index: 2; top: 19.2%; left: 53.6%; height: 0; width: 0; margin: 0; padding: 0;&quot;&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; text-align: center; left: -4px; top: -4px; width: 8px; font-size: 8px; z-index:100;&quot;&gt;[[File:Red pog.svg|7px]]&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;font-size:90%; line-height: 110%; z-index:90; position: relative; top: -1.5em; width: 6em; right: 6.5em; text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;padding: 1px;&quot;&gt;'''The attack site'''&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
| caption       =
| place         = Israeli embassy at [[Giza]], [[Egypt]]&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot;/&gt;
| coordinates   = {{coord|30|01|43.20|N|31|13|01|E|display=inline}}
| date          = 9–10 September 2011
| status        =
| goals         =
| howmany1      = Several thousand protesters&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;/&gt;
| causes        =
| methods       = [[Demonstration (people)|Demonstrations]], rioting, [[online activism]], infiltration&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost1&quot;/&gt;
| injuries      = ~1,049 Egyptian protesters&lt;ref name=jpost1 /&gt;
| fatalities    = 3 Egyptian protesters&lt;ref name=jpost1 /&gt;
| arrests       =
| concessions   =
}}
On 9 September 2011, several thousand protesters forcibly entered the Israeli embassy in [[Giza]], [[Greater Cairo]], after breaking down a recently constructed wall built to protect the compound.&lt;ref name=autogenerated4 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://ireport.cnn.com/docs/DOC-671532 The return of calm in front of the embassy of Israel in Giza - CNN iReport]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/3/12/21049/Business/Economy/Israeli-workers-in-Egypt-fly-home-in-fear-for-own-.aspx Israeli workers in Egypt fly home in fear for safety - Economy - Business - Ahram Online]&lt;/ref&gt; Later, after the protesters broke into a police station and stole weapons, the police fired [[tear gas]] in an attempt to protect themselves. The demonstrators eventually broke through the security wall and entered the offices of the embassy. Six embassy staff, who had been in a &quot;safe room&quot;, were evacuated from the site by Egyptian [[commando]]s, following the personal intervention of US President [[Barack Obama]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://af.reuters.com/article/egyptNews/idAFL5E7KA0UV20110910 Israel lauds Obama's role in Cairo crisis | News by Country | Reuters]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/494183 Obama asks Egypt to protect Israeli embassy | Al-Masry Al-Youm: Today's News from Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the attack, the Israeli deputy ambassador remained in Cairo; 85 staff members and their families returned to Israel.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;/&gt; The Egyptian army declared a state of alert.

== Background ==
{{main|Egypt–Israel relations}}
[[File:Burning the Israeli flag at embassy in Cairo.jpg|thumb|right|On 15 May 2011, Egyptian protesters waved [[Palestinian flag]]s in front of the Israeli embassy in [[Giza]] as they burned a makeshift [[Israeli flag]].]]
During 2011, relations between Israel and Egypt deteriorated after the resignation of Egyptian President [[Hosni Mubarak]], reaching their lowest point since peace was established between the two nations by the [[Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty|1979 Egypt–Israel Peace Treaty]]. The Israeli-Egyptian border became a region of conflict and instability due to increased militant activity in Egypt's [[Sinai Peninsula]], and anti-Israeli sentiment was expressed in protests by masses of Egyptians in the streets of Giza.

On 18 August 2011, a squad of militants crossed the border from the [[Sinai Peninsula]] into southern Israel, [[2011 southern Israel cross-border attacks|killing eight Israelis]]. The ensuing Israeli counter-terrorist operations in close proximity to the border resulted in the deaths of &quot;at least three&quot; Egyptian soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;/&gt; The soldiers' deaths by Israeli fire{{citation needed|date=September 2011}} ignited protests at the Israeli Embassy in Giza.  During a demonstration on 20 August 2011, an Egyptian protester climbed 20&amp;nbsp;feet up the building's facade to remove the [[Israeli flag]].

The Egyptian [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces]] considered recalling the Egyptian ambassador in Tel Aviv. Eventually, Israel publicly apologized for the deaths of the Egyptian soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;/&gt; Egypt stated that Israel's apology was &quot;insufficient.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz&quot;/&gt;

== The attack ==
{{see also|Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Supreme Council of the Armed Forces#September}}
On 9 September 2011, hundreds of Egyptian protesters began gathering outside of the Israeli embassy.  Around 6:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. local time, they began to assault a concrete security perimeter wall with hammers and a [[battering ram]].&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube&quot;/&gt; Egyptian authorities had erected the wall following intense protests in August.

=== Building infiltration ===
At 12:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. Saturday morning, several thousand protesters&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost&quot;/&gt; breached the security wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;Egyptians protest against military rule - Middle East&quot;/&gt; By 1:00&amp;nbsp;a.m. they had entered the lobby and proceeded through the rest of the building. The demonstrators ransacked the embassy, located on the 20th and 21st floors of the building, and threw items including documents, some marked &quot;[[confidential]]&quot;, from the windows of the building to the crowded street below.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahram&quot;/&gt; The documents were quickly scanned and publicly commented on.{{citation needed|date=September 2011}} Israel later revealed that the remaining Israeli security staff had been separated from the rioters only by the steel door of a [[safe room]] in which they had taken refuge.

In Jerusalem, Israeli Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] and various other senior Israeli officials watched the events unfold from a direct feed from the surveillance cameras installed in the embassy.

Israeli Foreign Ministry spokesman Yigal Palmor estimated that about 3,000 protesters were involved in destroying the security wall.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt; An Israeli diplomat condemned the attack as a &quot;serious violation&quot; of diplomatic behaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera&quot;/&gt;

Immediately after the protesters had infiltrated the embassy, United States Secretary of Defense [[Leon Panetta]] received a call from Israeli [[Ministry of Defense (Israel)|Minister of Defense]] [[Ehud Barak]] asking for help. The United States assisted in assuring the protection of the Israeli embassy personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz1&quot;/&gt; Prime Minister Netanyahu later emphasized that he &quot;would like to thank the US President [[Barack Hussein Obama|Barack Obama]] for his help&quot; in securing the lives of the Israeli embassy staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera2&quot;/&gt;

=== Rescue of embassy staff and end of the riots===
Six Israeli security staff who were on the premises hid inside a reinforced safe room. Egyptian commando forces entered the embassy building and rescued the six Israeli guards.&lt;ref name=autogenerated3 /&gt; All other embassy staff and their family members were escorted to [[Cairo International Airport]]. At 2:40&amp;nbsp;a.m., the Israeli ambassador and approximately 85 other Israeli diplomats and their family members arrived at the airport and were flown out of Egypt. Only the deputy Israeli ambassador remained in Egypt, staying at the US embassy.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes4&quot;/&gt; A senior Egyptian security official stated that the Egyptian commandos had been sent to the embassy after Israeli Ambassador Yitzhak Levanon spoke on the phone with an anonymous member of [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces|Egypt's ruling military council]], and asked him to arrange the safe evacuation of the embassy staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;/&gt;

The demonstration and ransacking of the embassy building continued into the early morning hours as the protesters burned tires and set several police cars on fire.  The Egyptian police eventually suppressed the riots and dispersed the thousands of rioters by using [[tear gas]] and firing warning shots into the air.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

Prime Minister Netanyahu and Former Mossad director Efraim Halevy praised the actions of American president Obama in helping with the evacuation.&lt;ref&gt;Wexler, Robert. [http://www.jpost.com/Opinion/Op-EdContributors/Article.aspx?id=238954 &quot;Defending Obama’s pro-Israel credentials.&quot;] ''The Jerusalem Post'', 22 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
Following the attack, the Egyptian army heightened the state of alert in the country and reinstated martial law, otherwise known as [[State of Emergency]], on a temporary basis.&lt;ref name=&quot;businessweek&quot;/&gt;

On the morning of Saturday, 10 September, [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces|Egypt's ruling military council]] rejected resignation requests that had been submitted by Egyptian Prime Minister [[Essam Sharaf]] and several Egyptian ministers. Their request was made because of the failure to handle the disturbances.&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhuanet&quot;/&gt;

One day after the attacks on the embassy, a group of reporters were attacked by a crowd of people still lingering near the scene of the riots. A reporter and producer were knocked to the ground and trampled, but managed to get to a vehicle in which they retreated, with protesters throwing stones at them. They were able to flee the area without sustaining any major injuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Angry crowd turns on journalists reporting embassy attack in Egypt&quot;/&gt;

== Official reactions ==
;Involved parties
* '''{{Flagu|Egypt}}:''' Following the attack on the Israeli Embassy in Giza, Information Minister [[Osama Heikal]] stated that Egypt is still committed to all of the international treaties to which it is a signatory, and added that Egypt is also committed to the safety of all foreign diplomats residing in the country. In addition, Heikal stated that a series of measures would be taken to ensure that no further disturbances would occur.&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz5&quot;/&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|Israel}}:''' During a televised press conference conducted on the evening of 10 September, Prime Minister [[Benjamin Netanyahu]] emphasized the need to maintain Israel's strategic relations with Egypt, which is crucial to the region's stability. In addition, he thanked the Egyptian commando unit for preventing a disaster.&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost6&quot;/&gt; Netanyahu also stated that the peace agreement with Egypt will be maintained in spite of the violent protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost7&quot;/&gt;

; International
* '''{{Flagu|Bahrain}}:''' Foreign Minister Sheik [[Khalid ibn Ahmad Al Khalifah]] condemned the attack on the Israeli Embassy in Giza. The minister said that &quot;the failure to defend the embassy building is a blatant violation of the [[Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations|1961 Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ynetnews&quot;/&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|Canada}}:''' Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]] released a statement that said, &quot;Our government strongly condemns the attack on the embassy of Israel in Egypt&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;/&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|Germany}}:''' Foreign Minister [[Guido Westerwelle]] released a statement in which he condemned the attack on the Israeli embassy. In addition, the statement said that he expects &quot;the Egyptian authorities to provide for the security of the embassy in accordance with international obligations. Any further escalation of the situation must be avoided.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost8&quot;/&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|Iran}}:''' Deputy head of the [[Islamic Consultative Assembly|Majlis]] Committee on National Security and Foreign Policy [[Esmail Kowsari]] said that members of the Iranian parliament had expressed full support for the &quot;ransacking&quot; of the Israeli embassy in Cairo.&lt;ref&gt;[[Press TV]] [http://www.presstv.ir/detail/198690.html 'Iran Majlis hails raid on Israel embassy'], November 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|United Kingdom}}:''' Prime Minister [[David Cameron]] condemned the attacks on the Israeli embassy, stating that Egypt is responsible for protecting diplomatic property. &quot;I strongly condemn the attack on the Israeli Embassy in Cairo. We have urged the Egyptian authorities to meet their responsibilities under the [[Vienna Convention]] to protect diplomatic property and personnel, including the Israeli Embassy in Cairo. They have reassured us that they take these very seriously.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost9&quot;/&gt;
* '''{{Flagu|United States}}:''' In a statement to the press, the [[White House]] said that President [[Barack Obama]] expressed his great concern about the situation at the embassy and the security of the Israelis serving there.&lt;ref name=&quot;thestatesman&quot;/&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|35em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;Angry crowd turns on journalists reporting embassy attack in Egypt&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Watson|first=Ivan|title=Angry crowd turns on journalists reporting embassy attack in Egypt|url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/09/10/egypt.journalists.targeted/|accessdate=11 September 2011|newspaper=CNN|date=11 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Egyptians protest against military rule - Middle East&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2011/09/20119993150747146.html |title=Egyptians protest against military rule - Middle East |publisher=Al Jazeera English |date=2001-09-11 |accessdate=2011-09-10}} {{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ahram&quot;&gt;[http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContentP/1/20856/Egypt/The-storming-of-Cairos-Israeli-embassy-an-eyewitne.aspx The storming of Cairo's Israeli embassy: an eyewitness account (part I) - Politics - Egypt - Ahram Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera&quot;&gt;[http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/09/201191064219436657.html Israel pulls envoy after embassy attack - Middle East - Al Jazeera English]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;aljazeera2&quot;&gt;.http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/09/201191064219436657.html&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=From Mohamed Fadel Fahmy, For CNN |url=http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/09/09/egypt.protests/index.html |title=Protesters in Egypt breach wall, enter Israeli Embassy - CNN.com |publisher=Edition.cnn.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated2&quot;&gt;[http://articles.cnn.com/2011-08-21/world/israel.egypt.tensions_1_israel-and-egypt-egyptian-border-amos-gilad?_s=PM:WORLD Egypt says Israel apology of troop deaths is insufficient - CNN]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated3&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5gOeNzm5enw2UCmoyMeAhPHxkHCOw?docId=ce87ccb85ead47fabe87b2d2b47e0fd0 The Associated Press: Egypt commandos save 6 Israelis in embassy attack]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated4&quot;&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=237393 J'lem seeks US help in guarding breached Cairo embassy]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;businessweek&quot;&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-09-10/egypt-declares-state-of-emergency-after-israeli-embassy-struck.html Egypt Declares Emergency After Attack on Israeli Embassy - Businessweek]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/09/09/egypt.protests/index.html?hpt=hp_t1 Egypt declares state of alert in wake of attack on Israeli Embassy]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;foxnews&quot;&gt;[http://www.foxnews.com/world/2011/08/20/israel-apologizes-for-deaths-egyptian-troops-in-shootout-with-militants/ Israel Apologizes For Deaths Of Egyptian Troops In Shootout With Militants | Fox News]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gON8NTBbMy_Bvm14RlCMBjaxRcAw?docId=CNG.4dd28a7c98f80c593e306e83d0eeefa5.8f1 AFP: Canada condemns attack on Israeli embassy in Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz&quot;&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/middle-east/egypt-deems-israel-s-apology-for-policemen-deaths-insufficient-1.379797 Egypt deems Israel's apology for policemen deaths 'insufficient' - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz1&quot;&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/u-s-told-egypt-it-must-rescue-israeli-embassy-workers-or-suffer-consequences-sources-say-1.383675 U.S. told Egypt it must rescue Israeli embassy workers or suffer 'consequences,' sources say - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News] {{dead link|date=September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;haaretz5&quot;&gt;[http://www.haaretz.com/news/diplomacy-defense/egypt-we-are-committed-to-maintaining-israel-peace-treaty-1.383642 Egypt: We are committed to maintaining Israel peace treaty - Haaretz Daily Newspaper | Israel News]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/08/20/ehud-barak-egyptian-soldiers_n_932097.html Ehud Barak, Israel Defense Minister, Regrets Deaths Of Egyptian Troops]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;huffingtonpost6&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/09/10/israel-embassy-attacked-egypt_n_956627.html Israel Embassy Attacked: Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu Condemns Violence In Egypt]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost&quot;&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=237393 Egyptians attack Israeli embassy; Obama is... JPost - Middle East]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Egypt says it will try those behind Israel mission violence|url=http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=237437|accessdate=10 September 2011|newspaper=The Jerusalem Post and Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost7&quot;&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=237452 Netanyahu: Peace agreement with Egypt will b... JPost - Headlines]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost8&quot;&gt;[http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=237434 Germany condemns attack on Israeli Embassy i... JPost - Headlines]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;jpost9&quot;&gt;http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=237435 UK's Cameron condemns attack on Israeli Embassy in Cairo&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/11/world/middleeast/11egypt.html?_r=1 After Attack on Embassy, Egypt Vows a Tougher Stance on Protests - NYTimes.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes4&quot;&gt;David Kirkpatrick, [http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/11/world/middleeast/11egypt.html Israelis Quit Cairo Embassy as Protesters Invade Offices] ''[[New York Times]]'' 10 September 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thestatesman&quot;&gt;http://www.thestatesman.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=382788&amp;catid=37 Israeli Embassy attacked in Egypt, envoy flees 10 September 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;xinhuanet&quot;&gt;[http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/world/2011-09/10/c_131132013.htm Egypt's ruling military council rejects PM's resignation]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;&gt;[http://news.yahoo.com/egypt-commandos-save-6-israelis-embassy-attack-190607978.html Egypt commandos save 6 Israelis in embassy attack - Yahoo! News]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ynetnews&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4120247,00.html |title=Egypt to try Israel embassy rioters - Israel News, Ynetnews |publisher=Ynetnews.com |date=1995-06-20 |accessdate=2011-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H3lpufbsJMI Egyptians break concrete wall at Cairo's Israeli embassy on Sept. 9, 2011 - YouTube]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== External links ==
{{Portal box|Egypt|Israel}}
* [http://www.jpost.com/MiddleEast/Article.aspx?id=237423 Timeline of Israel embassy attack in Cairo] - published on the [[Jerusalem Post]] on 10 September 2011
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-14863671 In pictures: Cairo embassy attack] - published on [[BBC News]] on 10 September 2011
* [http://af.reuters.com/article/commoditiesNews/idAFL5E7KA10X20110910 Egypt vows to try those who targeted Israel mission] - published on [[Reuters]] on 10 September 2011
* [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/africaandindianocean/egypt/8754193/Israeli-ambassador-to-Egypt-flees-in-night-of-rioting.html Israeli ambassador to Egypt flees in night of rioting] - published on [[The Daily Telegraph]] on September 10, 2011
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-14863756 Egyptian security forces clash with protesters] - published on [[BBC News]] on September 10, 2011
* [http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/09/09/egypt.protests/ Egypt declares state of alert in wake of attack on Israeli Embassy] - published on [[CNN]] on September 10, 2011
* [http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/0/20875/Egypt/The-storming-of-Cairos-Israeli-embassy-eyewitness-.aspx The storming of Cairo's Israeli embassy: eyewitness account (part II)] - published on [[Ahram Online]] on September 11, 2011

{{DEFAULTSORT:Embassy Attack, Israeli, 2011 In Cairo}}
[[Category:2011 in Egypt]]
[[Category:2011 in international relations]]
[[Category:Diplomatic incidents]]
[[Category:Egypt–Israel relations]]
[[Category:Political controversies]]
[[Category:Terrorist attacks against embassies]]

[[ar:اقتحام السفارة الإسرائيلية في مصر]]
[[fa:تصرف سفارت اسرائیل در مصر]]
[[id:Penyerbuan Kedutaan Besar Israel di Kairo (2011)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
