<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33035590" ns="0" title="Programming The Nation? The Film"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox film
| name           = Programming The Nation?
| image          = PTN Movie Poster 2011 27x40 8bit.jpg
| alt            = &lt;!-- see WP:ALT --&gt;
| caption        = {{deletable image-caption|Monday, 3 October 2011|date=October 2011}} Programming The Nation? (2011)
| director       = Jeff Warrick
| producer       = Marty Collins
| writer         = Jeff Warrick
| starring       = [[Noam Chomsky]], [[Amy Goodman]], [[Dennis Kucinich]], Eldon Taylor, &amp; [[Wilson Bryan Key]]
| music          = Evan Evans and Robin Macomber
| cinematography = Marty Collins
| editing        = Jeff Warrick
| studio         = Digital Media Factory &amp; Ignite Productions
| distributor    = International Film Circuit (theatrical)
| released       = {{Film date|2009|08||USA}}
| runtime        = 105 minutes
| country        = {{Film US}}
| language       = English
| budget         = $500,000 (estimated)
| gross          = 
}}

'''''Programming The Nation?'''''&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb info&quot;&gt;{{imdb title|id=1023345}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a 2011 feature social documentary written, produced and directed by [[Jeff Warrick]].  The film revisits the alleged history, research, implementation, and potential effects of subliminal programming in American mass-media, including interviews with [[Noam Chomsky]], [[Amy Goodman]], [[Dennis Kucinich]], Eldon Taylor, [[Wilson Bryan Key]], and other authors and experts in the field of advertising, psychology, music, film, politics, and military weaponry.

[[LA Times]]'s Kevin Thomas [http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/la-et-capsules-programming-the-nation-20110923,0,3550409.story reviewed] ''Programming The Nation?'' noting that &quot;Warrick is [] rightly concerned by the power of media conglomerates to manipulate the news.&quot;

== Interviewees in Programming The Nation? ==

[[Noam Chomsky]], co-creator of ''Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media,'' ''Profit Over People,'' and ''Failed States.'' Chomsky is a retired and world-renowned Massachusetts Institute of Technology Professor (Department of Linguistics &amp; Philosophy), and asserts that “The purpose of the ad is to delude and deceive you with imagery… [The public] will be uninformed and make an irrational choice.   That’s what businessmen spend hundreds and millions of dollars a year on…what they want is coercion and control.&quot;

Wilson Bryan Key, &quot;The Godfather of Subliminals,&quot; wrote ''The Age of Manipulation'', ''Media Sexploitation'', and best seller ''Subliminal Seduction''. &quot;You look at something, smell something, hear something, it's going into your brain at the speed of light... And all being retained...&quot; Key claims that only small bits and fragments of this actually rise to the &quot;conscious surface.&quot;  Key states that Freud warned about &quot;toying&quot; with the subconscious due to its highly unexplored and misunderstood nature, coupled with its capacity to set off unpredictable pathological response.

August Bullock, author of ''The Secret Sales Pitch,'' discusses Sigmund Freud's probing of the subconscious mind, and his postulations about the presence of hidden emotions and drives. According to Bullock, Freud believed the barrier between conscious and subconscious awareness relaxed and through analyzing and interpreting dreams, we could better understand out underlying motivations and emotions and the conflicts caused by them.

[[Dennis Kucinich]] assumed office in 1997 as a member of the U.S. House of Representative from Ohio’s 10th district. He is currently an incumbent and the Chairman of the Domestic Policy Subcommittee of the House Committee on Oversight and Government Reform.  From 1977 to 1979, Kucinich was the mayor of Cleveland, Ohio.  A candidate for the Democratic nomination of the US President in 2004 and in 2008 elections, popularized his title of attaining “the strongest liberal” perspective.  &quot;There should be criminal implications for this kind of behavior [media manipulation]” Kucinich states.

[[Douglas Rushkoff]], author of ''Coercion'', asserts that Edward Bernays, Freud's nephew, utilized Freudian psychoanalytic theory to provide consumers with substitutes for their carnal urges in the form of a product. 

Dr. Eldon Taylor, author of ''Mind Programming,'' claims that Edward Bernays, in his book, &quot;Propaganda&quot; states that it's &quot;the duty of marketing people to lead an otherwise, unleadable, irrational, free people to making a consensus or a decision that was a responsible decision.&quot; Taylor says marketing is founded on manipulation and influence.

[[Amy Goodman]] is a progressive American broadcast journalist, columnist, author, and investigative reporter.  She is the principal host and co-founder of the independent global news program, Democracy Now!.  Goodman has received many awards for her accomplishments such as the Robert F. Kennedy Journalism Award, George Polk Award, and the Islamic Community Award for Journalism. Her books are nationally recognized and have appeared on the New York Times bestseller list.  Goodman’s narration of the film ''One Bright Shining Moment: The Forgotten Summer of George McGovern'' won the Sarasota Film Festival’s award for “Best Documentary Feature.” Goodman’s stance on mainstream news media practices :“They have a responsibility to bring out full diversity of opinion and to get to the truth, not to bring you news stories that are disguised as their own when they are simply government or corporate propaganda.”

== Cast ==
'' Cast List From: [http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1023345/fullcredits#cast Programming the Nation? IMDB Page] ''
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
| [[John B. Alexander]] || Richard Beggs
|-
| [[Nick Begich]] || August Bullock
|-
| [[Noam Chomsky]] || Christopher Coppola
|-
| Phillip Farber || David Fricke
|-
| [[Amy Goodman]] || Hilton A. Green
|-
| Anthony Greenwald || Andy Johns
|-
| Wilson Bryan Key ||  Dennis Kucinich
|-
| Jerry Mander || Mark Crispin Miller
|-
| Mark Mothersbaugh  || William Poundstone
|-
| [[Douglas Rushkoff]] || Joe Schimmel
|-
| Howard Shevrin || Ann Simonton
|-
| Geoff Tate || [[Eldon Taylor]]
|-
| Diane Watson || Bill Yousman
|}

==== Previous Screenings&lt;ref&gt;http://www.programmingthenation.com/screenings.html&lt;/ref&gt; ====

True Crime New York Series: Post 9/11 Universe - Sept. 16, 2011

The Maysles Cinema, New York, NY

7:30 PM Screening followed by Q&amp;A with filmmaker, Jeff Warrick (via Skype), and WHCR, 90.3FM radio talk show host, Leroy Baylor, &quot;The Voice of Harlem&quot; - (in person).

Theatrical Premiere - New York City   -   August 19–25, 2011

Quad Cinema - Official Announcement

An International Film Circuit and Buzzledom Release

St. Pete for Peace Film Series - Wednesday, October 27, 2010

Cafe Bohemia

St Pete for Peace, in conjunction with Café Bohemia, sponsors a free film showing every Wednesday night in the outside patio of this downtown St Petersburg bistro. The weekly film series, running since January 2007, shows documentaries, full feature movies and other films on such topics as U.S. militarism, environmentalism, political processes, and other global areas of concern.

Seattle True Independent Film Festival - June 8, 2010

Northwest Film Forum

Filmmaker, Jeff Warrick and Interviewee, Dr. Eldon Taylor will both be in attendance for Q&amp;A following the film. Online Festival Schedule

Carnegie Community Center Vancouver, B.C. - June 12, 2010

This free screening is part of a weekly event called Documentary Evenings held by Colleen Carroll at the Downtown East Side Carnegie Community Center in Vancouver, B.C. Canada. Every Saturday night they show Indie Docs that are not covered in mainstream media to the economically disadvantaged. Free refreshments are also provided.

== See also ==
[[Dennis Kucinich]]
[[Amy Goodman]]

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

== External links ==
* http://www.programmingthenation.com
* http://www.programmingthenation.com/screenings.html

[[Category:2010s documentary films]]
[[Category:American documentary films]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
