<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Windows App Store" to="Features new to Windows 8" tofragment="Windows App Store" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="32918892" ns="0" title="Features new to Windows 8"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Windows 8}}
[[Windows 8]] is expected to include several new features, including [[USB 3.0]] support, Live ID integration, the Windows App Store, the ability to run from USB Flash drives with [[Windows To Go]], and easier system restore options, among others.

== Development platform ==
===Language and standards support===
Windows 8 has a new developer platform according to Microsoft Vice President Julie Larson-Green, who called it &quot;our new developer platform, which is...based on [[HTML5]] and [[JavaScript]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Why Microsoft has made developers horrified about coding for Windows 8&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url= http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2011/06/html5-centric-windows-8-leaves-microsoft-developers-horrified.ars |title= Why Microsoft has made developers horrified about coding for Windows 8 |author= Peter Bright |publisher= Arstechnica |date= 2011-06-13 |accessdate= 2011-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The new applications developed for Windows 8 could be easily ported as a [[Metro (design language)|Metro]] style application and developers could use any existing Windows Application Development language to port applications as a Metro style app (by adding minimal amount of code). This is possible because of the architectural changes done to the Windows platform. All applications developed whether using [[C Sharp (programming language)|C#]], [[Microsoft Foundation Class Library|MFC]] or HTML5/JavaScript will translate into WinRT (Windows Runtime) API's, which sits above the Windows Kernel directly.  The new applications run in full-screen, but two of them can be displayed side-by-side using &quot;Snap&quot;. Examples of new applications that were demoed include a [[Twitter]] client, a weather application, a stock-tracking application, an [[RSS]] news feeder, and a virtual piano.

The new platform is primarily designed for [[16:9]] screen resolutions, with 1366×768 and larger screens able to display two Windows 8 &quot;Metro-style&quot; applications side-by-side by &quot;snapping&quot;. 1024×768 screens can display one application in full-screen, and 1024×600 screens can only use the traditional desktop applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.infopackets.com/news/business/microsoft/2011/20110603_microsoft_demos_windows_8_at_first_public_event.htm | title=Microsoft Demos Windows 8 at First Public Event |publisher=Infopackets.com |date=2011-08-20 |accessdate=2011-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows 8 also introduces [[API]]s to support [[Near Field Communication]] (NFC) on Windows 8 devices, allowing functionality like launching URLs/applications and sharing of information between devices via NFC.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=NFC: Windows 8′s hidden connection to tags and devices|url=http://www.istartedsomething.com/20110917/nfc-windows-8s-hidden-connection-to-tags-and-devices/|publisher=istartedsomething.com|accessdate=19 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Windows Store ===
{{Main|Windows Store}}
Microsoft has confirmed the introduction of a Windows Store on Windows 8, similar to the [[Mac App Store]], that allows developers to publish their Metro-style applications on Windows 8 devices. The Windows Store will also allow developers to publish their Win32 or &quot;traditional desktop&quot; applications, however, the store will only provide links to the application on their website. Ted Dworkin, a Partner Director of Program Management on the Windows Web Services team highlighted that the Windows Store will be the only means of distributing Metro-style apps to users to allow Microsoft to scan apps for security flaws and malware.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Tom|first=Warren|title=Microsoft details and demos the Windows Store for Windows 8|url=http://www.winrumors.com/microsoft-details-and-demos-the-windows-store-for-windows-8-video/|publisher=Winrumors.com|accessdate=19 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The licensing and revenue share through the Windows Store has yet to be confirmed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Paul |first=Ian |url=http://www.pcworld.com/article/239994/windows_8_app_store_what_we_know_so_far.html |title=Windows 8 App Store: What We Know So Far |publisher=PCWorld |date=2011-09-14 |accessdate=2011-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Shell and user interface ==
[[File:Win8 lock screen.png|thumb|right|220px|Metro-style lock screen]]
[[Image:Windows8102MultiMonitorAndApp.png|thumb|Screenshot showing Windows 8's ability to pin apps and show different wallpapers on different monitors, as well as displaying the new Explorer file browser interface, Task Manager, and multi-monitor taskbar (in &quot;Duplicated on all taskbars&quot; mode).]]

===Metro style===

Windows 8 features an extensively redesigned &quot;[[Metro (user interface)|Metro]]-style&quot; user interface, optimized for touchscreens as well as mice and keyboards. A new &quot;Start screen&quot;, similar to the one in [[Windows Phone 7]], includes live application tiles. The start screen replaces the Start menu, being triggered by the Start button or Windows key, and is also the first screen shown on start up. The user can go to the regular desktop by choosing the &quot;Desktop&quot; tile or a traditional desktop-based application. The Start screen also displays the user's name and picture.

Windows 8 features a new login/lock screen that shows the date and time and notifications, along with a customizable background.

===Picture Password===
A new authentication method allows users to sketch in three different places over the picture to login, instead of typing a password.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://channel9.msdn.com/events/BUILD/BUILD2011/KEY-0001 |title=Keynote #1 &amp;#124; BUILD2011 &amp;#124; Channel 9 |publisher=Channel9.msdn.com |date=2011-09-13 |accessdate=2011-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=ankur@ankurmittal.com |url=http://windows8beta.com/2011/09/windows-8-picture-password-patent-filed-by-microsoft |title=Windows 8 Picture Password Patent Filed by Microsoft |publisher=Windows 8 Beta |date=2011-09-21 |accessdate=2011-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taskbar===
Windows 8 provides a configurable taskbar in the traditional Windows desktop that spans multiple monitors. The Multiple Monitor Taskbar can be turned on and off and is used to display the minimized windows. Similarly, Windows 8 provides the user with the ability to show different wallpapers on different monitors, or the same wallpaper stretched across multiple monitors.

===Windows Explorer===
Similar to [[Microsoft Office 2010]] and [[Windows Live Essentials]], the re-designed Windows Explorer will use the [[Ribbon interface]] to enhance discoverability of commands and bring relevant commands to users depending on their file selection. For example, selecting photos in a folder brings up tools to rotate the photos and to start a slide show. The interface was selected to bring forward the most commonly used commands for easy access.&lt;ref name=&quot;Explorer Improvements&quot;&gt;[http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/08/29/improvements-in-windows-explorer.aspx &quot;Improvements in Windows Explorer&quot;]. Building Windows 8. Microsoft.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additionally, Windows Explorer features a redesigned preview pane that takes advantage of widescreen layouts and the &quot;Up&quot; button removed from Windows Explorer in [[Windows Vista]] and [[Windows 7]] is now included in the interface.&lt;ref name=&quot;Explorer Improvements&quot; /&gt;

Windows Explorer will feature a new user interface for copying and moving files, offering both a simplified interface and an advanced interface for users to monitor the speed of the operations. Users now view all simultaneous file operations in one consolidated window, and can pause file operations in progress.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/08/23/improving-our-file-management-basics-copy-move-rename-and-delete.aspx &quot;Improving our file management basics: copy, move, rename and delete&quot;]. Building Windows 8.&lt;/ref&gt; A new interface has also been introduced for managing file name collisions in a file operation, allowing users to easily control which conflicting files are copied.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/08/26/designing-the-windows-8-file-name-collision-experience.aspx &quot;Designing the Windows 8 file name collision experience&quot;]. Building Windows 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Windows Explorer can now mount [[ISO image|ISO]], [[IMG (file format)|IMG]], and [[VHD (file format)|VHD]] files as virtual drives through simple right-clicks or the Explorer toolbar&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Accessing data in ISO and VHD files|url=http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/08/30/accessing-data-in-iso-and-vhd-files.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Windows 7 could mount VHDs but in a less-discoverable way via the Disk Management section in the Computer Management MMC&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sevenforums.com/tutorials/566-virtual-hard-disk-create-attach-vhd.html Virtual Hard Disk - Create and Attach VHD]&lt;/ref&gt;).
===Task Manager===
A new Task Manager replaces [[Windows Task Manager]] (though the old version is also included). 

The following changes were made:
*The tabs are hidden by default. This view only shows applications.
*Resource utilization in the Processes tab is shown with various shades of yellow, with darker color representing heavier use.
*The Performance tab is split into CPU, memory, disk, Ethernet, and wireless network (if applicable) sections. There are overall graphs for each, and clicking on one reaches details for that particular resource.
**The CPU tab no longer displays individual graphs for every logical processor on the system by default. It now can show data for each [[Non-uniform memory access|NUMA]] node.
**The CPU tab now displays simple percentages on heat-mapping tiles to display utilization for systems with many (64 or more, up to 640) logical processors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/10/27/using-task-manager-with-64-logical-processors.aspx | title=Using Task Manager with 64+ logical processors | accessdate=October 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The color used for these heat maps is blue, with darker color again indicating heavier utilization.
**Hovering the cursor over any logical processor's data now shows the NUMA node of that processor and its ID.
*A new Startup tab has been added that lists startup applications.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.itproportal.com/2011/10/24/how-get-most-out-new-windows-8-task-manager/ | title=How to Get the Most out of New Windows 8 Task Manager? | accessdate=October 29, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The Processes tab now lists application names, application status, and overall usage data for CPU, memory, hard disk, and network resources for each process.
**The new task manager recognizes when a [[WinRT]] application is in &quot;Suspended&quot; status.
**The normal process information found in the older Task Manager can be found in the new Details tab.

==New easy restore==
The Developer Preview comes with two new recovery functions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/home/br229518 Windows Dev Center]&lt;/ref&gt; Namely, '''Refresh''' and '''Reset''', which both make a complete restore easier than a re-installation. The former keeps all settings &amp; files of the user intact and only reverses all changes to Windows files to its original state and removes all installed programs and apps. The latter deletes all files and effectively re-installs Windows, but without any additional user input such as agreeing to license agreements or selecting a hard disk required. After a reset completes, the user will be asked for the product key and will then proceed to account creation.&lt;ref&gt;[http://arstechnica.com/microsoft/news/2011/09/making-the-lives-of-it-easier-windows-8-refresh-reset-and-windows-to-go.ars Ars Technica - Making the lives of IT easier: Windows 8 Refresh, Reset, and Windows To Go]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Windows Live ID integration==
One big change is that user accounts do not have to be local-only anymore but can be linked up to one's Windows Live ID. This has the advantage that users will not lose their settings and files as they move from their home computer to their work laptop or to any other computer also using Windows 8.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.askvg.com/what-are-the-benefits-of-windows-live-id-integration-in-windows-8/ askvg.com Tweaking with Vishal - Windows 8 Live ID Integration]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Windows To Go==
[[File:Windows To Go USB Drive.png|thumb|Bootable [[Windows To Go]] USB flash drive|link=Windows To Go]]
{{Main|Windows To Go}}
[[Windows To Go]] is an upcoming Windows 8 feature that will allow users to create a bootable USB Flash drive (usually called a [[Live USB]]) with Windows 8 in it, including the user's programs, settings, and files.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Gregg Keizer |url=http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9220004/Windows_8_will_run_from_USB_thumb_drive?taxonomyId=125 |title=Windows 8 will run from USB thumb drive |publisher=Computerworld |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/232480/technology/windows-8-fits-on-a-thumb-drive |title=Windows 8 fits on a thumb drive - Technology - GMA News Online - Latest Philippine News |publisher=Gmanews.tv |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.softpedia.com/news/Windows-8-Running-on-a-USB-Windows-To-Go-221470.shtml |title=Windows 8 Running on a USB – Windows To Go - Softpedia |publisher=News.softpedia.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.engadget.com/2011/04/15/windows-8-to-feature-usb-runnable-portable-workspaces-sales-of/ |title=Windows 8 to feature USB-runnable Portable Workspaces, sales of 16GB thumb drives set to soar |publisher=Engadget |date=2011-04-15 |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is planned to work on both USB 2.0 and USB 3.0, and both on legacy BIOS and UEFI firmware.&lt;ref name=&quot;techie-buzz1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://techie-buzz.com/microsoft/windows-8-usb-to-go-demo.html |title=[Videos&amp;#93; Microsoft Demonstrates Windows To Go (Run Windows 8 From USB On Any PC) |publisher=Techie-buzz.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to that, the system will freeze if the USB drive is removed, and will continue to operate if the USB drive is inserted in the next 60 seconds after removal.&lt;ref name=&quot;techie-buzz1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xFSLy2u4eCc&amp;feature=player_embedded |title=What Happens When You Remove A Windows To Go USB drive (Windows 8) |publisher=YouTube |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Protogon filesystem==
Windows 8 will supposedly support a new filesystem codenamed [[Protogon]].  Not much is published about the new filesystem.  The Developer Preview of Windows 8 harbors [[Windows registry|registry]] references regarding Protogon. Certain builds of Windows 8 supposedly allow users to [[Disk formatting|format]] a [[Disk partitioning|partition]] with the Protogon filesystem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neowin.net/news/windows-8-new-protogon-filesystem-could-be-the-next-big-thing |title=Windows 8: New &quot;Protogon&quot; filesystem could be the next big thing |publisher=Neowin.net |date= |accessdate=2011-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Device support ==
===USB 3.0===
Windows 8 will have built-in support of [[USB 3.0]] for better power management and longer battery life.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.zdnet.com/blog/microsoft/microsoft-to-provide-usb-30-support-for-better-battery-life-in-windows-8/10396 Microsoft to provide USB 3.0 support for better battery life in Windows 8]&lt;/ref&gt;

==New Architecture Support==
Windows 8 will support System on a Chip (SoC) architectures, including ARM-based systems. On the x86 architecture, Intel Corporation and AMD continue their work on low-power SoC designs that fully support Windows.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/press/2011/jan11/01-05SOCsupport.mspx |title=Microsoft Announces Support of System on a Chip Architectures From Intel, AMD, and ARM for Next Version of Windows: January 5, 2011 |publisher=Microsoft.com |date=2011-01-05 |accessdate=2011-11-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Other features and changes ==
===Activation===
Mike Angiulo confirmed at Computex 2011 that Windows 8 will use OEM Activation 3.0 instead of OEM Activation 2.1 (used by Windows 7), which supposedly makes it less prone to cracks.

===Virtualization===
Windows 8 will also include Microsoft's [[Hyper-V]] virtualization software.  Previously only offered in Windows Server, Hyper-V will now be available in client versions of Windows for the first time.  The system requirements for Hyper-V are a 64-bit processor, a 64-bit version of Windows 8, and a minimum of 4 GB of RAM.  Hyper-V also requires a 64-bit system that has [[Second Level Address Translation]] (SLAT), a feature that helps with memory management.  Many of Intel's and AMD's recent processors support this feature, including many of Intel's i-Series processors (with [[Extended Page Table]]) and AMD's 10h family processors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.cnet.com/8301-10805_3-20103376-75/windows-8-to-include-hyper-v-virtualization/ |title= Microsoft announces Hyper-V in Windows 8 |publisher=cnet.com |date=2011-09-08}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shorter boot times===
On September 8, 2011, Microsoft announced that Windows 8 has short boot times, because it saves the [[Kernel (computing)|kernel]]'s memory to the hard disk on shutdown (similar to the existing [[Hibernation (computing)|hibernate]] option) and reloads it on start up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.winsupersite.com/blog/supersite-blog-39/windows8/microsoft-touts-incredible-windows-8-boot-times-140515 | title=Microsoft Touts Incredible Windows 8 Boot Times | accessdate=September 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Boot security===
Windows 8 will support the [[Unified Extensible Firmware Interface|UEFI]] secure boot feature.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/archive/2011/09/22/protecting-the-pre-os-environment-with-uefi.aspx|title=Protecting the pre-OS environment with UEFI}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This will enable new foundation for an architecturally neutral approach to platform and firmware security. It is based on  Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) process to validate firmware images before they are allowed to execute, secure boot helps reduce the risk of boot loader attacks.

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://blogs.msdn.com/b/b8/ Building Windows 8 Blog]

[[Category:Windows 8]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
