<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33121168" ns="0" title="Occupy Wall Street"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the protests in New York City|the wider movement|Occupy movement}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2011}}
{{Pp-semi|expiry=January 2, 2012|small=yes}}
{{Infobox civil conflict
| title = Occupy Wall Street
| image = [[Image:Wall-Street-1.jpg|alt=Poster depicting a female ballerina pirouetting on the back of the Charging Bull statue on Wall Street; on the street behind her, a line of gas-masked rioters struggle through smoke. Text on the poster reads: &quot;What is our one demand? #OCCUPYWALLSTREET September 17th. Bring Tent.&quot;]]
|partof = the [[Occupy movement]]
| caption = ''Adbusters'' poster promoting the start date of the occupation, September 17, 2011.
| date = {{Start date|2011|09|17}}&amp;nbsp;– ''ongoing''&lt;br&gt;({{Age in days|2011|09|17}} days)
| place= [[New York City]]
| coordinates =
| causes = [[Wealth inequality in the United States|Wealth inequality]], [[Big Business#Influence over government|Corporate influence of government]], [[Populism]], (in support of) [[Social Democracy]], ''inter alia''.
| status = Ongoing
| goals =
| result =
| methods = &lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;
*[[Non violent protest]]
*[[Civil disobedience]]
*[[Occupation (protest)|Occupation]]
*[[Picketing (protest)|Picketing]]
*[[Demonstration (people)|Demonstrations]]
*[[Internet activism]]
| side1=
| side2=
| side3=
| leadfigures1 =
| leadfigures2 =
| leadfigures3 =
| howmany1 =
| howmany2 =
| howmany3 = Zuccotti Park

'''Other activity in NYC: '''
*2,000+ marchers &lt;br/&gt;(march on police headquarters, October 2, 2011)&lt;ref name=&quot;Arrests-BBC&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Hundreds of Occupy Wall Street protesters arrested|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15140671|accessdate=October 2, 2011|newspaper=BBC News  |date=October 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*700+ marchers &lt;br/&gt;(crossing Brooklyn Bridge, October 3, 2011)&lt;ref name=700arrest/&gt;

*15,000+ marchers &lt;br/&gt;(Lower Manhattan solidarity march, October 5, 2011)&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street: protests and reaction Thursday October 6&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/blog/2011/oct/06/occupy-wall-street-protests-live |accessdate=October 7, 2011 |newspaper=Guardian |title=Occupy Wall Street: protests and reaction Thursday 6 October |first=Adam |last=Gabbatt |date=October 6, 2011 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*6,000+ marchers &lt;br/&gt;(Times Square recruitment center march, October 15, 2011)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20111017/ECONOMY/111019895 “Wall Street protests span continents, arrests climb“], ''Crain's New York Business'', October 17, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;
| notes =
}}

&lt;!-- Definition : name, location, date --&gt;
'''Occupy Wall Street''' ('''OWS''') is an ongoing series of [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]] initiated by the Canadian activist group [[Adbusters]] which began September 17, 2011 in [[Zuccotti Park]], located in [[New York City]]'s [[Wall Street]] financial district. The protests are against social and [[economic inequality]], high unemployment, greed, as well as corruption, and the undue influence of corporations—particularly from the [[financial services]] sector—on government. The protesters' slogan ''[[We are the 99%]]'' refers to the growing [[income inequality in the United States|difference in wealth]] in the U.S. between the wealthiest 1% and the rest of the population.

==Background==
===Origin===
In a July 13, 2011 blog post, the Canadian-based Adbusters Foundation, best known for its advertisement-free [[Anti-consumerism|anti-consumerist]] magazine ''[[Adbusters]]'', proposed a peaceful occupation of Wall Street to protest corporate influence on democracy, the absence of legal repercussions for the bankers behind the recent global financial crisis, and a growing disparity in wealth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/technology/technology-news/from-a-single-hashtag-a-protest-circled-the-world-20111019-1m72j.html |title=From a single hashtag, a protest circled the world |publisher=Brisbanetimes.com.au |date=2011-10-19 |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Fleming|first=Andrew|title=Adbusters sparks Wall Street protest Vancouver-based activists behind street actions in the U.S|url=http://www.vancourier.com/Adbusters+sparks+Wall+Street+protest/5466332/story.html|publisher=The Vancouver Courier|date=September 27, 2011|accessdate=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  They sought to combine the symbolic location of the 2011 protests in [[Tahrir Square#2011 Egyptian Revolution|Tahrir Square]] with the [[consensus decision making]] of the [[2011 Spanish protests]].&lt;ref name=&quot;huffpo&quot;&gt;[http://www.huffingtonpost.com/shira-lazar/micah-white-adbusters-_b_996931.html Sira Lazar “Occupy Wall Street: Interview With Micah White From Adbusters”, Huffington Post, October 7, 2011, at 3:40 in interview]&lt;/ref&gt; Adbusters' senior editor [[Micah M. White|Micah White]] said they had suggested the protest via their email list and it &quot;was spontaneously taken up by all the people of the world.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Fleming&quot;/&gt; Adbusters' website said that from their &quot;one simple demand, a presidential commission to separate money from politics,&quot; they would &quot;start setting the agenda for a new America.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wallstreet&quot;&gt;[http://www.adbusters.org/blogs/adbusters-blog/occupywallstreet.html Adbusters], ''Adbusters'', July 13, 2011; accessed September 30, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  They promoted the protest with a poster featuring a dancer atop Wall Street's iconic [[Charging Bull]].&lt;ref name=&quot;inline.poster&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|journal=[[The Link (newspaper)|The Link]]|title=The Ballerina and the Bull: Adbusters' Micah White on 'The Last Great Social Movement'|first=Laura|last=Beeston|date=October 11, 2011|url=http://thelinknewspaper.ca/article/1951|accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nation.FAQ&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Occupy Wall Street: FAQ|first=Nathan|last=Schneider|date=September 29, 2011|work=The Nation|url=http://www.thenation.com/article/163719/occupy-wall-street-faq|accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The internet group [[Anonymous (group)|Anonymous]] encouraged its readers to take part in the protests, calling protesters to &quot;flood lower Manhattan, set up tents, kitchens, peaceful barricades and occupy Wall Street.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cnn&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|work=CNN tech|last=Saba|first=Michael|title=Twitter #occupywallstreet movement aims to mimic Iran|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/09/16/tech/social-media/twitter-occupy-wall-street/index.html|date=September 17, 2011|accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;adbusters3&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Adbusters |title=Anonymous Joins #OCCUPYWALLSTREET &quot;Wall Street, Expect Us!&quot; says video communique. |url=http://www.adbusters.org/blogs/adbusters-blog/anonymous-joins-occupywallstreet.html |publisher=Adbusters |date=August 23, 2011 |accessdate=October 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Other groups began to join in the organization of the protest, including the U.S. Day of Rage and the NYC General Assembly, the governing body of the Occupy Wall Street group.&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot;/&gt;  An Occupy Wall Street page on [[Facebook]] began on September 19 with a YouTube video of the early protests, and by September 22, it had reached critical mass.  By mid-October, Facebook listed  125 Occupy-related pages and roughly one in every 500 hashtags used on Twitter, all around the world, was the movement's own #OWS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.brisbanetimes.com.au/technology/technology-news/from-a-single-hashtag-a-protest-circled-the-world-20111019-1m72j.html |title=From a single hashtag, a protest circled the world |publisher=Brisbanetimes.com.au |date=2011-10-19 |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Adbusters''' [[Kalle Lasn]], when asked why it took three years after the implosion of [[Lehman Brothers]]' for people to begin protesting, said that after the election of President [[Barack Obama]] there was a feeling among the young that he would pass laws to regulate the banking system and &quot;take these financial fraudsters and bring them to justice.&quot; However, as time passed, &quot;the feeling that he's a bit of a gutless wonder slowly crept in&quot; and they lost their hope that his election would result in change.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tyee&amp;nbsp;– Adbusters' Kalle Lasn Talks About OccupyWallStreet&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://thetyee.ca/News/2011/10/07/Kalle-Lasn-Occupy-Wall-Street/ |title=The Tyee&amp;nbsp;– Adbusters' Kalle Lasn Talks About OccupyWallStreet |publisher=Thetyee.ca |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The protest was begun at [[Zuccotti Park]] since it was private property and police could not legally force protesters to leave without being requested to do so by the property owner.&lt;ref name=&quot;twsC65&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Laura |last=Batchelor |title=Occupy Wall Street lands on private property |work=CNNMoney |quote=Many of the Occupy Wall Street protesters might not realize it, but they got really lucky when they elected to gather at Zuccotti Park in downtown Manhattan |date=October 6, 2011 |url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/10/06/news/companies/occupy_wall_street_park/index.htm |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
At a press conference held on the same day as the protests began, New York City mayor [[Michael Bloomberg]] explained, &quot;People have a right to protest, and if they want to protest, we'll be happy to make sure they have locations to do it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot;/&gt;

Immediate prototypes for OWS are the British student protests of 2010, Greece's and Spain's anti-austerity protests of the &quot;indignados&quot; (indignants), as well as the Middle Easts' Arab Spring protests. These antecedents have in common with OWS a reliance on social media and electronic messaging to circumvent the authorities, as well as the feeling that financial institutions, corporations, and the political elite have been [[wikt:malfeasant|malfeasant]] in their behavior toward youth and the middle class.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reutersmalfeasant&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Apps |first=Peter |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/10/11/uk-global-politics-protest-idUSLNE79A03Z20111011 |title=Wall Street action part of global Arab Spring? |publisher=Reuters |date= October 11, 2011|accessdate=2011-11-24}} &quot;What they all share in common is a feeling that the youth and middle class are paying a high price for mismanagement and malfeasance by an out-of-touch corporate, financial and political elite...they took on slogans from U.S. protesters who describe themselves as the &quot;99 percent&quot; paying the price for mistakes by a tiny minority.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArabSpring&quot;&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/oct/25/egyptian-protesters-occupy-wall-street?newsfeed=true Tahrir Square protesters send message of solidarity to Occupy Wall Street] by Jack Shenker and Adam Gabbatt  [[The Guardian]], Tuesday 25 October 2011 &quot;Much of the tactics, rhetoric and imagery deployed by protesters has clearly been inspired by this year's political upheavals in the Middle East...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Occupy Wall Street, in turn, gave rise to the [[Occupy movement]] in the United States and around the world.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/oct/17/city-protest-occupied-mainstream In the City and Wall Street, protest has occupied the mainstream] By Polly Toynbee in [[The Guardian]], Monday 17 October 2011 &quot;From Santiago to Tokyo, Ottawa, Sarajevo and Berlin, spontaneous groups have been inspired by Occupy Wall Street.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://theweek.com/article/index/220100/occupy-wall-street-a-protest-timeline Occupy Wall Street: A protest timeline]  &quot;A relatively small gathering of young anarchists and aging hippies in lower Manhattan has spawned a national movement. What happened?&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;top5&quot; /&gt;

===Goals===
The protesters targeted Wall Street because of the part it played in the economic crisis of 2008 which started the Great Recession.  They say that Wall Street's risky lending practices of mortgage-backed securities which ultimately proved to be worthless caused the crisis, and that [[Emergency Economic Stabilization Act of 2008|the government bailout]] breached a sense of propriety.  The protesters say that Wall Street recklessly and blatantly abused the credit default swap market, and that the instability of that market must have been known beforehand.  They say that the guilty parties should be prosecuted.&lt;ref name=&quot;top5&quot;/&gt;

Some journalists have criticized the protests saying it is hard to discern a unified aim for the movement, while other commentators have said that although the movement is not in complete agreement on its message and goals, it does have a message which is fairly coherent.  [[Douglas Rushkoff]], writing for CNN, said that even though the protesters are not ready to articulate an exact array of problems or how to solve them,

{{Quotation|Anyone who says he has no idea what these folks are protesting is not being truthful. Whether we agree with them or not, we all know what they are upset about, and we all know that there are investment bankers working on Wall Street getting richer while things for most of the rest of us are getting tougher. What upsets banking's defenders and politicians alike is the refusal of this movement to state its terms or set its goals in the traditional language of campaigns...They mean to show that there is an inappropriate and correctable disconnect between the abundance America produces and the scarcity its markets manufacture.&lt;ref name=&quot;DouglasRushkoff&quot; /&gt;}}

The protesters want, in part, more and better jobs, more equal distribution of income, bank reform, and a reduction of the influence of corporations on politics.&lt;ref name=&quot;DouglasRushkoff&quot;&gt;[http://edition.cnn.com/2011/10/05/opinion/rushkoff-occupy-wall-street/index.html Think Occupy Wall St. is a phase? You don't get it] By Douglas Rushkoff, Special to CNN October 5, 2011 &quot;...there are a wide array of complaints, demands, and goals from the Wall Street protesters: the collapsing environment, labor standards, housing policy, government corruption, World Bank lending practices, unemployment, increasing wealth disparity and so on...they believe they are symptoms of the same core problem.  Are they ready to articulate exactly what that problem is and how to address it? No, not yet. But neither are Congress or the president...&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/occupy-wall-street-its-not-a-hippie-thing-10272011.html Occupy Wall Street: It’s Not a Hippie Thing] By Roger Lowenstein, ''[[Bloomberg Businessweek]]'' October 27, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Adbusters co-founder Kalle Lasn has compared the protests to the [[Situationist International|Situationists]] and the [[Protests of 1968]] movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://english.aljazeera.net/indepth/features/2011/10/20111078196449621.html|title= Occupy Wall Street: All day, all week |publisher= [[Aljazeera]]
|author=  Ben Piven|date = 2011-10-07|accessdate=2011-10-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;top5&quot;&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2011/1024/Top-5-targets-of-Occupy-Wall-Street/Wall-Street-obviously Top 5 targets of Occupy Wall Street] [[The Christian Science Monitor]] by Maud Dillingham&lt;/ref&gt; and addresses critics saying that while no one person can speak for the movement, he believes that the goal of the protests is economic justice, specifically, a &quot;transaction tax&quot; on international financial speculation, the reinstatement of the [[Glass-Stegall Act]] and the revocation of [[corporate personhood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;huffpo&quot;/&gt;

The General Assembly, the governing body of the OWS movement, has adopted a “Declaration of the Occupation of New York City,” which includes a list of grievances against corporations, and to many protesters a general statement is enough.  However, saying, &quot;‘Power concedes nothing without a demand' &quot; others within the movement  have favored a fairly concrete set of national policy proposals.&lt;ref name=&quot;nytimes1&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/17/nyregion/occupy-wall-street-trying-to-settle-on-demands.html?scp=1&amp;sq=occupy%20wall%20street%20demands%20groups%20&amp;st=cse ''New York Times'']&lt;/ref&gt; One group has written an unofficial document, &quot;The 99 Percent Declaration”, that calls for a national general assembly of representatives from all 435 congressional districts to gather on July 4, 2012, to assemble a list of grievances and solutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;motherjones1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/10/occupy-wall-street-demands-new-deal |title=Occupy Protesters' One Demand: A New New Deal—Well, Maybe |publisher=Mother Jones |date=2011-10-18 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;walsh1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Walsh |first=Joan |url=http://www.salon.com/2011/10/20/do_we_know_what_ows_wants_yet/singleton/ |title=Do we know what OWS wants yet? |publisher=Salon.com |date=2011-10-20 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://sites.google.com/site/the99percentdeclaration/ |title=The99PercentDeclaration |publisher=Sites.google.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;  OWS protesters that  prefer a looser, more localized set of goals have also written a document,  the [[Liberty Square Blueprint]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.freenetworkmovement.org/commons/index.php?title=Liberty_Square_Blueprint |title=Liberty Square Blueprint - The Commons |publisher=Freenetworkmovement.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; a [[wiki]] page edited by some 250 occupiers and still undergoing changes. Written as a wiki the wording changes, however, an early version read: ''&quot;Demands cannot reflect inevitable success. Demands imply condition, and we will never stop. Demands cannot reflect the time scale that we are working with.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;motherjones1&quot;/&gt;
The Guardian interviewed OWS and found three main demands: get the money out of politics; reinstate the [[Glass-Steagall]] act; and draft laws against the little-known loophole that currently allows members of Congress to pass legislation affecting Delaware-based corporations in which they themselves are investors. &lt;ref&gt; Naomi Wolf. 
Naomi Wolf
guardian.co.uk, Friday 25 November 2011 12.25 EST
http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2011/nov/25/shocking-truth-about-crackdown-occupy?INTCMP=SRCH &lt;/ref&gt;

===We are the 99%===
{{Main|We are the 99%}}
[[File:2008 Top1percentUSA.png|thumb|275px|A chart showing the disparity in income distribution in the United States.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&amp;id=3309 &quot;Tax Data Show Richest 1 Percent Took a Hit in 2008, But Income Remained Highly Concentrated at the Top. Recent Gains of Bottom 90 Percent Wiped Out.&quot;] [http://www.cbpp.org Center on Budget and Policy Priorities]. Accessed October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.demos.org/inequality/numbers.cfm “By the Numbers.”] [http://www.demos.org Demos.org]. Accessed October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Wealth inequality and income inequality have been central concerns among OWS protesters.&lt;ref name=&quot;CFR Analysis&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cfr.org/united-states/occupy-wall-streets-global-echo/p26216 |title=Occupy Wall Street's Global Echo |first=Christopher |last=Alessi |date=October |month=17 |year=2011 |publisher=Council on Foreign Relations |accessdate=October 17, 2011 |quote=&quot;The Occupy Wall Street protests that began in New York City a month ago gained worldwide momentum over the weekend, as hundreds of thousands of demonstrators in nine hundred cities protested corporate greed and wealth inequality.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;HuffPo Income Inequality&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/clarence-b-jones/obama-mlk-memorial-_b_1016077.html |title=Occupy Wall Street and the King Memorial Ceremonies |first=Clarence |last=Jones |date=October 17, 2011 |publisher=The Huffington Post |accessdate=October 17, 2011 |quote=&quot;The reality is that 'Occupy Wall Street' is raising the consciousness of the country on the fundamental issues of poverty, income inequality, economic justice, and the Obama administration's apparent double standard in dealing with Wall Street and the urgent problems of Main Street: unemployment, housing foreclosures, no bank credit to small business in spite of nearly three trillion of cash reserves made possible by taxpayers funding of TARP.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Wall Street protesters need to find their 'sound bite' |author=Chrystia Freeland |newspaper=[[The Globe and Mail]] |date=October 14, 2011 |url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/commentary/chrystia-freeland/wall-street-protesters-need-to-find-their-sound-bite/article2200223/ |accessdate=October 17, 2011 |location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt; CBO data shows that in 1980, the top 1% earned 9.1% of all income, while in 2006 they earned 18.8% of all income.&lt;ref name=LAT1&gt;{{cite news |title=Occupy Wall Street shifts from protest to policy phase |author=Michael Hiltzik |newspaper=[[Los Angeles Times]] |date=October 12, 2011 |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2011/oct/12/business/la-fi-hiltzik-20111012 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

The phrase &quot;The 99%&quot; is a [[political slogan]] of [[&quot;Occupy&quot; protests|&quot;Occupy&quot; protesters]].&lt;ref name=dcourier&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.dcourier.com/main.asp?SectionID=1&amp;SubSectionID=1&amp;ArticleID=100176| title=Occupy Prescott protesters call for more infrastructure investment| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=Western News&amp;Info, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally launched as a Tumblr blog page in late August 2011.&lt;ref name=motherjonesfoundation&gt;{{cite web | url=http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/10/we-are-the-99-percent-creators| title=&quot;We Are the 99 Percent&quot; Creators Revealed| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=Mother Jones and the Foundation for National Progress.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=foreignpolicy&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/10/18/occupy_wall_street_99_percent| title=The World's 99 Percent| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=FOREIGN POLICY, PUBLISHED BY THE SLATE GROUP}}&lt;/ref&gt; It refers to the vast concentration of wealth among the top 1% of income earners compared to the other 99 percent, and indicates that most people are paying the price for the mistakes of a tiny minority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reutersmalfeasant&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=cbsprotestsspread&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.cbsnews.com/2300-201_162-10009481-50.html| title=Wall Street protests spread| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The top 1 percent of income earners have more than doubled their income over the last thirty years according to a [[Congressional Budget Office]] (CBO) report.&lt;ref name=&quot;ref name&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/26/us/politics/top-earners-doubled-share-of-nations-income-cbo-says.html?_r=1| title=Top Earners Doubled Share of Nation’s Income, Study Finds| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=The New York Times Company| first=Robert| last=Pear| date=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The report was released just as concerns of the Occupy Wall Street movement were beginning to enter the national political debate.&lt;ref name=WashPostBloomberg&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/cbo-incomes-of-top-earners-grow-at-a-pace-far-faster-than-everyone-elses/2011/10/26/gIQAHlVFKM_story.html| title=CBO: Incomes of top earners grow at a pace far faster than everyone else’s| accessdate=11-17-11| publisher=The Washington Post| date=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the CBO, between 1979 and 2007 the incomes of the top 1% of Americans grew by an average of 275%. During the same time period, the 60% of Americans in the middle of the income scale saw their income rise by 40%. Since 1979 the average pre-tax income for the bottom 90% of households has decreased by $900, while that of the top 1% increased by over $700,000, as federal taxation became less [[Progressive tax|progressive]].   From 1992-2007 the top 400 income earners in the U.S. saw their income increase 392% and their average tax rate reduced by 37%.&lt;ref name=Stupid&gt;[http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/02/income-inequality-in-america-chart-graph It's the Inequality, Stupid] By Dave Gilson and Carolyn Perot in Mother Jones, March/April 2011 Issue&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2009, the average income of the top 1% was $960,000  with a minimum income of $343,927.&lt;ref name=CNNstats&gt;[http://money.cnn.com/2011/10/20/news/economy/occupy_wall_street_income/index.htm Who are the 1 percent?], CNN, October 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CBPP&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbpp.org/cms/index.cfm?fa=view&amp;id=3309 &quot;Tax Data Show Richest 1 Percent Took a Hit in 2008, But Income Remained Highly Concentrated at the Top.&quot;] [http://www.cbpp.org Center on Budget and Policy Priorities]. Accessed October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=doubled&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/26/us/politics/top-earners-doubled-share-of-nations-income-cbo-says.html?_r=1 Top Earners Doubled Share of Nation’s Income, Study Finds] New York Times By Robert Pear, October 25, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007 the richest 1% of the American population owned 34.6% of the country's total wealth, and the next 19% owned 50.5%.  Thus, the top 20% of Americans owned 85% of the country's wealth and the bottom 80% of the population owned 15%.  Financial inequality (total net worth minus the value of one's home)&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Financial wealth&quot; is defined by economists as [http://www2.ucsc.edu/whorulesamerica/power/wealth.html &quot;total net worth minus the value of one's home,&quot;] including investments and other liquid assets.&lt;/ref&gt; was greater than inequality in total wealth, with the top 1% of the population owning 42.7%, the next 19% of Americans owning 50.3%, and the bottom 80% owning 7%.&lt;ref name=&quot;ForbesJacobs&quot;&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/sites/deborahljacobs/2011/11/01/occupy-wall-street-and-the-rhetoric-of-equality/ Occupy Wall Street And The Rhetoric of Equality] ''Forbes'' November 1, 2011 by Deborah L. Jacobs&lt;/ref&gt;  However, after the [[Great Recession]] which started in 2007, the share of total wealth owned by the top 1% of the population grew from 34.6% to 37.1%, and that owned by the top 20% of Americans grew from 85% to 87.7%.  The Great Recession also caused a drop of 36.1% in median household wealth but a drop of only 11.1% for the top 1%, further widening the gap between the 1% and the 99%.&lt;ref name=&quot;ForbesJacobs&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.levyinstitute.org/pubs/wp_589.pdf Recent Trends in Household Wealth in the United States: Rising Debt and the Middle-Class Squeeze—an Update to 2007] by Edward N. Wolff, Levy Economics Institute of Bard College, March 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sociology.ucsc.edu/whorulesamerica/power/wealth.html Wealth, Income, and Power] by G. William Domhoff of the UC-Santa Barbara Sociology Department&lt;/ref&gt;  During the economic expansion between 2002 and 2007, the income of the top 1% grew 10 times faster than the income of the bottom 90%.  In this period 66% of total income gains went to the 1%, who in 2007 had a larger share of total income than at any time since 1928.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;  This is in stark contrast with surveys of US populations that indicate an &quot;ideal&quot; distribution that is much more equal, and a widespread ignorance of the true [[income inequality]]  and [[wealth inequality]].  &lt;ref&gt; Norton, M. I., &amp; Ariely, D. Building a Better America—One Wealth Quintile at a Time Perspectives on Psychological Science January 2011 6: 9-12&lt;/ref&gt;.

===Demographics===
Early on the protesters were mostly young due to their pronounced use of social networks through which they promoted the protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kleinfield&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;christianpost&quot;/&gt; As the protest grew, older protesters also became involved.&lt;ref name=&quot;LIP&quot;/&gt; The average age of the protesters is 33, with people in their 20s balanced by people in their 40s.&lt;ref name=CSMprofile&gt;[http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/2011/1101/Who-is-Occupy-Wall-Street-After-six-weeks-a-profile-finally-emerges/%28page%29/2 Who is Occupy Wall Street? After six weeks, a profile finally emerges.] [[The Christian Science Monitor]] By Gloria Goodale, November 1, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Various religious faiths have been represented at the protest including Muslims, Jews, and Christians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Religion1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://news.yahoo.com/religion-claims-place-occupy-wall-street-171204904.html| title = Religion claims its place in Occupy Wall Street|quote=Inside, a Buddha statue sits near a picture of Jesus, while a hand-lettered sign in the corner points toward Mecca.|publisher = Boston University|year=2011|=accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;huffington post&quot;/&gt; On October 10 the Associated Press reported that &quot;there’s a diversity of age, gender and race&quot; at the protest.&lt;ref name=LIP/&gt; Some news organizations have compared the protest to a [[left-leaning]] version of the [[Tea Party protests]].&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast&quot;/&gt;

According to a survey of Zuccotti Park protesters by the Baruch College School of Public Affairs published on October 19, of 1,619 web respondents, 1/3 were older than 35, half were employed full-time, 13% were unemployed and 13% earned over $75,000. 27.3% of the respondents called themselves Democrats, 2.4% called themselves Republicans, while the rest, 70%, called themselves independents.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fastcompany.com/1789018/occupy-wall-street-demographics-statistics#disqus_thread The Demographics Of Occupy Wall Street] BY Sean Captain, Fast Company, Oct 19, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

===Organization and group process===
[[File:Day 14 Occupy Wall Street September 30 2011 Shankbone 2.JPG|left|thumb|Protesters engaging in the '[[human microphone]]']]

The New York City General Assembly (NYCGA), held every evening at seven, is the main OWS decision-making body and provides much of the leadership and executive function for the protesters.  At its meetings the various OWS committees discuss their thoughts and needs, and the meetings are open to the public for both attendance and speaking.  The meetings are without formal leadership, although certain members routinely act as moderators. Meeting participants comment upon committee proposals using a process called a &quot;stack&quot;, which is a queue of speakers that anyone can join. New York uses what is called a [[progressive stack]], in which people from [[marginalized groups]] are sometimes allowed to speak before people from dominant groups, with [[facilitator]]s, or ''stack-keepers'', urging speakers to &quot;step forward, or step back&quot; based on which group they belong to, meaning that women and minorities may move to the front of the line, while white men must often wait for a turn to speak.&lt;ref name=&quot;SeltzNation&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Seltzer|first=Sarah|title=Where Are the Women at Occupy Wall Street?|url=http://www.truth-out.org/where-are-women-occupy-wall-street/1319895284|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=The Nation|date=29 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Penny|first=Laura|title=Protest By Consensus|url=http://www.newstatesman.com/blogs/laurie-penny/2011/10/spain-movement-square-world|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=New Statesman|date=16 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hinkle|first=A. Barton|title=OWS protesters have strange ideas about fairness| url=http://www2.timesdispatch.com/news/rtd-opinion/2011/nov/04/tdopin02-hinkle-ows-protesters-have-strange-ideas--ar-1433590/|accessdate=11 November 2011|newspaper=Richmond Times Dispatch|date=4 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Volunteers take minutes of the meetings so that organizers who are not in attendance can be kept up-to-date.&lt;ref name=IBT&gt;[http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/237339/20111025/occupy-wall-street-occupy-wall-street-structure-occupy-wall-street-general-assembly-occupy-wall-stre.htm?cid=2As Occupy Wall Street Expands, Tensions Mount Over Structure] ''International Business Times'' by Jeremy B. White, October 25, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr&quot;/&gt;  In addition to the over 70 working groups&lt;ref&gt;New York City General Assembly website, last visited 20 Nov. 2011, http://www.nycga.net/groups/&lt;/ref&gt; that perform much of the daily work and planning of Occupy Wall Street, the organizational structure also includes &quot;spokes councils,&quot; at which every working group can participate.&lt;ref&gt;The New York Observer, 8 Nov. 2011, &quot;Occupy Wall Street Moves Indoors With Spokes Council,&quot; http://www.observer.com/2011/11/occupy-wall-street-moves-indoors-with-spokes-council/&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Fordham University]] communications professor [[Paul Levinson]], Occupy Wall Street and similar movements symbolize another rise of [[direct democracy]] that has not actually been seen since ancient times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Politics/2011/1010/Does-Occupy-Wall-Street-have-leaders-Does-it-need-any| title=Does 'Occupy Wall Street' have leaders? Does it need any?| accessdate=October 25, 2011| publisher=The Christian Science Monitor}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sociologist Heather Gautney, also from Fordham University, has said that while the organization calls itself leaderless, the protest in Zuccotti Park has discernible &quot;organizers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: A Fordham University Professor Analyzes the Movement&quot;/&gt; Even with the perception of a movement with no leaders, leaders have emerged. Ad hoc leaders discussed whether to leave. They plan for the occupation of other cities and neighborhoods, with an infrastructure to keep the movement beyond just the park. A facilitator of some of the movement's more contentious discussions, Nicole Carty, says “Usually when we think of leadership, we think of authority, but nobody has authority here,” - “People lead by example, stepping up when they need to and stepping back when they need to.”&lt;ref name=Crain&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20111113/ECONOMY/311139975| title=Occupy Wall Street takes a new direction| accessdate=11-13-11| publisher=Crain Communications Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''TheStreet.com'', some organizers have made more of a commitment and are more visible than others, with a core of about five main organizers being the most active.&lt;ref name=thestreet.com5leaders&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.thestreet.com/story/11292354/1/5-occupy-wall-street-leaders.html| title=5 Occupy Wall Street Leaders (Update 1)| accessdate=11-14-11| publisher=TheStreet, Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Funding====
Most of OWS funding comes from middle-class donors with incomes in the $50,000 to $100,000 range, and the median donation was $22.&lt;ref name=CSMprofile/&gt;  According to finance group member Pete Dutro, OWS had accumulated over $600,000 and had $450,000 remaining as of November 21, 2011. During the period that protesters were encamped in the park the funds were being used to purchase food and other necessities and to bail out fellow protesters.  In the future members of the OWS finance committee say they will initiate a process to streamline the movement and re-evaluate their budget. They may eliminate or restructure some of the &quot;working groups&quot; they no longer need on a day-to-day basis.  &quot;We have some ideas but we want to hear ideas from the other working groups,&quot; said Dutro, &quot;So we can put forward a proposal that would be fair and suit everybody's needs.&quot;  Presently the movement continues to organize out of donated office space and give money to other &quot;occupations.&quot; 
&lt;ref name=&quot;burruss1&quot;/&gt;

According to ''The Wall Street Journal'', &quot;A few weeks ago, the Alliance for Global Justice, a Washington-based nonprofit, agreed to sponsor Occupy Wall Street and lend it its tax-exempt status, so donors could write off contributions. That means the Alliance for Global Justice's board has final say on spending, though it says it's not involved in decisions and will only step in if the protesters want to spend money on something that might violate their tax-exempt status.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;grossman1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;grossman1&quot;&gt;&quot;Protest's Money Problem. Occupy Wall Street May Have to Appoint Leaders to Deal With Its Donations&quot; by Andrew Grossman. ''The Wall Street Journal''. October 27, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Grossman |first=Andrew |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203687504577000320434317092.html?mod=e2tw |title=Occupy Wall Street's Money Problem - WSJ.com |publisher=Online.wsj.com |date=2011-10-27 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;sup&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Business/occupy-wall-street-members-find-finances-flash-point/story?id=14802788&lt;/sup&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; As of late October it was reported that the OWS Finance Committee works with a lawyer and an accountant to track finances; the group has a substantial amount of money deposited at the Amalgamated Bank nearby, after first making deposits at the Lower East Side People's Federal Credit Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Frank |first=Robert |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203752604576645480987452682.html |title=Goldman Sachs Sends Its Regrets to This Awkward Dinner Invitation |publisher=Wall Street Journal |date=2011-10-22 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In late October the General Assembly of Occupy Wall Street registered for tax exempt status as a [[501(c)(3)]]&lt;ref name=Shapiro&gt;&quot;Money Donated To Occupy Wall Street Brings Much Needed Supplies And Tension&quot; by Lila Shapiro. ''The Huffington Post''. October 24, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  Occupy Wall Street accepts tax-deductible donations, primarily through the movement's website.&lt;ref name=&quot;burruss1&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/11/21/news/occupy_wall_street_money/| title=Occupy Wall Street has money to burn| publisher=[[CNN|CNN.com]]|first=Logan |last=Burruss |accessdate=11-21-11 | date=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Zuccotti Park encampment===
[[File:Day 47 Occupy Wall Street November 2 2011 Shankbone 10.JPG|right|thumb|Zuccotti Park with the &quot;Occupy&quot; encampment's '[[The People's Library|People's Library]]']]
Prior to being closed to overnight use, somewhere between 100 and 200 people slept in Zuccotti Park. Initially tents were not allowed and protesters  slept in sleeping bags or under blankets.&lt;ref name=&quot;google11&quot;/&gt; Meals were served at a cost of about $1,000 a day and some visitors ate at nearby restaurants,&lt;ref name=&quot;kadet&quot;/&gt; however local vendors  fared badly,&lt;ref name=WSJ-Vendors&gt;{{cite news|last=Oloffson|first=Kristi|title=Food Vendors Find Few Customers During Protest|url=http://blogs.wsj.com/metropolis/2011/10/12/food-vendors-find-few-customers-during-protest/|accessdate=24 October 2011|newspaper=Wall Street Journal|date=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many businesses surrounding the park were adversely affected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=GIOVE|first=CANDICE|title=Occupy Wall Street costs local businesses $479,400!|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/item_Wq8d8Q0M0W98jwaQAVPvYL/|accessdate=15 November 2011|newspaper=New York Post|date=13 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Contribution boxes collected about $5,000 a day, and supplies came in from around the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;kadet&quot;/&gt; Eric Smith, a local chef who was laid off at the [[Sheraton]] in Midtown, said that he was running a five-star restaurant in the park.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan%20occu_pie_the_kitchen_PIZ7EsDJEZqzPgzzEWKX7I Protest mob is enjoying rich diet] By REBECCA ROSENBERG, New York Post, October 19, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  In late-October kitchen volunteers complained about working 18 hour days to feed people who were not part of the movement and served only brown rice, simple sandwiches, and potato chips for three days.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/zuccotti_hell_kitchen_i5biNyYYhpa8MSYIL9xSDL  Occupy Wall Street kitchen staff protesting fixing food for freeloaders] By Selim Algar and Bob Fredricks, New York Post, October 27, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

The protesters constructed a [[greywater]] treatment system to recycle dishwater contaminants.&lt;ref name=&quot;businessinsider&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;/&gt;  The filtered water was used for the park's plants and flowers.  Many protesters used the bathrooms of nearby business establishments.&lt;ref name=&quot;google10&quot;/&gt; Some supporters  donated use of their bathrooms for showers and the sanitary needs of protesters.&lt;ref name=Deprez/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WSJ OWS Economy&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204002304576631084250433462.html/|title=The Occupy Economy|last=Kadet|first=Anne|date=October 15, 2011|work=The Wall Street Journal }}&lt;/ref&gt;

New York City requires a permit to use &quot;amplified sound,&quot; including electric bullhorns. Since Occupy Wall Street does not have a permit, the protesters have created the &quot;[[human microphone]]&quot; in which a speaker pauses while the nearby members of the audience repeat the phrase in unison.  The effect has been called &quot;comic or exhilarating—often all at once.&quot;  Some feel this has provided a further unifying effect for the crowd.&lt;ref name=&quot;We Are All Human Microphones Now&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Occupy Wall Street Anonymous Skippy PB 2011 Shankbone.JPG|thumb|left|Feeding people in the temporary camp simple sandwiches]]
During the weeks that overnight use of the park was allowed, a separate area was set aside for an information area which contained laptop computers and several wireless routers.&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr6&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast7&quot;/&gt; The items were powered with gas generators until the [[New York Fire Department]] removed them on October 28, saying they were as a fire hazard.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-10-28/new-york-police-remove-gasoline-generators-from-occupy-wall-street-site.html New York Authorities Remove Fuel, Generators From Occupy Wall Street Site], Esmé E. Deprez and Charles Mead, Bloomberg News, Oct 28, 2011; accessed November 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  Protesters then used bicycles rigged with an electricity-generating apparatus to charge batteries to power the protesters' laptops and other electronics.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/30/with-generators-gone-wall-street-protesters-try-bicycle-power/ With Generators Gone, Wall Street Protesters Try Bicycle Power], Colin Moynihan, ''New York Times'', October 30, 2011; accessed November 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  According to the ''Columbia Journalism Review'''s New Frontier Database, the media team, while unofficial, runs websites like Occupytogether.org, video livestream, a &quot;steady flow of updates on Twitter, and Tumblr&quot; as well as [[Skype]] sessions with other demonstrators.&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr9&quot;/&gt;

In October a makeshift tent was erected, formally calling itself [[:The People's Library]], and began offering free wi-fi internet to protesters and containing over 5,000 books. The library operated [[24/7]] and used an [[honor system]] to manage returns. It offered weekly poetry readings on Friday nights, provided a reference serviced frequently staffed by professional librarians, and  procured materials available through the [[interlibrary loan]] system.&lt;ref name='NYDN 2011-10-17'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pUFn8kKDwuk | title = Voices from Zuccotti: Steve Syrek, 33 | accessdate = 2011-11-20 | work = The New York Daily News | publisher = [[YouTube]] | quote = I've even got one guy who wants to help us procure any materials we want from the interlibrary loan system, which means we are a legitimate, fully functioning research library. Someone could come here and request an article of any kind and we could theoretically get it for free and give it to them.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the library was removed on November 15 when the park was closed to overnight use and it was reported that many of the books were destroyed. The library's cataloging system is accessible online at [[LibraryThing]], which donated a free lifetime membership.

[[File:Day 60 Occupy Wall Street November 15 2011 Shankbone 7.JPG|thumb|Zuccotti Park, cleared and cleaned on November 15, 2011]]
On October 6, Brookfield Office Properties, which owns Zuccotti Park, issued a statement that &quot;Sanitation is a growing concern... Normally the park is cleaned and inspected every weeknight[, but] because the protesters refuse to cooperate ... the park has not been cleaned since Friday, September 16 and as a result, sanitary conditions have reached unacceptable levels.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cbslocal&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossman&quot;/&gt;

On October 13, New York City's mayor Bloomberg and Brookfield announced that the park must be vacated for cleaning the following morning at 7&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilkenny&quot;/&gt; However, protesters vowed to &quot;defend the occupation&quot; after police said they wouldn’t allow them to return with sleeping bags and other gear following the cleaning, under rules set by the private park’s owner—and many protesters spent the night sweeping and mopping the park.&lt;ref name=&quot;BusinessWeek Cleanup Canceled&quot;&gt;[http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-10-14/occupy-wall-street-park-cleaning-postponed-after-nyc-protest.html &quot;Cleanup Canceled&quot;], ''BusinessWeek'', 2011-10-14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Deprez2&quot;&gt;Deprez, Esmé E., Joel Stonington and Chris Dolmetsch, [http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-10-14/occupy-wall-street-park-cleaning-is-postponed-as-14-protesters-in-custody.html &quot;Occupy Wall Street Park Cleaning Postponed&quot;], ''Bloomberg'', Oct 14, 2011 11:37 AM EDT.&lt;/ref&gt; The next morning, the property owner postponed its cleaning effort.&lt;ref name=&quot;BusinessWeek Cleanup Canceled&quot;/&gt; Having prepared for a confrontation with the authorities to prevent the cleaning effort from proceeding, some protesters clashed with police in riot gear outside City Hall after it was canceled.&lt;ref name=Kilkenny/&gt; 

Shortly after midnight on November 15, 2011, the New York Police Department gave protesters notice from the park's owner (Brookfield Office Properties) to leave Zuccotti Park due to its purportedly unsanitary and hazardous conditions. The notice stated that they could return without sleeping bags, tarps or tents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/15/zuccotti-park-evacuation_n_1094164.html |title=Zuccotti Park Eviction: NYPD Orders Occupy Wall Street Protesters To Temporarily Evacuate Park [LATEST UPDATES&amp;#93; |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=RestrainingOrderVacated&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/15/us/new-york-occupy-eviction/index.html?hpt=hp_t1 |title=New York court upholds eviction of &quot;Occupy&quot; protesters |author=CNN Wire Staff |date=November 15, 2011 |publisher=www.cnn.com |accessdate=November 15, 2011 |quote= A New York Supreme Court has ruled not to extend a temporary restraining order that prevented the eviction of &quot;Occupy&quot; protesters who were encamped at Zuccotti Park, considered a home-base for demonstrators.
Police in riot gear cleared out the protesters early Tuesday morning, a move that attorneys for the loosely defined group say was unlawful.
But Justice Michael Stallman later ruled in favor of New York city officials and Brookfield properties, owners and developers of the privately-owned park in Lower Manhattan. The order does not prevent protesters from gathering in the park, but says their First Amendment rights not do include remaining there, &quot;along with their tents, structures, generators, and other installations to the exclusion of the owner's reasonable rights and duties to maintain Zuccotti Park.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; About an hour later, police in riot gear began removing protesters from the park, arresting some 200 people in the process, including a number of journalists. While the police raid was in progress, the Occupy Wall Street Media Team issued an official response under the heading, &quot;You can't evict an idea whose time has come.&quot;&lt;ref name=evict-idea&gt;[http://occupywallst.org/article/you-cant-evict-idea-whose-time-has-come &quot;You can't evict an idea whose time has come.&quot;]- official statement of Occupy Wall Street Media Team, posted November 15, 2011, 1:36 a.m. EST&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reaction==
===Public opinion===
National polls over October and November 2011 were mixed, with agreement/approval ratings for Occupy Wall Street varying from 59% to 22%, but approval was fairly consistently larger than disapproval, with large numbers often not giving an opinion. The age group that most strongly supports OWS are 50 to 64, rather than under 35. OWS has the strongest support among those making $50,000 to $70,000 a year, rather than under $30,000, with 27% of people making over $75,000 a year backing the movement. Managers and other professionals support the movement more than blue-collar workers, and men over 50 show the strongest support.&lt;ref name=&quot;WSJPolls&quot;&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203503204577037980400569026.html Populist Movements Rooted in Same Soil] [[The Wall Street Journal]] By GERALD F. SEIB, NOVEMBER 15, 2011 &quot;You know how they have been pigeonholed: The tea-party movement is nothing but a collection of right-wing, under-educated rubes and radicals, while the Occupy Wall Street movement attracts only young, scruffy, unemployed left-wing zealots.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; 

A November 3 poll done by [[Quinnipiac University]] found that 30 percent of American voters have a favorable view of the protests, while 39 percent do not. The same poll found that among independent voters, 29 percent have a favorable view opposed to 42 percent who have an unfavorable view, while 45% of democrats have a favorable view opposed to 19% who have an unfavorable view.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Zeke Miller |url=http://articles.businessinsider.com/2011-11-03/politics/30353835_1_tea-party-movement-unfavorable-view-positive-views#ixzz1dY2Je9NI |title=In Reversal, More Americans Oppose Occupy Wall Street Than Support It - Business Insider |publisher=Articles.businessinsider.com |date=2011-11-03 |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;QuinnipiacNov3&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Quinnipiac University - Office of Public Affairs |url=http://www.quinnipiac.edu/x1295.xml?ReleaseID=1670 |title=National (US) Poll * November 3, 2011 * U.S. Voters Say Super Committe - Quinnipiac University – Hamden, Connecticut |publisher=Quinnipiac.edu |date=2011-11-03 |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An [[NBC]]/[[Wall Street Journal]] survey released October 12 found that 37 percent of respondents &quot;tend to support&quot; the occupy movement, while 18 percent &quot;tend to oppose&quot; it.&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews&quot;/&gt; An October 13 survey by ''[[Time (magazine)|TIME]]'' magazine found that 54 percent of Americans have a favorable impression of the protests, while 23 percent have a negative impression. An October 18 [[The Gallup Organization|Gallup poll]] found that 22 percent of Americans agree with the protest's goals, while 15 percent disapprove and the remaining 61% say they don't know enough to decide.  Gallup found that Democrats, Independents and Republicans all follow the news about OWS in equal numbers, and those who closely followed OWS were more likely to approve of its goals and methods.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gallup.com/poll/150164/americans-uncertain-occupy-wall-street-goals.aspx |title=Most Americans Uncertain About &quot;Occupy Wall Street&quot; Goals |publisher=Gallup.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  An October [[CBS News]]/''[[New York Times]]'' polls found 43% of Americans agree with Occupy Wall Street while 27% disagree.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYTPoll&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-20125515-503544/poll-43-percent-agree-with-views-of-occupy-wall-street/|title=Poll: 43 percent agree with views of &quot;Occupy Wall Street&quot;|publisher=CBS News|date=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An October [[Rasmussen Reports|Rasmussen]] poll found an almost even split, shows that 33 percent of Americans have a favorable view, while 27 percent are unfavorable and 40 percent have no opinion.&lt;ref name=&quot;SlateEarly&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2011/10/05/poll_occupy_wall_street_starts_off_with_favorable_ratings.html|title=Poll: Occupy Wall Street Starts Off With Favorable Ratings|work=Slate|date=October 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An October United Technologies/National Journal Congressional poll found that 59 percent of Americans agree with the movement while 31 percent disagree.&lt;ref name=&quot;TheAtlantic&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2011/10/poll-most-americans-support-occupy-wall-street-taxing-millionaires/246963/|title=Poll: Most Americans Support Occupy Wall Street|work=The Atlantic|date=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An October Quinnipiac University poll of New York City voters found that 67 percent of New Yorkers approved of the movement with 23 percent disapproving. The results also found 87 percent of New Yorkers find it OK that they are protesting.&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/nationnow/2011/10/occupy-wall-street-new-yorkers-quinnipiac-poll.html|title=Occupy Wall Street: Most N.Y. voters back protests, poll finds|work=The Los Angeles Times|date=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite [[Occupy Wall Street#Media response|media criticism]] that the protesters views are incoherent, the poll also found that 72 percent of New York City voters understand their views.&lt;ref name=&quot;SlatePoll&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://slatest.slate.com/posts/2011/10/18/occupy_wall_street_poll_shows_protests_mainstream_popularity.html|title=Occupy Wall Street Seeks Mainstream Appeal|Slate|date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A NY1-Marist Poll released November 1 showed 44 percent of New York voters supported the Occupy Wall Street movement, while only 21 percent supported the Tea Party.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Associated Press |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/AP90ca9632708b4bc38476140917973b7c.html |title=Poll: More NY voters support Occupy Wall Street - WSJ.com |publisher=Online.wsj.com |date=2011-11-01 |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Political response===
====The White House====
During an October 6 news conference, President Obama said &quot;I think it expresses the frustrations the American people feel, that we had the biggest financial crisis since the Great Depression, huge collateral damage all throughout the country ... and yet you're still seeing some of the same folks who acted irresponsibly trying to fight efforts to crack down on the abusive practices that got us into this in the first place.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama news conference: Obama: Occupy Wall Street protests show Americans' frustration&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama acknowledges Wall Street protests as a sign&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama Speaks on Occupy Wall Street Oct 6&quot;/&gt; When [[Jake Tapper]] of ABC News pushed Obama to explain the fact that his administration hasn't prosecuted any Wall Street executives who didn't play by the rules, he replied, &quot;One of the biggest problems about the collapse of Lehman's and the subsequent financial crisis and the whole subprime lending fiasco is that a lot of that stuff wasn't necessarily illegal; it was just immoral or inappropriate or reckless.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wall Street Corruption, Solyndra, and Fast &amp; Furious: Today's Q's for O&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama: Not all pre-crisis financial ploys illegal&quot;/&gt; On October 18, when interviewed by ABC news, he said &quot;in some ways, they’re not that different from some of the protests that we saw coming from the Tea Party.  Both on the left and the right, I think people feel separated from their government. They feel that their institutions aren’t looking out for them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/politics/2011/10/obama-occupy-wall-street-not-that-different-from-tea-party-protests |title=Obama: Occupy Wall Street ‘Not That Different’ From Tea Party Protests - ABC News |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=|accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/obama-occupy-wall-street-not-different-tea-party-171041906.html |title=Obama: Occupy Wall Street 'Not That Different' From Tea Party Protests - Yahoo! News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |date=|accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 22nd, President Barack Obama was &quot;[[Human microphone#As a form of protest|mike-checked]]&quot;&lt;ref name=CBS20111122&gt;{{cite news |first=Brian |last=Montopoli |date=November 22, 2011 |title='Mic check': Occupy protesters interrupt Obama |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-57329652-503544/mic-check-occupy-protesters-interrupt-obama/ |publisher=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt; at a speech in New Hampshire by a group of Occupy Wall Street protesters as a series of call-and-response quips ensued, &quot;Mr. President: Over 4,000 peaceful protesters have been arrested while bankers continue to destroy the economy. You must stop the assault on our First Amendment rights. Your silence sends a message that police brutality is acceptable. Banks got bailed out. We got sold out.&quot;&lt;ref name=CBS20111122/&gt;&lt;ref name=RT20111123&gt;{{cite web |url=http://rt.com/usa/news/obama-occupy-wall-street-985/ |title=OWS protesters interrupt Obama's speech (VIDEO) |date=November 23, 2011 |publisher=[[RT (TV network)|RT]] |url=http://rt.com/usa/news/obama-occupy-wall-street-985/}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crowd quickly drowned the protesters out with chants of “Obama!” Obama then responded, &quot;I appreciate you guys making your point. Let me go ahead and make mine.&quot;&lt;ref name=CBS20111122/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://politicalticker.blogs.cnn.com/2011/11/22/occupy-protesters-disrupt-obama-speech/ |title='Occupy' protesters disrupt Obama speech |publisher=CNN |date=November 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the speech, Obama said “families like yours, young people like the ones here today — including the ones who were just chanting at me — you’re the reason that I ran for office in the first place.”&lt;ref name=RT20111123/&gt;

Vice President [[Joe Biden]] likened the protest to the Tea Party's similar anger at the banks, saying, &quot;Look guys the bargain is not on the level anymore in the minds of the vast majority of the American (people) the middle class has been screwed.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;oliphant&quot;/&gt;

====Congress====
[[File:Eric Cantor.jpg|thumb|House Majority Leader [[Eric Cantor]] ([[Republican Party (United States)|R]]-[[Virginia|Va]]), at the Values Voter Summit]]
[[Party leaders of the United States House of Representatives|House Democratic Leader Rep.]] [[Nancy Pelosi]], said she supports the growing nationwide Occupy Wall Street movement. Pelosi said she includes herself in the group of Americans dissatisfied with [[United States Congress|Congress]] and stated, &quot;I support the message to the establishment, whether it's Wall Street or the political establishment and the rest, that change has to happen. We cannot continue in a way (that) is not relevant to their lives.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pelosi Supports Occupy Wall Street Movement&quot;/&gt;

[[Independent (politician)|Independent]] Senator [[Bernie Sanders]] of Vermont, who [[Congressional caucus|caucuses]] with the [[Democratic Caucus of the United States Senate|Democratic Party]], appeared on ''[[Countdown with Keith Olbermann]]'' and supported the protests saying, &quot;We desperately need a coming together of working people to stand up to Wall Street. We need to rebuild the middle-class in this country and you guys can't have it all.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Olbermann&quot;/&gt;

[[House Majority Leader]] [[Eric Cantor]] ([[Republican Party (United States)|R]]-[[Virginia|Va]]), in a speech to a Values Voter Summit, characterized the movement as &quot;growing mobs&quot; and said that Obama's &quot;failed policies&quot; and rhetoric &quot;condon[ing] the pitting of Americans against Americans&quot; were to blame. In response, White House Press Secretary [[Jay Carney]] accused Cantor of &quot;unbound&quot; hypocrisy, given the Majority Leader's support of the Tea Party protests, adding, &quot;I don't understand why one man's mob is another man's democracy.&quot; Carney characterized both movements as examples of American democratic traditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama, Cantor spar over Occupy Wall Street&quot;/&gt;

The Democratic co-chairs of the [[Congressional Progressive Caucus]], [[United States House of Representatives|Representatives]] [[Raúl Grijalva]] and [[Keith Ellison]], announced their solidarity with the movement on October 4.&lt;ref name=&quot;house&quot;/&gt; The [[Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee]] is asking for 100,000 names on its website which will subsequently be added to 100,000 letters to [[Speaker of the House]] [[John Boehner]] and House Majority Leader Eric Cantor expressing support for the Occupy Wall Street protesters, the middle class, and opposition to tax [[loopholes]] for millionaires and [[big oil]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DCCC1&quot;/&gt;

====2012 Presidential candidates====
U.S. Congressman and [[Ron Paul presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Ron Paul]] (R-TX) stated, &quot;If they were demonstrating peacefully, and making a point, and arguing our case, and drawing attention to the Fed—I would say, 'good!'&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thehill&quot;/&gt; In a GOP debate, mentioning the ongoing “Occupy Wall Street” protesters, he stated that crony capitalists are those “that benefit from contract from government, benefit from the Federal Reserve, benefit from all the bailouts. They don’t deserve compassion. They deserve taxation or they deserve to have all their benefits removed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Eric W. Dolan |url=http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2011/11/09/ron-paul-on-occupy-protests-im-all-for-going-after-crony-capitalism/ |title=Ron Paul on ‘Occupy’ protests: I’m all for going after crony capitalism |publisher=The Raw Story |date=2007-11-13 |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; When protesters conducted a 'mic check,' at one of Ron Paul's rallies, he replied, &quot;If you listen carefully, I'm very much involved with the 99. I've been condemning that 1% because they've been ripping us off. The people on Wall Street got the bailouts and you guys got stuck with the bills and that's where I see the problem is.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newworldradical.com/2011/11/mic-check-yourself-ron-paul-town-hall.html |title=(Mic) Check Yourself: Ron Paul Town Hall Gets Occupied ~ New World Radical |publisher=Newworldradical.com |date=2011-11-21 |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://theopenglobe.org/wiki/'Mic_check':_OWS_protesters_heckle_Obama,_Ron_Paul_at_speeches |title='Mic check': OWS protesters heckle Obama, Ron Paul at speeches |publisher=OpenGlobe |date= |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Former [[Herman Cain presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Herman Cain]] accused the movement of being &quot;[[Anti-capitalism|anti-capitalist]]&quot; and argued &quot;Don't blame Wall Street, don't blame the big banks, if you don't have a job and you're not rich, blame yourself!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews&quot;/&gt; In an interview with the ''Wall Street Journal'', Cain also expressed his belief that Occupy Wall Street was &quot;planned and orchestrated to distract from the failed policies of the Obama administration,&quot; but admitted that he &quot;[didn't] have facts&quot; to back up his accusation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Herman Cain: I'm More Than the 'Anti-Romney'&quot;/&gt; 

Former Speaker of the House of Representatives and [[Newt Gingrich presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Newt Gingrich]] was quoted as saying at the 2012 Bloomberg/Washington Post Debate, &quot;Let me draw a distinction. Virtually every American has a reason to be angry. I think virtually [every] American has a reason to be worried. I think the people who are protesting in Wall Street break into two groups: one is left-wing agitators who would be happy to show up next week on any other topic, and the other is sincere middle-class people who frankly are very close to the Tea Party people who care. And actually... you can tell which are which. The people who are decent, responsible citizens pick up after themselves. The people who are just out there as activists trash the place and walk off and are proud of having trashed it, so let’s draw that distinction.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/11/newt-gingrich-dodd-frank-occupy-wall-street-debate_n_1006165.html |title=Newt Gingrich On Occupy Wall Street: Barney Frank, Chris Dodd Should Go To Jail (VIDEO) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On November 21, Gingrich was quoted as saying to the protesters that they should &quot;Go get a job right after you take a bath.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dailycaller.com/2011/11/21/gingrich-to-occupy-go-get-a-job-right-after-you-take-a-bath-video/#ixzz1eNnrCG1N |title=Newt Gingrich &amp;#124; Occupy Wall Street &amp;#124; Take A Bath |publisher=The Daily Caller |date= |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mitt Romney presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Mitt Romney]] said that while there were &quot;bad actors&quot; that needed to be &quot;found and plucked out&quot;, he believes that to aim at one industry or region of America is a mistake and views encouraging the Occupy Wall Street protests as &quot;dangerous&quot; and inciting &quot;class warfare&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=WCVBtv |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iJ_orudj6hA |title=Romney On Occupy Wall Street Protests |publisher=YouTube |date=|accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Romney: Wall Street Protests 'Class Warfare'&quot;/&gt; Romney later expressed sympathy for the movement, saying, &quot;I look at what's happening on Wall Street and my view is, boy, I understand how those people feel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Geiger |first=Kim |url=http://www.chicagotribune.com/news/politicsnow/la-pn-romney-wall-street-20111011,0,4608358.story |title=Mitt Romney sympathizes with Wall Street protesters |publisher=chicagotribune.com |date=October 11, 2011 |accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Buddy Roemer presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Buddy Roemer]] expressed support for the movement, saying, &quot;We have almost permanent unemployment. They say it’s nine percent, but the real unemployment rate is more like 16 percent. These are people there are no jobs for, or they have to work part time to try to make ends meet. It’s disturbing. The Wall Street protest is unshaped, unfocused, but there’s a lot of power in it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;roemer&quot;/&gt;

On October 18, [[Gary Johnson presidential campaign, 2012|2012 Republican presidential candidate]] [[Gary Johnson]] visited with the protesters in New York, expressing his support for the movement, stating, &quot;I just have to express my solidarity with everyone there that expresses the notion that we have a country that doles it out unfairly.  Corporatism is alive and well in this country.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2011/10/cautiously-libertarians-reach-out-to-occupy-wall-street/247045/|title=Cautiously, Libertarians Reach Out to Occupy Wall Street|date=October 20, 2011|first=Conor|last=Friedersdorf|publisher=''[[The Atlantic]]''|accessdate=October 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other politicians====
Mayor Bloomberg said that the protests &quot;aren't productive,&quot; although he also expressed sympathy for some of their complaints.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street protesters running out of space&quot;/&gt; On October 8, during his weekly radio show, Bloomberg complained that the protesters are trying to &quot;take the jobs from the people working in the city,&quot; and said that although &quot;[t]here are some people with legitimate complaints, there are some people who just like to protest.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NY Post Bloomberg article&quot;/&gt;

In an interview with ''[[The Washington Post]]'', Former Democratic U.S. Senator [[Russ Feingold]] endorsed the movement on October 5 stating, &quot;This is like the Tea Party—only it's real... By the time this is over, it will make the Tea Party look like ... a tea party.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost&quot;/&gt; Former [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] and [[Secretary of State]] [[Colin Powell]] declared that the demonstrations of the OWS movement were &quot;as American as apple pie,&quot; adding &quot;“This is something that our political leaders need to think about. It isn’t enough just to scream at our Occupy Wall Street demonstrators — we need our political system to start reflecting this anger back into how do we fix it? How do we get the economy going again?”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1111/68154.html |title=Colin Powell: Listen to Occupy Wall Street - MJ Lee |publisher=Politico.Com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Labor unions===
[[File:Day 20 Occupy Wall Street October 5 2011 Shankbone 3.JPG|thumb|left|On October 5 members of the [[National Nurses United]] labor union march to [[Foley Square]] in support of OWS]]
In September, various [[Trade union|labor unions]], including the [[Transport Workers Union of America]] Local 100 and the New York Metro 32BJ [[Service Employees International Union]], pledged their support for demonstrators.&lt;ref name=&quot;union support&quot;/&gt;  
Union leaders say that unions and OWS can offer mutual support, with OWS gaining from the union's money, stature, and large membership, and the weakened labor movement absorbing the protesters vitality.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/06/nyregion/major-unions-join-occupy-wall-street-protest.html?pagewanted=all Seeking Energy, Unions Join Protest Against Wall Street] By STEVEN GREENHOUSE and CARA BUCKLEY, October 5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT-OWS-background&quot;&gt;[http://topics.nytimes.com/top/reference/timestopics/organizations/o/occupy_wall_street/index.html?inline=nyt-org Times Topics], Occupy Wall Street background, retrieved November 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Industrial Workers of the World]] announced on September 28, 2011, that its General Executive Board (GEB), and the General Defense Committee (GDC) had issued statements of support for Occupy Wall Street.&lt;ref&gt;IWW.org Editor, &quot;IWW Endorses Occupy Wall Street,&quot; http://www.iww.org/en/content/iww-endorses-occupy-wall-street retrieved October 22, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;IWW.org Editor, &quot;IWW General Defense Committee Statement in Support of Occupy Wall Street,&quot; http://www.iww.org/en/content/iww-general-defense-committee-statement-support-occupy-wall-street retrieved October 22, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; After numerous arrests of protesters on the Brooklyn Bridge, police commandeered city buses to pick up detained protesters and union drivers later sued the New York Police Department.  Union President John Samuelsen said, &quot;We're down with these protesters. We support the notion that rich folk are not paying their fair share. Our bus operators are not going to be pressed into service to arrest protesters anywhere&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AP-Hawley-10032011&quot;/&gt;  On October 4, representatives from more than 14 of the country's largest labor unions joined the protesters for a mass rally and march.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: Police Make Numerous Arrests&quot;/&gt; In early November, [[National Nurses United]] (NNU), the largest union of registered nurses in the nation, expressed support for OWS and rallied in front of the White House and Department of Treasury.  Karen Higgins, co-president of NNU, said, &quot;A real finance tax would generate $350 billion a year in the U.S. alone and bring relief to families out of homes, friends out of work, patients out of care, communities running out of time.  The tax starts a revenue flow back to the 99 percent.&quot;  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Nurses |first=National |url=http://www.sacbee.com/2011/11/03/4029485/nurses-from-four-continents-urge.html |title=Nurses from Four Continents Urge Global Finance Tax; &quot;We Are Running Out of Time&quot; - PR Newswire |publisher=sacbee.com |date=2011-11-03 |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

Noting the growing union support, an article in the progressive-leaning ''[[Mother Jones magazine|Mother Jones]]'' magazine said that union support could splinter and derail the protests rather than sustain them because while unions are tightly organized, hierarchical, and run with a clear chain of command, Occupy Wall Street is the opposite in that they are &quot;a horizontal, autonomous, leaderless, modified-consensus-based system with roots in anarchist thought.&quot;  However, the article went on to suggest that if the unions and OWS joined together they could work to create a progressive movement that &quot;effectively taps into the rising feeling among many Americans that economic opportunity has been squashed by corporate greed and the influence of the very rich in politics.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street, Powered by Big Labor&quot;/&gt;  As the success of the movement has become apparent, union organizers have begun to embrace some of their social media skills, bold tactics, and the simplicity of the 99% slogan. Damon Silvers, the [[AFL–CIO]]'s policy director, said, “We think the Occupy movement has given voice to something very basic about what’s going on in our country right now.  The fact that they’ve figured out certain concepts and language for doing that, we think is really important and positive.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/business/occupy-movement-inspires-unions-to-embrace-bold-tactics.html | work=The New York Times | first=Steven | last=Greenhouse | title=Occupy Movement Inspires Unions to Embrace Bold Tactics | date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace and Agricultural Implement Workers of America (UAW) has endorsed the movement saying, &quot;We recognize the need to work together and learn from each other.  The vitality, energy and dialogue growing from the Occupy Wall Street movement show the potential to organize, build power and win justice for the middle class.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uaw.org/page/uaw-endorses-occupy-wall-street |title=endorses Occupy Wall Street! |publisher=UAW |date= |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Federal Reserve===
During a hearing before the Joint Economic Committee October 4, 2011, [[Federal Reserve]] Chairman [[Ben Bernanke]] said, &quot;[P]eople are quite unhappy with the state of the economy and what’s happening. They blame, with some justification, the problems in the financial sector for getting us into this mess, and they’re dissatisfied with the policy response here in Washington. And at some level, I can’t blame them. Certainly, 9 percent unemployment and very slow growth is not a good situation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;thinkprogress&quot;/&gt; Dallas Federal Reserve President [[Richard W. Fisher]] said that he was &quot;somewhat sympathetic&quot; to the views of the protesters, and added, &quot;We have too many people out of work. We have a very [[Income inequality in the United States|uneven distribution of income]]. We have a very frustrated people, and I can understand their frustration.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;/&gt;
[[Federal Reserve]] Chairman [[Ben Bernanke]] commented about protester's blame of the Fed saying: &quot;“The concerns about the Fed are based on misconceptions, A very simplistic interpretation of that [criticism] was that we were doing that because we wanted to preserve banker salaries. That was obviously not the case.” Bernanke has stated that policies aimed at boosting the economy will continue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://thehill.com/blogs/on-the-money/801-economy/191415-bernanke-takes-on-critics-defends-fed-efforts-to-boost-economy| title=Bernanke takes on Occupy Wall Street| accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=Capitol Hill Publishing Corp}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media response===

[[File:Day 12 Occupy Wall Street September 28 2011 Shankbone 31.JPG|thumb|left|upright|A protester's sign references the alleged lack of news coverage by mass media as a '[[media blackout]].' &lt;ref&gt;Grant, Drew Grant; Sanders, Anna (September 30, 2011). [http://www.observer.com/2011/09/media-coverage-on-occupy-wall-street/ &quot;Media Coverage: Must Reads.&quot;] [http://www.observer.com ''The New York Observer'']. Accessed November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goodale, Gloria (October 5, 2011). [http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/Elections/Vox-News/2011/1005/Occupy-Wall-Street-Why-this-revolution-isn-t-made-for-TV &quot;'Occupy Wall Street': Why this revolution isn't made for TV.&quot;] [http://www.csmonitor.com The Christian Science Monitor]. Accessed November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Udstuen, Lukas; et al. (October 11, 2011.) [http://www.newsy.com/videos/analyzing-media-coverage-of-occupy-wall-street/ &quot;U.S. News: Occupy Wall Street Media Coverage.&quot;] [http://www.newsy.com NewsNY]. Accessed November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

Five days into the protest, [[Keith Olbermann]] criticized the initial media response for failing to adequately cover the protests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street's Media Problems&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Will Bunch on mainstream media's failure to cover Occupy Wall Street protests&quot;/&gt; The protests began on Saturday, September 17. The following Wednesday, ''[[The New York Observer]]'' reported on the nascent protests in Zuccotti Park.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street's Media Problems&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Wall Street Protesters: What the Hell Do They Want?&quot;/&gt;  On Friday, September 23, Ginia Bellafante panned the movement in ''The New York Times''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunning For Wall Street, With Faulty Aim&quot;/&gt;  Joanna Weiss of ''[[The Boston Globe]]'' found it difficult to take the protests seriously, criticizing Occupy Wall Street for its &quot;circus&quot; atmosphere.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The right way to get heard&quot;/&gt; In a September 27 article, Lauren Ellis of ''Mother Jones'' magazine criticized the movement's lack of a clear message.&lt;ref name=&quot;ellis&quot;/&gt;

By October 4, economist [[Richard D. Wolff|Richard Wolff]] commented that the unclear shape of the movement is &quot;mostly irrelevant&quot; at this early stage and the priority should be to invite all interested parties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi19&quot;/&gt; [[Kalle Lasn]], co-founder of ''Adbusters'', believed that the protests had gone mainstream and expressed the opinion that &quot;it's become kind of a political left movement in the U.S., hopefully to rival the Tea Party.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;msn20&quot;/&gt; Michael Daly, of ''[[Newsweek]]'' and ''[[The Daily Beast]]'' characterized the position of the protesters as a &quot;feeling that there is just a fundamental unfairness. From their point of view, the very people who almost wrecked the U.S. economy on Wall Street continue to get wealthy while working people are struggling to pay their bills.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews21&quot;/&gt;  On October 11, [[Katrina vanden Heuvel]], who writes a weekly column for ''[[The Post]]'' and is the editor and publisher of ''[[The Nation]]'', said &quot;most understand that the main task ahead is growing the movement,&quot; and pointing to recent legislation, she suggests that the movement has already influenced public dialogue.&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost22&quot;/&gt; From October 17–21 [[Cenk Uygur]] of the internet news show ''[[The Young Turks]]'' filmed the political segment of the show in Zuccotti Park.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

MSNBC's ''Technolog'' noted that policymakers had failed to address economic problems, and news media had failed to cover the unemployment crisis: &quot;Tracking CNN, MSNBC and Fox, ThinkProgress found 7,583 mentions of the word 'debt,' compared to 427 mentions of 'unemployment' on all three networks combined.&quot; [[Nielsen Online|NM Incite]] said 22% of [[Twitter|tweets]] using the #OccupyWallStreet [[hashtag]] voiced general support for the movement, 11% indicated participation in it,&lt;!-- we should measure this in terms of what it means for the number of tweeters who say they are participating --&gt; 5% described celebrity support, 11% were complaints against the movement, 13% shared news, 6% shared videos, 4% blamed government, 2% blamed Obama, and 1% blamed capitalism.

===Police response===
[[File:Day 36 Occupy Wall Street October 21 2011 Shankbone 40.JPG|thumb|right|upright|Community relations detective, Rick Lee, called &quot;The Hipster Cop&quot;]]
Police reaction has varied. Some incidents have been criticized. The [[New York City Police Department]] has assigned Rick Lee, a First Precinct community relations detective, to duty at the demonstration. He is one of the department's main liaisons with the protesters on behalf of the police department, and advises protesters on such matters as, avoiding arrest and getting along with police as well as attempting to get information of protesters plans. As a plainclothes officer, he has been referred to as the &quot;hipster cop&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gq.com/style/profiles/201110/hipster-cop-rick-lee-interview-occupy-wall-street| title=The Hipster Cop: An Occupy Wall Street Conversation| accessdate=11-10-11| publisher=gq.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; for his attire consisting of glasses, cardigan sweaters, skinny ties and skinny trousers. Reaction to his presence is mixed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kilgannon|first=Cory|title=Revealed: The Officer Behind the Skinny Tie|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/18/in-a-sea-of-protesters-one-mysterious-and-well-dressed-officer/|accessdate=October 19, 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Occupy Wall Street has cost the Police Department $5 million in overtime as of October 27.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hennelly|first=Bob|title=NYPD Overtime For Wall Street Protests Divides City Council|url=http://www.wnyc.org/blogs/wnyc-news-blog/2011/oct/27/nypd-overtime-wall-street-protests-divides-city-council/|accessdate=October 31, 2011|newspaper=WNYC AM Radio}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police statistics show competing information. Arrests and crimes have risen, while the number of summonses has fallen. How dangerous it may be for Occupy Wall Street protesters and nearby residents is difficult to assess due to an informal divide that has sprung up between who patrols inside and outside the park. While NYC police are stationed around the periphery, police seem to have ceded patrol of the interior to protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/nyregion/at-occupy-wall-street-protest-rising-concern-about-crime.html?_r=1| title=At Scene of Wall St. Protest, Rising Concerns About Crime| accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=New York times| first1=Cara| last1=Buckley| first2=Matt| last2=Flegenheimer| date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International response===
*[[Brazilian]] President [[Dilma Rousseff]] said, &quot;We agree with some of the expressions that some movements have used around the world [in] demonstrations like the ones we see in the US and other countries.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.latercera.com/noticia/mundo/2011/10/678-399166-9-indignados-en-brasil-manifestaciones-son-pacificas-y-cuentan-con-el-apoyo-de.shtml Indignados en Brasil: manifestaciones son pacíficas y cuentan con el apoyo de presidenta], ''[[La Tercera]]'', October 15, 2011; accessed October 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Canadian]] Prime Minister [[Stephen Harper]] said that because there was nothing like a Canadian [[Troubled Asset Relief Program|TARP]] program, he did not think Canadians were as angry as Americans.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/15/earlyshow/saturday/main20120870.shtml &quot;Occupy Wall Street&quot; protests go global], CBS News, October 15, 2011; accessed October 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  Finance Minister [[Jim Flaherty]] expressed sympathy with the protests, citing high unemployment amongst the youth.  Comparing Canada to the U.S., he said that unlike the U.S., Canada has a [[progressive tax|progressive income tax system]] that favors the vulnerable, and the government has regulated and supervised its financial institutions.&lt;ref name=&quot;vancouverobserver&quot;/&gt;
*[[People's Republic of China]] state news agency [[Xinhua News Agency|Xinhua]] said the protests had exposed &quot;fundamental problems&quot; with the US economic and political systems, and that it showed &quot;a clear need for Washington, which habitually rushes to demand other governments to change when there are popular protests in their countries, to put its own house in order.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Protests reveal US 'messy house': China agency&quot;/&gt;
*[[Egypt]]ian protesters from Tahrir Square have spoken out in support of Occupy Wall Street.  A message of solidarity issued by a collective of Cairo-based protesters declared:  &quot;As the interests of government increasingly cater to the interests and comforts of private, transnational capital, our cities and homes have become progressively more abstract and violent places, subject to the casual ravages of the next economic development or urban renewal scheme.  An entire generation across the globe has grown up realizing, rationally and emotionally, that we have no future in the current order of things.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ArabSpring&quot;/&gt;
*[[Greece|Greek]] Prime Minister [[George Papandreou]] supported the U.S. protests saying, &quot;We fight for changing the global economic system, like many anti-Wall Street citizens who rightly protest against the inequalities and injustices of the system.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot;/&gt;
*[[India]]n Prime Minister [[Manmohan Singh]] stated, &quot;There are reasons why people are protesting. People are protesting in Wall Street, in Europe about the fat salaries that the bankers are getting when people are being asked to tighten their belts. There is problem of growing unemployment in the United States. There is also worry in Europe. So there are problems which the system must have credible answers to take them on board.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraphindia.com/1111020/jsp/frontpage/story_14646335.jsp Singh swims with civil society tide - Anna to Wall Street protest, PM soft], Manini Chatterjee, ''[[The Telegraph (Kolkata)|The Telegraph]]'', October 20, 2011; accessed October 20, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Korean Central News Agency]] of [[North Korea]] commented that the Occupy Wall Street movement were &quot;in protest against exploitation and oppression by capital, shaking all fabrics of society.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;North Korean State Press Writes About Occupy Wall Street&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;News From Korean Central News Agency Of Dprk&quot;/&gt;
*Former president of [[Poland]] and cofounder of the [[Solidarity (Polish trade union)|Polish Solidarity Movement]], [[Lech Wałęsa]], has expressed his support for Occupy Wall Street and is considering a visit to the site.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walesa&quot;/&gt;
*Former [[Soviet Union]] President [[Mikhail Gorbachev]] compared it to the [[perestroika]] period and the collapse of the [[Soviet Union]] superpower, calling the protests justified. He said Americans should put their own house in order before attempting to do such with other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;winnipegfreepress&quot;/&gt;
*Former [[United Kingdom]] Prime Minister [[Gordon Brown]] said the protests were about fairness.  &quot;There are voices in the middle who say, ‘Look, we can build a better financial system that is more sustainable, that is based on a better and proportionate sense of what’s just and fair and where people don’t take reckless risks or, if they do, they’re penalized for doing so.’&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-10-21/ex-british-chief-brown-says-wall-street-protests-seek-fairness.html Ex-British Chief Brown Says Wall Street Protests Seek Fairness], David Lynch, Reuters, October 21, 2011; accessed October 23, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*Former United Kingdom Prime Minister [[Tony Blair]] criticized the movement, stating, “a protest is not the same as a policy. Someone who’s demonstrating will often make demands, but they don’t necessarily have answers.”&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forbes.com/sites/halahtouryalai/2011/11/02/tony-blair-criticizes-occupy-wall-street/ Tony Blair Criticizes Occupy Wall Street], Halah Touryalai, ''Forbes'', November 2, 2011; accessed November 4, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Vatican City]] Cardinal [[Peter Turkson]], a senior Vatican official, defended the protests: &quot;Do people at a certain time have a right to say: 'Do business differently, look at the way you are doing business because this is not leading to our welfare, to our good'? Can people demand this of the people of Wall Street? I think people can and should be able to.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/finance/2011/1025/1224306446936.html Vatican official defends Occupy Wall Street], Paddy Agnew, ''[[The Irish Times]]'', October 25, 2011; accessed October 24, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  The comment was in light of a new publication the Vatican released entitled ''Towards Reforming the International Financial and Monetary Systems in the Context of Global Public Authority'', which agreed with many of the protesters' issues.&lt;ref&gt;[http://content.usatoday.com/communities/Religion/post/2011/10/wall-street-protests-ows-vatican-pope/1 Vatican meets OWS: 'The economy needs ethics'], Cathy Lynn Grossman, ''[[USA Today]]'', October 24, 2011; accessed October 24, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://life.nationalpost.com/2011/10/24/vatican-calles-for-global-economic-authority/ Vatican sides with ‘Occupy’ protesters in call for crackdown on financial markets], Phillip Pullella, ''[[National Post]]'', October 24, 2011; accessed October 24, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Venezuelan]] President [[Hugo Chávez]] condemned the &quot;horrible repression&quot; of the Occupy Wall Street activists and expressed solidarity with the movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo Chavez condemns 'horrible repression' of Wall Street protests&quot;/&gt;

{{space}}
===Responses by notable people===

====Authors and academics====

[[File:Naomi Klein Occupy Wall Street 2011 Shankbone 2.JPG|thumb|left|[[Naomi Klein]] leading an open forum on October 6]]
[[Kate Pickett]], coauthor of ''[[The Spirit Level: Why More Equal Societies Almost Always Do Better]],'' said in [[The Guardian]] that &quot;Few doubt that it was the actions of the rich and the super-rich, the 1%, that created the crisis.  But sadly, debate has not yet been translated into action...This is why we need the Occupy movement and the staunch actions of the trade unions – why we need protest and demonstrations and activism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2011/nov/15/occupy-equality-kate-pickett?newsfeed=true We need Occupy to help deliver equality] by Kate Pickett in the Guardian, Tuesday 15 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Canadian writer [[Naomi Klein]] has spoken at the protest several times.  Writing in the New York Times she said she is &quot;delighted&quot; that OWS has not given in to issuing a list of demands. &quot;This is a young movement still in the process of determining just how powerful it is, and that power will determine what demands are possible. Small movements have to settle for small reforms: big ones have the freedom to dream.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/10/06/can-occupy-wall-street-spark-a-revolution/occupy-wall-st-learns-from-globalization-protests |title=Occupy Wall St. Learns From Globalization Protests - Room for Debate |publisher=NYTimes.com |date=2011-10-06 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Professor and author [[Cornel West]] addressed the frustrations that some critics have expressed at the protest’s lack of a clear and unified message, saying, &quot;It’s impossible to translate the issue of the greed of Wall Street into one demand, or two demands. We’re talking about a democratic awakening.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman2&quot;/&gt;

Philosopher [[Slavoj Žižek]] gave a speech on Wall Street in which he expressed support for the protests saying, &quot;They tell you we are dreamers. The true dreamers are those who think things can go on indefinitely the way they are. We are not dreamers. We are awakening from a dream which is turning into a nightmare.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;24ur&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS PART1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS PART2&quot;/&gt;

On November 15, when police closed the park to overnight use by the protesters, [[Chris Hedges]], who has been participating since the onset, wrote in his weekly column  that he believed that through a rigid adherence to nonviolence and a verbal respect for the police, the movement would continue to move forward to see the realization of its goals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.truthdig.com/report/item/this_is_what_revolution_looks_like_20111115/ |title=Chris Hedges: This Is What Revolution Looks Like - Chris Hedges' Columns |publisher=Truthdig |date=2011-04-08 |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Author [[Barbara Ehrenreich]], in response to the dismantling of the occupations, stated that &quot;One of the appalling things here is that there are so many Democratic mayors involved in these crackdowns or in Bloomberg's case, someone who is seen as a liberal.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/15/barbara-ehrenreich-occupy-wall-street Ehrenreich: Democratic establishment abandoned Occupy Wall Street] ''[[The Guardian]]''. Accessed: 29 November 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

Over one thousand authors have announced their support for the movement via “Occupy Writers”, an online petition that states “We, the undersigned writers and all who will join us, support Occupy Wall Street and the Occupy Movement around the world.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://occupywriters.com/ |title=OccupyWriters.com |publisher=OccupyWriters.com |date=1963-11-22 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The initiative began when [[Jeff Sharlet]] e-mailed [[Salman Rushdie]] to suggest a petition for writers who support Occupy Wall Street,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Witt |first=Emily |url=http://www.observer.com/2011/10/the-zuccotti-literatti-slumbering-prolixariat-awakes/ |title=The Zuccotti Literatti: Slumbering Prolixariat Awakes &amp;#124; The New York Observer |publisher=Observer.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and signatories range the spectrum of literary genres and academic disciplines and include [[Margaret Atwood]],&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon&quot; /&gt; [[Noam Chomsky]],&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Chomsky |first=Noam |url=http://inthesetimes.com/article/12206/occupy_the_future |title=Occupy The Future |publisher=In These Times |date=2011-11-01 |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Neil Gaiman]], [[Daniel Handler]] also known as [[Lemony Snicket]], and [[Alice Walker]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Alison Flood |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2011/oct/20/occupy-movement-authors-atwood-rushdie |title=Occupy movement attracts support of top authors &amp;#124; Books &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk |publisher=Guardian |date= October 20, 2011|accessdate=2011-11-01 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; The site also features original work from the writers expressing their take on the Occupy movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Hynes |first=Eric |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2011/10/25/neil_gaiman_gloria_steinem_and_other_writers_on_occupy_wall_stre.html |title=Neil Gaiman, Gloria Steinem and Other Writers on Occupy Wall Street |publisher=Slate.com |date=2011-10-25 |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Driscoll|first=Molly|title=Lemony Snicket releases &quot;Thirteen Observations on Occupy Wall Street&quot;|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/Books/chapter-and-verse/2011/1019/Lemony-Snicket-releases-Thirteen-Observations-on-Occupy-Wall-Street|accessdate=October 30, 2011|newspaper=[[The Christian Science Monitor]]|date=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Authors and academics supporting include professor of economics and best-selling author [[Ravi Batra]],&lt;ref name=&quot;truth-out&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Batra advise to OWS&quot;/&gt; anthropologist [[David Graeber]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street rediscovers the radical imagination&quot;/&gt; [[Stéphane Hessel]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Stéphane Hessel on Occupy Wall Street: Find the Time for Outrage When Your Values Are Not Respected&quot;/&gt; Nobel Prize winning economists [[Paul Krugman]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Panic of the Plutocrats&quot;/&gt; and [[Joseph Stiglitz]],&lt;ref name=&quot;businside&quot; /&gt; [[Jeff Madrick]],&lt;ref name=&quot;businside&quot;/&gt; Wikipedia founder [[Jimmy Wales]],&lt;ref name=jwales&gt;{{cite news|title=Wikipedia Founder Backs Anti-Greed Demos|url=http://news.sky.com/home/business/article/16090679|accessdate=October 21, 2011|newspaper=[[Sky News]]|date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and professor of economics [[Richard D. Wolff]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi&quot;/&gt;
====Businesspeople====
[[John Paulson]], billionaire and founder of the hedge fund [[Paulson &amp; Co.]], criticized the protesters for &quot;vilifying our most successful businesses,&quot; citing that &quot;The top 1% of New Yorkers pay over 40% of all income taxes, providing huge benefits to everyone in our city and state.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Billionaire Tells Occupy Wall Street to Get Off His Lawn|author=Shira Ovide|newspaper=[[Wall Street Journal]] |date=October 11, 2011 |url=http://blogs.wsj.com/deals/2011/10/11/billionaire-tells-occupy-wall-street-to-get-off-his-lawn/?mod=wsj_share_twitter|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Vikram Pandit]], head of [[Citigroup]], called the protesters' sentiments &quot;completely understandable&quot; and said that Wall Street had broken the trust of its clients.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Now Vikram Pandit Has Responded To The Wall Street Protesters|author=Gus Lubin|newspaper=[[Business Insider]] |date=October 12, 2011 |url=http://www.businessinsider.com/vikram-pandit-responded-occupy-wall-street-protesters-2011-10|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Bill Gross]], manager of [[PIMCO]]'s Total Return Fund, the world's largest [[mutual fund]], stated &quot;Class warfare by the 99%? Of course, they're fighting back after 30 years of being shot at.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=The Occupy Wall Street Protesters Are Just Fighting Back After &quot;30 Years Of Being Shot At'|author=Joe Weisenthal|newspaper=[[Business Insider]] |date=October 11, 2011 |url=http://articles.businessinsider.com/2011-10-11/wall_street/30265981_1_class-warfare-protesters-pimco|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; PIMCO's co-CEO [[Mohamed El-Erian]] argued that people should &quot;listen to Occupy Wall Street.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Financiers for Occupying Wall Street |author=Ezra Klein|newspaper=The Washington Post |date=October 14, 2011 |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/ezra-klein/post/financiers-for-occupying-wall-street/2011/08/25/gIQAypFwjL_blog.html|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Businessman and CEO [[Peter Schiff]] wrote an opinion column where he stated, &quot;I own a brokerage firm, but I didn't receive any bailout money... Yes, I am the 1% - but I've earned every penny. Instead of trying to take my wealth away, I hope they learn from my example.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.safehaven.com/article/23113/in-defense-of-the-1 In Defense of the 1%], by Peter Schiff, safehaven.com, October 28, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; The lobbying firm [[Clark Lytle Geduldig &amp; Cranford]] proposed to the [[American Bankers Association]] a plan to respond to the Occupy movement by researching the 'backers' and doing [[public relations]] work against them like putting negative stories in the media.&lt;ref name=msnbc1/&gt;

[[Karl Denninger]], former [[CEO]] and one of the original co-founders of the [[Tea Party movement]], expressed support for the movement, saying &quot;The problem with protests and the political process is that it is very easy, no matter how big the protest is, for the politicians to simply wait until the people go home, and then they can ignore you. Well, Occupy Wall Street was a little different, and back in 2008, I wrote that when we will actually see change is when the people come, they set up camp, and they refuse to go home. That appears to be happening now.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2011/10/14/tea-party-co-founded-expresses-support-for-occupy-wall-street/|title=Tea Party co-founder expresses support for Occupy Wall Street|date=October 14, 2011|last=Kane|first=Muriel|publisher=Raw Story|accessdate=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jeff Immelt]], CEO of [[General Electric]] and a member of Obama's [[President's Economic Recovery Advisory Board|Economic Recovery Advisory Board]], stated &quot;It is natural to assume that people are angry, and I think we have to be empathetic and understand that people are not feeling great.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=And Now Jeff Immelt Has Sided With Occupy Wall Street|author=Gus Lubin|newspaper=[[Business Insider]] |date=October 19, 2011 |url=http://articles.businessinsider.com/2011-10-19/news/30295099_1_jeff-immelt-ge-s-ceo-vikram-pandit|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Ray Dalio]], founder of [[Bridgewater Associates]], the world's largest [[hedge fund]], stated in an interview with [[Charlie Rose]], &quot;I think the number one problem is that we're not having a quality dialogue...I certainly understand the frustration, I understand the dilemma, I understand the discontent.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Bridgewater Founder Ray Dalio On Occupy Wall Street, The Economy, And The 'Cult' Of His Own Company|author=Lisa Du|newspaper=[[Business Insider]] |date=October 22, 2011 |url=http://www.businessinsider.com/bridgewater-founder-ray-dalio-talked-about-ows-the-cult-of-his-company-with-charlie-rose-last-night-2011-10|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other business leaders lending their support include [[George Soros]]&lt;ref name=&quot;lemonde&quot;/&gt; and [[Russell Simmons]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Russell Simmons visits 'Occupy Wall Street' protesters with bottles of water, words of encouragement&quot;/&gt;

==== Celebrities ====
[[File:Day 28 Occupy Wall Street Tom Morello 2011 Shankbone 7.JPG|left|thumb|[[Tom Morello]] of [[Rage Against the Machine]], who is a member of the [[Industrial Workers of the World]], on Day 28 of Occupy Wall Street&lt;ref name=&quot;madison1&quot;&gt;Derby, Samara Kalk, [http://host.madison.com/wsj/news/local/govt-and-politics/article_04cbc112-3e41-11e0-be90-001cc4c03286.html &quot;Monona Terrace rocked by workers' rights concert&quot;], ''Wisconsin State Journal''. Retrieved October 22, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

On September 19, [[Roseanne Barr]], the first celebrity to endorse the protest, spoke to protesters calling for a combination of [[capitalism]] and [[socialism]] and a system not based on &quot;bloated talk radio hosts and that goddamn Ayn Rand book.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street: A protest timeline&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street: Celebrities Show Support&quot;/&gt;

[[Filmmaking|Filmmaker]] [[Michael Moore]] also spoke in support, saying, &quot;They have tried to take our democracy and turn it into a kleptocracy.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Moore gives speech at Liberty Plaza for 'Occupy Wall Street'&quot;/&gt;
[[Rapper]] [[Lupe Fiasco]], one of the initial supporters of Occupy Wall Street, wrote a poem, &quot;Moneyman,&quot; for the protest.&lt;ref name=&quot;U.S. Day of Rage planned for Saturday&amp;nbsp;– an Arab Spring in America?&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lupefiasco&quot;/&gt;  [[Susan Sarandon]] spoke at the demonstration saying, &quot;I came down here to educate myself.... There's a huge void between the rich and the poor in this country.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Susan Sarandon lends star power to Wall Street protests&quot;/&gt;  Actor and activist [[Mark Ruffalo]] has supported the Occupy Wall Street protest saying, &quot;Peaceful Resistance. That is what changes the world. We must be peaceful. This movement is about decency.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: Mark Ruffalo Adds to Star Power, Christian News&quot;/&gt;

[[Jeff Mangum]] of [[Neutral Milk Hotel]] played a solo acoustic set for the protesters on October 4,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youaintnopicasso.com/2011/10/04/jeff-mangum-playing-at-occupy-wall-st-watch-it-live/|title=Jeff Mangum playing at Occupy Wall St! Watch it live!|date=October 5, 2011|first=Matt|publisher=''You Ain't No Picasso''|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Tom Morello]] performed on October 13.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.rawstory.com/rs/2011/10/09/tom-morello-plays-at-occupy-los-angeles-protest/|title=Tom Morello at Occupy Wall Street: 'Take It Easy, but Take It' - Performs four-song set as the Nightwatchman in support of protest movement|date=October 13, 2011|last=Sundermann|first=Eric|work=Rolling Stone|accessdate=October 23, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Folk singer [[Pete Seeger]] led a group of several hundred protesters on a march through the streets on October 22, singing several songs, including &quot;[[This Land Is Your Land]]&quot; and &quot;[[We Shall Overcome]].&quot; Other musicians joining them included [[Arlo Guthrie]], [[Tao Rodríguez-Seeger]], [[Tom Chapin]], [[David Amram]], and [[Guy Davis (musician)|Guy Davis]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/22/pete-seeger-leads-protesters-on-foot-and-in-song/|title=Pete Seeger Leads Protesters, on Foot and in Song|date=October 22, 2011|last=Moynihan|first=Colin|work=The New York Times|accessdate=October 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 23, [[Asmaa Mahfouz]], whose video blog helped spark the 2011 uprising in Egypt, held a teach-in at Liberty Plaza.  When asked why she came to the OWS protest she replied, &quot;Many of U.S. residents was in solidarity with us. So, we have to keep going all over the world, because another world is possible for all of us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.democracynow.org/2011/10/25/from_tahrir_to_wall_street_egyptian |title=From Tahrir to Wall Street: Egyptian Revolutionary Asmaa Mahfouz Speaks at Occupy Wall Street |publisher=Democracynow.org |date= |accessdate=2011-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 23, musicians [[Sean Lennon]] and [[Rufus Wainwright]] showed their support for the Occupy movement and played among a large crowd in Zuccotti Park.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/24/sean-lennon-performs-at-occupy-wall-street_n_1028924.html |title=Sean Lennon Performs At Occupy Wall Street With Rufus Wainwright (VIDEO) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/24/rufus-wainwright-sean-lennon-material-girl-ows_n_1029298.html |title=Rufus Wainwright, Sean Lennon Perform Madonna's 'Material Girl' At Occupy Wall Street Protests (VIDEO) |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On October 25, international street artist [[Above (artist)|Above]] completed a 255 foot long mural in Miami, Florida that read &quot;Give a wall st. banker enough rope and he will hang himself&quot; next to [[Interstate 95 in Florida|Interstate 95]]. The artist installed a controversial effigy that mimicked a 'wall st' banker hanging from a noose.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vimeo.com/31551453 |title=Give a wall street banker... |publisher=vimeo.com/above |date= |accessdate=October 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbcmiami.com/news/Occupy-Art-Has-Miami-Motorists-Doing-Double-Take-133233768.html |title=Occupy Art Has Miami Motorists Doing Double-Take |publisher=Donna Rappado |date= |accessdate=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 8, folk-rock singers [[David Crosby]] and [[Graham Nash]] appeared at Zuccotti Park to offer their support and sing to the occupiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.rollingstone.com/videos/new-and-hot/david-crosby-and-graham-nash-perform-at-occupy-wall-street-20111108|title=David Crosby and Graham Nash Perform at Occupy Wall Street|last=Vozick-Levinson|first=Simon|date=8 November 2011|work=[[Rolling Stone]]|accessdate=28 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Three days later, on November 11, folk singer [[Joan Baez]] sang there as well. Many of the young protesters were not familiar with her songs and were unaware of her long history as an activist.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/folkie-protest-singer-joan-baez-sings-ows-protesters-young-article-1.976364 |title=Folkie protest singer Joan Baez sings for OWS protesters too young to know her |publisher=NY Daily News |date=2011-11-11 |accessdate=2011-11-17 |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In fellowship with &quot;Occupy Writers&quot;, hundreds are signed supporters as &quot;Occupy Musicians&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.occupymusicians.com/ Occupy Musicians]&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Occupy Filmmakers&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.occupyfilmmakers.com/ Occupy Filmmakers]&lt;/ref&gt; respectively. Additionally, &quot;Occupy Comics&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://occupycomics.com/ Occupy Comics]&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;Occupy Design&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[Occupy Design http://occupydesign.org/]&lt;/ref&gt; have lent their talent in support. Other celebrities lending their support include [[John Carlos]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman&quot;/&gt; [[Anti-Flag]],&lt;ref name=&quot;anti-flag&quot;/&gt; [[Radiohead]],&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.radiohead.com/deadairspace/index.php?c=637|title=Hello Fluffy - Radiohead}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Talib Kweli]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=By&amp;nbsp;Eric Sundermann |url=http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/talib-kweli-at-occupy-wall-street-we-have-to-grow-20111007 |title=Talib Kweli at Occupy Wall Street: 'We Have to Grow' &amp;#124; Music News |publisher=Rolling Stone |date=2011-10-07 |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Kanye West]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kanye West, Russell Simmons lend support to Occupy Wall Street protesters&quot;/&gt;

[[Miley Cyrus]] released a video on her official YouTube channel for the remix of &quot;[[Liberty Walk]]&quot; from her album &quot;[[Can't Be Tamed]].&quot;  The video is entirely made of footage from the Occupy movement, including police beatings.  On her YouTube channel the video is dedicated &quot;to the thousands of people who are standing up for what they believe in...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/gossip/2011/11/miley-cyrus-ows-occupy-wall-street-liberty-walk-video.html Miley Cyrus supports Occupy Wall Street with new video] The Los Angeles Times, November 28, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/news/opinion/opedcolumnists/miley_cyrus_occupy_exploit_LItCWr0SdqpOnN6CB78cEM Miley Cyrus’ ‘Occupy’ exploit] [[New York Post]], December 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

====Wealthy supporters====

Several wealthy supporters have joined the protest, and have started a blog, westandwiththe99percent,&lt;ref&gt;[http://westandwiththe99percent.tumblr.com/ westandwiththe99percent] blog&lt;/ref&gt; in which they say, &quot;I am the 1%. I stand with the 99%,&quot; and give their stories.&lt;ref name=&quot;wealthy&quot;&gt;[http://blogs.wsj.com/metropolis/2011/10/20/occupy-wall-street-attracts-one-percenters/ Super-Wealthy Join Protesters on Wall Street], By Rebecca Rothbaum, Wall Street Journal, October 20, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The granddaughter of oil tycoon [[H. L. Hunt]], Leah Hunt-Hendrix, 28, was quoted as saying “We should acknowledge our privilege and claim the responsibilities that come with it.”&lt;ref name=&quot;wealthy&quot;/&gt; Farhad Ebrahimi, who received an inheritance as a teenager, has been participating in the Occupy Boston protest wearing a T-shirt that says, &quot;Tax me. I'm good for it.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;wealthy&quot;/&gt;  [[Russell Simmons]], hip-hop artist and successful businessman, has actively supported the OWS movement saying that he believes that it is his moral duty to do so. &quot;You give what you get. I want to do what I can to relieve suffering and improve the quality of other's lives.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/23/russell-simmons-on-occupy_n_1108795.html |title=Russell Simmons On Occupy Wall Street: 'It Is My Moral Duty To Do This' |publisher=Huffingtonpost.com |date= |accessdate=2011-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Criticism===
{{POV section|New_version_of_text_summarizing_how_RS_have_characterized_criticism_of_OWS|date=December 2011}}
There has been criticism of the Occupy Wall Street movement by various groups and individuals. According to recent polling, most Republican voters have an unfavorable view of the movement by a large margin.&lt;ref name=&quot;QuinnipiacNov3&quot;/&gt;

In an opinion piece in the ''Wall Street Journal'', pollster [[Douglas Schoen]] wrote that the protesters reflect &quot;values that are dangerously out of touch with the broad mass of the American people&quot; and have &quot;a deep commitment to left-wing policies: opposition to free-market capitalism and support for radical redistribution of wealth, intense regulation of the private sector, and protectionist policies to keep American jobs from going overseas,&quot; and that politicians who support them will be hurt in the 2012 elections.&lt;ref name=&quot;WSJ-Schoen&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204479504576637082965745362.html |title=Polling the Occupy Wall Street Crowd |first=Douglas |last=Schoen |date=18 |month=October |year=2011 |publisher=The Wall Street Journal |quote=Last week, senior White House adviser David Plouffe said that &quot;the protests you're seeing are the same conversations people are having in living rooms and kitchens all across America. . . . People are frustrated by an economy that does not reward hard work and responsibility, where Wall Street and Main Street don't seem to play by the same set of rules.&quot; Nancy Pelosi and others have echoed the message.  Yet the Occupy Wall Street movement reflects values that are dangerously out of touch with the broad mass of the American people—and particularly with swing voters who are largely independent and have been trending away from the president since the debate over health-care reform.  The protesters have a distinct ideology and are bound by a deep commitment to radical left-wing policies. On Oct. 10 and 11, Arielle Alter Confino, a senior researcher at my polling firm, interviewed nearly 200 protesters in New York's Zuccotti Park. Our findings probably represent the first systematic random sample of Occupy Wall Street opinion.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Journalist [[David Weigel]] responded in an opinion piece published on [[Slate]] characterizing Schoen's opinion piece as &quot;a dishonest column full of claims that couldn't be backed up by his own research&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Slate-Weigel&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.slate.com/blogs/weigel/2011/11/10/doug_schoen_the_official_anti_spokesman_of_occupy_wall_street.html |title=Doug Schoen, the Official Anti-Spokesman of Occupy Wall Street |first=Weigel |last=David |date=10 |month=November |year=2011 |publisher=Slate}}&lt;/ref&gt; while ''Washington Monthly'' lead blogger [[Steve Benen]] wrote an opinion piece accusing Schoen of political spin in his analysis and referring to Schoen, a frequent contributor to Fox News, as &quot;the quintessential 'Fox News Democrat'&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;WM-Benen&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/political-animal/2011_10/doug_schoen_isnt_helping_his_r032892.php# |title=Doug Schoen isn't helping his reputation|first=Benen |last=Steve |date=18 |month=October |year=2011 |publisher=Washington Monthly}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A group of bloggers, led by political commentator [[Erick Erickson]], organized a website criticizing the movement entitled &quot;We Are the 53%,&quot; referring to the 53% of Americans who earn enough income to pay federal income taxes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Luhby |first=Tami |url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/10/26/news/economy/occupy_wall_street_backlash/index.htm |title=The 53%: Occupy Wall Street backlash - Oct. 26, 2011 |publisher=Money.cnn.com |date=2011-10-26 |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; An opinion piece by CBS contributor Jim Edwards, comparing the [[We are the 99%]] blog to the 53% blog, commented that &quot;once you've looked at both blogs, the impression you come away with is that the recession is as devastating to conservatives as it is to liberals, but that conservatives regard their misfortunes as their own fault whereas the liberals see structural forces at work -- lack of health insurance, student loans -- that they cannot overcome.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-505123_162-42750571/occupy-wall-street-we-are-the-53-counter-protestors-are-in-the-same-boat/ Occupy Wall Street: 'We Are the 53%' Counter-Protestors Are in the Same Boat] By Jim Edwards, CBS News October 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Mike Brownfield of [[The Heritage Foundation]] argued that rejection of the capitalist system and the policies that OWS protesters advocate, including limits on trade and student loan forgiveness, would not lead to improved economic conditions for unemployed Americans. According to Brownfield, the Foundation believes it is &quot;right to decry out-of-control bailouts and corporate subsidies&quot; and there are valid concerns regarding the economy, unemployment rates and low job creation. However, Heritage argued that capitalism is key to improving the economy and that the movement is focusing on the wrong solutions to the problems they protest: it should be protesting the expansion of government instead of calling for more government intervention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://blog.heritage.org/2011/10/18/morning-bell-wall-street-is-the-wrong-place-to-occupy/ |title=Morning Bell: Wall Street is the Wrong Place to Occupy |last1=Brownfield |first1=Mike |date=October 18, 2011 |work=blog.heritage.org |publisher=The Heritage Foundation |accessdate=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mark Tooley]] of the [[Institute on Religion and Democracy]], said that while Occupy Wall Street has succeeded in getting attention, it is limited because it is only attracting religious support from the left.&lt;ref name=&quot;IRD&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://news.yahoo.com/religion-claims-place-occupy-wall-street-171204904.html| title = Religion claims its place in Occupy Wall Street|quote=Mark Tooley of the Institute on Religion and Democracy, an advocacy group for conservative mainline Protestants, said while Occupy Wall Street has succeed in getting attention, it's limited because it's only attracting religious support from the left. A call for government redistribution of wealth and reliance on street activism doesn't appeal to the swath of suburban churchgoers with conservative political and religious leanings, he said.|publisher = [[Yahoo! News]]|year=2011|=accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He said that a call for the government redistribution of wealth and reliance on street activism did not appeal to those with conservative political or religious leanings.&lt;ref name=&quot;IRD&quot;/&gt; The protest has been criticized for tolerating [[antisemitism|anti-Semitic]] activists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thejewishweek.com/news/national/adl_urges_protest_organizers_condemn_anti_semitic_incidents|title=ADL Urges Protest Organizers To Condemn Anti-Semitic Incidents|last=Chandler|first=Doug|date=October 18, 2011|publisher=The Jewish Week|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Emergency Committee for Israel]] ran an ad condemning anti-Semitic remarks and calling on Obama and other political officials to do likewise.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/right-turn/post/occupy-wall-street-does-anyone-care-about-the-anti-semitism/2011/03/29/gIQA43p8rL_blog.html|title=Occupy Wall Street: Does anyone care about the anti-Semitism?|last=Rubin|first=Jennifer|date=October 17, 2011|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; These allegations lead the Anti-Defamation League to call on the movement &quot;to condemn anti-Semitic signs and comments that have appeared at some of the protest rallies across the country and around the world.&quot;&lt;ref name=Foxman&gt;{{cite news|last=Foxman|first=Abraham H.|title=ADL Calls On 'Occupy Wall Street' Organizers To Condemn Anti-Semitic Remarks Made At rallies|url=http://www.adl.org/PresRele/ASUS_12/6138_12.htm|newspaper=Anti-Defamation League|date=17 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other journalists have disputed allegations of anti-Semitism as not reflecting the movement as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/where-are-the-anti-semites-of-occupy-wall-street/2011/10/24/gIQAP89eDM_story.html|title=Where are the anti-Semites of Occupy Wall Street?|last=Cohen|first=Richard|date=October 24, 2011|publisher=The Washington Post|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/22/nyregion/occupy-wall-street-criticized-for-flashes-of-anti-semitism.html|title=Cries of Anti-Semitism, but Not at Zuccotti Park|last=Berger|first=Joseph|date=October 21, 2011|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Complaints by local residents====
[[File:Day 14 Occupy Wall Street September 30 2011 Shankbone 11.JPG|thumb|left|Protesters dance in front of drummers at the protest]]
Some residents of the area surrounding Zuccotti Park have voiced complaints about the demonstrations. A caller to a radio show complained that the park has been rendered &quot;unusable&quot; by the protesters, and that &quot;a general atmosphere of incivility,&quot; together with loud shouting and drums, prevailed; another complained that the drums from the protest, which he said &quot;start in the morning&quot; and get louder in the evening until 11:30&amp;nbsp;pm, made it difficult for his children to sleep or do their homework. Another resident complained that protesters had been vandalizing and urinating in the vestibule to his apartment building.&lt;ref name=&quot;NY Post Bloomberg article&quot;/&gt;  Responding to a caller to his radio show complaining about noise and incivility at the park, Mayor Michael Bloomberg said &quot;we couldn't agree more.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NY Post Bloomberg article&quot;/&gt; The Mayor has been criticized for alienating both supporters and critics for his stance that seems supportive of the protests one day and opposed on others. The Mayor has vowed to crack down on the protester's behavior as well as saying he’ll allow the protests indefinitely.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/conflicting-remarks-mayor-bloomberg-chooses-words-carefully-occupy-wall-street-article-1.976417?localLinksEnabled=false| title=After conflicting remarks, Mayor Bloomberg chooses words carefully on Occupy Wall Street | accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=NYDailyNews.com| location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{space}}
{{space}}

=== Popular culture references ===
CNBC correspondent [[Jane Wells]] reported that the Occupy Wall Street movement sparked parodies which connect the movement to pop culture icons from  ''[[Star Wars]]'' and ''[[Lord of the Rings]]'' and others. An image of [[Luke Skywalker]] holding a protest sign was published: &quot;It wasn't glamorous but I had a steady living working on my uncle's moisture farm... my aunt and uncle were unjustly murdered and the farm destroyed. I was forced to leave my home and join an extinct cult just to survive. I am now a member of an upstart movement to take down a greedy corrupt establishment. I AM THE 99%.&quot; Skywalker's enemies, the [[Stormtrooper (Star Wars)|Imperial Storm Troopers]], joined the protest on another image circulating on the Internet holding signs: &quot;End Galactic Corporate Greed&quot;, &quot;Get Our Troops Off Tatooine&quot; and &quot;Keep Your Empirical Hands Off My Healthcare&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://badassdigest.com/2011/10/18/occupy-arrakis-luke-skywalker-is-the-99/
|title=Occupy Arrakis! Luke Skywalker Is The 99%!|last=Faraci|first=Devin|date=18 October 2011|work=|publisher=[[Badass Digest]]|accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Parodies relating to [[Middle Earth]] include a woman who had written her complaint in [[Elvish]], allegedly translated: &quot;I spend every waking hour fighting Orcs while Elrond and Galadriel eat lembas bread all day. I am the 99%&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jane Wells&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Wells|first=Jane|title=Occupy Movement Is Out of This World|url=http://www.cnbc.com/id/45018850|accessdate=25 October 2011|publisher=[[CNBC]]|date=24 Oct 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other parodies include Occupy [[Narnia]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Jane Wells&quot; /&gt; and Occupy [[Sesame Street]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Sesame Street&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/wireStory/occupy-protests-give-birth-catchphrase-14823246|title='Occupy' Protests Give Birth to New Catchphrase|last=Hill| first=Michael|date=27 October 2011|agency=Associated Press|publisher=[[ABC News]]|accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Occupy Sesame Street went viral and, following violent encounters between NYPD and the protesters, [[Tumblr]] posted pictures of [[Elmo]] arrested, [[Grover]] restrained, and [[Count von Count]] pepper-sprayed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goes Viral&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/10/occupy-sesame-street_n_1004014.html|title=Occupy Sesame Street Goes Viral|last=Stampler|first=Laura|date=October 11, 2011|publisher=Huffington Post|accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Occupy Wall Street and its related protests were satirized in the ''[[South Park]]'' episode [[1% (South Park)|&quot;1%&quot;]], which aired on November 2, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.southparkstudios.com/full-episodes/s15e12-one-percent |title=1% (Season 15, Episode 12) - Full Episode Player |publisher=South Park Studios |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ross |first=Dalton |url=http://watching-tv.ew.com/2011/11/02/south-park-the-1-obama/ |title='South Park' review: Cartman was the '1%' &amp;#124; Ken Tucker's TV &amp;#124; EW.com |publisher=Watching-tv.ew.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Remy Munasifi]] wrote and sang a song called &quot;Occupy Wall Street Protest Song,&quot; which criticized the protestors for not understanding, in his opinion, how well off they are.  According to [[Agence France-Presse|AFP]], the song went [[viral video|viral]] in early October.&lt;ref&gt;[http://reason.com/blog/2011/10/10/remys-occupy-wall-street-prote Remy's Occupy Wall Street Protest Song], Reason magazine, October 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5gq0RG06ogF_lhrt4NamzD82Y8OOA?docId=CNG.a82b52e7bd3813cbcd907bbf111de5d6.1191 Occupy Wall Street gets a theme song ... sort of], AFP, October 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

Popular culture images are also employed by protesters to make statements. For example, [[Guy Fawkes mask]]s from the film ''[[V for Vendetta (film)|V for Vendetta]]'' are worn by protesters in New York and around the world as visual symbols of resistance against corporate greed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-15359735|title=V for Vendetta masks: Who's behind them?|last=Waites|first=Rosie|date=20 October 2011|work=[[BBC Online]]|accessdate=27 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Crime==
On October 11, it was reported that OWS protesters staying in Zuccotti Park were dealing with a worsening security problem with reports of multiple incidents of assault, drug dealing and use, and sexual assault.&lt;ref name=&quot;nypost1&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/party_over_bum_ezkUNyRYN1Z94jCRyIddFM |title='Occupy' crasher busted in grope |publisher=www.nypost.com |date=October 11, 2011 |first1=Helen |last1=Freund |first2=Lachlan |last2=Cartwright |first3=Josh |last3=Saul}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Crown Heights man was charged with sexually assaulting a protester at the park raising the level of public discussion of lawlessness at the demonstrations. Protesters use de-escalation techniques, talking down or blocking with their bodies those people throwing punches. In more tense situations, protesters encircle troublemakers and usher them out. But many times, those kicked out or arrested return.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/nyregion/at-occupy-wall-street-protest-rising-concern-about-crime.html?_r=1| title=At Scene of Wall St. Protest, Rising Concerns About Crime| accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=New York Times| first1=Cara| last1=Buckley| first2=Matt| last2=Flegenheimer| date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protester sanitation teams have reported finding needles in tents, and reports of crack and crystal meth use have surfaced. But most protesters say that the most serious concern is the risk of assault, especially for women and at night. Demonstrators have complained of thefts of assorted items such as cell phones and laptops. Thieves also stole $2500 of donations that were stored in a makeshift kitchen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/criminal_occupation_oh3CnKANUqYHrGPCaZaLRK |title=Thieves preying on fellow protesters |publisher=www.nypost.com |date=October 18, 2011 |first1=Larry |last1=Celona}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 10, a &quot;methadone-addled man freeloading off the Wall Street protest&quot; was arrested for groping a woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;nypost1&quot;/&gt; On Nov 10, 2011, A man was arrested at OWS for breaking an [[Emergency medical technician|EMT]]'s leg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Siegal |first=Ida |url=http://www.nbcnewyork.com/news/local/Occupy-Wall-Street-EMT-Assaulted-Zuccotti-Park-Arrest-133613788.html |title=Man Arrested for Breaking EMT's Leg at Occupy Wall Street |publisher=NBC New York |date= |accessdate=2011-11-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Police Commissioner Paul Browne complained that protesters delayed reporting crime. He stated that it's OWS protocol not to report such incidents to the police until there were three complaints against the same individual.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.metro.us/newyork/local/article/1015197--michael-bloomberg-occupy-crime-is-unreported| title=Michael Bloomberg: Crime at Occupy Wall Street goes unreported| accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=Free Daily News Group Inc.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The protesters denied a &quot;three strikes policy&quot;, and one protester told the ''New York Daily News'' that he had heard police respond to a complaint by saying, &quot;You need to deal with that yourselves&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.nydailynews.com/new-york/occupy-wall-street-protesters-odds-mayor-bloomberg-nypd-crime-zuccotti-park-article-1.971741| title=Occupy Wall Street protesters at odds with Mayor Bloomberg, NYPD over crime in Zuccotti Park| accessdate=11-11-11| publisher=NYDailyNews.com| location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

:&quot;A lot of the folks that are involved in the security operations at the park have been saying that -- when they encounter, you know, sort of transient, homeless type of people there in the park -- they are hearing reports that the police have been encouraging them to head down to Zuccotti, to &quot;Take it to Zuccotti.&quot;  It's very upsetting. Particularly, when you consider that some of the people that are arriving to the park have severe psychiatric problems or drug-addiction problems.&quot; Ryan Devereaux, reporter for ''[[Democracy Now!]]''.&lt;ref&gt;http://i2.crtcdn1.net/shows/countdown/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/KOCompleteTranscript10-31-2011.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;New York Daily News, 30 Oct. 2011, &quot;At Occupy Wall Street Central, a Rift Is Growing between East and West Sides of the Plaza: The Wall Street Protesters Determined to “Occupy Everything” Now Find Themselves, in a Sense, Occupied,&quot; http://www.nydailynews.com/opinion/occupy-wall-street-central-a-rift-growing-east-west-sides-plaza-article-1.969320?pgno=2&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 16, 2011, police arrested Nkrumah Tinsley, 29, and charged him with with making a terroristic threat, after police saw a video of him saying, “On the 17th, we going to burn New York City to the fucking ground,” and &quot;In a few days they’re going to see what a Molotov cocktail can do to Macy’s.&quot; He had been previously arrested for assaulting a police officer during another protest on October 26.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/ows_protester_busted_for_alleged_FrkekP1AnYGiwtYtnp8YHP OWS protester busted for allegedly threatening to hurl Molotov cocktails at Macy's], New York Post, November 16, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/150863/protesters-to-move-beyond-the-park-in--day-of-action-| title=Protester Arrested After Threatening To Attack Macy's | accessdate=11-16-11| publisher=NY1.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nymag.com/daily/intel/2011/11/molotov-cocktail-ows-protester-arrested.htmlOccupy Wall Street Protester Who Threatened ‘Molotov Cocktail’ Arrested] [[New York Magazine]] November 16, 2011 By Brett Smiley&lt;/ref&gt; Defense lawyer Pierre Sussman said that Tinsley had been exercising his right to free speech, and that he was not really going to do the things he said.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nbcnewyork.com/news/local/Occupy-Wall-Street-Protest-Arrest-Macys-Molotov-Cocktail-Bomb-134054463.html Occupy Protester's Macy's Bomb Threat &quot;Bluster:&quot; Attorney], NBC, November 17, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; When police carried out a search warrant of Tinsley's home, they did not find any bomb making materials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nydailynews.com/news/crime/nkrumah-tinsley-protester-accused-molotov-cocktail-threats-rants-court-article-1.979310 Nkrumah Tinsley, the protester accused of molotov cocktail threats, rants in court], New York Daily News, November 17, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

====Sexual assaults====
After several weeks of occupation, Occupy Wall Street protesters had made enough allegations of sexual assault and gropings that women-only sleeping tents were set up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gothamist.com/2011/11/05/occupy_wall_street_erects_women-onl.php |title=Occupy Wall Street Erects Women-Only Tent After Reports Of Sexual Assaults |publisher=The Gothamist News |date= |accessdate=2011-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;  David Park was arrested for a sexual assault that occurred in Zuccotti Park on October 8.  At the time of the incident, Park had numerous warrants for his arrests.  Tonye Iketubosin who worked as a kitchen helper was charged with an October 24 sexual assault of an 18-year-old fellow protester. Prosecutors believe he is responsible for an assault on another 18-year-old woman.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/protester_busted_in_tent_grope_QxAzp8mG8pULWA6cPzgnXL |title= Protester busted in tent grope, suspected in rape of another demonstrator |publisher=NY POST |date= November 3, 2011|accessdate=2011-11-21 |first=Jamie |last=Schram}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wpix.com/news/wpix-zuccotti-sex-abuse,0,2577863.story |title=Man Arrested For Groping Protester Also Eyed In Zuccotti Park Rape Case |publisher=WPIX |date= |accessdate=2011-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.nydailynews.com/2011-11-02/news/30352474_1_connecticut-man-encampment-demonstrators |title=Arrest made in Occupy Wall St. sex attack; Suspect eyed in another Zuccotti gropingCase |publisher=NY Daily News |date= |accessdate=2011-11-21 |location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Occupy Wall Street organizers released a statement regarding the sexual assaults stating, &quot;As individuals and as a community, we have the responsibility and the opportunity to create an alternative to this culture of violence, We are working for an OWS and a world in which survivors are respected and supported unconditionally… We are redoubling our efforts to raise awareness about sexual violence. This includes taking preventative measures such as encouraging healthy relationship dynamics and consent practices that can help to limit harm.”  A police union leader stated, “We have no way of really knowing. If you have three or five crimes reported, you really don’t know if it’s eight or 10 that happened.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2011/11/09/rash-sex-attacks-and-violent-crime-breaks-out-at-occupy-protests |title=Occupy Protests Plagued by Reports of Sex Attacks, Violent Crime |publisher=NY Daily News |date= November 9, 2011|accessdate=2011-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Chronology==
{{main|Timeline of Occupy Wall Street}}

=== First four weeks (September 17 – October 14) ===
[[File:Wallst14occupy.jpg|left|thumb|Protesters rallying near New York police headquarters, [[St. Andrew's Church (New York City)|St. Andrew's Church]] in the background.]]
On September 17, 1,000 protesters marched through the streets, with an estimated 100 to 200 staying overnight in cardboard boxes.  By September 19, seven people had been arrested.&lt;ref name=&quot;NYPD Arrest Seven Wall Street Protesters&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;businessweek1&quot;/&gt;{{anchor|Anthony Bologna}}
At least 80 arrests were made on September 24,&lt;ref name=&quot;arrests&quot;/&gt; after protesters started marching uptown and forcing the closure of several streets.&lt;ref name=&quot;crackdown&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;times2&quot;/&gt; Most of the 80 arrests were for blocking traffic, though some were also charged with [[disorderly conduct]] and resisting arrest. Police officers used a technique called [[kettling]] which involves using orange nets to isolate protesters into smaller groups.&lt;ref name=crackdown/&gt;&lt;ref name=times2/&gt;  Videos which showed several penned-in female demonstrators being hit with [[pepper spray]] by a police official were widely disseminated, sparking controversy.&lt;ref name=&quot;dailynews0929&quot;/&gt; That police official was identified as [[Inspector#United States|Deputy Inspector]] Anthony Bologna, and other videos imerged showing him hitting a photographer with a burst of spray as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt0928&quot;/&gt;

The activist [[Anonymous]] subsequently published the name, phone number and family details of the police officer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Karen McVeigh in New York |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/sep/26/occupy-wall-street-police-named |title=Occupy Wall Street activists name officer over pepper spray incident &amp;#124; World news &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk |publisher=Guardian |date= September 26, 2011|accessdate=2011-12-05 |location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Initially Police Commissioner [[Raymond W. Kelly]] and a representative for Bologna defended his actions, while decrying the disclosure of his personal information.&lt;ref name=&quot;dailynews0929&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt0928&quot;/&gt; After growing public furor, Kelly announced that [[Internal affairs (law enforcement)|Internal Affairs]] and the Civilian Complaint Review Board were opening investigations,&lt;ref name=&quot;dailynews0929&quot;/&gt; again criticizing Anonymous for &quot;[trying] to intimidate, putting the names of children, where children go to school,&quot; and adding that this tactic was &quot;totally inappropriate, despicable.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dailynews0929&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, Manhattan [[District Attorney]] [[Cyrus Vance, Jr.]] started his own inquiry.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt0928&quot;/&gt;

Public attention to the pepper-sprayings resulted in a spike of news media coverage, a pattern that was to be repeated in the coming weeks following confrontations with police.&lt;ref name=&quot;five38&quot;/&gt; [[Clyde Haberman]], writing in ''The New York Times'', said that &quot;If the Occupy Wall Street protesters ever choose to recognize a person who gave their cause its biggest boost, they may want to pay tribute to Anthony Bologna,&quot; calling the event &quot;vital&quot; for the still nascent movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt1010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt1012&quot;/&gt; &quot;After Ron Kuby, an attorney for one of the protesters, demanded Mr. Bologna’s arrest, [Bologna] was instead docked 10 vacation days and given a [...] reassignment to Staten Island, where he lives,&quot; according to an account by blogger Daniel Edward Rosen.&lt;ref&gt;Rosen, Daniel Edward, [http://www.observer.com/2011/11/is-ray-kellys-nypd-spinning-out-of-control/?show=all &quot;Is Ray Kelly’s NYPD Spinning Out of Control?&quot;], ''The [New York] Observer'', 11/01/2011 6:39pm. 2011-11-03.&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 1, 2011, protesters set out to march across the [[Brooklyn Bridge]]. ''The New York Times'' reported that more than 700 arrests were made.&lt;ref name=&quot;Police Arrest More Than 700 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge&quot;/&gt; The police used ten buses to carry protesters off the bridge. Some said the police had tricked protesters, allowing them onto the bridge, and even escorting them partway across.  Jesse A. Myerson, a media coordinator for Occupy Wall Street said, “The cops watched and did nothing, indeed, seemed to guide us onto the roadway.”&lt;ref name=&quot;Police Arrest More Than 400 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge&quot;/&gt;  However, some statements by protesters supported descriptions of the event given by police: for example, one protester Tweeted that &quot;The police didn't lead us on to the bridge. They were backing the [expletive] up.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/oct/02/occupy-wall-street-nypd-tactics|title=Occupy Wall Street protest: NYPD accused of heavy-handed tactics|last=Pilkington|first=Ed|publisher=Guardian.co.uk|year=2011|date=Oct. 2|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; A spokesman for the [[New York Police Department]], Paul Browne, said that protesters were given multiple warnings to stay on the sidewalk and not block the street, and were arrested when they refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;700arrest&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=700 Arrested After Wall Street Protest on N.Y.'s Brooklyn Bridge|url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2011/10/01/500-arrested-after-wall-street-protest-on-nys-brooklyn-bridge/?test=latestnews|accessdate=October 1, 2011|date=October 1, 2011|publisher=Fox News Channel}}&lt;/ref&gt; By October 2, all but 20 of the arrestees had been released with citations for disorderly conduct and a criminal court summons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hundreds freed after New York Wall Street protest&quot;/&gt;  On October 4, a group of protesters who were arrested on the bridge filed a lawsuit against the city, alleging that officers had violated their constitutional rights by luring them into a trap and then arresting them; Mayor Bloomberg, commenting previously on the incident, had said that &quot;[t]he police did exactly what they were supposed to do.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT Bridge Lawsuit&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Citing Police Trap, Protesters File Suit |author=ELIZABETH A. HARRIS |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/05/nyregion/citing-police-trap-protesters-file-suit.html?_r=1 |newspaper=The New York Times |date=October 5, 2011 |page=A25 |accessdate=October 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 5, thousands of union workers joined protesters marching through the Financial District. The march was mostly peaceful until after nightfall, when scuffles erupted. About 200 protesters tried to storm barricades blocking them from Wall Street and the Stock Exchange. Police responded with pepper spray and penned the protesters in with orange netting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street protests: Police make arrests, use pepper spray as some activists storm barricade&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian13&quot;/&gt;

=== Weeks 5–8 (October 15 – November 11) ===
{{See also|&quot;Occupy&quot; protests}}
[[File:Occupy Bay Street.JPG|thumb|Right|[[Occupy Toronto]] was inspired by Occupy Wall Street.]]

On October 15, tens of thousands of demonstrators staged rallies in 900 cities around the world, including Auckland, Sydney, Hong Kong, Taipei, Tokyo, São Paulo, Paris, Madrid, Berlin, Hamburg, Leipzig, and many other cities.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wall Street protests go global; riots in Rome&quot;/&gt;  In Frankfurt, 5,000 people protested at the European Central Bank and in Zurich, Switzerland's financial hub, protesters carried banners reading &quot;We won't bail you out yet again&quot; and &quot;We are the 99 percent.&quot; Protests were largely peaceful, however a protest in Rome that drew thousands turned violent when &quot;a few thousand thugs from all over Italy, and possibly from all over Europe&quot; caused extensive damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/15/501364/main20120893.shtml |title=&quot;Occupy&quot; protests go global, turn violent |publisher=CBS News |date=October 15, 2011 |accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Thousands of Occupy Wall Street protesters gathered in [[Times Square]] in New York City and rallied for several hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;ChicagoSun-Times-WallStreet&quot;&gt;Hawley, Chris (October 16, 2011.) [http://www.suntimes.com/news/nation/8245614-418/thousands-of-occupy-protesters-fill-new-york-times-square.html &quot;Thousands of ‘Occupy‘ protesters fill New York Times Square.&quot;] [http://www.suntimes.com ''Chicago Sun-Times]. Accessed October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;(October 16, 2011.) [http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/16/national/main20121154.shtml &quot;Occupy Wall Street has raised $300,000.&quot;] [http://www.cbsnews.com CBS News]. Accessed October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Several hundred protesters were arrested across the U.S., mostly for refusing to obey police orders to leave public areas.  In Chicago there were 175 arrests, about 100 arrests in Arizona (53 in Tucson, 46 in Phoenix), and more than 70 in New York City, including at least 40 in Times Square.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Associated Press October 16, 2011, 11:02&amp;nbsp;pm |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/nationworld/nation/la-na-occupy-wall-street-20111017,0,7374570.story |title=Hundreds arrested in 'Occupy' protests |work=Los Angeles Times  |date=July 13, 2011 |accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Multiple arrests were reported in Chicago, and about 150 people camped out by city hall in Minneapolis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/10/17/politics/occupy-wall-street/index.html?hpt=hp_t2 |title=Occupy Wall Street: How long can it last? |publisher=CNN |accessdate=October 19, 2011 |date=October 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early morning hours of October 25, police cleared and closed an Occupy Oakland encampment in Frank Ogawa Park in Oakland, California.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bulwa|first=Demian|title=Police clear Occupy Oakland camps, arrest dozens|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/10/25/BAUB1LLTC9.DTL|accessdate=25 October 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=JESSE |first=McKINLEY |title=Some Cities Begin Cracking Down on ‘Occupy’ Protests. |url= http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/27/us/oakland-and-other-cities-crack-down-on-occupy-protests.html?pagewanted=2 |accessdate=27 October 2011 |date=27 October 2011 |work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The raid on the encampment was described as &quot;violent and chaotic at times,&quot; and resulted in over 102 arrests and several injuries to protesters. The city of Oakland contracted the use of over 12 other regional police departments to aid in the clearing of the encampment. An Iraqi war veteran, Scott Olson, was allegedly hit in the head with a teargas canister and suffered a skull fracture. His condition was later upgraded from critical to fair.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Romney|first=Lee|title=Occupy Oakland regroups; injured Iraq war veteran recovering|url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/lanow/2011/10/occupy-oakland-regroups-injured-iraq-war-veteran-.html|accessdate=11/15/11|newspaper=LA Times|date=10/28/11}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next night, approximately 1,000 protesters reconvened in the plaza and held marches late into the night.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kurpnick|first=Nick|title=Occupy Oakland: Officials shift into damage control|url=http://www.insidebayarea.com/news/ci_19205555|accessdate=10/27/11|newspaper=Oakland Tribune|date=10/27/11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 2, protesters in [[Oakland, California|Oakland]], California shut down the [[Port of Oakland]], the fifth busiest port in the nation.  Police estimated that about 3,000 demonstrators were gathered at the port and 4,500 had marched across the city; a spokesman for the protest movement, who gave only his first name, told the BBC that he had heard people say that there were as many as 20,000 or 30,000 demonstrators, but added, &quot;It's impossible to tell.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15568057 |title=BBC News - US Occupy protesters clash with police at Oakland port |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-10-27 |accessdate=2011-11-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Weeks 9 &amp; 10 (November 12 - November 26) ===
{{see also|Chronology of Occupy movement raids}}

After midnight on November 15, police delivered notices that protesters had to temporarily vacate the park to allow cleaning/sanitation crews access.&lt;ref name=cleaning&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57324763/nyc-police-clear-occupy-wall-st-camp/ Occupy Wall Street Protests] CBS News. 15 Nov 2011. Last accessed 16 Nov 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  According to the police notice, protesters would have been allowed back in after the cleaning, but without tents, tarps, or sleeping bags. Police moved in around 1:00 AM on November 15 and arrested about 200 people, some of whom attempted to stop the entry of cleaning crews. Among those arrested were journalists representing the [[Agence France-Presse]],&lt;ref name='Estes 2011-11-16'&gt;{{cite news | first = Adam Clark | last = Estes | title = Press Is Not Forgetting the Journalists Arrested at Zuccotti Park | date = 2011-11-16 | url = http://www.theatlanticwire.com/national/2011/11/press-not-foregetting-journalists-arrested-zuccotti-park/45047/ | work = The Atlantic | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HneHjTy|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Associated Press]],&lt;ref name='McCarthy 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | first = Megan | last = McCarthy | title = Bloomberg Spokesperson Admits Arresting Credentialed Reporters, Reading The Awl | date = 2011-11-17 | url = http://www.observer.com/2011/11/bloomberg-spokesperson-admits-arresting-credentialed-reporters-reading-the-awl/ | work = The New York Observer | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Hngyiiv|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daily News (New York)|Daily News]],&lt;ref name='CBS 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | title = Several Journalists Among Those Arrested During Zuccotti Park Raid | date = 2011-11-15 | publisher = CBS News | url = http://newyork.cbslocal.com/2011/11/15/officials-journalists-among-those-arrested-during-zuccotti-park-raid/ | work = CBSNewsYork/AP | accessdate = 2011-11-16|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63FSXRa1j|archivedate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; DNAInfo,&lt;ref name='Ventura 2011-11-16'&gt;{{cite news | first = Michael | last = Ventura | title = DNAinfo.com Journalists Arrested While Covering OWS Police Raids | date = 2011-11-16 | url = http://gamma.dnainfo.com/20111115/downtown/dnainfo-journalists-arrested-while-covering-ows-police-raids | work = DNAinfo | accessdate = 2011-11-18 | quote = |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HnkhWBB|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[NPR]],&lt;ref name='Memmott 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Mark | last = Memmott | title = New York Police Clear Occupy Wall Street Protesters From Park | date = 2011-11-15 | url = http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2011/11/15/142336656/new-york-police-clear-occupy-wall-street-protesters-from-park | work = NPR | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Hno1k7M|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Television New Zealand]],&lt;ref name='AP WSJ'&gt;{{cite news | title = Journalists detained at NYC Occupy protests | date = 2011-11-15 | publisher = The Wall Street Journal | url = http://online.wsj.com/article/AP7788a68e595d4722950196f35c6d4e5b.html | agency = Associated Press | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HnqegCw|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''The New York Times'',&lt;ref name='Malsin 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Jared | last = Malsin | title = Reporter for The Local Is Arrested During Occupy Wall Street Clearing | date = 2011-11-15 | publisher = The New York Times | url = http://eastvillage.thelocal.nytimes.com/2011/11/15/video-reporter-for-the-local-is-arrested-during-occupy-wall-street-clearing/ | work = NYU Arthur L. Carter Journalism Institute | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Hnti54Z|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Vanity Fair (magazine)|Vanity Fair]],&lt;ref name='Weiner 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Juli | last = Weiner | title = Journalists, Among Those a Vanity Fair Correspondent, Arrested While Covering Occupy Wall Street | date = 2011-11-15 | url = http://www.vanityfair.com/online/daily/2011/11/Journalists-Among-Those-a-emVanity-Fair-Correspondentem-Arrested-While-Covering-Occupy-Wall-Street | work = Vanity Fair | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HnxWeXm|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as [[New York City Council]] member [[Ydanis Rodríguez]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/AP074a245fd66f46d492c3a34fbbde728e.html NYC councilman arrested near Occupy camp released] [[The Wall Street Journal]]. 15 Nov 2011. Last accessed 16 Nov 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; An NBC reporter's press pass was also confiscated.&lt;ref name='Johnston 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Garth | last = Johnston | title = Police Arrest OWS Reporter As He Pleads &quot;I'm A Reporter!&quot; | date = 2011-11-15 | url = http://gothamist.com/2011/11/15/video_police_arrest_ows_reporter_sc.php | work = Gothamist | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HqESagQ|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

While the police cleared the park, credentialed members of the media were kept a block away, preventing them from documenting the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/11/occupy-wall-street-police-raid-eviction |title=Exclusive Video: Inside Police Lines at the Occupy Wall Street Eviction |publisher=Mother Jones |date= |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=David Badash |url=http://thenewcivilrightsmovement.com/defiant-nyc-mayor-bloomberg-to-occupy-protestors-no-right-is-absolute/politics/2011/11/15/30224 |title=Defiant NYC Mayor Bloomberg To Occupy Protestors: ‘No Right Is Absolute’ |publisher=The New Civil Rights Movement |date= |accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police helicopters prevented NBC and CBS news helicopters from filming the clearing of the park.&lt;ref name='Stableford 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | first = Dylan | last = Stableford | title = Press clash with police during Occupy Wall Street raid; seven journalists arrested | date = 2011-11-17 | publisher = [[Yahoo News]] | url = http://news.yahoo.com/blogs/cutline/press-clash-police-during-occupy-wall-street-raid-232215675.html | work = The Cutline | accessdate = 2011-11-18 | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HLuZt3W | archivedate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many journalists complained of being treated roughly or violently by the police.&lt;ref name='Telegraph 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Amy | last = Willis | coauthors = Chris Irvine | title = Occupy Wall Street eviction: as it happened | date = 2011-11-15 | url = http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/8890772/Occupy-Wall-Street-eviction-as-it-happened.html | work = The Telegraph | accessdate = 2011-11-17 | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63FxCrrjf|archivedate=2011-11-17 | quote = CBS News NY News Desk tells me their helicopter was forced down by NYPD -- they had to go down for fuel but weren't allowed back up. #ows | location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='Gitlin 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite news | first = Sarah | last = Gitlin | coauthors = Janine Balekdjian | title = Reoccupy Wall Street | date = 2011-11-15 | url = http://www.columbiaspectator.com/2011/11/15/reoccupy-wall-street | work = The Columbia Daily Spectator | accessdate = 2011-11-17 | archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63FxWzwQd|archivedate=2011-11-17| quote = A CBS helicopter that tried to cover the eviction aerially was forced to leave the airspace over the park by the NYPD, depriving the world of a view of what, exactly, the police were doing. }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='CPJ'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.cpj.org/2011/11/journalists-obstructed-from-covering-ows-protests.php | title = Journalists obstructed from covering OWS protests | accessdate = 2011-11-18 | date = 2011-11-15 | publisher = [[Committee to Protect Journalists]] | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/63HpunRea | archivedate = 2011-11-15|quote=Lindsey Christ, a reporter for the TV channel NY1, told the Times she witnessed police officers put a New York Post reporter &quot;in a choke-hold.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Washington Post'', 2011 Nov. 15, &quot;Bloomberg’s Disgraceful Eviction of Occupy Wall Street,&quot;
http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-partisan/post/bloombergs-disgraceful-eviction-of-occupy-wall-street/2011/11/15/gIQASRiqON_blog.html&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Society of Professional Journalists]], the [[Committee to Protect Journalists]], [[Reporters Without Borders]] and the [[New York Civil Liberties Union]] expressed concerns and criticisms regarding the situation.&lt;ref name='Ventura 2011-11-16' /&gt;&lt;ref name='SPJ 2011-11-15'&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.spj.org/news.asp?REF=1091#1091 | title = SPJ condemns arrests of journalists at Occupy protests | accessdate = 2011-11-18 | date = 2011-11-15 | publisher = [[Society of Professional Journalists]] | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/63HdgVgJr | archivedate = 2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='HP AP 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | title = Human rights group concerned over journalists’ arrests at Occupy protests | date = 2011-11-17 | publisher = Huffington Post | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/human-rights-group-concerned-over-journalists-arrests-at-occupy-wall-street/2011/11/17/gIQAZ0kNVN_story.html | agency = Associated Press | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archivedate=2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HyxJz54}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='RSF 2011-11-16'&gt;{{cite news | title = Journalists arrested and obstructed again during Occupy Wall Street camp eviction | date = 2011-11-16 | url = http://en.rsf.org/united-states-absurd-charges-brought-against-09-11-2011,41370.html | work = Reporters Without Borders | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HdyEWIx|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[OAS Special Rapporteur for Freedom of Expression]] issued a statement saying that the &quot;disproportionate restrictions on access to the scene of the events, the arrests, and the criminal charges resulting from the performance of professional duties by reporters violate the right to freedom of expression.&quot;&lt;ref name='OAS 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite press release| url = http://cidh.org/relatoria/showarticle.asp?artID=875&amp;lID=1 | title = Office of the Special Rappoteur Expresses Concern over Arrests and Assaults on Journalists Covering Protests in the United States | accessdate = 2011-11-18 | date = 2011-11-17 | publisher = [[Organization of American States]] | archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/63Hc6A1i4 | archivedate = 2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 21, the [[New York Daily News]], the [[New York Post]], the [[Associated Press]], [[Dow Jones]], [[NBC Universal]] and [[WNBC-TV]] joined in a letter written by ''New York Times'' General Council George Freeman criticizing the New York Police Department's handling of the media during the raid.  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=11/21/11 |url=http://www.amny.com/urbanite-1.812039/media-upset-at-nypd-for-treatment-of-reporters-at-ows-1.3338559 |title=Media upset at NYPD for treatment of reporters at OWS - am New York |publisher=Amny.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Half an hour into the police removal, the Occupy Wall Street Media Team put out an official statement under the heading, &quot;You can't evict an idea whose time has come.&quot; It went on to say, &quot;Some politicians may physically remove us from public spaces — our spaces — and, physically, they may succeed. But we are engaged in a battle over ideas.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;evict-idea&quot;/&gt;

The tents and personal effects of the protesters, and the five thousand books of [[The People's Library]]&lt;ref&gt;Al Jazeera, 16 Nov. 2011, &quot;The People's Library and the Future of OWS: The Massive Library Carted Away by Authorities at Zuccotti Park is a Formidable Weapon in Occupy Wall Street's Arsenal,&quot; http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2011/11/2011111681642279467.html&lt;/ref&gt; were put in dump trucks by the police and removed.&lt;ref&gt;Democracy Now, 15 Nov. 2011, &quot;Inside Occupy Wall Street Raid: Eyewitnesses Describe Arrests, Beatings as Police Dismantle Camp,&quot; http://www.democracynow.org/2011/11/15/inside_occupy_wall_street_raid_eyewitnesses&lt;/ref&gt;  On the November 15 edition of [[The Rachel Maddow Show]], footage of the raid was shown with the following commentary:
:&quot;New York City police officers dressed in riot gear, handed out a written notice to the protesters telling them where their personal articles from the encampment could be retrieved, which sounds lovely until you saw what they were doing to the protesters` personal belongings. There were reports that police use knives to cut up the sturdy military-grade tents that were the best hope of surviving winter down there. You can see police here cutting down the protesters` tent poles with hand-held saws, with sawsalls.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://supermomwannabe.com/2011/11/16/occupy-is-here-to-stay/ |title=Occupy is here to stay |publisher=SuperMomWannabe.com |date=2011-11-16 |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/45322520/ns/msnbc_tv-rachel_maddow_show/#.Ts-wQBzN4pI |title=Tuesday, November 15 - msnbc tv - Rachel Maddow show - msnbc.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=2011-11-16 |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Computers retrieved after the raid were found to be smashed.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dailykos.com/story/2011/11/18/1037890/-Irony-of-What-Bloomberg’s-Done,-Threw-out-Fahrenheit-451&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Submit |url=http://www.motherboard.tv/2011/11/18/who-smashed-the-laptops-from-occupy-wall-street-inside-the-nypd-s-lost-and-found |title=Who Smashed the Laptops from Occupy Wall Street? Inside the NYPD's Lost and Found &amp;#124; Motherboard |publisher=Motherboard.tv |date= |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Jardin |first=Xeni |url=http://boingboing.net/2011/11/18/the-irony-of-what-bloomberg.html |title=One week after attending NY Public Library gala, Bloomberg destroys #OWS library containing honorees' books (and his own) |publisher=Boing Boing |date= |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Gabbatt |first=Adam |url=http://www.guardiannews.com/world/blog/2011/nov/16/occupy-wall-street-live-protesters-eviction |title=Occupy Wall Street: protesters regroup after eviction - Wednesday 16 November &amp;#124; World news &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk |publisher=Guardiannews.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Christopher Robbins |url=http://gothamist.com/2011/11/19/did_the_nypd_purposefully_destroy_o.php |title=Did The City Purposefully Destroy Occupy Wall Street's Property? |publisher=Gothamist |date=2011-11-19 |accessdate=2011-11-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the removal, New York City officials ordered police to keep the entire park closed and to prevent any protesters from returning, pending the outcome of a court hearing on whether and in what circumstances the protesters could return; a judge issued a temporary restraining order that protesters could return to the park with their tents, which ''Washington Post'' opinion writer James Downie accused Mayor Bloomberg of ignoring.&lt;ref&gt;''The Washington Post'', 2011 Nov. 15, &quot;Bloomberg’s Disgraceful Eviction of Occupy Wall Street,&quot; http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-partisan/post/bloombergs-disgraceful-eviction-of-occupy-wall-street/2011/11/15/gIQASRiqON_blog.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Newman |first=Andy |url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/15/updates-on-the-clearing-of-zuccotti-park/?src=twt&amp;twt=cityroom#judge-says-protesters-can-return-to-park-for-now |title=Updates on the Clearing of Zuccotti Park - NYTimes.com |location=New York City;Zuccotti Park (NYC) |publisher=Cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com |date= November 15, 2011|accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; A judge in the late afternoon ruled that the temporary order should not be extended, saying that the First Amendment did not give protesters the right to fill the park with &quot;tents, structures, generators, and other installations to the exclusion of the owner's reasonable rights and duties to maintain Zuccotti Park.&quot;&lt;ref name=RestrainingOrderVacated&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/15/us/new-york-occupy-eviction/index.html?hpt=hp_t1 |title=New York court upholds eviction of &quot;Occupy&quot; protesters |author=CNN Wire Staff |date=November 15, 2011 |publisher=www.cnn.com |accessdate=November 15, 2011 |quote= A New York Supreme Court has ruled not to extend a temporary restraining order that prevented the eviction of &quot;Occupy&quot; protesters who were encamped at Zuccotti Park, considered a home-base for demonstrators.
Police in riot gear cleared out the protesters early Tuesday morning, a move that attorneys for the loosely defined group say was unlawful.
But Justice Michael Stallman later ruled in favor of New York city officials and Brookfield properties, owners and developers of the privately-owned park in Lower Manhattan.
The order does not prevent protesters from gathering in the park, but says their First Amendment rights not do include remaining there, &quot;along with their tents, structures, generators, and other installations to the exclusion of the owner's reasonable rights and duties to maintain Zuccotti Park.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/16/nyregion/police-begin-clearing-zuccotti-park-of-protesters.html?pagewanted=3&amp;_r=1 Police Clear Zuccotti Park of Protesters] ''The New York Times''. 15 Nov 2011. Last accessed 16 Nov 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 17, journalists representing the Indypendent Reader, [[Independent Media Center|IMC]] and [[In These Times]] were arrested.&lt;ref name='Voorhees 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | first = Josh | last = Voorhees | coauthors = Abby Ohlheiser | title = Re-Energized OWS Protesters Stage Nationwide &quot;Day of Action&quot; | date = 2011-11-17 | url = http://slatest.slate.com/posts/2011/11/17/ows_day_of_action_protesters_head_to_the_new_york_stock_exchange.html | work = Slate | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Ho0vY6o|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name='Mirkinson 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | first = Jack | last = Mirkinson | title = Occupy Wall Street November 17: Journalists Arrested, Beaten By Police | date = 2011-11-17 | url = http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/17/occupy-wall-street-nov-17-journalists-arrested-beaten_n_1099661.html | work = The Huffington Post | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Ho2zdh5|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two reporters for the [[The Daily Caller|Daily Caller]] and a reporter for [[RT (TV network)|RT]] were reportedly struck with [[Baton (law enforcement)|police baton]]s.&lt;ref name='Mirkinson 2011-11-17' /&gt;&lt;ref name='Jilani 2011-11-17'&gt;{{cite news | first = Zaid | last = Jilani | title = Reporters For Right-Wing Publication Daily Caller Beaten By NYPD, Helped By Protesters | date = 2011-11-17 | url = http://thinkprogress.org/special/2011/11/17/371349/reporters-for-right-wing-publication-daily-caller-beaten-by-nypd-helped-by-protesters/ | work = ThinkProgress | accessdate = 2011-11-18|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63HpihHOr|archivedate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
&lt;!-- OCCUPY LINKS - PLEASE KEEP LIST ALPHABETIZED --&gt;
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
'''Occupy articles'''
* [[List of Occupy movement protest locations]]
* [[Occupy Marines]]
* [[The People's Library]]

'''Other U.S. protests'''
*[[Bonus army]] 1932
*[[Poor People's Campaign]] 1968
*[[1971 May Day Protests]]
*[[2011 United States public employee protests]]
*[[2011 Wisconsin protests]]

'''International'''
* [[Impact of the Arab Spring]]
* [[2010–2011 Greek protests]]
* [[15 October 2011 global protests]]
{{col-2}}
'''Related articles'''
&lt;!-- PLEASE KEEP THIS LIST ALPHABETIZED --&gt;

* [[Bank Transfer Day]]
* [[Corporatocracy]]
* [[Corruption Perceptions Index#Rankings|Corruption Perceptions Index]]
* [[Empowered democracy]]
* [[Grassroots|Grassroots movement]]
* [[List of countries by income equality]]
* [[List of countries by inequality-adjusted HDI]]
* [[Plutocracy]]
* [[Income tax in the United States#Historical income tax rates (1913–2010)|Selected Historical income tax rates in the U.S. (1913–2010)]]
* [[Social peer-to-peer processes]]
* ''[[The One Percent]]''{{ndash}}documentary about the growing wealth gap between America's wealthy elite compared to the overall citizenry
* [[Wealth inequality in the United States]]

{{col-end}}

{{space}}
{{Portal bar|Social movements|Politics|Business and economics|Society|New York City|New York|United States}}

==References==
{{reflist|30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=msnbc1&gt;
[http://upwithchrishayes.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2011/11/19/8896362-exclusive-lobbying-firms-memo-spells-out-plan-to-undermine-occupy-wall-street-video Exclusive: Lobbying Firm's Memo Spells Out Plan to Undermine Occupy Wall Street], Sat Nov 19, 2011, by Jonathan Larsen and Ken Olshansky, MSNBC, msn.com, retrieved 2011 11 20
&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;truth-out&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.truth-out.org/occupy-wall-street-movement-and-coming-demise-crony-capitalism/1318341474|title=&quot;The Occupy Wall Street Movement and the Coming Demise of Crony Capitalism,&quot; Truthout, October 11, 2011 |author=Ravi Batra|accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Batra advise to OWS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.opednews.com/articles/Economist-Ravi-Batra-Offer-by-Richard-Clark-111027-259.html|title=Economist Ravi Batra Offers Some Political-Economic Insights To The Occupywallstreeters|author=Kim Hill |publisher=OpEdNews|date=October 27, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cite web|url=http://www.c4chaos.com/2011/11/why-ravi-batra-is-my-kind-of-kick-ass-economist-for-the-99/ |title=Why Ravi Batra is My Kind of Kick-Ass Economist for the 99%!|publisher=C4CHAOS blog|date=November 14, 2011 |author= |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cite web|url=http://www.closingthegap.org.nz/site-map/research-material/ravi-batra-usa-prof-economics-on-economic-chaos-kim-hill-interview/ |title=Ravi Batra-USA Prof Economics on Economic Chaos|author= Kim Hill |publisher=Closing the gap|date=November 14, 2011 |accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cite web|url=http://archive.fwweekly.com/content.asp?article=7369 |title= Prophet of Boom (and Bust) Now will they listen to Ravi Batra? |newspaper=Fort Worth Weekly |author=Kendall Anderson|date=December 17, 2008 |accessdate=October 26, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cite web|url=http://www.fwweekly.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=5095:rising-up&amp;catid=30:cover-story&amp;Itemid=375|title=Uprising|date=October 19, 2011|newspaper=Ft. Worth Weekly|accessdate=October 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;DCCC1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dccc.org/pages/occupytwad/ |title=100,000 Strong Standing with Occupy Wall Street |publisher=DCCC |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;24ur&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://24ur.com/novice/svet/zakona-med-kapitalizmom-in-demokracijo-je-konec.html |title=Žižek: Protestniki nismo komunisti |publisher=24ur.com |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Walesa&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://online.wsj.com/article/APb6ba79d7a2c741ddb02b45462a3ad68e.html |title=AP Interview: Walesa backs Wall Street protesters |work=Wall Street Journal |date=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;AP-Hawley-10032011&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Anti-Wall Street protests spread nationwide|url=http://news.yahoo.com/anti-wall-street-protests-spread-nationwide-210839665.html|author=|Chris Hawley|publisher=Yahoo News|agency=Associated Press|date=October 3, 2011|accessdate=October 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Olbermann&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nationofchange.org/bernie-sanders-and-keith-olbermann-celebrate-wall-street-protests-1317392475 |title=Bernie Sanders and Keith Olbermann on Wall Street Protests |publisher=NationofChange |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Deprez&quot;&gt;[http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-10-10/wall-street-occupiers-need-kindness-of-strangers-to-stay-clean.html Wall Street Occupiers Rely on Free Showers], Esmé E. Deprez, Bloomberg News, October 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Goodman |first=Amy |authorlink=Amy Goodman |title=Civil Rights Pioneer, Olympic Medalist John Carlos &amp; Sportswriter Dave Zirin at Occupy Wall Street |publisher=Democracy Now! |date=October 11, 2011 |url=http://www.democracynow.org/2011/10/11/civil_rights_pioneer_olympic_medalist_john }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodman2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Cornel West on Occupy Wall Street: It's the Makings of a U.S. Autumn Responding to the Arab. Occupy Wall Street was hit by a major troll attack which caused to site to be member only. Spring |url= http://www.democracynow.org/blog/2011/9/29/cornel_west_on_occupy_wall_street_its_the_makings_of_a_us_autumn_responding_to_the_arab_spring |work=[[Democracy Now!]]|date=September 29, 2011|accessdate=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;The Christian Science Monitor&quot;/&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;Dems Co-Opt Occupy Wall St.&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=om een reactie te plaatsen! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jn6Np_5S7vM |title=Dems Co-Opt Occupy Wall St. |publisher=YouTube |date=October 3, 2011 |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;From Tahrir Square to...Wall Street?&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Rapoza|first=Kenneth|title=From Tahrir Square to...Wall Street?|url=http://www.forbes.com/sites/kenrapoza/2011/07/15/from-tahrir-square-to-wall-street/|newspaper=Forbes|date=July 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=froomkin2011&gt;Froomkin, D. (October 5, 2011) [http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/05/lessig-new-book_n_996519.html &quot;Lawrence Lessig's New Book On Political Corruption Offers Protesters A Possible Manifesto&quot;] ''Huffington Post''&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;[http://www.salon.com/news/opinion/glenn_greenwald/2011/09/28/protests/index.html What's behind the scorn for the Wall Street protests?], Glenn Greenwald, ''[[Salon.com|Salon]]'', September 29, 2011; accessed September 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Grossman&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204831304576593371443552888.html|title=Protest Has Unlikely Host|last=Grossman|first=Andrew|date=September 26, 2011|work=The Wall Street Journal|accessdate=October 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Gunning For Wall Street, With Faulty Aim&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Bellafante |first=Ginia |date=September 23, 2011 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/25/nyregion/protesters-are-gunning-for-wall-street-with-faulty-aim.html |title=Gunning For Wall Street, With Faulty Aim |work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Herman Cain: I'm More Than the 'Anti-Romney'&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2011/10/05/herman-cain-im-more-than-the-anti-romney/ |title=Herman Cain: I'm More Than the 'Anti-Romney' |work=Wall Street Journal |date=October 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=hill2011&gt;Hill, A. (October 4, 2011) [http://marketplace.publicradio.org/display/web/2011/10/04/am-campaign-finance-lobbying-major-roadblocks-to-effective-government/ &quot;Campaign finance, lobbying major roadblocks to effective government&quot;] ''Marketplace Morning Report'' (American Public Media)&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hugo Chavez condemns 'horrible repression' of Wall Street protests&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/hugo-chavez-condemns-horrible-repression-of-wall-street-protests/article2195735/|publisher=Reuters|title=Hugo Chavez condemns 'horrible repression' of Wall Street protests |first=Enrique Andres|last=Pretel|date=October 8, 2011|accessdate=October 10, 2011|location=Toronto}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hundreds freed after New York Wall Street protest&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15143509|title=Hundreds freed after New York Wall Street protest|date=October 2, 2011|work=BBC News  |publisher=BBC  |accessdate=October 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kanye West, Russell Simmons lend support to Occupy Wall Street protesters&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Croghan|first=Lore|title=Kanye West, Russell Simmons lend support to Occupy Wall Street protesters |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/ny_local/2011/10/10/2011-10-10_kanye_west_russell_simmons_lend_support_to_occupy_wall_street_protesters.html|accessdate=October 15, 2011|newspaper=[[Daily News (New York){{!}}Daily News]]|date=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kilkenny&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Allison Kilkenny on October 14, 2011&amp;nbsp;– 8:46&amp;nbsp;am ET |url=http://www.thenation.com/blog/163981/occupy-wall-street-protesters-win-showdown-bloomberg |title=Occupy Wall Street Protesters Win Showdown With Bloomberg |publisher=The Nation |accessdate=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kleinfield&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Kleinfield|first=N.R.|last2=Buckley|first2=Cara|title=Wall Street Occupiers, Protesting Till Whenever|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/01/nyregion/wall-street-occupiers-protesting-till-whenever.html?_r=1&amp;ref=occupywallstreet|work=New York Times|date=September 30, 2011|accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=lessigbook&gt;Lessig, L. (2011) [http://www.twelvebooks.com/books/republic_lost.asp ''Republic, Lost: How Money Corrupts Congress&amp;nbsp;– and a Plan to Stop It''] (New York City: Hachette/Twelve) [http://www.rollingstone.com/politics/blogs/national-affairs/lawrence-lessig-on-how-we-lost-our-democracy-20111005 excerpt]&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;LIP&quot;&gt;[http://www.longislandpress.com/2011/10/10/protesters-want-world-to-know-theyre-just-like-us-2/ Protesters Want World to Know They’re Just Like Us], Jocelyn Noveck, Associated Press via the ''Long Island Press'', October 10, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Michael Moore gives speech at Liberty Plaza for 'Occupy Wall Street'&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Strachan|first=Jessica|title=Michael Moore gives speech at Liberty Plaza for 'Occupy Wall Street'|url=http://www.mlive.com/entertainment/flint/index.ssf/2011/09/michael_moore_gives_speech_at.html|work=The Flint Journal|accessdate=September 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NY Post Bloomberg article&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nypost.com/p/news/local/manhattan/driving_mike_up_the_wall_IHDGV6o4aelsoDQX2iuZTM|title=Bloomberg blasts Wall Street protests as bad for the city|work=NY Post |location=New York |accessdate=October 10, 2011|first1=David|last1=Seifman|first2=Maura|last2=O'Connor|first3=Dan|last3=Mangan|date=October 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NYPD Arrest Seven Wall Street Protesters&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Marcinek|first=Laura|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-09-19/new-york-city-police-arrest-seven-wall-street-protesters.html|title=NYPD Arrest Seven Wall Street Protesters|publisher=Bloomberg |date=September 19, 2011|accessdate=September 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;New York Times&quot;&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/09/opinion/sunday/protesters-against-wall-street.html?_r=1&amp;partner=rss&amp;emc=rss], NewYorkTimes.com, Oct. 8, 2011; accessed September 29, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;News From Korean Central News Agency Of Dprk&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kcna.co.jp/index-e.htm |title=News From Korean Central News Agency Of Dprk |publisher=Kcna.co.jp |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;North Korean State Press Writes About Occupy Wall Street&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://globalspin.blogs.time.com/2011/10/11/north-korean-state-press-writes-about-occupy-wall-street/|work=The Times |location=UK|title=North Korean State Press Writes About Occupy Wall Street|first=ISHAAN |last=THAROORE|date=October 8, 2011|accessdate=October 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;OWSproposedDemands&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=anonymous |coauthors=Hart, Lloyd J. |title=Proposed List Of Demands For Occupy Wall St Movement! (User Submitted) |publisher=occupywallstreet.org |url=http://occupywallst.org/forum/proposed-list-of-demands-for-occupy-wall-st-moveme/ |accessdate=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama Speaks on Occupy Wall Street Oct 6&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oBWNH0Q1fLQ |title=Obama Speaks on Occupy Wall Street Oct 6th |publisher=YouTube |date=October 6, 2011|accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama acknowledges Wall Street protests as a sign&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Salazar |first=Cristian |url=http://www.businessweek.com/ap/financialnews/D9Q6U0O83.htm |agency=Associated Press |title=Obama acknowledges Wall Street protests as a sign |work=BusinessWeek   |date=October 6, 2011 |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama news conference: Obama: Occupy Wall Street protests show Americans' frustration&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Memoli |first=Michael A. |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/politics/la-pn-obama-occupy-wall-street-20111006,0,1992639.story |title=Obama news conference: Obama: Occupy Wall Street protests show Americans' frustration |work=Los Angeles Times |date=July 13, 2011 |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama, Cantor spar over Occupy Wall Street&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://money.cnn.com/2011/10/07/news/economy/occupy_wall_street/ |title=Obama, Cantor spar over Occupy Wall Street|first=Chris |last=Isidore |publisher=@CNNMoney |date=October 7, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obama: Not all pre-crisis financial ploys illegal&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Obama: Not all pre-crisis financial ploys illegal|date=October 6, 2011 |url= &lt;!--http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/n/a/2011/10/06/national/w085150D41.DTL#ixzz1a9DZWwh4{{dead link}}--&gt;https://www.mail.com/business/markets/744602-obama-pre-crisis-financial-ploys-illegal.html |archiveurl= http://www.webcitation.org/63IfSnEOI |archivedate=2011-11-18 |agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: A Fordham University Professor Analyzes the Movement&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Maggie |last=Astor |url=http://www.ibtimes.com/articles/224719/20111004/occupy-wall-street-protest-demands-zuccotti-heather-gautney-fordham.htm |title=Occupy Wall Street Protests: A Fordham University Professor Analyzes the Movement |work=[[International Business Times]] |date=October 4, 2011 |accessdate=October 7, 2011 |quote=Fordham University Sociologist Heather Gautney in an interview with the [[International Business Times]] 'the movement doesn't have leaders, but it certainly has organizers, and there are certainly people providing a human structure to this thing. There might not be these kinds of public leaders, but there are people running it, and I think that's inevitable.'}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: Mark Ruffalo Adds to Star Power, Christian News&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://global.christianpost.com/news/occupy-wall-street-protests-mark-ruffalo-adds-to-star-power-57169/ |title=Occupy Wall Street Protests: Mark Ruffalo Adds to Star Power, Christian News |publisher=Global.christianpost.com |date=October 4, 2011 |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street Protests: Police Make Numerous Arrests&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://abcnews.go.com/US/labor-unions-join-occupy-wall-street-york-rally/story?id=14673346 |title=Occupy Wall Street Protests: Police Make Numerous Arrests |publisher=ABC News |accessdate=October 7, 2011 |date=October 5, 2011 |first=Gregory J. |last=Krieg}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Wolff |first=Richard |title=Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi |newspaper=The Guardian |location=London |date=October 4, 2011 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2011/oct/04/occupy-wall-street-new-york }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi19&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2011/oct/04/occupy-wall-street-new-york|title=Occupy Wall Street ends capitalism's alibi|first=Richard|last=Wolff|publisher=TheGuardian.co.uk|year=2011|date=Oct. 4|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street protesters running out of space&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Occupy Wall Street protesters running out of space |publisher=MSNBC |date=October 9, 2011|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/44834449 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street protests: Police make arrests, use pepper spray as some activists storm barricade&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/ny_local/2011/10/05/2011-10-05_occupy_wall_street_protests_unions_join_epic_march_in_downtown_manhattan.html |title=Occupy Wall Street protests: Police make arrests, use pepper spray as some activists storm barricade |work=Daily News |location=New York  |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street rediscovers the radical imagination&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Graeber |first=David |title=Occupy Wall Street rediscovers the radical imagination |newspaper=The Guardian |location=London |date=September 25, 2011 |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/cifamerica/2011/sep/25/occupy-wall-street-protest }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street's Media Problems&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.observer.com/2011/09/occupy-wall-streets-media-problems/|last=Stoeffel |first=Kat|title= Occupy Wall Street's Media Problems |publisher=[[The New York Observer]] |date=September 26, 2011 |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street, Powered by Big Labor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Occupy Wall Street, Powered by Big Labor |work=MotherJones.com |date=October 5, 2011 |first=Andy |last=Kroll |url=http://motherjones.com/politics/2011/10/occupy-wall-street-labor-unions?utm_source=twitterfeed }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street: A protest timeline&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Occupy Wall Street: A protest timeline |work=TIMELINE |publisher=[[The Week]] |date=October 7, 2011 |url=http://theweek.com/article/index/220100/occupy-wall-street-a-protest-timeline |accessdate=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Occupy Wall Street: Celebrities Show Support&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Occupy Wall Street: Celebrities Show Support |url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/10/02/occupy-wall-street-celebrities-_n_991066.html |accessdate=October 4, 2011 |newspaper=The Huffington Post |date=October 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;On way to Wall Street, confronting a protest&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Condon |first=Bernard |last2=Matthews |first2=Karen |title=On way to Wall Street, confronting a protest |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/03/ap/business/main20114915.shtml |accessdate=October 5, 2011 |publisher=CBS News |date=October 3, 2011 |agency=Associated Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Panic of the Plutocrats&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Krugman |first=Paul |title=Panic of the Plutocrats |newspaper=The New York Times |date=October 8, 2011 |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/10/opinion/panic-of-the-plutocrats.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pelosi Supports Occupy Wall Street Movement&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/pelosi-supports-occupy-wall-street-movement/story?id=14696893 |title=Pelosi Supports Occupy Wall Street Movement| publisher=ABC news |date=October 9, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Police Arrest More Than 400 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Baker|first=Al|title=Police Arrest More Than 400 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/01/police-arresting-protesters-on-brooklyn-bridge/|accessdate=October 1, 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=October 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Police Arrest More Than 700 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/01/police-arresting-protesters-on-brooklyn-bridge/ |title=Police Arrest More Than 700 Protesters on Brooklyn Bridge |author=Al Baker, Colin Moynihan and Sarah Maslin Nir |date=October 1, 2011 |newspaper=New York Times }}&lt;/ref&gt;



&lt;ref name=&quot;Protests reveal US 'messy house': China agency&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5goeWRCoxUSA0UdBOp7zDIFWhUYJw?docId=CNG.b398dca3be09b742ac9603ec4088bcb7.6d1|agency=AFP  |title=Protests reveal US 'messy house': China agency|date=October 10, 2011|accessdate=October 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;Read Demands of 'Occupy Wall Street' ... and Try Not to Laugh&amp;nbsp;– Occupy Wall Street&amp;nbsp;– Fox Nation&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nation.foxnews.com/occupy-wall-street/2011/10/04/read-demands-occupy-wall-street-and-try-not-laugh |title=Read Demands of 'Occupy Wall Street' ... and Try Not to Laugh&amp;nbsp;– Occupy Wall Street&amp;nbsp;– Fox Nation |publisher=nation.foxnews.com |date=October 3, 2011 |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Romney: Wall Street Protests 'Class Warfare'&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nationaljournal.com/2012-presidential-campaign/romney-wall-street-protests-class-warfare--20111004|title=Romney: Wall Street Protests 'Class Warfare'|date=October 5, 2011|last=Boxer|first=Sarah|work=[[National Journal]]|accessdate=October 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Russell Simmons visits 'Occupy Wall Street' protesters with bottles of water, words of encouragement&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/ny_local/2011/09/30/2011-09-30_russell_simmons_visits_occupy_wall_street_protesters_with_bottles_of_water_words.html|title=Russell Simmons visits 'Occupy Wall Street' protesters with bottles of water, words of encouragement|work=Daily News |location=New York |accessdate=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS PART1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=om een reactie te plaatsen! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eu9BWlcRwPQ&amp;feature=player_embedded |title=SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS (PART 1) |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS PART2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=om een reactie te plaatsen! |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;v=7UpmUly9It4 |title=SLAVOJ ZIZEK AT OWS (PART 2) |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Stéphane Hessel on Occupy Wall Street: Find the Time for Outrage When Your Values Are Not Respected&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Gonzalez |first=Juan |authorlink=Juan Gonzalez (journalist) |title=Stéphane Hessel on Occupy Wall Street: Find the Time for Outrage When Your Values Are Not Respected |publisher=Democracy Now! |date=October 10, 2011 |url=http://www.democracynow.org/blog/2011/10/10/stphane_hessel_on_occupy_wall_street_find_the_time_for_outrage_when_your_values_are_not_respected }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Susan Sarandon lends star power to Wall Street protests&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Cox|first=Jeff|title=Susan Sarandon lends star power to Wall Street protests|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/Business/Latest-News-Wires/2011/0928/Susan-Sarandon-lends-star-power-to-Wall-Street-protests|work=The Christian Science Monitor|date=September 28, 2011|accessdate=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Wall Street Protesters: What the Hell Do They Want?&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.observer.com/2011/09/the-wall-street-protesters-what-the-hell-do-they-want/ |title= The Wall Street Protesters: What the Hell Do They Want? |publisher=observer.com |date=September 21, 2011 |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warning Occupy Wall Street Has for President Obama&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Engelhardt |first=Tom |url=http://www.commondreams.org/view/2011/10/10-2 |title=The Warning Occupy Wall Street Has for President Obama |publisher=Common Dreams |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The right way to get heard&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Weiss|first=Joanna|title=The right way to get heard|url=http://articles.boston.com/2011-09-27/bostonglobe/30209075_1_tea-party-protest-female-protesters-liberal-rage/2|accessdate=October 6, 2011|newspaper=[[The Boston Globe]]|date=September 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;U.S. Day of Rage planned for Saturday&amp;nbsp;– an Arab Spring in America?&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|title=U.S. Day of Rage planned for Saturday&amp;nbsp;– an Arab Spring in America?|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/blogpost/post/us-day-of-rage-planned-for-saturday--an-arab-spring-in-america/2011/09/15/gIQAd6uKVK_blog.html|date=September 15, 2011|accessdate=September 17, 2011|work=The Washington Post}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wall Street Corruption, Solyndra, and Fast &amp; Furious: Today's Q's for O&quot;&gt;{{cite news |first=Jake |last=Tapper|date=October 6, 2011 |title=Wall Street Corruption, Solyndra, and Fast &amp; Furious: Today's Q's for O |publisher=abcnews.go.com |url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/politics/2011/10/wall-street-corruption-solyndra-and-fast-furious-todays-qs-for-o-1062011/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wall Street protests go global; riots in Rome&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/10/15/us-protests-idUSTRE79E0FC20111015|title=Wall Street protests go global; riots in Rome|first=Phillip|last=Pullella|date=October 15, 2011 |work=Reuters}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;We Are All Human Microphones Now&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=Richard Kim on October 3, 2011&amp;nbsp;– 7:19&amp;nbsp;pm ET |url=http://www.thenation.com/blog/163767/we-are-all-human-microphones-now |title=We Are All Human Microphones Now |publisher=The Nation |date=October 3, 2011 |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Will Bunch on mainstream media's failure to cover Occupy Wall Street protests&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://current.com/shows/countdown/videos/will-bunch-author-of-the-backlash-on-mainstream-medias-failure-to-cover-wall-street-protests |title=Will Bunch on mainstream media's failure to cover Occupy Wall Street protests |work=Countdown with Keith Olberann |publisher=current.com |date=September 21, 2011 |accessdate=September 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews&quot;&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/Politics/cain-tells-occupy-wall-street-protesters-blame/story?id=14674829 &quot;Herman Cain Tells Occupy Wall Street Protesters to 'Blame Yourself'&quot;]. ABC News. October 5, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;ref name=&quot;adbusters1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.adbusters.org/campaigns/occupywallstreet |title=Occupy Wall Street &amp;#124; September 17th |publisher=Adbusters.org |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;anti-flag&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anti-flag.com/?p=146|title=Let's Occupy Wall Street!|publisher=anti-flag.com|date=September 30, 2011|accessdate=October 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;arrests&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Smith|first=Candice|title=Occupy Wall Street Movement Reports 80 Arrested Today in Protests|url=http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/headlines/2011/09/occupy-wall-street-movement-reports-80-arrested-today-in-protests/|publisher=abc|accessdate=September 25, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;businessinsider&quot;&gt;[http://www.businessinsider.com/occupy-wall-street-amenities-2011-10#the-kitchen-also-has-a-grey-water-system-to-filter-out-dirty-dishwater-contaminants-11 Check Out All The Awesome Amenities at Occupy Wall Street's Camp], ''Business Insider'',October 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;businessweek1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|first=Laura|last=Marcinek|url=http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-09-19/wall-street-areas-blocked-as-police-arrest-seven-in-protest.html|title=Wall Street Areas Blocked as Police Arrest Seven in Protest|work=Businessweek  |date=September 19, 2011|accessdate=September 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;businside&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Lopez|first=Linette|title=Joseph Stiglitz Was At Occupy Wall Street Yesterday And He Looked Like He Was Having A Great Time|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/joseph-stiglitz-was-at-occupy-wall-street-yesterday-and-he-looked-like-he-was-having-a-great-time-2011-10|accessdate=October 6, 2011|newspaper=[[Business Insider]]|date=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cbslocal&quot;&gt;[http://newyork.cbslocal.com/2011/10/06/kelly-protesters-to-be-met-with-force-if-they-target-officers/ Kelly: Protesters To Be ‘Met With Force’ If They Target Officers], CBS News, October 6, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-20120052-503544.html |title=Occupy Wall Street: More popular than you think&amp;nbsp;– Political Hotsheet |publisher=CBS News |accessdate=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews15&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Michael Moore helps to &quot;Occupy Wall Street&quot;|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/09/27/national/main20112025.shtml|work=CBS News|accessdate=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cbsnews21&quot;&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/08/earlyshow/saturday/main20117634.shtml &quot;Occupy&quot; protesters garner increased support]. ''CBS News''. Accessed: October 9, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;christianpost&quot;&gt;[http://global.christianpost.com/news/protesters-occupy-wall-street-to-rally-against-corporate-america-55853/ Protesters 'Occupy Wall Street' to Rally Against Corporate America], Ray Downs, ''Christian Post'', September 18, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr&quot;&gt;[http://www.cjr.org/the_news_frontier/occupy_wall_streets_media_team.php &quot;Occupy Wall Street’s Media Team], Columbia Journalism Review's New Frontier Database, October 5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr6&quot;&gt;&quot;Behind the sign marked “info” sat computers, , generators, wireless routers, and lots of electrical cords. This is the media center, where the protesters group and distribute their messages. Those who count themselves among the media team for Occupy Wall Street are self appointed; the same goes with all teams within this community.&quot; &quot;&quot;I later learned that power comes from a gas-powered generator which runs, among other things, multiple 4G wireless Internet hotspots that provide Internet access to the scrappy collection of laptops.&quot; [http://www.cjr.org/the_news_frontier/occupy_wall_streets_media_team.php &quot;Occupy Wall Street’s Media Team], Columbia Journalism Review's New Frontier Database, October 5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cjr9&quot;&gt;&quot;as the protest has grown, the media team has been busy coordinating, notably through the “unofficial,” Occupytogether.org. It’s a hub for all Occupy-inspired happenings and updates, a key part of the internal communications network for the Occupy demonstrations. While sitting in the media tent I saw several Skype sessions with other demonstrators. At one point a bunch of people gathered around a computer shouting, “Hey Scotland!” Members of the media team also maintain a livestream, and keep a steady flow of updates on Twitter, Facebook, and Tumblr.&quot; [http://www.cjr.org/the_news_frontier/occupy_wall_streets_media_team.php &quot;Occupy Wall Street’s Media Team], Columbia Journalism Review's New Frontier Database, October 5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;coupmedia1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://coupmedia.org/the-sovereign-peoples-movement.html |title=The Sovereign People's Movement @ #Occupy Wall Street|work=Select Below and Vote to Include in the Official Demands for #Occupy Wall Street |publisher=Coup Media Group |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;crackdown&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Police Arrest 80 During 'Occupy Wall Street' Protest|url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2011/09/24/police-arrest-80-during-occupy-wall-street-protest/|publisher=Fox New.com|accessdate=September 25, 2011|date=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dailynews0929&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Christina Boyle and John Doyle|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/news/ny_crime/2011/09/29/2011-09-29_probe_nypd_bigs_nasty_peppering_of_protesters_spray_it_aint_so.html|title=Pepper-spray videos spark furor as NYPD launches probe of Wall Street protest incidents|work=[[The Daily News]]|accessdate=October 11, 2011|location=New York|deadurl=yes}} {{Dead link|date=November 2011|bot=RjwilmsiBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ellis&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://motherjones.com/mojo/2011/09/occupy-wall-street |title=Is #OccupyWallStreet Working? |publisher=Mother Jones |first=Lauren |last=Ellis |date=September 27, 2011 |accessdate=October 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;five38&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=[[Nate Silver]]|url=http://fivethirtyeight.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/07/police-clashes-spur-coverage-of-wall-street-protests/|title=Police Clashes Spur Coverage of Wall Street Protests|work=The New York Times|accessdate=October 11, 2011|date=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google&quot;&gt;&quot;A general assembly of anyone who wants to attend meets twice daily. Because it's hard to be heard above the din of lower Manhattan and because the city is not allowing bullhorns or microphones, the protesters have devised a system of [[Occupy hand signals|hand symbols]]. Fingers downward means you disagree. Arms crossed means you strongly disagree. Announcements are made via the &quot;people's mic... you say it and the people immediately around you repeat it and pass the word along. &quot;[http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5j1cCvOt8hya8vGX0L0BuZu6lxt_A?docId=0b872a8c42874850a511343166b0b871 Wall Street functions like a small city], ''Associated Press'', October 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google10&quot;&gt;&quot;There are no bathrooms in the park, so protesters go to nearby businesses like Burger King and McDonald's. 'Anywhere we can go that they won't throw us out,' Cristiano said.&quot; [http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5j1cCvOt8hya8vGX0L0BuZu6lxt_A?docId=0b872a8c42874850a511343166b0b871 Wall Street functions like a small city], ''Associated Press'', October 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google11&quot;&gt;&quot;Somewhere between 100 and 200 people sleep in Zuccotti Park....&quot; &quot;Many occupiers were still in their sleeping bags at 9 or 10&amp;nbsp;am&quot; [http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5j1cCvOt8hya8vGX0L0BuZu6lxt_A?docId=0b872a8c42874850a511343166b0b871 Wall Street functions like a small city], ''Associated Press'', October 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;


&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian0927&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Karen McVeigh|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/sep/27/occupy-wall-street-anthony-bologna?INTCMP=SRCH|title=Occupy Wall Street: 'Pepper-spray' officer named in Bush protest claim|work=The Guardian |location=UK|accessdate=October 11, 2011|date=September 27, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;guardian13&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Matt Wells and Karen McVeigh |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/oct/05/occupy-wall-street-new-york-march?newsfeed=true |title=Occupy Wall Street: thousands march in New York &amp;#124; World news &amp;#124; guardian.co.uk |work=The Guardian |location=UK |accessdate=October 7, 2011 |date=October 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;house&quot;&gt;[http://cpc.grijalva.house.gov/index.cfm?sectionid=61&amp;sectiontree=5,61&amp;itemid=429 &quot;CPC Co-Chairs Applaud Occupy Wall Street Movement&quot;]. Congressional Progressive Caucus. October 4, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;huffington post&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|work=The Huffington Post|last=Vitchers|first=Tracey|title=Occupying—Not Rioting—Wall Street|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tracey-e-vitchers/occupyingnot-riotingwall-_b_980003.html|date=September 26, 2011|accessdate=October 1, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ibtimes&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |work=IBTimes New York |title='Occupy Wall Street' to Turn Manhattan into 'Tahrir Square' |url= http://newyork.ibtimes.com/articles/215511/20110917/occupy-wall-street-new-york-saturday-protest.htm |date=September 17, 2011 |accessdate=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;kadet&quot;&gt;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970204002304576631084250433462.html The Occupy Economy], by Anne Kadet, Wall Street Journal, October 15, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cite web |last=Kane |first=Muriel |title=Chris Hedges: Occupy Wall Street is ‘where the hope of America lies’ |publisher=The Raw Story |date=September 25, 2011 |url=http://www.rawstory.com/rawreplay/2011/09/chris-hedges-occupy-wall-street-is-where-the-hope-of-america-lies/ |accessdate=October 12, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;lemonde&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lemonde.fr/ameriques/article/2011/10/03/le-milliardaire-soros-soutient-les-indignes-de-wall-street_1581740_3222.html |title=Le milliardaire Soros soutient les &quot;indignés&quot; de Wall Street |work=Le Monde |location=France |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;lupefiasco&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lupefiasco.com/news/ad146c-to-the-sep17-occupiers-moneyman/ |title=To The Sep17 Occupiers &quot;Moneyman&quot;&amp;nbsp;– Blog Detail |publisher=LupeFiasco.com |date=September 14, 2011 |accessdate=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;marcinek&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|publisher=Bloomberg |last=Marcinek|first=Laura|title=Protesters Converge on Lower Manhattan, Plan ‘Occupation’|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-09-16/wall-street-protesters-vow-to-occupy-lower-manhattan-for-months.html|date=September 17, 2011|accessdate=September 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;msn&quot;&gt;[http://news.ph.msn.com/business/article.aspx?cp-documentid=5395125 Greek PM supports US protests, urges pragmatism at home], Agence France-Presse via MSN.com, October 12, 2011; accessed October 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;msn20&quot;&gt;[http://today.msnbc.msn.com/id/44775365/ns/today-today_news/t/wall-street-rallies-could-be-lefts-tea-party/ Wall Street rallies could be left’s Tea Party] msnbc.com. Accessed: October 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.ny1.com/content/top_stories/148557/kelly--nypd-presence-at-wall-street-protests-costly/ &quot;Kelly: NYPD Presence At Wall Street Protests Costly&quot; ]. ''NY1.com''. October 7, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;nymag&quot;&gt;[http://nymag.com/news/intelligencer/topic/occupy-wall-street-2011-10/ Meet the Occupants], New York Magazine, October 2, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt0928&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Al Baker and Joseph Goldstein|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/28/police-department-to-examine-pepper-spray-incident/?scp=2&amp;sq=anthony%20bologna&amp;st=cse|title=Officer’s Pepper-Spraying of Protesters Is Under Investigation|work=The New York Times|accessdate=October 11, 2011|date=September 28, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt1010&quot;&gt;{{cite news|author=Clyde Haberman|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/10/a-new-generation-of-dissenters/|title=A New Generation of Dissenters|work=The New York Times|accessdate=October 11, 2011|date=October 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt1012&quot;&gt;[http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/13/overtime-solidarity-and-complaints-in-wall-st-protests// Overtime, Solidarity and Complaints in Wall St. Protests]. ''New York Times''. October 13, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;occupywallst1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=https://occupywallst.org/forum/proposed-list-of-demands-please-help-editadd-so-th/ |title=PROPOSED LIST OF DEMANDS |publisher=OccupyWallSt.org Forum |date=September 28, 2011 |accessdate=October 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;oliphant&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Oliphant |first=James |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-20116717-503544.html |title=Biden: The &quot;middle class has been screwed |publisher=cbsnews |date=October 6, 2011 |accessdate=October 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters&quot;&gt;Nichols, M. (October 7, 2011) [http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/10/07/us-wallstreet-protests-idUSTRE7945JB20111007 &quot;Protests spread to more than a dozen cities&quot;] ''Reuters''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;roemer&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1011/65378.html|title=Buddy Roemer: The Occupy Wall Street candidate? |publisher=Politico.com|work=Burns &amp; Haberman |first=Alexander|last=Burns | date=October 6, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;solomon&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Solomon|first=Linda|title=Michael Moore, Susan Sarandon, Margaret Atwood and Noam Chomsky throw weight behind #OccupyWallSt protest|url=http://www.vancouverobserver.com/politics/news/2011/09/30/michael-moore-susan-sarandon-margaret-atwood-and-noam-chomsky-throw-weight|accessdate=October 15, 2011|newspaper=[[The Vancouver Observer]]|date=September 30, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast&quot;&gt;&quot;As Occupy Wall Street explodes, the movement is being pegged as a left-wing Tea Party John Avlon on the key differences between the protests—and why they both miss the mark&quot; [http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2011/10/10/occupy-wall-street-this-is-not-the-left-wing-tea-party.html &quot;Tea Party for the Left?&quot;], The Daily Beast, posted October 10, 2011, accessed October 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thedailybeast7&quot;&gt;[http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2011/10/06/occupy-wall-street-protests-tech-gurus-televise-the-demonstrations.html The Technology Propelling #OccupyWallStreet] , [[the Daily Beast]] , October 6, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thehill&quot;&gt;[http://thehill.com/blogs/blog-briefing-room/news/185081-paul-offers-support-for-anti-fed-occupy-wall-street-protestors &quot;Paul supports anti-Wall Street protests&quot;]. TheHill.com. October 3, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;thenation&quot;&gt;[http://www.thenation.com/blog/163626/abysmal-occupy-wall-street-coverage-rubbernecking-new-york-times Correcting the Abysmal 'New York Times' Coverage of Occupy Wall Street], Allison Killkenny, ''The Nation'', September 26, 2011; accessed September 29, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;thinkprogress&quot;&gt;Garofalo, P. (October 5, 2011) [http://thinkprogress.org/economy/2011/10/05/336510/bernanke-occupy-wall-street/ &quot;Bernanke on Occupy Wall Street&quot;] ''ThinkProgress.org''&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;times&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Bellafante|first=Ginia|title=Gunning for Wall Street, With Faulty Aim|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/25/nyregion/protesters-are-gunning-for-wall-street-with-faulty-aim.html|accessdate=September 24, 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=September 23, 2011|agency=The New York Times Company|location=New York City}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;times2&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Moynihan|first=Colin|title=80 Arrested as Financial District Protest Moves North|url=http://cityroom.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/09/24/80-arrested-as-financial-district-protest-moves-north/?hp|work=The New York Times|accessdate=September 25, 2011|date=September 24, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;union support&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.upi.com/Top_News/US/2011/09/30/Occupy-Wall-Street-gets-union-support/UPI-89641317369600 |publisher=United Press International |date=September 30, 2011 |accessdate=October 2, 2011 |title=Occupy Wall Street gets union support}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;vancouverobserver&quot;&gt;[http://www.vancouverobserver.com/world/canada/2011/10/13/finance-minister-sympathizes-occupywallst-protesters &quot;Finance Minister sympathizes with #OccupyWallSt protesters &quot;], Zi-Ann Lum. Vancouver Observer. 13 october 2011. Accessed 13 october 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/plum-line/post/russ-feingold-endorses-occupy-wall-street-this-will-make-the-tea-party-look-like--a-tea-party/2011/03/03/gIQANucZNL_blog.html &quot;Russ Feingold endorses Occupy Wall Street: 'This will make the Tea Party look like...a tea party.'&quot;]. ''The Washington Post''. October 5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost1&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/blogpost/post/occupy-wall-street-an-interview-with-kalle-lasn-the-man-behind-it-all/2011/10/12/gIQAC81xfL_blog.html Occupy Wall Street: An interview with Kalle Lasn, the man behind it all]. By Elizabeth Flock. October 12, 2011. ''The Washington Post''.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!-- &lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost17&quot;&gt;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/business/anti-wall-street-protesters-march-past-millionaires-homes-in-new-york-tax-the-rich/2011/10/12/gIQAdccQeL_story.html Wall Street protests draw political remarks from Iran leader; more US actions planned], Associated Press via ''The Washington Post'', October 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;washingtonpost22&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/will-occupy-wall-streets-spark-reshape-our-politics/2011/10/10/gIQArPJjcL_story.html |title=Will Occupy Wall Street’s spark reshape our politics? |work=The Washington Post |date=February 24, 2011 |accessdate=October 13, 2011 |first=Emily |last=Matchar}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;winnipegfreepress&quot;&gt;[http://www.winnipegfreepress.com/canada/breakingnews/mikhail-gorbachev-compares-occupy-wall-street-protests-to-perestroika-131820373.html &quot;Gorbachev calls Wall Street protests just; Flaherty say they have a point&quot;], Colin Perkel. Winnipeg Free Press. 13 october 2011. Accessed 13 october 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wired&quot;&gt;[http://www.wired.com/rawfile/2011/10/political-hackathon/?pid=1214 Occupy Wall Street Ignites Political Hackathon], Keith Axline and Bryan Derballa, October 7, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

[http://www.wnyc.org/blogs/wnyc-news-blog/2011/oct/11/occupying-wall-street-and-trying-be-good-neighbor/ Occupying Wall Street and Trying to Be a Good Neighbor], Bob Hennelly, WNYC, October 11, 2011; accessed October 14, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;wordpress&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://peopleslibrary.wordpress.com/ |title=Occupy Wall Street Library &amp;#124; The People's Library at Liberty Plaza |publisher=Peopleslibrary.wordpress.com |date=October 12, 2011 |accessdate=October 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;==&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yahoo&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://news.yahoo.com/democrats-seek-own-occupy-wall-street-movement-222048239.html |title=Democrats Seek to Own 'Occupy Wall Street' Movement&amp;nbsp;– Yahoo! News |publisher=News.yahoo.com |accessdate=October 13, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!---&lt;ref name=&quot;youtube&quot;&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rWBlLvYCx3U&amp;feature=related &quot;Michael Moore Live • Occupy Wall Street Interview • MSNBC Lawrence O'Donnell&quot;] (video). YouTube. September 28, 2011. Retrieved October 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=&quot;Best Sellers From 1987's Book Crop&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1988/01/06/books/best-sellers-from-1987-s-book-crop.html?pagewanted=all&amp;src=pm|title=Best Sellers From 1987's Book Crop |accessdate=October 13, 2011|work=New York Times|first=Edwin|last=McDowell|date=January 6, 1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=callaconvention&gt;{{cite web|url=http://callaconvention.org |title=CallAConvention.org |publisher=CallAConvention.org |accessdate=October 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;

&lt;!--&lt;ref name=conconcon&gt;[http://conconcon.org Conference on the Constitutional Convention], Harvard University, September 24-5, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;--&gt;
}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
{{Wikinews}}
{{Wikiquote}}

;Occupy websites
* [http://nycga.cc/ NYC General Assembly]{{ndash}} The official website of the General Assembly at #OccupyWallStreet
* [http://occupywallst.org Unofficial website]{{ndash}} backed by ''Adbusters''
* [http://www.adbusters.org/campaigns/occupywallstreet ''Adbusters'' page]{{ndash}} A listing of websites and updates
* [http://occupytogether.org Occupy Together]{{ndash}} A hub for events occurring across the U.S.
** [http://www.meetup.com/occupytogether Occupy Together Meetups Everywhere]{{ndash}} ([[Meetup]])
* [http://www.youtube.com/occupytv OccupyTV's YouTube Channel]
* [http://www.occupythegame.com/occupy_the_game/ Occupy Wall Street: The Game]

;Related websites
* [http://www.occupywiki.info OccupyWiki.info]{{ndash}} Wiki on the [[Occupy movement]]
* [http://wiki.shop.tm/ wiki.shop.tm]{{ndash}} Wiki on the [[Occupy movement]]
* [http://occupywiki.org OccupyWiki.org]{{ndash}} Directory and information
* [https://docs.google.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AjnECehlgV69dHdzUUJVV19nYkM4NjFubHV3bjI1Snc&amp;hl=en_US#gid=0 Occupy Directory]{{ndash}} Google Documents spreadsheet
* [http://www.firstgameworld.com/occupywallstreet.php FirstGameWorld.com]{{ndash}} Media Network &quot;Occupy&quot; support site
*[http://american-rattlesnake.org/?s=Zuccotti+Park American Rattlesnake]{{ndash}} Archive Of Photo Essays Relating to Occupy Wall Street
*[http://www.businessinsider.com/what-wall-street-protesters-are-so-angry-about-2011-10?op=1 Charts: Here's What The Wall Street Protesters Are So Angry About...]{{ndash}} from [[Business Insider]]
* [http://www.gvu.tv Occupy Wall Street Videos]{{ndash}} The growing and expanding movement captured on video
* [http://photos.denverpost.com/mediacenter/2011/10/photos-wall-street-protests-around-the-nation/ &quot;Occupy&quot; photographs from around the nation]{{ndash}} from the ''Denver Post''
* [http://inequality.org/ Inequality.org]{{ndash}} from [http://inequality.org/program-inequality-common-good/ Program on Inequality and the Common Good], an [http://www.ips-dc.org/ Institute for Policy Studies] project
* [http://equalitytrust.org.uk/ The Equality Trust] (UK){{ndash}} An organization for reducing income inequality in the United Kingdom
* [http://nlgnyc.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/Order-re-Liberty-Park.pdf ''In Re Waller'' Order to Show Cause and Temporary Restraining Order of November 15, 2011] from the [[National Lawyer's Guild]] website
* [http://www.courts.state.ny.us/press/OWS111511.pdf Decision of November 15, 2011 overturning the TRO in ''Matter of Waller v City of New York''] from the [[New York State Unified Court System]] website

&lt;!--spacing--&gt;

{{Navboxes
|title=Articles and topics related to {{PAGENAME}}
|state=collapsed
|list1=&lt;/span&gt;
{{Occupy movement}}
{{2008 economic crisis}}
{{Arab Spring}}
{{Anti-government protests in the 21st century}}
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Occupy Wall Street}}
[[Category:Occupy Wall Street| ]]
[[Category:Occupy movement in the United States]]
[[Category:2011 in New York]]
[[Category:Culture jamming]]
[[Category:Nonviolent resistance movements]]
[[Category:Progressivism in the United States]]
[[Category:Wall Street]]

[[ar:احتلوا وول ستريت]]
[[be:Захапі Уол-стрыт]]
[[bg:Окупирай Уол Стрийт]]
[[bs:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[cs:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[cy:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[da:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[de:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[et:Okupeerige Wall Street]]
[[es:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[eo:Okupu Wall Street]]
[[eu:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[fa:جنبش اشغال وال استریت]]
[[fr:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[ko:월 가를 점거하라]]
[[hr:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[it:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[he:כיבוש וול סטריט]]
[[la:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[ml:വാൾ സ്ട്രീറ്റ് കയ്യടക്കൽ സമരം]]
[[ms:Protes Wall Street 2011]]
[[nl:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[ja:ウォール街を占拠せよ]]
[[no:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[pl:Okupuj Wall Street]]
[[pt:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[ru:Захвати Уолл-стрит]]
[[simple:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[sr:Окупирајте Волстрит]]
[[sh:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[fi:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[sv:Occupy Wall Street]]
[[ta:வோல் வீதி ஆக்கிரமிப்பு]]
[[th:ออคคิวพายวอลล์สตรีท]]
[[tr:Wall Street'i İşgal Et]]
[[uk:Захопи Уол-стріт]]
[[ur:قبضہ وال سٹریٹ]]
[[vi:Chiếm lấy Phố Wall]]
[[zh:佔領華爾街]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
