<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33153461" ns="0" title="New York City Fire Department Ladder Company 3"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox fire department
| name          = FDNY Ladder 3
| logo          = &lt;br&gt;[[Image:FDNY ladder 3.jpg|150px]]
| motto         
| nickname
| established   =Pre 1883 
| strength      = 25
| stations      = 108 E. 13th St, New York City, New York
| engines       = 1
| trucks        = 
| battalions    = 
| foam units    = 
| divisions     = 
| squads        = 
| rescues       = 
| fireboats     = 
| helicopters   = 
| EMSunits      =  
| MERV units    = 
| per shift     =  
| FirstResponderBLSorALS   = 
| chief         = Battalion 6
| commissioner  = Division 1 (Manhattan)
}}

'''FDNY Ladder Company 3''' is a unit in the [[New York City Fire Department]] that has fire stewardship over a several block area of [[Manhattan]]’s [[East Village, Manhattan|East Village]].  Ladder Company 3 received the most casualties of any fire department in the FDNY, losing half of its men in the [[September 11th attacks]].&lt;ref&gt;Amy Reiter, &quot;These are big strong guys. They ain't going down easy&quot; Salon, September 13, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;  The company reported to the north tower of the [[World Trade Center]], where Captain Paddy Brown and his men were last reported on the 40th floor of the tower.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Daly,You can feel the presence of loved ones lost on 9/11 and only hope that somehow they feel ours, too. [[The New York Daily News]], September 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;  The company reported to the WTC running “heavy” meaning that it had more men than would actually be on a shift (tour), as the attacks came during a shift change and both shifts ended up reporting to duty.

[[File:FDNY Ladder 3 Apparatus.jpg|thumb|left|300px|Sheathed in plastic and US and FDNY flags, workers prepare to lower Ladder 3's [[fire apparatus|apparatus]] into the [[National September 11 Memorial &amp; Museum]].]]Ladder Company 3 consists of at least 25 men.  It is organizationally with Division 1 (Manhattan), Battalion 6.  The company is located at 108 E. 13th St., and also serves as the [[Battalion]] Chief's headquarters.  The company was created prior to 1883 and is one of New York’s oldest ladder companies.&lt;ref&gt;New York Fire Department's website (Source date: September 20, 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;  

Ladder Company 3’s fire truck (apparatus) that responded to the World Trade Center spent ten years housed at Hangar 17 at [[John F. Kennedy International Airport]]. At the time of the collapse, the truck was parked on [[West Side Highway|West Street]] and damaged beyond repair by the collapse of the Twin Towers. In 2011, Firefighters stood alongside victims’ families and assorted bystanders and watched as the flag-covered, 60,000-pound fire truck was lowered by crane 70 feet below ground be part of  the [[National September 11 Memorial &amp; Museum]]. It will not only represent the  members it lost on September 11, which are Captain Patrick(Paddy) J. Brown,  Lt. Kevin W. Donnelly,  Michael Carroll,  James Raymond Coyle, Gerard Dewan,  Jeffrey John Giordano,  Joseph Maloney,  John Kevin McAvoy,  Timothy Patrick McSweeney,  Joseph J. Ogren,  Steven John Olson, but also all  FDNY casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Michael Daly,You can feel the presence of loved ones lost on 9/11 and only hope that somehow they feel ours, too. [[The New York Daily News]], September 12, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references /&gt;



[[Category:New York City Fire Department|Ladder Company 3]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
