<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33164615" ns="0" title="New York City Fire Department Squad Company 1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox fire department
| name          = FDNY Squad 1
| logo          = &lt;br&gt;[[Image:Squad 1.jpg|150px]]
| motto         
| nickname
| established   =1955 
| strength      = 25
| stations      = 788 Union St Brooklyn, NY 11215
| engines       = 1
| trucks        = 
| battalions    = 
| foam units    = 
| divisions     = 
| squads        = 
| rescues       = 
| fireboats     = 
| helicopters   = 
| EMSunits      =  
| MERV units    = 
| per shift     =  
| FirstResponderBLSorALS   = 
| chief         = 
| commissioner  = 
}} 
'''[[New York City Fire Department]] (FDNY) Squad Company 1''' is one of 7 Squads in the FDNY Special Operations Command (SOC). Other SOC units include Rescue, [[HazMat]] and Marine. Squad 1 responds to fires and other emergencies throughout New York City, operating primarily in [[Brooklyn]]. Squad 1 is located in the Park Slope section of Brooklyn. They are a single company which operates a [[Seagrave Fire Apparatus|Seagrave]] [[Pumper]], 1000 g.p.m. with a 500 gallon tank. There are currently four officers and twenty-five assigned to this company.&lt;ref&gt;Tony Tricarico, Tricks of the Trade: The Rescue/Pumper and the FDNY Squad Concept. Firehouse.Com , September 22, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
==History==
Squad 1 was organized in [[Harlem]] at Engine 59 in 1955, moved to the [[Bronx]] at Ladder 58 in 1972, then to Engine 45 in 1975 and then disbanded in 1976. Squad 1 was re-established in 1977 in Brooklyn at 786 Union Street, the former quarters of Engine 269; which had been closed during the budget crisis. The local community had placed great pressure on the city to reopen the former house of Engine 269 and the city responded by reopening it and making it the new quarters for Squad 1.&lt;ref&gt;New York Fire Department (Source Date: September 2011)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Squad 1 door.jpg|thumb|left|150px|The door of the Squad 1 fire truck, now on display at the [[Smithsonian]] [[National Museum of American History]].]]
The new Squad 1 was assigned a fully equipped pumper with ladder company hand and power tools. Squad 1’s responses included the former “first due” boxes of Engine 269 and working fires within a designated area. In 1998 New York City recognized the need to have more specialized units that could handle hazardous material incidents as well as increased readiness for incidents involving weapons of mass destruction. Six more engines were then designated as Squad Companies. Engine Company 41 was already an enhanced engine company but was redesigned as a Squad Company.&lt;ref&gt;New York Fire Department (Source Date: September 2011)&lt;/ref&gt; 
Squad 1 responds as an engine in its first, second and third due assignments and as a Squad Company to working fires, high angle, collapse, confined space, subway emergencies and hazardous material emergencies in Brooklyn and throughout the city as needed. Squad 1 responds to approximately 1800 runs per year.&lt;ref&gt;Tony Tricarico, Tricks of the Trade: The Rescue/Pumper and the FDNY Squad Concept. Firehouse.Com , September 22, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;
==September 11th Attacks==
Squad 1 lost half of its squad at the [[World Trade Center]] in the [[September 11th attacks]].  The squad would be one of the most devastated FDNY units impacted by the collapse of the Twin Towers losing 11 members:  Captain James M. Amato,  Lt. Edward A. D'Atri,  Lt. Michael Esposito,  Lt. Michael N. Fodor,  Brian Bilcher, Thomas M. Butler,  Peter Carroll,  Robert Cordice,  David J. Fontana,  Matthew David Garvey, and Stephen Gerard Siller.  Squad 1 crossed [[Brooklyn Bridge]] to respond to the attacks and was last seen in the south tower.  The door of their pumper engine was recovered and is now on display at the [[Smithsonian]] [[National Museum of American History]].&lt;ref&gt;The 9/11 World Trade Center attacks, through the eyes of a former NYC fire official. New Jersey Star-Ledger. September 11, 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;
[[Category:New York City Fire Department|Squad 1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
