<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33184614" ns="0" title="Ahmad Nady"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name         = 
| image        = Ahmad Nady.jpg
| alt          = 
| caption      = A caricature drawing of Ahmad Nady by himself
| birth_date   = {{Birth date and age|1981|12|31}}
| birth_place  = [[Cairo]], Egypt
| nationality  = [[Egypt]]ian
| alma_mater   = [[Fine art|School of Fine Arts]], [[Helwan University]] 
| parents      = Mohammad Nady and Iman Ezzat
| children     = Hamza and Khadija
| employer     = Tarek Nour’s Advertising Agency
| occupation   = [[Cartoonist]], [[Comics artist]]
}}

'''Ahmad Mohammad Nady''' ({{lang-ar|أحمد محمد نادي}}) is an Egyptian [[political cartoon]]ist, comic artist and activist. Belonging to a family of artists, Nady began his career early on, steadily rising to become one of the best known comic artists in Egypt at a young age. He has drawn political cartoons since an early age, and since the [[Egyptian Revolution of 2011]], has become increasingly active in this area of work, garnering a significant reputation for the boldness of his work.

==Biography==
===Background===
Nady was born on December 31, 1981 into a family of artists. His father, Mohammad Nady, was a cartoonist and his mother, Iman Ezzat, is a sculptor and writer.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahram1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/News/18633.aspx |title=Ahmad Nady: A budding Egyptian cartoonist - Arts &amp; Culture - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date=2011-08-12 |accessdate=2011-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to his parents, Nady has cited his childhood and upbringing in the 10th of Ramadan City&lt;ref group=note&gt;The &quot;10th of Ramadan City&quot; is like the [[6th of October City]].&lt;/ref&gt; as an early influence in becoming an artist. As a child, he was an avid reader of comic books and magazines and he would occasionally create comics about his relatives, basing his characters on their features.

Over time, this became a hobby with his father acting as mentor. He drew caricatures of schoolmates and teachers. Among his first comic characters was the &quot;Amazing Mido&quot; ({{lang-ar|ميدو العجيب}} ''Mido al-'Ajeeb''), a young inventor who was subjected to radiation that allowed him to easily control and change his shape and form.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mawhopon.net/ver_ar/news.php?news_id=4832 |title=Ahmed Nady: One of the most famous comics artists in Egypt |publisher=Mawhopon.net |date=2010-10-31 |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;youm7&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youm7.com/News.asp?NewsID=172483 |title=Pharaohs were the first discovered the art of Comics |publisher=Youm7.com |date=2009-12-31 |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Nady, his first published cartoon was political. The cartoon was made during the [[Gulf War]], while Nady was in elementary school, and it portrayed [[Sindbad]] hitting [[Saddam Hussein]] on the head, saying, &quot;You've made the children of the world hate me now that they know I'm an Iraqi.&quot; In 1992, at barely 11 years of age, he won his first award in a workshop at the Mahmoud Mukhtar Museum. The following year, he was given the best caricature award by a caricature magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;youm7&quot;/&gt;

===Career===
Ahmad Nady began his professional career at the age of 14 when his father was suffering from fatigue and overwork. Nady asked him if he could draw for a Lebanese magazine and his father agreed and encouraged him. He started out at first as an assistant at a workshop producing Pharaonic sculptures, before working with a number of magazines, including Karma ({{lang-ar|كرمة}}) company, known for several of its comics: Simsim's World ({{lang-ar|عالم سمسم}} ''The Egyptian version of [[Sesame Street]]''), Sameer and Alaa el-Din ({{lang-ar|سمير علاء الدين}}) and the Young Arab ({{lang-ar|العربي الصغير}}), among others.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;/&gt;

During this time, Nady started mailing several comic magazine editors with samples of his work and his ideas, all of which were rejected in Egypt. One of these, among his very first professional work, was a series of adventures called Fayek w Rayek ({{lang-ar|فايق ورايق}}) after its two main characters, a [[chimpanzee]] and a [[sloth]]. The series was published by the Saudi comic magazine ''Basme'' ({{lang-ar| باسم}}) and was popular among children.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;/&gt;

While steadily advancing as a comic artist, Nady began entering the realm of political cartoons. In 1996, he won third place in a [[UNESCO]] exhibition, &quot;''Where We Live''&quot;, and in 2004, participated in an art exhibition organized by the Artists' Syndicate in solidarity with Palestine. He promoted comics and cartoons by setting up numerous workshops across Egypt, including at least one in the [[Bibliotheca Alexandrina]]. He has also won three awards from [[deviantArt]], an online community of artists.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;/&gt;

==Activism==
Nady participated in the [[2008 Egyptian general strike]] and, for a time, in [[Mohamed ElBaradei]]'s presidential campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;jadaliyya&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jadaliyya.com/pages/index/2048/revolutionary-cartoons_an-interview-with-ahmad-nad|title=Revolutionary Cartoons: An Interview With Ahmad Nady |publisher=www.jadaliyya.com |date=2011-07-04 |accessdate=2011-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nady joined the [[2011 Egyptian revolution|2011 revolution]] from the very beginning, participating politically at [[Tahrir Square]] and drawing cartoons on the spot, inviting those around him to suggest ideas and captions.&lt;ref name=&quot;jadaliyya&quot;/&gt; He was one of the many people who camped out in Tahrir Square&lt;ref name=&quot;jadaliyya&quot;/&gt; and was hit by a rubber bullet on [[Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Mubarak's rule#28 January—Friday of Anger|January 28]] during the violent clashes with the police. He also was attacked by members of the &quot;Popular Committees&quot; due to the propaganda by [[ERTU|state owned media]],&lt;ref name=&quot;jadaliyya&quot;/&gt; which claimed that the protesters had a  &quot;foreign agenda&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2011-02-08-egypt-protests_N.htm |title=Regime won't halt, but rallies must, Egypt's VP says |publisher=Usatoday.Com |date=2011-02-08 |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

When asked about what should be done with [[National Democratic Party (Egypt)|National Democratic Party]] headquarters set on fire during the 2011 revolution, Nady praised the idea of turning the headquarters into a centre that holds cultural activities, saying, &quot;It should be a place for workshops of all artistic fields inviting all artists from all over Egypt&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ahram2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/~/NewsContent/5/35/19486/Arts--Culture/Stage--Street/NDP-headquarters-building-what-will-it-be.aspx |title=NDP headquarters building- what will it be? - Stage &amp; Street - Arts &amp; Culture - Ahram Online |publisher=English.ahram.org.eg |date=2011-08-23 |accessdate=2011-09-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Awards and honors==
;Local recognition
* Merit certificate of Mahmoud Mukhtar Museum Workshop, 1992.&lt;ref name=&quot;FineArtSectorBiographies&quot;&gt;[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:YSeuPIS_oWEJ:www.fineart.gov.eg/eng/cv/cv.asp%3FIDS%3D2146+http://www.fineart.gov.eg/Eng/CV/CV.asp%3FIDS%3D2146&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=ae FineArt Sector - Biographies - Ahmed Mohammed Nady]. 2011-09-05.Archived at webcite at http://www.webcitation.org/61TOArgrU&lt;/ref&gt;
* Prize for the best caricature in caricature magazine, 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;FineArtSectorBiographies&quot;/&gt;
* Honorable mention from the exhibition of &quot;''Egypt in my Heart''&quot;, by the Republican Youth and the [[Ministry of Culture (Egypt)|Ministry of Culture]], 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;FineArtSectorBiographies&quot;/&gt;
* Recognition Award from the Artists' Syndicate for his contribution to an art exhibition in solidarity with Palestine, 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;FineArtSectorBiographies&quot;/&gt;

;International recognition
* Third prize at UNESCO exhibition, &quot;Where We Live&quot;, 1996.&lt;ref name=&quot;mawhopon&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FineArtSectorBiographies&quot;/&gt;
* Three Daily Deviations awards from Deviant Art, 2005, 2006 and 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ahmad-nady.deviantart.com/gallery/32140719 |title=Daily Deviation on deviantART |publisher=www.deviantart.com |date=2011-09-19 |accessdate=2011-09-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Sebo3 althawra almasria.jpg|The [[Muslim Brotherhood]], The [[Coptic church]], Elites and the [[SCAF]] trying to control the [[2011 Egyptian revolution|Jan25 youth]]
File:No to Military Trials in Egypt.jpg|SCAF trailing peaceful protesters in [[Human rights in Egypt under the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces#Military_trials|Military courts]] while Mubarak faces a [[Hosni Mubarak#Trial|civilian court]]
File:SCAF and 6 April Youth Movement.jpg|Supreme Council of the Armed Forces accusing the [[April 6 Youth Movement|6 April Youth Movement]] of receiving American funds
File:SCAF oppose Right2Vote For EgyAbroad.jpg|SCAF opposing the [[right to vote]] for [[Egyptian diaspora|Egyptians living abroad]], claiming that Egyptians abroad are unpatriotic and have a secret agenda
File:Freedom under SCAF.jpg|Freedom under SCAF
File:Ali Jawad al-Sheikh by Ahmad Nady.jpg|[[Ali Jawad al-Sheikh]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==See also==
{{Portalbox|Egypt|Biography|Comics}}
* [[Carlos Latuff]]

==Further reading==
* [http://aawsat.com/details.asp?section=37&amp;article=638345&amp;feature=1&amp;issueno=11965 Carlos Latuff: Happy to be a friend of the Revolution of January 25]
* [http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2011/aug/22/carlos-latuff-cartoon-arab-spring Carlos Latuff: The voice of Tripoli – live from Rio]

== Footnotes ==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Ahmad Nady}}
* [http://ahmadnady.blogspot.com Ahmad Nady's blog]
* [http://www.behance.net/ahmad-nady Nady on Behance Network]
* [http://ahmad-nady.deviantart.com/ Nady on DeviantArt]
* [https://www.facebook.com/pages/ahmad-nady/21584000631?sk=info Fan page on Facebook]
* [http://www.flickr.com/photos/ahmad_nady/ Nady on Flickr]
* [http://twitter.com/#!/ahmad_nady Nady on Twitter]

{{Persondata
|NAME= Nady, Ahmad
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Political cartoonist
|DATE OF BIRTH= December 21, 1981
|PLACE OF BIRTH= [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]]
|DATE OF DEATH=
|PLACE OF DEATH=
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nady, Ahmad}}
[[Category:1981 births]]
[[Category:Egyptian artists]]
[[Category:Egyptian cartoonists]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:People from Cairo]]
[[Category:People of the 2011 Egyptian revolution]]
[[Category:Articles created via the Article Wizard]]

[[ar:أحمد نادي]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
