<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33230775" ns="0" title="New York City Fire Department Rescue Company 1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox fire department
| name          = FDNY Rescue 1
| logo          = &lt;br&gt;[[Image:Rescue 1 Patch.png|150px]]
| motto         =''Outstanding''
| nickname      =
| established   = March 8, 1915
| strength      = 25
| stations      = 530 West 43rd Street, New York City, NY 10036
| engines       = 
| trucks        = 
| battalions    = 
| foam units    = 
| divisions     = 
| squads        = 
| rescues       = 1
| fireboats     = 
| helicopters   = 
| EMSunits      =  
| MERV units    = 
| per shift     =  10 - 11
| FirstResponderBLSorALS   = 
| chief         = 
| commissioner  = Manhattan
}}
'''[[New York City Fire Department]] Rescue Company 1 (FDNY Rescue 1)''' is a specialized unit of the New York Fire Department that responds to fire situations where there are rescue operations (i.e. elevator shafts) that require specialized equipment and training. Rescue 1 is one of five rescue companies in FDNY, and services the [[Manhattan]] borough of New York City. It was organized March 8, 1915 and its firehouse is located on 530 West 43rd Street, New York City in the [[Hell's Kitchen, Manhattan|Hell’s Kitchen]] section of the borough.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Natale Schneiderman.  The Firefighting Buff's Guide to New York City: The Five Borough, Five Alarm Reference to the Second Homes of New York's Bravest. Publisher:  iUniverse, 2002 ISBN 0595246028&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Rescue 1 Rig 2002.png|thumb|left|200px|Rescue 1's apparatus in [[Times Square]]]]Rescue companies have an emphasis on equipping the company with tools that could be instrumental in performing rescues of civilians and firefighters at structural fires as well as operating at &quot;odd jobs&quot;. Early versions of Self Contained Breathing Apparatus SCBA were first assigned to the Rescue Companies. Heavy duty lifting equipment, torches, and saws were initially introduced to the Rescue Companies. Life lines and a line gun ([[Lyle gun]]) were among the initial equipment used by rescue companies, and as technology evolved, the Rescues were instrumental in pioneering the fire service application of Artificial Resuscitation techniques, SCBA, and firefighting foam.  Rescue 1 is staffed with one captain, one lieutenant, and typically 20 to 25 firefighters that are split into tours (shifts).&lt;ref&gt;Paul Hashagen.  Fire Department, City of New York. Editor: Janet Kimmerly; Publisher Turner Publishing Company, 2002 ISBN 1563118327&lt;/ref&gt;

Rescue 1’s firehouse was destroyed in 1985 by a fire in a neighboring warehouse.  Rescue 1 was already out on a call, when fire collapsed the warehouse onto their quarters.  The unit then temporary relocated until 1989 when their present firehouse was finished.  Their distinctive door was saved and relocated to the back of the building.  Their present rig is an Emergency One/Saulsbury Rescue Truck.  Its design came with recommendations from Rescue 1’s senior officer, Capt. Terry Hatton, who was killed during the September 11th attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Joseph Natale Schneiderman.  The Firefighting Buff's Guide to New York City: The Five Borough, Five Alarm Reference to the Second Homes of New York's Bravest. Publisher:  iUniverse, 2002 ISBN 0595246028&lt;/ref&gt;

==September 11th==
Rescue 1 was one of the most decimated units during the [[September 11th attacks]] at the [[World Trade Center]], losing nearly half of its company.  The company responded to the North Tower, and can be seen as one of the first units entering the stairwell in [[Jules and Gedeon Naudet]]’s documentary [[9/11 (film)|9/11]].  The company lost members Captain Terence S. Hatton, Lieutenant Dennis Mojica, Joseph Angelini  Sr.,  Gary Geidel,  William Henry,  Kenneth Joseph Marino,  Michael Montesi, Gerard Terence Nevins,  Patrick J. O'Keefe,  Brian Edward Sweeney,  and David M. Weiss.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Hashagen.  Fire Department, City of New York. Editor: Janet Kimmerly; Publisher Turner Publishing Company, 2002 ISBN 1563118327&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

[[Category:New York City Fire Department|Rescue 1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
