<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3326429" ns="0" title="WIPR-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=April 2008}}
{{Infobox broadcast
| call_letters             = WIPR-TV
| city                     =
| station_logo             = [[Image:wipr-prtv.jpeg|200px|WIPR - Puerto Rico TV]]
| station_slogan           =
| station_branding         = Puerto Rico TV
| analog                   =
| digital                  = 43 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| other_chs                = WIPM-TV 35 [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]]
| affiliations             =
| subchannels              = ''(see article)''
| network                  =
| founded                  =
| airdate                  = January 6, 1958
| location                 = [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]]
| callsign_meaning         = '''I'''nstrucción&lt;br&gt;'''P'''ública&lt;br&gt;'''R'''adio-Televisión
| former_callsigns         =
| former_channel_numbers   = 6 (1958–2009, analog)
| owner                    = Corporación de Puerto Rico para la Difusión Pública
| licensee                 = Puerto Rico Public Broadcasting Corporation
| sister_stations          =
| former_affiliations      = [[National Educational Television|NET]] (1958–1970)&lt;br&gt;[[Public Broadcasting Service]] (1970–2011)
| effective_radiated_power = 1000 [[kilowatt|kW]]
| HAAT                     = 776 m
| class                    = Full service
| facility_id              = 53859
| coordinates              = {{coord|18|6|35|N|66|3|4|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage                 = [http://www.prnet.pr/ Puerto Rico Network]
}}

'''WIPR-TV''' is an [[non-commercial educational]], full-power [[public television]] station located in San Juan, Puerto Rico transmitting over analog channel 6, digital 43. The station is owned and operated by Corporación de Puerto Rico para la Difusión Pública ''('''English:''' Puerto Rico Corporation for Public Broadcasting)''. Most of its [[television show|television shows]] on the main channel is [[local programming]].

Because of its audience, much of WIPR's programming is in Spanish, as with most Puerto Rico television stations. The station is branded as ''Puerto Rico TV''. Previously, the station was branded as ''Teve 6 / Teve 3'' and ''TUTV - Tu Universo Televisión''.

WIPR-TV operates a [[semi-satellite]] on the island west Coast, '''WIPM-TV''', channel 3 in [[Mayagüez, Puerto Rico|Mayagüez]]. WIPM-TV largely repeats WIPR, but does produce some local programming. WIPM-TV transmits its digital signal on channel 35, virtual 3.

==History==
WIPR-TV was created as a result of lobbying for public broadcasting in Puerto Rico, beginning in the 1950s. The station went on the air for the first time on [[Three Kings Day]] (January 6), 1958 becoming the first [[educational television]] station in Latin America.

It was also unique among other government-controlled broadcasters in the [[Caribbean]] as it did not show [[commercials]]. All other government-controlled broadcasters (with the exception of [[Cuba]] and the [[US Virgin Islands]]) showed [[advertising]].

The station was one of the few TV stations in Puerto Rico with English-language programming, via a membership with [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]] (and an affiliation with [[National Educational Television]] prior to PBS' founding in 1970); this ended on July 1, 2011 after WIPR and PBS failed to reach an agreement to renew the station's membership, with money previously allocated to PBS membership dues being invested in the station's extensive local programming.  PBS programming remains available on Puerto Rico via [[WMTJ]].&lt;ref name=c-wiprnopbs&gt;{{cite news|last=Sefton|first=Dru|title=Puerto Rican station drops PBS shows|url=http://www.current.org/ptv/ptv1115puertorico.html|accessdate=October 11, 2011|newspaper=[[Current (newspaper){{!}}Current]]|date=July 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[1996]], WIPR-TV was the first Puerto Rican television station that used [[streaming media]] to broadcast programming to the [[internet]].

===Administration===

'''General Administrators for Radio and Television Services under the Department of Education'''

* Rafael Delgado Márquez (1958–1961)
* Jack Delano (1961–1968)
* Leopoldo Santiago Lavandero (1969) (6 months)
* Elsie Calero (1970–1972)
* José Buitrago (Radio)
* José M. García (1973–1975)
* Alberto Cordero Albino (1975–1977)
* Manuel Collazo (1977) (acting)
* Elsie Calero (1977–1981)
* Héctor Suárez	(1981) (acting)
* Jorge Inserni	(1981–1983)
* Sigfredo Quiñones
* Agustín Mercado (1985–1988)

'''Executive Directors/Presidents (CPRDP)'''

* Carmen Junco (1988–1990)
* Dr. Pedro González Ramos (1990–1991)
* Eduardo Rivero Albino	(1991–1993)
* Jorge Inserni (1993–2001)
* Linda Hernández (2001–2004)
* Yolanda Zavala (2004–2005)
* Víctor J. Montilla (2005–2009)
* Ray Cruz (2009–Present)

==WIPR-TV 50th Anniversary==

The channel celebrated their 50th anniversary by producing a documentary focusing on their history.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculosasi/festejan_sus_50_anos_con_documental/203619| title=Festejan sus 50 años con documental| author=Mariela Fullana Acosta| publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-06-23| accessdate=2008-06-27}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; On July 1, 2008, TuTv renewed 150 contracts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/tutv_renovara_cerca_de__150_contratos/205834| title=TUTV renovará cerca de 150 contratos| author=Rosalina Marrero-Rodríguez| publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-07-01| accessdate=2008-07-01}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008, Puerto Rico’s Public Broadcasting Station, WIPR-TV, celebrated it’s 50 years of broadcasting with a documentary that relived some of the best and worst moments in its history.

The documentary &quot;50 Años WIPR-Televisión&quot;, (50 Years of WIPR Television) is about 70 minutes long and reviews some of the news, entertainment programming, music and sports events that the station has presented during half a century.

WIPR-TV, today better known as the Puerto Rico’s Public Broadcasting Corporation (CPRDP), or its branding, TUTV or Tu Universo Televisión, was inaugurated on January 6, 1958 under the administration of the then-current governor, [[Luis Muñoz Marín]].

The documentary was dedicated to the actor, director and historian Ángel Rivera Vázquez, who had worked in WIPR since its beginning.

Spearheaded by Investigator Flavia García, who had been working for the previous 9 years on an investigation of the history of television, headed the production of this special along with Luis Rosario Albert and [http://www.susannemarte.net84.net Susanne Marte].

The Corporation’s President, [[Víctor J. Montilla]], received a congratulatory resolution on behalf of the Puerto Rican Senate for the “good music, art and television” that have distinguished the channel for the past five decades.

Some of the historical moments aired include:

* The first airing on WIPR-TV, a music program with local performers
* The [[Casals Festival]], which first aired live from the [[University of Puerto Rico]]’s theater in 1961
* WIPR-TV was the first Puerto Rican station to air a live basketball game.
* The 1961 signing of a law by then-governor [[Roberto Sánchez Vilella]] that would declare WIPR-TV an official part of the [[Government of Puerto Rico]].
* President [[John F. Kennedy]]’s visit to the island.
* The pardon granted to the nationalist leader [[Pedro Albizu Campos]] in 1964
* The accomplishments of the former baseball player [[Roberto Clemente]] in the Major Leagues
* Puerto Rico’s first [[Miss Universe]]: [[Marisol Malaret]]
* The death of three &quot;independentista&quot; (seekers of independence for the island) young men that were killed during by police during the ambush in [[Cerro Maravilla]] in 1978
* The [[Dupont Plaza Hotel arson]] in 1986
* The termination of 314 employees at WIPR-TV in 1990.
* The broadcasting of the [[Central American and Caribbean Games]] in 1993
* [[Dayanara Torres]] being crowned Miss Universe
* The attack on the [[World Trade Center|Twin Towers]] in New York in 2001
* Two new Miss Universe title winners:  [[Denise Quiñones]] (2003) and [[Zuleyka Rivera]] (2006)
* The broadcasting of the [[Central American and Caribbean Games Mayaguez]] in 2010
* The full broadcasting of the President Barack Obama visit in 2011
===Present===

===2009===
* June 2009, The new era in digital television. Emmy Award
* PRTV is the biggest TV station in Puerto Rico, with five additional Channels : WIPR TV (6:1), Noticias 24/7 (6.2), Kids TV Puerto Rico (6.3) 24 hours for kids enterteinment , VME (6.4)the largest TV Station in Spanish at the USA,  (6.5) ECH El Canal de La Historia , (6:6) Radio Station 940AM.
* Kids TV won the first place in audience polls according the Mediafax Surveys.
* August 2009, TUTV changes to Puerto Rico TV (PRTV) with a fresh look and new image. 
* August 2009, Broadcast of FIBA World Championship-men in San Juan Puerto Rico. One more time, PRTV went over the local tv stations with excellent numbers.
* Spelling Bee
* September 2009, Noticias 24/7 a different news format with all the information on the same screen.
* October 2009, PRTV launch : ¡Que Noche! Music. Personality. Show business and information. &quot;Each weeknight we give you everything and more&quot;. With Gricel Mamery and Rony Campos. 
* October 2009, Puertoriqueñísimo: &quot;A five day trip through the scenery, the attractions, the businesses and the unique people of our towns. Tune in and come back to the Island with Yoyo Boing, Alejandro Croatto and other hosts as we explore the flavor, rthythm and beauty of Puerto Rico&quot;.
* November 2009, Puerto Rico TV became the fist tv station with a Christmas  CD: “''Hay Tuna Pa’Rato''” La Tuna de Cayey, The CD was awarded the first place in sales during the Christmas season.
* CAPECO Fire, Puerto Rico TV was the first media to cover the disaster and get exclusive images from helicopter.

===2010===
* January 2010 “Abracemos de Haití” Fundraising Telethon for Haiti.  A few hours after the earthquake, Puerto Rico TV called radio and tv stations in Puerto Rico to organize the special found raising  event. The result: $4 million USD for the American Red Cross.
* January 2010  New format for 940AM including music from  50's, 60's and 70's. The change increased audience ratings according the Arbitron Surveys.  
* Puerto Rico TV and Allegro Radio Station open two new radio stations :  HD-2 Jazz and  91.3-HD-3 radio Netherlands.
* March 2010 Puerto Rico TV Launch four new programs: 
* Kandela :  &quot;Iron Chef Roberto Treviño and Chef Enrique Piñeiro present the flavors and soul of the new boricua cuisine, cooked to the beat of the hottest music of the planet. You have to get a taste of Kandela!&quot;
* Te Llegó la Hora :Héctor Marcano: &quot;There is no topic that Héctor Marcano and his roundtable of experts shies away from. From the extreme to the light, Marcano invites you to speak and debate about it!&quot;
* Ahora Podemos Hablar : Carmen Jovet, The hottest interviews, the most incredible stories, the confessions that newsmakers only reveal to [[Carmen Jovet]], “La Mujer Noticia”.
* El Show de Eddie Miró: Eddie Miró. Music and interviews with some comedy. 
* Internet site: www.autismo.pr  Puerto Rico and all the latin culture  has the first site for autism. The project is a public service from Puerto Rico TV. 
* Deportes Puerto Rico TV, Sports with Carlos Baerga and Henry Neumann
* May 2010 Volleyball North Central American and Caribbean Confederation, NORCECA
* July 2010 Centrobasket 2010 July 5-10, Puerto Rico won gold.
* July 2010 The Central American and Caribbean Games (CAC or CACGs) are a multi-sport regional championships event.
* 2010 World best 10K Broadcast
* 2010 Está de Show: &quot;Luisito Vigoreaux, Otilio Warrington “Bizcocho” and their guests heat up your lunch hour with the best of Latino popular music and easy, delicious recipes seasoned with a lot of humor. And with the best of Puerto Rican retro comedies, it's gonna be a show you'll enjoy!&quot;
* 2010 Spelling Bee
* Fiesta en Ballajá:  &quot;Enjoy the beauty of Old San Juan and a spectacular open-air stage where Puerto Rico Network presents the best and most popular orchestras and popular artists of our time.&quot;
* Special coverage of the Earthquake on December 24 in San Juan, Puerto Rico.

===2011===
* 2011 Sesame Street - Puerto Rico TV, Sesame Street and various artists  created the Campaign against Dengue. The campaign included the famous characters that traveled to San Juan. 
* Puerto Rico TV Launch the first Web-TV Store in Puerto Rico www.mitienda.pr
* 2011 “Chevy Island”  Special program for kids with the host Melwin Cedeño- Chevy
* FIBV world championship- June 2011
* Royal Wedding from London 
* Direct from Rome: Beatification of John Paul II
* Miss World 2011
* Puerto Rico Network part of the USA Cable System.
* New Site: www.puertoriconetwork.tv 
* US President Barack Obama's Visit to Puerto Rico: &quot;The most Complete Coverage form all the areas&quot;. According the Puerto Rico Daily Sun, Puerto Rico TV had the best coverage of the event.
* Special Coverage: José Juan &quot;J.J.&quot; Barea Mora:Point guard for the National Basketball Association's 2011 Champion Dallas Mavericks. 
* 4th of July and Inauguration of the Bridges in San Juan.

===Digital and high definition===
WIPR-TV, the island's first public television station, also became the first in the evolution to digital and high definition.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.hispanicad.com/cgi-bin/news/newsarticle.cgi?article_id=24801| title=Puerto Rico’s first Public TV Station celebrates 50 Years! | publisher=Hispanic Ad| date=2008-07-11| accessdate=2008-07-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
.On July 7, 2008, President [[Víctor J. Montilla]] held a press conference at the station, where he inaugurated WIPR-TV's high definition facilities. TUTV became the first station in Puerto Rico to produce and broadcast in high definition format.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/tutv_inaugura_modernas_instalaciones_digitales/207865| title=TUTV inagura modernas instalaciones digitales| author=Mariela Fullana Acosta| publisher=Primera Hora| language=Spanish| date=2008-07-08| accessdate=2008-07-08}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The station created new scenarios and employed several illumination estragies to abjust the product.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cero rollos&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/estrena_look_de_alta_definicion/218017| title=Estrena look de alta definición| author=Rosalina Marrero-Rodríguez| publisher=''Primera Hora''| language=Spanish| date=2008-08-09| accessdate=2008-08-11}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some artists underwent lifestyle changes, including abjusting their diet, to project a better image in the higher definition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cero rollos&quot;/&gt; The first program to be transmitted in this format was &quot;Contigo&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Ahora sí no habrá caras perfectas| url=http://www.primerahora.com/noticia/tv/espectaculos_asi/ahora_si_no_habra_caras_perfectas/218867| publisher=''Primera Hora''| language=Spanish| date=2008-08-13| accessdate=2008-08-17}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The digital signals of WIPR and WIPM are multiplexed:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
'''Digital channels'''
! Channel
! Name
|-
| 6.1 / 3.1 || Puerto Rico TV HD
|-
| 6.2 / 3.2 || Create TV (includes programming from [[Create (TV network)|Create]] and [[PBS World]])
|-
| 6.3 / 3.3 || Kids TV Puerto Rico (featuring mainly [[PBS Kids]] programming and local shows)
|-
| 6.4 / 3.4 || [[V-me]] 
|-
| 6.5 / 3.5 || Noticias 24/7 (news channel)
|-
| 6.6 / 3.6 || [[WIPR (AM)|WIPR]] live feed
|}

===Puerto Rico Network===

There is also a Cable channel that is only available in cable systems in the [[United States]] it is known as the Puerto Rico Network.

==Programming==
=== Noticias 24/7 ===

In 1996, WIPR launched a [[newscast]] branded as '''Noti-Seis''' or &quot;News Six&quot;. The newscast was first anchored by Pedro Luis García and Gloria Soltero and only had a 6:00 PM edition. Later that year, the station premiered a 9:00 PM edition anchored by the same 6:00 PM team.

In 2002, a new news format was created with a local newscast (''TUTV Informa'') and an international newscast (''TUTV Internacional''); the newscasts were anchored by Gloria Soltero and David Reyes. TUTV also produced a weekly in-depth newscast on Sundays, called ''TuTV Analiza''.

This year,{{When|date=May 2011}} TUTV's programming received various awards.  Locally, En Todas was awarded by the [[American Heart Association]].  Five productions received Emmy Award nominations and one of TUTV's producers received an [[Emmy]] in the Entertainment Program category.

In 2009, when TUTV was rebranded as &quot;Puerto Rico TV&quot;, its news department was relaunched as ''Noticias 24/7''; around this time, WIPR introduced a 24-hour news channel of the same name on channel 6.5 and 3.5.

===List of original programs seen on WIPR-TV===

* ''Así canta Puerto Rico'', with [[Luisito Vigoreaux]]
* ''El Show de [[Chucho Avellanet]]''
* ''Contigo'', with Linette Torres and Myraida Chaves (''In High Definition on digital sub-channel 6.5'')
* ''¿Y cómo fue?'', with [[Johanna Rosaly]]
* ''Cultura Viva'', with Johanna Rosaly and Cordelia González
* ''De Pura Cepa'', with [[Danny Rivera]]
* ''En la Punta de la Lengua''
* ''Lexicon''
* ''Geo-Ambiente'', with María Falcón
* ''Reto Estudiantil'', with Gilberto Valenzuela
* ''Prohibido Olvidar''
* ''El Son del Caribe'', with Andy Montañez and Giovanna Huyke
* ''Tiempo Pedido'', with Lissette Santiago
* ''Un día antes''
* ''Noche de Gala'', with host [[Deborah Carthy Deu]]
* ''La Cocina de Giovanna'', with Giovanna Huyke
* ''El Planeta de Remi'', with the character created by [[Jose Vega Santana]]
* ''La Casa de Maria Chuzema'', produced by Tere Marichal
* ''Que Noche'',Ronny, Grisel Mamery y Kristal Ayala
* ''Puertorriqueñísimo'', Alejandro Croato , Yoyo Boing y [[Jailene Cintrón]], created by Coco Salazar

==See also==
* [[WIPR (AM)]]
* [[WIPR-FM]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.prnet.pr/ Puerto Rico TV]
*[http://www.noticias247.pr/ Noticias 24/7]
*[http://www.puertoriconetwork.tv/ Puerto Rico Network]
*[http://www.facebook.com/noticias247pr Noticias 24/7 on Facebook]
*[http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/P/htmlP/puertorico/puertorico.htm Museum of Broadcasting and Communications: Puerto Rico]
*{{TVQ|WIPR-TV}}
*{{TVQ|WIPM-TV}}
*{{BIA|WIPR|TV|TV}}
*{{BIA|WIPM|TV|TV}}

{{Puerto Rico TV}}
{{LocalCableNews}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wipr-Tv}}
[[Category:San Juan, Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:Television stations in Puerto Rico]]
[[Category:Independent television stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1958]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
