<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="332711" ns="0" title="Churchill White Paper"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Churchill White Paper''' (also known as ''The British White Paper of 1922'') of 3 June 1922 clarified how Britain viewed the [[Balfour Declaration, 1917]]. That Declaration announced the [[United Kingdom|British]] intent to aid the &quot;establishment in [[Palestine]] of a national home for the [[Jew]]ish people.&quot;

==Key provisions==

The main provisions of this [[white paper]] are summarized by these quotations from it:

* &quot;The tension which has prevailed from time to time in Palestine is mainly due to apprehensions, which are entertained both by sections of the [[Arab]] and by sections of the Jewish population. These apprehensions, so far as the Arabs are concerned are partly based upon exaggerated interpretations of the meaning of the [Balfour] Declaration favouring the establishment of a Jewish National Home in Palestine, made on behalf of [[British government|His Majesty's Government]] on 2 November 1917.&quot;

* 'Unauthorized statements have been made to the effect that the purpose in view is to create a wholly Jewish Palestine. Phrases have been used such as that Palestine is to become &quot;as Jewish as [[England]] is English.&quot; His Majesty's Government regard any such expectation as impracticable and have no such aim in view. They would draw attention to the fact that the terms of the Declaration referred to do not contemplate that Palestine as a whole should be converted into a Jewish National Home, but that such a Home should be founded &quot;in Palestine.&quot; In this connection it has been observed with satisfaction that at a meeting of the [[Zionist Congress]], the supreme governing body of the [[Zionist Organization]], held at [[Karlovy Vary|Carlsbad]] in September, 1921, a resolution was passed expressing as the official statement of Zionist aims &quot;the determination of the Jewish people to live with the Arab people on terms of unity and mutual respect, and together with them to make the common home into a flourishing community, the upbuilding of which may assure to each of its peoples an undisturbed national development&quot;'.

* 'it is contemplated that the status of all citizens of Palestine in the eyes of the law shall be [[Palestinian people|Palestinian]], and it has never been intended that they, or any section of them, should possess any other juridical status. So far as the Jewish population of Palestine are concerned it appears that some among them are apprehensive that His Majesty's Government may depart from the policy embodied in the Declaration of 1917. It is necessary, therefore, once more to affirm that these fears are unfounded, and that that Declaration, re-affirmed by the Conference of the Principal Allied Powers at San Remo and again in the [[Treaty of Sèvres]], is not susceptible of change.'

* 'During the last two or three generations the Jews have recreated in Palestine a community, now numbering 80,000… it is essential that it should know that it is in Palestine as of right and not on the sufferance. That is the reason why it is necessary that the existence of a Jewish National Home in Palestine should be internationally guaranteed, and that it should be formally recognized to rest upon ancient historic connection.'

* 'This, then, is the interpretation which His Majesty's Government place upon the Declaration of 1917, and, so understood, the Secretary of State is of opinion that it does not contain or imply anything which need cause either alarm to the Arab population of Palestine or disappointment to the Jews.'

Having clarified the understanding and intent of the British government, the White Paper continues, outlining measures to assist in attaining the objectives: 'For the fulfilment of this policy it is necessary that the Jewish community in Palestine should be able to increase its numbers by [[Jewish immigration to Palestine|immigration]]. This immigration cannot be so great in volume as to exceed whatever may be the economic capacity of the country at the time to absorb new arrivals.  It is essential to ensure that the immigrants should not be a burden upon the people of Palestine as a whole, and that they should not deprive any section of the present population of their employment. Hitherto the immigration has fulfilled these conditions.  The number of immigrants since the British occupation has been about 25,000.'  The document notes an exception however, saying: ‘It is necessary also to ensure that persons who are politically undesirable be excluded from Palestine, and every precaution has been and will be taken by the Administration to that end.’

It also expressed the British view on the reason for not immediately forming an independent government of Palestine, addressing the conflicting claims related to the [[Hussein-McMahon Correspondence]], [[Sykes-Picot Agreement]] and subsequent Balfour Declaration:

'It is not the case, as has been represented by the Arab Delegation, that during the war His Majesty's Government gave an undertaking that an independent national government should be at once established in Palestine. This representation mainly rests upon a letter dated the 24 October 1915, from [[Sir Henry McMahon]], then His Majesty's High Commissioner in Egypt, to the [[Sharif of Mecca]], now King Hussein of the Kingdom of the Hejaz. That letter is quoted as conveying the promise to the Sherif of Mecca to recognise and support the independence of the Arabs within the territories proposed by him. But this promise was given subject to a reservation made in the same letter, which excluded from its scope, among other territories, the portions of [[Syria]] lying to the west of the [[District of Damascus]]. This reservation has always been regarded by His Majesty's Government as covering the [[vilayet of Beirut]] and the independent [[Sanjak of Jerusalem]]. The whole of Palestine west of the [[River Jordan|Jordan]] was thus excluded from Sir. Henry McMahon's pledge'. Churchill's interpretation of the agreements was contrary to the interpretation given by Prime Minister Lloyd George during the Paris Peace Conference.&lt;ref&gt;see [http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=turn&amp;entity=FRUS.FRUS1919Parisv05.p0011&amp;isize=M 'The Council of Four: minutes of meetings March 20 to May 24, 1919, page 1-8]&lt;/ref&gt;  

The 1922 White Paper did not put an end to the controversy, The text of the Sykes-Picot Agreement had included a proviso that required coordination with the Sharif of Mecca regarding the so-called international zone (Palestine). It also called for an Arab State or confederation under an Arab Chief, and the British government had arranged for the meetings leading up to the Faisal-Weizmann Agreement.  

[[Image:Faisal-Weizmann map.png|thumb|right|200px|Map showing the boundaries of the proposed Jewish state, as outlined by the Zionist representatives at the 1919 Paris Peace Conference, superimposed on modern boundaries.]]

The [[Faisal-Weizmann Agreement]] said that the boundaries between an Arab State and Palestine should be determined by a Commission after the Paris Peace Conference. The Zionist delegation submitted a map that proposed a border west of the Hedjaz Railway, exactly where Balfour had suggested it be drawn in an [[Balfour Declaration of 1917#Conflicts_and_Broken_Treaty_Commitments|infamous memo]] to the British Foreign Secretary, Lord Curzon.  

Contrary to popular belief, the borders of Palestine were not defined in the texts of the [[Balfour Declaration of 1917]], The [[San Remo conference]], The [[Treaty of Sèvres]], the [[Treaty of Lausanne]], or even by the [[British Mandate of Palestine]]. The preamble of the Mandate read:&lt;blockquote&gt;
The Council of the League of Nations:

Whereas the Principal Allied Powers have agreed, for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of Article 22 of the Covenant of the League of Nations, to entrust to a Mandatory selected by the said Powers the administration of the territory of Palestine, which formerly belonged to the Turkish Empire, '''within such boundaries as may be fixed by them;'''&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On the day that the first High Commissioner, Herbert Samuel, signed for 'one Palestine, complete' &lt;ref&gt;Herbert Samuel received the mandated territory from its military commander along with a receipt 'Handed over to Sir Herbert Samuel, one Palestine, complete' [http://books.google.com/books?id=YbTh44KfkPIC&amp;pg=PA7&amp;dq=&amp;ei=We_3SM_SGIuYMqOx5KYL&amp;client= Rosalind Franklin, By Brenda Maddox, Page 7]&lt;/ref&gt; there were no formally recognized borders. The Zionist Committee's modest proposal excluded the area from Amman to the Mesopotamian and Arabian frontiers. According to Sykes, Churchill, and Balfour the areas lying east of the line from Damascus, Homs, Hama, and Alleppo (the Hedjaz Railway route) had been pledged to the Arabs (as noted in Churchill's analysis). The Vilayet of Ma'an and the port of Aqaba were annexed to Transjordan from the Kingdom of Hedjaz as the latter fell to Ibn Saud. The Occupied Enemy Territory which later became Syria Mesopotamia, and Palestine were mentioned in Section VII, Articles 94-97 of the Treaty of Sèvres, the short-lived [[Kingdom of Hejaz]] is mentioned separately in Section VIII, articles 98-100.

==Subsequent revelations==

A committee established by the British in 1939 to clarify the various arguments observed that many commitments had been made during and after the war—and that all of them would have to be studied together. The Arab representatives submitted a statement to the committee from Sir [[Michael McDonnell]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/3d14c9e5cdaa296d85256cbf005aa3eb/4c4f7515dc39195185256cf7006f878c!OpenDocument Report of a Committee Set up to Consider Certain Correspondence Between Sir Henry McMahon and the Sharif of Mecca in 1915 and 1916], UNISPAL, Annex C.&lt;/ref&gt; which explained that whatever McMahon had intended to mean was of no legal consequence, since it was his actual statements that constituted the pledge from His Majesty's Government. They also pointed out that McMahon had been acting as an intermediary for the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Lord Grey. Speaking in the House of Lords on the 27th March, 1923, Lord Grey had made it clear that, for his part, he entertained serious doubts as to the validity of the Churchill White Paper's interpretation of the pledges which he, as Foreign Secretary, had caused to be given to the Sharif Hussein in 1915. 

Years later, scholars searching through the declassified files in the National Archives discovered evidence that Palestine had been pledged to Hussein. The Eastern Committee of the Cabinet, previously known as the Middle Eastern Committee, had met on 5 December 1918 to discuss the government's commitments regarding Palestine. Lord Curzon chaired the meeting. General Jan Smuts, Lord Balfour, Lord Robert Cecil, General Sir Henry Wilson, Chief of the Imperial General Staff, and representatives of the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Admiralty, the War Office, and the Treasury were present. T. E. Lawrence also attended. According to the minutes Lord Curzon explained the Hussein, Sykes-Picot, and Balfour commitments:

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The Palestine position is this. If we deal with our commitments, there is first the general pledge to Hussein in October 1915, under which '''Palestine was included in the areas as to which Great Britain pledged itself that they should be Arab and independent in the future''' . . . Great Britain and France—Italy subsequently agreeing—committed themselves to an international administration of Palestine in consultation with Russia, [and the Sharif of Mecca] who was an ally at that time . . . A new feature was brought into the case in November 1917, when Mr Balfour, with the authority of the War Cabinet, issued his famous declaration to the Zionists that Palestine 'should be the national home of the Jewish people, but that nothing should be done—and this, of course, was a most important proviso—to prejudice the civil and religious rights of the existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine. Those, as far as I know, are the only actual engagements into which we entered with regard to Palestine.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Palestine Papers 1917-1922, Doreen Ingrams, page 48 and UK Archives PRO. CAB 27/24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[Sykes-Picot Agreement]] of 16 May 1916, proposing borders of what would become Palestine
*[[Balfour Declaration, 1917|Balfour Declaration]] of 2 November 1917, British statement of support for establishment of a Jewish national homeland in Palestine.
*[[1922 Text: League of Nations Palestine Mandate]]
*[[White Paper of 1939|The White Paper of 1939]], also known as the ''MacDonald White Paper''
*[[1947 UN Partition Plan]]
*[[Declaration of the Establishment of the State of Israel, May 14, 1948]]
*[[White paper]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://domino.un.org/UNISPAL.NSF/eed216406b50bf6485256ce10072f637/f2ca0ee62b5680ed852570c000591beb!OpenDocument text of the Churchill White Paper, 1922] at UNISPAL
*[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/mideast/brwh1922.htm text of the 1922 White Paper] from the Avalon Project
*[http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/mideast/balfour.htm text of the Balfour Declaration, 1917] from the Avalon Project
*[http://www.shoaheducation.com/balfdoc.html Balfour Declaration, 1917] from Shoah Education Project Web

{{Documents of Mandate Palestine}}
{{Arab–Israeli diplomacy}}

[[Category:1922 in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:History of Jordan]]
[[Category:Jews and Judaism in Jordan]]
[[Category:British Mandate for Palestine]]
[[Category:Political history of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:White Papers]]
[[Category:Zionism]]
[[Category:Borders of the Palestinian territories]]
[[Category:Fertile Crescent]]
[[Category:Documents of the British Mandate for Palestine]]

[[ar:وثيقة تشرشل البيضاء 1922]]
[[cs:Churchillova bílá kniha]]
[[he:הספר הלבן הראשון]]
[[ru:Белая книга Черчилля (1922)]]
[[yi:ערשטע ווייסבוך]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
