<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33370756" ns="0" title="Maspero demonstrations"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox civil conflict
| title         = Maspero demonstrations
| partof        = [[Timeline of the 2011 Egyptian revolution under Supreme Council of the Armed Forces]]
| image         = [[File:Maspiro October 9 victims.jpg|290px]]
| caption       = Some of the victims of the 9 October protests.
| place         = [[Maspiro television building|Maspiro]], [[Cairo]], [[Egypt]]
| coordinates   = 
| date          = 9–10 October 2011
| status        =
| goals         =
| howmany1      = 
| causes        =
| methods       = 
| injuries      = 212
| fatalities    = 27
| arrests       =
| concessions   =
}}
'''Maspero Demonstrations''' were staged by a group predominated by [[Egypt]]ian [[Copts]] in reaction to the burning of a number of churches in [[Upper Egypt]].&lt;ref name=BBC1&gt;{{cite news|title=Cairo clashes leave 24 dead after Coptic church protest|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-15235212|accessdate=11 October 2011|newspaper=BBC|date=9 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The peaceful protesters who intended to stage a sit-in in front of the [[Maspiro television building]] were attacked by security forces and the [[Egyptian Armed Forces|army]], resulting in 27 deaths, mostly among the Coptic protestors, and 212 injuries, most of which were sustained by Copts.&lt;ref name=AFP1&gt;{{cite news|last=Michael|first=M|title=Christians Under Siege in Post-Revolution Egypt |url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/christians-siege-post-revolution-egypt-14707870|accessdate=11 October 2011|newspaper=AP|date=9 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== The demonstration ==
The peaceful protesters gathered in peaceful chants, angered by a statement made publicly by Aswan’s governor, Mustafa Kamel el-Sayyed, who, after the destruction of the church in Aswan, denied the existence of the church, and then later retracted his statements, and claimed instead that the construction of the Church was illegal. It was later revealed that extremist followers of the [[Salafist]] Islamic sect had pronounced threats and made demands for Aswan’s Christian congregation not to have any loudspeakers in the church and to limit the visibility of any Christian symbols such as crosses on the church structure. In order to diffuse tensions, the Aswan governorate organized a meeting between Salafist and Coptic leaders, wherein the Copts refused the latter demand of eliminating crosses and steeples. The threats eventually escalated to actual destruction of the church by the extremists, and to the subsequent statements by the Aswan governor. It was this incident that led to the protest, which is presented in the following details based on a number of credible sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Carr, Sarah. “A First-Hand Account: Marching from Shubra to Deaths at Maspiro” Al Masry Al Youm. October, 10, 2011. |url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/503496|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Almasry Alyoum|date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The march set out towards Maspiro from the downtown poverty-stricken neighborhood of Shubra, densely populated by both Muslims and Christians. Reporters agree that it was a sizeable demonstration comparable to the numbers at the January 28 protest, the day when Mubarak sent army vehicles to confront protesters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Blair, Edmund. “Egypt’s Mubarak sends in army, resists demands to quit” Reuters. January 28, 2011. |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/01/28/us-egypt-protest-idUSTRE70O3UW20110128|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Reuters|date=28 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Protesters were also angry about injury sustained by a Christian priest during the violent confrontation by army and police at Wednesday’s demonstration at Maspiro, when a smaller group had been demonstrating against the situation in Aswan.

== Clashes ==
{{Modern persecution of Coptic Christians}}
Reports suggest that the army began using violence even before the protesters reached Maspiro. Gunshots were heard from the end of Shubra Street and rocks were thrown from a nearby bridge. The protesters responded in chants against the Field Commander. The attacks suddenly stopped as the protesters proceeded on Galaa Street. As they crossed the Al Ahram headquarters, one rock was thrown at the building. Reports suggest this was in response to Al Ahram’s poor coverage of violence against Copts in a recent issue.{{cn|date=October 2011}}

Army attacks resumed when the protesters turned the corner at Ramsis Hotel and reached Maspiro. Witnesses saw two armored personnel carriers crushing protesters to death, and soldiers firing wildly at the congregation, followed by riot police throwing tear gas. These incidents have been documented by video and later broadcast on CNN.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Mackey, Robert. “Social Media Accounts of Violence in Cairo Challenge Official Narrative.” The New York Times. October 10, 2011. |url=http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/10/social-media-accounts-of-violence-in-cairo-challenge-official-narrative/|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports count between 24&lt;ref&gt;[http://english.ahram.org.eg/~/NewsContentP/1/24102/Egypt/Maspero-survivors-testify-army-shot-at-unarmed-dem.aspx]&lt;/ref&gt; and 27 deaths, mostly Coptic civilians, and over 300 injured.

State television within minutes of violence first reported the death of three soldiers and requested that all noble Egyptian patriots protect the military against the “violent crowd of Copts,” also alluding to “foreign infiltrators” inciting violence. Eye witness reports which are attached to this brief, describe the response to the televised announcement by crowds of Muslims zealous to protect the military against allegedly violent Copts: “I saw groups in civilian clothing with sticks and machetes walking around yelling ‘Where are the Christians? Islam is here!’”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Bushra, Hani. “My testimony about the attack I suffered in downtown Cairo on October 9, 2011” Facebook. October 9, 2011|url=https://www.facebook.com/notes/hani-bushra/my-testimony-about-the-attack-that-i-suffered-in-downtown-cairo-on-october-9-201/10150321526196820|accessdate=20 October 2011|Facebook=Hani Bushra|date=09 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; This eyewitness stated he fled the scene as various crowds asked him whether or not he was a Christian. That evening, state television continued to broadcast a manipulated version of the story claiming the protesters were armed and that a “conflict” had broken out between civilians and military personnel with riot police, leaving deaths and injuries on both sides. Later, the Department of Health released another statement indicating that there were no military deaths and associating all bodies with deceased civilian protesters.{{cn|date=October 2011}}

== Response ==
According to an official statement by the [[Supreme Council of the Armed Forces|Egyptian military]], it was the protesters who first attacked the army resulting in the death of 3 police officers. They responded by firing blank cartridges, military personnel were being pulled out of their armoured vehicles and attacked by rioters which caused other military personnel to panic and unintentionally mow down some protesters as they drove off.&lt;ref name=LA&gt;{{cite news|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2011/oct/13/world/la-fg-egypt-military-denial-20111013|newspaper=LA times|date=13 October 2011 | first=Amro|last=Hassan|title=Egypt military says soldiers didn't intentionally kill Copts}}&lt;/ref&gt; Human rights organisations have dismissed the Army's response as partial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Egypt military takes over inquiry of Coptic unrest|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/13/ap/middleeast/main20119761.shtml|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=CBS news|date=13 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Several international media outlets, including BBC and CNN, picked up this version of the events. Egyptian state television later retracted the claims when it broadcast a mild report on the events the following day, but continued to exhibit a reluctance to condemn the actions of the army&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Ammar, Manar. “Egypt state television admits to making up news over soldiers’ deaths” Bikya Masr. October 10, 2011.|url=http://bikyamasr.com/45280/egypt-state-television-admits-to-making-up-news-over-soldiers-deaths/|accessdate=20 October 2011|movement=Bik ya Masr|date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

Public figures, including prominent Muslim and Coptic leaders, have demanded the prosecution of army generals. The military council then called for the civilian Prime Minister to investigate the incident and identified 15 suspects to be tried in military courts. The military council and state television remain targets of heated criticism from prominent activists and journalists. The representatives at the state television have not issued any statements, but a newscaster has publicly expressed feeling “ashamed” to be working for an institution that “[proved] itself to be a slave for whoever rules Egypt.”&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=El Gundy, Zeinab. “Outrage over state TV’s misinformation and anti-Coptic incitement” Ahram Online. October 10, 2011.|url=http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/23813/Egypt/Politics-/Outrage-over-state-TVs-misinformation-and-antiCopt.aspx|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=Ahram online|date=10 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Activists also blame state television for provoking sectarian tensions.

Governor Mustafa Kamel El Sayyed reportedly said that the demolition of the Church was agreed to by the local Coptic community and absolved himself of any responsibility in the tragic events at Maspiro[12]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Free Christian Voice. October 11, 2011.|url=http://www.light-dark.net/vb/showthread.php?p=8127#post8127|accessdate=20 October 2011|news=Free Christian Voice|date=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;. The Ministerial Cabinet announced it will amend laws pertaining to the construction of houses of worship and toughen the anti-discrimination laws, but local human rights activists doubt the effectiveness or follow-through of the Cabinet’s approach[13]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Fahmy, Heba. “Experts say tougher measures needed after Maspero, slam state media coverage” The Daily News Egypt. October 11, 2011.|url=http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/egypt/experts-say-tougher-measures-needed-after-maspero-slam-media-coverage.html|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=CBS news|date=11 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;. Identical promises have been made following other similar incidents (recently and in the more distant past) without any follow-through to amend the archaic laws that differentially govern construction of houses of worship.
In addition, the Egyptian military, which is responsible for these deaths, has taken over the investigation, prompting Human Rights Watch to issue a statement which concluded that  &quot;official denials suggest investigation will be flawed.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Egypt: Don’t Cover Up Military Killing of Copt Protesters October 15, 2011.[14]|url=http://www.hrw.org/news/2011/10/25/egypt-don-t-cover-military-killing-copt-protesters|accessdate=25 October 2011|International Organsiation=Human Rights Watch|date=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== See also ==
* [[2011 Alexandria bombing]]
* [[2011 Imbaba Church Attacks]]
* [[Human rights in Egypt under the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces]]

==External links==
*{{cite news|last=Carr|first=S|title=A firsthand account: Marching from Shubra to deaths at Maspero|url=http://www.almasryalyoum.com/en/node/503496|accessdate=11 October 2011|newspaper=Almasry Alyoum|date=9 October 2011}}
*Blair, Edmund. [http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/01/28/us-egypt-protest-idUSTRE70O3UW20110128 “Egypt’s Mubarak sends in army, resists demands to quit”] Reuters. January 28, 2011.
*Mackey, Robert. [http://thelede.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/10/10/social-media-accounts-of-violence-in-cairo-challenge-official-narrative/ “Social Media Accounts of Violence in Cairo Challenge Official Narrative.”], The New York Times. October 10, 2011.
*El Gundy, Zeinab. [http://english.ahram.org.eg/NewsContent/1/64/23813/Egypt/Politics-/Outrage-over-state-TVs-misinformation-and-antiCopt.aspx “Outrage over state TV’s misinformation and anti-Coptic incitement”], Ahram Online. October 10, 2011.
*Fahmy, Heba. [http://www.thedailynewsegypt.com/egypt/experts-say-tougher-measures-needed-after-maspero-slam-media-coverage.html “Experts say tougher measures needed after Maspero, slam state media coverage”], The Daily News Egypt. October 11, 2011.
*Human Rights Watch. [http://www.hrw.org/news/2011/10/25/egypt-don-t-cover-military-killing-copt-protesters “Egypt: Don’t Cover Up Military Killing of Copt Protesters”], HRW. October 15, 2011.

[[ar:أحداث ماسبيرو]]
[[fr:Altercations inter-religieuses égyptiennes d'octobre 2011]]

[[Category:History of Egypt]]
[[Category:Religiously motivated violence in Egypt]]
[[Category:Coptic history]]
[[Category:2011 in Egypt|Maspero demonstrations]]
[[Category:Persecution of Christians]]
[[Category:Protests in Egypt]]
[[Category:2011 Egyptian revolution]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
