<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3340875" ns="0" title="AntiVirus Gold"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{distinguish2|[[AVG (software)|the legitimate AVG line of antivirus programs]]}}

'''AntiVirus Gold''' is [[rogue software]] developed by [[ICommerce Solutions]] S.A. that poses as a legitimate [[antivirus program]]&lt;ref name=&quot;ca.com&quot;&gt;http://www.ca.com/us/securityadvisor/pest/pest.aspx?id=453094194&lt;/ref&gt;. It attempts to persuade users to buy the software by displaying ads and other [[nagware]]. It is believed that the name of the program is an attempt at [[Social engineering (security)|social engineering]] to confuse people about the legitimate program [[AVG Anti-Virus]]. 

AntiVirus Gold may be downloaded as bundle with other software or by some trojans.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.bleepingcomputer.com/forums/topic22397.html&lt;/ref&gt; Antivirus Gold has also been rebranded under many names such as Antivirus Golden and Antispyware Gold.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spywarewarrior.com/rogue_anti-spyware.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== Symptoms of infection ==
In a typical infection, the desktop wallpaper is modified and an advertisement is displayed urging the user to buy Antivirus Gold. Upon clicking on the message, a web browser is opened to point to www.AntiVirus-Gold.com&lt;ref name=&quot;ca.com&quot;/&gt;. Users have also reported that they are being directed to the site after clicking on the infected desktop. The program attempts to reinstall itself after a reboot if removed by uninstalling or system restore.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.symantec.com/security_response/writeup.jsp?docid=2006-032415-1558-99&amp;tabid=2&lt;/ref&gt;

== Removal ==
AntiVirus Gold is detected in common [[Anti-virus programs]], including CA Antispyware, the Norton Family of Security products, AVG Anti-Virus. Antimalware programs, such as Malwarebytes' AntiMalware, are also very effective in detecting and removing [[rogue software]] such as AntiVirus Gold.

== See also ==
* [[Spy Sheriff]]
* [[Rogue security software]]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==

{{DEFAULTSORT:Antivirus Gold}}
[[Category:Rogue software]]


{{malware-stub}}

[[es:Antivirus-Gold]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
