<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3347357" ns="0" title="Pecunix"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">'''Pecunix''' is a [[digital gold currency]] founded in 2002 by [[Simon Davis (businessman)|Simon Davis]]. Similar to competing systems such as [[e-gold]], Pecunix allows for the instant transfer of [[gold]] between user accounts.

Estimates at the end of [[2004]] suggest that there were over 6,500 funded accounts in the Pecunix system at that time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://indomitus.net/2004status.html#pec Status Report on Free Market Money], ''Indomitus Report'', January 31, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Pecunix had at that time 1,579.499 oz of gold in storage&lt;ref&gt;[http://indomitus.net/2004status.html#pec Status Report on Free Market Money], ''Indomitus Report'', January 31, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;, but the amount has grown since. As of November 2011, Pecunix had 2777.796 oz of gold in storage, which as of November 2011 is valued at approximately $4,914,754 [http://pecunix.com/money.refined...ind.goldbars].  Pecunix gold bullion is stored with Mat Securitas Express AG in [[Zurich]], [[Switzerland]]. Pecunix, Inc. is [[incorporation (business)|incorporated]] in the Republic of [[Panama]].

== Features ==
Pecunix provides an alternative to reserveless currencies, as do the other competing digital gold currencies. One benefit claimed by many proponents of digital gold currencies is that by keeping assets out of [[fiat money|fiat currencies]], one avoids some [[inflation]]ary risks. Another claimed benefit is low fees. Transactions made in the Pecunix system are charged a fee of 0.50% of the payment amount up to 100 [[gram]]s of gold and 0.15% of any amount over 100 grams up to a maximum fee of 3 grams. The minimum fee payment is 0.0001 gram. 

According to Jim Davidson, author of ''The Indomitus Report'', Pecunix has never had a security breach of any kind and never had an account emptied by [[Trojan horse (computing)|trojan]] or [[phishing]] attacks.&lt;ref&gt;[http://indomitus.net/2004status.html#pec Status Report on Free Market Money], ''Indomitus Report'', January 31, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Its software integrates [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP]] in order to enhance privacy and security.

== Exchanging fiat currency ==
Pecunix does not sell its currency directly to clients.  Instead numerous [[digital currency exchanger]]s act as [[market maker]]s selling Pecunix in exchange for fiat currency and a transaction fee.

== See also==
*[[Digital gold currency]]
*[[e-gold]]
*[[Bitcoin]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.pecunix.com Pecunix - Money Refined]
*[http://firstwm.ru/article/?aid=Pecunix+(eng)&amp;lng=eng Description Pecunix by Firstwm.ru]

[[Category:Digital gold currencies]]

[[fr:Pecunix]]
[[id:Pecunix]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
