<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33499978" ns="0" title="Battle of Zahleh"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of Zahleh &lt;br&gt; معركة زحلة 
| partof = the [[Lebanese Civil War]]
| image =  
| caption = 
| date = December 1980 - June 1981
| place = [[Zahleh]], [[Lebanon]], [[Middle-East]]  
| result = A tentative strategic victory for the Lebanese Forces 

&lt;!--  Flags and combatants   --&gt;
|combatant1={{flagicon image|Forces Libanaises Flag.svg}} [[Lebanese Forces]]&lt;br&gt;
----
|combatant2= {{flagicon image|Flag of the Arab League.svg}} [[Syrian Army|Syrian Army Forces]] aka [[Arab Deterrent Force]] &lt;br&gt;
----
{{flagicon|Palestine}} [[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO (Palestine Liberation Organization)]] &lt;br&gt;
----
[[The Hanache Group]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

&lt;!--  Units  --&gt;
| units1 = [[Lebanese Forces|'''Lebanese Forces''']]:&lt;br&gt;
* Al Wahdat el-Markazaiya (Special LF Central Units)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Abou Nade|first=Fouad|title=On Battle of Zahleh|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2eUT9bRVDA&amp;feature=related|work=you tube video|publisher=michel10452|accessdate=5 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Internal Security Forces|ISF]] (Internal Security Forces)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Zahlawi Local Resistance'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=10}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| units2 = [[Syrian Army|'''Syrian Army Forces''']]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=11}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;
* 35th Brigade (Special Forces)
* 41st Brigade (Special Forces)
* 47th Brigade (Mechanized Infantry)
* 51st Brigade (Ind. Armored)
* 62nd Brigade (Mechanized Infantry)
* 67th Brigade
* 85th Brigade
* 78th Brigade
[[Palestine Liberation Organization|PLO (Palestine Liberation Organization)]]:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban: du Coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=106–107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; 
* al-Yarmouk Faction
*al-Kostol Faction
}}
'''The Battle of Zahleh''' ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: معركة زحلة) took place during the Lebanese Civil War, between December 1980 and June 1981. During the seven month period, the city of [[Zahleh]] ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: زحلة) endured a handful of political and military setbacks. The opposing key players were on the one side, the LF ([[Lebanese Forces]]) ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: القوات اللبنانية) aided by Zahlawi townspeople, and on the other side, the [[Syrian Armed Forces|Syrian Army Forces]] also known as ADF [[Arab Deterrent Force]] (Arabic: قوات الردع العربية), aided by some [[PLO]] (Palestinian Liberation Organization) factions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=106–107}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Demographically, Zahleh is one the largest predominantly Christian towns in Lebanon.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD}}&lt;/ref&gt; Adjacent to the town's outskirts, the [[Bekaa valley]] (Arabic: وادي البقاع), spanning the length of the Syrian borders. Given Zahleh's close proximity to the Bekaa Valley, the Syrian Army Forces feared a potential alliance between Israel and the LF in Zahleh. This potential alliance would not only threaten the Syrian military presence in the Bekaa valley, but was regarded as a national security threat from the Syrians' point of view, given the close proximity between Zahleh and the [[Damascus]] highway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=106–107}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, as a clamp down strategy, the Syrian forces controlled major roads leading in and out of the city and fortified the entire Valley. Around December 1980, tension increased between Zahlawi Lebanese Forces and Syrian backed Leftist militants. From April to June 1981, throughout the four month period, a handful of LF members, aided by Zahlawi Local Resistance, stood headway with the Syrian war machine and defended the city from Syrian intrusion and potential invasion.

== Zahleh’s Strategic Location ==
From the start of the Civil War, the city of Zahleh’s key strategic location served as a main artery for the fighting groups involved in the conflict. In particular, the Syrian Army Forces who occupied the adjacent Bekaa Valley from May 1976.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Syrian Occupation of Lebanon (1976-2005)|url=http://www.lgic.org/en/help_syria.php|work=Lgic|accessdate=November 06, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout history, the city of Zahleh served as trade-hub for commerce; located between Damascus on the East side, including the fertile Bekaa valley that borders [[Syria]], and [[Beirut|Beirut City]] on the opposite west side. Despite that Zahlawi’s readily took advantage of their location for trade and commerce, their geo-strategic location was a deterrent on the socio-political level  between 1980 and 1981. From the west side, the city lies at the base of the 8,622 feet high [[Mount Sannine]] ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: جبل صنين‎). The peak of Mount Sannine, not only overlooked the entire Bekaa Valley, but the Israeli occupied Golan heights and even further. With that said, the Syrian’s securing at least the base of Mount Sannine prevents any potential Israeli or LF attempt to scrutinize the occupied [[Golan Heights]] and further deep into Syrian territories. 

== The Syrian Reaction to Zahleh’s Location ==
Strategically, the prime concern of the Syrians was to curb the Christian controlled city’s geo-strategic attributes. Consequently, the Syrian Forces blocked the main roads leading in out of the city. The Syrian forces, however, remained stationed outside the city, in particular, along the outskirts. The Syrian army chief of staff at the time, General Hikmat Chehabi ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: حكمت شهابي) expressed concerns over a free and uncontrolled Zahleh falling into the hands of the Israeli Forces. For the reason that, the Israelis were providing military aid to the LF, whose presence was apparent inside Zahleh. Chehabi’s concern was, that the LF might hand over the base of mount Sannine to the Israelis; given the mount peek outlooks the Golan heights and deep inside Syrian territories. To that end, Chehabi foresaw a problematic scenario on more than one level. One, if the Israeli Forces cut through Zahleh city and position their forces along its outskirts, they would be stationed only four miles West of the Syrian fifth division in the town of [[Chtaura]] ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: شتورة), located by the Beirut [[Damascus|Damascus highway]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Two, such scenario, if actualized, will not only threaten Syrian military presence in the Valley, but even the Syrian capital itself –– the Israeli army would be 8.6 miles West of the Syrian borders and 31 miles from the Syrian capital, Damascus. For that reason, the Syrian 85th and 78th brigades along with the 7th division regrouped across the valley. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=108}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition, Chehabi armed PLO’s (Palestinian Liberation Organization) factions such as, al-Yarmouk, al-Kostol and Ain jallout positioned between the [[Litani River]] ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: نهر الليطاني‎) and Zahrani River&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]: نهر الزهراني).

== The Initial Setbacks ==
Prior to the December setbacks, the ''Moukhabarat'' ([[Arabic language|Arabic]]:المخابرات السورية), the Syrian Secret Service, were congregating surreptitiously in and around the city, aiding the left-wing armed group, Hanache.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=6}}&lt;/ref&gt;Tensions between the local right-wing LF and left-wing Hanache were building up.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; The catalyst to the initial setbacks ensued when Hanache Group attempted to control the offices of the [[National Liberal Party (Lebanon)|National Liberal Party]] (NLP) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=7}}&lt;/ref&gt;. On December 22, 1980, shootings broke out between LF local members and the Hanache group &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=7}}&lt;/ref&gt;. A Syrian [[Armored personnel carrier|armored personnel carrier]] (APC) ventured between the two opposing groups, was attacked by the LF &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=7}}&lt;/ref&gt;. When the Syrians attempted to retrieve their damaged vehicles and dead occupants they directly engaged with the LF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mclaurin|first=R.D|title=The battle of Zahle (Technical memorandum 8-86)|year=1986|publisher=U.S Army Human Engineering Laboratory|location=MD|pages=7}} &lt;/ref&gt; During the confrontations, a total of five Syrian soldiers were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the Syrian Forces shelled the overpopulated city for six consecutive hours, to pressure Zahlawis to hand over the militants responsible for the killing. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; To even further increase the psychological pressure on the City, the Syrian checkpoints dispersed around the outskirts of the city blocked foodstuff and supply materials going in and out of the Zahleh.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On the international level, the disproportionate Syrian reaction triggered  a unified international criticism. France for example, described the shelling as a barbaric act; Washington described the shelling as a deplorable Syrian act.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, the shelling stopped due to the international pressure; the turmoil cooled off between January and March due to heavy snow storms the city endured during the winter of 1980 - 1981.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Menargues|first=Alain|title=Les secrets de la guerre au Liban : du coup d'Etat de Bachir Gémayel aux Massacres des Camps Palestiniens|year=2004|publisher=Albin Michel|pages=111}} &lt;/ref&gt; The two sides, however, remained alert while preparing for the upcoming conclusive battle.

==See also==
*[[Lebanese Front]]
*[[Kataeb Regulatory Forces]]
*[[Army of Free Lebanon]]
*[[Outline of Lebanon]]
*[[Syrian Armed Forces]]

== External links ==
*[http://www.lebanese-forces.org Lebanese Forces Official Website]
*[http://www.lebanese-forces.org/forum/index.php Lebanese Forces Forum]
*[http://www.lfmartyrs.org Lebanese Forces Martyrs Website]
*[http://lftv.tv/ Lebanese Forces Television]
*[http://www.ouwet.com Lebanese Forces Blog]
*[http://adonis49.wordpress.com/2011/07/28/battle-of-zahleh-lebanon-april-1982-revisiting-this-melancholic-civil-war/ Adonis Diaries ]

==References==
{{reflist}}

[[Category:Lebanese Civil War]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
