<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33505804" ns="0" title="International reactions to the death of Muammar Gaddafi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''international reactions to the [[death of Muammar Gaddafi]]''' concern the responses of foreign governments and supranational organisations to the killing of former [[Libya]]n leader [[Muammar Gaddafi]] at the [[Battle of Sirte (2011)|Battle of Sirte]], the last major engagement of the [[2011 Libyan civil war]], on 20 October 2011.

== International role in Gaddafi's downfall ==
{{main|2011 military intervention in Libya}}
{{seealso|United Nations Security Council Resolution 1970|United Nations Security Council Resolution 1973}}
The [[United Nations Security Council]] voted to authorize a [[Libyan no-fly zone]], as well as preventative strikes to stop [[Libyan Armed Forces|Gaddafi's forces]] from attacking Libya's civilian population, on 17 March 2011.&lt;ref name=&quot;U.N. News Centre&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.un.org/apps/news/story.asp?NewsID=37808&amp;Cr=libya&amp;Cr1= |title=Security Council Authorizes 'All Necessary Measures' To Protect Civilians in Libya |date=17 March 2011 |publisher = [[U.N. News Centre]] |accessdate=17 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, the [[French Air Force]] [[Second Battle of Benghazi|struck]] an armoured division and artillery pieces arrayed outside [[Benghazi]], the ''de facto'' capital of the [[National Transitional Council|interim rebel governing authority]], beginning [[2011 military intervention in Libya|international military operations in the Libyan theatre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Jonathan Marcus |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-12795971 |title=BBC News - Libya: French plane fires on military vehicle |publisher=Bbc.co.uk |date=2011-03-19 |accessdate=2011-09-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[NATO]] forces involved in [[Operation Unified Protector]], the codename for the military intervention in Libya, participated in the [[Battle of Sirte (2011)|Battle of Sirte]] in which Gaddafi was captured and killed. [[France|French]] and [[United States|U.S.]] aircraft struck the convoy in which Gaddafi was traveling, leaving him wounded and forcing him to abandon his attempted flight from the besieged city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dailymail&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2051782/How-NATO-air-strike-finished-Gaddafi.html |title=How a NATO air strike finished off Gaddafi |publisher=Dailymail |date=21 October 2011 |accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In an official statement, NATO claimed it was unaware that Gaddafi was part of the convoy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chu&quot;&gt;Henry Chu. &quot;[http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/world_now/2011/10/libya-nato-kadafi-convoy-airstrike.html NATO says it didn't know Kadafi was in targeted Libyan convoy]&quot; (21 October 2011). ''Los Angeles Times''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Reactions==
===National representatives===
====Africa====
*{{Flag|Côte d'Ivoire}}&amp;nbsp;– Minister of State, Foreign Minister [[Daniel Kablan Duncan]] said that Côte d'Ivoire was &quot;for dialogue and peace in Libya. But with regard to the death of Colonel Gaddafi must wait until all items before deciding&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.connectionivoirienne.net/?p=62648|title=Décès de Kadhafi (Libye) : Abidjan « attend d'avoir tous les éléments » avant de se prononcer|trans_title=Death of Gaddafi (Libya): Abidjan &quot;expects to have all the elements&quot; before deciding|publisher=connectionivoirienne.net|date=29 October 2011|accessdate=30 October 2011|language=French}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Ethiopia}}&amp;nbsp;– The spokesperson of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs said: “Gaddafi has not been part of the solution for Libyan crisis. So his death was the only option for the Libyan people. It’s the Libyan people who already overthrew him, so Ethiopian government respects the move and demand of the Libyan people”.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ezega.com/News/NewsDetails.aspx?Page=heads&amp;NewsID=3096|author=Yonas Abiye|title=Ethiopia Resented Gaddafi's Repeated Attempt to Move AU Headquarters to Libya|publisher=ezega.com|date=21 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Ghana}}&amp;nbsp;– Former president [[John Agyekum Kufuor]] siad that &quot;Gaddafi’s death is a historic sad day in Africa&quot; and &quot;showed that oppressed people would surely rise one day to demand accountability from their leaders.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ghanaweb.com/GhanaHomePage/NewsArchive/artikel.php?ID=222228|title=Kufuor In Tears For Gaddafi|publisher=GhanaWeb|date=24 October=|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Kenya}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Raila Odinga]] said that &quot;reign and life of one of Africa's most flamboyant leaders and one of AU's biggest financiers in a hail of bullets&quot; and criticized [[African Union]] for its &quot;inaction and its solidarity with African leaders in the face of excesses committed against own people&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.the-star.co.ke/national/national/46949-pm-flays-au-over-libya-crisis|author= Nzau Musau|title=PM flays AU over how it handled Libya crisis|date=31 October 2011|accessdate=31 October 2011|publisher=Ths Star&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Namibia}}&amp;nbsp;– The Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Utoni Nujoma]] said that &quot;we have witnessed was an extra-judicial killing of Gaddafi by the NTC [National Transitional Council] under the command of Nato.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.namibian.com.na/news/full-story/archive/2011/october/article/namibia-deplores-assassination/|author=Catherine Sasman|title=Namibia deplores ‘assassination’|publisher=The Namibian|date=24 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also the ex-president of Namibia [[Sam Nujoma]] said that &quot;foreign-sponsored killing of Libya’s Muammar Gaddafi must serve as a lesson to Africa that foreign aggressors are readying themselves to pounce on the continent.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newera.com.na/article.php?articleid=41337|author=Toivo Ndjebela|title=Nujoma condemns Gaddafi killing|date=26 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|publisher=New Era}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Nigeria}}&amp;nbsp;– Statement of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs said: &quot;Nigeria has taken cognisance of the death of Gaddafi. This happening vindicates our foresight and vision in taking the step to recognise the fledging NTC then.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ngrguardiannews.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=65117:ex-libyan-leaders-death-vindicates-nigeria-says-govt&amp;catid=1:national&amp;Itemid=559|author=Oghogho Obayuwana,Debo Olademeji, Kemi Amushan|title=Ex-Libyan Leader’s Death Vindicates Nigeria, Says Govt|publisher=The Guardian. Nigeria|date=22 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}The government was facing a strong opposition of media after the [[International recognition of the National Transitional Council|recognition of the NTC]] in August.&lt;/ref&gt; 

*{{Flag|South Africa}}&amp;nbsp;– The South African [[Department of International Relations and Cooperation]] said in a statement that it took notice of the death of Gaddafi and stated the South African government's view that &quot;a lasting and sustainable peaceful solution is possible through an all inclusive political process that will culminate in the holding of the first ever democratic elections&quot;. According to the statement, the government hoped that &quot;the latest events will lead to a cessation of hostilities and the restoration of peace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Media statement on the death of the former Libyan leader, Colonel Muammar Gaddafi |publisher=Government of South Africa |date=20 October 2011 |url=http://www.info.gov.za/speech/DynamicAction?pageid=461&amp;sid=22558&amp;tid=46726 |accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Sudan}}&amp;nbsp;– Minister of State [[Amin Hassan Omar Abdullah]] said that &quot;his (Gaddafi's) tragic death was expected and Sudan would be spared many problems.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.afriquejet.com/gaddafi-death-video-2011102125500.html|title=Gaddafi's death: Sudanese 'welcome' Gaddafi's death|publisher= Afrique en ligne|date=20 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Swaziland}}&amp;nbsp;– Many [[Senate of Swaziland|senators]] made condolences and agreed that country authorities should make condolences too.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.observer.org.sz/index.php?news=31462|author=Winile Masinga|title=Senators praise Gaddafi|publisher=The Swazi Observer|date=26 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Some sources published informations that Swaziland's monarch, [[Mswati III]], was upset hearing about death of Muammar Gaddafi, his close friend&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sabc.co.za/news/a/477294004915fdf9be6ebfbf69489bc3/Swaziland-cash-crunch-'critical',-Aids-spending-hit-20111116|title=Swaziland cash crunch 'critical', Aids spending hit|publisher=The South African Broadcasting Corporation News|date=16 November 2011|accessdate=17 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

*{{Flag|Tanzania}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Cooperation (Tanzania)|Foreign Minister]] [[Bernard Membe]] said that it is not Tanzanian culture to celebrate any death even of its enemies;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailynews.co.tz/home/?n=24756&amp;cat=home Gaddafi's death saddens Tanzania]&lt;/ref&gt; and that Tanzania was 'shocked and saddened' by the manner of [[Death of Muammar Gaddafi|Gaddafi's death]]. &quot;Although he is dead, our stance remains the same – that the fighting in Libya was wrong in the first place, and that it is going to be a big challenge to bring that country together.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://thecitizen.co.tz/news/2-international-news/16334-dar-condemns-gaddafi-killing Dar condemns Gaddafi killing]&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Uganda}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Yoweri Museveni]] described the death as a &quot;cowardly act by the National Transitional Council (NTC) leaders&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.monitor.co.ug/News/National/-/688334/1264684/-/bhfb23z/-/|author=Robert Muhereza|coauthors= John Njoroge|title=Museveni targets NRM ‘rebel’ MPs|date=31 October 2011|accessdate=31 October 2011|publisher=Dialy Monitor}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Zimbabwe}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Cairo Mhandu]], a member of the [[Parliament of Zimbabwe|Zimbabwean Parliament]] with President [[Robert Mugabe]]'s ruling [[Zimbabwe African National Union&amp;nbsp;– Patriotic Front]] (ZANU-PF) party, expressed grief over Gaddafi's death. &quot;This is a sad day for the people of Africa... Muammar Gaddafi won elections and was a true leader. It is foreigners who toppled him, not Libyans. Gaddafi died fighting. He is a true African hero.&quot; Mhandu called the former leader's downfall &quot;the beginning of a new recolonisation of Africa&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.globalpost.com/dispatches/globalpost-blogs/africa-emerges/gaddafi-dead-gaddafi-praised-african-hero-mugabe|agency=GlobalPost|date=20 October 2011|accessdate=20 October 2011|title=Gaddafi praised as &quot;an African hero&quot; by Mugabe's party|first=Andrew|last=Meldrum}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Asia====
*{{Flag|China}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China|Foreign Ministry]] spokeswoman [[Jiang Yu]], in a statement issued on the ministry's website, said that &quot;At the moment, Libya's history has turned a new page&quot; and expressed hope that the transition to an inclusive political process will start as soon as possible, (so as to) safeguard ethnic unity and national unity, restore social stability as soon as possible and rebuild the economy, so that citizens can lead happy and peaceful lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Reuters|url=http://af.reuters.com/article/commoditiesNews/idAFL3E7LL06P20111021|title=China urges &quot;inclusive&quot; political transition in Libya|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|India}}&amp;nbsp;– While India refrained from reacting officially to the death of Muammar Gaddafi, a joint statement issued after his death by [[Minister of External Affairs (India)|India's External Affairs minister]] [[S M Krishna]] and his French counterpart, [[Alain Juppé]], in New Delhi, declared that the two countries support the efforts of the National Transition Council representing the Libyan people as a whole, to establish democratic institutions in a free Libya, to promote human rights, and to rebuild their country after the sufferings they have endured.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=The Economic Times|url=http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics/nation/muammar-gaddafi-dead-india-offers-to-rebuild-liberated-libya/articleshow/10437192.cms|title=Muammar Gaddafi dead: India offers to rebuild liberated Libya|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[File:Kashmir independent.svg|border|22px]] [[Kashmir]]&amp;nbsp;– [[Jammu Kashmir Liberation Front]] Chairman [[Yasin Malikhis]] said that Gaddafi's means that &quot;the people of Kashmir have lost their friend&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://paktribune.com/news/Gaddafis-death-a-loss-for-Kashmir-Yasin-Malik-244576.html|title=Gaddafi's death a loss for Kashmir: Yasin Malik|date=23 October 2011|accessdate=12 November 2011|publisher|Pakistan Tribune}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

*{{Flag|Iran}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Foreign Affairs Minister of Iran|Foreign Minister]] [[Ali Akbar Salehi]] congratulated the Libyan people and National Transitional Council officials and said that Iran is ready to help to build a &quot;new and democratic Libya&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Tabnak|url=http://www.tabnak.ir/fa/news/198542/%D8%A7%DB%8C%D8%B1%D8%A7%D9%86-%D8%A8%D9%87-%D9%85%D9%84%D8%AA-%D9%84%DB%8C%D8%A8%DB%8C-%D8%AA%D8%A8%D8%B1%DB%8C%DA%A9-%DA%AF%D9%81%D8%AA|title=Fri, 21 Oct 2011, 07:00 GMT+3:30&amp;nbsp;– Iran|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Iraq}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Nouri al-Maliki]] hailed the killing of Gaddafi, saying, &quot;We congratulate our Libyan brothers and the [National] Transitional Council on the occasion of getting rid of the tyrant Gaddafi, who ran Libya for four decades filled with oppression.&quot; Maliki compared Gaddafi's death to that of former Iraqi strongman [[Saddam Hussein]], found in similar conditions during the [[Iraq War]] eight years earlier. &quot;The similarity of the fate of tyrants in Iraq and Libya and elsewhere is proof of the potential of the people to defeat dictators, however long they have been in power,&quot; Maliki said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=Al Jazeera Blogs|url=http://blogs.aljazeera.net/liveblog/iraq-oct-20-2011-2056|title=Thu, 20 Oct 2011, 18:56 GMT+3&amp;nbsp;– Iraq|accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Gaddafi's death Iraqi security forces having the documents forwarded by [[Mahmoud Jibril]] at his unexpected visit to [[Baghdad]] on 16 October arrested more than 200 suspects, former members of [[Saddam Hussein]]'s military and [[Baath Party]], of plotting with Gaddafi to overthrow the [[Cabinet of Iraq|Iraqi federal government]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tehrantimes.com/index.php/middle-east/4030-gaddafi-plotted-iraq-coup-with-baathists|title=Gaddafi plotted Iraq coup with Baathists|publisher=Tehran Times|date=28 October 2011|accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Israel}}&amp;nbsp;– Undisclosed senior government officials were quoted as saying that &quot;there is no reason for Israel to be sorry over the loss of Gaddafi&quot; as Muammar Gaddafi &quot;supported terror and advocated terror against Israelis all over the world&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.jpost.com/Headlines/Article.aspx?id=242502|title=Israelis not sorry Muammar Gaddafi is dead|work=[[Jerusalem Post]]|date=2011-10-20|accessdate=2011-10-28|quote=Jerusalem has not yet made an official statement about reports on Thursday from Libya that Muammar Gaddafi was killed, but senior officials have told reporters that there is no reason for Israel to be sorry over the loss of Gaddafi, Israel Radio reported.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Kuwait}}&amp;nbsp;– Minister of State for Cabinet Affairs, Acting Foreign Minister and the official spokesman of the Government, Ali Al-Rashed, expressed, in a statement, hope that the end of Gaddafi's regime would constitute start of a new chapter in the history of the Libyan people for realizing their aspirations for security, stability and prosperity. The government spokesman called on the Libyans to unite and back the Transitional Council in its efforts for establishing a new ruling system, based on justice, equality and respect for legitimate rights of the people. He affirmed Kuwait's support for the Libyan people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=http://www.kuna.net.kw/NewsAgenciesPublicSite/ArticleDetails.aspx?id=2197883&amp;Language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Lebanon}}&amp;nbsp;– Speaker of the [[Lebanese Parliament]] [[Nabih Berri]] welcomed Gaddafi's death issuing a statement reading &quot;God's justice will come, sooner or later.&quot; Former Prime Minister [[Saad Hariri]] also welcomed the demise of Gaddafi stating &quot;The end of Muammar Gaddafi is the inevitable end of all tyrants who are facing their people's will for freedom and democracy with killing, repression and blood.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|agency=The Daily Star Lebanon|url=http://www.dailystar.com.lb/News/Politics/2011/Oct-21/151850-rival-lebanese-leaders-hailgadhafis-death.ashx#axzz1bPE3Tgri|title=Rival Lebanese leaders hail Gadhafi's death|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Oman}}&amp;nbsp;– On 27 October the Sultanate of Oman offered the Gaddafi family asylum.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spanish.ruvr.ru/2011/10/27/59470952.html|title=Sultanato de Omán dispuesto a recibir a familiares de Gadafi|trans_title=Sultanate of Oman offered Gadafi family asylum|date=27 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|language=Spanish|publisher=La Voz de Rusia}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Philippines}}&amp;nbsp;– The Department of Foreign Relations congratulated Libyan people &quot;their latest victory and the total liberation of Libya.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gmanews.tv/story/236138/nation/phl-govt-wishes-lasting-peace-stability-for-new-libya|author=Kimberly Jane Tan|title=PHL govt wishes lasting peace, stability for 'new Libya'|date= 21 October 2011|accessdate=29 October 2011|publisher=GMA News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Sri Lanka}}&amp;nbsp;– In a statement [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Sri Lanka)|Ministry of External Affairs of Sri Lanka]] called for probe in case of Gaddafi's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ibnlive.in.com/news/sri-lanka-calls-for-probe-on-gaddafi-death/195709-2.html|title=Sri Lanka calls for probe on Gaddafi death|date=23 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|publisher=IBN Live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Yemen}}&amp;nbsp;– Abdul Janadi, deputy information minister and government's spokesman, told [[Xinhua]] news agency on Friday that the Yemeni government should not be busy with the death of Gaddafi at a time when it was trying to lift the country out of the current crisis.&lt;ref&gt;Gaddafi's death may influence political crisis in Yemen, Xinhua, 22/10/2011&lt;/ref&gt;

====Europe====
*{{Flag|Albania}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Bamir Topi]] and Prime Minister [[Sali Berisha]] described Gaddafi's death as an event that meant the end of the war in Libya. The president declared that the war had left behind great suffering, but ended one of the longest dictatorships in the world. Topi added that a clear perspective of peace and democracy lies ahead for Libya. Berisha expressed his pleasure for the end of the Libyan conflict, although he declared that it would have been better if Gaddafi was caught alive and brought to justice. Berisha considered Gaddafi's elimination as a much-expected event for the Libyan people and the entire world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.top-channel.tv/english/artikull.php?id=3248 |title=Albanian President and PM react on Libya – Top Channel (In English) |publisher=Top-channel.tv |accessdate=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.keshilliministrave.al/?fq=brenda&amp;m=news&amp;lid=15288&amp;gj=gj1 |title=Prime Minister of Albania web site (in Albanian) |language={{sq icon}} |publisher=Keshilliministrave.al |accessdate=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Austria}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Foreign Minister of Austria|Foreign Minister]] [[Michael Spindelegger]] said that he was relieved because the bloodshed would now come to an end.&lt;ref name=&quot;standard-reaction&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://derstandard.at/1318726404940/Reaktionen-Gefuehl-der-Erleichterung |title=Reaktionen: &quot;Gefühl der Erleichterung&quot; |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011 |language=German |publisher=Der Standard}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Belarus}}&amp;nbsp;– In response to the death of Muammar Gaddafi the president of Belarus [[Alexander Lukashenko]] started to militarize the state apparatus and society to repel the expected attack. He also directly responded to the death: &quot; He was tortured, shot, raped when was wounded, his head and hand twisted. They tortured him to death! They treated him worse than the nazis.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://wyborcza.pl/1,75477,10593670,Po_smierci_Kaddafiego_Lukaszenka_szykuje_sie_na_wojne.html|author Andrzej Poczobut|title= Po śmierci Kaddafiego Łukaszenka szykuje się na wojnę|trans_title= After the death of Gaddafi, Lukashenko is getting ready for war is preparing for war|publisher=Gazeta Wyborcza|date=5 October 2011|accessdate=5 October 2011|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt;  

*{{Flag|Bulgaria}}&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Minister [[Nikolay Mladenov]] said that Gaddafi's death marks the beginning of a new era in Libya with her future in the hands of the Libyan people.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa.bg/bg/news/view/31900 По повод новината за смъртта на Муамар Кадафи, министърът на външните работи Николай Младенов заяви:] (in Bulgarian), Foreign Ministry of Bulgaria, 20 October 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Czech Republic}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Petr Necas]] told that &quot;death of toppled former long-standing Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi proves that the crimes dictators commit in relation to their own nations do not go unpunished&quot;. Also the Ministry of Foreign Affairs expressed its &quot; hope that by the death of Muammar Gaddafi the bloodshed in Libya is now finally coming to an end&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.anhourago.eu/show.aspx?l=35913975&amp;d=504|title=Dictators' crimes do not go unpunished, PM reacts to Gaddafi's death|publisher=Prague Daily Monitor|date=21 October 2011|accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Denmark}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Helle Thorning-Schmidt]] said that it is a historic day in the Libyan people's struggle for freedom and democracy. She fully understands the happiness of the Libyan people, and says that Denmark is ready to support the Libyan people.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=I forbindelse med oberst Gaddafis død udtaler statsminister Helle Thorning-Schmidt:|url=http://www.statsministeriet.dk/_p_13533.html|publisher=Statsministeriet|accessdate=21 October 2011|language=Danish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|France}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of France|President]] [[Nicolas Sarkozy]] called Gaddafi's death a milestone in the Libyan people's battle &quot;to free themselves from the dictatorial and violent regime that was imposed on them for more than 40 years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2011/10/20/501364/main20123328.shtml &quot;Gaddafi's death met with little sadness&quot;] ''CBS News''&amp;nbsp;– 20 October 2011. Retrieved 20 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Germany}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Chancellor of Germany|Chancellor]] [[Angela Merkel]] said that this is an important day for Libya and a new peaceful beginning is possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;standard-reaction&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://derstandard.at/1318726404940/Reaktionen-Gefuehl-der-Erleichterung|title=Reaktionen: &quot;Gefühl der Erleichterung&quot; |date=20 October 2011|accessdate=20 October 2011|language=German|publisher=Der Standard}}&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;With this, a bloody war comes to an end, which Gaddafi led against his own people. Libya must now quickly take further resolute steps towards democracy and make the achievements so far of the Arab Spring irreversible.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aj-reaction&quot; /&gt;

* {{Flag|Hungary}} – Foreign Minister [[János Martonyi]] said that Gaddafi's death means the end of decades of tyranny and opens a new chapter in the [[history of Libya]]. He also stated that Hungary ready to continue to have played a key role to contribute to the creation of a democratic Libya.&lt;ref name=&quot;kormanyhu&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.kormany.hu/hu/kulugyminiszterium/hirek/martonyi-janos-kulugyminiszter-nyilatkozata |title=Martonyi János külügyminiszter nyilatkozata |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011 |language=Hungarian |publisher=Hungarian Ministry of Foreign Affairs}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Italy}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Silvio Berlusconi]] reacted to reports of Gaddafi's death by saying &quot;[[Sic transit gloria mundi]]&quot; (thus passes the glory of the world) and that now &quot;the war is over.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=News of Gadhafi's Death Met With Relief |agency=[[Associated Press]] &amp;amp; [[Thomson Reuters|Reuters]] |publisher=[[Voice of America|VOA News]] |date=20 October 2011 |url= http://www.voanews.com/english/news/africa/Reports-of-Gadhafis-Death-Met-with-Relief--132240193.html |accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{flag|Kosovo}} – [[President of Kosovo|President]] [[Atifete Jahjaga]] said Gaddafi's death was a triumph for Libyans &quot;over the forces of evil&quot; and said it marked &quot;the end of a tragic and difficult chapter for the people and the opening of the new perspective for the progress and development of democracy in Libya&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.president-ksgov.net/?page=2,6,2032 STATEMENT OF THE OFFICE OF THE PRESIDENT OF KOSOVO REGARDING THE TERMINATION OF THE CONFLICT IN LIBYA]&lt;/ref&gt; Prime Minister [[Hashim Thaçi]] called the event &quot;a victory of peace in the world&quot; and said it meant the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kryeministri-ks.net/?page=1,9,2411 Statement by the Prime Minister of the Republic of Kosovo, Mr. Hashim Thaci (in Albanian)]&lt;/ref&gt; The Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Enver Hoxhaj]], sent on behalf of the Government of Kosovo, a letter of congratulations to the National Council of Libya and congratulated the people of Libya on the liberation of the country from the totalitarian regime of Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mfa-ks.net/?page=2,4,992 Government of Kosovo congratulates Libyan people over their liberation from Gaddafi regime, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Kosovo]&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Malta}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Lawrence Gonzi]] reacted to reports of Gaddafi's death by saying that, &quot;Gaddafi's death marks a new beginning for Libya&quot; and that “The Maltese will help according to our capabilities&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gaddafi's death marks a new beginning for Libya&amp;nbsp;– PM |url=http://www.timesofmalta.com/articles/view/20111020/local/pm-gaddafi.390033 |publisher=The Times (Malta) |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Netherlands}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Prime Minister of the Netherlands]] [[Mark Rutte]] said the people of Libya had opened themselves up to great personal danger by rebelling against Gaddafi’s rule. &quot;We would have rather saw that he had been called to account for his crimes in The Hague. In any case, let us hope the others who are being sought can be brought before the international criminal court.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Gaddafi death: Dutch politicians regret he will not be prosecuted |url=http://www.dutchnews.nl/news/archives/2011/10/dutch_politicians_regret_gadda.php |publisher=DutchNews.nl |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Norway}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Jens Stoltenberg]] reacted to reports of Gaddafi's death by saying that, &quot;this is a turning point for Libya&quot; and that “Now it is all about making a democratic Lybia. Although Gaddafi's death is not a guarantee for that, it is a good basis&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Stoltenberg: – Et vendepunkt for Libya&amp;nbsp;– PM |url=http://www.abcnyheter.no/nyheter/2011/10/20/stoltenberg-et-vendepunkt-libya |publisher=ABC Nyheter (Norwegien) |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Poland}}&amp;nbsp;– In an announcement, the [[Polish Foreign Ministry]] expressed hope of upcoming peace and democracy in Libya and that &quot;We regret that falling dictator, to defend his power, plunged the country into a civil war, in which tens of thousands of Libyans died.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |title=Oświadczenie MSZ po śmierci płk. Kadafiego |language=Polish |publisher=[[Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Poland)]] |date=20 October 2011 |url=http://www.msz.gov.pl/Oswiadczenie,MSZ,po,smierci,plk.,Kadafiego,46181.html |accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Russia}}&amp;nbsp;– Special envoy [[Mikhail Margelov]] warned that the war could continue in spite of Gaddafi's death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://english.ruvr.ru/2011/10/20/59075793.html |agency=The Voice of Russia |title=Libyan war can go on without Gaddafi&amp;nbsp;– Russia's envoy |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Foreign Minister [[Sergei Lavrov]] said the killing of Gaddafi violated the [[Geneva Conventions]] prohibiting summary execution of [[prisoner of war|prisoners of war]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/gaddafis-death-breached-the-law-says-russia-2374250.html|agency=The Independent|date=22 October 2011|first=Shaun|last=Walker|title=Gaddafi's death breached the law, says Russia|accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Prime Minister [[Vladimir Putin]] expressed &quot;disgust&quot; over videos of Gaddafi's death and said, &quot;There is nothing good that all these scenes were demonstrated on the screens and millions of people, including children, saw that.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.xinhuanet.com/english2010/world/2011-10/27/c_122202127.htm|agency=Xinhua|title=Putin voices disgust at TV broadcasting of Gaddafi's death|date=27 October 2011|accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Spain}}&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Minister [[Trinidad Jiménez]] has appealed for reconciliation and offered Spain's assistance in the forthcoming peace process in Libya.  She also called for those responsible for crimes to be made accountable.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thinkspain.com/news-spain/20247/spanish-foreign-minister-reacts-to-gadhafis-death &quot;Spanish Foreign Minister reacts to Gadhafi's death&quot;]&amp;nbsp;– Think Spain&amp;nbsp;– 21 October 2011. Retrieved 21 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Turkey}}&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Minister [[Ahmet Davutoglu]] said, &quot;The fate of Gaddafi and his regime constitutes a bitter lesson that should be reviewed carefully regarding the movements of change and transformation in the region&quot;.{{cn|date=October 2011}}

*{{Flag|United Kingdom}}&amp;nbsp;– [[British Prime Minister]] [[David Cameron]] said &quot;we should also remember the many, many Libyans who died at the hands of this brutal dictator and his regime&quot; and that &quot;people in Libya today have an even greater chance, after this news, of building themselves a strong and democratic future.&quot; [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|Foreign Secretary]] [[William Hague]] expressed regret that Gaddafi was killed before he could be brought to trial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-15387273 |title=David Cameron: Remember Colonel Gaddafi Libya victims |date=20 October 2011 |work=BBC News  |accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Defence Secretary [[Philip Hammond]] said that Gaddafi's death left the reputation of the NTC &quot;a little bit stained&quot;, adding, &quot;It's certainly not the way we do things. We would have liked to see Gaddafi going on trial to answer for his misdeeds.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;harding&quot;/&gt;

*{{flag|Vatican City}}&amp;nbsp;– A statement was released by the [[Holy See Press Office]], saying that Gaddafi's death &quot;closes an overly long and tragic phase of the bloody fight for the overthrow of a hard and oppressive regime.&quot; It continues that it shows &quot;the immense human suffering that accompanies the affirmation and the collapse of every system that is not based on the respect and dignity of the person, but on the prevailing assertion of power.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.catholicnewsagency.com/news/vatican-voices-hope-for-libya-after-ghadafis-death/|title=Vatican voices hope for Libya after Ghadafi's death|agency=[[Catholic News Agency]]|date=20 October 2011|accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====North America====

*{{Flag|Canada}}&amp;nbsp;– [[Prime Minister of Canada|Prime Minister]] [[Stephen Harper]] heralded the day's developments, saying Gaddafi will &quot;never again be in a position to support terrorism or to allow others to fire on his own citizens.&quot;  &quot;The people of Libya can finally turn the page after 42 years of a chapter of terrible oppression, and it can now seek a better future,&quot; he said from the foyer of the [[House of Commons of Canada|House of Commons]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Libya's Moammar Gadhafi killed |publisher=CBC News |date=20 October 2011 |url=http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/story/2011/10/20/libya-gadhafi-capture.html |accessdate=21 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Costa Rica}}&amp;nbsp;– The Ministry of Foreign Affairs after expressed &quot;hope that the death of former Libyan leader, Muammar Gaddafi, allow the reconciliation of that African nation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://spanish.peopledaily.com.cn/31617/7622852.html|title=Costa Rica aboga por reconciliación en Libia tras muerte de Gadafi|trans_title= Costa Rica calls for reconciliation in Libya after Gadhafi's death|publisher=People's Daily (Spanish Edition)|date=21 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Cuba}}&amp;nbsp;– On 23 October [[Fidel Castro]] condemned the assassination of Muammar Gaddafi, and the genocidal role of NATO. He added also that &quot;Gaddafi's body has been kidnapped and displayed as a trophy of war, conduct that violates the most elementary principles of Islamic rules and other religious beliefs prevailing in the world.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cdn.com.mx/sitio2/?p=1306|title=Fidel Castro condena el asesinato del coronel|trans_title=Fidel Castro condemned the murder of Colonel|publisher=cdn.com.mx|language=Spanish|date=24 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Dominica}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Roosevelt Skerrit]]  on 23 September said &quot;Like any civilised society we will never condone the manner in which a person is killed. We will never tolerate it, irrespective of who the person is, or what the person may have done, or alleged to have done. Extra judicial killings should never be supported or promoted by any civilised nation.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dominica&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://go-jamaica.com/news/read_article.php?id=32741|title=Dominica PM condemns Gaddafi’s killing|publisher=Go-Jamaica|date=24 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Grenada}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Tillman Thomas]] named Gaddafi’s death as “unfortunate”.&lt;ref name=&quot;Dominica&quot;/&gt;

*{{Flag|Mexico}}&amp;nbsp;– In statement Foreign Ministry said that &quot;in light of the events today in Libya and the death of Colonel Muammar Gaddafi, Mexico hopes to soon restore peace in that country, begin a process of national reconciliation and generate the conditions to build an inclusive government.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.noticiassin.com/2011/10/mexico-espera-que-se-restablezca-la-paz-en-libia-tras-la-muerte-de-gadaffi/|title=México espera que se restablezca la paz en Libia tras la muerte de Gadaffi|trans_title=Mexico hopes that peace is restored in Libya after Gadhafi's death|date=20 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Panama}}&amp;nbsp;– Panama Foreign Ministry through a statement said that the death of Muammar Gaddafi opens a &quot;new era of dignity and democracy&quot; in Libya and hoped that [[National Transitional Council]] will create a government - &quot;product of elections free and fair.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://noticias.emisorasunidas.com/noticias/internacionales/panama-dice-que-muerte-gadafi-abre-una-nueva-era-dignidad-libertad-libia|title=Panamá dice que la muerte de Gadafi abre una nueva era de dignidad y libertad en Libia|trans_title= Panama says Gaddafi's death marks a new era of dignity and freedom in Libya|date=21 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Saint Lucia}}&amp;nbsp;– Foreign Minister [[Rufus Bousquet]] said that Gaddafi will be missed because of his &quot;using his money for investment in Africa in the development of the African world and the Caribbean.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dominica&quot;/&gt;

*{{Flag|United States}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Barack Obama]] gave a press conference, confirming the death of Gaddafi, and said that &quot;the shadow of tyranny over Libya has been lifted&quot;, but also added &quot;we're under no delusions; Libya has a long and winding road ahead of it towards democracy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://content.usatoday.com/communities/theoval/post/2011/10/obama-team-tracks-news-of-gadhafi/1 |title=Obama: Gadhafi regime is 'no more' |author=David Jackson |work=USA Today |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Secretary of State [[Hillary Rodham Clinton]] said her government would have preferred to see Gaddafi tried and called for a joint [[United Nations|UN]]–Libyan investigation into how he died in custody.&lt;ref name=&quot;harding&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/oct/23/gaddafi-will-libya|title=Gaddafi's will tells Libyans: we chose confrontation as a badge of honour|first=Luke|last=Harding|agency=The Guardian|date=23 October 2011|accessdate=23 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Oceania====
*{{Flag|Australia}}&amp;nbsp;– Prime Minister [[Julia Gillard]] said the fall of [[Sirte]] and the death of Gaddafi marked &quot;a day of relief in Libya as the long war of liberation comes to an end&quot;. She expressed Australian support for Libya's [[National Transitional Council|NTC]] in the transitional phase. She said she was ready to help Libya's new leaders work towards peace and stability in the wake of the former leader's death. Foreign Minister [[Kevin Rudd]] called for the events to mark an end to violence in Libya.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-10-21/gillard-abbott-on-gaddafi-death/3590956|agency=Australian Broadcasting Corporation|title=Gaddafi death brings 'relief' to Libya: Gillard|date=21 October 2011|accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====South America====
*{{Flag|Brazil}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of Brazil|President]] [[Dilma Rousseff]] said &quot;I think Libya is going through a process of democratic transformation. However, that does not mean we should celebrate the death of a leader. The fact that Libya is going through a democratic process ought not be 'celebrated', but rather supported and given incentive and, in fact, what we want is that [all] countries have the capacity, internally, to live in peace and with democracy.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://zerohora.clicrbs.com.br/zerohora/jsp/default.jsp?uf=1&amp;local=1&amp;section=Mundo&amp;newsID=a3533554.xml|title=Dilma diz que não se deve comemorar a morte de um líder e que Líbia merece apoio na transição|language=Portuguese|date=20 October 2011|work=Zero Hora|accessdate=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Chile}}&amp;nbsp;– Minister of Foreign Affairs [[Alfredo Moreno]] said that Gaddafi's death &quot;creates an opportunity for peace&quot; and progress in Libya. He added: &quot;He had requested an arrest warrant, and would been better if he had been before the courts, but these are the things that happen when there is war&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lanacion.cl/chile-muerte-de-gadafi-crea-una-oportunidad-para-la-paz/noticias/2011-10-20/195650.html|title=Chile: Muerte de Gadafi “crea una oportunidad para la paz”|trans_title=Chile: Death of Gaddafi &quot;creates an opportunity for peace&quot;|publisher=Nación|date=20 Octobre 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Colombia}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Juan Manuel Santos]] stated in a declaration from the [[Palace of Nariño]] that &quot;With the death of Gaddafi, we hope Libya can return to normal as soon as possible, that democracy and freedom can finally prevail.&quot; The mandatary also trusted that &quot;the Libyans are responsible for their own future and that they become aware of their own country and that they can prosper in peace.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Que regrese la libertad y la democracia en Libia|url=http://www.eltiempo.com/mundo/africa/muerte-de-muamar-gadafi_10599785-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Ecuador}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Rafael Correa]] called Gaddafi's death &quot;murder&quot; and said he was &quot;executed&quot;. Correa demanded that the UN investigate Gaddafi's death as well as the deaths of [[Moatassem Gaddafi]] and the earlier deaths of [[Saif al-Arab Gaddafi]] and two of Gaddafi's grandchildren in [[Tripoli]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://en.mercopress.com/2011/10/24/ecuador-president-condemns-killing-of-gaddafi-and-family-members-as-homicide|agency=MercoPress South Atlantic News Agency|title=Ecuador president condemns killing of Gaddafi and family members as ‘homicide’|date=24 October 2011|accessdate=26 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{flag|Uruguay}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Jose Mujica]] said that Gaddafi's death &quot;seems that nation have no right to self-determination.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uypress.net/hnnoticiaj1.aspx?21199,58|title=Mujica opinó sobre la muerte de Muamar Gadafi|trans_title=Mujica's opinion about the death of Muamaf Gadafi|publisher=Agencia uruguaya de noticias|date=25 October 2011|accessdate=28 October 2011|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Venezuela}}&amp;nbsp;– President [[Hugo Chávez]] told the AFP, &quot;We shall remember Gaddafi our whole lives as a great fighter, a revolutionary and a martyr. They assassinated him. It is another outrage.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=As it happened: Libya's Col Gaddafi killed|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-15387872|accessdate=20 October 2011|newspaper=BBC |date=20 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intergovernmental organizations===
====Regional communities====
* [[File:Flag African Union.svg|border|25px]] [[African Union]]&amp;nbsp;– African Union officials said that it had lifted the suspension of Libya's membership and it would allow the NTC to fill the Libyan seat in the Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;aj-reaction&quot;&gt;{{cite new |url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/10/20111020135216487214.html |title=Gaddafi's death: World reaction |date=20 October 2011 |accessdate=20 October 2011 |publisher=Al Jazeera}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Arab League}}&amp;nbsp;– Arab League [[Secretary-General]] [[Nabil al-Arabi]] said that he hoped the death of ousted Libyan leader Muammar Gaddafi and all the other Arabs' leaders, who ruled with an iron fist.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vanguardngr.com/2011/10/arab-league-hopes-gaddafi-death-turns-page-of-tyranny/ &quot;Arab League hopes Gaddafi death ‘turns page of tyranny’&quot;]&amp;nbsp;– ''Vanguard''&amp;nbsp;– 20 October 2011. Retrieved 21 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|Caribbean Community}}&amp;nbsp;– CARICOM Chairman [[Denzil L. Douglas]] said Gaddafi's death &quot;marks the end of a painful and tumultuous chapter for the people of Libya who have endured a protracted conflict in that country over the past eight months&quot;. He called for the NTC, NATO, and the UN Security Council to oversee the establishment of a lasting peace and a democratic civil state. Douglas also expressed concern over &quot;the widespread reports of violations of human rights against former members of the Libyan government and minority groups, including migrants from Sub-Saharan countries&quot; on behalf of CARICOM.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.caricom.org/jsp/pressreleases/press_releases_2011/pres387_11.jsp|agency=Caribbean Community (CARICOM) Secretariat|title=`LAY DOWN ARMS IN PEACE’ – CARICOM CHAIRMAN URGES PEOPLE OF LIBYA|date=24 October 2011|accessdate=25 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*{{Flag|European Union}}&amp;nbsp;– [[President of the European Council]] [[Herman Van Rompuy]] said, &quot;The death of Gaddafi marks the end of an era of despotism. That Gaddafi died in a raid in Sirte means an end also to the repression from which the Libyan people have suffered for too long.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aj-reaction&quot; /&gt;

==== NATO ====
The top officer of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, Admiral [[James G. Stavridis]], [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe|Supreme Allied Commander Europe]], announced that he will recommend that the alliance's Libya air campaign be brought to an end.&lt;ref name=Stavridis&gt;&quot;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-202_162-20123633/nato-commander-to-recommend-libya-mission-end/ NATO commander to recommend Libya mission end]&quot; (21 October 2011). Associated Press.&lt;/ref&gt; Officials have said the alliance would likely continue its air patrols over Libya for several more days and then be gradually phased out.&lt;ref name=Stavridis/&gt;

NATO Secretary-General [[Anders Fogh Rasmussen]] said in a statement that &quot;NATO and our partners have successfully implemented the historic mandate of the United Nations to protect the people of Libya. We will terminate our mission in co-ordination with the United Nations and the National Transitional Council. With the reported fall of Bani Walid and Sirte, that moment has now moved much closer.&quot; The [[North Atlantic Council]], the governing body of NATO, will meet on 21 October to officially terminate the seven-month campaign.&lt;ref name=Cloud&gt;David S. Cloud.&quot; [http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/world_now/2011/10/libya-nato-airstrikes.html NATO commander expected to recommend ending Libya airstrikes]&quot; (20 October 2011).&lt;/ref&gt;

NATO defense ministers, meeting in [[Brussels]] earlier in October, decided not to halt air operations. However, following Gaddafi's death and the NTC's taking of Sirt, the last city under Gaddafi's control, NATO is likely to officially end the campaign. And the [[Intergovernmental organization|inter-governmental military alliance]] is now expected to bring the campaign to an end. While only suspending airstrikes and beginning a monitoring period was considered, a NATO officer speaking to the ''[[Los Angeles Times]]'' on condition of anonymity stated that the sentiment within NATO is to end the campaign entirely, including the enforcement of the [[no-fly zone]] and the [[arms embargo]] enforced by naval ships.&lt;ref name=Cloud/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stavridis/&gt;

The death of Gaddafi and end of the campaign was viewed as a &quot;rare clear-cut victory&quot; for NATO after long operations in [[Afghanistan]] and [[Piracy in Somalia|anti-piracy patrols off Somalia]]. According to Michael Clarke, director of the London-based [[Royal United Services Institute]] [[think tank]], &quot;NATO can say unambiguously this was a military and political success. That's why today is a good day for NATO, and NATO has not had many good days in the last several years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/middle-east/end-of-libyan-aerial-campaign-is-rare-victory-for-embattled-nato/2011/10/20/gIQADFQM1L_story.html End of Libyan aerial campaign is rare victory for embattled NATO]&quot; (20 October 2011). Associated Press.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Julian E. Barnes and Adam Entous. &quot;[http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203752604576643531745513712.html NATO Air Strategy Gains Renewed Praise: Alliance Action Was Beset by Skepticism and Logistical Shortcomings, but Many Call It Template for Future Interventions]&quot; (21 October 2011). ''Wall Street Journal''.&lt;/ref&gt;

NATO announced that its mission will end on 31 October 2011. Rasmussen said that NATO will make sure that there would be no attacks against civilians during that transition period.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc22&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-15412529 |title=Libya: Muammar Gaddafi's body to undergo post-mortem |publisher=BBC  |date=22 October 2011 |accessdate=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== United Nations ====
[[Secretary-General of the United Nations|UN Secretary-General]] [[Ban Ki-moon]] stated that &quot;This day marks a historic transition for Libya. In the coming days, we will witness scenes of celebration as well as grief for those who lost so much. Now is the time for all Libyans to come together. Libyans can only realise the promise of the future for national unity and reconciliation. Combatants on all sides must lay down their arms in peace. This is the time for healing and rebuilding, for generosity of spirit, not for revenge.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;aj-reaction&quot; /&gt;

Rupert Colville, spokesperson for the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights, said in a briefing: &quot;As you are aware, there are at least two cell-phone videos, one showing him alive and one showing him dead. Taken together, these videos are very disturbing. We believe there is a need for an investigation and more details are needed to ascertain whether he was killed in the fighting or after his capture&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=11520&amp;LangID=E Briefing note on Libya]&lt;/ref&gt;. [[Christof Heyns]], the [[United Nations Special Rapporteur]] on extrajudicial, summary or arbitrary executions, called for an international investigation into Gaddafi's death, stating that his killing may have been a [[war crime]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=UN calls for probe into Gaddafi's death|url=http://english.aljazeera.net/news/africa/2011/10/20111021235116164421.html|publisher=[[Al Jazeera]]|accessdate=25 October 2011|date=22 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Non-governmental organizations ===
*[[Amnesty International]]&amp;nbsp;– The [[London]]-based [[human rights]] group immediately called for &quot;a full, independent and impartial inquiry&quot; into Gaddafi's death and said other former regime members and fighters should be treated &quot;humanely&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-202_162-20123505/amnesty-inquiry-needed-into-qaddafis-death/|agency=CBS News|date=20 October 2011|accessdate=23 October 2011|title=Amnesty: Inquiry needed into Qaddafi's death}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*[[File:Hrw logo.svg|20px]] [[Human Rights Watch]]&amp;nbsp;– The group reviewed documentary materials of Gaddafi's capture and corpse and concluded that he and others &quot;might have been executed after being detained&quot;. The organisation called for an investigation, with official [[Sarah Leah Whitson]] saying, &quot;Finding out how they died matters.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;harding&quot;/&gt;

== Regional ramifications ==

In its immediate aftermath, the killing of Gaddafi was thought to have significant implications in North Africa and the Middle East, as a critical part of the &quot;[[Arab Spring]]&quot;. Pundits speculated that the death would intensify protesting in [[Syria]] and [[Yemen]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily Beast Next&quot;/&gt; and French officials stated that because of this they were &quot;watching the Algerian situation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Daily Beast Next&quot;&gt;[http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2011/10/20/qaddafi-s-death-send-clear-message-to-middle-east-dictators-run-will-algiers-be-next.html &quot;Which Middle East Dictator Is Going Down Next?&quot;] World News – ''The Daily Beast -'' 20 October 2011 – 20 October 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[International reactions to the 2011 Libyan civil war]]
*[[International reactions to the 2011 military intervention in Libya]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{2011 Libyan protests}}
{{Muammar Gaddafi}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:International Reactions To The Death Of Muammar Gaddafi}}
[[Category:2011 Libyan civil war]]
[[Category:Muammar Gaddafi]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of Libya]]

[[fa:بازتاب جهانی مرگ معمر قذافی]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
