<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3353234" ns="0" title="Eddie Eagle"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the NRA's safety program|the British ski-jumper|Eddie 'the Eagle' Edwards}}

{{multiple issues|lead too short=November 2010|original research=November 2010|primarysources=November 2010|refimprove=November 2010}}
{{No footnotes|date=November 2010}}
The '''Eddie Eagle''' program and its namesake character were developed by the [[National Rifle Association]] for [[child]]ren who are generally considered too young to be allowed to handle [[firearms]].  While maturity levels vary, the Eddie Eagle program is intended for children of any age from pre-school through third grade.

== Training program ==
The program trains children to avoid causing harm when they encounter firearms, through an easily-remembered litany:

* '''Stop''' &amp;mdash; to take time to remember the rest of the instructions.
* '''Don't touch''' &amp;mdash; A firearm that is not touched or acted upon by an outside force is highly unlikely to fire, or endanger a person.
* '''Leave the area''' &amp;mdash; By leaving the area the child removes himself/herself from temptation, as well as from the danger that another person might pick up the gun and negligently cause it to fire.
* '''Tell an adult''' &amp;mdash; An adult, if not personally trained in handling firearms, should know enough to seek professional assistance.

The NRA, which also sponsors training for adults in safe gun-handling, developed this program in response to news stories about deaths and injuries of youths by negligent gunfire.

== Criticism ==
{{Original research|section|date=November 2010}}
The [[ABC News]] program ''[[20/20 (US television series)|20/20]]'' did a feature{{When|date=November 2010}} on Eddie Eagle which was highly critical of the program. This feature stated that it did not work to simply &quot;Tell [very young] kids what to do&quot; and expect them to follow those instructions implicitly.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

The producers had a group of schoolchildren (aged 3 to 10 years old) watch the Eddie Eagle video along with a presentation by a police officer on [[gun safety]]. While the children all appeared to understand the message that guns are not toys, when the children were left alone with prop guns (and a hidden camera capturing their reactions), they all proceeded to use them as if they were toys.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}}

In response, gun rights advocates{{who|date=November 2010}} claimed that the children in the segment may have been encouraged to play with the gun and knowing that they would be on television would act in a manner to get attention.{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

It is also pointed out{{by whom|date=November 2010}} that the Eddie Eagle program &amp;ndash; like many child-education methods &amp;ndash; depended on repeated contact with the message. Materials such as coloring books provide this necessary contact. Likewise, teachers and parents are encouraged{{by whom|date=November 2010}} to talk with their children about the subject. The children in the segment were exposed a single time to the message, as part of a series of lectures, and not given the follow-up materials or support. Rarely does such a method succeed in teaching young children anything.{{Or|date=November 2010}}{{Citation needed|date=November 2007}}

NRA spokespersons have numerous{{quantify|date=November 2010}} [[anecdotal]] accounts of &quot;saves&quot; made by the program in which children who were in live situations where a gun was found lying around did exactly as the program instructed them to.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nraila.org/Issues/Articles/Read.aspx?id=197&amp;issue=009|title=NRA Victories: EIghteen Million Safer Kids|date=July 27, 2006|publisher=[[|National Rifle Association of AmericaNational Rifle Association of America, Institute for Legislative Action]]|accessdate=2010-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.nrahq.org/safety/eddie/ Eddie Eagle]

[[Category:Fictional birds of prey]]
[[Category:Firearm safety]]
[[Category:National Rifle Association]]
[[Category:Public service announcement characters]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
