<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg" to="Lake Chaubunagungamaug" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="2432758" ns="0" title="Lake Chaubunagungamaug"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_lake
 |lake_name = Lake Chaubunagungamaug
 |image_lake = Lake Chaubunagungamaugg.jpg
 |caption_lake = 
 |image_bathymetry = 
 |caption_bathymetry = 
 |location = [[Webster, Massachusetts]]
 |coords = {{Coord|42|02|30|N|71|50|30|W|type:waterbody_region:US-MA|display=inline,title}}
 |type = 
 |inflow = 
 |outflow = 
 |catchment = 
 |basin_countries = United States
 |length = {{convert|3.25|mi|km|abbr=on}}
 |width = {{convert|1.125|mi|km|abbr=on}}
 |area = {{convert|1442|acre|ha|abbr=on}}
 |depth = 
 |max-depth = 
 |volume = 
 |residence_time = 
 |shore = {{convert|17|mi|km|abbr=on}}
 |elevation = {{convert|477|ft|m}}
 |islands = 8
 |cities = 
}}

'''Lake Chaubunagungamaug''', also known as '''Webster Lake''', is a lake in the [[New England town|town]] of [[Webster, Massachusetts]], United States. It is located near the [[Connecticut]] border and has a surface area of {{convert|1442|acre|km2}}. 

==Name==
The lake's name comes from [[Nipmuc]], an [[Algonquian languages|Algonquian language]], and is said to mean, &quot;Fishing Place at the Boundaries -- Neutral Meeting Grounds&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Association&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://classic-web.archive.org/web/20071026034058/http://www.websterlakeassociation.com/GeneralInterest/Fabricationleavesusgasping.htm |title=Fabrication leaves us gasping - Old twist to name of lake comes to light |last=Patenaude |first=Ed |date=June 28, 2001 |publisher=Worcester Telegram &amp; Gazette |accessdate=2011-05-31}} &lt;/ref&gt; This is different from the humorous translation, &quot;You fish on your side, I fish on my side, and nobody fish in the middle&quot;, given by the late Laurence J. Daly, a Worcester newspaper correspondent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Association&quot; /&gt;

Lake Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg ({{IPA|/ˌleɪk tʃəˈɡɒɡəɡɒɡ ˌmænˈtʃɔːɡəɡɒɡ tʃəˌbʌnəˈɡʌŋɡəmɔːɡ/}}),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/audiopages/2004/11/19/national/20041120_LAKE_AUDIO.html], [http://www.oldewebster.com/home_archive.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; 
a 45-letter alternative name for this body of fresh water, is often cited as the longest [[place name]] in the United States and one of the longest in the world. It is spelled incorrectly on the sign bordering Connecticut.&lt;ref name=gnis&gt;{{cite gnis|619290|Lake Chaubunagungamaug|2011-4-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Today, &quot;Webster Lake&quot; may be the name most used, but some (including many residents of Webster), take pride in reeling off the longer versions.&lt;!--not a reliable source: &lt;ref name=&quot;miller&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Miller |first=Jeff |date=1 April 2006 |url=http://members.aol.com/gulfhigh2/words10.html  |title=A Collection of Word Oddities and Trivia |accessdate=2006-05-25 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071013132235/http://members.aol.com/gulfhigh2/words10.html |archivedate = 2007-10-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;

This lake has several alternative names. Lake Chaubunagungamaug is the name of the lake as recognized by the [[U.S. Department of the Interior]],&lt;ref name=gnis/&gt; however, many area residents, as well as the official website of the town of Webster, consider the longer version correct.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webster-ma.gov/ Town of Webster], accessed January 15, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Algonquian languages|Algonquian]]-speaking peoples had several different names for the lake as recorded on old maps and historical records. However, all of these were similar in part and had almost the same translation. Among other early names were &quot;Chabanaguncamogue&quot; and &quot;Chaubanagogum&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;oldewebster&quot;&gt;[http://www.oldewebster.com/history/lake_chargogg.htm Old Webster History]&lt;/ref&gt; Early town records show the name as &quot;''Chabunagungamaug'' Pond&quot;, also the name of the local Nipmuc town (recorded in 1668 and 1674 with somewhat different spellings). This has been translated as 'boundary fishing place',&lt;ref name=&quot;trumbull&quot;&gt;Trumbull, James Hammond. 1881. ''Indian Names of Places etc., In and On the Borders of Connecticut: With interpretations of Some of Them''. Reprinted in facsimile 1974 under title ''Indian Names in Connecticut'' by Archon Books, Hamden, Conn.&lt;/ref&gt; but something close to &quot;fishing place at the boundary&quot; or &quot;that which is a divided island lake&quot; may be more accurate.&lt;ref name=&quot;goddard&quot;&gt;Goddard, Ives. 1974. [http://www.jstor.org/stable/1264936?seq=2 Untitled review of Trumbull] in ''International Journal of American Linguistics'' Vol. 43, No. 2 (Apr., 1977), pp. 157-159, University of Chicago Press.&lt;/ref&gt; 

A map of 1795, showing the town of [[Dudley, Massachusetts|Dudley]], indicated the name as &quot;Chargoggaggoggmancogmanhoggagogg&quot;. A survey of the lake done in 1830 lists the name as &quot;Chaubunagungmamgnamaugg&quot;, the older name. The following year, both Dudley and [[Oxford, Massachusetts|Oxford]], which adjoined the lake, filed maps listing the name as &quot;Chargoggagoggmanchoggagogg&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;oldewebster&quot;/&gt;

&quot;Manchaug&quot; is derived from the &quot;Monuhchogogoks&quot;, a group of Nipmuck that lived by the lakeshore. Spellings of the long name vary, even on official signs near the lake; in 2009, following six years of press reports, the local Chamber of Commerce agreed to have the spelling corrected on its signs, where a 45-letter version of the name arrayed in a semicircle was used. It did not correspond to any of the two dozen variants in the [[GNIS]].&lt;ref name=&quot;brianlee&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=Misspelling on lake signs to get overdue correction |url=http://www.telegram.com/article/20090414/NEWS/904140367 |author=Brian Lee |publisher=Worcester Telegram &amp;amp; Gazette |date=2009-04-14 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Webster [[school]]s use one long form of the name in various capacities.&lt;ref name=&quot;oldewebster&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nativetech.org/Nipmuc/placenames/mainmass.html Nipmuc Place Names of New England]&lt;/ref&gt;

Three songs about the lake's name have been written. The first was a regional song from the 1930s. The second was recorded by [[Ethel Merman]] and [[Ray Bolger]] and released in 1954 by [[Decca Records|Decca]] and incorporates the tale about the lake's name according to Daly. The most recent was released in 2010 by [[Diane Taraz]].

[[Image:Patch of a lake with a really long name.jpg|thumb|200px|A patch with the name of the lake]]
In the 1950s, a plan to shorten the official name of the lake inspired a poem of [[doggerel]] verse which concludes:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Touch not a g!&quot; No impious hand&lt;br /&gt;
Shall wrest one from that noble name&lt;br /&gt;
Fifteen in all their glory stand&lt;br /&gt;
And ever shall the same.&lt;br /&gt;
For never shall that number down,&lt;br /&gt;
Tho [[Gog and Magog|Gogg and Magogg]] shout and thunder;&lt;br /&gt;
Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg's renown&lt;br /&gt;
Shall blaze, the beacon of the town,&lt;br /&gt;
While nations gaze and wonder.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldewebster.com/history/evolution.htm Poem by Bertha A. Joslin].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Geography==
Webster Lake is a {{convert|1442|acre|km2|adj=on}} lake with a {{convert|17|mi|km|adj=on}} shoreline in southern Massachusetts, near the Connecticut border. The lake is spring-fed, making it the second largest natural lake in the state. The largest is Long Pond in Lakeville, MA at {{convert|1721|acre|km2}}, according to the Massachusetts Department of Wildlife.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://www.mass.gov/dfwele/dfw/habitat/maps/ponds/pdf/dfwlongl.pdf
|title=Long Pond
|publisher=Commonwealth of Massachusetts: Division of Fisheries &amp; Wildlife
|format=pdf
|date=September 12, 2007
|accessdate=2011-05-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; The average depth is {{convert|13|ft|m}} and the maximum depth is {{convert|45|ft|m}}.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.websterlakeassociation.com/GeneralInterest/LakeMaps.htm Webster Lake Association.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the lake is natural in origin, its outlet has a dam that raises the water level by a few feet. The dam is owned by Cranston Print Works, which controls the water level.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

The lake is commonly divided into three smaller bodies of water: North Pond, Middle Pond, and South Pond. They are connected by narrow channels.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}

===Islands===
Webster lake has about 7-8 islands. Some have houses and are habitable; a few are extremely small and uninhabitable. They include:

*Long Island: The largest island in Webster Lake. It has many homes and has electric power lines, underground/underwater municipal water and sewer service, and several fire hydrants. It is in the Middle Pond.
*Goat Island: The second largest island. It has a few homes and boats. It is in the Middle Pond but isolated from the cluster of islands that include Long Island.
*Well Island:  A smaller island with one house west of Long Island in the Middle Pond.
*Strip Island: Generally northeast of Long Island and north of Cobble Island with one house, also in the Middle Pond.
*Cobble Island: East of Long Island, in the Middle Pond.
*Little Island: In South Pond, right out of the [[Wake#Recreation|no wake zone]] from the Middle Pond, one house.

===Marinas===
Webster lake has two marinas: 

* Lakeview Marine: The only full service marine store and service shop on Webster Lake. They feature new and used boat sales, parts and accessories, and a full-service maintenance and repair shop. Major lines carried include: Bennington, Yamaha, Larson, OMC parts, Volvo Penta. 

* Point Breeze: A restaurant with a small marina. Point Breeze Marina has the only dockside gas pump on the lake.

===Restaurants===
Webster Lake has two waterfront restaurants open to the public:

* Waterfront Mary's is on the Middle Pond, near the narrows that lead to the North Pond. Customers can beach their personal water crafts or dock their boats; the restaurant has food, drinks, and a patio with great views of the largest section of the lake.

* Point Breeze Restaurant is on the Middle Pond, next to Point Breeze Marina. Customers can dock pontoon boats and take a staircase to the restaurant. They have occasional live music and hold wedding functions.

==See also==
*[[Longest word in English]]
*[[Llanfairpwllgwyngyllgogerychwyrndrobwllllantysiliogogogoch]], the longest place name in the UK
*[[Longest words]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{commons cat|Lake Chaubunagungamaug}}
*[http://www.oldewebster.com/history/lake_chargogg.htm A history of the lake]
*[http://www.nytimes.com/2004/11/20/national/20lake.html NY Times - What's the Name of That Lake? It's Hard to Say]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yhL4rg7yO4E Listen to the Lake Song]
*[http://www.websterlakerealty.com/webster-lake-boat-tours-webster-ma/ Webster Lake Real Estate Boat Tours]
*[http://www.websterlakeassociation.com/Environmental%20Issues/Proposed%20Treatment%20Areas%202006%206-22-06.jpg Map of Lake Chaubunagungamaug]
*[http://www.websterlakeassociation.com/images/Maps/Watershed25%25.jpg Map of the area watershed]
*[http://www.websterlake.net/pictures.htm Lake Chaubunagungamaug photos 1]
*[http://www.websterlake.net/ariel.htm Lake Chaubunagungamaug photos 2]

[[Category:Lakes of Massachusetts|Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[Category:Lakes of Worcester County, Massachusetts]]

[[ca:Llac Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg]]
[[cs:Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[de:Lake Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[es:Lago Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[eo:Chargoggagogg­manchauggagogg­chaubunagungamaugg]]
[[fr:Chargoggagogg­manchauggagogg­chaubunagungamaugg]]
[[ko:처바너강거모그 호]]
[[hr:Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg]]
[[id:Danau Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[it:Lago Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[lt:Čaubunagungamaugo ežeras]]
[[nl:Chaubunagungamaugmeer]]
[[ja:チャーゴグガゴグマンチャウグガゴグチャウバナガンガマウグ]]
[[pl:Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[ro:Lacul Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[ru:Чаубунагунгамауг]]
[[simple:Lake Chaubunagungamaug]]
[[sl:Čargogagogmančaugagogčaubunagungamaug]]
[[sh:Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg]]
[[fi:Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg]]
[[sv:Chargoggagoggmanchauggagoggchaubunagungamaugg]]
[[th:ทะเลสาบเว็บสเตอร์]]
[[zh:查哥加哥文程加哥朮巴根加馬古]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
