<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3361076" ns="0" title="Anurognathus"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{italictitle}}{{speciesbox
| fossil_range = [[Late Jurassic]], {{fossilrange|150}}
| name = ''Anurognathus''
| image = AnurognathusDB.jpg|thumb
| image_caption = Life restoration, illustrated hunting a [[lacewing]] ''[[Kalligramma haeckeli]]''
| image_width = 240px
| display_parents = 2
| grandparent_authority = [[Franz Nopcsa von Felső-Szilvás|Nopcsa]], 1928
| genus = Anurognathus
| parent_authority = [[Ludwig Döderlein (biologist)|Döderlein]], 1923
| species = ammoni
| authority = Döderlein, 1923
}}
'''''Anurognathus''''' is a [[genus]] of small [[pterosaur]] that lived approximately 150 {{Fact|date=December 2009}} million years ago during the late [[Jurassic]] [[Period (geology)|Period]] ([[Tithonian]] stage).

''Anurognathus'' was first named and described by [[Ludwig Döderlein (biologist)|Ludwig Döderlein]] in 1923.&lt;ref name=&quot;doderlein1923&quot;&gt;Döderlein, L. (1923). &quot;''Anurognathus Ammoni'', ein neuer Flugsaurier&quot;. ''Sitzungsberichte der Mathematisch-Naturwissenschaftlichen Abteilung der Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu München'', 1923, 306-307.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[type species]] is ''Anurognathus ammoni''. The genus name ''Anurognathus'' is derived from the [[Ancient Greek|Greek]] ''αν''/''an-'' (&quot;without&quot;), ''оυρα''/''oura'' (&quot;tail&quot;), and ''γναθος''/''gnathos'' (&quot;jaw&quot;) in reference to its unusually small tail relative to other &quot;[[Rhamphorhynchoidea|rhamphorhynchoid]]&quot; (i.e. basal) pterosaurs.&lt;ref name=&quot;cranfield-Anurognathus&quot;&gt;&quot;Anurognathus.&quot; In: Cranfield, Ingrid (ed.). ''The Illustrated Directory of Dinosaurs and Other Prehistoric Creatures''. London: Salamander Books, Ltd. Pp. 292-295.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[specific name (zoology)|specific name]] ''ammoni'' honours the Bavarian geologist [[Ludwig von Ammon]], from whose collection Döderlein had acquired the fossil in 1922.

==Description==
The genus is based on [[holotype]] '''BSP 1922.I.42''' ([[Bayerische Staatssammlung für Palaeontologie und Geologie]]), found in the [[Solnhofen limestone]] near [[Eichstätt]]. It consists of a crushed relatively complete skeleton on a slab. The counterslab is missing and with it most of the bones: much of the skeleton is only visible as an impression. 

''Anurognathus'' had a short head with pin-like teeth for catching [[insect]]s and although it traditionally is ascribed to the long-tailed pterosaur group &quot;[[Rhamphorhynchoidea]]&quot;, its tail was comparatively short, allowing it more maneuverability for hunting.&lt;ref name=DU06&gt;{{cite book |last=Unwin |first=David M. |title=The Pterosaurs: From Deep Time |year=2006 |publisher=Pi Press |location=New York |isbn=0-13-146308-X |page=246}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Döderlein the reduced tail of ''Anurognathus'' was similar to the pygostyle of modern birds.&lt;ref name=&quot;cranfield-Anurognathus&quot; /&gt; Its more typical &quot;rhamphorhynchoid&quot; characters include its elongated fifth toe and short metacarpals and neck.&lt;ref name=&quot;cranfield-Anurognathus&quot; /&gt; With an estimated wingspan of fifty centimetres (20 inches) and a nine centimetre long body (skull included), its weight was limited: in 2008 [[Mark Paul Witton]] estimated a mass of forty grammes for a specimen with a 35 centimetre wingspan.&lt;ref&gt;Witton, M.P. (2008) &quot;A new approach to determining pterosaur body mass and its implications for pterosaur flight&quot;. ''Zitteliania'' '''B28''': 143-159&lt;/ref&gt; The holotype was redescribed by [[Peter Wellnhofer]] in 1975. 

Later a second, smaller, specimen was found, probably of a subadult individual. Its slab and counterslab are separated and both were sold to private collections; neither has an official registration. It was described by [[S. Christopher Bennet]] in 2007. This second exemplar is much more complete and better articulated. It shows impressions of a large part of the flight membrane and under UV-light remains of the muscles of the thigh and arm become visible. It provided new information on many points of the anatomy. The skull was shown to have been very short and broad, wider than long. It transpired that Wellnhofer had incorrectly reconstructed the skull in 1975, mistaking the large eye sockets for the ''fenestrae antorbitales'', skull openings that in most pterosaurs are larger than the orbits but in ''Anurognathus'' are small and together with the nostrils placed at the front of the flat snout. The eyes pointed forwards to a degree, providing some binocular vision. Most of the skull consisted of bone struts. The presumed pygostyle was absent; investigating the real nine tail vertebrae instead of impressions showed that they were unfused, though very reduced. The wing finger lacked the fourth phalanx. According to Bennett a membrane, visible near the shin, showed that the wing contacted the ankle and was thus rather short and broad. Bennett also restudied the holotype, interpreting bumps on the jaws as an indication that hairs forming a protruding bristle were present on the snout.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, S. C. (2007). &quot;A second specimen of the pterosaur ''Anurognathus ammoni''&quot;, ''Paläontologische Zeitschrift'', '''81''': 376-398&lt;/ref&gt;

''Anurognathus'' was in 1937 assigned by [[Oskar Kuhn]] to the [[Family (biology)|family]] [[Anurognathid]]ae. In the modern [[clade]] Anurognathidae, ''Anurognathus'' is the sister taxon of the clade [[Asiaticognathidae]], which contains the species ''[[Batrachognathus]]'', ''[[Dendrorhynchoides]]'' and ''[[Jeholopterus]]''.

According to Döderlein ''Anurognathus'' was, with its long wings, a swift flyer, surprising its prey, similar to the modern [[nightjar]]. Bennett however, infers from the discovery of the true shorter size of the wings, combined with the short tail, that it was a slower flying predator, specialised in hunting by manoeuvrability, its large eyes adapted to a crepuscular way of life. This would also be proven by a very large flexibility of the wing finger joints.

==In popular culture==
''Anurognathus'' was featured in the second episode of the [[Great Britain|British]] [[documentary film|documentary]] series ''[[Walking with Dinosaurs]]''. It was shown having a [[Mutualism (biology)|mutual]] [[symbiosis|symbiotic]] relationship with the [[dinosaur]] ''[[Diplodocus]]'', eating [[parasitism|parasitic]] [[insect]]s off its [[skin]]. Such a, purely hypothetical, symbiosis would make it similar to the modern day [[Yellow-headed Caracara|tick bird]].

''Anurognathus'' was featured in the fifth episode of the [[ITV]] science fiction television series ''[[Primeval (TV series)|Primeval]]''. Here, ''Anurognathus'' was erroneously portrayed as living in the Late Cretaceous period, 85 million years ago, with behavior akin to a [[piranha]]. The producers of the program portrayed ''Anurognathus'' as having an amazingly keen sense of smell, able to detect blood from hundreds of feet away. A flock was depicted stripping the flesh from a carcass in a matter of minutes, behavior at odds with anatomical evidence that shows this species to have been insectivorous akin to the modern [[Frogmouth]].&lt;ref name=DU06/&gt; These changes were made for dramatic effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Framestore&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Milne | first = Mike | url = http://www.framestore-cfc.com/television/primeval/index.html| title = Primeval sees Framestore CFC's Creatures Leap into the 21st Century}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Anurognathus'' made a reappearance in the ffth episode of the fifth series.

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{portal|Paleontology}}

[[Category:Jurassic pterosaurs]]
[[Category:Rhamphorhynchoids]]
[[Category:Prehistoric reptiles of Europe]]
[[Category:Solnhofen fauna]]

[[ca:Anurognathus]]
[[de:Anurognathus]]
[[es:Anurognathus]]
[[fr:Anurognathus]]
[[ko:아누로그나투스]]
[[it:Anurognathus ammoni]]
[[hu:Anurognathus]]
[[nl:Anurognathus]]
[[pl:Anurognat]]
[[ru:Anurognathus]]
[[pt:Anurognathus]]
[[simple:Anurognathus]]
[[fi:Anurognathus]]
[[zh:蛙嘴龍]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
