<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33660804" ns="0" title="Penn State sex abuse scandal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{TOC-right}}
The '''Penn State sex abuse scandal''' refers to allegations that former [[Pennsylvania State University]] [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|football]] assistant coach [[Jerry Sandusky]] sexually assaulted or had inappropriate contact with at least eight underage boys on or near university property.  After an extensive [[grand jury]] investigation, Sandusky was indicted on 40 counts of child molestation dating from 1994 to 2009, though the abuse may date as far back as the 1970s.&lt;ref name=1970s&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/exclusive_jerry_sandusky_inter.html |title=Exclusive: Jerry Sandusky interview prompts long-ago victims to contact lawyer |author=Sara Ganim |work=''[[The Patriot-News]]'' |date=November 17, 2011 |accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Per the findings of the investigation, several high-level school officials were charged with [[perjury]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Two Top Officials Step Down Amid Penn State Scandal|url=http://www.foxnews.com/sports/2011/11/05/penn-state-ex-coach-others-charged-in-child-sex-case/|agency=Associated Press|accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; suspended, or dismissed for allegedly [[cover-up|covering up]] the incidents or failing to notify authorities. In the wake of the scandal, head football coach [[Joe Paterno]] was dismissed from his position and school president [[Graham Spanier]] was forced to resign. Sandusky has denied the allegations.&lt;ref name=&quot;admission&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15730317 |title=Jerry Sandusky regrets showers with boys at Penn State |date=November 14, 2011 |accessdate=November 14, 2001 |publisher=BBC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
Sandusky was an assistant coach under head coach Joe Paterno for the [[Penn State Nittany Lions football|Penn State football]] team for 31 seasons from 1969 to 1999.  For the last 23 of those years, he was the team's defensive coordinator.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wetzel&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://wap.yahoo.com/w/sports/home/experts/article?offset=3&amp;urn=urn%3Anewsml%3Asports.yahoo%2Cyhoo%3A20050301%3Ancaaf%2Carticle%2Cdw-wetzel_penn_state_child_sex_case_110511%3A1&amp;.ts=1320564205&amp;.ysid=YrvwsCSswypAL.sUbZLwWEwk&amp;.intl=US&amp;.lang=en
| first=Dan
| last=Wetzel
| authorlink=Dan Wetzel
| title=Penn State's insufficient action amid child sex allegations stunning
| work=[[Yahoo! Sports]]
| date=November 5, 2011
| accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1977, Sandusky founded [[The Second Mile]], a charity formed to help troubled young boys, in [[State College, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Lentz |first=Charlie |url=http://pennstate.scout.com/2/630302.html |title=Sandusky Second to None |date=March 27, 2007 |work=pennstate.scout.com |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20110716021727/http://pennstate.scout.com/2/630302.html |archivedate=July 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1998, he was investigated for sexual abuse of a child by the University Police, State College Police, Centre County District Attorney, Pennsylvania Department of Public Welfare, and a &quot;child protection agency,&quot; but no charges were filed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/06/jerry-sandusky-penn-state-child-sex-scandal-curley-schultz-cover-up_n_1078493.html
| title=Jerry Sandusky Charged With Sexual Abuse: Did Penn State Officials Tim Curley, Gary Schultz It Cover Up?
| first=Genaro C.
| last=Armas
| first2=Mark
| last2=Scolford
| newspaper=The Huffington Post
| date=November 6, 2011
| accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sandusky was considered for spearheading a football program at Penn State Altoona in 1998-99, but the idea was scrapped and he retired in 1999.&lt;ref name=Altoona&gt;{{cite news|title=Offering Sandusky to PSU Altoona troubling|url=http://www.altoonamirror.com/page/content.detail/id/555789/Offering-Sandusky-to-PSU-Altoona---.html|accessdate=28 November 2011|newspaper=Altoona Mirror|date=27 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his retirement as Penn State's defensive coordinator, he remained as a coach emeritus with an office in, and access to, Penn State's football facilities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/news/s_765879.html | title=Three charged in Penn State sex crime case | first=Tom | last=Fontaine | newspaper=Pittsburgh Tribune-Review | date=November 6, 2011 | accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Grand jury investigation==
The investigation was initiated in the spring of 2008, after the mother of a boy (identified in court papers as &quot;Victim 1&quot;), then a freshman at [[Central Mountain High School]] in [[Clinton County, Pennsylvania]], reported that the boy had been sexually abused by Sandusky. According to court papers, Sandusky had been having a relationship involving &quot;inappropriate touching&quot; with Victim 1 since 2005 or 2006, when the boy was 11 or 12. Sandusky had met the boy through the Second Mile program before retiring from the program in 2010.&lt;ref name=&quot;Key dates&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://espn.go.com/college-football/story/_/id/7212054/key-dates-penn-state-sex-abuse-case |title=Sandusky, Penn State case timeline |work=ESPN.com |date=November 9, 2011 |accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/jerry_sandusky_a_penn_state_un.html |title=Jerry Sandusky, a Penn State University football legend and founder of The Second Mile, faces charges of sex crimes |first=Sara |last=Ganim |work=[[The Patriot-News]] |location=[[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania]] |date=November 4, 2011 |accessdate=November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sandusky was also volunteering as an assistant high school football coach at Central at the time of the alleged actions.&lt;ref name=PN01&gt;Ganim, Sara, [http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/03/jerry_sandusky_former_penn_sta.html &quot;Jerry Sandusky, former Penn State football staffer, subject of grand jury investigation&quot;], ''[[Patriot-News]]'', March 31, 2011 8:00/8:20 am. Retrieved 2011-11-13.&lt;/ref&gt; The investigation included testimony from various individuals at Penn State and The Second Mile. Pennsylvania Attorney General [[Linda Kelly]] has said that during the grand jury investigation there was an &quot;uncooperative atmosphere&quot; from some of these officials.&lt;ref name=ap1 /&gt;

In December 2010, assistant coach [[Mike McQueary]] appeared before the [[grand jury]] looking into the Victim 1 case.  McQueary testified that, on March 1, 2002, at 9:30 p.m., he entered the locker room at the Lasch Football Building at Penn State and heard what he believed to be the sounds of sexual activity coming from the shower.  He looked in the shower and &quot;saw a naked boy, Victim 2, whose age he estimated to be ten years old, with his hands up against the wall, being subjected to [[anal intercourse]] by a naked Sandusky.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/report_former_coach_jerry_sand.html
|title=Report: Former coach Jerry Sandusky used charity to molest kids
|first=Sara
|last=Ganim
|work=The Patriot-News
|date=November 6, 2011
|accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, McQueary reported the incident to Joe Paterno, who informed Athletic Director [[Tim Curley]]. Ultimately, the only action taken by Curley and Gary Schultz, Senior vice president for finance and business (who also oversaw the Penn State police department), was to order Sandusky not to bring any children from Second Mile to the football building &amp;mdash; an action that was approved by school president [[Graham Spanier]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Key dates&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wetzel/&gt; The identity of the boy remains unknown to the authorities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard/article-24008921-when-morality-bows-down-to-sport-and-cash.do|title=When morality bows down to sport and cash|work=London Evening Standard|date=November 11, 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In their testimony before the grand jury, Paterno, Curley, and Schultz rejected the version of the incident presented by Mike McQueary. Paterno testified that he was only told about Sandusky &quot;fondling or doing something of a sexual nature&quot; to the victim. Curley and Schultz both denied having been told about alleged anal intercourse. Curley denied that McQueary reported anything of sexual nature whatsoever, and described the conduct as merely &quot;horsing around&quot;. Graham Spanier likewise testified that he was only apprised of an incident involving Jerry Sandusky and a younger child &quot;horsing around in the shower&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt;

On November 14, 2011, Sandusky's lawyer claimed that he was able to track down Victim 2 and that, according to the child, the incident did not occur as described by McQueary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/15/joe-amendola-lawyer-jerry-sandusky-costas-interview_n_1094163.html|title=Joseph Amendola, Lawyer For Jerry Sandusky, Hints At New Information With Bob Costas}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite Penn State banning Sandusky from bringing boys onto the main campus in 2002, he was allowed to operate a summer camp through his Sandusky Associates company&lt;ref name=&quot;ap1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|author=By KEVIN BEGOS and MARK SCOLFORO Associated Press |url=http://abcnews.go.com/Sports/wireStory/coach-accused-charity-assault-boys-14939549 |title=Sandusky Had Access to Vulnerable Kids Via Charity (Associated Press, Nov. 12, 2011) |publisher=Abcnews.go.com |date=2011-11-12 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; from 2002 to 2008 at Penn State's [[Penn State Erie, The Behrend College|Behrend satellite campus]] near Erie, where he had daily contact with boys from fourth grade to high school.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/nationnow/2011/11/sandusky-penn-state-.html |title=Penn State sex scandal: Jerry Sandusky ran boys camps for years |work=Los Angeles Times |date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Gerald Sandusky Sexual Abuse Findings of Grand Jury.png|thumb|center|800px|Illustration of victims, people with alleged knowledge of alleged crimes, and official responses as of November 11, 2011]]

The Pennsylvania statewide investigating [[grand jury]] identified a total of eight boys singled out for sexual advances or [[sexual assault|assaults]] by Sandusky from 1994 through 2009, after six more victims were identified:&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Report of Thirty Third Statewide Investigating Grand Jury ('Grand Jury Report')|url=http://www.attorneygeneral.gov/uploadedFiles/Press/Sandusky-Grand-Jury-Presentment.pdf|publisher=Pennsylvania Attorney General|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/636FfNYZ6 |archivedate=November 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/06/sports/ncaafootball/former-coach-at-penn-state-is-charged-with-abuse.html |title=Former Coach at Penn State Is Charged With Abuse |work=The New York Times |date=5November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Five alleged victims testified that they met Sandusky through The Second Mile; each also stated that they showered with him on the campus.  According to the witnesses, the showers included physical contact ranging from hugs and wrestling to, in one case, Sandusky placing the boy's hand on his erect penis.&lt;ref&gt;Grand Jury Report&lt;/ref&gt;

One child's mother reported the incident to Penn State police when he came home with his hair wet.  After an investigation by Detective Ronald Shreffler, [[Centre County]] District Attorney [[Ray Gricar]] chose not to prosecute. Shreffler testified before the Grand Jury that director of the campus police, Thomas Harmon, told him to drop the case.  University police eavesdropped on conversations during which the mother confronted Sandusky about the incident.  He admitted to showering with other boys and refused to discontinue the practice. District Attorney Gricar was not available to testify, as he had disappeared in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/mothers_of_two_of_jerry_sandus.html |title=Mothers of two of Jerry Sandusky's alleged victims lash out at Penn State officials' handling of scandal |first=Sara |last=Ganim |work=The Patriot-News |date=November 7, 2011 |accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Victims also commonly reported that Sandusky would place his hand on their thighs or inside the waistband of their underpants.  Two recounted oral sex with Sandusky, sometimes culminating in his ejaculation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt;  Penn State janitor James Calhoun reportedly observed Sandusky giving oral sex to an unidentified boy in 2000, but Calhoun is in a nursing home suffering from dementia, he was deemed not competent to testify.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt;

At least 20 of the incidents allegedly took place while Sandusky was still employed by Penn State.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.philly.com/philly/sports/colleges/20111106_Two_Penn_State_officials_charged_in_connection_with_sex-abuse_investigation.html |title=Two Penn State officials charged in connection with sex-abuse investigation |first=Joe |last=Juliano |work=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]] |date=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Criminal charges and further investigation ==
[[File:GrahamSpanierCCSG.png|thumb|right|200px|Penn State President [[Graham Spanier]] released a statement of support for Curley and Schultz before being forced to resign.]]
On November 4, 2011, [[Attorney General of Pennsylvania|Pennsylvania Attorney General]] [[Linda Kelly]] indicted Sandusky on 40 counts of sex crimes against young boys, following a three-year investigation. Sandusky was arrested on November 5 and charged with seven counts of involuntary deviant sexual intercourse, as well as eight counts of corruption of minors, eight counts of endangering the welfare of a child, seven counts of [[indecent assault]], and other offenses.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/football/story/2011-11-05/penn-state-abuse-case/51083628/1
|title=Penn State ex-coach charged with abuse, AD with perjury
|agency=Associated Press
|work=[[USA Today]]
|date=November 5, 2011
|accessdate=November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Senior vice president Gary Schultz and Athletic Director Tim Curley were found to be not credible by the grand jury. The two administrators were charged with grand jury perjury and failure to report suspected child abuse by Sandusky. The indictment accused Curley and Schultz of not only failing to tell the police, but falsely telling the grand jury that Mike McQueary never informed them of sexual activity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Key dates&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wetzel/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://collegefootballtalk.nbcsports.com/2011/11/05/penn-state-ad-charged-with-perjury-failure-to-report-in-sandusky-sex-case/related/
|title=Penn State AD charged with perjury, failure to report in Sandusky sex case (MSNBC)
|publisher=NBC Sports
|date= |accessdate=November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Mark |last=Scolforo
|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Sports/wireStory/penn-st-coach-charged-child-sex-case-14888291
|title=Penn St Ex-Coach, Others Charged in Child Sex Case (ABC News)
|publisher=Abcnews.go.com
|date= 
|accessdate=November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Sandusky is currently free on $100,000 bail pending trial. He could face [[life in prison]] if convicted of the charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/sandusky_could_face_life_in_pr.html |title=Former Penn State coaching legend Jerry Sandusky could face life in prison if convicted on charges of sex abuse against boys |first=Sara |last=Ganim |work=The Patriot-News |date=November 5, 2011 |accessdate=November 5, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Curley and Schultz appeared in a [[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania|Harrisburg]] courtroom on November 7, where a judge set bail at $75,000 and required them to surrender their passports.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57319878/sandusky-case-officials-seek-alleged-victims/ |title=Sandusky case: Officials seek alleged victims |publisher=CBS News}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Penn State officially banned Sandusky from campus on November 6, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://espn.go.com/college-football/story/_/id/7199068/penn-state-nittany-lions-bar-accused-ex-coach-jerry-sandusky-campus |title=Penn State to pay AD's legal costs |publisher=[[ESPN]] |date=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Later that day, Tim Curley was placed on administrative leave, and Gary Schultz resigned to go back into retirement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nbcsports.msnbc.com/id/45186257/ns/sports-college_football/ |title=Paterno to retire after season amid scandal |publisher=msnbc.com |date=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the charges came to light, Spanier issued a statement in which he said Curley and Schultz had his unconditional support, and saying they &quot;operate at the highest levels of honesty.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.statecollege.com/news/local-news/spanier-curley-schultz-operate-at-the-highest-levels-of-honesty-924039/ |title=Spanier: Curley, Schultz 'Operate at the Highest Levels of Honesty' |date=November 5, 2011 |work=StateCollege.com |publisher=State College, PA}}&lt;/ref&gt; Spanier was criticized for expressing support for Curley and Schultz, and failing to express any concern for Sandusky's alleged victims.&lt;ref name=Wetzel/&gt;

Congressman [[Pat Meehan]] (R-[[Pennsylvania's 4th congressional district|PA04]]) asked [[United States Secretary of Education|Education Secretary]] [[Arne Duncan]] to probe whether Penn State violated the [[Clery Act]] when it failed to report Sandusky's alleged incidents of child molestation that took place on campus.  Duncan announced an investigation into possible Clery Act violations at Penn State, saying that colleges and universities have &quot;a legal and moral responsibility to protect children&quot;, and that Penn State's failure to report the alleged abuse would be a &quot;tragedy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Weinger, Mackenzie. [http://www.politico.com/news/stories/1111/67999.html Penn State to be investigated by Department of Education]. [[The Politico]], 2011-11-09.&lt;/ref&gt; The investigation, which began on November 28, could result in fines or the loss of federal student aid if the university is found in violation.&lt;ref name=CBS-AP&gt;{{cite web|last=Associated Press|title=Sandusky's Second Mile charity: Donate elsewhere|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57332367/sanduskys-second-mile-charity-donate-elsewhere/|work=CBSNews.com|publisher=CBS News|accessdate=29 November 2011|date=28 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Officials in [[San Antonio, Texas]] also began investigating whether Sandusky molested one of the victims at the [[1999 Alamo Bowl]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://abcnews.go.com/US/penn-state-sex-scandal-spreads-texas-alleged-alamo/story?id=14932340 Penn State Sex Abuse Scandal Spreads to Texas for Alleged Alamo Bowl Tryst]. [[ABC News]], 2011-11-11.&lt;/ref&gt;

Trustee [[Kenneth Frazier]] announced on November 21 that [[Louis Freeh]], former director of the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|FBI]], would lead an internal investigation into the university's actions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://live.psu.edu/story/56476 Former FBI director Freeh to conduct independent investigation] Penn State Live, 21 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt; Freeh annouced that the team assisting him in his investigation would include former FBI agents and federal prosecutors. &lt;ref&gt;[http://espn.go.com/college-football/story/_/id/7264524/penn-state-nittany-lions-hire-ex-fbi-director-louis-freeh-investigation Penn St. hires Louis Freeh to investigate] ESPN, 21 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Media reaction==
''[[The Patriot-News]]'' of [[Harrisburg, Pennsylvania]], was the first to report on the grand jury investigation, in March 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/03/jerry_sandusky_former_penn_sta.html |title=Jerry Sandusky, former Penn State football staffer, subject of grand jury investigation |publisher=PennLive.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The story did not receive much attention outside of the immediate area,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lang |first=Brent |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/11/11/us-media-pennstate-idUSTRE7AA4YJ20111111 |title=Penn State scandal: what took the media so long? |publisher=Reuters |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and many readers at the time assailed the newspaper for impugning Sandusky's and Penn State's reputations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/penn_state_child_sex-abuse_sca.html |title=Penn State child sex-abuse scandal: When we had the facts, we ran the story |publisher=PennLive.com |date= |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:PaternoTemple.png|thumb|right|200px|[[Joe Paterno]] was heavily criticized for his reaction to the allegations, and was subsequently fired.]]
[[Joe Paterno]] was not accused of legal wrongdoing by the grand jury, since he fulfilled his obligation to report the incident to his immediate supervisor, Curley, and he also reported it to Gary Schultz, who oversaw the campus police at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Grand Jury Report&quot;/&gt; However, he was harshly criticized for not reporting the incident to police, or at least seeing to it that it was reported.&lt;ref name=Dowd&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/opinion/dowd-personal-foul-at-penn.html?_r=1&amp;ref=maureendowd |title=Personal Foul at Penn State|first=Maureen |last=Dowd |authorlink=Maureen Dowd |work=The New York Times |date=November 9, 2011 |accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Several advocates for sexual abuse victims have called for charges to be brought against him for not contacting the police himself,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.nydailynews.com/sports/college/penn-state-coach-jerry-sandusky-arrested-child-sex-case-ad-tim-curley-charged-perjury-article-1.972670 | title=Former Penn State coach Jerry Sandusky arrested in child sex case; AD Tim Curley charged with perjury | first=Michael | last=O’Keefe | newspaper=New York Daily News | date=November 6, 2011 | accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; despite the fact that he complied with the law by informing his superiors of the incident.&lt;ref name=Miller&gt;{{cite web|last=Miller|first=Dave|title=For Joe Pa, the time is up|url=http://www.nationalfootballpost.com/For-Joe-Pa-the-time-is-up.html|work=National Football Post|publisher=Reign Net Media, LLC|accessdate=21 November 2011|date=7 November 2011|quote=When Pennsylvania attorney general Linda Kelly said Monday that the Sandusky investigation is ongoing, she noted that Paterno is “not regarded as a target at this point.” For Joe Pa, this has nothing to do with legality. He obeyed the law by relaying the knowledge of sexual assault to his superiors.}}&lt;/ref&gt;  After McQueary was identified as the graduate assistant who reported the 2002 incident, he was criticized for not intervening to protect the boy from Sandusky (an accusation McQueary has since disputed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abclocal.go.com/kabc/story?section=news/national_world&amp;id=8433662|title=McQueary on alleged Sandusky attack: 'I did stop it'|last=Michaelson|first=Elex|publisher=KABC|location=State College, Pennsylvania|date=November 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;), as well as for not reporting the incident to police himself.&lt;ref name=SI&gt;Staples, Andy. [http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2011/writers/andy_staples/11/10/penn-state-mike-mcqueary/index.html Penn State making progress, but two personnel moves still remain]. [[Sports Illustrated]], 2011-11-10.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rana L. Cash, [http://aol.sportingnews.com/ncaa-football/feed/2011-11/penn-state-scandal/story/tom-bradley-steps-in-with-very-mixed-emotions-at-penn-state &quot;Tom Bradley steps in with 'very mixed emotions' at Penn State&quot;], Sportingnews.com, 11 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt; On November 7, Pennsylvania state police Commissioner Frank Noonan said that though some may have fulfilled their legal obligation to report suspected abuse, &quot;somebody has to question about what I would consider the moral requirements for a human being that knows of sexual things that are taking place with a child.&quot;  Noonan added that anyone who knows about suspected abuse, &quot;whether you're a football coach or a university president or the guy sweeping the building,&quot; has &quot;a moral responsibility to call us.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url= http://www.cbssports.com/collegefootball/story/16017251/two-top-officials-step-down-amid-penn-state-scandal?ttag=gen10_on_all_fb_na_txt_0001 | title=Police official: Paterno didn't do enough to stop abuse | publisher=CBSSports.com | date=November 7, 2011 | accessdate=November 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Paterno said McQueary informed him that &quot;he had witnessed an incident in the shower ... but he at no time related to me the very specific actions contained in the Grand Jury report.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last1=Rittenberg |first1=Adam |last2=Bennett |first2=Brian |title=Joe Paterno statement on Sandusky case |date=November 6, 2011 |work=ESPN.com |url=http://espn.go.com/blog/bigten/post/_/id/37765/joe-paterno-statement-on-sandusky-case |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/639PgaQkQ |archivedate=November 12, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Further, criticism and condemnation of Penn State leadership and Paterno himself, including calls for his dismissal, followed reports of these arrests for their role in &quot;protecting Penn State’s brand instead of a child&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/sports/if-jerry-sandusky-allegations-are-true-penn-state-and-joe-paterno-deserve/2011/11/05/gIQAYIucqM_story.html?hpid=z2 | title=If Jerry Sandusky allegations are true, Penn State and Joe Paterno deserve part of the blame | first=Mike | last=Wise | newspaper=The Washington Post | location=Washington, DC | date=November 5, 2011 | accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://aol.sportingnews.com/ncaa-football/story/2011-11-07/university-culture-protected-paterno-buried-penn-state-deeper-in-scandal#ixzz1d4DsqvBZ | title=University culture protected Paterno, buried Penn State deeper in scandal | first=Matt | last=Hayes | newspaper=Sporting News | date=November 7, 2011 | accessdate=November 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and allowing Sandusky to retain emeritus status and unfettered access to the university's football program and facilities, despite knowledge of the allegations of sexual abuse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wetzel&quot;/&gt; In an interview with [[New York City]] radio station [[WFAN]], sports reporter [[Kim Jones (reporter)|Kim Jones]], a Penn State alumna, stated that, &quot;I can't believe [Paterno's] heart is that black, where he simply never thought about [Sandusky's 2002 incident] again and never thought about those poor kids who were looking for a male mentor, a strong man in their life.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://newyork.cbslocal.com/audio-on-demand/mike-francesa-1/ Mike'd Up]'', WFAN, November 9, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Former sports commentator [[Keith Olbermann]] called for Paterno to be immediately fired, saying that &quot;he failed all of the kids—the kid kids and the player kids—he purported to be protecting.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://current.com/shows/countdown/videos/worst-persons-michele-bachmann-bill-oreilly-joe-paterno Countdown with Keith Olbermann]'', Current TV, November 9, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 8, 2011, ''[[The Patriot-News]]'' of Harrisburg published a rare full-page, front-page editorial calling for the immediate resignation of Penn State President [[Graham Spanier]]; it also called for this to be Joe Paterno's last season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/our_view.html |title=OUR VIEW: Penn State's Graham Spanier, Joe Paterno need to leave as result of Jerry Sandusky case. Doing what the law required wasn't enough |author=''Patriot-News'' Editorial Board |work=The Patriot-News |date=November 8, 2011 |accessdate=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same day, an editorial in the ''[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]'' called for the resignations of both Joe Paterno and his assistant coach Mike McQueary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11312/1188241-87-0.stm |title=Paterno, McQueary need to do right thing |work=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette |date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sandusky gave his first interview since being arrested on November 14. In a phone interview with [[NBC]]'s [[Bob Costas]] on ''[[Rock Center with Brian Williams]]'', Sandusky denied the allegations, though he admitted showering with teenage boys and inadvertently touching them &quot;without intent of sexual contact.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;admission&quot; /&gt;  The interview received substantial coverage in the media, particularly regarding the manner in which Sandusky answered Costas when asked if he is sexually attracted to young boys:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2c811Br5qh8|title= Video report by Slate magazine about Costas’ interview|work=Slate - YouTube|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/3036789//vp/45302975#45302975|title=Morning Joe: Costas on Sandusky|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|url=http://www.thedailyshow.com/watch/tue-november-15-2011/jerry-sandusky-phone-interview|title=Jerry Sandusky phone interview|work=The Daily Show with Jon Stewart|2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{blockquote|COSTAS: &quot;Are you sexually attracted to young boys, to underage boys?&quot;&lt;/br&gt;
SANDUSKY: &quot;Am I sexually attracted to underage boys?&quot;&lt;/br&gt;
COSTAS: &quot;Yes.&quot;&lt;/br&gt;
SANDUSKY: &quot;Sexually attracted, you know, I enjoy young people. I love to be around them. But no I'm not sexually attracted to young boys.&quot;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/21134540/vp/45296467#45298030|title=Video of Bob Costas interview with Jerry Sandusky|work=NBC: Rock Center with Brian Williams|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/1111/15/ddhln.01.html|title=Transcripts - Sandusky: I`m Not a Pedophile; Penn State: How Could it Happen?|work=CNN|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nbcphiladelphia.com/news/local/133872303.html|title=Transcript: Jerry Sandusky Interview|work=[[WCAU]]|date=2011-11-15|accessdate=2011-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In the days following the interview, several potential victims contacted State College lawyer Andy Shubin to tell their stories, with one claiming Sandusky had abused him in the 1970s;&lt;ref name=1970s/&gt; as many as eight victims may be in contact with attorneys, according to ''Sports Illustrated''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first1=L. Jon|last1=Wertheim|first2=David|last2=Epstein|title=Special Report: Scandal. Shame. A search for answers at Penn State|date=November 21, 2011; posted online on November 16, 2011|publisher=Sports Illustrated|url=http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/2011/magazine/11/16/penn.st/index.html|accessdate=2011-11-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Response==
The allegations have impacted personnel and operations for both Penn State and The Second Mile. Penn State has responded in various ways, such as removing Sandusky's image from a mural near the college,&lt;ref name=Armas&gt;{{cite news|last=Armas|first=Genaro C.|title=Paterno, Penn State president fired amid sex-abuse scandal|url=http://www.twincities.com/ci_19302188|accessdate=10 November 2011|newspaper=Pioneer Press|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and renaming an ice cream flavor which had been created in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sandusky Ice Cream Yanked on Website|url=http://www.lostlettermen.com/11-7-2011-sandusky-ice-cream-penn-state|accessdate=10 November 2011|newspaper=PennLive.com|date=9 November 2011}} ].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Wayback|date=20100608123651 |url=http://creamery.psu.edu/products/ice-cream |title=All Ice Cream Flavors }}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has also responded by ousting both Joe Paterno and Graham Spanier, as well as placing Mike McQueary on indefinite paid administrative leave.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11315/1189216-100.stm |title=Penn State coach McQueary on 'indefinite' paid leave (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, November 11, 2011) |publisher=Post-gazette.com |date=2011-11-11 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;mcqueary&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://blog.pennlive.com/davidjones/2011/11/mcqueary_tells_psu_wideouts_he.html | title = McQueary tells PSU wideouts he's out as coach and in &quot;protective custody&quot; | author = Jones, David | publisher = Harrisburg Patriot-News | date = November 11, 2011 | accessdate = November 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the week after Paterno's firing, the [[Big Ten Conference]] removed his name from the championship trophy for its [[Big Ten Football Championship Game|conference championship game]], renaming it the Stagg Championship Trophy.  The inaugural game was scheduled for December 2011, and the trophy was originally named the Stagg-Paterno Championship Trophy after Paterno and [[Amos Alonzo Stagg]], a college football pioneer.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Rittenberg |first=Adam |title=Joe Paterno's name off Big Ten trophy |date=November 14, 2011 |work=ESPN.com |url=http://espn.go.com/college-football/story/_/id/7233492/big-ten-removes-joe-paterno-name-championship-trophy |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63C8Ryuw0 |archivedate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Fernandez | first=Bernard |title=Big Ten reveals new divisions, names trophy after Stagg and Paterno |date=December 14, 2011 |work=philly.com |publisher=[[Philadelphia Media Network]] |url=http://articles.philly.com/2010-12-14/sports/25292051_1_jim-delany-divisions-football-awards |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63C8GCgIi |archivedate=November 14, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In anticipation of further fallout, Penn State's Aa1 [[bond rating|revenue-bond rating]] was &quot;placed on review for possible downgrade&quot; by [[Moody's Investors Service]] because of the scandal's possible effects on the university's finances.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Pennsylvania State May Be Downgraded by Moody’s in Wake of Abuse Scandal|author=Brian Chappatta and Greg Chang|publisher=Bloomberg|date=November 11, 2011|url=http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2011-11-11/pennsylvania-state-may-be-downgraded-by-moody-s-in-wake-of-abuse-scandal.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Jack Raykovitz, the longtime president and CEO of The Second Mile, announced his resignation on November 14.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/us/2011/11/14/president-charity-linked-to-penn-state-sex-abuse-scandal-resigns/ |title=President Of Charity Linked To Penn State Sex Abuse Scandal Resigns |publisher=Fox News |date=2010-04-07 |accessdate=2011-11-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the United States Congressional program [[Angels in Adoption]], subsequently rescinded its earlier 2002 award to Sandusky for his work with The Second Mile &quot;in light of the serious allegations against him, and to preserve the integrity of the Angels in Adoption program.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |publisher=[[Angels in Adoption]] |title= 
A Statement from the Congressional Coalition on Adoption Institute (11/10/2011) |date=November 15, 2011 |url=http://www.angelsinadoption.org/ |archiveurl=http://webcitation.org/63DYKx9ke |archivedate=November 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Fitzgerald |first=Thomas |title=Santorum sponsored honor for accused PSU Coach |date=November 9, 2011 |newspaper=[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]] |url=http://www.philly.com/philly/blogs/big_tent/Santorum-honored-accused-PSU-Coach-as-angel.html |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/63Deb5ZUN |archivedate=November 15, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Victim One has withdrawn from Central Mountain High School due to [[bullying]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.pennlive.com/midstate/index.ssf/2011/11/alleged_jerry_sandusky_victim.html&lt;/ref&gt;, and the boy's mother has stated that the high school did not do enough to prevent the fallout.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/22/penn-state-scandal-jerry-sandusky-victim-mother_n_1108979.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student response===
[[File:ThecornerSC.JPG|thumb|250px|Downtown [[State College, Pennsylvania|State College]] was the location of the November 9-10 student protest.]]
A few Penn State students, angered over Spanier's role in the 2002 incident as well as his statement of support for Curley and Schultz, created a [[Facebook]] page, &quot;Fire Graham Spanier&quot;, to call on Penn State's Board of Trustees to fire Spanier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.collegian.psu.edu/archive/2011/11/06/student_reaction_to_grand_jury.aspx | title=Penn State students react to grand jury investigation, charges against former coach Sandusky, AD Curley, VP for Finance and Business Schultz | first=Jessica | last=Tully | newspaper=The Daily Collegian | location=University Park, PA | date=November 6, 2011 | accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; An online petition at [[change.org]] calling for Spanier's ouster garnered over 1,700 signatures in four days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.pittsburghlive.com/x/pittsburghtrib/news/breaking/s_766403.html | title=Online petition seeks ouster of Penn State president Spanier| first=Tom| last=Fontaine | newspaper=[[Pittsburgh Tribune-Review]] | location=[[Pittsburgh]]| date=November 6, 2011 | accessdate=November 6, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

After the termination of Paterno was announced on live television, students and non-students rioted near the Penn State campus. Sources estimate that thousands of students and others gathered to support Paterno, with some tipping over a [[WTAJ-TV|WTAJ]] news truck.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11314/1188877-100.stm |title=Riots break out as thousands take to State College streets |newspaper=Pittsburgh Post-Gazette |date=November 10, 2011 |first=Michael |last=Sanserino}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police used tear gas in response. No major injuries were reported.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nj.com/rutgersfootball/index.ssf/2011/11/penn_state_sex_scandal_scene_t.html |newspaper=The Star-Ledger |title=Penn State scandal: Scene turns ugly as students react to Joe Paterno's firing |date=November 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately $20,000 in damages resulted from the riot, with police criticizing the timing of the announcement at 10 P.M. in the evening as exarcebating the situation.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.centredaily.com/2011/11/16/2988118/king-says-psu-gave-little-warning.html&lt;/ref&gt;

On November 10, a group of Penn State alumni set up and announced ProudPSUforRAINN,&lt;ref name=&quot;abcnews_rainn&quot; /&gt; a fundraiser for the anti-sexual violence network [[Rape, Abuse &amp; Incest National Network|RAINN]] with a goal of $500,000, saying
&lt;blockquote&gt;
After having so closely identified with all things Penn State over the past 15 years, the recent events have shaken our beliefs – and those of other alumni – to the core. Simply put, Penn State is way bigger than the alleged actions of a few people. To honor the victims, our goal is to raise over $500,000 – one dollar for each of Penn State’s 557,000 alumni.&lt;ref name=psu_for_rainn&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rainn.org/ProudPSUforRAINN|title=ProudPSUforRAINN|publisher=RAINN|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=abcnews_rainn&gt;{{cite web|last=James|first=Susan Donaldson|title=Penn State Alums Raise Funds for Victims, Bring Back Pride|url=http://abcnews.go.com/Health/penn-state-alums-raise-money-victims-sex-crimes/story?id=14931201#.Tr1rL_KwUwZ|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=washpost_studentsplan&gt;{{cite web|last=Johnson|first=Jenna|title=Penn State students plan candlelight vigil, raise money for victims|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/campus-overload/post/penn-state-students-plan-candlelight-vigil-raise-money-for-victims/2011/11/10/gIQAZPXM9M_blog.html|publisher=Washington Post|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
&lt;/blockquote&gt; 
As of 2:00 p.m. the next day, they had raised over $113,000 and as of 3:00 p.m. the following Sunday, over $320,000.&lt;ref name=psu_for_rainn /&gt; Students also planned a [[candlelight vigil]] on the lawn of Old Main with over 10,000 planning on attending.&lt;ref name=candlelight_vigil&gt;{{cite web|title=Candle Light Vigil for Abused Victims|url=http://www.facebook.com/event.php?eid=144845055615007|accessdate=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=washpost_studentsplan /&gt;  Former [[NFL]] player and Penn State alum, sports broadcaster [[LaVar Arrington]] spoke at the event which attracted an estimated ten thousand.&lt;ref name=ap_vigil&gt;{{cite news|title=Candlelight vigil draws thousands at Penn State, tries to brighten university’s darkest week|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/national/candlelight-vigil-draws-hundreds-at-penn-state-tries-to-brighten-universitys-darkest-week/2011/11/11/gIQAphiiDN_story.html|agency=Associated Press|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=sportscenter&gt;{{cite news|title=Sportscenter, 10:30pm EST|accessdate=12 November 2011|newspaper=ESPN}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the start of the season's final home game, a November 12 game against [[Nebraska Cornhuskers football|Nebraska]], the players and coaches from both teams knelt at midfield for a group prayer led by Nebraska's assistant coach Ron Brown.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Bob|last=Ford|title=Sorrow and resolve on this day for Penn State faithful|date=November 13, 2011|publisher=''[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]]''|url=http://www.philly.com/philly/sports/colleges/20111113_Bob_Ford__Sorrow_and_resolve_on_this_day_for_Penn_State_faithful.html|accessdate=2011-11-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Frank|last=Fitzpatrick|title=Bizarre day highlights Penn State's past, present, future|date=November 13, 2011|publisher=''[[The Philadelphia Inquirer]]''|url=http://www.philly.com/philly/sports/colleges/20111113_Bizarre_day_highlights_Penn_State_s_past__present__future.html|accessdate=2011-11-14|quote=The majority of fans wore blue, as student leaders and school officials had urged, to help raise awareness of child abuse.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ouster of Spanier and Paterno===
[[File:RodneyErickson.png|thumb|right|250px|Penn State's Board of Trustees appointed [[Rodney Erickson]] as interim president on November 9.]]
On November 8, 2011, Spanier canceled Paterno's weekly Tuesday news conference, citing legal concerns.  It was to have been the coach's first public appearance since Sandusky's arrest.  Paterno reported that Spanier canceled the press conference without providing Paterno with an explanation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Report: Penn St. planning Paterno's exit|publisher=Fox Sports|url=http://msn.foxsports.com/collegefootball/story/Penn-State-planning-Joe-Paterno-exit-amid-sexual-abuse-scandal-110811|date=November 8, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  That same day, ''[[The New York Times]]'' reported that Penn State was planning Paterno's exit at the close of the college football season.  Based on interviews with two individuals briefed on conversations among top university officials, the ''Times'' reported: &quot;The Board of Trustees has yet to determine the precise timing of Mr. Paterno’s exit, but it is clear that (he) will not coach another season.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Penn State Said to Be Planning Paterno Exit Amid Scandal|newspaper=The New York Times|date=November 8, 2011|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/09/sports/ncaafootball/penn-state-said-to-be-planning-paternos-exit.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The following day, the Associated Press reported that Paterno had decided to retire at the end of the 2011 football season, saying that he didn't want to be a distraction.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=AP Source: Paterno to retire at end of season|newspaper=Associated Press|date=November 9, 2011|url=http://hosted.ap.org/dynamic/stories/F/FBC_PENN_STATE_ABUSE?SITE=AZPHG&amp;SECTION=HOME&amp;TEMPLATE=DEFAULT}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a statement announcing his retirement, Paterno said, &quot;It is one of the great sorrows of my life. With the benefit of hindsight, I wish I had done more.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-400_162-57321343/paterno-to-retire-at-end-of-football-season/ |title=Paterno to retire at end of football season |publisher=CBS News |date=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the afternoon of November 9, ''[[The Express-Times]]'' of [[Easton, Pennsylvania]], reported that the board had given Spanier an ultimatum—resign before that night's meeting or be fired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Penn State President Graham Spanier will quit or be fired today in wake of Sandusky charges |work=[[The Express-Times]] |date=November 9, 2011 |url=http://www.lehighvalleylive.com/breaking-news/index.ssf/2011/11/penn_state_president_graham_sp.html |accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Simpson |first=Ian |publisher=Reuters |date=November 9, 2011 |title=UPDATE 3-Paterno retires, Penn State president may be next |url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/11/09/usa-crime-coach-idUSN1E7A80Z520111109 |accessdate=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  At that night's meeting, Spanier, facing almost certain termination, resigned; provost [[Rodney Erickson]] was named interim president.&lt;ref&gt;McGill, Andrew; Assad, Matt; Sheehan, Daniel Patrick (November 10, 2011).  [http://articles.mcall.com/2011-11-10/news/mc-penn-state-spanier-20111109_1_joe-paterno-president-graham-spanier-joepa &quot;Penn State President Graham Spanier Resigns in Wake of Scandal&quot;]. ''[[The Morning Call]]''. Retrieved November 11, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;  At the same meeting, the board turned down Paterno's offer to resign, instead voting to fire him immediately; defensive coordinator [[Tom Bradley (American football)|Tom Bradley]] was named interim coach for the remainder of the season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nj.com/sports/mustsee/index.ssf/2011/11/penn_state_fires_joe_paterno_a.html |title=Penn State fires Joe Paterno as head coach amid sex-abuse scandal |newspaper=The Star-Ledger |date=November 9, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://live.psu.edu/story/56306 |title=Board of Trustees announces leadership changes at Penn State |date=November 9, 2011 |publisher=The Pennsylvania State University |work=Penn State Live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/09/justice/pennsylvania-coach-abuse-charges/index.html?hpt=hp_t1 |title=Trustees: Penn State president removed, Paterno out immediately |publisher=CNN |date=November 10, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An attorney retained by the families of some of the boys who were allegedly abused by Sandusky has criticized the decision by the board to fire Paterno, saying, &quot;The school let the victims down once, and I think they owed it to the victims to at least gauge how the immediate termination decision would impact them as opposed to Mr. Paterno's resignation at the end of the year.&quot;&lt;ref name=dc_lawyercriticizes&gt;{{cite web|last=Gallagher|first=Christina|title=Lawyer criticizes Board of Trustees' decision to fire Joe Paterno|url=http://www.collegian.psu.edu/archive/2011/11/11/lawyer_criticizes_board_of_trustees_decision_to_fire_joe_paterno.aspx|publisher=The Daily Collegian|accessdate=12 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, one of the trustees told ''[[The Morning Call]]'' of [[Allentown, Pennsylvania|Allentown]] that he and his colleagues had no choice but to fire Paterno in order to contain the growing outrage over the scandal.  According to the trustee, the board considered letting Paterno stay on for the rest of the year with Bradley as team spokesman, but ultimately decided it would still keep the focus on Paterno.  The board also didn't like that Paterno released statements on his own rather than through the school, with some feeling he may have breached his contract.  The anonymous trustee said that he and many of his colleagues felt Paterno either &quot;knew about [the abuse] and swept it under the rug, or he didn't ask enough questions.&quot;  As for Spanier, the board was very angered by Spanier's statements of support for Curley and Schultz.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy, Sam; McGill, Andrew. [http://www.mcall.com/news/breaking/mc-penn-state-trustees-turnaround-20111110,0,3236661.story Trustee: Media frenzy forced board's hand]. ''[[The Morning Call]]'', 2011-11-10.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Civil lawsuits===

Soon after the scandal broke, commentators noted that civil lawsuits against Jerry Sandusky and Penn State were inevitable.&lt;ref&gt;Armas, Genaro; Scolforo, Mark. [http://news.yahoo.com/penn-state-abuse-scandal-likely-spawn-lawsuits-073155706.html Penn State abuse scandal likely to spawn lawsuits]. ''[[Yahoo News]]'', 2011-11-18.&lt;/ref&gt; On November 28, 2011, &quot;Victim 1&quot;, as he was identified in the indictment, and his mother, hired attorneys to pursue civil claims against Sandusky and Penn State.&lt;ref&gt; [http://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/boni--zack-llc-and-mclaughlin--lauricella-pc-to-represent-victim-1-and-his-mother-in-the-jerry-sandusky-sexual-abuse-matter-134631603.html Boni &amp; Zack LLC and McLaughlin &amp; Lauricella, P.C. to Represent Victim 1 and His Mother in the Jerry Sandusky Sexual Abuse Matter]. ''[[PR Newswire]]'', 2011-11-28.&lt;/ref&gt; On November 30, 2011, the first lawsuit by a victim of sexual abuse was filed against Penn State and Sandusky alleging over 100 incidents of sexual abuse; the victim was identified in the suit only as &quot;John Doe A.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cnn.com/2011/11/30/justice/pennsylvania-penn-state-scandal/index.html First lawsuit filed against Sandusky in Penn State child sex scandal]. ''[[CNN.com]]'', 2011-11-30.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
*[http://espn.go.com/college-football/story/_/id/7212054/key-dates-penn-state-nittany-lions-sex-abuse-case Sandusky, Penn State case timeline]

{{Penn State sex abuse scandal}}
{{Penn State Nittany Lions football navbox}}

[[Category:2011 scandals]]
[[Category:Child sexual abuse]]
[[Category:College football controversies]]
[[Category:Penn State Nittany Lions football|Sex abuse scandal]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania State University|Sex abuse scandal]]
[[Category:2011 in Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Crime in Pennsylvania]]

[[id:Skandal pelecehan seksual terhadap anak Jerry Sandusky]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
