<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33685" ns="0" title="Weimar Republic"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox former country
|native_name = ''Deutsches Reich''
|conventional_long_name = German Reich
|common_name = Germany
|government_type = [[Federalism|Federal]] [[Parliamentary republic|parliamentary]] [[republic]]
|continent = Europe
|region = Central Europe
|country = Germany
|era = Interwar period
|year_start = 1918
|date_start = 9 November
|event1 = Hitler appointed chancellor
|date_event1 = 30 January 1933
|year_event1 = 1933
|event2 = [[Reichstag fire]]
|date_event2 = 27 February 1933
|year_event2 = 1933
|event_end = [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]]
|year_end = 1933
|date_end = 23 March
|p1 = German Empire
|flag_p1 = Flag of the German Empire.svg
|s1 = Nazi Germany
|flag_s1 = Flag of Germany 1933.svg
|image_flag =Flag_of_Germany_(3-2_aspect_ratio).svg
|flag = Flag of Germany#Weimar Republic
|image_coat = Coat of Arms of Germany.svg
|symbol = 
|symbol_type = Coat of Arms
|image_map =Weimar Republic 1930.svg
|image_map_caption = Territory of Germany during the Weimar period
|national_anthem = Das Lied der Deutschen
|common_languages = German
|capital = Berlin
|latd=52|latm=31|latNS=N|longd=13|longm=24|longEW=E
|currency = [[German Papiermark|Mark (ℳ), coll. Papiermark]] (1919-1923)&lt;br/&gt;[[German Rentenmark]]&lt;br/&gt;(1923-1924)&lt;br/&gt;[[Reichsmark|Reichsmark (ℛℳ)]] (1924–1933)
|
|title_leader = [[President of Germany (1919–1945)|President]]
|leader1 = [[Friedrich Ebert]]
|year_leader1 = 1918–1925
|leader2 = [[Paul von Hindenburg]]
|year_leader2 = 1925-1934
|title_deputy = [[Chancellor of Germany#Chancellor of the Weimar Republic (1919–1933)|Chancellor]]
|deputy1 = [[Philipp Scheidemann]] (first)
|year_deputy1 = 1919
|year_deputy2= 1919-20
|deputy2 = [[Gustav Bauer]]
|year_deputy3= 1923
|deputy3 = [[Gustav Stresemann]]
|deputy4 = [[Heinrich Brüning]]
|year_deputy4= 1930-32
|deputy5 = [[Franz von Papen]]
|year_deputy5 = 1932
|deputy6 = [[Kurt von Schleicher]]
[[Adolf Hitler]] (last)
|year_deputy6 = 1932
- 1933
|deputy7 = [[Adolf Hitler]] (last)
|year_deputy7 = 1933
|stat_year1 = 1925&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gonschior.de/weimar/Deutschland/index.htm|title= Das Deutsche Reich im Überblick|work=Wahlen in der Weimarer Republik|accessdate=2007-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|stat_area1 = 468787
|stat_pop1 = 62411000
|house1 = [[Reichsrat (Germany)|Reichsrat]]
|type_house1 = State council
|legislature = [[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]
|footnotes = The above shown coat-of-arms was the version used until 1928, then replaced by the conclusive version as shown in section [[#Flag and coat of arms|Flag and coat of arms]].&lt;ref&gt;Cf. ''Der Große Brockhaus: Handbuch des Wissens in zwanzig Bänden'': 21 vols., completely revis. ed., Leipzig: F. A. Brockhaus, &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;1928-1935, vol. 4 (1929): &quot;Vierter Band Chi–Dob&quot;, article: 'Deutsches Reich', pp. 611-704, here pp. 648 and 651. No ISBN.&lt;/ref&gt;
|today = {{flag|Germany}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Poland}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Russia}}
}}

The '''Weimar Republic''' ({{lang|de|Weimarer Republik}} {{IPA-de|ˈvaɪmaʁɐ ʁepuˈbliːk||De-WeimarRepublic.ogg}}) is the name given by [[historian]]s to the parliamentary republic established in 1919 in [[Germany]] to replace the [[German Empire|imperial form of government]]. It was named after [[Weimar]], the city where the [[constitutional assembly]] took place. 
Its official name was ''Deutsches [[Reich]]'' (sometimes translated as ''German Empire'', but ''[[:wikt:Reich|Reich]]'' can also mean &quot;[[realm]]&quot;), but it was usually just referred to as Germany in English, and as ''Deutschland'' in German. 

Following [[World War I]], the republic emerged from the [[German Revolution of 1918–1919|German Revolution]] in November 1918. In 1919, a [[Weimar National Assembly|national assembly]] convened in [[Weimar]], where [[Weimar constitution|a new constitution]] for the German Reich was written, then adopted on 11 August of that same year. Germany's period of [[liberal democracy]] lapsed in the early 1930s, leading to the ascent of the [[Nazi Party]] and [[Adolf Hitler]] in 1933. Although the constitution of 1919 was never officially repealed, the legal measures taken by the Nazi government in February and March 1933, commonly known as ''[[Gleichschaltung]]'' (&quot;coordination&quot;) meant that the government could legislate contrary to the constitution. The constitution became irrelevant; thus, 1933 is usually seen as the end of the Weimar Republic and the beginning of Hitler's [[Nazi Germany|Third ''Reich'']].

In its 14 years, the Weimar Republic was faced with numerous problems, including [[Inflation in the Weimar Republic|hyperinflation]], political extremists on the left and the right and their paramilitaries, and hostility from the victors of World War I, who tried twice to restructure Germany's reparations payments through the [[Dawes Plan]] and the [[Young Plan]]. However, it overcame many of the requirements of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], (Germany eventually repaid a reduced amount of the reparations required of the treaty with the last payment being made on October 3, 2010&lt;ref&gt;http://www.jpost.com/International/Article.aspx?id=189637&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agreement_on_German_External_Debts&lt;/ref&gt;), reformed the [[currency]], and unified tax politics and the [[railway]] system, as well as creating a unique cultural impact with its art, music and cinema.

==Name==
Despite its political form, the new republic was still known as ''Deutsches Reich'' in German. This phrase was commonly translated into English as ''[[German Empire]]'', although the German word ''[[Reich]]'' has a broader range of connotations than the English &quot;empire&quot;, so the name is most often translated to the ''German Reich'' in English. The English word &quot;realm&quot; captures broadly the same meaning. The common short form remained ''Germany''.

==Flag and coat of arms==
After the introduction of the republic, the flag and coat of arms of Germany were altered to reflect the political changes. The republican [[tricolour]] is based on the flag that the [[Paulskirche Constitution]] of 1849 introduced, which was decided upon by the [[Frankfurt National Assembly|German National Assembly]] in Frankfurt upon Main, at the peak of the German civic movement that demanded parliamentary participation and unification of the German states.
[[File:Flag of the German Confederation (war).svg|thumb|left|Naval ensign of Reichsflotte (1848-1852).]]
[[File:Flag of German Empire (jack 1903).svg|thumb|left|Jack of the Kaiserliche Marine 1903-19]]
[[File:Flag of Weimar Republic (jack).svg|thumb|left|Jack of the Reichsmarine 1918-35]]


The achievements and signs of this movement were mostly done away with after its downfall and the political reaction. Only the tiny German [[Principality of Waldeck-Pyrmont]] upheld the tradition and continued to use the [[National colours of Germany|German colours]] called [[Schwarz-Rot-Gold]] in German ({{lang-en|[[Sable (heraldry)|Black]]-[[Gules|Red]]-[[Or (heraldry)|Gold]]}}).

These signs had remained symbols of the Paulskirche movement and Weimar Germany wanted to express its view of being also originated in that political movement between 1848 and 1852. However, anti-republicans opposed this flag. While the first [[Reichsflotte|German Confederal Navy (''Reichsflotte'')]] (1848-1852) had proudly used a naval [[ensign]] based on Schwarz-Rot-Gold, the Weimar republic navy, or ''[[Reichsmarine]]'' (1918-1935) insisted on using the pre-1918 colours of the previous [[Kaiserliche Marine]] (1871-1918), which were Black-White-Red, as did the German merchant marine.
[[File:Coat of Arms of Germany.svg|thumb|right|The official German coat of arms (Reichswappen) from 1928 to 1935.]]

The republican coat of arms took up the idea of the German crest established by the Paulskirche movement, using  the same [[Heraldic animal|charge animal]], an eagle, in the same colours (black, red and gold), but modernising its form, including a reduction of the heads from two to one. [[Friedrich Ebert]] initially declared the official German coat of arms to be a design by [[Emil Doepler]] (shown in the infobox above) as of 11 November 1919, following a decision of the German government.&lt;ref&gt;Jana Leichsenring, &quot;Staatssymbole: Der Bundesadler&quot;, in: ''Aktueller Begriff'', [[Deutscher Bundestag]]&amp;nbsp;— Wissenschaftliche Dienste (ed.), No. 83/08 (12 December 2008), p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, in 1928 the ''Reichswappen'' (Reich's coat of arms) designed by Tobias Schwab (1887–1967) in 1926 [or 1924&lt;ref&gt;According to sources of the German national football team Schwab created the emblem for the team in 1924.&lt;/ref&gt;] replaced it as the official emblem for the German Olympic team.&lt;ref&gt;Cf. Reichswappen as depicted in the table: &quot;Deutsches Reich: Wappen I&quot; in: ''Der Große Brockhaus: Handbuch des Wissens in zwanzig Bänden'': 21 vols., Leipzig: Brockhaus, &lt;sup&gt;15&lt;/sup&gt;1928–1935; vol. 4 &quot;Chi–Dob&quot; (1929), p. 648.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jürgen Hartmann, &quot;Der Bundesadler&quot;, in: ''Vierteljahreshefte für Zeitgeschichte'' (No. 03/2008), [[Institut für Zeitgeschichte]] (ed.), pp. 495-509, here p. 501.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jana Leichsenring 2008 p. 2&quot;&gt;Jana Leichsenring, &quot;Staatssymbole: Der Bundesadler&quot;, in: ''Aktueller Begriff'', [[Deutscher Bundestag]]&amp;nbsp;— Wissenschaftliche Dienste (ed.), No. 83/08 (12 December 2008), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Reichswehr]] adopted the new Reichswappen in 1927.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jana Leichsenring 2008 p. 2&quot;/&gt;

Doepler's design then became the ''Reichsschild'' (Reich's [[Escutcheon (heraldry)|escutcheon]]) with restricted use such as [[pennon|pennant]] for government vehicles. The 1949 the [[West Germany|Federal Republic of Germany (West Germany)]] adopted all three signs of Weimar Republic, Reichswappen, Reichsschild and Reichsflagge as Bundeswappen, Bundesschild and Bundesflagge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jana Leichsenring 2008 p. 2&quot;/&gt;

==November Revolution==
{{Main|German Revolution of 1918–1919}}

In October 1918, the [[constitution]] of the German Empire was reformed to introduce a [[parliamentary]] system similar to the British, but this soon became obsolete.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}  On 29 October, [[rebellion]] broke out in [[Kiel]] among sailors. There, sailors, soldiers and workers began electing worker and soldier councils (''Arbeiter''- und ''Soldatenräte'') modeled after the [[Soviet (council)|soviets]] of the [[Russian Revolution of 1917]]. The revolution spread throughout Germany, and participants seized military and civil powers in individual cities. The power takeover was achieved everywhere without loss of life and control was firmly in the hands of the largest political party, the social democrats.  Nevertheless, the rebellion caused great fear in the establishment and in the middle classes because of the [[Russian SFSR|Soviet Russia]] connotation of the councils. For the supporters of a monarchy, the country seemed to be on the verge of a communist revolution. On 7 November, the revolution had reached [[Munich]], causing King [[Ludwig III of Bavaria]] to flee.  Groener, a self-appointed military expert in the MSPD was sent to Kiel to prevent any further unrest and took on the task of controlling the mutinous sailors and their supporters in the Kiel barracks.  The sailors and soldiers, inexperienced in matters of revolutionary combat, welcomed Groener as an experienced politician and allowed him to negotiate a settlement, thus defusing the initial anger of the revolutionaries in uniform. 

At the time, the traditional political representation of the working class, the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democratic Party]] was divided into two major factions: one group, the Independent Social Democrats called for immediate peace [[negotiations]] and favoured  a [[socialist]] system of industrial control. To keep their influence, the remaining Majority Social Democrats (MSPD), who supported the war efforts and a parliamentary system, decided to make use of their support at grass roots and put themselves at the front of the movement, and on 7 November, demanded that Kaiser [[Wilhelm II, German Emperor|Wilhelm II]] abdicate. When he refused, [[Prince Max of Baden]] simply announced that he had done so and frantically attempted to establish a [[Regent|regency]] under another member of the [[House of Hohenzollern]]. On 9 November 1918, the &quot;German Republic&quot; was proclaimed by MSPD member [[Philipp Scheidemann]] at the [[Reichstag (building)|''Reichstag'' building]] in Berlin, to the fury of [[Friedrich Ebert]] and James Mitchell, the leaders of the MSPD, who thought that the question of monarchy or republic should be answered by a national assembly. Two hours later, a &quot;Free Socialist Republic&quot; was proclaimed, {{convert |2|km|mi|abbr=on}} away, at the ''[[Berliner Stadtschloss]]''. The proclamation was issued by [[Karl Liebknecht]], co-leader (with [[Rosa Luxemburg]]) of the [[communist]] [[Spartakusbund]] (Spartacist League), a group of a few hundred supporters of the Russian revolution that had allied itself with the USPD in 1917.
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-P011502, Berlin, Reichskanzlei, Philipp Scheidemann.jpg|thumb|upright|Philipp Scheidemann talking from a window of the [[Reich Chancellery]] building to the people, November 9, 1918]]

On 9 November, in a legally questionable act, ''Reichskanzler'' Prince Max of Baden transferred his powers to Friedrich Ebert, who, shattered by the monarchy's fall, reluctantly accepted. In view of the mass support for more radical reforms among the workers's councils a [[coalition]] government called &quot;Council of People's Commissioners&quot; (''Rat der Volksbeauftragten'') was established, consisting of three MSPD and three USPD members. Led by Ebert for the MSPD and [[Hugo Haase]] for the USPD it sought to act as a provisional cabinet of ministers. But the power question was unanswered.  Although the new government was confirmed by the Berlin worker and soldier council, it was opposed by the [[Spartacist League]]. Ebert called for a National Congress of Councils, which took place from 16 December to 20 December 1918, and in which the MSPD had the majority. Thus, Ebert was able to institute elections for a provisional National Assembly that would be given the task of writing a democratic constitution for parliamentary government, marginalizing the movement that called for a socialist republic (see below).

On 11 November, [[Armistice with Germany (Compiègne)|an armistice was signed at Compiègne]] by German representatives. It effectively ended military operations between the Allies and Germany. It amounted to German capitulation, without any concessions by the Allies; the naval blockade would continue until complete peace terms were agreed.

From November 1918 to January 1919, Germany was governed by the Council of People's Commissioners, under the leadership of Ebert and Haase. It issued a large number of decrees that radically shifted German policies. It introduced the eight-hour workday, domestic labour reform, works councils, agricultural labour reform, right of civil-service associations, local municipality social welfare relief (split between ''Reich'' and States) and important national health insurance, re-instatement of demobilised workers, protection from arbitrary dismissal with appeal as a right, regulated wage agreement, and universal suffrage from 20 years of age in all types of elections&amp;nbsp;— local and national.

To ensure his fledgling government maintained control over the country, Ebert made an agreement with the [[Oberste Heeresleitung|OHL]] (supreme army command), now led by Ludendorff's successor General [[Wilhelm Groener]]. The '[[Ebert–Groener pact]]' stipulated that the government would not attempt to reform the army so long as the army swore to protect the state. On the one hand, this agreement symbolised the acceptance of the new government by the military, assuaging concern among the middle classes; on the other hand, it was thought contrary to working-class interests by left wing social democrats and communists, and was also opposed by the far right who believed democracy would make Germany weaker. The new ''Reichswehr'' armed forces, limited by the [[Treaty of Versailles]] to 100,000 army soldiers and 15,000 sailors, remained fully under the control of the German [[Officer (armed forces)|Officer]] Class despite its nominal re-organisation.

As in other countries, it came to the permanent split in the social democratic movement, into the democratic SPD and the Communists.{{Citation needed|date=June 2009}}&lt;!--Did it really? After WW1, communist and socialist parties split in two all over Europe and beyond; that was also the policy of the 3rd international.--&gt; There was no revolution because the right wing of the socialist movement, led by Ebert and Scheideman, supported the republic they had brought into being.  Combined action on the part of the socialists was not possible without action from the millions of workers who stood midway between the [[parliament]]arians and the revolutionaries wanted to strengthen the powers of the workers' councils. 

The rift between the two socialist parties became final after Ebert called upon the OHL for troops to put down another Berlin army mutiny on 23 November 1918, in which soldiers had captured the city's garrison commander and closed off the ''Reichskanzlei'' where the Council of People's Commissioners was situated. The ensuing street fighting left several dead and injured on both sides. The USPD leaders were outraged by what they believed was treachery by the MSPD, which, in their view, had joined with the anti-communist military to suppress the revolution. Thus, the USPD left the Council of People's Commissioners after only seven weeks. In December, the split deepened when the [[Communist Party of Germany]] (KPD) was formed out of a number of radical left-wing groups, including the left wing of the USPD and the &quot;[[Spartacist League]]&quot; group.

In January, the Spartacist League and others in the streets of Berlin made more armed attempts to establish [[communism]], known as the [[Spartacist uprising]]. Those attempts were put down by paramilitary ''[[Freikorps]]'' units consisting of volunteer soldiers. Bloody street fights culminated in the beating and shooting deaths of [[Rosa Luxemburg]] and [[Karl Liebknecht]] after their arrests on 15 January. With the affirmation of Ebert, those responsible were not tried before a [[court martial]], leading to lenient sentences, which made Ebert unpopular among radical leftists.
[[File:Offizielle Postkarte Weimarer Nationalkversammlung.jpg|thumb|left|Official postcard of the National Assembly.]]

The National Assembly elections took place on 19 January 1919. In this time, the radical left-wing parties, including the USPD and KPD, were barely able to get themselves organized, leading to a solid majority of seats for the MSPD moderate forces. To avoid the ongoing fights in Berlin, the National Assembly convened in the city of [[Weimar, Germany|Weimar]], giving the future Republic its unofficial name. The [[Weimar Constitution]] created a republic under a [[parliamentary republic|parliamentary republic system]] with the ''Reichstag'' elected by [[proportional representation]]. The democratic parties obtained a solid 80% of the vote.

During the debates in Weimar, fighting continued. A [[Bavarian Soviet Republic|Soviet republic]] was declared in [[Munich]], but was quickly put down by ''Freikorps'' and remnants of the regular army. The fall of the [[Munich Soviet Republic]] to these units, many of which were situated on the extreme right, resulted in the growth of [[far-right]] movements and organizations in [[Bavaria]], including [[Organisation Consul]], the [[NSDAP]], and societies of exiled Russian Monarchists. Sporadic fighting continued to flare up around the country. In eastern provinces, forces loyal to Germany's fallen Monarchy fought the republic, while militias of Polish nationalists fought for independence: [[Greater Poland Uprising (1918–1919)|Great Poland Uprising]] in [[Provinz Posen]] and three [[Silesian Uprisings]] in [[Upper Silesia]].

Germany lost the war because the country ran out of allies and its economic resources were running out; support among the population began to crumble in 1916 and by mid-1918 there was support for the war only among the die-hard monarchists and conservatives. The decisive blow came with the entry of the United States into the conflict, which made the vast industrial resources available to the beleaguered allies.&lt;ref&gt;Kitchen, Germany, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge UK 1996)|&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the German armies were still on French and Belgian territory when the war ended on 11 November.  In a hearing on the reasons for Germany's defeat in 1920, Hindenburg claimed that it was the defeatism of the civilian population that had made defeat inevitable.  The die-hard nationalists then blamed the civilians for betraying the army and the surrender. This was the &quot;Stab-in-the-Back Myth&quot; that was unceasingly propagated by the right in the 1920s and ensured that the monarchists and conservatives would never support the government of the &quot;November criminals&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wilhelm Diest and E. J. Feuchtwanger, &quot;The Military Collapse of the German Empire: the Reality Behind the Stab-in-the-Back Myth,&quot; ''War in History,'' April 1996, Vol. 3 Issue 2, pp 186-207&lt;/ref&gt;{{Request quotation|date=February 2011}}&lt;!-- Quote abd discussion needed to indicate how much of this paragraph is supported by the reference  --&gt;

==Treaty of Versailles==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2011}}
{{Main|Treaty of Versailles}}
[[File:German losses after WWI.svg|thumb|Germany after Versailles
----
{{legend|#ffffcf|Lost by Germany after [[World War I]]; Annexed by neighbouring countries}}
{{legend|#ddefd0|Lost by Germany after [[World War I]]; [[Saar (League of Nations)|Saar Basin]] administered by the [[League of Nations]] 1920-35}}
{{legend|#f6d3a9|Germany (1919–1935)}}]]


The growing postwar economic crisis was a result of lost pre-war industrial exports, the loss of supplies in raw materials and foodstuffs from [[Alsace-Lorraine]], Polish districts and the colonies, along with worsening debt balances, but above all, the result of an exorbitant issue of promissory notes raising money to pay for the war.  Military-industrial activity had almost ceased, although controlled demobilisation kept unemployment at around one million. The fact that the Allies continued to blockade Germany until after the [[Treaty of Versailles]] did not help matters, either.

The allies permitted only low import levels of goods that most Germans could not afford.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}} After four years of war and famine, many German workers were exhausted, physically impaired and discouraged. Millions were disenchanted with capitalism and hoping for a new era. Meanwhile, the currency depreciated. The currency would continue to depreciate following the French invasion of the Ruhr.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

The German peace delegation in France signed the [[Treaty of Versailles]], accepting mass reductions of the German military, the prospect of substantial war reparations payments to the victorious allies, and the controversial &quot;[[War Guilt Clause]]&quot;. [[Adolf Hitler]] later blamed the republic and its democracy for the oppressive terms of this treaty. The Republic's first ''[[Reichspräsident]]'' (&quot;Reich President&quot;), [[Friedrich Ebert]] of the SPD, signed the new German constitution into law on 11 August 1919.

The new post-World War I Germany, stripped of all colonies, became 13.3% smaller in its European territory than its imperial predecessor. Of these losses, a large proportion consisted of provinces that were originally Polish and Alsace-Lorraine, seized by Germany in 1870, so the real loss of territory was rather less than the nationalists were to claim.

== Years of crisis (1919–1923) ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=October 2011}}
[[File:WiemarRepublic September 01 1923 50MillionMark.jpg|thumb|right|1923-issue 50 million mark banknote. Worth approximately US$1 when printed, this sum would have been worth approximately US$12 million, nine years earlier. The note was practically worthless a few weeks later, because of continued inflation.]]

The Republic was soon under attack from both [[Left-wing politics|left-]] and [[right-wing politics|right-wing]] sources. The radical left accused the ruling Social Democrats of having betrayed the ideals of the workers' movement by preventing a communist revolution. Various right-wing sources opposed any democratic system, preferring an authoritarian state like the 1871 Empire. To further undermine the Republic's credibility, some right-wingers (especially certain members of the former [[officer corps]]) also blamed an alleged conspiracy of [[Socialist]]s and [[Jew]]s for Germany's defeat in [[World War I]].

In the next five years, the central government, assured of the support of the Reichswehr dealt severely with the occasional outbreaks of violence in Germany's large cities.  The left claimed that the Social Democrats had betrayed the ideals of the revolution, while the army and the government-financed ''Freikorps'' committed hundreds of acts of gratuitous violence against striking workers.  

The first challenge to the Weimar Republic came when a group of [[communist]]s and [[anarchist]]s took over the [[Bavaria]]n government in [[Munich]] and declared the creation of the [[Bavarian Soviet Republic]]. The uprising was brutally attacked by ''Freikorps'', which consisted mainly of ex-soldiers dismissed from the army and who were well-paid to kill the most active supporters of a democratic Germany.  The ''Freikorps'' was an army outside the control of the government, but they were in close contact with their allies in the Reichswehr.

The [[Kapp-Luttwitz Putsch]] took place on 13 March 1920: 5000 ''Freikorps'' soldiers occupied Berlin and installed [[Wolfgang Kapp]] (a right-wing journalist) as chancellor. The national government fled to [[Stuttgart]] and called for a [[general strike]] against the putsch.  The strike meant that no &quot;official&quot; pronouncements could be published and with the civil service out on strike the Kapp government collapsed after only four days on 17 March.

Inspired by the general strikes, a workers' [[Ruhr Uprising|uprising]] began in the [[Ruhr area|Ruhr region]] when 50,000 people formed a &quot;Red Army&quot; and took control of the province. The regular army and the ''Freikorps'' ended the uprising on their own authority. The rebels were campaigning for an extension of the plans to nationalise major industries and supported the national government, but the S.P.D. leaders did not want to lend support to the growing USPD, who favoured the establishment of a socialist regime.  The repression of an uprising of S.P.D. supporters by the reactionary forces in the ''Freikorps'' on the instructions of the S.P.D. ministers was to become a major source of conflict within the socialist movement and thus contributed to the weakening of the only movement that could have withstood the Hitler movement.  Other rebellions were put down in March 1921 in [[Saxony]] and [[Hamburg]].

In 1922, Germany signed the [[Treaty of Rapallo, 1922|Treaty of Rapallo]] with the Soviet Union, which allowed Germany to train military personnel in exchange for giving Russia military technology. This was against the [[Treaty of Versailles]], which limited Germany to 100,000 soldiers and no conscription, naval forces of 15,000 men, twelve destroyers, six battleships, and six cruisers, no [[submarine]]s or aircraft. However, Russia had pulled out of [[World War I]] against the Germans as a result of the 1917 Russian Revolution, and was excluded from the [[League of Nations]]. Thus, Germany seized the chance to make an ally. [[Walther Rathenau]], the [[Jewish]] [[Foreign Minister of Germany|Foreign Minister]] who signed the treaty, was assassinated two months later by two ultra-nationalist army officers.

In the early postwar years, inflation was growing at an alarming rate, but the government simply printed more and more banknotes to pay the bills. By 1923, the Republic claimed it could no longer afford the [[World War I reparations|reparations]] payments required by the Versailles Treaty, and the government defaulted on some payments. In response, French and Belgian troops [[Occupation of the Ruhr|occupied the Ruhr region]], Germany's most productive industrial region at the time, taking control of most mining and manufacturing companies in January 1923. Strikes were called, and passive resistance was encouraged. These strikes lasted eight months, further damaging the economy. The strike prevented some goods from being produced, but one industrialist, Hugo Stinnes, was able to create a vast empire out of bankrupt companies. Because the production costs in Germany were falling almost hourly, the prices for German products were unbeatable.  Stinnes made sure that he was paid in dollars, which meant that by mid-1923, his industrial empire was worth more than the entire German economy.  By the end of the year, over two hundred factories were working full time to produce paper for the spiralling bank note production. Stinnes' empire collapsed when the government-sponsored inflation was stopped in November 1923.  
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-00193, Inflation, Ein-Millionen-Markschein.jpg|thumb|1 Million Mark notes, used as note paper, October 1923]]

Since striking workers were paid benefits by the state, much additional currency was printed, fueling a period of [[hyperinflation]]. The [[1920s German inflation]] started when Germany had no goods to trade. The government printed money to deal with the crisis; this meant payments within Germany were made with worthless paper money, and helped formerly great industrialists to pay back their own loans. This also led to pay raises for workers and for businessmen who wanted to profit from it. Circulation of money rocketed, and soon banknotes were being overprinted to a thousand times their nominal value and every town produced its own promissory notes. The value of the [[German papiermark|Papiermark]] had declined from 4.2 per U.S. dollar at the outbreak of World War I to 1 million per dollar by August 1923. This led to further criticism of the Republic. On 15 November 1923, a new currency, the [[German rentenmark|Rentenmark]], was introduced at the rate of 1 [[1000000000000 (number)|trillion]] (1,000,000,000,000) Papiermark for one Rentenmark, an action known as a [[monetary reset]]. At that time, one U.S. dollar was equal to 4.2 Rentenmark. Reparation payments resumed, and the Ruhr was returned to Germany under the Locarno Pact, which defined a border between Germany, France and Belgium.

Further pressure from the right came in 1923 with the [[Beer Hall Putsch]], also called the Munich Putsch, staged by the NSDAP under [[Adolf Hitler]] in [[Munich]]. In 1920, the [[German Workers' Party]] had become the National Socialist German Workers' Party (NSDAP), or [[Nazi Party]], and would become a driving force in the collapse of Weimar. Hitler named himself chairman of the party in July 1921. On 8 November 1923, the ''[[Kampfbund]]'', in a pact with [[Erich Ludendorff]], took over a meeting by Bavarian prime minister [[Gustav Ritter von Kahr|Gustav von Kahr]] at a beer hall in Munich. Ludendorff and Hitler declared that the Weimar government was deposed and that they were planning to take control of Munich the following day. The 3,000 rebels were thwarted by 100 policemen. Hitler was arrested and sentenced to five years in prison for high [[treason]], a minimum sentence for the charge. In the event, he served less than eight months in a comfortable cell, receiving a daily stream of visitors before his release on December 20, 1924. While in jail, Hitler dictated ''[[Mein Kampf]]'', which laid out his ideas and future policies. Hitler now decided to focus on legal methods of gaining power.

==Golden Era (1924–1929)==
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2009}}

[[Gustav Stresemann]] was ''[[Chancellor of Germany (German Reich)|Reichskanzler]]'' for 100 days in 1923, and served as foreign minister from 1923–1929, a period of relative stability for the Weimar Republic, known in Germany as ''Goldene Zwanziger'' (&quot;[[Golden Twenties]]&quot;). Prominent features of this period were a growing economy and a consequent decrease in civil unrest.

Once civil stability had been restored, Stresemann began stabilising the German currency, which promoted confidence in the German economy and helped the recovery that was so ardently needed for the German nation to keep up with their reparation repayments, while at the same time feeding and supplying the nation.

Once the economic situation had stabilised, Stresemann could begin putting a permanent currency in place, called the ''Rentenmark'' (1924), which again contributed to the growing level of international confidence in the German economy.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-00231, Radioansprache von Kanzler Wilhelm Marx.jpg|thumb|Christmas broadcast of [[Wilhelm Marx]] in December 1923. Marx was the longest serving chancellor of the republic.]]

To help Germany meet reparation obligations, the [[Dawes Plan]] (1924) was created. This was an agreement between American banks and the German government in which the American banks lent money to German banks with German assets as collateral to help it pay reparations. The German railways, the National Bank and many industries were therefore mortgaged as securities for the stable currency and the loans.&lt;ref&gt;Kitchen, Illustrated History of Germany, Cambridge University Press, 1996, p 241&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after, the French and Germans agreed that the borders between their countries would not be changed by force, which meant that the Treaty of Versailles was being diluted by the signing countries.&lt;ref&gt;Kitchen ibid&lt;/ref&gt; Other foreign achievements were the evacuation of the Ruhr in 1925 and the 1925 Treaty of Berlin, which reinforced the Treaty of Rapallo in 1922 and improved relations between the [[Soviet Union]] and Germany. In 1926, Germany was admitted to the [[League of Nations]] as a permanent member, improving her international standing and giving her the ability to [[veto]] League of Nations legislation.  However, this progress was funded by overseas loans, increasing the nation's debts, while overall trade increased and unemployment fell. Stresemann's reforms did not relieve the underlying weaknesses of Weimar but gave the appearance of a stable democracy. The major weakness in constitutional terms was the inherent instability of the coalitions.   The growing dependence on American finance was to prove dangerous and Germany was one of the worst hit nations in the [[Wall Street Crash of 1929]].
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-K0623-0502-001, Berlin, Tanztee im &quot;Esplanade&quot;.jpg|thumb|left|190px|''Roaring twenties'' in Berlin hotel ''Esplanade'', 1926]]

The 1920s saw a remarkable cultural renaissance in Germany. During the worst phase of hyperinflation in 1923, the clubs and bars were full of speculators who spent their daily profits so they wouldn't lose the value the following day.  Berlin intellectuals responded by condemning the excesses of capitalism, and demand revolutionary changes on the cultural scenery.  Influenced by the brief cultural explosion in the Soviet Union, German literature, cinema, theatre and music worlds entered a phase of great creativity. Innovative street theatre brought plays to the public, the [[cabaret]] scene and jazz band became very popular. According to the cliché, modern young women were Americanised, wearing makeup, short hair, smoking and breaking with traditional [[mores]]. The euphoria surrounding [[Josephine Baker]] in the metropolis Berlin for instance, declared &quot;erotic [[goddess]]&quot; and in many ways admired and respected, kindled further &quot;ultramodern&quot; sensations in the minds of the German public.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title= Josephine Baker in Berlin |url= http://www.cabaret-berlin.com/?p=440 |work = Cabaret Berlin - Exploring the entertainment of the Weimar era |date = 8 December 2010 |accessdate = 11 June 2011 | location= }}&lt;/ref&gt; A new type of [[architecture]] taught at &quot;[[Bauhaus]]&quot; schools, and Art reflected the new ideas of the time, with artists such as [[George Grosz]] being fined for defaming the [[military]] and for [[blasphemy]].

Artists in Berlin were influenced by other contemporary progressive cultural movements, such as the Impressionist and Expressionist painters in Paris, as well as the Cubists. Likewise, American progressive architects were admired. Many of the new buildings built during this era followed a straight-lined, geometrical style. Examples of the new architecture include the Bauhaus Building by Gropius, Grosses Schauspielhaus, and the Einstein Tower.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Delmer|first=Sefton|title=Weimar Germany: Democracy on Trial|year=1972|publisher=Macdonald|location=London|pages=82-93}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Not everyone, however, was happy with the changes taking place in Weimar culture. Conservatives and reactionaries feared that Germany was betraying her traditional values by adopting popular styles from abroad, particularly the U.S. Hollywood popularised American film, while New York became the global capital of fashion. Germany was more susceptible to Americanisation, because of the close economic links brought about by the Dawes plan.

In 1929, three years after receiving the 1926 [[Nobel Peace Prize]], Stresemann died of a heart attack at age 51. When stocks on the New York Stock Exchange crashed in October, the inevitable knock-on effects on the German economy brought the &quot;Golden Twenties&quot; to an abrupt end.

==Decline (1930–1933)==
===Economic instability===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-Z0127-305, Berlin 1927, Reichstreffen RFB, Thälmann, Leow.jpg|thumb|Members of the Communist [[Roter Frontkämpferbund]] marching through Berlin-Wedding, 1927]]
[[File:Flag of the Communist Party of Germany.svg|thumb|right|Flag of the [[Communist Party of Germany]].]]
[[File:Flag of Nazi Germany (1933-1945).svg|thumb|right|Flag of the [[Nazi Party|National Socialist German Workers' Party]].]]

In 1929, the onset of the depression in the United States of America produced a severe shock wave in Germany.  The economy was supported by the granting of loans through the Dawes Plan (1924) and the Young Plan.  When American banks withdrew their loans to German companies the onset of severe unemployment could not be stopped by conventional economic measures.  Unemployment grew rapidly and in September 1930 a political earthquake shook the republic to its foundations.  The [[Nazi Party|NSDAP]] entered the Reichstag with 19% of the popular vote and made the fragile coalition system by which every chancellor had governed, unworkable. The last years of the Weimar Republic were stamped by even more political instability than in the previous years. The administrations of Chancellors [[Heinrich Brüning|Brüning]], [[Franz von Papen|Papen]], [[Kurt von Schleicher|Schleicher]] and [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] (from 30 January to 23 March 1933) governed through presidential decree, rather than through consultation with the ''[[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]'' (the German parliament).

The finance expert [[Heinrich Brüning]] was appointed as successor of Chancellor Müller by ''Reichspräsident'' [[Paul von Hindenburg]] on 29 March 1930, after months of political lobbying by General [[Kurt von Schleicher]] on behalf of the military. The new government was expected to lead a political shift towards conservatism, based on the emergency powers granted to the ''Reichspräsident'' by the constitution, since it had no majority support in the ''Reichstag''.

After a bill to reform the Reich's finances was opposed by the ''Reichstag'', Hindenburg established the bill as an emergency decree based on [[Article 48 (Weimar Constitution)|Article 48]] of the constitution.  On 18 July, the bill was again invalidated by a slim majority in the ''Reichstag'' with the support of the SPD, [[Communist Party of Germany|KPD]], the (then small) NSDAP and [[German National People's Party|DNVP]]. Immediately afterwards, Brüning submitted to the ''Reichstag'' the president's decree that it would be dissolved.

The [[German federal election, 1930|''Reichstag'' general elections on 14 September]] resulted in an enormous political shift: 18.3% of the vote went to the Nazis, five times the percentage compared to 1928. It was no longer possible to form a pro-republican majority in the ''Reichstag'', not even a Grand Coalition of all major parties except the KPD, NSDAP and DNVP. This encouraged the supporters of the Nazis to force their claim to power by increasing organization of public demonstrations and paramilitary violence against rival paramilitary groups.

From 1930-1932, Brüning tried to reform the devastated state without a majority in Parliament, governing with the help of the President's emergency decrees. During that time, the [[Great Depression]] reached its low point. In line with conservative economic theory that less government spending would spur economic growth, Brüning drastically cut state expenditures, including in the social sector. He expected and accepted that the economic crisis would, for a while, deteriorate before things would improve. Among others, the ''Reich'' completely halted all public grants to the obligatory unemployment insurance (which had been introduced only in 1927), which resulted in higher contributions by the workers and fewer benefits for the unemployed.

The bulk of German capitalists and land-owners originally supported the conservative experiment: not from any personal liking for Brüning, but believing the conservatives would best serve their interests. But as the mass of the working class and middle classes turned against Brüning, more of the great capitalists and landowners declared themselves in favour of his opponents&amp;nbsp;— Hitler and [[Alfred Hugenberg|Hugenberg]]. By late 1931, conservatism as a movement was dead, and the time was coming when Hindenburg and the ''[[Reichswehr]]'' would drop Brüning and come to terms with Hugenberg and Hitler. Although Hindenburg disliked Hugenberg and despised Hitler, he was no less a supporter of the sort of anti-democratic counter-revolution represented by the DNVP and NSDAP.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Rosenberg|first=Arthur|authorlink=Arthur Rosenberg|title=A History of The German Republic|publisher=Methuen|year=1936|location=London|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 30 May 1932, Brüning resigned after no longer having Hindenburg's support. Five weeks earlier, Hindenburg had been re-elected ''Reichspräsident'' with Brüning's active support, running against Hitler (the president was directly elected by the people while the ''Reichskanzler'' was not).

===The Von Papen deal===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-T0706-501, berlin, Armenspeisung.jpg|thumb|Army feeds the poor, 1931 in Berlin]]

Hindenburg then appointed [[Franz von Papen]] as new ''Reichskanzler''. Von Papen lifted the ban on the NSDAP's [[Sturmabteilung|SA]] paramilitary, imposed after the street riots, in an unsuccessful attempt to secure the backing of Hitler.

Von Papen was closely associated with the industrialist and land-owning classes, and pursued an extreme Conservative policy along Hindenburg's lines. He appointed as ''Reichswehr'' Minister [[Kurt von Schleicher]], and all the members of the new cabinet were of the same political opinion as Hindenburg. This government was expected to assure itself of the co-operation of Hitler. Since the Republicans were not yet ready to take action, the Communists did not want to support the republic, and the Conservatives had shot their political bolt, Hitler and Hugenberg were certain to achieve power.

===Elections of July 1932===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 102-02134, Bad Harzburg, Gründung der Harzburger Front.jpg|thumb|''Harzburger Front'' of 1931, a coalition of nationalist conservatives and the extreme right]]

Because most parties opposed the new government, von Papen had the ''[[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]'' dissolved and called for new elections. [[German federal election, July 1932|The general elections on 31 July 1932]] yielded major gains for the [[Communist Party of Germany|KPD]] and the NSDAP (the Nazis), who won 37.2% of the vote, supplanting the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany|Social Democrats]] as the largest party in the ''Reichstag''.

The new question was what part the now immense Nazi Party would play in the Government of the country. The Nazi party owed its huge increase to growing support from middle-class people, whose traditional parties were swallowed up by the Nazi Party. The millions of radical adherents at first forced the Party towards the Left. They wanted a renewed Germany and a new organisation of German society. The left of the Nazi party strove desperately against any drift into the train of such capitalist and feudal reactionaries. Therefore Hitler refused ministry under Papen, and demanded the chancellorship for himself, but was rejected by Hindenburg on 13 August 1932. There was still no majority in the ''Reichstag'' for any government; as a result, the ''Reichstag'' was dissolved and elections took place once more in the hope that a stable majority would result.

===Cabinet Schleicher===
[[German federal election, November 1932|The 6 November 1932 elections]] yielded 33.1% for the Nazis,&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans| first=Richard J.|authorlink=Richard J. Evans|title=The Coming of the Third Reich|publisher=The Penguin Press|year=2004|location=New York|page=446|isbn=1594200041}}&lt;/ref&gt; two million voters fewer than in the previous election. Franz von Papen stepped down and was succeeded by General [[Kurt von Schleicher]] as ''Reichskanzler'' on 3 December. Schleicher, a political army officer, had developed in an atmosphere of semi-obscurity and intrigue that encompassed the Republican military policy. He had for years been in the camp of those supporting the Conservative counter-revolution. Schleicher's bold and unsuccessful plan was to build a majority in the ''Reichstag'' by uniting the [[trade unionist]] left wings in the various parties, including that of the Nazis led by [[Gregor Strasser]]. This did not prove successful either.

In this brief Presidential Dictatorship entr'acte, Schleicher took the role of 'Socialist General', and entered into relations with the Christian Trade Unions, the left-wing members of the Nazi party and even with the Social Democrats. Schleicher planned for a sort of labour government under his Generalship. But the ''Reichswehr'' officers were not prepared for this, the working class had a natural distrust of their future allies, and great capitalists and landowners did not like the plans. The SPD and KPD could have achieved success building on a Berlin transport strike.
[[File:Plakat Hugenberg Papen Seldte 1933.jpg|thumb|200px|left|Poster for the nationalist &quot;Black-White-Red&quot; coalition of DNVP leader [[Alfred Hugenberg]], [[Franz von Papen]] and [[Franz Seldte]].]]

Hitler learned from von Papen that the general had no authority to abolish the ''Reichstag'' parliament, whereas any majority of seats did. The cabinet (under a previous interpretation of Article 48) ruled without a sitting Reichstag, which could vote only for its own dissolution. Hitler also learned that all past crippling Nazi debts were to be relieved by German big business.

On 22 January, Hitler's efforts to persuade Oskar von Hindenburg (the President's son) included threats to bring criminal charges over estate taxation irregularities at the President's [[Munich|Neudeck]] estate (although {{convert|5000|acre|km2|abbr=on}} extra were soon allotted to Hindenburg's property). Out-maneuvered by von Papen and Hitler on plans for the new cabinet, and having lost Hindenburg's confidence, Schleicher asked for new elections. On 28 January, von Papen described Hitler to [[Paul von Hindenburg]] as only a minority part of an alternative, von Papen-arranged government. The four great political movements, the SPD, KPD, [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre]], and the Nazis were in opposition.

On 29 January, Hitler and von Papen thwarted a last-minute threat of an officially sanctioned ''Reichswehr'' takeover, and on 30 January 1933 Hindenburg accepted the new Papen-Nationalist-Hitler coalition with the Nazis holding only three of 11 Cabinet seats. Later that day, the first cabinet meeting was attended by only two political parties, representing a minority in the ''Reichstag'': The Nazis and the [[German National People's Party|DNVP]] led by [[Alfred Hugenberg]] (196 + 52 seats). Eyeing the Catholic [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]]'s 70 (+ 20 [[Bavarian People's Party|BVP]]) seats, Hitler refused their leader's demands for constitutional &quot;concessions&quot; (amounting to protection) and planned for dissolution of the ''Reichstag''.

Hindenburg, despite his misgivings about the Nazis' goals and about Hitler as a person, reluctantly agreed to Papen's theory that, with Nazi popular support on the wane, Hitler could now be controlled as chancellor. This date, dubbed by the Nazis as the ''[[Machtergreifung]]'' (seizure of power) by Nazi propaganda, is commonly seen as the beginning of [[Nazi Germany]] but the phase of German history in which the democratic principles of the constitution and personal liberty came to an end with the appointment of Brüning as Chancellor by Hindenburg.

===Hitler's chancellorship (1933)===
[[Hitler]] was sworn in as [[Chancellor]] on the morning of 30 January 1933 in what some observers later described as a brief and indifferent ceremony. By early February, a mere week after Hitler's assumption of the chancellorship, the government had begun to clamp down on the opposition. Meetings of the left-wing parties were banned and even some of the moderate parties found their members threatened and assaulted. Measures with an appearance of legality suppressed the Communist Party in mid-February and included the plainly illegal arrests of ''Reichstag'' deputies.

The [[Reichstag Fire]] on 27 February was blamed by Hitler's government on the Communists. Hitler used the ensuing state of emergency to obtain the assent of President von Hindenburg to issue the [[Reichstag Fire Decree]] the following day. The decree invoked [[Article 48 (Weimar Constitution)|Article 48]] of the [[Weimar Constitution]] and &quot;indefinitely suspended&quot; a number of constitutional protections of civil liberties, allowing the Nazi government to take swift action against political meetings, arresting and killing the Communists.

Hitler and the Nazis exploited the German state's broadcasting and aviation facilities in a massive attempt to sway the electorate, but this election yielded a scant majority of 16 seats for the coalition. At the ''Reichstag'' elections, which took place on 5 March, the NSDAP obtained 17 million votes. The Communist, Social Democrat and Catholic Centre votes stood firm. This was the last multi-party election until the end of the [[Third Reich]] 12 years later and the last all-German election for 57 years.

Hitler addressed disparate interest groups, stressing the necessity for a definitive solution to the perpetual instability of the Weimar Republic. He now blamed Germany's problems on the Communists, even threatening their lives on 3 March. Former Chancellor [[Heinrich Brüning]] proclaimed that his Centre Party would resist any constitutional change and appealed to the President for an investigation of the ''Reichstag'' fire. Hitler's successful plan was to induce what remained of the now Communist-depleted Reichstag to grant him, and the Government, the authority to issue decrees with the force of law. The hitherto Presidential Dictatorship hereby was to give itself a new legal form.

On 15 March, the first [[cabinet meeting]] was attended by the two coalition parties, representing a minority in the ''Reichstag'': The Nazis and the [[DNVP]] led by [[Alfred Hugenberg]] (196 + 52 seats). According to the [[Nuremberg Trials]], this cabinet meeting's first order of business was how at last to achieve the complete counter-revolution by means of the constitutionally allowed [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]], requiring ⅔ parliamentary majority. This Act would, and did, lead Hitler and the [[NSDAP]] toward his goal of unfettered dictatorial powers.&lt;ref&gt;As Kershaw notes (p. 468), after the passage of the Act, &quot;Hitler was still far from wielding absolute power. But vital steps toward consolidating his dictatorship now followed in quick succession.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hitler cabinet meeting in mid-March===
At the meeting of the new cabinet on 15 March, Hitler introduced the [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]], which would have authorised the cabinet to enact legislation without the approval of the ''Reichstag''. Meanwhile, the only remaining question for the Nazis was whether the Catholic [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]] (''Zentrum'') would support the Enabling Act in the ''Reichstag'', thereby providing the ⅔ majority required to ratify a law that amended the constitution. Hitler expressed his confidence to win over the Centre's votes. Hitler is recorded at the Nuremberg Trials as being sure of eventual [[Centre Party Germany]] capitulation and thus rejecting of the DNVP's suggestions to &quot;balance&quot; the majority through further arrests, this time of Social Democrats. Hitler however assured his coalition partners that arrests would resume after the elections and, in fact, some 26 SPD Social Democrats were physically removed. After meeting with Centre leader Monsignor [[Ludwig Kaas]] and other Centre Trade Union leaders daily and denying them a substantial participation in the government, negotiation succeeded in respect of guarantees towards Catholic civil-servants and education issues.

At the last internal Centre meeting prior to the debate on the Enabling Act, Kaas expressed no preference or suggestion on the vote, but as a way of mollifying opposition by Centre members to the granting of further powers to Hitler, Kaas somehow arranged for a letter of constitutional guarantee from Hitler himself prior to his voting with the centre ''en bloc'' in favor of the [[Enabling Act of 1933|Enabling Act]]. This guarantee was not ultimately given. Kaas, the party's chairman since 1928, had strong connections to the [[Vatican City|Vatican]] Secretary of State, later [[Pope Pius XII]]. In return for pledging his support for the act, Kaas would use his connections with the Vatican to set in train and draft the [[Holy See]]'s long desired ''[[Reichskonkordat]]'' with Germany (only possible with the co-operation of the Nazis).

Ludwig Kaas is considered along with von Papen as being one of the two most important political figures in the creation of a [[National Socialist German Workers Party|National Socialist]] dictatorship.&lt;ref name=&quot;vKlemperer&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=von Klemperer|first=Klemens|authorlink=| coauthors=|title=German Resistance Against Hitler:The Search for Allies Abroad 1938–1945|publisher= OUP / Clarendon Press|year=1992|location=Oxford|pages=|isbn=0-19-821940-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Enabling Act negotiations===
On 20 March, negotiation began between Hitler and Frick on one side and the Catholic [[Centre Party (Germany)|Centre Party]] (''Zentrum'') leaders&amp;nbsp;— Kaas, Stegerwald and Hackelsburger on the other. The aim was to settle on conditions under which Centre would vote in favor of the [[Enabling Act]]. Because of the Nazis' narrow majority in the ''Reichstag'', Centre's support was necessary to receive the required two-thirds majority vote. On 22 March, the negotiations concluded; Hitler promised to continue the existence of the German states, agreed not to use the new grant of power to change the constitution, and promised to retain ''Zentrum'' members in the civil service. Hitler also pledged to protect the Catholic confessional schools and to respect the concordats signed between the [[Holy See]] and [[Bavaria]] (1924), [[Prussia]] (1929) and [[Baden]] (1931). Hitler also agreed to mention these promises in his speech to the ''Reichstag'' before the vote on the Enabling Act.

The ceremonial opening of the ''Reichstag'' on 21 March was held at the [[Garrison Church (Potsdam)|Garrison Church]] in [[Potsdam]], a shrine of [[Prussia]]nism, in the presence of many [[Junker]] landowners and representatives of the imperial military caste. This impressive and often emotional spectacle&amp;nbsp;— orchestrated by [[Joseph Goebbels]]&amp;nbsp;— aimed to link Hitler's government with Germany's imperial past and portray National Socialism as a guarantor of the nation's future. The ceremony helped convince the &quot;old guard&quot; Prussian military elite of Hitler's homage to their long tradition and, in turn, produced the relatively convincing view that Hitler's government had the support of Germany's traditional protector&amp;nbsp;— the Army. Such support would publicly signal a return to conservatism to curb the problems affecting the Weimar Republic, and that stability might be at hand. In a cynical and politically adroit move, Hitler bowed in apparently respectful humility before President and Field Marshal [[Paul von Hindenburg|von Hindenburg]].

===Passage of the Enabling Act===
The ''Reichstag'' convened on 23 March 1933, and in the midday opening, Hitler made a historic speech, appearing outwardly calm and conciliatory. Hitler presented an appealing prospect of respect towards Christianity by paying tribute to the Christian faiths as &quot;essential elements for safeguarding the soul of the German people&quot;. He promised to respect their rights and declared his government's &quot;ambition is a peaceful accord between [[Separation of church and state|Church and State]]&quot; and that he hoped &quot;to improve our friendly relations with the [[Holy See]].&quot; This speech aimed especially at the future recognition by the named [[Holy See]] and therefore to the votes of the Centre Party addressing many concerns Kaas had voiced during the previous talks. Kaas is considered to have had a hand therefore in the drafting of the speech.&lt;ref name=&quot;vKlemperer&quot;/&gt; Kaas is also reported as voicing the Holy See's desire for Hitler as bulwark against [[atheist]]ic Russian [[nihilism]] previously as early as May 1932.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Mowrer|first=Edgar Ansel|authorlink=Edgar Ansel Mowrer| title=Triumph and Turmoil|year=1970|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=London|page=209|isbn= 0049200267}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hitler promised that the Act did not threaten the existence of either the ''[[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]'' or the ''[[Reichsrat (Germany)|Reichsrat]]'', that the authority of the [[President]] remained untouched and that the [[States of Germany|Länder]] would not be abolished. Of course, all the promises would be broken soon enough, but they served their purpose. During an adjournment, the other parties (notably the Centre) met to discuss their intentions.&lt;ref&gt;''Kershaw'' pp. 467–68.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the debate prior to the vote on the Enabling Act, Hitler orchestrated the full political menace of his [[paramilitary]] forces like the [[Sturmabteilung|storm troopers]] in the streets to intimidate reluctant ''Reichstag'' deputies into approving the Enabling Act. The Communists' 81 seats had been empty since the ''Reichstag'' Fire Decree and other lesser known procedural measures, thus excluding their anticipated &quot;No&quot; votes from the balloting. [[Otto Wels]], the leader of the Social Democrats, whose seats were similarly depleted from 120 to below 100, was the only speaker to defend democracy and in a futile but brave effort to deny Hitler the ⅔ majority, he made a speech critical of the abandonment of [[democracy]] to [[dictatorship]]. At this, Hitler could no longer restrain his [[wrath]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=[[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]]| authorlink=William L. Shirer|last=Shirer|first=William L.|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster]]|location= New York|year=1960|isbn=0-671-72868-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In his retort to Wels, Hitler abandoned earlier pretence at calm statesmanship and delivered a characteristic screaming diatribe, promising to exterminate all Communists in Germany and threatening [[Otto Wels|Wels']] Social Democrats as well. He did not even want their support for the bill. &quot;Germany will become free, but not through you,&quot; he shouted.&lt;ref&gt;''Kershaw'' p. 468.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile Hitler's promised written guarantee to Monsignor Kaas was being typed up, it was asserted to Kaas, and thereby Kaas was persuaded to silently deliver the Centre bloc's votes for the Enabling Act anyway. The Act&amp;nbsp;— formally titled the &quot;Act for the Removal of Distress from People and Reich&quot;&amp;nbsp;— was passed by a vote of 441 to 94. Only the SPD had voted against the Act. Every other member of the ''Reichstag'', whether from the largest or the smallest party, voted in favor of the Act. It went into effect the following day, March 24.

===Aftermath===
{{Main|Nazi Germany}}

The passage of the [[Enabling Act of 1933]] is widely considered to mark the end of the Weimar Republic and the beginning of the [[Third Reich]]. It empowered the cabinet to legislate without the approval of Reichstag or the President, and to enact laws that were contrary to the constitution. Before the March 1933 elections Hitler had persuaded Hindenburg to promulgate the [[Reichstag Fire Decree]] using [[Article 48]], which empowered the government to restrict &quot;the rights of habeas corpus [...] freedom of the press, the freedom to organize and assemble, the privacy of postal, telegraphic and telephonic communications&quot; and legalised search warrants and confiscation &quot;beyond legal limits otherwise prescribed&quot;. This was intended to forestall any action against the government by the Communists. Hitler used the provisions of the Enabling Act to pre-empt possible opposition to his dictatorship from other sources, in which he was mostly successful.

The process of bringing all major organisations into line with Nazi principles and into the service of the state was called ''[[Gleichschaltung]]''. ''Gleichschaltung'' is usually translated as &quot;coordination&quot;, but sometimes as &quot;forcible coordination&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;''Kershaw'' p. 481.&lt;/ref&gt; It is a compound word, consisting of ''gleich'', meaning ''alike'', and ''schaltung'', which means ''switching''. The NSDAP meant to imply a particular mechanical meaning of the word: a certain means of wiring an electrical generator and electric motors, so that when the generator is made to turn at a given speed or turned to a certain angle, each motor connected to it will also turn at that speed, or to the same angle&amp;nbsp;— in other words, synchronization.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}} The NSDAP was thought of as the generator, and other civil groups as motors wired to it.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

Hitler's cabinet issued many decrees for the purpose of ''Gleichschaltung'' in the weeks following the passage of the Act. It removed Jews from the civil service (at Hindenburg's request, an exception was made for Jews who had served at the front during World War I). It banned all trade unions and eventually outlawed all other political parties. After the exiled SPD published its new weekly ''Neuer Vorwarts'' in Prague, Hitler banned the party, confiscating its assets and abolishing its parliamentary representation, by decree of 22 June.

However, opposition was frequently not addressed by legislation at all. The process of ''Gleichschaltung'' was often voluntary, or in any event not mandated by a formal decree. Most other parties had dissolved before being officially banned: the NSDAP's coalition partner, the DNVP, dissolved on 27 June, one day after Hugenberg's resignation from the cabinet. The ''Staatspartei'' (formerly the DDP) dissolved itself on 28 June and the DVP on 29 June. On 4–5 July, the Catholic parties (the BVP and the Centre) also wound up. By the time the formal decree banned the creation of new parties, there were none left except the NSDAP.&lt;ref&gt;''See Kershaw'' pp. 474–476.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''See Kershaw'' pp. 475–483.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;...&amp;nbsp;many organizations showed themselves only too willing to anticipate the [''Gleichschaltung''] process and to &quot;coordinate&quot; themselves in accordance with the expectations of the new era. By the autumn, the Nazi dictatorship&amp;nbsp;... had been enormously strengthened. What is striking is not how much, but how little, Hitler needed to do to bring this about&amp;nbsp;... Hitler took remarkably few initiatives. ''Kershaw'' p. 469.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Willing ''Gleichschaltung'' was termed ''Selbstgleichschaltung'' or &quot;self-coordination&quot;. There was a rush to join the NSDAP, overrunning the party's ability to process applications: on May 1, the party announced that it was suspending the admission of new members. The party's membership had increased to 2.5 million, from about 900,000 at the end of January. Many prominent intellectuals allied themselves with the new government: the country's most famous philosopher, [[Martin Heidegger]] and its most prominent constitutional scholar, [[Carl Schmitt]], spoke in favour of it, and Heidegger became the sponsor of a manifesto of German professors pledging allegiance to &quot;Adolf Hitler and the National Socialist State.&quot; Lists were prepared of writers whose works were unacceptable in the 'New Order', including Freud, Einstein and Brecht. On the evening of 10 May, under the leadership of the German Students' Association and without substantial protest by the university faculties,{{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} some 20,000 volumes were burned at Berlin's [[Opernplatz]].&lt;ref&gt;They included the works of [[Heinrich Heine]], a poet who had written that &quot;where books are burned, in the end people are also burned.&quot; ''Ibid''. pp. 469–478.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Reichswehr had, however, remained mostly untouched by ''Gleichschaltung''. It was not until Hindenburg's death in August 1934 that all military personnel swore an oath of loyalty directly to Hitler, instead of to the constitution. Thereafter, the military came under gradually increasing pressure to align itself with NSDAP ideology, but it never entirely capitulated. Likewise, the holdings of industrialists and aristocratic &quot;[[Junker]]&quot; landowners remained for the most part untouched, whilst the administrative and judicial machinery was only very slightly tampered with.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rosenberg&quot;/&gt; The Nazi efforts to &quot;co-ordinate&quot; the Christian churches (both [[Roman Catholic]] and [[Protestant]]) were mostly unsuccessful, and were largely abandoned. However, the churches as a whole did not present any serious opposition to Hitler.

==Legacy==
The constitution of 1919 was never formally repealed, but the Enabling Act meant that it was a dead letter. The Enabling Act itself was breached by Hitler on three occasions in 1934: Article 2 of the act stated that
&lt;blockquote&gt;'Laws enacted by the government of the Reich may deviate from the constitution as long as they do not affect the institutions of the Reichstag and the Reichsrat. The rights of the President remain undisturbed.'&lt;/blockquote&gt; The powers of the Länder (states) were transferred to the central government, rendering the ''Reichsrat'' obsolete. A month later, the ''Reichsrat'' itself was dissolved. President von Hindenburg died in August, and Hitler appropriated the president's powers for himself. The Enabling Act did not specify any recourse that could be taken if the chancellor violated Article 2, and no judicial challenge ensued.

After the death of Hindenburg in 1934, the constitution was largely forgotten, with some minor exceptions. In Hitler's 1945 [[The Political Testament of Adolf Hitler|political testament]] (written shortly before his suicide) he appointed Admiral [[Karl Doenitz]] to succeed him, but he named Doenitz as President rather than Fuehrer, thereby re-establishing a constitutional office dormant since Hindenburg's death twelve years earlier. On the 30th of April 1945 Doenitz formed what became known as the [[Flensburg government]], which controlled only a tiny area of Germany near the Danish border, including the town of [[Flensburg]]. It was dissolved by the Allies on 23 May. On 5 June, the Allied [[Berlin Declaration (1945)|Berlin Declaration]] stated in its preamble that the Allies assumed &lt;blockquote&gt;supreme authority with respect to Germany, including all the powers possessed by the German Government [...] and any state, municipal, or local government or authority.&lt;/blockquote&gt; It also declared that there was &lt;blockquote&gt;no central Government or authority in Germany capable of accepting responsibility for the maintenance of order, the administration of the country and compliance with the requirements of the victorious Powers.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Article 13 of the declaration read:
&lt;blockquote&gt;[T]he four Allied Governments will take such steps, including the complete disarmament and demilitarization of Germany, as they deem requisite for future peace and security.

The Allied Representatives will impose on Germany additional political, administrative, economic, financial, military and other requirements arising from the complete defeat of Germany. [...] All German authorities and the German people shall carry out unconditionally the requirements of the Allied Representatives, and shall fully comply with all such proclamations, orders, ordinances and instructions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
These provisions, not legally challenged by either of the subsequent German governments, meant that neither any NSDAP decree nor the 1919 constitution held any legal force over the Allies' administration of Germany.

The 1949 [[Constitution of East Germany|Constitution]] of the [[East Germany|German Democratic Republic]] contained many passages that were originally part of the 1919 constitution.&lt;ref&gt;http://web.wm.edu/law/publications/lawreview/documents/Vol49-4_Markovits.pdf?svr=law&lt;/ref&gt; It was intended to be the constitution of a united Germany, and was thus a compromise between liberal-democratic and Leninist ideologies. It was replaced by a new, explicitly Leninist constitution in 1968, which was substantially amended in 1974. In 1990, the GDR dissolved altogether.

The [[Basic Law for the Federal Republic of Germany]], enacted in 1949, stated that &lt;blockquote&gt;'The provisions of Articles 136, 137, 138, 139 and 141 of the German Constitution of 11 August 1919 shall be an integral part of this Basic Law.'&lt;ref&gt;Article 140 of the Basic Law. http://www.bundestag.de/interakt/infomat/fremdsprachiges_material/downloads/ggEn_downloand.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; These articles of the Weimar constitution (which dealt with the state's relationship to various Christian churches) remain part of the German Basic Law.

==Reasons for failure==
The reasons for the Weimar Republic's collapse are the subject of continuing debate. It may have been doomed from the beginning since even moderates disliked it and extremists on both the left and right loathed it. Germany had limited democratic traditions and Weimar democracy was widely seen as chaotic. And since Weimar politicians had been blamed for the [[Dolchstosslegende|'Dolchstosslegende]] (Stab In The Back legend)&amp;nbsp;— a then widely believed theory that Germany's surrender in World War I had been the unnecessary act of traitors&amp;nbsp;— the popular legitimacy of the government was on shaky ground.

No single reason can explain the failure of the Weimar Republic. The most commonly asserted causes can be grouped into three categories: economic problems, institutional problems and the roles of specific individuals.

=== {{Visible anchor|Economic problems}} ===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[W.E.B. Du Bois]] --&gt;
{{Main|Great Depression in Central Europe|Dawes Plan|Reichsbank}}

The Weimar Republic had some of the most serious economic problems ever experienced by any Western democracy in history. Rampant [[hyperinflation]], massive unemployment, and a large drop in living standards were primary factors. From 1923–1929, there was a short period of economic recovery, but the [[Great Depression]] of the 1930s led to a worldwide recession. Germany was particularly affected because it depended heavily on American loans. In 1926, about 2 million Germans were unemployed&amp;nbsp;— this rose to around 6 million in 1932. Many blamed the Weimar Republic. This was made apparent when political parties on both right and left wanting to disband the Republic altogether made any democratic majority in Parliament impossible.

The Weimar Republic was severely affected by the [[Great Depression]]. The economic stagnation led to increased demands on Germany to repay the debts owed to the United States. As the Weimar Republic was very fragile in all its existence, the depression was devastating, and played a major role in the [[NSDAP]]'s takeover.

Most Germans thought the [[Treaty of Versailles]] was a punishing and degrading document, because it forced them to surrender resource-rich areas and pay massive amounts of compensation. These punitive reparations caused consternation and resentment, although the actual economic damage resulting from the Treaty of Versailles is difficult to determine. While the official reparations were considerable, Germany ended up paying only a fraction of them. However, the reparations did damage Germany's economy by discouraging market loans, which forced the Weimar government to finance its deficit by printing more currency, causing rampant hyperinflation. In addition, the rapid disintegration of Germany in 1919, due to the return of a disillusioned army, the rapid change from possible victory in 1918 to defeat in 1919, and the political chaos may have caused a psychological imprint on Germans that could lead to extreme [[nationalism]], later epitomized and exploited by Hitler.

Most historians agree that many industrial leaders identified the Weimar Republic with labour unions and with the Social Democrats, who had established the Versailles concessions of 1918/1919. Although some did see Hitler as a means to abolish the latter, the Republic was already unstable before any industry leaders were supporting Hitler. Even those who supported Hitler's appointment often did not support Nazism in its entirety and considered Hitler a temporary solution in their efforts to abolish the Republic. Industry support alone cannot explain Hitler's enthusiastic support by large segments of the population, including many workers who had turned away from the left.

[[Princeton University|Princeton]] historian [[Harold James (historian)|Harold James]] argues that there was a clear link between economic decline and people turning to extremist politics.&lt;ref&gt;James, Harold, &quot;Economic Reasons for the Collapse of the Weimar Republic,&quot; in &quot;Weimar: Why Did German Democracy Fail,&quot; ed. Ian Kershaw, Widenfeld and Nicolson, (London: 1990), pp 30-57.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Institutional problems===
It is widely believed that the 1919 constitution had several weaknesses, making the eventual establishment of a dictatorship likely but it is unknown whether a different constitution could have prevented the Third Reich. However, the 1949 West German constitution (the ''[[Basic Law of the Federal Republic of Germany|Grundgesetz]])'' is generally viewed as a strong response to these flaws.

*The institution of the ''Reichspräsident'' was frequently considered as an ''Ersatzkaiser'' (&quot;substitute emperor&quot;), an attempt to replace the Kaiser with a similarly strong institution meant to diminish party politics. Article 48 of the constitution gave the President power to &quot;take all necessary steps&quot; if &quot;public order and security are seriously disturbed or endangered&quot;. Although this was intended as an emergency clause, it was often used before 1933 to issue decrees without the support of Parliament (see above) and also made ''[[Gleichschaltung]]'' easier.

*During the Weimar Republic, it was accepted that a law did not have to conform to the constitution as long as it had the support of two thirds of parliament, the same majority needed to change the constitution (''verfassungsdurchbrechende Gesetze''). This was a precedent for the [[Enabling Act of 1933]]. The Basic Law of 1949 requires an explicit change of the wording, and it prohibits abolishing the basic rights or the federal structure of the republic.

*The use of [[proportional representation]] meant any party with a small amount of support could gain entry into the ''[[Reichstag (Weimar Republic)|Reichstag]]''. This led to many small parties, some extremist, building political bases within the system. Yet, the Reichstag of the monarchy was fractioned to a similar degree, even though elected by [[majoritarian system|majority vote]] (under a [[two-round system]]). The republic did not fall due to the small parties, but to the strength of the communists, conservatives and national socialists. Nevertheless, the modern German Bundestag has introduced a 5% threshold limit for a party to gain parliamentary representation.

*The ''Reichstag'' could remove the ''Reichskanzler'' from office even if it was unable to agree on a successor. This &quot;[[Motion of No Confidence]]&quot; meant, since 1932, that a government could not be held in office when the parliament came together. As a result, the 1949 ''Grundgesetz'' stipulates that a chancellor may only be voted down by Parliament if a successor is elected at the same time (see [[Constructive Vote of No Confidence]]).

*The political parties started to have a role in creating a government only in October 1918. They had no time to get used to that, under the old system.

===Role of individuals===
Brüning's economic policy from 1930–1932 has been the subject of much debate. It caused many Germans to identify the Republic with cuts in social spending and extremely liberal economics. Whether there were alternatives to this policy during the [[Great Depression]] is an open question.

[[Paul von Hindenburg]] became ''Reichspräsident'' in 1925.

==Constituent states==
[[File:Karte_des_Deutschen_Reiches,_Weimarer_Republik-Drittes_Reich_1919–1937.svg|270px|thumb|right|Germany during the Weimar period, with the [[Free State of Prussia]] (in blue) as the largest state.]]
Prior to World War I, the [[States of the German Empire|constituent states of the German Empire]] were 22 smaller monarchies, three republican city-states and the Imperial territory of [[Alsace-Lorraine]]. After the territorial losses of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] and the German Revolution of 1918–1919, the remaining states continued as republics. The former [[Ernestine duchies]] continued briefly as republics before merging to form the state of [[Thuringia]] in 1920, except for [[Saxe-Coburg]], which became part of [[Bavaria]].
[[File:Deutsches Reich 1925 b.png|270px|thumb|right|States of Germany (1925)]]
{{Table of states in the Weimar Republic}}

These states were gradually ''de facto'' abolished under the Nazi regime via the [[Gleichschaltung]] process, as the states were largely re-organised into [[Gau (country subdivision)|Gaue]]. However, the city-state of [[Free City of Lübeck|Lübeck]] was formally incorporated into Prussia in 1937 following the [[Greater Hamburg Act]]&amp;nbsp;— apparently motivated by Hitler's personal dislike for the city. Most of the remaining states were formally dissolved by the Allies at the end of [[World War II]] and ultimately re-organised into the modern [[states of Germany]].

==See also==
{{Portal|Germany}}
*[[Weimar culture]]
*[[Inflation in the Weimar Republic]]
*[[Gleichschaltung]]
*[[Centre Party Germany]]
*[[Franz von Papen]]
*[[Weimar Constitution]]
*[[Württemberg Landtag elections in the Weimar Republic]]
*[[Timeline of the Weimar Republic]]
*[[The 1920s Berlin Project]]

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=William Sheridan Allen|last=Allen|first=William Sheridan|title=The Nazi seizure of Power: the experience of a single German town, 1922–1945|location=New York, Toronto| publisher=F. Watts|year=1984|isbn=0-531-09935-0}}
*{{cite book|first=V. R.|last=Berghahn|title=Modern Germany|location=Cambridge, UK|publisher= Cambridge University Press|year=1982|isbn=0-521-34748-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Bookbinder|first=Paul|title=Weimar Germany: the Republic of the Reasonable| location=Manchester, UK |publisher=Manchester University Press|year=1996|isbn=0-7190-4286-0}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Karl Dietrich Bracher|last=Bracher|first=Karl Dietrich|title=Die Auflösung der Weimarer Republik; eine Studie zum Problem des Machtverfalls in der Demokratie|location= Villingen, Schwarzwald|publisher=Ring-Verlag|year=1971|language=German}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Martin Broszat|last=Broszat|first=Martin|title=Hitler and the Collapse of Weimar Germany|location=Leamington Spa, New York|publisher=Berg&lt;!--: Distributed exclusively in the US by St. Martin's Press--&gt;|year=1987|isbn=0-85496-509-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Childers|first=Thomas|title=The Nazi Voter: The Social Foundations of Fascism in Germany, 1919–1933|location=Chapel Hill|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|year=1983|isbn =0-8078-1570-5}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Gordon A. Craig|last=Craig|first=Gordon A.|title=Germany 1866–1945 (Oxford History of Modern Europe)|location=Oxford|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1980|isbn= 0-19-502724-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Dorpalen|first=Andreas|title=Hindenburg and the Weimar Republic|location= Princeton, N.J.|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1964}}
*Eschenburg, Theodor (1972) &quot;The Role of the Personality in the Crisis of the Weimar Republic: Hindenburg, Brüning, Groener, Schleicher&quot; pages 3–50 from ''Republic to Reich The Making Of The Nazi Revolution'' edited by [[Hajo Holborn]], New York: Pantheon Books.
*{{cite book|last=Feuchtwanger|first=Edgar|title=From Weimar to Hitler: Germany, 1918–1933 | location=London|publisher=Macmillan |year=1993|isbn=0-333-27466-0}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Peter Gay|last=Gay|first=Peter|title=Weimar Culture: The Outsider as Insider|location=New York|publisher=Harper &amp; Row|year=1968}}
*{{cite book|last=Gordon|first=Mel|title=Volutpuous Panic: The Erotic World of Weimar Berlin| location=New York |publisher=Feral House|year=2000}}
*{{cite book|last=Hamilton|first=Richard F.|title=Who Voted for Hitler?|location=Princeton, N.J.| publisher=Princeton University Press|year=1982|isbn=0-691-09395-4}}
*{{cite book|last=James|first=Harold|title=The German Slump: Politics and Economics, 1924–1936| location=Oxford, Oxfordshire|publisher=Clarendon Press|year=1986|isbn=0-19-821972-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Kaes|first=Anton|coauthors=Jay, Martin; Dimendberg, Edward (eds.)|title=The Weimar Republic Sourcebook|location=Berkeley|publisher=University of California Press|year=1994| isbn=0-520-06774-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Kershaw|first=Ian|isbn=0-312-04470-4|author-link=Ian Kershaw|title=Weimar. Why did German Democracy Fail?|location=London|publisher=Weidenfield &amp; Nicholson|year=1990}}
*{{cite book|last=Kershaw|first=Ian|isbn=0-393-04671-0|author-link=Ian Kershaw|title=Hitler 1889–1936: Hubris|location=London|publisher=Allen Lane|year=1998}}
*{{cite book|last=Kolb|first=Eberhard|title=The Weimar Republic|others=P.S. Falla (translator)| location=London|publisher=Unwin Hyman|year=1988|isbn=0-04-943049-1}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Hans Mommsen|last=Mommsen|first=Hans|title=From Weimar to Auschwitz| others=Philip O'Connor (translator)|location=Princeton, N.J.|publisher=Princeton University Press| year=1991|isbn=0-691-03198-3}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Edgar Ansel Mowrer|first=Edgar Angel|last=Mowrer|title=Germany Puts The Clock Back|publisher=London|year=1933}}
*{{cite book|last=Nicholls|first=Anthony James|title=Weimar And The Rise Of Hitler|location=New York|publisher=St. Martin's Press,|year=2000|isbn=0-312-23350-7}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Detlev Peukert|last=Peukert|first=Detlev|title=The Weimar Republic: the Crisis of Classical Modernity|location=New York|publisher=Hill and Wang|year=1992|isbn= 0-8090-9674-9}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Henry Ashby Turner|last=Turner|first=Henry Ashby|title=Hitler's Thirty Days To Power: January 1933|location=Reading, Mass.|publisher=Addison-Wesley|year=1996|isbn= 0-201-40714-0}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Henry Ashby Turner|last=Turner|first=Henry Ashby|title=German Big Business and the Rise of Hitler|location=New York|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1985|isbn= 0-19-503492-9}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Eric D. Weitz|last=Weitz|first=Eric D.|title=Weimar Germany: Promise and Tragedy|location=Princeton|publisher=Princeton University Press|year=2007|isbn=978-0-691-01695-5}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=John Wheeler-Bennett|last=Wheeler-Bennett|first=John|title=The Nemesis of Power: German Army in Politics, 1918–1945|location=New York|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan Publishing Company|year=2005|isbn=1-4039-1812-0}}
*{{cite book|authorlink=Bernd Widdig|last=Widdig|first=Bernd|title=Culture and Inflation in Weimar Germany|location=Berkeley, CA|publisher=University of California Press|year=2001|isbn= 978-0520222908}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Spoken Wikipedia|Weimar.ogg|2009-10-28}}
*[http://www.zum.de/psm/weimar/weimar_vve.php The Constitution of the German Reich (Weimar constitution) of 11 August 1919] (English)
*[http://www.malc.eu/history/Weimar-Republic-Germany.general.html Weimar Republic World History Database]
*[http://www.zum.de/psm/weimar/index.php3 PSM Data Bank]
*[http://www.documentarchiv.de/ historical documents (German)]

{{States of the Weimar Republic}}

{{coord|52|31|N|13|24|E|type:country_source:kolossus-slwiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Weimar Republic}}
[[Category:1933 disestablishments]]
[[Category:Weimar Republic| ]]
[[Category:Weimar culture]]
[[Category:Great Depression]]
[[Category:Interwar period]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 1919]]

{{Link GA|de}}
{{Link GA|zh}}
{{Link FA|eo}}

[[af:Republiek van Weimar]]
[[ar:جمهورية فايمار]]
[[an:Republica de Weimar]]
[[az:Veymar Respublikası]]
[[bn:ভাইমার প্রজাতন্ত্র]]
[[be:Веймарская рэспубліка]]
[[be-x-old:Ваймарская рэспубліка]]
[[bg:Ваймарска република]]
[[bs:Weimarska republika]]
[[br:Republik Weimar]]
[[ca:República de Weimar]]
[[cs:Výmarská republika]]
[[cy:Gweriniaeth Weimar]]
[[da:Weimarrepublikken]]
[[de:Weimarer Republik]]
[[et:Weimari vabariik]]
[[el:Δημοκρατία της Βαϊμάρης]]
[[es:República de Weimar]]
[[eo:Vajmara Respubliko]]
[[eu:Weimar Errepublika]]
[[fa:جمهوری وایمار]]
[[fr:République de Weimar]]
[[fy:Weimarrepublyk]]
[[ga:Poblacht Weimar]]
[[gv:Pobblaght Weimar]]
[[gl:República de Weimar]]
[[ko:바이마르 공화국]]
[[hsb:Weimarska republika]]
[[hr:Weimarska Republika]]
[[id:Republik Weimar]]
[[is:Weimar-lýðveldið]]
[[it:Repubblica di Weimar]]
[[he:רפובליקת ויימאר]]
[[ka:ვაიმარის რესპუბლიკა]]
[[sw:Jamhuri ya Weimar]]
[[la:Res Publica Vimariana]]
[[lv:Veimāras republika]]
[[lt:Veimaro respublika]]
[[hu:Weimari Köztársaság]]
[[mk:Вајмарска Република]]
[[mr:वायमार प्रजासत्ताक]]
[[ms:Republik Weimar]]
[[nl:Weimarrepubliek]]
[[ja:ヴァイマル共和政]]
[[no:Tysklands historie (1918–1933)]]
[[nn:Weimarrepublikken]]
[[uz:Veymar Respublikasi]]
[[pms:Repùblica 'd Weimar]]
[[pl:Republika Weimarska]]
[[pt:República de Weimar]]
[[ro:Republica de la Weimar]]
[[ru:Веймарская республика]]
[[sq:Republika e Wiemarit]]
[[simple:Weimar Republic]]
[[sk:Weimarská republika]]
[[sl:Weimarska republika]]
[[sr:Вајмарска Република]]
[[sh:Weimarska Republika]]
[[fi:Weimarin tasavalta]]
[[sv:Weimarrepubliken]]
[[th:สาธารณรัฐไวมาร์]]
[[tr:Weimar Cumhuriyeti]]
[[uk:Веймарська республіка]]
[[vi:Cộng hòa Weimar]]
[[war:Republika han Weimar]]
[[yo:Weimar Olómìnira]]
[[zh:魏瑪共和國]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
