<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="336921" ns="0" title="Ahmed Orabi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
[[File:Ahmed Orabi 1882.png|thumb|Ahmed Orabi (1882)]]
Colonel '''Ahmed Orabi''' or '''Ahmed Urabi''' ({{lang-ar|أحمد عرابى}}, {{IPA-arz|ˈæħmæd ʕoˈɾˤɑːbi}}; April 1, 1841 – September 21, 1911; also known as Orabi [[Pasha]], Orabi Pasha and Ahmed Pasha Orabi el-Masri; his name was also transliterated Ahmad Arabi in older sources) was an [[Egyptians|Egyptian]] army general, and nationalist who led a [[Urabi Revolt|revolt]] in 1879 against [[Tewfik Pasha]], the [[Khedive]] of [[Egypt]] and [[Sudan]], and the increasing European domination of the country. The revolt was ultimately crushed in 1882 when the [[United Kingdom]] invaded at the request of Tewfik, thereby commencing the 74 year British occupation Egypt. Orabi was the first Egyptian national political and military leader to rise from the ''[[fellahin]]''.

==Early life==
He was born in 1841 in the village of Hreyya Razna near [[Zagazig]] in the [[Sharqia Governorate]], approximately 80 kilometres to the north of [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.egypttoday.com/article.aspx?ArticleID=2483 'Far and Away'] by [[Egypt Today]]&lt;/ref&gt; Orabi was the son of a village leader and one of the wealthier members of the community, which allowed him to received a decent education. After completing elementary education in his home village, he enrolled at [[Al-Azhar University]] to complete his schooling in 1849. He entered the army and moved up quickly through the ranks, reaching Lieutenant Colonel by age 20. The modern education and military service of Orabi, from a ''[[fellah]]'', or peasant background, would not be possible without the modernizing reforms of Khedive [[Ismail Pasha|Ismail]], who had done much to eliminate the barriers between the bulk of the Egyptian populace and the ruling elite, who were drawn largely from the military castes that had ruled Egypt for centuries. Ismail abolished the exclusive access to the Egyptian and Sudanese military ranks held by Egyptians of Balkan, Circassian, and Turkish origin, and conscripted soldiers, and recruited students throughout Egypt and Sudan regardless of class and ethnic backgrounds in order to form a &quot;modern&quot; and &quot;national&quot; Egyptian military and bureaucratic elite class. Without these reforms, Orabi's rise through the ranks of the military would likely have been far more restricted.

==Protest against Tewfiq==
He was a galvanizing speaker. Because of his peasant origins, he was at the time, and is still today, viewed as an authentic voice of the Egyptian people. Indeed, he was known by his followers as 'El Wahid' (the Only One), and when the British poet and explorer [[Wilfrid Scawen Blunt]] went to meet him, he found the entrance of Orabi's house was blocked with supplicants. When Khedive Tawfiq issued a new law preventing peasants from becoming officers, Orabi led the group protesting the preference shown to aristocratic officers (again, largely Egyptians of foreign descent). He and his followers, who included most of the army, were successful and the law was repealed. In 1879 they formed the Egyptian Nationalist Party.

He and his allies in the army joined with the reformers, and with the support of the peasants launched a broader effort to try to wrest Egypt and Sudan from foreign control, and also to end the absolutist regime of the Khedive, who was himself subject to Anglo-French control under the rules of the [[Caisse de la Dette Publique]]. The revolt spread to express resentment of the undue influence of foreigners, including the predominantly Turko-[[Circassians|Circassian]] aristocracy.

== Parliament planning ==
He was first promoted to [[Bey]], then made under-secretary of war, and ultimately a member of the cabinet. Plans were begun to create a parliamentary assembly. During the last months of the revolt (July to September 1882), it was claimed that Orabi held the office of prime minister.

Feeling threatened, Khedive Tawfiq called requested assistance against Orabi from the [[Ottoman Sultan]], to whom Egypt and Sudan still owed technical fealty. The Sublime Porte hesitated.

== British intervention ==
The British were especially concerned that Orabi would default on Egypt's massive debt and that he might try to re-gain control of the [[Suez Canal]]. They and the French therefore dispatched warships to Egypt to intimidate the nationalists, though the French later withdrew their contingent of the operation. This naval presence spurred fears of an imminent invasion (as had been the case in Tunisia in 1881) and caused anti-European riots to break out in [[Alexandria]] on the June 12, 1882. One month later, the warships opened fire on the city's gun emplacements after the Egyptians ignored the ultimatum issued by Admiral Seymour which demanded an immediate end to the installation of those emplacements. In September of that year a British army landed in Alexandria but failed to reach Cairo after being defeated at the battle of [[Kafr-el-Dawwar]]. Another army, led by [[Sir Garnet Wolseley]], landed in the Canal Zone and on September 13, 1882 they defeated Orabi's army at the [[Battle of Tel el-Kebir]]. From there, the cavalry advanced on Cairo which surrendered without a shot, as did Orabi and the other nationalist leaders.

== Exile and return ==
Orabi was tried by the restored Khedivate for rebellion on December 3, 1882.  In accordance with an understanding made with the British representative, [[Lord Dufferin]], Orabi pleaded guilty and was sentenced to death, but the sentence was immediately commuted to one of banishment for life.&lt;ref&gt;Lord Cromer, ''Modern Egypt, Volume 1'', p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt;  He left Egypt on December 28, 1882 for [[Ceylon]] (now [[Sri Lanka]]). His home in Halloluwa Road, Kandy is now the Orabi Pasha Museum and Cultural Centre. During his time in Ceylon, Orabi served to improve the quality of education amongst the Muslims in the country.  [[Zahira College, Colombo|Zahira College]], Sri Lanka's first school for Muslims, was established under his patronage.  In May 1901, Khedive [[Abbas_II_of_Egypt|Abbas II]], Tewfiq's son and successor permitted Orabi to return to Egypt. Abbas was a nationalist in the vein of his grandfather, Khedive [[Ismail Pasha|Ismail the Magnificent]], and was deeply opposed to the British occupation of the country. Orabi returned on October 1, 1901, and remained until his death on September 21, 1911.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2.sis.gov.eg/Functions/S_Print.asp?ArtId=2000000000000000000097&amp;lg=En Egypt state information]&lt;/ref&gt; 

While British intervention was meant to be short term, British forces continued to occupy the country, instituting the ousting of Khedive Abbas II in 1914, after which Egypt once more became a sultanate, and also a British [[protectorate]]. Britain finally recognised Egyptian [[Unilateral Declaration of Egyptian Independence|independence]] in 1922, following the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1919]]. Orabi's revolt also had a long lasting significance as the first instance of Egyptian anti-imperialist nationalism, which would later play a very important role in Egyptian history.  Especially under [[Gamal Abdel Nasser]], Orabi would be regarded as an Egyptian patriot, and a national hero and is considered an [[anti-imperialist]] hero in Sri Lanka.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sundaytimes.lk/080302/KandyTimes/kandytimes_0026.html Udumbara Udugama, &quot;That exile from Egypt who inspired many&quot;, ''Sunday Times'', March 2, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Legacy ==
* One of the [[Cairo Metro]] under ground stations in the downtown area of Cairo is named after Orabi.
* [[Ahmed Orabi Square|A large square]] is named after him in [[Alexandria]].
* [[Zagazig University]] has his picture in its emblem.
* The coastal road of the Palestine's [[Gaza Strip]] is named Ahmed Orabi Street in Orabi's honour.
* Orabi Pasha Street in Central [[Colombo]], [[Sri Lanka]] is named after him.
* An Orabi Pasha Museum and a cultural centre are housed at Orabi Pasha's former house in [[Kandy]].
* A main Street in Al Mohandessin district is named after his name.

== Quotes ==
* ''&quot;How can you enslave people when their mothers bore them free&quot;''
* &quot;God created us free , And didn't create us Heritage or real estate , I swear that there is no god but He, No bequeathing, No enslaved anymore&quot;

== Notes ==
* The earliest published work of [[Isabella Augusta, Lady Gregory]] – later to embrace [[Irish Nationalism]] and have an important role in the cultural life of Ireland – was ''Arabi and His Household'' (1882), a pamphlet (originally a letter to ''[[The Times]]'' newspaper) in support of Ahmed Orabi (&quot;Arabi&quot; being an archaic mistransliteration not uncommon in English at the time).  
{| border=&quot;1&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;
| width=&quot;30%&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| '''Preceded by''':&lt;br&gt;[[Mahmoud Sami el-Baroudi]]
| width=&quot;40%&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| [[Prime Minister of Egypt]]&lt;br&gt;(in rebellion)
| width=&quot;30%&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| '''Succeeded by''':&lt;br&gt;[[Muhammad Sharif Pasha]]
|}
{{EgyptPMs}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Ahmed Orabi}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Orabi, Ahmed
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = 
| DATE OF BIRTH     = April 1, 1841
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = 
| DATE OF DEATH     = September 21, 1911
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Orabi, Ahmed}}
[[Category:Al-Azhar University alumni]]
[[Category:Prime Ministers of Egypt]]
[[Category:Government ministers of Egypt]]
[[Category:Egyptian soldiers]]
[[Category:Egyptian revolutionaries]]
[[Category:1841 births]]
[[Category:Zagazig]]
[[Category:1911 deaths]]
[[Category:People of the Urabi Revolt]]
[[Category:Egyptian exiles]]
[[Category:People from Sharqia Governorate]]
[[Category:Egyptian prisoners sentenced to death]]
[[Category:Egyptian pashas]]

[[ar:أحمد عرابي]]
[[bg:Араби-паша]]
[[ca:Ahmed al-Arabí]]
[[de:Ahmad Urabi Pascha]]
[[el:Άχμεντ Ουράμπι]]
[[fr:Ahmed Urabi]]
[[ko:아라비 파샤]]
[[id:Arabi Pasha]]
[[it:Ahmad Urabi]]
[[arz:احمد عرابى]]
[[ms:Arabi Pasha]]
[[nl:Ahmed Urabi]]
[[pt:Ahmed Urabi]]
[[ru:Араби-паша]]
[[tr:Arabi Paşa]]
[[zh:艾哈邁德·阿拉比]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
