<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Oakland General Strike of 2011" to="2011 Oakland general strike" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="33699923" ns="0" title="2011 Oakland general strike"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = 2011 Oakland general strike
  |Image_Name     = Occupy Oakland General Strike banner.jpg
  |Imagesize      = &lt;!-- Image size in pixels - default is 220px--&gt;
  |Image_Alt      = The front of a marching crowd carrying a large banner. The banner reads &quot;General Strike!&quot;
  |Image_Caption  = 
  |Thumb_Time     = &lt;!--NA--&gt;
  |AKA            = &lt;!--NA--&gt;
  |Participants   = [[Occupy Oakland]]
  |Location       = [[Oakland, California]], [[United States]].
  |Date           = {{Start date|2011|11|02}}
  |nongregorian   = &lt;!--NA--&gt;
  |Deaths        = &lt;!--NA--&gt;
  |Result         = *Shut down of [[Port of Oakland]] evening shift.
*Evening confrontation with police results in multiple arrests and allegations of police misconduct.
*Widespread media reports of violence are condemned by Oakland mayor [[Jean Quan]] and City Council members.
  |URL            = 
}}
The '''Oakland General Strike of 2011''' was a [[general strike]] held in Oakland, California  on November 2, 2011 as part of the larger [[Occupy Oakland]] movement.    

==General strike==
Thousands of protesters gathered at [[Frank H. Ogawa Plaza]] to participate in rallies, marches, and teach-ins designed to empower citizens and to draw attention to economic inequity and corporate greed. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=California protesters shut down Oakland port|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-15568057|accessdate=November 2, 2011|date=November 2, 2011|publisher=BBC News}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=California protesters shut down Oakland port|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/02/occuply-oakland-general-strike-live|accessdate=November 3, 2011|date=November 2, 2011|publisher=The Guardian News Blog|location=London|first=Matt|last=Wells}}&lt;/ref&gt; The last general strike in the United States was in Oakland in 1946. Local unions expressed solidarity for the [[strike action|strike]] including Oakland's largest union, [[Service Employees International Union|Service Employees International Union]] Local 1021, Oakland Education Association, [[International Longshore and Warehouse Union|International Longshore and Warehouse Union]] Local 10, and [[United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America|United Brotherhood of Carpenters]]. While none of the unions were officially on strike, many urged their members to take a personal day, vacation day or to participate after work. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gee|first=Robyn|title=Teachers, Service Workers Support Oakland's Strike Without Striking|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/turnstyle/teachers-service-workers_b_1071604.html|accessdate=November 6, 2011|newspaper=Huffington Post|date=November 2, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Occupy Oakland General Strike Speakers.jpg|thumb|left|Speakers on the flatbed truck stage]]
A flatbed truck with a sound system was parked in the middle of the intersection of 14th Street and Broadway and used as a make-shift stage. The morning's rally began at 9 a.m. and a range of people addressed the audience including the scholar/activist [[Angela Davis]] and musician [[Boots Riley]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Hamilton|first=John|title=Video Report from Streets of Oakland: First General Strike in City Since 1946 Shuts Down Major Port|url=http://www.democracynow.org/2011/11/3/video_report_from_streets_of_oakland|accessdate=November 13, 2011|newspaper=Democracy Now!|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Live musical performances occurred simultaneously in the plaza amphitheater including local hip hop group [[BRWN BFLO]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Arnold|first=Eric|title=Occupy Oakland: “We shut down the port!” demonstrators say (Ongoing analysis)|url=http://oaklandlocal.com/article/occupy-oakland-%E2%80%9Cwe-shut-down-port%E2%80%9D-demonstrators-say-ongoing-analysis|accessdate=November 13, 2011|newspaper=Oakland Local|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Oakland General Strike 2011-11-02.jpg|thumb|right|One of the marches to the Port of Oakland on Nov. 2, 2011]]
While most of the day-time activities were peaceful, [[Oakland Police Department|Oakland Police]] chief Howard Jordan reported that a small group of &quot;anarchists&quot; vandalized a [[Whole Foods]] storefront, and broke windows and [[Automated teller machine|ATM]]s of [[Bank of America]] and [[Wells Fargo]] banks in the afternoon. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Occupy Oakland General Strike Shuts Down Port; Anarchists ‘Bent On Creating Problems’|url=http://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2011/11/02/general-strike-protesters-shut-down-port-of-oakland/|accessdate=3 November 2011|publisher=CBS San Francisco|date=2 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mercurynews.com/top-stories/ci_19246904 At least 4,000 are at the gates to the Port of Oakland]&lt;/ref&gt; Many buildings were vandalized, including some businesses that displayed signs of support for the general strike.  After the incidents of vandalism, members of Occupy Oakland guarded local businesses, boarded up broken windows, and cleaned graffiti caused by the small group of protesters utilizing [[black bloc]] tactics.  Oakland mayor [[Jean Quan]] described these protesters as &quot;a small and isolated group&quot; that &quot;shouldn't mar the overall impact of the demonstration and the fact that people in the 99 percent movement demonstrated peacefully and, for the most part, were productive and very peaceful.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=%2Fc%2Fa%2F2011%2F11%2F03%2FBACM1LQ5FU.DTL | work=The San Francisco Chronicle | first=Henry K. | last=Lee | title=Developer with shotgun scared off Oakland rioters | date=November 4, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Occupy the Banks Banner.jpg|thumb|left|A banner hung in downtown Oakland during a bank march]]

===March to the Port of Oakland===
Thousands of protesters marched from Frank Ogawa Plaza to the [[Port of Oakland]], the fifth busiest port in the United States, in two separate groups leaving the plaza at 4:00 pm and 5:00 pm. The number of protesters marching to the port has not been confirmed. While police estimate 7,000 people marched, local organizers &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Video Report from Streets of Oakland: First General Strike in City Since 1946 Shuts Down Major Port|url=http://www.democracynow.org/seo/2011/11/3/video_report_from_streets_of_oakland|accessdate=November 6, 2011|publisher=Democracy Now|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and participants &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Abraham|first=Zennie|title=Occupy Oakland Strike Draws 100,000; Violence Caused By 100|url=http://blog.sfgate.com/abraham/2011/11/03/occupy-oakland-strike-draws-100000-violence-caused-by-100/|accessdate=November 6, 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle - Blog|date=November 1, 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; put the number somewhere between 20,000 and 100,000. As protesters completely filled Middle Harbor Road, the main road leading to the port, all truck traffic entering or exiting the port was halted. Port operations were &quot;effectively shut down&quot; a couple hours later.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Occupy Oakland throng closes down port|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/03/MN8Q1LPI1J.DTL|accessdate=November 3, 2011|date=November 2, 2011|newspaper=The San Francisco Chronicle|first1=Demian|last1=Bulwa|first2=Matthai|last2=Kuruvila|first3=Kevin|last3=Fagan}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

====Protesters injured by car====
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 
| video1= &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P_JnuV_K4IU Protesters struck by vehicle]&quot; During march to port, Nov. 2
}}
During the evening march to the port, the driver of a silver Mercedes-Benz was headed south on 11th Street when he encountered a stream of protesters walking along Broadway. Cell phone video footage shows the driver of the Mercedes attempting to drive through the intersection as the march is happening prompting one protester, Lance Laverdure, to jump in front of the car and bang on the hood.&lt;ref name=KGO_mercedes&gt;KGO [http://abclocal.go.com/kgo/story?section=news/local/east_bay&amp;id=8429027#&amp;cmp=twi-kgo-article-8429027 Protesters hit by car press for driver's arrest]&lt;/ref&gt; The driver hit the gas and both Laverdure and a nearby protester Margaret So were hit by the car and sustained leg and ankle injuries. Nearby witnesses then surrounded the car as emergency personnel attended to the protesters. The driver was questioned by [[BART Police]] and released, angering witnesses who called for the driver's arrest.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kuruvila|first=Matthai|title=Mercedes hits 2 Occupy Oakland protesters|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/03/BA5G1LQ06S.DTL|accessdate=November 6, 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two protesters suffered leg and ankle injuries and were taken to Highland Hospital. 

On November 11, the two victims held a press conference alleging that the incident was a criminal act and questioned why the Oakland Police Department had not prosecuted the driver. Victims said that nine days after the incident, they still had not been contacted by police. Lance Laverdure told press that,  &quot;We want this person arrested for the attempted murder of myself and Margaret&quot;.&lt;ref name=KGO_mercedes /&gt;

==Night of November 2==
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 
| video1= &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CQl0g2Rqyfs  CA Violence: RT footage from 'occupied' Oakland]&quot;  Night of Nov. 2 
}}
===Occupation of vacant building=== 

Later in the evening, a group of protesters took over a vacant building that once served as the headquarters of the Traveler's Aid Society, a non-profit organization that provided services to the local homeless population. Police soon arrived to break up the protesters gathered outside of the building. Some protesters fled while others set a barricade on fire. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Loftis|first=Emily|title=Occupy Oakland shuts down port|url=http://www.salon.com/2011/11/03/occupy_oakland_shuts_down_port/|accessdate=November 4, 2011|newspaper=Salon|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Police used teargas and flash bangs to try to clear protesters.  &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Occupy Oakland general strike – Thursday 3 November|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/blog/2011/nov/03/occupy-oakland-general-strike-live#block-13|accessdate=November 3, 2011|date=November 2, 2011|newspaper=The Guardian|location=London|first=Haroon|last=Siddique}}&lt;/ref&gt; Clashes continued past midnight. 103 people were arrested.

===Incidents of alleged police misconduct=== 

====Scott Campbell shooting====
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 
| video1= &quot;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I0pX9LeE-g8 Shot by police with rubber bullet at Occupy Oakland]&quot; Filmed by Oakland resident Scott Campbell, moments before being shot by an Oakland Police officer. 
}}
Shortly before 1 a.m., Oakland resident Scott Campbell was shot by police using a [[Non-lethal_weapon#Ammunition|less-lethal round]] while he was filming a stationary line of police in riot gear. The apparently-unprovoked shooting was documented by the resulting point-of-view video from Campbell's own camera.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-201_162-57321440/experts-occupy-vid-shows-excessive-force/ Experts: &quot;Occupy&quot; video shows excessive force]&lt;/ref&gt;  Geoffrey Alpert, a criminal justice professor from the University of South Carolina said watching a video of the incident left him &quot;astonished, amazed and embarrassed&quot; and that &quot;unless there's something we don't know, that's one of the most outrageous uses of a firearm that I've ever seen.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.mercurynews.com/top-stories/ci_19284774|accessdate=Nov 7, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Kayvan Sabeghi beating====
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 
| video1= &quot;[http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/video/2011/nov/18/occupy-oakland-veteran-beaten-police-video Iraq war veteran Kayvan Sabehgi beaten by a police officer]&quot;  
}}
Kayvan Sabeghi, a local business owner and former [[United States Army Rangers|U.S. Army Ranger]] who served in the [[Iraq War]] and the [[War in Afghanistan (2001–present)|War in Afghanistan]], was hit numerous times by a police officer with a baton then arrested on the evening of November 2. &lt;ref name=N18guard&gt;{{cite news|last=Gabbatt|first=Adam|title=Occupy Oakland: footage shows police beating 'peaceful' Iraq war veteran|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/video/2011/nov/18/occupy-oakland-veteran-beaten-police-video|accessdate=November 21, 2011|newspaper=The Guardian|date=November 18, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sabeghi was charged with resisting arrest and remaining at the scene of a riot. While in police custody, Sabeghi complained of severe pain and asked for medical treatment but was transferred to [[Highland Hospital (Oakland, California)|Highland Hospital]] 14-18 hours after his arrest. Sabeghi underwent emergency surgery for a ruptured spleen and remained in the intensive care unit. &lt;ref name=kayvan_reuters&gt;{{cite news|last=Randewich|first=Noel|title=Army veteran injured in Oakland clashes with police|url=http://www.reuters.com/article/2011/11/05/us-protests-oakland-veteran-idUSTRE7A37A820111105|accessdate=6 November 2011|newspaper=Reuters|date=4 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=N18guard /&gt;  

The organization [[Iraq Veterans Against the War]] issued a statement on November 4 stating, &quot;police struck Sabeghi with nightsticks on his hands, shoulders, ribs and back, and that in addition to a lacerated [[spleen]] he suffered from internal bleeding&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gabbatt|first=Adam|title=Occupy Oakland: second Iraq war veteran injured after police clashes|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/nov/04/occupy-oakland-second-veteran-injured|accessdate=November 6, 2011|newspaper=The Guardian|date=November 4, 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;, a description that is corroborated by the video made available on November 18. The Oakland Police Department is &quot;investigating the incident.&quot;&lt;ref name=N18guard /&gt;

====Susie Cagle arrest and imprisonment====
Although she was obviously wearing a press pass, journalist Susie Cagle was arrested in the early hours of November 3 and spent 14 hours at 2 different jails. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Daetz|first=Ama|title=Journalist arrested while covering Oakland protest|url=http://abclocal.go.com/kgo/story?section=news/local/east_bay&amp;id=8418546|accessdate=November 21, 2011|newspaper=KGO-TV|date=November 3, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She was charged with failure to leave the scene of a riot. Journalists' rights in the United States are constitutionally protected through the [[First_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution#Freedom_of_the_press|First Amendment]]. Cagle is one of several journalists covering the Occupy movement that have been arrested. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Human Rights Group Condemns Journalist Arrests At Occupy Protests|url=http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2011/11/17/human-rights-group-condem_n_1100282.html|accessdate=November 21, 2011|newspaper=The Huffington Post|date=November 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, Cagle reported having been subject to and witness to mistreatment of protestors during her imprisonment.&lt;ref name=Cagle&gt;[http://www.alternet.org/story/152990/police_state_in_oakland_one_reporter%27s_arrest_contradicts_official_story/?page=entire]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{Occupy movement}}

[[Category:2011 riots]]
[[Category:General strikes]]
[[Category:Occupy Oakland]]
[[Category:Riots and civil disorder in the United States]]
[[Category:Police brutality in California‎]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
