<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33705425" ns="0" title="Occupy Cal"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Occupy Cal Sproul Plaza 2011.jpg|thumb|Occupy Cal, November 15, 2011]]
'''Occupy Cal''' is an ongoing series of [[Demonstration (people)|demonstrations]] that began on November 9, 2011, on the [[University of California, Berkeley]] campus in [[Berkeley, California]]. It is allied with the [[Occupy Wall Street]] movement in [[New York City]], [[San Francisco Bay Area]] Occupy groups such as [[Occupy Oakland]], [[Occupy Berkeley]], and [[Occupy San Francisco]], and other public California universities. &quot;Cal&quot; in the name &quot;Occupy Cal&quot; is the nickname of the Berkeley campus and generally refers specifically to [[UC Berkeley]].  

A major theme of the Occupy Cal demonstrations is the role of education in creating jobs and improving quality of life for society as a whole, and the failure of the [[UC Regents]] and the State of California to honor commitments made in the [[California Master Plan for Higher Education]]. Tuition increases for students, mandatory furloughs for professors and staff, firings or forced realignment of lower-ranking workers as part of the &quot;Operational Excellence&quot; reorganization, and raises for the highest paid administrators have further fueled discontent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gordon|first=Larry|title=UC to seek state funds to avoid tuition hike next year|url=http://articles.latimes.com/2011/nov/09/local/la-me-uc-20111109|accessdate=21 November 2011|newspaper=Los Angeles Times|date=9 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://berkeley.edu/news/media/releases/2009/07/10_furlough.shtml|title=Furloughs, pay cuts proposed for UC staff and faculty|date=July 10, 2009|author=Barry Bergman|accessdate=November 20, 2011|publisher=UCBerkeleyNews}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Cash-strapped UC hands out millions in raises|url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2011-08-18/bay-area/29899242_1_uc-service-workers-president-lakesha-harrison-uc-officials|date=August 18, 2011|author=Nanette Asimov|publisher=SFGate.com|accessdate=November 20, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{See also|2009 California college tuition hike protests}} 

Budget cuts, tuition increases, and unpaid furlough days affecting public California universities have been the target of protest by UC Berkeley students, faculty, and employees in recent years. The UC Regents has approved increased tuition fees nine times in seven years. In September 2009, several thousand students, faculty, and employees converged on [[Sproul Plaza]] to protest a proposed tuition increase of 32%. Simultaneous protests on [[University of California]] and [[California State University]] campuses occurred throughout the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/25/education/25calif.htm|title=California university cuts protested|newspaper=[[The New York Times]]|accessdate=21 November 2011| date=25 September 2009|first=Malia|last=Wollan}}&lt;/ref&gt; The state-wide campus protests did not sway the UC Regents, however, and the 32% tuition increase was approved in November 2009, setting off another round of protests that included the temporary occupation of campus buildings.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2009/1210/p02s30-usgn.html|title=Fee hikes bring student protests back to California universities|publisher=[[Christian Science Monitor]]|accessdate=21 November 2011| date=10 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Protests continued through 2010 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Timeline: UC Berkeley fee increase protests|url=http://oaklandnorth.net/2010/03/03/timeline-uc-berkeley-fee-increase-protests/|date=March 3, 2010|author=Josh Wolf|publisher=Oakland North|accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Timeline: California students protest education cuts|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2010/03/05/education/05protests.html|date=March 5, 2010|author=Jesse McKinley|publisher=The New York Times|accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Tuition hikes spark UC Berkeley protests|url=http://abclocal.go.com/kgo/story?section=news/education&amp;id=7799384 |date=November 19, 2010|author=Terry McSweeney|publisher=[[KGO-TV]]|accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and 2011&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Protesters on ledge at UC Berkeley come down|url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2011-03-04/bay-area/28652824_1_protesters-students-barricaded-budget-cuts|date=March 4, 2011|author=Mihir Zaveri|publisher=San Francisco Chronicle|accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=UC Berkeley students protest tuition hikes, cuts|url=http://articles.sfgate.com/2011-09-23/bay-area/30192464_1_tuition-hikes-callie-maidhof-protests|date=September 23, 2011|author=Nanette Asimov|publisher=San Francisco Chronicle|accessdate=November 21, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Occupy Cal being the most recent iteration of a multi-year protest for affordable public education.

==November 9 protest and police response==
{{ external media
| align  = right
| width  = 
| video1= [http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=buovLQ9qyWQ  Police response to Occupy Cal protesters], Nov 9
}}

On November 9, 2011, students and professors at UC Berkeley participated in a series of &quot;teach-outs&quot; around campus, a noon rally and march.  Approximately 1,500 demonstrators attended the days' events.&lt;ref name=10KGO&gt;{{cite news|last=Hollyfield|first=Amy|title=Occupy Cal calm, but ready for showdown|url=http://abclocal.go.com/kgo/story?section=news/local/east_bay&amp;id=8426365|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=KGO-TV|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The march route included a Bank of America location adjacent to campus.  Not long after demonstrators set up seven tents in front of Upper [[Sproul Plaza]] in the mid-afternoon, law enforcement officials from UC Berkeley Police, the [[Alameda County Sheriff's Office]] and other [[University of California Police Department|UC Police]] officers in [[riot gear]] arrived to remove the tents.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Asimov|first=Nanette|title=Occupy Cal protesters vote to strike on Tuesday|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/10/MNH21LT6ND.DTL|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SF2&gt;{{cite news|last=Asimov|first=Nanette|title=UC campus police move in on student protesters|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/10/BA861LSR8G.DTL|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Protesters linked arms to form a human chain in front of the tents to prevent officers from dismantling the encampment. Police used [[Baton (law enforcement)|36-inch riot batons]] to &quot;[[jab]]&quot; and push back the protesters and to break the human chain.&lt;ref name=10KGO /&gt;

Video footage of the afternoon confrontation shows police using batons and dragging two protesters by the hair, one of whom was UC Berkeley English professor Celeste Langan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Gollan|first=Jennifer|title=UC Berkeley Pledges to Investigate Police Response to Occupy Cal Protest|url=http://www.baycitizen.org/occupy-movement/story/uc-berkeley-pledges-investigate-police/|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=The Bay Citizen|date=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ucberkinvetpoltac&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.baycitizen.org/education/story/uc-berkeley-investigate-allegations/|title=UC Berkeley Investigating Police Tactics|date=November 14, 2011|author=Jennifer Gollan|publisher=The Bay Citizen|accessdate=November 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  39 protesters, including Professor Langan, were arrested for charges including &quot;resisting and delaying a police officer in the performance of their duties and failure to disperse when given a dispersal order.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bowe|first=Rebecca|title=Occupy Cal makes its dramatic entrance|url=http://www.sfbg.com/politics/2011/11/10/occupy-cal-makes-its-dramatic-entrance|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Bay Guardian|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Robert Hass]], a UC Berkeley professor of poetry and former [[United States Poet Laureate]], wrote about the police response in a November 19 ''[[New York Times]]'' opinion piece entitled &quot;Poet-Bashing Police&quot;: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;the deputies in the cordon surged forward and, using their clubs as battering rams, began to hammer at the bodies of the line of students. It was stunning to see. They swung hard into their chests and bellies. Particularly shocking to me — it must be a generational reaction — was that they assaulted both the young men and the young women with the same indiscriminate force. If the students turned away, they pounded their ribs. If they turned further away to escape, they hit them on their spines.&quot;&lt;ref name=hassnyt&gt;{{cite news|last=Hass|first=Robert|title=Poet-Bashing Police|url=http://www.nytimes.com/2011/11/20/opinion/sunday/at-occupy-berkeley-beat-poets-has-new-meaning.html|accessdate=November 27, 2011|newspaper=The New York Times|date=November 19, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; 

Hass himself was hit in the ribs by a police officer wielding a baton. His wife Brenda Hillman was shoved to the ground by a police officer.&lt;ref name=hassnyt /&gt;

==Reaction to Nov. 9 police response==
====UC Berkeley Administration and Police====
In response to questions about the officers' use of force, UC Police Captain Margo Bennett stated: {{quote|The individuals who [[Nonviolent Resistance|linked arms and actively resisted]], that in itself is an act of [[violence]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Kane|first=Will|title=UC cops' use of batons on Occupy camp questioned|url=http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/c/a/2011/11/10/MNH21LTC4D.DTL|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=San Francisco Chronicle|date=11 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; }}

[[Robert Birgeneau]], UC Berkeley Chancellor, [[George Breslauer]], Executive Vice Chancellor and Provost, and [[Harry Le Grande]], Vice Chancellor for Student Affairs initially released a &quot;Message to the Campus Community&quot; in which they stated, &quot;It is unfortunate that some protesters chose to obstruct the police by linking arms and forming a human chain to prevent the police from gaining access to the tents.  This is not non-violent [[civil disobedience]].&quot; The administrators also stated, &quot;We regret that, given the instruction to take down tents and prevent encampment, the police were forced to use their [[Baton (law enforcement)|batons]] to enforce the policy.  We regret all injuries, to protesters and police, that resulted from this effort.  The campus's Police Review Board will ultimately determine whether police used [[excessive force]] under the circumstances.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Khan|first=Sara|title=Campus administrators send out message responding to Occupy Cal demonstrations|url=http://www.dailycal.org/2011/11/10/campus-administrators-send-out-message-responding-to-occupy-cal-demonstrations/|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=The Daily Californian|date=10 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Following media criticism and statements of disapproval from the university community and academic departments&lt;ref name=&quot;interbio&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.dailycal.org/2011/11/14/integrative-biology-faculty-students-condemn-campus-response-to-occupy-cal/|title=Integrative biology faculty, students condemn campus response to Occupy Cal|date=November 14, 2011|author=Sarah Burns|publisher=The Daily Californian|accessdate=November 22, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!-- (add links to others too) --&gt; [[Robert Birgeneau|Chancellor Birgeneau]] released a further &quot;Message regarding events on campus&quot; in which he stated, &quot;I returned to Berkeley yesterday after a week-long trip to Seoul, Tokyo and Shanghai where we successfully advanced some important new partnerships that will benefit our campus... While away, I remained in intermittent contact with Provost [[George Breslauer]] and other members of our leadership team and was kept informed, as much as possible, about the Occupy Cal activities on campus.  However, it was only yesterday that I was able to look at a number of the videos that were made of the protests on November 9.  These videos are very disturbing.  The events of last Wednesday are unworthy of us as a university community.&quot; Birgeneau also stated, &quot;we cannot condone any [[excessive use of force]] against any members of our community,&quot; and granted amnesty to students involved in the protests.  Birgeneau's statement that he could not watch videos available on the internet while in Asia was widely met with cynicism from the university community.&lt;ref name=&quot;ucberkinvetpoltac&quot; /&gt;

====UC Faculty and Students====
The UC Student Association is &quot;outraged by the brutal tactics used by the UCPD against students.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Applegate|first=Jamie|title=Reactions to the police response to Occupy Cal on Nov. 9|url=http://www.dailycal.org/2011/11/13/reactions-to-the-police-response-to-occupy-cal-on-nov-9/|accessdate=13 November 2011|newspaper=The Daily Californian|date=13 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Department of Integrative Biology stated, &quot;We are deeply disturbed by the images of [[violence]] against members of the campus community, as well as the justification and defense of these acts that followed&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;interbio&quot; /&gt; The School of Social Welfare issued an open letter to the campus community stating, &quot;We are outraged and appalled by the violent silencing of UC Berkeley student voices.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://socialwelfare.berkeley.edu/NewsEvents/student_openletter_nov15.shtml|title=An Open Letter To:The Office of the Chancellor, UC Berkeley, California Members of the National Association of Social Workers, Students, Faculty and Alumni of the UC Berkeley School of Social Welfare|date=September 15, 2011|accessdate=November 20, 2011|publisher=University of California, Berkeley}}&lt;/ref&gt; 70 faculty of the School of Law condemned the police action and called for &quot;a reestablishment of the campus's reputation as a beacon of free speech&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Samad|first=Aaida|title=UC Berkeley School of Law faculty condemn police actions at Occupy Cal|url=http://www.dailycal.org/2011/11/09/coverage-of-nov-9-day-of-action/|accessdate=2011-11-20|newspaper=The Daily Californian}}&lt;/ref&gt;  2,363 faculty and staff stated &quot;We express [[no confidence]] in the willingness of the Chancellor, and other leaders of the UC Berkeley administration, to respond appropriately to student protests, to secure student welfare, and to respect [[freedom of speech]] and [[freedom of assembly|assembly]] on the Berkeley campus.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Open letter to Chancellor Birgeneau|url=http://ucsdfa.org/uc-berkeley-faculty-petition/384|work=originally on www.ipetitions.com and reposted by UCSD Faculty Association}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Other reactions====
The ACLU made a statement saying they have &quot;grave concerns&quot; about the use of batons on protesters.

==General Strike on November 15 and later events==
[[File:Occupy Cal General Assembly at night.jpg|thumb|right|Occupy Cal General Assembly at night]]
In response to the actions of police officers and other perceived failings of Chancellor Birgeneau and the [[UC Regents]], the Occupy Cal voted to call for a general strike at UC Berkeley on November 15, 2011.  The timing of the strike and protests was intended to coincide with a meeting of the [[UC Regents]] the next day, which was then cancelled by [[UC Regents]] and administrators from the UC Office of the President, citing &quot;credible law enforcement intelligence&quot;&lt;!-- (cite Asimov 2011 article) --&gt;.  Many students and faculty did not attend classes and walked out, or incorporated teach-ins, or spent at least part of the day actively protesting.  The [[UC Davis]] Faculty Association also voted to endorse the November 15 systemwide strike.&lt;ref&gt;[http://ucdfa.org/2011/11/11/dfa-endorses-occupy-cals-call-for-strike/ Davis Faculty Association Endorses Occupy Cal’s Call for Strike]&lt;/ref&gt;  Events included a downtown march past Berkeley High School and Berkeley City College, speeches, and resolutions.

A small encampment was set up and allowed to exist for a day before being peacefully dismantled on November 17, with 2 voluntary arrests at 3:30 AM&lt;!-- (cite Chronicle article) --&gt;.  Approximately 100 to 120 police in riot gear were used to dismantle the tents and make the arrests.  Following that, tents were flown over Upper Sproul using balloons, including a banner claiming &quot;Our Space&quot;.  Occupy Cal events have, to this point, been completely peaceful except for violence initiated by [[police]] as part of [[police action]].  

On November 18, newspaper reports indicate that [[UC Davis]] police officers used pepper spray on protesters sitting peacefully on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | newspaper=[[The Cleveland Leader]] | title=UC Davis Police Brutally Pepper Spray OWS Protesters Sitting Peacefully  on Campus | url=http://www.clevelandleader.com/node/17846 | first=Julie | last= Kent | date= 19 November 2011 | accessdate = 21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |newspaper= [[Los Angeles Times]] |title=UC Davis chief launches probe into pepper-spraying of Occupy protesters |url=http://www.latimes.com/news/local/la-me-occupy-uc-davis-20111120,0,2407596.story |first1=Paul |last1= Pringle | first2=Sam 
 | last2=Quinones | date= 19 November 2011 | accessdate = 21 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The close proximity of Berkeley and Davis, university-provided shuttle service between campuses, and ties between Occupy Cal and [[Occupy UC Davis]] suggest this most recent police action will cause further unrest and have already prompted statements from UC President [[Mark Yudof]] calling for a review of police procedures.

==See also==
*[[List of Occupy movement protest locations|List of global Occupy protest locations]]
{{Portal bar|Social movements|Politics|Business and economics|San Francisco Bay Area|California|United States}}

==External links==
* {{official website|http://www.occupyucdavis.org/}}
* [http://oe.berkeley.edu/ Operational Excellence]
* [http://www.berkeley.edu/ University of California, Berkeley]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Occupy movement}}

[[Category:Occupy movement in the United States]]
[[Category:University of California, Berkeley]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
