<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><redirects><r from="Morris Pratt Institute" to="Morris Pratt" /></redirects><pages><page pageid="33814990" ns="0" title="Morris Pratt"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:MorrisPratt.gif|right|thumb|alt=Oval portrait of bearded man|Portrait of Morris Pratt]] --&gt;&lt;!--Non free file removed by DASHBot--&gt;

'''Morris Pratt''' (1820–1902) was the founder of the [[Morris Pratt Institute]] of [[spiritualism]].  He built a college in [[Whitewater, Wisconsin]] for the study of [[psychic]] phenomenon that became known by residents as the &quot;Spook Temple&quot;.

== Birth ==
Very little information is known about Morris Pratt's birth.  He was born in 1820 in [[Madison County, New York]].

== Morris Pratt Institute's Description of Pratt ==
There is little written concerning the life of Morris Pratt. However, it is well known that after his visit to the Lake Mills Spiritualist Center in 1851, he became very interested in psychic phenomena and the Religion of Spiritualism. Being well educated, he frequently argued with ministers who criticized Spiritualism and on several occasions was evicted from their churches. At one time, he was fined for his controversial actions. Being dedicated to the promotion of Spiritualism, he fully recognized the need for educated workers to present the religion to the intellect of the times.

It is said that &quot;one day his Red Indian guide told him of certain mineral deposits unknown to any white man.&quot; He made an investment in a company which later became the profitable [[Ashland Mine]] of [[Ironwood, Michigan]]. Pratt always said, &quot;If I am made rich, I will give part of it to [[Spiritualism]].&quot;

Within a few month's time, he made over $200,000. He did not hesitate in fulfilling his promise by using part of the monies for the benefit of the cause of [[Spiritualism]]. In 1889, the Temple was dedicated. When opened, it consisted of lecture rooms, office, a chapel and dormitories. The land and original building at [[Whitewater, Wisconsin]] was deeded to the [[Morris Pratt Institute]].

== Wisconsin Historical Society Description ==
Spiritualist, and founder of Morris Pratt Institute; born in 1820 in Madison Co., [[New York]], he came with his brother to Milton about 1850, where he created a successful farm. Pratt became an ardent spiritualist in the 1850s, when seances, spirit knockings, mediums, and trances were much in vogue, and vowed that if he were ever wealthy he would give his fortune to support the movement. About 1884, he followed the advice of mystic [[Mary Hayes Chynoweth]] (q.v.) and invested his small savings in the Germania and Ashland mines in the [[Gogebic Iron Range]]. In a few months he sold his shares for $200,000 and, true to his word, in 1888 began building an edifice in downtown [[Whitewater|Whitewater, Wisconsin]] to house his spiritualist institution. Known locally as &quot;Pratt's Folly,&quot; it was not finished or occupied until after his death in 1902, when the [[Morris Pratt Institute]] registered its first students.

== Sources ==
#[http://www.morrispratt.org/ Morris Pratt Institute]
#[http://www.answers.com/topic/morris-pratt Answers.com Biography]
#[http://stevepearson.org/moseshull/23.htm Biography]
#[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/dictionary/index.asp?action=view&amp;term_id=10529&amp;term_type_id=1&amp;term_type_text=People&amp;letter=P Wisconsin Historical Society]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Pratt, Morris
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1820
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = Madison County, New York
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1902
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Pratt, Morris}}
[[Category:Spiritualists]]
[[Category:Paranormal investigators]]
[[Category:1820 births]]
[[Category:1902 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Madison County, New York]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
