<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3388950" ns="0" title="WVAW-LD"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox broadcast |
  call_letters   = WVAW-LD|
  station_logo   = [[File:Wvaw lp 2008.png|150px]] 
  station_slogan = ''Where Charlottesville''&lt;br&gt;''News Comes First''|
  station_branding = ABC 16 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;CBS 19 News&lt;br&gt;CBS 19 &lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;|
  digital        = 16 ([[UHF]])|
  subchannels    = 16.1 [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]&lt;br&gt;[[WCAV|16.2]] [[CBS]]|
  affiliations   = | 
  founded        = 1979|
  location       = [[Charlottesville, Virginia]]|
  callsign_meaning       = '''VA''' ([[Virginia]] postal abbreviation)|
  former_callsigns = W64AO (1979-2004)&lt;br&gt;WVAW-LP (2004-2009)|
  former_channel_numbers   = 64 (UHF analog, 1979-2004)&lt;br&gt;16 (UHF analog, 2004-2009)|
  owner          = [[Gray Television]]|
  licensee                 = Gray Television Licensee, Inc.|
  sister_stations          = [[WCAV]], [[WAHU-CD]], [[WHSV-TV]]|
  effective_radiated_power = 15 [[kilowatt|kW]]|
  HAAT                     = 324 m|
  class                    = |
  facility_id              = 4687|
  coordinates              = {{coord|37|59|3|N|78|28|52|W|type:landmark}} |
  homepage       = [http://www.newsplex.com newsplex.com]|
}}

'''WVAW-LD''' is the [[low-power television|low-powered]]  [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for [[Charlottesville, Virginia]]. It broadcasts a [[high-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 16 from a transmitter on Carters Mountain. The station can also be seen on [[Comcast]] channel 3 and in high definition on digital channel 210. Owned by Gray Television, WVAW is sister to [[CBS]] affiliate [[WCAV]] and low-powered [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliate [[WAHU-CD]]. 

All three share studios, known as the &quot;Charlottesville Newsplex&quot;, on 2nd Street Southeast in Downtown Charlottesville. In addition, some behind-the-scenes duties are run alongside that of sister station [[WHSV-TV]] in [[Harrisonburg, Virginia|Harrisonburg]] (which the &quot;Newsplex&quot; has a resource sharing alliance with). [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on the station includes: ''[[Inside Edition]]'', ''[[The Ellen DeGeneres Show|Ellen]]'', ''[[The Real Housewives of New York City]]'', and ''[[The Wendy Williams Show]]''.

===Digital programming===
On WVAW-DT2 is a [[SDTV|standard definition]] simulcast of WCAV.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! [[Video resolution|Video]]
! [[Aspect ratio|Aspect]]
! Programming
|-
| 16.1 || [[720p]] || [[16:9]] || main WVAW programming/ABC HD
|-
| 16.2 || [[480i]] || [[4:3]]  || WCAV &quot;CBS 19&quot;
|}

==History==
What is now WVAW-LD originally began in 1979 on analog UHF channel 64 with the call sign '''W64AO'''. The station was a low-powered repeater of WHSV which was the area's default ABC affiliate even though [[Richmond, Virginia|Richmond]]'s [[WRIC-TV]] puts a strong signal into Charlottesville. In 2004, W64AO moved to UHF channel 16, gained the '''WVAW-LP''' call letters, and became the [[media market|market]]'s first ABC affiliate not long after WCAV signed-on. However, it was still officially licensed as a translator station according to the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC). 

In early-2005 after the launch of WCAV and WVAW, Gray Television launched a third station in the area, Fox affiliate WAHU-CA. Since 2006, the three have been the official flagships of [[University of Virginia]] sports. WVAW was temporarily taken off-the-air by a fire on its transmitter tower at the top of Carters Mountain on November 9, 2006. The signal was restored on November 13. On December 28, WVAW moved to Comcast channel 3. After performing a [[flash-cut]], the station replaced its analog signal with a 15 [[kilowatt|kW]] digital signal on the same frequency on February 16, 2009. It also changed its calls to the current '''WVAW-LD''' with &quot;LD&quot; standing for low-powered digital. 

Of all of the Richmond and [[Washington, D.C.]] stations replaced on the main tier for the new Charlottesville ABC, CBS, and Fox affiliates, only [[WTTG]] survived. On Comcast digital cable, Richmond channels include WRIC and [[WTVR-TV]]. [[WUSA (TV)|WUSA]] is not on digital cable nor is any other district station. Other Comcast systems north and west of Charlottesville do pick up Washington and Richmond locals either on the main tier or digital lineup. On October 27, 2009, WVAW's digital transmitter had a glitch over-the-air. The signal was put on WAHU-DT2 for a short time and the problem was fixed a day later.

==Newscasts==
WVAW and its sister stations employ the largest television news team dedicated exclusively to the Charlottesville market. While WVIR dedicates some staff to adjacent areas, WVAW focuses its coverage solely on the counties that comprise the Charlottesville viewing area. As the primary station in the &quot;Charlottesville Newsplex&quot; operation, WCAV airs the most newscasts. WVAW simulcasts the second hour of ''Good Morning Charlottesville'' on weekday mornings, ''Charlottesville Tonight'' weeknights at 7, and ''CBS 19 News Nightcast'' weeknights at 11. It also simulcasts news from WCAV on weeknights from 5 until 6:30.

'''Anchors'''
*Bo Sykes - weekday mornings
*Stephanie Satchell - weekday mornings and reporter
*Jim Hanchett - News Director seen weeknights at 5 and 5:30
*Dan Schutte - weeknights at 6 and 11
*John Rodgers - weeknights at 7
*Tara Wheeler - weeknights at 7 and reporter

'''''Weather Authority Meteorologists'''''
*Travis Koshko ([[National Weather Association|NWA]] Seal of Approval) - Chief seen weekday mornings
*Brantley Ussery - weeknights 

'''Sports'''
*Damon Dillman - Director seen weeknights
*Kristi Fulkerson - sports reporter

'''Reporters'''
*Beth Duffy - Special Correspondent and &quot;Beth on the Bright Side&quot; segment producer
*Bailey Disselkoen - producer
*Carter Johnson
*Jessica Jaglois
*Chris Stover
*Frankie Jupiter
*Rachel Ryan

==External links==
*[http://www.newsplex.com WVAW-LD &quot;ABC 16&quot;]
*[http://www.newsplex.com/mobi WVAW-LD mobile]
*{{TVQ|WVAW-LD}}
*{{TV Fool|WVAW-LD}}
*{{BIA|WVAW|TV|LP}}

{{Charlottesville TV}}
{{ABC Virginia}}
{{Gray TV}}

[[Category:ABC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Gray Television]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1979]]
[[Category:Channel 16 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Digital low-power stations]]
[[Category:Television stations in Virginia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
