<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3388912" ns="0" title="WCAV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox broadcast |
  call_letters             = WCAV|
  city                     = |
  station_logo             = [[Image:Wcav 2009.png|200px]]|
  station_slogan           = ''Where Charlottesville''&lt;br&gt;''News Comes First''|
  station_branding         = CBS 19 &lt;small&gt;(general)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;CBS 19 News&lt;br&gt;WAHU Fox 27&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(on DT3)&lt;/small&gt;|
  digital                  = 19 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]]) &amp;&lt;br&gt;[[WVAW-LD|WVAW]]-DT 16.2 (UHF)|
  subchannels              = 19.1 [[CBS]]&lt;br/&gt;19.2 [[The AccuWeather Channel|AccuWeather]]&lt;br&gt;[[WAHU-CD|19.3]] [[Fox Network|Fox]]|
  other_chs                = |
  affiliations             = |
  airdate                  = August 15, 2004|
  location                 = [[Charlottesville, Virginia]]|
  callsign_meaning         = '''CAV'''alier&lt;br&gt;(the [[University of Virginia|UVA]] mascot)|
  former_callsigns         = |
  former_channel_numbers   = 19 (UHF analog, 2004-2009)|
  owner                    = [[Gray Television]]|
  licensee                 = Gray Television Licensee, Inc.|
  sister_stations          = [[WVAW]], [[WAHU]], [[WHSV-TV]]|
  former_affiliations      = |
  effective_radiated_power = 155 [[kilowatt|kW]]&lt;br&gt;15 kW (WVAW-DT2)|
  HAAT                     = 325.6 m&lt;br&gt;324 m (WVAW-DT2)|
  facility_id              = 363&lt;br&gt;4687 (WVAW-DT2)|
  coordinates              = {{coord|37|59|3|N|78|28|52|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}|
  homepage                 = [http://www.newsplex.com/ newsplex.com]|
}}

'''WCAV''' is the [[CBS]]-affiliated [[television station]] for [[Charlottesville, Virginia]]. It broadcasts a [[High-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 19 from a transmitter on Carters Mountain. The station can also be seen on [[Comcast]] channel 6 and in high definition on digital channel 212. Owned by [[Gray Television]], WCAV is sister to [[low-power television|low-powered]] [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] affiliate [[WVAW-LD]] and low-powered [[Fox Network|Fox]] affiliate [[WAHU-CD]]. All three share studios, known as the &quot;Charlottesville Newsplex&quot;, on 2nd Street Southeast in Downtown Charlottesville. 

In addition, some behind-the-scenes duties are run alongside that of sister station [[WHSV-TV]] in [[Harrisonburg, Virginia|Harrisonburg]] (which the &quot;Newsplex&quot; has a resource sharing alliance with). [[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on the station includes: ''[[Entertainment Tonight]]'', ''[[Judge Judy]]'', ''[[Family Feud]]'', and ''[[Who Wants to Be a Millionaire (US game show)|Who Wants to Be a Millionaire]]''. WCAV can also be seen on WVAW's second digital subchannel (on UHF channel 16.2) from the same transmitter. 

===Digital programming===
On WCAV-DT2 and Comcast digital channel 209 is [[The Local AccuWeather Channel]]. On WCAV-DT3 is a [[SDTV|standard definition]] simulcast of WAHU.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! [[Video resolution|Video]]
! [[Aspect ratio|Aspect]]
! Programming
|-
| 19.1 || [[1080i]] || [[16:9]] || main WCAV programming/CBS HD
|-
| 19.2 || [[480i]] || [[4:3]]  || WCAV-DT2 &quot;CBS 19 Weather Now&quot;
|-
| 19.3 || 480i || 4:3 || WAHU-CD &quot;Fox 27&quot;
|}

==History==
WCAV began broadcasting on August 15, 2004 becoming the [[media market|market]]'s first CBS affiliate and first station to mount a challenge against established [[NBC]] affiliate [[WVIR-TV]]. Previously, the analog UHF channel 19 allocation was considered to bring [[Richmond, Virginia|Richmond]] a primary [[The WB|WB]] station. That area had lacked such an affiliation since the switch of [[WUPV]] to [[UPN]] in 1997. Charlottesville had previously received CBS programming on cable from Richmond's [[WTVR-TV]] and [[Washington D.C.]]'s [[WUSA (TV)|WUSA]]. When it launched, WCAV immediately replaced WUSA on local cable systems. 

During 2007, the station first swapped analog cable channel allocations with WTVR. After that, the Richmond station moved to the digital tier. Shortly after WCAV's sign-on, owner Gray Television signed on ABC affiliate WVAW-LP on UHF channel 16. That station was formerly a low-powered repeater (on UHF channel 64) of Harrisonburg's WHSV and it replaced that station on Charlottesville-area cable systems. In early-2005, the two stations were joined by new [[Class A television service|Class A]] Fox affiliate WAHU-CA on UHF channel 27. 

Since 2006, the three have been the official flagships of [[University of Virginia]] sports.  The station is not related to the former WCAV-FM (now [[WKAF (FM)|WKAF-FM]]) in [[Brockton, Massachusetts]]. After performing a [[flash-cut]], WCAV's broadcasts have been digital-only since February 16, 2009. Of all of the Richmond and Washington D.C. stations replaced on the main tier for the new Charlottesville ABC, CBS, and Fox affiliates, only [[WTTG]] survived. On Comcast digital cable, Richmond channels include [[WRIC-TV]] and WTVR. WUSA is not on digital cable nor is any other district station. Other Comcast providers north and west of Charlottesville do pick up Washington and Richmond locals either on the main tier or digital lineup.

==News operation==
[[Image:Wcav news open.png|right|thumb|News open.]]

WCAV and its sister stations employ the largest television news team dedicated exclusively to the Charlottesville market. While WVIR dedicates some staff to adjacent areas, WCAV focuses its coverage solely on the counties that comprise the Charlottesville viewing area. In June 2006, WCAV received the runner-up award for &quot;Outstanding News Operation&quot; by the [[Virginia]] Association of Broadcasters. [[WWBT]] in Richmond was the winner in that category. In 2007, the station received the &quot;Outstanding Sports Coverage&quot; award for a commercial television station from the Virginia Association of Broadcasters. 

That same year, its website was the runner up to [[WVEC]] in [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk]] for an outstanding website award. Beth Duffy, formerly of WVIR, returned to the airwaves on WCAV on April 16, 2007. On September 21, 2007 WCAV launched The Local AccuWeather Channel on a new second digital subchannel and live streaming video on its website. Known on-air as &quot;CBS 19 Weather Now&quot;, it was added to Comcast digital channel 209 in December. Programming consists of local weather updates and national weather forecasts provided by [[AccuWeather]]. 

As the primary station in the &quot;Charlottesville Newsplex&quot; operation, it airs the most newscasts. WVAW simulcasts the second hour of ''Good Morning Charlottesville'' on weekday mornings, ''Charlottesville Tonight'' weeknights at 7, and ''CBS 19 News Nightcast'' weeknights at 11. WAHU airs an hour long extension of ''Good Morning Charlottesville'' weekday mornings at 7 and nightly prime time newscasts at 10 that competes with [[The CW|CW]] affiliate [[WVIR-DT3]]. All shows, except the extension of ''Good Morning Charlottesville'' on WAHU, are streamed live on the &quot;Charlottesville Newsplex&quot; website.

===News team===
'''Anchors'''
*Jim Hanchett - news director; weeknights at 5 and 5:30 p.m.
*Carter Johnson - weekend evenings; also weeknight reporter
*John Rodgers - weeknights at 7 and 10 p.m.
*Stephanie Satchell - weekday mornings; also reporter
*Dan Schutte - weeknights at 6 and 11 p.m.
*Bo Sykes - weekday mornings and noon
*Tara Wheeler - weeknights at 7 and 10 p.m.; also reporter

'''''Weather Authority'''''
*Travis Koshko ([[National Weather Association|NWA]] Seal of Approval) - chief meteorologist; weekday mornings and noon
*Brantley Ussery - weeknights at 5, 5:30, 6, 7, 10 and 11 p.m.
*Melanie Niemann - weekend evenings

'''Sports team''' (also seen on ''Friday Night EndZone'')
*Damon Dillman - sports director; weeknights at 6, 7, 10 and 11 p.m.
*Kristi Fulkerson - sports anchor; weekend evenings, also sports reporter

'''Reporters'''
*Bailey Disselkoen - also producer
*Beth Duffy - special correspondent and &quot;Beth on the Bright Side&quot; segment producer
*Jessica Jaglois
*Frankie Jupiter
*Rachel Ryan
*Chris Stover

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.newsplex.com/ WCAV &quot;CBS 19&quot;]
*[http://www.newsplex.com/mobi WCAV mobile]
*{{TVQ|WCAV}}
*{{TV Fool|WCAV}}
*{{BIA|WCAV|TV|TV}}

{{Charlottesville TV}}
{{CBS Virginia}}
{{Fox Virginia}}
{{Gray TV}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wcav}}
[[Category:CBS network affiliates]]
[[Category:Gray Television]]
[[Category:Channel 19 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 2004]]
[[Category:Local AccuWeather Channel affiliates]]
[[Category:Television stations in Virginia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
