<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="33898" ns="0" title="Website"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-indef}}
[[File:Barack Obama White House.gov bio 2-17-09.jpg|thumb|right|240px|The biography of U.S. President [[Barack Obama]] that appears on [[White House|White House.gov]]]]

A '''website''', also written as '''Web site''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/Website |title=website - definition of website by the Free Online Dictionary, Thesaurus and Encyclopedia |publisher=Thefreedictionary.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; '''web site''', or simply '''site''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.thefreedictionary.com/site |title=site - definition of site by the Free Online Dictionary, Thesaurus and Encyclopedia |publisher=Thefreedictionary.com |date= |accessdate=2011-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a collection of related [[web page]]s containing [[image]]s, [[video]]s or other digital assets. A website is hosted on at least one [[web server]], accessible via a network such as the [[Internet]] or a private [[local area network]] through an Internet address known as a [[Uniform Resource Locator]]. All publicly accessible websites collectively constitute the [[World Wide Web]].

A web page is a [[document]], typically written in [[plain text]] interspersed with formatting instructions of Hypertext Markup Language ([[HTML]], [[XHTML]]). A web page may incorporate elements from other websites with suitable [[HTML anchor|markup anchors]].

Web pages are accessed and transported with the [[Hypertext Transfer Protocol]] (HTTP), which may optionally employ encryption ([[HTTP Secure]], HTTPS) to provide security and privacy for the user of the web page content. The user's application, often a [[web browser]], renders the page content according to its HTML markup instructions onto a [[Computer monitor|display terminal]].

The pages of a website can usually be accessed from a simple Uniform Resource Locator (URL) called the [[homepage]]. The URLs of the pages organize them into a hierarchy, although [[hyperlink]]ing between them conveys the reader's perceived [[site map|site structure]] and guides the reader's navigation of the site.

Some websites require a subscription to access some or all of their content. Examples of subscription websites include many business sites, parts of news websites, [[academic journal]] websites, gaming websites, file-sharing websites, [[Internet forum|message boards]], web-based [[email]], [[social networking]] websites, websites providing real-time [[stock market]] data, and websites providing various other services (e.g., websites offering storing and/or sharing of images, files and so forth).

==History==
The [[World Wide Web]] (WWW) was created in 1990 by CERN physicist [[Tim Berners-Lee]].&lt;ref name='First page'&gt;{{cite web | url=http://info.cern.ch/ |title=The website of the world's first-ever web server |accessdate=2008-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 30 April 1993, [[CERN]] announced that the World Wide Web would be free to use for anyone.&lt;ref name='w3c'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.w3.org/History.html |title=A Little History of the World Wide Web |accessdate=2007-02-16 |last=Cailliau |first=Robert }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Before the introduction of HTML and HTTP, other protocols such as [[File Transfer Protocol]] and the [[gopher protocol]] were used to retrieve individual files from a server. These protocols offer a simple directory structure which the user navigates and chooses files to download. Documents were most often presented as plain text files without formatting, or were encoded in [[word processor]] formats.

==Overview==
Organized by function, a website may be
* a [[personal website]]
* a commercial website
* a [[e-Government|government website]]
* a [[nonprofit organization]] website.

It could be the work of an individual, a business or other organization, and is typically dedicated to some particular topic or purpose. Any website can contain a hyperlink to any other website, so the distinction between individual sites, as perceived by the user, may sometimes be blurred.

Websites are written in, or dynamically converted to, HTML (Hyper Text Markup Language) and are accessed using a [[software]] interface classified as a [[user agent]]. Web pages can be viewed or otherwise accessed from a range of [[computer]]-based and Internet-enabled devices of various sizes, including desktop computers, laptops, PDAs and cell phones.

A website is [[Web hosting service|hosted]] on a computer system known as a [[web server]], also called an HTTP server, and these terms can also refer to the software that runs on these systems and that retrieves and delivers the web pages in response to requests from the website users. [[Apache HTTP Server|Apache]] is the most commonly used web server software (according to [[Netcraft]] statistics) and [[Microsoft]]'s [[Internet Information Services]] (IIS) is also commonly used.

==Static website==
{{Main|static web page}}
A static website is one that has web pages stored on the server in the format that is sent to a client web browser. It is primarily coded in Hypertext Markup Language, HTML.

Simple forms or marketing examples of websites, such as ''classic website'', a ''five-page website'' or a ''brochure website'' are often static websites, because they present pre-defined, static information to the user. This may include information about a company and its products and services via text, photos, animations, audio/video and interactive menus and navigation.

This type of website usually displays the same information to all visitors. Similar to handing out a printed brochure to customers or clients, a static website will generally provide consistent, standard information for an extended period of time. Although the website owner may make updates periodically, it is a manual process to edit the text, photos and other content and may require basic website design skills and software.

In summary, visitors are not able to control what information they receive via a static website, and must instead settle for whatever content the website owner has decided to offer at that time.

They are edited using four broad categories of software:

*[[Text editor]]s, such as [[Notepad (Windows)|Notepad]] or [[TextEdit]], where content and HTML markup are manipulated directly within the editor program
* [[WYSIWYG]] offline editors, such as [[Microsoft FrontPage]] and [[Adobe Dreamweaver]] (previously Macromedia Dreamweaver), with which the site is edited using a [[GUI]] interface and the final HTML markup is generated automatically by the editor software
* WYSIWYG online editors which create media rich online presentation like web pages, widgets, intro, blogs, and other documents.
* Template-based editors, such as [[RapidWeaver]] and [[iWeb]], which allow users to quickly create and upload web pages to a web server without detailed HTML knowledge, as they pick a suitable template from a palette and add pictures and text to it in a [[desktop publishing]] fashion without direct manipulation of [[Character encodings in HTML|HTML code]].

==Dynamic website==
{{Main|dynamic web page}}
A dynamic website is one that changes or customizes itself frequently and automatically, based on certain criteria.

Dynamic websites can have two types of dynamic activity: Code and Content. Dynamic code is invisible or behind the scenes and dynamic content is visible or fully displayed.

===Dynamic code===
The first type is a web page with dynamic code. The code is constructed dynamically on the fly using active programming language instead of plain, static HTML.

A website with dynamic code refers to its construction or how it is built, and more specifically refers to the code used to create a single web page. A dynamic web page is generated on the fly by piecing together certain blocks of code, procedures or routines. A dynamically-generated web page would recall various bits of information from a database and put them together in a pre-defined format to present the reader with a coherent page. It interacts with users in a variety of ways including by reading cookies recognizing users' previous history, session variables, server side variables etc., or by using direct interaction (form elements, mouse overs, etc.). A site can display the current state of a dialogue between users, monitor a changing situation, or provide information in some way personalized to the requirements of the individual user.

===Dynamic content===
The second type is a website with dynamic content displayed in plain view. Variable content is displayed dynamically on the fly based on certain criteria, usually by retrieving content stored in a database.

A website with dynamic content refers to how its messages, text, images and other information are displayed on the web page, and more specifically how its content changes at any given moment. The web page content varies based on certain criteria, either pre-defined rules or variable user input. For example, a website with a database of news articles can use a pre-defined rule which tells it to display all news articles for today's date. This type of dynamic website will automatically show the most current news articles on any given date. Another example of dynamic content is when a retail website with a database of media products allows a user to input a search request for the keyword Beatles. In response, the content of the web page will spontaneously change the way it looked before, and will then display a list of Beatles products like CDs, DVDs and books.

===Purpose of dynamic websites===
The main purpose of a dynamic website is automation. A dynamic website can operate more effectively, be built more efficiently and is easier to maintain, update and expand. It is much simpler to build a template and a database than to build hundreds or thousands of individual, static HTML web pages.

==Software systems==
There is a wide range of software systems, such as [[ANSI C]] [[servlets]], [[JavaServer Pages]] (JSP), the [[PHP]], [[Perl]], [[Python (programming language)|Python]], and [[Ruby (programming language)|Ruby]] [[programming languages]], [[ASP.NET]], [[Active Server Pages]] (ASP), YUMA and [[ColdFusion]] (CFML) that are available to generate dynamic web systems and dynamic sites. Sites may also include content that is retrieved from one or more [[database]]s or by using [[XML]]-based technologies such as [[RSS]].

Static content may also be dynamically generated either periodically, or if certain conditions for regeneration occur (cached) in order to avoid the performance loss of initiating the dynamic engine on a per-user or per-connection basis.

[[Plug-in (computing)|Plug in]]s are available to expand the features and abilities of web browsers to show ''active content'' or even create [[rich internet application]]s. Examples of such plug-ins are [[Microsoft Silverlight]], [[Adobe Flash]], [[Adobe Shockwave]] or [[applet]]s written in [[Java (programming language)|Java]]. [[Dynamic HTML]] also provides for user interactivity and realtime element updating within web pages (i.e., pages don't have to be loaded or reloaded to effect any changes), mainly using the [[Document Object Model]] (DOM) and [[JavaScript]], support which is built-in to most modern web browsers.

Turning a website into an income source is a common practice for web developers and website owners. There are several methods for creating a website business which fall into two broad categories, as defined below.

===Content-based sites===
Some websites derive revenue by selling advertising space on their site either through direct sales or through an advertising network. (see [[Contextual advertising]]).

===Product- or service-based sites===
Some websites derive revenue by offering products or services for sale. In the case of [[e-commerce]] websites, the products or services may be purchased at the website itself, by entering credit card or other payment information into a payment form on the site. While most business websites serve as a shop window for existing [[brick and mortar business]]es, it is increasingly the case that some websites are businesses in their own right; that is, the products they offer are only available for purchase on the web.

Websites occasionally derive income from a combination of these two practices. For example, a website such as an online auctions website may charge the users of its auction service to list an auction, but also display third-party advertisements on the site, from which it derives further income.

==Spelling==
The form &quot;website&quot; has become the standard spelling, but previously &quot;Web site&quot; (capitalised) and &quot;web site&quot; were also widely used. Some academia, some large [[Publishing|book publishers]], and some dictionaries still use &quot;Web site&quot;, reflecting the origin of the term in the proper name, ''[[World Wide Web]]''. There has also been similar debate regarding related terms such as [[web page]], [[webmaster]], and [[webcam]].

Among leading [[style guide]]s, the [[Reuters]] style guide,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://handbook.reuters.com/index.php/W#Web.2C_website|title=Handbook of Journalism|publisher=Reuters|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[The Chicago Manual of Style]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/CMS_FAQ/InternetWebandOtherPost-WatergateConcerns/InternetWebandOtherPost-WatergateConcerns13.html|title=Internet, Web, and Other Post-Watergate Concerns|publisher=University of Chicago|accessdate=2010-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[AP Stylebook]] (since April 2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://twitter.com/APStylebook/status/12296505018 |title=AP tweets that it will change from Web site to website |accessdate=2010-04-16 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt; all recommend &quot;website&quot;.

Among leading dictionaries and encyclopedias, the [[Canadian Oxford Dictionary]] prefers &quot;website&quot;, and the [[Oxford English Dictionary]] changed to &quot;website&quot; in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.askoxford.com/asktheexperts/faq/usage/website?view=uk |title=Ask Oxford: How should the term ''website'' be written in official documents and on the web? |accessdate=2007-02-23 |work=Oxford Dictionaries Online }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Wikipedia]] also uses &quot;website&quot;, but [[Encyclopædia Britannica]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/690679/Web-site|title=Web site (computer science)|publisher=Encyclopaedia Britannica|accessdate=2010-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; (including its [[Merriam-Webster]] subsidiary&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/website|publisher=Merriam-Webster|title=Website - Definition and More|accessdate=2010-09-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;) uses &quot;Web site&quot;.

Among leading language-usage commentators, ''[[Garner's Modern American Usage]]'' acknowledges that &quot;website&quot; is the standard form,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lisagoldresearch.wordpress.com/2010/04/17/ap-stylebook-surrenders-the-battle-over-web-site-vs-website/|author=Lisa Gold|title=AP Stylebook surrenders the battle over “Web site” vs. “website”|accessdate=2010-08-05|date=2010-04-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; but [[Bill Walsh (author)|Bill Walsh]], of [[The Washington Post]], argues for using &quot;Web site&quot; in his books and on his website&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theslot.com/email.html |title=The Slot—Sharp Points: Here We Go Again—Eeee! |accessdate=2007-02-25 |work= }}&lt;/ref&gt; (however, The Washington Post itself uses &quot;website&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/|title=The Washington Post|publisher=Washington Post|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;).

Among major internet technology companies and corporations, [[Microsoft]] uses &quot;website&quot; and occasionally &quot;web site&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/windows/default.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|title=Microsoft Windows|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/ie/ff468705.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|title=Internet Explorer 9 Preview Builds|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.microsoft.com/expression/products/StudioUltimate_Overview.aspx|publisher=Microsoft|title=Microsoft (R) Expression (R)|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Apple Inc.|Apple]] uses &quot;website&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.apple.com/sitemap/|publisher=Apple|title=Site Map|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Google]] uses &quot;website&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.google.com/intl/en/services/|publisher=Google|title=Welcome to Google Business Solutions|accessdate=2010-08-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Types of websites==
Websites can be divided into two broad categories - static and interactive.  Interactive sites are part of the [[Web 2.0]] community of sites, and allow for interactivity between the site owner and site visitors.  Static sites serve or capture information but do not allow engagement with the audience directly.

There are many varieties of websites, each specializing in a particular type of content or use, and they may be arbitrarily classified in any number of ways. A few such classifications might include:{{Or|date=September 2007}}
{|class=&quot;wikitable collapsible&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 89%&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;3&quot;| Click &quot;show&quot; or &quot;hide&quot; to toggle this table
|-
!Type of Website
!Description
!Examples
|-
|'''[[Affiliate]]'''
|A site, typically few in pages, whose purpose is to sell a third party's product.  The seller receives a commission for facilitating the sale.
|
|-
|'''[[Affiliate Agency]]'''
|Enabled [[Web portal|portal]] that renders not only its custom [[Content management system|CMS]] but also syndicated content from other content providers for an agreed fee. There are usually three relationship tiers. [[Affiliate marketing|Affiliate Agencies]]
|(e.g., [[Commission Junction]]), [[Advertisers]] (e.g., [[eBay]]) and consumer (e.g., [[Yahoo!]]).
|-
|'''[[Archive site]]'''
|Used to preserve valuable electronic content threatened with extinction. Two examples are: [[Internet Archive]], which since 1996 has preserved billions of old (and new) web pages; and [[Google Groups]], which in early 2005 was archiving over 845,000,000 messages posted to [[Usenet]] news/discussion groups.
|[[Internet Archive]], [[Google Groups]]
|-
|'''[[Malware|Attack site]]'''
|A site created specifically to attack visitors computers on their first visit to a website by downloading a file (usually a [[Trojan horse (computing)|trojan horse]]). These websites rely on unsuspecting users with poor anti-virus protection in their computers.
|
|-
|'''[[Blog]] (web log)'''
|Sites generally used to post online diaries which may include discussion forums (e.g., [[blogger.com|blogger]], [[Xanga]]).  Many bloggers use blogs like an editorial section of a newspaper to express their ideas on anything ranging from politics to religion to video games to parenting, along with anything in between.  Some bloggers are professional bloggers and they are paid to blog about a certain subject, and they are usually found on news sites.
|
|-
|'''Brand building site'''
|A site with the purpose of creating an experience of a brand online. These sites usually do not sell anything, but focus on building the brand. Brand building sites are most common for low-value, high-volume [[fast moving consumer goods]] (FMCG).
|
|-
|'''[[Celebrity|Celebrity website]]'''
|A website whose information revolves around a [[celebrity]]. This sites can be official (endorsed by the celebrity) or fan made (run by his/her fan, fans, without implicit endorsement).
|[[Jim Carrey|jimcarrey.com]]
|-
|'''[[Click-to-donate site]]'''
|A website that allows the visitor to donate to charity simply by clicking on a button or answering a question correctly. An advertiser usually donates to the charity for each correct answer generated.
|[[The Hunger Site]], [[Freerice]], [[Ripple (charitable organisation)]]
|-
|'''[[Community site]]'''
|A site where persons with similar interests communicate with each other, usually by [[Online chat|chat]] or message boards.
|[[Myspace]], [[Facebook]], [[orkut]]
|-
|'''[[Content (media)|Content]] site'''
|Sites whose business is the creation and distribution of original content
|(e.g., [[slate.com|Slate]], [[About.com]]).
|-
|'''[[Corporate website]]'''
|Used to provide background information about a business, organization, or service.
|
|-
|'''[[Dating website]]'''
|A site where users can find other single people looking for long range relationships, dating, or just friends.
|Many of them are pay per services such as [[eHarmony]] and [[Match.com]], but there are many free or partially free dating sites.  Most dating sites today have the functionality of social networking websites.
|-
|'''[[Electronic commerce]] (e-commerce) site'''
|A site offering goods and services for [[Online shopping|online sale]] and enabling online transactions for such sales.
|
|-
|'''[[Internet forum|Forum website]]'''
|A site where people discuss various topics.
|
|-
|'''[[Gallery|Gallery Website]]'''
|A website designed specifically for use as a Gallery, these may be an art gallery or photo gallery and of commercial or non-commercial nature. 
|
|-
|'''[[Government|Government Site]]'''
|A website made by the local, state, department or national government of a country. Usually these sites also operate websites that are intended to inform tourists or support tourism.
|For example, Richmond.com is the [[geodomain]] for [[Richmond, Virginia]].
|-
|'''[[Gripe site]]'''
|A site devoted to the criticism of a person, place, corporation, government, or institution.
|
|-
|'''[[Online game|Gaming website]]'''&lt;br&gt;
'''[[Online gambling|Gambling website]]'''
|A site that lets users play online games.  Some enable people to gamble online.
|
|-
|'''[[Humor site]]'''
|Satirizes, parodies or otherwise exists solely to amuse.
|
|-
|'''Information site'''
|Most websites could fit in this type of website to some extent many of them are not necessarily for commercial purposes
|[[RateMyProfessors.com]], Free Internet Lexicon and Encyclopedia. Most government, educational and nonprofit institutions have an informational site.
|-
|'''[[Media sharing]] site'''
|A site that enables users to upload and view media such as [[image hosting service|pictures]], [[music hosting service|music]], and [[video hosting service|videos]]
|[[Flickr]], [[YouTube]], [[PureVolume]] and [[Google Videos]]
|-
|'''[[Mirror (computing)|Mirror]] site'''
|A website that is the replication of another website. This type of websites are used as a response to spikes in user visitors. Mirror sites are most commonly used to provide multiple sources of the same information, and are of particular value as a way of providing reliable access to large downloads.
|
|-
|'''[[Microblog|Microblog site]]'''
|A short and simple form of blogging.  Microblogs are limited to certain amounts of characters and works similar to a status update on [[Facebook]]
| [[Twitter]]
|-
|'''[[News site]]'''
|Similar to an information site, but dedicated to dispensing news, politics, and commentary.
|[[CNN|cnn.com]]
|-
|'''[[Personal website]]'''
|Websites about an individual or a small group (such as a family) that contains information or any content that the individual wishes to include.  Many personal homepages are rare, thanks to the modern era of social networking sites such as [[Myspace]], but some are still used for at home businesses. This website is different from a ''Celebrity website'', which can be very expensive and run by a publicist or agency.
|
|-
|'''[[Phishing|Phishing site]]'''
|a website created to fraudulently acquire [[Information sensitivity|sensitive information]], such as passwords and [[credit card]] details, by masquerading as a trustworthy person or business (such as [[Social Security Administration]], [[PayPal]]) in an [[Telecommunication|electronic communication]] (see [[Phishing]]).
|
|-
|'''[[Peer-to-peer file sharing|p2p]]/[[Torrent file|Torrents website]]'''
|Websites that index torrent files. This type of website is different from a [[BitTorrent (protocol)|Bit torrent client]] which is usually a stand alone software.
|[[Mininova]], [[The Pirate Bay]]
|-
|'''Political site'''
|A site on which people may voice political views, show political humor, campaigning for elections, or show information about a certain political party or ideology.
|
|-
|'''[[Internet pornography|Porn site]]'''
|A site that shows sexually explicit content for enjoyment and relaxation. They can be similar to a personal website when it's a website of a porn actor/actress or a media sharing website where user can upload from their own sexually explicit material to movies made by adult studios.
|
|-
|'''[[List of Question and Answer Websites|Question and Answer (Q&amp;A) Site]]'''
|Answer site is a site where people can ask questions &amp; get answers.
|[[Yahoo! Answers]], [[Stack Exchange Network]] (including [[Stack Overflow]])
|-
|'''[[Rating site]]'''
|A site on which people can praise or disparage what is featured.
|
|-
|'''[[Religion and the Internet|Religious site]]'''
|A site in which people may advertise a place of worship, or provide inspiration or seek to encourage the faith of a follower of that religion.
|
|-
|'''[[Review site]]'''
|A site on which people can post reviews for products or services.
|
|-
|'''[[School website|School site]]'''
|a site on which teachers, students, or administrators can post information about current events at or involving their school. U.S. elementary-high school websites generally use k12 in the URL
|
|-
|'''[[Scraper site]]'''
|a site which largely duplicates without permission the content of another site, without actually pretending to be that site, in order to capture some of that site's traffic (especially from search engines) and profit from advertising revenue or in other ways.
|
|-
|'''[[Web search engine|Search engine]] site'''
|A website that indexes material on the internet or an [[intranet]] (and lately on traditional media such as books and newspapers)and provides links to information as a response to a query.
|[[Google Search]], [[Bing]], [[GoodSearch]], [[Ecosia]]
|-
|'''[[Shock site]]'''
|Includes [[image]]s or other material that is intended to be offensive to most viewers
|[[Goatse.cx]], [[rotten.com]]
|-
|'''[[Social bookmarking]] site'''
|A site where users share other content from the Internet and rate and comment on the content.
|[[StumbleUpon]] and [[Digg]] are examples.
|-
|'''[[Social networking service|Social networking]] site'''
|A site where users could communicate with one another and share media, such as pictures, videos, music, blogs, etc. with other users. These may include games and [[web application]]s.
|[[Facebook]], [[Orkut]]
|-
|'''[[Warez]]'''
|A site designed to host or link to materials such as music, movies and software for the user to download.
|
|-
|'''[[Webmail]]'''
|A site that provides a webmail service.
|[[Hotmail]], [[Gmail]]
|-
|'''[[Web portal]]'''
|A site that provides a starting point or a gateway to other resources on the Internet or an intranet.
|[[msn.com]], [[msnbc.com]], [[yahoo]]
|-
|'''[[Wiki]] site'''
|A site which users collaboratively edit its content.
|[[Wikipedia]], [[WikiHow]]
|}
Some websites may be included in one or more of these categories. For example, a business website may promote the business's products, but may also host informative documents, such as [[white paper]]s. There are also numerous sub-categories to the ones listed above. For example, a [[porn]] site is a specific type of e-commerce site or business site (that is, it is trying to sell memberships for access to its site) or have social networking capabilities. A [[fansite]] may be a dedication from the owner to a particular [[celebrity]].

Websites are constrained by architectural limits (e.g., the computing power dedicated to the website). Very large websites, such as Facebook, Yahoo!, Microsoft, and Google employ many servers and [[load balancing (computing)|load balancing]] equipment such as [[Cisco Systems|Cisco]] Content Services [[Network switch|Switches]] to distribute visitor loads over multiple computers at multiple locations.  As of early 2011, Facebook utilized 9 data centers with approximately 63,000 servers.

In February 2009, [[Netcraft]], an [[Internet monitoring]] company that has tracked Web growth since 1995, reported that there were 215,675,903 websites with domain names and content on them in 2009, compared to just 18,000 websites in August 1995.

==Awards==
The [[Webby Awards]], [[Favourite Website Awards]], [[Interactive Media Awards]] and [[WebAwards]] are prominent award organizations recognizing the world's best websites.

==See also==
{{Portal|Internet}}
{{wiktionary|website}}
&lt;div style=&quot;-moz-column-count:4; column-count:4;&quot;&gt;
* [[Link rot]]
* [[Lists of websites]]
* [[Web content management system]]
* [[Web design]]
* [[Web development]]
* [[Web hosting service]]
* [[Web template]]
* [[Website architecture]]
* [[Website awards]]
* [[Website governance]]
* [[Website monetization]]
* [[World Wide Web Consortium]] (Web standards)
&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.icann.org/ Internet Corporation For Assigned Names and Numbers (ICANN)]
* [http://www.w3.org/ World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)]
* [http://www.isoc.org/ The Internet Society (ISOC)]
[[Category:Websites| ]]

[[af:Webwerf]]
[[am:ዌብሳይት]]
[[ang:Webbsīde]]
[[ar:موقع ويب]]
[[az:Veb-sayt]]
[[bn:ওয়েবসাইট]]
[[zh-min-nan:Bāng-chām]]
[[be:Сайт]]
[[be-x-old:Вэб-сайт]]
[[bg:Уебсайт]]
[[bs:Web sajt]]
[[br:Lec'hienn]]
[[ca:Lloc web]]
[[ceb:Websayt]]
[[cs:Website]]
[[cy:Gwefan]]
[[da:Websted]]
[[de:Website]]
[[et:Veebisait]]
[[el:Ιστότοπος]]
[[es:Sitio web]]
[[eo:TTT-ejo]]
[[eu:Webgune]]
[[fa:وب‌گاه]]
[[fr:Site web]]
[[gv:Ynnyd-eggey]]
[[gl:Sitio web]]
[[ko:웹사이트]]
[[hy:Ցանցակայք]]
[[id:Situs web]]
[[ia:Sito web]]
[[it:Sito web]]
[[he:אתר אינטרנט]]
[[jv:Situs wèb]]
[[ka:ვებ-საიტი]]
[[sw:Tovuti]]
[[ku:Malper]]
[[lo:ເວັບໄຊຕ໌]]
[[la:Situs interretialis]]
[[lv:Tīmekļa vietne]]
[[li:Website]]
[[lmo:Sit internet]]
[[mk:Мрежно место]]
[[mt:Sit elettroniku]]
[[mr:संकेतस्थळ]]
[[ms:Tapak web]]
[[mn:Цахим хаяг]]
[[nl:Website]]
[[ne:वेबसाईट]]
[[ja:ウェブサイト]]
[[no:Nettsted]]
[[nn:Nettstad]]
[[mhr:Сайт]]
[[pfl:Indaneduufdridd]]
[[km:វែបសាយ]]
[[pl:Serwis internetowy]]
[[pt:Site]]
[[ro:Sit web]]
[[ru:Сайт]]
[[sco:Wabsteid]]
[[sq:Vëndi i rrjetës]]
[[scn:Situ web]]
[[si:වෙබ්-අඩවිය]]
[[simple:Website]]
[[sk:Webová lokalita]]
[[sl:Spletišče]]
[[so:Website]]
[[ckb:وێبگە]]
[[sr:Вебсајт]]
[[su:Ramatloka]]
[[fi:Verkkosivusto]]
[[sv:Webbplats]]
[[tl:Websayt]]
[[ta:வலைத்தளம்]]
[[tt:Веб-сәхифә]]
[[te:వెబ్‌సైటు]]
[[th:เว็บไซต์]]
[[tr:Web sitesi]]
[[uk:Веб-сайт]]
[[ur:موقعِ حبالہ]]
[[vi:Website]]
[[wa:Waibe (Daegntoele)]]
[[vls:Website]]
[[wo:Dalub web]]
[[yi:וועבזייטל]]
[[zh:網站]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
