<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3390492" ns="0" title="Our Lady of the Rockies"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Our Lady of the Rockies.JPG|thumb|Our Lady of the Rockies]]
'''Our Lady of the Rockies''' is a 90-foot (27 m) [[statue]] dedicated to mothers everywhere, that sits atop the [[Continental Divide]] overlooking [[Butte, Montana]]. It is the [[United States]]' largest [[Madonna (art)|Madonna]] and its second largest statue.&lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_the_tallest_statues_in_the_United_States&lt;/ref&gt;

The statue was built by volunteers using donated materials to honor women everywhere, especially mothers.  The base is 8,510 feet above sea level and 3,500 feet above the town. The statue is lit and visible at night.

==Construction==
The statue was first imagined by local resident Bob O'Bill.  In 1979, his wife was seriously ill with cancer.  He promised the [[Blessed Virgin Mary]] that he would make a 5 foot statue of her in his yard if his wife recovered.&lt;ref&gt;http://billingsgazette.com/news/state-and-regional/montana/article_39f6e28f-240e-5f83-8ac7-e7c8868024f6.html&lt;/ref&gt;  When she recovered he began the project with his fellow workers who gradually changed the initial vision to a mountain top statue nearly the size of the [[Statue of Liberty]] (151&amp;nbsp;feet). Many people in Butte donated materials and time to make the statue a reality.  The design for the statue was engineered by [[Laurien Eugene Riehl]]. He was a retired engineer for the Anaconda Company who donated his engineering skills to the project.  The statue had to withstand the powerful windsheers that buffet the ridge tops. Joe Roberts donated his lot and buildings for the construction of the statue. The statue was airlifted from Roberts Rocky Mountain Equipment to its present site on the Continental Divide.   

Work on the project began December 29, 1979.  Volunteers spent many summer evenings blasting a road to the top of the Rockies, sometimes making only 10 feet of progress a day.  The base of the statue was poured in September 1985 with 400 tons of concrete.  The concrete was provided by Pioneer Concrete Company, a long time family business in Butte, Montana. On December 17, 1985, a [[CH-54 Tarhe]] from the Army National Guard's [[137th Aviation Company]] lifted the statue in four sections into place.

==Tourism==
Two-hour roundtrip bus tours are available from June until September from the Our Lady of the Rockies shop at the Butte Plaza Mall.  A [[tram]] consisting of handicapped accessible two 25-passenger cars is in the planning stages.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mtstandard.com/news/local/article_200759e2-10c6-55a1-ad77-0c85826e82db.html&lt;/ref&gt;  As proposed, it would carry visitors over a mile-long vertical rise of 2,000 feet to the base of the statue in about 5 minutes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mtstandard.com/news/local/article_200759e2-10c6-55a1-ad77-0c85826e82db.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of statues by height]]
*[[List of the tallest statues in the United States]]

==References==
*[http://www.visitmt.com/categories/moreinfo.asp?IDRRecordID=11122&amp;SiteID=1 VisitMT.com]
*[http://www.roadsideamerica.com/tips/getAttraction.php?tip_AttractionNo==793 Roadside America]
*[http://www.ourladyoftherockies.net Official Website]
{{coord|46|0|1.70|N|112|26|46.58|W|display=title}}

{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Colossal statues]]
[[Category:Concrete sculptures]]
[[Category:Landmarks in Montana]]
[[Category:Monuments and memorials in Montana]]
[[Category:Roadside attractions in the United States]]
[[Category:1985 works]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Butte, Montana]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Silver Bow County, Montana]]
[[Category:Outdoor sculptures in Montana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
