<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3420992" ns="0" title="Psychological thriller"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Multiple issues
 | citation style=September 2009
 | refimprove=May 2010
}}
'''Psychological thriller''' is a specific [[sub-genre]] of the broad ranged [[Thriller (genre)|thriller]] with heavy focus on characters. However, it often incorporates elements from the [[Mystery fiction|mystery]] and [[drama film|drama]] [[genre]], along with the typical traits of the thriller genre. In addition to drama and mystery, many psychological thrillers contain elements of, and often overlap with, the [[horror film|horror]] genre, particularly [[psychological horror]].

==Definition==
{{sectOR|date=January 2011}}
*'''[[Psychology|Psychological]]''' – Elements that are related to the mind or processes of the [[mind]]; they are mental rather than physical in nature. Sometimes the suspense comes from within one solitary character where characters must resolve [[Emotional conflict|conflicts]] with their own minds. Usually, this conflict is an effort to understand something that has happened to them. These conflicts are made more vivid with physical expressions of the conflict in the means of either physical manifestations, or physical torsions of the characters at play.
*'''[[Thriller (genre)|Thriller]]''' – Generally, thrillers focus on [[Plot (narrative)|plot]] over [[fictional character|character]], and thus emphasize intense, physical action over the character's psyche. Psychological thrillers tend to reverse this formula to a certain degree, emphasizing the characters just as much, if not more so, than the plot.
*'''Psychological thriller''' – Characters are no longer reliant on physical strength to overcome their brutish enemies (which is often the case in typical action-thrillers), but rather are reliant on their mental resources, whether it be by battling wits with a formidable opponent or by battling for equilibrium in the character's own mind. The [[wikt:suspense|suspense]] created by psychological thrillers often comes from two or more characters preying upon one another's minds, either by playing deceptive games with the other or by merely trying to demolish the other's mental state

==Literary devices and techniques==
*'''[[Stream of consciousness writing|Stream of consciousness]]''' – a literary technique which seeks to describe an individual's point of view by giving the written equivalent of the character's thought processes. In psychological thrillers, the narrative tries to manifest the character's psyche through word usage, descriptions, or visuals.
*'''[[First-person narrative]]''' – a literary technique in which the story is narrated by one or more of the characters, who explicitly refers to him or herself in the first person, that is, &quot;I&quot;. This direct involvement that the characters have with the story in turn makes the reader more involved with the characters themselves, and thus able to understand the mechanics of the characters' minds.  This technique is often paired with the concept of the [[unreliable narrator]]. 
*'''[[Back-story]]''' – the history behind the situation extant at the start of the main story. This deepens the psychological aspect of the story since the reader is able to more fully understand the character; more specifically, what the character's motivations are and how his past has shaped his current cognitive perceptions.

== Themes ==
Many psychological thrillers have emerged over the past years, all in various media (film, literature, radio, etc.). Despite these very different forms of representation, general trends have appeared throughout the narratives. Some of these consistent themes include:

*'''[[Reality]]''' 
*'''[[Perception]]''' 
*'''[[Mind]]'''
*'''[[Existence]]/Purpose'''
*'''[[Identity (philosophy)|Identity]]''' 
*'''[[Death]]'''

These major subgenres help develop the plot of a psychological thriller film, shaping the characters'personalities.
eg. usually character will find the true identidy/ the devil side of himself/herself in psychological thriller, in which it is one of the architypes -  the loss of innocence.

== Examples ==
=== Screenwriters and directors of the genre ===
*'''[[Sriram Raghavan]]''' – Indian film director presents the noir-thrillers focusing on the main characters mind for their crime in the film such as ''[[Ek Hasina Thi]]'' and ''[[Johnny Gaddaar]]''.
*'''[[Brad Anderson (film director)|Brad Anderson]]''' – Works effectively in the [[psychological horror]] genre. He is the director of ''[[The Machinist]]'' and ''[[Session 9]]''.
*'''[[Dario Argento]]''' – Italian director considered the master of [[giallo]]. He often creates mysteries that are very psychological in nature, with the past of characters influencing their present actions, as in ''[[Four Flies on Grey Velvet|4 mosche di velluto grigio]]'', ''[[Tenebrae (film)|Tenebrae]]'', ''[[Trauma (1993 film)|Trauma]]'' and ''[[The Stendhal Syndrome|La sindrome di Stendhal]]''.
*'''[[Darren Aronofsky]]''' – Director of harsh paranoid thrillers such as ''[[Pi (film)|Pi]]'', ''[[Requiem for a Dream]]'' and ''[[Black Swan (film)|Black Swan]]''.
*'''[[Park Chanwook]]''' – Korean director who significantly explored the genre in his &quot;vengeance trilogy&quot; (''[[Sympathy for Mr. Vengeance]]'', ''[[Oldboy]]'' and ''[[Sympathy for Lady Vengeance]]'').
*'''[[David Cronenberg]]''' – Canadian director who focuses on the psychological horrors of our minds. His storylines often make issues of the mind explicit, as in ''[[The Brood]]'', ''[[Scanners]]'', ''[[Videodrome]]'', ''[[Dead Ringers (film)|Dead Ringers]]'' and ''[[Spider (film)|Spider]]''.
*'''[[Brian De Palma]]''' – Infuses eroticism with the thriller genre. Often uses the motifs of doubling and splitting in the characters minds, as in ''[[Sisters (1973 film)|Sisters]]'', ''[[Obsession (1976 film)|Obsession]]'', ''[[Dressed to Kill (1980 film)|Dressed to Kill]]'', ''[[Body Double]]'' and ''[[Raising Cain]]''.
*'''[[David Fincher]]''' – Dark and ominous thrillers that focus on the psychology of men, as in ''[[Se7en]]'', ''[[The Game (film)|The Game]]'', ''[[Fight Club (film)|Fight Club]]'' and ''[[Zodiac (film)|Zodiac]]''.
*'''[[Mary Harron]]''' Canadian director who directed ''[[American_Psycho_(film)|American Psycho]]''
*'''[[Alfred Hitchcock]]''' – The master of [[thriller (genre)|suspense]], Hitchcock often applied [[Sigmund Freud|Freudian]] concepts to his thrillers, as in ''[[Rebecca (1940 film)|Rebecca]]'', ''[[Spellbound (1945 film)|Spellbound]]'', ''[[Vertigo (film)|Vertigo]]'', ''[[Psycho (film)|Psycho]]'', ''[[Marnie (film)|Marnie]]'' and ''[[Rear Window]]''.
*'''[[Richard Kelly (director)|Richard Kelly]]''' – Director who examined many of the themes illustrated above in the film ''[[Donnie Darko]]''.
*'''[[Stanley Kubrick]]''' - His films are characterized by a formal visual style and attention to detail – often combining elements of [[surrealism]] and [[expressionism]] that give the viewers a feeling of discomfort, such as in ''[[2001: A Space Odyssey (film)|2001: A Space Odyssey]]'', ''[[The Shining (film)|The Shining]]'', ''[[Eyes Wide Shut]]'' and ''[[A Clockwork Orange (film)|A Clockwork Orange]]''.
*'''[[David Lynch]]''' – [[surrealism|Surrealistic]] director whose mysteries are usually puzzles of the mind. Both the audience and the characters themselves must figure out what is real and what is not, especially in ''[[Inland Empire (film)|Inland Empire]]'', ''[[Lost Highway (film)|Lost Highway]]'', ''[[Eraserhead]]'' and ''[[Mulholland Drive (film)|Mulholland Drive]]''.
*'''[[Christopher Nolan]]''' – British-American director whose narrative structures often reflect the mental construction of the characters, as in ''[[The Dark Knight (film)|The Dark Knight]]'', ''[[Insomnia (2002 film)|Insomnia]]'', ''[[Memento (film)|Memento]]'', ''[[Following (film)|Following]]'', ''[[The Prestige (film)|The Prestige]]'' and ''[[Inception]]
*'''[[Roman Polanski]]''' – Polish director whose thrillers focus on the alienation and isolation of the characters, as in ''[[Repulsion]]'' and ''[[Le Locataire]]''.
*'''[[Martin Scorsese]]''' – American director who directed ''[[Shutter Island (film)|Shutter Island]]''.
*'''[[M. Night Shyamalan]]''' – Indian-American director well known for making psychological thrillers which often have a [[twist ending]] in them. He successfully executed the psychological thrillers, ''[[The Sixth Sense]]'', ''[[Unbreakable (film)|Unbreakable]]'' and ''[[Signs]]''.
*'''[[Satoshi Kon]]''' – Japanese anime director whose well known for making psychological anime thrillers, as in ''[[Perfect Blue]]'', ''[[Paranoia Agent]]'', ''[[Millennium Actress]]'' and ''[[Paprika (2006 film)|Paprika]]

=== Video games ===
*'''[[Alan Wake]]''' – An [[Xbox 360]] video game developed by [[Remedy Entertainment]] contains a main plot line that follows author Alan Wake, who is suffering from [[writer's block]] for two years and vacations in a town called Bright Falls with his wife. Once there, his wife goes missing and an evil presence stalks the town and its residents. Alan must overcome this force, but at the same time discern what is real and what is in his head. The works of [[Stephen King]], [[The X-Files]], [[Lost (TV series)|Lost]] and [[Twin Peaks]] are listed as influences for making the game.

*'''[[Heavy Rain]]'''- A [[PS3]] exclusive developed by [[Quantic Dream]], putting you into four different perspectives, and giving you one task: to track down a serial killer on loose.

=== Examples in film ===
{{Main|List of thriller films}}

=== Examples in television ===
*'''[[Battlestar Galactica (2004 TV series)|Battlestar Galactica]]'''
*'''[[Damages (TV series)|Damages]]'''
*'''[[Death Note]]'''
*'''[[Dollhouse (TV series)|Dollhouse]]'''
*'''[[Exile (TV series)|Exile]]'''
*'''[[Homeland (TV series)|Homeland]]'''
*'''[[Mad Dogs (TV series)|Mad Dogs]]'''
*'''[[Twin Peaks]]'''

=== Examples in literature ===
*'''[[Emile Zola]]''' – His novel La Bete Humaine is a chilling psychological thriller that focuses on the dark recesses of human nature.
*'''[[Patricia Highsmith]]''' – Highsmith's novels usually focus on troubled young men who are either [[psychopathy|sociopathic]] or emotionally unstable; throughout each story the protagonist is somehow drawn into a murky murder case, and must contend with persistent policemen and suspicious friends. Her most famous character is the charming [[confidence trick|con man]] and serial murderer [[Tom Ripley]] who, over the course of five books, successfully kills nine people.
*'''[[Desmond Cory]]''' – Cory's popular novels have been made into successful films (''The Mark of the Phoenix'', ''Deadfall'') and a television series (''Circe Complex''). Cory explored many different aspects of the psychological thriller, featuring a wide spectrum of characters that ranged from the jewel-thief to the terrorist.
*'''[[Rod Glenn]]''' – Glenn's novel, Sinema: The Northumberland Massacre explores the idea that a seemingly well-adjusted individual with an unremarkable upbringing can make a sane decision to commit murder.  Sinema features the unusually likeable and charismatic character of Hannibal Whitman as the central anti-hero.  
*'''[[Jonathan Kellerman]]''' – Kellerman's [[Alex Delaware]] novels often deal with various matters of [[criminal psychology]].
*'''[[Melanie Wells]]''' – Unlike her contemporaries, Wells has taken a different approach to the genre by adding supernatural elements. Her novels, such as ''When The Day of Evil Comes'', ''The Soul Hunter'' and ''My Soul to Keep'', feature the psychological mind games of Peter Terry - a [[demon]] who seeks to steal his victim's peace of mind and hope. 
*'''[[Mary Higgins Clark]]''' – Clark's novels typically focus on a successful woman caught up in the diaboloical games of men, who are usually either psychotic or [[human sexuality|sexually perverse]]. The crimes in her stories often involve children in some way, and occasionally deal with child [[telepathy]].
*'''[[Nicci French]]''' – The [[pseudonym]] of husband-and-wife team '''Nicci Gerrard''' and '''Sean French'''. Their novels often revolve around a young female protagonist who is either targeted by or is suspected of being a [[psychopath]]ic killer. The stories are quite unique in that they focus just as much, if not more so, on the victims of crime rather than the actual criminals.
*'''[[Stephen King]]''' – Although his books ''[[Carrie (novel)|Carrie]]'', ''[[Cycle of the Werewolf]]'', ''[[Thinner (novel)|Thinner]]'' and others are considered as horror novels, his book often focus on the protagonist(s) and antagonist(s), their origins, backgrounds for character and certain activities.
*'''[[Orson Scott Card]]''' – ''[[Ender's Game]]'', though usually identified as a science fiction novel, gets more into the life of a child, rather than focusing upon the technology and means of the future.

== External links ==
* [http://www.imdb.com/keyword/psychological-thriller/ IMDb - Psychological Thriller] at the [[Internet Movie Database]]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Psychological Thriller}}
[[Category:Psychological thriller films| ]]
[[Category:Literary genres]]
[[Category:Narratology]]
[[Category:Thrillers]]

[[de:Psychothriller]]
[[es:Thriller psicológico]]
[[fa:تریلر روانشناسانه]]
[[it:Thriller psicologico]]
[[nl:Psychologische thriller]]
[[no:Psykologisk thriller]]
[[sv:Psykologisk thriller]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
