<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3431539" ns="0" title="WPCH-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=September 2009}}

{{for|the FM station that held call letters WTBS 1961—1979|WMBR}}
{{Infobox broadcast
| call_letters             = WPCH-TV
| station_logo             = [[Image:Peachtree.png|200px]]
| location                 = [[Atlanta, Georgia]]
| city                     = Atlanta
| station_branding         = '''Peachtree TV'''
| station_slogan           = &quot;Something good is coming on&quot;
| analog                   =
| digital                  = 20 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Virtual channel|Virtual]]: 17 ([[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]])
| virtual                  = 17
| subchannels              = 17.1 - Peachtree TV
| other_chs                =
| affiliations             = [[Independent station (North America)|Independent]]|
| owner                    = [[Turner Broadcasting System]], Inc.&lt;br /&gt;(a [[Time Warner]] company);&lt;br&gt;operated by [[Meredith Corporation]]&lt;/small&gt;
| licensee                 = SuperStation, Inc.
| founded                  = September 1, 1967
| airdate                  = September 1, 1967
| enddate                  =
| callsign_meaning         = '''P'''ea'''CH'''tree TV&lt;br /&gt;(on-air branding; common [[Peachtree City, Georgia|place]]/[[Peachtree Street|road naming theme]] in Atlanta area)
| sister_stations          = [[:Template:Turner Broadcasting System|Cable networks of Turner Broadcasting System]]
| former_callsigns         = WJRJ-TV (1967–1970)&lt;br /&gt;WTCG (1970–1979)&lt;br /&gt;WTBS (1979–2007)
| former_channel_numbers   = '''Analog''':&lt;br /&gt;17 (UHF, 1967–2009)
| former_affiliations      =
| former_locations         =
| former_cities            =
| effective_radiated_power = 1000 [[kilowatt|kW]]|
| HAAT                     = 310.3 m|
| class                    =
| facility_id              = 64033
| coordinates              = {{coord|33|48|26|N|84|20|22|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage                 = [http://www.peachtreetv.com/ www.peachtreetv.com]
}}

'''WPCH-TV''', [[virtual channel]] 17, is an [[independent station (North America)|independent]] [[television station]] in [[Atlanta, Georgia]], [[United States|USA]] where &quot;something good is coming on&quot;.  WPCH-TV is owned by the [[Turner Broadcasting System]], a subsidiary of [[Time Warner]], and is the only over-the-air broadcast television station owned by Time Warner (this is despite the fact the company is also half-owner of [[The CW Television Network]],{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} whose Atlanta affiliate is [[WUPA]], channel 69). Known by the on-air branding of '''Peachtree TV''', WPCH-TV has its studios and transmitter located just northeast of Atlanta.

This station was known as '''WTBS''' from August 27, 1979 until October 1, 2007, when its operations were split from the co-owned [[TBS (TV channel)|TBS]].  WTBS was the pioneering [[superstation]], and its signal was carried to cable and satellite viewers throughout the [[United States]] and [[Canada]].

On January 18, 2011, Turner and Time Warner announced that it will transfer the operations of WPCH-TV to [[Meredith Corporation]] by way of a [[local marketing agreement]].  Meredith owns [[WGCL-TV]] (channel 46), Atlanta's [[CBS]] affiliate, and the deal would give Meredith a de facto television duopoly in Atlanta.  Turner and Time Warner will continue to own WPCH-TV's license.&lt;ref name=&quot;ajc-meredithcontrol&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Swartz|first=Kristi E.|title=Parent of CBS Atlanta to take over operations of Peachtree TV|url=http://www.ajc.com/business/parent-of-cbs-atlanta-807725.html|accessdate=January 18, 2011|newspaper=[[Atlanta Journal-Constitution]]|date=January 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This marketing agreement with Meredith apparently also ended Turner Broadcasting's yearly sponsorship of Piedmont Park's &quot;Screen on the Green&quot; beginning in 2011.

==History==
===As WJRJ-TV===
Channel 17 commenced broadcasting on September 1, 1967, as '''WJRJ-TV'''. It was the Atlanta market's first [[Independent station (North America)|independent station]], and one of the first in the entire [[Southeastern United States]].  The station was named for its founder, Atlanta entrepreneur '''J'''ack '''R'''ice, '''J'''r.

WJRJ-TV was launched on a shoestring budget, with an afternoon and evening schedule (4 p.m. to 11 p.m.) filled with old movies and a few off-network reruns like ''[[Father Knows Best]]'', ''[[The Danny Thomas Show]]'', ''[[The Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet]]'', ''[[Riflemen]]'', and others, as well as a 15-minute news program. In addition to placing daily ads on the ''[[Atlanta Journal-Constitution]]'' TV page, WJRJ ran exactly one ''[[TV Guide]]'' advertisement: a half-page ad in a September 1967 issue with the headline, &quot;Yes, Atlanta, there is a channel 17.&quot; Despite WJRJ billing itself as &quot;Good-looking Channel 17&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.gainesvilletimes.com/news/article/499/ |title=Remote control can't keep classics on |publisher=Gainesvilletimes.com |date=2008-05-31 |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; technical snafus were the norm in the station's early months: film broke down, slides frequently appeared backwards, and there were often long pauses when nothing appeared on screen. The station did carry a top-rated show for a few weeks: Then-CBS affiliate [[WAGA-TV]] (channel 5) ran a local movie on Wednesday night, and channel 17 stepped in to run ''[[Medical Center (TV series)|Medical Center]]'' (the rights to which would later be owned by the station's future owners) for a time.

===Ted Turner enters the picture===
In [[1970#January|January 1970]] [[entrepreneur]] [[Ted Turner]], who ran his father's [[billboard (advertising)|billboard]] business and also owned radio stations, bought the low-rated UHF outlet. Soon after, Turner changed the call letters to '''WTCG''', which reportedly stood for &quot;'''W'''atch '''T'''his '''C'''hannel '''G'''row&quot; (though the &quot;TCG&quot; officially stood for [[Turner Communications Group]], the forerunner to Turner Broadcasting System). WTCG initially retained its original programming format.

During an interview in 2004, Turner revealed that some of the problems that had dogged WJRJ were present in the early days at WTCG.  First, when Turner bought the station, it was the only one in the Atlanta market still broadcasting exclusively in black-and-white because the previous owners had not made necessary color upgrades. Second, money was still very tight during the first couple of years that Turner owned the station. The station decided to purchase the color broadcasting equipment it needed on credit after Turner took over.  However, some months had passed and Turner found himself unable to make the payments on the equipment. As a last resort (after unsuccessfully attempting to secure further financing), Turner held an on-air telethon, much in the manner of [[public television]], to raise the money needed to pay the station's bills.  Third, there was new competition in the form of new UHF station [[WATL (TV)|WATL]] (channel 36) beginning operations.  Once the financial problems were settled, WTCG eventually drove WATL off the air.  WTCG threw an on-air party in celebration, but they would soon have a new competitor when WHAE-TV (channel 46, now WGCL-TV) went on the air in 1971.  Originally owned by [[Christian Broadcasting Network]], that station ran a general entertainment format mixed with Christian religious programs (like CBN's flagship, ''[[The 700 Club]]'') and competitive, but WTCG remained the leading independent in Atlanta.

Turner had a low budget in terms of programming purchases, and would bid very low on new shows offered in syndication and network stations like WAGA-TV, [[WSB-TV]] (channel 2) and [[WXIA-TV]] (channel 11) would get the best product. But due to network commitments, the three major affiliates could only keep programs for few years. Turner would then buy the shows that the major affiliates did not renew for nearly half the price of original purchase. Turner also bought most of the movie packages in this manner.  The station placed an on-air emphasis on its movie library; one notable program was ''Academy Award Theatre'', which showcased only Oscar-winning films.  The sports programming included games of the [[Atlanta Braves]], [[Atlanta Hawks]], and [[Georgia Championship Wrestling]], one of the roots of the later [[World Championship Wrestling]]. The sports and wrestling would become foundation blocks during the early satellite years (see below).

WTCG made its name also by producing humorous, satirical newscasts.  One such newscast was ''17 Update Early in the Morning'', which featured usually straight-faced [[Bill Tush]] and Tina Seldin reporting the news in a mostly normal fashion, occasionally interacting with the studio crew, and with comedic sideline gags at times by another co-anchor (The Unknown Newsman) wearing a brown paper grocery bag over his head. The newscast, which often contained elements resembling that of a comedic morning drive radio show, had a several-year run between late night/early morning movie presentations from 1975 to 1979. Turner discontinued that program after a [[United States Congress|Congressional]] investigation took place concerning his fulfilling [[Federal Communications Commission]] public service requirements, some months before Turner would prepare to launch [[CNN]], an all-news channel that would strive to be anything but comedic. Turner reassigned Tush to regular interview programs on WTCG and during the early years of CNN, as well as a [[skit comedy]] show between 1980 and 1982.

Another show on the WTCG lineup was hosted by the legendary [[R&amp;B]] singer [[James Brown]] and called ''James Brown's Future Shock''.  The show, which bore similarities to ''[[American Bandstand]]'' and ''[[Soul Train]]'', aired late nights each Friday in the mid-1970s.

In the 1970's, WTCG was the first local Atlanta channel to bring back telecasts of old films from the 1930's and '40's. This came after a rather long period in which local stations had abandoned their practice of telecasting very old films, and had begun concentrating on films made in the 1950's and afterwards.

===The first &quot;Superstation&quot;===
{{main|TBS (TV network)}}
Beginning in the early 1970s many cable systems in surrounding states would microwave the WTCG signal into neighboring [[Alabama]], [[Tennessee]] and [[South Carolina]], far beyond the Atlanta TV market. WTCG was one of the first TV stations to broadcast via [[satellite]]. It, along with WOR-TV (now [[WWOR-TV]]) in [[New York (city)|New York]] and [[WGN-TV]] in [[Chicago]], were among America's first &quot;superstations&quot;: independent channels distributed to cable systems throughout their respective regions, or the entire country.

At 1 p.m. [[Eastern Standard Time]] on December 17, 1976, WTCG's signal was beamed via the [[Satcom 1]] satellite to four cable systems in [[Grand Island, Nebraska]]; [[Newport News, Virginia]]; [[Troy, Alabama]]; and [[Newton, Kansas]]. All four cable systems started receiving the sleepy [[1948 in film|1948]] [[Dana Andrews]] and [[Cesar Romero]] film ''[[Deep Waters (film)|Deep Waters]]'', which was already 30 minutes in progress. Instantly, WTCG added 24,000 more [[household]]s to its viewing audience, which consisted of 675,000 households in metropolitan Atlanta. That number would grow exponentially in the next several years, with the first heaviest concentrations in the [[Southern United States]] (where WTCG's telecasts of Atlanta Braves baseball and [[professional wrestling]] were highly popular), but eventually encompassing the nation. The station, and Turner's innovation, signaled the start of the [[basic cable]] revolution. By 1978, WTCG was on cable systems in all 50 states, many of which lacked access to a local commercial independent station and in some cases even a distant one.

Programming stayed pretty similar as shows such as ''[[Brady Bunch]]'', ''[[Beverly Hillbillies]]'', ''[[Bewitched]]'', ''[[I Dream Of Jeannie]]'', ''[[Hogan's Heroes]]'', made for TV ''[[Popeye]]'' cartoons, and other vintage shows would be purchased second and even third hand. They did manage to win bids for ''[[All In The Family]]'' and ''[[Sanford and Son]]'' however.

===As WTBS===
After using the callsign WTCG for most of its first decade under Turner's ownership, the station became '''WTBS''' on August 27, 1979. The WTBS callsign had been held by the [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]] radio station, but MIT agreed to cede the letters to Turner's station after Turner donated the money for a new transmitter for MIT's radio station, which is now known as [[WMBR (FM)|WMBR]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wmbr.mit.edu/history.html |title=WMBR history |publisher=Wmbr.mit.edu |date= |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Through the 1980s, the station was primarily known as '''SuperStation WTBS''', but the &quot;W&quot; was dropped from the branding late in the decade. In Atlanta, through the early 1990s, station promos and digital on-screen graphics referred to the station as '''TBS 17'''. Another difference was that local commercials airing locally on channel 17 would not air over the satellite feed and be substituted. Eventually, the &quot;SuperStation&quot; branding was dropped in 1990, and for a short while in the late-1990s, the &quot;SuperStation&quot; name returned without the &quot;TBS&quot; branding. As the 1990s and 2000s wore on, the station began to more closely resemble a basic cable network and not a superstation. Outside of Braves baseball, the only Atlanta-centric programming on WTBS by 2002 was a public affairs show on Sunday morning that was only broadcast over WTBS and not the national feed.

In 1986 Turner would buy the MGM library, giving WTBS the rights to air it. WTBS added more feature films from MGM at that point. In September 1998, due to the trend of children's shows moving more toward cable, WTBS dropped all their cartoons and now focused on comedy movies, drama movies, '80s and '90s sitcoms, and a few drama shows.  [[music video|Music videos]] were also aired from 1983 to 1992 on its late night weekend lineup branded as ''[[Night Tracks]]'' with up to 14 hours of programming (barring constant preemptions from sporting events running overtime).

In 2003, WTBS dropped most drama movies and all their drama shows and focused on comedy (sister network [[TNT (TV channel)|TNT]] in turn began [[TNT (TV channel)#&quot;We Know Drama&quot; era|specializing in drama]] by this time). The station now consisted of comedy movies and sitcoms from 1990s. At this point it was determined that WTBS should be split up. The satellite channel would be known as TBS while the over the air channel would be a commercial independent station also focused on sitcoms as well as other movies and local interest programs.

===Transition to Peachtree TV===
On October 1, 2007, Turner Broadcasting rebranded WTBS as '''Peachtree TV''', with new [[call letters]], '''WPCH-TV'''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.turnerinfo.com/newsitem.aspx?P=TBS&amp;CID01=aa8051cc-f1f4-4b7f-ad1d-ce2809be3b6f Turner Pressroom&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As a result of this, the nationwide version of TBS became available to cable and satellite viewers in the Atlanta market for the first time. Peachtree TV carries [[Atlanta Braves]] baseball as well as classic and more recent off-network syndicated programming and movies. The new station contains significantly more paid programming, African-American programming, and older less expensive programming than its predecessor WTBS.

WPCH-TV broadcast 45 Atlanta Braves baseball games in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://atlanta.bizjournals.com/atlanta/stories/2007/06/25/daily32.html?surround=lfn |title=WTBS to become PeachTree TV |publisher=Atlanta.bizjournals.com |date=2007-06-27 |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Braves games are being made available to cable customers in the Southeastern U.S. (outside Metro Atlanta) by [[Comcast Sports Southeast/Charter Sports Southeast|CSS]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.citizen-times.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=200880329063 Deal allows more Braves games to air locally | CITIZEN-TIMES.com | Asheville Citizen-Times&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]{{dead link|date=September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Viewers on [[DirecTV]] who are outside of the Atlanta [[designated market area]] but inside the Braves' market can see the Peachtree TV telecasts on channel 651, as well as  viewers outside of the Braves' DMA who subscribe to [[MLB Extra Innings]]. Viewers with [[Dish Network]] can watch Peachtree TV on Channel 17 in the Atlanta [[designated market area]] and on one of Dish Network's sports alternate channels in the rest of the Braves' television territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;SECSports&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.satelliteguys.us/dish-network-forum/168047-peachtree-tv-atlanta-braves-baseball-10.html|title=PEACHTREE TV ATLANTA BRAVES BASEBALL|date=2009-07-17|publisher=[[SatelliteGuys.us]]|accessdate=2010-01-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first regular season Braves game presented on WPCH was the team's [[2008 Atlanta Braves season|2008 season home opener]] on March 31.  In that game, the Braves lost to the [[Pittsburgh Pirates]], 12–11 in 11 [[inning (baseball)|inning]]s.

WPCH has been the affiliate for [[SEC Network|ESPN's syndication package for the Southeastern Conference]] in the Atlanta metropolitan area since ESPN replaced [[Raycom Sports]] in 2009.  Unlike most affiliates, this includes the full SEC football, men's basketball, and women's basketball package.  The SEC games are broadcast in [[1080i]] [[High-definition television|high definition]] by Peachtree TV but Comcast customers in Atlanta are only able to view the games in SD as of October 3, 2009.  On October 10, 2009 Comcast customers were able to watch the SEC Network game UGA vs Tenn in HD; it is not known if this change is permanent.&lt;ref name=&quot;SECSports&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secsports.com/news/sec-network-schedule.aspx|title=SEC Network Game of the Week|date=2009-09-22|publisher=[[Southeastern Conference]]|accessdate=2009-09-23}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Turner announced on January 18, 2011 that operations for WPCH would be taken over by [[Meredith Corporation]], owner of [[CBS]] affiliate [[WGCL-TV]], though Turner will retain the broadcast license.  In addition, production of the station's 45 Atlanta Braves broadcasts will be transferred from [[Turner Sports]] to [[Fox Sports South]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ajc-meredithcontrol&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Swartz|first=Kristi E.|title=Parent of CBS Atlanta to take over operations of Peachtree TV|url=http://www.ajc.com/business/parent-of-cbs-atlanta-807725.html|accessdate=January 18, 2011|newspaper=[[Atlanta Journal-Constitution]]|date=January 18, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other stations called WPCH===
WPCH-TV is not related to a similarly-called FM radio station in the [[Macon, Georgia|Macon]] area, [[WPCH (FM)|WPCH]] (102.5 FM), which is owned by [[Clear Channel Communications]].  WPCH was also the call letters in the 1970s, 1980s, and 1990s for &quot;Peach 94.9&quot;, the Atlanta radio station that is now [[WUBL (FM)|WUBL]]; and after that (2003 to 2006) on 1380 AM in the [[Augusta, Georgia|Augusta]] area, now [[WNRR]]. Like WPCH FM, WNRR and WUBL are both owned by Clear Channel.

Probably the first use of the WPCH call letters was for a station which operated from November 6, 1926 to June 4, 1933 in [[New York City|New York]]. The station was created as a merger of two earlier stations, WFBH and WRW, under the ownership of Concourse Radio Corporation. In the fall of 1927 the station was bought by the owners of [[WMCA]] and six years later it was merged into that station.

===Canada===
Peachtree TV is carried on most Canadian cable and satellite service providers as part of one of the main specialty tiers, generally as part of &quot;full cable&quot; for analog cable subscribers. The station was first made available in Canada in the 1980s (as WTBS), when the [[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission|CRTC]], Canada's telecommunications regulator, permitted Canadian service providers to carry the Atlanta station, and other U.S. superstations, as premium channels packaged with Canadian premium services, such as the services now known as [[The Movie Network]] or [[Movie Central]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/1985/PB85-72.htm|title=Public Notice CRTC 1985-72 - Optional Canadian and Non-Canadian Satellite Services|author=[[Canadian Radio-television and Telecommunications Commission]]|date=1985-04-04|accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; By late 1997, many service providers had moved the station from pay service to their third specialty tier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mediacastermagazine.com/issues/story.aspx?aid=1000111924&amp;type=Print%20Archives|title=A look at Tier III: Launched in October 1997, much doom was predicted for the launch of Tier III. Looking at those channels now, there sure isn't much to nit-pick about.|author=Greg O'Brien|date=2002-01-01|accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

When WTBS became Peachtree TV, Canadian service providers were only permitted to continue carrying the Atlanta station, and not the TBS cable channel. The national cable feed that had split off from WTBS in the 1990s was technically a separate channel and was never formally approved by the CRTC as a replacement for the over-the-air Atlanta station.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/eng/archive/2007/pb2007-132.htm|title=Broadcasting Public Notice CRTC 2007-132 - Renaming of WTBS Atlanta as WPCH-TV Atlanta on the lists of eligible satellite services|date=2007-11-19|accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, in informing the CRTC of WTBS's change of call sign and branding, Turner Broadcasting apparently did not make any request to have the TBS cable channel approved in its place.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.crtc.gc.ca/public/broad/applications/2007/PN2007-132_21Sept.pdf|author=Richard Warren (Turner Network Sales)|title=Re: Commission's Revised List of Eligible Satellite Signals - The Renaming of WTBS Atlanta as WPCH|date=2007-09-21|accessdate=2010-10-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peachtree TV continues to carry some of the same programs as TBS (albeit at different times), and hence some Canadians may continue to perceive Peachtree TV as either a renaming of, or equivalent to, the U.S. TBS service.&lt;ref&gt;See, for example, the comments on [http://backofthebook.ca/2010/04/12/what-the-hell-conan-tbs/2442/ this blog post] regarding the Canadian availability of ''[[Conan (TV series)|Conan]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; However, WPCH does not carry flagship TBS programs such as [[Major League Baseball postseason]] coverage, or the talk show ''[[Conan (TV series)|Conan]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;peachtreetv&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vancouversun.com/entertainment/Conan+Brien+okays+deal+talk+show+updated/2851812/story.html|author=Bart Jackson|title=Conan O'Brien okays deal for new talk show |date=April 13, 2010|accessdate=April 13, 2010|publisher=[[Vancouver Sun]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; both of which are instead carried by other Canadian channels. On March 11, 2011, Peachtree TV was removed from the [[Cogeco]] channel line up due to contractual issues encountered with the channel provider.

==Digital transition==
Via [[Radio frequency|RF]] [[TV channel]] 20, the station [[digital TV|digitally]] transmits its main Peachtree TV programming in [[1080i]] mode on [[virtual channel]] 17.1.  However, until 2011 it was entirely [[Video scaler|upconvert]]ed and [[pillarbox]]ed [[SDTV]] programming, even for [[movie]]s; the only exceptions were Atlanta Braves and SEC College Football games, which were in [[widescreen]] [[HDTV]].  On April 3, 2011 the movie [[Forrest Gump]] was broadcast in widescreen format (16:9) without being pillarboxed, and since then much more programming has been airing in HD.

At the end of January 2009, [[digital subchannel]] 17.2 appeared, but as of February 5 it was blank, without [[digital audio|audio]] or [[digital video|video]], and soon disappeared.  It is possible for TBS to be broadcast [[terrestrial television|over the air]] along with Peachtree TV, however the station did not release any information on what it planned to do with the new channel.

After the 2009 [[DTV transition in the United States|analog television shutdown]] on June 12,&lt;ref name=&quot;Analog to Digital&quot;&gt;http://hraunfoss.fcc.gov/edocs_public/attachmatch/DA-06-1082A2.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; WPCH-DT continues on its current pre-transition channel number, 20 &lt;ref name=&quot;FCCForm387&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fjallfoss.fcc.gov/cgi-bin/ws.exe/prod/cdbs/forms/prod/cdbsmenu.hts?context=25&amp;appn=101234305&amp;formid=387&amp;fac_num=64033 |title=CDBS Print |publisher=Fjallfoss.fcc.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; using [[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]] to display as 17.1.

The station's digital antenna is located near [[North Druid Hills]], on a tower shared with several other FM and TV stations.  Its analog antenna (aka the [[Turner Broadcasting tower]] was located on a very large tower on the east side of the [[Downtown Connector]], and was dismantled in 2010.  This was a condition of its [[land lease]], as it sits on property owned by [[Comcast]], the primary [[cable TV]] competitor to Time Warner.  This quirk of history is explained by the fact that it was originally the site of a different tower for [[WAGA-TV]], which was owned by [[Storer Broadcasting]].  [[Storer Cable]] went with a different owner, and eventually was absorbed into Comcast.  (See the [[list of Atlanta broadcast stations by location#Towers]].)

The station's digital signal is at the maximum allowable power (1000&amp;nbsp;kW [[effective radiated power|ERP]]), while its original analog signal is not.  Its DTV channel 20 is [[diplex]]ed with [[WUVG-TV]] 34 into a master TV antenna at a separate tower, located at 1800 Briarcliff Road NE, in Atlanta's [[Morningside (Atlanta)|Morningside]] neighborhood.  The station has also applied for an analog backup facility at this location, with a corresponding [[construction permit]] dating from its original application in 2003 to transmit from the [[WATL (TV)|WATL]] digital antenna on the same tower.  Two subsequent applications in 2006 to increase the power of the backup have not been ruled on {{As of|2007|10|lc=on}}.  Several other TV stations are on this tower, including [[WUVM-LP]] and [[W23DN]], and possibly WGCL-TV.  [[WNNX]] is now located on this tower, sharing the same antenna with [[WVEE (FM)|WVEE]] and [[WZGC (FM)|WZGC]]. [[WKHX-FM]] is slightly lower on the tower, while [[WRFG (FM)|WRFG]] has an application for much lower on the tower.  According to the FCC database, another tower holding several other stations is located about 110 meters or 350 feet east-northeast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/fmq?state=&amp;call=&amp;city=&amp;arn=&amp;serv=&amp;vac=&amp;freq=0.0&amp;fre2=107.9&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;dkt=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=1&amp;dlat2=33&amp;mlat2=48&amp;slat2=26&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=84&amp;mlon2=20&amp;slon2=22&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9 |title=FM Query Results - Audio Division (FCC) USA |publisher=Fcc.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fcc.gov/fcc-bin/tvq?state=&amp;call=&amp;city=&amp;arn=&amp;serv=&amp;vac=&amp;freq=0.0&amp;fre2=107.9&amp;facid=&amp;class=&amp;dkt=&amp;list=1&amp;dist=1&amp;dlat2=33&amp;mlat2=48&amp;slat2=26&amp;NS=N&amp;dlon2=84&amp;mlon2=20&amp;slon2=22&amp;EW=W&amp;size=9 |title=TV Query Results - Video Division (FCC) USA |publisher=Fcc.gov |date= |accessdate=2009-09-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.peachtreetv.com/}}
*{{TVQ|WPCH-TV}}
*{{BIA|WPCH|TV|TV}}
*[http://www.billtush.com/update.html Clips of 17 Update Early in the Morning maintained by former anchor Bill Tush]
&lt;!--Navigation boxes--&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
{{Atlanta TV}}
{{Other Georgia Stations}}
{{Atlanta Hawks}}
{{Atlanta Braves}}
{{Superstations}}
{{TBS}}
{{Time Warner}}
{{Meredith Corporation}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wpch-Tv}}
[[Category:Television stations in Georgia (U.S. state)]]
[[Category:Superstations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 17 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 20 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Turner Television networks]]
[[Category:Time Warner subsidiaries]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1967]]
[[Category:The NHL Network (1975–79) affiliates]]
[[Category:Atlanta Braves broadcasters]]
[[Category:Atlanta Hawks broadcasters]]
[[Category:Atlanta Thrashers broadcasters]]
[[Category:Major League Baseball over-the-air television broadcasters]]
[[Category:National Hockey League over-the-air television broadcasters]]

[[fr:WPCH-TV]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
