<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="344642" ns="0" title="Carl Andrew Spaatz"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military person
|name = Carl Andrew Spaatz
|birth_date = {{birth date|1891|06|28}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|1974|07|14|1891|06|28}}
|birth_place = [[Boyertown, Pennsylvania]], USA
|death_place = [[Washington, D.C.]], USA
|placeofburial=
|placeofburial_label= Place of burial
|image = [[File:Carl Spaatz, Air Force photo portrait, color.jpg|250px]]
|caption = Gen. Spaatz
|nickname = ''Tooey''
|allegiance = [[United States of America]]
|branch = [[United States Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United States Army Air Forces]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United States Army Air Corps]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United States Army Air Service|Air Service, U.S. Army]]&lt;br/&gt;[[United States Army]]
|serviceyears = 1914 - 1948
|rank = [[File:US-O10 insignia.svg|35px]] [[General (United States)|General]]
|unit =
|battles = [[Pancho Villa Expedition|Mexican Expedition]]&lt;br/&gt;[[World War I]]&lt;br/&gt;[[World War II]]
|awards = [[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Army Distinguished Service Medal]] (3)&lt;br/&gt;[[Legion of Merit]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]]&lt;br/&gt;Knights Grand Cross of the [[Order of the British Empire]] [[GBE]]&lt;br/&gt;
Grand Officiers of the [[Légion d'honneur]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Croix de guerre]]}}

'''Carl Andrew &quot;Tooey&quot; Spaatz''' (June 28, 1891 – July 14, 1974) [[Order of the British Empire|GBE]] (hon.) was an [[United States|American]] [[World War II]] general and the first [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force]]. He was of [[Germans|German]] descent.

==Early life==
Born as '''Carl Andrew Spatz''', he added the second &quot;a&quot; in 1937 at the request of his wife and daughters to clarify the pronunciation of the name, as many pronounced it &quot;[[Spats (disambiguation)|spats]]&quot;. He added the second &quot;a&quot; to draw it out to sound like &quot;ah&quot;, like the &quot;a&quot; in &quot;father&quot;. (The name is thus correctly pronounced &quot;Spahtz&quot;.)&lt;ref&gt;Spaatz was a neighbor and close associate of Lieutenant Colonel [[Robert Olds]] at Langley Field, Virginia in the 1930's. Olds had similarly changed the spelling of his name (from Oldys) in 1931 because of common mispronunciation.&lt;/ref&gt;

Spaatz received his nickname at [[United States Military Academy|West Point]] because of his resemblance to another red-headed cadet named F.J. Toohey.  He graduated as a [[second lieutenant]] of Infantry 12 June 1914. He was assigned as a student in the [[Rockwell Field|Signal Corps Aviation School]] at San Diego, California, between 13 October 1915 and 15 May 1916. He was detached to the [[Aviation Section, U.S. Signal Corps]] in [[Mexico]] on 8 June 1916.

Spaatz served in the [[1st Reconnaissance Squadron|First Aero Squadron]] which was attached to General [[John J. Pershing]] during the [[Punitive Expedition]]. Spaatz was promoted to [[First Lieutenant#United States|First Lieutenant]] on 1 July 1916 and to [[Captain (U.S. Army)|Captain]] on 15 May 1917.

[[File:CarlSpaatz-bust.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Bust of General Spaatz at the [[Imperial War Museum Duxford]]]]

==World War I==
Following America's entry into [[World War I]], Spaatz was sent with the [[American Expeditionary Force]]s (AEF) in command of the [[31st Aero Squadron]]. Spaatz was appointed Officer in Charge, American Aviation School at Issoudun, [[France]] but after receiving orders to return to the United States, he saw three weeks of action during the final months of the war with the [[13th Aero Squadron]] as a supernumerary pilot. In this brief period, Spaatz shot down three enemy planes and was awarded the [[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]] ([[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|DSC]]); during the time he was promoted to the temporary rank of [[Major (United States)|major]] on 17 June 1918.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.homeofheroes.com/valor/1_Citations/01_wwi_dsc/dsc_05wwi_AirService2.html |title=Full Text Citations For Award of The Distinguished Service Cross World War I}}{{Dead link|date=March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Inter-war years==
In 1919 he served in California and Texas and became assistant department air service officer for the Western Department in July 1919. Spaatz experienced the chaotic ups and downs in rank common to Regular officers in 1920, when the National Defense Act of 1920 reorganized the military. He first reverted to his permanent rank of captain of Infantry 27 February 1920. On 1 July 1920, when the [[United States Army Air Service|Air Service]] became a combatant arm of the line, he transferred to the Air Service as a captain, then was promoted to major on the same date by virtue of a provision in the National Defense Act that allowed officers who earned their rank in service with the AEF to retain it. This made him senior to a number of officers, including [[Henry H. Arnold]] (his superior at the time), with greater longevity of service. On 18 December 1922 he was discharged when Congress set a new ceiling on the number of majors authorized the Air Service, and reappointed as a captain, then promoted again to major on 1 February 1923.

As a major, he commanded [[Kelly Field]], Texas, from October 5, 1920, to February 1921, served at [[Fort Sam Houston]] as air officer of the Eighth Corps Area until November 1921, and was commanding officer of the [[1st Operations Group|1st Pursuit Group]], first at [[Ellington Air Force Base|Ellington Field]], Texas, and later at [[Selfridge Air Force Base|Selfridge Field]], Michigan, until September 24, 1924. He graduated from the [[Air Corps Tactical School]], [[Langley Field]], Virginia, in June 1925, and then served in the Office of the Chief of Air Corps at Washington, D.C.

[[File:Atlantic C-2A refuelled by Douglas C-1 USAF.JPG|thumb|285px|The ''Question Mark'' being refueled by a Douglas C-1]]

From January 1 to January 7, 1929, Spaatz along with fellow Air Corps officers, Captain [[Ira Eaker]] and Lieutenant [[Elwood Quesada]], both of whom would later become senior [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) generals, established an aviation record by keeping the airplane ''[[Question Mark (airplane)|Question Mark]]'' in the air over the [[Los Angeles]] vicinity for over 150 hours.

From May 8, 1929, to October 29, 1931, Spaatz commanded the [[7th Operations Group|7th Bombardment Group]] at [[Rockwell Field]], California, and the 1st Bombardment Wing at [[March Field]], California, until June 10, 1933. He then served in the Office of the Chief of Air Corps and became chief of the Training and Operations Division. In August 1935, he enrolled in the [[Command and General Staff School]] at [[Fort Leavenworth]], Kansas, and while there was promoted to lieutenant colonel on 16 September. He graduated in June 1936, and then served at Langley Field on the staff of Maj. Gen. [[Frank M. Andrews]], commander of General Headquarters Air Force, until January 1939, when he returned to the Office of the Chief of Air Corps at Washington as assistant executive officer.

On 7 November 1939, Spaatz received a temporary promotion to colonel, and during the [[Battle of Britain]] in 1940, spent several weeks in [[England]] as a special military observer. In August 1940, he was assigned in the Office of the Chief of Air Corps, and two months later was appointed assistant to the chief of Air Corps, General Arnold, with the temporary rank of brigadier general. He became chief of the Plans Division of the Air Corps in November 1940, and the following July was named chief of the air staff at [[United States Army Air Forces|Army Air Forces]] Headquarters.

==World War II==
Arnold named Spaatz commander of [[USAAF#Creation of the Army Air Forces|Air Forces Combat Command]] in January 1942 and promoted him to the temporary rank of [[Major general (United States)|major general]].  In May 1942 Spaatz became commander of the [[Eighth Air Force]] and transferred its headquarters to England in July. Spaatz was placed in overall command of the USAAF in the [[European Theater of Operations]], while retaining his Eighth Air Force command.  He was promoted to the permanent rank of Colonel in September 1942 and subsequently assigned command of the [[Twelfth Air Force]] in [[North Africa]] in December 1942.  He was named commander the Allied Northwest African Air Force in February 1943, the [[Fifteenth Air Force]] and Royal Air Forces in [[Italy]] in November 1943, and the [[U.S. Strategic Air Forces in Europe]] in January 1944. Spaatz received a temporary promotion to [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]] in March 1943.

As commander of Strategic Air Forces, Spaatz directed the United States portion of the [[Strategic bombing during World War II|strategic bombing]] campaign against [[Germany]], directing the Eighth Air Force, which was now commanded by Lieutenant General [[Jimmy Doolittle]], based in England, and the Fifteenth Air Force, which was now commanded by Lieutenant General [[Nathan Twining]], based in Italy.

{{Quote box |width=25em |align=left  |bgcolor=#B0C4DE
|title=
|fontsize=70% |quote=&quot;''It is hard to think of another commander in the USAAF who had enough influence with General Eisenhower to hold off, as well as Spaatz did, the diversions proposed by Leigh-Mallory.  Neither is it easy to think of any other who had both the perception to identify [[Oil Campaign of World War II|oil targets as decisive]] and the strength to conserve a part of the U.S. strategic air striking power for them.&lt;ref name=Mets&gt;{{cite book |last=Mets |first=David R. |year=1997 - paperback |origyear=1988 |title=Master of Airpower: General Carl A. Spaatz |pages=260–1,265}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Rp|340}}
|salign    = right
|source    = biographer David R. Mets
}}
As the commander of Strategic Air Forces in Europe, Spaatz was under the direct command of Gen. [[Dwight Eisenhower]]. In March 1944, Spaatz proposed the [[Oil Campaign of World War II|Oil Plan for bombing]], and in June 1944 during the [[Operation Crossbow]] priority bombing of V-1 sites aimed at the UK, Spaatz advocated, and received authorization from Eisenhower for, bombing of those targets at a lower priority.  Spaatz also identified that &quot;''…the chimera of one air operation that will end the war…does not exist''&quot;, and &lt;ref name=Mets/&gt;{{Rp|273}} advocated [[Transportation Plan|Tedder's plan]] &quot;''which retained the oil system in first position, but more clearly placed Germany's rail system in second priority''&quot;, which encouraged Eisenhower to overrule Air Ministry fears that the &quot;''thrust against the oil industry''&quot; might be weakened.&lt;ref name=Mets/&gt;{{Rp|260-1}}  Spaatz's '''Oil Plan''' became the highest bombing priority in September 1944.  After the war, Eisenhower said that Spaatz, along with General [[Omar Bradley]], was one of the two American general officers who had contributed the most to the victory in Europe.

Spaatz received a temporary promotion to the rank of general on March 11, 1945.  He was transferred to the Pacific and assumed command of the [[U.S. Strategic Air Forces in the Pacific]] as part of the [[Pacific Theatre of Operations]], with headquarters on [[Guam]], in July 1945. From this command, Spaatz directed the strategic bombing of [[Japan]], including the [[nuclear weapon|atomic bombing]] of [[Hiroshima]] and [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]]. Spaatz had been present at [[Reims]] when the Germans surrendered to the Americans on May 7, 1945; at [[Berlin]] when they surrendered to the [[Russia]]ns on May 9; and aboard the [[battleship]] [[USS Missouri (BB-63)|''Missouri'']] in [[Tokyo Bay]] when the Japanese surrendered on September 2. He was the only man of General rank or equivalent present at all three of these acts of surrender.

==Later life==
In July 1945, President [[Harry S. Truman|Truman]] nominated Spaatz for promotion to the permanent rank of [[Major general (United States)|major general]]. Spaatz was appointed Commanding General of the Army Air Forces in February 1946 following Arnold's retirement. After the creation of the independent Air Force by the [[National Security Act of 1947]] and Truman's Executive Order No. 9877, Spaatz was appointed as the first Chief of Staff of the new [[United States Air Force]] in September 1947.

Spaatz retired from the military at the rank of [[General (United States)|general]] on June 30, 1948&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=General Carl A. Spaatz |url=http://www.af.mil/information/bios/bio.asp?bioID=7210 Public domain biography from U.S. Air Force |work=Biographies |publisher=Air Force Link |accessdate=2009-03-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; and worked for ''[[Newsweek]]'' [[magazine]] as military affairs editor until 1961. He also served on the Committee of Senior Advisors to the [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force|Air Force Chief of Staff]], from 1952 until his death. From 1948 until 1959, he served as [[National Commander of the Civil Air Patrol]]. In 1954, Spaatz was appointed to the congressional advisory board set up to determine the site for the new [[United States Air Force Academy]]. Spaatz died on July 14, 1974 and is buried at the [[United States Air Force Academy|Academy's]] [[United States Air Force Academy Cemetery|cemetery]] in [[Colorado Springs]], [[Colorado]].

==Awards and decorations==
&lt;small&gt;Source: USAF Historical Study 91: ''Biographical Data on Air Force General Officers, 1917-1952'', Vol. II, &quot;L-Z&quot;&lt;/small&gt;

[[File:COMMAND PILOT WINGS.png|120px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[USAF Aeronautical Ratings#Pilot ratings|Command pilot]]

{|
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Service Cross ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=2|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Distinguished Service Medal (United States)|Distinguished Service Medal]] (with two [[oak leaf cluster]]s)
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Legion of Merit ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Legion of Merit]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Flying Cross ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)|Distinguished Flying Cross]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=oak|ribbon=Bronze Star ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=Mexican Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Mexican Service Medal|Mexican Interior Campaign Medal]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=3|type=service-star|ribbon=World War I Victory Medal ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[World War I Victory Medal (United States)|World War I Victory Medal]] with three battle stars
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=American Defense Service ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[American Defense Service Medal]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=American Campaign Medal ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[American Campaign Medal]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=0|type=service-star|ribbon=Asiatic-Pacific Campaign ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Medal]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=6|type=service-star|ribbon=European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign ribbon.svg|width=80}}
|[[European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal]] with six battle stars
|-
|}

[[File:World War II Victory Medal ribbon.svg|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[World War II Victory Medal]]

[[File:Order BritEmp rib.png|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Order of the British Empire|Knight Grand Cross and Knight Commander of the Order of the British Empire]]

[[File:BEL Kroonorde Palm Goud BAR.svg|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Order of the Crown (Belgium)|Order of the Crown with palms]] (Belgium)

[[File:Oorlogskruis with Palm.jpg|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Croix de Guerre|Belgian Croix de Guerre]], with palm

[[File:Legion Honneur GC ribbon.svg|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Grand Cross]] of the [[Légion d'honneur|Legion of Honor]] ([[France]])

[[Image:Croix de guerre 1939-1945 with palm.jpg|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Croix de Guerre|Croix de Guerre with Palm]] (France)

[[File:POL Polonia Restituta Komandorski ZG BAR.svg|80px|Ribbon]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Commander's Cross with Star (''Krzyż Komandorski z Gwiazdą''), [[Order of Polonia Restituta]] (Poland)

[[File:NLD Order of Orange-Nassau - Grand Officer BAR.png|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Grand Officer, [[Order of Orange-Nassau]] (Netherlands)

[[Image:Order suvorov2 rib.png|80px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Order of Suvorov|Order of Suvorov 2d Class]] (Soviet Union)

[[File:ObserverBadge.jpg|100px]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[Observer Badge|Combat Observer]]

Spaatz also received the [[Collier Trophy]] for 1944 for &quot;demonstrating the air power concept through employment of American aviation in the war against Germany.&quot;

===Distinguished Service Cross citation===
;Citation:
The President of the United States of America, authorized by Act of Congress, July 9, 1918, takes pleasure in presenting the Distinguished Service Cross to Major (Air Service) Carl Andrew Spatz (ASN: 0-3706), United States Army Air Service, for extraordinary heroism in action while serving with 13th Aero Squadron, U.S. Army Air Service, A.E.F., during the St. Mihiel offensive, 26 September 1918. Although he had received orders to go to the United States, Major Spatz begged for and received permission to serve with a pursuit squadron at the front. Subordinating himself to men of lower rank, he was attached to a squadron as a pilot and saw continuous and arduous service through the offensive. As a result of his efficient work he was promoted to the position of night commander. Knowing that another attack was to take place in the vicinity of Verdun, he remained on duty in order to take part. On the day of the attack west of the Meuse, while with his patrol over enemy lines, a number of enemy aircraft were encountered. In the combat that followed he succeeded in bringing down three enemy planes. In his ardor and enthusiasm he became separated from his patrol while following another enemy far beyond the lines. His gasoline giving out, he was forced to land and managed to land within friendly territory. Through these acts he became an inspiration and example to all men with whom he was associated.
:General Orders: War Department, General Orders No. 123 (1918)
:Action Date: 26 September 1918
:Service: Air Service
:Rank: Major
:Company: 13th Aero Squadron
:Division: American Expeditionary Forces

===Legacy===
*The [[Civil Air Patrol]]'s highest [[cadet]] award is the [[General Carl A. Spaatz Award]].
*Carl A. Spaatz Field is the regional airport serving [[Reading, Pennsylvania]]. It is also home to the [[Mid-Atlantic Air Museum]].
*Spaatz is the exemplar for the [[United States Air Force Academy]]'s Class of 2006.
*[[National Museum of the United States Air Force]] is located at 1100 Spaatz Street on [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]], Ohio.
* General Spaatz Boulevard is located adjacent to Sarasota-Bradenton International Airport (SRQ) intersecting Tamiami Trail / US 41
* The Outstanding Air Refueling Squadron in the USAF is annually awarded the Gen Carl A. Spaatz trophy

==See also==
{{Portal box|Biography|United States Air Force}}

{{Commons category}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{S-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box|title=Commanding General, [[United States Army Air Forces]]| before= Gen. of the Army [[Henry H. Arnold]]| after=Office abolished, Army Air Forces replaced by [[USAF]] | years=1946&amp;ndash;1947
}}
{{succession box|title = [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force]]| before = New title| after = Gen. [[Hoyt Vandenberg]]| years = 1947&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;1948}}
{{S-end}}
{{CSUSAF}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Spaatz, Carl Andrew
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= [[United States]] [[United States Army|Army]] [[General officer|general]]
|DATE OF BIRTH=June 28, 1891
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Boyertown, Pennsylvania]]
|DATE OF DEATH=July 14, 1974
|PLACE OF DEATH=[[Washington, D.C.]]}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Spaatz, Carl Andrew}}
[[Category:1891 births]]
[[Category:1974 deaths]]
[[Category:Aerial warfare pioneers]]
[[Category:Chiefs of Staff of the United States Air Force]]
[[Category:Members of the Early Birds of Aviation]]
[[Category:National Commanders of the Civil Air Patrol]]
[[Category:Oil Campaign of World War II]]
[[Category:United States Air Force personnel]]
[[Category:United States Army Air Forces pilots of World War II]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:United States Army Command and General Staff College alumni]]
[[Category:Air Corps Tactical School alumni]]
[[Category:United States Army Air Forces generals]]
&lt;!-- Orders and honours : United States --&gt;
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Flying Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Air Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
&lt;!-- Orders and honours --&gt;
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]
[[Category:Honorary Knights Grand Cross of the Order of the British Empire]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of St. Olav]]
[[Category:Grand Croix of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of the Crown (Belgium)‎‎]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (Belgium)]]
[[Category:Commanders with Star of the Order of Polonia Restituta]]
[[Category:Grand Officers of the Order of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Suvorov]]

[[da:Carl Andrew Spaatz]]
[[de:Carl A. Spaatz]]
[[fr:Carl A. Spaatz]]
[[it:Carl Andrew Spaatz]]
[[ja:カール・スパーツ]]
[[pl:Carl Andrew Spaatz]]
[[ru:Спаатс, Карл]]
[[sl:Carl Spaatz]]
[[tr:Carl A. Spaatz]]
[[uk:Карл Спаатс]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
