<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3490131" ns="0" title="Schloss Hartheim"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Alkoven Schloss Hartheim 2005-08-18 3589.jpg|thumb|250px|Hartheim Castle]]
'''Schloss Hartheim''',  located at [[Alkoven]] in [[Upper Austria]], some 14 km. from [[Linz]], [[Austria]], became notorious as one of the [[Nazism|Nazi]] [[Euthanasia]] killing centers, where the killing program [[Action T4]] took place. 

The castle was built by [[Jakob von Aspen]] in 1600. It is one of the most important [[Renaissance]] castles in Austria. 

In 1898, Prince [[Camillo Heinrich Starhemberg]] (1835 - 1900) donated the castle as a gift to the Upper Austria Charity Organization. With the help of additional donations, they used the castle from the beginning of the 20th century as a psychiatric institution (German: ''Psychiatrische Anstalt'', but originally called the ''Idioten-Anstalt'').

== History to 1940 ==
[[File:Hartheim 1898.jpg|thumb|Tablet commemorating its gifting to the OÖ Landeswohltätigkeitsverein in 1898]]
Hartheim lies in the middle of the so-called [[Eferding Basin]], that runs along the [[River Danube]] from [[Ottensheim]] to [[Aschach an der Donau]]. As early as 1130 a family with the name Hartheim is mentioned in the records. They were vassals of the [[bishops of Passau]]. In 1287 three brothers, Conrad, Peter and Henry of Hartheim, were named as owners of the castle as part of a barter arrangement with the [[Wilhering Abbey]]. In any case by 1323 another family was named as the owners. Until the middle of the 14th century the site consisted mainly of just one tower, subsequently a residence was added and it was surrounded by a small wall with ramparts and ditches.

After changing hands several times the castle ended up in the possession of the Aspan family, who probably built the castle into its present shape. At the beginning of the 1690s they had a completely new castle built conforming to perceptions of the ideal [[Renaissance]] style with a regular four-winged building with four polygonal corner towers and a higher central tower. 

In 1799 [[George Adam of Starhemberg|George Adam, Prince of Starhemberg]], purchased the castle. But by 1862 the castle was in a rather poor condition, as a contemporary report describes: 
''Doors, windows and ovens are entirely missing, ... and several ceilings must be replaced''. 

In 1898 Camillo Henry, Prince of Starhemberg, made a present of the castle building, the outbuildings and some land to the Upper Austrian State Welfare Society (''Oberösterreichischen Landeswohltätigkeitsverein'' or ''OÖ. LWV''). It was intended to use further donation to convert the building into an &quot;Idiot's Institute&quot; as it was described at the time. In addition between 1900 and 1910 major renovation and conversion work was carried out to enable the building to be used as a care home for mentally handicapped people. In 1926 a staircase was dismantled and replaced by a bed lift.

== Nazi era ==
{{main|Hartheim Euthanasia Centre}}
Following Hitler's euthanasia decree in 1939, Hartheim  was selected as one of six euthanasia centres in the Reich. Between May 1940 and December 1944, approximately 18,000 people physically and mentally disabled were killed at Schloss Hartheim by [[Gas chamber|gassing]] and [[lethal injection]] as part of the [[Action T4|T-4 Euthanasia Program]], named after the infamous Berlin address &quot;Tiergartenstrasse 4&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Klee: ''Dokumente zur Euthanasie'', p.&amp;nbsp;232&amp;nbsp;f.&lt;/ref&gt; These included about twelve thousand prisoners from the [[Dachau concentration camp|Dachau]] and [[Mauthausen-Gusen concentration camp|Mauthausen]] concentration camps who were sent here to be gassed.&lt;ref&gt;Klee: ''Euthanasie im Dritten Reich'', p.&amp;nbsp;290.&lt;/ref&gt; The castle was regularly visited by the psychiatrists [[Karl Brandt (physician)|Karl Brandt]], Professor of Psychiatry at [[Würzburg University]], and [[Werner Heyde]]. 

After World War II, the building was converted into apartments. Beginning in 1969, the gas chamber was opened to visitors. Hartheim Castle is now a Memorial Site dedicated to the thousands of physically and mentally handicapped persons who were murdered here by the Nazis.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.schloss-hartheim.at/index.asp?Seite=441&amp;Lg=2 Schloss Hartheim memorial and documentation center] Official website. Retrieved May 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt; 

In 1946, Countess [[Alice Ricciardi-von Platen]] (28 April 1910 in [[Wangels|Weissenhaus]] -  23 February 2008 in [[Cortona]], [[Italy]]), a psychiatrist who practised near [[Linz]], [[Austria]], was invited to join the German team observing the so-called [[Doctors Trial]] in [[Nuremberg]]. The trial was presided over by American judges, who indicted [[Karl Brandt (physician)|Karl Brandt]] and 22 others. The 16 who were convicted included Dr. [[Josef Mengele]]; seven were sentenced to death. Her 1948 book, ''Die Tötung Geisteskranker in Deutschland'', (&quot;The killing of the mentally ill in Germany&quot;), was judged a scandal by German medical professionals.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article3752671.ece Alice Ricciardi-von Platen obituary] ''The Times'' online. (April 15, 2008) Retrieved May 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Paul Weindling, [http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/mar/13/secondworldwar.germany Alice Ricciardi-von Platen obituary] ''The Guardian'' (March 13, 2008) Retrieved May 17, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Nazi Euthanasia Programme]] - Action T4
* [[Action 14f13]]

== Further reading ==
* Angela Gluck Wood, [http://www.scribd.com/doc/19898262/Holocaust ''Holocaust - the events and their impact on real people''] Foreword by [[Steven Spielberg]]. Lots of photos. DK Publishing (2007) ISBN&amp;nbsp;978-0-75662-535-1

== Sources ==
* Pierre Serge Choumoff, ''Les Assassinats Nationaux-Socialistes par Gaz en Territoire Autrichien'', Vienna, Bundesministerium für Inneres, 2000, ISBN 978-3-9500867-1-3
* [http://www.palgrave.com/PDFs/140393911X.Pdf ''Nazi Medicine and the Nuremburg Trials''] (PDF) Table of contents, introduction and index only.
* [http://www.storiaxxisecolo.it/deportazione/T4%20TESTO.doc Eutanasia, le radici dello sterminio] {{it icon}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.scrapbookpages.com/Hartheim/Tour05.html Photos of Hartheim Castle]

{{coord|48|16|52|N|14|06|50|E|region:AT-4_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:Castles in Austria]]

[[ca:Castell de Hartheim]]
[[de:Schloss Hartheim]]
[[el:Σλος Χάρτχαϊμ]]
[[es:Castillo de Hartheim]]
[[fr:Schloss Hartheim]]
[[id:Schloss Hartheim]]
[[it:Castello di Hartheim]]
[[pl: Hartheim_(Alkoven)]]
[[pt:Castelo de Hartheim]]
[[sv:Hartheim]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
