<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3501164" ns="0" title="Cain Dingle"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox soap character 2 |series=Emmerdale
|image=[[File:Cain Dingle.jpg|200px]]
|caption=Cain Dingle in 2009
|name= Cain Dingle
|portrayer=[[Jeff Hordley]]
|introducer= Kieran Roberts (2000)&lt;br&gt;[[Anita Turner]] (2009)
|first=30 March 2000
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present characters|Present; regular]]
|spinoffs= ''Emmerdale: The Dingles, For Richer for Poorer (2010)
|years= 2000–06, 2009—
|born = 30 November 1974
|family=[[Dingle family|Dingle]]
|occupation={{nowrap|[[Mechanic]] (2000–06, since 2009)&lt;br /&gt;[[Businessperson|Businessman]] (2006–09)}}
|home=Tug Ghyll|
|father = [[Zak Dingle]]
|mother= [[Faith Dingle]] 
|halfbrothers = Nathan Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Ben Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Butch Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Sam Dingle]]
|halfsisters = Tina Dingle&lt;br&gt;[[Chastity Dingle|Chas Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Belle Dingle]] 
|daughters = [[Debbie Dingle]] 
|sons = Kyle
|granddaughters = Sarah Sugden
|nephews = [[Aaron Livesy]]&lt;br&gt;[[Samson Dingle]]
|uncles = [[Shadrach Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Albert Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Caleb Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ezra Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;Zebediah Dingle&lt;br&gt;Moses Dingle
|grandfathers = [[Jedediah Dingle]]
|grandmothers = [[Peg Dingle]]
|cousins =[[Marlon Dingle]] &lt;br&gt;[[Eli Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;Mandy Dingle &lt;br&gt;[[Lilith Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Delilah Dingle]]&lt;br&gt;[[Genesis Walker|Gennie Walker]]}}

'''Cain Dingle''' is a [[fictional character]] in the British [[ITV]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[Jeff Hordley]]. 

==Creation and casting==
In 2000 series producer Kieran Roberts introduced three new members of the [[Dingle family]]. The new characters were introduced to the regular cast in 2000, who first arrived at the funeral of [[Butch Dingle]] ([[Paul Loughran]]). Among them were Cain ([[Jeff Hordley]]) son of [[Zak Dingle]] ([[Steve Halliwell]]) and [[Faith Dingle]] (Gillian Jephcott). Cain's cousin and one-time lover [[Charity Dingle]] ([[Emma Atkins]]), and Zak's brother [[Shadrach Dingle|Shadrach]] ([[Andy Devine (English actor)|Andy Devine]]). &lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|url=http://www.emmerdale.org/emmerdale/dingles/cain/cain.htm|title=Emmerdale's Cain Dingle|publisher=Emmerdale Org|author=Emmerdale Org|date=3 April 2004|accessdate=25 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April 2006 it was announced that Jeff Hordley had quit, however the door had been left open for a possible return in the future. Cain's final scenes aired in September 2006. His storyline saw Cain bow out of the serial drama following the character's successful kidnap and extortion plot involving [[Tom King (Emmerdale)|Tom King]] ([[Ken Farrington]]) and [[Sadie King]] ([[Patsy Kensit]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{citenews|last=Green|first=Kris|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a31731/jeff-hordley-quits-emmerdale.html|title=Jeff Hordley quits 'Emmerdale'|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=18 April 2006|accessdate=25 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 2009 it was announced that Cain Dingle would return to Emmerdale in April that year after a three-year break, his return storyline saw him support and help his daughter, [[Debbie Dingle]] ([[Charley Webb]]) who was being held on remand for the murder of PC [[Shane Doyle]] ([[Paul McEwan]]).&lt;ref name=quit&gt;{{citenews|last=Green|first=Kris |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a141846/cain-dingle-returns-to-emmerdale.html|title=Cain Dingle returns to 'Emmerdale'|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=12 January 2009|accessdate=25 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Speaking to [[Digital Spy]] about his return, Hordley said &quot;I am really looking forward to returning to Emmerdale. The storylines that lead to Cain’s return are in keeping with his character and a perfect way to bring him back to the heart of the Dingle clan where he belongs&quot;.

==Development==
===Characterisation===
{{cquote|Cain is a master criminal and the bad boy of the village. He's been involved in many scams (mostly involving money) and been to jail on more than one occasion, however, he's not evil to the core and has developed a conscience in recent years. Despite his difficult relationship with his daughter Debbie, he would do anything for her.|4=''[[itv.com]] on Cain''.&lt;ref name=itv&gt;{{cite web|title=Cain Dingle|url=http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/cain-dingle/|work=''[[itv.com]]''|publisher=([[ITV plc]])|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
The character was labelled a &quot;ruthless hard man&quot;, a &quot;bad boy&quot; and a &quot;villain&quot; by ''Digital Spy''.&lt;ref name=quit /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=Cain Dingle returns to 'Emmerdale'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a141846/cain-dingle-returns-to-emmerdale.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=12 January 2009|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ds&gt;{{cite web|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|title=Corrie actress worries about receiving abuse|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s3/coronation-street/news/a68387/corrie-actress-worries-about-receiving-abuse.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=29 July 2007|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Itv.com also described Cain as the &quot;village pariah&quot; and commented that he likes &quot;being in charge&quot; but dislikes &quot;being made a fool of&quot;.&lt;ref name=itv /&gt; [[What's on TV]] described him as saying&quot; &quot;a villain through and through, Cain Dingle will even cross his own family if it's worth his while!&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Home Soaps Emmerdale Who's Who Cain Dingle|url=http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/cain-dingle/1017|work=[[What's on TV]]|publisher=[[IPC Media]]|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; When casting a new family for the serial one character specification casting a similar character to Cain described Cain's earlier tenure saying: &quot;much in the early Cain Dingle mould, ruthless, unscrupulous, and extremely promiscuous&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title='Emmerdale' in hunt for new 'bad boy' |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a147206/emmerdale-in-hunt-for-new-bad-boy.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=19 February 2009|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Who attacked Cain===
In 2011, it was announced that Cain would become part of a &quot;major&quot; storyline where he is attacked by a &quot;mystery&quot; assailant. The storyline developed after Cain had made several enemies throughout the year and forced one of his enemies to &quot;take the ultimate revenge&quot;.&lt;ref name=who/&gt; Producers stylised the plot as a &quot;[[whodunit|whodunit storyline]]&quot; which will keep viewers guessing as to whom attacks Cain. The potential attackers were revealed to be [[John Barton (Emmerdale)|John Barton]] ([[James Thornton (actor)|James Thornton]]), [[Moira Barton]] ([[Natalie J Robb]]), [[Jai Sharma]] ([[Chris Bisson]]), [[Amy Wyatt]] (Chelsea Halfpenny), Zak and Charity.&lt;ref name=who/&gt; A spokesperson for the serial stated that the characters had become &quot;sworn enemies&quot; of Cain, all &quot;all pushed to the limit after months of manipulation and destruction&quot;. While ''Emmerdale's'' executive producer Stuart Blackburn said that the climax of Cain's actions &quot;will be one of our most dramatic episodes this year&quot; as veiwers decide who took &quot;matters into their own hands&quot;.&lt;ref name=who&gt;{{cite web|last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|title='Emmerdale' announces shock whodunit storyline|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/news/a351288/emmerdale-announces-shock-whodunit-storyline.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hearst Magazines UK]])|accessdate=17 November 2011|date=17 November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Storylines==
===2000–06===
[[File:EarlyCainDingle.jpg|150px|thumb|left|Cain Dingle as he appeared in 2000.]]
Cain arrives for his cousin [[Butch Dingle]]'s funeral and takes an dislike to [[Chris Tate]] who he feels is responsible for Butch's death and policewoman [[Angie Reynolds]]. He speds months letting Angie's daughter Ollie believe he fancies her but shows his true colours by making a play for Angie. Angie is horrified but can't deny the sparks between them and after a year of flirting, they begin an affair. Cain causes havoc when Angi ends the relationship by sleeping with Ollie, pushing [[Len Reynolds]] down a flight of stairs and causing Angie to loose her job. Cain and Angie plan to rob a Tate Haulage truck and escape together but Angie sets Cain up to get him out of her life permanently. Angie's car crashs and she sustains fatal injuries. Cain begs her to say she loves him but she says she loves her children before dying, leaving Cain distraught. As a teenager, Cain had a brief relationship with his cousin Charity and when Charity arrives in Emmerdale, Cain begins causing trouble for her. On hearing she is dating [[Chris Tate]], Cain hits her. After [[Paddy Kirk|Paddy]] and [[Emily Kirk]] foster [[Debbie Dingle|Debbie Jones]], she makes friends with the Dingles. She shows Cain a picture of her biological mother and when he sees Sam looking at old family pictures he realises Charity is her mother. Cain's stepfather, [[Shadrach Dingle]], compares Debbie to Cain at the same age, making Cain realise he is Debbie's father. Cain grabs the opportunity to blackmail Charity, hreatening to tell Chris but Charity tells him first. 

Cain and Debbie become close. Cain and Charity begin having an affair. Chris realises what is happening and on discovering he had a fatal [[brain tumour]], framed Charity for his murder. Cain is there when Chris dies and runs away with Debbie but returns to clear his name. With Charity in gaol, they declared their love and planned to stay together. On her release, Charity couldn't live with Cain and they soon split up. [[Tom King]] and Charity become engaged. [[Sadie King]] hires Cain to ruin Tom and Charity's wedding. Sadia and Cain make it seem as though Cain and Charity are having an affair, including Cain having a picture taken when he took Charity by surprise and kissed her. Charity clears her name and leaves the village. Sadie and Cain spend the night together and after Sadie rejects him, Cain kills her dog, Damon. Cain and Debbie move in to Butler's Farm with [[Andy Sugden]]. 

Debbie has a brief relationship with Andy and falls pregnant. Cain and the Dingles discover Debbie had a daughter, [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2005)#Sarah Sugden|Sarah]] and are overjoyed. Cain becomes close to baby Sarah. Debbie makes it clear that she doesn't want to be a mother. Cain pressures her to face up to her responsibilities so she becomes desperate and persuades Emily to take Sarah with her when she leaves the village, angering the Dingles. Cain begins acting nastily towars Debbie. Debbie moves in with [[Ashley Thomas]]. Debbie bonds with Ashley's niece, [[Jasmine Thomas]] and they have a brief relationship which Cain ends by seducing Jasmine and making sure Debbie finds them together. Debbie vows revenge on Cain. Debbie cuts her ties Cain and Jasmine. She and Jasmine reconcile when Jasmine tells her that she was pregnant and wanted an abortion. Cain is thrilled at the prospect of becoming a father again. Sadie discovers this and decides to pay for Jasmine to have a private abortion as revenge for Cain killing her dog. Cain searchs for Jasmine but she has the abortion before he can try to speak to her.

Cain and Sadie damage the King's River Show Home. Sadie refuses to sleep with Cain, infuriating him so he tells Jimmy that Sadie had paid him to trash the house and claimed they were having an affair. He and Jimmy plan to set her up. When Sadie confronts him, Cain said he would tell Matthew, that they were having an affair. Sadie hit back by telling Ashley that Cain was sleeping with Jasmine, resulting in the Dingles throwing Cain out and letting Debbie move back in. Cain leaves the village temporarily. The damage caused by Cain to the show house had damaged the gas pipes. Jimmy had them patched up, meaning to do a proper job later. Unfortunately gas built up in a cupboard and when sparked by an automatic light switch, the show house exploded, causing the deaths of [[Dawn Woods]], [[Noreen Bell]] and [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2006)#David Brown|David Brown]]. Cain and Jimmy feel guilty for their part in the showhome explosion but Sadie showed no remorse. Feeling the need to be punished for what he'd done, he confessed to murdering his late sister-in-law, Alice, so Samson wouldn't lose both his parents. This act redeemed him with his family, even Debbie. He was bailed by Sadie, who sent money to Wishing Well cottage, which Zak and Shadrach surrendered at the hearing. Out on bail, Cain agrees to help Sadie get revenge on [[Tom King|Tom]] and [[Matthew King]]. After learning the King's were millionaires, Cain and Sadie plotted to [[Major Storylines of Emmerdale#Tom King.2C Cain Dingle and Sadie King Kidnap Plot 2006|kidnap Tom]] for a large ransom. Sadie knew nobody would believe Cain was capable of murder so they planned to fake her death so Tom would co-operate. However, things didn't go to plan. Debbie tells Cain that Sadie had paid for Jasmine's abortion, leaving Cain furious. After a violent confrontation with Sadie, Cain follows her to the meeting place. As Sadie and Tom discussed the house collapse, Cain kidnaps them. Cain returns to the village and is confronted by [[Chastity Dingle|Chastity]]. Cain denied knowing anything about Tom and Sadie's disappearance and left. The police begin closing in on his hideout, Cain took them to an abandoned factory and switched cars. The police followed him to a quarry where Cain sidetracked them by sending his empty car over a cliff, making everyone think Tom and Sadie were inside. While the police searched the lake, Cain assaulted two policemen and disguised himself in a police uniform. After shooting Sadie, Cain forces Tom to phone Chastity to deliver the ransom. Debbie begs her father to take her with him, even suggesting she get Sarah back but they part in tears. Cain gave some of the ransom to an old lady, asking her to post it to Debbie. Cain was surprised by her honesty and realised he wanted to change. At the airport, Cain got into the plane alone, telling Sadie that he didn't want to be the same person he'd always been. Cain leaves Debbie a message on her voicemail, telling her to ignore what the others said, that he had left Sadie and that he loved Debbie more than he'd shown. On Debbie's 18th, he sends her an expensive silver watch.

===2009—===
In February 2009, Cain was arrested on his return to the country. He was attempting to return to support and help Debbie, who was being held on remand for the murder of PC [[Shane Doyle]]. He hires a lawyer who specialises in self-defence cases to help Debbie, paying him in advance.
Cain returned on 28 April and they immediately went up to Butler's Farm. Debbie told him that Andy was refusing her access to Sarah. The same day, [[Jimmy King (Emmerdale)|Jimmy King]] and [[Carl King]] demanded their money back before beating Cain up when he refuses. He supports Debbie through her custody battle, which she eventually wins. He begins flirting with [[Maisie Wylde]], whose parents [[Mark Wylde|Mark]] and [[Natasha Wylde|Natasha]], take an instant dislike to Cain. After a brief relationship with Maisie, Cain flirts with [[Faye Lamb]].

Cain takes a dislike to Debbie's new boyfriend, Michael. Michael admits that he is getting married to his pregnant fiancee. Cain and Debbie [[Wedding crashing|crashed the wedding]] and were shocked to discover that his fiancée was Charity Tate. Michael calls the wedding off, after discovering that Charity had lied about being pregnant. Debbie invites Charity to stay with her, despite Cain's protests. She and Carl King plan to rob Cain's money. Cain and Debbie catch Charity in the act and refuse to believe her when she said she was replacing it. Cain threw her and [[Noah Tate|Noah]] out. He gives her the money she had been about to steal and before leaving the village. He returns on December 22nd with presents for Debbie and Sarah. He and Charity reconcile on Christmas Day. Charity proposes and Cain accepts. Cain learns Shadrach who he believes to be his father has died. Cain discovers Mark Wylde's wallet in the woods. Mark had been shot and killed by his wife Natasha, which Cain was unaware of. Cain blackmails Natasha and Nathan into paying him to keep quiet about the wallet as he thinks there is something sinister behind Mark's disappearance, however when Sam's dog Alfie digs up the body Nathan sets up his half-brother and Cain's mechanic [[Ryan Lamb]] for Mark's murder and he is subsequently charged with murdering Mark. Cain tells Maisie he had blackmailed Nathan and Natasha and they had paid him to keep quiet. Cain can't help Ryan without incriminating himself for fraud and blackmail. He attends Ryan's trial and after witnessing Nathans lie in the witness box he decided to take action. After making sure that Sam keeps quiet about the wallet during his witness testimony, Cain kidnaps Nathan. Cain holds him hostage in a disused barn. He threatens to kill Nathan if Ryan if foung guilty. Ryan is found guilty of the murder and Natasha soon after confessed. 

In April 2011 Cain, on the rebound after [[Charity Tate]] makes it clear that she has moved on and their relationship is over, has a [[one-night stand]] with troubled teenager [[Amy Wyatt]]. Cain immediately regrets it and rejects Amy the following day. However his troubles are far from over when Amy announces that she is pregnant with his child in August 2011. Cain bullies her into having an [[abortion]] but at the last minute Amy backs out of the termination and decides to keep her pregnancy a secret, lying that she went ahead with the procedure. Cain makes an enemy out of the Barton family, after having a passionate fling with [[Moira Barton]] and then revealing all to her devastated husband [[John Barton]] the following day. Amy later gives birth to their son Kyle alone in the graveyard in December 2011 and believing him to be dead, she panics and places him in the phonebox where he is discovered by [[Hazel Rhodes]]. Hazel, along with Cain's stepmother Lisa, brings the boy back to life and later Amy comes forward as his mother, leaving Cain to realise that she had lied to him and not gone ahead with the abortion.

==Reception==
At the 2002 [[British Soap Awards]] Hordley was nominated for &quot;Sexiest Male&quot; and &quot;Villian of the Year&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Welsh|first=James|title=British Soap Awards 2002: Nominations|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/feature/a7412/british-soap-awards-2002-nominations.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=16 May 2002|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the 2007 British Soap Awards Hordley was nominated for &quot;Sexiest Male&quot;, &quot;Villian of the Year&quot; and &quot;Best Exit&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=The British Soap Awards 2007: The Winners|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a58280/the-british-soap-awards-2007-the-winners.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=27 May 2007|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; For his portrayal of Cain, Hordley was nominated in the category of &quot;Villan of the Year&quot; at the 2011 [[Inside Soap Awards]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Kilkelly|first=Daniel|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a307476/british-soap-awards-2011-voting-opens.html|title=British Soap Awards 2011 voting opens|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=7 March 2011|accessdate=7 March 2011&lt;!-- |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5x0jSLWib|archivedate=7 March 2011 --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hordley was nominated in the category of &quot;Serial Drama Performance&quot; at the 2012 [[National Television Awards]], for his portrayal of Cain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wightman|first=Catriona|title=National Television Awards 2012: The nominees|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/tv/news/a342357/national-television-awards-2012-the-nominees.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=([[Hachette Filipacchi UK]])|accessdate=27 September 2011|date=27 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a poll to find the &quot;most kissable soap stud&quot; run by dating agency Dating Direct, Hordley came 6th with 1% of the vote.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Wilkes|first=Neil |title=Corrie's Charlie is 'most kissable soap stud'|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/news/a17829/corries-charlie-is-most-kissable-soap-stud.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=22 December 2004|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Digital Spy reported that Hordley received a mainly positive reaction for his role.&lt;Ref name=ds /&gt; [[Tom Lister]] who plays Tom King said Cain is a &quot;great character&quot; adding that it was a &quot;coup to get Jeff back&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris|title=Carl King on Tom's murder and Cain's return|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/s12/emmerdale/scoop/a144562/carl-king-on-toms-murder-and-cains-return.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=27 January 2009|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lucy Pargeter]] who plays Chas said commented on Hordley's return saying &quot;I really hope that they get us together and give us a storyline which highlights the strength between them&quot; before adding that Hordley is &quot;amazing and everyone's so excited that he's coming back&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Green|first=Kris |title='Emmerdale's Chas on Lexi, Aaron and Cain|url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/soaps/scoop/a150441/emmerdales-chas-on-lexi-aaron-and-cain.html|work=[[Digital Spy]]|publisher=[[Hachette Filipacchi UK]]|date=24 May 2009|accessdate=3 December 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/emmerdale/characters/cain-dingle/ Cain Dingle] at [[Itv.com]]
*[http://www.whatsontv.co.uk/soaps/emmerdale/whos-who/cain-dingle/1017 Cain Dingle] at [[What's on TV]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Emmerdale characters}}
{{EDDingles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dingle, Cain}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional businesspeople]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 2000]]
[[Category:Fictional criminals]]
[[Category:Fictional mechanics]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
