<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="350913" ns="0" title="Maxwell D. Taylor"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other persons|Max Taylor}}
{{Cleanup|date=September 2010}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Maxwell Davenport Taylor
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1901|8|26}}
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1987|4|19|1901|8|26}}
|birth_place=[[Keytesville, Missouri]]
|death_place=[[Washington, D.C.]]
|placeofburial= [[Arlington National Cemetery]]
|image=[[File:Maxwell D Taylor official portrait.jpg|250px]]
|caption=General Maxwell Taylor Portrait
|nickname=Max
|allegiance= [[United States of America]]
|branch=[[United States Army]]
|serviceyears=1922&amp;ndash;1964
|rank= [[File:US-O10 insignia.svg|35px]] [[General (United States)|General]]
|commands=
[[101st Airborne Division (United States)|101st Airborne Division]]&lt;br/&gt;Superintendent of the U.S. Military Academy&lt;br/&gt;Chief of Staff, U.S. Army&lt;br/&gt;[[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
|unit=
|battles=[[World War II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Korean War]]
|awards=[[File:Distinguished Service Cross ribbon.svg|30px]] [[Distinguished Service Cross (United States)|Distinguished Service Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Service Medal (United States)|Distinguished Service Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Silver Star ribbon.svg|30px]] [[Silver Star]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Legion of Merit ribbon.svg|30px]] [[Legion of Merit]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Bronze Star ribbon.svg|30px]] [[Bronze Star Medal|Bronze Star]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Purple Heart BAR.svg|30px]] [[Purple Heart]]
|relations=
|laterwork=Ambassador to South Vietnam (1964-65)
}}
General '''Maxwell Davenport &quot;Max&quot; Taylor''' (August 26, 1901 &amp;ndash; April 19, 1987) was an [[United States Army]] [[Four-star rank|four star]] [[General (United States)|general]] and [[diplomat]] of the mid-20th century, who served as the fifth [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] after having been appointed by the [[President of the United States]] [[John F. Kennedy]].


== Early Life ==
Taylor was born in [[Keytesville]], [[Missouri]] and graduated from the [[United States Military Academy]] in 1922.

==World War II==
Taylor's rise to the highest echelons of U.S. government began under the tutelage of General [[Matthew B. Ridgway]] in the US Army's [[U.S. 82nd Airborne Division|82nd Airborne Division]] when Ridgway commanded the division in the early part of [[World War II]].  In 1943, Taylor's diplomatic and language skills resulted in his secret mission to Rome to coordinate an 82nd air drop with Italian forces. General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] would later say that &quot;the risks he ran were greater than I asked any other agent or emissary to take during the war.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;taylorobit&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1987/04/21/obituaries/maxwell-d-taylor-soldier-and-envoy-dies.html|title=Maxwell D. Taylor, Soldier and Envoy, Dies|last=Krebs|first=Albin|date=1987-04-21|work=The New York Times|accessdate=2009-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Hundreds of miles behind the front lines of battle, Taylor was forced by rules of engagement to wear his American military uniform, so that if captured he could not be shot as a spy. He met with the new Italian Prime Minister, Marshal [[Pietro Badoglio]] and general [[Giacomo Carboni|Carboni]]. The air drop near Rome to capture the city was called off at the last minute, when Taylor realized that it was too late. German forces were already moving in to cover the intended drop zones.  Transport planes were already in the air when Taylor's message canceled the drop, preventing the suicide mission.  These efforts behind enemy lines got Taylor noticed at the highest levels of the Allied command.

After the campaigns in the Mediterranean, Taylor was assigned to command the [[101st Airborne Division]], which was training in England, after the 101st's first commander [[William C. Lee|Major General Bill Lee]] suffered a heart attack.

Taylor jumped into [[Normandy]] on June 6, 1944, with his men. He was the first Allied general to land in France on D-Day.  He commanded the 101st Airborne Division for the rest of the war, among other things during [[Operation Market Garden]] in The Netherlands, but missed out leading the division during its most famous conflict, the [[Battle of Bastogne]] during the [[Battle of the Bulge]], because he was attending a staff conference in the United States.  The Division Artillery commander, Brig. Gen. [[Anthony McAuliffe]] exercised command in his absence.  Some of the [[paratroopers]] resented Taylor for this later.  General Taylor called the defense of Bastogne the 101st Airborne Division's &quot;finest hour&quot; of the war and stated that his absence there was one of his greatest disappointments in World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|author=Cole C. Kingseed |title=An American Soldier: the Wars of General Maxwell Taylor - Book Review'|publisher=”Infantry Magazine''|date=Fall 2003, http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0IAV/is_1_92/ai_114049389}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==After World War II==
[[File:TheCadetHonorCodeMonument.jpg|thumb|left|Honor Monument at West Point]]
From 1945 to 1949 Taylor was [[Superintendents of the United States Military Academy|superintendent]] of [[West Point]]. In 1947, he drafted the first official Honor Code publication marking the beginning of the written “[[Cadet Honor Code]]” at West Point.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usma.edu/PublicAffairs/PressReleasesbd/nr14-08_brigade_honor_cpt.htm West Point&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;  Afterwards he was the commander of allied troops in [[Berlin]] from 1949 to 1951.

In 1953, he was sent to the [[Korean War]]. From 1955 to 1959, he was the [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]], succeeding his former mentor, [[Matthew Ridgway|Matthew B. Ridgway]].  During his tenure as Army Chief of Staff, Taylor attempted to guide the service into the age of nuclear weapons by restructuring the infantry division.  Observers such as [[Colonel]] [[David Hackworth]] have written that the effort gutted the role of US Army company and field grade officers, rendering it unable to adapt to the dynamics of combat in Vietnam.

During 1957, President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] ordered General Taylor to deploy 1,000 troops from the [[101st Airborne Division]] to [[Little Rock, Arkansas]] to enforce Federal court orders to desegregate [[Central High School (Little Rock)|Central High School]] during the [[Little Rock Crisis]].

As Army Chief of Staff, Taylor was an outspoken critic of the Eisenhower Administration's [[New Look (policy)|&quot;New Look&quot;]] defense policy, which he viewed as dangerously over-reliant on nuclear arms and neglectful of conventional forces; he also criticized the inadequacies of the Joint Chiefs of Staff system.  Frustrated with the administration's failure to heed his arguments, General Taylor retired from active service in July 1959.  He campaigned publicly against the &quot;New Look,&quot; culminating in the publication in January 1960 of a highly critical book entitled &quot;The Uncertain Trumpet.&quot;

==Return to duty==
{{Refimprove|date=June 2008}}
As the 1960 presidential campaign unfolded, Democratic nominee [[John F. Kennedy]] criticized Eisenhower's defense policy and championed a muscular &quot;[[flexible response]]&quot; policy intentionally aligned with Taylor's views as described in &quot;The Uncertain Trumpet.&quot;  After the April 1961 failure of the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]], Kennedy, who felt the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]] had failed to provide him with satisfactory military advice, appointed Taylor to head a task force to investigate the failure of the invasion.

Both President Kennedy and his brother, Attorney General [[Robert F. Kennedy]], had immense regard for Taylor, whom they saw as a man of unquestionable integrity, sincerity, intelligence, and diplomacy.{{Citation needed|date=June 2008}} The Cuba Study Group met for six weeks from April to May 1961 to perform an &quot;autopsy&quot; on the disastrous events surrounding the [[Bay of Pigs Invasion]]. In the course of their work together, Taylor developed a deep regard and a personal affection for [[Robert F. Kennedy]], a friendship that was wholly mutual and which remained firm until RFK's assassination in 1968.

Taylor spoke of Robert Kennedy glowingly: &quot;He is always on the lookout for a 'snow job,' impatient with evasion and imprecision, and relentless in his determination to get at the truth.&quot; Robert Kennedy named one of his sons [[Matthew Maxwell Taylor Kennedy]] (better known as an adult as &quot;Max&quot;).

Shortly after the investigation concluded, the Kennedys' warm feelings for Taylor and the President's lack of confidence in the Joint Chiefs of Staff led John Kennedy to recall Taylor to active duty and install him in the newly created post of military representative to the president.  His close personal relationship with the President and White House access effectively made Taylor the President's primary military adviser, cutting out the Joint Chiefs. On October 1, 1962, Kennedy ended this uncomfortable arrangement by appointing Taylor as [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]], a position in which he served until 1964.

==The Vietnam War==

{{See also|1963 South Vietnamese coup|Arrest and assassination of Ngo Dinh Diem|Reaction to the 1963 South Vietnamese coup|Cable 243|Buddhist crisis|Krulak Mendenhall mission|McNamara Taylor mission}}
Taylor was of crucial importance during the first weeks and months of the [[Vietnam War]]. Whereas initially President Kennedy had told Taylor that &quot;the independence of South Vietnam rests with the people and government of that country,&quot; Taylor was soon to recommend that 8,000 American combat troops be sent to the region at once. After making his report to the Cabinet and the Chiefs of Staff, Taylor was to reflect on the decision to send troops to South Vietnam: &quot;I don't recall anyone who was strongly against, except one man, and that was the President. The President just didn't want to be convinced that this was the right thing to do.... It was really the President's personal conviction that U.S. ground troops shouldn't go in.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Schlesinger, Robert Kennedy: His Life and Times&lt;/ref&gt;

Taylor opposed the [[1963 South Vietnamese coup]] that overthrew and killed President [[Ngo Dinh Diem]].
{{Main|1964 South Vietnamese coup|September 1964 South Vietnamese coup attempt|December 1964 South Vietnamese coup|1965 South Vietnamese coup}}
A series of short-lived juntas followed, and after Taylor was made ambassador in 1964, he frequently clashed with General [[Nguyen Khanh]] and helped to engineer his removal, having supported Khanh's deposal of General [[Duong Van Minh]].

==Criticisms==
Taylor received fierce criticism in Maj. (now BG) [[H.R. McMaster]]'s book ''Dereliction of Duty.''  Specifically, Gen. Taylor was accused of intentionally misrepresenting the views of the Joint Chiefs to [[Robert McNamara|Secretary of Defense McNamara]], and cutting the Joint Chiefs out of the decision-making process.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Dereliction of duty: Lyndon Johnson, Robert McNamara, the Joint Chiefs of Staff, and the lies that led to Vietnam
 |last=McMaster |first=H. R. |authorlink= |edition=Reprint, illustrated|year=1998 |publisher=HarperPerennial |location= |isbn=9780060929084 |page=63 |pages=480 |url=http://books.google.co.in/books?id=igxF_GoEptQC |accessdate=25 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Whereas the Chiefs felt that it was their duty to offer unqualified assessments and recommendations on military matters, Gen. Taylor was of the firm belief that the chairman should not only support the president's decisions but also be a true believer in them.  This discrepancy manifested itself during the early planning phases of the war, while it was still being decided what the nature of American involvement should be. McNamara and the civilians of the office of the secretary of defense were firmly behind the idea of graduated pressure—that is, to escalate pressure slowly against North Vietnam in order to demonstrate U.S. resolve. The Joint Chiefs, however, strenuously disagreed with this and believed that if the US got involved further in Vietnam, it should be with the clear intention of winning and through the use of overwhelming force.  McMaster contends that using a variety of political maneuvering, including liberal use of outright deception, Gen. Taylor succeeded in keeping the Joint Chiefs' opinions away from the President and helped set the stage for McNamara to begin to dominate systematically the U.S. decision making process on Vietnam.

==Second retirement==
He again retired and became [[United States Ambassador to South Vietnam|Ambassador to South Vietnam]] from 1964 to 1965, succeeding [[Henry Cabot Lodge Jr.]]  He was Special Consultant to the President and Chairman of the [[President's Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board|Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board]] (1965–1969) and President of the [[Institute for Defense Analyses]] (1966–1969).

General Taylor died in [[Washington, D.C.]] on April 19, 1987, of [[ALS]].  He was interred at [[Arlington National Cemetery]].

==Dramatic portrayals==
*Taylor was portrayed by [[Paul Maxwell]] in ''[[A Bridge Too Far (film)|A Bridge Too Far]]'', [[Andrew Duggan]] in [[The Missiles of October]] and by [[Bill Smitrovich]] in ''[[Thirteen Days (film)|Thirteen Days]]''.

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Army}}
*[[The Best and the Brightest]]
{{Clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*For Bay of Pigs and Vietnam War material - &quot;Robert F. Kennedy and His Times&quot;, Arthur M. Schlesinger, Jr.

*&quot;The Chairmanship of the Joint Chiefs of Staff.&quot;  Ronald H. Cole, Lorna S. Jaffe, Walter S. Poole, Willard J. Webb.  Joint History Office, Office of the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 1995.  Section II, pp.&amp;nbsp;77–84. http://www.dtic.mil/doctrine/jel/history/jcspart2.pdf

*&quot;An American Soldier: the Wars of General Maxwell Taylor&quot; John M. Taylor, Presidio Press, 1989

==External links==
*[http://www.history.army.mil/books/cg&amp;csa/Taylor-MD.htm General Maxwell Taylor, Official Army Bio] in '''Commanding Generals and Chiefs of Staff''' a publication of the [[United States Army Center of Military History]]
*[http://www.jcs.mil/cjs/history_files/bios/taylor_bio.pdf General Maxwell Taylor, Official Joint Chiefs of Staff Bio] in pdf format
*[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/mdtaylor.htm Maxwell Davenport Taylor, General, United States Army] at [http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net Arlington National Cemetery Website]

{{S-start}}
{{S-mil}}
{{Succession box|before = [[Francis Bowditch Wilby]] |title = [[Superintendents of the United States Military Academy]] |years = 1945&amp;ndash;1949 |after = [[Bryant Moore]]}}
{{Succession box|before = Gen. [[Matthew Ridgway]] |title = [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]] |years = 1955&amp;ndash;1959 |after = Gen. [[Lyman Lemnitzer]]}}
{{Succession box|before = Gen. [[Lyman Lemnitzer]] |title = [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]] |years = 1962&amp;ndash;1964 |after = Gen. [[Earle G. Wheeler]]}}
{{Succession box|
 title=Commanding General of the [[Eighth United States Army]]|
 before= Lt Gen. [[James Van Fleet]] |
 years= 1953&amp;ndash;1955 |
 after= Gen. [[Lyman Lemnitzer]]}}
{{S-dip}}
{{Succession box|before=[[Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.]]|title=[[United States Ambassador to South Vietnam|U.S. Ambassador to South Vietnam]]|years=1964&amp;ndash;1965|after=[[Henry Cabot Lodge, Jr.]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{US Army Chiefs of Staff}}
{{JCS}}
{{USMA Superintendents}}
{{Buddhist crisis}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Taylor, Maxwell D.
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = August 26, 1901
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Keytesville, Missouri]]
| DATE OF DEATH     = April 19, 1987
| PLACE OF DEATH    = [[Washington, D.C.]]
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Taylor, Maxwell D.}}
[[Category:1901 births]]
[[Category:1987 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Chariton County, Missouri]]
[[Category:United States Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:Superintendents of the United States Military Academy]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Cross (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Star]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Legion of Merit]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Bronze Star Medal]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Purple Heart medal]]
[[Category:Légion d'honneur recipients]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]
[[Category:American people of World War II]]
[[Category:American military personnel of the Korean War]]
[[Category:United States Army Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Chairmen of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:Joint Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:American people of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord people]]
[[Category:Deaths from motor neurone disease]]
[[Category:Cold War diplomats]]
[[Category:Ambassadors of the United States to South Vietnam]]
[[Category:Lyndon B. Johnson Administration personnel]]
[[Category:Nixon administration personnel]]
[[Category:United States Army Command and General Staff College alumni]]
[[Category:Knights Fourth Class of the Military William Order]]

{{Link FA|sl}}

[[bg:Максуел Тейлър]]
[[ca:Maxwell Taylor]]
[[de:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[es:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[fr:Maxwell Davenport Taylor]]
[[ko:맥스웰 테일러]]
[[it:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[hu:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[nl:Maxwell Davenport Taylor]]
[[ja:マクスウェル・D・テイラー]]
[[no:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[pl:Maxwell Taylor]]
[[pt:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[ru:Тейлор, Максвелл]]
[[sq:Maxwell Taylor]]
[[sl:Maxwell Davenport Taylor]]
[[sv:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[tr:Maxwell Taylor]]
[[uk:Максвелл Давенпорт Тейлор]]
[[vi:Maxwell D. Taylor]]
[[zh:馬克斯維爾·D·泰勒]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
