<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3512033" ns="0" title="List of supporting Harry Potter characters"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}{{DISPLAYTITLE:List of supporting ''Harry Potter'' characters}}
The following are '''supporting characters in the ''[[Harry Potter]]'' series''' written by [[J. K. Rowling]].

==The Dursleys==
[[Image:Dursleyfamily.jpg|thumb|right|250 px|From left to right: [[Fiona Shaw]] as Aunt Petunia, [[Harry Melling (actor)|Harry Melling]] as Dudley, and [[Richard Griffiths]] as Uncle Vernon in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]''.]]
The '''Dursley family''' are [[Harry Potter (character)|Harry Potter's]] last living relatives. In order to ensure Harry's safety, [[Albus Dumbledore]] placed him in the Dursleys' care when he was a baby. The Dursleys live at Number 4, Privet Drive, [[Little Whinging]] in Surrey, England. They are all [[Muggle]]s, and despise all things related to [[Magic in Harry Potter|magic]]--and anything out of the ordinary in general—and the [[Harry Potter universe|Wizarding World]], especially the Potters.

The name &quot;[[Dursley]]&quot; derives from the small town in [[Gloucestershire]], near Rowling's birthplace.

===Vernon Dursley===
'''Vernon Dursley''' is Harry's uncle, Petunia's husband (and therefore [[Lily Potter]]'s brother-in-law), and Dudley's father. Vernon is described as a big, beefy man, with hardly any neck, and a large moustache. He is very much the head of his family, laying down most of the rules for Harry and doing most of the threatening, as well as spoiling Dudley. He is also the director of a drill-making firm, Grunnings, and seems to be quite successful in his career. He regularly reads the [[Daily Mail]].

Uncle Vernon and his wife have grudgingly raised Harry from an early age. He and Petunia never informed Harry about the magical world, including how his parents died; they explained it away as a car crash. Unlike Petunia, who proves to have a slight feeling of familial loyalty to Harry, Vernon seems to hate his nephew so much that in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'', he is willing to throw him out of the house, knowing that doing so would put him in grave danger. In fact, while discussing the [[Dementors|Dementor]] attack with Harry, Vernon actually hopes aloud that Harry will receive the death penalty. Vernon also has an aversion to imagination, to any references to magic, and anything even slightly out of the ordinary; in the first book, when Harry mentions dreaming about a flying motorbike, Vernon responds by angrily, bellowing that motorbikes do not fly, despite Harry's protests that it was only a dream.

When the Dursleys decide to leave Privet Drive to go into hiding, Vernon nearly shakes Harry's hand good-bye, though he ultimately cannot bring himself to do it. In the film version, he leaves without even a word to Harry. On a deleted scene on the Blu-ray/DVD release, Vernon and Harry's departure plays out like the novel; however, Vernon shows no sentiment whatsoever.

Vernon is portrayed by [[Richard Griffiths]] in the film series.

===Petunia Dursley===
'''Petunia Dursley''' &lt;!-- Do not insert her maiden name here, that would be in-universe style writing and will be removed. --&gt; is Harry’s aunt and Lily Potter's sister. She is described as a blonde (though dark-haired in the films), bony woman with a &quot;rather horsey&quot; face and a very long neck, and spends most of her time spying on her neighbours. Her eyes are large and pale, quite unlike Lily's. Her whole family is made up of Muggles, except for Lily, a Muggle-born witch. According to Petunia, her parents were proud of having a witch in the family, but Petunia saw her sister as a freak. In fact, she was envious and resentful of Lily's magical abilities&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2007/7/30/j-k-rowling-web-chat-transcript|title=J.K. Rowling Web Chat Transcript|date=30 July 2007|accessdate=30 July 2007|publisher=[[The Leaky Cauldron (website)|The Leaky Cauldron]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and went so far as to write to Dumbledore, pleading to be allowed to enter [[Hogwarts]]. Dumbledore gently denied her enrolment. Afterwards, Petunia grew cold towards the school and, by extension, towards the wizarding world in general. She had no contact with Lily after her marriage to [[James Potter (character)|James Potter]] and the birth of her nephew, Harry, though she did send the family a &quot;horrible vase&quot; that baby Harry broke while riding on a toy broom. The gift echoes Harry's Dursley-sent Christmas presents, which are never pretty or welcome.

Petunia has more knowledge of the wizarding world than she is initially willing to admit. After the Dementors attack Harry and Dudley, Petunia states that she knows Dementors guard the wizard prison, [[Azkaban]]. When Harry and the rest of her family look at her strangely, she explains that she heard &quot;that awful boy&quot; telling Lily about them years ago. Harry assumes that the &quot;awful boy&quot; was his father, James, but in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', he learns via memories that it was actually [[Severus Snape]], who knew both Lily and Petunia when they were children. On one
occasion, Petunia and her husband almost send Harry out of their house but she receives a Howler from Albus Dumbledore and decides not to send the boy away.

Before the Dursleys leave Privet Drive to go into hiding, Petunia almost wishes Harry good luck, suggesting that she does feel a tiny sense of familial attachment to her nephew; however her self-imposed hatred of Harry and magic prevent her from doing so, and she leaves without a word. In the film version of ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'', she leaves Harry without showing any sentiment; however, in a deleted scene on the Blu-ray/DVD release, Petunia shows acknowledgment of the wizarding world, and ultimately deep remorse for the loss of her sister Lily.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ricks|first=Hanako|title=Deleted Scene from &quot;Deathly Hallows&quot; Shows Different Side to Disliked Character|url=http://www.hollywoodnews.com/2011/03/24/deleted-scene-from-deathly-hallows-shows-different-side-to-disliked-character/|title=Deleted scene from deathly hallows shows different side to disliked character |date=24 March 2011|work=Hollywood News|accessdate=28 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Actress [[Fiona Shaw]] portrays adult Petunia in the films, with Ariella Paradise playing her as a child.

===Dudley Dursley===
'''Dudley Dursley''' is the only child of Vernon and Petunia, and is Harry's only cousin. Described as a very large, blonde (though brown-haired in the films) boy, Dudley is generally given his way in almost everything, and shows the symptoms of a [[spoiled brat]]. In the first book, for example, he is showered with an enormous number of incredibly expensive presents (including a bicycle, a gold [[wristwatch]] and his own television), and yet shows no signs of gratitude. Dudley is a cold-hearted bully and the leader of a gang of thugs with whom he regularly beats up Harry and younger children on the flimsiest of excuses. He is only one month older than Harry. The same year Harry starts at Hogwarts, Dudley is enrolled at his father's old private boarding school, Smeltings.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'', Dudley is given a pig's tail by [[Rubeus Hagrid]] as punishment for Vernon &quot;[insulting] Albus Dumbeldore in front of me&quot;. &lt;ref&gt; Harry Potter and the Philospoher's Stone. London : Bloomsbury, 1997, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; The tail has to be removed at a private hospital in London. In ''Goblet of Fire'', Dudley becomes wider than he is tall, and the Smeltings school nurse advises the Dursleys to put him on a strict diet. During the summer when this diet is enforced (all members of the family must follow this diet too), the Weasleys arrive at Number 4, Privet Drive to pick Harry up for the [[Quidditch]] World Cup, and [[Fred Weasley]] &quot;accidentally&quot; drops a [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Weasleys' Wizard Wheezes|Ton-Tongue Toffee]], which enlarges Dudley's tongue to four feet long before his hysterical mother reluctantly allows Arthur Weasley to shrink it.

In the fifth book, two Dementors attack Dudley and Harry. Dudley collapses, and Harry uses the [[Spells in Harry Potter#Expecto Patronum (Patronus Charm)|Patronus Charm]] to drive a group of Dementors away from himself and his cousin. He half carries the shaken Dudley home, though Dudley is convinced that Harry used magic to draw the Dementors to them. After the confrontation, Harry wonders what sort of bad memories Dudley could have relived, as Dementors force people to relive their worst experiences. Rowling later revealed, in an on-line chat, that Dudley's worst fear was seeing himself for who he really was: a cruel, selfish, violent bully with no feelings whatsoever for others, and this revelation shocked him to the core.&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot;/&gt; The experience does, in fact, give Dudley a more favourable impression of Harry, as seen in ''Deathly Hallows'', when Dudley is the only member of the family to accept Harry: he shakes his hand and thanks him for saving his soul from the Dementor attack, and shows some concern for him when the Dursleys leave to go into hiding. In his appreciation of his cousin's belated gratitude, Harry says good-bye to him using Dudley's former gang name, &quot;Big D&quot;. In the film version, however, there is no such sentiment as Dudley leaves Harry before he can say any final words; however, on the Blu-ray/DVD release, a deleted scene includes the reconciliation between the two cousins.&lt;ref name=&quot;Additional Scenes&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Deathly Hallows – Part 1 DVD &amp; Blu-ray|url=http://www.mugglenet.com/movies/movie7/dhpt1dvd.shtml|work=Mugglenet|accessdate=28 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rowling revealed on her website that many people have asked her to include an adult Dudley with a wizarding child in the epilogue of ''Deathly Hallows'', and that she herself considered it, but decided upon reflection that any &quot;latent wizarding genes would never survive contact with Uncle Vernon's DNA&quot; and thus she did not do so. Rowling says that Harry and Dudley would &quot;stay on Christmas card&quot; terms for the rest of their lives,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by: Edward |url=http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2007/10/19/j-k-rowling-talks-marriage-writing-and-more-at-open-book-tour-stop-in-new-york-city |title=J. K. Rowling Talks Marriage, Writing and More at Open Book Tour Stop in New York City – The Leaky Cauldron |publisher=The-leaky-cauldron.org |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that Harry would take his family to visit Dudley's when they were in the neighbourhood, but it was something that James, Albus and Lily &quot;would dread&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Site design and technology by Lightmaker.com |url=http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/extrastuff_view.cfm?id=26 |title=J.K.Rowling Official Site |publisher=Jkrowling.com |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Dudley's kids and Harry's occasionally would &quot;get together while the adults sat in awkward silence&quot;.

Dudley is portrayed by [[Harry Melling (actor)|Harry Melling]] in the ''Harry Potter'' films.

===Marge Dursley===
'''Marjorie &quot;Marge&quot; Dursley''' is Vernon's sister and described as physically resembling him; a large woman with hardly any neck and even a bit of a moustache, even though it is not as bushy as Vernon's. Though she is not a blood relative of Harry, he has been forced to call her &quot;Aunt Marge&quot; throughout his whole life with the Dursleys. Marge lives in the country, where she breeds bulldogs and because of her commitment to her animals, she rarely visits Privet Drive, to Harry's considerable relief. Each of her visits stands out in Harry's mind for her cruelty to him. Owing to Vernon's and Petunia's lies, Aunt Marge believes that Harry is a horrible boy, and delights in insulting both him and his dead parents. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]'' after she insults Harry's parents, Harry loses his temper and accidentally inflates her, thus causing her to blow up like a balloon and float up to the ceiling. Marge is later rescued, changed back to normal, and the [[Ministry of Magic]] modifies her memory. She also appeared in a memory in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'': When Harry is chased up a tree by one of Marge's bulldogs while the Dursleys laugh at him from the ground and Marge refuses to call the dog off.

[[Pam Ferris]] appeared as Marge in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]''.

==Others==
===Bathilda Bagshot===
'''Bathilda Bagshot''' is a noted historian in the wizarding world, and author of the book ''A History of Magic''. She lives in the village where Harry Potter was born, Godric's Hollow, and is an old family friend of [[Dumbledore]], and the Potters' neighbour. [[#Gellert Grindelwald|Gellert Grindelwald]] is her great-nephew, which is why he comes to live in Godric's Hollow after being expelled from [[Durmstrang]]. Bathilda is a major source of information for [[#Rita Skeeter|Rita Skeeter]]'s biography of Dumbledore, who extracts this information under the influence of [[Veritaserum]]; it is possible her memory is also modified following the &quot;interview&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', Chapter 18, it is revealed that Bathilda Bagshot was sent a copy of ''The Life and Lies of Albus Dumbledore'' accompanied by a note: &quot;Dear Batty, Thanks for your help. Here's a copy of the book, hope you like it. You said everything, even if you don't remember it. Rita.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; Harry decides to go to Godric's Hollow in order to get information from Bathilda, and because he wants to see his parents' grave. Hermione thinks that Dumbledore might have entrusted her with [[Sword of Gryffindor|Gryffindor's Sword]]. She dies before Harry's arrival in Godric's Hollow, possibly at the hand of [[Lord Voldemort]], who enchants her decaying body to use as a disguise for his snake, [[Nagini (Harry Potter)|Nagini]] to wait for Harry. The snake is then instructed to subdue Harry when he arrives in Bathilda's house looking for the sword until Voldemort himself can get there to finish him off.

[[Hazel Douglas]] plays Bathilda in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'', though the storyline is rewritten so that Nagini was fed polyjuice to assume the woman's form while her corpse is hidden away within her house.

===Frank Bryce===
'''Frank Bryce''' is a reclusive Muggle World War II veteran who works as the caretaker of the [[Riddle family]] mansion in [[Little Hangleton]]. In 1942, the Riddles were murdered by [[Lord Voldemort|Tom Riddle]] (later to become Lord Voldemort), and since Bryce had the keys to the large house where the deaths occurred, he was arrested and questioned in connection with the murders. As there was lack of evidence (because the bodies were unmarked as the [[Avada Kedavra|Killing Curse]] leaves no sign of violence or damage on the victims) the police could not prove that the Riddles had been murdered, and were forced to release Bryce. However, the community of Little Hangleton still believed Bryce to be guilty. As a result, he lived out the rest of his life as a pariah, isolated and living on the grounds of the Riddles' estate, while still working in the grounds.

In the beginning of ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'' Voldemort secretly returns to the Riddle house. Bryce inadvertently finds himself overhearing Voldemort's plan to kill Harry, initially believing Voldemort and [[Wormtail]] to be spies, but before he can take action, [[Nagini]] finds him and reveals his presence to Voldemort, who kills him almost immediately with the [[Avada Kedavra]] curse. He appears once more in the same book, during Harry and Voldemort's graveyard duel. The [[Priori Incantatem]] effect brings back an &quot;echo&quot; of Bryce from the tip of Voldemort's wand. Despite not knowing who he is, Bryce enthusiastically encourages Harry to keep fighting.

Dumbledore states his belief in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'' that the murder of Bryce was used to create Voldemort's presumably sixth and final [[Horcrux]], implanted in Nagini. However, Rowling later said Voldemort used the earlier murder of [[Bertha Jorkins]] for this.&lt;ref name=webchat&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bloomsbury.com/jkrevent/content.asp?sec=3&amp;sec2=1 |title=Harry Potter at Bloomsbury |publisher=Bloomsbury.com |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Eric Sykes]] appeared as Bryce in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire (film)|Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]''.

===Crabbe and Goyle===
[[Image:GoyleMalfoyCrabbePansy.jpg|thumb|250 px|Left to right: Gregory Goyle, Draco Malfoy, Vincent Crabbe and [[#Pansy Parkinson|Pansy Parkinson]] from director [[Alfonso Cuarón]]'s film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]''.]]
'''Vincent Crabbe''' and '''Gregory Goyle''' are [[Hogwarts#Slytherin|Slytherin]] students in Harry's year; both of their fathers, Crabbe Sr and Goyle Sr, are [[Death Eater|Death Eaters]]. Due to their size and strength, the pair act as [[Draco Malfoy]]'s minions and serve to intimidate fellow students. Crabbe and Goyle are both brawn-over-brains type; they are entirely lacking in introspection or curiosity. They seem unable to make up their own minds or to see things their own way. Nonetheless, Crabbe is depicted as slightly more intelligent than Goyle; in ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'', he is hand-picked by Malfoy as his second in the Midnight Duel with Harry that never takes place.

Crabbe and Goyle make their first and only appearance as new Slytherin [[Quidditch]] Beaters in the opening match against Gryffindor in their fifth year; after Harry catches the Snitch, Crabbe vents his frustration by purposely hitting a Bludger into Harry's back and knocking him off his broom, but receives the light punishment of writing lines. They do not return to the team the following year, as they regularly serve as Malfoy's lookouts during his forays into the [[Room of Requirement]]. After Malfoy leaves the school following the death of Dumbledore just before the end of the term, Crabbe and Goyle are left in a state of loneliness.

The three of them are reunited in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. Both of them speak for the first time, Crabbe's voice being described as &quot;oddly soft for someone with his huge frame&quot; and Goyle's simply as a grunt. Crabbe has sided with the Death Eaters with more conviction than either Goyle or Malfoy, and becomes increasingly independent of Malfoy, well aware of the Malfoy family's falling out of favour with Voldemort. The pair have developed into surprisingly powerful wizards. Crabbe and Goyle are mentioned as having excelled in inflicting the [[Cruciatus Curse]] on other pupils who had received detentions under [[Amycus Carrow]]'s direction: according to [[Neville Longbottom]], it was &quot;the first time they were the best in anything&quot;. During the fight for the Horcrux diadem with Harry, [[Ron Weasley]] and [[Hermione Granger]] in the Room of Requirement, Crabbe defies Malfoy's order to not kill Harry and casually throws around the [[Avada Kedavra]] curse. Finally, he summons [[Fiendfyre]] and turns the room into a blazing inferno, but it quickly rages beyond his control and ultimately leads to his death and the destruction of the Horcrux. Goyle is knocked unconscious during the ensuing fight, but is rescued along with Malfoy by Harry, Ron and Hermione. Goyle and Malfoy are left mourning Crabbe's death.

[[Joshua Herdman]] has played Goyle and [[Jamie Waylett]] portrayed Crabbe in the first six films of the ''[[Harry Potter (film series)|Harry Potter]]'' film series to date; only Herdman appears in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2]]'', with Crabbe's role in the plot being replaced by Goyle, and Goyle's being replaced by Blaise Zabini.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.snitchseeker.com/harry-potter-news/jamie-waylett-won-t-return-deathly-hallows-66514/ |title=Jamie Waylett won't return for Deathly Hallows |publisher=SnitchSeeker.com |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ss2&quot;&gt;[http://www.snitchseeker.com/harry-potter-news/joshua-herdman-louis-cordice-reprise-goyle-zabini-roles-deathly-hallows-66023/ Joshua Herdman &amp; Louis Cordice to reprise Goyle and Zabini roles for Deathly Hallows] – Snitchseeker.com Forums&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gabrielle Delacour===
'''Gabrielle Delacour''' is the only younger sister of [[Fleur Delacour]]. Her age in ''Goblet of Fire'' is estimated by Harry to be no more than eight, and this statement is reinforced when it is stated in ''Deathly Hallows'' that she is eleven. During the Triwizard Tournament, in which Fleur is the champion for [[Beauxbatons]], Gabrielle along with Ron, Hermione, and [[Cho Chang]] is used as underwater &quot;bait&quot; for the champions to rescue. Unfortunately Fleur does not manage to rescue Gabrielle in time because she is held back by [[Grindylow]]s and is forced to return to the surface, but Harry goes on to save her as well as his own hostage, Ron. She makes a small appearance later on in the book when the contestants' families are allowed to watch them compete. She is clinging to her mother and gives Harry a smile and a wave when she sees him, which is when he returns.

Fleur hints in ''Half-Blood Prince'' that Gabrielle (much like the young [[Ginny Weasley]]) has developed a crush on Harry, since she &quot;never stops talking&quot; about him. Gabrielle and Ginny serve as bridesmaids at [[Bill Weasley]] and Fleur's wedding in ''Deathly Hallows''. Her part-[[Veela]] heritage begins to develop as she matures and she is nicknamed &quot;Fleur in miniature&quot;. She retains the crush on Harry at that time, causing Ginny to clear her throat loudly in mild jealousy when she throws him a flirtatious look.

Gabrielle was portrayed by [[Angelica Mandy]] in the film adaptation of [[Goblet of Fire]]. Mandy reprised her role for ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows - Part 1]]'', but appeared only in background scenes and was uncredited

===Cedric Diggory===
'''Cedric Diggory''' was a [[Hufflepuff]] student three years above Harry.&lt;!-- Cedric is first seen in PoA as a fifth year (Harry's third). Therefore, it is two years, not three.--&gt; In addition to being a Hufflepuff prefect, he is first mentioned in ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]'' when the female Gryffindor Chasers say that they find him &quot;strong and silent&quot; amid giggles prior to the Hufflepuff-[[Gryffindor]] match, and shows a notable streak of modesty and fairness; when he catches the Snitch and wins the match after Harry falls off his broomstick following an encounter with the [[Dementors]], he believes the circumstances of the match to be unfair and protests that the result should be nullified and the match replayed. He is described as being exceptionally handsome, tall, with chiselled features, a straight nose, dark hair, and bright grey eyes.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'', Cedric is selected as the Hogwarts champion for the Triwizard Tournament. After Harry is also picked to compete, Malfoy makes &quot;Support Cedric Diggory/Potter Stinks&quot; badges, which Cedric tries to discourage his housemates from wearing. For the first task, Cedric transfigures a rock into a dog in order to distract his dragon and successfully finds his golden egg, but he receives a burn on his cheek in the process. He is later [[Cho Chang]]'s date for the Yule Ball. As compensation for Harry's warning about the dragons before the first task, Cedric assists Harry in solving the clue of the second task by telling him to take a bath with the egg in the prefects' bathroom, and just &quot;mull things over in the hot water&quot;. Cedric is the second of the four champions to find the village of the merpeople and rescue his hostage, using a [[List of spells in Harry Potter#(Bubble-Head Charm)|Bubble-Head Charm]], but surfaced one minute over the one-hour time limit.

During the third task, Harry saves Cedric's life twice while in the maze, and when they find the Triwizard Cup, Cedric refuses to take it without Harry, so they grab hold of it together. The cup turns out to be a [[Portkey]] which transports them to the Little Hangleton graveyard, where Voldemort and [[Peter Pettigrew]] await Harry's arrival; Pettigrew murders Cedric on the spot upon Voldemort's order to &quot;kill the spare&quot;. In the midst of the ''Priori Incantatem'' effect during Harry's duel with Voldemort, Cedric's spirit appears and asks Harry to take his body back to his parents. Despite an attempted cover-up of the incident by the [[Ministry of Magic]], Dumbledore candidly reveals the true nature of Cedric's demise to the students at the end-of-term feast, stating that to attribute it to an accident would be &quot;an insult to his memory&quot;. Cedric Diggory was in his seventh year at Hogwarts in ''The Goblet of Fire''.

[[Robert Pattinson]] appeared as Cedric in [[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire (film)|the film adaptation of ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire'']], and made a brief cameo in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix (film)|Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'' in a flashback taken from ''Goblet of Fire''. The actor who portrayed him in ''Prisoner of Azkaban'' is unidentified.

===Gellert Grindelwald===
'''Gellert Grindelwald''' is a [[Dark Arts (Harry Potter)|Dark wizard]] who, in a list of &quot;Most Dangerous Dark Wizards of All Time&quot;, would be second only to Voldemort, according to [[#Rita Skeeter|Rita Skeeter]]'s book ''The Life and Lies of Albus Dumbledore''. His name is first mentioned on Dumbledore's Chocolate Frog card, which notes that Dumbledore defeated Grindelwald in 1945.

Grindelwald attended the wizarding school [[Durmstrang]], from which he was expelled at age sixteen for his dangerous and evil experiments that nearly resulted in the deaths of some of his fellow students. He left the symbol of the [[Deathly Hallows (objects)|Deathly Hallows]] on one of the walls in Durmstrang before departing. After Durmstrang, he went to live with his great-aunt Bathilda Bagshot in Godric's Hollow, where he met the young Dumbledore. In ''Deathly Hallows'', it was revealed that Grindelwald had gone to Godric's Hollow to investigate the grave of the [[Peverell brothers]] (the original owners of the Hallows), but struck up a close friendship with Dumbledore, and the two planned to establish a new world order, where wizards would rule over Muggles &quot;for the greater good&quot; (the phrase later became Grindelwald's excuse for the atrocities he committed in his reign of terror). They also planned to work together in their quest for the Hallows. Later Rowling revealed at a Q&amp;A session that Dumbledore was once in love with Grindelwald, and thus 'lost his moral compass', but she did not say whether those feelings were returned.&lt;ref name=&quot;nydncarnegie&quot;&gt;{{Citation |title= Rowling dubs Dumbledore of 'Harry Potter' books as gay |url=http://www.nydailynews.com/gossip/2007/10/19/2007-10-19_rowling_dubs_dumbledore_of_harry_potter_.html |accessdate=20 October 2007 | work=Daily News | date=19 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;365carnegie&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url = http://www.365gay.com/Newscon07/10/102007potter.htm |title = J.K. Rowling outs Hogwarts character |agency=Associated Press |date=  20 October 2007 |accessdate =22 October 2007 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071021081806/http://365gay.com/Newscon07/10/102007potter.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 21 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, [[Aberforth Dumbledore]], Albus' younger brother, argued against these plans, because he feared their grand ambitions would leave his disabled, traumatised sister, [[Ariana Dumbledore|Ariana]], abandoned. Later the argument culminated in a three-way duel among Albus, Aberforth, and Grindelwald. Ariana was inadvertently killed by one of them. Grindelwald fled, fearing retribution and henceforth, Albus ended his friendship with him. Grindelwald successfully became master of one of the Deathly Hallows, the [[Elder Wand]], by stealing it from the previous owner, the wand-maker Gregorovitch. Gaining the Elder Wand's immense power, he subsequently committed many terrible acts. It is revealed that Grindelwald's actions have caused many deaths that have greatly affected the students of Durmstrang, including [[Viktor Krum]], whose grandfather was murdered by Grindelwald.

After Grindelwald's rise to power, Dumbledore delayed meeting him again for several years due to his fear of being confronted with his sister's death and the fact that he himself might have been the one who accidentally killed her. Both wizards were highly intelligent and skilled in battle, and when their battle eventually occurred, those who witnessed it later said that no other wizarding duel ever matched it. Grindelwald, who at the time possessed the supposedly unbeatable Elder Wand, lost to Dumbledore. Since Dumbledore won the duel over Grindelwald, the Elder Wand transferred its allegiance to Dumbledore. After Dumbledore triumphed over Grindelwald, the defeated dark wizard was imprisoned in the top-most cell of [[Nurmengard]]. He remained there, growing emaciated and toothless through the ravages of the prison, until the events of ''Deathly Hallows'' when Voldemort arrives, seeking the Elder Wand. Grindelwald, showing no fear of Voldemort and welcoming death, tells him that he never owned the wand, and Voldemort kills him in rage. In the chapter &quot;King's Cross&quot;, Harry suggests to Dumbledore that Grindelwald lied to Voldemort in order to prevent him from breaking into Dumbledore's tomb, where he knew the Elder Wand lay.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'', young Grindelwald is portrayed by [[Jamie Campbell Bower]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by: sue |url=http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2009/6/30/jamie-campbell-bower-talks-role-as-young-grindlewald-in-deathly-hallows |title=Jamie Campbell Bower Talks Role as Young Grindelwald in Deathly Hallows |publisher=The-leaky-cauldron.org |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The older Grindelwald is played by [[Michael Byrne (actor)|Michael Byrne]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0926084/fullcredits#cast&lt;/ref&gt; In the film, unlike in the book, Grindelwald reveals to Voldemort the whereabouts of the Elder Wand, and thus is not killed.

===Viktor Krum===
'''Viktor Krum''' ({{lang-bg|Виктор Крум}}) is a Seeker for the Bulgarian national Quidditch team. Many wizards of his time consider him a prodigy, having entered the International Quidditch League at an early age. He is described as having bushy eyebrows and a hooked nose, which he inherited from his father. He is also described as being more coordinated on a broom, as he is described as being slightly duck-footed and slightly round-shouldered on land.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=J.K. Rowling and the Live Chat, Bloomsbury.com, July 30, 2007 (2.00–3.00&amp;nbsp;pm BST). |url=http://www.accio-quote.org/articles/2007/0730-bloomsbury-chat.html |accessdate=9 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Despite his success and fame, Krum appeared to be unhappy and lonely, and was further characterised as being very quiet and reserved, though Hermione says he is a genuinely nice person beneath the sullen exterior. In the Quidditch World Cup title game between Bulgaria and Ireland, he suffers a severe bloody nose during the match and catches the Snitch as quickly as he can to end it, which hands victory to Ireland because Bulgaria was trailing by 160 points at the time.

Krum is named Durmstrang champion upon entering his name for the prestigious Triwizard Tournament. He is often viewed with suspicion by his peers due to Durmstrang's reputation for teaching the Dark Arts, while looked upon with admiration for his feats, mainly by giggling Hogwarts girls. Whilst competing in the Triwizard Tournament, he takes to visiting the Hogwarts library in order to try to talk to Hermione. He eventually gains the courage to ask her to the Yule Ball, a traditional formal dance associated with the Triwizard Tournament. Krum has to rescue her from the merpeople in the Great Lake for the Second Task, revealing his deep affection for her. Immediately afterward, he invited her to stay with him in Bulgaria and stated that he had &quot;never felt this way about a girl before.&quot; He becomes jealous of Harry when a slanderous news article by [[Rita Skeeter]] falsely states that Hermione is toying with both boys' affections, and confronts him about it. When he learns the truth, he and Harry become friendly, shortly before the appearance of a mentally incapacitated [[Bartemius Crouch Sr]]. Crouch's disguised son stuns Krum shortly afterward, to murder his father unnoticed. In the climax of the book, Krum, under the influence of an [[Imperius Curse]] cast by [[Barty Crouch Jr]], uses the [[Cruciatus Curse]] on Cedric Diggory to eliminate any opposition for Harry to win the tournament, but is not arrested nor punished for this, as he was not in control of his own functions.

Krum briefly returns in ''Deathly Hallows,'' as a wedding guest of Bill and Fleur. He has a heated discussion with Xenophilius Lovegood, after he recognises a symbol that Xenophilius wears around his neck as the mark of Grindelwald; the symbol is later discovered to be the mark of the Deathly Hallows. His attitude suggests that he wants to get back together with Hermione, and he is disgruntled to see her dancing with Ron. J.K. Rowling later stated that Krum eventually found love in his native Bulgaria.

[[Stanislav Ianevski]] portrayed Krum in the film adaptations of ''Goblet of Fire'' and ''Deathly Hallows''.

===Augusta Longbottom===
'''Augusta Longbottom''' is [[Neville Longbottom]]'s paternal grandmother, introduced in ''Philosopher's Stone'' before Neville leaves for Hogwarts. She raised him from a young age after [[Frank and Alice Longbottom|Neville's parents]] were tortured and permanently incapacitated by a group of Death Eaters led by [[Bellatrix Lestrange]]. Early on, it is established that Neville is terrified of his grandmother, who is a very strict disciplinarian, a perfectionist, a staunch opponent of [[Voldemort]] and a no-nonsense witch, especially towards Neville, sometimes complaining he is not as gifted a wizard as his father.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix|Order of the Phoenix]]'', Neville discloses that his grandmother fully supports Harry and Dumbledore's proclamations that Voldemort had returned, even going so far as to cancel her subscription to the ''[[Daily Prophet]]'', because they keep toeing the [[Ministry of Magic]] line that Harry was lying. Later, Harry and his friends are visiting Arthur Weasley in [[St Mungo's Hospital for Magical Maladies and Injuries]] and meet Augusta and Neville who are visiting Frank and Alice; Augusta explains to Harry's friends how Neville's parents got into that state. She reprimands Neville for failing to have already told his friends what happened to his parents, saying he should be &quot;proud&quot; to be their son for their bravery.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince|Half-Blood Prince]]'', Augusta wants Neville to continue studying [[Transfiguration (Harry Potter)|Transfiguration]] instead of [[Hogwarts#Charms|Charms]], which she considers a soft option. It is revealed by [[Minerva McGonagall]] that Augusta thinks like this because she failed her Charms O.W.L. McGonagall also writes a letter to Augusta telling her it's time that she &quot;learned to be proud of the grandson she's got, rather than the one she thinks she ought to have&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{HP6ref}}, chapter 9&lt;/ref&gt;

''Deathly Hallows'' is a definite turning point for the relationship between Augusta and her grandson. Towards the climax of the book, it is revealed that the Death Eaters targeted Augusta when Neville began acting as leader of the reformed Dumbledore's Army. The Ministry official [[John Dawlish]] is sent to arrest her; according to Neville, he was expecting an old woman living alone to be an easy target. Dawlish ends up in St. Mungo's Hospital and Augusta goes on the run, sending Neville an encouraging letter, which he keeps by his heart. Augusta arrives to the Battle of Hogwarts to assist her grandson. Bolstered by Neville's leadership of the D.A. during his seventh year at Hogwarts, Augusta ultimately becomes extremely proud of him.

===Xenophilius Lovegood===
'''Xenophilius &quot;Xeno&quot; Lovegood''' is [[Luna Lovegood]]'s father and the editor of ''[[The Quibbler]]'', a magazine that often publishes stories about wild conspiracy theories or research on seemingly non-existent creatures.

He is introduced in ''Deathly Hallows'' as a guest at the wedding of Fleur Delacour and Bill Weasley, and is said to be a friend. He is described as eccentric looking, being slightly cross-eyed, with shoulder-length white hair the texture of [[candyfloss]] and wearing garishly coloured robes. Xenophilius wears the symbol of the Deathly Hallows around his neck as a way of showing his willingness to help other believers in the Hallows in their quest to obtain them.

Later in the story, he explains to Harry, Ron, and Hermione the significance of the Deathly Hallows. Although initially one of the staunchest supporters of the anti-Voldemort, pro-Harry Potter movement through his magazine, Xenophilius later betrays the trio's location to the Death Eater-controlled [[Ministry of Magic]] in a bid to ensure the safe return of his kidnapped daughter. After an ensuing battle with Xenophilius and the Death Eaters, the trio escape and the Death Eaters arrest Xenophilius, which saves his reputation, as he is mentioned on the clandestine &quot;''Potterwatch''&quot; radio broadcast as a persecuted anti-Voldemort dissident, and the issue of ''The Quibbler'' in which he attacks Harry is buried under the ruins of his home and never distributed. Harry, Ron, and Hermione never reveal his attempted betrayal, which was motivated solely by fear for Luna's life.

Welsh actor and singer [[Rhys Ifans]] portrays Xenophilius in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows - Part 1|Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''.

===Teddy Lupin===
'''Ted Remus &quot;Teddy&quot; Lupin''' is the orphaned only son of [[Remus Lupin]] and [[Nymphadora Tonks]] and godson of Harry Potter. He is named after Tonks's late father, [[#Ted Tonks|Ted Tonks]], and his own father, Remus. Teddy is a [[Metamorphmagus]] like his mother Nymphadora, and is not affected by his father's lycanthropy.&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | title=TIME Person of The Year Runner-up: J.K. Rowling |work=Time | date=23 December 2007 | url=http://www.time.com/time/specials/2007/personoftheyear/article/0,28804,1690753_1695388_1695569,00.html |accessdate=23 December 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, in the epilogue of ''Deathly Hallows'', he is announced by Harry's elder son [[#James Potter|James]] as being in King's Cross Station and [[kissing|snogging]] [[#Victoire Weasley|Victoire Weasley]], the daughter of Fleur Delacour and Bill Weasley. Rowling stated that Teddy was raised by his maternal grandmother, [[#Andromeda Tonks|Andromeda Tonks]],&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt; and not by his godfather, Harry. However, he has a very close relationship with Harry, who mentions that he usually comes to dinner at his house four times a week and a prospect of having his godson move in.

===Narcissa Malfoy===
'''Narcissa &quot;Cissy&quot; Malfoy''', born Narcissa Black to Cygnus Black III and Druella Rosier, is the youngest of three sisters, her older sisters being [[Bellatrix Lestrange]] and [[#Andromeda Tonks|Andromeda Tonks]]. She is a cousin of [[Sirius Black|Sirius]] and [[Regulus Black]] and an aunt to [[Nymphadora Tonks]], Andromeda's daughter. Narcissa attended Hogwarts, where she was in [[Slytherin]]. She later married [[Lucius Malfoy]], with whom she has one son, [[Draco Malfoy|Draco]], of whom she is extremely protective. Narcissa is first described as a tall, slim blonde who would have been attractive had it not been for &quot;a look that suggested there was a nasty smell under her nose&quot;. Although Narcissa certainly seems to share the Blacks' and her husband's views on blood purity on the outside,&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt; her actions indicate she is far more concerned about the welfare of her family than helping Voldemort.

Although Narcissa makes her first, very brief appearance in ''Goblet of Fire'', where she attends the Quidditch World Cup with her husband and son, her role in the series first becomes important in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]''. At the beginning of the book, Narcissa and Bellatrix arrive suddenly at [[Spinner's End|Snape's home]]. Narcissa is distraught, almost [[hysteria|hysterical]], with her husband imprisoned in [[Azkaban]] and her son forced to accept a difficult and dangerous assignment by Voldemort. She begs Snape to help Draco and asks him to make an [[Unbreakable Vow]], to which he agrees. Narcissa also appears later in the novel, shopping with Draco for his new robes at [[Places in Harry Potter#Madam Malkin's Robes for All Occasions|Madam Malkin's]]. She and Draco bump into Harry, Ron and Hermione. Harry taunts Narcissa for her husband being sent to Azkaban, and in turn, she mocks his dead godfather, Sirius Black. Draco defuses the situation by leaving with his mother.

In ''Deathly Hallows,'' [[Malfoy Manor|Narcissa's home]] is being used (against her will) as the Headquarters for Voldemort and his Death Eaters and for confining several prisoners, including eventually, Harry, Ron, and Hermione. When this group escapes with the help of [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Dobby|Dobby]], Voldemort places Narcissa and her family under house arrest. In the climax of the book, the Malfoys are brought with the other Death Eaters to Hogwarts, when Voldemort invades the castle. When Voldemort casts a Killing Curse on Harry, Narcissa is ordered to verify his death. When she feels Harry's heart beating, she quietly asks him whether Draco is still alive at Hogwarts, a fact that Harry confirms. Knowing that she will not be free to search for her son unless she can return with the Death Eaters as part of a &quot;conquering army&quot;, Narcissa lies to Voldemort and declares Harry to be dead. She is later seen at the end of the book, with her husband and son, unsure what to do and how to behave amidst the celebration of Voldemort's death. However, thanks to her lie to Voldemort, the Malfoys manage to &quot;weasel their way&quot; out of imprisonment in Azkaban.&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt;

In the film series, Narcissa shows very little to no animosity towards Harry, only dueling him after he attacks Draco during the Battle of Malfoy Manor. After Harry and Voldemort start fighting, she is seen fleeing with Lucius and Draco, thus renouncing their Death Eater lifestyle which later grants them amnesty. Narcissa is portrayed by [[Helen McCrory]] in the film series.

===Olympe Maxime===
'''Madame Olympe Maxime''' is the headmistress of [[Beauxbatons]], the French wizarding school. The character is introduced in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire|Goblet of Fire]]'' when her school is invited to the Triwizard Tournament, with [[Fleur Delacour]] being elected as Beauxbaton's champion. When Harry is chosen as the fourth champion and second Hogwarts champion, she is angered and is about to leave the tournament, but she eventually agrees to stay. In ''Goblet of Fire'', she is described as being elegant and wearing black satin robes, and having olive skin and handsome features, but being extremely tall. It is revealed that Madame Maxime's huge size is due to her half-giant background. She fiercely denies this, although she is around the same height as fellow half-giant [[Rubeus Hagrid]]. Upon first sight, Hagrid immediately takes a crush on Madame Maxime, which he shows by attempting to groom himself properly.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix|Order of the Phoenix]],'' Hagrid tells Harry, Ron, and Hermione that he and Madame Maxime visited the giants during that summer in order to get them into the [[Order of the Phoenix (organisation)|Order of the Phoenix]]'s side. Unfortunately, they failed in their mission, because Voldemort also sent a group of Death Eaters to address the giants. When giants attack Hagrid, Madame Maxime defended him by using a conjunctivitis curse. Hagrid describes her spell work as &quot;brilliant&quot;. She separates from Hagrid during the return journey, however, because he would not abandon his giant half-brother [[Grawp]], who proves to be a highly taxing travelling companion. She returns to Beauxbatons alone. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince|Half-Blood Prince]]'', Madame Maxime is among those paying respects at Dumbledore's funeral. Her last appearance is in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows|Deathly Hallows]]'', where she attends the wedding of [[Bill Weasley]] and Fleur Delacour.

[[Frances de la Tour]] appeared as Madame Maxime in ''Goblet of Fire'', and reappeared in the role in ''Deathly Hallows''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.harry-potter-movie-buzz.com/news/729/scoop-on-filming-the-deathly-hallows-wedding-scene.html |title=Scoop on Filming the ‘Deathly Hallows’ Wedding Scene |publisher=Harry Potter Movie Buzz |date=28 October 2009 |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cormac McLaggen===
'''Cormac McLaggen''' is a Gryffindor student one year above Harry. He is introduced for the first time during the train journey to Hogwarts in ''Half-Blood Prince'' as a member of [[Horace Slughorn]]'s Slug Club, due to his uncle's close ties with the Ministry of Magic. Cormac is shown as an unsympathetic Gryffindor character, and his Gryffindor bravery is both a strength and a flaw: he is foolhardy and proud, bordering on arrogant. Cormac tries out for the position of Keeper when Harry becomes captain; however, Hermione secretly jinxes him with the Confundus Charm, causing him to miss his last save and thus helping Ron retain his spot on the team. Cormac does not take his loss well, accusing Ginny of favouritism by giving Ron easy shots to block.

Cormac fills in during Gryffindor's match against Hufflepuff as Keeper when Ron is unable to play due to poisoning, but his debut is disastrous, as he orders the team about instead of focusing on his own position, knocks Harry unconscious with a [[bludger]], and contributes to Gryffindor's lopsided 320–60 loss, thus earning him universal dislike among his housemates. Cormac also briefly becomes a pawn in the escalating tensions between Ron and Hermione, when he accompanies Hermione to Slughorn's Christmas party as her date, in retaliation for Ron's relationship with [[Lavender Brown (Harry Potter)|Lavender Brown]]. The plan backfires when she becomes exasperated with McLaggen's arrogant behaviour, and she leaves him stranded under the mistletoe and avoids him for the remainder of the party.

[[Freddie Stroma]] appears as McLaggen in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince (film)|Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'', ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2|Part 2]]''.

===Auntie Muriel===
'''Muriel''' is a great-aunt of the Weasley children (on Molly's side). According to Ron, she is rude to just about everyone she meets. Harry first meets her in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'' during Bill and Fleur's wedding. She is described as having bloodshot eyes and a large, feathery pink hat, making her look like a &quot;badly tempered flamingo&quot;. She lends her beautiful [[Goblin (Harry Potter)|goblin]]-made tiara to Fleur for the wedding. During the wedding, she starts an argument with [[Emmeline Vance|Elphias Doge]] about Dumbledore's past and [[Rita Skeeter]]'s ''The Life and Lies of Albus Dumbledore''. Muriel provides her house in ''The Deathly Hallows'' to act as a place The Order of the Phoenix members can take Harry when they remove him from the safety of the [[Dursley family|Dursleys']]. Later in the book, most of the Weasleys and several others hide in her house because they are targeted as blood traitors or Mudbloods.

Matyelok Gibbs appears as Muriel in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows - Part 1]]'', but during the film she is never identified.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Posted by: sue |url=http://www.the-leaky-cauldron.org/2009/6/26/deathly-hallows-casting-updates-aunt-muriel-cast-mafilda-hopkins-recast-and-clemence-confirmed |title=Deathly Hallows Casting Updates: Aunt Muriel Cast, Mafald Hopkirk Recast and Clemence Confirmed! |publisher=The Leaky Cauldron |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Moaning Myrtle===
'''Moaning Myrtle''' is a [[Ghosts (Harry Potter)|ghost]] that haunts the second floor girls' lavatory at Hogwarts. True to her nickname, she has a tendency to sob, whine, wail and complain, especially when death is mentioned. Her constant moping and wailing causes plumbing problems in the lavatory she haunts. Rowling revealed on her website that Myrtle was in [[Ravenclaw]] House.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Site design and technology by Lightmaker.com |url=http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/faq_view.cfm?id=117 |title=What houses were Tonks and Myrtle in? |publisher=Jkrowling.com |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''Chamber of Secrets'', it is established that the character is the ghost of a Muggle-born witch who died while a student at Hogwarts, fifty years before the events in the book. Myrtle was hiding in the second floor girls' lavatory to elude Olive Hornby, a classmate of hers who perpetually tormented her about her glasses, when the [[Chamber of Secrets]] was opened and the [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Basilisk|basilisk]] emerged and killed her. Tom Riddle used her death to create his [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Tom Riddle's Diary|second Horcrux]]: his diary.&lt;ref name=&quot;webchat&quot;/&gt; After death, Myrtle haunted Olive everywhere she went, until Olive complained to the Ministry of Magic, which ordered Myrtle to return to Hogwarts. Ever since then, Myrtle has sulkily haunted the same lavatory where she died. Despite living up to her name, she has been shown to be flirtatious with Harry – especially during his bath, and saying that if he should die, he can share haunting the lavatory with her. She also makes lascivious comments regarding Cedric's bath suggesting voyeuristic tendencies.

Myrtle also helps Harry with his second task in the [[Triwizard Tournament]], in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]''. Myrtle tells Harry how to solve the puzzle of the golden egg that he retrieved in the first task, by opening the egg underwater. She is shown being much less miserable, and enjoys having Harry briefly to herself to boss around. He later meets her in the lake where she directs him to the merpeople's village and says they don't like her. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'', she appears to comfort Draco, who is worried about the task Voldemort assigned him. After Harry injures Malfoy using [[Sectumsempra]], Myrtle quickly spreads the news throughout the school, screaming, ''&quot;Murder! Murder in the bathroom!&quot;''

[[Shirley Henderson]] portrays Myrtle in the film versions of ''[[Harry Potter and the Chamber of Secrets (film)|Chamber of Secrets]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire (film)|Goblet of Fire]]''.

===Garrick Ollivander===
'''Garrick Ollivander''' is the proprietor of ''[[Ollivanders]]'', a prestigious shop which sells magical wands in [[Diagon Alley]]. Although Ollivander is generally presented as a genial elderly man, Harry is unnerved both times he meets him in the series because the wandmaker appears to admire what Voldemort could do with his original wand and, later, the [[Elder Wand]]. Despite his wares' popularity, he can easily remember the materials and attributes of every wand he has ever sold. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone|Philosopher's Stone]]'', Ollivander assists a young Harry in selecting his first wand. Finding Harry a particularly difficult customer to match, Ollivander finally selects an eleven-inch-long wand made of [[holly]] containing a [[Phoenix (mythology)|phoenix]] feather (later revealed to have come from Dumbledore's phoenix, [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Fawkes|Fawkes]]), which is perfectly suited to Harry. Ollivander is intrigued that that particular wand would suit Harry, and reveals that Fawkes contributed only one other feather, to the wand being used by Voldemort.

Ollivander appears in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire|Goblet of Fire]]'' during the preliminary ceremonies of the Triwizard Tournament, where he acts as an expert judge for the Weighing of the Wands. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince|Half-Blood Prince]]'', his shop has closed and is boarded up, and Ollivander himself is missing. The opening scene of the ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince (film)|Half-Blood Prince]]'' film shows Mr Ollivander hooded and forcibly seized from his shop by three [[Death Eaters]]. In ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows|Deathly Hallows]]'', Ollivander has been captured by Voldemort and imprisoned at [[Malfoy Manor]] with Luna, with whom he develops an affectionate relationship as the two strive to keep each other's spirits up. He is among those rescued from the manor by [[Magical creatures (Harry Potter)#Dobby|Dobby]], after which, at [[Shell Cottage]], he provides Harry and his friends with some useful information about the [[Elder Wand]]. He later goes into hiding at the home of [[Weasley family#Auntie Muriel|Auntie Muriel]] and sends Luna a new wand as a gift.

British actor [[John Hurt]] appears as Ollivander in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone (film)|Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'' and reprised his role in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2|Part 2]]''.

His first name was revealed in ''[[Pottermore]]''. It was also revealed that he is married and has a son and a daughter (the latter deceased). Some of the names of his wandmaker ancestors were also revealed: Geraint Ollivander (ancestor), Gerbold Octavius Ollivander (paternal grandfather), Gervaise Ollivander (father).

===Pansy Parkinson===
'''Pansy Parkinson''' is a Slytherin student who is described as pug-faced and frequently seen with an unnamed gang of Slytherin girls, acting as their leader, or at least spokeswoman. She is also Draco Malfoy's female counterpart and apparent love interest. She is first mentioned in the Sorting in ''Philosopher's Stone'', and makes her first appearance in [[Madam Hooch]]'s flying class, during which she teases [[Parvati Patil]] for defending [[Neville Longbottom]] after Draco steals Longbottom's [[Magic Objects (Harry Potter)#Remembrall|Remembrall]]. In ''Prisoner of Azkaban,'' she cries and follows Malfoy to the hospital wing after he is attacked by [[Buckbeak]], and continues to fawn over him despite his deliberate exaggeration of the extent of his injury. They attended the Yule Ball together in ''Goblet of Fire,'' and on the train ride to Hogwarts at the start of ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'', she is seen stroking Malfoy's hair while his head lay in her lap, visibly impressed by his bold claims concerning his job for Voldemort, even though he does not tell her what it is.

Throughout the series, Pansy regularly mocks Harry and his companions. She gives false information on Harry, Hermione, and Hagrid to Rita Skeeter, and openly voices criticisms of Hagrid to Umbridge in terms of her displeasure about his [[Care of Magical Creatures]] class and her difficulty in understanding his voice. She and other Slytherins also taunt the Gryffindor Quidditch players from the stands during a morning practice, notably teasing [[Angelina Johnson]] about her braided hair. During a Gryffindor-Slytherin match, which is also Ron's debut as the new Gryffindor Keeper, she conducts the Slytherin students as they sing a demeaning song entitled &quot;Weasley is our King&quot;.

Pansy has a moderately increased role in ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]''. She is made a Slytherin [[prefect]] along with Malfoy, and later joins [[Dolores Umbridge]]'s Inquisitorial Squad. When [[Dumbledore's Army]] flees the Room of Requirement following Dobby's revelation of an informant, Pansy searches the girls' bathrooms for escaped members and seizes Hermione's list of names as evidence. However, the Inquisitorial Squad members are jinxed in the midst of a student rebellion following [[Fred and George Weasley]]'s departure from Hogwarts. Pansy is thereafter admitted to the hospital wing and misses a day's worth of lessons after sprouting a pair of antlers. Near the conclusion of ''Deathly Hallows,'' when Voldemort demands Harry's surrender in order to prevent the Death Eaters from attacking Hogwarts, Pansy urges [[Minerva McGonagall]] to comply, and the Gryffindors, Ravenclaws and Hufflepuffs collectively respond by standing up and pointing their wands at her. She eventually evacuates with the other Slytherins.

Pansy was portrayed by [[Genevieve Gaunt]] in ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|Prisoner of Azkaban]]'', and by [[List of Harry Potter cast members|Scarlett Byrne]] in ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince (film)|Half-Blood Prince]]'', ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 1]]'' and ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows – Part 2|Part 2]]''.

===The Peverell brothers===
The '''Peverell family''' is first mentioned in ''Half-Blood Prince'' as ancestors of [[Marvolo Gaunt]], the maternal grandfather of Voldemort. In the final book of the series, they are revealed to be the original owners of the [[Deathly Hallows (objects)|Deathly Hallows]], which, according to ''[[The Tales of Beedle the Bard]]'', they received from Death, although Dumbledore believed it is more likely that they created them themselves. The Peverell lineage continues through its  living descendants, including Harry Potter and his children.

After Hermione saw the symbol of the Deathly Hallows on Ignotus Peverell's grave in Godric's Hollow, Harry recalled Marvolo Gaunt boasting that his ring held the Peverell [[coat of arms]] on it, thus realising that the three brothers were the Peverells. Harry deduces that he is descended from Ignotus, as the cloak is passed down through his family. Furthermore, Rowling has confirmed that Harry and Voldemort are indeed distant relatives because of their relation to the Peverells, as the majority of wizard families share common ancestry.&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt;

Antioch Peverell was the eldest of the three Peverell brothers, and owner of the [[Elder Wand]]. He was killed in his sleep after bragging about the wand's invincibility, having won a duel with it. The murderer then stole the Elder Wand, thus initiating its bloody history.

Cadmus Peverell was the middle of the three Peverell Brothers, and owner of the [[Resurrection Stone]]. Using the Stone, he resurrected the girl he had once hoped to marry, who had died an untimely death. Though she had returned to the mortal world, she did not truly belong there and suffered. Driven mad by this, he killed himself to join her. The Stone was later embedded in a ring that ended up belonging to Marvolo Gaunt.

Ignotus Peverell was the youngest of the three Peverell brothers, described in ''The Tales of Beedle the Bard'' as 'the humblest and also the wisest of the brothers'. He was the owner of the [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Cloak of Invisibility|Cloak of Invisibility]], due to which, unlike his brothers, he successfully avoided dying for many years, living a full and long life, and ultimately &quot;greeting Death as a friend.&quot; Harry deduces that his invisibility cloak is the original cloak owned by Ignotus. Unlike other cloaks of invisibility, it has never shown any kind of fading or damage despite the cloak being passed down through many generations of the Peverell family and ultimately to Harry. Harry is therefore a descendant of Ignotus Peverell. Both by birthright and by blood relations, Harry Potter is the rightful owner of the three Deathly Hallows yet he decides to keep the Cloak only, returning the Elder wand to Dumbledore's grave, and leaving The Resurrection Stone lost in The Forbidden Forest. In the film ''Deathly Hallows Part 2'', Harry destroys the Elder Wand, snapping it in half and throwing the two broken halves away.

===Madam Rosmerta===
'''Madam Rosmerta''' is the landlady of [[The Three Broomsticks]] pub. She is described in the books as &quot;a curvy sort of woman&quot; with curly hair; several pupils—including Ron—have a crush on her. In ''Prisoner of Azkaban'', Madam Rosmerta is angered when [[Dementors]] are in [[Hogsmeade]] as their presence is scaring away many of her customers. Apart from hosting an informal meeting between McGonagall, [[Cornelius Fudge]], [[Filius Flitwick]], and Hagrid, she does not play a major role in the early part of the ''Harry Potter'' series.

In ''Half-Blood Prince'', however, it emerges that, in order to fulfil his mission to assassinate Dumbledore, Draco has managed to place Rosmerta under the [[Imperius Curse]]. He uses her to pass on a cursed necklace to Hogwarts student [[Katie Bell]], who accidentally touches the necklace and is herself subjected to the very harmful curse intended for the Headmaster. Draco also commands her to send a bottle of poisoned mead to [[Horace Slughorn]] intending it to be a Christmas present for Dumbledore, after overhearing Hermione mentioning that the school security would not recognise something put in a mislabelled bottle, and knowing that a package from Rosmerta would not be checked. Malfoy communicates with Rosmerta through [[Magical objects in Harry Potter#Enchanted coins|enchanted fake Galleons]]. After Harry and Dumbledore's adventure in the cave to retrieve a locket they believe to be one of Voldemort's Horcruxes, they [[Apparate]]d to Hogsmeade, where Madam Rosmerta alerts them to the presence of the [[Dark Mark]] above the school and gives them brooms on which they can travel rapidly back to Hogwarts, where Draco's plan can be brought to completion. Rosmerta is among those paying respects at Dumbledore's funeral.

She is named after the [[Gallo-Roman religion|Gaulish goddess]] [[Rosmerta]], whose attributes include abundance and fertility.

[[Julie Christie]] appeared as Madam Rosmerta in the film adaptation of ''[[Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban (film)|Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban]]''.

===Stan Shunpike===
'''Stanley &quot;Stan&quot; Shunpike''' is the young, pimply conductor of the [[Knight Bus]]. He speaks with a [[Cockney]] accent, and converses with Harry as he travels to London in the first part of ''Prisoner of Azkaban''. He also appears briefly in ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'' at the Quidditch World Cup, boasting to a group of Veela, the Bulgarian team's official mascot, of his ambitious plans to become the next Minister of Magic. In ''Order of the Phoenix,'' he conducts the Knight Bus when Harry, Ron, Hermione, Fred, George, Ginny, Lupin, and Tonks take it to return to Hogwarts after the Christmas holidays. Stan mentions that he does not believe the media rumours about Harry being insane, though Harry interprets Stan's actions as not caring how insane someone is as long as he/she is famous enough to get into the papers.

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]'', Stan is arrested on suspicion of Death Eater activity. Harry and Dumbledore, however, believe that he is almost certainly not guilty. Even so, Stan is kept in Azkaban in order for the Ministry of Magic to give the pretence that progress is being made in the capturing of Death Eaters. When the new Minister for Magic asks Harry to be a sort of mascot for the Ministry, Harry refuses on the grounds of the Ministry's actions at the time – namely holding Stan under arrest. In ''Deathly Hallows'', a &quot;strangely blank&quot; looking Stan is among the Death Eaters who pursue Harry during his escape from Privet Drive. Harry gives himself away to his attackers by attempting to only disarm Stan, as Harry believes him to be under the Imperius Curse. Later on, when Harry, Ron and Hermione are captured in the forest by Fenrir Greyback, Ron attempts to pose as Stan only to be immediately disbelieved and told Stan has &quot;put a bit of work their way&quot; referring to turning in missing or wanted Muggle-borns. 

Stan was portrayed by [[Lee Ingleby]] in the film adaptation of ''Prisoner of Azkaban''.

===Rita Skeeter===
'''Rita Skeeter''' is a reporter for the ''[[Daily Prophet]]'' and a correspondent for the ''Witch Weekly'', who specialises in [[yellow journalism]], for which she is armed with such magical devices as the [[Quick-Quotes Quill]]. Rita is an unregistered [[Animagus]], capable of transforming into a beetle to spy on unsuspecting victims for her stories. As a reporter who fabricates information in order to write an appealing story, she is an antagonist to Harry and his friends throughout ''Goblet of Fire'', and a brief but reluctant ally in ''Order of the Phoenix''. She is described as having curly blonde hair, jewelled spectacles, thick fingers with two inch long nails painted crimson, a crocodile-skin handbag, and a heavy jawed face.

Harry first encounters Rita when she interviews the [[Triwizard Tournament]] contestants for an article in the ''Daily Prophet'', which turns out to be a highly falsified story of Harry himself. During the situations where Rita overhears information, the book subtly refers to her presence: [[#Viktor Krum|Viktor Krum]] mentions that Hermione has a water beetle in her hair, and during the Yule Ball, she overhears Hagrid telling [[#Olympe Maxime|Madame Maxime]] that he is half-giant, Harry having noticed a beetle on a nearby statue. Rita prints an article that portrays Hagrid as dangerous, prompting letters from parents frightened by the idea of having a &quot;ferocious&quot; giant teach their children. When Rita encounters Harry, Ron, and Hermione in Hogsmeade, Hermione insults her. Rita, in revenge, then writes a nasty story about Hermione based on false rumours provided by [[#Pansy Parkinson|Pansy Parkinson]], making her out to be a plain but skilled witch who uses love potions to &quot;satisfy her taste for celebrity wizards,&quot; including Harry and Krum. Rita's last defaming article states that Harry is &quot;disturbed and dangerous,&quot; and uses comments from Draco and his Slytherin cronies as its basis. Ultimately, Hermione discovers the means by which Rita spies on others and forces her to &quot;keep her quill to herself for a full year&quot;, threatening to report her to the authorities as an illegal Animagus. Unfortunately her last article would discredit Harry and serve as the basis for Cornelius Fudge to refuse to believe Harry's story about Voldemort's return that would start the Ministry's smear campaign against Harry and Dumbledore.&lt;ref&gt;[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]] Chapter 36: The Parting of the Ways.&lt;/ref&gt;

In ''[[Harry Potter and the Order of the Phoenix]]'' Hermione [[blackmail]]s Rita, using the above threat, to interview Harry about Voldemort returning and to submit the true story to ''[[The Quibbler]]''. Rita later makes a brief cameo in ''Half-Blood Prince'', where Harry is infuriated to notice her clutching a notebook at Dumbledore's funeral. Although Rita does not make a physical appearance in ''Deathly Hallows,'' she is mentioned on numerous occasions throughout the novel, generally in a negative light in relation to her unauthorised biography of Dumbledore entitled ''The Life and Lies of Albus Dumbledore''. The book depicts the former headmaster in an extremely negative light but is mostly based on truth, much to Harry's horror. It is implied that she got some of her information in unethical or illegal ways.&lt;ref&gt;{{HP7ref}}, chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{HP7ref}}, chapter 18&lt;/ref&gt; When asked on a web chat if Rita was still reporting, Rowling answered; &quot;Naturally, what could stop Rita? I imagine she immediately dashed off a biography of Harry after he defeated Voldemort. One quarter truth to three quarters rubbish&quot;, along with ''Snape: Scoundrel or Saint?''&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt;

It has been speculated that the fraught relationship between Rowling and the press was the inspiration for the author to develop the character. However, Rowling noted in 2000 that the character actually predates her rise to fame.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Books: transcript of J. K. Rowling's live interview on Scholastic.com|url=http://www.scholastic.com/harrypotter/books/author/interview2.htm}} 16 October 2000. Accessed 30 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Rita was intended to be in ''Philosopher's Stone'', as Rowling revealed in an interview: &quot;you know when Harry walks into the Leaky Cauldron for the first time and everyone says, &quot;Mr. Potter you're back!&quot;, I wanted to put a journalist in there. She wasn't called Rita then but she was a woman. And then I thought, as I looked at the plot overall, I thought, that's not really where she fits best, she fits best in Four when Harry's supposed to come to terms with his fame.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.accio-quote.org/articles/2000/fall00-bbc-newsround.html Transcript of interview with J.K. Rowling]. ''BBC Newsround''. 2000. Accessed 25 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Miranda Richardson]] appeared as Rita in the film adaptation of ''Goblet of Fire'' as well as a cameo in the ''Deathly Hallows''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.snitchseeker.com/harry-potter-news/miranda-richardson-reprise-rita-skeeter-role-deathly-hallows-70121/|title=Miranda Richardson to reprise Rita Skeeter role in Deathly Hallows|date=23 December 2009|accessdate=24 December 2009|publisher=SnitchSeeker}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[IGN]]'s Joe Utichi called Rita his eighth favourite ''Harry Potter'' character, saying that she was &quot;terrifyingly familiar&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Joe Top&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://uk.movies.ign.com/articles/113/1132181p2.html |title=The Top 10 Harry Potter Characters |author=Joe Utichi |date=3 November 2010 |work=[[IGN]] |accessdate=3 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Hepzibah Smith===
'''Hepzibah Smith''' is introduced within Dumbledore's [[Pensieve]], as part of a series of memories shown to Harry by his headmaster probing into Voldemort's past. She is described as having been an extremely wealthy, well-born old witch who enjoyed collecting antiques and collectibles. In the memory, Hepzibah wears long robes and gowns of pink, and when sitting upon her throne-like chair, she is described as giving the impression of a large &quot;melting iced cake&quot;. She wears a large, elaborate, ginger wig upon her head and dabs her red cheeks with rouge.

[[Tom Riddle]], fresh out of Hogwarts and working for [[Borgin and Burkes]], visits Hepzibah to make an offer for some goblin-made armour which she owns. He presents her with flowers and charms and flatters her. Enamoured with Riddle, Hepzibah shows him her most prized possessions – a cup, owned by her ancestor [[Helga Hufflepuff]], and a locket which once belonged to [[Salazar Slytherin]], that she had purchased from Borgin and Burkes. Two days after the events of the memory occurred, Hepzibah died, and Hufflepuff's cup and Slytherin's locket were never found. Dumbledore theorises that Riddle had killed Hepzibah and tampered with the memory of her house-elf, [[Magical creatures in Harry Potter#Hokey|Hokey]], so that she thought she had accidentally poisoned her mistress's evening drink. This is not the case; however, it proves at an early age, that Tom Riddle had a certain thirst for trophies, and other valuable objects that he could collect. Hufflepuff's cup and Slytherin's locket would go on to become two of Voldemort's seven Horcruxes: Tom Riddle's diary, Marvolo Gaunt's ring, Voldemort's pet snake Nagini, Salazar Slytherin's locket, Helga Hufflepuff's cup, Rowena Ravenclaw's Diadem, and albeit inadvertently, Harry Potter. Rowling has confirmed that Hepzibah's death was used by the Dark Lord to create a Horcrux using the cup.&lt;ref name=webchat/&gt;

===Andromeda Tonks===
'''Andromeda &quot;Dromeda&quot; Tonks''' is the mother of [[Nymphadora Tonks]]. Born Andromeda Black, she is a [[pure-blood]] witch, daughter of [[Black family|Cygnus Black and Druella Rosier]] and sister of [[Bellatrix Lestrange]] and [[Narcissa Malfoy]]. The middle sister, she was burned off the family tapestry in [[Number 12, Grimmauld Place]] by her aunt Walburga and estranged from the family because she married [[#Ted Tonks|Ted Tonks]], a [[Muggle-born]] wizard. She was [[Sirius Black]]'s favourite cousin. Andromeda is responsible for giving her daughter the name &quot;Nymphadora&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;{{HP5ref}}, Chapter 3&lt;/ref&gt; a name like those typical of her family. She has a talent for household spells and cleanliness, lacked by her husband and daughter.

She is not introduced until the beginning of ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. She strongly resembles her sister Bellatrix, so much so that Harry thinks she is Bellatrix upon first meeting her, but Andromeda is kind looking and has soft brown rather than black hair. She and Ted are later tortured for information on Harry's whereabouts. For someone who is not a member of the Order of the Phoenix, the war with Voldemort and his followers exacts a very heavy toll on Andromeda: her husband, her daughter, her sister and her son-in-law are all killed. Rowling stated in an interview that after the war, Andromeda raises [[#Teddy Lupin|Teddy Lupin]], her grandson.&lt;ref name=&quot;transcript&quot; /&gt;

===Ted Tonks===
'''Ted Tonks''' is a Muggle-born wizard who is described as a &quot;fair-haired, big-bellied man&quot;. He marries Andromeda Black. Their marriage led to his wife's disownment by the rest of her strict pure-blood family. Ted and Andromeda are the parents of Nymphadora Tonks. Ted plays an active role in ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]''. Near the beginning of the novel, his home is a hideout for Harry and Hagrid, as the two are on the run from Voldemort. His home holds the Portkey that helps Harry escape to [[The Burrow (Harry Potter)|The Burrow]]. Later due to Ted's refusal to register as a Muggle-born, he is one of the Muggle-born wizards to flee the Ministry's new oppressive regime after the Death Eaters take over. During his flight, he meets the goblins [[Griphook]] and Gornuk, as well as [[Dean Thomas (Harry Potter)|Dean Thomas]] and [[Dirk Cresswell]]. Soon after, Ted is murdered by Snatchers who also kill Gornuk and Cresswell.&lt;ref&gt;{{HP7ref}}, Chapter 22&lt;/ref&gt; When Nymphadora gives birth to her and Lupin's son, they name him Teddy in honour of her father.


===Oliver Wood===
'''Oliver Wood''' is Captain of the Gryffindor Quidditch team in the first three novels and was first introduced in ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]''. He is simply described as being big and burly. Wood is a talented and keen player and a born leader as captain, but also tends to act as a taskmaster due to his obsession with the game; he never cancels practices, poor weather conditions notwithstanding, and holds training sessions in early morning hours. Although Oliver is in general a nice person, he lacks tact. In his seventh year, before the Quidditch Cup final, he constantly harangues Harry to catch the [[Golden Snitch]] only when Gryffindor is fifty points ahead of Slytherin during the match. Oliver says that he does not care if Harry falls off Firebolt so long as he catches the Snitch first, not realising how this would sound. Oliver appears briefly in ''Goblet of Fire'', when he excitedly introduces Harry to his parents at the [[Quidditch World Cup]] and announces that he joined the Puddlemere United reserve team. He is one of many Hogwarts students, past and present, who takes part in the Battle of Hogwarts in ''Deathly Hallows'', and is among the survivors; Harry sees him assisting [[Neville Longbottom]] in carrying the body of [[Colin Creevey]]. 

Oliver Wood was portrayed by [[Sean Biggerstaff]] in the first two films and returned for the final battle in the eighth film.

===The Muggle Prime Minister {{anchor|The Muggle Prime Minister of Britain}}===
The [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom]], referred to as '''the Muggle Prime Minister''' by wizards, receives a visit from [[Cornelius Fudge]] and [[Rufus Scrimgeour]] in the opening chapter of ''[[Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince]]''. Using a series of flashbacks, Rowling describes how the Prime Minister is aware of the existence of the wizarding world, through several meetings with Fudge that include his first night as Prime Minister, the night in which [[Sirius Black]] escaped from [[Azkaban]], the notification of the incident in the [[Quidditch]] World Cup and the announcement of the importation of dragons and a sphinx for the Triwizard Tournament, and finally the Azkaban mass break-out from the fifth book. Rowling intended to include the Prime Minister scene in earlier books, but she thought that it could not properly fit until the sixth book.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Site design and technology by Lightmaker.com |url=http://www.jkrowling.com/textonly/en/extrastuff_view.cfm?id=6 |title=J.K.Rowling Official Site |publisher=Jkrowling.com |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first chapter of ''Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince'', the Prime Minister recalls his day, during which one of his political opponents had been criticising him and his government for several catastrophes that have recently happened in Britain. Readers discover a little later during the discussion with Fudge, that these catastrophes are, in fact, the doings of Voldemort and his followers. He also discovers that he is protected by an [[Auror]] who now works in his office, [[Kingsley Shacklebolt]].

===The Weird Sisters===
'''The Weird Sisters''' are a fictional rock band in the ''Harry Potter'' series. Their instruments include guitars, bass, flute, cello, bagpipes and drums. They were booked by Dumbledore to play at Hogwarts during the [[Yule Ball]]. In the book version of ''[[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire]]'' they are described as &quot;all extremely hairy and dressed in black robes that had been artfully ripped and torn.&quot; A full music video of the band playing at the Yule Ball is included as an extended scene on the [[Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire (film)|''Goblet of Fire'' film]] 2-disc DVD. In 2005, [[Warner Bros.]], the international distributor of ''Goblet of Fire'' was sued for trademark violations by members of a Canadian [[folk-rock]] band named [[Legal disputes over Harry Potter#Wyrd Sisters|The Wyrd Sisters]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cbc.ca/arts/story/2005/11/04/wyrdlawsuit_051104.html|title='Wyrd Sisters' cannot stop Harry Potter| publisher=Canadian Broadcasting Corporation | date=4 November 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mtv.com/movies/news/articles/1510896/10042005/story.jhtml Canadian Group Sues Radiohead, Warner Bros. Over Use Of Name In 'Harry Potter' Flick] Long-running folk group claims trademark infringement&lt;/ref&gt; The name, however, originates from Norse Mythology, as a reference to the Norns. The term is also used in Shakespeare's play &quot;MacBeth&quot; to describe the three witches.

The members of the band according to [[Wizards of the Coast]] Famous Wizard cards are:
:*Heathcote Barbary – rhythm guitar
:*Gideon Crumb – bagpipes
:*Kirley Duke – lead guitar
:*Merton Graves – cello
:*Orsino Thruston – drums
:*Donaghan Tremlett – bass
:*Myron Wagtail – lead singer
:*Herman Wintringham – lute

They appear as a conventional band in the film version ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire''. The members were:
:*[[Jarvis Cocker]] (of [[Pulp (band)|Pulp]]) as Myron Wagtail – vocals
:*[[Jonny Greenwood]] (of [[Radiohead]]) as Kirley Duke – lead guitar
:*[[Jason Buckle]] (of [[All Seeing I]]) as Heathcote Barbary – rhythm guitar
:*[[Steve Mackey]] (of [[Pulp (band)|Pulp]]) as Donaghan Tremlett – bass
:*[[Steven Claydon]] (of [[Add N to (X)]]) as Gideon Crumb – keyboards and bagpipes
:*[[Phil Selway]] (of [[Radiohead]]) as Orsino Thruston – drums

They performed three songs (all composed by Cocker), entitled &quot;Do the Hippogriff&quot;, &quot;This Is the Night&quot; and &quot;Magic Works&quot; during the Yule Ball. The band was originally to be played by [[Franz Ferdinand (band)|Franz Ferdinand]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |last=Perez |first=Rodrigo |title=Franz Ferdinand To Play Ugly Sisters In Next 'Harry Potter' Flick? |url=http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1492215/20041012/franz_ferdinand.jhtml |publisher=MTV |date=12 October 2004 |accessdate=27 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Grandchildren of the Weasley family==
===James Sirius Potter===
'''James Sirius Potter''' is the first-born child of Harry and Ginny, born at least one year before his brother Albus. He was named after Harry's father and godfather and he is described as being similar in character to both of his namesakes as well as his uncles, Fred and George Weasley, with a penchant for practical jokes and general misbehaviour.{{HP7}}
James is played by Will Dunn in ''Deathly Hallows: Part 2''.

===Albus Severus Potter===
'''Albus Severus &quot;Al&quot; Potter''' Harry and Ginny's second child. He is said to look much like Harry, and the only one to have inherited Lily Potter's green eyes. During the ''Deathly Hallows'' epilogue, when he is being sent to Hogwarts for the first time he fears that he will be placed in Slytherin not Gryffindor, but Harry tells him that it doesn't really matter to them, but the Sorting Hat will listen to him if he wants to be a Gryffindor.

Albus is played by [[Arthur Bowen]] in ''Deathly Hallows: Part 2''.

===Lily Luna Potter===
'''Lily Luna Potter''' is the daughter of Harry and Ginny, and is the youngest of their three children. She is named after Harry's mother and his good friend, [[Luna Lovegood]].&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'&gt;J.K.Rowling – A Year In The Life; James Runcie; Independent Television (ITV); 2007&lt;/ref&gt; She is two years younger than her brother Albus, and is the same age as Ron and Hermione's son Hugo. In the epilogue of ''Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows'', she accompanied her parents as they escorted James and Albus to Platform 9¾.

Lily Luna Potter is played by Daphne de Beistegui in ''Deathly Hallows: Part 2.''

===Rose Weasley===
'''Rose 'Rosie' Weasley''' is Hermione and Ron's daughter and oldest child. Rose is introduced in the ''Deathly Hallows'' epilogue in which she is leaving for her first year at Hogwarts, as is Harry and Ginny's middle child Albus. According to Ron she inherited her mother's brains and is jokingly instructed by Ron not to befriend Scorpius, Draco Malfoy's son, but to beat him in everything, including their exams. Like her mother, she changes into her Hogwarts robes earlier than necessary. 

Rose Weasley is played by [[Helena Barlow]] in ''Deathly Hallows: Part 2''.

===Hugo Weasley===
'''Hugo Weasley''' is Hermione and Ron's son and youngest child. He is close in age to Harry and Ginny's daughter and youngest child, Lily, and had not yet started at Hogwarts by the epilogue of ''Deathly Hallows''.

Hugo is played by Ryan Turner in ''Deathly Hallows: Part 2''.

===Victoire Weasley===
'''Victoire Weasley''' is the eldest child of Bill and Fleur Weasley (née Delacour) and the oldest of the Weasley grandchildren.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brown |first=Jen |url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/19959323 |title=Exclusive: Finished ‘Potter’? Rowling tells what happens next – Wild about Harry – MSNBC.com |publisher=MSNBC |date=26 July 2007 |accessdate=31 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is named Victoire as she was born on the second anniversary of the Battle of Hogwarts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rowling Documentary&quot;/&gt; (&quot;Victoire&quot; means &quot;Victory&quot; in French, the native language of her mother Fleur). Victoire herself is only mentioned in the epilogue of ''[[Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows]]'', where James (Harry's son) saw her [[kissing|snogging]] [[#Teddy Lupin|Teddy Lupin]] and proceeded to tell his family along with Ron, Hermione, Rose and Hugo.

===Other children===
*'''Dominique Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jkrowling.co.uk/|title=J.K. Rowling Official Site|accessdate=12 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; second daughter of Bill and Fleur
*'''Louis Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'/&gt; son of Bill and Fleur
*'''Molly Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'/&gt; first daughter of [[Percy Weasley|Percy]] and Audrey named after her grandmother
*'''Lucy Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'/&gt; second daughter of Percy and Audrey
*'''Fred Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bloomsbury.com/harrypotter/content.asp?sec=3&amp;sec2=1|date=31 July 2007|accessdate=31 July 2007|publisher=[[Bloomsbury Publishing|Bloomsbury]]|title=Online Chat Transcript}}&lt;/ref&gt; son of George and [[Angelina Johnson|Angelina]], named after his father's deceased twin.
*'''Roxanne Weasley'''&lt;ref name='Rowling Documentary'/&gt;&lt;ref name='jkrowling web site'/&gt; daughter of George and Angelina

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Harry Potter|Fictional characters}}
{{Wikipedia-Books|Harry Potter}}
*[http://www.hp-lexicon.org/muggle/dursley.html The Harry Potter Lexicon's page on the Dursley family]

{{harrypotter}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:List Of Supporting Harry Potter Characters}}
[[Category:Harry Potter characters|Supporting Characters]]
[[Category:Lists of minor fictional characters|Harry Potter]]

[[ca:Llista de personatges secundaris en els llibres de Harry Potter]]
[[cs:Vedlejší postavy v Harrym Potterovi]]
[[da:Bipersoner i Harry Potter-universet]]
[[el:Διάσημοι μάγοι και μάγισσες (κάρτες Χάρι Πότερ)]]
[[es:Anexo:Personajes secundarios de Harry Potter]]
[[fr:Personnages secondaires de l’univers de Harry Potter]]
[[it:Personaggi minori di Harry Potter]]
[[he:הארי פוטר - דמויות משנה]]
[[la:Index personarum secundarum in Harrio Pottero]]
[[lt:Sąrašas:Antraeiliai Hario Poterio veikėjai]]
[[mk:Споредни ликови од Хари Потер]]
[[ja:マージョリー・ダーズリー]]
[[pl:Postacie drugoplanowe z cyklu Harry Potter]]
[[pt:Olivaras]]
[[sv:Mindre rollfigurer i Harry Potter]]
[[vi:Danh sách nhân vật phụ trong truyện Harry Potter]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
