<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3540766" ns="0" title="National Register of Historic Places listings in Arizona"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">This is a directory of properties and districts listed on the '''National Register of Historic Places in Arizona'''. There are 1,372 listed sites in the state, and each of its [[List of counties in Arizona|15 counties]] has at least eight listings on the National Register. Forty of the state's sites are further designated as [[National Historic Landmarks]].

{{Arizona NRHP topnav}}
{{clear}}

== Numbers of listings by county ==
The following are approximate tallies of current listings in Arizona on the National Register of Historic Places. These counts are based on entries in the National Register Information Database as of April 24, 2008&lt;ref name=&quot;nris&quot;&gt;{{NRISref|2008b}}&lt;/ref&gt; and new weekly listings posted since then on the National Register of Historic Places web site.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cr.nps.gov/nr/nrlist.htm |title=National Register of Historic Places: Weekly List Actions |accessdate=January 2, 2009 |publisher=National Park Service}}&lt;/ref&gt; There are frequent additions to the listings and occasional delistings, and the counts here are not official. Also, the counts in this table exclude boundary increase and decrease listings which modify the area covered by an existing property or district and which carry a separate National Register reference number.

{| width=100%
| style=&quot;width:330px; vertical-align:top&quot; |
[[File:Maricopa County Court House 330594-3.jpg|thumb|center|[[Maricopa County Courthouse]], Phoenix]]
[[File:Douglas Municipal Airport AZ - 8 Oct 1996.jpg|thumb|center|[[Douglas Municipal Airport (Arizona)|Douglas Municipal Airport]]]]
| style=&quot;width:330px; vertical-align:top&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; |
{|class=&quot;wikitable sortable&quot;
! {{NRHP color}}|
! {{NRHP color}}| '''County'''
! {{NRHP color}}| '''# of Sites'''
|--
| 1
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Apache County, Arizona|Apache]]
| 32
|--
| 2
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Cochise County, Arizona|Cochise]]
| 80
|--
| 3
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Coconino County, Arizona|Coconino]]
| 152
|--
| 4
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Gila County, Arizona|Gila]]
| 51
|--
| 5
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Graham County, Arizona|Graham]]
| 34
|--
| 6
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Greenlee County, Arizona|Greenlee]]
| 10
|--
| 7
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in La Paz County, Arizona|La Paz]]
| 9
|--
| 8.1
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Phoenix, Arizona|Maricopa: Phoenix]]
| 206
|--
| 8.2
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Maricopa County, Arizona|Maricopa: Other]]
| 167
|--
| 8.3
| Maricopa: Total
| 373
|--
| 9
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Mohave County, Arizona|Mohave]]
| 69
|--
| 10
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Navajo County, Arizona|Navajo]]
| 55
|--
| 11
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Pima County, Arizona|Pima]]
| 163
|--
| 12
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Pinal County, Arizona|Pinal]]
| 109
|--
| 13
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Santa Cruz County, Arizona|Santa Cruz]]
| 52
|--
| 14.1
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Prescott, Arizona|Yavapai: Prescott]]
| 71
|--
| 14.2
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Yavapai County, Arizona|Yavapai: Other]]
| 60
|--
| 14.3
| Yavapai: Total
| 131
|--
| 15
| [[National Register of Historic Places listings in Yuma County, Arizona|Yuma]]
| 60
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | (duplicates)
! (6)&lt;ref&gt;The following sites are listed in multiple counties: [[Coolidge Dam]] (Gila and Pinal), [[El Camino Del Diablo]] (Pima and Yuma), [[Fossil Creek Bridge]] (Gila and Yavapai), [[Kentucky Camp Historic District]] (Pima and Santa Cruz), [[Los Robles Archeological District]] (Pima and Pinal), [[Sierra Bonita Ranch]] (Cochise and Graham)&lt;/ref&gt;
|- class=&quot;sortbottom&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Total:
! 1,374
|}
| style=&quot;width:330px; vertical-align:top&quot; |
[[File:PaintedDesertInn.JPG|thumb|center|[[Painted Desert Inn]]]]
[[File:Fox-200.jpg|thumb|center|[[Fox Tucson Theatre]] then and now]]
|}
{{clear}}

==See also==
*[[List of National Historic Landmarks in Arizona]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Arizona}}
{{Registered Historic Places}}

[[Category:National Register of Historic Places in Arizona| ]]
[[Category:National Register of Historic Places lists by state|Arizona]]
[[Category:Arizona-related lists|Historic Places]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
