<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3544002" ns="0" title="Takoma Park Middle School"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox school
|name=Takoma Park Middle School
|seal_image=[[Image:TPMS Seal.png|200px]]
|alt=Takoma Park Middle School Seal
|established=1925&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot; /&gt;
|opened=March 15, 1940&lt;ref name=&quot;history&quot;&gt;[http://cityoftakomapark.org/library/reference/tphistory/stern.html History of the Takoma Park Junior High School]&lt;/ref&gt;
|website=[http://www.mcps.k12.md.us/schools/takomaparkms/ www.tpmsweb.com]
|faculty=approx. 100
|students=986 &lt;ref&gt;[http://md.localschooldirectory.com/schools_info.php/school_id/38214 Takoma Park Middle School from Local School Directory]&lt;/ref&gt;
|principal=Mildred Charley-Greene&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.montgomeryschoolsmd.org/schoolodex/schooloverview.aspx?s=03755 Takoma Park Middle School on the MCPS Website]&lt;/ref&gt;
|street=7611 Piney Branch Road
|county=[[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]]
|city=[[Silver Spring, Maryland|Silver Spring]]
|state=[[Maryland]]
|zip code=20910
|country=[[United States]]
|coordinates={{Coord|38.985408|-77.012894|region:US-MD_type:edu_scale:2000_source:Wikimapia|display=inline,title}}
|campus=Hodges Tract (Suburban)
|campus size=18.8 acres (7.61 ha)
|oversight=[[Montgomery County Public Schools]]
|colors=Blue and white {{Color box|#0000FF}}{{Color box|#FFFFFF}}
|mascot=Blue Devil
|nickname=Takoma
|motto=''Ad Astra''
|motto_translation=To the stars!
|type=[[Public school (government funded)|Public]] ([[Magnet school|Magnet]])  [[Middle School]]
|grades=6-8
|athletics=6 [[varsity sport]]s
|newspaper = [http://web.archive.org/web/20031030025556/http://tpmsbluechips.com ''Blue Chips'']
}}

'''Takoma Park Middle School''' (TPMS) is a [[Public school (government funded)|public]] [[middle school]] in [[Takoma Park, Maryland|Takoma Park]] in [[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]], [[Maryland]], [[United States]]. TPMS contains a total of 18 academic departments, as well as a specialized magnet program. The city of [[Takoma Park, Maryland|Takoma Park]] is assigned to this school.

The school is notable for its [[magnet school|magnet program]], which draws students from both the Silver Spring area and across [[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]], and makes up approximately 30% of TPMS's student population. TPMS is also recognized as a [[Maryland Green School]]. The principal of the school is Mrs. Mildred Charley-Greene.

== History ==
&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:T-SSHS Campus.jpg|left|200px|thumb|Takoma-Silver Spring School in the late 1920s {{deletable image-caption|Tuesday, 7 December 2010}}]] --&gt;
Takoma Park Middle School's foundations stretch back to the historic Takoma-Silver Spring School, which was located on a 3.8-acre campus at the corner of Philadelphia Avenue and Chicago Avenue in suburban [[Takoma Park, Maryland]]. In the late 1920s, T-SSHS expanded to consist of the middle grades 7 through 9, and by the early 1930s, grades K through 12. Due to an ever growing population, the high grades (10 through 12) left the school to form [[Montgomery Blair High School]] in 1935. By the end of the 1930s, further population growth fueled the need for a new [[middle school|junior high school]]; as a result, the middle grades relocated from Takoma-Silver Spring School to the new Takoma Park Middle School in March of 1940. Takoma-Silver Spring School was then renamed Silver Spring Intermediate School (SSI), which served as an elementary school until 1972, not to be confused with [[Silver Spring International Middle School]]. In 1992, the historic SSI building was demolished and the former school campus became a community park.

Several additions were made to the original Takoma Park Middle School building throughout the twentieth century. Six classrooms were added August 12, 1941. In December 1941 an estimate was made for a 3-classroom and shop addition, but this construction was delayed by war-time shortages. The next additions did not occur until September 1949: 7 classrooms, a library, office and gymnasium. In 1961, four teaching stations and an office were added. Lastly, in 1966 a new Library was added. In 1997, the original 60-year-old building was demolished and rebuilt.

== Campus ==
[[Image:TPMS Campus Aerial.jpg|200px|thumb|Aerial photograph of the TPMS campus]]
The Takoma Park Middle School campus covers 18.8 acres in suburban Takoma Park and is approximately rectangular in shape. The original school building, built on March 15, 1940, contained  {{convert|107758|sqft|m2|abbr=on}} of space. However, the current building, constructed in 1998, currently contains {{convert|137348|sqft|m2|abbr=on}} of space. At one point, the campus included three additional [[portable classroom|portable buildings]], but they were removed by 2007.

The Lee Jordan Athletic Field, consisting of a 400-meter [[Track and field|track]] which encloses the general combination football/soccer/baseball/softball field, resides north of the main building. To the east of the building are three basketball courts and four tennis courts. A [[greenhouse]] is located to the southwest of the building for use by horticulture groups. The school has three main parking lots, one for over 12 buses, one adjacent to the field, and one for both faculty members and visitors. 

The main building is composed of three floors, with two [[gym]]nasia and a [[cafeteria]] which doubles as an auditorium. The school also has standard classrooms and academic facilities, including six science laboratories, at least four computer technology labs, and a home economics lab. There is a media center/library and television studio located on the second floor. The television studio is the sight of filming for the daily announcements, called 'Wake-Up Takoma'.

== Demographics ==
As of 2005, the school has an enrollment of 986 students. TPMS is notable for the diversity of its student body: African Americans make up 29.5% of the population, Caucasians 34.6%, Hispanics 13.6% and Asians 22%. [http://www.montgomeryschoolsmd.org/departments/regulatoryaccountability/glance/currentyear/schools/03755.pdf]

== Academics ==
Because of its Mathematics/Science/Computer Science Magnet Program, TPMS attracts students from across the entire county. Additionally, the school has a [[Gifted education|Gifted and Talented (GT) Program]]. TPMS is home to the print newspaper ''Blue Chips'' and the now defunct online newspaper [http://web.archive.org/web/20031030025556/http://tpmsbluechips.com ''Blue Chips Online'']. TPMS also has a student television production unit that produces a daily announcement program called ''Wake Up Takoma'', which aires at 8:00 on weekday mornings and is run by students. Takoma Park Middle School offers an instructional program for all public school students living within its boundary area. This program includes not only the core academic subjects but also foreign language, arts, music, physical education, and four 'arts rotation' elective courses. A METS (Multidisciplinary Education, Training, and Support) program serves students with limited English proficiency and interrupted schooling.

TPMS consists of a specialized program and 17 academic departments, offering a diverse range of disciplines and courses. These 17 departments are as follows: Art, Counseling, English, English for Speakers of Other Languages (ESOL), Family and Consumer Science (Home Economics), Foreign Language, Health and Physical Education, Instrumental Music, Mathematics/Science/Computer Science Magnet Program, Mathematics, Media Center, Media Productions, Reading, Science, Social Studies, Special Education, and Technology Education.

=== Mathematics/Science/Computer Science Magnet Program ===
[[Image:TPMS Magnet Program Seal.png|right|175px]]
In the mid-1980s, [[Montgomery County Public Schools]] opened its first middle school Mathematics/Science/Computer Science Magnet Program within Takoma Park Middle School. The Magnet Program offers accelerated, interdisciplinary courses in mathematics, science, and computer science for students who are particularly interested in these subjects. The current coordinator of the Magnet Program is Scott DeGasperis. 

Before the start of second semester in 5th grade, students who reside in [[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]] are eligible to apply to the Magnet Program. The application process involves a written application including essays, teacher recommendations, and elementary school transcripts. All applicants are required to take a written entrance exam in the spring which tests math, science, humanities, and logical thinking. The program accepts only 100 students from across the county each year. However, students may be recommended for the magnet program for 7th or 8th grade.

Magnet students take three advanced courses each semester within the Magnet curriculum — mathematics, science, and computer science — and five courses each semester in other disciplines (English, social studies, fine arts, foreign language, physical education, etc.) with the rest of the TPMS student body. Math courses include [[Pre-algebra]], [[Algebra|Algebra I]], [[Geometry]], and [[Algebra|Algebra II]]. Most students begin their math course sequence with [[Pre-algebra]] in sixth grade, however, depending on their skill level and experience, students may choose to begin their course sequence with [[Algebra|Algebra I]] or even [[Geometry]] in sixth grade. The most advanced Magnet students may commute each day to [[Montgomery Blair High School]] to take the course Magnet Functions (accelerated [[Precalculus]]). A unit in Magnet [[Algebra|Algebra I]] explores the relationships between [[Set (mathematics)|Mathematical Sets]] and [[Rubik's Cube]]s, which leads to TPMS's annual Rubik's Cube Competition. In the Magnet [[Computer Science]] 6, students study the [[history of computers|evolution of computers]], [[telecommunications]], [[typing]], and the software components of [[Microsoft Office]], including [[Microsoft Excel|Excel]], [[Microsoft Access|Access]], and [[Powerpoint]], as well as the basics for the programming language, [[TrueBASIC]]. Seventh grade computer science topics include further [[TrueBASIC]] programming, and the study of web publishing and design with the [[HTML|Hypertext Markup Language]]. Advanced [[TrueBASIC]] programming skills and object-oriented programming are taught in Magnet [[Computer Science]] 8, in addition to [[JavaScript]] and advanced [[HTML]]. A language known as [[Logo (programming language)|Logo]] was formerly taught in eighth grade, but now a unit in the curriculum is based on the object-oriented programming language [[Scratch (programming language)|Scratch]]. Science courses cover the basics of various topics in [[Physics]], [[Chemistry]], [[Environmental Science]], [[Geology]], [[Space Science]], [[Biology]], [[Anatomy]], [[Meteorology]], and [[Astronomy]]. Each year, magnet students complete a Science Expo project to be displayed on Science Expo night along with the projects of their non-magnet peers. Magnet Science 6 contains a unique unit at the end of the year that covers [[Rube Goldberg Machine]]s, and their relations to physics and energy transformations. During this unit, students are required to design and build their own Rube Goldberg Machine. In Magnet Science 8, the Science Expo project is expanded into a year-long Capstone project.

The Mathematics, Science, and Computer Science Magnet Program at [[Montgomery Blair High School]] is considered to be a continuation of TPMS's Magnet Program. As such, approximately 50% of TPMS Magnet students are accepted to continue their education at [[Montgomery Blair High School|MBHS]]'s Magnet Program.

Magnet students have been winners of many state and national competitions. In 2005, four Magnet students from TPMS achieved perfect scores on the [[American Mathematics Contest|AMC 8]], tying the school with [[Fort Bend Independent School District|First Colony Middle School]] for the most perfect scores from a single school {{Citation needed|date=January 2008}}. Students in the Magnet Program began competing in the [[National Science Bowl]] in the 2007-2008 school year. In all the three years they have won the Maryland Regional Science Bowl and progressed onto the national competitions, where they placed 13th in 2008, 5th in 2009, 5th again in 2010, and 9th in 2011.

Notable magnet teachers include Kathryn Saftner, who teaches Magnet [[Algebra I]], hosts the annual [[Rubik's Cube]] Competition, and leads the competitive Math Team. &lt;ref&gt;http://www.montgomeryschoolsmd.org/schools/takomaparkms/academics/math/math.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; Another notable teacher is James Street, the seventh grade [[computer science]] teacher, who maintains the school's website, though he recently left to teach Research and Experimentation at Montgomery Blair High School.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.montgomeryschoolsmd.org/schools/takomaparkms/academics/cs/magnet78/daytoday/s12095.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===Foreign Language Department===
The Foreign Language Department offers studies in [[Spanish language|Spanish]] and [[French language|French]]. While foreign languages are technically a high-school courses, and large percentage of the student body is enrolled in a foreign language, many beginning in sixth grade or earlier.

===Instrumental Music Department===
The Instrumental Music Department consists of two orchestras, four bands, and one jazz band: Advanced Orchestra, Intermediate Orchestra, Advanced Band, Intermediate Band, 6th Grade Band, Beginning Band, and Jazz Band. The Advanced Orchestra has consistently earned superior ratings at county and state orchestra festivals for many years. Members of the Advanced Orchestra and Advanced Band have performed with various other ensembles, such as the Montgomery County Honors and Maryland All-State Honors Bands and Orchestras. They also participate in high-level select orchestra groups such as the [[Maryland Classic Youth Orchestras]], [[District of Columbia Youth Orchestras]], and the [[American Youth Philharmonic Orchestras]].

== Athletics ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=February 2008}}
The student athletics program offers 6 different sports, including: [[Basketball]], [[Baseball]], [[Softball]], [[Soccer]], [[Cross country running|Cross Country]], and [[Step dance|Step]]. The Boys Basketball team went undefeated from 2005 to 2006 (14-0) led by Leon Scales and Agwe Tabrey, and Ben Hukill (2 points all year) played a key role cheering from the end of the bench. Although it went 6-1 in the 2007 season, the team still captured 1st place for the 3rd straight year, setting a new middle school record for Montgomery County. The Girls Soccer Team went undefeated from 2005 to 2008. TPMS also holds an annual sporting event for students called the ''Turkey Trot'', which is an approximately 1 mile run around the school. Takoma hopes to have more success in the future. The current sixth graders have shown amazing potential.

== Student activities ==
TPMS has over 40 specialized teams or clubs: 
{{col-begin}}
{{col-1-of-3}}
*Chess Club
*Computer Team
*Drama Club
*Eureka! Club
*Games Club
*Geography Club
*Green Club

{{col-2-of-3}}
*GRRL Technology Club
*Homework Club
*Horticulture Club
*International Club
*Jazz Ensemble
*Difference Makers Club
*Jump Start Club
*MathCounts

{{col-3-of-3}}
*Math Team
*Model United Nations Club
*Multimedia Club
*Robotics Team
*Science Bowl Team
*Science Club
*Ski Club
*Step Team
*Student Government Association (SGA)
*Yearbook Club

{{col-end}}

===Science Bowl Team===
The Takoma Park Middle School science bowl team has been in existence for only 4 full years to date. However, those four years have generated four regional winning champion teams, with the most recent including former 8th graders Catherine Xue, Michael Winer, Bendeguz Offertaler, Sarah Wagner, Victor Xu.

===Chess Club===
The Chess Club possesses several chess trophies, and took second place at the 2008 USCF-rated Maryland Scholastic Chess Championships.

===MathCounts===
MathCounts participates in math competitions at the chapter and state level each year. It is held by Magnet Geometry and Magnet Algebra II teacher, Sarah Manchester. The group has also sent students to the national level, representing the state of Maryland. Their team has come in first place at the state level competition since TPMS's MathCounts team was founded.

== Notable alumni ==
&lt;!--Please add new names to the list alphabetically by last name--&gt;
===Sports===
* [[Steve Francis]], NBA All-Star with the Houston Rockets, Orlando Magic, and New York Knicks

===Arts and Media===
* [[Connie Chung]], journalist
* [[Goldie Hawn]], actress (Class of 1959)
* [[Ron Holloway]], tenor saxophonist (Class of 1968)
* [[Rick Leventhal]], broadcast journalist, Correspondent, [[Fox News Channel]] (Class of 1974)

== References ==
&lt;references/&gt;

== External links ==
* [http://www.mcps.k12.md.us/schools/takomaparkms/ Takoma Park Middle School]
* [http://www.mcps.k12.md.us/schools/takomaparkms/administration/magnet/intro.shtml Mathematics/Science/Computer Science Magnet Program]
* [http://web.archive.org/web/20031030025556/http://tpmsbluechips.com Blue Chips Online]
* [http://www.tpmspta.org Takoma Park Middle School PTA]

{{Montgomery County Public Schools}}

[[Category:Middle schools in Maryland]]
[[Category:Public schools in Montgomery County, Maryland]]
[[Category:Magnet schools in Maryland]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
