<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="355699" ns="0" title="Salafi"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{dablink|Salafism is also used sometimes as a synonym of [[Wahhabism]].}}
{{Cleanup|date=May 2011}}
A '''Salafi''' come from [[Sunni Islam]] ({{lang-ar|سلفي}}) is a follower of an [[Islam|Islamic]] movement, '''Salafiyyah''', that is supposed to take the ''Salaf'' who lived during the [[Patristics|patristic]] period of early [[Islam]] as model examples.&lt;ref&gt;''Ghazali And The Poetics Of Imagination'', by Ebrahim Moosa ISBN 0-8078-5612-6 – Page 21&lt;/ref&gt; The word ''Salafi'' should not be confused with the Arabic word ''[[Salaf]]'' (&quot;predecessor&quot; or &quot;forefather&quot;), and the first three Muslim generations are collectively referred to as &quot;''as-Salaf as-Saleh''&quot;, or The Pious Predecessors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://muttaqun.com/salafiyyah.html |title=Dawat-us-Salafiyyah (Call of those who preceded us) |publisher=Muttaqun.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; The generations are specifically called the ''[[Sahabah]]'' (&quot;Companions&quot;), the ''[[Tabi‘un]]'' (&quot;Followers&quot;) and the ''[[Tabi‘ al-Tabi‘in]]'' (&quot;Followers of the Followers&quot;). These three generations and their understanding of the texts and tenets of Islam are considered by the Salafis as the Islamic [[orthodoxy]]. Salafism has usually been used by [[Sunni Islam|Sunni]] theologians since the fifth Muslim generation or earlier to differentiate the creed of the first three generations from subsequent variations in creed and methodology.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=[http://www.alsaha.com/sahat/6/topics/77466 alasha.com]|title=Salafiyyah is not a sect amongst sects, by Shaikh Saleh al-Fawzan|publisher= http://www.alsaha.com/date=5/24/2004 |accessdate= 10/19/2010}}  &lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;مجموع الفتاوى 4/ 149 Compilation of Verdicts, Sheikh ul-Islam Ahmad ibn Taimiyyah&lt;/ref&gt; Landmarks in the history of Salafi [[da'wah]] are [[Ahmad ibn Hanbal]] (d.240 AH / 855 AD) who is known among Salafis as ''[[Imam]] Ahl al-[[Sunnah]]'', and one of the three scholars commonly titled with the honorific ''[[Sheikh ul-Islam]]'', namely, Taqi ad-Deen [[Ibn Taymiyyah]] (d.728 AH / 1328 AD) and [[Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya|Ibn al-Qayyim]] (d.751 AH / 1350).&lt;ref&gt; التجديد بمفهومية Renewal and its Understanding, Shaikh Muhammad Aman al-Jaamee, Part 1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;صور من الجاهليات المعاصرة Glimpses From the Modern Jahiliyyah, Shaikh Muhammad Amaan al-Jaamee&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt; سلسلة مفهوم السلفية Understanding Salafiyyah, A Series On, by Shaikh Muhammad Naasir ad-Deen al-Albaani, Parts 1-2, 6&lt;/ref&gt;

In contemporary times, Salafism has become associated with literalist and puritanical approaches to Islamic theology. In the West the term Salafi has become particularly associated with Muslims who espouse violent [[jihad]] against civilians as a legitimate expression of Islam, the so-called [[Salafist jihadism|Salafi Jihadis]].&lt;ref&gt;Dr Abdul-Haqq Baker, , ''Extremists in Our Midst: Confronting Terror,'' Palgrave Macmillan, 2011&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Definition==
Salafis view the first three generations of Muslims&amp;mdash;the Sahabah, or Companions of the [[Prophets of Islam|Islamic prophet]] [[Muhammad]], and the two succeeding generations after them, the Tabi‘un and the Tabi‘ al-Tabi‘in&amp;mdash;as an eternal model for all succeeding Muslim generations, especially in their beliefs and methodology of understanding the texts, but also in their method of worship, mannerisms, morality, piety and conduct. This belief is based on a number of sources in the [[Qur'an]] and [[Sunnah]], such as the narration in Saheeh al-Bukhari of [[`Abd Allah ibn `Umar]] (a companion of Muhammad) who narrated that Muhammad said: {{Quote|&quot;The best people are those of my generation, and then those who will come after them (the next generation), and then those who will come after them (i.e. the next generation),...&quot;|''[[Sahih al-Bukhari]]'' collected by [[Muhammad al-Bukhari]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|bukhari|usc=yes|8|76|437}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
In other narrations, it is indicated that there will then follow a group of people who will falsely bear witness of Islam,&lt;ref&gt;{{Hadith-usc|bukhari|usc=yes|3|48|819}}&lt;/ref&gt; as occurred with the beginning of factionalism and the spread of innovations with [[Siege of Uthman|the murder]] of [[Uthman ibn Affan]], the third Sunni [[caliph]].

The principal tenet of Salafism is that the Islam that was preached by Muhammad and practiced by his Companions, as well as the second and third generations succeeding them, was pure, unadulterated, and, therefore, the ultimate authority for the interpretation of the two sources of revelation given to Muhammad, namely the Qur'an and the Sunnah.&lt;ref&gt;Sharh Usool I'tiqaad Ahl as-Sunnah wal-Jama'ah, al-Laalika'ee, tahqeeq of Nash'at Kamaal Misree, 1/7-9&lt;/ref&gt; This is not interpreted to mean an imitation of cultural norms or trends that are not part of the legislated worship of Islam, but rather the fundamental beliefs of Islam, or ''[[Islamic theology|'Aqeedah]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alagidah.com/vb/showthread.php?p=27549|title= ضوابط البدعة (The meaning and conditions of bida')|publisher= http://alagidah.com|date= 07/2009|accessdate= 10/12/2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The term Salafi is sometimes replaced with &quot;[[Wahhabi]]&quot;, especially in American [[Oriental studies|Orientalist]] and popular literature in a derogatory sense. However, the term is used overwhelmingly so in [[Shia Islam|Shi'ite]] and many [[Sufism|Sufi]] references, where it is replaced with the word &quot;Wahhabi&quot; almost as a rule. The term &quot;Wahhabism&quot; is, in turn, connected to various accusations of heresies and practices quite unknown to Salafi adherents, and is often spoken of in the American media in relation to terrorism, or &quot;extremist&quot; Islam.

Salafis categorically reject the Wahhabi label, because they consider it to be largely unfounded, an object of some controversy.&lt;ref&gt;The Wahhabi Myth, H.J.Oliver&lt;/ref&gt; Salafis will argue that [[Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab]] did not establish a new school of thought but rather revived the pure, unadulterated Islam that was practiced by the earliest generations of Muslims.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}} Abd-al-Wahhab's writings, such as his magnum opus, ''Kitab at-Tawheed'' (The Book of Tawheed), plus others such as ''Masaa'il al-Jaahiliyyah'' (Aspects of the Days of Ignorance), and ''Kashf ash-Shubuhaat'' (A Removal of the Doubts) are agreed upon almost without exception{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}, and are rarely considered by those that use the term &quot;Wahhabi&quot; for an understanding of &quot;Wahhabism&quot;{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}, or those who denigrate his methodology and beliefs openly, further consolidating the perceived intent of malice, or misconception.{{Citation needed|date=March 2011}}

While the ascription of &quot;Salafi&quot; has most commonly been used in the [[Arab World]], and possibly even more so now by Muslims in the West, it is usually contextual, and secondary to the more common term ''Ahl-as-Sunnah'' (i.e., &quot;People of the ''Sunnah''&quot;). ''[[Ahl al-Hadith|Ahl al-Hadeeth]]'' (The People of [[Hadith|Hadeeth]]) is more often used in the [[Indian subcontinent]] within the same context, identifying the adherents of Salafi orthodoxy, while used more in Arabic academia to specifically indicate the scholars and students of Hadeeth. All are considered to bear the same or similar connotation and have been used interchangeably by Muslim scholars throughout the ages, Ahl al-Hadeeth possibly being the oldest recorded term used to describe the adherents to the beliefs of the first three generations.&lt;ref&gt; شرف أصحاب الحديث (The Noble Status of the People of Hadeeth, al-Khateeb al-Baghdaadi&lt;/ref&gt; Ahl as-Sunnah is overwhelmingly used by  Muslim scholars, including Salafi scholars, but often by other than the Salafis, such as the [[Ash'ari]] sect, leading to a greater use of the term &quot;Salafi&quot; in the context of differentiation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://islameye.com/%D8%AD%D9%83%D9%85-%D9%82%D9%88%D9%84-%D8%A7%D9%86%D8%A7-%D8%B3%D9%84%D9%81%D9%89-%D9%84%D9%84%D8%B4%D9%89%D8%AE-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%86%D9%89-t4699s150.html|title= حكم قول انا سلفي (The Ruling On Saying &quot;I am Salafi&quot;, Shaikh al-Albani|publisher= [http://islameye.com islameye.com]|date= |accessdate= 10/12/2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History of the Salafi Da'wa==
From the perspective of Salafis, the history of the Salafi [[dawah]] starts with Muhammad himself. They consider themselves direct followers of his teachings as outlined in the Qur'an and ''Sunnah'' (prophetic traditions), and wish to emulate the piety of the first three generations of Islam (the Salaf). All later scholars are merely reviver's (not 'founders') of the original practices. Modern scholars may only come to teach (or remind) Muslims of the instructions of the original followers of Islam, who based their beliefs and actions on the Qur'an and Sunnah.

===Etymology===
An example of early usage of the word ''salaf'' is in the hadith of Muhammad who noted, &quot;I am the best ''Salaf'' for you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://al-ibaanah.com/articles.php?ArtID=97 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20080304023423/http://al-ibaanah.com/articles.php?ArtID=97 |archivedate=2008-03-04 |title=Why the Word Salafee? |publisher=Web.archive.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early usage of the term as an ascription appears in the book ''Al-Ansaab'' by Abu Sa'd Abd al-Kareem al-Sama'ni, who died in the year 1166 (562 of the [[Islamic calendar]]). Under the entry for the ascription ''al-Salafi'' he stated, &quot;This is an ascription to the salaf, or the predecessors, and the adoptation of their school of thought based upon what I have heard.&quot; He then mentions an example or more of people who were utilizing this ascription in his time.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Ansab'', by Abu Sa'd Abd al-Kareem Al-Sama'ni, vol. 7, pg. 168, photocopied from the ''Da'iah Al-Ma'arif Al-Uthmaniyah'' edition by the ''Al-Faruq'' publishing company of Egypt, no date provided. The names of those using this ascription were described by the verifier as being blank in all of the manuscript copies of the book, he obtained them by means of cross referencing.&lt;/ref&gt; In commenting upon as-Sam'aanee's saying, [[Ali ibn al-Athir|Ibn al-Athir]] noted: &quot;And a group were known by this ascription.&quot; Thus the term Salafi, and its ascription to the group, was a matter known in the time of early Islamic scholars.&lt;ref&gt;''A Reply to the Doubts of the Qutubiyyah Concerning Ascription to Sunnah and Salafiyyah'', page 29,, [http://www.salafipublications.com/ SalafiPublications.com], Article ID: SLF010004.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Early examples of usage====
* Some scholars, such as Ibn Taymiyyah, have noted: &quot;There is no criticism for the one who proclaims the ''[[madh'hab]]'' of the Salaf, who attaches himself to it and refers to it. Rather, it is obligatory to accept that from him by unanimous agreement because the way of the Salaf is nothing but the truth.&quot;&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com&gt;''Statements from the Salaf on Ascription to the Salaf'', [http://www.salafipublications.com/ SalafiPublications.com], Article ID: SLF010001&lt;/ref&gt;

* The term ''salafi'' has been used to describe to theological position of particular scholars. Abo al-Hasan Ali ibn Umar al-Daraqutuni (d. 995 C.E., 385 A.H.) was described by [[al-Dhahabi]] as: &quot;Never having entered into rhetoric or polemics, instead he was ''salafi''.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Siyar pg. 457&quot;&gt;''Siyar 'Alam al-Nubula'', by al-Dhahbi, vol. 16, pg. 457, no. 332, Mua'ssash al-Risalah, Beirut, 11th edition, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Also, al-Dhahabi described [[Ibn al-Salah]], a prominent 12th century hadith specialist, as: &quot;Firm in his religiosity, ''salafi'' in his generality and correct in his denomination. [He] refrained from falling into common pitfalls, believed in [[Allah]] and in what Allah has informed us of from His names and description.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Siyar 'Alam al-Nubala'', vol. 23, pg. 142-3, by al-Dhahabi, Muassah al-Risalah, Beirut, 11th Edition, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;

* In another of his works, ''Tadhkirat al-huffaz'', al-Dhahabi said of Ibn al-Salah: &quot;I say: He was ''salafi'', of sound creed, abstaining from the interpretations of the scholars of [[Kalam|rhetoric]], believing in what has been textually established, without recourse to unjustified interpretation or elaboration.&lt;ref&gt;''Tadhkirah al-huffaz'', vol. 4, pg. 1431, Da'irah al-Ma'arif al-'Uthmaniyyah, India.&lt;/ref&gt;

* In his book, ''Tabsir al-Muntabih'', [[Ibn Hajar al-Asqalani]] mentioned the ascription ''al-Salafi'' and named Abd al-Rahman ibn Abdillah ibn Ahmad Al-Sarkhasi al-Salafi as an example of its usage. Ibn Hajar then said: &quot;And, likewise, the one ascribing to the ''salaf''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Tabsir al-Muntabih Bitahrir al-Mushtabih'', vol. 2, pg. 738, published by: ''Al-Mu'assasah al-Misriyyah al-'Ammah Lil-Talif wa Al-Anba' wa al-Nashr'', edited by: Ali al-Bajawi, no additional information.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Ibn Hajar al-Asqalani also used the term, ''salafi'' to describe Muhammad ibn al-Qaasim ibn Sufyan al-Misri al-Maliki (d. 966 C.E., 355 A.H.) He said that al-Malaiki was: &quot;''Salafi al-madh'hab'' – ''salafi'' in his school of thought.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Lisan al-Mizan'', by Ibn Hajar, vol. 5, pg. 348, no. 1143, Dar al-Kitab al-Islami, no additional information; it is apparently a reprint of the original Indian print. The quoted segment of Ibn Hajar's biography for al-Misri originated from Ibn Hajar, as this was not included in al-Dhahabi's biography of the same individual (who is named 'ibn Sha'ban' instead of ibn Sufyan).&lt;/ref&gt;

===Muhammad Abduh, Jamal al-Din Afghani, Rashid Rida===
In the opinion of contemporary historians, the use of the word Salafi to describe a revival movement within Islam started in [[Egypt]] in the mid 19th century among intellectuals at [[al-Azhar University]], the preeminent center of Islamic learning, located in [[Cairo]]. Prominent among them were [[Muhammad Abduh]] (1849–1905), [[Jamal-al-Din Afghani]] (1839–1897) and [[Rashid Rida]] (1865–1935).&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Islam and the Muslim World'', Macmillan Reference, 2004, v.2, p.609&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The New Encyclopedia of Islam'' by Cyril Glasse, Rowman and Littlefield, 2001, p.19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''The Oxford Dictionary of Islam'' by John L. Esposito, OUP, 2003, p.275&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Historical Dictionary of Islam'' by Ludwig W. Wadamed, Scarecrow Press, 2001, p.233&lt;/ref&gt;

These early reformers recognized the need for [[al-Nahda|an Islamic revival]], noticing the changing fortunes in the Islamic world following the [[Age of Enlightenment|Enlightenment]] in Europe. Al-Afghani was a political activist, whereas Abduh, an educator, and head of Egypt's religious law courts, sought gradual social reform and legal reform &quot;to make [[sharia]] relevant to modern problems.&quot;

Abduh argued that the early generations of Muslims (the ''salaf al-salihin'', hence the name ''Salafiyya'', which was self-ascribed to Abduh and his disciples) had produced a vibrant civilization because they had creatively interpreted the Qur'an and hadith to answer the needs of their times.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of Islam and the Muslim World'', Macmillan Reference, 2004, p.7&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Salafis themselves disavow these figures. One prominent Salafi website, for example, describing itself as promoting &quot;the creed and manhaj of the salaf us-saalih – pure and clear,&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.salafipublications.com/ |title=salafipublications.com |publisher=salafipublications.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; includes claims that al-Afghani and Muhammad ‘Abduh were &quot;known [[Freemasonry|freemasons]] and ... [show] great misguidance in their ideologies,&quot; and alleges they were interested in an &quot;[[Anti-imperialism|anti-colonial]] political movement&quot; rather than &quot;orthodox Islam&quot; or &quot;the way of the Salaf,&quot; but their call was deceptively surrounded with slogans of `returning back to the way of the forefathers.`&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.salafipublications.com/sps/sp.cfm?subsecID=MNJ18&amp;articleID=MNJ180008&amp;articlePages=1 &quot;Historical Development of the Methodologies of al-Ikhwaan al-Muslimeen And Their Effect and Influence Upon Contemporary Salafee Dawah: Part 8 Updated. ] accessed 12 May 2007.p.5&lt;/ref&gt;{{Clarify|date=October 2009}}

===Muhammad ibn Abd-al-Wahhab===
{{Main|Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab}}
Many Salafis today point also to Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab as the first figure in the modern era to push for a return to the religious practices of the ''salaf as-salih'' or &quot;righteous predecessors&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.salafipublications.com/sps/sp.cfm?subsecID=SLF02&amp;articleID=SLF020001&amp;articlePages=1 |title=The Principles of Salafiyyah |publisher=Salafipublications.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; His evangelizing in 18th century [[Saudi Arabia]] was a call to return to what were the practices of the early generations of Muslims.

His works, especially ''Kitab at-Tawhid'', are still widely read by Salafis around the world today, and the majority of Salafi scholars still reference his works frequently.&lt;ref&gt;Shaikh Muhammad Ibn Abdul-Wahhab: His Salafi Creed, Reformist Movement and Scholars' Praise of Him, 4th ed. by Judge Ahmad Ibn 'Hajar Ibn Muhammad al-Butami al-Bin Ali, Ad-Dar as-Salafiyyah, Kuwait, 1983, p.108-164&lt;/ref&gt;  After his death, his views flourished under his descendants, the [[Al ash-Sheikh]], and the generous financing of the [[House of Saud]] and initiated the current worldwide Salafi movement.{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}}

==Beliefs and practices==
Just who, or what groups and movements, qualify as ''Salafi'' remains in dispute. Some define the term broadly, including the [[Muslim Brotherhood]] (who include the term Salafi in the &quot;about us&quot; section of their website).&lt;ref&gt;[http://ikhwanonline.net/Article.asp?ArtID=120&amp;SecID=0 ikhwanonline.net]{{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Others exclude the Muslim Brotherhood&lt;ref&gt;[http://salafipublications.com/sps/ Hasan al-Banna and the Ways and Means of Da'wah] Hasan al-Banna, the founder of the Muslim Brotherhood, &quot;... is the imaam of this crooked path/way which makes permissible for itself every single way or means for the sake of actualizing what they call the 'benefit of the da'wah' but [in reality] it is nothing but the 'benefits of dejected hizbiyyah (party-spirit)'...&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt; since they believe or claim the group commits religious innovations (''[[bid‘ah]]'').

===Staunch monotheism===
Salafis place a particular emphasis on monotheism (''tawhid''); they condemn many Muslim practices which have  become common as [[polytheism]] ([[Shirk (Islam)|''shirk'']]). Salafis believe, based on scriptural evidence, that widespread Muslim practices such as venerating the graves of Islamic prophets and [[Saint#Islam|saints]] are ''shirk''. Salafis in general oppose both Sufi and Shia doctrines, which Salafis regard as having many aspects of ''shirk'', ''bid‘ah'' and [[tawassul|impermissible intercession]] of religious figures.The Salafis state:

{{Quote|Likewise if you want to know the Salafi creed we first and foremost look at the statements of the Messenger of Allah, the Sahaba, the Scholars of the Tabieen like [[Hasan al-Basri|Hasan-al Basri]], Awzaaee and the scholars of the Salaf.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://asalafiyaleicester.wordpress.com/2010/03/14/a-critical-analysis-of-the-sufi-creed-of-the-elders-of-the-deobandi-and-the-tablighi-jamaah/ |title=A Critical Analysis of the Sufi Creed of the Elders of the Deobandi and the Tableeghi Jamaah « Asalafiya in Leicester |publisher=Asalafiyaleicester.wordpress.com |date=2010-03-14 |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Prohibition of rhetoric and of speculative theology===
Salafis reject Islamic speculative [[theology]] (also known as ''[[kalam]]'''), which involves the usage of discourse and debate in the development of the Islamic creed. They consider this process as a foreign import from [[Ancient Greek philosophy|Greek philosophy]] (such as [[Plato]] and [[Aristotle]]) and alien to the original practice of Islam. They note that the [[Imam]], Al-Dhahabi (d. 748H / 1348) said:

{{Quote|It is authentically related from ad-Daaraqutnee that he said: There is nothing more despised by me than kalam (innovating speech and rhetoric). I say: He never entered into kalam, nor argumentation. Rather, he was a Salafi (a follower of the Salaf).&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com /&gt;
}}

===Abstaining from &quot;innovative&quot; beliefs and practices===
Salafis maintain that ''bid‘ah'' or innovation in the Islamic creed or actions of worship are totally without sanction, and, based on scriptural evidence, that they are unacceptable to [[God in Islam|God]]. Muslims in one part of the world who engage in ''bid‘ah'' practices, such as circumambulating around shrines of saints,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ahya.org/amm/modules.php?name=Sections&amp;op=viewarticle&amp;artid=191c |title=Shocking Images of Graves and Tombs from Banglore, India |publisher=Ahya.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Mawlid|celebrating Muhammad's birthday]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ahya.org/amm/modules.php?name=Sections&amp;op=viewarticle&amp;artid=36 |title=Who Really Loves the Messenger of Allah? |publisher=Ahya.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}
&lt;/ref&gt; or commemorating the day of the death of a saint (&quot;[[urs]]&quot;), may not receive their newly invented practice with much welcome in other areas of the [[Muslim world|Islamic world]] where the practice is totally foreign.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}

Salafis assert further that actions stemming from a practice rooted in ''bid‘ah'' will not result in any reward in spite of a worshipper's good intentions and are dangerous to the Islamic creed since they replace or corrupt the religious practices (&quot;Sunnah&quot;) of Muhammad. Salafis assert that if such practices increase a devotee's faith, Muhammad would have known about it and assuredly directed Muslims to do such acts since he was the best worshipper amongst mankind and most dutiful.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://www.al-ibaanah.com/articles.php?ArtID=98 Every Innovation is Misguidance and all misguidance leads to hell-fire] {{Dead link|date=February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In showing textual support for the impermissibility of bid‘ah or innovation in the Islamic creed, Salafis frequently cite a Sunni tradition attributed to Muhammad which states: &quot;Every innovation is misguidance and going astray.&quot;&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;''Bid'ah'', [http://www.salafipublications.com/ SalafiPublications.com], Knowledge Base – Bid'ah section&lt;/ref&gt;

They also point out that Muhammad himself warned against the people of innovation, from befriending, supporting, or taking from them, as he stated:

{{Quote|Whoever innovates or accommodates an innovator then upon him is the curse of Allah, [[Islamic view of angels|His Angels]], and the whole of mankind.&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com /&gt;}}

{{Quote|Whoever introduces into our matter (religion) that which is not a part of it, will have it (his innovation) rejected &lt;ref&gt;''Explanation of the Hadeeth &quot;Whoever introduced into our matter..'',, [http://www.islaam.com/Article.aspx?id=211/ islaam.com],&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

{{Quote|Ibn Hajar said of this hadith, &quot;This Hadith is considered one of the basis of Islam and a pillar of the religion.&quot; An-Nawawi said, &quot;This Hadith deserves to be preserved, publicly announced and (firmly) implemented in rejecting the impermissible.&quot;

At-Turaqi said, &quot;This is a Hadith that deserves to be called 'one half of the proofs of the religion.' This is because the proof (evidence, Text, etc.) is used to confirm or reject a rule, and this Hadith is a tremendous tool to confirm or reject all religious rulings.&quot;

In addition, ibn Rajab said &quot;This Hadith is one of the major basis of Islam, just like the Hadith 'Actions are only considered according to the intentions...', which is the scale with which the actions, in both their hidden and apparent aspects, are weighed.&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;
''Explanation of the Hadeeth &quot;Whoever introduced into our matter..'',, [http://www.islaam.com/Article.aspx?id=211/ islaam.com]
&lt;/ref&gt; 

Salafis often quote many companions of Muhammad, including a hadith in which [[`Abd Allah ibn `Abbas]] states:

{{Quote|Indeed the most detestable of things to Allah are the innovations,&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com /&gt;}}
and, a tradition in which `Abd Allah ibn `Umar states:
{{Quote|Every innovation is misguidance, even if the people see it as something good.&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com /&gt;
}}

They also note that earlier generations of Muslims like [[Malik ibn Anas]] conveyed similar sentiments:

{{Quote|Whosoever introduces into Islam an innovation, and holds it to be something good, has indeed alleged that Muhammad has betrayed his message.}}
Imam Malik then stressed:
{{Quote|Read the saying of Allah – the Most Blessed, the Most High: &quot;This day I have perfected your Religion for you, completed My favour upon you and I have chosen for you Islam as your Religion.&quot; [[Al-Ma'ida|Al-Maa‘idah]] 5:3&lt;ref&gt;{{cite quran|5|3|s=ns|t=s}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Malik then concluded:
{{Quote|So that which was not part of the Religion at that time, cannot be part of the Religion today...And the last part of this Ummah cannot be rectified, except by that which rectified its first part.&quot; Similarly, they state that [[Abū Ḥanīfa]] emphasized: &quot;Adhere to the athar (narration) and the tareeqah (way) of the Salaf (Pious Predecessors) and beware of newly invented matters (in Religion) for all of it is innovation.&lt;ref name=salafipublications.com /&gt;}}

Likewise, Shaikh Saalih Aal ash-Shaikh, Minister of Islamic Affairs of Saudi Arabia, stated:

{{Quote|Muslims are of two groups: Salafis and Khalafis. As for the Salafis, they are the followers of As-Salaf-us-Saalih (the 'pious predecessors' from the first three generations of Muslims). And as for the Khalafis, they are the followers of the understanding of the Khalaf and they are also called Innovators – since everyone who is not pleased and satisfied with the path of the Salaf-us-Saalih, in knowledge and action, understanding and ''[[fiqh]]'', then he is a khalafi, an innovator.&lt;ref&gt;''A Reply to the Doubts of the Qutubiyyah Concerning Ascription to Sunnah and Salafiyyah'', page 24, [http://www.salafipublications.com/ SalafiPublications.com], Article ID: SLF010004&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

===Practices===
Whichever definition is used, Salafis idealize an uncorrupted, pure Islamic religious community. They believe that Islam's decline after the early generations results from religious innovations (''bid‘ah'') and from an  abandoning of pure Islamic teachings; that an Islamic revival will only result through the emulation of the three early generations of Muslims and the purging of foreign influences from the religion.

Salafis, similar to adherents of most other Islamic denominations, place great emphasis on ritual - not only in prayer but in every activity in daily life. Many are careful to always use three fingers when eating, drink water in three pauses with the right hand while sitting,&lt;ref&gt;''Six Points of Tabligh'', the chapter on &quot;Desired Manners of Eating and Drinking&quot; includes 26 norms on the etiquette of eating and drinking. From: ''Globalized Islam : the Search for a New Ummah'', by [[Olivier Roy (professor)|Olivier Roy]], [[Columbia University Press]], 2004
&lt;/ref&gt; make sure their [[Jellabiya|galabea]] or other garment worn by them does not extend below the ankle — so as to follow the example of Muhammad and his companions as they endeavor to make religion part of every activity in life.

===On following a madh'hab===
Salafis believe that following only the Qur'an and the Hadith and the [[Ijma]] (consensus) of the [[Ulama]], are sufficient guidance for the believing Muslim. 

As the Salafi ''[[da'wa]]'' is a methodology and not a ''[[madh'hab]]'', Salafis can come from the [[Maliki]], the [[Shafi'i]], the Hanbali, or the [[Hanafi]] schools of law.&lt;ref name=global&gt;GlobalSecurity.org [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/intro/islam-salafi.htm Salafi Islam]&lt;/ref&gt; Salafis accept teaching of all four school of law only if their rulings are supported by clear and authenticated evidences from the Qur'an and Sunnah, they are not divided on the question of adherence to the four recognized schools of legal interpretation (madh'habs). For example, Ibn Taymiyyah followed the Hanbali madhhab. Some of his students (such as Ibn Kathir and al-Dhahabi) followed the Shafi`i madhhab. Other students (such as [[Ibn Abi al-Izz]]) follow the Hanafi madhhab.

Salafis themselves base their jurisprudence directly on the Qur'an and Sunnah as applied and practiced by the first three generations of Muslims. Their interpretation is based on a strict form of [[Athari]] theology.

==Contemporary Salafism==
===Modern use===
In modern times the word has come to have two sometimes dissimilar definitions. The first, used by academics and historians, refers to denote &quot;a school of thought which surfaced in the second half of the 19th century as a reaction to the spread of European ideas,&quot; and &quot;sought to expose the roots of modernity within Muslim civilization.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;KepelJihad&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=OLvTNk75hUoC&amp;dq=islamism&amp;printsec=frontcover |title='&amp;#39;Jihad'&amp;#39; By Gilles Kepel, Anthony F. Roberts |publisher=Books.google.com |date= 2006-02-24|accessdate=2010-04-18|isbn=9781845112578}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The second, quite different use of the word favored by self-described contemporary salafis, defines a salafis as a Muslim who follows &quot;literal, traditional ... injunctions of the sacred texts&quot; rather than the &quot;somewhat freewheeling interpretation&quot; of earlier &quot;salafis.&quot; These ''salafis'' look to Ibn Taymiyyah, not the 19th century figures of Muhammad Abduh, Jamal al-Din, and Rashid Rida.&lt;ref name=&quot;KepelJihad&quot;/&gt;

===Current disagreements and division===
A majority of Salafi scholars stand firmly against the present-day manifestations of [[jihad]], particularly as it relates to terrorism and the killing of civilians and innocents. They hold their opinion as:
{{Quote|No individual has the right to take the law into his own hands on any account. Even the closest of Prophet Muhammad's companions never killed a single of his opponents even when invectives were hurled at him day and night in the first thirteen years of his Da'wah at [[Mecca|Makkah]]. Nor did they kill anyone in retaliation when he was pelted with stones at [[Ta’if|Ta'if]].}}

In recent years, Salafis have come to be associated with the jihad of [[Al-Qaeda]] and related groups that advocate the killing of civilians, which are opposed by most other Muslim groups and governments, including the Saudi government. Debate continues today over the appropriate methods of reform, ranging from violent &quot;Qutubi [[Offensive jihad|jihadism]]&quot; to lesser politicized proselytizing.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

Despite some similarities, the different contemporary self-proclaimed [[Qutbism|Qutubi]] groups often strongly disapprove of each other and deny the others Islamic character.&lt;ref name=&quot;thewahhabimyth.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;thewahhabimyth.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Abou El Fadl, Khaled, ''The Great Theft'' Harper San Francisco, 2005, p.62-8&lt;/ref&gt;

===Spread and effect===
From intelligent academics and professionals to rootless immigrants in [[Europe]], Salafism is attractive because of its claim to authenticity and textual associations. For those living in the metropolises of the [[Middle East]], it offers an emotionally and theologically rich alternative to the slogans of [[Arab nationalism]] and a puritan alternative to the mystical Sufi tradition.

Salafism often appeals to younger Muslims as a way to differentiate themselves from the beliefs of parents and grandparents because it is seen as &quot;pure&quot;, stripped of &quot;the local, superstitious, and customary Muslim practices of their families' countries of origin&quot;. It often confers a sense of [[moral superiority]]. Salafism can be said to have a potent appeal because it underscores Islam's universality.&lt;ref name='Next'&gt;''The Next Attack'', By [[Daniel Benjamin]] [[Steven Simon]], ISBN 0-8050-7941-6 – Page 55&lt;/ref&gt;

Salafism insists on the literal truth of Muslim scripture and what might be called a strict constructionist brand of sharia or religious law.&lt;ref name='Next' /&gt; Salafism may have more appeal than [[secularism]] by appropriating secularisms' traditional role of defending the socially and politically weak against the powerful.&lt;ref&gt;''Brief History of Islam'', Hassan Hanafi, ISBN 1-4051-0900-9 – Page 258-259&lt;/ref&gt;

The spread of Salafism has prompted political leaders in the Middle East to accommodate a greater role for religion in public policy.&lt;ref&gt;''The Next Attack'', By [[Daniel Benjamin]], [[Steven Simon]], ISBN 0-8050-7941-6 – Page 274&lt;/ref&gt;

===Association with 'Wahhabism'===
{{Main|Wahhabi}}
As the second definition has predominated, the terms &quot;Wahhabism&quot; – which also pays great respect to Ibn Taymiyyah – and &quot;Salafism&quot; are now often used interchangeably. Followers of Salafiyyah consider it wrong to be called &quot;Wahhabis&quot; due to the 16th Name of Allah, al-Wahhab (the Bestower) and to be called a &quot;Wahhabi,&quot; they see it as being associated equal to Allah, which the Salafis strictly prohibit anything being associated with Allah. Wahhabism has been called a &quot;belittling&quot; and derogatory term for Salafi,&lt;ref name=&quot;thewahhabimyth.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.thewahhabimyth.com/salafism.htm What is a Salafi and What is Salafism?]&lt;/ref&gt; while another source defines it as &quot;a particular orientation within Salafism,&quot;&lt;ref name=global/&gt; an orientation some consider ultra-conservative,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/09/04/AR2006090401107_2.html |title=Washington Post, For Conservative Muslims, Goal of Isolation a Challenge |publisher=Washingtonpost.com |date=2007-01-15 |accessdate=2010-04-18 | first=Caryle | last=Murphy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;John L. Esposito, ''What Everyone Needs to Know About Islam'', p.50&lt;/ref&gt; and yet another describes it as a formerly separate current of Islamic thought that appropriated &quot;language and symbolism of Salafism&quot; until the two became &quot;practically indistinguishable&quot; in the 1970s.&lt;ref&gt;Abou El Fadl, Khaled M., ''The Great Theft'', HarperSanFrancisco, 2005, p.79&lt;/ref&gt;

Scholar Trevor Stanley states that while the origins of the terms Wahhabism and Salafism &quot;were quite distinct&quot; – &quot;Wahhabism was a pared-down Islam that rejected modern influences, while Salafism sought to reconcile Islam with modernism&quot; – they both shared a rejection of &quot;traditional&quot; teachings on Islam in favor of direct, more puritan reinterpretation.

Stéphane Lacroix, a postdoctoral fellow and lecturer at [[Institut d'Études Politiques de Paris|Sciences Po]] in [[Paris]], also affirmed a distinction between the two: &quot;As opposed to Wahhabism, Salafism refers here to all the hybridations that have taken place since the 1960s between the teachings of Muhammad bin ‘Abd al-Wahhab and other Islamic schools of thought. [[Muhammad Nasiruddin al-Albani|Al-Albani’s]] discourse can therefore be a form of Salafism, while being critical of Wahhabism.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Albani’s Revolutionary Approach to Hadith'', by Stéphane Lacroix, ISIM Review, issue 21, Spring 2008, pg. 7, as appears at [http://www.isim.nl/files/review_21/review_21-6.pdf ISIM Review ''Al-Albani’s Revolutionary Approach to Hadith'']{{Dead link|date=April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

But despite their beginnings &quot;as two distinct movements&quot;, the migration of Muslim Brotherhood members from Egypt to Saudi Arabia and [[Faisal of Saudi Arabia|Saudi King Faisal]]'s &quot;embrace of Salafi [[pan-Islamism]] resulted in cross-pollination between Muhammad ibn Abd-al-Wahhab's teachings on tawhid, shirk and bid‘ah and Salafi interpretations of ahadith (the sayings of Muhammad).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Stanley |first=Trevor |url=http://www.jamestown.org/single/?no_cache=1&amp;tx_ttnews%5Bswords%5D=8fd5893941d69d0be3f378576261ae3e&amp;tx_ttnews%5Bany_of_the_words%5D=%20Trevor%20Stanley%20&amp;tx_ttnews%5Btt_news%5D=528&amp;tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D=7&amp;cHash=a5ad45ee77 |title=Understanding the Origins of Wahhabism and Salafism by Trevor Stanley |publisher=Jamestown.org |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comparison with Islamism===
{{Main|Islamism}}
Salafism differs from the earlier contemporary Islamic revival movements of the 1970s and 1980s commonly referred to as [[Islamism]], in that (at least many) Salafis reject not only [[Western culture|Western]] ideologies such as [[Socialism]] and [[Capitalism]], but also common Western concepts like economics, constitutions, political parties and revolution.

Salafi Muslims often promote not engaging in Western activities like politics, &quot;even by giving them an Islamic slant.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Globalized Islam : the Search for a New Ummah'', by [[Olivier Roy (professor)|Olivier Roy]], [[Columbia University Press]], 2004 (p.245)&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, it is thought that Muslims should stick to traditional activities, particularly Dawah. Salafis promote that the ''Sharia'' (Islamic law) takes precedence over civil or state law. Nevertheless, Salafis do not preach wilful ignorance of civil or state law. While preaching that the Sharia takes precedence, Salafi Muslims conform to civil or state law as far as they are required, for example in purchasing mandatory motor insurance. Here, a Salafi Muslim would purchase &quot;third party, fire and theft&quot; insurance in order to avoid going to jail, but he/she would not purchase &quot;fully comprehensive&quot; insurance because commercial insurance is seen as gambling.

===Criticism===
Salafism, or at least the so called &quot;puritanical&quot; forms of it, has been recently criticized by Professor [[Khaled Abou El Fadl]] of [[UCLA School of Law]]. El Fadl claims that the Salafi methodology &quot;drifted into stifling apologetics&quot; by the mid-20th century, a reaction against &quot;anxiety&quot; to &quot;render Islam compatible with modernity,&quot; by its leaders earlier in the century.&lt;ref&gt;Abou El Fadl, Khaled, ''The Great Theft,'' Harper San Francisco, 2005, p.77&lt;/ref&gt;

Some Salafi writers would allegedly claim, for example, that &quot;any meritorious or worthwhile modern institutions were first invented and realized by Muslims.&quot; The result was that &quot;an artificial sense of confidence and an intellectual lethargy&quot; developed, according to Abou El Fadl, &quot;that took neither the Islamic tradition nor&quot; the challenges of the modern world &quot;very seriously.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Abou El Fadl, Khaled, ''The Great Theft'' Harper San Francisco, 2005, p.78-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Abou El Fadl, Khaled, ''The Great Theft'' Harper San Francisco, 2005, p.52-56&lt;/ref&gt;

Egyptian scholar [[Tawfik Hamid]] says that Salafist [[Islamic fundamentalism|Muslim fundamentalists]] believe that Saudi Arabia's petroleum-based wealth is a divine gift, and that Saudi influence is sanctioned by God. Thus this extreme brand of Sunni Islam that spread from the Saudi Arabia to the rest of the Islamic world is regarded not merely as one interpretation of the religion but the only genuine interpretation. The expansion of violent and regressive Islam, he continues, began in the late 1970s, and can be traced precisely to the growing financial clout of Saudi Arabia. He says &quot;is puritanical, extreme and does, yes, mean that women can be beaten, [[Apostasy|apostates]] killed and [[Jews]] called pigs and monkeys.&quot;. Although he says this, the Holy Quran and authentic narrations of the Islamic Prophet forbid such things that Tawfik Hamid mentioned, such as violence and name-calling. &lt;ref name=&quot;Coren&quot;&gt;{{cite news|last=Coren|first=Michael|title=Hot for martyrdom|url=http://www.canada.com/nationalpost/news/issuesideas/story.html?id=eb74b136-3729-42a1-821b-77366f7af920|accessdate=17 June 2010|newspaper=CanWest MediaWorks Publications Inc.|date=November 3, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Salafism is intensely opposed by the [[Hui people|Hui]] [[Islam in China|Muslims in China]], by the Hanafi Sunni [[Gedimu]] and Sufi [[Ma Laichi|Khafiya]] and [[Jahriyya]]. So much so that even the [[Yihewani]] (Ikhwan) Chinese sect, which is fundamentalist and was founded by [[Ma Wanfu]] who was originally inspired by the Salafis, condemned Ma Debao and Ma Zhengqing as heretics when they attempted to introduce Salafism as the main form of Islam. Ma Debao established a Salafi school, called the Sailaifengye (Salafi) [[menhuan]] in [[Lanzhou]] and [[Linxia Hui Autonomous Prefecture|Linxia]], and it is a completely separate group than other [[Muslim groups in China|Muslim sects in China]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=hUEswLE4SWUC&amp;pg=PA72&amp;dq=ma+anliang&amp;q=wahhabism%20ma%20debao|title=China's Muslim Hui community: migration, settlement and sects|author=Michael Dillon|year=1999|publisher=Curzon Press|location=Richmond|page=208|isbn=0700710264, 9780700710263|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Salafis have a reputation for radicalism among the Chinese Gedimu and Yihewani groups. The Sunni Muslim Hui avoid Salafis, even if they are family members, and they constantly disagree.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=b21aKLh6_KkC&amp;pg=PA79&amp;dq=gedimu+ikhwan#v=onepage&amp;q=gedimu%20ikhwan&amp;f=false|title=Between Mecca and Beijing: modernization and consumption among urban Chinese Muslims|author=Maris Boyd Gillette|year=2000|publisher=Stanford University Press|location=|page=279|isbn=0804736944|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The amount of Salafis in China is so insignificant that they are not included on percentage lists of Muslim sects in China.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=imw_KFD5bsQC&amp;pg=PA458&amp;dq=gedimu+ikhwan#v=onepage&amp;q=kubrawiyya%20percent%20gedimu%20hui%20ma%20tong&amp;f=false|title=The Oxford history of Islam|author=John L. Esposito|year=1999|publisher=Oxford University Press US|location=|page=749|isbn=00195107993|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Persecution of Salafis===
The [[Kuomintang]] Sufi Muslim General [[Ma Bufang]], who backed the Yihewani (Ikhwan) Muslims, persecuted the Salafis, forcing them into hiding. They were not allowed to move or worship openly. The Yihewani had become secular and Chinese nationalists, and they considered the Salafiyya to be &quot;heterodox&quot; (xie jiao), and people who followed foreigners' teachings (waidao). Only after the [[Communist Party of China|Communists]] took over were the Salafis allowed to come out and worship openly again.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=wEih57-GWQQC&amp;pg=PA79&amp;dq=ma+bufang+secret+war#v=onepage&amp;q=ma%20bufang%20secret%20war&amp;f=false|title=Guide to Islamist Movements|author=BARRY RUBIN|year=2000|publisher=M.E. Sharpe|location=|page=800|isbn=0765617471|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In contrast to his treatment of Salafis, General Ma allowed polytheists to openly worship, and [[Christian]] missionaries to station themselves in [[Qinghai]]. General Ma and other high ranking Generals even attended the [[Qinghai Lake|Kokonuur Lake]] Ceremony where the Chinese &quot;God of the Lake' was worshipped, and during the ritual, the [[Historical Chinese anthems|Chinese national anthem]] was sung, all participants bowed to a portrait of Kuomintang party founder Dr. [[Sun Yat-sen]], and the God of the Lake was also bowed to, and offerings were given to him by the participants.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=g3C2B9oXVbQC&amp;dq=ma+bufang+son&amp;q=genocidal#v=onepage&amp;q=ma%20bufang%20lake%20god&amp;f=false|title=Dilemmas The Mongols at China's edge: history and the politics of national unity |author=Uradyn Erden Bulag|year=2002|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|location=|page=51|isbn=0742511448|pages=|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ma Bufang invited some [[Kazakhs|Kazakh]] Muslims to attend the ceremony honoring her god.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=g3C2B9oXVbQC&amp;dq=ma+bufang+son&amp;q=genocidal#v=snippet&amp;q=kazakh%20hui%20soldiers&amp;f=false|title=Dilemmas The Mongols at China's edge: history and the politics of national unity |author=Uradyn Erden Bulag|year=2002|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|location=|page=52|isbn=0742511448|pages=|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ma Bufang received audiences of Christian missionaries, who sometimes gave him the [[Gospel]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=NrtBAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=ma+pu-fang+gospel&amp;dq=ma+pu-fang+gospel|title=Journal of the American Water Works Association, Volume 39, Part 1|author=American Water Works Association|year=1947|publisher=The Association|location=|page=24|isbn=|pages=|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=http://books.google.com/?id=eUAhAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=ma+pu-fang+gospel&amp;dq=ma+pu-fang+gospel|title=Journal, Volume 39|author=American Water Works Association|year=1947|publisher=The Association|location=|page=24|isbn=|pages=|accessdate=2010-6-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; His son Ma Jiyuan received a silver cup from Christian missionaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;HORLEMANN&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=5858164|title=The Divine Word Missionaries in Gansu, Qinghai and Xinjiang, 1922–1953: A Bibliographic Note|last=HORLEMANN|first=BIANCA |publisher=|accessdate=2010-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Salafist jihadism===
''See main article [[Salafist jihadism]]''

'''Salafist jihadism''' (also Salafi jihadism) is a school of thought of Salafi Muslims who support [[jihad]]. The term was coined by scholar [[Gilles Kepel]]&lt;ref name=&quot;BLivesey&quot;&gt;[http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/pages/frontline/shows/front/special/sala.html The Salafist movement by Bruce Livesey]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/martinkramerorg/Terms.htm&amp;date=2009-10-26+02:20:35 Coming to Terms: Fundamentalists or Islamists? Martin Kramer. ''Middle East Quarterly'', Spring 2003), pp. 65-77. ]&lt;/ref&gt; to describe Salafi who began developing an interest in jihad during the mid-1990s. Practitioners are often referred to as Salafi jihadis or Salafi jihadists. Journalist [[Bruce Livesey]] estimates Salafi jihadists constitute less than 1 percent of the world's 1.9 billion Muslims (c. 10 million).&lt;ref name=&quot;BLivesey&quot;/&gt;

==Salafi scholars==
===Older authorities accepted by modern Salafis as Salafi===
====[[Arabian Peninsula]]====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
*[[Malik ibn Anas]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Muhammad ibn Abd al-Wahhab]]
{{col-end}}

====[[Egypt]]====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Ahmad ibn Muhammad al-Tahawi]]

====[[Mesopotamia]] and [[Greater Khorasan]]====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Abū Ḥanīfa]]
* [[Sufyan al-Thawri]]
* [[Muhammad ibn Idris ash-Shafi`i]]
* [[Muslim ibn al-Hajjaj Nishapuri]]
* [[Ibn Majah]]
* [[Abu Dawood]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Tirmidhi]]
* [[al-Nasa'i]]
* [[Al-Hasan ibn 'Ali al-Barbahari]]
* [[Muhammad ibn Jarir al-Tabari]]
* [[Ibn Battah]]
* [[Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi]]
* [[Abul-Hasan Ali ibn Umar ad-Daraqutni]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Siyar pg. 457&quot;/&gt;
* [[Ibn Rajab]]
{{col-end}}

====[[Greater Syria]]====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Abd al-Rahman al-Awza'i]]
* [[Ibn Qudamah]]
* [[Yahya ibn Sharaf al-Nawawi]]
* [[Ibn Taymiyyah]]
* [[Al-Dhahabi]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Ibn Qayyim Al-Jawziyya]]
* [[Ibn Kathir]]
* [[Ibn Abi al-Izz]]
* [[Ibn al-Salah]]&lt;ref&gt;''Siyar 'Alam al-Nubala'', vol. 23, pg. 142-3, by al-Dhahabi, Muassah al-Risalah, Beirut, 11th Edition, 2001. And ''Tadhkirah al-huffaz'', vol. 4, pg. 1431, Da'irah al-Ma'arif al-'Uthmaniyyah, India.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{col-end}}
====[[Al-Andalus]]====
{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Yusuf ibn abd al-Barr]]
* [[Al-Qurtubi]]
{{col-2}}
* [[Abu Ishaq al-Shatibi]]
* [[Ibn Hazm]]
{{col-end}}
===Contemporary Salafi scholars===
====Afghanistan====
* [[Muhammad Muhsin Khan]]

====Albania====

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Muhammad Nasiruddin al-Albani]]
{{col-end}}

====Egypt====

{{col-begin}}

{{col-2}}
* [[Safwat Al-Shwadfy]]
{{col-end}}

====Mauritania====
* [[Muhammad Ash-Shanqeeti]]

====Morocco====
* [[Muhammad Taqi-ud-Din al-Hilali]]

====[[Pakistan]]====

* [[Ehsan Elahi Zaheer]]

====Saudi Arabia====

{{col-begin}}
{{col-2}}
* [[Abd ar-Rahman ibn Nasir as-Sa'di]]
* [[‘Abdullaah bin Muhammad Al-Qar’aawee]]
* [[Haafidh ibn Ahmed 'Alee al-Hakamee]]
* [[Ali Jaber]]
* [[Abd al-Aziz ibn Abd Allah ibn Baaz]]
* [[Muhammad ibn al Uthaymeen]]
* [[Saleh Al-Fawzan]]
* [[Rabee Al-Madkhali]]

{{col-2}}
* [[Abdul-Azeez ibn Abdullaah Aal ash-Shaikh]]
* [[Abdul Rahman Al-Sudais]]
* [[Saud Al-Shuraim]]
* [[Salih Al-Talib]]
*
* [[Usaama bin Abdullah al Khayyat]]
* [[Salih bin Abdullah al Humaid]]
{{col-end}}

====Somalia====
* [[Muhammad Al-Sumaalee]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fatwa-online.com/scholarsbiographies/15thcentury/assumaalee.htm |title=SCHOLARS BIOGRAPHIES \ 15th Century \ Shaykh Muhammad ibn 'Abdullaah as-Sumaalee |publisher=Fatwa-online.com |date= |accessdate=2010-04-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Syria====
* [[Muhammad bin Jamil Zeno]]

====Yemen====
* [[Abdur-Rahman al-Mu'allimee al-Yamani]]
* [[Muqbil bin Haadi al-Waadi'ee]]

====India====
* [[Zakir Naik]]
* [[MM Akbar]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Islam}}
* [http://www.calgaryislam.com/ CalgaryIslam.com – Aqeedah &amp; manhaj of the Salaf]
* [http://www.salafipublications.com/ The creed and manhaj of the Salaf us-saalih – pure and clear]
* [http://www.salaf.com/ The manhaj of the Salaf us-saalih]
* [http://www.salafimanhaj.com/ Salafi Manhaj]
* [http://www.sayingsofthesalaf.net/ English translations of traditions from the Salaf]
* [http://www.salafidawa.be/ Salafi Fr Home]
* [http://www.salafidawa.be/dawa Salafi dawa Nl/Fr]
* [http://www.salafidawa.be/forum Salafi Forum Nl/Fr]
* [http://www.dawavoice.com/   Salafi Dawa voice]
* [http://www.nicheoftruth.org/  MM Akbar]



{{Islam topics|state=collapsed}}


[[Category:Salafi| ]]

[[ar:سلفية]]
[[bg:Салафизъм]]
[[ca:Salafisme]]
[[cy:Salaffiaeth]]
[[da:Salafisme]]
[[de:Salafiyya]]
[[el:Ουαχαμπισμός]]
[[es:Salafismo]]
[[eo:Salafismo]]
[[fa:سلفی]]
[[fr:Salafisme]]
[[id:Salafiyah]]
[[it:Salafiyya]]
[[he:סלפיה]]
[[ml:സലഫി]]
[[ms:Salafi]]
[[nl:Salafisme]]
[[no:Salafisme]]
[[pl:Salafizm]]
[[pt:Salafismo]]
[[ru:Салафия]]
[[sq:Selefizmi]]
[[so:Salafiya]]
[[fi:Salafismi]]
[[sv:Salafism]]
[[tr:Selefiyye]]
[[uk:Салафія]]
[[ur:سلفی]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
