<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="357602" ns="0" title="The Castafiore Emerald"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
englishtitle=The Castafiore Emerald
|foreigntitle=Les Bijoux de la Castafiore
|image=Tintin cover - The Castafiore Emerald.JPG
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=[[1963]]
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]''
|origdate=|&lt;!-- October 31, 1956 - January 1, 1958 --&gt;
|origisbn=|&lt;!-- 2-203-00118-6 --&gt;
|transtitle=The Castafiore Emerald
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]]
|transdate=1963
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' 
|transisbn=|&lt;!-- 0-316-35848-7 --&gt;
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[Tintin in Tibet]]'', [[1960]]
|nextissue=''[[Flight 714]]'', [[1968]]
}}

'''''The Castafiore Emerald''''' ({{lang-fr|'''Les Bijoux de la Castafiore'''}}) is an album in the classic comic-strip  series ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' by Belgian writer and illustrator [[Hergé]], featuring young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] as a hero.  

''The Castafiore Emerald'' is the twenty-first and the slowest-moving and most sedate in the series. It was conceived as a narrative exercise by Hergé.  Becoming disillusioned with his most famous creation, the cartoonist wanted to see if he could maintain suspense throughout sixty-two pages in which nothing much happens.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oberle.org/tintin/bd/bijoux/ Tintinophile] {{fr icon}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently it is a story without [[villain]]s, guns or danger, but rich in comic setpieces, [[red herring (plot device)|red herrings]], mistaken interpretations, and colourful characters.  Moreover, this is one of only two Tintin books in which the characters do not go to another part of the world (the other being ''[[The Secret of the Unicorn]]'').

==Storyline==

[[Captain Haddock]] and [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] are walking through the countryside when they come across a [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]] community camped in a [[garbage dump]].  They investigate and upon learning that the community chose that site on account of being forbidden by the [[police]] to use any other location, the Captain invites them to the grounds of his estate, Marlinspike, over the objections of his butler Nestor.

Shortly afterwards, [[Bianca Castafiore]], famous [[opera]] Diva and scourge of the Captain, decides to invite herself to Marlinspike for a holiday. All manner of mayhem ensues. For some time, one of the marble steps leading to the foyer in Marlinspike Hall has had a plate-sized chip; Nestor has been waiting for the repairman, who has been fobbing the Captain off. Upon hearing of Bianca's impending visit, Haddock rushes to pack for a trip to [[Italy]], figuring that now would be a good time to visit, because he had always avoided visiting the country precisely to avoid Bianca. In his haste, Haddock misses the step, which, just moments before, he had been sanctimoniously warning Nestor and the others about. He sprains his ankle as a result. The doctor arrives, examines the Captain, and insists upon putting the foot and ankle in a cast while imposing a minimum of a fortnight (two weeks)'s bed rest. As a result, the Captain uses a wheelchair for all but the last couple of pages. The broken step becomes a running gag for the rest of the comic, and every character, with the exception of Castafiore, slips and falls down the step at least one time.

Bianca has brought her luggage, her slippers, her pyjamas, her entourage and a parrot for the Captain called &quot;Iago&quot;. Not unlike the parrots featured in ''[[Red Rackham's Treasure]]'', the creature manages to pick up some of the Haddockian argot, much to the Captain's chagrin. He narrowly averts having to share his study with Bianca and her piano, managing to convince her to locate the instrument, along with her somewhat rebellious pianist Wagner, in the maritime gallery. Wagner, it turns out, indulges a penchant for gambling by making furtive runs into the local village to place bets. Increasing the Captain's problems, two over-zealous [[Paris Match|Paris Flash]] reporters concoct a story claiming that Haddock and Castafiore intend to get married (following a misinterpreted conversation with the very hard-of-hearing [[Professor Calculus]]), and an avalanche of congratulations from friends from all over the world pour in for several hours.

Soon after Captain Haddock discovers to his horror the rumors of his engagement spread by the tabloids, he is forced to accommodate an entire television crew, who occupy Marlinspike Hall for several hours while conducting an extensive interview with Castafiore (which is interrupted by several comic mishaps). A few days later, Castafiore's most prized emerald goes missing, and all eyes turn to the [[Roma (Romani subgroup)|Roma]]. But they are vindicated when, in a deliberately anti-climactic dénouement, the culprit turns out to have been a [[magpie]]. As soon as the emerald is found, it is (temporarily) lost once again by the detectives [[Thompson and Thomson]], only to be found again a few frames later by [[Snowy (character)|Snowy]], who calls it a &quot;brandyball&quot;, underlining the fact that the emerald is merely a device for the whole story to happen, and is in itself meaningless. Beyond the opening with the initial encounter with the Roma at the landfill, the action never leaves the confines of the Marlinspike estate - all the adventures in this album are decidedly domestic.

[[File:Th calculus.jpg|thumb|right|Castafiore's mention of Calculus' &quot;ascents in balloons&quot; is a reference to Auguste Piccard, upon whom Calculus was modelled.&lt;ref&gt;Hergé in an interview with [[Numa Sadoul]]&lt;/ref&gt;]]

== Inspiration and cultural references ==

*The book alludes to the well-known French weekly [[Paris Match]] in its depiction of reporters from 'Paris Flash', and jibes at its reputation for the questionable accuracy of the articles.

*It also mentions a fashion designer named Tristan Bior, based upon [[Christian Dior]].
 
*The incident of the unwelcome band playing outside Marlinspike was based on a similar experience of Hergé's who was also obliged to serve them with drinks. To add insult to injury they gave a toast to &quot;[[Spirou (character)|Spirou]]&quot;, Tintin's most direct rival.&lt;ref name=TintinTheCompleteCompanion&gt;''Tintin The Complete Companion'' by [[Michael Farr]], ISBN 0719555221, ISBN 978-0719555220&lt;/ref&gt;

*Hergé also gave a TV interview at around the time he was working on the story.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tintinologist.org/forums/index.php?action=vthread&amp;forum=10&amp;topic=2651&amp;page=0 Interview on Québécoise television], translation at [http://www.tintinologist.org tintinologist.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/21castafiore.html The Castafiore Emerald] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Castafiore Emerald, The}}
[[Category:1963 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Tintin (magazine)]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]

[[frp:Les Pèguelyon de la Castafiore]]
[[bn:পান্না কোথায়]]
[[ca:Les joies de la Castafiore]]
[[es:Las joyas de la Castafiore]]
[[fa:جواهرات کاستافیوره]]
[[fr:Les Bijoux de la Castafiore]]
[[gl:As xoias da Castafiore]]
[[id:Permata Castafiore]]
[[nl:De juwelen van Bianca Castafiore]]
[[pt:Les bijoux de la Castafiore]]
[[fi:Castafioren korut]]
[[sv:Castafiores juveler]]
[[zh:綠寶石失竊案]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
