<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3586571" ns="0" title="SM Mall of Asia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox shopping mall|
  | shopping_mall_name = SM Mall of Asia
  | image = SM Mall Of Asia logo.png
  | image_width = 300px
  | caption = ''&quot;No other mall comes close&quot;''
  | location = [[Bay City (Metro Manila)|Bay City]], [[Pasay City]], [[Philippines]]
  | opening_date = May 21, 2006
  | developer = [[SM Prime Holdings]]
  | manager = [[SM Prime Holdings]]
  | architect = [[Arquitectonica]]
  | owner = [[SM Prime Holdings]]
  | building_costs = PhP 6.5 billion
  | number_of_stores = 780 shops, 300 dining establishments
  | number_of_anchors = 9    
  | floor_area = 407,101 m² m²
  | floor_total_area = 407,101 m²
  | parking = 8,000 cars
  | floors = {{·}}'''Main and Entertainment Building:''' ''Two'' &lt;br&gt; {{·}}'''North Parking Building:''' ''Six'' &lt;br&gt; {{·}}'''South Parking Building:''' ''Six''
  | website = [http://www.smmallofasia.com SM Mall of Asia]&lt;br&gt;[http://www.smprime.com/smprime/index.php?p=671&amp;mall=3 SM Mall of Asia at SM Prime]
}}
{{coord|14|32|6.24|N|120|58|55.75|E|type:landmark|display=title}}

'''SM Mall of Asia''' ('''MOA''') is a shopping mall owned and developed by [[SM Prime Holdings]], the largest mall developer and owner in the Philippines. SM Mall of Asia is the 2nd largest mall in the Philippines after [[SM City North EDSA]], 3rd largest [[shopping mall]] in [[Asia]] and the 4th&lt;ref name=&quot;philstar.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.philstar.com/Article.aspx?articleId=530034&amp;publicationSubCategoryId=78 &quot;SM Mall of Asia lights up Globamaze&quot;], ''[[Philippine Star]]'', 2009-12-07&lt;/ref&gt; (Ref. Forbes' World's 10 Largest Shopping Malls) [[List_of_largest_buildings_in_the_world#List_of_the_world.27s_largest_shopping_malls|largest shopping mall in the world]]. It has a land area of 42 hectares and has a gross floor area of an approximate 390,193 m² (4.2 million square feet)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forbes.com/2007/01/09/malls-worlds-largest-biz-cx_tvr_0109malls_slide_4.html?thisSpeed=30000 |title=The World's Largest Malls|accessdate=2009-09-20 |last=Van Riper |first=Tom |date=2008-01-18 |work=Forbes}}&lt;/ref&gt;  and 407,101 m² of total area. The mall is located in [[Bay City (Metro Manila)|Bay City]], [[Pasay City]], [[Philippines]] near the SM Central Business Park, the Manila Bay and the southern end of [[EDSA|EDSA (Epifanio de los Santos Avenue)]]. The mall attracts a daily average foot traffic of about 200,000 people.

==Location and vicinity==
The Mall of Asia was constructed within a reclaimed area. It is built on 19.5 hectares of reclaimed land and has a gross floor area of 390,193 square meters. The mall is located at the southmost tip of [[Epifanio de los Santos Avenue]]. A [[roundabout]] was constructed in the front of the mall with a huge bronze globe similar to that of the [[Universal Studios Theme Parks]] and the [[Unisphere]] in [[Flushing Meadows–Corona Park|Flushing Meadows Park]] in [[New York City]]. On November 18, 2009, the globe was turned into an [[Light-emitting diode|LED]] Globe also known as '''GlobAmaze'''. The first and only full global video display in Asia with its high resolution and full display graphics made possible by the LED’s 26,300 pieces of point lights. This cutting edge LED technology is among other things, weather-proof, has superior brightness, and a long lifetime.&lt;ref name=&quot;philstar.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;!--The globe was turned into an LED globe as the new attraction at the MOA. Here's the link that the globe is now an LED globe. http://onmylefthandcorner.blogspot.com/2009/11/mall-of-asia-globe-lights-attraction.html http://www.flickr.com/photos/daniele268/4160673188/ http://kalokohan.com/globamaze-at-moa/--&gt;

==Physical details==
The SM Mall of Asia mall grounds consists of four buildings interconnected by walkways; the Main Mall, the Entertainment Mall, and the North and South Carpark Buildings.

The '''Main Mall''' includes shopping and dining establishments and the food court. The '''Entertainment Mall''' is a two-story complex, majority of which is open-air, and facing the [[Manila Bay]].

The mall's 5,000 parking spaces are divided across two, six-story parking buildings conveniently designated the North and South parking buildings. The '''South Parking''' building houses the mall's official SM Department Store, while the mall's supermarket, the [[SM Hypermarket]] is located at the '''North Parking''' building. 

One of the mall's somewhat-unique features is a 20-seater [[tram]] traveling around the mall grounds to ferry shoppers around.

Concierge desks are located in the Main Mall and the Entertainment Mall.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006May19&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Vasquez | first =Dinna Chan | title =MALL OF ASIA: Raising the ante on shopping | work =Life &amp; Entertainment stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-05-19 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=goodLife01_may19_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attractions==
{{wide image|SM Mall of Asia wide pan.jpg|1200px|&lt;center&gt;Panoramic view of SM Mall of Asia (2009).&lt;/center&gt;}}
The mall includes branches of all of the standard [[anchor store]]s found in most of the [[SM Supermalls]]. The first-ever branch of Taste Asia, one of the SM Supermalls' food court brands, is located right outside the mall's supermarket, the sprawling SM Hypermarket.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006June30&quot;&gt;{{cite news  | last =Vasquez | first =Dinna Chan | title =Shop and dine at Mall of Asia's Hypermart | work =Life &amp; Entertainment stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-06-30 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=goodLife01_june30_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:MoA 178.jpg|thumb|The Entertainment Mall]]

[[File:Moaxmas.jpg|thumb|A giant [[Christmas Tree]] standing in San Miguel by the Bay with the Entertainment Mall at the background]]
One of the mall’s main attractions is the first ever [[IMAX]] theater in the country, along with a Director's Club Theater for intimate screenings (30 [[La-Z-Boy]] seats), a Premiere Cinema, and the CenterStage Cinema which can used for live musical concerts and theatrical performances. The [[San Miguel Corporation|San Miguel]]-[[Coca-Cola]] IMAX Theatre is one of the world's biggest [[IMAX]] screens in 3D including 2D screenings.

In addition to the mall's special theaters, it also has six regular two-tiered movie theaters similar to the ones found in almost every [[SM Supermall]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006May31&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Red| first =Isah V.| title =New malls, new cineplexes | work =Life &amp; Entertainment stories| publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-05-31|url =http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=goodLife02_may31_2006|accessdate=2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mall features the [[Philippines]]'s first [[Olympic Games|Olympic]]-sized [[ice skating rink]]. At 61 by 30 meters, the rink is described as the biggest of its kind in [[Southeast Asia]]. It can accommodate both recreational and competitive [[figure skating]], as well as [[ice hockey]]. Along with plain access and skate rentals, the rink's operators also offer training progams in both figure skating and ice hockey.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006Jun27&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Libarios| first =Gabby| title =For your ice only | work =Life &amp; Entertainment stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-06-27 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=goodLife01_june27_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Several [[ice skating]] competitions have been held at the mall's ice skating rink, the most prestigious yet having been [[Skate Asia]] 2007. It was also the first time that the Philippines had hosted any international ice skating event.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2007Jan16&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Salumbides | first =Willie A., jr. | title =Pretty young thing on ice | work =Sports stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date = 2007-01-16 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=sports1_jan16_2007 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2007Jan25&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Salumbides | first =Willie A., jr. | title =Leslie wins ice skating's top award | work =Sports stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2007-01-25 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=sports2_jan25_2007 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mall's open-air '''Music Hall''' directly facing the sea has also held several events, contests and concerts.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006Dec04&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Red| first =Isah V.| title =QTV's music video block's first anniversary bash | work =Life &amp; Entertainment stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-12-04 | url=http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=goodLife2_dec4_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The mall also provides office space. [[Dell International Services]], a subsidiary of [[Dell, Inc.]] once occupied a 13,470.5-square meter area at the second floor of the north parking building of the mall. At present, [[Teleperformance]] has taken over that space.

==History==
===Construction===
The mall is the centerpiece project of SM Prime at the SM Central Business Park, where five one-story buildings serve as the company's corporate offices (the sixth building being occupied by TeleTech Holdings, Inc. as their flagship site in the country). Construction began in mid-2002 right after the completion of a contemporary medical school, dining strip and residential complex at [[Diosdado Macapagal|Macapagal Boulevard]], adjacent to the SM Central Business Park.

The SM Mall of Asia’s design team includes [[Arquitectonica]], design Architect; Robert Carag Ong and Associates, architect of record; GHT Services, project manager, and [http://www.hcc.com.ph Hilmarc's Construction Corp.] (for the South Parking Building, Main Mall, and Entertainment Mall) and Monolith Construction Development Corp. (for the North Parking Building), general contractors.

The mall would have opened before [[Christmas Day]] of 2005 but had been delayed due to hitches in the delivery of construction materials. Frequent rains in the last quarter of 2005 also delayed the turnover of mall space to tenants. SM Prime decided to move the opening date to March 3, 2006. 

On February 27, 2006, local newspaper ''Manila Standard Today'', reported that a team of [[Pasay City]] engineers found huge cracks underneath the structure, which was causing the structure to vibrate.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006Feb27&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Caber | first =Michael | title =Cracks endanger Pasay's Mall of Asia | work =Metro Stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-02-27 | url =http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=police03_feb27_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When questioned about the inspection, the Pasay City Engineering Department denied making any statement regarding defects in the Mall of Asia. Engineer Edwin Javaluyas, Pasay City engineering officer, in his letter to SM Prime Holdings Inc., said he never stated that the city hall’s engineering department inspected the Mall of Asia on February 23, 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2006Feb28&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last =Caber | first =Michael | title =Engineer denies threat to Mall of Asia | work =Metro Stories | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2006-02-28 | url =http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=police03_feb28_2006 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

SM Prime however decided to move the opening to May 21 of that year. Jeffrey Lim, corporate information officer of SM Prime Holdings, emphasized that a rescheduling of the mall’s opening was made to give the company an opportunity to allow more tenants to open shops and denied that the change was due to structural defects.&lt;ref name=&quot;YN1&quot;&gt;&quot;{{cite web | last = | title =Philippines' SM Prime delays Mall of Asia opening to May | work =Yahoo! News | publisher =Yahoo!, Inc. | date =2006-02-22 | url =http://sg.biz.yahoo.com/060222/15/3yv2j.html | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
Also known as &quot;The Largest Mall in Asia&quot; and &quot;The 4th Largest Mall in the World&quot;
On May 20, 2006, the mall was officially inaugurated by [[President of the Philippines|President]] [[Gloria Macapagal-Arroyo]] with a special screening of ''[[Everest (film)|Everest]]'' in the San Miguel Coca-Cola [[IMAX]] Theater. The movie was shown three days after tri-athlete [[Leo Oracion]] reached the treacherous mountain’s summit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gmanews.tv/everest/20060603_blogcommunity.htm GMANews.tv Everest&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; SM Bay City Arena which is under construction will be the newest addition to the attractions at the mall where large events like concerts, circus, ice shows, sports and entertainment events can be held. It is located at the side of the mall church and will compete with the 50 year-old Araneta Coliseum located at [[Cubao]], [[Quezon City]].
[[SM Prime]] declares to replace every old SM Sign to a New One

===Esplanade===
An [[esplanade]] was constructed at the back of the mall where it served as the observation center for the First [[World Pyro Olympics]] in December 2005. 

The second World Pyro Olympics were held at the SM Mall of Asia's boardwalk area in early January, 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;MST2007Jan16&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Veneracion | first =Connie | title =The pyro-olympics experience | work =Op-Editorial: SassyLawyer | publisher =Manila Standard Today | date =2007-01-16 | url =http://www.manilastandardtoday.com/?page=connieVeneracion_jan16_2007 | accessdate = 2007-02-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Esplanade was also the venue for Lovapalooza 2, wherein more than 5,300 couples kissed for 10 seconds on February 10, 2007, breaking [[Hungary]]'s 4,445 in the [[Guinness World Records]].

Also, an events venue named One Esplanade was constructed here. One Esplanade is usually used for product launches, parties, and other events.

There is also a strip mall owned by Mr. Henry Sy and Mr. Mariano Nocom, called the San Miguel by the Bay at the Esplanade. The strip mall has retail shops and restaurants and is an extension of the retail facilities of the SM Mall of Asia. It was opened on November 2007.

===Nido Fortified Science Discovery Center===
{{Infobox Museum
 |name          = Nido Fortified Science Discovery Center
 |image         = MoA 017.jpg
 |imagesize     = 200
 |map_type      =
 |map_caption   = 
 |latitude      =
 |longitude     =
 |established   = October 13, 2007
 |dissolved     =
 |location      = [[Pasay City]], [[Metro Manila]]
 |type          = [[Science museum]]
 |visitors      = 
 |director      = 
 |curator       = 
 |publictransit = 
 |website       = [http://www.smsciencediscovery.com http://www.smsciencediscovery.com]
}}
On October 13, 2007, the P313-million SM Science Discovery Center, the first of its kind in the world, was opened. SM Prime Holdings has partnered with US-based Leisure Entertainment Consultancy (LEC) for the SDC, it features a digital planetarium and a wide range of technology and science-themed exhibits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Inq2007Aug10&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last =Buban | first =Charles E. | title =Sci-tech park in RP’s largest mall | work =Headlines | publisher =Inquirer.net | date =2007-08-10 | url=http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/inquirerheadlines/metro/view_article.php?article_id=81672 | accessdate = 2007-08-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2009, it was renamed into Nido Fortified Science Discovery Center after being bought by [[Nestlé|Nestlé Philippines]].

====Theme rooms====
*'''Life Clock - ''' Allows visitors to send [[e-mail]]s to the future addressed to friends or themselves.
*'''ImagePort - ''' Focuses on all things that deal with the lens - from manual to digital cameras capturing the latest gadgets and the future of digital imaging.
*'''SMART Media City''' -  Allows visitors to play installed computer games and GestureTek (a full-body motion-controlled game system).
*'''Transportation Nation - ''' Features the history and future of transportation and displays transportation methods such as [[SINAG]], Wheelsurf, and [[Segway PT|Segway]] [[PT]]. This is also the exhibit with a flight simulator.
*'''Grossology - ''' Features the grossness education.
*'''Spaceship Earth - ''' Previously, it featured exhibits on the environment. After [[Nestlé]] bought the museum, it was turned into a motion-game venue.
*'''Virtual Reef - ''' Focuses on marine or underwater life. It features Mr. T, a talking cartoon titan fish who explains how to save [[coral reefs]]. 
*'''City Science - ''' Features replicas of some of the [[List of tallest buildings and structures in the world|tallest]] [[skyscrapers]] in the world, a replica of [[PBCom Tower]], and an interactive [[earthquake]] experience.
*'''Robot Inc. - ''' Features robots both fictional and non-fictional, displaying their origins and other information about them.
*'''Digistar Planetarium - ''' A 15-meter planetarium which has a 3-D &quot;screen&quot; on top of the seats.
*'''[[LEGO]] Mindstorms Robotics Center - ''' Features [[LEGO]] Mindstorms robot designs. Addition entrance fees apply in this exhibit.

===SMX Convention Center===
{{main|SMX Convention Center}}
{{Infobox Venue
| name              = SMX Convention Center
| image             = [[Image:MoA 215.jpg|200px]]
| image_caption     = SMX Convention Center exterior
| nickname          = 
| location          = SM Mall of Asia &lt;br&gt;[[Pasay City]], [[Metro Manila]] &lt;br&gt;{{PHI}}
| coordinates       = 
| type              = [[Convention center]]&lt;br&gt; Concert venue
| genre             =
| broke_ground      = March 23, 2006
| built             = 
| opened            = November 5, 2007
| renovated         = 
| expanded          = 
| closed            = 
| demolished        = 
| owner             = SM Prime Holdings
| former_names      = 
| seating_type      = 
| seating_capacity  = 6,000
| website           = [http://www.smxconventioncenter.com Official Website]
}}
The SMX Convention Center (formerly Maitrade Expo and Convention Center) (Project Name: MAITrade) is the Philippines' largest privately run exhibition and convention center. The 46,647-square meter building will have three floors and basement parking with a total leasable area of 19,800 square meters featuring large exhibition areas and function rooms. The convention center can fit approximately 6,000 people.

The groundbreaking was held on March 23, 2006. The P900 million project, was completed and inaugurated on November 5, 2007. It is set to compete with the nearby state-run [[Philippine International Convention Center]] and [[World Trade Center Manila]].

The 46,647-square meter building will have three floors and basement parking with a total leasable area of 19,800 square meters. The Architect, Arch. Jose Siao Ling, designed the structure maximizing the use of space, giving exhibitors flexibility and options in terms of their specific area requirements. The exhibition area at the ground level will have a floor area of 9,000-square meters, which can be divided into four halls. Commercial shops will be located along the perimeter. A bridgeway on the second level will connect SMX Convention Center to the mall's south parking building. The third level will have a total floor area of 8,730 square meters, which can be divided into six halls for functions and conventions, along with nine meeting rooms.&lt;ref name=&quot;MAITrade&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title =SM Investments Gears up for the uptrend in property
| work =Business stories | publisher =SM Investments Corporation | date =2006-06-20 | url=http://smdevelopment.com/Announcements.php?BlurbID=91}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===OneE-comCenter===
[[File:One e com center.jpg|thumb|One E-Com Center, [[SM Mall Of Asia]]]]
'' OneE-comCenter ''(known as SM Corporate Center)  To provide for the office and workspace requirements of prospective IT-related locator companies and for support office and backroom operations of business process outsourcing. The first building, OneE-comCenter, began March 8, 2006. The building was completed on the first week of October 2007. Its first occupant, [[Fitness First]] opened its doors on October 12, 2007. Office space will start to fill on January 2008.

The 105,857 square meter, 10 storey OneE-com Center was designed by international firm Arquitectonica and Architect Felix Lim. The building itself will have a total of 71,934 square meters available for lease. Seven floors will be allotted for office space, and the ground floor for commercial use. The average floor plate will be 9,000 square meters. There will be two and a half levels for parking with 600 slots. Tenants on the fourth floor will enjoy the convenience of parking their cars on the same floor as their offices. Offices on all floors can look out into a courtyard in the middle of the whole structure.

More than its design features, tenants of OneE-com Center will also enjoy tax incentives as it is completes its registration with the [[Philippine Export Zone Authority]] (PEZA). Its strategic location and proximity to the airport will ensure a strong market response for OneE-com Center. The building is connected by a second level pedestrian bridgeway to the mall's north parking building.&lt;ref name=&quot;eCommCenter&quot;&gt;{{cite news | title =One EcomCenter Rises To Meet Strong Demand for BPO Offices| work =Business stories | publisher =SM Investments Corporation | date =2006-07-25 | url=http://sminvestments.com/Announcements.php?BlurbID=114}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ferry service===
Adjacent to the convention center, MetroStar Ferry Terminal, a ferry terminal has been completed to service passengers who wish to travel to peninsular [[Cavite City]]. The ferry service will cut travel time to Cavite City from 90 minutes by road to less than 30 minutes. The terminal will also serve as a passenger port for tourists who will travel to SM's tourism estate, the Hamilo Coast, in  [[Nasugbu, Batangas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MB2006Jul31&quot;&gt;{{cite news | last=Loyola | first =James | title =SMIC to build ferry terminal near Mall of Asia| work =Business stories | publisher =Manila Bulletin| date =2006-07-31 | url=http://www.mb.com.ph/issues/2006/07/31/BSNS2006073170491.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
On September 24, 2007, [[Philippine Export-Import Credit Agency]] (PhilEXIM) inaugurated the P135-million [[ferry]] [[project]] (between [[Cavite City]] and SM Mall of Asia). PhilEXIM President Virgilio R. Angelo stated that it guaranteed the [[loan]] of Metrostar Ferry, Inc. (Metrostar) for the [[government]]’s [[Manila Bay]] Transport Project. Angelo stated that the [[ferry]] service would also open in the [[Cavite City]]-[[Luneta]] Boardwalk-Del Pan Bridge [[waterway]]. 20,000 riders are expected to benefit (cost of  P60-70, 6:30 am until 7:00 pm).&lt;ref&gt;[http://business.inquirer.net/money/breakingnews/view_article.php?article_id=90399  Inquirer.net,  PhilEXIM unveils P135-M ferry project for Metro Manila]&lt;/ref&gt;

===''San Miguel by the Bay''===
[[Image:Mallofasia0.jpg|thumb|''San Miguel by the Bay'']]
[[Manila]] mayor [[Alfredo Lim]] ordered the demolition of structures along the shorelines of Manila Bay, Manila known as ''Baywalk''.&lt;ref&gt;[http://newsinfo.inquirer.net/breakingnews/metro/view_article.php?article_id=79566 Manila’s Lim orders ‘noisy’ Baywalk stages removed - INQUIRER.net, Philippine News for Filipinos&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; It was one of the flagship projects of his predecessor [[Lito Atienza]]. The demolition coincides with the construction of a dining strip and open park at the back of the mall called ''San Miguel by the Bay''. Patrons of the deserted Baywalk quickly flocked the new feature of the Mall of Asia complex, which is also along the shorelines of Manila Bay in Pasay City.

The dining strip also features a small seafood market (known as ''Dampa'') where patrons can buy fresh seafood and request to cook them in ''Paluto'' stalls.

===''[[Mall of Asia Arena]]''===
A multipurpose [[SM Arena|Arena]] set to be open in May 19, 2012, with a capacity of 20,000 people. It will be rival to the 51 year old [[Araneta Coliseum]].

===''Two E-com Center''===
[[File:Two E-Com Center.jpg|thumb|Two E-Com Center, [[SM Mall Of Asia]]]]
The second phase of the four BDO towers in Mall of Asia complex. Designed by the world-renowned firm [[Arquitectonica]]. It is expected to open in 4th quarter of 2011.

==Gallery==
&lt;center&gt;&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Sm mall of asia.jpg|The mall shown at the southern end of EDSA
Image:MoA 003.jpg|Mall Sign and Facade
Image:MoA 008.jpg|Main Mall Entrance
Image:MoA 007.jpg|Main Mall Atrium Ground Level
Image:MoA 009.jpg|Main Mall Lobby Second Level
Image:MoA 012.jpg|International Olympic-sized [[Ice rink|Ice Skating Rink]]
Image:MoA 013.jpg|Cinema Complex
Image:MoA 015.jpg|The Music Hall
Image:MoA 017.jpg|The SM Science Discovery Center
File:Mall of Asia IMAX theater exterior.jpg|[[IMAX]] Theater
Image:MoA 198.jpg|MetroStar Ferry Terminal
Image:MoA 214.jpg|The OneE-Com Center
Image:MoA 215.jpg|The SMX Convention Center
&lt;/gallery&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==See also==
*[[List of shopping malls in the Philippines]]
*[[SM Prime Holdings]]
*[[SM City Pampanga]]
*[[SM City North EDSA]]
*[[SM Megamall]]
*[[SM City Santa Rosa]]
*[[SM City Fairview]]

==External Links==
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.smmallofasia.com/ SM Mall of Asia Official Website]
*[http://www.forbes.com/2007/01/09/malls-worlds-largest-biz-cx_tvr_0109malls_slide.html?boxes=custom World's Largest Shopping Malls by Forbes Magazine]
*[http://www.smxconventioncenter.com/ SMX Convention Center]
*[http://www.mallofasiaarena.com/ Mall of Asia Arena]

{{S-start}}
{{S-bef|before=[[SM City Clark]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=25th ''[[SM Supermalls|SM Supermall]]''|years=2006}}
{{s-aft|after=[[SM Center Pasig]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{SMPH}}
{{Navbox
|name  = SM Department Store
|title = [[SM Department Store|{{color|#FFFFFF|SM Department Store}}]]
|titlestyle = background:#0000A0; color:#FFFFFF
|groupstyle = background::#0000A0; color:#0000A0

|group1 = Branches:|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000A0&gt;Branches:
|list1 = {{nowrap begin}} [[SM Quiapo|Clearance Outlet Quiapo]]{{·w}} [[SM Makati|Makati]]{{·w}} [[SM Delgado|Delgado-Iloilo]]{{·w}} [[SM Cubao|Cubao]]{{·w}} [[Harrison Plaza]]{{·w}} [[SM City North EDSA|North EDSA]] {{·w}} [[SM City Santa Mesa|Sta. Mesa]]{{·w}} [[SM Megamall|Ortigas]] {{·w}} [[SM City Cebu|Cebu]]{{·w}} [[SM City Southmall|Las Pinas]]{{·w}} [[SM City Bacoor|Bacoor]]{{·w}} [[SM City Fairview|Fairview]]{{·w}} [[SM City Iloilo|Mandurriao-Iloilo]]{{·w}} [[SM City Manila|Manila]]{{·w}} [[SM City Pampanga|Pampanga]]{{·w}} [[SM City Davao|Ecoland-Davao]]{{·w}} [[SM City Bicutan|Bicutan]]{{·w}} [[SM City Cagayan de Oro|Cagayan de Oro]] {{·w}} [[SM City Lucena|Lucena]]{{·w}} [[SM City Baguio|Baguio]]{{·w}} [[SM City Marilao|Marilao]]{{·w}} [[SM City Dasmariñas|Dasmariñas]]{{·w}} [[SM City Batangas|Batangas]] {{·w}} [[SM City San Lazaro|San Lazaro]]{{·w}} [[SM City Sucat|Sucat]]{{·w}} [[SM City Santa Rosa|Sta.Rosa]]{{·w}} [[SM City Clark|Clark]]{{·w}} [[SM Mall of Asia|Bay City]]{{·w}} [[Agana Shopping Center|Guam]]{{·w}} [[SM City Lipa|Lipa]]{{·w}} [[SM City Bacolod|Bacolod]]{{·w}} [[SM City Taytay|Taytay]]{{·w}} [[SM City Marikina|Marikina]]{{·w}} [[SM City Baliwag|Baliwag]]{{·w}} [[SM City Rosales|Rosales]]{{·w}} [[SM City Naga|Naga]]{{·w}} [[SM City Rosario|Rosario]]{{·w}} [[SM City Tarlac|Tarlac]]{{·w}} [[SM City San Pablo|San Pablo]]{{·w}} [[SM City Calamba|Calamba]]{{·w}} [[SM City Novaliches|Novaliches]]{{nowrap end}}

|group2 = Upcoming Branches:|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000A0&gt;Upcoming Branches:
|list2 = {{nowrap begin}} [[SM City Consolacion|Consolacion, Cebu]]{{·w}} [[SM City Taguig|Fort Bonifacio]]{{·w}} [[SM City North Davao|Lanang]]{{nowrap end}}
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{Navbox
|name  = SM Hypermarket Branches
|title = [[SM Hypermarket|{{color|#0000A0&lt;!--ditto--&gt;|SM Hypermarket}}]]
|titlegroup =  
|titlestyle = background:#00FF00; color:#0000A0
|groupstyle = background::#00FF00; color:#0000A0

|group1 = Branches:|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0000A0&gt;Branches:
|list1 = {{nowrap begin}} [[SM City Sucat|Sucat]]{{·w}} [[SM City Bicutan|Bicutan]]{{·w}} [[SM City Marilao|Marilao]]{{·w}} [[SM Center Valenzuela|Valenzuela]]{{·w}} [[SM Center Molino|Molino]]{{·w}} [[SM City Clark|Clark]] {{·w}} [[SM Mall of Asia|Bay City]]{{·w}} [[SM City North EDSA|North EDSA]] {{·w}} [[SM Center Pasig|Pasig]]{{·w}} [[SM City Taytay|Taytay]]{{·w}} [[SM Center Muntinlupa|Muntinlupa]]{{·w}} [[SM City Rosales|Rosales]]{{·w}} [[SM City Baliwag|Baliwag]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Mandaluyong|Mandaluyong]]{{·w}} [[SM City Fairview|Fairview]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Makati|Makati]]{{·w}} [[SM Center Las Piñas|Las Piñas]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Novaliches|Novaliches]] {{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Centris|Centris Station]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket North Harbour|North Harbour]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Adriatico|Adriatico]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Jaro|Jaro]]{{·w}} [[SM Hypermarket Cubao|Cubao]]{{·w}}[[SM Hypermakret Batangas|Batangas]]{{·w}}[[SM Hypermarket Mabalacat|Mabalacat]]{{nowrap end}}
}}&lt;noinclude&gt;
{{EDSA}}
[[Category:Shopping malls in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Shopping malls established in 2006]]
[[Category:SM Prime Holdings|Mall of Asia]]
[[Category:Landmarks in the Philippines]]
[[Category:IMAX venues]]

[[de:SM Mall of Asia]]
[[ilo:SM Mall of Asia]]
[[fi:SM Mall of Asia]]
[[tl:SM Mall of Asia]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
