<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3587056" ns="0" title="Great Railroad Strike of 1877"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">The '''Great Railroad Strike of 1877''' began on July 14 in [[Martinsburg, West Virginia]], [[United States]] and ended some 45 days later after it was put down by local and state militias, and federal troops.

==Economic conditions in the 1870s==
{{see|Long Depression#United States}}
The 1870s saw a significant economic depression in Europe. The effects of this  reached the United States on September 18, 1873, with the failure of banking firm [[Jay Cooke]] and Company. As Cooke was the country’s top investment banker, the principal backer of the [[Northern Pacific Railroad]] as well as a prime investor in other railroads, and as the company which had handled most of the government’s wartime loans, its failure was catastrophic. In response, the [[U.S. economy]] sputtered and then collapsed. Shortly after Cooke’s demise, the [[New York Stock Exchange]] closed for 10 days, [[Credit (finance)|credit]] dried up, [[foreclosure]]s and factory closings became common. Of the country's 364 railroads, 89 went bankrupt, over 18,000 businesses failed between 1873 and 1875.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}&lt;!-- This is a fact...You need a citation. --&gt; [[Unemployment]] reached 14 percent by 1876, while workers who kept their jobs were employed for a mere six months out of the year and suffered a 45% cut in their wages to approximately one dollar per day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Shelton|first=Josh|title=Pages from US Labor History: The Great Railroad Strike of 1877|publisher= |date= |url=http://www.socialistappeal.org/uslaborhistory/great_railroad_strike_of_1877.htm
|doi= |accessdate =2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; This economic cataclysm is now referred to as the [[Panic of 1873]].

While the public blamed President [[Ulysses S. Grant]] and the [[United States Congress]] for mishandling the economy, in particular Grant's [[monetary policy]] of contracting the [[money supply]], the causes of the panic were actually much deeper{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}. With the end of the [[American Civil War|Civil War]], the country experienced feverish, unregulated growth, especially in the railroad industry, with the government giving massive land grants and [[subsidies]] to railroad companies.&lt;ref&gt;[[Hear That Lonesome Whistle Blow]], [[Dee Brown]]&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the massive overbuilding of the nation’s railroads, and the overinvestment by bankers of depositors’ funds in the railroads laid the foundation for the Panic and the depression that followed{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}. A full economic recovery was not seen until 1878-79.

==Causes of the strike==
When the [[American Civil War|Civil War]] ended, a boom in railroad construction ensued, with roughly 35,000 miles of new track being laid from coast-to-coast between 1866 and 1873. The railroads, then the second largest employer outside of [[agriculture]], required large amounts of capital investment, and thus entailed massive financial risk. [[Speculation|Speculators]] fed large amounts of money into the industry, causing abnormal growth and over expansion. Jay Cooke's firm, like many other banking firms, was investing a disproportionate share of depositors’ funds in the railroads, thus paving the way for the ensuing collapse.

In addition to Cooke's direct infusion of [[Financial capital|capital]] in the railroads, the firm had become a federal agent for the government in the government’s direct financing of railroad construction. As building new track in areas where land had not yet been cleared or settled required [[land grants]] and [[loans]] that only the government could provide, the use of Jay Cooke’s firm as a conduit for federal funding worsened the effects that Cooke’s bankruptcy had on the nation’s economy.The way it trite-pained

[[Image:Harpers 8 11 1877 Blockade of Engines at Martinsburg W VA.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Blockade of engines at Martinsburg, West Virginia, 16 July 1877]]

In the wake of the Panic of 1873, a bitter antagonism between workers and the leaders of industry developed. By 1877, 10% wage cuts, distrust of capitalists and poor working conditions led to a number of railroad strikes that prevented the trains from moving. This antagonism lingered well after the depression ended in 1878-79, eventually erupting into the labor unrest that marked the following decades and that eventually led to the birth of [[Trade union|labor unions]] in the United States.

Additionally, the [[U.S. presidential election, 1876|1876 presidential election]] between [[Samuel J. Tilden]] and [[Rutherford B. Hayes]] had been a narrow victory for Tilden in the popular vote, but while Tilden had a plurality of [[U.S. Electoral College|electoral votes]] (184-165) he did not have a majority as is required by the [[United States Constitution]]. This sent the election to the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] who were unable to reach agreement. On January 29, 1877, the U.S. Congress passed a law forming a 15-member [[Electoral Commission (United States)|Electoral Commission]] to decide on a winner. Five members came from each house of the U.S. Congress, with the other five members coming from the [[Supreme Court of the United States]]. Thanks in part to a deal brokered by [[Thomas Alexander Scott]] (who will surface as a figure during the strike), the commission awarded the disputed electoral votes to Hayes. Thus, the mood of the country grew darker, as those who had voted for Tilden felt disenfranchised.&lt;ref name=&quot;AH&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia= The American Heritage Book of the Presidents|publisher = American Heritage|year=1967|location=volume=VI|pages=|url = | doi = | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The strike==
[[Image:Harpers 8 11 1877 6th Regiment Fighting Baltimore.jpg|thumb|right|280px|Maryland National Guard Sixth Regiment fighting its way through Baltimore, Maryland, 20 July 1877]]

The great railroad strike of 1877 started on July 14 in Martinsburg, West Virginia, in response to the cutting of wages for the second time in a year by the [[Baltimore &amp; Ohio Railroad]] (B&amp;O). Striking workers would not allow any of the stock to roll until this second wage cut was revoked.  The governor sent in state militia units to restore train service, but the soldiers refused to use force against the strikers and the governor called for federal troops.

===Maryland===

Meanwhile, the strike spread to [[Cumberland, Maryland]], stopping freight and passenger traffic. When Governor [[John Lee Carroll|John Carroll]] of Maryland directed the 5th and 6th Regiments of the [[Maryland Army National Guard|National Guard]] to put down the strike, citizens from Baltimore attacked the troops as they marched from their armories towards B&amp;O's [[Camden Yards station|Camden Station]] for the train to Cumberland, causing violent street battles between the striking workers and the Maryland militia.  When the outnumbered troops of the 6th Regiment fired on an attacking crowd, they killed 10 and wounded 25.&lt;ref name=&quot;scharf&quot;&gt;{{Cite document|last=Scharf|first=J. Thomas|title=History of Maryland From the Earliest Period to the Present Day|publisher=Tradition Press|date=1967 (reissue of 1879 ed.)|location = Hatboro, PA|volume=3|pages=733–42 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The rioters injured several members of the militia, damaged engines and train cars, and burned portions of the train station.&lt;ref name=&quot;scharf&quot;/&gt; On July 21–22, the President sent federal troops and Marines to [[Baltimore]] to restore order.

===Pennsylvania===

[[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh]], [[Pennsylvania]] became the site of the worst violence.  [[Thomas Alexander Scott]] of the [[Pennsylvania Railroad]], often considered one of the first [[robber baron (industrialist)|robber baron]]s, suggested that the strikers should be given &quot;a rifle diet for a few days and see how they like that kind of bread.&quot; However, local law enforcement officers refused to fire on the strikers.

Nonetheless, his request came to pass on July 21, when militiamen [[bayoneted]] and fired on rock-throwing strikers, killing twenty people and wounding twenty-nine others.&lt;ref name=&quot;UE&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last= |first= |title=The Great Stike of 1877: Remembering a Worker Rebellion|work= |publisher=UE News|date=June 2002|url=http://www.ranknfile-ue.org/uen_1877.html|doi= |accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rather than quell the uprising however, this action merely infuriated the strikers who then forced the militiamen to take refuge in a railroad [[roundhouse]], and then set fires that razed 39 buildings and destroyed 104 locomotives and 1,245 freight and passenger cars.  On July 22, the militiamen mounted an assault on the strikers, shooting their way out of the roundhouse and killing 20 more people on their way out of the city.  After over a month of constant rioting and bloodshed, President [[Rutherford B. Hayes]] sent in federal troops to end the strikes.

Three hundred miles to the east, [[Philadelphia]] strikers battled local militia and set fire to much of Center City before federal troops intervened and put down the uprising.

Pennsylvania's third major industrial city at the time, [[Reading, Pennsylvania|Reading]], was also hit by the Strike's fury. This city was home of the engine works and shops of its namesake [[Reading Company|Reading Railroad]], against which engineers were already on strike since April 1877.  Sixteen citizens were shot by state militia in the [[Reading Railroad Massacre]].  Preludes to the massacre include:  fresh work stoppage all classes of the railroad's local workforce; mass marches; blocking of rail traffic; trainyard arson; and the burning down of the bridge providing this railroad's only link to the west -  to prevent local militia from being mustered to Harrisburg or Pittsburgh.  The militia responsible for the shootings was mobilized by Reading Railroad management, not by local public officials.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Zinn |first=Howard |authorlink= |title=A People's History of the United States 1492-present |publisher=Harper Collins | year=1995 |location=New York |pages=248 |url=http://books.google.com/?id=P8V7J5qm5-YC&amp;dq=People's+History+of+the+United+States&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;q= |doi= |accessdate= 2009-10-05 |isbn =0-06-052842-7 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Harpers 8 11 1877 Steeple View of Pittsburgh Conflagaration.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Burning of Pennsylvania Railroad and Union Depot, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 21–22 July 1877]]

The [[1877 Shamokin Uprising]] occurred on July 25, when 1000 men and boys, many of them coal miners, marched to the Reading Railroad Depot in [[Shamokin, Pennsylvania|Shamokin]], Pennsylvania. They looted the depot when the town announced it would only pay them $1/day for emergency public employment. The mayor, who owned coal mines, formed a vigilante group that killed 2 out of 14 civilian shooting casualties.

=== Illinois ===

On July 24, rail traffic in [[Chicago]] was paralyzed when angry mobs of unemployed citizens wreaked havoc in the rail yards, shutting down both the [[Baltimore and Ohio]] and the [[Illinois Central]] Railroads.  Soon, other railroads were brought to a standstill, with demonstrators shutting down railroad traffic in [[Bloomington, Illinois|Bloomington]], [[Aurora, Illinois|Aurora]], [[Peoria, Illinois|Peoria]], [[Decatur, Illinois|Decatur]], [[Urbana, Illinois|Urbana]] and other rail centers throughout [[Illinois]].  In sympathy, coal miners in the pits at Braidwood, [[LaSalle]], Springfield, and [[Carbondale, Illinois|Carbondale]] went on strike as well.  In Chicago, the [[Workingmen's Party of the United States|Workingmen’s Party]] organized demonstrations that drew crowds of twenty thousand people.

Judge [[Thomas Drummond (judge)|Thomas Drummond]] of the [[United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit]], who was overseeing numerous railroads that had declared [[bankruptcy]] in the wake of the [[Panic of 1873]] rules that &quot;A strike or other unlawful interference with the trains will be a violation of the United States law, and the court will be bound to take notice of it and enforce the penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;cahan&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Cahan |first=Richard |authorlink= |title= A Court That Shaped America: Chicago's Federal District Court from Abe Lincoln to Abbie Hoffman |publisher=Northwestern University Press |year=2002 |location= |pages=33–34 |url =http://books.google.com/?id=ALsW1pAD4A0C&amp;dq=Court+That+Shaped+America&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;q= |accessdate=2009-10-05 |id= |isbn=0-8101-1981-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Drummond told federal marshals to protect the railroads, and asked for federal troops to enforce his decision: he subsequently had strikers arrested and then tried them for [[contempt of court]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cahan&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Harpers 8 11 1877 Destruction of the Union Depot.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Burning of Union Depot, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, 21–22 July 1877]]

The mayor of Chicago, [Monroe Heath], asked for five thousand vigilantes to help restore order (they were partially successful), and shortly thereafter the National Guard and federal troops arrived. On July 25, violence between police and the mob erupted with events reaching a peak the following day. These blood-soaked confrontations between police and enraged mobs occurred at the Halsted Street viaduct, at nearby 16th Street, at Halsted and 12th, and on Canal Street. The headline of the ''[[Chicago Times]]'' screamed, &quot;Terrors Reign, The Streets of Chicago Given Over to Howling Mobs of Thieves and Cutthroats.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;UE&quot;/&gt; Order was finally restored, however, with the deaths of nearly 20 men and boys, the wounding of scores more, and the loss of property valued in the millions of dollars.

===Missouri===

:''see main article [[1877 Saint Louis general strike]]

On July 21, disgruntled workers in the industrial rail hub of [[East St. Louis]], Missouri, halted all freight traffic, with the city remaining in the control of the strikers for almost a week.  

In response the St. Louis Workingman's Party led a group of approximately 500 people across the Missouri River in an act of solidarity with the nearly 1,000 workers on strike.  That act transformed an initial strike among railroad workers into a strike by thousands of workers in several industries for the [[eight-hour day]] and a ban on [[child labor]], the first [[general strike]] in the United States.  

The strike on both side of the river was ended when some 3,000 federal troops and 5,000 deputized special police killed at least eighteen people in skirmishes around the city.  On July 28, 1877, they took control of the Relay Depot, the Commune's command center, and arrested some seventy strikers.

==Strike Over==
The Great Railroad Strike of 1877 began to lose momentum when President Hayes sent federal troops from city to city.  These troops suppressed strike after strike, until at last, approximately 45 days after it had started, the Great Railroad Strike of 1877 was over.

==Laying blame==
The strike and its repercussions were attributed on a number of factors by contemporaries:

*[[Xenophobia]]: [[German people|German]] and [[Bohemian]] agitators were blamed most often, but in some cities other ethnic groups were blamed as well.

*Idle hands: Illinois governor [[Shelby Cullom]] stated that &quot;''the vagrant, the willfully idle, was the chief element in all these disturbances,''&quot; his premise being that an unemployed man was unemployed due to choice, rather than the paucity of jobs.

*[[Communism]]:  Still others asserted that the Great Railroad Strike was due to Communist influences.  The ''[[New York World]]'' blamed &quot;the hands of men dominated by the devilish spirit of Communism.&quot;  Given that the Workingmen’s Party (WP) was a [[Socialist]] party affiliated with the Marxist movement sweeping Europe, it is understandable that this connection was made.  However, it should be noted that the WP did not instigate the strike, rather it fanned its flames. In his 1878 book ''Strikers, Communists, Tramps and Detectives'', [[Allan Pinkerton]] blamed the unrest on a combination of [[Paris Commune]] proponents and the high degree of transiency of the American working class at the time.

*Lack of [[Trade unions]]: While there was some union activity, especially from the [[Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers]] and [[Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen]], many of the strikers had yet to organize.

*The 1876 Election Deal: Thomas Scott, of the Pennsylvania Railroad, delivered the disputed congressional votes to Hayes in exchange for a federal bailout of failing investments in the Texas and Pacific railroad.   While it is not clear if this deal led to Hayes’ sending of federal troops to the strike-torn areas, the possibility of a ''[[quid pro quo]]'' arrangement is tenable.

==Economic impact==
While no complete accounting of the economic losses caused by this strike exists, it is known that the engineers' and firemen's brotherhoods lost approximately $600,000 over the forty-five days of the strike, while for the Burlington Railroad the losses were at least $2,100,000.

In Pittsburgh, it was estimated that property damage reached about five million dollars{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}, with Chicago, Baltimore and other cities facing losses of a similar magnitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;AH&quot;&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|encyclopedia= The American Heritage Book of the Presidents|publisher = American Heritage|year=1967|location=
|volume=VI|pages=|url = | doi =  | id = | isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact on future labor relations==
After the Great Railroad Strike of 1877, union organizers planned for their next battles while politicians and business leaders took steps to ensure that such chaos could not reoccur. Many states enacted conspiracy statutes. States formed new militia units, and National Guard armories were constructed in a number of cities. For workers and employers alike, the strikes had shown the power of workers in combination to challenge the status quo. They were driven, as a Pittsburgh state militiaman, who was ordered to break the 1877 strike, pointed out, by “one spirit and one purpose among them -– that they were justified in resorting to any means to break down the power of the corporations.”

Thus, in the wake of the strike, unions became better organized and the number of strikes increased. In the 1880s there were nearly ten thousand strikes and lockouts and in 1886 nearly 700,000 workers went on strike. As is to be expected, business leaders took a more rigid stance against the unions. Nonetheless, and possibly because of the more rigid stance, the labor movement continued to grow.

One result of the strike was increased public awareness of the grievances of railroad workers. In 1880 the B&amp;O railroad, which had the lowest wage rate of any major railroad, established the Baltimore and Ohio Employees' Relief Association, which provided coverage for sickness, injury from accidents, and a death benefit.&lt;ref name=&quot;BaltBook&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Gillett|first=Sylvia|editor=Fee, Elizabeth, Shopes, Linda; and Zeidman, Linda (eds.)
 |title=The Baltimore Book: New Views of Local History|publisher=Temple University Press|year=1991|location=Philadelphia|pages=11–14|chapter=Camden Yards and the Strike of 1877|url=http://books.google.com/?id=626B6J8at00C&amp;pg=PA171&amp;lpg=PA171&amp;dq=baltimore+book&amp;q=|isbn=0-87722-823-X}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1884, the B&amp;O became the first major employer to offer a [[pension plan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;BaltBook&quot;/&gt;

In 1886, there was a national strike aimed at reducing the average workday from twelve to eight hours, and 340,000 workers struck at 12,000 companies nationwide. In Chicago, police were trying to break up a large labor meeting in [[Haymarket Riot|Haymarket Square]], when a bomb exploded without warning, killing a police officer. Police fired into the crowd, killing one and wounding many more. Because of the riot, four labor organizers were hanged. The hangings of these organizers took the steam out of the national labor movement and energized management. By 1890, [[Knights of Labor]] membership had fallen to ten percent of its previous levels.

In 1893-1894, a severe depression swept the nation and America saw some of its worst strikes in history, including that against the [[Pullman Palace Car Company]]. The strike, which had been caused by severe wage cuts, stopped railroad traffic, with battles between troops and strikers breaking out in twenty-six states.

The defeat of the [[Pullman Strike]] fed an intense [[Labor federation competition in the United States|debate within the labor movement]] between the proponents of [[craft unionism]] and of [[industrial unionism]], an argument that continued for several decades.

==Commemoration==
The [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Martinsburg Shops]], where the strike began, were declared a [[National Historic Landmark]] in 2003.

==See also==
{{Portal|Organized labour}}
* [[History of rail transport in the United States]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==General references==
* [http://www.u-s-history.com/pages/h213.html Panic of 1873. By u-s-history ]
* [http://thehistorybox.com/ny_city/panics/panics_article9a.htm Panic of 1873. By thehistorybox]
* [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/grant/peopleevents/e_panic.html US Grant]
* [http://college.hmco.com/history/readerscomp/rcah/html/ah_073500_railroadstri.htm RAILROAD STRIKE OF 1877]
* [http://www.eslarp.uiuc.edu/ibex/archive/vignettes/1877_rr_strike.htm THE GREAT RAILROAD STRIKE OF 1877]
* [http://www.catskillarchive.com/rrextra/sk881.Html THE GREAT RAILROAD STRIKE.Harper's Weekly—April 21, 1888]
* [http://www.socialistappeal.org/uslaborhistory/great_railroad_strike_of_1877.htm Pages from US Labor History: The Great Railroad Strike of 1877]
* ''The American Heritage Book of the Presidents'', Vol VI, American Heritage, 1967

==External links==
* [http://www.catskillarchive.com/rrextra/sk7711.Html The Great Strike, Harper's Weekly, August, 11, 1887]
* [http://www.catskillarchive.com/rrextra/sk881.Html The Great Railroad Strike Harper's Weekly, April 21, 1888]
* [http://teachingamericanhistorymd.net/000001/000000/000070/html/t70.html The Strike of 1877, Maryland State Archives]
* [http://www.wvculture.org/HISTORY/labor/bandostrike01.html The B&amp;O Railroad Strike of 1877, The (Martinsburg) Statesman, July 24, 1877]
* [http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/scott_w_dunlap/Main2.html&amp;date=2009-10-26+02:12:59 The Baltimore and Ohio Railroad Network]
* [http://www.on-track-on-line.com/forums/index.php?showtopic=19083&amp;hl= The 1877 Shamokin Uprising and the Great Railroad Strike, The News Item of Shamokin, mid-eastern Pennsylvania, July 25, 2007]
* [http://libcom.org/history/1877-the-great-railroad-strike Excerpt from ''A People's History of the United States'' by Howard Zinn, New York: HarperCollins, 1999. p.245-251 ISBN 0060528370]
* [http://www.berkshistory.org/articles/railroad.html &quot;Reading's Place in The Great Strike &amp; After&quot;, Berks County(,Pennsylvania) Historical Society]

== Further reading ==
{{Refbegin}}
* Bruce, Robert V., ''1877: Year of Violence'', 1959. [Reprinted 1989. ISBN 0-929587-05-7]
* [[Philip Foner|Foner, Philip S.]], ''The Great Labor Uprising of 1877'', 1977. ISBN 0-87348-828-8 (paper)
* Brecher, Jeremy., ''Strike!'', 1997. ISBN 0-89608-570-8 (cloth)
* Dailey, Lucia. &quot;Mine Seed,&quot; 2002. ISBN I-4033-6697-7
{{Refend}}
{{American Labor Conflicts}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Great Railroad Strike Of 1877}}
[[Category:1877 in the United States]]
[[Category:1877 labor disputes and strikes]]
[[Category:History of the United States (1865–1918)]]
[[Category:History of West Virginia]]
[[Category:Labor disputes in the United States]]
[[Category:History of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:Rail transport strikes]]
[[Category:1877 in rail transport]]
[[Category:Political repression in the United States]]
[[Category:History of rail transportation in the United States]]

[[ja:1877年の鉄道大ストライキ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
