<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3608404" ns="0" title="Corruption"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses}}
{{redirect4|Corrupt|Corruptor}}
{{redirect2|Corrupted|Corruptors|the Japanese doom metal band|Corrupted (band)|the American television series|Target: The Corruptors!}}
{{redirect|Debauchery|the German death metal band|Debauchery (band)}}
In [[philosophy|philosophical]], [[theology|theological]], or moral discussions, '''corruption''' is [[spiritual]] or [[moral]] [[impurity]] or deviation from an [[Ideal (ethics)|ideal]]. In [[economy]], corruption is [[payment]] for services or material which the recipient is not due, under law. This may be called [[bribery]], [[kickback]], or, in the Middle East, [[baksheesh]].

==Etymology==
The word '''corrupt''' (Middle English, from Latin ''corruptus'', past participle of ''corrumpere'', to abuse or destroy : ''com-'', [[intensive]] pref. and ''rumpere'', to break) when used as an adjective literally means &quot;utterly broken&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/corrupt |title=Corrupt &amp;#124; Define Corrupt at Dictionary.com |publisher=Dictionary.reference.com |date= |accessdate=2010-12-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Corrupt activities==
{{Expand section|English text rather than a &quot;see also&quot; type list|date=August 2011}}
* [[Abuse of the system]]
* [[Bid rigging]]
* [[Bribery]] in politics, business, or sport
* [[Cartel]]
* [[Collusion]], an agreement between two or more persons, sometimes illegal and therefore secretive, to limit open competition by deceiving, misleading, or defrauding others of their legal rights, or to obtain an objective forbidden by law typically by defrauding or gaining an unfair advantage
* [[Cronyism]]
* [[Electoral fraud]]
* [[Embezzlement]]
* [[Influence peddling]]
* [[Nepotism]]
* [[Organized crime]]
* [[Patronage]]
* [[Price Fixing]]

==By field==
===Politics===
{{main|Political corruption}}
Political corruption is the abuse of public power, office, or resources by elected government officials for personal gain, e.g. by extortion, soliciting or offering bribes&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | last = Chinhamo | first = Obert | last2 = Shumba | first2 = Gabriel
 | title = Institutional working definition of corruption
 | publisher = Anti-Corruption Trust of Southern Africa | year = 2007
 | url =  http://www.actsouthernafrica.org/Working%20Paper%201-%20Draft%20Institutional%20Working%20definition%20of%20Corruption.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; It can also take the form of office holders maintaining themselves in office by purchasing votes by enacting laws which use taxpayer money.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sos.mo.gov/archives/pubs/article/article.asp]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Systemic corruption]], the complete subversion of a political or economic system.
Governmental corruption of judiciary is broadly known in many transitional and [[developing countries]] because the [[budget]] is almost completely controlled by the executive. The latter undermines the separation of powers, as it creates a critical financial dependence of the judiciary. The proper national wealth distribution including the government spending on the judiciary is subject of the [[constitutional economics]].
It is important to distinguish between the two methods of corruption of the judiciary: the government (through budget planning and various privileges), and the private.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first= Peter |last=Barenboim |title= Defining the rules |publisher= The European Lawyer |volume= Issue 90 |date=October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Police===
{{main|Police corruption}}
Police corruption is a specific form of [[police misconduct]] designed to obtain financial benefits, other personal gain, and/or career advancement for a police officer or officers in exchange for not pursuing, or selectively pursuing, an investigation or arrest. One common form of police corruption is soliciting and/or accepting [[bribe]]s in exchange for not reporting organized drug or prostitution rings or other illegal activities. Another example is police officers flouting the police [[code of conduct]] in order to secure convictions of suspects — for example, through the use of [[falsified evidence]]. More rarely, police officers may deliberately and systematically participate in [[organized crime]] themselves. In most major cities, there are [[Internal affairs (law enforcement)|internal affairs]] sections to investigate suspected police corruption or misconduct. Similar entities include the British [[Independent Police Complaints Commission]].

==Philosophy==
Frequently in philosophical discussions, corruption takes the form of contrasting a pure spiritual form with a corrupted manifestation in the physical world.  Many philosophers, in fact, have regarded the physical world as inevitably corrupt ([[Plato]]{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} being the most famous example of this school of thought). The [[Book of Genesis]] 6:12 similarly describes a world before [[Noah's Ark|the flood]] where 'everyone on earth was corrupt' ([[New Living Translation|NLT]]).

Another philosophical use of the term &quot;corruption&quot; is in opposition to &quot;generation,&quot; as in [[Aristotle's]] book ''[[On Generation and Corruption]]'' also known as ''On Coming to Be and Passing Away''.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}} In this sense, corruption is the process of ceasing to exist and is closely related to the concept of dying given certain views about the nature of living things. In a moral sense, corruption generally refers to [[decadence]] or [[hedonism]]. In theological or political debates, certain viewpoints are sometimes accused of being corruptions of orthodox systems of belief, which is to say, they are accused of having deviated from some older correct view.

==See also==
*[[Orthodoxy]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
{{Corruption}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Corruption (Philosophical Concept)}}

[[Category:Concepts in ethics]]
[[Category:Corruption| ]]

{{Link GA|ru}}

[[ar:فساد (توضيح)]]
[[az:Korrupsiya]]
[[be:Карупцыя]]
[[be-x-old:Карупцыя]]
[[bs:Korupcija]]
[[bg:Корупция]]
[[ca:Corrupció]]
[[cs:Korupce]]
[[da:Korruption]]
[[de:Korruption]]
[[es:Corrupción]]
[[et:Korruptsioon]]
[[eo:Korupto]]
[[fr:Corruption]]
[[hi:भ्रष्टाचार (आचरण)]]
[[hr:Korupcija]]
[[id:Korupsi]]
[[it:Corruzione]]
[[la:Corruptio]]
[[lt:Korupcija]]
[[hu:Korrupció]]
[[mg:Kolikoly]]
[[ms:Korupsi]]
[[nl:Corruptie]]
[[no:Korrupsjon]]
[[nn:Korrupsjon]]
[[pl:Korupcja]]
[[pt:Corrupção]]
[[ro:Corupție]]
[[ru:Коррупция]]
[[sq:Korrupsioni]]
[[sk:Korupcia]]
[[sr:Корупција]]
[[su:Basilat]]
[[fi:Korruptio]]
[[sv:Korruption]]
[[tg:Фасод]]
[[tr:Usulsuzlük]]
[[uk:Корупція]]
[[yo:Ìwàìbàjẹ́]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
