<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="362136" ns="0" title="University of Northern Colorado"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Cleanup|date=September 2010}}
{{coord|40.404853|-104.696741|display=title|type:edu}}
{{Infobox University
 |name = University of Northern Colorado
 |image_name = University of Northern Colorado.svg 
 |image_size = 200px
 |motto = Sapientia in aeterum est
 |mottoeng = Wisdom is eternal
 |established = April 1, 1889
 |type = [[Public university|Public]]
 | endowment = [[United States Dollar|US $]]61.5 million&lt;ref&gt;As of June 30, 2009.  {{Cite web | title = U.S. and Canadian Institutions Listed by Fiscal Year 2009 Endowment Market Value and Percentage Change in Endowment Market Value from FY 2008 to FY 2009| work = 2009 NACUBO-Commonfund Study of Endowments | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf| format = PDF | accessdate = February 26, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |chairman = Dick Monfort
 |chancellor =
 |president = [[Kay Norton]]
 |vice-president =
 |superintendent =
 |provost = Abe Harraf
 |vice_chancellor =
 |rector =
 |principal =
 |dean =
 |director =
 |head_label =
 |head =
 |faculty = 413&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/about_unc/index.html|title=About UNC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |staff =
 |students =
 |undergrad = 10,097&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot;/&gt;
 |postgrad = 2,261&lt;ref name=&quot;about&quot;/&gt;
 |doctoral =
 |other =
 |alumni = 90,000&lt;ref name=&quot;alumni&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.uncalumni.org/|title=University of Northern Colorado Alumni}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |city = [[Greeley, Colorado|Greeley]]
 |state = [[Colorado]]
 |country = [[United States]]
 |campus = [[urban area|Suburban]]&lt;br/&gt;{{convert|250|acre|km2|1}}
 |former_names = Colorado State Normal School&lt;br/&gt;Colorado State Teachers College&lt;br/&gt;Colorado State College of Education&lt;br/&gt;Colorado State College
 |colors = [[Navy blue]] and [[Gold (color)|gold]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#000066}} {{color box|#FFCC33}}
 |former_colors = [[Purple]] and [[Gold (color)|gold]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#660099}} {{color box|#FFCC33}}
 |nickname = Bears
 |mascot = &quot;Klawz&quot;
 |athletics = [[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] FCS&lt;br/&gt;19 varsity teams
 |affiliations = [[Big Sky Conference]]
 |website = [http://www.unco.edu www.unco.edu]|
 |footnotes = Enrollment figures are as of Fall 2010.{{citation needed|date=December 2010}}&lt;ref name=&quot;enrollment&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/acctservices/instanalysis/pdf/Fall06FactBook.pdf|title=Fall 2006 Fact Book|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
The '''University of Northern Colorado''' ('''UNC''' or '''Northern Colorado''') is a coeducational public institution of higher education in [[Greeley, Colorado]] with a satellite campus in [[Lowry, Denver|Lowry]] in [[Denver, Colorado]]. Established in 1889 as the State Normal School of Colorado, the University has a strong background in teacher education. The university offers over 100 undergraduate programs in the arts, sciences, humanities, business, human sciences, and education. Undergraduate degrees are typically 4 year programs and degree programs have a strong emphasis in liberal arts education. The university offers nearly 50 graduate programs primarily in education. Academic programs are distributed among six colleges.&lt;ref name=&quot;degrees&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/about_unc/|title=About UNC}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
The history of The University of Northern Colorado begins in the late 1880s, when citizens of Greeley petitioned the Colorado government to create a school to educate teachers in their community. In April 1889 Governor Cooper signed a bill establishing the Colorado State Normal School. Classes began in October of the next year. Since then the institution has been through many changes in focus, architecture, and student ideals.&lt;ref name=&quot;brief_history&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/library/archives/arc_previous_names.htm|title=Archives}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The University of Northern Colorado opened on October 6, 1890, as the '''Colorado State Normal School''' to train qualified teachers for the state's public schools, with a staff of four instructors and 96 students, offering certification after completing a two-year course. Greeley's citizens raised the necessary money for the first building. At that time, certificates were granted upon the completion of a two-year course. In 1911 the school's name was changed to '''Colorado State Teachers College''' and offered bachelor degrees after completion of a four-year course. In 1935 the name changed again to '''Colorado State College of Education''' to recognize the graduate program, which was started in 1913. In 1957 the name was shortened to '''Colorado State College''' to recognize the further growth of programs and offerings. Finally, in 1970 the name was changed to the current '''University of Northern Colorado'''.

Originally Colorado State Normal School occupied only one building, Cranford Hall.  It was set fire to in 1949 by a disgruntled theater student who was later arrested for this and several other crimes. The building was repaired, and classes were held there until 1965 when the building was deemed unsafe for classroom use. Many offices were held here until December 1971 when the entire structure became too unsafe to use, and in 1972 the building was demolished. The cornerstone was saved and now graces the northeast corner of &quot;Cranford Park&quot; with four commemorative plaques regarding Cranford's significance and legacy in UNC's history.

The south end of Central Campus grew with the addition of Gordon Hall, Belford Hall, and Decker Hall in 1921, which were originally built as female residence halls. Around this time, the Faculty Apartments were built, later known as Presidents Row. The Faculty Apartments were built shortly after the President's House, now used as the Visitors Center. Sabin, Snyder, and Tobey-Kendel Halls were added in 1936 when enrollment was growing, and men's residence halls were added on the old East Campus. These halls, Hadden and Hayes, are east of Campus on 6th Avenue. The institution sold the land and buildings, and are no longer used as residence halls.  In the 1950s Weibking Hall, Wilson Hall, and a larger dining space were added on to the already existing Tobey-Kendel Hall to accommodate the large influx of students after the war had ended. In 1997, students voted on a fee increase to fund two buildings to house the Women's Resource Center, the Counseling Center, and the Student Health Center.  Scott-Willcoxon and Cassidy Halls opened in 1999 with the new Hansen-Willis residence hall.

In the late 1950s the school grew beyond the available acreage.  The institution found an outlet for expansion in the Petrikin family farm to the southwest of the main campus, adding about {{convert|150|acre|km2}}.  West Campus expanded to include a new library, several residence halls, academic halls, recreation center, and football and other athletic facilities.  The 1960s was a flurry of construction with a new building erected almost every year.  Built in 1963, McCowen Hall was the first co-educational residence hall, and hosted nearly 30,000 students over the course of its lifetime.  In the late part of the decade, McKee Hall and Turner Residence Hall opened, adding spaces for the College of Education and 600 residents, respectively.  In the early 1970s, James A. Michener Library, Lawrenson Hall and Candelaria Hall would be the last buildings to be added to campus for almost 20 years, until the Campus Recreation Center opened in the mid-1990s.  Most recently,  McCowen was torn down in 2008 to make room for new residence halls, North and South Hall.

==Traditions==
===Alma mater===
''Ah! Well I Remember'' is the [[alma mater]] of the University of Northern Colorado. It was written by J. De Forest Cline. The words Purple and Gold refer to the previous colors of the institution. While the current colors are Navy Blue and Gold the alma mater retained the former colors.&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Ah! Well I Remember, Friends of “Purple and Gold.”&lt;/br&gt;
Friends met in September, Pledging their Faith to hold.&lt;/br&gt;
Gone, Friends of September, Gone dear friends of old.&lt;/br&gt;
Time never shall sever, Friends of “Purple and Gold.”&lt;/br&gt;
Time never shall sever, Friends of “Purple and Gold.”
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Campus==
The campus is divided into two main areas: central, and west. UNC's Central Campus includes the areas north of 20th Street and west of 8th Avenue in [[Greeley, Colorado]]. The residence halls on Central Campus have been designated a state historic district.&lt;ref name=&quot;refname1&quot; group=&quot;Ref&quot;/&gt; UNC's Central Campus was the original part of the campus and currently houses the College of Performing &amp; Visual Arts, schools in the College of Natural &amp; Health Science, and the Kenneth W. Monfort College of Business.  Central has a quieter, more traditional &quot;collegiate&quot; feeling.

West Campus includes the areas south of 20th Street and west of 10th Avenue, including the College of Humanities &amp; Social Sciences, College of Education &amp; Behavioral Sciences, and schools in the College of Natural &amp; Health Sciences.  West Campus houses 2,000 students and is generally the more social area of campus.

===Other locations===
The university operates several satellite campuses, with locations in [[Loveland, Colorado]], [[Denver, Colorado]], and [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]].  The Denver campus hosts two programs, the Center for Urban Education (focuses on providing opportunities for working teachers), and the DO-IT Center (ASL-English interpreter training).

Old Man Mountain is a group of cabins owned by the University located in [[Estes Park, Colorado]], and serves as a common retreat location for the community.

===References===
{{reflist|group=&quot;Ref&quot;|refs=
&lt;ref name=&quot;refname1&quot;&gt;http://www.coloradohistory-oahp.org/programareas/register/1503/cty/wl.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Organization==
The University of Northern Colorado offers 100 undergraduate programs and more than 100 graduate programs.&lt;ref name=&quot;majors&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/about_unc/index.html|title=About UNC|publisher=unco.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university has a satellite campus in [[Denver, Colorado]]

The Board of Trustees for the University oversees the administration and approves the University's annual budget. Several members of the University's administrative team are ex-oficio members of the Board (for example, the Vice President for Finance &amp; Administration is also the Treasurer to the Board).

===Presidents===
* Thomas J. Gray 1890-1891
* James H. Hayes. Interim 1891, November 11, 1915–1916
* Zachariah Xenophon Snyder. 1891-1915
* John Grant Crabbe. Late summer 1916-1924
* George Willard Frasier. 1924-1947
* William Robert Ross. 1947-1964 (assumed office December 20, 1947)
* Darrell Holmes. 1964-1971
* Frank P. Lakin. 1969, 1971 Interim President
* Richard R. Bond. 1971-1981
* Charles Manning, Acting President. 1981
* Robert C. Dickeson. 1981-1991
* Richard Davies. 1987 Acting President January 1-August 29, 1987
* Stephen T. Hulbert. 1991 Interim President July 1-September 30, 1991
* Herman Lujan. 1991-1996
* Howard Skinner. Interim President June 1996-June 1998
* Hank Brown. July 1998-June 2002
* Kay Norton. July 2002 -

===Current trustees===
* Dick Monfort, Chairman
* Kevin Smith
* Dr. Gilbert (Gil) Carbajal
* Jerry Morgensen
* Dr. Darlene LeDoux
* Carlotta Lanier
* Dr. Joan Clinefelter
* Michael Johnston&lt;ref name=&quot;trustees&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/trustees/trustees.htm|title=Trustees|publisher=unco.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academic profile==
By enrollment, The University of Northern Colorado is the third largest university in Colorado. It had a Fall 2010 enrollment of 10,090 undergraduate students and 2,268 graduate students for a total of 12,358 students.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/news/releases.asp?ID=1033|title=University of Northern Colorado Fall 2010 Census|publisher=unco.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt; In that year most of the students came from Colorado but the student population represents 48 states, three territories, 42 countries, and six continents. The Student population is 62% female and 38% male. 15% of students identified themselves as &quot;minorities.&quot; Typically, 96% of undergraduates are employed or attending graduate school one year after graduating from the University of Northern Colorado.&lt;ref name=&quot;alumni&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.unco.edu/about_unc|title=About the University of Northern Colorado|publisher=unco.edu}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Colleges and schools===
In August 2003, President Kay Norton began a planning and reorganization process to guide the University. On of the outcomes of that process was to re-organize the University into five colleges of approximately equal size in addition to the University College. University College has programs for freshman and transfer students before they declare a major. Within each college are several schools that administer the various academic programs.
&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About the Charting the Future Process|publisher=University of Northern Colorado|url=http://www.unco.edu/pres/charting/|accessdate=2009-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* College of Education and Behavioral Sciences
**School of Educational Research Leadership and Technology;
**School of Psychological Sciences
**School of Applied Psychology and Counselor Education
**School of Special Education; and Teacher Education
* College of Humanities and Social Sciences
**School of Communication
**School of English Language and Literature
**School of History, Philosophy, and Political Science
**School of Modern Languages and Cultural Studies
**School of Social Sciences
* College of Natural and Health Sciences
**School of Biological Sciences
**School of Chemistry, Earth Science and Physics
**School of Human Sciences
**School of Mathematical Sciences
**School of Nursing
**School of Sport and Exercise Science
* College of Performing and Visual Arts
**School of Art and Design
**School of Music
**School of Theatre Arts and Dance
* [[Monfort College of Business|Kenneth W. Monfort College of Business]]
**School of Accounting and Computer Information Systems
**School of Finance and Quantitative Methods
**School of Management and Marketing
*University College

===Libraries===
===James A. Michener Library===
The University of Northern Colorado’s main library houses approximately 1.8 million items including books, periodicals, government publications, CDs, videos, DVDs and maps. It is named after author [[James A. Michener]], who received his master's degree from and taught at the university before beginning his writing career. Michener bequeathed the majority of his literary legacy to the university upon his death. The reference desk at the library is open to the public from 9 a.m. to 9 p.m. weekdays.

===Howard M. Skinner Music Library===
Skinner Library specializes in curricular support of the School of Music and Musical Theatre Programs. Its collections, comprising more than 90,000 musical scores, books, periodicals and recordings, are housed in a state-of-the-art facility that opened in October 1997.

==Student life==
===Greek Life===
====Traditional Sororities====
*[[Alpha Omicron Pi]]
*[[Alpha Sigma Alpha]]
*[[Alpha Phi]]
*[[Delta Zeta]]
*[[Sigma Kappa]]

====Traditional Fraternities====
*[[Delta Tau Delta]]
*[[Sigma Chi]]
*[[Alpha Kappa Lambda]]
*[[Delta Sigma Phi]]
*[[Kappa Sigma]]
*[[Lambda Chi Alpha]]
*[[Pi Kappa Phi]]

====Multicultural Sororities====
*[[Lambda Theta Nu]]
*[[Pi Lambda Chi]]
*[[Sigma Lambda Gamma]]

====Multicultural Fraternities====
*[[Sigma Lambda Beta]]
*[[Nu Alpha Kappa]]

====Other====
[[Phi Sigma Pi]] National Honor Fraternity (Co-ed)

===Cultural centers===
*Asian/Pacific American Student Services
*César Chávez Cultural Center
*Marcus Garvey Cultural Center
*Native American Student Services
*Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, Transgender and Allies Resource Office
*Women's Resource Center

===Student housing===
The University of Northern Colorado has 17 student residence halls; twelve on Central Campus and five on West Campus.

Students have a variety of options when &quot;claiming their space&quot; on-campus. Options include, but are not limited to: same-gender communities for males and females, co-educational communities, and even co-educational rooms. Room options include everything from traditional suite-style rooms to fully furnished on-campus apartments. 

There are also a variety of &quot;living &amp; learning communities&quot; at UNC, including floors for elementary education majors, performing and visual arts majors, quiet lifestyles, GLBTA, leadership focused and healthy-living/wellness.

===Radio Station===
UNC Student Radio (UNCSR) broadcasts 24/7 on the internet at http://www.uncradio.com or www.uncradio.com. The station generally plays pre-programmed rock/pop during the day, with live, student-hosted shows in the afternoons and evenings during the school year.
The station, first chartered in 1995 and which is almost entirely student-run, currently operates from the basement of Davis House and streams to all the UNC dorms via cable TV channel 3. The station currently is run by [http://www.uncradio.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=7:sam-wood-general-manager&amp;catid=14:board-members&amp;Itemid=6 Sam Wood]

==Athletics==
[[Image:NorthernColorado.jpeg|thumb|right|The logo of Northern Colorado athletics, in use since 2004]]

Sports teams at the school are called ''Bears.'' Northern Colorado is currently in the fourth year of a four-year process of moving from [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]]’s [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]] to [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]], Football Championship Subdivision (formerly I-AA) for [[American football|football]]. Northern Colorado joined the [[Big Sky Conference]] on July 1, 2006. The school mascot is Klawz the [[Bear]] and the school colors are Navy Blue and [[Gold]]. The Fight Song is the “UNC Fight Song”.

Before, UNC was a member of the [[Rocky Mountain Athletic Conference]] from 1923 to 1972. Joining the [[Great Plains Athletic Conference]] for four years (1972–76). Following several years of being conference independent, The University of Northern Colorado joined the [[North Central Conference]]. The Bears have won two Division II Football National Championships in 1996 and 1997.  Northern Colorado's Athletic Director is Jay Hinrichs. On [[March 9]], [[2011]] the Bears won the [[Big Sky Conference]] tournament championship in [[men's basketball]], clinching a trip to the [[2011 NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]], the first in the school's history.

The Bears play their football games at [[Nottingham Field]], while the Men's and Women's Basketball teams and Women's Volleyball team play at the [[Butler-Hancock Sports Pavilion]]. &quot;Fear The Claw&quot; is the student section slogan. Northern Colorado won its first Big Sky Championship in 2009 when the Women's Volleyball team beat Portland State to capture the Big Sky Volleyball Championship. The Bears have many athletes in the pros. Probably the biggest is [[Vincent Jackson]] who attended and played football at Northern Colorado from 2001 to 2004 before being drafted by the [[San Diego Chargers]] in the [[2005 NFL Draft]]. Other famous football alums for the school are: punter [[Dirk Johnson]], safety [[Reed Doughty]] who plays for the [[Washington Redskins]], defensive lineman [[Aaron Smith (American football)|Aaron Smith]] of the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]], and over 10 others.

===Mascots===
[[Image:2005 1029Homecoming0142.JPG|thumb|right|The university's mascot, &quot;Klawz&quot;]]

The bear is the mascot of the UNC. The bear officially became the mascot in 1923. Before the school adopted the bear as their mascot, athletes used the nickname the Teachers.&lt;ref&gt;Various ''The Mirror''s and ''Cache La Poudre''s&lt;/ref&gt;  The bear was said to be inspired by a bear on top of an Alaskan totem pole donated by an 1897 alum in 1914. The totem pole was kept in the University Center, but under the federal Native American Graves Protection and Repatriation Act of 1990, the pole was reclaimed by the [[Tlingit people|Tlingit]] in 2003. Klawz in the mascot that attends all the sports games. Klawz is the newest addition to the long line of Bears' mascots over the years at the University of Northern Colorado. He was recruited after Gunter Bear became exhausted from his duties and retired.  Klawz made his first appearance in Nottingham Field on August 30, 2003 before the UNC football team opened their season against New Mexico Highlands.

==Achievements==
===Normal school===
Founded in 1889 as the State Normal School, Northern Colorado met a vital need to train qualified teachers in the growing state of Colorado, which was then less than 15 years old. More than a century and four name changes later, the institution has grown to become a [http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=4917&amp;start=782 Doctoral Research] university. At Northern Colorado's centennial in 1989, only four universities in the U.S. surpassed it in the total number of teachers trained.{{cite book | last = Larson | first = Robert | title = Shaping educational change: the first century of the University of Northern Colorado at Greeley | origyear = 1889 | accessdate = 2006}} All current Northern Colorado programs are clustered around an institutional mission devoted to teacher education. Its early dedication to reaching the highest levels of educational excellence, coupled with the generation and dissemination of new pedagogical knowledge, earned Northern Colorado the name “Columbia of the West.”{{cite book | last = Larson | first = Robert | title = Shaping educational change: the first century of the University of Northern Colorado at Greeley | origyear = 1889 | accessdate = 2006}} In 1985, the Colorado Legislature took the unique step of designating Northern Colorado as “the primary institution for undergraduate and graduate teacher education in the state of Colorado.”{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}

===Monfort College of Business===
The Kenneth W. [[Monfort College of Business]] at the University of Northern Colorado offers the only program of its kind in the Rocky Mountain region – focused exclusively on undergraduate business education and internationally accredited in business administration and accounting. One of five undergraduate-only programs in the United States to hold such accreditations, Monfort is the sole business school to receive the Malcolm Baldrige National Quality Award from the Office of the President of the United States and the U.S. Department of Commerce, the Timberline Award from Colorado Performance Excellence, and the Program of Excellence Award from the Colorado Commission on Higher Education. Students at Monfort score in the top 5% on nationwide standardized exit exams and earn a degree in Business Administration with an emphasis in accounting, computer information systems, finance, general business, management, or marketing.

===School of Music===
The University of Northern Colorado [[Music school|School of Music]] is one of the larger and more successful programs within the University and is well-known in the region for its [[music education]] and [[Jazz]] Studies programs, as well as having one of the first full-scale [[music technology]] centers in the country. The award-winning Jazz Studies program, reared from infancy by [[Gene Aitken]], is currently led by Grammy-nominated jazz composer/pianist [[Dana Landry]]. The program under Landry has received much acclaim in recent years. The Northern Colorado Jazz Lab I under his direction has received the [[Down Beat]] magazine award for best college big band in 2005 and 2006. It has also recently become one of a very limited number of schools in the world to offer a doctoral program in jazz, with their Doctor of Arts with an emphasis in Jazz Studies.

==Notable alumni==
* Steve Antonopulos, head athletic trainer of the [[Denver Broncos]]
* [[Glen Alps]], printmaker, coiner of the term [[collagraph]]
* [[Gregg Brandon]], college football coach of the [[Wyoming Cowboys]]
* Fred Brown, ''[[The Denver Post]]'' political writer and columnist
* [[Jennifer and Natalie Jo Campbell]], December Playmates 2008
* [[Steven Dietz]], playwright
* [[Reed Doughty]], football player of the [[Washington Redskins]]
* [[Ben Dreith]], [[American Football League]] and [[National Football League]] referee
* [[Bill Frisell]], jazz guitarist
* [[Greg Germann]], actor from ''[[Ally McBeal]]''
* Marian Hesse, Grammy-winning horn player
* [[Vincent Jackson]], football player of the [[San Diego Chargers]]
* [[Virgil Jester]], baseball player
* [[Dirk Johnson]], football player
* [[Dave Keller]], baseball player and coach
* [[James P. Kelley]], money manager
* [[Bill Kenney]], football player and politician
* [[Maryanne Kusaka]], politician
* [[Carlotta Walls LaNier]], member of the Little Rock Nine
* [[James A. Michener]], author
* [[Carol Mutter]], [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] Lieutenant General
* Brad Nuccio, Senior Vice President of Saint Louis Science Center and Executive Director of National Center for Science
* Mark Nuccio, currently the Assistant Principal and Eb clarinetist of the [[New York Philharmonic]]
* Brad Pyatt, former [[National Football League]] player and current [[Arena Football League (1987–2008)|Arena Football League]] [[wide receiver]]
* [[Sayyid Qutb]], author and a leading [[Islamist]] of the 20th century
* [[Jeannie Ritter]], Colorado First Lady
* [[Neal Rubin]], ''[[The Detroit News]]'' columnist and author of comic strip [[Gil Thorp]].
* [[Chesley Sullenberger|Chesley B. &quot;Sully&quot; Sullenberger]], Captain of U.S. Airways Flight 1549, that successfully landed in the Hudson River in 2009, he has a M.A. in Public Relations from UNC
* [[Aaron Smith (American football)|Aaron Smith]], football player of the [[Pittsburgh Steelers]]
* [[Tom Tancredo]], R-CO, member of [[United States House of Representatives]] and presidential candidate.
* [[Tom Walsh (Wyoming politician)|Tom Walsh]], R-WY, [[mayor]] of [[Casper, Wyoming|Casper]] and member of the [[Wyoming House of Representatives]] (2003–2008); received [[Ed.D.]] through UNC&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.casperjournal.com/articles/2010/01/04/news/news10.txt|title=Carol Crump, &quot;Dr. Tom Walsh, 67, died of leukemia in Casper on New Years Day, 2010&quot;|publisher=''Casper Journal'', January 3, 2010|accessdate=January 7, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Wellington Webb]], former mayor of Denver
* [[Ed Werder]], reporter for [[ESPN]]
* [[Connie Willis]], science fiction author
* [[Kenneth W. Winters]], member of the [[Kentucky State Senate]]
* [[Jack Cassinetto]], plein air painter

== References ==
{{reflist}}

==Further reading==
* Albert Frank Carter - &quot;Forty years of Colorado State Teachers College, formerly the State Normal School of Colorado, 1890-1930&quot;
* Larson, Robert W; Boulder: Colorado Associated University Press, (1989). ''Shaping educational change: the first century of the University of Northern Colorado at Greeley&quot;. ISBN 0-87081-172-X.
* Kurt Hinkle - &quot;Northern Light: The Complete History of the University of Northern Colorado Football Program.&quot; (1998).

==External links==
{{Portal box|Colorado|University}}
{{commons category|University of Northern Colorado}}
*{{Official|http://www.unco.edu}}
*[http://www.uncbears.com/ Official athletics website]

{{University of Northern Colorado}}
{{Navboxes|titlestyle = background:#000066; color:#FFCC33; border:1px solid #000066;|list1=
{{Public colleges and universities in Colorado}}
{{Big Sky Conference}}
{{ColoCol}}
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Northern Colorado, University Of}}
[[Category:University of Northern Colorado|*]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Land-grant universities and colleges]]
[[Category:Greeley, Colorado|University of Northern Colorado]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1889]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Education in Weld County, Colorado]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Weld County, Colorado]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Weld County, Colorado]]

[[de:University of Northern Colorado]]
[[fa:دانشگاه کلرادو شمالی]]
[[fr:University of Northern Colorado]]
[[no:University of Northern Colorado]]
[[simple:University of Northern Colorado]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
