<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3622054" ns="0" title="Punjabi Shaikh"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{ethnic group|
|group= Punjabi Shaikh 
|image= [[File:A Khattri nobleman, in 'Kitab-i tasrih al-aqvam' by Col. James Skinner, aka Sikandar (1778-1841).jpg|150px]]
|caption = A Khattri nobleman, in ''Kitab-i tasrih al-aqvam'' by [[James Skinner (soldier)|Col. James Skinner]] in (1778-1841)
|poptime = 10 million 
|popplace = • {{flagcountry|Pakistan}} • {{flagcountry|India}} •{{flagcountry|Europe}} • {{flagcountry|United States}} • {{flagcountry|Canada}} • {{flagcountry|Australia}} • {{flagcountry|Dubai}} • {{flagcountry|Saudi Arabia}}  
|langs = • [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]] • [[English language|English]] • [[Urdu language|Urdu]]
|rels=• [[Image:Allah-green.svg|18px]] [[Islam]] 100%
|related=• [[Shaikhs in South Asia]] • [[Khatri]]s 
}}

'''Sheikh''' ([[Arabic language|Arabic]] and [[Punjabi language|Punjabi]]: '''شيخ''' ), is an Arabic word meaning elder of a tribe, lord, Honorable revered old man, or [[Ulema|Islamic scholar]]. In South Asia it is used as an ethnic title generally attributed to Muslim trading families. 

From the beginning of [[Muslim]] rule in [[South Asia]] in 713 AD, the [[Muslim]] technocrats, bureaucrats, soldiers, traders, scientists, architects, teachers, theologians and [[sufis]] traveled from the rest of the [[Muslim]] world to the Islamic Sultanate in South Asia and settled permanently. 

In [[South Asia]], after the advent of [[Islam]], some high caste ([[Brahmins]], [[Rajputs]] and [[Khatri]]s) converted to [[Islam]] in the [[Punjab region]] and adopted this title. They are known as '''Punjabi Shaikh''' ([[Punjabi language|Punjabi]]) '''پنجابی شيخ'''. Punjabi Shaikhs are mostly urban and non agriculturist but a few families also cultivate their own land in the western districts. Their main professions are business and public service. In Punjab, they stereotypically have a reputation for business acumen. The [[Khawaja Shaikh]], with their sub-division the [[Chiniotis]] and the [[Qanungoh Shaikh]] are two such communities.

Before the independence of [[Pakistan]] in 1947, [[Khatri]]s were living in all the districts of [[Punjab region|Punjab]]. Most of them were concentrated in the western districts. People from all classes; Khatris, [[Muslim Rajput|Rajput]]s, [[Gujjar]]s, [[Gakhars]], etc; had converted to [[Islam]]. The [[Siddiqui]] Shaikhs and [[Quraishi]] Shaikhs are communities that are the descended from these converted classes. They are found in Punjab as Punjabi speaking Shaikhs and also found in Sindh as Sindhi speaking Shaikhs. 

The Saraswat [[Brahmins]], including Mohyals, adopted Sheikh as their title upon high cast conversion to [[Islam]]. Similarly, many [[Rajput]] clans had converted to Islam during the early 12th century and were also given the honorary title of Sheikh (elder of the tribe) by their Arab rulers. Sheikh rajputs were the earliest in Rajputs to embrace [[Islam]].

==Muslim Khatris==

Khatris have an extensive military tradition and have excelled in the Armed Forces, having received many honors and gallantry awards for their service. Former chief of Indian Army, General Deepak Kapoor was Khatri and he took charge from another Khatri, General Joginder Jaswant Singh (Marwah) who took charge from another Khatri, General Nirmal Chander Vij. Khatris have sometimes expanded into trade and mercantile businesses, including architecture. All ten [[Sikh Gurus]] were Khatri.  

The [[Muslim]] Khatri ({{lang-ur|''' کهتری '''}}) are the Khatri converts to Islam. Although a large majority of Khatris are Hindus, some converted to Islam. The conversion started in 12th century and continued till 1947. In western districts of the Punjab (Sargodha, Mianwali, Multan, Jhang, Chakwal, Rawalpindi and Faislabad) converted Khatri traders called themselves &quot;Khoja&quot;. Some time they are called &quot;Khoja Sheikh&quot;.  With the advent of Islam following invasions by [[Turkic peoples|Turkic]] tribes from [[Afghanistan]] and the [[North West Frontier Province]] from the 11th century onwards, there were conversions of Hindus to the faith from among various Punjabi communities, including Khatris.Generally they retained their tribal, clan or caste affiliations as has been the norm in the region. Similarly, the Khatris who converted to Islam, continue to retain a strong social identity and are known as ''Punjabi Shaikhs''.

Pakistan continues to have a prominent community of Khatris known as Punjabi Shaikhs as well as [[Khawaja Shaikh]]s. Some Muslim Khatris like the [[Sahgal family]], [[Aftab Ahmed Vohra]], [[Najam Sethi]], etc of Pakistan are examples of well-known and successful Muslim Khatris. They are also known as [[Khoja]] and [[Chiniotis]].

In addition the [[Punjabi Saudagaran-e-Delhi]] community are also of Khatri ancestry. Historically, this community lived in [[Delhi]], and other north Indian towns, but after the [[partition of India]], they have all moved to [[Pakistan]].In [[Pakistan]] also the [[Muslim]] [[Khatris]] are expanded to various occupations.

== Khawaja Shaikh ==
{{Main|Khawaja Shaikh}}

Members of the [[Khatris]] caste, after converting to [[Islam]] adopted the title [[Khawaja Shaikh]] ({{lang-ar|''' خواجہ شيخ'''}}) and to this community belong many prominent [[Muslim]] trading families of [[South Asia]].

When Khatri traders from the western districts of the Punjab like [[Sargodha District|Sargodha]], [[Jhang District|Jhang]], [[Jhelum District|Jehlum]], [[Chakwal District|Chakwal]], [[Faisalabad District|Faisalabad]] accepted Islam called themselves [[Khawaja]] and adopted [[Shaikh]] as title. They are thus called ''Khawaja Sheikh''. Some of them have also adopted [[Mian]] as title. In recent years traders from a small town of [[Chiniot]],in the [[Chiniot District]], became prominent due to their contribution in the industries of [[Pakistan]]. These traders are known as [[Chiniotis]] or ''[[Chinioti Shaikh]]s''. The famous trading family of [[Sahgal]]s, Sahgal Khatris of [[Chakwal District|Chakwal]], are known simply as ''Punjabi Shaikh'' instead of ''Khawaja Shaikh''. They use [[Mian]] as title.

The first censuses of the Punjab were conducted by [[Denzil Ibbetson]] and [[Edward Maclagan]] in 1883 and 1892. According to their reports, the Khawajas of Bhera in Shahpur, [[Sargodha District]]  were converted from Khatris, and those from [[Jhang]] were said to be converted from [[Arora]]. At [[Chiniot]] in [[Jhang District]], Majority of the Khawajas are Khatris, while some are Arora. They reported the following sections (gotras) of Khatris from Chiniot:

''[[Adal]], [[Behrara]], [[Churra]], [[Maggun]] (or Maghoon), [[Sahgal]], [[Wadhaun]] (or Vadhavan), Wihara, [[Talwar]], [[Puri]], [[Topra]]''.

Only one section of Arora is reported from Chiniot:

''Goruwala''.

The sections of Khawajas from Bhera were reported as follows:

''[[Vohra]], [[Sahgal]], [[Kapur]], [[Sethi]], [[Duggal]], [[Nanda]], [[Magun]], [[Mehndru]], [[Motali]].'' These are all [[Khatri]] sections.

The sections of Khawajas from Pindi Bhattian were reported as follows:
''[[Sahgal]] and [[Wadhaun]].'' These are all [[Khatri]] sections.

And one section of Phaphra Sheikh's is reported from there:

''[[Phaphra]]''.

The Khawajas of [[Layyah]], [[Punjab (Pakistan)|Punjab]] have following Khatri sections:

''[[Kapur]], [[Puri]] and [[Tandan]] ''.&lt;ref&gt;Ibbetson, Denzil; Edward MacLagan and H.A. Rose. ''A Glossary of the Tribes and Castes of the Punjab and North-West Frontier Province'', vol. II, 1911, pp. 537-538.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Qanungoh Shaikh ==

{{Main|Qanungoh Shaikh}}

Qanungoh Shaikhs ({{lang-fa|''' قانونگوہ شيخ'''}}) belonged to all the districts of the [[Punjab region|Punjab]]. They have different lineages and represent families who were holding hereditary  office of  ‘’Qanungoh’’ (‘’Law readers’’)  during the Muslim period.

This designation was used in the Punjab and other provinces of India and Pakistan for hereditary registrar of landed property in a subdivision of a district.

== Siddiqui and Quraishi Shaikhs ==

The [[Siddiqui]] and [[Quraishi]] are also clans of Shaikh found in the Punjab.

==Kashmiri Shaikhs==
[[File:Iqbal.jpg|thumb|right|[[Muhammad Iqbal]], the national poet of Pakistan]]
Kashmiri Shaikh are another community living in different districts of the Punjab. They emigrated from [[Kashmir]] during 19th &amp; 20th century. [[Muhammad Iqbal|Allama Shaikh Muhammad Iqbal]] belonged to this group. Muhammad Iqbal grandfather Shaikh Rafiq migrated to [[Sialkot]] in early 19th century. It has been suggested that Kashmiri Shaikhs are descendants of [[Kashmiri Pandit]]s who converted to [[Islam]] and adopted this title. Shaikh are descended from the Brahmin tribes.

== Distinguished Sheikhs ==
* [[Allama Muhammad Iqbal]], National Poet of Pakistan, Poet of the East. A '' Sheikh'' from Sialk
* [[Abdul Hafeez Sheikh]], CEO of Bismillah Group and BNP.
* [[Mian Muhammad Mansha]], Chairman of “Nishat Group” - the biggest industrial and financial conglomerate of Pakistan.
* [[Wasim Sajjad]], Chairman of Senate and 2 time Acting President of Pakistan. A ''Qanungo Shaikh'' from Jalandhar.
* [[Najam Sethi]], Chief Editor of  Weekly &quot;''The Friday Times''&quot;.
*[[Aftab Ahmed Vohra]], Chief Executive of Vohra Group of Industries
*[[Amin Saigol]], Founder of House of Saigols.
*[[Khwaja Muhammad Sharif]], Chief Justice of Lahore High Court Punjab (2009).

== See also ==
* [[Shaikhs in South Asia]]
* [[Kashmiri Shaikh]]
* [[Khawaja Shaikh]]
* [[Qanungoh Shaikh]]
* [[Punjabi Saudagaran-e-Delhi]]
* [[Siddiqui]]
* [[Sindhi Shaikh]]
* [[Phaphra Sheikh]]
* [[Chinioti Shaikh]]
* [[Mian]]
* [[Khawaja]]
* [[Khatri]]

==External links==
* [http://www.shaikhsiddiqui.com/ Shaikh Siddiqui]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}
# [[Denzil Ibbetson]], [[Edward MacLagan]], [[H. A. Rose]], &quot; ''A Glossary of The Tribes &amp; Casts of The Punjab &amp; North West Frontier Province''&quot;, 1911, pp 502 Vol II
# Wendy Doniger, tr. &quot;''The Law of Manu''&quot;, (Penguin Books, 1991 ) Verses 43-44, Chapter 10.
# A.L. Basham &quot; ''The Wonder That Was India''&quot;, ( Sidgwick &amp; Jackson, 1967)
# D. Ibbetson, E.MacLagan, H.A. Rose, pp 58, Vol I
# Abu Fazal, &quot;''[[Ain-i-Akbari]]''&quot;, translated by H.Blocmann &amp; H.S. Jarrett, (Calcutta, 1873–94) 3 Vols., a gazetteer of the Mughal Empire compiled in 1590 AD.
# D. Ibbetson, E.MacLagan, H.A. Rose, pp 513–514 Vol II

{{Ethnic groups, tribes and clans of the Punjab}}

[[Category:Social groups of Pakistan]]
[[Category:Surnames]]
[[Category:Ethnic groups in Pakistan]]
[[Category:Punjabi tribes]]
[[Category:Shaikh clans]]
[[Category:Social groups of Punjab (Pakistan)]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
