<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3628683" ns="0" title="West Indies women&#039;s cricket team"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox women's national cricket team | country_name = [[West Indies]] | image_file =   | image_caption =   | current_captain = [[Stephanie Power]] | first_match = 7 May 1976 v [[Australian women's cricket team|Australia]] at [[Montego Bay]], [[Jamaica]] | wc_apps = 4 | wc_first = 1993 | wc_best = 5th, 2005 &amp; 2009 | test_matches = 11 | test_win_loss_record = 2/9 | odi_matches = 45 | odi_win_loss_record = 17/27 | asofdate = 19 September 2006}}

The '''West Indian women's cricket team''' is the team that represents the [[West Indies]] in international [[women's cricket]] matches.

==History==

===Test history===

:''See also: [[List of West Indian women's Test cricketers]]''

The first Test series played by the West Indies was at home to [[Australian women's cricket team|Australia]] in 1975-76, when both the three day matches were drawn. In 1976-77 the same team then played a six Test series away to [[Indian women's cricket team|India]]. They lost the fourth and then won the sixth Test by over an innings to level the series. The remaining games were drawn.

[[1979 English cricket season|1979]] then saw the Windies play their third Test series, this time away to [[English women's cricket team|England]]. However, they fared poorly, losing the first and third Tests and drawing the second to go down 2-0.

Finally, in 2003-04, after a 24 year wait, the West Indies resumed Test cricket with a one-off match away to [[Pakistani women's cricket team|Pakistan]], this time played over 4 days. The result was a draw.

===One-day international history===

:''See also: [[List of West Indian women's ODI cricketers]]''&lt;br&gt;

When the first World Cup was played in 1973, the West Indies did not compete as an individual unit. Instead a separate team represented Jamaica, and another side represented Trinidad and Tobago. Additionally, three West Indian players participated in an International XI side that also competed in the 1973 World Cup. None of the teams fared well, however, with the International XI finishing in fourth place out of seven with a record of won three, lost two and one no result; Trinidad and Tobago finishing fifth with two wins and four losses; and Jamaica finishing sixth with one win, four losses and one match abandoned.

The first one-day internationals (ODIs) played by a combined West Indian side were two games away to [[English women's cricket team|England]] during their 1979 tour. Three ODIs were planned, but the second ODI was washed out without a ball being bowled. In the first ODI, England won comfortably by eights wickets, and in the third ODI saw the West Indies level the series with a two wicket win.

1993 saw West Indian players compete in a World Cup for the second time, this time as part of a combined team. They finished seventh, with only Denmark and the Netherlands below them, after winning only two and losing five of their seven matches. Their next games were in the 1997-98 World Cup, where they finished in ninth place, above only Denmark and Pakistan. The only match they won was the 9th place play-off game against the Danes.

2002-03 saw the [[Sri Lankan women's cricket team]] tour the West Indies and play a six-match ODI series, which the Sri Lankan's won six-nil. The closest match was the fourth, where the Windies went down by only 9 runs. 2003 saw the Windies greatest cricketing success, when they finished second in the International Women's Cricket Council Trophy, after winning four and losing one of their five games. The Trophy was competed for by the weaker ODI sides - Ireland, Windies, the Netherlands, Pakistan, Scotland and Japan.

2003-04 saw the Windies play five ODIs in [[Indian women's cricket team|India]] followed by a seven ODI and one Test tour to [[Pakistani women's cricket team|Pakistan]]. All five games against India were lost comfortably. As expected, the tour to Pakistan was more successful and the ODI series was won five-two.

They finished fifth in the 2004-05 World Cup, ahead of Sri Lanka, South Africa and Ireland, but behind Australia, India, New Zealand and India. They won two and lost three games, with one no result and one abandoned match. After being eliminated from the World Cup, the team stayed on to play three ODIs against [[South African women's cricket team|South Africa]] and won the series two-nil.

===Tournament History===

====[[Women's Cricket World Cup]]====

*1973 to 1988: Did not participate
*1993: 6th place
*1997: 9th place
*2000: Did not participate
*2005: 5th place
*2009: 5th place

====[[ICC Women's World Twenty20]]====

*[[2009 ICC Women's World Twenty20|2009]]: 5th place
*[[2010 ICC Women's World Twenty20|2010]]: semi-finalists

====[[ICC Women's Cricket Challenge]]====

*[[2010 ICC Women's Cricket Challenge|2010]]: 1st place

==Current Team==
* 4. Shakera Selman
* 5. [[Deandra Dottin]]
* 6. [[Juliana Nero]]
* 7. [[Stefanie Taylor]]
* 9. Afy Fletcher
* 10. [[Debbie-Ann Lewis]]
* 11. [[Merissa Aguilleira]]
* 12. [[Kirbyina Alexander]]
* 14. Anisa Mohammed
* 15. Stacy-Ann King
* 17. Pearl Etienne
* 20. [[Pamela Lavine]]
* 23. [[Cordel Jack]]
* 31. [[Shanel Daley]]
* 3?. Britney Cooper
* Melisia Billingy
* Shemaine Campbelle
* Phernel Charles
* Maria David
* Keila Elliott
* Erva Giddings
* Geneille Greaves
* Tracey Miller
* Chedean Nation
* Gaitri Seetahal
* Amanda Samaroo
* Zaheeda Samdally
* Nicole Samuel
* [[Danielle Small]]
* Tremayne Smartt
* Charlene Taitt
* Joann Vansertima
* Vanessa Watts

==Records==

===Test cricket===

*Highest team total: 440 v [[Pakistani women's cricket team|Pakistan]], 15 March 2004 at [[National Stadium, Karachi|National Stadium]], [[Karachi]], [[Pakistan]]
*Highest individual innings: 118, [[Nadine George]] v [[Pakistani women's cricket team|Pakistan]], 15 March 2004 at [[National Stadium, Karachi|National Stadium]], [[Karachi]], [[Pakistan]]
*Best innings bowling: 5/48, [[Vivalyn Latty-Scott]] v [[Australian women's cricket team|Australia]], 7 May 1976 at [[Montego Bay]], [[Jamaica]]
*Best match bowling: 5/26, [[Peggy Fairweather]] v [[Indian women's cricket team|India]], 27 November 1976 at [[Jammu]], [[India]]

===ODI cricket===

*Highest team total: 229/5 v [[Danish women's cricket team|Denmark]], 20 December 1997 at [[Delhi]], [[India]]
*Highest individual innings: 108 not out, [[Stafanie Taylor]] v [[South African women's cricket team|South Africa]], 16 October 2009 at [[Paarl]], [[South Africa]]
*Best innings bowling: 5/36, [[Cherry-Ann Singh]] v [[Irish women's cricket team|Ireland]], 29 July 1993 at [[Dorking]], [[England]]

==See also==

*[[Women's cricket]]
*[[List of West Indian women's Test cricketers]]
*[[List of West Indian women's ODI cricketers]]
*[[West Indian cricket team|West Indian men's cricket team]]

==References==

*[http://www.cricketarchive.co.uk/Archive/Records/WestIndies/WTests/index.html Cricket Archive details of West Indies in women's Tests]
*[http://www.cricketarchive.co.uk/Archive/Records/WestIndies/WOdis/index.html Cricket Archive detaiils of West Indies in women's ODIs]

{{National women's cricket teams}}

[[Category:Cricket in the West Indies]]
[[Category:National sports teams of the West Indies|Cricket, women's]]
[[Category:National women's cricket teams]]
[[Category:West Indies in international cricket|Women]]

[[mr:वेस्ट ईंडीझ राष्ट्रीय महिला क्रिकेट संघ]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
