<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="363905" ns="0" title="Rik Mayall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comedian
|[http://www.nndb.com/people/809/000060629/rik_mayall.jpg Rick Mayall]
| name          = Rik Mayall
| caption       =
| birth_name    = Richard Michael Mayall
| birth_date    = {{Birth date and age|1958|03|7|df=y}}
| birth_place   = [[Harlow]], [[Essex]], [[England]]
| medium        = [[Television]], [[Film]], [[Stand up comedy|Stand-up]]
| nationality   = [[British nationality law|British]]
| active        = 1980–present
| genre         = [[Black comedy]], [[Physical comedy]] 
| influences    = [[Monty Python]], [[Derek and Clive]], [[Rowan Atkinson]]
| influenced    = [[David Walliams]], [[Matt Lucas]], [[Stewart Lee]]
| notable_work= ''Rick'' in [[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]&lt;br&gt;''Richie Richard'' in [[Bottom (TV series)|Bottom]]&lt;br&gt;[[The Comic Strip|The Comic Strip Presents...]]&lt;br&gt;''Alan B'stard'' in [[The New Statesman]]&lt;br&gt;''Richie Twat'' in [[Guest House Paradiso]]
| spouse        = Barbara Robbin (m. 1985-present, 3 children)
| module = {{Infobox comedian awards
  |child=yes
  | emmyawards   = '''[[Primetime Emmy Award for Outstanding Voice-Over Performance|Outstanding Voice-Over Performance]]'''&lt;br&gt;1997 ''The Willows in Winter''
 }}
}}
'''Richard Michael &quot;Rik&quot; Mayall''' (born 7 March 1958) is an English comedian, writer, and actor. He is known for his [[double act|comedy partnership]] with [[Adrian Edmondson|Ade Edmondson]], his over-the-top, energetic portrayal of characters, and as a pioneer of [[alternative comedy]] in the early 1980s. Such notability has led him to appear in [[sitcoms]] such as ''[[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]'', ''[[Blackadder]]'', ''[[The New Statesman]]'', and ''[[Bottom (TV series)|Bottom]]'' and even onto the big screen in [[comedy film]]s such as ''[[Drop Dead Fred]]'' and ''[[Guest House Paradiso]]''.

== Early life ==
Mayall, the second of four children, was born in [[Harlow]], [[Essex]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nndb.com/people/809/000060629/ NNDB biodata]&lt;/ref&gt; to John and Gillian Mayall. He has an older brother, Anthony, and two younger sisters, Libby and Kate.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.filmreference.com/film/96/Rik-Mayall.html Rik Mayall Biography in ''Film Reference'']&lt;/ref&gt; When he was only three years old, Mayall and his parents — who taught [[drama]] — moved to [[Droitwich Spa]], [[Worcestershire]], where he spent the rest of his childhood and performed in his parents' plays. After attending [[The King's School, Worcester]], Mayall studied drama at the [[University of Manchester]] in 1976, where he befriended his future comedy partner [[Adrian Edmondson]]. He also met [[Ben Elton]] and [[Lise Mayer]], with whom he later co-wrote ''[[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]''.

== Career ==

Edmondson and Mayall gained their reputation at [[The Comedy Store, London|The Comedy Store]], from 1980. The [[double act]], &quot;[[20th Century Coyote]]&quot;, became popular. Mayall also developed solo routines using characters such as [[Kevin Turvey]] and a pompous anarchist poet named Rick. This led to Edmondson and Mayall, along with Comedy Store [[Master of Ceremonies|compere]] [[Alexei Sayle]] and other upcoming comedians including [[Nigel Planer]], [[Peter Richardson (actor)|Peter Richardson]], [[French and Saunders]], [[Arnold Brown (comedian)|Arnold Brown]], and [[Pete Richens]], to set up their own comedy club called &quot;[[The Comic Strip]]&quot; in the Raymond Revue Bar, a strip club. Mayall's popularity led to a regular slot for Kevin Turvey on ''[[A Kick Up the Eighties]]'', first broadcast in 1981. He appeared as &quot;Rest Home&quot; Ricky in [[Richard O'Brien]]'s ''[[Shock Treatment]]'', sequel to ''[[The Rocky Horror Picture Show]]''. He played Dentonvale's resident attendant as the love interest to Nell Campbell's Nurse Ansalong.  

Mayall's television appearances as Kevin Turvey in 1977 along with Johnathan PP Seller warranted a [[mockumentary]] based on the character entitled ''Kevin Turvey — The Man Behind The Green Door'', broadcast in 1982. The previous year, he appeared in a bit role in ''[[An American Werewolf in London]]''. His stage partnership with Edmondson continued, often appearing together as &quot;[[The Dangerous Brothers]]&quot;, hapless daredevils whose hyper-violent antics foreshadowed their characters in ''[[Bottom (TV series)|Bottom]]''. Mayall also made a cameo appearance in the 1983 gothic horror movie, ''[[The Keep (film)|The Keep]]'' directed by [[Michael Mann (director)|Michael Mann]]. [[Channel 4]] offered the Comic Strip group six short films, which became ''[[The Comic Strip|The Comic Strip Presents...]]'', debuting on 2 November 1982. The series, which continued sporadically for many years, saw Mayall play a wide variety of roles. It was known for anti-establishment humour and for parodies such as ''[[Bad News|Bad News On Tour]]'', a spoof &quot;[[rockumentary]]&quot; starring Mayall, Richardson, Edmondson and Planer as a [[heavy metal music|heavy metal]] band.

At the time ''The Comic Strip Presents...'' was negotiated, the [[BBC]] took an interest in ''[[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]'', a sitcom written by Mayall and then-girlfriend [[Lise Mayer]], in the same [[anarchy|anarchic]] vein as ''Comic Strip''. Ben Elton joined the writers. The series was commissioned and first broadcast in 1982, shortly before ''Comic Strip''. Mayall played Rik, a pompous [[sociology]] student and [[Cliff Richard]] devotee. Despite the sitcom format, Mayall maintained his double-act with Edmondson, who starred as violent [[punk rock|punk]] Vyvyan. [[Nigel Planer]] (as hippie Neil) and [[Christopher Ryan]] (as &quot;Mike the cool person&quot;) also starred, with additional material written and performed by [[Alexei Sayle]]. The first series was successful and a second was commissioned in 1984. The show owed a comic debt to [[Spike Milligan]], but Milligan was disapproving of Mayall, and once wrote: &quot;Rik Mayall is putrid - absolutely vile. He thinks nose-picking is funny and farting and all that. He is the arsehole of British comedy.&quot; &lt;ref&gt; From a 2002 BBC Obituary of Spike Milligan, for which the author has been unable to find the original,  cited in No Such Thing as Society by Andy McSmith, Constable 2011, page 15 ISBN 978-1-84901-979-8 &lt;/ref&gt;


=== Becoming a household name ===
Mayall continued to work on ''The Comic Strip'' films. He returned to standup, starring on ''[[Saturday Live (UK TV series)|Saturday Live]]'' — a British version of the American ''[[Saturday Night Live]]'' — first broadcast in 1985. He and Edmondson had a regular section as &quot;[[The Dangerous Brothers]]&quot;, their earlier stage act. In 1985, Mayall debuted another comic creation. He had starred in the final episode of ''[[The Black Adder]]'' in 1983 as &quot;Mad Gerald&quot;. He returned to play [[Lord Flashheart]] in the ''[[Blackadder II]]''-episode entitled &quot;[[Bells (Blackadder)|Bells]]&quot;.  A descendant of this character, Squadron Commander Flashheart, was in the ''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'' episode &quot;Private Plane&quot;. A similar character, also played by Mayall, appeared in 2000's ''[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]'' as [[Robin Hood]]. 

In 1986, Mayall joined with [[Nigel Planer|Planer]], Edmondson and Elton to star in ''[[Filthy Rich &amp; Catflap]]'' as Richie Rich in what was billed as a follow-up to ''The Young Ones''. The idea of &quot;Filthy Rich and Catflap&quot; was in reaction to comments [[Jimmy Tarbuck]] made about the &quot;Young Ones&quot;.  The series primary focus was to highlight the &quot;has been&quot; status of light entertainment.  While Mayall received positive critical reviews, viewing figures were poor and the series was never repeated on the BBC. In later years, release on video, DVD and repeats on UK TV found a following. Mayall suggested the series did not last because he was uncomfortable acting in an Elton project, when they had been co-writers on ''The Young Ones''.&lt;ref&gt;
Mayall, interviewed for a ''[[Comedy Connections]]'' profile of ''The Young Ones''&lt;/ref&gt;  1987 saw Mayall co-star with Edmondson in the [[ITV]] sit-com ''[[Hardwicke House]]''. Due to adverse reaction of press and viewers, ITV withdrew the series after two episodes.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.ukonline.co.uk/sotcaa/sotcaa.html?/sotcaa/archive/hardwicke.html UK Online website]&lt;/ref&gt; The same year, Mayall had a number one hit in the [[UK Singles chart]]s when he and his co-stars from ''The Young Ones'' teamed with Cliff Richard to record &quot;[[Living Doll (song)|Living Doll]]&quot; for the inaugural ''[[Comic Relief]]'' campaign. Mayall played Rick one last time in the stage show and has supported the ''Comic Relief'' cause ever since. He appeared on the children's television series ''[[Jackanory]]''. His crazed portrayal of [[Roald Dahl]]'s ''[[George's Marvellous Medicine]]'' proved memorable.&lt;ref&gt;Acknowledged [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/tv_and_radio/4648357.stm here] on the BBC News website&lt;/ref&gt; However, the BBC received complaints &quot;with viewers claiming both story and presentation to be both dangerous and offensive.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Reported at [http://www.televisionheaven.co.uk/jackanory.htm Television Heaven website]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1987, Mayall played fictional [[Conservative Party (UK)|Conservative MP]] Alan Beresford B'Stard in the sitcom ''[[The New Statesman]]'' for [[Yorkshire Television]], written by [[Laurence Marks (British writer)|Laurence Marks]] and [[Maurice Gran]]. The character was a satire of [[Tory]] [[Member of Parliament|MP]]s in the United Kingdom in the 1980s and early 1990s. The programme ran for four series — incorporating two BBC specials — between 1987–1994 and was a success critically and in ratings. In a similar vein to his appearance on ''Jackanory'', in 1989, Mayall starred in a series of bit shows for ITV called ''[[Grim Tales]]'', in which he narrated [[Brothers Grimm|Grimm Brothers]] [[fairy tale]]s while puppets acted the stories. In the early 1990s Mayall starred in humorous adverts for [[Nintendo]] games and consoles. With money from the ads, he bought his house in London which he calls 'Nintendo Towers'. He lent his voice to the [[PlayStation]] and Windows PC video game ''[[Hogs of War]]''. In the early 1990s, he auditioned for Banzai, Zazu and Timon in'' [[The Lion King]]''. He was asked to audition by lyricist [[Tim Rice]]. The role of Zazu finally went to his Blackadder co-star Rowan Atkinson.

=== 1990s ===
[[File:bottom001.jpg|thumb|left|[[Adrian Edmondson]] (left) and Rik Mayall (right) as Eddie and Richie in ''Bottom'']]
In 1991, Edmondson and Mayall co-starred in the [[West End theatre|West End]] production of [[Samuel Beckett|Beckett's]] ''[[Waiting for Godot]]'' at the Queen's Theatre. Here they came up with the idea for ''[[Bottom (TV series)|Bottom]]'', which they said was a cruder cousin to ''Waiting for Godot''. ''Bottom'' was commissioned by the BBC and three series were shown between 1991–1995. Mayall starred as &quot;Richard 'Richie' Richard&quot; alongside Edmondson's
&quot;Eddie Elizabeth Hitler&quot;. The series featured [[slapstick]] violence taken to new extremes. The series gained a strong cult following. In 1993, following the second series, Mayall and Edmondson decided to take a stage show version of the series on a national tour. ''Bottom: Live'' was a commercial success, filling large venues. Four additional stage shows were embarked upon in 1995, 1997, 2001 and 2003, each to great success. The violent natures of these shows saw both Edmondson and Mayall ending up in hospital at various points. A film version, ''[[Guest House Paradiso]]'', was released in 1999. A fourth TV series was also written, but not commissioned by the BBC.

[[File:Dropdeadfred.jpg|230px|thumb|right|[[Phoebe Cates]] (left) and Mayall as Elizabeth and Fred in ''[[Drop Dead Fred]]''.]]
Mayall starred alongside [[Phoebe Cates]] in 1991's ''[[Drop Dead Fred]]'' as the eponymous character, a troublesome [[imaginary friend]] reappearing from a woman's childhood. He also appeared in ''[[Carry On Columbus]]'' (1992) with other alternative comedians. In 1991 he played Vladimir in [[Samuel Beckett]]'s ''[[Waiting for Godot]]'' at the [[Queen's Theatre]] in the [[West End theatre|West End]], alongside Edmondson (Estragon) and [[Christopher Ryan]] (Lucky). Mayall also provided the voice of the character Froglip, the leader of the [[goblins]], in the 1992 animated film adaption of the 1872 children's tale, ''[[The Princess and the Goblin]]'' by [[George MacDonald]]. In 1993, he appeared in ''Rik Mayall Presents'', three individual comedy dramas. Mayall's performances won a Best Comedy Performer award at that year's [[British Comedy Awards]], and a second series of three was broadcast in early 1995. He provided the voice for Little Sod in [[Simon Brett]]'s ''[[How to Be a Little Sod]]'', written in 1991 and adapted as 10 consecutive episodes broadcast on the BBC in 1995.

In 1995 Mayall co-starred in a production of the play ''[[Cell Mates (play)|Cell Mates]]'', alongside [[Stephen Fry]]. Not long into the run, Fry had a [[mental breakdown|nervous breakdown]] and fled to [[Belgium]], where he remained for several days, and the play closed.{{Citation needed|date=February 2011}} In 2007, Mayall said of the incident: &quot;You don't leave the trenches ... selfishness is one thing, being a cunt is another. I mustn't start that war again.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orangeneko.com/Rik/library/theatre111.htm Interview with Theatre.com 11 January 2007]&lt;/ref&gt; Edmondson poked fun at the event during their stage tours. In ''[[Bottom Live: The Big Number Two Tour]]'', after Mayall gave mocking gestures to the audience and insulted their town in a silly voice, Edmondson said &quot;Have you finished yet? It's just I'm beginning to understand why Stephen Fry fucked off.&quot; In ''[[Bottom Live 2003: Weapons Grade Y-Fronts Tour]]'', after Richie accidentally fondles Eddie, he replies &quot;I see why Stephen Fry left that play.&quot; Towards the end of ''Cell Mates'' Mayall revealed a replica gun — a prop from the play — to a passer-by in the street. He was cautioned over the incident. Mayall later conceded that this was &quot;incredibly stupid, even by my standards&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orangeneko.com/Rik/library/telegra8.htm Police Rebuke Rik Mayall for 'Stupid' Gun Prank]&lt;/ref&gt; Since 1999, Mayall was the voice of the black-headed seagull Kehaar in the first and the second season of the animated television series ''[[Watership Down]]''.

=== 2000s&amp;ndash;present ===
In 2000, Mayall appeared in the video production of ''[[Jesus Christ Superstar]]'' as [[Herod Antipas|King Herod]]. He joked in the &quot;Making of&quot; documentary, which was included on the [[DVD]] release, that &quot;the real reason why millions of people want to come and see this is because I'm in it!  Me and [[Jesus]]!&quot; In 2002, Mayall teamed up with Marks and Gran once more when he starred as Professor Adonis Cnut in the [[ITV]] sitcom, ''[[Believe Nothing]]''. However, the sitcom failed to repeat the success of ''The New Statesman'' and lasted only one series. Following 2003's ''Bottom: Live'' tour, ''Bottom 5: Weapons Grade Y-Fronts'', Mayall stated that he and Edmondson would return with another tour.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orangeneko.com/Rik/faq/tourbottom.htm The Rik Mayall FAQ]&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, however, Edmondson told ''[[Daily Mail|The Daily Mail]]'' that he no longer wished to work on ''Bottom''. This effectively dissolved their nearly 30-year partnership. Edmondson claimed they were &quot;too old&quot; to continue portraying the characters. Edmondson added that, since Mayall had recovered from his coma, he was slower on the uptake and it had become more difficult to work with him, as well as citing that due to taking medication, Mayall had been advised to stop drinking alcohol. However, Edmondson said that the pair remained very close friends.&lt;ref&gt;Article in ''The Daily Mail'''s &quot;Weekend&quot; supplement (2003)&lt;/ref&gt;

Mayall voiced Edwin in the BBC show ''[[Shoebox Zoo]]''. He released an 'in-character' semi-fictionalised [[autobiography]] in September 2005 entitled ''Bigger than Hitler, Better than Christ'' (ISBN 0-00-720727-1). At the same time, he starred in a new series for ITV, ''All About George''. Mayall reprised the role of Alan B'Stard in 2006 in the play ''The New Statesman 2006: Blair B'stard Project'', written by Marks and Gran. By this time B'Stard had left the floundering Conservatives and become a [[Labour Party (UK)|Labour MP]]. Following a successful two-month run in London's West End at The Trafalgar Studios in 2007, a heavily re-written version toured theatres nationwide, with Marks and Gran constantly updating the script to keep it topical. However, Mayall succumbed to chronic [[fatigue (medical)|fatigue]] and [[influenza|flu]] in May 2007, and withdrew from the show. Alan B'Stard was played by his understudy, Mike Sherman during his hiatus. 

Mayall was cast as the [[poltergeist]] Peeves in ''[[Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone (film)|Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone]]'', the first of the [[Harry Potter]] films in 2001.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.orangenko.com/Rik/library/iccroydon.htm &quot;Rik Mayall Acts Up&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; Comments by Mayall suggest material for the role was filmed and shown in cinemas but then never released to the public on any subsequent release for no apparent reason.  He tells the story of this hiring/firing on his second website blog for his 2008 film, ''[[Evil Calls: The Raven]]''.   For ''Evil Calls'', he shot his role as Winston the Butler in 2002, when the film was titled ''Alone in the Dark''. The film was not completed until 2008 and was released under its new 'Evil Calls' title to distance itself from the ''[[Alone in the Dark]]'' computer game movie.  He may appear in a possible sequel. Mayall provides the voice of the Andrex puppy in the UK TV commercials for Andrex toilet paper, and also has a voice part in the UK Domestos cleaning product adverts.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.houseoffear.co.uk/films/raven1/raven1.html House of Fear.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt; He performs the voice of King Arthur in the children's television cartoon series ''King Arthur's Disasters'', alongside [[Matt Lucas]] ([[Little Britain]]) who plays Merlin. Mayall also had a recurring role in the Channel Five remake of the lighthearted drama series, ''[[Minder (TV series)|Minder]]''.

In September 2009, Mayall played a supporting role in the British television program ''Midsomer Murders'', shown on [[ITV1]] (and made by [[Meridian Broadcasting]]) as 'David Roper', a recovering party animal and tenuous friend of the families in and around Chettham Park House. 

In April 2010, Motivation Records released&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.motivationrecords.co.uk Noble Englands Record Label].&lt;/ref&gt; Mayall's England Football anthem 'Noble England' for the [[2010 FIFA World Cup]] which he recorded with Coventry producer [http://www.daveloughran.com Dave Loughran].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.daveloughran.com The Producer of Riks Football Anthem]&lt;/ref&gt; On the track Mayall performs an adapted speech from Shakespeare's Henry V &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nobleengland.com Noble England — Riks Football Anthem]&lt;/ref&gt; In June 2010 the official BBC Match Of The Day compilation CD (2010 Edition) was released by Sony/Universal featuring Noble England - Track 18, CD2. 

In September 2010 ''Cutey And The Sofaguard'' was released as an audio book, narrated by Mayall. The book was written by Chris Wade and released by Wisdom Twins Books as a digital download. Mayall told Hound Dawg Magazine that he had the task of voicing 25 different characters. In this same month Mayall played the voice of Roy’s Dad in cult animation ''[[Dog Judo]]''. He recorded five episodes all of which exclusively streamed from http://www.dogjudo.com. 

In November 2010, Mayall provided narrative for five characters for CDs accompanying books from the publishing house [http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk Clickety Books]. The books are for children and aid speech and language development by bombarding the child with troublesome sound targets. 

Rik has so far recorded introductions and narratives for the titles:[http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk/shop/jake-the-achy-snake/c-005-jas/ Jake the Achy Snake], [http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk/shop/corky-the-squawky-hawk/c-002-csh/ Corky the Squawky Hawk], [http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk/shop/erica-the-picky-chicken/c-003-epc/ Erica the Picky Chicken], [http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk/shop/lucky-the-plucky-duck/c-004-lpd/ Lucky the Plucky Duck] and [http://www.clicketybooks.co.uk/shop/jacqueline-the-black-alpaca/c-001-jpa/ Jacqueline the Black Alpaca]. The books are written by Craig Green and illustrated by  Sarah-Leigh Wills. The recording and prouction was undertaken by Matt Bernard and Jay Auborn at the [http://www.deepbluesound.co.uk/studio/ Deep Blue Sound] studio in Plymouth, UK. 

On 5 March 2011, Mayall appeared on ''[[Let's Dance For Comic Relief]]'' in which he came on stage and attacked [[Adrian Edmondson|Ade Edmondson]] with a [[frying pan]] during his performance of ''[[The Dying Swan]]'' [[Ballet]]. Edmondson mentioned backstage that it was the first time in eight years they've done something like that together and claimed Mayall had left his head with a small bump.

In April 2011, Mayall again revived the character of Alan B'Stard to make an appearance in a satirical television advertisement for the [[No2AV]] campaign prior to the 2011 voting reform referendum in the UK. The character is shown being unfairly elected under the alternative vote system, then using his newly gained position of power to renege on his campaign promises. In his personal life, Rik Mayall does not support the alternative vote. In May of the same year Mayall became the eponymous 'Bombardier' in a TV advertising campaign for [[Bombardier Bitter]] in the UK, arguably reviving his [[Lord Flashheart]] persona from the UK TV series ''[[Blackadder]]''. &lt;ref&gt; [http://www.thedrum.co.uk/news/2011/05/13/21475-rik-mayall-stars-in-4m-campaign-for-bombardier-beer/] &lt;/ref&gt;

== Personal life ==
=== Family ===
Since 1985 Mayall has been married to [[Scottish people|Scottish]] make-up artist Barbara Robbin, with whom he has three children: Rosie (born 1986), Sidney (born 1988) and Bonnie (born 18 September 1995). The couple met in 1981 while filming ''A Kick Up The Eighties''. At the time, Mayall was in a long-term relationship with [[Lise Mayer]]. Mayall and Robbin embarked on a secret affair which lasted until 1985. Mayall and Robbin immediately eloped to [[Barbados]]. Mayer would later suffer a [[miscarriage]].&lt;ref name=&quot;laws&quot;&gt;Interview with Roz Laws, IC Birmingham, 29 December 2002&lt;/ref&gt; Mayall maintains that, despite a longstanding feud, he and Mayer are now friends.&lt;ref name=&quot;laws&quot;/&gt;

=== Quad bike accident ===
On 9 April 1998, Mayall was injured after crashing a [[All-terrain vehicle|quad bike]] near his home in [[Devon]].&lt;ref&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/77157.stm&lt;/ref&gt; Mayall's daughter Bonnie and her cousin had asked him to take them for a ride on the bike — a [[Christmas]] gift from his wife — but he refused due to rain, and went alone. Mayall's wife Barbara looked out the window and saw him lying on the ground with the bike, believing he was joking. He was in a [[coma]] for several days. Mayall was airlifted to [[Plymouth]]'s Derriford Hospital, with two [[hematoma]]s and a fractured skull. During the following 96 hours, Mayall was kept sedated to prevent movement which could cause pressure on his [[brain]]. His family was warned he could die or have [[brain damage]].&lt;ref&gt;Interviewed by Michael Owen, ''You'', 21 November 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

After five days doctors felt it safe to bring Mayall back to consciousness. In his 2005 spoof biography, Mayall claims he &quot;[[resurrection|rose from the dead]]&quot;. During Mayall's hospitalisation, the ''Comic Strip'' special ''Four Men in a Car'' was broadcast for the first time. The film involves Mayall's character being hit by a car.  Mayall believed he was held hostage at the hospital. After transfer to hospital in London, he took a taxi home but was taken back that day after being sedated. He was to take medication for a year to prevent epileptic [[seizure]]s. Mayall stopped taking it. He had epileptic seizures. During one, he bit through his tongue. He is now on medication for life. Mayall returned to work with [[voice acting|voice-over work]]. His first post-accident job was in the 1998 ''[[Jonathan Creek]]'' Christmas special, as DI Gideon Pryke. Mayall and Edmondson have joked about this event in stage versions of ''Bottom'', Edmondson quipping: 'If only I'd fixed those brakes properly'. The pair wrote the first draft of their feature film ''[[Guest House Paradiso]]'' while Mayall was hospitalised. They planned to co-direct but Edmondson took on the duties himself.

== Recognition ==
In the 2005 poll  ''The Comedian's Comedian'', Mayall was voted among the top 50 comedy performers of all time.

In 2008, Mayall was awarded an honorary Doctor of Letters (DLitt) from the [[University of Exeter]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.exeter.ac.uk/honorarygraduates/2009/prev_hongrads.shtml&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 2010 poll &quot;Top 100 Stand-Up Comedians&quot;, Mayall was placed 91.

== Filmography ==
*''[[An American Werewolf in London]]'' (1981)
*''[[Shock Treatment]]'' (1981)
*''[[The Young Ones (TV series)|The Young Ones]]'' (1982)
*''[[Filthy Rich &amp; Catflap]]'' (1986)
*''[[Blackadder II]]'' (1986)
*''[[Mr Jolly Lives Next Door]]'' (1987)
*''[[French &amp; Saunders: The Ingenue Years]]'' (1987)
*''[[Eat the Rich]]'' (1987)
*''[[The New Statesman]]'' (1987)
*''[[Blackadder Goes Forth]]'' (1989)
*''[[Drop Dead Fred]]'' (1991)
*''[[Bottom (TV series)|Bottom]]'' (1991)
*''[[Carry On Columbus]]'' (1992)
*''[[Midsomer Murders]]'' (episode &quot;The Creeper&quot;) (1997) 
*''[[The Canterville Ghost]]'' (1997)
*''[[Bring Me the Head of Mavis Davis]]'' (1997)
*''[[Johnathan Creek: Christmas Special]]'' (1998)
*''[[A Monkey's Tale]]'' (1999)
*''[[Guest House Paradiso]]'' (1999)
*''[[Blackadder: Back &amp; Forth]]'' (1999)
*''[[Escape to Watership Down]]'' (1999)
*''[[Journey to Watership Down]]'' (1999)
*''[[Winter on Watership Down]]'' (1999)
*''[[Jesus Christ Superstar: 2000]]'' (2000)
*''[[Merlin: The Return]]'' (2000)
*''[[Chilly Dogs]]'' (2001)
*''[[Kevin of the North]]'' (2001)
*''[[Believe Nothing]]'' (2002)
*''[[Oh Marbella!]]'' (2003)
*''[[Chaos &amp; Cadavers]]'' (2003) 
*''[[Churchill: The Hollywood Years]]'' (2004)
*''[[Valiant (2005 film)|Valiant]]'' (2005)
*''[[Just For the Record]]'' (2010)
*''[[Cutey and the Sofaguard]]'' (2010)
*''[[Ted (film)|Ted]]'' (2012)

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{wikiquote}}
* {{imdb name|562201}}
* {{Screenonline name|476762}}
* [http://www.theatre.com/story/id/3005429/ Interview with Rik Mayall on Theatre.com]
* (http://www.scribd.com/doc/37736644/Hound-Dawg-Issue-10-RIK-MAYALL-INTERVIEW)

{{The Comic Strip}}
{{Bottom (TV Series)}}
{{EmmyAward VoiceOver 1990-2000}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] --&gt;
| NAME              = Mayall, Rik
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 7 March 1958
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = [[Harlow]], [[Essex]], England
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Mayall, Rik}}
[[Category:1958 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Alumni of the Victoria University of Manchester]]
[[Category:English comedians]]
[[Category:English film actors]]
[[Category:English television actors]]
[[Category:English voice actors]]
[[Category:Old Vigornians]]
[[Category:People from Droitwich Spa]]
[[Category:People from Harlow]]
[[Category:People with epilepsy]]
[[Category:The Comic Strip]]

[[ca:Rik Mayall]]
[[es:Rik Mayall]]
[[fr:Rik Mayall]]
[[hr:Rik Mayall]]
[[nl:Rik Mayall]]
[[no:Rik Mayall]]
[[pt:Rik Mayall]]
[[fi:Rik Mayall]]
[[sv:Rik Mayall]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
