<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="366243" ns="0" title="Poser"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{For|the [[pejorative]] for a person who inauthentically adopts a certain subculture|poseur}}
{{Multiple issues|primarysources=June 2007|COI=September 2008|notability=October 2010|rewrite=October 2010}}
{{Infobox software
|name = Poser
|screenshot = &lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Poser6ui.JPG|250px]] --&gt;
|caption = User interface of Poser 6
|developer = [[Smith Micro Software]]
|latest_release_version = Pro 2012
|latest_release_date = September 2011
|operating_system = [[Mac OS X]], [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]]
|genre = [[3D computer graphics]]
|license = [[Proprietary software|Proprietary]]
|website = [http://my.smithmicro.com/platform_detect/graphics.html Poser Homepage]
}}

'''Poser''' is a [[3D computer graphics|3D]] CGI [[Rendering (computer graphics)|rendering]] and [[Computer animation|animation]] software program optimized for models that depict the human figure in three-dimensional form, mostly used to pose and animate the figures in a similar way as a mannequin. The program has gained popularity due to allowing beginners to produce basic animations and digital images, and the extensive availability of third-party digital models.

== Overview ==

&lt;!--  Commented out: [[Image:Juggler.jpg|thumb|right|&quot;Dharma Juggler&quot;, by [[Berkus|Gunther Berkus]], 1997. Early Poser 1 / [[Bryce (software)|Bryce]] composite image. The original Poser wireframe image has been enhanced using [[Adobe Photoshop]].]] --&gt;
Poser is a [[3D computer graphics|3D]] rendering software package for the posing, animating and rendering of 3D polymesh human and animal figures. Akin to a virtual photography studio, Poser allows the user to load figures, props, lighting and cameras for still and animated renderings.

Natively using a subset of the [[Alias Systems Corporation|Alias]] object ([[Wavefront .obj file|OBJ]]) file format and a text-based markup for content files, Poser comes with a basic library of human, animal, robotic, and cartoon figures. The package also includes poses, hair pieces, props, textures, hand gestures and facial expressions. As Poser itself does not allow for original modeling of objects, a large community market of merchants and artists creating, selling and marketing third-party Poser content emerged, but these new models are usually crafted in [[Autodesk Maya|Maya]] or [[Autodesk 3ds Max|3DS Max]].

Poser is available in English, Japanese, German and French for both [[Microsoft Windows|Windows]] and [[Apple Macintosh|Macintosh]] platforms. However, after a series of owner changes, the program has become a bit outdated and its main interface lacks many features present in the newest 3D programs. Poser can re-modelate already-existing figures, almost as if you were working with clay, which allows you to create completely new characters, but always using a previously existing one as a basis, since its modeling tools and capabilities cannot be used to create new figures from scratch. For this same reason, clothes and props can be retooled if necessary, but they must be created in a different program and then imported into Poser.

Most Poser figures can be used with [[DAZ Studio]], which is designed to be compatible with the changing Poser file formats. Compatibility also exists with [[Carrara (software)|Carrara]], [[Bryce (software)|Bryce]] (via DAZ Studio), [[Shade 3D|Shade]] and [[E-on Vue|Vue]]. Shade and Vue use [[PoserFusion]], a file hosting system.

== Features ==
Poser comes with a host of features, such as the inclusion of &quot;Primitive&quot; zygotes; spheres, cubes and other shapes at both low and high resolution. As with Poser 5.0, it is compatible with [[3ds Max]], [[LightWave]] and [[Maya (software)|Maya]], which enables Poser version 6.0 and higher to render more than simply people.  As a result of its huge third-party community, many models are available, such as spaceships, aliens, weapons, scenes, buildings,  and other such props.{{Citation needed|date=March 2010}}

== Usage ==
Poser is a popular tool for home artists creating original images featuring human figures. They use '''Poser''' for both human rendering &quot;[[pin-up]]s&quot; and [[comics]].  ''Poser'' has limited animation capability.  However, Poser animation can be seen in industry applications, such as the animated instructions for checkout automated machines in [[Albertson city]]`s, [[Save-On store]]s and [[Wal-Mart]], and at least one full-length [[Star Trek]] fan-film, ''Star Trek: Aurora''.&lt;ref&gt;www.auroratrek.com&lt;/ref&gt; Poser characters and animations were used for early computer games from buddies game creators (&quot;Desert Rifle&quot; games and &quot;Cake shop&quot; from Qi and ELEFUN(TM) game developers).{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}  Several [[Poser figures|Poser characters]] and ''''several animated actions'''' have been used on different Discovery channel documentaries to graphically render human body working, without intrusion.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}} [[Infography|Humanoid]]s printed in several science and technology magazines around the US are often Poser rendered and postworked models.{{Citation needed|date=July 2010}}

== Library ==
The Poser package comes with many already-installed features that do not have to be purchased at an online store. These are stored in the &quot;Library.&quot; The Library includes:
*Humanoids, which contains people characters and [[human]]
*[[animal life|animal]]s, [[cartoon|marvel character BatBoy]], [[dinosaur]], [[insect|bug life]]s {{Citation needed |date=July 2011}}
*[[wildlife|wildlife surroundings]], including [[soja]]{{Citation needed |date=July 2011}}
*plenty of [[animation]]s tool to work on the characters, include ''built-in actions'' for run and duck.
*Posery and [[countenance]] for almost every figure, from sleeping, picking up, fighting and fly.
*A Mien of anatomy Library, contain any expression imaginable, or close to it.
*Anatomy Hair Library, which has many types of [[hairstyle]]s to assign to character.
*''''[[Props]]'''', which contains objects like [[coat]]s, ''clothes'', ''skirts'', ''trousers'', ''hats'', ''make-up''s, ''shadow'', ''skin colour''ing, ''scenery elements'', ''plenty of wardrobes'' and [[chair]]s.
*Illuminiscence props, to enlight any surrounding;
*Lights Library, contain many objects for light in scenery;
*Cameras, ''[[camera]] angles'', and [[3D vieports]]

===Family of characters===
{|cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;
|-
|Millennium Figures (Generation 4)
|Primarily realistic human
|DAZ 3D
|&lt;u&gt;'''Core Figures'''&lt;/u&gt;: [[Victoria (3D figure)|Victoria]] 4, Michael 4, Kids 4; &lt;u&gt;'''Morphs of Victoria 4'''&lt;/u&gt;: Aiko 4, Girl 4, She Freak 4, Stephanie 4 (Elite Body Shape), [[Reby Sky]]; &lt;u&gt;'''Morphs of Michael 4'''&lt;/u&gt;: Hiro 4, Freak 4. ''These morphs are injectable.  This makes it easier to make clothing usable across multiple figures. Reported intention to have been a David 4, but was left unfulfilled. The Kids 4 figure represents a pre-teen child and it has been stated that no specific teenage figure is under development, with the adult figures meant to be morphable into teens.''
|DAZ 3D
|-
|Millennium Figures (Generation 3)
|Primarily realistic human
|DAZ 3D
|[[Victoria (3D figure)|Victoria]] 3, Michael 3, Aiko 3, Hiro 3, Stephanie Petite 3, David 3, the Girl, The FREAK, She Freak 2, Millennium Kids - Young Teens (aka Luke &amp; Laura), Millennium Kids- Preschoolers (aka Matt &amp; Maddie), Millenium Baby 3, Troll. '''The Girl', a stylized female figure, was developed by Kim Goossens in conjunction with Daz, but is marketed as and technologically indistinguishable from the other third generation Millennium figures.''
|DAZ 3D
|-
|Millennium Figures (Generation 2)
|Primarily realistic human
|DAZ 3D
|[[Victoria (3D figure)|Victoria]] 2, Michael 2, Aiko, Stephanie, Millennium Girls, Millennium Boys, Millennium Baby. ''These Victoria and Michael figures keep the mesh shapes of Generation 1, but add morphs and are an unusual case of some add-on compatibility being maintained across generations.''
|DAZ 3D
|-
|Millennium Figures (Generation 1)
|Realistic human
|DAZ 3D
|[[Victoria (3D figure)|Victoria]], Michael. ''Victoria 1 was originally released as 'The Millennium Woman', but common colloquial shortening to &quot;Millie&quot; led to DAZ 3D renaming her as Victoria.''
|DAZ 3D
|}

== Program history ==
Poser was created by artist and programmer [[Larry Weinberg (computer animator)|Larry Weinberg]], as a software replacement for artist's mannequins. Versions 1.0 and 2.0 were published by Fractal Design; in 1997, Fractal Design was acquired by [[MetaCreations]], and Poser's interface was redesigned by MetaCreations' [[Phil Clevenger]] for release as Poser 3 in 1998. This interface has remained as the basis for all subsequent versions. In 1999, MetaCreations sold Poser to egi.sys AG, which established the subsidiary ''Curious Labs'', with Larry Weinberg as CEO, to handle Poser development and publication. Curious Labs and Poser were sold to the publisher [[e frontier|e-frontier]], in 2003. On 15 November 2007, [[Smith Micro Software]] announced the purchase of Poser, [[Anime Studio]] and [[Manga Studio]] from e-frontier.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| url = http://www.smithmicro.com/default.tpl?group=news_full&amp;id1=414&amp;id2=13
| title = Smith Micro Software press release|publisher=[[Smith Micro Software]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early versions of Poser were bundled with fully clothed humanoid figures specifically designed for the then-current version of Poser. Next, add-on packages of human figures were sold by the manufacturer of Poser. Soon, third party companies began creating figures which work with Poser. As clothing became separate from the humanoid figure, collections of 3D garments were created for specific models which conform to the shape and pose of the Poser figure. 'Poses' for figures were packaged and sold by the software vendor and by third parties. 'Morphs' allowing customization of body or face shape or other features are also for sale. Different skin textures, frequently combined with settings for morph technology, are marketed to allow one base model to be customized into many different 'characters'; similar 'texture' packages allow one garment to take on many different appearances, an animal to represent different breeds of the same species, or a vehicle to show many different colour schemes.

Each major release of Poser has come with a new generation of figures for use with the tool, however separate figures rapidly became available as the content market developed. Notably [[Zygote Media Group|Zygote]] (later [[DAZ 3D]]) made a Poser model of a young woman, higher-resolution than Posette, and called her &quot;the Millennium Girl&quot;. Poser users often colloquially shortened this name to &quot;[[Millie]]&quot;. Zygote, disliking this name, officially named her Victoria, which is often colloquially shortened to Vicky. Victoria then became the initial member of a large family of figures which has developed across four generations of technology. Following their merger with Gizmoz in late 2009, DAZ 3D released all of their poser figures (except the original Millennium Man/Millennium Woman) as free downloads.
{{Cleanup-laundry|date=October 2010}}
{| cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; border=&quot;1&quot; bgcolor=&quot;white&quot;
|-
! Version
! Release date
! Publisher
! Improvements / Notes
|-
| 1.0
| 1995
| [[Fractal Design]]
|
* First release
|-
| 2.0
| 1996
| Fractal Design
|
* Ability to add props
* Animation
* High resolution models{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}
|-
| 3.0
| 1998
| [[MetaCreations|MetaCreations developer]]
|
* New user interface
* Facial posing and animation{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}
* Human figures with jointed fingers.{{citation needed|date=July 2011}}
|-
| 4.0
| 1999
| MetaCreations
|
* Natural-media sketch renderer
* Figure sculpting via deformers
* Transparent mode for materials
* Conforming Clothes
* Transparency (which lead up to TransHair that increased the quality of hair sold today)
|-
| 4.0.3
| September 1999
| [[Curious Labs]]
|
* Markup path names made to use relative paths
* Currently sold as entry level ''Poser Artist''
|-
| Pro Pack
| February 2000
| Curious Labs
|
* Add on pack for Poser 4
* Implementation of [[Python (programming language)|Python]] scripting,
* Custom figure rigging
* Ability to host Poser scenes in [[3D Studio Max|3ds max]], [[Lightwave|Lightwave 3d]], and [[Cinema 4D]].
* No longer available
|-
| 5.0
| 2003
| Curious Labs
|
* FireFly [[Reyes rendering|Reyes]]/[[Ray tracing (graphics)|ray tracing]] renderer
* Dynamic hair and cloth
* Collision detection
|-
| 6.0
| March 2005
| Curious Labs ; e-frontier
|
* [[OpenGL]] Hardware acceleration
* Image-based lighting, Ambient Occlusion
* Cartoon outline rendering effects
* Inclusion of &quot;Primitives&quot; Zygote Props
* Binary Morphs (allows you to load the morphs for a characters in a separate file linked to Cr2 resulting in faster load time in Poser)
* Inclusion of male and female genitalia
|-
| 7.0
| December 2006
| [[e frontier|e-frontier]]
|
* Simon and Sydney (new AdultG2 male and female figures)
* [[Wildlife]] including [[eagle]] and [[wolf]]
* Updates to Ben and Kate the Poser Child figures with new morphs, textures and rigging
* New motion capture data, light sets, poses, and materials
* Talk Designer for lip-sync animation
* Multiple Undo/Redo
* [[Thread (computer science)|Multithreaded]] rendering
* [[High dynamic range imaging]]
* Brush morphing
* Animation Layers
* Universal Poses for bipedal figures, with automatic conversion of Poser 1-6 poses
* Streamlined access to Runtime libraries
* [[Universal Binary]]
|-
| Poser Pro
| May 2008
| [[Smith Micro Software]]
|
*Poser Pro was released adding [[COLLADA]] support and plug in support for Cinema C4d and Maya.
|-
| Poser 8
| August 4, 2009
| [[Smith Micro Software]]
|
* 8 new characters
* New [[User Interface]]
* New Content Management System
* Cross body morph tool
* [[Global illumination]]
* Improved [[OpenGL]] performance
* Tone Mapping and exposure control
* Normal Mapping
* Wardrobe Wizard
* Performance optimisations
* [[wxPython]] support
|
|-
| Poser Pro 2010
| March 10, 2010
| [[Smith Micro Software]]
|
*Enhanced User Interface
** 8 new human figures with advanced rigging
** Full set of legacy figures
** Over 2.5 GB included content
** Keyword and online content search
** Parameter change indicator
** Joint strength indicator
** Recent render palette
** StuffIt Connect image export
** Facebook image export

*Professional Art and Animation Tools
** Full body part morph import
** Auto-conform drag and drop
** Conform with scaling
** Updated PoserFusion Hosting plug-ins
** Dynamic cloth and strand based hair
** Improved OpenGL real-time scene preview
** Face Room
** WalkDesigner and TalkDesigner
** Dependent Parameters Tool
** Improved joint rigging system
** Cross Body Part Morph Tool
** Wardrobe Wizard Tool
** wxPython support

*Refined Lighting and Rendering Tools
** HDRI Export
** Gamma correction for linear rendering
** Normal mapping
** PSD layer rendering
** Network rendering
** 64 bit render engine
** Indirect Lighting for Global Illumination
** Physically correct light falloff
** Tone mapping and exposure
|}

== See also ==
*[[MakeHuman]]
*[[Avimator]]
*[[Renderosity]]
*[[Digital art]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{wiktionary|poser}}
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
&lt;!--| DO NOT ADD MORE LINKS TO THIS ARTICLE. WIKIPEDIA IS NOT A COLLECTION OF |--&gt;
&lt;!--| LINKS. If you think that your link might be useful, do not add it here, |--&gt;
&lt;!--| but put it on this article's discussion page first or submit your link  |--&gt;
&lt;!--| to the appropriate category at the Open Directory Project (www.dmoz.org)|--&gt;
&lt;!--| and link back to that category using the {{dmoz}} template.             |--&gt;
&lt;!--|                                                                         |--&gt;
&lt;!--|           Links that have not been verified WILL BE DELETED.            |--&gt;
&lt;!--|  See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details    |--&gt;
&lt;!--===========================({{NoMoreLinks}})===============================--&gt;
*[http://poser.smithmicro.com Poser Official Site]
* {{dmoz|Computers/Software/Graphics/3D/Animation_and_Design_Tools/Poser|Poser}}

&lt;!-- no additional external links below this line --&gt;

{{3D software}}

{{Commons category|Poser}}

[[Category:3D graphics software]]
[[Category:Animation software]]
[[Category:Mac OS software]]
[[Category:Mac OS X software]]
[[Category:Windows software]]
[[Category:Anatomical simulation]]

[[de:Poser (Software)]]
[[fr:Poser]]
[[it:Poser (software)]]
[[ja:Poser]]
[[sv:Poser]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
