<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="36623" ns="0" title="George Marshall"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Other people|George Marshall}}
{{Infobox US cabinet official
|honorific-prefix = &lt;small&gt;[[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
|name=George Catlett Marshall
|honorific-suffix=
|image=General George C. Marshall, official military photo, 1946.JPEG
|imagesize=250px
|order1=50th
|title1=[[United States Secretary of State]]
|term_start1=January 21, 1947
|term_end1=January 20, 1949
|president1=[[Harry S. Truman]]
|predecessor1=[[James F. Byrnes]]
|successor1=[[Dean Acheson]]
|order2=3rd
|title2=[[United States Secretary of Defense]]
|term_start2=September 21, 1950
|term_end2=September 12, 1951
|president2=[[Harry S. Truman]]
|predecessor2=[[Louis A. Johnson]]
|successor2=[[Robert A. Lovett]]
|order3=15th
|title3=[[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|United States Army Chief of Staff]]
|term_start3=September 1, 1939
|term_end3=November 18, 1945
|preceded3=[[Malin Craig]]
|succeeded3=[[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]
|birth_date={{Birth date|1880|12|31|mf=y}}
|birth_place=[[Uniontown, Pennsylvania|Uniontown]], Pennsylvania
|death_date={{death date and age|1959|10|16|1880|12|31|mf=y}}
|death_place=Washington, D.C.
|signature=George C Marshall Signature.svg
|party=[[Nonpartisan]]&lt;ref&gt;Marshall Papers Pentagon Office Selected Correspondence Box 69 Folder 18 George C. Marshall Foundation http://www.marshallfoundation.org&lt;/ref&gt;
|religion=[[Episcopal Church in the United States of America|Episcopal]]&lt;ref name=e&gt;[http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/gcm.htm George Catlett Marshall,  General of the Army]&lt;/ref&gt;
|spouse=Katherine Boyce Tupper&lt;br/&gt;Elizabeth Carter Cole 
|alma_mater=[[Virginia Military Institute]]
|profession=Soldier&lt;br/&gt;[[Statesman]]
|allegiance=[[United States of America]]
|branch=[[United States Army]]
|serviceyears=1902–1945 also through to 1959 (General of the Army regulations)
|rank=[[File:US-O11 insignia.svg|35px]] [[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]]
|commands=[[File:Flag US Army Chief of Staff.svg|35px]] [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]]
|battles=[[Philippine–American War]]&lt;br/&gt;World War I
*[[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
*[[Meuse-Argonne Offensive]]
World War II
|awards=[[Distinguished Service Medal (Army)|Distinguished Service Medal]] (2)&lt;br/&gt;[[Silver Star]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Nobel Peace Prize]]
}}
'''George Catlett Marshall''' (December 31, 1880 – October 16, 1959) was an American [[Military of the United States|military]] leader, [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Chief of Staff of the Army]], [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]], and the third [[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]].  Once noted as the &quot;organizer of victory&quot; by [[Winston Churchill]] for his leadership of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] victory in World War II,&lt;ref name=a&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/kbank/profiles/marshall/|title=George Catlett Marshall, U.S. Army Chief of Staff, Secretary of State|publisher=CNN|accessdate=2007-12-12 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20071113061529/http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/kbank/profiles/marshall/ &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-11-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Marshall served as the United States Army Chief of Staff during the war and as the chief military adviser to [[President of the United States|President]] [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]. As Secretary of State, his name was given to the [[Marshall Plan]], for which he was awarded the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 1953.&lt;ref name=b&gt;{{cite book|last=W. Del Testa|first=David|coauthors=Florence Lemoine and John Strickland|year=2001|title=Government Leaders, Military Rulers, and Political Activists|pages=120}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life==
George Cattlet Marshall was born into a middle-class family in [[Uniontown, Pennsylvania]], the son of George C. Marshall, Sr. and Laura Bradford Marshall.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/about/timeline/childhood.html George Marshall Childhood]&lt;/ref&gt; Marshall was a scion of an old Virginia family, as well as a distant relative of former [[Chief Justice of the United States|Chief Justice]] [[John Marshall]]. Marshall graduated from the [[Virginia Military Institute]] (VMI),&lt;ref name=c&gt;{{cite book|last=Uldrich|first=Jack|year=2005|title=Soldier, Statesman, Peacemaker: Leadership Lessons From George C. Marshall|pages=14–15}}&lt;/ref&gt; where he was initiated into the [[Kappa Alpha Order]], in 1901.

==World War I==
Following graduation from VMI, Marshall was commissioned a Second Lieutenant in the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]].  Until World War I, he was posted to various positions in the US and the [[Philippines]] and was trained in modern warfare.  During the war, he had roles as a planner of both training and operations.  He went to France in mid-1917 as the director of training and planning for the [[U.S. 1st Infantry Division|1st Infantry Division]]. In mid-1918, he was promoted to [[American Expeditionary Forces]] headquarters, where he worked closely with his mentor General [[John J. Pershing]] and was a key planner of American operations. He was instrumental in the design and coordination of the [[Meuse-Argonne offensive]], which contributed to the defeat of the [[German Army]] on the Western Front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Lengel|first=Edward G.|title=To Conquer Hell.|year=2008|publisher=Henry Holt|location=New York|isbn=0805079319.}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:Col George C Marshall.jpg|left|thumb|Colonel Marshall in France during or just after World War I.]]

==Between World War I and II==
{{Ref improve section|date=March 2008}}In 1919, he became an [[aide-de-camp]] to General [[John J. Pershing]]. Between 1920 and 1924, while Pershing was Army Chief of Staff, Marshall worked in a number of positions in the US Army, focusing on training and teaching modern, mechanized warfare. Between World Wars I and II, he was a key planner and writer in the [[United States Department of War|War Department]], commanded the [[15th Infantry Regiment (United States)]] for three years in China, and taught at the [[United States Army War College|Army War College]]. From June 1932 to June 1933 he was the Commanding Officer at Fort Screven, Savannah Beach, Georgia, now named [[Tybee Island]]. In 1934, Col. Marshall put [[Edwin F. Harding]] in charge of the Infantry School's publications, and Harding became editor&lt;ref name=&quot;campbell&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last= Campbell |first=James |title=The Ghost Mountain Boys: Their Epic March and the Terrifying Battle for New Guinea—The Forgotten War of the South Pacific |publisher=Three Rivers Press|date=September 30, 2008|pages=400 |isbn=978-0307335975}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|41}} of ''Infantry in Battle'', a book that codified the lessons of World War I. ''Infantry in Battle'' is still used as an officer's training manual in the Infantry Officer's Course and was the training manual for most of the infantry officers and leaders of World War II.
Marshall was promoted to [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]] in October 1936.  He commanded the [[Vancouver Barracks]] in [[Vancouver, Washington|Vancouver]], Washington from 1936–1938. Nominated by President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt|Franklin Roosevelt]] to be [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]], Marshall was promoted to [[General (United States)|General]] and sworn in on September 1, 1939, the day German forces invaded Poland, which began World War II.  He would hold this post until the end of the war in 1945.

==World War II==
As Chief of Staff, Marshall organized the largest military expansion in U.S. history, inheriting an outmoded, poorly-equipped army of 189,000 men and, partly drawing from his experience teaching and developing techniques of modern warfare as an instructor at the Army War College, coordinated the large-scale expansion and modernization of the U.S. Army.  Though he had never actually led troops in combat, Marshall was a skilled organizer with a talent for inspiring other officers.&lt;ref&gt;Bland, Larry I., ''George C. Marshall and the Education of Army Leaders'', Military Review 68 (October 1988) 27–51,  [[Fort Leavenworth|Ft. Leavenworth]], Kansas&lt;/ref&gt;  Many of the American generals who were given top commands during the war were either picked or recommended by Marshall, including [[Dwight Eisenhower]], [[Lloyd Fredendall]], [[Leslie McNair]], [[Mark Wayne Clark]] and [[Omar Bradley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Ossad, Steven L., ''Command Failures: Lessons Learned from Lloyd R. Fredendall'', Army Magazine, March 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

===Expands military force forty fold===

Faced with the necessity of turning an army of former civilians into a force of over eight million soldiers by 1942 (a fortyfold increase within three years), Marshall directed General Leslie McNair to focus efforts on rapidly producing large numbers of soldiers.  With the exception of airborne forces, Marshall approved McNair's concept of an abbreviated training schedule for men entering Army land forces training, particularly in regards to basic infantry skills, weapons proficiency, and combat tactics.&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Citizen Soldiers: The U.S. Army from the Normandy Beaches to the Bulge to the Surrender of Germany June 7, 1944 – May 7, 1945'', New York: [[Simon &amp; Schuster]] (1997), pp. 271–284&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keast, William R. (Maj), ''Provision of Enlisted Replacements'', Army Ground Forces Study No. 7, Washington, D.C.: Historical Section – Headquarters Army Ground Forces, 314.7(1 Sept 1946)GNHIS September 1, 1945&lt;/ref&gt;  At the time, most U.S. commanders at lower levels had little or no combat experience of any kind; without the input of experienced British or Allied combat officers on the nature of modern warfare and enemy tactics, many of them resorted to formulaic training methods emphasizing static defense and orderly large-scale advances by motorized convoys over improved roads.&lt;ref&gt;George, John B. (Lt. Col), ''Shots Fired In Anger'', NRA Press (1981), ISBN 0-935998-42-X, pp. 13–21&lt;/ref&gt;  In consequence, Army forces deploying to Africa suffered serious initial reverses when encountering German armored combat units in Africa at [[Kasserine Pass]] and other major battles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Keast, William R. (Maj), ''Provision of Enlisted Replacements''&lt;/ref&gt;  Even as late as 1944, U.S. soldiers undergoing stateside training in preparation for deployment against German forces in Europe were not being trained in combat procedures and tactics currently being employed there.&lt;ref&gt;Hanford, William B., ''A Dangerous Assignment'', Stackpole Books, ISBN 978-0-8117-3485-1, p. viii&lt;/ref&gt;

===Replacement system criticized===

Originally, Marshall had planned a 200-division Army with a system of unit rotation such as practiced by the British and other Allies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Article&quot;&gt;Vandergriff, Donald E., ''Seven Wars and a Century Later, a Failed System'', [http://www.military.com/NewContent/0,13190,Vandergriff_091203,00.html Article]&lt;/ref&gt;  By mid-1943, however, after pressure from government and business leaders to preserve manpower for industry and agriculture, he had abandoned this plan in favor of a 90-division Army using individual replacements sent via a circuitous process from training to divisions in combat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Article&quot;/&gt;  The individual replacement system (IRS) devised by Marshall and implemented by McNair greatly exacerbated problems with [[unit cohesion]] and effective transfer of combat experience to newly-trained soldiers and officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ambrose, Stephen pp. 277-284&quot;&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Citizen Soldiers'', pp. 277–284&lt;/ref&gt; In Europe, where there were few pauses in combat with German forces, the individual replacement system had broken down completely by late 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Henry, Mark R., ''The US Army in World War II: Northwest Europe'', [[Osprey Publishing]] (2001), ISBN 1-84176-086-2, 9781841760865, pp. 12–14&lt;/ref&gt;  Hastily-trained replacements or service personnel re-assigned as infantry were given six weeks' refresher training and thrown into battle with Army divisions locked in front-line combat.  
The new men were often not even proficient in the use of their own rifles or weapons systems, and once in combat, could not receive enough practical instruction from veterans before being killed or wounded, usually within the first three or four days.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Henry, Mark R. 2001 pp. 12-14&quot;&gt;Henry, Mark R., ''The US Army in World War II: Northwest Europe'', Osprey Publishing (2001), ISBN 1-84176-086-2, 9781841760865, pp. 12–14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Citizen Soldiers'', pp. 271–284&lt;/ref&gt;  Under such conditions, many replacements suffered a crippling loss of morale, while veteran soldiers were kept in line units until they were killed, wounded, or incapacitated by battle fatigue or physical illness.  Incidents of soldiers AWOL from combat duty as well as battle fatigue and self-inflicted injury rose rapidly during the last eight months of the war with Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ambrose, Stephen pp. 277-284&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Henry, Mark R. 2001 pp. 12-14&quot;/&gt;  As one historian later concluded, &quot;Had the Germans been given a free hand to devise a replacement system..., one that would do the Americans the most harm and the least good, they could not have done a better job.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Henry, Mark R. 2001 pp. 12-14&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, Stephen, ''Citizen Soldiers'', p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;

Marshall's abilities to pick competent field commanders during the early part of the war was decidedly mixed.  While he had been instrumental in advancing the career of the able Dwight D. Eisenhower, he had also recommended the swaggering [[Lloyd Fredendall]] to Eisenhower for a major command in the American invasion of North Africa during [[Operation Torch|Operation ''Torch'']].  Marshall was especially fond of Fredendall, describing him as &quot;one of the best&quot; and remarking in a staff meeting when his name was mentioned, &quot;I like that man; you can see determination all over his face.&quot;  Eisenhower duly picked him to command the 39,000-man Central Task Force (the largest of three) in Operation ''Torch''.  Both men would later come to regret that decision after the U.S. Army debacle at [[Kasserine Pass]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

===Plans invasion of Europe===
 
During World War II, Marshall was instrumental in preparing the U.S. Army and [[United States Army Air Forces|Army Air Forces]] for the invasion of the European continent.  Marshall wrote the document that would become the central strategy for all Allied operations in Europe. He initially scheduled [[Operation Overlord|Operation ''Overlord'']] for April 1, 1943, but met with strong opposition from Winston Churchill, who convinced Roosevelt to commit troops to Operation ''Husky'' for the invasion of Italy. Some authors think that World War II could have been terminated one year earlier if Marshall had had his way, others think that such invasion would have meant utter failure. But it is true that the German Army in 1943 was overstretched, and defense works in Normandy were not ready.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}} 

It was assumed that Marshall would become the Supreme Commander of Operation ''Overlord'', but Roosevelt selected [[Dwight Eisenhower]] as Supreme Commander. While Marshall enjoyed considerable success in working with Congress and President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], he refused to lobby for the position. President Roosevelt didn't want to lose his presence in the states. He told Marshall, &quot;I didn't feel I could sleep at ease if you were out of Washington.&quot;&lt;ref name=d&gt;{{cite book|last=Buell|first=Thomas B.|coauthors=John H. Bradley|title=The Second World War: Europe and the Mediterranean|pages=258}}&lt;/ref&gt;  When rumors circulated that the top job would go to Marshall, many critics viewed the transfer as a demotion for Marshall, since he would leave his position as Chief of Staff of the Army and lose his seat on the [[Combined Chiefs of Staff]].{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}  

On December 16, 1944, Marshall became the first American general to be promoted to [[five-star rank]], the newly created [[General_of_the_Army_%28United_States%29#World_War_II_era|General of the Army]].  He was the second American to be promoted to a five-star rank, as [[William Daniel Leahy|William Leahy]] was promoted to [[Fleet Admiral (United States)|fleet admiral]] the previous day.  This position is the American equivalent rank to [[field marshal]].

Throughout the remainder of World War II, Marshall coordinated Allied operations in Europe and the Pacific.  He was characterized as the organizer of Allied victory by [[Winston Churchill]]. ''[[Time Magazine]]'' named Marshall [[Person of the Year|Man of the Year]] for 1943. Marshall resigned his post of Chief of Staff in 1945, but did not retire, as regulations{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}} stipulate that Generals of the Army remain on active duty for life.

==Analysis of Pearl Harbor intelligence failure==

After World War II ended, the Congressional Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack received testimony on the intelligence failure. It amassed 25,000 pages of documents, 40 volumes, and included nine reports and investigations, eight of which had been previously completed. Among these documents was a report critical of Marshall for his delay in sending General [[Walter Short]], the Army commander in Hawaii, important information concerning a possible attack on December 6 and 7. The report also criticized Marshall’s admitted lack of knowledge of the readiness of the Hawaiian Command during November and December 1941. Ten days after the attack, Lt. General Short and Admiral [[Husband E. Kimmel]], commander of the Navy at Pearl Harbor, were both relieved of their duties. The final report of the Joint Committee did not single out and fault Marshall. While the report was critical of the overall situation, the committee noted that  subordinates had failed to pass on important information to their superiors, including Marshall. The report noted that once General Marshall received information about the impending attack, he immediately passed it on.&lt;ref&gt;Hearings before the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack, Congress of the United States, Seventy-Ninth Congress (Washington, D.C.), Part 39, P 144-145.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Conclusions and Recommendations of the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack, Congress of the United States, Seventy-Ninth Congress (Washington, D.C.)P. 252, 265&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post War: China, Secretary of State, Nobel Peace Prize==

In December 1945, President [[Harry Truman]] sent Marshall to China to broker a coalition government between the [[Kuomintang|Nationalist]] allies under Generalissimo [[Chiang Kai-shek]] and [[Communist Party of China|Communists]] under [[Mao Zedong]]. Marshall had no leverage over the Communists, but he threatened to withdraw American aid essential to the Nationalists. Both sides rejected his proposals and the [[Chinese Civil War]] escalated, with the Communists winning in 1949. His mission a failure, he returned to the United States in January 1947.&lt;ref name=f&gt;{{cite book|last=Stoler|first=Mark A.|year=1989|title=George C. Marshall|pages=145–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=g&gt;{{cite book|last=Tsou|first=Tang|year=1963|title=America's Failure in China, 1941–50}}&lt;/ref&gt; As Secretary of State in 1947–48, Marshall seems to have disagreed with strong opinions in [[The Pentagon]] and State department that Chiang's success was vital to American interests, insisting that U.S. troops not become involved.

After Marshall's return to the U.S. in early 1947, Truman appointed Marshall [[United States Secretary of State|Secretary of State]]. He became the spokesman for the State Department's ambitious plans to rebuild Europe. On June 5, 1947 in a speech&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.georgecmarshall.org/learn/index.asp?L=17|title=The Marshall Plan|accessdate=2009-02-17}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; at [[Harvard University]], he outlined the American plan. The European Recovery Program, as it was formally known, became known as the [[Marshall Plan]]. [[Clark Clifford]] had suggested to Truman that the plan be called the Truman Plan, but Truman immediately dismissed that idea and insisted that it be called the Marshall Plan.&lt;ref name=&quot;mcculloughtrumanbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= McCullough |first= David |authorlink= David McCullough |title= Truman |year= 1992 |publisher=Simon and Schuster|location= New York|isbn= 0-671-86920-5 |pages= 717}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Behrman | first= Greg | title=The Most Noble Adventure: The Marshall Plan and the Time When America Helped Save Europe | publisher=Free Press| year=2007 | isbn=0743282639}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Marshall Plan would help Europe quickly rebuild and modernize its economy along American lines. The [[Soviet Union]] forbade its [[Satellite state|satellites]] to participate.
[[File:George marshall&amp;henry stimson.jpg|thumb|Marshall with [[United States Secretary of War|Secretary of War]] [[Henry Stimson]]]]
[[File:Infantry in battle cover.gif|thumb|Cover to the book ''Infantry in Battle'', the World War II officer's guide to infantry combat operations. Marshall directed production of the book, which is still used as a reference today.]]

Marshall was again named TIME's Man of the Year for 1947 and received the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] for his post-war work in 1953. He was the only U.S. Army General to have received this honor.

As Secretary of State, Marshall strongly opposed recognizing the State of [[Israel]]. Marshall felt that if the state of Israel was declared that a war would break out in the Middle East (which it did in 1948 one day after Israel declared independence). Marshall saw recognizing the Jewish state as a political move to gain Jewish support in the up coming election, in which Truman was expected to lose to Dewey. He told President Truman in May 1948, &quot;If you (recognize the state of Israel) and if I were to vote in the election, I would vote against you.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DBID=1&amp;LNGID=1&amp;TMID=111&amp;FID=376&amp;PID=0&amp;IID=2203|title=President Truman's Decision to Recognize Israel|accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wrmea.com/backissues/0591/9105017.htm|title=Truman Adviser Recalls May 14, 1948 US Decision to Recognize Israel|date=May/June 1991|work=Washington Report on Middle East Affairs|pages=17|accessdate=2009-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.trumanlibrary.org/hst/h.htm|title=Recognition of Israel|accessdate=2009-02-17|publisher=The Truman Library}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
Marshall resigned from the [[United States Department of State|State Department]] because of ill health on January 7, 1949, and the same month became chairman of American Battle Monuments Commission.&lt;ref&gt;New York Times:  January 8, 1949, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1949, Marshall was named president of the [[American National Red Cross]].

==Secretary of Defense==
When the early months of the [[Korean War]] showed how poorly prepared the Defense Department was, Truman fired Secretary [[Louis A. Johnson]] and named Marshall as [[United States Secretary of Defense|Secretary of Defense]] in September 1950. On September 30, Defense Secretary George Marshall sent an eyes-only message to MacArthur instructing MacArthur to escalate the war in Korea &quot;We want you to feel unhampered tactically and strategically to proceed north of the 38th parallel.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Weintraub, Stanley. MacArthur’s war: Korea and the Undoing of an American Hero, Simon &amp; Schuster, ISBN 0-684-83419-7. p.157:158.&lt;/ref&gt;  His main role was to restore confidence and rebuild the armed forces from the post-war state of demobilization.  He served in that post for one year, retiring from public office for good in September 1951. In 1953, he represented America at the [[Coronation of the British monarch|coronation]] of Queen [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom]].

==Impact of McCarthyism==
U.S. Senator [[Joe McCarthy]], whose hearings and [[black list]]s later spawned the term [[McCarthyism]], gave a speech titled ''America's Retreat from Victory: The Story of George Catlett Marshall'' (1951), in which he argued that General [[Albert Coady Wedemeyer]] had prepared a wise plan that would keep China a valued ally, but that it had been sabotaged. He concluded that &quot;If Marshall were merely stupid, the laws of probability would dictate that part of his decisions would serve this country's interest.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McCarthy|first=Joe|year=1951|title=Major Speeches and Debates|pages=264}}&lt;/ref&gt; He suggested that Marshall was old and feeble and easily duped but did not charge Marshall with treason. McCarthy specifically alleged:

{{quote
|&quot;When Marshall was sent to China with secret State Department orders, the Communists at that time were bottled up in two areas and were fighting a losing battle, but that because of those orders the situation was radically changed in favor of the Communists. Under those orders, as we know, Marshall embargoed all arms and ammunition to our allies in China. He forced the opening of the Nationalist-held Kalgan Mountain pass into Manchuria, to the end that the Chinese Communists gained access to the mountains of captured Japanese equipment. No need to tell the country about how Marshall tried to force [[Chiang Kai-shek]] to form a partnership government with the Communists.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=McCarthy|first=Joe|year=1951|title=Major Speeches and Debates|pages=191, from speech of March 14, 1951}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Reeves|first=Thomas C.|year=1982|title=The Life and Times of Joe McCarthy|pages=371–374}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Legacy==

Marshall died on Friday, October 16, 1959. He is buried at [[Arlington National Cemetery]].

After leaving office, in a television interview, Harry Truman was asked who he thought was the American who made the greatest contribution of the last thirty years.  Without hesitation, Truman picked Marshall, adding &quot;I don't think in this age in which I have lived, that there has been a man who has been a greater administrator; a man with a knowledge of military affairs equal to General Marshall.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''The David Susskind Show'': Interview with President Harry S. Truman
|url=http://www.hulu.com/watch/46482/the-david-susskind-show-interview-with-president-harry-s-truman#s-p2-so-i0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Orson Welles, in an interview with [[Dick Cavett]], called Marshall &quot;...the greatest human being who was also a great man... He was a tremendous gentlemen, an old fashioned institution which isn't with us anymore.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r1fauAc48tA&amp;feature=related |title=Orson Welles talks about Cornelia Lunt |publisher=YouTube}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In spite of world-wide acclaim, dozens of national and international awards and honors and the Nobel Peace prize, public opinion became bitterly divided along party lines on Marshall's record. While campaigning for president in 1952, Eisenhower denounced the Truman administration's failures in Korea, campaigned alongside McCarthy, and refused to defend Marshall's policies. Marshall, who assisted Eisenhower in his promotions, and stood aside, turning down the opportunity to command the allied forces to allow Eisenhower to take that role, was surprised at the lack of a positive statement supporting him from Eisenhower during the McCarthy hearings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''American Experience: The Presidents'': Dwight D. Eisenhower|url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/presidents/34_eisenhower/printable.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=''American Experience: The Presidents'': Dwight D. Eisenhower (Film Script |url=http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/presidents/34_eisenhower/filmmore/filmscript.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family life==

[[File:Statue of George C. Marshall at Dodona Manor.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.4|Statue of [[George C. Marshall]] at Dodona Manor in Leesburg, Virginia. The museum is a [[National Historic Landmark]] and is owned by the George C. Marshall International Center]]

He married [[Elizabeth Carter Cole]] of [[Lexington, Virginia]], in 1902. She died in 1927. In 1930, he married [[Katherine Boyce Tupper]].  Marshall's stepson with Tupper, Army Lt. Allen Tupper Brown, was killed by a German sniper in Italy in 1944.  George Marshall maintained a home, known as [[Dodona Manor]] (now restored), in [[Leesburg, Virginia]]. Actress [[Kitty Winn]] is his step-granddaughter.

==Dramatic portrayals==
* Marshall was played by [[Donald Eugene McCoy]] in the Chinese movie ''[[Founding of a Republic]]''.
* Marshall was played by [[Harris Yulin]] in the television drama ''[[Truman (film)|Truman]]''.
* Marshall was played by [[Scott Wilson (actor)|Scott Wilson]] in the 2001 film ''[[Pearl Harbor (film)|Pearl Harbor]].
* Marshall was played by [[Harve Presnell]] in the 1998 film ''[[Saving Private Ryan]]''.
* Marshall was played by [[Keith Andes]] in the 1970 film ''[[Tora! Tora! Tora!]]''.
* Marshall was played by [[Ward Costello]] in the 1977 film ''[[MacArthur (film)|MacArthur]]''.

==Dates of rank==
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;background:white&quot;
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |''No pin insignia in 1902''
|[[Second Lieutenant#United States|Second Lieutenant]], [[United States Army]]: February 2, 1902
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-OF1A.svg|13px]]
|[[First Lieutenant#United States|First Lieutenant]], United States Army: March 7, 1907
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|33px]]
|[[Captain (U.S. Army)|Captain]], United States Army: July 1, 1916
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|40px]]
|[[Major (United States)|Major]], [[National Army (USA)|National Army]]: August 5, 1917
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|40px]]
|[[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]], National Army: January 5, 1918
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O6 insignia.svg|60px]]
|[[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]], National Army: August 27, 1918
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O3 insignia.svg|33px]]
|Captain, [[Regular Army]] (reverted to peacetime rank): June 30, 1920
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O4 insignia.svg|40px]]
|Major, [[Regular Army]] : July 1, 1920
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O5 insignia.svg|40px]]
|Lieutenant Colonel, Regular Army: August 21, 1923
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O6 insignia.svg|60px]]
|Colonel, Regular Army: September 1, 1933
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O7 insignia.svg|33px]]
|[[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]], Regular Army: October 1, 1936
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O8 insignia.svg|66px]]
|[[Major general (United States)|Major General]], Regular Army: July 1, 1939
|-
|[[File:US-O9 insignia.svg|100px|center|]]
|[[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]], [[Regular Army (United States)|Regular Army]]: August 1, 1939
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; |[[File:US-O10 insignia.svg|133px]]
|[[General (United States)|General]], Regular Army, for service as [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]]: September 1, 1939
|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot; |[[File:US-O11 insignia.svg|95px]]
|[[General of the Army (United States)|General of the Army]], [[Army of the United States]]: December 16, 1944
|-
|General of the Army rank made permanent in the Regular Army: April 11, 1946
|}

==Awards and decorations==
===U.S. military honors===
{|
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=1|type=oak|ribbon=Distinguished Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[Army Distinguished Service Medal|Distinguished Service Medal]] with one [[Oak Leaf Cluster]]
|-
|[[File:Silver Star ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Silver Star]]
|-
|[[File:Philippine Campaign Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Philippine Campaign Medal]]
|-
|{{Ribbon devices|number=4|type=service-star|ribbon=World War I Victory Medal ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[World War I Victory Medal (United States)|World War I Victory Medal]] with four [[battle clasp]]s
|-
|[[File:Army of Occupation of Germany ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Army of Occupation of Germany Medal]]
|-
|[[File:American Defense Service ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[American Defense Service Medal]]
|-
|[[File:American Campaign Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[American Campaign Medal]]
|-
|[[File:World War II Victory Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[World War II Victory Medal]]
|-
|}

===Foreign military honors===
*Brazilian Order of Military Merit
*[[Order of the Bath|British Order of the Bath (Knight Grand Cross)]]
*Chilean Order del Merito
*Colombian Grand Cross of the Order of Boyacá Cherifien (Given by President Ospina Perez as he opened the IX Panamerican Conference)
*Cuban Order of Military Merit, First Class
*Ecuadorian Star of Abdon Calderon, First Class
*[[Croix de Guerre|French Croix de Guerre]]
*[[French Legion of Honor]]
*Greek Grand Cross [[Order of George I]] with swords
*Liberian Centennial Medal
*Montenegro Silver Medal for Bravery
*Netherlands Grand Cross with Swords in the [[Order of Orange-Nassau|Order of Orange Nassau]]
*[[Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus]] (Italy)
*Order of the Crown of Italy
*[[Order of Ouissam Alaouite|Moroccan Grand Cross of Ouissam Alaouite]]
*[[Order of Military Merit|Soviet Grand Cross Order of Military Merit]]
*[[Order of Suvarov|Soviet Order of Suvorov]]
*Panamanian Medal of La Solidaridad, Second Class
*Peruvian Gran Official del Sol del Peru

===Civilian honors===
*In 1948, he was awarded the Distinguished Achievement Award for his role and contributions during and after World War II.
*[[Nobel Peace Prize]] 1953 for the Marshall Plan.
*The [[United States Postal Service]] honored him with a [[Prominent Americans series]] (1965–1978) 20¢ postage stamp.
*1959 [[Charlemagne Award|Karlspreis (International Charlemagne Prize of the city of Aachen)]].
*1960 George C. [[Marshall Space Flight Center]], originally the Army Ballistics Missile Agency at Redstone Arsenal, Huntsville Alabama, became a NASA field center and was renamed.
*The British Parliament established the [[Marshall Scholarship]] in recognition of Marshall's contributions to Anglo-American relations.
*Many buildings and streets throughout the U.S. and other nations are named in his honor.
*George C. Marshall Award, the highest award given to a chapter in Kappa Alpha Order.
*[[George C. Marshall High School]], founded in 1962 and located in [[Falls Church, Virginia]], is the only public high school in the United States named for Marshall. The nickname of the school – &quot;The Statesmen&quot; – appropriately reflects his life and contributions.
*The Marshall Elementary School is in the Laurel Highlands School District, Uniontown, Pennsylvania.
*George C. Marshall Elementary School: located in Vancouver, Washington.
The George C. Marshal European Center for Security Studies in Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Germany

==Bibliography==
*Cray, Ed.  ''General of the Army: George C. Marshall, Soldier and Statesman.'' Norton, 1990. 847 pp.
*Harold I. Gullan; &quot;Expectations of Infamy: Roosevelt and Marshall Prepare for War, 1938–41.&quot; ''Presidential Studies Quarterly'' Volume: 28#3 1998. pp 510+ [http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;d=5001392305 online edition]
*May, Ernest R. &quot;1947–48: When Marshall Kept the U.S. out of War in China.&quot; ''Journal of Military History'' 2002 66(4): 1001–1010. Issn: 0899-3718
*Levine, Steven I. &quot;A New Look at American Mediation in the Chinese Civil War: the Marshall Mission and Manchuria.&quot; ''Diplomatic History'' 1979 3(4): 349–375. Issn: 0145-2096
*Parrish, Thomas.  ''Roosevelt and Marshall: Partners in Politics and War.'' 1989. 608 pp.
*Steele, Richard W.  ''The First Offensive, 1942: Roosevelt, Marshall, and the Making of American Strategy.'' 1973. 239 pp.
*Mark C. Stoler, ''George C. Marshall: Soldier-Statesman of the American Century. '' (1989) 252pp
*[[Forrest Pogue]], Viking, (1963–87) Four-volume authorized biography: complete text is online
**''[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/library/poguecollection.htm George C. Marshall: Education of a General, 1880–1939]''
**''[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/Library/PogueCollection.htm George C Marshall: Ordeal and Hope, 1939–1943]''
**''[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/Library/PogueCollection.htm George C. Marshall: Organizer of Victory 1943–1945]''
**''[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/Library/PogueCollection.htm George C. Marshall: Statesman 1945–1959]''

==See also==
{{Portal box|Biography|World War I|World War II|United States Army}}
*[[German Marshall Fund]]
*[[George C. Marshall Center for European Security Studies]]
*[[George C. Marshall High School]]
*[[Marshall Mission]] to China
*[[Marshall Scholarship]]
*[[Marshall Space Flight Center]]
*[[Task Force Marshall]] a training organization of the [[South Carolina Army National Guard]], was named in his honor
*[[The George C. Marshall Foundation]]
*[[USS George C. Marshall (SSBN-654)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

===Primary sources===
*''The Papers of George Catlett Marshall:'' (Larry I. Bland and Sharon Ritenour Stevens, eds.)
**Vol. 1: The Soldierly Spirit,&quot; December 1880 – June 1939. (1981)
**Vol. 2: &quot;We Cannot Delay,&quot; July 1, 1939 – December 6, 1941. (1986)
**Vol. 3: The Right Man for the Job, December 7, 1941 – May 31, 1943. (1991)
**Vol. 4: &quot;Aggressive and Determined Leadership,&quot; June 1, 1943 – December 31, 1944. (1996)
**Vol. 5: &quot;The Finest Soldier,&quot; January 1, 1945 – January 7, 1947.  (2003)
*Bland, Larry; Jeans, Roger B.; and Wilkinson, Mark, ed.  ''George C. Marshall's Mediation Mission to China, December 1945 – January 1947.'' Lexington, Va.: George C. Marshall Found., 1998. 661 pp.
*Marshall, George C.  ''George C. Marshall: Interviews and Reminiscences for Forrest C. Pogue.'' Lexington, Va.: George C. Marshall Found., 1991. 698 pp.  [http://www.marshallfoundation.org/library/pogue.html online edition]
*George Catlett Marshall. ''Memoirs of My Services in the World War, 1917–1918'' (1976)
*Greg Behrman. ''The Most Noble Adventure: The Marshall Plan and the Time When America Helped Save Europe'' [[Free Press (publisher)|Free Press]], 2007.

==Further reading==
*{{cite book| title=Infantry in Battle|isbn=0940328046|author=The Infantry Journal Incorporated|location=Washington, DC|year=1939|publisher=Garrett and Massey|url=http://www-cgsc.army.mil/carl/download/csipubs/infantry/inf_intro_cvii.pdf}}

==External links==
{{Wikiquote}}
{{Commons}}
{{Wikisource author}}
*[http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1953/marshall-bio.html Brief biography at the official Nobel Prize site]
*[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/ The Marshall Foundation]
*[http://www.marshallcenter.org/ George C. Marshall Center, Garmisch Germany]
*[http://www.marshallfoundation.org/library/index_av.html The Marshall Plan Speech MP3]
*[http://www.marshallfilms.org/ The Marshall Films Collection]
*[http://www.marshallscholarship.org/ Marshall Scholarships]
*[http://www.georgecmarshall.org/lt/speeches/marshall_plan.cfm/ The Marshall Plan Speech]
*[http://www.georgecmarshall.org/ Dodona Manor]
*[http://www.npg.si.edu/exh/marshall/marsh2.htm &quot;George C. Marshall: Soldier of Peace&quot; (Smithsonian Institution)]
*[http://www.janson.com/rights/2009/06/26/george-marshall-and-the-american-century/ &quot;George Marshall and the American Century&quot; (Documentary Film)]
*[http://alsos.wlu.edu/qsearch.aspx?browse=people/Marshall,+George Annotated bibliography for George Marshall from the Alsos Digital Library for Nuclear Issues]
*[http://www.history.army.mil/books/Last_Salute/Ch19.htm The Last Salute: Civil and Military Funeral, 1921–1969, CHAPTER XIX, General of the Army George C. Marshall, Special Military Funeral, 16 – October 20, 1959] by B.&amp;nbsp;C.&amp;nbsp;Mossman and M.&amp;nbsp;W.&amp;nbsp;Stark. [[United States Army Center of Military History]], 1991. CMH Pub 90-1.
*[http://docs.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box3/folo43.html The George C. Marshall Index at the Franklin D. Roosevelt Presidential Library and Museum, Part 1] and [http://docs.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box4/folo44.html Part 2]
*[http://www.cityofvancouver.us/marshall.asp?menuid=10466&amp;submenuid=10537&amp;itemID=16097 City of Vancouver, Washington's &quot;General George C. Marshall and Vancouver&quot; page]
*[http://www.jackson.army.mil/IRR/TFM.htm Task Force Marshall Information Page]
*[http://www.ibiblio.org/pha/pha/congress/part_0.html Joint Committee on The Investigation of Pearl Harbor, 79th Congress]

{{S-start}}
{{S-mil}}
{{Succession box|title=[[Chief of Staff of the United States Army]]|before=[[Malin Craig]]|after=[[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]|years=1939&amp;nbsp;– 1945}}
{{S-off}}
{{U.S. Secretary box
|before=[[James F. Byrnes]]
|after=[[Dean Acheson]]
|years=1947–1949
|president=[[Harry S. Truman]]
|department=Secretary of State}}
{{U.S. Secretary box
|before=[[Louis A. Johnson]]
|after=[[Robert A. Lovett]]
|years=1950–1951
|president=[[Harry S. Truman]]
|department=Secretary of Defense}}
{{S-ach}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Prince Konoye]]}} 
{{S-ttl|title=[[Time (magazine)|Cover of Time Magazine]]  
|years=July 29, 1940}} 
{{S-aft|after=[[Alan Brooke, 1st Viscount Alanbrooke|Sir Alan F. Brooke]]}} 
{{S-bef|before=[[Ed Flynn]]}} 
{{S-ttl|title=[[Time (magazine)|Cover of Time Magazine]]  
|years=October 19, 1942}} 
{{S-aft|after=[[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Patriarch Sergius I of Moscow]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Time (magazine)|Cover of Time Magazine]]
|years=January 3, 1944}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Erich von Manstein]]}}
{{S-end}}
{{US Army Chiefs of Staff}}
{{USSecState}}
{{USSecDef}}
{{Cold War}}
{{Cold War figures}}
{{Nobel Peace Prize Laureates 1951-1975}}
{{Time Persons of the Year|27–50}}
{{Truman cabinet}}
{{Charlemagne Prize recipients}}

{{Persondata
|NAME= Marshall, George
|ALTERNATIVE NAMES=
|SHORT DESCRIPTION= Politician and United States Army general
|DATE OF BIRTH=December 31, 1880
|PLACE OF BIRTH=[[Uniontown, Pennsylvania|Uniontown]], Pennsylvania
|DATE OF DEATH=October 16, 1959
|PLACE OF DEATH=Washington, D.C.
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Marshall, George}}
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1959 deaths]]
[[Category:American 5 star officers]]
[[Category:American Episcopalians]]
[[Category:American humanitarians]]
[[Category:American military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:American Nobel laureates]]
[[Category:American people of World War II]]
[[Category:Burials at Arlington National Cemetery]]
[[Category:Cold War diplomats]]
[[Category:Cold War leaders]]
[[Category:Congressional Gold Medal recipients]]
[[Category:Charlemagne Prize recipients]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of Saints Maurice and Lazarus]]
[[Category:Légion d'honneur recipients]]
[[Category:Nobel Peace Prize laureates]]
[[Category:People from Loudoun County, Virginia]]
[[Category:People from Uniontown, Pennsylvania]]
[[Category:People of the Chinese Civil War]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de Guerre (France)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Distinguished Service Medal (United States)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Silver Star]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Military Merit (Brazil)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of George I with Swords]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of George I]]
[[Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of Orange-Nassau]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Crown of Italy]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Ouissam Alaouite]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Suvorov]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Medal of La Solidaridad]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Sun (Peru)]]
[[Category:Honorary Knights Grand Cross of the Order of the Bath]]
[[Category:Truman Administration cabinet members]]
[[Category:United States Secretaries of State]]
[[Category:United States Secretaries of Defense]]
[[Category:United States Army Chiefs of Staff]]
[[Category:United States Army Command and General Staff College alumni]]
[[Category:Virginia Military Institute alumni]]

[[ar:جورج مارشال]]
[[be:Джордж Маршал]]
[[be-x-old:Джордж Маршал]]
[[br:George Marshall]]
[[bg:Джордж Маршал]]
[[ca:George Marshall]]
[[cs:George Catlett Marshall]]
[[da:George Marshall]]
[[de:George C. Marshall]]
[[et:George Marshall]]
[[es:George Marshall]]
[[eo:George Catlett Marshall]]
[[fa:جورج مارشال]]
[[fr:George Marshall (général)]]
[[ko:조지 마셜]]
[[hr:George Marshall]]
[[io:George Marshall]]
[[id:George Marshall]]
[[it:George Marshall]]
[[he:ג'ורג' מרשל]]
[[ka:ჯორჯ მარშალი]]
[[ku:George Marshall]]
[[la:Georgius Catlett Marshall]]
[[lv:Džordžs Māršals]]
[[lt:George Marshall]]
[[hu:George C. Marshall]]
[[nl:George Marshall (generaal)]]
[[ja:ジョージ・マーシャル]]
[[no:George Marshall]]
[[pnb:جارج مارشل]]
[[pl:George Marshall]]
[[pt:George Marshall]]
[[ro:George Marshall]]
[[ru:Маршалл, Джордж]]
[[simple:George Marshall]]
[[sk:George C. Marshall]]
[[sl:George Catlett Marshall]]
[[sr:Џорџ Маршал (генерал)]]
[[fi:George Marshall]]
[[sv:George C. Marshall]]
[[th:จอร์จ มาร์แชลล์]]
[[tr:George C. Marshall]]
[[uk:Джордж Маршалл]]
[[vi:George Marshall]]
[[yo:George Marshall]]
[[zh:乔治·卡特莱特·马歇尔]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
