<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3663633" ns="0" title="WKPT-TV"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox_Broadcast
| call_letters = WKPT-TV
| city = Kingsport
| station_logo = [[Image:WKPT-TV 2008.png|150px]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;!-- Do NOT add a non-free image here without adding a rationale per WP:FURG --&gt;[[Image:Wkpt dt3.PNG|125px]]
| station_slogan = 
| station_branding = ABC 19 WKPT&lt;br&gt;My Tri-Cities WAPK &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(on DT2)&lt;/small&gt;
| digital = 27 ([[ultra high frequency|UHF]])
| other_chs = 
| affiliations = 
| subchannels = 19.1 [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]&lt;br /&gt;[[WAPK-CA|19.2]] [[MyNetworkTV]]&lt;br&gt;19.3 [[Retro Television Network|RTV]]
| network = 
| founded = 
| airdate = [[1969 in television|August 20, 1969]]
| location = [[Kingsport, Tennessee|Kingsport]]-[[Johnson City, Tennessee|Johnson City]]- [[Bristol, Tennessee]]-[[Bristol, Virginia]]
| callsign_meaning = '''W'''e're in '''K'''ings'''P'''ort, '''T'''ennessee
| former_callsigns = 
| former_channel_numbers = '''Analog:'''&lt;br&gt;19 (UHF, 1969-2009)
| owner = Holston Valley Broadcasting Corporation
| licensee = 
| sister_stations = WAPK-CA, [[WTFM]], [[WRZK]], [[WVEK-FM]], [[WMEV-FM]] [[WKPT (AM)|WKPT]], [[WOPI (AM)|WOPI]], [[WKTP]]
| former_affiliations = 
| effective_radiated_power = 25 [[kilowatt|kW]]
| HAAT = 695 m
| class = 
| facility_id = 27504
| coordinates = {{coord|36|25|54|N|82|8|15|W|type:landmark_scale:2000}}
| homepage = [http://www.abc19.tv www.abc19.tv]
}}

'''WKPT-TV''' is the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]-affiliated [[television station]] for the [[Tri-Cities, Tennessee|Tri-Cities]] area of Northeastern [[Tennessee]] and Southwestern [[Virginia]]  that is licensed to [[Kingsport, Tennessee]]. It broadcasts a [[high-definition television|high definition]] digital signal on [[UHF]] channel 27 from a transmitter at Holston High Point on [[Holston Mountain]] in the [[Cherokee National Forest]]. Owned by the Holston Valley Broadcasting Corporation, the station is co-owned with [[Class A television service|Class A]] [[MyNetworkTV]] affiliate [[WAPK-CA]] and several radio stations. All share studios on Commerce Street in Downtown Kingsport. 

Although the station is located in Kingsport, the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC) requires it to include Johnson City and Bristol, Tennessee/Virginia in its legal station identification.&lt;ref&gt;Television Factbook #49, 1980 Edition, page 788-B, WKPT-TV&lt;/ref&gt;

[[television syndication|Syndicated]] programming on WKPT includes: ''[[TMZ on TV]]'', ''[[Entertainment Tonight]]'', ''[[The Insider (TV series)|The Insider]]'' and ''[[The Dr. Oz Show]]''.

==Digital programming==

Its signal is multiplexed. Due to its Class A status, WAPK does not broadcast a digital signal of its own. Therefore, it can be seen on WKPT's second digital subchannel. On WKPT-DT3, [[Charter Communications|Charter]] digital channel 199 and [[Comcast]] digital channel 231 is the area's [[Retro Television Network|RTV]] affiliate. This can also be seen over-the-air on WOPI-CA, [[VHF]] channel 9, also from a transmitter at Holston High Point.

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Channel
! Programming
|-
| 19.1 / 27.1 || main WKPT programming / ABC HD
|-
| 19.2 / 27.2 || WAPK-CA &quot;My Tri-Cities WAPK&quot;
|-
| 19.3 / 27.3 || WOPI-CA RTV
|}

==History==
[[Image:WkpttvLogoGRAY.jpg|left|150px|thumb|Logo used by WKPT from April 2007 until August 2008.]]

WKPT-TV began broadcasting on [[August 20]], [[1969]] as the Tri-Cities' ABC affiliate. Previously, the network had been shared between [[NBC]] affiliate [[WCYB-TV]] and [[CBS]] affiliate [[WJHL-TV]], each of which picked its own ABC programs to air. However, many viewers in the area could view the entire ABC schedule on nearby [[WLOS-TV]] in [[Asheville, North Carolina]]. Before WKPT signed on, WLOS included the Tri-Cities as part of its primary coverage area as it was widely available off-air and on cable. 

WKPT has three historical distinctions. First, it is the oldest UHF television station in Tennessee to have maintained continuous operation on the UHF band to the present.  Secondly, it is the second oldest station in Tennessee to have had the same licensee from its inaugural date to the present. [[WBBJ-TV]] in [[Jackson, Tennessee]] is the oldest but only after it was sold to [[Bahakel Communications]]. Third, for years it was the only locally owned-and-operated full-power station in the Tri-Cities. However, that was merely by default. Because the antenna heights of its two VHF rivals, WJHL and WCYB, are above the {{convert|2000|ft|m|abbr=on}} above average terrain full power ceiling height mandated by the [[Federal Communications Commission]] (FCC), those two could not operate at their full power capacities. WCYB radiated 65,000 watts ERP analog visual while WJHL radiated 245,000 watts ERP analog visual. 

WKPT was also one of the first stations in the country to utilize a newly-adopted (at the time) FCC rule called [[must-carry]] that required local cable companies to black out stations in nearby cities affiliated with the same network that were carried on local cable systems and cover the channel with the local network affiliate. As a result, the easily receivable off-air network signal from WLOS, {{convert|110|mi|km}} away, was always blacked out on cable systems in Kingsport, Bristol, [[Johnson City, Tennessee|Johnson City]], and the surrounding communities while being covered by the WKPT signal any time both stations were broadcasting ABC programming. Local WLOS programming was not blacked out. After deregulation of the cable industry, stations from adjacent [[media market|markets]] were taken off most local cable systems altogether in favor of satellite stations like [[TBS (TV network)|TBS]], [[Superstation WGN|WGN America]], [[CNN]], and others. 

WCYB and WJHL received ABC via traditional ground microwave relay stations provided by [[AT&amp;T]] back in the 1950s and 1960s. However when WKPT started in 1969, its owners could not afford the expensive network feed estimated to have been around a half-million dollars per year. As a result, the station developed its own low-cost way of bringing ABC to upper East Tennessee and Southwestern Virginia. Before the advent of satellite technology, WKPT utilized a series of private microwave relay stations between Kingsport and [[Knoxville]]. As the ABC signal was being transmitted via traditional microwave from AT&amp;T into the studios of then-ABC affiliate WTVK-TV on [[Sharp's Ridge]] in Knoxville (now CBS affiliate [[WVLT-TV]]), WKPT would literally &quot;grab&quot; the Telco signal just as it was going into the WTVK studios. It then sent the signal via private microwave to a relay station {{convert|70|mi|km}} line-of-sight miles east to Camp Creek Bald on the Tennessee/[[North Carolina]] border in Southern [[Greene County, Tennessee]]. The ABC signal was then re-transmitted via another WKPT microwave {{convert|33|mi|km}} line-of-sight miles further east to the WKPT transmitter site on Holston Mountain. From the relay point there, it was transmitted by a third WKPT microwave {{convert|25|mi|km}} line-of-sight miles down to the studios in Downtown Kingsport through the station's master control board and then back to Holston Mountain via the station's regular studio-transmitter link and then broadcast on Channel 19.

Private microwave relays of network programming were prevalent before the advent of A.T. &amp; T. commercial microwave.  [[WVVA-TV]] in Bluefield, West Virginia operated its own private microwave relay that brought NBC to Bluefield from [[WSLS-TV]] in Roanoke, Virginia.  In its early days, [[WSMV-TV]], Nashville received its NBC feed from [[WAVE-TV]], Louisville, and [[WSAZ-TV]], Huntington operated a private microwave to deliver NBC first from [[WLWT]], Cincinnati, then from WLWC-TV (now [[WCMH-TV]], Columbus).

Whenever any part of WKPT-TV's private microwave relay system malfunctioned, as it did periodically because of heavy snowfall or downed trees, station engineers were forced to broadcast the signal of either WTVK or WLOS whenever network programming was airing. Occasionally, WKPT accidentally aired the local commercials and the station identifications of either WTVK or WLOS being unable to cover them up quickly. When WTVK swapped networks with [[WATE-TV]], WKPT merely moved its Knoxville microwave relay {{convert|800|ft|m|abbr=on}} west to WATE's transmitter site, also on Sharp's Ridge, and continued to receive ABC via its privately-owned microwave relay system. Ironically, the AT&amp;T network signals for WJHL and WCYB were both delivered from [[Greenville, South Carolina]] to the phone company microwave that is also atop Camp Creek Bald that fed the Knoxville television stations. 

WKPT's first branding in the 1970s was &quot;WKPT, Tri-Cities' ABC&quot; which featured the first musical station IDs in the area. That concept was later used by WATE when that station became an ABC affiliate in 1979. In 1998, the station re-branded as &quot;ABC 19 WKPT&quot; which marked the first time the station's channel number was actually mentioned on-air since the 1980s. Initially, WOPI-CA schedule consisted of infomercials and [[Pentagon Channel]] programming. That station was a full-time affiliate of [[America One]] until December 21, 2007. On that date, WKPT-DT3 and WOPI switched to the Retro Television Network. After the analog to digital switch, WKPT began transmitting on digital Channel 27, which it continues on today.&lt;ref name=&quot;FCCForm387&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://fjallfoss.fcc.gov/cgi-bin/ws.exe/prod/cdbs/forms/prod/cdbsmenu.hts?context=25&amp;appn=101234049&amp;formid=387&amp;fac_num=40761|title=CDBS Print&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, through the use of [[Program and System Information Protocol|PSIP]], digital television receivers display its [[virtual channel]] as 19. 

Under federal must-carry rules, broadcasters can either allow cable systems in their market to carry their signals for free or charge a fee under [[retransmission consent]] provisions. On December 3, 2008, it was announced that Inter Mountain Cable (IMC), a cable provider serving parts of Eastern Kentucky, announced that it would drop WKPT from their lineup unless an agreement was reached over retransmission consent. &lt;ref name=&quot;IMC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imctv.com/news_viewNews.php?news_id=41|title=WKPT, WCYB &amp; WJHL Possible Programming Issue For 2009|date=2008-12-03|publisher=Inter Mountain Cable|accessdate=2009-01-15}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''[[The Mountain Eagle]]'',  this dispute has caused concern among officials in the city of [[Fleming-Neon, Kentucky|Fleming-Neon]], where IMC holds the cable television franchise there. &lt;ref name=&quot;Farley&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.themountaineagle.com/news/2009/0114/news/004.html|title=Neon council upset by threat of TV changes|last=Farley|first=William|date=2009-01-14|publisher=The Mountain Eagle|pages=2|accessdate=2009-01-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city council in Fleming-Neon have stated that the removal of WKPT would violate IMC's franchise agreement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Farley&quot; /&gt;

==Out-of-market cable coverage==
In [[Kentucky]], WKPT is available on Harlan Community Television in [[Harlan, Kentucky|Harlan]] and Access Community Television in [[Cumberland, Kentucky|Cumberland]], which are part of the [[Knoxville, Tennessee|Knoxville, TN]] [[media market|DMA]].

In [[Virginia]], WKPT is available on [[Time Warner Cable]] in [[Tazewell, Virginia|Tazewell]], which is part of the [[Bluefield, West Virginia|Bluefield, WV]] DMA.

In [[North Carolina]], WKPT is available on [[Charter Communications]] in [[Boone, North Carolina|Boone]] and Zito Media in [[Creston, North Carolina|Creston]], which are part of the [[Charlotte, North Carolina|Charlotte]] DMA.

==News operation==
WKPT's first personalities in the early 1970s included news anchors Martin Karant and Bill Freehoff along with weather/sports with Bill Trailer. These distinguished broadcasters had been popular personalities on [[WKPT (AM)|WKPT-AM]] 1400 and made the move to television. Karant continued to hold his position on WKPT-AM until his retirement in 1997. Until February 2002, WKPT produced news in-house. &lt;ref&gt;http://mobile.broadcastingcable.com/article/141197-Original_news_kaput_on_WKPT.php&lt;/ref&gt; From that date until September 2006, nightly 6 and 11 o’clock newscasts originated from WJHL and were simulcast on both WKPT and WJHL. In situations where one station was off (due to network run over or other circumstances), the news was broadcast on the other station at the correct time. 

As of September 2006, WJHL's nightly 11 o’clock broadcast was repeated on WKPT at or around 1:06 in the morning. In addition, a five minute news and weather summary was provided at 11:30 P.M. to accommodate for the gap between the end of syndicated programming and the beginning of ''[[Nightline (US news program)|Nightline]]''. At some point, this programming was dropped. Also, WJHL's weekday Noon show had been repeated on WAPK and WKPT-DT3 / WOPI-CA on a half-hour delay at 12:30. Like all RTV affiliates in the [[Eastern Time Zone]], that station currently airs ''[[Daytime (US TV series)|Daytime]]'' weekday mornings at 9.

Since 2009, WKPT has been airing news and weather briefs during daytime programming, anchored by Duane Nelson and taped in the radio news department. In 2010 Cyrus Fees relaunched the news department for the 6:25-6:30 PM &amp; 11:00-11:08 PM News as &quot;WKPT-TV News 19.&quot;

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.abc19.tv/ WKPT-DT channel 19]
*[http://www.wkpttv.com/dt3/index.html WKPT-DT3 / WOPI-CA channel 9]
*[http://www.wapktv.com/ WAPK-CA &quot;My Tri-Cities WAPK&quot; ]
*[http://wkpt1400tribute.tripod.com/ Tribute Page to WKPT Radio and TV, 1969-1971]
*[http://www.wkptam.com/martin2.html Martin Karant Tribute Page]
*{{TVQ|WKPT-TV}}
*{{TVQ|WOPI-CA}}

{{Tri-Cities TV}}
{{ABC Tennessee}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wkpt-Tv}}
[[Category:Television stations in Tennessee]]
[[Category:ABC network affiliates]]
[[Category:Channel 27 digital TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Channel 19 virtual TV stations in the United States]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1969]]
[[Category:Retro Television Network affiliates]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
