<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="36647" ns="0" title="Christine McVie"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Christine Perfect|the album|Christine Perfect (album)}}
{{BLP sources|date=October 2009}}
{{Infobox musical artist
|image=
| name                = Christine McVie
| image               =
| background          = solo_singer
| birth_name          = Christine Anne Perfect
| alias               =
| Born                = {{Birth date and age|df=y|1943|7|12}}&lt;br/&gt; [[Bouth]], [[Lancashire]], England
| death_date          =
| instrument          = Vocals, [[keyboard instrument|keyboards]], piano, [[accordion]], [[harmonica]]
| genre               = [[Blues]], pop rock, soft rock, pop
| occupation          =
| years_active        = 1967–2004
| label               = [[Blue Horizon]] (1968–1970)&lt;br&gt;[[Reprise Records]] (1970–1977)&lt;br&gt;[[Sire Records]] (1977–1997)&lt;br&gt;[[E1 Music]] (US) (2004)&lt;br&gt;[[Sanctuary Records]] (2004)
| associated_acts     = [[Fleetwood Mac]] (1970–1998), [[Chicken Shack]] (1968–1969)
}}
'''Christine McVie''' (born '''Christine Anne Perfect''', 12 July 1943, in [[Bouth]], near [[Ulverston]], [[Lancashire]], England)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.findmypast.co.uk/BirthsMarriagesDeaths.jsp |title=Marriages and Births England and Wales 1837–2006 |publisher=Findmypast.co.uk|date= |accessdate=2011-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an English rock singer, [[keyboardist]], and songwriter. Her primary fame came as a member of the British/American rock band [[Fleetwood Mac]], though she has also released three solo albums. As a member of Fleetwood Mac, she was inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame in 1998.

==Early life==
Christine was born in the small village of [[Bouth]] in the [[Lake District]] of England and grew up in the [[Bearwood, West Midlands|Bearwood]] area of [[Smethwick]] near [[Birmingham]], where her father, Cyril P.A.Perfect, was a  concert violinist and music lecturer at [[Saltley College|St Peter's College of Education]], [[Saltley]], [[Birmingham]]. Christine's mother Beatrice E.M.(called Tee) née Reece, was a medium, psychic, and faith healer. Her grandfather had been an organist at [[Westminster Abbey]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=11&amp;c=2 |title=Christine McVie |publisher=''Contemporary Keyboard'' |date=October 1980 |last=Doerschuk |first=Bob}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Christine was introduced to the piano at the age of four, it was not until age eleven that she studied music seriously, when she was re-introduced to the instrument by Philip Fisher, a local musician and school friend of her older brother John.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Continuing her classical training until the age of fifteen, her musical focus made a radical shift to [[Rock and roll|rock &amp; roll]] when John brought home a [[Fats Domino]] songbook.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=942&amp;c=2 |title=Christine McVie: Life After Fleetwood Mac |publisher=Sunday Express |date=27 June 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other early influences included [[The Everly Brothers]].

==Early music==
Christine studied sculpture at an art college in Birmingham for five years, with the goal of becoming an art teacher. During that time she met a number of budding musicians in Britain's blues scene.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Her first foray into the music field didn't come until she met two friends, [[Stan Webb]] and [[Andy Silvester]] in a pub one night. At the time, they were playing in a band called &quot;Sounds Of Blue&quot; which had a few dates booked, but no bass guitarist. Knowing that Christine had musical talent, they asked her to join.&lt;ref name=&quot;perfect&quot;&gt;[http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=1027&amp;c=2 Disc Magazine (11/08–15/1969), Who's Perfect?]&lt;/ref&gt; Also during that time she would often sing with [[Spencer Davis]]. After five years, Christine graduated from art college with a teaching degree, but by that time &quot;Sounds of Blue&quot; had split up.

Fresh out of art college, Christine found that she did not have enough money to launch herself into the art world, so she moved to London, where she worked briefly as a department store [[window dresser]].&lt;ref name=&quot;perfect&quot;/&gt;

===Chicken Shack===
In 1967, a friend told her that her ex-band mates Andy Silvester and Stan Webb were forming a blues band and were looking for a pianist, so she wrote to them asking to join them. A few days later they replied, inviting her to play keyboards/piano and sing background vocals in their band [[Chicken Shack]]. Chichen Shack's first record release was &quot;It's okay with me baby&quot; written and featuring Christine.&lt;ref name=&quot;perfect&quot;/&gt; Christine stayed with Chicken Shack for two albums. It was in that combo that her genuine feel for the blues became evident, not only in her [[Sonny Thompson]]-style piano playing, but in her soft, low alto which rendered the songs and standards she did sing authentic.&lt;ref&gt;Fleetwood Mac, by Steve Clarke, Proteus Books, 1984, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  In fact, Chicken Shack scored the British hit &quot;[[I'd Rather Go Blind]]&quot; with Christine on lead vocals.&lt;ref&gt;Fleetwood Mac, by Steve Clarke, Proteus Books, 1984, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; She was given a [[Melody Maker]] award for female vocalist for both 1969 and 1970 respectively, and she was lauded for having one of the &quot;top 10 pairs of legs in all of Britain&quot;. Christine left Chicken Shack in 1969 after meeting Fleetwood Mac bassist John McVie.

==Fleetwood Mac==
{{BLP unsourced section|date=August 2010}}
Christine was a fan of Fleetwood Mac at the time, and while touring with Chicken Shack the two bands would often run into each other. They were also stablemates at [[Blue Horizon]], and Fleetwood Mac had asked Christine to play piano as a session musician for Peter Green's songs on the band's second album, ''Mr. Wonderful''.&lt;ref&gt;Mike Vernon's CD Booklet, Fleetwood Mac: The Complete Blue Horizon Sessions 1967-1969, Chapter 2&lt;/ref&gt;

Encouraged to continue her career, she recorded a solo album, ''[[Christine Perfect (album)|Christine Perfect]]''; following her success as a member of Fleetwood Mac, the album was reissued under the name ''The Legendary Christine Perfect Album''. After marrying Fleetwood Mac bass guitarist John McVie, she joined the band in 1970. She had already contributed backup vocals and painted the cover for ''[[Kiln House]]''. The band had just lost founding member [[Peter Green (musician)|Peter Green]], and its members were nervous about touring without him. Christine had been a huge fan of the Peter Green-era Fleetwood Mac, and since she knew all the lyrics to their songs, she went along.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=1048&amp;c=2 |title=Goldmine Magazine 1992 interview}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christine McVie quickly became an essential member of the group and the author of some of its finest songs, over the course of nearly 25 years. {{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

The early 1970s was a rocky time for the band, with a revolving door of musicians, and only the albums ''[[Bare Trees]]'' and ''[[Mystery to Me]]'' scoring any successes.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Furthermore, a group impersonating Fleetwood Mac was touring the United States without their permission.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

In 1974, Christine reluctantly agreed to move with the rest of the band to the US and make a fresh start. Within a year, [[Stevie Nicks]] and [[Lindsey Buckingham]] of [[Buckingham Nicks]] joined the band, giving it an added dimension. Their first album together, 1975's ''[[Fleetwood Mac (1975 album)|Fleetwood Mac]]'', had several hit songs, with Christine's &quot;[[Over My Head (Fleetwood Mac song)|Over My Head]]&quot; and &quot;[[Say You Love Me]]&quot;, both reaching [[Billboard magazine|Billboard]]'s top-20 singles chart. It was &quot;Over My Head&quot; which first put Fleetwood Mac on American radio and into the national Top 20.&lt;ref&gt;Fleetwood Mac, by Steve Clarke, Proteus Books, 1984, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1976, Christine began an on-the-road affair with the band's lighting director,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=208&amp;c=18 |title=Five Go Mad |publisher=Uncut Magazine |date=May 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; which inspired her to write &quot;[[You Make Loving Fun]]&quot;, a top-10 hit on the landmark smash ''[[Rumours]]'', one of the best-selling albums of all-time. Her biggest hit was &quot;[[Don't Stop (Fleetwood Mac song)|Don't Stop]]&quot;, which climbed all the way to #3. The ''Rumours'' tour also included Christine's &quot;Songbird&quot;, a ballad played as the encore of many Fleetwood Mac concerts.

By the end of the ''Rumours'' tour, the McVies had divorced. The 1979 double album ''[[Tusk (album)|Tusk]]'' produced three more US top-20 hits (&quot;Tusk&quot;, which is also the band's first &quot;conceptual&quot; music video,{{Citation needed|date=April 2011}} &quot;Sara&quot;, and Christine's &quot;Think About Me&quot;), but it came nowhere near to matching the success of the ''Rumours'' album.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=13&amp;c=2 |title=Mac's McVie: Rumours Fly About Fleetwood Mac's Christine McVie--And That's No Mirage |publisher=''[[US Magazine]]'' |date=September 25, 1982}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Tusk'' tour continued into 1980, after which, the band took time apart. They reunited in 1981 to record the album ''[[Mirage (Fleetwood Mac album)|Mirage]]'' at a château in France. The album, released in 1982, returned the band to the top of the US charts and also contained the top-5 hit &quot;[[Hold Me (Fleetwood Mac song)|Hold Me]]&quot;, co-written by Christine. Christine's inspiration for the song was her tortured relationship with [[Beach Boys]] member [[Dennis Wilson]].&lt;ref&gt;Fleetwood, Mick &amp; Stephen Davis. ''My Life and Adventures in Fleetwood Mac.'' Avon Books, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;  Her song, &quot;Love in Store&quot;, became the third single from the album peaking at #22 in early 1983.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

In 1984, Christine decided to record another solo album. She created hits with the songs &quot;[[Got a Hold on Me]]&quot; (Top 10 pop and #1 [[adult contemporary]]) and &quot;Love Will Show Us How&quot; (#30). Christine is quoted in ''The Billboard Book of Number One Adult Contemporary Hits'' as saying of her solo album, &quot;Maybe it isn't the most adventurous album in the world, but I wanted to be honest and please my own ears with it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Connelly, Christopher. &quot;From British Blues with Chicken Shack to Soft Rock with Fleetwood Mac: Christine McVie Keeps a Level Head after Two Decades in the Fast Lane.&quot; Rolling Stone, June 7, 1984, @ http://bla.fleetwoodmac.net/index.php?page=index_v2&amp;id=1046&amp;c=2&lt;/ref&gt;

She also met keyboardist Eddy Quintela (12 years her junior), whom she married on October 18, 1986. Quintela would go on to co-write many songs with her that would be featured on subsequent Fleetwood Mac albums. The couple divorced in the mid-1990s.

After covering the [[Elvis Presley]] standard &quot;[[Can't Help Falling in Love]]&quot; for the [[Ted Danson]] / [[Howie Mandel]] film ''[[A Fine Mess]]'', she rejoined Fleetwood Mac to record the ''[[Tango in the Night]]'' album, which went on to become the band's biggest success since ''Rumours'' ten years earlier. The biggest hit from the album which was top 5 in both the UK and US, was Christine's &quot;Little Lies&quot;, co-written with her husband Quintela. Another McVie single from the album, &quot;Everywhere&quot;, reached #4 in the UK, which would be the band's third highest ever chart peak there and their final top 40 UK hit to date (the single peaked at #14 in the US).&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chartstats.com/artistinfo.php?id=841 Fleetwood Mac UK singles positions at Chart Stats]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1990, the band (now without Lindsey Buckingham) recorded ''[[Behind the Mask (album)|Behind the Mask]]'', but the sales were considerably lower than previous albums and the singles were only marginally successful.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} The album did however, enter the UK album chart at #1, but there were no UK hits from the album and only Christine's song &quot;Save Me&quot; made the US Top 40. The second US single release from the album, Christine's &quot;Skies the Limit&quot;, was a flop, never even making the Hot 100. Christine had always been reluctant to go on concert tours, preferring to stay close to home with friends and family.{{Citation needed|date=October 2010}} Upon the death of her father, Cyril Perfect, while she was touring for ''Behind the Mask'', Christine made the decision to retire from touring altogether.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Despite the departure of Stevie Nicks, Christine remained loyal to Mick Fleetwood and her former husband, recording five songs for the band's 1995 effort ''[[Time (Fleetwood Mac album)|Time]]''.

The members of the band seemed to have gone their separate ways until Mick Fleetwood, John McVie, and Lindsey Buckingham got together again for one of Lindsey Buckingham's solo projects. Christine McVie was soon asked to sing and play on some of the tracks. Once 4/5 of the Rumours-era band was reunited, the members decided a reunion was possible. Stevie Nicks was called out of premature retirement and the resulting live album, 1997's ''[[The Dance (album)|The Dance]]'', went to #1 in the US album charts. Despite her reservations,{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Christine complied with the band's touring schedule, and then performed for the group's 1998 induction into the [[Rock and Roll Hall of Fame]], as well as the Grammy Awards show, and the [[BRIT Awards]] in the UK. Thereafter, she retired from Fleetwood Mac altogether.

In 2006, [[Paste (magazine)|''Paste'' magazine]] named McVie, together with bandmates [[Lindsey Buckingham]] and [[Stevie Nicks]], as the 83rd greatest living songwriter or songwriting team.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pastemagazine.com/articles/2006/06/pastes-100-best-living-songwriters-the-list.html &quot;Paste's 100 Best Living Songwriters: The List&quot;] June 8, 2006, Paste Magazine&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life after Fleetwood Mac==
In the years after ''The Dance'', Christine returned to England to be near her family and stepped out of public view almost completely, although in 2000 she appeared in public to receive an [[Honorary Doctorate]] in Music from the [[University of Greenwich]], England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://w3.gre.ac.uk/pr/releasearchive/464.htm] &quot;FLEETWOOD MAC STAR, CHRISTINE McVIE,
AWARDED HONORARY DEGREE AT ROCHESTER CATHEDRAL&quot;, July 20, 2000, University of Greenwich press release&lt;/ref&gt; Sometime after leaving Fleetwood Mac, she and Quintela divorced. In a 2004 interview, she admitted to not listening much to pop music anymore and instead prefers [[Classic FM (UK)|Classic FM]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2004/jun/18/1 | work=The Guardian | location=London | title=Surviving the Fleetwoods | first=Will | last=Hodgkinson | date=2004-06-18 | accessdate=2010-04-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|subject= Christine McVie |interviewer= Amy Scott |title= In The Meantime interview, part 4/6 |type= |url= http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-inZpp2c76c |format= |program= [[All Star Jams]] |callsign= |city= |date= |year= 2004 |month= |accessdate= 2010-10-07 |archiveurl= |archivedate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2003, she went to see Fleetwood Mac's last UK performance on the ''Say You Will'' tour in London, but did not join her former bandmates on the stage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite interview|subject= Christine McVie |interviewer= Amy Scott |title= In The Meantime interview, part 3/6 |type= |url= http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B6p2MQ55hz0 |format= |program= [[All Star Jams]] |callsign= |city= |date= |year= 2004 |month= |accessdate= 2010-10-07 |archiveurl= |archivedate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mid-2004 saw the release of Christine's new solo album, ''[[In the Meantime (album)|In the Meantime]]'', her third in a career spanning five decades. Recorded in her converted barn in Kent, Christine worked on the project with her nephew, Dan Perfect, who contributed guitar-playing, backing vocals, and songwriting. There was no tour to accompany this album, though Christine consented to a limited number of press interviews in the UK and the US. In 2006, Christine was awarded the [[British Academy of Songwriters, Composers and Authors]]' Gold Badge of Merit at a ceremony held in London's [[Savoy Hotel]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bmi.com/news/entry/335047 Christine McVie Honored With Gold Badge Award] October 30, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

Once again, in November 2009, Christine went to see Fleetwood Mac's last UK performance on their ''Unleashed'' tour in London, but did not join her former bandmates on the stage.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

==Discography==
===With Fleetwood Mac===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|Year
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Album
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|[[United States|U.S.]] [[Billboard 200]]
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|[[UK Albums Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 205}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Additional information
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1968
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Mr. Wonderful (album)|Mr. Wonderful]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|10
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|First Fleetwood Mac album to feature Christine McVie as a session musician. According to Mike Vernon, Producer, Christine played piano on all of Peter Green's songs, whereas Jeremy Spencer played piano on his own.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1969
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Then Play On]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|192
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|6
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Christine McVie featured as a session musician on this album.  Although piano appears on a few of the tracks it is not clear if it was played by Christine or Jeremy.  Christine has said she contributed background vocals to the album.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1970
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Kiln House]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|69
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|39
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Christine McVie created the album art and duetted vocals with Danny Kirwan on &quot;Station Man&quot; (uncredited but audible).  While Jeremy Spencer is credited with all keyboard parts on the album, Christine may have played the electric keyboard on &quot;Tell Me All the Things You Do&quot;.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1971
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Future Games]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|91
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|First album with Christine McVie as a full member of Fleetwood Mac.  She contributed and sang two songs.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1972
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Bare Trees]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|70
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Included McVie's &quot;Spare Me A Little Of Your Love&quot; and &quot;Homeward Bound&quot;.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1973
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Penguin (album)|Penguin]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|49
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| McVie's &quot;Remember Me&quot; and &quot;Did You Ever Love Me&quot; were selected as singles but neither charted.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1973
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Mystery to Me]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|68
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|- Contains four McVie songs, on which she sings lead vocals, and a lead vocal on one of Welch's.  Her voice is also featured prominently in the mix on Welch's tunes &quot;Somebody,&quot; &quot;Miles Away,&quot; &quot;Emerald Eyes&quot; and &quot;Hypnotized&quot;.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1974
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Heroes Are Hard to Find]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|34
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|McVie's title track was selected as the album's only single. It did not chart.  She contributed and sang four songs.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1975
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Fleetwood Mac (1975 album)|Fleetwood Mac]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|23
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|First album with Stevie Nicks &amp; Lindsey Buckingham. Christine McVie's own &quot;Over My Head&quot; became Fleetwood Mac's first radio hit in the US, peaking at #20 on the Billboard Hot 100. Her &quot;Say You Love Me&quot; was also a Top 20 record.  &quot;Warm Ways&quot; was selected as the album's first single but did not chart.  The uptempo blues, &quot;Sugar Daddy&quot; has never been performed live.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1977
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Rumours]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| Featured Christine's biggest charting single with Fleetwood Mac—&quot;Don't Stop&quot; — coming in at #3 on the US Charts. It also included her &quot;You Make Lovin' Fun&quot;, which made the US Top Ten.  Christine's signatures tune, &quot;Oh Daddy&quot; and &quot;Songbird&quot;, are also included.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1979
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Tusk (album)|Tusk]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|4
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| Featured her &quot;Think About Me&quot;, which hit #20 on Billboard in 1980.  Peter Green added some guitar to McVie's &quot;Brown Eyes&quot;
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1980
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Live (Fleetwood Mac album)|Live]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|14
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|31
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Featured a new Christine McVie song—&quot;One More Night&quot;
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1982
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Mirage (Fleetwood Mac album)|Mirage]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|5
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| Featured Christine McVie's &quot;Hold Me&quot; (US#4) and &quot;Love in Store&quot; (US#22).
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1987
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Tango in the Night]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|7
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Included Christine McVie standards &quot;Little Lies&quot; (UK#5, US#4), &quot;Everywhere&quot; (UK#4, US#14), and &quot;Isn't It Midnight&quot; (UK#60).
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1988
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Greatest Hits (1988 Fleetwood Mac album)|Greatest Hits]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|14
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|3
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Featured two new songs including Christine McVie's &quot;[[As Long as You Follow]]&quot; which peaked at #43 on Billboard's Hot 100, #15 on its Rock chart, and #1 on Adult Contemporary
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1990
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Behind the Mask (album)|Behind the Mask]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|18
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| Christine McVie's &quot;Save Me&quot; reached the US Top 40 in 1990. McVie stopped touring with Fleetwood Mac after the Behind The Mask tour was complete
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1995
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Time (Fleetwood Mac album)|Time]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|47
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|The last studio release with Christine McVie as a full-time member.  &quot;I Do&quot; was released as a single but failed to chart. 
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1997
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[The Dance (album)|The Dance]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|15
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;| Christine McVie participated in her final tour with Fleetwood Mac and retired from the group thereafter.  &quot;Temporary One&quot; was released as a single but failed to chart.
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|2003
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Say You Will]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|3
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|6
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Christine McVie was credited as an additional musician. She played keyboards and provided background vocals on &quot;Bleed to Love Her&quot; and &quot;Steal Your Heart Away&quot;.
|}

===Solo albums===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|Year
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Album
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|U.S. [[Billboard 200]]
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|[[UK Albums Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums 2&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 341}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Additional information
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1970
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Christine Perfect (album)|Christine Perfect]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Featured a cover version of Fleetwood Mac's &quot;When You Say&quot;
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1984
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[Christine McVie (album)|Christine&lt;br&gt;McVie]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|26
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|58
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Featured Christine McVie's biggest charting single outside Fleetwood Mac—&quot;Got A Hold On Me&quot; coming in at #10 on the US charts
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|2004
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[In the Meantime (album)|In the Meantime]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|133
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Christine McVie co-produced this album with her nephew Dan Perfect.  &quot;Friend&quot; reached #29 on the Adult Contemporary Chart.
|}

===With Chicken Shack===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|Year
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Album
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|U.S. [[Billboard 200]]
!align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;40&quot;|[[UK Albums Chart]]&lt;ref name=&quot;British Hit Singles &amp; Albums 3&quot;&gt;{{Cite book
| first= David
| last= Roberts
| year= 2006
| title= British Hit Singles &amp; Albums
| edition= 19th
| publisher= Guinness World Records Limited
| location= London
| isbn= 1-904994-10-5
| page= 104}}&lt;/ref&gt;
!align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|Additional information
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1968
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[40 Blue Fingers, Freshly Packed and Ready to Serve]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|12
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|-
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|1969
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|''[[O.K. Ken?]]''
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|align=&quot;center&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|9
|align=&quot;left&quot; valign=&quot;top&quot;|-
|}

===Singles===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! Year
! Song
! width=&quot;40&quot;|&lt;small&gt;[[Billboard Hot 100|U.S. Hot 100]]&lt;/small&gt;
! width=&quot;40&quot;|&lt;small&gt;[[Hot Adult Contemporary Tracks|U.S. A/C]]&lt;/small&gt;
! Album
|-
| 1969
| &quot;[[When You Say]]&quot;
| &lt;center&gt;-
| &lt;center&gt;-
| ''Christine Perfect''
|-
| 1984
| &quot;[[Got a Hold on Me]]&quot;
| &lt;center&gt;10
| &lt;center&gt;1
| ''Christine McVie''
|-
| 1984
| &quot;[[Love Will Show Us How]]&quot;
| &lt;center&gt;30
| &lt;center&gt;32
| ''Christine McVie''
|-
| 2004
| &quot;Friend&quot;
| &lt;center&gt;-
| &lt;center&gt;29
| ''In the Meantime''
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[{{Allmusic|class=artist|id=p19273|pure_url=yes}} AMG Entry for Christine McVie]
*[http://fleetwoodmac.net/penguin/chris.htm Extensive bio, links to charts, discography]

{{Fleetwood Mac}}
{{Grammy Award for Album of the Year 1970s}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Macvie, Christine
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =12 July 1943
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =Bouth
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Macvie, Christine}}
[[Category:1943 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Alumni of the University of Greenwich]]
[[Category:English contraltos]]
[[Category:English female singers]]
[[Category:English singer-songwriters]]
[[Category:English keyboardists]]
[[Category:Female rock singers]]
[[Category:Fleetwood Mac members]]
[[Category:People from Birmingham, West Midlands]]
[[Category:People from Ulverston]]
[[Category:E1 Music artists]]
[[Category:Musicians from Birmingham, West Midlands]]
[[Category:British rhythm and blues boom musicians]]
[[Category:British rhythm and blues singers]]

[[cs:Christine McVie]]
[[cy:Christine McVie]]
[[da:Christine McVie]]
[[de:Christine McVie]]
[[eo:Christine McVie]]
[[fr:Christine McVie]]
[[it:Christine McVie]]
[[nl:Christine Perfect]]
[[ja:クリスティン・マクヴィー]]
[[pl:Christine McVie]]
[[fi:Christine McVie]]
[[sv:Christine McVie]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
