<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3721191" ns="0" title="AppArmor"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Out of date|article|date=October 2010}}
{{Infobox software
| name                   = AppArmor
| logo                   =
| screenshot             =
| caption                =
| author                 = [[Immunix]]
| developer              = 
| released               = 1998
| latest release version = 2.6.1
| latest release date    = Mar 24, 2011
| latest preview version =
| latest preview date    =
| programming language   = [[C (programming language)|C]], [[Perl]]
| operating system       = [[Linux]]
| platform               =
| language               =
| status                 =
| genre                  = Security
| license                = [[GNU General Public License]]
| website                = https://apparmor.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/Main_Page
}}
'''AppArmor''' (&quot;Application Armor&quot;) is a security module for the [[Linux kernel]], released under the [[GNU General Public License]].   AppArmor allows the system administrator to associate with each program a security profile that restricts the capabilities of that program. It supplements the traditional Unix [[discretionary access control]] (DAC) model by providing [[mandatory access control]] (MAC). It was included as of the 2.6.36 version of the mainline Linux kernel. Since 2009, Canonical contributes to the ongoing AppArmor development.

In addition to manually specifying profiles, AppArmor includes a learning mode, in which violations of the profile are logged, but not prevented. This log can then be turned into a profile, based on the program's typical behavior.

AppArmor is implemented using the [[Linux Security Modules]] (LSM) kernel interface.

AppArmor is offered in part as an alternative to [[Security-Enhanced Linux|SELinux]], which critics consider difficult for administrators to set up and maintain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.linux.com/articles/58942
 | title = Linux.com :: SELinux: Comprehensive security at the price of usability
 | author = Mayank Sharma
 | date=2006-12-11 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike SELinux, which is based on applying labels to files, AppArmor works with file paths. Proponents of AppArmor claim that it is less complex and easier for the average user to learn than SELinux.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | title=Protective armor: Shutting out intruders with AppArmor
 | author=Ralf Spenneberg
 | url=http://www.linux-magazine.com/issues/2006/69/protective_armor
 | date=August 2006
 | accessdate=2008-08-02
 | publisher=Linux Magazine }}&lt;/ref&gt; They also claim that AppArmor requires fewer modifications to work with existing systems:{{Citation needed|date=October 2007}} for example, SELinux requires a filesystem that supports &quot;security labels&quot;, and thus cannot provide access control for files mounted via NFS. AppArmor is filesystem-neutral.

== Other systems ==

{{refimprove|section|date=June 2009}}

AppArmor represents one of several possible approaches to the problem of restricting the actions that installed software may take.

The [[SELinux]] system generally takes a similar approach to AppArmor.  One important difference is that it identifies file system objects by [[inode]] number instead of path.  This means that, for example, a file that is inaccessible may become accessible under AppArmor when a [[hard link]] is created to it, while SELinux would deny access through the newly created hard link.  On the other hand, data that is inaccessible may become accessible under SELinux when applications update the file by replacing it with a new version (a frequently used technique), while AppArmor would continue to deny access to the data.  (In both cases, a default policy of &quot;no access&quot; avoids the problem.)  {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

While there has been considerable debate about which approach is better, there is as yet no strong evidence that either approach is preferable.  Discussion about their relative merits often revolves around which approach is more aligned with existing Unix/Linux access control mechanisms, but Unix and Linux use a combination of path-based and inode-based access control.  Note also that existing access control mechanisms remain in place with either system. {{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

SELinux and AppArmor also differ significantly in how they are administered and how they integrate into the system.

Isolation of processes can also be accomplished by mechanisms like virtualization; the [[One Laptop per Child]] (OLPC) project, for example, sandboxes individual applications in lightweight [[Vserver]].

In 2007, the [[Simplified Mandatory Access Control Kernel]] was introduced.

In 2009, a new solution called [[TOMOYO Linux|Tomoyo]] was included in Linux 2.6.30; like AppArmor, it also uses path-based access control.

=== Availability ===
AppArmor was first used in [[Immunix]] Linux 1998-2003; at the time, AppArmor was known as SubDomain&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://articles.techrepublic.com.com/5100-10878_11-1053405.html
 | title=Immunix System 7: Linux security with a hard hat (not a Red Hat)
 | author=Vincent Danen
 | date=2001-12-17 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.immunix.org/
 | title=Immunix.org: The Source for Secure Linux Components and Platforms
 | author=WireX Communications, Inc.
 | date=2000-11-15 |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20010203215300/http://www.immunix.org/ |archivedate=2001-02-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;, a reference to the ability for a security profile for a specific program to be segmented into different domains, which the program can switch between dynamically.  AppArmor was first made available in SUSE and openSUSE, and was first enabled by default in [[SUSE Linux Enterprise Server]] 10 and in [[openSUSE]] 10.1.

From 2005 through September 2007, AppArmor was maintained by [[Novell]].

AppArmor was first successfully ported/packaged for [[Ubuntu (operating system)|Ubuntu]] in April 2007. AppArmor comes installed by default in Ubuntu 7.10 Gutsy Gibbon, and came as a part of the release of Ubuntu 8.04, protecting only [[Common Unix Printing System|CUPS]] by default. As of Ubuntu 9.04 Jaunty Jackalope more items such as MySQL have installed profiles. AppArmor hardening continued to improve in Ubuntu 9.10 Karmic Koala as it ships with profiles for its guest session, [[libvirt]] virtual machines, the Evince document viewer, and an optional Firefox profile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://wiki.ubuntu.com/SecurityTeam/KnowledgeBase/AppArmorProfiles|title=SecurityTeam/KnowledgeBase/AppArmorProfiles - Ubuntu Wiki|accessdate=9 January 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

AppArmor was integrated into the October 2010, 2.6.36 kernel release&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://lwn.net/Articles/409810
 | title=The 2.6.36 kernel is out
 | author=James Corbet
 | date=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/v2.6/ChangeLog-2.6.36
 | title=Change Log
 | author=Linus Torvalds
 | date=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://kernelnewbies.org/Linux_2_6_36
 | title=Linux 2 6 36
 | author=
 | date=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | url=http://www.linuxplanet.com/linuxplanet/reports/7203/1/
 | title=Linux Kernel 2.6.36 Gets AppArmor
 | author=Sean Michael Kerner
 | date=2010-10-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[Immunix]], the original developers of AppArmor
* [[Linux Intrusion Detection System|Linux Intrusion Detection System (LIDS)]]
* [[Security-Enhanced Linux]]
* [[Systrace]]
* [[Grsecurity]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://wiki.apparmor.net/index.php/Main_Page AppArmor Wiki]
* [http://en.opensuse.org/SDB:AppArmor AppArmor] description from openSUSE.org
* [http://lkml.org/lkml/2006/4/19/199 LKML thread] containing comments and criticism of AppArmor
* [https://wiki.ubuntu.com/AppArmor Apparmor packages for Ubuntu]
* [http://www.linux-magazine.com/issues/2006/69/counterpoint Counterpoint:] Novell and Red Hat security experts face off on AppArmor and SELinux
* http://www.novell.com/linux/security/apparmor/

{{Novell}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Apparmor}}
&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:Linux security software]]
[[Category:Linux kernel features]]
[[Category:Operating system security]]

[[cs:AppArmor]]
[[de:AppArmor]]
[[es:AppArmor]]
[[fr:AppArmor]]
[[it:AppArmor]]
[[ru:AppArmor]]
[[sv:AppArmor]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
