<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="37653" ns="0" title="CBS"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{About|the broadcast network|its parent company|CBS Corporation|other uses of CBS|CBS (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox broadcasting network
|name = CBS Broadcasting Inc. (CBS)
|logo = [[File:CBS logo.svg|200px]]
|type = [[Terrestrial television|Broadcast]] radio network and&lt;br /&gt;television network
|branding = &quot;Only CBS&quot;
|airdate = January 21, 1927 (as United Independent Broadcasters)
|country = United States
|available = National
|founded =
|founder = (as CBS) [[William S. Paley]]
|slogan = ''Only CBS''
|motto = America's Most Watched Network
|market_share =
|license_area =
|broadcast_area =
|area =
|erp =
|owner = [[Independent business|Independent]] (1927–1995)&lt;br /&gt;[[Westinghouse Electric (1886)|Westinghouse Electric (renamed CBS Corp. in 1997)]] (1995–2000)&lt;br /&gt;[[Viacom (1971–2005)|Viacom]] (2000–2005)&lt;br /&gt;[[CBS Corporation]] (2006–present)
|key_people = [[Leslie Moonves]], Chairman of CBS,&lt;br /&gt;[[Nancy Tellem]] (President of CBS Network Television Entertainment)
|foundation =
|launch_date = September 18, 1927 (radio)&lt;br /&gt;July 1, 1941 (television)
|dissolved =
|Picture format = [[480i]] ([[16:9]] [[Standard-definition television|SDTV]])&lt;br /&gt;[[720p]]/[[1080i]] ([[High-definition television|HDTV]])
|former_names = United Independent Broadcasters (1927)&lt;br /&gt;Columbia Phonographic Broadcasting System (1927–1928)&lt;br /&gt;Columbia Broadcasting System (1928–1995 in official usage)
|digital =
|analog =
|servicename1 =
|service1 =
|servicename2 =
|service2 =
|servicename3 =
|service3 =
|servicename4 =
|service4 =
|callsigns =
|callsign_meaning = '''C'''olumbia '''B'''roadcasting '''S'''ystem (former legal name)
|former_callsigns =
|affiliation =
|affiliates =
|groups =
|former_affiliations =
|website = [http://www.cbs.com/ CBS.com]
|footnotes =
}}

'''CBS Broadcasting Inc.''' ('''CBS''') is a major US [[commercial broadcasting]] television network, which started as a radio network. The name is derived from the initials of the network's former name, '''Columbia Broadcasting System'''. The network is sometimes referred to as the &quot;Eye Network&quot; in reference to the shape of the company's logo. It has also been called the &quot;Tiffany Network&quot;, which alludes to the perceived high quality of CBS programming during the tenure of its founder [[William&amp;nbsp;S. Paley]] (1901–90).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iht.com/articles/1995/08/02/cbs_0.php|title=Westinghouse Bids for Role In the Remake : CBS Deal Advances TV's Global Reach}}&lt;/ref&gt;
It can also refer to some of CBS's first demonstrations of [[color television]], which were held in a former [[Tiffany&amp;nbsp;&amp; Co.]] building in New York City in 1950,&lt;ref&gt;According to a ''The New York Times'' piece on November&amp;nbsp;9, 1950, &quot;the first local public demonstrations of color television will be initiated Tuesday by the Columbia Broadcasting System. Ten color receivers are being installed on the ground floor of the former Tiffany building at 401 Fifth Avenue, near Thirty-seventh Street, where several hundred persons can be accommodated for each presentation&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; thus earning it the name &quot;Color broadcasting system&quot; back when such a feat was innovative.{{citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The network has its origins in United Independent Broadcasters Inc., a collection of 16 radio stations that was bought by William&amp;nbsp;S. Paley in 1928 and renamed the Columbia Broadcasting System.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1990/10/28/obituaries/william-s-paley-who-built-cbs-into-a-communications-empire-dies-at-89.html?pagewanted=all|title=William S. Paley, Who Built CBS Into a Communications Empire, Dies at 89|date=October 28, 1990|first=Jeremy|last=Gerard|work=The New York Times |newspaper=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under Paley's guidance, CBS would first become one of the largest radio networks in the United States and then one of the big three American broadcast television networks. In 1974, CBS dropped its full name and became known simply as ''CBS, Inc.'' The [[Westinghouse Electric Corporation]] acquired the network in 1995 and eventually adopted the name of the company it had bought to become ''CBS Corporation''. In 2000, CBS came under the control of [[Viacom]], which coincidentally had begun as a spin-off of CBS in 1971. In late 2005, Viacom split itself and reestablished [[CBS Corporation]] with the CBS television network at its core. CBS Corporation is controlled by [[Sumner Redstone]] through [[National Amusements]], its parent.

== History ==
=== The radio years ===

The origins of CBS date back to January 21, 1927, with the creation of the &quot;United Independent Broadcasters&quot; network in Chicago by New York [[talent agent| talent-agent]] [[Arthur Judson]]. The fledgling network soon needed additional investors though, and the Columbia Phonograph Company, manufacturers of [[Columbia Records]], rescued it in April 1927; as a result, the network was renamed &quot;Columbia Phonographic Broadcasting System&quot;. Columbia Phonographic went on the air on September 18, 1927, with a presentation by the Howard Barlow Orchestra&lt;ref name=bartow&gt;[[Erik Barnouw|Barnouw, Erik]] (1966). ''A Tower in Babel: A History of Broadcasting in the United States to 1933''. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978-0195004748. p. 222
&lt;/ref&gt; from flagship station [[WOR-AM|WOR]] in Newark, New Jersey, and fifteen affiliates.&lt;ref&gt;
''Radio Digest'', September 1927, quoted in: McLeod, Elizabeth (September 20, 2002). [http://members.aol.com/jeff560/cbs.html CBS—In the Beginning]{{dead link|date=June 2011}}, ''History of American Broadcasting''. Retrieved on 2007-01-01. The sixteen stations were
[[WOR (AM)|WOR]] in [[Newark, New Jersey|Newark]];
[[WPHT|WCAU]] in [[Philadelphia]];
[[WARF|WADC]] in [[Akron, Ohio|Akron]];
[[WTVN|WAIU]] in [[Columbus, Ohio|Columbus]];
[[WCAO]] in [[Baltimore]];
[[WPRV|WEAN]] in [[Providence, Rhode Island|Providence]];
[[WFBL]] in [[Syracuse, New York|Syracuse]];
[[WXYT (AM)|WGHP]] in [[Detroit]];
[[WJAS]] in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh]];
[[WKRC (AM)|WKRC]] in [[Cincinnati]];
[[WBEN (AM)|WMAK]] in [[Buffalo, New York|Buffalo-Lockport]];
[[WMAQ (AM)|WMAQ]] in [[Chicago]];
[[WRKO|WNAC]] in [[Boston]];
[[WOWO]] in [[Fort Wayne, Indiana|Fort Wayne]];
[[KMOX (AM)|KMOX]] in [[St. Louis, Missouri|St. Louis]]; and
[[KKAR|KOIL]] in [[Council Bluffs, Iowa]].&lt;/ref&gt;

Operational costs were steep, particularly the payments to AT&amp;T for use of its land lines, and by the end of 1927, Columbia Phonograph wanted out.&lt;ref name=bartow223&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 223&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1928, Judson sold the network to brothers Isaac and Leon Levy, owners of the network's Philadelphia affiliate [[WPHT|WCAU]], and their partner Jerome Louchenheim. None of the three was interested in assuming day-to-day management of the network, so they installed wealthy 26-year-old [[William S. Paley]], scion of a Philadelphia cigar family and in-law of the Levys, as president. With the record company out of the picture, Paley quickly streamlined the corporate name to &quot;Columbia Broadcasting System.&quot;&lt;ref name=bartow223/&gt; He believed in the power of radio advertising since his family's &quot;La Palina&quot; cigars had doubled their sales after young William convinced his elders to advertise on radio.&lt;ref name=bartow224&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; By September 1928, Paley bought out the Louchenheim share of CBS and became its majority owner with 51% of the business.&lt;ref name=berg&gt;[[Laurence Bergreen|Bergreen, Laurence]] (1980). ''Look Now, Pay Later: The Rise of Network Broadcasting''. New York: Doubleday and Co. ISBN 978-0451619662. p. 59. Page numbers in this article refer to the first paperback edition, May 1981&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Turnaround: Paley's first year ====
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:BurnsAndAllenCBS1935.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Vaudevillians Burns and Allen, an early CBS hit before moving to NBC; they returned in time for TV]] --&gt;
During Louchenheim's brief regime, Columbia paid $410,000 to [[Alfred H. Grebe|A.H. Grebe's]] Atlantic Broadcasting Company for a small Brooklyn station, WABC, which would become the network's [[flagship]] station. WABC was quickly upgraded, and the signal relocated to a stronger frequency, 860 [[Hertz|kHz]].&lt;ref name=berg56&gt;Bergreen, p. 56. The station moved to a new frequency, 880&amp;nbsp;kHz, in the FCC's 1941 reassignment of stations; in 1946, WABC was re-named [[WCBS (AM)|WCBS]].&lt;/ref&gt; The physical plant was relocated also—to [[Steinway Hall]] on West 57th Street in Manhattan. It was where much of CBS's programming originated. Other owned-and-operated stations were [[KNX (AM)|KNX]] Los Angeles, [[KCBS (AM)|KCBS]] San Francisco (originally KQW), [[WBBM (AM)|WBBM]] Chicago, [[WPHT|WCAU]] Philadelphia, [[WJSV]] Washington, D.C. (later WTOP, which moved to the FM dial in 2005; the AM facility today is [[WFED]], also a secondary CBS affiliate), [[KMOX]] St. Louis, and [[WCCO (AM)|WCCO]] Minneapolis. These remain the core affiliates of the [[CBS Radio Network]] today, with WCBS still the flagship, and all except WTOP and WFED (both [[Hubbard Broadcasting]] properties) owned by CBS Radio. By the turn of 1929, the network could boast to sponsors of having 47 affiliates.&lt;ref name=berg59&gt;Bergreen, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;

Paley moved right away to put his network on a firmer financial footing. In the fall of 1928, he entered into talks with [[Adolph Zukor]] of [[Paramount Pictures]] who planned to move into radio in response to [[RCA|RCA's]] forays into motion pictures with the advent of talkies.&lt;ref name=berg61&gt;Bergreen, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; The deal came to fruition in September 1929: Paramount got 49 percent of CBS in return for a block of its stock worth $3,800,000 at the time.&lt;ref name=bartow224/&gt; The agreement specified that Paramount would buy that same stock back by March 1, 1932 for a flat $5,000,000, provided CBS had earned $2,000,000 during 1931 and 1932.&lt;ref name=berg61/&gt; For a brief time there was talk that the network might be renamed &quot;Paramount Radio&quot;, but it only lasted a month—the [[Wall Street Crash of 1929|1929 stock market crash]] sent all stock value tumbling. It galvanized Paley and his troops, though: they &quot;had no alternative but to turn the network around and earn the $2,000,000 in two years.... This is the atmosphere in which the CBS of today was born.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg61/&gt; The near-bankrupt movie studio sold its CBS shares back to CBS in 1932; Paramount was in trouble, CBS was not.&lt;ref name=bartow251&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;

In the first year of Paley's watch, CBS's gross earnings more than tripled, going from $1,400,000 to $4,700,000.&lt;ref name=halfirst&gt;[[David Halberstam|Halberstam, David]] (1979). ''[[The Powers That Be (book)|The Powers That Be]]''. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. ISBN 978-7025270212. p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:WmSPaley1939.jpg|thumb|left|Paley's management saw a twentyfold increase in gross income in his first decade]]
Much of the increase was a result of Paley's second upgrade to the CBS business plan—improved affiliate relations. There were two types of program at the time: ''sponsored'' and ''sustaining'', i.e., unsponsored. Rival [[NBC]] paid affiliates for every sponsored show they carried and charged them for every sustaining show they ran.&lt;ref name=bargoldfirst&gt;[[Erik Barnouw|Barnouw, Erik]] (1968). ''The Golden Web: A History of Broadcasting in the United States, 1933–1953''. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978-0195004755. p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; It was onerous for small and medium stations, and resulted in both unhappy affiliates and limited carriage of sustaining programs. Paley had a different idea, designed to get CBS programs emanating from as many radio sets as possible:&lt;ref name=hal25&gt;Halberstam, p. 25&lt;/ref&gt; he would ''give'' the sustaining programs away for free, provided the station would run every sponsored show, and accept CBS's check for doing so.&lt;ref name=bargold57&gt;Barnow, ''Golden'', p. 57&lt;/ref&gt; CBS soon had more affiliates than either [[NBC Red Network|NBC Red]] or [[NBC Blue]].&lt;ref&gt;In 1943, the FCC would force NBC to sell off its Blue network, which thereupon became ABC. Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 190&lt;/ref&gt;

Paley was a man who valued style and taste,&lt;ref name=hal26&gt;Halberstam, pp. 26–27&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1929, once he had his affiliates happy and his company's creditworthiness on the mend, he relocated his concern to sleek, new 485 Madison Avenue, the &quot;heart of the advertising community, right where Paley wanted his company to be&quot;&lt;ref name=berg60&gt;Bergreen, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; and where CBS would stay until its move to [[CBS Building|Black Rock]] in 1965. When his new landlords expressed skepticism about the network and its fly-by-night reputation, Paley overcame their qualms by purchasing a lease for $1,500,000.&lt;ref name=berg60/&gt;

==== 1930s: CBS takes on the Red and the Blue ====
[[File:Kate Smith.jpg|thumb|upright|right|Wholesome Kate Smith, Paley's choice for ''La Palina Hour'', was unthreatening to home and hearth]]
Since NBC was the broadcast arm of radio set manufacturer [[RCA]], its chief [[David Sarnoff]] approached his decisions as both a broadcaster and as a hardware executive; NBC's affiliates had the latest RCA equipment, and were often the best-established stations, or were on &quot;[[clear-channel station|clear channel]]&quot; frequencies. Yet Sarnoff's affiliates were mistrustful of him. Paley had no such split loyalties: his—and his affiliates'—success rose and fell with the quality of CBS programming.&lt;ref name=hal25/&gt;

Paley had an innate, pitch-perfect, sense of entertainment, &quot;a gift of the gods, an ear totally pure,&quot;&lt;ref name=hal26a&gt;Halberstam, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; wrote [[David Halberstam]]. &quot;[H]e knew what was good and would sell, what was bad and would sell, and what was good and would not sell, and he never confused one with another.&quot;&lt;ref name=hal24&gt;Halberstam, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; As the 1930s loomed, Paley set about building the CBS talent stable. The network became the home of many popular musical and comedy stars, among them [[Jack Benny]], (&quot;Your [[Canada Dry]] Humorist&quot;), [[Al Jolson]], [[George Burns]] &amp; [[Gracie Allen]], and [[Kate Smith]], whom Paley personally selected for his family's ''[[La Palina]] Hour'' because she was not the type of woman to provoke jealousy in American wives.&lt;ref name=berg69&gt;Bergreen, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; When, on a mid-ocean voyage, Paley heard a phonograph record of a young unknown crooner, he rushed to the ship's radio room and &quot;cabled&quot; New York to sign [[Bing Crosby]] immediately to a contract for a daily radio show.&lt;ref&gt;Halberstam, p. 26, and Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 273&lt;/ref&gt;

While the CBS prime-time lineup featured music, comedy and variety shows, the daytime schedule was a direct conduit into American homes—and into the hearts and minds of American women; for many, it was the bulk of their adult human contact during the course of the day. CBS time salesmen recognized early on that this intimate connection could be a bonanza for advertisers of female-interest products.&lt;ref name=berg63&gt;Bergreen, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; Starting in 1930, astrologer [[Evangeline Adams]] would consult the heavens on behalf of listeners who sent in their birthdays, a description of their problems—and a box-top from sponsor Forhan's toothpaste.&lt;ref name=bartow240&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 240&lt;/ref&gt; The low-key murmuring of smooth-voiced Tony Wons, backed by a tender violin, &quot;made him a soul mate to millions of women&quot;&lt;ref name=bartow2401&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', pp. 240–241&lt;/ref&gt; on behalf of the [[R. J. Reynolds]] tobacco company, whose cellophane-wrapped [[Camel (cigarette)|Camel]] cigarettes were &quot;as fresh as the dew that dawn spills on a field of clover.&quot;&lt;ref name=bartow241&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 241&lt;/ref&gt; The most popular radio-friend of all was M. Sayle Taylor, ''The Voice Of Experience'', though his name was never uttered on air.&lt;ref name=bartow241/&gt; Women mailed descriptions of the most intimate of relationship problems to The Voice in the tens of thousands per week; sponsors Musterole ointment and Haley's M–O laxative enjoyed sales increases of several hundred percent in just the first month on ''The Voice Of Experience''.&lt;ref name=bartow242&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', p. 242&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Chaplin cbs 1933.jpg|thumb|left|When [[Charlie Chaplin]] finally allowed the world to hear his voice after twenty years of pantomime, he chose CBS air to do it on]]
As the decade progressed, a new genre joined the daytime lineup: serial dramas—soap operas, so named for the products that sponsored them, by way of the ad agencies that actually produced them. Although the form, usually in quarter-hour episodes, proliferated widely in the middle and late 1930s, they all had the same basic premise: that characters &quot;fell into two categories: 1) those in trouble and 2) those who helped people in trouble. The helping-hand figures were usually older.&quot;&lt;ref name=bargol96&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 96&lt;/ref&gt; At CBS, ''[[Just Plain Bill]]'' brought human insight and [[Anacin]] pain reliever into households; ''[[Your Family and Mine]]'' came courtesy of [[Sealtest Dairy]] products; ''[[Bachelor's Children]]'' first hawked Old Dutch Cleanser, then [[Wonder Bread]]; ''[[Aunt Jenny's Real Life Stories]]'' was sponsored by [[Spry Vegetable Shortening]]. ''[[Our Gal Sunday]]'' (Anacin again), ''[[The Romance of Helen Trent]]'' (Angélus cosmetics), ''[[Big Sister (radio)|Big Sister]]'' ([[Rinso]] laundry soap) and many others filled the daytime ether.&lt;ref&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 94n9&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:CBS radio hollywood.JPG|thumb|200px|CBS west coast headquarters reflected its industry stature while hosting its top Hollywood talent]]
Thanks to its daytime and primetime schedules, CBS prospered in the 1930s. In 1935, gross sales were $19,300,000, yielding a profit of $2,270,000.&lt;ref name=bargol62&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; By 1937, the network took in $28,700,000 and had 114 affiliates,&lt;ref name=hal25/&gt; almost all of which cleared 100% of network-fed programming, thus keeping ratings, and revenue, high. In 1938, CBS even acquired the [[American Record Corporation]], parent of its onetime investor [[Columbia Records]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.musicinthemail.com/audiohistoryLP.html LPs historic&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1938, NBC and CBS each opened studios in Hollywood to attract movieland's top talent to their networks – NBC at Radio City on Sunset and Vine, CBS two blocks away at [[CBS Columbia Square|Columbia Square]].&lt;ref name=berg99&gt;Bergreen, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt;

==== CBS launches an independent news division ====
The extraordinary potential of radio news showed itself in 1930, when CBS suddenly found itself with a live telephone connection to a prisoner called &quot;The Deacon&quot; who described, from the inside and in real time, a riot and conflagration at the Ohio State Penitentiary; for CBS, it was &quot;a shocking journalistic coup.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg105&gt;Bergreen, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt; Yet as late as 1934, there was still no regularly scheduled newscast on network radio: &quot;Most sponsors did not want network news programming; those that did were inclined to expect veto rights over it.&quot;&lt;ref name=bargol17&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; There had been a longstanding wariness between radio and the newspapers as well; the papers had rightly concluded that the upstart radio business would compete with them on two counts—advertising dollars and news coverage. By 1933, they fought back, many no longer publishing radio schedules for readers' convenience, or allowing &quot;their&quot; news to be read on the air for radio's profit.&lt;ref name=bargol18&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; Radio, in turn, pushed back when urban department stores, newspapers' largest advertisers and themselves owners of many radio stations, threatened to withhold their ads from print.&lt;ref name=bargol22&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; A short-lived attempted truce in 1933 even saw the papers proposing that radio be forbidden from running news before 9:30&amp;nbsp;am, and then only after 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm—and that no news story could air until it was twelve hours old.&lt;ref name=bargol21&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:CBSNewsRemote1937.jpg|thumb|left|CBS News engineers prepare a remote: Justice Hugo Black's 1937 denial of Klan ties]]
It was in this climate that Paley set out to &quot;enhance the prestige of CBS, to make it seem in the public mind the more advanced, dignified and socially aware network.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg90&gt;Bergreen, p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; He did it through sustaining programming like the [[New York Philharmonic]], the thoughtful drama of [[Norman Corwin]]—and an in-house news division to gather and present news, free of fickle suppliers like newspapers and wire services.&lt;ref name=berg90/&gt; In the fall of 1934, CBS launched its independent news division, shaped in its first years by Paley's vice-president, former ''The New York Times'' man Ed Klauber, and news director [[Paul White (journalist)|Paul White]]. Since there was no blueprint or precedent for real-time news coverage, early efforts of the new division used the short-wave link-up CBS had been using for five years&lt;ref name=bartow2456&gt;Barnouw, ''Tower'', pp. 245–246&lt;/ref&gt; to bring live feeds of European events to its American air.

A key early hire was [[Edward R. Murrow]] in 1935; his first corporate title was Director of Talks. He was mentored in microphone technique by [[Robert Trout]], the lone full-timer of the News Division, and quickly found himself in a growing rivalry with boss White.&lt;ref name=berg107&gt;Bergreen, p. 107&lt;/ref&gt; Murrow was glad to &quot;leave the hothouse atmosphere of the New York office behind&quot;&lt;ref name=berg109&gt;Bergreen, p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; when he was dispatched to London as CBS's European Director in 1937, a time when the growing [[Hitler]] menace underscored the need for a robust European Bureau. Halberstam described Murrow in London as &quot;the right man in the right place in the right era.&quot;&lt;ref name=hal38&gt;Halberstam, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt; Murrow began assembling the staff of broadcast journalists—including [[William L. Shirer]], [[Charles Collingwood (journalist)|Charles Collingwood]] and [[Eric Sevareid]]—who would become known as &quot;[[Murrow's Boys]]&quot;. They were &quot;in [Murrow's] own image, sartorially impeccable, literate, often liberal, and prima donnas all.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg110&gt;Bergreen, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; They covered history in the making, and sometimes made it themselves: on March 12, 1938, Hitler boldly annexed nearby [[Anschluss|Austria]] and Murrow and Boys quickly assembled coverage with Shirer in London, [[Edgar Ansel Mowrer]] in Paris, [[Pierre Huss]] in Berlin, [[Frank Gervasi]] in Rome and Trout in New York.&lt;ref name=bargol78&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[CBS World News Roundup|News Round-Up]]'' format was born and is still ubiquitous today in broadcast news.

Murrow's nightly reports from the rooftops during the dark days of the [[The Blitz|London Blitz]] galvanized American listeners: even before [[Pearl Harbor attack|Pearl Harbor]], the conflict became &quot;the story of the survival of Western civilization, the most heroic of all possible wars and stories. He was indeed reporting on the survival of the English-speaking peoples.&quot;&lt;ref name=hal39&gt;Halberstam, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; With his &quot;manly, tormented voice,&quot;&lt;ref name=berg112&gt;Bergreen, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; Murrow contained and mastered the panic and danger he felt, thereby communicating it all the more effectively to his audience.&lt;ref name=berg112/&gt; Using his trademark self-reference &quot;This reporter&quot;,&lt;ref name=bargol140&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 140&lt;/ref&gt; he did not so much report news as interpret it, combining simplicity of expression with subtlety of nuance.&lt;ref name=berg112/&gt; Murrow himself said he tried &quot;to describe things in terms that make sense to the truck driver without insulting the intelligence of the professor.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg112/&gt; When he returned home for a visit late in 1941, Paley threw an &quot;extraordinarily elaborate reception&quot;&lt;ref name=berg114&gt;Bergreen, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt; for him at the [[Waldorf-Astoria]]. Of course, its goal was more than just honoring CBS's latest &quot;star&quot;—it was an announcement to the world that Mr. Paley's network was finally more than just a pipeline carrying other people's programming: it was now a cultural force in its own right.&lt;ref name=berg1145&gt;Bergreen, pp. 114–115&lt;/ref&gt;

Once the war was over and Murrow returned for good, it was as &quot;a superstar with prestige and freedom and respect within his profession and within his company.&quot;&lt;ref name=hal40&gt;Halberstam, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; He possessed enormous capital within that company, and as the unknown form of television news loomed large, he would spend it freely, first in radio news, then in television, taking on Senator [[Joseph McCarthy]] first, then eventually William S. Paley himself,&lt;ref name=bargol276&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; and with a foe that formidable, even the vast Murrow account would soon run dry.

==== Panic: ''The War of the Worlds'' radio broadcast ====
[[File:Orson Welles 1937.jpg|thumb|upright|right|''Enfant terrible'' Orson Welles's &quot;Hallowe'en joke&quot; frightened the country and snared a sponsor]]
On October 30, 1938, CBS gained a taste of infamy when [[Orson Welles]] and the ''[[Mercury Theatre|Mercury Theatre on the Air]]'' broadcast a [[The War of the Worlds (radio)|radio adaptation]] of [[H. G. Wells|H. G. Wells's]] ''[[The War of the Worlds]]''. Its unique format, a contemporary version of the story in the form of ''faux'' news broadcasts, had many CBS listeners panicked into believing invaders from [[Mars]] were actually devastating [[Grover's Mill, New Jersey]], despite three disclaimers during the broadcast that it was a work of fiction. The flood of publicity after the broadcast had two effects: an FCC ban on ''faux'' news bulletins within dramatic programming, and sponsorship for ''Mercury Theatre on the Air''—the former sustaining program became ''[[The Campbell Playhouse]]'' to sell soup.&lt;ref name=bargol88&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; Welles, for his part, summarized the episode as &quot;the ''Mercury Theater's'' own radio version of dressing up in a sheet and jumping out of a bush and saying 'Boo!'&quot;&lt;ref name=berg96&gt;Bergreen, p. 96&lt;/ref&gt;

==== CBS recruits Edmund A. Chester ====
Before the onset of World War II, CBS recruited [[Edmund Albert Chester, Sr.|Edmund A. Chester]] from his position as Bureau Chief for Latin America at [[Associated Press]] to serve as Director of Latin American Relations and Director of Short Wave Broadcasts for the CBS radio network (1940). In this capacity, Mr. Chester coordinated the development of the Network of the Americas (La Cadena de las Americas) with the [[United States Department of State|Department of State]], the [[Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs|Office for Inter-American Affairs]] (as chaired by [[Nelson Rockefeller]]) and [[Voice of America]]. This network provided vital news and cultural programming throughout South America and Central America during the crucial World War II era and fostered diplomatic relations between the United States of America and the less developed nations of the continent. It featured such popular radio broadcasts as ''[[Viva América]]''&lt;ref&gt;[http://radiogoldindex.com/cgi-local/p2.cgi?ProgramName=Viva+America Copyright 2011 J. David Goldin&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; which showcased leading musical talent from both North and South America accompanied by the CBS Pan American Orchestra under the musical direction of [[Alfredo Antonini]]. The post war era also marked the beginning of CBS's dominance in the field of radio as well.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/C/htmlC/columbiabroa/columbiabroa.htm|title=Columbia Broadcasting System}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== 1940s: Zenith of network radio ====
As 1939 wound down, Bill Paley announced that 1940 would &quot;be the greatest year in the history of radio in the United States.&quot;&lt;ref name=bargol139&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 139&lt;/ref&gt; He was right—times ten: the decade of the 1940s would indeed be the apogee of network radio by every gauge. Nearly 100% of 1939's advertisers renewed their contracts for 1940; manufacturers of farm tractors made radios standard equipment on their machines.&lt;ref name=bargol138&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; Wartime rationing of paper limited the size of newspapers—and hence advertisers—and when papers turned them away, they migrated to radio sponsorship.&lt;ref name=bargol165&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 165&lt;/ref&gt; A 1942 act of Congress made advertising expenses a tax benefit&lt;ref name=bargol165/&gt; and that sent even automobile and tire manufacturers—who had no products to sell since they had been converted to war production—scurrying to sponsor symphony orchestras and serious drama on radio.&lt;ref name=bargol166&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; In 1940, only one-third of radio programs were sponsored, while two-thirds were sustaining; by mid-decade, the statistics had swapped—now two out of three shows had cash-paying sponsors and only one-third were sustaining.&lt;ref name=berg167&gt;Bergreen, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;

The CBS of the 1940s was vastly different from that of the early days; many of the old guard veterans had died, retired or moved on.&lt;ref name=berg168&gt;Bergreen, p.168&lt;/ref&gt; No change was greater than that in Paley himself: he had become difficult to work for, and had &quot;gradually shifted from leader to despot.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg168/&gt; He spent much of his time seeking social connections and in cultural pursuits; his &quot;hope was that CBS could somehow learn to run itself.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg168/&gt; His brief to an interior designer remodeling his townhouse included a requirement for closets that would accommodate three hundred suits, one hundred shirts and had special racks for a hundred neckties.&lt;ref name=hal31&gt;Halberstam, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:FrankStantonCBSPrez.jpg|thumb|right|Dr. Frank Stanton, second only to Paley in his impact on CBS, president 1946–1971]]
As Paley grew more remote, he installed a series of buffer executives who sequentially assumed more and more power at CBS: first Ed Klauber, then Paul Kesten, and finally [[Frank Stanton]]. Second only to Paley as the author of CBS's style and ambitions in its first half-century, Stanton was &quot;a magnificent mandarin who functioned as company superintendent, spokesman, and image-maker.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg169&gt;Bergreen, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; He had come to the network in 1933 after sending copies of his PhD thesis &quot;A Critique Of Present Methods and a New Plan for Studying Radio Listening Behavior&quot; to CBS top brass and they responded with a job.&lt;ref name=berg170&gt;Bergreen, p. 170&lt;/ref&gt; He scored an early hit with his study &quot;Memory for Advertising Copy Presented Visually vs. Orally&quot; which CBS salesmen used to great effect bringing in new sponsors.&lt;ref name=berg170/&gt; In 1946 Paley named Stanton President of CBS and promoted himself to Chairman. Stanton's colorful, but impeccable, wardrobe—slate-blue pinstripe suit, ecru shirt, robin's egg blue necktie with splashes of saffron—made him, in the mind of one sardonic CBS vice-president, &quot;the greatest argument we have for color television.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg171&gt;Bergreen, p. 171&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the influx of advertisers and their cash, or perhaps because of them, the 1940s were not without bumps for the radio networks. The biggest challenge came in the form of the FCC's ''chain broadcasting investigation''—the &quot;monopoly probe&quot;, as it was often called.&lt;ref name=bargol168&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; Though started in 1938, it only gathered steam in 1940 under new-broom chairman [[James L. Fly]].&lt;ref name=bargol1689&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden, pp. 168–169&lt;/ref&gt; By the time the smoke had cleared in 1943, NBC found itself shorn of its Blue network, which became [[Citadel Media#WJZ/NBC Blue Network|ABC]]. CBS was also hit, though not as severely: Paley's brilliant 1928 affiliate contract which had given CBS first claim on local stations' air during sponsored time—the ''network option''—came under attack as being restrictive to local programming.&lt;ref name=bargol171&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 171&lt;/ref&gt; The final compromise permitted the network option for three out of four hours during certain dayparts, but the new regulations had virtually no practical effect, since most all stations accepted the network feed, especially the sponsored hours that earned them money.&lt;ref name=bargol171/&gt; Fly's panel also forbade networks from owning artists' representation bureaus, so CBS sold its bureau to [[Music Corporation of America]] and it became Management Corporation of America.&lt;ref name=bargol172&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 172&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:GodfreyCBS1938.jpg|thumb|upright|Arthur Godfrey spoke directly to listeners individually, making him a foremost pitchman into TV era]]

On the air, the war had an impact on most every show. Variety shows wove patriotism through their comedy and music segments; dramas and soaps had characters join the service and go off to fight. Even before hostilities commenced in Europe, one of the most played songs on radio was [[Irving Berlin|Irving Berlin's]] &quot;[[God Bless America]]&quot;, popularized by CBS's own Kate Smith.&lt;ref name=bargol155&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; Although an Office of Censorship sprang up within days of [[Pearl Harbor attack|Pearl Harbor]], censorship would be totally voluntary. A few shows submitted scripts for review; most did not.&lt;ref name=bargol156&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; The guidelines that the Office did issue banned weather reports, including announcement of sports rainouts, news about troop, ship or plane movements, war production and live man-on-the-street interviews. The ban on ad-libbing caused quizzes, game shows and amateur hours to wither for the duration.&lt;ref name=bargol156/&gt;

Surprising was &quot;the granite permanence&quot; of the shows at the top of the ratings.&lt;ref name=bargol284&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 284&lt;/ref&gt; The vaudevillians and musicians who were huge after the war were the same stars who had been huge in the 30s: Benny, Crosby, Burns and Allen, Edgar Bergen all had been on the radio almost as long as there had ''been'' network radio.&lt;ref name=bargol285&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; A notable exception to this was relative newcomer [[Arthur Godfrey]] who, as late as 1942, was still doing a local morning show in Washington, D.C.&lt;ref name=berg179&gt;Bergreen, p. 179&lt;/ref&gt; Godfrey, who had been a cemetery-lot salesman and a cab driver, pioneered the style of talking directly to the listener as an ''individual'', with a singular &quot;you&quot; rather than phrases like &quot;Now, folks...&quot; or &quot;Yes, friends...&quot;.&lt;ref name=berg180&gt;Bergreen, p. 180&lt;/ref&gt; His combined shows contributed as much as 12% of ''all'' CBS revenues; by 1948, he was pulling down a half-million dollars a year.&lt;ref name=berg179/&gt;

In 1947, Paley, still the undisputed &quot;head talent scout&quot; of CBS,&lt;ref name=berg169/&gt; led a much-publicized &quot;talent raid&quot; on NBC. One day, while [[Freeman Gosden]] and [[Charles Correll]] were hard at work at NBC writing their venerable [[Amos and Andy]] show, a knock came on the door; it was Paley himself, with an astonishing offer: &quot;Whatever you are getting now I will give you twice as much.&quot;&lt;ref name=berg181&gt;Bergreen, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; Capturing NBC's cornerstone show was ''coup'' enough, but Paley repeated in 1948 with longtime NBCers [[Edgar Bergen]] and [[Charlie McCarthy]] and [[Red Skelton]], as well as former CBS defectors [[Jack Benny]], radio's top-rated comedian, and [[Burns and Allen]]. Paley achieved this rout with a legal agreement reminiscent of his 1928 contract that caused some NBC station affiliates to jump ship and join CBS:&lt;ref name=berg181/&gt; CBS would buy the stars' names as a property, in exchange for a large lump sum and a salary.&lt;ref name=bargol245&gt;Barnouw, p. 245&lt;/ref&gt; The plan relied on the vastly different tax rates between income and capital gains, so not only would the stars enjoy more than twice their income after taxes, but CBS would preclude any NBC counterattack because CBS owned the performers' names.&lt;ref name=berg181/&gt;
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:JackBennyPubPhoto.jpg|thumb|left|Jack Benny came back to CBS Radio; within months he would be on CBS-TV]] --&gt;
As a result of this sortie, Paley got in 1949 something he had sought for twenty years: CBS finally beat NBC in the ratings.&lt;ref name=berg183&gt;Bergreen, p. 183&lt;/ref&gt;

But it wasn't just to one-up rival Sarnoff that Paley led his talent raid; he, and all of radio, had their eye on the coming force that threw a shadow over radio throughout the 1940s—television.

==== 1950s: Prime time radio gives way to television ====
In the spring of 1940, CBS staff engineer [[Peter Carl Goldmark|Peter Goldmark]] devised a system for [[color television]] that CBS management hoped would leapfrog the network over NBC and its existing black-and-white RCA system.&lt;ref name=berg153&gt;Bergreen, p. 153. Goldmark also invented the 33-1/3 r.p.m. microgroove Long-Play phonograph record that made the RCA-Victor 78s quickly obsolete.&lt;/ref&gt; The CBS system &quot;gave brilliant and stable colors,&quot; while NBC's was &quot;crude and unstable but 'compatible.'&quot;&lt;ref name=bargol243&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;  Ultimately, the FCC rejected the CBS system because it was incompatible with RCA's; that, and the fact that CBS had moved to secure many UHF, not VHF, TV licenses, left CBS flatfooted in the early television age.&lt;ref name=berg1557&gt;Bergreen, pp. 155–157. Shortly after ruling in favor of NBC, FCC chairman Charles Denny resigned from the FCC to become vice president and general counsel of NBC: Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; In 1946, only 6,000 TV sets were in operation, all in greater New York; by 1949, the number was 3,000,000, and by 1951, 12,000,000.&lt;ref name=berg1589&gt;Bergreen, pp. 158–159&lt;/ref&gt; Sixty-four American cities had TV stations, though most of them only had one.&lt;ref name=bargol295&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;

Radio continued to be the backbone of the company, at least in the ''early'' 1950s, but it was &quot;a strange, twilight period.&quot;&lt;ref name=bargol285/&gt; NBC's venerable [[Fred Allen]] saw his ratings plummet when he was pitted against upstart ABC's game show ''Stop The Music!''; within weeks, he was dropped by longtime sponsor [[Ford Motor Company]] and was shortly gone from the scene.&lt;ref name=bargol2878&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', pp. 287–288&lt;/ref&gt; Radio powerhouse [[Bob Hope]]'s ratings plunged from 23.8 in 1949 to 5.4 in 1953.&lt;ref name=bargol288&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 288&lt;/ref&gt; By 1952, &quot;death seemed imminent for network radio&quot; in its familiar form;&lt;ref name=bargol290&gt;Barnouw, ''Golden'', p. 290&lt;/ref&gt; most telling of all, the big sponsors were eager for the switch.

Gradually, as the television network took shape, radio stars began to migrate to the new medium. Many programs ran on both media while making the transition. The radio soap opera ''[[Guiding Light|The Guiding Light]]'' moved to television in 1952 and ran another fifty-seven years; Burns &amp; Allen, back &quot;home&quot; from NBC, made the move in 1950; [[Lucille Ball]] a year later; ''[[Our Miss Brooks]]'' in 1952 (though it continued simultaneously on radio for its full television life). The high-rated [[Jack Benny Program]] ended its radio run in 1955, and Edgar Bergen's Sunday-night show went off the air in 1957. When CBS announced in 1956 that its radio operations had lost money, while the television network had made money,&lt;ref name=berg230&gt;Bergreen, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; it was clear where the future lay. When the soap opera [[Ma Perkins]] went off the air November 25, 1960 only eight, relatively minor series remained. Prime time radio ended on September 30, 1962, when ''[[Yours Truly, Johnny Dollar]]'' and ''[[Suspense (radio program)|Suspense]]'' aired for the final time.&lt;ref name=dun742&gt;[[John Dunning (writer)|Dunning, John]] (1998). ''On The Air: The Encyclopedia of Old-Time Radio''. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-507678-8, p. 742&lt;/ref&gt;

==== CBS's radio programming after 1972 ====
The retirement of [[Arthur Godfrey]] in April 1972 marked the end of the longform program on CBS radio; programming thereafter consisted of hourly news summaries and news features, known in the 1970s as ''Dimension'', and commentaries, including the ''Spectrum'' series that evolved into the &quot;Point/Counterpoint&quot; feature on the television network's ''60 Minutes'' and ''First Line Report'', a news and analysis feature delivered by CBS correspondents. The network also continued to offer traditional radio programming through its nightly ''[[CBS Radio Mystery Theater]]'', the lone holdout of old-style programming, from 1974 through 1982.&lt;ref name=dun143&gt;Dunning, p. 143&lt;/ref&gt; The [[CBS Radio Network]] continues to this day, offering hourly newscasts, including its centerpiece ''[[CBS World News Roundup]]'' in the morning and evening, weekend sister program ''[[CBS News Weekend Roundup]]'', the news-related feature segment ''[[Charles Osgood|The Osgood File]]'', ''What's In the News'', a one-minute summary of one story, and various other segments such as commentary from Seattle radio personality [[Dave Ross]], tip segments from various other sources, and technology coverage from [[CBS Interactive]] property [[CNET]]. It is the last of the Big Four radio networks to be an autonomous company; ABC was broken up in 2007 while Mutual and NBC were bought by [[Westwood One]] in the 1980s (Westwood One and CBS were under common ownership from 1993 to 2007).

=== The television years: expansion and growth ===
CBS's first television broadcasts were experimental, often only for one hour a day, and reaching a limited area in and around New York City (over station W2XAB channel 2, later called WCBW and finally WCBS-TV). To catch up with rival RCA, CBS bought Hytron Laboratories in 1939, and immediately moved into set production and television broadcasting. Though there were many competing patents and systems, RCA dictated the content of the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC's]] technical standards, and grabbed the spotlight from CBS, [[DuMont Television Network|DuMont]] and others by introducing television to the general public at the [[1939 New York World's Fair]]. The FCC began licensing commercial television stations on July 1, 1941; the first license went to RCA and NBC's WNBT (now [[WNBC]]); the second license, issued that same day, was to WCBW, (now [[WCBS-TV|WCBS]]). CBS-Hytron offered a practical color system in 1941, but it was not compatible with the black-and-white standards set down by RCA. In time, and after considerable dithering, the FCC rejected CBS's technology in favor of that by RCA.

During the World War II years, commercial television broadcasting was reduced dramatically. Toward the end of the war, commercial television began to ramp up again, with an increased level of programming evident in the 1945–1947 period on the three New York television stations which operated in those years (the local stations of NBC, CBS and DuMont) But as RCA and DuMont raced to establish networks and offer upgraded programming, CBS lagged, advocating an industry-wide shift and re-start to UHF for their incompatible (with black and white) color system. Only in 1950, when NBC was dominant in television and black and white transmission was widespread, did CBS begin to buy or build their own stations (outside of New York) in Los Angeles, Chicago and other major cities. Up to that point, CBS programming was seen on such stations as [[KTTV]] Channel 11 in Los Angeles, which CBS—as a bit of insurance and to guarantee program clearance in Los Angeles—quickly purchased a 50% interest in, partnering with the [[Los Angeles Times]] newspaper. CBS then sold their interest in KTTV (which today is the West Coast flagship of the [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] network) and purchased outright Los Angeles pioneer station KTSL (Channel 2) in 1950, renaming it KNXT (after CBS's existing Los Angeles radio property, KNX), later to become [[KCBS-TV]]. The &quot;talent raid&quot; on NBC of the mid-forties had brought over established radio stars; they now became stars of CBS television as well. One reluctant CBS star refused to bring her radio show, &quot;My Favorite Husband&quot;, to television unless the network would re-cast the show with her real-life husband in the lead. Paley and network president [[Frank Stanton]] had so little faith in the future of [[Lucille Ball]]'s series, re-dubbed ''[[I Love Lucy]]'', that they granted her wish and allowed the husband, [[Desi Arnaz]], to take financial control of the production. This was the making of the Ball-Arnaz [[Desilu Productions|Desilu]] empire, and became the template for series production to this day.

In the late 1940s, CBS offered the first live television coverage of the proceedings of the [[United Nations General Assembly]] (1949). This journalistic tour-de-force was under the direction of [[Edmund Albert Chester, Sr.|Edmund A. Chester]], who was appointed to the post of Director for News, Special Events and Sports at CBS Television in 1948.

As television came to the forefront of American entertainment and information, CBS dominated television as it once had radio. {{Citation needed|date=April 2009}} In 1953, the CBS television network would make its first profit,&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museum.tv/archives/etv/P/htmlP/paleywillia/paleywillia.htm|title=Paley, William S}}&lt;/ref&gt; and would maintain dominance on television between the years 1955 and 1976 as well&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt; By the late 1950s, the network often controlled seven or eight of the slots on the &quot;top ten&quot; ratings list with well-respected shows like ''[[Route 66 (TV series)|Route 66]]''. This success would continue for many years, with CBS bumped from first place only by the rise of [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]] in the mid-1970s. Perhaps because of its status as the top-rated network, during the late 1960s and early 1970s CBS felt freer to gamble with controversial properties like the ''[[Smothers Brothers|Smothers Brothers Comedy Hour]]'' and ''[[All in the Family]]'' and its many spinoffs during this period.

[[Image:CBS color.svg|200px|right|thumb|CBS &quot;Eye&quot; Logo in 1965, displayed before shows presented in color]]

One of CBS's most popular shows at that time was ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', a [[Comedy-drama|dramedy]] based on the hit [[Robert Altman]] film. It ran from 1972–1983, and was set, like the [[MASH (film)|film]], during the Korean War in a Mobile Army Surgical Hospital. The final episode aired on February 28, 1983 and was 2½ hours long. It was viewed by nearly 106&amp;nbsp;million Americans (77% of viewership that night) which established it as the most watched episode in United States television history, a record which stood until the broadcast of [[Super Bowl XLIV]] in 2010, also on CBS.

==== Color telecasts (1953–1965) ====
Although CBS-TV was the first with a working color television system, they lost out to [[RCA]] in 1953, due in part because the CBS color system was incompatible with existing black-and-white sets. Although RCA, then-parent company of [[NBC]], made its color system available to CBS, the network was not interested in boosting RCA's profits and televised only a few specials in color for the rest of the decade. The specials included the ''[[Ford Star Jubilee]]'' programs (which included the first telecast ever of MGM's 1939 film classic ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]''). Other specials were also shown: the 1957 telecast of [[Rodgers and Hammerstein]]'s ''[[Cinderella (musical)|Cinderella]]'', [[Aladdin (TV special)|Cole Porter's musical version of ''Aladdin'']], and ''[[Playhouse 90]]'''s only color broadcast, the 1958 production of ''[[The Nutcracker]]'', featuring choreography by [[George Balanchine]]. This telecast was based on the famous production staged annually since 1954 in New York, and performed by the New York City Ballet. CBS would later show two other versions of the ballet, a semi-forgotten one-hour German-American version hosted by [[Eddie Albert]] ,shown annually for three years beginning in 1965, and the well-loved [[Mikhail Baryshnikov|Baryshnikov]] production from 1977 to 1981. (This production later moved to PBS.)

Beginning in 1959, ''The Wizard of Oz'', now telecast by CBS as a family special in its own right (after the cancellation of ''Ford Star Jubilee''), became an annual tradition on color TV.
However, it was the success of NBC's 1955 telecast of the musical [[Peter Pan (1954 musical)|''Peter Pan'']], starring [[Mary Martin]], the most watched television special of its time, that inspired CBS to telecast ''The Wizard of Oz'', ''Cinderella'' and ''Aladdin''.

===== 1960–1967 =====
From 1960 to 1965, CBS-TV limited its color transmissions to only a few specials such as ''The Wizard of Oz'', and only then if the sponsor would pay for it. [[Red Skelton]] was the first CBS host to telecast his weekly programs in color, using a converted movie studio, in the early 1960s; he tried unsuccessfully to persuade the network to use his facility for other programs, then was forced to sell it. Color was being pushed hard by rival NBC. Even ABC had several color programs, beginning in the fall of 1962, but those were limited because of the network's financial and technical situations. One famous CBS-TV special made during this era was the [[Charles Collingwood (journalist)|Charles Collingwood]]-hosted tour of the [[Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis#White House restoration|White House with First Lady Jackie Kennedy]]. It was, however, shown in black-and-white. Beginning in 1963, at least one CBS show, ''[[The Lucy Show]]'', began filming in color at its star and producer [[Lucille Ball]]'s insistence; she realized that color episodes would command more money when they were eventually sold into syndication, but even it was broadcast in black and white through the end of the 1964–65 season. This would all change by the mid-1960s, when market pressure forced CBS-TV to add color programs to the regular schedule for the 1965–66 season and complete the changeover during the 1966–67 season. By the fall of 1967, nearly all of CBS's TV programs were in color, as were NBC's and ABC's. A notable exception was ''[[Twentieth Century (TV series)|Twentieth Century]]'', which consisted mostly of newsreel archival footage, though even this program used at least some color footage by the late 1960s.

In 1965, CBS telecast a new color version of Rodgers and Hammerstein's ''Cinderella''. This version, starring [[Lesley Ann Warren]] and [[Stuart Damon]] in the roles formerly played by [[Julie Andrews]] and [[Jon Cypher]], was shot on videotape rather than being telecast live, and would become an annual tradition for the next nine years.

In 1967, NBC outbid CBS for the rights to the annual telecast of ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'' and the film moved to NBC. However, the network quickly realized their mistake in allowing what was then one of its prime ratings winners to be acquired by another network, and by 1976, the film was back on CBS, where it remained through the end of 1997. CBS showed it twice in 1991, in March and again the night before Thanksgiving. Thereafter, it was shown the night before Thanksgiving.

==== 1971–86: The &quot;Rural purge&quot; and success in the 1970s ====
{{Main|Rural purge}}
By the end of the 1960s, CBS was broadcasting virtually all of its schedule in color, but many of its shows (including ''[[The Beverly Hillbillies]]'', ''[[Mayberry R.F.D.]]'', ''[[Petticoat Junction]]'', ''[[Hee Haw]]'' and ''[[Green Acres]]'') were appealing more to older and more rural audiences and less to the young, urban and more affluent audiences that advertisers sought to target. [[Fred Silverman]] (who would later head ABC, then NBC) made the decision to cancel most of those otherwise hit shows by mid-1971 in what became colloquially referred to as the &quot;[[Rural Purge]]&quot;, with ''Green Acres'' star [[Pat Buttram]] remarking that the network cancelled &quot;anything with a tree in it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kenberry.com/ken_berry_interview.htm|title=Ken Berry interview}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last1=Harkins |first1=Anthony |title=Hillbilly: A Cultural History of an American Icon |accessdate=March 23, 2009 |year=2005|publisher=Oxford University Press US|isbn=0195189507|page=203|url=http://books.google.com/?id=dtehLu1cissC&amp;pg=PA203&amp;lpg=PA203&amp;dq=CBS+cancelled+everything+with+a+tree+in+it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the &quot;rural&quot; shows got the axe, new hits, like ''[[The Mary Tyler Moore Show]]'', ''[[All in the Family]]'', ''[[M*A*S*H (TV series)|M*A*S*H]]'', ''[[The Bob Newhart Show]]'', &lt;!--''[[The Waltons]]'', - - - this is not a rural show? --&gt;''[[Cannon (TV series)|Cannon]]'', ''[[Barnaby Jones]]'', ''[[Kojak]]'' and ''[[The Sonny &amp; Cher Comedy Hour]]'' took their place and kept CBS at the top of the ratings through the early '70s. The majority of these hits were overseen by then East Coast vice president [[Alan Wagner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NYT&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| url=http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/22/arts/22wagner.html?_r=2&amp;pagewanted=print|title=Alan Wagner, 76, First President of the Disney Channel, Is Dead |work=The New York Times|first=Dennis|last=Hevesi| date=December 22, 2007 | accessdate=June 22, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also, ''[[60 Minutes]]'' moved to 7&amp;nbsp;pm ET on Sundays in 1976 and became an unexpected hit. {{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}

Silverman also first developed his strategy of spinning new shows off an established hit while at CBS, with ''[[Rhoda]]'' and ''[[Phyllis (TV series)|Phyllis]]'' spun from ''The Mary Tyler Moore Show'', ''[[Maude (TV series)|Maude]]'' and ''[[The Jeffersons]]'' spun from ''All in the Family'' and ''[[Good Times]]'' from ''Maude''.

After Silverman's departure, CBS dropped behind ABC in the 1976–77 season, but still rated strongly, based on its earlier hits and some new ones: ''[[One Day at a Time]]'', ''[[Alice (TV series)|Alice]]'', ''[[WKRP in Cincinnati]]'', ''[[The Dukes of Hazzard]]'' (suspiciously &quot;rural&quot;) and, the biggest hit of the early '80s, ''[[Dallas (TV series)|Dallas]]''.

By 1982, ABC had run out of steam, NBC was in dire straits with many failed programming efforts greenlighted by Silverman during his 1978 to 1981 tenure there, and CBS once more nosed ahead, courtesy of ''Dallas'' (and its spin-off ''[[Knots Landing]]''), ''[[Falcon Crest]]'', ''[[Magnum, P.I.]]'', ''[[Simon &amp; Simon]]'' and ''60 Minutes''. CBS also [[College Basketball on CBS|broadcast]] the popular [[NCAA Men's Division I Basketball Tournament]] every March beginning in 1982 (taking over for [[College Basketball on NBC|NBC]]). There were a few new hits – ''[[Kate &amp; Allie]]'', ''[[Newhart]]'', ''[[Cagney &amp; Lacey]]'', ''[[Scarecrow and Mrs. King]]'', ''[[Murder, She Wrote]]'' – but the resurgence was short-lived. CBS had gone deeply into debt as a result of the failed effort by Ted Turner to take control over CBS. The battle was headed by CBS chairman Thomas Wyman. CBS sold its St. Louis station KMOX-TV and allowed the purchase of a large portion of its shares (under 25 percent) by Loew’s Inc. chairman Lawrence Tisch. Consequently, collaboration between Paley and Tisch led to the slow dismissal of Wyman, Tisch becoming chief operating officer, and Paley returning as chairman.&lt;ref&gt;Sterling, C. H., &amp; Kittross, J. M. (1990). Stay Tuned: A concise history of American broadcasting (2nd ed.). Belmont, CA:Wadsworth.&lt;/ref&gt;

==== 1986–2002: Tiffany Network in distress ====
In 1984, ''[[The Cosby Show]]'' and ''[[Miami Vice]]'' debuted on NBC and grabbed high ratings immediately, bringing that network back to first place by the 1985–1986 season along with other huge hits ''[[Family Ties]]'', ''[[The Golden Girls]]'', ''[[LA Law]]'', and ''227''. ABC had in turn also rebounded with hits like ''[[Dynasty (TV series)|Dynasty]]'', ''[[Who's the Boss?]]'', ''[[Hotel (TV series)|Hotel]]'', and ''[[Growing Pains]]''. By the 1988–1989 season, CBS had fallen to third place behind both ABC and NBC, and had some major rebuilding to do.

Ironically, some of the groundwork had been laid as the network fell in the ratings, with hits ''Simon &amp; Simon'', ''Falcon Crest'', ''Murder, She Wrote'', ''Kate &amp; Allie'' and ''Newhart'' still on the schedule from the most recent resurgence, and future hits ''[[Designing Women]]'', ''[[Murphy Brown]]'', ''[[Jake and the Fatman]]'', and ''[[48 Hours (TV series)|48 Hours]]'' having recently debuted. Plus, CBS was still getting decent ratings from ''60 Minutes'', ''Dallas'' and ''Knots Landing''. But the ratings for ''Dallas'' were a far cry from what they were in the early 1980s. During the early 1990s, the network would bolster its sports lineup by adding [[Major League Baseball on CBS|Major League Baseball]] telecasts and the [[Olympics on CBS|Winter Olympics]].

Under network president Jeff Sagansky, the network was able to get strong ratings from new shows ''[[Diagnosis: Murder]]'', ''[[Touched by an Angel]]'', ''[[Dr. Quinn, Medicine Woman]]'', ''[[Walker, Texas Ranger]]'', and a resurgent ''[[Jake and the Fatman]]'' during this period, and CBS was able to reclaim the first place crown briefly, in the 1992–1993 season, though its demographics skewed older than ABC, NBC or even Fox, with its relatively limited presence at that time. In 1993, the network made a breakthrough in establishing a successful late night talk show franchise to compete with NBC's ''[[Tonight Show]]'' when it signed [[David Letterman]] away from NBC after the ''Late Night'' host was passed over as [[Johnny Carson]]'s successor on ''Tonight'' in favor of [[Jay Leno]]. However, CBS' would soon suffer a major blow in a move that would change American television forever.

In 1993, the fledgling [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] network outbid CBS for the rights to air the [[National Football League]], resulting in several stations switching to Fox. The loss of the NFL, along with an ill-fated effort to court younger viewers, led to a drop in CBS' ratings. The network also dropped its MLB coverage (after losing approximately US$500&amp;nbsp;million over a four year span) in 1993 and NBC, which already aired the Summer Olympics, took over coverage of the Winter Olympics beginning with the [[2002 Winter Olympics|2002 Games]].

Still, CBS was able to produce some hits, such as ''[[Cosby]]'', ''[[The Nanny (TV series)|The Nanny]]'', and ''[[Everybody Loves Raymond]]'', and would regain the NFL (taking over the [[American Football Conference]] package from [[NFL on NBC|NBC]]) in 1998.

==== 2002–present: Return to top spot, rivalry with Fox ====
Another turning point for CBS came in the summer of 2000 when it debuted the summer reality shows ''[[Survivor (U.S. TV series)|Survivor]]'', and ''[[Big Brother (US)|Big Brother]]'' which became surprise summer hits for the network. In January 2001, CBS debuted the second season of the show after its airing of the Super Bowl and scheduled it Thursdays at 8&amp;nbsp;pm ET, and moved the police procedural ''[[CSI: Crime Scene Investigation|CSI]]'' (which had debuted that fall Fridays at 9&amp;nbsp;pm ET) to Thursdays at 9&amp;nbsp;pm ET and was both able to chip away at and eventually beat NBC's Thursday night lineup, and attract younger viewers to the network.

CBS has had additional successes with police procedurals ''[[Cold Case (TV series)|Cold Case]]'', ''[[Without a Trace]]'', ''[[Criminal Minds]]'', ''[[NCIS (TV series)|NCIS]]'', and ''[[The Mentalist]]'', along with ''CSI'' spinoffs ''[[CSI: Miami]]'' and ''[[CSI: NY]]'', and sitcoms ''[[Everybody Loves Raymond]]'', ''[[The King of Queens]]'', ''[[Mike &amp; Molly]]'', ''[[Two and a Half Men]]'', ''[[How I Met Your Mother]]'', ''[[The Big Bang Theory]]'' and ''[[The New Adventures of Old Christine]]''.

During the 2007–08 season, Fox ranked as the top-rated network, primarily due to its reliance on ''[[American Idol]]''. However, according to [[Nielsen ratings|Nielsen]], CBS ended up as the top-rated network for the 2008–2009 and 2009–2010 seasons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://tvlistings.zap2it.com/ratings/network.html|title=Nielsen Television (TV) Ratings: Network Primetime Averages}}&lt;/ref&gt; The two tend to nearly equal one another in the 18–34, 18–49, and 25–54 demographics, although Fox typically wins these by the narrowest of margins.

=== The conglomerate ===
During the 1960s, CBS began an effort to diversify, and looked for suitable investments. In 1965, it acquired electric guitar maker [[Fender Musical Instruments Corporation|Fender]] from [[Leo Fender]], who agreed to sell his company due to health problems. The purchase also included that of [[Rhodes piano|Rhodes]] electric pianos, which had already been acquired by Fender. This and other acquisitions led to a restructuring of the corporation into various operating groups and divisions; the quality of the products coming out of these acquired companies was extremely lower, hence the term &quot;pre-CBS&quot; (meaning higher, sought after quality) and &quot;CBS&quot; (mass produced lower quality).

In other diversification attempts, CBS would buy (and later sell) sports teams (especially the [[New York Yankees]] baseball club), book and magazine publishers ([[Fawcett Publications]] including [[Woman's Day]], and [[Holt McDougal|Holt, Rinehart and Winston]]), map-makers, toy manufacturers (Gabriel Toys, Child Guidance, Wonder Products), and other properties.

As William Paley aged, he tried to find the one person who could follow in his footsteps. However, numerous successors-in-waiting came and went. By the mid-1980s, the investor [[Laurence Tisch]] had begun to acquire substantial holdings in CBS. Eventually he gained Paley's confidence, and with his support took control of CBS in 1986.

Tisch's sole interest was turning profits. When CBS faltered, under-performing units were given the axe. Among the first properties to go was the [[Columbia Records]] group, which had been part of the company since 1938. Tisch also shut down in 1986 the [[CBS Laboratories|CBS Technology Center]] in [[Stamford, Connecticut|Stamford]], which had started in New York City in the 1930s as CBS Laboratories and evolved to be the company's technology Research and development unit.

==== Columbia Records ====
{{main|Columbia Records}}
Columbia Records was a record label owned by CBS since 1938. In 1962, CBS launched CBS Records to market Columbia recordings outside North America, where the Columbia name was controlled by others. In 1966, CBS Records was made a separate subsidiary of Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |date=June 18, 1966 |title=Lieverson to Helm Group; Other Changes Made in the CBS Guard |journal=Billboard |pages=1, 10 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=0igEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false |accessdate=February 16, 2011 |author1=Nielsen Business Media |first1=Inc }}&lt;/ref&gt; CBS sold the CBS Records Group to the Japanese conglomerate [[Sony]] in 1988 initiating the Japanese buying spree of US companies ([[MCA Inc.|MCA]], [[Pebble Beach Golf Links|Pebble Beach]] Co., [[Rockefeller Center]], [[Empire State Building]], et al.) that continued into the 1990s. The record label company was re-christened [[Sony Music Entertainment]] in 1991, as Sony had a short term license on the CBS name.

Sony purchased from [[EMI]] its rights to the Columbia Records name outside the US, Canada, Spain and Japan. Sony now uses Columbia Records as a label name in all countries except Japan, where Sony Records remains their flagship label. Sony acquired the Spanish rights when Sony Music merged with [[Bertelsmann]] subsidiary [[Bertelsmann Music Group|BMG]] in 2004 as [[Sony BMG]], co-owned by Sony and Bertelsmann. Sony bought out BMG's share in 2008.

[[CBS Corporation]] revived [[CBS Records]] in 2006.

==== Publishing ====
CBS entered the publishing business in 1967 by acquiring [[Henry Holt and Company|Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston]], who published trade books, textbooks, and the magazine ''[[Field &amp; Stream]]''. The next year, CBS added the medical publisher [[Saunders (publisher)|Saunders]] to Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston. In 1971, CBS acquired Bond/Parkhurst, the publisher of ''[[Road &amp; Track]]'' and ''[[Cycle World]]''.

CBS greatly expanded its magazine business by purchasing [[Fawcett Publications]] in 1974, bringing in such magazines as ''Woman's Day''. It acquired the majority of the [[Ziff Davis]] publications in 1984.

CBS sold its book publishing businesses in 1985. The educational publishing division, which retained the name Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston, was sold to [[Harcourt (publisher)|Harcourt Brace Jovanovich]]; the trade book division, renamed [[Henry Holt and Company]], was sold to the West German publisher [[Georg von Holtzbrinck Publishing Group|Holtzbrinck]].

CBS exited the magazine business by selling the unit to its executive [[Peter Diamandis]]. Diamandis sold the magazines to [[Hachette Filipacchi Médias]] in 1988, forming [[Hachette Filipacchi Media U.S.]]

==== CBS Musical Instruments division ====
Forming the CBS Musical Instruments division, the company also acquired [[Steinway &amp; Sons|Steinway]] pianos, [[Gemeinhardt]] flutes, [[Lyon &amp; Healy]] harps, [[Rodgers Instruments|Rodgers]] (institutional) organs, Gulbransen home organs, Electro-Music Inc. ([[Leslie speaker]]s), and [[Rogers Drums]]. The last musical purchase was the 1981 acquisition of the assets of then-bankrupt [[ARP Instruments, Inc.|ARP Instruments]], developer of electronic synthesizers.

Between 1965 and 1985 the quality of Fender guitars and amplifiers declined significantly. Encouraged by outraged Fender fans, CBS Musical Instruments division executives executed a leveraged buyout in 1985 and created [[Fender Musical Instruments Corporation|FMIC]], the Fender Musical Instrument Corporation. At the same time, CBS divested itself of Rodgers, along with Steinway and Gemeinhardt, all of which were purchased by Steinway Musical Properties. The other musical instruments properties were also liquidated.

==== Film production ====
{{Main|CBS Films}}
CBS made a brief, unsuccessful move into film production in the late 1960s, creating [[Cinema Center Films]]. This profit-free unit was shut down in 1972; today the distribution rights to the Cinema Center library rest with Paramount Pictures for home video (via [[CBS Home Entertainment]]) and theatrical release, and with CBS Paramount Television for TV distribution (most other ancillary rights remain with CBS). It released such films as ''[[The Reivers (film)|The Reivers]]'' (1969), starring [[Steve McQueen]], and the musical ''[[Scrooge (1970 film)|Scrooge]]'' (1970), starring [[Albert Finney]].

Yet ten years later, in 1982, CBS took another try at Hollywood, in a joint venture with [[Columbia Pictures]] and [[HBO]] called [[TriStar Pictures]]. Despite releasing such box office successes as ''[[The Natural]]'', ''[[Places in the Heart]]'', and ''[[Rambo: First Blood Part II]]'', CBS felt the studio was not making a profit and in 1985, sold its stake in TriStar to [[The Coca-Cola Company]], Columbia Pictures' owner at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1985/11/16/business/cbs-sells-stake-in-tri-star-inc.html|title=CBS Sells Stake In Tri-Star Inc. – NY Times.com| work=The New York Times | date=November 16, 1985}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, CBS Corp. announced its desire to get back into the feature film business slowly launching CBS Films and hiring key executives in the Spring of 2008 to startup the new venture. The name CBS Films was actually used once before in 1953 when the name was briefly used for CBS's distributor of off-network and first-run syndicated programming to local TV stations in the United States and abroad.

==== Home video ====
CBS entered into the home video market, when joined with MGM to form [[MGM/CBS Home Video]] in 1978, but the joint venture was broken by 1982. CBS joined another studio: [[20th Century Fox]], to form [[CBS/Fox Video]]. CBS's duty was to release some of the movies by [[TriStar Pictures]] under the [[CBS/Fox Video]] label.

==== Gabriel Toys ====
CBS entered the video game market briefly, through its acquisition of Gabriel Toys (renamed CBS Toys), publishing several arcade adaptations and original titles under the name &quot;CBS Electronics&quot;, for the [[Atari 2600]], and other consoles and computers, also producing one of the first karaoke recording/players. CBS Electronics also distributed all [[Coleco]]-related video game products in Canada, including the [[ColecoVision]]. CBS later sold Gabriel Toys to [[View-Master]], which eventually ended up as part of [[Mattel]].

==== Venture to the UK ====
On September 14, 2009, it was revealed that the international arm of CBS, [[CBS Studios International]], struck a joint venture deal with [[Chellomedia]] to launch six CBS-branded channels in the UK during 2009. The new channels would replace [[Zone Romantica (UK)|Zone Romantica]], [[Zone Thriller]], Zone Horror and [[Zone Reality (UK)|Zone Reality]], plus timeshift services Zone Horror +1 and Zone Reality +1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://newsroom.zonemedia.net/Scripts/FileDownload.asp?fPath=D%3A%5CWWW%5FDomains%5CZONE%5FPRESS%5CFiles%5CPress%5CCBS+FINALChello+Zone+partnership+press+release%2Edoc|title=CBS FINALChello Zone partnership press release|format=DOC|publisher=Chello Zone|date=September 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadcastnow.co.uk/news/international/cbs-to-launch-uk-channels-with-chellomedia/5005560.article|title=CBS to launch UK channels with Chellomedia|publisher=Broadcastnow|date=September 14, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On October 1, 2009, it was announced that [[CBS Reality]], CBS Reality +1, CBS Drama and [[CBS Action]] would launch on November 16, 2009 replacing Zone Reality, Zone Reality +1, Zone Romantica and Zone Thriller respectively.&lt;ref name=broadcastnow&gt;{{cite web |first=Chris |last=Curtis |url=http://www.broadcastnow.co.uk/news/international/cbs-channels-to-launch-in-uk/5006298.article |title=CBS channels to launch in UK |publisher=Broadcastnow |date=October 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On April 5, 2010, Zone Horror and Zone Horror +1 were rebranded as [[Horror Channel]] and Horror Channel +1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.broadbandtvnews.com/2010/03/31/zone-horror-rebrands-as-horror-channel/|title=Zone Horror rebrands as Horror Channel|publisher=Broadband TV News|date=March 31, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New owners ===
By the early 1990s, profits had fallen as a result of competition from cable companies, video rentals, and the high cost of programming. About 20 former CBS affiliates switched to the rapidly rising [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox Television Network]] in the mid 1990s, while many television markets across the country (e.g. [[KDFX-CA|KDFX]] in [[Palm Springs, California]] and [[KECY-TV|KECY]] in [[Yuma, Arizona]] reportedly the first to do so in August 1994) lost their CBS affiliate for awhile. CBS ratings were acceptable, but the network struggled with an image of stodginess. Laurence Tisch lost interest and sought a new buyer.
[[Image:Ed sullivan theater.jpg|thumb|right|230px|CBS's [[Ed Sullivan Theater]] in Manhattan, home to the ''[[Late Show with David Letterman]]'']]

==== Westinghouse Electric Corporation ====
In 1995, [[Westinghouse Electric Corporation]] acquired CBS for $5.4&amp;nbsp;billion. As one of the major broadcasting group owners of commercial radio and television stations (as [[Westinghouse Broadcasting|Group W]]) since 1920, Westinghouse sought to transition from a station operator into a major media company with its purchase of CBS. This was followed in 1997 with the $4.9-billion purchase of [[Infinity Broadcasting Corporation]], owner of more than 150 radio stations. Also that year, Westinghouse began the CBS Cable division by acquiring two existing cable channels ([[Gaylord Entertainment Company|Gaylord's]] [[The Nashville Network]] and [[Country Music Television]]) and starting a new one (CBS Eye on People, which was later sold to [[Discovery Communications]]).

Following the Infinity purchase, operation and sales responsibilities for the [[CBS Radio Network]] was handed to Infinity, which turned management over to [[Westwood One]], a company Infinity managed. WWO is a major radio program syndicator that had previously purchased the Mutual Broadcasting System, NBC's radio networks and the rights to use the &quot;NBC Radio Networks&quot; name. For a time, CBS Radio, NBC Radio Networks and CNN's radio news services were all under the WWO umbrella.

{{As of|2008}}, Westwood One continues to distribute CBS radio programming, but as a self-managed company that put itself up for sale and found a buyer for a significant amount of its stock.

CBS also owned [[Telemundo Puerto Rico (TV channel)|CBS Telenoticias]], a Spanish-language news network.

In that same year of 1997, Westinghouse changed its name to CBS Corporation, and corporate headquarters were moved from [[Pittsburgh]] to New York. And to underline the change in emphasis, all non-entertainment assets were put up for sale. Another 90 radio stations were added to Infinity's portfolio in 1998 with the acquisition of American Radio Systems Corporation for $2.6&amp;nbsp;billion.

In 1999, CBS paid $2.5&amp;nbsp;billion to acquire [[King World Productions]], a television syndication company whose programs include ''[[The Oprah Winfrey Show]]'', ''[[Jeopardy!]]'' and ''[[Wheel of Fortune (US game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]''. By the end of 1999, all pre-CBS elements of Westinghouse's industrial past (beyond retaining rights to the name for [[brand licensing]] purposes) were gone.

==== Viacom ====
By the 1990s, CBS had become a broadcasting giant, but in 1999 entertainment conglomerate [[Viacom (1971–2005)|Viacom]], a company created years earlier to syndicate old CBS series, announced it was taking over CBS in a deal valued at $37&amp;nbsp;billion. Following completion of this effort in 2000, Viacom was ranked as the second-largest entertainment company in the world.

==== CBS Corporation and CBS Studios ====
Having assembled all the elements of a communications empire, Viacom found that the promised synergy was not there, and at the end of 2005 it split itself in two. CBS became the center of a new company, [[CBS Corporation]], which included the broadcasting elements, Paramount Television's production operations (renamed [[CBS Television Studios]]), [[UPN]] (which later merged with [[Time Warner]]'s [[The WB Television Network|The WB]] into [[The CW Television Network|The CW]]), Viacom Outdoor advertising (renamed [[CBS Outdoor]]), [[Showtime Networks|Showtime]], [[Simon &amp; Schuster]], and [[Paramount Parks]], which the company sold in May 2006. It is the legal successor to the old Viacom.

The second company, keeping the [[Viacom]] name, kept Paramount Pictures, assorted MTV Networks, BET, and, until May 2007, [[Famous Music]], which was sold to [[Sony/ATV Music Publishing]].

As a result of the aforementioned Viacom/CBS corporate split, as well as other acquisitions over recent years, CBS (under the moniker CBS Studios) owns a massive film and television library spanning nine decades; these include not only acquired material from Viacom and CBS in-house productions and network programs, but also programs aired originally on competing networks. Shows and other material in this library include ''[[I Love Lucy]]'', ''[[The Twilight Zone (1959 TV series)|The Twilight Zone]]'', ''[[The Honeymooners]]'', ''[[Hawaii Five-O]]'' (both the original and current remake), ''[[Gunsmoke]]'', ''[[The Fugitive (TV series)|The Fugitive]]'', ''[[Little House on the Prairie (TV series)|Little House on the Prairie]]'' (US TV rights only), ''[[Star Trek: The Original Series|Star Trek]]'', ''[[The Brady Bunch]]'', ''[[Cheers]]'', ''[[The Young Indiana Jones Chronicles]]'', ''[[Evening Shade]]'', ''[[Duckman]]'' ''[[CSI: Crime Scene Investigation]]'' and its spin-offs, the CBS theatrical library (''[[My Fair Lady (film)|My Fair Lady]]'', ''[[Scrooge (1970 film)|Scrooge]]'', etc.), and the entire [[Terrytoons]] library from 1921 forward, among others.

Both CBS Corporation and the new Viacom are still owned by Sumner Redstone's company, National Amusements. As such, [[Paramount home entertainment|Paramount Home Entertainment]] continues to handle DVD distribution for the CBS library.

== Coverage and availability ==
[[ACNielsen]] estimated in 2003 that CBS can be seen in 96.98% of all American households, reaching 103,421,270 homes in the United States. CBS has 204 VHF and UHF affiliated stations in the U.S. and U.S. possessions. CBS is also carried on cable television across Canada, via its affiliates, as well as in [[Bermuda]], via local affiliate [[ZBM-TV]].

== Logos and slogans ==
{{TV network logos}}
[[Image:CBSeye.svg|thumb|right|125px|CBS current eye logo, popularly known as the &quot;CBS Eye&quot; or &quot;The Eyemark&quot;, from 1951 through the present.]]

CBS unveiled its Eye Device logo on October 20, 1951. Before that, from the 1940s through 1951, CBS Television used an oval spotlight on the block letters C-B-S.&lt;ref&gt;See an illustration of this early logo at {{cite web |url=http://www.pharis-video.com/cbs-1949.jpg |title=cbs-1949.jpg |format=[[JPEG]] |publisher=Chuck Pharis Web Page |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Eye device was conceived by [[William Golden]] based on a [[Pennsylvania Dutch]] [[hex sign]] as well as a [[Shakers|Shaker]] drawing. (While commonly attributed to Golden, there is speculation that at least some design work on the symbol may have been done by another CBS staff designer, Georg Olden, one of the first African-Americans to attract some attention in the postwar graphic design field.)&lt;ref&gt;Lasky, Julie, &quot;The Search for Georg Olden&quot;. (Steven Heller with Georgette Ballance, editors) ''Graphic Design History'', New York: Allworth Press, 2001; pp. 121–122.&lt;/ref&gt; The Eye device made its broadcasting debut on October 20, 1951. The following season, as [[William Golden|Golden]] prepared a new &quot;ident&quot;, CBS President [[Frank Stanton]] insisted on keeping the Eye device and using it as much as possible. (Golden died unexpectedly in 1959, and was replaced by one of his top assistants, [[Lou Dorfsman]], who would go on to oversee all print and on-air graphics for CBS for the next thirty years.)

An example of CBS Television Network's imaging (and the distinction between the television and radio networks) may be seen in a video of ''[[The Jack Benny Program]]'' from 1953; the video appears to be converted from [[kinescope]], and &quot;unscoped&quot; or unedited. One sees the program very nearly as one would have seen it live on CBS. [[Don Wilson (announcer)|Don Wilson]] is the program announcer, but also voices a promo for ''[[Private Secretary (TV series)|Private Secretary]]'', which starred [[Ann Sothern]] and alternated weekly with [[Jack Benny]] on the CBS schedule. Benny continued to appear on CBS radio and television at that time, and Wilson makes a promo announcement at the end of the broadcast for Benny's radio program on the [[CBS Radio Network]]. The program closes with the &quot;CBS Television Network&quot; ID slide (the &quot;CBS eye&quot; over a field of clouds with the words &quot;CBS Television Network&quot; superimposed over the eye). There is, however, no voiceover accompanying the ID slide. It is unclear whether it was simply absent from the recording or never originally broadcast (a staff announcer may have provided a voiceover message, if so, it was not recorded on this clip).{{citation needed|date=October 2010}}

The CBS eye is now an American icon. While the symbol's settings have changed, the Eye device itself has not been redesigned in its entire history.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.famouslogos.us/cbs-logo/ CBS Logo: Design and History]. FamousLogos.us. Retrieved May 2, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; In the network's new graphic identity created by [[Trollbäck + Company]] in 2006, the eye is being placed in a &quot;trademark&quot; position on show titles, days of the week and descriptive words, an approach highly respecting the value of the eye. The eye logo has frequently been copied or borrowed by television networks around the world, notable examples being the Austrian Broadcasting System ([[Österreichischer Rundfunk|ORF]]) which used to use a red version of the eye logo, [[Associated TeleVision]] in the United Kingdom, [[Frecuencia Latina]] in Peru, [[Nippon Television]] in Japan and [[Rede Bandeirantes]] in Brazil. The logo is alternately known as the ''Eyemark'', which was also the name of CBS's domestic and international [[Broadcast syndication|syndication]] divisions in the mid-to-late 1990s before the King World acquisition and Viacom merger.

=== 1980s ===
Through the years, CBS has developed several notable image campaigns, and several of the network's most well-known slogans date from the 1980s. 1981's &quot;Reach for the Stars&quot; used a space-themed campaign to capitalize on both CBS's stellar improvement in the ratings and the historic launch of the space shuttle Columbia. 1982s &quot;Great Moments&quot; juxtaposed scenes from classic CBS programming such as ''I Love Lucy'' with scenes from the network's then-current classics such as ''Dallas'' and ''M*A*S*H''. From 1983 through 1986, CBS (by now firmly atop the ratings) featured a campaign based on the slogan &quot;We've Got the Touch&quot;. Vocals for the campaign's jingle were contributed by Richie Havens (1983–84 and 1984–85), Aaron Neville (1984–85) and Kenny Rogers (1985–86). The 1986–87 programming season ushered in the &quot;Share the Spirit of CBS&quot; campaign, the network's first to use full-out computer graphics and DVE effects. Unlike most network campaign promos, the full length version of Share the Spirit not only showed a brief clip preview of each new fall series, but also utilized the CGI effects to map out the entire fall schedule by night. The success of that campaign led to the 1987–88 &quot;CBSpirit&quot; campaign. Most CBSpirit promos utilized a procession of show clips once again. However, the new graphic motif was a swirling (or &quot;swishing&quot;) blue line, that was used to represent &quot;the spirit&quot;. The full length promo, like the previous year, had a special portion that identified new fall shows, but the mapped-out fall schedule shot was abandoned.

[[File:CBS.svg|thumb|right|Long-time secondary logo of CBS from 1971, still in use.]]
For the 1988–89 season, CBS unveiled its new image campaign, officially known as &quot;Television You Can Feel&quot; but more commonly identified as &quot;You Can Feel It On CBS&quot;. The goal was to convey a more sensual, new-age image through distinguished, advanced-looking computer graphics and soothing music, backgrounding images and clips of emotionally powerful scenes and characters. However, it was this season in which CBS began its ratings free fall, the deepest in the network's history. CBS ended the decade with &quot;Get Ready for CBS&quot;. The 1989–90 version was a very ambitious campaign that attempted to elevate CBS out of last place (among the major networks); the motif was network stars interacting with each other in a remote studio set, getting ready for photo and TV shoots, as well as for the new season on CBS. The high-energy promo song and the campaign's practices saw many variations across the country as every CBS affiliate participated in it, as per a network mandate. Also, for the first time in history, CBS became the first broadcast network to team with a national retailer to encourage viewership, with the CBS/Kmart Get Ready Giveaway.

=== 1990s ===
For the 1990–91 season, the campaign featured a new jingle—[[The Temptations]] offered an altered version of their hit &quot;[[Get Ready (song)|Get Ready]]&quot;. The early 1990s featured less-than-memorable campaigns, with simplified taglines such as &quot;This is CBS&quot; (1992) and &quot;You're On CBS&quot; (1995). Eventually, the advertising department gained momentum again late in the decade with ''Welcome Home to a CBS Night '' (1996–1997), simplified to ''Welcome Home'' (1997–1999) and succeeded by the spin-off campaign ''The Address is CBS'' (1999–2000).

=== 2000s ===
[[File:CBS logo wordmark 2006.svg|thumb|right|CBS logo/wordmark, 2007–2011]]
Throughout the first decade of the 21st century, CBS's ratings resurgence was backed by their &quot;It's All Here&quot; campaign, and their strategy led, in 2005, to the proclamation that they were &quot;America's Most Watched Network&quot;. Their most recent campaign, beginning in 2006, proclaims &quot;We Are CBS&quot; with the voice of [[Don LaFontaine]]. {{As of|2009}}, the network has shifted to a campaign entitled &quot;Only CBS&quot; in which the network proclaims several unique qualities it has. In 2011, CBS returned to the usage of &quot;America's Most Watched Network&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tvbythenumbers.zap2it.com/2011/06/13/cbs-americas-most-watched-network-also-posts-the-largest-live-plus-7-day-dvr-lift-during-the-2010-2011-season/95448/ CBS, America’s Most Watched Network, Also Posts The Largest Live Plus 7-Day DVR Lift During The 2010–2011 Season – Ratings | TVbytheNumbers&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Promos ==
Especially during the 1960s, the three major networks, NBC, CBS and ABC, would show elaborate promos during the summer months of their upcoming fall schedule of that year. In 1961, CBS took the unusual step of airing a program entitled ''CBS Fall Preview Special: Seven Wonderful Nights'',&lt;ref&gt;{{IMDb title|1275554|CBS Fall Preview Special: Seven Wonderful Nights}}. 1961. Accessed February 16, 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; using, not the usual television voiceovers, but stars of several CBS shows to promote the upcoming shows, stars such as Ed Sullivan (''The Ed Sullivan Show''), [[Rod Serling]] (''The Twilight Zone''), and [[Raymond Burr]] and [[Barbara Hale]] (''Perry Mason''). The stars would appear and show previews of the entire lineup for one specific day of the week.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dLv1W8sMfF8 |title=1961 CBS Friday Night Preview w/Rod Serling |date=16 may 2008 |publisher=YouTube |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Programming ==
{{See|List of programs broadcast by CBS|List of shows previously aired by CBS}}
As of fall 2010, CBS operates on an 87½-hour regular network programming schedule. It provides 22 hours of prime time programming to affiliated stations: 8–11 p.m. Monday to Saturday (all times ET/PT) and 7–11 p.m. on Sundays. Programming is also provided 10&amp;nbsp;am–3 p.m. weekdays (game shows ''[[The Price Is Right (U.S. game show)|The Price Is Right]]'' and ''[[Let's Make a Deal]]'', soaps ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'' and ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful]]'', and talk show ''The Talk''); 7–9 a.m. weekdays and Saturdays (''[[The Early Show]]''); ''[[CBS News Sunday Morning]]'', nightly editions of the ''[[CBS Evening News]]'', the Sunday political talk show ''[[Face the Nation]]'', a 2½-hour early morning news program ''[[Up to the Minute]]'' and ''[[CBS Morning News]]''; the late night talk shows ''[[Late Show with David Letterman]]'' and ''[[The Late Late Show with Craig Ferguson]]''; and a three-hour Saturday morning live-action/animation block under the name ''[[Cookie Jar TV]]''.

In addition, sports programming routinely appears on the weekends, although with a somewhat unpredictable schedule (mostly between noon and 7:00&amp;nbsp;pm ET).

=== Daytime ===
CBS's daytime schedule is the home of the popular long-running game show ''[[The Price Is Right (U.S. game show)|The Price Is Right]]''. ''The Price is Right'', which began production in 1972, is notable as the longest continuously running daytime game show on network television. After being hosted by [[Bob Barker]] for 35 years, the show has been hosted by actor/comedian [[Drew Carey]] since 2007. The network is also home to a new version of the classic game show ''[[Let's Make a Deal]]'', hosted by singer/comedian [[Wayne Brady]]. As of 2011, CBS is the only network still producing daytime game shows.

CBS introduced a new talk show titled ''[[The Talk (TV series)|The Talk]]'' on October 18, 2010. The show is similar to ABC's ''[[The View (U.S. TV series)|The View]]'' with a panel of hosts including [[Julie Chen]], [[Sara Gilbert]], [[Sharon Osbourne]], [[Holly Robinson Peete]] and [[Leah Remini]]. The show addresses motherhood and other contemporary issues in a candid environment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1= Domanick |first1=Andrea |date=August 11, 2011 |title=CBS' 'The Talk' to Premiere Oct. 18 |work=[[Broadcasting &amp; Cable]] |url=http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/455932-CBS_The_Talk_to_Premiere_Oct_18.php |accessdate=February 16, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|2010|9}}, CBS Daytime airs two daytime soap operas each weekday: the hourlong series ''[[The Young and the Restless]]'' and the half-hour series ''[[The Bold and the Beautiful]]''. CBS has generally aired the most soap operas of the Big Three networks (it aired 3½ hours of soap operas from 1982 to 2009, more than NBC and as many or more than ABC in that time frame), though as of 2011 it is behind ABC, which is still airing three hours of soaps; CBS will surpass ABC in 2012 when it cancels two of its three remaining soap operas.

Notable daytime soaps that once aired on CBS include ''[[As the World Turns]]'' (1956–2010), ''[[Guiding Light]]'' (1952–2009), which began on radio in 1937, ''[[Love of Life]]'' (1951–80), ''[[Search for Tomorrow]]'' (1951–82), which later moved to NBC, ''[[The Secret Storm]]'' (1954–1974), ''[[The Edge of Night]]'' (1956–75), which later moved to ABC, and ''[[Capitol (TV series)|Capitol]]'' (1982–87).

Notable daytime game shows that once aired on CBS include ''[[Match Game]]'' (1973–79), ''[[Tattletales]]'' (1974–78 and 1982–84), ''[[Pyramid (game show)|The $10/25,000 Pyramid]]'' (1973–74 and 1982–88), ''[[Press Your Luck]]'' (1983–86), ''[[Card Sharks]]'' (1986–89), ''[[Family Feud]]'' (1988–93), and ''[[Wheel of Fortune (U.S. game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]'' (1989–1991). CBS games that also aired in prime time include ''[[Beat the Clock]]'' (1950–58 and 1979–80), ''[[To Tell the Truth]]'' (1956–68) and ''[[Password (game show)|Password]]'' (1961–67, and a 2008 prime time revival). Two long-running primetime-only games were the panel shows ''[[What's My Line?]]'' (1950–67) and ''[[I've Got a Secret]]'' (1952–68, 1976).

=== Children's programming ===
{{Main|Children's programming on CBS}}
CBS broadcast the live action series ''[[Captain Kangaroo]]'' on weekday mornings from 1955 through 1982, and on Saturdays through 1984. From 1971 through 1986, the CBS News department produced one-minute ''[[In the News]]'' segments broadcast between other Saturday morning programs. Otherwise, in regards to children's programming, CBS has aired mostly animated series for kids, such as reruns of ''[[Mighty Mouse]]'' cartoons (from the 1950's to the 1980's) reruns of ''[[Bugs Bunny]]'' cartoons, the original version of ''[[Scooby-Doo]]'', ''[[Jim Henson's Muppet Babies]]'', ''[[Garfield and Friends]]'' and ''[[Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles (1987 TV series)|Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles]]''. In 1997, CBS began broadcasting ''[[Wheel 2000]]'' (a children's version of the popular syndicated game show ''[[Wheel of Fortune (U.S. game show)|Wheel of Fortune]]''), and was broadcasting it simultaneously with [[Game Show Network|GSN]].

In September 1998, CBS began contracting out to other companies to provide programming and material for their Saturday morning schedule. The first of these special blocks was ''[[CBS Kidshow]]'', which featured programming from Canada's [[Nelvana]] studio.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nick Jr. on CBS&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117782661.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1&amp;query=|title=CBS picks Nick mix|date=June 15, 2000|work=Variety|accessdate=August 13, 2009 | first=Michael | last=Schneider}}&lt;/ref&gt; It aired on CBS Saturday mornings from 1998 to 2000, with shows like ''[[Anatole (TV series)|Anatole]]'', ''[[Mythic Warriors]],'' ''[[Rescue Heroes]]'', and ''[[Flying Rhino Junior High]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117489638.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1&amp;query=|title=CTV pacts for 3 Nelvana series|date=December 22, 1998|work=Variety|accessdate=August 13, 2009 | first=Brendan | last=Kelly}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its tagline was, ''&quot;The CBS Kids Show: Get in the Act.&quot;''

In 2000, CBS's deal with Nelvana ended. They then began a deal with [[Nickelodeon (TV channel)|Nickelodeon]] (owned by CBS's former parent company Viacom, which at one time was a subsidiary of CBS) to air its [[Nick Jr. (block)|Nick Jr.]] programming under the banner ''[[Nickelodeon on CBS|Nick Jr. on CBS]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nick Jr. on CBS&quot;/&gt; From 2002 to 2004, Nick's non-preschool series aired on it as well, under the name ''Nick on CBS''.

In 2006, after the Viacom-CBS split (as described above), CBS decided to discontinue the Nick Jr. lineup in favor of a lineup of programs produced by [[DIC Entertainment]] and later, the [[Cookie Jar Group]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjar.com/press/cj_press_20080620.php |title=Cookie Jar and Dic Entertainment to Merge, Creating independent global children's entertainment and education powerhouse|work=Cookie Jar Group |date=June 20, 2008|accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cjar.com/press/cj_press_20080723a.php |title=COOKIE JAR ENTERTAINMENT EXPANDS BRAND PORTFOLIO, TALENT AND GLOBAL REACH WITH CLOSING OF DIC TRANSACTION |work=Cookie Jar Group |date=July 23, 2008 |accessdate=December 23, 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; as part of a three-year deal which includes distribution of selected Formula One auto races on tape delay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldscreen.com/newscurrent.php?filename=dic30706.htm|title=World Screen – Home}}{{dead link|date=June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117936466.html?categoryid=1050&amp;cs=1&amp;query=|title=Synergy not kid-friendly at Eye web|work=Variety|date=January 19, 2006|accessdate=August 13, 2009 | first=Elizabeth | last=Guider}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''KOL Secret Slumber Party on CBS'' premiered in September of that year; in the inaugural line-up, two of the programs were new shows, one aired in syndication in 2005 and three were pre-2006 shows. In mid-2007, KOL withdrew sponsorship from CBS's Saturday Morning Block and the name was changed to ''KEWLopolis on CBS''. Complimenting CBS's 2007 line-up was ''[[Care Bears]]'', ''[[Strawberry Shortcake]]'', and ''[[Sushi Pack]]''. On February 24, 2009, it was announced that CBS renewed its contract with Cookie Jar for another three seasons, through 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.broadcastingcable.com/article/179789-CBS_Reups_With_Kids_Programmer_Cookie_Jar.php|title=CBS Reups With Kids Programmer Cookie Jar|date=February 24, 2009|work=Broadcasting &amp; Cable|accessdate=February 26, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cjar.com/press/cj_press_20090224.php|title=CBS RENEWS COOKIE JAR ENTERTAINMENT'S SATURDAY MORNING BLOCK FOR THREE MORE SEASONS |date=February 24, 2009|work=Cookie Jar Group|accessdate=March 25, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On September 19, 2009, KEWLopolis has been changed into ''[[Cookie Jar TV]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.worldscreen.com/articles/display/22324|title=CBS Sets Lineup for Cookie Jar Block|date=September 4, 2009|work=WorldScreen|accessdate=September 10, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==== Animated primetime holiday specials ====
CBS was the original broadcast network for the animated primetime holiday specials based on the comic strip ''[[Peanuts]]'', beginning with ''[[A Charlie Brown Christmas]]'' in 1965. Over thirty holiday Peanuts specials (each for a specific holiday such as [[Halloween]]) were broadcast on CBS from that time until 2000, when ABC acquired the broadcast rights. CBS also aired several primetime animated specials based on the work of ''[[Dr. Seuss]]'' (Theodor Geisel), beginning with ''[[How the Grinch Stole Christmas! (TV special)|How the Grinch Stole Christmas]]'' in 1966, as well as several specials based on the comic strip ''[[Garfield]]'' over the course of the 1980s (which led to Garfield getting his own [[Saturday morning cartoon]] on the network, ''[[Garfield and Friends]]'', from 1988 to 1995). ''[[Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer (TV special)|Rudolph the Red-Nosed Reindeer]]'', produced in [[stop motion]] by the [[Rankin/Bass]] studio, has been another annual holiday staple of CBS since 1972, but that special originated on NBC in 1964. As of 2011, ''Rudolph'' and ''[[Frosty the Snowman (TV special)|Frosty the Snowman]]'' are the only two pre-1990 animated specials remaining on CBS; ''Charlie Brown'' and ''The Grinch'' moved to ABC, while cable network [[ABC Family]] owns the ''Garfield'' specials.

All of these animated specials, from 1973 until 1990, began with a fondly remembered opening animated logo which showed the words &quot;A CBS Special Presentation&quot; in colorful lettering (the [[ITC Avant Garde]] typeface, widely used in the 1970s, was used for this logo). The word &quot;SPECIAL&quot;, in [[all caps]] and repeated multiple times in multiple colors, slowly zoomed out from the frame in a spinning counterclockwise motion against a black background, and rapidly zoomed back into frame as a single word, in white, at the end; the logo was accompanied by a jazzy yet majestic up-tempo fanfare (edited incidental music from the CBS crime drama ''[[Hawaii Five-O]]'' [this music is titled &quot;Call to Danger&quot; on the Capitol Records' soundtrack LP) with dramatic horns and percussion (this appeared at the beginning of all CBS specials of the period (such as the [[Miss USA]] pageants and the annual [[Kennedy Center Honors]] presentation), not just animated ones). (This opening logo was presumably designed by, or under the supervision of, longtime CBS creative director Lou Dorfsman, who oversaw print and on-air graphics for CBS for nearly thirty years, replacing William Golden, who died in 1959.)

=== Classical music specials ===
CBS was also responsible for telecasting the series of ''[[Young People's Concerts]]'' conducted by [[Leonard Bernstein]]. Telecast every few months between 1958 and 1972, first in black-and-white and then switching to color in 1966, these programs introduced millions of children to classical music through the eloquent commentaries by Maestro Bernstein. They were nominated for several [[Emmy Award]]s, and were among the first programs ever broadcast from [[Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts]].

On June 1, 1977, it was announced that [[Elvis Presley]] had signed a deal with CBS for a new television special. It was agreed that CBS would videotape concerts during the summer of 1977. It was filmed during Presley's final tour in the cities of [[Omaha, Nebraska]], on June 19, 1977, and [[Rapid City, South Dakota]], on June 21, 1977. On August 16, 1977, [[Death of Elvis Presley#Final year and death|Elvis Presley died]] in his [[Graceland]] mansion. On October 3, 1977, CBS showed [[Elvis in Concert|a posthumous 1977 TV special starring Elvis Presley]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.elvispresley.com.au/elvis/presley/elvis_in_concert.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; It was released nearly two months after the death of Elvis.

Over the years, CBS has broadcast three different productions of Tchaikovsky's famous ballet ''The Nutcracker'' –  two live telecasts of the [[George Balanchine]] [[New York City Ballet]] production in 1957 and '58 respectively, a little-known German-American filmed production in 1965 (which was subsequently repeated three times and starred [[Edward Villella]], [[Patricia McBride]], and [[Melissa Hayden]]), and beginning in 1977, the [[Mikhail Baryshnikov|Baryshnikov]] staging of the ballet, starring the Russian dancer along with [[Gelsey Kirkland]] – a version that would become a television classic, and remains so today. This production later moved to [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]].

In April 1986, CBS presented a slightly abbreviated version of ''Horowitz in Moscow'', a live piano recital by [[Vladimir Horowitz]], arguably the greatest pianist of the 20th century. It marked Horowitz's return to Russia after more than sixty years. The program was shown as an episode of the series ''[[CBS News Sunday Morning]]'' (9:00&amp;nbsp;am in the U.S. is 4:00&amp;nbsp;pm in Russia). It was so successful that CBS repeated it a mere two months later by popular demand, this time on videotape, rather than live. In later years, the program was shown as a stand-alone special on [[Public Broadcasting Service|PBS]], and the current DVD of it omits the [[Charles Kuralt]] commentary, but includes additional selections not heard on the CBS telecast.

In 1986, CBS telecast ''Carnegie Hall: The Grand Reopening'' in primetime, in what was now a rare move for a commercial network station, since most primetime classical music specials were now relegated to PBS and [[A&amp;E Network|A&amp;E]]. The program was a concert commemorating the re-opening of Carnegie Hall after its complete renovation. It featured, along with luminaries such as Leonard Bernstein, popular music artists such as Frank Sinatra.

== International broadcasts ==
[[File:Cbs-building.jpg|thumb|right|[[CBS Building|CBS Headquarters]] in New York City]]
CBS programs are shown outside the US. For instance, CBS News is shown for a few hours a day on satellite channel [[Orbit News]] in Europe, Africa and the Middle East. ''[[The CBS Evening News]]'' is shown in the UK, Ireland, Australia, New Zealand and Italy on [[Sky News]], despite the fact that Sky is part of [[News Corporation]] (owners of Fox News Channel).

In the UK, CBS took over 6 of [[Chello Zone]]'s channels in 2009. These were the first channels branded CBS outside the US.&lt;ref name=broadcastnow/&gt; The channels are called CBS Action, CBS Drama, and CBS Reality, while CBS Reality has a [[Timeshift channel|timeshifted]] (+1) channel as well. Other channels as part of the deal are The Horror Channel and its timeshifted channel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/digitaltv/news/a180007/cbs-to-launch-new-uk-channels.html |title=CBS to launch new UK channels |first=Andrew |last= Laughlin |date=October 1, 2009 |publisher=[[Digital Spy]] |accessdate=February 16, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Australia, [[Network Ten]] has an output deal with CBS Paramount giving them rights to carry the programs [[Jericho (TV series)|''Jericho'']], [[Dr. Phil (TV series)|''Dr. Phil'']], ''[[Late Show with David Letterman]]'', [[NCIS (TV series)|''NCIS'']] and ''[[Numb3rs]]'' as well access to stories from ''[[60 Minutes]]'' (the rights of which have been sold to the [[Nine Network]] which broadcasts [[60 Minutes (Australian TV program)|their own ''60 Minutes'']]).

In [[Bermuda]], there is a CBS affiliate owned by the state-run [[Bermuda Broadcasting|Bermuda Broadcasting Company]] using the callsign [[ZBM-TV|ZBM]].

In Canada, CBS, like all major American TV networks, is carried in the basic program package of all cable and satellite providers. The broadcast is shown almost exactly the same in Canada as in the United States. However, CBS's programming on Canadian cable and satellite systems are subject to the practice of &quot;[[Simultaneous substitution|simsubbing]]&quot;, in which a signal of a Canadian station is placed over CBS's signal, if the programming at that time is the same. As well, many Canadians live close enough to a major American city to pick up the over the air broadcast signal of an American CBS affiliate with an antenna.

In Hong Kong, ''The CBS Evening News'' is aired live in the early morning and the local networks have an agreement to rebroadcast sections 12 hours later to fill up the local news programs when they have insufficient content to report.

''The CBS Evening News'' is seen in the Philippines via satellite on Q-TV (a sister network of broadcaster [[GMA Network]]) while ''[[The Early Show]]'' is shown in that country on the Lifestyle Network. Studio 23 and Maxx, channels owned by broadcaster ABS-CBN in the Philippines show ''[[The Late Show with David Letterman]]''.

In India CBS is affiliated with a set of CBS-branded channels, including Prime Big CBS and Love Big CBS.

== Controversy==

In 1995, CBS refused to air a segment of ''60 Minutes'' that would have featured an interview with a former president of research and development for Brown &amp; Williamson, the nation's third largest tobacco company. The controversy raised questions about the legal roles in decision making and whether journalistic standards should be compromised despite legal pressures and threats. The decision nevertheless sent shock waves throughout the television industry, the journalism community, and the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=The 60 Minutes controversy: What lawyers are telling the news media |last=Russomannno, |first=Joseph A. |last2=Youm |first2=Kyo Ho. |journal=Communications and the Law |month=September|date=1996 |volume=18 |issue=3 |page=65 |url=http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/coml18&amp;div=18&amp;id=&amp;page=}}{{subscription required}}&lt;/ref&gt; This incident was the basis for the 1999 film by [[Michael Mann (director)|Michael Mann]], ''[[The Insider (film)|The Insider]]''.

In 2001, [[Bernard Goldberg]], who was a reporter with CBS for 28 years, had his book, ''Bias: A CBS Insider Exposes How the Media Distort the News'', published. This book heavily criticized the media, and some CBS reporters and news anchors in particular, such as [[Dan Rather]]. Goldberg accused CBS of having a liberal bias in most of their news.

In 2004, the [[Federal Communications Commission|FCC]] imposed a record $550,000 fine on CBS for its broadcast of a [[Super Bowl]] [[Super Bowl XXXVIII halftime show controversy|half-time show]] (produced by then sister-unit MTV) in which singer [[Janet Jackson]]'s breast was briefly exposed. It was the largest fine ever for a violation of federal decency laws. Following the incident CBS apologized to its viewers and denied foreknowledge of the event, which was broadcast live on TV. In 2008, a Philadelphia federal court annulled the fine imposed on CBS, labelling it &quot;arbitrary and capricious&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|first= Ann |last= Woolner |title= Janet Jackson's Breast Freed, This Time by Court  |work=[[Bloomberg L.P.]] |date=July 25, 2008 |accessdate=July 25, 2008 |url= http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=20601039&amp;sid=aKVPpRZ9A3tE&amp;refer=home}}&lt;/ref&gt;

CBS aired a controversial episode of ''[[60 Minutes]]'', which questioned U.S. President [[George W. Bush]]'s service in the [[National Guard of the United States|National Guard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=New Questions On Bush Guard Duty, 60 Minutes Has Newly Obtained Documents On President's Military Service|work=CBS News| date=September 8, 2004|first=Rebecca |last=Leung|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2004/09/08/60II/main641984.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following allegations of forgery, CBS News admitted that [[Killian documents controversy|documents used in the story]] had not been properly authenticated. The following January, CBS fired four people connected to the preparation of the news-segment.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|title=CBS Ousts 4 For Bush Guard Story, Independent Panel Faults 'Myopic Zeal' To Be 1st To Deliver Story|first=Jarrett |last=Murphy|work=CBS News| date=January 10, 2005 |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/01/10/national/main665727.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Former network news anchor [[Dan Rather]] filed a $70&amp;nbsp;million lawsuit against CBS in 2007, contending the story, and his termination, were mishandled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Dan Rather Sues CBS for $70 Million |first=Scott |last=Mayerowitz |work=ABC News Business Unit |date=Sept. 19, 2007 |url=http://abcnews.go.com/Business/story?id=3625465&amp;page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Parts of the suit were dismissed in 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Rather’s Lawsuit Shows Role of G.O.P. in Inquiry|first=Jacques |last=Steinberg| date=November 16, 2008|newspaper=New York Times |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/17/business/media/17rather.html?pagewanted=all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
the suit was dismissed, and his motion to appeal was denied in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Dan Rather loses bid in CBS lawsuit|date=January 13, 2010|first=Matea |last=Gold|newspaper=Los Angeles Times |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2010/jan/13/entertainment/la-et-rather13-2010jan13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2006, CBS announced it would air only three of its [[NFL on CBS|NFL]] games per week in high definition. The move created some outrage among fans, with some accusing the network of being &quot;cheap.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Phillip |last=Swann|date=September 8, 2006 |title=CBS: The 'C' Stands For Cheap |publisher=TVPredictions.com |url=http://www.tvpredictions.com/cbscheap090806.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2007, retired Army Major Gen. [[John Batiste]], consultant to [[CBS News]], appeared in a political ad for [[VoteVets.org]] critical of President Bush and the war in Iraq.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|id=aMPIi03wSfY|title=General Batiste: &quot;Protect America, Not George Bush&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two days later, CBS stated that appearing in the ad violated Batiste's contract with them and the agreement was terminated.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news  |title=CBS News Asks Batiste To Step Down As Consultant |accessdate=May 12, 2007 |author=Montopoli, Brian |date=May 11, 2007 |publisher=CBS News |quote= |url=http://www.cbsnews.com/blogs/2007/05/11/publiceye/entry2791091.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2011, CBS sponsored a Republican Primary Presidential debate, in which candidate Congressman Ron Paul of Texas was only given 89 seconds to speak during a one hour televised debate.  Congressman Paul had been surging in the polls in the early primary states of both Iowa and New Hampshire in the weeks leading up to the debate.  Many people, not only those associated with the Paul campaign, saw this as an attempt by CBS to silence the views of Congressman Paul and to shape the outcome of the election.

== See also ==
{{div col|colwidth=30em}}
* [[CBS Cable]], the company's early (and abortive) foray into cable broadcasting.
* [[CBS Daytime]]
* [[CBS Interactive]]
* [[CBS Kidshow]]
* [[CBS Mobile]]
* [[CBS News]]
* [[CBS Radio]]
* [[CBS Radio Network]]
* [[CBS Sports]]
* [[CBS Studio Center]]
* [[CBS Television City]]
* [[CBS Television Distribution]]
* [[CBS Television Stations]]
* [[CBS Productions]]
* [[Cookie Jar TV]]
* [[The CW Television Network]]
* [[History of CBS]]
* [[List of assets owned by CBS]]
* [[List of CBS television affiliates (table)|List of CBS affiliates, arranged by market]]
* [[List of CBS television affiliates (by U.S. state)|List of CBS affiliates, arranged by state]]
* [[List of programs broadcast by CBS]]
* [[List of shows previously aired by CBS]]
* [[Westmoreland v. CBS]]
{{div col end}}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== References ==
* {{Cite book |last=Auletta |first=Ken |title=Three Blind Mice: How the TV Networks Lost Their Way |location=New York |publisher=Vintage |year=1992 |isbn=0679741356 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Bagdikian |first=Ben H. |title=The New Media Monopoly |edition=6th |location=Boston |publisher=Beacon Press |year=2000 |isbn=0807061794 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Barnouw |first=Erik |title=A Tower in Babel: A History of Broadcasting in the United States to 1933 |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1966 |isbn=978-0195004748 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Barnouw |first=Erik |title=The Golden Web: A History of Broadcasting in the United States, 1933–1953 |location=New York |publisher=Oxford University Press |year=1968 |isbn=978-0195004755 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Epstein |first=Edward J. |title=News From Nowhere: Television and the News |location=New York |publisher=Random House |year=1973 |isbn=0394463161 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Goldberg |first=Bernard |title=Bias: A CBS Insider Exposes How the Media Distorts the News |location=Washington, D.C. |publisher=Regnery |year=2002 |isbn=0895261901 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Kisseloff |first=Jeff |title=The Box: An Oral History of Television, 1920–1961 |location=New York |publisher=Viking |year=1995 |isbn=0670864706 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Matusow |first=Barbara |title=The Evening Stars: The Making of the Network News Anchor |location=New York |publisher=Ballantine Books |year=1984 |isbn=0345317149 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Paley |first=William |title=As It Happened: A Memoir |location=Garden City, NY |publisher=Doubleday |year=1979 |isbn=0385146396 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Robinson |first=Michael J. |lastauthoramp=yes |last2=Sheehan |first2=Margaret |title=Over the Wire and On TV: CBS and the UPI in Campaign '80 |location=New York |publisher=Russell Sage Foundation |year=1983 |isbn=0871547228 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Smith |first=Sally Bedell |title=In All His Glory: The Life of William S. Paley, the Legendary Tycoon and His Brilliant Circle |location=New York |publisher=Simon &amp; Schuster |year=1990 |isbn=0671617354 }}

== Further reading ==
* {{Cite book |last=Paper |first=Lewis J. |year=1987 |title=Empire: William S. Paley and the Making of CBS |location=New York |publisher=St. Martin's Press |isbn=0312005911}}

== External links ==
* {{Official website|http://www.cbs.com}}
* {{youtube|user=CBS}}
* [http://promonet.cbs.com/external/CBSEyeDentity_Site/toc.html CBS Eye-dentity Logo Guidelines website]

{{Navboxes|list1=
{{American broadcast television}}
{{CBS}}
{{Webby Awards|cat=Halovine|year=1996|type=Nominee}}
{{New York Yankees owners}}
}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=July 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cbs}}
[[Category:1927 establishments in the United States]]
[[Category:American television networks]]
[[Category:CBS Television Network|CBS television network]]
[[Category:Companies established in 1927]]
[[Category:New York Yankees owners]]
[[Category:Orphan initialisms]]
[[Category:Peabody Award winners]]
[[Category:CBS Corporation subsidiaries]]

[[ar:سي بي إس]]
[[as:চিবিএস]]
[[bs:CBS]]
[[bg:CBS]]
[[ca:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[cs:CBS]]
[[da:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[de:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[es:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[eo:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[fa:سی‌بی‌اس (شبکه)]]
[[fr:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[gl:CBS]]
[[ko:CBS (미국 방송사)]]
[[hi:सीबीएस]]
[[hr:CBS (TV postaja)]]
[[id:CBS]]
[[it:CBS]]
[[he:CBS]]
[[kn:ಸಿಬಿಎಸ್]]
[[lt:CBS]]
[[hu:CBS]]
[[ms:CBS]]
[[nl:CBS (televisiezender)]]
[[ja:CBS]]
[[no:CBS]]
[[nn:CBS]]
[[pl:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[pt:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[ro:CBS]]
[[ru:CBS]]
[[sah:CBS]]
[[sq:Columbia Broadcasting System]]
[[simple:CBS]]
[[sk:CBS]]
[[sr:Си-Би-Ес]]
[[sh:CBS]]
[[fi:CBS]]
[[sv:CBS]]
[[tl:CBS]]
[[te:CBS]]
[[th:ซีบีเอส]]
[[tr:CBS]]
[[uk:CBS]]
[[vi:CBS]]
[[yi:סי בי עס]]
[[zh:哥倫比亞廣播公司]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
