<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="380781" ns="0" title="Common Raven"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{for|the German band named after this bird|Corvus Corax (band)}}
{{for|the butterfly|Papilio castor}}
{{Taxobox
| name=Common Raven
| status = LC
| status_system = iucn3.1 
| status_ref=&lt;ref name=&quot;iucn&quot;&gt;{{IUCN2008|assessors=BirdLife International|year=2009|id=146677|title=Corvus corax|downloaded=23 November 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| image=Common raven by David Hofmann.jpg
| image_caption= At Bodega Head State Park, USA
| regnum=[[Animal]]ia
| phylum=[[Chordate|Chordata]]
| classis=[[Bird|Aves]]
| ordo=[[passerine|Passeriformes]]
| familia=[[Corvidae]]
| genus=''[[Crow|Corvus]]''
| species='''''C. corax'''''
| binomial=''Corvus corax''
| binomial_authority=[[Carl Linnaeus|Linnaeus]], [[10th edition of Systema Naturae|1758]]
| range_map=Corvus_corax_map.jpg
| range_map_width =
| range_map_caption=Common Raven range
| subdivision_ranks=[[Subspecies]]
| subdivision=
8-11, see ''[[#Classification|Classification]]''
}}

The '''Common Raven''' (''Corvus corax''), also known as the '''Northern Raven''', is a large, all-black [[passerine]] bird. Found across the [[northern hemisphere]], it is the most widely distributed of all [[Corvidae|corvids]]. There are at least eight [[subspecies]] with little variation in appearance&amp;mdash; although recent research has demonstrated significant genetic differences among populations from various regions. It is one of the two largest corvids, alongside the [[Thick-billed Raven]], and is possibly the heaviest passerine bird; at maturity, the Common Raven averages 63&amp;nbsp;cm (25&amp;nbsp;inches) in length and 1.2&amp;nbsp;kg (2.6&amp;nbsp;[[Pound (mass)|pounds]]). Common Ravens typically live about 10 to 15 years in the wild, although lifespans of up to 40 years have been recorded. Young birds may travel in flocks, but later mate for life, with each mated pair defending a territory.

The Common Raven has coexisted with humans for thousands of years and in some areas has been so numerous that it is considered a pest. Part of its success comes from its [[omnivore|omnivorous]] diet; Common Ravens are extremely versatile and opportunistic in finding sources of nutrition, feeding on [[carrion]], insects, cereal grains, berries, fruit, small animals, and food waste.

Some remarkable feats of problem-solving have been observed in the species, leading to the belief that it is highly [[intelligence|intelligent]]. Over the centuries, it has been the subject of mythology, folklore, [[Cultural depictions of ravens|art, and literature]]. In many indigenous cultures, including those of [[Norse mythology|Scandinavia]], ancient [[Ireland]] and [[Wales]], [[Bhutan]], the [[Indigenous peoples of the Pacific Northwest Coast|northwest coast of North America]], and [[Indigenous peoples of Siberia|Siberia]] and northeast Asia, the Common Raven has been revered as a spiritual figure or god.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last =Jones | first =Noragh | authorlink = | coauthors = | title =Power of Raven, Wisdom of Serpent | publisher =Floris Books | year =1995 | location = | pages = | url = | doi = | isbn = 0-9402-6266-5 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Taxonomy==
The Common Raven was one of the many species originally described by [[Carolus Linnaeus|Linnaeus]] in his 18th century work, ''[[Systema Naturae]]'', and it still bears its original name of ''Corvus corax''.&lt;ref&gt;{{la icon}} {{cite book | last=Linnaeus | first=Carl | authorlink=Carolus Linnaeus | title=Systema naturae per regna tria naturae, secundum classes, ordines, genera, species, cum characteribus, differentiis, synonymis, locis. Tomus I. Editio decima, reformata. | publisher=Holmiae. (Laurentii Salvii). | year=1758| page=105 | quote = C. ater, dorso caerulescente, cauda subrotundata.}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is the [[type species]] of the genus ''[[Corvus_(genus)#List_of_Species_in_the_genus_Corvus|Corvus]]'', derived from the [[Latin (language)|Latin]] for &quot;Raven&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Simpson | first = D.P. | title = Cassell's Latin Dictionary | publisher = Cassell Ltd. | year = 1979 | edition = 5 | location = London | page = 155 | isbn = 0-304-52257-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; The specific epithet, ''corax''/κοραξ, is the [[Ancient Greek]] word for &quot;raven&quot; or &quot;crow&quot;.&lt;ref name=Liddell1980&gt;{{cite book | author = [[Henry George Liddell|Liddell, Henry George]]; [[Robert Scott (philologist)|Robert Scott]] | year = 1980 | title = [[A Greek-English Lexicon]] (Abridged Edition) | publisher = [[Oxford University Press]] | location = United Kingdom | isbn =0-19-910207-4|page=387}}&lt;/ref&gt; The name &quot;raven&quot; has been applied to several other (generally large) species of the genus ''Corvus'', though they are not necessarily closely related to ''Corvus corax''. Some, such as the [[Australian Raven]] and [[Forest Raven]], are clearly closer to the other Australian crows.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p69&lt;/ref&gt; The original raven is now called the Common or Northern Raven.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Monroe B.L. Jr, Sibley C.G. | title = A World Checklist of Birds | publisher = Yale University Press | year = 1993 | location = | pages = 400 | url = http://www.ornitaxa.com/SM/SMOrg/sm.html | id = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern English word ''raven'' has cognates in all other [[Germanic languages]], including [[Old Norse language|Old Norse]] ''hrafn''&lt;ref&gt;See Oxford English Dictionary entry for &quot;raven.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Old High German]] ''(h)raban'',&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite encyclopedia| title=Raven|encyclopedia=Oxford English Dictionary|editor=J. Simpson, E. Weiner (eds)| year=1989 |edition= 2nd| location=Oxford |publisher=Clarendon Press|isbn= 0-19-861186-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; all which descend from [[Proto-Germanic]] ''*khrabanas''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title=Raven| work=Online Etymology Dictionary| url=http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=raven| accessdate=2007-05-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; An old [[Scots language|Scottish]] word ''corby'' or ''corbie'', akin to the [[French language|French]] ''corbeau'', has been used for both this bird and the [[Carrion Crow]].&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p144&lt;/ref&gt; 
Obsolete [[collective noun]]s for a group of ravens (or at least the Common Raven) include &quot;unkindness&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://baltimorebirdclub.org/gnlist.html | title=Baltimore Bird Club. Group Name for Birds: A Partial List | accessdate=2007-06-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and &quot;conspiracy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ucgc.org/terms-for-collections.htm | title=University of California Golf Club. List of Collective Nouns | accessdate=2008-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In practice, most people use the more generic &quot;flock&quot;.

===Classification===
The closest relatives of the Common Raven are the [[Brown-necked Raven]] ''(C. ruficollis)'' and the [[Pied Crow]] ''(C. albus)'' of Africa, and the [[Chihuahuan Raven]] ''(C. cryptoleucus)'' of the North American southwest.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p70-72&lt;/ref&gt; While some authorities recognized as many as 11 [[subspecies]],&lt;ref name=HBW&gt;Marzluff, J. M. (2009). Common Raven (Corvus corax). pp. 638-639 in: del Hoyo, J., A. Elliott, &amp; D. A. Christie. eds. (2009). ''[[Handbook of the Birds of the World]].'' Bush-shrikes to Old World Sparrows. Lynx Edicions, Barcelona. ISBN 978-84-96553-50-7&lt;/ref&gt; others only recognize eight:&lt;ref name=Clements&gt;Clements, J.F. (2007). ''The Clements Checklist of the Birds of the World.'' 6th edition. Christopher Helm. ISBN 978-0-7136-8695-1&lt;/ref&gt;

* ''C. c. corax'' (the nominate subspecies) occurs from Europe eastwards to [[Lake Baikal]], south to the [[Caucasus]] region and northern [[Iran]]. It has a relatively short, arched bill. The population in south-western Europe (including the [[Balearic Islands]], [[Corsica]] and [[Sardinia]]) has an even more arched bill and shorter wings than &quot;typical&quot; nominate, leading some authorities to recognize it as a separate subspecies, ''C. c. hispanus''.&lt;ref name=HBW/&gt;
* ''C. c. varius'' occurs in [[Iceland]] and the [[Faroe Islands]]. It is less glossy than ''C. c. principalis'' or nominate ''corax'', is intermediate in size, and the bases of its neck feathers are whitish (not visible at a distance). An [[extinct]] [[Polymorphism (biology)|color morph]] found only on the Faroes is known as [[Pied Raven]]
[[File:Krummi 1.jpg|thumb|North Atlantic subspecies (''C. c. varius'') in flight over [[Seltjarnarnes]], [[Iceland]]]]
[[File:3782 Common Raven in flight.jpg|thumb|North American subspecies (''C. c. principalis'') in flight at [[Muir Beach]] in [[Northern California]]]]
* ''C. c. subcorax'' occurs from Greece eastwards to north-west India, [[Central Asia]] and western China though not the [[Himalayas|Himalayan]] region. It is larger than the nominate form, but has relatively short throat feathers (''hackles''). Its plumage is generally all black, though its neck and breast have a brownish tone similar to that of the Brown-necked Raven; this more evident when the plumage is worn. The bases of its neck feathers, although somewhat variable in colour, are often almost whitish. (The name ''C. c. laurencei'' is sometimes used instead of ''C. c. subcorax''.&lt;ref name=HBW/&gt; It is based on the population from [[Sindh]] described by [[Allan Octavian Hume|Hume]] in 1873&lt;ref name=pcr&gt;{{cite book|author=Rasmussen, PC &amp; JC Anderton| year=2005| title=Birds of South Asia: The Ripley Guide. Volume 2|publisher=Smithsonian Institution &amp; Lynx Edicions| pages=600–601}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is sometimes preferred since the type specimen of ''subcorax'' collected by [[Nikolai Severtzov]] is possibly a [[Brown-necked Raven]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Dickinson, E.C., R.W.R.J. Dekker, S. Eck &amp; S. Somadikarta|title= Systematic notes on Asian birds. 45. Types of the Corvidae| journal=Zool. Verh. Leiden |volume=350|year=2004|pages=111–148| url=http://www.repository.naturalis.nl/document/43939}}&lt;/ref&gt;)
* ''C. c. tingitanus'' occurs in North Africa and the [[Canary Islands]]. It is the smallest subspecies, with the shortest throat hackles and a distinctly oily plumage gloss. Its bill is short but markedly stout, and the [[Culmen (bird)|culmen]] is strongly arched. Canary Ravens are browner than the North African Ravens, leading some authorities to treat them as separate subspecies, with the latter maintaining the name ''C. c. tingitanus'' and the former known as ''C. c. canariensis''.&lt;ref name=HBW/&gt;
* ''C. c. tibetanus'' occurs in the Himalayas. It is the largest and glossiest subspecies, with the longest throat hackles. Its bill is large but less imposing than that of ''C. c. principalis'', and the bases of its neck feathers are grey.
* ''C. c. kamtschaticus'' occurs in north-eastern Asia, intergrading into the nominate subspecies in the [[Lake Baikal|Baikal]] region. It is intermediate in size between ''C. c. principalis'' and ''C. c. corax'' and has a distinctly larger and thicker bill than does the nominate race.
* ''C. c. principalis'' occurs in northern North America and [[Greenland]]. It has a large body and the largest bill, its plumage is strongly glossed, and its throat hackles are well developed.
* ''C. c. sinuatus'', the '''Western Raven''', occurs in south-central USA and Central America. It is smaller, with a smaller and narrower bill than ''C. c. principalis''. Populations in far south-western USA and north-western Mexico (including the [[Revillagigedo Islands]]) are the smallest in North America. They are sometimes included in ''C. c. sinuatus'', while other authorities recognize them as a distinct subspecies, ''C. c. clarionensis''.&lt;ref name=HBW/&gt;

===Evolutionary history===
The Common Raven evolved in the [[Old World]] and crossed the [[Bering land bridge]] into North America.&lt;ref&gt;Marzluff and Angell p86&lt;/ref&gt; Recent genetic studies, which examined the [[DNA]] of Common Ravens from across the world, have determined that the birds fall into at least two [[clade]]s: a [[California]] clade, found only in the southwestern United States, and a [[Holarctic]] clade, found across the rest of the northern hemisphere. Birds from both clades look alike, but the groups are genetically distinct and began to diverge about two million years ago.&lt;ref name=USGS/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author= Omland KE, Tarr CL, Boarman WI, Marzluff JM, Fleischer RC |year=2000 |month= |title=Cryptic genetic variation and paraphyly in ravens  |journal=Proceedings of the Royal Society Biological Sciences |volume= Series B|issue=267 |pages=2475–82|doi=10.1098/rspb.2000.1308 |pmid= 11197122 |pmc= 1690844}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The findings indicate that based on mitochondrial DNA, Common Ravens from the rest of the United States are more closely related to those in Europe and Asia than to those in the California clade, and that Common Ravens in the California clade are more closely related to the [[Chihuahuan Raven]] ''(C. cryptoleucus)'' than to those in the Holarctic clade.&lt;ref name=USGS&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.werc.usgs.gov/news/2000-12-19.html|title=California Ravens Are a Breed Apart|accessdate=2007-05-11|author=U.S. Geological Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ravens in the Holarctic clade are more closely related to the [[Pied Crow]] ''(C. albus)'' than they are to the California clade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Feld05&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last=Feldman| first=Christopher R.| coauthor=Kevin E. Omland| month=March| year=2005| title=Phylogenetics of the common raven complex (''Corvus'': Corvidae) and the utility of ND4, COI and intron 7 of the β-fibrinogen gene in avian molecular systematics| journal=Zoologica Scripta|volume=34| issue=2| page=145|doi=10.1111/j.1463-6409.2005.00182.x| pages=145}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the Common Raven species as traditionally delimited is considered to be [[paraphyletic]].&lt;ref name=Feld05/&gt; 

One explanation for these surprising genetic findings is that Common Ravens settled in California at least two million years ago and became separated from their relatives in Europe and Asia during an [[ice age]]. One million years ago, a group from the California clade evolved into a new species, the Chihuahuan Raven. Other members of the Holarctic clade arrived later in a separate migration from Asia, perhaps at the same time as humans.&lt;ref&gt;Marzluff and Angell p86-87&lt;/ref&gt;

A recent study of raven [[mitochondrial DNA]] showed that the isolated population from the Canary Islands is distinct from other populations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bakom06&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| last=Baker| first=Jason M.| coauthor=Kevin E. Omland| month=January| year=2006| title=Canary Island Ravens ''Corvus corax tingitanus'' have distinct mtDNA| journal=Ibis|volume=148| issue=1| page=174| doi=10.1111/j.1474-919X.2006.00493.x| pages=174}}&lt;/ref&gt; The study did not include any individuals from the North African population,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bakom06&quot;/&gt; and its position is therefore unclear, though its [[Morphology (biology)|morphology]] is very close to the population of the Canaries (to the extent that the two are often considered part of a single subspecies).&lt;ref name=Clements/&gt;

== Description ==
[[File:Raven Cypress Provincial Park 2.JPG|thumb|left|In sunlight, the [[plumage]] can display a blue or purple sheen which is due to [[iridescence]].]] 
A mature Common Raven ranges between 56 and 78&amp;nbsp;cm (22 to 30&amp;nbsp;inches) in length, with a [[wingspan]] of 100 to 150&amp;nbsp;cm (40 to 59 in).&lt;ref&gt;[http://nature.ca/notebooks/english/raven.htm Nature.ca]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.garden-birds.co.uk/birds/raven.htm Garden-birds.co.uk]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://geobirds.com/fieldguide/common_raven Geobirds.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Recorded weights range from 0.69 to 2&amp;nbsp;kg (1.5 to 4.4&amp;nbsp;lb),&lt;ref name=&quot;Boarman_Heinrich&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Boarman| first=W.I.|coauthor=B. Heinrich| year=1999| title=Common Raven (''Corvus corax'')| journal=Birds of North America| volume=476| pages=1–32|doi=10.2173/bna.476|last2=Heinrich|first2=Bernd|last3=Poole|first3=A.|last4=Gill|first4=F.|editor1-last=Poole|editor1-first=A.|editor2-last=Gill|editor2-first=F.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oiseaux-birds.com/card-common-raven.html Oiseaux-birds.com]&lt;/ref&gt; thus making the Common Raven one of the heaviest [[passerine]]s. Birds from colder regions such as the Himalayas and Greenland are generally larger with slightly larger bills, while those from warmer regions are smaller with proportionally smaller bills.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p138-139&lt;/ref&gt; The [[beak|bill]] is large and slightly curved. It has a longish, strongly graduated tail, mostly black [[iridescent]] plumage, and a dark brown [[Iris (anatomy)|iris]]. The throat feathers are elongated and pointed and the bases of the neck feathers are pale brownish-grey. Juvenile plumage is similar but duller with a blue-grey iris.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p138&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from its greater size, the Common Raven differs from its cousins, the [[crow]]s, by having a larger and heavier, black beak, shaggy feathers around the throat and above the beak, and a wedge-shaped tail.&lt;ref name=&quot;observerbook&quot;/&gt; The species has a distinctive, deep, resonant ''prruk-prruk-prruk'' call, which to experienced listeners is unlike that of any other corvid. Its very wide and complex vocabulary includes a high, knocking ''toc-toc-toc'', a dry, grating ''kraa'', a low guttural rattle and some calls of an almost musical nature.&lt;ref name =&quot;Gwinner64&quot;&gt;{{de icon}} {{cite journal|doi=10.1111/j.1439-0310.1964.tb01212.x|last=Gwinner| first=E.| year=1964| title=Untersuchungen über das ausdrucks und Sozialverhalten des Kolkraben (''Corvus corax'' L.)| journal=Zeitschrift für Tierpsychologie| volume=21| issue=6| pages=657–748}}&lt;/ref&gt; In flight the feathers produce a creaking sound that has been likened to the rustle of silk.&lt;ref name=hbk/&gt;

Common Ravens can be very long-lived, especially in captive or protected conditions; [[Ravens of the Tower of London|individuals at the Tower of London]] have lived for more than 40 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boarman_Heinrich&quot;/&gt; Lifespans in the wild are considerably shorter: typically only 10 to 15 years. The longest known lifespan of a [[bird ringing|banded]] wild Common Raven was 23 years, 3 months.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.euring.org/data_and_codes/longevity-voous.htm |title=European Longevity Records |publisher=European Union for Bird Ringing |accessdate=5 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Distribution and habitat ==
[[File:Raven's Craig Glen.JPG|thumb|Typical Raven habitat - Raven's Craig Glen, Dalry, Ayrshire, Scotland.]]
[[File:Corvus corax jouveniles.jpeg|thumb|left|Two juveniles in [[Iceland]]]]
Common Ravens can thrive in varied climates; indeed this species has the largest range of any member of the genus.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Helm&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Madge |first=Steve| authorlink=Steve Madge |title=Crows and jays : a guide to the crows, jays and magpies of the world| year=1999| origyear=1994| series=[[Helm Identification Guides]] |publisher=Christopher Helm| location=London| isbn=0-7136-3999-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; They range throughout the [[Holarctic]] from [[Arctic]] and [[temperate]] habitats in North America and [[Eurasia]] to the deserts of North Africa, and to islands in the Pacific Ocean. In the [[British Isles]], they are more common in [[Scotland]], [[Wales]], northern England and the west of Ireland.&lt;ref name=&quot;observerbook&quot;&gt;{{cite book | last=Vere Benson| first= S. | year=1972 | title=The Observer's Book of Birds | publisher=Frederick Warne &amp; Co. Ltd | location=London | isbn= 0-7232-1513-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Tibet]], they have been recorded at altitudes up to 5,000&amp;nbsp;m (16,400&amp;nbsp;ft), and as high as 6,350&amp;nbsp;m (20,600&amp;nbsp;ft) on [[Mount Everest]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Helm&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| author=Hingston, R W G|year=1927 | title=Bird notes from the Mount Everest expedition of 1924|pages=320–329|journal=J. Bombay Nat. Hist. Soc.|volume=32| issue=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; The population sometimes known as the Punjab Raven — described as ''Corvus corax laurencei'' (also spelt ''lawrencii'' or ''laurencii'') by [[Allan Octavian Hume]] but more often considered synonymous with ''subcorax''&lt;ref name=pcr/&gt; — is restricted to the [[Sindh]] district of Pakistan and adjoining regions of northwestern India.&lt;ref name=hbk&gt;{{cite book|author=Ali, S &amp; S D Ripley| title=Handbook of the birds of India and Pakistan|edition=2|publisher=Oxford University Press|volume= 5|year= 1986|pages =261–265 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|author=Eates,KR |year=1939 |title= The distribution and nidification of the Indian (Punjab) Raven (''Corvus corax laurencei'' Hume) in Sind|journal= J. Bombay Nat. Hist. Soc.|volume=40|issue=4|pages=747–750}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Except in Arctic habitats,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last=Salomonsen| first=Finn| title=Gronlands Fugle = Birds of Greenland| year=1950| location=Copenhagen| publisher=Munksgaard|id={{LCCN|a+51|000|710}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; they are generally resident within their range for the whole year. Young birds may disperse locally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodwin. p139&quot;&gt;Goodwin. p139&lt;/ref&gt;

In the [[Faroe Islands]] a now extinct colour-morph of this species existed, known as the [[Pied Raven]].&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}}{{Cite journal | last = Droste | first = Ferdinand Baron von | title = Vogelfauna der Färöer (Färöernes Fuglefauna af Sysselmaand Müller 1862.) Aus dem Dänischen übersetzt und mit Anmerkungen versehen. Teil 1 | journal = [[Journal of Ornithology|J. Ornithol.]] | volume = 17 | issue = 2 | pages = 107–118 | year = 1869 | doi = 10.1007/BF02261546}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Most Common Ravens prefer wooded areas, with large expanses of open land nearby, or coastal regions for their nesting sites and feeding grounds. In some areas of dense human population, such as [[California]] in the United States, they take advantage of a plentiful food supply and have seen a surge in their numbers.&lt;ref name=mojave/&gt;

== Behaviour ==
Common Ravens usually travel in mated pairs, although young birds may form [[Flock (birds)|flocks]]. Relationships between Common Ravens are often quarrelsome, yet they demonstrate considerable devotion to their families.&lt;ref name=Oregon/&gt;

=== Diet ===
[[File:Common Raven Nationalpark Bayerischer Wald 01.jpg|thumb|left|Feeding]]
Common Ravens are [[omnivorous]] and highly opportunistic: their diet may vary widely with location, season and [[serendipity]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Nogales&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Nogales |first=Manuel |coauthors=Elizabeth C. Hernández |year=1997 |title=Diet of Common Ravens on El Hierro, Canary Islands |journal=Journal of Field Ornithology |volume=68 |issue=3 |pages=382–391 |url= http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/JFO/v068n03/p0382-p0391.pdf| accessdate=2007-05-16|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, those foraging on [[tundra]] on the [[Arctic North Slope]] of [[Alaska]] obtained about half their energy needs from predation, mainly of [[Microtus|microtine rodents]], and half by scavenging, mainly of [[caribou]] and [[rock ptarmigan|ptarmigan]] carcasses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Temple&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Temple |first= Stanley A. |year=1974 |month=March |title=Winter food habits of Ravens on the Arctic Slope of Alaska |journal=Arctic |volume=27 |issue=1 |pages=41–46 |url=http://pubs.aina.ucalgary.ca/arctic/Arctic27-1-41.pdf| accessdate=1007-05-16|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Common raves landfill.jpg|thumb|Flock feeding at a garbage dump]]
In some places they are mainly [[scavenger]]s, feeding on [[carrion]] as well as the associated [[maggots]] and [[carrion beetle]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Nelson |first= A.L. |year=1934 |month=January |title=Some early summer food preferences of the American Raven in southeastern Oregon |journal=Condor |volume=36 |issue=1 |pages=10–15 |url=http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/Condor/files/issues/v036n01/p0010-p0015.pdf| accessdate=2007-05-16 |doi=10.2307/1363515|format=PDF |jstor=1363515 |publisher=Cooper Ornithological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt; Plant food includes [[cereal|cereal grains]], [[berries]] and [[fruit]]. They prey on small [[invertebrate]]s, [[amphibians]], [[reptile]]s, small [[mammals]] and birds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Gaston| first=A.J.| coauthor=R.D. Elliot| year=1996| title=Predation by Ravens ''Corvus corax'' on [[Brunnich's Guillemot]] ''Uria lomvia'' eggs and chicks and its possible impact on breeding site selection|journal=Ibis |volume=138| pages=742–748| doi=10.1111/j.1474-919X.1996.tb08831.x| issue=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ravens may also consume the undigested portions of animal [[feces]], and human [[food waste]]. They store surplus food items, especially those containing fat, and will learn to hide such food out of the sight of other Common Ravens.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goodwin. p139&quot;/&gt; Ravens also raid the food caches of other species, such as the [[Arctic Fox]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Careau |first=Vincent |coauthors=Nicolas Lecomte, Jean-François Giroux and Dominique Berteaux |year=2007 |month=January |title=Common ravens raid arctic fox food caches |journal=Journal of Ethology |volume=25 |issue=1 |pages=79–82 |doi=10.1007/s10164-006-0193-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; They sometimes associate with another canine, the [[Grey Wolf]], as a [[kleptoparasite]], following to scavenge wolf-kills in winter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Stahler |first=Daniel |coauthors=Bernd Heinrich and Douglas Smith |year=2002 |month=August |title=Common ravens, ''Corvus corax'', preferentially associate with grey wolves, ''Canis lupus'', as a foraging strategy in winter |journal=Animal Behaviour |volume=64 |issue=2 |pages=283–290 |doi=10.1006/anbe.2002.3047}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ravens are regular predators at bird nests and are considered a threat to the nesting success of the endangered [[California Condor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=The Condor |title=Nest-site Biology of the California Condor |first1=Noel F. R. |last1=Snyder |first2=Rob R. |last2=Ramey |first3=Fred C |last3=Sibley |volume=88 |issue=2 |pages=228–241 |url=http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/Condor/files/issues/v088n02/p0228-p0241.pdf |format=PDF |doi=10.2307/1368920 |year=1986}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

Due to its size, gregariousness and its defensive abilities, the Common Raven has few natural predators. Predators of its eggs include [[owl]]s, [[marten]]s, and other ravens. Ravens are quite vigorous at defending their young and are usually successful at driving off perceived threats, including passing humans. There are records of predation by [[Golden Eagle]]s, with which ravens overlap considerably in range across the Northern Hemisphere. The [[Eurasian Eagle Owl]] and the [[Great Horned Owl]] have been recorded as grabbing ravens off of their nocturnal perches. Due to the fact that they are potential hazardous prey for raptorial birds, raptors usually must take them by surprise and most attacks are on fledgling ravens. Rarely, large mammalian predators such as [[lynx]]es, [[coyote]]s, and [[cougar]]s have attacked ravens. This principally occurs at a nest site and when other prey for the carnivores are scarce. Due to such predators, ravens are highly wary around novel carrion sites and, in [[North America]], have been recorded waiting for [[American Crow]]s and [[Blue Jay]]s to approach carrion first before they themselves move in.&lt;ref&gt;[http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Corvus_corax.html Animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu]&lt;/ref&gt;

Common Ravens nesting near sources of human [[Food waste|garbage]] included a higher percentage of food waste in their diet, birds nesting near roads consumed more [[roadkill|road-killed]] [[vertebrate]]s, and those nesting far from these sources of food ate more [[arthropod]]s and plant material. [[Fledging]] success was higher for those using human garbage as a food source.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kristan&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Kristan |first=William B. |coauthors=William I. Boarman and John J. Crayon |year=2004 |month=March |title=Diet composition of common ravens across the urban-wildland interface of the West Mojave Desert |url=http://www.werc.usgs.gov/sandiego/pdfs/kristan%20boarman%20and%20crayon%202004%20WSB.pdf |format=PDF|journal=Wildlife Society Bulletin |volume=32 |issue=1 |pages=244–253 |doi=10.2193/0091-7648(2004)32[244:DCOCRA]2.0.CO;2 |issn=0091-7648}}&lt;/ref&gt; In contrast, a 1984-1986 study of Common Raven diet in an agricultural region of south-western [[Idaho]] found that cereal grains were the principal constituent of [[pellet (ornithology)|pellet]]s, though small mammals, grasshoppers, cattle carrion and birds were also eaten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Engel |first=Kathleen A. |coauthors=Leonard S. Young |year=1989 |month=May |title=Spatial and temporal patterns in the diet of Common Ravens in southwestern Idaho |journal=Condor |volume=91 |issue= 2|pages=372–378 |url=http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/Condor/files/issues/v091n02/p0372-p0378.pdf| accessdate=2005-05-16 |doi=10.2307/1368316|format=PDF |jstor=1368316 |publisher=Cooper Ornithological Society}}&lt;/ref&gt;

One behavior is recruitment, where juvenile ravens call other ravens to a food bonanza, usually a carcass, with a series of loud yells. In ''Ravens in Winter,'' [[Bernd Heinrich]] posited that this behavior evolved to allow the juveniles to outnumber the resident adults, thus allowing them to feed on the carcass without being chased away.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bernd89&quot;&gt;{{cite book| last=Heinrich| first=Bernd| authorlink=Bernd Heinrich| year=1989| title=Ravens in Winter|location=New York|publisher=Summit Books| isbn=0-671-67809-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; A more mundane explanation is that individuals co-operate in sharing information about carcasses of large mammals because they are too big for just a few birds to exploit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinrich, B. 1999 pp 119-120&quot;&gt;Heinrich, B. (1999). ''Mind of the Raven: Investigations and Adventures with Wolf-Birds'' pp 119-120. New York: Cliff Street Books. ISBN 978-0-06-093063-9&lt;/ref&gt; Experiments with baits however show that such recruitment behaviour is independent of the size of the bait.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|title=Winter foraging at carcasses by three sympatric corvids, with emphasis on recruitment by the raven, ''Corvus corax''|journal=Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology | doi=10.1007/BF00300349|volume =23| issue=3| year= 1988 | pages=141–156| last=Heinrich| first=Bernd}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Breeding ===
[[File:Ravens nest Lastef.jpg|left|thumb|Young on a nest - Hvítserkur, [[Iceland]]]]
Juveniles begin to court at a very early age, but may not bond for another two or three years. Aerial acrobatics, demonstrations of intelligence, and ability to provide food are key behaviors of courting. Once paired, they tend to nest together for life, usually in the same location.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oregon&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oregonzoo.org/Cards/BirdsOfPrey/commonraven.htm|title= Oregon Zoo Animals: Common Raven|accessdate=2007-05-19 |work= | archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070429120446/http://www.oregonzoo.org/Cards/BirdsOfPrey/commonraven.htm| archivedate = April 29, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; Instances of non-monogamy have been observed in Common Ravens, by males visiting a female's nest when her mate is away.&lt;ref name=&quot;Heinrich, B. 1999 pp 119-120&quot;/&gt;

Breeding pairs must have a territory of their own before they begin nest-building and reproduction, and thus aggressively defend a territory and its food resources. Nesting territories vary in size according to the density of food resources in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Boarman_Heinrich&quot;/&gt; The nest is a deep bowl made of large sticks and twigs, bound with an inner layer of roots, mud, and bark and lined with a softer material, such as [[deer]] fur. The nest is usually placed in a large tree or on a cliff ledge, or less frequently in old buildings or utility poles.&lt;ref&gt;Savage p35&lt;/ref&gt;

Females lay between three to seven pale bluish-green, brown-blotched eggs.&lt;ref name=&quot;observerbook&quot;/&gt; Incubation is about 18 to 21 days, by the female only. However, the male may stand or crouch over the young, sheltering but not actually [[brooding]] them.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} {{cite journal |last=Gwinner |first=Eberhard |year=1965 |month=April |title=Beobachtungen über Nestbau und Brutpflege des Kolkraben (''Corvus corax'' L.) in Gefangenschaft |journal=Journal of Ornithology |volume=106 |issue=2 |pages=145–178 |doi=10.1007/BF01793758}}&lt;/ref&gt; Young [[fledge]] at 35 to 42 days, and are fed by both parents. They stay with their parents for another six months after fledging.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p141&lt;/ref&gt;

In most of their range, egg laying begins in late February. In colder climates, it is later, e.g. April in [[Greenland]] and [[Tibet]]. In Pakistan, egg-laying takes place in December.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helm&quot;/&gt; Eggs and hatchlings are rarely preyed on by large [[hawk]]s and [[eagle]]s, large [[owl]]s, [[marten]]s and [[canid]]s. The adults, which are very rarely predated, are often successful in defending their young from these predators, due to their numbers, large size and cunning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |accessdate=2008-06-03 |author=Berg R, Dewey T |year=1999 |publisher=University of Michigan
|url=http://animaldiversity.ummz.umich.edu/site/accounts/information/Corvus_corax.html |title=&quot;Corvus corax&quot; (On-line), Animal Diversity Web. }}&lt;/ref&gt; They have been observed dropping stones on potential predators that venture close to their nests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |journal=Condor |title=The apparent use of rocks by a raven in nest defense |first=Stewart W. |last=Janes |url=http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/Condor/files/issues/v078n03/p0409-p0409.pdf |volume=78 |issue=3 |page=409 |year=1976 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Vocalization ===
Like other corvids, Ravens can mimic sounds from their environment, including human speech. They have a wide range of [[Bird vocalization|vocalization]]s, which remain an object of interest to [[ornithologist]]s. Gwinner carried out important studies in the early 1960s, recording and photographing his findings in great detail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gwinner64&quot;/&gt;

Fifteen to 30 categories of vocalization have been recorded for this species, most of which are used for [[social]] interaction. Calls recorded include alarm calls, chase calls, and flight calls. Non-vocal sounds produced by the Common Raven include wing whistles and bill snapping. Clapping or clicking has been observed more often in females than in males. If a member of a pair is lost, its mate reproduces the calls of its lost partner to encourage its return.&lt;ref&gt;Goodwin. p142&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Intelligence ===
{{see also|Bird intelligence|Corvidae#Intelligence}}
[[File:Corvuscorax001.jpg|thumb|At the Norwegian Island of [[Runde]]]]

{{quote|Crows, ravens, magpies, and jays are not just feathered machines, rigidly programmed by their genetics. Instead, they are beings that, within the constraints of their molecular inheritance, make complex decisions and show every sign of enjoying a rich awareness.|[[Candace Savage]]&lt;ref name=birdinblack/&gt;}}

The brains of Common Ravens count among the largest of any bird species. Specifically, their [[hyperpallium]] is large (see [[avian pallium]]). For a bird, they display ability in problem solving, as well as other [[cognitive]] processes such as [[imitation]] and [[Insight phenomenology|insight]].&lt;ref name=birdinblack/&gt;

One experiment designed to evaluate insight and [[problem-solving]] ability involved a piece of meat attached to a string hanging from a perch. To reach the food, the bird needed to stand on the perch, pull the string up a little at a time, and step on the loops to gradually shorten the string. Four of five Common Ravens eventually succeeded, and &quot;the transition from no success (ignoring the food or merely yanking at the string) to constant reliable access (pulling up the meat) occurred with no demonstrable [[trial-and-error]] learning.&quot; This supports the hypothesis that Common Ravens are 'inventors'; that is, they have the ability to solve problems presented to them. Many of the Common Raven's [[problem-solving]] skills were formerly thought to be instinctive, but it is becoming clear that Common Ravens are actually quite intelligent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Heinrich |first=Bernd |year=1995 |month= |title=An Experimental Investigation of Insight in Common Ravens (Corvus Corax)|journal=The Auk|volume= 112|issue=4 |pages=994–1003 |url=http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/Auk/v112n04/p0994-p1003.pdf |accessdate= 2007-05-16|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Common Ravens have been observed to manipulate others into doing work for them, such as by calling [[wolves]] and [[coyote]]s to the site of dead animals. The canines open the carcass, making it more accessible to the birds.&lt;ref name=birdinblack&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pbs.org/wnet/nature/ravens/ravens.html|title= PBS Nature: The Bird in Black|accessdate=2007-05-07 |work= |publisher=[[Public Broadcasting Service]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; They watch where other Common Ravens bury their food and remember the locations of each other's food caches, so they can steal from them. This type of theft occurs so regularly that Common Ravens will fly extra distances from a food source to find better hiding places for food.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gi.alaska.edu/ScienceForum/ASF14/1426.html |title= The Raven's Game of Hide and Seek| accessdate=2007-05-07 |last=Rozell|first= Ned| work=Alaska Science Forum| publisher=Geophysical Institute, University of Alaska Fairbanks}}&lt;/ref&gt; They have also been observed pretending to make a cache without actually depositing the food, presumably to confuse onlookers.&lt;ref&gt;Marzluff and Angell p230&lt;/ref&gt;[[File:Old NIKE Missile radar dome with ravens.JPG|thumb|left|Dilapidated NIKE Missile radar dome in Alaska with an evening roost]]

Common Ravens are known to steal and cache shiny objects such as pebbles, pieces of metal, and golf balls. One theory is that they hoard shiny objects to impress other ravens.&lt;ref&gt;Marzluff and Angell p232&lt;/ref&gt; Other research indicates that juveniles are deeply curious about all new things, and that Common Ravens retain an attraction to bright, round objects based on their similarity to bird eggs. Mature birds lose their intense interest in the unusual, and become highly [[neophobia|neophobic]].&lt;ref&gt;Kijne M &amp; Kotrschal K (2002) &quot;Neophobia affects choice of food-item size in group-foraging common ravens (''Corvus corax'')&quot;. ''Acta ethologica'' '''5'''(1): 13-18&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Playful behavior ===
In recent years, biologists have recognized that birds engage in [[play (activity)|play]]. Juvenile Common Ravens are among the most playful of bird species. They have been observed to slide down snowbanks, apparently purely for fun. They even engage in games with other species, such as playing catch-me-if-you-can with wolves and dogs.&lt;ref&gt;Savage pp70 - 71&lt;/ref&gt; Common Ravens are known for spectacular aerobatic displays, such as flying in loops or interlocking talons with each other in flight.&lt;ref&gt;Savage p76&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Heinrich, B. (1999). ''Mind of the Raven: Investigations and Adventures with Wolf-Birds'' pp 290. New York: Cliff Street Books. ISBN 978-0-06-093063-9&lt;/ref&gt;

They are also one of only a few species who make their own toys. They have been observed breaking off twigs to play with socially.&lt;ref&gt;Heinrich, B. (1999). ''Mind of the Raven: Investigations and Adventures with Wolf-Birds'' pp 282. New York: Cliff Street Books. ISBN 978-0-06-093063-9&lt;/ref&gt;

== Relationship with humans ==
=== Conservation and management===
[[File:Corvus corax and half dome.jpg|thumb|By [[Half Dome]] Yosemite]]
Common Ravens are widely distributed and are not currently in danger of [[extinction]]. In some parts of their range, there have been localised declines due to [[habitat loss]] and direct persecution. Compared to many smaller ''[[Corvus]]'' species (such as [[American Crow]]), ravens prefer undisturbed montane or forest habitat or rural areas over urban areas.&lt;ref&gt;[http://elibrary.unm.edu/sora/wb/v33n03/p0202-p0217.pdf Elibrary.unm.edu]&lt;/ref&gt; In other areas, their numbers have increased dramatically and they have become [[agriculture|agricultural]] [[Pest (organism)|pests]]. Common Ravens can cause damage to crops, such as nuts and grain, or can harm livestock, particularly by killing young [[Goat|goat kids]], [[Domestic sheep|lambs]] and [[Cattle|calves]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Larsen |first=Kenneth H. |coauthors=John H. Dietrich |year=1970 |month=January |title=Reduction of a raven population on lambing grounds with DRC-1339 |journal=Journal of Wildlife Management |volume=34 |issue=1 |pages=200–204 |doi=10.2307/3799509 |publisher=Allen Press |jstor=3799509}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ravens generally attack the faces of young livestock, but the more common Raven behavior of scavenging may be misidentified as predation by ranchers.&lt;ref name=&quot;nass&quot;&gt;{{Cite book| publication-date =May 6, 2005 | title =Sheep and Goats Death Loss  | publisher =[[National Agricultural Statistics Service]] | url =http://usda.mannlib.cornell.edu/MannUsda/viewDocumentInfo.do?documentID=1628 | accessdate = 2007-12-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the western [[Mojave desert]], human settlement and land development have led to an estimated 16-fold increase in the Common Raven population over 25 years. Towns, landfills, sewage treatment plants and artificial ponds create sources of food and water for scavenging birds. Ravens also find nesting sites in utility poles and ornamental trees, and are attracted to roadkill on highways. The explosion in the Common Raven population in the Mojave has raised concerns for the [[desert tortoise]], a [[threatened species]]. Common Ravens prey upon juvenile tortoises, which have soft shells and are slow-moving.&lt;ref name=mojave&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.usgs.gov/newsroom/article.asp?ID=160|title=Scientists Estimate Risk of Raven Predation on Desert Tortoises in the Western Mojave Desert|accessdate=2007-05-11|author=U.S. Geological Survey}}&lt;/ref&gt; Plans to control the population have included shooting and trapping birds, as well as contacting landfill operators to ask that they reduce the amount of exposed garbage.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite conference | first = WI | last = Boarman | title = The Raven Management Program of the Bureau of Land Management : Status as of 1992 | pages = 113–117| booktitle = Proceedings of 1992 Symposium | publisher = | year = 1993 | location = California | url = http://www.werc.usgs.gov/sandiego/pdfs/Boarman_1993_DTCS_RavenManagementProgram.pdf | accessdate = 2007-05-21 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; A hunting bounty as a method of control was historically used in Finland from the mid-18th century until 1923.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal | author = Pohja-Mykrä M, Vuorisalo T, Mykrä S
 | title = Hunting bounties as a key measure of historical wildlife management and game conservation: Finnish bounty schemes 1647–1975 | journal = Oryx | volume = 39 | issue = 3 | pages = 284–291 | year = 2005 | doi = 10.1017/S0030605305000785}}&lt;/ref&gt; Culling has taken place to a limited extent in [[Alaska]], where the population increase in Common Ravens is threatening the vulnerable [[Steller's Eider]] ''(Polysticta stelleri)''.&lt;ref name =&quot;MMS2007&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author = Minerals Management Service, Alaska | title = Foraging Ecology of Common Ravens (''Corvus corax'') on Alaska's Coastal Plain (AK-93-48-51) | publisher = Minerals Management Service | year = 2007 | url = http://www.mms.gov/alaska/ess/ongoing_studies/biology/Gleason%20-%207B.pdf | accessdate = 2007-05-24|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Cultural depictions ===
[[File:Bill Reid raven.jpg|thumb|right|[[Bill Reid]]'s sculpture ''The Raven and The First Men'', showing part of a [[Haida mythology|Haida]] creation myth. Museum of Anthropology, [[University of British Columbia]].]]
{{See also|Cultural depictions of ravens}}

Across its range in the northern hemisphere, and throughout human history, the Common Raven has been a powerful symbol and a popular subject of mythology and folklore.

In many post-conversion [[Western culture|Western tradition]]s, ravens have long been considered to be birds of ill omen and death, in part because of the negative symbolism of their all-[[Black#Beliefs.2C_religions_and_superstitions|black]] plumage and the eating of [[carrion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wildlife.alaska.gov/index.cfm?adfg=birds.raven |title=Raven: The Northern Bird of Paradox |accessdate=2007-02-12 |last=Schwan |first=Mark |year=1990 |month=January |publisher=Alaska Fish and Game}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Sweden, ravens are known as the ghosts of murdered people, and in Germany as the souls of the damned. In [[Danish folklore]], [[valravn]]e that ate a king's heart gained human knowledge, could perform great malicious acts, could lead people astray, had superhuman powers, and were &quot;terrible animals&quot;.&lt;ref name=KRISTENSEN132&gt;Kristensen, Evald Tang. (1980) ''Danske Sagn: Som De Har Lyd I Folkemunde'', page 132. Nyt Nordisk Forlag Arnold Busck, Copenhagen. ISBN 87-17-02791-8&lt;/ref&gt;

As in traditional mythology and folklore, the Common Raven features frequently in more modern writings such as the works of [[William Shakespeare]], and, perhaps most famously, in the poem &quot;[[The Raven]]&quot; by [[Edgar Allan Poe]]. Ravens have appeared in the works of [[Charles Dickens]],&lt;ref&gt;Dickens, Charles (1841) ''[[Barnaby Rudge: A Tale of the Riots of 'Eighty]]'' [http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/917 online]&lt;/ref&gt; [[J. R. R. Tolkien]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | authorlink = J. R. R. Tolkien | title = [[The Hobbit]] | publisher = Ballantine Books | year = 1985 | isbn = 0-345-33207-5 | author = J. R. R. Tolkien. | unused_data = Tolkien, J. R. R. = }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stephen King]],&lt;ref&gt;King, Stephen (1976). ''[[The Dark Tower: The Gunslinger]].'' ISBN 0-8488-0780-4&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Joan Aiken]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Aiken | first = Joan | authorlink = Joan Aiken | title = Tales of Arabel's Raven | publisher = Cape | year = 1974 | pages = 160 | isbn = 0-224-01059-X}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Aiken | first = Joan | authorlink = Joan Aiken | title = Arabel and Mortimer | publisher = Cape | year = 1980 | pages = 144 | isbn = 0-224-01765-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Aiken, Joan | authorlink = Joan Aiken | title = Mortimer's Cross | publisher = Cape | year = 1983 | pages = 141 | isbn = 0-224-02108-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Aiken, Joan | authorlink = Joan Aiken | title = Mortimer Says Nothing and other stories | publisher = Cape | year = 1985 | pages = 181 | isbn = 0-224-02335-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; among others.  

It continues to be used as a symbol in areas where it once had mythological status: as the [[List of national birds|National Bird]] of Bhutan,&lt;ref name = &quot;ravenbhutan&quot;/&gt; Official Bird of the [[Yukon]] territory,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.gov.yk.ca/aboutyukon/emblemsandsymbols.html#Official_Bird |title=Yukon Territorial Bird| publisher=Government of Yukon| accessdate=2007-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and on the Coat of Arms of the [[Isle of Man]] (once a Viking colony).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Isle of Man Government | title = Island Facts - Isle of Man Government | work = | publisher = Isle of Man Government | url = http://www.gov.im/isleofman/facts.xml | accessdate = 2007-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Baltimore Ravens]] of the [[National Football League]] have had a raven named &quot;Poe&quot; as their official mascot since the [[Cleveland Browns]] relocated in 1995.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.baltimoreravens.com/Ravenstown/Mascots.aspx|title = Official website of the Baltimore Ravens mascot Poe|unused_data = &quot;Baltimore Ravens&quot;|retrieved: October 19, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The modern [[unisex given name]] ''[[Raven (given name)|Raven]]'' is derived from the English word &quot;raven&quot;. As a masculine name, ''Raven'' parallels the Old Norse ''[[Hrafn]]'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Hanks-226&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last1=Hanks |first1=Patrick |last2=Hardcastle |authorlink1=Patrick Hanks |first2=Kate |last3=Hodges |first3=Flavia |title=A Dictionary of First Names |edition=2nd |series=Oxford Paperback Reference |year=2006 |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |location=[[Oxford]] |isbn=978-0-19-861060-1 |page=226 |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt; and Old English ''*Hræfn'', which were both [[byname]]s and [[personal names]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reaney&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Reaney |first=Percy Hilde |coauthors=Wilson, Richard Middlewood |title=A Dictionary of English Surnames |edition=3rd |year=2006 |publisher=[[Routledge]] |location=London |isbn=0-203-99355-1 |page=2594 |postscript=&lt;!-- Bot inserted parameter. Either remove it; or change its value to &quot;.&quot; for the cite to end in a &quot;.&quot;, as necessary. --&gt;{{inconsistent citations}} }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Mythology ===
{{Main|Raven in mythology}}
[[File:Valkyrie and raven.jpg|thumb|A [[valkyrie]] speaks with a raven in a 19th century illustration of the [[Old Norse]] poem ''[[Hrafnsmál]]'' (&quot;raven song&quot;) by [[Anthony Frederick Augustus Sandys]]]]
Many [[indigenous peoples of the Pacific Northwest Coast]] of North America and [[Russian Far East|northeast Asia]] revered it as a [[Raven (mythology)|god]]. In [[History_of_the_Tlingit#Creation_story_and_the_Raven_Cycle|Tlingit]] and [[Haida mythology|Haida cultures]], Raven was both a Trickster and Creator god.  Related beliefs are widespread among the peoples of [[Siberia]] and northeast Asia.&lt;ref&gt;W. Bogoras. (1902) The Folklore of Northeastern Asia, as Compared with That of Northwestern America. American Anthropologist, 4:4, pp. 577-683.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Kamchatka peninsula]], for example, was supposed to have been created by the raven god [[Kutkh]].&lt;ref&gt;D.D. Worth (1961). ''Kamchadal Texts Collected by W. Jochelson'', 's-Gravenhage, Mouton.&lt;/ref&gt; There are several references to Common Ravens in the [[Old Testament]] of the [[Bible]] and it is an aspect of [[Mahakala]] in [[Bhutan]]ese mythology.&lt;ref name = &quot;ravenbhutan&quot;&gt;{{cite web | author = Bhutan Tourism Corporation | title = The Himalaya Kingdom | publisher = Bhutan Tourism Corporation | url = http://www.kingdomofbhutan.com/kingdom/kingdom_2_.html | accessdate = 2007-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Norse mythology]], [[Huginn and Muninn|Huginn]] (from Old Norse &quot;thought&quot;) and [[Huginn and Muninn|Muninn]] (Old Norse &quot;memory&quot;or &quot;mind&quot;) are a pair of ravens that fly all over the world, [[Midgard]], and bring the god [[Odin]] information. Additionally among the Norse, [[Raven banner]] standards were carried by such figures as the [[Earl of Orkney|Jarls of Orkney]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Trans. Pálsson, Hermann and Edwards, Paul | title = Orkneyinga Saga: The History of the Earls of Orkney | publisher = Hogarth Press | year = 1978 | location = London | isbn= 0-7012-0431-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; King [[Canute the Great]] of England, Norway and Denmark,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author = Campbell, Alistair | coauthors = Keynes, Simon | title = Encomium Emmae Reginae | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 1998 | location = Cambridge | isbn= 0-521-62655-2 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Harald III of Norway|Harald Hardrada]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Sturluson|first= Snorri | title = King Harald's Saga: Harald Hardradi of Norway: From Snorri Sturluson's Heimskringla | publisher = Penguin | year = 2005 | isbn=0-14-044183-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[British Isles]], ravens also were symbolic to the [[Celt]]s. In [[Irish mythology]], the goddess [[Morrígan]] alighted on the hero [[Cú Chulainn]]'s shoulder in the form of a raven after his death.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Jones, M | title = The Death of Cu Chulainn | publisher = Academy for Ancient Texts | url = http://www.ancienttexts.org/library/celtic/ctexts/cuchulain3.html | accessdate = 2007-05-19}}&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Welsh mythology]] they were associated with the Welsh god [[Bran the Blessed]], whose name translates to &quot;raven.&quot; According to the ''[[Mabinogion]]'', Bran's head was buried in the White Hill of London as a talisman against invasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Ford | first = Patrick K. | title = The Mabinogi and Other Medieval Welsh Tales | chapter = Branwen daughter of Llŷr | publisher = University of California Press | year = 1977 | location = Berkeley | pages = | isbn= 0-520-03414-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Tower of London====
{{Main|Ravens of the Tower of London}}
A legend developed that England would not fall to a foreign invader so long as there were ravens at the [[Tower of London]]; although this is often thought to be an ancient belief, the official Tower of London historian, Geoff Parnell, believes that this is actually a romantic Victorian invention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Tower's raven mythology may be a Victorian flight of fantasy |curly=y |url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/uk/2004/nov/15/britishidentity.artsandhumanities |publisher=[[The Guardian]] |date=15 November 2004 |accessdate=5 December 2008 | location=London | first=Maev | last=Kennedy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aboutbritain.com/TowerOfLondon.htm |title=The Tower of London |accessdate=2007-03-03 |work=AboutBritain.com |quote=...legend has it that, if they leave, the kingdom will fall. }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Christianity===
In the [[Judeo-Christian]] tradition, the raven was the first animal to be released from [[Noah's ark]]. &quot;6 So it came to pass, at the end of forty days, that Noah opened the window of the ark which he had made. 7 Then he sent out a raven, which kept going to and fro until the waters had dried up from the earth. 8 He also sent out from himself a dove, to see if the waters had receded from the face of the ground.&quot; Genesis 8:6-8 NKJV.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Genesis%208:6-8&amp;version=NKJV Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; In Christianity the raven appears throughout the Bible in twelve different verses. Genesis 8:7,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Genesis+8:7&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Leviticus 11:15,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Leviticus+11:15&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Deuteronomy 14:14,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+14:14&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; 1 Kings 17:1,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Kings+17:1&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; 1 Kings 17:4,&lt;ref name=&quot;Biblegateway.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Kings+17:4&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; 1 Kings 17:6,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1%20Kings+17:6&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Job 38:41,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Job+38:41&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Psalm 147:9,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Psalm+147:9&amp;version=NLT  Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Proverbs 30:17,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Proverbs+30:17&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Song of Solomon 5:11,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Song%20of%20Solomon+5:11&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Isaiah 34:11,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Isaiah+34:11&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; Luke 12:24.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;[http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Luke+12:24&amp;version=NLT Biblegateway.com]&lt;/ref&gt; God sends ravens to feed the prophet Elijah in book of 1 Kings 17:1.&lt;ref name=&quot;Biblegateway.com&quot;/&gt; In the [[New Testament]] Jesus tells a parable using the raven to show how people should rely on God for their needs and not riches. See Luke 12:24.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

== References ==
&lt;!-- Condor18:38[Western Raven local extinction],58:107. FieldMusNatHistZoolSer18:343. --&gt;
{{reflist|colwidth=15em}}

===Cited texts===
*{{cite book|author=Goodwin D.|year=1983|title=Crows of the World |publisher=Queensland University Press, St Lucia, Qld|isbn=0-7022-1015-3}}
* {{cite book | author= John M. Marzluff |coauthors= Tony Angell| year=2005 | title=In the Company of Crows and Ravens | isbn=0-300-10076-0 | publisher= Yale Univ. Press | location= New Haven }}
* {{cite book | first=Candace | last=Savage | authorlink=Candace Savage | year=1995 | title=Bird Brains: The Intelligence of Crows, Ravens, Magpies and Jays | isbn=1-55054-189-7 | publisher=Douglas &amp; McIntyre | location=Toronto }}

== Further reading ==
* Heinrich, B. (1999). ''Mind of the Raven: Investigations and Adventures with Wolf-Birds.'' New York: Cliff Street Books. ISBN 978-0-06-093063-9

== External links ==
{{Commons|Corvus corax}}
{{Wikispecies|Corvus corax|Common Raven}}
*[http://www.pbs.org/wnet/nature/ravens/index.html PBS Nature: Ravens]
*[http://www.rspb.org.uk/birds/guide/r/raven/index.asp RSPB: Raven]
*[http://bswy.org/ Beringia South Raven Research]
*[http://www.birds.cornell.edu/AllAboutBirds/BirdGuide/Common_Raven.html Cornell Laboratory of Ornithology Species Account]
*[http://sdakotabirds.com/species/common_raven_info.htm Common Raven Information and Photos] on South Dakota Birds and Birding
*[http://ibc.lynxeds.com/species/common-raven-corvus-corax Common Raven videos] on the Internet Bird Collection
*[http://www.ibercajalav.net/img/415_RavenCcorax.pdf Ageing and sexing (PDF) by Javier Blasco-Zumeta]
*[http://www.arkive.org/species/ARK/birds/Corvus_corax/ ARKive images]
*[http://eol.org/pages/1177364 Encyclopedia of Life]

===Image links===
* [http://www.mbr-pwrc.usgs.gov/id/framlst/i4860id.html USGS species account, including CBC/BBS range maps]

===Sound link===
* [http://www.naturesongs.com/tyrrcert.html#cora Raven recordings]

{{featured article}}
{{Corvidae|2}}

[[Category:Arctic birds|Raven, Common]]
[[Category:Birds of Africa|Raven, Common]]
[[Category:Birds of Asia|Raven, Common]]
[[Category:Birds of Europe|Raven, Common]]
[[Category:Birds of North America|Raven, Common]]
[[Category:Corvus]]
[[Category:Ravens]]
[[Category:Talking birds]]
[[Category:Territorial symbols of Yukon]]
[[Category:Animals described in 1758]]

{{Link GA|zh}}
{{Link FA|hu}}
{{Link FA|sv}}

[[kbd:Вынд]]
[[als:Kolkrabe]]
[[an:Corvus corax]]
[[be-x-old:Крумкач]]
[[bg:Гарван гробар]]
[[br:Marc'hvran]]
[[ca:Corb]]
[[cv:Çăхан]]
[[cs:Krkavec velký]]
[[co:Corbu]]
[[cy:Cigfran]]
[[da:Ravn]]
[[de:Kolkrabe]]
[[nv:Zhį́ʼii]]
[[et:Ronk]]
[[es:Corvus corax]]
[[eo:Korako]]
[[eu:Erroi]]
[[fo:Ravnur]]
[[fr:Grand Corbeau]]
[[gd:Fitheach]]
[[gl:Corvo grande]]
[[hr:Obični gavran]]
[[io:Korniko]]
[[os:Сынт]]
[[is:Hrafn]]
[[it:Corvus corax]]
[[he:עורב שחור]]
[[ka:ყორანი]]
[[csb:Krëk]]
[[kk:Құзғын]]
[[kv:Кырныш]]
[[ku:Qelareşk]]
[[lv:Krauklis]]
[[lt:Kranklys]]
[[li:Raof]]
[[hu:Holló]]
[[nl:Raaf (dier)]]
[[ja:ワタリガラス]]
[[no:Ravn]]
[[nn:Ramn]]
[[koi:Кырныш]]
[[pcd:Grand corbieu]]
[[pms:Corvus corax]]
[[pl:Kruk]]
[[pt:Corvo-comum]]
[[ro:Corb]]
[[rue:Ворон]]
[[ru:Ворон]]
[[sah:Суор]]
[[se:Gáranas]]
[[sk:Krkavec čierny]]
[[sr:Обични гавран]]
[[sh:Obični gavran]]
[[fi:Korppi]]
[[sv:Korp]]
[[tr:Bayağı kuzgun]]
[[uk:Крук]]
[[vi:Quạ thường]]
[[zh:渡鴉]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
