<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="380922" ns="0" title="Indiana State University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name         = Indiana State University
|image_name   = Indiana State University Seal.svg
|image_size   = 180px
|motto        = More. From Day One.
|established  = 1865 ([[Indiana State University#History|details]])
|type         = [[public university|Public]]
|endowment    = $75+ million As of September 30, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstatefoundation.org/AboutOverview.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;  
|faculty      = 501&lt;ref name=&quot;indstate.edu&quot;&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/whyisu/fastfacts.htm&lt;/ref&gt;
|president    = Daniel J. Bradley&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/president/&lt;/ref&gt;
|students     = 11,494&lt;ref name=&quot;indstate.edu&quot;/&gt;
|undergrad    = 9,373
|postgrad     = 2,121
|city         = [[Terre Haute, Indiana|Terre Haute]]
|state        = [[Indiana|IN]]
|country      = [[United States|USA]]
|campus       = small city: {{convert|235|acre|km2}}
|former_names = &lt;small&gt;Indiana St. Normal School&lt;br&gt;Indiana St. Teachers College&lt;br&gt;Indiana State College&lt;/small&gt;
|mascot       = Sycamore Sam
|colors       = Sycamore Blue and [[White]]
{{color box|#0F4D92}} {{color box|white}}
|athletics    = 12 [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] teams&lt;br&gt;called [[Indiana State Sycamores|Sycamores]]
|affiliations   = [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools|NCA]],  [[American Association of State Colleges and Universities|AASCU]], [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business|AACSB]], [[Missouri Valley Conference|MVC]]
|website      = [http://www.indstate.edu www.indstate.edu]
|logo         = [[Image:Indiana State University Logo.svg|center|200px]]
}}
'''Indiana State University''' ('''ISU''') is a [[public university]] located in [[Terre Haute, Indiana]], [[United States]]. 

The ''[[Princeton Review]]'' has named Indiana State as one of the &quot;Best in the Midwest&quot; seven years running,&lt;ref name=Taylor2010&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.indstate.edu/news/news.php?newsid=2364|title=List of best Midwestern colleges once again includes Indiana State|last=Taylor|first=Dave|date=2010-08-04|publisher=Indiana State University|accessdate=2010-10-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the College of Education's Graduate Program was recently named as a 'Top 100' by [[U.S. News &amp; World Report]] while the graduate program in nursing was recognized as among the &quot;Top 75' in the nation by U.S. News.&lt;ref&gt;http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-nursing-schools/rankings/page+4&lt;/ref&gt;  The magazine currently classifies Indiana State University as a tier 2 national university.  The current [[Carnegie Classification of Institutions of Higher Education|Carnegie classification]] for ISU is Doctoral/Research University.&lt;ref name=Carnegie&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=14235&amp;start=782|title=Carnegie Classifications &gt; Indiana State University|publisher=Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching|accessdate=2009-02-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Indiana State University is accredited by the Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/accreditation/&lt;/ref&gt; ISU is also included in Carnegie's new Curricular Engagement and Outreach &amp; Partnerships category that recognizes substantial commitments to both an academic approach to mutually beneficial and respectful community collaboration and extensive outreach and partnerships.&lt;ref&gt;http://classifications.carnegiefoundation.org/descriptions/community_engagement.php?key=1213&lt;/ref&gt; 

Indiana State offers 100+ majors, notably education, business, criminology, finance, insurance and risk management, nursing, athletic training, and construction technology;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/majors/&lt;/ref&gt; the university's graduate education, financial services, nursing and clinical psychology programs are nationally recognized.

Indiana State is a diverse university, with 3.8% of students attending as [[international students]] and 19.5% of students belonging to a minority. Of the 19.5% minority students, 75.4% are African American, 8.3% are [[multiracial]], 8.3 percent are [[Hispanic and Latino American]], 5.8 percent are [[Asian American]], and 2.1 percent are Native American.&lt;ref name=University2010&gt;{{Cite web | year = 2010 | title = Indiana State University Fast Facts | url = http://www1.indstate.edu/whyisu/fastfacts.htm | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Indiana State is the first public university in Indiana to require incoming freshmen to have a laptop. ISU offers Dell Latitude E6400 laptops to incoming freshmen with high high school GPAs of 3.0 or higher (on a 4.0 scale) as part of its Laptop Initiative.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/oit1/laptop/&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[File:Fairbanks Hall Dome.jpg|thumb|Fairbanks Hall Dome]]
Indiana State University was established by the [[Indiana General Assembly]] on December 20, 1865, as the '''Indiana State Normal School''' in [[Terre Haute]]. As the State Normal School, its core mission was to educate elementary and high school teachers. The school awarded its first baccalaureate degrees in 1908 and the first master's degrees in 1928.  In 1929, the Indiana State Normal School was renamed the '''Indiana State Teachers College''', and in 1961, was renamed '''Indiana State College''' due to an expanding mission.  In 1965, the Indiana General Assembly renamed the college as '''Indiana State University''' in recognition of continued growth.

== Campus ==
[[File:Rankin Hall.jpg|thumb|Rankin Hall]]

The Indiana State University main campus is located on the north side of Terre Haute’s downtown business district and covers more than {{convert|200|acre|km2}} in the heart of the city. Over 60 brick and limestone buildings and laboratories comprise the main campus. Starting in the 1960s and continuing through the 1990s, ISU lost many of its historic buildings, but efforts  to beautify the campus continue: a section of Seventh Street that runs by the university has been converted into a boulevard with flower beds and antique light posts; the old power plant was razed in 2002 and replaced with a modern facility;&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/PowerPlant.htm&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stalker Hall]] reopened in fall 2005 after a complete renovation;&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/StalkerHall.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Normal Hall, a Neo-Classic building erected in 1909, originally served as the library, and is line for renovation in 2011-12.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/NormalHall.htm&lt;/ref&gt; In 2009, the university dedicated a more than {{convert|109000|sqft|m2|adj=on}} Student Recreation Center, financed via private funding and student fees. Also in 2009, the College of Education was relocated to the newly renovated, historic University Hall.&lt;ref&gt;http://www1.indstate.edu/coe/universityhall/index.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  Beginning in 2012, the College of Business will relocate to the renovated Terre Haute Federal Building, a classic Art Deco building erected in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/business/magazine/spring2008/fedbldg.htm&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Indiana State University field campus is an outdoor teaching, learning, and research area designed to accommodate educational programs and services. The field campus is located on {{convert|93|acre|m2}} approximately {{convert|18|mi|km}} east of Terre Haute near [[Brazil, Indiana]], and includes eight man-made lakes.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/rcsm/fieldcampus.html&lt;/ref&gt;

===2010 Master Plan===
[[File:DedePlazaISU.jpg|thumb|Dede Plaza]]
[[File:ISU Student Recreation Center.jpg|thumb|Student Recreation Center]]
On December 18, 2009; the Indiana State University Board of Trustees accepted a new Master Plan,
This plan will guide the physical growth and development of the Indiana State
University campus for the next 15 to 20 years. It provides a blueprint for campus
improvements in the near and mid-term and an overriding philosophy for the long term.
Primary components of the plan include:
• Meeting the functional needs of academic programs within the current facility square footage.
• Improving student housing choices.
• Serving as a partner and catalyst to the redevelopment of downtown Terre Haute.
• Improving vehicular and pedestrian circulation systems and wayfinding.
• Supporting the redevelopment of the Wabash Riverfront.
• Providing athletic facilities that are competitive with peer institutions
• Responding to contemporary and practical sustainable design practices.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/strategic_plan/masterplan.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
=== Colleges and school ===
Indiana State University is organized into six academic colleges:

* '''College of Arts and Sciences'''
**containing the Departments of: African and African American Studies • Art • Biology • Chemistry and Physics • Communication • Criminology • Economics • English • Earth and Environmental Systems • History • Languages, Literatures, and Linguistics • Mathematics and Computer Science • Music • Philosophy • Political Science • Psychology • Theater
**also containing: Center for Biodiversity Studies • Criminology Institute • Center for Economic Education • Center for Governmental Studies • Sociology Research Lab (SRL) • Center for the Study of Health, Religion, and Spirituality • Science Education Center • Center for Urban and Environmental Change

* '''Donald W. Scott College of Business'''
**organized into the three Departments effective January 2011: Accounting, Finance, Insurance and Risk Management (AFIRM) • Marketing and Operations • Management, Information Systems, and Business Education (MISBE)
**also containing: Small Business Development Center • Gongaware Center for Insurance Management • NetWorks Financial Institute • Center for Public Service and Community Engagement • Center for Research, Enterprise and Economic Development (CREED) • Leadership Development Institute (LDI)[http://www.indstate.edu/business]

* '''Bayh College of Education''' [http://coe.indstate.edu]
**containing the Departments of: Communication Disorders • Counseling • Curriculum, Instruction, and Media Technology • Educational Leadership, Administration, and Foundations • Educational and School Psychology • Elementary, Early, and Special Education
** also containing: Education Student Services • Professional Development Schools (PDS) • Blumberg Center for Interdisciplinary Studies in Special Education • Instructional &amp; Information Technology Services • North Central Association (NCA)

* '''College of Graduate and Professional Studies'''
ISU offers more than 90 programs in the Colleges of Arts &amp; Sciences, Business, Education, Technology, and Nursing, Health and Human Services. The College of Graduate and Professional Studies offers programs that lead to doctoral and master's degrees. Students can also pursue certificates in a concentrated area of study, enroll in professional development courses, and fulfill continuing education requirements.

* '''College of Nursing, Health, and Human Services''' [http://www.indstate.edu/nhhs/]
**containing the Departments of: Advanced Practice Nursing [http://www.indstate.edu/apn/] • Applied Health Sciences [http://www.indstate.edu/ahs/]• Applied Medicine and Rehabilitation [http://www.indstate.edu/amr/] • Baccalaureate Nursing [http://www.indstate.edu/bacc-nursing/]• Baccalaureate Nursing Completion [http://www.indstate.edu/bacc-comp-nsg/]• Physical Education [http://www.indstate.edu/pe/]• Recreation and Sport Management [http://www.indstate.edu/rcsm/] • and Social Work [http://www.indstate.edu/socwork/] as well as The Landsbaum Center for Health Education [http://lugarcenter.org/index.php?folder=landsbaum&amp;page=landsbaum-home]• Richard G. Lugar Center for Rural Health [http://lugarcenter.org/index.php?page=mcrh] • West Central Indiana Area Health Education Center (AHEC) [http://www.indstate.edu/wciahec/](This College was created July 1, 2007, incorporating the former College of Nursing and the College of Health and Human Performance.  The first Dean of the College is Dr. Richard Williams [http://www.indstate.edu/nhhs/dean-office/dean-welcome.htm]).

* '''College of Technology'''
**containing the Departments of: Applied Engineering and Technology Management • Aviation Technology • Built Environment • Electronics and Computer Engineering Technology • Human Resource Development and Performance Technologies
**also containing: Indiana Packaging Research and Development Center • Technology Services Center • Technology Student Services • Air Force ROTC • Army ROTC

===Library===
The '''[http://library.indstate.edu/ Cunningham Memorial Library]''' collections include more than 1.3 million items. Undergraduate students may check out most materials for a three-week loan period, using their student ID.  The library is part of the Library Consortium of Vigo County.  Through a search engine called Fusion, students may search through 400,000 records found in the library catalogs for the Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology, Saint Mary-of-the-Woods College, and the Vigo County Public Library. 

More than 110 full-time service computers are available throughout the library. Nine computers are equipped with scanners and one computer has ZoomText capabilities that enlarges print and screen and reads aloud for the visually challenged. New furniture, computer hardware, and software enable groups of students to collaborate electronically. Printers and photocopiers are also available. Collaborative, group, and individual study areas are offered as well as group study rooms. One study area is dedicated to adaptive technology, which includes a Braille display, a reading machine,a special individual monitor for people with retinal degenerative diseases, a head tracker, a multi-colored QWERTY layout with keys four times larger than normal, a voice-to-text program, and software to help people who struggle with reading. &lt;ref&gt;http://catalog.indstate.edu/content.php?catoid=13&amp;navoid=278&amp;returnto=search#libr_serv&lt;/ref&gt;

===Degrees===
* Undergraduate baccalaureate degrees: Bachelor of Arts (B.A.), Bachelor of Fine Arts (B.F.A.), Bachelor of Music (B.M.), Bachelor of Music Education (B.M.E), Bachelor of Science (B.S.), Bachelor of Social Work (B.S.W.),
* Graduate degrees: Master of Arts (M.A.), Master of Fine Arts (M.F.A.), Master of Public Administration (M.P.A.), Master of Science (M.S.), Master of Education (M.E.), Master of Music (M.M.), Master of Business Administration (M.B.A.)
* Doctorates: Doctor of Nursing Practice (DNP), Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.), Doctor of Physical Therapy (DPT), Doctor of Psychology (Psy.D.)

===Accreditation===
Indiana State University as a whole has been accredited by [[The Higher Learning Commission]] of the [[North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]] continuously since 1915.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.ncahlc.org/index.php?option=com_directory&amp;Action=ShowBasic&amp;instid=1191 |title=High Learning Commission |accessdate = 2007-08-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The College of Business is accredited by the [[Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business]] (AACSB) and the College of Education is accredited by the [[National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education]] (NCATE). The nursing programs are accredited by the [[National League for Nursing Accrediting Commission]] (NLNAC). The Bachelor in Social Work program is accredited by the [[Council on Social Work Education]] (CSWE). The Undergraduate Athletic Training program is accredited by the Commission on Accreditation of Athletic Training Education (CAATE). The Graduate Athletic Training program is accredited by the [[National Athletic Trainers' Association]]-Graduate Review Committee (NATA-PPEC). The Physical Education programs are accredited by the [[National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education]] (NCATE).

==University traditions==
===Donaghy Day===
Named for Fred Donaghy, graduate of the Normal School (1912) and a professor of life sciences, this tradition was initiated in 1976 as a day set aside for the community to celebrate the season and to work to help beautify the campus and surrounding community; Donaghy Day is now conducted during the first week of the fall semester and is used to acquaint new students with the university's commitment to community engagement.&lt;ref name=ISU&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/whyisu/history_trad.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

===Homecoming===
The term Homecoming was first used in print announcements for the Alumni-Varsity Basketball Game on December 9, 1916. By 1919, this event became known as Blue and White Day and featured dances and entertainment for alumni of the Normal School. In 1921 the events were organized around a football game scheduled earlier in the autumn. A bonfire and pep rally were added to the festivities in 1922; the Blue-and-White Parade in 1923; and in 1937, Bette Whitmore (Kappa Kappa) was elected ISU¹s first Homecoming Queen.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt;

===Founders Day===
Conducted in January or February of each year, this event commemorates the opening of the institution in 1870 when 23 students presented themselves to a faculty of three on the first day of classes at the Indiana State Normal School.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt;

===Mascots===
The school has had two mascots.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt;  Early on in the school's history, the athletes were referred to as the &quot;Fighting Teachers&quot;, until the students chose the name &quot;Sycamores&quot;, from the abundance of Sycamore trees in Indiana and especially in the [[Wabash River]] Valley; though it is believed that the students voted on 'Sycamores' on a lark, never thinking it would win.  During the 1950s and 60s, the sycamore tree itself was used as Indiana State's mascot. However, as a tree does not lend itself well to an athletic mascot, especially considering Indiana State's in-state rivalries with the Ball State Cardinals and Butler Bulldogs, the university created an Indian mascot named Chief Quabachi, and his Princess, in 1969.  This change paid homage to the fact that ISU was the &quot;State&quot; university of a state named after Indians (prior to statehood Indiana was primarily inhabited by Indians).  However, the university stopped using Chief Quabachi as a mascot in 1989.  For six years, Indiana State did not have a mascot, until 1995, a blue-and-white &quot;furry woodland creature&quot; named &quot;Sycamore Sam&quot; was developed to replace Chief Quabachi and continues to serve as Indiana State's mascot.

===Tandem===
[[File:Tandem race.jpg|thumb|Tandem race]]
This student-organized race was first run as part of Spring Week activities in 1970. Teams are coed mixed pairs, which compete on tandem bicycles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt;

===Trike===
The '''Indiana State Tricycle Derby''' was first run in 1963 as a 10-lap race around the sidewalks of the Quadrangle on children's tricycles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt; The races featured a men's and women's division (the Powder Puff Derby). The races now feature men's and women's teams racing on specially built tricycles at the new Recreation East complex at Ninth and Sycamore streets.  In October 2005, the Michael Simmons Student Activity Center opened at Rec East, featuring commemorative displays chronicling the history and the participants of trike and tandem, containing bleacher seating, an all-purpose room, restrooms, an observation deck, and storage.

===The Walk===
The unofficial tradition during homecoming is known as &quot;The Walk.&quot; A large number of students, typically reaching in the thousands, make the two mile (3&amp;nbsp;km) walk east on Wabash Avenue towards the Football Stadium stopping and having a drink at each bar along the way. In 2010, the university launched “SoberRide” and “Designated Walker” programs for homecoming.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/news/news.php?newsid=2417&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Walk can be traced back to the early 1980s when students walked from Saturday night football games back to campus, stopping for a beer at every establishment that served beer, including the Pizza Hut, on Wabash.

==Songs==
===Fight Song===
[[File:ISU marching band.jpg|thumb|Marching Sycamores]]
''March On (You Fighting Sycamores)'', the university’s fight song, was authored and arranged by Joseph A. Gramelspacher, an ISU professor of music, as a pep song. It was first performed at a homecoming-eve pep rally on October 20, 1939.

Indiana State&lt;BR&gt;
&quot;March On! (You Fighting Sycamores)&quot;
:March on! March on, you fighting Sycamores, Sycamores!
:March on, you Statesmen tried and true!
:March on! March on to glorious victory
:Raise that flag of royal blue!
:March on! March on, you fighting Sycamores, Sycamores!
:Shout out that vict'ry song!
:Onward, ever onward to our goal!
:As we march on and on!
:''Go Big Blue! Fight Big Blue!''
:''GO! STATE! WIN!''

===Alma Mater===
Charles M. Curry, Professor of English and Literature authored ''The Alma Mater''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ISU&quot; /&gt; It was originally entitled, &quot;Indiana’s Normal&quot; and first printed in a June 1912 issue of the ''Normal Advance''.  Dr. Curry used the music of [[Annie Lisle]] for ''The Alma Mater''.

==Athletics==
{{Main|Indiana State Sycamores}}

[[Image:IndianaStateSycamores.png|thumb|right|Athletic Logo]]

The school's athletic teams are known as the ''[[Sycamores]]''. They participate in the [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Missouri Valley Conference]] and [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Football Championship Subdivision|FCS]] [[Missouri Valley Football Conference]].

Athletically, it is best known as the alma mater of basketball legend [[Larry Bird]]; World Champion gymnast [[Kurt Thomas (gymnast)|Kurt Thomas]]; and Olympic, World and Pan-American Champion free-style wrestler, [[Bruce Baumgartner]].  The legendary basketball coach [[John Wooden]] coached the Sycamores before accepting the Head Coaching position at UCLA.  The Men's Basketball team won the 1950 NAIB National Champions and were National Runner-Up in 1946 and 1948.  They were also the NCAA College Division (Div II) National Runner-Up in 1968 and the Division I National Runner-Up in 1979.  The 1950 team comprised the core of the 1951 Pan-American Gold Medal Team. In 1971, Coach Grete Treiber led the ISU Women's gymnastics team to a National Runner-up finish at the [[AIAW]] National Championships.  Kurt Thomas led the Men's Gymnastics Team to the 1977 NCAA National Championship.  Indiana State University Chess Captain, Taylor Pinnick, has led the Sycamores to 9 consecutive wins in the Missouri Valley Conference.

===Facilities===
[[Hulman Center]], originally named [[Hulman Center|Hulman Civic-University Center]], is a multi-use arena that opened in December 1973.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/HulmanCenter.htm&lt;/ref&gt; It seats 10,200 people for basketball and is home to the Indiana State University Sycamores men's and women's basketball teams of the [[Missouri Valley Conference]]. It has hosted multiple concerts and the [[Missouri Valley Conference]] men's basketball tournament title game in 1979, the year legendary [[Larry Bird]] helped the undefeated [[Indiana State Sycamores men's basketball|Sycamores]] reach the championship game of the [[NCAA]] tournament.

The baseball field is located within a mile of the main campus along the scenic Wabash River. Bob Warn Field at Sycamore Stadium is home to the [[Terre Haute Rex]] team.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.indstate.edu/news/news.php?newsid=2064&lt;/ref&gt; Memorial Stadium, the home field for Indiana State's NCAA Football Championship Subdivision football team of the [[Missouri Valley Football Conference]], and the women's soccer team is located on Wabash Avenue, two miles (3&amp;nbsp;km) east of the main campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/MemorialStadium.htm&lt;/ref&gt; Walter E. Marks Field for track and field and Ferne Price Field for softball are among the many athletic facilities located on campus.&lt;ref&gt;http://library.indstate.edu/archives/exhibits/architecture/MarksField.htm&lt;/ref&gt;  

Indiana State University has hosted seven (2002, 2004–2009) NCAA Division I cross country championships at the spectacular [[LaVern Gibson Championship Cross Country Course]].  Indiana State will host the championships in 2010 and again in 2013.  

The school also hosted the 10th NCAA Wrestling Championships in 1937; remarkable considering the school had yet to establish a wrestling program.  The University also hosted the 1975 NCAA Gymnastics National Championships.
[[File:ISU Memorial Stadium.jpg|thumb|Memorial Stadium]]

===Men===
*Baseball - [[Sycamore Field]]
*[[Indiana State Sycamores men's basketball|Basketball]] - [[Hulman Center]]
*Cross Country - [[LaVern Gibson Championship Cross Country Course]], [[Wabash Valley]] Family Sports Center
*[[American football|Football]] - [[Memorial Stadium (Terre Haute)|Memorial Stadium]]
*[[Track &amp; Field]] - Marks Field

===Women===
*Basketball - [[Hulman Center]]
*Cross Country - [[LaVern Gibson Championship Cross Country Course]], Wabash Valley Family Sports Center
*[[Soccer]] - [[Memorial Stadium (Terre Haute)|Memorial Stadium]]
*Track &amp; Field - Marks Field
*[[Softball]] - Eleanor Forsythe St. John Softball Complex
*[[Golf]] - multiple (The Country Club of Terre Haute {Private}; Idle Creek {Semi-Private}, Rea Park {Public} and Hulman Links {Public} Golf Courses)
*[[Volleyball]] - ISU Arena

== Notable faculty and alumni ==
{{Main|List of Indiana State University people}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[http://www.indstate.edu Official website]
*[http://www.gosycamores.com Official Athletic website]
*[http://www.indianastatesman.com Indiana Statesman - Student Newspaper]
*Facebook - http://www.facebook.com/IndianaState
*Myspace - http://www.myspace.com/indianastate
*Twitter - http://twitter.com/indianastate
*YouTube - http://www.youtube.com/user/IndianaStateU
*Indiana State Blogs - http://blogs.indstate.edu/
*Indiana State Podcast - http://www.indstate.edu/sycamorepodcast/

{{Coord|39.469525|-87.40706|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}
{{Indiana State University}}
{{Public colleges and universities in Indiana}}
{{Indiana Colleges and Universities}}
{{Missouri Valley Conference}}
{{Missouri Valley Football Conference}}
{{Terre Haute, Indiana}}

[[Category:Indiana State University| ]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1865]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Education in Terre Haute, Indiana]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Terre Haute, Indiana]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Vigo County, Indiana]]

[[de:Indiana State University]]
[[la:Universitas Civica Indianensis]]
[[ja:インディアナ州立大学]]
[[no:Indiana State University]]
[[fi:Indianan osavaltionyliopisto]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
