<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="38188" ns="0" title="United States Navy SEALs"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|SEAL|other uses|SEAL (disambiguation)|the animal|Pinniped}}
{{Redirect|Navy SEALs|the 1990 film|Navy SEALs (film)}}
{{Redirect|Navy seals|military uses of seals and sea lions (the animals)|U.S. Navy Marine Mammal Program}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{Infobox military unit
| unit_name = U.S. Navy SEALs
| image = [[File:US Navy SEALs insignia.png|250px]]
| caption = The [[Special Warfare insignia]], or &quot;SEAL Trident.&quot;
| dates = 1 January 1962&amp;nbsp;– ''present''
| country = {{flagicon|US}} United States of America

| allegiance =
| branch = [[File:United States Department of the Navy Seal.svg|20px]] [[United States Navy]]
| type = [[United States Special Operations Forces#United States Navy|Maritime Special Operations Force]]&lt;br /&gt;'''Se'''a, '''A'''ir, '''L'''and

| role =
Primary tasks:
* Special reconnaissance
* Direct action
* Foreign internal defense
* Counter-terrorism
* Unconventional warfare

Other roles:
* Counter-drug operations
* Personnel recovery
* Hydrographic reconnaissance
| size = ~2400 &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= Navy Steps Up Search for New SEALs-Changes to special-warfare recruiting, training practices show promise for growing unit
|work=The Navy Times |url= http://www.navyseals.com/navy-steps-search-new-seals-changes-special-warfare-recruiting-training-practices-show-promise-growi|accessdate=27 July 201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

| command_structure= [[File:Navsoc logo.jpg|20px]] [[United States Naval Special Warfare Command]]&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Special Operations Specops Army.svg|20px]] [[United States Special Operations Command]]
| current_commander=
| garrison = [[Naval Amphibious Base Coronado|Coronado, California]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Naval Amphibious Base Little Creek|Little Creek, Virginia]]
| nickname = Team Guys, Frogmen, The Teams, The Green Faces&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book |title=Men In Green Faces |last=Wentz |first=Gene |coauthors=B. Abell Jurus |year=1993 |publisher=St. Martin's Paperbacks |isbn=978-0312950521 |pages= |url= }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
| patron =
| motto = &quot;The Only Easy Day Was Yesterday&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;It Pays to be a Winner&quot;
| colorsanalyn =
| march =
| mascot =
| battles =[[Vietnam War]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Multinational Force in Lebanon]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Urgent Fury]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Achille Lauro#1985 hijacking|Achille Lauro hijacking]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Just Cause]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Gulf War|Operation Desert Storm]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Restore Hope]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Battle of Mogadishu (1993)|Battle of Mogadishu]]&lt;ref&gt;Four operators from [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group|DevGru]] were a part of the assault convoy during Battle of Mogadishu&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation United Shield]]&lt;br /&gt;[[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|Operation Enduring Freedom]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Red Wings]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Iraq War|Operation Iraqi Freedom]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Maersk Alabama hijacking]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Death of Osama bin Laden]]
| anniversaries =
}}
The [[United States Navy]]'s '''Sea, Air and Land Teams''', commonly known as '''Navy SEALs''', are the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]]'s principal [[special operations force]] and a part of the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Command|Naval Special Warfare Command]] (NSWC) as well as the maritime component of the [[United States Special Operations Command]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title= SEALs Surface to Blow Holes in Navy Nerd Image|work=The Los Angeles Times |url= http://articles.latimes.com/1990-07-27/local/me-625_1_navy-seals|accessdate=28 December 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The acronym is derived from their capacity to operate at sea, in the air, and on land. In the [[War on Terror]], SEALs have been utilized almost exclusively for land-based operations, including [[Direct action (military)|Direct Action]], [[Hostage Rescue]], [[Counter Terrorism]], [[Special Reconnaissance]], [[unconventional warfare]] and [[foreign internal defense]] operations.  Without exception, all SEALs are male members of either the United States Navy or the [[United States Coast Guard]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://coastguard.dodlive.mil/index.php/2010/05/coast-guard-graduates-first-two-seals/ |title=Coast Guard Graduates First Two SEALs « Coast Guard Compass |publisher=Coastguard.dodlive.mil |date= |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=SEAL Requirements |author=US Navy |publisher=navyseals.com |url=http://www.navyseals.com/seal-challenge-requirements SEAL requirements |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]]'s highly secretive [[Special Activities Division]] (SAD) and more specifically its elite Special Operations Group (SOG) recruits operators from the SEAL Teams.&lt;ref&gt;Waller, Douglas (3 February 2003). &quot;The CIA Secret Army&quot;. TIME (Time Inc). http://www.time.com/time/covers/1101030203/&lt;/ref&gt; Joint Navy SEALs and CIA operations go back to the famed [[MACV-SOG]] during the [[Vietnam War]].&lt;ref&gt;SOG: The Secret Wars of America's Commandos in Vietnam by John L. Plaster&lt;/ref&gt; This cooperation still exists today and is seen in the wars in Iraq and Afghanistan,&lt;ref&gt;Haney, Eric L. (2002). Inside Delta Force. New York: Delacorte Press&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Efran, Shawn (producer), &quot;Army Officer Recalls Hunt For Bin Laden&quot;, 60&amp;nbsp;Minutes, CBS News, 5 October 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; and more recently in the finding and killing of [[Osama bin Laden]] in Pakistan. 
==History==
===Origins===

Navy SEALs can trace their roots to the Second World War. The United States Navy recognized the need for the covert [[Amphibious reconnaissance|reconnaissance]] of [[Amphibious assault|landing beaches]] and coastal defenses. As a result the [[Scouts and Raiders|Amphibious Scout and Raider School]] was established in 1942 at [[Fort Pierce, Florida]]. The Scouts and Raiders were formed in September of that year, just nine months after the attack on Pearl Harbor, from the [[Observer Group]], a joint Army-USMC-Navy unit.

=== Scouts &amp; Raiders ===

==== First Group ====

The first group included Phil H. Bucklew, the &quot;Father of Naval Special Warfare,&quot; after whom the Naval Special Warfare Center building is named. Commissioned in October 1942, this group saw combat in November 1942 during Operation Torch, the first allied landings in Europe, on the North African coast. Scouts and Raiders also supported landings in Sicily, Salerno, Anzio, Normandy, and southern France.

==== Second Group ====

A second group of Scouts and Raiders, code-named Special Service Unit #1, was established on 7 July 1943, as a joint and combined operations force. The first mission, in September 1943, was at Finschafen on New Guinea. Later operations were at Gasmata, Arawe, Cape Gloucester, and the East and South coast of New Britain, all without any loss of personnel. Conflicts arose over operational matters, and all non-Navy personnel were reassigned. The unit, renamed 7th Amphibious Scouts, received a new mission, to go ashore with the assault boats, buoy channels, erect markers for the incoming craft, handle casualties, take offshore soundings, blow up beach obstacles and maintain voice communications linking the troops ashore, incoming boats and nearby ships. The 7th Amphibious Scouts conducted operations in the Pacific for the duration of the conflict, participating in more than 40 landings

==== Third Group ====

The third Scout and Raiders organization operated in China. Scouts and Raiders were deployed to fight with the Sino-American Cooperative Organization, or SACO. To help bolster the work of SACO, Admiral Ernest J. King ordered that 120 officers and 900 men be trained for &quot;Amphibious Raider&quot; at the Scout and Raider school at Fort Pierce, Florida. They formed the core of what was envisioned as a &quot;guerrilla amphibious organization of Americans and Chinese operating from coastal waters, lakes and rivers employing small steamboats and sampans.&quot; While most Amphibious Raider forces remained at Camp Knox in Calcutta, three of the groups saw active service. They conducted a survey of the upper Yangtze River in the spring of 1945 and, disguised as coolies, conducted a detailed three-month survey of the Chinese coast from Shanghai to Kitchioh Wan, near Hong Kong.

=== Naval Combat Demolition Units ===

Along with the Scouts and Raiders were the Naval Combat Demolition Units. They specialized in demolitions, explosive cable cutting, and commando raiding techniques. On May 7, 1943, Lieutenant Commander Draper L. Kauffman, &quot;The Father of Naval Combat Demolition,&quot; was directed to set up a school and train people to eliminate obstacles on an enemy-held beach prior to an invasion. On June 6, 1943, LCDR Kaufmann established Naval Combat Demolition Unit training at Fort Pierce. By April 1944, a total of 34 NCDUs were deployed to England in preparation for Operation OVERLORD, the amphibious landing at Normandy. On June 6, 1944, in the face of great adversity, the NCDUs at Omaha Beach managed to blow eight complete gaps and two partial gaps in the German defenses. The NCDUs suffered 31 killed and 60 wounded, a casualty rate of 52%. Meanwhile, the NCDUs at Utah Beach met less intense enemy fire. They cleared 700 yards (640 m) of beach in two hours, another 900 yards (820 m) by the afternoon. Casualties at Utah Beach were significantly lighter with six killed and eleven wounded. During Operation OVERLORD, not a single demolitioneer was lost to improper handling of explosives. In August 1944, NCDUs from Utah Beach participated in the landings in southern France, the last amphibious operation in the European Theater of Operations. NCDUs also operated in the Pacific theater. NCDU 2, under LTjg Frank Kaine, after whom the Naval Special Warfare Command building is named, and NCDU 3 under LTjg Lloyd Anderson, formed the nucleus of six NCDUs that served with the Seventh Amphibious Force tasked with clearing boat channels after the landings from Biak to Borneo.

=== OSS Operational Swimmers ===

Some of the earliest World War II predecessors of the SEALs were the Operational Swimmers of the Office of Strategic Services, or OSS.[9] Many current SEAL missions were first assigned to them. OSS specialized in special operations, dropping operatives behind enemy lines to engage in organized guerrilla warfare as well as to gather information on such things as enemy resources and troop movements. [10]
British Combined Operations veteran LCDR Wooley, of the Royal Navy, was placed in charge of the OSS Maritime Unit in June 1943. Their training started in November 1943 at Camp Pendleton, California, moved to Santa Catalina Island, California in January 1944, and finally moved to the warmer waters of The Bahamas in March 1944. Within the U.S. military, they pioneered flexible swimfins and [[diving mask]]s, closed-circuit diving equipment (under the direction of Dr. Chris Lambertsen), the use of Swimmer Delivery Vehicles (a type of submersible), and combat swimming and limpet mine attacks.[9] In May 1944, General Donovan, the head of the OSS, divided the unit into groups. He loaned Group 1, under Lieutenant Choate, to Admiral Nimitz, as a way to introduce the OSS into the Pacific theater. They became part of UDT-10 in July 1944. Five OSS men participated in the very first UDT submarine operation with the USS Burrfish (SS-312) in the Caroline Islands in August 1944.

=== Underwater Demolition Teams ===

On November 23, 1943, the [[United States Marine Corps|U.S. Marine]] [[Battle of Tarawa|landing]] on [[Tarawa Atoll]] emphasized the need for hydrographic reconnaissance and underwater demolition of obstacles prior to any amphibious landing. Offshore [[coral reef]]s and other obstacles in the surf had resulted in many of the Marines drowning or being hit by enemy fire because their landing craft could not reach the beach. After the [[Battle of Tarawa|Tarawa]], Rear Admiral [[Richmond K. Turner]] directed the formation of nine [[Underwater Demolition Team]]s. 30 officers and 150 enlisted men were moved to the [[Waimānalo, Hawai'i|Waimānalo]] Amphibious Training Base to form the nucleus of a demolition training program. This group became [[Underwater Demolition Teams]] (UDT) ONE and TWO. 

The UDTs saw their first combat on January 31, 1944, during Operation Flintlock in the Marshall Islands. FLINTLOCK became the real catalyst for the UDT training program in the Pacific Theater. In February 1944, the Naval Combat Demolition Training and Experimental Base was established at Kīhei, Maui, next to the Amphibious Base at Kamaole. Eventually, 34 UDT teams were established. Wearing swim suits, fins, and dive masks on combat operations, these &quot;Naked Warriors&quot; saw action across the Pacific in every major amphibious landing including: Eniwetok, Saipan, Guam, Tinian, Angaur, Ulithi, Peleliu, Leyte, Lingayen Gulf, Zambales, Iwo Jima, Okinawa, Labuan, Brunei Bay, and on July 4, 1945 at Balikpapan on Borneo, which was the last UDT demolition operation of the war.
The rapid demobilization at the conclusion of the war reduced the number of active duty UDTs to two on each coast with a complement of seven officers and 45 enlisted men each.

The Korean War began on June 25, 1950, when the North Korean army invaded South Korea. Beginning with a detachment of 11 personnel from UDT 3, UDT participation expanded to three teams with a combined strength of 300 men. As part of the Special Operations Group, or SOG, UDTs successfully conducted demolition raids on railroad tunnels and bridges along the Korean coast. On September 15, 1950, UDTs supported Operation Chromite, the amphibious landing at Incheon. UDT 1 and 3 provided personnel who went in ahead of the landing craft, scouting mud flats, marking low points in the channel, clearing fouled propellers, and searching for mines. Four UDT personnel acted as wave-guides for the Marine landing. In October 1950, UDTs supported mine-clearing operations in Wonsan Harbor where frogmen would locate and mark mines for minesweepers. On October 12, 1950, two U.S. minesweepers hit mines and sank. UDTs rescued 25 sailors. The next day, William Giannotti conducted the first U.S. combat operation using an &quot;aqualung&quot; when he dove on the USS Pledge (AM-277). For the remainder of the war, UDTs conducted beach and river reconnaissance, infiltrated guerrillas behind the lines from sea, continued mine sweeping operations, and participated in Operation Fishnet, which severely damaged the North Korean's fishing capability.

[[File:US Navy SEALs SEAL jumps over side boat.jpg|thumb|left|UDT members using the casting technique from a speeding boat]]

===Vietnam===
{{Main|Vietnam War}}
President [[John F. Kennedy]], aware of the situations in Southeast Asia, recognized the need for [[unconventional warfare]] and [[special operations]] as a measure against [[guerrilla warfare]]. In a speech to [[United States Congress|Congress]] on 25 May 1961, Kennedy spoke of his deep respect for the [[Special Forces (United States Army)|United States Army Special Forces]]. While his announcement of the government's [[Apollo program|plan to put a man on the moon]] drew all of the attention, in the same speech he announced his intention to spend over $100&amp;nbsp;million to strengthen U.S. special operations forces and expand American capabilities in unconventional warfare.

The Navy needed to determine its role within the special operations arena. In March 1961, [[Arleigh Burke]], [[Chief of Naval Operations]], recommended the establishment of [[Guerrilla warfare|guerrilla]] and [[Counter-guerrilla warfare|counter-guerrilla]] units. These units would be able to operate from sea, air or land. This was the beginning of the Navy SEALs. Most SEALs came from the Navy's Underwater Demolition Teams, who had already gained extensive experience in [[commando]] warfare in [[Korean War|Korea]]; however, the Underwater Demolition Teams were still necessary to the Navy's amphibious force.
[[File:US Navy 050505-N-3093M-009 Members of SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team Two (SDVT-2) huddle together inside a flooded Dry Deck Shelter mounted on the back of the Los Angeles-class attack submarine USS Philadelphia (SSN 690).jpg|thumb|Members of SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team Two in a [[Dry Deck Shelter]] of the submerged [[USS Philadelphia (SSN 690)|USS ''Philadelphia'']]]]

The first two teams were on both US coasts: Team One at [[Naval Amphibious Base Coronado]], in [[San Diego]], California and Team Two at [[Naval Amphibious Base Little Creek]], in [[Virginia Beach, Virginia]]. Men of the newly formed SEAL Teams were trained in such unconventional areas as [[hand-to-hand combat]], [[HALO jump|high-altitude parachuting]], [[demolitions]], and foreign languages. The SEALs attended Underwater Demolition Team replacement training and they spent some time training in UDTs. Upon making it to a SEAL team, they would undergo a SEAL Basic Indoctrination (SBI) training class at Camp Kerry in the [[Cuyamaca Peak|Cuyamaca Mountains]]. After SBI training class, they would enter a [[platoon]] and conduct platoon training.

The [[United States Pacific Command|Pacific Command]] recognized [[Vietnam]] as a potential hot spot for unconventional forces. At the beginning of 1962, the UDTs started [[hydrographic survey]]s and along with other branches of the US Military, the [[Military Assistance Command Vietnam]] (MACV) was formed. In March 1962, SEALs were deployed to [[South Vietnam]] as advisors for the purpose of training [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] [[commando]]s in the same methods they were trained themselves.

The [[Central Intelligence Agency]] began using SEALs in [[covert operation]]s in early 1963. The SEALs were involved in the CIA sponsored [[Phoenix Program]] where it targeted key North Vietnamese Army personnel and [[Vietcong]] sympathizers for capture and assassination.

The SEALs were initially deployed in and around [[Da Nang]], training the South Vietnamese in combat diving, demolitions, and guerrilla/anti-guerrilla tactics. As the war continued, the SEALs found themselves positioned in the Rung Sat Special Zone where they were to disrupt the enemy supply and troop movements and in the [[Mekong Delta]] to fulfill [[Brown-water navy|riverine]] operations, fighting on the inland waterways.

[[File:NavySeal1967Vietnam.jpg|thumb|left|SEALs on patrol in the [[Mekong Delta]]]]

Combat with the [[National Front for the Liberation of South Vietnam|Viet Cong]] was direct. Unlike the conventional warfare methods of firing artillery into a coordinate location, the SEALs operated within inches of their targets. Into the late 1960s, the SEALs were successful in a new style of warfare, effective in anti-guerrilla and guerrilla actions. SEALs brought a personal war to the enemy in a previously safe area. The Viet Cong referred to them as &quot;the men with green faces,&quot; due to the [[camouflage]] [[Body painting#Use in military|face paint]] the SEALs wore during combat missions.&lt;ref&gt;Point Man by Chief James Watson &amp; Kevin Dockery, 1993, ISBN 0-380-71986-X&lt;/ref&gt;

SEALs continued to make forays into North Vietnam and Laos, and covertly into [[Cambodia]], controlled by the [[Studies and Observations Group]]. The SEALs from Team Two started a unique deployment of SEAL team members working alone with South Vietnamese Commandos ([[Army of the Republic of Vietnam|ARVN]]). In 1967, a SEAL unit named Detachment Bravo (Det Bravo) was formed to operate these mixed US and ARVN units, which were called South Vietnamese Provincial Reconnaissance Units (PRUs).

At the beginning of 1968, the North Vietnamese and the Viet Cong orchestrated a major offensive against [[South Vietnam]]: the &quot;[[Tet Offensive]]&quot;. The North hoped it would prove to be America's [[Dien Bien Phu]], attempting to break the American public's desire to continue the war. As propaganda, the Tet Offensive was successful in adding to the American protest of the Vietnam war. However, North Vietnam suffered tremendous casualties, and from a purely military standpoint, the Tet Offensive was a major disaster for the Communists.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=The Vietnam Wars, Section 8: The Tet Offensive and its Aftermath |author=Edwin E. Moïse |publisher=Clemson University |url=http://www.clemson.edu/caah/history/FacultyPages/EdMoise/viet8.html |accessdate=2011-07-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1970, President [[Richard Nixon]] initiated a Plan of [[Role of United States in the Vietnam War#Vietnamization, 1969–1975|Vietnamization]], which would remove the US from the Vietnam War and return the responsibility of defense back to the South Vietnamese. Conventional forces were being withdrawn; the last SEAL advisor left Vietnam in March 1973 and Vietnam fell to the communists in 1975. The SEALs were among the highest decorated units for their size in the war. SEALs were awarded 2 [[Navy Cross]]es, 42 [[Silver star]]s, 402 [[Bronze Star]]s, 2 [[Legions of Merit]], 352 Commendation Medals, 3 Presidential Unit Citations&lt;ref name=NYT1968&gt;{{Citation |title= President Cites Seal Team |newspaper=[[The New York Times]] |date= 12 November 1968 |format= [[ProQuest]] |page= 21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NYT1970&gt;{{Citation |title= Washington For the Record |date= 19 Jun 19, 1970 |newspaper=The New York Times |date= 19 June 1970 |format= [[ProQuest]] |page= 4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and 3 [[Medals of Honor]].{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}}

===Grenada===
{{Main|Invasion of Grenada|Operation Urgent Fury}}
Both SEAL Team 4 and SEAL Team 6, the predecessor to [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group#Operation Urgent Fury|DEVGRU]], participated in the US invasion of Grenada. The SEALs' two primary missions were the extraction of Grenada's [[Paul Scoon|Governor-General]] and the capture of Grenada's only radio tower. Neither mission was well briefed or sufficiently supported with timely intelligence and the SEALs ran into trouble from the very beginning. One of their two transport planes missed its drop zone, and four SEALs drowned in a rain squall while making an airborne insertion with their boats off the island's coast. Their bodies were never recovered.

After regrouping from their initial insertion the SEALs split into two teams and proceeded to their objectives. After digging in at the Governor's mansion, the SEALs realized they had forgotten their [[SATCOM]] gear on the helicopter. As Grenadian and Cuban troops surrounded the team, the SEALs' only radio ran out of battery power, and they used the mansion's land line telephone to call in [[AC-130]] fire support. The SEALs were pinned in the mansion overnight and were relieved and extracted by a group of [[United States Marine Corps Force Reconnaissance|Force Recon]] Marines the following morning.

The team sent to the radio station also ran into communication problems. As soon as the SEALs reached the radio facility they found themselves unable to raise their command post. After beating back several waves of Grenadian and Cuban troops supported by BTR-60s, the SEALs decided that their position at the radio tower was untenable. They destroyed the station and fought their way to the water where they hid from patrolling enemy forces. After the enemy had given up their search the SEALs, some wounded, swam into the open sea where they were extracted several hours later after being spotted by a reconnaissance plane.

===Persian Gulf===
{{Main|Operation Prime Chance}}
During the closing stages of the [[Iran-Iraq War]] the United States Navy began conducting operations in the [[Persian Gulf]] to protect US flagged ships from attack by Iranian naval forces. A secret plan was put in place and dubbed [[Operation Prime Chance]]. Navy SEAL Teams 1 and 2 along with several Special Boat Units and [[United States Navy EOD|Navy EOD]] teams were deployed on mobile command barges and transported by helicopters from the [[160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment (United States)|Army's 160th Special Operations Aviation Regiment]]. Over the course of the operation SEALs conducted [[VBSS]] (Visit, Board, Search, and Seizure) missions to counter Iranian mine laying boats. The only loss of life occurred during the take down of the ''[[Iran Ajr]]''. Evidence gathered on the ''Iran Ajr'' by SEALs and EOD techs later allowed the US Navy to trace the mines that struck the [[USS Samuel B. Roberts (FFG-58)|''USS Samuel B. Roberts]]. This chain of events lead to [[Operation Praying Mantis]], the largest US Naval surface engagement since the Second World War.
During Operation Desert Shield and Storm, Navy SEALs trained Kuwaiti Special Forces. They set up naval special operations groups in Kuwait, working with the Kuwaiti Navy in exile. Using these new diving, swimming, and combat skills, these foreign SEALs took part in combat operations such as the liberation of the capital city.

===Panama===
{{Main|United States invasion of Panama}}
[[File:SEAL Team 4 Grenada.jpg|thumb|Members of SEAL Team 4 immediately before the start of Operation Just Cause]]
The United States Navy contributed extensive special operations assets to the invasion of Panama, code named Operation Just Cause. This included SEAL Teams 2 and 4, Naval Special Warfare Unit 8, and Special Boat Unit 26, all falling under Naval Special Warfare Group 2; and the separate [[Naval Special Warfare Development Group]] (DevGru). DevGru fell under Task Force Blue, while Naval Special Warfare Group 2 composed the entirety of Task Force White. Task Force White was tasked with three principal objectives: the destruction of [[Panamanian Defense Forces]] (PDF) naval assets in Balboa Harbor and the destruction of [[Manuel Noriega|Manuel Noriega's]] private jet at Paitilla Airport (collectively known as [[Operation Nifty Package]]), as well as isolating PDF forces on Flamenco Island.

The strike on Balboa Harbor by Task Unit Whiskey is notably marked in SEAL history as the first publicly acknowledged combat swimmer mission since the Second World War. Prior to the commencement of the invasion four Navy SEALs, Lt Edward S. Coughlin, EN-3 Timothy K. Eppley, ET-1 Randy L. Beausoleil, and PH-2 Chris Dye, swam underwater into the harbor on Draeger LAR-V [[rebreathers]] and attached [[C-4 (explosive)|C4 explosives]] to and destroyed Noriega's personal gunboat the ''Presidente Porras''.

Task Unit Papa was tasked with the seizure of Paitilla airfield and the destruction of Noriega's plane there. Several SEALs were concerned about the nature of the mission assigned to them being that airfield seizure was usually the domain of the [[75th Ranger Regiment (United States)|Army Rangers]]. Despite these misgivings and a loss of operational surprise, the SEALs of TU Papa proceeded with their mission. Almost immediately upon landing, the 48 SEALs came under withering fire from the PDF stationed at the airfield. Although Noriega's plane was eventually destroyed, the SEALs suffered four dead and thirteen wounded. Killed were Lt. John Connors, Chief Petty Officer Donald McFaul, Torpedoman's Mate 2nd Class Issac Rodriguez, and Boatswain's Mate 1st Class Chris Tilghman.

===Afghanistan===
{{Main|War in Afghanistan (2001–present)}}

====Invasion====
In the immediate aftermath of the [[11 September attacks]], Navy SEALs quickly dispatched to [[Camp Doha]], and those already aboard US Naval vessels in the Persian Gulf and surrounding waters began conducting [[VBSS]] operations against ships suspected of having ties to or even carrying [[al Qaeda]] operatives. SEAL Teams 3 and 8 also began rotating into Oman from the United States and staging on the island of [[Masirah Island|Masirah]] for operations in Afghanistan. One of the SEALs' immediate concerns was their lack of suitable vehicles to conduct [[special reconnaissance]] (SR) missions in the rough, landlocked terrain of Afghanistan. After borrowing and retrofitting Humvees from the [[U.S. Army Rangers|Army Rangers]] also staging on Masirah, the SEALs inserted into Afghanistan to conduct the SR of what would become [[Camp Rhino]], as part of [[War in Afghanistan (2001-present)|Operation Enduring Freedom]] (OEF). These early stages of OEF were commanded by a fellow SEAL, [[Rear admiral (United States)|Rear Admiral]] [[Albert Calland]].

[[File:US Navy SEALs at Zhawar Kili cave entrance.jpg|thumb|left|Task Force K-Bar SEALs at one of the entrances to the [[Zhawar Kili]] cave complex]]

The SR mission in the region of [[Camp Rhino]] lasted for four days, after which two [[United States Air Force Combat Control Team]]s made a nighttime [[HALO jump]] to assist the SEALs in guiding in [[U.S. Marine Corps|Marines]] from the [[15th Marine Expeditionary Unit]] who seized control of the area and established a [[Forward operating base]]. While at Camp Rhino, the [[Central Intelligence Agency|CIA]] passed on intelligence from a [[predator drone]] operating in the [[Paktia]] province that [[Taliban]] Mullah [[Khirullah Said Wali Khairkhwa]] was spotted leaving a building by vehicle convoy. SEALs and Danish [[Jægerkorpset]] commandos boarded Air Force [[Pave Low]] helicopters and seized Khairkhwa on the road less than two hours later. The SEALs continued to perform reconnaissance operations for the Marines until leaving after having spent 45 days on the ground.

[[File:US Navy SEALs in Khawar Kili.jpg|thumb|Task Force K-Bar SEALs searching munitions found in the [[Zhawar Kili]] cave complex]]

Subsequent SEAL operations during the invasion of Afghanistan were conducted within [[Task Force K-Bar]], a joint special operations unit of [[United States Army Special Forces|Army Special Forces]], [[Air Force Special Operations Command|United States Air Force Special Tactics Teams]], and special operations forces from Germany, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, Denmark, Norway, and Turkey, under the command of Navy SEAL Captain [[Robert Harward]]. Task Force K-Bar conducted combat operations in the massive cave complexes at [[Zhawar Kili]], the city of [[Kandahar]] and surrounding territory, the town of Prata Ghar and hundreds of miles of rough terrain in southern and eastern Afghanistan. Over the course of six months Task Force K-Bar killed or captured over 200 Taliban and al Qaeda fighters, and destroyed tens of thousands of pounds of weapons and ordnance.

Navy SEALs participated extensively in [[Operation Anaconda]]. During insertion, AB1 [[Neil C. Roberts|Neil Roberts]] was thrown from his helicopter when it took fire from entrenched al Qaeda fighters. Roberts was eventually killed after engaging and fighting dozens of enemies for almost an hour. Several SEALs were wounded in a rescue attempt and their Air Force Combat Controller, Technical Sergeant John Chapman, was killed. Attempts to rescue the stranded SEAL also led to the deaths of several US Army Rangers and an [[United States Air Force Pararescue|Air Force Pararescueman]] acting as a Quick Reaction Force.

SEALs were present at the [[Battle of Qala-i-Jangi]] alongside their counterparts from the British [[Special Boat Service]]. Chief Petty Officer [[Stephen Bass]] was awarded the [[Navy Cross]] for his actions during the battle. 

Lieutenant [[Michael P. Murphy]] was posthumously awarded the Medal of Honor after his four-man counterinsurgency team was almost wiped out during [[Operation Red Wing]] in June 2005.

The SEALs are also known for executing the notorious mission that assasinated Al Qaeda leader Osama Bin Laden in April 2011.


===Iraq War===
{{Main|Iraq War}}

====Al Faw and Iraqi oil infrastructure====
[[File:AlBasrahMESD823.png|300px|thumb|US military security personnel on the [[Al Basrah Oil Terminal]] after its capture]]

Several days before the beginning of the invasion of Iraq two SDV teams were launched from [[Mark V Special Operations Craft]] in the Persian Gulf. Their objectives were the [[Hydrographic survey|hydrographic reconnaissance]] of the [[KAAOT|Al Basrah (MABOT) and Khawr Al Amaya (KAAOT) Oil Terminals]]. After swimming under the terminals and securing their [[SEAL Delivery Vehicle|Mark 8 mod 1s]] the SDV SEALs spent several hours taking pictures and surveying Iraqi activity on both platforms before returning to their boats.

On 20 March 2003 the Navy SEALs launched what is the largest single SEAL operation in history from US Naval vessels, Ras al-Qulayah Naval Base and [[Ali Al Salem Air Base]] in Kuwait as part of a mixed force of US Navy SEALs, Polish [[GROM]] and British [[Royal Marines]]. Their targets were not only the ABOT and KAAOT platforms but their respective onshore petroleum pumping locks and the [[Al Faw]] port and refinery. Each force was to be inserted via helicopter or boat on the perimeter of the targets and then assault the main facilities. The first attacks occurred at the pumping locks for each offshore terminal. At MABOT's pumping lock the team's landing zone was covered in [[concertina wire]] that was unreported by their intelligence and so the SEALs and Royal Marines were forced to hover several feet off the ground. The Royal Marines, led by a Provost Sergeant, were the first off the helicopter followed by the SEALs and all immediately became entangled in the obstacles. In this exposed position the SEALs and Marines began taking fire from the platform's garrison. The landing at the KAAOT pumping lock ran into similar problems with their landing zone but both teams at both locations regrouped and successfully assaulted the pumping locks taking the main buildings and several occupied bunkers. After securing the facility an Iraqi armored vehicle approached the SEALs' position. Their embedded [[United States Air Force Combat Control Team|Air Force Combat Controller]] coordinated with an Air Force [[Fairchild Republic A-10 Thunderbolt II|A-10]] and destroyed the vehicle. In total five Iraqis were killed and sixteen captured.

The assault on the offshore platforms were carried out by SWCC manned [[RHIB|rigid-hulled inflatable boats (RHIB)]] carrying the SEALs and SWCC manned Mk Vs carrying the GROM. The SEALs were assigned MABOT and GROM the KAAOT. Two days before the launch of the operation the Iraqis replaced the MABOT garrison with elite [[Iraqi Republican Guard|Republican Guard troops]]. With this last minute change in opposition in mind, and the added fear of the Republican Guard blowing up the platforms upon attack, the SEALs decided to change their plan to quickly take out all opposition before physically securing MABOT. Once the SEALs assaulted MABOT via RHIB the Republican Guard forces immediately began to surrender. The GROM on KAAOT encountered the same unwillingness by the Iraqis to fight allowing both platforms to be taken with no deaths. Subsequent inspection on MABOT showed that the Iraqi forces had not primed their explosives having been unwilling to destroy the facility.
The assault on the Iraqi positions on the Al Faw peninsula consisted of a [[Desert Patrol Vehicle|DPV]] mounted SEAL force at the refinery and port with a larger force of US Marines from the [[5th Marine Regiment (United States)|5th Regimental Combat Team]] of the [[1st Marine Expeditionary Force]] attacking Iraqi positions farther north in the [[Rumaila field|Rumaila oil fields]]. Before the operation the SEALs raised objections that the ground looked unsuitable for DPV use but the faulty intelligence was assured by their attached intelligence liaison that the land on Al Faw would be hardpack. The teams went ahead and landed with their DPVs straight off the helicopters but their fears were confirmed when the oil soaked and muddy ground on the peninsula rendered their underpowered, rear wheel drive vehicles useless. Now on foot and surrounded by approximately 300 entrenched Iraqi soldiers and armored vehicles the SEALs relied on their Combat Controller to call in air strikes. In coordination with close air support the SEALs swept the entire facility on foot fighting through enemy positions until day break when they were relieved by the [[42 Commando]] of the British Royal Marines. In total several hundred Iraqis were killed, 100 captured and all the armored vehicles destroyed.

====Mukarayin Dam====
Coalition military planners were concerned that retreating Iraqi forces would destroy the Mukatayin hydroelectric dam northeast of Baghdad in an attempt to slow advancing US troops. In addition to restricting the maneuver of Coalition forces, the destruction of the dam would deny critical power needs to the surrounding area as well as cause massive flooding and loss of Iraqi civilian life. A mixed SEAL/GROM force was called in to seize the dam. This force was flown several hours by US Air Force [[Sikorsky MH-53|MH-53 Pave Lows]] to the dam. The SEALs employed DPVs into blocking positions to defend against counter-attack and roving bands of Iranian bandits that had been crossing the border and raiding Iraqi towns. As in Al Faw the SEALs found their DPVs to be ineffective and this marked the last time they would employ them in Iraq.

The SEALs and GROM on foot fast-roped out of their helicopters and immediately stormed the dam. The minimal Iraqi security forces on site surrendered, and with the exception of a GROM operator who broke an ankle during the insertion, the operation went off with no casualties. After several hours of searching the dam for remaining hostile forces or any explosives, the SEALs fully secured the dam and were later relieved by advancing elements of the US Army.

===Somali Pirates===
On 12 April 2009, in response to a hostage-taking incident off of the coast of [[Somalia]] by [[Somalian pirates]], three Navy SEALs from [[DEVGRU]] simultaneously engaged and killed the three pirates who were closely holding the hostage, [[Captain Richard Phillips]], of the freighter ship, the ''[[Maersk Alabama]]''. The pirates and their hostage were being towed in a lifeboat approximately 100 yards behind the ''[[USS Bainbridge (DDG-96)]]'', when the three pirates were killed by three [[DEVGRU]] snipers with single shots to each of their heads.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.cnn.com/2009/WORLD/africa/04/08/ship.hijacked/index.html |publisher=CNN | title=U.S. warship near boat carrying pirates&amp;nbsp;— CNN.com | date=9 April 2009 | accessdate=4 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Abbottabad, Pakistan ''(Death of Osama bin Laden)''===
{{Main|Death of Osama bin Laden}}

In the early morning of 2 May 2011 [[Pakistan Standard Time|local time]], a team of 40 CIA-led Navy SEALs from [[DEVGRU]], 24 on the ground, successfully completed an operation to kill [[Osama bin Laden]] in [[Abbottabad]], Pakistan about {{convert|35|mi|km}} from [[Islamabad]], the country's capital.&lt;ref name=SEALS_kill_OBL/&gt; The Navy SEALs were part of the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group|Naval Special Warfare Development Group]], previously called &quot;Team 6&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/blogpost/post/navy-seals-who-killed-osama-bin-laden-are-from-the-elite-team-6/2011/05/02/AFCC93YF_blog.html |title= Navy SEALs who killed Osama bin Laden are from the elite ‘Team 6’|first=Elizabeth|last=Flock|work=The Washington Post |date=2 May 2011|accessdate=2 May 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; President [[Barack Obama]] later confirmed the death of bin Laden, but did not directly mention the involvement of [[DEVGRU]], saying only that a &quot;small team&quot; of Americans undertook the operation to bring down bin Laden.&lt;ref name=SEALS_kill_OBL&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503543_162-20058792-503543.html|title=The raid on Osama bin Laden's compound|date=2 May 2011|newspaper=[[CBS News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The unprecedented media coverage raised the public profile of the SEAL community, particularly the counter-terrorism specialists commonly known as SEAL Team 6. [[The Walt Disney Company]] tried unsuccessfully to trademark the name &quot;SEAL Team 6&quot; the day after the raid.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.foxnews.com/politics/2011/05/25/mickey-mouse-surrenders-navy-seals-trademark-battle/|title=Mickey Mouse Surrenders to Navy SEALs in Trademark Battle|first=Jana|last=Winter|date=25 May 2011|accessdate=8 June 2011|work=[[Fox News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wardak Province Helicopter Crash===
{{Main|2011 Chinook shootdown in Afghanistan}}
On 6 August 2011, 17 Navy SEALs, were killed when their CH-47 Chinook helicopter was shot down by an RPG fired by Taliban Soldiers. The SEALs were en route to support Army Rangers who were taking fire while attempting to capture a senior Taliban leader in the Tangi Valley. Fifteen were SEALs belonging to the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group|Naval Special Warfare Development Group]]. Two others were SEALs assigned to a regular naval special warfare unit.&lt;ref&gt;Pentagon releases names of Chinook crash victims [http://news.blogs.cnn.com/2011/08/12/pentagon-releases-names-of-chinook-crash-victims/], CNN News blog, August 12, 2011. Retrieved 2011-08-14.&lt;/ref&gt; Eight other Americans and eight Afghans were also killed in the crash.

==Training==
{{Main|United States Navy SEAL selection and training}}
[[File:US Navy 071019-N-6552M-190 SEAL trainees scan the room for possible threats as part of a SEAL qualification training exercise.jpg|thumb|Students practice [[CQB]] drills during SEAL Qualification Training.]]

SEAL training is very rigorous, having a reputation as some of the toughest anywhere in the world. The drop out rate for BUDs classes are sometimes over 90 percent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Military Advantage |url=http://www.military.com/Content/MoreContent1?file=AS_specops |title=Content |publisher=Military.com |date=2007-02-15 |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; The average Navy SEAL spends over a year in a series of formal training environments before being awarded the [[List of United States Navy ratings|Special Warfare Operator Naval Rating]] and the [[Navy Enlisted Classification]] (NEC) 5326 Combatant Swimmer (SEAL) or, in the case of commissioned naval officers, the designation Naval Special Warfare (SEAL) Officer.

All Navy SEALs must attend and graduate from their rating's 24-week &quot;A&quot; [[United States Navy SEAL selection and training]]
course known as Basic Underwater Demolition/SEAL (BUD/S) school and then the 28-week SEAL Qualification Training (SQT) program. SQT qualifies all BUD/S graduates in basic SEAL skillsets in MAROPS, Combat Swimmer, Communications, TCCC, Close Quarters Combat, Land Warfare, Staticline/Freefall Parachute Operations, [[SERE]] and [[Combatives]]. All sailors entering the SEAL training pipeline with the Navy Hospital Corpsman rating or those chosen by Naval Special Warfare Command must also attend the 26&amp;nbsp;week Special Operations Combat Medic course and subsequently earn the NEC SO-5392 Naval Special Warfare Medic before joining an operational Team. Once outside the formal schooling environment SEALs entering a new Team at the beginning of an operational rotation can expect 18&amp;nbsp;months of Professional Development/Schools (PRODEV) and Troop unit level training (ULT) before each 6-month deployment. In total, from the time a prospective SEAL enters military service to the time he finishes his first predeployment training cycle, it can take as much as 30&amp;nbsp;months to completely train a Navy SEAL for his first deployment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Ann |first=Lee |url=http://science.howstuffworks.com/navy-seal3.htm |title=HowStuffWorks &quot;Navy SEAL Training&quot; |publisher=Science.howstuffworks.com |date=2006-11-27 |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Navy SEAL Teams and structures==
[[File:SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team (SDV) 2.jpg|thumb|Two members of, now disbanded, SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team 2 conduct lockout training with the [[USS Hawaii (SSN-776)|USS Hawaii]] in 2007.]]
[[File:US Navy 060117-N-3541A-002 A SEAL delivery vehicle team (SDV) perform a fast-roping exercise from a MH-60S Seahawk helicopter to the topside of Los Angeles-class fast attack submarine USS Toledo (SSN 769).jpg|thumb|SEALs from SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team Two fast-rope to the deck of the [[USS Toledo (SSN-769)|USS ''Toledo'']] (2005)]]

===Naval Special Warfare Groups===
Naval Special Warfare Command is organized into the following configuration:
* Naval Special Warfare Group 1: SEAL Teams 1, 3, 5, 7
* Naval Special Warfare Group 2: SEAL Teams 2, 4, 8, 10
* [[Naval Special Warfare Group 3]]: SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team 1
* Naval Special Warfare Group 4: Special Boat Teams 12, 20, 22
* Naval Special Warfare Group 11: SEAL Teams 17, 18 (formerly ''Operational Support Teams'' 1, 2)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Communication |first=Mass |url=http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=38975 |title=Naval Special Warfare Reserve Command Renamed |publisher=Navy.mil |date= |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The total number of Navy SEALs assigned to Naval Special Warfare Command is approximately 2,000 out of a total staffing of 6,500. About half of the SEAL contingent are based at [[Naval Amphibious Base Little Creek|Little Creek Naval Amphibious Base]] and [[Dam Neck Annex]] in [[Virginia Beach]], [[Virginia]]. Most of the remainder are headquartered at [[Naval Amphibious Base Coronado]], California or with SDVT-1 in [[Pearl Harbor]], Hawaii.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen, Louis, &quot;SEAL's Death At Training Facility Raises Safety Concerns&quot;, ''[[Norfolk Virginian-Pilot]]'', 28 February 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

===SEAL Teams===
SEAL Teams are organized into two groups: Naval Special Warfare Group One (West Coast), and Naval Special Warfare Group Two (East Coast), which come under the command of [[United States Naval Special Warfare Command|Naval Special Warfare Command]], stationed at NAB Coronado, California. As of 2006, there are eight confirmed Navy SEAL Teams. The original SEAL Teams in the Vietnam War were separated between West Coast (Team ONE) and East Coast (Team TWO) SEALs. The current SEAL Team deployments include Teams 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, and 10.

The Teams deploy as Naval Special Warfare Squadrons or Special Operations Task Forces and can deploy anywhere in the world. Squadrons will normally be deployed and fall under a Joint Task Force (JTF) or a Combined Joint Special Operations Task Force (CJSOTF) as a Special Operations Task Force (SOTF).

[[File:Combat Rubber Raiding Craft manned by SEAL-Team 5.jpg|thumb|left|upright|SEAL Team 5 conducts an exercise in a [[Combat Rubber Raiding Craft]] in 2000]]
Each SEAL Team is commanded by a Navy [[Commander]] (O-5), and has a number of operational SEAL platoons and a headquarters element.

A SEAL Team has a Staff Headquarters element and three 40-man Troops. Each Troop consist of a Headquarters element consisting of a Troop Commander (O-4), a Troop Senior Enlisted (E-8), a Targeting/Operations Officer (O-2/3) and a Targeting/Operations Leading/Chief Petty Officer (E-6/7). Under the HQ element are two SEAL platoons of 16–20 men (two officers, 14–16 enlisted SEALs and sometimes two enlisted EOD Operators making a platoon of 18–20); a company-sized Combat Service Support (CSS) and/or Combat Support (CS) consisting of staff N-codes (the Army and Marine Corps use S-codes); N1 Administrative support, N2 Intelligence, N3 Operations, N4 Logistics, N5 Plans and Targeting, N6 Communications, N7 Training, and N8 Air/Medical.

Each Troop can be easily task organized into four squads or eight 4–5 man fire teams for operational purposes. The size of each SEAL “Team” with Troops and support staff is approximately 300 personnel. The typical SEAL platoon has an OIC (Officer in Charge, usually an O-3), an AOIC (Assistant Officer in Charge, usually an O-2), a platoon chief (E-7), an Operations NCO/LPO (Leading Petty Officer, E-6) and other operators E-4 to E-6. The core leadership in the Troop and Platoon are the Commander/OIC and the Senior Enlisted NCO (Senior Chief/Chief).

Troop core skills consist of: Sniper, Breacher, Communicator, Maritime/Engineering, Close Air Support, Corpsman, Point-man/Navigator, Primary Driver/Navigator (Rural/Urban/Protective Security), Heavy Weapons Operator, Sensitive Site Exploitation, Air Operations Master, Lead Climber, Lead Diver/Navigator, Interrogator, Explosive Ordnance Disposal, Technical Surveillance, and Advanced Special Operations.

[[Naval Amphibious Base Little Creek]], a [[naval base]] in [[Virginia Beach, Virginia]], is home to SEAL Teams 2, 4, 8, and 10. [[Naval Amphibious Base Coronado]], a naval base in [[Coronado, California]], is home to SEAL Teams 1, 3, 5, and 7. There is also a [[SEAL Delivery Vehicle]] (SDV) unit, SDVT-1, located in [[Pearl Harbor, Hawaii]]. SDVT-2 was based in Virginia; it was disestablished and merged into SDVT-1. SDV Teams are SEAL teams with an added underwater delivery capability. An SDV [[platoon]] consists of 12–15 SEALs.
{{-}}
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;margin:0.5em 0.5em 0.5em 1em; padding:0.5em; font-size:95%;&quot;
|- style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot;
! Insignia!!Team!!Deployment !!Number of Platoons!!HQ!!Notes
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-1.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 1'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||[[Coronado, California]]||
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-2.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 2'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Little Creek, Virginia||SEAL Team 2 is the only SEAL Team that has arctic warfare capabilities
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-3.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 3'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Coronado, California||
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-4.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 4'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Little Creek, Virginia||SEAL Team 4 is the only SEAL Team with a viable standing language capability, which is Spanish.
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-5.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 5'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Coronado, California||
|-
|[[File:Sealteam-6scannedpatch.jpg|70px]]||'''[[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]]'''||Worldwide||Classified||Dam Neck, Virginia||SEAL Team 6 was dissolved in 1987. The operators of SEAL Team Six established the [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]], also known as DEVGRU. While DEVGRU is administratively supported by [[United States Naval Special Warfare Command|Naval Special Warfare Command]], they are operationally under the command of the [[Joint Special Operations Command]].
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-7.jpg|50px|SEAL Team 7]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 7'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Coronado, California||
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-8.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 8'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Little Creek, Virginia||
|-
|&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:SEAL-Team-10.jpg|70px]] --&gt;||'''SEAL Team 10'''||Worldwide||6 Platoons||Little Creek, Virginia||
|-
|[[File:Sealdeliveryvehicleteamonepatchsmall.jpg|70px]]||'''SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team One'''|||Worldwide||4 Platoons||Pearl Harbor, Hawai'i&lt;br /&gt;Dets in:&lt;br /&gt;Little Creek, Virginia&lt;br /&gt;San Diego, California||
|-
|[[File:21357 big.jpg|70px]]||'''SEAL Delivery Vehicle Team Two'''||Worldwide||4 Platoons||Little Creek, Virginia||Merged with SDVT-1
|}

==United States Navy Parachute Team &quot;Leap Frogs&quot;==
{{main|United States Navy Parachute Team &quot;Leap Frogs&quot;}}[[File:Ram air square.jpg|thumb|left|upright|A member of the U.S. Navy Parachute Demonstration Team the &quot;Leap Frogs&quot; returns to earth after a successful jump]]  The primary mission of the Navy Parachute Team (NPT) is to support Naval Special Warfare recruiting by gaining access and exposure to appropriate candidates through aerial parachuting demonstrations.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.leapfrogs.navy.mil/pdf/npt_handbook.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;
The U.S. Navy Parachute Team is a fifteen-man team comprised entirely of U.S. Navy SEAL and SWCC commandos. Each member comes to the team for a three-year tour from one of the two Naval Special Warfare Groups located on the east and west coasts. On completion of the tour, members return to operational units.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.leapfrogs.navy.mil/default.asp |title=Official U.S. Navy Parachute Team Web Site - Leap Frogs |publisher=Leapfrogs.navy.mil |date= |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The parachute team began in 1969 when Navy SEALs and Frogmen volunteered to perform at weekend air shows. The team was officially commissioned as the U.S. Navy Parachute Team in 1974 by the Chief of Naval Operations and assigned the mission of demonstrating Navy excellence throughout the United States.

A typical Leap Frogs performance consists of fourteen jumpers leaping out of an aircraft at an altitude of 12,500 feet. After freefalling sometimes using smoke or streamers, the Leap Frogs fly their canopies together to build canopy-relative work formations. After performances, the Leap Frogs make themselves available to the public to answer questions about the Navy and the Naval Special Warfare community, as well as to sign autographs.

==Women as Navy SEALs==
Women are not currently allowed to become Navy SEALs; this is the only Navy position closed to women.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.com/faq.html |title=Frequently Asked Questions |work=Navy.com |accessdate=2011-09-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Admiral [[Eric T. Olson]], a former SEAL and then-commander of [[United States Special Operations Command]], suggested in July 2011 that he believes women should serve as SEALs in combat roles, noting that physical strength was not the sole quality important in a SEAL;&lt;ref name=&quot;ABCfemaleseals&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://abcnews.go.com/Blotter/female-navy-seals-special-forces-chief-ready-road/story?id=14180174 |work=ABC News |title=Female Navy SEALs? Special Operations Commander 'Ready to Go Down That Road' |date=July 28, 2011 |first=Martha |last=Raddatz |first2=Rym |last2=Montaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; Secretary of the Navy [[Ray Mabus]] also did not rule out the idea of a woman becoming a SEAL, observing that while women cannot serve in combat roles, many work in auxiliary roles with Special Ops forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPofemaleseals&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |agency=Associated Press |url=http://www.washingtonpost.com/local/politics/a-female-navy-seal-not-yet/2011/05/31/AG4v6CGH_story.html |first=Lolita |last=Baldor |date=June 1, 2011 |title=A female Navy Seal? Not yet}}&lt;/ref&gt; Such roles include Cultural Support Teams, teams of two to four women troops which can gain access to and information from local women in conservative societies.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABCfemaleseals&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;WaPofemaleseals&quot;/&gt;

==National Navy UDT-SEAL Museum and Memorial==
{{main|National Navy UDT-SEAL Museum}}
The National Navy UDT-SEAL Museum, in [[Fort Pierce, Florida]], was recognized as a National Museum by an act of Congress&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navyseals.com/ft-pierce-museum-now-official-national-museum-navy-seals-and-their-predecessors |title=Ft. Pierce Museum Now the Official National Museum of Navy SEALs and Their Predecessors |publisher=NavySEALs.com |date= |accessdate=2011-10-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is dedicated to preserving the history of the Navy SEALs and their predecessors. The [http://www.navysealmuseum.com/ SEAL Museum] stands on the training site of the first Navy frogmen. There through [[World War II]], thousands of service members were trained as members of [[Naval Combat Demolition Units]] and [[Underwater Demolition Teams]]. The Museum houses rare historic artifacts from the founding of the UDT to present day, including weapons, vehicles, equipment, and most recently added, the [[MV Maersk Alabama|Alabama Maersk]] lifeboat aboard which [[Piracy in Somalia|Somali pirates]] held Captain Richard Phillips hostage.




==See also==
{{multicol}}
* [[List of Navy SEALs]]
* [[Red Cell]]
* [[SEAL Delivery Vehicle]]
{{multicol-break}}
{{Portal|Military of the United States}}
* [[Underwater Demolition Team]]
* [[United States Naval Special Warfare Development Group]]
* [[United States Navy SEALs in fiction]]
{{multicol-end}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
* {{cite web|title = Navy Fact File: Navy SEALs|publisher=San Diego: Naval Special Warfare Command&amp;nbsp;– Public Affairs Office, United States Navy|date=3 March 2005 |url=http://www.chinfo.navy.mil/navpalib/factfile/personnel/seals/seals.html |accessdate=25 June 2006 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20050303001021/http://www.chinfo.navy.mil/navpalib/factfile/personnel/seals/seals.html |archivedate = 3 March 2005}}
* McCoy, Shane T. (August 2004). &quot;Testing Newton's Law&quot;, ''All Hands Magazine'', p.&amp;nbsp;33.
* {{cite web|author=Obringer, Lee Ann|title= How the Navy SEALs Work | publisher=How Stuff Works |url= http://science.howstuffworks.com/navy-seal.htm|accessdate=14 June 2006}}
* Sasser, Charles W. ''Encyclopedia of The Navy SEALs'', Facts on File, 2002. (ISBN 0-8160-4569-0)

==Further reading==
* Bosiljevac, T.L. ''SEALs: UDT/SEAL Operations in Vietnam''. Ballantine Books, 1990. (ISBN 0-8041-0722-X)
* Bosiljevac, T.L. ''SEAL Team Roll-Back''. Avon Books, 1999. (ISBN 0-380-78714-8)
* Bahmanyar, Mir. ''US Navy SEALs''. Osprey Publishing, 2005. (ISBN 1-84176-807-3)
* Bahmanyar, Mir with Chris Osman. ''SEALs The US Navy's Elite Fighting Force''. Osprey Publishing, 2008. (ISBN 1-84603-226-1)
* Couch, Dick. ''The Sheriff of Ramadi: Navy SEALs and the Winning of al-Anba''. U.S. Naval Institute Press, 2008. (ISBN 1591141389)
* Couch, Dick. ''The Warrior Elite. The Forging of SEAL Class 228.'' Three Rivers Press, 2003. (ISBN 1400046955)
* Couch, Dick. ''The Finishing School. Earning the Navy SEAL Trident.'' Three Rivers Press, 2004. (ISBN 0-609-81046-4)
* Couch, Dick. ''Down Range. Navy SEALs in the War on Terrorism.'' Three Rivers Press, 2005. (ISBN 1-4000-8101-7)
* {{cite web |last=Jansing |first=Chris |title=A typical SEAL? Think 007, not Rambo |publisher=NBC Field Notes (NBC News) |date=29 January 2010 |url=http://fieldnotes.msnbc.msn.com/archive/2010/01/29/2188823.aspx |accessdate=29 January 2010}}
* Luttrell, Marcus. ''Lone Survivor: The Eyewitness Account of Operation Redwing and the Lost Heroes of SEAL Team 10''. Little, Brown and Company, 2009. (ISBN 0316044695)

==External links==
{{Commons|United States Navy Sea, Air and Land|United States Navy SEALs}}
* [http://www.sealswcc.com/ US Navy SEAL &amp; SWCC] official website
* [http://www.leapfrogs.navy.mil/ United States Navy Parachute Team] official website

{{US Special Operations Forces}}
{{US Navy navbox}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:United States Navy Seals}}
[[Category:Armed forces diving|US Navy SEALs]]
[[Category:Special Operations Forces of the United States|Navy SEALs]]
[[Category:United States Naval Special Warfare Command|SEALs]]
[[Category:United States Navy SEALs| ]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1961]]
[[Category:Commandos]]

[[da:United States Navy SEALs]]
[[de:United States Navy SEALs]]
[[es:SEAL]]
[[fa:یگان ویژه نیروی دریایی ایالات متحده آمریکا]]
[[fr:SEAL]]
[[ko:네이비 실]]
[[id:Navy SEAL]]
[[it:Navy SEAL]]
[[he:אריות הים (יחידה)]]
[[ka:ზღვის ლომები (ქვედანაყოფი)]]
[[mr:नेव्ही सील]]
[[nl:Navy SEALs]]
[[ja:Navy SEALs]]
[[no:United States Navy SEALs]]
[[pl:United States Navy SEALs]]
[[pt:Navy Seals]]
[[ru:SEAL]]
[[sl:Sea Air Land]]
[[fi:Navy SEAL]]
[[sv:Navy SEAL]]
[[tr:Navy SEALs]]
[[uk:Морські котики (спецназ)]]
[[zh:海豹部隊]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
