<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="382766" ns="0" title="Edwin Chadwick"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:SirEdwinChadwick.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Sir Edwin Chadwick.]]
'''Sir Edwin Chadwick''' [[Order of the Bath|KCB]] (24 January 1800 – 6 July 1890) was an [[England|English]] social reformer, noted for his work to reform the [[Poor Law]]s and improve [[sanitation|sanitary]] conditions and [[public health]]. One of the reasons why Chadwick believed in improvement to public health was because he believed it would save money.{{fact|date=May 2011}}

==Life==
In 1832 Chadwick was employed by the [[Royal Commission into the Operation of the Poor Laws 1832|Royal Commission]] appointed to inquire into the operation of the [[Poor Law]]s, and in 1833 he was made a full member of that body. Chadwick and [[Nassau William Senior]] drafted the famous report of 1834 recommending the reform of the old [[Poor Law]]. Under the 1834 system individual parishes were formed into [[Poor Law Unions]]{{ndash}} each Poor Law Union  was to have a union [[workhouse]]. Chadwick  favoured a more centralised system of administration than that which was adopted, and he felt the [[Reform movement|Poor Law reform]] of 1834 should have provided for the management of poor law relief by salaried officers controlled from a central board, the boards of guardians acting merely as inspectors.  

In 1834 he was appointed secretary to the Poor Law commissioners. Unwilling to administer an act of which he was largely the author in any way other than the way he thought best, he found it hard to get along with his superiors. This disagreement, among others, contributed to the dissolution of the Poor Law Commission in 1847. Chadwick's chief contribution to political controversy was his belief in entrusting certain departments of local affairs to trained and selected experts, instead of two representatives elected on the principle of local self-government.

While still officially working with the Poor Law, Chadwick took up the question of [[sanitation]] in conjunction with Dr [[Thomas Southwood Smith]].  Their joint efforts produced a salutary improvement in the [[public health]]. His report on ''The Sanitary Condition of the Labouring Population'' (1842)&lt;ref name=&quot;EdwinChadwick1842&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=excerpt from '''Report...from the Poor Law Commissioners on an Inquiry into the Sanitary Conditions of the Labouring Population of Great Britain''' (pp.369-372) (online source)|url=http://www.victorianweb.org/history/chadwick2.html| last=Chadwick| first=Edwin | chapter=Chadwick's Report on Sanitary Conditions | year=1842| publisher=to The Victorian Web  | location=added by Laura Del Col| pages=|accessdate=2009-11-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; was researched and published at his own expense. A supplementary report was also published in 1843.&lt;ref name=&quot;EdwinChadwick1843&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Report on the Sanitary Condition of the Labouring Population of Great Britain. A Supplementary Report on the results of a Special Inquiry into The Practice of Internment in Towns|url=http://www.archive.org/details/reportonsanitary00chaduoft| last= Chadwick| first= Edwin | edition= | year=1843| publisher=Printed by R. Clowes &amp; Sons, for Her Majesty's Stationery Office| location= London| page=|accessdate=2009-11-08}} Full text at Internet Archive (archive.org)&lt;/ref&gt; Chadwick's efforts were acknowledged by at least one health reformer of the day: [[William James Erasmus Wilson]] dedicated his 1854 book ''Healthy Skin'' to Chadwick &quot;In admiration of his strenuous and indefatigable labors in the cause of Sanitary Reform&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ErasmusWilson1854&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Healthy Skin: A Popular Teatise on the Skin and Hair, their Preservation and Management |url=http://www.archive.org/details/healthyskinapop04wilsgoog| last= Wilson| first= Erasmus| edition=2nd American, from the 4th Revised London | year=1854| publisher=Blanchard &amp; Lea | location= Philadelphia| page=|accessdate=2009-11-08}} Full text at Internet Archive (archive.org)&lt;/ref&gt;

Chadwick was a commissioner of the [[Metropolitan Commission of Sewers]] in [[London]] from 1848 to 1849; he was also a commissioner of the [[Local board of health#General Board of Health|General Board of Health]] from its establishment in 1848 to its abolition in 1854, when he retired on a pension, and occupied the remainder of his life in voluntary contributions to sanitary, health and economical questions. In January 1884 he was appointed as the first president of the Association of Public Sanitary Inspectors (now the [[Chartered Institute of Environmental Health]]). 

In recognition of his public service Chadwick was [[knight]]ed in 1889. He served in his post until his death in 1890 at [[East Sheen]] in [[Surrey]].

* {{1911}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Biography}}
* [http://www.victorianweb.org/history/chad1.html  Marjie Bloy, &quot;Edwin Chadwick (1800-1890)&quot;, ''The Victorian Web'']
* [http://www.cieh.org/ Chartered Institute of Environmental Health]
* {{NRA|P5267}}
* {{Citation |title=Eminent persons: Biographies reprinted from the Times, Vol IV, 1887-1890|publisher=Macmillan &amp; Co.|pages=244–250|year=1893|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=PxIYAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA244 Sir Edwin Chadwick (Obituary) in}}
* {{Find a Grave|6532416|accessdate=September 3, 2010}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Chadwick, Edwin
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 1800-01-24
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =
| DATE OF DEATH     = 1890-07-16
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Chadwick, Edwin}}
[[Category:1800 births]]
[[Category:1890 deaths]]
[[Category:London water infrastructure]]
[[Category:People from Longsight]]

[[de:Edwin Chadwick]]
[[es:Edwin Chadwick]]
[[fr:Edwin Chadwick]]
[[ja:エドウィン・チャドウィック]]
[[pl:Edwin Chadwick]]
[[sv:Edwin Chadwick]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
