<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="382809" ns="0" title="Dyne:bolic"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{lowercase|title=dyne:bolic}}
{{Infobox OS
|name = dyne:bolic
|logo = [[Image:Dynebolic logo bevel.png|180px|dyne:bolic logo]]
|screenshot = [[Image:Dynebolic 2-5-2.png|180px|dyne:bolic XFCE User Interface Screenshot]]
|caption = Screenshot of dyne:bolic
|developer = [[Jaromil]], [http://dyne.org dyne.org]
|family = [[Unix-like]]
|source_model = [[Free and open source software]]
|latest_release_version = 3.0.0
|latest_release_date = September 8, 2011
|working_state = Stable
|kernel_type = [[Monolithic kernel|Monolithic]] [[Linux kernel]]
|ui = [[GNOME|Gnome2]]
|license = [[GNU GPL]] and other [[free and open source software]] licenses
|website = [http://www.dynebolic.org/ www.dynebolic.org]
}}
'''dyne:bolic''' is a [[Live CD]]/DVD based on the [[Linux kernel]] with a focus on [[multimedia]] production,&lt;ref name=&quot;Compworld&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.computerworld.com.au/article/142024/dine_geek_heaven_dyne_bolicii?fp=16&amp;fpid=0|title=Dine in geek heaven with Dyne:bolicII |last= McConnachie |first=Dahna|date=2005-10-25|publisher=Computer World|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;independent&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/media/open-source-websites-all-change-on-the-internet-522183.html|title=Open source websites: All change on the internet|last=Kronschnabl|first=Ana |coauthors=Tomas Rawlings |date=2006-01-09|publisher=The Independent|accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is distributed with a large assortment of applications for audio and video manipulation. Termed &quot;[[Rastafari movement|Rasta]][[software|soft]]&quot; by its author, dyne:bolic is based entirely on [[free software]], and is recognized by the [[GNU Project]] for this characteristic.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gnu.org/distros/free-distros.html GNU project website]&lt;/ref&gt;

'''dyne:bolic''' is designed and optimized for old and slower computers, turning them into full media stations: this is why the software in it is often not at the newest version available. But the result for this is that the minimum you need is a [[P5 (microarchitecture)|Pentium1]] or [[AMD K5|K5]] PC with only 64 MB RAM and an IDE CD-ROM, or an [[Xbox]] game console - and if you have more than one, you can easily do clusters.&lt;ref name=&quot;dynebolic.org&quot;&gt;http://dynebolic.org&lt;/ref&gt;

Latest version is 3.0.0, codename [[Munir_Said_Thalib|MUNIR]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dynebolic.org/2011/09/announce-3-0-0/#sec-1_5 dynebolic.org version 3.0.0 announcement, section codename]&lt;/ref&gt;, released on September 8, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dynebolic.org/2011/09/announce-3-0-0/ dynebolic.org version 3.0.0 announcement]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Live CD/DVD ==
dyne:bolic is designed from ground up to be used as Live CD/DVD. It does not require installation to a hard drive, and attempts to recognize most devices and peripherals automatically (for example: sound, video, TV, etc.). Its kernel is highly optimized for low latency and high performance, making it suitable for audio and video production.&lt;ref name=&quot;dynebolic.org&quot;/&gt;

== System requirements ==
dyne:bolic is not based on any other existing Live CD/DVD technology. Version 3.x has higher system requirements than older versions of dyne:bolic, and is the first version released as DVD image instead of CD-ROM image.

Basic system requirements for version 1.x and 2.x are relatively low: a PC with a Pentium MMX (i586) class CPU and 64 [[Megabyte|MB]] of RAM is sufficient. Some versions of dyne:bolic can be used on an [[Xbox]] game console (Xbox is not currently supported by v2.0). 

== Installation ==
The user copies the dyne directory from the CD (described in dyne:bolic literature as &quot;Docking&quot;) to any suitably formatted partition or drive. This filesystem will be recognised and booted by the CD, or there is the option to install a bootloader or edit an existing one. Booting from floppy disk is also supported. Dyne:bolic can save user settings in a file on a partition (or even user's own [[USB flash drive]]) which can also be encrypted for better privacy (described as &quot;Nesting&quot; in the db literature).

== Multimedia support ==
dyne:bolic has been shaped by the needs of [[mass media|media]] [[activism|activist]]s, [[artist]]s and creators, to be a practical tool for [[multimedia]] production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sharma_07&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title=Dyne:Bolic 2.4.2: A live CD multimedia studio | author=Mayank Sharma | url=http://www.linux.com/feature/61140 | date=2007-04-10 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It allows manipulation and [[Broadcasting|broadcast]] of both sound and video with tools to record, edit, encode, and stream. In addition to many multimedia specific programs, dyne:bolic also provides word processors and common desktop computing tools.

The dyne:bolic author and maintainer [[Jaromil]] has also created various multimedia tools included in the distribution: MuSE, HasciiCam, [[FreeJ]], as well as other software functionalities such as the nesting and docking, while co-developer and friend, Smilzo contributed the port for Xbox game consoles.

== Modules ==
dyne:bolic can be extended by downloading extra modules such as development tools or [[OpenOffice.org]]. The modules are [[SquashFS]] files placed in the &lt;tt&gt;modules&lt;/tt&gt; directory of a dock (see above) or a CD and are automatically integrated at boot.

== dyne:bolic 1.x ==
Version 1.4.1 (using Linux 2.4) is a CD-ROM image, and is provided for [[Xbox]] use. [[Xfce]] is used as the [[Desktop environment|desktop]] interface.
There are few things that were present in dyne:bolic line 1.x. It was:
* [[openMosix]] - clustering software&lt;ref name=&quot;db_1_0_readme&quot;&gt;''whenever you boot dyne:bolic on a local network, configuring it or having it configured automatically thru DHCP, the system automatically discovers for other dyne:bolic running on it and joins them in a CLUSTER: which means they SHARE their CPU POWER like a &quot;supercomputer&quot;''&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[WindowMaker]] as fast and small [[memory footprint|footprint]] [[X window manager]]
* [[The_World_Factbook|CIA Factbook]] - local copy
* ability to boot on [[Xbox]] game console
These features were abandoned in the dyne:bolic 2.x series.

== dyne:bolic 2.x ==
Version 2.5.2 uses Linux 2.6, and is a CD-ROM image. [[Xfce]] is used as the [[Desktop environment|desktop]] interface.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
* [[List of GNU/Linux distributions endorsed by the Free Software Foundation]]
* [[Comparison of Linux LiveDistros]]
* [[Musix]]
* [[Ubuntu Studio]]
* [[64 Studio]]
* [[puredyne]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.dynebolic.org dyne:bolic website]
* [http://puredyne.goto10.org pure:dyne] — dyne:II based live CD focused on audio and video processing
{{Xfce}}
{{Linux distributions}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dyne:Bolic}}
[[Category:Free audio software]]
[[Category:Operating system distributions bootable from read-only media]]
[[Category:Linux media creation distributions]]

[[de:Dyne:bolic]]
[[es:Dyne:bolic]]
[[fr:Dynebolic]]
[[it:Dyne:bolic]]
[[nl:Dyne:bolic]]
[[pl:Dyne:bolic]]
[[sk:Dyne:bolic]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
