<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="383130" ns="0" title="California State University, Long Beach"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name            = California State University,&lt;br&gt;Long Beach
|image           = [[File:CSU-Longbeach seal.svg|200px|CSULB official school seal]]
|motto           = ''Vox Veritas Vita'' (Latin)
|mottoeng        = &quot;Voice, Truth, Life&quot;
|type            = [[Public university|Public]]
|endowment       = [[United States dollar|US $]]31.1 million (2009)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.foundation.csulb.edu/misc/csulbf_finstate_09.pdf CSULB Foundation Audited Financial Statements]&lt;/ref&gt;
|established     = 1949
|president       = [[F. King Alexander]]
|provost         = Don Para
|city            = [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]]
|state           = [[California]]
|country         = [[United States]]
|students        = 33,417 (Fall 2010)&lt;ref name=enrollment10&gt;[http://campus-sas.csulb.edu/IRHTMLRepts/StudentHC_104.html Fall 2010 Headcount]&lt;/ref&gt;
|undergrad       = 27,437&lt;ref name=enrollment10 /&gt;
|postgrad        = 5,980&lt;ref name=enrollment10 /&gt;
|faculty         = 1,996 (1,098 full time)&lt;ref name=faculty&gt;[http://campus-sas.csulb.edu/IRpdfreports/univfacts20094.pdf University Facts Fall 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;
|campus          =[[Urban area|Urban]], {{convert|323|acre|ha}}
|former_names    = *Los Angeles-Orange County State College (1949-50)
*Long Beach State College (1950-64)
*California State College, [at] Long Beach (1964-72)
|athletics       = 18 varsity teams,&lt;br&gt;[[NCAA]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|mascot          = Prospector Pete |
|nickname        = [[California Gold Rush#Forty-niners|49ers]], [[The Dirtbags|Dirtbags]], The Beach
|colors          = [[Or (heraldry)|Gold]] and [[Sable (heraldry)|Black]] {{color box|#FFCC00}}{{color box|#000000}}
|affiliations    = [[California State University]] system; [[Big West Conference]],&lt;br&gt; [[Mountain Pacific Sports Federation]], [[American Association of State Colleges and Universities|AASCU]], [[Association of Southeast Asian Institutions of Higher Learning|ASAIHL]]
|logo            = [[Image:Beach-Big.png|200px|LBSU Athletics Department Logo]]
|website         = http://www.csulb.edu/
}}

'''California State University, Long Beach''' (also known as '''Cal State Long Beach''', '''Long Beach State''', '''CSULB''', '''LBSU''', or '''The Beach''') is the second largest [[campus]] of the [[California State University]] (CSU) system and the third largest [[university]] in the state of [[California]] by enrollment.&lt;ref name=csuenrollment&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/as/stat_reports/2009-2010/f09_01.htm CSU | AS | Term Enrollment Summary]&lt;/ref&gt; The University is located at the southeastern coastal tip of [[Los Angeles County]], less than one mile from the border with [[Orange County, California|Orange County]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=W+Campus+Dr+%26+E+State+University+Dr,+Long+Beach,+CA+90840&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;om=1 Map]&lt;/ref&gt;

CSULB has been recognized repeatedly as one of &quot;America's Best Value Colleges&quot; by the ''[[Princeton Review]]''. More than 30 factors are considered to rate the colleges in four categories: academics, tuition GPA (the sticker price minus average amount students receive in gift aid scholarships and grants), financial aid (how well colleges meet students' financial need) and student borrowing.  The university attained its highest ranking in the 2007 edition: the No. 3 best value public college in the nation.&lt;ref name=&quot;bestvalue07&quot;&gt;The Beach Review, Spring 2006: [http://www.csulb.edu/misc/beachreview/archives/2006/spring/noteworthy.htm Princeton Review Ranks Cal State Long Beach No. 3 Best Value Public College in the United States]. ''Public Affairs and Publications.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; Every year that CSULB has been included in the ''[[Princeton Review|Review]]'s'' &quot;Best Value Colleges&quot; rankings, it was the only university in the [[California State University|CSU]] system to receive such recognition.&lt;ref name=bestvalue09&gt;[http://karl.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=1093 The Princeton Review Ranks Cal State Long Beach Among Top 50 ‘Best Value’ Public Colleges for 2009 in United States]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bestvalue10&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/news/education/best-value-colleges.htm 100 Best Value Colleges for 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

Long Beach State has also been ranked as one of the top five public Master's Degree-granting institutions in the [[Western United States|West]] by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'''s &quot;America's Best Colleges Guide&quot; in every year's edition from 2005 to 2011.&lt;ref name=usnewsrank&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/masters-west-search U.S. News &amp; World Report: September 3, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=revranks&gt;[http://karl.papubs.csulb.edu/cms/index.cfm?contentID=12&amp;# The Beach Review, Fall 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=revranks3&gt;[http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/masters-west-top-public Best Colleges: Top Public Schools: Master's Universities (West)] Feb 1, 2010&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Long Beach State is one of the [[West Coast of the United States|West Coast's]] top universities in student body racial diversity, being named the 5th most diverse university in the West by U.S. News &amp; World Report.&lt;ref name=&quot;diversity&quot;&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/misc/beachreview/archives/2007/fall/noteworthy/ CSULB Receives High Rankings] Retrieved 2/18/09&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;diversity2&quot;&gt;[http://cf.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=1418 This Week @ The Beach] Retrieved 8/18/10&lt;/ref&gt; It is also home to the largest publicly funded art school west of the [[Mississippi River|Mississippi]]. The university currently operates with one of the lowest student fees in the country at [[United States dollar|US $]]4,370 per year for full time students having California residence.&lt;ref name=&quot;fees&quot;&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/depts/enrollment/registration/fees_basics.html Fees and Finances - Basics]. ''Division of Administration &amp; Finance.'' Retrieved July 8, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
[[Image:Los Angeles-Orange County State College.jpg|left|thumb|200px|The original location of Los Angeles-Orange County State College.]]
  
The College was established in 1949 by California Governor [[Earl Warren]], to serve the rapidly expanding post-[[World War II]] population of [[Orange County, California|Orange]] and Southern [[Los Angeles, California|Los Angeles]] counties. Since then, CSULB has grown to become one of the state's largest and most well respected universities.

The institution was first known as ''Los Angeles-Orange County State College''. It offered 25 courses, taught by 13 faculty members, in two apartment buildings at 5381 Anaheim Road in [[Long Beach, California|Long Beach]]. In June 1950, the citizens of Long Beach voted overwhelmingly to purchase {{convert|320|acre|ha}} as a permanent campus for the college, then known as ''Long Beach State College''. The purchase price was nearly $1,000,000. Student enrollment grew rapidly in this new, permanent location.

By 1960, the student body exceeded 10,000 students, and by 1966, 20,000. In 1964, LBSC changed its name to ''California State College at Long Beach'' to conform to the state system and enhance its prestige (it was renamed ''California State College, Long Beach'' in 1968).

In 1965, CSCLB hosted the first [[International Sculpture Symposium]] to be held in the [[United States]] and the first such symposium to be held at a college or university. Six sculptors from abroad and two from the United States created many of the monumental sculptures present on the campus. The event received national media attention from newspapers around the country, including the ''[[New York Times]]'', ''[[Los Angeles Times]] Magazine'', ''[[Art in America]]'' and a six-page color spread in ''[[Fortune Magazine]]''.

The school acquired [[university]] status in 1972, along with 12 other state college campuses. The promotion was decided by the Board of Trustees of the [[California State University]] system, according to total enrollment, size of graduate programs, complexity and diversity of majors and number of doctorates held by faculty at each college. CSCLB thus became ''CSULB''.

Also in 1972, the campus became the home of the largest library facility in the then 19-campus [[California State University|CSU]] system: a modern six-story building with a [[seating capacity]] of nearly 4,000 students.

In 1995, President [[Robert Maxson]] initiated the privately-funded President's Scholars Program, providing selected qualified California high school [[valedictorian]]s and [[National Merit]] finalists and semi-finalists with a full four-year scholarship package, including tuition, a book stipend, and housing. {{As of|2010|May}}, over 1000 students have accepted the scholarship.&lt;ref&gt;http://karl.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=1014&lt;/ref&gt; For applicants for Fall 2010, National Achievement Program Semifinalists/Finalists and National Hispanic Recognition scholars were also considered.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.csulb.edu/divisions/students/presidents_scholars/application_process/&lt;/ref&gt;

{{As of|2008|September|alt=As of Fall 2008}}, CSULB had 37,890 students in attendance, making it the most populous campus of the CSU system.

==Campus==
The campus spans {{convert|323|acre|ha}} across 84 buildings, and is located {{convert|3|mi|km}} from the [[Pacific Ocean]]. It has its own U.S. Postal [[Zip code]]: 90840. CSULB is located at 1250 Bellflower Boulevard. It is bounded by East 7th Street to the south, East Atherton Street to the north, Bellflower Boulevard to the west, and Palo Verde Avenue to the east.

===Architecture===
The architecture of the campus is mostly of the [[International style (architecture)|International style]] (designed primarily by noted architect [[Edward Killingsworth]]) and is very minimalist, placing emphasis instead on the landscaping that surrounds it. This naturalistic, park-like layout has earned the campus numerous design awards, as well as other awards from gardening societies. Recent construction maintains the characteristic glass-and-brick style. The integration of landscaping and architecture is apparent at the school's theater complex, where a dense grove of [[ficus]] trees is planted in such a way that it forms a continuation of the pillar-supported canopy at the theater's entrance. The University's registration offices are located in the open courtyard of Brotman Hall, which is &quot;roofed&quot; by a similar jungle-like canopy. The Psychology building is also notable for its soaring, airy courtyard planted with tall [[Eucalyptus]] trees.

===Campus landmarks===
[[Image:Walter Pyramid.jpg|right|thumb|275px|The [[Walter Pyramid]], the University's most prominent sporting complex and most recognizable landmark.]]

The '''University Student Union''' (USU) building is located at the center of campus. The three-story glass building occupies roughly {{convert|180000|sqft|m2}}, housing numerous offices, and offering more casual attractions, including a study lounge, a ballroom, a food court, a bowling alley, an arcade, and a movie theater.

49er basketball and volleyball games are currently played in the iconic, eighteen-story '''[[Walter Pyramid]]''' (formerly known as the Long Beach Pyramid) located on north campus. The Pyramid is a state-of-the-art sporting complex that can accommodate over 5,000 fans, including temporary seating and standing room. Two sections of interior stands are fitted with large [[hydraulic]] lifts which can lift the seating elements forty-five degrees into the air, creating room for five volleyball courts or three basketball courts.&lt;ref name=&quot;pyramid&quot;&gt;[http://www.longbeachstate.com/local/facilities/pyramid.html The Walter Pyramid]. ''Long Beach State Athletics.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt; The Pyramid is home to the [[Southern California Summer Pro League]], a noted showcase for current and prospective NBA basketball players.

The '''University Art Museum''' (UAM) ranks in the top 10% of the nation's over 6,000 museums. Its permanent collection contains primarily abstract expressionist paintings, works on paper, and an outdoor sculpture garden that began in 1966. The UAM was the first accredited museum in the [[California State University|CSU system]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal| last = Melrod| first = George | title = University Galleries: Los Angeles Region | journal = art ltd. | page = 45 | publisher = Lifescapes Publishing, Inc. | date = January/February 2010 | issn = 1941-8558|url=http://www.artltdmag.com/index.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1262633830&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=28&amp;|accessdate=March 3, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the museum's Gordon F. Hampton collection is housed at the [[Downtown Los Angeles]] law offices of [[Sheppard, Mullin, Richter &amp; Hampton]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Art|url=http://www.sheppardmullin.com/industries-31.html|work=Sheppard Mullin|publisher=[[Sheppard, Mullin, Richter &amp; Hampton]]|accessdate=23 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The campus is also home to the '''[[Carpenter Performing Arts Center]]''', a 1,074-seat theater named after CSULB alumni [[The Carpenters|Richard and Karen Carpenter]].

The '''[[Earl Burns Miller Japanese Garden]]''' is an artistic retreat of solitude and beauty. Among its many picturesque attractions, The Garden features a large pond populated with [[koi]].

One of the newest areas that has become integral to student life in the Parkside dormitories is The Circle. The Circle was formed as part of the central landscaping of the Parkside Commons outdoor common area when a group of students moved the 4 'S' shaped stone benches residing there into a circle formation in the Fall of 2008. Since then, The Circle (also known as the Late Night Circle, due to its high concentration of nighttime denizens) has become the defining marker of the Parkside experience, and it continues to provide a fun hangout for the residents of Parkside Commons.
{{wide image|Csulb10-pano.jpg|1090px|&lt;center&gt;Panoramic view of the campus's sports fields, prior to the construction of the SRWC.&lt;/center&gt;}}

===Puvunga===
The campus is believed to be the location of an ancient [[Tongva people|Tongva]] village and burial site known as [[Puvunga]], and is listed on the [[National Register of Historic Places]]. CSULB has challenged this designation, claiming they were not consulted when the application was filed.{{Citation needed|date=September 2008}} From 1992 to 1995, when the university attempted to build a [[strip mall]] and student housing on the last undeveloped portion of the campus, the Tongva people filed a lawsuit and initiated a protest, which involved physically occupying the land day and night to stave off [[bulldozer]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;puvunga&quot;&gt;[http://www.csulb.edu/~eruyle/puvudoc_0000_about.html Background on Puvunga and the Sacred Site Struggle]. ''About Puvungna.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

===Future development===
In the Spring of 2007, the student body voted to approve the construction of a student recreation and wellness center on campus. Slated for completion by Fall 2010, the Rec and Wellness Center was planned to be an extensive all-purpose athletic center covering about {{convert|125000|sqft|m2}} on North Campus. Plans included facilities for fitness programs and aerobics classes, courts for volleyball, basketball and badminton, rock climbing walls, an indoor track, a student lounge, and much more.  This program is funded and managed by CSULB's Associated Students, Incorporated. This project has been completed and had its first opening the week before the fall semester of 2010.&lt;ref name=readysetrec&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.asirecreation.org |title=ASI Recreation |accessdate=September 17, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Campus sustainability===
[[Image:csulb1.jpg|right|thumb|200px]]
[[Image:csulb2.jpg|right|thumb|200px]]

The University, in its push to support climate sustainability, installed solar panels on the Brotman Hall building and the Facilities Management canopy parking in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;solar panels&quot;&gt;[http://clubesp.googlepages.com/CSULBSolarPanels091007.pdf]. ''CSULB's installation of solar panels.'' Retrieved September 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;  The University has been taking steps in addressing the challenge of sustainability, with the support of its student government, student body, and organizations, such as the Environmental Science &amp; Policy Club.

The Environmental Science &amp; Policy Club (ES&amp;P Club)&lt;ref name=&quot;CSULB ES&amp;P Club&quot;&gt;[http://clubesp.googlepages.com]. ''CSULB ES&amp;P Club.'' Retrieved August 2007&lt;/ref&gt; has brought support to environmental awareness and sustainability through club activities, such as coastal clean-ups, hikes, plant-restoration project, tabling, conferences, guest speakers, &amp; Kaleidoscope.  In 2006, the ES&amp;P Club supported the installation of waterless urinals in the University's men's restrooms.&lt;ref name=&quot;urinals&quot;&gt;[http://clubesp.googlepages.com/WaterConservation042006.pdf]. ''Water Conservation at CSULB.'' Retrieved April 2006&lt;/ref&gt; The ES&amp;P Club hosts an annual Earth Week celebration each April, including documentary screenings, discussions, and speaker series.&lt;ref name=&quot;wetlands&quot;&gt;[http://clubesp.googlepages.com/WetlandsConservationistVisit042607.pdf]. ''Wetland Discussion at CSULB.'' Retrieved April 26, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;earth week&quot;&gt;[http://clubesp.googlepages.com/2007EarthWeekEvent042407.pdf]. ''EarthWeek at CSULB.'' Retrieved April 24, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The University &quot;has a comprehensive energy management program incorporating real-time metering and energy-saving technologies such as the EnergySaver, which provides a more sophisticated alternative to turning off the lights by automatically varying the voltage to the ballasted fixtures and reducing the power consumed, while maintaining appropriate lighting levels.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;energy&quot;&gt;[http://csuchico.edu/sustainablefuture/practices/Chico-DST-final-041905.pdf]. ''Decisions for a Sustainability Tomorrow.'' Retrieved April 19, 2005&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Public transportation ===
The campus is currently serviced by:

*[[Long Beach Transit]] (routes 81, 91, 92, 93, 94, 171, 173, 96 ZAP, and Passport D)
*[[Orange County Transportation Authority|OCTA]] (routes 1, 50, and 60)
*[[Los Angeles County Metropolitan Transportation Authority|LACMTA]] [[Metro Express|Express]] (route 577X, [[LACMTA Blue Line]] also provides service to the Long Beach area, accessible by bus routes)

In September 2008, President F. King Alexander announced the school's new &quot;U-PASS&quot; program in conjunction with Long Beach Transit. Under the new partnership, students with a valid CSULB I.D. card ride any Long Beach Transit bus for free during school months.&lt;ref name=upass&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.csulb.edu/misc/inside/archives/v60n18/stories/22.htm |title=CSULB, Long Beach Transit Announce Extension of U-PASS |accessdate= |author= |date=October 15, 2008 |work=Inside CSULB |publisher=California State University, Long Beach}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[Image:Brotman Hall.jpg|thumb|250px|E. James Brotman Hall, the University's administrative headquarters on campus.]]

CSULB comprises eight academic colleges:
*College of the [[Arts]]
*College of [[Business Administration]]
*College of [[Education]]
*College of [[Engineering]]
*College of [[Health]] &amp; Human Services
*College of [[Liberal Arts]]
*College of [[Natural Sciences]] and [[Mathematics]]
*College of [[Continuing &amp; Professional Education]]

Together, the colleges offer a total of 81 [[Bachelor's degree|baccalaureate]] degrees, 67 [[Master's degree|master's]] degrees, 16 education-related [[credential]] programs, and three [[Doctorate|doctoral]] degrees (two joint and one independent).&lt;ref name=&quot;degrees&quot;&gt;Introduction to the Institutional Report: [http://www.ced.csulb.edu/accreditation/introduction/index.html Overview of the Institution]. ''College of Education.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

The University's educational goals reflect its large population of students and faculty. Among the numerous classes and majors, [[Liberal Arts]] and [[Sciences]] represent the [[Core curriculum|General Education]] (GE) core, while a variety of classes make up GE electives; all GE classes focus on the development of writing and critical thinking skills.

===Academic department reputations===

CSU Long Beach's College of the Arts has more art and [[design]] majors than any other public university in America. CSU Long Beach also produces the most master of science in [[nursing]] (MSN) graduates in the 23-campus CSU system.&lt;ref name=sciences&gt;http://www.calstate.edu/impact/campus/longbeach.html&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' has repeatedly ranked CSULB engineering program as one of the Top 50 undergraduate programs in the nation (amongst [[Master's degree|master's]] level universities), and even commended the University's programs for first-year students as &quot;stellar examples of academic programs that lead to student success.&quot;&lt;ref name=engineering&gt;CSULB News and Events: [http://karl.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=467 This Week @ The Beach].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=engineering2&gt;CSULB News and Events: [http://cf.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=1214 This Week @ The Beach] August 24, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2008, CSULB's engineering program received its highest ever ranking at number 38 Long Beach's programs in [[Accounting]], [[Business Administration]], [[Geography]], [[History]], [[Nursing]], and [[The arts|Art]] are also well respected in the industry{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}.

In addition, according to the [[National Science Foundation]], CSULB is the top campus in the nation amongst Master's level-granting universities for producing students who go on to earn [[Doctorate|doctoral]] degrees in [[Science|the Sciences]].&lt;ref name=sciences&gt;The Beach Review, Fall 2006: [http://www.csulb.edu/misc/beachreview/archives/2006/fall/feature6.htm Building the Foundation of Science]. ''Public Affairs and Publications.'' Retrieved August 10, 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2008, the music department was renamed the [[Bob Cole Conservatory of Music]] in honor of an endowment gift of $16.4 million from his estate. Cole, a Long Beach real estate investor, long-time music lover, and amateur pianist, died in 2004. The gift benefits the students of the conservatory in the form of scholarships and other awards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://signaltribunenewspaper.com/?p=1866 $16.4M donation will create Bob Cole Conservatory of Music at CSULB | Signal Tribune Newspaper&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Admission===
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;big&gt;'''Fall Freshman Statistics'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;applications&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/AS/stat_reports/2009-2010/apps_fall09.htm CSU new students applications and admissions, Fall 2009]. ''CSU Analytic Studies.'' 3/11/09&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;apps2&quot;&gt;http://www.daily49er.com/news/csulb-receives-highest-number-of-fall-applications-in-csu-1.2424116&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;applicants&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/AS/stat_reports/2010-2011/apps_fall10.shtml]. ''CSU Analytic Studies, Fall 2010.'' 7/9/11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;applicants&quot;&gt;[http://www.calstate.edu/AS/stat_reports/2007-2008/apps-fall07.htm]. ''CSU Analytic Studies, Fall 2007.''&lt;/ref&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
! &amp;nbsp; !! 2010 !! 2009 !! 2008 !! 2007 !! 2006
|-
! Applicants
| 47,709 || 45,786 || 48,561 || 45,220 || 42,850
|-
! Accepted
| 16,428 || 14,543 || 20,391 || 21,245 || 22,132
|-
! % Admitted
| 34.4 || 31.8 || 42.0 || 47.0 || 51.6
|-
! SAT Score
| 1031 ||1026 || 1020 || 1010 || 1014
|}
&lt;/div&gt;
For the Fall 2010 semester, CSULB received 79,715 applications for admission, by far the highest total in school history and continuing the increasing trend of recent years. The total also was the highest in the [[California State University|CSU]] system, as well as one of the highest among all universities in the nation. The campus also had the highest number of first time freshman and transfer applicants in the CSU.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cf.papubs.csulb.edu/news-events/story.cfm?hackid=1276 CSULB Receives Record Number of Undergraduate Applications] ''CSULB News and Events'' Retrieved 9/9/09&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the growing number of applications, the lack of state funding due to California's continuing budget crisis meant that CSULB could only offer admission to 25,142 (31.5%) of the applicants; that again marked the lowest percentage in school history. In turn 8,920 (35.5%) of those offered admission did in fact enroll, meaning the total application yield rate for the Fall 2010 semester was 11.6%.&lt;ref name=&quot;apps2&quot;/&gt;

The average high school [[Academic grading in the United States|GPA]] of incoming freshmen for Fall 2010 was 3.60, and the average [[SAT]] score for Fall 2010 was 1031/1600 (the writing section is not considered).&lt;ref name=&quot;csu long beach admission profile&quot;&gt;[http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;q=cache:JSRArn3G2ioJ:www.calstate.edu/sas/conferences/2010/campuses/LongBeach.ppt+cal+state+long+beach+fall+2010+freshman+admission&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;pid=bl&amp;srcid=ADGEESidPEQIrhqSFrrdEhHFDO3n--gdWZxJ6IkaLoptx69dNPln0tR93EhH01VcSiXN6ff62PlkxHvIUc9wyfXos2O2RaxVgwSYHEZhIzK_ovEY0L3rzb7bYGnuVWlbHawtYX8wfmMv&amp;sig=AHIEtbTH32G1Hvr63cm6Ok_Ahy0b5Z7qMQ] Retrieved 15/07/09&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;freshsat1&quot;&gt;[http://campus-sas.csulb.edu/IRpdfreports/satwebcomb.pdf First-Time Freshmen SAT scores] ''Institutional Research and Assessment.'' Retrieved 12/10/09&lt;/ref&gt; In recent years, the university has been forced to limit admit rates to about one-third of all applicants. CSULB had the lowest admit rate in the CSU system in Fall 2009, and the second lowest in Fall 2010 (behind [[San Diego State University|San Diego State]]'s 30%). CSULB's average SAT score was the 7th highest in the [[California State University#Profile_of_Enrolling_Freshmen_by_Campus|CSU]].

For the Fall 2011 semester, Initial reports indicate that CSULB received 70,536 applications, once again topping all other campuses in the CSU system. While the total number of applications dropped by over 9,000 from the previous year, the number of first-time freshman applicants grew by over 2,000 to 49,764. And even though the number of transfer applicants dropped to 20,039, it was still only the second time in school history that the number topped 20,000. In light of further anticipated state budget cuts, school officials declined to speculate on how many offers of admission would be made.

==Student life==
{| style=&quot;text-align:center; float: right; font-size:85%; margin-left: 2em;&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ ''2011 Demographics of student body''{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}
! !! Undergraduate
|-
! [[African American]]
| 4.2%
|-
! [[Asian American]]
| 21.0%
|-
! [[White American]]
| 26.3%
|-
! [[Hispanics in the United States|Hispanic American]]
| 29.7%
|-
! [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]]
| 0.6%
|-
! [[International]]
| 9.1%
|-
! Ethnicity unreported/unknown
| 9.2%
|}

CSULB hosts over 350 events annually, welcoming more than 150,000 patrons to its performance halls, conference centers, and exhibit venues.


===Greek Life - Sororities &amp; Fraternities===

National sororities on campus are governed by the [[Panhellenic Association]] and are members of the [[National Panhellenic Conference]]. Eleven general fraternities and two fraternity colonies are members of and governed by the [[Interfraternity Council]].

===Campus publications===
[[Image:Csulb-sign.jpg|left|thumb|300px]]

The university has two student publications: the ''Daily 49er''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.daily49er.com/&lt;/ref&gt; and the ''Union Weekly''&lt;ref&gt;http://www.lbunion.com/&lt;/ref&gt; (formerly ''The Long Beach Union Newspaper''). The first issue of the ''Daily 49er'', the campus newspaper, was published on November 11, 1949. It publishes Monday through Thursday during the fall and spring semesters, and once weekly during the summer sessions. It was one of the first college newspapers in the country to have an Internet edition, starting in August 1994.

The ''Union Weekly'', which is partially student-funded, and affiliated with ASI, publishes every Monday during fall and spring semesters. It began on April 22, 1977, when it was formed in response to the ''Daily 49er''. The ''Union Weekly'' focuses on being an alternative voice on campus and features a satirical section called &quot;The Grunion&quot; (not to be confused with the Long Beach paper the Grunion Gazette). At one time in the early 1980s, the ''Union'' was a daily newspaper, giving heavy competition to the ''Daily 49er''.

===KKJZ 88.1 FM===
The California State University Long Beach Foundation owns the [[KKJZ]] non-commercial broadcast license of 88.1 FM, a [[jazz]] and [[blues]] radio station. Global Jazz, Inc., an affiliate of [[Mount Wilson FM Broadcasters, Inc.]], programs and manages the radio station. [http://www.jazzandblues.org/index.aspx KJAZZ Official Website]

===KBeach internet radio===
[[Kbeach]] is a student-run Internet stream that has had a presence on campus in various forms since the 1970s. The independent and mainstream music channel is streamed over the Internet and piped into the University Student Union.

===Pow Wow===
Each March since 1970, the University has hosted the largest [[pow-wow]] in [[Southern California]]. This free two-day event, which attracts more than 6,000 persons each year, features [[Native Americans in the United States|Native American]] [[dancing]], [[art]]s, [[craft]] and native foods.

==Athletics==
{{main|Long Beach State 49ers}}

==Notable people==
[[Image:Spielberg99.jpg|thumb|right|[[Steven Spielberg]], BFA 2002, [[Academy Award]]-winning director]]
{{main|List of California State University, Long Beach people}}

Alumni have written and directed screenplays that have attracted Oscar-caliber talent.  [[David Twohy]] (BA&lt;ref name=&quot;Did you know by COTA&quot;/&gt;) co-wrote the screenplay for the [[Academy Award]] winning film ''[[The Fugitive (1993 film)|The Fugitive]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Fugitive (1993 film)|The Fugitive]]''  was nominated for seven Academy Awards, and won for Best Supporting Actor ([[Tommy Lee Jones]]).,&lt;/ref&gt; [[Linda Woolverton]] (BA 1974&lt;ref name=&quot;Did you know by COTA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cota.csulb.edu/index.cfm?fuseaction=about.didyouknow|title=Did you Know?|publisher=College of the Arts, California State University, Long Beach}}&lt;/ref&gt;) wrote the screenplays for the Academy Award winning,&lt;ref&gt;''[[The Lion King]]'' was nominated for four Academy Awards, and won for Best Original Score&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[[Beauty and the Beast (1991 film)|Beauty and the Beast]]'' was nominated for Best Picture and five other Academy Awards, and won for Best Original Score and Best Original Song&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Disney]] animated films ''[[Beauty and the Beast (1991 film)|Beauty and the Beast]]'' and ''[[The Lion King]]'', and the live-action 2010 film ''[[Alice in Wonderland (2010 film)|Alice in Wonderland]]'' directed by Oscar-nominated director [[Tim Burton]] and starring Oscar-nominated actor [[Johnny Depp]] .  [[J.F. Lawton]] (BA&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=|title=JAN 10, 2008 - ALUMNUS DONATES CAMERA TO FEA|publisher=California State University, Long Beach - Film &amp; Electronic Arts Department|date=2008-01-10}}&lt;/ref&gt;) wrote the screenplay to ''[[Pretty Woman]]'', starring the Oscar-winning actress [[Julia Roberts]].  [[Mark Steven Johnson]] (BA 1989&lt;ref name=&quot;Did you know by COTA&quot;/&gt;) has co-written and directed  the films ''[[Daredevil (film)|Daredevil]]'', starring Oscar-winning actor [[Ben Affleck]], and ''[[Ghost Rider (film)|Ghost Rider]]'', starring Oscar-winning actor [[Nicolas Cage]].
[[Image:Misty may-treanor.jpg|thumb|left|[[Misty May-Treanor]], BA 2002, multiple gold-medal winning [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] [[beach volleyball]] player]]

Former students have won at least five [[Academy Awards]]. [[Steven Spielberg]] (Class of 1969, BFA 2002&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.calstate.edu/newsline/Archive/01-02/020514-LB.shtml|title=teven Spielberg To Graduate from California State University, Long Beach With Bachelor's Degree in Film and Electronic Arts|date=2002-05-14|publisher=California State University, Long Beach|author=Public Affairs Office/Campus News, California State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;) won two Oscars for Best Directing for ''[[Schindler's List]]'' and ''[[Saving Private Ryan]]''  and has directed a number of other successful movies such as ''[[Jaws (film)|Jaws]]'', ''[[E.T. the Extra-Terrestrial]]'', and ''[[Jurassic Park (film)|Jurassic Park]]''.  Former industrial design major [[John Dykstra]], who has been nominated five times for Academy Awards,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csulb.edu/misc/beachreview/archives/2005/fall/intouch2.htm|publisher=California State University, Long Beach, in the alumni magazine ''The Beach Review''|title=In Touch| date=Fall 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; won two Oscars for his special effects work on the [[George Lucas]] film ''[[Star Wars Episode IV: A New Hope|Star Wars]]'' and the [[Sam Raimi]] film ''[[Spider-Man 2]]''.  Deborah L. Scott (BA&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Her art does go on, and it fits 'Titanic' costume designer matched clothing with era|publisher=[[New York Daily News]]|author=Lewis Beale|date=1998-03-17|url=http://www.nydailynews.com/archives/entertainment/1998/03/17/1998-03-17_her_art_does_go_on__and_it_f.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;)  won&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://movies.tvguide.com/titanic/cast/132077|publisher=[[TV Guide]]|title=Titanic: Cast and Details}}&lt;/ref&gt; an Oscar for costume design for the [[James Cameron]] film ''[[Titanic (1997 film)|Titanic]]''.
[[Image:Carpenters - Nixon - Office.png|thumb|right|Former students [[Karen Carpenter]] and [[Richard Carpenter (musician)|Richard Carpenter]] (Honorary Doctorate, 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardCarpenterHDoc2000&quot;/&gt;) of ''[[The Carpenters]]'']]

[[Emmy Award]]-nominated director [[Chris Carter (screenwriter)|Chris Carter]] (BA 1979) created the series ''[[The X Files]]'', which garnered several [[List of awards and nominations received by The X-Files|awards]] during its nine seasons on television. Former student [[Steve Martin]], whose philosophy classes at the university inspired him to become a professional comedian,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;He majored in philosophy at California State University, Long Beach (which Steven Spielberg would attend a few years later). ... 'I was romanticized by philosophy. I thought it was the highest thing you could study. At one point I wanted to teach it.' And then along came Ludwig Wittgenstein, the Austrian philosopher whose Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus redefined and reduced the scope of the discipline. Says Martin: 'As I studied the history of philosophy, the quest for ultimate truth became less important to me, and by the time I got to Wittgenstein it seemed pointless. Then I realized that in the arts you don't have to discover meaning, you create it. There are no rules, no true and false, no right and wrong. Anyway, these were the musings of a 21-year-old kid.'&quot;{{cite web|url=http://www.time.com/time/printout/0,8816,965275,00.html|publisher=[[Time magazine]]|title=Sensational Steve Martin|date=1987-08-24|author=}}&lt;/ref&gt; is an [[Emmy Award]] winner and a [[Disney Legend]].

Alumni and former students have also participated in the world of sports. [[Jason Giambi]], [[Evan Longoria]],  [[Troy Tulowitzki]], [[Harold Reynolds]], [[Jered Weaver]] and [[Steve Trachsel]] have all been selected to play in the [[Major League Baseball All-Star Game|Major League Baseball All Stars]] games. Golfer [[Mark O'Meara]] (BA 1980)  won the [[Masters Tournament]] and [[The Open Championship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;50th Anniversary Celebration&quot;/&gt;   [[Craig Hodges]] is a two-time [[NBA Finals|NBA Champion]], [[Terrell Davis]] is a two-time [[Super Bowl]] champion and [[Billy Parks]] played five seasons in the [[NFL]]. [[Diving|Diver]] [[Pat McCormick (diver)|Pat McCormick]]&lt;ref name=&quot;50th Anniversary Celebration&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csulb.edu/programs/50th/alumni.html|title=50th Anniversary Celebration - California State University, Long Beach - Distinguished Alumni|year=1999}}&lt;/ref&gt; won four gold medals in two consecutive Olympics ([[1952 Summer Olympics|Helsinki]] and [[1956 Summer Olympics|Melbourne]]), and [[Misty May-Treanor]] (BS 2002) won two gold medals in women's [[beach volleyball]] in two other consecutive Olympics ([[2004 Summer Olympics|Athens]] and [[2008 Summer Olympics|Beijing]] ).

Former students [[Karen Carpenter]] and [[Richard Carpenter (musician)|Richard Carpenter]] (Class of 1972, Honorary Doctorate 2000&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardCarpenterHDoc2000&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.calstate.edu/newsline/Archive/99-00/000519-LB.shtml|title=Richard Carpenter, James Gray Receive Honorary Doctorate Degrees At California State University, Long Beach Commencement Ceremonies|date=2000-05-19|publisher=California State University, Long Beach|author=Public Affairs Offices/Campus News, California State University}}&lt;/ref&gt;) of  ''[[The Carpenters]]''  are the nameakes of the [[Carpenter Performing Arts Center]], a  1,065-seat performance hall on the campus of the university&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.csulb.edu/divisions/students/uosr/Campus_Tours/Hot_Spots_@_The_Beach/part.htm|title=Hot Spots @ The Beach - Carpenter Performing Arts Center|author=California State University, Long Beach|publisher=California State University, Long Beach}}&lt;/ref&gt; that also houses an exhibit on the Carpenters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carpenterarts.org/carpenterexhibit.html|title=About - Richard &amp; Karen Carpenter Exhibit|author=Carpenter Performing Arts Center|publisher=Carpenter Performing Arts Center}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Richard Carpenter's college  instructor and choir director [[Frank Pooler]] inspired him in choral arrangement,&lt;ref name=&quot;Carpenters_35th&quot;/&gt; and both Karen and Richard participated in Pooler's choir.  Pooler also introduced Richard  to fellow undergraduate and future song-writing collaborator [[John Bettis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Carpenters_35th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.richardandkarencarpenter.com/Album_gold_35th_anniversary.htm|title=Carpenters Gold - 35th Anniversary - Album Notes|publisher=The Carpenters (official website) and [[A &amp; M Records]]|author=[[Richard Carpenter (musician)|Richard Carpenter]]|date=2003-10 (written), 2004-02-10 (published)}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another undergraduate, Wesley Jacobs,&lt;ref name=&quot;Carpenters_35th&quot;/&gt; would join the Carpenters as a musical instrumentalist.   The Carpenters sold over 100 million records,&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardCarpenterHDoc2000&quot;/&gt; won three [[Grammy Awards]]&lt;ref name=&quot;RichardCarpenterHDoc2000&quot;/&gt; out of eighteen nominations, and created numerous [[RIAA certification|gold]] and [[RIAA certification|platinum]] [[The Carpenters discography|albums]].   One of Pooler's personal poems formed the basis for ''[[Merry Christmas Darling]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=[[Richard Carpenter (musician)|Richard Carpenter]]|title=Marry Christmas Darling - Song Notes|publisher=The Carpenters (official website) and [[Broadcast Music Incorporated]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; which went to #1  on the [[Billboard charts|''Billboard'' charts]] for three years.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.richardandkarencarpenter.com/Album_ChristmasCollection.htm|publisher=The Carpenters (official site) and [[A &amp; M Records]]|author=Paul Grein|title=Carpenters Christmas Collection|date=2008-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bettis, who later would win an [[Emmy Award]] himself,&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonAnkeny&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://new.music.yahoo.com/john-bettis/biography/|title=John Bettis|author=Jason Ankeny|publisher=[[All Music Guide]] via [[Yahoo Music]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; also successfully collaborated on songs with other artists, such as  ''[[Human Nature (Michael Jackson song)|Human Nature]]'' performed by [[Michael Jackson]],&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonAnkeny&quot;/&gt;  ''[[Crazy for You (song)|Crazy for You]]'' performed by [[Madonna (entertainer)|Madonna]],&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonAnkeny&quot;/&gt; and ''[[One Moment in Time]]'' performed by [[Whitney Houston]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JasonAnkeny&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
{{Portal box|Los Angeles|University}}
{{Commons category}}
*[http://www.csulb.edu/ Official website]

{{Coord|33.783022|-118.112858|region:US-CA_type:edu|display=title}}

&lt;br&gt;
{{California_State University}}
{{Big_West Conference}}
{{Colleges and universities in Los Angeles County}}
{{National Register of Historic Places}}

[[Category:Big West Conference]]
[[Category:California State University, Long Beach| ]]
[[Category:California State University|Long Beach]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1949]]
[[Category:Education in Long Beach, California]]
[[Category:Schools on the National Register of Historic Places in California]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Los Angeles County, California]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Schools accredited by the Western Association of Schools and Colleges]]

[[de:California State University, Long Beach]]
[[es:Universidad Estatal de California, Long Beach]]
[[fa:دانشگاه ایالتی کالیفرنیا، لانگ بیچ]]
[[fr:Université d'État de Californie à Long Beach]]
[[id:Universitas Negeri California, Long Beach]]
[[simple:California State University Long Beach]]
[[sh:California State University, Long Beach]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
