<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="38398" ns="0" title="Stargate SG-1"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|SG1}} 
{{for|the videogame|Stargate SG-1: The Alliance}}
{{Infobox television
 |show_name = Stargate SG-1
 |image = [[File:Stargate SG-1 cast minus Jonas Quinn.jpg|260px]]
 |caption = Main Cast (minus Corin Nemec)
 |genre = [[military science fiction]], [[adventure science fiction]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.allmovie.com/work/stargate-132284|work=Allmovie|accessdate=January 4, 2010|title=Stargate: Overview|author=Brenner, Paul}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 |company = [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]]
 |runtime = 43 minutes
 |theme_music_composer = [[Joel Goldsmith]]
 |creator = {{Unbulleted list| [[Brad Wright]] | [[Jonathan Glassner]] }}
 |executive_producer = {{Unbulleted list| [[Jonathan Glassner]] (1–3) | [[Brad Wright]] (1–10) | [[Robert C. Cooper]] (5–10) | [[Joseph Mallozzi]] (8–10) | [[Paul Mullie]] (8–10) | [[Richard Dean Anderson]] (1–8) | [[Michael Greenburg]] (1–8) }}
 |starring = {{Unbulleted list| [[Richard Dean Anderson]] | [[Michael Shanks]] | [[Amanda Tapping]] | [[Christopher Judge]] | [[Don S. Davis]] | [[Corin Nemec]] | [[Ben Browder]] | [[Beau Bridges]] | [[Claudia Black]] }}
 |country = {{Unbulleted list| Canada | United States }}
 |language = English
 |network = {{Unbulleted list| [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] (seasons 1–5) | [[Syfy|Sci-Fi Channel]] (seasons 6–10) }}
 |preceded_by = ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' ''(film)''
 |followed_by = ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' &lt;!-- Continuum does not follow SG-1; it follows after Ark of Truth. Please do not add --&gt;
 |related = {{Unbulleted list| ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' | ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' }}
 |first_aired = {{Start date|1997|7|27}}
 |last_aired = {{End date|2007|3|13}}
 |status  = Ended
 |num_seasons = 10
 |num_episodes = 214 + 2 [[List of Stargate SG-1 episodes#Movies|DVD films]]
 |list_episodes = List of Stargate SG-1 episodes
 |website = http://stargate.mgm.com/view/series/1/
}}
&lt;!--Note to editors: Please do not change &quot;is&quot; to &quot;was&quot;. Creative works &quot;are&quot;, Wikipedia guidelines for fiction refer to creative works in the present tense, even after a show ends its run (see also [[WP:TENSE]]). --&gt;
'''''Stargate SG-1''''' (often abbreviated as '''''SG-1''''') is a [[Canadian science fiction television|Canadian]]-[[U.S. television science fiction|American]] [[Adventure film|adventure]] and [[military science fiction]] [[television series]] and part of [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer]]'s [[Stargate|''Stargate'' franchise]]. The show, created by [[Brad Wright]] and [[Jonathan Glassner]], is based on the 1994 feature film ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' by [[Dean Devlin]] and [[Roland Emmerich]]. The television series was filmed in and around the city of [[Vancouver]], [[Canada]]. In  the United States, [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] broadcast the first five seasons, from 1997 to 2002, and then the series moved to the [[Syfy|Sci Fi Channel]] for its last five seasons, from 2002 to 2007. The final episode premiered on [[Sky1]] in the United Kingdom on March 13, 2007, three months before its United States premiere. With ten seasons and 214 episodes, ''Stargate SG-1'' surpassed ''[[The X-Files]]'' in 2007 as the longest-running North American science fiction series on television, before being surpassed by ''[[Smallville]]'' in 2011 with 218 episodes in ten seasons.

The story of ''Stargate SG-1'' begins about a year after the events of the feature film, when the [[Federal government of the United States|United States government]] learns that a network of ancient alien devices called [[Stargate (device)|Stargates]] connects a vast multitude of planets within our Milky Way galaxy, facilitating near-instantaneous interstellar travel.  Later episodes reveal that this network is capable of spanning not just planets within the Milky Way, but with sufficient power, can provide intergalactic travel as well.  ''Stargate SG-1'' chronicles the adventures of the elite [[special forces|special force]] [[United States Air Force|Air Force]] squad, SG-1, the flagship team of over two dozen teams from Earth who explore the galaxy and defend Earth against alien threats such as the [[Goa'uld]], [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]], and later the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]. The composition of the SG-1 team is stable in the show's first five seasons but changes several times in the remaining seasons. The series expands upon many Ancient Earth mythologies such as [[Ancient Egyptian religion|Egyptian mythology]], [[Norse mythology]], and [[Arthurian legend]]. The 2008 [[direct-to-DVD]] films ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' and ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' continue the adventures of SG-1.

The series was a ratings success for [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] and the Sci Fi Channel, and was particularly popular in Europe and Australia. Although it received little critical response, ''Stargate SG-1'' was honored with numerous awards and award nominations in its ten-season run. It also spawned the animated television series ''[[Stargate Infinity]]'' in 2002, the live-action spin-off TV series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' in 2004, and the live-action TV series ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' in 2009 which ended in the Spring of 2011. Merchandise for ''Stargate SG-1'' includes games and toys, print media, and an original audio series.

==Series overview==
{{Main|List of Stargate SG-1 episodes|Mythology of Stargate|Stargate Program}}
''Stargate SG-1'' resumes the plot of the [[Stargate (film)|original feature film]] and follows the present-day adventures of SG-1, a military team from Earth. SG-1 and two dozen other SG teams venture to distant planets using a fictional alien portal known as a [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]], which in the series is housed in a top-secret [[United States Air Force]] military base known as [[Stargate Command]] (SGC) underneath [[Cheyenne Mountain]] in [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]]. In the first eight seasons, the mission of the SG teams is to explore the galaxy and search for alien technology and allies to defend Earth against the [[Goa'uld]], a snake-like parasitic alien race that takes humans as unwilling hosts. As explained in the series' backstory, the Goa'uld transported human slaves from [[Earth]] to other habitable planets across the galaxy thousands of years ago and now pose as gods of Ancient Earth mythologies, particularly Egyptian mythology. SG-1 eventually learns that highly evolved human-like beings, known as the [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancients]], had originally built the Stargate network millions of years earlier, before they used their extraordinary powers to [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascend to a higher plane of existence]], after which they pledged to not interfere in the lives of other species. The [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]], who belong to the same race of ascended beings as the Ancients but who use their powers to subjugate other species, forcing them to worship the Ori and to believe a doctrine of religious fundamentalism, assume the role of the main antagonists in seasons 9 and 10.

===Goa'uld arc===
[[File:NORADNorth-Portal.jpg|thumb|The [[Cheyenne Mountain complex]] in Colorado, United States is home to Earth's fictional Stargate Command in the ''Stargate'' universe.]]{{Main|Goa'uld}}
The pilot episode, set two years after the events of the original feature film, introduces the Goa'uld [[System Lord]] and main villain [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] ([[Peter Williams (actor)|Peter Williams]]) as he attacks Earth's mothballed SGC military base through the Stargate and kidnaps a soldier. The SGC is brought back into action when the Stargate is revealed to be part of an interplanetary network connecting countless planets. SG teams are created to help defend Earth against the Goa'uld, who have interstellar pyramid warships and vast armies of [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] (hereditary slaves and human incubators to the Goa'uld) at their disposal. Earth's flagship team SG-1, which includes Apophis's defected First Prime (lead Jaffa soldier) [[Teal'c]], initiates several alliances with other cultures in the galaxy, such as the Goa'uld-like but truly symbiotic [[Tok'ra]], the advanced human [[Tollan (Stargate)|Tollan]], the pacifist [[Nox (Stargate)|Nox]], the benevolent [[Roswell UFO Incident|Roswell]]-alien [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]], and remnants of the powerful Ancients. Another alien threat arises in the season 3 finale in the form of sentient machines called [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]]. Meanwhile, rogue agents of a shadowy intelligence agency on Earth, the [[NID (Stargate)|NID]], repeatedly attempt to take control of the Stargate and other alien technology. Despite Apophis's death in the beginning of season 5, the [[Goa'uld Empire]] remains a major foe in ''Stargate SG-1'' until the end of season 8. The only influential Goa'uld in the last two seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'' is the System Lord [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] ([[Cliff Simon]]), who is defeated in the direct-to-DVD film ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]''.

===Anubis arc===
{{Main|Anubis (Stargate)}}
After Apophis's defeat in the season 5 premiere, the half-Ascended Goa'uld System Lord [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]] ([[David Palffy]]) becomes the main villain. He possesses much knowledge of the Ancients and their technology. While Earth builds its first interstellar spaceship (the ''[[Prometheus (Stargate)|Prometheus]]'') in seasons 6 and 7, Anubis creates an army of almost invincible [[Kull Warrior]]s and wipes out many of his fellow System Lords. In the season 7 finale, SG-1 discovers a powerful weapon in an Ancient outpost in Antarctica that annihilates Anubis's entire fleet and also sets the stage for the spin-off series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. Ba'al subsumes much of Anubis's power in season 8, while Anubis secretly regains control of his forces. Human-form Replicators begin to conquer the System Lords, but SG-1 finds and adjusts an Ancient weapon to destroy all Replicators throughout the galaxy. The end of season 8 reveals the benevolent Ascended Being [[Oma Desala]] ([[Mel Harris]]) to be responsible for Anubis's original ascension. When she engages Anubis in an eternal stalemated battle on the Ascended plane to prevent his acting on the mortal plane, the Replicators and most System Lords have already been annihilated, and the Jaffa win their freedom from Goa'uld rule.

===Ori arc===
{{Main|Ori (Stargate)}}
The original SG-1 team disbands after the events of season 8, but slowly reunites under new team leader [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Col. Cameron Mitchell]] after the SGC inadvertently draws the attention of the Ancient-like Ori from another galaxy to the existence of sentient life in the Milky Way. While the Ori send enhanced human beings named [[Prior (Stargate)|Priors]] to the Milky Way to spread a religion that will augment the Ori's power, Ba'al and some minor Goa'uld infiltrate Earth through the [[Trust (Stargate)|Trust]] (a coalition of rogue NID operatives) to rebuild their power. At the end of season 9, the Ori begin an evangelistic crusade with their warships and effortlessly wipe out the combined fleet of Earth and its allies. The leader of the Ori, [[Adria (Stargate)|Adria]] ([[Morena Baccarin]]), is introduced in the premiere of season 10. SG-1 searches for the [[Sangraal (Stargate)|Sangraal]], an Ancient weapon that might defeat the Ori, while Ba'al and his clones attempt to find the weapon for their own purposes. With the help of the powerful Ancient [[Merlin (Stargate)|Merlin]] ([[Matthew Walker (Canadian actor)|Matthew Walker]]), SG-1 finds the construction plans of the Sangraal and sends a working version to the Ori galaxy. Shortly thereafter, Adria ascends. The direct-to-DVD film ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'' ends the Ori arc.

==Cast==
{{Main|List of Stargate SG-1 characters}}
* [[Richard Dean Anderson]] as [[Jack O'Neill|Jonathan &quot;Jack&quot; O'Neill]] (seasons 1–8 main, seasons 9–10 recurring) &amp;nbsp;– A [[United States Air Force]] Colonel and [[Special forces|special operations]] veteran who led the original mission through the Stargate in ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' (where he was played by [[Kurt Russell]]). He is coaxed out of retirement in the pilot episode and serves as the leader of the SG-1 team in the first seven seasons. He takes charge of Stargate Command (SGC) after his promotion to Brigadier General at the beginning of season 8. The series repeatedly alludes to romantic feelings between O'Neill and his second-in-command, Carter, but the relationship is never shown as consummated outside of alternate reality scenarios. O'Neill is reassigned to Washington, D.C. before season 9 and receives a promotion to Major General. He appears in a recurring role in seasons 9 and 10 of ''Stargate SG-1'', as well as in ''Stargate: Continuum'' and in seasons 1 and 3 of ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. O'Neill appears as a Lieutenant General in multiple episodes of ''[[Stargate Universe]]''.
* [[Michael Shanks]] as [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] (seasons 1–5 and 7–10 main, season 6 recurring) &amp;nbsp;– A brilliant [[Egyptologist]] whose far-fetched theories about Egyptian pyramids having been built by aliens led to his participation in the original Stargate mission in the feature film (where he was played by [[James Spader]]). He joins the SG-1 team to facilitate his search for his wife, who was kidnapped by Apophis in the pilot episode, but his naïveté and curiosity regularly create obstacles for the team.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_40/&gt; He gradually evolves from being an archaeologist and translator into the moral conscience for the team,&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; and remains part of SG-1 until he [[ascension (Stargate)|ascends to a higher plane of existence]] at the end of season 5. Following his forceful de-ascension at the beginning of season 7, he rejoins SG-1 for the remainder of the series. The last three seasons show his flirty yet antagonistic relationship with Vala Mal Doran.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_40&gt;{{Cite journal|last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Michael Shanks – Curious Mind |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 64 |pages=40–42 |date=July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Daniel also appears in both direct-to-DVD films, in seasons 1 and 5 of ''Stargate Atlantis'', and in three ''Stargate Universe'' episodes.
* [[Amanda Tapping]] as [[Samantha Carter|Samantha &quot;Sam&quot; Carter]] (seasons 1–10 main) &amp;nbsp;– A brilliant young astrophysicist&lt;ref name=booker_181/&gt; and United States Air Force Captain who joins SG-1 under the command of Col. O'Neill in the pilot episode. Following her promotion to Major in season 3, she is promoted to Lieutenant Colonel early in season 8 and assumes command of SG-1. The series repeatedly alludes to romantic feelings between Carter and O'Neill, but the relationship is never shown as consummated outside of alternate reality scenarios. Carter assists Lt. Col. Cameron Mitchell in seasons 9 and 10. After her appearance in ''Stargate: The Ark of Truth'', she is promoted to Colonel and becomes the new commander of the Atlantis expedition in season 4 of ''Stargate Atlantis'', before joining SG-1 again for ''Stargate: Continuum''. Carter appears in a recurring role in all seasons of ''Stargate Atlantis'' (and as a regular in Season 4) and in the first episode of ''Stargate: Universe''.
* [[Christopher Judge]] as [[Teal'c]] (seasons 1–10 main) &amp;nbsp;– A quiet and strong [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] alien who defects from his position as the First Prime of the [[Goa'uld]] [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]]. He joins SG-1 after the pilot episode in hopes of leading his race to freedom. Despite succeeding in this goal at the end of season 8, he remains a member of SG-1 until the end of the series. He also appears in both direct-to-DVD films and in season 4 of ''Stargate Atlantis'' as the commander of the starship George Hammond.
* [[Don S. Davis]] as [[George Hammond (Stargate)|George Hammond]] (seasons 1–7 main, seasons 8–10 recurring) &amp;nbsp;– A United States Air Force Major General (later Lieutenant General) who commands Stargate Command in the first seven seasons. Besides recurring in seasons 8 through 10 of ''Stargate SG-1'', he appears in season 1 of ''Stargate Atlantis''. Davis died from a heart attack in June 2008, making his appearance in ''Stargate: Continuum'' his last.&lt;ref name=gw_death&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=David |url=http://gateworld.net/news/2008/06/don_s._davis_1942-2008.shtml |title=Don S. Davis: 1942-2008 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=June 30, 2008 |accessdate=2008-11-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Corin Nemec]] as [[Jonas Quinn]] (season 6 main, seasons 5 and 7 recurring) &amp;nbsp;– A humanoid alien and scientist from the country of Kelowna on the planet Langara. Daniel sacrifices his life (leading to his ascension) at the end of season 5 in an attempt to save Kelowna, but the following gleeful reaction of the Kelownan leaders causes Jonas to turn his back on Langara. Jonas is a fast learner and fills Daniel's empty spot on SG-1 in season 6. Following Daniel's return, Jonas returns to his planet and remains a recurring character in season 7.
* [[Ben Browder]] as [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Cameron &quot;Cam&quot; Mitchell]] (seasons 9–10 main) &amp;nbsp;– A United States Air Force Lieutenant Colonel who is assigned as the new commanding officer of SG-1 at the beginning of season 9. He struggles to reunite its former members under his command and commands SG-1 (with Lt. Col. Carter's assistance) until the end of season 10. He is promoted to Colonel between his appearances in ''Stargate: The Ark of Truth'' and ''Stargate: Continuum''.
* [[Beau Bridges]] as [[Hank Landry (Stargate)|Henry &quot;Hank&quot; Landry]] (seasons 9–10 main) &amp;nbsp;– A United States Air Force Major General and the commander of Stargate Command in seasons 9 and 10. He is the estranged father of the SGC's medical officer [[Carolyn Lam]] and appears in both direct-to-DVD films and in seasons 2 and 3 of ''Stargate Atlantis''.
* [[Claudia Black]] as [[Vala Mal Doran]] (season 10 main, seasons 8–9 recurring) &amp;nbsp;– A con artist from an unnamed planet and a former human host to the Goa'uld [[Qetesh (Stargate)|Qetesh]]. Her first appearance in season 8's &quot;[[Prometheus Unbound (Stargate SG-1)|Prometheus Unbound]]&quot; is the beginning of her flirty yet antagonistic relationship with Daniel.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_40/&gt; In her recurring role in season 9, she and Daniel unintentionally set off the new [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] threat. She joins SG-1 after giving birth to the new leader of the Ori at the beginning of season 10, and appears in both direct-to-DVD films.

==Production==
{{See also|List of Stargate SG-1 episodes}}

===Conception===
[[File:Brad Wright Comic Con 2008.jpg|thumb|Brad Wright created ''Stargate SG-1'' with Jonathan Glassner.]]
{{main|Children of the Gods|Stargate SG-1 (season 1)}}
[[Brad Wright]] and [[Jonathan Glassner]] had worked together on the [[MGM]] television series ''[[The Outer Limits (1995 TV series)|The Outer Limits]]'' since 1995. Upon hearing of MGM's plan to create a television spin-off series of the feature film ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'', Wright and Glassner independently and unbeknownst to each other approached MGM and proposed their concept for the television series. MGM president John Symes greenlit the project on the condition that Wright and Glassner work together as executive producers of the new show.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Brad Wright|Wright, Brad]]; [[Jonathan Glassner|Glassner, Jonathan]]; [[Michael Greenburg|Greenburg, Michael]]; [[Richard Dean Anderson|Anderson, Richard Dean]]; [[Michael Shanks|Shanks, Michael]] |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Timeline To The Future – Part 1: Legacy Of The Gate | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The show was named ''Stargate SG-1'' after Wright flightily agreed to Symes's pitch question of whether the team should be called &quot;SG-1&quot;. MGM released posters titled ''Stargate SG-1'' within the next week without the knowledge of Wright or Glassner.&lt;ref name=dvdprofilewright&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Brad Wright|Wright, Brad]] |date=2006 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 9 – Profile On: Brad Wright | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

John Symes approached [[Michael Greenburg]] and [[Richard Dean Anderson]] of ''[[MacGyver]]'' fame.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; Anderson agreed to become involved with the project if his character [[Jack O'Neill]] was allowed significantly more comedic leeway than [[Kurt Russell]]'s character in the feature film. He also requested ''Stargate SG-1'' to be more of an ensemble show, so that he would not be carrying the plot alone as on ''MacGyver''.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_4&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Richard Dean Anderson – Mr Anderson – Colonel O'Neill |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 46 |pages=4–9 |month=July |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; The American subscription channel [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] made a two-season commitment for 44 episodes in 1996.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; Principal photography began in Vancouver in February 1997.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt;

===Casting and cast changes===
After Anderson accepted the part, Brad Wright and Jonathan Glassner reviewed several thousand taped auditions and invited approximately 25 promising actors to screen tests in Los Angeles.&lt;ref name=dvdproducingstargate&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Brad Wright|Wright, Brad]] and [[Jonathan Glassner|Glassner, Jonathan]] |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Producing Stargate | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Michael Shanks, Amanda Tapping and Christopher Judge are said to have gravitated towards each other during the casting process before they knew that they would ultimately be cast.&lt;ref name=dvdprofiledaniel&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Michael Shanks|Shanks, Michael]] |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Profile On Daniel Jackson | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers found Judge the easiest to cast due to his muscular presence.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; Shanks was cast because he did &quot;the perfect imitation of James Spader&quot;, according to Wright.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; The producers knew Don S. Davis from his work as a stand-in and stunt-double for [[Dana Elcar]] in ''MacGyver'' and approached him to read for the role of George Hammond.&lt;ref name=dvdprofilehammond&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Don S. Davis|Davis, Don. S]] |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Profile On General Hammond | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=gw_intimate1&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/intimate_portrait_part_1_o.shtml |title=Intimate Portrait – GateWorld talks with Don S. Davis (Part 1) |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=September |year=2006 |accessdate=2008-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Showtime's announcement to not renew ''Stargate SG-1'' after season 5 coincided with Michael Shanks's decision to leave the show due to concerns of being under-utilized,&lt;ref name=storm_61&gt;Storm 2005, pp. 61–63.&lt;/ref&gt; but the [[Syfy|Sci Fi Channel]] decided to continue the show and fill the void with a new character. Casting agents met Corin Nemec at the courtyard of MGM's [[Santa Monica]] offices by chance and offered him the role of Jonas Quinn.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_22&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Corin Nemec – Jonas Quinn |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 46 |pages=22–26 |month=July |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although Nemec's early appearances, beginning with the penultimate episode of season 5 &quot;[[Meridian (Stargate SG-1)|Meridian]]&quot;, evoked strong distrust by loyal fans,&lt;ref name=storm_61/&gt; Nemec was open to continue playing the character after season 6 or in a feature film or a spin-off series.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_22 /&gt; However, the producers reached a new contract with Michael Shanks to return full time in season 7, leaving Nemec with a recurring role.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/art-main.html?2002-11/15/13.00.sfc |title=Stargate Cast Returning |publisher=scifi.com |date=November 15, 2002 |accessdate=2008-11-01|archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20060325043143/http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/art-main.html?2002-11/15/13.00.sfc|archivedate=March 25, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Don S. Davis decided to leave ''Stargate SG-1'' after season 7 for health reasons&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/intimate_portrait_part_2_o.shtml |title=Intimate Portrait – GateWorld talks with Don S. Davis (Part 2) |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=September |year=2006 |accessdate=2008-12-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; but appeared in a recurring capacity until his death on June 29, 2008.

Due to prior engagements, [[Claudia Black]] of ''[[Farscape]]'' fame could not accept the offers to guest-star on ''Stargate SG-1'' until the season 8 episode &quot;[[Prometheus Unbound (Stargate SG-1)|Prometheus Unbound]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=sg_mag_april07&gt;{{Cite journal |title=Vala Unveiled |journal=Official Stargate Magazine |pages=20–21 |date=April 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers liked the on-screen chemistry between Black's Vala Mal Doran and Shanks's Daniel so much that they re-introduced her in a six-episode story arc to cover for the maternity leave of Amanda Tapping at the beginning of season 9.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudolph 41&quot;&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Rudolph |first=Illeane |title=Black Is Back |journal=[[TV Guide]] |issue=February 27 – March 5, 2006 |pages=41 |date=February 27, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Richard Dean Anderson left the show to spend more time with his daughter (his schedule had been reduced incrementally since season 6).&lt;ref&gt;Gibson 2003, p. 66, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; The role of the leading man was filled with [[Ben Browder]] (also of ''Farscape'' fame), who had met with the ''Stargate'' producers as soon as the introduction of new main characters for season 9 was discussed.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_12&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Ben Browder – Work in progress |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 64 |pages=12–16 |date=July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers had met him during sci-fi conventions and had previously discussed casting him in other ''Stargate'' roles.&lt;ref name=making_901&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url=http://www.gateworld.net/sg1/s9/making/901.shtml |title=In the Making – Avalon Part 1 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date = July 2005|accessdate=2009-03-07}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers approached [[Emmy Award]]-winning actor Beau Bridges directly to play the role of Hank Landry.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_50&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven |title=Beau Bridges – Helping Bridge the Gap |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 64 |pages=50–52 |date=July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt; Claudia Black's guest appearances were so popular with the cast, crew and audience&lt;ref name=&quot;Rudolph 41&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=gw_i_claudia&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/i_claudia.shtml |title=I, Claudia – GateWorld talks with Claudia Black |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=July | year=2006 |accessdate=2008-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; that the actress returned for the last two season 9 episodes (with her pregnancy worked into the plot), and she joined the cast full time in season 10.

===Crew===
[[File:Robertcooper.jpg|thumb|Robert C. Cooper became ''SG-1''{{'}}s show runner in season 7.]]
Most producers, crew members and guest actors behind ''Stargate SG-1'' were Canadian.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; Creators Brad Wright and Jonathan Glassner were executive producers and show runners of ''Stargate SG-1'' in the first three seasons,&lt;!--based on the closing credits--&gt; having the final say (besides MGM and the network) on stories, designs, effects, casting, editing, and episode budgets.&lt;ref name=gw_brad/&gt; After Glassner's departure, Wright ran ''Stargate SG-1'' alone for three seasons.&lt;!--based on the closing credits--&gt; Executive producer [[Robert C. Cooper]] took over as show-runner in season 7 when Brad Wright took time off to develop the [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2004/08/willsg-1gatetoseasonnine.shtml |title=Will SG-1 gate to Season Nine? |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=August 8, 2004 |accessdate=2009-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cooper and Wright remained show-runners of their respective shows until the end of ''SG-1''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2005/02/new_seasons_begin_filming_in_van.shtml |title=New seasons begin filming in Vancouver |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=February 28, 2005 |accessdate=2009-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Also serving as executive and co-executive producers were Michael Greenburg and Richard Dean Anderson (seasons 1–8), N. John Smith (seasons 4–10), and the writer team [[Joseph Mallozzi]] &amp; [[Paul Mullie]] (seasons 7–10).

Although ''Stargate SG-1'' employed freelance writers, most of the 214 ''Stargate SG-1'' episodes were written by Brad Wright (seasons 1–10), Jonathan Glassner (seasons 1–3), [[Katharyn Powers]] (seasons 1–6), Robert C. Cooper (seasons 1–10), [[Peter DeLuise]] (seasons 4–8), Joseph Mallozzi &amp; Paul Mullie (seasons 4–10), [[Damian Kindler]] (seasons 6–10), and [[Alan McCullough]] (seasons 9–10). [[Martin Wood]] and Peter DeLuise directed the most episodes, with 46 episodes (seasons 1–10) and 57 episodes (seasons 2–10), respectively. Wood and DeLuise regularly made cameo appearances in their episodes and notably played the [[show-within-a-show]] directors in the cameo-heavy milestone episodes &quot;[[Wormhole X-Treme!]]&quot; and &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot;. [[Andy Mikita]] had been an assistant director since the pilot episode and directed 29 episodes from season 3 through 10. ''SG-1'' director of photography [[Peter Woeste]] and camera operator [[William Waring]] directed 13 episodes each. Most staff writers and staff directors held producer positions. Several cast members contributed story ideas and directed ''SG-1'' episodes.

===Filming===
[[File:Bridge Studios.jpg|thumb|''Stargate SG-1'' was filmed at The Bridge Studios in Burnaby, British Columbia, Canada.]]
''Stargate SG-1'' was filmed in and around [[Vancouver]], [[British Columbia]], mainly at [[The Bridge Studios]] and NORCO Studios,&lt;ref name=dvdsecrets/&gt;&lt;ref name=gw_bridge&gt;{{cite web |author=Sumner, Darren &amp; Read, David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/02/stargate-universe-begins-principal-photography/ |title=''Stargate Universe'' begins principal photography |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=February 18, 2009 |accessdate=2009-02-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; which offered ''Stargate SG-1'' tax breaks throughout its run.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; The cost of an ''SG-1'' episode increased from US$1.3 million&lt;ref name=v_levitates&gt;{{cite web |last=Dempsey |first=John |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117871914.html?categoryid=1236&amp;cs=1 |title='Stargate' levitates |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=August 26, 2002 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the first seasons to an estimated US$2 million per episode in season 10, partly due to unfavorable exchange rates.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt;&lt;ref name=mcn_200/&gt; Many Vancouver area landmarks were incorporated into the episodes, such as the campus of [[Simon Fraser University]], which became the setting of an alien civilization's capitol.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Heckman, Candace and Chansanchai, Athima |url=http://www.seattlepi.com/movies/251525_hollywoodnorthact3.html |title=Vancouver: A sci-fi film and TV fan's paradise |publisher=''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' |date=December 12, 2005 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Production faced many weather problems because of the moderate oceanic [[climate of Vancouver]], although rain could be eliminated from film. The season 3 episode &quot;[[Crystal Skull (Stargate SG-1)|Crystal Skull]]&quot; was the first episode to be filmed on a virtual set.&lt;ref name=dvdsecrets/&gt;

The main setting of ''Stargate SG-1'', the fictional [[Stargate Command]] (SGC) at the (real) [[Cheyenne Mountain|Cheyenne Mountain Air Force Station]] near [[Colorado Springs, Colorado]], was filmed at stage 5 of The Bridge Studios.&lt;ref name=gw_bridge/&gt; Martin Wood filmed half a dozen stock shots of the real Cheyenne Mountain complex for use in the series approximately ten days before the premiere of the pilot episode. Although these shots wore out over the years, the producers did not film new shots until the beginning of season 9, thinking that ''Stargate SG-1'' would be cancelled after each current year.&lt;ref name=ac_904&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Joseph Mallozzi|Mallozzi, Joseph]], [[Martin Gero|Gero, Martin]] |date=2006 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[The Ties That Bind (Stargate SG-1)|The Ties That Bind]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ac_701&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Martin Wood|Wood, Martin]] |date=2004 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 7 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Fallen (Stargate SG-1)|Fallen]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; By then, visitor questions and fan theories about the existence of a Stargate at the real Cheyenne Mountain complex had become so common that Cheyenne Mountain had installed a seemingly high-security door labeled &quot;Stargate Command&quot; for one of their storage rooms holding brooms and detergent.&lt;ref name=comiccon&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Martin Wood|Wood, Martin]]; [[Amanda Tapping|Tapping, Amanda]] |date=2008 |title=Stargate: The Ark of Truth – Stargate at Comic-Con | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first seven seasons had 22 episodes each, which was reduced to 20 episodes for the last three seasons. Episodes of the first seasons were filmed over a period of 7.5 working days, which decreased to a targeted average of six working days in the last seasons.&lt;ref name=ac_803/&gt; All episodes were filmed in [[16:9]] wide-screen, although ''Stargate SG-1'' was broadcast in [[4:3]] aspect ratio in its first years.&lt;ref name=gw_rainmaker&gt;{{cite video |people=Woloshyn, Bruce |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/a_day_at_rainmaker.shtml |title=&quot;A Day At Rainmaker – GateWorld talks with Bruce Woloshyn |time=13&amp;nbsp;min |date = February 2005|accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The transition to the broadcast of episodes in the wider 16:9 ratio gave directors more freedom in frame composition.&lt;ref name=ac_1019&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Will Waring|Waring, Will]] and [[Alan McCullough|McCullough, Alan]] |date=2007 |title=Stargate SG-1 Season 10 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Dominion (Stargate SG-1)|Dominion]]&quot; |time=7 &amp;nbsp;min |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first three seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'' were filmed on [[16 mm film|16&amp;nbsp;mm film]], notwithstanding scenes involving visual effects that had always been shot on [[35 mm film|35&amp;nbsp;mm film]] for various technical reasons. After a test run with the season 3 finale, &quot;[[Nemesis (Stargate SG-1)|Nemesis]]&quot;, ''Stargate SG-1'' switched to 35&amp;nbsp;mm film for all purposes at the beginning of season 4.&lt;ref name=ac_401_jt&gt;{{cite video |people=Tichenor, James |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 4 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Small Victories]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Digital HD cameras were used for filming beginning with season 8.&lt;ref name=ac_803&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Will Waring|Waring, Will]] and [[Jim Menard|Menard, Jim]] |date=2005 |title=Stargate SG-1 Season 8 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Lockdown (Stargate SG-1)|Lockdown]]&quot; |time=1 and 8&amp;nbsp;min |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Production design===
{{See also|Stargate (device)|List of starships in Stargate|Technology in Stargate}}
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[File:Stargate SG-1 Gates.png|thumb|Since the original Stargate prop from the feature film had severely deteriorated, a new prop was designed for the TV series.]] --&gt;
The art department generated all of the concepts and drawing for the prop department, the set decoration department, the construction department, the paint department, and the model shop. They also collaborated with the visual effects department.&lt;ref name=dvdsecrets&gt;{{cite video |people=Hudolin, Richard; [[Michael Greenburg|Greenburg, Michael]]; Smith, N. John |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Timeline To The Future – Part 2: Secrets Of The Gate | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' employed about 200 Canadian union workers, although that number could exceed 300 when new sets were built.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; Lead production designer Richard Hudolin joined the project in October 1996. Bridget McGuire, ''SG-1''{{'}}s art director since the pilot episode, took over as lead production designer in season 6.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gibson 2003, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;

Hudolin flew to Los Angeles in 1996 to gather material from the feature film as reference and found the original Stargate [[Theatrical property|prop]] stored outside in the Californian desert. Although the prop had severely deteriorated, he was able to take a detailed mold for ''Stargate SG-1'' production to build its own prop. The new Stargate was engineered to turn, to lock the chevrons, and to be computer-controlled to dial specific gate addresses. A portable Stargate prop was built for on-location shoots and required six workers and one full day to set up.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt;&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt; Since visual effects are sometimes faster and cheaper,&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt; a computer-generated Stargate was occasionally used in on-location shoots in later seasons.&lt;ref name=ac_403/&gt;

The SGC set had to be twice as high for shooting as the {{convert|22|ft|m|adj=mid|-tall}} Stargate prop,&lt;ref name=dvdproducingstargate/&gt; but one of Hudolin's original plans of a three-level set was rejected in favor of a two-level set.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt; The gateroom was the biggest room on set and could be redesigned for other scenes.&lt;ref name=ac_403&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Martin Wood|Wood, Martin]] and Tichenor, James |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 4 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Upgrades (Stargate SG-1)|Upgrades]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two multi-purpose rooms were frequently redecorated into the infirmary, Daniel's lab, the cafeteria or the gym.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt;&lt;ref name=ac_601_mw&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Martin Wood|Wood, Martin]] |date=2003 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 6 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Redemption (Stargate SG-1)|Redemption (Part 1)]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The SGC set and all other sets from the pilot episode were constructed within six weeks in January and February 1997, incorporating some original set pieces from the feature film.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign&gt;{{cite video |people=Hudolin, Richard |date=2001 |title= Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Production Design: Richard Hudolin | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The SGC set would be largely dismantled in late 2008 to make room for the Icarus Base set of ''[[Stargate Universe]]''.&lt;ref name=jm_090120&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url=http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/01/20/january-20-2009-the-return-of-norman-shuttlecock-junior/ |title=January 20, 2009: The Return of Norman Shuttlecock Junior |publisher=[[WordPress]]|date=January 20, 2009 |accessdate=2009-01-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Make-up and costumes===
Most ''SG-1'' main characters are US [[airmen]] and wear authentic [[United States Air Force]] uniforms. During missions, the members of the SG-1 team normally wear olive green [[Battle Dress Uniform]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |url=http://www.discoverychannel.co.uk/sci-files/cinema/stargate/index.shtml |title=Science Fiction in the Cinema – Stargate |publisher=[[Discovery Channel]] |date=2006 |time=29&amp;nbsp;min}}&lt;/ref&gt; Richard Dean Anderson and Don S. Davis received a regular military-style haircut on set.&lt;ref name=tvzones58_28&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Christopher Judge – Judge For Yourself |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 58 |pages=28–32 |month=July |year=2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gibson 2003, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; Amanda Tapping had her hair comparably short until the filming of the direct-to-DVD films. Playing a civilian, Michael Shanks adopted James Spader's hairstyle from the feature film but cut it short for the season 2 finale and subsequent seasons.&lt;!--Hair of AT and MS obvious--&gt; The Jaffa alien Teal'c (Christopher Judge) was the only main character whose look required more than basic make-up. His Egyptian look was reflective of the Goa'uld Ra from the feature film and was complemented with a forehead symbol and a gold skin tone, although his make-up process was simplified over the years.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_62&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Jan Newman – Born With It – Make-up |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 46 |pages=62–65 |month=July |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Judge shaved his head at home each day until the producers allowed him to let his hair grow in season 8.&lt;ref name=tvzones58_28/&gt; As a trained nurse, key make-up artist Jan Newman could make burns, cuts, bruises and the SG-1 team's other wounds look authentic.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_62/&gt;

For the look of aliens, the make-up department collaborated with prosthetics companies from Vancouver and Los Angeles, including Todd Masters. While the human origins of many alien races and human civilizations were left recognizable, the recurring [[Unas (Stargate)|Unas]] race required elaborate prosthetics and make-up work.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_62/&gt; To mirror the independent development of the fictional human civilizations after their displacement from Earth, the costume designers took elements of the respective Earth cultures, and combined them with modern fabrics, elaborate trims and chains that would give a historical yet otherworldly appearance.&lt;ref name=dvdcostumedesign&gt;{{cite video |people=McQuarrie, Christina |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Costume Design: Christina McQuarrie | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The look of the Goa'uld such as Apophis was initially based on Ra in the feature film.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_62/&gt; For the design of the Ori and the Priors in season 9, the art department looked at Japanese and Samurai garments for costume design. Art director James Robbins found the face painting, scarification and burns of remote jungle tribes mystical, serving as inspiration for the face scarification of the Priors and the Doci. Early considerations of finger extensions and scarification on their hands were discarded as impracticable.&lt;ref name=tvzones64_24&gt;{{cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven |title=Stargate SG-1 Season 9 preview - Nine Lives |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 64 |pages=24–30; 44–48 56–60 |date=July 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Visual effects===
''Stargate SG-1'' was one of the biggest employers in the Vancouver [[visual effects]] market,&lt;ref name=playback/&gt; spending $400,000 per episode.&lt;ref&gt;Gibson 2003, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; The largest role was played by [[Rainmaker Digital Effects]],&lt;ref name=playback/&gt; whose senior digital compositing artist, Bruce Woloshyn, worked approximately 10 months a year in close collaboration with ''SG-1''{{'s}} visual effects supervisor/producer James Tichenor and visual effects supervisor Michelle Comens.&lt;ref name=gw_bruce/&gt; Many companies were hired to create the Stargate's water-like event horizon in the beginning, but Rainmaker eventually became the only company to create those visual effects.&lt;ref name=gw_rainmaker/&gt; Rainmaker's regular effects shots included the activation and use of the Stargate itself (with well over 300 event horizon shots in the first few years), the transport rings, and the blast shots of the staff weapons and zat guns. They created the visual effects for Goa'uld cargo ships and death gliders on a less regular basis.&lt;ref name=gw_bruce&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/bruce_woloshyn.shtml |title=GateWorld talks with Bruce Woloshyn |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=December |year=2002 |accessdate=2009-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lost Boys Studios provided visual effects for ''SG-1'' from the very beginning of the series up to the end of season 5,&lt;ref name=&quot;LBStudios&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lostboys-studios.com/tv/stargate.php |title=Lostboys Studios: Digital Effects For Film &amp; Television |publisher=Lost Boys Studios |accessdate=2009-05-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Image Engine]] worked on the show from season 2. ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Stargate Atlantis'' were responsible for an estimated 30% to 40% of the business of [[Atmosphere Visual Effects]].&lt;ref name=playback&gt;{{cite web |last=Careless |first=James |url=http://www.playbackonline.ca/articles/magazine/20060501/sg1post.html |title=B.C. post shops create series' alien worlds |publisher=''[[Playback (magazine)|Playback]]'' |date=May 1, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; James Tichenor considered the few episodes with big visual effects budgets the most likely works to contain visual cues that would impress award judges.&lt;ref name=variety&gt;{{cite web |last=Zahed |first=Ramin |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117850978.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1 |title=Emmys nominees: Sci-fiers impress with innovative effects |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=August 8, 2001 |accessdate=2008-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' helped win the local post production shops industry recognition, with season 4's &quot;[[Small Victories]]&quot;, season 5's &quot;[[Revelations (Stargate SG-1)|Revelations]]&quot; and season 7's &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot; receiving the most visual effects awards and nominations ''(see [[List of awards and nominations received by Stargate SG-1]])''.

===Music===
According to composer [[Joel Goldsmith]], ''Stargate SG-1'' had a traditional action-adventure score, &quot;with a sci-fi, fantasy flair&quot; that goes &quot;from comedy to drama to wondrous to suspense to heavy action to ethereal&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Burlingame |first=Jon |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117870437.html?categoryid=1329&amp;cs=1 |title=Sci-fi series: a musical odyssey |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=July 29, 2002 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brad Wright and Jonathan Glassner had known Goldsmith since the second season of ''The Outer Limits'' before they approached him to work on the pilot episode of ''Stargate SG-1''. Goldsmith and [[David Arnold]], the composer of the original feature film score, discussed themes for a television adaptation. The main titles of ''Stargate SG-1'' were a medley of several themes from the feature film, although Goldsmith also wrote a unique end title for ''SG-1'' to establish the show as its own entity.&lt;ref name=joel/&gt; MGM eventually insisted on using Arnold's score in the pilot episode instead of Goldsmith's, but Brad Wright's 2009 direct-to-DVD recut of ''[[Children of the Gods]]'' uses Goldsmith's original score.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=Sumner, Daren and Read, David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/breaking_the_ice_part_22.shtml |title=Breaking The Ice – GateWorld talks with Brad Wright (Part 2) |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=May |year=2008 |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For each episode's score, Goldsmith simulated a real orchestra with a synthesizer palette of an eighty-piece symphony orchestra for budgetary reasons,&lt;ref name=joel/&gt; although he occasionally used two or three musicians for added orchestral authenticity.&lt;ref name=companion56_150_151/&gt; Goldsmith's long-time assistant Neal Acree started composing additional music for ''Stargate SG-1'' in season 8.&lt;ref name=gw_emotion/&gt; The amount of composed music varied between 12 and 33 minutes out of a 44-minute episode, with an average of around 22 to 26 minutes,&lt;ref name=gw_emotion&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/the_language_of_emotion.shtml |title=The Language of Emotion – GateWorld talks with Neal Acree |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=March |year=2009 |accessdate=2009-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; making the full symphonic score of ''SG-1'' more time-consuming to create than for general TV shows.&lt;ref name=joel/&gt; Since Goldsmith lived a thousand miles away from Vancouver, he and the producers discussed ideas over the phone&lt;ref name=companion56_150_151&gt;Gibson 2003, pp. 150–151.&lt;/ref&gt; and exchanged tapes via [[Federal Express]] for several years until the show switched to Internet file transfers.&lt;ref name=joel2&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/gate_harmonics_part_2_of_2.shtml |title=Gate Harmonics – GateWorld talks with Joel Goldsmith (Part 2) |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=November | year=2006 |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Goldsmith's reliance on Arnold's score decreased over the seasons when ''Stargate SG-1'' departed from the Goa'uld theme and introduced new characters and races. Goldsmith had a thematic approach to races and spaceships.&lt;ref name=joel&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/gate_harmonics_part_1_of_2.shtml |title=Gate Harmonics – GateWorld talks with Joel Goldsmith (Part 1) |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=November | year=2006 |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; For example, he wanted a mechanical, repetitive musical motif for the Replicators;&lt;ref name=joel2/&gt; Gothic, [[Gregorian chant|Gregorian]], and Christian themes were the inspiration for the Ori motif.&lt;ref name=joel/&gt; The Ancient theme was deliberately carried over to ''Stargate Atlantis''. The end of &quot;Lost City&quot; has a basic melody that would become part of the main title of ''Atlantis'' per a suggestion by Goldsmith's assistant.&lt;ref name=joel2/&gt; Non-original music was rarely used on ''SG-1'', although Goldsmith chose the aria &quot;Vesti la giubba&quot; from [[Leoncavallo]]'s &quot;Pagliaccio&quot; for the season 3's &quot;[[Shades of Grey (Stargate SG-1)|Shades of Grey]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=gw_brad&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/brad_wright.shtml |title=Interviews – Brad Wright |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |month=July |year=2002 |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, [[Lily Frost]]'s song &quot;Who am I&quot; played in season 7's &quot;[[Fragile Balance (Stargate SG-1)|Fragile Balance]]&quot;, and [[Creedence Clearwater Revival|CCR]]'s song &quot;[[Have You Ever Seen the Rain?]]&quot; played in the series finale &quot;[[Unending]]&quot;. A television soundtrack with Goldsmith's adapted score was released in 1997,&lt;ref name=&quot;ost1997&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Stargate SG-1 Soundtrack|url=http://www.soundtrack.net/albums/database/?id=1044|publisher=SoundtrackNet|accessdate=29 May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; followed by a best-of release in 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;ost2001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last=Goldwasser|first=Dan|title=The Best of Stargate SG-1 Soundtrack|url=http://www.soundtrack.net/albums/database/?id=2844|publisher=SoundtrackNet|accessdate=29 May 2010|date=29 August 2001}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opening title sequence===
[[File:King Tut Ankh Amun Golden Mask.jpg|thumb|The opening credits of ''Stargate SG-1''{{'s}} first five seasons show Ra's mask in close-up, as demonstrated here with [[Tutankhamun]]'s Golden mask.]]

''Stargate SG-1'' has had several opening title sequences, which are generally preceded by a [[teaser act]]. The credits are normally sixty seconds long. Richard Dean Anderson was the only ''SG-1'' actor whose name appeared before the show's title. Michael Shanks's name was moved near the end of the opening credits with the appendage &quot;as Daniel Jackson&quot; after his return to the show in season 7. Some DVD versions of early ''SG-1'' seasons have different opening credits than the television versions, as do the direct-to-DVD films. Composer Joel Goldsmith adapted [[David Arnold]]'s ''Stargate'' feature film score for ''SG-1''{{'}}s opening title theme, which remained the same during the run of ''Stargate SG-1'' and its direct-to-DVD films.

The first opening title sequence, used in the first five seasons, shows a slow-pan camera move over [[Ra]]'s mask. The ''Stargate SG-1'' producers had run out of time before the premiere of season 1 and simply re-used the accelerated opening title sequence of the feature film.&lt;ref name=ac_402/&gt; [[Ra]]'s mask had been created in the feature film's model shop and had originally been filmed with a [[motion control photography|motion-control camera]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Dean Devlin|Devlin, Dean]] and [[Roland Emmerich|Emmerich, Roland]] |date=2001 |title=Audio Commentary for [[Stargate (film)|Stargate]] |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Partly because [[Ra]]'s mask looked cross-eyed, Brad Wright approached the art department in the following years to produce a new opening title sequence; however, the sequence remained the same until the show's move to the Sci-Fi Channel. During the first five seasons when the show was syndicated a separate introduction was used; this intro is still used by Sci-Fi for seasons 1-5. This version uses action shots of the original cast.&lt;ref name=ac_402&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Peter DeLuise|DeLuise, Peter]] and Tichenor, James |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 4 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[The Other Side (Stargate SG-1)|The Other Side]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ac_610&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Andy Mikita|Mikita, Andy]]; [[Damian Kindler|Kindler, Damien]]; [[Jim Menard|Menard, Jim]] |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 6 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Cure (Stargate SG-1)|Cure]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The opening title sequence of the first two season 6 episodes shows a turning Stargate, for which a [[Frazier lens]] was put as close as 1/8&amp;nbsp;inch (3&amp;nbsp;mm) to the Stargate prop.&lt;ref name=ac_610/&gt; The opening credits of the following episodes intercut this material with live-action shots of the characters from previous seasons and ended with the SG-1 team stepping through the Stargate. The opening credits stayed the same in the next two seasons except for minor clip and cast changes. The opening credits of season 9 intercut shots of the Stargate with action sequences similar to the previous opening credits, although the Stargate was visibly computer-generated. The Sci Fi Channel cut the opening credits from sixty to ten seconds in their original broadcast of the first half of season 9, but re-instated the full opening credits after strong negative fan reactions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2005/09/sci_fi_to_reinstate_full-length_.shtml |title=SCI FI to reinstate full-length openings |date=September 1, 2005 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |accessdate=2007-07-20}}&lt;/ref&gt; The writers poked fun at this move in ''SG-1''{{'}}s milestone episode &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot; in season 10, showing a five-second clip instead of the full titles.&lt;ref name=ac1006rccbw&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Robert C. Cooper|Cooper, Robert C.]] and [[Brad Wright|Wright, Brad]] |date=2007 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 10 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning with season 10's &quot;[[Company of Thieves (Stargate SG-1)|Company of Thieves]]&quot;, the last clip of the opening credits shows Vala Mal Doran almost missing SG-1's trip through the Stargate.

===Collaboration with the military===
{{multiple image
 | footer = [[General (United States)|Generals]] Michael E. Ryan and John P. Jumper, USAF Chiefs of Staff, appeared as themselves in &quot;Prodigy&quot; ({{start date|2001}}) and &quot;Lost City&quot; ({{start date|2004}}).
 | image1 = Michael Ryan, official military photo.jpg
 | width1 = 175
 | image2 = John-P-Jumper.jpg
 | width2 = 180
}}

The [[United States Air Force]] (USAF) cooperated closely with the ''Stargate SG-1'' producers. Before the beginning of the series, the USAF granted production access to the Cheyenne Mountain complex to film stock shots. They also read every script for mistakes and provided help with plausible background stories for all characters, ribbons, uniform regulations, hair advice, plotlines, and military relationships.&lt;ref name=dvdbeyond/&gt; The USAF flew up several [[T-38 Talon]], [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15]] and [[F-16]] fighter jets to Vancouver for various episodes and direct-to-DVD films.&lt;ref name=comiccon/&gt;&lt;ref name=tvzones46_66/&gt;&lt;ref name=ac_910/&gt; Many of the extras portraying USAF personnel were real USAF personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;air force press release&quot;/&gt;

Two successive [[Chief of Staff of the United States Air Force|Chiefs of Staff of the USAF]], Generals [[Michael E. Ryan]] and [[John P. Jumper]], appeared as themselves in season 4's &quot;[[Prodigy (Stargate SG-1)|Prodigy]]&quot; and season 7's &quot;[[Lost City (Stargate SG-1)|Lost City]]&quot;, respectively. General Jumper's second scheduled appearance in season 9's &quot;[[The Fourth Horseman]]&quot; was cancelled due to ongoing conflicts in the [[Middle East]].&lt;ref name=ac_910&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Andy Mikita|Mikita, Andy]] and [[Damian Kindler|Kindler, Damian]] |date=2006 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 9 – Audio Commentary for &quot;[[The Fourth Horseman|The Fourth Horseman (Part 1)]]&quot; |medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Air Force Association]] recognized Richard Dean Anderson at its 57th annual dinner on September 14, 2004 for his work as actor and executive producer of the show, and for the show's positive depiction of the Air Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;air force press release&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Thar |first=Doug |publisher=Air Force Link |url=http://www.af.mil/news/story.asp?storyID=123008593 |title=Air Force to honor actor, producer |date=September 9, 2004 |accessdate=2009-03-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Stargate SG-1'' also received support from the United States and other international navies. Several scenes of season 4's &quot;[[Small Victories]]&quot; were filmed aboard and outside of a Russian [[Foxtrot class submarine|''Foxtrot''-class submarine]], which had been brought from [[Vladivostok]] to Vancouver.&lt;ref name=dvdproductiondesign/&gt; The [[United States Navy]] invited the cast and producers to film aboard the nuclear submarine [[USS Alexandria (SSN-757)|USS ''Alexandria'']] (SSN-757) and at their [[Applied Physics Laboratory Ice Station]] in the [[Arctic]] for ''Stargate: Continuum''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://stargate.mgm.com/news_detail.php?id=5 |title=SG-1 headed to the Arctic |date=March 14, 2007 |publisher=[[MGM]] |accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes and allusions==
{{Main|Mythology of Stargate}}
[[File:La Tombe de Horemheb cropped.jpg|thumb|upright|Many ''SG-1'' stories are built around Egyptian gods, such as (from left to right) Osiris, Anubis and Horus.]]
''Stargate SG-1'' takes place in a [[military science fiction]] environment and employs the common science fiction concepts of strongly differentiated characters fighting an unequivocally evil enemy (the [[Goa'uld]]). However, it links alien races with well-known Earth mythologies, by use of the central Stargate device. Near-instantaneous interplanetary travel allows quick narrative shifts between the politics on Earth and the realities of fighting an interstellar war.&lt;ref&gt;Beeler 2008, pp. 267–269.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' gradually evolves the basic premise of the ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' film into its own unique mythological superstructure,&lt;ref name=beeler_intro&gt;Beeler and Dickson 2005. &quot;Introduction&quot;, pp. 1–5.&lt;/ref&gt; expanding upon [[Ancient Egyptian religion|Egyptian mythology]] (notably the gods [[Apep]]/Apophis and [[Anubis]] as Goa'uld villains), [[Norse mythology]] (notably the god [[Thor]] as an [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard ally]]), and [[Arthurian legend]] (notably [[Merlin]] as an [[Ancient (Stargate)|Ancient ally]] against the god-like [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]]), among others. ''SG-1'' introduces new alien races (as opposed to alien human civilizations) less often than other science fiction television series and integrates newly encountered races or visited planets in stand-alone episodes into its established mythology while leaving the plotlines accessible for new audience members.&lt;ref&gt;Beeler 2008, pp. 273–277.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the show's extensive intergalactic mythology and science fiction elements, scholar M. Keith Booker considered ''SG-1'' ultimately character-driven and heavily dependent on the camaraderie among the SG-1 members.&lt;ref name=booker_181&gt;Booker 2004, pp. 181–182.&lt;/ref&gt;

The producers embraced humor and wanted ''SG-1'' to be a fun show that did not take itself too seriously.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; Brad Wright regarded ''SG-1'' as a family show with adequate violence as opposed to random or gratuitous violence.&lt;ref name=gw_specialpilot/&gt; Christopher Judge did not consider ''SG-1'' as a &quot;message show by any stretch of the imagination, but occasionally there are messages there&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Gbison 2003, p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt; Aimed at a popular audience, ''Stargate SG-1'' emphasized its present-day-Earth story frame by frequently referencing [[popular culture]], like ''[[The X-Files]]'' and ''[[Buffy the Vampire Slayer (TV series)|Buffy the Vampire Slayer]]'' had done before.&lt;ref name=hipple&gt;Hipple, Dave, &quot;Stargate SG-1: Self-possessed Science Fiction&quot;. In Beeler and Dickson 2005, p. 27–28.&lt;/ref&gt; Jonathan Glassner had written ''[[The Wizard of Oz (1939 film)|The Wizard of Oz]]'' references into his own scripts since the first season, which the other writers imitated after Richard Dean Anderson began referencing the film on his own.&lt;ref name=dvduniverse&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Jonathan Glassner|Glassner, Jonathan]] |date=2002 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 4 – The Stargate Universe | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; O'Neill references Richard Dean Anderson's favorite television series, ''[[The Simpsons]]'', throughout the show.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2005/06/anderson_to_guest_star_on_ithe_s.shtml |title=Anderson to guest star on The Simpsons |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=June 20, 2005 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''SG-1'' makes meta-textual references to the process of writing and filming a science fiction TV series in several episodes&lt;ref&gt;Beeler 2008, pp. 277-278.&lt;/ref&gt; and alludes to the main actors' previous TV roles in the pilot episode (Carter: &quot;It took us fifteen years and three supercomputers to [[MacGyver]] a system for the gate on Earth&quot;) and in a ''[[Farscape]]'' vignette in the milestone episode &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot;.

==Broadcast and release==
{{See also|List of Stargate SG-1 episodes}}

===Showtime and US syndication (1997–2002)===
The American subscription channel [[Showtime (TV network)|Showtime]] ordered the first two seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'' with 44 episodes total in 1996.&lt;ref name=dvdlegacy/&gt; The two-hour pilot episode received Showtime's highest-ever ratings for a series premiere with an audience of approximately 1.5 million households in the 8 p.m. Sunday slot of July 27, 1997.&lt;ref name=nyt_farside/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Richmond |first=Ray |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1116678643.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1 |title='Stargate' Showtime's home run |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=August 1, 1997 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the ''SG-1'' producers, a broadcast network would have cancelled ''SG-1'' after a few episodes, but Showtime put no pressure on the show to &quot;deliver the meteoric ratings the way network shows do&quot;.&lt;ref name=spi_cruising/&gt; The show was consistently the channel's most-watched program (including theatrical movies),&lt;ref name=nyt_appeal/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Dempsey |first=John |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117790288.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1 |title=TV biz's gay pride parade |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=December 13, 2000 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; so Showtime ordered a third and fourth season of 22 episodes each in July 1998,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Morgan |first=Richard |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117478828.html?categoryid=18&amp;cs=1 |title=MGM posts larger loss |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=July 27, 1998 |accessdate=2009-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since ''Stargate SG-1'' was expensive to produce, MGM arranged an agreement with Showtime that ''SG-1'' could air in syndication six months after their premiere on Showtime.&lt;ref name=v_stakes&gt;{{cite web |last=Dempsey |first=John |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117892381.html?categoryid=10&amp;cs=1 |title=Cablers raise syndie stakes |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=September 14, 2003 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; All 22 [[Fox Broadcasting Company|Fox]] stations aired the first seasons after their Showtime debut, providing a clearance of 41% of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Moss |first=Linda |title=Showtime's 'Stargate' going to Fox in syndication |publisher=Multichannel News |date=August 18, 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Pursell |first=Chris |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117758132.html?categoryid=14&amp;cs=1 |title='Stargate' fences in Fox |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date= November 17, 1999 |accessdate=2009-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Syfy|Sci Fi Channel]] made its largest single programming acquisition of $150 million in 1998 by buying the exclusive basic cable rights to the MGM package ''Stargate SG-1'', ''[[The Outer Limits (1995 TV series)|The Outer Limits]]'', and ''[[Poltergeist: The Legacy]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Richard |first=Ray |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117469302.html?categoryid=18&amp;cs=1 |title=Sci-fi aiming high |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=March 31, 1998 |accessdate=2009-03-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Showtime decided to end its association with ''Stargate SG-1'' at the end of season 5, saying that the show still had a sizeable viewership but could no longer draw new subscribers due to its availability in syndication.&lt;ref name=mcn_200&gt;{{cite web |last=McNamara |first=Mary |url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/123363-Stargate_200.php |title=Science-Fiction Series 'SG-1' Is Cable's First to Reach Historic Milestone |publisher=Multichannel News |date=May 7, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sci Fi Channel and US syndication (2002–2007)===
Since ''SG-1''{{'s}} ratings were good from a financial standpoint, the Sci Fi Channel picked up MGM's offer to continue the show into a sixth season, yet with a slightly reduced budget.&lt;ref name=tvzones46_66&gt;{{Cite journal |last=Eramo |first=Steven | title=Season Six Preview – Coming up, on SG-1... |journal=[[TV Zone]] |issue=Special 46 |pages=66–76 |month=July |year=2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sci Fi aired new episodes of ''Stargate SG-1'' in the 9 p.m. Friday slot between ''[[The Dead Zone (TV series)|The Dead Zone]]'' and ''[[Farscape]]'', while it aired older ''SG-1'' episodes in a four-hour block every Monday at 7 p.m. Episodes were broadcast in US syndication six months after their premiere on Sci Fi.&lt;ref name=&quot;v_levitates&quot;/&gt; The sixth season was supposed to be the show's last,&lt;ref name=tvzones46_4/&gt; but Sci Fi renewed ''SG-1'' at the last minute.&lt;ref&gt;Storm 2005, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; The sixth and seventh seasons made ''Stargate SG-1'' Sci Fi's highest-rated original series with an average of 2 million viewers in over 1.3 million households,&lt;ref name=scifi_pr03&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scifi.com/stargate/press/press_02.html |title= Sci Fi Channel Renews Stargate SG-1 For Eighth Season |publisher=scifi.com |date=July 23, 2003 |accessdate=2009-03-24}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; elevating Sci Fi into the top 10 cable networks in the United States.&lt;ref name=reelwest&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.reelwest.com/happening/wire/2006/april/stargate.htm |title=Canadian Produced TV Series &quot;Stargate SG-1&quot; Films Landmark 200th Original Episode |publisher=reelwest.com |date = April 2006|accessdate=2009-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the next few years, the producers believed each current season to be the show's last and repeatedly wrote big series finales,&lt;ref name=spi_cruising&gt;{{cite web |last=McFarland |first=Melanie |url=http://www.seattlepi.com/tv/267484_tv21.html |title=On TV: 'Stargate SG-1' keeps cruising, despite the light years |publisher=''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'' |date=April 21, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the success of ''Stargate SG-1'' put off their plans of ending the show to write a new ''Stargate'' feature film.&lt;ref name=duoefficiency/&gt; Sci Fi cut the length of an ''SG-1'' season from 22 to 20 episodes from season 8 onwards.

Originally envisioned as a replacement for ''SG-1'', the [[Spin-off (media)|spin-off]] series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'' began airing in tandem with ''SG-1''{{'s}} eighth season in summer 2004, setting a series record of 3.2 million viewers for ''SG-1'' and a Sci Fi record as most-watched episode of a regular series ever (at the time) for ''Atlantis'' with 4.2 million viewers.&lt;ref name=duoefficiency&gt;{{cite web |last=Littleton |first=Cynthia |url=http://www.allbusiness.com/services/amusement-recreation-services/4735235-1.html |title=Duo found portal to sci-fi efficiency |publisher=Entertainment News Wire |date=August 9, 2004 |accessdate=2009-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Battlestar Galactica (2004 TV series)|Battlestar Galactica]]'' joined the two ''Stargate'' series in January 2005, making Sci Fi the leader among basic cablers on Friday nights over the summer of 2005.&lt;ref name=v_pair/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thefutoncritic.com/news/2004/11/15/sci-fi-opens-the-gates-to-more-adventures/20041115scifi01/ |title=Sci Fi Opens The 'Gates' To More Adventures |publisher=The Futon Critic |date=November 15, 2004 |accessdate=2010-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The producers considered replacing ''Stargate SG-1'' with a new show named ''Stargate Command'' after ''SG-1''{{'}}s eighth season,&lt;ref name=ac_901&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Robert C. Cooper|Cooper, Robert C.]], [[Andy Mikita|Mikita, Andy]] |date=2006 |title=Audio Commentary for &quot;[[Avalon (Stargate SG-1)|Avalon, Part 1]]&quot; |medium= DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the Sci Fi Channel decided to continue ''SG-1'' with a slightly changed cast for a ninth season instead. Season 9's average slipped from 2.4 million viewers in late 2005&lt;ref name=v_pair&gt;{{cite web |last=Martin |first=Denise |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117931513.html?categoryid=1417&amp;cs=1 |title=Sci Fi picks up 'Stargate' pair |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=October 24, 2005 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; to 2.1 million viewers with 1.8 household rating during early 2006, which Sci Fi's Mark Stern attributed to the &quot;tech-savvy, toy-loving, time-shifting audience&quot; whose use of digital video recorders excluded them in ratings compilations.&lt;ref name=mcn_200/&gt; Meanwhile, the decline of ''SG-1''{{'s}} 2005–2006 syndication household ratings was consistent with the overall decline in syndicated sci-fi action hours.&lt;ref name=v_swinging/&gt; Sci Fi ordered a record-breaking tenth season of ''SG-1'' in 2005, but announced it would not renew the show for an eleventh season in summer 2006 ''(see [[#Cancellation and future]])''. The final ''SG-1'' episode, &quot;[[Unending]]&quot;, premiered on [[Sky1]] in the UK on March 13, 2007, and attracted approximately 2.2 million viewers on the Sci Fi Channel on June 22, 2007.&lt;ref name=triumphs&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thefutoncritic.com/news.aspx?id=20070626scifi01 |title=Stargate SG-1's series finale triumphs | publisher=The Futon Critic |date=June 26, 2007 |accessdate=2010-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===International broadcast===
According to Wright and Cooper, the worldwide popularity of science fiction was a factor in ''SG-1''{{'s}} success and the good international reception helped keep the series on the air in the beginning.&lt;ref name=hr_global/&gt; Several newspapers reported in 2005–2006 that ''Stargate SG-1'' aired in over 100 countries with a weekly worldwide viewership of around 10 million,&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt;&lt;ref name=spi_cruising/&gt;&lt;ref name=hr_global&gt;{{cite web |last=Brennan |first=Steve |url=http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/hr/search/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1002728447 |title='Stargate' on global trek that spans 200 episodes |publisher=''[[The Hollywood Reporter]]'' |date=June 27, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-21}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; but ''[[The New York Times]]'' gave different numbers in 2004, saying that the show was broadcast in sixty-four countries with more than 17 million viewers a week.&lt;ref name=nyt_deepblue&gt;{{cite web |last=Gates |first=Anita |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/04/tv/cover-story-between-the-wraith-and-the-deep-blue-sea.html |title=Cover Story: Between the Wraith and the Deep Blue Sea |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=July 4, 2004 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' had a particularly fervent response in the [[United Kingdom]], [[Germany]], [[France]], and [[Australia]].&lt;ref name=duoefficiency/&gt;&lt;ref name=nyt_deepblue/&gt;

''Stargate SG-1'' aired in the United Kingdom on [[Sky One]] with repeats on [[Sky Two]], [[Sky Three]], and [[Channel 4]]. Sky One broadcast new episodes of the second half of most seasons before their American premiere. Brad Wright found it &quot;almost embarrassing&quot; that ''Stargate SG-1'' was much more popular in the United Kingdom than in Canada,&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; where the show aired on [[Space (TV channel)|Space]], [[Citytv]], [[A (TV system)|A-Channel]], [[Movie Central]], and French-language channels [[TQS]] and [[Ztélé]].&lt;ref name=reelwest/&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' aired in Australia on [[Sci Fi Australia]], [[Seven Network|Channel Seven]], and [[Golden West Network]].

===Cancellation and future===
On August 21, 2006, a few days after the premiere of ''SG-1''{{'s}} milestone episode &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot;, the Sci Fi Channel confirmed that ''Stargate SG-1'' was not being renewed for an eleventh season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=2&amp;id=37607 |title=SG-1 Ends Run; Atlantis Back| publisher=scifi.com | date=August 22, 2006 |accessdate=2006-08-27 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060825081141/http://www.scifi.com/scifiwire/index.php?category=2&amp;id=37607 &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2006-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; While news outlets cited declining ratings, expensive production and lack of promotion as possible reasons for the cancellation,&lt;ref name=v_swinging/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=McNamara |first=Mary |url=http://www.multichannel.com/article/124883-Sci_Fi_s_Stargate_SG_1_Said_to_Be_Axed.php |title=Sci Fi's Stargate SG-1 Said to Be Axed |publisher=Multichannel News |date=August 21, 2006 |accessdate=2009-05-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; the Sci Fi Channel's Mark Stern merely stated the decision was not ratings-based.&lt;ref name=v_swinging/&gt; Instead, he said the production staff was given enough time to tie up all the loose ends of the story, and ''SG-1'' cast members were planned to be incorporated into the renewed ''Stargate Atlantis''.&lt;ref name=v_swinging&gt;{{cite web |author=John Dempsey, Ben Fritz |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety News]]'' |url=http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117948764.html?categoryid=1417&amp;cs=1 |title=Sci Fi's 'Stargate' swinging closed |date=August 21, 2006 |accessdate=2006-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the ''SG-1'' producers and rights-holder MGM expressed a desire to continue ''SG-1'' as a movie, mini-series, or an eleventh season on another network.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/mgm_considers_isg-1is_future.shtml |title= MGM considers SG-1's future |date=August 26, 2006 |accessdate=2006-08-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;coopersg1&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=|last=Sumner |first=Darren |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/cooper_isg-1i_will_go_on.shtml |title=Cooper: SG-1 will go on |date=August 21, 2006 |accessdate=2006-08-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Brad Wright confirmed the production of two direct-to-DVD films in October 2006,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/10/istargate_sg-1i_movies_coming_to.shtml |title=Stargate SG-1 movies coming to DVD |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date= October 11, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Amanda Tapping joined the ''Atlantis'' cast for their fourth season. The first film, ''[[Stargate: The Ark of Truth]]'', was released in March 2008 and wraps up the Ori storyline. The second film, ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'', is an alternate time-line [[time travel]] story and was released in July 2008. A special edition of the two-hour pilot episode &quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot; with re-edited scenes and a different score has also been produced.&lt;ref name=gw_specialpilot&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://gateworld.net/news/2008/04/special_edition_of_isg-1i_pilot_.shtml |title=Special edition of SG-1 pilot episode in the works |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=April 4, 2008 |accessdate=2009-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2009, MGM confirmed a third new ''SG-1'' film that Brad Wright had first announced in May 2008.&lt;ref name=gw_need_rda/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/04/anderson-confirms-sgu-appearances/ |title=Anderson confirms SGU appearances |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=April 6, 2009 |accessdate=2009-04-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph Mallozzi revealed the working title as ''Stargate: Revolution''.&lt;ref name=jm_091111&gt;{{cite web |author=Joseph Malozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/11/11/november-11-2009-tech-troubles-x-2-get-your-questions-in-for-adam-troy-castro-mailbag/ |title=Tech Troubles x 2! Get your questions in for Adam-Troy Castro! Mailbag! |work=WordPress |date=2009-11-11|accessdate=2009-11-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The film was planned to be written by Wright and former ''Stargate Atlantis'' executive producer [[Carl Binder]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2008/10/09/october-9-2008-actor-tyler-mcclendon-answers-your-questions/ |title=October 9, 2008: Actor Tyler McClendon Answers Your Questions |publisher=[[WordPress]] |date=October 9, 2008 |accessdate=2009-03-18}}&lt;/ref&gt; Martin Wood would serve as director.&lt;ref name=jm_090102/&gt; The premise of the film would have been the &quot;possibility of the Stargate program going public&quot;.&lt;ref name=jm_110515&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url=http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2011/05/15/may-14-2011-the-apocalypse-approacheth-more-sg-1-season-6-memories-another-monster-mailbag/ |title=May 15, 2011: The Apocalypse Approacheth! More SG-1 Season 6 Memories! Another Monster Mailbag! |publisher=[[WordPress]] |date=May 15, 2011 |accessdate=2011-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Wright, the film would center on the Jack O'Neill character and would reunite as many of the ''SG-1'' cast as possible, depending on the cost of the film and actor availability.&lt;ref name=gw_need_rda&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/05/wright_stargate_movies_need_onei.shtml |title=Wright: Stargate movies need O'Neill |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=May 12, 2008 |accessdate=2009-03-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The character of [[Vala Mal Doran]] would not appear in the film.&lt;ref name=jm_090102&gt;{{cite web |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2009/01/02/january-2-2009-brad-wright-answers-your-questions/ |title=Brad Wright Answers Your Questions |publisher=[[WordPress]] |date=January 2, 2009 |accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amanda Tapping confirmed her appearance in this ''SG-1'' film and the first ''Atlantis'' movie in September 2008,&lt;ref name=cinemablend&gt;{{cite web |last=West |first=Kelly |url= http://www.cinemablend.com/television/Amanda-Tapping-Talks-About-Sanctuary-12460.html |title=Amanda Tapping Talks About Sanctuary |publisher=cinemablend.com |date=September 28, 2008 |accessdate=2008-10-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Michael Shanks (Daniel Jackson) confirmed his and Richard Dean Anderson's participation in January 2009.&lt;ref name=scifi_surprise&gt;{{cite web |last=Spelling |first=Ian |url=http://scifiwire.com/2009/01/michael-shanks-has-a-surprise-about-stargate-universe.php |title=Michael Shanks has a surprise about Stargate Universe |publisher=scifi.com |date=January 26, 2009 |accessdate=2009-01-27}}&lt;/ref&gt; No contracts had been signed by April 2009,&lt;ref name=gw_expanding&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/interviews/an_expanding_universe.shtml |title=An Expanding Universe – GateWorld talks with Brad Wright &amp; Robert Cooper |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date = April 2009|accessdate=2009-04-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Wright stated that he &quot;can almost guarantee we are proceeding with the ''SG-1'' movie this year [2009]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/04/third-sg-1-movie-has-a-go/ |title=Third SG-1 movie has a go! |date=April 8, 2009 |accessdate=2009-10-30 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |first=Darren |last=Sumner}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, production was put on hold. Wright explained that the [[late-2000s recession]] made DVD premieres less lucrative for MGM than in the years before,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://blastr.com/2009/08/new-sg-1-atlantis-films-d.php |title=New SG-1, Atlantis films due, just not yet |date=August 12, 2009 |accessdate=2010-09-30 |publisher=[[Sci Fi Wire]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; and he also pointed to the financial crisis of MGM as reason for the delay.&lt;ref name=wrightpreviewssgus2&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tvdeathray.com/2010/09/27/interview-stargate-universe-co-creator-brad-wright-previews-season-2/ |title=Interview: 'Stargate Universe' Co-Creator Brad Wright Previews Season 2 |publisher=tvdeathray.com |date=September 27, 2010 |first=Mike |last=Moody |accessdate=2010-09-30}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wright and Joe Mallozzi expressed optimism that production would eventually start,&lt;ref name=wrightpreviewssgus2 /&gt;&lt;ref name=jm_101106&gt;{{cite web |author=Joseph Malozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2010/11/06/november-6-2010-stargate-ratings-fandom-and-my-picky-aunt/ |title=November 6, 2010: Stargate ratings, fandom, and my picky aunt! |work=WordPress |date=November 6, 2010 |accessdate=2010-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; until Wright announced in April 2011 that the ''SG-1'' film project was permanently shelved, along with plans for future ''Atlantis'' and ''[[Stargate Universe]]'' films and a cross-over film incorporating elements from all three series.&lt;ref name=&quot;sgmoviesdead&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=jm_110417&gt;{{cite web |author=Joseph Malozzi |url= http://josephmallozzi.wordpress.com/2011/04/17/april-17-2011-until-we-meet-again/ |title=until we meet again |work=WordPress |date=April 17, 2011 |accessdate=2011-04-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; By then, neither the ''Atlantis'' nor ''Universe'' television series were produced anymore. Still, Wright did not rule out future ''Stargate'' films, saying; &quot;It's a franchise. ''Stargate'' is not over. Somebody smart from MGM is going to figure it out, and something will happen.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;sgmoviesdead&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Colvin |first=Chad |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2011/04/wright-sgu-continuation-other-movies-dead-for-now/ |title=SGU continuation, other movies dead — for now |date=April 17, 2011 |accessdate=2011-04-18 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Home video release===
{{Main||1=List of Stargate SG-1 episodes#Series overview and home release|l1=Series overview and home release}}
''Stargate SG-1'' was first released on [[DVD]] in some European nations in volumes of typically four episodes each, beginning with &quot;The Best of Season 1&quot; as Volume 1 in the United Kingdom in 2000. Each following season was released as six individual volumes (except season 10 with five volumes), beginning with the first four episodes of season 2. Beginning in 2001, seasons 1 through 8 were released in five-disc [[amaray]] box sets in the United States. [[MGM Home Entertainment]] (Europe) began releasing complete season box sets (including season 1) alongside the individual volumes in 2002. The British season box sets were usually released half a year after a season's last volume release in the UK. ''Stargate SG-1'' was also released in DVD season box sets in Australia.

Most DVDs contain behind-the-scenes features, audio commentaries for nearly all episodes beginning with season 4, and production galleries. The box sets of the first eight seasons were re-released with slim packaging in all regions, beginning in the United States in summer 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://gateworld.net/news/2006/04/sony_switching_to_slim-line_isg-.shtml |title=Sony switching to slim-line ''SG-1'' DVD sets |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=April 3, 2006 |accessdate=2009-05-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; A complete series set was first released in the United States in October 2007, containing 50 discs from the ten seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'' and four bonus discs with content not part of the original sets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2007/08/bonus_features_for_isg-1_complet.shtml |title=Bonus features for SG-1: Complete Series DVDs |date=August 3, 2007 |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |accessdate=2007-08-08}}&lt;/ref&gt; More than 30 million copies of DVDs had been sold by 2006.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt;

===Online distribution===
New episodes of ''Stargate SG-1'' were first released on [[iTunes]] in the US in August 2006, each time one day after their premiere on the Sci Fi Channel. The commercial-free episodes were priced $1.99 each, while a season pass with twenty episodes cost $37.99.&lt;ref name=v_swinging/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/08/istargatei_arrives_on_itunes.shtml |title=Stargate arrives on iTunes |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=August 20, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; A release on iTunes UK followed in October 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Read |first=David |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2007/08/istargatei_comes_to_uk_itunes.shtml |title=Stargate comes to UK iTunes |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=August 31, 2007 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; All ten seasons of ''SG-1'' were available on iTunes and [[Amazon Unbox]] by January 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2008/01/istargatei_expands_itunes_amazon.shtml |title=Stargate expands iTunes, Amazon presence |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=January 11, 2008 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' made its debut on [[hulu.com]] in March 2009, starting with the first season. At first, viewers in the United States could only watch episodes of the first seasons, but as of December 2009 all episodes of seasons 1 to 10 were available free of charge with a small number of commercials on Hulu, through January 31, 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2009/03/stargate-sg-1-arrives-on-hulu/ |title=Stargate SG-1 arrives on [[Hulu]] |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=March 19, 2009 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Free access to all SG-1 episodes continued until July 31, 2011, when the episodes were finally removed. As of February 1, 2011, all episodes of the entire Stargate franchise are available on [[Netflix]]'s paid online video streaming service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Colvin |first=Chad |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2010/08/entire-stargate-library-streaming/ |title=Entire Stargate television library now streaming on Netflix |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=August 16, 2010 |accessdate=2011-02-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==
===Critical reception===
In his review for the pilot episode &quot;[[Children of the Gods]]&quot; in 1997, Will Joyner of ''[[The New York Times]]'' considered ''Stargate SG-1'' a &quot;challenging, if derivative, mix&quot; that is &quot;more than a ''Stargate'' [feature film] fan might expect but certainly less than one would hope for.&quot; He had a mixed opinion about the cast and was disturbed by ''SG-1''{{'s}} use of visual shock tactics to make up for its lower television budget.&lt;ref name=nyt_farside&gt;{{cite web |last=Joyner |first=Will |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1997/07/26/arts/through-a-gate-to-the-far-side-of-the-universe-a-tv-series.html |title=Through a Gate to the Far Side of the Universe: A TV Series |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=July 26, 1997 |accessdate=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reviewing the same episode, ''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]''{{'s}} Tony Scott criticized that &quot;superficial characters wander through their roles without stirring a modicum of conviction&quot; in a show that is &quot;essentially for young people&quot;. He mocked that the wooden acting, &quot;pedestrian writing, pulp-mag plotting, shopworn characters, hackneyed dialogue [...] and Mario Azzopardi's broad direction will all undoubtedly delight billions and billions.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Scott |first=Tony |url=http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117911984.html?categoryid=32&amp;cs=1 |title=Stargate SG-1 |publisher=''[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]'' |date=July 28, 1997 |accessdate=2009-03-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many critics responded negatively to the gratuitous use of sexual implication and female nudity in the pilot episode, which according to Wright had been filmed on Showtime's insistence despite his vocal opposition and was cut from the pilot's 2009 direct-to-DVD version.&lt;ref name=gw_specialpilot/&gt;

According to Sharon Eberson of the [[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]], &quot;Stargate SG-1's&quot; place in the sci-fi universe can be measured in longevity, spot-on cast chemistry, rabid fans and tough subject it has tackled although she argued that the show was rarely a critical darling.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Eberson |first=Sharon |url=http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/07172/795812-237.stm |title='Stargate: SG-1' signs off, but we haven't seen the last of it |publisher=''[[Pittsburgh Post-Gazette]]'' |date=June 21, 2007 |accessdate=2009-05-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although the show was the most-watched program on Showtime, it received almost no media mention outside hard-core science fiction circles in its first seasons.&lt;ref name=nyt_appeal&gt;{{cite web |last=Meisler |first=Andy |url=http://www.nytimes.com/1998/10/04/arts/television-radio-not-even-trying-to-appeal-to-the-masses.html |title=Television/Radio: Not Even Trying to Appeal to the Masses |publisher=''[[The New York Times]]'' |date=October 4, 1998 |date=2009-04-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Stargate SG-1'' gained media attention when ''Stargate Atlantis'' was greenlit (the cover of the July 26, 2003 ''[[TV Guide]]'' issue notably called to &quot;Forget ''[[Star Trek|Trek]]''! ''Stargate SG-1'' is now sci-fi's biggest hit!&quot;), but the ''[[Toronto Star]]'' noted in 2006 that &quot;Nobody seemed to like [''Stargate SG-1''] but the fans; it somehow always slipped under the radar of most TV critics&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thestar.com/entertainment/article/227758 |title=Best Bets |publisher=''[[Toronto Star]]'' |date=June 21, 2007 |accessdate=2009-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Melanie McFarland of the ''[[Seattle Post-Intelligencer]]'', ''SG-1''{{'s}} records did not earn it &quot;the kind of wide-ranging respect a successful series with a 200-episode run deserves&quot;; ''SG-1'' rarely occupied a slot on 'best show' lists because the show remained &quot;relegated to the back of the bus in terms of popularity&quot; behind the glory of ''[[Battlestar Galactica (2004 TV series)|Battlestar Galactica]]'', although every week, the show attracts an average of 10 million viewers worldwide. It has also been pointed out by Cooper that &quot;By the way, neither did the original 'Star Trek' in its time, It wasn't until 30 years later that people started looking back at it and realizing it was a milestone. I think we secretly hope that 10, 15, 20 years from now, that 'Stargate' will be considered in the same way.&quot;&lt;ref name=spi_cruising/&gt; Scott D. Pierce from ''[[Deseret News]]'' said that the series never made a &quot;sort of cultural impact&quot; as ''Star Trek'' because the show was &quot;pretty derivative&quot; which he further stated it became &quot;more so over the years.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=D. Pierce, Scott |url=http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qn4188/is_20070622/ai_n19326904/?tag=content;col1 |title='Stargate' signs off |publisher=''Deseret News'' |date=June 22, 2007 |accessdate=2009-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Hanks from the British [[newspaper]] ''[[The Independent]]'' said that the series &quot;Did the job&quot; during its second season of broadcasting.&lt;ref name=&quot;theindependent&quot;&gt;{{cite news| author=Hanks, Robert | url=http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/television-review-1110317.html |title=Television Review |publisher=The Independent |date=2 August 1999 |accessdate=2009-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Awards and nominations===
{{Main|List of awards and nominations received by Stargate SG-1}}
''Stargate SG-1'' was nominated for numerous awards during its ten-season run. Its nominations for seven [[Emmy]]s in the &quot;Outstanding Special Visual Effects for a Series&quot; category and one Emmy for &quot;Outstanding Music Composition for a Series (Dramatic Underscore)&quot; did not result in a win.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.emmys.org/awards/2007pt/history.php |title=Primetime Awards |publisher=[[Emmy]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''SG-1'' won two [[Gemini Awards]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://academy.ca/hist/history.cfm?stitle=stargate+sg-1&amp;awyear=0&amp;winonly=1&amp;awards=2&amp;rtype=2&amp;curstep=4&amp;submit.x=0&amp;submit.y=0 |title=Canada's Awards Database |publisher=The Academy of Canadian Cinema &amp; Television |accessdate=2009-03-31}}&lt;/ref&gt; twelve [[Leo Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.leoawards.com/past_winners.html |title=Past Winners |publisher=[[Leo Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and five [[Saturn Awards]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.saturnawards.org/past.html |title=Saturn Awards – Past Award Winners |publisher=[[Saturn Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-244}}&lt;/ref&gt; out of over thirty nominations each. ''Stargate SG-1'' was also nominated for two [[VES Award]]s in 2003 and 2005&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vesawards.com/awards/history/1.html |title=1st Annual VES Awards Nominees and Recipients |publisher=[[VES Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vesawards.com/awards/history/3.html |title=3rd Annual VES Awards Nominees and Recipients |publisher=[[VES Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; and for two [[Hugo Award]]s in 2005 and 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thehugoawards.org/?page_id=12 |title=2005 Hugo Awards |publisher=[[Hugo Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thehugoawards.org/?page_id=127 |title=2007 Hugo Awards |publisher=[[Hugo Awards]] |accessdate=2009-03-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fandom===
[[File:Stargate SG-1 SG team Dragon Con 2008 cropped.jpg|thumb|Fans costuming as SG teams at Dragon Con in 2008]]
{{Main|Stargate fandom}}
Brad Wright used the term &quot;Gaters&quot; to refer to fans of ''Stargate SG-1'' in 2001,&lt;ref name=dvdbeyond&gt;{{cite video |people=[[Brad Wright|Wright, Brad]]; [[Jonathan Glassner|Glassner, John]]; [[Paul Mullie|Mullie, Paul]]; [[Stuart Tyson Smith|Smith, Stuart T.]]; Giannazzo, Tom |date=2001 |title=Stargate SG-1: Season 3 – Timeline To The Future – Part 3: Beyond The Gate | medium = DVD |publisher=[[MGM Home Entertainment]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the term did not become widespread. Some fans' belief that there was a real Stargate device under Cheyenne Mountain inspired writers Joseph Mallozzi and Paul Mullie to come up with their own conspiracy story for season 4's &quot;[[Point of No Return (Stargate SG-1)|Point of No Return]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=dvdbeyond/&gt; The fansite [[GateWorld]] became a major franchise news site with special arrangements with MGM; GateWorld's founder Darren Sumner was later hired to serve as a news editor for the official ''Stargate SG-1'' magazine and to check ''Stargate'' comic books for continuity errors with the TV shows before publication.&lt;ref&gt;Storm 2005, pp. 81–86.&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Late Night with Conan O'Brien]]'' graphic designer [[Pierre Bernard (comedian)|Pierre Bernard]] gained notoriety among ''Stargate'' fans for devoting several of his &quot;Recliner of Rage&quot; ''Late Night'' segments to ''SG-1''. The producers invited him to make cameo appearances in the episodes &quot;[[Zero Hour (Stargate SG-1)|Zero Hour]]&quot; and &quot;[[200 (Stargate SG-1)|200]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/09/iconan_obrieni_notes_istargatei_.shtml |title=Conan O'Brien notes Stargate cancellation |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=September 9, 2006 |accessdate=2009-04-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until 2005, Gatecon was the main ''SG-1'' fan convention. It was held in the Vancouver area, with more actor and crew member participation than other conventions. ''SG-1'' conventions by [[Creation Entertainment]] were also marketed as &quot;The Official ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Stargate Atlantis'' Tour&quot;, which mostly took place in the United States until Creation Entertainment acquired the license for Vancouver conventions in 2005. Wolf Events organized many ''SG-1'' conventions in Europe, particularly in the UK and Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Storm 2005, pp. 93–95.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Merchandise===
{{Main|Stargate literature|Stargate games}}
''Stargate SG-1'' spawned an industry of spin-off products. From 1999 to 2001, [[ROC (publisher)|ROC]] published four ''Stargate SG-1'' novels written by [[Ashley McConnell]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/archive/001014_2.shtml |title=Publisher cancels SG-1 novel series |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=October 14, 2000 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, UK-based [[Fandemonium (publisher)|Fandemonium Press]] launched a new series of licensed tie-in novels based on ''Stargate SG-1'', although these books were unavailable in North America until 2006 when the license conflict with ROC expired.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2006/06/fandemonium_novels_coming_to_u.s.shtml |title=Fandemonium novels coming to U.S. |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=June 6, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Titan Publishing publishes the official ''Stargate Magazine'',&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; while [[Avatar Press]] published a [[List of Stargate comics|series of ''Stargate SG-1'' comics]].&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; British company [[Big Finish Productions]] began to produce [[List of Stargate audiobooks|''Stargate SG-1'' audio adventures]] in early 2008, voiced by members of the ''SG-1'' cast.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.bigfinish.com/news/STARGATE-SG-1-AND-STARGATE-ATLANTIS |title=Stargate SG-1 and Stargate Atlantis: The Gate is still open, the missions continue |date=February 25, 2008 |publisher=bigfinish.com |accessdate=2008-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Stargate SG-1 (roleplaying game)|''Stargate SG-1'' roleplaying game]] and a [[Stargate TCG|''Stargate'' trading card game]] were released in 2003 and 2007. Diamond Select Toys and [[Hasbro]] launched a series of toys in 2005 and 2006, respectively.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Sumner |first=Darren |url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2005/10/sg-1_atlantis_action_figures_in_.shtml |title=SG-1, Atlantis action figures in the works |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=October 12, 2005 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.theforce.net/latestnews/story/Hasbro%E2%80%99s_Plans_For_2006_95314.asp |title=Hasbro's Plans For 2006 |publisher=theforce.net |date=October 18, 2005 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The planned video game ''[[Stargate SG-1: The Alliance]]'' was cancelled in 2005, and the futures of the [[MMORPG]] ''[[Stargate Worlds]]'', and the Third Person Shooter from the same studio (Cheyenne Mountain Entertainment) named ''[[Stargate Resistance]]'' were made clear in November 2010 following MGM's decision not to renew CME's Stargate license. Four amusement rides are based on ''Stargate''&amp;nbsp;– the [[Stargate SG-3000]] theme park ride operating at Space Park [[Bremen]] in Germany, and at [[Six Flags]] theme parks in [[Chicago]], [[San Francisco]] and [[Louisville, Kentucky|Louisville]].&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt;

===Legacy===
{{Quote box | quote=&quot;We were off the radar for so long. [...] We were like the slowly burning candle. We're not a huge hit by any means. We're a nice little show that does well and makes MGM a lot of money.&quot;| source = Creator [[Brad Wright]] in 2006&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; | width =250px | align =right}}
''Stargate SG-1'' spawned the live-action spin-off TV series ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', the animated ''[[Stargate Infinity]]'' and the second live-action spin-off ''[[Stargate Universe]]''. By ''SG-1''{{'s}} tenth season in 2006, ''Stargate SG-1'' and ''Stargate Atlantis'' were said to have brought US$500 million in production to British Columbia.&lt;ref name=vs_success&gt;{{cite web |last=Andrews |first=Marke |url=http://www2.canada.com/vancouversun/news/business/story.html?id=8cadeca7-c0a8-403f-b6d6-7c1f728a9aa7&amp;k=25558 |title=Stargate's success is out of this world |publisher=''[[The Vancouver Sun]]'' |date=April 8, 2006 |accessdate=2009-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; MGM executive vice president Charles Cohen described ''Stargate SG-1'' and its spinoff series as the television counterpart of their ''[[James Bond]]'' franchise, being very profitable and improving their image.&lt;ref name=mcn_200/&gt;

According to Stan Beeler and Lisa Dickson in their 2005 book ''Reading Stargate SG-1'', the only science fiction shows to exceed the staying power of ''SG-1'' are ''[[Doctor Who]]'' and the ''[[Star Trek]]'' franchise, although ''[[The X-Files]]'' and ''[[Buffy (TV series)|Buffy]]''/''[[Angel (TV series)|Angel]]'' might have comparable longevity.&lt;ref name=beeler_intro/&gt; Brad Wright cited continuity in the creative team and fan loyalty as reasons for the show's longevity.&lt;ref name=vs_success/&gt; With its 202nd episode, &quot;[[Company of Thieves (Stargate SG-1)|Company of Thieves]]&quot;, ''Stargate SG-1'' surpassed ''The X-Files'' as the longest-running North American science fiction series on television, before being overtaken by the [[Superman]]-inspired series ''[[Smallville]]'' in 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|author=Sumner, Darren|url=http://www.gateworld.net/news/2011/05/smallville-bows-this-week-with-stargates-world-record/ |title=Smallville bows this week — with Stargate's world record |publisher=[[GateWorld]] |date=May 10, 2011 |accessdate=May 11, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Doctor Who'' fans dispute ''SG-1''{{'s}} listing in the 2007 [[Guinness World Records]] as the &quot;longest-running science fiction show (consecutive)&quot;, as 694 episodes of the British show were produced and shown consecutively between 1963 and 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;record&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/doctorwho/news/cult/news/drwho/2006/09/23/36558.shtml |title=Record breaker? |publisher=[[BBC News]] |accessdate=2006-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/5390372.stm |title=Dr Who 'longest-running sci-fi' |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=September 28, 2006 |accessdate=2006-09-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''Stargate SG-1'' ranked #28 on ''[[TV Guide]]''{{'}}s Top Cult Shows Ever.&lt;ref name=&quot;top cult&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tvguide.com/news/top-cult-shows-40239.aspx |title=TV Guide Names the Top Cult Shows Ever |publisher=''[[TV Guide]]'' |date=June 29, 2007 |accessdate=2008-11-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, ''SG-1'' and ''Atlantis'' shared the number four spot in a poll about the &quot;most popular cult TV shows&quot; on the British ''Cult TV'' website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/entertainment/tv_and_radio/4102754.stm |title=Doctor Who named 'top cult show' |publisher=[[BBC News]] |date=June 17, 2005 |accessdate=2009-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''SG-1'' was also included in the list of &quot;17 All-Time Great Cult TV Shows You Say We Missed&quot; by ''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.ew.com/ew/gallery/0,,20311716_6,00.html |title=17 All-Time Great Cult TV Shows You Say We Missed |publisher=''[[Entertainment Weekly]]'' |date=|accessdate=2009-10-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The astronomers [[David J. Tholen]] and [[Roy A. Tucker]] enjoyed the ''SG-1'' arch villain [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] so much that they named their discovered [[near-Earth asteroid]] &quot;[[99942 Apophis]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Cooke |first=Bill |url=http://www.astronomy.com/asy/default.aspx?c=a&amp;id=3434 |title=Asteroid Apophis set for a makeover |publisher=''[[Astronomy Magazine]]'' |date=August 18, 2005 |accessdate=2009-04-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==

{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book |last = Beeler | first = Stan |editor=Telotte, J.P | title = The Essential Science Fiction Television Reader |chapter=Stargate SG-1 and The Quest For The Perfect Science Fiction Premise | publisher = [[University Press of Kentucky]] | location = United States | url =http://books.google.com/?id=cFQicvXd5bwC&amp;printsec=frontcover | isbn = 0813124921 |pages = 370 |date = 2008-05 }}
* {{cite book |editor= Beeler, Stanley W. and Dickson, Lisa | title = Reading Stargate SG-1 | publisher = [[I.B. Tauris]] | location = London | year = 2005 | url = http://books.google.com/?id=MO30KAzBb_MC&amp;printsec=frontcover | isbn = 978-1845111830 |pages= 308 |date= 2006-07-11 }}
* {{cite book |last=Booker |first=M. Keith |title=Science Fiction Television |publisher=[[Praeger Publishing]] |url=http://books.google.com/?id=WyJf3m1G0ksC&amp;printsec=frontcover |year=2004 |isbn = 0275981649 |pages=238 }}
* {{cite book |last=Gibson |first=Thomasina |title=Stargate SG-1: The Illustrated Companion Seasons 5 and 6 |year=2003 |publisher=Titan Books |location=London |isbn=978-1840236064 }}
* {{cite book | last = Storm | first = Jo | title = Approaching the Possible: The World of Stargate SG-1 | publisher = [[ECW Press]] | location = Toronto, Canada | url = http://books.google.com/?id=T196lU-jXI8C | isbn = 1-55022-705-X | pages = 534 | date = 2005-12-06 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
&lt;!--WARNING; PLEASE READ BEFORE EDITING; do not link the MGM Stargate Video site, as it will be deleted should someone add it again.--&gt;
{{commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
* {{official website|http://stargate.mgm.com/view/series/1/index.html}} at [[MGM|mgm.com]]
* {{official website|http://syfy.com/stargate/}} at [[SyFy (United States)|syfy.com]]
* {{IMDb title|118480}}
* {{wikia|stargate|Stargate Wiki|Stargate SG1|''Stargate SG-1''}}
* [http://www.gateworld.net/sg1/ ''Stargate SG-1'' episode guide] at [[GateWorld]]

{{Stargate}}
{{Saturn Award for Best Syndicated/Cable Television Series}}
{{ShowtimeNetwork Shows}}
{{Science fiction}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stargate Sg-1}}
[[Category:1997 American television series debuts]]
[[Category:2007 American television series endings]]
[[Category:1990s American television series]]
[[Category:2000s American television series]]
[[Category:CTV Two network shows]]
[[Category:American science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Ancient Egypt in fiction]]
[[Category:Canadian science fiction television series]]
[[Category:Citytv network shows]]
[[Category:English-language television series]]
[[Category:Syfy original programs]]
[[Category:Showtime (TV network) original programs]]
[[Category:Stargate|SG-1]]
[[Category:Television programs based on films]]
[[Category:Television series by MGM Television]]
[[Category:Television series produced in Vancouver]]
[[Category:Television shows set in Colorado]]
[[Category:Wormholes in fiction]]
[[Category:Space adventure television series]]

{{Link FA|bs}}
&lt;!-- interwiki --&gt;

[[ar:ستارغيت إس جي 1 (مسلسل)]]
[[bar:Stargate – Kommando SG-1]]
[[bs:Stargate SG-1]]
[[br:Stargate SG-1]]
[[bg:Старгейт (сериал)]]
[[ca:Stargate SG-1]]
[[cs:Hvězdná brána (seriál)]]
[[da:Stargate SG-1]]
[[de:Stargate – Kommando SG-1]]
[[et:Tähevärav SG-1#Sarja tootmine]]
[[es:Stargate SG-1]]
[[eo:Stargate SG-1]]
[[fa:دروازه ستارگان اس‌جی-۱]]
[[fr:Stargate SG-1]]
[[ko:스타게이트 SG-1]]
[[hr:Zvjezdana vrata SG-1]]
[[it:Stargate SG-1]]
[[he:סטארגייט SG-1]]
[[ka:ვარსკვლავთკარიბჭე SG-1]]
[[lv:Zvaigžņu Vārti SG-1]]
[[lt:Žvaigždžių vartai SG-1]]
[[hu:Csillagkapu (televíziós sorozat)]]
[[mn:Stargate SG-1]]
[[nl:Stargate SG-1 (televisieserie)]]
[[ja:スターゲイト SG-1]]
[[no:Stargate SG-1]]
[[pl:Gwiezdne wrota (serial telewizyjny)]]
[[pt:Stargate SG-1]]
[[ro:Stargate SG-1]]
[[ru:Звёздные врата: SG-1]]
[[simple:Stargate SG-1]]
[[sk:Hviezdna brána (seriál)]]
[[sl:Zvezdna vrata SG-1]]
[[sh:Stargate SG-1]]
[[fi:Tähtiportti]]
[[sv:Stargate SG-1]]
[[tr:Yıldız Geçidi SG-1]]
[[uk:Зоряна брама: SG-1]]
[[zh:星際之門：SG-1]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
