<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="38420" ns="0" title="Johns Hopkins University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|image_name=Johns Hopkins University seal.svg
|image_size=200px
|caption = Official Seal
|name=The Johns Hopkins University
|motto=''[[Veritas vos liberabit|Veritas vos Liberabit]]'' ([[Latin]])
|mottoeng=The Truth Will Set You Free
|established=1876
|type=[[Private university|Private]]
|calendar=Quarter
|president=[[Ronald J. Daniels]]|
|provost=[[Lloyd B. Minor]]|
|city=[[Baltimore, Maryland]]
|state=
|country=[[United States|U.S.]]
|faculty=3,100 (full time)&lt;ref name=JHU_Glance&gt;{{cite web|title=At a Glance|url=http://www.johnshopkins.edu/glance/index.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2008-04-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|staff=15,000 (full time)&lt;ref name=JHU_Glance/&gt;
|undergrad=4,744&lt;ref name=JHU_Fastfacts&gt;{{cite news|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|title=Hopkins Admissions|date=2007-03-05|accessdate=2008-04-15|url= http://apply.jhu.edu/facts/facts.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|postgrad=14,275&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.jhu.edu/administration/provost/pura/images/pdf/JHUFactSheet2007-08.pdf JHU.edu]{{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|campus= [[Maryland|State of Maryland (MD)]]
*[[Baltimore]] (Main)
*[[Laurel, Maryland|Laurel]]
*[[Columbia, Maryland|Columbia]]
*[[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]]
[[Washington, D.C.]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Bologna, Italy|Bologna]], [[Italy]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Nanjing, China|Nanjing]], [[China]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Singapore]]
|colors=[[Old Gold]] &amp; [[Sable (heraldry)|Sable]]&lt;br /&gt;{{color box|#CFB53B}} {{color box|black}} ([[Academic]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Columbia Blue]] &amp; [[Black]]&lt;br /&gt; {{color box|#9BDDFF}} {{color box|black}} ([[College athletics|Athletic]])
|nickname=[[Johns Hopkins Blue Jays|Blue Jays]]
|athletics=[[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] [[Lacrosse]]&lt;br /&gt;[[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]] &lt;br /&gt;[[Centennial Conference]]
|endowment=[[United States dollar|US $]]2.22 [[1000000000 (number)|billion]] (2010)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = 2010 NACUBO Endowment Study  | publisher = National Association of College and University Business Officers  | url = http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2010NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values_Final.pdf  | format = PDF  | accessdate = February 17, 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|nobel_laureates=32&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Nobel Prize Winners|url= http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/facts_and_statistics/nobel_prize_winners/index.cfm|author=jhu.edu|year=2007|accessdate=2007-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|website=[http://www.jhu.edu/ jhu.edu]
|logo= [[File:Hopkinslogo2.png|The Johns Hopkins University Logo]]
}}
'''The Johns Hopkins University''',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About The Johns Hopkins University|publisher=The Johns Hopkins University|url= http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/|accessdate=2010-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; commonly referred to as '''Johns Hopkins''', '''JHU''', or simply '''Hopkins''', is a [[private university|private]] [[research university]] based in [[Baltimore]], [[Maryland]], [[United States]]. Johns Hopkins maintains campuses in [[Maryland]], [[Washington, D.C.]], [[Italy]], [[China]] and [[Singapore]].

The university was founded on January 22, 1876 and named for its benefactor, the [[philanthropist]] [[Johns Hopkins]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The is Only One Johns Hopkins|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/featured/history/}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Coit Gilman]] was inaugurated as first [[chancellor (education)#United States|president]] on February 22, 1876.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Inaugural Address of Daniel Coit Gilman|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/about_jhu/daniel_coit_gilman/}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Johns Hopkins pioneered the concept of the modern research university in the United States and has ranked among the world's top such universities throughout its history. The [[National Science Foundation]] (NSF) has ranked Johns Hopkins #1 among U.S. academic institutions in total science, medical and [[engineering]] [[research and development]] spending for 31 consecutive years.&lt;ref name=nsf09&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.nsf.gov/statistics/infbrief/nsf10329/|title=Universities Report $55 Billion in Science and Engineering R&amp;D Spending for FY 2009; Redesigned Survey to Launch in 2010|publisher=National Science Foundation|first=Ronda|last= Britt|date=September 2010|accessdate=2010-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;  As of 2011, thirty-seven [[Nobel Prize]] winners have been affiliated with Johns Hopkins,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Johns Hopkins University|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/facts_and_statistics/nobel_prize_winners/index.cfm}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the university's research is among the most cited in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScienceWatch.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url= http://sciencewatch.com/inter/ins/09/09Top20Overall/ |title=2009 The Most-Cited Institutions Overall, 1999–2009  |publisher=ScienceWatch.com |year=2009 |accessdate=2009-09-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===The philanthropist and the founding===
{{See also|Johns_Hopkins#Death_and_Philanthropy|l1=Johns Hopkins' Philanthropy and Legacy}}
[[File:Hopkinsp.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Johns Hopkins]]]]

On his death in 1873, [[Johns Hopkins]], a [[Quaker]] [[entrepreneur]] and childless bachelor, bequeathed $7 million to fund a hospital and university in Baltimore, Maryland.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.jhu.edu/%7Egazette/1999/jan0499/obit.html] Obituary, Baltimore Sun, December 25, 1873 in Johns Hopkins Gazette, Jan. 4, 1999,v. 28,no. 16&lt;/ref&gt; At that time this fortune, generated primarily from the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Who Was Johns Hopkins?|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/about_jhu/who_was_johns_hopkins/}}&lt;/ref&gt; was the largest philanthropic gift in the history of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Facts at a Glance|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/about_jhu/facts_at_a_glance/index.cfm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first name of philanthropist Johns Hopkins is the surname of his great-grandmother, Margaret Johns, who married Gerard Hopkins. They named their son Johns Hopkins, who named his own son Samuel Hopkins. Samuel named one of his sons after his father and that son would be the university's benefactor.

In his 2001 undergraduate commencement address, university president [[William R. Brody]] said about the name: &quot;In 1888, just 12 years after the university was founded, [[Mark Twain]] wrote about this university in a letter to a friend. He said: 'A few months ago I was told that the Johns Hopkins University had given me a degree. I naturally supposed this constituted me a Member of the Faculty and so I started in to help as I could there. I told them I believed they were perfectly competent to run a college as far as the higher branches of education are concerned, but what they needed was a little help here and there from a practical commercial man. I said the public is sensitive to little things and they wouldn't have full confidence in a college that didn't know how to spell the name ''John''.' More than a century later, we continue to bestow diplomas upon individuals of outstanding capabilities and great talent. And we continue to spell ''Johns'' with an ''s''.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Commencement 2001|author=Headlines@Hopkins|accessdate=2007-02-14|url= http://www.jhu.edu/news/commence01/wrb.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Milton Eisenhower]], once the university' president, once spoke to a convention in [[Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|Pittsburgh]]. Making a common mistake, the [[Master of Ceremonies]] introduced him as &quot;President of ''John''&lt;!--[sic]---&gt; Hopkins.&quot; Eisenhower retorted that he was &quot;glad to be here in ''Pitt''burgh.&lt;!--[sic]---&gt;&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/local/bal-md.vozzella15dec15,0,7196427.column?coll=bal-home-columnists|title=Cheesecake on the Tart Side|author=Laura Vozzella|publisher=The Baltimore Sun|date=2006-12-15|accessdate=2007-01-10 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070320152617/http://www.baltimoresun.com/news/local/bal-md.vozzella15dec15,0,7196427.column?coll=bal-home-columnists |archivedate = March 20, 2007}}: &quot;University spokesman Dennis O'Shea checked with Ross Jones, who was Eisenhower's assistant. And Jones confirmed it... Ross told O'Shea: 'I remember him telling me about it first thing after he got back. He was tickled with himself for picking up on it so quickly with that response. And then it became a legend! He would love the fact that it still has legs.'&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early years and Daniel Coit Gilman===
The original board opted for an entirely novel university model dedicated to the discovery of knowledge at an advanced level, extending that of contemporary Germany. Johns Hopkins thereby became the model of the modern research university in the United States. Its success eventually shifted higher education in the United States from a focus on teaching revealed and/or applied knowledge to the scientific discovery of new knowledge. The university was intended to be national in scope to strengthen ties across a divided country in the aftermath of the [[American Civil War]]. Therefore, the university's official inauguration took on great significance: 1876 was the nation's centennial year and February 22 was [[George Washington]]'s birthday.{{Wikisource1911Enc|Johns Hopkins University|the Early History}}

The University's viability depended on its first president, [[Daniel Coit Gilman]], recruited from the presidency of the [[University of California]]. Gilman launched what many at the time considered to be an audacious and unprecedented academic experiment to merge teaching and research. He dismissed the idea that the two were mutually exclusive: &quot;The best teachers are usually those who are free, competent and willing to make original researches in the library and the laboratory,&quot; he stated. To implement his plan, Gilman recruited internationally known luminaries such as the biologist [[H. Newell Martin]]; the physicist [[Henry Augustus Rowland|Henry A. Rowland]] (the first president of the [[American Physical Society]]), the [[classical scholars]] [[Basil Gildersleeve]] and Charles D. Morris;&lt;ref&gt;The Johns Hopkins University Circular 1886, p.65&lt;/ref&gt; the economist [[Richard T. Ely]]; and the chemist [[Ira Remsen]], who became the second president of the university in 1901.
[[File:Daniel Coit Gilman.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Daniel Coit Gilman]]]]

Gilman focused on the expansion of knowledge, graduate education and support of faculty research. To Gilman, Johns Hopkins existed not for the sake of God, the state, the community, the board, the parents, or even the students, but for knowledge. Faculty who added to such knowledge were rewarded. A complementary focus on [[graduate education]] fused advanced scholarship with such professional schools as medicine and engineering. Hopkins became the national trendsetter in [[PhD|doctoral]] programs and the host for numerous [[scholarly journal]]s and associations with the founding of the first [[university press]] in 1878.

With the completion of [[Johns Hopkins Hospital]] in 1889 and the [[medical school]] in 1893, the university's research–focused mode of instruction soon began attracting world-renowned faculty members who would become major figures in the emerging field of academic medicine, including [[William Osler]], [[William Halsted]], [[Howard Kelly]], and [[William H. Welch|William Welch]]. During this period Hopkins made more history by becoming the first medical school to admit women on an equal basis with men and to require a [[Bachelors degree]], based on the efforts of [[Mary Garrett|Mary E. Garrett]], who had endowed the school at Gilman's request.

In his will and in his instructions to the trustees of the university and the hospital, Hopkins requested that both institutions be built upon the vast grounds of his Baltimore estate, Clifton. When Gilman assumed the presidency, he decided that it would be best to use the university's endowment for recruiting faculty and students, deciding to &quot;build men, not buildings.&quot; In his will Hopkins stipulated that none of his endowment should be used for construction; only interest on the principal could be used for this purpose. Unfortunately, stocks in The [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] from which most of the interest would have been generated became virtually worthless soon after Hopkins's death. The university's first home was thus in Downtown [[Baltimore]] delaying plans to site the university in Clifton. This decision became the only major criticism of Gilman's presidency. In the early 1900s the university outgrew its buildings and the trustees began to search for a new home. Developing Clifton for the university was too costly, and so the estate became a public park. In the end, the {{convert|140|acre}} estate in north Baltimore known as [[Homewood campus|Homewood]] was purchased as the university's new campus with assistance from prominent Baltimore citizens.

Since the 1910s, Johns Hopkins University has famously been a &quot;fertile cradle&quot; to [[Arthur Lovejoy]]'s [[history of ideas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Paulson1970&quot;&gt;[[Ronald Paulson]] [http://www.jstor.org/pss/468272 ''English Literary History at the Johns Hopkins University''] in ''New Literary History'', Vol. 1, No. 3, History and Fiction (Spring, 1970), pp. 559-564&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:10px&quot;
|+Presidents of the university
!Name!!Term
|-
|[[Daniel Coit Gilman]]|| May 1875 – August 1901
|-
|[[Ira Remsen]]|| September 1901 – January 1913
|-
|[[Frank Goodnow]]|| October 1914 – June 1929
|-
|[[Joseph Sweetman Ames]]|| July 1929 – June 1935
|-
|[[Isaiah Bowman]]|| July 1935 – December 1948
|-
|[[Detlev Bronk]]|| January 1949 – August 1953
|-
|[[Lowell Reed]]|| September 1953 – June 1956
|-
|[[Milton S. Eisenhower]]|| July 1956 – June 1967
|-
|[[Lincoln Gordon]]|| July 1967 – March 1971
|-
|[[Milton S. Eisenhower]]|| March 1971 – January 1972
|-
|[[Steven Muller]]|| February 1972 – June 1990
|-
|[[William C. Richardson]]|| July 1990 – July 1995
|-
|[[Daniel Nathans]]|| June 1995 – August 1996
|-
|[[William R. Brody]]|| August 1996 – February 2009
|-
|[[Ronald J. Daniels]]|| March 2009–Present
|}

===Institutions===
The [[Johns Hopkins University Press]], founded in 1878, is the oldest American [[university press]] in continuous operation. Along with the hospital, Hopkins established one of the nation's oldest [[Johns Hopkins School of Nursing|schools of nursing]] in 1889. The [[Johns Hopkins School of Medicine|school of medicine]] was the nation's first coeducational, graduate-level medical school and the prototype for academic medicine which emphasized bedside learning, research projects, and laboratory training. In 1909, the university was among the first to start adult [[continuing education]] programs and in 1916 it founded the US' first [[Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health|school of public health]]. Programs in international studies and the performing arts were established in 1950 and 1977 when the [[Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies]] in Washington D.C and the [[Peabody Institute]] in Baltimore became divisions of the university.

===Civil rights===
====African-Americans====
Hopkins was a prominent [[abolitionist]] who supported [[Abraham Lincoln]] during the [[American Civil War]]. After his death his conviction was reported to be a decisive factor in enrolling Hopkins' first [[African-American]] student, [[Kelly Miller (scientist)|Kelly Miller]], a graduate student in physics, astronomy and mathematics, and in admitting Harvard-trained physician Whitfield Winsey and two other African-American physicians to Maryland's Medical and Chirurgical Society [[MedChi]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mdhistoryonline.net/mdmedicine/cfm/dsp_detail.cfm?id=1895 MDhistoryonline.net], Medicine in Maryland 1752–1920&lt;/ref&gt; These physicians could attend meetings only because they were held on campus. As the memory of Hopkins faded and trustees like King died, Hopkins became like other Baltimore institutions, particularly in terms of race. The Johns Hopkins University chronology stated that on March 15, 1892, an administrator hired by Gilman recommended that the hospital should have a &quot;separate ward for colored patients&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;webapps.jhu.edu&quot;&gt;[http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/about_jhu/chronology/index.cfmChronology JHU.edu]{{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johns Hopkins Hospital subsequently became a segregated facility. Johns Hopkins' &quot;separate but equal&quot; stance was evident when it came to these segregated wards: &quot;Special care will be taken to see that the heating and ventilation apparatus is as perfect as possible. A sun balcony will be erected on each floor on the east side, for convalescents, while a sun bay-window will be constructed at the south end of the south wing. On each floor there will be a dining room, kitchen, lavatory and bath-rooms...The building will be [[fireproof]] throughout.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;webapps.jhu.edu&quot;/&gt;

As segregation grew within Johns Hopkins institutions, it affected pay, hiring and promotions. Staff in segregated wards and those employed in the lower rungs of the service industries had the longest history within the Johns Hopkins Institutions. Johns Hopkins' students, physicians, administrators and staff of African descent had a much shorter history within these institutions.
The first black undergraduate was [[Frederick Scott]] who entered the school in 1945. In 1967 the first black students earned graduate degrees. Dr. James Nabwangu a British-trained [[Kenya]]n, was the first black graduate of the medical school. A second was earned by Robert Gamble.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/hmn/w98/sea.html |title=In a Sea of White Faces |publisher=Hopkinsmedicine.org |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first African-American instructor was laboratory supervisor [[Vivien Thomas]], who also invented and developed research instruments, served as an assistant in surgery to surgeon [[Alfred Blalock]] and worked closely with Blalock and [[Helen Taussig]] in developing and conducting the first successful [[blue baby syndrome|blue baby operation]]. Black students and professionals were rare at Johns Hopkins Institutions and Maryland's state medical societies until after the 1940s. Diversity increased only in the 1960s and 1970s. African-Americans and women were labeled &quot;The Uninvited&quot; in the second major history of the university.{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}

====Women====
Hopkins' most well–known battle for women's rights was the one led by daughters of trustees of the university; [[Mary Garrett|Mary E. Garrett]], [[M. Carey Thomas]], Mamie Gwinn, Elizabeth King, and Julia Rogers.&lt;ref name=women&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/~jhumag/1107web/women2.html |title=&quot;A Timeline of Women at Hopkins&quot; |publisher=Jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; They donated and raised the funds needed to open the medical school, and required Hopkins' officials to agree to their stipulation that women would be admitted. Unfortunately, this stipulation applied only to the medical school. Other graduate schools were opened to women by president [[Ira Remsen]] only in 1907. [[Christine Ladd-Franklin]] was the first woman to earn a [[PhD]] at Hopkins, in mathematics in 1882. The trustees denied her the degree and refused to change the policy about admitting women; she finally received her degree 44 years later. In 1893 Florence Bascomb became the university's first female PhD.&lt;ref name=women/&gt;

The [[nursing school]] opened in 1889 and accepted women and men as students.

The decision to admit women at undergraduate level was not considered until the late 1960s and was eventually adopted in October 1969; in the fall of 1970, 90 females, five of them African-American, became undergraduates. In the academic year 1970–1971, 4.7% of students in the Arts and Sciences programs were women. In the year 1985–1986 the proportion of female students in the Arts and Sciences programs had increased to around 38%. As of 2009–2010, the undergraduate population was 47% female and 53% male.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://members.ucan-network.org/jhu |publisher=Ucan-network.org]|title= Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campuses==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;font-size:90%; width:100%; border:0; text-align:center; line-height:120%;&quot;
|-
!colspan=&quot;10&quot;|'''Main Campuses &amp; Divisions'''
|-
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0;&quot;|'''[[#Homewood|Homewood]]'''
| colspan=&quot;3&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0;&quot;|'''[[#East Baltimore|East Baltimore]]'''&lt;br/&gt;(Medical Institutions Campus)
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0;&quot;|'''[[#Downtown Baltimore|Downtown Baltimore]]'''
| style=&quot;border-bottom:0;&quot;|'''[[#Washington, D.C.|Washington D.C.]]'''
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;border-bottom:0;&quot;|'''[[#Laurel, Maryland|Laurel, Maryland]]'''
|-
|[[Zanvyl Krieger School of Arts and Sciences|School of Arts and Sciences]]&lt;br/&gt;1876
|[[Johns Hopkins University School of Education|School of Education]]&lt;br/&gt;1909
|[[Whiting School of Engineering|School of Engineering]]&lt;br/&gt;1913
|[[Johns Hopkins School of Nursing|School of Nursing]]&lt;br/&gt;1889
|[[Johns Hopkins School of Medicine|School of Medicine]]&lt;br/&gt;1893
|[[Bloomberg School of Public Health|School of Public Health]]&lt;br/&gt;1916
|[[Peabody Institute]]&lt;br/&gt;1857
|[[Carey Business School|School of Business]]&lt;br/&gt;2007
|[[Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies|School of Advanced International Studies]]&lt;br/&gt;1943
|[[Applied Physics Laboratory]]&lt;br/&gt;1942
|}

===Homewood===
{{Main|Homewood Campus of Johns Hopkins University}}
[[File:JHU-H.jpg|thumb|200px|alt=Homewood House|&lt;center&gt;Homewood House&lt;/center&gt;]]
*'''[[Zanvyl Krieger School of Arts and Sciences]]''': The Krieger School offers more than 60 undergraduate majors and minors and more than 40 graduate programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Krieger School of Arts &amp; Sciences|url=http://www.krieger.jhu.edu/about/history.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|year=2006|accessdate=2006-12-06 |archiveurl =http://web.archive.org/web/20061126185452/http://www.krieger.jhu.edu/about/history.html |archivedate = November 26, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Whiting School of Engineering|G.W.C. Whiting School of Engineering]]''': The Whiting School contains 14 undergraduate and graduate engineering programs and 12 additional areas of study.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Departments &amp; Areas of Study|url=http://eng.jhu.edu/wse/page/departments-study|work=Johns Hopkins University Whiting School of Engineering|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Johns Hopkins University School of Education|School of Education]]''': Originally established in 1909 as The School of Professional Studies in Business and Education, the divisions of Education and Business became separate schools in 2007.

The first campus was located on Howard Street. Eventually, they relocated to Homewood, in northern Baltimore, the estate of Charles Carroll, son of the oldest surviving signer of the [[United States Declaration of Independence|Declaration of Independence]]. Carroll's [[Homewood House]] is considered to be one of the finest examples of Federal residential architecture. The estate then came to the Wyman family, which participated in making it the park-like main campus of the schools of arts and sciences and engineering at the turn of the 20th century. Most of its architecture was modeled after the [[Federal architecture|Federal style]] of [[Homewood House]]. Homewood House is preserved as a museum. Most undergraduate programs are here.{{-}}

===East Baltimore===
[[File:Hopkins hospital.jpg|right|thumb|200px|&lt;center&gt;Johns Hopkins Hospital&lt;/center&gt;]]
Collectively known as Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions (JHMI) campus, the East Baltimore facility occupies several city blocks spreading from the [[Johns Hopkins Hospital]] trademark dome.
*'''[[Johns Hopkins School of Nursing|School of Nursing]]''': The School of Nursing is is one of America's oldest and pre-eminent schools for nursing education. It has consistently ranked first in the nation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/nur/search |title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Nursing Graduate Schools Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2011 |accessdate=2011-06-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Johns Hopkins School of Medicine|School of Medicine]]''': The School of Medicine is widely regarded as one of the best medical schools and [[biomedical research]] institutes in the world.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-biological-sciences-programs/rankings|title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Biological Sciences Graduate Schools Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2010 |accessdate=2010-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools/research-rankings|title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Medical School Research Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report|year=2010 |accessdate=2010-10-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*'''[[Bloomberg School of Public Health]]''': The Bloomberg School was founded in 1916, the world's first and largest public health school. It has consistently been ranked first in its field.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/pub/search |title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Public Health Graduate Schools Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2008|accessdate=2009-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{-}}

===Downtown Baltimore===
[[File:Peabody Institute, Mount Vernon Place, Baltimore, MD.jpg|right|thumb|200px|&lt;center&gt;Peabody Institute&lt;/center&gt;]]
*'''[[Carey Business School]]''': The Carey Business School was established in 2007, incorporating divisions of the former School of Professional Studies in Business and Education. It was originally located on [[Maryland Route 139|Charles Street]], but relocated to the Legg Mason building in Harbor East in 2011.
*'''[[Peabody Institute]]''': founded in 1857, is the US' oldest continuously active music conservatory; it became a division of Johns Hopkins in 1977. The Conservatory retains its own student body and grants degrees in musicology and performance, though both Hopkins and Peabody students may take courses at both institutions. It is located on East Mount Vernon Place.{{-}}

===Washington, D.C.===
[[File:SAIS front.jpg|right|thumb|200px|&lt;center&gt;Washington D.C. Campus (SAIS)&lt;/center&gt;]]
*'''[[Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies]] (SAIS)''' is located on the Washington D.C. campus near [[Dupont Circle]]. SAIS is devoted to international studies, particularly [[international relations]], [[diplomacy]], and [[economics]]. SAIS has full-time international campuses in [[Bologna Center|Bologna, Italy]] and [[Hopkins-Nanjing Center|Nanjing, China]]. Founded in 1943, SAIS became a part of the university in 1950. In a 2005 survey 65% of respondents ranked SAIS as the nation's top [[Master's Degree]] program in [[International Relations]].&lt;ref name='saistop'&gt;{{cite web|last=Peterson|first=Susan|coauthors= Michael J. Tierney, Daniel Maliniak|month=August |year=2005|url=http://mjtier.people.wm.edu/intlpolitics/teaching/surveyreport.pdf| title=Teaching and Research Practices, Views on the Discipline, and Policy Attitudes of International Relations Faculty at U.S. Colleges and Universities|format=PDF }}The study's results also appeared in ''[[Foreign Policy (magazine)]]Nov/Dec 2005.''&lt;/ref&gt;
*  [[Zanvyl Krieger School of Arts and Sciences#Advanced Academic Programs|The Krieger School of Arts and Sciences' Advanced Academic Programs (AAP)]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://advanced.jhu.edu/contact/campuses/washington |title=Campuses &amp; Centers – The Washington DC Center |publisher=Advanced.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Carey Business School]]
The Washington, D.C. campus is on [[Massachusetts Avenue (Washington, D.C.)|Massachusetts Avenue]].

===Laurel, Maryland===
[[File:New Horizons LORRI.jpg|right|thumb|200px|&lt;center&gt;Installing a [[New Horizons]] Imager at the APL&lt;/center&gt;]]
*'''[[Applied Physics Laboratory|Johns Hopkins University Applied Physics Laboratory (APL)]]''': The APL in Laurel, Maryland, specializes in research for the [[United States Department of Defense|U.S. Department of Defense]], [[NASA]] and other government and civilian research agencies. It has developed more than 100 biomedical devices, many in collaboration with the Johns Hopkins Medical Institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/125th/links/history.html |title=The 125th Anniversary of The Johns Hopkins University |publisher=Jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also linked to the [[Space Telescope Science Institute]] on the Homewood campus which controls, analyzes, and collects data from the [[Hubble Space Telescope]].

The Applied Physics Laboratory, a division of the university co-equal to the nine schools but with a non-academic mission, lies between Baltimore and Washington in [[Laurel, Maryland|Laurel]], [[Maryland]].

===Other campuses===
: ''see also [[Johns Hopkins University#Research centers and institutes|List of Johns Hopkins University Research Centers and Institutes]]''

====Domestic====
*[[Columbia, Maryland|Columbia, Maryland Center]] (Branches of [[Carey Business School|The Carey Business School]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://onestop.jhu.edu/carey/campuses/columbia-center |title=Columbia Center|publisher=Onestop.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Johns Hopkins University School of Education|The School of Education]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://education.jhu.edu/campuses/columbia|title=School of Education at Johns Hopkins University-Columbia Center |publisher=Education.jhu.edu |date=|accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Montgomery County, Maryland|Montgomery County]], [[Maryland]] Campus (Part-time programs in Biosciences, Engineering, Business &amp; Education&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mcc.jhu.edu |title=index|publisher=Mcc.jhu.edu |date=2010-01-21 |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

====International====
*[[Bologna Center|The SAIS Bologna Center, Italy]]
*[[Hopkins-Nanjing Center|The SAIS Hopkins-Nanjing Center for Chinese and American Studies, China]]
*[[National University of Singapore#Yong Siew Toh Conservatory of Music|Yong Siew Toh Conservatory of Music]] (Collaboration between the [[Peabody Institute]] and the [[National University of Singapore]])

In 2009, JHU ranked fifth among US universities in private fund–raising, collecting [[United States dollar|$]]433.39 million.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cae.org/content/pdf/VSE_2009_Press_Relsease.pdf|title=Contributions to the Nation’s Colleges and Universities Decline in 2009|date=February 3, 2010|publisher=Council for Aid to Education|accessdate=2010–11–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The President is JHU's chief executive officer, and the university is organized into nine academic divisions.&lt;ref name=overview/&gt;

==Campus environmental initiatives==

Johns Hopkins University has implemented a number of [[sustainability]] initiatives.&lt;ref name='2008 JHU Sustainability Initiatives'&gt;{{cite web|title=2008 JHU Sustainability Initiatives|url=http://www.sustainability.jhu.edu/index.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|year=2008|accessdate=2008-05-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, the ''Sustainable Endowments Institute'' gave Johns Hopkins a  College Sustainability Report Card grade of &quot;C+.&quot; In particular the Institute criticized JHU for failing to disclose its endowment's holdings and proxy voting record on environmental issues.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sustainable Endowments Institute Report Card&quot;&gt;{{cite web | title =College Sustainability Report Card 2011 | publisher =Sustainable Endowments Institute | url =http://www.greenreportcard.org/report-card-2011/schools/johns-hopkins-university|accessdate = 2011-11-19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Transportation===
In 2007 carbon emissions were inventoried and electric vehicles were used for some campus transportation needs.

===Food===
As of 2007 dining services managers sought locally–sourced produce and seafood, and integrated organic food into menus.&lt;ref name='2007-sustainability-report' /&gt; In addition, the smaller cafés around campus sell exclusively organic, shade–grown coffees. A small pilot composting program operated on the undergraduate campus.&lt;ref name='2007-sustainability-report' /&gt;

===Buildings===
In 2007 the university was pursuing [[Leadership in Energy and Environmental Design|LEED]] certification for several buildings.&lt;ref name='2007-sustainability-report' /&gt; Energy retrofits in certain buildings have resulted in over 50% less energy consumption.&lt;ref name='2007-sustainability-report'&gt;{{cite web|title=2007 National Sustainability Report|url=http://www.endowmentinstitute.org/sustainability/CollegeSustainabilityReportCard.pdf|publisher=Endowments Institute of America |year=2007|accessdate=2007-01-24|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Retrofits included a green roof, experimentation with waterless [[urinal (restroom)|urinal]]s and low-flow shower heads, and upgraded [[fluorescent]] lighting that reduced electricity for lighting on one campus by over 40 percent. Similar lighting retrofits were underway at all campuses.

===Water===
In 2004, one campus completed a water conservation retrofit that annually saved over {{convert|8000000|usgal|l}} of water.&lt;ref name='2007-sustainability-report' /&gt;

===Student support===
As of 2010 students contributed significantly to environmental initiatives, setting up the JHU recycling program, hosting a national &quot;Greening&quot; conference, launching a transportation shuttle service between campuses and making the campus more bike-friendly.&lt;ref name='2008 JHU Sustainability Initiatives'&gt;{{cite web|title=2008 JHU Sustainability Initiatives|url=http://www.sustainability.jhu.edu/student_groups.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|year=2008|accessdate=2008-05-25}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each year, students conduct the &quot;S.E.X.:I.T.&quot; competition to see which dormitory can save the most electricity.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sustainability.jhu.edu/student%20programs/dorm_competitions.html|title=Dorm Competitions|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Organization==
The Johns Hopkins entity is structured as two corporations, the university and The Johns Hopkins Health System, formed in 1986. The latter has grown to be the bigger entity, with fiscal year 2005 consolidated net revenue of $3.3 billion, employing 27,700 people, including some 4,700 full–time physicians.&lt;ref name=overview&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trustees.jhu.edu/overview.php|title=JHU Board of Trustees Overview|accessdate=2010–11–19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

JHU's bylaws specify a Board of Trustees of between 18 and 65 voting members. Trustees serve six–year terms subject to a two–term limit. The alumni select 12 trustees. Four recent alumni serve 4-year terms, one per year, typically from the graduating class. The bylaws prohibit students, faculty or administrative staff from serving on the Board, except the President as an ex–officio trustee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://trustees.jhu.edu/bylaws.php|title=Bylaws|accessdate=2010–11–19}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The Johns Hopkins Health System has a separate Board of Trustees, many of whom are doctors or health care executives. Some JHU Trustees also serve on the Johns Hopkins Health System Board.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/news/media/releases/johns_hopkins_medicine_adds_four_to_board_of_trustees|title=Johns Hopkins Medicine Adds Four to Board|accessdate=2010–11–19}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Academics==
[[File:JHU-Z.jpg|right|300px|thumb|Mason Hall, the Visitor's Center &amp; Admissions Office at Johns Hopkins University]]
The full-time, four year undergraduate program is &quot;most selective&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/college/items/2077 |title=Johns Hopkins University – Best Colleges – Education – US News and World Report |publisher=Colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date=2009-08-19 |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; with low transfer-in and a high graduate co-existence.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.carnegiefoundation.org/classifications/sub.asp?key=748&amp;subkey=14582&amp;start=782 |title=Carnegie Classifications – Johns Hopkins University |publisher=Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching |accessdate=2008-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university is one of fourteen founding members of the [[Association of American Universities]] (AAU); it is also a member of the [[Consortium on Financing Higher Education]] (COFHE) and the [[Universities Research Association]] (URA).

===Undergraduate Admissions===

{| style=&quot;text-align:center; float:right; font-size:85%; margin-left:2em; margin:10px;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Johns Hopkins University&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://gazette.jhu.edu/2010/04/12/applications-up-14-percent-for-incoming-homewood-class/ |title=Applications up 14 percent for incoming Homewood class |first= Amy |last=Lunday |date=12 April 2010 |publisher=gazette.jhu.edu |accessdate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|C/O 2015 Applicants
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 19,355
|-
|C/O 2015 Admitted
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 3,550 (18.3%)
|-
|SAT Median (2400)
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 720R, 760M, 730W
|-
|ACT Median (36)
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 33
|-
|Freshman Class Size
| style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot;| 1,235
|}
In 2010, 87% of admitted students graduated in the top tenth of their high school class and the inter-quartile range on the [[SAT]] reading was 670–750, math was 690–780, and writing was 670–770. 97% of freshmen returned after the first year, 84% of students graduated in 4 years and 92% graduated in 6 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;CDS&quot;/&gt;  Over time, applications to Johns Hopkins University have risen steadily.  As a result, the selectivity of Johns Hopkins University has also increased.  [[Early Decision]] is an option at Johns Hopkins University for students who wish to demonstrate that the university is their first choice.  These students, if admitted, are required to enroll.  This application is due November 1.  Most students do, however, apply Regular Decision which is a traditional non-binding round.  These applications are due January 1 and students are notified April 1.

{| style=&quot;text-align:center; float:right; font-size:85%; margin-left:2em; margin:10px;&quot; class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Population
! Year!! Applicants !! Growth !! Acceptance rate !! Accepted !! Enrolled || Yield
|-
|2011 || 19,355 || 4.04% || 18.3% || 3,550 || 1,272&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Lunday|first=Amy|title=Record-breaking class of 2015: Highest yield, most diverse|url=http://gazette.jhu.edu/2011/06/06/record-breaking-class-of-2015-highest-yield-most-diverse/|work=Reporter|publisher=The JHU Gazette|accessdate=14 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; || 37%
|-
| 2010 || 18,455 || 14.5% || 20.4% || 3,764 || 1,235 || 33%
|-
| 2009 || 16,123 || 0.7% || 26.8% || 4,318 || 1,350 || 31%
|-
| 2008 || 16,006 || 7.7% || 25.3% || 4,056 || 1,238&lt;ref name=&quot;CDS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/~registr/reports/CDS2007_08.pdf |title=Common Data Set|year=2007–2008 |publisher=Johns Hopkins University |accessdate=2008-12-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; || 31%
|-
| 2007 || 14,858 || 7.17% || 24.2% || 3,603 || 1,206&lt;ref name=&quot;CDS&quot;/&gt;  || 33%
|-
| 2006 || 13,863 || 22.9% || 27% || 3,698 || 1,235 || 33%
|-
| 2005|| 11,278 || 1.58% || 35% || 3,910 || 1,155 || 30%
|-
| 2004|| 11,102 || 10.75% || 30% || 3,322 || 1,050 || 32%
|-
| 2003 || 10,024 || -% || 31% || 3,071 || 1,050 || 34%
|}

===Rankings===
{{Infobox US university ranking
| ARWU_N               = 16
| ARWU_W               = 18
| QS_W                    = 16
| THES_W               = 14
| USNWR_NU             = 13
| Wamo_NU              = 25
}}

At the undergraduate level, Hopkins was ranked &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;13 among National Universities by ''[[U.S. News and World Report]] (USNWR)''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=America's Best Colleges 2010: National Universities Rankings|url=http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/national-universities-rankingst|year=2010|accessdate=2010-08-17}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It is ranked &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;6 in the nation in the high school counselor reputation rankings.&lt;ref name=&quot;HS Counselor&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=US News |year=2011 |publisher=US News and World Report |url= http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/rankings/national-universities/high-school-counselor|accessdate=2011-08-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The 2010 ''[[Academic Ranking of World Universities]] (ARWU)'' ranked Hopkins &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;18 internationally (&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;16 nationally) and 3rd in the world for Clinical Medicine and Pharmacy.&lt;ref name=&quot;shanghai2&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Top 500 World Universities |year=2010 |publisher=Shanghai Jiao Tong University |url= http://www.arwu.org/ARWU2010.jsp|accessdate=2010-08-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2010, Johns Hopkins ranked 13th in the [[Times Higher Education World University Rankings]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World University Rankings 2010–11|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 16th in the 2011 [[QS World University Rankings]].&lt;ref name=&quot;QS World University Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topuniversities.com/university-rankings/world-university-rankings/2011 |title=QS World University Rankings |publisher=Topuniversities |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;World University Rankings&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/world-university-rankings/2010-2011/top-200.html |title=World University Rankings|year=2010 |publisher=The Times Higher Educational Supplement |accessdate=2010-09-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Top 200 World Universities&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/hybrid.asp?typeCode=243&amp;pubCode=1&amp;navcode=137 |title=Top 200 World Universities |publisher=Times Higher Education |accessdate=2008-12-24 |year=2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Johns Hopkins also placed &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;2 in the 2010 University Ranking by Academic Performance (URAP),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=2010 University Ranking by Academic Performance (URAP)|url=http://www.urapcenter.org/2010/}}&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;2 in the 2011 [[HEEACT – Performance Ranking of Scientific Papers for World Universities]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ranking.heeact.edu.tw/en-us/2011/TOP/100 |title=World Universities Rankings |year=2011 |publisher=Higher Education Evaluation and Accreditation Council of Taiwan |accessdate=2011-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt; ranked &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;7 among Top Performing Schools according to the ''[[Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index]] (FSPI)'' in 2008,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.academicanalytics.com/TopSchools/TopSchools.aspx |title=Top Schools |publisher=academicanalytics.com }}&lt;/ref&gt; and was listed &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;9 among research universities by the ''[[Center for Measuring University Performance]]'' in 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mup.asu.edu/research2007.pdf |title=Top American Research Universities |year=2007 |publisher=Center for Measuring University Performance |accessdate=2008-12-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For [[medical]] and [[public health]] research ''U.S. News and World Report'' ranks the [[Johns Hopkins School of Medicine|School of Medicine]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;3&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-medical-schools/research-rankings|title=America's Best Graduate Schools 2011: Top Medical Schools|accessdate=2011-04-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and has consistently ranked the [[Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health|Bloomberg School of Public Health]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;1&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-public-health-schools/rankings|title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Public Health Graduate Schools Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2009 |accessdate=2009-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the nation. The [[Johns Hopkins School of Nursing|School of Nursing]] was ranked &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;1 nationally among peer institutions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/grad/nur/search |title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Nursing Graduate Schools Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2011 |accessdate=2011-06-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Times Higher Education Supplement'' ranked Johns Hopkins University &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;3 in the world for [[biomedicine]] and [[life sciences]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.topuniversities.com/worlduniversityrankings/results/2008/subject_rankings/life_sciences_biomedicine/ |title=Top Universities QS World University Rankings 2008: Life Sciences and Biomedicine |publisher= Times Higher Education|year=2008 |accessdate=2009-03-09}} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopkins ranks &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;1 nationally in receipt of federal research funds and the School of Medicine is &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;1 among medical schools in receipt of extramural awards from the [[National Institutes of Health|National Institutes of Health (NIH)]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/about_jhu/facts_at_a_glance/index.cfm |title=Johns Hopkins University Facts at a Glance |publisher=JHU |year=2009 |accessdate=2008-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt; Newsweek named Johns Hopkins as the &quot;Hottest School for Pre-meds&quot; in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.newsweek.com/id/32225/output/print |title=25 Hottest Schools |publisher=Newsweek |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-12-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Johns Hopkins Hospital]] was ranked as the top hospital in the United States for the eighteenth year in a row by the ''[[U.S. News and World Report]]'' annual ranking of American hospitals.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://health.usnews.com/articles/health/best-hospitals/2008/07/10/best-hospitals-honor-roll.html |title=U.S. News &amp; World Report: Best Hospital Rankings |publisher=U.S. News &amp; World Report |year=2008 |accessdate=2008-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The university's graduate programs in the areas of [[Biological science|Biological]] &amp; [[Biomedical science|Biomedical Sciences]], Engineering ([[Biomedical engineering|Biomedical]], [[Electrical engineering|Electrical]] &amp; [[Environmental engineering|Environmental]]), [[Developmental psychology|Human Development]] &amp; [[Sociology of the family|Family Studies]], [[Health Sciences]], [[Humanities]], [[Physical sciences|Physical]] &amp; [[Mathematical Sciences]] and [[International relations|International Affairs]] &amp; [[International Development|Development]] all rank among the top-10 of their respective disciplines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=
http://chronicle.com/stats/productivity/page.php?year=2007&amp;institution=1591&amp;byinst=Go |title=2007 Faculty Scholarly Productivity Index: Johns Hopkins University  |publisher=The Chronicle of Higher Education |year=2006 |accessdate=2009-01-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=FSP Index Top Performing Individual Programs |url=http://www.academicanalytics.com/TopSchools/TopPrograms.aspx|publisher=Academic Analytics|year=2008|accessdate=2008-12-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Paul H. Nitze School of Advanced International Studies]] (SAIS) ranked #1 (2005), #2 (2007), and #2 (2009), by [[College of William and Mary]]'s surveys conducted once every two years beginning in 2005, for its MA program among the world's top schools of International Affairs for those who want to pursue a policy career.{{Citation needed|date=August 2011}}

The [[Johns Hopkins University School of Education|School of Education]] is ranked &lt;sup&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps&quot;&gt;#&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;6 nationally by ''U.S. News and World Report''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-education-schools/rankings |title=Rankings – Best Education Schools – Graduate Schools – Education – US News and World Report |publisher=Grad-schools.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although no formal rankings exist for [[music school|music conservatories]], the [[Peabody Institute]] is generally considered one of the most prestigious conservatories in the country, along with [[Juilliard]] and the [[Curtis Institute]].

Johns Hopkins is ranked the #1 Social Media College by StudentAdvisor&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.studentadvisor.com/top-100-social-media-colleges |title=Top 100 Social Media Colleges|publisher=studentadvisor.com |date=2011-05-25 |accessdate=2011-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;  primarily due to the Hopkins Interactive website which use social media platforms such as Blogs, Facebook, Twitter, YouTube, and Flickr to reach outside prospective audiences.

===Libraries===
The Johns Hopkins University Library system houses more than 3.6 million volumes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=American Library Association Fact Sheet|url=http://www.ala.org/ala/alalibrary/libraryfactsheet/alalibraryfactsheet22.cfm|publisher=ALA|year= 2007|accessdate=2007-04-26 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070423074412/http://www.ala.org/ala/alalibrary/libraryfactsheet/alalibraryfactsheet22.cfm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-04-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; It includes ten main divisions: the Sheridan Libraries at Homewood, the Medical Institutions Libraries, the School of Nursing Library, Abraham M. Lilienfeld Library at the Bloomberg School, the Peabody Institute Library, the Carey Business School and School of Education libraries, the School of Advanced International Studies Libraries (Sydney R. and Elsa W. Mason Library and Bologna Center Library), the R.E. Gibson Library at the Applied Physics Laboratory Library and other minor satellite locations, as well as the archives.
[[File:JHU Eisenhower Library.jpg|right|thumb|&lt;center&gt;[[Milton S. Eisenhower Library]]&lt;/center&gt;]]
The [[Milton S. Eisenhower Library]], located on the [[Homewood campus]], is the main library. It was built in the 1960s. It houses over 2.6 million volumes and over 20,000 journal subscriptions. The Eisenhower Library is a member of the university's Sheridan Libraries encompassing collections at the Albert D. Hutzler Reading Room (called &quot;The Hut&quot; by students) in Gilman Hall, the John Work Garrett Library at Evergreen House, and the George Peabody Library at Mount Vernon Place. Together these collections provide the major research library resources for the university, serving Johns Hopkins academic programs worldwide. The library was named for [[Milton S. Eisenhower]], former president of the university and brother of former U.S. president [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]. JHU's library was originally housed in Gilman Hall, and the library stacks in that building continue to house certain collections.&lt;ref name=gil&gt;{{cite news|url= http://www.jhu.edu/jhumag/0206web/halls.html|title=If These Halls Could Talk|work=Johns Hopkins Magazine|first=Maria |last=Blackburn |date=February 2006|accessdate=2010-11-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Only two of the Eisenhower library's six stories are above ground, though architects designed the building so that every level has windows and natural light. The design accords with a bit of traditional campus lore which says no structure can be taller than Gilman Hall, the oldest academic building, although no written rule limits building height. In December 2008, an addition directly to the south of the library was announced. The six-and-a-half-story expansion will be named the Brody Learning Commons in honor of University President [[William R. Brody]] and will function as a &quot;collaborative learning space&quot;. It is scheduled to be completed by 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Johns Hopkins Gazette|url=http://www.jhu.edu/~gazette/2008/08dec08/08blc.html| publisher = Johns Hopkins University|year=2008|accessdate=2008-12-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Research==
The opportunity to participate in important research is one of the distinguishing characteristics of Hopkins' undergraduate education. About 80 percent of undergraduates perform independent research, often alongside top researchers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Carnegie&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Johns Hopkins News Release – JHU|url=http://jhuniverse.jhu.edu/news_info/news/home01/apr01/wood.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|year= 2001|accessdate=2007-01-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; In FY 2009, Johns Hopkins received $1.856 billion in federal research grants—more than any other US university.&lt;ref name=nsf09/&gt; Thirty-three (33) [[Nobel Prize]] winners have been affiliated with the university as alumni or faculty members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/JHUniverse/information_about_hopkins/facts_and_statistics/nobel_prize_winners/index.cfm |title=The Johns Hopkins University: Nobel Prize Winners |publisher=Webapps.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; JHU views its academic strengths as being in art history, biological, physical and other natural sciences, biomedical engineering, creative writing, English, history, economics, international studies, medicine, music, neuroscience, nursing, political theory, public health, public policy, and the [[Romance languages]].{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Between 1999 and 2009, Johns Hopkins was among the most cited institutions in the world. It attracted nearly 1,222,166 citations and produced 54,022 papers under its name, ranking &lt;sup&gt;#&lt;/sup&gt;3 globally behind [[Harvard University]] and [[Max Planck Society]] with the highest total citations published in Thomson Reuters-indexed journals over 22 fields in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;ScienceWatch.com&quot;/&gt;

In FY 2000, Johns Hopkins received $95.4 million in research grants from the [[National Aeronautics and Space Administration]] (NASA), making it the leading recipient of NASA [[research and development]] funding.&lt;ref name=JHU_NASA_R&amp;D_2000&gt;{{cite news|title=JHU #1 recipient of [[NASA]] research grants: &quot;Dollars From Heaven: NASA-funded research small but vital&quot;|url=http://www.post-gazette.com/localnews/20030217research0217p2.asp|work=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2009-06-25 | first1=Byron | last1=Spice | date=2003-02-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; In FY 2002, Hopkins became the first university to cross the $1 billion threshold on either list, recording $1.14 billion in total research and $1.023 billion in federally sponsored research. In FY 2008, Johns Hopkins University performed $1.68 billion in science, medical and engineering research, making it the leading U.S. academic institution in total R&amp;D spending for the 30th year in a row, according to a  [[National Science Foundation]] (NSF) ranking.&lt;ref name=ascribe_oct09_r&amp;d&gt;{{cite web|title=Johns Hopkins First in R&amp;D Expenditures for 30th Year|url=http://newswire.ascribe.org/cgi-bin/behold.pl?ascribeid=20091006.062525&amp;time=07%2056%20PDT&amp;year=2009&amp;public=0|work=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2009-10-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; These totals include grants and expenditures of JHU's Applied Physics Laboratory in Laurel, Maryland.&lt;ref name=nsf09/&gt;

===Research centers and institutes===
{{Multicol}}

====Divisional====
*School of Medicine (28)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/Research/core_research_facilities.html |title=Johns Hopkins Medicine: Research Centers &amp; CORE Facilities |publisher=Hopkinsmedicine.org |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Public Health (70)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhsph.edu/researchcenters |title=Research and Centers at the School of Public Health |publisher=Jhsph.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Nursing (2)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.son.jhmi.edu/research/ccir/Default.aspx |title=Johns Hopkins University School of Nursing &amp;#124; Research &amp;#124; CCIR &amp;#124; |publisher=Son.jhmi.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Arts and Sciences (27)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://krieger.jhu.edu/academics/pci/index.html |title=Programs, Centers &amp; Institutes |publisher=Krieger.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Advanced International Studies (17)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sais-jhu.edu/centers/index.htm |title=SAIS Research Centers |publisher=Sais-jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Engineering (16)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://engineering.jhu.edu/centers-institutes/ |title=Johns Hopkins University Whiting School of Engineering |publisher=Engineering.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*School of Education (3)&lt;ref&gt;[http://education.jhu.edu/centers/ JHU.edu]{{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Applied Physics Laboratory]]
{{Multicol-break}}

====Medical====
*[[Johns Hopkins Hospital]]
*[[Johns Hopkins Bayview Medical Center]]
*[[Johns Hopkins Singapore International Medical Centre]]
*[[Howard County General Hospital]]
*[[Suburban Hospital]]
*[[Sibley Memorial Hospital]]
*[[All Children's Medical Center]]
{{Multicol-break}}

====Others====
*Center for Biotechnology&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://biotechnology.jhu.edu |title=Center for Biotechnology |publisher=Web.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-08-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Center for Language and Speech Processing|The Center for Language and Speech Processing]]
*[[Johns Hopkins Institute for Policy Studies]]
*[[Johns Hopkins Berman Institute of Bioethics|The Berman Institute of Bioethics]]
*Johns Hopkins Information Security Institute&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/jhuisi |title=Johns Hopkins University Information Security Institute |publisher=Web.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-03-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Space Telescope Science Institute]]
*Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Center for Communication Programs
*[[Center for Talented Youth]]- Summer institute for gifted students
{{Multicol-end}}

[[File:Lower Quad at JHU.jpg.JPG|center|thumb|500px|&lt;center&gt;Wyman Quad, home to the Whiting School of Engineering at Johns Hopkins University&lt;/center&gt;]]

==Johns Hopkins University Press==
{{Main|Johns Hopkins University Press}}

The Johns Hopkins University Press is the publishing division of the Johns Hopkins University. It was founded in 1878 and holds the distinction of being the oldest continuously running [[university press]] in the [[United States]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=About the Press |url=http://www.press.jhu.edu/about/index.html |publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press |accessdate={{Date|2006-01-14|mdy}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; To date the Press has published more than 6,000 titles and currently publishes 65 scholarly periodicals and over 200 new books each year. Since 1993, the Johns Hopkins University Press has run [[Project MUSE]], an online collection of over 250 full–text, peer–reviewed journals in the humanities and social sciences. The Press also houses the Hopkins Fulfilment Services (HFS), which handles distribution for a number of university presses and publishers. Taken together, the three divisions of the Press—Books, Journals (including MUSE) and HFS—make it one of the largest of America's university presses.

==Student life==
[[File:JHUQuad.jpg|right|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Students gather under the holidays lights at the yearly Lighting of the Quad, a Hopkins tradition&lt;/center&gt;]]
The Johns Hopkins Student Government Association represents undergraduates in campus issues and projects. It is elected annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhusga.com/aboutus|title=About Us|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Blueprints for a new programming board called The Hopkins Organization for Programming (&quot;The HOP&quot;) were drawn up during the summer and fall of 2006.

In addition [[Charles Village, Baltimore|Charles Village]], the region of North Baltimore surrounding the university, has undergone several restoration projects, and the university has gradually bought the property around the school for additional student housing and dormitories. ''The Charles Village Project'', scheduled for completion in 2008, brought new commercial spaces to the neighborhood. The project included Charles Commons, a new, modern residence hall that includes popular retail franchises.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Charles Commons|accessdate=2006–08–07|url=http://www.jhu.edu/hds/campushousing/charlescommons.htm |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20060910004805/http://www.jhu.edu/hds/campushousing/charlescommons.htm |archivedate = September 10, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.einsteinbros.com/index.cfm Einsteinbros.com]{{Dead link|date=March 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Hopkins invested in improving campus life with an arts complex in 2001, the Mattin Center, and a three–story sports facility, the O'Connor Recreation Center. The large on–campus dining facilities at Homewood were renovated in the summer of 2006.

Quality of life is enriched by the proximity of neighboring academic institutions, including [[Loyola College in Maryland|Loyola College]], [[Maryland Institute College of Art|Maryland Institute College of Art (MICA)]], [[UMBC]], [[Goucher College]], and [[Towson University]], as well as nearby [[Inner Harbor]].

Annually, the Johns Hopkins Spring Fair is held on the Homewood campus over a three day weekend in mid to late April. Food, arts and crafts, and non–profit vendors, along with a popular musical act and various other activities attract nearly 25,000 people from the greater Baltimore–Washington area. The Spring Fair is the largest entirely student–run fair in the country.

===Housing===
[[File:AMRs at JHU.JPG|upright|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Freshman Residence Hall at JHU&lt;/center&gt;]]
[[File:JHU Campus Map.JPG|300px|right|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Johns Hopkins University Campus, Schematic&lt;/center&gt;]]
Living on campus is required for first- and second-year students, except for commuter students who live with a parent or legal guardian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Johns Hopkins Freshman Room Selection Brochure|url=http://home_at_hopkins.jhu.edu/flipbook/FreshmenBrochure/FRSPBrochure2011/index.html|work=Johns Hopkins University Housing and Dining Department|publisher=Johns Hopkins|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Housing is not guaranteed for juniors or seniors at Johns Hopkins.

Freshmen housing is centered around Freshman Quad which consists of three major residence hall complexes: The Alumni Memorial Residences (AMR I and AMR II), Building A and Building B.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freshman Residence Halls&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/hds/incoming_frosh/explore_residence_halls.html|title=Our Residence Halls|work=Johns Hopkins University Housing and Dining Department|publisher=Johns Hopkins|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; AMR I was built in 1923 and includes Royce, Sylvester, Vincent, Willard, Wilson and Wood houses; AMR II in 1954, holding Adams, Baker, Clark, Gildersleeve, Griffin, Hollander, Jennings, Lazear houses.{{cn|date=October 2011}} The houses were named for Hopkins Alumni who died in World Wars I and II. While each house has its own outside entrance, there are no dividers indoors that distinguish them. In 1983, Buildings A and B were added to Freshmen Quad.{{cn|date=October 2011}} They have not yet been dedicated. Freshmen are also housed in Wolman Hall and the terrace floor of McCoy Hall, located on the other side of North Charles Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freshman Residence Halls&quot;/&gt;

Freshman enter a housing lottery in their spring semester to determine where they will live during their sophomore year. Juniors and seniors may choose between entering the campus housing lottery or moving into nearby apartments or row houses. They occupy one of four buildings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freshman Room Selection&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://home_at_hopkins.jhu.edu/flipbook/FreshmenBrochure/FRSPBrochure2011/index.html|title=Freshman Room Selection Brochure|work=Johns Hopkins University Housing and Dining Department|publisher=Johns Hopkins|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first, McCoy Hall, is located next to Wolman Hall on North Charles Street. McCoy Hall is predominantly composed of sophomores and transfer students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oncampus: Buildings&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/hds/oncampus/buildings.html|title=Oncampus: Buildings|work=Johns Hopkins University Housing and Dining Department|publisher=Johns Hopkins|accessdate=8 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apartment-style housing is offered in the Bradford Apartments, one block east of campus on St. Paul Street, and in the Homewood Apartments, two blocks south on North Charles Street.&lt;ref name=&quot;Freshman Room Selection&quot;/&gt; The last is Charles Commons, the newest and largest university–owned dormitory, located at the corner of North Charles and East 33rd. It was completed in 2006 to house 618 students and represented a major step by the university towards offering on–campus housing to students.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oncampus: Buildings&quot;/&gt; Charles Commons consists of two 11–story towers connected by a bridge, residential suites and features a ballroom, fitness center and several conference rooms. Nolan's on 33rd, a dining hall specializing in dinner services, is also located in the building.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oncampus: Buildings&quot;/&gt;

JHU rents several buildings on North Charles Street to house students when necessary. At full capacity, dormitory buildings can house approximately 60% of undergraduates.{{cn|date=October 2011}} Privately–owned apartment buildings around Homewood are usually filled with Hopkins upperclassmen, so despite the lack of university–owned dormitories, housing is available.

===Fraternities and Sororities===
The University Office of Greek Life recognizes thirteen fraternities and eight sororities, which include approximately 25% of the student body. Greek life has been a part of the university culture since 1877, when [[Beta Theta Pi]] fraternity became the first to form a chapter on campus. Sororities arrived at Hopkins in 1982. As with all Hopkins programs, Greek discrimination on the basis of &quot;marital status, pregnancy, race, color, ethnicity, national origin, age, disability, religion, sexual orientation, veteran status&quot; is prohibited.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/administration/jhuoie/compliance.html|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|title=Equity Compliance and Education|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt; JHU also has an anti–hazing policy&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/hazingpolicy.html|title=Hazing Information|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt; and prohibits alcohol at recruitment activities.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/InterfraternityCouncil/ifcrushrules07.html|title=IFC Recruitment Rules|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopkins does not permit &quot;city–wide&quot; chapters, and requires all members of a JHU recognized fraternity or sorority to be a JHU student.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/greeklifepolicies.html|title=Office of Greek Life Policies|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As of Spring 2011, 1,208 students were members of one of Hopkins' fraternities or sororities. The All–Greek Average [[GPA]] was 3.31, above the undergraduate average GPA.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Turning|first=Robert|title=Greek Grade Information, Spring 2011|publisher=Office of Student Development and Programming, Johns Hopkins University|year=2011|accessdate=2011–10–09|url= http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/GradeInformation/greekgradesspring11.html}} {{Dead link|date=October 2010|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; In Spring 2010 the university was considering construction of a &quot;fraternity row&quot; of houses to consolidate the groups on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://media.www.jhunewsletter.com/media/storage/paper932/news/2010/11/18/NewsFeatures/Hopkins.Greek.Life.Considers.Fraternity.Row–3961579.shtml|title=Hopkins Greek Life considers fraternity row|first=Megan|last=Cants|work=The Johns Hopkins News–Letter|date=November 18. 2010|accessdate=2010–11–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

All Johns Hopkins fraternities and sororities belong to one of four Councils: the '''Inter–Fraternity Council''', the '''[[National Panhellenic Conference]]''', the '''[[National Pan-Hellenic Council]]''' and the '''Multicultural Council'''.

The Inter–Fraternity Council includes eleven fraternities:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/InterfraternityCouncil/inter_fraternity.html|title=
Johns Hopkins Inter–Fraternity Council|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ΑΔΦ – [[Alpha Delta Phi]] fraternity, ''chapter founded 1889.''
* ΑΕΠ – [[Alpha Epsilon Pi]] fraternity, ''Psi chapter founded 1936. Jewish interest.''
* ΒΘΠ – [[Beta Theta Pi]] fraternity, ''Alpha Chi chapter founded 1877.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hopkinsbeta.org/index.html|title=Beta Theta Pi at Hopkins University|publisher=Beta Theta Pi Alpha Chi Chapter|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ΛΦΕ – [[Lambda Phi Epsilon]] fraternity, ''Upsilon chapter founded 1994. Asian–American interest.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/chapter_pages/lpe|title=Lambda Phi Epsilon Fraternity|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ΦΔΘ – [[Phi Delta Theta]] fraternity, ''Maryland Delta chapter founded 2008.''
* FIJI – [[Phi Gamma Delta]] fraternity, ''Beta Mu chapter founded 1891.''
* ΦΚΨ – [[Phi Kappa Psi]] fraternity, ''Maryland Alpha chapter founded 1879.''
* ΠΚΑ – [[Pi Kappa Alpha]] fraternity, ''Iota Tau chapter founded 1994.''
* ΣΑΕ – [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]] fraternity, ''Maryland Phi chapter founded 1994.''
* ΣΧ – [[Sigma Chi]] fraternity, ''Kappa Upsilon chapter founded 2003.''
* ΣΦΕ – [[Sigma Phi Epsilon]] fraternity, ''Maryland Alpha chapter founded 1929.''
The National Panhellenic Conference includes four sororities:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/PanhellenicCouncil/panhellenic.html|title=
Johns Hopkins National Pan-Hellenic Council|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2011–10–08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ΑΦ – [[Alpha Phi]] sorority, ''Zeta Omicron chapter founded 1982.''
* ΚΚΓ – [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]] sorority, ''Eta Epsilon chapter founded 1999.''
* ΦM – [[Phi Mu]] sorority, ''Gamma Tau chapter founded 1982.''
* ΠBΦ – [[Pi Beta Phi]] sorority, ''Maryland Gamma chartered November 20, 2010.''

The National Pan–Hellenic Council includes two historically African–American groups:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/national.html|title=
Johns Hopkins National Pan-Hellenic Council|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2011–10–08}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ΑΦΑ – [[Alpha Phi Alpha]] fraternity, ''Sigma Sigma chapter founded 1991.''
* ΣΓP – [[Sigma Gamma Rho]] sorority, ''Rho Omega chapter founded 2009.''

The '''Multicultural Council''' includes four groups:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web.jhu.edu/studentlife/greek_life/multicult.html|title=Multicultural Greeks|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2010–11–27}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:JHU-Aerial.JPG|right|300px|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Johns Hopkins University Main Campus at Homewood.&lt;/center&gt;]]
* αΚΔΦ – [[Alpha Kappa Delta Phi]] sorority, ''associate chapter founded 1997. Asian–American interest.''
* ΔΞΦ – [[Delta Xi Phi]] sorority, ''Lambda chapter founded 2003. Multicultural interest.''
* INΔ – [[Iota Nu Delta]] fraternity, ''chapter founded 2008. South Asian interest.''
* ΣΟΠ – [[Sigma Omicron Pi]] sorority, ''Lambda chapter founded 2002. Asian–American interest.''

[[Delta Phi]] Fraternity, also known as St. Elmo's, maintains a chapter exclusive to students at Johns Hopkins, though it is not recognized by the Office of Greek Life.

Unrecognized [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]] and [[Delta Sigma Theta]] African–American interest sororities often recruit Johns Hopkins undergraduates, in their city–wide chapters. [[Delta Sigma Theta]] was the first '''National Pan–Hellenic Council''' member to charter on the campus in 1976, as well as the first sorority of any kind on the JHU campus.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

[[Kappa Alpha Theta]], a [[National Panhellenic Conference]] (NPC) sorority, was disbanded by its national headquarters on April 14, 2009 after twelve years on campus.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Patnaik|first=Payal|title=Theta to be disbanded indefinitely|publisher=Johns Hopkins News–Letter|date=2009–04–16|accessdate=2009–05–21|url=http://media.www.jhunewsletter.com/media/storage/paper932/news/2009/04/16/NewsFeatures/Theta.To.Be.Disbanded.Indefinitely–3713697.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; The removal was due to repeated risk management violations.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

In March 2010, Johns Hopkins University officially opened for NPC extension.{{Clarify|date=November 2010}} In May 2010, the University Panhellenic Council selected [[Pi Beta Phi]], which opened in the fall of 2010.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Plestis|first=Vicky|title=New sorority to begin recruitment this fall|publisher=Johns Hopkins News–Letter|date=2010–09–16|accessdate=2010–10–20|url=http://media.www.jhunewsletter.com/media/storage/paper932/news/2010/09/16/NewsFeatures/New–Sorority.To.Begin.Recruitment.This.Fall–3933214.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Recruitment for Inter–Fraternity Council and Panhellenic Conference fraternities and sororities takes place during the spring semester for freshmen, though some groups recruit upperclassmen during the fall semester.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} All participants must have completed one semester and must be in good academic standing.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}

Many of the fraternities maintain houses off campus, but no sororities do.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}}  Baltimore City allows housing to be zoned specifically for use as a fraternity or sorority house, but in practice this zoning code has not been awarded for at least 50 years.{{Citation needed|date=November 2010}} Only Sigma Phi Epsilon's building has this zoning code due to its consistent ownership since the 1920s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Baltimore Zoning Laws&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.transformbaltimore.net/portal/zoning–apr–draft?pointId=1273165766647 |title=Baltimore Zoning Law |publisher=Baltimore City}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student publications===
[[File:GilmanHall.JPG|right|upright|thumb||200px|&lt;center&gt;Gilman Hall, Center for the Humanities&lt;/center&gt;]]
Hopkins has many student publications.
*''[[The Johns Hopkins News-Letter]]'', founded in 1896, is one of the oldest continuously published weekly college newspapers in the nation with a press run of 5,200.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhunewsletter.com/home/generalinformation/ |title=The Johns Hopkins News–Letter |publisher=Jhunewsletter.com |date= |accessdate=2010–11–24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The News-Letter won a Associated Collegiate Press Newspaper Pacemaker award for four–year, non–daily college newspapers in 2007.

*''The Hopkins Donkey'' is a political newspaper with a [[Democratic Party (United States)|Democratic]] perspective on international, national and state–wide political topics.

*''The Carrollton Record'' is a political newspaper with an [[American conservatism|American conservative]] perspective on campus and city–wide politics.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tcrecord.com |title=tcrecord.com homepage |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Epidemic Proportions'' is the university's public health research journal, designed to highlight JHU research and field work in public health. Combining research and scholarship, the journal seeks to capture the breadth and depth of the JHU undergraduate public health experience.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/ep/publish.html |title=Epidemic Proportions |publisher=Jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Thoroughfare,'' ''Zeniada'' and ''j.mag'' are literary magazines. ''Prometheus'' is the undergraduate philosophy journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.prometheus–journal.com |title=Prometheus – Johns Hopkins Undergraduate Journal of Philosophy |publisher=Prometheus–journal.com |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Frame of Reference'' is an annual magazine that focuses on film and film culture.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hopkinsfilmfest.com |title=Johns Hopkins Film Festival |publisher=Hopkinsfilmfest.com |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''The New Diplomat'' is the multi–disciplinary international relations journal. ''Foundations'' is the undergraduate history journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jhu.edu/foundations |title=Foundations |publisher=Jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Américas'' is the Latin American Studies journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.americasrevista.com/ |title=Américas
 |publisher=americasrevista.com |accessdate=21 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''Argot'' is the undergraduate anthropology journal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://anthropology.jhu.edu/argot |title=Argot Research Journal |publisher=Anthropology.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''The Triple Helix'' is the university's journal to address issues concerning science, law and society.

*''Perspectives'' is the official newsletter of the ''Black Student Union''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ww2.jhu.edu/bsu/ |title=The Black Student Union |publisher=Ww2.jhu.edu |date= |accessdate=2010–03–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*''The Black &amp; Blue Jay'' is among the nation's oldest campus humor magazines. It was founded in 1920.&lt;ref&gt;''“With the publication of the first of The Black and Blue Jay in November 1920“''
{{cite web|title=Records of The Black and Blue Jay/The Blue Jay|author=Sean DiGiovanna|coauthors=Wendell O'Brien &amp; Charlene Mendoza|url=http://www.library.jhu.edu/collections/specialcollections/archives/inventories/rg14–090.html|publisher=The Ferdinand Hamburger Archives, The Milton S. Eisenhower Library|accessdate= 2006–08–07}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to ''The Johns Hopkins News–Letter'', the magazine's name led the News–Letter to first use the moniker Blue Jays to refer to a Hopkins athletic team in 1923.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Where did they get that darn Blue Jay?|first=Yong| last=Kwon|date=1997–09–25|publisher= The Johns Hopkins News–Letter|url=http://www.jhu.edu/~newslett/09–25–97/Sports/4.html| accessdate=2006–08–07}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the magazine enjoyed popularity among students, it received repeated opposition from the university administration, reportedly for its vulgar humor. In October 1934, Dean Edward R. Berry removed financial support for the magazine; without funding, the magazine continued under the name ''The Blue Jay'' until Berry threatened to expel the editors in 1939. The magazine had a revival in 1984, and has appeared intermittently since then.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Black and Blue Jay returns to campus with a vengeance|last=Krut–Landau|first=Raphael|date=2006–11–02|publisher=The Johns Hopkins News–Letter|url= http://www.jhunewsletter.com/news/2006/11/02/Features/The–Black.And.Blue.Jay.Returns.To.Campus.With.A.Vengeance–2761306.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Student–Run Businesses===
Hopkins Student Enterprises (HSE)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/~hse/ |title=What is HSE? &amp;#124; Hopkins Student Enterprises |publisher=Web1.johnshopkins.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; is a startup incubator with the goal of fostering student innovation and encouraging the development of student–run businesses. Currently, 4 businesses are in operation:&lt;ref name = &quot;Young Money&quot;&gt;[http://www.youngmoney.com/entrepreneur/hopkins–student–enterprise–helping–student–entrepreneurs–find–success &quot;Hopkins Student Enterprise&quot;], Young Money Magazine. Cara Newman. December 29, 2009. Retrieved 15 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

* [[Hopkins Consulting Agency]] (HCA)—Business and technology consulting company that prepares technology commercialization reports and business plans.

* Hopkins Student Movers (HSM)—Moving and storage company that serves JHU faculty, staff, and students and the broader Baltimore community.&lt;ref&gt;http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/~hse/hss/&lt;/ref&gt;

* Hopkins Student Creative Services (HSCS)—Full service graphic design company.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web1.johnshopkins.edu/~hse/hcs/ |title=Hopkins Creative Services |publisher=Web1.johnshopkins.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

* The Blue Jay Cleaners - Student janitorial service for all on-campus and select off campus residence halls. [http://www.thebluejaycleaners.com]

==Athletics==
[[File:Blue Jay Head.svg|thumb|right|Athletics logo]]
{{Main|Johns Hopkins Blue Jays}}
Athletic teams are called Blue Jays. Even though [[sable (heraldry)|sable]] and [[or (heraldry)|gold]] are used for [[academic dress|academic robes]], the university's athletic colors are [[Columbia blue]] (PMS 284) and [[black]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hopkinssports.com/trads/jhop-quick-facts.html |title=The Official Athletic Site of Johns Hopkins University – Athletic Quick Facts |publisher=Hopkinssports.com |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hopkins celebrates [[Homecoming]] in the spring to coincide with the height of the [[lacrosse]] season. The Men's and Women's lacrosse teams are in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] (NCAA) [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]. Other teams are in [[Division III (NCAA)|Division III]] and participate in the [[Centennial Conference]]. JHU is also home to the [[Lacrosse Museum and National Hall of Fame]], maintained by [[US Lacrosse]].

===Men's lacrosse===
{{Main|Johns Hopkins Blue Jays men's lacrosse}}
[[File:JHU 001.jpg|right|thumb|Johns Hopkins Men's Lacrosse at [[Homewood Field]]]]
The school's most prominent team is its men's [[lacrosse]] team. The team does not belong to a conference. The team has won 44 national titles – nine Division I (2007, 2005, 1987, 1985, 1984, 1980, 1979, 1978, 1974), 29 [[United States Intercollegiate Lacrosse Association]] ([[United States Intercollegiate Lacrosse Association|USILA]]), and six Intercollegiate Lacrosse Association (ILA) titles. Hopkins' primary national rivals are [[Princeton University]], [[Syracuse University]], and the [[University of Virginia]]; its primary intrastate rivals are [[Loyola College in Maryland|Loyola College]] (competing in what is called the &quot;[[Charles Street Massacre]]&quot;), [[Towson University]], the [[United States Naval Academy]], and the [[University of Maryland, College Park|University of Maryland]]. The [[Johns Hopkins—Maryland rivalry|rivalry with Maryland]] is the oldest. The schools have met 103 times since 1899, twice in playoff matches.

===Women's lacrosse===
{{Main|Johns Hopkins Blue Jays women's lacrosse}}
The women's team is a member of the [[American Lacrosse Conference]] (ALC). The team is developing into a top twenty team. The Lady Blue Jays were ranked number 19 in the 2008 Inside Lacrosse Women's DI Media Poll (ILWDIMP). They ranked number 8 in both the 2007 Intercollegiate Women's Lacrosse Coaches Association (IWLCA) Poll for Division I and the ILWDIMP. In 2006, they were ranked 14th in the ILWDIMP, in 2005, they were 11th, and, in 2004, they were 9th. However, recently the team has struggled and finished with a record of 5 wins and 12 losses in the 2009 season.

===Other teams===
Hopkins has notable Division III Athletic teams. In 2009–2010, Hopkins won 8 Centennial Conference titles in Women's Cross Country, Women's Track &amp; Field, Baseball, Men's and Women's Soccer, Football, and Men's and Women's Tennis. The Women's Cross Country team became the first women's team at Hopkins to achieve a #1 National ranking. In 2006–2007 teams won Centennial Conference titles in Baseball, Men's and Women's Soccer, Men's and Women's Tennis and Men's Basketball.
Hopkins has an acclaimed [[fencing]] team, which ranked in the top three Division III teams in the past few years and in both 2008 and 2007 defeated the [[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill|University of North Carolina]], a Division I team. In 2008, they defeated UNC and won the MACFA championship. The [[swimming (sport)|Swimming]] team ranked in the top two of Division III for the last 10 years.

The Men's Swimming team placed second at DIII Nationals in 2008. The Water Polo team was number one in Division III for several of the past years, playing a full schedule against Division I opponents. Hopkins also has a century-old rivalry with [[McDaniel College]] (formerly Western Maryland College), playing the Green Terrors 83 times in football since the first game in 1894. In 2009 the football team reached the quarterfinals of the NCAA Division III tournament. In 2008, the baseball team ranked second, losing in the final game of the DIII [[College World Series]] to [[Trinity College, Hartford|Trinity College]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.titans.uwosh.edu/NCAAChampionship/2008/ |title=2008 NCAA Division III Baseball Championship, University of Wisconsin–Oshkosh Titans website |publisher=Titans.uwosh.edu |date= |accessdate=2011-09-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notable alumni, faculty and staff==
{{Main|List of Johns Hopkins University people}}

===Nobel laureates===
{{Main|List of Nobel laureates affiliated with Johns Hopkins University}}
As of 2011, there had been 37 [[Nobel Prize|Nobel]] Laureates, who attended the university as undergraduate students, graduate students or were faculty members.&lt;ref name=&quot;WinnersList&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://webapps.jhu.edu/jhuniverse/information_about_hopkins/facts_and_statistics/nobel_prize_winners/index.cfm|title=Nobel Prize Winners|publisher=Johns Hopkins University|accessdate=2009-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Woodrow Wilson]], who received his PhD from Johns Hopkins in 1886, was Hopkins' first affiliated laureate, winning the [[Nobel Peace Prize]] in 1919.&lt;ref name=&quot;WinnersList&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Peace1919&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1919/index.html|title=Nobel Peace Prize 1919|publisher=[[Nobel Foundation]]|accessdate=2009-01-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-three laureates were faculty members, five earned PhDs, eight earned [[Doctor of Medicine|M.D.]] while [[Francis Peyton Rous]] and [[Martin Rodbell]] earned [[undergraduate degrees]].

Eighteen Johns Hopkins laureates have won the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine, more than any other category.&lt;ref name=&quot;WinnersList&quot;/&gt; Four Nobel Prizes were shared by Johns Hopkins laureates: [[George Minot]] and [[George Whipple]] won the 1934 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicine1934&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1934/index.html|title = The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 1934|accessdate = 2009-03-13|publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joseph Erlanger]] and [[Herbert Spencer Gasser]] won the 1944 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicine1944&quot;&gt;
{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1944/index.html|title = The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 1944|accessdate = 2009-03-13|publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Daniel Nathans]] and [[Hamilton O. Smith]] won the 1978 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine,&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicine1978&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1978/index.html|title = The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 1978|accessdate = 2009-03-13|publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[David H. Hubel]] and [[Torsten N. Wiesel]] won the 1981 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Medicine1981&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/1981/index.html|title = The Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine 1981|accessdate = 2009-03-13|publisher = [[Nobel Foundation]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|University}}
*[[Johns Hopkins University in Popular Culture]]
*[[DirectHit]] - pharmacodiagnostic test for breast cancer developed by researchers from Johns Hopkins University
{{clear}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{EB1922 Poster}}
*{{Official website|http://www.jhu.edu}}
*[http://hopkinssports.ocsn.com/ Official athletics website]
{{Commons category inline|Johns Hopkins University}}
{{JHU}}
{{Johns Hopkins presidents}}
{{Centennial Con}}
{{Association of American Universities}}
{{Universities Research Association}}
{{Colleges and Universities in Maryland}}
[[Category:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[Category:Association of American Universities]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1876]]
[[Category:Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Oak Ridge Associated Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Baltimore, Maryland]]

[[ar:جامعة جونز هوبكينز]]
[[az:Con Hopkins Universiteti]]
[[bg:Университет Джонс Хопкинс]]
[[cs:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[da:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[de:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[el:Πανεπιστήμιο Τζονς Χόπκινς]]
[[es:Universidad Johns Hopkins]]
[[eo:Johns Hopkins Universitato]]
[[fa:دانشگاه جانز هاپکینز]]
[[fr:Université Johns-Hopkins]]
[[ko:존스 홉킨스 대학교]]
[[id:Universitas John Hopkins]]
[[is:Johns Hopkins-háskóli]]
[[it:Università Johns Hopkins]]
[[he:אוניברסיטת ג'ונס הופקינס]]
[[ka:ჯონს ჰოპკინსის უნივერსიტეტი]]
[[hu:Johns Hopkins Egyetem]]
[[ms:Universiti Johns Hopkins]]
[[nl:Johns Hopkins-universiteit]]
[[ja:ジョンズ・ホプキンス大学]]
[[no:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[pnb:جان ہاپکنز یونیورسٹی]]
[[pl:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[pt:Universidade Johns Hopkins]]
[[ru:Университет Джонса Хопкинса]]
[[simple:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[fi:Johns Hopkinsin yliopisto]]
[[sv:Johns Hopkins University]]
[[th:มหาวิทยาลัยจอนส์ฮอปกินส์]]
[[vi:Đại học Johns Hopkins]]
[[zh:约翰·霍普金斯大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
