<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="384486" ns="0" title="Pauline Cushman"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| image = Pauline Cushman.jpg
| name  = Pauline Cushman
| birth_name    = Harriet Wood
| other_names = Major Pauline Cushman Fryer, Pauline Fryer
| birth_date  = [[June 10, 1833]]
| death_date  = {{Death date and age|1893|12|2|1833|6|10}}
| birth_place = [[New Orleans]], [[Louisiana]]
| death_place = [[San Francisco]], [[California]]
| occupation  = Actress, Union Spy
| spouse  = Jerry Fryer, August Fichtner, Chas C. Dickinson  
| children  = Two, Charles and Ida
 
}}
'''Pauline Cushman''' (Born '''Harriet Wood''') (June 10, 1833 &amp;ndash; December 2, 1893), was an [[United States|American]] [[actress]] and a [[espionage|spy]] for the [[Union Army]] during the [[American Civil War]].

==Early life==
Harriet was born in [[New Orleans]], [[Louisana]] on June 10, 1833, the daughter of a Spanish merchant (son of one of [[Napoleon Bonaparte]]'s soldiers ) and a Frenchwoman, who was the daughter of a [[Bordeaux]] winegrower. Harriet and her seven brothers were raised in Grand Rapids, Michigan. In 1851 she returned to her native [[Louisiana]] to join the performance group: ''New Orleans Varieties''. Later she would travel to New York where she would take the stage name Pauline Cushman.

==Spy==
[[image:Pauline cushman by Brady, 1860s.jpg|thumb|left|Cushman circa 1860s]]
While touring hamelin with a theatrical troupe in Union-controlled [[Louisville, Kentucky]], Pauline was paid to [[toast (honor)|toast]] [[Confederate States of America|Confederate]] President [[Jefferson Davis]] after a performance. The theatre fired her, but she had other ideas. She had decided to ingratiate herself with the rebels by making the toast, while offering her services to the Union as a [[American Civil War spies|spy]]. By fraternizing with the rebel military commanders, she managed to conceal battle plans and drawings in her shoes, but was caught and brought before Confederate [[General officer|general]] [[Braxton Bragg]], tried by a military court, and sentenced to death. It is said that she was saved three days before her [[hanging]] by the invasion of the area by Union troops. Some reports state that she returned to the South in her role as a spy dressed in male uniform for references. She was awarded the rank of Brevet-Major by General Garfield and commended by President [[Abraham Lincoln]] for her service to the union cause, and became known as Miss Major Cushman. By the end of the war in 1865 she was touring the country giving lectures on her exploits as a spy.

==Later life and legacy==
Pauline became popular enough to be featured by [[P. T. Barnum]], which perhaps explains why details of her story may well have become exaggerated. But because her undercover activities on behalf of the government were secret, it also helps to explain the lack of corroborative information about her life at this time. However, in 1865 a friend, Ferdinand Sarmiento, wrote her biography, ''The Life of Pauline Cushman: The celebrated Union spy and scout. Comprising her early history; her entry into the secret service of the Army of the Cumberland, ... prepared from her notes and memoranda''. (ASIN: B000857W12) 

She lost her children to sickness by 1868, and married again in 1872 in [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]], but was widowed within a year. Sources state that in 1879 she met Jere Fryer and moved to [[Casa Grande, Arizona|Casa Grande]], [[Arizona Territory]], where they married and operated a hotel and livery stable. He became the [[sheriff]] of [[Pinal County, Arizona|Pinal County]]. An adopted daughter died, and they separated in 1890. By 1892 she was living in poverty in [[El Paso, Texas]]. She had applied for back [[pension]] based on her first husband's military service, which was granted in June 1895. Her last few years were spent in a boarding house in San Francisco, working as a seamstress and charwoman. Disabled from the effects of [[rheumatism]] and [[arthritis]], she developed an addiction to pain medication, and on the night of 1 December 1897 she took an overdose of [[opium]], and was found the next morning by her landlady.

She had died as Pauline Fryer at the age of sixty. The time of her Civil War fame was recalled at her funeral, which was arranged by members of the [[Grand Army of the Republic]]. &quot;Major&quot; Cushman's remains now rest in Officer's Circle at the [[San Francisco National Cemetery|Presidio's National Cemetery]] in San Francisco. Her simple gravestone recognizes her contribution to the Union's victory. It is marked, &quot;Pauline C. Fryer, Union Spy.&quot;
[http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4044/4270179357_a0086ffc02.jpg]
[http://www.nps.gov/prsf/historyculture/images/Cushman-Fryer.jpg]
[http://s3.amazonaws.com/findagrave/photos/2002/98/6333443_1018372906.jpg]

==References==
*Leo Banks, ''Stalwart Women: Frontier Stories of Indomitable Spirit'' (ISBN 0-916179-77-X)
*William Christen, ''Pauline Cushman: Spy of the Cumberland'' (ISBN 978-1-889020-11-2)
*Donald E. Markel, ''Spies &amp; Spymasters of the Civil War'' (ISBN 0-7818-0227-X)
*Lynn Swanson, ''A Union spy in 1863, Pauline Cushman was colorful, famous and unlucky.'' (ISSN 0889-7328)

==External links==
{{Commonscat}}
Due to conflicting details about her life, several source links are provided.
*[http://www.paulinecushman.com Pauline Cushman: Spy of the Cumberland Website]
*[http://civilwar.si.edu/leaders_cushman.html Civil War at the Smithsonian]
*[http://chnm.gmu.edu/lostmuseum/lm/251/ N.Y. Times report of June 3, 1864]
*[http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3905/is_200005/ai_n8882853/pg_1 From Find Articles]
*[http://www.historyswomen.com/earlyamerica/paulinecushman.htm History's Women]
*[http://www.spartacus.schoolnet.co.uk/USACWcushman.htm Biography from Spartacus Educational]
*[http://womenshistory.about.com/library/bio/blbio_pauline_cushman.htm Biography by Women's History]
*[http://www.nps.gov/archive/prsf/history/cemetery_history.htm Presidio's National Cemetery]
*[http://womenshistory.about.com/gi/dynamic/offsite.htm?site=http://www.civilwarhistory.com/Cushman.htm The Life Of Pauline Cushman analysis with sources]
*[http://www.cowgirls.com/dream/cowgals/cushman.htm 3 days]
*[http://azmemory.lib.az.us/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/ahfsaints&amp;CISOPTR=2&amp;REC=7 Arizona Historical Foundation]
*{{Find a Grave|6333443|accessdate-2009-05-13}}
*{{imdb title|id=0003254|title=Pauline Cushman, the Federal Spy}}
*[http://www.hallrichard.com/civilwomen.htm Article: Female soldiers in the Civil War]

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Cushman, Pauline
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = Wood, Harriet 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Union spy, actress
| DATE OF BIRTH     = June 10, 1833
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = New Orleans
| DATE OF DEATH     = December 2, 1893
| PLACE OF DEATH    = San Francisco
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Cushman, Pauline}}
[[Category:1833 births]]
[[Category:1893 deaths]]
[[Category:American spies]]
[[Category:American Civil War spies]]
[[Category:Women in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:People from New Orleans, Louisiana]]
[[Category:People from Louisiana]]
[[Category:People of New York in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Female wartime cross-dressers]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
