<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3854948" ns="0" title="War crimes of the Wehrmacht"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-179-1575-08, Ioannina, Deportation von Juden.jpg|thumb|A woman weeps during the deportation of Jews from [[Ioannina]] on March 25, 1944. The deportation was enforced by the German army. Almost all of the people deported were murdered on or shortly after April 11, 1944, when the train carrying them reached [[Auschwitz concentration camp|Auschwitz-Birkenau]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kehila&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Raptis&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;
{{Commons category|Deportation of Jews of Ioannina March 1944}}]]

'''War crimes of the ''Wehrmacht''''' were those carried out by the German armed forces during [[World War II]]. While the principal perpetrators of the [[Holocaust]] amongst German armed forces were the [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] 'political' armies (the ''[[SS-Totenkopfverbände]]'' and particularly the ''[[Einsatzgruppen]]''), the regular armed forces represented by the ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' committed war crimes of their own, particularly on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] in the [[Operation Barbarossa|war against the Soviet Union]]. The [[Nuremberg Trials]] at the end of World War II judged that the ''Wehrmacht'' was not an inherently criminal organization, but that it had committed crimes during the course of the war. More recently, the judgement of Nuremberg has come under question. 

The Israeli historian [[Omer Bartov]], a leading expert on the Wehrmacht&lt;ref name=&quot;Leitz, Bartov&quot;/&gt; wrote in 2003 that the Wehrmacht was a willing instrument of genocide, and that it is simply untrue that the Wehrmacht was an apolitical, professional fighting force that had only a few &quot;bad apples&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;/&gt; Bartov argues that far from being the &quot;untarnished shield&quot;, as successive German apologists stated after the war, the Wehrmacht was a criminal organization.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov&quot;/&gt;

==Before the war==
When the National Socialists ([[Nazi]]s) came to power, it was welcomed by many officers of the ''Wehrmacht'' as a way of creating the ''Wiederwehrhaftmachung'' of Germany, namely the total militariztion of German society in order to ensure that Germany did not lose the next war.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster&quot;/&gt; As such, what both the Nazis and the German Army wanted to see was a totally militarized ''[[Volksgemeinschaft]]'' that would be purged of those perceived internal enemies like the [[Jews]] who it was believed had &quot;stabbed&quot; Germany in &quot;the back&quot; in 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 268&quot;/&gt;

As such, many officers willingly embraced National Socialist ideology in the 1930s. Acting on his own initiative, the Defence Minister [[Werner von Blomberg]] had purged the Army of all its Jewish personnel in February 1934.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 268&quot;/&gt; On December 8, 1938, the Army leadership had instructed all officers to be thoroughly well versed in National Socialism and to apply its values in all situations. Starting in February 1939, pamphlets were issued that were made required reading in the Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 270&quot;/&gt; The content can be gauged by the titles: &quot;The Officer and Politics&quot;, &quot;Hitler's World Historical Mission&quot;, &quot;The Army in the Third Reich&quot;, &quot;The Battle for German Living Space&quot;, &quot;Hands off Danzig!&quot;, and &quot;The Final Solution of the Jewish Question in the Third Reich&quot;. In the last essay, the author, C.A. Holberg wrote:

{{quote|The defensive battle against Jewry will continue, even if the last Jew has left Germany. Two big and important tasks remain: 1) the eradication of all Jewish influence, above all in the economy and in culture; 2) the battle against World Jewry, which tries to incite all people in the world against Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 270&quot;/&gt;}}

Attitudes like the ones expressed above coloured all the instructions that came to ''Wehrmacht'' troops in the summer of 1939 as a way of preparing for the attack on Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 270&quot;/&gt;

==War crimes==	 
Some examples of the war crimes the ''Wehrmacht'' committed include:

===Invasion of Poland===
{{See also|German AB-Aktion in Poland|Częstochowa massacre}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title      = AB-Aktion
| image      = Polish hostages preparing by Nazi Germans for mass execution 1940.jpg
| caption    =A picture taken secretly by the [[Polish Underground]] of [[RSHA|Nazi Security Police]] rounding up Polish intelligentsia at [[Palmiry]] near [[Warsaw]] in 1940. 
| location   = [[Palmiry|Palmiry Forest]] and other locations in [[General Government|Occupied Poland]].
| target     = [[Polish people|Polish]] intellectuals and the upper classes.
| coordinates = 
| date       = Spring – summer 1940
| time       = 
| timezone   = 
| type       = [[Mass murder|Massacres]] 
| fatalities = 7,000
| injuries   = 
| perps      = {{flagicon|Germany|Nazi}} [[Nazi Germany]]
| perp       = 
| susperps   = 
| susperp    = 
| weapons    = [[Automatic weapons]]
| numparts   =
| numpart    =
| dfens      =
| dfen       =
}}

''Wehrmacht'' attitudes towards Poles were a combination of contempt, fear, and a belief that violence was the best way to deal with them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;/&gt;

''Wehrmacht'' units killed thousands of Polish civilians during the September 1939 campaign through executions and the [[terror bombing]] of cities. Any act of defiance was met with the most ruthless violence, although the Army leadership did seek to discourage so-called &quot;wild&quot; shootings&quot; where Wehrmacht troops would indiscriminately shoot all Poles on their own initiative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;/&gt; Court martial proceedings were begun against some of the junior officers who had led these shootings, but this was nullified on October 4 1939, when Hitler pardoned all military personnel who had been involved in war crimes in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;/&gt; After the end of hostilities, during the ''Wehrmacht'''s administration of Poland, which went on until October 25 1939, 531 towns and villages were burned; the ''Wehrmacht'' carried out 714 mass executions, alongside many incidents of plunder, banditry and murder. Altogether, it is estimated that 16,376 Poles fell victim to these atrocities. Approximately 60% of these crimes were committed by the ''Wehrmacht''.&lt;ref name=&quot;forgotten&quot;/&gt; ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers frequently engaged in the massacre of [[Jews]] on their own, rather than just assisting in rounding them up for the SS.&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;/&gt;

In the summer of 1940, [[Reinhard Heydrich]], the chief of the Reich Main Security Office (including the ''[[Gestapo]]''), noted that: &quot;...compared to the crimes, robberies and excesses committed by the army [part of the Wehrmacht], the SS and the police don't look all that bad&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bohler2&quot;/&gt; Even when the German Army was not involved in war crimes, all of the top military leaders were aware of what was happening in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;/&gt; None made any objection on moral principles; the few who did object did so because of concerns about discipline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;/&gt; Moreover, the general who objected the loudest to war crimes in Poland, General [[Johannes von Blaskowitz]], was opposed to the Army committing war crimes with the SS, not the idea of atrocities against Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov1&quot;/&gt; The Israeli historian [[Omer Bartov]] wrote that Blaskowitiz was actually &quot;legitimizing murder&quot; by expressing approval of SS massacres while demanding that the Army be kept out of the massacres as damaging to discipline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999, page 147&quot;/&gt; Bartov wrote that once officers and troops saw that murder was &quot;legitimate&quot; in Poland, the effect was that the Army tended to copy the SS.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999, page 147&quot;/&gt;

====Polish POWs====
{{See also|Massacre in Ciepielów}}
Numerous examples exist in which Polish soldiers were killed after capture; for instance, at [[Śladów]], where 252 [[prisoners of war]] (POW)s were [[German 4th Panzer Division#War Crimes|shot or drowned]], at [[Ciepielów (Masovian Voivodeship)|Ciepielów]], where some 300 POWs were killed, and at [[Zambrów]], where a further [[Massacre in Ciepielów|300 were killed]]. Polish POWs of Jewish origin were routinely selected and shot on the spot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Krakowski&quot;/&gt; The prisoners of the POW camp in [[Żyrardów]], captured after the [[Battle of the Bzura]], were denied any food and starved for ten days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bohler&quot;/&gt; In many cases Polish POWs were burned alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;boehler&quot;/&gt; Units of the [[7th Infantry Division (Poland)|Polish 7th Infantry Division]] were massacred after being captured in several individual acts of revenge for their resistance in combat. On September 11, ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers threw hand grenades into a school building where they kept Polish POWs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;/&gt;

====Mass rapes====
Rapes were committed by ''Wehrmacht'' forces against women and girls during the Invasion of Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;/&gt;

Rapes were also committed against Polish women and girls during mass executions carried out primarily by the ''[[Selbstschutz]]'', which were accompanied by ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers and on territory under the administration of the German military; the rapes were carried out before shooting the female captives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obozy podlegle organom policyjnym&quot;/&gt;

Only one case of rape was prosecuted by a German court during the military campaign in Poland, the case of gang rape committed by three soldiers against women of the Jewish Kaufmann family in [[Busko-Zdrój]]; however, the German judge sentenced the guilty for ''[[Rassenschande]]'' - shame against the [German] race as defined by the [[racial policy of Nazi Germany]] - and not rape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wprost&quot;/&gt;

====Destruction of Warsaw====
[[File:Destroyed Warsaw, capital of Poland, January 1945.jpg|thumb|During World War II [[Planned destruction of Warsaw|85% of buildings in Warsaw were destroyed by German troops]].]]

{{See also|Battle of Warsaw (1939)|Warsaw Uprising}}
Up to 13,000 soldiers and between 120,000 and 200,000 civilians were killed by German-led forces during the [[Warsaw Uprising]]. At least 5,000 German regular soldiers assisted the SS in crushing Polish resistance, most of them reserve units.&lt;ref name=&quot;publishing&quot;/&gt; Human shields were used by German forces during the fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kroker&quot;/&gt;

===Invasion of France===
====Vinkt massacre====
{{Main|Vinkt Massacre}}
Between May 25 and May 28, 1940, the ''Wehrmacht'' committed several war crimes in and near the small Belgian village of Vinkt. Hostages were taken and used as human shields. As the Belgian army continued to resist, farms were searched and looted, and more hostages were taken. In all, 86 civilians are known to have been executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;montefiore&quot;/&gt; Besides Vinkt, other massacres and shootings happened with estimates of 600 victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;weltanschauungskrieg&quot;/&gt;

===Invasion of the Soviet Union===
The German military had traditionally considered Communism in the Soviet Union to be a Jewish plot before the Third Reich. In 1918, Karl von Bothmer, the German Army's plenipotentiary in Moscow called the Bolsheviks &quot;a gang of Jews&quot; and expressed the desire &quot;to see a few hundred of these louts hanging on the Kremlin wall&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p. 118.&quot;/&gt; Evaluations of the Red Army by the visiting ''Reichswehr'' officers during the period of German-Soviet co-operation in the 1920s often show anti-Semitism with comments about the &quot;Jewish slyness&quot; of General Lev Snitman or the &quot;Jewish blood&quot; of General Leonid Vajner being very typical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p. 118.&quot;/&gt; In 1932, Ewald Banse, a leading German professor and a member of the National Association for the Military Sciences (a group secretly financed by the ''Reichswehr'') wrote in a pamphlet calling for &quot;intellectual world domination&quot; by Germany wrote that the Soviet leadership was mostly Jewish who dominated an apathetic and mindless Russian masses.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster2&quot;/&gt;
 
In 1935, Colonel [[Carl-Heinrich von Stülpnagel]] in a report about the military capacity of the Red Army wrote that the commissars were &quot;mostly of the Jewish race&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster3&quot;/&gt; 

====Commissar Order====
{{Main|Commissar Order}}
The order cast the war against Russia as one of ideological and racial differences, and it provided for the immediate liquidation of [[political commissar]]s in the Red Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 273&quot;/&gt; The order was formulated on Hitler's behalf in 1941 by the ''Wehrmacht'' command and distributed to field commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 502&quot;/&gt;  General [[Franz Halder]], contrary to what he was to claim after the war, did not oppose the Commissar Order, and instead welcomed it writing that &quot;Troops must participate in the ideological battle in the Eastern campaign to the end&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 502&quot;/&gt; The enforcement of the Commissar Order led to thousands of executions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 502&quot;/&gt; The German historian Jürgen Förster was to write in 1989 that it was simply not true as most German Army commanders claimed in their memoirs and some German historians like [[Ernst Nolte]] were still claiming that the Commissar Order was not enforced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 502&quot;/&gt;

On July 17, 1941 the OKW declared that the Wehrmact was to: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;free itself from all elements among the prisoners of war considered Bolshevik driving forces. The special situation of the Eastern Campaign therefore demands ''special measures'' [an euphemism for killing] which are to be carried out free from bureaucratic and administrative influence and with a willingness to accept responsibility. While so far the regulations and orders concerning prisoners of war were based solely on ''military'' considerations, now the ''political'' objective must be attained, which is to protect the German nation from Bolshevik inciters and forthwith take the occupied territory strictly in hand&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 504&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; As such, all Soviet POWs considered to be commissars together with all Jewish POWs were to handed over to the ''Einsatzgruppen'' to be shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 504&quot;/&gt; The OKW attached great importance to the killings of POWs believed to be commissars as it was believed that if the captured commissars reached POW camps in Germany that they would stage another ''Dolchstoß'' like that believed to have caused Germany's defeat in World War I.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 504&quot;/&gt; Between July–October 1941, between 580, 000-600, 000 POWs in Wehrmacht custody were turned over to the SS to be killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 504&quot;/&gt; In September 1941, both [[Helmuth James von Moltke]] and Admiral [[Wilhelm Canaris]] wrote memos pointing out to the OKW that the order of July 17, 1941 was illegal under international law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 505&quot;/&gt; In particular, both Moltke and Admiral Canaris noted that the German claim that Soviet POWs had no rights because the Soviet Union had not ratified the [[Third Geneva Convention|Geneva Convention]] was invalid as Germany had ratified the Geneva Convention and thus under international law was obliged to provide humane treatment for the POWs in its care.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 505&quot;/&gt; In response, Field-Marshal [[Wilhelm Keitel]] wrote: &quot;These scruples accord with the soldierly concepts of a chivalrous war! Here we are concerned with the extermination of an ideology. That is why I approve and defend this measure&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 505&quot;/&gt; 

In the summer of 1942, there was an illusory liberalization of the treatment of captured political officers. On June 10, the Gestapo chief [[Heinrich Müller (Gestapo)|Heinrich Müller]] issued an order on the segregation of prisoners and ordered that commissars be isolated from the rest of the prisoners and sent to [[Mauthausen-Gusen]] concentration camp. However, this did not change the plight of commissars much, as Mauthausen was one of the worst German concentration camps where they usually waited for a slow death. On October 20, 1942, Müller again ordered commissars captured in battle to be shot on the spot. Only those commissars who were identified as deserters were sent to Mauthausen.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt;

In the following months reports continued to be filed regarding the executions of Soviet commissars.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt; The last known account of the liquidation of a political officer came from units of Army Group South in July 1943.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt;

====Barbarossa Decree====
The background behind the Barbarossa Decree was laid out by Hitler during a high level meeting with military officials on March 30, 1941,&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt; where he declared that war against [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] Russia would be a war of [[genocide|extermination]], in which both the political and intellectual elites of Russia would be eradicated by German forces, in order to ensure a long-lasting German victory.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt; Hitler underlined that executions would not be a matter for military courts, but for the organised action of the military.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt; The decree, issued by [[Wilhelm Keitel|FeldMarshal Keitel]] a few weeks before [[Operation Barbarossa]], exempted punishable offenses committed by enemy civilians (in Russia) from the jurisdiction of [[court martial|military justice]]. Suspects were to be brought before an officer who would decide if they were to be shot. Prosecution of offenses against civilians by members of the ''Wehrmacht'' was decreed to be &quot;not required&quot; unless necessary for the maintenance of discipline. 

The order specified:
*&quot;The partisans are to be ruthlessly eliminated in battle or during attempts to escape,&quot; and all attacks by the civilian population against ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers are to be &quot;suppressed by the army on the spot by using extreme measures, till [the] annihilation of the attackers;
*Every officer in the German occupation in the East of the future will be entitled to perform execution(s) without trial, without any formalities, on any person suspected of having a hostile attitude towards the Germans&quot;, (the same applied to prisoners of war);
*&quot;If you have not managed to identify and punish the perpetrators of anti-German acts, you are allowed to apply the principle of collective responsibility. 'Collective measures' against residents of the area where the attack occurred can then be applied after approval by the battalion commander or higher level of command&quot;;
*German soldiers who commit crimes against humanity, the USSR and prisoners of war are to be exempted from criminal responsibility, even if they commit acts punishable according to German law.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Front&quot;/&gt;

The &quot;Guidelines for the Conduct of the Troops in Russia&quot; issued by the OKW on May 19th 1941  declared &quot;Judeo-Bolshevism&quot; to be the most deadly enemy of the German nation, and that &quot;It is against this destructive ideology and its adherents that Germany is waging war&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 500&quot;/&gt; The guidelines went on to demand &quot;ruthless and vigorous measures against Bolshevik inciters, guerrillas, saboteurs, Jews, and the complete elimination of all active and passive resistance.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 500&quot;/&gt; Influenced by the guidelines, in a directive sent out to the troops under his command, General [[Erich Hoepner]] of the Panzer Group 4 stated: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The war against Russia is an important chapter in the German nation's struggle for existence. It is the old battle of the Germanic against the Slavic people, of the defence of European culture against Muscovite-Asiatic inundation and of the repulse of Jewish Bolshevism. The objective of this battle must be the demolition of present-day Russia and must therefore be conducted with unprecedented severity. Every military action must be guided in planning and execution by an iron resolution to exterminate the enemy remorselessly and totally. In particular, no adherents of the contemporary Russian Bolshevik system are to be spared&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster4&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; In the same spirit, General Müller, who was the Wehrmacht's senior liaison officer for legal matters, in a lecture to military judges on June 11th 1941 advised the judges present that &quot;...in the operation to come, feelings of justice must in certain situations give way to military exigencies and then revert to old habits of warfare... One of the two adversaries must be finished off. Adherents of the hostile attitude are not be conserved, but liquidated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 501&quot;/&gt; General Müller declared that, in the war against the Soviet Union, any Soviet civilian who was felt to be hindering the German war effort was to be regarded as a &quot;guerrilla&quot; and shot on the spot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 501&quot;/&gt; The Army's Chief of Staff, General [[Franz Halder]], declared in a directive that in the event of guerrilla attacks, German troops were to impose &quot;collective measures of force&quot; by massacring villages.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 501&quot;/&gt;  

In November 1935, the psychological war laboratory of the ''Reich'' War Ministry submitted a study about how best to undermine Red Army morale should a German-Soviet war break out.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster5&quot;/&gt; Working closely with the émigré [[Russian Fascist Party]] based in [[Harbin]], the German psychological warfare unit created a series of pamphlets written in Russian for distribution in the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 122&quot;/&gt; Much of it was designed to play on Russian anti-Semitism, with one pamphlet calling the &quot;Gentlemen commissars and party functionaries&quot; a group of &quot;mostly filthy Jews&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 122&quot;/&gt; The pamphlet ended with the call for &quot;brother soldiers&quot; of the Red Army to rise up and kill all of the &quot;Jewish commissars&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 122&quot;/&gt; Though this material was not used at the time, later in 1941 the material the psychological war laboratory had developed in 1935 was dusted off, and served as the basis not only for propaganda in the Soviet Union but also for propaganda within the German Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;/&gt;  Before Barbarossa, German troops were exposed to violent anti-Semitic and anti-Slavic indoctrination via movies, radio, lectures, books and leaflets.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans59&quot;/&gt; The lectures were delivered by &quot;National Socialist Leadership Officers&quot;, who were created for that purpose, and by their junior officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans59&quot;/&gt; German Army propaganda portrayed the Soviet enemy in the most dehumanized terms, depicting the Red Army as a force of Slavic ''[[Untermensch]]'' (sub-humans) and &quot;Asiatic&quot; savages engaging in &quot;barbaric Asiatic fighting methods&quot; commanded by evil Jewish [[commissars]] to whom German troops were to grant no mercy.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster6&quot;/&gt; Typical of the German Army propaganda was the following passage from a pamphlet issued in June 1941:

{{quote|Anyone who has ever looked into the face of a Red commissar knows what the Bolsheviks are. There is no need here for theoretical reflections. It would be an insult to animals if one were to call the features of these, largely Jewish, tormentors of people beasts. They are the embodiment of the infernal, of the personified insane hatred of everything that is noble in humanity. In the shape of these commissars we witness the revolt of the subhuman against noble blood. The masses whom they are driving to their deaths with every means of icy terror and lunatic incitement would have brought about an end of all meaningful life, had the incursion not been prevented at the last moment;&quot; [the last statement is a reference to the &quot;preventive war&quot; that Barbarossa was alleged to be].&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;/&gt;}}

As a result of this sort of propaganda, the majority of the ''[[Wehrmacht Heer]]'' officers and soldiers tended to regard the war in Nazi terms, seeing their Soviet opponents as so much sub-human trash deserving to be trampled upon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;/&gt; One German soldier wrote home to his father on August 4th 1941 that:

{{quote|The pitiful hordes on the other side are nothing but felons who are driven by alcohol and the [commissars'] threat of pistols at their heads...They are nothing but a bunch of assholes!...Having encountered these Bolshevik hordes and having seen how they live has made a lasting impression on me. Everyone, even the last doubter, knows today that the battle against these sub-humans, who've been whipped into a frenzy by the Jews, was not only necessary but came in the nick of time. Our ''Führer'' has saved Europe from certain chaos.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;/&gt;}}

As a result of these views, the majority of the German Army worked enthusiastically with the SS in murdering Jews in the [[Soviet Union]]. The British historian [[Richard J. Evans]] wrote that junior officers tended to be especially zealous National Socialists with a third of them being Nazi Party members in 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans59&quot;/&gt; The ''Wehrmacht'' did not just obey Hitler's criminal orders for Barbarossa because of obedience, but rather because they shared Hitler's belief that the Soviet Union was run by Jews, and that it was necessary for Germany to completely destroy &quot;[[Judeo-Bolshevism]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 273&quot;/&gt; Jürgen Förster wrote that the majority of ''Wehrmacht'' officers sincerely believed that most Red Army commissars were Jews, and that the best way to defeat the Soviet Union was to kill all of the commissars so as to deprive the Russian soldiers of their Jewish leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster7&quot;/&gt; 

The order was in line with the interests of the ''Wehrmacht'' command, which was eager to secure logistical facilities and routes behind the front line for the divisions on the Eastern Front.&lt;ref name=Front/&gt;
On May 24th 1941, Field Marshal [[Walther von Brauchitsch]], the head of the German Army High Command (''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'' - OKH), slightly modified the assumptions of the &quot;Barbarossa Jurisdiction.&quot; His orders were to use the jurisdiction only in cases where the discipline of the army would not suffer. Contrary to what was claimed after the war, the ''Wehrmacht'' generals such as [[Heinz Guderian]], did not intend to mitigate the records of the jurisdiction of an order, or in any way violate Hitler's intentions.&lt;ref name=Front/&gt; His command was intended solely to prevent individual excesses which could damage discipline within army ranks, without changing the extermination intentions of the order.&lt;ref name=SDatner/&gt;

As part of the policy of harshness towards Slavic &quot;sub-humans&quot; and to prevent any tendency towards seeing the enemy as human, German troops were ordered to go out of their way to mistreat women and children in Russia.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov8&quot;/&gt; In October 1941, the commander of the 12th Infantry Division sent out a directive saying &quot;the carrying of information is mostly done by youngsters in the ages of 11-14&quot; and that &quot;as the Russian is more afraid of the truncheon than of weapons, flogging is the most advisable measure for interrogation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov9&quot;/&gt; In November 1941, the commander of the 18th Panzer Division warned his soldiers not to have sex with &quot;sub-human&quot; Russian women, and ordered that any Russian women found having sex with a German soldier was to be handed over to the SS to be executed at once.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov10&quot;/&gt; It should be noted that these directives applied only to consensual sex; the Wehrmacht's view towards rape was much more tolerant.

====Anti-Partisan and anti-Jewish actions====
[[Image:Wsaw-exec.jpg|thumb|left|A mass execution of Polish hostages in [[Palmiry]] - The German execution of 51 Polish hostages in retaliation for an attack on a Nazi police station by the underground organization &quot;White Eagle&quot;]]
Under the guise of anti-[[Soviet partisans|partisan]] operations, the ''Wehrmacht'' in the Soviet Union massacred Jews. Co-operation with the SS in anti-partisan and anti-Jewish operations was close and intensive.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 276&quot;/&gt; In the spring of 1941, Reinhard Heydrich and the First Quartermaster of the German Army, General [[Eduard Wagner]] successfully completed negotiations for co-operation between the ''Einsatzgruppen'' and the German Army to allow the implementation of &quot;special tasks&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;hillgruber&quot;/&gt; Following the Heydrich-Wagner agreement on April 28, 1941, Feldmarshal [[Walther von Brauchitsch]] ordered when Operation Barbarossa began that all German Army commanders were to identify and register all Jews in the occupied areas in the Soviet Union at once and to co-operate fully with the ''Einsatzgruppen''&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 96&quot;/&gt; Each ''Einsatzgruppen'', in its area of operations, were under the control of the Higher SS-Police Chiefs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 96&quot;/&gt; In a further agreement between the Army and the SS concluded in May 1941 by General Wagner and [[Walter Schellenberg]], it was agreed that the ''Einsatzgruppen'' in front-line areas were to operate under Army command while the Army would provide the ''Einsatzgruppen'' with all necessary logistical support.&lt;ref name=&quot;richard&quot;/&gt;

In August 1941, following the protests by two Lutheran chaplains about the massacre of a group of Jewish women and children at [[Bila Tserkva|Byelaya Tserkov]], General von Reichenau wrote:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The conclusion of the report in question contains the following sentence, &quot;In the case in question, measures against women and children were undertaken which in no way differ from atrocities carried out by the enemy about which the troops are continually being informed&quot;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have to describe this assessment as incorrect, inappropriate and impertinent in the extreme. Moreover this comment was written in an open communication which passes through many hands.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It would have been far better if the report had not been written at all.&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;dressen&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; One SS man who saw the killings at Byelaya Tserkov described them as follows:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;I went to the woods alone. The Wehrmacht had already dug a grave. The children were brought along in a tractor. I had nothing to do with this technical procedure. The Ukrainians were standing around trembling. The children were taken down from the tractor. They were lined up along the top of the grave and shot so that they fell into it. The Ukrainians did not aim at any particular part of the body. They fell into the grave. The wailing was indescribable. I shall never forget the scene throughout my life. I find it very hard to bear. I particularly remember a small fair-haired girl who took me by the hand. She too was shot later...The grave was near some woods. It was not near the rifle-range. The execution must had taken place in the afternoon at about 3.30 or 4.00. It took place the day after the discussions at the ''Feldkommandanten''...Many children were hit four or five times before they died.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;dressen11&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In the summer of 1941, the [[SS Cavalry Brigade]] commanded by [[Hermann Fegelein]] during the course of &quot;anti-partisan&quot; [[Pripyat swamps (punitive operation)|operations]] in the [[Pripyat Marshes]] killed 699 [[Red Army]] soldiers, 1,100 partisans and 14,178 Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 276&quot;/&gt; Before the operation, Fegelein had been ordered to shoot all adult Jews while driving the women and children into the marshes. After the operation, General [[Max von Schenckendorff]], who commanded the rear areas of [[Army Group Centre]] ordered on August 10, 1941 that all ''Wehrmacht'' [[Security Division (Germany)|security divisions]] when on anti-partisan duty were to emulate Fegelein's example and organized between September 24 and 26 1941 in [[Mogilev]], a joint SS-''Wehrmacht'' seminar on how best to murder Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 276&quot;/&gt; The seminar ended with the 7th Company of Police Battalion 322 shooting 32 Jews at a village called Knjashizy before the assembled officers as an example of how to &quot;screen&quot; the population for partisans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 277&quot;/&gt; As the war diary of the Battalion 322 read:

{{quote|The action, first scheduled as a training exercise was carried out under real-life conditions (''ernstfallmässig'') in the village itself. Strangers, especially partisans could not be found. The screening of the population, however resulted in 13 Jews, 27 Jewish women and 11 Jewish children, of which 13 Jews and 19 Jewish women were shot in co-operation with the Security Service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 277&quot;/&gt;}}

Based on what they had learned during the Mogilev seminar, one ''Wehrmacht'' officer told his men &quot;Where the partisan is, there is the Jew and where the Jew is, there is the partisan&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 277&quot;/&gt;

The 707th division of the ''Wehrmacht'' put this principle into practice during an &quot;anti-partisan&quot; sweep that saw the division shoot 10,431 people out of the 19,940 it had detained during the sweep while suffering only two dead and five wounded in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 278&quot;/&gt; In Order #24 of November 24, 1941, the commander of the 707th division declared:

{{quote|5. ''Jews and Gypsies'':...As already has been ordered, the Jews have to vanish from the flat country and the Gypsies have to be annihilated too. The carrying out of ''larger'' Jewish actions is not the task of the divisional units. They are carried out by civilian or police authorities, if necessary ordered by the commandant of White Ruthenia, if he has special units at his disposal, or for security reasons and in the case of collective punishments. When smaller or larger groups of Jews are met in the flat country, they can be liquidated by divisional units or be massed in the ghettos near bigger villages designated for that purpose, where they can be handed over to the civilian authority or the SD.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 278&quot;/&gt;}}

At [[Myrhorod|Mirgorod]], the 62nd Infantry Division executed &quot;the entire Jewish population (168 people) for associating with partisans&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 279&quot;/&gt; At [[Novomoskovsk, Ukraine|Novomoskovsk]], the 444th Security Division reported that they had killed &quot;305 bandits, 6 women with rifles (''Flintenweiber''), 39 prisoners-of-war and 136 Jews&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 279&quot;/&gt; In revenge for a partisan attack that had killed one German soldier, the ''Ersatz-Brigade'' 202 &quot;as an act of retaliation shot 20 Jews from the villages of Bobosjanka and Gornostajewka and burnt down 5 Jew-houses&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster12&quot;/&gt; Even more extreme was the case in [[Serbia]], where the majority of the Jews there were murdered by the Wehrmacht, not the SS.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 280&quot;/&gt; At [[Dulag 183|Šabac]], &quot;Central European Jewish refugees, mostly [[Austrians|Austrian]]s, were shot by troops of predominantly Austrian origin in retaliation for casualties inflicted by Serbian partisans on the German Army&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 279&quot;/&gt; The orders issued by Field Marshal Wilhelm Keitel in September 1941 called for the German Army to shoot 100 Serbs for every German soldier killed by the Serb guerrillas and did not call for Jews to be singled out.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 pages 279-280&quot;/&gt; But because of rampant anti-Semitism in the German officer corps, it was more or less automatically assumed that the Serbian Jewish community were behind all of the partisan attacks, hence the targeting of Jews in the mass shootings carried out in retaliation for guerilla attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 pages 279-280&quot;/&gt; The German historian Jürgen Förster, a leading expert on the subject of ''Wehrmacht'' war crimes, argued that the ''Wehrmacht'' played a key role in the Holocaust and it is wrong to ascribe the ''Shoah'' as solely the work of the SS while the ''Wehrmacht'' were a more or less passive and disapproving bystander.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 280&quot;/&gt;

[[Image:Kiev Jew Killings in Ivangorod (1942).jpg|thumb|left||Killing of Jews at Ivangorod, Ukraine, 1942. A woman is attempting to protect a child with her own body just before they are fired on with rifles at close range]]
Besides its own war crimes, the Wehrmacht worked very closely with the ''Einsatzgruppen'' in murdering members of the Jewish population of the Soviet Union. On October 10, 1941 General [[Walther von Reichenau]] drafted an order to be read to the troops under his command stating that: &quot;the soldier must achieve full understanding of the necessity for a harsh but just vengeance against Jewish subhumanity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 102&quot;/&gt; Upon hearing of Reichenau's [[Severity Order]], Field Marshal [[Gerd von Rundstedt]], the commander of [[Army Group South]] announced his &quot;complete agreement&quot; with it, and sent out a circular to all of the Army generals under his command urging them to send out their own versions of the Severity Order, which would impress upon the troops the need to exterminate Jews.&lt;ref name=&quot;pantheon&quot;/&gt; General [[Erich von Manstein]], in an order to his troops on November 20, 1941 stated: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Jewry is the middleman between the enemy at our rear and the still fighting remnants of the Red Army and the Red leadership; more than in Europe, it [Jewry] occupies all key posts of the political leadership and administration, of trade and crafts and forms the nucleus for all disquiet and possible revolts. The Jewish-Bolshevist system must be exterminated once and for all.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 102&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; On July 6, 1941 ''[[Einsatzkommando]]'' 4b of ''[[Einsatzgruppe]]'' C, which was operating in [[Tarnopol]] at the time sent a report which noted &quot;Armed forces surprisingly welcome hostility against the Jews&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilburg, Raul p 301&quot;/&gt; On September 8, 1941 ''Einsatzgruppe'' D reported that relations with the German Army were &quot;excellent&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilburg, Raul p 301&quot;/&gt; [[Franz Walter Stahlecker]] of ''Einsatzgruppe'' A wrote in September 1941 that [[Army Group North]] had been exemplary in co-operating with his men in murdering Jews and that relations with the Fourth Panzer Army commanded by General [[Erich Hoepner]] were &quot;very close, almost cordial&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilburg, Raul p 301&quot;/&gt;

====Mass rapes====
Rapes were allowed in practice by the German military in eastern and southeastern Europe, while northern and western countries were spared.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muss&quot;/&gt;
Historian [[Szymon Datner]] wrote in his work about the fate of POWs taken by the Wehrmacht, that thousands of Soviet female nurses, doctors and field medics fell victim to rape when captured, and were often murdered afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;SDatner&quot;/&gt; 
Ruth Seifert in ''War and Rape. Analytical Approaches'' wrote: &quot;in the Eastern territories the ''Wehrmacht'' used to brand the bodies of captured partisan women - and other women as well - with the words &quot;Whore for Hitler's troops&quot; and to use them accordingly.&quot;&lt;ref name=seifert1992/&gt;

[[Birgit Beck]] in her work ''Rape: The Military Trials of Sexual Crimes Committed by Soldiers in the Wehrmacht, 1939-1944'' describes the leniency in punishing sex crimes by German authorities in the East, at the same time pointing out heavy punishments applied in the West.&lt;ref name=&quot;h-net.org&quot;/&gt; If a soldier who committed a rape was subsequently convicted by a court-martial, he would usually be sentenced to four years in prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck&quot;/&gt; The German penal code was also valid for soldiers in war.&lt;ref name=&quot;beck13&quot;/&gt;

Rapes were rarely prosecuted in practice; in Denmark German rapes were not widespread, and German officials promised to punish them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muss&quot;/&gt; Rape by Germans of non-German women was not taken seriously, nor was it punishable by death, especially in the eastern European territories.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt;

In Soviet Russia rapes were only a concern if they undermined military discipline.&lt;ref name=&quot;h-net.org&quot;/&gt; The German military command viewed them as another method of crushing Soviet resistance.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt; Since 1941, rape was theoretically punishable with the death sentence; however, this only concerned the rape of German women and was intended to protect German communities.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt; 
Estimates regarding the rape of Soviet women by the ''Wehrmacht'' reached up to 10,000,000 cases, with between 750,000 and 1,000,000 children born as a result.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wendy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;implementing&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;encounters&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;gegenwind&quot;/&gt;

In October 1940 the laws on rape were changed, making it a &quot;petitioned crime&quot; - that is a crime for which punishment had to be requested. Historian [[Christa Paul]] writes that this resulted in &quot;a nearly complete absence of prosecution and punishment for rape&quot;.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt; There were rape cases in the east where the perpetrators were sentenced if the rape was highly visible, damaging to the image of the German Army and the courts were willing to pass a condemning verdict against the accused.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt;

According to the historian [[Regina Mühlhäuser]] the ''Wehrmacht'' also used sexual torture and undressing in numerous cases of interrogations.&lt;ref name=&quot;eurozine&quot;/&gt;

===''Wehrmacht'' brothel system===
{{Main|German military brothels in World War II}}
The ''Wehrmacht'' also ran brothels where women were forced to work.&lt;ref name=&quot;seifert1992&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Nuremberg&quot;/&gt; The reason for establishing these brothels was the German officials' fear of [[Sexually transmitted disease|venereal disease]] and [[onanism]] (masturbation). The ''Oberfeldarzt der Wehrmacht'' (Chief Field Doctor of the Wehrmacht) drew attention to &quot;the danger of [the] spread of [[homosexualism]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=Wprost/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ostrowska&quot;/&gt;

On May 3, 1941 the Foreign Ministry of the [[Polish Government in Exile]] issued a document describing the mass raids carried out in Polish cities with the aim of capturing young women, who were later forced to work in brothels attended by German officers and soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wprost&quot;/&gt;

In the Soviet Union women were kidnapped by German forces for prostitution; one report by the [[International Military Tribunal]] stated that &quot;in the city of Smolensk the German Command opened a brothel for officers in one of the hotels into which hundreds of women and girls were driven; they were mercilessly dragged down the street by their arms and hair.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;/&gt;

====Nuremberg Trials====
The [[Nuremberg trials]] did not prosecute anyone for rape or other sexual violence; rape was defined as a crime against humanity, but prosecution was not included because such crimes had &quot;no nexus to war&quot;.&lt;ref name=Wendy/&gt;

===POW maltreatment===
====POW Camps====
{{Main|Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs}} 
{{See also|Prisoner of war|Geneva Convention (1929)}}
The ''Third [[Geneva Convention (1929)]] relative to the Treatment of [[Prisoners of War]]'' had been signed by Germany and [http://www.cicr.org/ihl.nsf/WebSign?ReadForm&amp;id=305&amp;ps=P most other countries] in 1929, while the USSR and [[Empire of Japan|Japan]] did not sign until after the war (the final version of the [[Third Geneva Convention]] of 1949). This meant that Germany was legally obliged to treat all POWs according to it, while in turn, Germans captured by the Red Army could not expect to be treated in such a manner. The Soviet Union and Japan did not treat prisoners of war in accordance with the Geneva Convention.

While the Wehrmacht's prisoner-of-war camps for inmates from the west generally satisfied the humanitarian requirement prescribed by international law, prisoners from Poland (which never capitulated) and the USSR were incarcerated under significantly worse conditions. 

By December 1941, more than 2.4 million Soviet Red Army troops had been taken prisoner. These men suffered from malnutrition and diseases such as [[typhus]] that resulted from the Wehrmacht's failure to provide sufficient food, shelter, proper sanitation and medical care. Prisoners were regularly subject to torture, beatings and humiliation. All Jews, commissars, &quot;intellectuals&quot; and Muslims serving in the Red Army were either executed by the Wehrmacht or handed over to the SS to be shot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 pages 529-530&quot;/&gt; The Muslim POWs were shot because they were circumcised, and therefore might be Jewish; it was felt to be safer to simply shoot all circumcised POWs rather run the risk that a Jewish POW might escape execution by claiming to be a Muslim.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 pages 529-530&quot;/&gt; Reflecting the close co-operation between the Wehrmacht and the SS was an ''Einsatzgruppen'' report, which read:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;In Borispol, following a demand by the Commandant of the local P/W camp, a platoon of ''Sonderkommando'' 4 shot 752 Jewish prisoners of war on 14 October and 356 on 16 October 1941 including several commissars and 78 wounded Jews handed over by the camp medical officer.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 page 529&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; According to a RHSA report of December 5 1941, the Wehrmacht had since June 22 handed over to the ''Einsatzgruppen'' 16, 000 Soviet POWs to be &quot;liquidated&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 page 529&quot;/&gt; A Typical of the Wehrmacht's treatment of Soviet POWs were the reports of the 11th Army commanded by [[Erich von Manstein]] on the &quot;wastage&quot; rates in the first half of 1942. According to the reports:&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 page 529&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Date !! Died/shot !! Escaped !! Handed over to the SD !! Discharged !! Total wastage
|-
| 7.1.1942 || 135 || 181 || 140 || 26 || 507
|-
| 6.2.1942 || 1,116 || 155 || 111 || 2,293 || 3,680
|-
| 6.3.1942 || 1,115 || 36 || 66 || 298 || 1,522
|}

Between the launching of [[Operation Barbarossa]] in the summer of 1941 and the following spring, 2.8 million of the 3.2 million prisoners taken died while in German hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies_271&quot;/&gt; The German failure to attain their anticipated victory in the East led to significant shortages of labor for German war production and, beginning in 1942, prisoners of war in the eastern POW camps — primarily Soviets — were seen as a source of slave labor to keep Germany's wartime economy running.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies_271&quot; /&gt; On  August 6 1941, the OKW declared that Soviet POWs capable of work were to receive 2,200 calories/day and those not capable of work 2,040 calories/day.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster14&quot;/&gt; On October 21 1941, the OKW ordered a huge reduction in the food rations for Soviet POWs, with POWs incapable of work henceforth to receive only 1,490 calories/day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 507&quot;/&gt; In a meeting of senior generals called at Orša on November 13 1941, the Army's First Quarter-master General [[Eduard Wagner]] stated &quot;Non-working prisoners of war in the camps are to starve&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 507&quot;/&gt;

A grand total of 5.7 million Soviet soldiers were taken prisoner during the war, of whom at least 3.3 million (58 percent of the total) died in captivity.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans_185&quot;/&gt;

====Massacres====
The killing of POWs by ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers started during the September 1939 Poland campaign. In many cases large groups of Polish soldiers were murdered after capture. Hitler's [[Commando Order]], issued in 1942, provided &quot;justification&quot; for the shooting of enemy [[commando]]s, whether uniformed or not.  

The massacres include that of at least 1500 black French POWs of West African origin and was preceded by propaganda depicting the Africans as savages.&lt;ref name=&quot;cambridge&quot;/&gt; From October 1942 onwards, the ''Wehrmacht'' carried out the 'Commando Order' calling for the summary execution of all captured commandos, even if in uniform. After the [[Italian armistice]] in 1943, many POWs were executed on several occasions when Italian troops resisted their forcible disarmament by the Germans. The [[massacre of the Acqui Division]] at [[Kefalonia]] is the most infamous.

On March 26, 1944, 15 uniformed US Army officers and men were shot without trial at [[La Spezia]], in Italy, after orders of the commander of the German 75th Army Corps, General [[Anton Dostler]], despite the opposition of his subordinates of the 135th Fortress Brigade. Dostler was sentenced to death by an American [[military tribunal]] and executed by firing squad in December 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;uwe&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;www&quot;/&gt;

===Night and Fog Decree===
{{Main|Nacht und Nebel}}
[[File:KZ-Hinzert-Plakette-Nacht-und-Nebel.jpg|thumb|A commemorative plaque to the French victims at [[Hinzert concentration camp]], using the expressions &quot;Nacht und Nebel&quot; and &quot;NN-Deported&quot;]]
The [[Night and Fog Decree]], issued by Hitler in 1941 and disseminated along with a directive from Keitel, was operated within the conquered territories in the West (Belgium, France, Luxembourg, Norway, Denmark and the Netherlands). The decree allowed those &quot;endangering German security&quot; to be seized and made to disappear without trace. Keitel's directive stated that &quot;efficient intimidation can only be achieved either by capital punishment or by measures by which the relatives of the criminal and the population do not know his fate.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;yjil&quot;/&gt;

===Reprisal actions===
{{See also|Partisan (military)}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-779-0003-22, Griechenland, Schild über Zestörung von Kandanos.jpg|left|upright|thumb|A German soldier in front of a sign erected after the [[razing of Kandanos]], in Crete in 1941. The sign roughly translates to &quot;Kandanos was destroyed in reprisal for the brutal murders of paratrooper and pioneer convoys in an ambush by armed men and women.&quot;]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-166-0527-04, Kreta, Kondomari, Erschießung von Zivilisten.jpg|thumb|The murder of Greek civilians in [[Massacre of Kondomari|Kondomari]], [[Crete]] by German Paratroopers 1941 (although they operated under the command of the [[Luftwaffe]])]]

In Yugoslavia and Greece, many villages were razed and their inhabitants murdered during anti-partisan operations. Examples in Greece include: [[Massacre of Kondomari|Kondomari]], [[Distomo massacre|Distomo]], [[Kommeno]], [[Drakeia massacre|Drakeia]] and [[Massacre of Kalavryta|Kalavryta]]; the [[razing of Kandanos]] and the holocausts of [[holocaust of Viannos|Viannos]] and [[holocaust of Kedros|Kedros]].

In [[Polish resistance movement in World War II|occupied Poland]] and the USSR, hundreds of villages were wiped out and their inhabitants murdered. In the USSR, captured [[Soviet partisans|Soviet]] and [[Jewish partisans]] were used to sweep fields of [[land mine]]s. 

In a number of occupied countries, the ''Wehrmacht'''s response to partisan attacks by [[resistance movement]]s was to take and shoot hostages. Examples are: [[Putten]] (Netherlands), [[Oradour-sur-Glane]] (France), [[Telavåg]] (Norway) and [[Lidice]] (Czech Republic). As many as 100 hostages were murdered for every German killed. In 1944, prior to and after the [[D-Day]] invasion, the [[French Resistance]] and the [[Maquis (World War II)|Maquis]] increased their activities against all German organisations, including the ''Wehrmacht'' and ''[[Waffen-SS]]''. 

In issuing orders for hostage-taking, Keitel stated that &quot;it is important that these should include well-known personalities or members of their families.&quot; A ''Wehrmacht'' commander in France stated that &quot;the better known the hostages to be shot, the greater will be the deterrent effect on the perpetrators.&quot;  The author [[William Shirer]] stated that over 30,000 hostages are believed to have been executed in the West alone.{{Citation needed|date=February 2009}} The ''Wehrmacht'''s hostage policy was also pursued in Greece, Yugoslavia, Scandinavia, and Poland.

===Human experimentation===
{{see also|Doctor's Trial}}
[[File:Siegfried Handloser NS-Arzt.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Siegfried Handloser]] at Nuremberg in November 1946. He was ''Generaloberstabsarzt'' (Colonel General, Medical Service); Medical Inspector of the Army (''Heeressanitätsinspekteur''); and Chief of the Medical Services of the Armed Forces (''Chef des Wehrmachtsanitätswesens''). He was  convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment]] 

Throughout the war Germany engaged in numerous experiments on human prisoners and POWs. The ''Wehrmacht'' had full knowledge of those experiments, and performed some of its own. It provided assistance regarding: 
*[[Nazi human experimentation#High altitude experiments|High altitude test]]s
*[[Nazi human experimentation#Sea water experiments|Drinking seawater]]
*[[Nazi human experimentation#Freezing experiments|Freezing of the human body]]
*typhus research.&lt;ref name=&quot;experimentation&quot;/&gt;

In many cases the test subjects, even if they survived, were murdered afterwards to study any changes within their bodies that happened during the experiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;diapozytyw&quot;/&gt;

Examples of experiments conducted by the ''Wehrmacht'' include:

*Experiments on [[homosexuals]]: ''Wehrmacht'' doctors wanted to &quot;cure&quot; homosexuality by hormone treatments and putting homosexuals into battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;university15&quot;/&gt;

*Experiments on prisoners at [[Auschwitz-Birkenau]] by doctor [[Emil Kaschub]]. Kaschub came from Upper Silesia and was an ensign in the ''Wehrmacht'' (he was not a member of the SS). He performed experiments on the limbs of middle-aged and young prisoners; they would deliberately be infected with various toxic substances, which caused sores, abscesses and pain. The condition of the patients would be photographed by Kaschub every few days and liquid from their wounds collected. The probable motive for those experiments was to find out how soldiers made themselves sick in order to escape service in the ''Wehrmacht''.&lt;ref name=&quot;interpretations&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;resistance&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;university16&quot;/&gt;

*In August 1941. the staff doctor assigned to the Sixth Army, [[Gerhart Panning]], learned about captured Russian [[Expanding bullet|dumdum bullets]] by using Jewish POWs. To determine the effects of this type of ammunition on German soldiers, he decided to test them on other human beings after asking [[Schutzstaffel|SS]]-''[[Standartenführer]]'' (Colonel) and a member of the [[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]] [[Paul Blobel]] for some &quot;guinea pigs&quot;, (Jewish POWs).&lt;ref name=&quot;organization&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Holocaust in the Soviet Union Symposium Presentations&quot;/&gt;

==Biological warfare==
During the war members of the ''Wehrmacht'' attempted to influence Hitler's decision to study biological warfare only regarding defense. The head of the Science Division of the ''Wehrmacht'', Erich Schumann, urged the [[Führer]] that ''&quot;America must be attacked simultaneously with various human and animal epidemic pathogens, as well as plant pests.&quot;''&lt;ref name=&quot;deichmann&quot;/&gt; Laboratory tests were prepared for the use of [[Plague (disease)|plague]], [[anthrax]], [[cholera]] and [[typhoid]]. The possibility of using [[foot and mouth disease]] against Britain was also studied.&lt;ref name=&quot;deichmann17&quot;/&gt;

==Postwar views==
At the end of the war in 1945, several ''Wehrmacht'' generals made a statement that defended the actions against partisans, the executions of hostages and the use of slave labor as necessary to the war effort. The generals contended that the Holocaust was committed by the SS and its partner organizations, and that the ''Wehrmacht'' command had been unaware of these actions in the death camps. The statement said that the armed forces had fought honorably and left the impression that the ''Wehrmacht'' had not committed war crimes.

However, a number of high-ranking ''Wehrmacht'' officers stood trial for war crimes. The ''Oberkommando der Wehrmacht'' (OKW) commander-in-chief, Field Marshal Wilhelm Keitel and chief of operations staff [[Alfred Jodl]], were both indicted and tried for war crimes by the [[International Military Tribunal]] at [[Nuremberg]] in 1946. They were convicted of all charges, sentenced to death and executed by hanging, although Jodl was acquitted post-mortem seven years later. While the tribunal declared that the ''Gestapo'', ''[[Sicherheitsdienst|SD]]'' and ''SS'' (including the ''Waffen-SS'') were inherently criminal organizations, the court did not reach the same conclusion with respect to the ''Wehrmacht'' General Staff and High Command. The accused were members of the Nazi Party itself and were executing the parties' beliefs through their rank. The German ''Wehrmacht'' along with Allied Armies committed what are classified as war crimes. The SS and political &quot;Armed&quot; groups committed what is classified as crimes against humanity. 

The prosecution of war crimes lost momentum during the 1950s as the [[Cold War]] intensified; both German states needed to establish armed forces and could not do so without trained officers and soldiers that had served in the ''Wehrmacht''. German historiography in the 1950s viewed war crimes by German soldiers as exceptional rather than ordinary; soldiers were seen as victims of the Nazi regime. Traces of this attitude can still be seen in some German works today, which minimize the number of soldiers who took part in Nazi crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;university18&quot;/&gt; This was especially the case as the German public in the immediate post-war period were more interested in seeing themselves rather than others as victims.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt; Thus the subject of Red Army atrocities against German civilians in 1944-45 received vastly more popular and historical interest in the 1950s than did the subject of Wehrmacht atrocities against Soviet civilians in 1941-44.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt; Beyond that, Operation Barbarossa had been portrayed in Germany as a &quot;preventive war&quot; forced on Germany by Soviet attack alleged to be planned for July 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt; This claim was widely believed in the ''Reich'' during the war, and indeed was so popular that as late as the 1950s some West German historians were still arguing Operation Barbarossa was a &quot;preventive war&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt; As a result of this view of Operation Barbarossa, meant that for many Germans, violence inflicted by the Wehrmacht on Soviet civilians and Pows was seen as something that the Soviets had brought down on themselves, hence the absence of any guilt on the part of many Germans.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster19&quot;/&gt; Cold War priorities and taboos about revisiting the most unpleasant aspects of World War II meant that the ''Wehrmacht'''s role in war crimes was not seriously re-examined until the early 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leitz, Bartov&quot;/&gt; 

In their memoirs, German Army generals claimed that the war had been a &quot;clean war&quot; on their part with the Army fighting because of the noble Prussian-German traditions, patriotism and a deep sense of honour and duty and that National Socialism had virtually no influence on the Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans55&quot;/&gt; In this version, almost all German war crimes were the work of the SS and any &quot;excesses&quot; committed by the Army where only the product of a long and bitter war and were no different from Allied war crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans55&quot;/&gt; Very typical were the claim of the commander of the 12th Infantry Division, who claimed in his memoirs that all of the battles fought by his men were &quot;always fairly conducted, through tough and bitter. Its name, its coat of arms and its weapons remained unsullied till the very last day as even the enemy conceded&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans&quot;/&gt; Such claims were widely believed not only in Germany but abroad, with the British military historian Captain [[Basil Liddell Hart]] writing that &quot;the German Army in the field on the whole observed the rules of war better than in 1914-18&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans20&quot;/&gt; Typical{{Fact|date=November 2011}} of post-war views was an anthology about [[Wilhelm Keitel]] edited by Walter Görlitz published in 1961 entitled ''Felddmarshal Wilhelm Keitel Offizier oder Verbrecher?'' (''Fieldmarshal Wilhelm Keitel Officer or Criminal?'')&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg2010_pg6&quot;/&gt; The American historian [[Gerhard Weinberg]] noted that the general thesis was indicated by the question in the subtitle, suggesting that being a Wehrmacht officer and being a war criminal were mutually incompatible, and since Keitel was in fact a German Army officer, hence he could not have been a war criminal&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg2010_pg6&quot;/&gt; On December 11, 1979 the West German television show ''Report'' aired a documentary entitled &quot;Crimes of the Wehrmacht in World War Two&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt; The public's reaction was almost overwhelming negative, with World War Two veterans leading a campaign to have the producer of ''Report'' fired for the &quot;defamation&quot; of German soldiers, even though as the German historian Jürgen Förster was to write in 1989, the producers of the documentary had gone out of their way to be fair and unbiased.&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;/&gt;  

In 1986, the German historian [[Hans Mommsen]] wrote about the role of the Wehrmacht under National Socialism:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The leadership of the Wehrmacht rather willingly made themselves into accomplices in the policy of extermination. It did this by generating the &quot;criminal orders&quot; and implementing them. By no means did they merely passively support the implementation of their concept, although there was a certain reluctance for reasons of military discipline and a few isolated protests. To construct a &quot;casual nexus&quot; over all this amounts in fact to steering away from the decisive responsibility of the military leadership and the bureaucratic elites&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;piper&quot;/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; In 1989, the British historian [[Richard J. Evans]] wrote that right from the beginning of the war against the Soviet Union, the Wehrmacht fought a genocidal war of &quot;extreme brutality and barbarism&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans21&quot;/&gt; Evans noted that the Wehrmacht officers regarded the Russians as &quot;sub-human&quot;, were from the time of the invasion of Poland in 1939 telling their troops that war was caused by &quot;Jewish vermin&quot; and explained to the troops that the war against the Soviet Union was a war to wipe out what were variously called &quot;Jewish Bolshevik subhumans&quot;, the &quot;Mongol hordes&quot;, the &quot;Asiatic flood&quot; and the &quot;red beast&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans22&quot;/&gt; Such views helped to explain why 3,300,000 of the 5,700,000 Soviet POWs taken by the Germans died in captivity.&lt;ref name=&quot;evans23&quot;/&gt; In 1992, Omer Bartov noted that all of the three leaders of the &quot;new revisionism&quot; in German history that sparked the ''[[Historikerstreit]]'' of the late 1980s were all in some ways seeking to promote the image of the Wehrmacht as a force for the good, and seeking to portray the Wehrmacht as a victim of the Allies rather the victimizer of the peoples of Europe, writing of &quot;...the bizarre inversion of the Wehrmacht's roles proposed by all three exponents of the new revisionism, whereby overtly or by implication the Army is transformed from culprit to saviour, from an object of hatred and fear to one of empathy and pity, from victimizer to victim&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt; Specially, Bartov noted that for:
*That [[Michael Stürmer]]’s geographical interpretation of German history meant that Germany’s &quot;mission&quot; in Central Europe was to serve as a bulwark against the Slavic menace from the East in both World Wars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt;
*That [[Ernst Nolte]]’s argument about a &quot;casual nexus&quot; with the National Socialist genocide as an logical, if extreme response to the horrors of Communism led to Wehrmacht crimes in the Soviet Union being portrayed as essentially justified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt; This was even more the case as Nolte insisted that Operation Barbarossa was as Hitler claimed a &quot;preventive war&quot;,  which meant that for Nolte Wehrmacht war crimes were portrayed as a defensive response to the threat posed to Germany by the &quot;Asiatic hordes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt;
*That [[Andreas Hillgruber]]’s call for historians to &quot;identity&quot; and &quot;empathize&quot;  with German troops fighting on the Eastern Front in 1944-45 implicitly devalued the lives of those suffering and dying in the Holocaust, which was allowed to continue in part because the German troops held out for so long.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt;
Bartov wrote that all three historians had in varying ways sought to justify and excuse Wehrmacht war crimes by depicting the Wehrmacht as engaging in a heroic battle for Western civilization, often using the same language as the Nazis such as referring to the Red Army as the &quot;Asiatic hordes&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt; Bartov ended that these sorts of arguments reflected a broader unwillingness of the part of some Germans to admit to what their Army did during the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;/&gt; In 1998, [[Jürgen Förster]], a German historian, wrote that for too long most people have accepted at face value the self-serving claims made by generals like [[Erich von Manstein]] and [[Siegfried Westphal (general)|Siegfried Westphal]] who promoted the idea of the ''Wehrmacht'' in their memoirs as a highly professional, apolitical force who were victims of [[Adolf Hitler]] rather than his followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster24&quot;/&gt; Förster argues that the ''Wehrmacht'' played a key role in the [[Holocaust]] in [[Eastern Europe]] and other war crimes.&lt;ref name=&quot;rster25&quot;/&gt; In 1999, the New Zealand historian [[Christian Leitz]] wrote that the claims promoted after the war that the Wehrmacht had been an &quot;untarnished shield&quot; with the Army somehow standing apart from the regime it served so loyally was a &quot;myth&quot; that no serious historian had taken seriously since the 1980s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leitz, Bartov&quot;/&gt;

===Films===
In his 2004 essay &quot;Celluloid Soldiers&quot; about post-war German films, the Israeli historian Omer Bartov wrote that German films of the 1950s showed the average German soldier as a heroic victim: noble, tough, brave, honourable and patriotic, while fighting hard in a senseless war for a regime that he did not care for.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov26&quot;/&gt; The [[08/15 (film)|''08/15'']] film trilogy of 1954–55 concerns a sensitive young German soldier named Asch ([[Joachim Fuchsberger]]) who would rather be playing the piano; he fights on the Eastern Front without understanding why. No mention is made of the genocidal aspects of Germany's war in the East with instead the German soldiers being shown as the victims of a war that they can not fathom the reasons for.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt; Bartov commented that given the intense indoctrination in the Wehrmacht about how the war against the Soviet Union was a war to destroy &quot;Judeo-Bolshevism&quot; that the real-life Lieutenant Aschs would most definitely have known what they were fighting for.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt; The war on the Eastern Front was portrayed in a manner that suggested that all who fought in the war were equally victims, but since the focus in the ''08/15'' films is on the unit commanded by Asch inevitably the impression is given that it was German soldiers who were the primary victims of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt; The term 8/15 refers to a type of machine gun used in World War I that was manufactured in such quantities that 8/15 became German Army slang for anything was standard issue, which implied that Asch and the soldiers under his command were Everyman characters of the war on the Eastern Front.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 323&quot;/&gt; The last of the ''08/15'' films ends with Germany being occupied by a gang of American soldiers portrayed as bubble-gum chewing, slack-jawed morons and uncultured louts, totally inferior in every respect to the heroic German soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt; The only exception is the black-marketing Jewish American officer, who is shown as both hyper-intelligent and unscrupulous, which Bartov noted seems to imply that the real tragedy of World War II was the Nazis did not get a chance to exterminate all of the Jews, who have now returned with Germany's defeat to once more exploit the German people.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt; This is especially the case because the Jewish officer speaks his German with an upper-class accent, which is evidently meant to suggest he is a rich German Jew who fled to the United States in the 1930s and upon his return after 1945 is engaging in the same sort of black-market activities that had led the Nazis to run people like him out of Germany in the first place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;/&gt;

In ''Der Arzt von Stalingrad'' (''The Doctor from Stalingrad'') of 1958, dealing with German POWs in the Soviet Union, the Germans are portrayed as more civilized, humane and intelligent than the Soviets, who are shown for the most part as Mongol savages who brutalized the German prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 137&quot;/&gt; One of the German POWs, the dashing Doctor Sellnow (Walter Reyer), successfully seduces the beautiful and tough Red Army Captain Alexandra Kasalniskaya ([[Eva Bartok]]), who prefers him to the sadistic and hideously deformed camp commandant Piotr Markov ([[Hannes Messemer]]), which as Bartov comments is also meant to show that even in defeat, German men were more sexually virile and potent than their Russian counterparts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 137&quot;/&gt; This was especially important to German audiences because of the &quot;crisis in masculinity&quot; in Germany after the war, namely doubts about how manly German men were after losing the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 323&quot;/&gt; Hence the exaggerated picture German films liked to show of the typical Wehrmacht soldier as an ultra-macho type who was just as much a victorious conquering hero in the bedroom as on the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 135-137&quot;/&gt; Bartov argued that the need to show German soldiers as manly war heroes meant they could never be shown as war criminals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 135-137&quot;/&gt; Bartov wrote that the portrayal of the Soviet guards as mostly Asian shows disturbing affinities to war-time [[Nazi propaganda]], where the Red Army was often described as &quot;the Asiatic horde&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 137&quot;/&gt; A recurring theme in ''Der Arzt von Stalingrad'' was that the German soldiers were being punished for crimes that they had not committed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 137&quot;/&gt; In the 1959 film [[Stalingrad: Dogs, Do You Want to Live Forever?|''Hunde, wolt ihr ewig leben?'']] (''Dogs, do you want to live forever?''), which deals with the [[Battle of Stalingrad]], the focus is on celebrating the heroism of the German soldiers in that battle, who are shown as valiantly holding out against overwhelming odds with no mention at all of what those soldiers were fighting for, namely National Socialist ideology or the Holocaust.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 138&quot;/&gt; Bartov noted that the clear impression that these films give is that the average German soldier who fought on the Eastern Front was a hero worthy of the highest admiration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 138&quot;/&gt; This in turn led to a tendency to portray the war in the East in a manner that was devoid of its political context with the war being reduced to struggle between German soldiers whom the audiences were expected to like and admire vs. vast hordes of nameless, faceless, brutal Russian soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 138-139&quot;/&gt; In such a narrative, war crimes by the Wehrmacht had no place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 138-139&quot;/&gt; Even as late as the 1993 film [[Stalingrad (film)|''Stalingrad'']], the heroic victim template was for the most part still being followed with German soldiers fighting and dying heroically at Stalingrad with no political context for why, through in this film one Wehrmacht officer is shown as physically and sexually abusing a captured Russian women (who is albeit promptly avenged by a gallant young Wehrmacht lieutenant who kills his cruel commanding officer out of disgust with his actions).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 138-139&quot;/&gt;

This period also saw a number of films that depicted the military [[Widerstand|resistance to Hitler]]. In ''[[Des Teufels General]]'' (''The Devil's General'') of 1954, a Luftwaffe general named Harras ([[Curd Jürgens]]), loosely modeled on [[Ernst Udet]], appears at first to be a cynical fool whose major interests in life appear to be beautiful women and alcohol, but who turns out to a gallant and upright anti-Nazi officer who is secretly sabotaging the German war effort by designing faulty planes (the real life General Udet did design faulty planes, but this was because of incompetence, not anti-Nazism).&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;/&gt; General Harras, who is represented as a great German patriot has turned against the Nazi regime because of certain unspecified “abominations” which are neither shown nor explained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;/&gt; Bartov commented that in this film, the German officer corps is shown as a group of fundamentally noble and honourable men who happened to be serving an evil regime made up of a small gang of gangsterish misfits totally unrepresentative of German society, which served to exculpate both the officer corps and by extension German society.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov27&quot;/&gt; This impression is further reinforced by the comic exchanges between the decent and upright Harras and various thuggish Nazis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;/&gt; The witty, elegant, and sophisticated ''bon vivant'' Harras whose wisecracks aimed at boorish Nazi leaders served to show that while the latter may be Harras's political superiors, the former remains their social superior.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;/&gt; Officers such as Harras may had served a criminal regime, but ''Des Teufels General'' seems to suggest that there never a part of that regime.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;/&gt; Bartov wrote that no German film of the 1950s showed the deep commitment felt by many German soldiers to National Socialism, the utterly ruthless way the German Army fought the war and the mindless nihilist brutality of the later Wehrmacht.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov28&quot;/&gt; 

Bartov also wrote that German film-makers liked to show the heroic last stand of the 6th Army at Stalingrad, but none has so far showed the 6th Army's massive co-operation with the ''[[Einsatzgruppen]]'' in murdering Soviet Jews in 1941 during its march across the Ukraine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 139&quot;/&gt; Likewise, Bartov commented that German films tended to dwell on the suffering of the 6th Army during the Battle of Stalingrad and its aftermath without reflecting on the fact that it was the Germans who invaded the Soviet Union and that the Russians were fighting to defend their country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 139&quot;/&gt; Bartov went on to state that as late as the 1991 film ''Mein Krieg'' (''My War''), featuring interview footage of six German veterans juxtaposed with their amateur films the veterans shot during the war, contains strong hints that the interviewees saw and/or were involved in war crimes with at one point a mass grave of civilians in Russia being glimpsed in the background of one of the amateur films; but the point is not pressed by the film-makers.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov29&quot;/&gt; Only with ''Jenseits des Krieges'' (released in the US as ''East of War'') in 1996, a documentary directed by [[Ruth Beckermann]] dealing with the public's reaction to the exhibition &quot;War of Extermination&quot; in Vienna in 1995, did a German film admit to ''Wehrmacht'' war crimes being commonplace instead of an exception to the rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov30&quot;/&gt; Some veterans in ''Jenseits des Krieges'' denied that the German Army committed any war crimes at all while others express relief at long last that the truth has been told.&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov31&quot;/&gt; One critic wrote of the veterans in ''Jenseits des Krieges'' that &quot;Some are sorry for their brutality, while others rationalize such acts as shooting POWs, raping women and butchering Jewish people as part of what soldiers were expected to do&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Review of Jenseits des Krieges&quot;/&gt;

===Wehrmachtsausstellung===
{{Main|Wehrmachtsausstellung}}

====Original exhibition, 1995–1999====
The view of the &quot;unblemished&quot; ''Wehrmacht'' was challenged by an exhibition produced by the ''Hamburger Institut für Sozialforschung'' (Hamburg Institute for Social Research) [http://www.his-online.de/] titled ''Vernichtungskrieg. Verbrechen der ''Wehrmacht'' 1941 bis 1944'' (&quot;War of Annihilation. Crimes of the ''Wehrmacht'' 1941 to 1944&quot;). The traveling exhibition, seen by an estimated 1.2 million visitors over the last decade,{{When|date=November 2011}} asserted, with the support of written documents and photographs, that the ''Wehrmacht'' was &quot;involved in planning and implementing a war of annihilation against the Jews, prisoners of war and the civilian population&quot;. Historians [[Hannes Heer]] and [[Gerd Hankel]] had prepared it. The exhibition became controversial and required changes when some allegations were made that a relatively small portion of the photographs presented did not in fact document what was alleged (these criticisms were subsequently addressed and the main thrust of the allegations were judged to be sound in an investigation; see below).

====Criticism====
After criticisms about the incorrect attribution and captioning of some of the images in the exhibition by Polish historian [[Bogdan Musial]] and Hungarian historian [[Krisztián Ungváry]], the head and founder of the Hamburg Institute for Social Research, [[Jan Philipp Reemtsma]], suspended the display pending a review of its content by a committee of historians. In 1999, the institute transferred the exhibition to a &quot;''Trägerverein''&quot;, Hannes Heer resigned from his post as &quot;''Leiter''&quot;; in 2000 he resigned from the institute as well. Reports had surfaced about his extreme left-wing past during which he had been convicted several times.{{Citation needed|date=July 2007}}.

The committee's report &lt;ref name=&quot;his-online&quot;/&gt; in 2000 stated that accusations of forged materials were not justified. It suggested some of the exhibition's documentation was inaccurate. Even so, the committee reaffirmed the reliability of the exhibition in general:

{{quote|The fundamental statements made in the exhibition about the ''Wehrmacht'' and the war of annihilation in 'the east' are correct. It is indisputable that, in the Soviet Union, the ''Wehrmacht'' not only 'entangled' itself in genocide perpetrated against the Jewish population, in crimes perpetrated against Soviet POWs and in the fight against the civilian population, but in fact participated in these crimes, playing at times a supporting, at times a leading role. These were not isolated cases of 'abuse' or 'excesses'; they were activities based on decisions reached by top level military leaders or troop leaders on or behind the front lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crimes of the German Wehrmacht: Dimensions of a War of Annihilation 1941-1944: An outline of the exhibition&quot;/&gt;}}

The committee recommended that the exhibition should be reopened in a revised form, presenting the material, and as far as possible, leaving the formation of conclusions to the exhibition's viewers. It said that &quot;the key statements made in the exhibition about the ''Wehrmacht'' and the war of annihilation in 'the east' do not have to be revised, but must be safeguarded from misunderstandings.&quot;

====Revised exhibition, 2001–2004====
The revised exhibition was now named ''Verbrechen der Wehrmacht: Dimensionen des Vernichtungskrieges 1941–1944.''(Crimes of the German Wehrmacht: Dimensions of a War of Annihilation 1941-1944).&lt;ref name=&quot;Verbrechen der Wehrmacht. Dimensionen des Vernichtungskrieges 1941—1944&quot;/&gt; It focuses on [[Public international law]] and travelled from 2001 to 2004. Since then, it has permanently been at the [[Deutsches Historisches Museum]] in Berlin.

====Movie====
The documentary ''Der unbekannte Soldat'' (&quot;The Unknown Soldier&quot;) by [[Michael Verhoeven]] was in cinemas from August 2006; it has been available on DVD since February 2007. It compares the two versions of the exhibition and brings out the background of its maker Jan Philipp Reemtsma, heir of the [[Reemtsma]] tobacco company.

===Exhibition about the ''Wehrmacht'' in Poland in 1939===
One criticism was that both exhibitions only covered the German presence in the Soviet Union between 1941 and 1945 and excluded the German occupation of Poland after September 1939. The Polish exhibition &quot;''Größte Härte ... Verbrechen der Wehrmacht in Polen September/Oktober 1939''&quot;, a cooperative effort of the Polish [[Institute of National Remembrance]] [http://www.dhi.waw.pl/de/ Deutsches Historisches Institut in Warsaw], was presented on September 1, 2004, in Poland and a German version in 2005([http://www.dhi.waw.pl/de/instytut/projekty/2/] &lt;ref name=&quot;library&quot;/&gt;). It was scheduled to be shown in [[Nuremberg]] at the [[Documentation Center Nazi Party Rallying Grounds|Documentation Center of the Nazi Party Rallying Grounds]] from September 1, 2007 to early 2008. &lt;ref name=&quot;Ausstellungen - Dokumentationszentrum Reichsparteitagsgelände&quot;/&gt;

==Analysis of photos and letters==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-287-0872-28A, Russland, Hinrichtung von Partisanen.jpg|thumb|German soldiers photographing the hanging of a Soviet citizen (the original caption claims he was a partisan)]]

{{rquote|right|Rumors immediately began circulating of appalling crimes committed in the occupied territories — wholesale deportations and systematic massacres ... A story solemnly made the rounds of the world's newspapers that [[storks]] migrating from Holland to South Africa had been found with messages taped to their legs that read, ''&quot;Help us! The Nazis are killing us all!&quot;'' &lt;ref name=&quot;Lose&quot;/&gt;}}

The attitude of German soldiers towards atrocities committed on Jews and Poles in World War II was also studied using photographs and correspondence left after the war. 

Photographs serve as a valuable source of knowledge; taking them and making albums about the persecution of Jews was a popular custom among German soldiers. These pictures are not the official propaganda of the German state but represent personal experience. Their overall attitude is antisemitic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt; 

German soldiers as well as police members took pictures of Jewish executions, deportations, humiliation and the abuse to which they were also subjected. According to researchers, pictures indicate the consent of the photographers to the abuses and murders committed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt; &quot;This consent is the result of several factors, including the [[anti-Semitic]] ideology and prolonged, intensive [[indoctrination]].&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt; Archival evidence as to the reaction to policies of racial extermination can also be traced in various letters that survived the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt; Many letters from ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers were published in 1941 and entitled &quot;German Soldiers See the Soviet Union&quot;; this publication includes authentic letters from soldiers on the Eastern front. To give an example of the intensive indoctrination &quot;that transcends the mere results of military service&quot;, researchers Judith Levin and Daniel Uziel quote a German soldier writing: 

{{quote|The German people is deeply indebted to the Fuehrer, because if these animals, our enemies here, had reached Germany, murders of a nature not yet witnessed in the world would have occurred.... No newspaper can describe what we have seen. It verges on the unbelievable, and even the Middle Ages do not compare with what has transpired here. Reading Der Stuermer and observing its photos give only a limited impression of what we have seen here and of the crimes committed here by the Jews.}}

Judith Levin and Daniel Uziel state that this type of writing and opinion was very common in correspondence left by German soldiers, especially on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt;
 
Other samples of German soldiers' letters were sent home and copied during the war by a special [[Polish Home Army]] cell that infiltrated the German postal system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kazdemu&quot;/&gt; These letters have been analyzed by historians and the picture they paint is similar to views expressed by Judith Levin and Daniel Uziel. Many soldiers wrote openly about the extermination of Jews and were proud of it. Support for &quot;''untermensch''&quot; and &quot;master race&quot; concepts were also part of the attitude expressed by German soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kazdemu&quot;/&gt; Presented examples reflecting this trend include samples such as: 
{{quote|I'm one of those who are decreasing [the] number of partisans. I put them against the wall and everyone gets a bullet in his head, [a] very merry and interesting job.
 
...My point of view: this nation deserves only the knaut, only by it can they be educated; a part of them already experienced that; others still try to resist. Yesterday I had [the] possibility to see 40 partisans, something like that I had never encountered before. I became convinced that we are the masters, others are untermenschen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kazdemu&quot;/&gt;}}
 
Much more evidence of such trends and thoughts among ''Wehrmacht'' soldiers exists and is subject to research by historians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt;

The historians responsible for the exhibition assume that the anti-Semitic climate and propaganda in Nazi Germany had an immense impact on the entire population and emphasize the importance of the indoctrination.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;/&gt;

==See also==
*[[German war crimes]]
*[[Japanese war crimes]]
*[[British war crimes]]
*[[United States war crimes]]
*[[Soviet war crimes]]
*[[Allied war crimes during World War II]]
*[[Holocaust]]
*[[Concentration camps]]
*[[Wehrmachtsausstellung]]
*[[Command responsibility]]
==Notes==
{{BareURLs|date=November 2011}}
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ausstellungen - Dokumentationszentrum Reichsparteitagsgelände&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museen.nuernberg.de/dokuzentrum/ausstellungen.html#polen |title=Ausstellungen - Dokumentationszentrum Reichsparteitagsgelände |publisher=Museen.nuernberg.de |date= |accessdate=2011-11-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999 page 148&quot;&gt;Bartov 1999 page 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 1999, page 147&quot;&gt;Bartov 1999, page 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 136&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 137&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 137.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 138&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 138.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 139&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 139.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, page 323&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 323.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, pages 132-133.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 135-137&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 135-137.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bartov 2004, pages 138-139&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 138-139.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bohler&quot;&gt;* {{cite book |first=Jochen |last=Böhler |title=Auftakt zum Vernichtungskrieg; Die Wehrmacht in Polen 1939 |year=2006 |publisher=Fischer Taschenbuch Verlag |location=Frankfurt |isbn=3-596-16307-2 |language=German| page = 189}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Bohler2&quot;&gt;Jochen Bohler, &quot;Zbrodnie Wehrmachtu w Polse&quot; (Wehrmacht's crimes in Poland), Znak, 2009, pg. 260&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Crimes of the German Wehrmacht: Dimensions of a War of Annihilation 1941-1944: An outline of the exhibition&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.verbrechen-der-wehrmacht.de/pdf/vdw_en.pdf| title= Crimes of the German Wehrmacht: Dimensions of a War of Annihilation 1941-1944: An outline of the exhibition| publisher=Hamburg Institute for Social Research| format=PDF| accessdate=March 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;&gt;&quot;55 Dni Wehrmachtu w Polsce&quot; [[Szymon Datner]] Warsaw 1967 page 67 &quot;Zanotowano szereg faktów gwałcenia kobiet i dziewcząt żydowskich&quot;(Numerous cases of rapes against Jewish women and girls were reported).&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;&gt;Datner, ''Crimes against Prisoners-of-War. Responsibility of the Wehrmacht, pp. 20-35'', 1964&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Datner&quot;&gt;{{cite book  | last = Datner  | first = Szymon  | title = 55 Dni Wehrmachtu w Polsce  | trans_title= 55 days of the ''Wehrmacht'' in Poland  | publisher = Wydawn, Ministerstwa Obrony Narodowej  | location = Warsaw  | language= Polish  | year = 1967  | oclc = 12624404  | pages = 67–74  | authorlink = Szymon Datner }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies_271&quot;&gt;Davies (2006), p. 271&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans55&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 page 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans59&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Richard J.|title=In Hitler's Shadow West German Historians and the Attempt to Escape the Nazi Past|publisher=Pantheon|location=New York|year=1989|isbn=0-394-57686-1|page=59}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Evans_185&quot;&gt;Evans (2008), p. 185&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Front&quot;&gt;Geoffrey P. Megargee: Front Wschodni 1941. Wojna na wyniszczenie. Warszawa: Świat Książki, pages 65, 70-71 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 278&quot;&gt;Förster 1998 page 278.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 279&quot;&gt;Förster 1998 page 279.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 page 280&quot;&gt;Förster 1998 page 280.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998 pages 279-280&quot;&gt;Förster 1998 pages 279-280.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 268&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 268.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 270&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 270.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 271&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 271.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 273&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 273.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 276&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 276.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 1998, page 277&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 277.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 122&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p 122.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p 127&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p 127&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster 2004, p. 118.&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 493&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 493.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 500&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 500.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 501&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 501.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 502&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 502.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 504&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 504.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 505&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 505.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Förster, 1989 page 507&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 507.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hilburg, Raul p 301&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Hilburg, Raul |title=The Destruction of European Jews|volume=1|publisher=Holmes &amp; Meier|location=New York|year=1985|page=301}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 102&quot;&gt;Hillgruber 1989, p 102.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Hillgruber 1989, p 96&quot;&gt;Hillgruber 1989, p 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 page 529&quot;&gt;Jacobsen, 1968 page 529&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Jacobsen, 1968 pages 529-530&quot;&gt;Jacobsen, 1968 pages 529-530&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kazdemu&quot;&gt; [http://www.polityka.pl Niemieckie listy ze wschodu]  [[Polityka]] - nr 51 (2483) December 18, 2004; Jerzy Kochanowski, Marcin Zaremba&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kehila&quot;&gt;[http://www.kkjsm.org/holocaust/holocaust_intro.html Kehila Kedosha Janina Synagogue and Museum, ''The Holocaust in Ioannina''] URL accessed January 5, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Krakowski&quot;&gt;S. Krakowski, ''The Fate of Jewish Prisoners of War in the September 1939 Campaign'', YVS 1977, vol 12, p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Leitz, Bartov&quot;&gt;Leitz, Christian &quot;Editor's Introduction&quot; pages 131-132 from &quot;Army: Soldiers, Nazis and War in the Third Reich&quot; by Omer Bartov; pages 129-150 from ''The Third Reich The Essential Readings'' edited by Christian Leitz, London: Blackwell, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Lose&quot;&gt;Sandlin, Lee (1997). [http://www.leesandlin.com/articles/LosingTheWar.htm &quot;Losing the War&quot;]. Originally published in ''[[Chicago Reader]]'', March 7 &amp; 14, 1997&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Muss&quot;&gt;''Surviving Hitler and Mussolini: daily life in occupied Europe'' Robert Gildea, Olivier Wieviorka, Anette Warring page 90 Berg Publishers, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nuremberg&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title = Trial of the Major War Criminals before the International Military Tribunal | publisher = International military tribunal - Nuremberg | url = http://www.loc.gov/rr/frd/Military_Law/pdf/NT_Vol-VII.pdf | volume=7| page=456| year = 1947| location= Nuremberg, Germany oclc = 300473195}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Obozy podlegle organom policyjnym&quot;&gt;{{cite web |language=Polish |title=Obozy podlegle organom policyjnym |url=http://kki.net.pl/~museum/rozdz3,2.htm |author= Chiechanowski, Konrad |archiveurl=http://web.archive.org/web/20090628171954/http://kki.net.pl/~museum/rozdz3,2.htm | publisher = Muzeum Stutthof w Sztutowie | archivedate=2009-06-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Ordinary&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www1.yadvashem.org/about_holocaust/studies/ordinary/levein_uziel_full.html |title=Ordinary Men, Extraordinary Photos |first1=Judith |last1=Levin |first2=Daniel |last2=Uziel |publisher=[[Yad Vashem]] Institute |series=Yad Vashem Studies No. 26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Raptis&quot;&gt;[http://www.kkjsm.org/archives/Deportation%20of%20Jews%20of%20Ioannina.pdf Raptis, Alekos and Tzallas, Thumios, ''Deportation of Jews of Ioannina'', Kehila Kedosha Janina Synagogue and Museum, July 28, 2005] URL accessed January 5, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Review of Jenseits des Krieges&quot;&gt;{{cite web| last = Brennan| first = Sandra| authorlink = | coauthors =| title = Review of Jenseits des Krieges| work =| publisher = Allmovie|month= | year=| url = http://www.allmovie.com/work/jenseits-des-krieges-154743 | doi =| accessdate = 2008-05-29  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;SDatner&quot;&gt;&quot;Zbrodnie Wehrmachtu na jeńcach wojennych w II Wojnie Światowej [[Szymon Datner]] Warsaw 1961 page 215,pages 97-117, 137&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;The Holocaust in the Soviet Union Symposium Presentations&quot;&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.ushmm.org/research/center/publications/occasional/2005-10/paper.pdf |publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum Center For Advanced Holocaust Studies |title= The Holocaust in the Soviet Union Symposium Presentations |chapter=The Holocaust and Colonialism in Ukraine: A Case Study of the Generalbezirk Zhytomyr, Ukraine, 1941–1944 |first1=Wendy |last1=Lower |page= 6 |year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Verbrechen der Wehrmacht. Dimensionen des Vernichtungskrieges 1941—1944&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.verbrechen-der-wehrmacht.de| title=Verbrechen der Wehrmacht. Dimensionen des Vernichtungskrieges 1941—1944| accessdate=March 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Weinberg2010_pg6&quot;&gt;Weinberg, Gerhard. ''Hitler's Foreign Policy 1933-1939: The Road to World War II'', New York: Enigma Books, 2010 page 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wendy&quot;&gt;Gertjejanssen, Wendy Jo. 2004. &quot;Victims, Heroes, Survivors: Sexual Violence on the Eastern Front during World War II.&quot; PhD diss., University of Minnesota.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wprost&quot;&gt;Numer: 17/18/2007 Wprost &quot;Seksualne Niewolnice III Rzeszy&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov&quot;&gt;Bartov, 1999 page 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov1&quot;&gt;Bartov 1999, pages 146-147.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov10&quot;&gt;Bartov 2001, pages 126-127.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov26&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, pages 134-135.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov27&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004,   page 133&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov28&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov29&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, pages 140-141.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov30&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 141&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov31&quot;&gt;Bartov 2004, page 142&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov8&quot;&gt;Bartov 2001, page 126.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;bartov9&quot;&gt;Bartov 2001, page 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;beck&quot;&gt;Beck 2002, p. 263&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;beck13&quot;&gt;Beck 2002, p. 259&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;boehler&quot;&gt;Boehler, pp. 183-184&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;cambridge&quot;&gt;Scheck, R. (2006). ''Hitler's African Victims''. Cambridge University Press. [http://www.cambridge.org/us/catalogue/catalogue.asp?isbn=9780521857994&amp;ss=exc Excerpt].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;deichmann&quot;&gt;Deichmann 1999, pg 280.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;deichmann17&quot;&gt;Deichmann 1999, pg 281.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;diapozytyw&quot;&gt;[http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20071016112711/http://www.diapozytyw.pl/pl/site/szoach/doswiadczenia_pseudomedyczne DiaPozytyw: &quot;Zagłada, Doświadczenia pseudomedyczne.&quot; (Extermination. Pseudo-medical experiments) Instytut Adama Mickiewicza, Warsaw]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dressen&quot;&gt;Klee/Dressen/Riess 1991, p 153.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;dressen11&quot;&gt;Klee/Dressen/Riess 1991, p 154.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;encounters&quot;&gt;''Jews, Germans, and Allies: Close Encounters in Occupied Germany'' Atina Grossmann page 290&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;eurozine&quot;&gt;{{cite web |first1=Miranda |last1=Alison |first2=Debra |last2=Bergoffen |first3=Pascale |last3=Bos |first4=Louise |last4=du Toit |first5= Regina |last5=Mühlhäuser |first6=Gaby |last6=Zipfel|title=&quot;My plight is not unique&quot; Sexual violence in conflict zones: a roundtable discussion |url=http://www.eurozine.com/articles/2009-09-02-zipfel-en.html |work=Mittelweg 36 |publisher=[[Eurozine]] |date=May 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evans&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 pages 55-56.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evans20&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 page 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evans21&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 pages 58-60.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evans22&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 pages 59-60.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;evans23&quot;&gt;Evans 1989 page 58.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;experimentation&quot;&gt;The Nazi Doctors and the Nuremberg Code: Human Rights in Human Experimentation  George J. Annas and Michael A. Grodin Oxford page 88 University Press, USA  1995&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;forgotten&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author=Lukas, Richard C. | title=Forgotten Holocaust: The Poles Under German Occupation 1939-1944 | editor= | others=[[Norman Davies|Davies, Norman]] | publisher=[[Hippocrene Books]] | isbn=0-7818-0901-0 | authorlink= Richard C. Lukas }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;gegenwind&quot;&gt;http://www.gegenwind.info/175/sonderheft_wehrmacht.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Kroker&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |author=Marilouise Kroker |title=Critical digital studies: a reader |publisher=University of Toronto Press |year=2008 |isbn=9780802095466 |url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fULy7r401OsC&amp;pg=PA260&amp;dq=Wehrmacht+human+shields&amp;as_brr=3#v=onepage&amp;q=Wehrmacht%20human%20shields&amp;f=false |page=260}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;h-net.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.h-net.org/reviews/showrev.php?id=9279 Gender and the World Wars: An Integrated Epoch of Change]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;hillgruber&quot;&gt;Hillgruber 1989, pp 94-96.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;his-online&quot;&gt;[http://www.his-online.de/download/Kommissionsbericht.pdf ]{{dead link|date=November 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;implementing&quot;&gt;A 1942 ''Wehrmacht'' document suggested that the Nazi leadership considered implementing a special policy for the eastern front through which the estimated 750,000 babies born through sexual contact between German soldiers and Russian women (an estimate deemed very conservative), could be identified and claimed to be racially German. (It was suggested that the middle names Friedrich or Luise be added to the birth certificates of male and female babies.) Although the plan was not implemented, such documents suggest that the births that resulted from rapes and other forms of sexual contact were deemed beneficial, increasing the &quot;Aryan&quot; race rather than as adding to the inferior Slavic race. The underlying ideology suggests that German rape and other forms of sexual contact may need to be seen as conforming to a larger military strategy of racial and territorial dominance. (Pascale R . Bos, Feminists Interpreting the Politics of Wartime Rape: Berlin, 1945; Yugoslavia, 1992–1993 Journal of Women in Culture and Society 2006, vol. 31, no. 4, p.996-1025)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;international&quot;&gt;''War crimes against women: prosecution in international war crimes tribunals'' Kelly Dawn Askin page 72&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;interpretations&quot;&gt;''Photographing the Holocaust: interpretations of the evidence'' Janina Struk page 109 I. B. Tauris 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;library&quot;&gt;http://library.fes.de/pdf-files/historiker/03431.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;montefiore&quot;&gt;''Dunkirk: fight to the last man'' Hugh Sebag-Montefiore, Harvard University Press, pages 303-317, November 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;organization&quot;&gt;Networks of Nazi Persecution: Bureaucracy, Business and the Organization of the Holocaust (Studies on War and Genocide) Gerald D. Feldman,Wolfgang Seibel page 241&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ostrowska&quot;&gt;Do burdelu, marsz! Joanna Ostrowska, Marcin Zaremba November 4, 2009 Polityka&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;pantheon&quot;&gt;Mayer, Arno J ''Why Did The Heavens Not Darken?'', New York: Pantheon, 1988, 1990 page 250.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;piper&quot;&gt;Mommsen, Hans &quot;The New Historical Consciousness&quot; pages 114–124 from ''Forever In The Shadow of Hitler?'' edited by Ernst Piper, Humanities Press, Atlantic Highlands, 1993 pages 120–121&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;publishing&quot;&gt;&quot;Most ''Wehrmacht'' regular units were held back in reserve, since this was to be an SS-run 'special action'.&quot; Forczyk, Robert and Dennis, Peter: ''Warsaw 1944: Poland's Bid for Freedom.'' Osprey Publishing, 2009, page 51. ISBN 1846033527&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;resistance&quot;&gt;The resistance movement Henryk Świebocki, Wacław Długoborski, Franciscek Piper, page 364 Auschwitz-Birkenau State Museum 2000&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;richard&quot;&gt;Rhodes, Richard ''Masters of Death'', New York: Alfred Knopf, 2002 p 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster12&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 page 514.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster14&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 pages 506-507.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster19&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 pages 493-494.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster2&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster24&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 266.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster25&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, pages 266-267.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster3&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster4&quot;&gt;Förster, 1989 pages 500-501.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster5&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, pp 121-122.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster6&quot;&gt;Förster 2004, p 126&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;rster7&quot;&gt;Förster 1998, page 274.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;seifert1992&quot;&gt;{{citation |first= Ruth |last=Seifert| title = War and Rape. Analytical Approaches1 | publisher = Women's International League for Peace and Freedom | url = http://www.wilpf.int.ch/publications/1992ruthseifert.htm | |archiveurl=http://replay.web.archive.org/20090529065019/http://www.wilpf.int.ch/publications/1992ruthseifert.htm |archivedate= 29 May 2009 |accessdate = March 12, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university&quot;&gt;Bartov, Omer ''Germany's War and the Holocaust: Disputed Histories'', Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 2003 page xiii&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university15&quot;&gt;Suicide in Nazi Germany Christian Goeschel page 125 Oxford University Press, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university16&quot;&gt;People in Auschwitz Hermann Langbein page 345 The University of North Carolina Press 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;university18&quot;&gt;''Guilt, Suffering, and Memory: Germany Remembers Its Dead of World War II'' Gilad Margalit page 3 Indiana University Press 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;uwe&quot;&gt;[http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/WCC/dostler.htm The Dostler Case]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;weltanschauungskrieg&quot;&gt;Peter Lieb Konventioneller Krieg oder NS-Weltanschauungskrieg-Kriegführung und Partisanenbekämpfung in Frankreich 1943/44, page 19,Oldenbourg Wissenschaftsverlag 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;www&quot;&gt;[http://www.nd.edu/~com_sens/issues/old/v17/v17_n5.html#dostler Dostler defense]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;yjil&quot;&gt;[http://www.yjil.org/docs/pub/35-1-finucane-enforced-disappearance.pdf Enforced Disappearance as a Crime Under International Law: A Neglected Origin in the Laws of War]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==References==
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book | last=Bartov|first=Omer| title=Hitler’s Army: Soldiers, Nazis, and War in the Third Reich| location=New York | publisher=Oxford University Press| year=1991|isbn=978-0-19-506879-5}}
*{{cite book| last=Bartov |first=Omer |chapter=Soldiers, Nazis and War in the Third Reich (pages 129–150)|title= The Third Reich The Essential Readings |editor=Christian Leitz |location=London |publisher=Blackwell|year=1999 |isbn=978-0-631-20700-9}}
*{{cite book | author=Bartov, Omer |authorlink=Omer Bartov | title=The Eastern Front, 1941-45 : German Troops and the Barbarisation of Warfare | location=London | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan | year=2001 |isbn=978-0-3339-4944-3 |edition=2nd}}
*{{cite book| last=Bartov |first=Omer |chapter=Celluloid Soldiers: Cinematic Images of the ''Wehrmacht'' (pages 130-143) |title=Russia War, Peace and Diplomacy |editor=Ljubica &amp; Mark Erickson |location=London |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-297-84913-1}}
*{{cite book |first=Birgit |last=Beck |chapter=Vergewaltigungen. Sexualdelikte von Soldaten vor Militärgerichten der deutschen Wehrmacht, 1939-1944 |editor=Karen Hagemann/Stefanie Schüler-Springorum (Hrsg.) |title=Heimat-Front. Militär und Geschlechterverhältnisse im Zeitalter der Weltkriege |publisher=Campus |location=Frankfurt |year=2002 |isbn=978-3-593-36837-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Davies|first=Norman|title=Europe at War 1939–1945: No Simple Victory|publisher=Pan Books|location=London|year=2006|isbn=978-0-330-35212-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Richard J.|title=In Hitler's Shadow West German Historians and the Attempt to Escape the Nazi Past|publisher=Pantheon|location=New York|year=1989|isbn=978-0-394-57686-2}}
*{{cite book |last1=Deichmann |first1=Ute |last2=Dunlap |first2=Thomas (translator) |title=Biologists Under Hitler |publisher=Harvard University Press |year=1999}}
*{{cite book|last=Evans|first=Richard J.|title=The Third Reich at War|publisher=Allen Lane|location=London|year=2008|isbn=978-0-7139-9742-2}}
*{{cite book| last=Förster |first=Jürgen |chapter=The Wehrmacht and the War of Extermination Against the Soviet Union (pages 492-520) |title=The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The &quot;Final Solution&quot;: The Implementation of Mass Murder Volume 2|editor=[[Michael Marrus]]|location=Westpoint, CT|publisher=Meckler Press |year=1989|isbn=978-0-88736-255-2}}
*{{cite book| last=Förster |first=Jürgen |chapter=Complicity or Entanglement? The Wehrmact, the War and the Holocaust (pages 266-283) |title=The Holocaust and History The Known, the Unknown, the Disputed and the Reexamiend |editor=Michael Berenbaum &amp; Abraham Peck |location=Bloomington |publisher=Indian University Press |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-253-33374-2}}
*{{cite book| last=Förster |first=Jürgen |chapter=The German Military’s Image of Russia (pages 117–129) |title=Russia War, Peace and Diplomacy |editor=Ljubica &amp; Mark Erickson |location=London |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-297-84913-1}}
*{{cite book | last=Fritz | first=Stephen G. | title=Frontsoldaten: The German Soldier in World War II | publisher=University Press of Kentucky | year=1997 | isbn=978-0-8131-0943-5 }}
*{{cite book | last=Heer | first=Hannes (ed.) | other=Klaus Naumann (ed.) | title=Vernichtungskrieg: Verbrechen der ''Wehrmacht'' 1941-1944 (War of Annihilation: Crimes of the Wehrmacht) | location=Hamburg | publisher=Hamburger Edition HIS Verlag | year=1995 | isbn=978-3-930908-04-2}}
*{{ cite book |last=Hillgruber |first=Andreas |chapter=War in the East and the Extermination of the Jews (pages 85–114) |title=The Nazi Holocaust Part 3 The &quot;Final Solution&quot;: The Implementation of Mass Murder Volume 1|editor=[[Michael Marrus]]|location=Westpoint, CT |publisher=Meckler Press |year=1989|isbn=978-0-88736-255-2}}
*{{cite book | last=Jacobsen |first=Hans-Adolf |chapter=The Kommisssarbefehl and Mass Executions of Soviet Russian Prisoners of War |pages=505–536 |title=Anatomy of the SS State |publisher=Walter and Company: New York |year=1968 |isbn=978-0-5860-8028-3}}&lt;!-- can only find the ISBN for the 1970 edition published by Flamingo --&gt;
*{{cite book | last=Rossino | first=Alexander B. | title=Hitler Strikes Poland: Blitzkrieg, Ideology, and Atrocity | publisher=Modern War Studies | year=2005 | isbn=978-0-7006-1392-2 }}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Klee|editor1-first=Ernst|editor2-last=Dressen|editor2-first=Willi|editor3-last=Riess|editor3-first=Volker|title=&quot;The Good old days&quot;: the Holocaust as seen by its perpetrators and bystanders|year=1991|location=New York|publisher=Free Press|isbn=978-0-241-12842-8}}
*{{cite book | last=Scheck | first=Raffael | title=Hitler's African Victims: The German Army Massacres of Black French Soldiers in 1940 | year=2006 | isbn=978-0-521-85799-4 }}
*{{cite book | author=Wheeler-Bennett, Sir John | title=The Nemesis of Power: German Army in Politics, 1918–1945 | location=New York | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan | year=2005 | authorlink=John Wheeler-Bennett |edition=2nd |isbn=978-1-4039-1812-3}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
; Movie (on-line)
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nSzejCWXKhA Poland under German occupation 1939-1945 ]
*[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L3lD8HYURzQ The Atrocities committed by German-Fascists in the USSR ]
; Other
*[http://wih.sagepub.com/cgi/reprint/11/2/148.pdf  ''Prisoner Taking and Prisoner Killing in the Age of Total War'']: Towards a Political Economy of Military Defeat

{{DEFAULTSORT:War Crimes Of The Wehrmacht}}
[[Category:Nazi war crimes]]
[[Category:Wehrmacht]]
[[Category:Military history of Germany during World War II]]

[[cs:Válečné zločiny Německa během druhé světové války]]
[[de:Verbrechen der Wehrmacht]]
[[es:Crímenes de guerra de la Wehrmacht]]
[[fr:Crimes de guerre de la Wehrmacht]]
[[it:Crimini di guerra della Wehrmacht]]
[[he:פשעי המלחמה של הוורמאכט]]
[[sq:Krimet e luftës të Wehrmachtit]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
