<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3869" ns="0" title="Bruce Perens"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox person
| name          = Bruce Perens
| image         = 051118-WSIS.2005-Bruce.Perens.ogg
| image_size    = 300px
| caption       = Perens at the World Summit on the Information Society 2005 in Tunis speaking on &quot;Is Free/Open Source Software the Answer?&quot; [[Richard Stallman]] is on Perens's right
| birth_name    =
| birth_date    = &lt;!-- {{Birth date|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| birth_place   =
| death_date    = &lt;!-- {{Death date and age|YYYY|MM|DD|YYYY|MM|DD}} --&gt;
| death_place   =
| body_discovered =
| death_cause   =
| resting_place =
| resting_place_coordinates = &lt;!-- {{coord|LAT|LONG|display=inline,title}} --&gt;
| residence     =
| nationality   =
| ethnicity     =
| citizenship   =
| other_names   =
| known_for     = [[Open Source Initiative]], [[BusyBox]]
| education     =
| alma_mater    =
| employer      =
| occupation    = [[Computer programmer]]
| years_active  =
| home_town     =
| salary        =
| networth      =
| height        =
| weight        =
| title         =
| term          =
| predecessor   =
| successor     =
| party         =
| opponents     =
| boards        =
| religion      =
| spouse        =
| partner       =
| children      =
| parents       =
| relations     =
| callsign      = K6BP
| awards        =
| signature     =
| website       = [http://perens.com/ perens.com]
}}

'''Bruce Perens''' is a [[computer programmer]] and advocate in the [[open source community]]. He created the [[Open Source Definition]] and published the first formal announcement and manifesto of [[open source]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LG&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ldp.dvo.ru/LDP/LGNET/issue26/perens.html |title=The Open Source Definition |publisher=ldp.dvo.ru |date= |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/opensources/book/perens.html |title=Open Sources: Voices from the Open Source Revolution |publisher=Oreilly.com |date=1999-03-29 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; He co-founded the [[Open Source Initiative]] (OSI) with [[Eric S. Raymond]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://opensource.org/history |title=History of the OSI &amp;#124; Open Source Initiative |publisher=Opensource.org |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2005, Perens represented Open Source at the [[World Summit on the Information Society|United Nations World Summit on the Information Society]], at the invitation of the [[United Nations Development Program]]. He has appeared before national legislatures and is often quoted in the press, advocating for open source and the reform of national and international technology policy.

Perens is also a [[ham radio|ham]], with [[callsign]] K6BP. He is well known in the [[amateur radio]] community for his efforts towards open radio communications standards.&lt;ref&gt; Interview with Leo Laporte on 'The Tech Guy' radio show, 2011-10-16&lt;/ref&gt;

== Viewpoint ==
Perens poses Open Source as a means of marketing the [[free software]] philosophy of [[Richard Stallman]] to business people who are more concerned with profit than freedom, and states that open source and free software are only two ways of talking about the same phenomenon. This differs from Stallman&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25169 |title=Review: Perens Speaks about Free Software in Copenhagen |publisher=Technocrat.net |date=2007-08-17 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25149 |title=Review: Perens Speaks about Free Software in Copenhagen |publisher=Technocrat.net |date=2007-08-17 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Raymond. Perens postulates an economic theory for business use of Open Source in his paper ''The Emerging Economic Paradigm of Open Source'' and his speech ''Innovation Goes Public''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/articles/Economic.html |title=The Emerging Economics of Open Source Software |publisher=Perens.com |date=2004-09-30 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; This differs from Raymond's theory in ''[[The Cathedral and the Bazaar]]'', which having been written before there was much business involvement in open source, explains open source as a consequence of programmer motivation and leisure.

== Organizations ==
Perens is a former [[Debian]] Project Leader, a founder of [[Software in the Public Interest]], founder and first project leader of the [[Linux Standard Base]] project, the initial author of [[BusyBox]], and founder of the [[UserLinux]] project. Perens also has a book series with Prentice Hall PTR called the [[Bruce Perens' Open Source Series]]. He is an avid [[amateur radio]] enthusiast ([[callsign]] K6BP&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://wireless2.fcc.gov/UlsApp/UlsSearch/license.jsp?licKey=254811 |title=ULS License - Vanity License - K6BP - PERENS, BRUCE J |publisher=Wireless2.fcc.gov |date=2006-09-26 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;) and maintained [[technocrat.net]], which he closed in late 2008 because its revenues did not cover its costs. He is also the founder of [[No Code International]], an organization whose primary purpose was to eliminate [[morse code]] proficiency as a requirement to obtain an [[amateur radio license]]. This goal has been reached with the removal of code requirements from international law (International Telecommunications Union treaty provision S25.5), the new &quot;code-free&quot; rules introduced on 2007-02-23, and similar legal changes in almost all nations worldwide.{{Citation needed|date=July 2009}}

Perens left OSI a year after co-founding it, with reasons explained in an email titled &quot;It's Time to Talk About Free Software Again&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/1999/debian-devel-199902/msg01641.html |title=It's Time to Talk About Free Software Again |publisher=Lists.debian.org |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2008, for the 10th anniversary of the Open Source, Perens published a message to the community called &quot;State of Open Source Message: A New Decade For Open Source&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/articles/State8Feb2008 |title=Bruce Perens - State of Open Source Message: A New Decade For Open Source |publisher=Perens.com |date=1998-02-09 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the same event, the 10th anniversary of Open Source, the ezine RegDeveloper published an interview with Bruce Perens where he revives an updated view on the past and the future, and the dangers of the Open Source, especially the useless proliferation of OSI approved licenses and the strength of the GPL 3.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url = http://www.regdeveloper.co.uk/2008/02/11/open_source_at_ten/ | title = Perens: 'Badgeware' threat to open source's next decade | first = Gavin | last = Clarke | date = 11 February 2008 | work = Developer | publisher = The Register | accessdate = 2009-07-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the interview covered [[Linus Torvalds]]' refusal to adopt the GPLv3 for the Linux kernel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.linux.com/feature/131346 |title=Linux.com |publisher=Linux.com |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt;

He was an employee of [[SourceLabs]] from June 2005 until December 2007.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/12/3/31038 |title=On My Own Again |publisher=Technocrat.net |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is currently CEO of [[Kiloboot]].

== Creation of the Open Source Definition ==
The Open Source Definition was first created by Perens as the [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]], itself part of the [[Debian Social Contract]]. Perens proposed a draft of the Debian Social Contract to the Debian developers on the debian-private mailing list early in June, 1997. Debian developers contributed discussion and changes for the rest of the month while Perens edited, and the completed document was then announced as Debian project policy. On February 3, 1998, a group of people met at VA Linux Systems (without Perens) to discuss the promotion of Free Software to business from pragmatic terms, rather than the moral terms preferred by Richard Stallman. Christine Petersen of the nanotechnology organization ''Foresight Institute'' was present because Foresight took an early interest in Free Software, and Petersen suggested the term &quot;Open Source&quot;. The next day, Eric Raymond recruited Perens to work with him on the formation of Open Source. Perens modified his Debian document into the Open Source Definition by removing Debian references and replacing them with &quot;Open Source&quot;.

The original announcement of the [[Open Source Definition]] was made on February 9, 1998 on [[Slashdot]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=98/02/09/213900 |title=Free Software's New Name |publisher=Slashdot |date=1998-02-09 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and elsewhere; the definition was given in [[Linux Gazette]] on February 10, 1998.&lt;ref name=&quot;LG&quot;/&gt;

== Film ==
Perens worked at [[Pixar]] for 12 years before leaving to work full-time on Open Source issues, and before then at the [[New York Institute of Technology Computer Graphics Lab]], spending a total of 19 years in the computer graphics and feature film industry. These two decades were the genesis of the 3-dimensional feature film animation that is taken for granted today. He is credited as a studio tools engineer on [[Toy Story 2]] and [[A Bug's Life]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0673302/ Bruce Perens] on IMDb.&lt;/ref&gt; He is featured in two documentaries on Open Source: [[Revolution OS]] and [[The Code-Breakers]]. He produced a video commercial, ''[[Impending Security Breach]]'', for Sourcelabs in 2007.

== Academia ==
{{BLP unsourced section|date=December 2009}}
Perens is finishing a three-year grant from the Competence Fund of Southern Norway. With this funding, he spent part of the summer as a visiting lecturer and researcher at [[University of Agder]] in 2006 and 2007, and does other work remotely. During this time he consulted the Norwegian Government and other entities on government policy issues related to computers and software. He previously worked remotely as Senior Scientist for Open Source with the [[Cyber Security Policy Research Institute]] of [[George Washington University]].

==UserLinux==
In 2003 Bruce Perens founded [[UserLinux]], a distribution whose stated goal was, &quot;Provide businesses with freely available, high quality Linux operating systems accompanied by certifications, service, and support options designed to encourage productivity and security while reducing overall costs.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author= |url=http://lwn.net/Articles/150701/ |title=Whither UserLinux? |publisher=lwn.net |date=2005-09-07 |accessdate=2011-07-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== 2007 activities ==
Perens remained active in representing open source to the world and advising several national governments and multinational corporations regarding Open Source. In 2007 some of his government advisory roles included: a meeting with the President of the [[Chamber of Deputies]] (the lower house of parliament) in Italy and testimony to the Culture Committee of the Chamber of Deputies;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25151 |title=Visit to Rome |publisher=Technocrat.net |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; a keynote speech at the foundation of Norway's Open Source Center, following Norway's Minister of Governmental Reform (Perens is on the advisory board of the center);&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://technocrat.net/d/2007/8/17/25148 |title=Norway opens Free Software Center |publisher=Technocrat.net |date= |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; he provided input on the revision of the [[EIF|European Interoperability Framework]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/articles/EIF2/ |title=Bruce Perens - The Confusion of Tongues: EIF 2.0, Standards, and Interoperability |publisher=Perens.com |date=2007-09-13 |accessdate=2009-07-15}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he was keynote speaker at a European Commission conference on ''Digital Business Ecosystems at the Centre Borschette, Brussels, on November 7.

== 2009 activities ==
In 2009, Perens acted as an [[expert witness]] on open source in the [[Jacobsen v. Katzer]] U.S. Federal lawsuit.  His report, which was made publicly available by Jacobsen, presented the culture and impact of open source software development to the federal courts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://perens.com/works/testimony/PerensJMRI.pdf|title=Expert Report of Bruce Perens |publisher=Northern California District Court |date=2009-10-20 |accessdate=2010-03-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Portal|Free software}}
{{Commons category}}
{{wikiquote}}
* [http://perens.com/ Bruce Perens' homepage]
* [http://lwn.net/1998/0528/a/lsb.html Project Proposal and Call for Participation: The Linux Standard Base]
* [http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/1999/02/msg01641.html &quot;It's Time to Talk About Free Software Again&quot;, 1999]
* [http://www.linux-magazin.de/news/video_bruce_perens_ueber_open_source_lizenzen Video with Bruce Perens at Hannover Industry Trade Fair, Germany, May 2008]
* [http://tllts.org/mirror.php?fname=tllts_132-04-05-06.ogg Linux Link Tech Show interview (audio), 2006], [http://tllts.org/mirror.php?fname=tllts_238-03-26-08.ogg 2008]
* [http://www.nocode.org No Code International]
* [http://www.meetthebloggers.net/2007/04/17/open-source-definition-author-bruce-perens/ Interview (audio) at Defrag Ohio with Meet the Bloggers]
* [http://www.spiderlessweb.com/?p=11 A talk about open source recorded in Rome in June 2007]
* [http://www.gutsygeeks.com/audio/listen.php?show_id=81&amp;code=4a7b1e61&amp;format=ogg Interview in ogg format on ''The Gutsy Geeks'' recorded 2009/07/25]

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box|before=[[Ian Murdock]]|after=[[Ian Jackson]]|years=April&amp;nbsp;1996 &amp;ndash; December&amp;nbsp;1997|title=[[Debian Project Leader]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{FOSS celeb}}
{{Debian}}

{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              = Perens, Bruce
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES = 
| SHORT DESCRIPTION = Computer programmer
| DATE OF BIRTH     = 
| PLACE OF BIRTH    = 
| DATE OF DEATH     = 
| PLACE OF DEATH    = 
}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Perens, Bruce}}
[[Category:Debian Project leaders]]
[[Category:Amateur radio people]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]
[[Category:Year of birth missing (living people)]]

[[ar:بروس بيرنز]]
[[ca:Bruce Perens]]
[[de:Bruce Perens]]
[[es:Bruce Perens]]
[[fr:Bruce Perens]]
[[it:Bruce Perens]]
[[ja:ブルース・ペレンズ]]
[[no:Bruce Perens]]
[[pl:Bruce Perens]]
[[pt:Bruce Perens]]
[[ru:Перенс, Брюс]]
[[sl:Bruce Perens]]
[[sr:Брус Перенс]]
[[sv:Bruce Perens]]
[[tr:Bruce Perens]]
[[zh:布魯斯·斐倫斯]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
