<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3872197" ns="0" title="Goa&#039;uld characters in Stargate"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Non-free|date=March 2011}}
{{Multiple issues| primarysources=January 2010
| in-universe=January 2010
| fiction=January 2010
}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:Goa'uld characters in ''Stargate''}}
This is a list of the '''Goa'uld characters''' that have appeared so far in ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'', ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'', and ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]''. In the ''[[Stargate]]'' [[fictional universe]], the [[Goa'uld]] are a [[parasitic]] alien race that use other beings as hosts. Ra stated in the ''Stargate'' film that he has used humans exclusively as hosts for millennia, as their technology can repair human bodies so easily that by inhabiting human forms he can be for all intents and purposes ageless, though they still can be injured and killed. Most Goa'uld pose as [[deity|gods]] to control slave armies and are considered evil, [[egocentrism|egocentric]] [[Narcissistic personality disorder|megalomaniacs]] by those who do not worship them. The Goa'uld are extremely intelligent and have an aptitude for understanding, working with and using technology that is superior. They each have full access to their species' [[genetic memory (parapsychology)|genetic memory]] from the moment of birth, meaning that no Goa'uld has to learn how to work with any technological device; they 'know' how to do so innately.

==Recurring characters==
===Anubis===
&lt;!-- Unsourced image removed: [[Image:ANUBISstargatelostcity.jpg|thumb|right|Anubis in &quot;Lost City&quot;.]] --&gt;
[[Image:Anubis Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Anubis.]]
'''Anubis''', originally played by [[David Palffy]] when as a cloaked figure with an obscured face, is an extremely powerful Goa'uld [[System Lord]] who replaces [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] as the main enemy on ''Stargate SG-1''. The character is first mentioned in the season 5 episode {{sgcite|Between Two Fires}}, although he is not seen in person until {{sgcite|Revelations}}. In {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, he is seen in different host bodies, played by [[Dean Aylesworth]] and [[Rik Kiviaho]]. In {{sgcite|Threads}}, in the persona of &quot;Jim&quot;, he is played by [[George Dzundza]]. Anubis has a tendency towards melodramatic pronouncements, even by Goa'uld standards; at one point [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] comments, &quot;Oh come on, who talks like that?&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Redemption&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Redemption|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anubis was banished by the System Lords thousands of years ago for crimes unspeakable even to the Goa'uld; Yu even tried to murder him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Last Stand|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis is believed dead, but in fact tricked [[Oma Desala]] into helping him [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascend]]. Once his evil became apparent, the other Ascended beings &quot;descended&quot; him but incompletely, allowing him to retain Ancient knowledge and do anything he could have done as a regular Goa'uld.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Threads|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis thus becomes an incorporeal being given form by a shield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Full Circle|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In secret, Anubis gathers his strength and develops advanced technologies that would gain him an advantage over the other Goa'uld; he also experiments with creating Ascension-capable humans using a [[DNA Resequencer]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prototype&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prototype|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis recruits Tanith, Zipacna, and Osiris to further his various goals; in season 5 he subjugates and later annihilates the [[Tollan (Stargate)|Tollan]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Between Two Fires&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Between Two Fires|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; launches a [[naqahdah]] asteroid towards Earth,&lt;ref name=&quot;Fail Safe&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fail Safe|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; decimates the [[Tok'ra]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt; and captures [[Thor (Stargate)|Thor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Revelations|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also has himself reinstated into the ranks of the System Lords, by unanimous consent, with the exception of [[Lord Yu]], despite having attacked their holdings, with the promise of eliminating the Tau'ri.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt;

In the season 6 premiere {{sgcite|Redemption}}, Anubis makes good on his promise by employing an Ancient weapon that would have detonated the naqahdah in Earth's Stargate, which would have wiped out all life on Earth. O'Neill flies the Stargate to a safe distance from Earth before it explodes, and the weapon is destroyed by Rya'c. In {{sgcite|Full Circle}}, Anubis seeks out six powerful artifacts to power a superweapon on his mothership. SG-1 finds the last artifact, the Eye of Ra, on Abydos, and at Daniel Jackson's behest hands it to Anubis in exchange for sparing Abydos. Anubis uses his superweapon to devastate the collected fleet of the System Lords before breaking his agreement and destroying Abydos; Jackson is stopped from acting against him by the other Ascended beings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot;&gt;{{Full Circle}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Fallen}}, SG-1 lures his mothership to Vis Uban and launches an F-302 attack that disables the superweapon. Anubis then travels to Langara to investigate [[naqahdriah]] as an alternate power source for his weapon, based on information he extracts from [[Jonas Quinn]]'s mind. The System Lords arrive at Langara and destroy his mothership, though Anubis escapes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Homecoming|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the second half of season 7, Anubis creates a new army of nearly invincible [[Kull Warrior]]s to replace his Jaffa. He assassinates a number of minor Goa'uld, absorbing their forces into his own in preparation for the upcoming war against the System Lords.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Evolution|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Lost City}}, Anubis launches a full-scale assault on Earth with a fleet of over thirty motherships. His fleet is annihilated by the [[Ancient technology in Stargate#Drone weapon|Ancient drone weapons]] launched from the Antarctica outpost by SG-1. However, Anubis survives in energy form and possesses several SGC personnel in a bid to reach the Stargate. Carter sends him, in the body of Colonel Vasilov, to a frozen wasteland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lockdown&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Lockdown|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis eventually frees himself and secretly establishes dominance over Ba'al, possessing a succession of host bodies as each one quickly deteriorates under his influence. During the Replicator invasion of the Milky Way, he plans to use the [[Dakara superweapon]] to destroy all life in the galaxy and then repopulate it to his own designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Reckoning|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Anubis continues his plan after the Replicators are destroyed, outmaneuvering the Free Jaffa and conquering Dakara. At the same time, as a man named &quot;Jim&quot;, he converses with Daniel Jackson and Oma Desala at an illusory diner between the normal and Ascended planes of reality. &quot;Jim&quot; reveals to Daniel that the reason Anubis was allowed to keep his Ascended memories is to punish Oma, who must watch helplessly as he wreaks havoc on the galaxy. Just as Anubis prepares to use the Dakara superweapon, Oma engages him in battle, ensuring that for all eternity he would be forced to contend with her to the exclusion of everything else.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot; /&gt;

===Apophis===
[[Image:Apophis Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Apophis.]]
'''Apophis''', played by [[Peter Williams (actor)|Peter Williams]], is a [[Goa'uld]] [[System Lord]] and the main villain for most of the first four seasons of ''Stargate SG-1''. He is based on the god [[Apep]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. As in mythology, Apophis is the enemy of [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Threshold&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Threshold|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and gains power after Ra is killed by [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] and [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]''&lt;/ref&gt; Apophis' first appearance on ''SG-1'' is commanding a raid on Earth through the Stargate, in which he abducts a female Airman as a potential host for his queen Amonet. He also raids Abydos for potential hosts, taking [[Sha're]] and [[Skaara]]. These incidents lead to the restarting of the [[Stargate Program]], and both O'Neill and Jackson joining a mission to Apophis' homeworld, Chulak. Their team escapes death by Apophis with the help of his then-First Prime, [[Teal'c]], though not before witnessing Sha're and Skaara being taken as hosts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Children of the Gods|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The existence of the Tau'ri now known to him, Apophis launches attacks on Earth that are blocked by the Earth gate's iris.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Enemy Within&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Enemy Within|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; His forces also skirmish with SG-1 on several worlds.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Nox&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Nox|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cor-ai&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Cor-ai|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apophis eventually launches a full-scale assault on Earth with two [[Ha'tak|motherships]]. None of Earth's weapons are effective against them, but SG-1 manages to infiltrate and destroy both. Apophis and his son Klorel escape,&lt;ref name=&quot;Within the Serpent's Grasp&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Within the Serpent's Grasp|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Serpent's Lair|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; though this defeat severely diminishes his standing amongst the System Lords. To strengthen his position, Apophis brainwashes Teal'c's son Rya'c into denouncing his father, and tries to use him in a plot to release a bioweapon at the [[Stargate Command|SGC]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Family&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Family|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Apophis also fathers a [[Harcesis]] child with Amonet/Sha're. He is led to believe that Heru-ur took the child, although in reality he has been hidden away by SG-1.&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Secrets|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Goa'uld [[Sokar (Stargate)|Sokar]] soon takes advantage of Apophis' weakness, crushing his forces and capturing him. Apophis manages to escape and seeks sanctuary with the Tau'ri. Severely wounded, Apophis dies at the SGC; in his last moments his host, an Egyptian scribe, emerges for the first time in thousands of years. Apophis' body is returned to Sokar to avert an attack on Earth.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Serpent's Song|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sokar revives Apophis with a sarcophagus for additional torture, eventually sending him to the hellish prison moon of Ne'tu. There, Apophis disguises himself as a mysterious figure named Na'onak and works his way back into power as the First Prime of Bynarr, Lord of Ne'tu. He recognizes SG-1 when they arrive at Ne'tu to rescue [[Jacob Carter|Jacob]]/[[Selmak]]. Killing Bynarr, he then interrogates SG-1, Martouf, and Selmak using a hallucinogenic drug (the &quot;blood of Sokar&quot;), hoping that with useful information he can get close enough to Sokar to assassinate him. Apophis escapes to Delmak after Sokar recognizes that he has only false information from his captives. Shortly after, Sokar is killed when the Tok'ra destroy Ne'tu, leaving Apophis in control of his domain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Jolinar's Memories|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Devil You Know|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With Sokar's massive fleet and army, Apophis becomes the most powerful Goa'uld in the galaxy. He attacks and reclaims Chulak,&lt;ref name=&quot;Maternal Instinct&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Maternal Instinct|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; kills Heru-ur and absorbs his domain after a failed attempt at an alliance,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Venom&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Serpent's Venom|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by the end of season 4 stands poised to destroy the System Lords and conquer the galaxy. To avert this, the Tok'ra lure him into a trap at Vorash, using a Stargate connected to a black hole to trigger a supernova that incinerates his fleet. Once again, Apophis survives by taking his mothership into hyperspace after SG-1 captured Ha'tak. Both ships are thrown to another galaxy by the nova,&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Exodus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; where Apophis' mothership comes under attack by [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]]. Apophis escapes to SG-1's Ha'tak, having brainwashed Teal'c into again serving as his First Prime, but the Replicators infest that ship as well and send it towards the Milky Way. Knowing the threat of the Replicators, SG-1 sabotages the engines so that the Ha'tak will crash into Delmak upon exiting hyperspace. Swarmed by Replicators, Apophis is helpless as his ship plummets into Delmak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Enemies&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Enemies|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In an alternate reality depicted in {{sgcite|Point of View}}, Apophis launches a devastating invasion of Earth that is only turned back after the SG-1 of this reality helps their alternates contact the Asgard. Another version of Apophis appears in the alternate timeline of {{sgcite|Moebius}}, ruling over Chulak. He also captures a team from Earth and has a Goa'uld symbiote implanted into Daniel Jackson to learn about Earth. Apophis appears briefly in ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as the last System Lord defeated by Ba'al; Teal'c brings him before Ba'al, who executes him by slicing off the top of his head.

[[David J. Tholen]] and [[Roy A. Tucker]], two astronomers who are reportedly fans of ''Stargate SG-1'', named a [[near-Earth asteroid]] that they co-discovered in 2004, [[99942 Apophis]] as an allusion to the ''Stargate'' villain.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.astronomy.com/asy/default.aspx?c=a&amp;id=3434 |title=Asteroid Apophis set for a makeover|author=Bill Cooke |journal=Astronomy Magazine|date=August 18, 2005|laydate=November 3, 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ba'al===
[[Image:Stargate-SG1-Ba'al.jpg|thumb|Ba'al in &quot;[[Reckoning (Stargate SG-1)|Reckoning, Part 1]]&quot;]]
[[Image:Baal Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Ba'al]]
'''Ba'al''', played by [[South Africa]]n actor [[Cliff Simon]], is a [[Goa'uld]] based on the [[Baʿal]] of [[Canaanite religion]]. He first appears in the season 5 episode {{sgcite|Summit}}, and becomes a recurring adversary in the remaining seasons of ''Stargate SG-1'' as well as in ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'', making him the longest-running villain in ''Stargate'' history. In the show, Ba'al is an intelligent and cunning [[System Lord]], though unlike most of his peers he is rather flippant about his &quot;godhood&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Abyss&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Abyss|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; At a meeting of the System Lords, Ba'al votes to accept Anubis back into their ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; In {{sgcite|Abyss}}, he captures Jack O'Neill and tortures him for information by repeatedly killing him and then reviving him in a sarcophagus. Ba'al eventually turns against Anubis along with the other System Lords; due to Lord Yu's senility, he takes command of their combined fleet and destroys Anubis's mothership at Langara.&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming&quot; /&gt; Ba'al proceeds to conquer Erebus&lt;ref name=&quot;Orpheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Orpheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and sends an operative to Langara.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallout&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fallout|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Avenger 2.0}}, Ba'al modifies Jay Felger's computer virus to disable the Stargate network, giving him an advantage due to his large fleet.

After Anubis's fleet is destroyed in {{sgcite|Lost City}}, Ba'al locates Tartarus and gains control of the [[Kull Warrior]]s. With this substantial advantage, he wages a highly successful war against all the other System Lords, driving them to the brink of defeat.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot; /&gt; However, at some point Anubis returns and secretly forces Ba'al back into his service, much to Ba'al's displeasure. During the Replicators' invasion of the galaxy, Ba'al contacts the SGC to tell them of Anubis's plan to use the [[Dakara superweapon]] to destroy all life in the galaxy. When Anubis orders Ba'al to retake Dakara from the Jaffa rebellion, Ba'al stalls as much as he can and assists [[Samantha Carter]] and [[Jacob Carter|Jacob]]/[[Selmak]] in calibrating the superweapon to destroy the Replicators. He also provides a means to dial all the Stargates in the galaxy simultaneously through the help of a minor Goa'uld named Nerus. After the Replicators are defeated, Ba'al beams away after his mothership is stormed by rebel Jaffa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot; /&gt; Anubis was aware of Ba'al's treachery, though it was of little concern to him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Threads&quot; /&gt;

With his traditional power base gone, Ba'al travels to Earth and takes over the [[Trust (Stargate)|Trust]], which had already been infiltrated by the Goa'uld. Ba'al establishes himself as a wealthy businessman and adopts Earth customs and fashions. He informs the SGC that he only intends to live out his exile in peace (and that he has also planted [[naqahdah]] explosives as insurance). It is revealed that Ba'al has made multiple clones of himself; one of these clones is captured and executed by the Free Jaffa Nation, but many more remain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ex Deus Machina&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Ex Deus Machina|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; After realizing the threat posed by the [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]], Ba'al begins a campaign to battle the invaders for control of the galaxy. He brainwashes half the Jaffa High Council, asserting that only his leadership would allow the Jaffa to resist the Ori. Teal'c and Bra'tac uncover Ba'al's plot, and the Ba'al clone responsible is killed by SG-1.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stronghold&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Stronghold|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ba'al also attempts to build his own private empire by stealing Stargates. The SGC uses an unwitting Nerus to locate and disable the Ba'al clone's [[Ha'tak]], which is destroyed by the [[Lucian Alliance]] after the ''Odyssey'' retrieves the Stargates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Off the Grid&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Off the Grid|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In {{sgcite|Insiders}}, the supposed real Ba'al turns to the SGC for help in neutralizing his clones, who he claims have turned against him. However, this is nothing more than an elaborate ruse to gain access to a list of planets where the Sangraal might be hidden. Ba'al had brainwashed NID agent [[Malcolm Barrett (Stargate)|Malcolm Barrett]] in preparation for his breakout at the SGC, and most of the Ba'al clones escape once they have the information. SG-1 eventually encounters a Ba'al clone while searching for the Sangraal. He, along with Adria, are forced to work with SG-1 to overcome Morgan Le Fay's various defensive measures protecting Merlin's resting place.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Quest&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Quest|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Dominion}}, Ba'al intercepts SG-1's plan to capture Adria and implants one of his cloned symbiotes within her. He also massacres most of his clones using symbiote poison, though it is by no means certain whether there are any more. The Ba'al symbiote is extracted by the Tok'ra after SG-1 recaptures Adria, though not before it releases a toxin that eventually forces her [[Ascension (Stargate)|Ascension]]. In ''[[Stargate Continuum]]'', the last Ba'al clone has been captured, though the real Ba'al changes history by going back in time and stopping the Stargate Program from happening. In the alternate timeline, he defeats the System Lords and prepares to conquer Earth, only to be betrayed and killed by his queen Qetesh onboard his flagship. [[SG-1]] repairs the timeline using Ba'al's time machine, and [[Cameron Mitchell (Stargate)|Cameron Mitchell]] travels back to before Ba'al enacts his plan and kills him when he appears. With the timeline restored, the Tok'ra extract the symbiote from the last Ba'al clone. However, the cloned host survives and is able to live on.

[[Cliff Simon]] met with [[executive producer]]s [[Robert C. Cooper]] and [[Brad Wright]] and auditioned eight months before the character Ba'al was created for the series. Simon, Cooper and Wright came to an agreement to wait until they found the right character for Simon in the show. Simon said &quot;I was very lucky,&quot; when talking about his character in an interview with The Sci Fi World.&lt;ref name=&quot;scifi&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| author=Gilles Nuytens |url=http://www.thescifiworld.net/interviews/cliff_simon_01.htm |title=Cliff Simon Interview |date= |publisher=''The Sci Fi World'' |accessdate=2009-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to portraying actor Simon, Ba'al was his most &quot;interesting&quot; he's done because of Ba'al's character development and diversity among others. Simon felt that he needed to diversify the character to make it more exciting, as he put it, &quot;if you’re always bad, it gets pretty boring.&quot; He wanted to change the development of the character, the writing staff eventually agreed with him and started fleshing out his character.&lt;ref name=&quot;dragon&quot;&gt;{{Cite web| author=Desiree Jackson |url=http://dailydragon.dragoncon.org/2008/system-lord-summit-with-cliff-simon/ |title=System Lord Summit: An Interview with Cliff Simon |date= |publisher=''Daily Dragon'' |accessdate=2009-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cronus===
[[Image:Cronus Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Cronus.]]
'''Cronus''', played by [[Ron Halder]], was one of the most influential of the [[System Lord]]s, named for [[Cronus]] in [[Greek mythology]]. He was the one who banished [[Sokar (Stargate)|Sokar]] and was the mortal enemy of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]]. [[Teal'c]]'s father was Cronus's First Prime; Cronus ordered him to fight an unwinnable battle against a more powerful Goa'uld. After his inevitable defeat, Cronus executed him by crushing his symbiote, causing its blood to mix with his in a slow and painful death. Thus, Teal'c vowed that he would one day become the First Prime of Apophis, Cronus' enemy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Crossroads&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Crossroads|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Cronus sent the Ashrak that hunts Jolinar of Malkshur in {{sgcite|In the Line of Duty}}. He also developed [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Weapons and military|kor mak bracelets]] for use in transporting prisoners.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Ties That Bind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, Cronus, Nirrti, and Yu travel to Earth to negotiate Earth's entry into the [[Protected Planets Treaty]]. During the talks, Teal'c is called into Cronus's room, whereupon both are attacked by an invisible force. Although it is initially feared that Teal'c attacked Cronus due to their enmity, eventually Nirrti is found to be responsible. [[Samantha Carter]] is able to heal Cronus's wounds using a [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Other technology|Goa'uld healing device]], salvaging the talks, and Nirrti is turned over to Cronus. In {{sgcite|Double Jeopardy}}, Cronus conquers Juna and captures SG-1, but is shocked to find that they are in fact android duplicates created by Harlan, who seeks out the real SG-1 for help. Both Teal'c and his android counterpart confront Cronus, though Cronus overpowers both of them. As he prepares to crush Teal'c's symbiote, he is shot in the back by android Teal'c, with the words &quot;for our father&quot;. SG-1 captures Cronus's [[Ha'tak]], which is later used in a Tok'ra plan to lure Apophis's fleet into a trap at Vorash.&lt;ref name=&quot;Exodus&quot; /&gt; Cronus appears briefly in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as one of Ba'al's allies.

===Nirrti===
[[Image:Stargate-SG1-Nirrti.jpg|thumb|Nirrti]]
[[Image:Nirrti Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Nirrti]]
'''Nirrti''', played by [[Jacqueline Samuda]], is a [[Goa'uld]] [[System Lord]] named for [[Nirrti|{{Unicode|Nirṛti}}]] in [[Hindu]] mythology. She is interested in engineering an advanced human host (a hok'taur) for herself. On the planet Hanka, she wipes out the entire population with a deadly pathogen except for one girl, [[Cassandra (Stargate)|Cassandra]], whom she modifies into a living bomb knowing that [[SG-1]] would take her back to Earth. She once used a similar tactic against her enemy Apophis. Cassandra is only saved through quick thinking by [[Samantha Carter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Singularity&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Singularity|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nirrti first appears in person in {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, in which she, Cronus, and Yu arrive on Earth to negotiate Earth's entry into the [[Protected Planets Treaty]]. During the talks, she attempts to murder Cronus and frame Teal'c, using a personal stealth device based on Reetou phase-shifting to move around the base. Yu is outraged when told that she has kept this technology hidden from the System Lords; Nirrti flees, but is captured and handed over to Cronus.

Nirrti escapes after Cronus is killed by SG-1. When Cassandra begins to manifest telekinesis and life-threatening physiological changes, Nirrti secretly follows SG-1 from her lab back to Earth to learn more. She is captured after Cassandra senses her presence, but she barters her freedom for healing Cassandra. Nirrti expresses surprise to O'Neill that they honor the agreement, stating that she doubts she would have done the same.&lt;ref name=&quot;Rite of Passage&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Rite of Passage|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Metamorphosis}}, a Russian SG team discovers Nirrti's new base, where she is using an [[Ancients (Stargate)|Ancient]] [[DNA Resequencer (Stargate)|DNA resequencer]] to experiment on the local population under the guise of helping them. Although they have been physically deformed by the device, she has given them abilities such as telepathy and telekinesis. Believing themselves responsible for the situation, the SGC authorizes Nirrti's assassination. All does not go as planned when Nirrti's subjects capture SG-1, but they turn against her after one of them, Eggar, reads her mind at SG-1's suggestion. Another subject, Wodan, kills her by telekinetically breaking her neck. Nirrti appears briefly in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as one of Ba'al's lieutenants.

===Osiris===
[[Image:Osiris (Stargate).jpg|thumb|Osiris/Sarah in &quot;Summit&quot;.]]
'''Osiris''', played by [[Anna-Louise Plowman]], is a [[Goa'uld]] based on the [[Osiris]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. Thousands of years ago, he was banished in a stasis jar along with his queen Isis by his brother Seth. Osiris escapes when the jar is opened by archaeologist Sarah Gardner, a former colleague of [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]]. He possesses her, and escapes Earth in a hidden starship.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Curse&quot; /&gt; Osiris is recruited by Zipacna into the service of Anubis, and represents him at a summit of the [[System Lord]]s. Daniel, who had infiltrated the meeting, uses the Re'ol chemical on her to prevent her from exposing him, and attempts to capture her in Yu's scoutship. However, Yu happens upon them and releases Osiris, who stabs him while Daniel escapes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; In {{sgcite|Revelations}}, Osiris commands a [[Ha'tak]] charged with locating the base of the Asgard Heimdall, and is able to defeat Thor's mothership and capture him due to Anubis' shield enhancements. She is momentarily thrown when Carter tells her that Daniel had died. Osiris is forced to retreat with the arrival of Asgard reinforcements. Osiris returns to Earth in {{sgcite|Chimera}}, using a Goa'uld memory device on Daniel while he sleeps in an attempt to find the location of the [[Atlantis (Stargate)|Lost City of the Ancients]] in his mind. She is eventually discovered and captured, and the symbiote extracted from Sarah's body.

===Ra===
[[Image:Ra stargate film.JPG|thumb|Ra in the ''Stargate'' film.]]

'''Ra''' is the villain in the original ''[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]'' movie, and is established in the television show ''[[Stargate SG-1]]'' as a [[Goa'uld]]. The character is based on the [[Ra]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. He is played by [[Jaye Davidson]] in the film and [[Jay Williams (actor)|Jay Williams]] in the series. In some scenes of the movie, the outline of Ra's original humanoid form can be seen. ''Stargate SG-1'' contradicts this, [[retcon]]ning Ra as a canonical Goa'uld.

[[Image:Ra original humanoid.jpg|100px|thumb|left|Concept drawing of Ra's original humanoid form by Patrick Tatopoulos.]]
[[Image:Ra Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Ra.]]
According to ''Stargate'' mythology, 10,000 years ago Ra voyaged across the galaxy searching for a new host that could sustain his dying form. He discovered Earth and found the native humans easy to repair using his advanced technology. He possessed the body of a young boy, and ruled over the planet as a god.&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Stargate (film)|Stargate]]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; During his reign, he seeded humans throughout the galaxy using the Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Enemy Within&quot;/&gt; Ra was the most powerful and cunning of the Goa'uld, holding the title of Supreme System Lord.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tok'ra&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Tok'ra|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; His Queen was [[Hathor (Stargate)|Hathor]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Hathor&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Hathor|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; his son was [[Heru-ur (Stargate)|Heru-ur]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Thor's Chariot|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; and his brother (and enemy) was [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Children of the Gods}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ra also defeated the [[Tok'ra]] Queen Egeria, and battled the Goa'uld Shaq'ran.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cure&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Cure|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Five thousand years ago, the people of Earth rebelled against Ra and buried the planet's [[Stargate (device)|Stargate]] in [[Egypt]]. In order to avert another such uprising, Ra outlaws reading and writing on his other planets, including [[Abydos (Stargate)|Abydos]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Movie&quot; /&gt; In the ''Stargate'' film, an Earth team led by Colonel [[Jack O'Neil (Stargate)|Jack O'Neil]] (his name was spelled O'Neil in the film and changed to O'Neill in the series) travels to Abydos after the Stargate is activated, to reconnoiter the area and if necessary close the way to Earth with a nuclear bomb. They are captured by Ra's forces upon his return to the planet. Ra plans to send the bomb back to Earth along with a quantity of [[naqahdah]], which will amplify the explosion. O'Neil and his team escape and eventually incite a successful rebellion amongst the Abydonians. As Ra abandons the planet, O'Neil and Jackson teleport the active bomb to his ship by way of a [[ring transporter]], destroying it and him. Ra's death draws the attention of the other Goa'uld to Earth, and creates a power vacuum amongst the System Lords that allows Apophis to become more powerful.&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot;/&gt;

Ra has only appeared once on ''Stargate SG-1'', in masked form, in the season 8 episode {{sgcite|Moebius}}. In that episode, [[SG-1]] travels back in time to steal a [[ZPM]] from Ra, and inadvertently changes history into one where Ra took the Stargate with him after the rebellion on Earth. The original timeline is restored after a second version of SG-1 travels back and ensures that the Stargate is left behind. An unmasked Ra appears briefly in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as one of Ba'al's lieutenants.

===Sokar===
[[Image:The Devil You Know.jpg|thumb|Sokar in &quot;The Devil You Know&quot;]]
[[Image:Sokar Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Sokar.]]
'''Sokar''', played by [[David Palffy]], is a Goa'uld who replaces [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]] as the principal enemy of [[SG-1]] for the first half of the third season. He is named for the [[Seker]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. Sokar only appears in person in {{sgcite|Jolinar's Memories}} and {{sgcite|The Devil You Know}}, although his magnified voice is heard in {{sgcite|Serpent's Song}}. Sokar is an ancient Goa'uld who once ruled the System Lords until he was defeated by an alliance that included Ra, Apophis, and Cronus.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot; /&gt; In those times, his host body was that of an [[Unas (Stargate)|Unas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot; /&gt; Sokar has posed as the god of death on many different worlds,&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot;/&gt; and [[Satan]] is one of his guises.&lt;ref name=&quot;Demons&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Demons|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He terraformed the moon Ne'tu, in orbit around his homeworld Delmak, into a literal version of hell to serve as a prison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;/&gt;

Apophis' defeat at the hands of [[SG-1]] paves the way for Sokar's return to power. Sokar captures the weakened Apophis and tortures him, but Apophis escapes and demands sanctuary amongst the Tau'ri. Sokar subsequently launches an attack against the [[Stargate Command|SGC]] by using a particle beam to melt through the Stargate iris at the SGC. At the urging of the [[Tok'ra]], Apophis' body is returned to Sokar, who revives him with a sarcophagus for further torture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Serpent's Song&quot; /&gt; Sokar eventually amasses the largest fleet in the entire Goa'uld domain, and is poised to launch an all-out attack on the System Lords that the Tok'ra believe will succeed. As this would give Sokar control of the galaxy and make him unstoppable, the Tok'ra enact a plan to assassinate him by blowing up Ne'tu while Sokar's ship is in orbit, which is complicated by the capture of [[Jacob Carter|Jacob]]/[[Selmak]]. At the same time, Apophis also attempts to assassinate Sokar by first currying favor with him while in disguise. Although Apophis fails, he manages to escape before Ne'tu explodes, giving him control of Sokar's massive army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Devil You Know&quot;/&gt;

===Tanith===
[[Image:Stargate-SG1-Tanith.jpg|thumb|Tanith]]
'''Tanith''', played by [[Peter Wingfield]], is a Goa'uld symbiote incubated by the [[Jaffa (Stargate)|Jaffa]] priestess Shan'auc. While within her, he communicates with her and leads her to believe that he intends to renounce the Goa'uld's evil ways, causing her to defect to the SGC and eventually the Tok'ra. However, once he matures and blends with his host Hebron, he murders Shan'auc for betraying her true god. Teal'c, who loved Shan'auc, swears revenge, but is stopped by the Tok'ra, who know of Tanith's duplicity and are using him to feed misinformation to the System Lords.&lt;ref name=&quot;Crossroads&quot;/&gt; In {{sgcite|Exodus}}, having set a trap for Apophis, the Tok'ra have no more use for Tanith and intend to extract him and let him die on the sands of Vorash. Tanith however escapes to Apophis, bringing Teal'c with him. He escapes again from Apophis' ship after the Tok'ra and [[SG-1]] spring their trap and destroy Apophis' fleet with a supernova.

In {{sgcite|Between Two Fires}}, Tanith is revealed to have switched masters to [[Anubis (Stargate)|Anubis]]. He travels to [[Tollan (Stargate)|Tollana]] on one of Anubis' enhanced [[Ha'tak]]s, which are immune to Tollan ion cannons, and extorts the Tollan Curia into building weapons of mass destruction equipped with phase-shifting devices that will allow them to penetrate the iris on the Earth Stargate. After Narim destroys the weapons, Tanith commands an assault that annihilates the Tollan. Tanith's final appearance is in {{sgcite|48 Hours}}, where he encounters SG-1 on a scouting mission. He attacks them from his [[Al'kesh]], but Teal'c kills him by firing his [[death glider]] [[staff weapon]] directly into the bomber's cockpit.

===Yu===
[[Image:Yu aboard a Goa'uld space station.jpg|thumb|Yu in &quot;Summit&quot;]]
[[Image:Yu Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|60px|Symbol of Yu]]
'''Yu''', played by [[Vince Crestejo]], is the eldest of the [[System Lord]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallen&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fallen|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the other System Lords, he didn't directly pretend to be a god,&lt;/sup&gt;[http://www.stargate-sg1-solutions.com/wiki/3.03_%22Fair_Game%22_Transcript] but took position as one of China's earliest emperors. Among all the Goa'uld leaders, it is notable that he did have several positive influences during his reign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Fair Game|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the show, he has been introduced as [[Yu the Great]] in {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, and the [[Jade Emperor|Jade Emperor, the exalted Yu Huang Shang Ti]] in {{sgcite|Summit}}, who are separate figures in Chinese mythology.

Yu is a pragmatic villain and the System Lord most willing to deal with Earth; while certainly no friend of the Tau'ri, his galactic interests lie far from Earth and he has cooperated with the SGC when it has suited him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abyss&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fair Game&quot; /&gt; His first appearance is in {{sgcite|Fair Game}}, when he travels to the SGC along with [[Cronus (Stargate)|Cronus]] and [[Nirrti (Stargate)|Nirrti]] to negotiate Earth's entry into the [[Protected Planets Treaty]]. Yu supports Earth's entry into the treaty after Nirrti is found to have betrayed the System Lords. In {{sgcite|Summit}} and {{sgcite|Last Stand}}, Yu attends a meeting of the System Lords to discuss a [[Anubis (Stargate)|mysterious new threat]]. [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]] infiltrates the meeting alongside him, using the Re'ol chemical to fool Yu into believing he is his lo'taur (personal human servant). After [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]]' surprise appearance, Yu is the only one of the System Lords present who votes against readmitting Anubis into their ranks.

After surviving an attack by Osiris,&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot;/&gt; Yu begins a lone battle campaign against Anubis and his System Lord supporters. His forces manage to hold their own despite facing superior numbers and technology, to the surprise of the SGC and the Tok'ra.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revelations&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Abyss&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Prophecy&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prophecy|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also defeats a rebel Jaffa assault on his homeworld led by Teal'c, which was planned by Kytano (in fact the Goa'uld Imhotep in disguise). Yu allows Teal'c to return to the Jaffa camp with the truth about Kytano's identity.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warrior&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Warrior|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Abyss}}, he launches an attack on [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]]'s secret outpost based on information provided by the SGC; this attack allows [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] to escape Ba'al's captivity.

In {{sgcite|Full Circle}}, Yu convinces the other System Lords to join him in opposing Anubis and claiming the powerful Eye of Ra for themselves. Their collected fleet confronts Anubis' mothership over [[Abydos (Stargate)|Abydos]], but are decimated after Anubis activates his superweapon. In {{sgcite|Fallen}}, Yu agrees to bring the full force of the System Lords down on Anubis once [[SG-1]] destroys his superweapon. However, he inexplicably takes his fleet elsewhere. His First Prime, Oshu, reveals to Teal'c that Yu's mind is failing due to old age, and furthermore he is no longer able to take a new host. Thus, they persuade Ba'al to take command of the fleet, which destroys Anubis' mothership over [[Langara (Stargate)|Langara]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Homecoming&quot;/&gt; Yu again travels to the SGC in {{sgcite|New Order}}, alongside Amaterasu and Camulus, to negotiate a new arrangement with the Tau'ri against the threat of Ba'al. However, his mind has deteriorated further, and Oshu must speak for him. The System Lords' war against Ba'al goes poorly, and eventually Yu and Amaterasu begin to rally their armies for a final stand.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|It's Good To Be King|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In {{sgcite|Reckoning}}, Yu and the last of the System Lords receive Ba'al's emissary, who demands their surrender. However, the meeting is interrupted by [[Replicator Carter]], who kills Yu as the first act of her invasion of the Milky Way. Yu appears briefly in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as one of Ba'al's lieutenants.

==Minor characters==
* {{anchor|Amaterasu}}'''Amaterasu''' (played by [[Kira Clavell]]) A [[System Lord]] named for the sun goddess [[Amaterasu]] in [[Japanese mythology]]. She visits the SGC after Anubis' defeat to negotiate a new arrangement against Ba'al.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|New Order|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; The war against Ba'al goes poorly, and she and Yu rally their armies for a last stand.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot;/&gt; Her motherships are amongst the first to be infested by [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reckoning&quot;/&gt; Kira Clavell originally auditioned for the role of [[Teyla Emmagan]] for ''[[Stargate Atlantis]]'', but although she caught the eye of the producers, she was not &quot;quite right for Teyla&quot; and was given the role of Amaterasu instead.&lt;ref name=gw_making_801&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.gateworld.net/sg1/s8/making/801.shtml |last=Mallozzi |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Mallozzi |title=In the Making: &quot;New Order, Part 1&quot; |publisher=''[[GateWorld]]'' |accessdate=2008-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Amaunet}}'''Amaunet''' (played by [[Vaitiare Bandera]]) The beloved Queen of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]], named for [[Amaunet]] of [[Egyptian mythology]], who abducts women from many different worlds to find a host acceptable to her. Amaunet ultimately chooses Sha're, an [[Abydos (Stargate)|Abydonian]] woman and wife of [[Daniel Jackson (Stargate)|Daniel Jackson]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot; /&gt; Amaunet/Sha're becomes pregnant by Apophis; as the child is a [[Harcesis]] born of two Goa'uld hosts, Amaunet goes into hiding on Abydos and becomes dormant so as not to harm the child. This allows Sha're to call Daniel for help, although Amaunet regains control after giving birth. Daniel takes the child, and Amaunet leads Apophis to believe that Heru-ur had taken him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets&quot;/&gt; After Apophis' defeat, Amaunet enters Heru-ur's service while searching for her child. During a raid on Abydos, she attacks Daniel with a hand device and Teal'c is forced to shoot her, killing Sha're as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forever in a Day&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Forever in a Day|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Aries Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Ares.]]
* {{anchor|Ares}}'''Ares''' A [[System Lord]], named for [[Ares]] of [[Greek mythology]], who is defeated by [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] and flees to one of his former holdings, where the [[Tok'ra]] had resettled [[Harry Maybourne]]. He is killed by General Jack O'Neill when he destroys his [[Ha'tak]] with a time-traveling Puddle Jumper.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Athena}}'''Athena''' (played by [[Sonya Salomaa]]) A minor Goa'uld, named for [[Athena]] of [[Greek mythology]], who rose to prominence by allying with whichever Goa'uld was in power. Most recently she serves as Ba'al's lieutenant on Earth, under the alias &quot;Charlotte Mayfield&quot;. Athena once allied with Qetesh to find the Clava Thessara Infinitas, only to be betrayed. To find it, she uses the Trust's resources to abduct Qetesh's former host [[Vala Mal Doran]] and probes her mind, but Vala escapes her.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ex Deus Machina&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Memento Mori&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Memento Mori|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Atum}}'''Atum''' A a minor Goa'uld [[System Lord]], named for [[Atum]] of [[Egyptian mythology]], who was once a rival of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]]. His last First Prime was Arkad who always led his armies to fight against Apophis over the last years of his reign. One of the planets under Atum's control was Co'rak  which was later conquered by Arkad.&lt;ref name=&quot;Talion&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Talion|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Bastet}}'''Bastet''' (played by [[Natasha Khadr]]) A [[System Lord]], named for [[Bastet]] of [[Egyptian mythology]], known for treachery, who came to power after the second Goa'uld dynasty's collapse. She votes to readmit Anubis into the ranks of the System Lords.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Summit|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; She is eventually killed by Ba'al's forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Bynarr}}'''Bynarr''' (played by [[Bob Dawson (actor)|Bob Dawson]]) An underling of Sokar and lord of his prison moon Ne'tu. The [[Tok'ra]] Jolinar once escaped Ne'tu by seducing him, for which Sokar ripped out one of his eyes. He is killed by his First Prime Na'onak, in fact Apophis in disguise, who succeeds him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jolinar's Memories&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Camulus}}'''Camulus''' (played by [[Steve Bacic]]) A [[System Lord]], named for [[Camulus]] of [[Celtic mythology]], who visits the SGC to negotiate a new arrangement against [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]]. After the talks break down, Camulus unexpectedly asks for asylum on Earth, revealing to [[Elizabeth Weir (Stargate)|Elizabeth Weir]] that his armies were one of the first to fall before Ba'al.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Order&quot; /&gt; Camulus later gives General [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|O'Neill]] the location of a [[ZPM]], but SGC scientists find that Camulus has tampered with the device so that it would explode if ever used. Camulus agrees to take the ZPM to Ba'al in an attempt to assassinate him. However, O'Neill is not confident that Ba'al wouldn't discover the sabotage as well and then use the tainted ZPM as a weapon, and so he secretly gives Camulus the inert ZPM from Proclarush Taonas instead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zero Hour&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Zero Hour|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Camulus appears briefly in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as one of Ba'al's lieutenants. When Robert C. Cooper created the character for &quot;New Order&quot; he already had Steve Bacic in mind since he was already familiar with his work as Major Coburn in season 3's &quot;[[Maternal Instinct (Stargate SG-1)|Maternal Instinct]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=gw_making_801 /&gt;
* {{anchor|Grannus}}'''Grannus''' One of Camulus' lieutenants, who was killed by his own Jaffa. However, he is still worshiped by fanatical followers. Named for [[Grannus]] of [[Celtic mythology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;The Ties That Bind&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Hathor}}'''Hathor''' (played by [[Suanne Braun]]) The Queen of [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]] and mother of [[Heru-ur (Stargate)|Heru-ur]], named for the goddess [[Hathor]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. She was imprisoned in a [[Sarcophagus (Stargate)|sarcophagus]] in [[Mexico]] and after being freed by archaeologists, she travels to the SGC and takes over the male population of the base using a weaker version of the brainwashing drug [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Other technology|nish'ta]]. She is defeated by Teal'c and the women of the base, and escapes through the Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hathor&quot;/&gt; Hathor builds a new army by brainwashing the Jaffa of other Goa'uld, and captures all of [[SG-1]] except Teal'c. She creates an elaborate deception with a replica of the SGC and tries to convince SG-1 that they have woken in the future, in order to extract information from them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Out of Mind&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Out of Mind|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; When this fails, she implants a symbiote into O'Neill, but he is saved by an undercover Tok'ra. Hathor's base is eventually assaulted by a force of rebel Jaffa led by Teal'c, Bra'tac, and General Hammond. Hathor is killed when O'Neill throws her unprotected into a cryogenic chamber.&lt;ref name=&quot;Into the Fire&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Into the Fire|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Heru-ur Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Heru-ur.]]
* {{anchor|Heru-ur}}'''Heru-ur''' (played by [[Douglas H. Arthurs]]) A powerful [[System Lord]], named for [[Horus]] in [[Egyptian mythology]]. He is the son of Ra and Hathor,&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot; /&gt; and his former holdings include the planets Tagrea and Juna.&lt;ref name=&quot;Memento&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Memento|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Double Jeopardy&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Double Jeopardy|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heru-ur invades Cimmeria after discovering Thor's Hammer, an [[Asgard (Stargate)|Asgard]] anti-[[Goa'uld]] device, is disabled (by [[SG-1]] in {{sgcite|Thor's Hammer}}). SG-1 and Gairwyn contact [[Thor (Stargate)|Thor]], who arrives in his mothership and removes Heru-ur's armies and ships, forcing Heru-ur to retreat through the Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thor's Chariot&quot;/&gt; He travels to Abydos to seize Amonet, the queen of his enemy Apophis, and her [[Harcesis]] child, but is beaten there by SG-1 and again forced to escape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Secrets&quot;/&gt; Heru-ur eventually plans an alliance with Apophis; the Tok'ra and SG-1 sabotage their meeting in the Tobin minefield hoping to incite a war, not expecting that Apophis has brought a fleet of cloaked motherships with him. Apophis destroy's Heru-ur's ship and absorbs his forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Venom&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Imhotep}}'''Imhotep''' (played by [[Rick Worthy]]) A minor Goa'uld who designed the Great Pyramids on Earth. He attempts to gain power by disguising himself as the charismatic rebel Jaffa leader Kytano. Despite his victories, his disregard for life alienates [[SG-1]]. Teal'c learns of his true nature after an ill-planned attack on Lord Yu, and kills him in ritual jomo'sequ.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warrior&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Ishkur}}'''Ishkur''' The former ruler of the [[Mythology of Stargate#Jaffa|Sodan]]. Named for [[Ishkur]] of [[Mesopotamian mythology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Babylon&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Babylon|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Isis}}'''Isis''' [[Osiris (Stargate)|Osiris]]' Queen, who was imprisoned alongside him in a stasis jar by Seth, but died after the jar was damaged. Named for [[Isis]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]&lt;ref name=&quot;The Curse&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Curse|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''&quot;Junior&quot;''' Jack O'Neill's nickname for the larval Goa'uld carried by [[Teal'c]]. It is originally transferred to Rya'c and then the replacement is killed during an ambush of rebel Jaffa leaders by the System Lords.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Changeling&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Changeling|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Kali}}'''Kali''' (played by [[Suleka Mathew]]), named for [[Kali]] of [[Hindu mythology]]. A [[System Lord]] who attends a meeting to discuss their new threat; she accuses Olokun as her First Prime had found Jaffa bearing his mark on an attacking mothership. She votes to readmit Anubis into their ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Khonsu}}'''Khonsu''' (played by [[Adam Harrington (actor)|Adam Harrington]]), named for [[Khonsu]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. An undercover [[Tok'ra]] posing as one of Anubis' underlords, who has captured [[SG-1]] so he can pass on important information. He is killed by his First Prime Herak after his Tok'ra identity is exposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Other Guys&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Other Guys|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Klorel}}'''Klorel''' (played by [[Alexis Cruz]]) The son of [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]], who takes the Abydonian [[Skaara]] as a host.&lt;ref name=&quot;Children of the Gods&quot; /&gt; Klorel accompanies Apophis in attacking on Earth, commanding his own [[Ha'tak]]. His mothership is infiltrated by [[SG-1]], and [[Jack O'Neill (Stargate)|Jack O'Neill]] is forced to shoot him to prevent him from using his hand device against them.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Lair&quot;/&gt; Klorel is revived by a sarcophagus, but is forced to escape as SG-1 and [[Bra'tac]] destroy their two attack ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Within the Serpent's Grasp&quot;/&gt; Klorel eventually flees from Heru-ur to Tollana. The [[Tollan (Stargate)|Tollan]] hold a triad (trial) to decide Skaara's request to have his symbiote removed, with the Goa'uld Zipacna representing Klorel. The Tollan rule against Klorel, and he is extracted from Skaara and sent to a planet of his choice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pretense&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Marduk}}'''Marduk''' (played by [[Alexander Kalugin]]), named for [[Marduk]] of [[Mesopotamian mythology]]. A Goa'uld so evil that his own priests rose up against him and imprisoned him in a sarcophagus with a flesh-eating creature that would prolong his suffering. However, Marduk survived by possessing the creature and is released by a Russian SG team. He possesses Major Vallarin and tries to escape, but is buried when Jack O'Neill sets off C-4 explosives inside his ziggurat. Marduk possessed the Eye of Tiamat, a powerful weapon.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tomb&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Tomb|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Image:Moloc Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Moloc.]]
* {{anchor|Moloc}}'''Moloc''' (played by [[Royston Innes]]) A powerful Goa'uld named for [[Moloch]] of [[Canaanite mythology]]. In order to strengthen his armies, Moloc ordered that all female children born to his Jaffa be sacrificed in the Ceremony of Fire. Appalled by this, his High Priestess [[List of recurring alien characters in Stargate SG-1#Ishta|Ishta]] began to secretly take those children to another planet. These female Jaffa become the Hak'tyl resistance, a substantial force that launches regular raids against Moloc's forces and eventually ally themselves with the SGC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brithright&quot;&gt;&quot;[[Birthright (Stargate SG-1)|Birthright]]&quot; (''[[Stargate SG-1]]'')&lt;/ref&gt; Moloc eventually discovers Hak'tyl, forcing Ishta's group to evacuate, and attacks a meeting of rebel Jaffa who are planning an insurrection against him. He then prepares his [[Ha'tak]]s to crush a rebel army marching on his temple, but before he can give the order he is struck by two [[missile]]s fired by the SGC through the Stargate, and laser-guided to him by Aron.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sacrifices&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Sacrifices|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Montu}}'''Montu''' A minor Goa'uld who served Ra, and later Ba'al. His First Prime was [[Gerak]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Origin&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Origin|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Morrigan}}'''Morrigan''' (played by [[Bonnie Kilroe]]) A [[System Lord]] named for [[Morrigan]] of [[Celtic mythology]] known for using her lo'taur to draw out strategic information from the servants of her enemies. She votes to readmit Anubis as a System Lord.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; She is eventually forced to capitulate to Ba'al.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Mot}}'''Mot''' (played by [[Victor Talmadge]]) A minor Goa'uld in service of Ba'al. He controlled a naqahdah mining operation on P4S-237, hoarding the naqahdah for himself in the hopes of one day rising up against his master. He is killed in a [[SG-1]]-supported uprising on the planet.&lt;ref name=&quot;Prophecy&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Nefertum}}'''Nefertum''' Goa'uld worshiped by the [[Bedrosian]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;New Ground&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|New Ground|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Nerus}}'''Nerus''' (played by [[Maury Chaykin]]) A minor Goa'uld, named for [[Nereus]] of [[Greek mythology]], who served Ba'al, known for his &quot;many appetites&quot;. An inventor, he figured out the means to dial all the Stargates in the galaxy at once, that was used to defeat the [[Replicator (Stargate)|Replicators]]. Nerus travels to Earth with information about an [[Ori (Stargate)|Ori]] beachhead at Kallana, but is revealed to be working for them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Beachhead&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Beachhead|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; He is imprisoned in Area 51 without food until he is released (with a tracking device) in exchange for information about why Ba'al is stealing Stargates. As expected he returns to Ba'al, who executes him after finding he unwittingly brought along a SGC computer virus as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Off the Grid&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Olokun}}'''Olokun''' (played by [[Kwesi Ameyaw]]) A [[System Lord]], named for [[Olokun]] of [[Yoruba mythology]]. He attends a meeting of the System Lords to discuss a new enemy, and votes to readmit Anubis into their collective.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; Anubis later sends his [[Kull Warrior]]s against Olokun, slaughtering thousands of his Jaffa and capturing many of his commanders. At the time, the rebel Jaffa were attempting to recruit from Olokun's ranks. As the [[Tok'ra]] also had a spy in Olokun's inner circle, the rebel Jaffa asked them to assassinate Olokun. The Tok'ra refused for fear that Anubis would simply absorb Olokun's forces into his own, driving a wedge between the two allies. It is believed that either the rebel Jaffa agents or the Tok'ra spy could have compromised the location of the [[Alpha Site]] to Anubis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Death Knell&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Death Knell|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Olokun is eventually killed by [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]]'s forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;It's Good To Be King&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Pelops}}'''Pelops''' Goa'uld who experimented on the people of Argos using nanocites. Named for [[Pelops]], an ancient king of [[Greek mythology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brief Candle&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Brief Candle|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Qetesh}}'''Qetesh''' (played by [[Claudia Black]]), named for [[Qetesh]] of [[Canaanite mythology]]. A powerful Goa'uld who was extracted from her host [[Vala Mal Doran]] by the [[Tok'ra]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prometheus Unbound&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prometheus Unbound|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of her holdings was P8X-412, where she enslaved the population to mine naqahdah, instituting mass torture and executions when quotas were not met.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Power That Be&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Powers That Be|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Qetesh once partnered with Athena to locate the [[Clava Thessara Infinitas]], but betrayed her and kept the information for herself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Memento Mori&quot;/&gt; Qetesh had an interesting relationship with Ba'al; though she once attacked his fleet at Selenis, crippling his flagship and slaughtering 10,000 of his best Jaffa, Vala would later claim that there was a &quot;spark&quot; between them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Insiders&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Insiders|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'', [[Ba'al (Stargate)|Ba'al]] makes Qetesh his queen though she chafes at her role. She eventually betrays and kills him, attempting to seize his time machine for herself, but is killed by Teal'c.
* {{anchor|Ramius}}'''Ramius''' (played by [[Sean Whale]]) A minor Goa'uld who barely escapes an attack by a [[Kull Warrior]] while trying to ally with Tilgath, another minor Goa'uld. He is later killed by another Kull Warrior on his homeworld, and his army absorbed into that of Anubis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Sekhmet}}'''Sekhmet''' (played by [[Kristen Dalton (actress)|Kristen Dalton]]) and named for [[Sekhmet]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. A Goa'uld who once served Ra. The rogue NID incorporated her DNA into a human ovum to create a woman named Anna, in the hopes of accessing the Goa'uld genetic memory. Sekhmet's evil personality emerges within Anna, leading to Anna's suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Resurrection&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Resurrection|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 [[Image:Seth Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Seth.]]
* {{anchor|Seth}}'''Seth''' (played by [[Robert Duncan (actor)|Robert Duncan]]) Also known as Setesh, Set, Seti, or Setekh and named for [[Set (mythology)|Set]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. He is a former [[System Lord]] who betrayed [[Ra (Stargate)|Ra]] and imprisoned his brother Osiris.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Curse&quot; /&gt; The [[Tok'ra]] uncover evidence that he never left Earth, and he is found to have led various Cults of Setesh for thousands of years. In the present day he is leading a heavily-armed cult in Washington state, brainwashing his followers with [[Goa'uld technology in Stargate#Other technology|nish'ta]]. He is killed by [[Samantha Carter]] as the ATF storms his compound. Seth's helmeted Jaffa, the Setesh Guard, are the butt of Jaffa jokes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Seth&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Seth|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Shaq'ran}}'''Shaq'ran''' The former ruler of Pangar, who conquered it from Ra. He was defeated by Apophis c. 1700 A.D.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cure&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Sobek}}'''Sobek''' A Goa'uld, named for [[Sobek]] of [[Egyptian mythology]], who once allied himself with Bastet and Kali, only to be betrayed at the celebration dinner. His decapitated head is said to decorate Bastet's palace at Bubastis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt;
{{Clear}}
[[Image:Svarog Symbol (Stargate).svg|thumb|100px|Symbol of Svarog.]]
* {{anchor|Svarog}}'''Svarog''' (played by unknown actor) One of the [[System Lord]]s named for [[Svarog]] of [[Slavic mythology]], who votes to readmit Anubis into their ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; He is &quot;sent away&quot; by the Sentinel, an advanced defensive technology, while trying to invade Latona.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Sentinel&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|The Sentinel|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{anchor|Telchak}}'''Telchak''' Goa'uld who discovered an Ancient healing device and used it to develop the [[Sarcophagus (Stargate)|sarcophagus]]; may have inspired myths of the [[Maya mythology|Maya]]n rain god [[Chaac]]. Anubis went to war with Telchak for the device, but though he was victorious he never found it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Terok}}'''Terok''' (played by [[Paul Koslo]]) A minor Goa'uld in service of Heru-ur, charged with torturing Teal'c into admitting that the Goa'uld are gods, to break the spirit of the Jaffa resistance. He is killed by Rak'nor, who has a change of heart after witnessing Teal'c resolve.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Serpent's Venom&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Thanos}}'''Thanos''' Ruler of Langara 3,000 years ago, who created [[naqahdriah]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Meridian&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Meridian|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Probably named for [[Thanatos]] of Greek mythology.
* {{anchor|Thoth}}'''Thoth''' (played by [[Ian Marsh (actor)|Ian Marsh]]), named for [[Thoth]] of [[Egyptian mythology]]. An underling of Anubis, responsible for overseeing the [[Kull Warrior]]s on Tartarus. He is killed by [[Samantha Carter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Tiamat}}'''Tiamat''' Namesake of the Eye of Tiamat, one of six such powerful devices. Named for [[Tiamat]] of [[Babylonian mythology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Full Circle&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Tomb&quot;/&gt;
* {{anchor|Tilgath}}'''Tilgath''' (played by unknown actor) Minor Goa'uld assassinated by a [[Kull Warrior]] during a meeting with Ramius, so that Anubis could usurp his armies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Evolution&quot; /&gt;
* {{anchor|Zipacna}}'''Zipacna''' (played by [[Kevin Durand]]), named for [[Zipacna]] of [[Maya mythology]]. A Goa'uld who once served [[Apophis (Stargate)|Apophis]]. He argues for [[Klorel]] being allowed to remain inside his host [[Skaara]] at a [[Tollan (Stargate)|Tollan]] trial, while secretly plotting to destroy the Tollan ion cannon network. When his attack fails, he escapes through the Stargate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pretense&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Pretense|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Zipacna later pledges allegiance to Anubis and recruits Osiris into his service. He commands an attack on the main Tok'ra base at Revanna, killing almost all the Tok'ra there but failing to find the symbiote poison.&lt;ref name=&quot;Last Stand&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt; The rebel Jaffa have mounted several raids on Zipacna's forces under Kytano,&lt;ref name=&quot;The Warrior&quot; /&gt; and the Tok'ra Kanan's last mission was to infiltrate one of Zipacna's motherships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Abyss&quot; /&gt; He is mentioned in the alternate timeline of ''[[Stargate: Continuum]]'' as serving Ba'al.
* An unnamed Goa'uld possessed [[Adrian Conrad]] (played by [[Bill Marchant]]) and [[Frank Simmons]] (played by [[John de Lancie]]). It was the larval Goa'uld of a Jaffa captured by the Russians and acquired by billionaire Adrian Conrad in the hopes of curing his terminal illness. After possessing Conrad, it is captured by Frank Simmons of the NID and gives them information for promises of freedom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Desperate Measures&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Desperate Measures|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;48 Hours&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|48 Hours|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simmons uses him to hijack the ''Prometheus''; after Conrad is shot the Goa'uld transfers into Simmons, who is blown out an airlock by [[SG-1]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Prometheus&quot;&gt;{{sgcite|Prometheus|show=ref}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* An unnamed Goa'uld possessed [[Kianna Cyr]] (played by [[Emily Holmes]]). The Goa'uld was an agent sent by Ba'al to Langara to investigate naqahdria, who poses as [[Jonas Quinn]]'s colleague. She plays a major part in designing an underground drilling machine and helps Jonas and [[SG-1]] save Langara from an impending naqahdria explosion, not entirely out of self-interest. She dies saving her host from gas poisoning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fallout&quot;/&gt;
* An unnamed Goa'uld who takes Colonel Steven Caldwell as a host and who is loyal to The Trust.  He sabatoges Atlantis in an attempt to destroy it, but is exposed by Lieutenant Laura Cadman.  He is interogated for the nessacary access code to stop the destruction, but refuses to give it up so Lieutenant Colonel John Sheppard tasers him, allowing Caldwell to regain control and give them the needed code.  Afterwards, the Goa'uld is extracted using Asgard beaming technology and presumably killed.

==References==
{{Reflist|3}}

{{Stargate}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Goa'uld Characters In Stargate}}
[[Category:Stargate characters]]

[[fr:Liste des Goa'ulds de Stargate]]
[[sv:Systemherrarna]]
[[tr:Goa'uld karakterleri listesi]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
