<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3874674" ns="0" title="Betty Eagleton"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{In-universe|subject = television|category = television|date = October 2009}}
{{Inappropriate tone|date=December 2007}}
{{Infobox soap character 2
|series=Emmerdale
|image=[[Image:Betty_Eagleton.jpg‎|200px]]
|caption=Paula Tilbrook as Betty in 2010.
|name=Betty Eagleton
|introducer=Mervyn Watson
|portrayer=[[Paula Tilbrook]]
|born= 22 January 1934
|death=
|years=1994—
|first=12 April 1994
|classification=[[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|home=Keepers Cottage
|occupation=[[retirement|Retired]]
|husband = Wally Eagleton (1954–93)
|father= Arthur Pendagast
|romances = [[Seth Armstrong]]  (1953, 1994–2005)
|first=12 April 1994
|last=
}}
'''Elizabeth &quot;Betty&quot; Eagleton''' (née '''Pendagast''') is a [[fictional character]] from the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[Paula Tilbrook]]. She made her first on-screen appearance on 12 April 1994 and, in [[2011]], following the death of [[Viv Hope]], she is the longest-serving female character.
==Backstory==

Betty Pendergrast and Seth Armstrong were childhood sweethearts and nearly married in 1944. Betty claims to have been born in January 1934 which would mean that she would have been just 10 years old when she nearly married Seth, so it is probable that Betty is a bit older than what she claims. She has one sister whose name is unknown. She later married Wally Eagleton in 1954 and was married for 39 years until Wally died in 1993. 

==Storylines==
===1994–2003===
Betty Eagleton is best known as one of the village busybodies.

She made her first appearance in the show in April 1994. Upon her arrival in 1994 she soon became associated as one of the village gossipers and even tried to call off [[Zoe Tate]]'s lesbian wedding in 1996. 

In 2000, her ex Reggie arrived in the village. It transpired that Betty and Reggie dated while working in the Windmill Theatre in London. On the day she went to tell him she was expecting their baby, Betty found him in bed with another woman and had an abortion. Unfortunately this left her unable to have children but kept this to herself. Knowing this, Reggie tried to blackmail Betty by threatening to tell Seth. Instead, Betty told him herself and Seth drove Reggie out of the village.

===2004—===
In 2004, Betty decided to visit her friend [[Kathy Brookman|Kathy]] in Australia and went on a long holiday. [[Seth Armstrong]] joined her, but when she got homesick and returned to Emmerdale several months later but came back alone. She spent a lot of time with Seth in Australia.

On Christmas Eve, Betty got the best present ever when Seth sung &quot;Silent Night&quot; to her over an Internet connection. However, on his way home, Seth died on the aeroplane. Betty was waiting at the airport when her friend [[Kathy Brookman]] broke the bad news. 

During Seth's funeral, Betty took Seth's coffin and buried it in the countryside, with help from [[Laurel Thomas|Laurel]], [[Zak Dingle|Zak]] and [[Sam Dingle]]. A fake coffin, containing a sack of sand, was buried  in the Emmerdale cemetery. The funeral also saw the return of Betty and Seth's former lodger [[Biff Fowler]].

Soon after, [[Alan Turner (Emmerdale)|Alan Turner]] moved in with Betty. After lamenting a lack of contact with his son Terence, it was Betty who got in touch with Terence and convinced him to return to Emmerdale. It was revealed that Terrence sexually abused his sister as a child. Unable to accept this, Alan lashed out at Betty and moved into Holdgate Farm with Terrence.  Alan later realised the truth and returned to live with Betty. Terence went missing soon after this and Steph began claiming that her new husband, Adam, murdered him. It turned out that she was telling the truth but nobody believed her as Adam had poisoned her and then had her sectioned. So she forfeited her freedom by claiming they murdered him together and both Adam and Steph were sent to jail.

As Betty and Alan struggled to get over this, a new person entered Betty's life, Sandy Thomas. He is the father of local vicar, Ashley Thomas. Ashley and Sandy didn't get on that well and following an argument, Sandy moved in with Betty and Alan.

Recently Betty's dog Charlie died, and she decided to spread the dog's cremated remains over Seth's burial place.

In June 2008, Betty told [[Laurel Thomas]] that she was like &quot;the daughter she never had&quot;.

Betty has discovered Donald De Souza's body, joined the church choir and was locked in a small room during a singing competition for several hours in December 2008.

In March 2009, [[Jamie Hope]] asked Betty to make a batch of [[chutney]] to send to [[Louise Appleton|Louise]] in [[Australia]]. Betty obliged, and spent hours making several jars. The following day, while cleaning at Home Farm she was tired, and [[Nathan Wylde]] told Natasha that Jamie had made a delivery of chutney. Betty had a funny turn, dropping a vase in the process. She took one jar of chutney and saw that Jamie had put a label on, replacing hers. Betty decided to get revenge on Jamie and Bob, who was also in on it, recalling the chutney she had made, saying Alan was ill because of the batch she had made the previous night. Betty said she would make another batch, making a disgusting alternative. She gave it to Jamie, who took it to Home Farm. Nathan unwittingly tasted a spoonful and had to rush to the sink because of its foul flavour. Natasha then went to the Woolpack and shoved a spoonful into Jamie's mouth, warning him not to pull a stunt like that again. Betty admitted what she had done, and wanted free tea and cakes in the café as compensation. However, [[Rodney Blackstock]] pointed out that she may have missed an opportunity with the Wyldes, but Betty eventually made an arrangement with Natasha and she produces chutney under the Home Farm brand.

When Mark Wylde's body was found, Betty thought it might have been Seth's and admitted to Alan that they buried him in Home Farm grounds and sandbags were buried at the cemetry. 

In Jan 2011, the fire that spread through Emmerdale went into Betty's home whilst she slept and she was unaware about the fire. She was saved by the residents and was taken to hospital due to her intake of the smoke. Her friends Edna, Pearl and Alan all helped Betty get better and she is now fighting fit, being observant and back to gossiping. In June 2011, Chastity heard Betty and Val gossiping over Hazel and Aaron helping Jackson to die. Chastity told Betty she had no idea what she was talking about. Betty then continued to drink her sherry.

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/page.asp?partid=3683 Betty Eagleton] at [[itv.com]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Emmerdale characters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Eagleton, Betty}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1994]]
[[Category:Fictional cleaners]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
