<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="38769" ns="0" title="Mercia"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{two other uses|the Anglo-Saxon kingdom|the Spanish city|Murcia}}
{{Infobox Former Country
|native_name = ''Miercna rīce''
|conventional_long_name = Kingdom of Mercia
|common_name = Mercia
|continent   = Europe
|region      = British Isles
|country     = England
|year_start  = 527
|year_end    = 918
|date_start  =
|date_end    = 4 December
|life_span   =
|event_start = [[Icel (person)|Icel]] led the [[Angles]] over the [[North Sea]] (traditional)
|event_end   = Mercia annexed to [[Wessex]] to form the [[Kingdom of England]]
|event1      = [[Creoda of Mercia|Creoda]] first true Mercian monarch at Tamworth
|date_event1 = 584
|p1          = Angles
|flag_p1     = Uffe den spake.jpg
|image_p1    =
|p2          =
|flag_p2     =
|s1          = Kingdom of England
|s2          =
|flag_s1     = Flag of England.svg
|flag_s2     =
|image_flag  = Saint Alban's cross.svg
|flag_type   = [[Saint Alban's Cross|Cross of Saint Alban]]
|image_coat  = Mercian eagle.png
|symbol_type = [[Leofric, Earl of Mercia|Eagle of Leofric]]
|image_map         = Kingdom of Mercia.PNG
|image_map_caption = Expansion of the Kingdom of Mercia: dark green 6th century; green 7th century; yellow 8th century.
|national_motto    =
|national_anthem   =
|capital           = [[Tamworth]]
|religion          = [[Anglo-Saxon paganism|Paganism]]&lt;br&gt;[[Christianity]]
|common_languages  = [[Mercian (Old English)|Old English]] (''Englisc'')
|government_type   = Monarchy
|title_leader      = Monarchs (see [[List of monarchs of Mercia|full list]])
|leader1           = [[Icel (person)|Icel]]
|year_leader1      = 527&amp;ndash;?
|leader2           = [[Creoda of Mercia|Creoda]]
|year_leader2      = 584&amp;ndash;593
|leader3           = [[Penda of Mercia|Penda]]
|year_leader3      = 626&amp;ndash;655
|leader4           = [[Offa of Mercia|Offa]]
|year_leader4      = 757&amp;ndash;796
|leader5           = [[Ælfwynn]]
|year_leader5      = 918
|legislature       = Witan
|house1            =
|stat_year1        =
|stat_area1        =
|stat_pop1         =
|currency          = [[Pound sterling]]
|footnotes         =
}}

'''Mercia''' ({{IPAc-en|icon|ˈ|m|ɜr|s|i|ə}}, {{IPAc-en|ˈ|m|ɜr|ʃ|ə}})&lt;ref&gt;Roach &amp; Hartman, eds. (1997) ''English Pronouncing Dictionary'', 15th edition. (Cambridge University Press). p. 316; see also J.C. Wells, ''Longman Pronouncing Dictionary'' and Upton et al., ''Oxford Dictionary of Pronunciation for Current English''.&lt;/ref&gt;
was one of the kingdoms of the [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] [[Heptarchy]]. It was centred on the valley of the [[River Trent]] and its tributaries in the region now known as the [[English Midlands]]. The name is a [[Latinisation (literature)|Latinisation]] of the [[Old English]] '''''Mierce''''' or '''''Myrce''''', meaning &quot;border people&quot;.

Mercia's neighbours included [[Northumbria]], [[Kingdom of Powys|Powys]], the kingdoms of southern [[Wales]], [[Wessex]], [[Kingdom of Sussex|Sussex]], [[Kingdom of Essex|Essex]], and [[Kingdom of the East Angles|East Anglia]].

The name ''Mercia'' is still in use today by a wide range of organisations, including military units, public, commercial and voluntary bodies.

== Early history ==
[[File:Staffordshire hoard annotated.jpg|thumb|left|The [[Staffordshire Hoard]], discovered in a field in [[Hammerwich]], near [[Lichfield]] in July 2009, is perhaps the most important collection of [[Anglo-Saxon]] objects found in [[England]]]]
Mercia's exact evolution from the [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] invasions is more obscure than that of [[Northumbria]], [[History of Kent|Kent]], or even [[Wessex]]. Also, Mercia developed an effective political structure and adopted [[Christianity]] later than the other kingdoms.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cambridge466&quot;&gt;Fouracre, Paul ed. ''The New Cambridge Medieval History v.I'', Cambridge (2005) pg. 466&lt;/ref&gt; Archaeological surveys show that [[Angles]] settled the lands north of the [[River Thames]] by the sixth century. The name Mercia is [[Old English]] for &quot;boundary folk&quot; (''see [[Welsh Marches]]''), and the traditional interpretation is that the kingdom originated along the frontier between the native [[Wales|Welsh]] and the Anglo-Saxon invaders. However, [[Peter Hunter Blair|P. Hunter Blair]]  argued an alternative interpretation: that they emerged along the frontier of Northumbria and the inhabitants of the [[River Trent|Trent river valley]].

While its earliest boundaries will never be known, there is general agreement that the territory that was called &quot;the first of the Mercians&quot; in the [[Tribal Hidage]] covered much of south Derbyshire, Leicestershire, Nottinghamshire, Staffordshire and Northern Warwickshire.&lt;ref&gt;Brooks, Nicholas ''Anglo-Saxon myths: state and church, 400-1066''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hill, D. ''Atlas of Anglo-Saxon England'', Oxford (1981), map 136&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hooke, Della ''Anglo-Saxon Territorial Organisation: The Western Margins of Mercia'', University of Birmingham, Dept. of Geography, Occasional Paper 22 (1986) pp.1-45&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest [[List of monarchs of Mercia|king of Mercia]] of whom any details are known is [[Creoda of Mercia|Creoda]], said to have been the great-grandson of [[Icel of Mercia|Icel]]. Coming to power around 584, he built a fortress at [[Tamworth]] which became the seat of Mercia's kings. His son [[Pybba]] succeeded him in 593. [[Cearl of Mercia|Cearl]], a kinsman of Creoda, followed Pybba in 606; in 615, Cearl gave his daughter Cwenburga in marriage to [[Edwin of Northumbria|Edwin]], king of [[Deira (kingdom)|Deira]] whom he had sheltered while he was an exiled prince.

== Penda and the Mercian Supremacy ==
{{Main|Penda|Wulfhere|Æthelbald|Mercian Supremacy}}
The next Mercian king was [[Penda of Mercia|Penda]], who ruled from about 626 or 633 until 655. Some of what is known about Penda comes through the hostile account of [[Bede]], who disliked him both for being an enemy king to Bede's own [[Northumbria]] and for being a [[Paganism|pagan]]. However, Bede admits that it was Penda who freely allowed [[Early Christianity|Christian]] [[missionary|missionaries]] from [[Lindisfarne]] into Mercia, and did not restrain them from preaching. Edwin, who had become ruler not only of the newly unified [[Northumbria]], but [[bretwalda]], or high king, over the southern kingdoms, was defeated and killed by Penda and his ally [[Cadwallon ap Cadfan|Cadwallon of Gwynedd]] in 633. When another Northumbrian king, [[Oswald of Northumbria|Oswald]], arose and again claimed overlordship of the south, he also was defeated and killed by Penda and his allies in 642 at the [[Battle of Maserfield]]. In 655, after a period of confusion in Northumbria, Penda brought 30 sub-kings to fight the new Northumbrian king [[Oswiu of Northumbria|Oswiu]] at the [[Battle of Winwaed]], in which Penda in turn lost the battle and his life.&lt;ref&gt;Fouracre, Paul ed. ''The New Cambridge Medieval History v.I'', Cambridge (2005) pg. 465&lt;/ref&gt;

The battle led to a temporary collapse of Mercian power. Penda was succeeded first by his son [[Peada]] (who converted to Christianity at [[Repton]] in 653), and who was set up by Oswiu as an under king, but in the spring of 656 he was murdered and Oswiu assumed direct control of the whole of Mercia. A revolt in 658 threw off Northumbrian domination and resulted in the appearance of another son of Penda, [[Wulfhere of Mercia|Wulfhere]], who ruled Mercia as an independent kingdom (though he apparently continued to render tribute to Northumbria for a while) until his death in 675. Wulfhere was initially successful in restoring the power of Mercia, but the end of his reign saw a serious defeat by Northumbria. The next king, [[Æthelred of Mercia|Æthelred]] defeated Northumbria in the [[Battle of the Trent]] in 679, settling once and for all the long disputed control of the former kingdom of [[Lindsey]]. Æthelred was succeeded by [[Cenred of Mercia|Cœnred]] son of Wulfhere, and both these kings are better known for their religious activities than anything else, but the king who succeeded them (in 709), [[Ceolred of Mercia|Ceolred]], is said in a letter of [[Saint Boniface]] to have been a dissolute youth who died insane. So ended the rule of the direct descendants of Penda.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cambridge466&quot;/&gt;

At some point before the accession of [[Ethelbald of Mercia|Æthelbald]], the Mercians conquered the region around [[Wroxeter]], known to the Welsh as [[Pengwern]] or &quot;The Paradise of Powys&quot;. Elegies written in the persona of its [[Cynddylan|dispossessed rulers]] record the sorrow at this loss.

The next important king of Mercia was Æthelbald (716&amp;ndash;757). For the first few years of his reign he had to face the obstacles of two strong rival kings, [[Wihtred of Kent]] and [[Ine of Wessex]]. But when Wihtred died in 725, and Ine abdicated his throne the following year to become a [[monk]] in [[Rome]], Æthelbald was free to establish Mercia's hegemony over the rest of the Anglo-Saxons south of the [[Humber]]. Æthelbald suffered a setback in 752, when he was defeated by the West Saxons under [[Cuthred of Wessex|Cuthred]], but he seems to have restored his supremacy over Wessex by 757.

In July 2009, the [[Staffordshire hoard]] of [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] gold was discovered in a field near [[Lichfield]] in [[Staffordshire]]. Lichfield was the religious centre of Mercia.  The artefacts have tentatively been dated to around AD 600–800. Whether the hoard was deposited by [[Anglo-Saxon paganism|Anglo-Saxon pagans]] or [[Christianity|Christians]] is debated, as is the purpose of the deposit.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbc&quot;&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/staffordshire/8272058.stm|title=Huge Anglo-Saxon gold hoard found|publisher=[[News.bbc.co.uk]]|accessdate=2009-09-24 | date=24 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Reign of Offa and rise of Wessex ==
[[Image:British kingdoms c 800.svg|thumb|Great Britain around the year 800]]
Following the murder of Æthelbald by one of his bodyguards in 757, a civil war followed, which was concluded with the victory of [[Offa of Mercia|Offa]]. Offa was forced to build the hegemony over the southern English of his predecessor anew, which he did so successfully that he became the greatest king Mercia ever knew. Not only did he win battles and dominate southern England, he also took an active hand to administering the affairs of his kingdom by founding [[market town]]s and overseeing the first major issues of gold [[coin]]s in Britain, assumed a role in the administration of the [[Catholic Church]] in England (sponsoring the short-lived archbishopric of Lichfield), and even negotiated with [[Charlemagne]] as an equal. Offa is credited with the construction of [[Offa's Dyke]], marking the border between Wales and Mercia.

Offa exerted himself to ensure that his son [[Ecgfrith of Mercia]] would succeed him, but after his death in July 796, Ecgfrith survived for only five more months, and the kingdom passed to a distant relative named [[Coenwulf of Mercia|Coenwulf]] in December 796. In 821, Coenwulf was succeeded by his brother [[Ceolwulf I of Mercia|Ceolwulf]], who demonstrated his military prowess by his attack on and destruction of the fortress of [[Deganwy]] in [[Powys]]. The power of the [[Wessex|West Saxons]] under [[Egbert of Wessex|Egbert]] was rising during this period, however, and in 825 Egbert defeated the Mercian king [[Beornwulf of Mercia|Beornwulf]] (who had overthrown Ceolwulf in 823) at [[Ellendun]].

The Battle of Ellendun proved decisive. Beornwulf was slain suppressing a revolt amongst the East Angles, and his successor, a former [[ealdorman]] named [[Ludeca of Mercia|Ludeca]], met the same fate. Another ealdorman, [[Wiglaf of Mercia|Wiglaf]], subsequently ruled for less than two years before being driven out of Mercia by Egbert. In 830, Wiglaf regained independence for Mercia, but by this time Wessex was clearly the dominant power in England. Wiglaf was succeeded by [[Beorhtwulf of Mercia|Beorhtwulf]].

== Arrival of the Danes ==

In 852, [[Burgred]] came to the throne and with [[Ethelwulf of Wessex]] subjugated [[North Wales]]. In 868, [[Viking]] invaders (from Denmark) occupied [[Nottingham]]. The Vikings drove Burgred from his kingdom in 874 and appointed [[Ceolwulf II of Mercia|Ceolwulf II]] in his place. In 877 the Vikings seized the eastern part of Mercia, which became part of the [[Danelaw]].&lt;ref&gt;Frank Stenton, ''Anglo-Saxon England'', Oxford University Press, 1971, p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; Ceolwulf, the last king of Mercia, was left with the western half, but he disappeared by 881.&lt;ref&gt;This the date given in the Wikipedia article on Ceolwulf, although a Mercian regnal list assigns him a reign of five years (Stenton, p. 259n)&lt;/ref&gt; From 883 until 911 [[Earl Aethelred of Mercia|Earl Æthelred of Mercia]] ruled Mercia as an [[earl|ealderman]] under the king of Wessex, not a king himself. All coins struck in Mercia after the disappearance of Ceolwulf in c879 were in the name of the West Saxon king.&lt;ref&gt;Stewart Lyon, The coinage of Edward the Elder, in N. J. Higham &amp; D. H. Hill, Edward the Elder 899-924, London 2001, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt; Æthelred had married [[Æthelflæd]], daughter of [[Alfred the Great]] of Wessex. She gradually assumed power as her husband sickened after about 900, possibly as a result of his wounds gained at the decisive battle against the Vikings at [[Tettenhall]] where the last large Viking army to ravage England suffered a crushing defeat at the hands of the combined Mercian and Wessex army. After Æthelred's death Æthelflæd ruled alone as ‘Lady of the Mercians’ until her death in 918, when her brother, [[Edward the Elder]] of Wessex, became king over Mercia as well.
In 911, immediately after Æthelred’s death, Æthelflæd freely gave London and Oxford, with the lands belonging thereto, to her brother in Wessex as a token of loyalty.  She then concentrated on fortifying Mercia's existing borders &amp;ndash; east towards Nottingham, north to Chester, along the Welsh marches, and down to the [[River Severn|Severn]] estuary.  In 917 she expelled the Danes from [[Derby]].

==Loss of independence==

The [[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]] describes the end of independent political direction in Mercia following the death of Æthelflæd in 918.  Edward of Wessex took over the fortress at Tamworth and accepted the submission of all those settled in Mercia, both Danish and English.  In late 918, Ælfwynn, the daughter of Æthelred, was deprived of all authority in Mercia and taken to Wessex.

References to Mercia and the Mercians continue through the annals recording the reigns of [[Æthelstan]] and his successors.  In 975 King [[Edgar the Peaceful|Edgar]] is described as “friend of the West Saxons and protector of the Mercians”.

A separate political existence from Wessex was briefly restored in 955&amp;ndash;959, when Edgar became king of Mercia, and again in 1016, when the kingdom was divided between [[Cnut]] and [[Edmund Ironside]], Cnut taking Mercia.

The last reference to Mercia by name is in the annal for 1017, when [[Eadric Streona]] was awarded the government of Mercia by Cnut.  The later earls, [[Leofric]], [[Ælfgar, Earl of Mercia|Ælfgar]] and [[Edwin]], ruled over a territory broadly corresponding to historic Mercia, but the Chronicle does not identify it by name.  The Mercians as a people are last mentioned in the annal for 1049.

The [[Arden family]] claim descent from [[Leofric, Earl of Mercia]].

== Mercian dialect ==
{{Main|Mercian (Anglo-Saxon)|AB language}}
[[J.R.R. Tolkien]] is one of many scholars who have studied and promoted the Mercian dialect of [[Old English]], and introduced various Mercian terms into his [[Tolkien's legendarium|legendarium]] &amp;ndash; especially in relation to the [[Rohan|Kingdom of Rohan]], otherwise known as the ''Mark'' (a name cognate with ''Mercia''). Not only is the language of Rohan actually represented as&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Tolkien | first = J.R.R. | title = [[The Lord of the Rings]] | publisher = Houghton-Mifflin | year = 2005 | pages = 1133–1138 | isbn = 978-0-618-64561-9}} For more on Tolkien’s &quot;translation&quot; of the language of Rohan into [[Old English]], see especially page 1136.&lt;/ref&gt; the Mercian dialect of Old English, but a number of its kings are given the same names as monarchs who appear in the Mercian royal genealogy, e.g. [[Fréawine]], [[Fréaláf Hildeson|Fréaláf]] and [[Éomer]] (see [[List of kings of the Angles]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book  | last = Shippey  | first = Prof. Tom  | title = The Road to Middle Earth  | publisher = HarperCollins  | date = 2005 (1982)  | pages = 139–140  | isbn = 0-261-10275-3}} Shippey notes that Tolkien uses 'Mercian' forms of Anglo-Saxon, e.g.  &quot;''[[Saruman]]'',  ''[[Hasufel]]'', ''[[Herugrim]]'' for 'standard' [Anglo-Saxon] ''Searuman'', ''Heasufel'' and ''Heorugrim''&quot; Footnote page 140&lt;/ref&gt;

The dialect thrived between the 8th and 13th centuries and was referred to by [[John Trevisa]], writing in 1387:&lt;ref name=&quot;Elmes&quot;&gt;Elmes (2005)&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|For men of the est with men of the west, as it were undir the same partie of hevene, acordeth more in sownynge of speche than men of the north with men of the south, therfore it is that Mercii, that beeth men of myddel Engelond, as it were parteners of the endes, understondeth better the side langages, northerne and southerne, than northerne and southerne understondeth either other...}}

== Mercian religion ==
{{Main|Mercian Religion|Chad of Mercia|Cedd|Wulfhere|Merewalh}}
The first kings of Mercia were pagans, and they resisted the encroachment of Christianity longer than other kingdoms in the Anglo-Saxon Heptarchy.

Mercian rulers remained resolutely pagan until the reign of Peada in 656, although this did not prevent them joining coalitions with Christian Welsh rulers to resist Northumbria. The first appearance of Christianity in Mercia, however, had come at least thirty years earlier, following the [[Battle of Cirencester]] of 628, when Penda incorporated the formerly West Saxon territories of Hwicce into his kingdom.

The conversion of Mercia to Christianity occurred in the latter part of the 7th century, and by the time of Penda's defeat and death, Mercia was largely surrounded by Christian states. [[Diuma]], an Irish monk and one of Oswiu's missionaries was subsequently ordained a bishop - the first to operate in Mercia. Christianity finally gained a foothold in Mercia when Oswiu supported Peada as sub-king of the Middle Angles, requiring him to marry Oswiu's daughter, Alchflaed, and to accept her religion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bede|title=Ecclesiastical History of the English People, Book 3, chapter 21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Decisive steps to Christianise Mercia were taken by [[Chad of Mercia|Chad]] (Latinised by Bede as ''Ceadda''), the fifth&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bede|title=Ecclesiastical History of the English People, Book 3, chapter 24}}&lt;/ref&gt; bishop to operate in Mercia. This controversial figure was given land by King Wulfhere to build a monastery at [[Lichfield]]. As in other Anglo-Saxon kingdoms, the many small monasteries established by the Mercian kings allowed the political/military and ecclesiastical leadership to consolidate their unity through bonds of kinship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Fletcher, Richard|title=The Conversion of Europe, p. 172-174, 181-182|publisher=HarperCollins|year=1997|isbn=0-00-255203-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Subdivisions of Mercia ==

For knowledge of the internal composition of the Kingdom of Mercia, we must rely on a document of uncertain age (possibly late 7th century), known as the ''[[Tribal Hidage]]'' &amp;ndash; an assessment of the extent (but not the location) of land owned (reckoned in [[Hide (unit)|hides]]), and therefore the military obligations and perhaps taxes due, by each of the Mercian tribes and subject kingdoms by name. This hidage exists in several manuscript versions, some as late as the 14th century. It lists a number of peoples, such as the [[Hwicce]], who have now vanished, except for reminders in various placenames (see map at the head of this article). The major subdivisions of Mercia were as follows:&lt;ref&gt;Sarah Zaluckyj &amp; Marge Feryok. ''Mercia: The Anglo-Saxon Kingdom of Central England'' (2001) ISBN 1-873827-62-8&lt;/ref&gt;

*'''South Mercians'''
:The Mercians dwelling south of the River Trent. Folk groups within included the ''[[Tomsaete|Tomsæte]]'' around [[Tamworth]] and the ''[[Pencersæte]]'' around [[Penkridge]] (approx. S. [[Staffordshire|Staffs.]] &amp; N. [[Warwickshire|Warks.]]).
*'''North Mercians'''
:The Mercians dwelling north of the River Trent (approx. N. [[Staffordshire|Staffs.]], S. [[Derbyshire|Derbys.]] &amp; [[Nottinghamshire|Notts.]]).
*'''Outer Mercia'''
:An early phase of Mercian expansion, possibly 6th century (approx. S. [[Lincolnshire|Lincs.]], [[Leicestershire|Leics.]], [[Rutland]], [[Northamptonshire|Northants]]. &amp; N. [[Oxfordshire|Oxon.]]).
*'''[[Kingdom of Lindsey|Lindsey]]'''
:Once a kingdom in its own right, disputed with [[Northumbria]] in the 7th century before finally coming under Mercian control (approx. N. [[Lincolnshire|Lincs.]]).
*'''[[Middle Angles]]'''
:A collection of many smaller folk groups under Mercian control from the 7th century, including the ''[[Spaldingas]]'' around [[Spalding, Lincolnshire|Spalding]], the ''Bilmingas'' and ''Wideringas'' near [[Stamford, Lincolnshire|Stamford]], the ''North Gyrwe'' and ''South Gyrwe'' near [[Peterborough]], the ''West Wixna'', ''East Wixna'', ''West Wille'' and ''East Wille'' near [[Ely, Cambridgeshire|Ely]], the ''Sweordora'', ''Hurstingas'' and ''Gifle'' near [[Bedford]], the ''Hicce'' around [[Hitchin]], the ''[[Cilternsæte]]'' in the [[Chilterns]] and the ''Feppingas'' near [[Thame]] (approx. [[Cambridgeshire|Cambs.]], [[Huntingdonshire|Hunts.]], [[Bedfordshire|Beds.]], [[Hertfordshire|Herts.]], [[Buckinghamshire|Bucks.]] &amp; S. [[Oxfordshire|Oxon.]]).
*'''[[Hwicce]]'''
:Once a kingdom in its own right, disputed with [[Wessex]] in the 7th century before finally coming under Mercian control. Smaller folk groups within included the ''[[Stoppingas]]'' around [[Warwick]] and the ''Arosæte'' near [[Droitwich]] (approx. [[Gloucestershire|Gloucs.]], [[Worcestershire|Worcs.]] &amp; S. [[Warwickshire|Warks.]]).
*'''[[Magonsæte]]'''
:A people of the Welsh border, also known as the Westerna, under Mercian control from the 7th century. Smaller folk groups within included the ''Temersæte'' near [[Hereford]] and the ''Hahlsæte'' near [[Ludlow]] (approx. [[Herefordshire|Herefs.]] &amp; S. [[Shropshire|Shrops.]]).
*'''[[Wreocensæte|Wreocansæte]]'''
:A people of the Welsh border under Mercian control from the 7th century. Smaller folk groups within included the ''Rhiwsæte'' near [[Wroxeter]] and the ''Meresæte'' near [[Chester]] (approx. N. [[Shropshire|Shrops.]], [[Flintshire|Flints.]] &amp; [[Cheshire]]).
*'''[[Pecsaetan|Pecsæte]]'''
:An isolated folk group of the [[Peak District]], under Mercian control from the 7th century (approx. N. [[Derbyshire|Derbys.]]).
*'''[[Lancashire|Land Between Ribble &amp; Mersey]]'''
:A disorganised region under Mercian control from the 7th century (approx. S. [[Lancashire|Lancs.]]).
*'''[[Middlesex|Middle Saxons]]'''
:Taken over from [[kingdom of Essex|Essex]] in the 8th century, including [[London]] (approx. [[Middlesex]]).

After Mercia was annexed by Wessex in the early 10th century, the West Saxon rulers divided it into [[shire]]s modelled after their own system, cutting across traditional Mercian divisions. These shires survived mostly intact until 1974, and even today still largely follow their original boundaries.

==Mercian regional consciousness==

The term ‘midlands’ is first recorded (as ‘mydlande’) in 1555.&lt;ref name=&quot;McWhirter&quot;&gt;McWhirter (1976)&lt;/ref&gt;  It is possible therefore that until then Mercia had remained the preferred term, as the quote from Trevisa above would indicate.

John Bateman, writing in 1876 or 1883, referred to contemporary [[Cheshire]] and [[Staffordshire]] landholdings as being in Mercia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bateman&quot;&gt;Bateman (1971)&lt;/ref&gt;  The most credible source for the conceit of a contemporary Mercia is [[Thomas Hardy]]’s [[Wessex]] novels.  The first of these appeared in 1874 and Hardy himself considered it the origin of the conceit of a contemporary Wessex.  [[Bram Stoker]] set his 1911 novel, ''[[The Lair of the White Worm]]'', in a contemporary Mercia that may have been influenced by Hardy, whose secretary was a friend of Stoker’s brother.  Although ‘Edwardian Mercia’ never had the success of ‘Victorian Wessex’, it was an idea that appealed to the higher echelons of society.  In 1908 Sir Oliver Lodge, Principal of Birmingham University, wrote to his counterpart at Bristol, welcoming a new university worthy of:

''the great Province of Wessex whose higher educational needs it will supply.  It will be no rival, but colleague and co-worker with this University, whose province is Mercia…''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cottle &amp; Sherborne&quot;&gt;Cottle &amp; Sherborne (1951)&lt;/ref&gt; At this period, prior to [[World War I]], regional identities within England were being debated with the prospect of separate [[Regions_of_england#History|Home Rule parliaments]] being established.

The [[British Army]] has made use of regional identities in naming larger formations.  After the Second World War, the infantry regiments of Cheshire, Staffordshire, and Worcestershire were organised in the [[Mercian Brigade]] (1948&amp;ndash;1968). Today &quot;Mercia&quot; appears in the titles of two regiments, the new [[Mercian Regiment]] (which recruits in Cheshire, Derbyshire, Nottinghamshire, Worcestershire and parts of Greater Manchester and the West Midlands) and the [[Royal Mercian and Lancastrian Yeomanry]].

The [[West Mercia Constabulary]] was created in 1967, combining the police forces of Herefordshire, Shropshire and Worcestershire.

Telephone directories across the Midlands reveal a large number of commercial and voluntary organisations using ‘Mercia’ in their names.  In the early 1980s, Mercia Television was an unsuccessful contender for the Midlands franchise, then owned by [[Associated TeleVision|ATV]]. It was won by [[Central Independent Television]].  Mercia (formerly [[Mercia FM]]) is a commercial radio station broadcasting from [[Coventry]] founded in 1980 as Mercia Sound.

There are currently two main organisations campaigning for Mercian self-determination. Sovereign Mercia seeks independence for Mercia as a modern technological state,&lt;ref&gt;[http://sovereignmercia.webs.com/ Sovereign Mercia (website)]&lt;/ref&gt; whereas the Acting Witan of Mercia advocates a return to an agrarian subsistence economy.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independentmercia.org/ Acting Witan of Mercia (website)]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Symbols ==
{|
|-|
[[Image:Mercian regiment.PNG|85px|left|thumb|]]
[[Image:RMLY.PNG|85px|left|thumb|]]
|}

The Kingdom of Mercia predated the emergence of heraldry, so there is no authentic Mercian heraldic device.  However, later generations have ascribed a variety of devices to the rulers of Mercia or to the land itself.

===The eagle===
The silver double-headed eagle surmounted by a golden three-pronged Saxon crown has been used by several units of the [[British Army]] as a heraldic device for Mercia since 1958.  It is derived from the [[attributed arms]] of [[Leofric, Earl of Mercia|Leofric]], Earl of Mercia in the 11th century.&lt;ref&gt;A. L. Kipling and H. L. King, ''Head-dress Badges of the British Army'', Vol. 2, reprinted, Uckfield, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; It is worth noting, however, that Leofric is sometimes attributed a black, single-headed eagle instead.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ngw.nl/int/gbr/c/coventry.htm Arms of the City of Coventry]&lt;/ref&gt;) The examples on the left are the official devices of the [[Mercian Regiment]] and the [[Royal Mercian and Lancastrian Yeomanry]] respectively. The latter, being a merged unit, also sports the Lancastrian red rose and crown.

===The saltire===
[[Image:Arms-st-albans.jpg|130px|right|thumb|Arms of [[St Albans]] City Council]]
[[Image:Saint Alban's cross.svg|130px|right|thumb|[[Saint Alban's Cross|Cross of St Alban]]]]

By the thirteenth century, this latter device had become the [[attributed arms]] of the Kingdom of Mercia.&lt;ref&gt;College of Arms Ms. L.14, dating from the reign of [[Henry III of England|Henry III]]&lt;/ref&gt; The [[coat of arms|arms]] are [[blazon]]ed ''Azure, a saltire Or'', meaning a gold (or yellow) saltire on a blue field. The arms were subsequently used by the [[St Albans Cathedral|Abbey of St Albans]], founded by King Offa of Mercia. With the dissolution of the Abbey and the incorporation of the borough of [[St Albans]] the device was used on the town's corporate seal and was officially recorded as the arms of the town at an [[heraldic visitation]] in 1634.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.civicheraldry.co.uk/herts.html ''Civic Heraldry of England and Wales &amp;ndash; Hertfordshire'', accessed January 15, 2008]&lt;/ref&gt;

As a flag, the Cross of St Alban is flown from [[Tamworth Castle]], the ancient seat of the Mercian kings, to this day. It was also flown outside [[Council House, Birmingham|Birmingham Council House]] during 2009 while the [[Staffordshire Hoard]] was on display in the city before being taken to the [[British Museum]] in London. The cross has been incorporated into a number of [[coat of arms|coats of arms]] of Mercian towns, such as [[Tamworth]], [[Leek, Staffordshire|Leek]] and [[Blaby]].

[[Image:Wyvern sans legs.png|100px|left|thumb|]]

===The wyvern===

A [[wyvern]] is a [[European dragon|dragon]] with two legs, and since its adoption as an emblem by the Midland Railway in the mid-19th century it has been associated with Mercia.

The [[Leicester and Swannington Railway]], which opened in 1832, adopted as a badge the silver (white) wyvern that forms the crest of the Borough of Leicester as recorded at the [[heraldic visitation]] of Leicestershire in 1619: ''a wyvern sans legs argent strewed with wounds gules, wings expanded ermine'' (the term ''sans legs'' does not imply that the wyvern was legless; rather, that its legs are not depicted, being hidden or folded under).&lt;ref&gt;Geoffrey Briggs, ''Civic &amp; Corporate Heraldry'', London 1971&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;C. W. Scot-Giles, ''Civic Heraldry of England and Wales'', 2nd edition, London, 1953&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A. C. Fox-Davies, ''The Book of Public Arms'', London 1915&lt;/ref&gt; This was inherited by the [[Midland Railway]] in 1845, where it became the crest of its unofficial [[coat of arms]].&lt;ref&gt;Cuthbert Hamilton Ellis, ''The Midland Railway'', 1953&lt;/ref&gt; The company asserted that the ''&quot;wyvern was the standard of the Kingdom of Mercia&quot;'', and that it was a ''&quot;a quartering in the town arms of Leicester&quot;''.&lt;ref&gt;Frederick Smeeton Williams, ''The Midland Railway: Its rise and progress: A narrative of modern enterprise'', 1876&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;railmag&quot;&gt;''The Railway Magazine'', Vol.  102, 1897&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Dow&quot;&gt;Dow (1973)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clement Edwin Stretton, ''History of The Midland Railway'', 1901&lt;/ref&gt; However, in 1897 the ''Railway Magazine'' noted that there appeared ''&quot;to be no foundation that the wyvern was associated with the  Kingdom of Mercia&quot;.''&lt;ref name=&quot;railmag&quot;/&gt;

The wyvern in Leicester's crest was derived from that of [[Thomas, 2nd Earl of Lancaster|Thomas of Lancaster, second Lancastrian Earl of Leicester]]. The seal of Thomas, who was executed in 1327, included a wyvern.&lt;ref&gt;John Hewitt, ''Ancient Arms in Modern Europe, Vol II: The Fourteenth Century'', 1860&lt;/ref&gt;

A similar theme was later taken up by [[Bram Stoker]] in his 1911 novel, ''[[The Lair of the White Worm]]'', which was explicitly set in Mercia (see above). The word &quot;worm&quot;, derived from [[Old English]] ''wyrm'', originally referred to a dragon or serpent. &quot;Wyvern&quot; is derived from [[Old Saxon]] ''wivere'', also meaning serpent (and etymologically related to [[Viperidae|viper]]).

The ultimate source for the symbolism of white dragons in England would appear to be [[Geoffrey of Monmouth]]’s fictional ''History of the Kings of Britain'' (c. 1136), where an incident occurs in the life of Merlin in which a red dragon is seen fighting a white dragon which it overcomes. The red dragon was taken to represent the Welsh and their eventual victory over the Anglo-Saxon invaders, symbolised by the white dragon. However, there is no archaeological or artefactual evidence that the early Anglo-Saxons used a white dragon to represent themselves.

The cap badge of the 2nd Mercian Battalion of the Territorial Army in the 1980s was a wyvern.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

==Regional government==
[[Image:Midlands councils.png|thumb|350px|Former Government Office Regions: West &amp; East Midlands.]]
With more restricted boundaries than the Kingdom of Mercia at its greatest extent and the traditional area known as the [[English Midlands|Midlands]], two former [[Regions of England|Government Office Regions]] together cover the latter: [[West Midlands (region)|West Midlands]] and [[East Midlands]]. These are also [[European Parliament constituency|constituencies]] of the [[European Parliament]].

The West Midlands comprises the shire counties of &lt;small&gt;(1)&lt;/small&gt; [[Staffordshire]], &lt;small&gt;(2)&lt;/small&gt; [[Warwickshire]] and &lt;small&gt;(3)&lt;/small&gt; [[Worcestershire]] (with their respective districts), the unitary counties of &lt;small&gt;(4)&lt;/small&gt; [[Herefordshire]] and &lt;small&gt;(5)&lt;/small&gt; [[Shropshire]], the metropolitan boroughs of &lt;small&gt;(6)&lt;/small&gt; [[Birmingham]], &lt;small&gt;(7)&lt;/small&gt; [[Coventry]], &lt;small&gt;(8)&lt;/small&gt; [[Metropolitan Borough of Dudley|Dudley]], &lt;small&gt;(9)&lt;/small&gt; [[Sandwell]], &lt;small&gt;(10)&lt;/small&gt; [[Metropolitan Borough of Solihull|Solihull]], &lt;small&gt;(11)&lt;/small&gt; [[Metropolitan Borough of Walsall|Walsall]] and &lt;small&gt;(12)&lt;/small&gt; [[Wolverhampton]], and the unitary boroughs of &lt;small&gt;(13)&lt;/small&gt; [[Stoke-on-Trent]] and &lt;small&gt;(14)&lt;/small&gt; [[Telford and Wrekin]]. The East Midlands comprises the shire counties of &lt;small&gt;(15)&lt;/small&gt; [[Derbyshire]], &lt;small&gt;(16)&lt;/small&gt; [[Leicestershire]], &lt;small&gt;(17)&lt;/small&gt; [[Lincolnshire]], &lt;small&gt;(18)&lt;/small&gt; [[Northamptonshire]] and &lt;small&gt;(19)&lt;/small&gt; [[Nottinghamshire]] (with their respective districts), the unitary county of &lt;small&gt;(20)&lt;/small&gt; [[Rutland]], and the unitary boroughs of &lt;small&gt;(21)&lt;/small&gt; [[Derby]], &lt;small&gt;(22)&lt;/small&gt; [[Leicester]] and &lt;small&gt;(23)&lt;/small&gt; [[Nottingham]]. The two regions have a combined population of 9,439,516 (2001 census), and an area of {{convert|11,053|sqmi|km2|abbr=on}}.

==See also==
*[[Lichfield]]
*[[List of monarchs of Mercia]]
*[[Mercian (Old English)|Mercian – Anglo-Saxon dialect]]
*[[Mercian Trail]]
*[[Old English language|Old English]]
*[[Repton]]
*[[Staffordshire Hoard]]
*[[Tamworth]]
*[[J. R. R. Tolkien]]
*[[Wessex]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==

* Ian W. Walker. ''Mercia and the Making of England'' (2000) ISBN 0-7509-2131-5 (also published as ''Mercia and the Origins of England'' (2000) ISBN 0-7509-2131-5)
* Sarah Zaluckyj &amp; Marge Feryok. ''Mercia: The Anglo-Saxon Kingdom of Central England'' (2001) ISBN 1-873827-62-8
* Michelle Brown &amp; Carol Farr (eds). ''Mercia: An Anglo-Saxon Kingdom in Europe'' (2005) ISBN 0-8264-7765-8
* Margaret Gelling.  'The Early History of Western Mercia'.  (p.&amp;nbsp;184&amp;ndash;201; In: ''The Origins of the Anglo-Saxon Kingdoms''. S. Bassett. 1989)  (Western Mercia and the upper [[River Trent|Trent]] being the probable cradle of early Mercia).
* Simon Schama. ''A History of Britain: At the Edge of the World? &amp;ndash; 3000 BC&amp;ndash;AD 1603 Vol 1'' BBC Books 2003
* {{Cite book | last = Elmes | first = Simon  | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | title = Talking for Britain: A Journey Through the Nation’s Dialects  | publisher = Penguin | year = 2005  | location =  | url =   | doi =   | isbn = 0 140 51562 3}}
* {{Cite book | last = Baxter | first = Stephen  | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | title = The earls of Mercia: lordship and power in late Anglo-Saxon England  | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 2007  | location =  | url =   | doi =   | isbn = 0 19923098 6}}
* {{Cite book | last = McWhirter | first = Norris  | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | title = The Guinness Book of Answers  | publisher = Guinness Superlatives Ltd  | year = 1976  | location = Enfield  | url =   | doi =   | isbn = 0 900424 35 4}}
* {{Cite book | last = Bateman | first = John  | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | title = The Great Landowners of Great Britain and Ireland  | publisher = Leicester University Press  | year = 1971  | location =  | url =   | doi =   | id = SBN 391 00157 4}}
* {{Cite book | last = Cottle | first = Basil  | authorlink =   | coauthors = Sherborne J.W. | title = The Life of a University  | publisher = University of Bristol | year = 1951 | location =  | url =   | doi =   | id = }}
* {{Cite book | last = Dow | first = George  | authorlink =   | coauthors =   | title = Railway Heraldry  | publisher =  | year = 1973  | location =  | url =   | doi =   | id = }}

==External links==
*[http://www.btinternet.com/~simonmarchini/History/History_Measham.htm Mercian History: History Project]
*[http://www.georgetown.edu/labyrinth/library/oe/texts/hidage.html Recensions of manuscripts of the &quot;Hidage&quot;]
*[http://www.staffordshirehoard.org.uk/ The Staffordshire Hoard]

{{heptarchy}}

{{Coord|52.6|N|1.6|W|type:adm1st_region:GB|display=title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

[[Category:918 disestablishments]]
[[Category:States and territories established in 527]]
[[Category:Petty kingdoms of England]]
[[Category:Anglo-Saxon kingdoms]]
[[Category:Peoples of Anglo-Saxon England]]
[[Category:Regions of England]]
[[Category:Mercia| ]]

{{Link GA|ja}}

[[ang:Mierce]]
[[ar:مرسيا]]
[[be:Мерсія]]
[[be-x-old:Мэрсія]]
[[br:Mercia]]
[[ca:Mèrcia]]
[[cs:Mercie]]
[[cy:Mercia]]
[[da:Mercia]]
[[de:Mercia]]
[[el:Μερκία]]
[[es:Reino de Mercia]]
[[eo:Mercia]]
[[eu:Mercia]]
[[fr:Mercie]]
[[fy:Keninkryk Mercia]]
[[gl:Mercia]]
[[got:𐌼𐌰𐌹𐍂𐌺𐌾𐌰]]
[[ko:머시아 왕국]]
[[hr:Kraljevstvo Mercija]]
[[is:Mersía]]
[[it:Regno di Mercia]]
[[he:ממלכת מרסיה]]
[[la:Mercia]]
[[nl:Mercia]]
[[ja:マーシア]]
[[no:Kongedømmet Mercia]]
[[nn:Mercia]]
[[nds:Mercia]]
[[pl:Mercja]]
[[pt:Reino da Mércia]]
[[ro:Mercia]]
[[ru:Мерсия]]
[[sk:Mercia]]
[[sh:Mercija]]
[[fi:Mercia]]
[[sv:Mercia]]
[[th:ราชอาณาจักรเมอร์เซีย]]
[[uk:Мерсія]]
[[zh:默西亞王國]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
