<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="38809" ns="0" title="GNU Privacy Guard"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox software
| logo                   = [[Image:Gnupg logo.svg|The GNU Privacy Guard logo|200px]]
| developer              = [[GNU Project]]
| latest_release_version = 2.0.18
| latest_release_date    = {{Release date and age|2011|08|04}}
| operating_system       = [[Cross-platform]]
| genre                  = [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP]]
| license                = [[GNU General Public License version 3]]
| website                = [http://www.gnupg.org/ www.gnupg.org]
}}
'''GNU Privacy Guard''' ('''GnuPG''' or '''GPG''') is a [[GNU General Public License|GPL Licensed]] alternative to the [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP]] suite of [[cryptography|cryptographic]] software. GnuPG is compliant with RFC 4880, which is the current [[Internet Engineering Task Force|IETF]] standards track specification of [[OpenPGP]]. Current versions of PGP (and Veridis' Filecrypt) are [[Interoperability|interoperable]] with GnuPG and other OpenPGP-compliant systems.

GnuPG is a part of the [[Free Software Foundation]]'s [[GNU]] software project, and has received major funding from the [[German government]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/Bundesregierung-foerdert-Open-Source-24110.html&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
{{refimprove|section|date=April 2011}}
GnuPG was initially developed by [[Werner Koch]]. Version 1.0.0 was released on September 7, 1999. The [[Federal Ministry of Economics and Technology (Germany)|German Federal Ministry of Economics and Technology]] funded the documentation and the port to [[Microsoft Windows]] in 2000.

Because GnuPG is an OpenPGP standard compliant system, the history of OpenPGP is of importance. It was designed to interoperate with [[Pretty Good Privacy|PGP]], the email encryption program initially designed and developed by [[Phil Zimmermann]].

Version 2.0 was released 13 November 2006. The old stable 1.x branch, whose latest version is 1.4.11, will be continued in parallel with the new GnuPG 2 series because there were significant changes in the architecture of the program which will not fit every purpose.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-announce/2006q4/000239.html GnuPG-2.0 released], Werner Koch, 2006-11-13&lt;/ref&gt;

== Usage ==

Although the basic GnuPG program has a [[command line interface]], there exist various [[front-end]]s that provide it with a [[graphical user interface]]. For example, GnuPG encryption support has been integrated into [[KMail]] and [[Evolution (software)|Evolution]], the graphical [[e-mail client]]s found in [[KDE]] and [[GNOME]], the most popular [[Linux]] desktops. There are also graphical GnuPG front-ends ([[Seahorse (software)|Seahorse]] for GNOME, [[KGPG]] for KDE). For [[Mac OS X]], the Mac GPG project provides a number of [[Aqua (user interface)|Aqua]] front-ends for OS integration of encryption and [[key management]] as well as GnuPG installations via [[Installer (Mac OS X)|Installer]] [[Software package (installation)|packages]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|title=Mac GNU Privacy Guard|url=http://macgpg.sourceforge.net/|publisher=''[[sourceforge.net|sourceforge]]''|accessdate=2008-04-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the [[GPGTools]] Installer&lt;ref&gt;{{citeweb|title=GPGTools Installer|url=http://www.gpgtools.org/|publisher=''[[GPGTools|gpgtools]]''|accessdate=2011-03-22}}&lt;/ref&gt; installs all related OpenPGP applications (GPG Keychain Access), plugins ([[GPGMail]]) and dependencies ([[MacGPG]]) to use GnuPG based encryption. [[Instant messaging]] applications such as [[Psi (instant messaging client)|Psi]] and [[Fire (instant messaging client)|Fire]] can automatically secure messages when GnuPG is installed and configured. Web-based software such as [[Horde (Software)|Horde]] also makes use of it. The cross-platform [[Plug-in (computing)|plugin]] [[Enigmail]] provides GnuPG support for [[Mozilla Thunderbird]] and [[SeaMonkey]]. Similarly, [[Enigform]] provides GnuPG support for [[Mozilla Firefox]].  FireGPG was discontinued June 7, 2010.

In 2005, G10 Code and [[Intevation]] released [[Gpg4win]], a software suite that includes GnuPG for Windows, [[WinPT]], [[Gnu Privacy Assistant]], and GnuPG plug-ins for [[Windows Explorer]] and [[Microsoft Outlook|Outlook]]. These tools are wrapped in a standard Windows installer, making it easier for GnuPG to be installed and used on Windows systems.

== Process ==
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:PGP form.png|thumb|[[Plaintext]] and GnuPG-generated [[cyphertext]]]] --&gt;

GnuPG encrypts messages using [[public-key cryptography|asymmetric keypairs]] individually generated by GnuPG users. The resulting public keys can be exchanged with other users in a variety of ways, such as Internet [[key server (cryptographic)|key server]]s. They must always be exchanged carefully to prevent identity spoofing by corrupting public key ↔ &quot;owner&quot; identity correspondences. It is also possible to add a cryptographic [[digital signature]] to a message, so the message integrity and sender can be verified, if a particular correspondence relied upon has not been corrupted.

GnuPG also supports [[symmetric encryption]] algorithms. By default GnuPG uses the [[CAST5]] symmetrical algorithm.

GnuPG does not use patented or otherwise restricted software or algorithms, like the [[International Data Encryption Algorithm|IDEA]] encryption algorithm used in PGP.  (It is in fact possible to use IDEA in GnuPG by downloading a plugin for it, however this may require getting a license for some uses in some countries in which IDEA is patented.)  Instead, GnuPG uses a variety of other, non-patented algorithms, including:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnupg.org/features.en.html|title=GnuPG Features|accessdate=October 1, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Block cipher]]s (symmetric encryption algorithms): [[CAST5]], [[Camellia_(cipher)|Camellia]], [[Triple DES]], [[Advanced Encryption Standard|AES]], [[Blowfish (cipher)|Blowfish]], and [[Twofish]].
* Asymmetric-key ciphers: [[ElGamal]] and [[RSA (algorithm)|RSA]]
* Cryptographic hashes: [[RIPEMD-160]], [[MD5]], [[SHA-1]], [[SHA-2]], and [[Tiger (cryptography)|Tiger]]
* Digital signatures: [[Digital Signature Algorithm|DSA]] and [[RSA (algorithm)|RSA]]

GnuPG is a hybrid encryption software program in that it uses a combination of conventional [[symmetric-key algorithm|symmetric-key cryptography]] for speed, and [[public-key cryptography]] for ease of secure key exchange, typically by using the recipient's public key to encrypt a [[session key]] which is only used once. This mode of operation is part of the OpenPGP standard and has been part of PGP from its first version.

== Problems ==

The OpenPGP standard specifies several methods of [[digital signature|digitally signing]] messages. In 2003, due to an error in a change to GnuPG intended to make one of those methods more efficient, a security vulnerability was introduced.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.di.ens.fr/~pnguyen Phong Q. Nguyen] [http://www.di.ens.fr/~pnguyen/pub.html#Ng04 &quot;Can We Trust Cryptographic Software? Cryptographic Flaws in GNU Privacy Guard v1.2.3.&quot; EUROCRYPT 2004: 555&amp;ndash;570]&lt;/ref&gt; It affected only one method of digitally signing messages, only for some releases of GnuPG (1.0.2 through 1.2.3), and there were fewer than 1000 such keys listed on the key servers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-announce/2003q4/000160.html GnuPG's ElGamal signing keys compromised] Werner Koch, November 27, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; Most people did not use this method, and were in any case discouraged from doing so, so the damage caused (if any, and none has been publicly reported) would appear to have been minimal. Support for this method has been removed from GnuPG versions released after this discovery (1.2.4 and later). Two further vulnerabilities were discovered in early 2006; the first being that scripted uses of GnuPG for signature verification may result in [[false positives]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-announce/2006q1/000211.html False positive signature verification in GnuPG] Werner Koch, February 15, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; the second that non-MIME messages were vulnerable to the injection of data which while not covered by the digital signature, would be reported as being part of the signed message.&lt;ref&gt;[http://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-announce/2006q1/000218.html GnuPG does not detect injection of unsigned data], Werner Koch, March 9, 2006&lt;/ref&gt; In both cases updated versions of GnuPG were made available at the time of the announcement.

GnuPG is a command-line based system, that is not written as an [[Application programming interface|API]] which can be incorporated into other software. [[GPGME]] is an API wrapper around GnuPG which [[parsing|parses]] the output of GnuPG, and various graphical front-ends based on GPGME have been created. This currently requires an out-of-process call to the GnuPG executable for many GPGME API calls. Because GPGME makes use of a special GnuPG interface designed for machine use, a stable and maintainable API between the components is given. Possible security problems in an application do not propagate to the actual crypto code due to the process barrier.

Other software wraps the command line in a [[Perl]] script (e.g. [[gpg-dialog]]) that is menu based.

== See also ==
{{Portal box|Free software|Cryptography}}
* [[Claws mail]] – email client with GPG plugin
* [[Comparison of e-mail clients]]
* [[E-mail privacy]]
* [[Enigform]] – Firefox extension
* [[Enigmail]] – [[Mozilla Thunderbird]] plug-in
* [[FireGPG]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://getfiregpg.org/ getfiregpg.org]&lt;/ref&gt; – Firefox extension (discontinued)
* [[Gpg4win]] – a Windows package with tools and manuals for email and file encryption
* [[Gpg4usb]] - a simplified package for Windows and Linux for portable devices (like a USB drive)
* [[GPGMail]] – OS X Mail.app plug-in
* [[GPGServices]] – OS X Services Menu plug-in
* [[GPGTools]] – an OS X package with tools for email and file encryption (incl. GPGMail, GPG Keychain Access, MacGPG2, GPG Services, ...)
* [[Key signing party]]
* [[KGPG]] – KDE graphical frontend for GnuPG,
* [[MCabber]] – Jabber client
* [[Mutt (e-mail client)|Mutt]] – email client with PGP/GPG support built-in
* [[Off-the-Record Messaging]] – also known as OTR.
* [[OpenPGP card]] – a smartcard with many GnuPG functions
* [[Psi (instant messaging client)]]
* [[Web of trust]]
* [[WinPT]] – a graphical frontend to GPG for Windows

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.gnupg.org/ Project home page]
* [http://lists.gnupg.org/pipermail/gnupg-announce/2007q4/000268.html A Short History of the GNU Privacy Guard], written by Werner Koch, published on GnuPG's 10th birthday
* [http://www.gpg4win.org/ GPG4WIN - EMail-Security using GnuPG for Windows]
* {{Freshmeat|gnupg|GNU Privacy Guard}}
* [http://enigmail.mozdev.org/home/index.php Enigmail] is a security extension to Mozilla Thunderbird and Seamonkey. It integrates the renowned OpenPGP standard provided by GnuPG
* [http://www.emiic.net/reference/57-encrypting-email Another Thunderbird/GnuPG/Enigmail howto]
* [http://www.acontrario.org/node/352 ''A contrario'': Protect your email with GnuPG] -- A tutorial that covers the installation and configuration of GnuPG with Thunderbird or Microsoft Outlook/Express
{{GNU}}

&lt;!-- Interlang --&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gnu Privacy Guard}}
&lt;!-- Categories --&gt;
[[Category:1999 software]]
[[Category:PGP]]
[[Category:GNU Project software|Privacy Guard]]
[[Category:Cryptographic software]]
[[Category:Privacy software]]
[[Category:Cross-platform software]]
[[Category:Linux security software]]

[[be:GnuPG]]
[[be-x-old:GnuPG]]
[[bs:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[ca:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[cs:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[de:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[es:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[eu:GnuPG]]
[[fr:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[ko:지엔유 프라이버시 가드]]
[[hr:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[it:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[nl:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[ja:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[pl:GPG]]
[[pt:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[ro:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[ru:GnuPG]]
[[sk:GnuPG]]
[[sl:Gnu Privacy Guard]]
[[sr:GPG]]
[[sv:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[th:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[tr:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[uk:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[vi:GNU Privacy Guard]]
[[zh:GnuPG]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
