<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="389841" ns="0" title="Memorial University of Newfoundland"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
| name         = Memorial University of Newfoundland
| latin_name   = Universitas Memorailis Terrae Novae
| image_name   = Memorial University of Newfoundland CoA.svg
| image_size   = 180px
| motto        = ''Provehito In Altum'' ([[Latin]])
| mottoeng     = &quot;Launch forth into the deep&quot;
| established  = 1925
| former_names = {{nowrap|Memorial University College}}
| type         = [[Public]]
| endowment    = [[Canadian dollar|$]]62 million&lt;ref name=FS&gt;{{cite web
| url          = http://www.mun.ca/finance/forms/MUN_FS_March_31_2010.pdf
| format       = PDF| title = Consolidated Financial Statements of Memorial University of Newfoundland (March 31, 2010)
| accessdate   = 2011-02-23 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
| city    = [[St. John's, Newfoundland|St. John's]]
| state   = [[Newfoundland and Labrador|NL]]
| country = [[Canada]] 
| coor    = {{coord|47.57203|-52.73265|display=inline,title|type:edu}} 
|undergrad = 14,941&lt;ref name=MUNfactbook&gt;{{cite web
  | title = University Factbook(Memorial University of Newfoundland)
  | publisher = [[MUN|Memorial University of Newfoundland]]
  | url = http://www.mun.ca/ciap/FACT_BOOK_2007.pdf
  |format=PDF| accessdate = 2008-06-30 }} {{Dead link|date=September 2010|bot=H3llBot}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
| postgrad     = 2,582&lt;ref name=MUNfactbook/&gt;
| faculty      = 1,144 full-time&lt;br/&gt;850 sessional
| chancellor   = [[Rick Hillier]] 
| president    = Dr. Gary Kachanoski
| campus       = Urban&lt;br&gt;Main: {{convert|279|acre|ha}}&lt;br&gt;Grenfell: {{convert|185|acre|ha}}&lt;br&gt;Harlow: {{convert|25|acre|ha}}
| affiliation  = Non-denominational 
| affiliations = [[Association of Commonwealth Universities|ACU]], [[Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada|AUCC]], [[Atlantic University Sport|AUS]], [[Canadian Association of Research Libraries|CARL‎]], [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport|CIS]], [[Canadian Virtual University|CVU]], [[Canadian University Society for Intercollegiate Debate|CUSID]], [[University of the Arctic|UArctic]], [[Association of Theological Schools in the United States and Canada|ATS]], [[Canadian Bureau for International Education|CBIE]], [[Canadian University Press|CUP]].
| colours      = {{scarf|start}}
{{cell2|#8C2633}}{{cell|#D4AF37}}{{cell|#FFFFFF}}{{cell|#D4AF37}}{{cell2|#8C2633}}{{cell|#D4AF37}}{{cell|#FFFFFF}}{{cell|#D4AF37}}{{cell2|#8C2633}}{{scarf|end}}
| nickname     = [[Memorial Sea-Hawks|Sea-Hawks]]
| mascot       = Sammy The Seahawk
| former_names = Memorial University College 
| website      = [http://www.mun.ca www.mun.ca]
| logo         = [[File:Memorial University of Newfoundland Logo.svg|125px|center|University logo]]
| footnotes    = 
}}
'''Memorial University of Newfoundland''', (colloquially known as '''Memorial University''' or '''&quot;MUN&quot;''') is a comprehensive university located primarily in [[St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador|St. John's]], [[Newfoundland and Labrador]], [[Canada]].

With historical strengths in engineering, business, geology, and medicine, it is one of the top comprehensive universities in Canada.&lt;ref name=Ranking&gt;{{cite web
| title     = 2008 Comprehensive University Rankings
| publisher = [[Maclean's]]
| url       = http://www.macleans.ca/education/universities/acomprehensive.pdf
| format    = PDF| accessdate = 2008-05-30 }} An online preview of the year ranking published in the Nov 19, 2007 edition of Maclean's magazine.
&lt;/ref&gt;
With over 17,500 students, it is also the largest university in [[Atlantic Canada]].&lt;ref name=CanadianUniversities&gt;{{cite web
| title      = University Profiles (Memorial University of Newfoundland)
| publisher  = Canada's Higher Education and Careers Guide
| url        = http://www.canadian-universities.net/Universities/Memorial-University-of-Newfoundland.html
| accessdate = 2008-05-30 }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
MUN's four main campuses are served by more than 900 faculty and 2,300 staff members. Memorial University of Newfoundland has been featured in the [[SJTU]] World university rankings, the TOP 500 and many other rankings.

==Campuses==
MUN has four main campuses and two satellite campuses across three regions of Newfoundland and Labrador, and in two countries (Canada and England). The main campus in [[St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador]] is split by Prince Philip Drive where the northern section is bounded by [[Pippy Park]], and the southern section is largely surrounded by residential areas.

===St. John's campus===

The largest campus is located in St. John's. [[Parkway (St. John's)|Prince Philip Drive]] runs east-west through the main campus, with Westerland Road bordering it to the west, Elizabeth Avenue to the south and Allandale Road to the east. The majority of the academic buildings are located south of Prince Philip Drive; the Arts and Administration building, Science building, Chemistry and Physics, Mathematics, Music, Education, Physical Education and the Bruneau Centre for Research and Innovation.

The Queen Elizabeth II Library, also located south of the [[Parkway (St. John's)|Parkway]], contains 1,058,500 monographs, 93,900 maps, 13,600 audio-visual titles and over 9,000 journal titles. The Commons, located on the main floor of the library, has computers available for use by students as well as a Digital Media Centre. The University Centre is home to the food court, bookstore, campus bar (&quot;Breezeway&quot;), and the [[CHMR-FM]] campus radio station.

===Marine Institute===

The [[Marine Institute of Memorial University of Newfoundland|Marine Institute]] is a marine [[institute of technology#Canada|polytechnic]] institution located on Ridge Road in St. John's within Pippy Park, north of the city. It has unique facilities such as a full ships bridge simulator and the worlds largest flume tank. It offers degrees, diplomas, certifications and industry training for the maritime sector.

===Grenfell Campus===

''See [[Grenfell Campus, Memorial University|Main Article]] on Grenfell Campus for more information.''

The [[Grenfell Campus]] is a {{convert|185|acre|ha|sing=on}} site in [[Corner Brook, Newfoundland and Labrador|Corner Brook]]. It has approximately 1400 students, 156 faculty, 235 staff and offers programs in the Arts, Fine Arts, Business, Science, Resource Management and Nursing.

It had been referred to as '''Sir Wilfred Grenfell College''' until September 10, 2010.

===Harlow===
The Harlow Campus, located in Old Harlow, Essex, England consists of the Maltings, which can accommodate 30 students and Cabot House which can accommodate 10 students. A former schoolhouse and a teacher's cottage have been converted into a lecture facility and an apartment and a former shop has been converted into apartments. Memorial's Harlow Campus is not a school unto itself. Rather, professional schools and academic departments at Memorial use the Harlow Campus to deliver special programs. Harlow offers courses in Biology, Business, Drama &amp; Performance, English Cultural Landscape, Fine Arts (both Theatre and Visual Arts), Faith, Love &amp; Lore and History &amp; Political Science.

==Students and campus housing==

[[File:burton's pond.JPG|left|thumb|250px|Burton's Pond apartments at night]]

There are over 17,000 students currently enrolled in full and part time studies at MUN.  This number includes both undergraduate and graduate students. Approximately 85% of students are from Newfoundland and Labrador. The most popular programs include Engineering, Business Administration, Nursing, Education, English, Folklore, French, History, Biology, Biochemistry, and Psychology. The university has an international reputation in a variety of disciplines. In particular, it is well recognized as having one of the top folklore departments in the world.

The department of Housing, Food and Conference Services provides on campus housing at the St. John's campus in two residential complexes; [[Paton College]] and Burton's Pond. The [[Paton College]] dormitories offer traditional dormitory style accommodations for approximately 1000 students in ten residences, called &quot;Houses&quot;. The four &quot;Courts&quot; of Burton's Pond apartments accommodate 500 single students in four bedroom apartments, and provide a more independent lifestyle on campus. Small family apartments are available for students with a family, in Baltimore Court.
&lt;ref name=AUCCProfile&gt;{{cite web
| url        = http://www.aucc.ca/can_uni/our_universities/memorial_e.html
| title      = Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada Profile
| accessdate = 2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

Memorial University of Newfoundland is a non-denominational university in [[St John's, Newfoundland]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;[http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/index.cfm?PgNm=TCE&amp;Params=U1ARTU0002335 Memorial University of Newfoundland&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; Memorial University began as Memorial University College (MUC), which opened in September 1925 at a campus on Parade Street in St. John's.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; 

The first president was J. L. Paton. It offered the first two years of university studies. MUC's initial enrollment was 57 students, rising to a peak of over 400 in the 1940s. In 1933 it merged with the adjacent Normal School and took responsibility for teacher training. During the College's early years it received considerable support from the [[Carnegie Corporation of New York]].

The college was established as a memorial to the Newfoundlanders who had lost their lives on active service during the First World War.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; It was later rededicated to also encompass the province's war dead of the Second World War.&lt;ref name=MUNHistory&gt;{{cite web
| url        = http://www.mun.ca/memorial/history/
| title      = History of Memorial University
| accessdate = 2008-05-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[Alan Beddoe]] designed the coats of arms for the Memorial University of Newfoundland.&lt;ref&gt;http://collectionscanada.gc.ca/ourl/res.php?url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;url_tim=2010-03-07T21%3A52%3A20Z&amp;url_ctx_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Actx&amp;rft_dat=104827&amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fcollectionscanada.gc.ca%3Apam Alan Beddoe collection at Library and Archives Canada&lt;/ref&gt;
The post-Confederation government elevated the status of Memorial University College to full university status in August 1949, renaming the institution to Memorial University of Newfoundland.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; Memorial University was established by the Memorial University Act.&lt;ref&gt;assembly.nl.ca/Legislation/sr/statutes/m07.htm Memorial University Act&lt;/ref&gt;

The enrollment in MUN's first year was 307 students. In 1961, enrollment having increased to 1400, MUN moved from Parade Street to its present location on Elizabeth Avenue (Main Campus).
&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

On8 March 1965, the government of Newfoundland announced free tuition for first year students enrolled at Memorial University in St. John's. &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title='Fitzhenry and Whiteside Book of Canadian Facts and Dates'  |last=Pound |first=Richard W. |publisher=Fitzhenry and Whiteside |year=2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Faculty of Medicine of Memorial University of Newfoundland]] was established in 1967, and the first students were admitted in 1969. It admits approximately 60 students into the M.D. program each year, and also offers M.Sc. and Ph.D. programs.

MUN maintains a campus in [[Harlow]], England which opened to students in 1969. This campus has been a popular location for internships in Education, and now offers credit courses, work terms, and internships in a number of areas. The campus accommodates approximately 50 students.

Memorial established the Institut Frecker in [[St. Pierre and Miquelon|St. Pierre]] in 1973, to offer one-semester French immersion programs. It was housed in a building provided by the archdiocese of St. Pierre until 2000. Now known as the Programme Frecker, it is currently run from the [[FrancoForum]], a language teaching facility owned by the government of St. Pierre. The program is partly supported by the governments of Canada and Newfoundland and Labrador.

In September 1975 a campus was opened in [[Corner Brook, Newfoundland and Labrador|Corner Brook]]; it was first renamed [[Sir Wilfred Grenfell College]] in 1979 and renamed again in 2010 as [[Grenfell Campus, Memorial University of Newfoundland]].  Currently 1300 students attend Grenfell, which offers full degree programs in several disciplines, including Fine Arts, and partial programs, which can be completed at the main campus, in many other subjects.
[[File:MemorialUniversity.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The St. John's campus of MUN]]
[[File:Burton's Pond MUN.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Burton's Pond]]
[[File:QEII MUN.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The Queen Elizabeth II Library]]
[[File:Gushue Hall MUN.jpg|right|thumb|250px|R. Gushue Hall]]
[[File:IIC MUN.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Bruneau Centre for Research]]
[[File:OSC MUN.jpg|right|thumb|250px|The Ocean Sciences Centre]]

In 1977, the Memorial University of Newfoundland Educational Television Centre implemented the [[Telemedicine]] project.    

In 1992, the Institute of Fisheries and Marine Technology in St. John's  became affiliated with MUN as the Fisheries and Marine Institute of Memorial University of Newfoundland.  Today it is named the [[Marine Institute of Memorial University of Newfoundland]]. It offers both degree and non-degree programs.

==Schools and faculties==
Memorial has six faculties (Arts, Business Administration, Education, Engineering, Medicine, and Science) and six Schools (Graduate Studies, Music, Nursing, Pharmacy, Human Kinetics, Recreation, and Social Work). These offer a wide variety of undergraduate and graduate degree programs. 

Memorial’s Faculty of Business Administration is recognized as a leader in Canadian business education, offering innovative programs at the undergraduate and graduate levels, including bachelor of commerce, international bachelor of business administration, bachelor of business administration, master of business administration, master of employment relations and PhD degrees.

Students can choose to specialize in the following engineering disciplines: [[Civil Engineering]], [[Computer Engineering]], [[Electrical Engineering]], [[Mechanical Engineering]], [[Offshore construction|Ocean]] and [[Naval architecture|Naval Architectural]] Engineering (combined degree), and [[Process Engineering]].   
&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.cemf.ca/Engineering/UniversityList.htm Canadian Engineering Memorial Foundation - University List&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Memorial University of Newfoundland Department of Biochemistry has an accredited dietetic program. The university is accredited by a professional organization such as the [[Dietitians of Canada]] and the university's graduates may subsequently become registered dietitians. [[List of universities with accredited dietetic programs]]

Queen's College, an affiliated College of Memorial University, offers diploma and degree studies in theology, pastoral studies, church history and related programs. Queen's College is an associate member of the [[Association of Theological Schools in the United States and Canada]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ats.edu/MemberSchools/Pages/SchoolDetail.aspx?ID=473 ATS Member School Profile]&lt;/ref&gt;

The university operates the [[Bonne Bay Marine Station]] in [[Gros Morne National Park]].

==Motto, shield, and arms==
The university's motto, ''Provehito in Altum'' (Launch forth into the deep), captures the spirit of the adventure of learning and urges students to extend the frontiers of knowledge.  The shield of arms bears a representation of the sea, books, and a cross.  The Arms of Memorial University have as their central element a [[Cross (heraldry)|cross moline]], which is a fitting symbol for an institution dedicated to the memory of soldiers of Newfoundland who died during the Great Wars.

==Memorial University of Newfoundland Botanical Garden==
The [[Memorial University of Newfoundland Botanical Garden]] is a botanical garden operated by the university. It is located at Oxen Pond along Mount Scio Road in the suburbs of St. John's and was founded in 1972. The park has adopted the Twinflower (''[[Linnaea borealis]]'') as its emblem.

==Sports, clubs, and traditions==
MUN's sports teams, the [[Memorial Sea-Hawks]] (formerly The [[Beothuks]]), are part of the Atlantic University Sport (AUS) league of [[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]]. There are varsity teams in men's and women's basketball, cross-country, soccer, swimming, volleyball and wrestling.

Memorial University also has a very active student media including a radio station, [[CHMR-FM]], and a newspaper, ''[[The Muse (student paper)|The Muse]]''.

== Rankings ==
The Globe and Mail's 2009 University Report Card, which is a national survey on student satisfaction gave MUN the following grades in the Medium-sized University category:

* Quality of Teaching: B+ (6th in Canada)
* Quality of Education: A- (6th in Canada)
* Most Satisfied Students: A- (6th in Canada)
* Class Size: A- (4th in Canada)
* Student Faculty Interaction: B (6th in Canada)
* Course Availability: B (4th in Canada)
* Student Services: B+ (2nd in Canada)
* Libraries: A- (3rd in Canada)
* Academic reputation: B (7th in Canada)
On November 11, 2010 Maclean's magazine ranked MUN number 5 of 12 in its comprehensive university rankings for the second year in a row.

In the 2007 Academic Ranking of World Universities published by The Institute of Higher Education of Shanghai Jiao Tong University, MUN placed in the fourth quintile category (305th–401st overall) of the top 500 universities of the world.

==Presidents==
* [[John Lewis Paton]], 1925–1933
* [[Albert Hatcher]], 1933–1952
* [[Raymond Gushue]], 1952–1966
* [[Moses Morgan]] (''pro tempore''), 1966–1967
* [[Stephen Taylor, Baron Taylor|The Rt. Hon. The Lord Taylor of Harlow]], 1967–1973
* [[Moses Morgan]], 1973–1981
* Leslie Harris, 1981–1990
* [[Arthur May]], 1990–1999
* [[Axel Meisen]], 1999–2007
* [[Eddy Campbell]], 2008–2009
* Chris Loomis, 2009–2010
* Gary Kachanoski, 2010- Current

==Chancellors==
* [[Esmond Harmsworth, 2nd Viscount Rothermere|The Rt. Hon. Viscount Rothermere of Hemsted]], 1952–1961
* [[Roy Thomson, 1st Baron Thomson of Fleet|The Rt. Hon. The Lord Thomson of Fleet]], 1961–1968
* G. Alain Frecker, 1971–1979
* [[Paul Desmarais|Paul G. Desmarais]], 1979–1988
* [[John C. Crosbie|His Honour the Hon. John Crosbie]], 1994–2008
* [[Rick Hillier]], 2008-

==Notable faculty and alumni==
{{main|List of Memorial University of Newfoundland people}}

==Scholarships==
The University joined Project Hero, a scholarship program cofounded by General (Ret'd) [[Rick Hillier]] for the families of fallen [[Canadian Forces]] members.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.accc.ca/english/services/cdnforces/hero.htm Project Hero&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{portal|University of the Arctic}}
*[[Higher education in Newfoundland and Labrador]]
*[[Memorial University of Newfoundland Students' Union]]
*[[Canadian Interuniversity Sport]]
*[[Canadian government scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian university scientific research organizations]]
*[[Canadian industrial research and development organizations]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

===Books===
* Dr. Mel Baker, Memorial University archivist  'Celebrate Memorial: A Pictorial History of Memorial University of Newfoundland' (St. John's Newfoundland: Memorial University Press © 1999)
* Malcolm MacLeod. 'A Bridge Built Halfway: A History of Memorial University College, 1925-1950.' Montreal and Kingston: McGill-Queen's University Press, 1990.
* J.A. Meaden, 'Queen’s College, Newfoundland' (St.John’s Newfoundland: Memorial University Press, 1947)

==External links==
{{Commons category|Memorial University of Newfoundland}}
*{{Official website|http://www.mun.ca/}}
*[http://emun.ca/ Unofficial Student site of Memorial University of Newfoundland]
*[http://www.themuse.ca/ ''The Muse''] Memorial University's student newspaper
*[http://www.mun.ca/ciap/fact_book.php Fact Book]
*[http://www.heritage.nf.ca/society/education.html Education: Newfoundland and Labrador Heritage]
*[http://www.aucc.ca/can_uni/search/index_e.html Directory of Canadian Universities’ programs database]
*[http://www.aucc.ca/can_uni/our_universities/memorial_e.html Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada Profile]
*[http://www.globecampus.ca/in-the-news/globecampusreports/#canadian-university-report-2009
{{Memorial University of Newfoundland}}
{{St. John's landmarks}}
{{Universities in Canada}}
{{ShadUni}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Memorial University Of Newfoundland}}
[[Category:Memorial University of Newfoundland| ]]
[[Category:Nursing schools in Canada]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1925]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Newfoundland and Labrador]]
[[Category:Association of Commonwealth Universities]]

[[fr:Memorial University of Newfoundland]]
[[no:Memorial University of Newfoundland]]
[[zh:纽芬兰纪念大学]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
