<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3914792" ns="0" title="Mozilla Corporation software rebranded by the Debian project"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Redirect|Iceweasel|the GNU browser formerly known as IceWeasel|GNU IceCat}}
In 2006, a branding issue developed when Mike Connor, representing the [[Mozilla Corporation]], requested that the [[Debian]] Project comply with Mozilla standards for use of the Thunderbird trademark when redistributing the Thunderbird software.&lt;ref name=&quot;bug&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=354622 | title=Debian bug report on use of Mozilla Firefox trademark without permission}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2004/12/msg00328.html | title=mozilla thunderbird trademark restrictions / still dfsg free ?}}&lt;/ref&gt; At issue were modifications not approved by the Mozilla Foundation, when the name for the software remained the same.

In 2006 the Debian Project subsequently [[rebranding|rebranded]] the [[Mozilla Firefox]] program,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/2006/10/msg00665.html | title=Re: Will IceWeasel be based on a fork or on vanilla FireFox? }}&lt;/ref&gt; and other software released by Mozilla, so that Debian could continue to distribute the software with modifications permitted, without being bound by the use of trademark requirements that the Mozilla Foundation had required.  The new names established by Debian were '''Iceweasel''' for [[Mozilla Firefox]], '''Icedove''' for [[Mozilla Thunderbird]], and '''Iceape''' for [[SeaMonkey]]. These changes were implemented in the subsequent version of [[Debian|Debian (Etch)]].  In July 2007, '''Iceowl''', a rebranded version of [[Mozilla Sunbird]], was added to the unstable branch of Debian.&lt;ref&gt;[http://packages.qa.debian.org/i/iceowl.html Overview of [[iceowl]] source package]&lt;/ref&gt;

== History ==
=== Origins of the issue and of the ''Iceweasel'' name ===
Mozilla Foundation owns the trademark “Firefox”&lt;ref&gt;{{US trademark|78344043}}; see [[History_of_Mozilla_Firefox#Naming]]&lt;/ref&gt;  and claims the right to deny the use of the name and other trademarks to unofficial builds.&lt;ref name=&quot;MozillaTrademarkPolicy&quot;&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://www.mozilla.org/foundation/trademarks/policy.html | title=Mozilla Trademark Policy}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]] are used by the Debian project to determine whether a license is a free license, which in turn is used to determine whether something can be included in Debian. As the logo did not meet these requirements, it could not be used by software which was to be included in Debian. This effect of the Mozilla trademark policy led to a long debate within the [[Debian Project]] in 2004 and 2005. During this debate, the name “Iceweasel” was coined to refer to rebranded versions of Firefox. The first known use of the name in this context is by Nathanael Nerode,&lt;ref name=naming&gt;{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2004/02/msg00279.html | title=Nathanael Nerode 27 Feb 2004 email to debian-legal}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
in reply to [[Eric Dorland]]'s suggestion of “Icerabbit”.&lt;ref name=naming2&gt;{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/2004/02/msg01876.html | title=Eric Dorland 27 Feb 2004 email to debian-devel}}
&lt;/ref&gt;
It was intended as a parody of “Firefox”.&lt;ref name=gzhome&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.gnu.org/software/gnuzilla/ |title=Gnuzilla Homepage |publisher=Gnu.org |date=2010-10-17 |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;
“Iceweasel” was subsequently used as the example name for a rebranded Firefox in the Mozilla Trademark Policy,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://viewvc.svn.mozilla.org/vc/projects/mozilla.org/trunk/foundation/trademarks/policy.html?revision=39674&amp;view=markup| title = Mozilla Trademark Policy (Version 0.6 (draft)) | publisher = [[Mozilla Foundation]] | date = 2004-09-28 | accessdate = 2011-06-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
and became the most commonly used name for a hypothetical rebranded version of Firefox. By January 1, 2005, rebranding as a strategy was being referred to as the “Iceweasel route”.&lt;ref name=naming3&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2005/01/msg00010.html | title=Joel Aelwyn 01 Jan 2005 email to debian-legal}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The term &quot;ice weasel&quot; appeared earlier in a line which [[Matt Groening]] fictionally attributed to [[Friedrich Nietzsche]]: &quot;''Love is a snowmobile racing across the tundra and then suddenly it flips over, pinning you underneath. At night, the ice weasels come.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Groening | first = Matt | authorlink = Matt Groening | title = Love Is Hell | publisher = [[Pantheon Books]] | year = 1986 | id = ISBN 0394744543 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Debian was initially given permission to use the trademarks, and adopted the Firefox name.&lt;ref name=Gervsemail&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-devel/2005/06/msg01182.html | title=Gervase Markham 14 June 2005 email to debian-devel}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, because the artwork in Firefox had a proprietary copyright license which was not compatible with the Debian Free Software Guidelines, the substituted logo had to remain.&lt;ref name=Gervsemail2&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2005/01/msg00757.html | title=Gervase Markham 19 June 2005 email to debian-devel}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Trademark agreement revocation ===
In February 2006, Mike Connor, representing the [[Mozilla Corporation]], wrote to the Debian bug tracker and informed the project that Mozilla did not consider the way in which Debian was using the Firefox name to be acceptable.&lt;ref name=bug /&gt; Connor confirmed that the Mozilla Corporation was revoking the previous agreement which allowed Debian to use the Firefox name. Further messages from Mike Connor clarified Mozilla's new trademark policies: usage of the Firefox name is not allowed unless the rest of the branding is used and all of the browser's changes are approved by Mozilla Corporation.

The immediate problem caused by the new policy was Debian's inability
to use the official Firefox logo due to its proprietary license
failing to comply with the [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]].
Additionally, as Debian releases are frozen on a long-term basis,
software in the frozen stable releases needs to be patched for any
newly-discovered security issue. Under the revised guidelines, in
order to use the Firefox name, approval from the Mozilla Corporation
would have been required for all security patches, but the Debian
project felt it could not put its security in the hands of an external
corporation in that manner.&lt;ref name=iceweaselsecurity&gt;{{cite web | url
= http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=354622#256 |
title=Debian Bug Report #354662 Message #256 (Approval of Security Backports)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The &quot;Iceweasel&quot; name was revived in the Debian community as a possible name to give the rebranded version of Firefox. The Iceweasel found in Debian is not [[GNU IceCat|GNU IceWeasel (now GNU IceCat)]] but a rebranded Firefox created by the Debian project. The Debian maintainer has stated that he will &quot;get in touch with [the GNU IceCat/IceWeasel team] to see what we can do together&quot;.&lt;ref name=2iceweasels&gt;
{{cite web | url=http://web.glandium.org/blog/?p=97 | title=Facts about Debian and Mozilla Firefox }}
&lt;/ref&gt;
Similarly, Debian renamed [[Mozilla Thunderbird]] and [[SeaMonkey]], to Icedove and Iceape, respectively.&lt;!-- Anyone have references for the coinage of Iceape and Icedove? --&gt;

===Rebranding===
According to packages.qa.debian.org, Iceweasel, Icedove and Iceape were first accepted into the [[Debian]] project's ''unstable'' repository on November 20, 2006, on October 14, 2006, and on December 1, 2006, respectively. Icedove migrated to Etch and Thunderbird was removed on November 11, 2006. Iceape migrated to Etch on January 11, 2007, (the old Mozilla suite having previously been removed on October 6, 2006). Iceweasel migrated (and Firefox was removed) on January 18, 2007. Debian's first stable release to include Iceweasel, Icedove, and Iceape was Debian 4.0 (Etch), released April 8, 2007. Soon after the renaming Debian also replaced Mozilla's unbranded logos with new logos designed to fit with the new names, drawn by Ricardo Fernandez Fuentes.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;copyright&quot; file from Iceweasel package in Debian, version 2.0.0.2+dfsg-3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;iceweasel_2006-11-13&quot;&gt;{{cite web |last=Dorland |first=Eric |last2=Hommey |first2=Mike |title=iceweasel (2.0+dfsg-1) unstable |work=Debian Changelog iceweasel |date=2006-11-13 |url=http://packages.debian.org/changelogs/pool/main/i/iceweasel/current/changelog#version2.0_dfsg-1 |accessdate=2011-11-22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent products ===
{{Infobox software
| name = Iceweasel
| logo = [[Image:Iceweasel-icon.svg|center|96px]]
| screenshot = [[Image:Iceweasel307.png|center|250px|Iceweasel on Debian squeeze]]
| caption =
| author =
| developer = [[Debian]] Project
| operating system = [[Linux]], [[GNU]] and [[GNU variants|variants]]
| genre = [[Web browser]]
| license = [[Mozilla Public License|MPL]]/[[GNU General Public License|GNU GPL]]/[[GNU Lesser General Public License|GNU LGPL]] tri-license
| website =
}}

Debian's Iceweasel, Icedove, Iceowl, and Iceape are respectively based on Mozilla's [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]], [[Mozilla Thunderbird|Thunderbird]], [[Mozilla Sunbird|Sunbird]], and [[SeaMonkey]].
The rebranded products still use some Internet-based services from Mozilla, including the Mozilla plugin finder service, and Mozilla add-ons and their update notifications. There has also been no change to how non-[[free software|free]] components, such as Flash, are found or used.

====Icedove====
{{Main| Mozilla Thunderbird}}
''Icedove'' is an [[e-mail client]] distributed by the Debian project. It is based on [[Mozilla Thunderbird]], but is made entirely of [[free software]]. With Icedove, the Debian project aims to provide a version of the Mozilla Thunderbird [[e-mail client]] which has not yet been kept in synchronization with upstream development of Thunderbird as originally planned. It removes the [[proprietary software|proprietary]] artwork and [[plug-in (computing)|plug-in]] repositories used in the official release by the [[Mozilla Corporation]], which are classified as non-free by free software advocates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.gnu.org/software/gnuzilla/ | title=GNUzilla and IceCat }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Iceape====
{{Main| SeaMonkey}}
'''Iceape''' is an [[Internet suite]] distributed by the Debian project. Iceape is based on [[SeaMonkey]], but is made entirely of [[free software]]. The Debian project aims with Iceape to provide a version of the SeaMonkey [[Internet suite]] which is kept in synchronization with upstream development of SeaMonkey while removing the [[proprietary software|proprietary]] artwork and [[plug-in (computing)|plug-in]] repositories used in the official release by the ''SeaMonkey Council'', which are classified as non-free by free software advocates.

:'''Note:''' As of Debian release Lenny, Iceape has been removed due to lack of development support within the Debian community. Libraries iceape-dev and iceape-dev-bin are still available but the application itself is not. However it is included with newer version of Lenny including the current stable, squeeze. The new version of iceape is based on Seamonkey 2.

====Iceowl====
{{Main| Mozilla Sunbird}}
'''Iceowl''' is a [[calendar]] application distributed by the Debian project. It is based on [[Mozilla Sunbird]], but is made entirely of [[free software]].

== Licensing ==
The rebranded programs are available under Mozilla's standard [[Mozilla Public License|MPL]]/[[GNU General Public License|GPL]]/[[GNU Lesser General Public License|LGPL]] tri-license. Unlike Mozilla, the default icons are under the same tri-license.

== User Agent problem ==
{{Further|[[Browser sniffing]]}}

Some web sites do not recognise the browsers' [[User agent]] strings and refuse to work properly.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Microsoft breaks HotMail for Linux users? |publisher=Linux-watch.com |date=2008-11-07 |url=http://www.linux-watch.com/news/NS6023147333.html |accessdate=2011-01-30 |archiveurl=http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20100103115321/http://linux-watch.com/news/NS6023147333.html |archivedate=2010-01-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a workaround, Iceweasel 3.5.5 adds a &quot;like [[Mozilla Firefox|Firefox]] x.x.x&quot; string to the User-Agent.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=399633#102 |title=#399633 - iceweasel: Please mention Firefox in the user-agent string. - Debian Bug report logs |publisher=Bugs.debian.org |date= |accessdate=2010-11-09}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Free software}}

* [[Mozilla Firefox]]
* [[History of Mozilla Firefox]]
* [[Debian Free Software Guidelines]]
* [[GNU IceCat]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://lwn.net/Articles/118268/ Debian and Mozilla - a study in trademarks] - a summary of the debate at [[LWN.net]]
* [http://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=354622 Arguments on the Debian Bug tracking system]

*{{cite news
 |date=October 17, 2006
 | title = Debian Fights Mozilla's Fire, Thunder With 'Ice'
 | publisher =  internetnews.com
 | author = Kerner, Sean Michael
 | url = http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/article.php/3638531
}}

{{Debian}}
{{Mozilla}}
{{FOSS}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mozilla Corporation Software Rebranded By The Debian Project}}
[[Category:Free web browsers]]
[[Category:POSIX web browsers]]
[[Category:Web browsers based on Firefox]]
[[Category:Software forks]]
[[Category:Debian]]

[[ar:IceWeasel]]
[[ca:IceWeasel]]
[[cs:IceWeasel]]
[[de:Namensstreit zwischen Debian und Mozilla]]
[[es:Iceweasel]]
[[fr:Renommage des applications de Mozilla par Debian]]
[[ko:데비안에서 개명된 모질라 소프트웨어들]]
[[it:IceWeasel]]
[[nl:Iceweasel]]
[[ja:Iceweasel]]
[[pl:IceWeasel]]
[[pt:Iceweasel]]
[[ru:Iceweasel]]
[[fi:Iceweasel]]
[[zh:Iceweasel]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
