<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="391531" ns="0" title="The Crab with the Golden Claws"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Graphic novel  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
|englishtitle=The Crab with the Golden Claws
|foreigntitle=Le Crabe aux pinces d'or
|image=Tintin cover - The Crab with the Golden Claws.jpg
|caption=Cover of the English edition
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=1941
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Le Soir]]'' (first part in ''Le Soir Jeunesse'')
|origdate=October 17, 1940 - October 18, 1941
|origisbn=2-203-00108-9
|transtitle=The Crab with the Golden Claws
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]]
|transdate=1958
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' 
|transisbn=1-4052-0620-9
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'', 1939
|nextissue=''[[The Shooting Star]]'', 1942
}}

'''''The Crab with the Golden Claws''''' ({{lang-fr|'''Le Crabe aux pinces d'or'''}}) is the ninth of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of classic comic-strip albums, written and illustrated by Belgian writer and illustrator [[Hergé]], featuring young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] as a hero. It is also the first to feature Tintin's longtime friend, [[Captain Haddock]].

==Synopsis==
Tintin is informed by the [[Thomson and Thompson|Thompsons]] of a case involving the ramblings of a drunken man, later killed, found with a scrap of paper from what appears to be a tin of [[crab]]-meat with the word ''Karaboudjan'' scrawled on it. His subsequent investigation and the kidnapping of a [[Japan]]ese man interested in talking to him leads Tintin to a ship called Karaboudjan, where he is abducted by a syndicate of criminals who have been hiding [[opium]] in the [[crab]] tins. Tintin escapes from his locked room after Snowy chews through his bonds and Tintin knocks out a man sent to bring him food. He leaves him bound and gagged in the room. Tintin encounters [[Captain Haddock]], an [[alcoholism|alcoholic]] who is manipulated by his [[Chief mate|first mate]], [[List of The Adventures of Tintin characters#Allan Thompson|Allan]], and is unaware of his crew's criminal activities. Tintin hides in the locker under the bed and defeats Jumbo, the sailor left in the cabin, as Tintin is thought by Allen to have climbed out of the porthole. The Mate finds Jumbo tied to a chair and gagged. Escaping the ship in a lifeboat in an attempt to reach [[Spain]], they are attacked by a seaplane. They hijack the plane and tie up the pilots, but a storm and Haddock's drunken behaviour causes them to crash-land in the [[Sahara Desert|Sahara]].

After trekking across the desert, Tintin and Haddock reach a [[Morocco|Moroccan]] port, but the Captain is kidnapped by members of his old crew. Tintin tracks them down and saves the Captain, but they both become intoxicated by the fumes from wine barrels breached in a shootout with the villains. Upon sobering up, Tintin discovers the necklace with the Crab with the Golden Claws on the now-subdued owner of the wine cellar, [[List of The Adventures of Tintin characters#Omar_Ben_Salaad|Omar Ben Salaad]], and realizes that he is the leader of the drug cartel. After capturing Allan, the gang is put behind bars.

==History==

===Background===

The Belgian comic book creator Georges Remi – who would become better known under his pen name of Hergé – first came up with the character of Tintin, a young boy reporter, whilst working at the right wing Belgian newspaper ''[[Le XXe Siècle]]'' (''The 20th Century''). Pioneering this new character in the story ''[[Tintin in the Land of the Soviets]]'', this comic, which involved Tintin battling the socialist authorities in the [[Soviet Union]], was serialised in ''Le XXe Siècle'''s supplement for children, ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'' (''The Little Twentieth''), from 10 January 1929 until 11 May 1930.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof92|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. pp. 22&amp;ndash;23.&lt;/ref&gt; Proving a success, Hergé went on to pen a string of new ''Adventures of Tintin'', sending his character to real locations such as the Belgian Congo, the United States, Egypt, India, China and the United Kingdom, and also to fictional countries of his own devising, such as the Latin American republic of [[San Theodoros]] and the East European kingdom of [[Syldavia]].

As he produced these works, his political approach to the world began to change; the earliest books reflected the [[Social conservatism|socially conservative]], [[fascism|fascist]] and [[imperialism|imperialistic]] attitudes of those for whom he worked.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; As he got older, he became more critical of the political far right, with the eighth Tintin adventure, ''[[King Ottokar's Sceptre]]'' (1939), involving Tintin battling the forces of fictional fascist state [[Borduria]], whose leader, named Müsstler, was a combination of Nazi German leader [[Adolf Hitler]] and Italian Fascist leader [[Benito Mussolini]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; He continued this anti-German sentiment in his subsequent work, ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'', in which the main antagonist, Dr Müller, is a German intent on sabotaging the oil supply in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 91-92&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 90-91.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Gestapomen following the white buses.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Himself an anti-fascist, Hergé focused his ''Adventures of Tintin'' on non-political themes to avoid trouble with the Gestapo (pictured here) during the period of Nazi occupation.]]

Then, in November 1939, Nazi Germany invaded Belgium as [[World War II]] broke out across Europe, and although Hergé initially considered fleeing into a self-imposed exile, he ultimately decided to stay in his occupied homeland.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 91-92.&lt;/ref&gt; To ensure their own dominance, the Nazi authorities closed down ''Le XXe Siècle'', leaving Hergé unemployed and his story ''Land of Black Gold'' unfinished.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 91-92&quot;/&gt; In search of employment, he was given a job as an illustrator by [[Raymond de Becker]], an executive of the popular newspaper ''[[Le Soir]]'' (''The Evening''), which was allowed to continue publication under German management.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 92-93.&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 October 1940 he was made editor of the paper's children's supplement, ''Le Soir Jeunesse'', in which he set about producing new Tintin adventures, ''The Crab with the Golden Claws'' (1941) and then ''[[The Shooting Star]]'' (1942).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. pp. 98-99.&lt;/ref&gt; In this new, more repressive political climate, Hergé could no longer explore political themes in his ''Adventures of Tintin'' lest he be arrested by the Nazi secret police, the [[Gestapo]]. As Tintinologist [[Harry Thompson]] noted, Tintin's role as a reporter came to an end, to be replaced by his new role as an explorer, something which was not a politically sensitive topic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thompson 1991. p. 112&quot;&gt;[[#Tho91|Thompson 1991]]. p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt; 

===Publication===
''The Crab with the Golden Claws'' was first published in serial comic strip form in 1941.

The story was written after Hergé had been forced to abandon his previous story, ''[[Land of Black Gold]]'', also set in the desert, when [[Nazi Germany]] took over [[Belgium]]. After the invasion, publication of ''[[Le Petit Vingtième]]'', the children's newspaper supplement that had published his previous Tintin adventures, was stopped and Hergé had to look for another means of publication. In addition, ''Land of Black Gold'' featured controversial political matter, depicting the conflicts between [[Jew]]s, [[Arab]]s and the [[United Kingdom|British]] troops in the [[British Mandate of Palestine]]. Hergé was asked by the newspaper ''[[Le Soir]]'' to create a weekly supplement, similar to that of ''Le Petit Vingtième'', called ''Le Soir Jeunesse'', and he began work on a new story about the less controversial subject of drug smuggling. 

''The Crab With the Golden Claws'' appeared for the first time on October 17, 1940, and every week Hergé published two full pages. But the supplement disappeared again after September 3, 1941, due to paper shortage during [[World War II]], when only 98 pages had appeared. The interruption continued until September 23 1941, when Hergé and ''Tintin'' got a daily strip in ''Le Soir''. It continued for 24 days until the story was finished on October 18. This meant a major change in the method of working of Hergé, with a daily instead of a weekly publication, and a consequent rethinking of the layout of the comic and the rhythm of the storytelling. This version was republished as an album in 1941.

The strip was completely redrawn in colour for publication as an album in 1943. 

In the 1960s, the book was published in America with a number of changes. In the original, the sailor Tintin leaves bound and gagged in Captain Haddock's cabin, and the man who beats Haddock in the cellar, are black Africans. These were changed in the 1960s to a white sailor and an Arab due to objections by American publishers of having blacks and whites mixing together. &lt;ref&gt;''Tintin: The Complete Companion'' by [[Michael Farr]], John Murray publishers, 2001&lt;/ref&gt; However, Haddock still refers to the man who beat him as a &quot;Negro&quot; in the English version. Also at the request of the Americans, scenes of Haddock drinking directly from the bottles of whisky on the lifeboat and the plane were taken out.&lt;ref&gt;''Tintin Crosses The Atlantic: The Golden Press Affair'' by Chris Owens at [http://www.tintinologist.org/articles/goldenpress.html www.tintinologist.org]&lt;/ref&gt;

In an interview, Hergé sarcastically stated that these moves were &quot;justified&quot; because &quot;Everyone knows that Americans never drink whisky(!)&quot; and &quot;that there are no blacks in America(!)&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.tintinologist.org/forums/index.php?action=vthread&amp;forum=10&amp;topic=2651 Translation of an interview with Hergé previously available on youtube.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Adaptations==
===Cinematic===
====Stop motion animated film, 1947====
:{{main|The Crab with the Golden Claws (film)}}
 
''The Crab with the Golden Claws'' was adapted into a [[stop motion]]-[[animation|animated]] [[feature film]] of the same name in [[1947 in film|1947]], produced by [[Wilfried Bouchery]] for [[Films Claude Misonne]].  It was the first ever film adaptation of Tintin and reproduces the story of the original comic almost exactly.  It was first shown at the [[ABC Cinema]] on January 11, 1947 for a group of invited guests.  It was screened publicly only once, on December 21 of that year, before Bouchery declared bankruptcy and fled to [[Argentina]].  All of the equipment was seized and a copy of the film is currently stored at [[Belgium]]'s [[Cinémathèque Royale]].{{Fact|date=December 2007}}.

====Motion capture film, 2011====
A [[motion capture]] [[film]] titled ''[[The Adventures of Tintin: Secret of the Unicorn]]'' directed by [[Steven Spielberg]] and produced by [[Peter Jackson]] is slated for a US release on December 21, 2011.  The film was released in Europe at the end of October 2011.

A video-game tie-in to the movie has been announced at E3, June 6 with an unknown game release date.{{Citation needed|date=October 2011}}

===Television===
====Belvision animation, 1957====
In 1957, the animation company [[Belvision]] produced a string of colour adaptations based upon Hergé's original comics, adapting eight of the ''Adventures'' into a series of daily five-minute episodes. ''The Crab with the Golden Claws'' was the fifth such story to be adapted, being directed by Ray Goossens and written by [[Michel Greg]], himself a well known comic book writer and illustrator who in later years would become editor-in-chief of the ''Journal De Tintin''.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. pp. 87-88.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ellipse/Nelvana animation, 1991====
In 1991, a second animated series based upon ''The Adventures of Tintin'' was produced, this time as a collaboration between the French studio [[Ellipse]] and the Canadian animation company [[Nelvana]]. Adapting 21 of the stories into a series of episodes, each 42 minutes long, ''The Crab with the Golden Claws'' was the seventh story to be produced into the series, with the story spanning two episodes. Directed by Stéphane Bernasconi, the series has been praised for being &quot;generally faithful&quot;, with compositions having been actually directly taken from the panels in the original comic book.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lof02|Lofficier and Lofficier 2002]]. p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==

In [[The Simpsons]] episode ''[[In the Name of the Grandfather]]'' [[Lisa Simpson]] mentions [[Ireland]] is on the forefront of [[Europe]]'s ''&quot;tech-boom&quot;''. [[Bart Simpson]] mockingly adds: ''&quot;In your face, [[Belgium]]!&quot;'', whereupon Marge threatens Bart with the words: ''&quot;Bart! If you hate Belgium so much, maybe I should take your [[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]]s away!&quot;'' This scares Bart, who clutches a copy of the album ''&quot;The Crab with the Golden Claws&quot;'', promising he'll be good.&lt;ref&gt;[http://tintinology.poosk.com/2009/03/28/tintin-on-the-simpsons/]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/09crab.html The Crab with the Golden Claws] at Tintinologist.org

{{Tintin and Hergé}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Crab with the Golden Claws, The}}
[[Category:1941 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:1930s in fiction]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Le Soir]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]

[[af:Die krap met die goue knypers]]
[[bn:কাঁকড়া রহস্য]]
[[ca:El cranc de les pinces d'or]]
[[cs:Krab se zlatými klepety]]
[[de:Die Krabbe mit den goldenen Scheren]]
[[es:El cangrejo de las pinzas de oro]]
[[eo:La Krabo kun oraj pinĉiloj]]
[[fa:خرچنگ پنجه‌طلایی]]
[[fr:Le Crabe aux pinces d'or]]
[[gl:O caranguexo das tenaces de ouro]]
[[id:Kepiting Bercapit Emas]]
[[is:Krabbinn með gylltu klærnar]]
[[it:Il granchio d'oro]]
[[he:הסרטן בעל צבתות הזהב]]
[[nl:De krab met de gulden scharen]]
[[no:Krabben med de gyldne klør]]
[[pl:Krab o złotych szczypcach]]
[[pt:Le crabe aux pinces d'or]]
[[fi:Kultasaksinen rapu]]
[[sv:Krabban med guldklorna]]
[[tr:Altın Kıskaçlı Yengeç]]
[[zh:金鉗螃蟹販毒集團]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
