<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="391524" ns="0" title="Flight 714"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=September 2011}}
{{plot|date=June 2011}}
{{Graphicnovelbox|  &lt;!--Wikipedia:WikiProject Comics--&gt; 
englishtitle=Flight 714
|foreigntitle=Vol 714 pour Sydney
|image=Tintin cover - Flight 714.JPG
|caption=Cover of the English language edition published in the USA
|publisher=[[Casterman]]
|date=1968
|series=''[[The Adventures of Tintin|The Adventures of Tintin (Les aventures de Tintin)]]''
|origlanguage=French
|origpublication=''[[Tintin (magazine)|Tintin]]''
|origdate=|&lt;!-- October 31, 1956 - January 1, 1958 --&gt;
|origisbn=|&lt;!-- 2-203-00118-6 --&gt;
|transtitle=Flight 714
|transpublisher=[[Methuen Publishing|Methuen]] {{flagicon|UK}}&lt;br&gt;[[Little, Brown and Company|Little, Brown]]/Hachette {{flagicon|USA}}
|transdate=1968
|transseriestitle=''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'' 
|transisbn=|&lt;!-- 0-316-35848-7 --&gt;
|translator=Leslie Lonsdale-Cooper and Michael Turner
|writers=[[Hergé]]
|artists=[[Hergé]]
|colorists=
|previssue=''[[The Castafiore Emerald]]'', 1963
|nextissue=''[[Tintin and the Picaros]]'', 1976
}}

'''''Flight 714''''', first published in 1968, is the 22nd and penultimate complete volume of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]'', a series of classic comic-strip albums by the [[Belgium|Belgian]] writer and illustrator [[Hergé]], featuring young reporter [[Tintin (character)|Tintin]] as a hero. Its original [[French language|French]] title is '''''Vol 714 pour Sydney''''' (&quot;Flight 714 to Sydney&quot;). The title refers to a flight that the heroes fail to catch, as they become involved in a plot to kidnap an eccentric  millionaire involving a [[private jet]] and an [[Indonesia]]n island.

This album is unusual in the Tintin series for its science fiction and paranormal influences. The central mystery is essentially left unresolved.

==Storyline==

Tintin, [[Captain Haddock]] and [[Professor Calculus]] are on their way to [[Sydney]] for an international conference on space exploration. While their flight makes a refueling stop in [[Jakarta]]'s [[Kemayoran Airport]], they unexpectedly meet their old friend [[Piotr Skut]] (see ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]'' for backstory), who is now the chief pilot for eccentric millionaire [[Laszlo Carreidas]]. A short time earlier, the Captain had erroneously taken the somewhat dishevelled Carreidas for a tramp and surreptitiously slipped him a five-dollar bill, which later is taken by the oblivious Professor Calculus, making the millionaire laugh for the first time in years. When introduced to Carreidas, the Captain inadvertently shakes the hand of the millionaire's secretary, the tall, aloof Spalding.

Unable to politely refuse Carreidas's offer of a lift, Tintin and his friends join the millionaire on his prototype private jet. Unbeknownst to Carreidas and the others, Spalding and two of the pilots, Boehm and Colombani, have been recruited to [[Aircraft hijacking|hijack]] the plane and bring it to a deserted volcanic island in the [[Lesser Sunda Islands]]. Skut is not involved in this plot; therefore he becomes a prisoner too. After a rough landing, our friends are escorted out of the plane, and a terrified [[Snowy (character)|Snowy]] breaks out of Tintin's arms and runs off. Armed guards shoot at him, and a horrified Tintin believes that he has died. 

A moment or two later, to Tintin's further shock, it is shown that the mastermind of the plot is none other than the evil [[Rastapopoulos]], who on grounds that &quot;it's a bore to stop being a millionaire&quot; is intent on taking Carreidas' fortune. Captain Haddock's corrupt ex-shipmate, Allan, is present as well, working (as in earlier books) as Rastapopoulos's henchman.

The prisoners are thereafter bound and held in [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] [[World War II]]-era [[bunkers]]. Meanwhile, Rastapopoulos takes the defiant Carreidas to another World War II-era bunker and has him strapped to a chair, to be interrogated by one [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#Doctor Krollspell|Dr. Krollspell]]. This corrupt scientist injects the millionaire with a [[truth serum]], so as to enable Rastapopulos to learn Carreidas's Swiss bank account number. Unfortunately for Rastapopoulos, Carreidas becomes relentlessly eager to tell the truth about everything except the Swiss bank account, launching into long disquisitions about his life of greed, perfidy and corruption. Furious, Rastapopulos lunges at Krollspell, who is still holding the truth-drug syringe, and is accidentally injected with the serum, becoming [[toxicity|intoxicated]]. He too recounts hideous deeds in a boasting manner, and he and Carreidas begin to quarrel over which is the more evil, during which it becomes evident that nearly all of the men recruited by Rastapopoulos, including Spalding, the aircraft pilots, and (the increasingly unnerved) Krollspell, are already marked to be killed by Rastapopoulos himself.

With the help of Snowy, who is not dead after all, Tintin and his friends manage to escape the bunker in which they were imprisoned and find the bunker where Carreidas is held prisoner. Tintin and Captain Haddock tie up and gag Krollspell, Rastapopulos, and even the irascible Carreidas, and escort them to lower ground, intending to use Rastapopulos as a hostage. However, the serum wears off and Rastapopulos escapes, while Allan also detects the escaping prisoners. However, Krollspell, in fear of Rastapopoulos, throws in his lot with Tintin and Haddock; he is subsequently released and continues to accompany Tintin and Haddock, watching the still irritable Carreidas. 

Rastapopoulos, freed from his bonds, sends Allan and his [[List of The Adventures of Tintin characters#The Sondonesians|Sondonesian henchmen]] to either kill or capture the fugitives. Led by a [[Telepathy|telepathic]] voice Tintin is hearing, the protagonists discover a hidden entrance to a statue-filled cave. They enter the cave, and through a large hallway discover a temple hidden in the inside of the island's volcano. They enter the volcano's core by triggering a hidden mechanism. Rastapopulos and his cohorts are not far behind, but they fail to find out how to open the secret passage after realising the group went through there. Instead, they use explosives to make their own entrance. 

Penetrating deeper into the volcano, Tintin and his friends meet a strange man, [[Minor characters in The Adventures of Tintin#Mik Kanrokitoff|Mik Kanrokitoff]], a writer for magazine ''Space Week'', who reveals to them that his is the guiding voice that they have followed, having received it into their minds via a telepathic transmitter. This device was given to Kanrokitoff by a technologically advanced, extraterrestrial race of humanoids, who were formerly worshipped on the island as [[god]]s and who use it as a landing-point to contact Earth's people. 

An earthquake and the explosion set off by Rastapopoulos and his men triggers a volcanic eruption. Carreidas's unreasonable behaviour presents a major hindrance for Tintin and his party's attempt to get to safety, but finally they all arrive inside the volcano's crater bowl. Meanwhile, Rastapopoulos and his henchmen flee the eruption by running down the outside of the volcano and go out to sea in a rubber dinghy from Carreidas' plane.

Once Tintin and his friends find their way out of the volcano, Kanrokitoff puts them all under telepathic [[hypnosis]]. He uses his transmitter to summon a [[flying saucer]] piloted by the extraterrestrials, whereupon the hypnotised group climb up a retractable ladder and board the saucer, narrowly escaping the volcano's dramatic eruption.  Kanrokitoff spots the rubber dinghy and exchanges Tintin and his companions for Allan, Spalding, Rastapopulos, and the treacherous pilots, who are whisked away in the saucer to an unknown fate. The group — including Krollspell, who is later deposited by the saucer at his institute in [[Cairo]] — awakes from hypnosis and cannot remember what happened to them. The party is eventually rescued, but no one has any recollection of the adventure. [[Professor Calculus]] has a souvenir, though — a crafted rod of alloyed [[cobalt]], [[iron]], and [[nickel]], which he had found in the caves and forgotten in his pocket. The cobalt is of a state that does not occur on Earth, and is the only evidence of a close encounter with its makers; only [[Snowy (character)|Snowy]], who cannot speak, remembers the hijacking and alien abduction.

The story ends with Tintin, Carreidas and companions resuming their journey to Australia on a public airline.

==Trivia==
* The [[Lost (TV series)|TV series ''Lost'']] plot has similarities to the story of this comic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www-origin.contenidosabcdesevilla.es/reportajes-sevilla/todo-sobre-perdidos/105-stories-behind-lost-flight-714-to-sidney-tintin.html|title=The stories behind Lost: Tintin and Flight 714 to Sidney|last=Padilla|first=Javier|language=Spanish|accessdate=18 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*The story is cited in chapter 4 of the novel ''[[The Reluctant Fundamentalist]]'' by [[Mohsin Hamid]].&lt;ref&gt;Mohsin Hamid, &quot;The Reluctant Fundamentalist&quot;. Orlando: Harcourt, 2007 at p.52&lt;/ref&gt;

*Writer Hugo Frey argues that Rastapopoulos' appearance was an example of post-war anti-Semitism on Hergé's part,&lt;ref&gt;Hugo Frey, &quot;Trapped in the Past: Anti-Semitism in Hergé's Flight 714&quot; in Mark McKinney, ed., History and Politics in French-Language Comics and Graphic Novels at p.31&lt;/ref&gt; though other writers argue against this, pointing out that Rastapoppulos is not Jewish and surrounds himself with explicitly German-looking characters: Kurt, the submarine commander of ''[[The Red Sea Sharks]]''; Doctor Krollspell, whom Hergé himself referred to as a former concentration camp official; and Hans Boehm, the sinister-looking navigator and co-pilot, both from ''Flight 714''.&lt;ref&gt;''The Metamorphoses of Tintin: or Tintin for Adults'' by Jean-Marie Apostolidès, Jocelyn Hoy, published in 2009 by Stanford University Press&lt;/ref&gt;

*The statues on the island have eyes similar to the Japanese [[Dogū]] figurines.

*A use of the real [[Indonesian language]] occurs here: while on duty, two of Tintin's captors talk about a particular Indonesian dish that originated in [[Java]], ''sambel bajak'' (ground chilli sauce with shrimp paste).

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==External links==
{{Portalbox|Belgium|Comics}}
*[http://www.tintinologist.org/guides/books/22f714.html Flight 714] at Tintinologist.org
----
{{Tintin and Hergé}}

[[Category:1968 books]]
[[Category:Tintin books]]
[[Category:Ancient astronauts in fiction]]
[[Category:Indonesia in fiction]]
[[Category:Works originally published in Tintin (magazine)]]
[[Category:Literature first published in serial form]]
[[Category:Aviation comics]]

[[bn:ফ্লাইট ৭১৪]]
[[ca:Vol 714 a Sidney]]
[[de:Flug 714 nach Sydney]]
[[es:Vuelo 714 para Sídney]]
[[fa:پرواز شماره ۷۱۴]]
[[fr:Vol 714 pour Sydney]]
[[gl:Voo 714 para Sidney]]
[[id:Penerbangan 714 ke Sydney]]
[[is:Flugrás 714 til Sydney]]
[[nl:Vlucht 714]]
[[pt:Vol 714 pour Sydney]]
[[fi:Lento 714]]
[[sv:Plan 714 till Sydney]]
[[tr:Sidney'e 714 Sefer Sayılı Uçuş]]
[[zh:714航班]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
