<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="391613" ns="0" title="Indiana University – Purdue University Fort Wayne"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{redirect-acronym|IPFW|'''ipfw''', or [[ipfirewall]]}}
{{Infobox university
|image_name   = IPFW Logo.png
|name         = Indiana University – Purdue University Fort Wayne&lt;br /&gt;(IPFW)
|established  = 1964 via the merger of [[IPFW#History|previously established]] institutions
|type         = [[public university|public]] [[coeducational]]
|endowment    = $42,400,000{{ref_label|endowment|1|1}}
|city         = [[Fort Wayne, Indiana|Fort Wayne]]
|state        = [[Indiana]]
|country      = [[United States]]
|campus       = suburban: {{convert|682|acre|km2}}{{ref_label|real_estate|2|2}} (2.60 km²)
|faculty      = 380{{ref_label|full-time_facultyIU|3|3}}{{ref_label|full-time_facultyPurdue|4|4}}
|chancellor   = [[Michael A. Wartell]]
|students     = 14,192
|colors       = blue and white
|mascot       = Don the [[Mastodon]]
|nickname     = [[IPFW Mastodons|Mastodons]]
|affiliations = [[Purdue University System]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Indiana University|Indiana University System]]
|free_label   = Athletics
|free         = 16 Division I [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] teams
|website      = [http://www.ipfw.edu www.ipfw.edu]
}}

'''Indiana University – Purdue University Fort Wayne''' is the largest university in northern [[Indiana]], [[United States]], offering more than 200 [[Indiana University]] (IU) and [[Purdue University]] degrees and certificates. Since 1968, IPFW has conferred nearly 8,800 master’s degrees, 27,000 bachelor’s degrees, more than 20,000 associate degrees, and nearly 2,000 certificates. There are more than 46,000 alumni.

During the 2010–11 academic year, more than 14,000 students of diverse ages, races, and nationalities pursued their education on the {{convert|682|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus. More than 9,000 students attended full time. Students have arrived from 43 states and 68 countries. And more than 13 percent of the student body reflects African American, American Indian/Alaskan Native, Asian/Pacific Islander, or Hispanic heritage. The campus has nearly 400 full-time faculty members, with approximately 70 professors, 115 associate processors, and approximately 130 assistant professors. It also has more than 60 instructors and lecturers and about 400 associate faculty. More than 80 percent of the full-time faculty earned the highest degree in their respective field.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;&gt;[http://www.ipfw.edu/ir IPFW Office of Institutional Research]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Governance==

IPFW is governed in various ways via the Purdue University Board of Trustees, the Indiana University Board of Trustees, and the IPFW Faculty Senate. Purdue serves as the fiscal agent for IPFW’s budget and substantially represents IPFW during budgetary negotiations with the State of Indiana. The Indiana-Purdue Foundation owns most of the land that constitutes IPFW and has entered into a 99-year lease with the county for additional land for $1. The IPFW Faculty Senate represents the faculty in the university’s shared governance model. The desire was so strong for an expansion of IPFW during the 1980s that the Faculty Senate and Indiana-Purdue Foundation explored the full independence from both Purdue and IU, not entirely unlike the [[University of Southern Indiana]]’s independence from [[Indiana State University]] in 1985. Since then, relations with Purdue have improved, as has the level of funding from the State of [[Indiana]]. Any moves toward independence now are largely a matter for history, as the current path of cooperative autonomy is pursued.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;/&gt;

==Academics==

Either Purdue or IU awards IPFW’s degrees on a program-by-program basis. IPFW's colleges, schools, and divisions are not each identified specifically as IU units or as Purdue units. Through an agreement between the IU and Purdue trustees, most of IPFW’s university services are administratively operated through Purdue’s processes. This is in contrast to IPFW's sibling university, [[Indiana University – Purdue University Indianapolis]], where IUPUI is a core campus of the [[Indiana University]] system, where IUPUI's university services are administratively operated through the Indiana University system, and where IUPUI's schools and academic divisions are each strongly identified by name as IU or Purdue aligned. Some students fulfill their freshman, sophomore, or even junior courses at IPFW before transferring to the main campuses in Bloomington or West Lafayette to complete their degrees in majors not offered at the regional campus. For instance, aeronautical and astronautical engineering is not an offering at IPFW, but many mechanical engineering courses apply through the sophomore year.

== Colleges, schools, and divisions ==

IPFW is academically organized into four colleges, two schools, and three divisions [3]:{{ref_label|academic_units|7|7}}
*'''College of Arts and Sciences'''
** contains the Departments of Anthropology • Biology • Chemistry • Communication • Communication Sciences and Disorders • English and Linguistics • Geosciences • History • Mathematical Sciences • International Language and Culture Studies • Philosophy • Physics • Political Science • Psychology • Sociology
*'''Richard T. Doermer School of Business'''
** contains the Departments of Accounting and Finance • Economics • Management and Marketing
*'''College of Education and Public Policy'''
** contains the Departments of Educational Studies • Professional Studies . Public and Environmental Affairs
*'''College of Engineering, Technology, and Computer Science'''
** contains the Departments of Computer and Electrical Engineering Technology &amp; Information Systems and Technology • Computer Science • Engineering • Manufacturing &amp; Construction Engineering Technology &amp; Interior Design • Organizational Leadership and Supervision
*'''College of Health and Human Services'''
** contains the Departments of Consumer and Family Sciences • Dental Education • Human Services • Nursing
*'''College of Visual and Performing Arts'''
** contains the Departments of Fine Arts • Music • Theatre • Visual Communication and Design
*'''Division of Continuing Studies'''
*'''Division of Labor Studies'''


IPFW also hosts the Indiana University School of Medicine–Fort Wayne and the Fort Wayne Center for Medical Education; both are units of the [[Indiana University School of Medicine]].

==Accreditations==

IPFW as a whole has been accredited by The Higher Learning Commission of the North Central Association of Colleges and Schools continuously since 1969. The [[Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology]] has continuously accredited IPFW’s following bachelor’s degrees since the date listed: computer engineering, 2004; computer science, 2002; construction technology, 1981; electrical engineering, 1991; electrical engineering technology, 1976; mechanical engineering, 1991; industrial engineering technology, 1981; and mechanical engineering technology, 1975. [[ABET]] has continuously accredited IPFW’s following associate degrees since the date listed: architectural technology, 1981; civil engineering technology, 1981; electrical engineering technology, 1976; industrial engineering technology, 1981; and mechanical engineering technology, 1972. The Association to Advance Collegiate Schools of Business International accredits the bachelor’s and master’s academic programs within IPFW’s Richard T. Doermer School of Business. The [[American Chemical Society]] has approved the Bachelor of Science in Chemistry (B.S.C.) degree conferred through IPFW’s Department of Chemistry. The [[American Dental Association]] has accredited IPFW’s dental assisting, dental hygiene, and dental laboratory technology programs. The American Music Therapy Association has approved the music therapy degree conferred through IPFW’s Department of Music. The [[National Association of Schools of Music]] has accredited IPFW’s Department of Music. The National Association of Schools of Public Administration and Affairs has accredited IPFW’s master’s degree in public affairs. The [[National Council for Accreditation of Teacher Education]] has continuously accredited IPFW’s (and the IU Fort Wayne Extension Center’s) bachelor’s degrees in education since 1954. Also, [[NCATE]] has accredited IPFW’s master’s degrees in education.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;/&gt;

== History ==
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; cellpadding=&quot;2&quot; cellspacing=&quot;2&quot; style=&quot;font-size: 90%;&quot; 
|+ style=&quot;font-size: 1.25em;&quot; | '''History at a glance'''
|-
!colspan=4 align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;background:#eFeFeF;&quot;| IPFW began as co-located extension campuses 
via the move to the joint campus in 1964, encompassing the:
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|•
|width=&quot;125pt&quot;| Indiana University Fort Wayne Extension 
| '''Established''' 
| 1917
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot;|•
|width=&quot;125pt&quot;| Purdue University Fort Wayne Extension 
| '''Established''' 
| 1947
|-
!colspan=4 align=&quot;left&quot; style=&quot;background:#eFeFeF;&quot;| and expanded through the 1976 merger with:
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; rowspan=2|•
|width=&quot;125pt&quot;| Fort Wayne Art Institute  
| '''Renamed''' 
| 1966
|-
|valign=&quot;top&quot; width=&quot;125pt&quot;| Fort Wayne Art School
| '''Established''' 
| 1897
|-
|
| '''Type''' 
| [[private university|private]]
|}
In 1917, Indiana University started offering courses in downtown Fort Wayne to 142 students in 12 courses. At a separate downtown location, Purdue University permanently established the Purdue University Center in 1941 to provide a site in Fort Wayne for students to begin their undergraduate studies prior to transferring to the West Lafayette main campus to complete their degree [5].

Under the direction of Purdue University President [[Frederick Hovde]], Indiana University President [[Herman Wells]], IU trustee John Hastings, and Purdue trustee Alfred Kettler Sr., the Indiana University and Purdue University extension centers began merging in 1958 via the formation of the Indiana-Purdue Foundation. To serve the extension centers’ now combined mission in Fort Wayne, the Indiana-Purdue Foundation acquired a 99-year lease on existing farmland owned by Allen County—the Indiana county containing Fort Wayne—and land used by the Fort Wayne State School, to form a total of {{convert|114|acre|km2}} at the then-suburban northeast edge of Fort Wayne on the eastern bank of the [[St. Joseph River (Maumee River)|St. Joseph River]]. Indiana University–Purdue University Fort Wayne opened on September 17, 1964, following nearly two years of construction that began on October 18, 1962. The first all-inclusive building on campus was known as the Education Building, but it has since been renamed Kettler Hall in honor of the combined university’s chief advocate. Kettler’s vision and passion during the 1950s made IPFW possible. IPFW awarded its first four-year degree in 1968 after awarding two-year degrees through the IU and [[Purdue]] Fort Wayne extension centers prior to the formation of the joint IPFW campus [5].

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image: IPFWgroundbreaking.jpg|right|250px|thumb|The groundbreaking for IPFW—which represented a first-of-its-kind merging in the country between two independent universities—took place in 1963.|{{deletable image-caption|}}|{{deletable image-caption|1=Saturday, 3 October 2009}}|{{deletable image-caption|1=Saturday, 3 October 2009}}]] --&gt;
In the spirit of Indiana University’s 1967 acquisition of the [[Herron School of Art]] in Indianapolis, which helped form IUPUI two years later, the [[Indiana General Assembly]] approved a similar merger of the Fort Wayne Art Institute with IPFW in 1976. The Fort Wayne Art Institute was founded in 1897 as the Fort Wayne Art School. Until 1991 the Fort Wayne Art Institute and resulting academic unit within IPFW maintained a small campus in downtown Fort Wayne. In 1998 this academic unit was renamed the School of Fine and Performing Arts. During the latter 1990s, the School of Fine and Performing Arts and its primary classroom building was renamed the School of Visual and Performing Arts and Visual and Performing Arts Building, respectively. In the mid-2000s, the Purdue University board of trustees granted the school “college” status, and it became the College of Visual and Performing Arts.

In 1988, a coalition of the then-[[Lincoln National Corporation]] under the direction of Ian Rolland, the M.E. Raker Foundation, the Olive B. Cole Foundation, and the Foellinger Foundation purchased an additional {{convert|152|acre|km2}} on the west bank of the [[St. Joseph River (Maumee River)|St. Joseph River]]. This tract was the remaining portion of the McKay family homestead.&lt;/&quot;ref name=IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;&gt; 

In 2007, the State of Indiana completed the process of closing the Fort Wayne State Developmental Center. A portion of the grounds had been transferred to IPFW years earlier for construction of the Northeast Indiana Innovation Center. The remaining property and buildings of the {{convert|142|acre|km2|adj=on}} developmental center was transferred later in 2007, with the land split between IPFW ({{convert|40|acre|m2}}) and [[Ivy Tech Community College]]–Northeast ({{convert|45|acre|m2}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;/&gt;

===Chancellors===
At the separate Indiana University and Purdue University extension centers, the most senior executive title was “dean and director.” Frank Schockley (1917), Floyd Neff (1917–1951), and Ralph Broyles (1951–1970) were the dean-directors at the IU Fort Wayne Extension Center. Broyles then served as the only chancellor of the IU regional campus from 1970 to 1974. Conwell Poling (1942–1947), Richard Bateman (1947–1960), Robert Ewigleben (1960–1965), D. Richard Smith (1965–1970), Lawrence Nelson (1970, interim), and Roger Manges (1970–1975) comprised the sequence of dean-directors at the Purdue University Fort Wayne Extension Center. 

Under Dean-Directors Neff and Broyles, the IU Extension Center expanded into an institution that granted associate degrees and presaged what was to come. Under Broyles’ leadership coupled with Alfred Kettler’s vision for a physically combined IPFW, the IPFW site became a reality in the 1960s. Kettler Hall (then the Education Building), Neff Hall, Helmke Library, and the Walb Student Union were built during this phase and into the early 1970s.

Through an agreement between Purdue University and IU that took effect June 1974, the schools dissolved the regional campus administrations and approved administrative reorganization at all of the regional campuses in the state. Donald Schwartz was named the single chancellor of all of IPFW in July 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;IPFW Office of Institutional Research&quot;/&gt; Schwartz (1974–1978), Francis Borkowski (summer 1978, acting), Dwight Henderson (1978–1979, acting), Joseph Giusti (1979–1984), Edward Nicholson Jr. (1984–1986, acting), Thomas Wallace (1986–1988), Joanne Lantz (1988–1994), and Michael A. Wartell (1994–present) have all led IPFW as the chancellor [5]. This sequence of leadership can be segmented into five major administrations in IPFW’s history and progress.

* '''The Schwartz Administration''' (1974–1978)—An immediate goal for Donald Schwartz was to unify the administrative offices, campus policies, and 32 academic departments between IU and Purdue programs [6]. To support the new institution’s image as a self-contained campus, what had been known as the Indiana-Purdue Regional Campus at Fort Wayne became Indiana University–Purdue University at Fort Wayne­. (The “at” was dropped in subsequent years.) As his tenure progressed, Schwartz continually challenged both IU’s and Purdue’s president to gain greater autonomy for the Fort Wayne campus. While this passion established greater local decision-making authority, the style and speed associated with these changes were not well received in Bloomington and West Lafayette. These reservations expressed by the respective presidents inspired Schwartz to resign from his post in early 1978 [6].

* '''The Giusti Administration''' (1979–1984)—Giusti’s administration continued the emphasis on unifying the operations of IPFW as a university serving northeast Indiana. Community relations were strengthened through the chancellor’s membership on numerous boards and his encouragement to faculty and staff to find ways to build town-gown relationships. Giusti also led efforts to beautify the campus, including the establishment of the Geogarden, the Friends Carrilon, the Neff Hall sculpture, and the Distinguished Alumni Room. The Medical-Education Building and the Gates Sports Center were constructed during his administration. In turn, the Fort Wayne Center for Medical Education was formed, and IPFW’s athletics programs moved to [[NCAA]] Division II and membership in the [[Great Lakes Valley Conference]]. Academic programs were established, including anthropology and engineering, and the Weekend College was inaugurated. The faculty governance structure reached a new level of maturity with the establishment of the joint faculty senate. Several IU technology programs were integrated with on-campus programs, and the downtown Barr Street facility was leased to a local nonprofit organization. The affirmative action office was established, major efforts were made to improve campus publications and communication strategies, and the IPFW cable TV station was launched. Enrollment surpassed the 10,000-student milestone [5].

* '''The Wallace Administration''' (1986–1988)—The arrival of Thomas Wallace was a burst of energy for IPFW. It began a densely condensed phase of history that defined a refreshed and re-energized vision for IPFW, which included the academic structure of its schools, the school colors, adjustments to the relationship with the parent university systems, and the current building-construction phase. Wallace left IPFW upon being selected as president of [[Illinois State University]] in June 1988, where he executed a substantially similar vision as to what he had developed at IPFW. By the close of the Wallace administration, the major accomplishment was the re-establishment of blue and white as IPFW’s official school colors, which is a notable act of autonomy because IPFW is the only member of either the Purdue system or the IU system to have neither red nor crimson nor gold nor old gold as one of its school colors [6]. The major accomplishments of the Wallace administration that were finalized shortly after Wallace’s departure were the reorganization of IPFW’s disparate collection of departments and divisions into a cohesive set of schools and the establishment of an MBA degree.

* '''The Lantz Administration''' (1988–1994)—The fourth phase was a period of renewing strong relationships with the parent university systems through Chancellor Lantz’s efforts. Following the energetic two years of the Wallace administration, Purdue was interested in establishing both a better relationship with IPFW as well as a firmer control over IPFW. Lantz negotiated a four-way agreement between Purdue, the IU system, the IPFW faculty, and the Indiana-Purdue Foundation (now the IPFW Foundation), which controls IPFW’s land. Under this agreement that is subject to quinquennial reviews by the IU system, Purdue is to administer IPFW’s operations, except the medical programs and any IU academic programs [5]. Brokering this agreement and finalizing the Wallace administration’s partially completed academic reorganization were the major accomplishments of the Lantz administration in advancing IPFW, the institution. During the Lantz administration, the Visual Arts Building, Parking Garage 1, Williams Theatre, and the Engineering, Technology, and Computer Science Building (then the Engineering and Technology Building) were constructed [5].

* '''The Wartell Administration''' (1994–present)—The Wartell administration has the longest tenure on record and has realized two successful five-year strategic plans. Under Wartell, the university has commenced on its most aggressive building construction efforts in its history, which includes overseeing the addition of more than {{convert|100|acre|km2}} to the campus property. His leadership is responsible for the construction of the [[Holiday Inn]] at IPFW, IPFW Student Housing on the Waterfield Campus (stages I–III), the Medical Education Center, the Science Building, the Rhinehart Music Center, the PLEX indoor soccer building and the Hefner Soccer Fields (12 outdoor soccer fields), Parking Garage 2, the Willis Family Bridge, the Ron Venderly Family Bridge, and the forthcoming Keith Busse Steel Dynamics Alumni Center and the Student Services Complex [5]. The administration’s most noteworthy academic advancements include expanding the university’s number of certificate and degree options to more than 200 possibilities. A long-standing advocate for quality instruction and access to education, Wartell secured a number of endowed and named professorships and top-level student scholarships. His administration executed the School-Based Concurrent Enrollment Program, where students who attend partnering high schools in northeast Indiana can earn IPFW General Education college credits that also satisfy high school graduation requirements. The administration has also been a front-runner in community engagement, creating the IPFW Centers of Excellence—more than a dozen research centers specializing in areas as broad as green building and animal conservation to wireless technologies and pension plan management [5]. A large number of public/private partnerships have been established as well, with organizations that include the defense industry, the Fort Wayne Center for Learning, the Fort Wayne Philharmonic, the Northeast Indiana Innovation Center, Parkview Health Systems, and PBS39 WFWA-DT, to name a few [5]. Also under Wartell’s leadership, IPFW’s endowment and level of public and private funding has significantly increased to previously unprecedented levels. The endowment has risen from $3 million to $35 million since he took office, and more than $60 million dollars has been raised from external sources [5]. The Wartell administration also ushered its 16 men’s and women’s sports into [[NCAA]] Division I athletic competition, as well as membership in [[The Summit League]] conference.

==Campus==
[[Image:2008 Rhinehart Music Center.jpg|right|250px|thumb|The John and Ruth Rhinehart Music Center, completed in 2007, features the 1,600-seat Auer Performance Hall.]]

===Primary campus structures===
These structures were acquired or constructed for IPFW:
*Child Care Center (1956)
*Physical Plant Building (1963)
*Education Building (Kettler Hall) (1963)
*Biggs Hall (1965)
*Craig Hall (1965)
*Dolnick Center (1965)
*Dunham Hall (1965)
*Ginsberg Center (1965)
*Handley Hall (1965)
*Neff Hall (1970)
*Helmke Library (1970)
*Walb Student Union (1971)
*Classroom-Medical Building (1981) (renamed the Liberal Arts Building in 2010)
*Gates Sports Center (1981)
*Life Sciences Resource Center (1986)
*Warehouse/Printing Services Building (1990)
*Fine Arts Building (1991)
*Parking Garage 1 (1991)
*Williams Theatre (1992)
*Engineering, Technology, and Computer Science Building (1992)
*Science Building (1997)
*Parking Garage 2 (1997)
*Soccer Support Facility (2002)
*Willis Family Bridge (2003)
*Hobson Center (2004)
*IPFW Student Housing on the Waterfield Campus (Phases I, II, III) (2004–2010)
*Northeast Indiana Innovation Center (2005)
*PBS39 WFWA-DT (2005)
*Rhinehart Music Center (2007)
*Holiday Inn at IPFW and the Coliseum (2008)
*Medical Education Center (2009)
*Ron Venderly Family Bridge (2009)
*Keith Busse Steel Dynamics Alumni Center (projected completion in 2011)
*Parking Garage 3 (projected completion in 2011)
*Student Services Complex (projected completion in 2011)

===Student housing===
[[Image:2008 IPFW Dorms.jpg|right|250px|thumb|Waterfield Student Housing.]]
Beginning with fall semester 2004, the university introduced a new variety of student housing to northeast Indiana—IPFW Student Housing on the Waterfield Campus. Rather than traditionally cramped dorm rooms, apartment-style housing opened with seven buildings, featuring furnished rooms, full kitchens, private bedrooms, and even free wireless Internet access. Phase II of the student housing initiative continued with two more buildings in August 2007, with total student housing occupancy approaching nearly 750 residents. Phase III of the project, which opened in August 2010, added 448 beds divided between four new residence buildings, bringing total occupancy to more than 1,200 students. Another student community center, The Clubhouse—a larger version of the existing Cole Commons, complete with classrooms—was added as well as a maintenance facility [7].

===Boundaries===
As can be seen in from an [http://www.google.com/local?f=q&amp;hl=en&amp;q=2101+East+Coliseum+Blvd,+Fort+Wayne,+Indiana&amp;t=h&amp;ll=41.118822,-85.109024&amp;spn=0.014937,0.033817&amp;t=h aerial vantage], IPFW's campus is composed of four parts:
* the '''main academic campus''', bounded by East Coliseum Boulevard ([[Indiana State Road 930]]) to the south, Crescent Avenue ([[Indiana State Road 37]]) to the east, Saint Joseph River to the west, and the Canterbury Green Apartment complex and golf course to the north;
* the '''residential campus''', bounded by Crescent Avenue to the west, Coliseum Boulevard and Trier Road to the south, and Hobson Road to the East;
* the '''research-incubator campus''', bounded by St. Joe Road to the west, Stellhorn Road ([[Indiana State Road 37]]) to the south, Dean Drive to the north, and Sirlin Drive to the east;[http://www.ipfw.edu/assets/images/news/downloadable/projects/hotelGardenBridge.gif]
* the '''former McKay-family farm''', the portion of campus on the western bank of the Saint Joseph River, which is bounded by East Coliseum Boulevard to the south, Saint Joseph River to the east, and development to the north and west. The &quot;Plex&quot; indoor soccer facility and the [[Holiday Inn]] hotel that are on this portion of the IPFW campus.

===Grounds and landmarks===
Architecturally, IPFW buildings generally feature brick in various shades of brown or tan as a variation on Purdue West Lafayette’s red brick. This is in contrast to IPFW’s sibling university, Indiana University–Purdue University Indianapolis, where IUPUI’s buildings generally feature the Indiana limestone that IU Bloomington’s buildings feature. Recent administrative efforts to improve campus accessibility, traffic flow, and grounds beautification have paid off to make IPFW more a campus of pedestrians and less a commuter campus focused on just a few buildings on one end of the campus. With the Willis Family Bridge over Crescent Avenue and the Ron Venderly Family Bridge spanning the [[St. Joseph River (Maumee River)|St. Joseph River]], IPFW’s residential campus, from east to west, has been made easier to navigate. The grounds at IPFW are manicured and landscaped as a pastoral multiple-hundred-acre park due in part to Virginia Ayers, an avid long-time exerciser on campus who willed her estate to IPFW upon her death. The campus landscape features the following highlights [8]:
*the Geogarden geological tour (northwest of Kettler Hall)
*the student-designed Set in Stone (art collection between Helmke Library and Parking Garage 1)
*the life-size bronze Mastodon statue (Alumni Plaza)
*the student-designed Student Legacy 25th Anniversary Sculpture composed of 25 upright poles of multiple colors, celebrating campus diversity and dedicated during the university’s 25th anniversary (north of the Liberal Arts Building)
*Chessboard, a human-sized chess board with giant chess pieces available for students to borrow (west of Walb Student Union)
*the wooded Aquarius Park, containing the Friends (of IPFW) Pavilion (west of Walb Student Union)
*the Onwood Memorial Wildflower Garden adjacent to the Friends Pavilion
*the Millennium Marker that serves as IPFW’s entrance sign along Coliseum Boulevard
*the Peace Pole Sculpture that is inscribed with translations of “May peace prevail on earth” in a variety of languages (near the Friends Pavilion)
*Matilda, a mastodon wall mural near the southeast entrance to Gates Sports Center
*the graduate-designed Lascaux Stacked Plus One sculpture (north of Aquarius Park)
*the Dirrim Quiet Spot along the eastern bank of the St. Joseph River (west of the Visual Arts Building)
*the Connie and Dan Dickey Alumni Fountain, a “flat” fountain with jumping jets of water (near Alumni Plaza)
*the SCAN (Stop Child Abuse &amp; Neglect) Children’s Garden (north of Williams Theatre)

Adjacent to IPFW’s campus are a collection of municipal, county, and state facilities that contribute to IPFW’s mission and function. To the southeast of the IPFW campus across Coliseum Boulevard, on the northwest corner of [[Johnny Appleseed Park]] is the [[Allen County War Memorial Coliseum]], which for major indoor intercollegiate athletics events IPFW shares with Fort Wayne’s professional indoor athletic teams. To the south across Coliseum Boulevard, is Fort Wayne’s branch of the [[Ivy Tech Community College]] system. The [[Holiday Inn]] at IPFW opened on the western side of the [[St. Joseph River (Maumee River)|St. Joseph River]] in November 2008. The hotel provides on-site classes for students enrolled in IPFW’s Hospitality Management Program.

IPFW is now a {{convert|662|acre|km2|adj=on}} campus on both sides of the [[St. Joseph River (Maumee River)|St. Joseph River]] with numerous educational buildings, student residence halls, a hotel, and various other athletic facilities and parking structures. The campus also hosts the Northeast Indiana Innovation Center and the studios for Fort Wayne’s public television station, PBS39 WFWA-DT.
Prior to the construction of residential apartments on the residential campus, and still today, many IPFW students live in the adjacent Canterbury Green Apartments—one of the largest apartment complexes in the United States with a population of nearly 5,000 residents—immediately to the north of the main academic campus.

The predecessor to WBNI, northeastern Indiana’s public radio station, was WIPU, whose broadcast tower was located next to Kettler Hall and whose studio was located within Kettler Hall. IPFW also sponsors College Access Television, a channel for college-produced [[Distance learning|Educational-access television]] programming. It is one of five [[Public-access television]] [[cable TV]] channels serving Fort Wayne and Allen County.

==Athletics==
===Mascot and monikers===
[[Image:IPFWMastodons.png|right|thumb|IPFW Mastodons logo]]
{{Main|IPFW Mastodons}}

IPFW student-athletes compete as a [[National Collegiate Athletic Association]] [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]] school in the [[The Summit League]] for most sports and in the [[Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]] for men's volleyball. The university participates in 15 men’s and women’s sports. Before joining NCAA Division I athletics, IPFW competed in the [[Great Lakes Valley Conference]] in the [[NCAA]] [[Division II (NCAA)|Division II]].

==Community engagement==

The university’s commitment to service makes it an economic, cultural, and societal leader in the region through examples such as fostering small business development, providing enlightenment from internationally known guest speakers, and enabling access to healthcare for underserved populations.{{Citation needed|date=February 2010}}

===Centers of Excellence===

IPFW’s 17 Centers of Excellence were established to satisfy the following university objectives [11]:

*recognize and advance faculty expertise
*engage undergraduate and graduate students in experiential learning opportunities through service and research
*market those capabilities to the public, private, and nonprofit sectors
*provide opportunities to integrate teaching, research, and service
*encourage multidisciplinary collaboration
*facilitate the administration of externally supported projects

'''Archaeological Survey'''—The Archaeological Survey serves as an umbrella for cultural resource management and research-based archaeological activities within IPFW’s geographic service area. 

'''Behavioral Health and Family Studies Institute'''—The Behavioral Health and Family Studies Institute provides professional education, community training, consultation, and research related to behavioral health and family studies topics.

'''Center for the Built Environment'''—The Center for the Built Environment promotes sustainable, green building and creates collaborative projects with community partners.

'''Center for Reptile and Amphibian Conservation and Management (also Herp Center)'''—The Center for Reptile and Amphibian Conservation and Management promotes the understanding and conservation of reptiles and amphibians native to the [[Midwest]] and beyond through research, education, and outreach.

'''Center for Social Research'''—The Center for Social Research contracts with public and private organizations to conduct social, opinion, attitudinal, and applied research at the local, regional, and state level to identify client-specific solutions.

'''Center of Excellence in Systems Engineering'''—The Center of Excellence in Systems Engineering is an industry-university collaboration in systems engineering education and research that focuses on interindustry collaboration and fosters the development of systems processes through the sponsorship of professional and technical symposia. 

'''Community Research Institute'''—The Community Research Institute links the academic expertise at IPFW with the needs of the public and nonprofit sectors in northeast Indiana by providing research and analytical support in the areas of socio-economic data, urban planning, municipal finance, public policy, and economic development.

'''Information Analytics and Visualization Center'''—The Information Analytics and Visualization Center provides state-of-the-art resources to business, industry, and government enterprises in areas such as information processing, data mining, virtual reality technology, [[usability engineering]], machine learning, and networking and security.

'''Institute for Decision Sciences and Theory'''—The Institute for Decision Sciences and Theory promotes research in decision theory, enhances faculty development, expands educational opportunities for IPFW students, attracts support for research by partnering with northeast Indiana industries, and serves the business community of northeast Indiana by supplying expertise for the development of decision-theory applications.

'''Institute for Holocaust and Genocide Studies'''—The Institute for Holocaust and Genocide Studies promotes public awareness of the [[Holocaust]] and other genocides; encourages and supports scholarship, research, and teaching about the [[Holocaust]] and genocide; and promotes public participation in efforts to confront contemporary genocide as it occurs.

'''Institute for Pension Plan Management'''—The Institute for Pension Plan Management supports and enhances the efforts of local, regional, and national retirement plan and employee benefits management providers in their efforts to meet the demands placed upon them as professionals and to assist in the preservation of sound quality retirement and benefits plan programs for American workers. 

'''IPFW Human Rights Institute'''—The IPFW Human Rights Institute underscores the convergence between the American national purpose and respect for individual rights by pursuing projects that develop local applications of universal principles and promoting global awareness of human rights issues. 

'''IPFW Wireless Technology Center'''—The IPFW Wireless Technology Center researches wireless communication concerns and furthers innovations in wireless communication technology given Fort Wayne’s importance as a hub for tactical wireless systems.

'''Mike Downs Center for Indiana Politics'''—The Mike Downs Center for Indiana Politics is the first non-partisan center in [[Indiana]] helping people to understand the importance of active participation in political and public processes.

'''Northeast Indiana Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math Education Resource Center (NISTEM)'''—The NISTEM Education Resource Center is a partnership with a cadre of regional stakeholders to support and encourage active engagement in science, technology, engineering, and math-related activities and educational pursuits for school-age children.

'''Scholar-Practitioner Center for the Advancement of Educational Leadership and Learning Organizations'''—The Scholar-Practitioner Center uses research to guide decision making and problem solving in the context of school corporations by examining policies for effectiveness and by authentically contributing to the educational field-base through scholarship.

'''Three Rivers Language Center'''—The Three Rivers Language Center preserves and revives endangered [[Native American languages]] of the lower [[Great Lakes]] area and elsewhere through documentation and education.

===Omnibus Lecture Series===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:fonzie.jpg|right|200px|thumb|2009 Omnibus speakers: Award-winning actors Henry &quot;The Fonz&quot; Winkler and Marlee Matlin|{{deletable image-caption|1=Tuesday, 29 September 2009}}|{{deletable image-caption|1=Tuesday, 29 September 2009}}]] --&gt;
The Omnibus Lecture Series presents diverse ideas through educated, respected, and entertaining speakers to the university community and the residents of northeast Indiana. Omnibus has featured such notable presenters as [[Henry Winkler]] &quot;The Fonz,&quot; [[Marlee Matlin]], [[Cheech Marin]], [[Betty Friedan]], [[James Earl Jones]], [[Robert F. Kennedy Jr.]], [[Ralph Nader]], [[Joyce Carol Oates]], [[Deepak Chopra]], [[Gail Sheehy]], [[Hal Holbrook]], [[Sandra Day O’Connor]], and Sean Astin [12].

===Northeast Indiana Area Health Education Center===
The Northeast Indiana Area Health Education Center is a collaboration among the IPFW College of Health and Human Services, Indiana Area Health Education Center Program office, Indiana University School of Medicine–Fort Wayne, Allen County Health Disparity Coalition, the Dr. Jeff Towles Health Disparities Initiative, and other community healthcare providers and schools to serve 19 counties in northeast and east central Indiana. The center is in the Lafayette Medical Building in the heart of urban Fort Wayne, with room to provide health services, educational programs, and resource materials [14].

===Lafayette Street Family Health Clinic===
The Lafayette Street Family Health Clinic is a nurse-practitioner clinic that provides high-quality, comprehensive family planning services to low-income women and men, specializing in clients of all cultural and ethnic backgrounds. The clinic offers most birth control methods, pap smears for cervical cancer screening, pregnancy tests, clinical breast exams, emergency contraception, testing and treatment of Sexually Transmitted Infections (STIs), HIV counseling and testing, and education on reproductive health. The clinic also serves as a remote site for IPFW’s Dental Clinic, which offers reduced-cost services [15].

===Tapestry: A Day for Women===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:ClintonKelly.jpg|right|150px|thumb|2009 Tapestry Keynote Speaker: &quot;What Not To Wear&quot; co-host Clinton Kelly|{{deletable image-caption|1=Tuesday, 29 September 2009}}]] --&gt;
Tapestry: A Day for Women provides a day of renewal and self-growth each spring through educational, motivational, and inspirational activities at the [[Allen County War Memorial Coliseum]]. Tapestry proceeds support the Tapestry Parkview Endowment Fund and the Tapestry gift account and provide scholarships to women studying health sciences at IPFW. Since its beginning in 2002, Tapestry has raised more than $370,000 and awarded more than $50,000 in scholarships. Tapestry has featured such notable keynote speakers as [[Dana Reeve]], [[Linda Ellerbee]], [[Patty Duke]], [[Marie Osmond]], and [[Clinton Kelly (TV personality)|Clinton Kelly]] [13].

===IPFW Dental Clinic===
The on-campus IPFW Dental Clinic offers complete cleanings, fluoride treatments, and dental sealants, plus full-mouth, bite-wing, and panographic X-rays at a reduced cost for the community [16].

==Public/private partnerships==
===Holiday Inn at IPFW and the Coliseum===
&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:HolidayInn.jpg|right|150px|thumb|The Holiday Inn at IPFW and the Coliseum is a full-service hotel with teaching facilities for IPFW's hospitality management majors.|{{deletable image-caption|1=Tuesday, 29 September 2009}}]] --&gt;
The [[Holiday Inn]] at IPFW represents a unique partnership. It operates on property leased from the Indiana-Purdue Foundation, and the establishment serves as a living laboratory for students enrolled in IPFW’s Hospitality Management Program [17].

===The Communicator===
[[The Communicator (IPFW)|IPFW’s award-winning student newspaper]] celebrated its 40th anniversary in 2009 [19].

===College Access Television===
College Access Television is operated by IPFW and is one of five [[Distance learning|Educational-access television]] channels serving Fort Wayne and Allen County. CATV is available on [[Frontier Communications]] and [[Comcast]] cable systems and serves as the higher education cable access channel and provides opportunities in higher education for area residents [20].

===Northeast Indiana Innovation Center===

IPFW leases a portion of its Northeast Campus, the corner of St. Joe and Stellhorn roads, to the Northeast Indiana Innovation Center. The Innovation Center leverages university resources to facilitate technology transfer, innovative business development, and economic growth in new ventures [18].

===Public television===
IPFW leases a portion of its East Campus, the corner of Coliseum Boulevard and Crescent Avenue, to Fort Wayne’s public television station, PBS39 WFWA-DT [21].

==Notable alumni==
* [[Lloy Ball]], U.S. [[Olympic Games|Olympic]] men's volleyball team captain (1996, 2000, 2004); U.S. Olympic men's volleyball gold medalist (2008)
* [[Julia Barr]], actress, ''[[All My Children]]''
* [[Tim Berry]], auditor, State of Indiana
* [[Randy Borror]], state representative, State of Indiana
* [[Keith Busse]], president and CEO, [[Steel Dynamics]]
* [[Dan Butler]], actor, ''[[Frasier]]''
* [[Dennis Kruse]], state senator, State of Indiana
* [[Mark Souder]], former Indiana representative, [[U.S. House of Representatives]]
* [[Thomas Wyss (politician)]], state senator, State of Indiana

== External links ==
* [http://www.ipfw.edu Official website]
* [http://www.gomastodons.com Official athletics website]
*[http://www.thesummitleague.org Summit League website]
* Campus Map [http://virtualtour.ipfw.edu/]
* [http://www.ipfwcommunicator.org ''The Communicator'', student newspaper]

{{Coord|41.118822|-85.109024|region:US_type:edu|display=title}}

==References==
{{reflist}}
*3. IPFW Designations List (http://www.ipfw.edu/publications/pdfs/ipfw-designations-list.pdf). Retrieved on May 22, 2009.
*5. The Creation Years: Indiana University–Purdue University Fort Wayne, John Ankenbruck, Evangel Press, 1983.
*7. “Regional Renaissance: New campus structures to benefits students, area.” IPFW Alumni Newsletter. Volume 12, Number 5, April 2009.
*10. IPFW Athletics (http://www.gomastondons.com). Retrieved on May 2, 2009.
*11. IPFW Centers of Excellence (http://www.ipfw.edu/ores/centers). Retrieved on September 4, 2009.
*12. Omnibus Lecture Series (http://www.omnibuslectures.org). Retrieved on September 17, 2009.
*13. Tapestry: A Day for Women (http://www.ipfw.edu/tapestry). Retrieved on July 7, 2009.
*14. Northeast Indiana Area Health Education Center (http://www.ipfw.edu/hhs/outreach/ahec). Retrieved on July 16, 2009.
*15. Lafayette Street Family Health Clinic (http://www.ipfw.edu/hhs/outreach/lafayettestreet). Retrieved on July 16, 2009.
*16. IPFW Dental Clinic (http://www.ipfw.edu/life/health/dental.shtml). Retrieved on July 16, 2009.
*17. Holiday Inn at IPFW and the Coliseum (http://www.fortwayneholidayinn.com). Retrieved on February 10, 2009.
*18. Northeast Indiana Innovation Center (http://www.niic.net). Retrieved on February 10, 2009.
*19. The Communicator (http://www.ipfwcommunicator.org). Retrieved on December 10, 2008.
*20. College Access Television (http://www.catv5.org). Retrieved on December 10, 2008.
*21. Public Television (http://www.wfwa.org/index.html). Retrieved on December 16, 2009.

{{The Summit League}}
{{MIVA Conference}}
{{Public colleges and universities in Indiana}}

[[Category:Indiana University – Purdue University Fort Wayne|*]]
[[Category:American Association of State Colleges and Universities]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges in Indiana]]
[[Category:Indiana University]]
[[Category:Purdue University]]
[[Category:Education in Fort Wayne, Indiana]]
[[Category:North Central Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Midwestern Intercollegiate Volleyball Association]]
[[Category:Joint Venture Schools]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Fort Wayne, Indiana]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Fort Wayne, Indiana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
