<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="392902" ns="0" title="Furman University"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox university
|name = Furman University
|image_name = Furman U Seal.png
|image_size  =  150px
|motto = ''Christo et Doctrinae'' 
|mottoeng = For Christ and Learning
|established = 1826
|type = [[Private school|Private]]
|president = [[Rodney A. Smolla]]
|city = [[Greenville, South Carolina|Greenville]]
|state = [[South Carolina]]
|country = [[United States]]
|undergrad = 2,801 
|postgrad = 176
|faculty = 272
|endowment = US$444 million &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nacubo.org/Documents/research/2009_NCSE_Public_Tables_Endowment_Market_Values.pdf |title=Part One |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2010-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Duke Endowment|Beneficiary of Duke Endowment]]
|campus = [[Suburban]]&lt;br&gt; {{convert|750|acre|ha|0|adj=on}}
|colors = [[Royal Purple]] and [[White]] {{color box|#6B3FA0}} {{color box|white}} 
|free_label = Athletics
|free = 21 varsity teams
|nickname = [[Paladin]]s 
|athletics= [[Division I (NCAA)|Division I]]
|affiliations   = [[Southern Conference]]
|website = [http://www.furman.edu/ www.furman.edu]
|logo = [[File:Furman Logo.png|center|250px]]
}}

'''Furman University''' is a selective, [[Private university|private]], [[coeducation]]al, [[liberal arts college]] in [[Greenville, South Carolina|Greenville]], [[South Carolina]], [[United States]].  Furman is one of the oldest&lt;ref&gt;http://www2.furman.edu/about/about/history/Pages/default.aspx&lt;/ref&gt;, and more selective&lt;ref&gt;http://colleges.usnews.rankingsandreviews.com/best-colleges/furman-university-3434&lt;/ref&gt; private institutions in South Carolina.  Founded in 1826, Furman enrolls approximately 2,600 undergraduate and 525 graduate students on its {{convert|750|acre|ha|0|adj=on}} campus.  

In recent years, more Furman University graduates have gone on to earn more [[Ph.D.]] degrees than those of any other private liberal arts college in the South, according to a survey conducted by the [[University of Chicago]]'s [[National Opinion Research Center]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.collegenews.org/x5417.xml http://www.collegenews.org/x5417.xml]&lt;/ref&gt;  Today Furman offers majors and programs in 42 subjects.  Most of Furman's 2,600 undergraduates are from the South Atlantic region, but more than 40 states and 15 foreign countries are represented in the student population.  Furman is a member of [[Associated Colleges of the South]].

==History==
[[Image:Furman University - old campus, Greenville, South Carolina.jpg|thumb|right|200 px|1909 postcard of Furman University, Greenville]]
Furman was founded in 1826 at Edgefield, SC as a Men's Academy and Theological Institute.  It relocated in [[Greenville, South Carolina]] in 1850. It was named for [[Richard Furman]] of Charleston, SC, a prominent [[minister (Christianity)|minister]] and president of the first [[Baptist]] convention in America, the Triennial Convention.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.furman.edu/general/history.htm |title=Furman University History |publisher=Furman.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original school building from that campus was transported to the Greenville campus, where it still stands. In 1933, students from the Greenville Women's College began attending classes with Furman students. Shortly thereafter, the two schools merged to form the present institution. 

In 1956 Furman began construction on its new campus, just five miles (8&amp;nbsp;km) north of downtown Greenville. Classes on the new campus began in 1958. Now a private, secular university, Furman was founded by, and affiliated with the South Carolina Baptist Convention and the [[Southern Baptist Convention]] until separating in the 1991 - 1992 school year. The university's motto remains ''Christo et Doctrinae'' (For Christ and Learning).  According to Furman University's official website, the university &quot;is rooted in the non-creedal, free church Baptist tradition which has always valued particular religious commitments while insisting not only on the freedom of the individual to believe as he or she sees fit but also on respect for a diversity of religious perspectives...&quot;. Furman University is part of the [[Duke Endowment]]. The Duke Endowment is a private foundation established by industrialist and philanthropist [[James B. Duke]]. The market value of the Duke Endowment's assets have grown to approximately $3.5 billion. From 1924-2007, the Duke Endowment has given Furman $110 million,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.furman.edu/about/about/Pages/DukeEndow.aspx|title=Duke Endowment: Partners in Progress|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is 5% of the Duke Endowment's total awards.

The current president is [[Rodney A. Smolla]], formerly the Dean of [[Washington and Lee University]]'s law school. He became the 11th president of the university, effective July 1, 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.furman.edu/about/about/newpresident/Pages/default.aspx|title=Rodney Smolla Named 11th President of Furman University|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; replacing [[David E. Shi]], a 1973 alumnus of Furman.  Shi has been a national leader in colleges' working to promote [[sustainability]] and to become [[carbon neutral]].

==Academics==
Furman offers majors and programs in 42 subjects.  Undergraduates come from 46 states and 31 countries. Furman has produced six [[Rhodes scholars]] and 17 [[Harry S. Truman Scholarship|Truman scholars]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.furman.edu/main/aboutfurman.htm |title=About Furman}}
&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[Image:Furman-Belltower2.jpg|thumb|250px|The Bell Tower, an [[icon]] of the university.]]

All students must complete general education requirements as part of the liberal arts curriculum. The general education requirements include wellness, textual analysis, a natural science, math/formal reasoning, empirical study of human behavior, history, and human culture. Furman becoming a leader in sustainability {{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} has now required a course on humans and their interaction with the environment as an undergraduate requirement.

Furman’s four-year graduation rate of 81 percent{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}  puts it at the top of public and private institutions deemed highly competitive in the South.

===Rankings===
Furman was ranked no. 15 in the list of the ''[[Washington Monthly]]'' &quot;Top US Liberal Arts Colleges Rankings&quot;, based on its production of research valuable to society and its commitment to national service.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Washington Monthly Online |url=http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/features/2005/0509.collegeguide.html |title=&quot;The Washington Monthly College Guide &quot; by The Editors |publisher=Washingtonmonthly.com |date= |accessdate=2010-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The university's engaged learning academic program, which promotes problem-solving, project-oriented, experience-based education, has received high praise from ''The Princeton Review'', ''Peterson's Competitive Colleges '', ''The Fiske Guide to Colleges'' and ''The College Board College Handbook''. In terms of the quality of the students, Furman was ranked no. 30 in the SSRN's &quot;U.S Colleges and Universities Preference Rankings&quot; (based on the choice to enroll of high-achieving students in US)&lt;ref&gt;[http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=601105 http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=601105]&lt;/ref&gt; ''The Chronicle of Higher Education'' noted Furman was no. 32 in the nation for the percentage of National Merit Scholars in its 2005-2006 freshman class.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://cgi.greenville.com/news/furman0206.html |title=Furman's National Merit Scholars}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a report from the [[American Institute of Physics]], Furman is one of 35 schools whose physics departments offer a bachelor’s as their highest degree to average 10 or more undergraduate degrees for the classes of 2003, 2004 and 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.furman.edu/?articleid=2386 http://www.furman.edu/?articleid=2386]&lt;/ref&gt; By survey, ''The Princeton Review'' ranked Furman University as number 9 in their top 10 most socially conservative schools in 2009.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|title=Top 10 Most Socially Conservative Colleges - MSN Encarta &lt;!-- BOT GENERATED TITLE --&gt;|url=http://encarta.msn.com/encnet/Departments/College/?article=Top10MostConservative09|work=|archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5kwpYqjoQ|archivedate=2009-10-31|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campus==
A {{convert|40|acre|ha|1|adj=on}} lake is at the center of the {{convert|750|acre|ha|0|adj=on}}
, wooded campus.  Most buildings are of [[Georgian-style]] architecture. Many academic buildings and student residences stand around the lake, including the Bell Tower. The Bell Tower figures highly in school insignias and is a replica of the tower that once existed on the men's campus in downtown Greenville. Today, the campus is anchored by its newly expanded 128,000-square foot (12,000 m²) [[James B. Duke Library]]. Informally known as &quot;The Country Club of the South,&quot; Furman was named one of the 362 most beautiful places in America by the [[American Society of Landscape Architects]]. 
The fall 1997 issue of ''Planning for Higher Education'' names Furman as a benchmark campus for its landscaping.  The 1997 ''Princeton Review'' ranked Furman fifth in its list of beautiful campuses, based on student ratings of campus beauty. Students are required to live on campus, except senior year when they may participate in a lottery for a chance to live off campus.[[File:Furman library.jpg|thumb|250px|left| The James B. Duke Library]]

On the north side of the lake are the four Greenbelt housing cabins,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ees.furman.edu/greenguide/greenbeltcommunity.htm|title=Engaged Living's Greenbelt Community|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Cliffs Cottage, which is a &quot;green&quot; building built as a showcase home in conjunction with ''Southern Living'' magazine.&lt;ref name=&quot;The Cliffs Cottage&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ees.furman.edu/greenguide/Cliffs.html|title=The Cliffs Cottage|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Most juniors and seniors live in North Village Apartments, located on the north side of the Cliffs Cottage. The remaining upperclassmen are either placed in dorm-style residence halls or enter a lottery to receive an apartment in The Vinings, an apartment complex next to campus owned by the university.  There are two other residence complexes (called Lakeside and South Housing). The campus also includes an [[Furman University Japanese Garden|Asian Garden]], the centerpiece of which is the Place of Peace, a Buddhist temple moved to the site from Japan and reconstructed by traditional carpenters. A replica of the cabin that Henry David Thoreau inhabited while writing ''On Walden Pond'' is located on the west side of the lake.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.furman.edu/Visitors/Visitors/Pages/default.aspx|title=The Simple Cabin by the Lake|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Student life==
===Undergraduate student housing===
All full-time students, except those who are married or living at home with their parents or guardians, are required to live on campus in university housing. Furman undergraduates can choose between south campus housing and lakeside housing. The south campus housing contains the Geer, Manly, Poteat, Blackwell and McGlothlin dorms. The lakeside housing includes the Gambrell, Ramsey, Judson, Townes, McBee, Haynsworth, and Chiles dorm. All student housing has air-conditioning, closets, wired Internet access, and washer-dryer usage. The North Village is an apartment complex built for the juniors and mainly seniors that offers apartment-style living for upperclassmen. North Village apartments offer two or four bedrooms, living room, full kitchen, balcony, two vanity areas, two bathrooms and closet and storage space. Within each bedroom, a full-size bed, desk, desk chair and dresser/hutch is provided for each resident.
[[Image:Furman welcome.jpg‎|thumb|right|Furman University's Hartness Welcome Center, Office of Admissions and Financial Aid]]

===Dining===
Furman University students are required to have a meal plan and freshmen are required to have an unlimited meal plan. The main dining facility is in the Daniel Hall. Renovated in 2006, Daniel Hall offers buffet-style dining and an [[Einstein Bros. Bagels]] location upstairs. Paladin food court offers [[Chick-Fil-A]], [[Moe's Southwest Grill]], [[Freshens]], and Pan Geos. Furman also has a dining facility named Tower Cafe, where students can get coffee from [[Starbucks]].

===Student government===
Furman University Student Government Association (SGA) works under a semi-Presidential system. SGA is made up of the executive council, and president, secretary, and two senators for each class. Each class elects a president, vice president, secretary, and treasurer, . Upon election council members are assigned within one of six committees to specialize in a particular area of student needs.

===Fraternities and sororities===
Furman Housing and Residence Life delegates halls and lounges for campus fraternities and sororities. Furman University has seven fraternities and seven sororities.  Fraternities on campus: [[Beta Theta Pi]], [[Kappa Alpha Order]], [[Kappa Alpha Psi]], [[Pi Kappa Phi]], [[Sigma Alpha Epsilon]], [[Sigma Chi]], and [[Sigma Nu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Furman University Office of Marketing and Public Relations |url=http://www.furman.edu/orgs/orglist.htm |title=Organizations: : |publisher=Furman.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sororities on campus: [[Alpha Delta Pi]], [[Alpha Kappa Alpha]], [[Chi Omega]], [[Delta Delta Delta]], [[Delta Gamma]], [[Kappa Delta]], and [[Kappa Kappa Gamma]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://panhellenic.furman.edu/ |title=Furman Panhellenic Council - Welcome |publisher=Panhellenic.furman.edu |date= |accessdate=2010-11-29}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The school also has two music based fraternities including [[Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia]], a men's social fraternity with emphasis in music, along with [[Sigma Alpha Iota]], a primarily female professional music organization.

==Athletics==
[[Image:FurmanPaladins.png|thumb|right|Furman Paladins logo]]
Furman competes in [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I athletics and is one of the smallest NCAA Division I schools in the nation. Furman fields 17 men’s and women’s teams, as well as 16 club sports and many intramural teams.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www2.furman.edu/About/About/Pages/default.aspx|title=About Furman University|accessdate=2010-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt; The team nickname, the [[Paladin]]s, was first used by a Greenville, South Carolina, sportswriter in the 1930s. For many years the name “Paladins” just referred to Furman’s basketball team. Until 1963 the school’s baseball teams were known as the &quot;Hornets&quot; and the football teams as the &quot;Hurricanes&quot;. On September 15 of that year, the student body voted to make &quot;Paladins&quot; the official nickname of all of the university's intercollegiate athletic teams. The university is a member of the [[Southern Conference]]. Furman is the only liberal arts college to be ranked in ''Sports Illustrated'' Top 100 America's Best Sports Colleges&lt;ref&gt;[http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/si_online/news/2002/10/01/1_10/ http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/si_online/news/2002/10/01/1_10/]&lt;/ref&gt; and has 32 former student-athletes competing at the professional level- the most of any Southern Conference member school.{{Citation needed|date=January 2010}}
In the 'upstate' area of South Carolina surrounding [[Greenville, SC]], there is a joking urban legend which claims the original team name was &quot;Furman University Christian Knights,&quot; but it was changed to ''Paladins'' when it was realized that the ''Christian Knights'' version would make an undesirable acronym.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.snopes.com/college/admin/furman.asp&lt;/ref&gt;

===Football===
In 1988 Furman won the NCAA I-AA National Football Championship. Furman also appeared in the 1985 and 2001 NCAA I-AA National Football Championship game, but lost (to [[Georgia Southern University|Georgia Southern]] and [[Montana Grizzlies football|Montana]], respectively). Furman, [[Colgate University|Colgate]], [[Lehigh Mountain Hawks|Lehigh]], [[Fordham Rams|Fordham]], [[Richmond Spiders|Richmond]] and [[Villanova Wildcats|Villanova]] remain the only private universities that have appeared in the I-AA Football Championship game, and Furman was the first private school to win it, with Richmond becoming the second 20 years later. The Paladins have also claimed 12 Southern Conference football titles, more than any school in league history. Furman has only won one national championship and that was in football.

===Golf===
Furman has had several successful [[golf]] teams, especially in women's golf. Few collegiate woman golf programs have produced more outstanding professionals than Furman, which has 11 former Lady Paladins on the LPGA tour, including two [[World Golf Hall of Fame|Hall of Fame]] inductees ([[Betsy King]] and [[Beth Daniel]]). Furman has claimed 13 [[Southern Conference]] Women's Golf Championships. PGA Tour players [[Brad Faxon]], Stuart Cook, and [[Bruce Fleisher]] played for the Paladins.

===Soccer===
Coached by [[Doug Allison (soccer)|Doug Allison]], the men's soccer team has been ranked as high as no. 3 in the nation and has produced a share of professional players.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/soccer/2002-09-11-furman_x.htm http://www.usatoday.com/sports/college/soccer/2002-09-11-furman_x.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Former star [[Clint Dempsey]], who now plays club soccer for [[Fulham F.C.]] in the English [[Premier League]], was the only American player to score a goal at the [[2006 FIFA World Cup]] in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;[http://fifaworldcup.yahoo.com/06/en/w/match/42/mr.html http://fifaworldcup.yahoo.com/06/en/w/match/42/mr.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Dempsey also scored notable goals in the US upset of Spain in 2009, the near defeat of Brazil in 2009 and the 1-1 draw with England at the [[2010 FIFA World Cup]] in South Africa. [[Ricardo Clark]], a current member of the [[United States Men's National Soccer Team]] and [[Eintracht Frankfurt]] also played soccer for Furman. Current MLS players [[Shea Salinas]] and [[Jonathan Leathers]] of the [[Vancouver Whitecaps FC|Vancouver Whitecaps]] also played for the Paladins.

===Tennis===
Furman men's tennis coach Paul Scarpa is the all-time winningest coach in American college tennis history, with a record spanning over 830 wins. A Florida State alumnus, he is a member of the South Carolina Tennis Hall of Fame and USTA Southern Section Hall of Fame, inventor of clay-court line Tenex, and has coached 108 All-Southern Conference players in his 46-year career.

===Rugby===
Furman's Rugby Club team won the East Coast Collegiate Division III Championship three years in a row from 2003-2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.usarugbysouth.com/competition/collegiate%20HISTORY/default.htm http://www.usarugbysouth.com/competition/collegiate%20HISTORY/default.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Started in 1998, the club excels in Division III rugby union.

===Lacrosse===
Furman Men's Lacrosse Club team is a member of the Southeast Lacrosse Conference in the [[Men's Collegiate Lacrosse Association]].

===Cross Country/ Track and Field===
==Notable alumni==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}

===Science===
* [[Brad Cox]] - computer scientist
* [[Hans Einstein]] - the foremost authority on the lung disease [[Coccidioidomycosis|Valley Fever]]
* [[Thomas T. Goldsmith]] - Physicist who helped pioneer the invention of Color Television, and Inventor of the first video game.
* [[Albert Ernest Radford]] - [[Botanist]], mainly known for the ''Manual of the Vascular Flora of the Carolinas'', the definitive [[Flora (plants)|flora]] for [[North Carolina]] and [[South Carolina]].
* [[Charles Townes]] - [[Nobel Prize]] in Physics winner, inventor of the [[maser]], laid theoretical groundwork for invention of [[laser]] &lt;ref name=&quot;The Cliffs Cottage&quot;/&gt;
* [[John B. Watson]] - American Psychologist, founder of [[Behaviorism]]

===Arts and theatre ===
* [[John Bloomfield (pianist/teacher)|John Bloomfield]] - Pianist
* [[Jay Bocook]] - Composer and Arranger - Work Featured at 1984 Olympic Games
* [[Ben Browder]] - Three-time [[Saturn Awards]] winner for Best Actor on Television on [[Farscape]]
* [[Jim David]] - comedian on [[Comedy Central Presents]], actor, writer
* [[Amy Grant]] - guitarist and Christian musician
* [[Keith Lockhart]] - Current conductor of the [[Boston Pops]]
* [[Chris Rickwood]] - [[Composer]], Game Audio Network Guild award winner
* Bear Rinehart - Lead vocalist of [[Needtobreathe]], a six time GMA Dove Award winning modern rock band.
* [[Elizabeth Bishop]] - mezzo soprano with the [[Metropolitan Opera]] New York, New York&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Bishop|first=Elizabeth|title=Bio of Elizabeth Bishop -- The Metropolitan Opera|url=http://www.metoperafamily.org/metopera/season/bio.aspx?id=380&amp;type=1|work=Our Artists|publisher=Metropolitan Opera|accessdate=13 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Writers, journalist, literature, and publishers===
* [[Maurice Bloomfield]] - Austrian-born U.S. philologist and [[Sanskrit]] scholar
* [[Orville Vernon Burton]] - Renowned Southern Historian and author of ''Age of Lincoln''
* [[Betsy Byars]] - children's author, winner of the [[Newbery Medal]], a [[National Book Award]], an [[Edgar Award]] and the [[Regina Medal]]
* [[Marshall Frady]] - Civil Rights Era journalist
* [[George Singleton]] – Novelist
* [[Eleanor Beardsley]] - NPR Correspondent

===Business===
* [[David C. Garrett, Jr.]] - Former CEO of [[Delta Air Lines]]
* [[Sanjay Kumar]] - Former CEO of [[Computer Associates]], sentenced to 12 years in prison for his role in a massive accounting fraud
* [[Herman Lay]] - Founder of the Lay's Corporation, later creating the largest-selling snack food company in the US, the [[Frito-Lay]] corporation
* [[Dr. Pete Claussen, Jr.]] - Vice President of Operations [[Gulf and Ohio Railways]]

===Politics and Law===
* [[Andrew L. Abrams]] - Dean of [[Charleston School of Law]]
* [[Maurice G. Burnside]] - [[United States Representative]] from [[West Virginia]]
* [[Judy Clarke]] - Attorney who defended convicted terrorist [[Zacarias Moussaoui]], &quot;Unabomber&quot; [[Ted Kaczynski]], [[Susan Smith]], 1996 Summer Olympics bomber [[Eric Robert Rudolph]], and [[Jared Lee Loughner]]
* [[Richard Cullen (attorney)|Richard Cullen]] - Former [[Attorney General of Virginia]] and high profile lawyer
* [[William Dimitrouleas]] (1973) - United States District Judge
* [[Joseph H. Earle]] - member of the [[South Carolina House of Representatives]] from 1878 to 1882, a member of the [[South Carolina Senate]] from 1882 to 1886, South Carolina [[attorney general]] from 1886 to 1890 and a [[United States Senator]] from [[South Carolina]] in 1897
* [[Wilton E. Hall]] - newspaper publisher and [[United States Senator]] from [[South Carolina]] from 1944 to 1945
* [[Clement Haynsworth]] - Former United States judge and an unsuccessful nominee for the [[United States Supreme Court]]
* [[Baron Hill]] - Indiana congressman
* [[John Michael McConnell]] - Served as [[Director of the National Security Agency|Director]] of the [[National Security Agency]] and [[Director of National Intelligence]]
* [[Libby Mitchell]] - [[Maine]] politician
* [[Roger C. Peace]] - [[United States Senator]] from [[South Carolina]]
* [[William H. Perry]] - [[United States Representative]] from South Carolina
* [[Richard Riley]] - Former [[Governor of South Carolina]] and U.S. Secretary of Education under the [[Bill Clinton|Clinton]] administration
* [[Mark Sanford]] - Former [[Governor of South Carolina]]
* [[John Calhoun Sheppard]] - The [[List of Governors of South Carolina|82nd]] [[Governor of South Carolina]]
* [[Cecil Staton]] - Politician, businessman, member of the [[Georgia Senate]]
* [[Alexander Stubb]] - [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Finland)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]] of [[Finland]]
* [[Nick Theodore]] - [[Lieutenant Governor of South Carolina]] from 1987 to 1995
* [[Druanne White]] - Trial lawyer in South Carolina
* [[Rob Woodall]] - [[United States Representative]] from [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]]

===Religion===
* [[Kirkman Finlay (bishop)|Kirkman Finlay]] - First [[bishop]] of the [[Episcopal Diocese of Upper South Carolina]].
* [[Issachar Jacox Roberts]] - Baptist missionary in [[China]]

===Athletes===
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}

====Soccer====
* [[Clint Dempsey]] - Professional soccer player for [[Fulham]] of the English [[Premier League]], 2004 [[MLS Rookie of the Year]] and member of the [[United States Men's National Soccer Team]], only US player to score a goal in the 2006 [[FIFA World Cup|World Cup]], scored first American goal in [[2010 World Cup]] in South Africa in 1-1 match versus England
* [[Ricardo Clark]] - Professional soccer player for [[Eintracht Frankfurt]], 2003 [[MLS Rookie of the Year]] runner-up, member of the [[United States Men's National Soccer Team]]
* [[Jonathan Leathers]] - Professional soccer player for the MLS [[Vancouver Whitecaps FC|Vancouver Whitecaps]]
* [[John Barry Nusum]] - Professional soccer player for the [[Virginia Beach Mariners]] and [[Philadelphia Kixx]]
* [[Shea Salinas]]- Professional soccer player for the MLS [[Vancouver Whitecaps FC|Vancouver Whitecaps]]
* [[Sergei Raad]] - Professional soccer player for the MLS [[Kansas City Wizards]]

====Football====
* [[Brian Bratton]] - [[NFL]] player, rookie free agent for the [[Atlanta Falcons]] in 2005, formerly a receiver for [[Baltimore Ravens]] assigned to the [[Cologne Centurions]] of NFL Europe.
*[[Luther Broughton]] - Former [[NFL]] [[tight end]]
* [[Jerome Felton]] - [[NFL]] player, 5th round draft pick by the [[Detroit Lions]] in 2008 NFL Draft, Furman fullback; Currently plays for [[Carolina Panthers]]
* [[Louis Ivory]] - College football running back, won the 2000 [[Walter Payton Award]]
* [[Stanford Jennings]] - Former [[NFL]] player for the [[Cincinnati Bengals]], scored a touchdown in [[Super Bowl XXIII]]; current New Balance sales executive
* [[David Kelly]] - Assistant Head Coach/Wide Receivers Coach at [[UCF]]
* [[Ingle Martin]] - [[NFL]] player, QB for [[Kansas City Chiefs]]
* [[Orlando Ruff]] - [[NFL]] player for [[Cleveland Browns]]
* [[David Whitehurst]] - Former quarterback for the [[Green Bay Packers]]
* [[Sam Wyche]] - Former NFL quarterback and head coach; led [[Cincinnati Bengals]] to [[Super Bowl XXIII]]

====Basketball====
* [[Beth Couture]] - Head coach of the [[Butler Bulldogs women's basketball]] team
* [[Darrell Floyd]] - Two-time NCAA Consensus All-American basketball player
* [[Frank Selvy]] - Former [[National Basketball Association|NBA]] All-Star; holds current [[National Collegiate Athletic Association|NCAA]] Division I record for the most points scored (100) in a single basketball game
* [[Derek Waugh]] - Head men's basketball coach at [[Stetson University]]

====Golf====
* [[Beth Daniel]] - [[LPGA Tour]], [[World Golf Hall of Fame]], 32 career victories
* [[Brad Faxon]] - eight-time winner on the [[PGA Tour]], played on two [[Ryder Cup]] teams
* [[Bruce Fleisher]] - won the [[U.S. Amateur]] in 1968, professional golfer on the [[PGA Tour]] and the [[Champions Tour]]
* [[Betsy King]] - [[LPGA Tour]], [[World Golf Hall of Fame]], 34 career victories
* [[Dottie Pepper]] - Former [[LPGA Tour]] champion; current [[NBC]] and [[The Golf Channel|Golf Channel]] commentator
* [[Sherri Turner]] - Professional golfer, won the 1988 [[LPGA Championship]]

====Other Sports====
* [[Consequences Creed]] (Austin Watson) - Professional wrestler for [[World Wrestling Entertainment]]
* [[Angel Martino]] - Olympic Gold Medalist in swimming
* [[Tom Mastny]] - [[MLB]] pitcher, former player for [[Cleveland Indians]], currently pitching for AAA [[New Orleans Zephyrs]] of the [[Florida Marlins]] farm system
* [[David Segal (athlete)|David Segal]] - Track athlete, Bronze medalist in 1960 Summer Olympics

==Notable faculty==
{{Unreferenced section|date=September 2009}}
* [[Jay Bocook]] - Music, composer of music for 1984 Olympic Games Opening Ceremonies in Los Angeles
* [[Thomas T. Goldsmith Jr.]] - Physics, television pioneer, video game inventor
* [[Mark Kilstofte]] - Music, winner of the [[American Academy in Rome]]'s [[Prix de Rome|Rome Prize]] for 2002-2003 &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aarome.org/rome_prize/2003winners.htm http://www.aarome.org/rome_prize/2003winners.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Points of interest==
[[Image:Furman Hall.jpg|thumb|right|160px|Furman's Johns Hall in winter]]  

* Doughboy Statue, honoring Furman students who served in World War I
* Daniel Chapel Organ
* The Bell Tower and Burnside [[Carillon]] (a 59 bell carillon by Van Bergen)
* Furman's [[special collections]] department houses the [[South Carolina Baptist Historical Collection]] and the [[South Carolina Poetry Archives]].

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
* [http://www.furman.edu/ Official website]
* [http://www.furmanpaladins.com/ Furman University athletics website]
* [http://www.engagefurman.com/ Furman University admissions]
* [http://www.thefurmanpaladin.com/ The Paladin]
* [http://www.RememberFurman.com/ Remember Furman | Gallery of Furman Photos]
* [http://www.hmdb.org/marker.asp?MarkerID=11383 Furman University Historical Marker]

{{Coord|34|55|33|N|82|26|8|W|type:edu|display=title}}
{{Colleges and universities in South Carolina}}
{{Southern Conference}}
{{Annapolis Group}}
{{Associated Colleges of the South}}

[[Category:Furman University]]
[[Category:Liberal arts colleges]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1826]]
[[Category:Council of Independent Colleges]]
[[Category:National Association of Independent Colleges and Universities members]]
[[Category:Universities and colleges accredited by the Southern Association of Colleges and Schools]]
[[Category:Members of the Annapolis Group]]
[[Category:Education in Greenville, South Carolina]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Greenville, South Carolina]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in Greenville, South Carolina]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
