<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3957540" ns="0" title="Alan Turner (Emmerdale)"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Inappropriate tone|date=August 2010}}
{{In-universe|date=August 2010}}

{{Infobox soap character 2 
|series         = Emmerdale
|image          = [[File:AlanTurner.jpg|200px]]
|name           = Alan Turner
|introducer     = Anne Gibbons
|portrayer      = [[Richard Thorp]]
|years          = 1982—
|first          = 18 March 1982
|born           = {{Birth-date and age|5 August 1935}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.itv.com/soaps/emmerdale/castandcharacters/qtoz/alanturner1.html/ Alan Turner at ITV.com]&lt;/ref&gt;
|home           = Keepers Cottage
|classification = [[List of Emmerdale characters#Present cast|Present; regular]]
|occupation     = [[Retirement|Retired]] (since 1999)&lt;br/&gt;[[Bartender|Barman]] (1990–99)&lt;br/&gt;[[Public house|Pub landlord]] (1991–99)
|brothers       = William Turner
|sons           = [[Terence Turner]]
|daughters      = [[Steph Forsythe]]
|wife           = {{nowrap|Jill Turner (1961–85)&lt;br /&gt;[[Shirley Foster]] (1994)}}
|granddaughters = Tricia Dingle
}}
'''Alan Jonathan Turner''' is a [[fictional character]] in the [[United Kingdom|British]] [[soap opera]] ''[[Emmerdale]]'' played by [[Richard Thorp]]. He first appeared on 18 March 1982, and is the longest running character in the soap. Originally portrayed as an inept, boozing and bullying manager for NY Estates at Home Farm, he has mellowed throughout the years and is now a 'pillar of the community' type figure. Due to Richard's Thorp's ageing and ailments in recent years, Alan has been written out for lengthy periods of time. 

==Character Backstory==

Born in 1935 in Chichester, Sussex, Alan Turner had a brother William who died young, and he was always cleverer than Alan. Alan had married Jill when they were very young and they had two children Terence in 1951 and Mary in 1953. He was appointed new manager of NY Estates in Beckindale in early 1982.

==Storylines==
===1982—===
Alan Turner came to Emmerdale in 1982. His early years were dominated by his business dealings and work on the local council. He worked as an estate manager for ''NY Estates'', having a rival of sorts in [[Joe Sugden]], who later got his job.

From 1982 to 1988, Alan often found himself outwitted by NY Estates' wiley gamekeeper [[Seth Armstrong]], in a long series of comic storylines which were highly popular with the show's viewers.

Alan was married to Jill, with whom he had two children: [[Terence Turner|Terence]] and [[Steph Forsythe|Steph]] (known as Mary until deciding to adopt her middle name as her first name). Alan favoured Terence over Steph in their youth.

Alan has had many relationships. His first within the soap's narrative at Emmerdale was with Caroline Bates ([[Diana Davies (actress)|Diana Davies]]) after she became his secretary at NY Estates in 1984. She saw him as an inadequate blustering man with charm and kindness underneath. Their business relationship was portrayed as a comedy duo during the series in the mid-to-late 1980s and the couple came close to marrying in 1989, shortly before Caroline left the village to care for her ailing mother in [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]].

Alan married [[Shirley Foster]] in 1994. She died four months after they married after being shot by [[Reg Dawson]] during the siege at Home Farm. 

Alan later became landlord of the Woolpack and became a more central character within the village. He formed a close friendship with [[Diane Blackstock]] but they never pursued a relationship.

Alan's granddaughter, Tricia Stokes, arrived in the village 1998 and they shared a close relationship. He gave his blessing when Tricia married local chef, [[Marlon Dingle]], and even let them live with him for a time. 

[[Steph Forsythe]], Alan's daughter and Tricia's mother arrived in 2002. She and Alan's relationship was a contrast to that of him and Tricia with them having many disagreements. They became united for a short time in their grief for Tricia after she was killed in the storm on New Year’s Eve 2003.

[[Shelly Williams]] was introduced in 2003 as a new love interest for Alan and as Steph’s best friend. Steph became jealous at having a rival for Alan’s attention and voiced her disapproval of their relationship. Their relationship continued and they began making plans to move to [[Spain]]. Steph started spreading rumours that Shelly was only after Alan's money and Shelley ended up leaving Emmerdale and Alan. 

With Shelley's departure, Alan began drinking heavily. One day, Alan and Steph had an argument on the stairs at the B&amp;B and Alan fell down them. His injuries left him at Steph’s mercy and she began doping him and formulated a plan to sell his business and have Alan admitted to sheltered accommodation.

Alan, eventually, realised what Steph was doing and managed to get word to his neighbours. Steph was stopped but not before she almost killed them by driving to a quarry edge. She was unable to go through with killing her father.

Evidence of Shelly being held in the B&amp;B cellar emerged and it looked like Steph had murdered her. 

After months waiting for news, Alan accepted Shelly was dead, only for her to come to the memorial service. Although he was horrified that Shelly had let Steph go to prison for suspected murder, he forgave her and they tried rebuilding their relationship. Shelly couldn’t live with Steph around, however, and Alan was unable to disown his daughter. Alan begged Steph to go after Shelly and bring her home. On the ferry, unknown to Alan, Steph and Shelly argued and Shelly fell overboard. Steph left her to drown, returning to the village, and her relationship with Alan grew stronger. He allowed her to take over the B&amp;B again and Steph later fell in love with local doctor, [[Adam Forsythe]].

Steph later told Alan she was sexually abused as a child by her older brother [[Terence Turner|Terence]]. Incensed, Alan dismissed her claims and resumed contact with his estranged son. He turned against Steph, Adam and [[Betty Eagleton|Betty]] and moved in to Holdgate Farm with Terence.

Soon after, Alan discovered that Terence had abused Steph, and he threw him out. Terence returned to torment Steph, leading to a violent struggle between Terence, Adam and Steph. This resulted in Terence’s death. Although Adam took her on holiday and married her, the murder  weighed on Steph's sanity. Alan was deeply distressed to see his daughter in such a bad way and was heartbroken when she was sectioned.

Adam lied to Alan, pretending Steph’s confession was a lie attributable to her crumbling sanity, but he felt Steph was telling the truth. He began to listen but with Adam holding all the cards and Steph in a terrible state, Alan wasn't sure if he could do anything to help her.

Adam did a runner when Steph was released from hospital and Terence's body was found under the rubble of Kings River Show House. With Adam gone, Steph was charged with her brother's murder. Alan was desperate to get his daughter out of prison as he feared that she couldn't cope.

On November 10, Steph confessed to Alan that she had a hand in Shelly's death and was later sentenced to life in prison for the murder of her brother. Following Steph's imprisonment and Terence's cremation, Alan wanted answers and went to see Adam in prison on November 12. He was shocked when Adam's ex-wife [[Isla Forsythe|Isla]] told him Adam had hanged himself.

Feeling low, Alan sought comfort from Betty, clumsily making a pass at her. Alan was  embarrassed when she rejected him and things were awkward for a while. In December 2006, Alan decided to visit [[Kathy Brookman]] in Australia and stayed over Christmas, reminiscing about old times with [[Seth Armstrong]], who had died the previous year. Alan returned to the village and lived with Betty and her beau [[Sandy Thomas]], but in early 2008, visited Kathy again, returning in June. In August, he shared a kiss with [[Pearl Ladderbanks]]. Since then they have been closer friends but wouldn't call themselves a couple.

In February 2009, Alan mourned the loss of his one-time foe turned friend, Jack Sugden. In April, [[David Metcalfe]] asked him to run for the Council in opposition to [[Eric Pollard]]. Alan had no desire to return to politics but advised David in his candidacy. David won but soon disappointed Alan due to lack of attention to his duties.

In July 2009, Alan's old biker mate, [[List of minor Emmerdale characters (2009)#Eddy Fox|Eddy Fox]], dropped into the village, asking Alan to go travelling with him. Alan was reluctant to go so Edna's sister, Lily, went instead. Alan joined them later and was away for a period of nine months. 

Alan returned on 9 April 2010. He gave newcomer Declan Macey advice on how to run Home Farm after Declan asked him about his tenure in the 1980s as Home Farm manager. In December 2010, [[Val Pollard]] asked Alan about the events surrounding Eric Pollard's second wife Elizabeth's death 17 years earlier in the plane crash after her son [[Michael Feldmann]] turned up accusing Eric of murdering her and using the crash to cover it up. Alan told Val that there had been a lot of suspicion about Eric in the aftermath of the plane crash. Alan also met Michael and after catching up with him, lent him some money when he could see Michael was struggling. In January 2011 Alan and Betty moved into Mill Cottage temporarily after a fire, started by corrupt policeman [[Nick Henshall]] ripped through the row of cottages which Keepers Cottage was part of. Alan and Betty moved back in once Keepers was renovated. For his 76th birthday on 5 August 2011, Alan was touched by the replacement watch that his friends had bought him after his old one stopped working. 

Later on Alan offered to look after Sandy Thomas after he had a fall. Alan soon began to regret this as Sandy was quite stubborn.

{{S-start}}
{{Succession box| before = [[Henry Wilks]]| title = Landlord of [[The Woolpack]] | years = 1991–99| after = [[Bernice Blackstock]]}}
{{S-end}}

==References==

{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.itv.com/page.asp?partid=3713 Alan Turner] at [[itv.com]]

{{Emmerdale}}
{{Emmerdale characters}}
{{EDTurner}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Turner, Alan}}
[[Category:Emmerdale characters]]
[[Category:Fictional bartenders]]
[[Category:Fictional businesspeople]]
[[Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1982]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
