<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3966364" ns="0" title="Yves Rodier"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox comics creator
| name          = Yves Rodier
| image         = 
| imagesize     = 
| caption       = 
| birth_name    = 
| birth_date    = 
| birth_place   = [[Farnham, Quebec|Farnham]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]
| death_date    = 
| death_place   = 
| nationality   = [[Canada|French-Canadian]]
| area          = 
| cartoonist    = y
| write         = 
| pencil        = 
| ink           = 
| letter        = 
| color         =
| edit          = 
| alias         = 
| notable works = ''[[The Adventures of Tintin|Tintin]]'' pastiches&lt;br /&gt;''Pignouf et Hamlet''
| awards        = 
| website       = http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/yves_rodier&amp;date=2009-10-26+00:31:39
| nonUS         = y
| sortkey       = Rodier, Yves
| subcat        = Canadian
| yob           = 1967
| mob           = 6
| dob           = 5
}}
'''Yves Rodier''' (born June 5, 1967, in [[Farnham, Quebec|Farnham]], [[Quebec]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bdquebec.qc.ca/auteurs/yrodier/yrodier.htm Yves Rodier website]&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;&lt;/ref&gt; is a [[France|Franco]]-[[Quebec|Québécois]] [[comic]] strip creator known for his many [[pastiche]]s of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''.

== Biography ==
Rodier always loved comics, but first set out to become a musician or cinematographer. He soon returned to comics. He started out by imitating the work of his favorite author, [[Hergé]], creating [[pastiches]] of ''[[The Adventures of Tintin]]''. These copies were illegal and did not earn him much money, though this allowed him to meet many other cartoonists, like [[Bob de Moor]], [[Jacques Martin (comics)|Jacques Martin]] and [[Greg (comics)|Greg]]. In 1995, he met Daniel and Richard Houde, and in their magazine ''Pignouf'' he started his comic series ''Pignouf et Hamlet'', about a boy and his pig. The magazine only lasted for five issues, though the series continued.

== Work ==
=== The Tintin Pastiches ===
Rodier always had a passion for ''The Adventures of Tintin'' by Hergé and so he embarked on writing some Tintin stories of his own. These are Tintin pastiches, meaning that they try to imitate the style of Hergé. They are illegal, as they breach the Tintin copyright owned by the [[Hergé Foundation]] (Moulinsart), but some have been published, and they are all found circulating on the Internet.

====Tintin and Alph-Art====
[[File:Th nightmare.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Yves Rodier's version of [[Tintin and Alph-Art]], first page in color.]]
The unfinished Tintin book ''[[Tintin and Alph-Art]]'' was unofficially completed by Rodier in black-and-white. Several groups have coloured it, such as 'Alph-junis', and have translated it into English. It was published in Autumn 1986 and then presented to Moulinsart. Rodier asked that it become an official book but Moulinsart refused. In 1991, Rodier met [[Bob de Moor]], and together they asked for permission to re-draw the book. Moulinsart still disagreed and De Moor died in 1992. Rodier later re-drew certain parts of it to make them more akin to the style of Hergé. This new edition is much rarer and was released on CD-ROM, as opposed to being printed like the original edition.

====A Day at the Airport====
Hergé once suggested that a good idea for a his next Tintin story would be to set it in an airport. However, he chose to set it in the art world instead and partially produced ''Tintin and Alph-art''.  Rodier started out a new book called ''A Day at the Airport'' though it was abandoned, with the first page leaking onto the web. The plot involves a character from the Tintin stories, [[General Alcazar]], being shot, apparently by [[Dr. J.W. Muller]], a villain from the Tintin series.

====Tintin in Tibet page 27b====
Rodier also did an extra page for Hergé's ''[[Tintin in Tibet]]'' which Hergé deleted from his comic.

====Tintin, Freelance reporter for ''Le Petit Vingtième''====
The origin of the story lies in a scenario for a drawing contest in the ''[[Spirou (magazine)|Journal de Spirou]]'' number 1027, from December 19, 1957.
Twenty years later, Yves Rodier used the story for another drawing contest, converted it as a Tintin plot and drew 6 half-pages of a story that takes place right before &quot;Tintin and The soviets&quot;. Those pages explains how Tintin gets the job as a reporter. 
For the story Rodier didn't win the contest as he was disqualified for using already existing characters.

====The Witches Lake====
This seven-page story was entirely thought up by Rodier and is sometimes called ''The Sorcerers Lake''. It is about a monster in the local lake and is set before ''Tintin in Tibet''.

====Tintin et le Thermozéro====
Yves Rodier's version of ''[[Le Thermozéro]]'' is an inking from page 4 of sketches made from Hergé.

===Pignouf and Hamlet===
The stories of a boy and his pig. Neither have been translated into English. They were published by David. 
*''The Wild Band'' — The first book was published in 2000; its French name is ''La Bande Sauvage''.
*''The Claw of the Tiger'' — The second book was abandoned when Rodier took up his next series. Some of it can be seen on the Internet.

===Simon Nian===
This series is published by [[François Corteggiani]].
*''Decimates and the Screw'' (June 2005)
*''The Demons of Petransac'' (2006)
*''The Cursed Exposure'' (2011)

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official|[http://www.geocities.com/yves_rodier}} http://www.geocities.com/yves_rodier}}]{{dead link|date=October 2010|bot=AnomieBOT}}

{{Tintin and Hergé}}


{{Persondata &lt;!-- Metadata: see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]]. --&gt;
| NAME              =Rodier, Yves
| ALTERNATIVE NAMES =
| SHORT DESCRIPTION =
| DATE OF BIRTH     =June 5, 1967
| PLACE OF BIRTH    =[[Farnham, Quebec|Farnham]], [[Quebec]], [[Canada]]
| DATE OF DEATH     =
| PLACE OF DEATH    =
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rodier, Yves}}
[[Category:French Quebecers]]
[[Category:People from Montérégie]]
[[Category:Tintin]]
[[Category:1967 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]

[[es:Yves Rodier]]
[[fr:Yves Rodier]]
[[id:Yves Rodier]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
