<?xml version="1.0"?><api><query><pages><page pageid="3969100" ns="0" title="Harrah&#039;s New Orleans"><revisions><rev xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox Casino|
casino=Harrah's New Orleans|
theme=French Quarter |
address=8 Canal Street&lt;br&gt;New Orleans, LA 70130|
image= HarrahsNOLAJan07B.jpg|
image_size=250px|
logo= |
logo_size=150 px|
|rooms=450|
date_opened= October 30, 1999|
space_gaming={{convert|115000|sqft|abbr=on}}|
attractions= |
shows= |
notable_restaurants=''The Besh Steakhouse''|
owner=[[Caesars Entertainment]]|
casino_type= Land|
renovations=2005, 2006 |
names_pre=none |
website=[http://www.harrahs.com/our_casinos/nor/ Harrah's New Orleans]|
}}

'''Harrah's New Orleans''' is a [[casino]] located in [[New Orleans, Louisiana]] near the foot of [[Canal Street, New Orleans|Canal Street]] a block away from the [[Mississippi River]]. It is a {{convert|115000|sqft|abbr=on}} casino with approximately 2,100 [[slot machine]]s, over 90 table games and a [[poker]] room.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.neworleansonline.com/news/2007/June/fultonstreet.html&lt;/ref&gt; There are several places to eat ranging from buffet style to fine dining. Since its opening in 1999 Harrah's has been renting nearby hotel rooms to accommodate its guests; currently, the newly-renovated 202-room Wyndham Riverfront Hotel is providing such accommodations. In order to avoid leasing rooms, the casino opened its own 27-story hotel tower with 450 rooms across the street from the casino on September 21, 2006 just days ahead of the [[New Orleans Saints]] return to the [[Louisiana Superdome]]. It is the only land-based private casino with table games in the state by Louisiana law (there are other casinos in the state with their gambling facilities on floating boats and [[horse racing]] [[racino]]s with slot machines). It is referred to in state statute as &quot;the official gaming establishment&quot;, see Chp.10, Title 4 of Louisiana Revised Statutes.

The casino shut down in the wake of [[Hurricane Katrina]] in 2005 but reopened in the midst of [[Mardi Gras]] on February 17, 2006.

The location of the casino was most recently previously the site of the [[Rivergate Convention Center]], demolished in 1995. A short tunnel built as part of the canceled [[Vieux Carré Riverfront Expressway]] is used for [[valet parking]] and for an entrance passing underneath Poydras Street.

==History==
The casino is the brainchild of [[Christopher Hemmeter]], a hotel developer in the Hawaiian Islands who returned to the mainland in 1991 when he began to develop casino gaming projects including the nearby [[River City Casino (New Orleans)|River City Casino]]. His biggest project was a proposed $1 billion casino in [[New Orleans]]. Billed at the time as &quot;the world's largest casino&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=McKinney|first=Louise|title=New Orleans: a cultural history|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2006|pages=165–166|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=jAIr2Cl2p1EC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;dq=%22christopher+hemmeter%22&amp;as_brr=3&amp;cd=4#v=onepage&amp;q=%22christopher%20hemmeter%22&amp;f=false | isbn=9780195301359}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original design resembled Monte Carlo's 1861 casino, intending to evoke the New Orleans 1885 Cotton Exposition and Chicago's 1893 World Columbia Exposition.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford&quot; /&gt; The developers estimated the casino would attract one million additional visitors to the city and would generate annual revenues of as much as $780 million, estimates that were based in part on the proven success of dockside gaming in the Mississippi Gulf Coast area.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford&quot; /&gt; 

In 1993 a partnership of Hemmeter and Caesar's World obtained the lease on the Rivergate property, which by law was the only place the land-based casino could be built in Louisiana, beating out a rival bid by Harrah's. In August, 1993, however, the State Casino Board awarded the state's sole casino license to Harrah's and not the Hemmeter-Caesar's partnership. The impasse of one company owning the only license and another owning the only lease was resolved when the two entities formed a joint venture under pressure from then-Governor, Edwin Edwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;96nyt&quot;&gt;{{cite journal|last=Myerson|first=Allen R.|date=2 June 1996|title=A Big Casino Wager That Hasn't Paid Off|journal=New York Times|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1996/06/02/business/a-big-casino-wager-that-hasn-t-paid-off.html?scp=11&amp;sq=chris%20hemmeter&amp;st=cse|accessdate=2 February 2010 | work=The New York Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new entity, known as &quot;Harrah's Jazz&quot; established a temporary casino in the [[Municipal Auditorium (New Orleans)|Municipal Auditorium]] in order to establish a cash flow while the main facility was under construction at the Rivergate. The temporary facility opened in May, 1995 and a week later was closed due to a flood. The poor location of the site resulted in the actual gaming take falling 60% below projections at only $13.1 million per month.&lt;ref name=&quot;96nyt&quot; /&gt; Equally concerning was the fact that 60% of gamers at the temporary facility were locals and not out-of-town tourists, undercutting the economic benefit backers hoped gaming to provide to the tourist industry.

Harrah's Jazz halted construction on the permanent facility at 3 AM the day before Thanksgiving, 1995 and laid off 1,600 construction workers, 2,500 casino employees, and filed for bankruptcy. Later, the project was taken over by Harrah's who completed (albeit scaled-back with only the first floor in use to this day) and opened in late October 1999 Harrah's New Orleans Casino on the site of Hemmeter's project.&lt;ref name=&quot;oxford&quot; /&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
{{Commonscat}}
*[http://www.harrahsneworleans.com/ Harrah's New Orleans Hotel website]
*[http://www.tulane.edu/~rivgate/ The Rivergate (1968-1995)]

{{Caesars Entertainment}}
{{coord missing|Louisiana}}

[[Category:Casinos in Louisiana]]
[[Category:Hotels in New Orleans, Louisiana]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1999]]
[[Category:Skyscrapers between 100 and 149 meters]]
[[Category:Caesars Entertainment Corporation]]
[[Category:Visitor attractions in New Orleans, Louisiana]]</rev></revisions></page></pages></query></api>
